  <page>
    <title>Distance education</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8997</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943234126</id>
      <parentid>940401904</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-29T18:09:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dumaro</username>
        <id>38641402</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* University correspondence courses */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{use dmy dates|date=April 2011}}

'''Distance education''' or '''distance learning''' is the education of students who may not always be physically present at a [[school]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Kaplan Haenlein 2016&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1016/j.bushor.2016.03.008 |title=Higher education and the digital revolution: About MOOCs, SPOCs, social media, and the Cookie Monster |journal=Business Horizons |volume=59 |issue=4 |pages=441–50 |year=2016 |last1=Kaplan |first1=Andreas M. |last2=Haenlein |first2=Michael }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last=Honeyman |first=M |author2=Miller, G |date=December 1993 | title= Agriculture distance education: A valid alternative for higher education? | journal =Proceedings of the 20th Annual National Agricultural Education Research Meeting | pages= 67–73 |url=http://files.eric.ed.gov/fulltext/ED366794.pdf#page=80 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Traditionally, this usually involved '''correspondence courses''' wherein the student corresponded with the school via [[mail|post]]. Today, it involves '''online education'''. A distance learning program can be completely distance learning, or a combination of distance learning and traditional classroom instruction (called hybrid&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Tabor | first = Sharon W |date= Spring 2007 |title= Narrowing the Distance: Implementing a Hybrid Learning Model |journal= Quarterly Review of Distance Education | volume = 8 |issue=1 |pages=48–49 |publisher=IAP |issn=1528-3518 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=b46TLTrx0kUC | accessdate=23 January 2011| isbn = 9787774570793 }}&lt;/ref&gt; or [[Blended learning|blended]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Vaughan |first1=Dr Norman D. |editor1-first=MF |editor1-last= Cleveland-Innes |editor2-first= DR | editor2-last =Garrison |title=An Introduction to Distance Education: Understanding Teaching and Learning in a New Era |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=AI5as0yooGoC | accessdate=23 January 2011 | year=2010 | publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis | isbn=978-0-415-99598-6 | page=165 | chapter=Blended Learning}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Massive open online course]]s (MOOCs), offering large-scale interactive participation and open access through the [[World Wide Web]] or other network technologies, are recent educational modes in distance education.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kaplan Haenlein 2016&quot;/&gt; A number of other terms (distributed learning, e-learning, m-learning, online learning, virtual classroom etc.) are used roughly synonymously with distance education.

== History ==
One of the earliest attempts was advertised in 1728. This was in the ''[[Boston Gazette]]'' for &quot;Caleb Philipps, Teacher of the new method of [[Short Hand]]&quot;, who sought students who wanted to learn through weekly mailed lessons.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Holmberg |first1=Börje |title=The evolution, principles and practices of distance education |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=YTtdNQAACAAJ | accessdate=2011-01-23 |series=Studien und Berichte der Arbeitsstelle Fernstudienforschung der Carl von Ossietzky Universität Oldenburg [ASF] |volume= 11 |year=2005 |publisher= Bibliotheks-und Informationssystem der Universitat Oldenburg |language=German |isbn=3-8142-0933-8 | page=13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The first distance education course in the modern sense was provided by Sir [[Isaac Pitman]] in the 1840s, who taught a system of shorthand by mailing texts transcribed into shorthand on [[postcard]]s and receiving transcriptions from his students in return for correction. The element of student feedback was a crucial innovation of Pitman's system.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.irrodl.org/index.php/irrodl/article/view/134/214|author=Alan Tait|publisher=The International Review of Research in Open and Distance Learning|title=Reflections on Student Support in Open and Distance Learning}}&lt;/ref&gt; This scheme was made possible by the introduction of [[Uniform Penny Post|uniform postage rates]] across [[England]] in 1840.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/?id=MEax6VBfRscC|title=distance learning... a magazine for leaders volume 2 number 6|author=IAP|page=18|isbn=9787774554229}}&lt;/ref&gt;

This early beginning proved extremely successful, and the Phonographic Correspondence Society was founded three years later to establish these courses on a more formal basis. The Society paved the way for the later formation of Sir Isaac Pitman Colleges across the country.&lt;ref name=MooreKearsley&gt;{{cite book | last= Moore | first= Michael G. |author2=Greg Kearsley | year= 2005 | title= Distance Education: A Systems View | edition= 2nd | location= Belmont, CA | publisher= Wadsworth | isbn= 0-534-50688-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The first correspondence school in the United States was the [[Society to Encourage Studies at Home]], which was founded in 1873.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Robinson|first=Cole, Elizabeth|date=2012|title=The Invisible Woman and the Silent University.|url=https://eric.ed.gov/?id=ED548106|journal=ProQuest LLC|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== University correspondence courses ===
The [[University of London]] was the first university to offer distance learning degrees, establishing its [[University of London External Programme|External Programme]] in 1858. The background to this innovation lay in the fact that the institution (later known as [[University College London]]) was [[non-denominational]] and, given the intense religious rivalries at the time, there was an outcry against the &quot;godless&quot; university. The issue soon boiled down to which institutions had [[Academic degree|degree]]-granting powers and which institutions did not.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rothblatt Article&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.2307/368852 |jstor=368852 |title=Supply and Demand: The &quot;Two Histories&quot; of English Education |journal=History of Education Quarterly |volume=28 |issue=4 |pages=627–44 |year=1988 |last1=Rothblatt |first1=Sheldon |last2=Muller |first2=Detlef K. |last3=Ringer |first3=Fritz |last4=Simon |first4=Brian |last5=Bryant |first5=Margaret |last6=Roach |first6=John |last7=Harte |first7=Negley |last8=Smith |first8=Barbara |last9=Symonds |first9=Richard }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:The London University by Thomas Hosmer Shepherd 1827-28.JPG|thumb|''The London University'' in 1827, drawn by [[Thomas Hosmer Shepherd]].|220x220px]]
The compromise solution that emerged in 1836 was that the sole authority to conduct the examinations leading to degrees would be given to a new officially recognized entity called the &quot;[[University of London]]&quot;, which would act as examining body for the [[University of London]] colleges, originally [[University College London]] and [[King's College London]], and award their students [[University of London]] degrees. As [[Sheldon Rothblatt]] states: &quot;Thus arose in nearly archetypal form the famous English distinction between [[teaching]] and [[exam]]ining, here embodied in separate institutions.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Rothblatt Article&quot; /&gt;

With the state giving examining powers to a separate entity, the groundwork was laid for the creation of a programme within the new university which would both administer examinations and award qualifications to students taking instruction at another institution or pursuing a course of self-directed study.

Referred to as &quot;People's University&quot; by [[Charles Dickens]] because it provided access to [[higher education]] to students from less affluent backgrounds, the External Programme was chartered by [[Queen Victoria]] in 1858, making the University of London the first university to offer distance learning degrees to students.&lt;ref name=&quot;External Programme History&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.londonexternal.ac.uk/about_us/history.shtml |title=&quot;History&quot;, University of London External Programme Website |publisher=Londonexternal.ac.uk |date=15 July 2009 |accessdate=27 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Key Facts&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.londonexternal.ac.uk/about_us/facts.shtml |title=&quot;Key Facts&quot;, University of London External Programme Website |publisher=Londonexternal.ac.uk |date=15 July 2009 |accessdate=27 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Enrollment increased steadily during the late 19th century, and its example was widely copied elsewhere.&lt;ref name=&quot;Guardian Article&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.guardianabroad.co.uk/education/article/283 |author=Tatum Anderson |title=History lessons at the people's university |date=16 May 2007 |publisher=Guardianabroad.co.uk |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070524102204/http://www.guardianabroad.co.uk/education/article/283 |archivedate=24 May 2007 |accessdate=20 September 2016 |url-status=dead |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt; This program is now known as the University of London International Programme and includes Postgraduate, Undergraduate and Diploma degrees created by colleges such as the London School of Economics, Royal Holloway and Goldsmiths.&lt;ref name=&quot;Key Facts&quot; /&gt;

[[File:Portrait of William Rainey Harper.jpg|thumb|200x200px|[[William Rainey Harper]], encouraged the development of external university courses at the new University of Chicago in the 1890s.]]
In the United States, [[William Rainey Harper]], founder and first president of the [[University of Chicago]], celebrated the concept of extended education, where a research university had satellite colleges elsewhere in the region.&lt;ref&gt;James T. Carey, ''Forms and Forces in University Adult Education'' (Brookline, MA: Center for the Study of Liberal Education for
Adults, 1961), 18-19. https://president.uchicago.edu/directory/william-rainey-harper&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1892, Harper encouraged correspondence courses to further promote education, an idea that was put into practice by Chicago, Wisconsin, Columbia, and several dozen other universities by the 1920s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Levinson |first1=David L |title=Community colleges: a reference handbook |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=xrnPJcb7c54C |year= 2005 |publisher=ABC-CLIO |isbn= 1-57607-766-7 |page=69 |accessdate=2011-01-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Von V. Pittman, ''Correspondence Study in the American University: A Second Historiographical Perspective,'' in Michael Grahame Moore, William G. Anderson, eds. ''Handbook of Distance Education'' pp 21-36&lt;/ref&gt; Enrollment in the largest private for-profit school based in [[Scranton, Pennsylvania]], the [[International Correspondence Schools]] grew explosively in the 1890s. Founded in 1888 to provide training for immigrant coal miners aiming to become state mine inspectors or foremen, it enrolled 2500 new students in 1894 and matriculated 72,000 new students in 1895. By 1906 total enrollments reached 900,000. The growth was due to sending out complete textbooks instead of single lessons, and the use of 1200 aggressive in-person salesmen.&lt;ref&gt;Joseph F. Kett, ''Pursuit of Knowledge Under Difficulties: From Self-Improvement to Adult Education in America'' (1996) pp 236-8&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;J.J. Clark, &quot;The Correspondence School—Its Relation to Technical Education and Some of Its Results,&quot; ''Science'' (1906) 24#611 pp 327-8, 332, 333. Clark was manager of the school's text-book department.&lt;/ref&gt; There was a stark contrast in pedagogy:

{{blockquote|The regular technical school or college aims to educate a man broadly; our aim, on the contrary, is to educate him only along some particular line. The college demands that a student shall have certain educational qualifications to enter it and that all students study for approximately the same length of time; when they have finished their courses they are supposed to be qualified to enter any one of a number of branches in some particular profession. We, on the contrary, are aiming to make our courses fit the particular needs of the student who takes them.&lt;ref&gt;Clark, &quot;The Correspondence School&quot; (1906) p 329&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Education was a high priority in the [[Progressive Era]], as American high schools and colleges expanded greatly. For men who were older or were too busy with family responsibilities, night schools were opened, such as the [[YMCA]] school in Boston that became [[Northeastern University]]. Outside the big cities, private correspondence schools offered a flexible, narrowly focused solution.&lt;ref&gt;Kett, ''Pursuit of Knowledge Under Difficulties,'' p 240&lt;/ref&gt; Large corporations systematized their training programs for new employees. The National Association of Corporation Schools grew from 37 in 1913 to 146 in 1920. Starting in the 1880s, private schools opened across the country which offered specialized technical training to anyone who enrolled, not just the employees of one company. Starting in Milwaukee in 1907, public schools began opening free vocational programs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=William Millikan|title=A Union Against Unions: The Minneapolis Citizens Alliance and Its Fight Against Organized Labor, 1903–1947|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=GseChEHIysAC&amp;pg=PA60|year=2003|publisher=Minnesota Historical Society Press|pages=60–61|isbn=978-0-87351-499-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Only a third of the American population lived in cities of 100,000 or more population In 1920; to reach the rest, correspondence techniques had to be adopted. Australia, with its vast distances, was especially active; the [[University of Queensland]] established its Department of Correspondence Studies in 1911.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1080/0158791820030207 |title=Distance education in Australian higher education — a history |journal=Distance Education |volume=3 |issue=2 |pages=255–78 |year=2009 |last1=White |first1=Michael }}&lt;/ref&gt; In South Africa, the [[University of South Africa]], formerly an examining and certification body, started to present distance education tuition in 1946. The International Conference for Correspondence Education held its first meeting in 1938.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Francis Lee|title=Letters and bytes: Sociotechnical studies of distance education|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=6_V7z998PlgC&amp;pg=PA48|year=2009|publisher=Francis Lee|page=48|isbn=9789173935180}}&lt;/ref&gt; The goal was to provide individualized education for students, at low cost, by using a pedagogy of testing, recording, classification, and differentiation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1080/07341510801900318 |title=Technopedagogies of mass‐individualization: Correspondence education in the mid twentieth century |journal=History and Technology |volume=24 |issue=3 |pages=239–53 |year=2008 |last1=Lee |first1=Francis }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ellen L. Bunker, &quot;The History of Distance Education through the Eyes of the International Council for Distance Education,&quot; in Michael Grahame Moore, William G. Anderson, eds. ''Handbook of Distance Education'' pp 49-66&lt;/ref&gt;  The organization has since been renamed as the International Council for Open and Distance Education (ICDE), with headquarters in [[Oslo, Norway]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.icde.org/who-we-are|title=Who we are|website=www.icde.org|access-date=2019-03-25|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190325213612/https://www.icde.org/who-we-are|archive-date=25 March 2019|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Open universities ===
[[File:Walton Hall Pen&amp;Ink.jpg|thumb|[[Walton Hall, Milton Keynes|Walton Hall]], renovated in 1970 to act as the headquarters of the newly established [[Open University]]. ''(Artist: Hilary French)'']]
The [[Open University]] in the United Kingdom was founded by the-then [[Labour Party (UK)|Labour]] government led by Prime Minister, [[Harold Wilson]], based on the vision of [[Michael Young (politician)|Michael Young]]. Planning commenced in 1965 under the [[Secretary of State for Education and Skills|Minister of State for Education]], [[Jennie Lee, Baroness Lee of Asheridge|Jennie Lee]], who established a model for the Open University (OU) as one of widening access to the highest standards of scholarship in higher education, and set up a planning committee consisting of university vice-chancellors, educationalists and television broadcasters, chaired by Sir Peter Venables. The British Broadcasting Corporation ([[BBC]]) Assistant Director of Engineering at the time, [[James Redmond (broadcaster)|James Redmond]], had obtained most of his qualifications at [[wikt:night school|night school]], and his natural enthusiasm for the project did much to overcome the technical difficulties of using television to broadcast teaching programmes.{{citation needed|date=May 2018}}

The Open University revolutionised the scope of the correspondence program and helped to create a respectable learning alternative to the traditional form of education. It has been at the forefront of developing new technologies to improve the distance learning service&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=A Brief History of Distance Education|author=Bizhan Nasseh|url=http://www.seniornet.org/edu/art/history.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as undertaking research in other disciplines. [[Walter Perry]] was appointed the OU's first vice-chancellor in January 1969, and its foundation secretary was [[Anastasios Christodoulou]]. The election of the new [[Conservative Party (UK)|Conservative]] government under the leadership of [[Edward Heath]], in 1970; led to budget cuts under [[Chancellor of the Exchequer]] [[Iain Macleod]] (who had earlier called the idea of an Open University &quot;blithering nonsense&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.open.ac.uk/about/ou/p3.shtml|title=The OU story|last=admin|date=12 March 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the OU accepted its first 25,000 students in 1971, adopting a radical open admissions policy. At the time, the total student population of conventional universities in the United Kingdom was around 130,000.{{citation needed|date=May 2018}}

[[Athabasca University]], Canada's Open University, was created in 1970 and followed a similar, though independently developed, pattern.&lt;ref name=&quot;byrne&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last =Byrne | first =T. C. | authorlink =Tim Byrne | title =Athabasca University The Evolution of Distance Education | publisher = University of Calgary Press | year= 1989 |location = Calgary, Alberta | page = 135| isbn = 0-919813-51-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Open University inspired the creation of Spain's [[National University of Distance Education]] (1972)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title= History of UNED (in Spanish) | location=ES | accessdate=2012-01-26| url= http://portal.uned.es/portal/page?_pageid=93,499271,93_20500119&amp;_dad=portal&amp;_schema=PORTAL }}&lt;/ref&gt; and Germany's [[FernUniversität in Hagen]] (1974).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title= Three Decades |url= http://www.fernuni-hagen.de/english/profile/3decades/learning.shtml |publisher= FernUniversität in Hage |location= UK |accessdate= 2011-01-23 |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20101123042944/http://fernuni-hagen.de/english/profile/3decades/learning.shtml |archive-date= 23 November 2010 |url-status= dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; There are now many similar institutions around the world, often with the name &quot;Open University&quot; (in [[English language|English]] or in the local language).{{citation needed|date=May 2018}}

Most [[open universities]] use distance education technologies as delivery methods, though some require attendance at local study centres or at regional &quot;summer schools&quot;. Some open universities have grown to become ''mega-universities'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Daniel | first1 = Sir John S |title= Mega-Universities and Knowledge Media: Technology Strategies for Higher Education | url= https://books.google.com/books?id=Sy3nDKphDAkC | accessdate=2011-01-23 |year=1998 | publisher= Routledge | isbn= 0-7494-2634-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; a term coined to denote institutions with more than 100,000 students.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.igi-global.com/dictionary/mega-universities/18251|title=What is Mega-Universities {{!}} IGI Global|website=www.igi-global.com|access-date=2019-01-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Technologies ==
Internet technology has enabled many forms of distance learning through [[open educational resources]] and facilities such as [[Educational technology|e-learning]] and [[Massive open online course|MOOC]]&lt;nowiki/&gt;s. Although the expansion of the Internet blurs the boundaries, distance education technologies are divided into two modes of delivery: [[synchronous learning]] and [[asynchronous learning]].

In synchronous learning, all participants are &quot;present&quot; at the same time. In this regard, it resembles traditional classroom teaching methods despite the participants being located remotely. It requires a timetable to be organized. [[Web conferencing]], [[videoconferencing]], [[educational television]], [[instructional television]] are examples of synchronous technology, as are [[direct-broadcast satellite]] (DBS), [[internet radio]], [[live streaming]], [[telephone]], and [[web-based VoIP]].&lt;ref name=&quot;lever-duffy&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last1=Lever-Duffy |first1=Judy |last2= McDonald |first2= Jean B |others= Ana A. Ciereszko, Al P. Mizell | title= Teaching and Learning with Technology | url= https://books.google.com/books?id=9wxKAAAAYAAJ | accessdate = 23 January 2011 | edition = 3rd |date=March 2007 | publisher=Allyn &amp; Bacon | isbn=978-0-205-51191-4 | page=377}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Web conferencing software helps to facilitate meetings in distance learning courses and usually contain additional interaction tools such as text chat, polls, hand raising, emoticons etc. These tools also support asynchronous participation by students being able to listen to recordings of synchronous sessions. Immersive environments (notably SecondLife) have also been used to enhance participant presence in distance education courses. Another form of synchronous learning that has been entering the classroom over the last couple of years is the use of robot proxies&lt;ref&gt;Brown, Robbie. (2013). A Swiveling Proxy That Will Even Wear a Tutu. ''New York Times.'' Retrieved from https://www.nytimes.com/2013/06/08/education/for-homebound-students-a-robot-proxy-in-the-classroom.html&lt;/ref&gt; including those that allow sick students to attend classes.&lt;ref&gt;Elizabeth Regan. (2015). &quot;Robot brings classroom to sick students'' Retrieved from http://www.norwichbulletin.com/article/20141109/NEWS/141109566?pagewanted=all&amp;_r=0&lt;nowiki/&gt;''&lt;/ref&gt;

Some universities have been starting to use robot proxies to enable more engaging synchronous hybrid classes where both remote and in person students can be present and interact using [[telerobotics]] devices such as the Kubi Telepresence robot stand that looks around and the Double Robot that roams around. With these telepresence robots, the remote students have a seat at the table or desk instead of being on a screen on the wall.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://designstudio.educ.msu.edu/from-a-spot-on-the-wall-to-a-seat-at-the-table/|title=From a Spot on the Wall to a Seat at the Table – CEPSE/COE Design Studio|access-date=25 June 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20181108162011/http://designstudio.educ.msu.edu/from-a-spot-on-the-wall-to-a-seat-at-the-table/|archive-date=8 November 2018|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Leila Meyer. (2015). &quot;Michigan State Tests Telepresence Robots for Online Students&quot; Retrieved from https://campustechnology.com/articles/2015/02/24/michigan-state-tests-telepresence-robots-for-online-students.aspx&lt;/ref&gt;

In asynchronous learning, participants access course materials flexibly on their own schedules. Students are not required to be together at the same time. Mail correspondence, which is the oldest form of distance education, is an asynchronous delivery technology, as are [[message board]] forums, [[e-mail]], [[video]] and [[audio recording]]s, print materials, [[voicemail]], and [[fax]].&lt;ref name=&quot;lever-duffy&quot; /&gt;

The two methods can be combined. Many courses offered by both open universities and an increasing number of campus based institutions use periodic sessions of residential or day teaching to supplement the sessions delivered at a distance.&lt;ref name=&quot;Burns&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last1=Burns |first1=Mary | title= Distance Education for Teacher Training: Modes, Models and Methods | url= http://go.edc.org/07xd | accessdate = 10 September 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; This type of mixed distance and campus based education has recently come to be called &quot;[[blended learning]]&quot; or less often &quot;hybrid learning&quot;. Many open universities uses a blend of technologies and a blend of learning modalities (face-to-face, distance, and hybrid) all under the rubric of &quot;distance learning&quot;.

Distance learning can also use interactive radio instruction (IRI), interactive audio instruction (IAI), online [[virtual world]]s, digital games, webinars, and webcasts, all of which are referred to as e-Learning.&lt;ref name=&quot;Burns&quot; /&gt;

=== Radio and television ===
{{external media | width = 210px | float = right | audio1 = [http://www.wnyc.org/story/745-air-college-talk/ Air college talk.], 2:45, December 2, 1931, [[WNYC]]&lt;ref name=&quot;smarth&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title =Air college talk. | website = | publisher =[[WNYC]] | date =December 2, 1931 | url =http://www.wnyc.org/story/745-air-college-talk/ | accessdate =November 5, 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt; }}
The rapid spread of film in the 1920s and radio in the 1930s led to proposals to use it for distance education.&lt;ref&gt;Larry Cuban. (1986). ''Teachers and Machines: The Classroom Use of Technology Since 1920'', pp&amp;nbsp;11–18 [https://books.google.com/books?id=uQeEn1vEUSQC online]&lt;/ref&gt; By 1938, at least 200 city school systems, 25 state boards of education, and many colleges and universities broadcast educational programs for the public schools.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Tyson | first1 = Levering | year = 1936 | title = Ten Years of Educational Broadcasting | url = | journal = School and Society | volume = 44 | issue = | pages = 225–31 }}&lt;/ref&gt; One line of thought was to use radio as a master teacher.
{{quote|Experts in given fields broadcast lessons for pupils within the many schoolrooms of the public school system, asking questions, suggesting readings, making assignments, and conducting tests. This mechanizes education and leaves the local teacher only the tasks of preparing for the broadcast and keeping order in the classroom.&lt;ref&gt;Lloyd Allen Cook.  (1938). ''Community Backgrounds of Education: A Textbook and Educational Sociology'', pp&amp;nbsp;249–250&lt;/ref&gt;}}
A typical setup came in Kentucky in 1948 when [[John Wilkinson Taylor (educator)|John Wilkinson Taylor]], president of the [[University of Louisville]], teamed up with [[National Broadcasting Corporation|NBC]] to use radio as a medium for distance education, The chairman of the [[Federal Communications Commission]] endorsed the project and predicted that the &quot;college-by-radio&quot; would put &quot;American education 25&amp;nbsp;years ahead&quot;. The University was owned by the city, and local residents would pay the low tuition rates, receive their study materials in the mail, and listen by radio to live classroom discussions that were held on campus.&lt;ref&gt;Dwayne D. Cox and William J. Morison. (1999). ''The University of Louisville'', pp&amp;nbsp;115–117&lt;/ref&gt; Physicist [[Daniel Q. Posin]] also was a pioneer in the field of distance education when he hosted a televised course through [[DePaul University]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Vyse|first1=Stuart|title=Before Carl Sagan and Neil deGrasse Tyson, There Was Dan Q. Posin|url=https://www.csicop.org/si/show/before_carl_sagan_and_neil_degrasse_tyson_there_was_dan_q._posin|website=Committee for Skeptical Inquiry|accessdate=25 April 2018|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20180424223305/https://www.csicop.org/si/show/before_carl_sagan_and_neil_degrasse_tyson_there_was_dan_q._posin|archivedate=24 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Charles Wedemeyer]] of the [[University of Wisconsin–Madison]] also promoted new methods. From 1964 to 1968, the [[Carnegie Corporation of New York|Carnegie Foundation]] funded Wedemeyer's ''Articulated Instructional Media Project'' (AIM) which brought in a variety of communications technologies aimed at providing learning to an off-campus population. The radio courses faded away in the 1950s.&lt;ref&gt;Cuban. (1986). ''Teachers and Machines: The Classroom Use of Technology Since 1920'', pp&amp;nbsp;19–26&lt;/ref&gt; Many efforts to use television along the same lines proved unsuccessful, despite heavy funding by the [[Ford Foundation]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Christopher H. Sterling|author2=Cary O'Dell|title=The Concise Encyclopedia of American Radio|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=dmmLAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA609|year=2011|publisher=Routledge|page=609|isbn=978-1-135-17684-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Robert J. Taggart. (2007). &quot;The Promise and Failure of Educational Television in a Statewide System: Delaware, 1964–1971.&quot; ''American Educational History Journal'', ''24''&amp;nbsp;(1), 111–122. [https://books.google.com/books?id=n_eEVfDG44kC&amp;pg=PA111 online]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Cuban.  (1986).''Teachers and Machines: The Classroom Use of Technology Since 1920'', pp&amp;nbsp;27–50&lt;/ref&gt;

From 1970 to 1972 the Coordinating Commission for Higher Education in California funded Project Outreach to study the potential of telecourses. The study included the [[University of California]], [[California State University]] and the community colleges. This study led to coordinated instructional systems legislation allowing the use of public funds for non-classroom instruction and paved the way for the emergence of telecourses as the precursor to the online courses and programs of today. The [[Coastline Community College]]s, The [[Dallas County Community College District]], and [[Miami Dade Community College]] led the way. The ''Adult Learning Service'' of the US [[Public Broadcasting Service]] came into being and the “wrapped” series, and individually produced telecourse for credit became a significant part of the history of distance education and online learning.

=== Internet ===
{{Main|Virtual education}}The widespread use of computers and the [[internet]] have made distance learning easier and faster, and today [[virtual school]]s and [[Virtual university|virtual universities]] deliver full curricula online.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1 = Gold|first1 = Larry|last2 = Maitland|first2 = Christine|editor1-first = Ronald A.|editor1-last = Phipps|editor2-first = Jamie P.|editor2-last = Merisotis|title = What's the difference? A review of contemporary research on the effectiveness of distance learning in higher education|url = https://books.google.com/books?ei=ldA7TcruEZG38gODpYykCA|accessdate = 23 January 2011|year = 1999|publisher = Institute for Higher Education Policy|location = Washington, DC}}&lt;/ref&gt; The capacity of Internet to support voice, video, text and immersion teaching methods made earlier distinct forms of telephone, videoconferencing, radio, television, and text based education somewhat redundant. However, many of the techniques developed and lessons learned with earlier media are used in Internet delivery.

The first completely online course for credit was offered by the [[University of Toronto]] in 1984&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.tonybates.ca/2016/01/17/celebrating-the-30th-anniversary-of-the-first-fully-online-course/|title=Celebrating the 30th anniversary of the first fully online course {{!}} Tony Bates|last=Bates|first=Tony|website=www.tonybates.ca|language=en-US|access-date=2019-06-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; through the Graduate School of Education (then called OISE: the [[Ontario Institute for Studies in Education]]).  The topic was “Women and Computers in Education”, dealing with gender issues and educational computing.  The first new and fully online university was founded in 1994 as the [[Open University of Catalonia]], headquartered in Barcelona, Spain. In 1999 [[Jones International University]] was launched as the first fully online university [[Educational accreditation|accredited]] by a regional accrediting association in the US.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title = Accreditation|url = http://www.jiu.edu/about-jiu/accreditation|publisher = Jones International University|location = US|accessdate = 23 January 2011|url-status = dead|archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20130421085153/http://www.jiu.edu/about-jiu/accreditation|archivedate = 21 April 2013|df = dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Between 2000 and 2008, enrollment in distance education courses increased rapidly in almost every country in both developed and developing countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Walton Radford, MPR Associates |first=Alexandria |title=Learning at a Distance: Undergraduate Enrollment in Distance Education Courses and Degree Programs |url=http://nces.ed.gov/pubs2012/2012154.pdf |publisher=National Center for Education Statistics |accessdate=30 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many private, public, [[non-profit]] and for-profit institutions worldwide now offer distance education courses from the most basic instruction through to the highest levels of degree and doctoral programs. [[New York University]], [https://iuc-edu.ca/ International University Canada], for example, offers [[online degree]]s in engineering and management-related fields through [[NYU Tandon Online]]. Levels of accreditation vary: widely respected universities such as Stanford University and Harvard now deliver online courses—but other online schools receive little outside oversight, and some are actually fraudulent, i.e., [[diploma mill]]s. In the US, the [[Distance Education Accrediting Commission]] (DEAC) specializes in the accreditation of distance education institutions.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.deac.org/accred.html |title=Accreditation |publisher=DEAC |accessdate=20 September 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the United States in 2011, it was found that a third of all the students enrolled in postsecondary education had taken an accredited online course in a postsecondary institution.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lederman2&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last = Lederman|first = Doug|title = Growth for Online Learning|url = http://www.insidehighered.com/news/2013/01/08/survey-finds-online-enrollments-slow-continue-grow|accessdate = 30 March 2013|newspaper = InsideHigherEd|date = 8 January 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Even though growth rates are slowing, enrollment for online courses has been seen to increase with the advance in technology. The majority of public and private colleges now offer full academic programs online.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lederman2&quot; /&gt; These include, but are not limited to, training programs in the [[mental health]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Blackmore, C. 2007&quot;&gt;Blackmore, C., van Deurzen, E., &amp; Tantam, D. (2007). Therapy training online: Using the internet to widen access to training in mental health issues. In T. Stickley &amp; T. Basset (Eds.) Teaching Mental Health (pgs. 337-352). Hoboken, NJ: John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd.&lt;/ref&gt; [[occupational therapy]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Jedlicka, J. S. 20022&quot;&gt;Jedlicka, J. S., Brown, S. W., Bunch, A. E., &amp; Jaffe, L. E. (2002). A comparison of distance education instructional methods in occupational therapy. Journal of Allied Health, 31(4), 247-251.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Stanton, S. 20012&quot;&gt;Stanton, S. (2001). Going the distance; Developing shared web-based learning programmes. Occupational Therapy International, 8(2), 96-106.&lt;/ref&gt; [[family therapy]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Maggio, L. M. 20012&quot;&gt;Maggio, L. M., Chenail, R., &amp; Todd, T. (2001). Teaching family therapy in an electronic age. Journal of Systemic Therapies, 20(1), 13-23.&lt;/ref&gt; [[art therapy]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Orr, P. 20102&quot;&gt;Orr, P. (2010). Distance supervision: Research, findings, and considerations for art therapy. The Arts in Psychotherapy, 37, 106-111.&lt;/ref&gt; [[physical therapy]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Stanton, S. 20012&quot; /&gt; and [[rehabilitation counseling]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Stebnicki, M. A. 20012&quot;&gt;Stebnicki, M. A. &amp; Glover, N. M. (2001). E-supervision as a complementary approach to traditional face-to-face clinical supervision in rehabilitation counseling: Problems and solutions. Rehabilitation Education, 15(3), 283-293.&lt;/ref&gt; fields.

Distance education has a long history, but its popularity and use has grown exponentially as more advanced technology has become available. By 2008, online learning programs were available in the United States in 44 states at the K-12 level.&lt;ref&gt;Olszewski-Kubilius, Paula; Corwith, Susan. &quot;Distance Education: Where It Started and Where It Stands for Gifted Children and Their Educators.&quot; Gifted Child Today, v. 34 issue 3, 2011, p. 16-24,.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Internet forum]]s, online [[discussion group]] and [[online learning community]] can contribute to an efficacious distance education experience. Research shows that [[socialization]] plays an important role in some forms of distance education.&lt;ref name=&quot;SRE4(13)2&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1016/j.sbspro.2013.09.199 |title=Alleviating the Senses of Isolation and Alienation in the Virtual World: Socialization in Distance Education |journal=Procedia - Social and Behavioral Sciences |volume=93 |pages=332–7 |year=2013 |last1=Sazmandasfaranjan |first1=Yasha |last2=Shirzad |first2=Farzad |last3=Baradari |first3=Fatemeh |last4=Salimi |first4=Meysam |last5=Salehi |first5=Mehrdad }}&lt;/ref&gt;

E-courses are also a viable option for distance learning.  There are many available that cover a broad range of topics.

== Paced and self-paced models ==
Distance education can be delivered in a paced format similar to traditional campus based models in which learners commence and complete a course at the same time. Paced delivery is currently the most common mode of distance education delivery. Alternatively, some institutions offer self-paced programs that allow for continuous enrollment and the length of time to complete the course is set by the learner's time, skill and commitment levels. Paced courses may be offered in either synchronous mode, but self-paced courses are almost always offered asynchronously. Each delivery model offers both advantages and disadvantages for students, teachers and institutions.

[[Andreas Kaplan|Kaplan]] and Haenlein classify distance education into four groups along the dimensions Time dependency and Number of participants: 1) [[MOOCs]] (Massive Open Online Courses): Open-access online course (i.e., without specific participation restrictions) that allows for unlimited (massive) participation; 2) [[Small private online course|SPOCs]] (Small Private Online Courses): Online course that only offers a limited number of places and therefore requires some form of formal enrollment; 3) SMOCs (Synchronous Massive Online Courses): Open-access online course that allows for unlimited participation but requires students to be &quot;present&quot; at the same time (synchronously); 4) SSOCs (Synchronous Private Online Courses): Online course that only offers a limited number of places and requires students to be &quot;present&quot; at the same time (synchronously).&lt;ref name=&quot;Kaplan Haenlein 2016&quot;/&gt;

Paced models are a familiar mode as they are used almost exclusively in campus based schools. Institutes that offer both distance and campus programs usually use paced models as teacher workload, student semester planning, tuition deadlines, exam schedules and other administrative details can be synchronized with campus delivery. Student familiarity and the pressure of deadlines encourages students to readily adapt to and usually succeed in paced models. However, student freedom is sacrificed as a common pace is often too fast for some students and too slow for others. In addition life events, professional or family responsibilities can interfere with a students capability to complete tasks to an external schedule. Finally, paced models allows students to readily form communities of inquiry&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = https://coi.athabascau.ca|title = Community of Inquiry site|date = |accessdate = |website = |publisher = Athabasca University|last = |first = }}&lt;/ref&gt; and to engage in collaborative work.

Self-paced courses maximize student freedom, as not only can students commence studies on any date, but they can complete a course in as little time as a few weeks or up to a year or longer. Students often enroll in self-paced study when they are under pressure to complete programs, have not been able to complete a scheduled course, need additional courses or have pressure which precludes regular study for any length of time. The self-paced nature of the programming, though is an unfamiliar model for many students and can lead to excessive procrastination resulting in course incompletion. Assessment of learning can also be challenging as exams can be written on any day, making it possible for students to share examination questions with resulting loss of academic integrity. Finally, it is extremely challenging to organize collaborative work activities, though some schools&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Teaching Crowds: Learning and Social Media|last = Dron|first = Jon|publisher = AU Press|year = 2014|isbn = |location = |pages = |last2 = Anderson|first2 = Terry}}&lt;/ref&gt; are developing cooperative models based upon networked and connectivist pedagogies,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.19173/irrodl.v12i3.890 |title=Three generations of distance education pedagogy	|journal=The International Review of Research in Open and Distance Learning |volume=12 |issue=3 |pages=80–97 |year=2011 |last1=Anderson |first1=Terry |last2=Dron |first2=Jon }}&lt;/ref&gt; for use in self-paced programs.

== Benefits ==
[[Distance line|Distance]]&lt;ref&gt;0&lt;/ref&gt; learning can expand access to education and training for both general populace and businesses since its flexible scheduling structure lessens the effects of the many time-constraints imposed by personal responsibilities and commitments.&lt;ref name=Oblinger&gt;{{cite journal |last=Oblinger |first=Diana G. |year=2000 |title=The Nature and Purpose of Distance Education |journal=The Technology Source |volume= |series= |issue=March/April |page= |pages= |publisher=Michigan Virtual University |location=Michigan |issn= |pmid= |pmc= |doi= |bibcode= |oclc= |id= |url=http://technologysource.org/article/nature_and_purpose_of_distance_education/ |language= |format= |accessdate=23 January 2011 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110718000146/http://technologysource.org/article/nature_and_purpose_of_distance_education/ |archive-date=18 July 2011 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CFP&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Masson|first1=M|title=Benefits of TED Talks|journal=Canadian Family Physician|date=December 2014|volume=60|issue=12|pages=1080|pmid=25500595|pmc=4264800|doi=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Devolving some activities off-site alleviates institutional capacity constraints arising from the traditional demand on institutional buildings and infrastructure.&lt;ref name=Oblinger /&gt; Furthermore, there is the potential for increased access to more experts in the field and to other students from diverse geographical, social, cultural, economic, and experiential backgrounds.&lt;ref name=&quot;Maggio, L. M. 20012&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CFP&quot;/&gt;
As the population at large becomes more involved in [[lifelong learning]] beyond the normal schooling age, institutions can benefit financially, and adult learning business courses may be particularly lucrative.&lt;ref name=Oblinger /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CFP&quot;/&gt; Distance education programs can act as a catalyst for institutional innovation&lt;ref name=Oblinger /&gt; and are at least as effective as face-to-face learning programs,&lt;ref name=&quot;Blackmore, C. 2007&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Jedlicka, J. S. 20022&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=Nguyen&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Nguyen|first1=Tuan|title=The Effectiveness of Online Learning: Beyond No Significant Difference and Future Horizons|journal=MERLOT Journal of Online Learning and Teaching|date=June 2015|volume=11|issue=2|pages=309–319|url=http://jolt.merlot.org/Vol11no2/Nguyen_0615.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; especially if the instructor is knowledgeable and skilled.&lt;ref name=&quot;Orr, P. 20102&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CFP&quot;/&gt;

Distance education can also provide a broader method of communication within the realm of education.&lt;ref name=&quot;CFP&quot;/&gt; With the many tools and programs that technological advancements have to offer, communication appears to increase in distance education amongst students and their professors, as well as students and their classmates. The distance educational increase in communication, particularly communication amongst students and their classmates, is an improvement that has been made to provide distance education students with as many of the opportunities as possible as they would receive in in-person education. The improvement being made in distance education is growing in tandem with the constant technological advancements. Present-day online communication allows students to associate with accredited schools and programs throughout the world that are out of reach for in-person learning. By having the opportunity to be involved in global institutions via distance education, a diverse array of thought is presented to students through communication with their classmates. This is beneficial because students have the opportunity to &quot;combine new opinions with their own, and develop a solid foundation for learning&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;calpoly1&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |title=Educational Benefits of Online Learning|pages=1–6|year=1998|url=http://blackboardsupport.calpoly.edu/content/faculty/handouts/Ben_Online.pdf|publisher=CalPoly.edu |accessdate=29 March 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; It has been shown through research that &quot;as learners become aware of the variations in interpretation and construction of meaning among a range of people [they] construct an individual meaning&quot;, which can help students become knowledgeable of a wide array of viewpoints in education.&lt;ref name=&quot;calpoly1&quot; /&gt; To increase the likelihood that students will build effective ties with one another during the course, instructors should use similar assignments for students across different locations to overcome the influence of co-location on relationship building.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1111/j.1083-6101.2006.00308.x |title=Homophily of Network Ties and Bonding and Bridging Social Capital in Computer-Mediated Distributed Teams |journal=Journal of Computer-Mediated Communication |volume=11 |issue=4 |pages=1062–84 |year=2006 |last1=Yuan |first1=Y. Connie |last2=Gay |first2=Geri }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The high cost of education affects students in higher education, to which distance education may be an alternative in order to provide some relief.&lt;ref name=Nguyen /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CFP&quot;/&gt; Distance education has been a more cost-effective form of learning, and can sometimes save students a significant amount of money as opposed to traditional education.&lt;ref name=&quot;CFP&quot;/&gt; Distance education may be able to help to save students a considerable amount financially by removing the cost of transportation.&lt;ref name=&quot;worldwidelearn2013&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.worldwidelearn.com/education-articles/benefits-of-online-learning.htm |title=Benefits of Online Education |publisher=Worldwidelearn.com |accessdate=1 April 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, distance education may be able to save students from the economic burden of high-priced course textbooks. Many textbooks are now available as electronic textbooks, known as e-textbooks, which can offer digital textbooks for a reduced price in comparison to traditional textbooks. Also, the increasing improvements in technology have resulted in many school libraries having a partnership with digital publishers that offer course materials for free, which can help students significantly with educational costs.&lt;ref name=&quot;worldwidelearn2013&quot; /&gt;

Within the class, students are able to learn in ways that traditional classrooms would not be able to provide. It is able to promote good learning experiences and therefore, allow students to obtain higher satisfaction with their online learning.&lt;ref name=Kirtman&gt;{{cite journal|last=Kirtman|first=Lisa|title=Online Versus In-Class Courses: An Examination of Differences in Learning Outcomes|journal=Issues in Teacher Education|date=Fall 2009|volume=18|issue=2|pages=103–115|url=http://www1.chapman.edu/ITE/public_html/ITEFall09/12kirtman.pdf|accessdate=30 March 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, students can review their lessons more than once according to their need. Students can then manipulate the coursework to fit their learning by focusing more on their weaker topics while breezing through concepts that they already have or can easily grasp.&lt;ref name=Kirtman /&gt; When course design and the [[learning environment]] are at their optimal conditions, distance education can lead students to higher satisfaction with their learning experiences.&lt;ref name=Nguyen /&gt; Studies have shown that high satisfaction correlates to increased learning. For those in a healthcare or mental health distance learning program, online-based interactions have the potential to foster deeper reflections and discussions of client issues&lt;ref name=&quot;Stanton, S. 20012&quot; /&gt; as well as a quicker response to client issues, since supervision happens on a regular basis and is not limited to a weekly supervision meeting.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stebnicki, M. A. 20012&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CFP&quot;/&gt; This also may contribute to the students feeling a greater sense of support, since they have ongoing and regular access to their instructors and other students.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stanton, S. 20012&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Stebnicki, M. A. 20012&quot; /&gt;

Distance learning may enable students who are unable to attend a traditional school setting, due to [[disability]] or illness such as decreased mobility and immune system suppression, to get a good education.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=An Exploration of the Representation of Students with Disabilities in Distance Education|url=http://www.westga.edu/~distance/ojdla/winter144/woods_maiden_brandes144.html|accessdate=7 December 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Children who are sick or are unable to attend classes are able to attend them in &quot;person&quot; through the use of [[robot]] proxies. This helps the students have experiences of the classroom and social interaction that they are unable to receive at home or the hospital, while still keeping them in a safe learning environment. Over the last few years{{When|date=July 2016}} more students are entering safely back into the classroom thanks to the help of robots. An article from the ''New York Times'', &quot;A Swiveling Proxy Will Even Wear a Tutu&quot;, explains the positive impact of virtual learning in the classroom,&lt;ref&gt;Brown, Robbie. (2013). ''The New York Times''. [https://www.nytimes.com/2013/06/08/education/for-homebound-students-a-robot-proxy-in-the-classroom.html A Swiveling Proxy That Will Even Wear a Tutu]&lt;/ref&gt; and another&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.norwichbulletin.com/article/20141109/news/141109566|title=Robot brings classroom to sick students|first=Elizabeth|last=Reganeregan@norwichbulletin.com(860) 425-4256|website=The Bulletin}}&lt;/ref&gt; that explains how even a simple, stationary telepresence robot can help.&lt;ref&gt;Elizabeth Regan. (2014). Robot brings classroom to sick students. ''Norwich Bulletin.''http://www.norwichbulletin.com/article/20141109/NEWS/141109566&lt;/ref&gt;
Distance education may provide equal access regardless of socioeconomic status or income, area of residence, gender, race, age, or cost per student.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://madamenoire.com/105928/cyber-charter-schools-the-end-of-public-education-or-a-new-beginning |title=Cyber-charter Schools: The end of Public Education or a New Beginning}}&lt;/ref&gt; Applying [[universal design]] strategies to distance learning courses as they are being developed (rather than instituting accommodations for specific students on an as-needed basis) can increase the [[accessibility]] of such courses to students with a range of abilities, disabilities, learning styles, and native languages.&lt;ref&gt;Burgstahler, S.,{{cite web |url=http://www.washington.edu/doit/Brochures/Technology/equal_access_uddl.html |title=Equal Access: Universal Design of Distance Learning |accessdate=12 February 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Distance education graduates, who would never have been associated with the school under a traditional system, may donate money to the school.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1080/01930826.2010.488597 |title=Untapped Potential: Seeking Library Donors among Alumni of Distance Learning Programs |journal=Journal of Library Administration |volume=50 |issue=5–6 |pages=515–29 |year=2010 |last1=Casey |first1=Anne Marie |last2=Lorenzen |first2=Michael |url=https://commons.erau.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1005&amp;context=hunt-library-staff-works }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Distance learning may also offer a final opportunity for adolescents that are no longer permitted in the general education population due to behavior disorders. Instead of these students having no other academic opportunities, they may continue their education from their homes and earn their diplomas, offering them another chance to be an integral part of society.

Distance learning offers individuals a unique opportunity to benefit from the expertise and resources of the best universities currently available. Students have the ability to collaborate, share, question, infer, and suggest new methods and techniques for continuous improvement of the content. The ability to complete a course at a pace that is appropriate for each individual is the most effective manner to learn given the personal demands on time and schedule.&lt;ref name=&quot;CFP&quot;/&gt; Self-paced distance learning on a mobile device, such is a smartphone, provides maximum flexibility and capability.

== Criticism ==
Barriers to effective distance education include obstacles such as domestic distractions and unreliable technology,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Östlund|first=Berit|title=Stress, disruption and community&amp;nbsp;— Adult learners' experiences of obstacles and opportunities in distance education|url=http://www.eurodl.org/index.php?p=&amp;sp=full&amp;article=179|publisher=Department of Child and Youth Education, Special Education and Counselling, Umeå University|accessdate=3 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as students' program costs, adequate contact with teachers and support services, and a need for more experience.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |first=Jill M. |last=Galusha |title=Barriers to Learning in Distance Education |url=http://www.infrastruction.com/barriers.htm |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20000229041104/http://www.infrastruction.com/barriers.htm |url-status=dead |archive-date=29 February 2000 |accessdate=10 April 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some students attempt to participate in distance education without proper training with the tools needed to be successful in the program. Students must be provided with training opportunities (if needed) on each tool that is used throughout the program. The lack of advanced technology skills can lead to an unsuccessful experience. Schools have a responsibility to adopt a proactive policy for managing technology barriers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Stephens |first=D. |date=July 2007 |title=Quality issues in distance learning |url=http://www.aacsb.edu/publications/whitepapers/quality-issues-distance-learning.pdf |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120601203911/http://www.aacsb.edu/publications/whitepapers/quality-issues-distance-learning.pdf |archivedate=1 June 2012 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Time management skills and self-discipline in distance education is just as important as complete knowledge of the software and tools being used for learning.

The results of a study of Washington state community college students showed that distance learning students tended to drop out more often than their traditional counterparts due to difficulties in language, time management, and study skills.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ccrc.tc.columbia.edu/publications/online-hybrid-courses-washington.html?UID=872|title=Online and Hybrid Course Enrollment and Performance in Washington State Community and Technical Colleges|last=Gabriel}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Dr. Pankaj Singhm, director of [[NIMS University|Nims University]], &quot;distance learning benefits may outweigh the disadvantages for students in such a technology-driven society; however before indulging into use of [[educational technology]] a few more disadvantages should be considered.&quot; He describes that over multiple years, &quot;all of the obstacles have been overcome and the world environment for distance education continues to improve.&quot; Dr. Pankaj Singhm also claims there is a debate to distance education stating, &quot;due to a lack of direct face-to-face social interaction. However, as more people become used to personal and social interaction online (for example dating, chat rooms, shopping, or blogging), it is becoming easier for learners to both project themselves and socialize with others. This is an obstacle that has dissipated.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.scdl.net/InternationalConference/PDFS/DigitalProceeding/Full%20paper%20Pankaj%20Singh.pdf|title=Unleashing the potential of ODL - &quot;Reaching the unreached&quot;|last=|first=|date=24 January 2018|website=Symbiosis Center for Distance Learning|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Not all courses required to complete a degree may be offered online. Health care profession programs in particular, require some sort of patient interaction through field work before a student may graduate.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.distancelearningnet.com/advantages-and-disadvantages-of-distance-learning/&lt;/ref&gt; Studies have also shown that students pursuing a medical professional graduate degree who are participating in distance education courses, favor face to face communication over professor-mediated chat rooms and/or independent studies. However, this is little correlation between student performance when comparing the previous different distance learning strategies.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jedlicka, J. S. 20022&quot; /&gt;

There is a theoretical problem about the application of traditional teaching methods to online courses because online courses may have no upper size limit. [[Daniel Barwick]] noted that there is no evidence that large class size is always worse or that small class size is always better, although a negative link has been established between certain types of instruction in large classes and learning outcomes; he argued that higher education has not made a sufficient effort to experiment with a variety of instructional methods to determine whether large class size is always negatively correlated with a reduction in learning outcomes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Barwick |first=Daniel W.|url=http://www.insidehighered.com/views/2007/12/06/barwick |title=Views: Does Class Size Matter? |website=Inside Higher Ed |accessdate=3 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Early proponents of Massive Open Online Courses ([[MOOC]])s saw them as just the type of experiment that Barwick had pointed out was lacking in higher education, although Barwick himself has never advocated for [[Massive open online course|MOOCs]].

There may also be institutional challenges. Distance learning is new enough that it may be a challenge to gain support for these programs in a traditional brick-and-mortar academic learning environment.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stanton, S. 20012&quot; /&gt; Furthermore, it may be more difficult for the instructor to organize and plan a distance learning program,&lt;ref name=&quot;Stebnicki, M. A. 20012&quot; /&gt; especially since many are new programs and their organizational needs are different from a traditional learning program.

Additionally, though distance education offers industrial countries the opportunity to become globally informed, there are still negative sides to it. Hellman states that &quot;These include its cost and capital intensiveness, time constraints and other pressures on instructors, the isolation of students from instructors and their peers, instructors’ enormous difficulty in adequately evaluating students they never meet face-to-face, and drop-out rates far higher than in classroom-based courses.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hellman, Judith Adler 2003&quot;&gt;Hellman, Judith Adler. &quot;The Riddle of Distance Education.&quot; Geneva. 1 June 2003.&lt;/ref&gt;

A more complex challenge of distance education relates to cultural differences between student and teachers and among students. Distance programmes tend to be more diverse as they could go beyond the geographical borders of regions, countries, and continents, and cross the cultural borders that may exist with respect to race, gender, and religion. That requires a proper understanding and awareness of the norms, differences, preconceptions and potential conflicting issues.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nasiri et Mafakheri&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1080/03075079.2014.914906 |title=Postgraduate research supervision at a distance: A review of challenges and strategies |journal=Studies in Higher Education |volume=40 |issue=10 |pages=1962–9 |year=2014 |last1=Nasiri |first1=Fuzhan |last2=Mafakheri |first2=Fereshteh }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Educational technology ==
The modern use of electronic [[educational technology]] (also called e-learning) facilitates distance learning and independent learning by the extensive use of [[information and communications technology]] (ICT),&lt;ref name=&quot;CFP&quot;/&gt; replacing traditional content delivery by postal correspondence. Instruction can be synchronous and asynchronous online communication in an interactive learning environment or virtual communities, in lieu of a physical classroom. &quot;The focus is shifted to the education transaction in the form of virtual community of learners sustainable across time.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Garrison, D.R. (2011, 20 May). E-Learning in the 21st Century: A Framework for Research and Practice. New York: Taylor &amp; Francis. {{ISBN|0-203-83876-9}}{{page needed|date=January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

One of the most significant issues encountered in the mainstream correspondence model of distance education is transactional distance, which results from the lack of appropriate communication between learner and teacher. This gap has been observed to become wider if there is no communication between the learner and teacher and has direct implications over the learning process and future endeavors in distance education. Distance education providers began to introduce various strategies, techniques, and procedures to increase the amount of interaction between learner and teacher. These measures e.g. more frequent face-to-face tutorials, increased use of information and communication technologies including teleconferencing and the Internet, were designed to close the gap in transactional distance.&lt;ref&gt;Soekartawi, Haryono, A. &amp; Librero, F. 2002. Greater Learning Opportunities Through Distance Education: Experiences in Indonesia and the Philippines. ''Journal of Southeast Asian Education'', Vol. 3, No. 2, pp. 283–320. Retrieved from http://www.seameo-journal.com/journal/index.php/education/article/viewFile/39/38{{dead link|date=February 2018 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Credentials ==
{{Main|Online credentials for learning}}

Online credentials for learning&amp;nbsp;are digital credentials that are offered in place of traditional paper credentials for a skill or educational achievement. Directly linked to the accelerated development of internet communication technologies, the development of&amp;nbsp;[[digital badge]]s,&amp;nbsp;[[electronic passport]]s&amp;nbsp;and&amp;nbsp;[[massive open online course]]s&amp;nbsp;(MOOCs) have a very direct bearing on our understanding of learning, recognition and levels as they pose a direct challenge to the status quo. It is useful to distinguish between three forms of online credentials: Test-based credentials, online badges, and online certificates.&lt;ref name=&quot;:02&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://unesdoc.unesco.org/images/0024/002428/242887e.pdf|title=Level-setting and recognition of learning outcomes: The use of level descriptors in the twenty-first century|last=Keevy|first=James|last2=Chakroun|first2=Borhene|publisher=Paris, UNESCO|year=2015|isbn=978-92-3-100138-3|location=|pages=129–131}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Degree completion program]]
* Distance and on-line learning advocates
** [[Herbert Gross]]
** [[Linda Harasim]]
* [[Educational technology]]
* [[Homeschooling]]
* [[Learning environment]]
* [[Low-residency program]]
* [[Media psychology]]
* [[New media]]
* [[Open supported learning]]
* [[Open-door academic policy]]
* [[Qualifications framework#Qualifications frameworks for online learning|Qualifications frameworks for online learning]]
* ''[[Sunrise Semester]]''
* [[Virtual education]]

== Sources ==
{{Free-content attribution
| title = Level-setting and recognition of learning outcomes: The use of level descriptors in the twenty-first century
| author = Keevey, James; Chakroun, Borhene
| publisher = UNESCO
| page numbers = 129-131
| source = UNESCO
| documentURL = http://unesdoc.unesco.org/images/0024/002428/242887e.pdf
| license statement URL = http://www.unesco.org/ulis/cgi-bin/ulis.pl?catno=242887&amp;set=0058D22B8C_1_128&amp;gp=1&amp;lin=1&amp;ll=1
| license = CC-BY-SA IGO 3.0
}}

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== Further reading ==
*Anderson, T. (2008). ''Theory and Practice of Online Education'' (2nd ed) {{ISBN|9781897425084}}
* Anderson, T., &amp; Dron, J. (2010). Three generations of distance education pedagogy. ''The International Review of Research in Open and Distance Learning'', 12(3), 80-97.
* Bates, T. (2005). ''Technology, e-learning and distance education'': RoutledgeFalmer.
* {{cite journal |doi=10.1126/science.24.611.327 |pmid=17772791 |title=The Correspondence School--Its Relation to Technical Education and Some of Its Results |journal=Science |volume=24 |issue=611 |pages=327–34 |year=1906 |last1=Clark |first1=J. J. |bibcode=1906Sci....24..327C |url=https://zenodo.org/record/1447968/files/article.pdf }}
* {{cite journal | last1 = Hampel | first1 = Robert L | year = 2010 | title = The Business of Education: Home Study at Columbia University and the University of Wisconsin in the 1920s and 1930s | url = | journal = Teachers College Record | volume = 112 | issue = 9| pages = 2496–2517 }}
*Holmberg, Börje. (1995). ''Theory and Practice of Distance Education'' (2nd ed) [https://www.questia.com/library/109055550/theory-and-practice-of-distance-education online]
* Kett, Joseph F. (1994). ''Pursuit of Knowledge Under Difficulties: From Self-Improvement to Adult Education in America'' {{ISBN|978-0804726801}}
* {{cite book|author=Moore, Michael Grahame and William Anderson|title=Handbook of Distance Education|year=2012|edition=2nd|publisher=Psychology Press|isbn=978-1-4106-0729-4}} [https://www.questia.com/library/104778858/handbook-of-distance-education online edition]
*Major, C. H. (2015). Teaching online: A guide to theory, research, and practice. (Johns Hopkins University Press).
* Moore, M. G. (1990). ''Contemporary issues in American distance education'' (Ed.)
* Peters, O. (1994). Distance education and industrial production: A comparative interpretation in outline(1973). ''Otto Peters on distance education: The industrialization of teaching and learning'', 107-127.
* Saba, F. (2011). Distance Education in the United States: Past, Present, Future. ''Educational Technology'', 51(6), 11.
*Stubblefield, Harold W. and Patrick Keane.  (1994). ''Adult Education in the American Experience: From the Colonial Period to the Present''  {{ISBN|  978-0787900250}}
* Taylor, J. C. (2001). Fifth generation distance education. ''e-Journal of Instructional Science and Technology'' (e-JIST), 4(1), 1-14.
* Terry Evans, M. H., David Murphy (Ed.). (2008). ''International Handbook of Distance Education''. Bingley: Emerald Group Publishing Limited.
* Walsh, T. (2011). ''Unlocking the Gates: How and Why Leading Universities Are Opening Up Access to Their Courses'' (Princeton University Press, 2011) [https://www.questia.com/read/120917363/unlocking-the-gates-how-and-why-leading-universities online]

== External links ==
{{Wikibooks|ICT in Education}}

* {{curlie|Reference/Education/Distance_Learning|Distance learning}}
* [http://onlinebooks.library.upenn.edu/webbin/book//browse?type=lcsubc&amp;key=Radio%20in%20education&amp;c=x &quot;Radio in education&quot;] full text books and articles online; from 1930s and 1940s
* [http://www.aupress.ca/index.php/books/bySeries?s=DistanceEducation &quot;Issues in Distance Education book series from Athabasca University Press&quot;]. A series of over 10 books related to distance education research. Available in print for sale or online as open access.
* [http://www.washington.edu/doit/Resources/accessdl.html The Center on Accessible Distance Learning (AccessDL)], DO-IT Center, University of Washington
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20181108162011/http://designstudio.educ.msu.edu/from-a-spot-on-the-wall-to-a-seat-at-the-table/ &quot;Using Telepresence Robots to Bring Online and Face-to-Face Students Closer.&quot;]. Michigan State University Design Studio

{{commons category}}

{{Open navbox|state=collapsed}}

[[Category:Distance education| ]]
[[Category:Educational television]]
[[Category:Learning methods]]
[[Category:Types of university or college]]
[[Category:Television terminology|Education]]</text>
      <sha1>iy1vbat24496pq6jcg6rspmq26ls18b</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
