  <page>
    <title>Dagger</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8972</id>
    <revision>
      <id>939348076</id>
      <parentid>933848354</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-05T22:24:59Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Narky Blert</username>
        <id>22041646</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bluelink</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Fighting weapon with a sharp point}}
{{About|the weapon}}
[[File:Fs-dagger.jpg|thumb|right|300px|The [[Fairbairn–Sykes fighting knife]], a modern-day dagger]]

A '''dagger''' is a [[knife]] with a very sharp point and usually two sharp edges, typically designed or capable of being used as a thrusting or stabbing weapon.&lt;ref&gt;State v. Martin, 633 S.W.2d 80 (Mo. 1982):  This is the dictionary or popular-use definition of a dagger, which has been used to describe everything from an ice pick to a folding knife with pointed blade as a 'dagger'.  The Missouri Supreme Court used the popular definition of 'dagger' found in Webster's New Universal Dictionary (&quot;a short weapon with a sharp point used for stabbing&quot;) to rule that an ordinary pointed knife with four-to-five inch blade constitutes a 'dagger' under the Missouri criminal code.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;California Penal Code 12020(a)(24):&quot;dagger&quot; means a ''knife or other instrument'' with or without a handguard that is ''capable of ready use as a stabbing weapon'' that may inflict great bodily injury or death.  The State of California and other jurisdictions have seized upon the popular-use definition of a dagger to classify items ranging from a pointed kitchen knife to a tent stake as a 'dagger' under the law.&lt;/ref&gt;  Daggers have been used throughout human history for [[close combat]] confrontations,&lt;ref&gt;Burton, Walter E., ''Knives For Fighting Men'', Popular Science, July 1944, Vol. 145 No. 1, p. 150: The dagger is classified as a type of '''fighting knife''', while a ''[[combat knife]]'' is a knife '''specifically designed for military use''', and is thus only certain types of daggers designed for military use are considered to be combat knives.  Thus, an ordinary dagger designed for civilian sale and use is only a fighting knife, while the U.S. Army M3 trench knife is both a combat knife ''and'' a fighting knife.&lt;/ref&gt; and many cultures have used adorned daggers in ritual and ceremonial contexts. The distinctive shape and historic usage of the dagger have made it iconic and symbolic. A dagger in the modern sense is a weapon designed for close-proximity combat or self-defense; due to its use in historic weapon assemblages, it has associations with assassination and murders. Double-edged knives, however, play different sorts of roles in different social contexts. In some cultures, they are neither a weapon nor a tool, but a potent symbol of manhood; in others they are ritual objects used in body modifications such as circumcision.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Frieman|first1=Catherine|title=Flint Daggers in Prehistoric Europe|date=1950|publisher=Oxbox Books|location=United Kingdom}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A wide variety of thrusting knives have been described as daggers, including knives that feature only a single cutting edge, such as the European [[rondel dagger]] or the Persian [[pesh-kabz]], or, in some instances, no cutting edge at all, such as the [[stiletto]] of the Renaissance. However, in the last hundred years or so, in most contexts, a dagger has certain definable characteristics,  including a short blade with a sharply tapered point, a central [[Knife#Materials, features, and construction|spine]] or [[fuller (weapon)|fuller]], and usually two cutting edges sharpened the full length of the blade, or nearly so.&lt;ref name=&quot;EME&quot;&gt;Emerson, Robert L., ''Legal Medicine and Toxicology'', New York: D. Appleton &amp; Co. (1909), p. 80&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=cas&gt;Cassidy, William L., ''The Complete Book Of Knife Fighting'', {{ISBN|0-87364-029-2}}, {{ISBN|978-0-87364-029-9}} (1997), pp. 9–18, 27–36&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;DRA&quot;&gt;Draper, Frank W., ''A Text-book of Legal Medicine'', Philadelphia: W.B. Saunders &amp; Co. (1905), pp. 341–343&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Gross, Hans, ''Criminal Investigation: A Practical Textbook for Magistrates, Police Officers and Lawyers'', London: Sweet &amp; Maxwell (1949), p. 185&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Harding, David, and Cann, Jefferson (eds.), ''Weapons: An International Encyclopedia from 5000 B.C. to 2000 A.D.'', The Diagram Visual Group, New York: St. Martin's Press/Macmillan, {{ISBN|0-312-03950-6}}, {{ISBN|978-0-312-03950-9}} (1990), pp. 32–33&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Goddard, Wayne, ''The Wonder of Knifemaking'', Iola, WI: Krause Publications, {{ISBN|1-4402-1684-3}}, {{ISBN|978-1-4402-1684-8}} (2011), pp. 50, 131–132&lt;/ref&gt; Most daggers also feature a full crossguard to keep the hand from riding forwards onto the sharpened blade edges.&lt;ref name=cas/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;WER&quot;&gt;''The New Werner Twentieth Century edition of the Encyclopædia Britannica'', Volume 6, Akron, OH: The Werner Co. (1907), p. 669&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''[http://definitions.uslegal.com/d/dagger/ Dagger Law &amp; Legal Definition]''&lt;/ref&gt;

Daggers are primarily weapons, so [[knife legislation]] in many places restricts their manufacture, sale, possession, transport, or use.

==History==

===Early history===
[[File:Poignard 0.188.1 2 fond.jpg|150px|thumb|A [[Neolithic]] dagger from the [[Muséum de Toulouse]].]]
[[File:Puñal íbero de frontón (M.A.N.) 01.jpg|thumb|upright=.5|left|Pre-Roman Iberian iron dagger forged between the middle of the 5th century BC and the 3rd century BC]]
[[File:Bronze age, Kurdistan, Sine.jpg|150px|thumbnail|Bronze Age swords, [[Kurdistan]], museum of Sanandaj]]
[[File:Puñal ibero de Almedinilla - M.A.N.jpg|thumb|upright=.5|right|Iberian triangular iron dagger]]
{{VT|Chronology of bladed weapons}}
The earliest daggers were made of materials such as [[flint]], [[ivory]] or [[bone]] in [[Neolithic]] times.

[[Copper]] daggers appeared first in the early [[Bronze Age]], in the 3rd millennium BC,&lt;ref&gt;Sheridan, Alison, ''A Beaker Period Copper Dagger Blade from the Silees River near Ross Lough, Co. Fermanagh'', Ulster Journal of Archaeology, Vol. 56 (1993), pp. 61–62&lt;/ref&gt; and copper daggers of [[Early Minoan III]] (2400–2000 BC) were recovered at [[Knossos]].&lt;ref&gt;C. Michael Hogan, [http://www.themodernantiquarian.com/site/10854/knossos.html#fieldnotes ''Knossos fieldnotes'', Modern Antiquarian (2007)]&lt;/ref&gt;

In ancient Egypt, daggers were usually made of copper or bronze, while royalty had gold weapons. At least since [[pre-dynastic Egypt]],&lt;ref&gt;Iorwerth Eiddon Stephen Edwards, Cyril John Gadd, Nicholas Geoffrey Lemprière Hammond, 1970&lt;/ref&gt; (c. 3100 BC) daggers were adorned as [[ceremonial weapon|ceremonial objects]] with golden hilts and later even more ornate and varied construction. One early silver dagger was recovered with midrib design. The 1924 opening of the [[Tutankhamun's mummy|tomb of Tutankhamun]] revealed two daggers, one with a gold blade, and one of smelted iron. It is held that mummies of the Eleventh Dynasty were buried with bronze sabres; and there is a bronze dagger of Thut-mes III. (Eighteenth Dynasty), circa B.C. 1600. As late as Mene-ptah II. of the Nineteenth Dynasty (B.C 1300), we read it in the list of his loot, after the Prosopis battle, of bronze armour, swords and daggers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Burton|first1=Richard F.|title=The Book of the Sword|url=https://archive.org/details/booksword00unkngoog|date=1884|publisher=London Chatto &amp; Windus|location=Piccadilly|page=80}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Ancient iron production|Iron production]] did not begin until 1200 BC, and iron ore was not found in Egypt, making the iron dagger rare, and the context suggests that the iron dagger was valued on a level equal to that of its ceremonial gold counterpart.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title =Tutankhamun's armies: battle and conquest during ancient Egypt's late eighteenth dynasty|author =Jay Cassell|editor=Peter J. Fiduccia|publisher =John Wiley and Sons|year=2007|page=77 |isbn =978-0-471-74358-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; These facts, and the composition of the dagger had long suggested a meteoritic origin,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url =http://www.incose-cc.org/king-tutankhamuns-dagger/
 | title =King Tutankhamun's Dagger
 | last =Anderson
 | first =George
 | date =1 March 2010
 | website =
 | publisher = INCOSE Chesapeake Chapter
 | access-date =5 June 2016
 | quote =History is replete with eyewitness accounts of meteors falling from the sky and impacting the earth.  Further, there is a continuous record of metal being recovered from the meteoric remnants and frequently being described or labeled as meteoric iron. }}&lt;/ref&gt; however, [[Tutankhamun's iron dagger blade|evidence for its meteoritic origin]] was not entirely conclusive until June 2016 when researchers using [[x-ray fluorescence]] spectrometry confirmed similar proportions of metals (Iron, 10% nickel, and 0.6% cobalt) in a meteorite discovered in the area, deposited by an ancient [[meteor shower]].&lt;ref name=june16&gt;
{{cite journal
 | title =The meteoritic origin of Tutankhamun's iron dagger blade
 | journal =Meteoritics &amp; Planetary Science
 | volume =51
 | issue =7
 | pages =1301–1309
 | publisher = Wiley Online
 | doi =10.1111/maps.12664| year =2016
 | last1 =Comelli
 | first1 =Daniela
 | last2 =d'Orazio
 | first2 =Massimo
 | last3 =Folco
 | first3 =Luigi
 | bibcode =2016M&amp;PS...51.1301C|display-authors=etal}}&quot;Early View (Online Version of Record published before inclusion in a printed issue)&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news
 | last =Panko
 | first =Ben
 | title =King Tut's dagger made from an ancient meteorite
 | newspaper =[[Science (journal)|Science]]
 | publisher =[[American Association for the Advancement of Science]]
 | date =2 June 2016
 | url =http://www.sciencemag.org/news/sifter/king-tut-s-dagger-made-ancient-meteorite
 | access-date =5 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

One of the earliest objects made of smelted iron is a dagger dating to before 2000 BC, found in a context that suggests it was treated as an ornamental object of great value.  Found in a Hattic royal tomb dated about 2500 BC, at Alaca Höyük in northern Anatolia, the dagger has a smelted iron blade and a gold handle.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title =Out of the fiery furnace: the impact of metals on the history of mankind |author =Robert Raymond |publisher =Penn State Press |year =1986 |page =[https://archive.org/details/outoffieryfurnac0000raym/page/61 61] |isbn =978-0-271-00441-9 |url =https://archive.org/details/outoffieryfurnac0000raym/page/61 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Antiquity===
The artisans and blacksmiths of [[Iberia]] in what is now southern Spain and southwestern France produced various iron daggers and swords of high quality from the 5th to the 3rd century BC, in ornamentation and patterns influenced by Greek, Punic (Carthaginian), and Phoenician culture.&lt;ref name=&quot;WIS&quot;&gt;Wise, Terence, ''Armies of the Carthaginian Wars, 265–146 BC'', London: Osprey Publishing Ltd., {{ISBN|0-85045-430-1}}, {{ISBN|978-0-85045-430-7}} (1982), pp. 20–21&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Keay, Simon (Prof.), ''[http://www.swanhellenic.com/library/phoenicians-carthaginians-and-romans-in-southern-iberia-13715.html Phoenicians, Carthaginians and Romans in Southern Iberia] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110907090040/http://www.swanhellenic.com/library/phoenicians-carthaginians-and-romans-in-southern-iberia-13715.html |date=2011-09-07 }}'', Swan Hellenic's Online Library &amp; Archive, 30 June 2011, retrieved 2 August 2011&lt;/ref&gt;  The exceptional purity of [[Iberians|Iberian]] iron and the sophisticated method of forging, which included cold hammering, produced double-edged weapons of excellent quality.&lt;ref name=&quot;WIS&quot;/&gt;  One can find technologically advanced designs such as folding knives rusted among the artifacts of many Second Iberian Iron Age cremation burials or in [[Roman Empire]] excavations all around Spain and the Mediterranean.&lt;ref&gt;De Fontcuberta, Eduardo A., ''Bandolero Blades'', Tactical-Life.com, Tactical Knives (September 2010), retrieved 13 August 2011&lt;/ref&gt;  Iberian infantrymen carried several types of iron daggers, most of them based on shortened versions of double-edged swords, but the true Iberian dagger had a triangular-shaped blade.  Iberian daggers and swords were later adopted by Hannibal and his Carthaginian armies.&lt;ref name=&quot;WIS&quot;/&gt;  The [[Lusitanians|Lusitanii]], a pre-Celtic people dominating the lands west of Iberia (most of modern [[Portugal]] and [[Extremadura]]) successfully held off the Roman Empire for many years with a variety of innovative tactics and light weapons, including iron-bladed short [[spear]]s and daggers modeled after Iberian patterns.

During the Roman Empire, legionaries were issued a ''[[pugio]]'' (from the Latin ''pugnō'', or “fight”), a double-edged iron thrusting dagger with a blade of 7–12 inches.  The design and fabrication of the ''pugio'' was taken directly from Iberian daggers and short swords; the Romans even adopted the triangular-bladed Iberian dagger, which they called the ''parazonium''.&lt;ref name=&quot;WIS&quot;/&gt;  Like the ''[[gladius]]'', the ''pugio'' was most often used as a thrusting (stabbing weapon).  As an extreme close-quarter combat weapon, the ''pugio'' was the Roman soldier's last line of defense.  When not in battle, the ''pugio'' served as a convenient utility knife.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title =A concise dictionary of Greek and Roman antiquities  |url =https://archive.org/details/aconcisediction00corngoog  |author =Sir William Smith |publisher =Murray|year=1898|page=66 |editor=Francis Warre Cornish }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Middle Ages===
{{further|Misericorde (weapon)|Rondel dagger|Bollock dagger|Baselard}}
The term ''[[:wikt:dagger|dagger]]'' appears only in the [[Late Middle Ages]], reflecting the fact that while the dagger had been known in antiquity, it had disappeared during the Early Middle Ages, replaced by the hewing knife or [[seax]].&lt;ref&gt;Underwood, Richard (1999) ''Anglo-Saxon Weapons and Warfare'' Stroud, England: Tempus, {{ISBN|0-7524-1910-2}} p70.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Gale, David (1989) ''The Seax'' in ''Weapons and Warfare in Anglo-Saxon England'' Oxford, England: Oxbow {{ISBN|0-947816-21-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:De Fechtbuch Talhoffer 169.jpg|thumb|right|Depiction of combat with the dagger (''degen'') in [[Hans Talhoffer]] (1467)]]
The dagger reappeared in the 12th century as the &quot;knightly dagger&quot;, or more properly cross-hilt or quillon dagger,&lt;ref&gt;Capwell, p. 28 and Thompson, p. 25. Note that the term “quillon” is a modern invention, though it is commonly used&lt;/ref&gt; and was developed into a common arm and tool for civilian use by the late medieval period.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title =Knight |author =Christopher Gravett  |publisher =Penguin|year=2007|page=17|isbn = 978-0-7566-6762-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:ReproMedievalDaggers.JPG|thumb|Modern reproductions of medieval daggers. From left to right: [[Ballock dagger]], [[Rondel dagger]], and a [[Quillon]] dagger]]
The earliest known depiction of a cross-hilt dagger is the so-called &quot;Guido relief&quot; inside the [[Grossmünster]] of [[Zürich]] (c. 1120).&lt;ref&gt;Daniel Gutscher, ''Das Grossmünster in Zürich'' (1983), 120–121, 214–215.&lt;/ref&gt;  A number of depictions of the fully developed cross-hilt dagger are found in the [[Morgan Bible]] (c. 1240).
Many of these cross-hilt daggers resemble miniature swords, with cross guards and pommels very similar in form to swords of the period.&lt;ref&gt;See Thompson, p. 10 and Peterson, plate 25, for good examples of this type in the Museum of London&lt;/ref&gt; Others, however, are not an exact match to known sword designs, having for example pommel caps, large hollow star shaped pommels on so-called “Burgundian Heraldic daggers” or antenna style cross and pommel, reminiscent of Hallstatt era daggers.&lt;ref&gt;See Capwell pp. 28, 122-123, Thompson pp. 24-25, and Peterson plates 26-29&lt;/ref&gt;
The cross-hilt type persisted well into the Renaissance &lt;ref&gt;Peterson plate 46 and Dean p.96, No. 100&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Old French]] term ''[[:wikt:dague|dague]]'' appears to have referred to these weapons in the 13th century, alongside other terms such as ''poignal'' and ''[[basilard]]''. The [[Late Middle English|Middle English]] ''dagger'' is used from the 1380s.

During this time, the dagger was often employed in the role of a [[companion weapon|secondary defense weapon]] in [[close combat]].  The knightly dagger evolved into the larger [[baselard]] knife in the 14th century. During the 14th century, it became fairly common for knights to fight on foot to strengthen the infantry defensive line. This necessitated greater dagger usage. At Agincourt (1415) archers used them to dispatch dismounted knights by thrusting the narrow blades through helmet vents and other apertures.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Thompson|first1=Logan|title=Daggers and Bayonets|date=1999|publisher=Spellmount ltd.|location=United Kingdom|page=24}}&lt;/ref&gt; The baselard was considered an intermediate between a short sword and a long dagger, and became popular also as a civilian weapon.  [[Sloane MS]]. 2593 (c. 1400) records a song satirizing the use of oversized baselard knives as fashion accessories.&lt;ref&gt;''prenegarde prenegarde, thus bere I myn baselard'' [https://books.google.com/books?id=s9iobZUO8nUC&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false ed. Pickering 1836].&lt;/ref&gt;

In the Late Middle Ages, knives with blade designs that emphasized thrusting attacks, such as the [[stiletto]], became increasingly popular, and some thrusting knives commonly referred to as 'daggers' ceased to have a cutting edge.  This was a response to the deployment of heavy armor, such as [[maille]] and [[plate armour]], where cutting attacks were ineffective and focus was on thrusts with narrow blades to punch through mail or aim at armour plate intersections (or the eye slits of the helmet visor).  These late medieval thrusting weapons are sometimes classed by the shape of their hilt as either [[roundel dagger|roundel]], [[bollock dagger|bollock]] or [[Ear dagger|ear]] daggers.
The term ''dagger'' is coined in this time, as are the [[Early Modern German]] equivalents ''[[:wikt:Dolch|dolch]]'' (''tolch'') and ''[[:wikt:Degen#Etymology 2|degen]]'' (''tegen'').
In the [[German school of fencing]], [[Johannes Liechtenauer]] ([[3227a|Ms. 3227a]]) and his successors (specifically Andres Lignizer in [[Cod. 44 A 8]]) taught fighting with the dagger.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title =Schools and Masters of Fencing: From the Middle Ages to the Eighteenth Century |author =Egerton Castle|publisher =Courier Dover Publications|year=2003|page=246|isbn = 978-0-486-42826-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

These techniques in some respects resemble modern [[knife fighting]], but emphasized thrusting strokes almost exclusively, instead of slashes and cuts.  When used offensively, a standard attack frequently employed the reverse or [[icepick grip]], stabbing downward with the blade to increase thrust and penetrative force.  This was done primarily because the blade point frequently had to penetrate or push apart an opponent's steel [[chain mail]] or [[plate armor]] in order to inflict an injury.  The disadvantage of employing the medieval dagger in this manner was that it could easily be blocked by a variety of techniques, most notably by a block with the weaponless arm while simultaneously attacking with a weapon held in the right hand.  Another disadvantage was the reduction in effective blade reach to the opponent when using a reverse grip.  As the wearing of armor fell out of favor, dagger fighting techniques began to evolve which emphasized the use of the dagger with a conventional or forward grip, while the reverse or icepick grip was retained when attacking an unsuspecting opponent from behind, such as in an assassination.

===Renaissance and Early Modern era===
{{further|Stiletto|Parrying dagger|Dirk}}
[[File:Dagger horse head Louvre OA7892 full.jpg|thumb|upright=.5|[[Mughal Empire|Mughal]] dagger, [[Louvre]].]]
[[File:Dagger with Zoomorphic Hilt MET DP253146.jpg|thumb|left|''Dagger with Zoomorphic Hilt'', ca. 16th century, [https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Dagger_with_Zoomorphic_Hilt_MET_DP253146.jpg Metropolitan Museum of Art]]]

The dagger was very popular as a fencing and personal defense weapon in 17th- and 18th-century Spain, where it was referred to as the ''daga'' or ''puñal''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title =Blade's Guide to Knives &amp; Their Values  |author =Steve Shackleford|publisher =Krause Publications|year=2010|page=246|isbn = 978-1-4402-0387-9 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  During the Renaissance Age the dagger was used as part of everyday dress, and daggers were the only weapon commoners were allowed to carry on their person.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Medieval and Renaissance Dagger Combat|author= Jason Vail |publisher= Paladin Press|year= 2006 |page=16|isbn = 978-1-58160-517-4 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
In English, the terms ''poniard'' and  ''dirk'' are loaned during the late 16th to early 17th century, the latter in the spelling ''dork, durk'' (presumably via Low German, Dutch or Scandinavian ''dolk, dolch'', ultimately from a West Slavic ''tulich''), the modern spelling ''dirk'' dating to 18th-century [[Scots language|Scots]].

Beginning with the 17th century, another form of dagger—the [[plug bayonet]] and later the socket [[bayonet]]—was used to convert [[musket]]s and other [[long gun|longarms]] into [[spear]]s by mounting them on the barrel. They were periodically used for eating; the arm was also used for a variety of other tasks such as mending boots, house repairs and farm jobs. The final function of the dagger was as an obvious and ostentatious means of enhancing a man's personal apparel, conforming to fashion which dictated that all men carried them.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Thompson|first1=Logan|title=Daggers and Bayonets|date=1999|publisher=Spellmount ltd.|location=United Kingdom|page=22,23,24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Modern (1815 to 21st century)===
{{main|Combat knife}}
[[File:Ek knives.JPG|thumb|left|20th-century daggers]]

WW1 trench warfare caused daggers and fighting knives to come back in play. They also replaced the sabres worn by officers, which were too long and clumsy for trench warfare. They were worn with pride as a sign of having served front line duty.

Daggers achieved public notoriety in the 20th century as ornamental uniform regalia during the Fascist dictatorships of Mussolini's Italy and Hitler's Germany. Dress daggers were used by several other countries as well, including Japan, but never to the same extent. As combat equipment they were carried by many infantry and [[commando]] forces during the [[World War II|Second World War]].  British Commando and other elite units were issued an especially slender dagger, the [[Fairbairn-Sykes fighting knife]], developed by [[William E. Fairbairn]] and [[Eric A. Sykes]] from real-life close-combat experiences gained while serving on the Shanghai Municipal Police Force.&lt;ref name=&quot;cas&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Chambers, John W., ''OSS Training in the National Parks and Service Abroad in World War II,'' Washington, D.C., U.S. National Park Service (2008), p. 191: Fairbairn reportedly engaged in hundreds of street fights in his twenty-year career in Shanghai, where he organized and headed a special anti-riot squad. Much of his body – arms, legs, torso, and even the palms of his hands was covered with scars from knife wounds from those fights.&lt;/ref&gt; The F-S dagger proved very popular with the commandos, who used it primarily for sentry elimination. Some units of the [[Marine Raiders|U.S. Marine Corps Raiders]] in the Pacific were issued a similar fighting dagger, the [[United States Marine Raider Stiletto|Marine Raider Stiletto]],&lt;ref&gt;Walker, Greg, ''Battle Blades: A Professional's Guide to Combat/Fighting Knives'', Boulder, Colo.: Paladin Press, {{ISBN|0-87364-732-7}} (1993), p. 77&lt;/ref&gt; though this modified design proved less than successful when used in the type of knife combat encountered in the Pacific theater&lt;ref&gt;Alexander, Joseph H., ''Edson's Raiders: The 1st Marine Raider Battalion in World War II'', Annapolis MD: Naval Institute Press, {{ISBN|1-55750-020-7}} (2001), p. 67&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Sledge, E.B., ''With The Old Breed: At Peleleiu and Okinawa'', Presidio Press, {{ISBN|978-0-89141-919-8}} (2007), pp. 21–22&lt;/ref&gt; due to this version using inferior materials and manufacturing techniques.&lt;ref&gt;McCarthy, John (2008). &quot;WWII Marine Raider Stiletto Reborn&quot;. Raider Patch (U.S. Marine Raider Association).&lt;/ref&gt;

During the Vietnam War, the [[Gerber Mark II]], designed by US Army Captain Bud Holzman and Al Mar, was a popular fighting knife pattern that was privately purchased by many U.S. soldiers and marines who served in that war.

Aside from military forces, most daggers are no longer carried openly, but concealed in clothing. One of the more popular forms of the concealable dagger is the ''[[boot knife]]''.  The boot knife is nothing more than a shortened dagger that is compact enough to be worn on the lower leg, usually by means of a sheath clipped or strapped to a boot or other footwear.&lt;ref name=des&gt;{{cite journal | last = Steele| first = David|  title = Boot Knife Fighting| journal = Black Belt| volume = 26| issue = 4| pages =48–51 | publisher = Active Interest Media, Inc.| year = 1988 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{-}}

==Cultural symbolism==
[[File:U.S. Army Special Operations Command CSIB.svg|thumb|upright=.5|right|U.S. Army emblem with dagger]]

The dagger is symbolically ambiguous. Daggers are commonly used as part of the insignias of elite military units or special forces, such as the US Army Airborne Special Operations unit or the Commando Dagger patch for those who have completed the British [[All Arms Commando Course]]. Daggers may be associated with deception, stealth, and/or treachery due to the ease of concealment and surprise that someone could inflict with one on an unsuspecting victim, and indeed many [[assassinations]] have been carried out with the use of a dagger, including that of [[Julius Caesar]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title =The History That Was Never Spoken  |author =David Gray |publisher =Lulu|year=2006|page=87|isbn = 978-1-4116-1703-2 }}&lt;/ref&gt;   A [[cloak and dagger]] attack is one in which a deceitful, traitorous, or concealed enemy attacks a person.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book  | last1 = Dickens | first1 = Charles | title = Barnaby Rudge: A Tale of the Riots of 'Eighty | year = 1841 | publisher = Chapman &amp; Hall | location = London | isbn = 0-14-043728-2 | pages = 203}}&lt;/ref&gt;  On the other hand, for some cultures and military organizations the dagger symbolizes courage and daring in combat.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title =The illustrated encyclopedia of military insignia of the 20th century: a comprehensive A-Z guide to the badges, patches, and embellishments of the world's armed forces |author =Guido Rosignoli  |publisher =Stanley Paul|year=1987|page=44 |isbn = 978-0-09-172670-6 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Reputation==
Dagger reputation was tainted by its periodic use, or alleged employment, in the commission of disreputable, secretive and unsavoury deeds. Perhaps these are exaggerated; however, it became associated with assassinations performed when the concealed weapon was suddenly flourished and used to kill. Consequently, it developed connotations with murky, cowardly assaults in dark alleys, upon shadowy staircases, and of hired murderers emerging from concealment to stab innocent, sleeping victims.&lt;ref name=&quot;Daggers and Bayonets&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Thompson|first1=Logan|title=Daggers and Bayonets|date=1999|publisher=Spellmount ltd.|location=United Kingdom|page=54}}&lt;/ref&gt;

To a degree, some antipathy towards the dagger has remained unchanged up to modern times. This is perhaps, partly due to the periodic, contemporary broadcasting of bloodthirsty films and television series depicting gangsters employing the stiletto daggers. History is punctuated with accounts of daggers being used in assassinations and coup d'état attempts. On March 15, 44BC, [[Julius Caesar|Gaius Julius Caesar]] was assassinated by a large group of conspirators who stabbed him repeatedly with their daggers. This took place in Rome in a room behind the [[Theatre of Pompey]] which was being used for government business whilst the Senate was being rebuilt.

To some degree, the dagger regained a little social prestige during the rapier age when personal combat became less brutal. Its involvement in this formalized, regulated martial endeavor did something to restore its reputation. When its advantages and purpose eventually declined and weapon carrying ceased, the dagger was saved from obsolescence by its retention as a field sports gadget. In the nineteenth century the custom of wearing a general purpose knife practically ceased and the hunting knife became a specialized instrument. However, its combat and military traditions were incorporated in the bayonet weapon which has continued in use until the present day.&lt;ref name=&quot;Daggers and Bayonets&quot;/&gt;

==Art knives==
[[File:Art Knives by Buster Warenski.jpg|thumb|left|[[Buster Warenski]] dagger]]
Daggers are a popular form of what is known as the &quot;art knife&quot;, due in part to the symmetry of the blade.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title= Images of Steel|first= Ethen |last=Edwards|journal= Blade Magazine|pages=40–43|year= 1990|issue=4|volume=27 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  One of the most famous examples is knifemaker [[Buster Warenski]]'s replication of the gold dagger found in [[Tutankhamun]]'s tomb.  Warenski's dagger was made with a cast gold blade and the knife contained 32 ounces of pure gold in its construction.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Winter|first=Butch|title=The Art of the Knife|journal = Popular Mechanics|year= 1989|pages=86–88|volume=166|issue= 3|publisher= Hearst Magazines|url= https://books.google.com/books?id=AeQDAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA86&amp;dq=gil+hibben#v=onepage&amp;q=gil%20hibben&amp;f=false|accessdate=2011-03-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;  One of the knives required of an [[American Bladesmith Society]] Mastersmith is the construction of an &quot;art knife&quot; or a &quot;European style&quot; dagger.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=ABS Testing Rules and Guidelines for the Master Smith Rating|url=http://www.americanbladesmith.com/uploads/file/Testing/MS%20Test%20FINAL%204-24-2010.pdf|accessdate=2011-03-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Difference between knife and dagger|url=https://finalscope.com/difference-between-knife-and-dagger/|accessdate=2019-05-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{-}}

==See also==
{{columns-list|colwidth=15em|
*[[Blade]]
*[[Dagger (typography)]]
*[[Fighting knife]]
*[[Dirk]]
*[[Knife]]
*[[Knife fight]]
*[[List of daggers]]
*[[Tantō]]
*[[Sword]]
}}

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==References==
* [[Tobias Capwell|Capwell, Dr. Tobias]]. ''The World Encyclopedia of Knives, Daggers, and Bayonets''. Hermes House. Leicestershire. 2011..
* Dean, Bashford. ''Catalogue of European Daggers 1300–1800''. Metropolitan Museum of Art. New York. 1929.
* Edge, David and Paddock, John Miles. ''Arms &amp; Armor of the Medieval Knight - An Illustrated History of Weapons in the Middle Ages''. Crescent Books. New York. 1988.
* Iorwerth Eiddon Stephen Edwards, Cyril John Gadd, Nicholas Geoffrey Lemprière Hammond. ''The Cambridge Ancient History''. Cambridge University Press. 1970. ({{ISBN|0-521-07051-1}})
* Peterson, Harold L. ''Daggers &amp; Fighting Knives of the Western World''. Bonanza Books. New York. 1970.
* Thompson, Logan. ''Daggers and Bayonets - A History''. Paladin Press. Boulder. 1999.
* Vail, Jason. ''Medieval and Renaissance Dagger Combat''. Paladin Press. Boulder. 2006.

== External links ==
{{commons category|Daggers}}

{{Knives}}

{{Authority control}}
* [http://www.iluvknives.com Dagger knife examples]
* [http://www.iluvknives.com Difference between knife and dagger]

[[Category:Daggers| ]]
[[Category:Egyptian inventions]]
[[Category:Blade weapons]]</text>
      <sha1>buwzdrsf158tz1toer03d6ocggforyj</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
