  <page>
    <title>Don McLean</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8987</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943132688</id>
      <parentid>943130538</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-29T01:32:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>AnomieBOT</username>
        <id>7611264</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Dating maintenance tags: {{Cn}}</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Other people}}
{{short description|American singer-songwriter}}

{{Use mdy dates|date=February 2020}}
{{Infobox musical artist
| image            = Don_McLean_in_Gateshead_UK_May_2018.jpg
| caption          = McLean at the [[The Sage, Gateshead]] in May 2018
| name             = Don McLean
| background       = solo_singer
| birth_name       = Donald McLean III
| birth_date       = {{Birth date and age|1945|10|2}}
| birth_place      = [[New Rochelle, New York]], U.S.
| instrument       = {{flatlist|
* Vocals
* guitar
}}
| genre            = {{flatlist|
* [[Folk music|Folk]]
* [[rock music|rock]]
* [[folk rock]]
}}
| label            = {{flatlist|
* [[United Artists Records|United Artists]]
* [[EMI America Records|EMI]]
* [[Curb Records|Curb]]
* [[Capitol Records|Capitol]]
}}
| occupation       = Singer-songwriter
| years_active     = 1964–present
| website          = {{url|don-mclean.com}}
| alias            = &quot;American Troubadour&quot;, &quot;King of the Trail&quot;, &quot;The Don&quot;
}}

'''Donald McLean III''' (born October 2, 1945) is an American singer-songwriter, best known for his 1971 hit song &quot;[[American Pie (song)|American Pie]]&quot;, an 8.5-minute folk rock &quot;cultural touchstone&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Smash Hits: The 100 Songs That Defined America|last=Perone|first=James E.|publisher=ABC-CLIO|year=2016|isbn=9781440834691|pages=230}}&lt;/ref&gt; about the loss of innocence of the early rock and roll generation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://understandingamericanpie.com/|title=Understanding American Pie – Interpretation of Don Mclean's epic anthem to the passing of an era.|work=UnderstandingAmericanPie.com |accessdate=March 30, 2017|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20030906142212/https://www.understandingamericanpie.com/|archivedate=September 6, 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt;

His other hit singles include &quot;[[Vincent (Don McLean song)|Vincent]]&quot;, &quot;Dreidel&quot;, a rendition of [[Roy Orbison]]'s &quot;[[Crying (Roy Orbison song)#Don McLean version|Crying]]&quot;, a rendition of [[the Skyliners]]' &quot;[[Since I Don't Have You]]&quot;, and &quot;[[Wonderful Baby]]&quot;.

His composition &quot;[[And I Love You So (song)|And I Love You So]]&quot; has been sung by [[Elvis Presley]], [[Perry Como]], [[Helen Reddy]], [[Glen Campbell]], and others, and in 2000, [[Madonna (entertainer)|Madonna]] had a hit with a rendition of &quot;American Pie&quot;.

In 2004, he was inducted into the [[Songwriters Hall of Fame]]. In January 2018, BMI certified that &quot;American Pie&quot; and &quot;Vincent&quot; had reached five million and three million airplays respectively.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://musicmattersmagazine.com/2018/01/24/don-mclean-becomes-a-bmi-multi-million-air/|title=Don McLean becomes a BMI multi million-air!|last=musicmattersmagazine|date=January 24, 2018|accessdate=January 17, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Musical roots==
McLean's grandfather and father, both also named Donald McLean, had roots originating in [[Scotland]]. McLean's mother, Elizabeth Bucci, originated from Abruzzo in central [[Italy]]. He has other extended family in Los Angeles and Boston.&lt;ref name=bio&gt;{{cite book|title=The Don McLean Story: Killing Us Softly With His Songs|last=Howard|first=Alan|year=2007|publisher=Lulu Press|isbn=978-1-4303-0682-5|page=420}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Though some of his early musical influences included [[Frank Sinatra]] and [[Buddy Holly]],&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|title=Bye-Bye, Mr. 'American Pie': Don McLean Gives His Pen a Rest|last=Arnold|first=Thomas|date=March 23, 1990|work=Los Angeles Times}}&lt;/ref&gt; as a teenager, McLean became interested in [[folk music]], particularly the [[the Weavers|Weavers]]' 1955 recording ''[[The Weavers at Carnegie Hall|At Carnegie Hall]]''. He often missed long periods of school because of childhood [[asthma]], particularly music lessons, and although McLean slipped back in his studies, his love of music was allowed to flourish. By age 16, he had bought his first guitar and began making contacts in the music business, becoming friends with the folk singers [[Erik Darling]] and [[Fred Hellerman]] of the Weavers. Hellerman said, &quot;He called me one day and said, 'I'd like to come and visit you', and that's what he did! We became good friends — he has the most remarkable music memory of anyone I've ever known.&quot;&lt;ref name=bio/&gt;

When McLean was 15, his father died. Fulfilling his father's request, the singer graduated from [[Iona Preparatory School]] in 1963,&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;/&gt; and briefly attended Villanova University, dropping out after four months. After leaving Villanova, McLean became associated with the famed folk music agent [[Harold Leventhal]] for several months before teaming up with his personal manager, Herb Gart, for 18 years. For the next six years, he performed at venues and events including [[The Bitter End]] and the [[the Gaslight Cafe|Gaslight Cafe]] in New York, the [[Newport Folk Festival]], the [[the Cellar Door|Cellar Door]] in Washington, D.C., and the [[Troubadour (West Hollywood, California)|Troubadour]] in Los Angeles.&lt;ref name=bio/&gt; Gart's 18-year tenure as McLean's manager ended acrimoniously in the 1980s. Following Herb Gart's death&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.facebook.com/herbgart/posts/10203946765866796 &quot;Herb Gart Facebook&quot;], Retrieved on January 1, 2019&lt;/ref&gt; in September 2018, Don McLean wrote:

{{Quote|I feel it is important to note that Herb did many good things for me in the beginning but could not deal with my success, as odd as that may sound.
In about 1982 Herb told me his associate Walter Hofer who ran Copyright Service Bureau (a collection business for song publishers) had stolen $90,000
from my account but had &quot;put it back&quot;. This was a cover story and a lie. Furthermore the amount turned out to be more like $200,000 and because Gart was now complicit in this crime I fired him. He sued me&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://thediscography.org/discoDbDetail.php?req=716|title=The Discography|website=thediscography.org|accessdate=January 17, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; but settled for a small amount and was never heard from again.
There is so much of this in my business and artists usually sweep it under the rug but I don’t.
I want people to know the truth about my journey. 

— Don McLean.}}

McLean attended [[night school]] at Iona College and received a bachelor's degree in business administration in 1968.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://don-mclean.com/2013/08/12/about-don-mclean/|title=About Don McLean|date=August 12, 2013|work=Don McLean|accessdate=February 25, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; He turned down a scholarship to Columbia University Graduate School in favor of pursuing a career as a singer-songwriter, performing at such venues as [[Caffè Lena]] in Saratoga Springs, New York and the [[The Main Point|Main Point]] in Bryn Mawr, Pennsylvania.

Later that year, with the help of a grant from the [[New York State Council on the Arts]], McLean began reaching a wider audience, with visits to towns up and down the Hudson River.&lt;ref name=bio/&gt; He learned the art of performing from his friend and mentor [[Pete Seeger]]. McLean accompanied Seeger on his [[Hudson River Sloop Clearwater|Clearwater]] boat trip up the Hudson River in 1969 to raise awareness about environmental pollution in the river. During this time, McLean wrote songs that appeared on his first album ''[[Tapestry (Don McLean album)|Tapestry]]''. McLean co-edited the book ''Songs and Sketches of the First Clearwater Crew'', with sketches by [[Thomas B. Allen (painter)|Thomas B. Allen]], for which Pete Seeger wrote the foreword. Seeger and McLean sang &quot;[[Oh Shenandoah|Shenandoah]]&quot; on the 1974 Clearwater album. McLean still thinks about his experiences of working with Seeger: &quot;Hardly a day goes by when I don’t think of Pete and how generous and supportive he was. If you could understand his politics and you got to know him, he really was some kind of modern day saint”. &lt;ref name=bio /&gt;

==Recording career==

===Early breakthrough===
McLean recorded ''[[Tapestry (Don McLean album)|Tapestry]]'' in 1969 in Berkeley, California during the student riots. After being rejected 72 times by labels, the album was released by [[Mediarts]], a label that had not existed when he first started to look for a label. He worked on the album for a couple of years before putting it out.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.songwriteruniverse.com/don-mclean-interview-2017.htm|title=Special Interview With Don McLean, Renowned Singer/Songwriter Of &quot;American Pie&quot; and Other Classic Songs|date=July 3, 2017|work=Songwriter Universe {{!}} Songwriting News, Articles &amp; Song Contest|accessdate=February 25, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; It attracted good reviews but little notice outside the folk community, though on the Easy Listening chart &quot;[[Castles in the Air (song)|Castles in the Air]]&quot; was a success, and in 1973 &quot;And I Love You So&quot; became a number 1 Adult Contemporary hit for [[Perry Como]].

McLean's major break came when Mediarts was taken over by [[United Artists Records]], thus securing the promotion of a major label for his second album, ''[[American Pie (Don McLean album)|American Pie]].'' The album launched two number one hits in the title song and &quot;[[Vincent (Don McLean song)|Vincent]]&quot;. ''American Pie''&amp;#39;s success made McLean an international star and piqued interest in his first album, which charted more than two years after its initial release.

===&quot;American Pie&quot;===
{{Main|American Pie (song)}}
McLean's [[Masterpiece|magnum opus]] &quot;[[American Pie (song)|American Pie]]&quot; is a sprawling, impressionistic ballad inspired partly by the deaths of [[Buddy Holly]], [[Ritchie Valens]], and J.P. Richardson ([[The Big Bopper]]) in a plane crash in 1959, and developments in American youth culture in the subsequent decade. The song popularized the expression &quot;[[The Day the Music Died]]&quot; in reference to the crash.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Music/DonMcLean?from=Main.DonMcLean|title=Don McLean (Music)|publisher=TV Tropes|accessdate=August 25, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The song was recorded on May 26, 1971, and a month later received its first radio airplay on New York's WNEW-FM and WPLJ-FM to mark the closing of [[Fillmore East]], the famous New York concert hall. &quot;American Pie&quot; reached number one on the [[Billboard Hot 100|''Billboard'' Hot 100]] from January 15 to February 5, 1972, and remains McLean's most successful single release. The single also topped the ''Billboard'' [[Adult Contemporary (chart)|Easy Listening]] chart. With a total running time of 8:36 encompassing both sides of the single, it is also the longest song to reach number 1. Some stations played only part one of the original split-sided single release.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.songfacts.com/detail.php?id=1193|title=American Pie by Don McLean Songfacts|website=Songfacts.com|accessdate=February 25, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[WMVP|WCFL]] DJ Bob Dearborn unraveled the lyrics and first published his interpretation on January 7, 1972, eight days before the song reached number 1 nationally (see &quot;Further reading&quot; under &quot;[[American Pie (song)|American Pie]]&quot;). Numerous other interpretations, which together largely converged on Dearborn's interpretation, quickly followed. McLean declined to say anything definitive about the lyrics until 1978.&lt;ref&gt;However, [[Casey Kasem]] confirmed the main outline of what Dearborn had said and seemed to indicate that McLean agreed with that outline, on the January 15, 1972, edition of ''[[American Top 40]]'', when &quot;American Pie&quot; had just ascended to number 1 on the Hot 100.&lt;/ref&gt; Since then McLean has stated that the lyrics are also somewhat autobiographical and present an abstract story of his life from the mid-1950s until the time he wrote the song in the late 1960s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.don-mclean.com/americanpie.asp|title=Don McLean's American Pie|work=Don McLean Online - The Official Website|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20061222185354/http://www.don-mclean.com/americanpie.asp|archivedate=December 22, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2001, &quot;American Pie&quot; was voted number 5 in a poll of the 365 [[Songs of the Century]] compiled by the [[Recording Industry Association of America]] and the [[National Endowment for the Arts]].

On April 7, 2015, McLean's original working manuscript for &quot;American Pie&quot; sold for $1,205,000 (£809,524/€1,109,182) at Christie's auction rooms, New York, making it the third highest auction price achieved for an American literary manuscript.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.christies.com/salelanding/index.aspx?intSaleID=25290|title=Don McLean's &quot;American Pie&quot;: The Original Lyrics|website=Christies.com|accessdate=August 25, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===&quot;Vincent (Starry Starry Night)&quot;===
{{Main|Vincent_(Don McLean song)}}
&quot;[[Vincent (Don McLean song)|Vincent]]&quot; is a tribute to the 19th-century Dutch painter [[Vincent van Gogh]]. The inspiration came to McLean one morning while looking at a book about Vincent Van Gogh. As he studied a print of Van Gogh's painting ''[[The Starry Night]]'', he realized that a song could be written about the artist through the painting.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://don-mclean.com/2007/04/11/vincent-starry-starry-night/
|title=Don McLean: Official Website|website=Don-mclean.com|date=April 11, 2007|accessdate=January 5, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although it reached only number 12 on the ''Billboard'' Hot 100, it proved to be a huge hit worldwide, including reaching number 1 in the UK Singles Chart. [[Mike Mills]] of REM said &quot;You can't change a note in that song&quot;.&lt;ref name=skydoc/&gt; The song was performed by [[NOFX]] on their album ''45 or 46 Songs That Weren't Good Enough to Go on Our Other Records'' and appears on the [[Fat Wreck Chords]] compilation ''Survival of the Fattest''. &quot;Vincent&quot; was sung by [[Josh Groban]] on his [[Josh Groban (album)|2001 debut album]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.joshgroban.com/node/78|title=Official Website For Josh Groban|website=Joshgroban.com|date=February 24, 2007|accessdate=August 25, 2015|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160303181718/http://www.joshgroban.com/node/78|archivedate=March 3, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2018, singer-songwriter [[Ellie Goulding]] recorded a new, stripped back, acoustic guitar-driven version of the song.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.udiscovermusic.com/news/ellie-goulding-don-mclean-vincent/|title=uDiscovermusic|website=Udiscovermusic.com|date=February 14, 2018|accessdate=January 5, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Subsequent recordings===
[[File:Don McLean 1976.JPG|thumb|McLean in a publicity photo, 1976]]
Personnel from the ''[[American Pie (Don McLean album)|American Pie]]'' album sessions were retained for his third album ''[[Don McLean (album)|Don McLean]]'', including the producer, Ed Freeman, [[Rob Stoner|Rob Rothstein]] on bass, and [[Warren Bernhardt]] on piano. The song &quot;The Pride Parade&quot; provides an insight into McLean's immediate reaction to stardom. McLean told ''Melody Maker'' in 1973 that ''Tapestry'' was an album by someone previously concerned with external situations. ''[[American Pie (Don McLean album)|American Pie]]'' combines externals with internals, and the resultant success of that album makes the third one (''[[Don McLean (album)|Don McLean]]'') entirely introspective.&quot;

Other songs written by McLean for the album include &quot;Dreidel&quot; (number 21 on the Billboard chart) and &quot;If We Try&quot; (number 58), which was recorded by [[Olivia Newton-John]].&lt;ref&gt;''[[The Great Olivia Newton-John]]'', Festival Records, 1999.&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;On the Amazon&quot; from the 1920s musical [[Mr. Cinders]] was an unusual choice but became an audience favorite in concerts and featured in ''Till Tomorrow'', a documentary film about McLean produced by Bob Elfstrom (Elfstrom held the role of Jesus Christ in Johnny and June Cash's ''Gospel Road)''. The film shows McLean in concert at Columbia University as he was interrupted by a bomb scare. He left the stage while the audience stood up and checked under their seats for anything that resembled a bomb. After the all-clear, McLean re-appeared and sang &quot;On the Amazon&quot; from exactly where he had left off. Don Heckman reported the bomb scare in his review for ''[[The New York Times]]'' titled &quot;Don McLean Survives Two Obstacles.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''[[The New York Times]]'', December 12, 1971&lt;/ref&gt;

The fourth album ''[[Playin' Favorites]]'' was a top-40 hit in the UK in 1973 and included the Irish folk classic, &quot;Mountains of Mourne&quot; and Buddy Holly's &quot;[[Everyday (Buddy Holly song)|Everyday]]&quot;, a live rendition of which returned McLean to the UK Singles Chart. McLean said &quot;The last album (''[[Don McLean (album)|Don McLean]]'') was a study in depression whereas the new one (''[[Playin' Favorites]]'') is almost the quintessence of optimism.&quot;

The 1974 album ''[[Homeless Brother]]'', produced by [[Joel Dorn]], was McLean's final studio recording for United Artists. The album featured fine New York session musicians, including Ralph McDonald on percussion, [[Hugh McCracken]] on guitar and a guest appearance by [[Yusef Lateef]] on flute. The [[The Persuasions|Persuasions]] sang the background vocals on &quot;Crying in the Chapel&quot;, and [[Cissy Houston]] provided a backing vocal on &quot;La La Love You&quot;. The album's title song was inspired by [[Jack Kerouac]]'s book ''[[Lonesome Traveler]]'', in which Kerouac tells the story of America's &quot;homeless brothers&quot; or hobos. The song features background vocals by [[Pete Seeger]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.allmusic.com/album/homeless-brother-mw0000046874|title=Homeless Brother: Don McLean {{!}} Songs, Reviews, Credits {{!}} AllMusic|website=AllMusic|accessdate=February 25, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The song &quot;The Legend of Andrew McCrew&quot; was based on an article published in ''The New York Times''&lt;ref name=bio/&gt; concerning a black Dallas hobo named Anderson McCrew who was killed when he leapt from a moving train. No one claimed him, so a carnival took his body, mummified it, and toured all over the South with him, calling him &quot;The Famous Mummy Man.&quot; McLean's song inspired radio station WGN in Chicago to tell the story and give the song airplay in order to raise money for a headstone for McCrew's grave. Their campaign was successful, and McCrew's body was exhumed and buried in the Lincoln Cemetery in Dallas.&lt;ref&gt;''Ellensburg Daily Record'', May 24, 1974.&lt;/ref&gt; The tombstone had an inscription with words from the fourth verse of McLean's song:

&lt;blockquote&gt;What a way to live a life, and what a way to die&lt;br/&gt;
Left to live a living death with no one left to cry&lt;br/&gt;
A petrified amazement, a wonder beyond worth&lt;br/&gt;
A man who found more life in death than life gave him at birth&lt;/blockquote&gt;

[[Joel Dorn]] later collaborated on the McLean career retrospective ''[[Rearview Mirror: An American Musical Journey|Rearview Mirror]]'', released in 2005 on Dorn's label, Hyena Records. In 2006, Dorn reflected on working with McLean:&lt;ref name=bio/&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;Of the more than 200 studio albums I've produced in the past 40 plus years, there is a handful; maybe 15 or so that I can actually listen to from top to bottom. ''[[Homeless Brother]]'' is one of them. It accomplished everything I set out to do. And it did so because it was a true collaboration. Don brought so much to the project that all I really had to do was capture what he did, and complement it properly when necessary.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In 1977 a brief liaison with [[Arista Records]] that yielded the album ''[[Prime Time (Don McLean album)|Prime Time]]'', and in October 1978, the single &quot;It Doesn't Matter Anymore&quot;. This was a track from the album ''[[Chain Lightning (album)|Chain Lightning]]'' that should have been the second of four with Arista.&lt;ref name=bio/&gt; McLean had started recording in Nashville, Tennessee, with [[Elvis Presley]]'s backing singers, the [[The Jordanaires|Jordanaires]], and many of Presley's musicians. However the Arista deal broke down following artistic disagreements between McLean and the Arista chief, [[Clive Davis]]. Consequently, McLean was left without a record contract in the United States, but through continuing deals, ''[[Chain Lightning (album)|Chain Lightning]]'' was released by EMI in Europe and by Festival Records in Australia.

In April 1980, the Roy Orbison song &quot;[[Crying (Roy Orbison song)|Crying]]&quot; from the album began picking up airplay on Dutch radio stations and McLean was called to Europe to appear on several important musical variety shows to plug the song and support its release as a single by EMI. The song achieved number 1 status in the Netherlands first, followed by the UK and then Australia.

McLean's number 1 successes in Europe and Australia led to a new deal in the United States with Millennium Records, which issued ''[[Chain Lightning (album)|Chain Lightning]]'' two and a half years after it had been recorded in Nashville and two years after its release in Europe. It charted on February 14, 1981, and reached number 28, and &quot;Crying&quot; climbed to number 5 on the pop singles chart. Orbison himself thought that McLean's version was the best interpretation he'd ever heard of one of his songs. Orbison thought McLean did a better job than he did and even went so far as to say that the voice of Don McLean is one of the great instruments of 20th-century America.&lt;ref name=skydoc&gt;{{cite AV media|title=Don McLean: An American Troubadour|medium=Television production|publisher=Sky Arts 1|location=UK|year=2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to Brian Wilson of the Beach Boys, &quot;McLean's voice could cut through steel - he is a very pure singer and he's up there with the best of them. He's a very talented singer and songwriter and he deserves his success.&quot;&lt;ref name=skydoc/&gt;

McLean had further chart successes in the United States in the early 1980s with &quot;[[Since I Don't Have You]]&quot;, a new recording of &quot;Castles in the Air&quot; and &quot;It's Just the Sun&quot;. In 1987, the release of the country-based album'' [[Love Tracks (Don McLean album)|Love Tracks]]'' gave rise to the hit singles &quot;Love in My Heart&quot; (a top-10 in Australia), &quot;[[You Can't Blame the Train]]&quot; (U.S. country number 49), and &quot;Eventually&quot;. The latter two songs were written by [[Terri Sharp]]. In 1991, [[EMI]] reissued &quot;[[American Pie (song)|American Pie]]&quot; as a single in the United Kingdom, and McLean performed on ''[[Top of the Pops]]''. In 1992, previously unreleased songs became available on ''[[Favorites and Rarities]]'', and ''Don McLean Classics'' featured new studio recordings of &quot;[[Vincent (Don McLean song)|Vincent]]&quot; and &quot;[[American Pie (song)|American Pie]]&quot;.

McLean has continued to record new material, including ''River of Love'' in 1995 on [[Curb Records]], and more recently, the albums ''You've Got to Share'', ''Don McLean Sings Marty Robbins'' and ''The Western Album'' for his own Don McLean Music label. ''Addicted to Black'' was released in May 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.don-mclean.com/?p=320 |title=Don McLean Online |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20121123224947/http://www.don-mclean.com/?p=320|archivedate=November 23, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Other songs===
McLean's other well-known songs include the following.
*&quot;[[And I Love You So (song)|And I Love You So]]&quot; featured on McLean's first album ''[[Tapestry (Don McLean album)|Tapestry]]'' first released in 1970.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.discogs.com/Don-McLean-Tapestry/master/84638|title=Don McLean - Tapestry|website=Discogs.com|accessdate=October 7, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; The song was later recorded by [[Elvis Presley]], [[Helen Reddy]], [[Shirley Bassey]], [[Glen Campbell]], [[Engelbert Humperdinck (singer)|Engelbert Humperdinck]], [[Howard Keel]], [[Claude François]], and a [[1973 in music|1973 hit]] for [[Perry Como]]. The song was performed at the Royal Wedding reception of [[Prince Harry]] and [[Meghan Markle]] in 2018.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.express.co.uk/news/royal/962039/Royal-Wedding-2018-Prince-Harry-Meghan-Markle-royal-fans-sing-funny-song|title=WATCH: Passionate royal fans SING funny song they created for Harry and Meghan|first=Thomas|last=Hunt|date=May 19, 2018|website=Express.co.uk|accessdate=January 17, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*&quot;[[Castles in the Air (song)|Castles in the Air]]&quot;, which McLean recorded twice. His 1981 re-recording was a top-40 hit, reaching number 36 on the ''Billboard'' Hot 100 in late 1981.&lt;ref name=&quot;Whitburn&quot;&gt;[[Joel Whitburn|Whitburn, Joel]] (2004). ''The Billboard Book of Top 40 Hits'', 8th edition. (Billboard Publications). p. 416.&lt;/ref&gt;
*&quot;[[Wonderful Baby]]&quot;, a tribute to [[Fred Astaire]] that Astaire himself recorded. Primarily rejected by pop stations, it reached number 1 on the ''Billboard'' Easy Listening chart.&lt;ref&gt;Hyatt, Wesley (1999). ''The Billboard Book of #1 Adult Contemporary Hits''. Billboard Publications. p. 166&lt;/ref&gt;
*&quot;Superman's Ghost&quot;, a tribute to [[George Reeves]], who portrayed Superman on television in the 1950s.
*&quot;The Grave&quot;, a song that McLean had written about the Vietnam War, was recorded by [[George Michael]] in 2003 in protest against the Iraq War.

The ''American Pie'' album features a version of [[Psalm 137]], titled &quot;Babylon&quot;. The song is based on a canon by [[Philip Hayes (composer)|Philip Hayes]]&lt;ref&gt;Hayes, Philip. ''The Muses Delight: Catches, Glees, Canzonets and Canons''. London, 1786.&lt;/ref&gt; and was arranged by McLean and [[Lee Hays]] (of The Weavers).&lt;ref&gt;''American Pie'' album song credits&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;Babylon&quot; was performed in the ''[[Mad Men]]'' [[Babylon (Mad Men episode)|episode of the same name]] despite the fact that the song would not be released until 10 years after the time in which the episode is set.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.slantmagazine.com/house/article/mad-men-fridays-season-1-episode-6-babylon|title=Mad Men Recap: Season 1, Episode 6, &quot;Babylon&quot; |work=Slant Magazine|accessdate=February 25, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1981, McLean had an international number one hit with a version of the Roy Orbison classic &quot;Crying&quot;. It was only after the record became a success overseas that it was released in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.discogs.com/Don-McLean-Crying/release/751196|title=Don McLean - Crying|website=Discogs.com|accessdate=February 25, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; The single hit reached number 5 on the ''Billboard'' Hot 100 in 1981.&lt;ref name=&quot;Whitburn&quot;/&gt; Orbison himself once described McLean as &quot;the voice of the century&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.festivalsearcher.com/artists.aspx?artist_id=Don_McLean|title=Don McLean Live Tour Festivals 2015|website=Festivalsearcher.com|accessdate=August 25, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; and in a subsequent re-recording of the song, Orbison incorporated elements of McLean's version.

For the 1982 animated cult movie ''[[The Flight of Dragons]]'', produced by [[Jules Bass]] and [[Arthur Rankin, Jr.]], McLean sang the opening theme. However, no soundtrack has ever been released. Another hit song associated with McLean (though never recorded by him) is &quot;[[Killing Me Softly with His Song]]&quot;, which was inspired by [[Lori Lieberman]] after she, also a singer-songwriter, saw him singing his composition &quot;Empty Chairs&quot; in concert.&lt;ref name=&quot;Daily News&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=O'Haire |first=Patricia |url=http://www.don-mclean.com/i/kill.jpg |title=A Killer of a Song |newspaper=Daily News |location=New York |date=April 5, 1973 |page=6 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130514165758/http://www.don-mclean.com/i/kill.jpg |archivedate=May 14, 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Afterwards she shared it with her manager [[Norman Gimbel]], who had long been searching for a way to use a phrase he had copied from a novel translated from Spanish, &quot;killing me softly with his blues&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Davis|first1=Sheila|title=The Craft of Lyric Writing|publisher=Writers Digest Books|year=1984|page=13|url=https://books.google.com/?id=uVePZ1Qwtb0C&amp;pg=PA13|accessdate=September 22, 2010|isbn=0-89879-149-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; Gimbel passed the lyrics to his songwriting partner [[Charles Fox (composer)|Charles Fox]] who composed the music to &quot;Killing Me Softly with His Song&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Billboard Magazine 1974. Page 53&quot;&gt;''Billboard'' magazine, June 22, 1974, p. 53.&lt;/ref&gt; Lieberman recorded the song and released it in 1972. This initial version was heard by [[Roberta Flack]] who recorded it with slight changes to create a number one hit. Two decades later it was recorded by [[the Fugees]] who had another hit.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1997/03/02/arts/l-the-true-source-of-killing-me-softly-836680.html|title=The True Source Of 'Killing Me Softly'|date=March 2, 1997|newspaper=[[The New York Times]]|accessdate=February 25, 2018|issn=0362-4331}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Concerts==
[[File:Don McLean at the NYCB Theatre at Westbury 2013-07-13 3.jpg|thumb|McLean at the [[NYCB Theatre at Westbury]] in July 2013]]
McLean's albums did not match the commercial success of ''American Pie'', but he became a major concert attraction in the United States and overseas.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.officialcharts.com/artist/14517/don-mclean/|title=Don McLean {{!}} full Official Chart History {{!}} Official Charts Company|website=Officialcharts.com|accessdate=February 25, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; His repertoire included old concert hall numbers and the catalogues of singers such as Buddy Holly and [[Frank Sinatra]]. The years spent playing gigs in small clubs and coffee houses in the 1960s transformed into well-paced performances. McLean's first concerts at Carnegie Hall in New York and the Albert Hall in London in 1972 were critically acclaimed.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://myweb.tiscali.co.uk/maguire/donarchive/lincoln.html|title=First ever UK Concert Appearances|website=Myweb.tiscali.co.uk|accessdate=February 25, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In recent years, McLean continued to tour the United States, Canada and Europe (2011, 2012) and Australia (2013). In June 2011, McLean appeared at the [[Glastonbury Festival]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/music/festivals/glastonbury/2011/artists/donmclean|title=BBC Glastonbury Festival|publisher=BBC|date=June 26, 2011|accessdate=August 25, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; in [[Pilton, Somerset|Pilton]], UK, and in 2014 at California's [[Stagecoach Festival|Stagecoach Country Music Festival]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dailynews.com/events/20140427/stagecoach-2014-don-mclean-performs-emotional-set-for-fans-celebs-ashton-kutcher-and-mila-kunis|title=Stagecoach 2014: Don McLean Performs Emotional Set for Fans, Celebs Ashton Kutcher and Mila Kunis|website=Dailynews.com|date=April 27, 2014|accessdate=August 25, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During 2018, McLean embarked on a world tour with concerts in North America, UK, Ireland, Belgium, Switzerland, Germany, Israel, Norway and Finland. His concert at the London Palladium was reviewed positively by ''The Times'':&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.thetimes.co.uk/article/pop-review-don-mclean-at-the-london-palladium-w1-5jld5xfdl|title=Pop review: Don McLean at the London Palladium, W1|date=May 11, 2018|accessdate=January 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Quote|“His masterpiece (&quot;American Pie&quot;) remains one of the great achievements of the singer-songwriter era: eight and a half minutes of allegory, reflection and melody documenting the history of rock’n’roll and the death of 1950s innocence. He played it, of course, and brilliantly, getting everyone creaking on to their feet and singing along. Before that came almost two hours of well-worn rock’n’roll and acoustic folk that placed McLean somewhere between a straight-up entertainer and a poetic maverick.”
– Marilynn Kingwell, The Times}}
The ''Jerusalem Post'' noted that &quot;McLean was the consummate professional in presenting his master class of the Great American Songbook&quot; in their review of his Tel Aviv concert, June 2018&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.jpost.com/Israel-News/Culture/McLean-goes-back-to-the-basics-560158|title=McLean Goes Back to the Basics|date=June 17, 2018|accessdate=January 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Later work and honors==

Don McLean's alma mater, [[Iona College (New York)]], conferred an honorary doctorate on him in 2001.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Iona College|url=http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/iona-college-2737|website=Colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com|accessdate=January 12, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; McLean has since been vocal in his criticism of the College: &quot;Iona was, in my day, a college for the average student who wanted to go home after class. The educational experience was perfect for me. I loved the small Greek revival style campus buildings and I got to put on little shows in Doorley Hall auditorium. Since those days, the Irish Christian Brothers have been virtually destroyed by the disgusting behavior of many in their order as charges of mass child molestation have destroyed their ranks&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.lohud.com/story/news/local/westchester/new-rochelle/2019/04/11/catholic-sex-abuse-iona-prep/3079451002/|title=Former Iona Prep student alleges abuse by Irish Christian Brothers, culture of silence|last=Esposito|first=Frank|website=lohud.com|language=en|access-date=2019-10-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;. No punishment is harsh enough when you think of trusting Catholic parents giving their children over to these cynical monsters. I am very disappointed in the Irish Christian Brothers and Iona College.&quot;

[[File:Don McLean poses with close friend and noted sculptor Zenos Frudakis.jpg|thumb|Don McLean poses with close friend, noted sculptor [[Zenos Frudakis]], at the mural featuring the singer and another New York icon Alicia Keys, revealed in November 2019.]]

In February 2002, &quot;American Pie&quot; was inducted into the [[Grammy Hall of Fame]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.grammy.org/recording-academy/awards/hall-of-fame|title=Grammy Hall of Fame|website=The Grammys|accessdate=January 31, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2004, McLean was inducted into the [[Songwriters Hall of Fame]]. Garth Brooks presented the award and said &quot;Don McLean: his work, like the man himself, is very deep and very compassionate. His pop anthem 'American Pie' is a cultural phenomenon&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/morning-mix/wp/2015/04/08/gloomy-don-mclean-reveals-meaning-of-american-pie-and-sells-lyrics-for-1-2-million/|title=Gloomy Don McLean Reveals Meaning of ‘American Pie’ — and Sells Lyrics for $1.2 Million|newspaper=[[Washington Post]]|accessdate=February 4, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Two years later, Brooks repaid the favor by appearing as a guest (with [[Nanci Griffith]]) on McLean's first American TV special, broadcast as the PBS program ''Starry Starry Night''. A month later, McLean wound up the 20th century by performing &quot;American Pie&quot; at the Lincoln Memorial Gala in Washington D.C.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.songwritershalloffame.org/exhibits/C337|title=Songwriters Hall of Fame: Don McLean Exhibit Home|website=Songwritershalloffame.org|accessdate=January 31, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The biography ''The Don McLean Story: Killing Us Softly With His Songs'' was published in 2007. Biographer Alan Howard conducted extensive interviews for this, the only book-length biography of the often reclusive McLean to date.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://alanhowardinfo.wordpress.com/don-mclean/|title=The Don McLean Story|date=November 2, 2016|work=Dr Alan Howard|accessdate=February 25, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In February 2012 McLean won the BBC Radio 2 Folk Awards Life Time Achievement award.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/radio2/events/folk-awards-2012|title=Radio 2 - Events - Radio 2 Folk Awards 2012|publisher=BBC|date=February 8, 2012|accessdate=April 15, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In March 2012, the PBS network broadcast a feature-length documentary about the life and music of McLean called ''Don McLean: American Troubadour'' produced by four-time Emmy Award-winning filmmaker [[Jim Brown (director)|Jim Brown]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.kpbs.org/news/2012/jan/06/don-mclean-american-troubadour/ |title=Don McLean: American Troubadour |date=November 6, 2012 |website=KPBS.org |accessdate=January 27, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

McLean is one of the primary influences on the UK singer-songwriter [[Jake Bugg]], who said McLean's song &quot;Vincent&quot; was &quot;the first song I liked&quot; after hearing it on an episode of ''[[The Simpsons]]''. He devoured McLean's back catalog and then delved into the artists that inspired McLean, including Buddy Holly and the Weavers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Jake Bugg: I have to Pinch Myself|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/entertainment-arts-19923871|work=BBC News|accessdate=July 14, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Tupac Shakur]] also cited McLean's &quot;Vincent&quot; as a personal inspiration.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Tupac Shakur: Biography|url=https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0000637/bio|publisher=Internet Movie Database|accessdate=July 14, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

McLean is credited as the writer of [[Drake (musician)|Drake]]'s song &quot;Doing It Wrong&quot;, featuring Stevie Wonder.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Doing it Wrong|url=http://www.allmusic.com/song/doing-it-wrong-mt0042497323/lyrics|website=[[AllMusic]]|accessdate=July 15, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; The song includes lyrics from two McLean compositions – &quot;The Wrong Thing to Do&quot; and &quot;When a Good Thing Goes Bad&quot; – both of which were featured on his 1977 album ''[[Prime Time (Don McLean album)|Prime Time]]''.

In March 2017, McLean's single &quot;American Pie&quot; was designated an &quot;aural treasure&quot; by the Library of Congress, &quot;worthy of preservation&quot; in the National Recording Registry &quot;as part of America’s patrimony&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.loc.gov/item/prn-17-029/national-recording-registry-picks-are-over-the-rainbow/2017-03-29/|title=National Recording Registry Picks Are &quot;Over the Rainbow&quot;|website=Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540 USA|accessdate=January 17, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1991, a re-issue of &quot;American Pie&quot; reached the UK top 20 singles chart and in July 2017, &quot;American Pie&quot; peaked at number 6 on the ''Billboard'' Rock Digital Songs Sales chart, nearly 50 years after its first release.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.billboard.com/music/don-mclean|title=Don McLean Chart History|website=Billboard.com|accessdate=January 17, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In May 2019, the UCLA Student Alumni Association awarded McLean its [[UCLA Spring Sing#The George and Ira Gershwin Award|George and Ira Gershwin Award]] for Lifetime Musical Achievement. However, the award was rescinded before it was formally bestowed, because of McLean being convicted of domestic abuse.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.pressherald.com/2017/07/20/don-mclean-pays-3660-fine-to-end-domestic-violence-case/|title=Don McLean pays $3,660 fine to end domestic violence case|author=Stephen Betts|website=Pressherald.com|date=July 21, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; In response, McLean issued the following statement: &quot;UCLA awarded this lifetime achievement award and then took it back because you found out about my squabble with my ex-wife. This has been all over the Internet for three years. Are you people morons? This is settled law. Maybe I need to give you some bribe money to grease the college wheels? I am guilty of nothing to do with assault and you had better make that clear. We live in a dark age of accusation and not law.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.bbc.com/news/entertainment-arts-48186337|title=Don McLean in row over withdrawn award|website=Bbc.com|date=May 7, 2019|accessdate=August 29, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On November 7, 2019, McLean returned to New Rochelle to view a new mural depicting a likeness of his younger self, with lyrics from &quot;American Pie&quot;, on the side of a building on the corner of 134 North Avenue and Bonnefoy Place, painted by artist Loic Ercolessi for a non-profit organization, Street Art for Mankind.  The mural includes the likeness of singer/songwriter [[Alicia Keys]], with lyrics to the song [[Empire State of Mind]], which she performed with [[Jay-Z]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.lohud.com/story/news/local/westchester/new-rochelle/2019/11/07/don-mclean-new-rochelle-mural/4176317002/|title=With mural as backdrop, Don McLean comes home to New Rochelle|website=lohud.com|date=November 7, 2019|accessdate=November 9, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 
[[File:2019-11-14 DonMcLean LasVegasWalkOfStars.tif|thumb|Don McLean presented with Star on Las Vegas Walk of Stars]]

Throughout McLean's career artists including [[Garth Brooks]], [[Madonna (entertainer)|Madonna]], [[Drake (musician)|Drake]], [[Josh Groban]] and others have recorded his songs. At a ceremony in October 2019, plaques certified by the Recording Industry Association of America for gold, platinum, and multi-platinum sales in the United States as well as presentations from Australia, Austria, Belgium, France, Sweden, Switzerland, and the United Kingdom were bestowed on McLean. He said: &quot;As a songwriter your songs are like your children, and you are hopeful everyone loves them as much as you do, but rarely is that the case. I am so grateful that songs I have written have touched so many lives and have been recorded by so many great artists.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://newmusicweekly.com/don-mclean-celebrated-with-worldwide-gold-platinum-multi-platinum-awards-during-television-taping/|title=Don McLean Celebrated With Worldwide Gold, Platinum &amp; Multi-Platinum Awards During Television Taping|date=October 19, 2019|website=New Music Weekly|language=en-US|access-date=October 22, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Personal life==
McLean was raised in the Catholic faith of his mother, Elizabeth McLean; his father, Donald McLean, was a Protestant.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thepaulleslie.com/don-mclean/?mobile=1|title=Don McLean: Legendary Singer-Songwriter|website=Thepaulleslie.com|accessdate=January 16, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; When McLean was 15, his father died months after their only vacation to Washington D.C.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://don-mclean.com/2013/08/12/about-don-mclean|title=About Don McLean|date=August 12, 2013|website=Don-mclean.com|accessdate=February 25, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Don McLean has been married twice, both marriages ending in divorce. His first wife was [[Carol Sauvion]], of Philadelphia, who went on to win an Emmy and Peabody Award for her PBS television series &quot;[[Craft in America]]&quot;. They were married from 1969 to 1976 and they had no children. His second wife was Patrisha Shnier McLean, of Montreal, Canada, from 1987 to 2016. They have two children— Jackie and Wyatt —and two grandchildren.{{cn|date=February 2020}}

The end of the marriage saw McLean arrested and charged with misdemeanor domestic violence stemming from an incident that occurred at his home in Camden, Maine. No other details from the incident were reported. Originally charged with six misdemeanors, McLean pleaded guilty to four as part of a plea agreement. One of the four charges, domestic violence assault, was dismissed. For the remaining three McLean paid around $3,000 in fines and was not sentenced to any jail time.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2019/10/20/us/domestic-violence-don-mclean.html|title=In Maine, a Celebrity Domestic Violence Case Continues to Send Out Ripples|last=Barry|first=Ellen|date=October 20, 2019|work=The New York Times|access-date=October 22, 2019|language=en-US|issn=0362-4331}}&lt;/ref&gt;  McLean said that it had been “hard emotional times for my wife, my children and me...the very painful breakdown of an almost 30-year relationship. Our hearts are broken and we must carry on.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/music/2016/jan/22/don-mclean-says-he-is-not-a-villain-following-his-domestic-violence-arrest|title=Don McLean says he is 'not a villain', following his domestic violence arrest|date=January 22, 2016|work=The Guardian|access-date=October 22, 2019|language=en-GB|issn=0261-3077}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

McLean is an ambassador for Teen Cancer America&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://teencanceramerica.org/member/don-mclean/|title=Don McLean|work=teencanceramerica.org|date=September 26, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; and performed at the Teen Cancer America and UCLA Health fundraising Backyard Concert in 2018. During the show, McLean sang a duet of his song &quot;Vincent&quot; with [[Ed Sheeran]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.nme.com/news/music/watch-ed-sheeran-join-forces-with-don-mclean-for-vincent-cover-2369141|title='Watch Ed Sheeran join forces with Don McLean for Vincent Cover|date=August 21, 2018|website=Nme.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Don McLean Foundation is a charity setup by McLean to be funded by all his income in perpetuity. Its headquarters is based at Lakeview, the Don McLean Maine residence, and it will serve as a center for fundraisers and conferences as well as a nature preserve. Organizations that support the needy in the State of Maine and throughout the United States will be beneficiaries.{{cn|date=October 2019}}

==Discography==
{{main|Don McLean discography}}

===Studio albums===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! rowspan=&quot;2&quot;| Year
! rowspan=&quot;2&quot;| Album
! colspan=&quot;3&quot;| Chart Positions
|-
! style=&quot;width:50px;&quot;| &lt;small&gt;[[Billboard 200|US]]&lt;/small&gt;
! style=&quot;width:50px;&quot;| &lt;small&gt;CAN&lt;/small&gt;
! style=&quot;width:50px;&quot;| &lt;small&gt;[[UK Albums Chart|UK]]&lt;/small&gt;
|-
| 1970
| ''[[Tapestry (Don McLean album)|Tapestry]]''&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 111
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 16
|-
| 1971
| ''[[American Pie (Don McLean album)|American Pie]]''
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 3
|-
| 1972
| ''[[Don McLean (album)|Don McLean]]''
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 23
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 15
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
|-
| 1973
| ''[[Playin' Favorites]]''
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 42
|-
| 1974
| ''[[Homeless Brother]]''
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 120
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
|-
| 1977
| ''[[Prime Time (Don McLean album)|Prime Time]]''
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
|-
| 1978
| ''[[Chain Lightning (album)|Chain Lightning]]''&lt;sup&gt;b&lt;/sup&gt;
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 28
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 25
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 19
|-
| 1981
| ''[[Believers (Don McLean album)|Believers]]''
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 156
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
|-
| 1987
| ''[[Love Tracks (Don McLean album)|Love Tracks]]''
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot;| 1989
| ''[[For the Memories Vols I &amp; II]]''
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
|-
| ''[[And I Love You So (Don McLean album)|And I Love You So (UK Release)]]''
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
|-
| 1991
| ''[[Headroom (Don McLean album)|Headroom]]''
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
|-
| 1991
| ''[[Christmas (Don McLean album)|Christmas]]''
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
|-
| 1995
| ''[[The River of Love (album)|The River of Love]]''
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
|-
| 1997
| ''[[Christmas Dreams]]''
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
|-
| 2001
| ''[[Sings Marty Robbins]]''
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot;| 2003
| ''[[You've Got to Share Songs for Children]]''
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
|-
| ''[[The Western Album]]''
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
|-
| 2005
| ''[[Rearview Mirror: An American Musical Journey]]''
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
|-
| 2009
| ''[[Addicted to Black]]''
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
|-
| 2018
| ''Botanical Gardens''
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| —
|}
*&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;''Tapestry'' wasn't charted in the UK until 1972, after the success of &quot;American Pie&quot;.
*&lt;sup&gt;b&lt;/sup&gt;''Chain Lightning'' also peaked at number 3 on the ''[[RPM (magazine)|RPM]]'' Country Albums chart in Canada.

== References ==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
{{Wikiquote}}
{{Commons category|Don McLean}}
*[http://www.don-mclean.com/ The Official Web Site of Don McLean and American Pie]
*[{{Allmusic|class=artist|id=p4876|pure_url=yes}} Allmusic Entry]
*[http://www.misterguitar.us/news/donmclean2a.html Tom Redmond - Working with Chet Atkins: an interview with Don McLean]
*[https://www.namm.org/library/oral-history/don-mclean Don McLean Interview - NAMM Oral History Library (2016)]
{{Don McLean}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:McLean, Don}}
[[Category:1945 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:20th-century American singers]]
[[Category:21st-century American singers]]
[[Category:American folk guitarists]]
[[Category:American folk singers]]
[[Category:American male singer-songwriters]]
[[Category:American singer-songwriters]]
[[Category:American people of Italian descent]]
[[Category:American rock songwriters]]
[[Category:American male songwriters]]
[[Category:Ballad musicians]]
[[Category:Folk musicians from New York (state)]]
[[Category:Iona College (New York) alumni]]
[[Category:Iona Preparatory School alumni]]
[[Category:People from Camden, Maine]]
[[Category:Musicians from New Rochelle, New York]]
[[Category:Singers from New York (state)]]
[[Category:Songwriters from New York (state)]]
[[Category:Rock banjoists]]
[[Category:American banjoists]]
[[Category:American rock singers]]
[[Category:American acoustic guitarists]]
[[Category:American male guitarists]]
[[Category:20th-century American guitarists]]
[[Category:21st-century American guitarists]]
[[Category:Guitarists from New York (state)]]
[[Category:American people of Scottish descent]]
[[Category:United Artists Records artists]]
[[Category:Curb Records artists]]
[[Category:Proper Records artists]]
[[Category:EMI Group artists]]</text>
      <sha1>eq0twva66bkyckl1nws2j4eps6xsyqj</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
