  <page>
    <title>Daily Planet</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8964</id>
    <revision>
      <id>939195192</id>
      <parentid>939195149</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-04T23:15:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>2607:EA00:200:500:3811:DB78:1E1:A7B4</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* In other media */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Fictional broadsheet newspaper}}
{{about|the fictional comic book newspaper|other uses}}
{{italic title}}
{{Infobox comics organization
&lt;!--Wikipedia:WikiProject Comics--&gt;
|name         = ''Daily Planet''
|image        = Daily Planet logo.png
|imagesize    = 
|caption      = 
|debut        = ''[[Action Comics]]'' #23&lt;br&gt;(April 1940)
|creators     =
|type         = Newspaper
|business     = y
|organisation =
|organization =
|base         =
|owners       =[[Morgan Edge]] &lt;br&gt;[[Franklin Stern]]&lt;br&gt;[[Lex Luthor]]&lt;br&gt;[[Batman|Bruce Wayne]] 
|employees    = [[Perry White]] (editor-in-chief)&lt;br&gt;[[Clark Kent]]&lt;br&gt;[[Lois Lane]]&lt;br&gt;[[Jimmy Olsen]]&lt;br&gt;[[Cat Grant]]&lt;br&gt;[[Ron Troupe]]&lt;br&gt;[[Steve Lombard]]&lt;br&gt;[[Lana Lang]]
|members      =
|fullroster   =
|cat          = newspapers
|subcat       = DC Comics
|hero         =
|villain      =
|sortkey      = Daily Planet
}}

The '''''Daily Planet''''' is a fictional [[broadsheet]] [[newspaper]] appearing in [[American comic book]]s published by [[DC Comics]], commonly in association with [[Superman]]. The newspaper was first mentioned in ''Action Comics'' #23 (April 1940). The ''Daily Planet'' building's most distinguishing and famous feature is the enormous [[globe]] that sits on top of the building.

The newspaper is based in the fictional city of [[Metropolis (comics)|Metropolis]], and employs [[Clark Kent]], [[Lois Lane]], and [[Jimmy Olsen]], with [[Perry White]] as its [[editor-in-chief]]. The building's original features appear to be based upon the [[Old Toronto Star Building]], where Superman co-creator [[Joe Shuster]] was a newsboy when the ''[[Toronto Star]]'' was still called the ''Daily Star''. Shuster has claimed that Metropolis was visually inspired by [[Toronto]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ctv.ca&quot;&gt;[http://www.ctv.ca/servlet/ArticleNews/story/CTVNews/20060628/superman_returns_cdn_060628/20060628?hub=Entertainment &quot;Superman Co-Creator has Humble Canadian Roots,&quot; CTV (Jan. 28, 2006).]. Retrieved July 25, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; However, over the years, Metropolis has served as a fictional analogue to [[New York City]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Fleisher&quot;&gt;Fleisher, Michael and Lincoln, Janet E. ''The Great Superman Book'' (Grand Central Publishing, 1978), pp. 223–225.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Fictional history==

===Golden and Silver Age===
[[File:TorontoStar3.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Old Toronto Star Building]], demolished in 1972, was Shuster's model for the ''Daily Planet'' building.]]
When Superman first appeared in comics (specifically 1938's [[Action Comics 1|''Action Comics'' #1]]), his [[alter ego]] [[Clark Kent]] worked for a newspaper named the ''[[Daily Star (DC Comics)|Daily Star]]'', under editor [[George Taylor (DC Comics)|George Taylor]]. Superman co-creator [[Joe Shuster]] named the ''Daily Star'' after the ''[[Toronto Star|Toronto Daily Star]]'' newspaper in [[Toronto]], [[Ontario]], which had been the newspaper that Shuster's parents received and for which Shuster had worked as a newsboy. It was not until later years that the fictional paper became the ''Daily Planet.'' (The real-world newspaper was called the ''Evening Star'' prior to 1899, the ''Toronto Daily Star'' is now known as the ''Toronto Star''.)&lt;ref name=&quot;ctv.ca&quot;/&gt;

While choosing a name for the fictitious newspaper, consideration was given to combining the names of ''[[The Globe and Mail]]'' and the ''Daily Star'' to become ''The Daily Globe''. But when the [[Superman (comic strip)|comic strip]] appeared, the newspaper's name was permanently made the ''Daily Planet'' to avoid a name conflict with real newspapers. In ''Superman'' (volume 1) #5 (Summer 1940), the publisher of the ''Daily Planet'' is shown to be Burt Mason, a man who is determined to print the truth even when corrupt politician Alex Evell threatens him.  In ''Superman'' #6 (September–October 1940), Mason gives free printing equipment to ''The Gateston Gazette'' after its editor, Jim Tirrell, is killed and its equipment is destroyed by racketeers that Tirrell insisted on reporting.

When DC made use of its [[multiverse (DC Comics)|multiverse]] means of continuity tracking between the early 1960s and mid-1980s, it was declared that the ''Daily Star'' was the newspaper's name in the [[Golden Age of Comics|Golden Age]] or &quot;Earth-Two&quot; versions of Clark Kent, Lois Lane and Jimmy Olsen, while the ''Daily Planet'' was used in the [[Silver Age of Comics|Silver Age]] or &quot;Earth-One&quot; versions. The [[Superman (Kal-L)|Clark Kent of Earth-Two]] eventually became the editor-in-chief of the ''Daily Star'', something his Earth-One counterpart did not achieve.&lt;ref&gt;''Superman Family'' #196 (July–August 1979)&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Daily Planet.jpg|thumb|A ''Daily Planet'' headline (1941)]]
In the Silver and Bronze Age universes, Clark's first contact with the ''Daily Planet'' came when reporter (and future editor) Perry White came to [[Smallville (comics)|Smallville]] to write a story about [[Superboy (Kal-El)|Superboy]], and wound up getting an interview where the Boy of Steel first revealed his [[extraterrestrial life|extraterrestrial]] origins. The story resulted in Perry earning a [[Pulitzer Prize]].&lt;ref&gt;''New Adventures of Superboy'' #12 (December 1980)&lt;/ref&gt; During Clark Kent's years in college, Perry White was promoted to editor-in-chief upon the retirement of the ''Daily Planet'''s previous editor, the Earth-One version of George Taylor.&lt;ref name=&quot;STSS4&quot;&gt;''Superman: The Secret Years'' #4 (May 1985)&lt;/ref&gt;

After graduating from Metropolis University with a degree in [[journalism]], Clark Kent went to work at the ''Planet'', and quickly met Lois Lane (who had been working there for some time already).&lt;ref name=&quot;STSS4&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Superman'' (vol. 1) #133 (November 1959)&lt;/ref&gt; After Clark was hired, Jimmy Olsen joined the paper's staff.&lt;ref&gt;''Superman’s Pal, Jimmy Olsen'' #36 (April 1959)&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1971, the ''Daily Planet'' was purchased by [[Morgan Edge]], president of the Galaxy Broadcasting System. Edge proceeded to integrate Metropolis [[television]] station WGBS-TV's studios into the ''Daily Planet'' building, and named Clark Kent as the anchor for the WGBS evening news.&lt;ref&gt;''Superman'' (vol. 1) #233 (January 1971)&lt;/ref&gt; Eventually, Clark's former schoolmate from Smallville [[Lana Lang]] joined Clark as a co-anchor.&lt;ref&gt;''Superman'' (vol. 1) #317 (November 1977)&lt;/ref&gt;

After the 1985–1986 miniseries ''[[Crisis on Infinite Earths]]'', many of these elements, including Morgan Edge buying the ''Daily Planet'', were [[Retroactive continuity|retroactively changed]] or eliminated from the Superman canon.

===Post-Crisis===
In the post-Crisis comics' canon, years before Clark or Lois began working for the paper, [[Lex Luthor]] owned the ''Daily Planet.'' When Luthor, deciding to sell the paper, began taking bids for the ''Planet'', Perry White convinced an international conglomerate, TransNational Enterprises, to buy the paper. They agreed to this venture with only one stipulation: that Perry White would become editor-in-chief. White had served as the ''Planet'' editor-in-chief ever since, barring the few times he was absent. During those times people such as Sam Foswell and Clark Kent have looked after the paper. [[Franklin Stern]], an old friend of White's, became the ''Daily Planet'''s publisher.

[[File:Daily Planet Action Comics 1014.png|thumb|upright|The Daily Planet building in ''Action Comics'' #1014 (October 2019). Art by Szymon Kudranski.]]
The ''Planet'' saw its share of rough times during White's tenure. For example, it had many violent worker [[strike action|strikes]]. The building itself, along with most of the city, was destroyed during the &quot;Fall of Metropolis&quot; storyline; it is only much later that it was restored by the efforts of various superheroes. The ''Planet'' building sustained heavy damages after the villain [[Doomsday (comics)|Doomsday]]'s rampage. Later, Franklin Stern decided to put the paper up for sale. [[Lex Luthor]], disliking the heavy criticism of himself and his company that the ''Planet'' became noted for, purchased the ''Daily Planet'' and subsequently closed the paper down. Luthor fired every employee of the newspaper except for four people: Simone D'Neige, Dirk Armstrong, [[Jimmy Olsen]], and [[Lois Lane]]. As a final insult, Luthor saw to it that the ''Planet'' globe was unceremoniously dumped in the Metropolis [[landfill]]. In the ''Planet'''s place emerged &quot;LexCom,&quot; a news-oriented [[Internet]] website that primarily catered to Luthor's views of &quot;quality journalism.&quot;

After Lois Lane made a deal with Luthor where, in exchange for him returning the ''Planet'' to Perry, she would kill one story of his choosing with no questions asked, Luthor sold the ''Daily Planet'' to Perry White for the token sum of one dollar. The paper was quickly reinstated, rehiring all of its old staff. Sometime later, ownership of the ''Planet'' fell into the hands of [[Batman|Bruce Wayne]], where it has remained ever since. In the ''[[Batman: Hush]]'' storyline, it is named a [[subsidiary]] of [[Wayne Enterprises#Wayne Entertainment|Wayne Entertainment]].

During the &quot;Y2K&quot; storyline (involving the city of Metropolis being infused with futuristic technology thanks to a descendant of the villain [[Brainiac (character)|Brainiac]]), the ''Daily Planet'' building was &quot;upgraded&quot; along with the rest of Metropolis, and a holographic globe replaced the physical one. Eventually due to temporal instabilities caused by the B13 Virus, Metropolis and the Daily Planet building, globe and all, were restored to their former states.

In the current comics and media spinoffs, the ''Daily Planet'' is presented as a thoroughly modern news operation, including operating an Internet website much like most large newspapers. The ''Planet'''s reporters also have access to the best modern equipment to aid their work, though Perry White has often been shown as still favoring his manual [[typewriter]]. In 2008, it was said that Clark (at least in this era/continuity) uses a typewriter at his desk due to his powers causing minor interference in regular desktop computers.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Action Comics|Action Comics Annual]]'' #11 (2008)&lt;/ref&gt;

During this era, the ''Planet''&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;s major competitors in Metropolis include the [[Tabloid (newspaper format)|tabloid]] newspaper the ''Daily Star'', WGBS-TV (which also employed [[Jimmy Olsen]] and [[Cat Grant]] for a time), and [[Lex Luthor]]'s various media operations. A contemporary publication is ''Newstime'' Magazine, where Clark Kent worked as the editor for a time. The publisher of ''Newstime'' is Colin Thornton, who is secretly the demon [[Blaze and Satanus|Satanus]], an enemy of Superman's.

===''Superman: Birthright''===
In the ''[[Superman: Birthright]]'' limited series, the ''Daily Planet'''s publisher was Quentin Galloway, an abrasive overbearing loudmouth who bullied Jimmy Olsen, and later Clark Kent, before being told off by Lois Lane, whom Galloway could not fire because of her star status.&lt;ref&gt;Bailey, Neal. [http://www.supermanhomepage.com/comics/comics.php?topic=articles/birthright &quot;Birthright&quot;! AKA Article 250: Let's Start Over Again...&quot; Superman Home Page (Aug. 3, 2004).] Accessed May 5, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; This was meant to be a new origin for Superman but one that applied to the Post-Crisis continuity, so later ''Planet'' history concerning Luthor temporarily owning it and other events still applied.

===Post-Infinite Crisis===
During the story ''[[Infinite Crisis]]'', parts of the Post-Crisis history were altered. These changes were explained gradually over the next several years. The 2009 mini-series ''[[Superman: Secret Origin]]'' clarified the earlier history of the ''Planet'' in the new continuity. The story established that while Lex Luthor, in the revised history, owns every media in Metropolis and uses it to enforce his [[public relations|public image]] as a wealthy benefactor, the ''Planet'' had always stood free, refusing him ownership and even condemning his actions in editorials signed by Perry White himself. As a result, when Clark Kent is first inducted into the ''Planet'', the newspaper was almost bankrupt, dilapidated and unable to afford new reporters.&lt;ref&gt;''Superman: Secret Origin'' #3 (January 2010)&lt;/ref&gt; This changed after Superman begins his career. Thanks to Superman granting exclusive interviews and photographs to Lois Lane and Jimmy Olsen when he debuts, the paper's circulation increased 700%.

General [[Sam Lane (comics)|Sam Lane]] (Lois' father) attempted to capture Superman, seeing him as an alien threat. When he failed to do so, he forcibly shut down the ''Planet'' as part of an attempt to force Perry White and Lois to turn over any information they had on Superman that they haven't released to the public. Eventually, Superman turned the public to his favor and Sam Lane was seen in a bad light after his soldier John Corben AKA [[Metallo]] ruthlessly endangered civilians. These events lead to the people of Metropolis no longer looking at Lex Luthor as a savior and ''The Daily Planet'' becomes the city's top-selling paper, as well as a major player in media.

In ''[[Final Crisis]]'' #2, the villain [[Clayface]] triggers an explosion in The ''Daily Planet'' building, greatly damaging the offices, leaving many injured and at least one person dead. Lois Lane is hospitalized. Despite the chaos of ''Final Crisis'' and more than half of humanity being enslaved by evil, the newspaper continues to spread news and inform the public via a printing press in Superman's [[Fortress of Solitude]]. In ''Final Crisis'' #7, it is shown functioning once again.

===The New 52===
[[File:The Daily Planet building.jpg|thumb|upright|The Daily Planet building as it appears in the New 52. Art from ''Superman'' vol. 3 #1 (Nov. 2011) by George Pérez and Jesús Merino.]]
With the reboot of DC's line of comics in 2011, the ''Daily Planet'' was shown in the ''Superman'' comics as being bought by Morgan Edge and merged with the [[Galaxy Broadcasting System]], similar to the Silver/Bronze Age continuity.&lt;ref&gt;''Superman'' (vol. 3) #1 (September 2011)&lt;/ref&gt; In ''Action Comics'', it is revealed that in the new history/universe, Clark Kent begins his journalism career in Metropolis roughly six years before Galaxy Broadcasting merges with the ''Daily Planet''. Along with being a writer for ''The Daily Star'', partly because editor George Taylor was a friend of his adopted parents, Clark is an active blogger who speaks against political corruption and reports on the troubles of everyday citizens who are not often the focus of news media. While working at the ''Star'', Clark meets ''Planet'' photographer Jimmy Olsen and the two become friends despite working at rival publications. Clark is also a great fan of Lois Lane's work at the ''Daily Planet'', eventually meeting her through Jimmy. Months after Superman makes his public debut, Clark leaves ''The Daily Star'' on good terms and accepts a position at ''The Daily Planet''.

After the merger with Galaxy Broadcasting, Lois was promoted to run the TV division, with Clark acting as an on-the-scene reporter for the TV division. Clark is later assigned the &quot;Superman beat.&quot; But after rising tension between himself and Lois, as well as with Galaxy Broadcasting head Morgan Edge, Clark concludes that the ''Daily Planet'' is now more concerned with ratings and internet page views than actual journalism. He quits and goes off to begin an independent, internet news site with fellow journalist Cat Grant. Though Lois and Jimmy consider this to be a bad and risky decision, they continue to act as Clark's friends and confidants, offering aid when they can.

At the conclusion of the New 52, following the New 52 Superman's death, Lex Luthor buys the ''Daily Planet''.&lt;ref&gt;''Justice League'' Vol. 2 #52&lt;/ref&gt;

===30th and 31st Centuries===
In virtually every incarnation of the era inhabited by the [[Legion of Super-Heroes]], the ''Daily Planet'' is depicted as a fixture in Metropolis, and one of Earth's major media sources. Frequently, the [[Flash (Barry Allen)|Flash]]'s wife [[Iris West Allen]] (a native of the era) is depicted as a member of its staff or editorial board.

==Fictional employees==
[[File:Daily Planet-Staff.jpg|thumb|The staff of the ''Daily Planet'' from ''Action Comics Annual'' #11 (July 2008). Art by Adam Kubert and Stéphane Roux.]]

''Daily Planet's'' staff at various times included:
* [[Clark Kent]] - Reporter
* [[Lois Lane]] - Reporter
* [[Jimmy Olsen]] - Photographer and Cub Reporter
* [[Perry White]] - Editor-in-Chief
* [[Lana Lang]] - Business Columnist and editor
* [[Cat Grant]] - Gossip Columnist and editor
* [[Ron Troupe]] - Political Columnist and editor
* [[Steve Lombard]] - Sports columnist and editor

==In other media==

The ''Daily Planet'' has been featured in all adaptations of ''Superman'' to other media.
*From 1976-1981, the ''[[Daily Planet (DC Comics house advertisement)|Daily Planet]]'' was a promotional page appearing in regular DC publications (similar to [[Marvel Comics]]' [[Bullpen Bulletins]]), featuring previews of upcoming publications set in the format of a page from the titular newspaper. Notable features of the page were &quot;The Answer Man&quot;, where DC writer/editor [[Bob Rozakis]] would answer questions sent in by readers, and a comic strip by cartoonist [[Fred Hembeck]] poking fun at DC characters.&lt;ref&gt;Voiles, Mike. [http://www.dcindexes.com/planet/weeklyplanet.php?issue=2 &quot;''Daily Planet'' Remembered,&quot; Mike's Amazing World of DC Comics, DCIndexes.com.] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090212162504/http://www.dcindexes.com/planet/weeklyplanet.php?issue=2 |date=2009-02-12 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*A 16-page &quot;Special Invasion Edition&quot; of ''The Daily Planet'' was published by DC in November 1988 as a tie-in to the ''[[Invasion! (DC Comics)|Invasion!]]'' [[fictional crossover|crossover]] event,&lt;ref&gt;Kimball, Kirk. [http://www.dialbforblog.com/archives/372/ &quot;Present at the Creation,&quot; Dial B for Blog (Oct. 10, 2006).]&lt;/ref&gt; ostensibly the same edition of the paper shown on the final page of ''Invasion!'' #1.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sequart.com/columns/index.php?col=12&amp;column=926 &quot;The DC Canon: ''Invasion!''&quot;, Sequart Research &amp; Literacy Organization] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090210234559/http://www.sequart.com/columns/index.php?col=12&amp;column=926 |date=February 10, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Live-action television===
*During most of the 1950s television series ''[[Adventures of Superman (TV series)|Adventures of Superman]]'', the ''Daily Planet'' exterior was [[Los Angeles City Hall]].  In season one, the [[E. Clem Wilson Building]] was used for exterior shots of the Planet building.
*''[[Lois and Clark: The New Adventures of Superman]]'' introduced the idea of a smaller globe above the building's entrance (the rooftop was never shown). At the end of the first season the paper was bought and closed down by Luthor (as would later happen in the comics). Its relaunch was funded by Metropolis businessman [[Franklin Stern]].
* In the 2000s live-action television series ''[[Smallville]]'', the ''Daily Planet'' building is located across the street from the LuthorCorp building. One of the main characters of ''Smallville'', [[Chloe Sullivan]], worked in the basement of the ''Planet'' (seasons 5-7). Her cousin [[Lois Lane#Smallville|Lois Lane]] continues to work there, as did Chloe's on again/off again love interest (and eventual husband) [[Jimmy Olsen]] until his death at the end of season 8. [[Clark Kent]] started to work at the ''Daily Planet'' as a copy boy in the show's eighth season, but eventually worked his way up to a reporter in the ninth season. In episode 10 of the 6th season a street sign is shown as Chloe ([[Allison Mack]]) runs out of the ''Daily Planet'' from Linda Lake ([[Tori Spelling]]) and shows that the ''Planet'' is located at 355 Burrard St. (which is the actual address of the [[Marine Building]] where location filming for the series was shot in Vancouver). Smallville also features the ''Daily Star'' as a separate newspaper, which was first seen in &quot;Icarus&quot;.
* ''The Daily Planet'' was mentioned in various episodes of ''[[Supergirl (TV series)|Supergirl]]''.

===Films===
*In 1978's ''[[Superman (1978 film)|Superman]]'' and its sequels, the ''Daily Planet'' exterior was the New York [[New York Daily News|''Daily News'']] building. The globe, which used to be on the top of the building, was apparently replaced with one in the lobby as to make room for a [[helipad]] on the roof. In fact, [[Daily News Building|The Daily News building]] in New York has featured a globe in its lobby for almost all of its history. The real-life ''Daily News'' was headquartered in The News Building until the mid-1990s.
*The 2006 ''[[Superman Returns]]'' movie has redesigned the ''Daily Planet'' as a completely computer generated image of a fictional building inserted into the [[Empire State Building]] skyline.
*In the 2013 film ''[[Man of Steel (film)|Man of Steel]]'' the ''Daily Planet'' exterior was filmed in the [[Chicago Board of Trade Building]]. The interior was filmed in the [[Willis Tower]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.chicagobusiness.com/article/20110907/NEWS07/110909951/willis-tower-cbot-building-star-in-superman-filming&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Planet'' appears again in ''[[Batman v Superman: Dawn of Justice]]''.

===Animations===
* In ''[[Superman: The Animated Series]]'', in the episode &quot;[[List of Superman: The Animated Series episodes|World's Finest Part 2]]&quot;, it is mentioned that the ''Daily Planet'' has offices in [[Gotham City]], as well when Lois Lane says she is transferring &quot;to the ''Planet''&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;s Gotham City bureau.&quot;
*The ''Daily Planet'' appears in ''[[Superman: Doomsday]]''.
*The ''Daily Planet'' appears in ''[[Superman Unbound]]''.
*In ''[[Justice League: War]]'', the Daily Planet building is seen in the background of a fight between [[Superman]], [[Batman]], and [[Green Lantern]].
* A parallel universe version of the ''Daily Planet'' renamed PLANETNWZ.COM appears in the 2015 animated film ''[[Justice League: Gods and Monsters]]''. PLANETNWZ.COM is a blog and a harsh critic of the Justice League's violent and destructive method.

===Video games===
* The ''Daily Planet'' appears in [[Superman: Shadow of Apokolips]].
* The ''Daily Planet'' appears as a stage in ''[[Mortal Kombat vs. DC Universe]]''.
* The ''Daily Planet'' appears in ''[[DC Universe Online]]''. It is located in Downtown Metropolis and has been bottled up by Brainiac.
* The ''Daily Planet'' building can be seen off in the distance in ''[[Batman Arkham Knight]]''. Additionally, newspapers can be found outside a storage crate that say strange meteors have struck Smallville hinting at the discovery of Kryptonite.
* The ''Daily Planet'' appears in ''[[Lego Dimensions]]'' where it is transported into the ''[[Back to the Future]]'' world by Lord Vortech.

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[https://dailyplanetdc.wordpress.com ''Daily Planet'] website.
*[https://mobile.twitter.com/dailyplanetdc?lang=en ''Daily Planet'] for Twitter.
*[https://m.facebook.com/DailyPlanetDC/ ''Daily Planet'] for Facebook.
*[https://pin.it/aq62fmb42io4ho ''Daily Planet'] for Pinterest.
* [http://www.instagram.com/dailyplanetdc/ ''Daily Planet'] for Instagram.
* [https://archive.is/20080518162253/http://members.tripod.com/~davidschutz/superman3.html &quot;Superman at the ''Star''&quot;: An interview with Superman co-creator Joe Shuster from the ''Toronto Star'', April 26, 1992, about Shuster's memories of Toronto and the ''Evening Star'' newspaper.]
* [http://www.supermanhomepage.com/comics/who/who-intro.php?topic=daily-planet The Superman Homepage's entry for the ''Daily Planet'']
* [http://supermanica.kinlok.nu/wiki/index.php/Daily_Planet Supermanica: ''Daily Planet''] Supermanica entry on the Pre-Crisis ''Daily Planet''

{{Timeline
|before= ← Batman's origin introduces Batman's parents (Thomas Wayne and Martha Wayne) and their killer by Bob Kane, Bill Finger, Jerry Robinson and Gardner Fox. See [[Origin of Batman]], [[Thomas Wayne]], [[Martha Wayne]] and [[Joe Chill]] for more info and next timeline.
|title= [[Timeline of DC Comics]] ([[Timeline of DC Comics (1930s)|1930s]])
|years= November 1939 
|after = The first Doll Man along with Martha Roberts (who later becomes Doll Girl) was debuted by Will Eisner. See [[Doll Man]] and [[Doll Girl]] for more info and next timeline. →
}}

{{Superman}}
{{Superman characters|state=expanded}}

[[Category:Metropolis (comics)]]
[[Category:1940 in comics]]
[[Category:Fictional elements introduced in 1940]]</text>
      <sha1>1lsozlitzggpe4vmiz8eebthyqzg77t</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
