  <page>
    <title>DirkJan</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8992</id>
    <revision>
      <id>928333170</id>
      <parentid>890605799</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-11-28T11:06:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rescuing 1 sources and tagging 0 as dead.) #IABot (v2.0</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">'''DirkJan''' is a Dutch comic strip series, created in 1989 by Dutch author and artist [[Mark Retera]].&lt;ref&gt;https://www.lambiek.net/artists/r/retera_mark.htm&lt;/ref&gt; It is also the name of its main character. The series is a [[gag-a-day]] comic.

==Description==

DirkJan is a loser who stumbles through life in mostly three-panel [[gag-a-day]] comic strips. He started out in 1989 as a student at the current [[Radboud University Nijmegen]] &lt;ref&gt;https://www.lambiek.net/artists/r/retera_mark.htm&lt;/ref&gt;  in the Netherlands, where he lived in a typical student house with all the stereotypical side-kicks, such as the frat boy, the beer drinker, the bossy girl who checks if everybody keeps to the house rules, and the tramps who use the heated shared hallway to stay the night. Early DirkJans contained many references to the student life of [[Nijmegen]].

==Publication==

DirkJan was first published in ''Critic'', the magazine for the local union of psychology students. It then moved on to monthly publication in the student magazine of Nijmegen ([[Algemeen Nijmeegs Studentenblad]], ANS). DirkJan became known nationally when the then only commercial comics magazine of the Netherlands SjoSji (now defunct) started publishing the strip. &lt;ref&gt;https://www.lambiek.net/artists/r/retera_mark.htm&lt;/ref&gt; 

With the last move, the nature of the strip changed. Most of the student side-kicks got cancelled and DirkJan left university, first for jail (DJ is a notorious [[Kabouter]] abuser) and then to wander the globe and indeed space.

As of November 2016, there are 22 DirkJan albums, tentatively named 'DirkJan 1' through 'DirkJan 22'. Several newspapers in the [[Netherlands]] publish the comic in their daily edition.

The amateur comics magazine [[Iris magazine|Iris]] (1990 - 1995) (re)published a number of DirkJan comics, some of which were refused for publication in SjoSji.

==Sources==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20130817053713/http://www.comichouse.nl/en/illustration/2d/retera/ Portfolio of Mark Retera]
* http://www.mooves.nl/ (two animated DirkJan strips, Flash-only site)

[[Category:Dutch comics characters]]
[[Category:Male characters in comics]]
[[Category:Fictional Dutch people]]
[[Category:Dutch comic strips]]
[[Category:Gag-a-day comics]]
[[Category:1989 comics debuts]]
[[Category:Comics characters introduced in 1989]]
[[Category:Comics set in the Netherlands]]


{{comic-strip-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>tm81ypuu613ctn60iqdyve2r24sovxk</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
