  <page>
    <title>Fairchild Channel F</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7487</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943250864</id>
      <parentid>943250621</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-29T20:04:28Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Maxeto0910</username>
        <id>35498457</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use mdy dates|date=August 2019}}
{{Infobox information appliance
| name = Fairchild Channel F
| title = 
| aka = Fairchild Video Entertainment System
| logo = Channel_F_Logo.svg
| image = Fairchild-Channel-F.jpg
| caption = A Fairchild Channel F and its two accompanying [[game controllers]]
| developer = 
| manufacturer = [[Fairchild Camera and Instrument]]
| family = 
| type = [[Home video game console]]
| generation = [[Second generation of video game consoles|Second generation]]
| releasedate = {{vgrelease|NA|November [[1976 in video gaming|1976]]|JP|October [[1977 in video gaming|1977]]}}
| lifespan = 1976–1983
| price = {{USD|169|1976}}
| discontinued = 1983
| unitssold = c. 250,000 (as of 1977)&lt;ref name=&quot;jones123&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=Strategic management: an integrated approach|year=2007|publisher=Houghton Mifflin|location=Boston|isbn=0-618-73166-0|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=P8q5AAAAIAAJ&amp;q=%22By+this+point,+second-place+Fairchild+sold+around+250000+units%22&amp;dq=%22By+this+point,+second-place+Fairchild+sold+around+250000+units%22|first1=Gareth R. |last1=Jones|edition=7th|first2=Charles W. L. |last2=Hill|accessdate=February 25, 2012|page=C-123|quote=By this point, second-place Fairchild sold around 250,000 units of its system.}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| unitsshipped = 
| media = 
| os = 
| power = 
| soc = 
| cpu = [[Fairchild F8]]
| memory = 64&amp;nbsp;bytes RAM&lt;br/&gt;2 KB video buffer
| storage = 
| memory card = [[ROM cartridge]]
| display = 
| graphics = 
| sound = 
| input = 
| controllers = {{plainlist|
* Joystick/paddle
* Keypad (canceled)}}
| camera = 
| touchpad = 
| connectivity = 
| platform = 
| service = 
| dimensions = 
| weight = 
| topgame = 
| compatibility = 
| predecessor = 
| successor = [[#Channel F System II|Channel F System II]]
| related = 
| website = &lt;!--{{URL|example.org}}--&gt;
}}

The '''Fairchild Channel F''', short for &quot;Channel Fun,&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.fastcompany.com/3040889/the-untold-story-of-the-invention-of-the-game-cartridge|title=The Untold Story Of The Invention Of The Game Cartridge|first=Benj|last=Edwards|date=January 22, 2015|website=Fast Company|accessdate=January 7, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; was the first programmable [[ROM cartridge]]–based [[video game console]], and the first console to use a [[microprocessor]]. It was released by [[Fairchild Camera and Instrument]] in November 1976 across North America&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.fndcollectables.com/CHANNEL_F_INFO/U_S_/Time_Line/time_line.html |title=Fairchild Channel F Patent, FCC Approval, &amp; Launch Brochure|website=Fndcollectables.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; at a retail price of {{USD|169.95|1976}}. It was also released in Japan (チャンネル F) in October the following year. It was originally named &quot;Video Entertainment System,&quot; but when [[Atari, Inc.]] released its [[Atari 2600|Video Computer System]] the next year, Fairchild changed the name for its machine, although they continued to use the old name alongside it. By 1977, the Fairchild Channel F had sold about 250,000 units, trailing behind sales of the VCS.&lt;ref name=&quot;jones123&quot; /&gt;

==Overview==
{{More citations needed section|date=August 2019}}
In 1974, Alpex Computer Corporation employees Wallace Kirschner and Lawrence Haskel developed a home video game prototype consisting of a base unit centered on an Intel 8080 microprocessor and interchangeable circuit boards containing ROM chips that could be plugged into the base unit. The duo attempted to interest several television manufacturers in the system, but were unsuccessful. Next, they contacted a buyer at Fairchild, which sent engineer [[Jerry Lawson (engineer)|Jerry Lawson]] to evaluate the system.  Lawson was impressed by the system and suggested Fairchild license the technology, which the company did in January 1976. Lawson worked with industrial designer Nick Talesfore and mechanical engineer Ron Smith to turn the prototype into a viable project. Changes included replacing the 8080 with Fairchild's own [[Fairchild F8|F8]] [[Central processing unit|CPU]], adapting the prototypes complex keyboard controls into a single control stick, and encasing the ROM circuit boards in a plastic cartridges reminiscent of 8-track tapes.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=They Create Worlds: The Story of the People and Companies That Shaped the Video Game Industry, Volume I|last=Smith|first=Alexander|publisher=[[CRC Press]]|year=2019|isbn=9781138389908|pages=318–320|ref=refSmith2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Talesfore was responsible for the design of the hand controllers, console, and video game cartridges. Smith was responsible for the mechanical engineering of the video cartridges and controllers. The F8 was very complex compared to the typical integrated circuits of the day and had more inputs and outputs than other contemporary chips. Because chip packaging was not initially available with enough pins, the F8 used in the original form of the VES/Channel F (replaced by System II) was instead fabricated as a pair of chips that had to be used together to form a complete CPU. However, due to the F8's design, there was a considerable savings in terms of pins that enabled the inclusion of 64 bytes of internal scratchpad RAM. A single-chip variant of the F8 was used by both the System II and the [[VideoBrain]] computer system.

[[File:Fairchild Channel F test picture.png|250px|thumb|right| The [[Palette (computing)|palette]] of the Channel F]] The graphics are quite basic by modern standards but were a vast improvement over monochrome systems such as [[Pong]]. The Channel F is only able to use one plane of graphics and one of four background colors per line, only three plot colors to choose from (red, green, and blue) that turned into white if the background is set to black, at a resolution of 128&amp;nbsp;×&amp;nbsp;64, with approximately 102 × 58 pixels visible and help from only 64 bytes of system RAM, half the amount of the later [[Atari 2600]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://classicdev.org/images/thumb/3/31/FVE100_schematic_sheet_1of3.gif/1280px-FVE100_schematic_sheet_1of3.gif |title=Archived copy |access-date=February 5, 2016 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110725180144/http://classicdev.org/images/thumb/3/31/FVE100_schematic_sheet_1of3.gif/1280px-FVE100_schematic_sheet_1of3.gif |archive-date=July 25, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://classicdev.org/images/thumb/5/55/FVE100_schematic_sheet_2of3.png/1280px-FVE100_schematic_sheet_2of3.png |title=Archived copy |access-date=February 5, 2016 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110725180151/http://classicdev.org/images/thumb/5/55/FVE100_schematic_sheet_2of3.png/1280px-FVE100_schematic_sheet_2of3.png |archive-date=July 25, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The Maze game (cartridge 10) required 1K of on-cartridge static RAM, adding to the cost to manufacture it. The Chess game contained considerably more on-cartridge RAM that that. The F8 processor at the heart of the console is able to produce enough AI to allow for player versus computer matches, a first in console history. All previous machines required a human opponent. ''Tic-Tac-Toe'' on Videocart-1 had this feature, it was only for one player against the machine. The same is true for the chess game, which would have very long turn times for the computer as the game progressed.

One feature unique to this console is the 'hold' button, which allows the player to freeze the game, change the time or change the speed of the game.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.old-computers.com/museum/computer.asp?c=890|title=OLD-COMPUTERS.COM : The Museum|website=Old-computers.com|accessdate=January 7, 2019|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180630162108/http://www.old-computers.com/museum/computer.asp?c=890|archive-date=June 30, 2018|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; The functions printed on the console is how they work in the built-in games and also some of the original games, all buttons (except reset) are controlled by the programming and can be used for anything the programmer decides. The hold function is not universal (like the hardwired reset). In the original unit, sound is played through an internal speaker, rather than the TV set. However, the System II passed sound to the television through the RF modulator.

==Controllers==
The controllers are a joystick without a base; the main body is a large handgrip with a triangular &quot;cap&quot; on top, the top being the portion that actually moved for eight-way directional control. It could be used as both a joystick and paddle (twist), and not only could it be pushed down to operate as a fire button, it could be pulled up as well.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Vinciguerra|first=Robert|title=Fairchild Channel F Video Entertainment System: The first modern game console|url=http://www.revrob.com/sci-a-tech-topmenu-52/66-fairchild-channel-f-video-entertainment-system-the-first-modern-game-console|publisher=The Rev. Rob Times|accessdate=January 6, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; The model 1 unit contained a small compartment for storing the controllers when moving it. The System II featured detachable controllers and had two holders at the back to wind the cable around and to store the controller in. [[Zircon (company)|Zircon]] later offered a special control that featured an action button on the front of the joystick. It was marketed by Zircon as &quot;Channel F Jet-Stick&quot; in a letter sent out to registered owners before Christmas 1982.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://fndcollectables.com/CHANNEL_F_INFO/U_S_/Adds___Offers/LETTERS/x82fr1f.jpg|format=JPG|title=Channel F Jet-Stick Advert|website=Fndcollectables.com|accessdate=January 7, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite the failure of the Channel F, the joystick's design was so popular—''[[Creative Computing]]'' called it &quot;outstanding&quot;— that Zircon also released an [[Atari joystick port]]-compatible version, the Video Command Joystick,&lt;ref name=&quot;ccvag1983spring&quot;&gt;{{Citation | first = David H. | last = Ahl | author-link = David H. Ahl | first2 = Randi J. | last2 = Rost | author2-link = Randi J. Rost | title = Blisters And Frustration: Joysticks, Paddles, Buttons and Game Port Extenders for Apple, Atari and VIC | journal = Creative Computing Video &amp; Arcade Games | volume = 1 | issue = 1 | pages = 106ff. | year = 1983 | url = http://www.atarimagazines.com/cva/v1n1/joysticks.php }}&lt;/ref&gt; first released without the extra fire button. Before that, only the downwards plunge motion was connected and acted as the fire button; the pull-up and twist actions were not connected to anything.{{citation needed|date=August 2019}}

==Games==
{{main|Fairchild Channel F Videocarts}}
{{More citations needed section|date=August 2019}}
Twenty-seven cartridges, termed &quot;Videocarts&quot;, were officially released to consumers in the [[United States]] during the ownership of Fairchild and Zircon, the first twenty-one of which were released by Fairchild. Several of these cartridges were capable of playing more than one game and were typically priced at $19.95. The Videocarts were yellow and approximately the size and overall texture of an [[8 track cartridge]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Kent|first=Steven L.|title=The Ultimate History of Video Games|year=2001|publisher=Three Rivers Press|isbn=0-7615-3643-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; They usually featured colorful label artwork. The earlier artwork was created by nationally known artist Tom Kamifuji and art directed by Nick Talesfore.{{Citation needed|date=February 2011}} The console contained two built-in games, Tennis and Hockey, which were both advanced ''[[Pong]]'' clones. In Hockey, the reflecting bar could be changed to diagonals by twisting the controller and could move all over the playing field. Tennis was much like the original Pong.

A sales brochure from 1978 listed &quot;Keyboard Videocarts&quot; for sale. The three shown were ''K-1 Casino Poker'', ''K-2 Space Odyssey'', and ''K-3 Pro-Football''. These were intended to use the Keyboard accessory. All further brochures, released after Zircon took over Fairchild, never listed this accessory nor anything called a Keyboard Videocart.

There was one additional cartridge released numbered Videocart-51 and simply titled &quot;Demo 1&quot;. This Videocart was shown in a single sales brochure released shortly after Zircon acquired the company. It was never listed for sale after this single brochure which was used in the winter of 1979.

===Games===
{{More citations needed section|date=August 2019}}
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|-
! Title
! Release date
! Genre
|-
| Democart
| 1976&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |url=https://books.google.com/?id=oK3D4i5ldKgC |title=Before the Crash: Early Video Game History |first=Mark J. P. |last=Wolf |year=2012 |publisher=[[Wayne State University Press]] |page=70}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| System demonstration
|-
| ''Hockey'' (integrated)
| 1976
| Sports
|-
| ''Tennis'' (integrated)
| 1976
| Sports
|-
| Videocart-1: ''Tic-Tac-Toe, Shooting Gallery, Doodle, Quadra-Doodle''
| 1976
| Trivia, shooter
|-
| Videocart-2: ''Desert Fox, Shooting Gallery''
| 1976
| Action, shooter
|-
| Videocart-3: ''Video Blackjack''
| 1976
| Gambling
|-
| Videocart-4: ''Spitfire''
| 1977&lt;ref&gt;''[[Mansfield News Journal]]'', April 15, 1977&lt;/ref&gt;
| Action, shooter
|-
| Videocart-5: ''Space War''
| 1977
| Action, shooter
|-
| Videocart-6: ''Math Quiz I (Addition &amp; Subtraction)''
| 1977
| Educational
|-
| Videocart-7: ''Math Quiz II (Multiplication &amp; Division)''
| 1977
| Educational
|-
| Videocart-8: ''Magic Numbers (Mind Reader &amp; Nim)''
| 1977
| Trivia
|-
| Videocart-9: ''Drag Race''
| 1977
| Racing
|-
| Videocart-10: ''Maze, Jailbreak, Blind-Man's-Bluff, Trailblazer''
| 1977
| Maze
|-
| Videocart-11: ''Backgammon, Acey-Deucey''
| 1977
| Trivia
|-
| Videocart-12: ''Baseball''
| 1977
| Sports
|-
| Videocart-13: ''Robot War, Torpedo Alley''
| 1977
| Platform, action
|-
| Videocart-14: ''Sonar Search''
| 1977
| Strategy
|-
| Videocart-15: ''Memory Match 1, Memory Match 2''
| 1978
| Puzzle
|-
| Videocart-16: ''Dodge' It''
| 1978
| Platform, action
|-
| Videocart-17: ''Pinball Challenge''
| 1978
| Pinball
|-
| Videocart-18: ''Hangman''
| 1978
| Puzzle
|-
| Videocart-19: ''Checkers''
| 1978
| Trivia
|-
| Videocart-20: ''Video Whizball''
| 1978
| Miscellaneous
|-
| Videocart-21: ''Bowling''
| 1978
| Sports
|-
| Videocart-22: ''Slot Machine''
| 1980
| Gambling
|-
| Videocart-23: ''Galactic Space Wars''
| 1980
| Action, shooter
|-
| Videocart-24: ''Pro Football''
| 1981
| Sports
|-
| Videocart-25: ''Casino Poker''
| 1981
| Gambling
|-
| Videocart-26: ''Alien Invasion''
| 1981
| Action, shooter
|}

Carts listed (as mentioned above) but never released:
* Keyboard Videocart-1: ''Casino Poker''
* Keyboard Videocart-2: ''Space Odyssey''
* Keyboard Videocart-3: ''Pro-Football''

Official carts that also exist:
* Democart 2

German electronics manufacturer [[SABA (electronics manufacturer)|SABA]] also released a few compatible carts different from the original carts: translation in Videocart-1 ''Tic-Tac-Toe'' to German words; Videocart-3 released with different abbreviations (German); Videocart-18 changed graphics and German word list; and SABA 20, a chess game released only by SABA.

A clone of ''[[Pac-Man]]'' for the Channel F was released in 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.consolecity.com/games/action-game_info/game_id-29406.html|title=Channel F – Videocart 27: Pac-Man (USC)|website=ConsoleCity|accessdate=January 7, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Reception==
[[Ken Uston]] reviewed 32 games in his book ''[[Ken Uston's Guide to Buying and Beating the Home Video Games]]'' in 1982, and rated some of the Channel F's titles highly; of these, ''Alien Invasion'' and ''Video Whizball'' were considered by Uston to be &quot;the finest adult cartridges currently available for the Fairchild Channel F System&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Uston, Ken. ''Ken Uston's Guide to Buying and Beating the Home Video Games'' (Signet, 1982) p.605&lt;/ref&gt; The games on a whole, however, rated last on his survey of over 200 games for the Atari, Intellivision, Astrocade and Odyssey consoles, and contemporary games were rated &quot;Average&quot; with future Channel F games rated &quot;below average&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Uston, Ken. ''Ken Uston's Guide to Buying and Beating the Home Video Games'' (Signet, 1982) p.20.&lt;/ref&gt; Uston rated almost one-half of the Channel F games as &quot;high in interest&quot; and called that &quot;an impressive proportion&quot; and further noted that &quot;Some of the Channel F cartridges are timeless; no matter what technological developments occur, they will continue to be of interest.&quot; His overall conclusion was that the games &quot;serve a limited, but useful, purpose&quot; and that the &quot;strength of the Channel F offering is in its excellent educational line for children&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Uston, Ken. ''Ken Uston's Guide to Buying and Beating the Home Video Games'' (Signet, 1982) p.603 and p.23.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1983, after Zircon announced its discontinuation of the Channel F, ''Video Games'' reviewed the console. Calling it &quot;the system nobody knows&quot;, the magazine described its graphics and sounds as &quot;somewhat primitive by today's standards&quot;. It described ''Space War'' as perhaps &quot;the most antiquated game of its type still on the market&quot;, and rated the 25 games for the console with an average grade of three (&quot;not too good&quot;) on a scale from one to ten. The magazine stated, however, that Fairchild &quot;managed to create some fascinating games, even by today's standards&quot;, calling ''Casino Royale'' (''Video Blackjack'') &quot;the best card game, from blackjack to bridge, made for ''any'' TV-game system&quot;. It also favorably reviewed ''Dodge-It'' (&quot;simple but great&quot;), ''Robot War'' (&quot;Berzerk without guns&quot;), and ''Whizball'' (&quot;thoroughly original ... hockey ''with'' guns&quot;), but concluded that only those interested in nostalgia, [[video game collecting]], or card games would purchase the Channel F in 1983.&lt;ref name=&quot;dionne198303&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url=https://archive.org/stream/Video_Games_Volume_1_Number_06_1983-03_Pumpkin_Press_US#page/n71/mode/2up | title=Channel F: The System Nobody Knows | work=Video Games | date=March 1983 | accessdate=May 26, 2014 | author=Dionne, Roger | pages=73–75}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Technical specifications==
{{More citations needed section|date=February 2020}}
[[File:Grandstand-video-entertainment-computer-pcb.jpg|thumb|PCB Scan of the Grandstand Video Entertainment Computer (UK Channel F II variant).]]
Original Channel F technical specifications:
* [[Central processing unit|CPU]] [[microprocessor]]: [[Fairchild F8]] ([[8-bit]])&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.videogameconsolelibrary.com/|title=Home Page|website=Video Game Console Library|accessdate=January 7, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Clock rate|operating]] at 1.7897725&amp;nbsp;[[megahertz|MHz]] ([[NTSC]]) ([[PAL]] gen. 1: 2.0000&amp;nbsp;MHz, PAL gen. 2: 1.7734475&amp;nbsp;MHz)
* [[Random-access memory|RAM]]: 2 [[kilobyte|KB]] (128&amp;nbsp;×&amp;nbsp;64&amp;nbsp;×&amp;nbsp;2 bits)&lt;ref name=&quot;books.google.co.uk&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=oK3D4i5ldKgC&amp;pg=PA65|title=Before the Crash: Early Video Game History|first=Mark J. P.|last=Wolf|date=June 15, 2012|publisher=Wayne State University Press|accessdate=January 7, 2019|via=Google Books}}&lt;/ref&gt; for the [[framebuffer]] plus the 64 [[bytes]] of [[scratchpad memory]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.oldcomputers.it/parts/f/fairchild/f8s/docs/channelf_bis.html|title=Fairchild Channel F|website=www.oldcomputers.it|access-date=2020-02-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Additional [[Static random-access memory|SRAM]] supported via add-in cartridges. Maze and Chess contain static RAM (SRAM), with the latter containing significantly more than the 1KB for Maze.
* [[Display resolution|Resolution]]: 128&amp;nbsp;×&amp;nbsp;64 [[pixel]]s,&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt; approximately 102×58 pixels visible depending on TV. Columns 125 and 126 controls palette (per row).
* [[Refresh rate]]: 60&amp;nbsp;Hz&lt;ref name=mame&gt;As emulated by [[MAME]]; see source code at {{cite web|url=https://github.com/mamedev/mame/blob/master/src/mame/drivers/channelf.cpp#L219 |title=MAME |work=GitHub |access-date=July 7, 2019 |url-status=live |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190707123659/https://github.com/mamedev/mame/blob/master/src/mame/drivers/channelf.cpp#L219 |archive-date=July 7, 2019 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[List of color palettes|Colors]]: 8 colors&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt; (either black/white lines or one of three background colors per line combined with red, green or blue pixels)
* Audio: 120&amp;nbsp;Hz, 500&amp;nbsp;Hz and 1&amp;nbsp;kHz beeps (can be [[Pulse-frequency modulation|modulated]] to produce different tones). Quality is quite superior on the System II, versus the original model.
* Input: two custom game controllers, hardwired to the console (original release) or removable (Channel F System II)
* Output: [[RF modulator|RF modulated]] composite video signal, cord hardwired to console in gen. 1, detachable in gen. 2

==Channel F System II==
{{Unreferenced section|date=August 2019}}
Sometime in 1979, Zircon International bought the rights to the Channel F and released the re-designed console as the '''Channel F System II''' to compete with Atari's VCS. This re-designed System II was completed by Nick Talesfore at Fairchild. He was the same industrial designer who designed the original game console. Only six new games were released after the debut of the second system before its demise, several of which were developed at Fairchild before they sold it off.

The major changes were in design, with the controllers removable from the base unit instead of being wired directly into it, the controller storage was moved to the rear of the unit, and the sound was now mixed into the RF TV signal so the unit no longer needed a speaker. Electronics was also simplified with custom logic chips instead of standard logic resulting in a much smaller circuit board. This version also featured a simpler and more modern-looking case design. However, by this time the market was in the midst of the first video game crash, and Fairchild eventually threw in the towel and left the market. A number of licensed versions were released in Europe, including the '''Luxor Video Entertainment System''' in Scandinavia (Sweden), '''Adman Grandstand''' in the UK, and the '''SABA Videoplay''', '''ITT Telematch Processor''' and '''Nordmende Color TelePlay''' from Germany, and also '''Dumont Videoplay''' and '''Barco Challenger''' from the Barco/Dumont company in Italy and Belgium.
&lt;gallery class=&quot;center&quot; heights=&quot;165&quot; widths=&quot;220&quot; style=&quot;margin: 25px 0;&quot;&gt;
Fairchild-Channel-F-System-II-Console.png|Channel F System II
Nordmende COLOR TelePlay.jpg|Nordmende Color TelePlay µP
Adman Grandstand Fairchild.jpg|Adman Grandstand Video Entertainment Computer
LuxorVideoEntertainmentComputer.jpg|Luxor Video Entertainment Computer
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==See also==
* [[TV POWWW]], interactive TV game show that used Channel F

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://thedoteaters.com/?bitstory=channel-f The Dot Eaters article] with a history of the Channel F and games
* [http://www.vintagecomputing.com/index.php/archives/545 Interview with designer Jerry Lawson]
* [http://www.mobygames.com/browse/games/channel-f/ MobyGames list] of Channel F games
* [http://channelf.se/ Channel F wiki] and gallery of labels, instructions, boxes
* [http://www.google.com/patents/US4095791 Patent: Cartridge programmable video game apparatus US 4095791 A]
* [http://www.fastcompany.com/3040889/the-untold-story-of-the-invention-of-the-game-cartridge The Untold Story of the Invention of the Video Game Cartridge] - how the Channel F's video game cartridge was created (January 22, 2015).
* [https://aux.avclub.com/channel-f-was-1977-s-top-game-system-before-atari-wiped-1798260297 Channel F was 1977’s top game system—before Atari wiped it out] at [[The A.V. Club]]'s AUX (4/09/2017)
* [https://archive.org/details/channelf_library Channel F games] playable for free in the browser at the [[Internet Archive]] ''Console Living Room''.

{{Second generation game consoles}}
{{Home video game consoles}}

[[Category:Computer-related introductions in 1976]]
[[Category:Home video game consoles]]
[[Category:Second-generation video game consoles]]
[[Category:Fairchild Corporation]]
[[Category:Products introduced in 1976]]
[[Category:1976 in video games]]</text>
      <sha1>q4vv2hok4vesn71cxsyyahkzoaf742y</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
