  <page>
    <title>Circumcision and law</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7447</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941849267</id>
      <parentid>932739565</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-21T01:34:42Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>DemonDays64 Bot</username>
        <id>37890503</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>HTTPS security. [[User talk:DemonDays64|Tell me]] if there's an issue with my edit. (via [[WP:JWB]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{about|laws concerning male circumcision|the legal status of female genital mutilation|female genital mutilation}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2014}}

Laws restricting, regulating, or banning [[circumcision]], some dating back to ancient times, have been enacted in many countries and communities. In modern states, circumcision is generally presumed to be legal, but laws pertaining to assault or child custody have been applied in cases involving circumcision. There are currently no states that unequivocally ban infant male circumcision for non-therapeutic reasons. In the case of non-therapeutic circumcision of children, proponents of laws in favor of the procedure often point to the rights of the parents or practitioners, namely the right of [[freedom of religion]]. Those against the procedure point to the boy's right of [[Freedom of religion#Secular law|freedom ''from'' religion]]. In several court cases, judges have pointed to the irreversible nature of the act,&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc.co.uk&quot;&gt;[https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-18604664 German court rules circumcision is 'bodily harm', BBC News Europe.] Retrieved 13 July 2012&lt;/ref&gt; the grievous harm to the boy's body,&lt;ref name=&quot;telegraph&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/germany/9358636/Jewish-groups-condemn-courts-definition-of-circumcision-as-grievous-bodily-harm.html |title=Jewish groups condemn court's definition of circumcision as grievous bodily harm |date=27 June 2012 |newspaper=The Daily Telegraph |accessdate=27 June 2012 |location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the right to self-determination, and bodily integrity.&lt;ref name = &quot;Reut06&quot;&gt;{{cite news
| url         = http://www.alertnet.org/thenews/newsdesk/N24253813.htm
| title       = US judge rules 9-year-old need not get circumcised
| date        = 24 October 2006
| work   = Reuters
| accessdate  =30 August 2010
| quote       = In a decision cheered by foes of routine circumcision for boys, a judge ruled on Tuesday that a 9-year-old need not be circumcised as his mother wanted....In granting the boy's father an injunction blocking the procedure, the judge said the boy could decide for himself whether to be circumcised when he turns 18.
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

== History==

=== Judaism ===
{{See also|Brit milah}}
There are ancient religious requirements for [[circumcision]]. The [[Hebrew Bible]] commands [[Jew]]s to circumcise their male children on the eighth day of life, and to circumcise their male [[slavery|slaves]] ({{bibleverse||Genesis|17:11–12|HE}}).

Laws banning circumcision are also ancient. The [[Ancient Greece|ancient Greeks]] prized the foreskin and disapproved of the Jewish custom of circumcision.&lt;ref name=Hodges2001&gt;{{cite journal |last=Hodges |first=Frederick M. |authorlink= |year=2001 |title=The Ideal Prepuce in Ancient Greece and Rome: Male Genital Aesthetics and Their Relation to Lipodermos, Circumcision, Foreskin Restoration, and the Kynodesme |journal=Bulletin of the History of Medicine |volume=75 |issue= 3|pages=375–405 |id= |url=http://www.cirp.org/library/history/hodges2/ |accessdate=22 January 2008 |quote=|doi=10.1353/bhm.2001.0119 |pmid=11568485}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[1 Maccabees]], 1:60–61 states that [[Antiochus IV Epiphanes|King Antiochus IV]] of [[Syria]], the occupying power of [[Judea]] in 170 BCE, outlawed circumcision on penalty of death.&lt;ref&gt;[[1 Maccabees]], 1:60–61&lt;/ref&gt; one of the grievances leading to the [[Maccabean Revolt]].&lt;ref name = &quot;Miller&quot;&gt;{{cite journal
| last        = Miller
| first       = Geoffrey P.
|date=Spring 2002
| title       = Circumcision: Cultural-Legal Analysis
| journal     = Virginia Journal of Social Policy &amp; the Law
| volume      = 9
| pages       = 497–585
| ssrn         = 201057
| format      = PDF (free download)
| accessdate  =| quote       = Ritual circumcision of boys is a durable tradition. Jews of ancient times refused to abandon the practice despite enormous pressure to do so. In 167 BCE the Seleucid emperor Antiochus IV, as part of a campaign to Hellenise the Jews, condemned to death every Hebrew who allowed a son to be circumcised. The Jews responded with the Maccabean revolt, a campaign of guerrilla warfare that resulted in major victories for the rebels and, eventually, a peace treaty that restored Jewish ritual prerogatives.
| doi        = 10.2139/ssrn.201057
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the ''[[Historia Augusta]]'', the [[Roman empire|Roman]] emperor [[Hadrian]] issued a decree banning circumcision in the empire,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cirp.org/library/history/hodges2/|title=The Ideal Prepuce in Ancient Greece and Rome|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; and some modern scholars argue that this was a main cause of the Jewish [[Bar Kokhba's revolt|Bar Kokhba]] revolt of 132 CE.&lt;ref&gt;See, e.g., Alfredo M. Rabello, The Ban on Circumcision as a Cause of Bar Kokhba's Rebellion, 29 ISRAEL L. REV. 176 (1995) (Arguing that the Bar Kokhba rebellion against Roman rule was primarily motivated by the superimposition of foreign religious standards, rather than by some important notion of independence or sovereignty).&lt;/ref&gt; The Roman historian [[Cassius Dio]], however, made no mention of such a law, and blamed the Jewish uprising instead on Hadrian's decision to rebuild [[Jerusalem]] as [[Aelia Capitolina]], a city dedicated to [[Jupiter (god)|Jupiter]].

[[Antoninus Pius]] permitted Jews to circumcise their own sons. However, he forbade the circumcision of non-Jews that were either foreign-slaves or non-Jewish members of the household, contrary to {{bibleverse||Genesis|17:12|HE}} He also made it illegal for a man to convert to Judaism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://bmcr.brynmawr.edu/2004/2004-03-29.html|title=Review of: Jews and Gentiles in the Holy Land in the Days of the Second Temple, the Mishna and the Talmud|first=Matthew|last=Kraus|date=29 March 2004|journal=Bryn Mawr Classical Review}}&lt;/ref&gt; Antoninus Pius exempted the Egyptian priesthood from the otherwise universal ban on circumcision.

=== Soviet Union ===
Before [[glasnost]], according to an article in [[The Jewish Press]], Jewish ritual circumcision was forbidden in the [[Soviet Union|USSR]].&lt;ref&gt;Barbara Oka, [http://www.russianjewry.org/about/media/jp9.php &quot;Soviet Jews Of All Ages Seek Circumcision&quot;], ''The Jewish Press'', 14 March 1991.&lt;/ref&gt; However, David E. Fishman, professor of Jewish History at the [[Jewish Theological Seminary of America]], states that, whereas the ''[[Cheder|heder]]'' and ''[[yeshiva]]'', the organs of Jewish education, &quot;were banned by virtue of the law separating church and school, and subjected to tough police and administrative actions,&quot; circumcision was not proscribed by law or suppressed by executive measures.&lt;ref&gt;David E. Fishman, &quot;Judaism in the USSR, 1917–1930: The Fate of Religious Education,&quot; in: Yaacov Ro'i, ed., ''Jews and Jewish Life in Russia and the Soviet Union'' (Cummings Center Series; London: Cass, 1995), 251–262; pp. 251–252.&lt;/ref&gt;
Jehoshua A. Gilboa writes that while circumcision was not officially or explicitly banned, pressure was exerted to make it difficult. ''[[Mohel]]s'' in particular were concerned that they could be punished for any health issue that might develop, even if it arose some time after the circumcision.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;There was no official prohibition of circumcision and, on the whole, even the propaganda attacks on it were relatively restrained, apparently out of consideration for the presence of many millions of Moslems [...] in the Soviet Union. But at the same time numerous pressures were exerted to make observance of this precept [i.e., circumcision] difficult. Needless to say, Jewish members of the [[Communist Party of the Soviet Union|Communist Party]] were in an embarrassing situation when they personally faced the question whether to circumcise their sons [...] And the uncertainty weighed heaviest on the ''mohalim'' themselves [...] Any health problem developing in the baby some time after circumcision could serve to incriminate the ''mohel''. It is easy to imagine, for example, the impact of news items on the death of children because of [...] circumcision (and the punishments imposed on ''mohalim''), even if there were no explicit legal bans on circumcision.&quot; Jehoshua A. Gilboa, ''A Language Silenced: The Suppression of Hebrew Literature and Culture in the Soviet Union'' (London: Associated University Press, 1982), pp. 34–35.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Albania ===
In 1967 all religion in Communist Albania was banned, along with the practice of circumcision. The practice was driven underground and many boys were secretly circumcised.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/?id=mnTCPH_ZGW4C&amp;pg=PA99&amp;dq=young+boys+were+secretly+circumcised#v=onepage&amp;q=young%20boys%20were%20secretly%20circumcised&amp;f=false|title=Albania: From Anarchy to a Balkan Identity|last=Vickers|first=Miranda|last2=Pettifer|first2=James|date=1997|publisher=Hurst|isbn=9781850652908|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Modern law ==
{{infobox
|image={{Graph:Map | scale = 50 | colorScale = category10 | domainMin = 0 | domainMax = 100 | AF=98.1 | AL=31.5 | DZ=97.9 | AS=95 | AD=1.1 | AO=96.1 | AI=0.3 | AG=0.6 | AR=2.9 | AM=0.1 | AW=0.46 | AU=16.1 | AT=5.8 | AZ=96.9 | BS=0.2 | BH=81.2 | BD=93.2 | BB=0.9 | BY=0.32 | BE=22.6 | BZ=0.1 | BJ=95.5 | BM=0.8 | BT=1 | BO=0.11 | BA=41.6 | BW=15.1 | BR=1.3 | VG=1.2 | BN=51.9 | BG=13.4 | BF=85.1 | BI=19.3 | CV=0.1 | KH=2.1 | CM=94.9 | CA=31.9 | KY=0.2 | CF=63 | TD=96.5 | CL=0.2 | CN=14 | CX=0.1 | CC=95 | CO=1.5 | KM=100 | CD=95.2 | CG=100 | CK=95 | CR=0.15 | CI=94 | HR=1.34 | CU=0.11 | CW=0.07 | CY=22.7 | CZ=0.14 | DK=5.3 | DJ=96.5 | DM=0.2 | DO=12.7 | EC=0.11 | EG=94.7 | SV=0.1 | GQ=87 | ER=97.2 | EE=0.25 | ET=94.7 | FK=0.1 | FO=0.1 | FJ=55 | FI=3 | FR=14 | PF=78 | GA=100 | GM=94.5 | PS=99.9 | GE=10.6 | DE=10.9 | GH=94.2 | GI=6 | GR=4.7 | GL=0.1 | GD=0.3 | GU=95 | GT=2.9 | GG=0.1 | GN=98.5 | GW=93.3 | GY=12.1 | HT=8.4 | VA=0.1 | HN=0.1 | HK=28 | HU=0.8 | IS=0.1 | IN=15.7 | ID=92.5 | IR=99.7 | IQ=98.9 | IE=0.9 | IM=0.2 | IL=91.7 | IT=2.6 | JM=14 | JP=9 | JE=0.1 | JO=98.8 | KZ=56.4 | KE=91 | KI=0.1 | KP=0.1 | KR=22.2 | KOSOVO=91.7 | KW=86.4 | KG=91.9 | LA=0.1 | LV=0.4 | LB=59.7 | LS=70.4 | LR=99.1 | LY=96.6 | LI=4.8 | LT=0.2 | LU=2.4 | MO=0.1 | MK=33.9 | MG=95.5 | MW=30 | MY=61.4 | MV=98.4 | ML=97.8 | MT=0.3 | MH=0.1 | MR=99.2 | MU=16.6 | MX=15.4 | FM=0.1 | MD=0.5 | MC=0.5 | MN=4.4 | ME=18.5 | MS=0.1 | MA=99.9 | MZ=64.5 | MM=3.9 | NA=31.4 | NR=95 | NP=4.2 | NL=5.7 | NC=50 | NZ=10 | NI=0.1 | NE=99.4 | NG=98.9 | NU=95 | NF=0.1 | MP=90 | NO=3 | OM=87.7 | PK=96.4 | PW=95 | PA=1 | PG=10.1 | PY=0.1 | PE=3.7 | PH=91.7 | PN=0.1 | PL=0.1 | PT=0.6 | PR=0.14 | QA=77.5 | RO=0.3 | RU=11.8 | RW=11.9 | BL=0.1 | SH=0.1 | KN=0.3 | LC=0.1 | MF=0.1 | PM=0.2 | VC=1.7 | WS=95 | SM=0.1 | ST=0.1 | SA=97.1 | SN=98.2 | RS=3.7 | SC=1.1 | SL=99.4 | SG=14.9 | SX=0.1 | SK=0.2 | SI=8.5 | SB=95 | SO=93.5 | ZA=45.5 | SS=23.6 | ES=6.6 | LK=8.5 | SD=39.4 | SR=15.9 | SJ=0.1 | SZ=8.6 | SE=5.1 | CH=5.9 | SY=92.8 | TW=8.3 | TJ=99 | TZ=80.4 | TH=11.9 | TL=6.9 | TG=98.7 | TK=95 | TO=95 | TT=5.8 | TN=99.8 | TR=98.6 | TM=93.4 | TC=0.1 | TV=95 | UG=33.2 | UA=2.2 | AE=76 | GB=3.1 | US=71.2 | UY=0.62 | UZ=96.5 | VU=95 | VE=0.3 | VN=0.2 | VI=0.6 | WF=0.1 | EH=99.6 | YE=99 | ZM=18.3 | ZW=14.3 }}
|image2={{Graph:Map | scale = 0 | colorScale = category10 | domainMin = 0 | domainMax = 100 | legend = yes | AF=99 }}
|caption2=[[List of countries by prevalence of genital cutting|Prevalence of circumcision by country]] among boys younger than 15 years-old}}

Whereas child custody regulations have been applied to cases involving circumcision, there seems to be no state which currently unequivocally bans infant male circumcision for non-therapeutic reasons, albeit the legality of such circumcision is disputed in some legislations.

The present table provides a non-exhaustive overview comparing legal restrictions and requirements on non-therapeutic infant circumcision in several countries. Some countries require one or both parents to consent to the operation; some of these (Finland,&lt;ref name=&quot;Denniston&quot;/&gt; United Kingdom&lt;ref name=&quot;Exeter&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC2207&quot;/&gt;) have experienced legal battles between parents when one of them had their son's circumcision carried out or planned without the other's consent. Some countries require the procedure to be performed by or supervised by a qualified physician (or a qualified nurse in Sweden&lt;ref name=&quot;Denniston&quot;/&gt;), and with (local) [[anaesthesia]] applied to the boy or man.
{{clear}}
{| class=&quot;sortable wikitable&quot; style=&quot;margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;&quot;
|+ '''Legal restrictions and requirements on non-therapeutic infant circumcision by country'''
! Country
! Parental consent
! Anaesthesia
! Qualified physician
! Payment
! ! class=&quot;unsortable&quot;| Notes
|-
| {{flagg|pspew|al=c|Belgium|plink=#Belgium}}
|
|
|
| Taxpayers&lt;ref name=&quot;Block&quot;/&gt;
| Health Minister rejected Bioethics Advisory Committee's recommended ban&lt;ref name=&quot;Block&quot;/&gt;
|-
| {{flagg|pspew|al=c|Denmark|plink=#Denmark}}
| 
|
|
| Parents&lt;ref name=&quot;Denniston&quot;/&gt;
|
|-
| {{flagg|pspew|al=c|Finland|plink=#Finland}}
| Both parents&lt;ref name=&quot;Denniston&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |last1=Denniston |first1=George C. |last2=Hodges |first2=Frederick Mansfield |last3=Milos |first3=Marilyn Fayre |authorlink3=Marilyn Milos |date=2008 |title=Circumcision and Human Rights |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=MNRJ0YuLNBUC&amp;pg=PA235 |location= |publisher=[[Springer Science+Business Media]] |pages=234–235 |isbn=9781402091674 |accessdate=27 June 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|
|
| Parents&lt;ref name=&quot;Denniston&quot;/&gt;
|
|-
| {{flagg|pspew|al=c|France|plink=#France}} 
| Both parents&lt;ref name=&quot;Denniston&quot;/&gt;
|
|
| Parents&lt;ref name=&quot;Denniston&quot;/&gt;
|
|- 
| {{flagg|pspew|al=c|Germany|plink=#Germany}}
|
|
|
| Parents&lt;ref name=&quot;Denniston&quot;/&gt;
|
|-
| {{flagg|pspew|al=c|Israel|plink=#Israel}}
| 
| 
| Performing or supervising&lt;ref name=&quot;WHO&quot;/&gt;
|
| Under six months, otherwise medical reason needed&lt;ref name=&quot;WHO&quot;/&gt;
|-
| {{flagg|pspew|al=c|Italy|plink=#Italy}}
|
|
|
| Parents&lt;ref name=&quot;Denniston&quot;/&gt;
|
|-
| {{flagg|pspew|al=c|Netherlands|plink=#Netherlands}}
|
|
|
| Parents&lt;ref name=&quot;Denniston&quot;/&gt;
|
|-
| {{flagg|pspew|al=c|Norway|plink=#Norway}}
| 
| Required&lt;ref name=&quot;NorwayLocal&quot;/&gt;
| Supervising&lt;ref name=&quot;NorwayLocal&quot;/&gt;
| Parents&lt;ref name=&quot;Denniston&quot;/&gt;
| Parents and clerics need to wait outside the [[Operating theater|operating room]]&lt;ref name=&quot;NorwayLocal&quot;/&gt;
|-
| {{flagg|pspew|al=c|Saudi Arabia|plink=#Saudi Arabia}}
| 
| 
| Performing&lt;ref name=&quot;WHO&quot;/&gt;
|
| 
|-
| {{flagg|pspew|al=c|South Africa|plink=#South Africa}}
| 
| 
| Performing&lt;ref name=&quot;WHO&quot;/&gt;
|
| 
|-
| {{flagg|pspew|al=c|Spain|plink=#Spain}}
|
|
|
| Parents&lt;ref name=&quot;Denniston&quot;/&gt;
|
|-
| {{flagg|pspew|al=c|Sweden|plink=#Sweden}}
|
| Required&lt;ref name=&quot;Denniston&quot;/&gt;
| Supervising&lt;ref name=&quot;Denniston&quot;/&gt;
| Parents&lt;ref name=&quot;Denniston&quot;/&gt;
| Under two months&lt;ref name=&quot;Denniston&quot;/&gt;
|-
| {{flagg|pspew|al=c|United Kingdom|plink=#United Kingdom}}
| Both parents&lt;ref name=&quot;WHO&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.who.int/hiv/pub/malecircumcision/neonatal_child_MC_UNAIDS.pdf |title=Neonatal and child male circumcision: a global review |author=Helen Weiss|display-authors=et al |work=UNAIDS |publisher=[[World Health Organization]] |date=April 2010 |accessdate=27 June 2018}} {{ISBN|9789291738557}}.&lt;/ref&gt;
|
|
| Parents&lt;ref name=&quot;Denniston&quot;/&gt;
| In only 6.2% of studied cases both parents consented&lt;ref name=&quot;WHO&quot;/&gt;
|}

=== Australia ===
The [[Royal Australasian College of Physicians|Royal Australasian College of Physicians (RACP)]] finds that routine infant circumcision is not warranted in [[Australia]] and [[New Zealand]] and that, since circumcision involves physical, physicians ought to raise and consider with parents and considered the option of leaving circumcision until later, when the boy is old enough to make a decision for himself: {{quote | After reviewing the currently available evidence, the [[Royal Australasian College of Physicians|RACP]] believes that the frequency of diseases modifiable by circumcision, the level of protection offered by circumcision and the complication rates of circumcision do not warrant routine infant circumcision in Australia and New Zealand. … Since circumcision involves physical risks which are undertaken for the sake of psychosocial benefits or debatable medical benefit to the child, … The option of leaving circumcision until later, when the boy is old enough to make a decision for himself does need to be raised with parents and considered.| author = {{Flagicon|AUS}} [[Royal Australasian College of Physicians]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Circumcision of infant males|last=|first=|publisher=[[Royal Australasian College of Physicians]]|year=2010|isbn=|location=Sydney, Australia|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

In 1993, a non-binding research paper of the [[Queensland Law Reform Commission]] (''Circumcision of Male Infants'') concluded that &quot;On a strict interpretation of the assault provisions of the [[Queensland]] Criminal Code, routine circumcision of a male infant could be regarded as a criminal act&quot;, and that doctors who perform circumcision on male infants may be liable to civil claims by that child at a later date.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cirp.org/library/legal/QLRC/|title=QLRC: Circumcision of Male Infants|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; No prosecutions have occurred in Queensland, and circumcisions continue to be performed.

In 1999, a [[Perth]] man won A$360,000 in damages after a doctor admitted he botched a circumcision operation at birth which left the man with a badly deformed penis.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cirp.org/news/perth1/|title=Man Receives $360,000 Compensation for Childhood Circumcision|publisher=cirp.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2002, Queensland police charged a father with grievous bodily harm for having his two sons, then aged nine and five, circumcised without the knowledge and against the wishes of the mother. The mother and father were in a family court dispute. The charges were dropped when the police prosecutor revealed that he did not have all family court paperwork in court and the magistrate refused to grant an adjournment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cirp.org/news/thesundaymail08-11-02/|title=Mother's Fury as Boys Circumcised|publisher=cirp.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Cosmetic circumcision for newborn males is currently banned in all Australian public hospitals, South Australia being the last state to adopt the ban in 2007; the procedure was not forbidden from being performed in private hospitals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Pengelley|first=J|title=SA to ban most circumcisions in state hospitals|url=http://www.news.com.au/national/sa-to-ban-most-circumcisions-in-state-hospitals/story-e6frfkvr-1111114853797|accessdate=7 April 2012|newspaper=The Advertiser|date=12 November 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.theaustralian.news.com.au/story/0,25197,22744548-5006787,00.html |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071112225609/http://www.theaustralian.news.com.au/story/0%2C25197%2C22744548-5006787%2C00.html |url-status=dead |archive-date=12 November 2007 |title=Public hospitals ban circumcision |date=12 November 2007 |newspaper=The Australian |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; In the same year, the Tasmanian President of the [[Australian Medical Association]], Haydn Walters, stated that they would support a call to ban circumcision for non-medical, non-religious reasons.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.abc.net.au/news/stories/2007/12/09/2113665.htm |title=Doctors back call for circumcision ban |date=9 December 2007 |publisher=ABC News}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2009, the Tasmanian Law Reform Institute released its Issues Paper investigating the law relating to male circumcision in Tasmania, it &quot;highlights the uncertainty in relation to whether doctors can legally perform circumcision on infant males&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.law.utas.edu.au/reform/malecircumcision.htm |title=Male circumcision |publisher=Tasmanian Law Reform Institute |access-date=2 June 2009 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090606212132/http://www.law.utas.edu.au/reform/malecircumcision.htm |archive-date=6 June 2009 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Tasmania Law Reform Institute released its recommendations for reform of Tasmanian law relative to male circumcision on 21 August 2012.&lt;ref&gt;Tasmanian Law Reform Institute.''[http://www.law.utas.edu.au/reform/documents/CircumcisionFinal.pdf Non Therapeutic Male Circumcision] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120831193618/http://www.law.utas.edu.au/reform/documents/CircumcisionFinal.pdf |date=31 August 2012 }}''. Report No. 17, August 2012&lt;/ref&gt; The report makes fourteen recommendations for reform of Tasmanian law relative to male circumcision.&lt;ref&gt;Tasmanian Law Reform Institute. ''[https://theconversation.edu.au/tasmanian-report-calls-for-groundbreaking-reform-of-circumcision-law-9105 Non Therapeutic Male Circumcision]''. Report No. 17, August 2012&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Belgium ===
The [https://www.health.belgium.be/en/belgian-advisory-committee-bioethics Belgian Advisory Committee on Bioethics] finds that circumcision is a radical operation, and that physical integrity of the child takes precedence over parents' belief systems: {{quote | As circumcision is irreversible and therefore a radical operation, we find the physical integrity of the child takes precedence over the belief system of the parents.| author = {{Flagicon|Belgium}} [https://www.health.belgium.be/en/belgian-advisory-committee-bioethics Belgian Advisory Committee on Bioethics]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.flanderstoday.eu/current-affairs/ethics-committee-rules-against-infant-circumcision|title=Ethics committee rules against infant circumcision {{!}} Flanders Today|website=www.flanderstoday.eu|access-date=2019-10-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.health.belgium.be/en/opinion-no-70-ethical-aspects-nonmedical-circumcision|title=Opinion no. 70 - ethical aspects of nonmedical circumcision|date=2017-11-23|website=FPS Public Health|language=en|access-date=2019-10-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

In 2012, ''[[Le Soir]]'' reported a 21% increase in the amount of circumcisions in [[Belgium]] from 2006 and 2011. In the previous 25 years, one in three Belgian-born boys had allegedly been circumcised. A questionnaire to hospitals in [[Wallonia]] and [[Brussels]] showed that about 80 to 90% of the procedures had religious or cultural motives. The Ministry of Health stressed the importance of safe circumstances, physicians warned that 'no surgical procedure is without risk' and that circumcision was 'not a necessary procedure'.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.nieuwsblad.be/cnt/dmf20120810_003 |title=Rituele besnijdenis in opmars in België |work=Het Nieuwsblad |date=10 August 2012 |accessdate=29 June 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2017, it was estimated that about 15% of Belgian men were circumcised. The [[Incidence (epidemiology)|incidence]] has been gradually rising: in 2002, about 17,800 boys or men underwent circumcision, which increased to almost 26,200 in 2016. The expenses of undergoing circumcision are covered by the National Institute for Disease and Disability Insurance (RIZIV/INAMI), costing about 2.7 million euros in 2016. After inquiries were submitted to the Belgian Bioethics Advisory Committee in early 2014, an ethics commission was set up to review the morality of covering the costs of medically unnecessary surgery through taxpayer money, especially considering that many taxpayers regard the practice as immoral. By July 2017, the commission reportedly reached consensus on discontinuing the financial coverage of non-medical circumcision, but was still debating whether to advise the government to institute a total ban of the practice.&lt;ref name=&quot;Vankersschaever&quot;&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://www.standaard.be/cnt/dmf20170630_02951236 |title=Ethisch comité stelt terugbetaling rituele besnijdenis in vraag |author=Sarah Vankersschaever |work=De Standaard |date=1 July 2017 |accessdate=25 June 2018 |language=nl}}&lt;/ref&gt; The commission's final (non-binding) recommendation, presented on 19 September 2017, was to cease public funding for non-medical circumcision, and to not circumcise anyone underage until they can consent or reject the procedure after being properly informed. This was in line with the 1990 [[Convention on the Rights of the Child]], and mirrors the 2013 non-binding [[Parliamentary Assembly of the Council of Europe]]'s resolution against underage non-therapeutic circumcision.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://www.standaard.be/cnt/dmf20170919_03082876 |title=Lichaam belangrijker dan geloof: ritueel besnijden is aantasting fysieke integriteit |author=Sarah Vankersschaever |work=De Standaard |date=20 September 2017 |accessdate=28 June 2018 |language=nl}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, Health Minister [[Maggie De Block]] rejected the commission's advice, arguing the RIZIV 'cannot know whether there is a medical motive or not' when parents request a circumcision, and when they are denied a professional procedure, chances are parents will have a non-expert perform it, leading to worse results for the children. The Health Minister's response was received with mixed reactions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Block&quot;&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://www.standaard.be/cnt/dmf20170920_03084394 |title=De Block blijft besnijdenis terugbetalen |author=Eveline Vergauwen |work=De Standaard |date=21 September 2017 |accessdate=28 June 2018 |language=nl}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Canada ===

The [[Canadian Paediatric Society]] doesn't recommend routine circumcision, finding that medical necessity has not been clearly established, and as such, that it should be deferred until the individual concerned is able to make his own choices: {{quote | The [[Canadian Paediatric Society|CPS]] does not recommend the routine circumcision of every newborn male. … With newborn circumcision, medical necessity has not been clearly established. … In cases in which medical necessity is not established or a proposed treatment is based on personal preference, interventions should be deferred until the individual concerned is able to make their own choices.| author = {{Flagicon|Canada}} [[Canadian Paediatric Society]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.cps.ca/en/documents/position/circumcision|title=Newborn male circumcision {{!}} Canadian Paediatric Society|last=Society|first=Canadian Paediatric|website=www.cps.ca|language=en|access-date=2019-10-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

According to the College of Physicians and Surgeons of British Columbia:

::&quot;To date, the legality of infant male circumcision has not been tested in the Courts. It is thus assumed to be legal if it is performed competently, in the child’s best interest, and after valid consent has been obtained.&quot;

::&quot;At all times the physician must perform the procedure with competence and at all times, the parent and physician must act in the best interests of the child. Signed parental consent for any treatment is assumed to be valid if the parent understands the nature of the procedure and its associated risks and benefits. However, proxy consent by parents is now being questioned. Many believe it should be limited to consent for diagnosis and treatment of medical conditions, and that it is not relevant for non-therapeutic procedures.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;cpsbc&quot;&gt;[https://www.cpsbc.ca/files/u6/Circumcision-Infant-Male.pdf Circumcision (Infant Male)] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120215182208/https://www.cpsbc.ca/files/u6/Circumcision-Infant-Male.pdf |date=15 February 2012 }} In: ''Professional Standards and Guidelines''. Vancouver, College of Physicians and Surgeons of British Columbia, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Denmark ===
The [[Danish Medical Association]] finds that circumcision ought to be an informed, personal choice, in line with individual's right to self-determination, and thus that parents have no right to make this decision for their children, leaving up to the individual when he's old enough to make it: {{quote |To be circumcised should be an informed, personal choice. It is most consistent with the individual’s right to self-determination that parents not be allowed to make this decision but that it is left up to the individual when he has come of age.| author = {{Flagicon|Denmark}} [[Danish Medical Association]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.thelocal.dk/20161205/danish-doctors-come-out-against-circumcision|title=Danish doctors come out against circumcision|date=2016-12-05|website=www.thelocal.dk|language=en-GB|access-date=2019-10-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

A January 2018 survey by polling company Megafon for the television network TV2 showed that 83% of Danish citizens favoured a ban on circumcising boys. A citizens' [[initiative]], put forward by [[Intact Denmark]], demanding a minimum age of 18 for circumcision to protect “children’s fundamental rights” reached 50,000 signatures on 1 June 2018, forcing the [[Folketing|Danish Parliament]] to consider it. It is unsure whether the proposal will gain a majority.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2018/06/02/world/europe/denmark-circumcision.html |title=Denmark Talks (Reluctantly) About a Ban on Circumcising Boys |author=Martin Selsoe Sorensen |work=The New York Times |date=2 June 2018 |accessdate=24 June 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/europe/denmark-boyhood-circumcision-petition-danish-parliament-debate-a8381366.html |title=Danish parliament to consider becoming first country to ban circumcision of boys |author=Mattha Busby |work=The Independent |date=3 June 2018 |accessdate=24 June 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; In September 2018, the Parliament's justice administration (Lovsekretariat) completed its review of the petition, finding it not to be in breach of the [[Danish Constitution]], and therefore valid for parliamentary consideration.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.thelocal.dk/20180927/danish-parliament-to-consider-ban-on-circumcision-in-october-report |title=Danish parliament to consider ban on circumcision: report |author= |work=The Local Denmark |date=27 September 2018 |accessdate=7 August 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

At the first parliamentary reading in November 23, 2018, spokesmen for [[Dansk Folkeparti|DF]], [[Venstre (Denmark)|V]], [[Socialdemokraterne|S]] and [[Radikale Venstre|RV]] reported that their parties would vote against the proposal. [[Enhedslisten|EL]] and [[Socialistisk Folkeparti|SF]] were supportive of a ban, but took issue with details of the proposal, particularly the legalization of circumcision of women of age (i.e., 18 years old). [[Liberal Alliance (Denmark)|LA]], [[Konservative Folkeparti|KF]] and [[Alternativet|ALT]] did not make a collective decision, leaving their members to decide for themselves.&lt;ref name=&quot;1beh&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.ft.dk/samling/20181/beslutningsforslag/B9/BEH1-25/forhandling.htm#t68924C542233449782137DDB3807CA3Atab1|title= B 9 Forslag til folketingsbeslutning om indførelse af 18-årsmindstealder for omskæring af raske børn (borgerforslag).|website=ft.dk|access-date=4 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

National security was cited as an argument against. For example, [[Minister of Health (Denmark)|Minister of Health]] [[Ellen Trane Nørby]], listed &quot;foreign-political implications as well as consequences of security, among other things in relation to the stationed soldiers of Denmark&quot; as some of the cabinet's reasons for opposing the proposal.&lt;ref name=&quot;1beh&quot;/&gt; When asked whether he felt that national concerns outweighed child rights, [[Socialdemokraterne]] spokesman [[Flemming Møller Mortensen]] said&lt;ref name=&quot;1beh&quot;/&gt;
{{quote|Everyone who was present at the consultation (''samråd'') in the Health Committee - it was a closed committee - would have received an understanding for the insecurity that may be generated to Danes and to Danish interests. So this is not an either-or situation; both the well-being of the child and the security of the nation are important.|author=[[Flemming Møller Mortensen]]}}
Venstre spokesman [[Jane Heitmann]] similarly reported concerns in her party that such a ban &quot;could be abused to misrepresent Denmark and have consequences for the international reputation of Denmark and for Danes living abroad. We do not wish to take that risk&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;1beh&quot;/&gt;

In November 2018, the [[Venstre (Denmark)|Venstre]] party and the [[Danish People's Party]] criticised the current wording of the proposal, raising concerns that it could legalise female genital mutilation, while the [[Ministry of Health (Denmark)|Ministry of Health]] denied Intact Denmark's claim that current legislation does not comply with the UN Convention on the Rights of the Child.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.thelocal.dk/20181116/petition-for-danish-circumcision-ban-loses-political-support |title=Petition for Danish circumcision ban loses political support |author=Ester Rose Wadsworth |work=The Local Denmark |date=16 November 2018 |accessdate=7 August 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

;In favour of the proposed ban (November 2018)
* [[Enhedslisten]]&lt;ref name=&quot;1beh&quot;/&gt;
* [[Socialistisk Folkeparti]]&lt;ref name=&quot;1beh&quot;/&gt;

;Against the proposed ban (November 2018)
* [[Dansk Folkeparti]]&lt;ref name=&quot;1beh&quot;/&gt;
* [[Venstre (Denmark)|Venstre]]&lt;ref name=&quot;1beh&quot;/&gt;
* [[Socialdemokraterne]]&lt;ref name=&quot;1beh&quot;/&gt;
* [[Radikale Venstre]]&lt;ref name=&quot;1beh&quot;/&gt;

;Neutral on the proposed ban (November 2018)
* [[Liberal Alliance (Denmark)|Liberal Alliance]]&lt;ref name=&quot;1beh&quot;/&gt;
* [[Konservative Folkeparti]]&lt;ref name=&quot;1beh&quot;/&gt;
* [[Alternativet]]&lt;ref name=&quot;1beh&quot;/&gt;

=== European Union and Council of Europe ===
A study commissioned by the [[European Parliament Committee on Civil Liberties, Justice and Home Affairs]] published in February 2013 stated that &quot;Male circumcision for non-therapeutic reasons appears to be practiced with relative
regularity and frequency throughout Europe,&quot; and said it was &quot;the only scenario, among the topics discussed in the present chapter, in which the outcome of the balancing between the right to physical integrity and religious freedom is in favour of the latter.&quot; The study recommended that &quot;the best interests of children should be paramount, while acknowledging the relevance of this practice for Muslims and Jews. Member States should ensure that circumcision of underage children is performed according to the medical profession’s art and under conditions that do not put the health of minors at risk. The introduction of regulations by the Member States in order to set the conditions and the
appropriate medical training for those called to perform it is warranted.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.europarl.europa.eu/RegData/etudes/etudes/join/2013/474399/IPOL-LIBE_ET(2013)474399_EN.pdf |title=Religious practice and observance in the EU Member States |author=Arnaiz|display-authors=et al |publisher=[[Secretariat of the European Parliament#Internal Policies|Directorate-General for Internal Policies]] |date=February 2013 |accessdate=25 February 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 1 October 2013, the [[Parliamentary Assembly of the Council of Europe]] adopted a non-binding resolution in which they state they are &quot;particularly worried about a category of violation of the physical integrity of children,&quot; and included in this category &quot;circumcision of young boys for religious reasons.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Parliamentary Assembly, Council of Europe. [http://assembly.coe.int/nw/xml/XRef/X2H-Xref-ViewPDF.asp?FileID=20174&amp;lang=en Children's Right to Physical Integrity], Resolution 1952., Adopted at Strasbourg, Tuesday, 1 October 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; On 7 October, [[Israel]]'s president [[Shimon Peres]] wrote a personal missive to the [[Secretary General of the Council of Europe]], [[Thorbjørn Jagland]], to stop the ban, arguing: &quot;The Jewish communities across Europe would be greatly afflicted to see their cultural and religious freedom impeded upon by the Council of Europe, an institution devoted to the protection of these very rights.&quot; Two days later, Jagland clarified that the resolution was non-binding and that “Nothing in the body of our legally binding standards would lead us to put on equal footing the issue of female genital mutilation and the circumcision of young boys for religious reasons.”&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.timesofisrael.com/circumcision-wont-be-banned-in-europe-officials-say/ |title=Circumcision won't be banned in Europe, officials say |author=Lazar Berman and Elhanan Miller |work=Times of Israel |date=9 October 2013 |accessdate=25 February 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As of February 2018, no European country has a ban on male circumcision, but [[Iceland]] was planning to become the first to outlaw the practice for non-medical reasons.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sherwood&quot;&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.theguardian.com/society/2018/feb/18/iceland-ban-male-circumcision-first-european-country |title=Iceland law to outlaw male circumcision sparks row over religious freedom |author=Harriet Sherwood |work=The Guardian |date=18 February 2018 |accessdate=25 February 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Finland===
The [https://www.tasa-arvo.fi/ Finnish Ombudsman for Equality] finds that circumcising young boys without a medical reason is legally highly questionable, The Finnish Supreme Court found that non-therapeutic circumcision of boys is assault, and the Finnish Ombudsman for Children proposed that Finland should ban non-therapeutic circumcision of young boys: {{quote | The Deputy Ombudsman took the view that circumcising young boys, who are unable to give their consent, without a medical reason is highly questionable from a legal standpoint. … On 31 March 2016, the Supreme Court adopted two decisions that complement a previous precedent in which the Court found that the non-medical circumcision of boys constitutes an assault offence but is not punishable when it is considered to be in the best interests of the child. … In 2013, the Nordic Ombudsmen for Children adopted a joint statement stating that boys should be given the chance to decide for themselves whether or not they want to be circumcised. In 2015, the Finnish Ombudsman for Children Tuomas Kurttila proposed that Finland should enact an act prohibiting the non-medical circumcision of young boys.| author = {{Flagicon|Finland}} [https://www.tasa-arvo.fi/ Finnish Ombudsman for Equality]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.tasa-arvo.fi/web/en/-/circumcision-of-boys-tas-143-2016-issued-on-23-august-2016-|archive-url=https://archive.today/20191016053752/https://www.tasa-arvo.fi/web/en/-/circumcision-of-boys-tas-143-2016-issued-on-23-august-2016-|url-status=dead|archive-date=2019-10-16|title=Circumcision of boys (TAS 143/2016, issued on 23 August 2016) - State…|date=2019-10-16|website=archive.fo|access-date=2019-10-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

In August 2006, a Finnish court ruled that the circumcision of a four-year-old boy arranged by his mother, who is Muslim, to be an illegal assault. The boy's father, who had not been consulted, reported the incident to the police.  A local prosecutor stated that the prohibition of circumcision is not gender-specific in Finnish law.  A lawyer for the Ministry of Social Affairs and Health stated that there is neither legislation nor prohibition on male circumcision, and that &quot;the operations have been performed on the basis of common law.&quot;  The case was appealed&lt;ref name=&quot;Helsingin Sanomat&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Court rules circumcision of four-year-old boy illegal |url=http://www.hs.fi/english/article/Court+rules+circumcision+of+four-year-old+boy+illegal/1135220958830}}&lt;/ref&gt; and in October 2008 the Finnish Supreme Court ruled that the circumcision, &quot;carried out for religious and social reasons and in a medical manner, did not have the earmarks of a criminal offence. It pointed out in its ruling that the circumcision of Muslim boys is an established tradition and an integral part of the identity of Muslim men&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://yle.fi/news/id104896.html|title=Supreme Court: Male Circumcision Not A Crime|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2008, the Finnish government was reported to be considering a new law to legalise circumcision if the practitioner is a doctor and if the child consents.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.yle.fi/news/id97605.html
|title=Finland Considers Legalising Male Circumcision|accessdate=17 September 2007
|date=2 August 2008
|publisher=Ylesiradio}}&lt;/ref&gt; In December 2011, Helsinki District Court said that the Supreme Court's decision does not mean that circumcision is legal for any non-medical reasons.&lt;ref name=HS&gt;[http://www.hs.fi/english/article/Circumcision+assault+case+brings+fine+%E2%80%93+conviction+but+no+punishment+for+parents/1135270121491 Circumcision assault case brings fine – conviction but no punishment for parents], Helsingin Sanomat, HS.fi 2 January 2012&lt;/ref&gt; The court referred to the Convention on Human rights and Biomedicine of the Council of Europe, which was ratified in Finland in 2010.&lt;ref name=HS/&gt;

In February 2010, a Jewish couple were fined for causing bodily harm to their then infant son who was circumcised in 2008 by a [[mohel]] brought in from the UK. Normal procedure for persons of Jewish faith in Finland is to have a locally certified mohel who works in Finnish healthcare perform the operation. In the 2008 case, the infant was not anesthetized and developed complications that required immediate hospital care. The parents were ordered to pay 1500 euros in damages to their child.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.yle.fi/uutiset/news/2010/02/parents_ordered_to_pay_circumcised_son_1500_euros_1479554.html
|title=Parents Ordered to Pay Circumcised Son 1,500 Euros|accessdate=24 February 2010
|date=24 February 2010
|publisher=Finnish Broadcasting Corporation}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Germany ===

The [https://www.bvkj.de German Association of Pediatricians (BVKJ)] finds no medical reason for non-therapeutic circumcision and that the [[American Academy of Pediatrics|AAP]] (2012) recommendation scientifically unsustainable, and that boys should have the same constitutional legal right to physical integrity as girls: {{quote | From a medical point of view, there is no reason to remove the intact foreskin of underage and non-consenting boys. … The tip of the foreskin is richly supplied with blood by important vascular structures. The foreskin serves as a connecting channel for numerous important veins. Circumcision can contribute to erectile dysfunction by destroying these blood lines. Their removal can, as the accounts of many sufferers show, lead to considerable restrictions on the sexual experience and mental stress. The frequently cited AAP opinion (DOI: 10.1542 / peds.2012-1989 Pediatrics &quot;originally published online Aug. 27, 2012) contradicts earlier statements by the same organization without being able to invoke new research findings. This AAP opinion is now considered scientifically unsustainable by almost all other pediatric societies and associations in the world. … The WHO recommendation on prophylactic circumcision also applies only to sexually mature sexually active men in low-hygiene countries and cannot be used as a basis for the prophylactic circumcision underage boys. … Worldwide, no medical professional society, not even the AAP, sees such a significant advantage in the general circumcision of young boys that it generally recommends them. … Religious regulations must not influence doctors in their care for their patients - and underage children deserve our very special care here. According to our sense of justice, boys have the same constitutional legal right to physical integrity as girls; they must not be disadvantaged because of their gender (Article 3 of the Basic Law). Parental rights and religious freedom end where the physical integrity of a child who is under the age of consent is not affected (Article 2 of the Basic Law) without a clear medical indication.| author = {{Flagicon|Germany}} [https://www.bvkj.de/ German Association of Paediatricians]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.bvkj.de/bvkj-news/pressemitteilungen/news/article/stellungnahme-drmed-wolfram-hartmann-praesident-des-berufsverbands-der-kinder-und-jugendaerzte/|title=Stellungnahme Dr.med. Wolfram Hartmann, Präsident des Berufsverbands der Kinder- und Jugendärzte, zur Anhörung am 26. November 2012 zum Gesetzentwurf der Bundesregierung zur Beschneidung: www.bvkj.de|website=www.bvkj.de|language=de|access-date=2019-10-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

In October 2006, a Turkish national who performed ritual circumcisions on seven boys was convicted of causing dangerous bodily harm by the state court in [[Düsseldorf]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://rawstory.com/news/2006/Germany_fines_circumciser_for_initi_10172006.html|title=The Raw Story - Germany fines circumciser for initiation of 7 boys|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In September 2007, a [[Frankfurt|Frankfurt am Main]] appeals court found that the circumcision of an 11-year-old boy without his approval was an unlawful personal injury. The boy, whose parents were divorced, was visiting his Muslim father during a vacation when his father forced him to be ritually circumcised. The boy had planned to sue his father for {{euro|10,000}}.&lt;ref&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20071017044733/http://jta.org/cgi-bin/iowa/breaking/104271.html Breaking News&amp;nbsp;– JTA, Jewish &amp; Israel News&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lareda.hessenrecht.hessen.de/jportal/portal/t/dz2/page/bslaredaprod.psml?pid=Dokumentanzeige&amp;showdoccase=1&amp;js_peid=Trefferliste&amp;documentnumber=1&amp;numberofresults=1&amp;fromdoctodoc=yes&amp;doc.id=KORE244012007:juris-r01&amp;doc.part=L&amp;doc.price=0.0&amp;doc.hl=1|title=Hessenrecht Landesrechtsprechungsdatenbank Entscheidungen der hessischen Gerichte|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In May 2012, the Cologne regional appellate court ruled that religious circumcision of male children amounts to bodily injury, and is a criminal offense in the area under its jurisdiction.&lt;ref name=&quot;telegraph&quot;/&gt; The decision based on the article &quot;Criminal Relevance of Circumcising Boys. A Contribution to the Limitation of Consent in Cases of Care for the Person of the Child&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Holm Putzke: [http://www.holmputzke.de/images/stories/pdf/2008_fs_herzberg_beschneidung.pdf ''Die strafrechtliche Relevanz der Beschneidung von Knaben. Zugleich ein Beitrag über die Grenzen der Einwilligung in Fällen der Personensorge'']. In: Festschrift für Rolf Dietrich Herzberg, Tübingen 2008, p. 669–709 - Translation: [http://www.holmputzke.de/images/stories/pdf/2008_putzke%20fs%20herzberg%20essay%20on%20circumcision.pdf ''Criminal Relevance of Circumcising Boys. A Contribution to the Limitation of Consent in Cases of Care for the Person of the Child''], translated by Katharina McLarren.&lt;/ref&gt; published by [[Holm Putzke]], a German law professor at the University of Passau.&lt;ref&gt;[http://blogs.reuters.com/faithworld/tag/germany-circumcision-jewish-muslim-law-court-verdict-cologne-putzke-jurist/ German verdict aims to delay circumcision, not ban it, jurist says.] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150222003812/http://blogs.reuters.com/faithworld/tag/germany-circumcision-jewish-muslim-law-court-verdict-cologne-putzke-jurist/ |date=22 February 2015 }} Retrieved 16 June 2014&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.circinfo.org/Circumcision_and_law.html German court rules non-therapeutic circumcision of boys unlawful.] Retrieved 16 June 2014&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.intactamerica.org/putzke Intactivist of the month: Holm Putzke]&lt;/ref&gt; The court arrived at its judgment by application of the human rights provisions of the Basic Law, a section of the Civil Code, and some sections of the Criminal Code to non-therapeutic circumcision of male children.{{citation needed|date=September 2012}}  Some observers said it could set a legal precedent that criminalizes the practice.&lt;ref name=&quot;telegraph&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.thelocal.de/opinion/20120626-43385.html |title=Circumcision: religious right or crime? |date=27 June 2012 |website=[[The Local|TheLocal.de]] |accessdate=27 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.thelocal.de/society/20120627-43409.html |title=Muslims, Jews denounce circumcision ruling |date=27 June 2012 |website=[[The Local|TheLocal.de]] |accessdate=27 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Holm Putzke [http://blogs.reuters.com/faithworld/tag/germany-circumcision-jewish-muslim-law-court-verdict-cologne-putzke-jurist/ German verdict aims to delay circumcision, not ban it, jurist says.] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150222003812/http://blogs.reuters.com/faithworld/tag/germany-circumcision-jewish-muslim-law-court-verdict-cologne-putzke-jurist/ |date=22 February 2015 }} Retrieved 16 June 2014&lt;/ref&gt; Jewish and Muslim groups were outraged by the ruling, viewing it as trampling on freedom of religion.&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc.co.uk&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-18793842 Evans, Stephen. German circumcision ban: Is it a parent's right to choose? BBC News Magazine.] Retrieved 13 July 2012&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/religion/9360203/Jewish-and-Muslim-groups-condemn-German-circumcision-ruling.html | location=London | work=The Daily Telegraph | first=Matthew | last=Day | title=Jewish and Muslim groups condemn German circumcision ruling | date=27 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The German ambassador to Israel, Andreas Michaelis, told Israeli lawmakers that Germany was working to resolve the issue and that it doesn't apply at a national level, but instead only to the local jurisdiction of the court in Cologne.&lt;ref name=CBS&gt;{{cite news|title=Israeli parliament slams German circumcision ban|url=http://www.cbsnews.com/8301-202_162-57468680/israeli-parliament-slams-german-circumcision-ban/|accessdate=15 July 2012|newspaper=CBS News|date=9 July 2012|agency=AP}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Council of the Coordination of Muslims in Germany condemned the ruling, stating that it is &quot;a serious attack on religious freedom.&quot; Ali Kizilkaya, a spokesman of the council, stated that, &quot;The ruling does not take everything into account, religious practice concerning circumcision of young Muslims and Jews has been carried out over the millennia on a global level.&quot;  The [[Roman Catholic]] [[archbishop]] of [[Aachen]], [[Heinrich Mussinghoff]], said that the ruling was &quot;very surprising&quot;, and the contradiction between &quot;basic rights on freedom of religion and the well-being of the child brought up by the judges is not convincing in this very case.&quot;  Hans Ulrich Anke, the head of the [[Protestant Church]] in Germany, said the ruling should be appealed since it didn't &quot;sufficiently&quot; consider the religious significance of the rite.&lt;ref name=EJP&gt;{{cite news|title=Key Muslim group in Germany slams circumcision ruling|url=http://www.ejpress.org/article/news/germany/59627|accessdate=15 July 2012|newspaper=European Jewish Press|date=28 June 2012|agency=AFP|archive-url=https://archive.today/20130414233803/http://www.ejpress.org/article/news/germany/59627|archive-date=14 April 2013|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; A spokesman, Steffen Seibert, for [[Chancellor of Germany|German Chancellor]] [[Angela Merkel]] stated that Jewish and Muslim communities will be free to practice circumcision responsibly, and the government would find a way around the local ban in Cologne. The spokesman stated &quot;For everyone in the government it is absolutely clear that we want to have Jewish and Muslim religious life in Germany. Circumcision carried out in a responsible manner must be possible in this country without punishment.&quot;.&lt;ref name=TimesofIsrael1&gt;{{cite news|last=Ahren|first=Raphael|title=German government looking for quick fix on circumcision ban|url=http://www.timesofisrael.com/german-government-looking-for-quick-fix-on-circumcision-ban/|accessdate=15 July 2012|newspaper=The Times of Israel|date=13 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Guardian&gt;{{cite news|title=Angela Merkel intervenes over court ban on circumcision of young boys|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2012/jul/13/angela-merkel-intervenes-ban-circumcision|accessdate=15 July 2012|newspaper=The Guardian|date=13 July 2012|agency=Reuters|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In July, a group of rabbis, imams, and others said that they view the ruling against circumcision &quot;an affront on our basic religious and human rights.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;HuffPoCirc&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url=https://www.huffingtonpost.com/2012/07/12/rabbis-urge-german-jews-to-continue-circumcisions_n_1667916.html | title=Rabbis Urge German Jews To Continue Circumcisions | work=Huffington Post | date=12 July 2012 | accessdate=17 July 2012 | author=Rising, David}}&lt;/ref&gt; The joint statement was signed by leaders of groups including Germany's [[Turkish-Islamic Union for Religious Affairs]], the Islamic Center Brussels, the Rabbinical Centre of Europe, the European Jewish Parliament and the European Jewish Association, who met with members of [[European Parliament]] from Germany, Finland, Belgium, Italy, and Poland.  European rabbis, who urged Jews to continue circumcision, planned further talks with Muslim and Christian leaders to determine how they can oppose the ban together.&lt;ref name=&quot;HurriyetCirc&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.hurriyetdailynews.com/german-courts-move-to-ban-circumcision-unites-religions.aspx?pageID=238&amp;nID=25429&amp;NewsCatID=351 | title=German court's move to ban circumcision unites religions | work=Hurriyet Daily News | agency=Anatolia News Agency | date=14 July 2012 | accessdate=17 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Jewish Hospital of Berlin suspended the practice of male circumcision.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ynetnews.com/articles/0,7340,L-4249122,00.html Jewish Hospital in Berlin suspends circumcisions]. YNET News, 1 July 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; On 19 July 2012, a joint resolution of the [[CDU/CSU]], [[SPD]] and [[Free Democratic Party (Germany)|FDP]] factions in the [[Bundestag]] requesting the executive branch to draft a law permitting circumcision of boys to be performed without unnecessary pain in accordance with best medical practice&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Rechtliche Regelung der Beschneidung minderjähriger Jungen |url=http://dipbt.bundestag.de/dip21/btd/17/103/1710331.pdf  |language=German}}&lt;/ref&gt; carried with a broad majority.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Beschneidung minderjähriger Jungen |url=http://www.bundestag.de/dokumente/textarchiv/2012/39861243_kw29_angenommen_abgelehnt/index.html  |language=German}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The New York Times reported that the [[German Medical Association]] &quot;condemned the ruling for potentially putting children at risk by taking the procedure out of the hands of doctors, but it also warned surgeons not to perform circumcisions for religious reasons until legal clarity was established.&quot;&lt;ref name=nytimes_germany&gt;{{cite news | url=https://www.nytimes.com/2012/07/14/world/europe/in-germany-ruling-over-circumcision-sows-anxiety-and-confusion.html?_r=1 | title=In Germany, Ruling Over Circumcision Sows Anxiety and Confusion | work=New York Times | date=13 July 2012 | accessdate=23 July 2012 | author=Eddy, Melissa}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ruling was supported by Deutsche Kinderhilfe, a German child rights organization, which asked for a two-year moratorium to discuss the issue and pointed out that religious circumcision may contravene the [[Convention on the Rights of the Child]] (Article 24.3: &quot;States Parties shall take all effective and appropriate measures with a view to abolishing traditional practices prejudicial to the health of children.&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.themenportal.de/politik/petitionsausschuss-korrigiert-fehlentscheidung-petition-gegen-vorschnelles-gesetz-zur-legalisierung-nicht-therapeutischer-beschneidungen-seit-gestern-vom-bundestag-zur-unterzeichnung-freigeschaltet-16702|title=themenportal: Petitionsausschuss korrigiert Fehlentscheidung: Petition gegen vorschnelles Gesetz zur Legalisierung nicht-therapeutischer Beschneidungen seit gestern vom Bundestag zur Unterzeichnung freigeschaltet - Politik - Pressemitteilung|access-date=23 September 2012|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120917014105/http://www.themenportal.de/politik/petitionsausschuss-korrigiert-fehlentscheidung-petition-gegen-vorschnelles-gesetz-zur-legalisierung-nicht-therapeutischer-beschneidungen-seit-gestern-vom-bundestag-zur-unterzeichnung-freigeschaltet-16702|archive-date=17 September 2012|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.kinderhilfe.de/blog/artikel/anlaesslich-des-weltkindertages-fordert-die-deutsche-kinderhilfe-ein-klares-bekenntnis-zu-kinderrechten-statt-festtagsreden-keine-nicht-medizinische-beschneidung-fuer-einwilligungsunfaehige-kinder/ |title=Anlässlich des Weltkindertages fordert die Deutsche Kinderhilfe ein klares Bekenntnis zu Kinderrechten statt Festtagsreden: keine nicht-medizinische Beschneidung für einwillig...&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt; |access-date=23 September 2012 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121004083247/https://www.kinderhilfe.de/blog/artikel/anlaesslich-des-weltkindertages-fordert-die-deutsche-kinderhilfe-ein-klares-bekenntnis-zu-kinderrechten-statt-festtagsreden-keine-nicht-medizinische-beschneidung-fuer-einwilligungsunfaehige-kinder/ |archive-date=4 October 2012 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.kinderhilfe.de/blog/artikel/bundestagspetition-zu-beschneidungen) |title=Bundestagspetition zu Beschneidungen {{!}} Deutsche Kinderhilfe&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt; |access-date=23 September 2012 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140110005748/https://www.kinderhilfe.de/blog/artikel/bundestagspetition-zu-beschneidungen) |archive-date=10 January 2014 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The German Academy for Pediatric and Adolescent Medicine (Deutsche Akademie für Kinder- und Jugendmedizin e.V., DAKJ),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://dakj.de/pages/posts/stellungnahme-zur-beschneidung-von-minderjaehrigen-jungen-123.php |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2016-06-07 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160316162734/http://dakj.de/pages/posts/stellungnahme-zur-beschneidung-von-minderjaehrigen-jungen-123.php |archivedate=16 March 2016 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://dakj.de/media/stellungnahmen/ethische-fragen/2012_Stellungnahme_Beschneidung.pdf |title=Archived copy |access-date=23 September 2012 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131203075723/http://dakj.de/media/stellungnahmen/ethische-fragen/2012_Stellungnahme_Beschneidung.pdf |archive-date=3 December 2013 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; the German Association for Pediatric Surgery (Deutsche Gesellschaft für Kinderchirurgie, DGKCH)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dgkic.de/index.php/presse/189-pressemitteilung-juli-2012 Presseerklärung (4. July 2012) (DGKCH).]&lt;/ref&gt; and the Professional Association of Pediatric and Adolescent Physicians (Berufsverband der Kinder- und Jugendärzte)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.kinderaerzte-im-netz.de/bvkj/aktuelles1/show.php3?id=4322&amp;nodeid=26|title=Startseite » Kinderaerzte-im-Netz|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; took a firm stand against non-medical routine infant circumcision.

In July, in Berlin, a criminal complaint was lodged against Rabbi Yitshak Ehrenberg for &quot;causing bodily harm&quot; by performing religious circumcision, and for vocal support of the continuation of the practice. In September, the prosecutors dismissed the complaint, concluding that &quot;there is no proof to establish that the rabbi's conduct met the 'condition of a criminal' violation.&quot;&lt;ref name=JPost_Ehrenberg&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.jpost.com/JewishWorld/JewishNews/Article.aspx?id=283252 | title=Berlin prosecutor nixes circumcision complaint | newspaper=Jerusalem Post | date=30 August 2012 | accessdate=6 September 2012 | author=WEINTHAL, BENJAMIN}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In September, Reuters reported &quot;Berlin's senate said doctors could legally circumcise infant boys for religious reasons in its region, given certain conditions.&quot;&lt;ref name=Reuters_Berlin_2012&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/48914968/ns/world_news-europe/#.UEjj5FLfu5k |title=Berlin reverses ban on religious circumcisions |work=MSNBC |date=9 May 2012 |agency=Reuters |accessdate=6 September 2012 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120911010141/http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/48914968/ns/world_news-europe |archivedate=11 September 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 12 December 2012, following a series of hearings and consultations, the Bundestag adopted the proposed law explicitly permitting non-therapeutic circumcision to be performed under certain conditions; it is now §1631(d) in the [[Bürgerliches Gesetzbuch|German Civil Code]]. The vote tally was 434 ayes, 100 noes, and 46 abstentions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Beschneidung von Jungen jetzt gesetzlich geregelt |url=http://www.bundestag.de/dokumente/textarchiv/2012/42042381_kw50_de_beschneidung/index.html |language=German}}&lt;/ref&gt; Following approval by the [[Bundesrat of Germany|Bundesrat]] and signing by the [[President of Germany|Bundespräsident]], the new law became effective on 28 December 2012 a day after its publication in the [[Bundesgesetzblatt (Germany)|Federal Gazette]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Gesetz über den Umfang der Personensorge bei einer Beschneidung des männlichen Kindes |url=http://www.bgbl.de/Xaver/media.xav?SID=anonymous3567343041308&amp;bk=Bundesanzeiger_BGBl&amp;name=bgbl%2FBundesgesetzblatt%20Teil%20I%2F2012%2FNr.%2061%20vom%2027.12.2012%2Fbgbl112s2749.pdf |language=German}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Iceland ===
In May 2005, [[Iceland]] amended its [[General Penal Code (Iceland)|General Penal Code]] to illegalize female genital mutilation&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.althingi.is/altext/stjt/2005.083.html|title=Lög um breytingar á almennum hegningarlögum, nr. 19/1940, með síðari breytingum (bann við limlestingu á kynfærum kvenna).|website=Alþingi|language=is|access-date=2019-05-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Quote|text=Any person who, in an assault, causes physical injury or damage to the health of a girl child or woman by removing her sexual organs, partly or in their entirety, shall be imprisoned for up to 6 years. If the assault results in serious physical injury or health damage, or in death, or if it is considered particularly reprehensible due to the method used, punishment for the offence shall take the form of up to 16 years’ imprisonment|sign=|source=General Penal Code, Article 218 a&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.government.is/publications/legislation/lex/?newsid=7e2af9c7-f488-11e7-9423-005056bc530c|title=General Penal Code, Nr. 19/1940|website=www.government.is|language=en-US|access-date=2019-05-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

In February 2018, the [[Progressive Party (Iceland)|Progressive Party]] proposed a bill that would change the words &quot;girl child&quot; to &quot;child&quot; and &quot;her sexual organs&quot; to &quot;[their] sexual organs&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.althingi.is/altext/148/s/0183.html|title=183/148 frumvarp: almenn hegningarlög|website=Alþingi|language=is|access-date=2019-05-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; thereby making Iceland the first European country to ban male circumcision for non-medical reasons. The bill discussed in the [[Alþing]], the Icelandic parliament, claimed the practice harmed the physical integrity of young boys, was often performed without anaesthesia and in an unhygienic manner by religious leaders instead of medical experts. These facts were deemed incompatible with the [[United Nations Convention on the Rights of the Child]] (1990). Critics argued the bill infringed on religious freedom or constituted antisemitism or anti-Muslim bigotry, making it hard for Muslims and Jews to live there. Silja Dögg Gunnarsdóttir, who proposed the ban, retorted that Iceland had already prohibited female circumcision in 2005, and “If we have laws banning circumcision for girls, then we should do so for boys.”&lt;ref name=&quot;Sherwood&quot; /&gt; On 29 April, the bill was sent back to Parliament for revisions.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://www.ruv.is/frett/vilja-visa-frumvarpi-um-umskurd-til-stjornar |title=Vilja vísa frumvarpi um umskurð til stjórnar |work=[[RÚV]] |date=28 May 2018 |accessdate=7 June 2018 |language=is}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 25 March 2018, members of [[Jews Against Circumcision]] spoke in the Alþing expressing their support for the proposed ban, dismissing claims that it was motivated by antisemitism, anti-Muslim bigotry, xenophobia or anti-immigration sentiment.&lt;ref name=&quot;JACAlþing&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.althingi.is/altext/erindi/148/148-1018.pdf |title=Comment on a bill amending the Criminal Code (prohibition on circumcision of boys), 148th Legislative Assembly |author=Jews Against Circumcision |work= |publisher=Alþing |date=25 March 2018 |accessdate=15 October 2019 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite rumours to the contrary spread by the ''[[Times of Israel]]'' and others in late April, the bill was not scrapped, but is still a “work in progress.”&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://aleteia.org/2018/05/29/bill-to-criminalize-male-circumcision-is-still-alive-in-iceland/ |title=Bill to criminalize male circumcision is still alive in Iceland |author=Zelda Caldwell |work=[[Aleteia]] |publisher=Foundation for Evangelization through the Media |date=29 May 2018 |accessdate=27 June 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

;In favour of the proposed ban (March 2018)
* [[Progressive Party (Iceland)|Progressive Party]]&lt;ref name=&quot;JACAlþing&quot;/&gt;
* [[People's Party (Iceland, 2016)|People's Party]]&lt;ref name=&quot;JACAlþing&quot;/&gt;
* [[Left-Green Movement]]&lt;ref name=&quot;JACAlþing&quot;/&gt;
* [[Pirate Party (Iceland)|Pirate Party]]&lt;ref name=&quot;JACAlþing&quot;/&gt;
* [[Jews Against Circumcision]]&lt;ref name=&quot;JACAlþing&quot;/&gt;

;Against the proposed ban (March 2018)
* [[European Jewish Congress]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Sherwood&quot; /&gt;
* [[Islamic Cultural Centre of Iceland]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Sherwood&quot; /&gt;
* [[Catholic Church]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Sherwood&quot; /&gt;
* [[Anti-Defamation League]]&lt;ref name=&quot;JACAlþing&quot;/&gt;

=== Ireland ===
In October 2005 a Nigerian man was cleared of a charge of reckless endangerment over the death of a baby from hemorrhage and shock after he had circumcised the child. The judge directed the jury not to &quot;bring what he called their white western values to bear when they were deciding this case&quot; and effectively imposed a not guilty verdict on the jury. After deliberating for an hour and a half they found the defendant not guilty.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=https://www.irishtimes.com/news/nigerian-cleared-in-circumcision-case-1.502734 | work=Irishtimes | title=Nigerian cleared over circumcision death | date=7 October 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Israel ===
In [[Israel]], Jewish circumcision is entirely legal. Though illegal, female circumcision is still practiced among the [[Negev Bedouin]], and tribal secrecy among the Bedouin makes it difficult for authorities to enforce the ban.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ynetnews.com/articles/0,7340,L-3568416,00.html|title=Bedouin women in Israel are still being circumcised|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2013, a Rabbinical court in Israel ordered a mother, Elinor Daniel, to circumcise her son or pay a fine of 500 Israeli Shekel for every day that the child is not circumcised. She appealed against the Rabbinical court ruling and the High Court ruled in her favour stating, among other considerations, the basic right of freedom from religion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.timesofisrael.com/high-court-rules-against-coerced-circumcision/|title=High Court rules against coerced circumcision|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Netherlands ===

The [[Royal Dutch Medical Association|Royal Dutch Medical Association (KNMG)]] finds non-therapeutic circumcision of male minors to be in conflict with children's right to autonomy and physical integrity, and that there are good reasons for its legal prohibition, as exists for female genital mutilation: {{quote | * There is no convincing evidence that circumcision is useful or necessary in terms of prevention or hygiene. Partly in the light of the complications which can arise during or after circumcision, circumcision is not justifiable except on medical/therapeutic grounds. Insofar as there are medical benefits, such as a possibly reduced risk of HIV infection, it is reasonable to put off circumcision until the age at which such a risk is relevant and the boy himself can decide about the intervention, or can opt for any available alternatives.
* Contrary to what is often thought, circumcision entails the risk of medical and psychological complications. The most common complications are bleeding, infections, meatus stenosis (narrowing of the urethra) and panic attacks. Partial or complete penis amputations as a result of complications following circumcisions have also been reported, as have psychological problems as a result of the circumcision.
* Non-therapeutic circumcision of male minors is contrary to the rule that minors may only be exposed to medical treatments if illness or abnormalities are present, or if it can be convincingly demonstrated that the medical intervention is in the interest of the child, as in the case of vaccinations.
* Non-therapeutic circumcision of male minors conflicts with the child’s right to autonomy and physical integrity.
* There are good reasons for a legal prohibition of non-therapeutic circumcision of male minors, as exists for female genital mutilation.| author = {{Flagicon|Netherlands}} [[Royal Dutch Medical Association]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://www.knmg.nl/circumcision|title=The non-therapeutic circumcision of male minors|last=|first=|publisher=KNMG|year=2010|isbn=|location=|pages=16}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

In May 2008 a father who had his two sons, aged 3 and 6 circumcised against the will of their mother was found not guilty of abuse as the circumcision was performed by a physician and due to the court's restraint in setting a legal precedent; instead he was given a 6-week suspended jail sentence for taking the boys away from their mother against her will.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dutchnews.nl/news/archives/2008/05/father_not_guilty_in_circumcis.php|title=Father 'not guilty' in circumcision case - DutchNews.nl|date=7 May 2008|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://repository.ubn.ru.nl/bitstream/handle/2066/101027/101027.pdf?sequence=1 |title=Religieuze jongens besnijdenis als mishandeling|date=2012|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

;In favour of a ban
* [[Royal Dutch Medical Association]] (KNMG), federation of physicians (since 2010)&lt;ref name=&quot;KNMG&quot;&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20140914140526/http://knmg.artsennet.nl/web/file?uuid=175a7dff-f20b-42b3-9c04-78fd83f24a3d&amp;owner=a8a9ce0e-f42b-47a5-960e-be08025b7b04&amp;contentid=77973 ''Niet-therapeutische circumcisie bij minderjarige jongens''], KNMG position, 27 May 2010 (PDF file)&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Youth Organisation Freedom and Democracy]], youth wing [[People's Party for Freedom and Democracy]] (VVD) (since 2014)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.trouw.nl/nieuws/jovd-wil-verbod-op-religieuze-besnijdenis~b40947bd/ |title=JOVD wil verbod op religieuze besnijdenis |author= |work=Trouw |date=5 March 2014 |accessdate=12 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.trouw.nl/nieuws/hoog-tijd-om-besnijdenis-van-minderjarige-jongens-te-verbieden~b73105ee/ |title=Hoog tijd om besnijdenis van minderjarige jongens te verbieden |author=Tom Leijte &amp; Matthijs van de Burgwal |work=Trouw |date=5 March 2014 |accessdate=12 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Young Democrats (Netherlands)|Young Democrats]], youth wing [[Democrats 66]] (D66) (since 2017, favours a gradual increase of the minimum age for circumcision)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.nrc.nl/nieuws/2017/05/05/vrijheid-van-religie-houdt-op-bij-jongensbesnijdenis-8692723-a1557375 |title=Vrijheid van religie houdt op bij jongensbesnijdenis |author=Wouter van Erkel en Koen Sijtsema |work=NRC Handelsblad |date=5 May 2017 |accessdate=12 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://jongedemocraten.nl/blog/zeven-argumenten-voor-jongensbesnijdenis-en-waarom-ze-niet-kloppen/ |title=Zeven argumenten voor jongensbesnijdenis en waarom ze niet kloppen |work=Website Jonge Democraten |date=15 May 2017 |accessdate=12 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[PINK!]], youth wing [[Party for the Animals]] (PvdD) (since 2018)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.blikopnieuws.nl/nieuws/263659/jongeren-pvdd-willen-verbod-jongensbesnijdenis.html |title=Jongeren PvdD willen verbod jongensbesnijdenis |author= |work=Blik op Nieuws |date=6 May 2018 |accessdate=12 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6AlGgV1WOyA |title=PINK! Ban circumcision of boys – interview Sebastiaan Wolswinkel |author= |work=Simon ten Kate |publisher= |date=16 May 2018 |accessdate=12 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://joop.bnnvara.nl/opinies/verbied-besnijdenis-in-het-belang-van-het-kind |title=Verbod besnijdenis in het belang van het kind |author=Marvin Gerritsen &amp; Sebastiaan Wolswinkel |work=Joop |date=29 June 2018 |accessdate=12 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

;Against a ban
* Council of Public Health and Care (RVZ), medical advisory committee for parliament and government (since 2010)&lt;ref name=&quot;RVZ&quot;&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20111203065953/http://rvz.net/nieuws/bericht/de-ene-besnijdenis-is-de-andere-niet-reactie-op-knmg-standpunt-jongensbesn ''De ene besnijdenis is de andere niet. Reactie op KNMG standpunt jongensbesnijdenis''], Raad voor de Volksgezondheid &amp; Zorg, 2 June 2010&lt;/ref&gt;
* Rabbi Herman Loonstein, president of Federative Jewish Netherlands&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.nrc.nl/nieuws/2012/07/13/wij-zien-besnijdenis-juist-als-iets-goeds-1130169-a1025570 |title=Wij zien besnijdenis juist als iets goeds |author=Danielle Pinedo &amp; Frederiek Weeda |work=NRC Handelsblad |date=13 July 2012 |accessdate=12 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Norway ===
The [https://barneombudet.no/ Norwegian Ombudsman for Children] opposes circumcising children, and it is right to wait until children are old enough to decide for themselves: {{quote |The Ombudsman for Children is opposed to having children circumcised when they are so small that they are unable to express their views on it. Being circumcised is something that cannot be changed. Then we think it is right to wait until the children are old enough to decide for themselves.| author = {{Flagicon|Norway}} [https://barneombudet.no/ Norwegian Ombudsman for Children]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://barneombudet.no/2013/09/29/aldersgrense-for-omskjaering-av-gutter/|title=Aldersgrense for omskjæring av gutter|last=Barneombudet|date=2013-09-29|website=Barneombudet|language=nb-NO|access-date=2019-10-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

In June 2012, the centre-right [[Centre Party (Norway)|Centre Party]] proposed a ban on circumcision on males under eighteen, after an [[Oslo]] infant died in May following a circumcision.&lt;ref name=&quot;Endsjø&quot;&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://www.dagbladet.no/2012/06/19/kultur/debatt/omskjering/helse_bergen/bar_overkropp/22180612/ |title=Attenårsgrense for omskjæring |author=Dag Øistein Endsjø |work=[[Dagbladet]] |date=19 June 2012 |accessdate=26 June 2018 |language=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In September 2013, the [[Children's Ombudsman|Children's ombudsmen]] in all [[Nordic countries]] issued a statement&lt;ref name=&quot;resolution&quot;&gt;{{vcite web | author=Nordic Association of Children's Ombudsmen | home= | title=Let the boys decide for themselves | url=https://www.crin.org/en/library/news-archive/male-circumcision-nordic-ombudspersons-seek-ban-non-therapeutic-male | date=30 September 2013 | accessdate=27 October 2013 }}[] Tuesday, 1 October 2013&lt;/ref&gt; by which they called for a ban on circumcision of minors for non-medical reasons, stating that such circumcisions violate the rights of children after the [[Convention on the Rights of the Child]] to co-determination and protection from harmful traditions.&lt;ref&gt;Lise Marit Kalstad (2 October 2013): [http://www.vl.no/samfunn/vil-la-gutter-bestemme-omskjaring-selv/ Vil la gutter bestemme omskjæring selv] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131004224140/http://www.vl.no/samfunn/vil-la-gutter-bestemme-omskjaring-selv/ |date=4 October 2013 }} ''[[Vårt Land (Norwegian newspaper)|Vårt Land]]''. {{in lang|no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A bill on ritual circumcision of boys was passed (against two votes) in the [[Storting|Norwegian Parliament]] in June 2014, with the new law going into effect on 1 January 2015. This law protects the right of Jews to brit mila and obligates the Norwegian Health Care regions to offer the Muslim minority a safe and affordable procedure. Local anaesthesia needs to be applied and a licensed physician needs to be present at the circumcision, which hospitals started to perform in March 2015.&lt;ref name=&quot;NorwayLocal&quot;&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.thelocal.no/20150310/norway-hospital-carries-out-first-ritual-circumcision |title=Norway hospital does first ritual circumcision |work=The Local |date=10 March 2015 |accessdate=26 June 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In May 2017, the right-wing [[Progress Party (Norway)|Progress Party]] proposed to ban circumcision for males under sixteen.&lt;ref name=&quot;Independent&quot;&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/europe/norwegian-ruling-progress-party-ban-circumcision-men-under-16-years-old-vote-annual-conference-a7723746.html |title=Norwegian ruling party votes to ban circumcision for men under 16 years old |author=Rachael Revesz |work=The Independent |date=8 May 2017 |accessdate=26 June 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

;In favour of a ban
* [[Centre Party (Norway)|Centre Party]] (under 18, since 2012)&lt;ref name=&quot;Endsjø&quot;/&gt;
* [[Progress Party (Norway)|Progress Party]] (under 16, since 2017)&lt;ref name=&quot;Independent&quot;/&gt;

=== South Africa ===
The [[Children's Act 2005]] makes the circumcision of male children under 16 unlawful except for religious or medical reasons. In the [[Eastern Cape]] province the Application of Health Standards in Traditional Circumcision Act, 2001, regulates traditional circumcision, which causes the death or mutilation of many youths by traditional surgeons each year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.irinnews.org/Report.aspx?ReportId=73278|title=SOUTH AFRICA: Clamping down on botched circumcisions|date=1 August 2007|work=IRIN In-Depth|location=MTHATA}}&lt;/ref&gt; Among other provisions, the minimum age for circumcision is age 18.

In 2004, a 22-year-old Rastafarian convert was forcibly circumcised by a group of [[Xhosa people|Xhosa]] tribal elders and relatives. When he first fled, two police returned him to those who had circumcised him.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.iol.co.za/index.php?set_id=1&amp;click_id=13&amp;art_id=vn20040704124240917C136839
| title = Rastafarian circumcised against his will
| accessdate =23 April 2007
| last = Peters
| first = Melanie
| date = 4 July 2004
| work = South Africa
| publisher = [[Sunday Tribune]]
| page = 3
| quote =  22-year-old Cape Town man was taken by force and circumcised against his will this week....He is a Rastafarian convert and strongly opposes Xhosa initiation. The men who forcibly circumcised him also cut off his Rasta dreadlocks.}}
&lt;/ref&gt; In another case, a medically circumcised Xhosa man was forcibly recircumcised by his father and community leaders. He laid a charge of unfair discrimination on the grounds of his religious beliefs, seeking an apology from his father and the Congress of Traditional Leaders of South Africa. According to South African newspapers, the subsequent trial became &quot;a landmark case around forced circumcision.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.iol.co.za/news/south-africa/forced-circumcision-son-takes-parents-on-1.454711
| title = Forced circumcision: Son takes parents on
| date = 11 August 2009
| accessdate =30 September 2010
| publisher = IOL: News for South Africa and the World
}}&lt;/ref&gt; In October 2009, the [[Eastern Cape High Court, Bhisho|Eastern Cape High Court at Bhisho]] (sitting as an [[Equality Court]]) clarified that circumcision is unlawful unless done with the full consent of the initiate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.legalbrief.co.za/article.php?story=20091014084902414
| title = Judgment in forced circumcision case
| date = 14 October 2009
| accessdate =30 September 2010
| publisher = Legalbrief Today
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Slovenia ===
The [http://www.varuh-rs.si/ Slovenian Human Rights Ombudsman] finds that circumcision for non-medical reasons is a violation of children's rights, that ritual circumcision for religious reasons is unacceptable in Slovenia for both legal and ethical reasons, and should not be performed by doctors: {{quote |Circumcision of boys for non-medical reasons is a violation of children's rights. … The ritual circumcision of boys for religious reasons in our country is unacceptable for legal and ethical reasons and should not be performed by doctors.| author = {{Flagicon|Slovenia}} [http://www.varuh-rs.si/ Slovenian Human Rights Ombudsman]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.varuh-rs.si/medijsko-sredisce/aktualni-primeri/novice/detajl/obrezovanje-fantkov-iz-nemedicinskih-razlogov-je-krsitev-otrokovih-pravic/?cHash=7364092ccb|title=Obrezovanje fantkov iz nemedicinskih razlogov je kršitev otrokovih pravic|website=www.varuh-rs.si|access-date=2019-10-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

=== Sweden ===
The [https://slf.se/ Swedish Medical Association] finds no known medical benefits to circumcision of children, and thus strong reasons to wait until the boy is old and mature enough to give informed consent, aiming at ceasing all non-medically justified circumcision without prior consent: {{quote |There are no known medical benefits to the (circumcision) intervention on children. … Therefore, there are strong reasons to wait for the intervention until the person who is the subject of the measure has reached such age and maturity that he can give informed consent. … The EAR believes that the goal is to cease non-medically justified circumcision without prior consent.| author = {{Flagicon|Sweden}} [https://slf.se/ Swedish Medical Association]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://slf.se/rad-och-stod/okategoriserad/omskarelse-av-pojkar/|title=Omskärelse av pojkar|website=Sveriges läkarförbund|language=sv-SE|access-date=2019-10-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

In 2001, the [[Parliament of Sweden]] enacted a law allowing only persons certified by the National Board of Health to circumcise infants. It requires a medical doctor or an anesthesia nurse to accompany the circumciser and for anaesthetic to be applied beforehand. After the first two months of life circumcisions can only be performed by a physician. The stated purpose of the law was to increase the safety of the procedure.&lt;ref name=&quot;SR&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://sverigesradio.se/sida/artikel.aspx?programid=1316&amp;artikel=974694 |newspaper=[[Sveriges Radio]] |date=22 October 2006 |title=Snitt som kostar – om omskärelse av pojkar |language=Swedish}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Swedish Jews and Muslims objected to the law,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
| url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/1572483.stm
| title = Sweden restricts circumcisions
| accessdate =18 October 2006
| date = 1 October 2001
| publisher = [[BBC|BBC Europe]]
| quote = Swedish Jews and Muslims object to the new law, saying it violates their religious rights.
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; and in 2001, the [[World Jewish Congress]] called it &quot;the first legal restriction on Jewish religious practice in Europe since the Nazi era.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title = Jews protest Swedish circumcision restriction | url = http://www.hrwf.net/religiousfreedom/news/sweden2001.html#JewsprotestSwedish | work = Reuters | date = 7 June 2001 | quote = A WJC spokesman said, &quot;This is the first legal restriction placed on a Jewish rite in Europe since the Nazi era. This new legislation is totally unacceptable to the Swedish Jewish community.&quot; | access-date = 20 May 2009 | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20100331011938/http://www.hrwf.net/religiousfreedom/news/sweden2001.html#JewsprotestSwedish | archive-date = 31 March 2010 | url-status = dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; The requirement for an anaesthetic to be administered by a medical professional is a major issue,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Hofvander Y |title=New law on male circumcision in Sweden |journal=Lancet |volume=359 |issue=9306 |page=630 |date=February 2002 |pmid=11867150 |doi=10.1016/S0140-6736(02)07737-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the low degree of availability of certified professionals willing to conduct circumcision has also been subject to criticism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://uppsalademokraten.etc.se/28460/lang-koetid-foer-omskaerelse/ |title=Lång kötid för omskärelse |language=Swedish |newspaper=UppsalaDemokraten |author=Malin Beeck |date=5 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to a survey, two out of three paediatric surgeons said they refuse to perform non-therapeutic circumcision, and less than half of all [[County Councils of Sweden|county councils]] offer it in their hospitals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Swedish doctors refuse to circumcise boys |url=http://www.thelocal.se/20900/20090725/ |newspaper=[[The Local]] |date=25 July 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, in 2006, the U.S. State Department stated, in a report on Sweden, that most Jewish [[mohel]]s had been certified under the law and 3000 Muslim and 40–50 Jewish boys were circumcised each
year. An estimated 2000 of these are performed by persons who are neither physicians nor have officially recognised certification.&lt;ref name=&quot;Holender2009&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.dn.se/nyheter/manga-lakare-vagrar-utfora-omskarelse-av-unga-pojkar-1.918069 |title=Många läkare vägrar utföra omskärelse av unga pojkar |newspaper=[[Dagens Nyheter]] |language=Swedish |date=24 July 2009 |first=Robert |last=Holender}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Swedish National Board of Health and Welfare reviewed the law in 2005 and recommended that it be maintained,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = https://2001-2009.state.gov/g/drl/rls/irf/2006/71410.htm
| title = Sweden
| accessdate =4 July 2007
| author = Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights, and Labor
| date = 15 September 2006
| work = International Religious Freedom Report 2006
| publisher = US Department of State
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; but found that the law had failed with regard to the intended consequence of increasing the safety of circumcisions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Soc2007&quot;/&gt; A later report by the Board criticised the low level of availability of legal circumcisions, partly due to reluctance among health professionals.&lt;ref name=&quot;Soc2007&quot;/&gt; To remedy this, the report suggested a new law obliging all county councils to offer non-therapeutic circumcision in their hospitals,&lt;ref name=&quot;Soc2007&quot;&gt;{{Cite report|title=Omskärelse av pojkar |url=http://www.socialstyrelsen.se/publikationer2007/2007-107-7 |date=March 2007 |publisher=[[National Board of Health and Welfare (Sweden)|National Board of Health and Welfare]] |language=Swedish |docket=2007-107-7 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120222063038/http://www.socialstyrelsen.se/publikationer2007/2007-107-7 |archivedate=22 February 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt; but this was later abandoned in favour of a non-binding recommendation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Holender2009&quot;/&gt;

In 2013, the children's ombudsmen of all Nordic countries — Finland, Iceland, Denmark, Sweden and Norway — released a joint declaration in 2013 proposing a ban on non-medical circumcision of male minors. In October 2018, the right-wing populist [[Sweden Democrats]] party submitted a draft motion to parliament calling for a ban. At the annual conference of the [[Centre Party (Sweden)|Centre Party]] in September 2019, 314 to 166 commissioners voted in favor of prohibiting boys' circumcision. Several Jewish and Islamic organisations voiced their opposition to a potential ban.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.timesofisrael.com/jews-join-fight-against-swedish-partys-call-to-ban-circumcisions/ |title=Jews join fight against Swedish party’s call to ban circumcisions |work=Times of Israel |date=3 October 2019 |accessdate=6 October 2019 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Left Party (Sweden)|Left Party]] has also expressed support for a prohibition on circumcising boys before the age of 18; other parties have so far not backed a potential ban, though the Green Party found the practice 'problematic'.&lt;ref name=&quot;Edwards&quot;&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.thelocal.se/20191002/jews-and-muslims-in-sweden-outraged-over-call-to-ban-male-circumcision |title=Jews and Muslims in Sweden outraged over call to ban male circumcision |author=Catherine Edwards |work=The Local |date=2 October 2019 |accessdate=6 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

;In favour of a ban
* [[Sverigedemokraterna]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Edwards&quot;/&gt;
* [[Centerpartiet]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Edwards&quot;/&gt;
* [[Vänsterpartiet]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Edwards&quot;/&gt;

;Against a ban
* [[Kristdemokraterna]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Edwards&quot;/&gt;
* [[Liberalerna]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Edwards&quot;/&gt;
* [[Moderata samlingspartiet]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Edwards&quot;/&gt;
* [[Sveriges socialdemokratiska arbetareparti]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Edwards&quot;/&gt;
* [[Miljöpartiet de Gröna]] (does find circumcision 'problematic')&lt;ref name=&quot;Edwards&quot;/&gt;

=== United Kingdom ===
Male circumcision has traditionally been presumed to be legal under British law,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=English Criminal Law and Ethnic Minority Customs |last=Poulter |first=Sebastian |publisher=Butterworths, London |isbn=0-406-18000-8&lt;!-- ISBN shown in the cited webpage is erroneous and invalid. --&gt; |year=1986 |url=http://www.cirp.org/library/legal/poulter/|quote=no amount of parental agreement or support can legitimise the circumcision, excision or infibulation of a young girl in this country, unless the operation is for therapeutic purposes.}}&lt;/ref&gt; however some authors have argued that there is no solid foundation for this view in English law.&lt;ref name=&quot;cirp&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cirp.org/library/legal/UKlaw/fox-thomson2005/|title=A covenant with the status quo? Male circumcision and the new BMA guidance to doctors|publisher=cirp.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;cirp.org&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cirp.org/library/legal/price/#n18|title=Male Circumcision: An Ethical and Legal Affront|first=Christopher|last=Price|publisher=cirp.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While legal, the [[British Medical Association]] finds it ethically unacceptable to circumcise a child or young person, either with or without competence, who refuses the procedure, irrespective of the parents’ wishes, and that parental preference alone does not constitute sufficient grounds for performing NTMC on a child unable to express his own view: {{quote | The [[British Medical Association|BMA]] considers that the evidence concerning health benefit from NTMC (non-therapeutic male circumcision) is insufficient for this alone to be a justification for boys undergoing circumcision. In addition, some of the anticipated health benefits of male circumcision can be realised by other means – for example, condom use. … There are clearly risks inherent in any surgical procedure: for example, pain, bleeding, surgical mishap and complications of anaesthesia. With NTMC there are associated medical and psychological risks …  The BMA cannot envisage a situation in which it is ethically acceptable to circumcise a child or young person, either with or without competence, who refuses the procedure, irrespective of the parents’ wishes. … Parental preference alone does not constitute sufficient grounds for performing NTMC on a child unable to express his own view. … Furthermore, the harm of a person not having the opportunity to choose not to be circumcised or choose not to follow the traditions of his parents must also be taken into account, together with the damage that can be done to the individual’s relationship with his parents and the medical profession, if he feels harmed by an irreversible non-therapeutic procedure.| author = {{Flagicon|GB}} [[British Medical Association]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.bma.org.uk/advice/employment/ethics/children-and-young-people/non-therapeutic-male-circumcision-of-children-ethics-toolkit/5-health-risks-and-benefits-of-circumcision|title=BMA - Health risks and benefits of non-therapeutic male circumcision|website=www.bma.org.uk|access-date=2019-10-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.bma.org.uk/advice/employment/ethics/children-and-young-people/non-therapeutic-male-circumcision-of-children-ethics-toolkit/6-determining-best-interests-when-it-comes-to-circumcision|title=BMA - Determining a child's best interests for non-therapeutic male circumcision|website=www.bma.org.uk|access-date=2019-10-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

The passage of the [[Human Rights Act 1998]] has led to some speculation that the lawfulness of the circumcision of male children is unclear.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cirp.org/library/legal/edge1/|title=Circumcision After the Human Rights Act 1998|publisher=cirp.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;

One 1999 case, ''Re &quot;J&quot; (child's religious upbringing and circumcision)''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cirp.org/library/legal/Re_J/|title=Re J (child's religious upbringing and circumcision)|publisher=cirp.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; said that circumcision in Britain required the consent of all those with parental responsibility (however this comment was not part of the reason for the judgement and therefore is not legally binding), or the permission of the court, acting for the best interests of the child, and issued an order prohibiting the circumcision of a male child of a non-practicing [[Muslim]] father and non-practicing Christian mother with custody. The reasoning included evidence that circumcision carried some medical risk; that the operation would be likely to weaken the relationship of the child with his mother, who strongly objected to circumcision without [[medical necessity]]; that the child may be subject to ridicule by his peers as the odd one out and that the operation might irreversibly reduce sexual pleasure, by permanently removing some sensory nerves, even though cosmetic foreskin restoration might be possible. The court did not rule out circumcision against the consent of one parent. It cited a hypothetical case of a Jewish mother and an agnostic father with a number of sons, all of whom, by agreement, had been circumcised as infants in accordance with Jewish laws; the parents then have another son who is born after they have separated; the mother wishes him to be circumcised like his brothers; the father for no good reason, refuses his agreement. In such a case, a decision in favor of circumcision was said to be likely.

In 2001 the General Medical Council had found a doctor who had botched circumcision operations guilty of abusing his professional position and that he had acted &quot;inappropriately and irresponsibly&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/health/1502729.stm | work=BBC News | title=Circumcision doctors 'abused position' | date=21 August 2001 | accessdate=30 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and struck him off the register.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;[http://archive.thisisthenortheast.co.uk/2003/3/3/101692.html Circumcision case GP told he can resume career&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; A doctor who had referred patients to him, and who had pressured a mother into agreeing to the surgery, was also condemned.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot; /&gt; He was put on an 18-month period of review and retraining, and was allowed to resume unrestricted practice as a doctor in March 2003, after a committee found that he had complied with conditions it placed on him. According to the ''Northern Echo'', he &quot;told the committee he has now changed his approach to circumcision referrals, accepting that most cases can be treated without the need for surgery.&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot; /&gt;

Fox and Thomson (2005) argue that consent cannot be given for non-therapeutic circumcision.&lt;ref name=&quot;cirp&quot; /&gt; They say there is &quot;no compelling legal authority for the common view that circumcision is lawful.&quot;

In 2005 a Muslim man had his son circumcised against the wishes of the child's mother who was the custodial parent.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://news.scotsman.com/latest.cfm?id=4497150 | archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20050523125330/http://news.scotsman.com/latest.cfm?id=4497150 | archivedate=23 May 2005 | title=Muslim Accused of Assaulting Son Through Circumcision | date=3 May 2005 | accessdate=5 June 2011 | first=James | last=Tapsfield | newspaper=[[The Scotsman]] | location=Edinburgh}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2009 it was reported that a 20-year-old man whose father had him ritually circumcised as a baby is preparing to sue the doctor who circumcised him. This is believed to be the first time a person who was circumcised as an infant has made a claim in the UK. The case is expected to be heard in 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.mirror.co.uk/news/top-stories/2009/11/17/snip-op-illegal-115875-21828059/|title=Ritual circumcisions 'illegal'|work=[[Daily Mirror]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Update inline|date=November 2015}}

In a 2015 case regarding female circumcision, a judge concluded that non-therapeutic circumcision of male children is a &quot;significant harm&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;http://journalofethics.ama-assn.org/2017/08/msoc2-1708.html&lt;/ref&gt; In 2016, the Family Court in [[Exeter]] ruled that a Muslim father could not have his two sons (aged 6 and 4) circumcised after their mother disagreed. Mrs Justice Roberts declared that the boys should first grow old enough &quot;to the point where each of the boys themselves will make their individual choices once they have the maturity and insight to appreciate the consequences and longer-term effects of the decisions which they reach.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Exeter&quot;&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.bbc.com/news/uk-england-cornwall-36074482 |title=Muslim father loses circumcision court battle over sons |work=BBC News |date=18 April 2016 |accessdate=27 June 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.bbc.com/news/world-europe-43111800 |title=Iceland's mooted circumcision ban sparks religious outrage |work=BBC News |date=19 February 2018 |accessdate=27 June 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

;Nottingham case
In June 2017, Nottinghamshire Police arrested three people on suspicion of &quot;conspiracy to commit grievous bodily harm&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC2207&quot;/&gt; The alleged victim was purportedly circumcised while in its Muslim father's care at his grandparents' in July 2013 without the consent of his mother (a non-religious white British woman who conceived the child after a casual affair with the man, whom she had separated from after the incident).&lt;ref name=&quot;Bannerman&quot;&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.thetimes.co.uk/article/mother-to-sue-over-son-s-circumcision-kh09k22p8 |title=Mother to sue over son's circumcision |author=Lucy Bannerman |work=The Times |date=9 April 2018 |accessdate=27 June 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; The mother first contacted social services and eventually the police in November 2014. The police initially dismissed the complaint, but after the mother got help from the anti-circumcision group Men Do Complain and leading human rights lawyer [[Saimo Chahal|Saimo Chahal QC]], they reopened the case, and ended up arresting three suspects involved.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC2207&quot;&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.bbc.com/news/uk-england-nottinghamshire-40358944 |title=Three arrested over boy's circumcision in Nottingham |work=BBC News|date=22 June 2017 |accessdate=27 June 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; In November 2017, the Crown Prosecution Service explained to the mother in a letter they were not going to prosecute the doctor, who claimed he was unaware of the mother's non-consent. However, Chahal appealed this decision, which she said &quot;lacks any semblance of a considered and reasoned decision and is flawed and irrational&quot;, and threatened to bring the case to court.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.independent.co.uk/news/uk/home-news/doctor-circumcision-three-month-old-baby-no-consent-prosecution-avoid-dr-balvinder-mehat-bakersfield-a8048261.html |title=Doctor avoids prosecution over circumcision on three-month-old baby 'without consent' |author=Jeff Farrell |work=The Independent |date=10 November 2017 |accessdate=27 June 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; The by then 29-year-old mother finally sued the doctor in April 2018.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bannerman&quot;/&gt; Niall McCrae, mental health expert from [[King's College London]], argued that this case could mean 'the end of ritual male circumcision in the UK', drawing comparisons with earlier rulings against female genital mutilation.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://theconversation.com/the-case-that-could-end-ritual-male-circumcision-in-the-uk-94873 |title=The case that could end ritual male circumcision in the UK |author=Niall McCrae |work=The Conversation UK |date=13 April 2018 |accessdate=27 June 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== United States ===
[[File:Intact America logo.jpg|thumb|[[Intact America]] is one of the groups campaigning for a ban on non-medical nonconsensual circumcision of minors.]]
Circumcision of adults who grant personal informed consent for the surgical operation is legal.

In the United States, non-therapeutic circumcision of male children has long been assumed to be lawful in every jurisdiction provided that one parent grants surrogate informed consent. Adler (2013) has recently challenged the validity of this assumption.&lt;ref&gt;Peter W. Adler. [http://rjolpi.richmond.edu/archive/Adler_Formatted.pdf Is Circumcision Legal?] 16(3) Richmond J. L. &amp; Pub. Int. 439 (2013).&lt;/ref&gt; As with every country, doctors who circumcise children must take care that all applicable rules regarding informed consent and safety are satisfied.&lt;ref&gt;J. Steven Svoboda, Robert S. Van Howe, James G. Dwyer, [http://www.cirp.org/library/legal/conundrum/ Informed Consent for Neonatal Circumcision: An Ethical and Legal Conundrum]. 17 J Contemporary Health Law Policy 61 (2000)&lt;/ref&gt;

While anti-circumcision groups have occasionally proposed legislation banning non-therapeutic child circumcision, it has not been supported in any legislature.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://edition.cnn.com/2005/LAW/04/08/colb.circumcision/index.html |author=Colb, Sherry |title=A proposed bill to ban male circumcision |date=8 April 2005 |publisher=CNN}}&lt;/ref&gt; After a failed attempt to adopt a local ordinance banning circumcision on a San Francisco ballot, the state of California enacted in October 2011 a law protecting circumcision from local attempts to ban the practice.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2011/10/02/BA411LCKEU.DTL&amp;type=printable |title=Circumcision law blocks local bans |author=Evangelista, Benny |newspaper=San Francisco Chronicle |date=3 October 2011 |pages=C–2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2012, New York City required those performing ''[[metzitzah b'peh]]'', the oral suction of the open circumcision wound required by [[Hasidim]], to obey stringent consent requirements, including documentation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=N.Y. Board Orders Forms for Circumcision Rite|url=http://forward.com/articles/162762/ny-board-orders-forms-for-circumcision-rite/?p=all|accessdate=26 December 2012|newspaper=[[The Jewish Daily Forward]]|date=13 September 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Agudath Israel of America]] and other Jewish groups have planned to sue the city in response.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Exclusive: Agudah Preparing To Sue City Over Metzitza Informed Consent|url=http://www.thejewishweek.com/news/breaking-news/exclusive-agudah-preparing-sue-city-over-metzitza-informed-consent|accessdate=26 December 2012|newspaper=[[The Jewish Week]]|date=11 September 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Disputes between parents'''

Occasionally the courts are asked to make a ruling when parents cannot agree on whether or not to circumcise a child.

In January 2001 a dispute between divorcing parents in New Jersey was resolved when the mother, who sought to have the boy circumcised withdrew her request. The boy had experienced two instances of foreskin inflammation and she wanted to have him circumcised. The father, who had experienced a traumatic circumcision as a child objected and they turned to the courts for a decision. The Medical Society of New Jersey and the Urological Society of New Jersey both opposed any court ordered medical treatment. As the parties came to an agreement, no precedent was set.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cirp.org/news/star-ledger01-25-01/|title=Accord Not To Circumcise Son Still Leaves Heated Legal Debate|publisher=cirp.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; In June 2001 a Nevada court settled a dispute over circumcision between two parents but put a strict gag order on the terms of the settlement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.reviewjournal.com/cgi-bin/printable.cgi?/lvrj_home/2001/Jun-25-Mon-2001/news/16387263.html|title=Gag order issued|last=Thevemot|first=Carri Geer|date=25 June 2001|work=[[Las Vegas Review-Journal]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; In July 2001 a dispute between parents in [[Kansas]] over circumcision was resolved when the mother's request to have the infant circumcised was withdrawn. In this case the father opposed circumcision while the mother asserted that not circumcising the child was against her religious beliefs. (The woman's pastor had stated that circumcision was &quot;important&quot; but was not necessary for salvation.) On 24 July 2001 the parents reached agreement that the infant would not be circumcised.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.cirp.org/news/wichitaeagle07-24-01 |title=Agreement reached in circumcision case |date=25 July 2001 |newspaper=The Wichita Eagle |accessdate=30 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.cirp.org/news/wichitaeagle07-13-01/ |title=Wichitans fight over their son's circumcision |author=Alex Branch |date=13 July 2001 |newspaper=The Wichita Eagle}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 14 July 2004 a mother appealed to the [[Missouri Supreme Court]] to prevent the circumcision of her son after a county court and the Court of Appeals had denied her a writ of prohibition.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://examiner.net/stories/071504/new_071504018.shtml |title=The Examiner: Parents in court over son's circumcision 07/15/04 |date=26 December 2004 |url-status=bot: unknown |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20041226064014/http://examiner.net/stories/071504/new_071504018.shtml |archivedate=26 December 2004 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, in early August 2004, before the Supreme Court had given its ruling, the father, who had custody of the boy, had him circumcised.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.kansascity.com/mld/kansascity/news/local/9359979.htm|title=Despite mother's protest, father has boy circumcised|date=10 August 2004|work=Kansas City Star|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20041029070148/http://www.kansascity.com/mld/kansascity/news/local/9359979.htm|archivedate=29 October 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In October 2006 a judge in Chicago granted an injunction blocking the circumcision of a 9-year-old boy. In granting the injunction the judge stated that &quot;the boy could decide for himself whether to be circumcised when he turns 18.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Reut06&quot;/&gt;

In November 2007, the [[Oregon Supreme Court]] heard arguments from a divorced [[Oregon]] couple over the circumcision of their son. The father wanted his son, who turned 13 on 2 March 2008, to be circumcised in accordance with the father's religious views; the child's mother opposes the procedure.  The parents dispute whether the boy is in favor of the procedure. A group opposed to circumcision filed briefs in support of the mother's position, while some Jewish groups filed a brief in support of the father.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Gerstein |first=Josh |title=Ore. Court Mulls Circumcision Case |url=http://www.nysun.com/article/65997?page_no=2 |work=The New York Sun |accessdate=28 December 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 25 January 2008, the Court returned the case to the trial court with instructions to determine whether the child agrees or objects to the proposed circumcision.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.publications.ojd.state.or.us/S054714.htm Oregon Judicial Department Appellate Court Opinions&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; The father appealed to the US Supreme Court to allow him to have his son circumcised&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://blog.oregonlive.com/breakingnews/2008/05/dad_appeals_teen_sons_circumci.html|title=Dad appeals teen son's circumcision to U.S. Supreme Court|date=May 2008 |work=[[The Oregonian]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; but his appeal was rejected. The case then returned to the trial court.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.oregonlive.com/politics/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/news/1223344525313320.xml&amp;coll=7&amp;thispage=1|title=U.S. Supreme Court rejects Oregon's circumcision, abortion cases|work=[[The Oregonian]] | first=Ashbel S.|last=Green|date=7 October 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; When the trial court interviewed the couple's son, now 14 years old, the boy stated that he did not want to be circumcised. This also provided the necessary circumstances to allow the boy to change residence to live with his mother. The boy was not circumcised.

'''Other disputes'''

In September 2004 the [[North Dakota Supreme Court]] rejected a mother's attempt to prosecute her doctor for circumcising her child without fully informing her of the consequences of the procedure. The judge and jury found that the plaintiffs were adequately informed of possible complications, and the jury further found that it is not incumbent on the doctors to describe every &quot;insignificant&quot; risk.&lt;ref name = &quot;FargoForum2004&quot;&gt;{{cite news
| title       = Hawley mother loses appeal
| first       = Janelle
| last        = Cole
| url         = http://www.cirp.org/news/theforum09-04-04/
| format      = [[WP:CONV|convenience link]]
| newspaper   = [[The Forum of Fargo-Moorhead]]
| publisher   = [[Forum Communications]]
| date        = 4 September 2004
| accessdate  =9 November 2011
| quote       = The mother who unsuccessfully sued MeritCare Hospital and one of its doctors over her infant son's circumcision won't get a new trial, the North Dakota Supreme Court said Friday. Anita Flatt of Hawley, Minn., also will have to pay more than $58,000 in costs the doctor and hospital incurred defending themselves, the court ruled. The justices rejected Flatt's argument that she received inadequate information before consenting to her son's circumcision shortly after his birth in 1997. If she had had more information, she would not have consented, she said....Jurors agreed with defense attorneys' arguments that Flatt had been told of the possible complications and that there is no need for doctors to outline every possible &quot;insignificant&quot; risk.
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In March 2009 a [[Fulton County, Georgia|Fulton County, Ga.]], State Court jury awarded $2.3 million in damages to a 4-year-old boy and his mother for a botched circumcision in which too much tissue was removed causing permanent disfigurement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.law.com/jsp/article.jsp?id=1202429531287 |author=Katheryn Hayes Tucker |title=Jury Awards $2.3 Million for Botched Circumcision |date=31 March 2009 |publisher=Law.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 2010 an eight-day-old boy was circumcised in a Florida hospital against the stated wishes of the parents. The hospital admitted that the boy was circumcised by mistake; the mother has sued the hospital and the doctor involved in the case.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.miamiherald.com/2010/09/15/1826768/moms-sues-hospital-over-babys.html |title=Accidental circumcision leads to lawsuit, protest |author=Fred Tasker |date=15 August 2010 |work=The Miami Herald |publisher=MiamiHerald.com |accessdate=17 September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Khitan (circumcision)]]
* [[Children's rights]]
* [[Ethics of circumcision]]
* [[Forced circumcision]]
* [[FGM]]
* [[Violence against men]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
* William E. Brigman. [http://www.cirp.org/library/legal/brigman/ Circumcision as Child Abuse: The Legal and Constitutional Issues.] 23 J Fam Law 337 (1985).
* Rich Winkel. [http://www.math.missouri.edu/~rich/MGM/primer.html Male Circumcision in the USA: A Human Rights Primer]
* Ross Povenmire. [http://www.cirp.org/library/legal/povenmire/ Do Parents Have the Legal Authority to Consent to the Surgical Amputation of Normal, Healthy Tissue From Their Infant Children?: The Practice of Circumcision in the United States.] 7 Journal of Gender, Social Policy &amp; the Law 87 (1998–1999).
* Gregory J Boyle, J. Steven Svoboda, Christopher P Price, J Neville Turner. [http://www.cirp.org/library/legal/boyle1/ Circumcision of Healthy Boys: Criminal Assault?] 7 Journal of Law and Medicine 301 (2000). The authors are leading anti-circumcision campaigners.
* Peter W. Adler. [http://rjolpi.richmond.edu/archive/Adler_Formatted.pdf Is Circumcision Legal?] 16(3) Richmond J. L. &amp; Pub. Int. 439 (2013).
* Amicus curiae briefs filed in Oregon circumcision case:
** [https://web.archive.org/web/20080227114043/http://www.doctorsopposingcircumcision.org/pdf/2007-04BoldtReview.pdf Amicus Brief without attachments (Doctors Opposing Circumcision)]
** [https://web.archive.org/web/20080227114042/http://www.doctorsopposingcircumcision.org/pdf/2007-07BoldtMerits.pdf Amicus Brief on the Merits (Doctors Opposing Circumcision)]
** [https://web.archive.org/web/20080227114042/http://www.ouradio.org/images/uploads/Oregon_Circumcision.pdf Amicus Brief on the Merits (American Jewish Congress, American Jewish Committee, Anti-Defamation League, and Union of Orthodox Jewish Congregations of America)]

{{Circumcision series}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Circumcision And Law}}
[[Category:Circumcision debate]]
[[Category:Tort law]]
[[Category:Health law]]</text>
      <sha1>7ed3xhk4qm99cvjgvebfk1moib8xdle</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
