  <page>
    <title>Corporation</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7485</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941521304</id>
      <parentid>941521300</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-19T02:21:05Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ClueBot NG</username>
        <id>13286072</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverting possible vandalism by [[Special:Contribs/92.6.15.23|92.6.15.23]] to version by PohranicniStraze. [[WP:CBFP|Report False Positive?]] Thanks, [[WP:CBNG|ClueBot NG]]. (3701023) (Bot)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{other uses}}
{{Redirect|Corporate|other uses|Corporate (disambiguation)}}
{{pp-pc1}}
{{Redir|Corp.|a common misspelling of copyright|Copr.}}
{{short description|Separate legal entity that has been incorporated through a legislative or registration process established through legislation}}
{{Companies law}}
[[File:New McDonald's restaurant in Mount Pleasant, Iowa.jpg|thumb|upright=0.95|[[McDonald's|McDonald's Corporation]] is one of the most recognizable corporations in the world.]]

A '''corporation''' is an organization—usually a group of people or a [[company]]—authorized by the state to act as a single entity (a legal entity; a [[legal person]] in legal context) and recognized as such in law for certain purposes. Early incorporated entities were established by [[charter]] (i.e. by an ''ad hoc'' act granted by a monarch or passed by a parliament or legislature). Most [[jurisdiction]]s now allow the creation of new corporations through [[List of company registers|registration]].

Corporations come in many different types but are usually divided by the law of the jurisdiction where they are chartered based on two aspects: by whether they can issue [[stock]], or by whether they are formed to make a [[profit (accounting)|profit]] .&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.corpnet.com/types-of-corporations/#gfp|title=Types Of Corporations {{!}} Incorporate A Business|website=www.corpnet.com|language=en|access-date=2017-06-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; Corporations can be divided by the number of owners: corporation aggregate or  [[corporation sole]]. The subject of this article is a corporation aggregate. A corporation sole is a legal entity consisting of a single (&quot;sole&quot;) incorporated office, occupied by a single (&quot;sole&quot;)  [[natural person]].

Where local law distinguishes corporations by the ability to issue stock, corporations allowed to do so are referred to as &quot;stock corporations&quot;, ownership of the corporation is through stock, and owners of stock are referred to as &quot;stockholders&quot; or &quot;shareholders&quot;. Corporations not allowed to issue stock are referred to as &quot;non-stock&quot; corporations; those who are considered the owners of a non-stock corporation are persons (or other entities) who have obtained membership in the corporation and are referred to as a &quot;member&quot; of the corporation.

Corporations chartered in regions where they are distinguished by whether they are allowed to be for profit are referred to as &quot;for profit&quot; and &quot;not-for-profit&quot; corporations, respectively.

There is some overlap between stock/non-stock and for-profit/not-for-profit in that not-for-profit corporations are always non-stock as well. A for-profit corporation is almost always a stock corporation, but some for-profit corporations may choose to be non-stock&lt;!-- non-stock --&gt;. To simplify the explanation, whenever &quot;[[Shareholder|Stockholder]]&quot; or &quot;[[shareholder]]&quot; is used in the rest of this article to refer to a stock corporation, it is presumed to mean the same as &quot;member&quot; for a non-profit corporation or for a profit, non-stock corporation.

Registered corporations have [[legal personality]] and their shares are owned by shareholders&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Company Law |last1=Pettet |first1=B. G. |publisher=Pearson Education |year=2005 |page=151 |quote=Reading the above, makes it possible to forget that the shareholders are the ''owners'' of the company.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=The Law of Private Companies |first1=Thomas B. |last1=Courtney |publisher=Bloomsbury Professional |year=2002 |edition=2nd |at=4.001}}&lt;/ref&gt; whose liability is generally [[limited liability|limited]] to their investment.  Shareholders do not typically actively manage a corporation; shareholders instead elect or appoint a [[board of directors]] to control the corporation in a [[fiduciary]] capacity.  In most circumstances, a shareholder may also serve as a director or officer of a corporation.

In [[American English]], the word ''corporation'' is most often used to describe large [[Corporate law|business corporations]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.collinsdictionary.com/dictionary/american/corporation corporation]. CollinsDictionary.com. Collins English Dictionary – Complete &amp; Unabridged 11th Edition. Retrieved December 07, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; In [[British English]] and in the [[Commonwealth countries]], the term ''company'' is more widely used to describe the same sort of entity while the word ''corporation'' encompasses all incorporated entities. In American English, the word ''company'' can include entities such as [[partnership]]s that would not be referred to as companies in British English as they are not a [[separate legal entity]].

Late in the 19th century, a new form of company having the limited liability protections of a corporation, and the more favorable tax treatment of either a sole proprietorship or partnership was developed. While not a corporation, this new type of entity became very attractive as an alternative for corporations not needing to issue stock. In Germany, the organization was referred to as ''[[Gesellschaft mit beschränkter Haftung]]'' or ''GmbH''. In the last quarter of the 20th Century this new form of non-corporate organization became available in the United States and other countries, and was known as the ''[[limited liability company]]'' or ''LLC''. Since the GmbH and LLC forms of organization are technically not corporations (even though they have many of the same features), they will not be discussed in this article.

==History==
{{see also|List of oldest companies}}
[[File: Stora Kopparberg 1288.jpg|thumb|1/8 share of the [[Falun Mine|Stora Kopparberg]] mine, dated June 16, 1288.]]
The word &quot;corporation&quot; derives from ''corpus'', the [[Latin]] word for body, or a &quot;body of people&quot;. By the time of [[Justinian I|Justinian]] (reigned 527–565), [[Roman law]] recognized a range of corporate entities under the names ''universitas'', ''corpus'' or ''collegium''. These included the state itself (the ''Populus Romanus''), municipalities, and such private associations as sponsors of a [[Cult (religious practice)|religious cult]], [[Burial society|burial clubs]], political groups, and guilds of craftsmen or traders. Such bodies commonly had the right to own property and make contracts, to receive gifts and legacies, to sue and be sued, and, in general, to perform legal acts through representatives. Private associations were granted designated privileges and liberties by the emperor.&lt;ref&gt;Harold Joseph Berman, ''Law and Revolution'' (vol. 1)'': The Formation of the Western Legal Tradition'', Cambridge: Harvard University Press, 1983, pp. 215–216. {{ISBN|0-674-51776-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Entities which carried on business and were the subjects of legal rights were found in [[ancient Rome]], and the [[Maurya Empire]] in ancient India.&lt;ref&gt;Vikramaditya S. Khanna (2005). [http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id= ''The Economic History of the Corporate Form in Ancient India.''] [[University of Michigan]].&lt;/ref&gt; In medieval Europe, churches became incorporated, as did local governments, such as the [[Pope]] and the [[City of London Corporation]]. The point was that the incorporation would survive longer than the lives of any particular member, existing in perpetuity. The alleged oldest commercial corporation in the world, the [[Falun Mine|Stora Kopparberg]] mining community in [[Falun]], [[Sweden]], obtained a [[charter]] from King [[Magnus IV of Sweden|Magnus Eriksson]] in 1347.

In [[Middle Ages|medieval times]], traders would do business through [[common law]] constructs, such as [[partnership]]s. Whenever people acted together with a view to profit, the law deemed that a partnership arose. Early [[guild]]s and [[Livery company|livery companies]] were also often involved in the [[restraint of trade|regulation of competition]] between traders.

===Mercantilism===
{{See also|Mercantilism}}
[[File:Vereenigde Oostindische Compagnie spiegelretourschip Amsterdam replica.jpg|thumb|upright=1.1|Replica of an [[East Indiaman]] of the [[Dutch East India Company]]/[[United East Indies Company]]. The Dutch East India Company ([[Vereenigde Oostindische Compagnie|VOC]])&lt;ref&gt;Gepken-Jager, Ella; van Solinge, Gerard; Timmermann, Levinus (eds.): ''VOC 1602–2002: 400 Years of Company Law'' (Series Law of Business and Finance, Vol. 6). (Deventer: Kluwer Legal Publishers, 2005, {{ISBN|90-13-01915-3}})&lt;/ref&gt; is often considered by many to be the first historical model of the modern corporation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.lrb.co.uk/v23/n07/murray-sayle/japan-goes-dutch |title=Japan goes Dutch |pages=3–7 |publisher=[[London Review of Books]], Vol. 23 No. 7  |author=[[Murray Sayle|Sayle, Murray]] |date=5 April 2001 |accessdate=23 March 2018|newspaper=London Review of Books }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;TimothyBrook&quot;&gt;[[Timothy Brook|Brook, Timothy]]: ''Vermeer's Hat: The Seventeenth Century and the Dawn of the Global World''. (Profile Books, 2008, {{ISBN|1-84668-120-0}}).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Wilson, Eric Michael: ''The Savage Republic: De Indis of Hugo Grotius, Republicanism and Dutch Hegemony within the Early Modern World-System (c. 1600–1619)''. (Martinus Nijhoff, 2008, {{ISBN|978-90-04-16788-9}}), pp. 215–217.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Jonker, Joost; Gelderblom, Oscar; de Jong, Abe (2013). ''The Formative Years of the Modern Corporation: The Dutch East India Company VOC, 1602–1623''. (The Journal of Economic History / Volume 73 / Issue 04 / December 2013, pp.&amp;nbsp;1050–1076)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.economicstudents.com/2014/04/voc-the-birth-of-the-modern-corporation/# |author=Tarrant, Nicholas |title=The VOC: The Birth of the Modern Corporation |publisher=The Economics Student Society of Australia |date=29 Apr 2014 |accessdate=23 March 2018 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.pbs.org/wgbh/roadshow/fts/corpuschristi_201205A19.html |author=Phelan, Ben |title=Dutch East India Company: The World's First Multinational |publisher=[[PBS.org]] (PBS Online) |date= 7 January 2013 |accessdate=13 March 2018 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.businessinsider.com/rise-and-fall-of-united-east-india-2013-11 |author= Taylor, Bryan |title=The Rise and Fall of the Largest Corporation in History |publisher=[[BusinessInsider.com]] |date= 6 November 2013 |accessdate=13 March 2018 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://badatsports.com/2016/in-the-late-afternoon-of-modernism-an-interview-with-graham-harman/ |author=Picard, Caroline |title=In The Late Afternoon of Modernism: An Interview with Graham Harman |publisher=Badatsports.com |date=2 August 2016 |accessdate=23 March 2018 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The VOC was also the first permanently organized [[limited liability company|limited-liability]] [[joint-stock corporation]], with a permanent [[Financial capital|capital base]].&lt;ref&gt;Steensgaard, Niels (1982). &quot;The Dutch East India Company as an Institutional Innovation&quot;, in Maurice Aymard (ed.), ''Dutch Capitalism and World Capitalism / Capitalisme hollandais et capitalisme mondial'' (Studies in Modern Capitalism / Etudes sur le capitalisme moderne), pp.&amp;nbsp;235–257&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Niall Ferguson|Ferguson, Niall]] (2002). ''Empire: The Rise and Demise of the British World Order and the Lessons for Global Power'', p. 15.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Smith, B. Mark (2003). ''A History of the Global Stock Market: From Ancient Rome to Silicon Valley''. (University of Chicago Press, {{ISBN|978-0-226-76404-7}}), p. 17.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Von Nordenflycht, Andrew: ''The Great Expropriation: Interpreting the Innovation of &quot;Permanent Capital&quot; at the Dutch East India Company'', in ''Origins of Shareholder Advocacy'', edited by Jonathan GS Koppell (Palgrave Macmillan, 2011), pp.&amp;nbsp;89–98&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Clarke, Thomas; Branson, Douglas (2012). ''The Sage Handbook of Corporate Governance (Sage Handbooks)''. (Sage Publications Ltd., {{ISBN|978-1-4129-2980-6}}, p. 431). &quot;The [[British East India Company|EIC]] first issued permanent shares in 1657 (Harris, 2005: 45).&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;]]Dutch and English chartered companies, such as the [[Dutch East India Company]] (VOC) and the [[Hudson's Bay Company]], were created to lead the colonial ventures of European nations in the 17th century. Acting under a charter sanctioned by the Dutch government, the Dutch East India Company defeated [[Portugal|Portuguese]] forces and established itself in the [[Maluku Islands|Moluccan Islands]] in order to profit from the [[Europe]]an demand for [[spice]]s. Investors in the VOC were issued paper certificates as proof of share ownership, and were able to trade their shares on the original [[Amsterdam Stock Exchange]]. Shareholders were also explicitly granted [[limited liability]] in the company's royal charter.&lt;ref&gt;Om Prakash, ''European Commercial Enterprise in Pre-Colonial India'' (Cambridge University Press, Cambridge 1998).&lt;/ref&gt;[[File:Vereinigte Ostindische Compagnie bond - Middelburg - Amsterdam - 1622.jpg|thumb|upright=0.9|A [[bond (finance)|bond]] issued by the Dutch East India Company (VOC), dating from 1623, for the amount of 2,400 florins]]

In England, the government created corporations under a [[royal charter]] or an [[Act of Parliament]] with the grant of a [[monopoly]] over a specified territory. The best-known example, established in 1600, was the [[East India Company]] of [[London]]. [[Elizabeth I of England|Queen Elizabeth I]] granted it the exclusive right to trade with all countries to the east of the [[Cape of Good Hope]]. Some corporations at this time would act on the government's behalf, bringing in revenue from its exploits abroad. Subsequently, the Company became [[Company rule in India|increasingly integrated]] with English and later British military and colonial policy, just as most corporations were essentially dependent on the [[Royal Navy]]'s ability to control trade routes.

Labeled by both contemporaries and historians as &quot;the grandest society of merchants in the universe&quot;, the English East India Company would come to symbolize the dazzlingly rich potential of the corporation, as well as new methods of business that could be both brutal and exploitative.&lt;ref&gt;John Keay, ''The Honorable Company: A History of the English East India Company'' (MacMillan, New York 1991).&lt;/ref&gt; On 31 December 1600, Queen Elizabeth I granted the company a 15-year monopoly on trade to and from the [[East Indies]] and [[Africa]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://web.utk.edu/~gerard/romanticpolitics/britisheastindia.html|title=British East India Company|first=Gerard Cohen-Vrignaud, Stephanie Metz, Jody Dunville, Shannon Heath, Julia P. McLeod, Kat Powell, Brent Robida, John Stromski, Brandon|last=Haynes|publisher=|accessdate=19 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; By 1711, shareholders in the East India Company were earning a [[return on investment|return on their investment]] of almost 150 per cent. Subsequent stock offerings demonstrated just how lucrative the Company had become. Its first stock offering in 1713–1716 raised £418,000, its second in 1717–1722 raised £1.6 million.&lt;ref&gt;''Ibid.'' at p. 113&lt;/ref&gt;

A similar [[chartered company]], the [[South Sea Company]], was established in 1711 to trade in the Spanish South American colonies, but met with less success. The South Sea Company's monopoly rights were supposedly backed by the [[Treaty of Utrecht]], signed in 1713 as a settlement following the [[War of the Spanish Succession]], which gave [[Kingdom of Great Britain|Great Britain]] an ''[[asiento]]'' to trade in the region for thirty years. In fact the Spanish remained hostile and let only one ship a year enter. Unaware of the problems, investors in Britain, enticed by extravagant promises of profit from [[Corporate promoter|company promoters]] bought thousands of shares. By 1717, the South Sea Company was so wealthy (still having done no real business) that it assumed the [[Government debt|public debt]] of the British government. This accelerated the inflation of the share price further, as did the [[Bubble Act|Bubble Act 1720]], which (possibly with the motive of protecting the South Sea Company from competition) prohibited the establishment of any companies without a Royal Charter. The share price rose so rapidly that people began buying shares merely in order to sell them at a higher price, which in turn led to higher share prices. This was the first [[Economic bubble|speculative bubble]] the country had seen, but by the end of 1720, the bubble had &quot;burst&quot;, and the share price sank from £1000 to under £100. As bankruptcies and recriminations ricocheted through government and high society, the mood against corporations and errant directors was bitter.

[[File:South-sea-bubble-chart.png|thumb|left|Chart of the [[South Sea Company]]'s stock prices. The rapid inflation of the stock value in the 1710s led to the [[Bubble Act|Bubble Act 1720]], which restricted the establishment of companies without a [[royal charter]].]]
In the late 18th century, [[Stewart Kyd]], the author of the first treatise on [[corporate law]] in English, defined a corporation as:

{{quote|a collection of many individuals united into one body, under a special denomination, having [[perpetual succession]] under an artificial form, and vested, by policy of the law, with the capacity of acting, in several respects, as an individual, particularly of taking and granting property, of contracting obligations, and of suing and being sued, of enjoying privileges and immunities in common, and of exercising a variety of political rights, more or less extensive, according to the design of its institution, or the powers conferred upon it, either at the time of its creation, or at any subsequent period of its existence.|A Treatise on the Law of Corporations, Stewart Kyd (1793–1794)}}

===Development of modern company law===
Due to the late 18th century abandonment of [[Mercantilism|mercantilist]] economic theory and the rise of [[classical liberalism]] and [[laissez-faire]] economic theory due to a revolution in [[economics]] led by [[Adam Smith]] and other economists, corporations transitioned from being government or [[guild]] affiliated entities to being public and private economic entities free of governmental directions.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://political-economy.com/adam-smith-laissez-faire/|title=Adam Smith Laissez-Faire|website=political-economy.com|language=en-US|access-date=2017-06-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; Smith wrote in his 1776 work ''[[The Wealth of Nations]]'' that mass corporate activity could not match private entrepreneurship, because people in charge of others' money would not exercise as much care as they would with their own.&lt;ref&gt;A Smith, ''[[An Inquiry into the Nature and Causes of the Wealth of Nations]]'' (1776), Book V, ch 1, para 107.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Deregulation====
[[File: Jack and the Giant Joint-Stock.jpg|thumb|&quot;Jack and the Giant Joint-Stock&quot;, a cartoon in ''Town Talk'' (1858) satirizing the 'monster' joint-stock economy that came into being after the [[Joint Stock Companies Act 1844]].]]
The British Bubble Act 1720's prohibition on establishing companies remained in force until its repeal in 1825. By this point, the [[Industrial Revolution]] had gathered pace, pressing for legal change to facilitate business activity.&lt;ref&gt;See [[Bubble Companies, etc. Act 1825]], 6 Geo 4, c 91&lt;/ref&gt; The repeal was the beginning of a gradual lifting on restrictions, though business ventures (such as those chronicled by [[Charles Dickens]] in ''[[Martin Chuzzlewit]]'') under primitive companies legislation were often scams. Without cohesive regulation, proverbial operations like the &quot;Anglo-Bengalee Disinterested Loan and Life Assurance Company&quot; were undercapitalised ventures promising no hope of success except for richly paid promoters.&lt;ref&gt;See [[C Dickens]], ''[[Martin Chuzzlewit]]'' (1843) [[s:Martin Chuzzlewit/Chapter 27|ch 27]]&lt;/ref&gt;

The process of [[incorporation (business)|incorporation]] was possible only through a [[royal charter]] or a [[local and personal Acts of Parliament in the United Kingdom|private act]] and was limited, owing to Parliament's jealous protection of the privileges and advantages thereby granted. As a result, many businesses came to be operated as [[Voluntary association|unincorporated associations]] with possibly thousands of members. Any consequent [[Lawsuit|litigation]] had to be carried out in the joint names of all the members and was almost impossibly cumbersome. Though Parliament would sometimes grant a private act to allow an individual to represent the whole in legal proceedings, this was a narrow and necessarily costly expedient, allowed only to established companies.

Then, in 1843, [[William Ewart Gladstone|William Gladstone]] became the chairman of a Parliamentary Committee on Joint Stock Companies, which led to the [[Joint Stock Companies Act 1844]], regarded as the first modern piece of company law.&lt;ref&gt;''Report of the Parliamentary Committee on Joint Stock Companies'' (1844) in ''British Parliamentary Papers'', vol. VII&lt;/ref&gt; The Act created the [[Registrar of Companies|Registrar of Joint Stock Companies]], empowered to register companies by a two-stage process. The first, provisional, stage cost £5 and did not confer corporate status, which arose after completing the second stage for another £5. For the first time in history, it was possible for ordinary people through a simple registration procedure to incorporate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=LQflMqcZyOoC|title=Introduction to Company Law|author=Paul Lyndon Davies|year=2010|publisher=Oxford University Press|page=1|isbn=978-0-19-960132-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; The advantage of establishing a company as a [[Legal personality|separate legal person]] was mainly administrative, as a unified entity under which the rights and duties of all investors and managers could be channeled.

====Limited liability====
However, there was still no limited liability and company members could still be held responsible for unlimited losses by the company.&lt;ref&gt;''Re Sea Fire and Life Assurance Co., Greenwood's Case'' (1854) 3 De GM&amp;G 459&lt;/ref&gt; The next, crucial development, then, was the [[Limited Liability Act 1855]], passed at the behest of the then Vice President of the Board of Trade, Mr. [[Robert Lowe]]. This allowed investors to limit their liability in the event of business failure to the amount they invested in the company – [[shareholder]]s were still liable directly to [[creditor]]s, but just for the unpaid portion of their [[share (finance)|shares]]. (The principle that shareholders are liable to the corporation had been introduced in the Joint Stock Companies Act 1844).

The 1855 Act allowed limited liability to companies of more than 25 members (shareholders). [[Insurance|Insurance companies]] were excluded from the act, though it was standard practice for insurance contracts to exclude action against individual members. Limited liability for insurance companies was allowed by the [[Companies Act 1862]].

This prompted the English periodical ''[[The Economist]]'' to write in 1855 that &quot;never, perhaps, was a change so vehemently and generally demanded, of which the importance was so much overrated.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Graeme G. Acheson &amp; John D. Turner, ''The Impact of Limited Liability on Ownership and Control: Irish Banking, 1877–1914'', School of Management and Economics, Queen's University of Belfast, available at {{cite web|url=http://www.ehs.org.uk/ehs/conference2004/assets/AchesonTurnerPaper.pdf |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2011-11-16 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120113082939/http://www.ehs.org.uk/ehs/conference2004/assets/AchesonTurnerPaper.pdf |archivedate=2012-01-13 |df= }} and {{cite web|url=http://www1.fee.uva.nl/fm/conference/legal/ehr_2006_%20Acheson%20and%20Turner.pdf |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2011-11-16 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120111172110/http://www1.fee.uva.nl/fm/conference/legal/ehr_2006_%20Acheson%20and%20Turner.pdf |archivedate=2012-01-11 |df= }}.&lt;/ref&gt; The major error of this judgment was recognised by the same magazine more than 70 years later, when it claimed that, &quot;[t]he economic historian of the future... may be inclined to assign to the nameless inventor of the principle of limited liability, as applied to trading corporations, a place of honour with [[James Watt|Watt]] and [[George Stephenson|Stephenson]], and other pioneers of the Industrial Revolution. &quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Economist'', December 18, 1926, at 1053, as quoted in Mahoney, ''supra'', at 875.&lt;/ref&gt;

These two features – a simple registration procedure and limited liability – were subsequently codified into the landmark 1856 [[Joint Stock Companies Act 1856|Joint Stock Companies Act]]. This was subsequently consolidated with a number of other statutes in the Companies Act 1862, which remained in force for the rest of the century, up to and including the time of the decision in ''[[Salomon v A Salomon &amp; Co Ltd]]''.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Salomon v A Salomon &amp; Co Ltd]]'' [1897] AC 22&lt;/ref&gt;

The legislation shortly gave way to a railway boom, and from then, the numbers of companies formed soared. In the later nineteenth century, depression took hold, and just as company numbers had boomed, many began to implode and fall into insolvency. Much strong academic, legislative and judicial opinion was opposed to the notion that businessmen could escape accountability for their role in the failing businesses.

====Further developments====
[[File:LordLindley cropp.jpg|thumb|right|[[Nathaniel Lindley, Baron Lindley|Lindley LJ]] was the leading expert on partnerships and company law in the ''[[Salomon v A Salomon &amp; Co Ltd|Salomon v. Salomon &amp; Co.]]'' case. The landmark case confirmed the [[corporate identity|distinct corporate identity]] of the company.]]
In 1892, [[Germany]] introduced the [[Gesellschaft mit beschränkter Haftung]] with a separate [[legal personality]] and limited liability even if all the shares of the company were held by only one person. This inspired other countries to introduce corporations of this kind.

The last significant development in the history of companies was the 1897 decision of the House of Lords in ''[[Salomon v A Salomon &amp; Co Ltd|Salomon v. Salomon &amp; Co.]]'' where the House of Lords confirmed the separate legal personality of the company, and that the liabilities of the company were separate and distinct from those of its owners.

In the [[United States]], forming a corporation usually required an act of legislation until the late 19th century. Many private firms, such as [[Andrew Carnegie|Carnegie]]'s steel company and [[John D. Rockefeller|Rockefeller]]'s [[Standard Oil]], avoided the corporate model for this reason (as a [[Trust law|trust]]). State governments began to adopt more permissive corporate laws from the early 19th century, although these were all restrictive in design, often with the intention of preventing corporations from gaining too much wealth and power.&lt;ref name=&quot;Corporate Law textbook&quot;&gt;{{Citation|last1=Smiddy|first1=Linda O.|last2=Cunningham|first2=Lawrence A.|title=Corporations and Other Business Organizations: Cases, Materials, Problems|publisher=LexisNexis|year=2010|edition=Seventh|pages=228–231, 241|isbn=978-1-4224-7659-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[New Jersey]] was the first state to adopt an &quot;enabling&quot; corporate law, with the goal of attracting more business to the state,&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=ftzqaBv7X_sC&amp;pg=PA159&amp;lpg=PA159&amp;dq=%22new+jersey%22+%22first+state%22+%22business+corporation%22&amp;source=web&amp;ots=n5Af0liBo5&amp;sig=A2RRh_zOyS7W3CCMK4ZyG6Scmwk The Law of Business Organizations], Cengage Learning&lt;/ref&gt; in 1896. In 1899, Delaware followed New Jersey's lead with the enactment of an enabling corporate statute, but Delaware only became the leading corporate state after the enabling provisions of the 1896 New Jersey corporate law were repealed in 1913.&lt;ref name = &quot;Corporate Law textbook&quot;/&gt;

The end of the 19th century saw the emergence of [[Holding company|holding companies]] and corporate [[Mergers and acquisitions|mergers]] creating larger corporations with dispersed shareholders. Countries began enacting [[Competition law|antitrust]] laws to prevent anti-competitive practices and corporations were granted more legal rights and protections.
The 20th century saw a proliferation of laws allowing for the creation of corporations by registration across the world, which helped to drive economic booms in many countries before and after World War I. Another major post World War I shift was toward the development of [[Conglomerate (company)|conglomerates]], in which large corporations purchased smaller corporations to expand their industrial base.

Starting in the 1980s, many countries with large state-owned corporations moved toward [[privatization]], the selling of publicly owned (or 'nationalised') services and enterprises to corporations. [[Deregulation]] (reducing the regulation of corporate activity) often accompanied privatization as part of a laissez-faire policy.

==Ownership and control==
A corporation is, at least in theory, owned and controlled by its members. In a [[joint-stock company]] the members are known as shareholders and each of their shares in the ownership, control, and profits of the corporation is determined by the portion of shares in the company that they own. Thus a person who owns a quarter of the shares of a joint-stock company owns a quarter of the company, is entitled to a quarter of the profit (or at least a quarter of the profit given to shareholders as dividends) and has a quarter of the votes capable of being cast at general meetings.

In another kind of corporation, the legal document which established the corporation or which contains its current rules will determine who the corporation's members are. Who a member is depends on what kind of corporation is involved. In a [[worker cooperative]], the members are people who work for the cooperative. In a [[credit union]], the members are people who have accounts with the credit union.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Principles of Finance |first1=Scott |last1=Besley |first2=Eugene |last2=Brigham |publisher=Cengage Learning |year=2008 |isbn=978-0-324-65588-9 |edition=4th |page=[https://archive.org/details/principlesoffina0000besl_4edi/page/105 105] |url=https://archive.org/details/principlesoffina0000besl_4edi/page/105 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The day-to-day activities of a corporation are typically controlled by individuals appointed by the members. In some cases, this will be a single individual but more commonly corporations are controlled by a committee or by committees. Broadly speaking, there are two kinds of committee structure.
* A single committee known as a [[board of directors]] is the method favored in most [[common law]] countries. Under this model, the board of directors is composed of both executive and non-executive directors, the latter being meant to supervise the former's management of the company.
* A two-tiered committee structure with a [[supervisory board]] and a [[Vorstand|managing board]] is common in [[civil law (legal system)|civil law]] countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Company &amp; Commercial – Netherlands: In a nutshell – one-tier boards |date=10 April 2012 |publisher=International Law Office |url=http://www.internationallawoffice.com/newsletters/detail.aspx?g=f4815d3b-0de3-44d3-81d8-16114b49b8d8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Formation===
Historically, corporations were created by a charter granted by government. Today, corporations are usually registered with the state, province, or national government and regulated by the laws enacted by that government. Registration is the main prerequisite to the corporation's assumption of limited liability. The law sometimes requires the corporation to designate its principal address, as well as a [[registered agent]] (a person or company designated to receive legal service of process). It may also be required to designate an [[Law of agency|agent]] or other legal representative of the corporation.{{citation needed|date=August 2012}}

Generally, a corporation files [[articles of incorporation]] with the government, laying out the general nature of the corporation, the amount of stock it is authorized to issue, and the names and addresses of directors. Once the articles are approved, the corporation's directors meet to create [[By-law|bylaws]] that govern the internal functions of the corporation, such as meeting procedures and officer positions.

The law of the jurisdiction in which a corporation operates will regulate most of its internal activities, as well as its finances. If a corporation operates outside its home state, it is often required to register with other governments as a [[foreign corporation]], and is almost always subject to laws of its host state pertaining to [[employment]], [[crime]]s, [[contract]]s, [[Lawsuit|civil actions]], and the like.{{citation needed|date=August 2012}}

===Naming===
Corporations generally have a distinct name. Historically, some corporations were named after their membership: for instance, &quot;The President and Fellows of Harvard College&quot;. Nowadays, corporations in most jurisdictions have a distinct name that does not need to make reference to their membership. In Canada, this possibility is taken to its logical extreme: many smaller Canadian corporations have no names at all, merely numbers based on a registration number (for example, &quot;12345678 Ontario Limited&quot;), which is assigned by the provincial or territorial government where the corporation incorporates.

In most countries, corporate names include a term or an abbreviation that denotes the corporate status of the entity (for example, &quot;Incorporated&quot; or &quot;Inc.&quot; in the United States) or the limited liability of its members (for example, &quot;Limited&quot; or &quot;Ltd.&quot;). These terms vary by jurisdiction and language. In some jurisdictions, they are mandatory, and in others they are not.&lt;ref&gt;The U.S. state of California is an example of a jurisdiction that does not require corporations to indicate corporate status in their names, except for close corporations. The drafters of the 1977 revision of the California General Corporation Law considered the possibility of forcing all California corporations to have a name indicating corporate status, but decided against it because of the huge number of corporations that would have had to change their names, and the lack of any evidence that anyone had been harmed in California by entities whose corporate status was not immediately apparent from their names. However, the 1977 drafters were able to impose the current disclosure requirement for close corporations. See Harold Marsh, Jr., R. Roy Finkle, Larry W. Sonsini, and Ann Yvonne Walker, ''Marsh's California Corporation Law'', 4th ed., vol. 1 (New York: Aspen Publishers, 2004), 5–15 — 5–16.&lt;/ref&gt; Their use puts everybody on [[constructive notice]] that they are dealing with an entity whose [[legal liability|liability]] is limited: one can only collect from whatever assets the entity still controls when one obtains a judgment against it.

Some jurisdictions do not allow the use of the word &quot;'''company'''&quot; alone to denote corporate status, since the word &quot;[[company]]&quot; may refer to a partnership or some other form of collective ownership (in the United States it can be used by a [[sole proprietorship]] but this is not generally the case elsewhere).{{citation needed|date=August 2012}}

==Personhood==
Despite not being individual human beings, corporations, as far as US law is concerned, are [[Legal personality|legal persons]], and have many of the same rights and responsibilities as  [[natural person]]s do. For example, a corporation can own property, and can sue or be sued. Corporations can exercise [[human rights]] against real individuals and the state,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=The Human Rights of Companies: Exploring the Structure of ECHR Protection |first1=Marius |last1=Emberland |publisher=Oxford University Press |year=2006 |isbn=978-0-19-928983-7 |page=1 |url=http://fds.oup.com/www.oup.co.uk/pdf/0-19-928983-2.pdf |accessdate=2 June 2012 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120617104051/http://fds.oup.com/www.oup.co.uk/pdf/0-19-928983-2.pdf |archive-date=17 June 2012 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;e.g. [[South African Constitution]] Sect.8, especially Art.(4)&lt;/ref&gt; and they can themselves be responsible for human rights violations.&lt;ref&gt;Phillip I. Blumberg, The Multinational Challenge to Corporation Law: The Search for a New Corporate Personality, (1993) discusses the controversial nature of additional rights being granted to corporations.&lt;/ref&gt; Corporations can be &quot;dissolved&quot; either by statutory operation, order of court, or voluntary action on the part of shareholders. [[Insolvency]] may result in a form of corporate failure, when creditors force the liquidation and dissolution of the corporation under court order,&lt;ref&gt;See, for example, the Business Corporations Act (B.C.) [SBC 2002] ChapterH 57, Part 10&lt;/ref&gt; but it most often results in a restructuring of corporate holdings. Corporations can even be convicted of criminal offenses, such as [[fraud]] and [[manslaughter]]. However, corporations are not considered living entities in the way that humans are.&lt;ref&gt;e.g. [[Corporate Manslaughter and Corporate Homicide Act 2007]]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Columns-list|colwidth=30em|
'''Law'''
* [[Commercial law]]
* [[United States corporate law]]
* [[European corporate law]]
* [[German company law]]
* [[History of company law in the United Kingdom]]
* [[United Kingdom company law]]

'''Other'''
* [[Anti-corporate activism]]
* [[Business attire]]
* [[Blocker corporation]]
* [[Community interest company]]
* [[Cooperative]]
* [[Corporate crime]]
* [[Corporate governance]]
* [[Corporate group]]
* [[Corporate haven]]
* [[Corporate welfare]]
* [[Corporation sole]]
* [[Corporatism]]
* [[Corporatization]]
* [[Decentralized autonomous organization]]
* [[Evil corporation]]
* [[Fascism]]
* [[Good standing]]
* [[State-owned enterprise|Government-owned corporation]]
* [[History of competition law]]
* [[Incorporation (business)]]
* [[Limited liability company]]
* [[Living wage]]
* [[Megacorporation]]
* [[Multinational corporation]]
* [[Nationalization]]
* [[Nonprofit corporation]]
* [[Organizational culture]]
* [[Preferred stock]]
* [[Privatization]]
* [[Professional corporation]] (PC or P.C.)
* [[Public limited company]] (PLC)
* [[Shelf corporation]]
* [[Small business]]
* [[South Sea Company]]
* [[Tulip mania]]
* [[United States antitrust law]]
* [[Unlimited company]]
* [[Unlimited liability corporation]]
}}

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
* [http://ssrn.com/abstract=1103644 A Comparative Bibliography: Regulatory Competition on Corporate Law]
* Blumberg, Phillip I., ''The Multinational Challenge to Corporation Law: The Search for a New Corporate Personality'', (1993)
* Bromberg, Alan R. ''Crane and Bromberg on Partnership''. 1968.
* Brown, Bruce. [http://www.astonisher.com/archives/corporation/corporation_intro.html ''The History of the Corporation''] (2003)
* Cadman, John William. ''The Corporation in New Jersey: Business and Politics, '', (1949)
* Conard, Alfred F. ''Corporations in Perspective''. 1976.
* Cooke, C.A., ''Corporation, Trust and Company: A Legal History'', (1950)
* Davis, John P. [http://socserv2.mcmaster.ca/~econ/ugcm/3ll3/davisjohn/index.html ''Corporations''] (1904)
* Davis, Joseph S. [http://socserv2.mcmaster.ca/~econ/ugcm/3ll3/davisjoe/index.html ''Essays in the Earlier History of American Corporations''] (1917)
* Dignam, A and Lowry, J (2006) Company Law, [[Oxford University Press]] {{ISBN|978-0-19-928936-3}}
* Dodd, Edwin Merrick. ''American Business Corporations until 1860, With Special Reference to Massachusetts'', (1954)
* DuBois, A.B. ''The English Business Company after the Bubble Act, '', (1938)
* Freedman, Charles. ''Joint-stock Enterprise in France, : From Privileged Company to Modern Corporation'' (1979)
* [[Ernst Freund|Freund, Ernst]]. [https://web.archive.org/web/20050129193644/http://socserv2.mcmaster.ca/~econ/ugcm/3ll3/freund/index.html MCMaster.ca], ''The Legal Nature of the Corporation'' (1897)
* Hallis, Frederick. ''Corporate Personality: A Study in Jurisprudence'' (1930)
* [[Robert Hessen|Hessen, Robert]]. ''In Defense of the Corporation''. Hoover Institute. 1979.
* Hunt, Bishop. ''The Development of the Business Corporation in England '' (1936)
* Klein and Coffee. ''Business Organization and Finance: Legal and Economic Principles''. Foundation. 2002.
* Majumdar, Ramesh Chandra. [http://socserv2.mcmaster.ca/~econ/ugcm/3ll3/majumdar/index.html ''Corporate Life in Ancient India''], (1920)
* Means, Robert Charles. ''Underdevelopment and the Development of Law: Corporations and Corporation Law in Nineteenth-century Colombia'', (1980)
* Micklethwait, John and Wooldridge, Adrian. ''The Company: a Short History of a Revolutionary Idea''. New York: Modern Library. 2003.
* Owen, Thomas. ''The Corporation under Russian Law, : A Study in Tsarist Economic Policy'' (1991)
* Rungta, Radhe Shyam. ''The Rise of the Business Corporation in India, 1851–1900'', (1970)
* Scott, W.R. [http://socserv2.mcmaster.ca/~econ/ugcm/3ll3/scott/index.html ''Constitution and Finance of English, Scottish and Irish Joint-Stock Companies to 1720''] (1912)
* [[Robert Sobel|Sobel, Robert]]. ''The Age of Giant Corporations: a Microeconomic History of American Business''. (1984)
* {{cite book |last1=Barnet |first1=Richard  |last2=Muller |first2=Ronald E. |title=Global Reach: The Power of the Multinational Corporation |url=https://archive.org/details/globalreachpower00barn |url-access=registration |publisher=Simon &amp; Schuster |year=1974 |location=New York}}
* PG Mahoney, 'Contract or Concession? An Essay on the History of Corporate Law' (2000) 34 Ga. Law Review 873
* PI Blumberg, ''The Multinational Challenge to Corporation Law'' (1993)
* PL Davies and LCB Gower, ''Principles of Modern Company Law'' (6th edn Sweet and Maxwell 1997) chapters 2–4
* RR Formoy, ''The Historical Foundations of Company Law'' (Sweet and Maxwell 1923) 21
* P Frentrop, ''A History of Corporate Governance 1602–2002'' (Brussels et al., 2003)
* S Kyd, ''A Treatise on the Law of Corporations'' (1793–1794)
* J Micklethwait and A Wooldridge, ''The company: A short history of a revolutionary idea'' (Modern Library 2003)
* W Blackstone, ''Commentaries on the Laws of England'' (1765) 455–473
* [[Adam Tooze|Tooze, Adam]], &quot;Democracy and Its Discontents&quot;, ''[[The New York Review of Books]]'', vol. LXVI, no. 10 (6 June 2019), pp.&amp;nbsp;52–53, 56–57.  &quot;Democracy has no clear answer for the mindless operation of [[bureaucracy|bureaucratic]] and [[technology|technological power]].  We may indeed be witnessing its extension in the form of [[artificial intelligence]] and [[robotics]].  Likewise, after decades of dire warning, the [[environmentalism|environmental problem]] remains fundamentally unaddressed.... Bureaucratic overreach and environmental catastrophe are precisely the kinds of slow-moving existential challenges that democracies deal with very badly.... Finally, there is the threat du jour:  corporations and the technologies they promote.&quot;  (pp.&amp;nbsp;56–57.)

==External links==
{{wikiquote|Corporations}}
* [[b:US Corporate Law|US Corporate Law]] at Wikibooks
* [http://www.brh.org.uk/dwtf2008/kcc.html an Audio from a talk about the history of corporations and the English Law by Barrister Daniel Bennett]

{{Aspects of corporations}}
{{Workplace}}
{{Portal bar|Companies}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Companies]]
[[Category:Business law]]
[[Category:Corporate law]]
[[Category:Corporations| ]]
[[Category:Legal entities]]
[[Category:Types of business entity]]</text>
      <sha1>f6a8l162wjdur7ankc43pfact2f5wdy</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
