  <page>
    <title>Catherine of Siena</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7471</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941729221</id>
      <parentid>941590622</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-20T08:52:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bluelink 2 books for [[Wikipedia:Verifiability|verifiability]]. [goog]) #IABot (v2.0) ([[User:GreenC bot|GreenC bot]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|14th-century Italian Dominican saint}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=February 2018}}
{{Infobox saint
| name           = Saint Catherine of Siena
| image          = File:Giovanni Battista Tiepolo 096.jpg
| caption        = ''St. Catherine of Siena'',&lt;br /&gt; by [[Giovanni Battista Tiepolo]]
|titles=Virgin, Patron of Europe (''Patrona Europae''), Stigmatist, [[Doctor of the Church]]
| birth_date     = 25 March 1347
| birth_place    = [[Siena]], [[Republic of Siena]]
| death_date     = 29 April 1380 (aged 33)
| death_place    = [[Rome]], [[Papal States]]
| venerated_in   = [[Catholic Church]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Anglican Communion]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://diobeth.typepad.com/files/holy-women-holy-men.pdf |title=Holy Men and Holy Women |website=Churchofengland.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[[Lutheranism]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.resurrectionpeople.org/saints.html |title=Notable Lutheran Saints |website=Resurrectionpeople.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| canonized_date = 29 June 1461
| canonized_by   = [[Pope Pius II]]
| major_shrine   = [[Santa Maria sopra Minerva]], [[Rome]] and {{Interlanguage link multi|Shrine of Saint Catherine (Siena)|it|Santuario di Santa Caterina (Siena)|lt=Shrine of Saint Catherine}}, [[Siena]]
| feast_day      = April 29; April 30 (Roman Calendar, 1628–1969)
| attributes     = [[Dominican Order|Dominican]] [[Religious habit|tertiaries' habit]], [[lilium|lily]], book, crucifix, heart, [[crown of thorns]], [[stigmata]], ring, dove, rose, skull, miniature church, miniature ship bearing [[Ecclesiastical heraldry|Papal coat of arms]]
| patronage      = against fire; bodily ills; Diocese of Allentown, Pennsylvania, USA; Europe; illness; Italy; [[Bambang, Nueva Vizcaya]], [[Samal, Bataan]], [[Philippines]]; miscarriages; people ridiculed for their piety; sexual temptation; sick people; sickness; [[nurse]]s
}}

'''Catherine of Siena''' (25 March 1347 – 29 April 1380), a laywoman associated with the [[Dominican Order]], was a mystic, activist, and author who had a great influence on Italian literature and the [[Catholic Church]]. Canonized in 1461, she is also a [[Doctor of the Church]].

She was born and raised in [[Siena]], and at an early age wanted to devote herself to [[God]], against the will of her parents. She joined the Dominican tertiaries. She made herself known very quickly by being marked by mystical phenomena such as invisible [[stigmata]] and a [[mystical marriage]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Classen2012p86&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Constance Classen|title=The Deepest Sense: A Cultural History of Touch|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=c1RC8kSUfgEC&amp;pg=PA86 |year=2012|publisher=University of Illinois Press|isbn=978-0-252-09440-8|pages=86–87}}&lt;/ref&gt; Her influence with [[Pope Gregory XI]] played a role in his decision to leave Avignon for [[Rome]]. She was then sent by him to negotiate peace with Florence. After Gregory XI's death and peace concluded, she returned to Siena. She dictated to secretaries her set of spiritual treatises ''The Dialogue of Divine Providence''. The [[Western Schism|Great Schism of the West]] led Catherine of Siena to go to Rome with the pope. She sent numerous letters to princes and cardinals to promote obedience to [[Pope Urban VI]] and defend what she calls the &quot;vessel of the Church.&quot; She died on 29 April 1380, exhausted by her penances. Urban VI celebrated her funeral and burial in the [[Basilica of Santa Maria sopra Minerva]] in Rome.

The devotion around Catherine of Siena developed rapidly after her death. She was canonized in 1461, declared [[patron saint]] of Rome in 1866, and of [[Italy]] (together with [[Francis of Assisi]]) in 1939.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Haegen|first1=Anne Mueller von der|last2=Strasser|first2=Ruth F.|title=Art &amp; Architecture: Tuscany|date=2013|publisher=H.F.Ullmann Publishing|location=Potsdam|isbn=978-3-8480-0321-1|page=334|chapter=St. Catherine of Siena: Mystic, Politician, and Saint}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Vatican&gt;{{in lang|it}} [[Pope Pius XII]], [http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/pius_xii/briefs/documents/hf_p-xii_brief_19390618_patroni-italia_it.html ''Pontifical Brief'', 18 June 1939].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Vatican1&gt;{{in lang|it}} [https://w2.vatican.va/content/paul-vi/it/homilies/1970/documents/hf_p-vi_hom_19701003.html ''Proclamation to Doctor of the Church'', Homily, 4 October 1970].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Vatican2&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/john_paul_ii/motu_proprio/documents/hf_jp-ii_motu-proprio_01101999_co-patronesses-europe_en.html ''Proclamation of the Co-Patronesses of Europe'', Apostolic Letter, 1 October 1999]. {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141120054044/http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/john_paul_ii/motu_proprio/documents/hf_jp-ii_motu-proprio_01101999_co-patronesses-europe_en.html |date=November 20, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Vatican3&gt;[https://webcache.googleusercontent.com/search?q=cache:EQVninoe8UwJ:https://w2.vatican.va/content/john-paul-ii/en/homilies/1999/documents/hf_jp-ii_hom_13111999_st-bridget.html++%22Saint+Bridget,+whom+I+recently+chose+to+proclaim+a+Co-Patroness+of+Europe,+together+with+Saint+Catherine+of+Siena+and+Saint+Teresa+Benedicta+of+the+Cross%22&amp;hl=en ''Liturgical Feast of St. Bridget'', Homily, 13 November 1999].&lt;/ref&gt; She was the first woman (along with [[Teresa of Ávila]]) to be declared a &quot;doctor of the Church,&quot; on 4 October 1970 by [[Pope Paul VI]]. She was also proclaimed [[Patron Saint of Europe|patron saint of Europe]] in 1999 by [[Pope John Paul II]]. Catherine of Siena is one of the outstanding figures of medieval Catholicism, by the strong influence she has had in the history of the papacy and her extensive authorship. She was behind the return of the Pope from Avignon to Rome, and then carried out many missions entrusted by the pope, something quite rare for a woman in the [[Middle Ages]]. Her ''Dialogue'', hundreds of letters, and dozens of prayers, also give her a prominent place in the history of Italian literature.

==Life==
[[File:House Catherine Siena Apr 2008.jpg|thumb|left|The house of Saint Catherine in [[Siena]]]]

Caterina di Giacomo di Benincasa was born on 25 March 1347 (shortly before the [[Black Death]] ravaged Europe) in [[Siena]], [[Republic of Siena]] (today [[Italy]]), to Lapa Piagenti, the daughter of a local poet, and Giacomo di Benincasa, a cloth dyer who ran his enterprise with the help of his sons.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gardner&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/03447a.htm |title=St. Catherine of Siena |publisher=newadvent.org |accessdate=1 December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The house where Catherine grew up in still exists. Lapa was about forty years old when she gave premature birth to twin daughters Catherine and Giovanna. She had already borne 22 children, but half of them had died. Giovanna was handed over to a [[wet-nurse]] and died soon after.  Catherine was nursed by her mother and developed into a healthy child. She was two years old when Lapa had her 25th child, another daughter named Giovanna.{{sfn|Skårderud|2008|p=411}} As a child Catherine was so merry that the family gave her the pet name of &quot;Euphrosyne&quot;, which is Greek for &quot;joy&quot; and the name of an [[Euphrosyne of Alexandria]].&lt;ref name=crawley&gt;[http://www.ewtn.com/library/MARY/CATSIENA.HTM ''Lives of Saints''], John J. Crawley &amp; Co., Inc.&lt;/ref&gt;

Catherine is said by her confessor and biographer [[Raymond of Capua]] [[Dominican Order|O.P.]]'s ''Life'' to have had her first vision of Christ when she was five or six years old: she and a brother were on the way home from visiting a married sister when she is said to have experienced a vision of [[Christ in Majesty|Christ seated in glory]] with the [[Apostles]] [[Saint Peter|Peter]], [[Paul of Tarsus|Paul]], and [[John the Apostle|John]]. Raymond continues that at age seven, Catherine vowed to give her whole life to God.&lt;ref name=crawley/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Raymond of Capua, ''Legenda Major'' I, iii.&lt;/ref&gt;

When Catherine was sixteen, her older sister Bonaventura [[death in childbirth|died in childbirth]]; already anguished by this, Catherine soon learned that her parents wanted her to marry Bonaventura's widower. She was absolutely opposed and started a strict fast. She had learned this from Bonaventura, whose husband had been far from considerate but his wife had changed his attitude by refusing to eat until he showed better manners. Besides fasting, Catherine further disappointed her mother by cutting off her long hair as a protest against being overly encouraged to improve her appearance to attract a husband.&lt;ref name=foley&gt;[http://www.americancatholic.org/Features/Saints/saint.aspx?id=1368 Foley O.F.M., Leonard. ''Saint of the Day, Lives, Lessons, and Feast''], (revised by Pat McCloskey O.F.M.), Franciscan Media, {{ISBN|978-0-86716-887-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Св Екатерина сиенская Ораторио Санта Катерина Neroccio.jpg|thumb|right|180px|[[Statuette]] by [[Neroccio di Bartolomeo de' Landi]], (1475)]] 
Catherine would later advise Raymond of Capua to do during times of trouble what she did now as a teenager: &quot;Build a cell inside your mind, from which you can never flee.&quot; In this inner cell she made her father into a representation of Christ, her mother into the [[Blessed Virgin Mary]], and her brothers into the [[Apostle (Christian)|apostles]]. Serving them humbly became an opportunity for spiritual growth. Catherine resisted the accepted course of marriage and motherhood on the one hand, or a [[nun]]'s veil on the other. She chose to live an active and prayerful life outside a convent's walls following the model of the Dominicans.&lt;ref name=bellitto&gt;[http://www.americancatholic.org/Messenger/Nov1999/feature2.asp#F5 Bellitto, Christopher M., &quot;10 Great Catholics of the Second Millennium&quot;, ''St. Anthony Messenger'']&lt;/ref&gt; Eventually her father gave up and permitted her to live as she pleased.

A vision of [[Saint Dominic]] gave strength to Catherine, but her wish to join his Order was no comfort to Lapa, who took her daughter with her to the baths in [[Bagno Vignoni]] to improve her health. Catherine fell seriously ill with a violent rash, fever and pain, which conveniently made her mother accept her wish to join the &quot;Mantellate&quot;, the local association of Dominican [[Third order|tertiaries]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Siena. Available Means 2001&quot;&gt;Catherine of Siena. Available Means. Ed. Joy Ritchie and Kate Ronald. Pittsburgh, Pa.: University of Pittsburgh Press, 2001. Print.&lt;/ref&gt; Lapa went to the Sisters of the Order and persuaded them to take in her daughter. Within days, Catherine seemed entirely restored, rose from bed and donned the black and white habit of the [[Third Order of Saint Dominic]]. Catherine received the habit of a [[Dominican Order|Dominican]] tertiary from the [[friar]]s of the order after vigorous protests from the tertiaries themselves, who up to that point had been only widows. As a tertiary, she lived outside the convent, at home with her family like before. The Mantellate taught Catherine how to read, and she lived in almost total silence and solitude in the family home.&lt;ref name=&quot;Siena. Available Means 2001&quot;/&gt;

Her custom of giving away clothing and food without asking anyone's permission cost her family significantly, but she requested nothing for herself. By staying in their midst, she could live out her rejection of them more strongly. She did not want their food, referring to the table laid for her in Heaven with her real family.{{sfn|Skårderud|2008|pp=412–413}} 
[[File:Giovanni di Paolo The Mystic Marriage of Saint Catherine of Siena.jpg|thumb|left|[[Giovanni di Paolo]], ''The Mystic Marriage of Saint Catherine of Siena'']]

According to [[Raymond of Capua]], at the age of twenty-one (c. 1368), Catherine experienced what she described in her letters as a &quot;[[Bridal theology|Mystical Marriage]]&quot; with [[Jesus]],{{sfn|Raymond of Capua|2003|pp=99–101}} later a popular subject in art as the ''[[Mystic marriage of Saint Catherine]]''. [[Caroline Walker Bynum]] explains one surprising and controversial aspect of this marriage that occurs both in artistic representations of the event and in some early accounts of her life: &quot;Underlining the extent to which the marriage was a fusion with Christ's physicality [...] Catherine received, not the ring of gold and jewels that her biographer reports in his bowdlerized version, but the ring of [[Holy Prepuce|Christ's foreskin]].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bynum&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=Holy Feast and Holy Fast. The Religious Significance of Food to Medieval Women|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=zhjT8CIZLM4C&amp;printsec=frontcover | first=Caroline Walker|last=Bynum|authorlink=Caroline Bynum|year=1987|publisher=[[University of California Press]] | page=[https://archive.org/details/holyfeastholyfas00bynu/page/246 &lt;!-- quote=&quot;Underlining the extent to which the marriage was a fusion with Christ's physicality&quot;&quot;Catherine received, not the ring of gold and jewels that her biographer reports in his bowdlerized version, but the ring of Christ's foreskin&quot;. --&gt; 246] |isbn=978-0-520-06329-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | title=Rag and Bone. A Journey Among the World's Holy Dead | url=https://books.google.com/books?id=T-FrEhVhIBgC&amp;printsec=frontcover | first=Peter | last=Manseau | year=2009 |publisher=[[Macmillan Publishers|Macmillan]] | location=London| isbn=978-142993-665-1 |quote=[https://books.google.com/books?id=T-FrEhVhIBgC&amp;pg=PT58&amp;dq=%22Some,+most+famously+Saint+Catherine+of+Siena,+imagined+wearing+the+foreskin+as+a+wedding+ring%22 Some {{bracket|nuns}}, most famously Saint Catherine of Siena, imagined wearing the foreskin as a wedding ring].}}&lt;/ref&gt; Catherine herself mentions the foreskin-as-wedding ring motif in one of her letters (#221), equating the wedding ring of a virgin with a foreskin; she typically claimed that her own wedding ring to Christ was simply invisible.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Jacobs|first1=Andrew|title=Christ Circumcised: A Study in Early Christian History and Difference|date=2012|publisher=University of Pennsylvania Press|page=192|url=https://books.google.com/?id=NU2D35QoNjEC&amp;pg=PA192&amp;lpg=PA192&amp;dq=catherine+of+siena+letter+221+foreskin#v=snippet&amp;q=catherine%20of%20siena&amp;f=false|accessdate=22 October 2015|isbn=978-0812206517}}&lt;/ref&gt; She wrote in a letter (to encourage a nun who seems to have been undergoing a prolonged period of spiritual trial and torment): &quot;Bathe in the blood of Christ crucified.  See that you don't look for or want anything but the crucified, as a true bride ransomed by the blood of Christ crucified-for that is my wish.  You see very well that you are a bride and that he has espoused you-you and everyone else-and not with a ring of silver but with a ring of his own flesh.  Look at the tender little child who on the eighth day, when he was circumcised, gave up just so much flesh as to make a tiny circlet of a ring!&quot;&lt;ref&gt;The Letters of Saint Catherine of Siena, Volume II, Suzanne Noffke OP, Arizona Center for Medieval and Renaissance Studies Tempe Arizona 2001, p. 184&lt;/ref&gt;  Raymond of Capua also records that she was told by Christ to leave her withdrawn life and enter the public life of the world.{{sfn|Raymond of Capua|2003|pp=105–107}} Catherine rejoined her family and began helping the ill and the poor, where she took care of them in hospitals or homes. Her early pious activities in Siena attracted a group of followers, women and men, who gathered around her.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gardner&quot; /&gt;

As social and political tensions mounted in Siena, Catherine found herself drawn to intervene in wider politics. She made her first journey to [[Florence]] in 1374, probably to be interviewed by the Dominican authorities at the General Chapter held in Florence in May 1374, though this is disputed (if she was interviewed, then the absence of later evidence suggests she was deemed sufficiently orthodox).&lt;ref name=foley/&gt; It seems that at this time she acquired Raymond of Capua as her confessor and spiritual director.{{sfn|Noffke, p. 5}}

After this visit, she began travelling with her followers throughout northern and central Italy advocating reform of the clergy and advising people that repentance and renewal could be done through &quot;the total love for God.&quot;{{sfn|Hollister|Bennett|2002|p=342}} In Pisa, in 1375, she used what influence she had to sway that city and [[Lucca]] away from alliance with the anti-papal league whose force was gaining momentum and strength. She also lent her enthusiasm towards promoting the launch of a new crusade. It was in Pisa in 1375 that, according to Raymond of Capua's biography, she received the [[stigmata]] (visible, at Catherine's request, only to herself).{{sfn|Noffke, p. 5}}
{{Christian mysticism}}
Physical travel was not the only way in which Catherine made her views known. From 1375{{sfn|Noffke, p. 5}} onwards, she began dictating letters to scribes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Siena. Available Means 2001&quot;/&gt; These letters were intended to reach men and women of her circle, increasingly widening her audience to include figures in authority as she begged for peace between the republics and principalities of Italy and for the return of the [[Papacy]] from [[Avignon Papacy|Avignon]] to [[Rome]]. She carried on a long correspondence with [[Pope Gregory XI]], asking him to reform the [[clergy]] and the administration of the [[Papal States]].

Towards the end of 1375, she returned to Siena, to assist a young political prisoner, Niccolò di Tuldo, at his execution.{{sfn|Noffke, p. 5}}&lt;ref&gt;Letter T273, written by Catherine to Raymond, probably in June 1375, describes the event.&lt;/ref&gt; In June 1376 Catherine went to [[Avignon]] as ambassador of the [[Republic of Florence]] to make peace with the Papal States (on 31 March 1376 Gregory XI had placed Florence under interdict). She was unsuccessful and was disowned by the Florentine leaders, who sent ambassadors to negotiate on their own terms as soon as Catherine's work had paved the way for them.{{sfn|Noffke, p. 5}} Catherine sent an appropriately scorching letter back to Florence in response.&lt;ref&gt;Letter 234 in Tommaseo's numbering.&lt;/ref&gt; While in Avignon, Catherine also tried to convince Pope Gregory XI, the last [[Avignon Papacy|Avignon Pope]], to return to Rome.{{sfn|Hollister|Bennett|2002|p=343}} Gregory did indeed return his administration to Rome in January 1377; to what extent this was due to Catherine's influence is a topic of much modern debate.&lt;ref&gt;See Bernard McGinn, ''The Varieties of Vernacular Mysticism'', (Herder &amp; Herder, 2012), p561.&lt;/ref&gt;

Catherine returned to Siena and spent the early months of 1377 founding a women's monastery of strict observance outside the city in the old fortress of Belcaro.{{sfn|Noffke, p. 6}} She spent the rest of 1377 at Rocca d'Orcia, about twenty miles from Siena, on a local mission of peace-making and preaching. During this period, in autumn 1377, she had the experience which led to the writing of her ''Dialogue'' and learned to write, although she still seems to have chiefly relied upon her secretaries for her correspondence.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gardner&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;This experience is recorded in Letter 272, written to Raymond in October 1377.&lt;/ref&gt;

Late in 1377 or early in 1378 Catherine again travelled to Florence, at the order of Gregory XI, to seek peace between Florence and Rome. Following Gregory's death in [[Western Schism|March 1378 riots]], the revolts of the [[Ciompi]], broke out in Florence on 18 June, and in the ensuing violence she was nearly assassinated. Eventually, in July 1378, peace was agreed between Florence and Rome; Catherine returned quietly to Florence.

In late November 1378, with the outbreak of the [[Western Schism]], the new Pope, [[Urban VI]], summoned her to Rome. She stayed at Pope Urban VI's court and tried to convince nobles and cardinals of his legitimacy, both meeting with individuals at court and writing letters to persuade others.{{sfn|Noffke, p. 6}}

For many years she had accustomed herself to a rigorous abstinence.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ewtn.com/library/MARY/CSIENA.HTM Butler, Alban. ''The Lives or the Fathers, Martyrs and Other Principal Saints'', Vol. IV, D. &amp; J. Sadlier, &amp; Company, (1864)]&lt;/ref&gt; She received the Holy [[Eucharist]] almost daily. This extreme fasting appeared unhealthy in the eyes of the clergy and her own sisterhood. Her confessor, Raymond, ordered her to eat properly. But Catherine claimed that she was unable to, describing her inability to eat as an ''infermità'' (illness). From the beginning of 1380, Catherine could neither eat nor swallow water. On February 26 she lost the use of her legs.{{sfn|Noffke, p. 6}}

Catherine died in Rome, on 29 April 1380, at the age of thirty-three,&lt;ref name=dictionary&gt;{{cite book |last=Farmer|first=David Hugh|title=The Oxford dictionary of saints|year=1997|publisher=Oxford Univ. Press|location=Oxford [u.a.]|isbn=978-0-19-280058-9|pages=93|edition=4.}}&lt;/ref&gt; having eight days earlier suffered a massive stroke which paralyzed her from the waist down. Her last words were, &quot;Father, into Your Hands I commend my soul and my spirit.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Caffarini|first1=Tommaso|title=Libellus de supplemento: legende prolixe virginis beate Catherine de Senis|url=https://books.google.com/?id=2SIGHAAACAAJ|year=1974}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Sources of her life==
There is some internal evidence of Catherine's personality, teaching and work in her nearly four hundred letters, her ''Dialogue'', and her prayers.

Much detail about her life has also, however, been drawn from the various sources written shortly after her death in order to promote her cult and canonisation. Though much of this material is heavily [[Hagiography|hagiographic]], it has been an important source for historians seeking to reconstruct Catherine's life. Various sources are particularly important, especially the works of Raymond of Capua, who was Catherine's spiritual director and close friend from 1374 until her death, and himself became [[Master of the Order of Preachers|Master General]] of the Order in 1380. Raymond began writing what is known as the ''Legenda Major'', his ''Life'' of Catherine, in 1384, and completed it in 1395.

Another important work written after Catherine's death was ''Libellus de Supplemento'' (''Little Supplement Book''), written between 1412 and 1418 by Tommaso d'Antonio Nacci da Siena (commonly called Thomas of Siena, or Tommaso Caffarini): the work is an expansion of Raymond's ''Legenda Major'' making heavy use of the notes of Catherine's first confessor, Tommaso della Fonte (notes that do not survive anywhere else). Caffarini later published a more compact account of Catherine's life, entitled the ''Legenda Minor''.

From 1411 onwards, Caffarini also co-ordinated the compiling of the ''Processus'' of Venice, the set of documents submitted as part of the process of [[canonisation]] of Catherine, which provides [[Christian testimony|testimony]] from nearly all of Catherine's disciples. There is also an anonymous piece entitled &quot;Miracoli della Beata Caterina&quot; (''Miracle of Blessed Catherine''), written by an anonymous Florentine. A few other relevant pieces survive.{{sfn|Noffke, p. 2}}

==Works==
[[File:Caterina - Libro della divina dottrina, circa 1475 - 2367969.jpg|thumb|'' Libro della divina dottrina'' (commonly known as ''The Dialogue of Divine Providence''), c.1475]]
[[File:L'epistole della serafica vergine s. Caterina da Siena.tif|thumb|''L'epistole della serafica vergine s. Caterina da Siena'' (1721)]]

Three genres of work by Catherine survive:
* Her major treatise is ''The Dialogue of Divine Providence''. This had probably begun in October 1377 and was certainly finished by November 1378. Contemporaries of Catherine are united in asserting that much of the book was dictated while Catherine was in ecstasy, though it also seems possible that Catherine herself may then have re-edited many passages in the book.{{sfn|Noffke, p. 13}} It is a dialogue between a soul who &quot;rises up&quot; to God and God himself.
* Catherine's letters are considered one of the great works of early Tuscan literature. Many of these were dictated, although she herself learned to write in 1377; 382 have survived. In her letters to the Pope, she often addressed him affectionately simply as ''Babbo'' (&quot;Daddy&quot;), instead of the formal form of address  Your Holiness&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://movies2.nytimes.com/library/magazine/millennium/m2/egan.html |title=Power Suffering |last=Egan |first=Jennifer |date=1999 |work=[[The New York Times Magazine]] |access-date=2019-04-15 |df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other correspondents include her various confessors, among them [[Raymond of Capua]], the kings of France and Hungary, the infamous mercenary [[John Hawkwood]], the Queen of Naples, members of the [[Visconti of Milan|Visconti family]] of Milan, and numerous religious figures.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |jstor=20176608 |title=The Radical Rhetoric of Caterina Da Siena |first=Cheryl |last=Forbes |volume=23 |issue=2 |pages=121–140 |year=2004 |publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis, Ltd. |journal=Rhetoric Review|doi = 10.1207/s15327981rr2302_2}}&lt;/ref&gt; Approximately one third of her letters are to women.
* Twenty-six prayers of Catherine of Siena also survive, mostly composed in the last eighteen months of her life.

==Theology==
Catherine's theology can be described as [[Christian mysticism|mystical]], and was employed towards practical ends for her own spiritual life or those of others.&lt;ref&gt;Noffke, Suzanne. &quot;Catherine of Siena.&quot; In Medieval Holy Women in the Christian Tradition c. 1100-c. 1500. Alastair J. Minnis and Rosalynn Voaden, eds. Turnhout: Brepols, 2010. 613.&lt;/ref&gt; She used the language of medieval [[scholastic philosophy]] to elaborate her experiential mysticism.&lt;ref&gt;Foster, Kenelm. &quot;St Catherine's Teaching on Christ.&quot; Life of the Spirit (1946–1964) 16, no. 187 (1962): 313. {{JSTOR|43705923}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Interested mainly with achieving an incorporeal union with God, Catherine practiced extreme fasting and [[Ascetical theology|asceticism]], eventually to the extent of living solely off the Eucharist every day.&lt;ref&gt;Finnegan, Mary Jeremy. &quot;Catherine of Siena: The Two Hungers.&quot; Mystics Quarterly 17, no. 4 (1991): 173–80. {{JSTOR|20717082}}.&lt;/ref&gt; For Catherine, this practice was the means to fully realize her [[Agape|love of Christ]] in her mystical experience, with a large proportion of her [[Religious ecstasy|ecstatic visions]] relating to the consumption or rejection of food during her life.&lt;ref&gt;Noffke, Suzanne. &quot;Catherine of Siena.&quot; In Medieval Holy Women in the Christian Tradition c. 1100-c. 1500. Alastair J. Minnis and Rosalynn Voaden, eds. Turnhout: Brepols, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; She viewed Christ as a &quot;bridge&quot; between the soul and God and transmitted that idea, along with her other teachings, in her book The Dialogue.&lt;ref&gt;Catherine of Siena. The Dialogue. Translated by Suzanne Noffke. The Classics of Western Spirituality. Paulist Press, 1980.&lt;/ref&gt; The Dialogue is highly systematic and explanatory in its presentation of her mystical ideas; however, these ideas themselves are not so much based on reason or logic as they are based in her ecstatic mystical experience.&lt;ref&gt;Noffke, Suzanne. &quot;Catherine of Siena.&quot; In Medieval Holy Women in the Christian Tradition c. 1100-c. 1500. Alastair J. Minnis and Rosalynn Voaden, eds. Turnhout: Brepols, 2010. 601–615.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Veneration==
[[File:Caterina sopra Minerva.jpg|thumb|[[Sarcophagus]] of Catherine beneath the [[High Altar]] of Santa Maria sopra Minerva, Rome]]
She was buried in the (Roman) cemetery of [[Santa Maria sopra Minerva]] which lies near the [[Pantheon, Rome|Pantheon]]. After miracles were reported to take place at her grave, Raymond moved her inside the [[Basilica]] of Santa Maria sopra Minerva, where she lies to this day.
[[File:Cappella di santa caterina, 01.jpg|thumb|left|The Chapel of Saint Catherine, Basilica of San Domenico in Siena]]
Her head however, was parted from her body and inserted in a gilt bust of [[bronze]]. This bust was later taken to Siena, and carried through that city in a procession to the Dominican church. Behind the bust walked Lapa, Catherine's mother, who lived until she was 89 years old. By then she had seen the end of the wealth and the happiness of her family, and followed most of her children and several of her grandchildren to the grave. She helped Raymond of Capua write his biography of her daughter, and said, &quot;I think God has laid my soul athwart in my body, so that it can't get out.&quot;{{sfn|Skårderud|2008|loc=&quot;Jeg tror at Gud har gjort det slik at sjelen ligger på tvers i kroppen min og ikke kan komme ut.&quot;}} The incorrupt head and thumb were entombed in the [[Basilica of San Domenico (Siena)|Basilica of San Domenico]] at Siena, where they remain.

[[Pope Pius II]], himself from Siena, [[canonized]] Catherine on 29 June 1461.&lt;ref name=beckwith&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20060422131354/http://www.americancatholic.org/Messenger/Apr2006/Feature1.asp Beckwith, Barbara. &quot;St. Catherine of Siena: A Feisty Role for Sister Nancy Murray&quot;, ''St. Anthony Messenger'']&lt;/ref&gt;

On 4 October 1970, [[Pope Paul VI]] named Catherine a [[Doctor of the Church]];&lt;ref name=Vatican1/&gt; this title was almost simultaneously given to [[Teresa of Ávila]] (27 September 1970),&lt;ref&gt;{{in lang|it}} [http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/paul_vi/homilies/1970/documents/hf_p-vi_hom_19700927_it.html ''Proclamation of Saint Teresa of Ávila to Doctor of the Church'', Homily, 27 September 1970].&lt;/ref&gt; making them the first women to receive this honour.&lt;ref name=beckwith/&gt;

Initially however, her [[feast day]] was not included in the [[General Roman Calendar]]. When it was added in 1597, it was put on the day of her death, April 29; however, because this conflicted with the feast of Saint [[Peter of Verona]] which also fell on the 29th of April, Catherine's feast day was moved in 1628 to the new date of April 30.&lt;ref&gt;''&quot;Calendarium Romanum&quot;'' (Libreria Editrice Vaticana, 1969), p. 91.&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[Mysterii Paschalis|1969 revision]] of the calendar, it was decided to leave the celebration of the feast of St Peter of Verona to local calendars, because he was not as well known worldwide, and Catherine's feast was restored to April 29.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Calendarium Romanum |publisher=Libreria Editrice Vaticana |year=1969 |page= 121}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Patronage===
In his decree of 13 April 1866, [[Pope Pius IX]] declared Catherine of Siena to be a co-patroness of Rome. On 18 June 1939 [[Pope Pius XII]] named her a joint [[patron saint]] of [[Italy]] along with [[Saint Francis of Assisi]].&lt;ref name=Vatican/&gt;

On 1 October 1999, [[Pope John Paul II]] made her one of Europe's [[patron saint]]s, along with [[Edith Stein|Saint Teresa Benedicta of the Cross]] and [[Bridget of Sweden|Saint Bridget of Sweden]].&lt;ref name=Vatican2/&gt;&lt;ref name=Vatican3/&gt; She is also the patroness of the historically Catholic American woman's fraternity, [[Theta Phi Alpha]].

===Severed head===
The people of Siena wished to have Catherine's body. A story is told of a miracle whereby they were partially successful: knowing that they could not smuggle her whole body out of Rome, they decided to take only her head which they placed in a bag. When stopped by the Roman guards, they prayed to Catherine to help them, confident that she would rather have her body (or at least part thereof) in Siena. When they opened the bag to show the guards, it appeared no longer to hold her head but to be full of rose petals.&lt;ref name=&quot;AO&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.atlasobscura.com/places/st-dominics-basilica |title=St. Catherine of Siena's Severed Head |website=Atlas Obscura |df=dmy-all |access-date=2019-04-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy==
Catherine ranks high among the mystics and spiritual writers of the Church.&lt;ref name=foley/&gt; She remains a greatly respected figure for her spiritual writings, and political boldness to &quot;speak truth to power&quot;—it being exceptional for a woman, in her time period, to have had such influence in politics and on world history.

==Main sanctuaries==
The main churches in honor of Catherine of Siena are:

* [[Santa Maria sopra Minerva]] in Rome: place where her body is preserved.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.santamariasopraminerva.it/en/5-tomb-of-st-catherine-of-siena.html |title=Tomb of St Catherine of Siena |website=Santa Maria sopra Minerva |access-date=2019-04-15 |df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Basilica of San Domenico, Siena|Basilica of San Domenico]] in Siena: in this church the incorrupt head of Catherine of Siena is preserved.&lt;ref name=&quot;AO&quot; /&gt;
* {{Interlanguage link multi|Shrine of Saint Catherine (Siena)|it|Santuario di Santa Caterina (Siena)|lt=Shrine of Saint Catherine}} in Siena: complex of religious buildings built around the birthplace of Catherine.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.viaesiena.it/en/caterina/itinerario/santuario-casa-di-santa-caterina |title=Santa Caterina |website=Viae Siena |access-date=2019-04-15 |df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Images==
{{main|Mystic marriage of Saint Catherine}}
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:CatherineSienaMeo.jpg|Michele de Meo, ''Catherine of Siena, Patroness of Europe'', 2003, Chapel of St. James, Church of Santa Maria sopra Minerva
File:CatherineCommunionBeccafumi.jpg|[[Domenico Beccafumi]], ''The Miraculous Communion of St. Catherine of Siena'', circa 1513-1515, Getty Center, Los Angeles, California
File:CSienaStigmataBeccafumi.jpg|Domenico Beccafumi, ''St. Catherine of Siena Receiving the Stigmata'', circa 1513-1515, Getty Center, Los Angeles, California
File:RosaryStaAgata.jpg|''The Virgin Mary Giving the Rosary to St. Dominic and St. Catherine of Siena'', Church of Santa Agata in Trastevere, Rome (Bottom of painting: the souls in Purgatory await the prayers of the faithful)
File:Franceschini, Baldassare - St Catherine of Siena - Google Art Project.jpg|[[Baldassare Franceschini]], ''Saint Catherine of Siena'', 17th century, [[Dulwich Picture Gallery]]
File:Giovanni di paolo, St Catherine of Siena.jpg|[[Giovanni di Paolo]], ''St. Catherine of Siena'', c. 1475, tempera and gold on panel.  Fogg Art Museum, Cambridge, England.
File:Lesser Poland St. Catherine of Siena.jpg|''St Catherine and the Demons'' by an unknown artist, c. 1500, tempera on panel. [[National Museum, Warsaw]].
File:Anoniem - Het kantoor van de belastingsdienst (biccherna) van Siena.jpg|''The office of the taxcollector (biccherna) of Siena'' by an unknown artist, 1451 - 1452, [[Rijksmuseum Amsterdam]]
File:Revelación del Santísimo Rosario a Santo Domingo de Guzmán.jpg|This painting depicts the Virgin giving the rosary to [[Saint Dominic|St. Dominic]]; in the scene also appear Fray Pedro de Santa María Ulloa, Saint Catherine of Siena and [[Servant of God]], [[Mary of Jesus de León y Delgado]]. The fresco is located in the Church of Santo Domingo in [[San Cristóbal de La Laguna]], [[Tenerife]], [[Spain]].
File:San Domenico74.jpg|''St Catherine's mystic communion'' by [[Francesco Brizzi]]
File:Head of Saint Catherine of Siena.jpg|The head exposed in the [[Basilica of San Domenico, Siena]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;

== Works ==
=== Modern editions and English translations ===
* The Italian critical edition of the ''Dialogue'' is Catherine of Siena, ''Il Dialogo della divina Provvidenza: ovvero Libro della divina dottrina'', 2nd ed., ed. Giuliana Cavallini (Siena: Cantagalli, 1995). [1st edn, 1968] [Cavallini demonstrated that the standard division of the ''Dialogue'' in into four treatises entitled the 'Treatise on Discretion', 'On Prayer', 'On Providence', and 'On Obedience', was in fact a result of a misreading of the text in the 1579 edition of the ''Dialogue''. Modern editors and translators, including Noffke (1980), have followed Cavallini in rejecting this fourfold division.]
* The Italian critical edition of the 26 ''Prayers'' is Catherine of Siena, ''Le Orazioni'', ed. Giuliana Cavallini (Rome: Cateriniane, 1978)
* The most recent Italian critical edition of the Letters is Antonio Volpato, ed, ''Le lettere di Santa Caterina da Siena: l'edizione di Eugenio Duprè Theseider e i nuovi problemi'', (2002)

English translations of The ''Dialogue'' include:
* [https://books.google.com/books?id=bsGXhNZyUSgC ''The Dialogue''], trans. Suzanne Noffke, O.P. Paulist Press (Classics of Western Spirituality), 1980.
* ''The Dialogue of St. Catherine of Siena'', [[TAN Books]], 2009.  {{ISBN|978-0-89555-149-8}}
* Phyllis Hodgson and Gabriel M Liegey, eds., ''The Orcherd of Syon'', (London; New York: Oxford UP, 1966) [A Middle English translation of the ''Dialogo'' from the early fifteenth century, first printed in 1519].

The Letters are translated into English as:
* {{cite book | last = Catherine of Siena| title = The Letters of St. Catherine of Siena |editor=Suzanne Noffke | publisher = Center for Medieval and Early Renaissance Studies, State University of New York at Binghamton | location = Binghamton | year = 1988 | isbn = 978-0-86698-036-4 |volume= 4}} (Republished as ''The letters of Catherine of Siena'', 4 vols, trans Suzanne Noffke, (Tempe, AZ: Arizona Center for Medieval and Renaissance Studies, 2000–2008))

The Prayers are translated into English as:
* ''The Prayers of Catherine of Siena'', trans. Suzanne Noffke, 2nd edn 1983, (New York, 2001)

Raymond of Capua's ''Life'' was translated into English in 1493 and 1609, and in Modern English is translated as:
* {{cite book | last = Raymond of Capua |authorlink=Raymond of Capua |editor= Conleth Kearns | title = The Life of Catherine of Siena | publisher = Glazier | location = Wilmington | year = 1980 | isbn = 978-0-89453-151-4 }}

==See also==
{{Portal|Saints|Politics}}
* [[Biblioteca Comunale degli Intronati]]
* [[Saints and levitation]]
* [[Mystical marriage of Saint Catherine]]
* [[Order of Preachers]]
* [[War of the Eight Saints]]
* [[St. Catherine of Siena's Church (disambiguation)|Churches dedicated to Catherine of Siena]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Sources==
*{{cite book|author=Blessed Raymond of Capua|title=The Life of St. Catherine of Siena|translator-last=Lamb|translator-first=George|location=Rockford, Illinois|publisher=TAN Books|year=2003|ref={{SfnRef|Raymond of Capua|2003}}}}
* {{Cite book|author=Catherine of Siena|title=The Dialogue|translator-last=Noffke|translator-first=Suzanne|publisher=Paulist Press|location=New York|year=1980|isbn=978-0-8091-2233-2|ref={{SfnRef|Noffke|1980}}|url=https://archive.org/details/dialogue00cath}}
* {{cite book | last = Hollister| first = Warren |last2=Bennett|first2=Judith |title = Medieval Europe: A Short History | url = https://archive.org/details/medievaleuropesh00holl_1| url-access = registration| publisher = McGraw-Hill Companies Inc. | location = Boston|edition=9| year = 2002|ref=harv}}
*{{cite journal |first=Finn |last=Skårderud |title=Hellig anoreksi Sult og selvskade som religiøse praksiser. Caterina av Siena (1347–80)|url=http://www.psykologtidsskriftet.no/?seks_id=42861&amp;a=2 |journal=Tidsskrift for Norsk Psykologforening |volume=45|issue=4|pages=408–420|year=2008|accessdate=12 May 2013|language=no|ref=harv}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite book|editor-last = Cross|editor-first = F. L.|title = The Oxford Dictionary of the Christian Church|publisher = Oxford U. P.|location = London|year = 2016|p = .&amp;nbsp;251|isbn = 978-0-192-11655-0|url = https://archive.org/details/oxforddictionary00late}}
* {{cite book | last = Emling| first = Shelley |title = Setting the World on Fire: The Brief, Astonishing Life of St. Catherine of Siena | publisher = St. Martin's Press| location = New York |year = 2016| isbn = 978-1-137-27980-4}}
* Girolamo Gigli, ed., ''L'opere di Santa Caterina da Siena'', 4 vols, (Siena e Lucca, 1707–1721)
* {{cite book| last = Hollister| first = Warren| author2 = Judith Bennett| title = Medieval Europe: A Short History| publisher = McGraw-Hill Companies Inc.| location = Boston| edition = 9| year = 2001| isbn = 978-0-07-234657-2| page = [https://archive.org/details/medievaleuropesh00holl_1/page/343 343]| url = https://archive.org/details/medievaleuropesh00holl_1/page/343}}
* {{cite book|last1=Faure|first1=Gabriel|title=Au pays de sainte Catherine de Sienne|date=1918|publisher=J. Rey|location=Grenoble|oclc=9435948}}
* {{cite book |last=McDermott|first=Thomas, O.P.|title=Catherine of Siena: spiritual development in her life and teaching|publisher=Paulist Press|location=New York|year=2008|isbn=978-0-8091-4547-8}}
* Carolyn Muessig, George Ferzoco, and Beverly Mayne Kienzle, eds., [https://books.google.com/books?id=6TQAtAtPDiAC ''A Companion to Catherine of Siena''], (Leiden: Brill, 2012), {{ISBN|978-90-04-20555-0}} / {{ISBN|978-90-04-22542-8}}.

==External links==
{{sisterproject|wikt=no}}
* {{Gutenberg author |id=2456}}
** [http://www.gutenberg.org/dirs/etext05/8ltcb10.txt Letters of Catherine from Gutenberg]
* {{Internet Archive author |sname=Catherine of Siena}}
* [http://www.intratext.com/Catalogo/Autori/AUT59.HTM Saint Catherine of Siena: Text with concordances and frequency list]
* [http://www.drawnbylove.com ''Drawn by Love, The Mysticism of Catherine of Siena'']
* [http://www.christianiconography.info/catherineSiena.html St. Catherine of Siena] at the [http://www.christianiconography.info Christian Iconography] web site
* [http://purl.stanford.edu/rm504km6504 ''Divae Catharinae Senensis Vita'' 15th-century manuscript] at ''Stanford Digital Repository''
* [http://www.stpetersbasilica.info/Exterior/Colonnades/Saints/St%20Catherine%20of%20Siena-117/StCatherineofSiena.htm St Catherine statue – St Peter's Square Colonnade Saints]
* {{cite web | url = https://digilander.libero.it/raxdi/caterina/inglese/index.htm | title = Saint Catherine of Siena: the ''De Docta Ignorantia '' | website = Invisible Monastery of charity and fraternity – Christian family prayer | language = en | archive-url = https://archive.today/20181031231642/https://digilander.libero.it/raxdi/caterina/inglese/index.htm# | archive-date = 31 October 2018 | url-status = live | access-date = 31 October 2018 | df = dmy-all }}

{{Catholic saints}}
{{Navboxes
|list=
{{History of Catholic theology}}
{{History of the Roman Catholic Church}}
}}
{{Authority control}}

[[Category:1347 births]]
[[Category:1380 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Siena]]
[[Category:Dominican mystics]]
[[Category:Dominican spirituality]]
[[Category:Dominican tertiaries]]
[[Category:Lay Dominicans]]
[[Category:Dominican theologians]]
[[Category:14th-century philosophers]]
[[Category:Medieval Italian theologians]]
[[Category:Women of medieval Italy]]
[[Category:14th-century people of the Republic of Florence]]
[[Category:14th-century Italian women writers]]
[[Category:14th-century Italian people]]
[[Category:14th-century Christian mystics]]
[[Category:Stigmatics]]
[[Category:Italian hermits]]
[[Category:Burials at Santa Maria sopra Minerva]]
[[Category:Italian Roman Catholic saints]]
[[Category:Dominican saints]]
[[Category:14th-century Christian saints]]
[[Category:Incorrupt saints]]
[[Category:Doctors of the Church]]
[[Category:Italian women philosophers]]
[[Category:Catholic philosophers]]
[[Category:Roman Catholic theologians]]
[[Category:Roman Catholic mystics]]
[[Category:Women religious writers]]
[[Category:Female saints of medieval Italy]]
[[Category:Anglican saints]]
[[Category:Pre-Reformation saints of the Lutheran liturgical calendar]]
[[Category:14th-century Roman Catholic theologians]]
[[Category:Ambassadors of the Republic of Florence]]
[[Category:Deaths from anorexia nervosa]]
[[Category:Women ambassadors]]
[[Category:Medieval Italian women writers]]
[[Category:14th-century Italian writers]]
[[Category:Medieval Italian saints]]
[[Category:Women mystics]]</text>
      <sha1>1eamjyfz9de0ys5p9oeobcuw1tj6tsk</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
