  <page>
    <title>Centaur</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7401</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941782493</id>
      <parentid>941782372</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-20T17:14:07Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Fylindfotberserk</username>
        <id>9023670</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>On second thought perhaps you are right. Didn't see the [[WP:OVERLINK]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{About|the mythological creatures}}
{{short description|Greek mythological creature}}
{{Infobox mythical creature
| name = Centaur
| image = Brooklyn Museum - Centauress - John La Farge - overall.jpg
| caption = ''Centauress'', by John La Farge
| Grouping = [[Legendary creature]]
| Sub_Grouping = [[Hybrid (biology)|Hybrid]]
| AKA = Kentaur, Κένταυρος, Centaurus, Sagittary&lt;ref&gt;	
For Collins English Dictionary:
&quot;sagittary.&quot; Collins English Dictionary – Complete and Unabridged, 12th Edition 2014. 1991, 1994, 1998, 2000, 2003, 2006, 2007, 2009, 2011, 2014. HarperCollins Publishers 1 Sep. 2019 https://www.thefreedictionary.com/sagittary&lt;/ref&gt;
| Similar_creatures = [[Minotaur]], [[satyr]], [[harpy]]
| Mythology = [[Greek mythology|Greek]]
| Region = [[Greece]], [[Cyprus]]
| Habitat = Land
}}

A '''centaur''' ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|s|ɛ|n|t|ɔːr}}; {{lang-el|κένταυρος}}, ''kéntauros'', {{Lang-la|centaurus}}), or occasionally '''hippocentaur''', is a creature from [[Greek mythology]] with the upper body of a [[human]] and the lower body and legs of a [[horse]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Definition of centaur|url=http://oxforddictionaries.com/definition/english/centaur?q=centaur|work=Oxford Dictionaries|publisher=Oxford University Press|accessdate=19 April 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Webster's Dictionary#Webster.27s Third New International Dictionary .281961.29|''Webster's Third New International Dictionary'']], [[Merriam-Webster|G. &amp; C. Merriam Company]] (1961), ''s.v.'' '''hippocentaur'''.&lt;/ref&gt; Centaurs are thought of in many Greek myths as being as wild as untamed horses, and were said to have inhabited the region of Magnesia and Mount [[Pelion]] in [[Thessaly]], the [[Foloi oak forest]] in [[Elis]], and the Malean peninsula in southern [[Laconia]]. Centaurs are subsequently featured in [[Roman mythology]], and were familiar figures in the medieval bestiary. They remain a staple of modern fantastic literature.

==Mythology==
[[File:Centaur mosaic - Google Art Project.jpg|thumb|&quot;Battle of Centaurs and Wild Beasts&quot; was made for the dining room of [[Hadrian's Villa]] and estimated to be made between 120-130 A.D. The mosaic now resides in the Staatliche Museen zu Berlin in Germany.|alt=|left]]

===Creation of centaurs===
The centaurs were usually said to have been born of [[Ixion]] and [[Nephele]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Nash |first1=Harvey |title=The Centaur's Origin: A Psychological Perspective |journal=The Classical World |date=June 1984 |volume=77 |issue=5 |pages=273–291 |doi=10.2307/4349592|jstor=4349592 }}&lt;/ref&gt; As the story goes, Nephele was a cloud made into the likeness of [[Hera]] in a plot to trick Ixion into revealing his lust for Hera to [[Zeus]]. Ixion seduced Nephele and from that relationship centaurs were created.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Alexander |first1=Jonathann |title=Tzetzes, Chiliades 9 |url=https://www.theoi.com/Text/TzetzesChiliades9.html#20 |website=Theoi.com |publisher=Theoi Project |accessdate=February 28, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another version, however, makes them children of [[Centaurus (Greek mythology)|Centaurus]], a man who mated with the [[Magnesia (regional unit)|Magnesia]]n mares. Centaurus was either himself the son of Ixion and Nephele (inserting an additional generation) or of [[Apollo]] and the nymph [[Stilbe]]. In the latter version of the story, Centaurus's twin brother was [[Lapithes (hero)|Lapithes]], ancestor of the [[Lapith]]s.[[File:Centauromachy Staatliche Antikensammlungen 2640.jpg|thumb|Centauromachy, tondo of an [[Red-figure pottery|Attic red-figure]] [[kylix (drinking cup)|kylix]], c. 480 BC|alt=|left]]

Another tribe of centaurs was said to have lived on [[Cyprus]].  According to [[Nonnus]], they were fathered by [[Zeus]], who, in frustration after [[Aphrodite]] had eluded him, spilled his seed on the ground of that land. Unlike those of mainland Greece, the Cyprian centaurs were horned.&lt;ref&gt;[[Nonnus]], ''[[Dionysiaca]]'', v. 611 ''ff'', xiv. 193 ''ff'', xxxii. 65 ''ff''.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theoi.com/Georgikos/KentauroiKyprioi.html|title=CYPRIAN CENTAURS (Kentauroi Kyprioi) - Half-Horse Men of Greek Mythology|website=www.theoi.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There were also the Lamian Pheres, twelve rustic [[Daemon (classical mythology)|daimones]] (spirits) of the [[Lamos (Cilicia)|Lamos river]]. They were set by [[Zeus]] to guard the infant [[Dionysos]], protecting him from the machinations of [[Hera]], but the enraged goddess transformed them into ox-horned Centaurs. The Lamian Pheres later accompanied Dionysos in his campaign against the [[Indian people|Indians]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theoi.com/Georgikos/PheresLamioi.html|title=LAMIAN PHERES - Centaurs of Dionysus in Greek Mythology|website=www.theoi.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The centaur's half-human, half-horse composition has led many writers to treat them as [[liminal being]]s, caught between the two natures they embody in contrasting myths; they are both the embodiment of untamed nature, as in their battle with the [[Lapith]]s (their kin), and conversely, teachers like [[Chiron]].{{citation needed|date=March 2019}}

===Centauromachy===
The Centaurs are best known for their fight with the [[Lapith]]s who, according to one origin myth, would have been cousins to the centaurs. The battle, called the Centauromachy, was caused by the centaurs' attempt to carry off [[Hippodamia (wife of Pirithous)|Hippodamia]] and the rest of the Lapith women on the day of Hippodamia's marriage to [[Pirithous]], who was the king of the Lapithae and a son of Ixion. [[Theseus]], a hero and founder of cities, who happened to be present, threw the balance in favour of the Lapiths by assisting Pirithous in the battle. The Centaurs were driven off or destroyed.&lt;ref&gt;[[Plutarch]], ''Theseus,'' 30.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Ovid]], ''[[Metamorphoses]]'' xii. 210.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Diodorus Siculus]]iv. pp. 69-70.&lt;/ref&gt; Another Lapith hero, [[Caeneus]], who was invulnerable to weapons, was beaten into the earth by Centaurs wielding rocks and the branches of trees. In her article &quot;The Centaur: Its History and Meaning in Human Culture,&quot; Elizabeth Lawrence claims that the contests between the centaurs and the Lapiths typify the struggle between civilization and barbarism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Lawrence |first1=Elizabeth Atwood |title=The Centaur: Its History and Meaning in Human Culture |journal=Journal of Popular Culture |date=1994 |volume=27 |issue=4 |page=58}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Centauromachy is most famously portrayed in the [[Parthenon]] [[Metope (architecture)|metopes]] by [[Phidias]] and in a Renaissance-era sculpture by [[Battle of the Centaurs (Michelangelo)|Michelangelo]].

== Etymology ==
The Greek word ''kentauros'' is generally regarded as being of obscure origin.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first=Alex |last=Scobie |title=The Origins of 'Centaurs' |journal=Folklore |volume=89 |issue=2 |date=1978 |pages=142–147 |ref=harv|doi=10.1080/0015587X.1978.9716101 }} Scobie quotes {{cite book |author=Martin P. Nilsson |title=Geschichte der griechischen Religion |date=1955 |quote=Die Etymologie und die Deutung der Ursprungs sind unsicher und mögen auf sich beruhen|author-link=Martin P. Nilsson }}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[etymology]] from ''ken + tauros'', &quot;piercing bull,&quot; was a [[euhemerism|euhemerist]] suggestion in [[Palaephatus]]' rationalizing text on Greek mythology, ''On Incredible Tales'' (Περὶ ἀπίστων), which included mounted archers from a village called ''Nephele'' eliminating a herd of bulls that were the scourge of Ixion's kingdom.{{sfnp|Scobie|1978|p=142}} Another possible related etymology can be &quot;bull-slayer&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[Alexander Hislop]], in his polemic ''[[The Two Babylons]]: Papal Worship Revealed to be the Worship of Nimrod and His Wife''. (1853, revised 1858) theorized that the word is derived from the [[Semitic languages|Semitic]] [[Kohen]] and &quot;tor&quot; (to go round) via [[phonetics|phonetic shift]] the less prominent [[consonant]]s being lost over time, with it developing into '''K'''h'''en''' '''Tor''' or ''Ken-Tor'', and being transliterated phonetically into [[Ionic Greek|Ionian]] as ''Kentaur'', but this is not accepted by any modern philologist.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Origin of the myth==
[[File:Achilleus Lyra.jpg|thumb|[[Chiron]] teaching [[Achilles]] how to play the [[lyre]], a Roman fresco from [[Herculaneum]], 1st century AD.]]
The most common theory holds that the idea of centaurs came from the first reaction of a non-riding culture, as in the [[Minoan civilization|Minoan]] [[Aegean Sea|Aegean world]], to nomads who were mounted on horses. The theory suggests that such riders would appear as half-man, half-animal. [[Bernal Díaz del Castillo]] reported that the [[Aztec]]s also had this misapprehension about Spanish cavalrymen.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Stuart Chase |title=Mexico: A Study of Two Americas |chapter=Chapter IV: The Six Hundred |chapter-url=http://xroads.virginia.edu/~Hyper2/chase/ch04.html |via=[http://xroads.virginia.edu/~HYPER/hypertex.html University of Virginia Hypertexts] |access-date=24 April 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Lapith tribe of Thessaly, who were the kinsmen of the Centaurs in myth, were described as the inventors of horse-back riding by Greek writers. The Thessalian tribes also claimed their horse breeds were descended from the centaurs.

[[Robert Graves]] (relying on the work of [[Georges Dumézil]],&lt;ref&gt;Dumézil, ''Le Problème des Centaures''  (Paris 1929) and ''Mitra-Varuna: An essay on two Indo-European representations of sovereignty'' (1948. tr. 1988).&lt;/ref&gt; who argued for tracing the centaurs back to the [[Hindu|Indian]] [[Gandharva]]), speculated that the centaurs were a dimly remembered, pre-Hellenic fraternal earth cult who had the horse as a [[totem]].&lt;ref&gt;Graves, ''The Greek Myths'', 1960 § 81.4; § 102 &quot;Centaurs&quot;; § 126.3;.&lt;/ref&gt; A similar theory was incorporated into [[Mary Renault]]'s ''[[The Bull from the Sea]].''

== Variations ==
===Female centaurs===
{{main|Centaurides}}
[[File:GiorcesBardo55.jpg|thumb|Female centaurs flanking [[Venus (mythology)|Venus]] (Mosaic from Roman Tunisia, 2nd century AD)]]
Though female centaurs, called [[centaurides]] or centauresses, are not mentioned in early Greek literature and art, they do appear occasionally in later antiquity. A [[Macedon]]ian mosaic of the 4th century BC is one of the earliest examples of the centauress in art.&lt;ref&gt;Pella Archaeological Museum&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Ovid]] also mentions a centauress named [[Hylonome]]{{efn-lr|The name ''Hylonome'' is Greek, so Ovid may have drawn her story from an earlier Greek writer.}} who committed suicide when her husband [[Cyllarus]] was killed in the war with the Lapiths.&lt;ref&gt;[[Ovid|Publius Ovidius Naso]], ''Metamorphoses'', xii. 210 ''ff''.&lt;/ref&gt;

===India===
The Kalibangan [[cylinder seal]], dated to be around 2600-1900 BC,&lt;ref name=&quot;MMA239&quot;/&gt; found at the site of [[Indus-Valley civilization]] shows a battle between men in the presence of centaur-like creatures.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Ameri |first1=Marta |last2=Costello |first2=Sarah Kielt |last3=Jamison |first3=Gregg |last4=Scott |first4=Sarah Jarmer |title=Seals and Sealing in the Ancient World: Case Studies from the Near East, Egypt, the Aegean, and South Asia |date=2018 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |isbn=9781108168694 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Mu9UDwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT255 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;MMA239&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Art of the first cities : the third millennium B.C. from the Mediterranean to the Indus. |publisher=Metropolitan Museum of Art |pages=239–246 |url=https://archive.org/details/ArtOfTheFirstCitiesTheThirdMillenniumB.C.FromTheMediterraneanToTheIndusEditedByJ/page/n263 |language=English}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other sources claim the creatures represented are actually half human and half tigers, later evolving into the [[Hindu]] [[Durga|Goddess of War]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Deciphering the Indus Script| publisher=Cambridge Univ. Press|last=Parpola |first=Asko}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.harappa.com/blog/indus-cylinder-seals |title=Indus Cylinder Seals |date=May 4, 2016 |website=Harappa.com |access-date=2019-07-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; These seals are also evidence of [[Indus-Mesopotamia relations]] in the 3rd millennium BC.

In a popular legend associated with [[Pazhaya Sreekanteswaram Temple]] in [[Thiruvananthapuram]], the curse of a saintly [[Brahmin]] transformed a handsome [[Yadava]] prince into a creature having a horse's body and the prince's head, arms, and torso in place of the head and neck of the horse.

[[Kinnara Kingdom|Kinnaras]], another half-man, half-horse mythical creature from [[Indian epic poetry|Indian mythology]], appeared in various ancient texts, arts, and sculptures from all around [[India]]. It is shown as a horse with the torso of a man where the horse's head would be, and is similar to a Greek centaur.&lt;ref&gt;Devdutt Pattanaik, “Indian mythology : tales, symbols, and rituals from the heart of the Subcontinent” (Rochester, USA 2003)  P.74: {{ISBN|0-89281-870-0}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;K. Krishna Murthy, ''Mythical Animals in Indian Art'' (New Delhi, India 1985).&lt;/ref&gt;

===Russia===
A centaur-like half-human, half-equine creature called ''[[Polkan]]'' appeared in [[Russia]]n folk [[art]] and [[lubok]] prints of the 17th–19th centuries. Polkan is originally based on ''Pulicane'', a half-dog from [[Andrea da Barberino]]'s poem ''I Reali di Francia'', which was once popular in the Slavonic world in prosaic translations.

==Artistic representations==

=== Classical art ===
[[File:Cantharus Stathatou Louvre CA1987.jpg|thumb|[[Boeotia]]n ''[[kantharos]]'', [[Geometric art|Late Geometric period]]]]
The extensive Mycenaean pottery found at [[Ugarit]] included two fragmentary Mycenaean terracotta figures which have been tentatively identified as centaurs. This finding suggests a [[Bronze Age]] origin for these creatures of myth.&lt;ref&gt;Ione Mylonas Shear, &quot;Mycenaean Centaurs at Ugarit&quot; ''The Journal of Hellenic Studies'' (2002:147–153); but see the interpretation relating them to &quot;abbreviated group&quot; figures at the [[Temple of Aphaea|Bronze-Age sanctuary of Aphaia]] and elsewhere, presented by Korinna Pilafidis-Williams, &quot;No Mycenaean Centaurs Yet&quot;, ''The Journal of Hellenic Studies'' '''124''' (2004), p. 165, which concludes &quot;we had perhaps do best not to raise hopes of a continuity of images across the divide between the Bronze Age and the historical period.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; A painted terracotta centaur was found in the &quot;Hero's tomb&quot; at [[Lefkandi]], and by the [[Geometric art|Geometric period]], centaurs figure among the first representational figures painted on Greek pottery. An often-published Geometric period bronze of a warrior face-to-face with a centaur is at the [[Metropolitan Museum of Art]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.metmuseum.org/toah/works-of-art/17.190.2072 |title=Bronze man and centaur |website=The MET |publisher=Metropolitan Museum of Art |access-date=2019-07-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Ancient Greek art|Greek art]] of the [[Archaic Greece#Art|Archaic period]], centaurs are depicted in three different forms.  Some centaurs are depicted with a human torso attached to the body of a horse at the [[withers]], where the horse's neck would be; this form, designated &quot;Class A&quot; by Professor Paul Baur, later became standard.  &quot;Class B&quot; centaurs are depicted with a human body and legs joined at the waist to the hindquarters of a horse; in some cases centaurs of both Class A and Class B appear together.  A third type, designated &quot;Class C&quot;, depicts centaurs with human forelegs terminating in hooves. Baur describes this as an apparent development of [[Aeolis|Aeolic]] art, which never became particularly widespread.&lt;ref&gt;Paul V. C. Baur, ''Centaurs in Ancient Art: The Archaic Period'', Karl Curtius, Berlin (1912), pp. 5–7.&lt;/ref&gt;  At a later period, paintings on some [[amphoras]] depict winged centaurs.{{cite needed|date=December 2019}}

Centaurs were also frequently depicted in Roman art. One example is the pair of centaurs drawing the chariot of [[Constantine I|Constantine the Great]] and his family in the Great Cameo of Constantine (''circa'' AD 314–16), which embodies wholly pagan imagery, and contrasts sharply with the popular image of Constantine as the patron of early Christianity.&lt;ref&gt;The Great Cameo of Constantine, formerly in the collection of [[Peter Paul Rubens]] and now in the Geld en Bankmuseum, Utrecht, is illustrated, for instance, in Paul Stephenson, ''Constantine, Roman Emperor, Christian Victor'', 2010:fig. 53.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Iain Ferris, ''The Arch of Constantine: Inspired by the Divine'', Amberley Publishing (2009).&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Medieval art ===
[[File:Grape harvest Abbatiale Mozac 2007 06 30.jpg|thumb|Centaurs harvest grapes on a 12th-century capital from the [[Mozac Abbey]] in the [[Auvergne (region)|Auvergne]]]]

Centaurs preserved a [[Dionysus|Dionysian]] connection in the 12th-century [[Romanesque architecture|Romanesque]] carved [[Capital (architecture)|capitals]] of [[Mozac Abbey]] in the [[Auvergne (region)|Auvergne]]. Other similar capitals depict harvesters, boys riding goats (a further Dionysiac theme), and [[griffin]]s guarding the [[Chalice (cup)|chalice]] that held the wine. Centaurs are also shown on a number of [[Picts|Pictish]] carved stones from north-east [[Scotland]] erected in the 8th–9th centuries AD (e.g., at [[Meigle]], [[Perthshire]]). Though outside the limits of the [[Roman Empire]], these depictions appear to be derived from Classical prototypes.

=== Modern art ===
The [[John C. Hodges library at The University of Tennessee]] hosts a permanent exhibit of a &quot;Centaur from [[Volos]]&quot; in its library. The exhibit, made by sculptor Bill Willers by combining a study human skeleton with the skeleton of a [[Shetland pony]], is entitled &quot;Do you believe in Centaurs?&quot;. According to the exhibitors, it was meant to mislead students in order to make them more critically aware.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://notes.utk.edu/bio/unistudy.nsf/0/22d591ecc61a2cca85256efd00631d45?OpenDocument |volume=97 |issue=7 or 8 |date=August 26, 2004 |title=Library hails centaur's 10th anniversary |first=Maggie |last=Anderson |accessdate=2006-09-21 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070920205755/http://notes.utk.edu/bio/unistudy.nsf/0/22d591ecc61a2cca85256efd00631d45?OpenDocument |archivedate=September 20, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another exhibit by Willers is now on long-term display at the International Wildlife Museum in Tucson, Arizona.  The full-mount skeleton of a Centaur, built by Skulls Unlimited International, Inc., is on display along with several other fabled creatures, including the [[Cyclopes]], [[Unicorn]], and Griffin.

=== In Heraldry ===
Centaurs are common in European heraldry, although more frequent in continental than in British arms. A centaur holding a bow is referred to as a '''sagittarius'''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Davies&quot;&gt;[[Arthur Fox-Davies]], ''A Complete Guide to Heraldry'', T.C. and E.C. Jack, London, 1909, p 228, https://archive.org/details/completeguidetoh00foxduoft.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Literature ==
=== Classical literature ===
[[File:Centaur nymph Marqueste Tuileries.jpg|thumb|Centaur carrying off a [[nymph]] (1892) by [[Laurent Marqueste]] ([[Tuileries Garden]], Paris)]]
Jerome's version of the ''Life'' of St [[Anthony the Great]], written by [[Athanasius of Alexandria]] about the hermit monk of Egypt, was widely disseminated in the Middle Ages; it relates Anthony's encounter with a centaur who challenged the saint, but was forced to admit that the old gods had been overthrown. The episode was often depicted in ''The Meeting of St Anthony Abbot and St Paul the Hermit'' by the painter [[Stefano di Giovanni]], who was known as &quot;Sassetta&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[National Gallery of Art]], Washington, DC: [http://www.wga.hu/support/viewer/z.html illustration].&lt;/ref&gt; Of the two episodic depictions of the [[Anthony the Great|hermit Anthony]]'s travel to greet the hermit Paul, one is his encounter with the demonic figure of a centaur along the pathway in a wood.

[[Lucretius]], in his first-century BC philosophical poem ''[[On the Nature of Things]],'' denied the existence of centaurs based on their differing rate of growth. He states that at the age of three years, horses are in the prime of their life while humans at the same age are still little more than babies, making hybrid animals impossible.&lt;ref&gt;Lucretius, ''On the Nature of Things'', book V, translated by William Ellery Leonard, 1916 ([http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/ptext?lookup=Lucr.+5.878 The Perseus Project].) Retrieved 27 July 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Modern day literature===
{{Main|Centaurs in popular culture}}

&lt;!--PLEASE DO NOT LIST TRIVIA HERE; PLACE SINGLE-SENTENCE ITEMS IN THE MAIN ARTICLE ABOVE--&gt;

[[C.S. Lewis]]' ''[[The Chronicles of Narnia]]'' series depicts centaurs as the wisest and noblest of creatures. [[Narnian Centaurs]] are gifted at stargazing, prophecy, healing, and warfare; a fierce and valiant race always faithful to the High King [[Aslan]] the Lion.

In [[J.K. Rowling]]'s ''[[Harry Potter]]'' series, centaurs live in the Forbidden Forest close to Hogwarts, preferring to avoid contact with humans. They live in societies called herds and are skilled at archery, healing, and astrology, but like in the original myths, they are known to have some wild and barbarous tendencies.

With the exception of [[Chiron]], the centaurs in [[Rick Riordan]]'s ''[[Percy Jackson &amp; the Olympians]]'' are seen as wild party-goers who use a lot of American slang. Chiron retains his mythological role as a trainer of heroes and is skilled in archery. In Riordan's subsequent series, ''[[Heroes of Olympus]]'', another group of centaurs are depicted with more animalistic features (such as horns) and appear as villains, serving the [[Gigantes]].

[[Philip Jose Farmer]]'s ''[[World of Tiers]]'' series (1965) includes centaurs, called Half-Horses or Hoi Kentauroi. His creations address several of the metabolic problems of such creatures—how could the human mouth and nose intake sufficient air to sustain both itself and the horse body and, similarly, how could the human ingest sufficient food to sustain both parts.

[[Brandon Mull]]'s ''[[Fablehaven]]'' series features centaurs that live in an area called Grunhold. The centaurs are portrayed as a proud, elitist group of beings that consider themselves superior to all other creatures. The fourth book also has a variation on the species called an Alcetaur, which is part man, part moose.

The myth of the centaur appears in [[John Updike]]'s novel ''[[The Centaur]]''. The author depicts a rural Pennsylvanian town as seen through the optics of the myth of the centaur. An unknown and marginalized local school teacher, just like the mythological Chiron did for Prometheus, gave up his life for the future of his son who had chosen to be an independent artist in New York.
&lt;!--PLEASE DO NOT LIST TRIVIA HERE; info added to this section should be in essay form; list trivia at the MAIN ARTICLE: CENTAURS IN POPULAR CULTURE--&gt;

==Gallery==
&lt;gallery mode=&quot;packed&quot; heights=&quot;150px&quot;&gt;
File:Centaur lekythos Met 51.163.jpg|[[Diosphos Painter]], [[white-ground]] [[lekythos]] (500 BC)

File:Sandro Botticelli 063.jpg|[[Botticelli]], ''[[Pallas Athena|Pallas]] and Centaur'' (1482–83)
File:Canova - Theseus defeats the centaur - close.jpg|[[Antonio Canova]], ''Theseus Defeats the Centaur'' (1805-1819)
File:Bova1860.jpg|Prince Bova fights ''Polkan'', Russian [[lubok]] (1860)
File:Centaure Malmaison crop.jpg|A bronze statue of a centaur, after the ''[[Furietti Centaurs]]''
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Ancient Greece|Myths}}
[[File:Sebastiano Ricci 045.jpg|thumb|Painting by [[Sebastiano Ricci]], of centaurs at the marriage of [[Pirithous]], king of the [[Lapithae]]]]

Other hybrid creatures appear in Greek mythology, always with some liminal connection that links Hellenic culture with archaic or non-Hellenic cultures:
*[[Furietti Centaurs]]
*[[Hippocamp]]
*[[Hybrid (mythology)]]
*[[Ipotane]]
*[[Legendary creature]]
*[[Lists of legendary creatures]]
*[[Minotaur]]
*[[Onocentaur]]
*[[Ichthyocentaur]]
*[[Sagittarius (astrology)|Sagittarius]]
*[[Satyr]]

Also,
*Hindu [[Kamadhenu]]
*Indian [[Kinnara Kingdom|Kinnara]] which are half-horse and half-man creature.
*Islamic [[Buraq]], a heavenly steed often portrayed as an equine being with a human face. 
*Philippine [[Tikbalang]]
*Roman [[Faun]], and the [[Hippopodes]] of [[Pomponius Mela]], [[Pliny the Elder]], and later authors.
*Scottish [[Each uisge]] and [[Nuckelavee]]
*Welsh [[Ceffyl Dŵr]]

Additionally, ''[[Bucentaur]]'', the name of several historically important [[Republic of Venice|Venetian]] vessels, was linked to a posited ox-centaur or ''βουκένταυρος'' ''(boukentauros)'' by fanciful and likely spurious folk-etymology.

==Footnotes==
{{notelist-lr}}

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
*M. Grant and J. Hazel. ''Who's Who in Greek Mythology''. David McKay &amp; Co Inc, 1979.
*{{cite book
  | last = Rose
  | first = Carol
  | title = Giants, Monsters, and Dragons: An Encyclopedia of Folklore, Legend, and Myth
  | publisher =W. W. Norton &amp; Company, Inc.
  | year = 2001
  | location = New York, New York
  | page = 72
  | isbn  = 0-393-32211-4 }}
* Homer's Odyssey, Book 21, 295ff
*[[Harry Potter]], books 1, 3, 4, 5, 6, and 7.
*[[The Chronicles of Narnia]], book 2.
*[[Percy Jackson &amp; the Olympians]], book 1, 2, 3, 4 and 5.
*Frédérick S. Parker. ''Finding the Kingdom of the Centaurs''.

==External links==
{{Commons category|Centaurs}}
*[http://www.theoi.com/Georgikos/KentauroiThessalioi.html Theoi Project on Centaurs] in literature
*[http://theoi.com/Georgikos/Kentaurides.html Centaurides] on female centaurs
*[http://www.mythweb.com/encyc/entries/centaurs.html MythWeb] article on centaurs
*[http://www.hp-lexicon.org/bestiary/bestiary_c.html#centaurs Harry Potter Lexicon] article on centaurs in the Harry Potter universe
*[http://www.erich-kissing.de/kentaure.htm Erich Kissing's centaurs] contemporary art

{{Greek religion|state=collapsed}}

[[Category:Centaurs| ]]
[[Category:Greek legendary creatures]]
[[Category:Mythological horses]]
[[Category:Roman mythology]]
[[Category:Mythological human hybrids]]</text>
      <sha1>6dkxl8q0t5ivycmukmkjcm34kbc112z</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
