  <page>
    <title>Jews as the chosen people</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7451</id>
    <revision>
      <id>938972728</id>
      <parentid>932977850</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-03T14:59:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rescuing 2 sources and tagging 0 as dead.) #IABot (v2.0</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Jews and Judaism sidebar|religion}}
{{Jewish philosophy}}
In [[Judaism]], &quot;chosenness&quot; is the belief that the [[Jews]], via descent from the ancient [[Israelites]], are the [[chosen people]], i.e. chosen to be in a [[covenant (biblical)|covenant]] with [[God in Judaism|God]]. The idea of the Israelites being chosen by God is found most directly in the [[Book of Deuteronomy]]&lt;ref&gt;Clements, Ronald (1968). ''God's Chosen People: a Theological Interpretation of the Book of Deuteronomy''. In series, ''Religious Book Club'', 182. London: S.C.M. Press&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=What does it mean that the Jews are God’s chosen people? | website=GotQuestions.org | date=February 22, 2014 | url=https://www.gotquestions.org/Gods-chosen-people.html | access-date=April 4, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; as the verb ''bahar'' ({{native name|he|בָּחַ֣ר|italics=off}}), and is alluded to elsewhere in the [[Hebrew Bible]] using other terms such as &quot;holy people&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=9nN8AgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA9#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false The Jews as a Chosen People: Tradition and Transformation, S. Leyla Gurkan] p. 9&lt;/ref&gt; Much is written about these topics in [[rabbinic literature]]. The three largest Jewish denominations—[[Orthodox Judaism]], [[Conservative Judaism]] and [[Reform Judaism]]—maintain the belief that the Jews have been chosen by God for a purpose. Sometimes this choice is seen as charging the Jewish people with a specific mission—to be a [[light unto the nations]], and to exemplify the [[Covenant (biblical)|covenant]] with God as described in the [[Torah]].

This view, however, did not preclude a belief that [[God]] has a relationship with other peoples—rather, Judaism held that God had entered into a covenant with all humankind, and that Jews and non-Jews alike have a relationship with God. Biblical references as well as rabbinic literature support this view:  [[Moses]] refers to the &quot;God of the spirits of all flesh&quot; ({{bibleverse||Numbers|27:16|HE}}), and the [[Tanakh]] ([[Hebrew Bible]]) also identifies [[prophet]]s outside the community of Israel.  Based on these statements, some rabbis theorized that, in the words of [[Nethanel ibn Fayyumi]], a Yemenite Jewish theologian of the 12th century, &quot;God permitted to every people something he forbade to others...&lt;nowiki&gt;[and]&lt;/nowiki&gt; God sends a prophet to every people according to their own language.&quot;(Levine, 1907/1966)  The [[Mishnah]] states that &quot;Humanity was produced from one man, Adam, to show God's greatness. When a man mints a coin in a press, each coin is identical. But when the King of Kings, the Holy One, blessed be He, creates people in the form of Adam not one is similar to any other.&quot; (Mishnah Sanhedrin 4:5) The Mishnah continues, and states that anyone who kills or saves a single human, not Jewish, life, has done the same (save or kill) to an entire world. The [[Tosefta]], an important supplement to the Mishnah,&lt;ref&gt;(see Wikipedia &quot;Tosefta&quot;)&lt;/ref&gt; also states: &quot;Righteous people of all nations have a share in the [[Olam Haba|world to come]]&quot; (Sanhedrin 105a).

According to the [[Israel Democracy Institute]], approximately two thirds of [[Israeli Jews]] believe that Jews are the &quot;chosen people&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://en.idi.org.il/media/2720081/Democracy%20Index%20English%202013.pdf 2013 Democracy Index], &quot;We asked: “To what extent do you believe that the Jews are the ‘chosen people’?” As shown in Figure 34, roughly two thirds of the Jewish respondents (64.3%) believe “very strongly” or “quite strongly” that the Jews are indeed the chosen people, while one third (32.7%) do not share this view.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

==In the Bible==
According to the Bible, Israel's character as the chosen people is unconditional as it says in {{Bible verse||Deuteronomy|14:2|HE}},
:&quot;For you are a holy people to [[YHWH]] your God, and God has chosen you to be his treasured people from all the nations that are on the face of the earth.&quot;

[[File:136.The Prophet Amos.jpg|thumb|Prophet Amos as depicted by [[Gustave Doré]]]]
The Torah also says,
:&quot;Now therefore, if you will obey my voice indeed, and keep my covenant, then you shall be a peculiar treasure unto me from all the peoples, for all the earth is mine&quot; ({{Bible verse||Exodus|19:5|HE}}).
God promises that he will never exchange his people with any other:
:&quot;And I will establish My covenant between Me and you and your descendants after you in their generations, for an everlasting covenant, to be God to you and your descendants after you.&quot; [http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=genesis%2017:7&amp;version=NKJV (Genesis 17:7)].

Other Torah verses about chosenness,
*&quot;And you shall be unto me a kingdom of priests, and a holy nation&quot; ({{Bible verse||Exodus|19:6|HE}}).
*&quot;The Lord did not set his love upon you, nor choose you, because you were more in number than any people; for you were the fewest of all people; but because the Lord loved you, and because he would keep the oath which he had sworn unto your ancestors.&quot; ({{Bible verse||Deuteronomy|7:7–8|HE}}).

The obligation imposed upon the Israelites was emphasized by the prophet [[Amos (prophet)|Amos]] ({{bibleverse-nb||Amos|3:2|HE}}):
:&quot;You only have I singled out of all the families of the earth: therefore will I visit upon you all your iniquities.&quot;

==Rabbinic views==

Sometimes this choice is seen as charging the Jewish people with a specific mission—to be a light unto the nations, and to exemplify the [[Covenant (biblical)|covenant]] with God as described in the Torah.  This view, however, did not preclude a belief that [[God]] has a relationship with other peoples—rather, Judaism held that God had entered into a covenant with all humankind, and that Jews and non-Jews alike have a relationship with God.
Biblical references as well as rabbinic literature support this view:  Moses refers to the &quot;God of the spirits of all flesh&quot; ({{bibleverse||Numbers|27:16|HE}}), and the [[Tanakh]] ([[Hebrew Bible]]) also identifies [[prophet]]s outside the community of Israel.  Based on these statements, some rabbis theorized that, in the words of [[Natan'el al-Fayyumi]], a Yemenite Jewish theologian of the 12th century, &quot;God permitted to every people something he forbade to others...&lt;nowiki&gt;[and]&lt;/nowiki&gt; God sends a prophet to every people according to their own language.&quot;(Levine, 1907/1966)  The [[Mishnah]] states that &quot;Humanity was produced from one man, Adam, to show God's greatness. When a man mints a coin in a press, each coin is identical. But when the King of Kings, the Holy One, blessed be He, creates people in the form of Adam not one is similar to any other.&quot; (Mishnah Sanhedrin 4:5) The Mishnah continues, and states that anyone who kills or saves a single human, not Jewish, life, has done the same (save or kill) to an entire world. The Tosefta, a collection of important post-Talmudic discourses, also states: &quot;Righteous people of all nations have a share in the [[Olam Haba|world to come]]&quot; (Sanhedrin 105a).

Most Jewish texts do not state that &quot;God chose the Jews&quot; by itself. Rather, this is usually linked with a mission or purpose, such as proclaiming God's message among all the nations, even though Jews cannot become &quot;unchosen&quot; if they shirk their mission. This implies a special duty, which evolves from the belief that Jews have been pledged by the covenant which God concluded with the biblical patriarch [[Abraham]], their ancestor, and again with the entire Jewish nation at [[Mount Sinai]].&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.britannica.com/topic/chosen-people &quot;Chosen people.&quot;] ''Encyclopedia Britannica''.  20 February 2018.&lt;/ref&gt; In this view, Jews are charged with living a holy life as God's priest-people.

In the [[Siddur|Jewish prayerbook (the Siddur)]], chosenness is referred to in a number of ways. The blessing for reading the [[Torah]] reads, &quot;Praised are You, Lord our God, King of the Universe, Who has chosen us out of all the nations and bestowed upon us His Torah.&quot; In the &quot;[[Kiddush]]&quot;, a prayer of sanctification, in which the [[Shabbat|Sabbath]] is inaugurated over a cup of wine, the text reads, &quot;For you have chosen us and sanctified us out of all the nations, and have given us the Sabbath as an inheritance in love and favour. Praised are you, Lord, who hallows the Sabbath.&quot; In the &quot;Kiddush&quot; recited on festivals it reads, &quot;Blessed are You ... who have chosen us from among all nations, raised us above all tongues, and made us holy through His commandments.&quot; The [[Aleinu]] prayer refers to the concept of Jews as a chosen people: &lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;It is our duty to praise the Master of all, to exalt the Creator of the Universe, who has not made us like the nations of the world and has not placed us like the families of the earth; who has not designed our destiny to be like theirs, nor our lot like that of all their multitude. We bend the knee and bow and acknowledge before the Supreme King of Kings, the Holy One, blessed be he, that it is he who stretched forth the heavens and founded the earth. His seat of glory is in the heavens above; his abode of majesty is in the lofty heights.&lt;ref&gt;Translation by Philip Birnbaum, &quot;High Holyday Prayerbook&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===Further interpretations===
:''The following section contains information from the Jewish Encyclopedia, originally published between 1901–1906, which is in the public domain.''

According to the Rabbis, &quot;Israel is of all nations the most willful or headstrong one, and the Torah was to give it the right scope and power of resistance, or else the world could not have withstood its fierceness.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Beẓah, 25b&lt;/ref&gt;

&quot;The Lord offered the Law to all nations; but all refused to accept it except Israel.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Mek. Yitro, Pes. R. K. 103b, 186a, 200a&lt;/ref&gt;

How do we understand &quot;A Gentile who consecrates his life to the study and observance of the Law ranks as high as the high priest&quot;, says R. Meïr, by deduction from Lev. xviii. 5; II Sam. vii. 19; Isa. xxvi. 2; Ps. xxxiii. 1, cxviii. 20, cxxv. 4, where all stress is laid not on Israel, but on man or the righteous one.&lt;ref&gt;Sifra, Aḥare Mot, 86b; Bacher, &quot;Ag. Tan.&quot; ii. 31&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Maimonides-Statue.jpg|thumb|Monument to [[Maimonides]] in [[Córdoba, Andalusia|Córdoba, Spain]]]]
[[Maimonides]] states: ''It is now abundantly clear that the pledges Hashem made to Avraham and his descendants would be fulfilled exclusively first in Yitzchak and then in Yaakov, Yitzchak son. This is confirmed by a passage that states, &quot;He is ever mindful of His covenant ... that He made with Avraham, swore to Yitzchak, and confirmed in a decree for Yaakov, for Yisrael, as an eternal covenant.&quot; (Tehillim 105: 8,9).''&lt;ref&gt;Avraham Yaakov Finkel. ''The essential Maimonides. Translations of the Rambam'', [[Jason Aronson Inc]], Northvale New Jersey London&lt;/ref&gt;

The Gemara states this regarding a non-Jew who studies Torah [his 7 mitzvot]{{clarify|date=May 2012}} and regarding this, see Shita Mekubetzes, Bava Kama 38a who says that this is an exaggeration.{{clarify|date=May 2012}} In any case, this statement was not extolling the non-Jew. The Rishonim explain that it is extolling the '''Torah'''.

Tosfos explains that it uses the example of a ''kohen gadol'' (high priest), because this statement is based on the verse, &quot;''y'kara hi mipnimim''&quot; (it is more precious than pearls). This is explained elsewhere in the Gemara to mean that the Torah is more precious ''pnimim'' (translated here as &quot;inside&quot; instead of as &quot;pearls&quot;; thus that the Torah is introspectively absorbed into the person), which refers to ''lifnai v'lifnim'' (translated as &quot;the most inner of places&quot;), that is the Holy of Holies where the ''kahon gadol'' went.&lt;!-- somebody please rewrite this paragraph --&gt;

In any case, in Midrash Rabba (Bamidbar 13:15) this statement is made with an important addition: a non-Jew who converts and studies Torah etc.

The Nation of Israel is likened to the olive. Just as this fruit yields its precious oil only after being much pressed and squeezed, so Israel's destiny is one of great oppression and hardship, in order that it may thereby give forth its illuminating wisdom.&lt;ref&gt;Ex. R. xxxvi:1.&lt;/ref&gt; Poverty is the quality most befitting Israel as the chosen people (Ḥag. 9b). Only on account of its good works is Israel among the nations &quot;as the lily among thorns&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;Cant. R. ii. 2&lt;/ref&gt; or &quot;as wheat among the chaff.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Midr. Teh. i. 4&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Weber's &quot;System der Altsynagogalen Theologie&quot;, etc., pp. 59–69, is full of glaring errors and misstatements on the subject of Israel as the chosen people&lt;/ref&gt;

==Modern Orthodox views==
[[Rabbi]] Lord [[Immanuel Jakobovits]], former Chief Rabbi of the United Synagogue of Great Britain (Modern Orthodox Judaism), described chosenness in this way: &lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;Yes, I do believe that the chosen people concept as affirmed by Judaism in its holy writ, its prayers, and its millennial tradition. In fact, I believe that every people—and indeed, in a more limited way, every individual—is &quot;chosen&quot; or destined for some distinct purpose in advancing the designs of Providence. Only, some fulfill their mission and others do not. Maybe the [[Hellenic civilization|Greek]]s were chosen for their unique contributions to art and philosophy, the [[ancient Rome|Roman]]s for their pioneering services in law and government, the [[British Empire|British]] for bringing parliamentary rule into the world, and the Americans for piloting democracy in a pluralistic society. The Jews were chosen by God to be 'peculiar unto Me' as the pioneers of religion and morality; that was and is their national purpose.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;qtd. in [https://books.google.com/books?id=Yr4_nhEmtcAC&amp;pg=PA21&amp;lpg=PA21&amp;dq=%22%22Yes,+I+do+believe+that+the+chosen+people+concept+as+affirmed+by+Judaism+in+its+holy+writ,+its+prayers,+and+its+millennial+tradition.%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=CgRAued75m&amp;sig=Z6jain4ueaEkX5Jh0cyDXJXbzhc&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwjm3JCnkKvZAhUkKsAKHSq7Dw0Q6AEIPTAE#v=onepage&amp;q=%22%22Yes%2C%20I%20do%20believe%20that%20the%20chosen%20people%20concept%20as%20affirmed%20by%20Judaism%20in%20its%20holy%20writ%2C%20its%20prayers%2C%20and%20its%20millennial%20tradition.%22&amp;f=false Mackenzie]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

[[File:Michael wyschogrod head shot2.jpg|thumbnail|Michael Wyschogrod]]
Modern Orthodox theologian [[Michael Wyschogrod]] wrote: &lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;[T]he initial election of [[Abraham]] himself was not earned.  ... We are simply told that God commanded Abraham to leave his place of birth and [[Lech Lecha|go to a land that God would show him]].  He is also promised that his descendants will become a numerous people.  But nowhere does the Bible tell us why Abraham rather than someone else was chosen.  The implication is that God chooses whom He wishes and that He owes no accounting to anyone for His choices.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Wyschogrod, Michael.  ''The Body of Faith, Judaism as a Corporeal Election''.
 1984.  pp. 174–177.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Rabbi [[Norman Lamm]], a leader of [[Modern Orthodox Judaism]] wrote: &lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;The chosenness of Israel relates exclusively to its spiritual vocation embodied in the Torah; the doctrine, indeed, was announced at Sinai. Whenever it is mentioned in our liturgy—such as the blessing immediately preceding the Shema....it is always related to Torah or Mitzvot (''commandments''). This spiritual vocation consists of two complementary functions, described as &quot;Goy Kadosh&quot;, that of a holy nation, and &quot;Mamlekhet Kohanim&quot;, that of a kingdom of priests. The first term denotes the development of communal separateness or differences in order to achieve a collective self-transcendence [...] The second term implies the obligation of this brotherhood of the spiritual elite toward the rest of mankind; priesthood is defined by the prophets as fundamentally a teaching vocation.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Lamm, Norman.  [https://books.google.com/books?id=24Ad49QfKe0C&amp;pg=PA94&amp;lpg=PA94&amp;dq=%22The+chosenness+of+Israel+relates+exclusively+to+its+spiritual+vocation+embodied+in+the+Torah%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=9R43LGv2JX&amp;sig=ThGEaVzkQJgyeyoUceqzPR0sd3o&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwid7uqOkavZAhVUQMAKHXM6C5cQ6AEINjAB#v=onepage&amp;q=chosenness%20of%20israel%20relates&amp;f=false &quot;Seventy Faces: Articles of Faith, Volume 1.&quot;] ''Google Books''.  16 February 2018.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Conservative views==
[[File:JTSA 122 Bway jeh.JPG|thumb|right|180px|The [[Jewish Theological Seminary of America]], the main rabbinical seminary of Conservative Judaism]]
[[Conservative Judaism]], views the concept of chosenness in this way: &lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;Few beliefs have been subject to as much misunderstanding as the 'Chosen People' doctrine.  The Torah and the Prophets clearly stated that this does not imply any innate Jewish superiority.  In the words of Amos (3:2) 'You alone have I singled out of all the families of the earth—that is why I will call you to account for your iniquities.' The Torah tells us that we are to be &quot;a kingdom of priests and a holy nation&quot; with obligations and duties which flowed from our willingness to accept this status. Far from being a license for special privilege, it entailed additional responsibilities not only toward God but to our fellow human beings. As expressed in the blessing at the reading of the Torah, our people have always felt it to be a privilege to be selected for such a purpose. For the modern traditional Jew, the doctrine of the election and the covenant of Israel offers a purpose for Jewish existence which transcends its own self interests. It suggests that because of our special history and unique heritage we are in a position to demonstrate that a people that takes seriously the idea of being covenanted with God can not only thrive in the face of oppression, but can be a source of blessing to its children and its neighbors. It obligates us to build a just and compassionate society throughout the world and especially in the [[land of Israel]] where we may teach by example what it means to be a 'covenant people, a light unto the nations.'&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Emet Ve-Emunah: Statement of Principles of Conservative Judaism'', JTSA, New York, 1988, p.33–34&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Rabbi [[Reuven Hammer]] comments on the excised sentence in the Aleinu prayer mentioned above: &lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;Originally the text read that God has not made us like the nations who &quot;bow down to nothingness and vanity, and pray to an impotent god&quot;, [...] In the Middle Ages these words were censored, since the church believed they were an insult to Christianity. Omitting them tends to give the impression that the Aleinu teaches that we are both different and better than others. The actual intent is to say that we are thankful that God has enlightened us so that, unlike the pagans, we worship the true God and not idols. There is no inherent superiority in being Jewish, but we do assert the superiority of monotheistic belief over paganism. Although paganism still exists today, we are no longer the only ones to have a belief in one God.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Reuven Hammer, ''Or Hadash'', The Rabbinical Assembly, New York, 2003&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Reform views==
[[Reform Judaism]] views the concept of chosenness in this way: &quot;Throughout the ages it has been Israel's mission to witness to the Divine in the face of every form of paganism and materialism. We regard it as our historic task to cooperate with all men in the establishment of the kingdom of God, of universal brotherhood, Justice, truth and peace on earth. This is our Messianic goal.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''The Guiding Principles of Reform Judaism'', Columbus, [[Ohio]], 1937&lt;/ref&gt; In 1999 the Reform movement stated, &quot;We affirm that the Jewish people are bound to God by an eternal covenant, as reflected in our varied understandings of Creation, Revelation and Redemption [...] We are Israel, a people aspiring to holiness, singled out through our ancient covenant and our unique history among the nations to be witnesses to God's presence. We are linked by that covenant and that history to all Jews in every age and place.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Statement of Principles for Reform Judaism'', adopted at the 1999 [[Pittsburgh]] Convention, Central Conference of American Rabbis&lt;/ref&gt;

==Alternative views==
{{see also|Kabbalah#Distinction between Jews and non-Jews}}

===Equality of souls===
[[File:Rabbi Menachem Mendel Schneerson2 crop.jpg|thumb|alt=Chest high portrait of Rabbi Menachem Mendel Schneerson wearing a black hat|upright|Rabbi [[Menachem Mendel Schneerson]], the &quot;Lubavitcher Rebbe&quot;]]
Many [[Kabbalah|Kabbalistic]] sources, notably the [[Tanya]], contain statements to the effect that the Jewish soul is qualitatively different from the non-Jewish soul.  A number of known [[Chabad]] rabbis offered alternative readings of the Tanya, did not take this teaching literally, and even managed to reconcile it with the [[Left-wing politics|leftist]] ideas of [[Internationalism (politics)|internationalism]] and [[class struggle]]. The original text of the Tanya refers to the &quot;idol worshippers&quot; and does not mention the &quot;nations of the world&quot; at all, although such interpretation was endorsed by [[Menachem Mendel Schneerson]] and is popular in contemporary Chabad circles. [[Hillel of Parich]], an early Tanya commentator, wrote that the souls of righteous Gentiles are more similar to the Jewish souls, and are generally good and not egoistic. This teaching was accepted by Schneerson and is considered normative in Chabad.&lt;ref&gt;Lessons in Tanya, Vol. 1, Ch. 1&lt;/ref&gt;

====Different in character but not value====
According to the author of the Tanya himself, a righteous non-Jew can achieve a high level of spiritually, similar to an angel, although his soul is still fundamentally different in character, but not value, from a Jewish one.&lt;ref&gt;סידור הרב, שער אכילת מצה&lt;/ref&gt; [[Menachem Mendel Schneersohn|Tzemach Tzedek]], the third rebbe of Chabad, wrote that the [[Islam|Muslims]] are naturally good-hearted people. Rabbi Yosef Jacobson, a popular contemporary Chabad lecturer, teaches that in today's world most non-Jews belong to the category of righteous Gentiles, effectively rendering the Tanya's attitude anachronistic.

====Altruism====
An [[anti-Zionism|anti-Zionist]] interpretation of Tanya was offered by [[Abraham Yehudah Khein]], a prominent [[Ukraine|Ukrainian]] Chabad rabbi, who supported [[anarchist communism]] and considered [[Peter Kropotkin]] a great [[Tzaddik]]. Khein basically read the Tanya backwards; since the souls of idol worshipers are known to be evil, according to the Tanya, while the Jewish souls are known to be good, he concluded that truly altruistic people are really Jewish, in a spiritual sense, while Jewish nationalists and class oppressors are not. By this logic, he claimed that [[Vladimir Solovyov (philosopher)|Vladimir Solovyov]] and [[Rabindranath Tagore]] probably have Jewish souls, while [[Leon Trotsky]] and other totalitarians do not, and many Zionists, whom he compared to [[ape]]s, are merely &quot;Jewish by birth certificate&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;ר' אברהם חן, במלכות היהדות (Rabbi Abraham Chen, &quot;In the Kingdom of Judaism&quot;)&lt;/ref&gt;

====Righteous non-Jews====
[[Nachman of Breslov]] also believed that Jewishness is a level of consciousness, and not an intrinsic inborn quality. He wrote that, according to the [[Book of Malachi]], one can find &quot;potential Jews&quot; among all nations, whose souls are illuminated by the leap of &quot;holy faith&quot;, which &quot;activated&quot; the Jewishness in their souls. These people would otherwise convert to Judaism, but prefer not to do so. Instead, they recognize the Divine unity within their pagan religions.&lt;ref&gt;Likutei Moharan, Part 2 ,5&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Isaac ben Moses Arama|Isaac Arama]], an influential philosopher and mystic of the 15th century, believed that righteous non-Jews are spiritually identical to the righteous Jews.&lt;ref&gt;Isaac Arama, Akedat Yitzchak, Ch. 60&lt;/ref&gt; Rabbi [[Menachem Meiri]], a famous [[Catalan people|Catalan]] [[Talmud]]ic commentator and [[Maimonides|Maimonidian]] philosopher, considered all people, who sincerely profess an ethical religion, to be part of a greater &quot;spiritual Israel&quot;. He explicitly included Christians and Muslims in this category. Meiri rejected all Talmudic laws that discriminate between the Jews and non-Jews, claiming that they only apply to the ancient idolators, who had no sense of morality. The only exceptions are a few laws related directly or indirectly to intermarriage, which Meiri did recognize.

Meiri applied his idea of &quot;spiritual Israel&quot; to the Talmudic statements about unique qualities of the Jewish people. For example, he believed that the famous saying that Israel is above astrological predestination (''Ein Mazal le-Israel'') also applied to the followers of other ethical faiths. He also considered countries, inhabited by decent moral non-Jews, such as [[Languedoc]], as a spiritual part of the [[Holy Land]].&lt;ref&gt;Gregg Stern. ''Philosophy and Rabbinic Culture: Jewish Interpretation and Controversy in Medieval Languedoc''. Routledge Jewish Studies Series&lt;/ref&gt;

===Spinoza===
[[File:Spinoza Tractatus Theologico-Politicus.jpg|right|180px|thumb|''Tractatus Theologico-Politicus'']]
One Jewish critic of chosenness was the philosopher [[Baruch Spinoza]].&lt;ref&gt;Levy,
 Zeev.  [https://www.myjewishlearning.com/article/spinoza-and-the-philosophical-impossibility-of-a-chosen-people/ &quot;Spinoza and the Philosophical Impossibility of a Chosen People.&quot;] ''My Jewish Learning''.  1993.  20 February 2018.&lt;/ref&gt; In the third chapter of his ''[[Theologico-Political Treatise]]'', Spinoza mounts an argument against a naive interpretation of God's choice of the Jews. Bringing evidence from the [[Bible]] itself, he argues that God's choice of Israel was not unique (he had chosen other nations before choosing the Hebrew nation) and that the choice of the Jews is neither inclusive (it does not include all of the Jews, but only the 'pious' ones) nor exclusive (it also includes 'true gentile prophets'). Finally, he argues that God's choice is not unconditional. Recalling the numerous times God threatened the complete destruction of the Hebrew nation, he asserts that this choice is neither absolute, nor eternal, nor necessary.

==Reconstructionist criticism==
[[Reconstructionist Judaism]] rejects the concept of chosenness. Its founder, Rabbi [[Mordecai Kaplan]], said that the idea that God chose the Jewish people leads to [[racist]] beliefs among Jews, and thus must be excised from Jewish theology. This rejection of chosenness is made explicit in the movement's [[siddur]]im (prayer books).  For example, the original blessing recited before reading from the Torah contains the phrase, &quot;asher bahar banu mikol ha’amim&quot;—&quot;Praised are you Lord our God, ruler of the Universe, ''who has chosen us from among all peoples'' by giving us the Torah.&quot;  The Reconstructionist version is rewritten as &quot;asher kervanu la’avodato&quot;, &quot;Praised are you Lord our God, ruler of the Universe, ''who has drawn us to your service'' by giving us the Torah.&quot; In the mid-1980s, the Reconstructionist movement issued its ''Platform on Reconstructionism''. It states that the idea of chosenness is &quot;morally untenable&quot;, because anyone who has such beliefs &quot;implies the superiority of the elect community and the rejection of others.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Federation of Reconstructionist Congregations and Havurot, newsletter, September 1986, pages D, E.&lt;/ref&gt;

Not all Reconstructionists accept this view.  The newest siddur of the movement, ''Kol Haneshamah'', includes the traditional blessings as an option, and some modern Reconstructionist writers have opined that the traditional formulation is not racist, and should be embraced.&lt;ref&gt;e.g. Mitchell Max, ''The Chosen People: Reclaiming Our Sacred Myth''&lt;/ref&gt;

An original prayer book, by Reconstructionist feminist poet [[Marcia Falk]], ''The Book of Blessings'', has been widely accepted by both Reform and Reconstructionist Jews. Falk rejects all concepts relating to hierarchy or distinction; she sees any distinction as leading to the acceptance of other kinds of distinctions, thus leading to prejudice. She writes that as a politically liberal feminist, she must reject distinctions made between men and women, homosexuals and heterosexuals, Jews and non-Jews, and to some extent even distinctions between the Sabbath and the other six days of the week. She thus rejects the idea of chosenness as unethical. She also rejects Jewish theology in general, and instead holds to a form of religious humanism. Falk writes: &lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;The idea of Israel as God's chosen people [...] is a key concept in rabbinic Judaism. Yet it is particularly problematic for many Jews today, in that it seems to fly in the face of monotheistic belief that all humanity is created in the divine image—and hence, all humanity is equally loved and valued by God [...] I find it difficult to conceive of a feminist Judaism that would incorporate it in its teaching: the valuing of one people ''over and above'' others is all too analogous to the privileging of one sex over another.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Falk, 1996&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; Reconstructionist author [[Judith Plaskow]] also criticises the idea of chosenness, for many of the same reasons as Falk. A politically liberal lesbian, Plaskow rejects most distinctions made between men and women, homosexuals and heterosexuals, and Jews and non-Jews. In contrast to Falk, Plaskow does not reject all concepts of difference as inherently leading to unethical beliefs, and holds to a more classical form of Jewish theism than Falk.{{citation needed|date=May 2012}}

A number of responses to these views have been made by Reform and Conservative Jews; they hold that these criticisms are against teachings that do not exist within liberal forms of Judaism, and which are rare in Orthodox Judaism (outside certain [[Haredi]] communities, such as [[Chabad]]). A separate criticism stems from the very existence of feminist forms of Judaism in all denominations of Judaism, which do not have a problem with the concepts of chosenness.{{citation needed|date=May 2012}}

==Views from other religions==

===Islam===
{{see also|Islamic-Jewish relations}}
The children of Israel enjoy a special status in the Islamic book, the Quran (2:47 and 2:122)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.askmusa.org/site/c.ehLKKZPJLuF/b.3125653/k.7027/The_Jews_and_the_Quran.htm |title=Archived copy |access-date=2010-09-04 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180331101317/http://www.askmusa.org/site/c.ehLKKZPJLuF/b.3125653/k.7027/The_Jews_and_the_Quran.htm |archive-date=2018-03-31 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, Muslim scholars point out that this status did not confer upon Israelites any racial superiority, and was only valid so long as the Israelites maintain their covenant with God:&lt;ref&gt;M. Abdulsalam. &quot;[http://www.islamreligion.com/articles/310/ Is the Quran Anti-Semitic?: The Semites, a Chosen People].&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

===Christianity===
[[Image:PaulT.jpg|thumb|right|180px|Artist's depiction of ''Saint Paul Writing His Epistles'', 16th century (Blaffer Foundation Collection, Houston, Texas).  Paul was the first major figure in Christian history to hold that [[Jewish law]] is no longer valid.]]
{{see also|Jewish-Christian relations}}
Some Christians believe that the Jews were God's chosen people ({{Bibleref2|Deuteronomy|14:2}}),&lt;ref&gt;''Liberation and reconciliation: a Black theology'' p.  24&lt;/ref&gt; but because of Jewish [[Rejection of Jesus]], the Christians in turn received that special status ({{bibleref2|Romans|11:11–24}}).&lt;ref&gt;''The Collegeville Bible Commentary: Based on the New American Bible'', Robert J. Karris, Liturgical Press, 1992, p. 1042&lt;/ref&gt; This doctrine is known as [[Supersessionism]].

Other Christians, such as the [[Christadelphians]], believe that God has not rejected Israel as his chosen people ({{bibleref2|Romans|11:2}}), and that the Jews will in fact accept Jesus as their Messiah at his Second Coming, resulting in their salvation ({{bibleref2|Zechariah|12:10}}, {{bibleref2|Romans|11:26}}).&lt;ref&gt;[https://thechristadelphian.com/read-israel-gods-land Israel: God's People, God's Land], David M. Pearce, [https://thechristadelphian.com/ Christadelphian Magazine and Publishing Association Ltd (UK)]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Augustine]] criticized Jewish chosenness as &quot;carnal.&quot; He reasoned that Israel was chosen &quot;according to the flesh.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Augustine.  ''Adversius Judaios''.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Influence on relations with other religions==
[[Avi Beker]], an Israeli scholar and former Secretary General of the [[World Jewish Congress]], regarded the idea of the chosen people as Judaism's defining concept and &quot;the central unspoken psychological, historical, and theological problem at the heart of Jewish-Gentile relations.&quot; In his book ''The Chosen: The History of an Idea, and the Anatomy of an Obsession'', Beker expresses the view that the concept of chosenness is the driving force behind Jewish-Gentile relations, explaining both the admiration and, more pointedly, the envy and hatred the world has felt for the Jews in religious and also secular terms. Beker argues that while Christianity has modified its doctrine on the displacement of the Jews, Islam has neither reversed nor reformed its theology concerning the succession of both the Jews and the Christians. According to Beker, this presents a major barrier to conflict resolution in the Arab-Israeli conflict.&lt;ref&gt;Avi Beker, The Chosen: The History of an Idea, and the Anatomy of an Obsession, New York: Palgrave Macmilan, 2008, Preface&lt;/ref&gt;{{Page needed|date=July 2011}}

==Ethnocentrism==
Israeli philosopher Ze’ev Levy&lt;!-- notable, has page in he and de wikis --&gt; writes that chosenness can be &quot;(partially) justified only from the historical angle&quot; with respect to its spiritual and moral contribution to Jewish life through the centuries, &quot;a powerful agent of consolation and hope&quot;. He points out however that modern [[anthropological]] theories &quot;do not merely proclaim the inherent universal equality of all people [as] human beings; they also stress the ''equivalence'' of all human cultures.&quot; [emphasis in original] He continues that &quot;there are no inferior and superior people or cultures but only different, ''other'', ones.&quot; He concludes that the concept of chosenness entails [[ethnocentrism]], &quot;which does not go hand in hand with otherness, that is, with unconditional respect of otherness&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Ze’ev Levy, ''Judaism and Chosenness: On Some Controversial Aspects from Spinoza to Contemporary Jewish Thought'', in {{cite book|editor=Daniel H. Frank|title=A People apart: chosenness and ritual in Jewish philosophical thought|year=1993|publisher=SUNY Press|isbn=978-0-7914-1631-0}}, p. 104&lt;/ref&gt;

Some people&lt;ref&gt;
*Dinstien, Yoram (Ed.), ''Israel Yearbook on Human Rights 1987, Volume 17; Volume 1987'', p 29&lt;!-- This source says that once in 1969 the Syrian ambassador to the UN compared the Chosen People concept to the Nazi doctrine of Aryan superiority, but was quickly shot down as being off the mark since it actually refers to responsibility, not superiority; the author of the source agrees with the rebutter. Can we cite someone's &quot;opinion&quot; when the only reliable source we have for that &quot;opinion&quot; is that it is wrong (and hateful)? --&gt;
*Sharoni, Simona, &quot;Feminist Reflections on the Interplay between Racism and Sexism in Israel&quot;, in ''Challenging racism and sexism: alternatives to genetic explanations'',	Ethel Tobach, Betty Rosoff (Eds), Feminist Press, 1994, p 319
*Beker, Avi, ''Chosen: the history of an idea, the anatomy of an obsession'', Macmillan, 2008, p 131, 139, 151
*Brown, Wesley, ''Christian Perspectives on the Israeli-Palestinian Conflict'', p 66
*Jacob, Jonathan, ''Israel: a divided Promised Land'', p 69
&lt;/ref&gt; have claimed that Judaism's chosen people concept is racist because it implies that Jews are superior to non-Jews. The [[Anti-Defamation League]] asserts that the concept of a chosen people within Judaism has nothing to do with racial superiority.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.adl.org/presrele/asus_12/the_talmud.pdf The Talmud in Anti-Semitic Polemics] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100805220714/http://www.adl.org/presrele/asus_12/the_talmud.pdf |date=2010-08-05 }}, ''[[Anti-Defamation League]]'' (February 2003)&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Religious nationalism]]
* [[Supersessionism]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==References==
* ''Emet Ve-Emunah: Statement of Principles of Conservative Judaism'', JTSA, New York, 1988, p.&amp;nbsp;33–34
* ''Platform on Reconstructionism'' Federation of Reconstructionist Congregations and Havurot, September 1986, pages D, E
* ''Statement of Principles for Reform Judaism'', 1999 Pittsburgh convention of the Central Conference of American Rabbis
* ''Encyclopaedia Judaica'', Keter Publishing
* [[Ismar Elbogen]] ''Jewish Liturgy: A Comprehensive History'' JPS, 1993. The most thorough academic study of the Jewish liturgy ever written.
* [[Marcia Falk]] ''The Book of Blessings'' HarperSanFranciso, 1996
* [[Reuven Hammer]], Ed. ''Or Hadash: A Commentary on Siddur Sim Shalom for Shabbat and Festivals'', The [[Rabbinical Assembly]], 2003
* [[Nosson Scherman]], Ed. ''The Complete [[Artscroll]] Siddur'', Mesorah Publications, 2nd edition, 1986

==Further reading==
* {{cite book|first=Arnold M.|last=Eisen|authorlink=Arnold Eisen|editor-last=Lipset|editor-first=Seymour Martin |editor-link=Seymour Martin Lipset|title=American pluralism and the Jewish community|year=1990|publisher=[[Transaction Publishers]]|isbn=978-0-88738-286-4|chapter=The Rhetoric of Chosenness and the Fabrication of American Jewish Identity}}
* {{cite book|editor=Daniel H. Frank|title=A People apart: chosenness and ritual in Jewish philosophical thought|year=1993|publisher=SUNY Press|isbn=978-0-7914-1631-0}} (Part 1. Chosenness)

==External links==
*[http://www.jcpa.org/JCPA/Templates/ShowPage.asp?DRIT=4&amp;DBID=1&amp;LNGID=1&amp;TMID=111&amp;FID=623&amp;PID=0&amp;IID=2669&amp;TTL=The_Contemporary_Rivalry_over_the_Chosen_People:_Jewish,_Christian,_and_Muslim_Perspectives The Contemporary Rivalry over the Chosen People: Jewish, Christian, and Muslim Perspectives&amp;nbsp;– Avi Beker] at the [http://www.jewishaffairs.org Institute for Global Jewish Affairs]
*[http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=478&amp;letter=C&amp;search=chosen%20people Chosen people] at the [[Jewish Encyclopedia]]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20031001205019/http://rj.org/rj.shtml Beliefs of Reform Judaism]
*[http://www.acs.ucalgary.ca/~elsegal/Shokel/Preaching/S970623_Covenanting.html The Jewish concept of chosenness]
*[https://www.degruyter.com/view/product/506053 When God Wanted to Destroy the Chosen People, Dr Gili Kugler]
*[http://www.simpletoremember.com/faqs/The_Jewish_Nation.htm The Chosen People FAQs]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20040825092219/http://www.bc.edu/research/cjl/meta-elements/texts/articles/rosenthal.htm Some are Chosen, All are Loved. Rabbi Gilbert S. Rosenthal]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20040905200320/http://www.adatshalom.net/dvarchin/max.html ''The Chosen People: Reclaiming Our Sacred Myth'', Mitchell Max]
* [http://www.chabad.org/520294 ''How does Jewish Pride differ from Nazi Supremacy?'', Rabbi Tzvi Freeman]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20031011093845/http://www.adl.org/hate-patrol/churchmovement.asp Anti-Defamation League paper on Christian Identity]
*[http://www.nizkor.org/hweb/orgs/american/adl/paranoia-as-patriotism/covenant.html The Covenant, the Sword, and the Arm of the Lord&amp;nbsp;– a Christian Identity movement]
*[http://talmud.faithweb.com/ The Real Truth About The Talmud] by Rabbi [[Gil Student]]. Exposes fraudulent or distorted Talmud quotes used by antisemites
*[http://www.chabad.org/library/article_cdo/aid/160993/jewish/Are-the-Jews-the-Chosen-People.htm Are the Jews the Chosen People?] chabad.org
*[http://www.oztorah.com/2011/06/being-the-chosen-people-ask-the-rabbi/ OzTorah&amp;nbsp;– Isn't it arrogant and exclusionist for Jews to regard themselves as the Chosen People?]

{{Jews and Judaism}}
{{Exceptionalism}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Jews as the Chosen People}}
[[Category:Jewish theology]]</text>
      <sha1>eto4tmmfa03favt8muad5xls7yqk2ak</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
