  <page>
    <title>Constitution of Canada</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7411</id>
    <revision>
      <id>934850824</id>
      <parentid>932146266</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-08T21:24:05Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>GreenC bot</username>
        <id>27823944</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reformat 1 archive link. [[User:GreenC/WaybackMedic_2.5|Wayback Medic 2.5]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use Canadian English|date=August 2015}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=August 2015}}
{{Constitutional history of Canada}}

The '''Constitution of Canada''' ({{lang-fr|Constitution du Canada}}) is the supreme [[law of Canada|law in Canada]].&lt;ref name=&quot;CanadaCanada2000&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author1=Supreme Court of Canada|author1-link=Supreme Court of Canada|author2=Public Works and Government Services Canada|title=The Supreme Court of Canada and its Justices 1875-2000: La Cour suprême du Canada et ses juges 1875-2000|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=s8QhYNvBBxYC&amp;pg=PA27|date=1 November 2000|publisher=Dundurn|isbn=978-1-77070-095-6|pages=27–}}&lt;/ref&gt; It outlines Canada's [[system of government]] and the [[civil rights|civil and human rights]] of those who are citizens of Canada and non-citizens in Canada.&lt;ref name=&quot;MalcolmsonMyers2016&quot;&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=xUErDQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT75|title=The Canadian Regime: An Introduction to Parliamentary Government in Canada, Sixth Edition|author1=Patrick Malcolmson|author2=Richard Myers|author3=Gerald Baier|author4=Tom Bateman|publisher=University of Toronto Press|year=2016|isbn=978-1-4426-3598-2|pages=75–76}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its contents are an amalgamation of various codified [[Act of Parliament|act]]s, treaties between the Crown and indigenous peoples (both historical and modern), [[uncodified constitution|uncodified]] traditions and [[constitutional convention (political custom)|convention]]s. Canada is one of the oldest constitutional democracies in the world.&lt;ref name=&quot;CourtneySmith2010&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author1=John Courtney. David Smith|title=The Oxford Handbook of Canadian Politics|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=5KomEXgxvMcC&amp;pg=PA21|year=2010|publisher=Oxford University press|isbn=978-0-19-533535-4|page=21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to subsection 52(2) of the [[Constitution Act, 1982]], the Canadian Constitution consists of the ''[[Canada Act 1982]]'' (which includes the ''Constitution Act, 1982''), acts and orders referred to in its schedule (including in particular the ''[[Constitution Act, 1867]]'', formerly the British North America Act, 1867), and any amendments to these documents.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dunn2015a&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Christopher Dunn|title=Provinces: Canadian Provincial Politics, Third Edition|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=uJjpCgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA297|year=2015|publisher=University of Toronto Press|isbn=978-1-4426-3399-5|page=297}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Supreme Court of Canada]] has held that the list is not exhaustive and also includes a number of pre-confederation acts and unwritten components as well.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dodek2016&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Adam Dodek|title=The Canadian Constitution|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=86s7CwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT13|year=2016|publisher=Dundurn - University of Ottawa Faculty of Law.|isbn=978-1-4597-3505-7|page=13}}&lt;/ref&gt; See [[list of Canadian constitutional documents]] for details.

==History of the constitution==
{{Main|Constitutional history of Canada}}
The first semblance of a constitution for Canada was the [[Royal Proclamation of 1763]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Webber2015&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Jeremy Webber|title=The Constitution of Canada: A Contextual Analysis|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=f357BwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA11%7Cyear%3D2015%7Cpublisher%3DBloomsbury+Publishing%7Cisbn%3D978-1-78225-631-1%7Cpage%3D11%7D%7D%3C%2Fref%3E|year=2015|publisher=Bloomsbury Publishing|isbn=978-1-78225-631-1|page=11}}&lt;/ref&gt; The act renamed the northeasterly portion of the former French province of [[New France]] as Province of Quebec, roughly coextensive with the southern third of contemporary Quebec. The proclamation, which established an appointed colonial government, was the constitution of Quebec until 1774, when the British parliament passed the ''[[Quebec Act]]'', which expanded the province's boundaries to the [[Ohio River|Ohio]] and [[Mississippi River]]s (one of the grievances listed in the [[United States Declaration of Independence]]). Significantly, the Quebec Act also replaced the French criminal law presumption of guilty until proven innocent with the English criminal law presumption of innocent until proven guilty; but the French code or civil law system was retained for non-criminal matters.&lt;ref name=&quot;May2013&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Stephen May|title=Language and Minority Rights: Ethnicity, Nationalism and the Politics of Language|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Ejhq5N0UMzEC&amp;pg=PA248|year=2013|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-1-136-83706-7|page=248}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:Fathers of Confederation LAC c001855.jpg|thumb|left|A painting depicting negotiations that would lead to the enactment of the [[British North America Act, 1867]]]]

The [[Treaty of Paris of 1783]] ended the [[American War of Independence]] and sent a wave of British loyalist refugees northward to Quebec and Nova Scotia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=[[James Harley Marsh]]|title=American Revolution|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=wR_-aSFyvuYC&amp;pg=PA71|year=1999|publisher=The Canadian Encyclopedia|isbn=978-0-7710-2099-5|page=71}} = {{cite encyclopedia|url=https://www.thecanadianencyclopedia.ca/en/article/treaty-of-paris-1783|title=Treaty of Paris 1783|encyclopedia=[[The Canadian Encyclopedia]]|accessdate=October 8, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1784, the two provinces were divided; Nova Scotia was split into Nova Scotia, Cape Breton Island (rejoined to Nova Scotia in 1820), Prince Edward Island, and New Brunswick, while Quebec was split into Lower Canada (southern Quebec) and Upper Canada (southern through lower northern Ontario). The winter of 1837–38 saw rebellion in both Canadas, prompting their being rejoined as the [[Province of Canada]] in 1841.

The [[British North America Act of 1867]] established the Dominion of Canada as a federation of provinces.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hussey&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=W. D. Hussey|title=Government in Great Britain the Empire, and the Commonwealth|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=xHg6AAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA250|publisher=Cambridge University Press|page=250|id=GGKEY:Z7HUCT7C4X9}}&lt;/ref&gt; Initially, on 1 July 1867, four provinces entered into confederation as &quot;One dominion under the name of Canada&quot;: [[Canada West]] (former [[Upper Canada]], now [[Ontario]]), [[Canada East]] (former [[Lower Canada]], now [[Quebec]]), [[Nova Scotia]], and [[New Brunswick]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Hussey&quot;/&gt; Title to the [[Northwest Territories]] was transferred by the [[Hudson's Bay Company]] in 1870, out of which the province of [[Manitoba]] (the first to be established by the Parliament of Canada) was created. [[British Columbia]] joined confederation in 1871, followed by Prince Edward Island in 1873. The [[Yukon Territory]] was created by Parliament in 1898, followed by [[Alberta]] and [[Saskatchewan]] in 1905 (all out of parts of the Northwest Territories). [[Dominion of Newfoundland|Newfoundland]], Britain's oldest colony in the Americas and by then also a Dominion, joined Confederation in 1949. [[Nunavut]] was created in 1999 from the Northwest Territories.

An [[1926 Imperial Conference|Imperial Conference in 1926]] that included the leaders of all Dominions and representatives from [[British Raj|India]] (which then included [[Myanmar|Burma]], [[Bangladesh]], and [[Pakistan]]), led to the eventual enactment of the [[Statute of Westminster 1931]]. The statute, an essential transitory step from the [[British Empire]] to the [[Commonwealth of Nations]], provided that existing Dominions became fully sovereign of the United Kingdom and any new Dominions would be fully sovereign upon the grant of Dominion status.&lt;ref name=&quot;HarrisonFriesen2015&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author1=Trevor Harrison|author2=John W. Friesen|title=Canadian Society in the Twenty-First Century, 3e: An Historical Sociological Approach|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=dksqCgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA67|year=2015|publisher=Canadian Scholars’ Press|isbn=978-1-55130-735-0|pages=67–69}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although listed, Newfoundland never ratified the statute so was still subject to imperial authority when its entire system of government and economy collapsed in the mid-1930s. Canada did ratify the statute but with a requested exception—the Canadian federal and provincial governments could not agree on an amending formula for the Canadian constitution. It would be another 50 years before this was achieved. In the interim, the British parliament periodically passed enabling acts with respect to requested constitutional amendments as they arose; this was never anything but a [[Rubber stamp (politics)|rubber stamp]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://dsp-psd.pwgsc.gc.ca/Collection-R/LoPBdP/BP/prb0004-e.htm |title=INTERNATIONAL TREATIES: CANADIAN PRACTICE |first=Daniel |last=Dupras |date=3 April 2000 |work=Depository Services Program |publisher=Public Works and Government Services Canada |accessdate=17 December 2010 |quote=&quot;In 1931, under the Statute of Westminster, Canada and a number of other British dominions, acquired full independence(4) and with it authority to act internationally with all the attributes of a sovereign state. Full power over foreign affairs was thus conferred on Canada and section 132 of the Constitution Act, 1867 became obsolete.&quot; Footnote 4:&quot;Except with respect to amendments to Canada’s Constitution, which remained under the British Parliament’s jurisdiction until 1982.&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[patriation]] of the Canadian constitution was achieved in 1982 when the British parliament, with the request and assent of the Canadian parliament, passed the [[Canada Act 1982]], which included in its schedules the [[Constitution Act, 1982]]. The United Kingdom thus formally absolving itself of any remaining responsibility for, or jurisdiction over, Canada. In a formal ceremony on [[Parliament Hill]] in Ottawa, Queen [[Elizabeth II]] proclaimed both acts as law on 17 April 1982.&lt;ref name=&quot;McMenemy2006&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=John McMenemy|title=The Language of Canadian Politics: A Guide to Important Terms and Concepts|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=WeV0CwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA271|year=2006|publisher=Wilfrid Laurier Univ. Press|isbn=978-0-88920-694-6|pages=271–272}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Constitution Act, 1982'', includes the [[Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms]]. Prior to the Charter, various statutes protected an assortment of civil rights and obligations but nothing was enshrined in the constitution until 1982. The Charter has thus placed a strong focus upon individual and collective rights of the people of Canada.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tierney2016&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Stephen Tierney|title=Accommodating Cultural Diversity|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=NBXPCwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT95|year=2016|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-1-317-18591-8|page=95}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Enactment of the Charter of Rights and Freedoms has fundamentally changed much of Canadian [[constitutional law]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Newman2004&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Stephen L. Newman|title=Constitutional Politics in Canada and the United States|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=28X4RsAOftgC&amp;pg=PA63|year=2004|publisher=York University Press|isbn=978-0-7914-5937-9|pages=63–65}}&lt;/ref&gt; The act also codified many previously oral constitutional conventions and made amendment of the constitution in general significantly more difficult. Previously, the Canadian federal constitution could be amended by a solitary act of the Canadian or British parliament, by formal or informal agreement between the federal and provincial governments, or even simply by adoption as custom of an oral convention or performance that shows precedential but unwritten tradition. Since the act, textual amendments must now conform to certain specified provisions in the written portion of the Canadian constitution.

==Constitution Act, 1867==
{{Main|Constitution Act, 1867}}
{{More citations needed section|date=June 2017}}
This was an Act of the British parliament, originally called the British North America Act 1867. It outlined Canada's system of government, which combines Britain's Westminster model of parliamentary government with division of sovereignty ([[Canadian federalism|federalism]]). Although it is the first of 20 [[British North America Acts]], it is the most famous as the primary document of [[Canadian Confederation]]. With the patriation of the Constitution in 1982, this Act was renamed ''Constitution Act, 1867''. In recent years, the 1867 document has mainly served as the basis on which the division of powers between the provinces and federal government are analyzed.

==Constitution Act, 1982==
{{Main|Constitution Act, 1982}}
{{More citations needed section|date=June 2017}}
Endorsed by all provincial governments except that of Quebec, this was the formal Act of Parliament that effected Canada's full legislative independence from the [[United Kingdom]]. Part V of this act established an amending formula for the Canadian constitution, the lack of which (due to more than 50 years of disagreement between the federal and provincial governments) meant Canada's constitutional amendments still required enactment by the British parliament after Statute of Westminster in 1931.

The Act was enacted as a schedule to the Canada Act 1982&lt;!-- NOTE: Acts of the UK Parliament don't use a comma between &quot;Act&quot; and date --&gt;, a British Act of Parliament which was introduced at the request of a joint address to the Queen by the Senate and House of Commons of Canada. As a bilingual act of parliament, the Canada Act 1982 has the distinction of being the only legislation in French that has been passed by an English or British parliament since Norman French ([[Law French]]) ceased to be the language of government in England. In addition to enacting the Constitution Act, 1982, the Canada Act 1982 provides that no further British Acts of Parliament will apply to Canada as part of its law, finalizing Canada's legislative independence.

===Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms===
{{Main|Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms}}
As noted above, this is Part I of the Constitution Act, 1982. The Charter is the constitutional guarantee of the civil rights and liberties of every citizen in Canada, such as freedom of expression, of religion, and of mobility. {{citation needed |date=July 2019}} Part II addresses the rights of [[Aboriginal peoples in Canada]]. {{citation needed |date=July 2019}}

It is written in plain language to ensure accessibility to the average citizen. It applies only to government and government actions with the intention to prevent government from creating laws that are unconstitutional.

===Amending formula===
{{Main|Amendments to the Constitution of Canada}}
Instead of the usual parliamentary procedure, that includes the monarch's formal [[royal assent]] for enacting legislation, amendments to the Constitution Act, 1982, must be done in accordance with Part V of the Constitution Act, 1982, which provides for five different amending formulae. Amendments can be brought forward under section 46(1) by any province or the federal legislature. The general formula set out in section 38(1), known as the &quot;7/50 formula&quot;, requires: (a) assent from both the House of Commons and the Senate; (b) the approval of two thirds of the provincial legislatures (at least seven provinces) representing at least 50 per cent of the population (effectively, this would include at least Quebec or Ontario, as they are the most populous provinces). This formula specifically applies to amendments related to the proportionate representation in Parliament, powers, selection, and composition of the Senate, the Supreme Court and the addition of provinces or territories.

The other amendment formulae are for particular cases as provided by in the act. An amendment related to the [[Monarchy of Canada|Office of the Queen]], the use of either official language (subject to section 43), the amending formula itself, or the composition of the Supreme Court, must be adopted by unanimous consent of all the provinces in accordance with section 41. In the case of an amendment related to provincial boundaries or the use of an official language within a province alone, the amendment must be passed by the legislatures affected by the amendment (section 43). In the case of an amendment that affects the federal government only, the amendment does not need approval of the provinces (section 44). The same applies to amendments affecting the provincial government alone (section 45).

==Sources of the constitution==
{{Further|List of Canadian constitutional documents|Aboriginal land title#Canada|The Canadian Crown and Indigenous peoples of Canada|Canadian Aboriginal law|Numbered treaties|page 4=|page 5=}}
Canada's constitution has roots going back to the thirteenth century, including England's [[Magna Carta]] and the first English parliament of 1275.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation| last=Tidridge| first=Nathan| title=Canada's Constitutional Monarchy: An Introduction to Our Form of Government| page=54| publisher=Dundurn Press| location=Toronto| year=2010| isbn=9781459700840| url=https://books.google.com/books?id=JvGsvHsAtDgC&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false| ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is one of the oldest working constitutions in the world (others are: the [[Constitution of the United Kingdom|United Kingdom]], [[United States Constitution|United States]], [[Constitution of Sweden|Sweden]], [[Constitution of Norway|Norway]], [[Swiss Federal Constitution|Switzerland]], [[Constitution of Denmark|Denmark]]).{{Citation needed|date=June 2019}} Canada's constitution is composed of several individual statutes. There are three general methods by which a statute becomes entrenched in the Constitution:
# Specific mention as a constitutional document in section 52(2) of the ''Constitution Act, 1982'' (e.g., the ''Constitution Act, 1867'').
# Constitutional entrenchment of an otherwise statutory English, British, or Canadian document because its (still in force) subject matter provisions are explicitly assigned to one of the methods of the amending formula (per the Constitution Act, 1982)—e.g., provisions with regard to the monarchy in the English [[Bill of Rights 1689]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://senparlvu.parl.gc.ca/Guide.aspx?viewmode=4&amp;categoryid=-1&amp;eventid=8763&amp;Language=E| last=Senate of Canada| title=LCJC Meeting No. 74| date=20 March 2013| publisher=Queen's Printer for Canada| accessdate=24 March 2013| url-status=dead| archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130614215631/http://senparlvu.parl.gc.ca/Guide.aspx?viewmode=4&amp;categoryid=-1&amp;eventid=8763&amp;Language=E| archivedate=June 14, 2013| df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://scc-csc.lexum.com/scc-csc/scc-csc/en/item/2519/index.do ''Re: Resolution to amend the Constitution'', [1981&lt;nowiki&gt;]&lt;/nowiki&gt; 1 SCR 753 at p. 785.]&lt;/ref&gt; or the [[Act of Settlement 1701]]. 
#*English and British statutes are part of Canadian law because of the [[Colonial Laws Validity Act 1865]]; section 129 of the Constitution Act, 1867; and the Statute of Westminster 1931. If still at least partially unrepealed those laws then became entrenched when the amending formula was made part of the constitution.{{citation needed| date=April 2013}}
# Reference by an entrenched document—e.g., the Preamble of the Constitution Act, 1867's entrenchment of written and unwritten principles from the [[constitution of the United Kingdom]] or the [[Constitution Act, 1982]]'s reference to the [[Proclamation of 1763]]. 
#*Crucially, this includes Aboriginal rights and Crown treaties with particular First Nations (e.g., historic &quot;numbered&quot; treaties; modern land-claims agreements).

===Unwritten or uncodifed sources===
The existence of unwritten constitutional components was reaffirmed in 1998 by the Supreme Court in ''[[Reference re Secession of Quebec]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pentassuglia2009&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Gaetano Pentassuglia|title=Minority Groups and Judicial Discourse in International Law: A Comparative Perspective|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=mZbl0WBuk8oC&amp;pg=PA117|year=2009|publisher=Martinus Nijhoff Publishers|isbn=978-90-04-17672-0|page=117}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;The Constitution is more than a written text. It embraces the entire global system of rules and principles which govern the exercise of constitutional authority. A superficial reading of selected provisions of the written constitutional enactment, without more, may be misleading.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In practice, there have been three sources of unwritten constitutional law:&lt;ref name=&quot;BaumanKahana2006&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author1=Richard W. Bauman|author2=Tsvi Kahana|title=The Least Examined Branch: The Role of Legislatures in the Constitutional State|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=0KpYkm9SJvAC&amp;pg=PA159|year=2006|publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=978-1-139-46040-8|pages=159–161}}&lt;/ref&gt;

; Conventions: [[Constitutional convention (political custom)|Constitutional convention]]s form part of the constitution, but they are not judicially enforceable.&lt;ref name=&quot;OliverFusaro2011&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author1=Dawn Oliver|author2=Carlo Fusaro|title=How Constitutions Change: A Comparative Study|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=AoV6BAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT16|date=9 August 2011|publisher=Bloomsbury Publishing|isbn=978-1-84731-788-9|pages=16–}}&lt;/ref&gt; They include the existence of a [[Prime Minister of Canada|prime minister]] and [[Cabinet of Canada|Cabinet]], the fact that the [[Governor General of Canada|Governor General]] in most circumstances is required to grant [[royal assent]] to bills adopted by both houses of parliament, and the requirement that the prime minister either resign or request a dissolution and general election upon losing a vote of confidence in the [[House of Commons of Canada|House of Commons]].
; Royal prerogative: Reserve powers of the [[Monarchy of Canada|Canadian Crown]], being remnants of the powers once held by the British Crown, reduced over time by the parliamentary system. Primarily, these are the [[Order in Council|Orders in Council]], which give the government the authority to declare war, conclude treaties, issue passports, make appointments, make regulations, incorporate, and receive lands that [[escheat]] to the Crown.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jackson2013&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=D. Michael Jackson|title=The Crown and Canadian Federalism|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Y9_abe_a1m8C&amp;pg=PT61|date=31 August 2013|publisher=Dundurn|isbn=978-1-4597-0990-4|pages=61–}}&lt;/ref&gt;
; Unwritten principles:Principles that are incorporated into the Canadian constitution by the preamble of the [[Constitution Act, 1867]], including a statement that the constitution is &quot;similar in Principle to that of the United Kingdom&quot;, much of which is unwritten.&lt;ref name=&quot;BrydenAnastakis2009&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author1=Penny Bryden|author2=Dimitry Anastakis|title=Framing Canadian Federalism|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ZrwpIRcRwIAC&amp;pg=PA21|year=2009|publisher=University of Toronto Press|isbn=978-0-8020-9436-0|page=21}}&lt;/ref&gt; Unlike conventions, they are [[Justiciability|justiciable]]. Amongst those principles most recognized as constitutional to date are [[federalism]], [[liberal democracy]], [[constitutionalism]], the [[rule of law]], and respect for minorities.&lt;ref&gt;these were identified in [[Reference re Secession of Quebec]] [1998] 2 S.C.R. 217&lt;/ref&gt; Others include [[responsible government]], [[representation by population]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.collectionscanada.gc.ca/confederation/023001-3010.43-e.html |title=ARCHIVED - Key Terms - Provinces and Territories - Canadian Confederation - Library and Archives Canada |publisher=Collectionscanada.gc.ca |accessdate=17 April 2013 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130213082237/http://www.collectionscanada.gc.ca/confederation/023001-3010.43-e.html |archive-date=February 13, 2013 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[judicial independence]], [[parliamentary supremacy]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mapleleafweb.com/features/parliamentary-government-canada-basic-organization-and-practices&lt; Parliamentary Government in Canada: Basic Organization and Practices]{{Dead link|date=July 2019 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt; and an [[implied bill of rights]]. In one case, the [[Provincial Judges Reference]] (1997), a law was held invalid for contradicting an unwritten principle (in this case judicial independence).

==Provincial constitutions==
Unlike in most federations, Canadian provinces do not have written provincial constitutions.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://statecon.camden.rutgers.edu/sites/statecon/files/subpapers/morton.pdf|title=Conference on &quot;Federalism and Sub-national Constitutions: Design and Reform&quot;|last=|first=|date=|website=|access-date=2019-12-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; Provincial constitutions are instead a combination of [[uncodified constitution]], provisions of the Constitution of Canada, and provincial statutes.

Structures of the provincial government are described in parts of the Constitution. Part&amp;nbsp;V of the ''Constitution Act, 1867'' describes the governmental structure of the original four provinces. The three colonies that joined Canada had existing UK legislation which described their governmental structure, and this was affirmed in the terms of union, which now form part of Canada's Constitution (''[[British Columbia Terms of Union]]'',&lt;ref&gt;''British Columbia Terms of Union'', 16 May 1871 (UK), reprinted in RSC 1985, App II, No 10.&lt;/ref&gt; the schedules of ''[[Prince Edward Island Terms of Union]]'',&lt;ref&gt;''Prince Edward Island Terms of Union'', 29 June 1873 (UK), reprinted in RSC 1985, App II, No 12.&lt;/ref&gt; and ''[[Terms of Union of Newfoundland with Canada]]''&lt;ref&gt;''Newfoundland Act'', 12 &amp; 13 Geo VI, c 22 (UK), reprinted in RSC 1985, App II, No 32.&lt;/ref&gt;). The remaining three provinces were created by statute, and their structures are described in those statutes, which now form part of Canada's Constitution (''Manitoba Act, 1870'',&lt;ref&gt;''Manitoba Act, 1870'', SC 1870, c 3.&lt;/ref&gt; ''Alberta Act'',&lt;ref&gt;''Alberta Act'', SC 1905, c 3.&lt;/ref&gt; and ''Saskatchewan Act''&lt;ref&gt;''Saskatchewan Act'', SC 1905, c 42.&lt;/ref&gt;).

Section&amp;nbsp;45 of the ''Constitution Act, 1982'' allows each province to amend its own constitution. However, if the desired change would require an amendment to any documents that form part of the Constitution of Canada, it would require the consent of the federal government under section&amp;nbsp;43. This was done, for example, by the ''Constitution Amendment, 1998'', when Newfoundland asked the federal government to amend the ''Terms of Union of Newfoundland'' to allow it to end denominational quotas for religion classes.&lt;ref&gt;''Constitution Amendment, 1998 (Newfoundland Act)'', SI/98-25, (1998) C Gaz II, Extra No 1.&lt;/ref&gt;

Provinces have used their power under section&amp;nbsp;45 to enact statutes related to elections and rules for its legislature. For examples of this, see [[Constitution of Quebec]] and [[Constitution Act (British Columbia)]]. However, these acts are regular statutes, and are not enshrined as constitutional documents. They do not, generally, require a referendum or a super-majority of legislators to amend them. However, there are a small number of statutes that cannot be amended by a simple majority of the legislative assembly. For example, section&amp;nbsp;7 of the ''Constitution of Alberta Amendment Act, 1990'' requires plebiscites of Metis settlement members before that act can be amended.&lt;ref&gt;''Constitution of Alberta Amendment Act, 1990'', RSA 2000, c C-24.&lt;/ref&gt; Courts have not yet ruled about whether this kind of language really would bind future legislatures, but it might do so if the higher bar was met when creating the law.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

One way that provinces have put some statutes 'above' others is through [[quasi-constitutionality]]. This is the practice of allowing some statutes to take precedence over all others. Quasi-constitutionality is often applied to human rights laws, allowing those laws to act as a ''de facto'' constitutional charter of rights.

==Vandalism of the proclamation paper==
In 1983, Peter Greyson, an art student, entered Ottawa's National Archives (known today as [[Library and Archives Canada]]) and poured red paint mixed with glue over a copy&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Why the Charter has its red blotch |url=https://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/politics/why-the-charter-has-its-red-blotch/article4100514/ |accessdate=18 October 2019 |work=The Globe and Mail |date=April 15, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; of the proclamation of the 1982 constitutional amendment. He said he was displeased with the federal government's decision to allow United States missile testing in Canada and had wanted to &quot;graphically illustrate to Canadians&quot; how wrong he believed the government to be. Greyson was charged with public mischief and sentenced to 89 days in jail, 100 hours of community work, and two years of probation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.cbc.ca/archives/entry/1984-missile-protester-sentenced-for-defacing-constitution | work=[[CBC News]] | title=Missile Protester sentenced for defacing constitution}}&lt;/ref&gt; A grapefruit-sized stain remains on the original document; restoration specialists opted to leave most of the paint intact, fearing that removal attempts would only cause further damage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.cbc.ca/archives/categories/politics/the-constitution/the-constitution-general/missile-protestor-defaces-constitution.html | work=[[CBC News]] | title=Missile Protestor defaces Constitution}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Canada|Politics|Law}}
* [[Canadian Bill of Rights]]
* [[Constitution Act (British Columbia)]]
* [[Constitution of Quebec]]
* [[Constitutionalism]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

== Further reading ==
{{refbegin}}
* {{citation |last=Munro |first=Joseph Edwin Crawford |year=1889 |title=The Constitution of Canada |url=https://books.google.ca/books?id=6P88AAAAIAAJ&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;dq=Constitution%20of%20Canada&amp;pg=PR9#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=true |publisher=Cambridge University Press |isbn=}}
*{{cite journal |last=Doull |first=James |authorlink=James Doull |title=The Philosophical Basis of Constitutional Discussion in Canada |journal=[[Animus (journal)|Animus]] |year=1997 |volume=2 |url=http://www2.swgc.mun.ca/animus/Articles/Volume%202/doull1.pdf |issn=1209-0689 |accessdate=August 9, 2011}}
*{{cite book |author=Christian Leuprecht |title=Essential Readings in Canadian Constitutional Politics |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=kDN1WzoaFNEC&amp;pg=PP1 |year=2011 |publisher=University of Toronto Press |isbn=978-1-4426-0368-4}}
*{{cite book |last=Manfredi |first=Christopher |author2=James B. Kelly |url=https://books.google.ca/books?id=y9bySE_p-UQC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PP1#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false |title=Contested Constitutionalism: Reflections on the Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms |year=2009 |publisher=UBC Press |isbn=978-0-7748-1674-8}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons category}}
{{Wikisourcepar|Constitution Act, 1982}}
{{Wikisourcepar|British North America Act, 1867}}
* [http://laws.justice.gc.ca/eng/Const/Const_index.html Full text of the Constitution]
* [http://www.canadiana.org/citm/ Canada in the Making] – a comprehensive history of the Canadian Constitution with digitized primary sources.
* [http://www.charterofrights.ca/language.php Fundamental Freedoms: The Charter of Rights and Freedoms] – Charter of Rights and Freedoms website with video, audio and the Charter in over 20 languages
* [http://www.solon.org/Constitutions/Canada/English/Proposals/MeechLake.html Meech Lake Accord, 1987]
* [http://www.solon.org/Constitutions/Canada/English/Proposals/CharlottetownConsensus.html Charlottetown Accord, 1992]
* [http://www.solon.org/Constitutions/Canada/English/Proposals/charlottetown-res.html Results of Referendum on the Charlottetown Accord, 1992]
* [http://www.cbc.ca/archives/categories/politics/the-constitution/charting-the-future-canadas-new-constitution/topic---charting-the-future-canadas-new-constitution.html CBC Digital Archives – Charting the Future: Canada's New Constitution]
* [http://www.cbc.ca/archives/categories/politics/the-constitution/canadas-constitutional-debate-what-makes-a-nation/topic---canadas-constitutional-debate-what-makes-a-nation.html CBC Digital Archives – Canada's Constitutional Debate: What Makes a Nation?]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20140427222923/http://originaldocuments.ca/ OriginalDocuments.ca]
*[https://www.thecanadianencyclopedia.ca/en/article/constitution/ Constitution of Canada]

{{Constitution of Canada}}
{{Canada topic|Constitution of}}
{{Canada topics}}
{{Americas topic|Constitution of|title=Constitutions of countries in the Americas}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Constitution Of Canada}}
[[Category:Constitution of Canada| ]]
[[Category:Uncodified constitutions]]</text>
      <sha1>1owqa91kiwkchuxqpk3v4bo91sb0wgw</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
