  <page>
    <title>Bay leaf</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3419</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943305947</id>
      <parentid>937396879</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-03-01T03:30:00Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Marchino61</username>
        <id>18450908</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Sources */ &quot;non English-speaking countries? Why? It is standard in stews in the UK, for example. The citation says nothing about non English-speaking. Deleted.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{See also|Laurus nobilis}}
[[File:Bay Leaves.JPG|thumb|right|Bay laurel leaves (''Laurus nobilis'')]]
[[File:Indian bay leaf - tejpatta - indisches Lorbeerblatt.jpg|thumb|right|Indian bay leaf ''[[Cinnamomum tamala]]'']]
[[File:Syzy polyan 070404-3398 sbrg.jpg|thumb|right|Indonesian bay leaf ''[[Syzygium polyanthum]]'']]

The '''bay leaf''' is an aromatic leaf commonly used in cooking. It can be used whole, or as dried and ground.

== Sources ==
Bay leaves come from several plants, such as:

*[[Bay laurel]] (''Laurus nobilis'', [[Lauraceae]]). Fresh or dried bay leaves are used in cooking for their distinctive flavour and fragrance. The leaves should be removed from the cooked food before eating (see [[#Safety|Safety]] section below). The leaves are often used to flavour soups, stews, braises and pâtés in many countries. The fresh leaves are very mild and do not develop their full flavour until several weeks after picking and drying.&lt;ref name=&quot;Spice Trade: Bay Leaf&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url= http://www.spice-trade.com/bay-leaf.html| title= Spice Trade: Bay Leaf| accessdate= 2009-04-11| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20090412090109/http://www.spice-trade.com/bay-leaf.html| archivedate= 12 April 2009| url-status= dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*California bay leaf&amp;nbsp;&amp;ndash; the leaf of the California bay tree (''[[Umbellularia californica]]'', Lauraceae), also known as California laurel, Oregon myrtle, and pepperwood, is similar to the Mediterranean bay laurel, but has a stronger flavour.
*Indian bay leaf or malabathrum (''[[Cinnamomum tamala]]'', Lauraceae) differs in that bay laurel leaves are shorter and light to medium green in colour, with one large vein down the length of the leaf, while tejpat (''Cinnamonum tamala'') leaves are about twice as long and wider, usually olive green in colour, and with three veins down the length of the leaf and is culinarily quite different, having a fragrance and taste similar to [[Cinnamomum aromaticum|cinnamon (cassia)]] bark, but milder.
*Indonesian bay leaf or Indonesian laurel (''salam'' leaf, ''[[Syzygium polyanthum]]'', Myrtaceae) is not commonly found outside Indonesia; this herb is applied to meat and, less often, to vegetables.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://gernot-katzers-spice-pages.com/engl/Euge_pol.html | title =Spice Pages: Indonesian Bay-Leaf | accessdate = 2012-12-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*West Indian bay leaf, the leaf of the West Indian bay tree (''[[Pimenta racemosa]]'', Myrtaceae), used culinarily and to produce the [[Eau de Cologne|cologne]] called [[bay rum]].
*Mexican bay leaf (''[[Litsea glaucescens]]'', Lauraceae).

== Chemical constituents==
The leaves contain about 1.3% essential oils (ol. lauri folii), consisting of 45% [[eucalyptol]], 12% other [[terpenes]], 8-12% terpinyl acetate, 3–4% [[sesquiterpenes]], 3% [[methyleugenol]], and other α- and β-[[pinene]]s, [[phellandrene]], [[linalool]], [[geraniol]], [[terpineol]], and contain [[lauric acid]] also.

== Taste and aroma==
If eaten whole, bay leaves (''Laurus nobilis'') are pungent and have a sharp, bitter taste. As with many spices and flavourings, the fragrance of the bay leaf is more noticeable than its taste. When dried, the fragrance is herbal, slightly floral, and somewhat similar to [[oregano]] and [[thyme]]. [[Myrcene]], which is a component of many essential oils used in perfumery, can be extracted from the bay leaf. They also contain [[eugenol]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Encyclopedia of Spices: Bay Leaf&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.theepicentre.com/Spices/bay.html | title=Encyclopedia of Spices: Bay Leaf | access-date=11 April 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Uses==
In Indian and Pakistani cuisine, bay laurel leaves are sometimes used in place of [[Cinnamomum tamala|Indian bay leaf]], although they have a different flavour. They are most often used in rice dishes like [[biryani]] and as an ingredient in [[garam masala]]. Bay (laurel) leaves are frequently packaged as {{lang|hi-Latn|tejpattā}} ({{lang|hi|तेजपत्ता}}, the Hindi term for Indian bay leaf), creating confusion between the two herbs.

In the Philippines, dried bay laurel leaves are used in several Filipino dishes such as [[menudo (stew)|menudo]], [[pares (food)|beef pares]], and [[philippine adobo|adobo]].

Bay leaves were used for flavouring by the ancient Greeks.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.reshafim.org.il/ad/egypt/botany/trees.htm &quot;Ancient Egyptian Plants: Trees&quot; ''www.reshafim.org.il''] Retrieved October 29, 2013&lt;/ref&gt; They are a fixture in the cooking of many European cuisines (particularly those of the Mediterranean), as well as in the Americas. They are used in soups, stews, meat, seafood, vegetable dishes, and sauces. The leaves also flavour many classic French dishes. The leaves are most often used whole (sometimes in a {{lang|fr|[[bouquet garni]]}}) and removed before serving (they can be abrasive in the digestive tract). Thai and Laotian cuisine employs bay leaf ({{lang-th|ใบกระวาน}}, {{lang|th-Latn|bai kra wān}}) in a few Arab-influenced dishes, notably [[massaman curry]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Tan |first=Hugh T. W. 
|title=Herbs &amp; Spices of Thailand |publisher=Marshall Cavendish |year=2005 |page=71 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Bay leaves can also be crushed or ground before cooking. Crushed bay leaves impart more fragrance than whole leaves, but are more difficult to remove, and thus they are often used in a muslin bag or tea infuser. Ground bay laurel may be substituted for whole leaves, and does not need to be removed, but it is much stronger.

Bay leaves are also used in the making of jerk chicken in the Caribbean Islands. The bay leaves are soaked and placed on the cool side of the grill. Pimento sticks are placed on top of the leaves and the chicken is placed on top and smoked.

Bay leaves can also be used scattered in a [[pantry]] to repel [[meal moth]]s,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.care2.com/greenliving/repel-grain-moths-with-bay-leaves.html |title=How to Repel Grain Moths with Bay Leaves |accessdate=2009-04-11 }}&lt;/ref&gt; flies,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Palacios |first1=S |last2=Bertoni |first2=A |last3=Rossi |first3=Y |last4=Santander |first4=R |last5=Urzua |first5=A |year=2009 |title=Efficacy of Essential Oils from Edible Plants as Insecticides Against the House Fly, ''Musca domestica'' L. |journal=Molecules |volume=14 |issue=5 |pages=1938–1947 |doi=10.3390/molecules14051938 |pmid=19471213 |pmc=6254201 }}&lt;/ref&gt; cockroaches,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=Naturally Occurring Pest Bioregulators |volume=449 |doi=10.1021/bk-1991-0449 |series=ACS Symposium Series |year=1991 |isbn=978-0-8412-1897-0 |last1=Hedin |first1=Paul Arthur |last2=Hedin |first2=Paul A. |url-access=registration |url=https://archive.org/details/naturallyoccurri00paul }}&lt;/ref&gt;  mice,{{citation needed |date=November 2012 }} and [[silverfish]].{{citation needed |date=November 2012 }}

Bay leaves have been used in entomology as the active ingredient in [[killing jar]]s. The crushed, fresh, young leaves are put into the jar under a layer of paper. The vapors they release kill insects slowly but effectively, and keep the specimens relaxed and easy to mount. The leaves discourage the growth of molds. They are not effective for killing large beetles and similar specimens, but insects that have been killed in a cyanide killing jar can be transferred to a laurel jar to await mounting.&lt;ref  name=JohnSmart&gt;{{cite book | last = Smart | first = John | title = British Museum (Natural History) Instructions for Collectors NO. 4A. Insects | publisher = Trustees of the British Museum | location = London | year = 1963  }}&lt;/ref&gt; There is confusion in the literature about whether ''Laurus nobilis'' is a source of cyanide to any practical extent, but there is no evidence that cyanide is relevant to its value in killing jars. It certainly is rich in various essential oil components that could incapacitate insects in high concentrations; such compounds include [[Eucalyptol|1,8-cineole]], alpha-terpinyl acetate, and [[methyl eugenol]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Marzouki | first1 = H | last2 = Piras | first2 = A | last3 = Salah | first3 = KB | last4 = Medini | first4 = H | last5 = Pivetta | first5 = T | last6 = Bouzid | first6 = S | last7 = Marongiu | first7 = B | last8 = Falconieri | first8 = D | year = 2009 | title = Essential oil composition and variability of Laurus nobilis L. growing in Tunisia, comparison and chemometric investigation of different plant organs | url = | journal = Nat Prod Res | volume = 23 | issue = 4| pages = 343–54 | doi = 10.1080/14786410802076200 | pmid = 19296375 }}&lt;/ref&gt; It also is unclear to what extent the alleged effect of cyanide released by the crushed leaves has been mis-attributed to ''Laurus nobilis'' in confusion with the unrelated ''[[Prunus laurocerasus]]'', the so-called cherry laurel, which certainly does contain dangerous concentrations of cyanogenic glycocides&lt;ref name= &quot;vWvHvO&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last1=van Wyk |first1=Ben-Erik |last2=van Heerden |first2=Fanie |last3=van Oudtshoorn |first3=Bosch |title=Poisonous Plants of South Africa |publisher=Briza |location=Pretoria |year=2002 |isbn=978-1875093304}}&lt;/ref&gt; together with the enzymes to generate the [[hydrogen cyanide]] from the glycocides if the leaf is physically damaged.&lt;ref name=&quot;SchomburgSalzmann2013&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author1=Dietmar Schomburg|author2=Margit Salzmann|title=Enzyme Handbook: Volume 1: Class 4: Lyases|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=8uf7CAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT270|date=11 November 2013|publisher=Springer Science &amp; Business Media|isbn=978-3-642-86605-0|pages=270–}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Safety==
Some members of the laurel family, as well as the unrelated but visually similar [[Kalmia latifolia|mountain laurel]] and [[Prunus laurocerasus|cherry laurel]], have leaves that are poisonous to humans and livestock.&lt;ref name= &quot;vWvHvO&quot;/&gt; While these plants are not sold anywhere for culinary use, their visual similarity to bay leaves has led to the oft-repeated belief that bay leaves should be removed from food after cooking because they are poisonous. This is not true; bay leaves may be eaten without toxic effect. However, they remain unpleasantly stiff even after thorough cooking, and if swallowed whole or in large pieces, they may pose a risk of harming the digestive tract or causing choking.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/lifestyle/food/bay-leaf-should-it-stay-or-should-it-go/2014/09/30/131eb444-429e-11e4-9a15-137aa0153527_story.html|title=Bay leaf: Should it stay or should it go?|first=Bonnie S.|last=Benwick|date=30 September 2014|access-date=5 January 2018|work=Washington Post}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thus, most recipes that use bay leaves will recommend their removal after the cooking process has finished.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.straightdope.com/columns/read/2695/what-is-the-origin-of-the-song-theres-a-place-in-france-where-the-naked-ladies-dance | title =Straight Dope: Are Bay Leaves Poisonous? | accessdate = 2009-04-11| date =2007-02-23 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Canadian food and drug regulations ===
The Canadian government requires that the bay leaves contain no more than 4.5% total ash material with a maximum of 0.5% of which is insoluble in hydrochloric acid. To be considered dried it has to contain 7% moisture or less. The oil content cannot be less than 1 milliliter per 100 grams of the spice. &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=http://laws.justice.gc.ca/eng/regulations/C.R.C.,_c._870/page-36.html#h-70 |title = Consolidated federal laws of canada, Food and Drug Regulations|date = 2019-06-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{Herbs &amp; spices}}
{{Non-timber forest products}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Bay Leaf}}
[[Category:Herbs]]
[[Category:Leaves]]
[[Category:Non-timber forest products]]
[[Category:Plant common names]]</text>
      <sha1>jm1d8irtf3u3f6iv0alxra18kse89w5</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
