  <page>
    <title>Cue sports</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3447</id>
    <revision>
      <id>939168793</id>
      <parentid>939168636</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-04T20:03:46Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>MinorEnglishMajor</username>
        <id>31910160</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>corrected punctuation</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Games in which billiard balls are struck with a cue}}
{{redirect|Billiards|text=This article covers the word as an umbrella term for cue sports in general. For specific games known as &quot;billiards&quot; and all other uses of the term, see [[Billiard (disambiguation)]]}}

{{Infobox sport
|name       = Cue sports
|image      = 1674 illustration-The Billiard Table.png
|imagesize  = 277px 
|caption    = Engraving of an early billiards game with obstacles and targets, from [[Charles Cotton]]'s 1674 book ''The Compleat Gamester''
|union      = [[World Confederation of Billiards Sports]]
|first      = 15th-century Europe, with roots in [[ground billiards]]
|contact    = No
|team       = Single opponents, doubles or teams
|mgender    = Yes, sometimes in separate leagues/divisions
|category   = [[Billiard hall|Indoor]], table
|equipment  = [[Billiard ball]], [[billiard table]], [[cue stick]]
|venue      = [[Billiard hall]] or home [[billiard room]]
|olympic    = No
|IWGA       = [[2001 World Games|2001]]{{snds}}present
}}

'''Cue sports''' (sometimes written '''cuesports'''), also known as '''billiard sports''',&lt;ref name=&quot;IOC&quot;&gt;{{Cite web
 |title       = Recognized Sports
 |url         = http://www.olympic.org/uk/sports/recognized/
 |work        = olympic.org – Official Website of the Olympic Movement
 |pages       = &quot;Sports&quot; section
 |publisher   = [[International Olympic Committee]]
 |location    = [[Lausanne, Switzerland]]
 |year        = 2009
 |accessdate  = 2009-06-01
 |url-status     = dead
 |archiveurl  = https://web.archive.org/web/20090705040134/http://www.olympic.org/uk/sports/recognized/
 |archivedate = 2009-07-05
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;WCBS&quot;&gt;{{Cite web
 |title       = WCBS
 |url         = http://www.billiard-wcbs.org/
 |pages       = Homepage and very name of organization
 |publisher   = [[World Confederation of Billiards Sports]]
 |location    = Lausanne
 |year        = 2005&lt;!--last known year of update--&gt;
 |accessdate  = 2009-06-01
 |url-status     = dead
 |archiveurl  = https://web.archive.org/web/20090206103227/http://billiard-wcbs.org/
 |archivedate = 2009-02-06
}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
are a wide variety of [[Game of skill|games of skill]] generally played with a [[cue stick]], which is used to strike [[billiard ball]]s and thereby cause them to move around a [[Baize|cloth]]-covered [[billiards table]] bounded by elastic bumpers known as {{Cuegloss|Cushion|cushions}}.

Historically, the umbrella term was '''billiards'''. While that familiar name is still employed by some as a generic label for all such games, the word's usage has splintered into more exclusive competing meanings in various parts of the world. For example, in [[British English|British]] and [[Australian English]], ''billiards'' usually refers exclusively to the game of [[English billiards]], while in [[American English|American]] and [[Canadian English]] it is sometimes used to refer to a particular game or class of games, or to all cue games in general, depending upon [[List of dialects of the English language|dialect]] and context. In colloquial usage, the term ''billiards'' may be used colloquially to refer to [[pocket billiards]] games, such as [[pocket billiards|pool]], [[snooker]], or [[Russian pyramid]].

There are 3 major subdivisions of games within cue sports:
*[[Carom billiards]], referring to games played on tables without {{Cuegloss|Pocket|pockets}}, typically 10 feet in length, including [[balkline and straight rail]], [[cushion caroms]], [[carom billiards#Three-cushion billiards|three-cushion billiards]], [[artistic billiards]] and [[Four-ball billiards|four-ball]]
*[[Pool (cue sports)|Pool]], covering numerous pocket billiards games generally played on six-pocket tables of 7-, 8-, or 9-foot length, including among others [[eight-ball]] (the world's most widely played cue sport), [[nine-ball]] (the dominant professional game), [[ten-ball]], [[straight pool]] (the formerly dominant pro game), [[one-pocket]], and [[bank pool]]
*[[Snooker]], [[English billiards]] and [[Russian pyramid]], games played on a billiards table with six pockets called a [[snooker table]] (which has dimensions just under 12&amp;nbsp;ft by 6&amp;nbsp;ft), all of which are classified entirely separately from pool based on a separate historical development, as well as a separate culture and terminology that characterize their play.

There are other variants that make use of obstacles and targets, and table-top games played with disks instead of balls.

Billiards has a long and rich history stretching from its inception in the 15th century, to the wrapping of the body of [[Mary, Queen of Scots]], in her billiard table cover in 1586, through its many mentions in the works of [[William Shakespeare|Shakespeare]],&lt;!--Michael Phelan's 1850 book has an entire chapter devoted to mentions in Shakespeare works; which might be useful.--&gt; including the famous line &quot;let's to billiards&quot; in ''[[Antony and Cleopatra]]'' (1606–07), and through the many famous enthusiasts of the sport such as: [[Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart|Mozart]], [[Louis XIV of France]], [[Marie Antoinette]], [[Immanuel Kant]], [[Napoleon]], [[Abraham Lincoln]], [[Mark Twain]], [[George Washington]], French president [[Jules Grévy]], [[Charles Dickens]], [[George Armstrong Custer]], [[Theodore Roosevelt]], [[Lewis Carroll]], [[W. C. Fields|W.C.&amp;nbsp;Fields]], [[Babe Ruth]], [[Bob Hope]], and [[Jackie Gleason]].

==History==
[[Image:A Game of Billiards by Adriaen Pietersz. van de Venne.jpg|thumb|Billiards in the 1620s was played with a &quot;port&quot;, a &quot;king&quot; pin, and maces.]]
All cue sports are generally regarded to have evolved into indoor games from outdoor stick-and-ball [[lawn game]]s (retroactively termed [[ground billiards]]),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | first = Victor | last = Stein and Rubino, Paul | year = 1996 | title = The Billiard Encyclopedia: An Illustrated History of the Sport (2nd ed.) | publisher = Blue Book Publications, June 1996 | isbn = 1-886768-06-4  }}{{Page needed|date=September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and as such to be related to the historical games [[jeu de mail]] and [[palle-malle]], and modern [[trucco]], [[croquet]] and golf, and more distantly to the stickless [[bocce]] and [[bowls (sport)|bowls]].
The word ''billiard'' may have evolved from the French word ''billart'' or ''billette'', meaning 'stick', in reference to the {{Cuegloss|Mace|mace}}, an implement similar to a [[Golf club (equipment)|golf club]], which was the forerunner to the modern [[Cue stick|cue]]; the term's origin may have also been from French ''bille'', meaning 'ball'.&lt;ref name=&quot;Everton 1986&quot;&gt;{{Cite book
|title=The History of Snooker and Billiards
|last=Everton
|first=Clive
|authorlink=Clive Everton
|location=[[Haywards Heath|Haywards Heath, UK]]
|publisher=[[Transworld (company)|Partridge Pr]]
|pages=8–11
|year=1986
|edition=rev. ver. of ''The Story of Billiards and Snooker'', 1979
|isbn=1-85225-013-5
}}&lt;/ref&gt; The modern term ''cue sports'' can be used to encompass the ancestral mace games, and even the modern cueless variants, such as finger billiards, for historical reasons. ''Cue'' itself came from ''queue'', the French word for a [[tail]]. This refers to the early practice of using the tail of the mace to strike the ball when it lay against a {{Cuegloss|Cushion|rail cushion}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;Everton 1986&quot; /&gt;
[[File:Cabanès, Éducation de Princes031 Les trois fils du Grand Dauphin, jouant au Jeu des Fortifications.jpg|thumb|left|The sons of [[Louis, Grand Dauphin]] playing the ''royal game of fortifications'', early form of obstacle billiard]]  
A recognizable form of billiards was played outdoors in the 1340s, and was reminiscent of croquet. King [[Louis XI of France]] (1461–1483) had the first known indoor billiard table.&lt;ref name=&quot;Everton 1986&quot; /&gt; [[Louis XIV of France|Louis XIV]] further refined and popularized the game, and it swiftly spread among the French nobility.&lt;ref name=&quot;Everton 1986&quot; /&gt; While the game had long been played on the ground, this version appears to have died out in the 17th century, in favor of croquet, golf and bowling games, while table billiards had grown in popularity as an indoor activity.&lt;ref name=&quot;Everton 1986&quot; /&gt; [[Mary, Queen of Scots]], claimed that her &quot;table de billiard&quot; had been taken away by those who eventually became her executioners (and who covered her body with the table's cloth).&lt;ref name=&quot;Everton 1986&quot; /&gt; Billiards grew to the extent that by 1727, it was being played in almost every Paris café.&lt;ref name=&quot;Everton 1986&quot; /&gt; In England, the game was developing into a very popular activity for members of the gentry.&lt;ref name=&quot;Everton 1986&quot; /&gt;

By 1670, the thin butt end of the mace began to be used not only for shots under the cushion (which itself was originally only there as a preventative method to stop balls from rolling off), but players increasingly preferred it for other shots as well. The cue as it is known today was finally developed by about 1800.&lt;ref name=&quot;Everton 1986&quot; /&gt;

Initially, the mace was used to push the balls, rather than strike them. The newly developed striking cue provided a new challenge. Cushions began to be stuffed with substances to allow the balls to rebound, in order to enhance the appeal of the game. After a transitional period where only the better players would use cues, the cue came to be the first choice of equipment.&lt;ref name=&quot;Everton 1986&quot; /&gt;

The demand for tables and other equipment was initially met in Europe by [[John Thurston (inventor)|John Thurston]] and other furniture makers of the era. The early balls were made from wood and [[clay]], but the rich preferred to use [[ivory]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Everton 1986&quot; /&gt;

Early billiard games involved various pieces of additional equipment, including the &quot;arch&quot; (related to the croquet hoop), &quot;port&quot; (a different hoop) and &quot;king&quot; (a pin or skittle near the arch) in the 1770s, but other game variants, relying on the cushions (and eventually on pockets cut into them), were being formed that would go on to play fundamental roles in the development of modern billiards.&lt;ref name=&quot;Everton 1986&quot; /&gt;

[[Image:Studenten Billard.JPG|thumb|left|280px|Illustration of a three-ball [[pocket billiards]] game in early 19th century [[Tübingen]], Germany, using a table much longer than the modern type]]
The early croquet-like games eventually led to the development of the '''[[carom billiards|carom or carambole billiards]]''' category – what most non-[[Commonwealth of Nations|Commonwealth]] and non-US speakers mean by the word ''billiards''. These games, which once completely dominated the cue sports world but have declined markedly in many areas over the last few generations, are games played with three or sometimes four balls, on a table without holes (and without obstructions or targets in most cases), in which the goal is generally to strike one {{Cuegloss|Object ball|object ball}} with a {{Cuegloss|Cue ball|cue ball}}, then have the cue ball rebound off of one or more of the cushions and strike a second object ball. Variations include [[three-cushion]], [[Balkline and straight rail|straight rail and the balkline variants]], [[cushion caroms]], [[five-pins]], and [[Four-ball billiards|four-ball]], among others.

Over time, a type of obstacle returned, originally as a hazard and later as a target, in the form of [[Billiards table#Pocket billiards tables|pockets]], or holes partly cut into the table bed and partly into the cushions, leading to the rise of [[pocket billiards]], including &quot;pool&quot; games such as eight-ball, nine-ball, straight pool and [[one-pocket]]; [[Russian pyramid]]; [[snooker]]; [[English billiards]] and others.

In the United States pool and billiards had died out for a bit, but between 1878 and 1956 pool and billiards became very popular. Players in annual championships began to receive their own [[cigarette card]]s. This was mainly due to the fact that it was a popular pastime for troops to take their minds off from battle. However, by the end of World War II pool and billiards began to die down once again. It was not until 1961 when the film &quot;The Hustler&quot; came out that sparked a new interest in the game. Now the game is generally a well-known game and has many players of all different skill levels.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.thebilliardshop.com/poolhistory.php |title=Pool History |publisher=The Pool Shop |access-date=1 December 2011 |url-status=dead |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20111119012508/http://www.thebilliardshop.com/poolhistory.php |archive-date=November 19, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Quote|There are few more cheerful sights, when the evenings are long, and the weather dull, than a handsome, well-lighted billiard room, with the smooth, green surface of the billiard table; the ivory balls flying noiselessly here and there, or clicking musically together.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first=Charles, Jr. |last=Dickens |date=April 13, 1889 |title=Billiards |journal=All the Year Round |publisher=Charles Dickens and Evans, Crystal Palace Press |location=London |volume=64 |page=349 |oclc=1479125}}&lt;/ref&gt;|Charles Dickens Jr., (1889)}}

==As a sport==
The games with regulated international professional competition, if not others, have been referred to as &quot;sports&quot; or &quot;sporting&quot; events, not simply &quot;games&quot;, since 1893 at the latest.&lt;ref name=&quot;NYTBig&quot;&gt;[https://www.nytimes.com/1893/12/10/archives/meeting-of-the-champions-the-big-billiard-tournament-to-begin.html &quot;Meeting of the Champions; The Big Billiard Tournament to Begin To-morrow – What Ives, Schaefer, and Slosson Have Been Doing in Practice – The Older Players Not Afraid of the Big Runs Made by Ives – Something About the Rise and Progress of the Young 'Napoleon' of the Billiard World&quot;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140316051135/http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F40613FF3A5F1A738DDDA90994DA415B8385F0D3 |date=2014-03-16 }}, no byline, ''[[The New York Times]]'', 1893-12-10, p. 10; [[The New York Times Company]], [[New York City|New York, NY]], USA.&lt;/ref&gt; Quite a variety of particular games (i.e., sets of rules and equipment) are the subject of present-day competition, including many of those already mentioned, with competition being especially broad in nine-ball, snooker, three-cushion and eight-ball.

Snooker, though technically a pocket billiards variant and closely related in its equipment and origin to the game of English billiards, is a professional sport organized at the international level, and its rules bear little resemblance to those of modern pool, pyramid and other such games.&lt;!-- There are other places where we need to &quot;respect&quot; snooker as a separate sport; it's really a global tour-de-force and had a WikiProject before &quot;WikiProject Cue sports&quot;, so let's see how we can help them and not step on their toes but also remain historically/logically accurate. -SMcCandlish--&gt;

A &quot;Billiards&quot; category encompassing pool, snooker and carom was featured in the 2005 [[World Games]], held in [[Duisburg]], Germany, and the 2006 [[Asian Games]] also saw the [[Cue sports at the 2006 Asian Games|introduction of a &quot;Cue sports&quot; category]].

==Equipment==
{{Maincat|Cue sports equipment}}
&lt;!-- Much of this entire section needs to be pared down, with details moving to more specific pages like [[Pool (cue sports)|Pool]], [[Snooker]], and [[Carom billiards]]. --&gt;

===Billiard balls===
{{Main|Billiard ball}}
[[File:Billiard ball comparison.jpg|thumb|right|200px|{{Cuegloss|Cue ball|Cue balls}} from (left to right): {{unordered list
| [[Russian pyramid|Russian pool]] and [[Kaisa (billiards)|kaisa]]—68&amp;nbsp;mm ({{frac|2|11|16}}&amp;nbsp;in)
| [[Carom billiards|Carom]]—61.5&amp;nbsp;mm ({{frac|2|7|16}}&amp;nbsp;in)
| American-style [[Pocket billiards|pool]]—57&amp;nbsp;mm ({{frac|2|1|4}}&amp;nbsp;in)
| [[Blackball (pool)|British-style]] pool (largish) —56&amp;nbsp;mm ({{frac|2|3|16}}&amp;nbsp;in)
| [[Snooker]]—52.5&amp;nbsp;mm ({{frac|2|1|15}}&amp;nbsp;in)
| Scaled-down pool—51&amp;nbsp;mm (2&amp;nbsp;in) for children's smaller tables
}}
Not shown: half-scale children's miniature pool—approximately 28.5&amp;nbsp;mm ({{frac|1|1|8}}&amp;nbsp;in).]]
Billiard balls vary from game to game, in size, design and quantity.

[[Russian pyramid]] and [[Kaisa (billiards)|kaisa]] have a size of 68&amp;nbsp;mm ({{frac|2|11|16}}&amp;nbsp;in).  In Russian pyramid there are sixteen balls, as in pool, but fifteen are white and numbered, and the {{cuegloss|cue ball|cue ball}} is usually red.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url= http://www.billiardsvillage.com/russian-pyramid.html |title=Russian Billiards |publisher=BilliardsVillage.com |access-date=August 14, 2008 |year=2007 |author=editors |url-status=dead |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20080613002125/http://www.billiardsvillage.com/russian-pyramid.html |archive-date=June 13, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; In kaisa, five balls are used: the yellow {{Cuegloss|object ball|object ball}} (called the ''kaisa'' in Finnish), two red object balls, and the two white cue balls (usually differentiated by one cue ball having a dot or other marking on it and each of which serves as an object ball for the opponent).

Carom billiards balls are larger than pool balls, having a diameter of 61.5&amp;nbsp;mm ({{frac|2|7|16}}&amp;nbsp;in), and come as a set of two cue balls (one colored or marked) and an object ball (or two object balls in the case of the game [[Four-ball billiards|four-ball]]).

American-style pool balls are 57&amp;nbsp;mm ({{frac|2|1|4}}&amp;nbsp;in), are used in many pool games found throughout the world, come in sets of two {{Cuegloss|Suit|suits}} of object balls, seven {{Cuegloss|Solids|solids}} and seven {{Cuegloss|Stripes|stripes}}, an {{Cuegloss|8 ball|8 ball}} and a {{Cuegloss|Cue ball|cue ball}}; the balls are racked differently for different games (some of which do not use the entire ball set). Blackball (English-style eight-ball) sets are similar, but have unmarked {{Cuegloss|Group|groups}} of {{Cuegloss|Red ball|red}} (or {{Cuegloss|Blue ball|blue}}) and {{Cuegloss|Yellow ball|yellow}} balls instead of solids and stripes, and at 56&amp;nbsp;mm ({{frac|2|3|16}}&amp;nbsp;in) are smaller than the American-style; they are used principally in Britain, Ireland, and some [[Commonwealth of Nations|Commonwealth]] countries, though not exclusively, since they are unsuited for playing nine-ball.

Snooker balls are smaller than American-style pool balls with a diameter of 52.5&amp;nbsp;mm ({{frac|2|1|15}}&amp;nbsp;in), and come in sets of 22 (15 reds, 6 &quot;{{Cuegloss|Color balls|colours}}&quot;, and a cue ball). English billiard balls are the same size as snooker balls and come in sets of three balls (two cue balls and a red, an object ball). Other games, such as [[bumper pool]], have custom ball sets.

Billiard balls have been made from many different materials since the start of the game, including clay, [[bakelite]], [[celluloid]], [[crystallite]], [[ivory]], plastic, steel and wood. The dominant material from 1627 until the early 20th century was ivory. The search for a substitute for ivory use was not for environmental concerns but based on economic motivation and fear of danger for elephant hunters. It was in part spurred on by a New York billiard table manufacturer who announced a prize of $10,000 for a substitute material. The first viable substitute was [[celluloid]], invented by [[John Wesley Hyatt]] in 1868, but the material was volatile, sometimes exploding during manufacture and was highly flammable.&lt;ref name=&quot;IEOB&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Shamos | first = Michael Ian | year = 1993 | title = The Illustrated Encyclopedia of Billiards | publisher = Lyons &amp; Burford | location = [[New York City|New York, NY]] | isbn = 1-55821-219-1 | nopp = true | url = https://archive.org/details/illustratedencyc0000sham }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The New York Times Company (September 16, 1875). [https://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=FB0F1EFD345D1A7493C4A81782D85F418784F9 Explosive Teeth.] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140316033727/http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=FB0F1EFD345D1A7493C4A81782D85F418784F9 |date=2014-03-16 }}. Retrieved January 2, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Tables===
{{main|Billiard table}}
[[Image:PoolTablewithEquipment-non.jpg|left|thumb|265px|Pool table with equipment.]]
There are many sizes and styles of pool and [[billiards table|billiard table]]s. Generally, tables are [[rectangle]]s twice as long as they are wide. Most pool tables are known as 7-, 8-, or 9-footers, referring to the length of the table's long side.  Full-size snooker and English billiard tables are {{convert|12|ft|m|1}} long on the longest side. [[Pool hall]]s tend to have {{convert|9|ft|m|1|sing=on}} tables and cater to the serious pool player. [[Public house|Pubs]] will typically use {{convert|7|ft|m|1|sing=on}} tables which are often coin-operated. Formerly, {{convert|10|ft|m|0|sing=on}} tables were common, but such tables are now considered antique collectors items; a few, usually from the late 19th century, can be found in pool halls from time to time. Ten-foot tables remain the standard size for carom billiard games. The slates on modern carom tables are usually heated to stave off moisture and provide a consistent playing surface.

The length of the pool table will typically be a function of space, with many homeowners purchasing an {{convert|8|ft|m|1|sing=on}} table as a compromise. Full-size pool tables are 4.5 by {{convert|9|ft|m|1|abbr=on}} (interior dimensions). High-quality tables have a {{cuegloss|bed}} made of thick slate, in three pieces to prevent warping and changes due to temperature and humidity. Smaller bar tables are most commonly made with a single piece of slate. Pocket billiards tables of all types normally have six pockets, three on each side (four corner pockets, and two side or middle pockets).{{clear}}

===Cloth===
{{Main|Baize}}
[[Image:Early-1880s-billiards-ladies-JMBB.jpg|right|thumb|250px|Women playing on an elaborately decorated green-covered table in an early 1880s advertising poster.]]
All types of tables are covered with billiard cloth (often called &quot;felt&quot;, but actually a woven wool or wool/nylon blend called [[baize]]). Cloth has been used to cover billiards tables since the 15th century.

Bar or tavern tables, which get a lot of play, use &quot;slower&quot;, more durable cloth. The cloth used in upscale [[pool halls|pool (and snooker) halls]] and home [[billiard room]]s is &quot;faster&quot; (i.e., provides less friction, allowing the balls to roll farther across the table {{Cuegloss|Bed|bed}}), and competition-quality pool cloth is made from 100% [[worsted|worsted wool]]. Snooker cloth traditionally has a nap (consistent fiber directionality) and balls behave differently when rolling against versus along with the nap.

The cloth of the billiard table has traditionally been green, reflecting its origin (originally the grass of ancestral lawn games), and has been so colored since the 16th century, but it is also produced in other colors such as red and blue.&lt;ref name=&quot;Shamos 1991&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Shamos | first = Michael Ian | year = 1991 | title = Pool | publisher = Hotho &amp; Co., June 1991 | isbn = 99938-704-3-9 }}{{Page needed|date=September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Television broadcasting of pool as well as 3 Cushion billiards prefers a blue colored cloth which was chosen for better visibility and contrast against colored balls.

The cloth was earlier said to be the most important part of the game, most likely because of the reflection of the game's origin. The players were determined that the cloth should not be ripped – women were made to continue to use maces after cues were invented, for fear that they would rip the cloth with the sharper cues.

===Rack===
{{main|Rack (billiards)}}
[[Image:Billiard Rack.jpg|left|thumb|250px|Aluminium billiard rack that is used for 8-ball, 9-ball, and straight pool.]]

A [[Rack (billiards)|rack]] is the name given to a frame (usually wood, plastic or aluminium) used to organize billiard balls at the beginning of a game. This is traditionally triangular in shape, but varies with the type of billiards played. There are two main types of racks; the more common triangular shape which is used for eight-ball and straight pool and the diamond-shaped rack used for nine-ball.

There are several other types of less common rack types that are also used, based on a &quot;template&quot; to hold the billiard balls tightly together.  Most commonly it is a thin plastic sheet with diamond-shaped cut-outs that hold the balls that is placed on the table with the balls set on top of the rack.  The rack is used to set up the &quot;break&quot; and removed before the &quot;break shot&quot; occurs.

===Cues===
{{main|Cue stick}}
Billiards games are mostly played with a stick known as a cue. A cue is usually either a one piece tapered stick or a two piece stick divided in the middle by a joint of metal or phenolic resin. High quality cues are generally two pieces and are made of a hardwood, generally maple for billiards and ash for snooker.

The {{Cuegloss|Butt|butt}} end of the cue is of larger circumference and is intended to be gripped by a player's hand. The {{Cuegloss|Shaft|shaft}} of the cue is of smaller circumference, usually tapering to an {{convert|0.4|to|0.55|in|mm}} terminus called a {{Cuegloss|Ferrule|ferrule}} (usually made of fiberglass or brass in better cues), where a rounded leather {{Cuegloss|Tip|tip}} is affixed, flush with the ferrule, to make final contact with balls. The tip, in conjunction with chalk, can be used to impart [[Cue sports techniques#Sidespin (english)|spin]] to the cue ball when it is not hit in its center.

Cheap cues are generally made of pine, low-grade maple (and formerly often of [[Gonystylus|ramin]], which is now endangered), or other low-quality wood, with inferior plastic ferrules. A quality cue can be expensive and may be made of exotic woods and other expensive materials which are artfully inlaid in decorative patterns. Many modern cues are also made, like [[Golf club (equipment)|golf club]]s, with high-tech materials such as woven graphite. Skilled players may use more than one cue during a game, including a separate generally lighter cue for the opening break shot (because of cue speed gained from a lighter stick) and another, shorter cue with a special tip for {{Cuegloss|Jump shot|jump shots}}.

===Mechanical bridge===
&lt;span id=&quot;The mechanical bridge&quot; &gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!--Orig. section name; may be linked-to somewhere.--&gt;The mechanical bridge, sometimes called a &quot;rake&quot;, &quot;crutch&quot;, &quot;bridge stick&quot; or simply &quot;bridge&quot;, and in the UK a &quot;rest&quot;, is used to extend a player's reach on a shot where the cue ball is too far away for normal hand bridging. It consists of a stick with a grooved metal or plastic head which the cue slides on. Many amateurs refuse to use the mechanical bridge based on the perception that to do so is unmanly.{{Citation needed|date=August 2014}} However, many aficionados and most professionals employ the bridge whenever the intended shot so requires.

Some players, especially current or former snooker players, use a screw-on cue butt extension instead of or in addition to the mechanical bridge.

Bridge head design is varied, and not all designs (especially those with cue shaft-enclosing rings, or wheels on the bottom of the head), are broadly tournament-approved.

In Italy a longer, thicker cue is typically available for this kind of tricky shot.

For snooker they are normally available in three forms, their use depending on how the player is hampered; the standard rest is a simple cross, the 'spider' has a raised arch around 12&amp;nbsp;cm with three grooves to rest the cue in and for the most awkward of shots, the 'giraffe' (or 'swan' in England) which has a raised arch much like the 'spider' but with a slender arm reaching out around 15&amp;nbsp;cm with the groove.

===Chalk===
[[Image:Billiard Chalk and Cue.jpg|thumb|240px|Billiard chalk is applied to the tip of the cue.]]Chalk is applied to the tip of the cue stick, ideally before every shot, to increase the tip's friction coefficient so that when it impacts the cue ball on a non-center hit, no {{Cuegloss|Miscue|miscue}} (unintentional slippage between the cue tip and the struck ball) occurs. Cue tip chalk is not actually the substance typically referred to as &quot;[[chalk]]&quot; (generally [[calcium carbonate]]), but any of several proprietary compounds, with a [[silicate]] base. It was around the time of the Industrial Revolution that newer compounds formed that provided better grip for the ball. This is when the English began to experiment with side spin or applying curl to the ball. This was shortly introduced to the American players and is how the term &quot;putting English on the ball&quot; came to be. &quot;Chalk&quot; may also refer to a cone of fine, white {{Cuegloss|Hand chalk|hand chalk}}; like [[talc]] (talcum powder) it can be used to reduce friction between the cue and bridge hand during shooting, for a smoother stroke. Some brands of hand chalk actually are made of compressed talc. (Tip chalk is not used for this purpose because it is abrasive, hand-staining and difficult to apply.) Many players prefer a slick pool glove over hand chalk or talc because of the messiness of these powders; buildup of particles on the cloth will affect ball behavior and necessitate more-frequent cloth cleaning.

Cue tip chalk (invented in its modern form by straight rail billiard pro [[William A. Spinks]] and chemist [[William Hoskins (inventor)|William Hoskins]] in 1897)&lt;ref name=&quot;Clark1&quot;&gt;[http://www.toaster.org/hoskins_tragic.html &quot;The World's Most Tragic Man Is the One Who Never Starts&quot;] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20060825063214/http://www.toaster.org/hoskins_tragic.html |date=August 25, 2006 }}, Clark, Neil M.; originally published in ''The American'' magazine, May 1927; republished in ''hotwire: The Newsletter of the Toaster Museum Foundation'', vol. 3, no. 3, online edition. Retrieved February 24, 2007. The piece is largely an interview of Hoskins.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Patent578514&quot;&gt;{{US patent|0578514}}, 9 March 1897&lt;/ref&gt; is made by crushing [[silica]] and the abrasive substance [[corundum]] or aloxite&lt;ref name=&quot;Patent578514&quot;/&gt; (aluminium [[oxide]]),&lt;ref name=&quot;Chem1&quot;&gt;[http://www.chemindustry.com/chemicals/14835.html &quot;Aloxite&quot;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070625100844/http://www.chemindustry.com/chemicals/14835.html |date=2007-06-25 }}, ChemIndustry.com database. Retrieved February 24, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;PubChem&quot;&gt;[https://pubchem.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/summary/summary.cgi?sid=158,243 &quot;Substance Summary: Aluminum Oxide&quot;], ''PubChem Database'', [[United States National Library of Medicine|National Library of Medicine]], [[National Institutes of Health|US National Institutes of Health]]. Retrieved February 24, 2007. {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140406175207/http://pubchem.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/summary/summary.cgi?sid=158,243 |date=April 6, 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt; into a powder.&lt;ref name=&quot;Patent578514&quot;/&gt; It is combined with dye (originally and most commonly green or blue-green, like traditional [[Baize|billiard cloth]], but available today, like the cloth, in many colours) and a binder (glue).&lt;ref name=&quot;Patent578514&quot;/&gt; Each manufacturer's brand has different qualities, which can significantly affect play. High humidity can also impair the effectiveness of chalk. Harder, drier compounds are generally considered superior by most players.&lt;!--RE-ENABLE THIS AFTER http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=MediaWiki_talk:Spam-whitelist RESOLVES BLACKLIST ISSUE: ref name=&quot;Tobey1&quot; /--&gt;

==Major games==
There are two main varieties of billiard games: '''carom''' and '''pocket'''.

The main carom billiards games are [[straight rail]], [[balkline and straight rail|balkline]] and especially [[three cushion]] billiards. All are played on a pocketless table with three balls; two cue balls and one object ball. In all, players shoot a cue ball so that it makes contact with the opponent's cue ball as well as the object ball.  Others of multinational interest are [[Four-ball billiards|four-ball]] and [[five-pins]].

The most globally popular of the large variety of pocket games are [[pool (cue sports)|Pool]] and [[snooker]]. A third, [[English billiards]], has some features of carom billiards. English billiards used to be one of the two most-competitive cue sports along with the carom game balkline, at the turn of the 20th century and is still enjoyed today in [[Commonwealth of Nations|Commonwealth]] countries. Another pocket game, [[Russian pyramid]] and its variants like [[kaisa (billiards)|kaisa]] are popular in the former [[Eastern bloc]].
[[Image:Cue and mace.jpg|thumb|Man playing billiards with a cue and a woman with mace, from an illustration appearing in [[Michael Phelan (billiards)|Michael Phelan]]'s 1859 book, ''The Game of Billiards''.]]

===Games played on a carom billiards table===
{{Main|Carom billiards}}

====Straight rail or straight billiards====
{{Main|Balkline and straight rail}}
In straight rail, a player scores a point and may continue shooting each time his cue ball makes contact with both other balls.

Although a difficult and subtle game, some of the best players of straight billiards developed the skill to {{Cuegloss|Gather shot|gather}} the balls in a corner or along the same rail for the purpose of playing a series of {{Cuegloss|Nurse|nurse shots}} to score a seemingly limitless number of points.

The first straight rail professional tournament was held in 1879 where [[Jacob Schaefer, Sr.]] scored 690 points in a single turn&lt;ref name=&quot;Shamos 1991&quot;/&gt;{{Page needed|date=September 2011}} (that is, 690 separate strokes without a miss). With the balls repetitively hit and barely moving in endless &quot;nursing&quot;, there was little for the fans to watch&lt;!--, though the matches were popular anyway and the subject of major press coverage **Dig up some good NYTimes 1800s articles and cite them here first.** --&gt;.

====Balkline====
{{Main|Balkline and straight rail}}
In light of these phenomenal skill developments in straight rail, the game of balkline soon developed to make it impossible for a player to keep the balls gathered in one part of the table for long, greatly limiting the effectiveness of nurse shots. A {{Cuegloss|Balkline|balkline}} (not to be confused with {{Cuegloss|Baulk line|baulk line}}, which pertains to the game of [[English billiards]]) is a line parallel to one end of a billiards table. In the ''games'' of balkline – 18.1 and 18.2 (pronounced &quot;eighteen-point-two&quot;) balkline, among other more obscure variations – the players have to drive at least one object ball past a balkline set at {{convert|18|in|mm}} from each rail, after one or two points have been scored, respectively.

====Three-cushion billiards====
{{main|Three-cushion billiards}}
A more elegant solution was three-cushion billiards, which requires a player to make contact with the other two balls on the table ''and'' contact three rail cushions in the process. This is difficult enough that even the best players can only manage to average one to two points per turn.
This is sometimes described as &quot;hardest to learn&quot; and &quot;require most skill&quot; of all billiards. Even quite good Pool or Snooker players may attempt an hour or more to score a single three cushion point, without even managing an accidental score.

===Games played on a pool table===
{{Main|Pool (cue sports)}}

There are many variations of games played on a standard pool table. Popular pool games include [[eight-ball]], [[nine-ball]], [[straight pool]] and [[one-pocket]]. Even within games types (e.g. [[eight-ball]]), there may be variations, and people may play recreationally using relaxed or local rules.  A few of the more popular examples of pool games are given below.

In eight-ball and nine-ball, the object is to sink object balls until one can legally pocket the winning [[:wikt:eponym|eponym]]ous &quot;{{Cuegloss|Money ball|money ball}}&quot;. Well-known but waning in popularity is straight pool, in which players seek to continue sinking balls, rack after rack if they can, to reach a pre-determined winning score (typically 150). Related to nine-ball, another well-known game is [[Rotation (pool)|rotation]], where the lowest-numbered object ball on the table must be struck first, although any object ball may be pocketed (i.e., combination shot). Each pocketed ball is worth its number, and the player with the highest score at the end of the rack is the winner. Since there are only 120 points available (1&amp;nbsp;+&amp;nbsp;2&amp;nbsp;+&amp;nbsp;3&amp;nbsp;⋯&amp;nbsp;+&amp;nbsp;15&amp;nbsp;=&amp;nbsp;120), scoring 61 points leaves no opportunity for the opponent to catch up. In both one-pocket and bank pool, the players must sink a set number of balls; respectively, all in a particular {{Cuegloss|Pocket|pocket}}, or all by {{Cuegloss|Bank shot|bank shots}}. In snooker, players score points by alternately potting {{Cuegloss|Red ball|red balls}} and various special &quot;{{Cuegloss|Colour ball|colour balls}}&quot;.

====Two-player or -team games====
*[[Eight-ball]]: The goal is to {{cuegloss|pocket}} ({{cuegloss|pot}}) all of one's designated {{cuegloss|group}} of balls (either {{cuegloss|stripes}} vs. {{cuegloss|solids}}, or {{cuegloss|red ball|reds}} vs. {{cuegloss|yellow ball|yellows}}, depending upon the equipment), and then pocket the {{cuegloss|8 ball}} in a {{cuegloss|call shot|called}} pocket.
*[[Nine-ball]]: The goal is to pocket the 9 ball; the initial contact of the {{cuegloss|cue ball}} each turn must be with the lowest-numbered {{cuegloss|object ball}} remaining on the table; there are numerous variants such as [[seven-ball]], [[six-ball]], and the older forms of three-ball and ten-ball, that simply use a different number of balls and have a different {{cuegloss|money ball}}.
*[[Straight pool]] (a.k.a. 14.1 continuous pool): The goal is to reach a predetermined number of {{cuegloss|point|points}} (e.g. 100); a point is earned by pocketing any called ball into a designated pocket; game play is by {{cuegloss|rack|racks}} of 15 balls, and the last object ball of a rack is not pocketed, but left on the table with the opponent re-racking the remaining 14 before game play continues.
*[[Bank pool]]: The goal is to reach a predetermined number of points; a point is earned by pocketing any called ball by {{cuegloss|bank shot|banking}} it into a designated pocket using one or more {{cuegloss|cushion}}.

====Speed pool====
[[Speed pool]] is a standard billiards game where the balls must be pocketed in as little time as possible. Rules vary greatly from tournament to tournament. The [[International Speed Pool Challenge]] has been held annually since 2006.

===Games played on a snooker table ===

====English billiards====
{{Main|English billiards}}
Dating to approximately 1800, English billiards, called simply billiards&lt;ref name=&quot;Everton 1986 other&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last = Everton|first = Clive|authorlink = Clive Everton|title = The History of Snooker and Billiards|year=1986|location=[[Haywards Heath|Haywards Heath, UK]]|publisher=[[Transworld (company)|Partridge Pr]]|isbn=1-85225-013-5|edition=rev. ver. of ''The Story of Billiards and Snooker'', 1979}}&lt;/ref&gt; in many [[Commonwealth of Nations|former British colonies]] and in the UK where it originated, was originally called the ''winning and losing carambole game'', folding in the names of three predecessor games, ''the winning game'', ''the losing game'' and ''the carambole game'' (an early form of [[straight rail]]), that combined to form it.&lt;ref name=&quot;Shamos 1999&quot;&gt;{{Shamos 1999|46, 61–62, 89, 244}}&lt;/ref&gt; The game features both {{Cuegloss|cannon|cannons}} (caroms) and the pocketing of balls as objects of play. English billiards requires two {{Cuegloss|Cue ball|cue balls}} and a red {{Cuegloss|Object ball|object ball}}. The object of the game is to score either a fixed number of points, or score the most points within a set time frame, determined at the start of the game.

Points are awarded for:
*Two-ball cannons: striking both the object ball and the other (opponent's) cue ball on the same shot (2 points). 
*&lt;!--{{Cuegloss|Winning hazard|--&gt;Winning hazards&lt;!--}}--&gt;: {{Cuegloss|Pot|potting}} the red ball (3 points); potting the other cue ball (2 points).
*{{Cuegloss|Losing hazard|Losing hazards}} (or &quot;in-offs&quot;): potting one's cue ball by cannoning off another ball (3 points if the red ball was hit first; 2 points if the other cue ball was hit first, or if the red and other cue ball were &quot;{{Cuegloss|Split|split}}&quot;, i.e., hit simultaneously).

====Snooker====
{{main|Snooker}}

Snooker is a pocket billiards game originated by [[History of the British Army|British officers]] stationed in [[Colonial India|India]] during the 19th century, based on earlier pool games such as black pool and life pool. The name of the game became generalized to also describe one of its prime strategies: to &quot;{{Cuegloss|Snooker|snooker}}&quot; the opposing player by causing that player to foul or leave an opening to be exploited.

In the United Kingdom, snooker is by far the most popular cue sport at the competitive level, and major national pastime along with association football and [[cricket]]. It is played in many [[Commonwealth of Nations|Commonwealth]] countries as well, especially in Asia. Snooker is uncommon in North America, where pool games such as eight-ball and nine-ball dominate, and Latin America and [[Continental Europe]], where carom games dominate. The first [[World Snooker Championship]] was held in 1927, and it has been held annually since then with few exceptions. The [[World Professional Billiards and Snooker Association]] (WPBSA) was established in 1968 to regulate the professional game, while the [[International Billiards and Snooker Federation]] (IBSF) regulates the amateur games.

==List of cue sports and games==
{{Anchor|List of cue sports|List of cue games|List of cue games and sports}}

===Carom games===
{{anchor|Carom billiards games}}
{{Main|Carom billiards}}
{{Maincat|Carom billiards}}
{{columns-list|colwidth=30em|
*'''[[Artistic billiards]]''' (a major world cue sport)
*[[Balkline and straight rail|Balkline]] games (18.1, 18.2, etc.)
*[[Four-ball billiards|Four-ball]] ({{transl|ja|''yotsudama''}}, {{transl|ko|''sagu''}})
*[[Balkline and straight rail|Straight-rail]]
*'''[[Three-cushion billiards]]''' (a major world cue sport)
*{{crossref|See also &quot;Hybrid games&quot;, below.}}

====Target carom games====
{{anchor|Target carom billiards games}}
*'''[[Five-pin billiards]]''' (a major international cue sport)
*''{{lang|it|[[Goriziana]]}}'' (or nine-pin billiards)
}}

===Pocket games===
{{anchor|Pocket billiards games}}
{{Main|Pocket billiards}}

====Pool games====
{{anchor|Pool billiards games|Pool pocket billiards games}}
{{Maincat|Pool (cue sports)}}
{{columns-list|colwidth=30em|
*[[American rotation]]
*[[Artistic pool]] (a major world cue sport)
*[[Bank pool]]
*[[Baseball pocket billiards]]
*[[Bowlliards]]
*[[Chicago (pool)|Chicago]]
*[[Cribbage (pool)|Cribbage]]
*[[Cutthroat (pool)|Cutthroat]]
*'''[[Eight-ball]]''' (a major world cue sport; informally a.k.a. stripes &amp; solids, or highs &amp; lows)
**[[Blackball (pool)|Blackball]] (a.k.a. eightball pool, British-style eight-ball)
**[[Chinese eight-ball|&quot;Chinese&quot; eight-ball]]
*[[Equal offense]]
*[[Fifteen-ball pool|Fifteen-ball]]
*[[Honolulu (pool)|Honolulu]]
*[[Kelly pool]]
*[[Killer (pool)|Killer]]
*'''[[Nine-ball]]''' (a major world cue sport)
*'''[[One-pocket]]''' (a major world cue sport)
*[[Rotation (pool)|Rotation]] (a.k.a. 61)
*[[Seven-ball]]
*[[Speed pool]]
*'''[[Straight pool]]''' (a major world cue sport; a.k.a. 14.1 continuous)
*'''[[Ten-ball]]''' (a major world cue sport)
*[[Three-ball]]
}}

====Non-pool pocket games====
{{anchor|Non-pool games|Non-pool pocket billiards games}}
{{columns-list|colwidth=30em|
*[[Golf (billiards)|Golf billiards]] (and its variant, around-the-world)
*'''[[Russian pyramid]]''' (a major cue sport in Eastern Europe and countries of the former USSR)
*{{crossref|See also &quot;Snooker games&quot; and &quot;Hybrid games&quot;, below.}}
}}

===Snooker games===
{{Anchor|Snooker}}
{{Maincat|Snooker}}
Technically a form of pocket billiards, snooker has its own worldwide sporting community separate from that of pool.
{{columns-list|colwidth=30em|
*'''[[Snooker]]''' (a major world cue sport)
*[[Six-red snooker]]
*[[American snooker]]
*[[Brazilian snooker]]
*[[Volunteer snooker]]
*[[Snooker plus]]
*[[Power Snooker]]
* {{crossref|See also golf billiards, above.}}
}}

===Hybrid carom and pocket games===
{{anchor|Hybrid games|Hybrid billiards games|Hybrid carom and pocket billiards games}}
These combine aspects of carom and pocket billiards, and are played on tables with pockets (often as {{cuegloss|hazard}}s not targets).
{{columns-list|colwidth=30em|
*[[Bottle pool]]
*[[Cowboy pool]]
*'''[[English billiards]]''' (a major world cue sport)
*[[Five-pin billiards]], historically
*[[Poker pool]]
*[[Kaisa (billiards)|Kaisa]]
}}

===Obstacle and target games===
{{anchor|Obstacle and target billiards games}}
{{maincat|Obstacle billiards}}&lt;!--Update that after cat. rename.--&gt;
{{columns-list|colwidth=30em|
*[[Bagatelle]] (obsolete)
*[[Bar billiards]]
*[[Bumper pool]]
*[[Danish pin billiards]] and other [[pin billiards (disambiguation)|pin billiards]] games
*[[Devil's pool (billiards)|Devil's pool]] and [[victory billiards]]
*[[Bottle pool]], skittle pool (pin pool), and Italian [[five-pin billiards]] and [[goriziana]] are vestigially classifiable here as well
}}

===Disk games===
{{anchor|Disk billiards games|Disc games|Disc billiards games}}
These are variations using small disks instead of balls, and light-weight cue sticks.
{{columns-list|colwidth=30em|
*[[Carrom]] (some variants of this table-top game use miniature cues; mostly played with the hands)
*[[Crokinole]] (some variants of this combination of carrom and shuffleboard use miniature cues)
*[[Novuss]] (uses full-length cues)
}}

===Ground games===
{{anchor|Ground billiards games}}
{{maincat|Ground billiards}}
{{columns-list|colwidth=30em|
Outdoor games played on a lawn, field or court, played with varying equipment that may include hoops, pins, holes or other targets or obstacles, and clubs, curved-head sticks, or mallets. Most such games are obsolete, aside from croquet. Golf and [[field hockey]], as well as stick-less games such as [[bocce]], [[boules]] and [[bowls]], are historically related.
* '''[[Croquet]]''' (popular lawn game and former [[List of Olympic sports|Olympic sport]])
* [[Jeu de mail]] (obsolete)
* [[Pall-mall]] (obsolete)
* [[Trucco]] (obsolete)
}}

===Cueless games===
{{anchor|Cueless billiards games}}
{{maincat|Finger billiards}}
{{columns-list|colwidth=30em|
These are developments from cue sports that dispense with the cues, and are played with the hands directly.
*[[Finger billiards]] or hand billiards (on a carom table)
**[[Boccette]] (an adaptation of [[five-pin billiards]] to cueless play)
*[[Finger pool]] (on a pool table)
**[[Crud (game)|Crud]] (the only billiards-based [[contact sport]])
*[[Bocce billiards]] or bocce pool (an adaptation of the lawn game [[bocce]] to billiard or pool tables)
}}

==See also==
*[[Glossary of cue sports terms]]
*[[BCA Hall of Fame]]
*[[Hustling]]
*[[Cue sports techniques]]

== References ==
=== Citations ===
{{Reflist}}

=== Sources ===
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book | last = Alciatore | first = David G. (&quot;Doctor Dave&quot;) | title = The Illustrated Principles of Pool and Billiards | url = http://dr-dave-billiards.com/book/book_description.html |date=August 2004 | publisher = [[Sterling Publishing]] | location = [[New York City|New York, NY]] | isbn = 1-4027-1428-9 }}
* {{cite book | last = Byrne | first = Robert | title = Byrne's New Standard Book of Pool and Billiards | year = 1998 | publisher = [[Harcourt Trade Publishers|Harcourt Brace &amp; Co]] | location = New York | isbn = 0-15-100325-4 | url = https://archive.org/details/byrnesnewstandar00byrn }}
{{refend}}

== External links ==
* {{Commons-inline|Billiards}}

{{-}}
{{Sports of the World Games program}}
{{Cue sports nav|state=expanded}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Cue Sports}}
[[Category:Cue sports| ]]
[[Category:Sports entertainment]]
[[Category:French inventions]]</text>
      <sha1>tl0lqc60ck4lw6c9kbbxjxp4ndi98hk</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
