  <page>
    <title>Bead weaving</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3403</id>
    <revision>
      <id>937833807</id>
      <parentid>903081516</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-27T14:09:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>AlluringBeader</username>
        <id>38404348</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>I corrected the definition of square stitch and added a definition for lader stitch.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">'''Bead weaving''' (or '''beadweaving''') using [[seed beads]] can be done either on a [[loom]] or using one of a number of off-loom stitches.

==On-loom beadweaving==
[[Image:Apachebeadloom1903.png|thumb|355px|An old bead loom. 1. Roller. 2. Roller end. 3. Spacers. 4. Spacers.]]

When weaving on a loom, the beads are locked in between the [[Warp (weaving)|warp]] threads by the [[weft]] threads.  The most common bead weaving technique requires two passes of the weft thread.  First, an entire row of beads is strung on the weft [[yarn|thread]].  Then the beads are pressed in between the warp threads.  The [[Sewing needle|needle]] is passed back through the beads above the warp threads to lock the beads into place. Heddle looms were popular near the beginning of the 20th century. They allowed weaving of beads by raising every other thread and inserting strung beads in the shed, the space between the lowered and raised threads. There are still a few Heddle Bead Looms being manufactured today. The most difficult part of loomwork is finishing off the warp threads.

Although loomed pieces are typically rectangular, it is possible to increase and decrease to produce angular or curvy shapes.  [[Fringe (trim)|Fringe]] can also be added during weaving or before the piece is removed from the loom.

Bead looms vary in size and are typically made of wood or metal.  Usually, a [[comb]] or [[Spring (device)|spring]] is used to hold the warp threads a bead-width apart.  Some looms have roller bars that allow the weaver to produce pieces that are longer than the loom.  Most looms are meant to sit on a table, but some have floor stands or are meant to sit in the [[lap]].

==Off-loom beadweaving==
[[File:Bead Weaving, Sarawak (7246866286).jpg|thumb|An example of off-loom beadweaving from Australia.]]
[[File:Bracelet in progress on a bead weaving loom 25Jan2011 arp.jpg|thumb|A [[bracelet]] in progress on a bead weaving loom]]

Off-loom beadweaving is a family of [[beadwork]] techniques in which seed [[bead]]s are woven together into a flat [[Cloth|fabric]], a tubular rope, or a three-dimensional object such as a ball, clasp, box, or a piece of jewelry. All off-loom techniques can be accomplished using a single needle and thread (no warp threads), but some have two-needle variations.
Different stitches produce pieces with distinct textures, shapes, and patterns.  There are many different off-loom bead stitches, including new stitches (distinct thread paths) published only in 2015:
* albion stitch, developed by Heather Kingsley-Heath, published May 2009&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Kingsley-Heath|first1=Heather|title= Albion Stitch: An Introduction to the New Beadwork Stitch |year = 2009 |publisher=Useful Booklet Company |isbn=0954367278}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[brick stitch]], also known as Comanche or Cheyenne stitch
* chevron stitch, a triangular form of bead netting&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = The Art &amp; Elegance of Beadweaving|last = Wells|first = Carol Wilcox|publisher = Lark Books|year = 2003|isbn = 978-1-57990-533-0|location = USA|pages = 54–64}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* diamond weave, developed over a number of years by Gerlinde Lenz, published August 2015&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Thomas|first1=Cath|last2=Lenz|first2=Gerlinde|title=Diamond Weave: A complete guide to mastering the bead world's newest stitch|date=2015|publisher=CreateSpace Independent Publishing Platform|isbn=978-1-5147-3715-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[herringbone stitch]], also known as Ndebele stitch
* hubble stitch, developed over a number of years by Melanie de Miguel &lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=de Miguel|first1=Melanie|title=Let's Hubble: A Journey into the Brand New Beadwork Stitch|date=2015|publisher=SRA Books|isbn=978-1-909116-47-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=de Miquel|first1=Melanie|title=Hubble Stitch|journal=Beadwork|volume=Oct/Nov 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* netting, to avoid confusion specifically ''bead'' netting
* [[peyote stitch]], also known as gourd stitch
* [[pondo stitch]], also known as African circle stitch
* [[right-angle weave]]
* [[Saint Petersburg chain]]
* [[square stitch]], an off loom stitch that mimics the look of loomed bead projects.  
*ladder stitch, a foundation stitch that is used to build a base for brick stitch or herringbone stitch.
* [[triangle weave]]
Spiral Bead Weaving Stitches
* Cellini spiral, a tubular peyote stitch&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|editor1-last=Gerlach|editor1-first=Julia|title=Best of [[Bead&amp;Button magazine]] : peyote stitch beading projects|date=2005|publisher=Kalmbach Pub.|location=Waukesha, Wis.|isbn=0-87116-218-0|pages=46–47}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Dutch spiral]]
* [[African helix]]
* Russian spiral
*Chenille

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
* Virginia Blakelock, ''Those Bad, Bad Beads!''  Virginia Blakelock Publisher, 1990.
* Don Pierce, ''Beading on a Loom.''  Interweave Press, 1999.  {{ISBN|1-883010-63-2}}
* Carol Wilcox Wells, ''Creative Bead Weaving.'' Lark Books, 1996.  {{ISBN|1-887374-05-1}}

{{beadwork}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Bead Weaving}}
[[Category:Weaving]]
[[Category:Beadwork]]</text>
      <sha1>htnivu4fgmijssng2t1filmdt15aiw5</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
