  <page>
    <title>Burgess Shale</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3422</id>
    <revision>
      <id>938028035</id>
      <parentid>931309905</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-28T18:18:31Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ornithopsis</username>
        <id>19534858</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Biota */  Removed OR paleoart.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Rock formation in the Canadian Rockies with exceptional preservation of fossils' soft parts}}
{{Further|Burgess Shale type fauna|Fossils of the Burgess Shale}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}
{{Infobox rockunit
| image = Ottoia tricuspida ROM 63057.jpg
| period = Miaolingian
| age = &lt;br&gt; Miaolingian &lt;br&gt; ~{{Fossil range|{{period start|Burgess Shale}}}}
| caption = ''[[Ottoia]]'', a soft-bodied worm, abundant in the Burgess Shale. (From Smith et al. 2015)
| type = [[Geological formation]]
| prilithology = [[Shale]]
| otherlithology =
| namedfor = [[Mount Burgess|Burgess Pass]]
| namedby = [[Charles Doolittle Walcott]], 1911
| region = [[Yoho National Park]] and [[Kootenay National Park]]
| country = [[Canada]]
| coordinates = {{Coord|51|26|N|116|28|W|region:CA-BC_type:landmark_source:dewiki}}
| unitof = [[Stephen Formation]]
| subunits =
| thickness = {{convert|161|m|ft|sp=us}}&lt;ref name=lexicon&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cgkn1.cgkn.net/weblex/weblex_litho_detail_e.pl?00053:002016|title=Burgess Shale|author=Lexicon of Canadian Geological Units|accessdate=2009-02-06|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://archive.is/20130111235204/http://cgkn1.cgkn.net/weblex/weblex_litho_detail_e.pl?00053:002016|archivedate=11 January 2013|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| extent =
| area =
| map = Canadian Rockies highlighting Yoho National Park.png
| map_caption = Map highlighting Yoho National Park in red
}}

The '''Burgess Shale''' is a [[fossil]]-bearing deposit exposed in the [[Canadian Rockies]] of [[British Columbia]], Canada.&lt;ref name=Gabbott2001&gt;{{Cite book
 | last = Gabbott | first = Sarah E.
 | year = 2001
 | journal = [[Encyclopedia of Life Sciences]]
 | title = Exceptional Preservation
 | doi = 10.1038/npg.els.0001622
| isbn = 978-0-470-01590-2
 }}&lt;/ref&gt; It is famous for the exceptional preservation of the soft parts of its fossils. At {{Ma|Burgess shale|million years}} old ([[Wuliuan|middle Cambrian]]),&lt;ref name=Butterfield2006&gt;{{cite journal
 | last = Butterfield | first = N.J.
 | year = 2006
 | title = Hooking some stem-group&quot; worms&quot;: fossil lophotrochozoans in the Burgess Shale
 | journal = [[BioEssays]]
 | volume = 28
 | issue = 12
 | pages = 1161–6
 | doi = 10.1002/bies.20507
|map=
| pmid = 17120226
}}&lt;/ref&gt; it is one of the earliest fossil beds containing soft-part imprints.

The rock unit is a black [[shale]] and crops out at a number of localities near the town of [[Field, British Columbia|Field]] in [[Yoho National Park]] and the [[Kicking Horse Pass]]. Another outcrop is in [[Kootenay National Park]] 42&amp;nbsp;km to the south.

== History and significance ==
{{Main|History of the Burgess Shale}}
[[File:ROM-BurgessShale-CompleteAnomalocarisFossil.png|thumb|left|The first complete ''[[Anomalocaris]]'' fossil found.]]
{{Burgess Shale}}

The Burgess Shale was discovered by [[palaeontologist]] [[Charles Doolittle Walcott|Charles Walcott]] on 30 August 1909,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://burgess-shale.rom.on.ca/en/history/discoveries/02-walcott.php | title=Charles Walcott | publisher=[[Royal Ontario Museum]] | accessdate=29 August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; towards the end of the season's fieldwork.{{fotbs}} He returned in 1910 with his sons, daughter, and wife, establishing a quarry on the flanks of Fossil Ridge. The significance of soft-bodied preservation, and the range of organisms he recognised as new to science, led him to return to the quarry almost every year until 1924. At that point, aged 74, he had amassed over 65,000 specimens. Describing the fossils was a vast task, pursued by Walcott until his death in 1927.&lt;ref name=&quot;fotbs&quot; /&gt; Walcott, led by scientific opinion at the time, attempted to categorise all fossils into living taxa, and as a result, the fossils were regarded as little more than curiosities at the time. It was not until 1962 that a first-hand reinvestigation of the fossils was attempted, by Alberto Simonetta. This led scientists to recognise that Walcott had barely scratched the surface of information available in the Burgess Shale, and also made it clear that the organisms did not fit comfortably into modern groups.

Excavations were resumed at the [[Walcott Quarry]] by the [[Geological Survey of Canada]] under the persuasion of [[trilobite]] expert [[Harry Blackmore Whittington]], and a new quarry, the Raymond, was established about 20 metres higher up Fossil Ridge.&lt;ref name=fotbs /&gt; Whittington, with the help of research students [[Derek Briggs]] and [[Simon Conway Morris]] of the [[University of Cambridge]], began a thorough reassessment of the Burgess Shale, and revealed that the fauna represented were much more diverse and unusual than Walcott had recognized.&lt;ref name=fotbs /&gt; Indeed, many of the animals present had bizarre [[body form|anatomical features]] and only the slightest resemblance to other known animals. Examples include ''[[Opabinia]]'', with five eyes and a snout like a vacuum cleaner hose and ''[[Hallucigenia]]'', which was originally reconstructed upside down, walking on bilaterally symmetrical spines.

With [[Parks Canada]] and [[UNESCO]] recognising the significance of the Burgess Shale, collecting fossils became politically more difficult from the mid-1970s. Collections continued to be made by the [[Royal Ontario Museum]]. The curator of invertebrate palaeontology, [[Desmond Collins]], identified a number of additional outcrops, [[stratigraphically]] both higher and lower than the original Walcott quarry.&lt;ref name=fotbs /&gt; These localities continue to yield new organisms faster than they can be studied.

[[Stephen Jay Gould]]'s book ''[[Wonderful Life (book)|Wonderful Life]]'', published in 1989, brought the Burgess Shale fossils to the public's attention. Gould suggests that the extraordinary diversity of the fossils indicates that life forms at the time were much more disparate in body form than those that survive today, and that many of the unique lineages were evolutionary experiments that became extinct. Gould's interpretation of the diversity of Cambrian fauna relied heavily on [[Simon Conway Morris]]'s reinterpretation of Charles Walcott's original publications. However, Conway Morris strongly disagreed with Gould's conclusions, arguing that almost all the Cambrian fauna could be classified into modern day [[Phylum|phyla]].&lt;ref name=&quot;crucible&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author =Simon Conway Morris|authorlink =Simon Conway Morris|title =The Crucible of Creation: The Burgess Shale and the Rise of Animals|publisher =Oxford University Press|year =1998|page =[https://archive.org/details/crucibleofcreati00conw/page/316 316]|isbn =978-0-19-286202-0|url =https://archive.org/details/crucibleofcreati00conw/page/316}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Burgess Shale has attracted the interest of [[Paleoclimatology|paleoclimatologists]] who want to study and predict long-term future changes in Earth's climate. According to [[Peter Ward (paleontologist)|Peter Ward]] and Donald Brownlee in the 2003 book ''[[The Life and Death of Planet Earth]]'',&lt;ref&gt;Ward, Peter Douglas; Brownlee, Donald (2003), The life and death of planet Earth: how the new science of astrobiology charts the ultimate fate of our world, Macmillan, {{ISBN|0-8050-7512-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; climatologists study the fossil records in the Burgess Shale to understand the climate of the [[Cambrian explosion]], and use it to predict what Earth's climate would look like 500 million years in the future when a warming and expanding Sun combined with declining [[Carbon dioxide|CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;]] and oxygen levels eventually heat the Earth toward temperatures not seen since the [[Archean]] Eon 3 billion years ago, before the first plants and animals appeared, and therefore understand how and when the last living things will die out. See also [[Future of the Earth]].

After the Burgess Shale site was registered as a [[World Heritage Site]] in 1980, it was included in the Canadian Rocky Mountain Parks WHS designation in 1984.

In February 2014, the discovery was announced of another Burgess Shale outcrop in [[Kootenay National Park]] to the south. In just 15 days of field collecting in 2013, 50 animal species were unearthed at the new site.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| title ='Epic' new fossil site found in B.C. national park| newspaper =[[Canoe.ca]]| publisher =[[Quebecor Media]]| date =11 February 2014| url =http://cnews.canoe.ca/CNEWS/Science/2014/02/10/21461856.html| accessdate =11 February 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Geological setting ==
{{Main|Stephen Formation}}
[[File:Burgess Shale, Yoho National Park of Canada.jpg|thumb|[[Satellite]] image of the area.]]

The fossil-bearing deposits of the Burgess Shale correlate to the [[Stephen Formation]], a collection of slightly calcareous dark mudstones, about {{Ma|burgess shale|million years}} old.&lt;ref name=fotbs /&gt; The beds were deposited at the base of a cliff about 160&amp;nbsp;m tall,&lt;ref name=fotbs /&gt; below the depth agitated by waves during storms.&lt;ref name=Gabbott2008&gt;{{cite journal
 | last1 = Gabbott | first1 = S.E.
 | last2 = Zalasiewicz | first2 = J.
 | last3 = Collins | first3 = D.
 | year = 2008
 | title = Sedimentation of the Phyllopod bed within the Cambrian Burgess Shale Formation of British Columbia
 | journal = [[Journal of the Geological Society]]
 | volume = 165
 | issue = 1
 | pages = 307–318
 | url = http://jgs.lyellcollection.org/cgi/content/abstract/165/1/307
 | doi = 10.1144/0016-76492007-023
| bibcode = 2008JGSoc.165..307G}}&lt;/ref&gt; This vertical cliff was composed of the calcareous reefs of the [[Cathedral escarpment|Cathedral Formation]], which probably formed shortly before the deposition of the Burgess Shale.&lt;ref name=fotbs /&gt; The precise formation mechanism is not known for certain, but the most widely accepted hypothesis suggests that the edge of the Cathedral Formation reef became detached from the rest of the reef, slumping and being transported some distance — perhaps kilometers — away from the reef edge.&lt;ref name=fotbs /&gt; Later reactivation of faults at the base of the formation led to its disintegration from about {{Ma|509}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;Collom2009&quot;&gt;{{cite journal| year = 2009| pages = 63–85| doi = 10.1016/j.palaeo.2009.02.012| last2 =   Johnston| last3 =   Powell| volume = 277| issue = 1–2| journal =  	Palaeogeography, Palaeoclimatology, Palaeoecology | first1 = C. J.| first2 = P. A.| first3 = W. G.| title = Reinterpretation of 'Middle' Cambrian stratigraphy of the rifted western Laurentian margin: Burgess Shale Formation and contiguous units (Sauk II Megasequence); Rocky Mountains, Canada| last1 = Collom }}&lt;/ref&gt; This would have left a steep cliff, the bottom of which would be protected from tectonic decompression because the limestone of the Cathedral Formation is difficult to compress. This protection explains why fossils preserved further from the Cathedral Formation are impossible to work with — tectonic squeezing of the beds has produced a vertical cleavage that fractures the rocks, so they split perpendicular to the fossils.&lt;ref name=fotbs /&gt; The Walcott quarry produced such spectacular fossils because it was so close to the Stephen Formation — indeed the quarry has now been excavated to the very edge of the Cambrian cliff.&lt;ref name=fotbs /&gt;

It was originally thought that the Burgess Shale was deposited in [[anoxic event|anoxic]] conditions, but mounting research shows that oxygen was continually present in the sediment.&lt;ref name=Powell2009&gt;{{cite journal| year = 2009| last1 = Powell| doi = 10.1016/j.palaeo.2009.02.016| pages = 127–140| issue = 1–2| title = Comparison of Geochemical and Distinctive Mineralogical Features Associated with the Kinzers and Burgess Shale Formations and their Associated Units| journal =  	Palaeogeography, Palaeoclimatology, Palaeoecology| volume = 277| first1 = W.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The anoxic setting had been thought to not only protect the newly dead organisms from decay, but it also created chemical conditions allowing the preservation of the soft parts of the organisms. Further, it reduced the abundance of burrowing organisms — burrows and trackways ''are'' found in beds containing soft-bodied organisms, but they are rare and generally of limited vertical extent.&lt;ref name=fotbs /&gt; Brine seeps are an alternative hypothesis; see [[Burgess Shale type preservation]] for a more thorough discussion.

== Stratigraphy ==
[[File:WalcottQuarry080509.jpg|thumb|Walcott Quarry of the Burgess Shale showing the Walcott Quarry Shale Member. The white parallel vertical streaks are remnants of drill holes made during excavations in mid-1990s.]]

The Burgess Shale Formation comprises 10 members, the most famous being the Walcott Quarry Shale Member comprising the greater phyllopod bed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gabbott2008&quot; /&gt;

== Taphonomy and diagenesis ==
{{further|Taphonomy|Diagenesis}}
{{expand section|date=January 2017}}
&lt;ref name=Butterfield1990&gt;{{cite journal
 | jstor = 2400788
 | author = Butterfield, N.J.
 | journal = [[Paleobiology (journal)|Paleobiology]]
 | volume = 16
 | issue = 3
 | pages = 272–286
 | year = 1990
 | title=Organic Preservation of Non-Mineralizing Organisms and the Taphonomy of the Burgess Shale
 | doi = 10.1017/S0094837300009994
 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Page2008&quot;&gt;{{cite journal
 | year = 2008
 | doi = 10.1130/G24991A.1
 | title = Ubiquitous Burgess Shale–style &quot;clay templates&quot; in low-grade metamorphic mudrocks
 | last1 = Page         | first1 = Alex
 | last2 = Gabbott      | first2 = Sarah
 | last3 = Wilby        | first3 = Phillip R.
 | last4 = Zalasiewicz  | first4 = Jan A
 | journal = [[Geology (journal)|Geology]]
 | volume = 36
 | issue = 11
 | pages = 855–858
 |bibcode = 2008Geo....36..855P }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=OrrEtAl1998&gt;{{cite journal
 | doi = 10.1126/science.281.5380.1173
 | pmid = 9712577
 | author = Orr, Patrick J.
 | author2 = Briggs, Derek E. G.
 | author2-link = Briggs, Derek E. G.
 | author3 = Kearns, Stuart L.
 | journal = [[Science (journal)|Science]]
 | volume = 281
 | issue = 5380
 | pages = 1173–5
 | year = 1998
 | title = Cambrian Burgess Shale Animals Replicated in Clay Minerals
 | bibcode=1998Sci...281.1173O
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=CARONEtAl2006&gt;{{cite journal
 | doi = 10.2110/palo.2003.P05-070R
 |author1=CARON, JEAN-BERNARD |author2=JACKSON, DONALD A. | journal = PALAIOS
 | volume = 21
 | issue = 5
 | pages = 451–465
 | year = 2006
 | title = Taphonomy Of The Greater Phyllopod Bed Community, Burgess Shale
| bibcode = 2006Palai..21..451C}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=GainesEtAl2005&gt;{{cite journal
 | doi = 10.1016/j.palaeo.2004.07.034
 |author1=Gaines, R.R. |author2=Kennedy, M.J. |author3=Droser, M.L. | journal = [[Palaeogeography, Palaeoclimatology, Palaeoecology]]
| volume = 220
 | issue = 1–2
 | pages = 193–205
 | year = 2005
 | title = A new hypothesis for organic preservation of Burgess Shale taxa in the middle Cambrian Wheeler Formation, House Range, Utah
 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=ButterfieldEtAl2007&gt;{{cite journal
 | doi = 10.1111/j.1475-4983.2007.00656.x
 |author1=Butterfield, N.J. |author2=Balthasar, U. |author3=Wilson, L.A. | journal = Palaeontology
 | volume = 50
 | issue = 3
 | pages = 537–543
 | year = 2007
 | title = Fossil Diagenesis In The Burgess Shale
 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Further|Burgess Shale type preservation}}

There are many other comparable Cambrian ''[[lagerstätte]]n''; indeed such assemblages are far more common in the Cambrian than in any other period. This is mainly due to the limited extent of burrowing activity; as such [[bioturbation]] [[Cambrian substrate revolution|became more prevalent]] throughout the Cambrian, environments capable of preserving organisms' soft parts became much rarer.&lt;ref name=fotbs /&gt; (The [[pre-Cambrian]] fossil record of animals is sparse and ambiguous.)

== Biota ==
{{Main|Fossils of the Burgess Shale|Burgess Shale type fauna}}

The biota of the Burgess Shale appears to be typical of middle Cambrian deposits.&lt;ref name=fotbs /&gt; Although the hard-part bearing organisms make up as little as 14% of the community,&lt;ref name=fotbs /&gt; these same organisms are found in similar proportions in other Cambrian localities. This means that there is no reason to assume that the organisms without hard parts are exceptional in any way; indeed, many appear in other lagerstätten of different age and locations.&lt;ref name=fotbs /&gt;

The biota consists of a range of organisms. Free-swimming ([[Nekton|nectonic]]) organisms are relatively rare, with the majority of organisms being bottom dwelling (benthic) — either moving about (vagrant) or permanently attached to the sea floor (sessile).&lt;ref name=fotbs /&gt; About two-thirds of the Burgess Shale organisms lived by feeding on the organic content in the muddy sea floor, while almost a third filtered out fine particles from the water column. Under 10% of organisms were predators or scavengers, although since these organisms were larger, the biomass was split equally among each of the filter feeding, deposit feeding, predatory and scavenging organisms.&lt;ref name=fotbs /&gt;

Many Burgess Shale organisms represent [[stem-group]] members of the modern animal phyla, though [[crown-group]] representatives of certain phyla are also present.&lt;ref&gt;e.g. {{cite journal|doi=10.1038/nature14573|pmid=26106857|title=Hallucigenia's head and the pharyngeal armature of early ecdysozoans|journal=Nature|volume=523|issue=7558|pages=75–8|year=2015|last1=Smith|first1=Martin R.|last2=Caron|first2=Jean-Bernard|url=http://www.repository.cam.ac.uk/handle/1810/248498|bibcode=2015Natur.523...75S}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Working with the Burgess Shale ==

The fossils of the Burgess Shale are preserved as black carbon films on black shales, and so are difficult to photograph; however, various photographic techniques can improve the quality of the images that can be acquired.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Bengtson|first=Stefan|title=Teasing Fossils out of Shales with Cameras and Computers|journal=Palaeontologia Electronica|year=2000|volume=3|issue=1|url=http://palaeo-electronica.org/2000_1/fossils/text.pdf|accessdate=3 December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other techniques include backscatter SEM, elemental mapping and ''[[camera lucida]]'' drawing.

Once images have been acquired, the effects of decay and [[taphonomy]] must be accounted for before a correct anatomical reconstruction can be made. A consideration of the combination of characters allows researchers to establish the taxonomic affinity.

== See also ==
* [[Body form]]
* [[History of invertebrate paleozoology]]
* [[Invertebrate paleontology]]
* [[List of fossil sites]] ''(with link directory)''
* [[List of notable fossils]]
* [[Maotianshan Shales]], which is often compared to Burgess Shale
* [[Wheeler Shale]], also compared to Burgess Shale

== References ==

{{Reflist|30em}}

== Further reading ==
{{Commons category|Burgess Shale}}
*Gould, Stephen Jay &amp; Conway Morris, Simon. Debating the significance of the Burgess Shale: {{cite journal |author1=Simon Conway Morris |author2=Stephen Jay Gould |lastauthoramp=yes |title=Showdown on the Burgess Shale |journal=Natural History Magazine |volume=107 |issue=10 |pages=48–55 |url=http://www.stephenjaygould.org/library/naturalhistory_cambrian.html |access-date=17 August 2008 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20101210200047/http://www.stephenjaygould.org/library/naturalhistory_cambrian.html |archive-date=10 December 2010 |url-status=dead }}
*Conway Morris, Simon. ''The Crucible of Creation: The Burgess Shale and the Rise of Animals'', Oxford University Press, Oxford, 1998 (paperback 1999) {{ISBN|0-19-850197-8}} (hbk), {{ISBN|0-19-286202-2}} (pbk)
*[[Fortey, Richard]]. ''Trilobite: Eyewitness to Evolution'', Flamingo, 2001. {{ISBN|0-00-655138-6}}
*Gould, Stephen Jay. ''[[Wonderful Life (book)|Wonderful Life: Burgess Shale and the Nature of History]]'', Vintage, 2000. {{ISBN|0-09-927345-4}}
*[[Briggs, D. E. G.]]; Erwin,  Douglas H. &amp; Collier, Frederick J. ''The Fossils of the Burgess Shale'', Smithsonian, 1994. {{ISBN|1-56098-364-7}}

== External links ==
* {{cite web | url = http://burgess-shale.rom.on.ca/en | title = Burgess Shale | publisher = Virtual Museum of Canada | year = 2011}}
* {{cite web | url = http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/p003k9bg | title = The Cambrian Explosion | publisher = BBC Radio 4 broadcast|work=In Our Time|date= 17 February 2005|author=Melvyn Bragg (host)}}  (includes links to resource pages)
* {{cite journal|journal=[[Nature Communications]]|title=A new phyllopod bed-like assemblage from the Burgess Shale of the Canadian Rockies|last1=Caron|first1=Jean-Bernard|last2=Gaines|first2=Robert R.|last3=Aria|first3=Cédric|last4=Mángano|first4=M. Gabriela|last5=Streng|first5=Michael|volume=5|pages=3210|date=February 2014|doi=10.1038/ncomms4210|issn=2041-1723|bibcode = 2014NatCo...5.3210C|pmid=24513643}}

{{World Heritage Sites in Canada}}

[[Category:Burgess Shale| ]]
[[Category:Burgess Shale fossils| ]]
[[Category:Cambrian System of North America]]
[[Category:Cambrian British Columbia]]
[[Category:Cambrian life by stratigraphic provenance]]
[[Category:Cambrian southern paleotropical deposits]]
[[Category:Paleontology in Canada]]
[[Category:Fossil parks in Canada]]
[[Category:Yoho National Park]]
[[Category:Geology of the Rocky Mountains]]
[[Category:Shale formations]]
[[Category:Lagerstätten]]</text>
      <sha1>mmnza5wdwjladd9j8xu1of24qnhy7kp</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
