  <page>
    <title>Abbreviation</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1171</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941913655</id>
      <parentid>941913626</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-21T12:20:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Serols</username>
        <id>9929111</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contributions/Pattison_john|Pattison_john]] ([[User talk:Pattison_john|talk]]) ([[WP:HG|HG]]) (3.4.9)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Shortened form of a word or phrase}}
{{redirect|Abbr|the &amp;lt;abbr&amp;gt; HTML tag|HTML element#abbr}}
{{More citations needed|date=May 2008}}
[[File:Schriftprobe Latein 15 Jh.jpg|thumb|upright=1.5|Example of 15th-century [[Latin]] manuscript text with [[scribal abbreviation]]s]]

An '''abbreviation''' (from [[Latin]] ''brevis'', meaning ''short'' &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=brevis/breve, brevis M – Latin is Simple Online Dictionary|url=https://www.latin-is-simple.com/en/vocabulary/adjective/91/|website=www.latin-is-simple.com|accessdate=29 March 2018|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;) is a shortened form of a word or phrase, by any method. It may consist of a group of letters, lower case letters do count or words taken from the full version of the word or phrase, for example, the word ''abbreviation'' can itself be represented by the abbreviation ''abbr.'', ''abbrv.'', or ''abbrev.''; ''NBM'', for [[Nothing by mouth|nil (or nothing) by mouth]] is an abbreviated medical instruction. It may also consist of initials only, a mixture of initials and words, or words or letters representing words in another language (for example, [[e.g.]], [[i.e.]] or [[RSVP]]). Some types of abbreviations are [[acronym]]s (which are pronounceable), [[initialism]]s (using initials only), or grammatical [[Contraction (grammar)|contractions]] or [[crasis]].

An abbreviation is a shortening by any of these, or other, methods abbreviations are just to make words smaller with apostrophes

==Different types of abbreviation==
Acronyms, initialisms, contractions and crasis share some [[semantic]] and [[phonetic]] functions, and all four are connected by the term &quot;abbreviation&quot; in loose parlance.&lt;ref name=harts&gt;{{cite book|title=New Hart's Rules: The handbook of style for writers and editors|publisher=Oxford University Press, 2005|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=3uwGtj8i_vkC&amp;dq=New+Hart%27s+Rules&amp;q=acronyms+contractions+10.1#v=snippet&amp;q=acronyms%20contractions%2010.1&amp;f=false|isbn=0-19-861041-6|date=2005-09-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|p167}}



A contraction is a reduction of size by the drawing together of the parts; a contraction of a word or words is made by omitting certain letters or [[syllable]]s and bringing together the first and last letters or elements, such as &quot;I'm&quot; . A contraction may be regarded as a type of abbreviation, but not [[vice versa]].

== History ==
{{See also|Scribal abbreviation}}

Abbreviations have a long history, created so that spelling out a whole word could be avoided. This might be done to save time and space, and also to provide secrecy.bad words were used and initial letters were commonly used to represent words in specific applications. In classical [[Ancient Greece|Greece]] and [[Ancient Rome|Rome]], the reduction of words to single letters was common.&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=HA9kAAAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA5&amp;dq=abbreviations+history&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=D2NaVIitA6vbsASp94DgAg&amp;ved=0CDoQ6AEwBA#v=onepage&amp;q=abbreviations%20history&amp;f=false ''The British Cyclopaedia of the Arts, Sciences, History, Geography, Literature, Natural History, and Biography'', Wm. S. Orr and Company, 1838, p.5.]&lt;/ref&gt; In Roman inscriptions, &quot;Words were commonly abbreviated by using the initial letter or letters of words, and most inscriptions have at least one abbreviation.&quot; However, &quot;some could have more than one meaning, depending on their context. (For example, ''A'' can be an abbreviation for many words, such as ''ager'', ''amicus'', ''annus'', ''as'', ''Aulus'', ''Aurelius'', ''aurum'' and ''avus''.)&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Adkins, L., [https://books.google.com/books?id=zGY1Sqjwf8kC&amp;dq=abbreviations++fashionable&amp;q=abbreviated+%22the+initial%22#v=snippet&amp;q=abbreviated%20%22the%20initial%22&amp;f=false ''Handbook to Life in Ancient Rome''], Infobase Publishing, 2004, p. 261.&lt;/ref&gt;

Abbreviations in English were frequently used from its earliest days. Manuscripts of copies of the [[old English]] poem ''[[Beowulf]]'' used many abbreviations, for example ''7'' or ''&amp;'' for ''and'', and ''y'' for ''since'', so that &quot;not much space is wasted&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=68EjAwAAQBAJ&amp;dq=abbreviations+history&amp;q=abbreviations+beowulf#v=snippet&amp;q=abbreviations%20beowulf&amp;f=false Gelderen, E. v, ''A History of the English Language: Revised edition'', John Benjamins Publishing Company, 2014, Ch. 4 1.]&lt;/ref&gt; The standardisation of English in the 15th through 17th centuries included such a growth in the use of abbreviations.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.spellingsociety.org/journals/j7/shortcuts.php Spelling Society : Shortcuts 1483–1660&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071015214606/http://www.spellingsociety.org/journals/j7/shortcuts.php |date=October 15, 2007 }} Doesn't work.&lt;/ref&gt;{{citation needed|date=November 2014}} At first, abbreviations were sometimes represented with various suspension signs, not only periods. For example, sequences like ‹er› were replaced with ‹ɔ›, as in ‹mastɔ› for ''master'' and ‹exacɔbate› for ''exacerbate''. While this may seem trivial, it was symptomatic of an attempt by people manually reproducing academic texts to reduce the copy time. An example from the Oxford University Register, 1503:{{citation needed|date=November 2014}}

{{quote|Mastɔ subwardenɔ y ɔmēde me to you. And wherɔ y wrot to you the last wyke that y trouyde itt good to differrɔ thelectionɔ ovɔ to quīdenaɔ tinitatis y have be thougħt me synɔ that itt woll be thenɔ a bowte mydsomɔ.}}

In the [[Early Modern English]] period, between the 15th and 17th centuries, the [[thorn (letter)]] Þ was used for ''th'', as in ''Þ&lt;sup&gt;e&lt;/sup&gt;''. However in modern times, Þ is commonly misread and wrongly rewritten as ''y'', as in ''Y&lt;sup&gt;e&lt;/sup&gt; Olde Tea Shoppe''.&lt;ref&gt;Lass, R., ''The Cambridge History of the English Language'', Cambridge University Press, 2006, Vol. 2, p. 36.&lt;/ref&gt;

During the growth of [[philology|philological]] linguistic theory in academic Britain, abbreviating became very fashionable. The use of abbreviation for the names of [[J. R. R. Tolkien]] and his friend [[C. S. Lewis]], and other members of the [[Oxford]] literary group known as the [[Inklings]], are sometimes cited as symptomatic of this.{{citation needed|date=October 2011}} Likewise, a century earlier in [[Boston]], a fad of abbreviation started that swept the United States, with the globally popular term [[Okay|OK]] generally credited as a remnant of its influence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.illinoisprairie.info/chocokeh.htm |title=The Choctaw Expression 'Okeh' and the Americanism 'Okay' |publisher=Jim Fay |date=2007-09-13 |accessdate=2008-05-12 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20101224185657/http://www.illinoisprairie.info/chocokeh.htm |archivedate=2010-12-24 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.straightdope.com/classics/a2_250.html |title=What does &quot;OK&quot; stand for? |work=[[The Straight Dope]] |accessdate=2008-05-12| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20080512085453/http://www.straightdope.com/classics/a2_250.html| archivedate= 12 May 2008 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After World War II, the British greatly reduced the use of the [[full stop]] and other punctuation points after abbreviations in at least semi-formal writing, while the Americans more readily kept such use until more recently, and still maintain it more than Britons{{Citation needed|date=April 2017}}. The classic example, considered by their American counterparts quite curious, was the maintenance of the internal comma in a British organisation of secret agents called the &quot;[[Special Operations, Executive]]&quot;—&quot;S.O., E&quot;—which is not found in histories written after about 1960.

But before that, many Britons were more scrupulous at maintaining the French form. In French, the period only follows an abbreviation if the last letter in the abbreviation is ''not'' the last letter of its antecedent: &quot;M.&quot; is the abbreviation for &quot;monsieur&quot; while &quot;Mme&quot; is that for &quot;madame&quot;. Like many other cross-[[English Channel|channel]] linguistic acquisitions, many Britons readily took this up and followed this rule themselves, while the Americans took a simpler rule and applied it rigorously.{{Citation needed|date=January 2020}}&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.arcjournals.org/pdfs/ijhsse/v5-i1/3.pdf|title=Sudan University of Science and Technology Graduate College|last=Said Ahmed Alawad|first=Mohamed|date=2018|website=ARC Journals|url-status=live|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Over the years, however, the lack of convention in some style guides has made it difficult to determine which two-word abbreviations should be abbreviated with periods and which should not. The U.S. media tend to use periods in two-word abbreviations like United States (U.S.), but not [[personal computer]] (PC) or television (TV). Many British publications have gradually done away with the use of periods in abbreviations.

Minimization of punctuation in typewritten material became economically desirable in the 1960s and 1970s for the many users of carbon-film [[IBM Selectric typewriter#Ribbons|ribbons]] since a period or comma consumed the same length of non-reusable expensive ribbon as did a capital letter.

Widespread use of electronic communication through mobile phones and the Internet during the 1990s allowed for a marked rise in colloquial abbreviation. This was due largely to increasing popularity of textual communication services such as instant- and text messaging. [[Short Message Service|SMS]], for instance, supports message lengths of 160 characters at most (using the [[GSM 03.38]] character set). This brevity gave rise to an informal abbreviation scheme sometimes called [[SMS language|Textese]], with which 10% or more of the words in a typical SMS message are abbreviated.&lt;ref&gt;Crystal, David. [[Txtng: the Gr8 Db8]]. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2008. {{ISBN|978-0-19-954490-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; More recently Twitter, a popular [[social networking service]], began driving abbreviation use with 140 character message limits.

== Style conventions in English ==

In modern English, there are several conventions for abbreviations, and the choice may be confusing. The only rule universally accepted is that one should be ''consistent'', and to make this easier, publishers express their preferences in a [[style guide]]. Questions which arise include those in the following subsections.

=== Lowercase letters ===

If the original word was capitalized then the first letter of its abbreviation should retain the capital, for example Lev. for ''Leviticus''. When a word is abbreviated to more than a single letter and was originally spelled with lower case letters then there is no need for capitalization. However, when abbreviating a phrase where only the first letter of each word is taken, then all letters should be capitalized, as in YTD for ''year-to-date'', PCB for ''printed circuit board'' and FYI for ''for your information''. However, see the following section regarding abbreviations that have become common vocabulary: these are no longer written with capital letters.

=== Periods (full stops) and spaces ===
[[File:“To Penna. R.R. Station”.jpg|thumb|Sign in New York City subway, reading “Penna.” for Penn''sylvani''a, showing American style of including the period even for contractions.]]
A period (full stop) is often used to signify an abbreviation, but opinion is divided as to when and if this should happen.

According to [[Hart's Rules]], the traditional rule is that abbreviations (in the narrow sense that includes only words with the ending, and not the middle, dropped) terminate with a full stop, whereas contractions (in the sense of words missing a middle part) do not, but there are exceptions.&lt;ref name=&quot;harts&quot;/&gt;{{rp|p167–170}} [[Fowler's Modern English Usage]] says full stops are used to mark both abbreviations and contractions, but recommends against this practice: advising them only for abbreviations and lower-case initialisms and not for upper-case initialisms and contractions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Pocket Fowler's Modern English Usage|edition=2nd|editor-first=Robert|editor-last=Allen|publisher=Oxford University Press|date=2008|isbn=9780191727078|contribution=Full stop}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
!Example
!Category
!Short form
!Source
|-
|[[Doctor (title)|Doctor]]
|Contraction
|Dr
|D——r
|-
|[[Professor]]
|Abbreviation
|Prof.
|Prof...
|-
|The [[Reverend]]
|Abbreviation
|Rev.
|Rev...
|-
|The [[Reverend]]
|Contraction
|Revd
|Rev——d
|-
|[[The Right Honourable]]
|Contraction and Abbreviation
|Rt Hon.
|R——t Hon...
|}

In [[American English]], the period is usually included regardless of whether or not it is a contraction, e.g. ''Dr.'' or ''Mrs.''. In some cases, periods are optional, as in either ''US'' or ''U.S.'' for ''United States'', ''EU'' or ''E.U.'' for ''European Union'', and ''UN'' or ''U.N.'' for ''United Nations''. There are some house styles, however—American ones included—that remove the periods from almost all abbreviations. For example:
* The U.S. [[Manual on Uniform Traffic Control Devices]] advises that periods should not be used with abbreviations on road signs, except for cardinal directions as part of a destination name. (For example, ''&quot;Northwest Blvd&quot;'', ''&quot;W. Jefferson&quot;'', and ''&quot;PED XING&quot;'' all follow this recommendation.) 
* [[AMA Manual of Style|AMA style]], used in many [[medical journal]]s, uses no periods in abbreviations or acronyms, with almost no exceptions. Thus [[exempli gratia|eg]], [[id est|ie]], [[wikt:versus|vs]], [[et al.]], [[Doctor (title)|Dr]], [[Mr.|Mr]], [[magnetic resonance imaging|MRI]], [[intensive care unit|ICU]], and hundreds of others contain no periods. The only exceptions are &quot;[[Numero sign|No.]]&quot; (to avoid the appearance of &quot;[[yes and no|No]]&quot;); initials within persons' names (such as &quot;George R. Smith&quot;); and &quot;St.&quot; within persons' names when the person prefers it (such as &quot;Emily R. St. Clair&quot;) (but not in city names such as ''St Louis'' or ''St Paul''). (AMA style also forgoes italic on terms long since naturalized into English from [[Latin]], [[New Latin]], other languages, or [[international scientific vocabulary|ISV]]; thus, no italic for [[exempli gratia|eg]], [[id est|ie]], [[wikt:versus|vs]], [[et al.]], [[in vivo]], [[in vitro]], or [[in situ]].)

Acronyms that were originally capitalized (with or without periods) but have since entered the vocabulary as generic words are no longer written with capital letters nor with any periods. Examples are [[sonar]], [[radar]], [[lidar]], [[laser]], [[SNAFU|snafu]], and [[Scuba set|scuba]].

Today, spaces are generally not used between single-letter abbreviations of words in the same phrase, so one almost never encounters &quot;U.&amp;nbsp;S.&quot;

When an abbreviation appears at the end of a sentence, only one period is used: ''The capital of the United States is Washington, D.C''.

=== Plural forms ===

There is a question about how to pluralize abbreviations, particularly acronyms. Often a writer will add an 's' following an apostrophe, as in &quot;PC's&quot;. However, this style is not preferred by many style guides. For instance, Kate Turabian, writing about style in academic writings,&lt;ref name=&quot;Chicago&quot;&gt;Turabian, K., ''A Manual for Writers of Research Papers, Theses, and Dissertations'', 7th Edition, subsection 20.1.2&lt;/ref&gt; allows for an apostrophe to form plural acronyms &quot;only when an abbreviation contains internal periods or both capital and lowercase letters&quot;. Turabian would therefore prefer &quot;DVDs&quot; and &quot;URLs&quot; and &quot;Ph.D.'s&quot;, while the [[Modern Language Association]]&lt;ref name=&quot;MLA&quot;&gt;Modern Language Association (MLA) Handbook for Writers of Research Papers, 7th Edition 2009, subsection 3.2.7.g&lt;/ref&gt; explicitly says, &quot;do not use an apostrophe to form the plural of an abbreviation&quot;. Also, the [[American Psychological Association]] specifically says,&lt;ref name=&quot;APA&quot;&gt;Publication Manual of the American Psychological Association (APA), 5th Edition 2001, subsection 3.28&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;''Publication Manual of the American Psychological Association'', 6th Edition 2010, subsection 4.29&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;without an apostrophe&quot;.

However, the 1999 style guide for ''[[The New York Times]]'' states that the addition of an apostrophe is necessary when pluralizing all abbreviations, preferring &quot;PC's, TV's and VCR's&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Siegal, AM., Connolly, WG., [https://books.google.com/books?ei=-y5aVHCTyLAEl5GB0AE&amp;id=RT5w0s7_op8C&amp;dq=new+york+times+style&amp;focus=searchwithinvolume&amp;q=plurals+abbreviations ''The New York Times Manual of Style and Usage''], Three Rivers Press, 1999, p. 24.&lt;/ref&gt;

Following those who would generally omit the apostrophe, to form the plural of [[run batted in]], simply add an s to the end of RBI.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Garner|first=Bryan|title=Garner's Modern American Usage|year=2009|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=Oxford; New York|isbn=978-0-19-538275-4|page=638}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*RBIs

For all other rules, see below:

To form the plural of an abbreviation, a number, or a capital letter used as a noun, simply add a lowercase ''s'' to the end. Apostrophes following decades and single letters are also common.
* A group of MPs
* The roaring 20s
* Mind your Ps and Qs

To indicate the plural of the abbreviation or symbol of a unit of measure, the same form is used as in the singular.
* 1&amp;nbsp;lb or 20&amp;nbsp;lb
* 1&amp;nbsp;ft or 16&amp;nbsp;ft
* 1 min or 45 min

When an abbreviation contains more than one full point, ''Hart's Rules'' recommends putting the ''s'' after the final one.
* Ph.D.s
* M.Phil.s
* the d.t.s
However, subject to any house style or consistency requirement, the same plurals may be rendered less formally as:
* PhDs
* MPhils
* the DTs. (This is the recommended form in the ''New Oxford Dictionary for Writers and Editors''.)

According to ''Hart's Rules'', an apostrophe may be used in rare cases where clarity calls for it, for example when letters or symbols are referred to as objects.
* The x's of the equation
* Dot the i's and cross the t's
However, the apostrophe can be dispensed with if the items are set in italics or quotes:
* The ''x''s of the equation
* Dot the 'i's and cross the 't's

In Latin, and continuing to the derivative forms in European languages as well as English, single-letter abbreviations had the plural being a doubling of the letter for note-taking. Most of these deal with writing and publishing. A few longer abbreviations use this as well.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
!Singular abbreviation
!Word/phrase
!Plural abbreviation
!Discipline
|-
|d.
| didot
|dd.
| typography
|-
|f.
| following line or page
|ff.
|notes
|-
|F.
| folio
|Ff.
|literature
|-
|h.
| hand
|hh.
| horse height
|-
|J.
| Justice
|JJ.
|law (job title)
|-
|l.
| line
|ll.
|notes
|-
|MS
| manuscript
|MSS
|notes
|-
|op.
| opus (plural: opera)
|opp.
|notes
|-
|p.
|page
|pp.
|notes
|-
|Q.
| quarto
|Qq.
|literature
|-
|s. (or §)
|section
|ss. (or §§)
|notes
|-
|v.
|volume
|vv.
|notes
|}

=== Conventions followed by publications and newspapers ===

==== United States ====

Publications based in the U.S. tend to follow the style guides of ''[[The Chicago Manual of Style]]'' and the [[Associated Press]].{{Verify source|date=May 2008}} The U.S. Government follows a style guide published by the [[U.S. Government Printing Office]]. The [[National Institute of Standards and Technology]] sets the style for abbreviations of units.

==== United Kingdom ====

Many British publications follow some of these guidelines in abbreviation:
* For the sake of convenience, many British publications, including the [[BBC]] and ''[[The Guardian]]'', have completely done away with the use of full stops or periods in all abbreviations. These include:
** Social titles, e.g. Ms or Mr (though these would usually have not had full stops—see above) Capt, Prof, ''etc.;''
** Two-letter abbreviations for countries (''&quot;US&quot;'', not ''&quot;U.S.&quot;'');
** Abbreviations beyond three letters (full caps for all except initialisms{{clarify|date=November 2015}});
** Words seldom abbreviated with lower case letters (''&quot;PR&quot;'', instead of ''&quot;p.r.&quot;'', or ''&quot;pr&quot;'')
** Names (''&quot;FW de Klerk&quot;'', ''&quot;GB Whiteley&quot;'', ''&quot;Park JS&quot;''). A notable exception is ''[[The Economist]]'' which writes ''&quot;Mr F. W. de Klerk&quot;''.
** Scientific units (see Measurement below).
* Acronyms are often referred to with only the first letter of the abbreviation capitalized. For instance, the [[North Atlantic Treaty Organisation]] can be abbreviated as ''&quot;Nato&quot;'' or ''&quot;NATO&quot;'', and [[Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome]] as ''&quot;Sars&quot;'' or ''&quot;SARS&quot;'' (compare with ''&quot;[[laser]]&quot;'' which has made the full transition to an English word and is rarely capitalised at all).
* Initialisms are always written in capitals; for example the ''&quot;British Broadcasting Corporation&quot;'' is abbreviated to ''&quot;BBC&quot;'', never ''&quot;Bbc&quot;''. An initialism is similar to acronym but is not pronounced as a word.
* When abbreviating scientific units, no space is added between the number and unit (&lt;nowiki&gt;100mph, 100m, 10cm, 10°C&lt;/nowiki&gt;). (This is contrary to the SI standard; see below.)

==== Miscellaneous and general rules ====

* A doubled letter appears in abbreviations of some Welsh names, as in [[Welsh language|Welsh]] the double &quot;l&quot; is a separate sound: &quot;Ll. George&quot; for (British prime minister) [[David Lloyd George]].
* Some titles, such as &quot;Reverend&quot; and &quot;Honourable&quot;, are spelt out when preceded by &quot;the&quot;, rather than as &quot;Rev.&quot; or &quot;Hon.&quot; respectively. This is true for most British publications, and some in the United States.
* A repeatedly used abbreviation should be spelt out for identification on its first occurrence in a written or spoken passage.&lt;ref&gt;[[Gary Blake]] and [[Robert W. Bly]], ''The Elements of Technical Writing'', pg. 53. New York City: Macmillan Publishers, 1993. {{ISBN|0020130856}}&lt;/ref&gt; Abbreviations likely to be unfamiliar to many readers should be avoided.

== Measurement shorthand—symbol or abbreviation ==
[[File:PRC Expressway RoadSign Distances.jpg|thumb|200px|Road sign in China—&quot;km&quot; is a symbol, not an abbreviation, as it is not a contraction of a Chinese word]]

Writers often use shorthand to denote units of measure. Such shorthand can be an abbreviation, such as &quot;in&quot; for &quot;[[inch]]&quot; or can be a symbol such as &quot;km&quot; for &quot;[[kilometre]]/kilometer&quot;.

The shorthand &quot;in&quot; applies to English only—in [[Afrikaans language|Afrikaans]] for example, the shorthand &quot;dm&quot; is used for the equivalent Afrikaans word &quot;duim&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
| title = Woordeboek/Dictionary; Afrikaans-English / Engels-Afrikaans
| editor = Abel Coetzee
| publisher = Collins
| year = 1969
| oclc = 29232187
| location = Glasgow and Johannesburg}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since both &quot;in&quot; and &quot;dm&quot; are contractions of the same word, but in different languages, they are abbreviations. A symbol on the other hand, defined as &quot;Mark or character taken as the conventional sign of some object or idea or process&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|title = Oxford Concise Dictionary
|publisher = Oxford University Press
|year = 1964}}&lt;/ref&gt; applies the appropriate shorthand by ''substitution'' rather than by ''contraction''. Since the shorthand for kilometre/kilometer (''[[:pt:Quilômetro|quilômetro]]'' in Portuguese or ''[[:el:Χιλιόμετρο|χιλιόμετρο]]'' in Greek) is &quot;km&quot; in both languages and the letter &quot;k&quot; does not appear in the expansion of either translation, &quot;km&quot; is a symbol as it is a substitution rather than a contraction. It is a [[logogram]] rather than an abbreviation.

In the [[International System of Units]] (SI) manual&lt;ref&gt;{{SIbrochure8th}}&lt;/ref&gt; the word &quot;symbol&quot; is used consistently to define the shorthand used to represent the various SI units of measure. The manual also [[International System of Units|defines the way in which units should be written]], the principal rules being:
*The conventions for upper and lower case letters must be observed—for example 1&amp;nbsp;MW (megawatts) is equal to 1,000,000,000&amp;nbsp;mW (milliwatts).
*No periods should be inserted between letters—for example &quot;m.s&quot; (which is an approximation of &quot;m·s&quot;, which correctly uses [[middle dot]]) is the symbol for &quot;metres multiplied by seconds&quot;, but &quot;ms&quot; is the symbol for milliseconds.
*No periods should follow the symbol unless the syntax of the sentence demands otherwise (for example a full stop at the end of a sentence).
*The singular and plural versions of the symbol are identical—not all languages use the letter &quot;s&quot; to denote a plural.

== Syllabic abbreviation ==
&lt;!--irony is this is linked from the MOS on how not to do it like this! - see [[MOS:CAPSACRS]]--&gt;
A syllabic abbreviation is usually formed from the initial syllables of several words, such as ''[[Interpol]]'' = '''''Inter'''national'' + '''''pol'''ice''. It is a variant of the acronym. Syllabic abbreviations are usually written using [[lower case]], sometimes starting with a [[capital letter]], and are always pronounced as words rather than letter by letter. Syllabic abbreviations should be distinguished from [[portmanteau]]s, which combine two words without necessarily taking whole syllables from each.

=== Usage ===

Syllabic abbreviations are not widely used in English. Some UK government ministries such as [[Ofcom]] ('''''Of'''fice of '''Com'''munications'') and [[Oftel]] ('''''Of'''fice of '''Tel'''ecommunications'') use this style.

New York City has various neighborhoods named by syllabic abbreviation, such as [[Tribeca]] ('''''Tri'''angle '''be'''low '''Ca'''nal Street'') and [[SoHo]] ('''''So'''uth of '''Ho'''uston Street''). This usage has spread into other American cities, giving [[South of Market, San Francisco|SoMa]], San Francisco ('''''So'''uth of '''Ma'''rket'') and [[LoDo, Denver]] ('''''Lo'''wer '''Do'''wntown''), among others.

Partially syllabic abbreviations are preferred by the US Navy, as it increases readability amidst the large number of initialisms that would otherwise have to fit into the same acronyms. Hence ''[[DESRON]] 6'' is used (in the full capital form) to mean &quot;Destroyer Squadron 6&quot;, while ''[[COMNAVAIRLANT]]'' would be &quot;Commander, Naval Air Force (in the) Atlantic.&quot;

==== Languages other than English====

Syllabic abbreviations prevailed in [[Nazi Germany]] and the [[Soviet Union]] for naming the plethora of new bureaucratic organisations. For example, ''[[Gestapo]]'' stands for '''''Ge'''heime '''Sta'''ats-'''Po'''lizei'', or &quot;secret state police&quot;. Similarly, Leninist organisations such as the ''[[Comintern]]'' (''Communist International'') and ''[[Komsomol]]'' ('''''Kom'''munisticheskii '''So'''yuz '''Mol'''odyozhi'', or &quot;Communist youth union&quot;) used Russian language syllabic abbreviations. This has given syllabic abbreviations negative connotations in some countries,{{citation needed|date=September 2012}} (as in Orwell's [[Newspeak]]), notwithstanding that such abbreviations were used in Germany even before the Nazis came to power, e.g., ''[[:de:Schupo|Schupo]]'' for ''Schutzpolizei'', and are still used, e.g. ''[[:de:Kripo|Kripo]]'' for ''[[:de:Kriminalpolizei|Kriminalpolizei]]''.

In the modern Russian language words like ''Minoborony'' (from '''Min'''isterstvo '''oborony''' — Ministry of Defence) and ''Minobrnauki'' (from '''Min'''isterstvo '''obr'''azovaniya i '''nauki''' — Ministry of Education and Science) are still commonly used.

Syllabic abbreviations were also typical for the [[German language]] used in the [[German Democratic Republic]], e.g. ''[[Stasi]]'' for '''''Sta'''ats'''si'''cherheit'' (&quot;state security&quot;, the secret police) or ''Vopo'' for ''Volkspolizist'' (&quot;people's policeman&quot;). Other uses are in company or product names such as [[Aldi]], from the name of the founder, Theo '''Al'''brecht, and the German word '''''Di'''skont'' (discount) or [[Haribo]], from the name of the founder and the headquarters of the company, '''Ha'''ns '''Ri'''egl '''Bo'''nn.

Syllabic abbreviations are more common in Spanish; examples abound in organization names such as [[Pemex]] for '''''Pe'''tróleos '''Mex'''icanos'' (&quot;Mexican Petroleums&quot;) or Fonafifo for '''''Fo'''ndo '''Na'''cional de '''Fi'''nancimiento '''Fo'''restal'' (National Forestry Financing Fund).

In Southeast Asian languages, especially in [[Malay languages]], syllabic abbreviations are also common; examples include [[Petronas]] (for '''''Petro'''liam '''Nas'''ional'', &quot;National Petroleum&quot;), its Indonesian equivalent [[Pertamina]] (from its original name '''''Per'''usahaan Per'''ta'''mbangan '''Mi'''nyak dan Gas Bumi '''N'''eg'''a'''ra'', &quot;State Oil and Natural Gas Mining Company&quot;), and [[Ministry of Transportation (Indonesia)|Kemenhub]] (from '''''Kemen'''terian Per'''hub'''ungan'', &quot;Ministry of Transportation&quot;)

East Asian languages whose writing systems use [[Chinese characters]] form abbreviations similarly by using key Chinese characters from a term or phrase. For example, in Japanese the term for the [[United Nations]], ''kokusai rengō'' (国際連合) is often abbreviated to ''kokuren'' (国連). (Such abbreviations are called [[:ja:略語|ryakugo]] (略語) in Japanese; see also [[Japanese abbreviated and contracted words]]). The syllabic abbreviation is frequently used for universities: for instance, ''Tōdai'' (東大) for ''Tōkyō daigaku'' (東京大学, [[University of Tokyo]]) and is used similarly in Chinese: ''Běidà'' (北大) for ''Běijīng Dàxué'' (北京大学, [[Peking University]]). The English phrase &quot;[[:wikt:gung ho|Gung ho]]&quot; originated as a Chinese abbreviation.

== See also ==
===Lists===
* [[List of abbreviations used in medical prescriptions]]
* [[List of abbreviations in photography]]
* [[List of acronyms]]
* [[List of classical abbreviations]]
* [[List of medieval abbreviations]]
* [[Wiktionary:Wiktionary:Abbreviations in Webster|The abbreviations used in the 1913 edition of Webster's dictionary]]

===Synonyms etc.===
* [[Abbreviation (music)]]
* [[Clipping (morphology)]]
* [[Gramogram]]
* [[SMS language]]
* [[Numeronym]]
* [[Neologism]]
* [[Unicode alias names and abbreviations]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Wiktionary|abbreviation}}
{{Wikisource1911Enc|Abbreviation}}
*{{Commonscatinline}}
*{{dmoz|Reference/Dictionaries/Acronyms/|Acronyms}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Abbreviations| ]]</text>
      <sha1>fysponvwvlthsk773dq5sj1amrzarxb</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
