  <page>
    <title>The Ashes</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1132</id>
    <revision>
      <id>937865955</id>
      <parentid>937865489</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-27T18:23:03Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ghmyrtle</username>
        <id>1698793</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>reverting - unsourced and mis-spelled</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{about|the Ashes in men's cricket|the women's equivalent|The Women's Ashes|other uses}}
{{EngvarB|date=March 2014}}{{Use dmy dates|date=March 2014}}
{{Infobox cricket tournament main
| name = The Ashes
| image = Ashes Urn.jpg
| caption = [[The Ashes urn]], made of [[terracotta]] and about 15 cm (6 inches) tall, is reputed to contain the ashes of a burnt [[Bail (cricket)|cricket bail]].
| country = {{cr|AUS}}&lt;br&gt;{{cr|ENG}}
| administrator = [[International Cricket Council]]
| cricket format = [[Test cricket]]
| first = [[English cricket team in Australia in 1882–83|1882–83]] &lt;small&gt;([[Australia]])&lt;/small&gt;
| last = [[2019 Ashes series|2019]] &lt;small&gt;([[England]])&lt;/small&gt;
| next = [[2021–22 Ashes series|2021–22]] &lt;small&gt;([[Australia]])&lt;/small&gt;
| tournament format = 5-match series
| participants = 2
| trophyholder = {{cr|AUS}}
| most successful = {{cr|AUS}} (33 series wins)
| most runs = {{flagicon|AUS}} [[Donald Bradman|Sir Donald Bradman]] (5,028)
| most wickets = {{flagicon|AUS}} [[Shane Warne]] (195)
| current =
}}
'''The Ashes''' is a [[Test cricket]] series played between [[England cricket team|England]] and  [[Australia national cricket team|Australia]]. The Ashes are regarded as being held by the team that most recently won the Test series. If the test series is drawn, the team that currently holds the Ashes retains the trophy. The term originated in a satirical obituary published in a British newspaper, ''[[The Sporting Times]]'', immediately after Australia's [[History of Test cricket from 1877 to 1883#Australia win in England 1882|1882 victory]] at [[The Oval]], its first Test win on English soil. The obituary stated that English cricket had died, and &quot;the body will be cremated and the ashes taken to Australia&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author=Wendy Lewis | author-link=Wendy Lewis | author2=Simon Balderstone | author3=John Bowan | last-author-amp=yes | title=Events That Shaped Australia | page=75 | publisher=New Holland | year=2006 | isbn=978-1-74110-492-9 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The mythical ashes immediately became associated with the [[History of Test cricket from 1877 to 1883#Bligh reclaims the Ashes 1882/3|1882–83 series played in Australia]], before which the English captain [[Ivo Bligh, 8th Earl of Darnley|Ivo Bligh]] had vowed to &quot;regain those ashes&quot;. The English media therefore dubbed the tour ''the quest to regain the Ashes''.

After England had won two of the three Tests on the tour, a small urn was presented to Bligh by a group of [[Melbourne]] women including [[Florence Bligh, Countess of Darnley|Florence Morphy]], whom Bligh married within a year.&lt;ref name=events&gt;[http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article63185850 Summary of Events] ''[[The Illustrated Australian News]]'', 20 February 1884, (foot of column 2) at [[National Library of Australia#Trove|Trove]]&lt;/ref&gt; The contents of the urn are reputed to be the ashes of a wooden [[bail (cricket)|bail]], and were humorously described as &quot;the ashes of Australian cricket&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article12673335 Cricket] ''[[The Mercury (Hobart)|Hobart Mercury]]'', 4 June 1908, p.8, at [[National Library of Australia#Trove|Trove]]&lt;/ref&gt; It is not clear whether that &quot;tiny silver urn&quot; is the same as the small terracotta urn given to the [[Marylebone Cricket Club|MCC]] by Bligh's widow after his death in 1927.

[[The Ashes urn|The urn]] has never been the official trophy of the Ashes series, having been a personal gift to Bligh.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Ashes History|url=http://www.lords.org/history/mcc-history/the-ashes|publisher=Lords|access-date=21 December 2018|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20181009142619/https://www.lords.org/history/mcc-history/the-ashes/|archive-date=9 October 2018|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, [[replica]]s of the urn are often held aloft by victorious teams as a symbol of their victory in an Ashes series. Since the [[English cricket team in Australia in 1998–99|1998–99 Ashes series]], a [[Waterford Crystal]] representation of the Ashes urn (called the Ashes Trophy) has been presented to the winners of an Ashes series as the official trophy of that series. Irrespective of which side holds the tournament, the urn remains in the MCC Museum at [[Lord's]]; it has however been taken to Australia to be put on touring display on two occasions: as part of the [[Australian Bicentenary]] celebrations in 1988, and to accompany the [[English cricket team in Australia in 2006–07|Ashes series in 2006–07]].

An Ashes series is traditionally of five Tests, hosted in turn by England and Australia at least once every two years. There have been 71 Ashes series: Australia have won 33, England 32 and six series have been drawn.

==1882 origins==
{{main|Australian cricket team in England in 1882}}
[[File:Ranji 1897 page 143 F. R. Spofforth, the demon bowler.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Fred Spofforth]], &quot;The Demon Bowler&quot;, was instrumental in Australia's 1882 victory over England with 14 wickets for 90.]]
The first [[Test cricket|Test match]] between England and Australia was played in [[Melbourne]], Australia, [[English cricket team in Australia and New Zealand in 1876–77|in 1877]], though the Ashes legend started later, after the ninth Test, played in 1882. On their [[Australian cricket team in England and the United States in 1882|tour of England]] that year the Australians played just one Test, at [[the Oval]] in London. It was a low-scoring affair on a difficult [[Cricket pitch|wicket]].&lt;ref&gt;Fred Spofforth, however, contended that, the fourth innings aside, it played perfectly well.&lt;/ref&gt; Australia made a mere 63 runs in its first [[innings]], and England, led by [[A. N. Hornby]], took a 38-run lead with a total of 101. In its second innings, Australia, boosted by a spectacular 55 runs off 60 deliveries from [[Hugh Massie]], managed 122, which left England only 85 runs to win. The Australians were greatly demoralised by the manner of their second-innings collapse, but fast bowler [[Fred Spofforth]], spurred on by the [[gamesmanship]] of his opponents, in particular [[W. G. Grace]], refused to give in. &quot;This thing can be done,&quot; he declared. Spofforth went on to devastate the English batting, taking his final four wickets for only two runs to leave England just eight runs short of victory.

When [[Ted Peate]], England's last batsman, came to the crease, his side needed just ten runs to win, but Peate managed only two before he was bowled by [[Harry Boyle (cricketer)|Harry Boyle]]. An astonished Oval crowd fell silent, struggling to believe that England could possibly have lost to a colony on home soil. When it finally sank in, the crowd swarmed onto the field, cheering loudly and chairing Boyle and Spofforth to the pavilion.

When Peate returned to the pavilion he was reprimanded by his captain for not allowing his partner, [[Charles Studd]] (one of the best batsman in England, having already hit two centuries that season against the colonists), to get the runs. Peate humorously replied, &quot;I had no confidence in Mr Studd, sir, so thought I had better do my best.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news
|first=Jack
|last=Worrall
|url=http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article83580262
|title=A Great Bowlers' Victory
|page=11 
|newspaper=[[Daily News (Perth, Western Australia)|Daily News]] 
|location=Perth, WA |date=23 August 1930 
|accessdate=25 August 2013
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

The momentous defeat was widely recorded in the British press, which praised the Australians for their plentiful &quot;pluck&quot; and berated the Englishmen for their lack thereof. A celebrated poem appeared in ''[[Punch (magazine)|Punch]]'' on Saturday, 9 September. The first verse, quoted most frequently, reads:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;poem&gt;
Well done, [[wikt:cornstalk|Cornstalks]]! Whipt us
Fair and square,
Was it luck that tript us?
Was it scare?
Kangaroo Land's 'Demon', or our own
Want of 'devil', coolness, nerve, backbone?
&lt;/poem&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

On 31 August, in the [[C. W. Alcock|Charles Alcock]]-edited magazine ''Cricket: A Weekly Record of The Game'', there appeared a mock obituary:

{{poemquote|
SACRED TO THE MEMORY
OF
ENGLAND'S SUPREMACY IN THE
CRICKET-FIELD
WHICH EXPIRED
ON THE 29TH DAY OF AUGUST, AT THE OVAL
&quot;ITS END WAS PEATE&quot;
}}

[[File:DeathofEnglishCricket.jpg|thumb|The death notice that appeared in ''[[The Sporting Times]]'']]
On 2 September a more celebrated mock obituary, written by [[Reginald Shirley Brooks]], appeared in ''[[The Sporting Times]]''. It read:

{{poemquote|
In Affectionate Remembrance
of
ENGLISH CRICKET,
which died at the Oval
on
29 August 1882,
Deeply lamented by a large circle of sorrowing
friends and acquaintances

R.I.P.

N.B.—The body will be cremated and the
ashes taken to Australia.
}}

[[Ivo Bligh, 8th Earl of Darnley|Ivo Bligh]] promised that on [[English cricket team in Australia in 1882–83|1882–83 tour of Australia]], he would, as England's captain, &quot;recover those Ashes&quot;. He spoke of them several times over the course of the tour, and the Australian media quickly caught on. The three-match series resulted in a two-one win to England, notwithstanding a fourth match, won by the Australians, whose status remains a matter of ardent dispute.{{Citation needed|date=July 2013}}

In the 20 years following Bligh's campaign the term &quot;the Ashes&quot; largely disappeared from public use. There is no indication that this was the accepted name for the series, at least not in England. The term became popular again in Australia first, when [[George Giffen]], in his memoirs (''With Bat and Ball'', 1899), used the term as if it were well known.&lt;ref&gt;Gibson, A., ''Cricket Captains of England'', p. 26.&lt;/ref&gt;

The true and global revitalisation of interest in the concept dates from 1903, when [[Plum Warner|Pelham Warner]] took a team to Australia with the promise that he would regain &quot;the ashes&quot;. As had been the case on Bligh's tour 20 years before, the Australian media latched fervently onto the term and, this time, it stuck. Having fulfilled his promise, Warner published a book entitled ''How We Recovered the Ashes''. Although the origins of the term are not referred to in the text, the title served (along with the general hype created in Australia) to revive public interest in the legend. The first mention of &quot;the Ashes&quot; in [[Wisden Cricketers' Almanack]] occurs in 1905, while ''Wisden'''s first account of the legend is in the 1922 edition.

==Urn==
{{Main|The Ashes urn}}
[[File:Ashes Urn 1921.jpg|right|thumb|The earliest published photo of [[the Ashes urn]], from ''[[The Illustrated London News]]'', 1921]]
[[File:Rupertswood mansion side angle shot.jpg|thumb|[[Rupertswood]] outside Melbourne, where the urn was presented to Bligh]]
As it took many years for the name &quot;The Ashes&quot; to be given to ongoing series between England and Australia, there was no concept of there being a representation of the ashes being presented to the winners. As late as 1925 the following verse appeared in ''The Cricketers Annual'':

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;poem&gt;
So here's to Chapman, Hendren and Hobbs,
Gilligan, Woolley and Hearne
May they bring back to the Motherland,
The ashes which have no urn!
&lt;/poem&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Nevertheless, several attempts had been made to embody the Ashes in a physical memorial. Examples include one presented to Warner in 1904, another to Australian captain M. A. Noble in 1909, and another to Australian captain W. M. Woodfull in 1934.

The oldest, and the one to enjoy enduring fame, was the one presented to Bligh, later Lord Darnley, during the 1882–83 tour. The precise nature of the origin of [[The Ashes urn|this urn]] is matter of dispute. Based on a statement by Darnley in 1894, it was believed that a group of [[Victoria (Australia)|Victorian]] ladies, including Darnley's later wife [[Florence Bligh, Countess of Darnley|Florence Morphy]], made the presentation after the victory in the Third Test in 1883. More recent researchers, in particular Ronald Willis&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book| first=Ronald | last=Willis | title=Cricket's Biggest Mystery: The Ashes | isbn=0-7270-1768-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Joy Munns&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book| first=Joy | last=Munns | title=Beyond Reasonable Doubt: The birthplace of the Ashes | isbn=0-646-22153-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; have studied the tour in detail and concluded that the presentation was made after a private cricket match played over Christmas 1882 when the English team were guests of [[Sir William John Clarke|Sir William Clarke]], at his property &quot;[[Rupertswood]]&quot;, in [[Sunbury, Victoria]]. This was before the matches had started. The prime evidence for this theory was provided by a descendant of Clarke.

In August 1926 Ivo Bligh (now Lord Darnley) displayed the Ashes urn at the ''[[Morning Post]]'' Decorative Art Exhibition held in the Central Hall, Westminster. He made the following statement about how he was given the urn:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article58247421?searchTerm=darnley%20cricket%20ashes&amp;searchLimits= |title=Sunday Times (Perth) 15 August 1926 page 9S. Online Reference |publisher=Trove.nla.gov.au |date=15 August 1926 |accessdate=22 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|When in the autumn the English Eleven went to Australia it was said that they had come to Australia to &quot;fetch&quot; the ashes. England won two out of the three matches played against Murdoch's Australian Eleven, and after the third match some Melbourne ladies put some ashes into a small urn and gave them to me as captain of the English Eleven.}}

A more detailed account of how the Ashes were given to Ivo Bligh was outlined by his wife, the Countess of Darnley, in 1930 during a speech at a cricket luncheon. Her speech was reported by the London Times as follows:&lt;ref&gt;The Times (London), 27 June 1930. page 7.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|In 1882, she said, it was first spoken of when the Sporting Times, after the Australians had thoroughly beaten the English at the Oval, wrote an obituary in affectionate memory of English cricket &quot;whose demise was deeply lamented and the body would be cremated and taken to Australia&quot;. Her husband, then Ivo Bligh, took a team to Australia in the following year. Punch had a poem containing the words &quot;When Ivo comes back with the urn&quot; and when Ivo Bligh wiped out the defeat Lady Clarke, wife of Sir W. J. Clarke, who entertained the English so lavishly, found a little wooden urn, burnt a bail, put the ashes in the urn, and wrapping it in a red velvet bag, put it into her husband's (Ivo Bligh's) hands. He had always regarded it as a great treasure.}}

There is another statement which is not totally clear made by Lord Darnley in 1921 about the timing of the presentation of the urn. He was interviewed in his home at Cobham Hall by Montague Grover and the report of this interview was as follows:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article66512851?searchTerm=%22cobham%20hall%22%20urn&amp;searchLimits=l-decade=192 |title=Geraldton Guardian 15 February 1921, page 1. Online reference |publisher=Trove.nla.gov.au |date=15 February 1921 |accessdate=22 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|This urn was presented to Lord Darnley by some ladies of Melbourne after the final defeat of his team, and before he returned with the members to England.}}

He made a similar statement in 1926. The report of this statement in the Brisbane Courier was as follows:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article21053463?searchTerm=darnley%20ashes%20urn&amp;searchLimits=l-decade=192|title=Brisbane Courier, 9 June 1926, page 7. Online reference |publisher=Trove.nla.gov.au |date=9 June 1926 |accessdate=22 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|The proudest possession of Lord Darnley is an earthenware urn containing the ashes which were presented to him by Melbourne residents when he captained the Englishmen in 1882. Though the team did not win, the urn containing the ashes was sent to him just before leaving Melbourne.}}

The contents of the urn are also problematic; they were variously reported to be the remains of a stump, bail or the outer casing of a ball, but in 1998 Darnley's 82-year-old daughter-in-law said they were the remains of her mother-in-law's veil, casting a further layer of doubt on the matter. However, during the tour of Australia in 2006/7, the MCC official accompanying the urn said the veil legend had been discounted, and it was now &quot;95% certain&quot; that the urn contains the ashes of a cricket bail. Speaking on Channel Nine TV on 25 November 2006, he said x-rays of the urn had shown the pedestal and handles were cracked, and repair work had to be carried out. The urn is made of [[terracotta]] and is about {{convert|6|in|mm}} tall and may originally have been a perfume jar.

[[File:Ashes song.jpg|thumb|The full version of the song from the ''[[Melbourne Punch]]'', the fourth verse of which is pasted onto the urn]]
A label containing a six-line verse is pasted on the urn. This is the fourth verse of a song-lyric published in the ''[[Melbourne Punch]]'' on 1 February 1883:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;poem&gt;
When [[Ivo Bligh, 8th Earl of Darnley|Ivo]] goes back with the urn, the urn;
[[Studd brothers|Studds]], [[A G Steel|Steel]], [[Walter Read|Read]] and [[Edward Tylecote|Tylecote]] return, return;
The [[wikt:make the welkin ring|welkin]] will ring loud,
The great crowd will feel proud,
Seeing [[Dick Barlow|Barlow]] and [[Billy Bates|Bates]] with the urn, the urn;
And the rest coming home with the urn.
&lt;/poem&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In February 1883, just before the disputed Fourth Test, a velvet bag made by Mrs Ann Fletcher, the daughter of Joseph Hines Clarke and Marion Wright, both of [[Dublin]], was given to Bligh to contain the urn. During Darnley's lifetime there was little public knowledge of the urn, and no record of a published photograph exists before 1921.  ''[[The Illustrated London News]]'' published this photo in January 1921 (shown above). When Darnley died in 1927 his widow presented the urn to the [[Marylebone Cricket Club]] and that was the key event in establishing the urn as the physical embodiment of the legendary ashes. MCC first displayed the urn in the Long Room at [[Lord's]] and since 1953 in the MCC Cricket Museum at the ground. MCC's wish for it to be seen by as wide a range of cricket enthusiasts as possible has led to its being mistaken for an official trophy. It is in fact a private memento, and for this reason it is never awarded to either England or Australia, but is kept permanently in the MCC Cricket Museum where it can be seen together with the specially made red and gold velvet bag and the scorecard of the 1882 match.

Because the urn itself is so delicate, it has been allowed to travel to Australia only twice. The first occasion was in 1988 for a museum tour as part of the [[Australian Bicentenary]] celebrations; the second was for the 2006/7 Ashes series.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/sport1/hi/cricket/6052544.stm | title=Ashes urn heads to Australia |work=BBC Sport  | date=15 October 2006 | accessdate=8 November 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; The urn arrived on 17 October 2006, going on display at the [[Museum of Sydney]]. It then toured to other states, with the final appearance at the Tasmanian Museum and Art Gallery on 21 January 2007.

In the 1990s, given Australia's long dominance of the Ashes and the popular acceptance of the Darnley urn as &quot;the Ashes&quot;, the idea was mooted that the victorious team should be awarded the urn as a trophy and allowed to retain it until the next series. As its condition is fragile and it is a prized exhibit at the MCC Cricket Museum, the MCC would not agree. Furthermore, in 2002, Bligh's great-great-grandson Lord Clifton, the heir-apparent to the [[Earl of Darnley|Earldom of Darnley]], argued that the Ashes urn should not be returned to Australia because it belonged to his family and was given to the MCC only for safe keeping.

As a compromise, the MCC commissioned a larger replica of the urn in [[Waterford Crystal]], known as the Ashes Trophy, to award to the winning team of each series starting with the [[English cricket team in Australia in 1998–99|1998–99 Ashes]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lords.org/news/our-blogs/the-cricket-history-blog/what-is-the-ashes-trophy/ &quot;What is the Ashes Trophy?&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130910205923/http://www.lords.org/news/our-blogs/the-cricket-history-blog/what-is-the-ashes-trophy |date=10 September 2013 }}, Lord's website. Retrieved 1 September 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; This did little to diminish the status of the Darnley urn as the most important icon in cricket, the symbol of this old and keenly fought contest.

==Series and matches==
{{more citations needed section|date=August 2011}}
:''See also: [[List of Ashes series]] for a full listing of all the Ashes series.''

===Quest to &quot;recover those ashes&quot;===
{{See also|History of Test cricket (to 1883)#The Ashes legend|l1=History of Test cricket (to 1883): The Ashes legend}}
[[File:Ivo Bligh Vanity Fair 7 April 1904.jpg|thumb|upright|The Honourable Ivo Bligh]]
Later in 1882, following the famous Australian victory at The Oval, [[Ivo Bligh, 8th Earl of Darnley|Bligh]] led an England team to Australia, as he said, to &quot;recover those ashes&quot;. Publicity surrounding the series was intense, and it was at some time during this series that the Ashes urn was crafted. Australia won the First Test by [[Result (cricket)|nine wickets]], but in the next two England were victorious. At the end of the Third Test, England were generally considered to have &quot;won back the Ashes&quot; 2–1. A fourth match was played, against a &quot;United Australian XI&quot;, which was arguably stronger than the Australian sides that had competed in the previous three matches; this game, however, is not generally considered part of the 1882–83 series. It &quot;is&quot; counted as a Test, but as a standalone. This match ended in a victory for Australia.

===1884 to 1896===
After Bligh's victory, there was an extended period of English dominance. The tours generally had fewer Tests in the 1880s and 1890s than people have grown accustomed to in more recent years, the first five-Test series taking place only in 1894–95. England lost only four Ashes Tests in the 1880s out of 23 played, and they won all the seven series contested.

There was more chopping and changing in the teams, given that there was no official board of selectors for each country (in 1887–88, two separate English teams were on tour in Australia) and popularity with the fans varied. The 1890s games were more closely fought, Australia taking its first series win since 1882 with a 2–1 victory in 1891–92. But England dominated, winning the next three series to 1896 despite continuing player disputes.

The [[English cricket team in Australia in 1894-95|1894–95]] series began in sensational fashion when England won the First Test at Sydney by just 10 runs having followed on. Australia had scored a massive 586 ([[Syd Gregory]] 201, [[George Giffen]] 161) and then dismissed England for 325. But England responded with 437 and then dramatically dismissed Australia for 166 with [[Bobby Peel]] taking 6 for 67. At the close of the second last day's play, Australia were 113–2, needing only 64 more runs. But heavy rain fell overnight and next morning the two slow left-arm bowlers, Peel and [[Johnny Briggs (cricketer)|Johnny Briggs]], were all but unplayable. England went on to win the series 3–2 after it had been all square before the Final Test, which England won by 6 wickets. The English heroes were Peel, with 27 wickets in the series at an average of 26.70, and [[Tom Richardson (cricketer)|Tom Richardson]], with 32 at 26.53.

In 1896 England under the captaincy of [[W. G. Grace]] won the series 2–1, and this marked the end of England's longest period of Ashes dominance.

===1897 to 1902===
Australia resoundingly won the 1897–98 series by 4–1 under the captaincy of [[Harry Trott]]. His successor [[Joe Darling]] won the next three series in 1899, 1901–02 and the [[Australian cricket team in England in 1902|classic 1902 series]], which became one of the most famous in the history of Test cricket.

Five matches were played in 1902 but the first two were drawn after being hit by bad weather. In the First Test (the first played at [[Edgbaston Cricket Ground|Edgbaston]]), after scoring 376 England bowled out Australia for 36 ([[Wilfred Rhodes]] 7/17) and reduced them to 46–2 when they followed on. Australia won the Third and Fourth Tests at [[Bramall Lane]] and [[Old Trafford Cricket Ground|Old Trafford]] respectively. At Old Trafford, Australia won by just 3 runs after [[Victor Trumper]] had scored 104 on a &quot;bad wicket&quot;, reaching his hundred before lunch on the first day. England won the last Test at [[The Oval]] by one wicket. Chasing 263 to win, it slumped to 48–5 before [[Gilbert Jessop|Jessop's]] 104 gave them a chance. He reached his hundred in just 75 minutes. The last-wicket pair of [[George Herbert Hirst|George Hirst]] and Rhodes were required to score 15 runs for victory. When Rhodes joined him, Hirst reportedly said: &quot;We'll get them in singles, Wilfred.&quot; In fact, they scored thirteen singles and a two.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.espncricinfo.com/ci/content/story/152487.html|title=Wisden – The glorious uncertainty|author=|date=|website=espncricinfo.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The period of Darling's captaincy saw the emergence of outstanding Australian players such as Trumper, [[Warwick Armstrong]], [[James Kelly (cricketer)|James Kelly]], [[Monty Noble]], [[Clem Hill]], [[Hugh Trumble]] and [[Ernie Jones (Australian sportsman)|Ernie Jones]].

===Reviving the legend===
After what the [[Marylebone Cricket Club|MCC]] saw as the problems of the earlier professional and amateur series they decided to take control of organising tours themselves, and this led to the first MCC tour of Australia in 1903–04. England won it against the odds, and [[Plum Warner]], the England captain, wrote up his version of the tour in his book ''How We Recovered The Ashes''.&lt;ref&gt;[[Plum Warner]], ''How We Recovered The Ashes'', Longman, 1905&lt;/ref&gt; The title of this book revived the Ashes legend and it was after this that England v Australia series were customarily referred to as &quot;The Ashes&quot;.

===1905 to 1912===
England and Australia were evenly matched until the outbreak of the First World War in 1914. Five more series took place between 1905 and 1912. In 1905 England's captain [[Stanley Jackson]] not only won the series 2–0, but also won the toss in all five matches and headed both the batting and the bowling averages. Monty Noble led Australia to victory in both 1907–08 and 1909. Then England won in 1911–12 by four matches to one. [[Jack Hobbs]] establishing himself as England's first-choice opening batsman with three centuries, while [[Frank Foster (cricketer)|Frank Foster]] (32 wickets at 21.62) and [[Sydney Barnes]] (34 wickets at 22.88) formed a formidable bowling partnership.

England retained the Ashes when it won the [[1912 Triangular Tournament]], which also featured [[South Africa national cricket team|South Africa]]. The Australian touring party had been severely weakened by a [[Big Six cricket dispute of 1912|dispute]] between the board and players that caused [[Clem Hill]], [[Victor Trumper]], Warwick Armstrong, [[Tibby Cotter]], [[Sammy Carter]] and [[Vernon Ransford]] to be omitted.&lt;ref&gt;Harte, pp. 251–256.&lt;/ref&gt;

===1920 to 1933===
After the war, Australia took firm control of both the Ashes and world cricket. For the first time, the tactic of using two express bowlers in tandem paid off as [[Jack Gregory (cricketer)|Jack Gregory]] and [[Ted McDonald]] crippled the English batting on a regular basis. Australia recorded overwhelming victories both in England and on home soil. It won the first eight matches in succession including a 5–0 [[whitewash (sport)|whitewash]] in [[English cricket team in Australia in 1920-21|1920–1921]] at the hands of Warwick Armstrong's team.

The ruthless and belligerent Armstrong led his team back to England in 1921 where his men lost only two games late in the tour to narrowly miss out of being the first team to complete a tour of England without defeat.

[[File:Herbert Sutcliffe 1924.jpg|thumb|left|[[Herbert Sutcliffe]] sweeps [[Arthur Mailey]] during the first Ashes Test in Sydney, 1924.]]
England won only one Test out of 15 from the end of the war until 1925.&lt;ref&gt;Harte, pp. 274–276.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=auslist&gt;{{cite web|url=http://stats.cricinfo.com/guru?sdb=team;team=AUS;class=testteam;filter=basic;opposition=0;notopposition=0;decade=0;homeaway=0;continent=0;country=0;notcountry=0;groundid=0;season=0;startdefault=1877-03-15;start=1877-03-15;enddefault=2007-11-20;end=2007-11-20;tourneyid=0;finals=0;daynight=0;toss=0;scheduledovers=0;scheduleddays=0;innings=0;followon=0;result=0;seriesresult=0;captainid=0;recent=;viewtype=resultlist;runslow=;runshigh=;wicketslow=;wicketshigh=;ballslow=;ballshigh=;overslow=;overshigh=;bpo=0;batevent=;conclow=;conchigh=;takenlow=;takenhigh=;ballsbowledlow=;ballsbowledhigh=;oversbowledlow=;oversbowledhigh=;bpobowled=0;bowlevent=;submit=1;.cgifields=viewtype |title=Statsguru – Australia – Tests – Results list |publisher=[[Cricinfo]] |accessdate=21 December 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a rain-hit series in 1926, England managed to eke out a 1–0 victory with a win in the final Test at The Oval. Because the series was at stake, the match was to be &quot;timeless&quot;, i.e., played to a finish. Australia had a narrow first innings lead of 22. Jack Hobbs and [[Herbert Sutcliffe]] took the score to 49–0 at the end of the second day, a lead of 27. Heavy rain fell overnight, and next day the pitch soon developed into a traditional sticky wicket. England seemed doomed to be bowled out cheaply and to lose the match. In spite of the very difficult batting conditions, however, Hobbs and Sutcliffe took their partnership to 172 before Hobbs was out for exactly 100. Sutcliffe went on to make 161 and England won the game comfortably.&lt;ref&gt;Harte, pp. 298–301.&lt;/ref&gt; Australian captain [[Herbie Collins]] was stripped of all captaincy positions down to club level, and some accused him of throwing the match.

Australia's ageing post-war team broke up after 1926, with Collins, [[Charlie Macartney]] and [[Warren Bardsley]] all departing, and Gregory breaking down at the start of the 1928–29 series.

Despite the debut of [[Donald Bradman]], the inexperienced Australians, led by [[Jack Ryder (cricketer)|Jack Ryder]], were heavily defeated, losing 4–1.&lt;ref&gt;Harte, pp. 312–316.&lt;/ref&gt; England had a very strong batting side, with [[Wally Hammond]] contributing 905 runs at an average of 113.12, and Hobbs, Sutcliffe and [[Patsy Hendren]] all scoring heavily; the bowling was more than adequate, without being outstanding.

In 1930, [[Bill Woodfull]] led an extremely inexperienced team to England.

Bradman fulfilled his promise in the 1930 series when he scored 974 runs at 139.14, which remains a world record Test series aggregate. A modest Bradman can be heard in a 1930 recording saying &quot;I have always endeavoured to do my best for the side, and the few centuries that have come my way have been achieved in the hope of winning matches. My one idea when going into bat was to make runs for Australia.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Don Bradman on australianscreen online&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://aso.gov.au/titles/spoken-word/1930-australian-xi-ashes/|title=Don Bradman in 'The 1930 Australian XI: Winners of the Ashes' |website=Aso.gov.au|accessdate=23 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[Headingley Cricket Ground|Headingley]] Test, he made 334, reaching 309* at the end of the first day, including a century before lunch. Bradman himself thought that his 254 in the preceding match, at [[Lord's]], was a better innings. England managed to stay in contention until the deciding final Test at The Oval, but yet another double hundred by Bradman, and 7/92 by [[Percy Hornibrook]] in England's second innings, enabled Australia to win by an innings and take the series 2–1. [[Clarrie Grimmett]]'s 29 wickets at 31.89 for Australia in this high-scoring series were also important.

Australia had one of the strongest batting line-ups ever in the early 1930s, with Bradman, [[Archie Jackson]], [[Stan McCabe]], [[Bill Woodfull]] and [[Bill Ponsford]]. It was the prospect of bowling at this line-up that caused England's 1932–33 captain [[Douglas Jardine]] to adopt the tactic of fast [[leg theory]], better known as [[Bodyline]].

[[File:4th Test Woodfull.jpg|right|thumb|[[Bill Woodfull]] evades a ball from [[Harold Larwood]] with [[Bodyline]] field settings.]]

Jardine instructed his [[fast bowling|fast bowlers]], most notably [[Harold Larwood]] and [[Bill Voce]], to bowl at the bodies of the Australian batsmen, with the goal of forcing them to defend their bodies with their bats, thus providing easy catches to a stacked [[leg side|leg-side]] field. Jardine insisted that the tactic was legitimate and called it &quot;leg theory&quot; but it was widely disparaged by its opponents, who dubbed it &quot;Bodyline&quot; (from &quot;on the line of the body&quot;). Although England decisively won the Ashes 4–1, Bodyline caused such a furore in Australia that diplomats had to intervene to prevent serious harm to Anglo-Australian relations, and the [[Marylebone Cricket Club|MCC]] eventually changed the [[Laws of cricket]] to curtail the number of leg side fielders.

Jardine's comment was: &quot;I've not travelled 6,000 miles to make friends. I'm here to win the Ashes&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/sport/more_sport/article2387560.ece | location=London | work=The Times | title=Top 50 British achievements | first=Patrick | last=Kidd | date=4 September 2007 | url-status=dead | archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080821160249/http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/sport/more_sport/article2387560.ece | archivedate=21 August 2008 | df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some of the Australians wanted to use Bodyline in retaliation, but Woodfull flatly refused. He famously told England manager [[Pelham Warner]], &quot;There are two teams out there. One is playing cricket; the other is making no attempt to do so&quot; after the latter had come into the Australian rooms to express sympathy for a Larwood bouncer had struck the Australian skipper in the heart and felled him.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book| author = Cashman| author2 = Franks| author3 = Maxwell| author4 = Sainsbury| author5 = Stoddart| author6 = Weaver| author7 = Webster | date = 1997 | title = The A-Z of Australian cricketers|pages = 322–323}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===1934 to 1953===
On the batting-friendly [[cricket pitch|wickets]] that prevailed in the late 1930s, most Tests up to the Second World War still gave results. It should be borne in mind that Tests in Australia prior to the war were all played to a finish. Many batting records were set in this period.

The 1934 Ashes series began with the notable absence of Larwood, Voce and Jardine. The MCC had made it clear, in light of the revelations of the bodyline series, that these players would not face Australia. The MCC, although it had earlier condoned and encouraged {{Citation needed|date=August 2007}} bodyline tactics in the 1932–33 series, laid the blame on Larwood when relations turned sour. Larwood was forced by the MCC to either apologise or be removed from the Test side. He went for the latter.

Australia recovered the Ashes in 1934 and held them until 1953, though no Test cricket was played during the Second World War.

As in 1930, the 1934 series was decided in the final Test at The Oval. Australia, batting first, posted a massive 701 in the first innings. Bradman (244) and Ponsford (266) were in record-breaking form with a partnership of 451 for the second wicket. England eventually faced a massive 707-run target for victory and failed, Australia winning the series 2–1.&lt;ref&gt;Harte, pp. 356–357.&lt;/ref&gt; This made Woodfull the only captain to regain the Ashes and he retired upon his return to Australia.

In 1936–37 Bradman succeeded Woodfull as Australian captain. He started badly, losing the first two Tests heavily after Australia were caught on [[sticky wicket]]s. However, the Australians fought back and Bradman won his first series in charge 3–2.

The 1938 series was a high-scoring affair with two high-scoring draws, resulting in a 1–1 result, Australia retaining the Ashes. After the first two matches ended in stalemate and the Third Test at Old Trafford never started due to rain. Australia then scraped home by five wickets inside three days in a low-scoring match at Headingley to retain the urn. In the timeless Fifth Test at The Oval, the highlight was [[Len Hutton]]'s then world-record score of 364 as England made 903-7 declared. Bradman and [[Jack Fingleton]] injured themselves during Hutton's marathon effort, and with only nine men, Australia fell to defeat by an innings and 579 runs,&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/sport2/hi/cricket/england/6109836.stm Classic Ashes clashes – 1938, The Oval] at [[BBC Sport]], 5 November 2006. Accessed 4 March 2006&lt;/ref&gt; the heaviest in Test history.

The Ashes resumed after the war when England toured in 1946–47 and, as in 1920–21, found that Australia had made the better post-war recovery. Still captained by Bradman and now featuring the potent new-ball partnership of [[Ray Lindwall]] and [[Keith Miller]], Australia was convincing 3–0 winners.

Aged 38 and having been unwell during the war, Bradman had been reluctant to play. He batted unconvincingly and reached 28 when he hit a ball to [[Jack Ikin]]; England believed it was a catch, but Bradman stood his ground, believing it to be a bump ball. The umpire ruled in the Australian captain's favour and he appeared to regain his fluency of yesteryear, scoring 187. Australia promptly seized the initiative, won the First Test convincingly and inaugurated a dominant post-war era. The controversy over the Ikin catch was one of the biggest disputes of the era.

In 1948 Australia set new standards, completely outplaying its hosts to win 4–0 with one draw. This [[Australian cricket team in England in 1948|Australian team]], led by Bradman, who turned 40 during his final tour of England, has gone down in history as ''The Invincibles''. Playing 34 matches on tour—three of which were not first-class—and including the five Tests, they remained unbeaten, winning 27 and drawing 7.

Bradman's men were greeted by packed crowds across the country, and records for Test attendances in England were set in the [[Second Test, 1948 Ashes series|Second]] and [[Fourth Test, 1948 Ashes series|Fourth Tests]] at Lord's and Headingley respectively. Before a record attendance of spectators at Headingley, Australia set a world record by chasing down 404 on the last day for a seven-wicket victory.

The 1948 series ended with one of the most poignant moments in cricket history, as Bradman played his final innings for Australia in the [[Fifth Test, 1948 Ashes series|Fifth Test]] at The Oval, needing to score only four runs to end with a career [[batting average (cricket)|batting average]] of exactly 100. However, Bradman made a second-ball duck, bowled by an [[Eric Hollies]] googly&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/sport2/hi/cricket/8036237.stm 1948 – Bradman's final innings duck] at [[BBC Sport]], 27 May 2009. Accessed 4 March 2015&lt;/ref&gt; that sent him into retirement with a career average of 99.94.

Bradman was succeeded as Australian captain by [[Lindsay Hassett]], who led the team to a 4–1 series victory in 1950–51. The series was not as one-sided as the number of wins suggest, with several tight matches.

The tide finally turned in 1953 when England won the final Test at The Oval to take the series 1–0, having narrowly avoided defeat in the preceding Test at Headingley. This was the beginning of one of the greatest periods in English cricket history with players such as captain Len Hutton, batsmen [[Denis Compton]], [[Peter May (cricketer)|Peter May]], [[Tom Graveney]], [[Colin Cowdrey]], bowlers [[Fred Trueman]], [[Brian Statham]], [[Alec Bedser]], [[Jim Laker]], [[Tony Lock]], wicket-keeper [[Godfrey Evans]] and all-rounder [[Trevor Bailey]].

===1954 to 1971===
[[File:Peter May.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Peter May (cricketer)|Peter May]] driving [[Bill Johnston (cricketer)|Bill Johnston]] on his way to a century at Sydney.]]
In [[English cricket team in Australia in 1954-55|1954–55]], Australia's batsmen had no answer to the pace of [[Frank Tyson]] and Statham. After winning the First Test by an innings after being controversially sent in by Hutton, Australia lost its way and England took a hat-trick of victories to win the series 3–1.&lt;ref&gt;Harte, pp. 435–437.&lt;/ref&gt;

A dramatic series in 1956 saw a record that will probably never be beaten: off-spinner [[Jim Laker]]'s monumental effort at [[Old Trafford Cricket Ground|Old Trafford]] when he bowled 68 of 191 overs to take 19 out of 20 possible Australian wickets in the Fourth Test.&lt;ref&gt;Harte, pp. 444–446.&lt;/ref&gt; It was Australia's second consecutive innings defeat in a wet summer, and the hosts were in strong positions in the two drawn Tests, in which half the playing time was washed out. Bradman rated the team that won the series 2–1 as England's best ever.

England's dominance was not to last. Australia won 4–0 in 1958–59, having found a high-quality spinner of their own in new skipper [[Richie Benaud]], who took 31 wickets in the five-Test series, and paceman [[Alan Keith Davidson|Alan Davidson]], who took 24 wickets at 19.00. The series was overshadowed by the furore over various Australian bowlers, most notably [[Ian Meckiff]], whom the English management and media accused of [[throwing (cricket)|illegally throwing]] Australia to victory.

In 1961 Australia won a hard-fought series 2–1, their first Ashes series win in England for 13 years.  After narrowly winning the Second Test at Lord's, dubbed &quot;The Battle of the Ridge&quot; because of a protrusion on the pitch that caused erratic bounce, Australia mounted a comeback on the final day of the Fourth Test at Old Trafford and sealed the series with [[Richie Benaud]] taking 6-70 during the English runchase.

The tempo of the play changed over the next four series in the 1960s, held in 1962–63, 1964, 1965–66 and 1968. The powerful array of bowlers that both countries boasted in the preceding decade moved into retirement, and their replacements were of lesser quality, making it more difficult to force a result. England failed to win any series during the 1960s, a period dominated by draws as teams found it more prudent to save face than risk losing. Of the 20 Tests played during the four series, Australia won four and England three. As they held the Ashes, Australia's captains [[Bob Simpson (cricketer)|Bob Simpson]] and [[Bill Lawry]] were happy to adopt safety-first tactics and their strategy of sedate batting saw many draws. During this period, spectator attendances dropped and media condemnation increased, but Simpson and Lawry flatly disregarded the public dissatisfaction.

It was in the 1960s that the bipolar dominance of England and Australia in world cricket was seriously challenged for the first time. West Indies defeated England twice in the mid-1960s and South Africa, in two series before they were banned for [[apartheid]], completely outplayed Australia 3–1 and 4–0. Australia had lost 2–1 during a tour of the West Indies in 1964–65, the first time it had lost a series to any team other than England.

In 1970–71, [[Ray Illingworth]] led England to a 2–0 win in Australia, mainly due to [[John Snow (cricketer)|John Snow]]'s fast bowling, and the prolific batting of [[Geoffrey Boycott]] and [[John Edrich]]. It was not until the last session of what was the 7th Test (one match having been abandoned without a ball bowled) that England's success was secured. Lawry was sacked after the Sixth Test after the selectors finally lost patience with Australia's lack of success and dour strategy. Lawry was not informed of the decision privately and heard his fate over the radio.&lt;ref&gt;Harte, pp. 526–530.&lt;/ref&gt;

===1972 to 1987===
The 1972 series finished 2–2, with England under Illingworth retaining the Ashes.&lt;ref&gt;Harte, pp. 538–540.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 1974–75 series, with the England team breaking up and their best batsman Geoff Boycott refusing to play, Australian pace bowlers [[Jeff Thomson]] and [[Dennis Lillee]] wreaked havoc. A 4–1 result was a fair reflection as England were left shell shocked.&lt;ref&gt;Harte, pp. 557–559.&lt;/ref&gt; England then lost the 1975 series 0–1, but at least restored some pride under new captain [[Tony Greig]].&lt;ref&gt;Harte, pp. 561–563.&lt;/ref&gt;

Australia won the 1977 Centenary Test&lt;ref&gt;Harte, pp. 580–581.&lt;/ref&gt; which was not an Ashes contest, but then a storm broke as [[Kerry Packer]] announced his intention to form [[World Series Cricket]].&lt;ref&gt;Harte, pp. 579–590&lt;/ref&gt; WSC affected all Test-playing nations but it weakened Australia especially as the bulk of its players had signed up with Packer; the Australian Cricket Board (ACB) would not select WSC-contracted players and an almost completely new Test team had to be formed. WSC came after an era during which the duopoly of Australian and English dominance dissipated; the Ashes had long been seen as a cricket world championship but the rise of the West Indies in the late 1970s challenged that view. The West Indies would go on to record resounding Test series wins over Australia and England and dominated world cricket until the 1990s.

With Greig having joined WSC, England appointed [[Mike Brearley]] as its captain and he enjoyed great success against Australia. Largely assisted by the return of Boycott, Brearley's men won the 1977 series 3–0 and then completed an overwhelming 5–1 series win against an Australian side missing its WSC players in 1978–79. [[Allan Border]] made his Test debut for Australia in 1978–79.

Brearley retired from Test cricket in 1979 and was succeeded by [[Ian Botham]], who started the [[Australian cricket team in England in 1981|1981 series]] as England captain, by which time the WSC split had ended. After Australia took a 1–0 lead in the first two Tests, Botham was forced to resign or was sacked (depending on the source). Brearley surprisingly agreed to be reappointed before the Third Test at Headingley. This was a remarkable match in which Australia looked certain to take a 2–0 series lead after it had forced England to follow-on 227 runs behind. England, despite being 135 for 7, produced a second innings total of 356, Botham scoring 149*. Chasing just 130, Australia were sensationally dismissed for 111, [[Bob Willis]] taking 8–43. It was the first time since 1894–95 that a team following on had won a Test match. Under Brearley's leadership, England went on to win the next two matches before a drawn final match at The Oval.&lt;ref&gt;Harte, pp. 627–628.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1982–83 Australia had [[Greg Chappell]] back from WSC as captain, while the England team was weakened by the enforced omission of their [[South African rebel tours|South African tour rebels]], particularly [[Graham Gooch]] and [[John Emburey]]. Australia went 2–0 up after three Tests, but England won the Fourth Test by 3 runs (after a 70-run last wicket stand) to set up the final decider, which was drawn.&lt;ref&gt;Harte, pp. 636–637.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1985 [[David Gower]]'s England team was strengthened by the return of Gooch and Emburey as well as the emergence at international level of [[Tim Robinson (cricketer)|Tim Robinson]] and [[Mike Gatting]]. Australia, now captained by [[Allan Border]], had itself been weakened by a rebel South African tour, the loss of [[Terry Alderman]] being a particular factor. England won 3–1.

Despite suffering heavy defeats against the West Indies during the 1980s, England continued to do well in the Ashes. Mike Gatting was the captain in 1986–87 but his team started badly and attracted some criticism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://content-aus.cricinfo.com/columns/content/story/268042.html | title=Can't bat, can't bowl, can't field | publisher=[[Cricinfo]] | last=Miller | first=Andrew |author2=Martin Williamson  | date=16 November 2006 | accessdate=8 November 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Then [[Chris Broad]] scored three hundreds in successive Tests and bowling successes from [[Graham Dilley]] and [[Gladstone Small]] meant England won the series 2–1.&lt;ref&gt;Harte, pp. 662–664.&lt;/ref&gt;

===1989 to 2003===
[[File:MCG99.jpg|right|thumb|[[Melbourne Cricket Ground]] Boxing Day Test 1998]]
The Australian team of 1989 was comparable to the great Australian teams of the past, and resoundingly defeated England 4–0.&lt;ref&gt;Harte, pp. 679–682.&lt;/ref&gt; Well led by [[Allan Border]], the team included the young cricketers [[Mark Taylor (cricketer)|Mark Taylor]], [[Merv Hughes]], [[David Boon]], [[Ian Healy]] and [[Steve Waugh]], who were all to prove long-serving and successful Ashes competitors. England, now led once again by [[David Gower]], suffered from injuries and poor form. During the Fourth Test news broke that prominent England players had agreed to take part in a &quot;rebel tour&quot; of South Africa the following winter; three of them ([[Tim Robinson (cricketer)|Tim Robinson]], [[Neil Foster]] and [[John Emburey]]) were playing in the match, and were subsequently dropped from the England side.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://content-www.cricinfo.com/wisdencricketer/content/story/139086.html|title=Rebels take a step too far (English rebel tour to South Africa, 1989)|first=Nick|last=Hoult|publisher=[[Cricinfo]]|date=July 2004|accessdate=22 October 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Australia reached a cricketing peak in the 1990s and early 2000s, coupled with a general decline in England's fortunes. After re-establishing its credibility in 1989, Australia underlined its superiority with victories in the 1990–91, 1993, 1994–95, 1997, 1998–99, 2001 and 2002–03 series, all by convincing margins.

Great Australian players in the early years included batsmen Border, Boon, Taylor and Steve Waugh. The captaincy passed from Border to Taylor in the mid-1990s and then to Steve Waugh before the 2001 series. In the latter part of the 1990s Waugh himself, along with his twin brother [[Mark Waugh|Mark]], scored heavily for Australia and fast bowlers [[Glenn McGrath]] and [[Jason Gillespie]] made a serious impact, especially the former. The wicketkeeper-batsman position was held by [[Ian Healy]] for most of the 1990s and by [[Adam Gilchrist]] from 2001 to 2006–07. In the 2000s, batsmen [[Justin Langer]], [[Damien Martyn]] and [[Matthew Hayden]] became noted players for Australia. But the most dominant Australian player was leg-spinner [[Shane Warne]], whose first delivery in Ashes cricket in 1993, to dismiss Mike Gatting, became known as the [[Ball of the Century]].

Australia's record between 1989 and 2005 had a significant impact on the statistics between the two sides. Before the 1989 series began, the win-loss ratio was almost even, with 87 test wins for Australia to England's 86, 74 tests having been drawn.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://stats.cricinfo.com/statsguru/engine/stats/index.html?class=1;filter=advanced;opposition=1;orderby=won;spanmax2=1+Apr+1989;spanval2=span;team=2;template=results;trophy=1;type=team |title=Team records &amp;#124; Test matches &amp;#124; Cricinfo Statsguru &amp;#124; ESPN Cricinfo |publisher=Stats.cricinfo.com |accessdate=22 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; By the 2005 series Australia's test wins had increased to 115 whereas England's had increased to only 93 (with 82 draws).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://stats.cricinfo.com/statsguru/engine/stats/index.html?class=1;filter=advanced;opposition=1;orderby=won;spanmax2=1+Apr+2005;spanval2=span;team=2;template=results;trophy=1;type=team |title=Team records &amp;#124; Test matches &amp;#124; Cricinfo Statsguru &amp;#124; ESPN Cricinfo |publisher=Stats.cricinfo.com |accessdate=22 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the period between 1989 and the beginning of the 2005 series, the two sides had played 43 times; Australia winning 28 times, England 7 times, with 8 draws. Only a single England victory had come in a match in which the Ashes were still at stake, namely the First Test of the 1997 series. All others were consolation victories when the Ashes had been secured by Australia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://stats.cricinfo.com/guru?sdb=team;team=AUS;class=testteam;filter=basic;opposition=ENG;notopposition=0;decade=0;homeaway=0;continent=0;country=0;notcountry=0;groundid=0;season=0;startdefault=1877-03-15;start=1877-03-15;enddefault=2005-03-29;end=2005-03-29;tourneyid=0;finals=0;daynight=0;toss=0;scheduledovers=0;scheduleddays=0;innings=0;followon=0;result=0;seriesresult=0;captainid=0;recent=;viewtype=series;runslow=;runshigh=;wicketslow=;wicketshigh=;ballslow=;ballshigh=;overslow=;overshigh=;bpo=0;batevent=;conclow=;conchigh=;takenlow=;takenhigh=;ballsbowledlow=;ballsbowledhigh=;oversbowledlow=;oversbowledhigh=;bpobowled=0;bowlevent=;submit=1;.cgifields=viewtype |title=Cricinfo – Statsguru – Australia – Tests – Series record |publisher=Stats.cricinfo.com |date=17 June 2008 |accessdate=22 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===2005 to 2015===
[[File:Trent Bridge, Flintoff century, 26 Aug 2005.jpg|left|thumb|[[Andrew Flintoff|Flintoff]] reaches 100 at [[Trent Bridge]] in 2005]]
England was undefeated in Test matches through the 2004 calendar year. This elevated them to second in the [[ICC Test Championship]]. Hopes that the [[2005 Ashes series]] would be closely fought proved well-founded, the series remaining undecided as the closing session of the final Test began. Experienced journalists including Richie Benaud rated the series as the most exciting in living memory. It has been compared with the great series of the distant past, such as 1894–95 and 1902.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://sport.y2u.co.uk/Cricket/Cricket_The_Ashes.htm|title=THE ASHES, a battle of wills between English and Australian Cricket|website=sport.y2u.co.uk|access-date=2017-01-16|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160104233724/http://sport.y2u.co.uk/Cricket/Cricket_The_Ashes.htm|archive-date=4 January 2016|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The First Test at [[Lord's]] was convincingly won by Australia, but in the remaining four matches the teams were evenly matched and England fought back to win the Second Test by 2 runs, the smallest winning margin in Ashes history, and the second-smallest in all Tests. The rain-affected Third Test ended with the last two Australian batsmen holding out for a draw; and England won the Fourth Test by three wickets after forcing Australia to [[follow-on]] for the first time in 191 Tests. A draw in the final Test gave England victory in an Ashes series for the first time in 18 years and their first Ashes victory at home since 1985.

Australia regained the Ashes on its home turf in the [[2006-07 Ashes series|2006–07 series]] with a convincing 5–0 victory, only the second time an Ashes series has been won by that margin. [[Glenn McGrath]], [[Shane Warne]] and [[Justin Langer]] retired from Test cricket after that series, while [[Damien Martyn]] retired during the series.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://content-usa.cricinfo.com/australia/content/player/6513.html|title=Damien Martyn|publisher=cricinfo}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Ashes 2010-11 Sydney Test final wicket.jpg|thumb|right|[[Chris Tremlett]] bowls [[Michael Beer (cricketer)|Michael Beer]] to complete England's 3–1 Ashes victory on 7 January 2011]]

The [[2009 Ashes series|2009 series]] began with a tense draw in the First Test at [[SWALEC Stadium]] in [[Cardiff]], with England's last-wicket batsmen [[James Anderson (cricketer)|James Anderson]] and [[Monty Panesar]] surviving 69 balls. England then achieved its first Ashes win at Lord's since 1934 to go 1–0 up. After a rain-affected draw at Edgbaston, the fourth match at Headingley was convincingly won by Australia by an innings and 80 runs to level the series. Finally, England won the Fifth Test at [[The Oval]] by a margin of 197 runs to regain the Ashes. [[Andrew Flintoff]] retired from Test cricket soon afterwards.

The [[2010–11 Ashes series|2010–11 series]] was played in Australia. The First Test at Brisbane ended in a draw, but England won the Second Test, at Adelaide, by an innings and 71 runs. Australia came back with a victory at Perth in the Third Test. In the Fourth Test at Melbourne Cricket Ground, England batting second scored 513 to defeat Australia (98 and 258) by an innings and 157 runs. This gave England an unbeatable 2–1 lead in the series and so it retained the Ashes. England went on to win the series 3–1, beating Australia by an innings and 83 runs at Sydney in the Fifth Test. Australia, captained by Michael Clarke, batted first on a cloudy day after winning the toss and were bowled out for 280. England made 644, their highest innings total since 1938. England then bowled Australia out again for 281. England's series victory was its most convincing for decades and its first on Australian soil for 24 years. The 2010–11 Ashes series was the only one in which a team had won three Tests by innings margins and it was the first time England had scored 500 or more four times in a single series.

Australia's build-up to the [[2013 Ashes series]] was far from ideal. [[Darren Lehmann]] took over as coach from [[Mickey Arthur]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.abc.net.au/news/2013-06-24/lehmann-named-australian-coach/4777030 Ashes 2013: Darren Lehmann replaces Mickey Arthur as Australia coach; Clarke steps down as selector] at [[ABC News (Australia)|ABC News]], 24 June 2013. Retrieved 24 June 2013&lt;/ref&gt; following a string of poor results. A batting line-up weakened by the previous year's retirements of former captain [[Ricky Ponting]] and [[Mike Hussey]], was also shorn of opener [[David Warner (cricketer)|David Warner]], who was suspended for the start of the series following an off-field incident.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Ashes 2013: David Warner set for southern Africa match practice |url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/sport/0/cricket/23261135 |work=BBC Sport |publisher=British Broadcasting Corporation |date=10 July 2013 |accessdate=11 July 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The tourists put those issues behind them to bowl England out for 215 after losing the toss in the First Test at Trent Bridge. In the face of high-class swing bowling from [[James Anderson (cricketer)|James Anderson]], who ended with 10 wickets in the match, Australia collapsed to 117–9. However, debutant 19-year-old [[Ashton Agar]] made a world-record 98 for a number 11 and [[Phillip Hughes|Phil Hughes]] an unbeaten 81 to secure a lead of 65. England's second-innings total of 375 set Australia a target of 311, against which it fell short by only 14 runs in a tense finish. In the Second Test, England beat Australia by 347 runs in a very one-sided contest. In the Third Test, held at a newly refurbished Old Trafford, Australia won the toss and elected to bat first. It amassed a commanding score of 527–7, led by captain Michael Clarke's 187. The pressure was then on the home side to avoid the follow-on. England scored 368 with a century for Kevin Pietersen. Australia's second innings score was 172–7 at the end of Day 4, characterised by batting order changes to achieve a fast run rate to allow enough time to bowl England out amid inclement weather forecasts. Australia declared overnight to post England a target of 332 to win. Contrary to expectations, play resumed with only a minor delay on Day 5, and with captain Alastair Cook being bowled out for 0 (his first duck in 26 innings as captain), Australia looked to be in with a significant chance of a win, keeping its series hopes alive. By lunch England were 37–3, but on resumption of play only 3 balls were bowled before rain stopped play. This rain persisted and, at 16:40, the captains shook hands and the match was declared a draw. With England 2–0 up with two Tests to play, England retained the Ashes on 5 August 2013.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Sheringham |first=Sam |url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/sport/0/cricket/23579840 |title=Ashes 2013: England retain Ashes as rain forces Old Trafford draw |work=BBC Sport |date=5 August 2013 |accessdate=17 August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the Fourth Test, England won the toss and batted first, putting on 238 runs, Australia took a narrow lead scoring 270 in its first innings. In the second innings England scored 330, Ian Bell top-scoring with 113. Needing only 298 runs to win Australia was in a strong position at 138/2, only 160 short with eight wickets in hand. Following a rain delay, Australia crashed to a 74-run defeat, losing all eight wickets for only 86 runs. England had taken 9 wickets in the final session of the fourth day. Stuart Broad was England's top wicket-taker in the match with 11 wickets. England held a 3–0 lead going into the final Fifth Test at The Oval.

The final Test was drawn. On the fourth day no play was possible due to rain, but on the final day after an aggressive Australian declaration, England came close to achieving its first 4–0 victory in an Ashes series. Play was abandoned, owing to bad light, denying a thrilling finish to the large crowd of spectators. There was media criticism of the new ICC rules requiring umpires to stop play when failing light was measured at a specified level.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/sport/0/cricket/23836394 |title=Ashes 2013: Ashes 2013: England win series 3–0 after bad light ends Oval Test |work=BBC Sport |date=25 August 2013 |accessdate=29 August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Australia won the Ashes 5-0.jpg|thumb|240px|Celebrations at the SCG after Australia won the Ashes 5–0 in 2014]]
In the second of two Ashes series held in [[2013–14 Ashes series|2013 (the series ended in 2014)]], this time hosted by Australia, the home team won the series five test matches to nil. This was the third time Australia has completed a clean sweep (or &quot;whitewash&quot;) in Ashes history, a feat never matched by England. All six Australian specialist batsmen scored more runs than any Englishman with 10 centuries among them, with only debutant Ben Stokes scoring a century for England. Mitchell Johnson took 37 English wickets at 13.97 and Ryan Harris 22 wickets at 19.31 in the 5-Test series.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.espncricinfo.com/magazine/content/story/708507.html;type=series|title=The best series for fast bowlers|work=Cricinfo|date=10 January 2014|accessdate=3 September 2017|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20151109234522/http://www.espncricinfo.com/magazine/content/story/708507.html|archivedate=9 November 2015|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; Only Stuart Broad and all-rounder Stokes bowled effectively for England, with their spinner Graeme Swann retiring due to a chronic elbow injury after the decisive Third Test.

Australia came into the [[2015 Ashes series]] in England as favourites to retain the Ashes. Although England won the first Test in Cardiff, Australia won comfortably in the second Test at Lords. In the next two Tests, the Australian batsmen struggled, being bowled out for 136 in the first innings at [[Edgbaston]], with England proceeding to win by eight wickets. This was followed by Australia being bowled out for 60 as [[Stuart Broad]] took five wickets and finished the spell with 8 for 15 in the first innings at Trent Bridge, the quickest – in terms of balls faced – a team has been bowled out in the first innings of a Test match. With victory by an innings and 78 runs on the morning of the third day of the Fourth Test, England regained the Ashes.

===2017 to present===
During the buildup, the [[2017–18 Ashes series]] was regarded as a turning point for both sides. Australia were criticised for being too reliant on captain Steve Smith and vice-captain David Warner, while England was said to have a shoddy middle to lower order.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.cricbuzz.com/amp/cricket-news/97160/australia-cricket-team-over-reliant-on-steve-smith-david-warner-feels-michael-slater]{{Dead link|date=July 2018 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt; Off the field, England all-rounder [[Ben Stokes]] was ruled out of the side indefinitely due to a police investigation.

England won the toss in the first test match in Brisbane and elected to bat. Despite losing [[Alastair Cook]] early they thrived on the unusually slow pitch and were well placed before [[Pat Cummins|Patrick Cummins]] removed opener [[Mark Stoneman]] and [[Nathan Lyon]] abruptly ended James Vince's innings with a run out. England eventually went on to make 302. Australia, however, lost four wickets early. A partnership between Steve Smith and [[Shaun Marsh]] ensured Australia would not be blown away, before Smith then paired with Patrick Cummins to see Australia pass England's score. Facing a first-innings deficit, England again lost Alastair Cook early, but Joe Root was able to steady the ship. After he was removed by [[Josh Hazlewood]], little resistance was provided, and the Australians only required 170 to win from tea on day four. Openers Warner and Bancroft easily saw Australia through to a 10 wicket win over the next two sessions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/sport/cricket/42132855|title=Ashes: Australia beat England by 10 wickets in first Test|author=|date=27 November 2017|publisher=|via=www.bbc.co.uk}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Australia won the second Test at Adelaide by 120 runs, which was the first ever day-night Ashes test match. Australia regained The Ashes with an innings and 41 run win in the third Test at Perth, the final Ashes Test at the WACA Ground.&lt;ref name=&quot;reclaim&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.cricket.com.au/news/match-report/day-five-australia-england-third-magellan-ashes-test-video-highlights-live-scores-stream-waca/2017-12-18 | title=Ruthless Australia regain the Ashes |work=Cricket Australia |accessdate=18 December 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Prior to the [[2019 Ashes series]], both teams were considered to have very strong bowling attacks, but struggling batting orders. Australia had its top-order batsmen [[David Warner (cricketer)|David Warner]], [[Steve Smith (cricketer)|Steve Smith]] and [[Cameron Bancroft]] available for international selection, who were banned from playing international cricket for 9–12 months due to the [[2018 Australian ball-tampering scandal]] in Cape Town against South Africa. Because of this, these players were unavailable for selection in Australia's previous two Test series against [[India national cricket team|India]] and [[Sri Lanka national cricket team|Sri Lanka]]. While India won their [[India cricket team in Australia in 2018–19|tour series]] 2–1, the first time India had won a Test series in Australia,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.icc-cricket.com/news/969301 |title=India secure historic series victory |work=International Cricket Council |accessdate=24 July 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Australia recovered to win the [[Sri Lanka cricket team in Australia in 2018–19|Test series]] against Sri Lanka 2–0.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.icc-cricket.com/news/1047647 |title=Starc takes ten as Australia sweep series |work=International Cricket Council |accessdate=24 July 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite winning the [[2019 Cricket World Cup Final|Cricket World Cup]] in July 2019 for the first time, England had also been criticised for its fragile top-order in Tests. The retirement of opener [[Alastair Cook]] in August 2018 ensured potential top-order batsmen [[Rory Burns]], [[Joe Denly]] and [[Jason Roy]] were able to secure a place in the side. Despite losing a Test series 2–1 in their [[England cricket team in the West Indies in 2018–19|tour of the West Indies]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/sport/cricket/47217347 |title=England in West Indies: Tourists claim consolation 232-run victory as hosts win series 2-1 |website=BBC Sport |accessdate=12 February 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; England then improved to win the [[Irish cricket team in England in 2019|one-off Test against Ireland]], by 143 runs.

==Summary of results and statistics==
:''See also: [[List of Ashes series]] for a full listing of all the Ashes series since 1882.''
In the 136 years since 1883, Australia have held the Ashes for approximately 80.5 years, and England for 55.5 years:
{{Ashes timeline}}

Test results, up to and including the 2019 Ashes series in England:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://stats.cricinfo.com/statsguru/engine/stats/index.html?class=1;filter=advanced;opposition=1;orderby=won;team=2;template=results;trophy=1;type=team |title=Team records &amp;#124; Test matches &amp;#124; Cricinfo Statsguru &amp;#124; ESPN Cricinfo |publisher=Stats.cricinfo.com |date=1 January 1970 |accessdate=22 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group=note&gt;Australia and England have played an additional 16 Tests{{citation needed|date=August 2015}} but the Ashes were not at stake in those games. Including these Tests, the win–loss record stands at 144 Australian wins, 108 English wins, and 94 draws (up to and including the 5th Test of the 2019 series). See [http://stats.cricinfo.com/statsguru/engine/stats/index.html?class=1;filter=advanced;opposition=1;orderby=won;team=2;template=results;type=team Cricinfo statistics]&lt;/ref&gt;
{|class=wikitable style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;
|- 
!colspan=4|Overall Test Results
|- 
|  '''Tests played'''   || {{flagicon|AUS}} '''[[Australia national cricket team|Australia]] wins'''|| {{flagicon|ENG}} '''[[England national cricket team|England]] wins''' || '''Draws'''
|-
|  335   ||  136    ||  108 ||  91
|- 
|}

Series results, up to and including the 2019 Ashes series:
{|class=wikitable style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;
|- 
!colspan=4|Overall Series Results
|- 
|  '''Series played'''   || {{flagicon|AUS}} '''[[Australia national cricket team|Australia]] wins'''|| {{flagicon|ENG}} '''[[England national cricket team|England]] wins''' || '''Draws'''
|-
|  71   ||  33    ||  32 ||  6
|- 
|}

A team must win a series to gain the right to hold the Ashes. A drawn series results in the previous holders retaining the Ashes. Ashes series have generally been played over five Test matches, although there have been four-match series (1938; 1975) and six-match series (1970–71; 1974–75; 1978–79; 1981; 1985; 1989; 1993 and 1997). Australians have made 264 [[century (cricket)|centuries]] in Ashes Tests, of which 23 have been scores over 200, while Englishmen have scored 212 centuries, of which 10 have been over 200. Australians have taken 10 [[dismissal (cricket)|wickets]] in a match on 41 occasions, Englishmen 38 times.{{citation needed|date=August 2013}}

==Match venues==
The series alternates between the United Kingdom and Australia, and within each country each of the usually five matches is held at different grounds.

In [[Australia]], the grounds currently used are [[the Gabba]] in Brisbane (first staged an England–Australia Test in the 1932–33 season), [[Adelaide Oval]] (1884–85), the [[Melbourne Cricket Ground]] (MCG) (1876–77), and the [[Sydney Cricket Ground]] (SCG) (1881–82). A single Test was held at the [[Brisbane Exhibition Ground]] in 1928–29. Traditionally, Melbourne hosts the [[Boxing Day Test]] and Sydney hosts the New Year Test. Additionally [[WACA Ground|the WACA]] in Perth (1970–71) hosted its [[2017–18 Ashes series#3rd Test|final Ashes Test]] in 2017–18 and is due to be replaced by [[Perth Stadium]] for the [[2021–22 Ashes series|2021–22 series]].

Cricket Australia proposed that the 2010–11 series consist of six Tests, with the additional game to be played at [[Bellerive Oval]] in Hobart. The England and Wales Cricket Board declined and the series was played over five Tests.

In [[England]] and [[Wales]], the grounds currently used are: [[Old Trafford Cricket Ground|Old Trafford]] in Manchester (1884), [[The Oval]] in [[Kennington]], [[South London]] (1884); [[Lord's]] in [[St John's Wood]], [[North London]] (1884); [[Headingley Cricket Ground|Headingley]] in [[Leeds]] (1899) and [[Edgbaston Cricket Ground|Edgbaston]] in [[Birmingham]] (1902). Additionally [[Sophia Gardens]] in [[Cardiff]], [[Wales]] (2009); the [[Riverside Ground]] in [[Chester-le-Street]], [[County Durham]] (2013) and [[Trent Bridge]] at [[West Bridgford]], Nottinghamshire (1899), have been used and one Test was also held at [[Bramall Lane]] in [[Sheffield]] in 1902. Traditionally the final Test of the series is played at the Oval. Sophia Gardens and the Riverside were excluded as Test grounds between the years of 2020 and 2024 and therefore will not host an Ashes Test until at least 2027. Trent Bridge is also not due to host an Ashes Test in 2019 or 2023.

==Cultural references==
[[File:The Ashes Urn Replica (2016).jpg|150px|thumb|right|A modern-day replica of [[The Ashes urn]]]]

The popularity and reputation of the cricket series has led to other sports and games using the name &quot;Ashes&quot; for contests between England and Australia. The best-known and longest-running of these events is the [[rugby league]] rivalry between [[Great Britain national rugby league team|Great Britain]] and [[Australia national rugby league team|Australia]] (see [[The Ashes (rugby league)|rugby league &quot;Ashes&quot;]]). Use of the name &quot;Ashes&quot; was suggested by the Australian team when rugby league matches between the two countries commenced in 1908. Other examples included the television game shows ''[[Gladiators (TV series)|Gladiators]]'' and ''[[Sale of the Century (Australian game show)|Sale of the Century]]'', both of which broadcast special editions containing contestants from the Australian and English versions of the shows competing against each other.

The term became further genericised in Australia in the first half of the twentieth century, and was used to describe many sports rivalries or competitions outside the context of Australia vs England. The [[Australian rules football]] [[Interstate matches in Australian rules football|interstate carnival]], and the small silver casket which served as its trophy, were symbolically known as &quot;the Ashes&quot; of Australian football,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|newspaper=Daily Herald|publication-place=Adelaide, SA|title=Carnival champions – presentation of the Ashes|page=9}}&lt;/ref&gt; and was spoken of as such until at least the 1940s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|newspaper=Barrier Daily Truth|publication-place=Broken Hill, NSW|page=6|title=Victoria's football ashes|date=11 August 1947}}&lt;/ref&gt; The soccer rivalry between Australia and New Zealand was described as &quot;the soccer ashes of Australasia&quot; until as late as the 1950s;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|newspaper=The Sporting Globe|publication-place=Melbourne, VIC|title=Kiwis to win the Ashes|author=J. O. Wishaw|page=7|date=25 August 1954}}&lt;/ref&gt; ashes from cigars smoked by the two countries' captains were put into a casket in 1923 to make the trophy literal.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|newspaper=Referee|publication-place=Sydney, NSW|page=16|title=The soccer ashes of Australasia|date=16 April 1924}}&lt;/ref&gt; The interstate [[rugby league]] [[State of Origin series#Interstate Rugby League prior to 1980|rivalry between Queensland and New South Wales]] was known for a time as Australia's rugby league ashes, and [[lawn bowls|bowls]] competitions between the two states also regularly used the term.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|newspaper=The Brisbane Courier|publication-place=Brisbane, QLD|title=Bowls – N.S.W. &quot;Knuts&quot; retain the &quot;Ashes&quot;|page=3|date=14 July 1920}}&lt;/ref&gt; Even some local rivalries, such as southern Western Australia's annual Great Southern Football Carnival, were locally described as &quot;the ashes&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|newspaper=Great Southern Herald|publication-place=Katanning, WA|page=3|date=21 September 1935|title=Great Southern Football Carnival}}&lt;/ref&gt; This genericised usage is no longer common, and &quot;the Ashes&quot; would today be assumed only to apply to a contest between Australia and England.

The Ashes featured in the film ''[[The Final Test]]'', released in 1953, based on a television play by [[Terence Rattigan]]. It stars [[Jack Warner (actor)|Jack Warner]] as an England cricketer playing the last Test of his career, which is the last of an Ashes series; the film includes cameo appearances of English captain [[Len Hutton]] and other players&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0045769/|title=The Final Test (1953)|publisher=[[Internet Movie Database]]|accessdate=13 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; who were part of England's 1953 triumph.

[[Douglas Adams]]'s 1982 science fiction comedy novel ''[[Life, the Universe and Everything]]'' – the third part of ''[[The Hitchhiker's Guide to the Galaxy]]'' series – features the urn containing the Ashes as a significant element of its plot. The urn is stolen by alien robots, as the burnt stump inside is part of a key needed to unlock the &quot;Wikkit Gate&quot; and release an imprisoned world called Krikkit.

''[[Bodyline (miniseries)|Bodyline]]'', a fictionalised television [[miniseries]] based on the &quot;[[Bodyline]]&quot; Ashes series of 1932–33, was screened in Australia in 1984. The cast included [[Gary Sweet]] as [[Donald Bradman]] and [[Hugo Weaving]] as England captain [[Douglas Jardine]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Frith|first1=David|title=Bodyline Autopsy: The full story of the most sensational Test cricket series: Australia v England 1932–33|publisher=Aurum Press|isbn=9781781311936|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ijnLAgAAQBAJ|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Cricket}}
* [[History of Test cricket from 1877 to 1883]]
* [[History of Test cricket from 1884 to 1889]]
* [[History of Test cricket from 1890 to 1900]]

==Notes==
{{reflist|group=note}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
* {{Cite book| last = Berry | first = S. | year = 2006 | title = Cricket's Burning Passion | location = London | publisher=Methuen | isbn = 0-413-77627-1 }}
* {{Cite book| last = Birley | first = D. | year = 2003 | title = A Social History of English Cricket | location = London |publisher=Aurum Press | isbn = 1-85410-941-3 }}
* {{Cite book| last = Frith | first = D. | year = 1990 | title = Australia versus England: a pictorial history of every Test match since 1877 | location = Victoria (Australia) | publisher=Penguin Books | isbn = 0-670-90323-X }}
* {{Cite book| last = Gibb | first = J. | year = 1979 | title = Test cricket records from 1877 | location = London | publisher=Collins | isbn = 0-00-411690-9 }}
* {{Cite book| last = Gibson | first = A. | year = 1989 | title = Cricket Captains of England | location = London | publisher=Pavilion Books | isbn = 1-85145-395-4 }}
* {{Cite book| last = Green | first = B. | year = 1979 | title = Wisden Anthology 1864–1900 | location = London | publisher=M &amp; J/QA Press | isbn = 0-356-10732-9 }}
* {{Cite book| last = Harte | first = Chris | year = 2003 | title = Penguin history of Australian cricket | publisher=Penguin Books | isbn = 0-670-04133-5 }}
* {{Cite book| last = Munns | first = J. | year = 1994 | title = Beyond reasonable doubt – Rupertswood, Sunbury – the birthplace of the Ashes | location = Australia | publisher=Joy Munns | isbn = 0-646-22153-1 }}
* {{Cite book| last = Warner | first = P. | year = 1987 | title = Lord's 1787–1945 | location = London | publisher=Pavilion Books | isbn = 1-85145-112-9 }}
* {{Cite book| last = Warner | first = P. | year = 2004 | title = How we recovered the Ashes: MCC Tour 1903–1904 | location = London | publisher=Methuen | isbn = 0-413-77399-X }}
* Willis, R. [http://www.lutterworth.com/product_info.php?products_id=486 ''Cricket's Biggest Mystery: The Ashes''], The Lutterworth Press (1987), {{ISBN|978-0-7188-2588-1}}.
* {{Cite book| last = Wynne-Thomas | first = P. | year = 1989 | title = The complete history of cricket tours at home and abroad |location = London | publisher=Hamlyn | isbn = 0-600-55782-0 }}

===Other===
* ''Wisden's Cricketers Almanack'' (various editions)

==External links==
{{Wikiquote}}
{{Commons category|The Ashes}}
* [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=toukmRyDuOE Ashes to Ashes] An audio history of the first hundred years of the Ashes, narrated by [[John Arlott]]
* [http://www.cricinfo.com/engvaus2009/content/story/259985.html Cricinfo's Ashes] website
* [http://www.mcc.org.au/News/Club%20Publications/~/media/Files/Origin%20of%20the%20Ashes.ashx The Origin of the Ashes – Rex Harcourt]
* Listen to a young [http://aso.gov.au/titles/spoken-word/1930-australian-xi-ashes/ Don Bradman speaking] after the 1930 Ashes tour

{{Ashes Test series}}
{{Compton–Miller Medal winners}}
{{Named Test Cricket series}}

{{authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Ashes}}
[[Category:The Ashes| ]]
[[Category:Australia in international cricket]]
[[Category:Cricket awards and rankings]]
[[Category:Cricket rivalries]]
[[Category:England in international cricket]]
[[Category:Recurring events established in 1882]]
[[Category:Recurring sporting events established in 1882]]
[[Category:Test cricket competitions]]</text>
      <sha1>by37ox4uc9rcllt22srj3hvjtgoxbnv</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
