  <page>
    <title>Agrarianism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1193</id>
    <revision>
      <id>938520968</id>
      <parentid>928907625</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-31T18:37:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>SUM1</username>
        <id>12712128</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Changing [[Wikipedia:Short description|short description]] from &quot;Political ideology&quot; to &quot;Political ideology supporting rural society&quot; ([[Wikipedia:Shortdesc helper|Shortdesc helper]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Political ideology supporting rural society}}
'''Agrarianism''' is a [[social philosophy]] or [[political philosophy]] which values rural society as superior to urban society and the independent farmer as superior to the paid worker, and sees farming as a way of life that can shape the ideal social values.&lt;ref&gt;Thompson, Paul. 2010. “Interview Eighteen” in Sustainability Ethics: 5 Questions Ed. Ryne Raffaelle, Wade Robinson, and Evan Selinger. United States: Automatic Press&lt;/ref&gt; It stresses the superiority of a simpler rural life as opposed to the complexity of city life.

== Philosophy ==
[[M. Thomas Inge]] defines agrarianism by the following basic tenets:&lt;ref&gt;M. Thomas Inge, ed. ''Agrarianism in American Literature'' (1969), introduction; [http://xroads.virginia.edu/~HYPER/HNS/Yoeman/agri1.html paraphrased]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Farming is the sole occupation that offers total independence and self-sufficiency.
*Urban life, capitalism, and technology destroy independence and dignity and foster vice and weakness.
*The agricultural community, with its fellowship of labor and co-operation, is the model society.
*The farmer has a solid, stable position in the world order. They have &quot;a sense of identity, a sense of historical and religious tradition, a feeling of belonging to a concrete family, place, and region, which are psychologically and culturally beneficial.&quot; The harmony of their life checks the encroachments of a fragmented, alienated modern society.
*Cultivation of the soil &quot;has within it a positive spiritual good&quot; and from it the cultivator acquires the virtues of &quot;honor, manliness, self-reliance, courage, moral integrity, and hospitality.&quot; They result from a direct contact with nature and, through nature, a closer relationship to God. The agrarian is blessed in that they follow the example of God in creating order out of chaos.

==History==
{{main|History of agrarianism}}
The philosophical roots of agrarianism include European and Chinese philosophers. The Chinese school of [[Agriculturalism]] (农家/農家) was a philosophy that advocated peasant utopian [[communalism]] and egalitarianism. In societies influenced by [[Confucianism]], the farmer was considered an esteemed productive member of society, but merchants who made money were looked down upon.&lt;ref name=&quot;wp&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last= Deutsch |first=Eliot |author2= Ronald Bontekoei|year=1999 | page= 183|title=A companion to world philosophies|publisher=Wiley Blackwell}}&lt;/ref&gt; That influenced European intellectuals like [[François Quesnay]], an avid Confucianist and advocate of China's agrarian policies, in forming the French agrarian philosophy of [[physiocracy]].&lt;ref&gt;L.A. Maverick, &quot;Chinese Influences upon the Physiocrats,&quot; ''Economic History'', 3:54–67 (February 1938),&lt;/ref&gt; The physiocrats, along with the ideas of [[John Locke]] and the [[Romantic Era]], formed the basis of modern European and American agrarianism.

United States president (1801–1809) [[Thomas Jefferson]] was a representative agrarian who built [[Jeffersonian democracy]] around the notion that farmers are “the most valuable citizens” and the truest [[Republicanism in the United States|republicans]].&lt;ref&gt;Thomas P. Govan, &quot;Agrarian and Agrarianism: A Study in the Use and Abuse of Words,&quot; ''Journal of Southern History'', Vol. 30#1  (Feb., 1964), pp. 35–47 [https://www.jstor.org/stable/2205372 in JSTOR]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Agrarian parties==
{{Main|List of agrarian parties}}
Peasant parties first appeared across Eastern Europe between 1860 and 1910, when commercialized agriculture and world market forces disrupted traditional rural society, and the railway and growing literacy facilitated the work of roving organizers. Agrarian parties advocated land reforms to redistribute land on large estates among those who work it. They also wanted [[village cooperatives]] to keep the profit from crop sales in local hands and credit institutions to underwrite needed improvements. Many peasant parties were also nationalist parties because peasants often worked their land for the benefit of landlords of different ethnicity.

Peasant parties rarely had any power before World War I but some became influential in the interwar era, especially in [[Bulgaria]] and [[Czechoslovakia]]. For a while, in the 1920s and the 1930s, there was a Green International ([[International Agrarian Bureau]]) based on the peasant parties in Bulgaria, Czechoslovakia, [[Poland]], and [[Serbia]]. It functioned primarily as an information center that spread the ideas of agrarianism and combating socialism on the left and landlords on the right and never launched any significant activities.

===Tunisia===

The [[Farmers' Voice Party]] won a seat in the district of [[Jendouba Governorate|Jendouba]] after the [[2014 Tunisian parliamentary election|parliamentary election of 2014]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.isie.tn/documents/arrete-resultats-preliminaires.pdf |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2015-06-19 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20141031105610/http://www.isie.tn/documents/arrete-resultats-preliminaires.pdf |archivedate=2014-10-31 }} in Arabic&lt;/ref&gt;

===Europe===

====Bulgaria====
In Bulgaria, the [[Bulgarian Agrarian National Union]] (BZNS) was organized in 1899 to resist taxes and build cooperatives. BZNS came to power in 1919 and introduced many economic, social, and legal reforms. However, conservative forces crushed BZNS in a 1923 coup and assassinated its leader, [[Aleksandar Stamboliyski]] (1879–1923). BZNS was made into a communist puppet group until 1989, when it reorganized as a genuine party.

====Czechoslovakia====
In [[Czechoslovakia]], the [[Republican Party of Agricultural and Smallholder People]] often shared power in parliament as a partner in the five-party pětka coalition. The party's leader, [[Antonin Svehla]] (1873–1933), was prime minister several times. It was consistently the strongest party, forming and dominating coalitions. It moved beyond its original agrarian base to reach middle-class voters. The party was banned by the [[National Front (Czechoslovakia)|National Front]] after the [[Second World War]].&lt;ref&gt;Sharon Werning Rivera, &quot;Historical cleavages or transition mode? Influences on the emerging party systems in Poland, Hungary and Czechoslovakia.&quot; ''Party Politics'' (1996) 2#2 : 177-208.&lt;/ref&gt;

====France====
In [[France]], the [[Hunting, Fishing, Nature, Tradition]] party is a moderate conservative, agrarianist party, reaching a peak of 4.23% in the [[2002 French presidential election]]. It would later on become affiliated to France's main conservative party, [[Union for a Popular Movement]].

====Ireland====

In the late 19th century, the [[Irish National Land League]] aimed to abolish [[landlordism]] in [[Ireland]] and enable tenant farmers to own the land they worked on. The &quot;[[Land War]]&quot; of 1878–1909 led to the [[Irish Land Acts]], ending [[absentee landlords]] and [[ground rent]] and redistributing land among peasant farmers.

Post-independence, the [[Farmers' Party (Ireland)|Farmers' Party]] operated in the [[Irish Free State]] from 1922, folding into the [[National Centre Party (Ireland)|National Centre Party]] in 1932. It was mostly supported by wealthy farmers in the east of Ireland.

[[Clann na Talmhan]] (Family of the Land; also called the ''National Agricultural Party'') was founded in 1938. They focused more on the poor smallholders of the west, supporting [[land reclamation]], [[afforestation]], [[social democracy]] and [[rates (tax)|rates]] reform. They formed part of the governing coalition of the [[Government of the 13th Dáil]] and [[Government of the 15th Dáil]]. Economic improvement in the 1960s saw farmers vote for other parties and Clann na Talmhan disbanded in 1965.

====Latvia====
In Latvia, the [[Union of Greens and Farmers]] is supportive of traditional small farms and perceives them as more environmentally friendly than large-scale farming: Nature is threatened by development, while small farms are threatened by large industrial-scale farms.

====Lithuania====
In Lithuania, as of 2017, the government is led by the [[Lithuanian Farmers and Greens Union]], under the leadership of industrial farmer [[Ramūnas Karbauskis]].

====Poland====
In [[Poland]], the [[Polish People's Party]] traces its tradition to an agrarian party in [[Austria-Hungary|Austro-Hungarian]]-controlled [[Galicia (Central Europe)|Galician Poland]]. After the fall of the communist regime, PPP's biggest success came in [[1993 Polish parliamentary election|1993 elections]], where it won 132 out of 460 parliamentary seats. Since then, PPP's support has steadily declined.

====Romania====
In [[Romania]], older parties from [[Transylvania]], [[Moldavia]], and [[Wallachia]] merged to become the [[National Peasants' Party]] in 1926. [[Iuliu Maniu]] (1873–1953) was a prime minister with an agrarian cabinet from 1928–1930 and briefly in 1932–1933, but the [[Great Depression]] made proposed reforms impossible. The [[Communist Romania|communist regime]] dissolved the party in 1947, but it reformed in 1989 after they fell from power.

The [[Christian Democratic National Peasants' Party|reformed party]], which also incorporated elements of [[Christian democracy]] in its ideology, governed Romania as part of the [[Romanian Democratic Convention]] between 1996–2000.

====Serbia====
In Serbia, [[Nikola Pašić]] (1845–1926) and his [[People's Radical Party]] dominated Serbian politics after 1903. The party also monopolized power in Yugoslavia from 1918 to 1929. During the dictatorship of the 1930s, the prime minister was from that party.

====Ukraine====
In Ukraine, the [[Radical Party of Oleh Lyashko]] has promised to purify the country of [[Ukrainian oligarchs|oligarchs]] &quot;with a [[pitchfork]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=BBCUE14RPst&gt;[http://www.bbc.com/nes/world-europe-29739514 Ukraine election: What to look for], [[BBC News]] (24 October 2014)&lt;/ref&gt; The party advocates a number of traditional left-wing positions (lower salary taxes, a ban on agricultural land sale and eliminating the illegal land market, a tenfold increase in budget spending on health, setting up primary health centres in every village
&lt;ref name=radppUW&gt;[http://ukrainianweek.com/Politics/121957 The Communist Party May Be on Its Last Legs, But Social Populism is Still Alive], [[The Ukrainian Week]] (23 October 2014)&lt;/ref&gt;), and mixes them with strong nationalist sentiments.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2014/10/25/world/europe/with-stunts-and-vigilante-escapades-a-populist-gains-ground-in-ukraine.html?_r=0 |title=With Stunts and Vigilante Escapades, a Populist Gains Ground in Ukraine|newspaper=[[The New York Times]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Oceania===

====Australia====
Historian F.K. Crowley finds that:
: Australian farmers and their spokesman have always considered that life on the land is inherently more virtuous, as well as more healthy, more important and more productive, than life in the towns and cities....The farmers complained that something was wrong with an electoral system which produced parliamentarians who spent money beautifying vampire-cities instead of developing the interior.&lt;ref&gt;F.K. Crowley, ''Modern Australia in Documents: 1901 – 1939'' (1973) pp 77-78.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[National Party of Australia]] (formerly called the Country Party), from the 1920s to the 1970s, promulgated its version of agrarianism, which it called &quot;[[countrymindedness]]&quot;.  The goal was to enhance the status of the graziers (operators of big sheep ranches) and small farmers and justified subsidies for them.&lt;ref&gt;Rae Wear, &quot;Countrymindedness Revisited,&quot; (Australian Political Science Association, 1990) [http://apsa2000.anu.edu.au/confpapers/wear.rtf online edition ] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110723145257/http://apsa2000.anu.edu.au/confpapers/wear.rtf |date=2011-07-23 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

====New Zealand====
The [[New Zealand Liberal Party]] aggressively promoted agrarianism in its heyday (1891–1912). The landed gentry and aristocracy ruled Britain at this time. New Zealand never had an aristocracy but its wealthy landowners largely controlled politics before 1891. The Liberal Party set out to change that by a policy it called &quot;[[populism]].&quot; [[Richard Seddon]] had proclaimed the goal as early as 1884: &quot;It is the rich and the poor; it is the wealthy and the landowners against the middle and labouring classes. That, Sir, shows the real political position of New Zealand.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Leslie Lipson|title=The Politics of Equality: New Zealand's Adventures in Democracy|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=oe8jAAAAMAAJ|year=1948|publisher=U. of Chicago Press}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The Liberal strategy was to create a large class of small landowning farmers who supported Liberal ideals. The [[Liberal Government of New Zealand|Liberal government]] also established the basis of the later welfare state such as [[old age pensions]] and developed a system for settling industrial disputes, which was accepted by both employers and trade unions. In 1893, it [[women's suffrage in New Zealand|extended voting rights to women]], making New Zealand the first country in the world to [[women's suffrage|do so]].

To obtain land for farmers, the Liberal government from 1891 to 1911 purchased {{convert|3,100,000|acres|ha}} of Maori land. The government also purchased {{convert|1,300,000|acres|ha}} from large estate holders for subdivision and closer settlement by small farmers. The Advances to Settlers Act (1894) provided low-interest mortgages, and the agriculture department disseminated information on the best farming methods. The Liberals proclaimed success in forging an egalitarian, anti-monopoly land policy. The policy built up support for the Liberal Party in rural North Island electorates. By 1903, the Liberals were so dominant that there was no longer an organized opposition in Parliament.&lt;ref&gt;James Belich, ''Paradise Reforged: A history of the New Zealanders'' (2001) pp. 39–46&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Tom Brooking, &quot;'Busting Up' the Greatest Estate of All: Liberal Maori Land Policy, 1891–1911,&quot; ''New Zealand Journal of History'' (1992) 26#1 pp. 78–98 [http://www.nzjh.auckland.ac.nz/document.php?wid=802&amp;action=null online]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Back-to-the-land movement ==
Agrarianism is similar to but not identical with the [[back-to-the-land movement]]. Agrarianism concentrates on the fundamental goods of the earth, on communities of more limited economic and political scale than in modern society, and on simple living, even when the shift involves questioning the &quot;progressive&quot; character of some recent social and economic developments. Thus, agrarianism is not [[industrial farming]], with its specialization on products and industrial scale.&lt;ref&gt;Jeffrey Carl Jacob, ''New Pioneers: The Back-to-the-Land Movement and the Search for a Sustainable Future'' (Penn State University Press. 1997)&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Agropedia}}
{{div col|colwidth=30em}}
*[[Agrarian Justice]]
*[[Agrarian socialism]]
*[[Agrarian society]]
*[[Agrarian system]]
*[[Georgism]]
*[[Jeffersonian democracy]]
*[[Agroecology]]
*[[Physiocrats]], 18th-century French thinkers
*[[International Agrarian Bureau]]
*[[Nordic agrarian parties]]
*[[Yeoman]], English farmers
*[[Permaculture]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

== Further reading ==

=== Agrarian values ===
* Brass, Tom. ''Peasants, Populism and Postmodernism: The Return of the Agrarian Myth'' (2000) 
* {{cite book|doi=10.1163/9789004273948|title=Class, Culture and the Agrarian Myth|year=2014|last1=Brass|first1=Tom|isbn=9789004273948}}
*{{cite journal|jstor=3743942|title=Romantic Agrarianism in Twentieth-Century America|journal=Agricultural History|volume=65|issue=4|pages=1–12|last1=Danbom|first1=David B.|year=1991}}
* {{cite journal|doi=10.2307/1053268|jstor=1053268|title=John Taylor: Economist of Southern Agrarianism|journal=Southern Economic Journal|volume=11|issue=3|pages=255–268|year=1945|last1=Grampp|first1=William D.}}
* {{cite journal|doi=10.2307/2707018|jstor=2707018|title=Parrington and the Jeffersonian Tradition|journal=Journal of the History of Ideas|volume=2|issue=4|pages=391–400|year=1941|last1=Hofstadter|first1=Richard}}* Inge, M. Thomas. ''Agrarianism in American Literature'' (1969)
* Kolodny, Annette. ''The Land before Her: Fantasy and Experience of the American Frontiers, 1630–1860'' (1984). [https://www.questia.com/library/book/the-land-before-her-fantasy-and-experience-of-the-american-frontiers-1630-1860-by-annette-kolodny.jsp online edition]
* Marx, Leo. ''The Machine in the Garden: Technology and the Pastoral Ideal in America'' (1964).
* Murphy, Paul V. ''The Rebuke of History: The Southern Agrarians and American Conservative Thought'' (2000)
*  [http://xroads.virginia.edu/~HYPER/parrington/ Parrington, Vernon. ''Main Currents in American Thought'' (1927), 3-vol online]
* {{cite journal|doi=10.1017/S0034670500004563|title=Agrarianism and the Jeffersonian Philosophy|journal=The Review of Politics|volume=2|pages=87–104|year=1940|last1=Quinn|first1=Patrick F.}}
* Thompson, Paul, and Thomas C. Hilde, eds. ''The Agrarian Roots of Pragmatism'' (2000)

===Primary sources===
* Sorokin, Pitirim A. et al., eds. ''A Systematic Source Book in Rural Sociology'' (3 vol. 1930) vol 1 pp.&amp;nbsp;1–146 covers many major thinkers down to 1800

=== Europe ===
* {{cite journal|doi=10.1111/j.1475-6765.2004.00164.x|title=Cleavages, competition and coalition-building: Agrarian parties and the European question in Western and East Central Europe|journal=European Journal of Political Research|volume=43|issue=4|pages=523–546|year=2004|last1=Batory|first1=Agnes|last2=Sitter|first2=Nick}}
* Bell, John D. ''Peasants in Power: Alexander Stamboliski and the Bulgarian Agrarian National Union, 1899–1923''(1923)
* Donnelly, James S. ''Captain Rock: The Irish Agrarian Rebellion of 1821–1824''  (2009)
* Donnelly, James S.  ''Irish Agrarian Rebellion, 1760–1800'' (2006)
* Gross, Feliks, ed. ''European Ideologies: A Survey of 20th Century Political Ideas'' (1948) pp.&amp;nbsp;391–481 [https://www.questia.com/read/8946552 online edition], on Russia and Bulgaria
* Kubricht, Andrew Paul. &quot;The Czech Agrarian Party, 1899-1914: a study of national and economic agitation in the Habsburg monarchy&quot; (PhD thesis, Ohio State University Press, 1974)
* {{cite book |author=Merlan, Francesca |title=Tracking Rural Change: Community, Policy and Technology in Australia, New Zealand and Europe|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=IVtNqlUPwREC&amp;pg=PA60|year=2009|publisher=ANU E Press|page=60|isbn=9781921536533}}
* Narkiewicz, Olga A. ''The Green Flag: Polish Populist Politics, 1867–1970'' (1976).
* Oren, Nissan. ''Revolution Administered: Agrarianism and Communism in Bulgaria'' (1973), focus is post 1945
* [[Thomas Paine|Paine, Thomas]]. ''Agrarian Justice'' (1794)
* {{cite book|doi=10.7228/manchester/9780719076930.001.0001|title=In the Wake of the Great Rebellion|year=2008|last1=Patterson|first1=James G.|isbn=9780719076930}}
* Roberts, Henry L. ''Rumania: Political Problems of an Agrarian State'' (1951).
* {{cite book|doi=10.1017/CBO9780511562839|title=Rebels and Rulers, 1500–1660|year=1982|last1=Zagorin|first1=Perez|isbn=9780521244732}}

=== North America ===
* {{cite journal|jstor=3739767|title=The Influence of Natural Rights and Physiocratic Doctrines on American Agrarian Thought during the Revolutionary Period|journal=Agricultural History|volume=21|issue=1|pages=13–23|last1=Eisinger|first1=Chester E.|year=1947}}
* {{cite journal|doi=10.2307/1950410|jstor=1950410|title=The Agrarian Democracy of Thomas Jefferson|journal=American Political Science Review|volume=40|issue=4|pages=657–681|year=1946|last1=Griswold|first1=A. Whitney}}

* Goodwyn, Lawrence. ''The Populist Moment: A Short History of the Agrarian Revolt in America'' (1978), 1880s and 1890s in U.S.
* {{cite journal|doi=10.2307/2707018|jstor=2707018|title=Parrington and the Jeffersonian Tradition|journal=Journal of the History of Ideas|volume=2|issue=4|pages=391–400|year=1941|last1=Hofstadter|first1=Richard}}
* {{cite journal|doi=10.1111/j.1540-5931.2010.00767.x|title=The Countryside Triumphant: Jefferson's Ideal of Rural Superiority in Modern Superhero Mythology|journal=The Journal of Popular Culture|volume=43|issue=4|pages=720–737|year=2010|last1=Johnson|first1=Jeffrey K.}}
* Lipset, Seymour Martin. ''Agrarian socialism: the Coöperative Commonwealth Federation in Saskatchewan'' (1950), 1930s-1940s
* McConnell, Grant. ''The decline of agrarian democracy''(1953), 20th century U.S.
* Mark, Irving. ''Agrarian conflicts in colonial New York, 1711–1775'' (1940)
* Ochiai, Akiko. ''Harvesting Freedom: African American Agrarianism in Civil War Era South Carolina'' (2007)
* Robison, Dan Merritt. ''Bob Taylor and the agrarian revolt in Tennessee'' (1935)
* Stine, Harold E. ''The agrarian revolt in South Carolina;: Ben Tillman and the Farmers' Alliance'' (1974)
* Summerhill, Thomas. ''Harvest of Dissent: Agrarianism in Nineteenth-Century New York'' (2005)
* Szatmary, David P. ''Shay's Rebellion: The Making of an Agrarian Insurrection'' (1984), 1787 in Massachusetts
* Woodward, C. Vann.  '' Tom Watson: Agrarian Rebel'' (1938) [https://www.questia.com/library/book/tom-watson-agrarian-rebel-by-c-vann-woodward.jsp online edition]
* {{cite journal|doi=10.2307/2191851|jstor=2191851|title=Tom Watson and the Negro in Agrarian Politics|journal=The Journal of Southern History|volume=4|issue=1|pages=14–33|year=1938|last1=Woodward|first1=C. Vann}}

=== Global South ===
* Brass, Tom (ed.). ''New Farmers' Movements in India'' (1995) 304 pages.
* {{cite book|doi=10.4324/9780203505663|title=Latin American Peasants|year=2004|isbn=9780203505663|last1=Brass|first1=Tom}}
* {{cite journal|doi=10.1017/S0022216X98005070|title=State Agrarianism versus Democratic Agrarianism: Adalberto Tejeda's Experiment in Veracruz, 1928–32|journal=Journal of Latin American Studies|volume=30|issue=2|pages=341–372|year=1998|last1=Ginzberg|first1=Eitan}}
*Handy, Jim. ''Revolution in the Countryside: Rural Conflict and Agrarian Reform in Guatemala, 1944–1954'' (1994)
* {{cite book|doi=10.7312/jaco90206|title=Agrarian Unrest in Southeast Asia|year=1949|last1=Jacoby|first1=Erich H.|isbn=9780231877589|hdl=2027/mdp.39015021933091}}
* {{cite journal|doi=10.2307/2651812|jstor=2651812|title=Bringing the Peasants Back In: Agrarian Themes in the Construction and Corrosion of Statist Historiography in Rwanda|journal=The American Historical Review|volume=105|issue=3|pages=832|year=2000|last1=Newbury|first1=David|last2=Newbury|first2=Catharine}}
* Paige, Jeffery M. '' Agrarian revolution: social movements and export agriculture in the underdeveloped world'' (1978)  435 pages [https://www.amazon.com/Agrarian-Revolution-Jeffrey-M-Paige/dp/0029235502 excerpt and text search]
* Sanderson, Steven E. ''  Agrarian populism and the Mexican state: the struggle for land in Sonora'' (1981)
*Stokes, Eric. ''The Peasant and the Raj: Studies in Agrarian Society and Peasant Rebellion in Colonial India'' (1980)
* {{cite journal|doi=10.1111/j.1471-0366.2012.00368.x|title=Illegal Evictions? Overwriting Possession and Orality with Law's Violence in Cambodia|journal=Journal of Agrarian Change|volume=13|issue=4|pages=520–546|year=2013|last1=Springer|first1=Simon}}
* Tannenbaum, Frank.  ''The Mexican Agrarian Revolution'' (1930)

==External links==
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20090203142256/http://www.thedeliberateagrarian.com/ Writings of a Deliberate Agrarian]
*[http://www.newagrarian.com/ The New Agrarian]

{{Simple living}}

[[Category:Agrarianism| ]]</text>
      <sha1>5jtha1gws9a67bwyqzxrgob299gl4es</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
