  <page>
    <title>Cardinal (Catholic Church)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6221</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942556608</id>
      <parentid>941467486</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-25T11:44:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ravenpuff</username>
        <id>22132037</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* top */ Fix</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Senior official of the Catholic Church}}
{{For|a current list of cardinals|List of living cardinals}}
{{Refimprove article|date=December 2018}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2017}}
[[File:External Ornaments of a Cardinal (not a bishop).svg|thumb|right|upright=0.8|The coat of arms of a cardinal is indicated by a red [[galero]] (wide-brimmed hat) with 15 tassels on each side (the [[motto]] and [[Escutcheon (heraldry)|escutcheon]] are proper to the individual cardinal).]]
{{Catholic Church Hierarchy}}

A '''cardinal''' ({{lang-la|Sanctae Romanae Ecclesiae cardinalis}}, literally &quot;cardinal of the Holy Roman Church&quot;) is a leading [[Bishop (Catholic Church)|bishop]] and [[Prince of the Church|prince]] of the [[College of Cardinals]] in the [[Catholic Church]]. Their duties include participating in [[Papal consistory|papal consistories]], and [[Papal conclave|conclaves]] when the [[Holy See]] is vacant. Most have additional missions, such as leading a [[diocese]] or a [[dicastery]] of the [[Roman Curia]], the equivalent of a government of the [[Holy See]]. During the ''[[sede vacante]]'' (the period between a pope's death or resignation and the election of his successor), the day-to-day governance of the Holy See is in the hands of the College of Cardinals. The right to enter the Papal conclave of cardinals where the pope is elected is limited to those who have not reached the age of 80 years by the day the vacancy occurs.

In 1059, the right of electing the pope was reserved to the principal clergy of Rome and the bishops of the seven [[Suburbicarian diocese|suburbicarian see]]s. In the 12th century the practice of appointing ecclesiastics from outside Rome as cardinals began, with each of them assigned a church in Rome as his [[titular church]] or linked with one of the suburbicarian dioceses, while still being incardinated in a diocese other than that of Rome.{{citation needed|date=July 2012}}

The term ''cardinal'' at one time applied to any priest permanently assigned or [[incardinated]] to a church,&lt;ref name=&quot;CE-cardinal&quot;&gt;{{CathEncy | wstitle=Cardinal | title=Cardinal | last=Sägmüller | first=Johannes Baptist}}&lt;/ref&gt; or specifically to the senior priest of an important church, based on the Latin ''cardo'' (hinge), meaning &quot;pivotal&quot; as in &quot;principal&quot; or &quot;chief&quot;. The term was applied in this sense as early as the 9th century to the priests of the ''tituli'' (parishes) of the [[diocese of Rome]].&lt;ref name=&quot;CE-cardinal&quot; /&gt;

==History==
{{further information|Papal selection before 1059}}
[[File:Richelieu, por Philippe de Champaigne (detalle).jpg|thumb|upright|[[Cardinal Richelieu]], chief minister of [[France]]]]

There is disagreement about the origin of the term, but the consensus that &quot;''cardinalis''&quot; from the word ''cardo'' (meaning &quot;pivot&quot; or &quot;hinge&quot;) was first used in late antiquity to designate a bishop or priest who was incorporated into a church for which he had not originally been ordained. In [[Rome]] the first persons to be called cardinals were the deacons of the seven regions of the city at the beginning of the 6th century, when the word began to mean &quot;principal&quot;, &quot;eminent&quot;, or &quot;superior&quot;. The name was also given to the senior priest in each of the &quot;title&quot; churches (the parish churches) of Rome and to the bishops of the seven sees surrounding the city. By the 8th century the Roman cardinals constituted a privileged class among the Roman clergy. They took part in the administration of the church of Rome and in the papal liturgy. By decree of [[Lateran Council (769)|a synod of 769]], only a cardinal was eligible to become Bishop of Rome. Cardinals were granted the privilege of wearing the red hat by Pope [[Innocent IV]] in 1244.&lt;ref&gt;Encyclopædia Britannica&lt;/ref&gt;

In cities other than Rome, the name cardinal began to be applied to certain church men as a mark of honour. The earliest example of this occurs in a letter sent by [[Pope Zacharias]] in 747 to [[Pippin III]] (the Short), ruler of the [[Franks]], in which Zacharias applied the title to the priests of [[Paris]] to distinguish them from country clergy. This meaning of the word spread rapidly, and from the 9th century various episcopal cities had a special class among the clergy known as cardinals. The use of the title was reserved for the cardinals of Rome in 1567 by [[Pius V]].

In the year 1563 the Ecumenical Council of Trent, headed by Pope [[Pius IV]], wrote about the importance of selecting good cardinals: &quot;nothing is more necessary to the Church of God than that the holy Roman pontiff apply that solicitude which by the duty of his office he owes the universal Church in a very special way by associating with himself as cardinals the most select persons only, and appoint to each church most eminently upright and competent shepherds; and this the more so, because our Lord [[Jesus|Jesus Christ]] will require at his hands the blood of the sheep of Christ that perish through the evil government of shepherds who are negligent and forgetful of their office.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Catholic bishops and Pope Pius IV|title=The Council of Trent|date=11 November 1563|publisher=Tan Books and Publishers}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The earlier influence of temporal rulers, notably the French kings, reasserted itself through the influence of cardinals of certain nationalities or politically significant movements. Traditions even developed entitling certain monarchs, including those of Austria, Spain, and France, to nominate one of their trusted clerical subjects to be created cardinal, a so-called &quot;[[crown-cardinal]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chadwick&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Chadwick|first1=Owen|title=The Popes and European Revolution|date=1981|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=9780198269199|page=266|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=XrLmCwAAQBAJ&amp;dq}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Early Modern period|early modern]] times, cardinals often had important roles in secular affairs. In some cases, they took on powerful positions in government. In [[Henry VIII of England|Henry VIII]]'s England, his chief minister was for some time [[Thomas Wolsey|Cardinal Wolsey]]. [[Cardinal Richelieu]]'s power was so great that he was for many years effectively the ruler of France.&lt;ref&gt;Henry Kitchell Webster, [[Hutton Webster]], ''Early European History'', p. 604. Retrieved from https://books.google.com/books?id=rXSqwPFMn3oC.&lt;/ref&gt; Richelieu's successor was also a cardinal, [[Cardinal Mazarin|Jules Mazarin]]. [[Guillaume Dubois]] and [[André-Hercule de Fleury]] complete the list of the four great cardinals to have ruled France.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chadwick&quot; /&gt; In Portugal, due to a succession crisis, one cardinal, [[Henry, King of Portugal]], was crowned king, the only example of a cardinal-king.

While the incumbents of some sees are regularly made cardinals, and some countries are entitled to at least one cardinal by [[concordate]] (usually earning either its [[primate (bishop)|primate]] or the metropolitan of the capital city the cardinal's hat), no see carries an actual right to the cardinalate, not even if its bishop is a [[Patriarch#Catholic_Church|Patriarch]].

==Papal elections==
In 1059, [[Pope Nicholas II]] gave cardinals the right to elect the Bishop of Rome in the [[papal bull]] ''[[In nomine Domini]]''. For a time this power was assigned exclusively to the cardinal bishops, but in 1179 the [[Third Lateran Council]] restored the right to the whole body of cardinals.&lt;ref name=TCE1&gt;{{cite book |last=Fanning |first=W. |editor-first= |editor-last= |title=The Catholic Encyclopaedia |publisher=Robert Appleton Company |year=1911 |pages= |chapter-url=https://archive.org/details/isbn_9780840731753 |chapter=Papal Elections |isbn=0840731752 |url-access=registration |url=https://archive.org/details/isbn_9780840731753 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Numbers==
In 1586 [[Pope Sixtus V]] limited the number of cardinals to 70:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | accessdate = 25 October 2017 | url = https://timesmachine.nytimes.com/timesmachine/1958/11/18/83425668.pdf | first=Arnaldo | last=Cortesi | work= New York Times | date= 18 November 2017 | title = Two Americans among 23 New Cardinals}}&lt;/ref&gt; six cardinal bishops, 50 cardinal priests, and 14 cardinal deacons. [[Pope John XXIII]] exceeded that limit citing the need to staff Church offices.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url = https://timesmachine.nytimes.com/timesmachine/1958/12/16/83430914.pdf | work = New York Times| accessdate = 25 October 2017 | date = 16 December 1958 | title = Pope Elevates 33 to Cardinalate; Deplores China Church Schism | first = Arnoldo | last = Cortesi}}&lt;/ref&gt; In November 1970 in ''[[Ingravescentem aetatem]]'', [[Pope Paul VI]] established that electors would be under the age of eighty years. When it took effect on 1 January 1971, it deprived twenty-five cardinals of the right to participate in a conclave.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Hoffman|first1=Paul|title=Voting for Popes Is Barred to Cardinals Over 80|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1970/11/24/archives/voting-for-popes-is-barred-to-cardinals-over-80-prelates-over-80.html|accessdate=30 October 2017|work=New York Times|date=24 November 1970}}&lt;/ref&gt; In October 1975 in ''[[Romano Pontifici eligendo]]'', he set the maximum number of electors at 120, while establishing no limit on the overall size of the College.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| url= https://books.google.com/?id=Iv8pAwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA101 | page=101 | title= Inside the Vatican: The Politics and Organization of the Catholic Church | first= Thomas J. |last = Reese | date= 1998 | publisher = Harvard University Press| isbn=9780674418028 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Popes can [[dispensation (Catholic Church)|set aside]] church laws&lt;ref&gt;[http://newcesite.com/2008/02/08/81136/ Are There Any Limitations on the Power of the Pope?] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110714172232/http://newcesite.com/2008/02/08/81136/ |date=14 July 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Mickens|first1=Robert|title=Letter from Rome The Next Stage of Francis's Mission| url=https://www.commonwealmagazine.org/letter-rome-121|accessdate=9 July 2017|work=Commonwealth Magazine|date=24 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; and they have regularly brought the number of cardinals under the age of 80 to more than 120, twice reaching as high as 135 with [[Cardinals_created_by_John_Paul_II#21_February_2001|Pope John Paul II's consistories]] of February 2001&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Stanley|first1=Alexandra |title=Shaping a Legacy, Pope Installs 44 Cardinals|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2001/02/22/world/shaping-a-legacy-pope-installs-44-cardinals.html|accessdate=1 September 2016|work=New York Times|date=22 February 2001}}&lt;/ref&gt; and October 2003. No more than 120 electors have ever participated in a [[Papal conclave|conclave]], but most canon lawyers believe that if their number exceeded 120 they would all participate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| url= https://books.google.com/?id=tHsltdTp6OgC&amp;pg=PT90&amp;dq=allen+%22violates+canon+law%22#v=onepage&amp;q=allen%20%22violates%20canon%20law%22&amp;f=false | first=John L. | last= Allen Jr. |title= Conclave: The Politics, Personalities, and Process of the Next Papal Election | date= 2002 | publisher=Random House |page=107|quote=Most canon lawyers take the opinion that the pope, in appointing more electors than anticipated by ''Universi Dominici Gregis'', made an exception to his own rules and hence all the cardinals under eighty, regardless of the limit of 120, are eligible to enter the conclave. (Canon lawyers ruefully joke that nobody violates canon law like a pope.) As a political matter, it seems probable that all cardinals under eighty will be admitted regardless of the wording of ''Universi Dominici Gregis'' because the task of trying to decide who cannot enter could paralyze the process indefinitely.| isbn=9780385504560 }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{efn|The rule set out in ''[[Universi Dominici gregis]]'' is that &quot;No Cardinal elector can be excluded from active or passive voice in the election of the Supreme Pontiff, for any reason or pretext.&quot;}}

Pope Paul VI also increased the number of cardinal bishops by assigning that rank, in 1965, to patriarchs of the [[Eastern Catholic Churches]] when named cardinals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | work = New York Times| url = https://timesmachine.nytimes.com/timesmachine/1965/02/23/97186241.pdf | accessdate = 26 October 2017 | date= 23 February 1965| title = Pontiff Installs 27 New Cardinals}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite document| date=11 February 1965 | url= http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/paul_vi/motu_proprio/documents/hf_p-vi_motu-proprio_19650211_ad-purpuratorum_lt.html |author=Pope Paul VI |title=Ad purpuratorum Patrum |publisher=Libreria Editrice Vaticana | accessdate=3 December 2017}}]&lt;/ref&gt; In 2018, Pope Francis expanded the cardinal bishops of Roman title, because this had not been done despite recent decades' expansion in the two lower orders of cardinals, besides having all six such cardinals being over the age limit for a conclave.

==Titular churches==
[[File:Theodor Kardinal Innitzer -001-.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Theodor Innitzer|Cardinal Innitzer]], [[Archbishop of Vienna]] and Cardinal-Priest of [[San Crisogono]]]]
Each cardinal takes on a titular church, either a church in the city of Rome or one of the [[Suburbicarian diocese|suburbicarian see]]s.  The only exception is for patriarchs of the Eastern Catholic Churches.&lt;ref name=&quot;Paul VI. 1965&quot;&gt;Pope Paul VI., Motuproprio &quot;Ad Purpuratorum Patrum Collegium&quot; (11 February 1965), par. II&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, cardinals possess no power of governance nor are they to intervene in any way in matters which pertain to the administration of goods, discipline, or the service of their titular churches.&lt;ref&gt;Code of Canon law: 357-1&lt;/ref&gt; They are allowed to celebrate Mass and hear confessions and lead visits and pilgrimages to their titular churches, in coordination with the staff of the church. They often support their churches monetarily, and many cardinals do keep in contact with the pastoral staffs of their titular churches.  The term cardinal is from the latin word &quot;cardo&quot; meaning a hinge.  Here it means a &quot;door&quot;, an example of synecdoche, a figure of speech whereby the part refers to the whole.  The &quot;door&quot; is the address of the titular church from which the cardinal derives his membership of the Roman clergy, who elect the Pope.  

The [[Dean of the College of Cardinals]] in addition to such a titular church also receives the [[Bishop of Ostia|titular bishopric of Ostia]], the primary suburbicarian see. Cardinals governing a [[particular church]] retain that church.&lt;ref&gt;Code of Canon law: 350&lt;/ref&gt;

==Title and reference style==
In 1630, [[Pope Urban VIII]] decreed their title to be ''[[His Eminence|Eminence]]'' (previously, it had been &quot;illustrissimo&quot; and &quot;reverendissimo&quot;){{efn|They were formerly called illustrissimi and reverendissimi; but Pope Urban VIII (of the Barberini family), in 1630, established the above as their title of honour. Edward Wigglesworth, Thomas Gamaliel Bradford: Encyclopædia Americana: a popular dictionary of arts, sciences. Volume 4. Page 493.}} and decreed that their secular rank would equate to Prince, making them secondary only to the Pope and crowned monarchs.{{efn|As the exclusive electors of the pope (at least since 1179), cardinals were deemed to be the ecclesiastical equivalents of the Holy Roman Empire's 'Prince-Electors,' an extremely elite group with precedence over all other nobility (including archdukes, dukes and counts), who were tasked with the responsibility of electing Holy Roman Emperors.... A decree of 10 June 1630, by Urban VII bestowed the title &quot;His Eminence&quot;, historically reserved for high nobility, upon the cardinals, thus elevating them above the 'His Excellency', then being used to refer to Italian princes.&quot; Guruge, Anura. The Next Pope. Alton, New Hampshire. 2010. p. 81.}}{{efn|Authoritarian, keenly conscious of his position, Urban kept business in his own hands and rarely discussed it with his cardinals: to compensate them he gave them the rank of princes of the church and a right to the title of 'eminence' (June 1630). ''Oxford Dictionary of Popes'', Urban VIII}}

In accordance with tradition, they sign by placing the title &quot;Cardinal&quot; (abbreviated ''Card.'') after their personal name and before their surname as, for instance, &quot;John Card(inal) Doe&quot; or, in [[Latin]], &quot;Ioannes Card(inalis) Doe&quot;. Some writers, such as James-Charles Noonan,&lt;ref&gt;Noonan, ''The Church Visible'', p. 205&lt;/ref&gt; hold that, in the case of cardinals, the form used for signatures should be used also when referring to them in English. However, official sources, such as the [[Catholic News Service]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.catholicnews.com/data/stylebook/stylebooksample.pdf|archive-url=http://webarchive.loc.gov/all/20051212193819/http://www.catholicnews.com/data/stylebook/stylebooksample.pdf|url-status=dead|archive-date=2005-12-12|title=Catholic News Service|website=www.catholicnews.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; say that the correct form for referring to a cardinal in English is normally as &quot;Cardinal [First name] [Surname]&quot;. This is the rule given also in stylebooks not associated with the church.&lt;ref&gt;[http://religionstylebook.com/entries/cardinal Religion Stylebook: &quot;Cardinals should be referred to conventionally, as in ''Cardinal Avery Dulles'', not ''Avery Cardinal Dulles'']&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.usfca.edu/uploadedFiles/Destinations/Offices_and_Services/Communications_and_Marketing/docs/USF_StyleGuide.pdf|title=University of San Francisco Editorial Style Guide: &quot;On first reference capitalize these titles before the individual's name: Cardinal Timothy Manning, archbishop of Los Angeles&quot;|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20141204212305/http://www.usfca.edu/uploadedFiles/Destinations/Offices_and_Services/Communications_and_Marketing/docs/USF_StyleGuide.pdf|archivedate=4 December 2014|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://neilreisner.com/class_docs/ap_guide.pdf|title=Associated Press Style Guide: &quot;The preferred form for first reference is ... Cardinal Daniel DiNardo&quot;|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;At first reference Cardinal John Doe. At subsequent references the cardinal or Doe&quot; ([http://handbook.reuters.com/index.php?title=R&amp;oldid=514#32.34 Reuters Handbook of Journalism])&lt;/ref&gt; This style is also generally followed on the websites of the Holy See and [[episcopal conference]]s.&lt;ref&gt;The websites of [http://www.vatican.va/phome_en.htm the Holy See] (except for signatures), and of the Episcopal Conferences in [http://www.usccb.org/ the United States], [http://www.catholicchurch.org.uk/ccb/catholic_church/the_church_in_england_and_wales/cardinal England and Wales]     {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080820211646/http://www.catholicchurch.org.uk/ccb/catholic_church/the_church_in_england_and_wales/cardinal |date=20 August 2008 }}, [http://www.catholiccommunications.ie/Dioceses/armagh.html Ireland]     {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080724160215/http://www.catholiccommunications.ie/Dioceses/armagh.html |date=24 July 2008 }} and the [http://www.acbc.catholic.org.au/bishops/bcmembers.asp Australia]     {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080720145633/http://www.acbc.catholic.org.au/bishops/bcmembers.asp |date=20 July 2008 }} agree with the stylebooks. The [http://www.bpsconfscot.com/Members/tabid/426/Default.aspx Bishops' Conference of Scotland]  {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080511233725/http://www.bpsconfscot.com/Members/tabid/426/Default.aspx |date=11 May 2008 }} uses both styles side by side. On diocesan sites, the &quot;John Cardinal Doe&quot; style is found on, for example, those of [http://www.rcab.org/People/cardinalOMalley.html Boston], [https://web.archive.org/web/19961029034800/http://www.archdiocese-chgo.org/ Chicago], [http://www.dublindiocese.ie/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=blogcategory&amp;id=19&amp;Itemid=30 Dublin], [http://www.archny.org/about-us/edward-cardinal-egan/ New York]   {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080703171151/http://archny.org/about-us/edward-cardinal-egan/ |date=3 July 2008 }}, [https://web.archive.org/web/20070708110901/http://www.archtoronto.org/about_us/cardinal_bishops.html Toronto], [http://www.adw.org/about/our_bishops.asp Washington]     {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070401083114/http://www.adw.org/about/our_bishops.asp |date=1 April 2007 }}, [http://www.diogh.org/bishops_dinardo.htm Galveston-Houston]  {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20101124143721/http://diogh.org/bishops_dinardo.htm |date=24 November 2010 }}, [http://www.aodonline.org/AODOnline/Meet+the+Bishops+12188/Adam+Cardinal+Maida+2244/Tribute.htm Detroit], [http://www.sacbc.org.za/Site/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=20&amp;Itemid=30 Durban]     {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080219020531/http://www.sacbc.org.za/Site/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=20&amp;Itemid=30 |date=19 February 2008 }}, [https://web.archive.org/web/20071026102440/http://www.archdioceseofcolombo.com/2_1.php Colombo], [http://archbom.org/ Bombay], and the &quot;Cardinal John Doe&quot; on, for example, those of [http://www.armagharchdiocese.org/cardinal Armagh],[http://www.archdiocese.la/archbishop/profile.html Los Angeles]     {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071029192113/http://www.archdiocese.la/archbishop/profile.html |date=29 October 2007 }}, [http://www.archdiocese-phl.org/rigali/biorigali.htm Philadelphia]     {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080517010920/http://www.archdiocese-phl.org/rigali/biorigali.htm |date=17 May 2008 }}, [http://www.archdiocese-edinburgh.org.uk/cardinal_about.htm St Andrews and Edinburgh]     {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080907161019/http://www.archdiocese-edinburgh.org.uk/cardinal_about.htm |date=7 September 2008 }}, [http://www.wn.catholic.org.nz/?sid=10 Wellington], [http://www.rcdow.org.uk/cardinal/default.asp?library_ref=1&amp;category_ref=8 Westminster].&lt;/ref&gt; Oriental patriarchs who are created cardinals customarily use &quot;Sanctae Ecclesiae Cardinalis&quot; as their full title,&lt;ref&gt;cfr. &quot;Klaus Ganzer, Kardinäle als Kirchenfürsten?&quot; in ''Stimmen der Zeit'' 2011, issue 5, pp. 313–323&lt;/ref&gt; probably because they do not belong to the Roman clergy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Paul VI. 1965&quot;/&gt;

The [First name] Cardinal [Surname] order is used in the [[Latin language|Latin]] [[Habemus Papam|proclamation]] of the election of a new pope by the cardinal protodeacon,{{efn|&quot;''Annuntio vobis gaudium magnum; habemus Papam: Eminentissimum ac Reverendissimum Dominum, Dominum (first name) Sanctae Romanae Ecclesiae Cardinalem (last name), ...''&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/benedict_xvi/elezione/index_en.htm|title=Election – BENEDICT XVI|website=www.vatican.va}}&lt;/ref&gt; (Meaning: &quot;I announce to you a great joy; we have a Pope: The Most Eminent and Most Reverend Lord, Lord (first name) Cardinal of the Holy Roman Church (last name), ...&quot;)}} if the new pope is a cardinal, as he has been since 1378.

== Orders and their chief offices ==
[[File:Vetements cardinal Gamarelli.jpg|thumb|right|Choir dress of a cardinal]]

=== Cardinal bishops ===
[[File:Sodano.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Angelo Sodano|Cardinal Sodano]], Dean Emeritus of the College]]
Cardinal bishops (cardinals of the episcopal order) are the senior order of cardinals. Though in modern times the vast majority of cardinals are also [[Bishop (Catholic Church)|bishop]]s or [[archbishops]], few are &quot;cardinal bishops&quot;. For most of the second millennium there were six cardinal bishops, each presiding over  one of the seven [[suburbicarian diocese|suburbicarian sees]] around Rome: [[Bishop of Ostia|Ostia]], [[Roman Catholic Suburbicarian Diocese of Albano|Albano]], [[Roman Catholic Suburbicarian Diocese of Porto-Santa Rufina|Porto and Santa Rufina]], [[Roman Catholic Suburbicarian Diocese of Palestrina|Palestrina]], [[Roman Catholic Suburbicarian Diocese of Sabina-Poggio Mirteto|Sabina and Mentana]], [[Roman Catholic Suburbicarian Diocese of Frascati|Frascati]], and [[Roman Catholic Suburbicarian Diocese of Velletri-Segni|Velletri]].&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=6YCpraE-7xcC&amp;pg=PA468 John P. Beal, ''New Commentary on the Code of Canon Law''] (Paulist Press 2000 {{ISBN|978-0-80910502-1}}), p. 468&lt;/ref&gt; Velletri was united with Ostia from 1150 until 1914, when [[Pope Pius X]] separated them again, but decreed that whichever cardinal bishop became [[Dean of the College of Cardinals]] would keep the suburbicarian see he already held, adding to it that of Ostia, with the result that there continued to be only six cardinal bishops.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/11346a.htm Umberto Benigni, &quot;Ostia and Velletri&quot; in ''Catholic Encyclopedia'' (New York 1911)]; [http://www.vatican.va/archive/aas/documents/AAS%2006%20%5B1914%5D%20-%20ocr.pdf Pope Pius X, motu proprio ''Edita a Nobis'' of 5 May 1914 in ''Acta Apostolicae Sedis'' VI (1914), p. 219-220] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130303051148/http://www.vatican.va/archive/aas/documents/AAS%2006%20%5B1914%5D%20-%20ocr.pdf |date=3 March 2013 }}; {{cite web|url=http://www.ewtn.com/holysee/interregnum/laws.asp|title=History of Papal Electoral Law|website=www.ewtn.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since 1962, the cardinal bishops have only a [[titular church|titular]] relationship with the suburbicarian sees, each of which is governed by a separate [[Ordinary (Catholic Church)|ordinary]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite document| url=http://w2.vatican.va/content/john-xxiii/la/motu_proprio/documents/hf_j-xxiii_motu-proprio_19620411_suburbicariis-sedibus.html | language=la | accessdate=2 November 2017| date= 9 April 1962 | title= Suburbicariis sedibus | publisher=  Libreria Editrice Vaticana | author= Pope John XXIII}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1965, [[Pope Paul VI]] decreed in his ''[[motu proprio]]'' ''Ad purpuratorum Patrum Collegium'' that [[patriarch]]s of the [[Eastern Catholic Churches]] who were named cardinals (i.e. &quot;cardinal patriarchs&quot;) would also be cardinal bishops, ranking after the six cardinal bishops of the suburbicarian sees.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite document| title=Ad Purpuratorum Patrum Collegium | url= http://w2.vatican.va/content/paul-vi/la/motu_proprio/documents/hf_p-vi_motu-proprio_19650211_ad-purpuratorum.html | publisher= Libreria Editrice Vaticana | accessdate=3 December 2017 | author= Pope Paul VI | language=la | date=11 February 1965}}&lt;/ref&gt; ([[Latin Church]] cardinal patriarchs are [[cardinal priest]]s, not cardinal bishops: for example [[Angelo Scola]] was made [[Patriarch of Venice]] in 2002 and cardinal priest of [[Santi XII Apostoli]] in 2003.) At the June 2018 consistory, it was announced that, corresponding to the expansion in cardinal priests and cardinal deacons in recent decades, there would be an expansion in cardinal bishops. Four cardinals were elevated to this rank by having their [[titular church|titular]] churches and deaconries granted suburbicarian rank ''[[pro hac vice]]'' (temporarily).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite document | accessdate = 26 June 2018 | url = http://press.vatican.va/content/salastampa/en/bollettino/pubblico/2018/06/26/180626c.html | publisher =Holy See Press Office | date= 26 June 2018 | title = Rescriptum of the Holy Father Francis ...}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | | work =National Catholic Reporter | date= 26 June 2018 | url = https://www.ncronline.org/news/vatican/new-papal-appointments-reflect-popes-wish-transparency | accessdate = 26 June 2018 | title = New papal appointments reflect pope's wish for transparency| agency = Catholic News Service | first = Carol | last = Glatz}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the time of the announcement, all six cardinal bishops of suburbicarian see titles, as well as two of the three cardinal patriarchs, were non-electors because of having reached age 80.

The [[Dean of the College of Cardinals]], the highest ranking cardinal, was formerly the longest serving cardinal bishop, but since 1965 is elected by the Latin Church cardinal bishops from among their number, subject to papal approval. Likewise the Vice-Dean, formerly the second longest serving, is also elected. Seniority of the remaining cardinal bishops is still by date of appointment to the rank. For a period ending in the mid-20th century, long-serving cardinal priests were entitled to fill vacancies that arose among the cardinal bishops, just as [[cardinal deacon]]s of ten years' standing are still entitled to become cardinal priests.

=== Cardinal priests ===
Cardinal priests are the most numerous of the three orders of cardinals in the Catholic Church, ranking above the cardinal deacons and below the cardinal bishops.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.catholicculture.org/culture/library/dictionary/index.cfm?id=32336 John Hardon, ''Modern Catholic Dictionary'']&lt;/ref&gt; Those who are named cardinal priests today are generally [[Bishop (Catholic Church)|bishop]]s of important [[diocese]]s throughout the world, though some hold [[Roman Curia|Curial]] positions.

In modern times, the name &quot;cardinal priest&quot; is interpreted as meaning a cardinal who is of the order of priests. Originally, however, this referred to certain key priests of important churches of the Diocese of Rome, who were recognized as the ''cardinal'' priests, the important priests chosen by the pope to advise him in his duties as [[Bishop]] of [[diocese of Rome|Rome]] (the Latin ''cardo'' means &quot;hinge&quot;). Certain clerics in many dioceses at the time, not just that of Rome, were said to be the key personnel—the term gradually became exclusive to Rome to indicate those entrusted with electing the bishop of Rome, the pope.

[[File:Cardinal Thomas Wolsey.jpg|thumb|left|Cardinal-priest [[Thomas Wolsey]]]]
While the cardinalate has long been expanded beyond the Roman pastoral clergy and [[Roman Curia]], every cardinal priest has a [[titular church]] in Rome, though they may be bishops or archbishops elsewhere, just as cardinal bishops were given one of the [[suburbicarian diocese]]s around Rome. [[Pope Paul VI]] abolished all administrative rights cardinals had with regard to their titular churches, though the cardinal's name and coat of arms are still posted in the church, and they are expected to celebrate mass and preach there if convenient when they are in Rome.

While the number of cardinals was small from the times of the [[Roman Empire]] to the [[Renaissance]], and frequently smaller than the number of recognized churches entitled to a cardinal priest, in the 16th century the College expanded markedly. In 1587, [[Pope Sixtus V]] sought to arrest this growth by fixing the maximum [[Size of the College of Cardinals|size of the College]] at 70, including 50 cardinal priests, about twice the historical number. This limit was respected until 1958, and the list of titular churches modified only on rare occasions, generally when a building fell into disrepair. When [[Pope John XXIII]] abolished the limit, he began to add new churches to the list, which Popes [[Pope Paul VI|Paul VI]] and [[Pope John Paul II|John Paul II]] continued to do. Today there are close to 150 titular churches, out of over 300 churches in Rome.

The cardinal who is the longest-serving member of the order of cardinal priests is titled ''cardinal [[protopriest]]''. He had certain ceremonial duties in the conclave that have effectively ceased because he would generally have already reached age 80, at which cardinals are barred from the conclave. The current cardinal protopriest is [[Michael Michai Kitbunchu]] of [[Thailand]].

=== Cardinal deacons ===
The cardinal deacons are the lowest-ranking cardinals. Cardinals elevated to the diaconal order are either officials of the [[Roman Curia]] or priests elevated after their 80th birthday. Bishops with diocesan responsibilities, however, are created cardinal priests.

Cardinal deacons derive originally from the seven deacons in the [[Papal Household]] and the seven deacons who supervised the Church's works in the districts of [[Rome]] during the early Middle Ages, when church administration was effectively the government of Rome and provided all social services. Cardinal deacons are given title to one of these deaconries.

Cardinals elevated to the diaconal order are mainly officials of the [[Roman Curia]] holding various posts in the church administration. Their number and influence has varied through the years. While historically predominantly Italian the group has become much more internationally diverse in later years. While in 1939 about half were Italian by 1994 the number was reduced to one third. Their influence in the election of the Pope has been considered important, they are better informed and connected than the dislocated cardinals but their level of unity has been varied.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thomas J. Reese p. 92-93&quot;&gt;Thomas J. Reese, '' Inside the Vatican: The Politics and Organization of the Catholic Church'',  Harvard University Press, 1996 p. 92-93&lt;/ref&gt; Under the 1587 decree of [[Pope Sixtus V]], which fixed the maximum [[size of the College of Cardinals]], there were 14 cardinal deacons. Later the number increased. As late as 1939 almost half of the cardinals were members of the curia. Pius XII reduced this percentage to 24 percent. John XXIII brought it back up to 37 percent but Paul VI brought it down to 27 percent where John Paul II maintained this ratio.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thomas J. Reese p. 92-93&quot;/&gt;

As of 2005, there were over 50 churches recognized as cardinalatial deaconries, though there were only 30 cardinals of the order of deacons. Cardinal deacons have long enjoyed the right to &quot;opt for the order of cardinal priests&quot; (''optazione'') after they have been cardinal deacons for 10 years. They may on such elevation take a vacant &quot;[[titular church|title]]&quot; (a church allotted to a cardinal priest as the church in Rome with which he is associated) or their diaconal church may be temporarily elevated to a cardinal priest's &quot;title&quot; for that occasion. When elevated to cardinal priests, they take their precedence according to the day they were first made cardinal deacons (thus ranking above cardinal priests who were elevated to the college after them, regardless of order).

When not celebrating Mass but still serving a liturgical function, such as the semiannual ''[[Urbi et Orbi]]'' [[papal blessing]], some Papal Masses and some events at Ecumenical Councils, cardinal deacons can be recognized by the [[dalmatic]]s they would don with the simple white mitre (so called ''mitra simplex'').

==== Cardinal protodeacon ====
The cardinal protodeacon is the senior cardinal deacon in order of appointment to the College of Cardinals. If he is a cardinal elector and participates in a conclave, he [[Habemus Papam|announces a new pope's election]] and name{{efn|once he has been ordained to the episcopate&lt;ref&gt;Ap. Const. [http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/john_paul_ii/apost_constitutions/documents/hf_jp-ii_apc_22021996_universi-dominici-gregis_en.html Universi Dominici Gregis, No. 89]&lt;/ref&gt;}} from the central balcony of [[St. Peter's Basilica]] in [[Vatican City]]. The proto-deacon also bestows the pallium on the new pope and crowns him with the [[papal tiara]], though coronations have been discontinued since Pope John Paul I opted for a simpler papal inauguration ceremony in 1978.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Acting in the place of the Roman Pontiff, he also confers the pallium upon [[Metropolitan bishop#Roman Catholic|metropolitan bishops]] or gives the pallium to their proxies.&quot; [http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG1104/__P19.HTM Canon 355 §2]&lt;/ref&gt; The current cardinal protodeacon is [[Renato Raffaele Martino]].

===== Cardinal protodeacons since 1911 =====
{{unreferenced section|date=July 2012}}
[[File:Coat_of_arms_of_Renato_Martino.svg|thumb|right|Coat of arms of [[Renato Raffaele Martino|Cardinal Martino]], current Cardinal [[Protodeacon]]]]
* [[Francesco Salesio Della Volpe]] (4 January 1911&amp;nbsp;– 5 November 1916†); announced election of [[Pope Benedict XV]] ([[Papal conclave, 1914|1914]])
* [[Gaetano Bisleti]] (5 November 1916&amp;nbsp;– 17 December 1928*); announced election of [[Pope Pius XI]] ([[Papal conclave, 1922|1922]])
* [[Camillo Laurenti]] (17 December 1928&amp;nbsp;– 16 December 1935*)
* [[Camillo Caccia-Dominioni]] (16 December 1935&amp;nbsp;– 12 November 1946†); announced election of [[Pope Pius XII]] ([[Papal conclave, 1939|1939]])
* [[Nicola Canali]] (12 November 1946&amp;nbsp;– 3 August 1961†); announced election of [[Pope John XXIII]] ([[Papal conclave, 1958|1958]])
* [[Alfredo Ottaviani]] (3 August 1961&amp;nbsp;– 26 June 1967*); announced election of [[Pope Paul VI]] ([[Papal conclave, 1963|1963]])
* [[Arcadio Larraona Saralegui]], [[Claretians|CMF]] (26 June 1967&amp;nbsp;– 28 April 1969*)
* [[William Theodore Heard]] (28 April 1969&amp;nbsp;– 18 May 1970*)
* [[Antonio Bacci]] (18 May 1970&amp;nbsp;– 20 January 1971†)
* [[Michael Browne (cardinal)|Michael Browne]], [[Dominican Order|OP]] (20 January 1971&amp;nbsp;– 31 March 1971†)
* [[Federico Callori di Vignale]] (31 March 1971&amp;nbsp;– 8 August 1971†)
* [[Charles Journet]] (8 August 1971&amp;nbsp;– 5 March 1973*)
* [[Pericle Felici]] (5 March 1973&amp;nbsp;– 30 June 1979*); announced elections of [[Pope John Paul I]] ([[Papal conclave, August 1978|1978]]) and [[Pope John Paul II]] ([[Papal conclave, October 1978|1978]])
* [[Sergio Pignedoli]] (30 June 1979&amp;nbsp;– 15 June 1980†)
* [[Umberto Mozzoni]] (15 June 1980&amp;nbsp;– 2 February 1983*)
* [[Opilio Rossi]] (2 February 1983&amp;nbsp;– 22 June 1987*)
* [[Giuseppe Caprio]] (22 June 1987&amp;nbsp;– 26 November 1990*)
* [[Aurelio Sabattani]] (26 November 1990&amp;nbsp;– 5 April 1993*)
* [[Duraisamy Simon Lourdusamy]] (5 April 1993&amp;nbsp;– 29 January 1996*)
* [[Eduardo Martínez Somalo]] (29 January 1996&amp;nbsp;– 9 January 1999*)
* [[Pio Laghi]] (9 January 1999&amp;nbsp;– 26 February 2002*)
* [[Luigi Poggi]] (26 February 2002&amp;nbsp;– 24 February 2005*)
* [[Jorge Medina Estévez]] (24 February 2005&amp;nbsp;– 23 February 2007*); announced election of [[Pope Benedict XVI]] ([[Papal conclave, 2005|2005]])
* [[Darío Castrillón Hoyos]] (23 February 2007&amp;nbsp;– 1 March 2008*)
* [[Agostino Cacciavillan]] (1 March 2008&amp;nbsp;– 21 February 2011*)
* [[Jean-Louis Tauran]] (21 February 2011&amp;nbsp;– 12 June 2014*); announced election of [[Pope Francis]] ([[Papal conclave, 2013|2013]])
* [[Renato Raffaele Martino]] (12 June 2014&amp;nbsp;– present)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | work = La Stampa | language =it | url = http://www.lastampa.it/2014/06/12/vaticaninsider/ita/vaticano/martino-diventa-cardinale-protodiacono-senza-habemus-papam-dHcpHr2npVizIsSXyjVfHM/pagina.html | accessdate = 23 January 2018 | date= 12 June 2014 |title= Martino diventa cardinale protodiacono (senza &quot;Habemus Papam&quot;) | first= Jacopo | last= Scaramuzzi}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;nowiki&gt;*&lt;/nowiki&gt;Ceased to be protodeacon upon being raised to the order of cardinal-priest
&lt;br&gt;†Was protodeacon at time of death

==Special types of cardinals==

===Camerlengo===
The Cardinal [[Camerlengo of the Holy Roman Church]], assisted by the Vice-Camerlengo and the other prelates of the office known as the Apostolic Camera, has functions that in essence are limited to a period of ''[[sede vacante]]'' of the papacy. He is to collate information about the financial situation of all administrations dependent on the Holy See and present the results to the College of Cardinals, as they gather for the [[papal conclave]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/john_paul_ii/apost_constitutions/documents/hf_jp-ii_apc_19880628_pastor-bonus-roman-curia_en.html#ADMINISTRATIVE+SERVICES|title=Pastor Bonus, – John Paul II – Apostolic Constitution (June 28, 1988) – John Paul II|website=www.vatican.va}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Cardinals who are not bishops===
[[File:Reginald Pole painting.jpg|thumb|[[Reginald Pole]] was a cardinal for 18 years before he was ordained a priest.]]
Until 1917, it was possible for someone who was not a priest, but only in [[minor orders]], to become a cardinal (see &quot;lay cardinals&quot;, below), but they were enrolled only in the order of cardinal deacons. For example, in the 16th century, [[Reginald Pole]] was a cardinal for 18 years before he was ordained a priest. In 1917 it was established that all cardinals, even cardinal deacons, had to be priests,&lt;ref&gt;Canon 232 §1 of the 1917 Code of Canon Law&lt;/ref&gt; and, in 1962, [[Pope John XXIII]] set the norm that all cardinals be ordained as [[bishop (Catholic Church)|bishops]], even if they are only priests at the time of appointment.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/john_xxiii/motu_proprio/documents/hf_j-xxiii_motu-proprio_19620415_cum-gravissima_lt.html Motu proprio ''Cum gravissima'', 15 April 1962] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130302231616/http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/john_xxiii/motu_proprio/documents/hf_j-xxiii_motu-proprio_19620415_cum-gravissima_lt.html |date=2 March 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt; As a consequence of these two changes, canon 351 of the 1983 Code of Canon Law requires that a cardinal be at least in the order of [[priesthood (Catholic Church)|priesthood]] at his appointment, and that those who are not already bishops must receive episcopal consecration. Several cardinals aged over 80 or close to it when appointed have obtained [[Dispensation (Catholic Church)|dispensation]] from the rule of having to be a bishop.{{efn|Examples include [[Domenico Bartolucci]], [[Karl Josef Becker]], [[Yves Congar]], [[Aloys Grillmeier]], [[Henri de Lubac]], [[Julien Ries]], [[Leo Scheffczyk]], [[Roberto Tucci]] and [[Albert Vanhoye]].}} These were all appointed cardinal-deacons, but [[Roberto Tucci]] and [[Albert Vanhoye]] lived long enough to exercise the right of option and be promoted to the rank of cardinal-priest.

A cardinal who is not a bishop is still entitled to wear and use the episcopal vestments and other [[pontificalia]] (episcopal regalia: [[mitre]], [[crozier]], [[zucchetto]], [[pectoral cross]] and ring). Even if not a bishop, any cardinal has both actual and honorary precedence over non-cardinal patriarchs, as well as the archbishops and bishops who are not cardinals, but he cannot perform the functions reserved solely to bishops, such as [[Holy Orders|ordination]]. The prominent priests who since 1962 were not ordained bishops on their elevation to the cardinalate were over the age of 80 or near to it, and so no cardinal who was not a bishop has participated in recent [[papal conclave]]s.

===&quot;Lay cardinals&quot;===
{{Main article|Lay cardinal}}
At various times, there have been cardinals who had only received [[tonsure#Western Christianity|first tonsure]] and [[minor orders]] but not yet been [[Holy Orders|ordained]] as [[deacon]]s or priests. Though [[clergy|clerics]], they were inaccurately called &quot;[[lay cardinal]]s&quot;. [[Teodolfo Mertel]] was among the last of the lay cardinals. When he died in 1899 he was the last surviving cardinal who was not at least ordained a priest. With the revision of the [[Code of Canon Law]] promulgated in 1917 by [[Pope Benedict XV]], only those who are already priests or bishops may be appointed cardinals.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.intratext.com/IXT/LAT0813/_PO.HTM canon 232 §1] of the 1917 Code of Canon Law&lt;/ref&gt; Since the time of [[Pope John XXIII]] a priest who is appointed a cardinal must be consecrated a bishop, unless he obtains a dispensation.&lt;ref&gt;Cf. [http://www.intratext.com/IXT/ENG0017/_P18.HTM canon 351 §1] of the 1983 Code of Canon Law&lt;/ref&gt;

==Cardinals ''in pectore'' or secret cardinals==
{{Main article|In pectore}}
In addition to the named cardinals, the pope may name secret cardinals or cardinals ''[[in pectore]]'' (Latin for ''in the breast''). During the [[Western Schism]], many cardinals were created by the contending popes. Beginning with the reign of [[Pope Martin V]],&lt;ref name=&quot;CE-cardinal&quot; /&gt; cardinals were created without publishing their names until later, a practice termed ''creati et reservati in pectore''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Catholic Encyclopedia|url=https://books.google.com/?id=9gIjAQAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA337|first=John|last=Rickaby|volume=3|page=337|date=1913}}&lt;/ref&gt; A cardinal named ''in pectore'' is known only to the pope. In the modern era popes have named cardinals ''in pectore'' to protect them or their congregations from political reprisals. If conditions change, the pope makes the appointment public. The cardinal in question then ranks in precedence with those made cardinals at the time of his ''in pectore'' appointment. If a pope dies before revealing the identity of an ''in pectore'' cardinal, the person's status as cardinal expires. The last pope known to have named a cardinal ''in pectore'' is [[Pope John Paul II]], who named four, including one whose identity was never revealed.{{efn|The three were:
[[Ignatius Kung Pin-Mei]], Bishop of [[Roman Catholic Diocese of Shanghai|Shanghai]], made cardinal 1979, revealed 1991; [[Marian Jaworski]], Archbishop of [[Roman Catholic Archdiocese of Lviv|Lviv]], made cardinal 1998, revealed 2001; [[Jānis Pujāts]], Archbishop of [[Roman Catholic Archdiocese of Riga|Riga]], made cardinal 1998, revealed 2001. John Paul created a fourth in 2003 but did not reveal his identity, not even in his will. Speculation centered on [[Joseph Zen Ze-kiun]], Bishop of [[Roman Catholic Diocese of Hong Kong|Hong Kong]], [[Tadeusz Kondrusiewicz (bishop)|Tadeusz Kondrusiewicz]], Archbishop of [[Roman Catholic Archdiocese of Moscow|Moscow]], and Archbishop [[Stanisław Dziwisz]], John Paul's longtime friend and secretary.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url = http://articles.latimes.com/2005/apr/07/world/fg-secret7 | work = Los Angeles Times | date = 7 April 2005 | title = Mystery Cardinal Will Never Be Able to Join Peers | first= Richard | last = Boudreau |accessdate= 6 July 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==Vesture and privileges==
{{Main article|Pontifical vestments}}
&lt;gallery heights=&quot;220&quot; widths=&quot;165&quot; style=&quot;font-size:95%; line-height:130%;&quot; class=&quot;center&quot; caption=&quot;Pontifical vestments&quot;&gt;
File:Cardinal Théodore Adrien Sarr 2.JPG|alt=Théodore Adrien Cardinal   Sarr with a ferraiolo, and wearing a red cassock, but not the rest of the choir dress.|[[Théodore-Adrien Sarr|Cardinal Sarr]] with a [[ferraiolo]], and wearing a red cassock, but not the rest of the choir dress.
File:Kardinaal III Danneels en Kasper.JPG|alt=Cardinals Walter Kasper (left) and Godfried Danneels (right) wearing their choir dress: scarlet (red) cassock, white rochet trimmed with lace, scarlet mozetta, scarlet biretta (over the usual scarlet zucchetto), and pectoral cross on cord.|Cardinals [[Walter Kasper]] (left) and [[Godfried Danneels]] (right) wearing their [[choir dress]]: scarlet (red) [[cassock]], white [[rochet]] trimmed with [[lace]], scarlet [[mozetta]], scarlet [[biretta]] (over the usual scarlet [[zucchetto]]), and [[pectoral cross]] on cord.
File:Cardinal Gerald Lacroix.jpg|alt=Gérald Cardinal Lacroix wearing the ordinary dress of a cardinal: black cassock with scarlet (red) piping and buttons, scarlet fascia (sash), pectoral cross on a chain, and a scarlet zucchetto.|[[Gérald Lacroix|Cardinal Lacroix]] wearing the ordinary dress of a cardinal: black cassock with scarlet (red) [[Piping (sewing)|piping]] and buttons, scarlet [[Fascia (vestment)|fascia]] (sash), pectoral cross on a chain, and a scarlet zucchetto.
File:Missione del Guaricano-cardinale Tarcisio Bertone.jpg|alt=Tarcisio Cardinal Bertone in dress for hot tropical countries (white cassock with scarlet piping and buttons).|[[Tarcisio Bertone|Cardinal Bertone]] in dress for hot tropical countries (white cassock with scarlet piping and buttons).
&lt;/gallery&gt;

When in [[choir dress]], a [[Latin Church]] cardinal wears [[Scarlet_(color)|scarlet]] garments—the blood-like red symbolizes a cardinal's willingness to die for his faith.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/news_services/press/documentazione/documents/cardinali_documentazione/cardinali_documentazione_generale_en.html#Ordinary%20Public%20Consistory The College of Cardinals – General Documentazion] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130317062254/http://www.vatican.va/news_services/press/documentazione/documents/cardinali_documentazione/cardinali_documentazione_generale_en.html#Ordinary%20Public%20Consistory |date=17 March 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://archive.is/20120719062740/http://www.belfasttelegraph.co.uk/news/local-national/article3196655.ece Applause and tears in Basilica greet Pontiff] (26 November 2007) ''Belfast Telegraph''. Retrieved 1 June 2008. Quote: &quot;In a ceremony televised across the world cardinal-elect Sean Brady knelt before Pope Benedict XVI and pledged his allegiance to the Church before receiving his special red birretta—a symbol of a cardinal's dignity and willingness to shed blood for the increase of the Christian faith.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Excluding the [[rochet]]—which is always white—the scarlet garments include the [[cassock]], [[mozzetta]], and [[biretta]] (over the usual scarlet [[zucchetto]]). The biretta of a cardinal is distinctive not merely for its scarlet color, but also for the fact that it does not have a pompon or tassel on the top as do the birettas of other prelates.  Until the 1460s, it was customary for cardinals to wear a [[violet (color)|violet]] or [[blue]] cape unless granted the privilege of wearing red when acting on papal business. His normal-wear cassock is black but has scarlet [[piping (sewing)|piping]] and a scarlet [[fascia (vestment)|fascia]] (sash). Occasionally, a cardinal wears a scarlet ''[[ferraiolo]]'' which is a cape worn over the shoulders, tied at the neck in a bow by narrow strips of cloth in the front, without any 'trim' or piping on it.&lt;ref name=vesture&gt;{{cite journal | title=Instruction on the dress, titles and coat-of-arms of cardinals, bishops and lesser prelates. | publisher=[[L'Osservatore Romano]], English ed. | date=17 April 1969 | pages=vol.4 | url=http://www.fiu.edu/~mirandas/instruction69.htm | accessdate=1 September 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is because of the scarlet color of cardinals' vesture that the [[cardinal (bird)|bird of the same name]] has become known as such.{{Citation needed|date=May 2012}}
[[File:A_Cardinal_in_Profile,_1880,_by_Jehan_Georges_Vibert_(Morgan_Library_and_Museum,_New_York_City).jpg|left|thumb|A Cardinal in Profile, 1880, by [[Jehan Georges Vibert]] ([[Morgan Library and Museum]], New York City)]]
[[Eastern Catholic Churches|Eastern Catholic]] cardinals continue to wear the normal dress appropriate to their liturgical tradition, though some may line their cassocks with scarlet and wear scarlet fascias, or in some cases, wear Eastern-style cassocks entirely of scarlet.&lt;ref&gt;Photograph of [[Josyf Slipyj]], [[Major Archbishop]] of the [[Ukrainian Greek Catholic Church|Ukrainian Catholic Church]] and Cardinal, wearing a galero on top of his red [[klobuk]]. Retrieved from http://photos1.blogger.com/blogger/6322/78/1600/SlypyjGalero1.jpg.&lt;/ref&gt;

In previous times, at the [[Papal consistory|consistory]] at which the pope named a new cardinal, he would bestow upon him a distinctive wide-brimmed hat called a [[galero]]. This custom was discontinued in 1969&lt;ref name=vesture/&gt; and the investiture now takes place with the scarlet biretta. In [[ecclesiastical heraldry]], however, the scarlet galero is still displayed on the cardinal's [[coat of arms]]. Cardinals had the right to display the galero in their cathedral, and when a cardinal died, it would be suspended from the ceiling above his tomb. Some cardinals will still have a galero made, even though it is not officially part of their apparel.{{citation needed|date=July 2012}}

To symbolize their bond with the [[papacy]], the pope gives each newly appointed cardinal a gold ring,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last=Paulson |first=Michael |date=25 March 2006 |title= Bling! examination of the ring of Cardinal O'Malley | work = Boston Globe | accessdate = 8 September 2010 | url = http://www.boston.com/news/globe/city_region/paulson/blog/2006/03/25/index.html }}&lt;/ref&gt; which is traditionally kissed by Catholics when greeting a cardinal (as with a bishop's episcopal ring). Before the new uniformity imposed by John Paul II, each cardinal was given a ring, the central piece of which was a gem, usually a sapphire, with the pope's stemma engraved on the inside.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nainfa1909&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=John Abel Nainfa|title=Costume of Prelates of the Catholic Church: According to Roman Etiquette|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ILddVVSkGx8C|year=1909|publisher=John Murphy Company|location=Baltimore-New York|page=107}}.  The new cardinal had to pay for the ring, in exchange for which he received the right to make his own Last Will and Testament.&lt;/ref&gt;  There is now no gemstone, and the pope chooses the image on the outside: under [[Pope Benedict XVI]] it was a modern depiction of the crucifixion of Jesus, with [[Virgin Mary|Mary]] and [[John the Evangelist|John]] to each side. The ring includes the pope's coat of arms on the inside.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.fogcityjournal.com/news_in_brief/mass_of_rings_060326.shtml|title=Elevated cardinals receive gold ring from the pope during Mass of Rings|website=www.fogcityjournal.com|language=en|access-date=2018-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Cardinals have in [[canon law (Catholic Church)|canon law]] a &quot;privilege of forum&quot; (i.e., exemption from being judged by ecclesiastical tribunals of ordinary rank): only the pope is competent to judge them in matters subject to ecclesiastical jurisdiction (cases that refer to matters that are spiritual or linked with the spiritual, or with regard to infringement of ecclesiastical laws and whatever contains an element of sin, where culpability must be determined and the appropriate
ecclesiastical penalty imposed). The pope either decides the case himself or delegates the decision to a tribunal, usually one of the tribunals or congregations of the Roman Curia. Without such delegation, no [[ecclesiastical court]], even the [[Roman Rota]], is competent to judge a canon law case against a cardinal.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG1104/__P5A.HTM Canon 1405 §1 and canon 1406 §2] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20060822022417/http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG1104/__P5A.HTM |date=22 August 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Cardinal-Infante (disambiguation)]]
* [[Cardinal-nephew]]
* [[Cardinal protector]]
* [[Hierarchy of the Catholic Church#Cardinals|Hierarchy of the Catholic Church]]
* [[Living cardinals]]
* [[List of the creations of the cardinals]]

==Notes==
{{Noteslist}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Bibliography==
* {{cite journal|last1=Kuttner|first1=Steven|title=Cardinalis: The History of a Canonical Concept|journal=Traditio|date=1945|volume=3|pages=129–214|jstor=27830076 |doi=10.1017/S0362152900016883}}
* {{CathEncy | wstitle=Ecclesiastical Addresses | last=Battandier | first=Albert}}
&lt;!-- *Mirriam-Webster (1997 HTML edition). [https://www.cs.harvard.edu/oldwikis/data/mW/Mwed00000140.html Handbook of Style]&amp;nbsp;— Clerical and Religious forms of address. Accessdate=2006-09-22. --&gt;
* {{cite book | last=Noonan, Jr. | first=James-Charles | title=The Church Visible: The Ceremonial Life and Protocol of the Roman Catholic Church | year=1996 | publisher=Viking | isbn=0-670-86745-4 | url=https://archive.org/details/churchvisiblecer0000noon }}
* {{CathEncy | wstitle=Cardinal | title=Cardinal | last=Sägmüller | first=Johannes Baptist}}
* {{Cite EB1911 | wstitle=Cardinal | last=Boudinhon | first=Auguste }}

==External links==
{{Commons|Category:Cardinals}}
* Salvador Miranda. [http://cardinals.fiu.edu The Cardinals of the Holy Roman Church]. A digital resource consisting of the biographical entries of the cardinals from 494 to 2014 and of the events and documents concerning the origin of the Roman cardinalate and its historical evolution
* [http://popes-and-papacy.com/wordpress/?p=571 Next Cardinal Creating Consistory by Pope Benedict XVI – The Required Background Data] (including statistical data and links). Popes and the Papacy website (Anura Guruge). Retrieved 2010-09-08.
* [http://www.gcatholic.org/hierarchy/cardinals.htm GCatholic on all Cardinals]
** [http://www.gcatholic.org/hierarchy/cardinals-alive-precedence.htm List of All Cardinals By Precedence] by GCatholic
** [http://www.gcatholic.org/hierarchy/cardinals-title-c2.htm List of all Cardinal Titular Churches] by GCatholic
** [http://www.gcatholic.org/hierarchy/cardinals-title-c3.htm List of all Cardinal Deaconries] by GCatholic
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20060829055027/http://www.catholic-pages.com/hierarchy/cardinals_list.asp Catholic-pages List of Cardinals]
* Thomas J. Reese, '' Inside the Vatican: The Politics and Organization of the Catholic Church'',  Harvard University Press, 1996    [https://books.google.com/books?id=FYMKOgA5lSAC&amp;pg=PA92&amp;lpg=PA92&amp;dq=how+many+curial+cardinals&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=r4kq_aS8Ln&amp;sig=ThDac8VDQDvgVabUQ4rwMon-74w&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=ocgtUezCLsKAhQefrYGgAg&amp;sqi=2&amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;q=how%20many%20curial%20cardinals&amp;f=false]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20160708031251/http://www.cardinalrating.com/ Cardinal Rating] a website listing the day to day statements printed in the news by current cardinals

{{Cardinals of the Catholic Church}}
{{Papacy}}
{{Holy See}}
{{Catholicism}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:College of Cardinals|!]]
[[Category:Cardinals (Catholic Church)|*]]
[[Category:Bishops by type]]
[[Category:Catholic ecclesiastical titles]]
[[Category:Religious leadership roles]]</text>
      <sha1>swy77sbcs8wsh06i7z0iyafn1xbmsg4</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
