  <page>
    <title>Commuter rail</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6286</id>
    <revision>
      <id>938201473</id>
      <parentid>938201379</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-29T18:49:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>62.231.87.86</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Europe */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{for|the [[Tiësto]] song|Suburban Train/Urban Train}}
{{More citations needed|date=August 2019}}[[File:DART Unit 8203.jpg|thumb|The [[Dublin Area Rapid Transit|DART]] is part of [[Dublin|Dublin's]] commuter rail network. It is operated by a fleet of [[Electric Multiple Units]].]]
[[File:Trem Linha Coral CPTM.jpg|thumb|A [[Companhia Paulista de Trens Metropolitanos|CPTM]] train on the [[Line 11 (CPTM)|Coral Line]] in [[São Paulo]], [[Brazil]].]]
[[File:UM MI 79R — gare d'Aulnay-sous-Bois.jpg|alt=|thumb|A renovated MI 79 of the [[Réseau Express Régional]] in [[Paris]].]]
[[File:AMA 103 at Puhinui.jpg|thumb|[[New Zealand AM class electric multiple unit|AM class]] electric multiple unit used in [[Auckland]], [[New Zealand]]]]

'''Commuter rail''', or '''suburban rail''', is a [[passenger rail transport]] service that primarily operates within a [[metropolitan area]], connecting [[Commuting|commuters]] to a [[Downtown|central city]] from adjacent [[suburb]]s or [[commuter town]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://onlinepubs.trb.org/Onlinepubs/glossary/001.pdf|title=Urban Public Transportation Glossary|last=Transportation Research Board|first=|date=1989|website=|url-status=live|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.apta.com/wp-content/uploads/Resources/resources/reportsandpublications/Documents/Transit_Glossary_1994.pdf|title=Glossary of Transit Terminology|last=American Public Transit Association|first=|date=1994|website=|url-status=live|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131113002142/http://www.ntdprogram.gov/ntdprogram/Glossary.htm|title=National Transit Database Glossary|date=2013-11-13|website=web.archive.org|access-date=2019-10-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; Generally commuter rail systems are considered [[heavy rail]], using electrified or diesel trains.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt; Distance charges or [[zone pricing]] may be used.

The term can refer to systems with a wide variety of different features and service frequencies, but is often used in contrast to [[rapid transit]] or [[light rail]].

Similar non-English terms include ''Treno suburbano'' in Italian, ''[[Cercanías]]'' in Spanish, ''[[Rodalies de Catalunya|Rodalies]]'' in Catalan, ''[[Proastiakos]]'' in Greek, ''Train de banlieue'' in French, ''Příměstský vlak'' or ''Esko'' in Czech, ''[[Elektrichka]]'' in Russian, ''Pociąg podmiejski '' in Polish and ''Pendeltåg'' in Swedish.

Some services share similarities with both commuter rail and high-frequency [[rapid transit]], such as the German [[S-Bahn]]'','' the [[Réseau Express Régional]] in Paris, many Japanese commuter systems, and some Australasian suburban networks. Some services, like [[Urban rail in the United Kingdom|British commuter rail]], share tracks with other passenger services and [[Cargo|freight]].

In the United States, commuter rail often refers to services that operate a higher frequency during [[Rush hour|peak periods]] and a lower frequency off-peak.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://usa.streetsblog.org/2017/02/13/what-american-commuter-rail-can-learn-from-paris/|title=What American Commuter Rail Can Learn From Paris|date=2017-02-13|website=Streetsblog USA|language=en-US|access-date=2019-10-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since the creation of [[GO Transit rail services|GO Transit's]] commuter service in 1967, commuter rail services and route length have been expanding in North America.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://onlinepubs.trb.org/onlinepubs/millennium/00080.pdf|title=North American Commuter Rail|last=Zullig|first=Walter|last2=Phraner|first2=David|date=|website=Committee on Commuter Rail Transportation|url-status=live|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the US, commuter rail is sometimes referred to as [[regional rail]].

==Characteristics==
[[File:Mumbai Train.JPG|thumb|[[Mumbai Suburban Railway]] carries more than 7.24 million commuters on a daily basis]]
[[File:GO Transit Bombardier Bilevel CEM 322.JPG|thumb|[[GO Transit]] serves the [[Golden Horseshoe]] region surrounding Toronto. Its train services are transitioning from a peak direction commuter railway to a [[GO Transit Regional Express Rail|Regional Express Network]].]]

Most commuter (or suburban) trains are built to main line rail standards,{{Citation needed|date=September 2018}} differing from [[light rail]] or [[rapid transit]] (metro rail)  systems by:
*being larger
*providing more seating and less standing room, owing to the longer distances involved
*having (in most cases) a lower frequency of service
*having scheduled services (i.e. trains run at specific times rather than at specific intervals)
*serving lower-density suburban areas, typically connecting [[suburb]]s to the city center
*sharing track or [[Right-of-way (railroad)|right-of-way]] with intercity or [[freight]] trains
*not fully grade separated (containing at-grade crossings with crossing gates)
*being able to skip certain stations as an express service due to normally being driver controlled

===Train schedule===
Compared to [[rapid transit]] (or metro rail), commuter/suburban rail often has lower [[headway|frequency]], following a schedule rather than fixed intervals, and fewer stations spaced further apart. They primarily serve lower density suburban areas (non inner-city), and often share [[right-of-way (railroad)|right-of-way]] with intercity or [[freight]] trains. Some services operate only during peak hours and others uses fewer departures during off peak hours and weekends. Average speeds are high, often 50&amp;nbsp;km/h (30&amp;nbsp;mph) or higher. These higher speeds better serve the longer distances involved. Some services include express services which skip some stations in order to run faster and separate longer distance riders from short-distance ones.{{Citation needed|date=September 2018}}

The general range of commuter trains' distance varies between 15 and 200&amp;nbsp;km (10 and 125 miles).{{Citation needed|date=September 2018}} Sometimes long distances can be explained by that the train runs between two or several cities (e.g. S-Bahn in the [[Ruhr]] area of Germany). Distances between stations may vary, but are usually much longer than those of urban rail systems. In city centers the train either has a terminal station or passes through the city centre with notably fewer station stops than those of urban rail systems. Toilets are often available on-board trains and in stations.

===Track===
Their ability to coexist with freight or intercity services in the same [[Right-of-way (railroad)|right-of-way]] can drastically reduce system construction costs. However, frequently they are built with dedicated tracks within that right-of-way to prevent delays, especially where service densities have converged in the inner parts of the network.

Most such trains run on the [[List of track gauges|local standard gauge]] track. Some systems may run on a narrower or broader gauge. Examples of [[Narrow gauge railway|narrow gauge]] systems are found in Japan, [[Kereta Commuter Indonesia|Indonesia]], [[KTM Komuter|Malaysia]], [[Greater Bangkok Commuter rail|Thailand]], Switzerland, in the [[Brisbane]] ([[Queensland Rail]]'s [[Queensland Rail City network|City network]]) and [[Perth]] ([[Transperth]]) systems in Australia, in some systems in Sweden, and on the [[:it:Ferrovia Genova-Casella|Genoa-Casella line]] in Italy. Some countries and regions, including [[Helsinki commuter rail|Finland]], India, Pakistan, [[Elektrichka|Russia]], Brazil and Sri Lanka, as well as [[San Francisco]] ([[Bay Area Rapid Transit|BART]]) in the US and [[Metro Trains Melbourne|Melbourne]] and [[Adelaide Metro|Adelaide]] in Australia, use [[broad gauge]] track.

===Distinction between other modes of rail===

====Metro====
Metro rail or [[rapid transit]] usually covers a smaller inner-urban area ranging outwards to between 12&amp;nbsp;km to 20&amp;nbsp;km (or 8 to 14 miles), has a higher train frequency and runs on separate tracks (underground or elevated), whereas commuter rail often shares tracks, technology and the legal framework within mainline railway systems.{{Citation needed|date=September 2018}}

However, the classification as a metro or rapid rail can be difficult as both may typically cover a metropolitan area exclusively, run on separate tracks in the centre, and often feature purpose-built rolling stock. The fact that the terminology is not standardised across countries (even across English-speaking countries) further complicates matters. This distinction is most easily made when there are two (or more) systems such as New York's [[New York City Subway|subway]] and the [[Long Island Rail Road|LIRR]] and [[Metro-North Railroad]], Paris' [[Paris Métro|Métro]] and [[Réseau Express Régional|RER]] along with [[Transilien]], London's tube lines of the [[London Underground|Underground]] and the [[London Overground|Overground]], (future) [[Crossrail]], [[Thameslink (route)|Thameslink]] along with other commuter rail [[Transport in London#Heavy rail|operators]], Madrid's [[Madrid Metro|Metro]] and [[Cercanías Madrid|Cercanías]], Barcelona's [[Barcelona Metro|Metro]] and [[Rodalies de Catalunya|Rodalies]], and Tokyo's [[Tokyo subway|subway]] and the [[East Japan Railway Company#Greater Tokyo Area|JR lines]] along with various privately owned and operated commuter rail systems.

====S-Bahn====

In Germany the [[S-Bahn]] is regarded as a train category of its own, and exists in many large cities and in some other areas, but there are differing service and technical standards from city to city. 
Most S-Bahns typically behave like commuter rail with most trackage not separated from other trains, and long lines with trains running between cities and suburbs rather than within a city. The distances between stations however, are usually short. In larger systems there is usually a high frequency metro-like central corridor in the city center where all the lines converge into. Typical examples of large city S-Bahns include Munich and Frankfurt. S-Bahns do also exist in some mid-size cities like Rostock and Magdeburg but behave more like typical commuter rail with lower frequencies and very little exclusive trackage. In [[Berlin]], the [[Berlin S-Bahn|S-Bahn systems]] arguably fulfill all considerations of a true metro system (despite the existence of [[U-Bahn]]s as well) – the trains run on tracks that are entirely separated from other trains, short distances between stations, high frequency and uses tunnels but do run a bit further out from the city centre, compared with U-Bahn. A similar network exists in [[Copenhagen]] called the [[Copenhagen S-train|S-tog]]. (where a [[Copenhagen Metro|metro system]] also exists). In Hamburg and Copenhagen, other, diesel driven trains, do continue where the S-Bahn ends (&quot;[[AKN Eisenbahn|A-Bahn]]&quot; in Hamburg area, and &quot;L-tog&quot; in Copenhagen).{{Citation needed|date=September 2018}}

====Regional rail====
[[Regional rail]] usually provides [[rail transport|rail services]] between towns and cities, rather than purely linking major population hubs in the way [[inter-city rail]] does. Regional rail operates outside major cities. Unlike Inter-city, it stops at most or all stations between cities. It provides a service between smaller communities along the line, and also connections with long-distance services at interchange stations located at junctions or at larger towns along the line. Alternative names are &quot;local train&quot; or &quot;stopping train&quot;. Examples include the former [[British Rail|BR]]'s [[Regional Railways]], France's [[Transport express régional|TER]] (''Transport express régional''), Germany's [[DB Regio]] and South Korea's [[Tonggeun]] services.{{Citation needed|date=September 2018}}

Regional rail does not exist in this sense in the United States, so the term &quot;regional rail&quot; has become synonymous with commuter rail there, although the two are more clearly defined in Europe.

====Inter-city rail====
{{see also|Inter-city rail}}
[[File:Sydney Trains H22 OSCAR.jpg|thumb|A [[NSW TrainLink]] [[NSW TrainLink H set|H set]] at Sydney's [[Central railway station, Sydney|Central station]].]]
In some European countries the distinction between commuter trains and long-distance/intercity trains is very hard to make, because of the relatively short distances involved. For example, so-called &quot;[[Inter-city rail|intercity]]&quot; trains in Belgium and the Netherlands carry many commuters and their equipment, range and speeds are similar to those of commuter trains in some larger countries. In the United Kingdom there is no real division of organisation and brand name between commuter, regional and inter-city trains, making it hard to categorize train connections.

[[Elektrichka|Russian commuter trains]], on the other hand, frequently cover areas larger than Belgium itself, although these are still short distances by Russian standards. They have a different ticketing system from long-distance trains, and in major cities they often operate from a separate section of the train station.

The easiest way to identify these &quot;inter-city&quot; services is that they tend to operate as express services - only linking the main stations in the cities they link, not stopping at any other stations. However, this term is used in Australia (Sydney for example) to describe the regional trains operating beyond the boundaries of the suburban services, even though some of these &quot;inter-city&quot; services stop all stations similar to German regional services. In this regard, the German service delineations and corresponding naming conventions are clearer and better used for academic purposes.

====High-speed rail====
Sometimes [[high-speed rail]] can serve daily use of commuters. The Japanese [[Shinkansen]] high speed rail system is heavily used by commuters in the [[Greater Tokyo Area]]. They commute between 100 and 200&amp;nbsp;km by [[Shinkansen]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.eesi.org/papers/view/fact-sheet-high-speed-rail-development-worldwide|title=Fact Sheet: High Speed Rail Development Worldwide {{!}} White Papers {{!}} EESI|website=www.eesi.org|access-date=2019-12-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; To meet the demand of commuters, [[Japan Railways Group|JR]] sells commuter discount passes and operates 16-car [[bilevel car|bilevel]] [[E4 Series Shinkansen]] trains at rush hour, providing a capacity of 1,600 seats. Several lines in China, such as the [[Beijing–Tianjin Intercity Railway]] and the [[Shanghai–Nanjing High-Speed Railway]], serve a similar role with many more under construction or planned.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.shine.cn/news/metro/1806116099/|title=Metro closes the gap with areas across the border - SHINE|website=SHINE|language=en|access-date=2018-06-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The high-speed services linking [[Zürich]], [[Bern]] and [[Basel]] in [[Switzerland]] ({{convert|200|km/h|abbr=on}}) have brought the Central Business Districts (CBDs) of these three cities within 1 hour of each other. This has resulted in unexpectedly high demand for new commuter trips between the three cities and a corresponding increase in suburban rail passengers accessing the high-speed services at the main city-centre stations (or Hauptbahnhof). The [[Regional-Express]] commuter service between [[Munich]] and [[Nuremberg]] in Germany go in ({{convert|200|km/h|abbr=on}}) along a [[Nuremberg–Munich high-speed railway|300 km/h high-speed line]].

The regional trains [[Stockholm]]–[[Uppsala]], Stockholm–[[Västerås]], Stockholm–[[Eskilstuna]] and [[Gothenburg]]–[[Trollhättan]] in [[Sweden]] reach {{convert|200|km/h|abbr=on}} and have many daily commuters.

==Train types==
Commuter/suburban trains are usually optimized for maximum passenger volume, in most cases without sacrificing too much comfort and [[luggage]] space, though they seldom have all the amenities of long-distance trains. Cars may be single- or [[bilevel car|double-level]], and aim to provide seating for all. Compared to intercity trains, they have less space, fewer amenities and limited baggage areas.

===Multiple unit type===

[[File:JR East E235 Series No.4 20181108.jpg|thumb|right|An [[electric multiple unit]] on the [[Yamanote Line]] operated by [[JR East]] in [[Tokyo]], Japan]]
Commuter rail trains are usually composed of [[multiple unit]]s, which are self-propelled, bidirectional, articulated passenger rail cars with driving motors on each (or every other) [[bogie]]. Depending on local circumstances and tradition they may be powered either by [[diesel engines]] located below the passenger compartment ([[diesel multiple unit]]s) or by electricity picked up from [[third rail]]s or [[overhead lines]] ([[electric multiple unit]]s). Multiple units are almost invariably equipped with control cabs at both ends, which is why such units are so frequently used to provide commuter services, due to the associated short turn-around time.

===Locomotive hauled services===
[[File:ACE EMD F40PH Fremont - San Jose.jpg|thumb|left|An [[Altamont Corridor Express]] train operating along the [[San Francisco Bay]]; a MPI F40PH-2C locomotive hauls a consist of Bombardier Bi-Level VI coaches.]]
Locomotive hauled services are used in some countries or locations. This is often a case of [[Business operations|asset sweating]], by using a single large combined fleet for intercity and regional services. Loco hauled services are usually run in [[Push-pull train|push-pull]] formation, that is, the train can run with the locomotive at the &quot;front&quot; or &quot;rear&quot; of the train (pushing or pulling). Trains are often equipped with a control cab at the other end of the train from the locomotive, allowing the train operator to operate the train from either end. The motive power for locomotive-hauled commuter trains may be either electric or [[Diesel-electric transmission|diesel-electric]], although some countries, such as Germany and some of the former Soviet-bloc countries, also use diesel-hydraulic locomotives.

=== Seat plans ===
In the US and some other countries, a three-and-two seat plan is used. However, few people sit in the middle seat on these trains because they feel crowded and uncomfortable.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2005/05/31/nyregion/for-train-riders-middle-seat-isnt-the-center-of-attention.html|title=For Train Riders, Middle Seat Isn't the Center of Attention|first=Patrick|last=McGeehan|date=31 May 2005|publisher=|via=NYTimes.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2005/06/06/opinion/on-the-802-express-threes-a-crowd-139947.html|title=On the 8:02 Express, Three's a Crowd|date=6 June 2005|publisher=|via=NYTimes.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Japan and South Korea, longitudinal (sideways window-lining) seating is widely used in many commuter rail trains to increase capacity in rush hours. Carriages are usually not organized to increase [[seating capacity]] (although in some trains at least one carriage would feature more doors to facilitate easier boarding and alighting and bench seats so that they can be folded up during rush hour to provide more standing room) even in the case of commuting longer than 50&amp;nbsp;km and commuters in the [[Greater Tokyo Area]] and the [[Seoul metropolitan area]] have to stand in the train for more than an hour.

==Commuter rail systems around the world==
{{Expand section|date=March 2009}}

===Africa===
{{See also|Template:Suburban railways in Africa}}
[[File:Kalk Bay Station 3.jpg|thumb|A [[Metrorail (South Africa)|Metrorail]] train pulling out of [[Kalk Bay]] station in [[Cape Town]]]]
Currently there are not many examples of commuter rail in Africa. [[Metrorail (South Africa)|Metrorail]] operates in the major cities of South Africa, and there are some commuter rail services in Algeria, Botswana, Kenya, Morocco, Egypt and Tunisia.
In Algeria, [[SNTF]] operates commuter rail lines between the capital [[Algiers]] and its southern and eastern suburbs. They also serve to connect [[Algiers]]' main [[University of Science and Technology, Houari Boumediene|universities]] to each other. The [[Dar es Salaam commuter rail]] offers intracity services in [[Dar es Salaam]], Tanzania. In Botswana, the ([[Botswana Railways]]) &quot;BR Express&quot; has a commuter train between [[Lobatse]] and [[Gaborone]].

===Asia===

====East Asia====
[[File:Tokyo metro 16000.JPG|thumb|right|A [[Tokyo Metro 16000 series]] train operating a through service on the [[JR East]] [[Joban Line]], an example of high-density commuter rail in Japan.]]

In Japan, commuter rail systems have extensive network and frequent service and are heavily used. In many cases, Japanese commuter rail is operationally more like a typical metro system (with very high operating frequencies, an emphasis on [[standing passenger]]s, short station spacing) than it is like commuter rail in other countries. Japanese commuter rail also tends to be heavily interlined with subway lines, with commuter rail trains continuing into the subway network, and then out onto different commuter rail systems on the other side of the city.  Many Japanese commuter systems operate several levels of express trains to reduce the travel time to distant locations, often using station bypass tracks instead of dedicated express tracks. It is notable that the larger Japanese commuter rail systems are owned and operated by for-profit [[private railway]] companies, without public subsidy.

Commuter rail systems have been inaugurated in several cities in China such as [[Beijing Suburban Railway|Beijing]], [[Jinshan Railway|Shanghai]], [[Central Plain Metropolitan Intercity Rail|Zhengzhou]], [[Wuhan Metropolitan Area Intercity Railway|Wuhan]], [[Changsha–Zhuzhou–Xiangtan Intercity Railway|Changsha]] and the [[Pearl River Delta Rapid Transit|Pearl River Delta]]. With plans for large systems in northeastern [[Zhejiang]], [[Jingjinji]], and [[Yangtze River Delta]] areas. The level of service varies considerably from line to line ranging [[high speed rail|high]] to near high speeds. More developed and established lines such as the [[Guangzhou–Shenzhen Railway|Guangshen Railway]] have more frequent metro like service. Hong Kong [[MTR]]'s [[East Rail Line]], [[West Rail Line]] and [[Tung Chung Line]] were built to commuter rail standards but are operated as a metro system.

In Taiwan, [[West Coast line (Taiwan)|Western Line]] in [[Taipei]]-[[Taoyuan City|Taoyuan]] Metropolitan Area, [[Taichung]] Metropolitan Area, [[Tainan]]-[[Kaohsiung]] Metropolitan Area as well as [[Neiwan Line|Neiwan]]-[[Liujia Line]] in [[Hsinchu]] Area is considered commuter rail.

Other examples in East Asia include [[Seoul Metropolitan Subway]] of which some lines are suburban lines operated by [[Korail]] in South Korea.

====Southeast Asia====
[[File:Commuterline at Palmerah Station 4.JPG|thumb|right|Electric multiple unit of [[KA Commuter Jabodetabek|KRL Commuterline]] [[KA Commuter Line Tanah Abang-Maja|Serpong Line]] train at Palmerah Station, [[Jakarta]]]]

In [[Indonesia]], the [[KRL Commuterline]] is the largest commuter rail system in the country, serving [[Jabodetabek|Jakarta metropolitan area]]. It connects the [[Jakarta]] city center with surrounding cities and sub-urbans in [[Banten]] and [[West Java]] provinces, including [[Depok]], [[Bogor]], [[Tangerang]], [[Bekasi]], Serpong and Maja. In July 2015, KA Commuter Jabodetabek served more than 850,000 passengers per day, which is almost triple of the 2011 figures, but still less than 3.5% of all Jabodetabek commutes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://megapolitan.kompas.com/read/2015/07/06/14142481/PT.KCJ.Keterlambatan.KRL.Sudah.di.Bawah.10.Menit |title=PT KCJ: Keterlambatan KRL Sudah di Bawah 10 Menit |date=July 6, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other commuter rail systems in Indonesia include the [[Metro Surabaya Commuter Line]], Prambanan Ekspres Commuter, Solo Ekspres, Kedung Sepur, Greater Bandung Commuter, and Cut Meutia.

In the Philippines, the [[Philippine National Railways]] has two commuter rail systems currently operational; the [[PNR Metro Commuter Line]] in the [[Greater Manila Area]] and the [[PNR Bicol Commuter]] in the [[Bicol Region]]. A new commuter rail line in Metro Manila, the [[North–South Commuter Railway]], is currently under construction. Its North section is set to be partially opened by 2021.

In Malaysia, the [[KTM Komuter]] serves [[Kuala Lumpur]] and the surrounding [[Klang Valley|Klang Valley area]].

In Thailand, the [[Greater Bangkok Commuter rail]] and the [[Airport Rail Link (Bangkok)|Airport Rail Link]] serve the [[Bangkok Metropolitan Region]]. The [[SRT Red Lines]], a new commuter line in Bangkok, started construction in 2009. It is currently slated to be opened by 2020.

Another commuter rail system in Southeast Asia is the [[Yangon Circular Railway]] in [[Myanmar]].

====South Asia====
In India, commuter rail systems are present in major cities. [[Mumbai Suburban Railway]], the oldest suburban rail system in Asia, carries more than 7.24 million commuters on a daily basis which constitutes more than half of the total daily passenger capacity of the Indian Railways itself. [[Kolkata Suburban Railway]] is the biggest Suburban Railway network in India covering 348 stations. The [[Chennai Suburban Railway]] along with [[Chennai MRTS|MRTS]] is another railway of comparison where more than 1 million people travel daily to different areas in [[Chennai]]. Other commuter railways in India include [[Hyderabad MMTS]], [[Delhi Suburban Railway]], [[Pune Suburban Railway]] and [[Lucknow-Kanpur Suburban Railway]].

==== West Asia ====
In Iran, SYSTRA has done a &quot;Tehran long term urban rail study&quot;. SYSTRA proposed 4 express lines similar to [[Réseau Express Régional|RER]] suburban lines in [[Paris]]. [[Tehran Metro]] is going to construct express lines. For instance, the Rahyab Behineh, a consultant for Tehran Metro, is studying Tehran Express Line 2. Tehran Metro currently has a commuter line between [[Tehran]] and [[Karaj]]. [[Isfahan]] has two lines to its suburbs [[Baharestan]] and [[Fuladshahr]] under construction, and a third line to [[Shahinshahr]] is planned.

===Europe===
{{Main|Réseau Express Régional|Commuter rail in the United Kingdom}}
[[File:Ny pendeltag stockholm.jpg|thumb|right|Type [[SL X60|X60]] at Stockholm Central in Sweden]]
Major metropolitan areas in most European countries are usually served by extensive commuter/suburban rail systems. Well-known examples include [[BG Voz]] in [[Belgrade]] (Serbia), [[S-Bahn]] in Germany and German-speaking areas of Switzerland and Austria, [[Proastiakos]] in Greece, [[Réseau Express Régional|RER]] in France and Belgium, [[Milan suburban railway service|suburban lines]] in [[Milan]] (Italy), [[Cercanías]] and [[Rodalies de Catalunya|Rodalies]] ([[Catalonia]]) in Spain, [[CP Urban Services]] in Portugal, [[Esko Prague|Esko]] in [[Prague]] and [[Ostrava]] (Czech Republic), [[HÉV]] in [[Budapest]] (Hungary) and [[Dublin Area Rapid Transit|DART]] in [[Dublin]] (Ireland).

In Russia, Ukraine and some other countries of the former [[Soviet Union]], electrical multiple unit passenger suburban trains called [[Elektrichka]] are widespread.

In Sweden, electrified commuter rail systems known as ''Pendeltåg'' are present in the cities of [[Stockholm]] and [[Gothenburg]]. The [[Stockholm commuter rail]] system, which began in 1968, is similar to the S-Bahn train systems of Munich and Frankfurt such that it may share railway tracks with inter-city trains and freight trains, but for the most part run on its own dedicated tracks, and that it is mainly used to transport passengers from nearby towns and other suburban areas into the city centre, not for transportation inside the city centre. The [[Gothenburg commuter rail]] system, which began in 1960, is similar to the Stockholm system, but does fully share tracks with long-distance trains. Other train systems that are also considered as commuter rail but not counted as ''pendeltåg'' include [[Roslagsbanan]] and [[Saltsjöbanan]] in Stockholm, [[Östgötapendeln]] in [[Östergötland County]], [[Upptåget]] in [[Uppsala County]] and [[Skåne Commuter Rail]].  Skåne Commuter Rail (''Pågatågen'') in [[Skåne County]] acts also as a regional rail system, as it serves cities over 100&amp;nbsp;km (62 miles) and over one hour from the principal city of [[Malmö]].

In Norway, the [[Oslo Commuter Rail|Oslo commuter rail]] system is the largest, which mostly shares tracks with more long-distance trains, but also runs on some local railways without other traffic. Oslo has the largest commuter rail system in Scandinavia measured as line lengths or number of stations. But some lines have travel times (over an hour from Oslo) and frequencies (once per hour) which are more like regional trains. Also [[Bergen Commuter Rail|Bergen]], [[Jæren Commuter Rail|Stavanger]] and [[Trønderbanen|Trondheim]] have commuter rail systems. These have only one or two lines each and they share tracks with other trains.

In [[Finland]], the [[Helsinki commuter rail]] network runs on dedicated tracks from [[Helsinki Central railway station]] to [[Leppävaara railway station|Leppävaara]] and [[Kerava]]. The [[Ring Rail Line]] serves [[Helsinki Airport]] and northern suburbs of [[Vantaa]] and is exclusively used by the commuter rail network. On 15 December 2019 Tampere got its own commuter rail service.

In Poland, commuter rail systems exist in [[Szybka Kolej Miejska (Tricity)|Tricity]], [[Szybka Kolej Miejska (Warsaw)|Warsaw]], [[Krakow]] and [[Katowice]]. There is also a similar system planned in [[Wrocław]] and [[Łódź]].

In Romania, the first commuter trains were introduced in December 2019. They operate currently between [[Bucharest]] and Funduea or [[Buftea]].

===Americas===
====North and Central America====
{{Main|Commuter rail in North America}}
[[File:Metrolink F59PHI 885.jpg|thumb|Metrolink provides commuter rail service to six counties in Southern California.]]
In the United States, Canada, Costa Rica, El Salvador and Mexico regional passenger rail services are provided by governmental or quasi-governmental agencies, with a limited number of metropolitan areas served.

Eight commuter rail systems in the United States carried over ten million trips in 2018:{{Fix|text=which eight out of this list?}}
* [[Metropolitan Transportation Authority]]'s [[Long Island Rail Road]], serving [[New York City]] and [[Long Island]]
* [[NJ Transit Rail Operations]], serving New York City, New Jersey ([[Newark, New Jersey|Newark]], [[Trenton, New Jersey|Trenton]]) and [[Philadelphia]]
* Metropolitan Transportation Authority's [[Metro-North Railroad]], serving New York ([[Yonkers, New York|Yonkers]] and New York City) and Southwest Connecticut ([[Bridgeport, Connecticut|Bridgeport]])
* [[Metra]], serving northeast Illinois ([[Chicago]]), [[Northern Indiana]], and [[Kenosha, Wisconsin]]
* [[SEPTA Regional Rail]], serving southeast Pennsylvania (Philadelphia), as well as [[Wilmington, Delaware]], and [[Trenton, New Jersey]]
* [[Massachusetts Bay Transit Authority]], serving Massachusetts (Boston, [[Worcester, Massachusetts|Worcester]]) and [[Providence, Rhode Island|Providence]], [[Rhode Island]]
* [[Caltrain]], serving California ([[San Francisco]], [[San Jose, California|San Jose]], and the [[San Francisco Peninsula]])
* [[Metrolink (California)|Metrolink]], serving California ([[Los Angeles]], [[Burbank, California|Burbank]], [[Anaheim, California|Anaheim]], [[San Bernardino, California|San Bernardino]], and [[Southern California]])
*[[Utah Transit Authority]] [[FrontRunner]], serving Utah ([[Wasatch Front]])
*[[North County Transit District]] [[Coaster (San Diego)|Coaster]], serving California ([[San Diego County]])
*[[Maryland Area Regional Commuter]], serving [[Maryland]] ([[Baltimore]]) and [[Washington, D.C.]]
*[[Regional Transportation District]], serving [[Colorado]] ([[Denver]])
*[[Virginia Railway Express]], serving suburbs of [[Northern Virginia]] and [[Washington, D.C.]]
*[[Sounder commuter rail]], serving [[Washington (state)|Washington]] ([[Seattle]] / [[Tacoma, Washington|Tacoma]])
*[[Tri-Rail]], serving [[Florida]] ([[Miami]] / [[Fort Lauderdale]] / [[West Palm Beach]])
*[[Trinity Railway Express]], serving [[Texas]] ([[Dallas]] / [[Fort Worth]])
*[[Altamont Corridor Express]], serving [[California]] ([[San Jose, California|San Jose]] / [[Stockton, California|Stockton]])
*[[SunRail]], serving [[Florida]] ([[Orlando]]/[[Poinciana, Florida|Poinciana]])
*[[WES Commuter Rail]], serving [[Oregon]] ([[Beaverton, Oregon|Beverton]]/[[willsonville, Oregon|Willsonville]])
*[[New Mexico Rail Runner Express]], serving [[New Mexico]] ([[Albuquerque, New Mexico|Albuquerque]])
*[[Northstar Line]], serving [[Minnesota]] ([[Big Lake, Minnesota|Big Lake]] and downtown [[Minneapolis]])
*[[Capital MetroRail]], serving [[Texas]] ([[Austin]])
*[[A-train (Denton County)|A-train]],serving [[Texas]] ([[Denton County]])
*[[Sonoma–Marin Area Rail Transit|SMART]], serving [[California]] ([[Sonoma County, California|Sonoma]] and [[Marin County, California|Marin]] counties)
*[[Music City Star]], serving [[Nashville]] and [[Lebanon, Tennessee]].

North American commuter rail systems outside of the United States include:
* [[GO Transit rail services]] in [[Toronto]]
* [[Exo (public transit)|Exo]] in [[Montreal]]
* [[West Coast Express]] in [[Vancouver]]
* [[Suburban Railway of the Valley of Mexico Metropolitan Area]] serving [[Mexico City]]
* [[Rail transport in Honduras|City Rail]] in [[La Ceiba]], [[Honduras]]
* [[Havana Suburban Railway]] in [[Cuba]]
* [[Panama Canal Railway]] in [[Panama]]
* [[Tren Urbano de Costa Rica]] in [[Costa Rica]]

====South America====
[[File:EMU CSR M20 en Barrancas.jpg|thumb|The [[Mitre Line]] is part of the extensive [[Rail transport in Argentina#Commuter networks|Buenos Aires metropolitan rail system]].]]
Examples include an {{convert|899|km|mi|adj=on|abbr=on}} commuter system in the [[Rail transport in Argentina#Commuter networks|Buenos Aires metropolitan area]], the {{convert|225|km|mi|adj=on|abbr=on}} long [[Supervia]] in [[Rio de Janeiro]], the [[Metrotrén]] in [[Santiago]], [[Chile]], and the [[Valparaíso Metro]] in [[Valparaíso]], Chile. Another example is [[Companhia Paulista de Trens Metropolitanos]] (CPTM) in [[Greater São Paulo]], [[Brazil]]. CPTM has 94 stations with seven lines, numbered starting on 7 (the lines 1 to 6 and the line 15 belong to the [[São Paulo Metro]]), with a total length of {{convert|273|km}}.

===Oceania===
{{Main|Rail transport in Australia}}
[[File:Siemens train in Metro Trains Melbourne Livery.jpg|thumb|A Melbourne Siemens commuter train]]
The five major cities in Australia have suburban railway systems in their metropolitan areas. These networks have frequent services, with frequencies varying from every 10 to every 30 minutes on most suburban lines, and up to 3–5 minutes in peak on bundled underground lines in the city centres of Sydney, Brisbane, Perth and Melbourne. The networks in each state developed from mainline railways and have never been completely operationally separate from long distance and freight traffic, unlike [[Rapid transit|metro]] systems in some comparable countries, but nevertheless have cohesive identities and are the backbones of their respective cities' public transport system. The suburban networks are almost completely electrified.

The main suburban rail networks in Australia are:
*The [[Railways in Sydney|Sydney rail network]] operated by [[Sydney Trains]] in [[Sydney]] (with connected suburban services in [[Newcastle, New South Wales|Newcastle]] and [[Wollongong]] run by its counterpart intercity operator, [[NSW TrainLink]]).
*The [[Railways in Melbourne|Melbourne rail network]] operated by [[Metro Trains Melbourne]] in [[Melbourne]].
*The [[Queensland Rail City network]] operated by [[Queensland Rail]] in [[Brisbane]].
*[[Transperth Trains]] in [[Perth]].
*The [[Railways in Adelaide|Adelaide rail network]] operated by [[Adelaide Metro]] in [[Adelaide]].

New Zealand has two frequent suburban rail services comparable to those in Australia: the [[Public transport in Auckland|Auckland rail network]] is operated by [[Transdev Auckland]] and the [[Public transport in the Wellington Region|Wellington rail network]] is operated by [[Transdev Wellington]].

==See also==
{{colbegin}}
*[[List of suburban and commuter rail systems]]
*[[Public transport]]
*[[Commuting]]
*[[Cercanías]], the commuter rail systems of Spain's major metropolitan areas
*[[Commuter rail in the United Kingdom]]
*[[Commuter rail in North America]]
*[[Commuter rail in Australia]]
*[[S-Bahn]], the combined city center and suburban railway system metro in Austria, Germany, Switzerland and Denmark
{{colend}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20070515131747/http://www.railserve.com/railnews/commuter_rail_transit.html Commuter Rail &amp; Transit News] Current news concerning commuter rail development and issues

{{Public transport}}
{{Portal bar|Transport}}

[[Category:Regional rail|*]]</text>
      <sha1>n18y9cxmzsjtm0lzzlsegbq648rd50u</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
