  <page>
    <title>Atari 7800</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2781</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941653603</id>
      <parentid>937673331</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-19T22:11:23Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Crgcrg</username>
        <id>38542067</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Updated Graphics Clock Information</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox CVG system
|title=Atari 7800 System
| logo = File:Atari 7800 Logo.png
| image = [[File:Atari-7800-Console-Set.jpg|300px|Atari 7800 System (American system with joystick controller)]]&lt;br /&gt;[[File:Atari-7800-wControl-Pad-L.jpg|frameless|300px|Atari 7800 System (PAL system with Joypad controller)]]
| caption = '''Top:''' North American 7800.&lt;br /&gt;'''Bottom:''' European 7800.
| manufacturer = [[Atari, Inc.]]&lt;br&gt;[[Atari Corporation]]
| type = [[Home video game console]]
| generation = [[Third generation of video game consoles|Third generation]]
| release date = US: May 1986&lt;ref name=&quot;CE2&quot;/&gt;&lt;br /&gt;PAL: 1987
| discontinued = January 1, [[1992 in video gaming|1992]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.gamesradar.com/f/consoles-of-the-80s/a-200806189420522063/p-4 |title=Consoles of the '80s |first=Shane |last=Patterson |author2=Brett Elston |publisher=[[GamesRadar]] |accessdate=1 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| CPU = Atari SALLY [[MOS Technology 6502|6502]] (&quot;6502C&quot;) clocked at 1.19-1.79MHz,
| memory = 4KB [[RAM]], 4KB [[BIOS]] [[Read-only memory|ROM]], 48KB Cartridge ROM Space
| display = 160×240, 320×240 (160×288/320×288 if [[PAL]]), 25 on-screen colours out of possible 256
| media = [[ROM cartridge]]
| onlineservice = 
| units sold =
| topgame = 
| compatibility = [[Atari 2600]]
| predecessor = [[Atari 5200]]
| successor = [[Atari XEGS]]
| price = {{US$|140|1986|round=0}}
| graphics = MARIA custom chip @ 7.16 MHz
}}

The '''Atari 7800 ProSystem''', or simply the '''Atari 7800''', is a [[home video game console]] officially released by the [[Atari Corporation]] in 1986.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ign.com/top-25-consoles/17.html Top 25 Videogame Consoles of All Time: Atari 7800 is Number 17], IGN.&lt;/ref&gt; It is almost fully [[Backward compatibility|backward-compatible]] with the [[Atari 2600]], the first console to have backward compatibility without the use of additional modules. It was considered affordable at a price of {{US$|140|1986|round=0}}.

The 7800 has significantly improved graphics hardware over the 2600, but uses the same audio chip. It also shipped with a different model of joystick from the 2600-standard [[Atari CX40 joystick|CX40]].

The 1986 launch is sometimes referred to as a &quot;re-release&quot; or &quot;relaunch&quot; because the Atari 7800 had originally been announced on May 21, 1984, to replace Atari Inc.'s [[Atari 5200]],&lt;ref name=&quot;press release&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[https://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?sec=technology&amp;res=9F06E5D7163BF931A15756C0A962948260 Atari Video Game Unit Introduced]&quot;, ''New York Times''&lt;/ref&gt; but a general release was shelved due to the sale of the company.&lt;ref&gt;[http://atariage.com/7800/history.html AtariAge: Atari 7800 History], AtariAge.&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
Atari had been facing pressure from Coleco and its [[ColecoVision]] console, which supported graphics that more closely mirrored [[arcade game]]s of the time than either the Atari 2600 or 5200. The Atari 5200 (released as a successor to the Atari 2600) was criticized for not being able to play 2600 games without an adapter.

The Atari 7800 ProSystem was the first console from [[Atari, Inc.]] designed by an outside company, [[General Computer Corporation]] (GCC). It was designed in 1983-1984 with an intended mass market rollout in June of 1984, but was canceled shortly thereafter due to the sale of the company to [[Jack Tramiel|Tramel Technology Ltd]] on July 2, 1984. The project was originally called the Atari 3600.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.atarimuseum.com/videogames/consoles/7800/7800menu/ |title=The Atari 7800 ProSystem |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://archive.is/20130117172550/http://www.atarimuseum.com/videogames/consoles/7800/7800menu/ |archivedate=2013-01-17 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

With a background in creating arcade games such as ''[[Food Fight (video game)|Food Fight]]'', GCC designed the new system with a graphics architecture similar to arcade machines of the time. Powering the system is a slightly customized [[MOS Technology 6502|6502]] processor, the Atari SALLY (sometimes described as a &quot;6502C&quot;),&lt;ref name=&quot;EGM62&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last= |first= |title=When Pac Ruled the Earth|work=[[Electronic Gaming Monthly]]|issue=62|publisher=EGM Media, LLC|date=September 1994|page=18}}&lt;/ref&gt; running at 1.79&amp;nbsp;MHz. By some measures the 7800 is more powerful, and by others less, than Nintendo's 1983 [[Famicom]].&lt;ref name=&quot;vs7800&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=7800 compared to the NES|url=https://sites.google.com/site/atari7800wiki/7800-compared-to-the-nes|website=Atari 7800 Programming}}&lt;/ref&gt; It uses the 2600's [[Television Interface Adaptor]] chip, with the same restrictions, for generating two-channels of audio.

=== Launch ===
The 7800 was initially released in southern [[California]] in June 1984,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Atari, Inc|last=Goldberg|first=Marty|publisher=Syzygy Co.|year=2012|isbn=0985597402|location=Carmel, NY|pages=|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/atariincbusiness0000gold}}&lt;/ref&gt; following an announcement on May 21, 1984, at the Summer [[Consumer Electronics Show]].&lt;ref name=&quot;press release&quot;&gt;{{cite press release |title=Atari unveils advanced video game that is expandable to introductory computer |publisher=Atari, Inc. |url=http://www.atari7800.org/museum/PressDoc1s.htm |accessdate=2010-04-30 |date=1984-05-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thirteen games were announced for the system's launch: ''[[Ms. Pac-Man]]'', ''[[Pole Position II]]'', ''[[Centipede (video game)|Centipede]]'', ''[[Joust (video game)|Joust]]'', ''[[Dig Dug]]'', ''[[Desert Falcon]]'', ''[[Robotron: 2084]]'', ''[[Galaga]]'', ''[[Food Fight (video game)|Food Fight]]'', ''[[Ballblazer]]'', ''[[Rescue on Fractalus!]]'', ''[[Track &amp; Field (video game)|Track &amp; Field]]'', and ''[[Xevious]]''.

On July 2, 1984, [[Time Warner|Warner Communications]] sold Atari's Consumer Division to [[Jack Tramiel]].&lt;ref&gt;[Retrogamer Magazine, Issue #78, pp 53.]&lt;/ref&gt; All projects were halted during an initial evaluation period. Modern publications have often incorrectly asserted that Jack Tramiel mothballed the Atari 7800, feeling that video games were a past fad, and subsequently asserted that he dusted off the Atari 7800 once the [[Nintendo Entertainment System]] became successful. The reality was that a contractual issue arose in that GCC had not been paid for their development of the 7800. Warner and Tramiel battled back and forth over who was accountable, with Tramiel believing that the 7800 should have been covered as part of his acquisition deal. In May 1985, Jack relented and paid GCC the overdue payment. This led to additional negotiations regarding the initial launch titles that GCC had developed and then an effort to find someone to lead their new video game division, which was completed in November 1985.&lt;ref&gt;[Retrogamer Magazine, Issue #78, pp 57]&lt;/ref&gt;

The original production run of the Atari 7800 languished on warehouse shelves until it was re-introduced in January 1986, after strong 2600 sales the previous Christmas.&lt;ref&gt;[http://tnca.myrmid.com/art9.htm Atari, Sega, and Nintendo Plan Comeback for Video Games - HFD: The Weekly Home Furnishings Newspaper]&lt;/ref&gt; The console was released nationwide in May 1986 for $79.95.&lt;ref name=&quot;CE2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=|title=Atari's &quot;Jr Pac-Man&quot; scores for looks, sound|last=Semrad|first=Edward|date=1986-06-26|work=The Milwaukee Journal|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The console's launch under  Tramiel was more subdued than Warner had planned for the system in 1984 with a marketing budget of just $300,000&lt;ref&gt;https://web.archive.org/web/20050309231257/http://www.icwhen.com/book/the_1980s/1986.shtml&lt;/ref&gt; ({{Inflation|US|300,000|1986|fmt=eq}}).The keyboard and high score cartridge were canceled, the expansion port was removed from later production runs of the system and, in lieu of new titles, the system was launched with titles intended for the 7800's debut in 1984.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|title=Atari 7800 - History of Video Game Consoles Wiki Guide - IGN|url=https://www.ign.com/wikis/history-of-video-game-consoles/Atari_7800|language=en|access-date=2019-01-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

By the end of 1986, ''Computer Entertainer'' claimed the Atari 7800 had sold 100,000 consoles in the United States,&lt;ref name=&quot;CE2&quot;&gt;''Computer Entertainer'', February 1987, [http://i.imgur.com/eUXac6M.jpg page 13]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CE1&quot;&gt;''Computer Entertainer'', December 1986, [http://i.imgur.com/fyarkYE.jpg page 8]&lt;/ref&gt; less than the [[Master System]]'s 125,000 and the NES's 1.1 million.&lt;ref name=&quot;CE2&quot;/&gt; According to Atari, due to manufacturing problems, it only managed to produce and sell 100,000 units by 1986, including units that had been in a warehouse since 1984. A common complaint in 1986 was a lack of games, including a gap of months between new releases (''[[Galaga]]''{{'}}s release in August was followed by ''[[Xevious]]'' in November).&lt;ref name=&quot;CE1&quot;/&gt; By the end of 1986, the 7800 had 10 games, compared to Sega's 20 and Nintendo's 36. Nine of the NES games were third-party, whereas the 7800 and Master System had no third-party games.&lt;ref name=&quot;CE2&quot;/&gt;

=== Games ===
Atari's lineup for the 7800 emphasized high-quality versions of popular arcade games like ''[[Joust (video game)|Joust]]'' and ''[[Asteroids (video game)|Asteroids]]'',&lt;ref name=&quot;cgw198808&quot;&gt;{{cite magazine | title=Video Gaming World | magazine=[[Computer Gaming World]] | issue=50 | date=August 1988 | url=http://www.cgwmuseum.org/galleries/issues/cgw_50.pdf | accessdate=17 April 2016 | last1=Katz | first1=Arnie | last2=Kunkel | first2=Bill | last3=Worley | first3=Joyce | pages=47}}&lt;/ref&gt; which at the time of the 1986 launch were four and seven years old, respectively.

Eleven titles were developed and sold by three third-party companies under their own labels for the 7800 ([[Absolute Entertainment]], [[Activision]], and [[Froggo]]) with the rest published by Atari themselves. However, most Atari development was contracted out.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Jung|first1=Robert A.|title=The Atari Timeline|url=https://www.landley.net/history/mirror/atari/museum/Atari-Timeline.html|website=Landley|accessdate=13 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some NES titles were developed by companies who had licensed their title from a different arcade manufacturer. While the creator of the NES version would be restricted from making a competitive version of an NES game, the original arcade copyright holder was not precluded from licensing out rights for a home version of an arcade game to multiple systems. Through this loophole, Atari 7800 conversions of ''[[Mario Bros.]]'', ''[[Double Dragon]]'', ''[[Commando (video game)|Commando]]'', ''[[Rampage (video game)|Rampage]]'', ''[[Xenophobe (video game)|Xenophobe]]'', ''[[Ikari Warriors]]'', and ''[[Kung-Fu Master (video game)|Kung-Fu Master]]'' were licensed and developed.{{citation needed|date=March 2014}}

=== Discontinuation ===
The Atari 7800 remained officially active in the United States between 1986 and 1991 and in Europe between 1989 and 1991. On January 1, 1992, Atari Corp. formally announced that production of the Atari 7800, the Atari 2600, the Atari 8-bit computer line, and the Atari XE Game System would cease. (It has since been discovered that Atari Corp. continued to develop games such as ''[[Toki (video game)|Toki]]'' for the Atari 7800 until all development was shut down in May 1993.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://betaphasegames.com/7800_Toki_Screens.html|title=TOKI FOR 7800: DISCOVERY ANNOUNCEMENT|website=Beta Phase Games|access-date=2018-04-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;) By the time of the cancellation, Nintendo's NES dominated the North American market, controlling 80% while Atari Corp. controlled just 12%.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=https://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3DD143EF935A25756C0A964958260 | work=[[The New York Times]] | title=COMPANY NEWS; Nintendo Suit by Atari Is Dismissed | date=May 16, 1992 | accessdate=April 25, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite trailing the Nintendo Entertainment System in terms of the number of units sold, the 7800 was a profitable enterprise for Atari Corp., benefiting largely from Atari's name and the system's 2600 compatibility. Profits were strong owing to low investment in game development and marketing.{{citation needed|date=March 2014}}

''Retro Gamer'' magazine issue 132 reported that according to Atari UK Marketing Manager Darryl Still &quot;it was very well stocked by European retail&quot;, &quot;Although it never got the consumer traction that the 2600 did, I remember we used to sell a lot of units through mail order catalogues and in the less affluent areas&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;retgam132&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Atari 7800 Prosystem 30th Anniversary |url=https://issuu.com/michelfranca/docs/retro_gamer____132 |publisher=Retro Gamer |accessdate=18 August 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Technical specifications==
[[File:Atari-7800-Motherboard-01.jpg|thumb|Motherboard of an American 7800 with the RF shielding removed]]
[[File:Atari-7800-Motherboard-Euro-wRGB-FL.jpg|thumb|European motherboard modified by Atari to output RGB though a SCART connector]]
* CPU: Atari SALLY [[MOS Technology 6502|6502]] (&quot;6502C&quot;)
** Speed: 1.79&amp;nbsp;MHz; drops to 1.19&amp;nbsp;MHz when the TIA [[Television Interface Adaptor]] or RIOT ([[MOS Technology 6532|6532 RAM-I/O-Timer]]) chips are accessed
** (note: Unlike a standard 6502, ''SALLY'' can be halted to allow other devices to control the bus)
* [[Random-access memory|RAM]]: 4 KB&lt;ref name=&quot;EGM62&quot;/&gt; (2 6116 2Kx8 RAM ICs)
* [[Read-only memory|ROM]]: built in 4 KB [[BIOS]] ROM, 48 KB Cartridge ROM space without [[bank switching]]
* Graphics: MARIA custom chip
** Resolution: 160×240 (160×288 [[PAL Region|PAL]]) or 320×240 (320×288 PAL)
** Color palette: 256&lt;ref name=&quot;EGM62&quot;/&gt; (16 hues * 16 luma), different graphics modes restricted the number of usable colors and the number of colors per sprite
** [[Direct memory access|Direct Memory Access]] (DMA)
** Graphics clock: 7.15&amp;nbsp;MHz&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.computinghistory.org.uk/det/15473/Atari-7800/|title=Atari 7800 - Game Console - Computing History|website=www.computinghistory.org.uk|access-date=2020-02-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=maria&gt;http://www.atarimuseum.com/ahs_archives/archives/pdf/videogames/7800/gcc1702b_maria_specs.pdf{{dead link|date=October 2016 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Framebuffer|Line buffer]]: 200 bytes ([[Multiple buffering#Double buffering in computer graphics|double buffering]]), 160 [[Texel (graphics)|sprite pixels]] per [[Scan line|scanline]],&lt;ref name=maria/&gt; up to 30 [[Sprite (computer graphics)|sprites]] per scanline (without background),&lt;ref&gt;http://sites.google.com/site/atari7800wiki/7800-compared-to-the-nes&lt;/ref&gt; up to 100 sprites on screen&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ataritimes.com/index.php?ArticleIDX%3D632 |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2014-09-29 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140628043258/http://ataritimes.com/index.php?ArticleIDX=632 |archivedate=2014-06-28 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.atarimuseum.com/videogames/consoles/7800/7800.html{{dead link|date=October 2016 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Sprite (computer graphics)|Sprite]]/zone sizes: 4&lt;ref name=programming&gt;http://sites.google.com/site/atari7800wiki/graphics-programming&lt;/ref&gt; to 160&lt;ref name=maria/&gt; width, height of 4,&lt;ref name=programming/&gt; 8 or 16&lt;ref name=guide/&gt; pixels
** Colors per sprite: 1 to 12 (1 to 8 visible colors, 1 to 4 transparency bits)&lt;ref name=guide&gt;http://atarihq.com/danb/files/7800%20Software%20Guide.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
* I/O: Joystick and console switch IO handled by [[MOS Technology 6532|6532 RIOT]] and TIA
* Ports: 2 joystick ports, 1 cartridge port, 1 expansion connector, power in, RF output
* Sound: [[Television Interface Adaptor|TIA]] as used in the 2600 for video and sound. In 7800 mode only the sound functionality is used.
** Cartridges could provide additional sound hardware. A [[POKEY]] [[sound chip]] was used on at least two games.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=bGEbLt1C168C&amp;pg=PA201#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|title=Hardware Hacking: Have Fun while Voiding your Warranty|last=Grand|first=Joe|last2=Mitnick|first2=Kevin D.|last3=Russell|first3=Ryan|date=2004-01-29|publisher=Elsevier|year=|isbn=978-0-08-047825-8|location=|pages=201|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://visual6502.org/images/pages/Atari_C012294_POKEY_die_shots.html|title=Atari C012294 POKEY|website=visual6502.org|access-date=2019-12-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Graphics ===
The graphics are generated by a custom chip called MARIA, which uses an approach common in contemporary arcade [[Arcade system board|system boards]]&lt;ref name=guide/&gt; and is  different from other [[Second generation of video game consoles|second]] and [[Third generation of video game consoles|third generation]] consoles. Instead of a limited number of hardware sprites, MARIA treats everything as a sprite described in a series of [[display list]]s. Each display list contains pointers to graphics data and color and positioning information.

MARIA supports a palette of 256 colors and graphics modes which are either 160 pixels wide or 320 pixels wide. While the 320 pixel modes theoretically enable the 7800 to create games at higher resolution than the 256 pixel wide graphics found in the [[Nintendo Entertainment System]] and [[Master System]], the processing demands of MARIA result in most games using the 160 pixel mode.{{citation needed|date=March 2014}}

Depending on various parameters, each individual sprite can use from 1 to 12 colors, with 3 colors (plus a 4th &quot;transparency&quot; color) being the most common. In this format, the sprite is referenced to one of 8 palettes, where each palette holds 3 assignable colors. There is also an assignable background color, which will be visible wherever another object has not covered it up. In total the system can reference a 25-color palette on a scanline.&lt;ref name=&quot;atarimuseum.com&quot;&gt;http://www.atarimuseum.com/ahs_archives/archives/archives-techdocs-7800.htm{{dead link|date=October 2016 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The graphics resolution, color palette assignments, and background color can be adjusted in between scanlines. This technique is documented in the original 1983 ''Atari 3600 Software Guide''.&lt;ref name=&quot;atarimuseum.com&quot;/&gt; This could be used to render high resolution text in one area of the screen, while displaying more colorful graphics at lower resolution in the gameplay area.

The MARIA's approach has advantages and disadvantages when it comes to generating graphics. It excels at moving large numbers of sprites on a static screen. Its flexible design enables games with a pseudo 3D appearance such as ''[[Ballblazer]]'' (1987) and ''F-18 Hornet'' (1988). While side-scrolling games in the vein of ''[[Super Mario Bros.]]'' are possible on the system (such as 1990's ''Scrapyard Dog''), it is harder to develop such a title than on a tile-based system such as the NES.{{citation needed|date=March 2014}}

=== Sound ===

A common criticism of the 7800 regards its use of the TIA to provide 2-channel sound effects and music, resulting in sound quality that is virtually identical to the Atari 2600 VCS from 1977. While the inclusion of 2600 hardware is required to maintain compatibility with the older system, this drove up production costs and reduced available space on the 7800's motherboard. As such, the 7800 does not include additional hardware for generating sound as it does with graphics, and the sound hardware is considered the weakest part of the system.

To compensate for this, GCC's engineers allowed games to include a [[Atari POKEY|POKEY audio chip]] in the cartridge which substantially improved the audio quality. To ensure software developers had an economical means of producing better sound than TIA, GCC had originally planned to make a low-cost, high performance sound chip, GUMBY, which could also be placed in 7800 cartridges to enhance its sound capabilities further. This project was cancelled when Atari was sold to Jack Tramiel.

Despite having the capability to support sound chips in cartridges, almost no 7800 cartridges feature POKEY hardware for enhanced sound. ''Ballblazer'', released in 1987, uses the POKEY to generate all music and sound effects. Similarly, ''[[Commando (video game)|Commando]]'', released in 1989, uses a POKEY to generate in-game music while the TIA generates the game's sound effects for a total of 6 channels of sound.

=== Lockout features ===
Following the debate over ''[[Custer's Revenge]]'', an Atari 2600 VCS title with adult themes, Atari had concerns over similar adult titles finding their way onto the 7800 and displaying adult content using the significantly improved graphics capabilities of the MARIA chip. To combat this, they included a digital signature protection method which prevented unauthorized 7800 games from being played on the system.

When a cartridge was inserted into the system, the 7800 BIOS included code which would generate a digital signature of the cartridge ROM and compare it to the signature stored on the cartridge. If a correct signature was located on the cartridge, the 7800 would operate in 7800 mode, granting the game access to MARIA and other features. If a signature was not located, the 7800 remained in 2600 mode and MARIA was unavailable. All 7800 games released in North America had to be digitally signed by Atari. This digital signature code is not present in PAL 7800s, which use various heuristics to detect 2600 cartridges, due to export restrictions. The signing utility was found and released by Classic Gaming Expo in 2001.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Boris|first=Dan|title=The Encryption Issue|url=http://atarihq.com/danb/a7800.shtml#encryption|work=Atari 7800 Tech Page|accessdate=2 October 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Backward compatibility ===
The Atari 7800 differs from the 2600 in several key areas. It features a full Atari SALLY 6502 processor whereas the 2600 VCS has a stripped-down 6507 processor running at a slower speed. It has additional [[RAM]] (Random Access Memory) and the ability to access more cartridge data at one time than the 2600. The most substantial difference, however, is a graphics architecture which differs markedly from either the Atari 2600 VCS or Atari's 8-bit line of computers.

The 7800's compatibility with the Atari 2600 is made possible by including many of the same chips used in the Atari 2600. When operating in “2600” mode to play Atari 2600 titles, the 7800 uses a Television Interface Adapter (TIA) chip to generate graphics and sound. The processor is slowed to 1.19&amp;nbsp;MHz, enabling the 7800 to mirror the performance of the 2600's 6507 processor. RAM is limited to 128 bytes found in the RIOT and game data is accessed in 4K blocks.

When in “7800” mode (signified by the appearance of the full-screen Atari logo), the graphics are generated entirely by the MARIA graphics processing unit. All system RAM is available and game data is accessed in larger 48K blocks. The system's SALLY 6502 runs at its normal 1.79&amp;nbsp;MHz instead of the reduced speed of 2600 mode. The 2600 chips are used in 7800 mode to generate sound and to provide the interfaces to the controllers and console switches.

The Atari 7800 does not support backward compatibility for Atari 5200 games or accessories.

===System revisions===
Prototypes:
* Atari 3600, original model number
* Atari CX-9000 Video Computer System

Production:
* Atari CX7800, two joystick ports on lower front panel. Side expansion port for upgrades and add-ons. Bundled accessories included two CX24 Pro-Line joysticks, AC adapter, switchbox, RCA connecting cable, and [[Pole Position II]] cartridge.
* Atari CX7800, second revision. Slightly revised motherboard, added an additional timing circuit. Expansion port connector removed from motherboard but is still etched. Shell has indentation of where expansion port was to be.
* Atari CX7800, third revision. Same as above but with only a small blemish on the shell where the expansion port was.

== Peripherals ==
[[File:Atari-CX78-7800-Controller-FL-wThumbStick.jpg|thumb|250px|The [[gamepad]] of later European Atari 7800s with the thumbstick screwed in]]

The Atari 7800 came bundled with the Atari Pro-Line Joystick, a two-button controller with a [[joystick]] for movement. The Pro-Line was originally developed for the 2600 and was advertised in 1983,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Catalog - Atari (CO21776-Rev. A) |url=https://atariage.com/catalog_thumbs.php?CatalogID=38 |website=AtariAge }}&lt;/ref&gt; but delayed until Atari proceeded with the 7800. The right fire button only works as a separate fire button for certain 7800 games that utilize it; otherwise, it duplicates the left fire button, allowing either button to be used for 2600 games. The 7800's controllers were incompatible with the [[Master System]], and Sega's controllers were unable to use the 7800's two-button mode.

In response to criticism over ergonomic issues in the 7800's Pro-Line controllers, Atari later released a joypad controller with the European 7800.{{Citation needed|date=December 2019}} It was similar in style to controllers found on Nintendo and Sega Systems. The joypad was not available in the United States.

There were few add-on peripherals for the 7800, though its backwards compatibility feature allowed it to use most Atari 2600 peripherals. The [[Atari XG-1 light gun]], which came bundled with the [[Atari XEGS]], was sold separately for other Atari systems and was compatible with the 7800. Atari released five 7800 light gun games: ''[[Alien Brigade]]'', ''Barnyard Blaster'', ''[[Crossbow (video game)|Crossbow]]'', ''Meltdown'', and ''Sentinel''.

=== Canceled peripherals ===
After the acquisition of the Atari Consumer Division by [[Jack Tramiel]] in 1984, a number of planned peripherals for the system were canceled:

* The High Score Cartridge was designed to save player high scores for up to 65 separate games.{{Citation needed|date=December 2019}} The cartridge was intended as a pass-through device (similar to the later [[Game Genie]]). Nine games were programmed with the feature but the cartridge was canceled before it was released.
* The 7800 has an expansion port to allow for the addition of a planned computer keyboard and connection to laserdisc players and other peripherals. The expansion port was removed in the second and third revisions of the 7800.{{cn|date=June 2017}}
* A dual joystick holder was designed for ''[[Robotron: 2084]]'' and future games like ''[[Battlezone (1980 video game)|Battlezone]]'', but not produced.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.atarimuseum.com/videogames/consoles/&lt;/ref&gt;

== Software library ==
{{Main|List of Atari 7800 games|List of Atari 2600 games}}
[[File:Atari 7800 with Cartridge.jpg|thumb|Atari 7800 with ''Donkey Kong Junior'' cartridge]]

While the 7800 can actually play hundreds of titles due to its compatibility with the Atari 2600, there was limited third-party support for the 7800 and fewer than 100 titles were specifically designed for it.

==Legacy==
===Atari Flashback===
In 2004, Atari (now owned by [[Infogrames Entertainment, SA|Infogrames]]) released the first [[Atari Flashback]] console. This system resembled a miniature Atari 7800 and joysticks and had 20 built in games (five 7800 and fifteen 2600 titles). While the unit sold well, it was controversial among Atari fans. Atari had given the engineering firm, Legacy Engineering, extremely limited development timelines. The firm was forced to build the Flashback using [[Nintendo Entertainment System hardware clone|NES-On-A-Chip]] hardware instead of recreating the Atari 7800 hardware. As a result, the Flashback has been criticized for failing to properly replicate the actual Atari gaming experience.

Legacy Engineering was later commissioned to create another 7800 project that was subsequently cancelled after prototypes were made.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.legacyengineer.com/portfolio-7800.html |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2010-12-22 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110311035331/http://www.legacyengineer.com/portfolio-7800.html |archivedate=2011-03-11 }} Legacy 7800 remade&lt;/ref&gt;

===Emulation and homebrew===
When emulators of 1980s video game consoles began to appear on home computers in the late 1990s, the Atari 7800 was one of the last to be emulated. The lack of awareness of the system, the lack of understanding of the hardware, and fears about the digital signature lockout initially caused concerns. Since that time, however, the 7800 has been emulated successfully and is now common on emulation sites. One such program is ProSystem, written in C/C++ for the [[Microsoft Windows]] operating system.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| last1         = Kohler| first1        = Chris| others        = foreword by [[Al Lowe]]| title         = Retro Gaming Hacks| edition       = 1st| date          = 2005-10-12| publisher     = [[O'Reilly Media]]| location      = Sebastopol, CA| isbn          = 0-596-00917-8| pages         = 156&amp;nbsp;–  157|chapter       = Playing Classic Console Games}}&lt;/ref&gt; It uses the Windows API and DirectX to display what it emulates in both [[PAL]] and [[NTSC]].

The digital signature long prevented homebrew games from being developed until the original encryption generating software was discovered. When the original digital signature generating software was turned over to the Atari community, development of new Atari 7800 titles began. In addition, the Atari community has slowly uncovered the original 7800 development tools and released them into the public domain. New tools, documentation, source code and utilities for development have since been created which has sponsored additional homebrew development. Several new commercial Atari 7800 titles such as ''Beef Drop'', ''B*nQ'', ''Pac-Man Collection'', ''Combat 1990'', ''Santa Simon'', and ''Space War'' have been released.

===Source code===
The source code for 13 games, as well as the OS and development tools (for the [[Atari ST]] computer system) were discovered in a dumpster behind the Atari building in Sunnyvale, California.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.atarimuseum.com/whatsnew/2009-JUN-11.html AtariMuseum - Site News: June 11, 2009], retrieved July 3, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; Commented [[assembly language]] source code was made available for ''[[Centipede (video game)|Centipede]]'', ''[[Commando (video game)|Commando]]'', ''[[Crossbow (video game)|Crossbow]]'', ''Desert Falcon'', ''[[Dig Dug]]'', ''[[Food Fight (video game)|Food Fight]]'', ''[[Galaga]]'', ''[[Hat Trick (video game)|Hat Trick]]'', ''[[Joust (video game)|Joust]]'', ''[[Ms. Pac-Man]]'', ''Super Stunt Cycle'', ''[[Robotron: 2084]]'', and ''[[Xevious]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.atarimuseum.com//videogames//consoles//7800//games// &quot;7800 Games &amp; Development&quot;] at [http://www.atarimuseum.com/ The Atari History Museum website], retrieved July 3, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[History of Atari]]
* [[List of Atari 7800 games]]
* [[List of Atari 2600 games]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Atari 7800}}
* [http://www.atariage.com/software_search.html?SystemID=7800 AtariAge &amp;ndash; Comprehensive Atari 7800 database and information]
* [http://www.atari7800.org Atari 7800 Information &amp; Resources]
* [http://www.atarimuseum.com/videogames/consoles/7800/7800menu/ Atari Museum &amp;ndash; History of the Atari 7800 ProSystem]
* [http://7800.8bitdev.org/ Atari 7800 Development Wiki]

{{Atari hardware}}
{{Third generation game consoles}}
{{Home video game consoles}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Atari 7800}}
[[Category:Atari consoles|7800]]
[[Category:Home video game consoles]]
[[Category:Backward-compatible video game consoles]]
[[Category:Third-generation video game consoles]]
[[Category:1986 in video games]]
[[Category:Computer-related introductions in 1986]]
[[Category:Products introduced in 1986]]
[[Category:Products and services discontinued in 1992]]
[[Category:1980s toys]]</text>
      <sha1>huc9l2fm472mj3qdai1badnys2dpz3y</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
