  <page>
    <title>Aberdour</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2712</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941831779</id>
      <parentid>932872897</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-20T23:04:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Suonii180</username>
        <id>27089876</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* History */ added ref</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2019}}
{{Infobox UK place
| country                          = Scotland
| official_name                    = Aberdour
| scots_name                       = Aiberdour
| gaelic_name                      = Obar Dobhair
| population                       = 1,633
| population_ref                   = &lt;ref name=&quot;Scotland's Census 2011&quot; /&gt;
| os_grid_reference                = NT190852
| map_type                         = Scotland
| coordinates                      = {{coord|56.052778|-3.302105|display=inline,title}}
| unitary_scotland                 = [[Fife]]
| lieutenancy_scotland             = [[Fife]]
| constituency_westminster         = [[Kirkcaldy and Cowdenbeath (UK Parliament constituency)|Kirkcaldy and Cowdenbeath]]
| constituency_scottish_parliament = [[Cowdenbeath (Scottish Parliament constituency)|Cowdenbeath]]
| post_town                        = BURNTISLAND
| postcode_district                = KY3 0''xx''
| postcode_area                    = KY
| dial_code                        = 01383 86
| static_image_name                = AberdourHarbour.jpg
| static_image_width               = 240
| static_image_caption             = A view across Aberdour Harbour
| static_image_alt                 = &lt;!-- see [[WP:ALT]] --&gt;
| static_image_2_name              =
| static_image_2_width             =
| static_image_2_caption           =
| static_image_2_alt               = &lt;!-- see [[WP:ALT]] --&gt;
}}

'''Aberdour''' ({{IPAc-en|ˌ|æ|b|ər|ˈ|d|aʊər|audio=Aberdour.ogg}}; {{lang-sco|Aiberdour}},&lt;ref&gt;[http://newsnetscotland.com/index.php/component/content/article/2999-list-of-railway-station-names.html List of railway station names in English, Scots and Gaelic] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130122064223/http://newsnetscotland.com/index.php/component/content/article/2999-list-of-railway-station-names.html |date=January 22, 2013 }} - NewsNetScotland&lt;/ref&gt; {{lang-gd|Obar Dobhair}}) is a scenic and historic village on the south coast of [[Fife]], Scotland. It is on the north shore of the [[Firth of Forth]], looking south to the island of [[Inchcolm]] and its Abbey, and to [[Leith]] and [[Edinburgh]] beyond. According to the 2011 census, the village has a population of 1,633.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotland's Census 2011&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.scotlandscensus.gov.uk/ods-web/area.html|title=Scotland's Census 2011- Aberdour Locality 2010 Profile |publisher=www.scotlandscensus.gov.uk|year=2011 |accessdate=2 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The village's winding High Street lies a little inland from the coast. Narrow lanes run off it, providing access to the more hidden parts of the village and the shoreline itself. The village nestles between the bigger coastal towns of [[Burntisland]] to the east and [[Dalgety Bay]] to the west.

The [[Civil parishes in Scotland|parish]] of Aberdour takes its name from this village, and had a population of 1,972 at the [[United Kingdom Census 2011|2011 Census]].&lt;ref name= &quot;KS101SC_1&quot;&gt;Census of Scotland 2011, Table KS101SC – Usual Resident Population, published by National Records of Scotland. Website http://www.scotlandscensus.gov.uk/ retrieved Apr 2018. See “Standard Outputs”, Table KS101SC, Area type: Civil Parish 1930, Area: Aberdour&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
The origins of the village lie with its harbour, where the Dour Burn enters the River Forth. The place-name itself is [[Pictish language|Pictish]], implying an origin in the [[Dark Ages (historiography)|Dark Ages]]: ''aber'' 'confluence'. The -dour element, referring to the Burn, means simply 'water' (archaic ''dobur''), and is unconnected to the Scots/English 'dour'.{{citation needed|date=February 2020}} For much of its history Aberdour was two villages, '''Wester Aberdour''' and '''Easter Aberdour''', on either side of the Dour Burn; however this distinction was blurred by the 19th century arrival of the railway.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Gifford |first1=John |title=The Buildings of Scotland: Fife |date=1992 |publisher=Penguin |isbn=978-0-300-09673-6 |page=58}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 18th century Aberdour's harbour was improved by the addition of a stone pier to help handle the coal traffic from nearby collieries. However, in the 1850s the traffic changed dramatically, and Aberdour Harbour became a popular destination for pleasure steamers from [[Leith]]. This in turn led to the building of a deeper water pier a little around the bay at Hawkcraig, and to the development of hotels and many of the other services still on view today in the village.[[File:Aberdour railway station garden.jpg|thumb|[[Aberdour railway station]]|alt=|left]]

The railway came to Aberdour in 1890, with the building of the line east from the newly opened [[Forth Bridge]]. The [[Aberdour railway station|station]] has won many &quot;best kept station&quot; awards.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.ca/books?id=vKJ1I75Mx0EC&amp;q=1890,+Forth+Bridge+awards+%22kept+station%22&amp;dq=1890,+Forth+Bridge+awards+%22kept+station%22&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwi3qtejysfjAhWYpZ4KHc9YD-QQ6AEIKTAA|first=Alan|publisher=[[F&amp;W Media International|David &amp; Charles]]|last=Hall|asin-tld=B01K94AOAW |title=Fife &amp; Perthshire: Including Kinross (Pevensey Guide)|date=2002|page=25|accessdate=2019-07-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; The half an hour journey to the centre of [[Edinburgh]] helped build on the existing popularity of the village, though it put the steamers out of business. The main result was a growth in the building of large and attractive houses, especially down the hill from Wester Aberdour to the West Sands. [[Ticket inspector]]s on the train line through Aberdour were known for their sing song refrain: ''&quot;Half an hour, Half an hour, Half an hour to Aberdour — tickets please.&quot;''{{Citation needed|date=July 2018}}

== Landmarks ==
[[Image:Aberdour Castle from dovecote.jpg|left|thumb|[[Aberdour Castle]]]]

Virtually between the two former settlements, though actually part of Easter Aberdour, lies [[Aberdour Castle]]. This started life as a modest [[hall house]] on a site overlooking the Dour Burn in the 13th century. The oldest part of the present semi-ruin constitutes one of the earliest surviving stone castles in mainland [[Scotland]]. Over the next four hundred years the Castle was successively developed according to contemporary architectural ideas. Notable are the parts, still largely roofed, built by the Earls of Morton, with refined [[Renaissance]] detail, in the second half of the 16th century. A fire in the late 17th century was followed by some repairs, but in 1725 the family purchased 17th century Aberdour House, on the west side of the burn and in Wester Aberdour, and the medieval Castle was allowed to fall into relative decay. Aberdour Castle is now in the care of [[Historic Environment Scotland]] and open to the public (entrance charge). After a period of dereliction Aberdour House was developed for residential use in the early 1990s.

[[Image:St Fillans Church -Aberdour -Scotland2.jpg|right|thumb|St Fillan's Church]]

Neighbouring St Fillan's Church is one of the best-preserved medieval parish churches in [[Scotland]], dating largely to the 12th century. A south arcade was added to the nave in the early 16th century (open in summer). The [[A921 road|A921]], the main road along the south coast of [[Fife]], leads down the High Street of Wester Aberdour, before kinking sharply left to cross the railway line, then right again to progress through Easter Aberdour's Main Street.

Wester Aberdour has the more 'olde worlde' feel of the two, with the narrower through road more closely hemmed in by shops and hotels. A number of vernacular buildings of the 17th-early 19th centuries add to the historic scene. Close to the railway bridge, three lanes continue eastwards, presumably once the route of the original High Street before the arrival of the railway. One now leads to [[Aberdour railway station]], a beautifully kept and cared for example of a traditional station, in keeping with its role of transporting at least a quarter of the village's working population to their work each day.

A second lane leads alongside the railway line to [[Aberdour Castle]], while a third leads to the restored Aberdour House. A little further west, a narrow road closely lined with high walls, Shore Road, leads down to the West Sands and the Harbour. For many this area is the highlight of any visit to Aberdour; parking at the foot of Shore Road is usually at a premium.

Another road leads coastwards from Easter Aberdour. Hawkcraig Road leads past St Fillan's Church and through Silversand Park, home to [[Aberdour Shinty Club]], en route to the much better parking area on Hawkcraig. This was formerly a sandstone quarry and then used as the council refuse tip before becoming a carpark, part of the overgrown and rocky bluff separating Aberdour's two bays. From here is it a short walk to the Silver Sands, Aberdour's busiest and most popular beach. On the west side of Hawkcraig Point there is a short concrete jetty that was used as part of the development of radio controlled torpedoes during World War One. The foundations of the Radio Hut can still be seen in the lea of the hill.

The Aberdour obelisk was built by [[James Douglas, 14th Earl of Morton|Lord Morton]] on his departure from the village to relocate to a large home in Edinburgh, it was built so he could see his former hometown from his new house when he looked through binoculars - it stands in a cowfield between the castle and the beach.

== Culture ==
Aberdour hosts an annual festival, which runs from late July to early August and features musical events, shows, sporting events and children's events.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Craig Robertson |url=http://www.aberdour-festival.org |title=Aberdour festival |publisher=Aberdour festival |date= |accessdate=2010-05-21 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190402152843/http://www.aberdour-festival.org/ |archive-date=2 April 2019 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Aberdour was a 2005 finalist in the prestigious &quot;Beautiful Scotland in Bloom&quot; awards. It was nominated for &quot;''Best Coastal Resort''&quot; in [[Scotland]] along with [[St Andrews]] in [[Fife]], [[North Berwick]] in [[East Lothian]], and [[Rothesay, Argyll and Bute|Rothesay]] in [[Argyll and Bute]].
In 2014 Aberdour was voted Best Coastal Village in Fife and Best Small Coastal Village in Scotland. It also received a Gold Award in Beautiful Fife and Beautiful Scotland. In 2018 Aberdour was voted the second-best place to live in Scotland by The Sunday Times list of Best Places to Live&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.thetimes.co.uk/article/aberdour-fife-best-places-to-live-qg32sckfh|title=Aberdour, Fife — best places to live in the UK 2018|first=The Sunday|last=Times|date=March 18, 2018|via=www.thetimes.co.uk}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Aberdour is home to Fife's only senior shinty club. [[Aberdour Shinty Club]] field teams in both the men's and women's senior national leagues.

== Aberdour's beaches ==
[[File:Silversands Bay from the air (geograph 5835067).jpg|thumb|right|Silversands Bay from the air]]
Aberdour has two beaches - the Silver Sands, and the Black Sands.

The Silver Sands&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://coastradar.com/places/united-kingdom/isle-of-wight/bembridge/beaches/silver-sands-beach/|title=Silver Sands Beach (Isle of Wight) - UK Coast Guide|website=Coast Radar}}&lt;/ref&gt; are located on the East side of the village, and has previously held a &quot;[[Blue Flag beach|Blue flag]]&quot; beach award, which denotes an exemplary standard of cleanliness, facilities, safety, environmental education and management. New facilities are currently under construction by Fife Council, which will much improve the beach throughout the year.

The Black Sands (also known as the West Beach), as the contrasting name would suggest, have a rockier and darker sand, and are also popular with visitors exploring the rock caves and fascinating sea life. During the summer months (April–September), dogs are banned from the Silver Sands but they are allowed all year round at the West Beach. The two beaches are linked by part of the [[Fife Coastal Path]] which also takes you past the harbour and the Hawkcraig - a popular rock climbing location.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.rockclimbing.com/routes/listArea.php?AreaID=7544|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20041221114813/http://www.rockclimbing.com/routes/listArea.php?AreaID=7544|url-status = dead|title=Rock Climbing Routes: Europe/Scotland/Central Lowlands/The Hawkcraig|archivedate=December 21, 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Silver Sands is becoming more popular with open water swimmers, who swim daily in the sea, both as a leisure pursuit, and as training for open water competition. The bay provides safety from the currents, although only the adventurous swim round to the harbour.

Several scenes of [[Richard Jobson (television presenter)|Richard Jobson]]'s 2003 movie &quot;[[16 Years of Alcohol]]&quot; were filmed at the Black Sands in Aberdour.

== Inchcolm ==
{{Main|Inchcolm}}

The island of [[Inchcolm]], or Island ([[Scottish Gaelic language|Gaelic]] ''innis'') of [[Columba]], a quarter of a mile from the shore, forms part of the parish of Aberdour. Its name implies associations dating back to the time of [[Columba]] and, although undocumented before the 12th century, it may have served the monks of the Columban family as an '[[Iona]] of the east' from early times.

During the First and Second World Wars, [[Inchcolm]] was occupied by the army as part of the defences of the [[Firth of Forth]]. There are extensive remains of gun emplacements, barracks, etc. from these periods.

The island is notable for its wildlife, especially seabirds and seals. These draw many visitors in summer, along with the remains of the historic Abbey, and is a popular setting for weddings.

== Notable residents ==
Notable past and present residents of the town include:
*[[Geoffrey Keyes (VC)|Geoffrey Keyes]], recipient of the [[Victoria Cross]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Geoffrey C T Keyes VC|url=http://www.victoriacrossonline.co.uk/geoffrey-c-t-keyes-vc/4587307857|website=www.victoriacrossonline.co.uk|accessdate=7 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Twin cities/towns ==
* {{flagicon|Italy}} - [[Corte Franca]], [[Italy]] (since 31 July 2004)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Town Twinning|url=https://www.fifedirect.org.uk/topics/index.cfm?fuseaction=service.display&amp;objectid=909a83ad-347e-4e30-828c-07b353b68048|website=www.fifedirect.org.uk|accessdate=26 January 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Aber and Inver as place-name elements]]
* [[Aberdour Shinty Club]]
* [[List of places in Fife]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Aberdour}}
{{Wikivoyage|Aberdour}}
{{EB1911 poster|Aberdour}}

* [http://www.aberdourfestival.org Aberdour Festival website]

[[Category:Aberdour| ]]
[[Category:Villages in Fife]]
[[Category:Parishes in Fife]]</text>
      <sha1>ordb8ysr2xky9h4ol9yajuoziqo85mn</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
