  <page>
    <title>AutoCAD DXF</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2754</id>
    <revision>
      <id>920016017</id>
      <parentid>885431671</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-10-07T06:12:28Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rescuing 1 sources and tagging 0 as dead.) #IABot (v2.0</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{refimprove|date=October 2012}}
{{Infobox file format
| name = Drawing Interchange Format
| icon =
| logo =
| screenshot =
| caption =
| extension = .dxf
| mime = image/vnd.dxf
| type code =
| uniform type =
| magic =
| owner = [[Autodesk]]
| released = {{start date and age|1982|12}}
| latest release version = u19.1.01.
| latest release date = {{start date and age|2007|01}}&lt;ref name=acad_dxf0.pdf&gt;{{Citation |title = DXF specifications |url = http://images.autodesk.com/adsk/files/autocad_2012_pdf_dxf-reference_enu.pdf }}&lt;/ref&gt;
| genre = [[CAD data exchange]]
| container for =
| contained by =
| extended from =
| extended to =
| standard =
| url =
}}

'''AutoCAD DXF''' (Drawing Interchange Format, or Drawing Exchange Format) is a [[Computer-aided design|CAD]] data [[file format]] developed by [[Autodesk]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.faqs.org/faqs/graphics/fileformats-faq/part3/section-45.html FAQS.org]&lt;/ref&gt; for enabling [[CAD data exchange|data interoperability]] between [[AutoCAD]] and other programs.

DXF was originally introduced in December 1982 as part of AutoCAD 1.0, and was intended to provide an exact representation of the data in the AutoCAD native file format, [[.dwg|DWG]] (Drawing), for which Autodesk for many years did not publish specifications. Because of this, correct imports of DXF files have been difficult. Autodesk now publishes the DXF specifications as a PDF&lt;ref name=acad_dxf0.pdf /&gt; on its website.

Versions of AutoCAD from Release 10 (October 1988) and up support both [[ASCII]] and [[binary file|binary]] forms of DXF.  Earlier versions support only ASCII.

As AutoCAD has become more powerful, supporting more complex object types, DXF has become less useful. Certain object types, including [[ACIS]] solids and regions, are not documented. Other object types, including AutoCAD 2006's dynamic blocks, and all of the objects specific to the [[vertical market]] versions of AutoCAD, are partially documented, but not well enough to allow other developers to support them. For these reasons many CAD applications use the [[.dwg|DWG]] format which can be licensed from [[Autodesk]] or non-natively from the [[Open Design Alliance]].

DXF coordinates are always without dimensions so that the reader or user needs to know the drawing unit or has to extract it from the textual comments in the sheets.

== File structure ==
ASCII versions of DXF can be read with any [[text editor]]. The basic organization of a DXF file is as follows:&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.autodesk.com/techpubs/autocad/acadr14/dxf/dxf_file_structure_al_u05_b.htm DXF File Structure]&lt;/ref&gt;

* '''HEADER''' section – General information about the drawing. Each parameter has a variable name and an associated value.
* '''CLASSES''' section – Holds the information for application-defined classes whose instances appear in the BLOCKS, ENTITIES, and OBJECTS sections of the database. Generally does not provide sufficient information to allow interoperability with other programs.
* '''TABLES''' section – This section contains definitions of named items.
: Application ID (APPID) table
: Block Record (BLOCK_RECORD) table
: Dimension Style (DIMSTYLE) table
: Layer (LAYER) table
: Linetype (LTYPE) table
: Text style (STYLE) table
: User Coordinate System (UCS) table
: View (VIEW) table
: Viewport configuration (VPORT) table
* '''BLOCKS''' section – This section contains Block Definition entities describing the entities comprising each Block in the drawing.
* '''ENTITIES''' section – This section contains the drawing entities, including any Block References.
* '''OBJECTS''' section – Contains the data that apply to nongraphical objects, used by AutoLISP and ObjectARX applications.
* '''THUMBNAILIMAGE''' section – Contains the preview image for the DXF file.
* '''END OF FILE'''

The data format of a DXF is called a &quot;tagged data&quot; format which &quot;means that each data element in the file is preceded by an integer number that is called a group code. A group code's value indicates what type of data element follows. This value also indicates the meaning of a data element for a given object (or record) type. Virtually all user-specified information in a drawing file can be represented in DXF format.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Chapter 1 -- DXF Format&quot; [http://www.autodesk.com/techpubs/autocad/acad2000/dxf/dxf_format.htm Autodesk.com]&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[.dwg]] (DWG)
* [[Design Web Format]] (DWF)
* [[QCad]], an open source CAD application that uses the DXF file format internally and to save and import files
** [[LibreCAD]], a version of QCAD Community Edition ported to Qt4
* [[Open Design Alliance]] (originally called OpenDWG)
* [[ShareCAD]], a free online CAD viewer that supports DXF, among other formats

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20171019003526/http://usa.autodesk.com/adsk/servlet/item?id=24240325&amp;siteID=123112 DXF Reference from Autodesk Developer Network]. Menu of documentation for chronological versions of DXF back to 1994.
* [http://www.autodesk.com/techpubs/autocad/acadr14/dxf/ AutoCAD DXF Reference (from Release 14, 1998)] ([http://images.autodesk.com/adsk/files/autocad_2012_pdf_dxf-reference_enu.pdf PDF version from 2012])
* [https://www.fileformat.info/format/dxf/egff.htm AutoCAD DXF File Format Summary].
* [http://www.autodesk.com/techpubs/autocad/acadr14/dxf/symbol_table_example_al_u05_b.htm Annotated example DXF file]
* {{cite web |url = http://paulbourke.net/dataformats/dxf/min3d.html |title = Minimum Requirements for Creating a DXF File of a 3D Model |author = Paul Bourke |date = March 1990 }}
* [https://viewer.autodesk.com AutoDesk Online DXF File Viewer].

{{Graphics file formats}}
{{AutoCAD related articles}}
{{CAD software}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Autocad Dxf}}
[[Category:AutoCAD|DXF]]
[[Category:Autodesk]]
[[Category:CAD file formats|D]]</text>
      <sha1>1q5bga8v0vhcvd11n9wf76icv0uav6c</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
