  <page>
    <title>Asexual reproduction</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2756</id>
    <revision>
      <id>940056885</id>
      <parentid>939324286</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-10T08:09:09Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Moaia</username>
        <id>37251116</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Reproduction without a sexual process}}
{{Use dmy dates |date=July 2013}}
[[File:caduco.jpg|thumb|Asexual reproduction in [[Marchantiophyta|liverworts]]: a [[dehiscence (botany)|caducous]] [[leaf|phylloid]] germinating]]
'''Asexual reproduction''' is a type of [[reproduction]] which does not involve the fusion of [[gamete]]s or change in the number of [[chromosomes]].  The offspring that arise by asexual reproduction from a single cell or from a [[multicellular organism]] inherit the genes of that parent. Asexual reproduction is the primary form of reproduction for [[single-celled organism]]s such as [[archaea]] and [[eubacteria|bacteria]]. Many multicellular [[animal]]s, [[plant]]s and [[Fungus|fungi]] can also reproduce asexually. &lt;ref name=&quot;Asexual but Not Clonal: Evolutionary Processes in Automictic Populations | Genetics&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.genetics.org/content/206/2/993 | title = Asexual but Not Clonal: Evolutionary Processes in Automictic Populations &amp;#124; Genetics | author = | authorlink = | date = | format = | website = | pages = | language = | archiveurl = | archivedate = | quote = | accessdate = 2018-08-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

While all [[prokaryote]]s reproduce without the formation and fusion of gametes, mechanisms for [[lateral gene transfer]] such as [[Bacterial conjugation|conjugation]], [[Transformation (genetics)|transformation]] and [[Transduction (genetics)|transduction]] can be likened to [[sexual reproduction]] in the sense of [[genetic recombination]] in [[meiosis]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Narra&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author1=Narra, H. P. |author2=Ochman, H.  |title=Of what use is sex to bacteria? |journal=Current Biology |year=2006 |volume=16 |pages=R705–710 |pmid=16950097 |doi=10.1016/j.cub.2006.08.024 |issue=17 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Types==

===Fission===
{{main|Fission (biology)}}

[[Prokaryote]]s ([[Archaea]] and [[Bacteria]]) reproduce asexually through [[Fission (biology)|binary fission]], in which the parent organism divides in two to produce two genetically identical daughter organisms. [[Eukaryote]]s (such as [[protist]]s and unicellular [[fungi]]) may reproduce in a functionally similar manner by [[mitosis]]; most of these are also capable of sexual reproduction.

Multiple fission at the cellular level occurs in many [[protist]]s, e.g. [[sporozoa]]ns and [[algae]]. The [[cell nucleus|nucleus]] of the parent cell divides several times by [[mitosis]], producing several nuclei. The cytoplasm then separates, creating multiple daughter cells.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrit&quot;&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |url=https://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/498542/reproduction/76146/Multiple-fission |title=Cell reproduction |encyclopedia=Encyclopædia Britannica}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;fap&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author=Britannica Educational Publishing |title=Fungi, Algae, and Protists |publisher=The Rosen Publishing Group |year=2011 |isbn=978-1-61530-463-9 |url=https://books.google.com/?id=_U9MB4iUpDIC&amp;lpg=PA102&amp;dq=multiple%20fission&amp;pg=PA101#v=onepage&amp;q=multiple%20fission&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;aff&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author=P.Puranik |author2=Asha Bhate |title=Animal Forms And Functions: Invertebrata |publisher=Sarup &amp; Sons |year=2007 |isbn=978-81-7625-791-6 |url=https://books.google.com/?id=-kdq6RyyVE0C&amp;lpg=PA87&amp;dq=multiple%20fission&amp;pg=PA87#v=onepage&amp;q=multiple%20fission&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[apicomplexa]]ns, multiple fission, or [[schizogony]] appears either as [[protozoal merogony|merogony]], [[sporogony]] or [[gametogony]]. Merogony results in [[merozoite]]s, which are multiple daughter cells, that originate within the same cell membrane,&lt;ref name=&quot;margulis&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author1=Margulis, Lynn |author1link=Lynn Margulis |author2=McKhann, Heather I. |author3=Olendzenski, Lorraine |title=Illustrated glossary of protoctista: vocabulary of the algae, apicomplexa, ciliates, foraminifera, microspora, water molds, slime molds, and the other protoctists |publisher=Jones &amp; Bartlett learn |year=2001 |url=https://books.google.com/?id=y55Efu3baksC&amp;lpg=PA72&amp;dq=Merogony%20multiple%20division&amp;pg=PA72#v=onepage&amp;q=Merogony%20multiple%20division&amp;f=false |isbn=978-0-86720-081-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;tanada&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author1=Yoshinori Tanada |author2=Harry K. Kaya |title=Insect pathology |publisher=Gulf Professional Publishing |year=1993 |isbn=978-0-12-683255-6 |url=https://books.google.com/?id=99YwOQnsgGUC&amp;lpg=PA415&amp;dq=difference%20between%20merogony%20and%20schizogony&amp;pg=PA415#v=onepage&amp;q=difference%20between%20merogony%20and%20schizogony&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt; sporogony results in [[sporozoite]]s, and gametogony results in micro[[gamete]]s.

=== Budding===
[[File:S cerevisiae under DIC microscopy.jpg|thumb|The yeast ''[[Saccharomyces cerevisiae]]'' reproducing by [[budding]]]]
{{main|Budding}}

Some cells divide by [[budding]] (for example [[Saccharomyces cerevisiae|baker's yeast]]), resulting in a &quot;mother&quot; and a &quot;daughter&quot; cell that is initially smaller than the parent. Budding is also known on a multicellular level; an animal example is the [[Hydra (genus)|hydra]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|date=1703-12-31|title=IV. Part of a letter from Mr Antony van Leeuwenhoek, F. R. S. concerning green weeds growing in water, and some animalcula found about them.|url=https://royalsocietypublishing.org/doi/10.1098/rstl.1702.0042|journal=Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London|language=en|volume=23|issue=283|pages=1304–1311|doi=10.1098/rstl.1702.0042|issn=0261-0523}}&lt;/ref&gt;, which reproduces by budding. The buds grow into fully matured individuals which eventually break away from the parent organism.

Internal budding is a process of asexual reproduction, favoured by parasites such as ''[[Toxoplasma gondii]]''. It involves an unusual process in which two (''endodyogeny'') or more (''endopolygeny'') daughter cells are produced inside a mother cell, which is then consumed by the offspring prior to their separation.&lt;ref name=smyth&gt;{{cite book |author1=Smyth, James Desmond |author2=Wakelin, Derek |title=Introduction to animal parasitology |year=1994 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |pages=101–102 |edition=3 |isbn=978-0-521-42811-8 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Also, budding (external or internal) occurs in some worms like ''[[Taenia (genus)|Taenia]]'' or ''[[Echinococcus]]''; these worms produce cysts and then produce (invaginated or evaginated) [[protoscolex]] with [[budding]].

=== Vegetative propagation===
{{main|Vegetative propagation}}
[[File:Bryophyllum daigremontianum nahaufnahme1.jpg|thumb|Vegetative plantlets of mother-of-thousands, ''[[Bryophyllum daigremontianum|Bryophyllum daigremontianum (Kalanchoe daigremontiana)]]'']]

Vegetative propagation is a type of asexual reproduction found in plants where new individuals are formed without the production of seeds or spores and thus without [[syngamy]] or [[meiosis]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ucmp.berkeley.edu/glossary/gloss6/asexual.html |title=Asexual Reproduction |publisher=Ucmp.berkeley.edu |date= |accessdate=13 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Examples of vegetative reproduction include the formation of miniaturized plants called plantlets on specialized leaves, for example in kalanchoe (''[[Bryophyllum daigremontianum]]'') and many produce new plants from [[rhizome]]s or [[stolon]] (for example in [[Garden strawberry|strawberry]]). Other plants reproduce by forming [[bulb]]s or [[tuber]]s (for example [[tulip]] bulbs and ''[[Dahlia]]'' tubers). Some plants produce [[adventitious]] shoots and may form a [[clonal colony]]. In these examples, all the individuals are clones, and the clonal population may cover a large area.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.fs.fed.us/wildflowers/communities/aspen/grow.shtml |title=Celebrating Wildflowers - Fading Gold - How Aspens Grow |publisher=Fs.fed.us |date=11 May 2010 |accessdate=13 August 2010 | archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20100923073834/http://www.fs.fed.us/wildflowers/communities/aspen/grow.shtml | archivedate= 23 September 2010  | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Spore formation===
{{main|Sporogenesis}} 
Many multicellular organisms form [[spore]]s during their [[biological life cycle]] in a process called ''sporogenesis''. Exceptions are animals and some protists, which undergo ''meiosis'' immediately followed by fertilization. Plants and many algae on the other hand undergo ''sporic meiosis'' where meiosis leads to the formation of [[haploid]] spores rather than gametes. These spores grow into multicellular individuals (called [[gametophyte]]s in the case of plants) without a fertilization event. These haploid individuals give rise to [[gamete]]s through [[mitosis]]. Meiosis and gamete formation therefore occur in separate generations or &quot;phases&quot; of the life cycle, referred to as [[alternation of generations]]. Since sexual reproduction is often more narrowly defined as the fusion of gametes ([[fertilization]]), spore formation in plant [[sporophyte]]s and algae might be considered a form of asexual reproduction (agamogenesis) despite being the result of [[meiosis]] and undergoing a reduction in [[ploidy]]. However, both events (spore formation and fertilization) are necessary to complete sexual reproduction in the plant life cycle.

Fungi and some algae can also utilize true asexual [[spore]] formation, which involves [[mitosis]] giving rise to reproductive cells called mitospores that develop into a new organism after dispersal. This method of reproduction is found for example in [[Conidium|conidial fungi]] and the [[red algae]] ''Polysiphonia'', and involves sporogenesis without meiosis. Thus the chromosome number of the spore cell is the same as that of the parent producing the spores. However, mitotic sporogenesis is an exception and most spores, such as those of plants, most [[Basidiomycota]], and many algae, are produced by [[meiosis]].

=== Fragmentation===
[[File:Tu - Linckia guildingi.jpg |thumb |right |alt=Regeneration from an arm |''[[Linckia guildingi]]'' &quot;comet&quot;, a [[starfish]] regrowing from a single arm]]
{{main|Fragmentation (reproduction)}}

Fragmentation is a form of asexual reproduction where a new organism grows from a fragment of the parent. Each fragment develops into a mature, fully grown individual. Fragmentation is seen in many organisms. Animals that reproduce asexually include [[planarian]]s, many [[annelid]] worms including [[polychaete]]s&lt;ref name=&quot;RuppertFoxBarnesPolychRepro&quot;&gt;{{cite book | author1=Ruppert, E. E. | author2=Fox, R. S. | author3=Barnes, R. D. | title=Invertebrate Zoology | chapter=Annelida | publisher=Brooks / Cole | edition=7 | isbn=978-0-03-025982-1 | year=2004 | pages=[https://archive.org/details/isbn_9780030259821/page/434 434–441] | url=https://archive.org/details/isbn_9780030259821/page/434 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and some [[oligochaete]]s,&lt;ref name=&quot;RuppertFoxBarnesOligochRepro&quot;&gt;{{cite book | author1=Ruppert, E.E. | author2=Fox, R.S. | author3=Barnes, R.D. | last-author-amp=yes | title=Invertebrate Zoology | chapter=Annelida | publisher=Brooks / Cole | edition=7 | isbn=978-0-03-025982-1 | year=2004 | pages=[https://archive.org/details/isbn_9780030259821/page/466 466–469] | url=https://archive.org/details/isbn_9780030259821/page/466 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[turbellarians]] and [[sea stars]]. Many fungi and plants reproduce asexually. Some plants have specialized structures for reproduction via fragmentation, such as ''[[Gemma (botany)|gemmae]]'' in [[Marchantiophyta|liverworts]]. Most [[lichen]]s, which are a [[Symbiosis|symbiotic]] union of a fungus and [[Photosynthesis|photosynthetic]] algae or [[cyanobacteria]], reproduce through fragmentation to ensure that new individuals contain both symbionts. These fragments can take the form of ''soredia'', dust-like particles consisting of fungal hyphen wrapped around photobiont cells.

Clonal Fragmentation in multicellular or colonial organisms is a form of asexual reproduction or cloning where an organism is split into fragments. Each of these fragments develop into mature, fully grown individuals that are clones of the original organism. In [[echinoderm]]s, this method of reproduction is usually known as ''fissiparity''.&lt;ref name=&quot;skold&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author1=Sköld, Helen Nilsson |author2=Obst, Matthias |author3=Sköld, Mattias |author4=Åkesson, Bertil |editor1=Baruch Rinkevich |editor2=Valeria Matranga |title=Stem Cells in Marine Organisms |chapter=Stem Cells in Asexual Reproduction of Marine Invertebrates |publisher=Springer |year=2009 |page=125 |isbn=978-90-481-2766-5 |chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=-eP2p0VF6VcC&amp;lpg=PA125&amp;dq=Fissiparity&amp;pg=PA125#v=onepage&amp;q=Fissiparity&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt; Due to many environmental and [[Epigenetics|epigenetic]] differences, clones originating from the same ancestor might actually be genetically and epigenetically different.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Neuhof |first1=Moran |last2=Levin |first2=Michael |last3=Rechavi |first3=Oded |title=Vertically and horizontally-transmitted memories – the fading boundaries between regeneration and inheritance in planaria |journal=Biology Open |date=26 August 2016 |pages=1177–1188 |doi=10.1242/bio.020149 |pmid=27565761 |pmc=5051648 |volume=5|issue=9 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Agamogenesis===
Agamogenesis is any form of reproduction that does not involve a male gamete. Examples are [[parthenogenesis]] and [[apomixis]].

==== Parthenogenesis====
[[File:Aphid-giving-birth.jpg |thumb |[[Aphid]] giving birth to live young from an unfertilized egg]]
{{main|Parthenogenesis}}

Parthenogenesis is a form of [[agamogenesis]] in which an unfertilized egg develops into a new individual. Parthenogenesis occurs naturally in many plants, [[invertebrate]]s (e.g. water fleas, [[rotifer]]s, aphids, [[stick insect]]s, some ants, bees and parasitic wasps), and [[vertebrate]]s (e.g. some reptiles, amphibians, rarely sharks and birds). In plants, [[apomixis]] may or may not involve parthenogenesis.

==== Apomixis and nucellar embryony====
{{main|Apomixis |Nucellar embryony}}

Apomixis in plants is the formation of a new [[sporophyte]] without fertilization. It is important in ferns and in flowering plants, but is very rare in other seed plants. In flowering plants, the term &quot;apomixis&quot; is now most often used for [[agamospermy]], the formation of seeds without fertilization, but was once used to include [[vegetative reproduction]]. An example of an [[apomictic]] plant would be the [[triploid]] European [[dandelion]]. Apomixis mainly occurs in two forms: In gametophytic apomixis, the embryo arises from an unfertilized egg within a diploid embryo sac that was formed without completing meiosis. In [[nucellar embryony]], the embryo is formed from the diploid [[nucellus]] tissue surrounding the embryo sac. Nucellar embryony occurs in some [[citrus]] seeds. Male apomixis can occur in rare cases, such as the Saharan Cypress ''[[Cupressus dupreziana]]'', where the genetic material of the embryo are derived entirely from [[pollen]].

== Alternation between sexual and asexual reproduction==
{{see also |Plant reproduction#Sexual reproduction}}
[[File:Soybeanaphidlifecycle.gif|thumb|upright=1.7|[[Aphid]] populations are often entirely female during the summer, with sexual reproduction only to produce eggs for overwintering.]]

Some species can alternate between sexual and asexual strategies, an ability known as ''[[heterogamy]]'', depending on 
many conditions. Alternation is observed in several [[rotifer]] species (cyclical parthenogenesis e.g. in [[Brachionus]] species) and a few types of insects, such as [[aphid]]s which will, under certain conditions, produce eggs that have not gone through meiosis, thus cloning themselves. The cape bee [[Apis mellifera capensis|''Apis mellifera'' subsp. ''capensis'']] can reproduce asexually through a process called [[thelytoky]]. The freshwater crustacean ''[[Daphnia]]'' reproduces by parthenogenesis in the spring to rapidly populate ponds, then switches to [[sexual reproduction]] as the intensity of competition and predation increases. Monogonont [[rotifer]]s of the genus ''[[Brachionus]]'' reproduce via cyclical parthenogenesis: at low population densities females produce asexually and at higher densities a chemical cue accumulates and induces the transition to sexual reproduction. Many protists and fungi alternate between sexual and asexual reproduction. A few species of amphibians, reptiles, and birds have a similar ability.{{which|date=February 2020}}  

The slime mold ''[[Dictyostelium]]'' undergoes binary fission (mitosis) as single-celled amoebae under favorable conditions. However, when conditions turn unfavorable, the cells aggregate and follow one of two different developmental pathways, depending on conditions. In the social pathway, they form a multi-cellular slug which then forms a fruiting body with asexually generated spores. In the sexual pathway, two cells fuse to form a giant cell that develops into a large cyst. When this macrocyst germinates, it releases hundreds of amoebic cells that are the product of meiotic recombination between the original two cells.&lt;ref name=&quot;MehrotraAneja1990&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author1=Mehrotra, R. S. |author2=Aneja, K. R. |title=An Introduction to Mycology |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=UUorj_O2dcsC&amp;pg=PA83 |accessdate=4 August 2010 |date=December 1990 |publisher=New Age International |isbn=978-81-224-0089-2 |pages=83 ff}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The hyphae of the common mold (''[[Rhizopus]]'') are capable of producing both mitotic as well as meiotic spores. Many algae similarly switch between sexual and asexual reproduction.&lt;ref name=&quot;ColeSheath1990&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author1=Cole, Kathleen M. |author2=Sheath, Robert G. |title=Biology of the red algae |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=F7CWXuYZFq8C&amp;pg=PA469 |accessdate=4 August 2010 |year=1990 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |isbn=978-0-521-34301-5 |pages=469–}}&lt;/ref&gt; A number of plants use both sexual and asexual means to produce new plants, some species alter their primary modes of reproduction from sexual to asexual under varying environmental conditions.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReekieBazzaz2005&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author1=Edward G. Reekie |author2-link=Fakhri A. Bazzaz |author2=Fakhri A. Bazzaz |title=Reproductive allocation in plants |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=_KJdaiLKAogC&amp;pg=PA99 |accessdate=4 August 2010 |date=28 October 2005 |publisher=Academic Press |isbn=978-0-12-088386-8 |pages=99–}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Inheritance in asexual species==
In the [[rotifer]] ''[[Brachionus]] calyciflorus'' asexual reproduction (obligate [[parthenogenesis]]) can be inherited by a recessive allele, which leads to loss of sexual reproduction in homozygous offspring.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1=Stelzer | first1=C.-P. | last2=Schmidt | first2=J. | last3=Wiedlroither | first3=A. | last4=Riss | first4=S. | year=2010 | title=Loss of Sexual Reproduction and Dwarfing in a Small Metazoan | url= | journal=PLoS ONE | volume=5 | issue=9 | page=e12854 | doi=10.1371/journal.pone.0012854 | pmid=20862222 | pmc=2942836}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1=Scheuerl | first1=T. | last2=Riss | first2=S. | last3=Stelzer | first3=C.P. | year=2011 | title=Phenotypic effects of an allele causing obligate parthenogenesis in a rotifer | journal=Journal of Heredity | volume=102 | issue=4 | pages=409–415 | doi=10.1093/jhered/esr036 | pmid=21576287 | pmc=3113615}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Inheritance of asexual reproduction by a single recessive locus has also been found in the [[parasitoid wasp]] ''Lysiphlebus fabarum''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author1=Sandrock, C. |author2=Vorburger, C.  |title=Single-locus recessive inheritance of asexual reproduction in a parasitoid wasp |journal=Curr. Biol. |volume=21 |issue=5 |pages=433–7 |year=2011 |pmid=21353557 |doi=10.1016/j.cub.2011.01.070}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Examples in animals==

Asexual reproduction is found in nearly half of the animal phyla.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Minelli, Alessandro |year=2009 |title=Asexual reproduction and regeneration |work=Perspectives in Animal Phylogeny and Evolution |publisher=Oxford University Press |pages=123–127 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=jIASDAAAQBAJ |isbn=978-0198566205}}&lt;/ref&gt; Parthenogenesis occurs in the [[hammerhead shark]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Savage |first=Juliet Eilperin |title=Female Sharks Can Reproduce Alone, Researchers Find |work=Washington Post |date= 23 May 2007 |url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/05/22/AR2007052201405.html |accessdate=27 April 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[blacktip shark]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |url=https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2008/10/081010173054.htm |title='Virgin Birth' By Shark Confirmed: Second Case Ever |doi=10.1111/j.1095-8649.2008.02018.x |publisher=Sciencedaily.com |date=11 October 2008 |accessdate=13 August 2010 |last1=Chapman |first1=D. D. |last2=Firchau |first2=B. |last3=Shivji |first3=M. S. |journal=Journal of Fish Biology |volume=73 |issue=6 |pages=1473–1477}}&lt;/ref&gt; In both cases, the sharks had reached sexual maturity in captivity in the absence of males, and in both cases the offspring were shown to be genetically identical to the mothers. The [[New Mexico whiptail]] is another example.

Some reptiles use the [[ZW sex-determination system]], which produces either males (with ZZ sex chromosomes) or females (with ZW or WW sex chromosomes). Until 2010, it was thought that the ZW chromosome system used by reptiles was incapable of producing viable WW offspring, but a (ZW) female [[boa constrictor]] was discovered to have produced viable female offspring with WW chromosomes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.cbc.ca/news/technology/boa-constrictor-produces-fatherless-babies-1.947269 |title=Boa constrictor produces fatherless babies |publisher=CBC News - Technology &amp; Science |date=3 November 2010 |accessdate=2014-10-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; The female boa could have chosen any number of male partners (and had successfully in the past) but on these occasions she reproduced asexually, creating 22 female babies with WW sex-chromosomes.

[[Polyembryony]] is a widespread form of asexual reproduction in animals, whereby the fertilized egg or a later stage of embryonic development splits to form genetically identical clones. Within animals, this phenomenon has been best studied in the parasitic [[Hymenoptera]]. In the [[9-banded armadillos]], this process is obligatory and usually gives rise to genetically identical quadruplets. In other mammals, [[monozygotic twinning]] has no apparent genetic basis, though its occurrence is common. There are at least 10 million identical human twins and triplets in the world today.

Bdelloid [[rotifer]]s reproduce exclusively asexually, and all individuals in the class [[Bdelloidea]] are females. Asexuality evolved in these animals millions of years ago and has persisted since. There is evidence to suggest that asexual reproduction has allowed the animals to evolve new proteins through the [[Matthew Meselson#The Meselson Effect|Meselson effect]] that have allowed them to survive better in periods of dehydration.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Pouchkina-Stantcheva |first1=N. N. |last2=McGee |first2=B. M. |last3=Boschetti |first3=C. |last4=Tolleter |first4=D. |last5=Chakrabortee |first5=S. |last6=Popova |first6=A. V. |last7=Meersman |first7=F. |last8=MacHerel |first8=D. |last9=Hincha |first9=D. K. |title=Functional Divergence of Former Alleles in an Ancient Asexual Invertebrate |journal=Science |volume=318 |issue=5848 |pages=268–71 |year=2007 |pmid=17932297 |doi=10.1126/science.1144363}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Molecular evidence strongly suggests that several species of the [[stick insect]] genus ''[[Timema]]'' have used only asexual (parthenogenetic) reproduction for millions of years, the longest period known for any insect.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first=T. |last=Schwander |first2=Lee |last2=Henry |first3=Bernard J. |last3=Crespi |displayauthors=1 |year=2011 |title=Molecular evidence for ancient asexuality in Timema stick insects |journal=[[Current Biology]] |volume=21 |issue=13 |pages=1129–34 |doi=10.1016/j.cub.2011.05.026 |pmid=21683598 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the grass [[thrips]] genus ''[[Aptinothrips]]'' there have been several transitions to asexuality, likely due to different causes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first=C. J. |last=van der Kooi |first2=T. |last2=Schwander |year=2014 |title=Evolution of asexuality via different mechanisms in grass thrips (Thysanoptera: ''Aptinothrips'') |journal=[[Evolution (journal)|Evolution]] |volume=86 |issue=7 |pages=1883–1893 |doi=10.1111/evo.12402 |pmid=24627993 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Adaptive significance of asexual reproduction ==
A complete lack of [[sexual reproduction]] is relatively rare among [[multicellular organism]]s, particularly [[animal]]s. It is not entirely understood why the ability to reproduce sexually is so common among them. Current hypotheses&lt;ref name=&quot;Dawson&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author=Dawson, K.J. |title=The Advantage of Asexual Reproduction: When is it Two-fold? |journal=Journal of Theoretical Biology |date=October 1995 |volume=176 |pages=341–347 |issue=3 |doi=10.1006/jtbi.1995.0203}}&lt;/ref&gt; suggest that asexual reproduction may have short term benefits when rapid population growth is important or in stable environments, while sexual reproduction offers a net advantage by allowing more rapid generation of genetic diversity, allowing adaptation to changing environments. Developmental constraints&lt;ref name=&quot;Engelstädter&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author=Engelstädter, J. |title=Constraints on the evolution of asexual reproduction |journal=BioEssays |date=November 2008 |volume=30 |pages=1138–1150 |issue=11–12 |pmid=18937362 |doi=10.1002/bies.20833}}&lt;/ref&gt; may underlie why few animals have relinquished sexual reproduction completely in their life-cycles. Another constraint on switching from sexual to asexual reproduction would be the concomitant loss of meiosis and the protective recombinational repair of DNA damage afforded as one function of meiosis.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid3324702&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author1=Bernstein, H. |author2=Hopf, F.A. |author3=Michod, R.E.  |title=The molecular basis of the evolution of sex |journal=Adv. Genet. |volume=24 |issue= |pages=323–70 |year=1987 |pmid=3324702 |doi= 10.1016/s0065-2660(08)60012-7 |url= |series=Advances in Genetics |isbn=9780120176243 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Avise, J. (2008) Clonality: The Genetics, Ecology and Evolution of Sexual Abstinence in Vertebrate Animals. See pp. 22-25. Oxford University Press. {{ISBN |019536967X}} {{ISBN |978-0195369670}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also==
{{Div col}}
* [[Alternation of generations]]
* [[Bacterial conjugation]]
* [[Biological life cycle]]
* [[Biological reproduction]], also simply [[reproduction]]
* [[Cloning]]
* [[Plant reproduction]]
* [[Sex]]
{{colend}}

== References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

== Further reading==
*{{cite book |last=Avise |first=J. |year=2008 |title=Clonality: The Genetics, Ecology, and Evolution of Sexual Abstinence in Vertebrate Animals |location= |publisher=Oxford University Press |isbn=978-0-19-536967-0 }}
*{{cite book |last=Graham |first=L. |last2=Graham |first2=J. |last3=Wilcox |first3=L. |year=2003 |title=Plant Biology |publisher=Pearson Education |location=Upper Saddle River, NJ |pages=258–259 |isbn=978-0-13-030371-4 }}
*{{cite book |last=Raven |first=P. H. |last2=Evert |first2=R. F. |last3=Eichhorn |first3=S. E. |year=2005 |title=Biology of Plants |url=https://archive.org/details/biologyofplants00rave_0 |url-access=registration |edition=7th |publisher=W.H. Freeman and Company |location=NY |isbn=978-0-7167-6284-3 }}

== External links==
{{Commons category |Asexual reproduction}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20050708073801/http://www.tiscali.co.uk/reference/encyclopaedia/hutchinson/m0030820.html Asexual reproduction]
* [http://www.tulane.edu/~wiser/protozoology/notes/intes.html Intestinal Protozoa]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Asexual Reproduction}}
[[Category:Asexual reproduction| ]]</text>
      <sha1>k21apdday88cws2smui20hzi06s1v1x</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
