  <page>
    <title>Alkyne</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2763</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943218646</id>
      <parentid>938731405</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-29T16:15:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>2601:40D:8400:E6E:B855:D203:16D3:E1F9</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Alkynes in nature and medicine */Fixed redundancy?</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{distinguish|Alkane|Alkene}}

[[File:Acetylene-3D-vdW.png|right|thumb|A 3D model of ethyne ([[acetylene]]), the simplest alkyne]]
In [[organic chemistry]], an '''alkyne''' is an [[Saturated and unsaturated compounds|unsaturated]] [[hydrocarbon]] containing at least one carbon—carbon [[triple bond]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/15818/alkyne Alkyne]. Encyclopædia Britannica&lt;/ref&gt; The simplest acyclic alkynes with only one triple bond and no other [[functional group]]s form a [[homologous series]] with the general chemical formula {{Carbon}}&lt;sub&gt;''n''&lt;/sub&gt;{{Hydrogen}}&lt;sub&gt;2''n''−2&lt;/sub&gt;. Alkynes are traditionally known as acetylenes, although the name ''acetylene'' also refers specifically to C&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, known formally as [[ethyne]] using [[IUPAC nomenclature of organic chemistry|IUPAC nomenclature]]. Like other hydrocarbons, alkynes are generally hydrophobic but tend to be more reactive.

==Chemical properties==
Alkynes are characteristically more [[Saturated and unsaturated compounds|unsaturated]] than alkenes. Thus they add two equivalents of [[bromine]] whereas an alkene adds only one equivalent in a reaction with hydrobromic acid. Other reactions are listed below. In some reactions, alkynes are less reactive than [[alkene]]s. For example, in a molecule with an -ene and an -yne group, addition occurs preferentially at the -ene.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Rosser|author2=Williams|last-author-amp=yes|title=Modern Organic Chemistry for A-level|year=1977|publisher=Collins|location=Great Britain|isbn=0003277402|page=82}}&lt;/ref&gt; Possible explanations involve the two π-bonds in the alkyne delocalising, which would reduce the energy of the π-system{{citation needed|date=June 2013}} or the stability of the intermediates during the reaction.
They show greater tendency to [[Polymerization|polymerize]] or [[oligomer]]ize than alkenes do. The resulting polymers, called [[polyacetylene]]s (which do not contain alkyne units) are [[conjugated system|conjugated]] and can exhibit semiconducting properties.

==Structure and bonding==
In acetylene, the H–C≡C [[bond angle]]s are 180°. By virtue of this bond angle, alkynes are rod-like. Correspondingly, cyclic alkynes are rare. [[Benzyne]] is highly unstable. The C≡C bond distance of 121 [[picometer]]s is much shorter than the C=C distance in [[alkene]]s (134&amp;nbsp;pm) or the C–C bond in alkanes (153&amp;nbsp;pm).

:[[File:Alkyne General Formulae V.2.png|thumb|center|580px|Illustrative alkynes: '''a''', acetylene, '''b''', two depictions of propyne, '''c''', 1-butyne, '''d''', 2-butyne, '''e''', the naturally-occurring 1-phenylhepta-1,3,5-triyne, and '''f''', the strained cycloheptyne. Triple bonds are highlighted &lt;span style=&quot;color:blue;&quot;&gt;'''blue'''&lt;/span&gt;.]]

The [[triple bond]] is very strong with a [[bond strength]] of 839 kJ/mol. The sigma bond contributes 369&amp;nbsp;kJ/mol, the first pi bond contributes 268&amp;nbsp;kJ/mol and the second pi-bond of 202&amp;nbsp;kJ/mol bond strength. Bonding usually discussed in the context of [[molecular orbital theory]], which recognizes the triple bond as arising from overlap of s and p orbitals. In the language of [[valence bond theory]], the carbon atoms in an alkyne bond are [[sp hybridized]]: they each have two unhybridized [[p orbital]]s and two [[Orbital hybridisation|sp hybrid orbitals]]. Overlap of an sp orbital from each atom forms one sp–sp [[sigma bond]]. Each p orbital on one atom overlaps one on the other atom, forming two [[pi bond]]s, giving a total of three bonds. The remaining sp orbital on each atom can form a sigma bond to another atom, for example to hydrogen atoms in the parent acetylene. The two sp orbitals project on opposite sides of the carbon atom.

===Terminal and internal alkynes===
Internal alkynes feature carbon substituents on each acetylenic carbon. Symmetrical examples include [[diphenylacetylene]] and [[3-hexyne]].

Terminal alkynes have the formula RC&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;H. An example is [[methylacetylene]] (propyne using IUPAC nomenclature). Terminal alkynes, like [[acetylene]] itself, are mildly acidic, with p''K''&lt;sub&gt;a&lt;/sub&gt; values of around 25. They are far more acidic than alkenes and alkanes, which have p''K''&lt;sub&gt;a&lt;/sub&gt; values of around 40 and 50, respectively. The acidic hydrogen on terminal alkynes can be replaced by a variety of groups resulting in halo-, silyl-, and alkoxoalkynes. The [[carbanion]]s generated by deprotonation of terminal alkynes are called [[acetylide]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;de57&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Bloch|first=Daniel R.|title=Organic Chemistry Demystified|year=2012|publisher=McGraw-Hill|isbn=978-0-07-176797-2|pages=57|edition=2nd}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Naming alkynes==
In [[Chemical nomenclature|systematic chemical nomenclature]], alkynes are named with the Greek prefix system without any additional letters. Examples include ethyne or octyne. In parent chains with four or more carbons, it is necessary to say where the triple bond is located. For [[octyne]], one can either write 3-octyne or oct-3-yne when the bond starts at the third carbon. The lowest number possible is given to the [[triple bond]]. When no superior functional groups are present, the parent chain must include the triple bond even if it is not the longest possible carbon chain in the molecule. Ethyne is commonly called by its trivial name acetylene.

In chemistry, the [[affix|suffix]] '''[[-yne]]''' is used to denote the presence of a triple bond. In [[organic chemistry]], the suffix often follows [[Chemical nomenclature|IUPAC nomenclature]]. However, [[inorganic compound]]s featuring [[Saturated and unsaturated compounds|unsaturation]] in the form of triple bonds may be denoted by substitutive nomenclature with the same methods used with alkynes (i.e. the name of the corresponding saturated compound is modified by replacing the &quot;[[-ane]]&quot; ending with &quot;-yne&quot;). [[Polyyne|&quot;-diyne&quot;]] is used when there are two triple bonds, and so on. The position of unsaturation is indicated by a numerical [[locant]] immediately preceding the &quot;-yne&quot; suffix, or 'locants' in the case of multiple triple bonds. Locants are chosen so that the numbers are low as possible. &quot;-yne&quot; is also used as an [[infix]] to name substituent groups that are triply bound to the parent compound.

Sometimes a number between [[hyphen]]s is inserted before it to state which atoms the triple bond is between. This suffix arose as a collapsed form of the end of the word &quot;[[acetylene]]&quot;. The final &quot;-e&quot; disappears if it is followed by another suffix that starts with a vowel.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |author=The Commission on the Nomenclature of Organic Chemistry |title=Nomenclature of Organic Chemistry |origyear= 1958 (A: Hydrocarbons, and B: Fundamental Heterocyclic Systems), 1965 (C: Characteristic Groups) |year=1971 |edition=3rd |publisher=Butterworths |location=London |isbn= 0-408-70144-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Synthesis==
===Cracking===
Commercially, the dominant alkyne is acetylene itself, which is used as a fuel and a precursor to other compounds, e.g., [[acrylate]]s. Hundreds of millions of kilograms are produced annually by partial oxidation of [[natural gas]]:&lt;ref name=Ullmann/&gt;
: 2&amp;nbsp;CH&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; + {{sfrac|3|2}}&amp;nbsp;O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; → HC≡CH + 3 H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O
Propyne, also industrially useful, is also prepared by [[thermal cracking]] of hydrocarbons. 

===Dehydrohalogenation and related reactions===
Specialty alkynes are prepared by double [[dehydrohalogenation]]. The reaction provides a means to generate alkynes from alkenes, which are first halogenated and then dehydrohalogenates. For example, [[phenylacetylene]] can be generated from styrene by bromination followed by treatment of the resulting of styrene dibromide with [[sodium amide]] in [[ammonia]]:&lt;ref&gt;{{OrgSynth | doi= 10.15227/orgsyn.030.0072| volume= 30 | page = 72 | year = 1950 | title = Phenylacetylene | author = Kenneth N. Campbell, Barbara K. Campbell}}&lt;/ref&gt;

:[[File:Phenylacetylene prepn.png|350px]]

Via the [[Fritsch–Buttenberg–Wiechell rearrangement]], alkynes are prepared from [[vinyl bromide]]s. Alkynes can be prepared from [[aldehyde]]s using the [[Corey–Fuchs reaction]] and from aldehydes or [[ketone]]s by the [[Seyferth–Gilbert homologation]].

==Reactions==
Featuring a reactive [[functional group]], alkynes participate in many [[organic reaction]]s. Such use was pioneered by [[Ralph Raphael]], who in 1955 wrote the first book describing their versatility as intermediates in [[organic synthesis|synthesis]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Raphael, Ralph Alexander | title =Acetylenic compounds in organic synthesis | year =1955 | publisher= Butterworths Scientific Publications  |location=London |url= https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=mdp.39015064396958;view=1up;seq=12 |oclc=3134811}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Addition of hydrogen, halogens, and related reagents===
Alkynes characteristically undergo reactions that show that they are &quot;doubly unsaturated&quot;, meaning that each alkyne unit is capable of adding two equivalents of H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, [[halogen]]s or related HX reagents (X&amp;nbsp;= halide, pseudohalide, etc.). Depending on catalysts and conditions, alkynes add one or two equivalents of hydrogen. Partial [[hydrogenation]], stopping after the addition of only one equivalent to give the [[alkene]], is usually more desirable since alkanes are less useful:
[[File:PhC2HH2.png|frameless|400px|center]]
The largest scale application of this technology is the conversion of acetylene to ethylene in refineries. The steam cracking of alkanes yields a few percent acetylene, which is selectively hydrogenated in the presence of a [[palladium]]/[[silver]] catalyst. For more complex alkynes, the [[Lindlar catalyst]] is widely recommended to avoid formation of the alkane, for example in the conversion of [[phenylacetylene]] to [[styrene]].&lt;ref&gt;{{OrgSynth | collvol = 5 | collvolpages = 880 | year = 1973 | prep = cv5p0880 | author = H. Lindlar |author2=R. Dubuis | title = Palladium catalyst for partial reduction of acetylenes}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, [[halogenation]] of alkynes gives the vinyl dihalides or alkyl tetrahalides:

:RC≡CR′ + 2 Br&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; → RCBr&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;CR′Br&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;

The addition of nonpolar E–H bonds across C≡C is general for silanes, boranes, and related hydrides. The [[hydroboration-oxidation reaction|hydroboration]] of alkynes gives vinylic boranes which oxidize to the corresponding [[aldehyde]] or ketone. In the [[thiol-yne reaction]] the substrate is a thiol.

Acid-promoted addition reactions are likewise analogous to those of alkenes, including [[Markovnikov's rule|Markovnikov]] selectivity. [[Hydrohalogenation]] gives the corresponding [[vinyl halide]]s or alkyl dihalides, again depending on the number of equivalents of HX added. The [[hydration reaction]] gives an [[enol]] via the addition of one equivalent of water, a structure that [[Keto–enol tautomerism|tautomerize]]s to form a ketone or aldehyde. For example, the hydration of [[phenylacetylene]] gives [[acetophenone]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author1=Fukuda, Y. |author2=Utimoto, K. | title = Effective transformation of unactivated alkynes into ketones or acetals with a gold(III) catalyst | journal = [[J. Org. Chem.]] | doi = 10.1021/jo00011a058 | year = 1991 | volume = 56 | pages = 3729 | issue = 11}}.&lt;/ref&gt; and the (Ph&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;P)AuCH&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;-catalyzed hydration of 1,8-nonadiyne to 2,8-nonanedione:&lt;ref&gt;{{OrgSynth | author = Mizushima, E. |author2=Cui, D.-M. |author3=Nath, D. C. D. |author4=Hayashi, T. |author5=Tanaka, M. | title = Au(I)-Catalyzed hydratation of alkynes: 2,8-nonanedione | volume = 83 | pages = 55 | year = 2005 | prep = v83p0055}}&lt;/ref&gt;
:PhC≡CH + H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O → PhCOCH&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;
:HC≡C(CH&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;)&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt;C≡CH + 2H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O → CH&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;CO(CH&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;)&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt;COCH&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;

===Cycloadditions and oxidation===
Alkynes undergo diverse [[cycloaddition]] reactions. Most notable is the [[Diels–Alder reaction]] with 1,3-[[diene]]s to give [[1,4-cyclohexadienes]]. This general reaction has been extensively developed and electrophilic alkynes are especially effective [[dienophile]]s. The &quot;cycloadduct&quot; derived from the addition of alkynes to [[2-pyrone]] eliminates [[carbon dioxide]] to give the [[aromatic]] compound. Other specialized cycloadditions include multicomponent reactions such as [[alkyne trimerisation]] to give [[aromatic]] compounds and the [2+2+1]-cycloaddition of an alkyne, [[alkene]] and [[carbon monoxide]] in the [[Pauson–Khand reaction]]. Non-carbon reagents also undergo cyclization, e.g. [[Azide alkyne Huisgen cycloaddition]] to give [[triazole]]s. Cycloaddition processes involving alkynes are often catalyzed by metals, e.g. [[enyne metathesis]] and [[alkyne metathesis]], which allows the scrambling of carbyne (RC) centers:
:RC≡CR + R′C≡CR′ {{eqm}} 2&amp;nbsp;RC≡CR′
Oxidative cleavage of alkynes proceeds via cycloaddition to metal oxides. Most famously, [[potassium permanganate]] converts alkynes to a pair of [[carboxylic acid]]s.

===Reactions specific for terminal alkynes===
Terminal alkynes are readily converted to many derivatives, e.g. by coupling reactions and condensations.  Via the condensation with formaldehyde and acetylene is produced [[1,4-Butynediol|butynediol]]:&lt;ref name=&quot;Ullmann&quot;&gt;{{Ullmann|first1=Heinz|last1=Gräfje|first2=Wolfgang|last2=Körnig|first3=Hans-Martin|last3=Weitz|first4=Wolfgang|last4=Reiß|first5=Guido|last5=Steffan|first6=Herbert|last6=Diehl|first7=Horst |last7=Bosche|first8=Kurt|last8=Schneider|first9=Heinz|last9=Kieczka|title=Butanediols, Butenediol, and Butynediol|year=2000|doi=10.1002/14356007.a04_455}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=UllmannC4&gt;{{Ullmann |author1=Peter Pässler |author2=Werner Hefner |author3=Klaus Buckl |author4=Helmut Meinass |author5=Andreas Meiswinkel |author6=Hans-Jürgen Wernicke |author7=Günter Ebersberg |author8=Richard Müller |author9=Jürgen Bässler |author10=Hartmut Behringer |author11=Dieter Mayer |title=Acetylene | year=2008 |doi=10.1002/14356007.a01_097.pub3 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  
:2 CH&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O  +  HC&amp;equiv;CH  →  HOCH&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;CCCH&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;OH

In the [[Sonogashira reaction]], terminal alkynes are coupled with aryl or vinyl halides
:[[File:Sonogashira reaction scheme ACS.png|left|400px|thumb|The Sonogashira Reaction]]

This reactivity exploits the fact that terminal alkynes are weak acids, with [[Acid dissociation constant|p''K''&lt;sub&gt;a&lt;/sub&gt;]] values (25) between that of [[ammonia]] (35) and [[ethanol]] (16):
:RC≡CH + MX → RC≡CM + HX{{spaces|5}} (MX = [[sodium amide|NaNH&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;]], [[N-Butyllithium|LiBu]], [[Grignard reagent|RMgX]])
The reactions of alkynes with certain metal cations, e.g. Ag&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; and Cu&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; also gives acetylides. Thus, few drops of [[Tollens reagent|diamminesilver(I) hydroxide]] (Ag(NH&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;)&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;OH) reacts with terminal alkynes signaled by formation of a white precipitate of the silver acetylide.  This reactivity is the basis of alkyne [[coupling reaction]]s, including the [[Cadiot–Chodkiewicz coupling]], [[Glaser coupling]], and the [[Eglinton coupling]]:&lt;ref&gt;{{OrgSynth | title = &lt;nowiki&gt;[18]Annulene&lt;/nowiki&gt; | author = K. Stöckel and F. Sondheimer | volume= 54 | page = 1| year = 1974 | doi= 10.15227/orgsyn.054.0001}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

:&lt;chem&gt;2R-\!{\equiv}\!-H -&gt;[\ce{Cu(OAc)2}][\ce{pyridine}] R-\!{\equiv}\!-\!{\equiv}\!-R&lt;/chem&gt;

In the [[Favorskii reaction]] and in [[alkynylation]]s in general, terminal alkynes add to [[carbonyl]] compounds to give the [[hydroxyalkyne]].

===Metal complexes===
{{main|Transition metal alkyne complex}}
Alkynes form complexes with transition metals. Such complexes occur also in metal catalyzed reactions of alkynes such as [[alkyne trimerization]].  Terminal alkynes, including acetylene itself, react with water to give aldehydes.  The transformation typically requires metal catalysts to give this anti-Markovnikov addition result.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.1055/s-2007-966002|title=Catalytic Hydration of Alkynes and Its Application in Synthesis|journal=Synthesis|volume=2007|issue=8|pages=1121–1150|year=2007|last1=Hintermann|first1=Lukas|last2=Labonne|first2=Aurélie|url=https://semanticscholar.org/paper/199ff28a7db593b20b7fbe565069da3785c7a85e}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Alkynes in nature and medicine==
According to Ferdinand Bohlmann, the first naturally occurring acetylenic compound, dehydromatricaria ester, was isolated from an ''Artemisia'' species in 1826. In the nearly two centuries that have followed, well over a thousand naturally occurring acetylenes have been discovered and reported. Polyynes, a subset of this class of natural products, have been isolated from a wide variety of plant species, cultures of higher fungi, bacteria, marine sponges, and corals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Annabelle L. K. Shi Shun |author2=Rik R. Tykwinski| title = Synthesis of Naturally Occurring Polyynes| journal = Angew. Chem. Int. Ed. | year = 2006| volume = 45 | pages = 1034–1057| doi = 10.1002/anie.200502071 | issue = 7 | pmid=16447152}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some acids like [[tariric acid]] contain an alkyne group. Diynes and triynes, species with the linkage RC≡C–C≡CR′ and RC≡C–C≡C–C≡CR′ respectively, occur in certain plants (''[[Ichthyothere]]'', ''[[Chrysanthemum]]'', ''[[Cicuta]]'', ''[[Water dropwort|Oenanthe]]'' and other members of the [[Asteraceae]] and [[Apiaceae]] families). Some examples are [[cicutoxin]], [[oenanthotoxin]], and [[falcarinol]] . These compounds are highly bioactive, e.g. as [[nematocide]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author =Lam, Jørgen |title=Chemistry and biology of naturally-occurring acetylenes and related compounds (NOARC): proceedings of a Conference on the Chemistry and Biology of Naturally-Occurring Acetylenes and Related Compounds (NOARC) |publisher=Elsevier |location=Amsterdam |year=1988 |pages= |isbn=0-444-87115-2 }}&lt;/ref&gt; 1-Phenylhepta-1,3,5-triyne is illustrative of a naturally occurring triyne.

Alkynes occur in some pharmaceuticals, including the contraceptive [[noretynodrel]]. A carbon–carbon triple bond is also present in marketed drugs such as the antiretroviral [[Efavirenz]] and the antifungal [[Terbinafine]]. Molecules called ene-diynes feature a ring containing an alkene (&quot;ene&quot;) between two alkyne groups (&quot;diyne&quot;). These compounds, e.g. [[calicheamicin]], are some of the most aggressive antitumor drugs known, so much so that the ene-diyne subunit is sometimes referred to as a &quot;warhead&quot;. Ene-diynes undergo rearrangement via the [[Bergman cyclization]], generating highly reactive radical intermediates that attack DNA within the tumor.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author1=S. Walker |author2=R. Landovitz |author3=W.D. Ding |author4=G.A. Ellestad |author5=D. Kahne | title = Cleavage behavior of calicheamicin gamma 1 and calicheamicin T | journal = Proc Natl Acad Sci USA | year = 1992| volume = 89 | issue = 10 | pages = 4608–12 | pmc=49132 | doi = 10.1073/pnas.89.10.4608 | pmid = 1584797|bibcode = 1992PNAS...89.4608W }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{wiktionary}}
{{wikiquote}}
* [[-yne]]
* [[cycloalkyne]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{Hydrocarbons}}
{{Alkynes}}
{{Functional Groups}}
{{BranchesofChemistry}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Alkynes| ]]
[[Category:Functional groups]]</text>
      <sha1>bkf0ht6ikg7t0auwk0kuw5q0t3s8bmm</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
