  <page>
    <title>Abiathar</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2740</id>
    <revision>
      <id>936321036</id>
      <parentid>934326202</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-18T01:58:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Alephb</username>
        <id>5105042</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>removing diacritics per [[WP:HEBREW]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{For|the legendary Jewish priest and convert to Christianity|Abiathar and Sidonia}}
'''Abiathar ''' ({{Lang-he|אֶבְיָתָר}} ''’Evyatar'', &quot;the father is great&quot;), in the [[Hebrew Bible]], is a son of [[Ahimelech]] or Ahijah, [[Kohen Gadol|High Priest]] at [[Nob, Israel|Nob]],{{sfn|Chisholm|1911}} the fourth in descent from [[Eli (Bible)|Eli]] ({{bibleverse|1 Samuel|23:6|KJV}}) and the last of Eli's House to be a High Priest.

==Bible account==
Abiathar was the only one of the priests to escape from [[Saul]] (reigned c. 1020–1000 BCE)'s massacre in [[Nob, Israel|Nob]], when his father and the priests of Nob were slain on the command of Saul. He fled to [[David]] (reigned c. 1003–970 BCE) at [[Keilah]], taking with him the [[ephod]] and other priestly regalia ({{bibleverse|1 Samuel|22:20|KJV}} f., {{bibleref2-nb|1 Samuel|23:6, 9|KJV}}). Rabbinical literature that linked the later extermination of the male descendants of David with the priests of Nob, also link the survival of David's descendant [[Jehoash of Judah|Joash]] with that of Abiathar (Sanh. 95b).&lt;ref name=je&gt;[https://archive.is/20071113024537/http://jewishencyclopedia.com/view_page.jsp?artid=265&amp;letter=A&amp;pid=0 ''Jewish Encyclopedia'' p.56]&lt;/ref&gt;

Abiathar joined David, who was then in the cave of [[Adullam]] ({{bibleref2|1 Samuel|22:20–23|KJV}}; {{bibleverse-nb|1 Samuel|23:6|KJV}}). He remained with David, and became priest of the party of which he was the leader ({{bibleverse|1 Samuel|30:7|KJV}}). He was of great service to David, especially at the time of the rebellion of [[Absalom]] ({{bibleref2|2 Samuel|15:24, 29, 35, 20:25|KJV}}).

When David ascended the throne of [[Kingdom of Judah|Judah]], Abiathar was appointed High Priest ({{bibleverse|1 Chronicles|15:11|KJV}}; {{bibleverse|1 Kings|2:26|KJV}}) and the &quot;king's counselor&quot; ({{bibleref2|1 Chronicles|27:33–34|KJV}}). Meanwhile, [[Zadok]], of the house of Eleazar, had been made High Priest.  Another version says he was Co-Pontiff with Zadok during King David. These appointments continued in force till the end of David's reign. In {{bibleverse|1 Kings|4:4|KJV}} Zadok and Abiathar are found acting together as priests under Solomon.

Abiathar was deposed (the sole historical instance of the deposition of a high priest) and banished to his home at [[Anathoth]] by [[Solomon]] ({{bibleref2|1 Kings|1:22, 26|KJV}}), because he took part in the attempt to raise [[Adonijah]] to the throne instead of Solomon ({{bibleref2|1 Kings|1:7, 19, 25|KJV}}). The priesthood thus passed from the house of Ithamar ({{bibleverse|1 Samuel|2:30–36|KJV}}; {{bibleref2|1 Kings|1:19; 2:26, 27|KJV}}) to the house of Eleazar.

==In rabbinic literature==
The rescue of the chief priest Abiathar, in the massacre of the priests of Nob ordered by Saul, was fortunate for the house of David; for if he had lost his life, David's descendants would through divine retaliation have been entirely wiped out of existence at the hands of Athaliah.&lt;ref&gt;Sanhedrin 95b&lt;/ref&gt; It was David's acts that had really brought about the death of the priests, and to make amends he appointed Abiathar high priest. Abiathar retained the office until he was deserted by the Holy Spirit, without which the high priest could not successfully consult the Urim and Thummim.&lt;ref name=je/&gt; When David, on his flight from Absalom, recognized this loss in Abiathar, he felt compelled to put Zadok in his place. See Seder 'Olam R. xiv.; Yoma, 73b; Soṭah, 48b; Ber. 4a (Rashi); Sanh. 21a. Compare also Ginzberg, &quot;Haggada bei den Kirchenvätern,&quot; i., on II Sam. xv. 24, 25.Abiathar's removal from the Priesthood fulfilled that other part of the curse on the House of Eli—that the Priesthood would pass out of the House of Eli

==Confusion of the name==
In {{bibleverse|2 Samuel|8:17|KJV}} ''Ahimelech, the son of Abiathar'' is suggested to be read, with the Syriac, for ''Abiathar, the son of Ahimelech.''&lt;ref name=Chisholm&gt;{{EB1911|inline=1|wstitle=Abiathar|volume=1|page=62}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A similar confusion occurs in [[Gospel of Mark]] {{bibleverse-nb|Mark|2:26|KJV}}:&lt;ref name=Chisholm/&gt;&lt;ref name=EB/&gt; in reporting Jesus' words, [[Mark the Evangelist|the evangelist]] used the name Abiathar when we might expect to see Jesus mention his father [[Ahimelech]].&lt;ref name=EB/&gt; Suggestions made to resolve the difficulty — e.g. that father and son each bore the same double name, or that Abiathar officiated during his father's lifetime and in his father's stead—have been supported by great names, but have not been fully accepted.&lt;ref name=EB&gt;&quot;Abiathar&quot;, ''[[Encyclopedia Biblica]]''&lt;/ref&gt;

==Later use of the name==

In Georgian traditions, [[Abiathar and Sidonia]] were a legendary [[Jewish]] priest of [[Mtskheta]] and his daughter. Abiathar is said to have been the first person [[Saint Nino]] converted to [[Christianity]].

&quot;Abiathar&quot; ({{IPA-he|evjaˈtar|pron}} in Modern Hebrew) is sometimes used as a male given name in contemporary [[Israel]] (see [[Eviatar Banai]], [[Eviatar Zerubavel]], [[Eviatar Manor]]).

==See also==
* [[Abiathar (name)]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* {{Britannica|1274}}

{{s-start}}
{{s-rel|isra}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Ahimelech]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[List of High Priests of Israel|High Priest of Israel]]}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Zadok]]}}
{{s-end}}
{{High Priests of Judaism}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Abiathar}}
[[Category:11th-century BC High Priests of Israel]]
[[Category:10th-century BC High Priests of Israel]]
[[Category:David]]
[[Category:11th-century BC clergy]]
[[Category:10th-century BC clergy]]
[[Category:11th-century BCE Hebrew people]]
[[Category:10th-century BCE Hebrew people]]
[[Category:Eli (biblical figure)]]
[[Category:High Priests of Israel]]</text>
      <sha1>cah2ncwiac58y4a33kmnzph7ztymhne</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
