  <page>
    <title>Atari Lynx</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2783</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941748334</id>
      <parentid>941747338</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-20T12:29:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Govvy</username>
        <id>715408</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 941747338 by [[Special:Contributions/108.53.126.5|108.53.126.5]] ([[User talk:108.53.126.5|talk]]) those machines came a lot later, they didn't have an effect on the Lynx.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use mdy dates|date=February 2015}}
{{Infobox information appliance
| name         = Atari Lynx
| logo         = File:Atari_Lynx_logo.svg
| image        = Atari-Lynx-I-Handheld.jpg
| caption      = Atari Lynx I
| developer    = {{unbulletedlist|[[Epyx]]|[[Atari Corporation]]}}
| manufacturer = Atari Corporation
| type         = [[Handheld game console]]
| generation   = [[fourth generation of video game consoles|Fourth generation]]
| releasedate  = {{Start date|1989|09|01}}
| lifespan     = 1989–1995
| price        =  US$179.99&lt;ref name=&quot;ToysRUs&quot;&gt;{{cite news |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |title=Toys R Us weekly ad |url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?nid=373&amp;dat=19901205&amp;id=ek1OAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=Oz8DAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=2470,1037511 |newspaper=The Catoosa County News |date=December 5, 1990 |accessdate=June 17, 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!-- this is price at initial release, not the current price. --&gt;
| unitssold    = Around 3 million
| media        = [[ROM cartridge]]
| cpu          = &quot;Mikey&quot; ([[WDC 65SC02]] 8-bit CPU + Sound processor + LCD driver)
| graphics     = &quot;Suzy&quot; (16-bit custom CMOS)
| display      = 160 × 102 standard resolution (16,320 addressable pixels)
| service      = &lt;!-- online service/s offered --&gt;
}}
The '''Atari Lynx''' is a 8/16-bit [[handheld game console]] that was released by [[Atari Corporation]] in September 1989 in North America, and in Europe and Japan in 1990.

It was the world's first [[handheld electronic game]] with a [[color]] [[LCD]]. It was also notable for its advanced graphics and [[ambidextrous]] layout. The Lynx competed with the [[Game Boy]] (released two months earlier), as well as the [[Game Gear]] and [[TurboExpress]], both released the following year. It was discontinued in 1995.

==History==
The Lynx system was originally developed by [[Epyx]] as the '''Handy Game'''. In 1986, two former [[Amiga]] designers, [[R. J. Mical]] and [[Dave Needle]], had been asked by former manager at Amiga, David Morse, if they could come up with a design for a portable gaming system.&lt;ref name= &quot;EGM1989&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Wired&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last=Jacobs |first=Steven |date= |title=Third Time's a Charm (They Hope) |url=http://archive.wired.com/wired/archive/2.01/3do_pr.html |journal=Wired |location=United States |publisher=Conde Nast |accessdate=June 17, 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Morse now worked at Epyx, a game software company that had a recent string of hit games. Morse's son had asked him if he could make a portable gaming system, prompting a meeting with Mical and Needle to discuss the idea. Morse convinced Mical and Needle to develop the idea and they were hired by Epyx to be a part of the design team.&lt;ref name=&quot;EGM1989&quot;/&gt; Planning and design of the console began in 1986 and was completed in 1987.&lt;ref name=&quot;retrogamer#4&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author=Peter Latimer |date=July 2005 |title=Atari Lynx |journal=Retro Gamer |issue=4 |pages=Pages 24–31 |issn=1742-3155 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Epyx first showed the Handy system at the Winter [[Consumer Electronics Show]] (CES) in January 1989.&lt;ref name=&quot;EGM1989&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Jermaine |first=John |date=November 1989 |title=Lynx, an interview with the men behind the machine |url=http://ataritimes.com/index.php?ArticleIDX=370 |journal=Electronic Gaming Monthly |location=United States |publisher=Sendai Publications |accessdate=June 17, 2014 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140916114505/http://ataritimes.com/index.php?ArticleIDX=370 |archivedate=September 16, 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Facing financial difficulties, Epyx sought out partners. [[Nintendo]], [[Sega]], and other companies declined, but Atari and Epyx eventually agreed that Atari would handle production and marketing, while Epyx would handle software development. Epyx declared bankruptcy by the end of the year, and Atari essentially owned the entire project; both Atari and others, however, had to purchase Amigas from Atari archrival [[Commodore Business Machines|Commodore]] to develop Lynx software.&lt;ref name=&quot;maher20161222&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.filfre.net/2016/12/a-time-of-endings-part-2-epyx/ |title=A Time of Endings, Part 2: Epyx |last=Maher |first=Jimmy |website=The Digital Antiquarian |publication-date=2016-12-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Handy was designed to run games from the cartridge format, and the game data must be copied from ROM to RAM before it can be used. Thus, less RAM is then available and each game's initial loading is slow.&lt;ref name=&quot;retrogamer&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author=Peter Latimer |date=July 2005 |title=Atari Lynx |journal=Retro Gamer |volume=2 |issue=6 |pages=Pages 24–31 |issn=1742-3155 }}&lt;/ref&gt; There are trace remnants of a [[Compact Cassette|cassette tape]] interface physically capable of being programmed to read a tape.  Lynx developers have noted that &quot;there is still reference of the tape and some hardware addresses&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Lynx programming tutorial&quot;&gt;{{cite web | work=Diary of an Atari Lynx developer | title=Atari Lynx programming tutorial series | author= | url=http://atarilynxdeveloper.wordpress.com/ | accessdate=June 18, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; and an updated vintage Epyx manual describes the bare existence of what could be utilized for tape support.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lynx Hardware Overview&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title=Lynx Hardware Overview | publisher=Epyx | url=http://www.monlynx.de/lynx/lynxdoc.html | year=1987 | accessdate=June 18, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|ch.2,8}}  A 2009 retrospective interview clarifies that although some early reports claimed that games were loaded from tape, Mical says there was no truth in them: &quot;We did think about hard disk a little.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Retroinspection: Atari Lynx&quot;&gt;{{ cite web | title=Retroinspection: Atari Lynx | date=January 22, 2009 | publisher=NOW Gamer | url=http://www.nowgamer.com/features/894712/retroinspection_atari_lynx.html | accessdate=June 18, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Atari changed the internal speaker and removed the thumb-stick on the control pad before releasing it as the Lynx, initially retailing in the US at {{US$|179.95}}. Atari then showed the Lynx to the press at the Summer 1989 CES as the &quot;Portable Color Entertainment System&quot;, which was changed to &quot;Lynx&quot; when actual consoles were distributed to resellers.&lt;ref name=&quot;retrogamer&quot;/&gt;

The Lynx started off successfully. Atari reported that they had sold 90% of the 50,000 units it shipped in its launch month in the U.S. with a limited launch in New York.&lt;ref name=&quot;NevadaDaily&quot;&gt;{{cite news |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |title=New games make big splash |url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?nid=1908&amp;dat=19900603&amp;id=yugfAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=lNkEAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=2239,4378537 |newspaper=The Nevada Daily Mail |location=Vernon County, Missouri |date=June 3, 1990 |accessdate=June 17, 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt; US sales in 1990 were approximately 500,000 units according to the [[Associated Press]].&lt;ref name=&quot;1990 sales&quot;&gt;{{cite press release|url=http://www.apnewsarchive.com/1991/Sega-Woos-Game-Boy-Lynx-Users-With-32-Color-Hand-Held-Video-System/id-a1288531efff2f9504f70dbcd9f8b6cc |title=Sega Woos Game Boy, Lynx Users With 32-Color, Hand-Held Video System |accessdate=November 7, 2013 |publisher=Associated Press| date =January 4, 1991|author=Catalina Ortiz}}&lt;/ref&gt; In late 1991, it was reported that Atari sales estimates were about 800,000, which Atari claimed was within their expected projections.&lt;ref name=&quot;Raze Magazine, issue 11&quot;&gt;{{ cite journal | url=https://archive.org/details/raze-magazine-11 | title=Raze Magazine | issue=11 | date=September 1991 | page=6 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Lifetime sales by 1995 amounted to fewer than 7&amp;nbsp;million units when combined with the Game Gear.&lt;ref name=seattle/&gt; In comparison, the Game Boy sold 16 million units by 1995&lt;ref name=seattle&gt;{{cite news|url=http://community.seattletimes.nwsource.com/archive/?date=19950105&amp;slug=2097913 |title=Virtual Fun - Nintendo Adds A New Dimension To Games |accessdate=November 7, 2013 |newspaper=Seattle Times| date =January 5, 1995|author=Steven Kent}}&lt;/ref&gt; because it was more rugged, cost half as much, had much longer battery life, was bundled with ''[[Tetris (Game Boy)|Tetris]]'', and had a superior software library.{{r|maher20161222}}

As with the actual console units, the game cartridges themselves evolved over the first year of the console's release. The first generation of cartridges were flat, and were designed to be stackable for ease of storage. However, this design proved to be very difficult to remove from the console and was replaced by a second design. This style, called &quot;tabbed&quot; or &quot;ridged&quot;, used the same basic design as the original cartridges with the addition of two small tabs on the cartridge's underside to aid in removal. The original flat style cartridges could be stacked on top of the newer cartridges, but the newer cartridges could not be easily stacked on each other, nor were they stored easily. Thus a third style, the &quot;curved lip&quot; style was produced, and all official and third-party cartridges during the console's lifespan were released (or re-released) using this style.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.atariage.com/system_labels.php?SystemID=LYNX Atari Lynx] cartridge style illustrations at AtariAge.com.&lt;/ref&gt;

In May 1991, Sega launched its Game Gear portable gaming handheld. Also a color handheld, in comparison to the Lynx it had a higher cost and shorter battery life (3–4 hours as opposed to 4-5 for the Lynx), but it was slightly smaller and was backed up by significantly more games.

Retailers such as [[Game (retailer)|Game]] and [[Toys R Us]] continued to sell the Lynx well into the mid-1990s on the back of the [[Atari Jaguar]] launch, helped by magazines such as ''Ultimate Future Games'' who continued to cover the Lynx alongside the new generation of 32-bit and 64-bit consoles.

===Lynx II===
[[File:Atari-Lynx-II-Handheld-Angled.jpg|right|thumb|The Atari Lynx II, smaller and lighter than the original]]
During 1990, the Lynx had moderate sales. In July 1991, Atari introduced the Lynx II with a new marketing campaign, new packaging, slightly improved hardware, better battery life and a new sleeker look. The new system (referred to within Atari as the &quot;Lynx II&quot;) featured rubber hand grips and a clearer backlit color screen with a power save option (which turned off the LCD panel's backlighting). It also replaced the monaural headphone jack of the original Lynx with one wired for stereo. The new packaging made the Lynx available without any accessories, dropping the price to $99. Although sales improved, Nintendo still dominated the handheld market.

===Decline===
In 1993, Atari started shifting its focus away from the Lynx in order to put greater focus on the Jaguar, which competed with the [[Super Nintendo Entertainment System|Super NES]] and [[Sega Genesis|Genesis]]. A few games were released during this time, including ''Battlezone 2000''. Support for the Lynx would not be formally discontinued until 1995.

In 1996, after the [[Failure#Commercial failures|commercial failure]] of the Jaguar, Atari terminated all internal game development and agreed to [[Reverse takeover|reverse merge]] with [[JT Storage|JTS, Inc.]], thus the [[Atari|Atari brand]] would leave the video game market for quite some time until [[Hasbro Interactive]] resurrected it in 1998.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=https://www.gamespot.com/articles/atari-goes-to-hasbro/1100-2462915/ | title=Atari goes to Hasbro | publisher=GameSpot | date=April 28, 2000}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Features==
[[File:Todd's Adventures in Slime World cover art (Atari Lynx).jpg|thumb|right|150px]]
The Atari Lynx's innovative features include being the first color handheld, with a backlit display, a switchable right-handed/left-handed (upside down) configuration, and the ability to network with up to 15 other units via its Comlynx system (though most games would network eight or fewer players). Comlynx was originally developed to run over infrared links (and was codenamed RedEye).&lt;ref name=&quot;retrogramer164&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |title=Todd's Adventures in Slime World |journal=Retro Gamer Magazine |volume= |issue=164 |pages=74 }}&lt;/ref&gt; This was changed to a cable-based networking system before the final release. According to Peter Engelbrite, when players walked through the beam, the link would be interrupted. The maximum stable connection allowed was eight players.&lt;ref name=&quot;retrogramer164&quot; /&gt; Engelbrite also developed the first recordable eight-player co-op game, and the only eight-player game for the Atari Lynx, ''[[Todd's Adventures in Slime World]]'', using the Comlynx system. Each Lynx needed a copy of the game, and one cable could connect two machines. The cables could be connected into a chain.

{{quote box 
| quote=&quot;The leading-edge display was the most expensive component, so the colour choice was one of economy. If the low-cost glass and drivers would have supported a million colours, I would have done it.&quot; 
| source=[[Dave Needle]], Lynx co-designer&lt;ref name=&quot;Retroinspection: Atari Lynx&quot;/&gt; 
| align=right 
| width=25% 
}}
The Lynx was cited as the &quot;first gaming console with [[Graphics processing unit|hardware]] support for zooming and distortion of [[sprite (computer graphics)|sprites]]&quot;.  Featuring a 4096 color palette and integrated math and graphics co-processors (including a [[blitter]] unit), its [[pseudo-3D]] color graphics display was said to be the key defining feature in the system's competition against Nintendo's monochromatic Game Boy.  The fast pseudo-3D graphics features were made possible on a minimal hardware system by co-designer [[Dave Needle]] having &quot;invented the technique for planar expansion/shrinking capability&quot; and using stretched, textured, triangles instead of full polygons.&lt;ref name=&quot;Retroinspection: Atari Lynx&quot;/&gt;

==Technical specifications==
[[File:Atari-Lynx-II-Motherboard.jpg|thumb|right|The motherboard of an Atari Lynx II. The larger chip is the &quot;Mikey&quot; and the smaller is called &quot;Suzy&quot;.]]
[[File:Atari-Lynx-II-Backlight.jpg|thumb|right|The backlight from an Atari Lynx II. The [[CCFL]] tube has high power consumption.]]
*Mikey (8-bit custom CMOS chip running at 16&amp;nbsp;MHz)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Atari Lynx FAQ|url=https://atariage.com/Lynx/faq/index.html|website=AtariAge|publisher=atariage.com|accessdate=October 24, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Western Design Center|WDC]] 8-bit 65SC02 processor (based on the [[MOS Technology 6502|MOS 6502]]) running at up to 4&amp;nbsp;MHz (3.6&amp;nbsp;MHz average)&lt;ref name=&quot;EGM1989&quot;/&gt;
**Sound engine
***4 channel sound
***8-bit DAC for each channel (4 channels × 8-bits/channel = 32 bits commonly quoted) these 4 sound channels can also switch in triple analogue sound mode to generate sound effects similar to FM &amp; PSG sound. Atari reports the range is &quot;100 Hz to above the range of human hearing&quot;; spectrum analysis shows the range may go as low as 32&amp;nbsp;Hz.{{citation needed|date=July 2018}}
***Stereo with panning (Lynx II PAG-0401 only, original Lynx and early Lynx II are mono)
**Video DMA driver for liquid-crystal display
***''Custom built and designed by [[Jay Miner]] and [[David Shannon Morse|David Morse]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://archive.org/stream/ace-magazine-23/ACE_Issue_23_1989_Aug#page/n25 |via=archive.org |publisher=ACE Magazine |date=August 1989 |accessdate=11 August 2018 |page=26 |issue=23 |title=Nintendo's island state of a stand at the Consumer Electronics Show in Chicago couldn't stop Atari stealing the limelight with their amazing hand-held video game machine.}}&lt;/ref&gt;
***160×102 pixels resolution
***4,096 color (12-bit) palette
***16 simultaneous colors (4 bits) from palette per scanline
***Variable frame rate (up to 75 frames/second)
**8 System timers (2 reserved for LCD timing, one for [[UART]])
**Interrupt controller
**UART (for Comlynx) (fixed format 8E1, up to 62500&amp;nbsp;Bd)
**512 bytes of bootstrap and game-card loading ROM
*Suzy (16-bit custom CMOS chip running at {{nowrap|16 MHz}})
**Unlimited number of [[blitter]] &quot;sprites&quot; with collision detection
**Hardware sprite scaling, distortion, and tilting effects
**Hardware decoding of compressed sprite data
**Hardware clipping and multi-directional scrolling
**Math engine
***Hardware 16-bit × 16-bit → 32-bit multiply with optional accumulation; 32-bit ÷ 16-bit → 16-bit divide
***Parallel processing of CPU
*[[RAM]]: 64 [[kilobyte|KB]] 120ns [[DRAM]]
*Cartridges of 128, 256, 512KiB and (with bank-switching) 1MiB
*Ports:
**[[Headphone]] port ({{nowrap|3.5 mm}} stereo; wired for mono on the original Lynx)
**ComLynx (multiple unit communications, serial)
*[[LCD]] Screen: 3.5&quot; diagonal
*[[Battery (electricity)|Battery]] holder (six AA) 4–5 hours (Lynx I) 5–6 hours (Lynx II)

==Reception==
The game system was reviewed in 1990 in ''[[Dragon (magazine)|Dragon]]'', which gave the Lynx 5 out of 5 stars. The review states that the Lynx &quot;throws the {{sic|Gameboy}} into the prehistoric age&quot;, and praises the built-in object scaling capabilities, the multiplayer feature of the ComLynx cable, and the strong set of launch games.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dragon155&quot;&gt;{{cite journal
|title=The Role of Computers
|last1=Lesser|last2=Lesser|last3=Lesser|first1=Hartley|first2=Patricia|first3=Kirk
|magazine=Dragon
|issue=155
|date=March 1990
|pages=95–101}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The infrequency of Lynx software releases and the system's minimal marketing budget have been cited as the main factors in its commercial failure.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine|last= |first= |title=The Next Generation 1996 Lexicon A to Z: Lynx|magazine=[[Next Generation (magazine)|Next Generation]]|issue=15 |publisher=[[Imagine Media]]|date=March 1996|page=36}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy==
[[Telegames]] released a number of games in the second half of the 1990s, including a port of ''[[Raiden (arcade game)|Raiden]]'' and a platformer called ''Fat Bobby'' in 1997,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine |title=News Bits|magazine=[[GamePro]] |issue=105 |publisher=[[International Data Group|IDG]] |date=June 1997|page=20}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as an action sports game called ''Hyperdrome'' in 1999.

In 1999, [[Hasbro]], which would continue to hold on to the Atari properties until 2000, released all development rights on the Lynx, as well as all patents relating to the Jaguar, into the [[public domain]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.retroisle.com/atari/lynx/general.php|title=Retro Isle - Atari Lynx|website=www.retroisle.com|access-date=2018-09-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; and thus the two platforms were declared open to everyone.

In 2008, Atari was honored at the 59th Annual [[Technology &amp; Engineering Emmy Award]]s for pioneering the development of [[handheld games]] with its Lynx game unit.&lt;ref name=&quot;CES 08 Nintendo Emmy&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gamespot.com/news/6184421.html |title=CES '08: Nintendo wins second Emmy |website=GameSpot |date=January 8, 2008 |accessdate=May 9, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Lynx games by independent developers include ''T-Tris'' (the first Lynx game with save-game feature),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://atariage.com/software_page.php?SoftwareID=2404|title=LYNX: T-Tris}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Alpine Games'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.duranik.com |title=Duranik|author=Duranik|publisher=|accessdate=February 13, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; and ''[[Zaku (video game)|Zaku]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.zaku-lynx.com/|title=Zaku - www.zaku-lynx.com|author=Brandon Cobb|publisher=|accessdate=February 13, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
*[[List of Atari Lynx games]]
*[[Atari#History|History of Atari]]

==References==
{{reflist | 30em}}

==External links==
{{commons category|Lynx (console)}}
* [http://www.atariage.com/software_search.html?SystemID=LYNX AtariAge &amp;ndash; Comprehensive Lynx Database and information]
* [http://www.retrovideogamer.co.uk/index.php?page=atarilynx Guide to Atari Lynx games at Retro Video Gamer]
* [http://www.usgamer.net/articles/too-good-for-its-day-ataris-lynx-remains-a-fan-favorite-25-years-later Too Powerful for Its Own Good, Atari's Lynx Remains a Favorite 25 Years Later]
* [http://st-news.com/issues/st-news-volume-5-issue-1/reviews/the-atari-lynx/ Atari Lynx review, 1990]
* [http://www.monlynx.de/lynx/lynxdoc.html Atari Lynx Hardware Documentation]

{{Atari hardware}}
{{Fourth generation game consoles}}
{{Handheld game consoles}}

[[Category:Computer-related introductions in 1989]]
[[Category:Handheld game consoles]]
[[Category:Fourth-generation video game consoles]]
[[Category:Atari consoles|Lynx]]
[[Category:1980s toys]]
[[Category:1990s toys]]</text>
      <sha1>rc3bi07p5sh8miti3xua8efis9qtbor</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
