  <page>
    <title>Chess</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5134</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943154120</id>
      <parentid>942831467</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-29T05:07:01Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bruce leverett</username>
        <id>27318187</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* History */ Mention the first Olympiad; mention that FIDE titles started in 1950.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{About|the Western board game|other chess games or other uses|Chess (disambiguation)}}
{{pp-vandalism|small=yes}}
{{short description|Strategy board game}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2016}}
{{Infobox game
|italic title=no
|title=Chess
|image=ChessSet.jpg
|image_size=250px
|alt=A selection of black and white chess pieces on a checkered surface.
|image_caption=Part of a [[Staunton chess set]] &lt;br /&gt;''Left to right:'' white [[king (chess)|king]], black [[rook (chess)|rook]], black [[queen (chess)|queen]], white [[pawn (chess)|pawn]], black [[knight (chess)|knight]], white [[bishop (chess)|bishop]]
|years={{circa}} 6th-century to present
|genre=[[Board game]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Abstract strategy game]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Mind sport]]
|players=2
|playing_time=Casual games usually last 10 to 60 minutes; tournament games last anywhere from about ten minutes ([[fast chess]]) to six hours or more.
|random_chance=None
|skills=[[Chess strategy|Strategy]], [[Chess tactic|tactics]]}}

'''Chess''' is a two-player [[abstract strategy game|strategy]] [[board game]] played on a checkered board with 64&amp;nbsp;squares arranged in an 8×8 grid. The game&lt;!--It is one of the world's most popular games{{citation needed|reason=This claim needs a reliable source|date=April 2015}}--&gt; is played by millions of people worldwide. Chess is believed to be derived from the Indian game ''[[chaturanga]]'' sometime before the 7th&amp;nbsp;century. Chaturanga is also the likely ancestor of the [[Eastern world|Eastern]] strategy games ''[[xiangqi]]'' (Chinese chess), ''[[janggi]]'' (Korean chess), and [[shogi]] (Japanese chess). Chess reached Europe by the 9th&amp;nbsp;century, due to the [[Umayyad conquest of Hispania]]. The pieces assumed their current powers in Spain in the late 15th&amp;nbsp;century; the modern rules were standardized in the 19th&amp;nbsp;century.

Play involves [[Perfect information|no hidden information]]. Each player begins with 16 [[chess piece|pieces]]: one [[king (chess)|king]], one [[queen (chess)|queen]], two [[rook (chess)|rooks]], two [[knight (chess)|knights]], two [[bishop (chess)|bishops]], and eight [[pawn (chess)|pawns]]. Each piece type [[#Movement|moves]] differently, with the most powerful being the queen and the least powerful the pawn. The objective is to [[checkmate]]{{refn|The word &quot;Checkmate&quot; is derived from the Persian ''Shah mat'' (&quot;the king is dead&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite EB1911 |wstitle=Chess |volume=6 |page=101 |short=1}}&lt;/ref&gt;|group=note}} the opponent's king by placing it under an inescapable threat of capture. To this end, a player's pieces are used to attack and capture the opponent's pieces, while supporting each other. During the game, play typically involves {{chessgloss|exchange|exchanging}} pieces for the opponent's similar pieces, and finding and engineering opportunities to trade advantageously or to get a better position. In addition to checkmate, a player wins the game if the opponent [[Rules of chess#Resigning|resigns]], or, in a timed game, runs out of time. There are also several ways that a game can end in a [[draw (chess)|draw]].

The first generally recognized [[World Chess Championship|World Chess Champion]], [[Wilhelm Steinitz]], claimed his title in 1886. Since 1948, the World Championship has been regulated by the [[Fédération Internationale des Échecs]] (FIDE), the game's international governing body. FIDE also awards life-time [[chess title|master titles]] to skilled players, the highest of which is [[Grandmaster (chess)|Grandmaster]] (GM). Many national chess organizations have a title system of their own. FIDE also organizes the [[Women's World Chess Championship|Women's World Championship]], the [[World Junior Chess Championship|World Junior Championship]], the [[World Senior Chess Championship|World Senior Championship]], the [[fast chess|Blitz and Rapid World Championships]], and the [[Chess Olympiad]], a popular competition among international teams. FIDE is a member of the [[International Olympic Committee]], which can be considered recognition of chess as a [[Olympic sports#Recognized sports|sport]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.olympic.org/world-chess-federation |title=Recognized Sports Federations: World Chess Federation |accessdate=22 October 2017 |publisher=International Olympic Committee |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20171023173859/https://www.olympic.org/world-chess-federation |archivedate=23 October 2017 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Several national sporting bodies (e.g. the Spanish ''[[Consejo Superior de Deportes]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.csd.gob.es/es/federaciones-y-asociaciones/federaciones-deportivas-espanolas/federaciones-espanolas |title=Federaciones Españolas |accessdate=19 February 2020 |publisher=Consejo Superior de Deportes |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;) also recognize chess as a sport. Chess was included in the 2006 and 2010 [[Asian Games]]. There is also a [[World Correspondence Chess Champion|Correspondence Chess World Championship]] and a [[World Computer Chess Championship]]. Online chess has opened amateur and professional competition to a wide and varied group of players.

Since the second half of the 20th century, [[chess engines]] have been programmed to play with increasing success, to the point where the strongest programs play at a higher level than the best human players. Since the 1990s, computer analysis has contributed significantly to [[chess theory]], particularly in the [[Chess endgame|endgame]]. The IBM computer [[Deep Blue (chess computer)|Deep Blue]] was the first machine to overcome a reigning World Chess Champion in a match when it [[Deep Blue versus Garry Kasparov|defeated]] [[Garry Kasparov]] in 1997. The rise of strong chess engines runnable on hand-held devices has led to increasing concern about [[Cheating in chess|cheating]] during tournaments.

There are many [[Chess variant|variants of chess]] that utilize different rules, pieces, or boards. One of these, [[Fischer Random Chess]], has gained widespread popularity and official FIDE recognition.

==Rules==
{{Main|Rules of chess}}
The rules of chess are published by [[FIDE]] (''Fédération Internationale des Échecs''), chess's international governing body, in its ''Handbook''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = https://handbook.fide.com/chapter/E012018 |title = Fide Laws of Chess taking effect from 1 January 2018 |accessdate = 18 February 2020 |publisher = FIDE |url-status=live |df = dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Rules published by national governing bodies, or by unaffiliated chess organizations, commercial publishers, etc., may differ. FIDE's rules were most recently revised in 2018.

===Setup===
{{Chess diagram small
|tright
|
|rd|nd|bd|qd|kd|bd|nd|rd
|pd|pd|pd|pd|pd|pd|pd|pd
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  |
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  |
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  |
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  |
|pl|pl|pl|pl|pl|pl|pl|pl
|rl|nl|bl|ql|kl|bl|nl|rl
|Initial position, ''first (bottom) row:'' rook, knight, bishop, queen, king, bishop, knight, and rook; ''second row:'' pawns
}}
[[File:ChessStartingPosition.jpg|thumb|upright=1.0|left|Setup at the start of a game]]
By convention, chess [[chess piece|game pieces]] are divided into [[White and Black in chess|white and black]] sets. Each set consists of 16 pieces: one king, one queen, two rooks, two bishops, two knights, and eight pawns. The pieces are set out as shown in the [[Chess diagram|diagram]] and photo. The players of the sets are referred to as ''White'' and ''Black'', respectively.

The game is played on a square [[Chessboard|board]] of eight rows (called ''{{chessgloss|ranks}}'', denoted ''1'' to ''8'' from bottom to top according to White's perspective) and eight columns (called ''{{chessgloss|files}}'', denoted ''a'' to ''h'' from left to right according to White's perspective). The 64 squares alternate in color and are referred to as ''light'' and ''dark'' squares. The chessboard is placed with a light square at the right-hand corner nearest to each player. Thus, each queen starts on a square of its own color (the white queen on a light square; the black queen on a dark square).
{{clear left}}

===Movement===
In competitive games, the colors are allocated by the organizers; in informal games, the colors are usually decided randomly, for example by coin toss, or by one player's concealing a white and black pawn in either hand and having the opponent choose. White moves first, after which players alternate turns, moving one piece per turn (except for [[castling]], when two pieces are moved). A piece is moved to either an unoccupied square or one occupied by an opponent's piece, which is captured and removed from play. With the sole exception of ''[[en passant]]'', all pieces capture by moving to the square that the opponent's piece occupies.

Moving is compulsory; it is illegal to skip a turn, even when having to move is [[zugzwang|detrimental]]. A player may not make any move that would put or leave the player's own king in [[#Check|check]]. If the player to move has no legal move, the game is over; the result is either [[checkmate]] (a loss for the player with no legal move) if the king is in check, or [[stalemate]] (a draw) if the king is not.

Each piece has its own way of moving. In the diagrams, the dots mark the squares to which the piece can move if there are no intervening piece(s) of either color (except the knight, which leaps over any intervening pieces).
{{col-begin|width=auto; float:right; clear:right}}
{{col-break}}
{{Chess diagram small
|tright
|Moves of the [[King (chess)|king]]
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  |
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  |
|  |  |  |  |xo|xo|xo|
|  |  |  |  |xo|kl|xo|
|  |  |  |  |xo|xo|xo|
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  |
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  |
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  | 
}}
{{col-break}}
{{Chess diagram small
|tright
|Moves of a [[Rook (chess)|rook]]
|  |  |  |xo|  |  |  | 
|  |  |  |xo|  |  |  | 
|  |  |  |xo|  |  |  | 
|xo|xo|xo|rl|xo|xo|xo|xo
|  |  |  |xo|  |  |  | 
|  |  |  |xo|  |  |  | 
|  |  |  |xo|  |  |  | 
|  |  |  |xo|  |  |  | 
}}
{{col-break}}
{{Chess diagram small
|tright
|Moves of a [[Bishop (chess)|bishop]]
|xo|  |  |  |  |  |xo|
|  |xo|  |  |  |xo|  | 
|  |  |xo|  |xo|  |  | 
|  |  |  |bl|  |  |  | 
|  |  |xo|  |xo|  |  | 
|  |xo|  |  |  |xo|  | 
|xo|  |  |  |  |  |xo| 
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  |xo
}}
{{col-end}}
{{col-begin|width=auto; float:right; clear:right}}
{{col-break}}
{{Chess diagram small
|tright
|Moves of the [[Queen (chess)|queen]]
|  |  |  |xo|  |  |  |xo
|xo|  |  |xo|  |  |xo| 
|  |xo|  |xo|  |xo|  | 
|  |  |xo|xo|xo|  |  | 
|xo|xo|xo|ql|xo|xo|xo|xo
|  |  |xo|xo|xo|  |  | 
|  |xo|  |xo|  |xo|  | 
|xo|  |  |xo|  |  |xo| 
}}
{{col-break}}
{{Chess diagram small
|tright
|Moves of a [[Knight (chess)|knight]]
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  | 
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  | 
|  |  |xo|  |xo|  |  | 
|  |xo|  |  |  |xo|  | 
|  |  |  |nl|  |  |  | 
|  |xo|  |  |  |xo|  | 
|  |  |xo|  |xo|  |  | 
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  | 
}}
{{col-break}}
{{Chess diagram small
|tright
|Moves of a [[Pawn (chess)|pawn]]
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  | 
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  | 
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  | 
|xx|xo|xx|  |  |  |  | 
|  |pl|  |  |  |xo|  | 
|  |  |  |  |xx|xo|xx| 
|  |  |  |  |  |pl|  | 
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  | 
}}
{{col-end}}
{{clear}}
* The [[king (chess)|king]] moves one square in any direction. The king also has a special move called ''[[#Castling|castling]]'' that involves also moving a rook.
* A [[rook (chess)|rook]] can move any number of squares along a rank or file, but cannot leap over other pieces. Along with the king, a rook is involved during the king's castling move.
* A [[bishop (chess)|bishop]] can move any number of squares diagonally, but cannot leap over other pieces.
* The [[queen (chess)|queen]] combines the power of a rook and bishop and can move any number of squares along a rank, file, or diagonal, but cannot leap over other pieces.
* A [[knight (chess)|knight]] moves to any of the closest squares that are not on the same rank, file, or diagonal. (Thus the move forms an &quot;L&quot;-shape: two squares vertically and one square horizontally, or two squares horizontally and one square vertically.) The knight is the only piece that can leap over other pieces.
* A [[pawn (chess)|pawn]] can move forward to the unoccupied square immediately in front of it on the same file, or on its first move it can advance two squares along the same file, provided both squares are unoccupied (black dots in the diagram); or the pawn can capture an opponent's piece on a square diagonally in front of it on an adjacent file, by moving to that square (black &quot;x&quot;s). A pawn has two special moves: the ''[[#En passant|en passant]]'' capture and [[#Promotion|promotion]].
{{clear left}}

===Castling===
{{Main|Castling}}
[[File:ChessCastlingMovie en.svg|thumb|upright=0.95|Examples of [[castling]] ([https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/5/55/ChessCastlingMovie_en.svg view animation])]]
Once in every game, each king can make a special move, known as ''[[castling]]''. Castling consists of moving the king two squares along the first rank toward a rook (that is on the player's first rank and then placing the rook on the last square that the king just crossed. Castling is permissible if the following conditions are met:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.fide.com/fide/handbook.html?id=207&amp;view=article |title=FIDE Laws of Chess, article 3.8.2 |publisher=World Chess Federation |work=fide.com |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170805002105/https://www.fide.com/fide/handbook.html?id=207&amp;view=article |archivedate=5 August 2017 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Neither the king nor the rook has previously moved during the game.
* There are no pieces between the king and the rook.
* The king cannot be in [[#Check|check]], nor can the king pass through any square that is under attack by an enemy piece, or move to a square that would result in check. (Note that castling ''is'' permitted if the rook is under attack, or if the rook crosses an attacked square.)

===''En passant''===
{{anchor|en passant}}
{{Main|En passant}}
[[File:ChessPawnSpecialMoves.gif|thumb|left|upright=1.15|Examples of pawn moves: &lt;br /&gt;(''left'') [[Promotion (chess)|promotion]]; (''right'') ''[[en passant]]'']]
When a pawn makes a two-step advance from its starting position and there is an opponent's pawn on a square next to the destination square on an adjacent file, then the opponent's pawn can capture it ''en passant'' (&quot;in passing&quot;), moving to the square the pawn passed over. This can be done only on the very next turn; otherwise the right to do so is forfeited. For example, in the animated diagram, the black pawn advances two steps from g7 to g5, and the white pawn on f5 can take it ''en passant'' on g6 (but only on White's next move).

===Promotion===
{{Main|Promotion (chess)}}
When a pawn advances to the eighth rank, as a part of the move it is ''promoted'' and must be exchanged for the player's choice of queen, rook, bishop, or knight of the same color. Usually, the pawn is chosen to be promoted to a queen, but in some cases another piece is chosen; this is called [[underpromotion]]. In the [[#En passant|animated diagram]], the pawn on c7 can be advanced to the eighth rank and be promoted. There is no restriction on the piece promoted to, so it is possible to have more pieces of the same type than at the start of the game (e.g., two or more queens).
{{clear left}}

===Check===
{{Main|Check (chess)}}
{{Chess diagram small
|tright
|
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  |
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  |
|  |  |kd|  |  |  |  |
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  |
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  |
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  |
|  |  |rl|  |  |  |  |
|  |  |  |  |kl|  |  |
|The black king is in [[Check (chess)|check]] by the rook.
}}
When a king is under immediate attack by one or two of the opponent's pieces, it is said to be ''in [[Check (chess)|check]]''. A move in response to a check is legal only if it results in a position where the king is no longer in check. This can involve capturing the checking piece; interposing a piece between the checking piece and the king (which is possible only if the attacking piece is a queen, rook, or bishop and there is a square between it and the king); or moving the king to a square where it is not under attack. Castling is not a permissible response to a check.

The object of the game is to checkmate the opponent; this occurs when the opponent's king is in check, and there is no legal way to remove it from attack. It is never legal for a player to make a move that puts or leaves the player's own king in check. In casual games it is common to announce &quot;check&quot; when putting the opponent's king in check, but this is not required by the rules of chess, and is not usually done in tournaments.

===End of the game===

====Win====
{{Chess diagram small
|tright
|
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  |
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  |
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  |
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  |
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  |
|  |  |  |  |bd|bd|  |kd
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  |
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  |kl
|White is in [[checkmate]], being unable to escape attack by the black bishops.
}}
Games can be won in the following ways:
* ''[[Checkmate]]:'' The player whose turn it is to move is in check and has no legal move to escape check.
* ''[[Rules of chess#Resigning|Resignation]]:'' Either player may resign, conceding the game to the opponent.&lt;ref&gt;Burgess (2000), p. 481&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''Win on time:'' In games with a [[time control]], a player wins if the opponent runs out of time, even if the opponent has a superior position, as long as the player has a theoretical possibility to checkmate the opponent.
* ''Forfeit:'' A player who cheats, violates the rules, or violates the rules specified for the particular tournament, can be forfeited. In high-level tournaments, players have been forfeited for such things as:
** arriving late for the game (even by a matter of seconds);
** receiving a call or text on a cell phone;
** refusing to undergo a drug test;
** refusing to undergo a body search for electronic devices;
** unsporting behavior (e.g. refusing to shake hands with the opponent).

====Draw====
{{Chess diagram small
|tright
|
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  |
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  |
|  |  |ql|  |  |  |  |
|kd|  |  |  |  |  |  |
|  |  |kl|  |  |  |  |
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  |
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  |
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  |
|Black is not in check and has no legal move. The result is [[stalemate]].
}}
There are several ways games can end in a [[Draw (chess)|draw]]:
* ''[[Draw by agreement]]:'' Draws are most commonly reached by mutual agreement between the players. The correct procedure is to verbally offer the draw, make a move, then start the opponent's clock. Traditionally, players have been allowed to agree to a draw at any point in the game, occasionally even without playing a move; in recent years efforts have been made to discourage short draws, for example by forbidding draw offers before move thirty.
* ''[[Stalemate]]:'' The player whose turn it is to move has no legal move and is not in check.
* ''[[Threefold repetition]] of position:'' This most commonly occurs when neither side is able to avoid repeating moves without incurring a disadvantage. In this situation, either player can claim a draw; this requires the players to keep a valid written record of the game so that the claim can be verified by the arbiter if challenged. The three occurrences of the position need not occur on consecutive moves for a claim to be valid. FIDE rules make no mention of [[perpetual check]]; this is merely a specific type of draw by threefold repetition.
* ''[[Fifty-move rule]]:'' If during the previous 50 moves no pawn has been moved and no capture has been made, either player can claim a draw. There are several known endgames where it is possible to force a mate but it requires more than 50 moves before a pawn move or capture is made; examples include some endgames with [[two knights endgame|two knights against a pawn]] and some [[pawnless chess endgame|pawnless endgames]] such as queen against two bishops. Historically, FIDE has sometimes revised the fifty-move rule to make exceptions for these endgames, but these have since been repealed. Some [[correspondence chess]] organizations do not enforce the fifty-move rule.{{refn|The fifty-move rule is not applied at FICGS.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ficgs.com/membership.html#chess |title=50 moves rules |accessdate=1 December 2009 |publisher=FICGS |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100209034210/http://www.ficgs.com/membership.html#chess |archivedate=9 February 2010 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;|group=note}}
* ''Fivefold repetition of position:'' Similar to the threefold-repetition rule, but in this case neither player needs to claim the draw; thus a tournament director can intervene and declare the game to be drawn. This is a relatively recent (2014) addition to the FIDE rules.
* ''Seventy-five-move rule:'' Similar to the fifty-move rule, but as with the fivefold repetition rule, this applies independently of claims by the players, and allows a tournament director to intervene. This rule likewise is a recent addition to the FIDE rules.
* ''{{chessgloss|Insufficient material}}:'' If neither player has a theoretical possibility to checkmate the opponent; for example, if a player has only the king and a knight, and the opponent has only the king, checkmate is impossible and the game is drawn by this rule. On the other hand, if both players still have a knight there is a highly unlikely yet theoretical possibility of checkmate, so this rule does not apply.
* ''Draw on time:'' In games with a [[time control]], the game is drawn if a player is out of time and the opponent has no theoretical possibility to checkmate the player.

===Time control===
[[File:DGT 2010 digital chess clock.ajb.jpg|alt=A chess clock with a brown base. A digital display shows the remaining time for each side.|thumb|A digital chess clock]]
In competition, chess games are played with a [[time control]]. If a player's time runs out before the game is completed, the game is automatically lost (provided the opponent has [[Rules of chess#Timing|enough pieces left]] to deliver checkmate). The duration of a game ranges from long (or &quot;classical&quot;) games, which can take up to seven hours (even longer if [[adjournment (chess)|adjournments]] are permitted), to [[bullet chess]] (under 3&amp;nbsp;minutes per player for the entire game). Intermediate between these are [[rapid chess]] games, lasting between 20&amp;nbsp;minutes and two hours per game, a popular time control in amateur weekend tournaments.

Time is controlled using a [[chess clock]] that has two displays, one for each player's remaining time. Analog chess clocks have been largely replaced by digital clocks, which allow for time controls with [[Time control#Compensation (increment or delay methods)|increments]].

Time controls are also enforced in correspondence chess competition. A typical time control is 50 days for every 10 moves.

==History==
{{Main|History of chess}}

===Predecessors===
{{Chaturanga diagram
|tright
|
|xx|  |  |xx|xx|  |  |xx
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  |
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  |
|xx|  |  |xx|xx|  |  |xx
|xx|  |  |xx|xx|  |  |xx
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  |
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  |
|xx|  |  |xx|xx|  |  |xx
|[[Ashtapada|Ashtāpada]], the uncheckered 8×8 board, sometimes with special marks, on which ''[[chaturanga]]'' was played
}}
Chess is believed to have originated in northwest [[India]], in the [[Gupta Empire]] ({{circa}} 280–550),&lt;ref&gt;Leibs (2004), p. 92&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Robinson &amp; Estes (1996), p. 34&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Murray (1913)&quot;&gt;Murray (1913)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bird (1893), p. 63&lt;/ref&gt; where its early form in the 6th&amp;nbsp;century was known as ''[[chaturanga|chaturaṅga]]'' ({{Lang-sa|चतुरङ्ग}}), literally ''four divisions'' [of the military]&amp;nbsp;– [[infantry]], [[cavalry]], [[war elephant|elephants]], and [[chariot]]ry, represented by the pieces that would evolve into the modern pawn, knight, bishop, and rook, respectively. Thence it spread eastward and westward along the [[Silk Road]]. The earliest evidence of chess is found in the nearby [[Sasanian Persia]] around 600, where the game came to be known by the name ''[[chatrang]]''. Chatrang was taken up by the [[Muslim world]] after the [[Islamic conquest of Persia]] (633–44), where it was then named ''[[shatranj]]'', with the pieces largely retaining their Persian names. In Spanish &quot;shatranj&quot; was rendered as ''ajedrez'' (&quot;al-shatranj&quot;), in [[Portuguese language|Portuguese]] as ''xadrez'', and in [[Greek language|Greek]] as ζατρίκιον (''zatrikion'', which comes directly from the Persian ''chatrang''),&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.04.0057%3Aentry%3Dzatri%2Fkion ζατρίκιον] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130703023305/http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.04.0057%3Aentry%3Dzatri%2Fkion |date=3 July 2013 }}, Henry George Liddell, Robert Scott, ''A Greek-English Lexicon'', on Perseus&lt;/ref&gt; but in the rest of Europe it was replaced by versions of the Persian ''shāh'' (&quot;king&quot;), which was familiar as an exclamation and became the English words &quot;check&quot; and &quot;chess&quot;.{{refn|At that time the Spanish word would have been written ''axedrez''. The Spanish &quot;x&quot; was pronounced as English &quot;sh&quot;, as the Portuguese &quot;x&quot; still is today. The spelling of ''ajedrez'' changed after [[Spanish orthography#Older conventions|Spanish lost the &quot;sh&quot; sound]].|group=note}}

The oldest archaeological chess artifacts, ivory pieces, were excavated in ancient [[Afrasiyab (Samarkand)|Afrasiab]], today's [[Samarkand]], in [[Uzbekistan]], central Asia, and date to about 760, with some of them possibly older. The oldest known chess manual was in Arabic and dates to 840–850, written by [[al-Adli ar-Rumi]] (800–870), a renowned Arab chess player, titled ''Kitab ash-shatranj'' (Book of the chess). This is a lost manuscript, but referenced in later works. The eastern migration of chess, into China and Southeast Asia, has even less documentation than its migration west. The first reference to Chinese chess, called ''xiàngqí'' {{lang|zh|象棋}}, appears in a book entitled ''Xuán guaì lù'' {{lang|zh|玄怪錄}} (&quot;Record of the Mysterious and Strange&quot;), dating to about 800. Alternatively, some contend that chess arose from Chinese chess or one of its predecessors,&lt;ref&gt;Li (1998)&lt;/ref&gt; although this has been contested.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Banaschak |first=Peter |title=A story well told is not necessarily true: a critical assessment of David H. Li's ''The Genealogy of Chess'' |url=http://www.banaschak.net/schach/ligenealogyofchess.htm |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130511071131/http://www.banaschak.net/schach/ligenealogyofchess.htm |archivedate=11 May 2013 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The game reached Western Europe and Russia by at least three routes, the earliest being in the 9th&amp;nbsp;century. By the year 1000, it had spread throughout both [[Al Andalus|Muslim Iberia]] and [[Latin Christianity|Latin Europe]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Hooper &amp; Whyld (1992), pp. 173–75&quot;&gt;Hooper &amp; Whyld (1992), pp. 173–75&lt;/ref&gt; A Latin poem ''[[Versus de scachis|de scachis]]'' dated to the late 10th century has been preserved in [[Einsiedeln Abbey]]. A famous 13th-century manuscript covering shatranj, [[backgammon]], and [[dice]] is known as the ''[[Libro de los juegos]]''.

===1200–1700: Origins of the modern game===
[[File:KnightsTemplarPlayingChess1283.jpg|thumb|right|[[Knights Templar]] playing chess, ''[[Libro de los juegos]]'', 1283]]
Around 1200, the rules of shatranj started to be modified in southern Europe, and around 1475, several major changes made the game essentially as it is known today.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hooper &amp; Whyld (1992), pp. 173–75&quot;/&gt; These modern rules for the basic moves had been adopted in Italy and Spain.&lt;ref&gt;Davidson (1949), pp. 13–17&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;nauiua&quot;&gt;{{cite web |author = Calvo, Ricardo |url = http://history.chess.free.fr/papers/Calvo%201998.pdf |title = Valencia Spain: The Cradle of European Chess |date = 1998 |accessdate = 3 March 2015 |url-status=live |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20160130113355/http://history.chess.free.fr/papers/Calvo%201998.pdf |archivedate = 30 January 2016 |df = dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Pawns gained the option of advancing two squares on their first move, while bishops and queens acquired their modern abilities. The [[Queen (chess)|queen]] replaced the earlier [[Vizier#Influence on chess|vizier]] chess piece towards the end of the 10th&amp;nbsp;century and by the 15th&amp;nbsp;century had become the most powerful piece;&lt;ref&gt;Yalom (2004)&lt;/ref&gt; consequently modern chess was referred to as &quot;Queen's Chess&quot; or &quot;Mad Queen Chess&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Weissberger (2004), pp. 152ff&lt;/ref&gt; Castling, derived from the &quot;kings leap&quot; usually in combination with a pawn or rook move to bring the king to safety, was introduced. These new rules quickly spread throughout western Europe.

[[File:Lucena1497.jpg|thumb|left|upright=0.70|A tactical puzzle from [[Luis Ramirez de Lucena|Lucena's]] 1497 book]]
Writings about the [[chess theory|theory]] of how to play chess began to appear in the 15th&amp;nbsp;century. The ''Repetición de Amores y Arte de Ajedrez'' (''Repetition of Love and the Art of Playing Chess'') by [[Spanish people|Spanish]] churchman [[Luis Ramirez de Lucena]] was published in [[Salamanca]] in 1497.&lt;ref name=&quot;nauiua&quot;/&gt; Lucena and later masters like Portuguese [[Pedro Damiano]], Italians [[Giovanni Leonardo Di Bona]], [[Giulio Cesare Polerio]] and [[Gioachino Greco]], and Spanish bishop [[Ruy López de Segura]] developed elements of [[#Opening|openings]] and started to analyze simple [[#Endgame|endgames]].

===1700–1873: The Romantic Era in chess===
[[File:André Philidor.jpg|thumb|[[François-André Danican Philidor]], 18th-century French chess master]]
In the 18th century, the center of European chess life moved from the Southern European countries to France. The two most important French masters were [[François-André Danican Philidor]], a musician by profession, who discovered the importance of pawns for chess strategy, and later [[Louis-Charles Mahé de La Bourdonnais]], who won a famous series of matches with the Irish master [[Alexander McDonnell]] in 1834.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.chessgames.com/perl/chessplayer?pid=31596 |title = Louis Charles Mahe De La Bourdonnais |website = [[Chessgames.com]] |accessdate = 26 November 2008 |url-status=live |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20081229231938/http://www.chessgames.com/perl/chessplayer?pid=31596 |archivedate = 29 December 2008 |df = dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Centers of chess activity in this period were [[coffee house]]s in major European cities like ''[[Café de la Régence]]'' in Paris and ''[[Simpson's-in-the-Strand|Simpson's Divan]]'' in London.&lt;ref&gt;Metzner (1998)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |author=Bird, Henry Edward |url=http://www.gutenberg.org/etext/4902 |title=Chess History and Reminiscences |accessdate=26 November 2008 |publisher=Gutenberg |date=January 2004 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090924125500/http://www.gutenberg.org/etext/4902 |archive-date=24 September 2009 |url-status=live |author-link=Henry Edward Bird }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Stalemate#History of the stalemate rule|The rules concerning stalemate]] were finalized in the early 19th&amp;nbsp;century. Also in the 19th&amp;nbsp;century, the convention that White moves first was established (formerly either White or Black could move first). Finally the rules around castling were standardized&amp;nbsp;– variations in the castling rules had persisted in Italy until the late 19th&amp;nbsp;century. The resulting standard game is sometimes referred to as ''Western chess''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.chessbase.com/newsdetail.asp?newsid=3492 |title = XiangQi – an alternate to Western Chess |publisher = ChessBase.com |author = René Gralla |url-status=live |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20110604145052/http://www.chessbase.com/newsdetail.asp?newsid=3492 |archivedate = 4 June 2011 |df = dmy-all |date = 2006-11-19 }}&lt;/ref&gt; or ''international chess'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.chessvariants.org/oriental.dir/thaikramnik.html |title = Kramnik plays Makruk Thai |author = René Gralla |accessdate = 12 December 2010 |website = [[The Chess Variant Pages]] |url-status=live |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20110606155706/http://www.chessvariants.org/oriental.dir/thaikramnik.html |archivedate = 6 June 2011 |df = dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; particularly in Asia where other games of the chess family such as [[xiangqi]] are prevalent. Since the 19th&amp;nbsp;century, the only rule changes have been technical in nature, for example establishing the correct procedure for claiming a draw by repetition.

As the 19th century progressed, chess organization developed quickly. Many [[chess club]]s, chess books, and chess journals appeared. There were correspondence matches between cities; for example, the London Chess Club played against the [[Edinburgh]] Chess Club in 1824.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.chessgames.com/perl/chessplayer?pid=80740 |title = London Chess Club |website = [[Chessgames.com]] |accessdate = 26 November 2008 |url-status=live |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20081225144954/http://www.chessgames.com/perl/chessplayer?pid=80740 |archivedate = 25 December 2008 |df = dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Chess problems]] became a regular part of 19th-century newspapers; [[Bernhard Horwitz]], [[Josef Kling]], and [[Samuel Loyd]] composed some of the most influential problems. In 1843, [[Tassilo von Heydebrand und der Lasa|von der Lasa]] published his and [[Paul Rudolf von Bilguer|Bilguer's]] ''[[Handbuch des Schachspiels]]'' (''Handbook of Chess''), the first comprehensive manual of chess theory.

[[File:immortal game animation.gif|frame|right|The &quot;[[Immortal Game]]&quot;, Anderssen vs. Kieseritzky, 1851]]
The first modern chess tournament was organized by [[Howard Staunton]], a leading English chess player, and was [[London 1851 chess tournament|held in London in 1851]]. It was won by the German [[Adolf Anderssen]], who was hailed as the leading chess master. His brilliant, energetic attacking style was [[Romantic chess|typical for the time]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://worldchessnetwork.com/English/chessHistory/salute/matchesTournaments/london1851.php |title=London, 1851 |author=Parr, Larry |publisher=World Chess Network |accessdate=26 November 2008 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20031004035110/http://worldchessnetwork.com/English/chessHistory/salute/matchesTournaments/london1851.php |archivedate=4 October 2003 |df=dmy-all |author-link=Larry Parr (editor) }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hartston (1985), p. 36&lt;/ref&gt; Sparkling games like Anderssen's [[Immortal Game]] and [[Evergreen Game]] or [[Paul Morphy|Morphy's]] &quot;[[Morphy versus the Duke of Brunswick and Count Isouard|Opera Game]]&quot; were regarded as the highest possible summit of the chess art.&lt;ref&gt;Burgess, Nunn, &amp; Emms (2004) p. 14&lt;/ref&gt;

The romantic era was characterized by opening [[gambit]]s (sacrificing pawns or even pieces), daring attacks, and brazen sacrifices. Many elaborate and beautiful but unsound move sequences called &quot;combinations&quot; were played by the masters of the time. The game was played more for art than theory. A profound belief that chess merit resided in the players' genius rather than inherent in the position on the board pervaded chess practice.

Deeper insight into the nature of chess came with the American [[Paul Morphy]], an extraordinary [[chess prodigy]]. Morphy won against all important competitors (except Staunton, who refused to play), including Anderssen, during his short chess career between 1857 and 1863. Morphy's success stemmed from a combination of brilliant attacks and sound strategy; he intuitively knew how to prepare attacks.&lt;ref&gt;Shibut (2004)&lt;/ref&gt;

===1873–1945: Birth of a sport===
[[Prague]]-born [[Wilhelm Steinitz]] beginning in 1873 described how to avoid weaknesses in one's own position and how to create and exploit such weaknesses in the opponent's position.&lt;ref&gt;Steinitz (2002)&lt;/ref&gt; The scientific approach and positional understanding of Steinitz revolutionized the game. Steinitz was the first to break a position down into its components.&lt;ref&gt;Kasparov (2003a), p. 6&lt;/ref&gt; Before Steinitz, players brought their queen out early, did not completely {{chessgloss|develop}} their other pieces, and mounted a quick attack on the opposing king, which either succeeded or failed. The level of defense was poor and players did not form any deep plan.&lt;ref&gt;Kasparov (2003a), p. 11&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to his theoretical achievements, Steinitz founded an important tradition: his triumph over the leading German master [[Johannes Zukertort]] in 1886 is regarded as the first official [[World Chess Championship]]. Steinitz lost his crown in 1894 to a much younger player, the German mathematician [[Emanuel Lasker]], who maintained this title for 27&amp;nbsp;years, the longest tenure of any world champion.&lt;ref&gt;Kasparov (1983a), p. 117&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Stanislaw Chlebowski - Chess Players.jpg|right|thumb|upright=0.80|''Chess Players, Cairo'' by [[Stanisław Chlebowski]] (1835–1884)]]
After the end of the 19th century, the number of master tournaments and matches held annually quickly grew. The first [[Chess Olympiad|Olympiad]] was held in Paris in 1924, and [[FIDE]] was founded initially for the purpose of organizing that event.  In 1927, the [[Women's World Chess Championship]] was established; the first to hold the title was Czech-English master [[Vera Menchik]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.chessgames.com/perl/chessplayer?pid=13277 |title=Vera Menchik |website=[[Chessgames.com]] |accessdate=26 November 2008 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20081026031307/http://www.chessgames.com/perl/chessplayer?pid=13277 |archivedate=26 October 2008 |df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It took a prodigy from Cuba, [[José Raúl Capablanca]] (World Champion 1921–1927), who loved simple positions and endgames, to end the German-speaking dominance in chess; he was undefeated in tournament play for eight years, until 1924. His successor was Russian-French [[Alexander Alekhine]], a strong attacking player who died as the world champion in 1946. He briefly lost the title to Dutch player [[Max Euwe]] in 1935 and regained it two years later.&lt;ref&gt;Kasparov (1983b), p. 9&lt;/ref&gt;

Between the world wars, chess was revolutionized by the new theoretical school of so-called [[Hypermodernism (chess)|hypermodernists]] like [[Aron Nimzowitsch]] and [[Richard Réti]]. They advocated controlling the {{chessgloss|center}} of the board with distant pieces rather than with pawns, thus inviting opponents to occupy the center with pawns, which become objects of attack.&lt;ref&gt;Hooper &amp; Whyld (1992), p. 178&lt;/ref&gt;

===1945–present: Post-World War II era===
&lt;!--[[File:Capablanca-Lasker 1925.jpg|thumb|left|World Champions [[José Raúl Capablanca]] (left) and [[Emanuel Lasker]] in 1925]]--&gt;
After the death of Alekhine, a new World Champion was sought. FIDE, which has controlled the title since then (except for one interruption), ran a tournament of elite players. The winner of the [[World Chess Championship 1948|1948 tournament]] was Russian [[Mikhail Botvinnik]].

In 1950 FIDE established a system of titles, conferring the titles of [[Grandmaster (chess)|Grandmaster]] and International Master on 27 players.  Some sources state that in 1914 the title of chess [[International Grandmaster|Grandmaster]] was first formally conferred by Tsar [[Nicholas II of Russia]] to Lasker, Capablanca, Alekhine, [[Siegbert Tarrasch|Tarrasch]], and [[Frank Marshall (chess player)|Marshall]], but this is a disputed claim.{{refn|This is stated in ''The Encyclopaedia of Chess'' (1970, p. 223) by [[Anne Sunnucks]], but is disputed by [[Edward Winter (chess historian)]] in his [http://www.chesshistory.com/winter/winter38.html Chess Notes 5144 and 5152].|group=note}}

Botvinnik started an era of [[Soviet Union|Soviet]] dominance in the chess world. Until the end of the Soviet Union, there was only one non-Soviet champion, American [[Bobby Fischer]] (champion 1972–1975).&lt;ref&gt;Kasparov (2003b), pp. 7–8&lt;/ref&gt; Botvinnik revolutionized [[Chess theory#Opening theory|opening theory]]. Previously Black strove for equality, to neutralize White's [[first-move advantage in chess|first-move advantage]]. As Black, Botvinnik strove for the initiative from the beginning.&lt;ref&gt;Kasparov (2003b), p. 7&lt;/ref&gt; In the previous informal system of World Championships, the current champion decided which challenger he would play for the title and the challenger was forced to seek sponsors for the match. FIDE set up a new system of qualifying tournaments and matches. The world's strongest players were seeded into [[Interzonal]] tournaments, where they were joined by players who had qualified from Zonal tournaments. The leading finishers in these Interzonals would go on the &quot;[[Candidates Tournament|Candidates]]&quot; stage, which was initially a tournament, and later a series of knockout matches. The winner of the Candidates would then play the reigning champion for the title. A champion defeated in a match had a right to play a rematch a year later. This system operated on a three-year cycle. Botvinnik participated in championship matches over a period of fifteen years. He won the world championship tournament in 1948 and retained the title in tied matches in 1951 and 1954. In 1957, he lost to [[Vasily Smyslov]], but regained the title in a rematch in 1958. In 1960, he lost the title to the 23-year-old Latvian prodigy [[Mikhail Tal]], an accomplished [[Chess tactics|tactician]] and attacking player. Botvinnik again regained the title in a rematch in 1961.

Following the 1961 event, FIDE abolished the automatic right of a deposed champion to a rematch, and the next champion, Armenian [[Tigran Petrosian]], a player renowned for his defensive and positional skills, held the title for two cycles, 1963–1969. His successor, [[Boris Spassky]] from Russia (champion 1969–1972), won games in both positional and sharp tactical style.&lt;ref&gt;Kasparov (2004a), pp. 5–6; Kasparov (2003b), p. 8&lt;/ref&gt; The next championship, the so-called [[World Chess Championship 1972|Match of the Century]], saw the first non-Soviet challenger since World War II, American [[Bobby Fischer]], who defeated his Candidates opponents by unheard-of margins and clearly won the world championship match. In 1975, however, Fischer refused to defend his title against Soviet [[Anatoly Karpov]] when FIDE did not meet his demands, and Karpov obtained the title by default.&lt;ref&gt;Kasparov (2004b), pp. 5–6&lt;/ref&gt; Fischer modernized many aspects of chess, especially by extensively preparing openings.&lt;ref&gt;Kasparov (2003a), p. 8&lt;/ref&gt;

Karpov defended his title twice against [[Viktor Korchnoi]] and dominated the 1970s and early 1980s with a string of tournament successes.&lt;ref&gt;Kasparov (2004b), pp. 5–6; Kasparov (2006), pp. 5–6&lt;/ref&gt; Karpov's reign finally ended in 1985 at the hands of [[Garry Kasparov]], another Soviet player from [[Baku]], [[Azerbaijan]]. Kasparov and Karpov contested five world title matches between 1984 and 1990; Karpov never won his title back.&lt;ref&gt;Keene (1993), p. 16&lt;/ref&gt; In 1993, Garry Kasparov and [[Nigel Short]] broke with FIDE to organize their own match for the title and formed a competing [[Professional Chess Association]] (PCA). From then until 2006, there were two simultaneous World Champions and World Championships: the PCA or Classical champion extending the Steinitzian tradition in which the current champion plays a challenger in a series of many games, and the other following FIDE's new format of many players competing in a tournament to determine the champion. Kasparov lost his Classical title in [[Classical World Chess Championship 2000|2000]] to [[Vladimir Kramnik]] of Russia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://archives.cnn.com/2000/WORLD/europe/11/02/chess.kramnik/index.html |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20060128031243/http://archives.cnn.com/2000/WORLD/europe/11/02/chess.kramnik/index.html |archivedate=28 January 2006 |title=Kramnik beats Kasparov, 2000 |accessdate=4 September 2010 |publisher=CNN |date=2 November 2000 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[World Chess Championship 2006]], in which Kramnik beat the FIDE World Champion [[Veselin Topalov]], reunified the titles and made Kramnik the undisputed World Chess Champion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.chessgames.com/perl/chessplayer?pid=12295 |title = Vladimir Kramnik |website = [[Chessgames.com]] |accessdate = 26 November 2008 |url-status=live |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20081222121703/http://www.chessgames.com/perl/chessplayer?pid=12295 |archivedate = 22 December 2008 |df = dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; In September 2007, he lost the title to [[Viswanathan Anand]] of India, who won the [[World Chess Championship 2007|championship tournament]] in [[Mexico City]]. Anand defended his title in the [[World Chess Championship 2008|revenge match of 2008]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title = Viswanathan Anand regains world chess title |date = 30 September 2007 |work = Reuters |url = http://in.reuters.com/article/sportsNews/idINIndia-29785520070930 |accessdate = 13 December 2007 |url-status=live |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20071226102028/http://in.reuters.com/article/sportsNews/idINIndia-29785520070930 |archivedate = 26 December 2007 |df = dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; 2010 and 2012. In 2013, [[Magnus Carlsen]] beat Anand in the [[World Chess Championship 2013|2013 World Chess Championship]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Doggers, Peter |url=http://www.chessvibes.com/breaking-magnus-carlsen-16th-undisputed-world-champion |title=Magnus Carlsen World Champion of Chess |publisher=ChessVibes |date=22 November 2013 |accessdate=13 January 2014 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140204071444/http://www.chessvibes.com/breaking-magnus-carlsen-16th-undisputed-world-champion |archivedate=4 February 2014 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; He defended his title [[World Chess Championship 2014|the following year]], again against Anand. Carlsen confirmed his title in 2016 against the Russian [[Sergey Karjakin]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = https://www.fide.com/component/content/article/1-fide-news/9901-fwccm2016.html|title = WCC 2016 Result Announcement by FIDE|date = 30 November 2016|access-date = 2 December 2018|archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20190105151204/http://www.fide.com/component/content/article/1-fide-news/9901-fwccm2016.html|archive-date = 5 January 2019|url-status = live}}&lt;/ref&gt; and in 2018 against the American [[Fabiano Caruana]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = https://fide.com/component/content/article/1-fide-news/11237-fide-wccm-game-11-one-game-may-decide-the-title-.html|title = WCC 2018 Result Announcement by FIDE|date = 29 November 2018|access-date = 2 December 2018|archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20181202070447/https://fide.com/component/content/article/1-fide-news/11237-fide-wccm-game-11-one-game-may-decide-the-title-.html|archive-date = 2 December 2018|url-status = live}}&lt;/ref&gt; in both occasions by a rapid tiebreaker match after equality in 12 games of classical [[time control]], and is the reigning world champion.

==Place in culture==
{{Main|Chess in the arts}}
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Meister der Manessischen Liederhandschrift 004.jpg|Noble chess players, Germany, {{circa|1320}}
File:UigChessmen SelectionOfKings.jpg|Two kings and two queens from the [[Lewis chessmen]] ([[British Museum]])
File:Qing Dynasty Chess pawns.jpg|19th-century decorative chess pawns, China ([[National Museum, Warsaw|National Museum]] in [[Warsaw]])
File:Large chess set.JPG|Large chess set in Franklin Square, Tasmania
File:Chess party with live figures, 1924.jpg|A chess party with live figures (in [[Bitola]], 1924)
&lt;/gallery&gt;

===Pre-modern===
In the [[Middle Ages]] and during the [[Renaissance]], chess was a part of [[nobility|noble]] culture; it was used to teach war strategy and was dubbed the &quot;[[Chess or the King's Game|King's Game]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Vale (2001), pp. 170–99&lt;/ref&gt; Gentlemen are &quot;to be meanly seene in the play at Chestes&quot;, says the overview at the beginning of [[Baldassare Castiglione]]'s ''[[The Book of the Courtier]]'' (1528, English 1561 by Sir Thomas Hoby), but chess should not be a gentleman's main passion. Castiglione explains it further:

&lt;blockquote&gt;And what say you to the game at chestes? It is truely&lt;!--sic--&gt; an honest kynde of enterteynmente and wittie, quoth Syr Friderick. But me think it hath a fault, whiche is, that a man may be to couning at it, for who ever will be excellent in the playe of chestes, I beleave he must beestowe much tyme about it, and applie it with so much study, that a man may assoone learne some noble scyence, or compase any other matter of importaunce, and yet in the ende in beestowing all that laboure, he knoweth no more but a game. Therfore in this I beleave there happeneth a very rare thing, namely, that the meane is more commendable, then the excellency.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|url=http://darkwing.uoregon.edu/~rbear/courtier/courtier2.html |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20000818234955/http://darkwing.uoregon.edu/~rbear/courtier/courtier2.html |url-status=dead |archivedate=18 August 2000 |title=The Second Book of the Courtier |author=Count Bladessar Castilio
|author2= Translated by Sir Thomas Hoby as edited by Walter Raleigh. Online at University of Oregon. Retrieved by Internet Archive, 2008-05-19
|publisher=David Nutt |location=London, 1900 |accessdate=7 May 2010 |year=1561}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Many of the elaborate chess sets used by the aristocracy have been lost, but others partially survive, such as the [[Lewis chessmen]].

Chess was often used as a basis of sermons on [[morality]]. An example is ''Liber de moribus hominum et officiis nobilium sive super ludo scacchorum'' ('Book of the customs of men and the duties of nobles or the Book of Chess'), written by an Italian [[Dominican Order|Dominican]] monk [[Jacobus de Cessolis]] {{circa|1300}}. This book was one of the most popular of the Middle Ages.&lt;ref&gt;Olmert (1996), p. 127&lt;/ref&gt; The work was translated into many other languages (the first printed edition was published at Utrecht in 1473) and was the basis for [[William Caxton]]'s ''The Game and Playe of the Chesse'' (1474), one of the first books printed in English.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bartleby.com/212/1303.html The Introduction of Printing into England and the Early Work of the Press: The First Book printed in English] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20061225125443/http://www.bartleby.com/212/1303.html |date=25 December 2006 }}, from ''[[The Cambridge History of English and American Literature]]'', Vol II. (1907) Online at bartleby.com. Retrieved 12 December 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; Different chess pieces were used as metaphors for different classes of people, and human duties were derived from the rules of the game or from visual properties of the chess pieces:&lt;ref&gt;Adams (2006)&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;The knyght ought to be made alle armed upon an hors in suche wyse that he haue an helme on his heed and a spere in his ryght hande/ and coueryd wyth his sheld/ a swerde and a mace on his lyft syde/ Cladd wyth an hawberk and plates to fore his breste/ legge harnoys on his legges/ Spores on his heelis on his handes his gauntelettes/ his hors well broken and taught and apte to bataylle and couerid with his armes/ whan the knyghtes ben maad they ben bayned or bathed/ that is the signe that they shold lede a newe lyf and newe maners/ also they wake alle the nyght in prayers and orysons vnto god that he wylle gyue hem grace that they may gete that thynge that they may not gete by nature/ The kynge or prynce gyrdeth a boute them a swerde in signe/ that they shold abyde and kepe hym of whom they take theyr dispenses and dignyte.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |author=Caxton, William |url=http://www.gutenberg.org/etext/10672 |title=The Game and Playe of the Chesse |publisher=Project Gutenberg |accessdate=20 May 2010 |date=January 2004 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090924213005/http://www.gutenberg.org/etext/10672 |archive-date=24 September 2009 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Known in the circles of clerics, students, and merchants, chess entered into the popular culture of Middle Ages. An example is the 209th song of [[Carmina Burana]] from the 13th&amp;nbsp;century, which starts with the names of chess pieces, ''Roch, pedites, regina...''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.fh-augsburg.de/~harsch/Chronologia/Lspost13/CarminaBurana/bur_cpo2.html |title=Carmina potoria |publisher=Bibliotheca Augustana |accessdate=26 November 2008 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071229151500/http://www.fh-augsburg.de/~harsch/Chronologia/Lspost13/CarminaBurana/bur_cpo2.html |archivedate=29 December 2007 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Modern===
During the [[Age of Enlightenment]], chess was viewed as a means of self-improvement. [[Benjamin Franklin]], in his article &quot;[[The Morals of Chess]]&quot; (1750), wrote:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
The Game of Chess is not merely an idle amusement; several very valuable qualities of the mind, useful in the course of human life, are to be acquired and strengthened by it, so as to become habits ready on all occasions; for life is a kind of Chess, in which we have often points to gain, and competitors or adversaries to contend with, and in which there is a vast variety of good and ill events, that are, in some degree, the effect of prudence, or the want of it. By playing at Chess then, we may learn:

'''I. Foresight''', which looks a little into futurity, and considers the consequences that may attend an action [...]

'''II. Circumspection''', which surveys the whole Chess-board, or scene of action: – the relation of the several Pieces, and their situations [...]

'''III. Caution''', not to make our moves too hastily [...]&lt;ref&gt;Franklin (1779)&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Chess was occasionally criticized in the 19th century as a waste of time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://medium.com/message/why-chess-will-destroy-your-mind-78ad1034521f |title=Why Chess Will Destroy Your Mind |first=Clive |last=Thompson |date=22 May 2014 |publisher= |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170901152810/https://medium.com/message/why-chess-will-destroy-your-mind-78ad1034521f|archivedate=1 September 2017|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.techdirt.com/articles/20140613/08020527566/that-time-when-people-thought-playing-chess-would-make-you-violent.shtml|title=That Time When People Thought Playing Chess Would Make You Violent |publisher= |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170324191000/https://www.techdirt.com/articles/20140613/08020527566/that-time-when-people-thought-playing-chess-would-make-you-violent.shtml |archivedate=24 March 2017 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Chess is taught to children in schools around the world today. Many schools host chess clubs, and there are many scholastic tournaments specifically for children. Tournaments are held regularly in many countries, hosted by organizations such as the [[United States Chess Federation]] and the National Scholastic Chess Foundation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nscfchess.org/nscfmiss.html |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20091230140133/http://www.nscfchess.org/nscfmiss.html |archivedate=30 December 2009 |title=National Scholastic Chess Foundation |accessdate=30 December 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Red King sleeping.jpg|thumb|right|''[[Through the Looking-Glass]]'': the Red King is snoring. Illustration by Sir [[John Tenniel]].]]
Chess is often depicted in [[Chess in the arts and literature|the arts]]; significant works where chess plays a key role range from Thomas Middleton's ''[[A Game at Chess]]'' to ''[[Through the Looking-Glass]]'' by Lewis Carroll, to Vladimir Nabokov's ''[[The Defense]]'', to ''[[The Royal Game]]'' by Stefan Zweig. Chess is featured in films like Ingmar Bergman's ''[[The Seventh Seal]]'' and Satyajit Ray's ''[[Shatranj Ke Khilari|The Chess Players]]''.

Chess is also present in contemporary popular culture. For example, the characters in ''[[Star Trek]]'' play a futuristic version of the game called &quot;[[Tri-Dimensional Chess]]&quot;. &quot;[[Wizard's Chess]]&quot; is featured in J.K. Rowling's ''[[Harry Potter]]'' plays. The hero of ''[[Searching for Bobby Fischer]]'' struggles against adopting the [[aggression|aggressive]] and [[misanthropic]] views of a world chess champion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=O'Neill, Eamonn |title=The Brain Issue |url=http://www.eamonnoneill.net/articles/Josh%20Waitzkins.PDF |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20060426004836/http://www.eamonnoneill.net/articles/Josh%20Waitzkins.PDF |url-status=dead |archive-date=26 April 2006 |accessdate=26 November 2008 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt; Chess is used as the core theme in the [[Musical theatre|musical]] ''[[Chess (musical)|Chess]]'' by [[Tim Rice]], [[Björn Ulvaeus]], and [[Benny Andersson]]. The [[Thriller(genre)|thriller]] film ''[[Knight Moves (film)|Knight Moves]]'' is about a chess grandmaster who is accused of being a [[serial killer]]. ''[[Pawn Sacrifice]]'', starring [[Tobey Maguire]] as [[Bobby Fischer]] and [[Liev Schreiber]] as [[Boris Spassky]], depicts the drama surrounding the [[1972 World Chess Championship]] in Iceland during the Cold War.&lt;ref name=&quot;deadlineill&quot;&gt;{{cite magazine |last=Pedersen |first=Erik |url=http://deadline.com/2015/02/ill-see-you-in-my-dreams-release-date-pawn-sacrifice-1201366262/ |title='I'll See You In My Dreams' and 'Pawn Sacrifice' Get Release Dates |magazine=Deadline |date=4 February 2015 |accessdate=30 May 2015 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150601205641/http://deadline.com/2015/02/ill-see-you-in-my-dreams-release-date-pawn-sacrifice-1201366262/ |archivedate=1 June 2015 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{clear left}}

===Prohibition in religion===
The game of chess, at times, has been discouraged by various religious authorities, including Jewish, Christian and Muslim. Jewish scholars [[Maimonides]] and [[Kalonymus ben Kalonymus]] both condemned chess, though the former only condemned it when played for money while the latter condemned it in all circumstances.&lt;ref&gt;Joseph Jacobs, A. Porter, &quot;[http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/articles/4314-chess CHESS],&quot; ''[[The Jewish Encyclopedia]]''&lt;/ref&gt; In medieval times both the [[Catholic]] and [[Orthodox church]]es condemned chess.&lt;ref&gt;Francesco Galofaro, &quot;[https://www.academia.edu/641259/Chess_and_variations_of Chess and Variations of],&quot; ''[[Encyclopedia of Play]]'', [[Sage Publications|Sage Publications Inc.]], Thousand Oaks, CA, USA.&lt;/ref&gt; Though the 16th century [[Russian Orthodox]] ''[[Domostroy]]'' condemned the game, chess nevertheless remained popular in Russia.&lt;ref&gt;Murray, H. J. R. ''A History of Chess'', Skyhorse. p. 141&lt;/ref&gt; In 1979, Iranian Ayatollah [[Ruhollah Khomeini]] [[fatwa|ruled]] against chess,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/jan/21/chess-forbidden-in-islam-rules-saudi-arabia-grand-mufti |title=Harry Potter and Terror's Networks |work=CounterPunch |date=24 November 2011 |accessdate=1 April 2019 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160213200335/http://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/jan/21/chess-forbidden-in-islam-rules-saudi-arabia-grand-mufti |archive-date=13 February 2016 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt; but later allowed it as long as it did not involve gambling. Iran now has an [[Iranian Chess Championship|active confederation for playing chess]] and sends players to international events.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.sistani.org/english/qa/01161/ |title=Chess forbidden in Islam, rules Saudi mufti, but issue not black and white |work=The Guardian |date=21 January 2016 |accessdate=1 April 2019 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190402001136/https://www.sistani.org/english/qa/01161/ |archive-date=2 April 2019 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt; Saudi [[Grand Mufti of Saudi Arabia|Mufti]] [[Abdul-Aziz ibn Abdullah Al ash-Sheikh|Abdul-Aziz ash-Sheikh]] similarly ruled against chess, arguing that it constituted [[gambling]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/jan/21/chess-forbidden-in-islam-rules-saudi-arabia-grand-mufti |title=Chess forbidden in Islam |work=[[The Guardian]] |date=21 January 2016 |accessdate=11 February 2016 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160213200335/http://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/jan/21/chess-forbidden-in-islam-rules-saudi-arabia-grand-mufti |archivedate=13 February 2016 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Iraqi Ayatollah [[Ali al-Sistani]] said chess was forbidden &quot;even without placing a bet”.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/jan/21/chess-forbidden-in-islam-rules-saudi-arabia-grand-mufti |title=Question &amp; Answer; Chess &amp; Backgammon |work=Sistani.org |accessdate=1 April 2019 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160213200335/http://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/jan/21/chess-forbidden-in-islam-rules-saudi-arabia-grand-mufti |archive-date=13 February 2016 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notation for recording moves==
{{Main|Chess notation}}
[[File:SCD algebraic notation.svg|frame|right|Square names in [[Algebraic notation (chess)|algebraic chess notation]]]]

Chess games and positions are recorded using a system of notation, most commonly [[Algebraic notation (chess)|algebraic chess notation]].&lt;ref&gt;See paragraph &quot;E. Algebraic notation&quot; in {{cite web |url=http://www.fide.com/component/handbook/?id=125&amp;view=article |title=E.I.01B. Appendices |accessdate=26 November 2008 |publisher=FIDE |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20081211031306/http://www.fide.com/component/handbook/?view=article&amp;id=125 |archivedate=11 December 2008 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Abbreviated algebraic (or short algebraic) notation generally records moves in the format:
:''abbreviation of the piece moved'' – ''file where it moved'' – ''rank where it moved''
The pieces are identified by their initials. In English, these are ''K'' (king), ''Q'' (queen), ''R'' (rook), ''B'' (bishop), and ''N'' (knight; N is used to avoid confusion with king). For example, '''Qg5''' means &quot;queen moves to the g-file, 5th rank&quot; (that is, to the square g5). Chess literature published in other languages may use different initials for pieces, or [[Algebraic notation (chess)#Figurine algebraic notation|figurine algebraic notation (FAN)]] may be used to avoid language issues. To resolve ambiguities, an additional letter or number is added to indicate the file or rank from which the piece moved (e.g. '''Ngf3''' means &quot;knight from the g-file moves to the square f3&quot;; '''R1e2''' means &quot;rook on the first rank moves to e2&quot;). The letter ''P'' for pawn is not used; so '''e4''' means &quot;pawn moves to the square e4&quot;.

If the piece makes a capture, &quot;x&quot; is inserted before the destination square. Thus '''Bxf3''' means &quot;bishop captures on f3&quot;. When a pawn makes a capture, the file from which the pawn departed is used in place of a piece initial, and ranks may be omitted if unambiguous. For example, '''exd5''' (pawn on the e-file captures the piece on d5) or '''exd''' (pawn on the e-file captures a piece somewhere on the d-file). Particularly in Germany, some publications use &quot;:&quot; rather than &quot;x&quot; to indicate capture, but this is now rare. Some publications omit the capture symbol altogether; so exd5 would be rendered simply as '''ed'''.

If a pawn moves to its last rank, achieving promotion, the piece chosen is indicated after the move (for example, '''e1Q''' or '''e1=Q'''). Castling is indicated by the special notations '''0-0''' for {{chessgloss|kingside}} castling and '''0-0-0''' for {{chessgloss|queenside}} castling. An ''en passant'' capture is sometimes marked with the notation &quot;e.p.&quot; A move that places the opponent's king in check usually has the notation &quot;+&quot; added (the notation &quot;++&quot; for a [[double check]] is considered obsolete). Checkmate can be indicated by &quot;#&quot;. At the end of the game, &quot;1–0&quot; means White won, &quot;0–1&quot; means Black won, and &quot;½–½&quot; indicates a draw.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.fide.com/fide/handbook.html?id=125&amp;view=article |title=FIDE Laws of Chess |accessdate=4 September 2010 |publisher=FIDE |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20101205225438/http://www.fide.com/fide/handbook.html?id=125&amp;view=article |archivedate=5 December 2010 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Chess moves can be annotated with [[punctuation (chess)|punctuation marks and other symbols]]. (For example: &quot;!&quot; indicates a good move; &quot;!!&quot; an excellent move; &quot;?&quot; a mistake; &quot;??&quot; a blunder; &quot;!?&quot; an interesting move that may not be best; or &quot;?!&quot; a dubious move not easily refuted.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hooper &amp; Whyld 1992, p. 92&quot;&gt;Hooper &amp; Whyld (1992), p. 92&lt;/ref&gt;)

[[File:Scholars mate animation.gif|frame|left|&quot;[[Scholar's mate]]&quot;]]
For example, one variation of a simple trap known as the [[Scholar's mate]] (see animated diagram) can be recorded:
:{{pad}}'''1. e4 e5 2. Qh5{{chesspunc|?!}} Nc6 3. Bc4 Nf6{{chesspunc|??}} 4. Qxf7{{chessAN|#}}'''

The text-based [[Portable Game Notation]] (PGN), which is understood by chess software, is based on short form English language algebraic notation.

Until about 1980, the majority of English language chess publications used a form of [[descriptive notation]]. In descriptive notation, files are named according to the piece which occupies the back rank at the start of the game, and each square has two different names depending on whether it is from White's or Black's point of view. For example, the square known as &quot;e3&quot; in algebraic notation is &quot;K3&quot; (King's 3rd) from White's point of view, and &quot;K6&quot; (King's 6th) from Black's point of view. When recording captures, the captured piece is named rather than the square on which it is captured (except to resolve ambiguities). Thus, Scholar's mate is rendered in descriptive notation:
:{{pad}}'''1. P-K4 P-K4 2. Q-R5?! N-QB3 3. B-B4 N-B3?? 4. QxBP [[Checkmate|mate]]'''

A few players still prefer descriptive notation, but it is no longer recognized by FIDE.

Another system is [[ICCF numeric notation]], recognized by the [[International Correspondence Chess Federation]] though its use is in decline. Squares are identified by numeric coordinates, for example a1 is &quot;11&quot; and h8 is &quot;88&quot;. Moves are described by the &quot;from&quot; and &quot;to&quot; squares, e.g. the opening move 1.e4 is rendered as 1.5254. Captures are not indicated. Castling is described by the king's move only; e.g. 5171 for White castling kingside, 5838 for Black castling queenside.

==Stages==
A game of chess can generally be loosely subdivided into three phases or stages of play: the ''opening'', followed by the ''middlegame'', then last the ''endgame''.

===Opening===
{{Main|Chess opening}}
A chess opening is the group of initial moves of a game (the &quot;opening moves&quot;). Recognized sequences of opening moves are referred to as ''openings'' and have been given names such as the [[Ruy Lopez]] or [[Sicilian Defense]]. They are catalogued in reference works such as the ''[[Encyclopaedia of Chess Openings]]''. There are dozens of different openings, varying widely in character from quiet {{chessgloss|positional play}} (for example, the [[Réti Opening]]) to very aggressive (the [[Latvian Gambit]]). In some opening lines, the exact sequence considered best for both sides has been worked out to more than 30 moves.&lt;ref&gt;Tamburro (2010), p. 18&lt;/ref&gt; Professional players spend years studying openings and continue doing so throughout their careers, as [[Chess opening theory|opening theory]] continues to evolve.

The fundamental strategic aims of most openings are similar:&lt;ref&gt;Tarrasch (1987)&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''development:'' This is the technique of placing the pieces (particularly bishops and knights) on useful squares where they will have an optimal impact on the game.
* ''control of the {{chessgloss|center}}:'' Control of the central squares allows pieces to be moved to any part of the board relatively easily, and can also have a cramping effect on the opponent.
* ''king safety:'' It is critical to keep the king safe from dangerous possibilities. A correctly timed castling can often enhance this.
* ''[[pawn structure]]:'' Players strive to avoid the creation of pawn weaknesses such as isolated, doubled, or backward pawns, and pawn islands&amp;nbsp;– and to force such weaknesses in the opponent's position.

Most players and [[Chess theory|theoreticians]] consider that White, by virtue of the first move, [[First-move advantage in chess|begins the game with a small advantage]]. This initially gives White the [[Initiative (chess)|initiative]].&lt;ref&gt;Evans (1958), p. 175&lt;/ref&gt; Black usually strives to neutralize White's advantage and achieve {{chessgloss|equality}}, or to develop {{chessgloss|dynamism|dynamic}} {{chessgloss|counterplay}} in an unbalanced position.

===Middlegame===
{{Main|Chess middlegame}}
The middlegame is the part of the game which starts after the opening. There is no clear line between the opening and the middlegame, but typically the middlegame will start when most pieces have been developed. (Similarly, there is no clear transition from the middlegame to the endgame; see [[Chess endgame#The start of the endgame|start of the endgame]].) Because the opening theory has ended, players have to form plans based on the features of the position, and at the same time take into account the tactical possibilities of the position.&lt;ref&gt;Harding (2003), pp. 32–151&lt;/ref&gt; The middlegame is the phase in which most [[Combination (chess)|combinations]] occur. Combinations are a series of tactical moves executed to achieve some gain. Middlegame combinations are often connected with an attack against the opponent's king. Some typical patterns have their own names; for example, the [[Boden's Mate]] or the [[Lasker - Bauer, Amsterdam, 1889|Lasker–Bauer]] combination.&lt;ref&gt;Hooper &amp; Whyld (1992), p. 86&lt;/ref&gt;

Specific plans or strategic themes will often arise from particular groups of openings which result in a specific type of pawn structure. An example is the {{chessgloss|minority attack}}, which is the attack of queenside pawns against an opponent who has more pawns on the queenside. The study of openings is therefore connected to the preparation of plans that are typical of the resulting middlegames.&lt;ref&gt;Silman (1998), pp. 202–05&lt;/ref&gt;

Another important strategic question in the middlegame is whether and how to reduce material and transition into an endgame (i.e. {{chessgloss|simplification|simplify}}). Minor material advantages can generally be transformed into victory only in an endgame, and therefore the stronger side must choose an appropriate way to achieve an ending. Not every reduction of material is good for this purpose; for example, if one side keeps a light-squared bishop and the opponent has a dark-squared one, the transformation into a [[Chess endgame#Bishop and pawn endings|bishops and pawns]] ending is usually advantageous for the weaker side only, because an endgame with [[opposite-colored bishops endgame|bishops on opposite colors]] is likely to be a draw, even with an advantage of a pawn, or sometimes even with a two-pawn advantage.&lt;ref&gt;Hooper &amp; Whyld (1992), p. 373&lt;/ref&gt;

===Endgame===
{{Main|Chess endgame}}
{{Chess diagram
|tright
|Example of [[zugzwang]]
|  |  |kd|  |  |  |  | 
|  |  |pl|  |  |  |  | 
|  |  |  |kl|  |  |  | 
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  | 
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  | 
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  | 
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  | 
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  | 
|The side having to move is disadvantaged.
}}
The endgame (also ''end game'' or ''ending'') is the stage of the game when there are few pieces left on the board. There are three main strategic differences between earlier stages of the game and the endgame:&lt;ref&gt;Harding (2003), pp. 187ff&lt;/ref&gt;
# Pawns become more important. Endgames often revolve around endeavors to [[Promotion (chess)|promote]] a pawn by advancing it to the furthest {{chessgloss|rank}}.
# The king, which requires safeguarding from attack during the middlegame, emerges as a strong piece in the endgame. It is often brought to the {{chessgloss|center}} where it can protect its own pawns, attack enemy pawns, and hinder moves of the opponent's king.
# [[Zugzwang]], a situation in which the player who is to move is forced to incur a disadvantage, is often a factor in endgames but rarely in other stages of the game. In the example diagram, either side having the move is in zugzwang: Black to move must play 1...Kb7 allowing White to promote the pawn after 2.Kd7; White to move must permit a draw, either by 1.Kc6 [[stalemate]] or by losing the pawn after any other legal move.

Endgames can be classified according to the type of pieces remaining on the board. [[Checkmate#Basic checkmates|Basic checkmates]] are positions in which one side has only a king and the other side has one or two pieces and can checkmate the opposing king, with the pieces working together with their king. For example, [[king and pawn endgame]]s involve only kings and pawns on one or both sides, and the task of the stronger side is to promote one of the pawns. Other more complicated endings are classified according to pieces on the board other than kings, such as &quot;[[rook and pawn versus rook]]&quot; endgames.
{{clear}}

==Strategy and tactics==
Chess strategy consists of setting and achieving long-term positioning advantages during the game&amp;nbsp;– for example, where to place different pieces&amp;nbsp;– while tactics concentrate on immediate maneuver. These two aspects of the gameplay cannot be completely separated, because strategic goals are mostly achieved through tactics, while the tactical opportunities are based on the previous strategy of play. A game of chess is normally divided into three phases: the [[#Opening|opening]], typically the first 10 moves, when players move their pieces to useful positions for the coming battle; the [[#Middlegame|middlegame]]; and last the [[#Endgame|endgame]], when most of the pieces are gone, kings typically take a more active part in the struggle, and pawn promotion is often decisive.

===Fundamentals of tactics===
{{Main|Chess tactics}}
{{Chess diagram
|tright
|Botvinnik vs. Yudovich, 1933&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.chessgames.com/perl/chessgame?gid=1031833 |title=Botvinnik vs. Yudovich, USSR Championship 1933 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090110164157/http://www.chessgames.com/perl/chessgame?gid=1031833 |website=[[Chessgames.com]] |archivedate=10 January 2009 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|rd|  |bd|  |  |rd|  |
|  |pd|  |nd|qd|  |bd|
|  |nd|pd|  |pd|  |kd|pd
|pd|  |  |  |  |  |  |
|  |  |  |pl|nl|  |  |
|  |pl|  |  |bl|  |  |
|  |  |ql|  |bl|pl|pl|pl
|  |  |rl|rl|  |  |kl|
|{{Hidden|multiline=y|ta1=left|fw1=normal|After [[Sacrifice (chess)|sacrificing]] a piece to expose Black's king, [[Mikhail Botvinnik|Botvinnik]] played 23.Bh5+ and [[Mikhail Yudovich|Yudovich]] [[Rules of chess#Resigning|resigned]], as mate is inevitable.|23.Bh5+ and now:
* 23...Kxh5 24.Ng3+ Kh4 25.Qe4+ Rf4 26.Qxf4{{chessAN|#}}
* 23...Kf5 24.g4#
* 23...Kh7 24.Nf6+ ([[double check]]) Kh8 25.Qh7#}}
}}
In chess, tactics in general concentrate on short-term actions&amp;nbsp;– so short-term that they can be calculated in advance by a human player or a computer. The possible depth of calculation depends on the player's ability. In {{chessgloss|quiet move|quiet}} positions with many possibilities on both sides, a deep calculation is more difficult and may not be practical, while in positions with a limited number of {{chessgloss|forced move|forced}} variations, strong players can calculate long sequences of moves.

Theoreticians describe many elementary tactical methods and typical maneuvers, for example: [[Pin (chess)|pins]], [[Fork (chess)|forks]], [[Skewer (chess)|skewers]], [[Battery (chess)|batteries]], [[discovered attack]]s (especially discovered checks), [[zwischenzug]]s, [[Deflection (chess)|deflections]], [[Decoy (chess)|decoys]], [[Sacrifice (chess)|sacrifices]], [[Undermining (chess)|underminings]], [[Overloading (chess)|overloadings]], and [[Interference (chess)|interferences]].&lt;ref&gt;Harding (2003), pp. 8ff&lt;/ref&gt; Simple one-move or two-move tactical actions&amp;nbsp;– threats, exchanges of {{chessgloss|material}}, and double attacks&amp;nbsp;– can be combined into more complicated sequences of tactical maneuvers that are often forced from the point of view of one or both players.&lt;ref name=&quot;Harding 2003, p. 70ff&quot;&gt;Harding (2003), pp. 70ff&lt;/ref&gt; A forced variation that involves a sacrifice and usually results in a tangible gain is called a ''[[Combination (chess)|combination]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Harding 2003, p. 70ff&quot;/&gt; Brilliant combinations&amp;nbsp;– such as those in the [[Immortal Game]]&amp;nbsp;– are considered beautiful and are admired by chess lovers. A common type of chess exercise, aimed at developing players' skills, is a position where a decisive combination is available and the challenge is to find it.&lt;ref&gt;Burgess, Nunn, &amp; Emms (2004), pp. 14–15&lt;/ref&gt;

===Fundamentals of strategy===
{{Main|Chess strategy}}
Chess strategy is concerned with evaluation of chess positions and with setting up goals and long-term plans for the future play. During the evaluation, players must take into account numerous factors such as the value of the pieces on the board, control of the center and centralization, the [[pawn structure]], king safety, and the control of key squares or groups of squares (for example, diagonals, open files, and dark or light squares).

The most basic step in evaluating a position is to count the [[Chess piece relative value|total value of pieces]] of both sides.&lt;ref&gt;Harding (2003), pp. 1–7&lt;/ref&gt; The point values used for this purpose are based on experience; usually pawns are considered worth one point, knights and bishops about three points each, rooks about five points (the value difference between a rook and a bishop or knight being known as [[The exchange (chess)|the exchange]]), and queens about nine points. The king is more valuable than all of the other pieces combined, since its checkmate loses the game. But in practical terms, in the endgame the king as a fighting piece is generally more powerful than a bishop or knight but less powerful than a rook.&lt;ref&gt;Lasker (1934), p. 73&lt;/ref&gt; These basic values are then modified by other factors like position of the piece (e.g. advanced pawns are usually more valuable than those on their initial squares), coordination between pieces (e.g. a pair of bishops usually coordinate better than a bishop and a knight), or the type of position (e.g. knights are generally better in {{chessgloss|closed game|closed positions}} with many pawns while bishops are more powerful in {{chessgloss|open game|open positions}}).&lt;ref&gt;Watson (1998), p. 163ff&lt;/ref&gt;

{| style=&quot;float:right;&quot;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|+ Example of underlying pawn structure
|
{{Chess diagram small
| tright
|
|rd|  |bd|  |rd|  |kd|
|pd|pd|  |nd|  |pd|bd|pd
|  |  |pd|rl|  |nd|pd|
|  |  |  |  |pd|  |  |
|  |  |pl|  |pl|  |  |
|  |  |nl|  |bl|nl|  |pl
|pl|pl|  |  |  |pl|pl|
|  |  |kl|  |  |bl|  |rl
| After 12...Re8 in Tarrasch–Euwe...&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.chessgames.com/perl/chessgame?gid=1006866 |title=Siegbert Tarrasch vs. Max Euwe, Bad Pistyan it, CZE 1922 |website=[[Chessgames.com]] |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090110122502/http://www.chessgames.com/perl/chessgame?gid=1006866 |archivedate=10 January 2009 |df=dmy-all }} (Java needed)&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
|
{{Chess diagram small
| tright
|
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  |
|pd|pd|  |  |  |pd|  |pd
|  |  |pd|  |  |  |pd|
|  |  |  |  |pd|  |  |
|  |  |pl|  |pl|  |  |
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  |pl
|pl|pl|  |  |  |pl|pl|
|  |  |  |  |  |   | |
| ...and its pawn &quot;Rauzer formation&quot;
}}
|}
Another important factor in the evaluation of chess positions is the ''pawn structure'' (sometimes known as the ''pawn skeleton''): the configuration of pawns on the chessboard.&lt;ref&gt;Harding (2003), pp. 138ff&lt;/ref&gt; Since pawns are the least mobile of the pieces, the pawn structure is relatively static and largely determines the strategic nature of the position. Weaknesses in the pawn structure, such as [[Isolated pawn|isolated]], [[Doubled pawns|doubled]], or [[backward pawn]]s and {{chessgloss|holes}}, once created, are often permanent. Care must therefore be taken to avoid these weaknesses unless they are compensated by another valuable asset (for example, by the possibility of developing an attack).&lt;ref&gt;Evans (1958), pp. 22–67&lt;/ref&gt;
{{clear left}}

==Competitive play==

===Organization of competitions===
Contemporary chess is an organized sport with structured international and national leagues, tournaments, and [[congress]]es. Chess's international governing body is [[FIDE]] (Fédération Internationale des Échecs). Most countries have a national chess organization as well (such as the [[US Chess Federation]] and [[English Chess Federation]]) which in turn is a member of FIDE. FIDE is a member of the [[International Olympic Committee]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.olympic.org/uk/organisation/if/fi_uk.asp?Id_federation=44 |title=World Chess Federation |publisher=International Olympic Committee |accessdate=26 November 2008 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080822115514/http://www.olympic.org/uk/organisation/if/fi_uk.asp?Id_federation=44 |archivedate=22 August 2008 |url-status=dead |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt; but the game of chess has never been part of the [[Olympic Games]]; chess has its own [[Chess Olympiad|Olympiad]], held every two years as a team event.

[[File:SchachWM2008.jpg|thumb|left|upright=1.1|Former world champion [[Viswanathan Anand]] (''left'') playing against his predecessor [[Vladimir Kramnik]]]]
The current World Chess Champion is [[Magnus Carlsen]] of Norway.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url = https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-25057654 |title = Norwegian prodigy Magnus Carlsen is new chess champion |publisher = BBC |accessdate = 22 November 2013 |date = 22 November 2013 |url-status=live |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20131123173345/http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-25057654 |archivedate = 23 November 2013 |df = dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; The reigning Women's World Champion is [[Ju Wenjun]] from China.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://en.chessbase.com/post/womens-world-championship-2020-ju-goryachkina-game-12 |title=Women's World Championship 2020 - Ju wins tiebreak |website=chessbase.com |date=24 January 2020 |accessdate=26 February 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other competitions for individuals include the [[World Junior Chess Championship]], the [[European Individual Chess Championship]], and the [[List of national chess championships|National Chess Championships]]. Invitation-only tournaments regularly attract the world's strongest players. Examples include Spain's [[Linares chess tournament|Linares]] event, Monte Carlo's [[Melody Amber]] tournament, the [[Dortmund Sparkassen Chess Meeting|Dortmund Sparkassen]] meeting, Sofia's [[M-tel Masters]], and Wijk aan Zee's [[Tata Steel Chess Tournament|Tata Steel]] tournament.

Regular team chess events include the [[Chess Olympiad]] and the [[European Team Chess Championship]]. The [[World Chess Solving Championship]] and World [[Correspondence Chess]] Championships include both team and individual events.

Besides these prestigious competitions, there are thousands of other chess tournaments, matches, and festivals held around the world every year catering to players of all levels. Chess is promoted as a &quot;mind sport&quot; by the [[Mind Sports Organisation]], alongside other [[mental-skill game]]s such as [[contract bridge]], [[Go (board game)|Go]], and ''[[Scrabble]]''.

===Titles and rankings===
{{Main|Chess titles}}
[[File:Kasparov-29.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Grandmaster (chess)|GM]] [[Garry Kasparov]], former [[World Chess Championship|World Chess Champion]], is considered by many to be one of the [[Comparison of top chess players throughout history|greatest chess players of all time]].]]
The best players can be awarded specific lifetime titles by the world chess organization FIDE:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.fide.com/component/handbook/?id=10&amp;view=category |publisher = FIDE |title = 01. International Title Regulations (Qualification Commission) |accessdate = 26 November 2008 |url-status=live |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20081220213328/http://www.fide.com/component/handbook/?id=10&amp;view=category |archivedate = 20 December 2008 |df = dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Grandmaster (chess)|Grandmaster]] (shortened as GM; sometimes ''International Grandmaster'' or IGM is used) is awarded to world-class chess masters. Apart from World Champion, Grandmaster is the highest title a chess player can attain. Before FIDE will confer the title on a player, the player must have an [[Elo rating system|Elo chess rating]] (see below) of at least 2500 at one time and three favorable results (called norms) in tournaments involving other grandmasters, including some from countries other than the applicant's. There are other milestones a player can achieve to attain the title, such as winning the World Junior Championship.
* [[International Master]] (shortened as IM). The conditions are similar to GM, but less demanding. The minimum rating for the IM title is 2400.
* [[FIDE Master]] (shortened as FM). The usual way for a player to qualify for the FIDE Master title is by achieving a FIDE rating of 2300 or more.
* [[Candidate Master]] (shortened as CM). Similar to FM, but with a FIDE rating of at least 2200.

All the titles are open to men and women. Separate women-only titles, such as Woman Grandmaster (WGM), are available. Beginning with [[Nona Gaprindashvili]] in 1978, a number of women have earned the GM title, and as of 2020, all of the top ten rated women hold the unrestricted GM title.&lt;ref group=note name=&quot;FIDE_top_players&quot;&gt;Current FIDE lists of top players with their titles are online at {{cite web |url = https://ratings.fide.com |accessdate = 18 February 2020 |publisher = FIDE |title = Top Chess players |url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{as of|2018}}, there are 1725 active grandmasters and 3903 international masters in the world. The top three countries with the largest numbers of grandmasters are Russia, the United States, and Germany, with 251, 98, and 96, respectively.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://ratings.fide.com/topfed.phtml |title=Federations Ranking |access-date=2018-11-30 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171227004927/http://ratings.fide.com/topfed.phtml |archive-date=27 December 2017 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;

FIDE also awards titles for arbiters and trainers.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.fide.com/fide/handbook.html?id=41&amp;view=category|title=06. Regulations for the Titles of Arbiters|last=|first=|date=|website=FIDE|archive-url=https://archive.today/20190818184357/https://www.fide.com/fide/handbook.html?id=41&amp;view=category|archive-date=18 August 2019|url-status=live|access-date=18 Aug 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.fide.com/fide/handbook.html?id=42&amp;view=category|title=07. Regulations for the Titles of Trainers|last=|first=|date=|website=FIDE|archive-url=https://archive.today/20190817202604/https://www.fide.com/fide/handbook.html?id=42&amp;view=category|archive-date=17 August 2019|url-status=live|access-date=17 Aug 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

International titles are awarded to composers and solvers of chess problems and to correspondence chess players (by the [[International Correspondence Chess Federation]]). National chess organizations may also award titles, usually to the advanced players still under the level needed for international titles; an example is the [[chess expert]] title used in the United States.

In order to rank players, FIDE, [[International Correspondence Chess Federation|ICCF]], and national chess organizations use the [[Elo rating system]] developed by [[Arpad Elo]]. Elo is a [[Statistical model|statistical system]] based on the assumption that the chess performance of each player in his or her games is a random variable. Arpad Elo thought of a player's true skill as the average of that player's performance random variable, and showed how to estimate the average from results of player's games. The [[US Chess Federation]] implemented Elo's suggestions in 1960, and the system quickly gained recognition as being both fairer and more accurate than older systems; it was adopted by FIDE in 1970.{{refn|For the official process see {{cite web |title=FIDE Rating Regulations effective from 1 July 2017 |url=https://handbook.fide.com/chapter/B022017 |website=FIDE |accessdate=26 February 2020}}|group=note}} A beginner or casual player typically has an Elo rating of less than 1000; an ordinary club player has a rating of about 1500, a strong club player about 2000, a grandmaster usually has a rating of over 2500, and an elite player has a rating of over 2700. The highest FIDE rating of all time, 2881, was achieved by [[Magnus Carlsen]] on the March 2014 FIDE rating list.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Carlsen with record-breaking lead |url=http://chessbase.com/newsdetail.asp?newsid=8744 |publisher=ChessBase News |date=1 January 2013 |accessdate=16 January 2013 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130122115753/http://chessbase.com/newsdetail.asp?newsid=8744 |archivedate=22 January 2013 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Composition==
{{Main|Chess problem}}
Chess composition is the art of creating chess problems (also called chess compositions). The creator is known as a [[chess composer]].&lt;ref&gt;Howard (1961)&lt;/ref&gt; There are many types of chess problems; the two most important are:
* ''{{chessprobgloss|directmate|Directmates}}'': White to move first and checkmate Black within a specified number of moves, against any defense. These are often referred to as &quot;mate in ''n''&quot;&amp;nbsp;– for example &quot;mate in three&quot; (a ''three-mover''); two- and three-move problems are the most common. These usually involve positions that would be highly unlikely to occur in an actual game, and are intended to illustrate a particular ''{{chessprobgloss|theme}}'', usually requiring a surprising or counter-intuitive ''{{chessprobgloss|key}}'' move.&lt;ref&gt;Hooper &amp; Whyld (1992), p. 110&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''[[Endgame study|Studies]]'': orthodox problems where the stipulation is that White to play must win or draw. Almost all studies are [[Chess endgame|endgame]] positions.&lt;ref&gt;Hooper &amp; Whyld (1992), pp. 400–01&lt;/ref&gt;

Chess composition is a distinct branch of chess sport, and tournaments exist for both the composition and solving of chess problems.&lt;ref&gt;Weenink (1926)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Example===
{{Main|Réti endgame study}}
{{Chess diagram
|tright
|Richard Réti &lt;br /&gt;''[[Ostrava|Ostrauer]] Morgenzeitung'', 1921
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  |kl
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  |
|kd|  |pl|  |  |  |  |
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  |pd
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  |
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  |
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  |
|  |  |  |  |  |  |  |
|White to move and draw
}}
This is one of the most famous chess studies; it was published by [[Richard Réti]] 4 December 1921. It seems impossible to catch the advanced black pawn, while the black king can easily stop the white pawn. The solution is a [[diagonal]] advance, which brings the king to ''both'' pawns simultaneously:
:'''1. Kg7{{chesspunc|!}} h4 2. Kf6! Kb6'''
Or 2...h3 3.Ke7 and the white king can support its pawn.
:'''3. Ke5{{chesspunc|!!}}'''
Now the white king comes just in time to support his pawn, or catch the black one.
:'''3... h3'''
If 3...Kxc6, 4.Kf4 and White will capture the pawn.
:'''4. Kd6 {{chessAN|½–½}}'''
Both sides will queen, resulting in a draw.&lt;ref&gt;de la Villa (2008), pp. 179–80&lt;/ref&gt;

==Publications==
{{main|Chess libraries|List of chess books|List of chess periodicals}}
Chess has an extensive literature. In 1913, the chess historian [[H.J.R. Murray]] estimated the total number of books, magazines, and [[chess columns in newspapers]] to be about 5,000.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Murray |first=H.J.R. |author-link=H. J. R. Murray |year=1913 |title=A History of Chess |publisher=Oxford University Press |pages=782–84 |isbn=978-0-19-827403-2 |title-link=A History of Chess }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hooper&amp;Whyld&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |last1=Hooper |first1=David |authorlink1=David Hooper (chess player) |last2=Whyld |first2=Kenneth |authorlink2=Ken Whyld |title=The Oxford Companion to Chess |publisher=Oxford University Press |year=1984 |page=189 |isbn=978-0-19-217540-3|title-link=The Oxford Companion to Chess }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Baruch Harold Wood|B.H. Wood]] estimated the number, as of 1949, to be about 20,000.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hooper&amp;Whyld&quot;/&gt; [[David Hooper (chess player)|David Hooper]] and [[Kenneth Whyld]] write that, &quot;Since then there has been a steady increase year by year of the number of new chess publications. No one knows how many have been printed.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hooper&amp;Whyld&quot;/&gt; There are two significant public chess libraries: the John G. White Chess and Checkers Collection at [[Cleveland Public Library]], with over 32,000 chess books and over 6,000 bound volumes of chess periodicals;&lt;ref name=&quot;PolgarRecords&quot;&gt;[[Susan Polgar]], [http://susanpolgar.blogspot.com/2008/02/chess-records.html Special Chess Records] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120210151833/http://susanpolgar.blogspot.com/2008/02/chess-records.html |date=10 February 2012 }} (11 February 2008). Retrieved on 11 January 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; and the Chess &amp; Draughts collection at the [[National Library of the Netherlands]], with about 30,000 books.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.kb.nl/en/resources-research-guides/kb-collections/collections-by-theme/chess-and-draughts-collection |title=Chess and draughts collection – Koninklijke Bibliotheek |work=kb.nl |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150602095256/http://www.kb.nl/en/resources-research-guides/kb-collections/collections-by-theme/chess-and-draughts-collection |archivedate=2 June 2015 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; GM [[Lothar Schmid]] owned the world's largest private collection of chess books and memorabilia.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;A collector of chess books and paraphernalia, he has the largest private chess library in the world.&quot; [[David Hooper (chess player)|David Hooper]] and [[Kenneth Whyld]], ''[[The Oxford Companion to Chess]]'' (2nd ed. 1992), p. 358. {{ISBN|0-19-866164-9}}. &quot;Schmid owns the largest private collection of chess books and other chess material.&quot; [[Harry Golombek]], ''Golombek's Chess Encyclopedia'', Crown Publishers, 1977, p. 290. {{ISBN|0-517-53146-1}}. In 1992, [[David Hooper (chess player)|Hooper]] and [[Kenneth Whyld|Whyld]] stated that Schmid's chess library &quot;is the largest and finest in private hands, with more than 15,000 items&quot;. Hooper &amp; Whyld, p. 226 (&quot;libraries&quot; entry). In 2008, [[Susan Polgar]] stated that Schmid &quot;has over 20,000 chess books&quot;.{{cite web |url=http://susanpolgar.blogspot.com/2008/02/chess-records.html |title=Chess Daily News |accessdate=2012-03-03 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120210151833/http://susanpolgar.blogspot.com/2008/02/chess-records.html |archivedate=10 February 2012 |df=dmy-all }} [[Dirk Jan ten Geuzendam]] states that Schmid &quot;boasts to have amassed 50,000 chess books. Dirk Jan ten Geuzendam, &quot;The Finest Chess Collection in the World&quot;, ''[[New in Chess]]'', 2010, No. 5, p. 18. The title of the article refers to David DeLucia's collection, not Schmid's.&lt;/ref&gt; David DeLucia's chess library contains 7,000 to 8,000 chess books, a similar number of autographs (letters, score sheets, manuscripts), and about 1,000 items of &quot;ephemera&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;ten Geuzendam, p. 19&lt;/ref&gt; [[Dirk Jan ten Geuzendam]] opines that DeLucia's collection &quot;is arguably the finest chess collection in the world&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;ten Geuzendam, p. 10&lt;/ref&gt;

==Mathematics and computers==
{{See also|Computer chess|Mathematical chess problem|Human–computer chess matches|Deep Blue versus Garry Kasparov|Chess engine|Solving chess}}
The game structure and nature of chess are related to several branches of mathematics. Many [[combinatorics|combinatorical]] and [[topology|topological]] problems connected to chess have been known for hundreds of years.

===Combinatorics of chess and chess puzzles===
[[File:Knight's tour.svg|thumb|Mathematicians [[Euler]], [[Adrien-Marie Legendre|Legendre]], [[de Moivre]], and [[Vandermonde]] studied the [[knight's tour]].]]
The number of legal positions in chess is estimated to be about 10&lt;sup&gt;43&lt;/sup&gt;, and has been proved to be fewer than 10&lt;sup&gt;47&lt;/sup&gt;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=John's Chess Playground |author=John Tromp |year=2010 |url=https://tromp.github.io/chess/chess.html |access-date=7 February 2019 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190305084124/http://tromp.github.io/chess/chess.html |archive-date=5 March 2019 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Chinchalkar, S. (1996). An Upper Bound for the Number of Reachable Positions. ICCA Journal, Vol. 19, No. 3, pp. 181–83.&lt;/ref&gt; with a [[game-tree complexity]] of approximately 10&lt;sup&gt;123&lt;/sup&gt;. The game-tree complexity of chess was first calculated by [[Claude Shannon]] as 10&lt;sup&gt;120&lt;/sup&gt;, a number known as the [[Shannon number]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://mathworld.wolfram.com/Chess.html Chess.] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20061206004013/http://mathworld.wolfram.com/Chess.html |date=6 December 2006 }} ''Mathworld.Wolfram.com''. Retrieved 5 December 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; An average position typically has thirty to forty possible moves, but there may be as few as zero (in the case of checkmate or stalemate) or (in a constructed position) as many as 218.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.chessbox.de/Compu/schachzahl2_e.html |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070613072827/http://www.chessbox.de/Compu/schachzahl2_e.html |archivedate=13 June 2007 |publisher=ChessBox.de |title=The biggest Number of simultaneous possible legal Moves |url-status=dead |df=dmy}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Chess has inspired many combinatorial puzzles, such as the [[knight's tour]] and the [[eight queens puzzle]].

===Computer chess===
The idea of creating a chess-playing machine dates to the 18th&amp;nbsp;century; around 1769, the chess-playing [[automaton]] called [[The Turk]] became famous before being exposed as a [[hoax]].&lt;ref&gt;Levitt (2000)&lt;/ref&gt; Serious trials based on automata, such as [[El Ajedrecista]], were too complex and limited to be useful.

Since the advent of the [[digital computer]] in the 1950s, chess enthusiasts, [[computer engineer]]s, and computer scientists have built, with increasing degrees of seriousness and success, chess-playing machines and computer programs.&lt;ref&gt;Hsu, F.H. (2004). Behind Deep Blue: Building the Computer that Defeated the World Chess Champion, Princeton University Press. {{ISBN|978-0-691-11818-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; The groundbreaking paper on computer chess, &quot;Programming a Computer for Playing Chess&quot;, was published in 1950 by Shannon.{{refn|[[Alan Turing]] made an attempt in 1953.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.turingarchive.org/browse.php/B/7 |title = Digital computers applied to games |author = Alan Turing |publisher = University of Southampton and King's College Cambridge |url-status=live |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20080509054855/http://www.turingarchive.org/browse.php/B/7 |archivedate = 9 May 2008 |df = dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;|group=note}} He wrote:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
The chess machine is an ideal one to start with, since: (1) the problem is sharply defined both in allowed operations (the moves) and in the ultimate goal (checkmate); (2) it is neither so simple as to be trivial nor too difficult for satisfactory solution; (3) chess is generally considered to require &quot;thinking&quot; for skillful play; a solution of this problem will force us either to admit the possibility of a mechanized thinking or to further restrict our concept of &quot;thinking&quot;; (4) the discrete structure of chess fits well into the digital nature of
modern computers.&lt;ref&gt;Shannon, Claude E. XXII. Programming a Computer for Playing Chess. ''Philosophical Magazine'', Ser. 7, Vol. 41, No. 314 – March 1950. Available online at {{cite web |url=http://archive.computerhistory.org/projects/chess/related_materials/text/2-0%20and%202-1.Programming_a_computer_for_playing_chess.shannon/2-0%20and%202-1.Programming_a_computer_for_playing_chess.shannon.062303002.pdf |title=''computerhistory.org'' |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100706211229/http://archive.computerhistory.org/projects/chess/related_materials/text/2-0%20and%202-1.Programming_a_computer_for_playing_chess.shannon/2-0%20and%202-1.Programming_a_computer_for_playing_chess.shannon.062303002.pdf |archivedate=6 July 2010 |df= }}&amp;nbsp;{{small|(175&amp;nbsp;KB)}} Retrieved 2006-12-06.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

[[File:RS Chess Computer.JPG|thumb|right|1990s chess-playing computer]]
The [[Association for Computing Machinery]] (ACM) held the first major chess tournament for computers, the [[North American Computer Chess Championship]], in September 1970. [[Chess (Northwestern University)|CHESS 3.0]], a chess program from [[Northwestern University]], won the championship. Nowadays, chess programs compete in the [[World Computer Chess Championship]], held annually since 1974. At first considered only a curiosity, the best [[chess engine|chess playing programs]] have become extremely strong. In 1997, a computer won a chess match using classical time controls against a reigning World Champion for the first time: [[International Business Machines|IBM's]] [[IBM Deep Blue|Deep Blue]] beat [[Garry Kasparov]] 3½–2½ (it scored two wins, one loss, and three [[draw (chess)|draws]]).&lt;ref&gt;Hsu (2002), pp. 295–96&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://researchweb.watson.ibm.com/deepblue/watch/html/c.shtml Deep Blue – Kasparov Match] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100302133413/http://researchweb.watson.ibm.com/deepblue/watch/html/c.shtml |date=2 March 2010 }}. ''research.ibm.com''. Retrieved 30 November 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; However, the match was [[Human–computer chess matches#1997|controversial]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine |url=https://www.wired.com/2012/09/deep-blue-computer-bug/ |title=Did a Computer Bug Help Deep Blue Beat Kasparov? |magazine=Wired |date=September 28, 2012 |access-date=14 May 2018 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180515043725/https://www.wired.com/2012/09/deep-blue-computer-bug/ |archive-date=15 May 2018 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt; and computers would only win such a match again [[Human–computer chess matches#Kramnik – Deep Fritz (2006)|in 2006]].

In 2009, a [[mobile phone]] won a [[Category (chess tournament)|category]] 6 tournament with a performance rating 2898: chess engine [[Hiarcs]] 13 running on the mobile phone [[HTC Touch HD]] won the Copa Mercosur tournament with nine wins and one draw.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.chess.co.uk/twic/twic771.html#13 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110930232108/http://www.chess.co.uk/twic/twic771.html#13 |archivedate=30 September 2011 |title=Hiarcs 13 wins Copa Mercosur |accessdate=4 September 2010
|publisher=[[The Week in Chess]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; The best chess programs are now able to consistently beat the strongest human players, to the extent that [[Human–computer chess matches|human–computer matches]] no longer attract interest from chess players or media.

With huge databases of past games and high analytical ability, computers can help players to learn chess and prepare for matches. [[Internet Chess Server]]s allow people to find and play opponents worldwide. The presence of computers and modern communication tools have raised concerns regarding [[Cheating in chess|cheating]] during games, most notably the &quot;[[FIDE World Chess Championship 2006#Bathroom controversy|bathroom controversy]]&quot; during the 2006 World Championship.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2006/08/08/sports/othersports/08chess.html |title=Cheating Accusations in Mental Sports, Too |accessdate=28 August 2010 |work=The New York Times |date=8 August 2006 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20111205235525/http://www.nytimes.com/2006/08/08/sports/othersports/08chess.html |archivedate=5 December 2011 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Relation to game theory===
In 1913, [[Ernst Zermelo]] used chess as a basis for his theory of game strategies, which is considered as one of the predecessors of [[game theory]].&lt;ref&gt;Zermelo, Ernst (1913), Uber eine Anwendung der Mengenlehre auf die Theorie des Schachspiels, Proceedings of the Fifth International Congress of Mathematicians 2, 501–04. Cited from Eichhorn, Christoph: Der Beginn der Formalen Spieltheorie: Zermelo (1913), [http://www.mathematik.uni-muenchen.de/~spielth/artikel/Zermelo.pdf Uni-Muenchen.de] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070612134609/http://www.mathematik.uni-muenchen.de/~spielth/artikel/Zermelo.pdf |date=12 June 2007 }}. Retrieved 23 March 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Zermelo's theorem (game theory)|Zermelo's theorem]] states that it is possible to [[Solving chess|solve chess]], i.e. to determine with certainty the outcome of a perfectly played game (either White can force a win, or Black can force a win, or both sides can force at least a draw).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.gap-system.org/~history/Projects/MacQuarrie/Chapters/Ch4.html |title=Fundamentals |work=gap-system.org |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110607183513/http://www.gap-system.org/~history/Projects/MacQuarrie/Chapters/Ch4.html |archivedate=7 June 2011 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; According to [[Claude Shannon]], however, there are 10&lt;sup&gt;43&lt;/sup&gt; legal positions in chess, so it will take an impossibly long time to compute a perfect strategy with any feasible technology.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Encyclopedia of Computer Science and Technology: Volume 8 |chapter=Games |page=394 |isbn=978-0-8247-2258-6 |publisher=CRC Press |year=1977}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{clear}}

The 11-category, game theoretical taxonomy of chess includes: two player, no-chance, combinatorial, Markov state (present state is all a player needs to move; although past state led up to that point, knowledge of the sequence of past moves is not required to make the next move, except to take into account of ''en passant'' and castling, which ''do'' depend on the past moves), zero sum, symmetric, perfect information, non-cooperative, discrete, extensive form (tree decisions, not payoff matrices), and sequential.&lt;ref name=&quot;Marsland Markov&quot;&gt;{{cite book |isbn=978-1420067187 |title=Machine Learning: An Algorithmic Perspective |author=Stephen Marsland |location=New York |publisher=Chapman and Hall |year=2009 |page=302}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Computational complexity===
Generalized chess (played on ''n''×''n'' board, without the [[fifty-move rule]]) is [[EXPTIME-complete]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Fraenkel1981&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author=[[Aviezri Fraenkel]] and D. Lichtenstein |title=Computing a perfect strategy for n×n chess requires time exponential in n |journal=J. Comb. Th. A |issue=31 |year=1981 |pages=199–214}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Combinatorial game theory===
Some applications of [[combinatorial game theory]] to chess endgames were found by [[Noam Elkies|Elkies]] (1996).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Elkies |first1=Noam |title=On Numbers and Endgames: Combinatorial Game Theory in Chess Endgames |journal=Games of No Chance, MSRI Publications |date=1996 |volume=29 |arxiv=math/9905198 |bibcode=1999math......5198E }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Psychology==
[[File:Kids chess tournament.jpg|thumb|upright=0.90|right|A children's chess tournament in the United States]]
There is an extensive scientific literature on chess psychology.{{refn|A survey is given in [http://jeays.net/files/psychchess.htm Mark Jeays, &quot;A brief survey of psychological studies of chess&quot;].|group=note}}{{refn|Chess is even called the &quot;[[drosophila]]&quot; of [[cognitive psychology]] and artificial intelligence ([[AI]]) studies, because it represents the domain in which expert performance has been most intensively studied and measured.&lt;ref&gt;Grabner, Stern, &amp; Neubauer (2007) pp. 398–420&lt;/ref&gt;|group=note}}&lt;ref&gt;De Groot &amp; Gobet (1996)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Gobet, de Voogt, &amp; Retschitzki (2004)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Holding (1985)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Saariluoma (1995)&lt;/ref&gt; [[Alfred Binet]] and others showed that [[knowledge]] and verbal, rather than visuospatial, ability lies at the core of expertise.&lt;ref&gt;Binet (1894)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Robbins (1996), pp. 83–93&lt;/ref&gt; In his doctoral thesis, [[Adriaan de Groot]] showed that chess masters can rapidly perceive the key features of a position.&lt;ref&gt;de Groot (1946)&lt;/ref&gt; According to de Groot, this [[perception]], made possible by years of practice and study, is more important than the sheer ability to anticipate moves. De Groot showed that chess masters can memorize positions shown for a few seconds almost perfectly. The ability to memorize does not alone account for chess-playing skill, since masters and novices, when faced with random arrangements of chess pieces, had equivalent recall (about six positions in each case). Rather, it is the ability to recognize patterns, which are then memorized, which distinguished the skilled players from the novices. When the positions of the pieces were taken from an actual game, the masters had almost total positional recall.&lt;ref&gt;Richards J. Heuer Jr. ''Psychology of Intelligence Analysis'' Center for the Study of Intelligence, Central Intelligence Agency 1999 (see [https://www.cia.gov/library/center-for-the-study-of-intelligence/csi-publications/books-and-monographs/psychology-of-intelligence-analysis/art6.html Chapter 3] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070912045710/https://www.cia.gov/library/center-for-the-study-of-intelligence/csi-publications/books-and-monographs/psychology-of-intelligence-analysis/art6.html |date=12 September 2007 }}).&lt;/ref&gt;

More recent research has focused on [[chess as mental training]]; the respective roles of knowledge and look-ahead search; [[brain imaging]] studies of chess masters and novices; [[blindfold chess]]; the role of [[Personality psychology|personality]] and [[intelligence]] in chess skill; gender differences; and computational models of chess expertise. The role of practice and talent in the development of chess and other domains of expertise has led to much recent research. Ericsson and colleagues have argued that deliberate practice is sufficient for reaching high levels of expertise in chess.&lt;ref&gt;Ericsson, K.A., Krampe, R. Th., &amp; Tesch-Römer, C. (1993). {{cite web|url=http://www.freakonomics.com/pdf/DeliberatePractice%28PsychologicalReview%29.pdf |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20060512183911/http://www.freakonomics.com/pdf/DeliberatePractice%28PsychologicalReview%29.pdf |url-status=dead |archivedate=12 May 2006 |title=The role of deliberate practice in the acquisition of expert performance |df= }}&amp;nbsp;{{small|(1.25&amp;nbsp;MB)}} ''Psychological Review'', 100, 363–406. Retrieved 21 March 2017.&lt;/ref&gt; Recent research indicates that factors other than practice are also important. For example, [[Fernand Gobet]] and colleagues have shown that stronger players started playing chess at a young age and that experts born in the Northern Hemisphere are more likely to have been born in late winter and early spring. Compared to general population, chess players are more likely to be non-right-handed, though they found no correlation between handedness and skill.&lt;ref&gt;Gobet, F. &amp; Chassy, P. (in press). {{cite web |url=http://bura.brunel.ac.uk/bitstream/2438/736/1/Seasonality%20and%20chess.pdf |title=Season of birth and chess expertise. |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110718172434/http://bura.brunel.ac.uk/bitstream/2438/736/1/Seasonality%20and%20chess.pdf |archivedate=18 July 2011 |df=dmy-all }}&amp;nbsp;{{small|(65.8&amp;nbsp;KB)}} ''Journal of Biosocial Science''. &lt;br&gt; Gobet, F. &amp; Campitelli, G. (2007). {{cite web |url= http://bura.brunel.ac.uk/bitstream/2438/611/1/Gobet_DevPsyc_Final.pdf |title= The role of domain-specific practice, handedness and starting age in chess. |url-status=live |archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20070808073144/http://bura.brunel.ac.uk/bitstream/2438/611/1/Gobet_DevPsyc_Final.pdf |archivedate= 8 August 2007 |df= dmy-all }}&amp;nbsp;{{small|(196&amp;nbsp;KB)}} ''Developmental Psychology'', 43, 159–72. Both retrieved 2007-07-15.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Chess and intelligence===
A relationship between chess skill and intelligence has long been discussed in the literature and popular culture. Academic studies of the relationship date back at least to 1927.&lt;ref&gt;Djakow, I. N., Petrowski, N. W., &amp; Rudik, P. A. (1927).

Psychologie des schachspiels.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal |date=2016-11-01 |title=The relationship between cognitive ability and chess skill: A comprehensive meta-analysis |journal=Intelligence |language=en |volume=59 |pages=72–83 |doi=10.1016/j.intell.2016.08.002 |issn=0160-2896 |last1=Burgoyne |first1=Alexander P. |last2=Sala |first2=Giovanni |last3=Gobet |first3=Fernand |last4=MacNamara |first4=Brooke N. |last5=Campitelli |first5=Guillermo |last6=Hambrick |first6=David Z.|url=http://eprints.lse.ac.uk/102241/1/INTELL_2016_117_The_Relationship_between_Cognitive_Ability_and_Chess_Skill_a_Comprehensive_Meta_Analysis.pdf }}&lt;/ref&gt; Academic opinion has long been split on how strong the relationship is, with some studies finding no relationship and others finding a relatively strong one.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Campitelli |first=Guillermo |last2=Gobet |first2=Fernand |date=October 5, 2011 |title=Deliberate Practice: Necessary But Not Sufficient |journal=Current Directions in Psychological Science |volume=20 |issue=5 |pages=280–285 |doi=10.1177/0963721411421922}}&lt;/ref&gt; A 2016 [[meta-analysis]] and review based on 19 studies and a total sample size of 1,779 found that various aspects of [[G factor (psychometrics)|general intelligence]] correlate with chess skill, with average correlations ranging from 0.13 (visuospatial ability) to 0.35 (numerical ability).&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt; The review did not find strong evidence of [[publication bias]] biasing these estimates. Moderator analyses indicated that the relationship was stronger in unranked players (r = 0.32) vs. ranked players (r = 0.14), as well as stronger in children (r = 0.32) than adults (r = 0.11).

==Variants==
{{Main|Chess variant|List of chess variants}}
[[File:Hexagonal chess.svg|thumb|upright=1.2|right|[[Hexagonal chess#Gliński's hexagonal chess|Gliński's hexagonal chess]], launched in 1949, became popular in Eastern Europe, reaching half a million fans. Three cell colors and three bishops per side are the norm for hexagonal variants.]]
There are more than two thousand published chess variants,&lt;ref&gt;Pritchard (2000), p. 8&lt;/ref&gt; most of them of relatively recent origin,&lt;ref&gt;Pritchard details 1,450 of them in {{cite book |last=Pritchard |first=D.B. |authorlink=David Pritchard (chess player) |title=The Encyclopedia of Chess Variants |publisher=Games &amp; Puzzles Publications |year=1994 |isbn=978-0-9524142-0-9}} &quot;Of these, about half date from between 700 and 1970 (1,200 years!), half from the last quarter of the twentieth century.&quot; Parlett (1999), p. 312&lt;/ref&gt; including:
* Direct predecessors of chess such as [[chaturanga]] and [[shatranj]].
* Traditional national or regional games that share common ancestors with Western chess such as [[xiangqi]], [[shogi]], [[janggi]], [[makruk]], and [[sittuyin]].
* Modern variations employing different rules (e.g. [[Losing chess]]), different forces (e.g. [[Dunsany's Chess]]), [[Fairy piece|non-standard pieces]] (e.g. [[Grand Chess]]), or different board geometries (e.g. [[hexagonal chess]]). One rules variant that has gained significantly in popularity is [[Chess960]] (named &quot;Fischerandom&quot; by its inventor). In Chess960, the starting position is [[Chess960 starting position|selected randomly]] from 960 unique possibilities, including the classic chess initial position without change, while the other 959 render the use of [[Chess opening|prepared opening lines]] impracticable.&lt;ref&gt;Verwer (2010), p. 63&lt;/ref&gt; In 2008, FIDE added Chess960 to its ''Handbook''.{{refn|In 2008 FIDE added Chess960 rules to an appendix of the ''Handbook''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.fide.com/component/handbook/?id=124&amp;view=article |title=Laws of Chess: For competitions starting before 1 July 2014 |publisher=FIDE |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140823212929/http://www.fide.com/component/handbook/?id=124&amp;view=article |archivedate=23 August 2014 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; This section is now classified under &quot;Guidelines&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.fide.com/component/handbook/?view=article&amp;id=207 |title=Fide Laws of Chess taking effect from 1 July 2017 |publisher=FIDE |date= |accessdate=20 April 2017 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170420145055/https://www.fide.com/component/handbook/?view=article&amp;id=207 |archivedate=20 April 2017 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; indicating that the rules presented do not have the weight of FIDE law.|group=note}}
* [[Infinite chess]], which has drawn the attention of mathematicians.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PN-I6u-AxMg &quot;Infinite Chess, PBS Infinite Series&quot;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170407211614/https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PN-I6u-AxMg |date=7 April 2017 }} PBS Infinite Series, with academic sources {{cite arxiv|eprint=1302.4377|last1=Evans|first1=C.D.A|title=Transfinite game values in infinite chess|author2=Joel David Hamkins|class=math.LO|year=2013}} and {{cite arxiv|eprint=1510.08155|last1=Evans|first1=C.D.A|title=A position in infinite chess with game value $ω^4$|author2=Joel David Hamkins|author3=Norman Lewis Perlmutter|class=math.LO|year=2015}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Prime sources in English describing chess variants and their rules include [[David Pritchard (chess player)|David Pritchard]]'s encyclopedias,&lt;ref&gt;These are ''The Encyclopedia of Chess Variants'' (1994), and (published posthumously, edited by John Beasley) ''The Classified Encyclopedia of Chess Variants'' (2007).&lt;/ref&gt; the website ''[[The Chess Variant Pages]]'' created by [[Hans Bodlaender]] with various contributors, and the magazine ''Variant Chess'' published from 1990 (George Jellis) to 2010 (the [[British Chess Variants Society]]).

In the context of chess variants, regular (i.e. FIDE) chess is commonly referred to as ''Western chess'', ''international chess'', ''orthodox chess'', ''orthochess'', and ''classic chess''.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Western culture regards Chess as a particular game with a particular set of rules governed by an international authority (FIDE – the Fédération Internationale des Echecs). Variously known as International Chess, World Chess, Orthochess, and so on, [...]&quot; Parlett (1999), p. 276&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Schmittberger |first=R. Wayne |authorlink= |title=New Rules for Classic Games |publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons Inc |year=1992 |page=[https://archive.org/details/newrulesforclass00rway/page/186 186] |quote=The form of chess most people know&amp;nbsp;– which is sometimes referred to as Western chess, orthodox chess, or orthochess&amp;nbsp;– is itself just one of many that have been played throughout history. |isbn=978-0471536215 |url=https://archive.org/details/newrulesforclass00rway/page/186 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Chess}}
'''Reference aids'''
* [[Outline of chess]] (subject-wide table of contents)
* [[Glossary of chess]]
* [[Index of chess articles]]

'''Lists'''
* [[List of chess books]]
* [[List of chess games]]
* [[List of chess players]]
* [[List of chess world championship matches]]
* [[List of strong chess tournaments]]
{{clear}}

==Notes==
{{Reflist|group=note|30em}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

===Bibliography===
{{Refbegin|30em}}
* {{Cite book
 | author=Adams, Jenny
 | title=Power Play: The Literature and Politics of Chess in the Late Middle Ages
 | publisher=University of Pennsylvania Press
 | location=Philadelphia
 | year=2006
 | isbn=978-0-8122-3944-7
 | oclc=238812746
}}
* {{Cite book
 | author=Binet, A.
 | year=1894
 | title=Psychologie des grands calculateurs et joueurs d'échecs
 | language=French
 | location=Paris
 | publisher=Hachette
 | oclc=287413777
}}
* {{Cite book
 | author=Bird, Henry Edward|authorlink=Henry Bird (chess player)
 | origyear=First published 1893
 | year=2008
 | title=Chess History and Reminiscences
 | publisher=Forgotten Books
 | isbn=978-1-60620-897-7
}}
* {{Cite book
 | author=Graham Burgess
 | title=The Mammoth Book of Chess
 | publisher=Carroll &amp; Graf
 | year=2000
 | isbn=978-0-7867-0725-6
 | location=New York
}}
* {{Cite book
 |last=Burgess
 |first=Graham
 |authorlink=Graham Burgess
 |last2=Nunn
 |first2=John
 |authorlink2=John Nunn
 |last3=Emms
 |first3=John
 |authorlink3=John Emms (chess player)
 |title=The Mammoth Book of the World's Greatest Chess Games
 |year=2004
 |edition=2nd
 |publisher=Carroll &amp; Graf
 |isbn=978-0-7867-1411-7
 |location=New York
 |url=https://archive.org/details/mammothbookofwor0000burg
 }}
* {{Cite book
 | last=Davidson
 | first=Henry A.
 | year=1949
 | title=A Short History of Chess
 | publisher=D. McKay Co
 | isbn=978-0-679-14550-9
 | oclc=17340178
 | location=New York
}}
* {{Cite book
 |author1=de Groot |author2=Adriaan D. | origyear=1946 (first Dutch ed.)
 |year=1965
 |edition=English
 |title=Thought and Choice in Chess
 |location=The Hague
 |publisher=[[Mouton de Gruyter|Mouton]]
 |oclc=4988227
}}
* {{Cite book
 |author1=de Groot, Adriaan D. |author2=Gobet, Fernand | title=Perception and Memory in Chess: Heuristics of the Professional Eye
 |location=Assen, NL
 |publisher= Van Gorcum
 |year=1996
 |isbn=978-90-232-2949-0
}}
* {{Cite book
| author=de la Villa, Jesús|authorlink=Jesús de la Villa
| title=100 Endgames You Must Know
| publisher=[[New in Chess]]
| year=2008
| isbn=978-90-5691-244-4
}}
* {{Cite book
 |author=Estes, Rebecca
 |author2=Robinson, Dindy
 |year=1996
 |title=World Cultures Through Art Activities
 |publisher=Teachers Ideas Press
 |location=Englewood, CO
 |isbn=978-1-56308-271-9
}}
* {{Cite book
 |last=Evans
 |first=Larry
 |authorlink=Larry Evans (chess grandmaster)
 |title=New Ideas in Chess
 |year=1958
 |publisher=Pitman (1984 [[Dover Publications|Dover]] edition)
 |isbn= 978-0-486-28305-0
 |location=New York
}}
* {{Cite book
 | author=Franklin, Benjamin|authorlink=Benjamin Franklin
 | url=https://books.google.com/?id=nAl9tOwf5psC&amp;pg=PA289
 | title=A Benjamin Franklin Reader
 | origyear = 1779
 | year=2003
 | publisher=[[Simon &amp; Schuster]]
 | location=New York
 | accessdate=12 December 2010
 | isbn=978-0-7432-5782-4
}}
* {{Cite book
 | author1=Gobet, Fernand
 | author2=de Voogt, Alex
 | author3=Retschitzki, Jean
 | title=Moves in Mind: The Psychology of Board Games
 | location=Hove, UK
 | publisher= Psychology Press
 | year=2004
 | isbn=978-1-84169-336-1
 | oclc= 53962630
}}
* {{Cite journal
 | title=Individual differences in chess expertise: A psychometric investigation
 | journal=Acta Psychologica
 | volume=124
 | issue=3
 | date=March 2007
 | pages=398–420
 | doi=10.1016/j.actpsy.2006.07.008
 | pmid=16942740
 | last=Grabner
 | first=RH
 | last2=Stern
 | first2=E
 | last3=Neubauer
 | first3=AC
}}
* {{Cite book
 | last=Harding
 | first=Tim
 | title=Better Chess for Average Players
 | year=2003
 | publisher=Courier Dover Publications
 | isbn=978-0-486-29029-4
 | oclc=33166445
 | location=New York
}}
* {{Cite book
 | author=Hartston, William R.
 | title=The Kings of Chess
 | year=1985
 | publisher=Pavilion Books
 | isbn=978-0-06-015358-8
 | location=New York
 | url=https://archive.org/details/kingsofchesshi00hart
 }}
* {{Cite book
 | author=Holding, Dennis
 | title=The Psychology of Chess Skill
 | publisher=Erlbaum
 | year=1985
 | isbn=978-0-89859-575-8
 | oclc=11866227
 | location=Hillsdale, NJ
}}
* {{Cite book
 | author1=Hooper, David|authorlink1=David Vincent Hooper
 | author2=Whyld, Kenneth|authorlink2=Kenneth Whyld
 | title=The Oxford Companion to Chess, Second edition
 | publisher=Oxford University Press
 | year=1992
 | isbn=978-0-19-866164-1
 | oclc=25508610
 | location=Oxford; New York
 | title-link=The Oxford Companion to Chess
 }}
* {{Cite book
 | author=Howard, Kenneth S
 | title=How to Solve Chess Problems
 | publisher=Courier Dover Publications
 | year=1961
 | isbn=978-0-486-20748-3
 | location=New York
}}
* {{Cite book
 | author=Feng-Hsiung Hsu
 | title=Behind Deep Blue: Building the Computer that Defeated the World Chess Champion
 | publisher=[[Princeton University Press]]
 | year=2002
 | isbn=978-0-691-09065-8
 | oclc=50582855
 | location=Princeton
}}
* {{Cite book
 | last=Kasparov
 | first=Garry
 | authorlink=Garry Kasparov
 | title=My Great Predecessors, part I
 | year=2003a
 | publisher=[[Everyman Chess]]
 | isbn=978-1-85744-330-1
 | oclc=223602528
 | location=London; Guilford, CT
 | title-link=My Great Predecessors
 }}
* {{Cite book
 | last=Kasparov
 | first=Garry
 | title=My Great Predecessors, part II
 | year=2003b
 | publisher=Everyman Chess
 | isbn=978-1-85744-342-4
 | oclc=223906486
 | location=London; Guilford, CT
}}
* {{Cite book
 | last=Kasparov
 | first=Garry
 | title=My Great Predecessors, part III
 | year=2004a
 | publisher=Everyman Chess
 | isbn=978-1-85744-371-4
 | oclc=52949851
 | location=London; Guilford, CT
}}
* {{Cite book
 | last=Kasparov
 | first=Garry
 | title=My Great Predecessors, part IV
 | year=2004b
 | publisher=Everyman Chess
 | isbn=978-1-85744-395-0
 | oclc=52949851
 | location=London; Guilford, CT
}}
* {{Cite book
 | last=Kasparov
 | first=Garry
 | title=My Great Predecessors, part V
 | year=2006
 | publisher=Everyman Chess
 | isbn=978-1-85744-404-9
 | oclc=52949851
 | location=London; Guilford, CT
}}
* {{Cite book
 | author=Keene, Raymond
 | title=Gary Kasparov's Best Games
 | publisher=B.T. Batsford
 | year=1993
 | isbn=978-0-7134-7296-7
 | oclc=29386838
 | location=London
}}
* {{Cite book
 | last=Lasker|first=Emanuel|authorlink=Emanuel Lasker
 | title=Lasker's Chess Primer
 | year=1934
 | publisher=Billings (1988 reprint)
 | isbn= 978-0-7134-6241-8
 | location=London
}}
* {{Cite book
 | author=Leibs, Andrew
 | year=2004
 | title=Sports and Games of the Renaissance
 | publisher=Greenwood Publishing Group
 | isbn=978-0-313-32772-8
 | location=Westport, CT
}}
* {{Cite book
 | author=Levitt, Gerald M.
 | title=The Turk, Chess Automaton
 | publisher=McFarland &amp; Company
 | year=2000
 | isbn=978-0-7864-0778-1
 | oclc=226148928
 | location=Jefferson, NC
}}
* {{Cite book
 | author=Li, David H.|authorlink=David H. Li
 | title=The Genealogy of Chess
 | publisher=Premier
 | year=1998
 | isbn=978-0-9637852-2-0
 | oclc=39281682
 | location=Bethesda, MD
}}
* {{Cite book
 | author=Metzner, Paul
 | title=Crescendo of the Virtuoso: Spectacle, Skill, and Self-Promotion in Paris during the Age of Revolution
 | publisher=University of California Press
 | year=1998
 | isbn=978-0-520-20684-7
 | oclc=185289629
 | url=http://publishing.cdlib.org/ucpressebooks/view?docId=ft438nb2b6&amp;brand=ucpress
 | location=Berkeley
}}
* {{Cite book
 | author=Murray, H.J.R.
 | authorlink=H. J. R. Murray
 | title=A History of Chess
 | publisher=Benjamin Press (originally published by Oxford University Press)
 | year=1913
 | isbn=978-0-936317-01-4
 | oclc=13472872
 | location=Northampton, Mass.
 | url=https://archive.org/details/historyofchess00murr
 }}
* {{Cite book
 | author=Olmert, Michael
 | year=1996
 | title=Milton's Teeth and Ovid's Umbrella: Curiouser &amp; Curiouser Adventures in History
 | publisher=Simon &amp; Schuster
 | location=New York
 | isbn=978-0-684-80164-3
 | url=https://archive.org/details/miltonsteethovid00olme
 }}
* {{cite book
 |last=Parlett
 |first=David
 |authorlink=David Parlett
 |title=The Oxford History of Board Games
 |url=https://archive.org/details/oxfordhistoryofb0000parl
 |url-access=registration
 |publisher=[[Oxford University Press]] Inc
 |year=1999
 |isbn=978-0-19-212998-7
}}
* {{Cite book
 | author=Pritchard, David
 | title=Popular Chess Variants
 | publisher=Batsford Chess Books
 | year=2000
 | isbn=978-0-7134-8578-3
 | oclc=44275285
 | location=London
}}
* {{Cite journal
 | last=Robbins
 | first=T.W.
 | year=1996
 | title=Working Memory in Chess
 | journal=Memory &amp; Cognition
 | pages=83–93
 | url=http://www.dur.ac.uk/c.p.fernyhough/Robbinsetal1996.pdf
 | doi=10.3758/BF03197274
 | pmid=8822160
 | last2=Anderson
 | first2=E.J.
 | last3=Barker
 | first3=D.R.
 | last4=Bradley
 | first4=A.C.
 | last5=Fearnyhough
 | first5=C.
 | last6=Henson
 | first6=R.
 | last7=Hudson
 | first7=S.R.
 | last8=Baddeley
 | first8=A.D.
 | volume=24| issue=1
 }}
* {{Cite book
 | author=Saariluoma, Pertti
 | title=Chess Players' Thinking: A Cognitive Psychological Approach
 | publisher=Routledge
 | year=1995
 | isbn=978-0-415-12079-1
 | location=New York
}}
* {{Cite book
 | last = Silman|first=Jeremy|authorlink=Jeremy Silman
 | title=The Complete Book of Chess Strategy
 | publisher=Silman-James Press
 | year=1998
 | isbn= 978-1-890085-01-8
 | location=Los Angeles
}}
* {{Cite book
 | author=Shibut, Macon
 | title=Paul Morphy and the Evolution of Chess Theory
 | publisher=Courier Dover Publications
 | year=2004
 | isbn=978-0-486-43574-9
 | oclc=55639730
 | location=New York
}}
* {{Cite book
 | author=Steinitz, William
 | author2=Landsberger, Kurt
 | title=The Steinitz Papers: Letters and Documents of the First World Chess Champion
 | publisher=McFarland &amp; Company
 | year=2002
 | isbn=978-0-7864-1193-1
 | oclc=48550929
 | location=Jeferson, NC
}}
* {{Cite journal
 | author = Tamburro, Pete
 | date=September 2010
 | title = Challenging the Ruy Lopez
 | journal = [[Chess Life]]
 | pages=18–21
 | volume =
 | issue =
 | doi =
 | id =
 | url =
 | accessdate =
 }}
* {{Cite book
 | author=Tarrasch, Siegbert|authorlink=Siegbert Tarrasch
 | title=The Game of Chess
 | publisher=Courier Dover Publications
 | year=1987
 | isbn=978-0-486-25447-0
 | oclc=15631832
 | location=New York
}}
* {{Cite book
 | author=Vale, Malcolm
 | title=The Princely Court: Medieval Courts and Culture in North-West Europe, 1270–1380
 | publisher=Oxford University Press
 | year=2001
 | isbn=978-0-19-926993-8
 | oclc=47049906
 | location=Oxford
}}
* {{Cite book
 | last=Verwer|first=Renzo
 | title=Bobby Fischer for Beginners
 | year=2010
 | publisher=[[New in Chess]]
 | isbn= 978-90-5691-315-1
 | location=Alkmaar
}}
* {{Cite book
 | last=Watson|first=John|authorlink=John L. Watson
 | title=Secrets of Modern Chess Strategy
 | year=1998
 | publisher=[[Gambit Publications]]
 | isbn= 978-1-901983-07-4
 | location=London
}}
* {{cite book
 | author=Weenink, H.G.M.
 | editor1=Hume, G. |editor2=White, A.C. | title=The Chess Problem
 | publisher=Office of The Chess Amateur
 | location=Stroud
 | year=1926
 | oclc=3617028
}}
* {{Cite book
 | author=Weissberger, Barbara F.
 | title=Isabel Rules: Qonstructing Queenship, Wielding Power
 | publisher=University of Minnesota Press
 | year=2004
 | isbn=978-0-8166-4164-2
 | oclc=217447754
 | location=Minneapolis
}}
* {{Cite journal
 | last=Wilkinson
 | first=Charles K.
 | title=Chessmen and Chess
 | journal=The Metropolitan Museum of Art Bulletin
 | volume=New Series 1
 | pages=271–79
 | date=May 1943
 | doi=10.2307/3257111
 | issue=9
 | jstor=3257111
}}
* {{Cite book
 | title=Birth of the Chess Queen
 | isbn=978-0-06-009064-7
 | author=Yalom, Marilyn
 | year=2004
 | publisher=Harper Collins Publishers
 | location=New York
}}
{{Refend}}

==Further reading==
* {{Cite book
 | author=Dunnington, Angus
 | year=2003
 | title=Chess Psychology: Approaching the Psychological Battle Both on and Off the Board
 | publisher=[[Everyman Chess]]
 | isbn=978-1-85744-326-4}}
* {{Cite book
 | author=Fine, Reuben
 | title=The World's Great Chess Games
 | publisher=Courier Dover Publications
 | year=1983
 | isbn=978-0-486-24512-6
 | oclc=9394460| author-link=Reuben Fine
 }}
* {{Cite book
 | author=Hale, Benjamin
 | year=2008
 | title=Philosophy Looks at Chess
 | publisher=[[Open Court Publishing Company]]
 | isbn=978-0-8126-9633-2}}
* {{Cite book
 | author=Kotov, Alexander
 | year=1971
 | title=Think Like a Grandmaster
 | publisher=B.T. Batsford Ltd
 | isbn=978-0-7134-3160-5| author-link=Alexander Kotov
 }}
* {{Cite book
 | author=Lasker, Emanuel
 | year=1960
 | title=Lasker's Manual of Chess
 | publisher=Dover
 | isbn=978-0-486-20640-0| author-link=Emanuel Lasker
 }}
* {{Cite book
 | author=Mason, James
 | title=The Art of Chess
 | publisher=Dover Publications
 | year=1947
 | isbn=978-0-486-20463-5
 | oclc=45271009| author-link=James Mason (chess player)
 }} (see the included supplement, &quot;How Do You Play Chess&quot;)
* {{Cite book
 | author=Pachman, Ludek
 | year=1971
 | title=Modern Chess Strategy
 | publisher=Dover
 | isbn=978-0-486-20290-7| author-link=Ludek Pachman
 }}
* {{Cite book
 | author=Reti, Richard
 | year=1960
 | title=Modern Ideas in Chess
 | publisher=Dover
 | isbn=978-0-486-20638-7| author-link=Richard Reti
 }}
* {{Cite book
 | author=Rizzitano, James
 | title=Understanding Your Chess
 | publisher=Gambit Publications
 | year=2004
 | isbn=978-1-904600-07-7
 | oclc=55205602}}

==External links==
&lt;!--PLEASE DISCUSS ALL ADDITIONAL LINKS ON TALK PAGES BEFORE YOU ADD THEM HERE. OTHERWISE THEY WILL BE REMOVED INSTANTLY.--&gt;
{{Spoken Wikipedia|Chess.ogg|2016-10-18}}
{{Sister project links|Chess|n=Category:Chess|s=Portal:Chess|d=Q718|voy=no|species=no|m=no|mw=no}}
* {{Curlie|Games/Board_Games/Abstract/Battle_Games/Chess/}}
;International organizations
* [http://www.fide.com/ FIDE]&amp;nbsp;– [[FIDE|World Chess Federation]]
* [http://www.iccf.com/ ICCF]&amp;nbsp;– [[International Correspondence Chess Federation]]

;News
* [http://www.chessbase.com/ Chessbase news]
* [http://www.theweekinchess.com/ The Week in Chess]

;History
* [http://www.chesshistory.com/winter/extra/factfinder.html Chesshistory.com]

{{Chess|sp=us}}
{{World Chess Championships}}
{{Chess tournaments}}
{{Chess piece|state=collapsed}}
{{Chess variants}}
{{Featured article}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Abstract strategy games]]
[[Category:Chess| ]]
[[Category:Individual sports]]
[[Category:Indian inventions]]
[[Category:Traditional board games]]
[[Category:Partially solved games]]
[[Category:Games related to chaturanga]]</text>
      <sha1>cjr1gty50gkvpdqfabus2z2wrsaryor</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
