  <page>
    <title>Duke Kahanamoku</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9118</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942025745</id>
      <parentid>942025457</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-22T03:26:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Gondorian</username>
        <id>1116763</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* Further reading */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|American swimmer, surfer and actor}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=November 2019}}
{{Infobox swimmer
| name           = Duke Kahanamoku
| image          = Duke Kahanamoku c1912.jpg
| alt            =
| caption        = Duke Kahanamoku c. 1912
| fullname       = Duke Paoa Kahinu Mokoe Hulikohola Kahanamoku
| nicknames      = &quot;Duke,&quot; &quot;The Big [[Kahuna]]&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;SurferToday&quot;&gt;{{cite web |author1=Editor for Surfer Today |title=10 interesting facts about Duke Kahanamoku |url=https://www.surfertoday.com/surfing/10-interesting-facts-about-duke-kahanamoku |website=Surfertoday |accessdate=8 November 2019 |language=en-us}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| national_team  = {{USA}}
| strokes        = [[Freestyle swimming|Freestyle]]
| club           = Waikiki Beach Boys
| collegeteam    =
| birth_date     = {{Birth date|1890|8|24|mf=y}}
| birth_place    = [[Haleʻākala]], [[Honolulu]], [[Kingdom of Hawaii]]
| death_date     = {{Death date and age|1968|1|22|1890|8|24|mf=y}}
| death_place    = [[Honolulu, Hawaii]]&lt;ref name=Murphy&gt;{{cite book|last1=Murphy, Kelly with Hallie Fryd|title=Historical Heartthrobs: 50 Timeless Crushes-From Cleopatra to Camus|date=2013|publisher=Zest Books|location=USA|page=109|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=djHTs6i9NnEC&amp;printsec=frontcover|isbn=9781936976102}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| height         = {{convert|6|ft|1|in|cm|abbr=on}}&lt;ref name=Murphy/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Men's Journal&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last1=See|first1=Jen|title=5 Things You Didn't Know About Duke Kahanamoku|url=http://www.mensjournal.com/adventure/watersports/5-things-you-didnt-know-about-duke-kahanamoku-20150824|website=MensJournal.com|publisher=Men's Journal|accessdate=August 25, 2015|date=August 24, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| weight         = {{convert|190|lb|kg|abbr=on}}&lt;ref name=Murphy/&gt;
| medaltemplates =
{{MedalCountry | the United States}}
{{MedalCompetition | [[Surfing at the Summer Olympics|Olympic Games]]}}
{{MedalGold | [[1912 Summer Olympics|1912 Stockholm]] | [[Swimming at the 1912 Summer Olympics – Men's 100 metre freestyle|100 m freestyle]]}}
{{MedalGold | [[1920 Summer Olympics|1920 Antwerp]] | [[Swimming at the 1920 Summer Olympics – Men's 100 metre freestyle|100 m freestyle]]}}
{{MedalGold | 1920 Antwerp | [[Swimming at the 1920 Summer Olympics – Men's 4 × 200 metre freestyle relay|4×200 m freestyle]]}}
{{MedalSilver | 1912 Stockholm | [[Swimming at the 1912 Summer Olympics – Men's 4 × 200 metre freestyle relay|4×200 m freestyle]]}}
{{MedalSilver | [[1924 Summer Olympics|1924 Paris]] | [[Swimming at the 1924 Summer Olympics – Men's 100 metre freestyle|100 m freestyle]]}}
}}
[[File:Duke Kahanamoku signature.svg|thumb|upright=1.2|Signature]]

'''Duke Paoa Kahinu Mokoe Hulikohola Kahanamoku''' (August 24, 1890 – January 22, 1968) was a [[Native Hawaiian]] competition swimmer who popularized the ancient Hawaiian sport of [[surfing]]. He was born towards the end of the [[Kingdom of Hawaii]], just before the [[Overthrow of the Kingdom of Hawaii|overthrow]], living into [[Hawaii Admission Act|statehood]] as a United States citizen. He was a five-time Olympic medalist in [[Swimming at the Summer Olympics|swimming]].  Duke was also a [[Scottish Rite Freemasonry|Scottish Rite Freemason]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = https://www.honoluluscottishritebodies.org/our-history/ | title = History of the Scottish Rite Masonic Lodge in Honolulu | website = honoluluscottishritebodies.org | access-date = September 30, 2018 | language = en | archive-url = https://archive.today/20180930171025/http://www.honoluluscottishritebodies.org/our-history/ | archive-date = September 30, 2018 | url-status = live }}&lt;/ref&gt;, a [[law enforcement]] officer, an actor, a beach volleyball player and a businessman.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hall&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Duke: A Great Hawaiian |last=Hall |first=Sandra Kimberly. |year=2004 |publisher=Bess Press |location=Honolulu, HI |isbn=1-57306-230-8 |pages= |url= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early years==
According to Kahanamoku, he was born in [[Honolulu]] at [[Haleʻākala]], the home of [[Bernice Pauahi Bishop]] which was later converted into the Arlington Hotel.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nendel&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= Duke Kahanamoku: Twentieth Century Hawaiian Nonarch |year=2006 |publisher=ProQuest | pages =1–13 |last=Nendel |first=James D. |last2= The Pennsylvania State University | isbn =0-542-84320-X |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=rSKo0rK3xYsC}}&lt;/ref&gt; He had five brothers and three sisters, including [[Samuel Kahanamoku]] and [[Sargent Kahanamoku]]. In 1893, the family moved to Kālia, Waikiki (near the present site of the [[Hilton Hawaiian Village]]), to be closer to his mother's parents and family. Duke grew up with his siblings and 31 Paoa cousins.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hall&quot;/&gt;{{rp|17}} Duke attended the Waikiki Grammar School, Kaahumanu School, and the [[Kamehameha Schools]], although he never graduated because he had to quit to help support the family.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gardiner&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.calodges.org/ncrl/duke-k.html |title=Duke Kahanamoku Paoa |author=Herbert G. Gardiner, PGS, Grand Historian |accessdate=March 22, 2011 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110928063018/http://www.calodges.org/ncrl/duke-k.html |archivedate=September 28, 2011  }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&quot;Duke&quot; was not a title or a nickname, but a [[given name]]. He was named after his father, Duke Halapu Kahanamoku, who was christened by Bernice Pauahi Bishop in honor of [[Alfred, Duke of Saxe-Coburg and Gotha|Prince Alfred, Duke of Edinburgh]], who was visiting Hawaii at the time. His father was a policeman. His mother Julia Pa{{okina}}akonia Lonokahikina Paoa was a deeply religious woman with a strong sense of family ancestry.

Even though not of the formal Hawaiian Royal Family, his parents were from prominent Hawaiian [[ohana]] (family); the Kahanamoku and the Paoa ohana were considered to be lower-ranking nobles, who were in service to the ''[[aliʻi]] nui'' or royalty.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nendel&quot;/&gt; His paternal grandfather was Kahanamoku and his grandmother, Kapiolani Kaoeha (sometimes spelled ''Kahoea''), a descendant of [[Alapainui]]. They were ''kahu'', retainers and trusted advisors of the Kamehamehas, to whom they were related. His maternal grandparents Paoa, son of Paoa Hoolae and Hiikaalani, and Mele Uliama were also of aliʻi descent.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hall&quot;/&gt;{{rp|9}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Brennan1968&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Brennan|first=Joe|title=Duke of Hawaii|url=https://books.google.com/books?id%3DBfTR8QtYHj8C|year=1968|publisher= |location= |pages=74–76}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Growing up on the outskirts of Waikiki, Kahanamoku spent his youth as a bronzed beach boy. At Waikiki Beach he developed his surfing and swimming skills. In his youth, Kahanamoku preferred a traditional surf board, which he called his &quot;papa nui&quot;, constructed after the fashion of ancient Hawaiian &quot;olo&quot; boards. Made from the wood of a [[koa]] tree, it was {{convert|16|ft|m}} long and weighed {{convert|114|lb|kg}}. The board was without a [[Skeg#Surfing|skeg]], which had yet to be invented. In his later career, he would often use smaller boards but always preferred those made of wood.

On August 11, 1911, Kahanamoku was timed at 55.4 seconds in the {{convert|100|yd|m}} [[freestyle swimming|freestyle]], beating the existing world record by 4.6 seconds, in the salt water of Honolulu Harbor. He also broke the record in the {{convert|220|yd|m|abbr=on}} and equaled it in the {{convert|50|yd|m|abbr=on}}. But the [[Amateur Athletic Union]] (AAU), in disbelief, would not recognize these feats until many years later. The AAU initially claimed that the judges must have been using alarm clocks rather than stopwatches and later claimed that ocean currents aided Kahanamoku.&lt;ref&gt;[http://galenet.galegroup.com/servlet/BioRC &quot;Duke Kahanamoku. Notable Asian Americans.] Gale Research, 1995. Reproduced in Biography Resource Center. Farmington Hills, Mich.: Thomson Gale. 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

He was initiated to the Hawaiian [[Masonic Lodge]] No 21&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://lubbockmasoniclodge.org/about-2/who-are-freemasons | title = Athletes and other sport figures notable masons | language = en | access-date= September 30, 2018 | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20130714123058/http://lubbockmasoniclodge.org/about-2/who-are-freemasons | archive-date = July 14, 2013 | url-status = live}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = https://web.archive.org/web/20111224182230/http://www.pinallodge30.com/famousmasons.aspx | title = Famous Masons | access-date = September 30, 2018 | language = en | archive-url = https://archive.today/20111224182230/http://www.pinallodge30.com/famousmasons.aspx | archive-date = December 24, 2011 | url-status = live }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.navesinklodge9.org/famous.htm | title = Athletes and Other Sports Figures in Freemasonry | language = en | access-date = September 30, 2018 | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20130929214429/http://www.navesinklodge9.org/famous.htm | archive-date = September 29, 2013 | url-status = dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; and was also a member of the [[Shriners]] society&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://encyclopediaofsurfing.com/entries/kahanamoku-duke | title = Duke Paoa Kahanamoku Kahinu Mokoe Hulikohola (1890 – 1968) | language = en | access-date = September 30, 2018 | quotation = Duke was a member of Hawaii Lodge #22, The Scottish Rite and the Shriners. | website = St. John's Lodge No 2, New Castle Delaware | archive-url = https://archive.today/20180930173818/http://www.stjohns-no2-de.com/trestle/2015/apr/trestleboard_pg3.html | archive-date = September 30, 2018 | url-status = live }}&lt;/ref&gt;.

==Career==
[[File:Duke Kahanamoku 1920.jpg|thumb|left|250px|Duke Kahanamoku with his solid redwood surfboard, in Corona Del Mar, California in 1921]]

Kahanamoku easily qualified for the U.S. Olympic swimming team in 1912.  At the [[1912 Summer Olympics]] in Stockholm, he won a gold medal in the [[Swimming at the 1912 Summer Olympics – Men's 100 metre freestyle|100-meter freestyle]], and a silver medal with the second-place U.S. team in the [[Swimming at the 1912 Summer Olympics – Men's 4 × 200 metre freestyle relay|men's 4×200-meter freestyle relay]].  During the [[1920 Summer Olympics|1920 Olympics]] in Antwerp, he won gold medals both in the 100 meters (bettering fellow Hawaiian [[Pua Kealoha]]) and in the relay.  He finished the 100 meters with a silver medal during the [[1924 Summer Olympics|1924 Olympics]] in Paris, with the gold going to [[Johnny Weissmuller]] and the bronze to Duke's brother, [[Samuel Kahanamoku]].  At age 34, this was Kahanamoku's last Olympic medal.&lt;ref name=Murphy/&gt; He also was an alternate for the U.S. water polo team at the [[1932 Summer Olympics]].

=== Post Olympic Career ===

Between Olympic competitions, and after retiring from the Olympics, Kahanamoku traveled internationally to give swimming exhibitions. It was during this period that he popularized the sport of surfing, previously known only in Hawaii, by incorporating surfing exhibitions into these visits as well. His surfing exhibition at Sydney's [[Freshwater Beach]] on December 24, 1914 is widely regarded as a seminal event in the development of surfing in Australia.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | author = Osmond, Gary. | year = 2010 | title = 'Honolulu Māori': Racial Dimensions of Duke Kahanamoku's Tour of Australia and New Zealand | url =  | journal = New Zealand Journal of History | volume = 44 | issue = 1 | pages = 22–34 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The board that Kahanamoku built from a piece of pine from a local hardware store is retained by the Freshwater Surf Club.  There is a statue of Kahanamoku on the Northern headland of Freshwater Beach, New South Wales.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://monumentaustralia.org.au/themes/people/foreigners/display/21512-duke-kahanamoku|title=Duke Kahanamoku {{!}} Monument Australia|last=Design|first=UBC Web|website=monumentaustralia.org.au|language=en|access-date=October 3, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;  He made surfing popular in mainland America first in 1912 while in Southern California.

During his time living in Southern California, Kahanamoku performed in Hollywood as a background actor and a character actor in several films. In this way, he made connections with people who could further publicize the sport of surfing. Kahanamoku was involved with the [[Los Angeles Athletic Club]], acting as a lifeguard and competing in both swimming and water polo teams.

While living in [[Newport Beach, California]] on June 14, 1925, Kahanamoku rescued eight men from a fishing vessel that capsized in heavy surf while attempting to enter the city's harbor.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author= |author2= |title=Kahanamoku Helps Save 13 in Launch. Hawaiian Swimmer and Others Go to Their Rescue With Surf Boards. Five Are Drowned |url=https://www.nytimes.com/1925/06/16/archives/kahanamoku-helps-save-13-in-launch-hawaiian-swimmer-and-others-go.html |quote=... swimming star, Duke Kahanamoku and his fellow surf-board experts, were the ... of the beach here, credited with saving the lives of thirteen persons. ... |work=[[The New York Times]] |date=June 16, 1925 |accessdate=November 2, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Twenty nine sport fishermen went into the water, and seventeen eventually drowned. Using his surfboard Duke was able to make repeated trips back &amp; forth from shore to the capsized ship increasing the number of  those rescued.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.hawaiianswimboat.com/duke6.html |title=Biography: Corona Del Mar Save |accessdate=November 21, 2008 |author=Gault-Williams, Malcolm |work=Legendary Surfers |publisher=Hawaiianswimboat.com |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090207184520/http://www.hawaiianswimboat.com/duke6.html |archivedate=February 7, 2009  }}&lt;/ref&gt; Two other surfers saved four more fishermen. At the time the Newport Beach  police chief  called Duke's efforts &quot;The most superhuman surfboard rescue act the world has ever seen&quot;. It also led to lifeguards across the US to begin using surfboards as standard equipment for water rescues.&lt;ref name=&quot;Men's Journal&quot;/&gt;

In 1940 Duke married Nadine Alexander, who accompanied him when he traveled. Kahanamoku was the first person to be inducted into both the [[Swimming Hall of Fame]] and the [[Surfing Hall of Fame]]. The [[Duke Kahanamoku Invitational Surfing Championship]]s in Hawaii, the first major professional surfing contest event ever held in the huge surf on the North Shore of Oahu, was named in his honor. He is a member of the [[United States Olympic Hall of Fame|U.S. Olympic Hall of Fame]]. Duke went on to  serve as the Sheriff of [[Honolulu, Hawaii]] from 1932 to 1961, serving 13 consecutive terms. During this period he also appeared in a number of television programs and films, such as ''[[Mister Roberts (1955 film)|Mister Roberts]]'' (1955), and was well liked throughout the Hollywood community.

Kahanamoku was a friend and surfing companion of heiress [[Doris Duke]], who built a home (now a museum) on Oahu named [[Shangri La (Doris Duke)|Shangri-la]].

== ''Duncan v. Kahanamoku'' ==
{{Further|Duncan v. Kahanamoku}}
In 1946, Kahanamoku was the ''[[pro forma]]'' defendant in the landmark [[Supreme Court of the United States|Supreme Court]] case ''[[Duncan v. Kahanamoku]]''. While Kahanamoku was a [[military police]] officer during [[World War II]], he arrested Duncan, a civilian [[shipfitter]], for public intoxication. At the time, Hawaii, not yet a state, was being administered under the [[Hawaiian Organic Act]] which effectively instituted [[martial law]] on the island. Duncan was therefore tried by a military tribunal and appealed to the Supreme Court. In a ''post hoc'' ruling, the court ruled that trial by military tribunal was, in this case, [[unconstitutional]].&lt;ref&gt;''[https://supreme.justia.com/cases/federal/us/327/304/case.html Duncan v. Kahanamoku]'', 327 U.S. 304 (1946).&lt;/ref&gt;

== Death and legacy ==

Kahanamoku died of a heart attack on January 22, 1968, at the age of 77.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author= |author2= |title=Duke Kahanamoku Dies at 77. Leading Swimmer of His Time. Olympic Swimming Champion of '12 and '20 in Freestyle. Best-Known Hawaiian |url=https://www.nytimes.com/1968/01/23/archives/duke-kahanamoku-dies-at-77-leading-swimmer-of-his-time-olympic.html |quote=Duke Kahanamoku, the Olympic swimming star, whose international sports career spanned 20 years and who became Hawaii's best-known citizen, died today at ... |work=[[The New York Times]] |date=January 23, 1968 |accessdate=November 2, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; For his [[burial at sea]] a long motorcade of mourners, accompanied by a 30-man police escort, moved across town to [[Waikiki|Waikiki Beach]]. Reverend [[Abraham Akaka]], the pastor of [[Kawaiahao Church]], performed the service, a group of beach boys sang Hawaiian songs, including &quot;[[Aloha Oe]]&quot;, and his ashes were scattered into the ocean. 

=== Statues and monuments ===
The City of Honolulu commemorated this Waikiki Beach burial site in 1990 with a 9-foot cast bronze [http://www.publicartinpublicplaces.info/duke-paoa-kahanamoku-1990-by-jan-gordon-fisher statue of Kahanamoku] by Jan Gordon Fisher that shows Kahanamoku with outstretched arms in front of his surfboard and flanked by honorary Hawaiian spears, surrounded by a dedication plaque and historic information marker.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.publicartinpublicplaces.info/duke-paoa-kahanamoku-1990-by-jan-gordon-fisher|title=&quot;Duke Paoa Kahanamoku&quot; (1990) by Jan Gordon Fisher|website=Public Art in Public Places|access-date=November 28, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The statue's orientation that placed Kahanamoku's back to the sea was initially criticized as being contrary to Hawaiian custom.  [[Public Art in Public Places]] claims, however, that its orientation toward the pedestrian activity and public realm on Kalakaua Avenue has created a highly popular local shrine and tourist locale; the statue's outstretched arms are always adorned with fresh leis and the locale receives annual tribute ceremonies and thousands of yearly tourist visits&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.publicartinpublicplaces.info/duke-paoa-kahanamoku-1990-by-jan-gordon-fisher|title=&quot;Duke Paoa Kahanamoku&quot; (1990) by Jan Gordon Fisher|website=Public Art in Public Places|access-date=November 28, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;.  In 1997, the historic public artwork ''The Stones of Life'', containing four ancient basaltic stones or pōhaku (circa 1500), was installed nearby.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.publicartinpublicplaces.info/the-stones-of-life-1997|title=&quot;The Stones of Life&quot; (installed 1997) by Billy Fields|website=Public Art in Public Places|access-date=November 28, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

On February 28, 2015, a monument featuring a replica of Kahanamoku's surfboard was unveiled at New Brighton beach, [[Christchurch]], [[New Zealand]] in honour of the 100th anniversary of Kahanamoku's visit to New Brighton.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.3news.co.nz/sport/new-brighton-honours-surfing-legend-2015022818#axzz3jiVMOu00 New Brighton Honours Surfing Legend] TV3, 2015&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Additional tributes ===
Hawaii music promoter [[Kimo Wilder McVay]] capitalized on Kahanamoku's popularity by naming his Waikiki showroom &quot;Duke Kahanamoku's&quot; at the [[International Market Place]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=The Rise, Fall and Rebirth of Waikīkī's International Market Place |url=http://www.honolulumagazine.com/Honolulu-Magazine/December-2013/The-Rise-Fall-and-Rebirth-of-Waikikis-International-Marketplace/index.php?cparticle=3&amp;siarticle=2#artanc |website=honolulumagazine.com |accessdate=March 17, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; and giving Kahanamoku a financial interest in the showroom in exchange for the use of his name. It was a major Waikiki showroom in the 1960s and is remembered as the home of [[Don Ho]] &amp; The Aliis from 1964 through 1969. The showroom continued to be known as Duke Kahanamoku's until Hawaii showman Jack Cione bought it in the mid-1970s and renamed it Le Boom Boom.

Kahanamoku's name is also used by Duke's Canoe Club &amp; Barefoot Bar, {{as of|2016|lc=y}} known as Duke's Waikiki, a beachfront bar and restaurant in the [[Outrigger Hotels &amp; Resorts|Outrigger]] Waikiki on the Beach Hotel. There is a chain of restaurants named after him in California, Florida and Hawaii called Duke's.

On August 24, 2002, the 112th anniversary of Kahanamoku's birth, the [[U.S. Postal Service]] issued a first-class [[commemorative stamp]] with Duke's picture on it. The First Day Ceremony was held at the Hilton Hawaiian Village in Waikiki and was attended by thousands. At this ceremony, attendees could attach the Duke stamp to an envelope and get it canceled with a First Day of Issue postmark. These [[first day cover]]s are very collectible.&lt;ref&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20060209204134/http://www.usps.com/news/2002/philatelic/sr02_048.htm Father Of International Surfing To Be Honored On New Postage Stamp]. USPS. July 30, 2002&lt;/ref&gt;

On August 24, 2015, a [[Google Doodle]] honored the 125th anniversary of Duke Kahanamoku's birthday.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Plucinska|first1=Joanna|title=New Google Doodle Honors Duke Kahanamoku, the Father of Surfing|url=http://time.com/4007604/duke-kahanamoku/|website=Time Inc.|publisher=Time Inc.|accessdate=August 24, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Filmography==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|- style=&quot;background:#b0c4de; text-align:center;&quot;
! Year
! Title
! Role
! Notes
|-
|rowspan=4|1925
| ''[[Adventure (1925 film)|Adventure]]''
| Noah Noa
|
|-
| ''[[The Pony Express (1925 film)|The Pony Express]]''
| Indian Chief
| Uncredited
|-
| ''[[No Father to Guide Him (short)|No Father to Guide Him]]''
| The Lifeguard
| Short
|-
| ''[[Lord Jim (1925 film)|Lord Jim]]''
| Tamb Itam
|
|-
| 1926
| ''[[Old Ironsides (film)|Old Ironsides]]''
| Pirate Captain
| Uncredited
|-
|rowspan=2|1927
| ''[[Hula (film)|Hula]]''
| Hawaiian Boy
| Uncredited
|-
| ''[[Isle of Sunken Gold]]''
| The Devil-Ape
|
|-
| 1928
| ''[[Woman Wise]]''
| Guard
|
|-
|rowspan=2|1929
| ''[[The Rescue (1929 film)|The Rescue]]''
| Jaffir
|
|-
| ''[[Where East Is East]]''
| Wild Animal Trapper
| Uncredited
|-
|rowspan=2|1930
| ''[[Girl of the Port]]''
| Kalita
|
|-
| ''[[Isle of Escape]]''
| Manua
|
|-
|rowspan=2|1931
| ''[[Around the World with Douglas Fairbanks (documentary)|Around the World with Douglas Fairbanks]]''
| Himself
| Documentary
|-
| ''[[The Black Camel (film)|The Black Camel]]''
| bit part as surf instructor
| at 0:01:36
|-
| 1948
| ''[[Wake of the Red Witch]]''
| Ua Nuke
|
|-
| 1955
| ''[[Mister Roberts (1955 film)|Mister Roberts]]''
| Native Chief
| (as Duke Kahanamoko)
|-
| 1957
| ''[[This Is Your Life]]''
| Himself
| Episode: &quot;Duke Kahanamoku&quot;
|-
|rowspan=2|1967
| ''[[Free and Easy (documentary)|Free and Easy]]''
| Himself
| Documentary
|-
| ''[[Surfari (documentary)|Surfari]]''
| Himself
| Documentary
|-
|colspan=5| Source:&lt;ref&gt;{{IMDb name|0434687}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|}

==See also==
{{Portal|Biography|Olympics}}
* [https://www.google.com/culturalinstitute/beta/u/0/asset/duke-paoa-kahanamoku/EQGOzr_-VCcuFQ Google Arts &amp; Culture - &quot;Duke Paoa Kahanamoku&quot;]
* [https://www.google.com/maps/place/Public+Art+%22Duke+Kahanamoku%22/@21.2755195,-157.8275125,17z/data=!3m1!4b1!4m5!3m4!1s0x7c007276ebe11ae1:0x8c1b0bb567c94087!8m2!3d21.2755195!4d-157.8253238?hl=en Google Maps - Public Art &quot;Duke Kahanamoku&quot;]
* [[Duke Paoa Kahanamoku Lagoon]]
* [[List of multiple Olympic gold medalists]]
* [[List of Olympic medalists in swimming (men)]]
* [[World record progression 100 metres freestyle]]
* [[World record progression 4 × 200 metres freestyle relay]]

== References ==
{{Reflist|30em}}

== Further reading ==
*Kahanamoku, Duke. &quot;Do's and Don't's.&quot; ''[[Photoplay]]'', September 1925. Tie-in to ''[[Adventure (1925 film)|Adventure]]''.
*Paniccia, Patti. &quot;Who Owns the Duke?: The battle for the trademark to Duke Kahanamoku’s name has been far less dignified than the man himself.&quot; ''Honolulu Magazine''. November 1, 2006. http://www.honolulumagazine.com/Honolulu-Magazine/November-2006/Who-Owns-the-Duke/
*{{cite book|last=Davis|first=David|title=Waterman: The Life and Times of Duke Kahanamoku|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=3SdICgAAQBAJ|year=2015|publisher=University of Nebraska Press|location=Lincoln|isbn=978-0-8032-8514-9|oclc=906027798}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Duke Kahanamoku}}
* {{Internet Archive author |sname=Duke Kahanamoku |sopt=t}}
* {{Sports-Reference|ka/duke-kahanamoku-1|archive=20121018044422}}
* {{IOC profile|duke-kahanamoku}}
* [http://www.ishof.org/duke-kahanamoku-(usa).html Duke Kahanamoku (USA)] – Honor Swimmer profile at International Swimming Hall of Fame
* [http://www.surfline.com/surfaz/kahanamoku_duke.cfm Surfline bio of Duke]
* [https://www.flickr.com/photos/library_of_congress/2332829819/ Undated photo of Kahanamoku from the Library of Congress collection]
* [http://www.publicartinpublicplaces.info/duke-paoa-kahanamoku-1990-by-jan-gordon-fisher/ &quot;Duke Paoa Kahanamoku&quot; Statue (1990) by Jan Gordon Fisher] -  [http://www.publicartinpublicplaces.info/ Public Art in Public Places Project]
* {{IMDb name|0434687}}

{{Footer USA Swimming 1912 Summer Olympics}}
{{Footer USA Swimming 1920 Olympics}}
{{Footer USA Swimming 1924 Summer Olympics}}
{{Footer Olympic Champions 100 m Freestyle Men}}
{{Olympic Champions Swimming 4x200 m Men Freestyle Relay}}
{{United States men's water polo squad 1920 Summer Olympics}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Kahanamoku, Duke}}
[[Category:1890 births]]
[[Category:1968 deaths]]
[[Category:Male actors from Hawaii]]
[[Category:American male freestyle swimmers]]
[[Category:American surfers]]
[[Category:American male water polo players]]
[[Category:Burials at sea]]
[[Category:World record setters in swimming]]
[[Category:Hawaiian nobility]]
[[Category:Kamehameha Schools alumni]]
[[Category:Medalists at the 1912 Summer Olympics]]
[[Category:Medalists at the 1920 Summer Olympics]]
[[Category:Medalists at the 1924 Summer Olympics]]
[[Category:Native Hawaiian sportspeople]]
[[Category:Olympic gold medalists for the United States in swimming]]
[[Category:Olympic silver medalists for the United States in swimming]]
[[Category:Olympic swimmers of the United States]]
[[Category:Olympic water polo players of the United States]]
[[Category:Sportspeople from Hawaii]]
[[Category:Swimmers at the 1912 Summer Olympics]]
[[Category:Swimmers at the 1920 Summer Olympics]]
[[Category:Swimmers at the 1924 Summer Olympics]]
[[Category:Water polo players at the 1920 Summer Olympics]]
[[Category:Hawaii sheriffs]]</text>
      <sha1>gjtk3ty0aiylsnijd1nkos5loivo7ul</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
