  <page>
    <title>Damon Runyon</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9128</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943037556</id>
      <parentid>942621900</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-28T12:52:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bluelink 1 book for [[Wikipedia:Verifiability|verifiability]]. [goog]) #IABot (v2.0) ([[User:GreenC bot|GreenC bot]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|American writer}}
{{Infobox writer
| name         = Damon Runyon
| image        = DamonRunyon.jpeg
| imagesize    = 
| caption      = 
| birth_name   = Alfred Damon Runyan
| birth_date   = {{birth date|1880|10|4}}
| birth_place  = [[Manhattan, Kansas]]
| death_date   = {{death date and age|1946|12|10|1880|10|4}} 
| death_place  = New York City
| occupation   = Writer
| nationality  = American
}}
'''Alfred Damon Runyon''' (October 4, 1880&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title = Birth Announcement | publisher = The (Manhattan, Kansas) Nationalist | date = October 7, 1880}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.cityofmhk.com/DocumentCenter/Home/View/1049&lt;/ref&gt; – December 10, 1946) was an American [[newspaperman]] and short-story writer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Detective stories |author= Philip Pullman, Nick Hardcastle|year=1998|publisher=Kingfisher Publications|url=https://books.google.com/?id=6OsgjZkA_pEC&amp;pg=PA96|isbn=0-7534-5636-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

He was best known for his short stories celebrating the world of [[Broadway (Manhattan)|Broadway]] in New York City that grew out of the [[Prohibition in the United States|Prohibition]] era. To New Yorkers of his generation, a &quot;Damon Runyon character&quot; evoked a distinctive social type from the [[Brooklyn]] or [[Midtown Manhattan|Midtown]] [[demi-monde]]. The adjective &quot;Runyonesque&quot; refers to this type of character as well as to the type of situations and dialog that Runyon depicted.&lt;ref&gt;Webber, Elizabeth; Feinsilber, Mike (1999). [https://books.google.com/books?id=ACB81ZeNN5sC&amp;pg=PA479&amp;q=runyonesque Merriam-Webster's dictionary of allusions], page 479–480. {{ISBN|978-0-87779-628-2}}.&lt;/ref&gt; He spun humorous and sentimental tales of gamblers, hustlers, actors, and gangsters, few of whom go by [[square (slang)|&quot;square&quot;]] names, preferring instead colorful monikers such as  &quot;Nathan Detroit&quot;, &quot;Benny Southstreet&quot;, &quot;Big Jule&quot;, &quot;Harry the Horse&quot;, &quot;Good Time Charley&quot;, &quot;Dave the Dude&quot;, or &quot;The Seldom Seen Kid&quot;.  His distinctive vernacular style is known as &quot;Runyonese&quot;: a mixture of formal speech and colorful slang, almost always in present tense, and always devoid of [[Contraction (grammar)|contractions]]. He is credited with coining the phrase &quot;[[Hooray Henry]]&quot;, a term now used in British English to describe an upper-class, loud-mouthed, arrogant twit.

Runyon's fictional world is also known to the general public through the musical ''[[Guys and Dolls (musical)|Guys and Dolls]]'' based on two of his stories, &quot;[[The Idyll of Miss Sarah Brown]]&quot; and &quot;Blood Pressure&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.ebooks-library.com/author.cfm/AuthorID/900 |title = Damon Runyon|work = Authors|publisher = The eBooks-Library|accessdate = 2008-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; The musical additionally borrows characters and story elements from a few other Runyon stories, most notably &quot;Pick The Winner&quot;. The film ''[[Little Miss Marker]]'' (and its three remakes, ''[[Sorrowful Jones]]'', ''[[40 Pounds of Trouble]]'' and the 1980 ''[[Little Miss Marker (1980 film)|Little Miss Marker]]'') grew from his short story of the same name.

Runyon was also a newspaper reporter, covering sports and general news for decades for various publications and syndicates owned by [[William Randolph Hearst]]. Already known for his fiction, he wrote a well-remembered &quot;present tense&quot; article on [[Franklin Delano Roosevelt]]'s Presidential inauguration in 1933 for the Universal Service, a [[Hearst Corporation|Hearst]] syndicate, which was merged with the co-owned [[International News Service]] in 1937.

==Life and work==
[[File:Damon Runyon House 2012-10-16 11-27-19.jpg|thumb|left|250px|Boyhood home of Damon Runyon in Manhattan, Kansas.]]
Damon Runyon was born '''Alfred Damon Runyan''' to Alfred Lee and Elizabeth (Damon) Runyan.&lt;ref&gt;Maxine Block, editor. &quot;Current Biography, 1942 edition&quot;. H.H. Wilson, 1942, p. 723.&lt;/ref&gt; His relatives in his birthplace of [[Manhattan, Kansas]] included several newspapermen.&lt;ref name=house/&gt; His grandfather was a newspaper printer from [[New Jersey]] who had relocated to Manhattan, Kansas in 1855, and his father was editor of his own newspaper in the town. In 1882 Runyon's father was forced to sell his newspaper, and the family moved westward. The family eventually settled in [[Pueblo, Colorado]] in 1887, where Runyon spent the rest of his youth. By most accounts, he attended school only through the fourth grade.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The Press: Hand Me My Kady&quot;. ''Time'' magazine, December 23, 1946, n.p.&lt;/ref&gt; He began to work in the newspaper trade under his father in Pueblo. In present-day Pueblo, Runyon Field, the Damon Runyon Repertory Theater Company, and [[Runyon Lake]] are named in his honor.

In 1898, when still in his teens, Runyon enlisted in the U.S. Army to fight in the [[Spanish–American War]]. While in the service, he was assigned to write for the ''Manila Freedom'' and ''Soldier's Letter''.
[[File:Runyon-Selective-Service-Registration-1918.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Runyon's World War I draft registration (September 1918)]]

After his military service, he worked for Colorado newspapers, beginning in Pueblo. His first job as a reporter was in September 1900, when he was hired by the ''Pueblo Star'';&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The Press: Broadway Columnist&quot;. ''Time'' magazine, September 30, 1940, n.p.&lt;/ref&gt; he then worked in the [[Rocky Mountains|Rocky Mountain]] area during the first decade of the 1900s: at the ''Denver Daily News'', he served as &quot;sporting editor&quot; (what would today be called &quot;sports editor&quot;) and then worked as a staff writer. His expertise was in covering the semi-professional teams in Colorado; he even briefly managed a semi-pro team in Trinidad, Colorado.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;An All-Star Team Picked by A.D. Runyon&quot;. ''Denver Daily News'', September 15, 1907, p. S2.&lt;/ref&gt; At one of the newspapers where he worked, the spelling of his last name was changed from &quot;Runyan&quot; to &quot;Runyon&quot;, a change he let stand.

After failing in an attempt to organize a [[Colorado]] [[minor league baseball|minor baseball league]], which lasted less than a week,&lt;ref&gt;Robert Phipps. &quot;Long Evening Kills League&quot;. ''Omaha World Herald'', December 21, 1946, p. 7&lt;/ref&gt; Runyon moved to New York City in 1910. In his first New York byline, the ''American'' editor dropped the &quot;Alfred&quot; and the name &quot;Damon Runyon&quot; appeared for the first time. For the next ten years he covered the [[New York Giants (NL)|New York Giants]] and professional boxing for the ''[[New York American]]''.

He was the [[Hearst Corporation|Hearst newspapers']] baseball columnist for many years, beginning in 1911, and his knack for spotting the eccentric and the unusual, on the field or in the stands, is credited with revolutionizing the way baseball was covered. Perhaps as confirmation, Runyon was inducted into the writers' wing (the [[J. G. Taylor Spink Award]]) of the [[Baseball Hall of Fame]] in 1967. He is also a member of the [[International Boxing Hall Of Fame]] and is known for dubbing heavyweight champion [[James J. Braddock]], the &quot;[[Cinderella Man]]&quot;. Runyon frequently contributed sports poems to the ''American'' on boxing and baseball themes, and also wrote numerous short stories and essays. 
{{Quote box |width=320px |align=left|quoted=true |bgcolor=#FFFFF0 |salign=right
|quote =&lt;poem&gt;
If I have all the tears that are shed on Broadway by guys in love, I will have enough salt water to start an opposition ocean to the Atlantic and Pacific, with enough left over to run the Great Salt Lake out of business. But I wish to say I never shed any of these tears personally, because I am never in love, and furthermore, barring a bad break, I never expect to be in love, for the way I look at it love is strictly the old phedinkus, and I tell the little guy as much.
&lt;/poem&gt;
|source = from &quot;Tobias the Terrible&quot;,&lt;br&gt; collected in ''More than Somewhat'' (1937)}} 
One year, while covering spring training in [[Texas]], he met [[Pancho Villa]] in a bar and later accompanied the unsuccessful American expedition into [[Mexico]] searching for Villa. It was while he was in Mexico that he met the young girl whom he eventually married.

Gambling, particularly on [[craps]] or horse races, was a common theme of Runyon's works, and he was a notorious gambler himself. One of his paraphrases from a line in [[Ecclesiastes]] ran: &quot;The race is not always to the swift, nor the battle to the strong, but that's how the smart money bets.&quot;

A heavy drinker as a young man, he seems to have quit drinking soon after arriving in New York, after his drinking nearly cost him the courtship of the woman who became his first wife, Ellen Egan. However, he remained a heavy smoker.

His best friend was mobster accountant [[Otto Berman]], and he incorporated Berman into several of his stories under the alias &quot;Regret, the horse player&quot;. When Berman was killed in a hit on Berman's boss, [[Dutch Schultz]], Runyon quickly assumed the role of damage control for his deceased friend, correcting erroneous press releases (including one that stated Berman was one of Schultz's gunmen, to which Runyon replied, &quot;Otto would have been as effective a bodyguard as a two-year-old.&quot;).

[[File:The Family Plot of Damon Runyon in Woodlawn Cemetery.JPG|thumb|The family plot of Damon Runyon in [[Woodlawn Cemetery (Bronx, New York)|Woodlawn Cemetery]]]]
Runyon's marriage to Ellen Egan produced two children (Mary and Damon, Jr.), but broke up in 1928 over rumors that Runyon had become infatuated with Patrice Amati del Grande, a Mexican woman he had first met while covering the Pancho Villa raids in 1916 and discovered once again in New York, when she called the ''American'' seeking him out. Runyon had promised her in Mexico that if she would complete the education he paid for her, he would find her a dancing job in New York. She became his companion after he separated from his wife. After Ellen Runyon's death, Runyon and del Grande married on July 7, 1932;&lt;ref&gt;New York, New York, Marriage Index 1866-1937&lt;/ref&gt; that marriage ended in 1946 when she left him for a younger man.

Runyon died in New York City from [[Esophageal cancer|throat cancer]] in late 1946, at age 66. His body was cremated, and his ashes were illegally scattered from a [[DC-3]] airplane over Broadway in [[Manhattan]] by [[Captain (United States O-3)|Captain]] [[Eddie Rickenbacker]] on December 18, 1946.&lt;ref&gt;''Eddie Rickenbacker: An American Hero in the Twentieth Century'', by W. David Lewis, pg. 506.&lt;/ref&gt; The family plot of Damon Runyon is located at [[Woodlawn Cemetery (Bronx, New York)|Woodlawn Cemetery]] in [[The Bronx]], [[New York (state)|New York]].

==Legacy==
* After Runyon's death, his friend and fellow journalist, [[Walter Winchell]], went on his radio program and appealed for contributions to help fight cancer, eventually establishing the [[Damon Runyon Cancer Research Foundation|Damon Runyon Cancer Memorial Fund]] to support scientific research into causes of, and prevention of, cancer.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.damonrunyon.org Damon Runyon Cancer Research Foundation]&lt;/ref&gt;
* The first-ever [[telethon]] was hosted by [[Milton Berle]] in 1949 to raise funds for the Damon Runyon Cancer Research Foundation.
* Each year the Denver Press Club assigns the Damon Runyon Award to a prominent journalist. Past winners include [[Jimmy Breslin]], [[Mike Royko]], [[George Will]] and [[Bob Costas]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.denverpressclub.org/damon-runyon-award| author=John C. Ensslin| publisher=Denver Press Club| title=Denver Press Club's Damon Runyon Award for contributions in the field of journalism| accessdate=June 22, 2010| archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20101108094329/http://www.denverpressclub.org/damon-runyon-award| archive-date=November 8, 2010| url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Damon Runyon Elementary school in [[Littleton, Colorado]], is named after him.&lt;ref&gt;[http://runyon.littletonpublicschools.net/ Damon Runyon Elementary school]&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[Damon Runyon Stakes]] is a thoroughbred horse race run every December at [[Aqueduct Race Track]]. Runyon loved horse racing and ran a small stable of his own.
* In the mid-1930s, Runyon persuaded promoter [[Leo Seltzer]] to formally change his [[History of roller derby|Roller Derby]] spectacle from a marathon [[roller-skating]] race into a full-contact team sport,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Blood on the Tracks |last=Turczyn |first=Coury |date=January 28, 1999 |work=[[Metro Pulse]] |url=http://www.popcultmag.com/obsessions/fadsandphenoms/rollerderby/derby2.html |accessdate=February 11, 2008 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080228045852/http://www.popcultmag.com/obsessions/fadsandphenoms/rollerderby/derby2.html |archivedate=February 28, 2008 }} (link points to the archived article in the Spring 2000 edition of the author's own ''PopCult Magazine'' website): &quot;The faster skaters would break out and try and get laps so they would get ahead in the race, and some of the slower skaters started to band together to try and hold them back&quot;, says Seltzer. &quot;And at first, they didn’t want to let them do that – but then the people liked it so much, they kind of allowed blocking. Then they came down to Miami – I think it was 1936, early '37 – and Damon Runyon, a very famous sports writer, saw it and he sat down with my father and hammered out the rules, almost exactly as they are today.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; an innovation that was eventually revived in a DIY spirit seven decades later.
* One block of West 45th Street (between 8th and 9th Avenues) in Manhattan's Hell's Kitchen is named Runyon's Way.
* The house in [[Manhattan, Kansas]], where Runyon was born is listed on the [[National Register of Historic Places]].&lt;ref name=house&gt;[http://www.cityofmhk.com/documentview.aspx?DID=1049 Manhattan's historic landmarks &amp; districts: Damon Runyon House] (Kansas State Historical Society National Register of Historic Places – Nomination form), cityofmhk.com. Retrieved March 20, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rileycountyks.gov/FAQ.aspx?QID=313 What buildings in Riley County are on the Historic Register?] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20111014095105/http://rileycountyks.gov/FAQ.aspx?QID=313 |date=2011-10-14 }}. Riley County Official Website, www.rileycountyks.gov. Retrieved March 20, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;
* In 2008, [[The Library of America]] selected &quot;The Eternal Blonde&quot;, Runyon's account of a 1927 murder trial, for inclusion in its two-century retrospective of American Crime Writing.

==Literary style==
[[File:Breach of promise by Nicolas Bentley.png|thumb|An illustration from &quot;Breach of Promise&quot; showing Spanish John and Harry the Horse]]

The English comedy writer [[Frank Muir]] comments&lt;ref&gt;''The Oxford Book of Humorous Prose'' (1990), OUP, p. 621&lt;/ref&gt; that Runyon's plots were, in the manner of [[O. Henry]], neatly constructed with professionally wrought endings, but their distinction lay in the manner of their telling, as the author invented a peculiar argot for his characters to speak.  Runyon almost totally avoids the past tense (English humourist [[E.C. Bentley]] thought there was only one instance, and was willing to &quot;lay plenty of 6 to 5 that it is nothing but a misprint&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;''Runyon on Broadway'', Pan Books, 1975, p. 11&lt;/ref&gt; but &quot;was&quot; appears in the short stories &quot;The Lily of St Pierre&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Broadway, Pan Books 1975, p. 116&quot;&gt;''Runyon on Broadway'', Pan Books, 1975, p. 116&lt;/ref&gt; and &quot;A Piece of Pie&quot;;&lt;ref&gt;''Runyon on Broadway'', Pan Books, 1975, p. 536&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;had&quot; appears in &quot;The Lily of St Pierre&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;Broadway, Pan Books 1975, p. 116&quot;/&gt; &quot;Undertaker Song&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Runyon on Broadway'', Pan Books, 1975, p. 258&lt;/ref&gt; and &quot;Bloodhounds of Broadway&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Runyon on Broadway'', Pan Books, 1975, p. 85&lt;/ref&gt;), and makes little use of the future tense, using the present for both. He also avoided the conditional, using instead the future indicative in situations that would normally require conditional. An example: &quot;Now most any doll on Broadway will be very glad indeed to have Handsome Jack Madigan give her a tumble&quot; (''Guys and Dolls'', &quot;Social error&quot;). [[E. C. Bentley]]&lt;ref&gt;Introduction to ''More Than Somewhat'', included in omnibus volume ''Runyon on Broadway'' (1950), Constable&lt;/ref&gt; comments that &quot;there is a sort of ungrammatical purity about it [Runyon's resolute avoidance of the past tense], an almost religious exactitude.&quot;  There is an homage to Runyon that makes use of this peculiarity (&quot;[[Chronic Offender]]&quot; by [[Spider Robinson]]) which involves a time machine and a man going by the name &quot;Harry the Horse&quot;.

He uses many slang terms (which go unexplained in his stories), such as:

* pineapple = pineapple [[grenade]]
* roscoe/john roscoe/the old equalizer/that thing = gun
* shiv = knife
* noggin = head
* snoot = nose

There are many recurring composite phrases such as:

* ever-loving wife (occasionally &quot;ever-loving doll&quot;)
* more than somewhat (or &quot;no little, and quite some&quot;); this phrase was so typical that it was used as the title of one of his short story collections
* loathe and despise
* one and all

[[E. C. Bentley]] notes&lt;ref&gt;Introduction to ''Furthermore'', included in omnibus volume ''Runyon on Broadway'' (1950), Constable.&lt;/ref&gt; that Runyon's &quot;telling use of the recurrent phrase and fixed epithet&quot; demonstrates a debt to [[Homer]].

Runyon's stories also employ occasional rhyming slang, similar to the [[cockney slang|cockney]] variety but native to New York (e.g.: &quot;Miss Missouri Martin makes the following crack one night to her: 'Well, I do not see any Simple Simon on your lean and linger.' This is Miss Missouri Martin's way of saying she sees no diamond on Miss Billy Perry's finger.&quot; (from &quot;Romance in the Roaring Forties&quot;)).

The comic effect of his style results partly from the juxtaposition of broad slang with mock-pomposity. Women, when not &quot;dolls&quot;, &quot;Judies&quot;, &quot;pancakes&quot;, &quot;tomatoes&quot;, or &quot;broads&quot;, may be &quot;characters of a female nature&quot;, for example. He typically avoided contractions such as &quot;don't&quot; in the example above, which also contributes significantly to the humorously pompous effect. In one sequence, a gangster tells another character to do as he is told, or else &quot;find another world in which to live&quot;.

Runyon's short stories are told in the first person by a protagonist who is never named, and whose role is unclear; he knows many gangsters and does not appear to have a job, but he does not admit to any criminal involvement, and seems to be largely a bystander.  He describes himself as &quot;being known to one and all as a guy who is just around&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;rob&quot;&gt;''Runyon on Broadway'', Pan Books, 1975, p. 12&lt;/ref&gt;  The radio program ''The Damon Runyon Theatre'' dramatized 52 of Runyon's works in 1949, and for these the protagonist was given the name &quot;Broadway&quot;, although it was admitted that this was not his real name, much in the way &quot;Harry the Horse&quot; and &quot;Sorrowful Jones&quot; are aliases.&lt;ref&gt;[https://archive.org/details/OTRR_Damon_Runyon_Singles] Damon Runyon Theater&lt;/ref&gt;

==Literary works==

===Books===
{{col-start}}
{{col-2}}
*''The Tents of Trouble'' (poems; 1911)
*''Rhymes of the Firing Line'' (poems; 1912)
*''Guys and Dolls'' (1932)
*''Damon Runyon's Blue Plate Special'' (1934)
*''Money From Home'' (1935)
*''More Than Somewhat'' (1937)
*''Furthermore'' (1938)
*''Take It Easy'' (1938)
*''My Wife Ethel'' (1939)
*''My Old Man'' (1939)
*''The Best of Runyon'' (1940)
*''A Slight Case of Murder'' (play; with Howard Lindsay, 1940)
*''Damon Runyon Favorites'' (1942)
*''Capt. Eddie Rickenbacker'' (with W. Kiernan, 1942)
*''Runyon à la Carte'' (1944)
*''The Damon Runyon Omnibus'' (1944)
*''[https://www.fadedpage.com/showbook.php?pid=20121228 Short Takes]'' (1946)
{{col-2}}
*''In Our Town'' (1946)
*''The Three Wise Guys and Other Stories'' (1946)
*''Trials and Other Tribulations'' (1947)
*''Poems for Men'' (Poems; 1947)
*''Runyon First and Last'' (1949)
*''Runyon on Broadway'' (1950; introduction by [[E. C. Bentley]]), Constable
*''More Guys and Dolls'' (1950)
*''The Turps'' (1951)
*''Damon Runyon from First to Last'' (1954), Constable
*''A Treasury of Damon Runyon'' (1958)
*''The Bloodhounds of Broadway and Other Stories'' (1985)
*''Romance in the Roaring Forties and other stories'' (1986)
*''On Broadway (1990)
*''Guys, Dolls, and Curveballs: Damon Runyon on Baseball'' (2005; Jim Reisler, editor)
*''Guys and Dolls and Other Writings'' (2008; introduction by Pete Hamill)
*''A Dangerous Guy Indeed'' (unknown)
{{col-end}}

===Stories===
There are many collections of Runyon's stories: in particular ''Runyon on Broadway'' and ''Runyon from First to Last'' between them provide extensive coverage.  The latter is claimed to contain&lt;ref&gt;Publisher's Note included in ''Runyon from First to Last'' (1954), Constable&lt;/ref&gt; all of Runyon's stories (i.e. fiction) not included in ''Runyon on Broadway''.  In fact, there are two Broadway stories originally published in ''Collier's Weekly'' but not included in either collection: &quot;Maybe a Queen&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Collier's Weekly'', December 12, 1931: https://www.unz.org/Pub/Colliers-1931dec12&lt;/ref&gt; and &quot;Leopard's Spots&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;''Collier's Weekly'', May 6, 1939: https://www.unz.org/Pub/Colliers-1939may06&lt;/ref&gt; both collected in ''More Guys And Dolls'' (1950).

''Runyon on Broadway'' contains the following stories, all of which are Broadway stories written in Runyonese:
{{col-start}}
{{col-3}}
'''More Than Somewhat'''
*Breach of Promise
*Romance in the Roaring Forties
*Dream Street Rose
*The Old Doll's House
*Blood Pressure
*The Bloodhounds of Broadway
*Tobias the Terrible
*The Snatching of Bookie Bob
*The Lily of St. Pierre
*Hold 'em, Yale
*Earthquake
*'Gentlemen, the King!'
*A Nice Price
*Broadway Financier
*The Brain Goes Home
{{col-3}}
'''Furthermore'''
*Madame La Gimp
*Dancing Dan's Christmas
*Sense of Humour
*Lillian
*Little Miss Marker
*Pick the Winner
*Undertaker Song
*Butch Minds the Baby
*The Hottest Guy in the World
*The Lemon Drop Kid
*What, No Butler?
*The Three Wise Guys
*A Very Honourable Guy
*Princess O'Hara
*Social Error
{{col-3}}
'''Take It Easy'''
*Tight Shoes
*Lonely Heart
*The Brakeman's Daughter
*Cemetery Bait
*It Comes Up Mud
*The Big Umbrella
*For a Pal
*Big Shoulders
*That Ever-Loving Wife of Hymie's
*Neat Strip
*Bred for Battle
*Too Much Pep
*Baseball Hattie
*Situation Wanted
*A Piece of Pie
*A Job for the Macarone
*All Horse Players Die Broke
{{col-end}}
 
''Runyon from First to Last'' includes the following stories and sketches:
{{col-start}}
{{col-3}}
'''The First Stories'''	(early non-Broadway stories):
*The Defence of Strikerville
*Fat Fallon
*Two Men Named Collins. First published in Reader Magazine, [Date Unknown]
*As Between Friends
*The Informal Execution of Soupbone Pew
*My Father
'''Stories à la Carte''' (Broadway stories written in Runyonese):
*Money from Home
*A Story Goes With It
*Broadway Complex
*So You Won't Talk!
{{col-3}}
*Dark Dolores
*Delegates at Large
*A Light in France
*Old Em's Kentucky Home
*Johnny One-Eye
*Broadway Incident
*The Idyll of Miss Sarah Brown
*The Melancholy Dane
*Barbecue
*Little Pinks
*Palm Beach Santa Claus
*Cleo
*The Lacework Kid
{{col-3}}
'''The Last Stories''' (Broadway stories written in Runyonese):
*Blonde Mink
*Big Boy Blues
'''Written in Sickness''' (sketches):
*Why Me?
*The Doctor Knows Best
*No Life
*Good Night
*Bed-Warmers
*Sweet Dreams
*Passing the Word Along
*Death Pays a Social Call
  
{{col-end}}

===Uncollected Stories===
*''The Art of High Grading''. Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, 2 January 1910
*''The Sucker''. San Francisco Examiner, 10 July 1910

===Film===
[[File:Lady-for-a-Day-William-Robson.jpg|thumb|Dave the Dude ([[Warren William]]) and Apple Annie ([[May Robson]]) in ''[[Lady for a Day]]'' (1933)]]
Twenty of his stories became motion pictures.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Essay and Annotations&quot; by Daniel R. Schwarz, ''Guys and Dolls and Other Writings'', 2008. Penguin Classics, UK. p. 616.&lt;/ref&gt;
*''[[Lady for a Day]]'' (1933) &amp;ndash; Adapted by [[Robert Riskin]], who suggested the name change from Runyon's title &quot;Madame La Gimp&quot;, the film garnered Academy Award nominations for Best Picture, Best Director ([[Frank Capra]]), Best Actress ([[May Robson]]), and Best Adaptation for the Screen (Riskin). It was remade as ''[[Pocketful of Miracles]]'' in 1961, with [[Bette Davis]] in the Apple Annie role (fused with the &quot;raggedy doll&quot; from Runyon's short story &quot;The Brain Goes Home&quot;); [[Frank Sinatra]] recorded the upbeat title song (his rendition is not used in the film). The film received Oscar nominations for composers [[Sammy Cahn]] and [[Jimmy Van Heusen]] and for co-star [[Peter Falk]] (Best Supporting Actor). In 1989, [[Jackie Chan]] adapted the story yet again for the Hong Kong action film ''[[Miracles (1989 film)|Miracles]]'', adding several of his trademark stunt sequences.
*''[[Little Miss Marker]]'' (1934) &amp;ndash; The film that made [[Shirley Temple]] a star, launched her career, and pushed her past [[Greta Garbo]] as the nation's biggest film draw of the year. Also starred [[Charles Bickford]]. Subsequent remakes include ''[[Sorrowful Jones]]'' (1949) with [[Bob Hope]] and [[Lucille Ball]]; ''[[40 Pounds of Trouble]]'' (1962) with [[Tony Curtis]], and ''[[Little Miss Marker (1980 film)|Little Miss Marker]]'' (1980) with [[Walter Matthau]], [[Julie Andrews]], [[Bob Newhart]] and Curtis.
*''[[The Lemon Drop Kid (1934 film)|The Lemon Drop Kid]]'' (1934) &amp;ndash; Starring [[Lee Tracy]], [[The Lemon Drop Kid|remade in 1951]] with Bob Hope (and ''[[I Love Lucy]]'' co-star [[William Frawley]] appearing in both adaptations); the latter version introduced the Christmas song &quot;[[Silver Bells]]&quot;.
*''Princess O'Hara'' (1935) &amp;ndash; Starring [[Jean Parker]], remade in 1943 as ''[[It Ain't Hay]]'' with [[Abbott and Costello]] and Patsy O'Connor
*''[[Professional Soldier (film)|Professional Soldier]]'' (1935) – an adventure story starring [[Victor McLaglen]] and [[Freddie Bartholomew]]
*''[[A Slight Case of Murder]]'' (1938) with [[Edward G. Robinson]] &amp;ndash; remade in 1953 as ''[[Stop, You're Killing Me]]'' with [[Broderick Crawford]] and [[Claire Trevor]]
*''[[The Big Street]]'' (1942) &amp;ndash; [[Henry Fonda]], Lucille Ball (adapted from Runyon's story &quot;Little Pinks&quot;)
*''Butch Minds the Baby'' (1942) &amp;ndash; Broderick Crawford, [[Shemp Howard]]
*''[[Johnny One-Eye]]'' – (1950) Starring [[Pat O'Brien (actor)|Pat O'Brien]], Wayne Morris, Delores Moran, and Gayle Reed
*''[[Money from Home]]'' (1953)  – Starring [[Dean Martin]] and [[Jerry Lewis]]
*''[[Guys and Dolls (film)|Guys and Dolls]]'' (1955)  – [[Marlon Brando]], [[Jean Simmons]], [[Frank Sinatra]], [[Vivian Blaine]], and [[Stubby Kaye]]. Blaine and Kaye reprised their roles from the 1950 Broadway production. Adapted from the story &quot;The Idyll of Miss Sarah Brown&quot;. The big [[craps]] game is adapted from the story &quot;Blood Pressure&quot;.
*''[[Bloodhounds of Broadway (1989 film)|Bloodhounds of Broadway]]'' (1989) – [[Ensemble cast]] starring [[Matt Dillon]], [[Jennifer Grey]], [[Madonna (entertainer)|Madonna]], and [[Julie Hagerty]], among others. The film combines elements from four stories into one large one: &quot;A Very Honorable  Guy&quot;, &quot;The Brain Goes Home&quot;, &quot;Social Error&quot;, and &quot;The Bloodhounds of Broadway&quot;.

In 1938, his unproduced play ''Saratoga Chips'' became the basis of [[The Ritz Brothers]] film ''[[Straight, Place and Show]]''.

===Plays and Musicals===
*''[[A Slight Case of Murder]]'' (1935) co-written for Broadway with [[Howard Lindsay]]&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Essay and Annotations&quot; by Daniel R. Schwartz, ''Guys and Dolls and Other Writings'', 2008. Penguin Classics, UK. p. 625.&lt;/ref&gt;
*''[[Guys and Dolls]]'' (1950) starring [[Robert Alda]] (Sky Masterson), [[Vivian Blaine]] (Miss Adelaide), [[Sam Levene]] (Nathan Detroit), [[Isabel Bigley]] (Sarah Brown), Pat Rooney, Sr., [[B.S. Pully]], [[Stubby Kaye]], Johnny Silver, [[Tom Pedi]]. Adapted from Runyon's stories &quot;The Idyll of Miss Sarah Brown&quot; and &quot;Blood Pressure&quot;.

===Radio===
''The Damon Runyon Theater'' radio series dramatized 52 of Runyon's short stories in weekly broadcasts running from October 1948 to September 1949 (with reruns until 1951).&lt;ref name=digideli&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.digitaldeliftp.com/DigitalDeliToo/dd2jb-Damon-Runyon-Theatre.html |title=The Damon Runyon Theatre |publisher=The Digital Deli Too |accessdate=March 9, 2012 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120127043041/http://www.digitaldeliftp.com/DigitalDeliToo/dd2jb-Damon-Runyon-Theatre.html |archivedate=January 27, 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Goldin, David J. (2012). [http://radiogoldindex.com/cgi-local/p2.cgi?ProgramName=The+Damon+Runyon+Theatre &quot;The Damon Runyon Theatre&quot;], radioGOLDINdex database. Retrieved March 9, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; The series was produced by [[Alan Ladd]]'s Mayfair Transcription Company for syndication to local radio stations. [[John Brown (actor)|John Brown]] played the character &quot;Broadway&quot;, who doubled as host and narrator. The cast also comprised [[Alan Reed]], [[Luis Van Rooten]], Joseph Du Val, [[Gerald Mohr]], [[Frank Lovejoy]], [[Herb Vigran]], [[Sheldon Leonard]], [[William Conrad]], [[Jeff Chandler (actor)|Jeff Chandler]], [[Lionel Stander]], [[Sidney Miller (actor)|Sidney Miller]], [[Olive Deering]] and [[Joe De Santis]]. [[Pat O'Brien (actor)|Pat O'Brien]] was initially engaged for the role of &quot;Broadway&quot;. The original stories were adapted for the radio by [[Russell S. Hughes|Russell Hughes]].

&quot;Broadway's New York had a crisis each week, though the streets had a rose-tinged aura&quot;, wrote radio historian [[John Dunning (detective fiction author)|John Dunning]]. &quot;The sad shows then were all the sadder; plays like ''For a Pal'' had a special poignance. The bulk of Runyon's work had been untapped by radio, and the well was deep.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Dunning&quot;&gt;{{cite book |url= https://archive.org/details/onairencyclop00dunn |url-access= registration |quote= The Damon Runyon Theater, dramatic anthology. |last=Dunning |first=John |authorlink=John Dunning (detective fiction author) |title=On the Air: The Encyclopedia of Old-Time Radio |date=1998 |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=New York, NY |isbn=978-0-19-507678-3 |page=[https://archive.org/details/onairencyclop00dunn/page/189 189] |edition=Hardcover; revised edition of ''Tune in Yesterday'' (1976) |accessdate=2019-10-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Rp|189|date=May 2013}}

===Television===
''[[Damon Runyon Theater|Damon Runyon Theatre]]'' aired on [[CBS|CBS-TV]] from [[1955–56 United States network television schedule|1955 to 1956]].

[[Mike McShane]] told Runyon stories as monologues on British TV in 1994, and an accompanying book was released, both called ''Broadway Stories''.

== See also ==
* {{Portal-inline|Biography}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
{{external media | width = 210px | align = right | headerimage= | video1 = [https://www.c-span.org/video/?23574-1/damon-runyon-life ''Booknotes'' interview (December 29, 1991) with Jimmy Breslin on his book, ''Damon Runyon: A Life''], [[C-SPAN]]}}
* Breslin, Jimmy (1991). ''Damon Runyon: A Life''. London: Houghton Mifflin. {{ISBN|978-0-89919-984-9}}
* Clark, Tom (1978). ''The World of Damon Runyon''. New York: Harper &amp; Row. {{ISBN|978-0-06-010771-0}}
* D'Itri, Patricia Ward (1982). ''Damon Runyon''. Boston: Twayne. {{ISBN|978-0-8057-7336-1}}
* Hoyt, Edwin P (1964). ''A Gentleman of Broadway: The Story of Damon Runyon''. Boston: Little Brown. {{ISBN|978-1-199-45217-7}}
* Mosedale, John (1981). ''The Men Who Invented Broadway: Damon Runyon, Walter Winchell &amp; Their World''. New York: Richard Marek Publishers. {{ISBN|978-0-399-90085-3}}
* Runyon, Damon Jr (1953). ''Father's Footsteps: The Story of Damon Runyon by his Son''. New York: Random House
* Schwarz, Daniel R (2003). ''Broadway Boogie Woogie: Damon Runyon and the Making of New York City Culture''. New York: Palgrave MacMillan. {{ISBN|978-0-312-23948-0}}
* Wagner, Jean (1965). ''Runyonese: The Mind and Craft of Damon Runyon''. Paris: Stechert-Hafner. {{ASIN|B0007ILK4K}}
* Weiner, Ed (1948). '' The Damon Runyon Story''. New York: Longmans Green. {{ASIN|B0007DPA5U}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Damon Runyon}}
{{wikiquote}}
* {{FadedPage|id=Runyon, Damon|name=Damon Runyon|author=yes}}
* {{Internet Archive author |sname=Damon Runyon}}
* [http://baseballhall.org/discover/awards/j-g-taylor-spink/damon-runyon Baseball Hall of Fame]
* [http://gutenberg.net.au/ebooks11/1100651h.html All the stories from: More than Somewhat, Furthermore, &amp; Take it Easy] at [[Project Gutenberg Australia]]
* [http://gutenberg.net.au/ebooks06/0606431.txt Text of story &quot;The Informal Execution of Soupbone Pew&quot;] at [[Project Gutenberg Australia]]
* [https://archive.org/details/DamonRunyonTheater ''The Damon Runyon Theatre'' – audio files of the complete series] at the [[Internet Archive]]
* {{IMDb name|0750357}}
* {{IBDB name}}
* [http://www.damonrunyon.org ''Damon Runyon Cancer Research Foundation and Broadway Theater Service]

{{1968 Baseball HOF}}
{{J. G. Taylor Spink Award}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Runyon, Damon}}
[[Category:1880 births]]
[[Category:1946 deaths]]
[[Category:American male journalists]]
[[Category:American military personnel of the Spanish–American War]]
[[Category:American short story writers]]
[[Category:American sportswriters]]
[[Category:Burials at Woodlawn Cemetery (Bronx)]]
[[Category:Deaths from cancer in New York (state)]]
[[Category:Deaths from esophageal cancer]]
[[Category:J. G. Taylor Spink Award recipients]]
[[Category:American male short story writers]]
[[Category:People from Pueblo, Colorado]]
[[Category:Writers from Manhattan, Kansas]]</text>
      <sha1>fnkghkxmox5t16xqx9b2joagi5wf0ls</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
