  <page>
    <title>Central Pacific Railroad</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7734</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942898621</id>
      <parentid>942898608</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-27T15:37:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ClueBot NG</username>
        <id>13286072</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverting possible vandalism by [[Special:Contribs/Safdcodskaiofjeisofji|Safdcodskaiofjeisofji]] to version by InternetArchiveBot. [[WP:CBFP|Report False Positive?]] Thanks, [[WP:CBNG|ClueBot NG]]. (3703574) (Bot)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{See also|First Transcontinental Railroad}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=September 2019}}
{{Infobox rail
|railroad_name     = Central Pacific Railroad
|logo              = [[File:Central pacific railroad logo.png|250px]]
|logo_size         = 
|logo_alt          =
|system_map        = 
|map_caption       = 
|map_size          = 
|map_alt           =
|image             = 
|image_size        = 
|image_caption     = 
|image_alt         =
|marks             = 
|locale            = [[Sacramento, CA]]-[[Ogden, Utah]]
|start_year        = June 28, 1861
|end_year          = April 1, 1885, but continued as an [[Southern Pacific Transportation Company|SP]] leased line until June 30, 1959
|predecessor_line  = 
|successor_line    = [[Southern Pacific Transportation Company|Southern Pacific]] 
|gauge             = {{Track gauge|Standard gauge}} → 1 &lt;!-- This needs to be able to handle two current gauges. --&gt;
|old_gauge         = &lt;!-- This needs a separate line --&gt;
|electrification   = 
|length            = 
|hq_city           = [[Sacramento, CA]]; San Francisco, California
|website           = &lt;!-- {{URL|example.com}} --&gt;
}}

[[File:Transcontinental railroad route.png|thumb|left|Route of the [[First Transcontinental Railroad|first American transcontinental railroad]]: The Central Pacific (red) and the [[Union Pacific Railroad|Union Pacific]] (blue) railroads met in Utah in 1869. ]]

[[File:Uploco.jpg|thumb|The ''[[Gov. Stanford]]'' locomotive]]
[[File:Truckee River at Verdi, east of the Sierra Nevada mountains, Nevada, Central Pacific R.R, by Thomas Houseworth &amp; Co..jpg|thumb|The [[Truckee River]] at [[Verdi, Nevada]]. When the Central Pacific Railroad reached its site in 1868, [[Charles Crocker]] pulled a slip of paper from a hat and read the name of [[Giuseppe Verdi]]; so, the town was named after the Italian opera composer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.verdihistory.org/ |title=A Brief History of Verdi |publisher=Verdihistory.org |accessdate=17 January 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
[[File:Trestle CPRR.jpg|thumb|Chinese workers complete a building near the [[Secret Town, California|Secret Town]] Trestle, [[Placer County, California]], c.1869. Photo: [[Carleton Watkins]] ]]
[[File:The Last Spike 1869.jpg|thumb|''The Last Spike,'' by [[Thomas Hill (painter)|Thomas Hill]], (1881)]]

The '''Central Pacific Railroad''' ('''CPRR''') was a rail company chartered by [[Pacific Railroad Acts|U.S. Congress in 1862]] to build a railroad eastwards from [[Sacramento, California]], to complete the western part of the &quot;[[First Transcontinental Railroad]]&quot; in North America.  Incorporated in 1861, CPRR ceased operation in 1885 when it was acquired by [[Southern Pacific Railroad]] as a leased line.

Following the completion of the [[Pacific Railroad Surveys]] in 1855, several national proposals to build a transcontinental railroad failed because of the energy consumed by political disputes over [[slavery]]. With the [[secession]] of [[Southern United States|the South]] in 1861, the modernizers in the [[Republican Party (US)|Republican Party]] controlled the [[US Congress]]. They passed [[Pacific Railroad Acts|legislation in 1862]] authorizing the central rail route with financing in the form of land grants and government railroad bond, which were all eventually repaid with interest.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Daggett|first=Stuart|title=Railroad Reorganization|year=1908|publisher=Harvard University Press|url=http://cprr.org/Museum/RR_Reorganization_1908.pdf|accessdate=December 13, 2011|page=256|chapter=Union Pacific|volume=4}}&lt;/ref&gt; The government and the railroads both shared in the increased value of the land grants, which the railroads developed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite court|litigants=Leo Sheep Co. v. United States|vol=440|reporter=U.S.|opinion=668|court-U.S. Supreme Court|year=1979|url=http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/scripts/getcase.pl?court=US&amp;vol=440&amp;page=668}}&lt;/ref&gt; The construction of the railroad also secured for the government the economical &quot;safe and speedy transportation of the mails, troops, munitions of war, and public stores.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=CPRR.org |url=http://cprr.org/Museum/Pacific_Railroad_Acts.html#1862-03 |title=Pacific Railroad Act of 1862, §2 |publisher=Cprr.org |date=September 24, 2009 |accessdate=17 January 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Authorization and construction==
Planned by [[Theodore Judah]], the Central Pacific Railroad was [[Pacific Railroad Acts|authorized by Congress]] in 1862. It was incorporated in 1861 by Judah and &quot;[[The Big Four (Central Pacific Railroad)|The Big Four]]&quot; (who called themselves &quot;The Associates&quot;): [[Sacramento, California]] businessmen [[Leland Stanford]], [[Collis Huntington]], [[Charles Crocker]], and [[Mark Hopkins (railroad)|Mark Hopkins]]. Stanford was elected president (at the same time he was elected [[Governor of California|governor]]), Huntington vice-president in charge of fund raising and purchasing, and Hopkins treasurer. Crocker was in charge of construction, which began officially in 1863 when the first rails were laid in Sacramento. Construction proceeded in earnest in 1865 when James Harvey Strobridge, the head of the construction work force, hired the first [[Cantonese people|Cantonese]] emigrant workers at Crocker's suggestion. The construction crew grew to include 12,000 Chinese laborers by 1868, when they constituted eighty percent of the entire work force.&lt;ref name=&quot;Workers of the Central Pacific Railroad&quot;&gt;[https://www.pbs.org/wgbh/americanexperience/features/general-article/tcrr-cprr/ Workers of the Central Pacific Railroad], PBS: The American Experience.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;George Kraus, &quot;Chinese Laborers and the Construction of the Central Pacific,&quot; ''Utah Historical Quarterly'', vol. 37, no. 1 (Winter 1969), pp. 41–57.&lt;/ref&gt; The &quot;[[Golden spike]]&quot;, connecting the western railroad to the [[Union Pacific Railroad]] at [[Promontory, Utah]], was hammered on May 10, 1869.&lt;ref name=&quot;WDL&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.wdl.org/en/item/11371/ |title = Ceremony at &quot;Wedding of the Rails,&quot; May 10, 1869 at Promontory Point, Utah |website = [[World Digital Library]] |date = May 10, 1869 |accessdate = 20 July 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Coast-to-coast train travel in eight days became possible, replacing months-long sea voyages and lengthy, hazardous travel by wagon trains.

In 1885 the Central Pacific Railroad was acquired by the [[Southern Pacific Transportation Company|Southern Pacific Company]] as a leased line. Technically the CPRR remained a corporate entity until 1959, when it was formally merged into Southern Pacific. (It was reorganized in 1899 as the Central Pacific &quot;Railway&quot;.) The original right-of-way is now controlled by the [[Union Pacific Railroad|Union Pacific]], which bought Southern Pacific in 1996.

The Union Pacific-Central Pacific (Southern Pacific) main line followed the historic [[Overland Trail|Overland Route]] from [[Omaha, Nebraska]] to [[San Francisco Bay]].

Chinese labor was the most vital source for constructing the railroad. Fifty Cantonese emigrant workers were hired by the Central Pacific Railroad in February 1865 on a trial basis, and soon more and more Cantonese emigrants were hired. Working conditions were harsh, and Chinese were compensated less than their white counterparts. Chinese laborers were paid thirty-one dollars each month, and while white workers were paid the same, they were also given room and board.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Takaki|first1=Ronald|title=A History of Asian Americans: Strangers From A Different Shore|date=1989|publisher=Little, Brown and Company|location=New York, NY|isbn=978-0-316-83130-7|pages=84–86|edition=Second}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Financing==
[[File:Central Pacific Railroad First Mortgage Bonds Advertisement 1867.jpg|thumb|right|Advertisement for CPRR First Mortgage Bonds (1867)]]Construction of the road was financed primarily by 30-year, 6% [[United States Treasury security|U.S. government bonds]] authorized by Sec. 5 of the [[Pacific Railway Acts|Pacific Railroad Act of 1862]]. They were issued at the rate of $16,000 ($265,000 in 2017 dollars) per mile of tracked grade completed west of the designated base of the [[Sierra Nevada (U.S.)|Sierra Nevada]] range near Roseville, CA where California state geologist Josiah Whitney had determined were the geologic start of the Sierras' foothills.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=CPRR.org |url=http://www.cprr.org/Museum/Pacific_Railroad_Acts.html#1862-05 |title=Pacific Railroad Act of 1862 §5 |publisher=Cprr.org |date=September 24, 2009 |accessdate=17 January 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sec. 11 of the Act also provided that the issuance of bonds &quot;shall be treble the number per mile&quot; (to $48,000) for tracked grade completed over and within the two mountain ranges (but limited to a total of {{convert|300|mi|km}} at this rate), and &quot;doubled&quot; (to $32,000) per mile of completed grade laid between the two mountain ranges.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=CPRR.org |url=http://www.cprr.org/Museum/Pacific_Railroad_Acts.html#1862-11 |title=Pacific Railroad Act of 1862 §11 |publisher=Cprr.org |date=September 24, 2009 |accessdate=17 January 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; The U.S. Government Bonds, which constituted a lien upon the railroads and all their fixtures, were repaid in full (and with interest) by the company as and when they became due.

Sec. 10 of the 1864 amending Pacific Railroad Act (13 Statutes at Large, 356) additionally authorized the company to issue its own &quot;First Mortgage Bonds&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=CPRR.org |url=http://cprr.org/Museum/Bond_Adv_CPRR_1867.html |title=FIRST MORTGAGE BONDS OF THE CENTRAL PACIFIC RAILROAD, Business Prospects and Operations of the Company, 1867 |publisher=Cprr.org |accessdate=17 January 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; in total amounts up to (but not exceeding) that of the bonds issued by the United States. Such company-issued securities had priority over the original Government Bonds.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=CPRR.org |url=http://www.cprr.org/Museum/Pacific_Railroad_Acts.html#1864-10 |title=Pacific Railroad Act of 1864 §10 |publisher=Cprr.org |date=September 24, 2009 |accessdate=17 January 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; (Local and state governments also aided the financing, although the City and County of San Francisco did not do so willingly. This materially slowed early construction efforts.) Sec. 3 of the 1862 Act granted the railroads {{convert|10|sqmi|km2|0}} of public land for every mile laid, except where railroads ran through cities and crossed rivers. This grant was apportioned in 5 sections on alternating sides of the railroad, with each section measuring {{convert|0.2|mi|m}} by {{convert|10|mi|km}}.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=CPRR.org |url=http://www.cprr.org/Museum/Pacific_Railroad_Acts.html#1862-03 |title=Pacific Railroad Act of 1862 §3 |publisher=Cprr.org |date=September 24, 2009 |accessdate=17 January 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; These grants were later doubled to {{convert|20|sqmi|km2|0}} per mile of grade by the 1864 Act.

Although the Pacific Railroad eventually benefited the Bay Area, the City and County of San Francisco obstructed financing it during the early years of 1863–1865. When Stanford was Governor of California, the Legislature passed on April 22, 1863, &quot;An Act to Authorize the Board of Supervisors of the City and County of San Francisco to take and subscribe One Million Dollars to the Capital Stock of the Western Pacific Rail Road Company and the Central Pacific Rail Road Company of California and to provide for the payment of the same and other matters relating thereto&quot; (which was later amended by Section Five of the &quot;Compromise Act&quot; of April 4, 1864). On May 19, 1863, the electors of the City and County of San Francisco passed this bond by a vote of 6,329 to 3,116, in a highly controversial Special Election.

[[File:San Francisco Pacific Railroad Bond WPRR 1865.jpg|thumb|left|An 1865 San Francisco '''Pacific Railroad Bond''' approved in 1863 but delayed for two years by the opposition of the San Francisco Board of Supervisors]]
The City and County's financing of the investment through the issuance and delivery of Bonds was delayed for two years, when Mayor [[Henry P. Coon]], and the County Clerk, Wilhelm Loewy, each refused to countersign the Bonds. It took legal actions to force them to do so: in 1864 the Supreme Court of the State of California ordered them under Writs of [[Mandamus]] (''The People of the State of California ''ex rel'' the Central Pacific Railroad Company vs. Henry P. Coon, Mayor; Henry M. Hale, Auditor; and Joseph S. Paxson, Treasurer, of the City and County of San Francisco.'' 25 Cal. 635) and in 1865, a legal judgment against Loewy (''The People ''ex rel'' The Central Pacific Railroad Company of California vs. The Board of Supervisors of the City and County of San Francisco, and Wilhelm Lowey, Clerk'' 27 Cal. 655) directing that the Bonds be countersigned and delivered.

In 1863 the State legislature's forcing of City and County action became known as the &quot;Dutch Flat Swindle&quot;. Critics claimed the CPRR's Big Four intended to build a railroad only as far as [[Dutch Flat, California]], to connect to the Dutch Flat-Donner Pass Wagon Road to monopolize the lucrative mining traffic, and not push the track east of Dutch Flat into the more challenging and expensive High Sierra effort.  CPRR's chief engineer, Theodore Judah, also argued against such a road and hence against the Big Four, fearing that its construction would siphon money from CPRR's paramount trans-Sierra railroad effort. Despite Judah's strong objection, the Big Four incorporated in August 1863 the Dutch Flat-Donner Lake Wagon Road Company. Frustrated, Judah headed off for New York via Panama to raise funds to buy out the Big Four from CPRR and build his trans-Sierra railroad.  Unfortunately, Judah contracted yellow fever in Panama and died in New York in November 1863.&lt;ref name=&quot;SierraSun2004&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last1=McLaughlin |first1=Mark |title=The Big Four and the ‘Dutch Flat swindle’ |url=https://www.sierrasun.com/news/the-big-four-and-the-dutch-flat-swindle/ |website=Sierra Sun: Serving Truckee, Tahoe City, Kings Beach and Incline Village |accessdate=April 28, 2019 |date=July 28, 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Museums and archives==
[[Image:Lmc tdj.jpg|thumb|right|CPRR Original Chief Assistant Engineer L.M. Clement&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cprr.org/Museum/Lewis_Metzler_Clement.html|title=Lewis Metzler Clement, Central Pacific Railroad Pioneer|website=cprr.org|accessdate=April 7, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; (''l'') &amp; Chief Engineer T.D. Judah (''r'')]]

A replica of the [[Sacramento, California]] Central Pacific Railroad passenger station is part of the [[California State Railroad Museum]], located in the [[Old Sacramento State Historic Park]].

Nearly all the company's early correspondence is preserved at [[Syracuse University]], as part of the Collis Huntington Papers collection. It has been released on microfilm (133 reels). The following libraries have the microfilm: [[University of Arizona]] at Tucson; and [[Virginia Commonwealth University]] at Richmond. Additional collections of manuscript letters are held at Stanford University and the [[Mariners' Museum]] at [[Newport News, Virginia]]. [[Alfred A. Hart]] was the official photographer of the CPRR construction.

==Locomotives==
[[File:CPRR Locomotive -113 FALCON 1869.jpg|thumb|CPRR#113 ''FALCON'', a Danforth 4-4-0, at Argenta, Nevada, March 1, 1869 (Photo: J.B. Silvis)]]

The Central Pacific's first three locomotives were of the then common [[4-4-0]] type, although with the [[American Civil War]] raging in the east, they had difficulty acquiring engines from eastern builders, who at times only had smaller [[4-2-4T|4-2-4]] or [[4-2-2]] types available. Until the completion of the [[First Transcontinental Railroad|Transcontinental rail link]] and the railroad's opening of its own shops, all locomotives had to be purchased by builders in the northeastern U.S. The engines had to be dismantled, loaded on a ship, which would embark on a four-month journey that went around [[Cape Horn|South America's Cape Horn]] until arriving in Sacramento where the locomotives would be unloaded, re-assembled, and placed in service.

Locomotives at the time came from many manufacturers, such as [[Cooke Locomotive and Machine Works|Cooke]], [[Schenectady Locomotive Works|Schenectady]], Mason, Rogers, Danforth, Norris, Booth, and McKay &amp; Aldus, among others. The railroad had been on rather unfriendly terms with the [[Baldwin Locomotive Works]], one of the more well-known firms. It is not clear as to the cause of this dispute, though some attribute it to the builder insisting on cash payment (though this has yet to be verified). Consequently, the railroad refused to buy engines from Baldwin, and three former [[Western Pacific Railroad (1862–1870)|Western Pacific Railroad]] (which the CP had absorbed in 1870) engines were the only Baldwin engines owned by the Central Pacific. The Central Pacific's dispute with Baldwin remained unresolved until well after the road had been acquired by the Southern Pacific.

In the 1870s, the road opened up its own locomotive construction facilities in Sacramento. [[Central Pacific 173|Central Pacific's 173]] was rebuilt by these shops and served as the basis for CP's engine construction. The locomotives built before the 1870s were given names as well as numbers. By the 1870s, it was decided to eliminate the names and as each engine was sent to the shops for service, their names would be removed. However, one engine that was built in the 1880s did receive a name: the [[El Gobernador]].

Construction of the rails was often dangerous work. Towards the end of construction, almost all workers were [[Chinese Railroad Workers|Chinese immigrants]]. The ethnicity of workers depended largely on the &quot;gang&quot; of workers/specific area on the rails they were working.

==Preserved locomotives==
{{see also|List of preserved Southern Pacific Railroad rolling stock}}

The following CP engines have been preserved:
* [[Gov. Stanford|Central Pacific 1, ''Gov. Stanford'']]
* CP 233, a [[2-6-2T]] the railroad had built, is stored at the [[California State Railroad Museum]].
* [[C. P. Huntington|Central Pacific 3, ''C. P. Huntington'']], later purchased by the [[Southern Pacific Transportation Company]].
* [[Stockton Terminal and Eastern No. 1|Former Western Pacific ''Mariposa'']], Central Pacific's second number 31. Was sold to [[Stockton Terminal and Eastern]] in 1914 and renumbered 1. Currently at the [[Travel Town Museum]] in Los Angeles.
* [[Virginia and Truckee Railroad]], though ''[[Virginia and Truckee 18 Dayton|The Dayton]]'' was not built for, nor served on the Central Pacific, the engine was one of two locomotives built by the CP's Sacramento shops in preservation (the other being CP 233). Moreover, its specifications were derived from CP 173, and thus is the only surviving example of that engine's design.
* Central Pacific's numbers [[Jupiter (locomotive)|60, ''Jupiter'']], and 63 ''Leviathan''. Although both engines have been scrapped, and therefore technically do not count as having been preserved, there were exact, full size operating replicas built in recent years. The ''Jupiter'' was built for the [[National Park Service]] along with a replica of Union Pacific's 119 for use at their [[Golden Spike National Historic Site]]. ''Leviathan'' was finished in 2009, is privately owned, and travels to various railroads to operate.

==Timeline==
'''1861'''
* June 28, 1861: &quot;Central Pacific Rail Road of California&quot; incorporated; name changed to &quot;Central Pacific Railroad of California&quot; on October 8, 1864, after the [[Pacific Railroad Acts|Pacific Railway Act]] amendment passes that summer.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cprr.org/Museum/CPRR_By-Laws.html By-Laws of the Central Pacific Railroad Company of California, Incorporated: June 28, 1861] &quot;THE INDUSTRIAL AND FINANCIAL RESOURCES OF THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA, as developed by the official returns of the Northern and Southern States and Territories, with an APPENDIX containing a detailed description of Federal, State, and City securities, railroad and canal bonds and shares, bank shares, etc. from statements nearest Jan. 1, 1863, and the CHARTERS OF THE UNION PACIFIC RAILROADS, the GENERAL RAILROAD LAW OF CALIFORNIA, and the BY-LAWS OF THE CENTRAL PACIFIC RAILROAD CO. OF CALIFORNIA.&quot; New York: SAMUEL HALLETT, Banker and Railroad Negotiator.  1864&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:CPRR Button 1867.jpg|right|thumb|CPRR logo gilded &quot;Staff&quot; uniform button]]
'''1862'''
* July 1, 1862: President [[Abraham Lincoln|Lincoln]] signs the [[Pacific Railway Act]], which authorized the Central Pacific and the [[Union Pacific Railroad|Union Pacific]] to build a railroad to the Pacific Ocean.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cprr.org/Museum/Pacific_Railroad_Acts.html &quot;An Act to aid in the construction of a railroad and telegraph line from the Missouri river to the Pacific ocean, and to secure to the government the use of the same for postal, military, and other purposes] 12 Stat. 489, July 1, 1862&lt;/ref&gt;
'''1863'''
* January 8, 1863: Ground-breaking ceremonies take place at [[Sacramento, California]], at the foot of &quot;K&quot; Street at the waterfront of the [[Sacramento River]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| last=Ambrose| first=Stephen E.| title=Nothing Like It in the World| publisher=Simon &amp; Schuster| year=2000| location=New York| page=[https://archive.org/details/nothinglikeitinw00ambr_0/page/106 106]| isbn=0-7432-0317-8| url=https://archive.org/details/nothinglikeitinw00ambr_0/page/106}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* October 26, 1863: First rail laid at [[Sacramento, California|Sacramento]].
'''1864'''
* April 26, 1864: Central Pacific opened to Roseville, {{convert|18|mi|km}}, where it makes a junction with the [[California Central Railroad]], operating from Folsom north to Lincoln.
* June 3, 1864: The first [[revenue]] train on the Central Pacific operates between [[Sacramento, California|Sacramento]] and [[Newcastle, California]]
* October 8, 1864: Following passage of the amendment to the Pacific Railroad Act, the company's name is changed to &quot;Central Pacific Railroad of California,&quot; a new corporation.
[[File:Central Pacific Railroad 1865 sand cast journal box cover.jpg|thumb|right|1865 CPRR journal cover]]
[[File:&quot;End of the Track. Near Humboldt River Canyon, Nevada.&quot; Campsite and train of the Central Pacific Railroad at foot of mo - NARA - 533792.jpg|thumb|right|End of the track near Humboldt River Canyon, Nevada, 1868]]
[[File:57. Summit station, C.P.R.R.jpg|thumb|Summit station at Sierra Nevada]]
'''1865'''
* February 1865: Central Pacific hired its first 50 [[Cantonese people|Cantonese]] emigrant laborers on a trial basis.
* May 13, 1865: Central Pacific opened {{convert|36|mi|km}} to [[Auburn, California]].
* September 1, 1865: Central Pacific opened {{convert|54|mi|km}} to [[Colfax, California]] (formerly known as &quot;Illinoistown.&quot;)
'''1866'''
* December 3, 1866: Central Pacific opened {{convert|92|mi|km}} to [[Cisco, California]].

'''1867'''
[[File:Donner Pass Summit Tunnel West Portal.jpg|thumb|right|Summit Tunnel, West Portal ''(Composite image with the tracks removed in 1993 digitally restored)'']]
* August 28, 1867: The [[Sierra Nevada (U.S.)|Sierra Nevada]]s were finally &quot;conquered&quot; by the Central Pacific Railroad, after almost five years of sustained construction effort by its mainly Chinese crew about 10,000 strong, with the successful completion at Donner Pass of its 1,659-foot (506 m) Tunnel No. 6 (a.k.a. the &quot;Summit Tunnel&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;Cooper, Bruce C. [http://cprr.org/Museum/Sierra_Grade_8-2003/Donner_Pass-Summit_Tunnel/index.html CPRR Summit Tunnel (#6), Tunnels #7 &amp; #8, Snowsheds, &quot;Chinese&quot; Walls, Donner Trail, and Dutch Flat Donner – Lake Wagon Road at Donner Pass] CPRR.org.&lt;/ref&gt;
* December 1, 1867: Central Pacific opened to Summit of the [[Sierra Nevada (U.S.)|Sierra Nevada]], {{convert|105|mi|km}}.
'''1868'''
* June 18, 1868: The first passenger train crosses the Sierra Nevada to Lake's Crossing (modern day [[Reno, Nevada]]) at the eastern foot of the Sierra in Nevada.
'''1869'''
* April 28, 1869: Track crews on the Central Pacific lay {{convert|10|mi|km}} of track in one day. This is the longest stretch of track that has been built in one day to date.
* May 10, 1869: The Central Pacific and Union Pacific tracks meet in [[Promontory, Utah]].
* May 15, 1869: The first transcontinental trains are run over the new line to [[Sacramento, California|Sacramento]].
* September 6, 1869: The first transcontinental train reaches the [[San Francisco Bay]] at [[Alameda Terminal]], achieving the first coast-to-coast railroad line.
* November 8, 1869: Central Pacific subsidiaries, [[Western Pacific Railroad (1862-1870)]] and [[San Francisco and Oakland Railroad]], complete the final leg of the route, connecting [[Sacramento, California|Sacramento]] to [[Oakland Pier]].
'''1870'''
* June 23, 1870: Central Pacific is consolidated with the [[Western Pacific Railroad (1862-1870)]], [[San Francisco and Alameda Railroad]] and [[San Francisco and Oakland Railroad]] to form the &quot;Central Pacific Railroad Co.&quot; (of June 1870).
* August 22, 1870: Central Pacific Railroad Co. is consolidated with the California &amp; Oregon; San Francisco, Oakland &amp; Alameda; and San Joaquin Valley Railroad; to form the &quot;Central Pacific Railroad Co.&quot;, a new corporation.
'''1876'''
* April 30, 1876: Operates the [[California Pacific Railroad]] between South [[Vallejo, California|Vallejo]] and Sacramento, [[Calistoga, California|Calistoga]] and [[Marysville, California|Marysville]] until April 1, 1885 (see below).
'''1877'''
* July 16, 1877: Start of the [[Great railroad strike of 1877]] when railroad workers on strike in [[Martinsburg, West Virginia]], derail and loot a train; United States President [[Rutherford B. Hayes]] calls in Federal troops to break the strike.
'''1883'''
* November 18, 1883: A system of one-hour standard [[time zone]]s for American railroads was first implemented. The zones were named Intercolonial, Eastern, Central, Mountain, and Pacific. Within one year, 85% of all cities having populations over 10,000, about 200 cities, were using [[standard time]].
'''1885'''
* April 1, 1885: Central Pacific is leased to [[Southern Pacific Railroad|Southern Pacific]].
'''1888'''
* June 30, 1888: Listed by ICC as a &quot;non-operating&quot; subsidiary of Southern Pacific.
'''1899'''
* July 29, 1899: Central Pacific is reorganized as the &quot;Central Pacific Railway&quot;.
'''1959'''
* June 30, 1959: Central Pacific is formally merged into the Southern Pacific.

==Acquisitions==
{{Expand section|date=March 2010}}
* Stockton and Copperopolis Railroad&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.usgennet.org/usa/ca/state1/tinkhamch18.html |title=Tinkham Chapter XVIII |publisher=Usgennet.org |accessdate=15 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Stockton and Visalia Railroad&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.oakdalehistory.net/article%2001.htm |title=Happy Birthday |publisher=Oakdalehistory.net |date=October 9, 2002 |accessdate=15 May 2012 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120305101944/http://www.oakdalehistory.net/article%2001.htm# |archive-date=5 March 2012 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Western Pacific Railroad (1862-1870)]]

==See also==
{{Portal|Railways}}
* [[Rail transport in California]]
* [[Donner Pass]] (Sierra Nevada)

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite book| title=Nothing Like It in the World: The Men Who Built the Transcontinental Railroad, 1863–1869| url=https://archive.org/details/nothinglikeitinw00ambr| url-access=registration| author=[[Stephen E. Ambrose|Ambrose, Stephen E.]]| location = New York| publisher=Simon &amp; Schuster| year=2000| isbn=0-684-84609-8}}
* {{cite book| title = Empire Express: Building the First Transcontinental Railroad| first = David Haward| last = Bain| location = New York| publisher = Viking| year = 1999| isbn = 0-670-80889-X| url = https://archive.org/details/empireexpressbui00bain}}
* {{cite book| title = The Central Pacific and Southern Pacific Railroads| first = Lucius| last = Beebe| location = Berkeley, CA| publisher = Howell-North Books| year = 1963}}
* {{cite book| title= Riding the Transcontinental Rails: Overland Travel on the Pacific Railroad 1865–1881| first = Bruce C.|last = Cooper| location = Philadelphia| publisher=Polyglot Press| year=2005| isbn=1-4115-9993-4}}
* {{cite book| title=The Classic Western American Railroad Routes| first = Bruce Clement|last = Cooper| location = New York| publisher=Chartwell Books/Worth Press| year=2010| isbn=0-7858-2573-8}}
* {{cite book| title=Chapters on the History of the Southern Pacific| first = Stuart| last = Daggett| location = New York| publisher=The Ronald Press| year=1922| url = https://books.google.com/books?id=KAb7M8x5QQcC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=chapters+southern+pacific&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=lFO0PTuHhQ&amp;sig=wiHQ-pCg6kS7b2MhKcyc9QQGgZ4&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=i7XrS_OhC8H68AaO4NzBCA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CBoQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false}}
* {{cite book| title=Collis Potter Huntington (2 vols.)| first = Cerinda W.| last = Evans| location = Newport News, Va.| publisher=Mariners' Museum| year=1954| url = https://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;d=4045484}}
* {{cite journal| title=The Central Pacific Railroad and the Railroad Land Grant Controversy| first = Heywood| last = Fleisig| journal = Journal of Economic History| volume = 35| issue = 3| year = 1975| pages = 552–566| doi=10.1017/s002205070007563x}} Questions whether promoters of the Central Pacific Railroad were oversubsidized. Confirms the traditional view that subsidies were not an economic necessity because they &quot;influenced neither the decision to invest in the railroad nor the speed of its construction.&quot; Notes that estimates of rate of return for the railroad developers using government funds range from 71% to 200%, while estimates of private rates of return range from 15% to 25%.
* {{cite book| title=The First Transcontinental Railroad: Central Pacific, Union Pacific| first = John Debo| last = Galloway| location = New York| publisher = Simmons-Boardman| year = 1950| url = https://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;d=14065867}}
* {{cite book| title=Waiting for the Cars: Alfred A. Hart's Stereoscopic Views of the Central Pacific Railroad, 1863–1869| first = and Wendell Huffman| last = Goldbaum, Howard| location = Carson City| publisher = Nevada State Railroad Museum| year = 2012| url = http://waitingforthecars.com}}
* {{cite book| title= A Work of Giants: Building the First Trans-continental Railroad| first = Wesley| last = Griswold| location = New York| publisher = McGraw-Hill | year = 1962}}
* {{cite book| title=Union Pacific (3 vols.)| first = Maury| last = Klein| location = Garden City, NY| publisher=Doubleday| year=1987| isbn = 0-385-17728-3}}
* {{cite book| title= High Road to Promontory: Building the Central Pacific (Now the Southern Pacific) across the High Sierra| url= https://archive.org/details/highroadtopromon00krau| url-access= registration| first = George|last = Kraus| location = Palo Alto| publisher = American West Pub. Co.| year = 1969}}
* {{cite journal| title=Chinese Laborers and the Construction of the Central Pacific| first = George|last = Kraus| journal = Utah Historical Quarterly| volume = 37| issue = 1| year = 1975| pages = 41–57}} Shows how Chinese railroad workers lived and worked, and managed the finances associated with their employment. Concludes that CPRR officials who employed the Chinese, even those at first opposed to the policy, came to appreciate the reliability of this group of laborers. There are many quotations from accounts by contemporary observers.
* {{cite journal| title=Construction of the CPRR: Chinese Immigrant Contribution| first = Holly| last = Lake| journal = Northeastern Nevada Historical Society Quarterly| volume = 94| issue = 4| year = 1994| pages = 188–199}}
* {{cite journal| title=Rates of Return for Land-grant Railroads: the Central Pacific System| first = Lloyd J.|last = Mercer| journal = Journal of Economic History| volume = 30| issue = 3| year = 1970| pages = 602–626}} Analyzes the impact of land grants from 1864 to 1890 on rates of return from investment in the Central Pacific Railroad. Results suggest that even without land grants, rates of return were high enough to induce investment. Also, land grants did not pay for the construction of the railroad. Land grants, however, did produce large social returns in western states by accelerating construction of the system.
* {{cite journal| title=Land Grants to American Railroads: Social Cost or Social Benefit?| first = Lloyd J.|last = Mercer| journal = Business History Review| volume = 43| issue = 2| year = 1969| pages = 134–151| doi=10.2307/3112269}} Uses econometrics to determine the value of railroad land grants of the 19th century to the railroads and to society. The author summarizes and criticizes previous treatments of this subject, and discusses his own findings. Using the Central Pacific and the Union Pacific systems as the basis for his investigation, the author concludes that the railroad owners received unaided rates of return that substantially exceeded the private rate of return on the average alternative project in the economy during the same period. Thus, the projects were profitable, although contemporary observers expected that the roads would be privately unprofitable without the land grant aid. The land grants did not have a major effect, increasing the private rate of return only slightly. Nevertheless, he says the policy of subsidizing those railroad systems was beneficial for society since the social rate of return from the project was substantial and exceeded the private rate by a significant margin.
* {{cite journal| title=The Central Pacific Railroad and Exploitation of Chinese Labor| first = Paul M.| last = Ong| journal = Journal of Ethnic Studies| volume = 13| issue = 2| year = 1985| pages = 119–124}} Ong tries to resolve the apparent inconsistency in the literature on Asians in early California, with contradictory studies showing evidence both for and against the exploitation of Chinese labor by the CPRR, using [[monopsony]] theory as developed by Joan Robinson. Because CPRR set different wages for whites and Chinese (each group had different elasticities of supply) and used the two classes in different types of positions, the two groups were complementary, rather than interchangeable. Calculations thus show higher levels of exploitation of the Chinese than found in previous studies.
* {{cite journal| title=The Army of Canton in the High Sierra| first = Alexander|last = Saxton| journal = Pacific Historical Review| volume = 35| issue = 2| year = 1966| pages = 141–151| doi=10.2307/3636678}}
* {{cite journal| title=Stanford's Responses to Competition: Rhetoric Versus Reality| first = Norman E.|last = Tutorow| journal = Southern California Quarterly| volume = 52| issue = 3| year = 1970| pages = 231–247| doi=10.2307/41170298}} Leland Stanford and the men who ran the CPRR paid lip-service to the idea of free competition, but in practice sought to dominate competing railroad and shipping lines. Analyzing the period 1869-1893, the author shows how Stanford and his associates repeatedly entered into pooling arrangements to prevent competition, bought out competitors, or forced rivals to agree not to compete. He concludes that Stanford and his partners viewed ''laissez-faire'' as applicable only to government controls, and not to businessmen's destruction of competition within the system.
* {{cite journal| title=Information, Markets, and Corruption: Transcontinental Railroads in the Gilded Age| first = Richard| last = White| journal = The Journal of American History| volume = 90| issue = 1| year = 2003}}
*{{cite book|last=[[Richard White (historian)|White]]|first=Richard|title=Railroaded: The Transcontinentals and the Making of Modern America|publisher=W. W. Norton &amp; Company|date=2011|isbn=978-0-393-06126-0|url=https://archive.org/details/railroadedtransc00whit_0}}
* {{cite book| title = A Great and Shining Road: The Epic Story of the Transcontinental Railroad| first = John Hoyt| last = Williams| location = New York| publisher = Times Books| year = 1988| isbn = 0-8129-1668-9| url = https://archive.org/details/isbn_9780812916683}}
* {{Cite episode| title = The Iron Road| series = The American Experience| credits = Neil Goodwin, Peace River Films| network = PBS| airdate = 1990}}
* {{cite book| title = Iron Horses to Promontory| first = Gerald M| last = Best| location = New York| publisher = Golden West| year = 1969| isbn= }}

==External links==
{{commons category}}
* [http://CPRR.org Central Pacific Railroad Photographic History Museum]
* [http://www.oac.cdlib.org/findaid/ark:/13030/kt6c602823 Railroads in California], handwritten report by L. M. Clement. Special Collections and Archives, The UC Irvine Libraries, Irvine, California.

{{The Big Four}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Central Pacific Railroad}}
[[Category:First Transcontinental Railroad]]
[[Category:Railway lines in the United States]]
[[Category:History of rail transportation in the United States]]
[[Category:History of the American West]]
[[Category:History of California]]
[[Category:History of the Sierra Nevada (U.S.)]]
[[Category:History of the United States (1865–1918)]]
[[Category:Defunct California railroads]]
[[Category:Defunct Nevada railroads]]
[[Category:Defunct Utah railroads]]
[[Category:Predecessors of the Southern Pacific Transportation Company]]
[[Category:Rail lines receiving land grants]]
[[Category:Railway companies established in 1861]]
[[Category:Railway companies disestablished in 1899]]
[[Category:1860s in California]]
[[Category:American frontier]]
[[Category:American companies established in 1899]]
[[Category:1861 establishments in the United States]]</text>
      <sha1>fvz1kht5a2gfzd45bhnasm0t5qy6bxu</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
