  <page>
    <title>Chet Atkins</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7756</id>
    <revision>
      <id>934667095</id>
      <parentid>929744047</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-07T20:19:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>BD2412</username>
        <id>196446</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* Death and legacy */Fixing [[Wikipedia:Disambiguation pages with links|links to disambiguation pages]], replaced: [[Eric Johnson]] → [[Eric Johnson (guitarist, born 1954)|Eric Johnson]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|Chester Atkins|the former U.S. congressman|Chester G. Atkins}}
{{Redirect|Mr. Guitar|the album by Charlie Byrd|Mr. Guitar (album)}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=December 2014}}
{{Infobox musical artist &lt;!-- See Wikipedia:WikiProject_Musicians --&gt;
| name                  = Chet Atkins
| background          = solo_singer
| image                  = Chet Atkins.jpg
| birth_name          = Chester Burton Atkins
| birth_date          = {{birth date|1924|6|20}}
| birth_place         = [[Luttrell, Tennessee|Luttrell]], Tennessee, U.S.
| death_date          = {{death date and age|2001|6|30|1924|6|20}}
| death_place         = Nashville, Tennessee
| genre                 = [[Country music|Country]], [[country rock]], [[rock and roll|rock]], [[Folk music|folk]], [[rockabilly]]
| occupation          = Musician, songwriter, producer
| instrument          = Guitar, violin, vocals, banjo, ukulele
| years_active        = 1942–1996
| label                     = [[RCA Victor]], [[Columbia Records|Columbia]]
| associated_acts     = [[The Country All-Stars]], [[Arthur Fiedler]], [[Les Paul]], [[Jerry Reed]], [[Hank Snow]], [[Merle Travis]], [[The Carter Sisters]], [[Mark Knopfler]], Jim Carney
| website                = {{URL|www.misterguitar.com}}
}}

'''Chester Burton Atkins''' (June 20, 1924&amp;nbsp;– June 30, 2001), known as &quot;'''Mr. Guitar'''&quot; and &quot;'''The Country Gentleman'''&quot;, was an American musician, occasional vocalist, songwriter, and [[record producer]] who, along with [[Owen Bradley]], [[Bob Ferguson (musician)|Bob Ferguson]] and others, created the [[country music]] style that came to be known as the [[Nashville sound]], which expanded country music's appeal to adult pop music fans. He was primarily known as a guitarist. He also played the mandolin, fiddle, banjo, and ukulele.

Atkins's signature picking style was inspired by [[Merle Travis]]. Other major guitar influences were [[Django Reinhardt]], [[George Barnes (musician)|George Barnes]], [[Les Paul]], and, later, [[Jerry Reed]].&lt;ref name=pc10/&gt; His distinctive picking style and musicianship brought him admirers inside and outside the country scene, both in the United States and abroad. Atkins spent most of his career at [[RCA Victor]] and produced records for the [[The Browns|Browns]], [[Hank Snow]], [[Porter Wagoner]], [[Norma Jean (singer)|Norma Jean]], [[Dolly Parton]], [[Dottie West]], [[Perry Como]], [[Floyd Cramer]], [[Elvis Presley]], the [[Everly Brothers]], [[Eddy Arnold]], [[Don Gibson]], [[Jim Reeves]], [[Jerry Reed]], [[Skeeter Davis]], [[Waylon Jennings]], and many others.

''[[Rolling Stone]]'' credited Atkins with inventing the &quot;popwise 'Nashville sound' that rescued country music from a commercial slump,&quot; and ranked him number 21 on their list of &quot;The 100 Greatest Guitarists Of All Time.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Chet Atkins&quot;&gt;[https://www.rollingstone.com/music/lists/100-greatest-guitarists-20111123/chet-atkins-20111122 &quot;Chet Atkins&quot;]. ''Rolling Stone''.&lt;/ref&gt; Among many other honors, Atkins received 14 [[Grammy Award]]s and the [[Grammy Lifetime Achievement Award]]. He also received nine [[Country Music Association]] awards for Instrumentalist of the Year. He was inducted into the [[Rock &amp; Roll Hall of Fame]], the [[Country Music Hall of Fame and Museum]], and the [[Musicians Hall of Fame and Museum]]. [[George Harrison]] was also inspired by Chet Atkins; Early Beatles songs such as &quot;[[All My Loving]]&quot; show the influence.

==Biography==

===Childhood and early life===
Atkins was born on June 20, 1924, in [[Luttrell, Tennessee]], near [[Clinch Mountain]]. His parents divorced when he was six years old, after which he was raised by his mother. He was the youngest of three boys and a girl. He started out on the [[ukulele]], later moving on to the [[fiddle]], but made a swap with his brother, Lowell, when he was nine: an old pistol and some chores for a [[guitar]].&lt;ref name=&quot;CMT&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cmt.com/artists/az/atkins_chet/bio.jhtml |title=Country Music Television biography. |publisher=Cmt.com |date= |accessdate=March 28, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; He stated in his 1974 autobiography, &quot;We were so poor and everybody around us was so poor that it was the forties before anyone even knew there had been a depression.&quot; Forced to relocate to Fortson, [[Georgia (U.S. state)|Georgia]], outside of [[Columbus, Georgia|Columbus]], to live with his father because of a critical [[asthma]] condition, Atkins was a sensitive youth who made music his obsession. Because of his illness, he was forced to sleep in a straight-back chair to breathe comfortably. On those nights, he played his guitar until he fell asleep holding it, a habit that lasted his whole life.&lt;ref name=&quot;CG&quot;&gt;Atkins, Chet; Neely, Bill (1974). &quot;Country Gentleman&quot;. Chicago. Harry Regnery. {{ISBN|0-8092-9051-0}}.&lt;/ref&gt; While living in Fortson, he attended the historic{{citation needed|date=May 2017}} Mountain Hill School. He returned in the 1990s to play a series of charity concerts to save the school from demolition.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
 | last = Rush
 | first = Dianne Samms
 | coauthors =
 | title = Chet Plays; Gatlin Lives
 | newspaper = Lakeland Ledger
 | location = Lakeland, Florida
 | page = 9C
 | publisher = 
 | date = October 23, 1994
 | url = https://news.google.com/newspapers?nid=1346&amp;dat=19941023&amp;id=9KpNAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=YfwDAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=2822,1595083
 | accessdate = July 6, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Stories have been told about the very young Chet, who, when a friend or relative would come to visit and play guitar, would crowd in and put his ear so close to the instrument that it became difficult for the visitor to play.&lt;ref name=&quot;CG&quot; /&gt;

Atkins became an accomplished guitarist while he was in high school.&lt;ref name=&quot;CMT&quot; /&gt; He used the restroom in the school to practice, because it had good acoustics.&lt;ref&gt;Atkins, Chet; Neely, Bill (1974). &quot;Country Gentleman&quot;. Chicago. Harry Regnery. p. 52. {{ISBN|0-8092-9051-0}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[David Halberstam|Halberstam, David]] (1961). liner notes. ''Chet Atkins' Workshop''. [[RCA Victor]] LSP-2232.&lt;/ref&gt; His first guitar had a nail for a nut and was so bowed that only the first few frets could be used.&lt;ref name=&quot;mamg&quot;&gt;Atkins, Chet; Cochran, Russ (2003). &quot;Me and My Guitars&quot;. Milwaukee: Hal Leonard. {{ISBN|0-634-05565-8}}.&lt;/ref&gt; He later purchased a semi-acoustic electric guitar and amp, but he had to travel many miles to find an electrical outlet, since his home didn't have electricity.&lt;ref&gt;Atkins, Chet; Neely, Bill. (1974). &quot;Country Gentleman&quot;. Chicago. Harry Regnery. pp. 61–62. {{ISBN|0-8092-9051-0}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Later in life, he lightheartedly gave himself (along with [[John Knowles (guitarist)|John Knowles]], [[Marcel Dadi]], [[Tommy Emmanuel]], [[Steve Wariner]], and [[Jerry Reed]]&lt;ref&gt;{{YouTube|M8AXs6oRPnQ|'Interview of Chet Atkins'}}&lt;/ref&gt;) the honorary degree CGP (&quot;Certified Guitar Player&quot;).&lt;ref name=&quot;mamg&quot; /&gt;
In 2011, his daughter Merle Atkins Russell bestowed the CGP degree on his longtime sideman [[Paul Yandell]].  She then declared no more CGPs would be allowed by the Atkins estate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| last = Freeman
| first = Jon
| title = A Guitarist Paul Yandell Passes
| url = http://www.musicrow.com/2011/11/guitarist-paul-yandell-passes/
| publisher = Music Row
| date = November 22, 2011
| accessdate = July 6, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

His half-brother, Jim, was a successful guitarist who worked with the [[Les Paul Trio]] in New York.&lt;ref name=&quot;CG&quot; /&gt;

Atkins did not have a strong style of his own until 1939, when (while still living in Georgia) he heard [[Merle Travis]] picking over [[WLW]] radio.&lt;ref name=&quot;CG&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;*[http://www.countrymusichalloffame.com/site/inductees.aspx?cid=99 Country Music Hall of Fame and Museum] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071014040342/http://www.countrymusichalloffame.com/site/inductees.aspx?cid=99 |date=October 14, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt; This early influence dramatically shaped his unique playing style.&lt;ref name=pc10/&gt; Whereas Travis's right hand used his index finger for the melody and thumb for bass notes, Atkins expanded his right-hand style to include picking with his first three fingers, with the thumb on bass.

Chet Atkins was an [[amateur radio]] general class licensee. Formerly using the call sign WA4CZD, he obtained the vanity call sign W4CGP in 1998 to include the CGP designation, which supposedly stood for &quot;Certified Guitar Picker&quot;.{{explain|date=January 2019}} He was a member of the [[American Radio Relay League]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.arrl.org/pages/display/error404|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20050920143059/http://www.arrl.org/news/stories/2001/07/02/1/?nc=1|url-status=dead|title=American Radio Relay League &amp;#124; Ham Radio Association and Resources|archivedate=September 20, 2005|website=Arrl.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Early musical career===
After dropping out of high school in 1942, Atkins landed a job at [[WNOX|WNOX-AM]] radio in [[Knoxville, Tennessee|Knoxville]], where he played fiddle and guitar with the singer [[Bill Carlisle]] and the comic [[Archie Campbell]] and became a member of the station's Dixieland Swingsters, a small swing instrumental combo. After three years, he moved to [[WLW|WLW-AM]] in [[Cincinnati, Ohio]], where Merle Travis had formerly worked.

After six months, he moved to Raleigh and worked with [[Johnnie and Jack]] before heading for [[Richmond, Virginia]], where he performed with [[Sunshine Sue|Sunshine Sue Workman]]. Atkins's shy personality worked against him, as did the fact that his sophisticated style led many to doubt he was truly &quot;country&quot;. He was fired often, but was soon able to land another job at another radio station on account of his unique playing ability.&lt;ref name=&quot;CG&quot; /&gt;

Atkins and [[Jethro Burns]] (of [[Homer and Jethro]]) married twin sisters, Leona and Lois Johnson, who sang as Laverne and Fern Johnson, the Johnson Sisters. Leona Atkins outlived her husband by eight years, dying in 2009 at the age of 85.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.countrystandardtime.com/news/newsitem.asp?xid=3389 |title=Chet Atkins' Widow Dies |date=October 22, 2009 |work=Country Standard Time |accessdate=October 29, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Travelling to Chicago, Atkins auditioned for [[Red Foley]], who was leaving his star position on [[WLS (AM)|WLS-AM]]'s ''[[National Barn Dance]]'' to join the [[Grand Ole Opry]].&lt;ref name=&quot;RollingStone&quot;&gt;[https://www.rollingstone.com/news/story/5931727/chet_atkins_dies/print &quot;Chet Atkins Dies&quot;] ''Rolling Stone''. Accessed on March 28, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Atkins made his first appearance at the Opry in 1946 as a member of Foley's band. He also recorded a single for Nashville-based [[Bullet Records]] that year. That single, &quot;Guitar Blues&quot;, was fairly progressive, including a clarinet solo by the Nashville dance band musician Dutch McMillan, with [[Owen Bradley]] on piano. He had a solo spot on the Opry, but when that was cut, Atkins moved on to [[KWTO (AM)|KWTO]] in [[Springfield, Missouri]]. Despite the support of executive [[Si Siman]], however, he soon was fired for not sounding &quot;country enough&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;CG&quot; /&gt;

===Signing with RCA Victor===
While working with a Western band in [[Denver, Colorado]], Atkins came to the attention of [[RCA Victor Records|RCA Victor]]. Siman had been encouraging [[Stephen H. Sholes|Steve Sholes]] to sign Atkins, as his style (with the success of Merle Travis as a hit recording artist) was suddenly in vogue. Sholes, A&amp;R director of country music at RCA, tracked Atkins down in Denver.

He made his first RCA Victor recordings in Chicago in 1947, but they did not sell. He did some studio work for RCA that year, but had relocated to Knoxville again where he worked with Homer and Jethro on WNOX's new Saturday night radio show ''The Tennessee Barn Dance'' and the popular ''Midday Merry Go Round''.

In 1949, he left WNOX to join [[June Carter]] with Mother Maybelle and the [[The Carter Sisters|Carter Sisters]] on KWTO. This incarnation of the old [[Carter Family]] featured Maybelle Carter and daughters June, Helen, and Anita. Their work soon attracted attention from the Grand Ole Opry. The group relocated to [[Nashville, Tennessee|Nashville]] in the mid-1950s. Atkins began working on recording sessions and performing on [[WSM (AM)|WSM-AM]] and the Opry.&lt;ref name=&quot;CG&quot; /&gt; Atkins became a member of the Opry in the 1950s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| title = Opry Timeline – 1950s
| url = http://www.opry.com/about/Timeline_1950.html
| date = 
| accessdate = July 2, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While he had not yet had a hit record for RCA Victor, his stature was growing. He began assisting Sholes as a session leader when the New York–based producer needed help organizing Nashville sessions for RCA Victor artists. Atkins's first hit single was &quot;[[Mr. Sandman]]&quot;, followed by &quot;Silver Bell&quot;, which he recorded as a duet with [[Hank Snow]]. His albums also became more popular. He was featured on ABC-TV's ''[[The Eddy Arnold Show]]'' in the summer of 1956 and on ''[[Ozark Jubilee|Country Music Jubilee]]'' in 1957 and 1958 (by then renamed ''Jubilee USA'').
[[File:Gretsch G6122-1958.jpg|thumb|upright|Atkins's [[Gretsch]] Country Gentleman, model G6122, 1962]]

In addition to recording, Atkins was a design consultant for [[Gretsch]], which manufactured a popular Chet Atkins line of electric guitars from 1955–1980. He became manager of RCA Victor's Nashville studios, eventually inspiring and seeing the completion of the legendary [[RCA Studio B]], the first studio built specifically for the purpose of recording on the now-famous [[Music Row]]. Also later on, Chet and [[Owen Bradley]] would become instrumental in the creation of studio B’s adjacent building [[RCA Studio A]] as well.&lt;ref name=&quot;mamg&quot; /&gt;

===Performer and producer===
When Sholes took over pop production in 1957—a result of his success with [[Elvis Presley]]—he put Atkins in charge of RCA Victor's Nashville division. With country music record sales declining as rock and roll became more popular, Atkins and [[Bob Ferguson (music)|Bob Ferguson]] took their cue from [[Owen Bradley]] and eliminated fiddles and steel guitar as a means of making country singers appeal to pop fans. This became known as the [[Nashville sound]], which Atkins said was a label created by the media for a style of recording during that period intended to keep country (and their jobs) viable.

Atkins used the [[Jordanaires]] and a rhythm section on hits such as [[Jim Reeves]]'s &quot;[[Four Walls (Jim Reeves song)|Four Walls]]&quot; and &quot;[[He'll Have to Go]]&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[{{Allmusic|class=album|id=r245817|pure_url=yes}} Allmusic entry for ''Welcome to My World'', Jim Reeves 1996 box set, Bear Family Records]&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Don Gibson]]'s &quot;[[Oh Lonesome Me]]&quot; and &quot;Blue Blue Day&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[{{Allmusic|class=artist|id=p1624|pure_url=yes}} Allmusic biography of Don Gibson]&lt;/ref&gt; The once-rare phenomenon of having a country hit [[Crossover (music)|cross over]] to pop success became more common. He and Bradley had essentially put the producer in the driver's seat, guiding an artist's choice of material and the musical background.

Atkins made his own records, which usually visited pop standards and [[jazz]], in a sophisticated home studio, often recording the rhythm tracks at RCA and adding his solo parts at home, refining the tracks until the results satisfied him.&lt;ref name=&quot;mamg&quot; /&gt; Guitarists of all styles came to admire various Atkins albums for their unique musical ideas and in some cases experimental electronic ideas. In this period, he became known internationally as &quot;Mister Guitar&quot;, inspiring an album, ''[[Mister Guitar]]'', engineered by both Bob Ferris and [[Bill Porter (sound engineer)|Bill Porter]], Ferris's replacement.

[[File:RCA Studio B - Chet Atkins, Bill Porter.jpg|thumb|upright|Atkins listening as [[Bill Porter (sound engineer)|Bill Porter]] adjusts a mix in RCA's Nashville studio]]
At the end of March 1959, Porter took over as chief engineer at RCA's Nashville studio, in the space eventually known as [[RCA Studio B|Studio B]] after the facility expanded with a second studio in 1960. (At the time, RCA's sole Nashville studio had no letter designation.) Porter soon helped Atkins get a better reverberation sound from the studio's German effects device, an [[Elektro-Mess-Technik|EMT]] [[Reverberation#Plate reverberators|plate reverb]]. With his [[golden ear]], Porter found the studio's acoustics to be problematic, and he devised a set of acoustic baffles to hang from the ceiling, then selected positions for microphones based on resonant [[room modes]]. The sound of the recordings improved significantly, and the studio achieved a string of successes. The Nashville sound became more [[Dynamic range|dynamic]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Ballou|first=Glen|title=Handbook for Sound Engineers|year=1998|publisher=Focal Press|page=1154}}&lt;/ref&gt; In later years, when Bradley asked how he achieved his sound, Atkins told him &quot;it was Porter.&quot;&lt;ref name=McClellan2004&gt;{{cite book |last1=McClellan |first1=John |last2=Bratic |first2=Deyan |title=Chet Atkins in Three Dimensions |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=mmCUExOXx0MC |volume=2 |year=2004 |publisher=Mel Bay Publications |isbn=978-0-7866-5877-0 |pages=149–152}}&lt;/ref&gt; Porter described Atkins as respectful of musicians when recording—if someone was out of tune, he would not single that person out by name. Instead, he would say something like, &quot;we got a little tuning problem&amp;nbsp;... Everybody check and see what's going on.&quot;&lt;ref name=McClellan2004/&gt; If that did not work, Atkins would instruct Porter to turn the offending player down in the mix. When Porter left RCA in late-1964, Atkins said, &quot;the sound was never the same, never as great.&quot;&lt;ref name=McClellan2004/&gt;

Atkins's trademark &quot;Atkins style&quot; of playing uses the thumb and first two or sometimes three fingers of the right hand. He developed this style from listening to Merle Travis,&lt;ref name=pc10&gt;{{Gilliland |url=https://digital.library.unt.edu/ark:/67531/metadc19758/m1/ |title=Show 10 – Tennessee Firebird: American Country Music Before and After Elvis. [Part 2] }}&lt;/ref&gt; occasionally on a primitive radio. He was sure no one could play that articulately with just the thumb and index finger (which was exactly how Travis played), and he assumed it required the thumb and two fingers—and that was the style he pioneered and mastered.

He enjoyed jamming with fellow studio musicians, and they were asked to perform at the [[Newport Jazz Festival]] in 1960. That performance was cancelled because of rioting, but a live recording of the group (''[[After the Riot in Newport|After the Riot at Newport]]'') was released. Atkins performed by invitation at the [[White House]] for every U.S. President from John F. Kennedy through to George H. W. Bush. Atkins was a member of the [[Million Dollar Band (country music group)|Million Dollar Band]] during the 1980s. He is also well known for his song &quot;Yankee Doodle Dixie&quot;, in which he played &quot;[[Yankee Doodle]]&quot; and &quot;[[Dixie (song)|Dixie]]&quot; simultaneously, on the same guitar.

Before his mentor Sholes died in 1968, Atkins had become vice president of RCA's country division. In 1987, he told [[Nine-O-One Network Magazine|''Nine-O-One Network'' magazine]] that he was &quot;ashamed&quot; of his promotion: &quot;I wanted to be known as a guitarist and I know, too, that they give you titles like that in lieu of money. So beware when they want to make you vice president.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Nine-O-One Interview, Nine-O-One Network Magazine, December 1987, p.10-11&lt;/ref&gt; He had brought [[Waylon Jennings]], [[Willie Nelson]], [[Connie Smith]], [[Bobby Bare]], [[Dolly Parton]], [[Jerry Reed]], and [[John Hartford]] to the label in the 1960s and inspired and helped countless others.&lt;ref name=&quot;RockHall&quot;&gt;[http://www.rockhall.com/inductees/chet-atkins &quot;Chet Atkins&quot;], Rock and Roll Hall of Fame. Accessed on March 28, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; He took a considerable risk during the mid-1960s, when the [[civil rights movement]] sparked violence throughout the South, by signing country music's first African-American singer, [[Charley Pride]], who sang rawer country than the smoother music Atkins had pioneered.

Atkins's biggest hit single came in 1965, with &quot;Yakety Axe&quot;, an adaptation of &quot;[[Yakety Sax]]&quot;, by his friend, the saxophonist [[Boots Randolph]]. He rarely performed in those days and eventually hired other RCA producers, such as [[Bob Ferguson (music)|Bob Ferguson]] and [[Felton Jarvis]], to lessen his workload.&lt;ref name=&quot;mamg&quot; /&gt;

===Later career===
In the 1970s, Atkins became increasingly stressed by his executive duties. He produced fewer records, but could still turn out hits such as [[Perry Como]]'s 1973 pop hit &quot;[[And I Love You So (song)|And I Love You So]]&quot;. He recorded extensively with close friend and fellow picker Jerry Reed, who had become a hit artist in his own right. A 1973 diagnosis of [[colorectal cancer|colon cancer]], however, led Atkins to redefine his role at RCA, to allow others to handle administration while he went back to his first love, the guitar, often recording with Reed or even Jethro Burns from Homer and Jethro (his brother-in-law) after Homer died in 1971.&lt;ref name=&quot;mamg&quot; /&gt; Atkins would turn over his administrative duties to [[Jerry Bradley (record producer)|Jerry Bradley]], son of Owen, in 1973 at RCA.

Atkins did little production work at RCA after stepping down and in fact, had hired producers at the label in the 1960s, among them [[Bob Ferguson (musician)|Bob Ferguson]] and [[Felton Jarvis]]. As a recording artist, Atkins grew disillusioned with RCA in the late 1970s. He felt stifled because the record company would not let him branch into jazz. He had also produced late 60's jazz recordings by Canadian guitarist [[Lenny Breau]], a friend and protege. His mid-1970s collaborations with one of his influences, [[Les Paul]], ''[[Chester and Lester|Chester &amp; Lester]]'' and ''[[Guitar Monsters]]'', had already reflected that interest; ''Chester &amp; Lester'' was one of the best-selling recordings of Atkins's career. At the same time, he grew dissatisfied with the direction Gretsch (no longer family-owned) was going and withdrew his authorization for them to use his name and began designing guitars with [[Gibson Guitar Corporation|Gibson]]. Atkins ended his 35-year association with RCA in 1982 and signed with [[Columbia Records]], for whom he produced a debut album in 1983.&lt;ref name=&quot;RollingStone&quot; /&gt;

Jazz had always been a strong love of his, and often in his career he was criticized by &quot;pure&quot; country musicians for his jazz influences. He also said on many occasions that he did not like being called a &quot;country guitarist,&quot; insisting that he was &quot;a guitarist, period.&quot; Although he played [[Playing by ear|by ear]] and was a masterful improviser, he was able to read music and even performed some classical guitar pieces. When [[Roger C. Field]], a friend, suggested to him in 1991 that he record and perform with a female singer, he did so with [[Suzy Bogguss]].&lt;ref name=&quot;mamg&quot;/&gt;

He returned to his country roots for albums he recorded with [[Mark Knopfler]] and Jerry Reed.&lt;ref name=&quot;mamg&quot; /&gt; Knopfler had long mentioned Atkins as one of his earliest influences. Atkins also collaborated with Australian guitar legend [[Tommy Emmanuel]]. On being asked to name the ten most influential guitarists of the twentieth century, he named [[Django Reinhardt]] to the first position, and also placed himself on the list.&lt;ref name=&quot;OfficialSite&quot;&gt;[http://www.misterguitar.com/news/chetsten.html Official Web Site of Chet Atkins]. Accessed on August 27, 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

In later years, he even went back to radio, appearing on [[Garrison Keillor]]'s ''[[Prairie Home Companion]]'' radio program, on [[American Public Media]] radio, even picking up a fiddle from time to time,&lt;ref name=&quot;mamg&quot; /&gt; and performing songs such as [[Bob Wills]]'s &quot;[[Corrina, Corrina (song)|Corrina, Corrina]]&quot; and [[Willie Nelson]]'s &quot;[[Seven Spanish Angels]]&quot; with Nelson on a 1985 broadcast of the show at the Bridges Auditorium on the campus of [[Pomona College]].

==Death and legacy==
Atkins received numerous awards, including 14 Grammy awards and nine Country Music Association awards for Instrumentalist of the Year.&lt;ref name=&quot;RollingStone&quot; /&gt; In 1993, he was honored with the Grammy Lifetime Achievement Award. ''Billboard'' magazine awarded him its Century Award, its &quot;highest honor for distinguished creative achievement,&quot; in December 1997.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.rollingstone.com/artists/chetatkins/biography &quot;Biography&amp;nbsp;– Chet Atkins&quot;]. ''Rolling Stone''. Accessed on May 10, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

Atkins is notable for his broad influence. His love for numerous styles of music can be traced from his early recording of the stride pianist [[James P. Johnson]]'s &quot;Johnson Rag&quot;, all the way to the rock stylings of [[Eric Johnson (guitarist, born 1954)|Eric Johnson]], an invited guest on Atkins's recording sessions, who, when Atkins attempted to copy his influential rocker &quot;[[Cliffs of Dover (song)|Cliffs of Dover]]&quot;, led to Atkins's creation of a unique arrangement of &quot;Londonderry Air (Danny Boy)&quot;.

The classical guitar selections included on almost all his albums were, for many American artists working in the field today, the first classical guitar they ever heard. He recorded [[smooth jazz]] guitar still played on American airwaves today.

Atkins continued performing in the 1990s, but his health declined after he was diagnosed again with colon cancer in 1996. He died on June 30, 2001, at his home in Nashville, Tennessee, at the age of 77.&lt;ref&gt;[http://archives.cnn.com/2001/SHOWBIZ/Music/07/02/obit.chet.atkins/index.html &quot;Obituary&quot;] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080323145021/http://archives.cnn.com/2001/SHOWBIZ/Music/07/02/obit.chet.atkins/index.html |date=March 23, 2008 }}, CNN, July 2, 2001 Accessed June 21, 2008&lt;/ref&gt; His memorial service was held at Ryman Auditorium in Nashville.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2001/07/04/us/guitars-gently-weep-as-nashville-pays-tribute-to-chet-atkins.html|title=Guitars Gently Weep as Nashville Pays Tribute to Chet Atkins|date=July 4, 2001|work=The New York Times|accessdate=September 19, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; He was buried at Harpeth Hills Memory Gardens in Nashville.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.findagrave.com/memorial/23366 Chet Atkins at Find a Grave.] Accessed November 24, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

A stretch of [[Interstate 185 (Georgia)|Interstate 185]] in southwest [[Georgia (U.S. state)|Georgia]] (between [[LaGrange, Georgia|LaGrange]] and [[Columbus, Georgia|Columbus]]) is named &quot;Chet Atkins Parkway&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ganet.org/services/leg/ShowBillPre.cgi?year=1997&amp;filename=1997/HR245.passed |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20050128185210/http://www.ganet.org/services/leg/ShowBillPre.cgi?year=1997&amp;filename=1997%2FHR245.passed |archivedate=January 28, 2005 |title=Chet Atkins Parkway Bill Resolution. |accessdate=January 9, 2012 |url-status=dead |df=mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; This stretch of interstate runs through Fortson, where Atkins spent much of his childhood.

In 2002, Atkins was posthumously inducted into the [[Rock and Roll Hall of Fame]].&lt;ref name=&quot;RockHall&quot; /&gt; His award was presented by [[Marty Stuart]] and [[Brian Setzer]] and accepted by Atkins's grandson, Jonathan Russell. The following year, Atkins ranked number 28 in [[Country Music Television]]'s &quot;40 Greatest Men of Country Music&quot;.

At the age of 13, the future jazz guitarist [[Earl Klugh]] was captivated watching Atkins's guitar playing on ''The [[Perry Como]] Show.''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.buffalostate.edu/pac/season/klugh.asp |title=Performing Arts Center, Buffalo State University |publisher=Buffalostate.edu |accessdate=February 27, 2012 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100527210241/http://www.buffalostate.edu/pac/season/klugh.asp |archive-date=May 27, 2010 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, he was a big influence on [[Doyle Dykes]]. Atkins also inspired Drexl Jonez and Tommy Emmanuel.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tommyemmanuel.com/bio/ Tommy Emmanuel official website biography.] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110825110639/http://www.tommyemmanuel.com/bio/ |date=August 25, 2011 }} Retrieved September 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Clint Black]]'s album ''[[Nothin' but the Taillights]]'' includes the song &quot;Ode to Chet&quot;, which includes the lyrics &quot;'Cause I can win her over like Romeo did Juliet, if I can only show her I can almost pick that legato lick like Chet&quot; and &quot;It'll take more than [[Mel Bay]] 1, 2, &amp; 3 if I'm ever gonna play like CGP.&quot; Atkins played guitar on the track. At the end of the song, Black and Atkins had a brief conversation.

Chet's song &quot;Jam Man&quot; is currently used in commercials for Esurance.

The opening guitar licks to the [[Miranda Lambert]] song &quot;[[Only Prettier]]&quot; sound very similar to Atkins's guitar-picking style.

In 1967, a tribute song, &quot;Chet's Tune&quot;, was produced for his birthday, with contributions by a long list of RCA Victor artists, including Eddy Arnold, Connie Smith, Jerry Reed, Willie Nelson, Hank Snow, and others. The song was written by the Nashville songwriter [[Cy Coben]], a friend of Atkins's. The single reached number 38 on the country charts.&lt;ref&gt;Billboard, June 3, 1967, p. 41.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;McClellan, John; Bratic, Deyan. ''Chet Atkins in Three Dimensions: 50 Years of Legendary Guitar'', vol. 1. Pacific, MO: Mel Bay Publications. pp. 47–49.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;whitburn&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Whitburn|first=Joel|title=Hot Country Songs 1944 to 2008|publisher=Record Research|date=2008|page=392|isbn=978-0-89820-177-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2009, [[Steve Wariner]] released an album titled ''My Tribute to Chet Atkins''. One song from that record, &quot;Producer's Medley&quot;, featured Wariner's recreation of several famous songs that Atkins both produced and performed. &quot;Producer's Medley&quot; won the Grammy for Best Country Instrumental Performance in 2010.

In November 2011, [[Rolling Stone (magazine)|''Rolling Stone'']] ranked Atkins number 21 on their list of the &quot;100 Greatest Guitarists of All Time&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chet Atkins&quot;/&gt;

==Discography==
{{further|Chet Atkins discography}}

==Industry awards==
'''[[Country Music Association]]'''
*[[Country Music Association Awards|1967 Instrumentalist of the Year]]
*[[Country Music Association Awards|1968 Instrumentalist of the Year]]
*[[Country Music Association Awards|1969 Instrumentalist of the Year]]
*[[Country Music Association Awards|1981 Instrumentalist of the Year]]
*[[Country Music Association Awards|1982 Instrumentalist of the Year]]
*[[Country Music Association Awards|1983 Instrumentalist of the Year]]
*[[Country Music Association Awards|1984 Instrumentalist of the Year]]
*[[Country Music Association Awards|1985 Instrumentalist of the Year]]
*[[Country Music Association Awards|1988 Instrumentalist of the Year]]

'''[[Country Music Hall of Fame and Museum]]'''
*[[Inductees of the Country Music Hall of Fame|Inducted in 1973]]

'''[[Grammy Awards]]'''
*[[Grammy Award for Best Country Instrumental Performance|1971 Best Country Instrumental Performance]] &lt;small&gt;with [[Jerry Reed]]&lt;/small&gt;&amp;nbsp;– ''Me and Jerry''
*1972 Best Country Instrumental Performance&amp;nbsp;– &quot;Snowbird&quot;
*1975 Best Country Instrumental Performance &lt;small&gt;with [[Merle Travis]]&lt;/small&gt;&amp;nbsp;– ''The Atkins-Travis Traveling Show''
*1976 Best Country Instrumental Performance&amp;nbsp;– &quot;The Entertainer&quot;
*1977 Best Country Instrumental Performance &lt;small&gt;with [[Les Paul]]&lt;/small&gt;&amp;nbsp;– ''Chester and Lester''
*1982 Best Country Instrumental Performance&amp;nbsp;– ''Country After All These Years''
*1986 Best Country Instrumental Performance &lt;small&gt;with [[Mark Knopfler]]&lt;/small&gt;&amp;nbsp;– &quot;Cosmic Square Dance&quot;
*1991 Best Country Instrumental Performance &lt;small&gt;with [[Mark Knopfler]]&lt;/small&gt;&amp;nbsp;– &quot;So Soft, Your Goodbye&quot;
*[[Grammy Award for Best Country Collaboration with Vocals|1991 Best Country Vocal Collaboration]] &lt;small&gt; with [[Mark Knopfler]]&lt;/small&gt;&amp;nbsp;– &quot;Poor Boy Blues&quot;
*1993 Best Country Instrumental Performance &lt;small&gt;with [[Jerry Reed]]&lt;/small&gt;&amp;nbsp;– ''Sneakin' Around''
*[[Grammy Lifetime Achievement Award|1993 Grammy Lifetime Achievement Award]]'
*1994 Best Country Instrumental Performance &lt;small&gt;with [[Asleep at the Wheel]], [[Eldon Shamblin]], [[Johnny Gimble]], [[Marty Stuart]], Reuben &quot;Lucky Oceans&quot; Gosfield &amp; [[Vince Gill]]&lt;/small&gt;&amp;nbsp;– &quot;Red Wing&quot;
*1995 Best Country Instrumental Performance&amp;nbsp;– &quot;Young Thing&quot;
*1997 Best Country Instrumental Performance&amp;nbsp;– &quot;Jam Man&quot;

'''[[Rock and Roll Hall of Fame]]'''
*[[Inductees of the Rock and Roll Hall of Fame]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
*Kienzle, Rich (1998). &quot;Chet Atkins&quot;. ''The Encyclopedia of Country Music''. Paul Kingsbury, ed. New York: Oxford University Press. pp.&amp;nbsp;26–27.

==External links==
{{Commons category}}
*{{Official website|http://www.misterguitar.com}}
*{{Rockhall}}
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20100427012020/http://www.countrymusichalloffame.org/full-list-of-inductees/view/chet-atkins Chet Atkins at the Country Music Hall of Fame]
*[{{Allmusic|class=artist|id=p1510|pure_url=yes}} Allmusic entry for Chet Atkins]
*[http://www.nashvillesound.net Bob Moore's A-Team Musicians Website]
*{{IMDb name|0040562}}
*{{Pop Chronicles |10 |4}}

{{Chet Atkins}}
{{Grand Ole Opry members}}
{{1970s Country Music Hall of Fame}}
{{2002 Rock and Roll Hall of Fame}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Atkins, Chet}}
[[Category:1924 births]]
[[Category:2001 deaths]]
[[Category:20th-century American singers]]
[[Category:20th-century classical musicians]]
[[Category:Amateur radio people]]
[[Category:American country guitarists]]
[[Category:American country singer-songwriters]]
[[Category:American folk guitarists]]
[[Category:American male guitarists]]
[[Category:American music industry executives]]
[[Category:Record producers from Tennessee]]
[[Category:Deaths from cancer in Tennessee]]
[[Category:Columbia Records artists]]
[[Category:Country Music Hall of Fame inductees]]
[[Category:Country musicians from Tennessee]]
[[Category:Deaths from colorectal cancer]]
[[Category:Fingerstyle guitarists]]
[[Category:Grammy Lifetime Achievement Award winners]]
[[Category:Grand Ole Opry members]]
[[Category:Million Dollar Band (country music group) members]]
[[Category:Music of East Tennessee]]
[[Category:Musicians from Appalachia]]
[[Category:Singers from Tennessee]]
[[Category:Musicians from Knoxville, Tennessee]]
[[Category:People from Union County, Tennessee]]
[[Category:RCA Records Nashville artists]]
[[Category:20th-century American guitarists]]
[[Category:Songwriters from Tennessee]]
[[Category:Guitarists from Tennessee]]
[[Category:20th-century American male musicians]]</text>
      <sha1>ids99ch0xa2vytxq2nmcycslkpz4o4w</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
