  <page>
    <title>Clairvoyance</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7737</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942877686</id>
      <parentid>940036995</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-27T12:21:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>The Eloquent Peasant</username>
        <id>18054835</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Importing Wikidata [[Wikipedia:Short description|short description]]: &quot;Ability to gain information about an object, person, location or physical event through extrasensory perception&quot; ([[Wikipedia:Shortdesc helper|Shortdesc helper]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Ability to gain information about an object, person, location or physical event through extrasensory perception}}
{{About|the alleged extrasensory ability|the 1986 album|Clairvoyance (album)|the 1899 book|Charles Webster Leadbeater}}
{{redirect|Clairvoyant|other uses|Clairvoyant (disambiguation)}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=June 2013}}
{{Paranormal|main}}
[[File:Paul Sedir - Les Miroirs Magiques - 1907 p22 Clairvoyance.gif|thumb|300px|Diagram by the French esotericist {{ill|Paul Sédir|fr}} to explain clairvoyance&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Les Miroirs Magiques |author=Paul Sédir | url=https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Paul_Sedir_-_Les_Miroirs_Magiques_-_1907.pdf |location=Paris |series=Librairie Générale des Sciences Occultes |edition=3rd |year=1907}}, p.22&lt;/ref&gt;]]
'''Clairvoyance''' ({{IPAc-en|k|l|ɛər|ˈ|v|ɔɪ|ə|n|s}}; from [[French language|French]] ''clair'' meaning &quot;clear&quot; and ''voyance'' meaning &quot;vision&quot;) is the ability to gain information about an object, person, location, or physical event through [[extrasensory perception]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://mw1.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/clairvoyance |title=Merriam-Webster Online dictionary, Retrieved 2007-10-05 &quot;1: the power or faculty of discerning objects not present to the senses 2: ability to perceive matters beyond the range of ordinary perception: penetration&quot; |publisher=Mw1.merriam-webster.com |access-date=November 17, 2011 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120227103952/http://mw1.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/clairvoyance |archive-date=February 27, 2012 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/ebc/article-9364105 Britannica Online Encyclopedia], Retrieved 2007-10-07. The ESP entry includes clairvoyance&lt;/ref&gt; Any person who is claimed to have such ability is said accordingly to be a '''clairvoyant''' ({{IPAc-en|k|l|ɛər|ˈ|v|ɔɪ|ə|n|t}})&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oxfordlearnersdictionaries.com/definition/english/clairvoyant_1|title=clairvoyant_1 noun - Definition, pictures, pronunciation and usage notes - Oxford Advanced Learner's Dictionary at OxfordLearnersDictionaries.com|author=|date=|work=OxfordLearnersDictionaries.com|access-date=April 8, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; (&quot;one who sees clearly&quot;).

Claims for the existence of [[paranormal]] and [[psychic]] abilities such as clairvoyance have not been supported by scientific evidence published in high-[[impact factor|impact-factor]] [[peer reviewed|peer-reviewed]] journals.&lt;ref name=skepdic1&gt;[[Robert Todd Carroll|Carroll, Robert Todd]]. (2003). [http://www.skepdic.com/clairvoy.html &quot;Clairvoyance&quot;]. Retrieved 2014-04-30.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Parapsychology]] explores this possibility, but the existence of the paranormal is not accepted by the [[scientific community]].&lt;ref&gt;
* [[Mario Bunge|Bunge, Mario]]. (1983). ''Treatise on Basic Philosophy: Volume 6: Epistemology &amp; Methodology II: Understanding the World''. Springer. p. 226. {{ISBN|90-277-1635-8}} &quot;Despite being several thousand years old, and having attracted a large number of researchers over the past hundred years, we owe no single firm finding to parapsychology: no hard data on telepathy, clairvoyance, precognition, or psychokinesis.&quot;
* [[Victor J. Stenger|Stenger, Victor]]. (1990). ''Physics and Psychics: The Search for a World Beyond the Senses''. Prometheus Books. p. 166. {{ISBN|0-87975-575-X}} &quot;The bottom line is simple: science is based on consensus, and at present a scientific consensus that psychic phenomena exist is still not established.&quot;
* Zechmeister, Eugene; Johnson, James. (1992). ''Critical Thinking: A Functional Approach''. Brooks/Cole Pub. Co. p. 115. {{ISBN|0534165966}} &quot;There exists no good scientific evidence for the existence of paranormal phenomena such as ESP. To be acceptable to the scientific community, evidence must be both valid and reliable.&quot;
* [[Terence Hines|Hines, Terence]]. (2003). ''Pseudoscience and the Paranormal''. Prometheus Books. p. 144. {{ISBN|1-57392-979-4}} &quot;It is important to realize that, in one hundred years of parapsychological investigations, there has never been a single adequate demonstration of the reality of any psi phenomenon.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Parapsychology, including the study of clairvoyance, is an example of [[pseudoscience]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/pseudoscience |title=Dictionary.com &quot;Pseudoscience&quot; |publisher=Dictionary.reference.com |date= |accessdate=September 22, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/pseudo-science/ |title=Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy &quot;Science and Pseudo-Science&quot; |publisher=Plato.stanford.edu |date=September 3, 2008 |accessdate=September 22, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.quackwatch.com/01QuackeryRelatedTopics/russian.html |title=Science Needs to Combat Pseudoscience: A Statement by 32 Russian Scientists and Philosophers |publisher=Quackwatch.com |date=July 17, 1998 |accessdate=September 22, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.csj.org/studyindex/studycrthk/study_pseddoscience/study_factscnfiction5.htm |title=International Cultic Studies Association &quot;Science Fiction in Pseudoscience&quot; |publisher=Csj.org |date= |accessdate=September 22, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
* {{citation|last1=Gross|first1=Paul R|last2=Levitt|first2=Norman|last3=Lewis|first3=Martin W|year=1996|title=The Flight from Science and Reason|publisher=New York Academy of Sciences|page=[https://archive.org/details/flightfromscienc0000unse_w3d8/page/565 565]|isbn=978-0801856761|quote=The overwhelming majority of scientists consider parapsychology, by whatever name, to be pseudoscience.|url=https://archive.org/details/flightfromscienc0000unse_w3d8/page/565}}
* {{citation|last=Friedlander|first=Michael W|year=1998|title=At the Fringes of Science|publisher=Westview Press|page=119|isbn=978-0-8133-2200-1|quote=Parapsychology has failed to gain general scientific acceptance even for its improved methods and claimed successes, and it is still treated with a lopsided ambivalence among the scientific community. Most scientists write it off as pseudoscience unworthy of their time.}}
* {{citation|last1=Pigliucci|first1=Massimo|last2=Boudry|first2=Maarten|year=2013|title=Philosophy of Pseudoscience: Reconsidering the Demarcation Problem|publisher=University Of Chicago Press|page=158|isbn=978-0-226-05196-3|quote=Many observers refer to the field as a 'pseudoscience'. When mainstream scientists say that the field of parapsychology is not scientific, they mean that no satisfying naturalistic cause-and-effect explanation for these supposed effects has yet been proposed and that the field's experiments cannot be consistently replicated.|hdl=1854/LU-3161824}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Cordón&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |author=Cordón, Luis A. |title=Popular Psychology: An Encyclopedia |publisher=[[Greenwood Publishing Group|Greenwood Press]] |location=Westport, Conn |year=2005 |page=[https://archive.org/details/popularpsycholog0000cord/page/182 182] |isbn=978-0-313-32457-4 |oclc= |doi= |accessdate= |quote=The essential problem is that a large portion of the scientific community, including most research psychologists, regards parapsychology as a pseudoscience, due largely to its failure to move beyond null results in the way science usually does. Ordinarily, when experimental evidence fails repeatedly to support a hypothesis, that hypothesis is abandoned. Within parapsychology, however, more than a century of experimentation has failed even to conclusively demonstrate the mere existence of paranormal phenomenon, yet parapsychologists continue to pursue that elusive goal. |url=https://archive.org/details/popularpsycholog0000cord/page/182 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Usage==
Pertaining to the ability of clear-sightedness, clairvoyance refers to the [[paranormal]] ability to see persons and events that are distant in time or space.  It can be divided into roughly three classes: [[precognition]], the ability to perceive or predict future events, [[retrocognition]], the ability to see past events, and [[remote viewing]], the perception of contemporary events happening outside of the range of normal perception.&lt;ref&gt;[[J. Gordon Melton|Melton, John]]. (2001). ''The Encyclopedia of Occultism &amp; Parapsychology''. p. 297. Gale Group, Detroit. {{ISBN|978-0810385702}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

==In history==
Throughout history, there have been numerous places and times in which people have claimed themselves or others to be clairvoyant.

A number of [[Christian saints]] were said to be able to see or know things that were far removed from their immediate sensory perception as a kind of gift from God, including [[Columba of Iona]], [[Padre Pio]] and [[Anne Catherine Emmerich]]. [[Jesus Christ]] in the Gospels is also recorded as being able to know things that were far removed from his immediate human perception.

In other religions, similar stories of certain individuals being able to see things far removed from their immediate sensory perception are commonplace, especially within pagan religions where [[oracle]]s were used. [[Prophecy]] often involved some degree of clairvoyance, especially when future events were predicted.

In most of these cases, however, the ability to see things was attributed to a higher power and not thought of as an ability that lay within the person himself.

== Jainism ==
{{Main|Jain epistemology}}
In [[Jainism]], clairvoyance is regarded as one of the five kinds of knowledge. The beings of hell and heaven ([[Deva (Jainism)|devas]]) are said to possess clairvoyance by birth. According to Jain text [[Sarvārthasiddhi]], &quot;this kind of knowledge has been called ''avadhi'' as it ascertains matter in downward range or knows objects within limits&quot;.{{sfn|S. A. Jain|1992|p=16}}

==Parapsychology==

===Early research===
The earliest record of somnambulistic clairvoyance is credited to the [[Armand-Marie-Jacques de Chastenet, Marquis of Puységur|Marquis de Puységur]], a follower of [[Franz Mesmer]], who in 1784 was treating a local dull-witted peasant named Victor Race. During treatment, Race reportedly would go into trance and undergo a personality change, becoming fluent and articulate, and giving diagnosis and prescription for his own disease as well as those of others.&lt;ref&gt;[[Ann Taves|Taves, Ann]]. (1999). ''Fits, Trances, and Visions: Experiencing Religion and Explaining Experience from Wesley to James''. Princeton University Press. p. 126. {{ISBN|0-691-01024-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; Clairvoyance was a reported ability of some mediums during the [[Spiritualism|spiritualist]] period of the late 19th and early 20th centuries, and psychics of many descriptions have claimed clairvoyant ability up to the present day.&lt;ref&gt;[[Ray Hyman|Hyman, Ray]]. (1985). ''A Critical Historical Overview of Parapsychology''. In [[Paul Kurtz|Kurtz, Paul]]. ''A Skeptic's Handbook of Parapsychology''. Prometheus Books. pp. 3-96. {{ISBN|0-87975-300-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Character reader and Clairvoyant.jpg|thumb|left|Character reader and clairvoyant in a British travelling show of the 1940s, collected by Arthur James Fenwick (1878–1957)]]

Early researchers of clairvoyance included [[William Gregory (chemist)|William Gregory]], Gustav Pagenstecher, and [[Rudolf Tischner]].&lt;ref&gt;Roeckelein, Jon. (2006). ''Elsevier's Dictionary of Psychological Theories''. Elsevier Science. p. 450. {{ISBN|0-444-51750-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; Clairvoyance experiments were reported in 1884 by [[Charles Richet]]. Playing cards were enclosed in envelopes and a subject put under hypnosis attempted to identify them. The subject was reported to have been successful in a series of 133 trials but the results dropped to chance level when performed before a group of scientists in Cambridge. J. M. Peirce and [[Edward Charles Pickering|E. C. Pickering]] reported a similar experiment in which they tested 36 subjects over 23,384 trials which did not obtain above chance scores.&lt;ref&gt;[[C. E. M. Hansel|Hansel, C. E. M]]. ''The Search for a Demonstration of ESP''. In [[Paul Kurtz]]. (1985). ''A Skeptic's Handbook of Parapsychology''. Prometheus Books. pp. 97-127. {{ISBN|0-87975-300-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Ivor Lloyd Tuckett]] (1911) and [[Joseph McCabe]] (1920) analyzed early cases of clairvoyance and came to the conclusion they were best explained by coincidence or fraud.&lt;ref&gt;[[Joseph McCabe|McCabe, Joseph]]. (1920). ''Is Spiritualism Based On Fraud? The Evidence Given By Sir A. C. Doyle and Others Drastically Examined''. Chapter ''The Subtle Art of Clairvoyance''. London: Watts &amp; Co. pp. 93-108&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Ivor Lloyd Tuckett|Tuckett, Ivor Lloyd]]. (1911). ''The Evidence for the Supernatural: A Critical Study Made with &quot;Uncommon Sense&quot;''. Chapter ''Telepathy and Clairvoyance''. K. Paul, Trench, Trübner. pp. 107-142&lt;/ref&gt; In 1919, the magician [[P. T. Selbit]] staged a séance at his own flat in [[Bloomsbury]]. The spiritualist [[Arthur Conan Doyle]] attended the séance and declared the clairvoyance manifestations to be genuine.&lt;ref&gt;Baker, Robert A. (1996). ''Hidden Memories: Voices and Visions From Within''. Prometheus Books. p. 234. {{ISBN|978-1-57392-094-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Christopher, Milbourne. (1996). ''The Illustrated History of Magic''. Greenwood Publishing Group. p. 264. {{ISBN|978-0-435-07016-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A significant development in clairvoyance research came when [[Joseph Banks Rhine|J. B. Rhine]], a parapsychologist at [[Duke University]], introduced a standard methodology, with a standard statistical approach to analyzing data, as part of his research into [[extrasensory perception]]. A number of psychological departments attempted to repeat Rhine's experiments with failure. W. S. Cox (1936) from [[Princeton University]] with 132 subjects produced 25,064 trials in a playing card ESP experiment. Cox concluded &quot;There is no evidence of extrasensory perception either in the 'average man' or of the group investigated or in any particular individual of that group. The discrepancy between these results and those obtained by Rhine is due either to uncontrollable factors in experimental procedure or to the difference in the subjects.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Cox | first1 = W. S. | year = 1936 | title = An experiment in ESP | doi = 10.1037/h0054630 | journal = Journal of Experimental Psychology | volume = 19 | issue = 4| page = 437 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Four other psychological departments failed to replicate Rhine's results.&lt;ref&gt;[[Joseph Jastrow|Jastrow, Joseph]]. (1938). ''ESP, House of Cards''. The American Scholar. Vol. 8, No. 1. pp. 13-22. &quot;Rhine's results fail to be confirmed. At Colgate University (40, 000 tests, 7 subjects), at Chicago (extensive series on 315 students), at Southern Methodist College (75, 000 tests), at Glasgow, Scotland (6, 650 tests), at London University (105, 000 tests), not a single individual was found who under rigidly conducted experiments could score above chance. At Stanford University it has been convincingly shown that the conditions favorable to the intrusion of subtle errors produce above-chance records which come down to chance when sources of error are eliminated.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[C. E. M. Hansel|Hansel, C. E. M]]. ''The Search for a Demonstration of ESP''. In [[Paul Kurtz]]. (1985). ''A Skeptic's Handbook of Parapsychology''. Prometheus Books. pp. 105-127. {{ISBN|0-87975-300-5}}
*{{cite journal | last1 = Adam | first1 = E. T. | year = 1938 | title = A summary of some negative experiments | url = | journal = Journal of Parapsychology | volume = 2 | issue = | pages = 232–236 }}
*Crumbaugh, J. C. (1938). ''An experimental study of extra-sensory perception''. Masters thesis. Southern Methodist University.
*{{cite journal | last1 = Heinlein | first1 = C. P | last2 = Heinlein | first2 = J. H. | year = 1938 | title = Critique of the premises of statistical methodology of parapsychology | url = | journal = Journal of Parapsychology | volume = 5 | issue = | pages = 135–148 | doi=10.1080/00223980.1938.9917558}}
*Willoughby, R. R. (1938). ''Further card-guessing experiments''. ''Journal of Psychology'' 18: 3-13.&lt;/ref&gt; It was revealed that Rhine's experiments contained methodological flaws and procedural errors.&lt;ref&gt;[[Harold Gulliksen|Gulliksen, Harold]]. (1938). ''Extra-Sensory Perception: What Is It?''. ''American Journal of Sociology''. Vol. 43, No. 4. pp. 623-634. &quot;Investigating Rhine's methods, we find that his mathematical methods are wrong and that the effect of this error would in some cases be negligible and in others very marked. We find that many of his experiments were set up in a manner which would tend to increase, instead of to diminish, the possibility of systematic clerical errors; and lastly, that the ESP cards can be read from the back.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Wynn, Charles; Wiggins, Arthur. (2001). ''Quantum Leaps in the Wrong Direction: Where Real Science Ends...and Pseudoscience Begins''. Joseph Henry Press. p. 156. {{ISBN|978-0-309-07309-7}} &quot;In 1940, Rhine coauthored a book, ''Extrasensory Perception After Sixty Years'' in which he suggested that something more than mere guess work was involved in his experiments. He was right! It is now known that the experiments conducted in his laboratory contained serious methodological flaws. Tests often took place with minimal or no screening between the subject and the person administering the test. Subjects could see the backs of cards that were later discovered to be so cheaply printed that a faint outline of the symbol could be seen. Furthermore, in face-to-face tests, subjects could see card faces reflected in the tester's eyeglasses or cornea. They were even able to (consciously or unconsciously) pick up clues from the tester's facial expression and voice inflection. In addition, an observant subject could identify the cards by certain irregularities like warped edges, spots on the backs, or design imperfections.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Terence Hines|Hines, Terence]]. (2003). ''Pseudoscience and the Paranormal''. Prometheus Books. p. 122. {{ISBN|978-1573929790}} &quot;The procedural errors in the Rhine experiments have been extremely damaging to his claims to have demonstrated the existence of ESP. Equally damaging has been the fact that the results have not replicated when the experiments have been conducted in other laboratories.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Eileen Garrett]] was tested by Rhine at Duke University in 1933 with [[Zener cards]]. Certain symbols that were placed on the cards and sealed in an envelope, and she was asked to guess their contents. She performed poorly and later criticized the tests by claiming the cards lacked a [[Energy (esotericism)|psychic energy]] called &quot;energy stimulus&quot; and that she could not perform clairvoyance to order.&lt;ref&gt;Hazelgrove, Jenny. (2000). ''Spiritualism and British Society Between the Wars''. Manchester University Press. p. 204. {{ISBN|978-0719055591}}&lt;/ref&gt; The parapsychologist [[Samuel Soal]] and his colleagues tested Garrett in May, 1937. Most of the experiments were carried out in the Psychological Laboratory at the [[University College London]]. A total of over 12,000 guesses were recorded but Garrett failed to produce above chance level.&lt;ref&gt;Russell, A. S; Benn, John Andrews. (1938). ''Discovery the Popular Journal of Knowledge''. Cambridge University Press. pp. 305-306&lt;/ref&gt; In his report Soal wrote &quot;In the case of Mrs. Eileen Garrett we fail to find the slightest confirmation of Dr. J. B. Rhine's remarkable claims relating to her alleged powers of extra-sensory perception. Not only did she fail when I took charge of the experiments, but she failed equally when four other carefully trained experimenters took my place.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Samuel Soal|Soal, Samuel]]. ''A Repetition of Dr. Rhine's work with Mrs. Eileen Garrett''. Proc. S.P.R. Vol. XLII. pp. 84-85. Also quoted in [[Antony Flew]]. (1955). ''A New Approach To Psychical Research''. Watts &amp; Co. pp. 90-92.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Remote viewing===

[[Remote viewing]], also known as remote sensing, remote perception, telesthesia and travelling clairvoyance is the alleged paranormal ability to perceive a remote or hidden target without support of the senses.&lt;ref&gt;Blom, Jan. (2009). ''A Dictionary of Hallucinations''. Springer. p. 451. {{ISBN|978-1441912220}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A well known study of remote viewing in recent times has been the US government-funded project at the [[SRI International|Stanford Research Institute]] during the 1970s through the mid-1990s. In 1972, [[Harold E. Puthoff|Harold Puthoff]] and [[Russell Targ]] initiated a series of human subject studies to determine whether participants (the ''viewers'' or ''percipients'') could reliably identify and accurately describe salient features of remote locations or ''targets''. In the early studies, a human ''sender'' was typically present at the remote location, as part of the experiment protocol. A three-step process was used, the first step being to randomly select the target conditions to be experienced by the senders. Secondly, in the viewing step, participants were asked to verbally express or sketch their impressions of the remote scene. Thirdly, in the judging step, these descriptions were matched by separate judges, as closely as possible, with the intended targets. The term [[remote viewing]] was coined to describe this overall process. The first paper by Puthoff and Targ on remote viewing was published in ''[[Nature (journal)|Nature]]'' in March 1974; in it, the team reported some degree of remote viewing success.&lt;ref name=nat251&gt;{{Cite journal|doi=10.1038/251602a0 |title=Information transmission under conditions of sensory shielding |year=1974 |first=Russel |last=Targ |first2=Harold |last2=Puthoff |journal=Nature |volume=251 |pages=602–607 |pmid=4423858 |issue=5476|bibcode=1974Natur.251..602T }}&lt;/ref&gt; After the publication of these findings, other attempts to replicate the experiments were carried out &lt;ref name=hast1&gt;{{Cite journal|doi=10.1109/PROC.1976.10369 |title=A confirmatory remote viewing experiment in a group setting |date=October 1976 |author=Hastings, A.C. |journal=Proceedings of the IEEE |volume=64 |pages=1544–1545 |last2=Hurt |first2=D.B.|issue=10}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|doi=10.1109/PROC.1976.10371 |title=Preliminary experiments in group 'Remote viewing' |date=October 1976 |author=Whitson, T.W. |journal=Proceedings of the IEEE |volume=64 |pages=1550–1551 |last2=Bogart |first2=D.N. |last3=Palmer |first3=J. |last4=Tart |first4=C.T.|issue=10}}&lt;/ref&gt; with remotely linked groups using computer conferencing.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|doi=10.1109/PROC.1976.10372 |title=Remote viewing experiments through computer conferencing |date=October 1976 |author=Vallee, J. |journal=Proceedings of the IEEE |volume=64 |pages=1551–1552 |last2=Hastings |first2=A.C. |last3=Askevold |first3=G.|issue=10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The psychologists [[David Marks (psychologist)|David Marks]] and Richard Kammann attempted to replicate Targ and Puthoff's remote viewing experiments that were carried out in the 1970s at the Stanford Research Institute. In a series of 35 studies, they were unable to replicate the results so investigated the procedure of the original experiments. Marks and Kammann discovered that the notes given to the judges in Targ and Puthoff's experiments contained clues as to which order they were carried out, such as referring to yesterday's two targets, or they had the date of the session written at the top of the page. They concluded that these clues were the reason for the experiment's high hit rates.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Marks | first1 = David | authorlink = David Marks (psychologist) | last2 = Kammann | first2 = Richard | year = 1978 | title = Information transmission in remote viewing experiments | url = | journal = Nature | volume = 274 | issue = 5672| pages = 680–681 | doi=10.1038/274680a0| bibcode = 1978Natur.274..680M }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Marks | first1 = David | authorlink = David Marks (psychologist) | year = 1981 | title = Sensory cues invalidate remote viewing experiments | url = | journal = Nature | volume = 292 | issue = 5819| page = 177 | doi=10.1038/292177a0| bibcode = 1981Natur.292..177M }}&lt;/ref&gt; Marks was able to achieve 100 per cent accuracy without visiting any of the sites himself but by using cues.&lt;ref&gt;Bridgstock, Martin. (2009). ''Beyond Belief: Skepticism, Science and the Paranormal''. Cambridge University Press. p. 106. {{ISBN|978-0521758932}} &quot;The explanation used by Marks and Kammann clearly involves the use of [[Occam's razor]]. Marks and Kammann argued that the 'cues' – clues to the order in which sites had been visited—provided sufficient information for the results, without any recourse to extrasensory perception. Indeed Marks himself was able to achieve 100 percent accuracy in allocating some transcripts to sites without visiting any of the sites himself, purely on the ground basis of the cues. From Occam's razor, it follows that if a straightforward natural explanation exists, there is no need for the spectacular paranormal explanation: Targ and Puthoff's claims are not justified&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; [[James Randi]] has written controlled tests by several other researchers, eliminating several sources of cuing and extraneous evidence present in the original tests, produced negative results. Students were also able to solve Puthoff and Targ's locations from the clues that had inadvertently been included in the transcripts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.randi.org/encyclopedia/remote%20viewing.html |title=James Randi Educational Foundation — An Encyclopedia of Claims, Frauds, and Hoaxes of the Occult and Supernatural |publisher=Randi.org |accessdate=2014-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1980, [[Charles Tart]] claimed that a rejudging of the transcripts from one of Targ and Puthoff's experiments revealed an above-chance result.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Tart | first1 = Charles | authorlink = Charles Tart | authorlink2 = Harold E. Puthoff | authorlink3 = Russell Targ | last2 = Puthoff | first2 = Harold | last3 = Targ | first3 = Russell | year = 1980 | title = Information Transmission in Remote Viewing Experiments | url = | journal = Nature | volume = 284 | issue = 5752| page = 191 | doi=10.1038/284191a0 | pmid=7360248| bibcode = 1980Natur.284..191T }}&lt;/ref&gt; Targ and Puthoff again refused to provide copies of the transcripts and it was not until July 1985 that they were made available for study when it was discovered they still contained [[sensory cue]]s.&lt;ref&gt;[[Terence Hines]]. (2003). ''Pseudoscience and the Paranormal''. Prometheus Books. p. 136. {{ISBN|978-1573929790}}&lt;/ref&gt; Marks and Christopher Scott (1986) wrote &quot;considering the importance for the remote viewing hypothesis of adequate cue removal, Tart's failure to perform this basic task seems beyond comprehension. As previously concluded, remote viewing has not been demonstrated in the experiments conducted by Puthoff and Targ, only the repeated failure of the investigators to remove sensory cues.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Marks | first1 = David | authorlink = David Marks (psychologist) | last2 = Scott | first2 = Christopher | year = 1986 | title = Remote Viewing Exposed | url = | journal = Nature | volume = 319 | issue = 6053| page = 444 | doi=10.1038/319444a0 | pmid=3945330| bibcode = 1986Natur.319..444M }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1982 [[Robert G. Jahn|Robert Jahn]], then Dean of the School of Engineering at Princeton University wrote a comprehensive review of psychic phenomena from an engineering perspective. His paper included numerous references to remote viewing studies at the time.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|doi=10.1109/PROC.1982.12260 |title=The persistent paradox of psychic phenomena: An engineering perspective |date=February 1982 |author=Jahn, R.G. |url=http://www.princeton.edu/~pear/pdfs/1982-persistant-paradox-psychic-phenomena.pdf |journal=Proceedings of the IEEE |volume=70 |pages=136–170|issue=2|citeseerx=10.1.1.15.8760 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Statistical flaws in his work have been proposed by others in the parapsychological community and within the general scientific community.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jeffers2006&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |url=http://www.csicop.org/si/show/pear_proposition_fact_or_fallacy/ |title= The PEAR proposition: Fact or fallacy? |journal= [[Skeptical Inquirer]] |author=Stanley Jeffers |date= May–June 2006 |accessdate= 2014-01-24 |volume= 30.3}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=George P. Hansen |url=http://www.tricksterbook.com/ArticlesOnline/PEARCritique.htm |title=Princeton [PEAR&amp;#93; Remote-Viewing Experiments - A Critique |publisher=Tricksterbook.com |accessdate=2014-04-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Scientific reception==

According to scientific research, clairvoyance is generally explained as the result of [[confirmation bias]], [[Observer-expectancy effect|expectancy bias]], fraud, [[hallucination]], self-[[delusion]], [[sensory leakage]], [[subjective validation]], [[wishful thinking]] or failures to appreciate the base rate of chance occurrences and not as a paranormal power.&lt;ref name=skepdic1/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Rawcliffe, Donovan. (1988). ''Occult and Supernatural Phenomena''. Dover Publications. pp. 367-463. {{ISBN|0-486-20503-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Graham Reed (psychologist)|Reed, Graham]]. (1988). ''The Psychology of Anomalous Experience: A Cognitive Approach''. Prometheus Books. {{ISBN|0-87975-435-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Zusne, Leonard; Jones, Warren. (1989). ''Anomalistic Psychology: A Study of Magical Thinking''. Lawrence Erlbaum Associates. pp. 152-168. {{ISBN|0-8058-0508-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; Parapsychology is regarded by the scientific community as a [[pseudoscience]].&lt;ref&gt;Friedlander, Michael W. (1998). ''At the Fringes of Science''. Westview Press. p. 119. {{ISBN|0-8133-2200-6}} &quot;Parapsychology has failed to gain general scientific acceptance even for its improved methods and claimed successes, and it is still treated with a lopsided ambivalence among the scientific community. Most scientists write it off as pseudoscience unworthy of their time.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Massimo Pigliucci|Pigliucci, Massimo]]; [[Maarten Boudry|Boudry, Maarten]]. (2013). ''Philosophy of Pseudoscience: Reconsidering the Demarcation Problem''. University Of Chicago Press p. 158. {{ISBN|978-0-226-05196-3}} &quot;Many observers refer to the field as a &quot;pseudoscience&quot;. When mainstream scientists say that the field of parapsychology is not scientific, they mean that no satisfying naturalistic cause-and-effect explanation for these supposed effects has yet been proposed and that the field's experiments cannot be consistently replicated.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; In 1988, the [[United States National Research Council|US National Research Council]] concluded &quot;The committee finds no scientific justification from research conducted over a period of 130 years, for the existence of parapsychological phenomena.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Thomas Gilovich|Gilovich, Thomas]]. (1993). ''How We Know What Isn't So: The Fallibility of Human Reason in Everyday Life''. Free Press. p. 160. {{ISBN|978-0-02-911706-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Scientific skepticism|Skeptics]] say that if clairvoyance were a reality it would have become abundantly clear. They also contend that those who believe in [[paranormal]] phenomena do so for merely psychological reasons.&lt;ref&gt;[[Chris French|French, Chis]]; Wilson, Krissy. (2007). ''Cognitive Factors Underlying Paranormal Beliefs and Experiences''. In Sala, Sergio. ''Tall Tales About the Mind and Brain: Separating Fact From Fiction''. Oxford: Oxford University Press. pp. 3-22. {{ISBN|978-0198568773}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to [[David Myers (academic)|David G. Myers]] (''Psychology,'' 8th ed.):

&lt;blockquote&gt;The search for a valid and reliable test of clairvoyance has resulted in thousands of experiments. One controlled procedure has invited 'senders' to telepathically transmit one of four visual images to 'receivers' deprived of sensation in a nearby chamber (Bem &amp; Honorton, 1994). The result? A reported 32 percent accurate response rate, surpassing the chance rate of 25 percent. But follow-up studies have (depending on who was summarizing the results) failed to replicate the phenomenon or produced mixed results (Bem &amp; others, 2001; Milton &amp; Wiseman, 2002; Storm, 2000, 2003).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;One skeptic, magician [[James Randi]], has a longstanding offer—now [[One Million Dollar Paranormal Challenge|U.S. $1 million]]—&quot;to anyone who proves a genuine psychic power under proper observing conditions&quot; (Randi, 1999). French, Australian, and Indian groups have parallel offers of up to 200,000 euros to anyone with demonstrable paranormal abilities (CFI, 2003). Large as these sums are, the scientific seal of approval would be worth far more to anyone whose claims could be authenticated. To refute those who say there is no ESP, one need only produce a single person who can demonstrate a single, reproducible ESP phenomenon. So far, no such person has emerged. Randi's offer has been publicized for three decades and dozens of people have been tested, sometimes under the scrutiny of an independent panel of judges. Still, nothing.  &quot;People's desire to believe in the paranormal is stronger than all the evidence that it does not exist.&quot; [[Susan Blackmore]], &quot;Blackmore's first law&quot;, 2004.&lt;ref&gt;[[David Myers (academic)|Myers, David]]. (2006). ''Psychology''. Worth Publishers; 8th edition. {{ISBN|978-0716764281}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Clairvoyance is considered [[hallucination]] by mainstream [[psychiatry]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Blom|first1=Jan Dirk|title=A Dictionary of Hallucinations|url=https://books.google.com/?id=qbF44AEMGdcC&amp;pg=PA99&amp;lpg=PA99&amp;dq=clairvoyance+is+hallucination#v=onepage&amp;q=clairvoyance%20is%20hallucination&amp;f=false|accessdate=2012-01-11|year=2010|publisher=Springer Science+Business Media, LLC|location=New York, Dordrecht, Heidelberg, London|isbn=978-1-4419-1222-0|oclc=|doi=10.1007/978-1-4419-1223-7|page=99|quote='''Clairvoyance'''&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Also known as lucidity, telesthesia, and cryptestesia. ''Clairvoyance'' is French for seeing clearly. The term is used in the parapsychological literature to denote a * visual or * compound hallucination attributable to a metaphysical source. It is therefore interpreted as * telepathic, * veridical or at least * coincidental hallucination.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;'''Reference'''&lt;br&gt;Guily, R.E. (1991) ''Harper's encyclopedia of mystical and paranormal experience.'' New York, NY: Castle Books.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Div col|colwidth=30em}}
* [[Astral projection]]
* [[Aura (paranormal)|Aura]]
* [[C. W. Leadbeater#Clairvoyance|''Clairvoyance'' (book)]]
* [[Inner eye]]
* [[List of topics characterized as pseudoscience]]
* [[Out-of-body experience]]
* [[Photoacoustic effect]]
* [[Postdiction]] (retroactive clairvoyance)
* [[Precognition]]
* [[Remote viewing]]
* [[Second sight]]
* [[Synchronicity]]
* [[Thought-Forms (book)|''Thought-Forms'' (book)]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

== Bibliography ==
*{{cite book|author=S. A. Jain|title=Reality|date=1992|publisher=Jwalamalini Trust|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=uRIaAAAAMAAJ|archive-url=https://archive.org/details/Reality_JMT|archive-date=2015|quote=Not in Copyright.}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin|40em}}
* [[James Alcock]] (1981). ''Parapsychology: Science or Magic? A Psychological Perspective''. Pergamon Press. {{ISBN|0-08-025772-0}}.
* Willis Dutcher (1922). [https://archive.org/stream/onothersideoffoo00dutcrich#page/n3/mode/2up ''On the Other Side of the Footlights: An Expose of Routines, Apparatus and Deceptions Resorted to by Mediums, Clairvoyants, Fortune Tellers and Crystal Gazers in Deluding the Public]''. Berlin, WI: Heaney Magic.
* [[Thomas Gilovich]] (1993). ''How We Know What Isn't So: Fallibility of Human Reason in Everyday Life''. Free Press. {{ISBN|978-0-02-911706-4}}.
* [[Henry Gordon (magician)|Henry Gordon]] (1988). ''Extrasensory Deception: ESP, Psychics, Shirley MacLaine, Ghosts, UFOs''. Macmillan of Canada. {{ISBN|0-7715-9539-5}}. 
*[[Donald O. Hebb|Donald Hebb]] (1980). [https://books.google.com/books?id=DvkhAwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA140 ''Extrasensory Perception: A Problem'']. In ''Essays on Mind''. Lawrence Erlbaum Associates. {{ISBN|978-0-898-59017-3}}.
* [[C. E. M. Hansel]] (1989). ''The Search for Psychic Power: ESP and Parapsychology Revisited''. Prometheus Books. {{ISBN|0-87975-516-4}}. 
* [[Terence Hines]] (2003). ''Pseudoscience and the Paranormal''. Prometheus Books. {{ISBN|1-57392-979-4}}.
* [[David Marks (psychologist)|David Marks]]. (2000). ''[[The Psychology of the Psychic]]'' (2nd Edition). Prometheus Books. {{ISBN|1-57392-798-8}}.
* [[Joseph McCabe]] (1920). [https://archive.org/stream/isspiritualismba00mccarich#page/93/mode/2up ''Is Spiritualism Based On Fraud? The Evidence Given By Sir A. C. Doyle and Others Drastically Examined'']. Chapter &quot;The Subtle Art of Clairvoyance&quot;. London: Watts &amp; Co. pp.&amp;nbsp;93–108.
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Wiktionary|clairvoyance|clairvoyant}}
{{Wikisource1911Enc|clairvoyance}}
* [http://www.csicop.org/sb/show/springer_psychic_a_study_in_clairvoyance/ Springer Psychic: &quot;A Study in 'Clairvoyance'{{-&quot;}}]—[[Joe Nickell]]
* [https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2014/01/140114092142.htm &quot;Debunking the Sixth Sense&quot;]—''[[Science Daily]]''
* [http://skepdic.com/clairvoy.html &quot;Clairvoyance&quot;]—''[[The Skeptic's Dictionary]]''

{{Parapsychology}}
{{New Age Movement}}

[[Category:New Age practices]]
[[Category:Paranormal terminology]]
[[Category:Parapsychology]]
[[Category:Pseudoscience]]
[[Category:Psychic powers]]
[[Category:Telepathy]]

[[de:Hellsehen]]</text>
      <sha1>copiaolfk4sshm83lukdt84nz1sqqro</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
