  <page>
    <title>Anaïs Nin</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2919</id>
    <revision>
      <id>937371631</id>
      <parentid>935683606</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-24T16:21:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>86.155.157.169</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|writer of novels, short stories.}}
{{Infobox person
| name         = Anaïs Nin
| image        = George Leite and Anaïs Nin at daliel's bookstore in Berkeley, CA, 1946.jpg
| imagesize    = 
| caption      = Nin at a book reading with [[George Leite]] in Berkeley, California, 1946
| pseudonym    =
| birth_name   = Angela Anaïs Juana Antolina Rosa Edelmira Nin y Culmell
| birth_date   = {{birth date|1903|02|21}}
| birth_place   = [[Neuilly-sur-Seine]], France
| death_date   = {{death date and age|1977|1|14|1903|2|21}}
| death_place  = [[Los Angeles]], California, U.S.
| occupation   = Author
| organization       = [[International College, Los Angeles]]
| nationality  = [[Cuban Americans|Cuban American]]
| parents= {{plainlist| [[Joaquín Nin]]
*Rose Culmell}}
| relatives    = [[Joaquín Nin-Culmell]] (brother)
| spouse       = {{plainlist|{{marriage|[[Hugh Parker Guiler]]&lt;br&gt;|1923|1977|end=her death}}
*{{marriage|[[Rupert Pole]] ([[bigamy]])&lt;br&gt;|1955|1966|end=[[Annulment|{{abbr|annul.|annulled}}]]}}
}}
| signature= Anaïs Nin signature.svg
}}
'''Angela Anaïs Juana Antolina Rosa Edelmira Nin y Culmell''' (February 21, 1903 – January 14, 1977), known professionally as '''Anaïs Nin''' ({{IPAc-en|æ|n|ə|.|iː|s|_|n|iː|n|}},&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=American Lives: An Anthology of Autobiographical Writing|page=597|editor=Sayre, Robert F.|year=1994|publisher=University of Wisconsin Press|isbn= 978-0-299-14244-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; {{IPA-fr|ana.is nin|lang}}) was a French-Cuban American diarist, essayist, novelist, and writer of short stories and erotica. Born to Cuban parents in [[France]], Nin was the daughter of composer [[Joaquín Nin]] and Rosa Culmell, a classically trained singer. Nin spent her early years in  Spain and Cuba, about sixteen years in Paris (1924–1940), and the remaining half of her life in the United States, where she became an established author.

Beginning at age eleven, Nin wrote [[diary|journal]]s prolifically for six decades and even up until her death. Her journals, many of which were published during her lifetime, detail her private thoughts and personal relationships. Her journals also describe her marriage to [[Hugh Parker Guiler]] and marriage to [[Rupert Pole]], in addition to her numerous affairs, including those with psychoanalyst [[Otto Rank]] and writer [[Henry Miller]], both of whom profoundly influenced Nin and her writing.

In addition to her journals, Nin wrote several novels, critical studies, essays, short stories, and volumes of [[erotic literature|erotica]]. Much of her work, including the collections of erotica ''[[Delta of Venus]]'' and ''[[Little Birds]]'', was published posthumously amid renewed critical interest in her life and work. Nin spent her later life in Los Angeles, California, where she died of cervical cancer in 1977.

==Early life==
Anaïs Nin was born in [[Neuilly-sur-Seine|Neuilly]], France, to [[Joaquín Nin]], a Cuban pianist and composer of [[Catalans|Catalan]] Spanish descent, and Rosa Culmell,&lt;ref name=&quot;kir&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.kirjasto.sci.fi/anaisnin.htm |title=Anaïs Nin profile|website=kirjasto.sci.fi|first=Petri|last=Liukkonen|publisher=[[Kuusankoski]] Public Library|location=Finland |archiveurl=http://arquivo.pt/wayback/20120123084641/http%3A//www%2Ekirjasto%2Esci%2Efi/anaisnin%2Ehtm|archivedate= 23 January 2012|url-status=dead|language=fi}}&lt;/ref&gt; a classically trained Cuban singer of French and Danish descent.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.morbidoutlook.com/nonfiction/articles/2001_03_anaisnin.html|title= The Unique Anaïs Nin|author=Fenner, Andrew|accessdate=December 26, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Her father's grandfather had fled France during the [[French Revolution|Revolution]], going first to [[Saint-Domingue]], then [[New Orleans]], and finally to [[Cuba]] where he helped build that country's first railway.{{sfn|Nin|1966|p=125}}

Nin was raised a [[Roman Catholic]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=A Spy In The House Of Love (Foreword)|author=Stuhlmann, Gunther|page=3|publisher=Swallow Press}}&lt;/ref&gt; but left the church when she was 16 years old.{{sfn|Nin|DuBow|1994|p=126}} She spent her childhood and early life in Europe. Her  parents separated when she was two; her mother then moved Anaïs and her two brothers, Thorvald Nin and [[Joaquín Nin-Culmell]], to [[Barcelona]], and then to New York City, where she attended high school. Nin would drop out of high school in 1919 at age sixteen,{{sfn|Nin|DuBow|1994|p=xxi}} and according to her diaries, ''Volume One, 1931–1934'', later began working as an artist's model. After being in the United States for several years, Nin had forgotten how to speak Spanish, but retained her French and became fluent in English.{{sfn|Nin|1966|p=183}}

On March 3, 1923, in [[Havana]], Cuba, Nin married her first husband, [[Hugh Parker Guiler]] (1898–1985), a banker and artist, later known as &quot;Ian Hugo&quot; when he became a maker of [[experimental film]]s in the late 1940s. The couple moved to Paris the following year, where Guiler pursued his banking career and Nin began to pursue her interest in writing; in her diaries she also mentions having trained as a [[flamenco]] dancer in Paris in the mid-to-late 1920s with [[Francisco Miralles Arnau]]. Her first published work was a critical evaluation of [[D. H. Lawrence]] called ''[[D. H. Lawrence: An Unprofessional Study]]'', which she wrote in sixteen days.&lt;ref name=&quot;kir&quot;/&gt;

Nin became profoundly interested in [[psychoanalysis]] and would study it extensively, first with [[René Allendy]] in 1932 and then with [[Otto Rank]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=American Writers|author=Oakes, Elizabeth H.|page=255|publisher=Infobase Publishing|year=2004|isbn=978-1-438-10809-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; Both men eventually became her lovers, as she recounts in her ''Journal''.&lt;ref&gt;Anais Nin, ''Journal (1931-1934)'', Paris: Le Livre de Poche, 1966, pp. 138, 171–172, 237, 404, 505, passim.&lt;/ref&gt; On her second visit to Rank, Nin reflects on her desire to be &quot;re-born&quot; as a woman and artist. Rank, she observes, helped her move back and forth between what she could verbalize in her journals and what remained unarticulated. She discovered the quality and depth of her feelings in the wordless transitions between what she could say and what she could not say.  &quot;As he talked, I thought of my difficulties with writing, my struggles to articulate feelings not easily expressed. Of my struggles to find a language for intuition, feeling, instincts which are, in themselves, elusive, subtle, and wordless.&quot;{{sfn|Nin|1966|p=276}}

In the late summer of 1939, when residents from overseas were urged to leave France due to the approaching [[Second World War|war]], Nin left Paris and returned to New York City with her husband. (Guiler was, according to his own wishes, edited out of the diaries published during Nin's lifetime; his role in her life is therefore difficult to gauge.)&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Several persons, when faced with the question of whether they wanted to remain in the diary 'as is' ... chose to be deleted altogether from the manuscript (including her husband and some members of her family).&quot; ''The Diary of Anaïs Nin'', ed. by Gunther Stuhlmann. Harcourt, 1966, p. xi.&lt;/ref&gt; During the war, Nin sent her books to Frances Steloff of the [[Gotham Book Mart]] in New York for safekeeping.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.anaisnin.com/history/Steloff.html |title=Frances Steloff |publisher=AnaisNin.com |date= |accessdate=October 2, 2017|author=Griffin, M. Collins}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In New York, Anaïs rejoined Otto Rank, who had previously moved there, and moved into his apartment. She actually began to act as a psychoanalyst herself, seeing patients in the room next to Rank's, and having sex with her patients on the psychoanalytic couch.{{sfn|Nin|1967|pages=17–25}} She quit after several months, however, stating: &quot;I found that I wasn't good because I wasn't objective. I was haunted by my patients. I wanted to intercede.&quot;&lt;ref name=fraser/&gt;  It was in New York that she met the Japanese-American modernist photographer [[Soichi Sunami]], who went on to photograph her for many of her books.

==Literary career==
===Journals===
Nin's most studied works are her diaries or journals, which she began writing in her adolescence. The published journals, which span several decades from 1933 onward, provide a deeply explorative insight into her personal life and relationships. Nin was acquainted, often quite intimately, with a number of prominent authors, artists, [[psychoanalysis|psychoanalysts]], and other figures, and wrote of them often, especially Otto Rank. Moreover, as a female author describing a primarily masculine constellation of celebrities, Nin's journals have acquired importance as a counterbalancing perspective.

In the third volume of her unexpurgated journal, ''Incest'', she wrote about her father candidly and graphically (207–15), detailing his sexual abuse of her at age nine.

Previously unpublished works are coming to light in ''A Café in Space, the Anaïs Nin Literary Journal'', which includes &quot;Anaïs Nin and Joaquín Nin y Castellanos: Prelude to a Symphony—Letters between a father and daughter&quot;.

So far sixteen volumes of her journals have been published.  All but the last five of her adult journals are in expurgated form.

===Erotic writings===
Nin is hailed by many critics as one of the finest writers of [[Women's erotica|female erotica]]. She was one of the first women known to explore fully the realm of erotic writing, and certainly the first prominent woman in the modern West known to write erotica. Before her, erotica acknowledged to be written by women was rare, with a few notable exceptions, such as the work of [[Kate Chopin]]. Nin often cited authors [[Djuna Barnes]] and D. H. Lawrence as inspirations, and she states in ''Volume One'' of her diaries that she drew inspiration from [[Marcel Proust]],{{sfn|Nin|1966|p=15}} [[André Gide]],{{sfn|Nin|1966|p=45}} [[Jean Cocteau]],{{sfn|Nin|1966|pages=60, 109}} [[Paul Valéry]],{{sfn|Nin|1966|p=60}} and [[Arthur Rimbaud]].{{sfn|Nin|1966|p=29, 40}}

According to ''Volume One'' of her diaries, ''1931–1934'', published in 1966, Nin first came across erotica when she returned to Paris with her husband, mother and two brothers in her late teens. They rented the apartment of an American man who was away for the summer, and Nin came across a number of French paperbacks: &quot;One by one, I read these books, which were completely new to me.  I had never read erotic literature in America... They overwhelmed me.  I was innocent before I read them, but by the time I had read them all, there was nothing I did not know about sexual exploits... I had my degree in erotic lore.&quot;{{sfn|Nin|1966|p=96}}

Faced with a desperate need for money, Nin, Henry Miller and some of their friends began in the 1940s to write erotic and pornographic narratives for an anonymous &quot;collector&quot; for a dollar a page, somewhat as a joke.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Gertzman, Jay A.|page=344|title=Bookleggers and Smuthounds: The Trade in Erotica, 1920-1940|publisher=University of Pennsylvania Press|year=2011|edition=Reprint|isbn=978-0-812-20585-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; (It is not clear whether Miller actually wrote these stories or merely allowed his name to be used.&lt;ref&gt;[[Noël Riley Fitch]], ''Anaïs: The Erotic Life of Anaïs Nin'' (Boston: [[Little, Brown and Company]], 1993) {{ISBN|0-316-28428-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;)  Nin considered the characters in her erotica to be extreme caricatures and never intended the work to be published, but changed her mind in the early 1970s and allowed them to be published as ''[[Delta of Venus]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Kowaleski-Wallace|first=Elizabeth|title=Encyclopedia of Feminist Literary Theory|publisher=[[Taylor &amp; Francis]]|year=1997|p=[https://archive.org/details/encyclopediaoffe0053unse/page/190 190]|isbn=978-0-8153-0824-9|url=https://archive.org/details/encyclopediaoffe0053unse/page/190}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Andrew|last=Gibson|title=Postmodernity, Ethics and the Novel: From Leavis to Levinas|publisher=Routledge|year=1999|isbn=978-0-415-19895-0|p=[https://archive.org/details/postmodernityeth00gibs_0/page/177 177]|url=https://archive.org/details/postmodernityeth00gibs_0/page/177}}&lt;/ref&gt; and ''[[Little Birds]]''. In 2016, a previously-undiscovered collection of erotica, ''Auletris'', was published for the first time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|work=Psychology Today|url=https://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/the-empowerment-diary/201611/the-sexual-censorship-controversy|date=November 3, 2016|author=Raab, Diana|title=The Sexual Censorship Controversy|accessdate=October 5, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Nin was a friend, and in some cases lover, of many literary figures, including Henry Miller, [[John Steinbeck]], [[Antonin Artaud]], [[Edmund Wilson]], [[Gore Vidal]], [[James Agee]], [[James Leo Herlihy]], and [[Lawrence Durrell]]. Her passionate love affair and friendship with Miller strongly influenced her both sexually and as an author. Claims that Nin was [[bisexual]] were given added circulation by the [[Philip Kaufman]] film ''[[Henry &amp; June]]'' about Henry Miller and his second wife [[June Miller]]. The first unexpurgated portion of Nin's journal to be published, ''[[Henry and June]]'', makes it clear that Nin was stirred by June to the point of saying (paraphrasing), &quot;I have become June,&quot; though it is unclear whether she consummated her feelings for her sexually. To both Anaïs and Henry, June was a femme fatale—irresistible, cunning, erotic. Nin gave June money, jewelry, clothes, often leaving herself broke.

===Novels and other publications===
In addition to her journals and collections of erotica, Nin wrote several novels, which were frequently associated by critics with [[Surrealism#Surrealist literature|surrealism]].&lt;ref name=eb&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.britannica.com/biography/Anais-Nin|title=Anaïs Nin|author= The Editors of Encyclopædia Britannica|work= [[Encyclopædia Britannica]]|accessdate=October 6, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Her first book of fiction, ''[[House of Incest]]'' (1936), contains heavily veiled allusions to a brief sexual relationship Nin had with her father in 1933: While visiting her estranged father in France, the then-thirty-year-old Nin had a brief incestuous sexual relationship with him.&lt;ref name=father&gt;{{cite journal|author=Charnock, Ruth|date=September 30, 2013|title= Incest in the 1990s: Reading Anaïs Nin's 'Father Story'|journal=Life Writing|volume = 11|pages=55–68|doi=10.1080/14484528.2013.838732|url=http://eprints.lincoln.ac.uk/11712/1/Life%20Writing%20article.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1944, she published a collection of short stories titled ''[[Under a Glass Bell]]'', which were reviewed by [[Edmund Wilson]].&lt;ref name=fraser/&gt;

Nin was also the author of several works of non-fiction: Her first publication, written during her years studying psychoanalysis, was ''[[D. H. Lawrence: An Unprofessional Study]]'' (1932), an assessment of the works of [[D.H. Lawrence]].{{sfn|Franklin|1996|p=6}} In 1968, she published ''[[The Novel of the Future]]'', which elaborated on her approach to writing and the writing process.{{sfn|Franklin|1996|p=127}}

==Personal life==
According to her diaries, ''Vol.1, 1931–1934'', Nin shared a [[bohemian style|bohemian]] lifestyle with Henry Miller during her time in Paris. Her husband Guiler is not mentioned anywhere in the published edition of the 1930s parts of her diary (Vol. 1–2) although the opening of Vol. 1 makes it clear that she is married, and the introduction suggests her husband refused to be included in the published diaries. The diaries edited by her second husband, after her death, tell that her union with Henry Miller was very passionate and physical, and that she believed that it was a pregnancy by him that she aborted in 1934.

In 1947, at the age of 44, she met former actor [[Rupert Pole]] in a Manhattan elevator on her way to a party.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2006/12/31/magazine/31pole.t.html?_r=1|work=New York Times|title=The Lover Who Always Stays|date=2006-12-31|accessdate=2011-02-16|author=Corbett, Sara}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;pole&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=5591676|work=National Public Radio (NPR)|title=Anais Nin Husband, Rupert Pole, Dies in L.A.|date=July 29, 2006|accessdate=February 16, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The two ended up dating and traveled to California together; Pole was sixteen years her junior. On March 17, 1955, while still married to Guiler, she married Pole at [[Quartzsite, Arizona]], returning with him to live in California.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://articles.latimes.com/2006/jul/26/local/me-pole26|date=July 26, 2006|title=The Ranger Who Told All About Anais Nin's Wild Life|author=Woo, Elaine|accessdate=October 4, 2017|work=Los Angeles Times}}&lt;/ref&gt; Guiler remained in New York City and was unaware of Nin's second marriage until after her death in 1977, though biographer [[Deirdre Bair]] alleges that Guiler knew what was happening while Nin was in California, but consciously &quot;chose not to know&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;pole&quot; /&gt;

Nin referred to her simultaneous marriages as her &quot;bicoastal trapeze&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;pole&quot; /&gt; According to Deidre Bair:

{{quote|[Anaïs] would set up these elaborate façades in Los Angeles and in New York, but it became so complicated that she had to create something she called the lie box. She had this absolutely enormous purse and in the purse she had two sets of checkbooks. One said Anaïs Guiler for New York and another said Anaïs Pole for Los Angeles. She had prescription bottles from California doctors and New York doctors with the two different names. And she had a collection of file cards. And she said, &quot;I tell so many lies I have to write them down and keep them in the lie box so I can keep them straight.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;pole&quot; /&gt;}}

In 1966, Nin had her marriage with Pole annulled, due to the legal issues arising from both Guiler and Pole trying to claim her as a dependent on their federal tax returns.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.boston.com/news/globe/obituaries/articles/2006/07/27/rupert_pole_executor_of_exotic_works_by_anas_nin/|work=Boston Globe|title=Rupert Pole, executor of exotic works by Anaïs Nin|author=Woo, Elaine|date=2006-07-27|accessdate=2011-02-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; Though the marriage was annulled, Nin and Pole continued to live together as if they were married, up until her death in 1977.  According to Barbara Kraft, prior to her death Anaïs had written to Hugh Guiler asking for his forgiveness.  He responded by writing how meaningful his life had been because of her.&lt;ref&gt;Kraft, Barbara. ''Anaïs Nin:  The Last Days'' Pegasus Books, {{ISBN|978-0-9889687-5-2}}, 2013, p. 200&lt;/ref&gt;

After Guiler's death in 1985, the [[expurgation|unexpurgated]] versions of her journals were commissioned by Pole.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Woo|first=Elaine|title=The Ranger Who Told All About Anais Nin's Wild Life|url=http://articles.latimes.com/2006/jul/26/local/me-pole26|accessdate=8 August 2012|newspaper=Los Angeles Times|date=July 26, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; Six volumes have appeared (''[[Henry and June]]'', ''[[Fire: From a Journal of Love|Fire]]'', ''[[Incest: From a Journal of Love|Incest]]'', ''[[Nearer the Moon]]'', ''[[Mirages: The Unexpurgated Diary of Anaïs Nin, 1939-1947|Mirages]]'', and ''[[Trapeze: The Unexpurgated Diary of Anaïs Nin, 1947–1955|Trapeze]]''). Pole arranged for Guiler's ashes to be scattered in the same area where Anaïs's ashes were scattered, a place called Mermaid Cove off the Pacific coast.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=5591676&amp;t=1575988142161&lt;/ref&gt; Pole died in July 2006.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|work=The New York Times|date=July 30, 2006|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2006/07/30/us/30pole.html|accessdate=October 6, 2017|title=Rupert Pole, 87, Diarist's Duplicate Spouse, Dies|author=Fox, Margalit}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Nin once worked at Lawrence R. Maxwell Books, located at [[45 Christopher Street]] in New York City.{{sfn|Franklin|1996|p=6}} In addition to her work as a writer,  Nin appeared in the [[Kenneth Anger]] film ''[[Inauguration of the Pleasure Dome]]'' (1954) as [[Astarte]]; in the [[Maya Deren]] film ''Ritual in Transfigured Time'' (1946); and in ''Bells of Atlantis'' (1952), a film directed by Guiler under the name &quot;Ian Hugo&quot; with a soundtrack of [[electronic music]] by [[Louis and Bebe Barron]].{{sfn|Nin|DuBow|1994|pages=xxi–ii}} In her later life, Nin worked as a tutor at the [[International College, Los Angeles|International College]] in Los Angeles.&lt;ref name=kraft/&gt;

==Death==
Nin was diagnosed with [[cervical cancer]] in 1974.{{sfn|Herron|1996|p=235}} She battled the cancer for several years as it metastasized, and underwent numerous surgeries, [[Radiation therapy|radiation]], and [[chemotherapy]].&lt;ref name=kraft&gt;{{cite web|work=Cultural Weekly|date=December 13, 2016|url=https://www.culturalweekly.com/anais-nin-last-days/|author=Kraft, Barbara|title=Anaïs Nin: The Last Days|accessdate=September 28, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nin died of the cancer at [[Cedars-Sinai Medical Center]] in [[Los Angeles]], California on January 14, 1977.&lt;ref name=herron&gt;{{cite book|title=Anaïs Nin: A Book of Mirrors|author=Herron, Paul|publisher=Sky Blue Press|year=1996|p=235|isbn= 978-0-965-23640-9 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Nin, Anaïs. Rauner Library Letters (September 1975): &quot;I suppose you know I have been fighting cancer for 9 months – just recovering very slowly.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=fraser&gt;{{cite news|work=The New York Times|date=January 16, 1977|author=Fraser, C. Gerald|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1977/01/16/archives/anais-nin-author-whose-diaries-depicted-intellectual-life-dead.html|title=Anais Nin, Author Whose Diaries Depicted Intellectual Life, Dead|accessdate=September 1, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Her body was [[cremation|cremated]], and her ashes were scattered over [[Santa Monica Bay]] in Mermaid Cove. Her first husband, Hugh Guiler, died in 1985, and his ashes were scattered in the cove as well.&lt;ref name=&quot;pole&quot; /&gt; Rupert Pole was named Nin's [[literary executor]], and he arranged to have new, unexpurgated editions of Nin's books and diaries published between 1985 and his death in 2006. Large portions of the diaries are still available only in the expurgated form. The originals are located in the [[UCLA]] library.

==Legacy==
[[File:Anais Nin.jpg|thumb|Portrait of Anaïs Nin in the 1970s by [[Elsa Dorfman]]]]
The explosion of the [[feminist movement]] in the 1960s gave feminist perspectives on Nin's writings of the past twenty years, which made Nin a popular lecturer at various universities; contrarily, Nin disassociated herself from the political activism of the movement.&lt;ref name=&quot;kir&quot; /&gt; In 1973, prior to her death, Nin received an [[Honorary degree|honorary doctorate]] from the [[Philadelphia College of Art]]. She was also elected to the United States [[National Institute of Arts and Letters]] in 1974, and in 1976 was presented with a ''[[Los Angeles Times]]'' Woman of the Year award.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://latimesblogs.latimes.com/thedailymirror/2011/06/times-woman-of-the-year-anais-nin.html|title=Times Woman of the Year – Anais Nin|date=June 6, 2011|work=[[Los Angeles Times]]|accessdate=February 2, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Philip Kaufman]] directed the 1990 film ''[[Henry &amp; June]]'' based on Nin's diaries published as ''[[Henry and June|Henry and June: From the Unexpurgated Diary of Anaïs Nin]]''. She was portrayed in the film by actress [[Maria de Medeiros]].

In February 2008, poet [[Steven Reigns]] organized ''Anaïs Nin at 105'' at the Hammer Museum in Westwood, Los Angeles.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|work=LA Weekly|title=All About Anais Nin|url=http://www.laweekly.com/arts/all-about-anais-nin-2151862|author=Kosnett, Rena|date=February 6, 2008|accessdate=October 5, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Reigns said: &quot;Nin bonded and formed very deep friendships with women and men decades younger than her. Some of them are still living in Los Angeles and I thought it'd be wonderful to have them share their experiences with [Nin].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dailybruin.ucla.edu/news/2008/feb/12/writer-garners-personal-praise/|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080524095148/http://www.dailybruin.ucla.edu/news/2008/feb/12/writer-garners-personal-praise/|archivedate=May 24, 2008|work= The Daily Bruin|publisher=University of California, Los Angeles|title=Writer garners personal praise|date=February 12, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Bebe Barron]], electronic music pioneer and longtime friend of Nin, made her last public appearance at the event.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://echoes.org/2008/04/21/the-first-lady-of-electronic-music-passes-bebe-barron/|work=Echoes|title=The First Lady of Electronic Music Passes: Bebe Barron|accessdate=October 4, 2017|date=2008-04-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; Reigns also published an essay refuting Bern Porter's claims of a sexual relationship with Nin in the 1930s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Bern Porter's Wild Sexual Life with Anais Nin or Wild Imaginings? |journal=A Cafe in Space: The Anais Nin Literary Journal|first=Steven | last=Reigns | date=February 2014}} republished: {{cite web |url=http://blog.anaisnin.com/2014/06/i-pursue-her-still-bern-porter-on-anais.html |first=Steven |last=Reigns |accessdate=May 30, 2016 |title=Bern Porter's Wild Sexual Life with Anais Nin or Wild Imaginings? |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160414023319/http://blog.anaisnin.com/2014/06/i-pursue-her-still-bern-porter-on-anais.html |archive-date=2016-04-14 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Cuban-American writer [[Daína Chaviano]] paid homage to Anaïs Nin and [[Henry Miller]] in her novel ''Gata encerrada'' (2001), where both characters are portraited as disembodied spirits whose previous lives they shared with Melisa, the main character --and presumably Chaviano's [[alter ego]]--, a young Cuban obsessed with Anaïs Nin.&lt;ref name=&quot;gata&quot;&gt;Rodríguez, Antonio O. and Andricaín, Sergio. &quot;Fusión de erotismo y magia: ''Gata encerrada'' es una novela cautivadora&quot;. [[Newsweek]] en Español, July 11, 2001&lt;/ref&gt;   
    
The Cuban poet and novelist [[Wendy Guerra]], long fascinated with Nin's life and works, published a fictional diary in Nin's voice, ''Posar desnuda en la Habana'' (''Posing Nude in Havana'') in 2012. She explained that &quot;[Nin's] Cuban Diary has very few pages and my delirium was always to write an apocryphal novel; literary conjecture about what might have happened&quot;.&lt;ref name=sanchez&gt;{{cite news|last1=Sanchez| first1=Yoani| title=Cuban Author Wendy Guerra: 'I'm a Demon Who Writes What She Feels'| url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/yoani-sanchez/cuban-author-wendy-guerra_b_6299348.html|accessdate=30 May 2016|publisher=HuffPost Latino Voices|date=9 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On September 27, 2013, screenwriter and author [[Kim Krizan]] published an article in ''[[The Huffington Post]]''&lt;ref name=gore/&gt; revealing she had found a previously unpublished love letter written by [[Gore Vidal]] to Nin. This letter contradicts Gore Vidal's previous characterization of his relationship with Nin, showing that Vidal did have feelings for Nin that he later heavily disavowed in his autobiography, ''Palimpsest''. Krizan did this research in the run up to the release of the fifth volume of Anaïs Nin's uncensored diary, ''Mirages'', for which Krizan provided the foreword.&lt;ref name=gore&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/kim-krizan/gore-vidals-secret-unpubl_b_4004916.html|title=Gore Vidal's Secret, Unpublished Love Letter To Anaïs Nin|date=September 27, 2013|work=[[The Huffington Post]]|accessdate=September 20, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Bibliography==
===Journals and letters===
{{Library resources box|by=yes|viaf=14774462}}
* ''[[The Early Diary of Anaïs Nin]]'' (1914–1931), in four volumes
* ''[[The Diary of Anaïs Nin]]'', in seven volumes, edited by herself
* ''[[Henry and June]]: From A Journal of Love. The Unexpurgated Diary of Anaïs Nin (1931–1932)'' (1986), edited by Rupert Pole after her death
* ''[[A Literate Passion]]: Letters of Anaïs Nin &amp; Henry Miller'' (1987)
* ''[[Incest: From a Journal of Love]]'' (1992)
* ''[[Fire: From A Journal of Love]]'' (1995)
* ''[[Nearer the Moon: From A Journal of Love]]'' (1996)
* ''[[Mirages: The Unexpurgated Diary of Anaïs Nin, 1939-1947|Mirages: The Unexpurgated Diary of Anaïs Nin, 1939–1947]]'' (2013)
* ''[[Trapeze: The Unexpurgated Diary of Anaïs Nin, 1947–1955]]'' (2017)

===Fiction===
====Novels====
* ''[[House of Incest]]'' (1936)
* ''[[Winter of Artifice]]'' (1939)
* ''[[Cities of the Interior]]'' (1959), in five volumes:
** ''[[Ladders to Fire]]''
** ''[[Children of the Albatross]]''
** ''[[The Four-Chambered Heart]]''
** ''[[A Spy in the House of Love]]''
** ''[[Seduction of the Minotaur]]'',  originally published as ''Solar Barque'' (1958).
* ''[[Collages (novel)|Collages]]'' (1964)

====Short stories====
* ''[[Waste of Timelessness]]: And Other Early Stories'' (written before 1932, published posthumously)
* ''[[Under a Glass Bell]]'' (1944)
* ''[[Delta of Venus]]'' (1977)
* ''[[Little Birds]]'' (1979)
* ''[[Auletris]]'' (2016)

===Non-fiction===
* ''[[D. H. Lawrence: An Unprofessional Study]]'' (1932)
* ''[[The Novel of the Future]]'' (1968)
* ''[[In Favor of the Sensitive Man]]'' (1976)
* ''[[The Restless Spirit: Journal of a Gemini]]'' by Barbara Kraft (1976) (preface by  Nin)
* ''[[Aphrodisiac: Erotic Drawings]] by John Boyce for Selected Passages from the Works of Anaïs Nin''

==Filmography==
*''Ritual in Transfigured Time'' (1946): Short film, dir. [[Maya Deren]]{{sfn|Nin|DuBow|1994|p=xxi}}
*''[[Inauguration of the Pleasure Dome]]'' (1946): Short film, dir. [[Kenneth Anger]]{{sfn|Nin|DuBow|1994|p=xxi}}
*''Bells of Atlantis'' (1952): Short film, dir. Ian Hugo{{sfn|Nin|DuBow|1994|p=xxii}}
*''Anais Nin Observed'' (1974): Documentary, dir. [[Robert Snyder (filmmaker)|Robert Snyder]]{{sfn|Nin|DuBow|1994|p=xxii}}

==See also==
*''[[Henry &amp; June]]''
*[[List of Cuban American writers]]
*[[List of Cuban Americans]]
*[[Otto Rank]]
{{Portalbar|Biography|Literature}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Works cited==
*{{cite book|last=Bair|first=Deirdre|author-link=Deirdre Bair|title=Anaïs Nin: A Biography|publisher= [[G. P. Putnam's Sons|Putnam]]|year=1995|isbn=978-0-399-13988-8|ref=harv|title-link=Anaïs Nin: A Biography}}
*{{cite book|last=Fitch|first=Noël Riley|author-link=Noël Riley Fitch|title=Anaïs: The Erotic Life of Anaïs Nin|publisher=[[Little, Brown and Company]]|year=1993|ref=harv|isbn=978-0-316-28428-8|url=https://archive.org/details/anaiseroticlifeo00fitc}}
*{{cite book|last=Franklin|first=Benjamin V, ed.|title=Recollections of Anaïs Nin|publisher=Ohio University Press|year=1996|ref=harv|isbn= 978-0-821-41164-3 }}
*{{cite book|last=Nin|first=Anaïs|title=The Diary of Anaïs Nin (1931-1934)|volume=1|publisher=Harcourt, Brace &amp; World|year=1966|isbn= 978-0-547-53870-9|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Nin|first=Anaïs|title=The Dairy of Anaïs Nin (1934–1939)|volume=2|publisher=Harcourt, Brace &amp; World|year=1967|isbn=978-0-156-26026-8 |ref=harv}}
*{{cite book |title=Conversations with Anaïs Nin |last1=Nin |first1=Anaïs |last2=DuBow |first2=Wendy M. |year=1994 |publisher=University Press of Mississippi |isbn=978-0-878-05719-1 |ref=harv |url=https://archive.org/details/conversationswit00nina }}

==Further reading==
*{{cite book|last=Jarczok|first=Anita|year=2017|title=Writing an Icon: Celebrity Culture and the Invention of Anaïs Nin|publisher=Ohio University Press|isbn= 978-0-804-04075-4}}
*{{cite book|last=Mason, ed.|first=Gregory H.|year=1998|title=Arrows of Longing: The Correspondence between Anaïs Nin and Felix Pollak, 1952-1976|publisher=Ohio University Press|isbn= 978-0-8040-1006-1}}
*[[Lili Bita]], ''Anais Nin.'' &quot;EI&quot; Magazine of [https://euarceblog.wixsite.com/euarce European Art Center (EUARCE)], Is. 7/1994 p. 9, 24-30

==External links==
{{Commons category|Anaïs Nin}}
{{wikiquote}}
*[http://anaisninblog.skybluepress.com/ The Official Anaïs Nin Blog]
*[http://www.skybluepress.com/ Sky Blue Press] Preserving and promoting her literary work.
*[http://www.anaisnin.com/ Anaïs Nin.com] Thinking of Anais NIn
*[http://www.theanaisninfoundation.org Anais Nin Foundation] Contact the Anais Nin estate for rights and permissions requests
*{{Internet Archive author |sname=Anaïs Nin}} 
*{{IMDb name|632405}}
*{{worldcat id|id=lccn-n79-41785}}
*[http://www.oldkewgardens.com/ss-2-homes-0125.html Anaïs Nin: 82nd Avenue]
*[http://www.roberthaller.com/firstlight/hugo.html Ian Hugo (Nin's husband)]
*[https://archives.lib.siu.edu/?p=collections/controlcard&amp;id=2079 Anaïs Nin Letters, 1932–1946] at Southern Illinois University Carbondale, Special Collections Research Center
*[http://segundaviola.com.ar/natvideos/#04 Anaïs Nin video text]

{{Authority control}}

{{Anaïs Nin}}
{{Henry Miller}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Nin, Anais}}
[[Category:1903 births]]
[[Category:1977 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Neuilly-sur-Seine]]
[[Category:American diarists]]
[[Category:Writers from Paris]]
[[Category:American people of Catalan descent]]
[[Category:American writers of Cuban descent]]
[[Category:American people of Danish descent]]
[[Category:French emigrants to the United States]]
[[Category:Burials at sea]]
[[Category:Burials in California]]
[[Category:Deaths from cancer in California]]
[[Category:20th-century women writers]]
[[Category:French novelists]]
[[Category:French essayists]]
[[Category:French short story writers]]
[[Category:French erotica writers]]
[[Category:Former Roman Catholics]]
[[Category:Analysands of Otto Rank]]
[[Category:Analysands of René Allendy]]
[[Category:Women memoirists]]
[[Category:Self-published authors]]
[[Category:Polyandry]]
[[Category:20th-century American non-fiction writers]]
[[Category:Women erotica writers]]
[[Category:French people of Cuban descent]]
[[Category:French people of Catalan descent]]
[[Category:French people of Danish descent]]
[[Category:People with acquired American citizenship]]
[[Category:Women diarists]]
[[Category:20th-century essayists]]</text>
      <sha1>bw5ys1sfwsb2h9yjw8zx032bt3zj3he</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
