  <page>
    <title>Association for Computing Machinery</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2928</id>
    <revision>
      <id>939316838</id>
      <parentid>939316767</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-05T18:36:58Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Headbomb</username>
        <id>1461430</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>ce</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|International learned society for computing}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=June 2012}}
{{Infobox organization
| name         = Association for Computing Machinery
| image        = Association for Computing Machinery (ACM) logo.svg
| image_border =
| size         = 100px
| alt          = &quot;acm&quot; in blue circle with gray rim, surrounded by blue diamond
| caption      =
| formation    = {{start date and age|1947}}
| type         = [[501(c) organization|501(c)(3) not-for-profit membership corporation]]
| headquarters = 1601 Broadway, Times Square, &lt;br /&gt;New York City
| membership   = 100,000
| leader_title = President
| leader_name  = [[Cherri M. Pancake]]
| key_people   =
| num_staff    =
| budget       =
| website      = {{URL|acm.org}}
}}

The '''Association for Computing Machinery''' ('''ACM''') is an international [[learned society]] for [[computing]]. It was founded in 1947, and is the world's largest scientific and educational [[computing]] society.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://newsinfo.iu.edu/news/page/normal/20613.html |title=Indiana University Media Relations |publisher=indiana.edu |accessdate=October 10, 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The ACM is a [[nonprofit organization|non-profit]] professional membership group,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://apps.irs.gov/app/eos/pub78Search.do?ein1=&amp;names=%22association+for+computing+machinery%22&amp;city=&amp;state=All...&amp;country=US&amp;deductibility=all&amp;dispatchMethod=searchCharities&amp;submitName=Search |title=ACM 501(c)3 Status as a group |publisher=irs.gov |accessdate=October 1, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; claiming nearly 100,000 student and professional members {{as of|2019|lc=y}}.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.acm.org/membership/membership-benefits|title=Membership Benefits|website=www.acm.org|language=en|access-date=2019-05-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its headquarters are in [[New York City]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Contact Information |url=https://www.acm.org/about-acm/contact-us |website=www.acm.org |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The ACM is an [[umbrella organization]] for academic and scholarly interests in [[computer science]]. Its motto is &quot;Advancing Computing as a Science &amp; Profession&quot;.

==History==
The ACM was founded in 1947 under the name ''Eastern Association for Computing Machinery'', which was changed the following year to the Association for Computing Machinery.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.acm.org/about-acm/acm-history|title=ACM History|website=www.acm.org|language=en|access-date=2018-02-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Activities==
[[File:1601Broadway.jpg|thumb|ACM headquarters are located at 1601 Broadway, Times Square, New York City.]]
ACM is organized into over 171 local chapters and 37 [[Special Interest Group]]s (SIGs), through which it conducts most of its activities. Additionally, there are over 500 college and university chapters. The first student chapter was founded in 1961 at the [[University of Louisiana at Lafayette]].

Many of the SIGs, such as [[ACM SIGGRAPH|SIGGRAPH]], [[SIGDA]], [[SIGPLAN]], [[SIGCSE]] and [[SIGCOMM]], sponsor regular conferences, which have become famous as the dominant venue for presenting innovations in certain fields. The groups also publish a large number of specialized journals, magazines, and newsletters.

ACM also sponsors other computer science related events such as the worldwide [[ACM International Collegiate Programming Contest]] (ICPC), and has sponsored some other events such as the chess match between [[Garry Kasparov]] and the [[IBM Deep Blue]] computer.

==Services==

===Publications===
{{main cat|Association for Computing Machinery publications}}
ACM publishes over 50 journals&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.acm.org/publications/journals|title=Journals &amp; Magazines|work=acm.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; including the prestigious&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first1=Paul Benjamin |last1=Lowry |first2=Denton |last2=Romans |first3=Aaron |last3=Curtis |title=Global Journal Prestige and Supporting Disciplines: A Scientometric Study of Information Systems Journals |journal=[[Journal of the Association for Information Systems]] |volume=5 |issue=2 |pages=29–80 |year=2004 |ssrn=666145|doi=10.17705/1jais.00045 }}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Journal of the ACM]]'', and two general magazines for computer professionals, ''[[Communications of the ACM]]'' (also known as ''Communications'' or ''CACM'') and ''[[ACM Queue|Queue]]''. Other publications of the ACM include:
*''[[XRDS (magazine)|ACM XRDS]]'', formerly &quot;Crossroads&quot;, was redesigned in 2010 and is the most popular student computing magazine in the US.
*''[[ACM Interactions (magazine)|ACM Interactions]]'', an interdisciplinary HCI publication focused on the connections between experiences, people and technology, and the third largest ACM publication.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal
| last1 = Wakkary | first1 = R.
| last2 = Stolterman | first2 = E.
| doi = 10.1145/1897239.1897240
| title = WELCOME: Our first interactions 
| journal = Interactions
| volume = 18
| pages = 5
| year = 2011
| pmid = 
| pmc = 
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*''[[ACM Computing Surveys]]'' (CSUR)
*''[[Computers in Entertainment]]'' (CIE)
*''[[ACM Journal on Emerging Technologies in Computing Systems]]'' (JETC) 
*''ACM Special Interest Group: Computers and Society'' (SIGCAS) &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title= Home page | url= http://www.sigcas.org/newsletter | website = sigcas.org | publisher= Association for Computing Machinery | access-date = 28 October 2017 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*A number of journals, specific to subfields of computer science, titled ''ACM Transactions''. Some of the more notable transactions include:
**''ACM Transactions on Computer Systems'' (TOCS)
**''[[IEEE/ACM Transactions on Computational Biology and Bioinformatics]]'' (TCBB)
**''[[ACM Transactions on Computational Logic]]'' (TOCL)
**''[[ACM Transactions on Computer-Human Interaction]]'' (TOCHI)
**''[[ACM Transactions on Database Systems]]'' (TODS)
**''[[ACM Transactions on Graphics]]'' (TOG)
**''[[ACM Transactions on Mathematical Software]]'' (TOMS)
**''[[ACM Transactions on Multimedia Computing, Communications, and Applications]]'' (TOMM)
**''[[IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking]]'' (TON)
**''[[ACM Transactions on Programming Languages and Systems]]'' (TOPLAS)

Although ''Communications'' no longer publishes primary research, and is not considered a prestigious venue, many of the great debates and results in computing history have been published in its pages.

ACM has made almost all of its publications available to paid [[subscriber]]s online at its [[#Digital Library|Digital Library]] and also has a [[ACM Guide to Computing Literature|Guide to Computing Literature]]. Individual members additionally have access to [[Safari Books Online]] and Books24x7. ACM also offers insurance, online courses, and other services to its members.

In 1997, ACM Press published ''Wizards and Their Wonders: Portraits in Computing'' ({{ISBN|0897919602}}), written by Christopher Morgan, with new photographs by [[Louis Fabian Bachrach, Jr.|Louis Fabian Bachrach]]. The book is a collection of historic and current portrait photographs of figures from the computer industry.

==Portal and Digital Library{{anchor|Portal}}{{anchor|Digital Library}}==
The '''ACM Portal''' is an online service of the ACM.&lt;ref name=portal&gt;{{cite web|url=http://portal.acm.org/|title=ACM Digital Library|work=acm.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
Its core are two main sections: '''ACM Digital Library''' and the '''[[ACM Guide to Computing Literature]]'''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.libs.uga.edu/research/subject/computer-science The University of Georgia Guide to Online Resources]&lt;/ref&gt;

The ACM Digital Library is the full-text collection of all articles published by the ACM in its articles, magazines and conference proceedings. The Guide is a bibliography in computing with over one million entries.&lt;ref name=portal/&gt;
The ACM Digital Library contains a comprehensive archive starting in the 1950s of the organization's journals, magazines, newsletters and conference proceedings. Online services include a forum called Ubiquity and Tech News digest. There is an extensive underlying bibliographic database containing key works of all genres from all major publishers of computing literature. This secondary database is a rich discovery service known as The ACM Guide to Computing Literature.

ACM adopted a hybrid [[Open access|Open Access]] (OA) publishing model in 2013. Authors who do not choose to pay the OA fee must grant ACM publishing rights by either a copyright transfer agreement or a publishing license agreement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://authors.acm.org/ | title=ACM Author Rights |publisher=Acm.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;

ACM was a &quot;green&quot; publisher before the term was invented. Authors may post documents on their own websites and in their institutional repositories with a link back to the ACM Digital Library's permanently maintained Version of Record.

All metadata in the Digital Library is open to the world, including [[abstracts]], linked references and citing works, citation and usage statistics, as well as all functionality and services. Other than the free articles, the full-texts are accessed by subscription.

There is also a mounting challenge to the ACM's publication practices coming from the [[Open access (publishing)|open access]] movement. Some authors see a centralized peer&amp;ndash;review process as less relevant and publish on their home pages or on unreviewed sites like [[arXiv]]. Other organizations have sprung up which do their peer review entirely free and online, such as ''[[Journal of Artificial Intelligence Research]]'', ''[[Journal of Machine Learning Research]]'' and the ''[[Journal of Research and Practice in Information Technology]]''.

==Membership grades==
{{main cat|Members of the Association for Computing Machinery}}
In addition to student and regular members, ACM has several advanced membership grades to recognize those with multiple years of membership and &quot;demonstrated performance that sets them apart from their peers&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.acm.org/membership/membership/senior_members/ |title=ACM Senior Members–An Overview |publisher=Acm.org |access-date=November 24, 2010 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120118200303/http://www.acm.org/membership/membership/senior_members/ |archive-date=January 18, 2012 |url-status=dead |df=mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The number of Fellows, Distinguished Members, and Senior Members cannot exceed 1%, 10%, and 25% of the total number of professional members, respectively.&lt;ref&gt;[https://awards.acm.org/advanced-member-grades]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Fellows===
{{main|ACM Fellow}}
{{main list|List of Fellows of the Association for Computing Machinery}}
The [[ACM Fellow]]s Program was established by Council of the Association for Computing Machinery in 1993 &quot;to recognize and honor outstanding ACM members for their achievements in computer science and information technology and for their significant contributions to the mission of the ACM.&quot; There are 1163 Fellows {{as of|2019|lc=y}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://awards.acm.org/fellow/all.cfm |title=List of ACM Fellows |publisher=Awards.acm.org |accessdate=March 3, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; out of about 100,000 members.

===Distinguished Members===
In 2006, ACM began recognizing two additional membership grades, one which was called Distinguished Members. Distinguished Members (Distinguished Engineers, Distinguished Scientists, and Distinguished Educators) have at least 15 years of professional experience and 5 years of continuous ACM membership and &quot;have made a significant impact on the computing field&quot;. Note that in 2006 when the Distinguished Members first came out, one of the three levels was called &quot;Distinguished Member&quot; and was changed about two years later to &quot;Distinguished Educator&quot;. Those who already had the Distinguished Member title had their titles changed to one of the other three titles.

===Senior Members===
Also in 2006, ACM began recognizing Senior Members. According to the ACM, &quot;The Senior Members Grade recognizes those ACM members with at least 10 years of professional experience and 5 years of continuous Professional Membership who have demonstrated performance through technical leadership, and technical or professional contributions&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[https://awards.acm.org/senior-members ACM Senior Members]&lt;/ref&gt; Senior membership also requires 3 letters of reference

===Distinguished Speakers===
While not technically a membership grade, the ACM recognizes distinguished speakers on topics in computer science. A distinguished speaker is appointed for a three-year period. There are usually about 125 current distinguished speakers. The ACM website describes these people as 'Renowned International Thought Leaders'.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = https://speakers.acm.org/ |title = Homepage|website = ACM Distinguished Speakers|publisher = Association for Computing Machinery}}&lt;/ref&gt; The distinguished speaker program is overseen by a committee &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = https://speakers.acm.org/committee| title = ACM Speakers Committee|website = ACM Distinguished Speakers|publisher = Association for Computing Machinery}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Chapters==
ACM has three kinds of chapters: [[Special Interest Group]]s,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.acm.org/sigs | title=ACM Special Interest Groups | accessdate=August 7, 2010 | archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100727190450/http://www.acm.org/sigs | archivedate=July 27, 2010 | url-status=dead | df=mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Professional Chapters, and [[ACM Student Chapter|Student Chapters]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.acm.org/chapters/ | title=ACM Chapters | accessdate=August 7, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{as of|2011}}, ACM has professional &amp; SIG Chapters in 56 countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | title       = Worldwide Professional Chapters
 | url         = http://www.acm.org/chapters/maps/
 | publisher   = Association for Computing Machinery (ACM)
 | date        = 
 | accessdate  = 2012-12-27
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{as of|2014}}, there exist ACM student chapters in 41 different countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://campus.acm.org/public/chapters/geo_listing/index.cfm?ct=Student&amp;inus=0 |title=Chapters Listing by Geographic Region — Association for Computing Machinery |publisher=Campus.acm.org |date= |accessdate=2013-10-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Special Interest Groups===
{{main cat|Association for Computing Machinery Special Interest Groups}}
{{div col|colwidth=30em}}
* [[Special Interest Group on Accessible Computing|SIGACCESS]]: Accessible Computing
* [[ACM SIGACT|SIGACT]]: Algorithms and Computation Theory
* SIGAda: [[Ada (programming language)|Ada]] Programming Language
* [[SIGAI]]: Artificial Intelligence
* SIGAPP: Applied Computing
* [[ACM SIGARCH|SIGARCH]]: Computer Architecture
* SIGBED: Embedded Systems
* SIGBio: Bioinformatics 
* SIGCAS: Computers and Society
* [[SIGCHI]]: Computer&amp;ndash;Human Interaction
* [[SIGCOMM]]: Data Communication
* [[SIGCSE]]: Computer Science Education
* [[Special Interest Group on Design Automation|SIGDA]]: Design Automation
* [[SIGDOC]]: Design of Communication
* SIGecom: Electronic Commerce
* SIGEVO: Genetic and Evolutionary Computation
* [[ACM SIGGRAPH|SIGGRAPH]]: Computer Graphics and Interactive Techniques
* [[ACM SIGHPC|SIGHPC]]: High Performance Computing
* [[Special Interest Group on Information Retrieval|SIGIR]]: Information Retrieval
* SIGITE: Information Technology Education
* [[SIGKDD]]: Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining
* SIGLOG: Logic and Computation&lt;ref&gt;
  {{cite web
  | url = http://siglog.acm.org/
  | title = ACM Special Interest Group on Logic and Computation
  | publisher=acm.org
  | accessdate=2015-01-28 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[SIGMETRICS]]: Measurement and Evaluation
* SIGMICRO: Microarchitecture
* SIGMIS: Management Information Systems
* [[SIGMM]]: Multimedia
* [[SIGMOBILE]]: Mobility of Systems, Users, Data and Computing
* [[SIGMOD]]: Management of Data
* [[ACM SIGOPS|SIGOPS]]: Operating Systems
* [[SIGPLAN]]: Programming Languages
* SIGSAC: Security, Audit, and Control
* [[SIGSAM]]: Symbolic and Algebraic Manipulation
* SIGSIM: Simulation and Modeling
* [[SIGSOFT]]: Software Engineering
* SIGSPATIAL: Spatial Information
* [[SIGUCCS]]: University and College Computing Services
* [[ACM SIGWEB|SIGWEB]]: Hypertext, Hypermedia, and Web
{{div col end}}

==Conferences==
{{main cat|Association for Computing Machinery conferences}}
ACM and its Special Interest Groups (SIGs) sponsors numerous conferences with 170 hosted worldwide in 2017. [http://www.acm.org/conferences ACM Conferences page] has an up-to-date complete list while a partial list is shown below. Most of the SIGs also have an annual conference. ACM conferences are often very popular publishing venues and are therefore very competitive. For example, the 2007 [[SIGGRAPH]] conference attracted about 30000 visitors, and CIKM only accepted 15% of the long papers that were submitted in 2005.

&lt;br /&gt;
{{div col|colwidth=30em}}
* COMPASS: [[International Conference on Computing and Sustainable Societies]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://acmcompass.org/|title=ACM SIGCAS Conference on Computing and Sustainable Societies (COMPASS)}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* ASPLOS: [[International Conference on Architectural Support for Programming Languages and Operating Systems]]
* CHI: [[Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems]]
* [[SIGCSE]]: [[SIGCSE Technical Symposium on Computer Science Education]]
* CIKM: [[Conference on Information and Knowledge Management]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cikmconference.org/ |title=Conference on Information and Knowledge Management (CIKM) |publisher=Cikmconference.org }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* DAC: [[Design Automation Conference]]
* DEBS: Distributed Event Based Systems&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.debs.org/|title=Distributed Event-Based Systems |website =  DEBS.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* FCRC: [[Federated Computing Research Conference]]
* GECCO: Genetic and Evolutionary Computation Conference&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sig.sigevo.org/index.html/tiki-index.php?page=GECCOs|title=GECCOs |website =Sigevo.org |publisher = ACM }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* SC: [[Supercomputing Conference]]
* SIGGRAPH: [[International Conference on Computer Graphics and Interactive Techniques]]
* Hypertext: Conference on Hypertext and Hypermedia&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ht2009.org/ |title=Hypertext 2009 |publisher=Ht2009.org }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* JCDL: [[Joint Conference on Digital Libraries]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jcdl.org/ |title=Joint Conference on Digital Library (JCDL)&amp;ndash;Home |publisher=JCDL }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* TAPIA: Richard Tapia Celebration of Diversity in Computing Conference 
* SIGCOMM: ACM [[SIGCOMM]] Conference
{{div col end}}

* MobiHoc: International Symposium on Mobile Ad Hoc Networking and Computing
The ACM is a co&amp;ndash;presenter and founding partner of the Grace Hopper Celebration of Women in Computing (GHC) with the [[Anita Borg Institute for Women and Technology]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Grace Hopper Celebration of Women in Computing, Largest Gathering of Women in Computing, Attracts Researchers, Industry|url=http://www.acm.org/press&amp;ndash;room/news&amp;ndash;releases&amp;ndash;2008/hopper&amp;ndash;08&amp;ndash;preview/|accessdate=June 27, 2011}}{{Dead link|date=July 2018 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some conferences are hosted by ACM student branches; this includes [[Reflections Projections]], which is hosted by UIUC ACM.{{Citation needed|date=October 2012}}.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://acm.illinois.edu/conference|title=ACM@UIUC|last=|first=|date=2017|website=|access-date=January 24, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, ACM sponsors regional conferences. Regional conferences facilitate increased opportunities for collaboration between nearby institutions and they are well attended.

For additional non-ACM conferences, see this [[list of computer science conferences]].

==Awards==&lt;!-- PLEASE RESPECT ALPHABETICAL ORDER --&gt;
The ACM presents or co&amp;ndash;presents a number of awards for outstanding technical and professional achievements and contributions in computer science and information technology.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://awards.acm.org/|title=ACM's awards recognize excellence in computer science and information technology.|website=awards.acm.org|language=en|access-date=2017-04-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://awards.acm.org/list-of-awards|title=List of ACM Awards|website=awards.acm.org|language=en|access-date=2017-04-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=ACM Awards |url=http://awards.acm.org/html/awards.cfm |accessdate=April 26, 2012 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120511073001/http://awards.acm.org/html/awards.cfm |archivedate=May 11, 2012 |df=mdy }}&lt;/ref&gt; 
{{div col|colwidth=30em}}
* [[Turing Award|ACM A. M. Turing Award]]
* [[Association for the Advancement of Artificial Intelligence#ACM - AAAI Allen Newell Award|ACM – AAAI Allen Newell Award]]
* [[Association for Computing Machinery#Athena Lectures|ACM Athena Lecturer Award]]
* ACM/CSTA Cutler-Bell Prize in High School Computing
* ACM Distinguished Service Award
* ACM Doctoral Dissertation Award&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Shun Receives ACM Doctoral Dissertation Award|url=https://www.cs.cmu.edu/news/shun-receives-acm-doctoral-dissertation-award|website=School of Computer Science|publisher=[[Carnegie Mellon University]]|accessdate=7 June 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[ACM Eugene L. Lawler Award]]
* [[ACM Fellow]]ship, awarded annually since 1993&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author=Anon | journal=[[Communications of the ACM]] |title=ACM Inducts Fellows| publisher=Association for Computing Machinery  | volume=59 | issue=2 | year=2016 | pages=24 | doi=10.1145/2856228}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Gordon Bell Prize|ACM Gordon Bell Prize]]
* [[Grace Murray Hopper Award|ACM Grace Murray Hopper Award]]
* ACM – IEEE CS George Michael Memorial HPC Fellowships
* [[Ken Kennedy Award|ACM – IEEE CS Ken Kennedy Award]]
* [[Eckert–Mauchly Award|ACM – IEEE Eckert-Mauchly Award]]
* ACM India Doctoral Dissertation Award
* ACM Karl V. Karlstrom Outstanding Educator Award
* [[Paris Kanellakis Theory and Practice Award|ACM Paris Kanellakis Theory and Practice Award]]
* ACM Policy Award
* ACM Presidential Award
* [[ACM Prize in Computing]] (formerly: ACM – Infosys Foundation Award in the Computing Sciences)
* ACM Programming Systems and Languages Paper Award
* [[ACM Student Research Competition]]
* [[Software System Award|ACM Software System Award]]
* [[International Science and Engineering Fair]]
* Outstanding Contribution to ACM Award
* [[SIAM/ACM Prize in Computational Science and Engineering]]
{{div col end}}
Over 30 of ACM's Special Interest Groups also award individuals for their contributions with a few listed below.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://awards.acm.org/sig-awards|title=Special Interest Group (SIG) Awards|website=awards.acm.org|language=en|access-date=2017-04-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{div col|colwidth=30em}}
* ACM [[Alan D. Berenbaum Distinguished Service Award]]
* ACM [[Maurice Wilkes Award]]
* [[ISCA Influential Paper Award]]
{{div col end}}

==Leadership==
{{category see also|Presidents of the Association for Computing Machinery}}

The President of ACM for 2018–2020 is [[Cherri M. Pancake]], Professor Emeritus at [[Oregon State University]] and Director of the Northwest Alliance for Computational Science and Engineering (NACSE). She is successor of Vicki L. Hanson (2016-2018), Distinguished Professor at the [[Rochester Institute of Technology]] and Visiting Professor at the [[University of Dundee]]; [[Alexander L. Wolf]] (2014–2016), Dean of the [[Jack Baskin School of Engineering]] at the [[University of California, Santa Cruz]]; [[Vint Cerf]] (2012–2014), an American computer scientist who is recognized as one of &quot;the fathers of the Internet&quot;; Alain Chesnais (2010–2012), a French citizen living in [[Toronto]], [[Ontario]], Canada, where he runs his company named Visual Transitions; and [[Wendy Hall|Dame Wendy Hall]] of the [[University of Southampton]], UK (2008–2010).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.acm.org/about/past-presidents |title=ACM Past Presidents |publisher=acm.org |accessdate=2014-10-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

ACM is led by a Council consisting of the President, Vice-President, Treasurer, Past President, SIG Governing Board Chair, Publications Board Chair, three representatives of the SIG Governing Board, and seven Members&amp;ndash;At&amp;ndash;Large. This institution is often referred to simply as &quot;Council&quot; in ''Communications of the ACM''.

==Infrastructure==
ACM has five &quot;Boards&quot; that make up various committees and subgroups, to help Headquarters staff maintain quality services and products. These boards are as follows:
# Publications Board
# SIG Governing Board
# Education Board
# Membership Services Board
# Practitioners Board

==ACM Council on Women in Computing==
[[ACM-W]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://women.acm.org/|title=Home|work=acm.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; the ACM council on [[women in computing]], supports, celebrates, and advocates internationally for the full engagement of women in computing. ACM–W's main programs are regional celebrations of women in computing, ACM-W chapters, and scholarships for women CS students to attend research conferences. In India and Europe these activities are overseen by ACM-W India and ACM-W Europe respectively.  ACM-W collaborates with organizations such as the [[Anita Borg Institute]], the [[National Center for Women &amp; Information Technology|National Center for Women &amp; Information Technology (NCWIT)]], and [[CRA-W: Committee on the Status of Women in Computing Research|Committee on the Status of Women in Computing Research (CRA-W)]].

===Athena Lectures===
The ACM-W gives an annual Athena Lecturer Award to honor outstanding women researchers who have made fundamental contributions to computer science.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://awards.acm.org/athena|title=About ACM Athena Lecturer Award|website=awards.acm.org|language=en|access-date=2017-04-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;  This program began in 2006. Speakers are nominated by SIG officers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| title = ACM-W Athena Lecturers Award Winners
| url = http://women.acm.org/ACM-W-Athena-Lectures
| publisher = ACM
| accessdate = 2013-12-01
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 2006–2007: [[Deborah Estrin]] of [[UCLA]]
* 2007–2008: [[Karen Spärck Jones]] of [[Cambridge University]]
* 2008–2009: [[Shafi Goldwasser]] of [[MIT]] and the Weitzmann Institute of Science
* 2009–2010: [[Susan J. Eggers]] of the [[University of Washington]]
* 2010–2011: [[Mary Jane Irwin]] of the [[Pennsylvania State University]]
* 2011–2012: [[Judith S. Olson]] of the [[University of California, Irvine]]
* 2012–2013: [[Nancy Lynch]] of [[MIT]]
* 2013–2014: [[Katherine Yelick]] of [[LBNL]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite pressrelease
| url = http://awards.acm.org/press_releases/athena_award_2013.pdf
| title = Berkeley Lab's Yelick Named &quot;Athena Lecturer&quot; for Contributions to Parallel Programming Languages that Improve Programmer Productivity
| publisher = ACM
| date = 2013-03-21
| accessdate = 2013-12-01
| url-status = dead
| archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20131203051039/http://awards.acm.org/press_releases/athena_award_2013.pdf
| archivedate = December 3, 2013
| df = mdy-all
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 2014–2015: [[Susan Dumais]] of [[Microsoft Research]]
* 2015–2016: [[Jennifer Widom]] of [[Stanford University]]
* 2016–2017: [[Jennifer Rexford]] of [[Princeton University]]

==Cooperation==
ACM's primary partner has been the [[IEEE Computer Society]] (IEEE-CS), which is the largest subgroup of the [[Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers]] (IEEE). The IEEE focuses more on hardware and standardization issues than theoretical [[computer science]], but there is considerable overlap with ACM's agenda. They have many joint activities including conferences, publications and awards.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=ACM / IEEE-CS Cooperation — Association for Computing Machinery|url=http://www.acm.org/acm-ieeecs-coop|website=www.acm.org|language=en|access-date=February 22, 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170101141809/http://www.acm.org/acm-ieeecs-coop|archive-date=January 1, 2017|url-status=dead|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; ACM and its SIGs co-sponsor about 20 conferences each year with IEEE-CS and other parts of IEEE.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=ACM / IEEE-CS Jointly Sponsored Conferences —Association for Computing Machinery|url=http://www.acm.org/acm-ieeecs-coop/conferences|website=www.acm.org|language=en|access-date=February 22, 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170101141814/http://www.acm.org/acm-ieeecs-coop/conferences|archive-date=January 1, 2017|url-status=dead|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Eckert-Mauchly Award]] and [[Ken Kennedy Award]], both major awards in computer science, are given jointly by ACM and the IEEE-CS.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=ACM / IEEE-CS Joint Awards — Association for Computing Machinery|url=http://www.acm.org/acm-ieeecs-coop/awards|website=www.acm.org|language=en|access-date=February 22, 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160406143733/http://www.acm.org/acm-ieeecs-coop/awards|archive-date=April 6, 2016|url-status=dead|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; They occasionally cooperate on projects like developing computing curricula.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2534860 |title=Computer Science Curricula 2013: Curriculum Guidelines for Undergraduate Degree Programs in Computer Science|author1 = Joint Task Force on Computing Curricula|author2 = Association for Computing Machinery (ACM)|author3 = IEEE Computer Society|authorlink3=IEEE Computer Society}}&lt;/ref&gt;

ACM has also jointly sponsored on events with other professional organizations like the [[Society for Industrial and Applied Mathematics]] (SIAM).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=SIAM: ACM-SIAM Symposium on Discrete Algorithms (SODA17)|url=https://www.siam.org/meetings/da17/|website=www.siam.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==ACM Code of Ethics and Professional Responsibility==
The ACM Code of Ethics and Professional Conduct&lt;ref&gt;https://www.acm.org/code-of-ethics&lt;/ref&gt; lays out codes of behavior for ACM members in their professional and personal conduct. The Code is conveyed under four general categories: General Ethical Principles, Professional Responsibilities, Professional Leadership Principles and Compliance with the Code:

*General Ethical Principles

The Code indicates that computing professionals should acknowledge their work contributes to societal well-being and that all people are impacted by the work of computing professionals. In addition, the Code calls on computing professionals to be obliged to ensure their work, both individually and collectively, benefits all of society, including respecting diversity and environmental sustainability.

The Code also calls on computing professionals to avoid harm in their professional and personal lives. Harm can be unintended or not, and can be physical, mental, involve disclosure of information, destruction of property, reputation or the environment. Actions should be taken to mitigate harm and to remedy any unintended harm that occurs do to computing professional work. Risk of computing systems causing harm should also be reported and actively mitigated upon discovery.

The Code calls on computing professionals to be honest and trustworthy. This include being forthright when a job or task calls on skills not readily known to the computing professional, and respecting organizational agency.

The Code calls on computing professionals to not discriminate. Discrimination is broadly defined, including &quot;discrimination on the basis of age, color, disability, ethnicity, family status, gender identity, labor union membership, military status, nationality, race, religion or belief, sex, sexual orientation, or any other inappropriate factor is an explicit violation of the Code.&quot; Efforts to mitigate the consequences of discrimination should be made when discrimination occurs.

The Code calls on computing professionals to respect privacy, and should use de-identification and anonymization methods on data when appropriate. Measures to prevent unauthorized data access should also be used. Furthermore, only the minimum amount of data needed to complete the task should be collected, and individuals should retain agency for how their data is used at all times. In a similar vein computing professionals should respect confidentiality when applicable.
 
*Professional Responsibilities

Computing professionals should strive for high work quality, both in terms of work process and work result. In that vein, computing professionals should strive to expand their capabilities and competencies both for themselves and the teams in which they operate. As rules for professional work differ from industry to industry, it is important that computing professionals know and respect these rules while maintaining a grounding in ethical conduct.

Computing professionals are often occasioned to review the work of others and have their work reviewed. This is a normal part of establishing a high level of work product, and computing professionals should seek such review. It is incumbent on computing professionals to provide comprehensive review of the work of others, both for the actual work and for anything missing (such as ignored risks or impacts) from the work. Computing professionals should also only perform work in which they have an area of competence, and only review the work of others in which they have said competence.

Computing professionals also have an affirmative duty to foster public awareness and understanding of the risks and advantages of their work. Such efforts should consider the public's existing understanding, and seek to generate an environment conducive to public engagement.

Computing professionals should only access computing and communication resources when authorized or compelled by the public interest. Many data resources reside in unsecured systems, yet their presence in an accessible format is not justification in itself to access them. Similarly computing professionals should design and implement systems that are sufficiently secure, and consider the risks of data being made public when determining what systems to implement to ensure data security.

*Professional Leadership Principles

Computing professionals in a positions of leadership has elevated responsibilities, both to society and to the people and organizations that they lead. The public good is a primary concern, and should seek to make public good considerations explicitly considered in their projects and work. As a leader, computing professionals should evaluate progress toward the social good in their projects and work, and seek to engage other computing professionals toward the same.

Computing professional leaders should also seek to improve the quality of life for themselves and the people and organizations they lead. This includes physical, mental and emotional well-being, but also seeking out educational and developmental opportunities. This should be done for technical skills, but also for ethical conduct.

Computing professional leaders should seek to integrate ethical considerations into automated systems and processes, and take especial care when retiring old systems or dealing with systems with the potential to become integrated with the infrastructure of society. Planning for transition of such systems, and allowing time for society to adapt to the new systems, should be undertaken.

*Compliance With the Code

Establishing a positive future for computing depends on both technical and ethical elevation of the field. Computing professionals should adhere to these principles and should take reasonable actions to ensure the code is operationalized in practice. This includes expressing concern to colleagues and people possibly violating the Code.

Violations of the Code should be reviewed by other computing professionals, not necessarily members of the ACM. Appropriate remedial action as determined by those professionals and as proscribed in the ACM's Code of Ethics and Professional Conduct Enforcement Policy should implemented as necessary.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.acm.org/code-of-ethics/enforcement-procedures&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{div col|colwidth=30em}}
* [[ACM Classification Scheme]]
* [[Franz Alt (mathematician)|Franz Alt]], former president
&lt;!-- * [[Association of Information Technology Professionals]] --&gt;
* [[Edmund Berkeley]], co&amp;ndash;founder
* [[Computer science]]
* [[Computing]]
* [[Bernard Galler]], former president
* [[List of Fellows of the Association for Computing Machinery|Fellows of the ACM (by year)]]
* [[:Category:Fellows of the Association for Computing Machinery|Fellows of the ACM (category)]]
* [[Grace Murray Hopper Award]]
&lt;!-- * [[Institution of Analysts and Programmers]] --&gt;
* [[:Category:Presidents of the Association for Computing Machinery|Presidents of the Association for Computing Machinery]]
* [[Timeline of computing hardware before 1950]]
* [[Turing Award]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Association for Computing Machinery}}
*{{Official website}}
*[http://portal.acm.org/ ACM portal] for publications
*[http://portal.acm.org/dl.cfm ACM Digital Library]
*[http://purl.umn.edu/51982 Association for Computing Machinery Records, 1947-2009], [[Charles Babbage Institute]], University of Minnesota.
* [http://upe.acm.org/about.html ACM Upsilon Phi Epsilon honor society]

{{Association for Computing Machinery}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Association For Computing Machinery}}
[[Category:Association for Computing Machinery| ]]
[[Category:1947 establishments in the United States]]
[[Category:Computer science-related professional associations]]
[[Category:International learned societies]]
[[Category:Organizations established in 1947]]</text>
      <sha1>e2g7hrawwd6b2udheoxcnyuw3eprvth</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
