  <page>
    <title>Anti-Ballistic Missile Treaty</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2975</id>
    <revision>
      <id>931231078</id>
      <parentid>931027442</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-12-17T19:43:32Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bluelinking 2 books for [[WP:V|verifiability]].) #IABot (v2.1alpha3</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{more citations needed|date=May 2017}}
{{Infobox treaty
| name                 = Anti-Ballistic Missile Treaty
| long_name            =
| image                = NIKE_Zeus.jpg
| image_alt            =
| caption              = Launch of a [[US Army]] [[Nike Zeus]] missile, the first ABM system to enter widespread testing.
| type                 = Bilateral treaty
| context              =
| date_drafted         =
| date_signed          = {{Start date|df=yes|1972|5|26}}
| location_signed      = [[Moscow]], [[Russian SFSR]], [[USSR]]
| date_sealed          =
| date_effective       =
| condition_effective  =
| date_expiration      =
| date_expiry          =
| mediators            =
| negotiators          =
| original_signatories =
| signatories          = {{Unbulleted list |{{flagicon|US}} [[Richard Nixon]] |{{flagicon|USSR}} [[Leonid Brezhnev]]}}
| parties              = {{Unbulleted list |{{flagcountry|United States}} |{{flagcountry|Soviet Union}} }}
| ratifiers            = {{Unbulleted list |[[US Senate]] |[[Supreme Soviet of the Soviet Union|Supreme Soviet]]}}
| depositor            =
| depositories         =
| citations            =
| language             =
| languages            =
| wikisource           = Anti-Ballistic Missile Treaty
| wikisource1          =
| footnotes            =
}}
The '''Anti-Ballistic Missile Treaty''' ('''ABM Treaty''' or '''ABMT''') (1972—2002) was an [[arms control]] [[treaty]] between the [[United States]] and the [[Soviet Union]] on the limitation of the [[anti-ballistic missile]] (ABM) systems used in defending areas against [[ballistic missile]]-delivered [[nuclear weapon]]s.  Under the terms of the treaty, each party was limited to two ABM complexes, each of which was to be limited to 100 anti-ballistic missiles.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|title=Nuclear Weapons and International Behaviour
|date=1 May 1975
|author=Henry T. Nash
|quote=Each site would consist of 100 ABMs, or a total of 200 ABMs for each country
|isbn=978-9028602656
|publisher=Kluwer Academic Publishers
|url-access=registration
|url=https://archive.org/details/nuclearweaponsin0000nash
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Signed in 1972, it was in force for the next 30 years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://2009-2017.state.gov/t/isn/trty/16332.htm |title=Treaty Between the United States of America and the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics on the Limitation of Anti-Ballistic Missile Systems |date=26 May 1972 |website=Bureau of Arms Control |publisher=United States Department of State}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1997, five years after the dissolution of the Soviet Union, four former Soviet republics agreed with the United States to succeed the USSR's role in the treaty.  In June 2002 the United States withdrew from the treaty, leading to its termination.

==Background==
[[File:Icbm-hist-en.png|thumb|left|165px|upright=1.2|Deployment history of land based ICBM 1959–2014]]
Throughout the late 1950s and into the 1960s, the United States and the Soviet Union had been developing missile systems with the ability to shoot down incoming [[ICBM]] warheads.  During this period, the US considered the defense of the US as part of reducing the overall damage inflicted in a full nuclear exchange. As part of this defense, [[Canada]] and the US established the North American Air Defense Command (now called [[NORAD|North American Aerospace Defense Command]]).

By the early 1950s, US research on the [[Project Nike|Nike Zeus]] missile system had developed to the point where small improvements would allow it to be used as the basis of an operational ABM system. Work started on a short-range, high-speed counterpart known as [[Sprint (missile)|Sprint]] to provide defense for the ABM sites themselves. By the mid-1960s, both systems showed enough promise to start development of base selection for a limited ABM system dubbed [[National Missile Defense#Sentinel Program|Sentinel]]. In 1967, the US announced that Sentinel itself would be scaled down to the smaller and less expensive [[Safeguard Program|Safeguard]]. Soviet doctrine called for development of its own ABM system and return to strategic parity with the US. This was achieved with the operational deployment of the [[A-35 anti-ballistic missile system|A-35 ABM system]] and its successors, which remain operational to this day.

The development of multiple independently targetable reentry vehicle ([[MIRV]]) systems allowed a single ICBM to deliver as many as ten separate warheads at a time.  An ABM defense system could be overwhelmed with the sheer number of warheads.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|title=International Arms Control: Issues and Agreements (Studies in International Security &amp; Arms Control)
|url=https://archive.org/details/internationalarm00blac
|url-access=registration
|author=Coit D. Blacker, Gloria Duffy
|publisher=Stanford University Press
|date=2002
|isbn=978-0804712224
|quote=The dramatic proliferation of warheads allowed by MIRV ensured that even an extensive ABM effort could not limit the destructiveness of an American retaliatory strike}}&lt;/ref&gt; Upgrading it to counter the additional warheads would be economically unfeasible: The defenders required one rocket per incoming warhead, whereas the attackers could place 10 warheads on a single missile at a reasonable cost. To further protect against ABM systems, the Soviet MIRV missiles were equipped with decoys; [[R-36 (missile)|R-36M]] heavy missiles carried as many as 40.&lt;ref name=&quot;Decoys&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/russia/article/0,2763,777379,00.html|title=Moscow extends life of 144 cold war ballistic missiles| accessdate = 2006-10-24|work=The Guardian | location=London | date=20 August 2002}}&lt;/ref&gt; These decoys would appear as warheads to an ABM, effectively requiring engagement of five times as many targets and rendering defense even less effective.

==ABM Treaty==
[[File:Carter_Brezhnev_sign_SALT_II.jpg|thumb|upright=1.3|[[Jimmy Carter]] and [[Leonid Brezhnev]] signing SALT II treaty, 18 June 1979, in Vienna.]]
The United States first proposed an anti-ballistic missile treaty at the 1967 [[Glassboro Summit Conference]] during discussions between U.S. Secretary of Defense [[Robert McNamara]] and Chairman of the Council of Ministers of the Soviet Union [[Alexei Kosygin]].  McNamara argued both that ballistic missile defense could provoke an arms race, and that it might provoke a first-strike against the nation fielding the defense. Kosygin rejected this reasoning. They were trying to minimize the number of nuclear missiles in the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|title=Contemporary Nuclear Debates: Missile Defenses, Arms Control, and Arms Races in the Twenty-First Century
|author=Alexander T.J. Lennon.
|publisher=MIT Press
|isbn=978-0262621663
|date=2002
|quote=Although Kosygin rejected this reasoning at Glassboro
|url-access=registration
|url=https://archive.org/details/contemporarynucl0000unse
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Following the proposal of the Sentinel and Safeguard decisions on American ABM systems, the [[SALT I|Strategic Arms Limitation Talks]] began in November 1969 (SALT I). By 1972 an agreement had been reached to limit strategic defensive systems. Each country was allowed two sites at which it could base a defensive system, one for the capital and one for ICBM silos.

The treaty was signed during the [[Moscow Summit (1972)|1972 Moscow Summit]] on 26 May by the [[President of the United States]], [[Richard Nixon]] and the [[General Secretary of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union]], [[Leonid Brezhnev]]; and ratified by the US Senate on 3 August 1972.

The 1974 Protocol reduced the number of sites to one per party, largely because neither country had developed a second site.&lt;ref name=&quot;FAS reference&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://fas.org/nuke/control/abmt/|title=ABM treaty reduces US and USSR to one ABM site each|work=The Nuclear Information Project|publisher=[[Federation of American Scientists|FAS]]|accessdate=27 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The sites were [[Moscow]] for the USSR and the North Dakota [[Stanley R. Mickelsen Safeguard Complex|Safeguard Complex]] for the US, which was already under construction.

===Missiles limited by the treaty===
The Treaty limited only ABMs capable of defending against &quot;strategic ballistic missiles&quot;, without attempting to define &quot;strategic&quot;. It was understood that both ICBMs and [[SLBM]]s are obviously &quot;strategic&quot;.&lt;ref name=Daalder&gt;{{cite journal|title=A tactical defence initiative for the Western Europe?|journal=Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists|date=May 1987|volume=43|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=pgYAAAAAMBAJ&amp;lpg=PA37&amp;pg=PA37|accessdate=8 February 2011|author=Ivo H. Daalder|page=37}}&lt;/ref&gt; Neither country intended to stop the development of counter-tactical ABMs. The topic became disputable as soon as most potent counter-tactical ABMs started to be capable of shooting down SLBMs (SLBMs naturally tend to be much slower than ICBMs), nevertheless both sides continued counter-tactical ABM development.&lt;ref name=Daalder /&gt;

==After the SDI announcement==
[[File:C13571-8a.jpg|thumb|upright=1.2|left|President Reagan delivering the 23 March 1983 speech initiating SDI]]
On 23 March 1983, [[Ronald Reagan]] announced the [[Strategic Defense Initiative]], a research program into ballistic missile defense which would be &quot;consistent with our obligations under the ABM Treaty&quot;. Reagan was wary of mutual deterrence with what he had recently called an &quot;[[Evil Empire speech|Evil Empire]]&quot;, and wanted to escape the traditional confines of [[mutual assured destruction]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Garthoff|first1=Raymond L.|title=The Great Transition: American-Soviet Relations and the End of the Cold War|url=https://archive.org/details/greattransitiona00gart|url-access=registration|date=1994|publisher=Brookings Institution|location=Washington, D.C.|isbn=978-0-8157-3060-6|page=[https://archive.org/details/greattransitiona00gart/page/99 99]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The project was a blow to [[Yuri Andropov]]'s so-called &quot;peace offensive&quot;. Andropov said that &quot;It is time [Washington] stopped thinking up one option after another in search of the best way of unleashing nuclear war in the hope of winning it. To do this is not just irresponsible. It is madness&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|work=[[Pravda]]|date=27 March 1983|title=Replies by Yu. V. Andropov to Questions from a Correspondent of Pravda}} Cited in {{cite book|last1=Garthoff|first1=Raymond L.|title=The Great Transition: American-Soviet Relations and the End of the Cold War|url=https://archive.org/details/greattransitiona00gart|url-access=registration|date=1994|publisher=Brookings Institution|location=Washington, D.C.|isbn=978-0-8157-3060-6|page=[https://archive.org/details/greattransitiona00gart/page/111 111]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Regardless of the opposition, Reagan gave every indication that SDI would not be used as a bargaining chip and that the United States would do all in its power to build the system. The Soviets were threatened because the Americans might have been able to make a nuclear first strike possible. In ''The Nuclear Predicament,'' Beckman claims that one of the central goals of Soviet diplomacy was to terminate SDI. A surprise attack from the Americans would destroy much of the Soviet ICBM fleet, allowing SDI to defeat a &quot;ragged&quot; Soviet retaliatory response. Furthermore, if the Soviets chose to enter this new arms race, they would further cripple their economy.  The Soviets could not afford to ignore Reagan's new endeavor, therefore their policy at the time was to enter negotiations with the Americans.&lt;ref&gt;Peter R. Beckman ''et al.'', The Nuclear Predicament: Nuclear Weapons In The Cold War And Beyond, 2nd ed. (New Jersey: Prentice-Hall Inc, 1992), 183.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;B. Wayne Howell, &quot;[http://msupress.msu.edu/journals/rpa/pdf/2_RP_11-3_Howell_389-415.pdf Reagan and Reykjavík: Arms Control, SDI, and the Argument From Human Rights] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20111003180126/http://msupress.msu.edu/journals/rpa/pdf/2_RP_11-3_Howell_389-415.pdf |date=3 October 2011 }},&quot; ''Rhetoric &amp; Public Affairs, Vol. 11'', No. 3, 2008, pp. 389–415&lt;/ref&gt;  By 1987, however, the USSR withdrew its opposition, concluding the SDI posed no threat and scientifically &quot;would never work.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Norman A. Graebner, Richard Dean Burns, and Joseph M. Siracusa, ''Reagan, Bush, Gorbachev: Revisiting the End of the Cold War,'' p. 95, 2008.  {{ISBN|0313352410}}, {{ISBN|978-0313352416}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Julian E. Zelizer|title=Arsenal of Democracy: The Politics of National Security—From World War II to the War on Terrorism|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=r_gH5s4B2SEC&amp;pg=PA350|year=2010|publisher=Basic Books|pages=350|isbn=9780465015078}}&lt;/ref&gt;

SDI research went ahead, although it did not achieve the hoped-for result. SDI research was cut back following the end of Reagan's presidency, and in 1995 it was reiterated in a presidential joint statement that &quot;missile defense systems may be deployed... [that] will not pose a realistic threat to the strategic nuclear force of the other side and will not be tested to... [create] that capability.&quot;  This was reaffirmed in 1997.

==Successor states to Soviet Union agree to continue treaty in force==
[[File:Bush and Putin signing SORT.jpg|thumb|236px|upright=1.3|Presidents [[Vladimir Putin]] and [[George W. Bush]] sign SORT on 24 May 2002 in Moscow]]
Although the Soviet Union ceased to exist in December 1991, in the view of the [[United States Department of State|U.S. Department of State]], the treaty continued in force.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://1997-2001.state.gov/www/global/arms/factsheets/missdef/mou.html
|title=Fact sheet: Memorandum of understanding on succession
|publisher=United States Department of State
|date=26 September 1997
|quote=Although the ABM Treaty continues in force, it nevertheless has become necessary to reach agreement as to which New Independent States (NIS) would collectively assume the rights and obligations of the USSR under the Treaty.}}&lt;/ref&gt;  An additional memorandum of understanding was prepared in 1997, establishing Belarus, Kazakhstan, the Russian Federation, and Ukraine as successor states to the Soviet Union, for the purposes of the treaty.

==United States withdrawal==
On 13 December 2001, [[George W. Bush]] gave [[Russia]] notice of the United States' withdrawal from the treaty, in accordance with the clause that required six months' notice before terminating the pact—the first time in recent history that the United States has withdrawn from a major international arms treaty.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=U.S. Withdrawal From the ABM Treaty: President Bush's Remarks and U.S. Diplomatic Notes|url=http://www.armscontrol.org/act/2002_01-02/docjanfeb02|publisher=Arms Control Association|accessdate=10 February 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;  This led to the eventual creation of the American [[Missile Defense Agency]].&lt;ref&gt;[https://georgewbush-whitehouse.archives.gov/news/releases/2001/12/20011213-2.html &quot;Announcement of Withdrawal from the ABM Treaty&quot;, White House press release]&lt;/ref&gt;

Supporters of the withdrawal argued that it was a necessity in order to test and build a limited [[National Missile Defense]] to protect the United States from [[nuclear blackmail]] by a [[rogue state]]. The withdrawal also had many critics. John Rhinelander, a negotiator of the ABM treaty, predicted that the withdrawal would be a &quot;fatal blow&quot; to the [[Treaty on the Non-Proliferation of Nuclear Weapons|Non-Proliferation Treaty]] and would lead to a &quot;world without effective legal constraints on [[nuclear proliferation]].&quot; The construction of a missile defense system was also feared to enable the US to attack with a nuclear [[first strike]]. Former [[U.S. Secretary of Defense]] [[William Perry]] also criticized the U.S. withdrawal as a very bad decision.&lt;ref&gt;New York Review of Books, 14 Jul. 2016, [https://www.nybooks.com/articles/2016/07/14/a-stark-nuclear-warning/ &quot;A Stark Nuclear Warning&quot;] &lt;/ref&gt;

Putin responded to the withdrawal by ordering a build-up of [[Russia and weapons of mass destruction#Nuclear weapons|Russia's nuclear capabilities]], designed to counterbalance U.S. capabilities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last=Majumdar | first=Dave | date=1 March 2018 | title=Russia's Nuclear Weapons Buildup Is Aimed at Beating U.S. Missile Defenses | url=https://nationalinterest.org/blog/the-buzz/russias-nuclear-weapons-buildup-aimed-beating-us-missile-24716 | work=The National Interest | location=USA | access-date=26 October 2018 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Russia and the United States signed the [[Strategic Offensive Reductions Treaty]] in Moscow on 24 May 2002. This treaty mandates cuts in deployed strategic nuclear warheads, but without actually mandating cuts to total stockpiled warheads, and without any mechanism for enforcement.

In [[The Putin Interviews|interviews]] with [[Oliver Stone]] in 2017, Russian president Vladimir Putin said that in trying to persuade Russia to accept US withdrawal from the treaty, both [[Bill Clinton]] and [[George W. Bush]] had tried, without evidence, to convince him of an emerging nuclear threat from [[Iran]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Stone |first1=Oliver |title=The Putin Interviews (Party 2 - 2:10) |url=https://www.sho.com/the-putin-interviews |website=www.sho.com |publisher=Showtime |accessdate=12 November 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==2018 statement by Putin on new weapons==
On 1 March 2018, Russian president [[Vladimir Putin]], in an [[Presidential Address to the Federal Assembly (Russia)|address]] to the Federal Assembly, announced the development of a series of technologically new missile systems and stressed that those were designed as a response to U.S. withdrawal from the ABM Treaty.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Presidential Address to the Federal Assembly|url=http://en.kremlin.ru/events/president/news/56957|website=kremlin.ru|language=en|date=1 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.nbcnews.com/nightly-news/video/exclusive-putin-denies-cold-war-1174558275948 Exclusive: Putin blames U.S. for arms race, denies 'new Cold War'] NBC News, 1 March 2018.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title=Beyond Russia's Development of New weapons: Insights From Military Innovation and Emulation Theory|url=https://www.academia.edu/37010220|journal=Boletim de Conjuntura Nerint|language=en|date=20 July 2018|last1=Dall|first1=Augusto César}}&lt;/ref&gt; His statements were referred to by the Trump administration officials as largely boastful untruths, but also as confirmation that &quot;Russia has been developing destabilizing weapons systems for over a decade, in direct violation of its treaty obligations&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[https://edition.cnn.com/2018/03/01/europe/putin-russia-missile-intl/ Putin claims new 'invincible' missile can pierce US defenses] CNN, 1 March 2018.&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
{{Wikisource|Anti-Ballistic Missile Treaty}}
*[https://2009-2017.state.gov/t/avc/trty/101888.htm Anti-Ballistic Missile Treaty], official State Department site, includes the [https://2009-2017.state.gov/t/avc/trty/101888.htm#text text] of the treaty and the [https://2009-2017.state.gov/t/avc/trty/101888.htm#protocolabm 1974 Protocol].
*[http://2001-2009.state.gov/t/ac/rls/fs/2001/6848.htm US Announcement of withdrawal (2001)]

{{Nuclear weapons limitation treaty}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2018}}


[[Category:1972 in the Soviet Union]]
[[Category:1972 in the United States]]
[[Category:Arms control treaties]]
[[Category:Cold War treaties]]
[[Category:Missile defense]]
[[Category:History of the United States (1991–present)]]
[[Category:Soviet Union–United States treaties]]
[[Category:Nuclear weapons governance]]
[[Category:Treaties concluded in 1972]]
[[Category:Treaties entered into force in 1972]]
[[Category:Presidency of Richard Nixon]]
[[Category:1972 in politics]]
[[Category:Nuclear technology treaties]]
[[Category:Russia–United States relations]]</text>
      <sha1>0m9dqwiialptf0cnhgbhqifvyip1zic</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
