  <page>
    <title>AIM (software)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2923</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943226101</id>
      <parentid>943225968</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-29T17:12:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Chuka Chief</username>
        <id>38326929</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 943225968 by [[Special:Contributions/68.32.141.134|68.32.141.134]] ([[User talk:68.32.141.134|talk]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use mdy dates|date=October 2017}}
{{Infobox software
| name = AIM
| logo = Logo of AOL Instant Messenger (2011).png
| logo caption = AIM's logo introduced in December 2011, replacing the earlier &quot;running man&quot; mascot
| screenshot = AIM 2013 screenshot.png
| caption = Windows version of AIM (2013 release)
| developer = [[AOL]]
| released = {{start date and age|1997|05}}
| discontinued = yes
| programming language = [[C++]], [[Adobe Flash]]
| operating system = [[Microsoft Windows]], [[Windows Mobile]], [[macOS]], [[Android (operating system)|Android]], [[iOS]], [[BlackBerry OS]], [[Android TV]]
| genre = [[Instant messaging]]
| license = [[proprietary software|Proprietary]]
| website = {{URL|www.aim.com}}
}}

'''AIM''' ('''AOL Instant Messenger''') was an [[instant messaging]] and [[presence information|presence]] [[computer program]] created by [[AOL]], which used the [[proprietary software|proprietary]] [[OSCAR protocol|OSCAR instant messaging protocol]] and the [[TOC protocol]] to allow registered users to communicate in real time.

AIM was popular from the late 1990s to the late 2000s in North America, and was the leading instant messaging application in that region. AIM's popularity declined steeply in the early 2010s as Internet social networks like [[Facebook]] and [[Twitter]] gained popularity, and its fall has often been compared with other once-popular Internet services such as [[Myspace]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mashable.com/2014/04/15/aim-history/|title=The Rise and Fall of AIM, the Breakthrough AOL Never Wanted | first=Jason | last=Abbruzzese|work=mashable.com|access-date=January 15, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 2015, AOL was acquired by [[Verizon Communications]].&lt;ref name=&quot;buyout-cnbc&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last1=Imbert|first1=Fred|title=Verizon to buy AOL for $4.4B; AOL shares soar|url=https://www.cnbc.com/id/102670331|publisher=CNBC|access-date=May 12, 2015|date=May 12, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Sawers |first=Paul |url=https://venturebeat.com/2015/06/23/verizon-completes-4-4b-acquisition-of-aol/ |title=Verizon completes $4.4B acquisition of AOL |work=VentureBeat |date=June 23, 2015 |access-date=June 23, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; In June 2017, Verizon combined AOL and Yahoo into its subsidiary Oath Inc (now called [[Verizon Media]]). The company discontinued AIM as a service on December 15, 2017.&lt;ref name=&quot;retirement&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://aimemories.tumblr.com/|title=Our Yellow Running Man is Ready to Retire|last=Albers|first=Michael|work=AOL Instant Messenger (AIM) on Tumblr|publisher=[[Oath Inc.]]|access-date=October 5, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
AOL Instant Messenger was initially integrated into [[AOL#AOL Desktop|AOL Desktop]] and later also released as a stand-alone download by [[AOL|America Online]] (AOL) in May 1997 for [[Microsoft Windows]].&lt;ref name=&quot;mashable&quot;&gt;Abbruzzese, Jason. [http://mashable.com/2014/04/15/aim-history/ &quot;The Rise and Fall of AIM, the Breakthrough AOL Never Wanted&quot;]. [[Mashable]].com. 2014-04-05.&lt;/ref&gt; AIM was an outgrowth of &quot;online messages&quot; in the original platform written in PL/1 on a Stratus computer by Dave Brown. The software, maintained by AOL, Inc., at one time had the largest share of the instant messaging market in North America, especially in the United States (with 52% of the total reported {{as of|2006|lc=y}}).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bigblueball.com/forums/general-other-im-news/34413-im-market-share.html |title=IM Market Share&amp;nbsp;— BigBlueBall Forums |publisher=Bigblueball.com |date= |access-date=December 4, 2010 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20101030030304/http://www.bigblueball.com/forums/general-other-im-news/34413-im-market-share.html |archivedate=October 30, 2010 |url-status=dead|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; This does not include other instant messaging software related to or developed by AOL, such as [[ICQ]] and [[iChat]].

[[File:AIM 4.7 screenshot.png|thumb|AIM version 4.7 (released 2001)]]
Its main competitors during its heyday were [[ICQ]] (although AOL acquired it in 1998), [[Yahoo! Messenger]] and [[Windows Live Messenger|MSN Messenger]]. AOL particularly had a rivalry or &quot;chat war&quot; with rival [[Microsoft]] starting in 1999. There were several attempts from Microsoft to simultaneously log into their own and AIM's protocol servers. AOL were not happy about this and started blocking MSN Messenger from being able to access AIM.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.theverge.com/2014/4/21/5635488/msn-messenger-vs-aol-aim-chat-wars|title=Inside Microsoft's '90s chat war with AOL|first=Tom|last=Warren|date=April 21, 2014|work=theverge.com|access-date=January 15, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://nplusonemag.com/issue-19/essays/chat-wars/|title=Chat Wars|date=March 25, 2014|work=nplusonemag.com|access-date=January 15, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:AIM 6.8 screenshot.png|thumb|AIM version 6.8 (released 2008)]]
Official mobile versions of AIM appeared as early as 2001 on [[Palm OS]] through the AOL application.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.macworld.com/article/1020672/m105.html|title=Palm introduces new m105 PDA|author=|date=March 6, 2001|website=Macworld|access-date=April 27, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Third-party applications allowed it to be used in 2002 for the [[Danger Hiptop|Sidekick]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://bgr.com/2007/10/02/mobile-im-clients-sidekick-helio-ocean-blackberry-iphone-and-more/|title=Mobile IM clients: Sidekick, Helio Ocean, BlackBerry, iPhone, and more|first=Jonathan S.|last=Geller|date=October 2, 2007|work=bgr.com|access-date=January 15, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; A version for [[Symbian OS]] was announced in 2003&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.zdnet.com/article/aol-and-symbian-cosy-up/|title=AOL and Symbian cosy up|first=Ben|last=Charny|date=|website=ZDNet|access-date=April 27, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; and others for [[BlackBerry]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.engadget.com/2007/04/11/get-your-official-blackberry-im-clients-now-if-you-dare/|title=Get your official BlackBerry IM clients now, if you dare|author=|date=|website=Engadget|access-date=April 27, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Windows Mobile]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://download.cnet.com/blog/download-blog/aims-windows-mobile-chat-app-nails-a-bullseye/|title=AIM's Windows Mobile chat app nails a bullseye&amp;nbsp;— The Download Blog&amp;nbsp;— CNET Download.com|work=cnet.com|access-date=January 15, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After 2012, stand-alone official AIM client software includes advertisements and was available for [[Microsoft Windows]], [[Windows Mobile]], [[Classic Mac OS]], [[macOS]], [[Android (operating system)|Android]], [[iOS]], [[BlackBerry OS]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://products.aim.com/products |title=Products AIM |publisher=Products AIM |date= |access-date=December 4, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Usage decline and product sunset===
Around 2011, AIM started to lose popularity rapidly, partly due to the quick rise of [[Gmail]] and its built-in real-time [[Google Talk|Google Chat]] instant messenger integration in 2011 and because many people started purely moving onto [[SMS]] [[text messaging]] and later [[Social networking service|social networking]] Web sites for instant messaging, in particular, [[Facebook Messenger]], which was released as a standalone application the same year.

As of June 2011, one source reported AOL Instant Messenger market share had collapsed to 0.73%.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.opswat.com/sites/default/files/OPSWAT-Market-Share-Report-June-2011.pdf|title=OPSWAT Market Share Report June 2011|publisher=opswat.com|date=|access-date=August 11, 2011|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130102180321/http://www.opswat.com/sites/default/files/OPSWAT-Market-Share-Report-June-2011.pdf|archive-date=January 2, 2013|url-status=dead|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, this number only reflects installed IM applications, and not active users. The engineers responsible for AIM claimed that they were unable to convince AOL management that free was the future.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Rise and Fall of AIM, the Breakthrough AOL Never Wanted|url=http://mashable.com/2014/04/15/aim-history/|website=Mashable}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On March 3, 2012, AOL ended employment of AIM's development staff while leaving it active and with help support still provided.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://gizmodo.com/5893031/aim-is-unofficially-dead|title=AIM Is (Unofficially) Dead (Updated)|first=Sam|last=Biddle|work=gizmodo.com|access-date=January 15, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; On October 6, 2017, it was announced that the AIM service would be discontinued on December 15;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://help.aol.com/articles/aim-discontinued|title=AIM Sunset|work=AOL Help Article|access-date=October 6, 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171006155404/https://help.aol.com/articles/aim-discontinued|archive-date=October 6, 2017|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;retirement&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.usatoday.com/story/tech/talkingtech/2017/10/06/rip-aim-aol-instant-messenger-dies-december/739076001/|title=RIP AIM: AOL Instant Messenger dies in December|first=Brett|last=Molina|work=[[USA Today]]|date=October 6, 2017|access-date=October 6, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; however, a non-profit development team known as Wildman Productions started up a server for older versions of AOL Instant Messenger known as AIM Phoenix.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.usatoday.com/story/tech/2018/06/26/aols-instant-messenger-back-aim-phoenix/736383002/|title=AOL's instant messenger is back: Meet AIM Phoenix|first=Dalvin|last=Brown|work=[[USA Today]]|date=June 26, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==The &quot;Running Man&quot;==
[[File:Farm-Fresh aol messenger.png|thumb|left|The &quot;Running Man&quot;]]
The AIM mascot was designed by JoRoan Lazaro and was implemented in the first release in 1997. This was a yellow [[stick figure|stickman]]-like figure, often called the &quot;Running Man&quot;. The mascot appeared on all AIM logos and most wordmarks, and always appeared at the top of the buddy list. AIM's popularity in the late 1990s and the 2000s led to the &quot;Running Man&quot; becoming a familiar brand on the Internet. After over 14 years, the iconic logo finally disappeared as part of the AIM rebranding in 2011. However, in August 2013, the &quot;Running Man&quot; once again returned.&lt;ref name=&quot;theatlantic.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2014/12/the-story-behind-aols-iconic-yellow-running-man/383652/|title=The Story Behind AOL's Iconic Yellow Running Man|first=Adrienne|last=LaFrance|work=theatlantic.com|access-date=January 15, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2014, a ''[[Complex (magazine)|Complex]]'' editor called it a &quot;symbol of America&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://uk.complex.com/style/2014/12/aol-designer-explains-the-companys-iconic-yellow-running-man-logo|title=AOL Designer Explains the Company's Iconic Yellow Running Man Logo|work=complex.com|access-date=January 15, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; In April 2015 the Running Man was officially featured in the [[London Marathon|Virgin London Marathon]], dressed by a person for the AOL-partnered [[WE Charity|Free The Children]] charity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.advertising.aol.co.uk/2015/03/31/aol-s-running-man-takes-part-in-london-marathon-in-support-of-fr/|title=AOL's Running Man takes part in London Marathon in Support of Free The Children|work=aol.co.uk|access-date=January 15, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Protocol==
The standard protocol that AIM clients used to communicate is called [[OSCAR protocol|Open System for CommunicAtion in Realtime]] (OSCAR). Most AOL-produced versions of AIM and popular third party AIM clients use this protocol. However, AOL also created a simpler protocol called [[TOC protocol|TOC]] that lacks many of OSCAR's features, but was sometimes used for clients that only require basic chat functionality. The TOC/TOC2 protocol specifications were made available by AOL, while OSCAR is a closed protocol that third parties have had to reverse-engineer.

In January 2008, AOL introduced experimental [[XMPP|Extensible Messaging and Presence Protocol]] (XMPP) support for AIM,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://florianjensen.com/2008/01/17/aol-adopting-xmpp-aka-jabber/|title=AOL adopting XMPP aka Jabber|date=2008-01-17|access-date=2008-01-17|author=Florian Jensen|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080120143857/http://florianjensen.com/2008/01/17/aol-adopting-xmpp-aka-jabber/|archivedate=January 20, 2008|url-status=dead|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; allowing AIM users to communicate using the standardized, open-source XMPP. However, in March 2008, this service was discontinued.{{Citation needed|date=December 2010}} In May 2011, AOL started offering limited XMPP support.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aim.com/xmpp |title=AOL XMPP Gateway |date=2011-05-14 |access-date=2011-05-14 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110522092331/http://www.aim.com/xmpp |archivedate=May 22, 2011 |url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; On March 1, 2017, AOL announced (via XMPP-login-time messages&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://pidgin.im/pipermail/support/2017-March/029513.html|title=Fwd: AOL|date=2017-03-01|access-date=March 1, 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170302030248/https://pidgin.im/pipermail/support/2017-March/029513.html|archive-date=March 2, 2017|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;) that the AOL XMPP gateway would be desupported, effective March 28, 2017.

==Privacy==
For privacy regulations, AIM had strict age restrictions. AIM accounts are available only for people over the age of 13; children younger than that were not permitted access to AIM.&lt;ref name=&quot;6 Facts About AIM's Privacy Policy&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://im.about.com/od/promotingimsafety/a/aim-privacy.htm|title=AIM Privacy -- Terms of Service Policy -- AIM Privacy|author=Brandon De Hoyos|work=About.com Tech|access-date=August 10, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Under the AIM Privacy Policy, AOL had no rights to read or monitor any private communications between users. The profile of the user had no privacy.&lt;ref name=&quot;6 Facts About AIM's Privacy Policy&quot; /&gt;

In November 2002, AOL targeted the corporate industry with Enterprise AIM Services (EAS), a higher security version of AIM.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.computerworld.com/article/2578769/aol-takes-aim-at-corporate-instant-messaging-users.html|title=AOL Takes AIM at Corporate Instant Messaging Users|first=Todd R.|last=Weiss|date=November 11, 2002|website=Computerworld|access-date=April 27, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

If public content was accessed, it could be used for online, print or broadcast advertising, etc. This was outlined in the policy and terms of service: &quot;...&amp;nbsp;you grant AOL, its parent, affiliates, subsidiaries, assigns, agents and licensees the irrevocable, perpetual, worldwide right to reproduce, display, perform, distribute, adapt and promote this Content in any medium&quot;. This allowed anything users posted to be used without a separate request for permission.&lt;ref name=&quot;6 Facts About AIM's Privacy Policy&quot; /&gt;

The issue of AIM's security was called into question. AOL stated that it had taken great steps to insure that personal information will not be accessed by unauthorized members, but that it cannot guarantee that it will not happen.&lt;ref name=&quot;6 Facts About AIM's Privacy Policy&quot; /&gt;

AIM was different from other clients, such as [[Yahoo! Messenger]], in that it did not require approval from users to be added to other users' buddy lists. As a result, it was possible for users to keep other unsuspecting users on their buddy list to see when they were online, read their status and away messages, and read their profiles. There was also a Web API to display one's status and away message as a widget on one's webpage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://dev.aol.com/data_sheets/WebAIM_Quick_Start_Guide.pdf |title=Integrate Your Site with AIM in 3 Easy Steps |work=AOL Developer Network |publisher=AOL Inc |page=2 |format=PDF |access-date=August 9, 2011 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110726062640/http://dev.aol.com/data_sheets/WebAIM_Quick_Start_Guide.pdf |archivedate=July 26, 2011 |url-status=dead|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; Though one could block a user from communicating with them and seeing their status, this did not prevent that user from creating a new account that would not automatically be blocked and therefore able to track their status. A more conservative privacy option was to select a menu feature that only allowed communication with users on one's buddy list; however, this option also created the side-effect of blocking all users who were not on one's buddy list.

==Chat robots==
AOL and various other companies supplied robots (bots) on AIM that could receive messages and send a response based on the bot's purpose. For example, bots could help with studying, like StudyBuddy. Some were made to relate to children and teenagers, like [[Spleak]].

Others gave advice, and others were for more general purposes, such as false. The more useful chat bots had features like the ability to play games, get sport scores, weather forecasts or financial stock information. Users were able to talk to automated chat bots that could respond to natural human language. They were primarily put into place as a marketing strategy and for unique advertising options. It was used by advertisers to market products or build better consumer relations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cnet.com/news/aol-tries-out-new-im-chat-bot/|title=tries out new IM chat bot |date=2003-01-27 |access-date=2015-10-27|website=[[CNET]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Before the inclusions of such bots, the other bots DoorManBot and AIMOffline provided features that were provided by AOL for those who needed it. ZolaOnAOL and ZoeOnAOL were short-lived bots that ultimately retired their features in favor of SmarterChild.

==URI scheme==
AOL Instant Messenger's installation process automatically installed an extra [[Uniform Resource Identifier|URI scheme]] (&quot;protocol&quot;) handler into some Web browsers, so URIs beginning &quot;&lt;tt&gt;aim:&lt;/tt&gt;&quot; could open a new AIM window with specified parameters. This was similar in function to the &lt;tt&gt;mailto:&lt;/tt&gt; URI scheme, which created a new e-mail message using the system's default mail program. For instance, a webpage might have included a link like the following in its HTML source to open a window for sending a message to the AIM user ''notarealuser'':
 &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;a href=&quot;aim:goim?screenname=notarealuser&quot;&amp;gt;Send Message&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;

To specify a message body, the &lt;code&gt;message&lt;/code&gt; parameter was used, so the link location would have looked like this:
 &lt;code&gt;aim:goim?screenname=notarealuser&amp;message=This+is+my+message&lt;/code&gt;

To specify an away message, the message parameter was used, so the link location would have looked like this:
 &lt;code&gt;aim:goaway?message=Hello,+my+name+is+Bill&lt;/code&gt;
When placing this inside a URL link, an AIM user could click on the URL link and the away message &quot;Hello, my name is Bill&quot; would instantly become their away message.

To add a buddy, the addbuddy message was used, with the &quot;screenname&quot; parameter
 &lt;code&gt;aim:addbuddy?screenname=notarealuser&lt;/code&gt;
This type of link was commonly found on forum profiles to easily add contacts.

==Vulnerabilities==
AIM had security weaknesses that have enabled [[exploit (computer security)|exploits]] to be created that used third-party software to perform malicious acts on users' computers.&lt;ref name=&quot;fileforum.betanews.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://fileforum.betanews.com/detail/AOL-Instant-Messenger-for-Windows/929853714/1|title=Reviews of AOL Instant Messenger for Windows|date=2011-01-08|access-date=2012-03-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although most were relatively harmless, such as being kicked off the AIM service, others performed potentially dangerous actions such as sending [[computer virus|viruses]]. Some of these exploits relied on [[social engineering (security)|social engineering]] to spread by automatically sending instant messages that contained a [[URL|Uniform Resource Locator]] (URL) accompanied by text suggesting the receiving user click on it, an action which leads to infection, ''i.e.'', a [[Trojan horse (computing)|trojan]]. These messages could easily be mistaken as coming from a friend and contain a link to a Web address that installed software on the user's computer to restart the cycle.

Users also have reported sudden additions of toolbars and advertisements from third parties in the newer version of AIM. Multiple complaints about the lack of control of third party involvement have caused many users to stop using the service.&lt;ref name=&quot;fileforum.betanews.com&quot; /&gt;

==Extra features==

===iPhone application===
On March 6, 2008, during [[Apple Inc.]]'s [[IOS SDK|iPhone SDK]] event, AOL announced that they would be releasing an AIM application for [[iPhone]] and [[iPod Touch]] users. The application is available for free from the App Store, but the company also provides a paid version, which displays no advertisements. Both are available from the [[App Store (iOS)|App Store]]. The AIM client for [[iPhone]] and [[iPod Touch]] supports standard AIM accounts as well as [[MobileMe]] accounts. There is also an express version of AIM accessible through the [[Safari (web browser)|Safari]] browser on the iPhone and iPod Touch.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.macrumors.com/2008/03/06/apple-releases-iphone-sdk-demos-spore-instant-messaging/ |title=Apple Releases iPhone SDK, Demos Spore, Instant Messaging |publisher=Mac Rumors |date=2008-03-06 |access-date=2010-12-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2011, AOL launched an overhaul of their Instant Messaging service. Included in the update was a brand new [[iOS]] application for iPhone and [[iPod Touch]] that incorporated all the latest features. A brand new icon was used for the application, featuring the new cursive logo for AIM. The user-interface was entirely redone for the features including: a new buddy list, group messaging, in-line photos and videos, as well as improved file-sharing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine|url=https://www.pcmag.com/article2/0,2817,2396491,00.asp/ |title=AOL Overhauls AIM, Adds New iPhone App |magazine=PC Magazine |date=2011-11-16 |access-date=2012-03-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Currently{{When|date=April 2019}} the application is in version 5.0.5, which was updated as of March 2012. In the latest iteration, it supports more social stream features, much like Facebook and Twitter, as well as the ability to send voice messages up to 60 seconds long.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://handheld.softpedia.com/get/Chat/AIM-for-iPhone-97755.shtml/ |title=AIM for iPhone 5.0.5 |publisher=Softpedia |date=2012-03-20 |access-date=2012-03-25 |url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20111227011258/http://handheld.softpedia.com/get/Chat/AIM-for-iPhone-97755.shtml |archivedate=2011-12-27 |df=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===iPad application===
On April 3, 2010, Apple released the first generation iPad. Along with this newly released device AOL released the AIM application for iPad. It was built entirely from scratch for the new version iOS with a specialized user-interface for the device. It supports geo location, Facebook status updates and chat, Myspace, Twitter, YouTube, Foursquare and many social networking platforms.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.macstories.net/ipad/aim-for-ipad-approved-screenshot/ |title=AIM for iPad Approved, Screenshot |publisher=MacStories |date=2010-04-01 |access-date=2012-03-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===AIM Express===
AIM Express ran in a pop-up browser window. It was intended for use by people who are unwilling or unable to install a standalone application or those at computers that lack the AIM application. AIM Express supported many of the standard features included in the stand-alone client, but did not provide advanced features like file transfer, audio chat, video conferencing, or buddy info. It was implemented in [[Adobe Flash]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aim.com/products/express |title=www.aim.com/products/express |publisher=Aim.com |access-date=2010-12-04| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20101205062532/http://www.aim.com/products/express| archivedate=December 5, 2010 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was an upgrade to the prior AOL Quick Buddy, which was later available for older systems that cannot handle Express before being discontinued. Express and Quick Buddy were similar to [[Windows Live Messenger#MSN Web Messenger|MSN Web Messenger]] and [[Yahoo! Messenger#Web Messenger|Yahoo! Web Messenger]]. This web version evolved into AIM.com's web-based messenger.

===AIM Pages===
{{Main|AIM Pages}}
AIM Pages was released in May 2006, allowing the 63 million AIM users to create an online, dynamic profile. The buddy list serves as the basis for the AIM Page [[social networking service]]. An AIM Page is built using modules following the ModuleT [[microformat]]. AIM Pages was discontinued in late 2007.

===AIM for Mac===
AOL released an all-new AIM for the [[Macintosh]] on September 29, 2008 and the final build on December 15, 2008. The redesigned AIM for Mac is a full [[universal binary]] [[Cocoa (API)|Cocoa API]] application that supports both Tiger and Leopard&amp;nbsp;— [[macOS|Mac OS X]] 10.4.8 (and above) or Mac OS X 10.5.3 (and above). On October 1, 2009, AOL released AIM 2.0 for Mac.

===AIM real-time IM===
This feature is available for AIM 7 and allows for a user to see what the other is typing as it is being done. It was developed and built with assistance from Trace Research and Development Centre at [[University of Wisconsin–Madison]] and [[Gallaudet University]]. The application provides visually impaired users the ability to convert messages from text (words) to speech.&lt;ref name=&quot;What is Real-Time IM&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aniesoft.com/realtime-im.html|title=What is Real-Time IM? Source: AOL Help|work=aniesoft.com|access-date=January 15, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; For the application to work users must have AIM 6.8 or higher, as it is not compatible with older versions of AIM software, AIM for Mac or iChat.&lt;ref name=&quot;What is Real-Time IM&quot; /&gt;

===AIM to mobile (messaging to phone numbers)===
This feature allows text messaging to a phone number ([[Message#Increasing competition|text messaging is less functional]] than instant messaging).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=How-To use AIM to send a Text Message to a phone|url=https://www.engadget.com/2004/07/13/how-to-use-aol-instant-messenger-to-send-a-text-message-to-a|website=engadget.com|date=July 13, 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Discontinued features==

===AIM for Phoneline===
AIM Phoneline was a [[Voice over IP]] PC-PC, PC-Phone and Phone-to-PC service&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.timewarner.com/corp/newsroom/pr/0,20812,1194787,00.html|title=Press Releases|publisher=|access-date=August 10, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; provided via the AIM application. It was also known to work with Apple's iChat Client.

Launched on May 16, 2006, AIM Phoneline provided users the ability to have several local numbers, allowing AIM users to receive free incoming calls.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://labnol.blogspot.ca/2006/05/aim-phoneline-free-phone-number-for.html|title=AIM Phoneline: Free Phone number for AOL Messenger users|publisher=|access-date=August 10, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The service allowed users to make calls to landlines and mobile devices through the use of a computer. The service, however, was only free for receiving and AOL charged users $14.95 a month for an unlimited calling plan.&lt;ref name=&quot;pcworld.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pcworld.com/article/126005/first_look_aim_phoneline_and_skype_25.html|title=First Look: AIM Phoneline and Skype 2.5|date=June 19, 2006|work=PCWorld|access-date=August 10, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In order to use AIM Phoneline users had to install the latest free version of AIM Triton software and needed a good set of headphones with a boom microphone. It could take several days after a user signed up before it started working.&lt;ref name=&quot;pcworld.com&quot; /&gt;

On January 13, 2009, the service was officially closed. The closing of the free service caused the number associated with the service to be disabled and not transferable for a different service.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dslreports.com/forum/r21456143-Free-AIM-Phoneline-Service-Closing-on-January-13-2009|title=Free AIM Phoneline Service Closing on January 13, 2009&amp;nbsp;— VOIP Tech Chat&amp;nbsp;— DSLReports Forums|publisher=|access-date=August 10, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===AIM Call Out===
AIM Call Out is a discontinued Voice over IP PC-PC, PC-Phone and Phone-to-PC service provided by AOL via its AIM application that replaced the defunct AIM Phoneline service in November 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aimphoneline.com/?promo=784114&amp;flv=1&amp;ncid=oyjqUzrKfk0000000465&amp;icid=one_click.M|title=Looking for AIM Phoneline?|publisher=Aimphoneline.com|access-date=2008-10-02}}{{dead link|date=March 2018 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; It did not depend on the AIM client and could be used with only an AIM screenname via the WebConnect feature or a dedicated SIP device. The AIM Call Out service was shut down on March 25, 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://voice.aol.com/|title=AOL Voice Services no longer offers new registrations|website=AOL.com|access-date=2014-12-18|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20141218012459/http://voice.aol.com/|archivedate=December 18, 2014|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Security==
On November 4, 2014, AIM scored one out of seven points on the [[Electronic Frontier Foundation]]'s secure messaging scorecard. AIM received a point for encryption during transit, but lost points because communications are not encrypted with a key to which the provider has no access, ''i.e.'', the communications are not [[End-to-end encryption|end-to-end encrypted]], users can't verify contacts' identities, past messages are not secure if the encryption keys are stolen, (''i.e.'', the service does not provide [[forward secrecy]]), the code is not open to independent review, ''i.e.'', the code is not [[Open-source software|open-source]]), the security design is not properly documented, and there has not been a recent independent security audit.&lt;ref name=&quot;secure-messaging-scorecard&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.eff.org/secure-messaging-scorecard |publisher=[[Electronic Frontier Foundation]] |title=Secure Messaging Scorecard. Which apps and tools actually keep your messages safe? |date=November 4, 2014 |access-date=June 1, 2015 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161115054343/https://www.eff.org/secure-messaging-scorecard |archive-date=November 15, 2016 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.pcmag.com/article2/0,2817,2471658,00.asp |work=[[PC Magazine]] |title=Only 6 Messaging Apps Are Truly Secure |date=November 5, 2014 |access-date=January 8, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[BlackBerry Messenger]], [[eBuddy|Ebuddy XMS]], [[Hushmail]], [[Kik Messenger]], [[Skype]], [[Viber]], and [[Yahoo! Messenger]] also scored one out of seven points.&lt;ref name=&quot;secure-messaging-scorecard&quot; /&gt;

==See also==
* [[Comparison of instant messaging clients]]
* [[List of defunct instant messaging platforms]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
* {{Official website|http://www.aim.com/}}
{{Instant messaging}}
{{Oath Inc.}}

[[Category:1997 software]]
[[Category:AIM clients|*]]
[[Category:Android (operating system) software]]
[[Category:AOL|Instant Messenger]]
[[Category:BlackBerry software]]
[[Category:Classic Mac OS instant messaging clients]]
[[Category:Computer-related introductions in 1997]]
[[Category:Internet properties disestablished in 2017]]
[[Category:Cross-platform software]]
[[Category:Instant messaging clients]]
[[Category:IOS software]]
[[Category:MacOS instant messaging clients]]
[[Category:Online chat]]
[[Category:Symbian software]]
[[Category:Unix instant messaging clients]]
[[Category:Videotelephony]]
[[Category:Windows instant messaging clients]]</text>
      <sha1>83es1kva1081qr1pcd63uu0l0h7e1qo</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
