  <page>
    <title>And did those feet in ancient time</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2940</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941822780</id>
      <parentid>940669663</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-20T22:01:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bluelink 2 books for [[Wikipedia:Verifiability|verifiability]]. [goog]) #IABot (v2.0) ([[User:GreenC bot|GreenC bot]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|1808 William Blake poem adapted into a popular English hymn}}
{{EngvarB|date=October 2017}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2017}}
{{Infobox anthem 
|title = And did those feet in ancient time 
|alt_title = Jerusalem
|image = Milton preface.jpg{{!}}border
|caption = The preface to ''[[Milton: A Poem in Two Books|Milton]]'', as it appeared in Blake's own illuminated version
|prefix = Unofficial national
|country = {{flagu|England}}
|author = [[William Blake]]
|lyrics_date = 1804
|composer = [[Hubert Parry]]
|music_date = 1916
}}
&quot;'''And did those feet in ancient time'''&quot; is a poem by [[William Blake]] from the preface to his epic ''[[Milton: A Poem in Two Books]]'', one of a collection of writings known as the [[Blake's prophetic books|Prophetic Books]]. The date of 1804 on the title page is probably when the plates were begun, but the poem was printed c. 1808.&lt;ref name=cocel&gt;Cox, Michael, editor, ''The Concise Oxford Chronology of English Literature'', &quot;1808&quot;, p 289, Oxford University Press, 2004, {{ISBN|0-19-860634-6}}&lt;/ref&gt; Today it is best known as the hymn &quot;'''Jerusalem'''&quot;, with music written by [[Hubert Parry|Sir Hubert Parry]] in 1916. It is not to be confused with another poem, much longer and larger in scope, but also by Blake, called ''[[Jerusalem The Emanation of the Giant Albion]]''.

The poem was inspired by the [[apocryphal]] story that a young Jesus, accompanied by [[Joseph of Arimathea]], a tin merchant, travelled to what is now England and visited [[Glastonbury]] during his [[unknown years of Jesus|unknown years]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Icons1&quot;&gt;Icons – a portrait of England. Icon: Jerusalem (hymn) [http://www.icons.org.uk/theicons/collection/jerusalem/features/and-did-those-feet Feature: And did those feet?] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20091212021243/http://www.icons.org.uk/theicons/collection/jerusalem/features/and-did-those-feet |date=12 December 2009 }} Accessed 7 August 2008&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Peter Stanford, &quot;[http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-1231308/Did-Jesus-REALLY-stay-England-A-new-film-claims-built-church-Somerset-learnt-maths-Druids.html Did Jesus REALLY stay in England? A new film claims he built a church in Somerset and learnt maths from the Druids]&quot;, ''Daily Mail'', 27 November 2009. Retrieved 2016.10.21.&lt;/ref&gt; The poem's theme is linked to the [[Book of Revelation]] ([[Revelation 3:12|3:12]] and [[Revelation 21|21]]:2) describing a [[Second Coming]], wherein Jesus establishes a [[New Jerusalem]]. Churches in general, and the [[Church of England]] in particular, have long used Jerusalem as a metaphor for [[Heaven (Christianity)|Heaven]], a place of universal love and peace.{{efn|The hymn 'Jerusalem the Golden with milk and honey blessed... I know not oh I know not what joys await me there....' uses Jerusalem for the same metaphor.}}

In the most common interpretation of the poem, Blake implies that a visit by Jesus would briefly create heaven in England, in contrast to the &quot;dark Satanic Mills&quot; of the [[Industrial Revolution]]. Blake's poem asks four questions rather than asserting the historical truth of Christ's visit. Thus the poem merely implies that there may have been a divine visit, when there was briefly heaven in England.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/blogs/theoneshow/onepassions/2008/10/whats-your-anthem.html |title= The One Show |publisher=BBC |date=17 October 2008 |accessdate=29 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.independent.co.uk/opinion/bring-no-spears-to-jerusalem-1347934.html John Walsh ''[[The Independent]]'' 18 May 1996]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Text==
The original text is found in the preface Blake wrote for inclusion with ''Milton, a Poem'', following the lines beginning &quot;The Stolen and Perverted Writings of Homer &amp; Ovid: of Plato &amp; Cicero, which all Men ought to contemn: ...&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;blakearchive&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.blakearchive.org/copy/milton.b?descId=milton.b.illbk.02|first=William|last=Blake|title=''Milton a Poem'', copy B object 2|work=[[The William Blake Archive]]|publisher=Ed. Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph Viscomi|accessdate=8 June 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Blake's poem'''&lt;!-- rendered literatim per [[WP:QUOTE]]; do not add apostrophes --&gt;
{{quote|&lt;poem&gt;
And did those feet in ancient time,
Walk upon Englands{{efn|Blake wrote ''Englands'' here, and twice later, where we would use the genitive ''England's''}} mountains green:
And was the holy [[Lamb of God]],
On Englands pleasant pastures seen!

And did the [[Divine countenance|Countenance Divine]],
Shine forth upon our clouded hills?
And was [[New Jerusalem|Jerusalem]] builded here,
Among these dark Satanic Mills?

[[Armor of God|Bring me my Bow]] of burning gold:
Bring me my Arrows of desire:
Bring me my Spear: O clouds unfold:
Bring me my [[wikisource:Bible (King James)/2 Kings#6:17|Chariot of fire]]!

I will not cease from Mental Fight,
Nor shall my Sword sleep in my hand:
Till we have built Jerusalem,
In Englands green &amp; pleasant Land.
&lt;/poem&gt;}}

Beneath the poem Blake inscribed a quotation from the Bible:&lt;ref name=&quot;Numbers&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Numbers+11%3A29&amp;version=KJV|title=Numbers 11:29 | work=King James Version | publisher=biblegateway.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{quote|&lt;poem&gt;&quot;Would to God that all the Lords{{efn|Blake wrote ''Lords'' where we would use the modern genitive ''Lord's''}} people were Prophets&quot;
[[Book of Numbers|Numbers]] XI. Ch 29.v&lt;ref name=&quot;blakearchive&quot;/&gt;&lt;/poem&gt;}}

===&quot;Dark Satanic Mills&quot;===
[[File:Albion Flour Mills Bankside.jpg|thumb|Albion Flour Mills, [[Bankside]], London]]
The phrase &quot;dark Satanic Mills&quot;, which entered the English language from this poem, is often interpreted as referring to the early [[Industrial Revolution]] and its destruction of nature and human relationships.&lt;ref&gt;Lienhard, John H. 1999 [http://www.uh.edu/engines/epi1413.htm Poets in the Industrial Revolution.] [[The Engines of Our Ingenuity]] No. 1413: (Revised transcription)&lt;/ref&gt;  This view has been linked to the fate of the [[Albion Mills, Southwark|Albion Flour Mills]] in [[Southwark]], the first major factory in London. This rotary steam-powered flour mill by [[Matthew Boulton]] and [[James Watt]] could produce 6,000 [[bushel]]s of flour per week. The factory could have driven independent traditional millers out of business, but it was destroyed in 1791 by fire, perhaps [[Luddite|deliberately]]. London's independent millers celebrated with placards reading, &quot;Success to the mills of [[Albion]] but no Albion Mills.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;ICONS1&quot;&gt;ICONS – a portrait of England. Icon: Jerusalem (hymn) [http://www.icons.org.uk/theicons/collection/jerusalem/features/and-did-those-feet Feature: And did those feet?] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20091212021243/http://www.icons.org.uk/theicons/collection/jerusalem/features/and-did-those-feet |date=12 December 2009 }} Accessed 7 August 2008&lt;/ref&gt; Opponents referred to the factory as [[satan]]ic, and accused its owners of adulterating flour and using cheap imports at the expense of British producers. A contemporary illustration of the fire shows a [[devil]] squatting on the building.&lt;ref&gt;Brian Maidment, ''Reading Popular Prints, 1790–1870'', Manchester University Press, 2001, p.40&lt;/ref&gt; The mills were a short distance from Blake's home.

Blake's phrase resonates with a broader theme in his works, what he envisioned as a physically and spiritually [[Political repression|repressive]] ideology based on a quantified reality. Blake saw the [[cotton mill]]s and [[collieries]] of the period as a mechanism for the enslavement of millions, but the concepts underpinning the works had a wider application:&lt;ref name=&quot;PortKaz&quot;&gt;[[Alfred Kazin]]: ''Introduction to a volume of Blake.'' 1946&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;HallGen&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.21learn.org/archive/articles/hall_genius.php |title=In Defense of Genius |last=Hall |first=Ernest |authorlink=Ernest Hall (businessman) |date=8 February 1996 |work=Annual Lecture to the Arts Council of England |publisher=21st Century Learning Initiative |accessdate=19 September 2009 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20081025003242/http://www.21learn.org/archive/articles/hall_genius.php |archivedate=25 October 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Quote|And all the Arts of Life they changed into the Arts of Death in Albion./...{{efn|[[Incipit]] of citation given in Hall, 1996:  &lt;poem&gt;&quot;And all the Arts of Life they changed into the Arts of Death in Albion.
The hour-glass contemned because its simple workmanship
Was like the workmanship of the Plowman and the water-wheel

That raises water into cisterns, broken and burned with fire
Because its workmanship was like the workmanship of the shepherd;
And in their stead intricate wheels invented, wheel without wheel
To perplex youth in their outgoings and to bind to labours in
Albion.&quot;&lt;/poem&gt;}}|''[[Jerusalem The Emanation of the Giant Albion|Jerusalem]]'' Chapter 3. [[William Blake]]}}

[[File:Milton a Poem, copy C, object 4 (Bentley 4, Erdman 6, Keynes 4) detail-a.jpg|thumb|400px|The first reference to Satan's &quot;mills&quot;, next to images of megaliths ([[Milton: A Poem in Two Books]], copy C, object 4)]] Another interpretation, amongst [[Nonconformist (Protestantism)|Nonconformist]]s, is that the phrase refers to the established [[Church of England]]. This church preached a doctrine of conformity to the established social order and class system, in contrast to Blake. In 2007 the new [[Bishop of Durham]], [[N. T. Wright]], explicitly recognised this element of English subculture when he acknowledged this alternative view that the &quot;dark satanic mills&quot; refer to the &quot;great churches&quot;.&lt;ref name=DurhBish&gt;[[N. T. Wright]], Bishop of Durham (23 June 2007) &quot;[http://www.ntwrightpage.com/sermons/Durham_Wisdom.htm Where Shall Wisdom be Found?] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131022005251/http://ntwrightpage.com/sermons/Durham_Wisdom.htm |date=22 October 2013 }}&quot; Homily at the 175th anniversary of the founding of the [[University of Durham]]. ntwrightpage.com&lt;/ref&gt; In similar vein, the critic [[F. W. Bateson]] noted how &quot;the adoption by the Churches and women's organizations of this anti-clerical paean of free love is amusing evidence of the carelessness with which poetry is read&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Quoted in [[Yvor Winters]], ''Forms of Discovery'' (1967) p. 166&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Stonehenge]] and other megaliths are featured in ''Milton'', suggesting they may relate to the oppressive power of priestcraft in general; as [[Peter Porter (poet)|Peter Porter]] observed, many scholars argue that the &quot;[mills] are churches and not the factories of the Industrial Revolution everyone else takes them for&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Peter Porter, ''The English Poets: from Chaucer to Edward Thomas'', Secker and Warburg, 1974, p.198., quoted in Shivashankar Mishra, ''The Rise of William Blake'', Mittal Publications, 1995, p.184.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!--[[File:Satanic mills.jpg|thumb|300px|The first reference to Satan's &quot;mills&quot;, next to images of megaliths]]--&gt;
An alternative theory is that Blake is referring to a mystical concept within his own mythology related to the ancient history of England. Satan's &quot;mills&quot; are referred to repeatedly in the main poem, and are first described in words which suggest neither industrialism nor ancient megaliths, but rather something more abstract: &quot;the starry Mills of Satan/ Are built beneath the earth and waters of the Mundane Shell...To Mortals thy Mills seem everything, and the Harrow of [[El Shaddai|Shaddai]] / A scheme of human conduct invisible and incomprehensible&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Blake, William, ''Milton: A Poem'', plate 4.&lt;/ref&gt;

===&quot;Chariot of fire&quot;===
The line from the poem &quot;Bring me my Chariot of fire!&quot; draws on the story of [[wikisource:Bible (King James)/2 Kings#2:11|2 Kings 2:11]], where the [[Old Testament]] prophet [[Elijah]] is taken directly to heaven: &quot;And it came to pass, as they still went on, and talked, that, behold, there appeared a chariot of fire, and horses of fire, and parted them both asunder; and Elijah went up by a whirlwind into heaven.&quot;  The phrase has become a byword for divine energy, and inspired the title of the 1981 film ''[[Chariots of Fire]]'', in which the hymn Jerusalem is sung during the final scenes.  The plural phrase &quot;chariots of fire&quot; refers to 2 Kings 6:17.

===&quot;Green and pleasant Land&quot;===
Blake lived in London for most of his life, but wrote much of ''Milton'' while living in the village of [[Felpham]] in Sussex. Amanda Gilroy argues that the poem is informed by Blake's &quot;evident pleasure&quot; in the Felpham countryside.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| first=Amanda | last=Gilroy | title=Green and Pleasant Land: English Culture and the Romantic Countryside | publisher=Peeters Publishers | year=2004 | page=66}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The phrase &quot;green and pleasant land&quot; has become a common term for an identifiably English landscape or society. It appears as a headline, title or sub-title in numerous articles and books. Sometimes it refers, whether with appreciation, nostalgia or critical analysis, to idyllic or enigmatic aspects of the English countryside.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.independent.co.uk/arts-entertainment/art/features/eric-ravilious-green-and-pleasant-land-2025022.html &quot;Eric Ravilious: Green and Pleasant Land,&quot; by Tom Lubbock, ''The Independent,'' 13 July 2010.]. Retrieved 7 January 2011&lt;/ref&gt; In other contexts it can suggest the perceived habits and aspirations of rural middle-class life.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.theguardian.com/uk/2007/mar/06/britishidentity.features11 &quot;This green and pleasant land,&quot; by Tim Adams, ''The Observer,'' 10 April 2005.]. Retrieved 7 January 2011&lt;/ref&gt; Sometimes it is used ironically,&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.theguardian.com/uk/2007/mar/06/britishidentity.features11 &quot;Green and pleasant land?&quot; by Jeremy Paxman, ''The Guardian,'' 6 March 2007.]. Retrieved 7 January 2011&lt;/ref&gt; e.g. in the [[Dire Straits]] song &quot;[[Iron Hand (song)|Iron Hand]]&quot;.

===Revolution===
Several of Blake's poems and paintings express a notion of universal humanity: &quot;As all men are alike (tho' infinitely various)&quot;. He retained an active interest in social and political events for all his life, but was often forced to resort to cloaking social idealism and political statements in Protestant mystical [[allegory]]. Even though the poem was written during the [[Napoleonic Wars]], Blake was an outspoken supporter of the [[French Revolution]], and [[Napoleon]] claimed to be continuing this revolution.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.spartacus.schoolnet.co.uk/PRblake.htm William Blake] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080705065137/http://www.spartacus.schoolnet.co.uk/PRblake.htm |date=5 July 2008 }} Spartacus Educational (schoolnet.co) – Accessed 7 August 2008&lt;/ref&gt; The poem expressed his desire for radical change without overt sedition. In 1803 Blake was charged at [[Chichester]] with high treason for having &quot;uttered seditious and treasonable expressions&quot;, but was acquitted.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.kirjasto.sci.fi/wblake.htm |title=William Blake |website=Books and Writers |first=Petri |last=Liukkonen |publisher=[[Kuusankoski]] Public Library |location=Finland |archiveurl=http://arquivo.pt/wayback/20120126033604/http%3A//www%2Ekirjasto%2Esci%2Efi/wblake%2Ehtm |archivedate= 26 January 2012 |url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; The poem is followed in the preface by a quotation from ''[[Book of Numbers|Numbers]]'' ch. 11, v. 29: &lt;!-- rendered literatim per [[WP:QUOTE]]; do not add apostrophe --&gt;&quot;Would to God that all the Lords people were prophets.&quot; [[Christopher Rowland (theologian)|Christopher Rowland]] has argued that this includes

&lt;blockquote&gt;everyone in the task of speaking out about what they saw. Prophecy for Blake, however, was not a prediction of the end of the world, but telling the truth as best a person can about what he or she sees, fortified by insight and an &quot;honest persuasion&quot; that with personal struggle, things could be improved. A human being observes, is indignant and speaks out: it's a basic political maxim which is necessary for any age. Blake wanted to stir people from their intellectual slumbers, and the daily grind of their toil, to see that they were captivated in the grip of a culture which kept them thinking in ways which served the interests of the powerful.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rowland&quot;&gt;Rowland, C. 2007 [http://www.opendemocracy.net/article/arts_culture/literature/william_blake_visionary William Blake: a visionary for our time] openDemocracy.net&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The words of the poem &quot;stress the importance of people taking responsibility for change and building a better society &lt;!-- rendered literatim per [[WP:QUOTE]]; do not add apostrophe --&gt;'in Englands green and pleasant land.'&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Rowland&quot;/&gt;

==Popularisation==
{{See also|William Blake in popular culture}}

The poem, which was little known during the century which followed its writing,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url = https://archive.org/details/jerusalemjerusal0000carr |url-access = registration |page = [https://archive.org/details/jerusalemjerusal0000carr/page/236 236]|title = Jerusalem, Jerusalem: How the Ancient City Ignited Our Modern World|first = James|last = Carroll|publisher = Houghton Mifflin Harcourt|year = 2011|isbn = 978-0-547-19561-2|authorlink = James Carroll (novelist)}}&lt;/ref&gt; was included in the patriotic anthology of verse ''The Spirit of Man,'' edited by the [[Poet Laureate of the United Kingdom]], [[Robert Bridges]], and published in 1916, at a time when morale had begun to decline because of the high number of casualties in World War I and the perception that there was no end in sight.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title = The Spirit of Man: An Anthology in English &amp; French from the Philosophers &amp; Poets|date = January 1916|url = https://archive.org/stream/spiritofmanantho00bridiala#page/n5/mode/2up|chapterurl = https://archive.org/stream/spiritofmanantho00bridiala#page/n335/mode/2up|page = 335|publisher = Longmans, Green &amp; Co.|accessdate =10 September 2012|editor-first = Robert|editor-last = Bridges|editor-link = Robert Bridges|chapter = Index|edition = First}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Under these circumstances, Bridges, finding the poem an appropriate hymn text to &quot;brace the spirit of the nation [to] accept with cheerfulness all the sacrifices necessary,&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url = https://archive.org/details/jerusalemjerusal0000carr |url-access = registration |page = [https://archive.org/details/jerusalemjerusal0000carr/page/235 235]|title = Jerusalem, Jerusalem: How the Ancient City Ignited Our Modern World|first = James|last = Carroll|publisher = Houghton Mifflin Harcourt|year = 2011|isbn = 978-0-547-19561-2|authorlink = James Carroll (novelist)}}&lt;/ref&gt; asked [[Hubert Parry|Sir Hubert Parry]] to put it to music for a [[Fight for Right Movement|Fight for Right campaign]] meeting in London's [[Queen's Hall]]. Bridges asked Parry to supply &quot;suitable, simple music to Blake's stanzas – music that an audience could take up and join in&quot;, and added that, if Parry could not do it himself, he might delegate the task to [[George Butterworth]].&lt;ref&gt;C. L.Graves, Hubert Parry, Macmillan 1926, p. 92&lt;/ref&gt;

The poem's idealistic [[Theme (literature)|theme]] or [[subtext]] accounts for its popularity across much of the political spectrum. It was used as a campaign slogan by the [[Labour Party (UK)|Labour Party]] in the [[1945 United Kingdom general election|1945 general election]]; [[Clement Attlee]] said they would build &quot;a new Jerusalem&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.pbs.org/wgbh/commandingheights/shared/minitextlo/tr_show01.html |title=Link to PBS script quoting Attlee in 1945 – Accessed 7 August 2008 |publisher=Pbs.org |date=24 October 1929 |accessdate=29 April 2011| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20110516015358/http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/commandingheights/shared/minitextlo/tr_show01.html| archivedate= 16 May 2011 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt; It has been sung at conferences of the [[Conservative Party (UK)|Conservative Party]], at the [[Glee Club (British politics)|Glee Club]] of the British [[Liberal Assembly]], the [[Labour Party (UK)|Labour Party]] and by the [[Liberal Democrats (UK)|Liberal Democrats]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://blogs.telegraph.co.uk/news/danhodges/100152734/what-does-it-really-mean-to-be-english-nothing-at-all-and-thats-how-it-should-be/ | work=The Daily Telegraph | title=What does it really mean to be English? Nothing at all – and that's how it should be | date=24 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Parry's setting of &quot;Jerusalem&quot;===
In adapting Blake's poem as a [[unison]] song, Parry deployed a two-[[stanza]] format, each taking up eight lines of Blake's original poem. He added a four-bar musical introduction to each verse and a [[coda (music)|coda]], echoing melodic [[motif (music)|motif]]s of the song.  The word &quot;those&quot; was substituted for &quot;these&quot; before &quot;dark satanic mills&quot;.

The piece was to be conducted by Parry's former student [[Walford Davies]], but Parry was initially reluctant to set the words, as he had doubts about the ultra-patriotism of Fight for Right, but not wanting to disappoint either Robert Bridges or Davies he agreed, writing it on 10 March 1916, and handing the manuscript to Davies with the comment, &quot;Here's a tune for you, old chap. Do what you like with it.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Benoliel, Bernard, Parry Before Jerusalem, Ashgate, Aldershot, 1997&lt;/ref&gt; Davies later recalled,

{{quote|We looked at [the manuscript] together in his room at the [[Royal College of Music]], and I recall vividly his unwonted happiness over it&amp;nbsp;... He ceased to speak, and put his finger on the note D in the second stanza where the words 'O clouds unfold' break his rhythm. I do not think any word passed about it, yet he made it perfectly clear that this was the one note and one moment of the song which he treasured&amp;nbsp;...&lt;ref name=&quot;dibble&quot;&gt;Dibble, Jeremy, C. Hubert H. Parry: His life and music, Oxford University Press, 1992&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Davies arranged for the vocal score to be published by [[Curwen Press|Curwen]] in time for the concert at the [[Queen's Hall]] on 28 March and began rehearsing it.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wilt&quot;&gt;Christopher Wiltshire (Former archivist, British Federation of Festivals for Music, Speech and Dance), [https://www.theguardian.com/letters/story/0,3604,408355,00.html Guardian newspaper 8 December 2000 Letters: Tune into Jerusalem's fighting history] ''[[The Guardian]]'' 8 December 2000.&lt;/ref&gt; It was a success and was taken up generally.

But Parry began to have misgivings again about Fight for Right and eventually wrote to Sir [[Francis Younghusband]] withdrawing his support entirely in May 1917. There was even concern that the composer might withdraw the song, but the situation was saved by [[Millicent Fawcett]] of the [[National Union of Women's Suffrage Societies]] (NUWSS). The song had been taken up by the Suffragists in 1917 and Fawcett asked Parry if it might be used at a Suffrage Demonstration Concert on 13 March 1918. Parry was delighted and orchestrated the piece for the concert (it had originally been for voices and organ). After the concert, Fawcett asked the composer if it might become the Women Voters' Hymn. Parry wrote back,

{{quote|I wish indeed it might become the Women Voters' hymn, as you suggest. People seem to enjoy singing it. And having the vote ought to diffuse a good deal of joy too. So they would combine happily.&lt;ref name=&quot;dibble&quot;/&gt;}}

Accordingly, he assigned the copyright to the NUWSS. When that organisation was wound up in 1928, Parry's executors reassigned the copyright to the [[Women's Institutes]], where it remained until it entered the public domain in 1968.&lt;ref name=&quot;dibble&quot;/&gt;

The song was first called &quot;And Did Those Feet in Ancient Time&quot; and the early published scores have this title. The change to &quot;Jerusalem&quot; seems to have been made about the time of the 1918 Suffrage Demonstration Concert, perhaps when the orchestral score was published (Parry's manuscript of the orchestral score has the old title crossed out and &quot;Jerusalem&quot; inserted in a different hand).&lt;ref&gt;The manuscripts of the song with organ and with orchestra, and of Elgar's orchestration, are in the library of the Royal College of Music, London&lt;/ref&gt; However, Parry always referred to it by its first title. He had originally intended the first verse to be sung by a solo female voice (this is marked in the score), but this is rare in contemporary performances. Sir [[Edward Elgar]] re-scored the work for very large orchestra in 1922 for use at the [[Leeds Festival (classical music)|Leeds Festival]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ICONS2&quot;&gt;ICONS – a portrait of England. Icon: Jerusalem (hymn) [http://www.icons.org.uk/theicons/collection/jerusalem/biography/sir-hubert-parry Sir Hubert Parry] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110809003129/http://www.icons.org.uk/theicons/collection/jerusalem/biography/sir-hubert-parry |date=9 August 2011 }}, &quot;Jerusalem&quot; and Elgar's orchestration.&lt;/ref&gt; Elgar's orchestration has overshadowed Parry's own, primarily because it is the version usually used now for the [[Last Night of the Proms]] (though Sir [[Malcolm Sargent]], who introduced it to that event in the 1950s, always used Parry's version).

===Use as a hymn===
Although Parry composed the music as a unison song, many churches have adopted &quot;Jerusalem&quot;; English cathedrals, churches and chapels frequently use it as an office or recessional hymn on [[Saint George's Day]].{{citation needed|date=August 2016}}

However, some clergy in the Church of England, according to the [[BBC TV]] programme ''Jerusalem: An Anthem for England'', have said that the song is not technically a [[hymn]] as it is not a prayer to God (which they claim hymns always are, though many counter-examples appear in any hymnal).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video |title=Jerusalem: An Anthem for England |date=8 July 2007 |publisher=[[BBC Four]] |url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b0074rmy}}&lt;/ref&gt; Consequently, it is not sung in some churches in England.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news
 |url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/uknews/1584578/Cathedral-bans-popular-hymn-Jerusalem.html 
 |title=Cathedral bans popular hymn Jerusalem 
 |date=10 April 2008 
 |work=The Daily Telegraph 
 |location=London 
 |accessdate=11 April 2008 
 |first=Sophie 
 |last=Borland 
 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080411001808/http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/main.jhtml?xml=%2Fnews%2F2008%2F04%2F10%2Fnjerusalem110.xml 
 |archivedate=11 April 2008 
 |url-status=live 
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; Despite this, it was sung as a hymn during the [[wedding of Prince William and Catherine Middleton]] in [[Westminster Abbey]].&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/uknews/royal-wedding/8479507/Royal-wedding-Prince-William-and-Kate-Middleton-choose-popular-hymns.html &quot;Royal Wedding: Prince William and Kate Middleton choose popular hymns&quot;], The Telegraph, 29 April 2011. Retrieved 29 April 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

Many schools use the song, especially [[Public school (UK)|public school]]s in Great Britain (it was used as the title music for the [[BBC]]'s 1979 series ''Public School'' at [[Radley College]]), and several private schools in Australia, New Zealand, New England and Canada. &quot;Jerusalem&quot; was chosen as the opening hymn for the [[London Olympics 2012]], although &quot;[[God Save the Queen]]&quot; was the anthem sung during the raising of the flag in salute to the Queen. Some attempts have also been made to increase its use elsewhere with other words; examples include the State Funeral of President Ronald Reagan in Washington National Cathedral on 11 June 2004 and the State Memorial Service for Australian Prime Minister [[Gough Whitlam]] on 5 November 2014.{{citation needed|date=January 2019}}

===Use as a national anthem===
{{See also|National anthem of England}}Upon hearing the orchestral version for the first time, [[George V of the United Kingdom|King George V]] said that he preferred &quot;Jerusalem&quot; over the British national anthem &quot;[[God Save the King]]&quot;. &quot;Jerusalem&quot; is considered to be England's most popular patriotic song; ''[[The New York Times]]'' said it was &quot;fast becoming an alternative national anthem,&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimes.com&quot;&gt;{{Cite news| url =https://www.nytimes.com/2009/07/20/theater/20time.html?ref=arts | work=The New York Times | title=Time, and the Green and Pleasant Land | first=Ben | last=Brantley | date=20 July 2009 | accessdate=23 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and there have even been calls to give it official status.&lt;ref&gt;[http://edmi.parliament.uk/EDMi/EDMDetails.aspx?EDMID=31408&amp;SESSION=875 Parliamentary Early Day Motion 2791] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090821141152/http://edmi.parliament.uk/EDMi/EDMDetails.aspx?EDMID=31408&amp;SESSION=875 |date=21 August 2009 }}, UK Parliament, 18 October 2006&lt;/ref&gt; England has no official anthem and uses the British national anthem &quot;[[God Save the Queen]]&quot;, also unofficial, for some national occasions, such as before English international football matches. However, some sports, including [[rugby league]], use &quot;Jerusalem&quot; as the English anthem. &quot;Jerusalem&quot; is the official hymn of the [[England and Wales Cricket Board]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://anthem4england.co.uk/category/correspondence/ |title= Correspondence |publisher=Anthem 4 England | location = UK |date= 8 May 2007 |accessdate=29 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; although &quot;God Save the Queen&quot; was the anthem sung before England's games in [[2010 ICC World Twenty20]], the [[2010–11 Ashes series]] and the [[2019 ICC Cricket World Cup]]. Questions in [[British Parliament|Parliament]] have not clarified the situation, as answers from the relevant minister say that since there is no official national anthem, each sport must make its own decision.

As Parliament has not clarified the situation, Team England, the English Commonwealth team, held a public poll in 2010 to decide which anthem should be played at medal ceremonies to celebrate an English win at the Commonwealth Games. &quot;Jerusalem&quot; was selected by 52% of voters over &quot;[[Land of Hope and Glory]]&quot; (used since 1930) and &quot;God Save the Queen&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Sir Andrew Foster |url=http://www.weareengland.org/news.asp?itemid=327&amp;itemTitle=England+announce+victory+anthem+for+Delhi+chosen+by+the+public%21&amp;section=115&amp;sectionTitle=News |title=England announce victory anthem for Delhi chosen by the public! – Commonwealth Games England |publisher=Weare England |date=30 May 2010 |accessdate=29 April 2011 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110611162431/http://www.weareengland.org/news.asp?itemid=327&amp;itemTitle=England+announce+victory+anthem+for+Delhi+chosen+by+the+public%21&amp;section=115&amp;sectionTitle=News |archivedate=11 June 2011 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2005 [[BBC Four]] produced ''Jerusalem: An Anthem For England'' highlighting the usages of the song/poem and a case was made for its adoption as the [[national anthem of England]]. Varied contributions come from [[Howard Goodall]], [[Billy Bragg]], [[Garry Bushell]], [[Lord Hattersley]], [[Ann Widdecombe]] and [[David Mellor]], [[Militarism|war proponents]], [[pacifism|war opponents]], [[suffragettes]], [[trade unionists]], [[Independent school (United Kingdom)|public schoolboys]], the [[Conservative Party (UK)|Conservatives]], the [[The Labour Party (UK)|Labour Party]], [[Football Supporters' Federation|football supporters]], the [[British National Party]], the [[Women's Institute#.22Jerusalem.22|Women's Institute]], [[London Gay Men's Chorus|a gay choir]], [[London Community Gospel Choir|a gospel choir]], [[Fat Les]] and [[Naturists#United Kingdom|naturists]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=https://www.imdb.com/title/tt1071222/ | title=Jerusalem: An Anthem for England (TV 2005) | website=[[Internet Movie Database]] | accessdate=27 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=https://www.theguardian.com/media/2005/sep/09/broadcasting.tvandradio | title=Get me to the clink on time |work=The Guardian |location=UK | date=9 September 2005 | accessdate=28 September 2011 | author=Sam Wollaston}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Emerson, Lake and Palmer version==
{{Infobox song
| name       = Jerusalem
| cover      =
| alt        =
| type       = single
| artist     = [[Emerson, Lake &amp; Palmer]]
| album      = [[Brain Salad Surgery]]
| B-side     = When the Apple Blossoms Bloom in the Windmills of Your Mind I'll Be Your Valentine
| released   = 1973
| format     = [[Single (music)#7-inch format|45 rpm]]
| recorded   =
| studio     =
| venue      =
| genre      = [[Progressive rock]]
| length     = 2:45
| label      = [[Manticore Records|Manticore]]
| writer     = William Blake, Hubert Parry
| producer   = [[Greg Lake]]
| prev_title = [[Rodeo (ballet)#In popular culture|Hoedown]]
| prev_year  = 1972
| next_title = [[Fanfare for the Common Man (Emerson, Lake &amp; Palmer song)|Fanfare for the Common Man]]
| next_year  = 1977
}}
In 1973, for their ''[[Brain Salad Surgery]]'' album, British progressive rock band [[Emerson, Lake &amp; Palmer]] recorded a version of the song titled &quot;Jerusalem&quot;. The track features the debut of the prototype [[Moog Apollo]], the first-ever [[polyphonic synthesizer|polyphonic music synthesizer]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Lake&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://ladiesofthelake.com/cabinet/bssliner.html|title=Liner Notes from the DVD-A of Brain Salad Surgery|publisher=Ladies of the Lake – A Greg Lake Tribute Site|accessdate=2 September 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; The subject matter of this song indicates a nod to ELP's unabashed Englishness and simultaneously lent an air of timeless tradition and ceremony to the music. Though a single was released of the song, it failed to chart, and it was banned from radio play in England. The BBC would not accept it as a serious piece of music, the band claims.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lake&quot;/&gt; Drummer [[Carl Palmer]] later expressed disappointment over this decision.
{{quote|We wanted to put it out as a single&amp;nbsp;... We figured it was worthy of a single. In England, they have this format where four or five people have to [approve it] before it gets played on the airwaves; it's a very old-fashioned way of doing it, but that's the way it was being done at the time. I think there was some apprehension [as] to whether or not we should be playing a hymn and bastardizing it, as they said, or whatever was being called at the time&amp;nbsp;... We thought we'd done it spot-on, and I thought that was very sad because I've got a jukebox at home, and that's a piece of music that I've got on the jukebox, so I actually thought the recording and just the general performances from all of us were absolutely wonderful. I couldn't believe the small-mindedness of the English&amp;nbsp;... committee to vote these things onto the radio or off the radio. They&amp;nbsp;... obviously didn't even listen to this. It got banned and there was sort of quite a big thing about it, these people just would not play it. They said no, it was a hymn, and we had taken it the wrong way.{{citation needed|date=April 2013}}}}

A live rendition was recorded during their subsequent ''Someone Get Me a Ladder'' tour, and was included on ''[[Welcome Back, My Friends, to the Show That Never Ends ~ Ladies and Gentlemen|Welcome Back, My Friends, to the Show That Never Ends ~ Ladies and Gentlemen... Emerson, Lake &amp; Palmer!]]''

==Performances==
&lt;!--PLEASE DO NOT TRY TO LIST PERFORMANCES OF JERUSALEM ON RECORD, FILM, TV OR THEATRE. LINKS TO MONTY PYTHON, BILLY BRAGG AND EMERSON, LAKE &amp; PALMER HAVE ALREADY BEEN PROVIDED--&gt;
The popularity of Parry's setting has resulted in many hundreds of recordings being made, too numerous to list, of both traditional choral performances and new interpretations by popular music artists. Consequently, only its most notable performances are listed below.

*'''Annually'''—It is sung every year by an audience of thousands at the end of the [[Last Night of the Proms]] in the [[Royal Albert Hall]] and simultaneously in the ''Proms in the Park'' venues throughout the country.&lt;ref&gt;{{YouTube|041nXAAn714}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''Annually'''—Along with &quot;[[The Red Flag]]&quot;, it is sung each year at the closing of the annual [[Labour Party (UK)|Labour Party]] conference.
*'''Annually'''—It is traditionally sung before [[rugby league]]'s [[Challenge Cup]] Final, along with &quot;[[Abide with Me]]&quot;, and before the [[Super League Grand Final]], where it is introduced as &quot;the rugby league anthem&quot;. Before 2008, it was the anthem used by the [[England national rugby league team|national side]], as &quot;[[God Save the Queen]]&quot; was used by [[Great Britain national rugby league team|the Great Britain team]]: since the Lions were superseded by England, &quot;God Save the Queen&quot; has replaced &quot;Jerusalem&quot;.
*'''1920s'''—The song was used by the [[National Union of Women's Suffrage Societies]] (indeed it was their property until 1928, when they were wound up after women won the right to vote – see above in relation to Millicent Garret Fawcett).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.songfacts.com/detail.php?id=8553 |title=Link to SongFacts – Accessed 7 August 2008 |publisher=Songfacts.com |accessdate=29 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the 1920s, many [[Women's Institutes]] (WI) started closing meetings by singing it, and this caught on nationally. Although it has never actually been adopted as the WI's official anthem, in practice it holds that position, and is an enduring element of the public image of the WI.&lt;ref&gt;The &quot;Jam and ''Jerusalem''&quot; caricature of the WI is still current enough that they have a [[FAQ]] about it on their site at [http://www.thewi.org.uk/standard.aspx?id=12466] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090111082408/http://www.thewi.org.uk/standard.aspx?id=12466 |date=11 January 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''1986'''—[[The Waterboys]] have incorporated verses into live performances of &quot;Savage Earth Heart&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{YouTube|id=GG7Do74zUWI#t=7m21s|title=The Waterboys using verses from Jerusalem}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''1991'''—The extended version of dance group [[The KLF]]'s hit single &quot;[[It's Grim Up North]]&quot; incorporates Parry's setting of the poem.
*'''2004—present'''—Since 2004, it has been the anthem of the [[England cricket team|England]] [[cricket]] team, being played before each day of their home test matches.
*'''2009'''—At a concert at the Royal Albert Hall on 4 July 2009, Jeff Beck performed a version featuring his touring band at the time ([[Vinnie Colaiuta]], [[Tal Wilkenfeld]] and [[Jason Rebello]]) and a guest appearance by David Gilmour.
*'''2010'''—A recording by the [[Grimethorpe Colliery Band]] was played in medal ceremonies when an [[England at the 2010 Commonwealth Games|English competitor at the 2010 Commonwealth Games]] was awarded gold.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation |url=http://www.weareengland.org/page.asp?section=210&amp;sectionTitle=Nation+has+chosen+anthem+for+England%27s+medallists |title=Nation has chosen anthem for England's medallists: And did those feet in Ancient times walk upon England’s mountains green..... |publisher=[[Commonwealth Games England]] |quote=Now we can reveal that the anthem has been recorded for us by The Grimethorpe Colliery Band...The new official anthem of the England Team will be played for English athletes on the podium in Delhi when a Gold medal is won. |date=May–June 2010 |accessdate=13 October 2010 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20101009122005/http://www.weareengland.org/page.asp?section=210&amp;sectionTitle=Nation+has+chosen+anthem+for+England%27s+medallists |archivedate=9 October 2010 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation| url=https://www.independent.co.uk/sport/general/athletics/the-paralympian-taking-on-ablebodied-athletes-2095333.html|title=The Paralympian taking on able-bodied athletes|work=The Independent |location=London |date=2 October 2010|accessdate=13 October 2010 | first=Simon | last=Turnbull| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20101005014340/http://www.independent.co.uk/sport/general/athletics/the-paralympian-taking-on-ablebodied-athletes-2095333.html| archivedate= 5 October 2010 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''2011'''—It was one of three hymns sung at the [[wedding of Prince William, Duke of Cambridge, and Catherine Middleton]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |url=http://www.officialroyalwedding2011.org/blog/2011/April/28/Music-for-the-Wedding-Service 
 |title=Music for the Wedding Service 
 |publisher=Official Royal Wedding 2011 (Blog) 
 |date=28 April 2011 
 |accessdate=28 April 2011 
 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110429040309/http://www.officialroyalwedding2011.org/blog/2011/April/28/Music-for-the-Wedding-Service 
 |archivedate=29 April 2011 
 |url-status=dead 
 |df=dmy 
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''2011'''—While performing at Glastonbury in June 2011, U2's Bono incorporated one of the verses into their songs &quot;Where The Streets Have No Name&quot; and &quot;Bad&quot;. Whilst being interviewed after the gig, he said it was a tribute to Glastonbury's historical significance.
*'''2012'''—It was used in the [[2012 Summer Olympics opening ceremony|opening ceremony]] of the [[2012 Summer Olympics]] held in London and inspired several of the opening show segments directed by [[Danny Boyle]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Navigating the 'Isles of Wonder': A guide to the Olympic opening ceremony|url=http://www.cnn.com/2012/07/27/sport/decoding-olympic-opening-ceremony/index.html|publisher=CNN|accessdate=28 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was included in the ceremony's soundtrack album, ''[[Isles of Wonder: Music for the Opening Ceremony of the London 2012 Olympic Games|Isles of Wonder]]''.
*'''2016'''—An a cappella version by [[Jacob Collier]] was selected for [[Beats Electronics|Beats by Dre]] &quot;The Game Starts Here&quot;  for the [[England at the Rugby World Cup|England Rugby World Cup]] campaign.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.campaignlive.co.uk/article/england-rugby-captain-stars-beats-dre-campaign/1364614|title=England rugby captain stars in Beats By Dre campaign|access-date=28 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=p-gOvn67d_8|title=Jerusalem – Jacob Collier (Soundtrack for Beats by Dre: &quot;The Game Starts Here&quot;)|access-date=28 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Use in film, television and theatre==
&lt;!--PLEASE DO NOT TRY TO LIST PERFORMANCES OF JERUSALEM ON RECORD, FILM, TV OR THEATRE. LINKS TO MONTY PYTHON, BILLY BRAGG AND EMERSON, LAKE &amp; PALMER HAVE ALREADY BEEN PROVIDED--&gt;
&quot;Bring me my Chariot of fire&quot; inspired the title of the film ''[[Chariots of Fire]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;welland&quot;&gt;[https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0082158/trivia IMDb trivia – Origin of title] – Accessed 11 August 2008&lt;/ref&gt; A church congregation sings &quot;Jerusalem&quot; at the close of the film and a performance appears on the ''[[Chariots of Fire (album)|Chariots of Fire soundtrack]]'' performed by the [[Ambrosian Singers]] overlaid partly by a composition by [[Vangelis]]. One unexpected touch is that &quot;Jerusalem&quot; is sung in four-part harmony, as if it were truly a hymn. This is not authentic: Parry's composition was a unison song (that is, all voices sing the tune – perhaps one of the things that make it so &quot;singable&quot; by massed crowds) and he never provided any harmonisation other than the accompaniment for organ (or orchestra). Neither does it appear in any standard hymn book in a guise other than Parry's own, so it may have been harmonised specially for the film. The film's working title was &quot;Running&quot; until [[Colin Welland]] saw a television programme, ''[[Songs of Praise]]'', featuring the hymn and decided to change the title.&lt;ref name=&quot;welland&quot; /&gt;

The hymn has featured in many other films and television programmes including ''[[Four Weddings and a Funeral]]'', ''[[How to Get Ahead in Advertising]]'', ''[[The Loneliness of the Long Distance Runner (film)|The Loneliness of the Long Distance Runner]]'', ''[[Calendar Girls]]'', Season 3: Episode 22 of ''[[Star Trek: Deep Space Nine]]'', ''[[Goodnight Mister Tom (1998 film)|Goodnight Mr. Tom]]'', ''[[Women in Love]]'', ''[[The Man Who Fell to Earth]]'', ''[[Shameless (UK TV series)|Shameless]]'', ''[[Quatermass and the Pit]]'', and ''[[Monty Python's Flying Circus]] ''. An extract was heard in the 2013 ''[[Doctor Who]]'' episode &quot;[[The Crimson Horror]]&quot; although that story was set in 1893, i.e., before Parry's arrangement. A punk version is heard in [[Derek Jarman]]'s 1977 film ''[[Jubilee (1978 film)|Jubilee]]''. In an episode of ''[[Peep Show (TV series)|Peep Show]]'', Jez ([[Robert Webb]]) records a track titled &quot;This Is Outrageous&quot; which uses the first and a version of the second line in a verse.&lt;ref&gt;{{YouTube|ySqtuxadnn4}}&lt;/ref&gt; A modified version of the hymn, replacing the word &quot;England&quot; with &quot;Neo&quot;, is used in ''[[Neo Yokio]]'' as the national anthem of the eponymous city state.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.animenewsnetwork.com/review/neo-yokio/.121543|title=Neo Yokio Review|first=Mike|last=Toole|work=[[Anime News Network]]|date=September 19, 2017|accessdate=September 26, 2017|quote=Neo Yokio's national anthem is William Blake's 'Jerusalem,' and fight scenes are underpinned by tunes by the likes of Mingus.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the theatre it appears in ''[[Jerusalem (play)|Jerusalem]]'',&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimes.com&quot; /&gt; ''[[Calendar Girls]]'' and in ''[[Time and the Conways]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimes.com&quot; /&gt; Eddie Izzard discusses the hymn in his 2000 ''[[Circle (Eddie Izzard)|Circle]]'' stand-up tour. Punk band [[Bad Religion]] have borrowed the opening line of Blake's poem in their &quot;God Song&quot;, from the 1990 album ''[[Against the Grain (Bad Religion album)|Against the Grain]]''.

==Other composers==
&lt;!--PLEASE DO NOT TRY TO LIST PERFORMANCES OF JERUSALEM ON RECORD, FILM, TV OR THEATRE. LINKS TO MONTY PYTHON, BILLY BRAGG AND EMERSON, LAKE &amp; PALMER HAVE ALREADY BEEN PROVIDED--&gt;
Blake's lyrics have also been set to music by other composers without reference to Parry's melody. [[Tim Blake]] (synthesiser player of [[Gong (band)|Gong]]) produced a solo album in 1978 called ''[[Blake's New Jerusalem]]'', including a 20-minute track with lyrics from Blake's poem. [[Mark E. Smith]] of [[The Fall (band)|The Fall]] interpolated the verses with a deadpan rant against his native land in the track &quot;Dog is life/Jerusalem&quot; from the 1988 ballet score &quot;[[I Am Kurious Oranj]]&quot;. The words, with some variations, are used in the track &quot;Jerusalem&quot; on [[Bruce Dickinson]]'s album ''[[The Chemical Wedding (Bruce Dickinson album)|The Chemical Wedding]]'', which also includes lines from book two of ''Milton''. [[Finn Coren]] also created a different musical setting for the poem on his album ''[[The Blake Project: Spring]]''. [[The Verve]] also referenced the song in their 2008 song ''[[Love Is Noise]]'' from the album [[Forth (album)|Forth.]] Lead singer and writer [[Richard Ashcroft]] said that Blake had influenced the lyric ''&lt;nowiki/&gt;'Will those feet in modern times''' from the song.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9rXLSWrFVqg The Verve – Love is Noise (Interview) – &quot;L''ook at it in the first few lines, as a kind of remake of Jerusalem by William Blake, rather than those feet in ancient times, its those feet in modern times.&quot;''&lt;/ref&gt; This is not the first Verve song influenced by Blake, as their previous single ''[[History (The Verve song)|History]]'' also featured the lyrics &quot;I wandered lonely streets/Behind where the old Thames does flow/And in every face I meet&quot;, referencing Blake's &quot;[[London (William Blake poem)|London]]&quot;
It is often thought that in the song “feel good inc” by Gorrilaz, the lyrics “windmill windmill for the land love forever hand in hand” is about the satanic mills in Blake’s poem.

==See also==
* [[Civil religion]]
* [[Industrial Revolution#Opposition from Romanticism|Romanticism and the Industrial Revolution]]

==Notes==
{{Notelist|30em}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
{{Wikisource|Milton (Blake)/Preface}}
*[http://www.blakearchive.org/exist/blake/archive/comparison.xq?selection=compare&amp;copies=all&amp;bentleynum=B2&amp;copyid=milton.a&amp;java= Comparisons of the Hand Painted copies of the Preface] on the [[William Blake Archive]]
* {{Cantorion|music/651/Jerusalem_Sheet_music|Jerusalem}}
* [http://www.hymnary.org/text/and_did_those_feet_in_ancient_time And did those feet in ancient time] at [[Hymnary.org]]

{{William Blake|lit}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:And Did Those Feet In Ancient Time}}
[[Category:1804 poems]]
[[Category:1916 songs]]
[[Category:English Christian hymns]]
[[Category:English patriotic songs]]
[[Category:National symbols of England]]
[[Category:Poetry by William Blake]]
[[Category:Adaptations of works by William Blake]]
[[Category:British Israelism]]
[[Category:Culture of Jerusalem]]
[[Category:Musical settings of poems by William Blake]]
[[Category: British anthems]]</text>
      <sha1>mtbg2xgto9yyhtqrocvoecsc89otdl7</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
