  <page>
    <title>Albinism in humans</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2909</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941400536</id>
      <parentid>941400506</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-18T10:32:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Eyeamgreat</username>
        <id>13648815</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Diagnosis */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox medical condition (new)
| name            = Albinism
| image           = Albinisitic man portrait.jpg
| caption         = A boy with albinism
| field           = [[Dermatology]]
| synonyms        = Achromia, achromasia, achromatosis
| pronounce       = albino ({{IPAc-en|uk|æ|l|ˈ|b|iː|n|oʊ}},&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/albino |title=albino |work=Random House Dictionary |date=2017 |via=Dictionary.Reference.com |access-date=10 November 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; or {{IPAc-en|us|æ|l|ˈ|b|aɪ|n|oʊ}})&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= https://www.macmillandictionary.com/pronunciation/american/albino |title=American Pronunciation of ''albino'' |work=Macmillan Dictionary |date=2017 |access-date=10 November 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| symptoms        = 
| complications   = 
| onset           = 
| duration        = 
| types           = 
| causes          = 
| risks           = 
| diagnosis       = 
| differential    = 
| prevention      = 
| treatment       = 
| medication      = 
| prognosis       = 
| frequency       = 
| 
}}
&lt;!-- Definition and symptoms --&gt;
'''Albinism''' is a [[congenital disorder]] characterized in humans by the complete or partial absence of [[Biological pigment|pigment]] in the skin, hair and eyes. Albinism is associated with a number of vision defects, such as [[photophobia]], [[nystagmus]], and [[amblyopia]]. Lack of skin pigmentation makes for more susceptibility to sunburn and skin cancers. In rare cases such as [[Chédiak–Higashi syndrome]], albinism may be associated with deficiencies in the transportation of melanin granules. This also affects essential granules present in immune cells leading to increased susceptibility to infection.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Kaplan |first1=J. |last2=De Domenico |first2=I. |last3=Ward |first3=D. M. |doi=10.1097/MOH.0b013e3282f2bcce |title=Chediak-Higashi syndrome |journal=Current Opinion in Hematology |volume=15 |issue=1 |pages=22–29 |date=2008 |pmid=18043242}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- Cause --&gt;
Albinism results from inheritance of [[Dominance (genetics)|recessive gene]] [[allele]]s and is known to affect all [[vertebrate]]s, including [[human]]s. It is due to absence or defect of [[tyrosinase]], a copper-containing enzyme involved in the production of [[melanin]]. It is the opposite of [[melanism]].  Unlike humans, other animals have multiple [[Biological pigments|pigments]] and for these, [[Albinism in biology|albinism]] is considered to be a hereditary condition characterised by the absence of melanin in particular, in the eyes, skin, hair, scales, feathers or cuticle.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |url= http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/12993/albinism |title=Albinism |encyclopedia=Encyclopædia Britannica |access-date=January 27, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; While an organism with complete absence of melanin is called an albino, an organism with only a diminished amount of melanin is described as [[Leucism|leucistic]] or albinoid.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tietz&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last=Tietz |first=W. |title=A Syndrome of Deaf-Mutism Associated with Albinism Showing Dominant Autosomal Inheritance |journal=American Journal of Human Genetics |volume=15 |pages=259–264 |pmid=13985019 |pmc=1932384 |date=1963}}&lt;/ref&gt; The term is from the [[Latin]] ''albus'', &quot;white&quot;.

==Signs and symptoms==
[[File:Albinistic girl papua new guinea.jpg|thumb|left|Girl with albinism from [[Papua New Guinea]]]]There are two principal types of albinism: [[Oculocutaneous albinism|oculocutaneous]], affecting the eyes, skin and hair, and [[Ocular albinism|ocular]] affecting the eyes only.

There are different types of oculocutaneous albinism depending on which gene has undergone mutation. With some there is no pigment at all. The other end of the spectrum of albinism is &quot;a form of albinism called rufous oculocutaneous albinism, which usually affects dark-skinned people&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://ghr.nlm.nih.gov/condition/oculocutaneous-albinism |title=oculocutaneous albinism |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |website=Genetics Home Reference |publisher=[[U.S. National Library of Medicine]], [[National Institutes of Health]] |location=Bethesda, Maryland |date=October 2015 |access-date=10 November 2017}}{{tertiary source|date=November 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the [[National Organization for Albinism and Hypopigmentation]], &quot;With ocular albinism, the color of the iris of the eye may vary from blue to green or even brown, and sometimes darkens with age. However, when an optician examines the eye by shining a light from the side of the eye, the light shines back through the iris since very little pigment is present.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Information Bulletin - Ocular Albinism |url=http://www.albinism.org/site/c.flKYIdOUIhJ4H/b.9260357/k.A94A/Information_Bulletin__Ocular_Albinism.htm |publisher=National Organization for Albinism and Hypopigmentation |access-date=11 March 2017 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170312070207/http://www.albinism.org/site/c.flKYIdOUIhJ4H/b.9260357/k.A94A/Information_Bulletin__Ocular_Albinism.htm |archive-date=12 March 2017 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Because individuals with albinism have skin that entirely lacks the dark pigment melanin, which helps protect the skin from the sun's [[ultraviolet]] [[radiation]], their skin can [[sunburn|burn]] more easily from overexposure.&lt;ref name=&quot;Atlas of Genetic Diagnosis&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Chen |first=Harold |title=Atlas of genetic diagnosis and counseling |publisher=Humana Press |location=Totowa, New Jersey |date=2006 |pages=37–40 |isbn=978-1-58829-681-8 |url= https://books.google.com/?id=2VcdAXJ_dZkC&amp;pg=PA36&amp;dq=Albinism&amp;q=Albinism |access-date=22 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The human eye normally produces enough pigment to color the [[Iris (anatomy)|iris]] blue, green or brown and lend opacity to the eye. In photographs, those with albinism are more likely to demonstrate &quot;red eye&quot;, due to the red of the [[retina]] being visible through the iris. Lack of pigment in the eyes also results in problems with vision, both related and unrelated to [[photosensitivity]].

Those with albinism are generally as healthy as the rest of the population (but see related disorders below), with growth and development occurring as normal, and albinism by itself does not cause mortality,&lt;ref name=&quot;eMedicine1&quot; /&gt; although the lack of pigment blocking [[ultraviolet]] [[radiation]] increases the risk of melanomas (skin cancers) and other problems.

===Visual problems===
[[Image:Mali Salif Keita2 400.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Mali]]an [[Mandinka people|Mandinka]] singer [[Salif Keita]] with albinism]]
Development of the optical system is highly dependent on the presence of melanin. For this reason, the reduction or absence of this pigment in people with albinism may lead to:
* Misrouting of the retinogeniculate projections, resulting in abnormal [[decussation]] (crossing) of optic nerve fibres&lt;ref name=&quot;Atlas of Genetic Diagnosis&quot; /&gt;
* [[Photophobia]] and decreased [[visual acuity]] due to light scattering within the eye ([[ocular straylight]])&lt;ref name=&quot;Atlas of Genetic Diagnosis&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=Ocular Straylight in Albinism |journal=Optometry and Vision Science |volume=88 |issue=5 |pages=E585–92 |date=2011 |last1=Kruijt |first1=Bastiaan |last2=Franssen |first2=Luuk |last3=Prick |first3=Liesbeth J. J. M. |last4=Van Vliet |first4=Johannes M. J. |last5=Van Den Berg |first5=Thomas J. T. P. |doi=10.1097/OPX.0b013e318212071e |pmid=21358444}}&lt;/ref&gt; Photophobia is specifically when light enters the eye, unrestricted—with full force. It is painful and causes extreme sensitivity to light.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url= http://www.lensshopper.com/eye-disorders/how-albinism-affects-vision.asp |title=How Albinism Affects Vision |website=LensShopper.com |language=sv |access-date=2017-02-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Unreliable source?|certain=y|date=November 2017|reason=Random e-shopping sites are not reliable sources for medical information. See WP:MEDRS.}}
* Reduced visual acuity due to [[Macular hypoplasia|foveal hypoplasia]] and possibly light-induced [[retina]]l damage.&lt;ref name=&quot;Atlas of Genetic Diagnosis&quot; /&gt;

Eye conditions common in albinism include:
* [[Nystagmus]], irregular rapid movement of the eyes back and forth, or in circular motion.&lt;ref name=&quot;Atlas of Genetic Diagnosis&quot; /&gt;
* [[Amblyopia]], decrease in acuity of one or both eyes due to poor transmission to the brain, often due to other conditions such as [[strabismus]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Atlas of Genetic Diagnosis&quot; /&gt;
* [[Optic nerve hypoplasia]], underdevelopment of the optic nerve.

The improper development of the [[retinal pigment epithelium]] (RPE), which in normal eyes absorbs most of the reflected sunlight, further increases glare due to light scattering within the eye.&lt;ref name=&quot;Optometry Albinism&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Albinism |pages=63A–65A |url=https://www.reviewofoptometry.com/CMSDocuments/2009/9/ro0409_handbook.pdf |url-status = live|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150824100916/https://www.reviewofoptometry.com/CMSDocuments/2009/9/ro0409_handbook.pdf |archive-date=24 August 2015 |work=The Handbook of Ocular Disease Management: Supplement to Review of Optometry |first1=Joseph W. |last1=Sowka |first2=Andrew S. |last2=Gurwood |first3=Allan G. |last3=Kabat |publisher=Jobson Medical Information |location=New York |edition=11th |date=15 April 2009 |via=ReviewOfOptometry.com |access-date=10 November 2017 |df= }}&lt;!--Note: Albinism has been removed, for some reason, from at least the 12th (2010) through 18th (2016) editions.--&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; The resulting sensitivity (photophobia) generally leads to discomfort in bright light, but this can be reduced by the use of sunglasses or brimmed hats.&lt;ref name=&quot;Facts Albinism&quot; /&gt;

==Genetics==
[[Oculocutaneous albinism]] is generally the result of the [[biological inheritance]] of [[dominance relationship|genetically recessive]] [[allele]]s ([[gene]]s) passed from both parents of an individual such as [[OCA1]] and [[OCA2]].  A mutation in the human TRP-1 gene may result in the deregulation of melanocyte tyrosinase enzymes, a change that is hypothesized to promote brown versus black melanin synthesis, resulting in a third oculocutaneous albinism (OCA) genotype, ″OCA3″.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=Mutation in and lack of expression of tyrosinase-related protein-1 (TRP-1) in melanocytes from an individual with brown oculocutaneous albinism: A new subtype of albinism classified as &quot;OCA3&quot; |last1=Boissy |first1=R. E. |last2=Zhao |first2=H. |last3=Oetting |first3=W. S. |last4=Austin |first4=L. M. |last5=Wildenberg |first5=S. C. |last6=Boissy |first6=Y. L. |last7=Zhao |first7=Y. |last8=Sturm |first8=R. A. |last9=Hearing |first9=V. J. |last10=King |first10=R. A. |last11=Nordlund |first11=J. J. |journal=American Journal of Human Genetics |volume=58 |issue=6 |date=1996 |pages=1145–1156 |pmid=8651291 |pmc=1915069}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some rare forms are inherited from only one parent. There are other [[genetic mutation]]s which are proven to be associated with albinism. All alterations, however, lead to changes in melanin production in the body.&lt;ref name=&quot;eMedicine1&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last=Boissy |first=Raymond E. |title=Dermatologic Manifestations of Albinism |date=21 July 2016 |url= https://emedicine.medscape.com/article/1068184-overview |work=[[Medscape]] |editor-first=William D. |editor1-last=James |display-editors=etal |publisher=[[eMedicine]] / [[WebMD]] |access-date=10 November 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;OMIM1&quot;&gt;[https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?CMD=search&amp;DB=omim&amp;term=albinism Online ''Mendelian Inheritance in Man''], at [[Johns Hopkins University]] {{crossref|(see also [[Mendelian Inheritance in Man]] for more information about this source)}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  Some of these are associated with increased risk of skin cancer {{crossref|([[List of cutaneous conditions associated with increased risk of nonmelanoma skin cancer|see list of such genetic variations]])}}.

The chance of offspring with albinism resulting from the pairing of an organism with albinism and one without albinism is low. However, because organisms (including humans) can be carriers of genes for albinism without exhibiting any traits, albinistic offspring can be produced by two non-albinistic parents. Albinism usually occurs with equal frequency in both sexes.&lt;ref name=&quot;eMedicine1&quot; /&gt; An exception to this is [[ocular albinism]], which it is passed on to offspring through X-linked inheritance. Thus, ocular albinism occurs more frequently in males as they have a single X and Y [[chromosome]], unlike females, whose genetics are characterized by two X&amp;nbsp;chromosomes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Haldeman-Englert |first=Chad |url= https://medlineplus.gov/ency/article/002051.htm |title=Sex-linked recessive |work=The ADAM Medical Encyclopedia |date=6 November 2017 | publisher=U.S. National Library of Medicine, National Institutes of Health / Ebix Inc. |location=Bethesda, Maryland / Atlanta, Georgia, US |access-date=10 November 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are two different forms of albinism: a partial lack of the melanin is known as hypomelanism, or hypomelanosis, and the total absence of melanin is known as [[amelanism]] or amelanosis.

===Enzyme===
The enzyme defect responsible for OCA1-type albinism is tyrosine 3-monooxygenase (tyrosinase), which synthesizes melanin from the amino acid [[tyrosine]].

===Evolutionary theories===
It is suggested that the early [[hominin]] evolved in East Africa around 3 million years ago.&lt;ref name=&quot;royalsocietypublishing.org&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last=Greaves |first=M. |date=2014 |title=Was skin cancer a selective force for black pigmentation in early hominin evolution? |journal=Proceedings of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences |volume=281 |issue=1781 |pages=20132955 |doi=10.1098/rspb.2013.2955 |pmid=24573849 |pmc=3953838}}&lt;/ref&gt; The dramatic [[phenotype|phenotypic]] change from [[primate]] to early hominin is hypothesized to have involved the extreme loss of body hair – except for areas most exposed to UV radiation, such as the head – to allow for more efficient [[thermoregulation]] in the early hunter-gatherers. The skin that would have been exposed upon general body hair loss in these early hominins would have most likely been non-pigmented, reflecting the pale skin underlying the hair of our chimpanzee relatives. A positive advantage would have been conferred to early hominids inhabiting the African continent that were capable of producing darker skin – those who first expressed the [[eumelanin]]-producing [[MC1R]] [[allele]] – which protected them from harmful epithelium-damaging ultraviolet rays. Over time, the advantage conferred to those with darker skin may have led to the prevalence of darker skin on the continent. The positive advantage, however, would have had to be strong enough so as to produce a significantly higher reproductive fitness in those who produced more melanin. The cause of a selective pressure strong enough to cause this shift is an area of much debate. Some hypotheses include the existence of significantly lower reproductive fitness in people with less melanin due to lethal skin cancer, lethal kidney disease due to excess [[vitamin D]] formation in the skin of people with less melanin, or simply natural selection due to mate preference and sexual selection.&lt;ref name=&quot;royalsocietypublishing.org&quot; /&gt;

When comparing the prevalence of albinism in Africa to its prevalence in other parts of the world, such as Europe and the United States, the potential evolutionary effects of skin cancer as a selective force due to its effect on these populations may not be insignificant.&lt;ref name=&quot;royalsocietypublishing.org&quot; /&gt; It would follow, then, that there would be stronger selective forces acting on albino populations in Africa than on albino populations in Europe and the US.&lt;ref name=&quot;biomedcentral.com&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Hong |first1=E. S. |last2=Zeeb |first2=H. |last3=Repacholi |first3=M. H. |title=Albinism in Africa as a public health issue |journal=BMC Public Health |volume=6 |pages=212 |doi=10.1186/1471-2458-6-212 |pmid=16916463 |pmc=1584235 |date=2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; In two separate studies in Nigeria, people with albinism were found to be of reproductively significant age more often than not. One study found that 89% of people diagnosed with albinism are between 0 and 30 years of age, while the other found that 77% of albinos were under the age of 20.&lt;ref name=&quot;biomedcentral.com&quot; /&gt;

==Diagnosis==
{{More citations needed section|date=November 2007}}
[[Genetic testing]] can confirm albinism and what variety it is, but offers no medical benefits, except in the case of non-OCA disorders. Such disorders cause other medical problems in conjunction with albinism, and may be treatable. Genetic tests are currently available for parents who want to find out if they are carriers of ty-neg albinism. Diagnosis of albinism involves carefully examining a person’s eyes, skin and hairs. Genealogical analysis can also help.

==Management==
Since there is no cure for albinism, it is managed through lifestyle adjustments. People with albinism need to take care not to get sunburnt and should have regular healthy skin checks by a dermatologist.

For the most part, treatment of the eye conditions consists of visual rehabilitation. Surgery is possible on the [[Extraocular muscles|extra-ocular muscles]] to decrease [[strabismus]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Atlas of Genetic Diagnosis&quot; /&gt; [[Nystagmus]]-damping surgery can also be performed, to reduce the &quot;shaking&quot; of the eyes back and forth.&lt;ref name=&quot;Surgical management of nystagmus&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last=Lee |first=J. |title=Surgical management of nystagmus |journal=Journal of the Royal Society of Medicine |volume=95 |issue=5 |pages=238–41 |date=May 2002 |pmid=11983764 |pmc=1279676 |doi=10.1258/jrsm.95.5.238}}&lt;/ref&gt; The effectiveness of all these procedures varies greatly and depends on individual circumstances.

[[Glasses]], low vision aids, [[large-print]] materials, and bright angled reading lights can help individuals with albinism. Some people with albinism do well using [[bifocals]] (with a strong reading lens), prescription reading glasses, hand-held devices such as [[Magnifying glass|magnifiers]] or [[monocular]]s or wearable devices like [[eSight]]
and [[Brainport]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Facts Albinism&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Facts About Albinism |first1=Richard |last1=King |first2=C. Gail |last2=Summers |first3=James W. |last3=Haefemeyer |first4=Bonnie |last4=LeRoy |date=2004 |work=Albinism.Med.UMN.edu |publisher=University of Minnesota |url=http://albinism.med.umn.edu/newfacts.htm |url-status = dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090125144209/http://albinism.med.umn.edu/newfacts.htm |archive-date=25 January 2009 |access-date=10 November 2017 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Pardes |first1=Arielle |title=The Wearables Giving Computer Vision to the Blind |url= https://www.wired.com/story/wearables-for-the-blind/ |journal=[[Wired (magazine)|Wired]] |publisher=[[Condé Nast]] |access-date=8 September 2017|date=2017-07-20 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The condition may lead to abnormal development of the [[optic nerve]] and sunlight may damage the [[retina]] of the eye as the [[Iris (anatomy)|iris]] cannot filter out excess light due to a lack of pigmentation. [[Photophobia]] may be ameliorated by the use of sunglasses which filter out ultraviolet light.&lt;ref name=&quot;news medical&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.news-medical.net/health/Albinism-Causes.aspx|title=Albinism causes|last1=Anon|date=2018-03-20|website=www.news-medical.net|publisher=News medical|archive-url=|archive-date=|accessdate=27 July 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some use [[bioptics (device)|bioptics]], glasses which have small telescopes mounted on, in, or behind their regular lenses, so that they can look through either the regular lens or the telescope. Newer designs of bioptics use smaller light-weight lenses. Some US states allow the use of bioptic telescopes for driving motor vehicles. (See also [[National Organization for Albinism and Hypopigmentation|NOAH]] bulletin &quot;Low Vision Aids&quot;.)

There are a number of national support groups across the globe which come under the umbrella of the World Albinism Alliance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Anon |title=World Albinism Alliance |url=https://worldalbinism.org/2015/01/07/introduction-to-the-world-albinism-alliance/ |publisher=WAA |accessdate=27 July 2018|date=2015-01-07 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Epidemiology==
Albinism affects people of all ethnic backgrounds; its frequency worldwide is estimated to be approximately one in 17,000. Prevalence of the different forms of albinism varies considerably by population, and is highest overall in people of [[sub-Saharan]] African descent.&lt;ref name=&quot;Oculocutaneous albinism&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Gronskov |first=K. |last2=Ek |first2=J. |last3=Brondum-Nielsen |first3=K. |title=Oculocutaneous albinism |journal=Orphanet Journal of Rare Diseases |date=2 November 2007 |doi=10.1186/1750-1172-2-43 |pmc=2211462 |pmid=17980020 |volume=2 |pages=43}}&lt;/ref&gt; Today, the prevalence of albinism in [[sub-Saharan Africa]] is around 1 in 5,000, while in Europe and the US it is 1 in 20,000.&lt;ref name=&quot;royalsocietypublishing.org&quot; /&gt; Rates as high as 1 in 1,000 have been reported for some populations in Zimbabwe and other parts of [[Southern Africa]].&lt;ref name=&quot;biomedcentral.com&quot;/&gt;

Certain ethnic groups and populations in isolated areas exhibit heightened susceptibility to albinism, presumably due to genetic factors. These include notably the [[Indigenous peoples of the Americas|Native American]] [[Kuna (people)|Kuna]], [[Zuni people|Zuni]] and [[Hopi]] nations (respectively of [[Panama]], [[New Mexico]] and [[Arizona]]); [[Japan]], in which one particular form of albinism is unusually common; and [[Ukerewe Island]], the population of which shows a very high incidence of albinism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.southern-africas-children.org.uk/ukerewe-albino.html |title=Ukerewe Albino Society |date=2009 |work=Southern Africas Children |access-date=21 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Society and culture==
In physical terms, humans with albinism commonly have visual problems and need sun protection.
&lt;!--************************************************
     ** DO NOT add new entries for people, fiction **
     ** characters, legends and myths, paintings   **
     ** or any other aspect of popular culture in  **
     ** this section; those go instead in the      **
     ** [[Albinism in popular culture]] article.   **
     ** This section summarizes that article and   **
     ** provides a place to add SOURCED material   **
     ** about albinism and CULTURE, not POP CULTURE  **
     ** (e.g. news reports of abuse of people with **
     ** albinism, or the rare counter-example).    **
     ************************************************--&gt;

===Persecution of people with albinism===
{{Main|Persecution of people with albinism}}
Humans with albinism often face social and cultural challenges (even threats), as the condition is often a source of ridicule, discrimination, or even fear and violence. It is especially socially stigmatised in many African societies. A study conducted in Nigeria on albino children stated that &quot;they experienced alienation, avoided social interactions and were less emotionally stable. Furthermore, affected individuals were less likely to complete schooling, find employment, and find partners&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Magna |first1=P. |title=Biology and genetics of Oculocutaneous albinism and vitiligo-common pigmentation disorders in Southern Africa |journal=South African Medical Journal |date=January 2014 |volume=103 |issue=1| pmid=24300644 |pages=984–8 |url= http://www.ajol.info/index.php/samj/article/view/98355|doi=10.7196/samj.7046 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Many cultures around the world have developed beliefs regarding people with albinism.

In African countries such as [[Tanzania]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/africa/7518049.stm |title=Living in fear: Tanzania's albinos |work=[[BBC News]] |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |publisher=[[British Broadcasting Corporation]] |date=21 July 2008 |access-date=27 February 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Burundi]],&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc.co.uk&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url= https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-11614957 |title=Burundi albino boy 'dismembered' |work=BBC News |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |date=24 October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/africa/8057956.stm |title=Burundian albino murders denied |work=BBC News |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |date=19 May 2009 |access-date=27 February 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; there has been an unprecedented rise in [[witchcraft]]-related killings of people with albinism in recent years, because their body parts are used in potions sold by [[witchdoctor]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= http://www.visuramagazine.com/franck-vogel-zeru-zeru |first=Franck |last=Vogel |author-link=Franck Vogel |title=Zeru, Zeru: Being Albino in Tanzania |work=Visura Magazine |publisher=Foto Visura |location=Westford, Vermont |issue=10 |date=August 2010 |access-date=10 November 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Numerous authenticated incidents have occurred in Africa during the 21st century.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/africa/7726743.stm |title=Man 'tried to sell' albino wife |work=BBC News |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |date=13 November 2008 |access-date=27 February 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/africa/7527729.stm |title=Tanzania albinos targeted again |work=BBC News |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |date=27 July 2008 |access-date=27 February 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Ntetema |first=Vicky |url= http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/africa/7523796.stm |title=In hiding for exposing Tanzania witchdoctors |work=BBC News |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |date=24 July 2008 |access-date=27 February 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/africa/7730193.stm |title=Mothers hacked in albino attacks |work=BBC News |date=14 November 2008 |access-date=27 February 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, in Tanzania, in September 2009, three men were convicted of killing a 14-year-old albino boy and severing his legs in order to sell them for witchcraft purposes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/africa/8270446.stm |title=Death for Tanzania albino killers |work=BBC News |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |date=23 September 2009 |access-date=27 February 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Again in Tanzania and Burundi in 2010, the murder and dismemberment of a kidnapped albino child was reported from the courts,&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc.co.uk&quot; /&gt; as part of a continuing problem.  The US-based [[National Geographic Society]] estimated that in Tanzania a complete set of albino body parts is worth [[United States dollar|US$]]75,000.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= http://news.nationalgeographic.com/news/2013/01/130125-albino-albinism-tanzania-witch-doctors/ |title=Pictures: Inside the Lives of Albinos in Tanzania |first1=Sasha |last1=Ingber |first2=Jacquelyn |last2=Martin |work=National Geographic News |publisher=[[National Geographic Society]] |location=Washington DC |date=27 January 2013 |access-date=10 November 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite video |title=Tanzanians with albinism targeted for witchcraft |date=30 April 2015 |publisher=[[UNICEF]] |via=YouTube |url= https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ocwWzE6_u20 |access-date=2017-02-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another harmful and false belief is that sex with an albinistic woman will cure a man of [[HIV]]. This has led, for example in [[Zimbabwe]], to rapes (and subsequent HIV infection).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.ipsnews.net/2002/11/rights-zimbabwe-the-last-minority-group-to-find-a-voice/ |title=The Last Minority Group to Find a Voice |last=Machipisa |first=Lewis |work=IPSNews.net |publisher=Inter Press Service News Agency |access-date=30 January 2010 |url-status = live|archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20090121145742/http://ipsnews.net/interna.asp?idnews=14122 |archive-date=21 January 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Albinism in popular culture===
{{Main|Albinism in popular culture}}
Famous people with albinism include historical figures such as [[Oxford University|Oxford]] don [[William Archibald Spooner]]; actor-comedian [[Victor Varnado]]; musicians such as [[Johnny Winter|Johnny]] and [[Edgar Winter]], [[Salif Keita]], [[Yellowman|Winston &quot;Yellowman&quot; Foster]], [[Brother Ali]], [[Sivuca]], [[Hermeto Pascoal]], [[Piano Red|Willie &quot;Piano Red&quot; Perryman]], [[Kalash Criminel]]; and fashion models [[Connie Chiu]] and [[Shaun Ross (model)|Shaun Ross]].  [[Emperor Seinei]] of Japan is thought to have been an albino because he was said to have been born with white hair.&lt;!--
     ************************************************
     ** DO NOT add new entries for people, fiction **
     ** characters, legends or folklore, paintings **
     ** or any other aspect of popular culture in  **
     ** this section; those go instead in the      **
     ** [[Albinism in popular culture]] article.   **
     ** This section summarizes that article and   **
     ** provides a place to add SOURCED material   **
     ** about albinism and CULTURE, not POP CULTURE  **
     ** (e.g. news reports of abuse of people with **
     ** albinism, or the rare counter-example).    **
     ************************************************--&gt;

===International Albinism Awareness Day===
{{Main|International Albinism Awareness Day}}
[[International Albinism Awareness Day]] was established after a motion was accepted on 18 December 2014 by the [[United Nations General Assembly]], proclaiming that as of 2015, 13 June would be known as International Albinism Awareness Day.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=International Albinism Awareness Day |url= https://www.un.org/en/events/albinismday/index.shtml}}&lt;/ref&gt;  This was followed by a mandate created by the [[United Nations Human Rights Council]] that appointed [[Ikponwosa Ero|Ms. Ikponwosa Ero]], who is from Nigeria, as the very first Independent Expert on the enjoyment of human rights by persons with albinism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Independent Expert on the enjoyment of human rights by persons with albinism |url= http://www.ohchr.org/EN/Issues/Albinism/Pages/IEAlbinism.aspx |work=OHCHR.org |publisher=[[Office of the High Commissioner for Human Rights]], [[United Nations]] |location=Geneva}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Columns-list|colwidth=30em|
* [[Albinism–deafness syndrome]]
* [[Marie Antoinette syndrome]]
* [[Amelanism]]
* [[Dyschromia]]
* [[Erythrism]], unusually red pigmentation
* [[Heterochromia iridum]]
* [[Human variability]]
* [[Isabelline (colour)#In animals|Isabellinism]]
* [[Leucism]]
* [[Melanism]]
* [[Nevus]], or birthmark
* [[National Organization for Albinism and Hypopigmentation]]
* [[Piebaldism]], patchy alternating loss of and concentrations of dermal pigmentation
* [[Vitiligo]] (or leukoderma), patchy loss of dermal pigmentation
* [[Xanthochromism|Xanthochromism and axanthism]], unusually yellow pigmentation and lack of yellow pigment, respectively
}}

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

==External links==
{{Medical resources
|  DiseasesDB = 318
|  ICD10 = {{ICD10|E|70|3|e|70}}
|  ICD9 = {{ICD9|270.2}}
|  ICDO =
|  OMIM = 203100
|  MedlinePlus = 001479
|  eMedicineSubj = derm
|  eMedicineTopic = 12
|  MeshID = D000417
| oMIM_mult       = {{OMIM4|103470}}, {{OMIM4|203200}}, {{OMIM4|606952}}, {{OMIM4|203290}}, {{OMIM4|203300}}, {{OMIM4|203310}}, {{OMIM4|256710}}, {{OMIM4|278400}}, {{OMIM4|214450}}, {{OMIM4|214500}}, {{OMIM4|220900}}, {{OMIM4|300500}}, {{OMIM4|300600}}, {{OMIM4|300650}}, {{OMIM4|300700}}, {{OMIM4|600501}}, {{OMIM4|604228}}, {{OMIM4|606574}}, {{OMIM4|606952}}, {{OMIM4|607624}}, {{OMIM4|609227}}
}}
{{Commons category|Albinism}}
{{Wiktionary|albinism|albino}}
* [https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/bookshelf/br.fcgi?book=gene&amp;part=oca2 GeneReview/NCBI/NIH/UW entry on Oculocutaneous Albinism Type 2]
* [https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/bookshelf/br.fcgi?book=gene&amp;part=oca4 GeneReview/NCBI/NIH/UW entry on Oculocutaneous Albinism Type 4]

{{Pigmentation disorders|state=collapsed}}
{{Skin colors}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Albinism| ]]
[[Category:Dermatologic terminology]]
[[Category:Disturbances of pigmentation]]
[[Category:Skin pigmentation]]
[[Category:Autosomal recessive disorders]]</text>
      <sha1>ruyy7apy0laitdc7g5x9bs0sc5e8s0f</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
