  <page>
    <title>Belgian hip hop</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2916</id>
    <revision>
      <id>936230072</id>
      <parentid>907168910</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-17T14:28:05Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>2A02:1811:D50C:B300:85A5:1769:82FF:D16</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Removed a dead (and irrelevant?) link</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=February 2013}}
'''Belgian hip hop music''' has a few [[rapper]]s stemming from [[Africa]] and [[Italy]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url=http://www.mtviggy.com/articles/artist-of-the-week-congolese-belgian-rapper-baloji/ |title=Artist of the Week: Congolese-Belgian Rapper Baloji! |publisher=Mtv Iggy |date=2011-01-11 |accessdate=2014-02-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Belgium]], like [[France]], controlled [[Africa]]n countries like the [[Democratic Republic of the Congo]] (formerly Zaire), [[Rwanda]], and [[Burundi]] until the early 1960s. Like in France, [[Immigration|immigrants]] from these countries started to study and live in [[Belgium]].

The Belgian [[hip hop music|hip hop]] scene started in the late 1980s with a U.S.-based [[techno music|techno]]/hip hop group called [[Technotronic]]. In the group was an emcee named [[Ya Kid K]] from the [[Democratic Republic of the Congo]] who later led the group into international fame with hits like &quot;Pump up the Jam&quot; and &quot;Shake That Body&quot;. In 1990, she also joined the group Hi-Tek 3 who were heard on ''[[Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles: The Original Motion Picture Soundtrack]]''. 

However, in the original belgian movement  the [[BRC Crew]] symbolise the real spirit of american underground Hip Hop culture with his singer [[Defi-J]] and also the first major pop rapper from Belgium was [[Benny B]], who had a very mainstream and commercial sound.  According to the European Music Office's report on ''Music in Europe'', this was the first of many pop acts that helped inspire a backlash and the creation of an underground hip hop scene.

Also in the late 1980s in the [[Wallonia|Walloon south]] of the country, French speaking/rapping [[Starflam]] was the biggest name in hip hop.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Andy Morgan |url=https://www.theguardian.com/music/2011/dec/04/baloji-rapper-congo-sorcerer-interview |title=Baloji: 'I want to make music that is very African and very modern' &amp;#124; Music &amp;#124; The Observer |publisher=Theguardian.com |date= |accessdate=2014-02-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[Flanders|Flemish]] north Dutch speaking/rapping groups like [['t Hof van Commerce]], Krapoel In Axe, St Andries MC's, and ABN were popular, rapping in their regional [[dialect]]s. 

In the year 2010 an authentic famous rapper [[James Deano]] make is come back with his binomial [[Olmo Carniselli]] AKA Mr Everybody after his succes song &quot;Les Blancs Ne Savent Pas Danser&quot; and innovate a new concept of Mr Everybody &quot;Les Freestyles De La semaine&quot; on Youtube. 

Today, the Belgian hip hop scene is growing. Rappers like [[Coely]], [[Roméo Elvis]] and [[Damso]] are achieving commercial success in their country and abroad. Other contemporary rappers/formations are [[Stikstof]], [[Woodie Smalls]], [[L'Or Du Commun]] and [[Isha (hip hop)|Isha]].

To find out more about today's Belgian hip hop scene, check out [http://www.belgianhiphop.be/ The Belgian Hip Hop Channel].

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{hiphop}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Belgian Hip Hop}}
[[Category:Belgian hip hop|*]]
__INDEX__</text>
      <sha1>nt4vrzw6aa0xus8nlr4dm2a37auj2jw</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
