  <page>
    <title>Artemis</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2905</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943101574</id>
      <parentid>942600414</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-28T21:01:57Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Simon.H05</username>
        <id>38207262</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Some edits</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Other uses}}
{{Pp-protected|small=yes}}
{{short description|Deity in ancient Greek religion and myth}}
{{Infobox deity
| type = Greek
| name = Artemis
| image = Diane de Versailles Leochares.jpg
| alt = 
| caption = The ''[[Diana of Versailles]]'', a [[Roman art|Roman]] copy of a [[Art in ancient Greece|Greek]] [[sculpture]] by [[Leochares]]&lt;br /&gt;([[Louvre Museum]])
| god_of = Greek goddess of the hunt, the wilderness, wild animals, the Moon, and chastity
| abode = [[Mount Olympus]]
| symbol = Bow, Arrow, Quiver, Hunting knives, Moon, Deer, Cypress
| consort = 
| parents = [[Zeus]] and [[Leto]]
| siblings = [[Apollo]], [[Aeacus]], [[Angelos (Greek mythology)|Angelos]], [[Aphrodite]], [[Ares]], [[Athena]], [[Dionysus]], [[Eileithyia]], [[Enyo]], [[Eris (mythology)|Eris]], [[Ersa]], [[Hebe (mythology)|Hebe]], [[Helen of Troy]], [[Hephaestus]], [[Heracles]], [[Hermes]], [[Minos]], [[Pandia]], [[Persephone]], [[Perseus]], [[Rhadamanthus]], the [[Graces]], the [[Horae]], the [[Litae]], the [[Muse]]s, the [[Moirai]]
| children = 
| mount = 
| Roman_equivalent = [[Diana (mythology)|Diana]]
|weapon=Bow, Arrows|animals=Stags, Deer|tree=[[Cypress]]}}
{{Contains special characters}}
{{Ancient Greek religion}}

'''Artemis''' ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|ɑr|t|ɪ|m|ɪ|s}}; {{lang-grc-gre|Ἄρτεμις}} Artemis, {{IPA-grc|ár.te.mis|att}}) is the [[Greek goddess]] of the hunt, the [[wilderness]], wild animals, the Moon, and [[chastity]].

Artemis is the daughter of [[Zeus]] and [[Leto]], and the twin sister of [[Apollo]]. She was the patron and protector of young girls, and was believed to bring disease upon women and relieve them of it. Artemis was worshipped as one of the primary goddesses of childbirth and midwifery along with [[Eileithyia]]. Much like [[Athena]] and [[Hestia]], Artemis preferred to remain a [[Virginity|maiden]] and is sworn never to marry.

Artemis was one of the most widely venerated of the Ancient Greek deities and her [[Temple of Artemis|temple]] at Ephesus was one of the [[Seven Wonders of the Ancient World]]. Artemis' symbols included a bow and arrow, a quiver and hunting knives and the [[deer]] and the [[Cupressus|cypress]] were sacred to her. The goddess [[Diana (mythology)|Diana]] is her Roman equivalent worshipped on the [[Aventine Hill]] near [[Lake Nemi]] and in [[Campania]].&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt;

== Etymology ==
The name Artemis ([[Proper noun|''noun'']], [[Gender (linguistics)|''feminine'']]) is of unknown or uncertain etymology,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite dictionary|title=Artemis|url=http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?term=Artemis&amp;allowed_in_frame=0|dictionary=[[Online Etymology Dictionary]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Babiniotis&quot;/&gt; although various sources have been proposed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Andrew Lang&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Charles Anthon&quot;/&gt;

According to [[Johann Theodor Jablonski|J. T. Jablonski]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Charles Anthon&quot;/&gt; the name is also [[Phrygia]]n and could be &quot;compared with the royal appellation ''Artemas'' of [[Xenophon]]. According to [[Charles Anthon]] the primitive root of the name is probably of Persian origin from *''arta'', *''art'', *''arte'', all meaning &quot;great, excellent, holy,&quot; thus Artemis &quot;becomes identical with the great mother of Nature, even as she was worshipped at Ephesus&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Charles Anthon&quot;&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |last=Anthon |first=Charles |author= |authorlink=Charles Anthon |authors= |editor= |encyclopedia= A Classical dictionary |title=Artemis |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=TIYMAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA210#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false |accessdate= |edition= |date= |year=1855 |month= |publisher=Harper &amp; Brothers|volume= |location=New York |id= |isbn= |oclc= |doi= |pages=210 |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt; Anton Goebel &quot;suggests the root στρατ or ῥατ, &quot;to shake,&quot; and makes Artemis mean the thrower of the dart or the shooter&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Andrew Lang&quot;/&gt;

The name may be possibly related to [[Greek language|Greek]] ''árktos'' &quot;[[bear]]&quot; (from [[Proto-Indo-European language|PIE]] *''h₂ŕ̥tḱos''), supported by the bear cult the goddess had in [[Attica]] ([[Brauronia#Cult of Artemis Brauronia|Brauronia]]) and the [[Neolithic]] remains at the [[Arkoudiotissa Cave]], as well as the story of [[Callisto (mythology)|Callisto]], which was originally about Artemis ([[Arcadia]]n epithet ''kallisto'');&lt;ref&gt;Michaël Ripinsky-Naxon, ''The Nature of Shamanism: Substance and Function of a Religious Metaphor'' (Albany, NY: State University of New York Press, 1993), 32.&lt;/ref&gt; this cult was a survival of very old totemic and shamanistic rituals and formed part of a larger [[bear worship|bear cult]] found further afield in other [[Proto-Indo-Europeans|Indo-European]] cultures (e.g., Gaulish [[Artio]]). It is believed that a precursor of Artemis was worshipped in [[Minoan civilization|Minoan Crete]] as the goddess of mountains and hunting, [[Britomartis]]. While connection with [[Anatolia]]n names has been suggested,&lt;ref&gt;Campanile, ''Ann. Scuola Pisa'' '''28''':305; Restelli, ''Aevum'' '''37''':307, 312.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Edwin L. Brown, &quot;In Search of Anatolian Apollo&quot;, ''Charis: Essays in Honor of Sara A. Immerwahr'', ''Hesperia Supplements'' '''33''' (2004:243–257). p. 251: Artemis, as Apollo's inseparable twin, is discussed in pp. 251ff.&lt;/ref&gt; the earliest attested forms of the name ''Artemis'' are the [[Mycenaean Greek]] {{lang|gmy|𐀀𐀳𐀖𐀵}}, ''a-te-mi-to'' /Artemitos/ and {{lang|gmy|𐀀𐀴𐀖𐀳}}, ''a-ti-mi-te'' /Artimitei/, written in [[Linear B]] at [[Pylos]].&lt;ref&gt;John Chadwick and [[Lydia Baumbach]], &quot;The Mycenaean Greek Vocabulary&quot; ''Glotta'', '''41'''.3/4 (1963:157-271). p. 176f, ''s.v.'' Ἂρτεμις, ''a-te-mi-to-'' (genitive); C. Souvinous, &quot;A-TE-MI-TO and A-TI-MI-TE&quot;, ''Kadmos'' '''9''' 1970:42–47; T. Christidis, &quot;Further remarks on A-TE-MI-TO and A-TI-MI-TE&quot;, ''Kadmos'' '''11''':125–28.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Robert S. P. Beekes|R. S. P. Beekes]] suggested that the ''e''/''i'' interchange points to a [[Pre-Greek]] origin.&lt;ref&gt;[[Robert S. P. Beekes|R. S. P. Beekes]], ''Etymological Dictionary of Greek'', Brill, 2009, p. 142.&lt;/ref&gt; Artemis was venerated in [[Lydia]] as ''Artimus''.&lt;ref&gt;''Indogermanica et Caucasica: Festschrift fur Karl Horst Schmidt zum 65. Geburtstag'' (Studies in Indo-European language and culture), W. de Gruyter, 1994, ''Etyma Graeca'', pp. 213–214, on [https://books.google.com/books?id=P3vb4KDB_UkC&amp;pg=PA213&amp;dq=lydian+artimus&amp;ei=QpsNTOjcC5bCzQSXlpXeCw&amp;cd=5#v=onepage&amp;q=lydian%20artimus&amp;f=false Google books]; Houwink ten Cate, ''The Luwian Population Groups of Lycia and Cilicia Aspera during the Hellenistic Period'' (Leiden) 1961:166, noted in this context by Brown 2004:252.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Georgios Babiniotis]], while accepting that the etymology is unknown, also states that the name is already attested in Mycenean Greek and is possibly of Pre-Greek origin.&lt;ref name=&quot;Babiniotis&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=[[Dictionary of Modern Greek|Λεξικό της Νέας Ελληνικής Γλώσσας]]|first=Georgios|last=Babiniotis|authorlink=Georgios Babiniotis|location=Athens|year=2005|publisher=Κέντρο Λεξικολογίας|chapter=Άρτεμις|page=286}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Ancient Greek writers, by way of [[folk etymology]], and some modern scholars, have linked Artemis (Doric ''Artamis'') to ἄρταμος, ''artamos'', i.e. &quot;butcher&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{LSJ|a)/rtamos|ἄρταμος|ref}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{LSJ|*)/artemis|Ἄρτεμις|ref}}.&lt;/ref&gt; or, like [[Plato]] did in ''[[Cratylus (dialogue)|Cratylus]]'', to {{lang|grc|ἀρτεμής}}, ''artemḗs'', i.e. &quot;safe&quot;, &quot;unharmed&quot;, &quot;uninjured&quot;, &quot;pure&quot;, &quot;the stainless maiden&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Andrew Lang&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=Myth, Ritual, and Religion|first=Andrew|last=Lang|authorlink=Andrew Lang|url=https://archive.org/stream/mythritualreligi02lang#page/209/mode/1up|pages=209–210|publisher=Longmans, Green and Co|location=London|year=1887}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Charles Anthon&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{LSJ|a)rtemh/s|ἀρτεμής|ref}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Mythology ==
{{quote| text=&lt;poem&gt;
Leto bore Apollo and Artemis, delighting in arrows,
Both of lovely shape like none of the heavenly gods,
As she joined in love to the [[Aegis]]-bearing ruler.
&lt;/poem&gt; | sign= [[Hesiod]] | source= ''[[Theogony]]'', lines 918–920 (written in the 7th century BC)}}

=== Birth ===
[[File:Apollo Artemis Brygos Louvre G151.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Apollo (left) and Artemis (right). [[Brygos]] (potter, signed), [[Briseis Painter]], Tondo of an Attic red-figure cup, ca. 470 BC, [[Louvre]].]]

[[File:Artemis Apollo Louvre Myr199.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Artemis (on the left, with a deer) and ''Apollo'' (on the right, holding a lyre) from [[Myrina, Greece|Myrina]], dating to approximately 25 BC]]

[[File:Artemis Kephisodotos Musei Capitolini MC1123.jpg|thumb|250px|Roman marble ''Bust of Artemis'' after [[Cephisodotus the Elder|Kephisodotos]] ([[Musei Capitolini]]), Rome.]]

Various conflicting accounts are given in Classical Greek mythology regarding the birth of Artemis and Apollo, her twin brother. However, in terms of parentage, all accounts agree that she was the daughter of Zeus and [[Leto]] and that she was the twin sister of Apollo. In some sources she is born at the same time as Apollo, in others, earlier or later.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=tOgWfjNIxoMC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;ots=Njj29ss-a-&amp;dq=Encyclopedia%20of%20Greek%20and%20roman%20mythology%20cite&amp;lr&amp;hl=uk&amp;pg=PP1#v=onepage&amp;q=Encyclopedia%20of%20Greek%20and%20roman%20mythology%20cite&amp;f=false|title=Encyclopedia of Greek and Roman Mythology|last=Roman|first=Luke|last2=Roman|first2=Monica|date=2010|publisher=Infobase Publishing|year=|isbn=9781438126395|location=|pages=85|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

An account by [[Callimachus]] has it that Hera forbade Leto to give birth on either terra firma (the mainland) or on an island. Hera was angry with her husband Zeus because he had impregnated Leto but the island of [[Delos]] disobeyed Hera and Leto gave birth there.

According to the [[Homeric Hymn]] to Artemis the island where Leto gave birth was [[Ortygia]].&lt;ref&gt;Hammond. ''Oxford Classical Dictionary.'' 597-598.&lt;/ref&gt;

In ancient Cretan history Leto was worshipped at [[Phaistos]] and, in Cretan mythology, Leto gave birth to Apollo and Artemis on the islands known today as [[Paximadia (islands)|Paximadia]].

A ''[[scholium]]'' of [[Maurus Servius Honoratus|Servius]] on ''[[Aeneid]]'' iii. 72 accounts for the island's archaic name Ortygia&lt;ref&gt;Or as a separate island birthplace of Artemis— &quot;Rejoice, blessed Leto, for you bare glorious children, the lord Apollon and Artemis who delights in arrows; her in Ortygia, and him in rocky Delos,&quot; says the [[Homeric Hymn]]; the etymology ''Ortygia'', &quot;Isle of Quail&quot;, is not supported by modern scholars.&lt;/ref&gt; by asserting that Zeus transformed Leto into a [[quail]] (''ortux'') in order to prevent Hera from finding out about his infidelity, and Kenneth McLeish suggested further that in quail form Leto would have given birth with as few birth-pains as a mother quail suffers when it lays an egg.&lt;ref&gt;McLeish, Kenneth. ''Children of the Gods'' pp 33f; Leto's birth-pangs, however, are graphically depicted by ancient sources.&lt;/ref&gt;

The myths also differ as to whether Artemis was born first, or Apollo. Most stories depict Artemis as born first, becoming her mother's midwife upon the birth of her brother Apollo.

=== Childhood ===
The childhood of Artemis is not fully related in any surviving myth. The ''[[Iliad]]'' reduced the figure of the dread goddess to that of a girl, who, having been thrashed by [[Hera]], climbs weeping into the lap of Zeus.&lt;ref&gt;''Iliad'' XXI 505-13&lt;/ref&gt;

A poem by [[Callimachus]] to the goddess &quot;who amuses herself on mountains with archery&quot; imagines some charming vignettes. Artemis, while sitting on the knee of her father, Zeus, asked him to grant her ten wishes:

# to always remain a virgin
# to have many names to set her apart from her brother Phoebus ([[Apollo]])
# to have a bow and arrow made by the Cyclopes
# to be the Phaesporia or Light Bringer
# to have a knee-length tunic so that she could hunt
# to have sixty &quot;daughters of [[Okeanos]]&quot;, all nine years of age, to be her choir
# to have twenty Amnisides Nymphs as [[handmaiden]]s to watch her dogs and bow while she rested
# to rule all the mountains
# any city
# to have the ability to help women in the pains of childbirth.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theoi.com/Text/CallimachusHymns1.html#3|title=Callimachus – Hymn III to Artemis 1-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Artemis believed that she had been chosen by [[Moirai|the Fates]] to be a midwife, particularly since she had assisted her mother in the delivery of her twin brother, Apollo.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.katinkahesselink.net/other/artemis.html On-line English translation].&lt;/ref&gt; All of her companions remained virgins, and Artemis closely guarded her own chastity. Her symbols included the golden bow and arrow, the hunting dog, the stag, and the Moon. Callimachus tells&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;Callimachus – Hymn III to Artemis 46&lt;/ref&gt; how Artemis spent her girlhood seeking out the things that she would need to be a huntress, how she obtained her bow and arrows from the isle of [[Lipari|Lipara]], where [[Hephaestus]] and the [[Cyclopes]] worked.

Oceanus' daughters were filled with fear, but the young Artemis bravely approached and asked for bow and arrows. Callimachus then tells how Artemis visited [[Pan (god)|Pan]], the god of the forest, who gave her seven female and six male dogs. She then captured six golden-horned deer to pull her chariot. Artemis practiced with her bow first by shooting at trees and then at wild beasts.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;

=== Intimacy ===
As a virgin, Artemis had interested many gods and men, but only her hunting companion, [[Orion (mythology)|Orion]], won her heart. Orion was accidentally killed either by Artemis or by Gaia.&lt;ref&gt;[[Scholia]] on ''[[Homer]], [[Iliad]]'' 18.486 citing [[Pherecydes of Leros|Pherecydes]]&lt;/ref&gt;

The river god [[Alpheus (mythology)|Alpheus]] was in love with Artemis, but as he realizes that he can do nothing to win her heart, he decides to capture her. Artemis, who is with her companions at Letrenoi, goes to Alpheus, but, suspicious of his motives, she covers her face with mud so that the river god does not recognize her. In another story, Alphaeus tries to rape Artemis' attendant [[Arethusa (mythology)|Arethusa]]. Artemis pities Arethusa and saves her by transforming Arethusa into a spring in Artemis' temple, [[Artemis Alphaea]] in Letrini, where the goddess and her attendant drink.

Bouphagos, the son of the Titan Iapetus, sees Artemis and thinks about raping her. Reading his sinful thoughts, Artemis strikes him at Mount Pholoe.

{{anchor|Siproites}} Siproites is a boy, who, either because he accidentally sees Artemis bathing or because he attempts to rape her, is turned into a girl by the goddess.

=== Actaeon ===
Multiple versions of the Actaeon myth survive, though many are fragmentary. The details vary but at the core, they involve a great hunter, [[Actaeon]] whom Artemis turns into a stag for a transgression and who is then killed by hunting dogs.&lt;ref&gt;Heath, &quot;The Failure of Orpheus&quot;, ''Transactions of the American Philological Association'' '''124''' (1994:163-196) p. 196.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Walter Burkert]], ''Homo Necans'' (1972), translated by Peter Bing (University of California Press) 1983, p 111.&lt;/ref&gt; Usually, the dogs are his own, who no longer recognize their master. Sometimes they are Artemis' hounds.

According to the standard modern text on the work, Lamar Ronald Lacey's ''The Myth of Aktaion: Literary and Iconographic Studies'', the most likely original version of the myth is that Actaeon was the hunting companion of the goddess who, seeing her naked in her sacred spring, attempts to force himself on her. For this hubris, he is turned into a stag and devoured by his own hounds. However, in some surviving versions, Actaeon is a stranger who happens upon her. According to the Latin version of the story told by the Roman [[Ovid]]&lt;ref&gt;Ovid, ''Metamorphoses'' iii.131; see also pseudo-Apollodorus' ''Bibliotheke'' iii. 4&lt;/ref&gt; having accidentally seen Artemis (Diana) on [[Mount Cithaeron]] while she was bathing, he was changed by her into a stag, and pursued and killed by his fifty hounds.{{sfn|Chisholm|1911}} Different tellings also diverge in the hunter's transgression, which is sometimes merely seeing the virgin goddess naked, sometimes boasting he is a better hunter than she,&lt;ref&gt;Lacy, &quot;Aktaion and a Lost 'Bath of Artemis'&quot; ''The Journal of Hellenic Studies'' '''110''' (1990:26-42)&lt;/ref&gt; or even merely being a rival of Zeus for the affections of [[Semele]].

=== Adonis ===
[[File:Giuseppe-Mazzuoli-The-Death-of-Adonis-hermitag.jpg|thumb|right|''The Death of Adonis'', by [[Giuseppe Mazzuoli (1644–1725)|Giuseppe Mazzuoli]], 1709. [[Hermitage Museum]], [[Saint Petersburg]], Russia.]]
In some versions of the story of [[Adonis]], Artemis sent a [[Boar|wild boar]] to kill Adonis as punishment for his hubristic boast that he was a better hunter than her.

In other versions, Artemis killed Adonis for revenge. In later myths, Adonis had been related as a favorite of [[Aphrodite]], and Aphrodite was responsible for the death of [[Hippolytus (mythology)#Hippolytus as Virbius|Hippolytus]], who had been a favorite of Artemis. Therefore, Artemis killed Adonis to avenge Hippolytus's death.

In yet another version, Adonis was not killed by Artemis, but by Ares, as punishment for being with Aphrodite.

=== Orion ===
[[Orion (mythology)|Orion]] was Artemis' hunting companion. In some versions, he is killed by Artemis, while in others he is killed by a [[Scorpius#Mythology|scorpion]] sent by [[Gaia (mythology)|Gaia]]. In some versions, Orion tries to seduce Opis,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Another name for Artemis herself&quot;, [[Karl Kerenyi]] observes, ''The Gods of the Greeks'' (1951:204).&lt;/ref&gt; one of Artemis' followers, and she kills him. In a version by [[Aratus]],&lt;ref&gt;Aratus, 638&lt;/ref&gt; Orion takes hold of Artemis' robe and she kills him in [[self-defense]].

In yet another version, Apollo sends the scorpion. According to [[Gaius Julius Hyginus|Hyginus]]&lt;ref&gt;Hyginus, ''[[Poeticon astronomicon]]'', ii.34, quoting the Greek poet Istrus.&lt;/ref&gt; Artemis once loved Orion (in spite of the late source, this version appears to be a rare remnant of her as the pre-Olympian goddess, who took consorts, as [[Eos]] did), but was tricked into killing him by her brother Apollo, who was &quot;protective&quot; of his sister's maidenhood.

=== The Aloadae ===
The twin sons of [[Poseidon]] and [[Iphidemia]], Otos and Ephialtes, grew enormously at a young age. They were aggressive, great hunters, and could not be killed unless they killed each other. The growth of the [[Aloadae]] never stopped, and they boasted that as soon as they could reach heaven, they would kidnap Artemis and [[Hera]] and take them as wives. The gods were afraid of them, except for Artemis who captured a fine deer (or in another version of the story, she changed herself into a doe) and jumped out between them. The Aloadae threw their spears and so mistakenly killed each other. In another version, Apollo sent the deer into the Aloadae's midst, causing their accidental killing of each other.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt;

=== Callisto ===

[[File:Tizian 015.jpg|thumb|''[[Diana and Callisto]]'', c. 1556–1559, by [[Titian]]. [[Scottish National Gallery]], Edinburgh]]

[[Callisto (mythology)|Callisto]] was the daughter of Lycaon, King of Arcadia and also was one of Artemis's hunting attendants. As a companion of Artemis, she took a vow of chastity. Zeus appeared to her disguised as Artemis, or in some stories Apollo gained her confidence and took advantage of her or, according to [[Ovid]], raped her. As a result of this encounter, she conceived a son, Arcas.

Enraged, Hera or Artemis (some accounts say both) changed her into a bear. Arcas almost killed the bear, but Zeus stopped him just in time. Out of pity, Zeus placed Callisto the bear into the heavens, thus the origin of Callisto the Bear as a constellation. Some stories say that he placed both Arcas and Callisto into the heavens as bears, forming the [[Ursa Minor]] and [[Ursa Major]] constellations.

=== Iphigenia and the Taurian Artemis ===
Artemis punished [[Agamemnon]] after he killed a sacred stag in a [[sacred grove]] and boasted that he was a better hunter than the goddess. When the Greek fleet was preparing at [[Aulis (ancient Greece)|Aulis]] to depart for [[Troy]] to begin the [[Trojan War]], Artemis becalmed the winds. The seer [[Calchas]] advised Agamemnon that the only way to appease Artemis was to sacrifice his daughter [[Iphigenia]]. Artemis then snatched Iphigenia from the altar and substituted a deer. Various myths have been told about what happened after Artemis took her. Either she was brought to Tauros and led the priests there or became Artemis' immortal companion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theoi.com/Olympios/ArtemisFavour.html#Iphigeneia |title=FAVOUR OF ARTEMIS : Greek mythology |publisher=Theoi.com |date= |author=Aaron J. Atsma |accessdate=2011-01-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Niobe ===
A Queen of [[Thebes (Greece)|Thebes]] and wife of [[Amphion]], [[Niobe]] boasted of her superiority to Leto because while she had fourteen children ([[Niobids]]), seven boys and seven girls, Leto had only one of each. When Artemis and Apollo heard this impiety, Apollo killed her sons as they practiced athletics, and Artemis shot her daughters, who died instantly without a sound. Apollo and Artemis used poisoned arrows to kill them, though according to some versions two of the Niobids were spared, one boy and one girl. Amphion, at the sight of his dead sons, killed himself. A devastated Niobe and her remaining children were turned to stone by Artemis as they wept. The gods themselves entombed them.

=== Chione ===
Chione was a princess of Pokis. She was beloved by two gods, [[Hermes]] and [[Apollo]], and boasted that she was prettier than Artemis because she made two gods fall in love with her at once. Artemis was furious and killed Chione with her arrow or struck her dumb by shooting off her tongue. However, some versions of this myth say Apollo and Hermes protected her from Artemis' wrath.

=== Atalanta, Oeneus and the Meleagrids ===
[[File:Artemis libation Louvre CA599.jpg|thumb|right|Artemis pouring a libation, c. 460-450 BC.]]
Artemis saved the infant [[Atalanta]] from dying of exposure after her father abandoned her. She sent a female bear to suckle the baby, who was then raised by hunters. In some stories, Artemis later sent a bear to hurt Atalanta because others claimed Atalanta was a superior hunter.

Among other adventures, Atalanta participated in the hunt for the [[Calydonian Boar]], which Artemis had sent to destroy [[Calydon]] because King [[Oeneus]] had forgotten her at the harvest sacrifices. In the hunt, Atalanta drew the first blood and was awarded the prize of the skin. She hung it in a sacred grove at [[Tegea]] as a dedication to Artemis.

[[Meleager]] was a hero of Aetolia. King [[Oeneus]] had him gather heroes from all over Greece to hunt the [[Calydonian Boar]]. After the death of [[Meleager]], Artemis turned his grieving sisters, the [[Meleagrids]] into [[guineafowl]] that Artemis loved very much.

=== Aura ===
In [[Nonnus]] ''[[Dionysiaca]]'',&lt;ref&gt;Aura does not appear elsewhere in surviving literature and appears to have been offered no [[Cult (religion)|cult]].&lt;/ref&gt; [[Aura (mythology)|Aura]] was the daughter of [[Lelantos]] and [[Periboia]]. She was a virgin huntress, just like Artemis and proud of her maidenhood. One day, she claimed that the body of Artemis was too womanly and she doubted her virginity. Artemis asked [[Nemesis (mythology)|Nemesis]] for help to avenge her dignity and caused the rape of Aura by [[Dionysus]]. Aura became a mad and dangerous killer. When she bore twin sons, she ate one of them while the other one, [[Iacchus]], was saved by Artemis. Iacchus later became an attendant of [[Demeter]] and the leader of [[Eleusinian Mysteries]].

=== Polyphonte ===

[[Polyphonte]] was a young woman who fled home preferring the idea of a virginal life with Artemis to the conventional life of marriage and children favoured by Aphrodite. As a punishment Aphrodite cursed her, causing her to have children by a bear. The resulting offspring, Agrius and Oreius, were wild cannibals who incurred the hatred of Zeus. Ultimately the entire family were transformed into birds and more specifically ill portents for mankind.&lt;ref&gt;[[Antoninus Liberalis]], Metamorphoses, 21&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Trojan War ===
Artemis may have been represented as a supporter of Troy because her brother [[Apollo]] was the patron god of the city and she herself was widely worshipped in western Anatolia in historical times. In the ''[[Iliad]]''&lt;ref&gt;Homer, ''Iliad'' 21.470 ff).&lt;/ref&gt; she came to blows with Hera, when the divine allies of the Greeks and Trojans engaged each other in conflict. Hera struck Artemis on the ears with her own quiver, causing the arrows to fall out. As Artemis fled crying to Zeus, Leto gathered up the bow and arrows.

Artemis played quite a large part in this war. Like her mother and brother, who was widely worshipped at Troy, Artemis took the side of the Trojans. At the Greek's journey to Troy, Artemis becalmed the sea and stopped the journey until an oracle came and said they could win the goddess' heart by sacrificing [[Iphigenia]], [[Agamemnon]]'s daughter. Agamemnon once promised the goddess he would sacrifice the dearest thing to him, which was Iphigenia, but broke that promise. Other sources{{which|date=November 2010}} said he boasted about his hunting ability and provoked the goddess' anger. Artemis saved Iphigenia because of her bravery. In some versions of the myth,{{which|date=November 2010}} Artemis made Iphigenia her attendant or turned her into [[Hecate]], goddess of night, witchcraft, and the underworld.

[[Aeneas]] was helped by Artemis, Leto, and Apollo. Apollo found him wounded by Diomedes and lifted him to heaven. There, the three of them secretly healed him in a great chamber.

== Worship ==
[[File:Jerash Temple of Artemis.jpg|thumb|''Roman Temple of Artemis'' in [[Jerash, Jordan]], built during the reign of [[Antoninus Pius]].]]

{{Main|Brauronia}}

Artemis, the goddess of forests and hills, was worshipped throughout [[ancient Greece]].&lt;ref&gt;“. . . a goddess universally worshipped in historical Greece, but in all likelihood pre-Hellenic.” Hammond, ''Oxford Classical Dictionary'', 126.&lt;/ref&gt; Her best known [[Cult (religious practice)|cults]] were on the island of [[Delos]]
(her birthplace), in Attica at [[Brauron]] and Mounikhia (near [[Piraeus]]), and in [[Sparta]]. She was often depicted in paintings and statues in a forest setting, carrying a bow and arrows and accompanied by a deer.

The ancient Spartans used to sacrifice to her as one of their patron goddesses before starting a new [[military campaign]].

[[Athenian festivals]] in honor of Artemis included [[Elaphebolia]], [[Mounikhia]], Kharisteria, and [[Brauronia]]. The festival of [[Artemis Orthia]] was observed in [[Sparta]].

Pre-pubescent and adolescent Athenian girls were sent to the [[sanctuary of Artemis at Brauron]] to serve the Goddess for one year. During this time, the girls were known as ''arktoi'', or little she-bears. A myth explaining this servitude states that a bear had formed the habit of regularly visiting the town of Brauron, and the people there fed it, so that, over time, the bear became tame. A girl teased the bear, and, in some versions of the myth, it killed her, while, in other versions, it clawed out her eyes. Either way, the girl's brothers killed the bear, and Artemis was enraged. She demanded that young girls &quot;act the bear&quot; at her sanctuary in atonement for the bear's death.&lt;ref&gt;[[Mark Golden|Golden, M.]], ''Children and Childhood in Classical Athens'' ([[Baltimore]]: [[Johns Hopkins University Press]], 1990), [https://books.google.com/books?id=LvV0CQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT84&amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false p. 84].&lt;/ref&gt;

Artemis was worship as one of the primary goddesses of childbirth and midwifery along with [[Eileithyia]]. Dedications of clothing to her sanctuaries after a successful birth was common in the [[Classical antiquity|Classical era]].&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{cite thesis|last=Wise|first=Susan|title=Childbirth Votives and Rituals in Ancient Greece|date=2007|publisher=University of Cincinnati|type=PhD}}&lt;/ref&gt; Artemis could be a deity to be feared by pregnant women, as deaths during this time were contributed to her. As childbirth and pregnancy was a very common and important event, there were numerous other deities associated with it, many localized to a particular geographic area, including but not limited to [[Aphrodite]], [[Hera]] and [[Hekate]].&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt; According to [[Bibliotheca (Pseudo-Apollodorus)|Pseudo-Apollodorus]], she assisted her mother in the delivery of her twin.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Bibliotheca|last=Pseudo-Apollodorus|first=|publisher=|year=|isbn=|location=|pages=1. 21}}&lt;/ref&gt; Older sources, such as [[Homeric Hymns|Homeric Hymn to Delian Apollo]] (in Line 115), have the arrival of Eileithyia on Delos as the event that allows Leto to give birth to her children. Contradictory is [[Hesiod|Hesiod's]] presentation of the myth in [[Theogony]], where he states that Leto bore her children before Zeus’ marriage to Hera with no commentary on any drama related to their birth.

During the [[classical antiquity|Classical period]] in [[Athens]], she was identified with [[Hecate|Hekate]]. Artemis also assimilated [[Caryatis]] ([[Carya (goddess)|Carya]]).

=== Epithets ===
{{Redirect|Alphaea|the genus of moth|Alphaea (moth)}}
[[File:Artemis found in Pompeii.jpg|thumb|right|Color reconstruction of a first-century AD statue of Artemis found in [[Pompeii]], reconstructed using analysis of trace pigments - imitation of Greek statues of the sixth century BC (part of [[Gods in Color]])]]
{{Coin image box 1 double
| header =
| image = File:Amfipolis+.jpg
| caption_left = '''[[Obverse and reverse|O:]]''' bare head of [[Augustus]]
[[Caesar (title)|ΚΑΙΣΑΡ]] / [[Son of God|ΘΕΟΥ ΥΙΟΣ]] 
| caption_right = '''[[Obverse and reverse|R:]]''' Artemis Tauropolos riding [[bull]]
[[Amphipolis|AMΦΙΠOΛEΙΤΩΝ]]
| width = 400
| footer = [[bronze]] [[coin]] struck by [[Augustus]] in [[Amphipolis]] 31 - 27 BC; ref.: RPC 1626
| position = right| margin = 4
}}

As '''Aeginaea''', she was worshipped in [[Sparta]]; the name means either huntress of [[chamois]], or the wielder of the javelin ({{lang|grc|αἰγανέα}}).&lt;ref&gt;[[Pausanias (geographer)|Pausanias]], iii. 14. §&amp;nbsp;2.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Schmitz |first=Leonhard |author-link =  |contribution=Aeginaea |editor-last=Smith | editor-first=William |title=[[Dictionary of Greek and Roman Biography and Mythology]] |volume=1 |page=26 |publisher= |place=Boston |year=1867 |contribution-url=http://www.ancientlibrary.com/smith-bio/0035.html |postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt; }}&lt;/ref&gt;
Also in Sparta, Artemis ''Lygodesma'' was worshipped. This epithet means &quot;willow-bound&quot; from the Gr. ''lygos'' (λυγός, willow) and ''desmos'' (δεσμός, bond). The [[willow tree]] appears in several ancient Greek myths and rituals.&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=YTfxZH4QnqgC&amp;pg=PA187&amp;lpg=PA187&amp;dq=artemis+lygodesma&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=g1MyQhf-b8&amp;sig=gBMucGkaGbYr7-hTHT11NCFovPo&amp;hl=el&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=y-KoT-i4D4Kd8gPFivnLBA&amp;ved=0CFIQ6AEwAw#v=onepage&amp;q=artemis%20lygodesma&amp;f=false Bremmer Jan N. (2008) ''Greek Religion and Culture, the Bible and the Ancient Near East'', Brill, Netherlands, p. 187.]&lt;/ref&gt;

As Artemis '''Isora''' also known as Isoria or Issoria, in the temple at the [[Issorium]] near lounge of the [[Crotani]] (the body of troops named the [[Pitanatae]]) near [[Pitane (Laconia)|Pitane]], [[Sparta]]. [[Pausanias (geographer)|Pausanias]] mentions that although the locals refer to her as Artemis Isora, he says  &quot;''They surname her also Lady of the Lake, though she is not really Artemis hut [[Britomartis]] of Crete''&quot;
&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Travels in the Morea: with a map and plans - William Martin Leake - Google Books| accessdate = 2020-01-16| url = https://books.google.com/books?id=eA0xf2SuS2gC&amp;pg=PA177&amp;lpg=PA177&amp;dq=polyaen+issorium&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=7SWQBOiodU&amp;sig=ACfU3U1xnSSZJ_vdwb4ErI8_6TxTLO9kRg&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=2ahUKEwiczqXa8YbnAhVIKa0KHeukD9oQ6AEwAXoECAkQAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=polyaen%20issorium&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = CALLIMACHUS, HYMNS 1-3 - Theoi Classical Texts Library| accessdate = 2020-01-16| url = https://www.theoi.com/Text/CallimachusHymns1.html#c32}}3, verse 170&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Plutarch • Life of Agesilaus| accessdate = 2020-01-16| url = http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Plutarch/Lives/Agesilaus*.html}}32,4&lt;/ref&gt;

She was worshipped at [[Naupactus]] as '''Aetole'''; in her temple in that town there was a statue of white marble representing her throwing a javelin.&lt;ref&gt;[[Pausanias (geographer)|Pausanias]], x. 38. §&amp;nbsp;6.&lt;/ref&gt; This &quot;Aetolian Artemis&quot; would not have been introduced at Naupactus, anciently a place of [[Ozolian Locris]], until it was awarded to the [[Aetolia]]ns by [[Philip II of Macedon]]. Strabo records another precinct of &quot;Aetolian Artemos&quot; at the head of the [[Adriatic Sea|Adriatic]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Among the Heneti certain honours have been decreed to Diomedes; and, indeed, a white horse is still sacrificed to him, and two precincts are still to be seen — one of them sacred to the Argive Hera and the other to the Aetolian Artemis. (Strabo, v.1.9 [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Strabo/5A*.html on-line text]).&lt;/ref&gt; As [[Agoraea]] she was the protector of the [[agora]].

As [[Artemis Orthia]] (Greek Ὀρθία) and was common to the four villages originally constituting Sparta: Limnai, in which it is situated, Pitana, Kynosoura and Mesoa.

As '''[[Agrotera]]''', she was especially associated as the patron goddess of hunters. In Athens Artemis was often associated with the local [[Aegina|Aeginian]] goddess, '''[[Aphaea]]'''. As '''[[Potnia Theron]]''', she was the patron of wild animals; [[Homer]] used this title. As '''[[Kourotrophos]]''', she was the nurse of youths. As '''Locheia''', she was the goddess of childbirth and midwives.

She was sometimes known as '''[[Cynthia]]''', from her birthplace on [[Cynthus|Mount Cynthus]] on [[Delos]], or '''Amarynthia''' from a festival in her honor originally held at Amarynthus in [[Euboea]].

She was sometimes identified by the name '''[[Phoebe (mythological characters)|Phoebe]]''', the feminine form of her brother Apollo's solar epithet [[Phoebus]].

'''Alphaea''', '''Alpheaea''', or '''Alpheiusa''' ([[Ancient Greek|Gr.]] {{lang|grc|Ἀλφαῖα}}, {{lang|grc|Ἀλφεαία}}, or {{lang|grc|Ἀλφειοῦσα}}) was an epithet that Artemis derived from the river god [[Alpheus (mythology)|Alpheius]], who was said to have been in love with her.&lt;ref name=&quot;DGRBM&quot;&gt;{{cite encyclopedia | last = Schmitz | first = Leonhard | authorlink = Leonhard Schmitz | title = Alphaea | editor = [[William Smith (lexicographer)|William Smith]] | encyclopedia = [[Dictionary of Greek and Roman Biography and Mythology]] | volume = 1 | pages = 133 | publisher = [[Little, Brown and Company]] | location = Boston | year = 1867 | url = http://www.ancientlibrary.com/smith-bio/0142.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was under this name that she was worshipped at Letrini in [[Elis]],&lt;ref&gt;[[Pausanias (geographer)|Pausanias]], ''Description of Greece'' vi. 22. §&amp;nbsp;5&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Strabo]], ''[[Geographica]]'' viii. p. 343&lt;/ref&gt; and in [[Ortygia]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Scholiast]] on [[Pindar]]'s ''Pythian Odes'' ii. 12, ''Nemean Odes'' i. 3&lt;/ref&gt; Artemis Alphaea was associated with the wearing of masks, largely because of the legend that while fleeing the advances of Alpheius, she and her [[nymph]]s escaped him by covering their faces.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite conference | first = G. | last = Dickins | authorlink = | author2 = Society for the Promotion of Hellenic Studies | title = Terracotta Masks | booktitle = The Sanctuary of Artemis Orthia: Supplementary Papers | pages = 172 | publisher = [[Macmillan Publishers]] | year = 1929 | location = London, England | url = https://www.google.com/books?id=bFlZAAAAMAAJ | accessdate = 2009-03-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As '''Artemis Anaitis''', the 'Persian Artemis' was identified with [[Anahita]]. As [[Apanchomene]], she was worshipped as a hanged goddess.

{{anchor|Tauropolos}}She was also worshiped as '''Artemis Tauropolos''', variously interpreted as &quot;worshipped at [[Taurica|Tauris]]&quot;, &quot;pulled by a yoke of bulls&quot;, or &quot;hunting bull goddess&quot;. A statue of Artemis &quot;Tauropolos&quot; in her temple at [[Brauron]] in Attica was supposed to have been brought from the [[Crimea|Taurians]] by [[Iphigenia]]. Tauropolia was also a festival of Artemis in [[Athens]]. There was a ''Tauropolion'', a temple in a ''[[temenos]]'' sacred to Artemis Tauropolos, in the north Aegean island of Doliche (now [[Ikaria]]). There is a Temple to 'Artemis Tauropolos' (as well as a smaller temple to an unknown goddess about {{convert|262|m|abbr=off}} south, on the beach) located on the eastern shore of Attica, in the modern town of Artemida (Loutsa). An aspect of the Taurian Artemis was also worshipped as [[Aricina]].

[[Pausanias (geographer)|Pausanias]] at the [[Description of Greece]] writes that near [[Pyrrhichus]] there was a sanctuary of Artemis, called '''Astrateias''' ({{lang-grc|Ἀστρατείας}}), with image of the goddess said to have been dedicated by the [[Amazons]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0525.tlg001.perseus-grc1:3.25.3 Pausanias, Description of Greece, § 3.25.3]&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Festivals ===
[[File:Brauron-2.jpg|thumb|right|Sanctuary of Artemis at [[Brauron]].]]

Artemis was born on the sixth day, which made it sacred for her.
* [[Brauronia|Festival of Artemis in Brauron]], where girls, aged between five and ten, dressed in [[Saffron (color)|saffron]] robes and played at being bears, or &quot;act the bear&quot;  to appease the goddess after she sent the plague when her bear was killed.
* Festival of Amarysia is a celebration to worship Artemis Amarysia in [[Attica]]. In 2007, a team of Swiss and Greek archaeologists found the ruin of Artemis Amarysia Temple, at [[Euboea]], Greece.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=mharrsch |url=http://passionateabouthistory.blogspot.com/2007/11/search-continues-for-temple-of-artemis.html |title=Passionate about History: Search continues for temple of Artemis Amarysia |publisher=Passionateabouthistory.blogspot.com |date=2007-11-04 |accessdate=2011-01-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Festival of Artemis Saronia, a festival to celebrate Artemis in Trozeinos, a town in [[Argolis]]. A king named Saron built a sanctuary for the goddess after the goddess saved his life when he went hunting and was swept away by a wave. He held a festival in her honor.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mythindex.com/greek-mythology/S/Saron.html |title=SARON, Greek Mythology Index |publisher=Mythindex.com |date= |accessdate=2011-01-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* On the 16th day of Metageitnio (second month on the Athenian calendar), people sacrificed to Artemis and [[Hecate]] at [[Deme]] in [[Erchia]].&lt;ref name=&quot;kharis&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.winterscapes.com/kharis/calendar.htm#Meta |title=Ancient Athenian Festival Calendar |publisher=Winterscapes.com |date=2007-07-24 |accessdate=2011-01-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Kharisteria Festival on 6th day of Boidromion (third month) celebrates the victory of the [[Battle of Marathon]], also known as the Athenian &quot;Thanksgiving&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.winterscapes.com/kharis/calendar.htm#Boed |title=Ancient Athenian Festival Calendar |publisher=Winterscapes.com |date=2007-07-24 |accessdate=2011-01-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Day six of Elaphobolia (ninth month) festival of Artemis the Deer Huntress where she was offered cakes shaped like stags, made from dough, honey and [[sesame]] seeds.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.winterscapes.com/kharis/calendar.htm#Elap |title=Ancient Athenian Festival Calendar |publisher=Winterscapes.com |date=2007-07-24 |accessdate=2011-01-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Day 6 or 16 of Mounikhion (tenth month) is a celebration of her as the goddess of nature and animals. A goat was sacrificed to her.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.winterscapes.com/kharis/calendar.htm#Moun |title=Ancient Athenian Festival Calendar |publisher=Winterscapes.com |date=2007-07-24 |accessdate=2011-01-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Day 6 of Thargelion (eleventh month), is the Goddess's birthday, while the seventh was Apollo's.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.winterscapes.com/kharis/calendar.htm#Thar |title=Ancient Athenian Festival Calendar |publisher=Winterscapes.com |date=2007-07-24 |accessdate=2011-01-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* A festival for [[Diktynna|Artemis Diktynna]] (of the net) was held in [[Hypsous]].
* [[Laphria (festival)|Laphria]], a festival for Artemis in [[Patrai]]. The procession starts by setting logs of wood around the altar, each of them 16 [[cubit]]s long. On the altar, within the circle, the driest wood is placed. Just before the festival, a smooth ascent to the altar is built by piling earth upon the altar steps. The festival begins with a splendid procession in honor of Artemis, and the maiden officiating as priestess rides last in the procession upon a chariot yoked to four deer, Artemis' traditional mode of transport (see below). However, the sacrifice is not offered until the next day.
* In [[Orchomenus (Arcadia)|Orchomenus]], a sanctuary was built for Artemis Hymnia where her festival was celebrated every year.

=== Modern ===
{{Empty section|date=January 2013}}

== Attributes ==
===Virginity===
An important aspect of Artemis' persona and worship was her virginity, which may seem contradictory given her role as a goddess associated with childbirth. It is likely that the idea of Artemis as a virgin goddess is related to her primary role as a huntress. Hunters traditionally abstained from sex prior to the hunt as a form of ritual purity and out of a belief that the scent would scare off potential prey. The ancient cultural context in which Artemis' worship emerged also held that virginity was a prerequisite to marriage, and that a married woman became subservient to her husband. In this light, Artemis' virginity is also related to her power and independence. Rather than a form of asexuality, it is an attribute that signals Artemis as her own master, with power equal to that of male gods. It is also possible that her virginity represents a concentration of fertility that can be spread among her followers, in the manner of earlier mother goddess figures. However, some later Greek writers did come to treat Artemis as inherently asexual and as an opposite to [[Aphrodite]].&lt;ref name=Hjerrild&gt;Hjerrild, B. (2009). Near Eastern equivalents to Artemis. Tobias Fischer-Hansen &amp; Birte Poulsen, eds. ''From Artemis to Diana: The Goddess of Man and Beast''. Museum Tusculanum Press. {{ISBN|8763507889}}, 9788763507882.&lt;/ref&gt;

===As a mother goddess===
Despite her virginity, both modern scholars and ancient commentaries have linked Artemis to the archetype of the [[mother goddess]]. Artemis was traditionally linked to fertility and was petitioned to assist women with childbirth. According to [[Herodotus]], the Greek playwright [[Aeschylus]] identified Artemis with [[Persephone]] as a daughter of [[Demeter]]. Her worshipers in [[Arcadia]] also traditionally associated her with Demeter and Persephone. In [[Asia Minor]], she was often conflated with local mother goddess figures, such as [[Cybele]], and [[Anahita]] in [[Iran]]. However, the archetype of the mother goddess was not highly compatible with the Greek pantheon, and though the Greeks had adopted worship of Cybele and other Anatolian mother goddesses as early as the 7th century BCE, she was not directly conflated with any Greek goddesses; instead, bits and pieces of her worship and aspects were absorbed variously by Artemis, Aphrodite, and others as Eastern influence spread.&lt;ref name=Hjerrild/&gt;

=== As the Lady of Ephesus ===
{{Main|Temple of Artemis}}
[[File:Statue of Artemis Ephesus.jpg|thumb|right|The Artemis of Ephesus, 1st century AD ([[Ephesus Archaeological Museum]])]]

At Ephesus in [[Ionia]], Turkey, her temple became one of the [[Seven Wonders of the Ancient World|Seven Wonders of the World]]. It was probably the best known center of her worship except for Delos. There the Lady whom the Ionians associated with Artemis through ''[[interpretatio graeca]]'' was worshipped primarily as a [[mother goddess]], akin to the Phrygian goddess [[Cybele]], in an ancient sanctuary where her [[cult image]] depicted the &quot;Lady of Ephesus&quot; adorned with multiple large beads. Excavation at the site of the ''Artemision'' in 1987–88 identified a multitude of tear-shaped [[amber]] beads that had been hung on the original wooden statue (''[[xoanon]]''), and these were probably carried over into later sculpted copies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.scribd.com/doc/98868504/49-MORRIS-Potnia-Aswiya-Anatolian-Greek-Religion|title=&quot;Potnia Aswia: Anatolian Contributions to Greek Religion&quot; by Sarah P. Morris|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140106033338/http://www.scribd.com/doc/98868504/49-MORRIS-Potnia-Aswiya-Anatolian-Greek-Religion|archivedate=2014-01-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Acts of the Apostles]], Ephesian metalsmiths who felt threatened by Saint Paul's preaching of Christianity, jealously rioted in her defense, shouting &quot;Great is Artemis of the Ephesians!&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Acts of the Apostles|Acts]] 19:28.&lt;/ref&gt; Of the 121 columns of her temple, only one composite, made up of fragments, still stands as a marker of the temple's location.

===Symbols===
* '''Bow and arrow'''

[[File:Ac artemisephesus.jpg|thumb|The site of the [[Temple of Artemis]] at Ephesus.]]

[[File:Didrachme de Ionie.jpg|thumb|right|Didrachm from [[Ephesus]], [[Ionia]], representing the goddess Artemis]]
[[File:Silver tetradrachm of Indo-Greek king Artemidoros.jpg|thumb|right|Silver tetradrachm of the [[Indo-Greek]] king [[Artemidoros]] (whose name means &quot;gift of Artemis&quot;), c. 85 BC, featuring Artemis with a drawn bow and a quiver on her back on the reverse of the coin]]

According to the [[Homeric Hymn]] to Artemis, she had golden bow and arrows, as her epithet was '''Khryselakatos''' (&quot;of the Golden Shaft&quot;) and '''Iokheira''' (&quot;showered by arrows&quot;). The arrows of Artemis could also bring sudden death and disease to girls and women. Artemis got her bow and arrow for the first time from The Kyklopes, as the one she asked from her father. The bow of Artemis also became the witness of Callisto's oath of her virginity. In later cult, the bow became the symbol of waxing moon.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.theoi.com/Olympios/ArtemisTreasures.html#Bow |title= Bow |author= |date= |work= |publisher= |accessdate= }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''Chariots'''
Artemis' chariot was made of gold and was pulled by four golden horned deer (Elaphoi Khrysokeroi). The bridles of her chariot were also made of gold.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.theoi.com/Olympios/ArtemisTreasures.html#Chariot |title= Chariot|author= |date= |work= |publisher= |accessdate= }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''Spears, nets, and lyre'''
&lt;!-- [[File:Artemis Spear.jpeg|thumb|right|upright=0.56|Artemis With A Hunting Spear, a statue at Venetia. {{deletable image-caption}}]]--&gt;
Although quite seldom, Artemis is sometimes portrayed with a hunting spear. Her cult in Aetolia, the Artemis Aetolian, showed her with a hunting spear. The description about Artemis' spear can be found in Ovid's Metamorphosis,{{Where|date=July 2011}} while Artemis with a fishing spear connected with her cult as a patron goddess of fishing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.theoi.com/Olympios/ArtemisTreasures.html#Spears |title= Spears|author= |date= |work= |publisher= |accessdate= }}&lt;/ref&gt; As a goddess of maiden dances and songs, Artemis is often portrayed with a lyre.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.theoi.com/Olympios/ArtemisGoddess.html#Dance |title= Dance |author= |date= |work= |publisher= |accessdate= }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''[[Deer]]'''
Deer were the only animals held sacred to Artemis herself. On seeing a deer larger than a bull with horns shining, she fell in love with these creatures and held them sacred. Deer were also the first animals she captured. She caught five golden horned deer called '''Elaphoi Khrysokeroi''' and harnessed them to her chariot.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1/&gt; The [[Labours of Hercules|third labour of Heracles]], commanded by [[Eurystheus]], consisted of catching the [[Cerynitian Hind]] alive. Heracles begged Artemis for forgiveness and promised to return it alive. Artemis forgave him but targeted Eurystheus for her wrath.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.theoi.com/Olympios/ArtemisTreasures.html#Kerynitian |title=Kerynitian |author= |date= |work= |publisher= |accessdate= }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''Hunting dog'''
Artemis got her hunting dogs from [[Pan (god)|Pan]] in the forest of Arcadia. Pan gave Artemis two black-and-white dogs, three reddish ones, and one spotted one – these dogs were able to hunt even lions. Pan also gave Artemis seven bitches of the finest Arcadian race. However, Artemis only ever brought seven dogs hunting with her at any one time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.theoi.com/Olympios/ArtemisTreasures.html#Pack|title=Pack |author= |date= |work= |publisher= |accessdate= }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''[[Bear]]'''
The sacrifice of a bear for Artemis started with the Brauron cult. Every year a girl between five and ten years of age was sent to Artemis' temple at Brauron. The Byzantine writer Suidos relayed the legend in Arktos e Brauroniois. A bear was tamed by Artemis and introduced to the people of Athens. They touched it and played with it until one day a group of girls poked the bear until it attacked them. A brother of one of the girls killed the bear, so Artemis sent a plague in revenge. The Athenians consulted an oracle to understand how to end the plague. The oracle suggested that, in payment for the bear's blood, no Athenian virgin should be allowed to marry until she had served Artemis in her temple ('played the bear for the goddess').&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.theoi.com/Cult/ArtemisCult.html |title=Cult |author= |date= |work= |publisher= |accessdate= }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''[[Boar]]'''
The boar is one of the favorite animals of the hunters, and also hard to tame. In honor of Artemis' skill, they sacrificed it to her. Oineus and Adonis were both killed by Artemis' boar.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.theoi.com/Olympios/ArtemisTreasures.html#Animals |title=Animals |author= |date= |work= |publisher= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''[[Guinea fowl]]'''
Artemis felt pity for the [[Meleagrids]] as they mourned for their lost brother, Meleagor, so she transformed them into Guinea Fowl to be her favorite animals.{{citation needed|date=November 2010}}
* '''Buzzard [[hawk]]'''
Hawks were the favored birds of many of the gods, Artemis included.{{citation needed|date=November 2010}}
* [[Arecaceae|Palm]] and [[Cypress]] were issued{{Clarify|date=August 2010}} to be her birthplace. Other plants sacred to Artemis are [[Amaranth]] and [[Asphodelus|Asphodel]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.theoi.com/Olympios/ArtemisTreasures.html#Plants|title= Plants |author= |date= |work= |publisher= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== In art ==
[[File:Bust of the goddess of Issa, Vis Museum, Croatia.JPG|thumb|right|Fourth century [[Praxiteles|Praxitelean]] bronze head of a goddess wearing a [[lunate]] crown, found at Issa ([[Vis (island)|Vis]], Croatia).]]

The oldest representations of Artemis in Greek Archaic art portray her as [[Potnia Theron]] (&quot;Queen of the Beasts&quot;): a winged goddess holding a stag and lioness in her hands, or sometimes a lioness and a lion. This winged Artemis lingered in ex-votos as [[Artemis Orthia]], with a sanctuary close by [[Sparta]].

In Greek classical art she is usually portrayed as a maiden huntress, young, tall and slim, clothed in a girl's short skirt,&lt;ref&gt;Homer portrayed Artemis as girlish in the ''[[Iliad]]''.&lt;/ref&gt; with hunting boots, a quiver, a bow&lt;ref&gt;Greek poets could not decide whether her bow was silver or gold: &quot;Over the shadowy hills and windy peaks she draws her golden bow.&quot; ([[Homeric Hymn]] to Artemis), and it is a golden bow as well in [[Ovid]], ''[[Metamorphoses]]'' 1.693, where her nymph's is of horn. &quot;And how often goddess, didst thou make trial of thy silver bow?&quot;, asks [[Callimachus]] for whom it is a [[Cydonia (ancient Greece)|Cydonian]] bow that the [[Cyclopes]] make for her (Callimachus, Hymn 3 to Artemis).&lt;/ref&gt; and arrows. Often, she is shown in the shooting pose, and is accompanied by a [[hunting dog]] or stag. When portrayed as a moon goddess, Artemis wore a long robe and sometimes a veil covered her head. Her darker side is revealed in some vase paintings, where she is shown as the death-bringing goddess whose arrows fell young maidens and women, such as the daughters of [[Niobe]].

Artemis was sometimes represented in Classical art with the crown of the [[crescent]] [[moon]], such as also found on [[Luna (goddess)|Luna]] and others.

On June 7, 2007, a Roman era bronze sculpture of ''[[Artemis and the Stag]]'' was sold at [[Sotheby's]] auction house in New York state by the [[Albright-Knox Art Gallery]] for $25.5 million.

== Legacy ==
===In astronomy===
[[105 Artemis]], the [[Artemis (crater)]], the [[Artemis Chasma]], the [[Artemis Corona]], and the [[Artemis program|Artemis lunar program]] have all been named after the goddess.

Artemis is the acronym for &quot;Architectures de bolometres pour des Telescopes a grand champ de vue dans le domaine sub-Millimetrique au Sol&quot;, a large [[bolometer]] camera in the [[Submillimetre astronomy|submillimeter]] range that was installed in 2010 at the [[Atacama Pathfinder Experiment]] (APEX), located in the [[Atacama desert|Atacama Desert]] in northern Chile.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.apex-telescope.org/instruments/pi/artemis/ |title=APEX – Artemis |publisher=Apex-telescope.org |date=2010-01-11 |accessdate=2013-03-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== In taxonomy ===
The [[Taxonomy (biology)|taxonomic]] genus ''[[Artemia]]'', which entirely comprises the family Artemiidae, derives from Artemis. ''Artemia'' are aquatic crustaceans known as brine shrimp, the best known species of which, ''[[Artemia salina]]'', or [[Sea Monkeys]], was first described by [[Carl Linnaeus]] in his ''[[Systema Naturae]]'' in 1758. ''Artemia'' live in salt lakes, and although they are almost never found in an open sea, they do appear along the [[Aegean Sea|Aegean coast]] near [[Ephesus]], where the [[Temple of Artemis]] once stood.

=== In Modern Spaceflight ===
The [[Artemis program]] is an ongoing [[List of human spaceflight programs|crewed spaceflight program]] carried out by [[NASA]], U.S. [[Private spaceflight|commercial spaceflight companies]], and international partners such as [[European Space Agency|ESA]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Artemis home&quot;&gt;[https://www.nasa.gov/specials/moon2mars/]. NASA. Accessed on 19 May 2019.&lt;/ref&gt; with the goal of landing &quot;the first woman and the next man&quot; on the [[lunar south pole]] region by 2024. NASA is calling this the Artemis program in honor of Apollo's twin sister in Greek mythology, the goddess of the Moon.&lt;ref name=&quot;Vice President Unveils NASA Spacecraft for Artemis 1 Lunar Mission on Moon Landing Anniversary&quot;&gt;[https://www.nasa.gov/press-release/vice-president-unveils-nasa-spacecraft-for-artemis-1-lunar-mission-on-moon-landing]. NASA. Accessed on 23 July 2019.&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{Portal|Ancient Greece|Myths|Religion}}
*[[Bendis]]
*[[Cybele]]
*[[Diana (mythology)]]
*[[Janus]]
*[[List of lunar deities]]
*[[Nemesis]]
*[[Palermo Fragment]]
*Regarding Tauropolos:
**[[Bull (mythology)]]
**[[Iphigenia in Tauris]]
**[[Taurus (constellation)#History and mythology|Taurus (Mythology)]]

== References and sources ==
;References
{{reflist|30em}}
;Sources
* [[Walter Burkert]], 1985. ''Greek Religion'' (Cambridge: [[Harvard University Press]])
*{{EB1911|wstitle=Actaeon|volume=1|page=157}}
* [[Robert Graves]] (1955) 1960. ''The Greek Myths'' (Penguin)
* [[Karl Kerenyi]], 1951. ''The Gods of the Greeks''
* [[Seppo Telenius]] (2005) 2006. ''Athena-Artemis'' (Helsinki: Kirja kerrallaan)
* [[LSJ]]
* A handbook of classical drama By Philip Whaley Harsh Page 220  {{ISBN|978-0-8047-0380-2}}

== External links ==
{{Commons|Artemis}}
* [http://www.theoi.com/Olympios/Artemis.html Theoi Project, Artemis, information on Artemis from original Greek and Roman sources, images from classical art].
* [http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/ptext?doc=Perseus:text:1999.04.0063&amp;query=label%3D%23290&amp;word=Amarysia ''A Dictionary of Greek and Roman Antiquities'' (1890) (eds. G. E. Marindin, William Smith, LLD, William Wayte)]
* [https://books.google.com/books?id=2garBSREfywC&amp;pg=PA27&amp;dq=eileithyia&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=G-Z8Tq-lKqKL4gSL7eiwDg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=10&amp;ved=0CFsQ6AEwCQ#v=onepage&amp;q=eileithyia&amp;f=false Fischer-Hansen T., Poulsen B. (eds.)  ''From Artemis to Diana: the goddess of man and beast''. Collegium Hyperboreum and Museum Tusculanum Press, Copenhagen, 2009]
* [http://warburg.sas.ac.uk/vpc/VPC_search/subcats.php?cat_1=5&amp;cat_2=86 Warburg Institute Iconographic Database: ca 1,150 images of Artemis]

{{Greek religion}}
{{Greek mythology (deities)}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Artemis| ]]&lt;!--please leave the empty space as standard--&gt;
[[Category:Animal goddesses]]
[[Category:Childhood goddesses]]
[[Category:Deities in the Iliad]]
[[Category:Lunar goddesses]]
[[Category:Hunting goddesses]]
[[Category:Mythological Greek archers]]
[[Category:Nature goddesses]]
[[Category:Greek Virgin goddesses]]
[[Category:Offspring of Zeus]]
[[Category:Plague gods]]
[[Category:Rape of Persephone]]
[[Category:Night goddesses]]
[[Category:Dogs in religion]]</text>
      <sha1>f66my7q4ti7m61ehqofl3a9c3msr14i</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
