  <page>
    <title>Democratic Progressive Party</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8845</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942329728</id>
      <parentid>942329696</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-24T01:19:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Chongkian</username>
        <id>8766034</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>same commons name</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Political party in Taiwan}}
{{Other uses}}
{{More citations needed|date=December 2010}}
{{Infobox political party
| name = Democratic Progressive Party{{efn native lang|tw|name=word1
  |t=民主進步黨
  |p=Mínzhǔ Jìnbù Dǎng
  |m=Bîn-tsú Tsìn-pōo Tóng
  |s=Mìn-chú Chin-phu Tóng}}
| logo = DPP-Taiwan.svg
| colorcode = {{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}
| leader = [[Tsai Ing-wen]] ([[President of the Republic of China]])
| chairman = [[Cho Jung-tai]]
| secretary_general = [[Luo Wen-jia]]
| foundation = {{Start date and age|1986|9|28|df=y}}
| ideology = [[Liberalism in Taiwan|Liberalism]]&lt;ref name=&quot;diplomat&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://thediplomat.com/2016/01/the-rise-of-taiwans-third-force/|website=The Diplomat|title=The Rise of Taiwan's 'Third Force'|date=January 6, 2016|last=van der Horst|first=Linda|accessdate=February 9, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;casey&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Time to Start Worrying about Taiwan|website=The National Interest|url=http://nationalinterest.org/feature/time-start-worrying-about-taiwan-16551|date=June 12, 2016|last=Casey|first=Michael|accessdate=February 9, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;[[Progressivism]]&lt;ref name=&quot;casey&quot;/&gt;&lt;br&gt;[[Social liberalism]]&lt;ref name=&quot;casey&quot;/&gt;&lt;br&gt;[[Taiwanese&amp;nbsp;independence]]&lt;ref name=&quot;casey&quot;/&gt;&lt;br&gt;[[Taiwanese nationalism]]&lt;ref name=&quot;casey&quot;/&gt;
| headquarters = [[Taipei]], [[Taiwan]]
| international = [[Liberal International]]
| website = {{URL|http://www.dpp.org.tw/|dpp.org.tw}}
| country = the Republic of China
| abbreviation = {{lang|zh-hant|民進黨}}
| flag = Flag of Democratic Progressive Party.svg
| think_tank = [http://www.dppnff.tw/ New Frontier Foundation]
| membership_year = 2014
| membership = {{Increase}} 335,643
| position = {{unbulleted list
  |[[Centrism|Centre]]&lt;ref&gt;{{bulleted list
|{{cite book|last1=Derbyshire|first1=J. Denis|last2=Derbyshire|first2=Ian|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=RyAGDAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA108|volume=1|title=Encyclopedia of World Political Systems|page=108|publisher=Routledge|date=15 April 2016|isbn=978-1-3174-7156-1}}
|{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=nFjPNItB6kAC|title=The Economist|page=58|publisher=Economist Newspaper Limited|date=2011}}
|{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/?id=nLAgAQAAMAAJ&amp;q=dpp+centrist|title=Business Asia|page=40|publisher=[[Business International Corporation]]|date=2001}}
|{{cite web|url=https://freedomhouse.org/report/freedom-world/2002/taiwan|title=Taiwan|work=[[Freedom in the World]] 2002|publisher=[[Freedom House]]|date=2012-01-13}}}}&lt;/ref&gt; to [[Centre-left politics|centre-left]]&lt;ref&gt;{{bulleted list
|{{cite journal|first=Dongtao|last=Qi|quote=Furthermore, the studies also suggest that the DPP, as a centre-left party opposed to the centre-right KMT, has been the leading force in addressing Taiwan's various social justice issues.|doi=10.1017/S0305741013001124|title=Globalization, Social Justice Issues, Political and Economic Nationalism in Taiwan: An Explanation of the Limited Resurgence of the DPP during 2008–2012|date=November 11, 2013|journal=[[The China Quarterly]]|volume=216|pages=1018&amp;ndash;1044}}
|{{cite journal|issn=1932-8036|url=https://ijoc.org/index.php/ijoc/article/view/2820|title=Celebrity Political Endorsement Effects: A Perspective on the Social Distance of Political Parties|first=Hsuan-Yi|last=Chou|volume=9|journal=[[International Journal of Communication]]}}
|{{cite journal|url=http://www.sppir.uav.ro/?p=53|url-access=|title=Taiwanese consciousness vs. Chinese consciousness: The national identity and the dilemma of polarizing society in Taiwan|first=Li-Li|last=Huang|pages=119–132|volume=1|issue=1|journal=Societal and Political Psychology International Review}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;economist&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=Hurry up: Taiwan's president has upset both business and workers |url=https://www.economist.com/asia/2018/05/26/taiwans-president-has-upset-both-business-and-workers |work=[[The Economist]] |accessdate=June 25, 2018 |date=May 26, 2018 |url-access=registration}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
| national = [[Pan-Green Coalition]]
| regional = [[Council of Asian Liberals and Democrats]]
| colours = {{Color box|{{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}|border=darkgray}} Green
| seats1_title = [[Legislative Yuan]]
| seats1 = {{Infobox political party/seats|62|113|hex={{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
| seats2_title = [[Special municipality (Taiwan)|Municipal]] mayors
| seats2 = {{Infobox political party/seats|2|6|hex={{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
| seats3_title = Magistrates/mayors
| seats3 = {{Infobox political party/seats|4|16|hex={{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
| seats4_title = Councillors
| seats4 = {{Infobox political party/seats|238|912|hex={{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
| seats5_title = [[Townships and county-administered cities|Township/city]] mayors
| seats5 = {{Infobox political party/seats|40|204|hex={{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
}}
{{Chinese
| title   = Democratic Progressive Party
| t       = {{linktext|民主|進步|黨}}|s={{linktext|民主|进步|党}}
| bpmf    = ㄇㄧㄣˊ ㄓㄨˇ ㄐㄧㄣˋ ㄅㄨˋ ㄉㄤˇ|w=Min²-chu³ Chin⁴-pu⁴ Tang³|p=Mínzhǔ Jìnbù Dǎng|tp=Mínjhǔ Jìnbù Dǎng|mps=Mínjǔ Jìnbù Dǎng|gr=Minjuu Jinnbuh Daang
| poj     = Bîn-chú Chìn-pō͘ Tóng|tl=Bîn-tsú Tsìn-pōo Tóng|h=Mìn-chú Chin-phu Tóng
| altname = Commonly abbreviated in Chinese as
| t2      = {{linktext|民進黨}}|s2 = {{linktext|民进党}}
| bpmf2   = ㄇㄧㄣˊ ㄐㄧㄣˋ ㄉㄤˇ|w2=Min²-chin⁴ Tang³|p2=Mínjìn Dǎng|tp2=Mínjìn Dǎng|mps2=Mínjìn Dǎng|gr2=Minjinn Daang
| poj2    = Bîn-chìn Tóng|tl2=Bîn-tsìn Tóng|h2=Mìn-chin Tóng
}}
{{Politics of Taiwan footer}}
The '''Democratic Progressive Party''' ('''DPP'''){{efn native lang|tw|name=word1}} is a [[Taiwanese nationalism|Taiwanese nationalist]] and [[Liberalism in Taiwan|liberal]] [[political party]] in [[Taiwan]].&lt;ref name=&quot;economist&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=解嚴後臺灣政黨的競爭策略：Downs 理論的再檢視 |url=http://www2.scu.edu.tw/politics/journal/doc/j323/1.pdf |website=Soochow University |accessdate=31 August 2019 |date=5 June 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=藍與綠 台灣選民的意識型態初探 |url=https://esc.nccu.edu.tw/files/paper/117_09747810.pdf |website=Election Study Center National Chengchi University |accessdate=31 August 2019 |date=May 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt; Controlling both the [[President of the Republic of China|Taiwan Presidency]] and the unicameral [[Legislative Yuan]], it is the majority [[ruling party]] and the dominant party in the [[Pan-Green Coalition]].

Founded in 1986, the DPP is one of two [[Major party|major parties]] in Taiwan, along with the historically dominant [[Kuomintang]]. It has traditionally been associated with strong advocacy of [[human rights]], [[anti-communism]], and a distinct [[Taiwanese identity]]. The incumbent President and former leader of the DPP, [[Tsai Ing-wen]], is the second member of the DPP to hold the office.&lt;ref name=&quot;chinapost.com.tw&quot;&gt;[http://www.chinapost.com.tw/taiwan/national/presidential-election/2012/01/14/329044/Tsai-steps.htm &quot;Tsai steps down as DPP chair after defeat in presidential poll&quot;] (14 January 2012). ''The China Post''. Retrieved 6 April 2018.&lt;/ref&gt;

The DPP is a long-term member of [[Liberal International]] and a founding member of the [[Council of Asian Liberals and Democrats]]. It represented Taiwan in the [[Unrepresented Nations and Peoples Organisation]]. The DPP and its affiliated parties are widely classified as [[socially liberal]] because of their strong support for human rights, including support for [[gender equality]], but they also advocate [[economic liberalism]] and a [[Taiwanese nationalism|Taiwanese national identity]]. In addition, the DPP is more willing to increase military expenditures, with foreign policy on closer ties with the United States and Japan.

==History==
The DPP's roots were in opposition to the [[Kuomintang]]'s [[One-party state|one-party]] [[Authoritarianism|authoritarian rule]]. It was founded as the [[Tangwai]] – or &quot;outside-the-KMT&quot; – movement. This movement culminated in the formation of the DPP as an alternative party on 28 September 1986 when eighteen founding members met at [[Grand Hotel (Taipei)|Grand Hotel Taipei]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Lu|first1=Lu Hsin-hui|last2=Kuo|first2=Chung-han|title=DPP should clarify its cross-strait policy: founding member|url=http://focustaiwan.tw/news/aipl/201609280026.aspx|accessdate=29 September 2016|agency=Central News Agency|date=28 September 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; A total of 132 people joined the party that day.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Chung|first1=Li-hua|last2=Chin|first2=Jonathan|title=DPP members say party must discuss core values|url=http://www.taipeitimes.com/News/taiwan/archives/2016/09/30/2003656223|accessdate=30 September 2016|work=Taipei Times|date=30 September 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The new party contested the [[1986 Taiwan legislative election|1986 election]] as &quot;nonpartisan&quot; when competing parties remained illegal under national law until the following year. The first members of the party drew heavily from the ranks of family members and defense lawyers of political prisoners as well as intellectuals and artists who had spent time abroad. Such individuals were strongly committed to political change that would ensure constitutional support in Republic of China's freedoms of speech, press, assembly, and association. The party did not at the outset give open support to an independent Republic of China's national identity – a move that could have invited a violent crackdown by the Republic of China's Kuomintang rulers. Its platform was pro-environment and pro-democracy. As more and more of its demands were met during the 1990s – such as the [[direct popular election]] of Republic of China's [[president of the Republic of China|president]] and all representatives in its [[Legislative Yuan]], and open discussion of Republic of China's repressive past as represented in the [[February 28 Incident]] and its long [[martial law]] aftermath – a greater variety of views could be advocated in the more liberal political atmosphere. Party members began openly promoting a national identity for Taiwan separate from China. The DPP doctrine also supported reform of the [[Constitution of the Republic of China|Constitution]] to change the name of Republic of China to &quot;Republic of Taiwan&quot;, though the DPP never aimed to amend the Constitution through a referendum.

Once the DPP had representation in the [[Legislative Yuan]] (LY, or Parliament), the party used the legislature as a forum to challenge the government. However, it did not emerge as a formidable force until 1991, when the elderly LY members elected from [[mainland China]] provinces in 1948 retired. As the major opposition in the LY, the DPP worked with then-President [[Lee Teng-hui]], the then-leader of KMT, to push through a series of amendments to transfer into a [[semi-presidential system]] (for example, Republic of China's [[premier of the Republic of China|premier]] would no longer have to be confirmed by the LY). Among the electoral reforms, a [[party-list proportional representation|PR list]] was adopted and aboriginal seats in the LY created.

===2000–2008: in minority government===
[[File:Chen Shui-bian from VOA.jpg|thumb|right|Former President Chen Shui-bian, the first DPP [[President of the Republic of China|President]] (2000-2008)]]
[[File:DPP-Taiwan-old.svg|thumb|right|Old DPP logo]]
The DPP won the presidency with the [[2000 Taiwan presidential election|election]] of [[Chen Shui-bian]] in March 2000 with a plurality, due to [[Pan-Blue]] voters splitting their vote between the Kuomintang and independent candidate [[James Soong]], ending more than half a century of KMT rule in Republic of China. Chen softened the party's stance on independence to appeal to moderate voters, appease the United States, and placate China. He also promised not to [[Four Noes and One Without|change the ROC state symbols or declare formal independence]] as long as the [[China|People's Republic of China]] did not attack Taiwan.

The DPP became the largest party having reached a plurality in the Legislative Yuan for the first time in 2002 following the [[2001 Taiwan legislative election|2001 legislative election]]. However, a majority coalition between the KMT, [[People First Party (Republic of China)|People First Party]], and [[New Party (Republic of China)|New Party]] prevented it from taking control of the chamber.

In 2004, [[President of the Republic of China|President]] Chen Shui-bian was re-elected by a narrow margin. He and Vice President [[Annette Lu]] had been involved in an assassination attempt only hours before the [[2004 Taiwan presidential election|election]]. The KMT candidate, [[Lien Chan]], demanded a recount the following morning. A judicial recount under the jurisdiction of a special panel of the High Court began on 10 May 2004 and ended on 18 May 2004. It was conducted by about 460 teams situated in 21 courthouses across the Taiwan area. Each team had seven members – one judge, two members each from the district court and the local government election authorities and two witnesses each representing the plaintiff ([[Pan-Blue Coalition]]) and the defendant ([[Pan-Green Coalition]]). Disputed votes were sent to High Court in Taipei for verification. After the recount, President Chen was confirmed the winner of the election by a smaller margin (25,563 as opposed to 29,518 originally). In the [[2004 Taiwan legislative election|later legislative election]], the Pan-Blue Coalition opposition retained control of the chamber.

The DPP suffered a significant election defeat in nationwide [[2005 Taiwanese local elections|local and county elections in December 2005]]. The pan-blue coalition captured 16 of 23 county and city government offices under the leadership of popular [[Taipei]] mayor and KMT Party Chairman [[Ma Ying-jeou]].

The results led to a shake up of the party leadership. [[Su Tseng-chang]] resigned as DPP chairman soon after election results were announced. Su had pledged to step down if the DPP lost either Taipei County or failed to win 10 of the 23 mayor/magistrate positions. Vice President [[Annette Lu]] was appointed acting DPP leader. Presidential Office Secretary-General [[Yu Shyi-kun]] was elected in a [[2006 Democratic Progressive Party chairmanship election|three-way race]] against legislator [[Chai Trong-rong]] and [[Wong Chin-chu]] with 54.4% of the vote.

Premier [[Frank Hsieh]], DPP election organizer and former mayor of [[Kaohsiung]] twice tendered a verbal resignation immediately following the election, but his resignation was not accepted by President Chen until 17 January 2006 after the DPP chairmanship election had concluded. The former DPP Chairman Su Tseng-chang was appointed to replace Hsieh as premier. Hsieh and his cabinet resigned en masse on January 24 to make way for Su and his new cabinet. President Chen had offered the position of Presidential Office Secretary-General (vacated by Su) to the departing premier, but Hsieh declined and left office criticizing President Chen for his tough line on dealing with China.

====Separate identity====
On 30 September 2007, the DPP approved a [[Resolution (law)|resolution]] asserting a separate identity from China and called for the enactment of a new constitution for a &quot;normal nation&quot;. It struck an accommodating tone by advocating general use of &quot;[[Taiwan]]&quot; as the country's name without calling for abandonment of the name Republic of China.&lt;ref&gt;[http://usatoday30.usatoday.com/news/world/2007-09-30-taiwan_N.htm AP, Republic of China Party Asserts Separate Identity]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:蔡英文官方元首肖像照.png|thumb|right|250px|[[Tsai Ing-wen]], the second DPP [[President of the Republic of China|President]] (2016-present) and the leader of the DPP since 2008, she is the first female leader of the DPP.]]
===2008–2016: back to opposition===
In the national elections held in early months of 2008, the DPP won less than 25% of the seats (38.2% vote share) in the new Legislative Yuan while its presidential candidate, former [[Kaohsiung]] mayor [[Frank Hsieh]], lost to KMT candidate [[Ma Ying-jeou]] by a wide margin (41.55% vs. 58.45%). In May, the DPP elected [[Tsai Ing-wen]] as the new leader, Tsai became the first female leader of the DPP and the first female leader to lead a major party in Taiwan.

The first months since backed to the opposition were dominated by press coverage of the travails of [[Chen Shui-bian]] and his wife [[Wu Shu-jen]]. On 15 August 2008, Chen resigned from the DPP and apologized: &quot;Today I have to say sorry to all of the DPP members and supporters. I let everyone down, caused you humiliation and failed to meet your expectations. My acts have caused irreparable damage to the party. I love the DPP deeply and am proud of being a DPP member. To express my deepest regrets to all DPP members and supporters, I announce my withdrawal from the DPP immediately. My wife Wu Shu-jen is also withdrawing from the party.&quot; DPP Chairperson followed with a public statement on behalf of the party: &quot;In regard to Chen and his wife's decision to withdraw from the party and his desire to shoulder responsibility for his actions as well as to undergo an investigation by the party's anti-corruption committee, we respect his decision and accept it.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pacificmagazine.net/news/2008/08/17/former-taiwan-president-resigns-from-party-over-corruption-charges pacificmagazine.net, Former Republic of China President Resigns From Party Over Corruption Charges]{{dead link|date=December 2016 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The DPP vowed to reflect on public misgivings towards the party. Chairperson Tsai insisted on the need for the party to remember its history, defend Republic of China's sovereignty and national security, and maintain its confidence.&lt;ref&gt;[http://tw.news.yahoo.com/article/url/d/a/080827/1/14w0t.html 中廣 via Yahoo! News, 媒體民調僅剩11趴　民進黨：虛心檢討]{{dead link|date=September 2017 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://tw.news.yahoo.com/article/url/d/a/080827/58/14wkq.html 央廣 via Yahoo! News, 民進黨支持度剩11%？ 蔡英文：覺得信心還在]{{dead link|date=September 2017 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The party re-emerged as a voice in Taiwan's political debate when Ma's administration reached the end of its first year in office. The DPP marked the anniversary with massive rallies in Taipei and Kaohsiung. Tsai's address to the crowd in Taipei on May 17 proclaimed a &quot;citizens' movement to protect Republic of China&quot; seeking to &quot;protect our democracy and protect Republic of China.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=http://dpptaiwan.wordpress.com/2009/05/17/tsai-ing-wens-opening-speech-at-the-517-rally/ | title=Tsai Ing-wen's Opening Speech at the 517 Rally| date=2009-05-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== 2016–present: in majority government ===
On [[2016 Taiwanese presidential election|16 January 2016]], Taiwan held a general election for its presidency and for the Legislative Yuan. The DPP gained the presidential seat, with the election of Tsai Ing-wen, who received 56.12% of the votes, while her opponent [[Eric Chu]] gained 31.2%.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title = Taiwan gets first female President as DPP sweeps election|url = http://www.channelnewsasia.com/news/asiapacific/taiwan-gets-first-female/2432040.html|website = Channel NewsAsia|access-date = 2016-01-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, the DPP gained a majority of the Legislative Yuan, [[2016 Taiwanese legislative election|winning 68 seats in the 113-seat legislature]], up from 40 in 2012 election, thus giving them the majority for the first time in its history.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |last=Hsiao |first=Alison |date=17 Jan 2016 |title = ELECTIONS: DPP to control Legislative Yuan |url = http://www.taipeitimes.com/News/taiwan/archives/2016/01/17/2003637414 |newspaper=Taipei Times |page=6}}&lt;/ref&gt; Tsai won reelection to the presidency on [[2020 Taiwanese presidential election|11 January 2020]], and the Democratic Progressive Party retained its legislative majority, [[2020 Taiwanese legislative election|winning 61 seats]].

=={{anchor|Policies|Ideology|Political views|Political positions|Political ideology}}Policies==
Programs supported by the party include moderate [[social welfare]] policies involving the rights of women, senior citizens, children, young people, labor, minorities, indigenous peoples, farmers, and other disadvantaged sectors of the society. Furthermore, its platform includes a legal and political order based on human rights and democracy; balanced economic and financial administration; fair and open social welfare; educational and cultural reform; and, independent defence and peaceful foreign policy with closer ties to United States and Japan. For these reasons, it used to be considered a party of the [[center-left]] economically though its base consisted largely of the [[middle class]]. The party also has a [[social liberal]] stance that includes support for [[gender equality]] and [[LGBT rights in Taiwan|LGBT rights]] (the party have supported [[Same-sex marriage in Taiwan|same-sex marriage]] under Tsai's leadership), and also have a strong [[social conservative]] base, including support from the [[Presbyterian Church in Taiwan]]. Since the democratisation of Taiwan in the 1990s, the DPP has had its strongest performance in the [[Hokkien]]-speaking counties and cities of Taiwan, compared with the predominantly [[Hakka]] and [[Mandarin Chinese|Mandarin]]-speaking counties, that tend to support the [[Kuomintang]].

The primary political axis in Taiwan involves the issue of [[Taiwan independence]] versus eventual [[Cross-Strait Unification|unification with China]]. Although the differences tend to be portrayed in polarized terms, both major coalitions have developed modified, nuanced and often complex positions. Though opposed in the philosophical origins, the practical differences between such positions can sometimes be subtle.

The current official position of the party is that Taiwan is an independent and sovereign country whose territory consists of Taiwan and its surrounding smaller islands and whose sovereignty derives only from the ROC citizens living in Taiwan (similar philosophy of [[self-determination]]), based on the &quot;[[Resolution on Taiwan's Future]]&quot; in 1999. It considers Taiwan as an independent nation under the name of Republic of China, making a formal declaration of independence unnecessary. The DPP rejects the so-called &quot;[[One China principle]]&quot; defined in 1992 as the basis for official diplomatic relations with the PRC and advocates a Taiwanese national identity which is separate from mainland China. The DPP argues that its efforts to promote a Taiwanese national identity are merely an effort to normalize a Taiwanese identity repressed during years of authoritarian Kuomintang rule. The DPP also differs from the KMT on foreign and defense policies in that the DPP considers relations with the United States, Japan, and European states, among other democratic countries, crucial for Taiwan's security.

In contrast, the KMT or pan-blue coalition agrees that the Republic of China is an independent and sovereign country that is not part of the PRC, but argues that a one China principle (with different definitions across the strait) can be used as the basis for talks with China. The KMT also opposes the purposes of Taiwan independence and argues that efforts to establish a Taiwanese national identity separated from the Chinese national identity are unnecessary and needlessly provocative. Some KMT conservative officials have called efforts from DPP &quot;[[anti-China]]&quot; (opposing migrants from mainland China, whom DPP officials did not recognize as Taiwanese, but Chinese). At the other end of the political spectrum, the acceptance by the DPP of the symbols of the Republic of China is opposed by the [[Taiwan Solidarity Union]].

The first years of the DPP as the ruling party drew accusations from the opposition that, as a self-styled Taiwanese [[nationalism|nationalist]] party, the DPP was itself inadequately sensitive to the ethnographic diversity of Taiwan's population. Where the KMT had been guilty of Chinese [[chauvinism]], the critics charged, the DPP might offer nothing more as a remedy than [[Hoklo people|Hoklo]] chauvinism.

China has maintained a hostile position toward the DPP. It has made some efforts to moderate its tone since passing its [[Anti-Secession Law]] in 2005 to prevent a popular backlash from Taiwan's voters. In 2008, China stated it was willing to negotiate with any party in Taiwan that &quot;accepts the so-called [[1992 consensus]]&quot; (the consensus agreed by the KMT and the Communist Party of China). The DPP denies the existence of the 1992 consensus between China and Taiwan and demands a greater democratic opening in China.

The deep-rooted hostility between [[Taiwanese aborigines]] and (Taiwanese) Hoklo, and the aboriginal communities effective KMT networks contribute to aboriginal skepticism against the DPP and the aboriginals tendency to vote for the KMT.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Damm|first1=Jens|editor1-last=Damm|editor1-first=Jens|editor2-last=Lim|editor2-first=Paul|title=European perspectives on Taiwan|date=2012|publisher=Springer VS|location=Wiesbaden|isbn=9783531943039|page=95|chapter=Multiculturalism in Taiwan and the Influence of Europe}}&lt;/ref&gt; Aboriginals have criticized politicians for abusing the &quot;indigenization&quot; movement for political gains, such as aboriginal opposition to the DPP's &quot;rectification&quot; by recognizing the Truku for political reasons, where the Atayal and Seediq slammed the Truku for their name rectification.&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=0t_CU9gmi8cC&amp;pg=PA220&amp;dq=truku&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=P0QfVbq1MomWsAXRt4SADA&amp;ved=0CD4Q6AEwBg#v=onepage&amp;q=truku&amp;f=false ed. Vinding 2004], p. 220.&lt;/ref&gt; In 2008, the majority of mountain townships voted for [[Ma Ying-jeou]].&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=ZOusAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA28#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Simon 2011], p. 28.&lt;/ref&gt; However, the DPP share of the aboriginal vote has been rising.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://frozengarlic.wordpress.com/2014/11/30/dpp-vote-share-in-aboriginal-townships/|title=DPP vote share in Aboriginal townships|date=2014-11-30|website=Frozen Garlic|access-date=2017-04-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.nationalia.info/new/10792/taiwan-president-to-apologize-to-aboriginal-people-promises-law-on-autonomy|title=Taiwan president to apologize to Aboriginal people, promises law on autonomy|work=Nationalia|access-date=2017-04-10|language=ca}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Structure==
[[File:Huashan Business Building 20130118.jpg|thumb|DPP headquarters at Huashan Business Building Level 10 in [[Taipei]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=http://dpptaiwan.blogspot.com/p/contact.html |title = Contact}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
The National Party Congress selects, for two year terms, the 30 members of the Central Executive Committee and the 11 members of the Central Review Committee. The Central Executive Committee, in turn, chooses the 10 members of the Central Standing Committee. The DPP since 2012 also has a &quot;China Affairs Committee&quot; to deal with [[Cross-Strait relations]]; the name caused some controversy within the party and in the Taiwan media, with critics suggesting that &quot;Mainland Affairs Committee&quot; or &quot;Cross-Strait Affairs Committee&quot; would show less of a hostile &quot;[[One Country on Each Side]]&quot; attitude.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://english.peopledaily.com.cn/90785/8031251.html|title=China Focus: &quot;China Affairs Committee&quot; negative to Taiwan opposition party: Taiwan media|agency=Xinhua|location=Taipei|date=2012-11-22|accessdate=2012-11-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

For many years the DPP officially recognized several factions within its membership, such as the [[New Tide faction]] ({{Script|hanb|新潮流系}}), the [[Formosa faction]] ({{Script|hanb|美麗島系}}), the [[Justice Alliance faction]] ({{Script|hanb|正義連線系}}) and [[Welfare State Alliance faction]] ({{Script|hanb|福利國系}}). Each faction endorsed slightly different policies. The factions were often generationally identifiable, representing individuals who had entered the party at different times. In 2006, the party ended recognition of factions.&lt;ref name=&quot;fractions&quot;&gt;{{cite news |first=Jewel |last=Huang |date=24 Jul 2006 |url=http://www.taipeitimes.com/News/front/archives/2006/07/24/2003320124 |newspaper=Taipei Times |title=DPP votes to do away with factions |page=1}}&lt;/ref&gt; The factions have since stated that they will comply with the resolution. However, the factions are still referred to by name in national media.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Engbarth|first1=Dennis|title=DPP campaign aims to bring people 'Happiness and Pride'|url=http://www.etaiwannews.com/etn/news_content.php?id=1322395&amp;lang=eng_news&amp;cate_img=logo_taiwan&amp;cate_rss=TAIWAN_eng|accessdate=30 January 2016|work=Taiwan News|date=19 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Su|first1=Justin|last2=Yeh|first2=Sophia|last3=Wen|first3=Kui-hsiang|last4=Chang|first4=S. C.|title=New Tide remains largest faction inside DPP|url=http://focustaiwan.tw/search/201207150023.aspx?q=bear|accessdate=31 January 2016|agency=Central News Agency|date=15 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Chair===
{{main|List of leaders of the Democratic Progressive Party}}
* Current Chair: [[Cho Jung-tai]] (since January 2019)

===Secretary-General===
{{main|List of Secretaries-General of the Democratic Progressive Party}}
* Current Secretary-General: [[Luo Wen-jia]] (since January 2019)

===Legislative Yuan leader (caucus leader)===
* [[Shih Ming-teh]] (1 February 1993–1 February 2002)
* [[Ker Chien-ming]] (since 1 February 2002)

==Election results==
[[File:2007TaipeiAudioVideoFair JTCho.jpg|thumb|[[Cho Jung-tai]], the Chairperson of DPP.]]

===Presidential elections===
{| class=wikitable
|-
! Election
! Candidate
! Running mate
! Total votes
! Share of votes
! Outcome
|-
![[2020 Taiwan presidential election|2020]]
| Tsai Ing-wen
|[[William Lai|Lai Ching‑te]]
| 8,170,231
| 57.1%
|{{Yes|Elected}}
|-
![[2016 Taiwan presidential election|2016]]
| Tsai Ing-wen
|[[Chen Chien-jen]] ([[File:Black-nill.png|15x15px]] {{small|[[Independent (politician)|Ind.]]}})
| 6,894,744
| 56.3%
|{{Yes|Elected}}
|-
![[2012 Taiwan presidential election|2012]]
|[[Tsai Ing-wen]]
|[[Su Jia-chyuan]]
| 6,093,578
| 45.6%
|{{No|Defeated}}
|-
![[2008 Taiwan presidential election|2008]]
|[[Frank Hsieh|Frank Hsieh Chang-ting]]
|[[Su Tseng-chang]]
| 5,445,239
| 41.5%
|{{No|Defeated}}
|-
![[2004 Taiwan presidential election|2004]]
| Chen Shui-bian
| Annette Lu Hsiu-lien
| 6,446,900
| 50.1%
|{{Yes|Elected}}
|-
![[2000 Taiwan presidential election|2000]]
|[[Chen Shui-bian]]
|[[Annette Lu|Annette Lu Hsiu-lien]]
| 4,977,737
| 39.3%
|{{Yes|Elected}}
|-
! [[1996 Taiwan presidential election|1996]]
| [[Peng Ming-min]]
| [[Frank Hsieh|Frank Hsieh Chang-ting]]
| 2,274,586
| 21.1%
|{{No|Defeated}}
|}

===Legislative elections===
&lt;!--Note: Legislative Yuan is the legislature of the Republic of China only. The members of the Executive Yuan, which can form the government of the Republic of China, are appointed by the President of the Republic of China and irrelevant to the Legislative Yuan.--&gt;{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|+
!Election
!Total seats won
!Total votes
!Share of votes
!Changes
!Party leader
!Status
!President
|-
![[2020 Taiwanese legislative election|2020]]
|{{Composition bar|61|113|{{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
|4,811,241
|33.98%
|{{decrease}} 7 seats
|[[Cho Jung-tai]]
|{{yes|Majority}}
|[[Tsai Ing-wen]] {{DPP/logo}}
|-
![[2016 Taiwan general election|2016]]
|{{Composition bar|68|113|{{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
|5,370,953
|44.1%
|{{increase}} 28 seats
|[[Tsai Ing-wen]]
|{{yes|Majority}}
|[[Tsai Ing-wen]] {{DPP/logo}}
|-
![[2012 Taiwan legislative election|2012]]
|{{Composition bar|40|113|hex={{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
|4,556,526
|34.6%
|{{increase}} 13 seats
|[[Tsai Ing-wen]]
|{{no|Minority}}
|[[Ma Ying-jeou]] {{KMT/logo}}
|-
![[2008 Taiwan legislative election|2008]]
|{{Composition bar|27|113|hex={{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
|3,775,352
|38.2%
|{{decrease}} 62 seats
|Chen Shui-bian
|{{no|Minority}}
|Chen Shui-bian {{DPP/logo}}
|-
![[2004 Taiwan legislative election|2004]]
|{{Composition bar|89|225|hex={{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
|3,471,429
|37.9%
|{{increase}} 2 seats
|Chen Shui-bian
|{{no|Minority}}
|Chen Shui-bian {{DPP/logo}}
|-
![[2001 Taiwan legislative election|2001]]
|{{Composition bar|87|225|hex={{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
|3,447,740
|36.6%
|{{increase}} 21 seats
|[[Chen Shui-bian]] {{DPP/logo}}
|{{no|Minority}}
|Chen Shui-bian {{DPP/logo}}
|-
![[1998 Taiwan legislative election|1998]]
|{{Composition bar|70|225|hex={{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
|2,966,834
|29.6%
|{{increase}} 16 seats
|[[Lin Yi-hsiung]]
|{{no|Minority}}
|[[Lee Teng-hui]] {{KMT/logo}}
|-
![[1995 Taiwan legislative election|1995]]
|{{Composition bar|54|164|hex={{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
|3,132,156
|33.2%
|{{increase}} 3 seats
|[[Shih Ming-teh]]
|{{no|Minority}}
|[[Lee Teng-hui]] {{KMT/logo}}
|-
![[1992 Taiwan legislative election|1992]]
|{{Composition bar|51|161|hex={{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
|2,944,195
|31.0%
|{{increase}} 30 seats
|[[Hsu Hsin-liang]]
|{{no|Minority}}
|[[Lee Teng-hui]] {{KMT/logo}}
|}

===Local elections===
{| class=wikitable
|-
! Election
! Magistrates and mayors
! Councillors
! Township/city mayors
! Township/city council representatives
! Village chiefs
! Party leader
|-
![[2018 Taiwanese local elections|2018]]&lt;br&gt;{{small|unified}}
|{{Composition bar|6|22|hex={{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
|{{Composition bar|238|912|hex={{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
|{{Composition bar|40|204|hex={{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
|{{Composition bar|151|2148|hex={{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
|{{Composition bar|285|7744|hex={{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
| Tsai Ing-wen
|-
![[2014 Taiwanese local elections|2014]]&lt;br&gt;{{small|unified}}
|{{Composition bar|13|22|hex={{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
|{{Composition bar|291|906|hex={{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
|{{Composition bar|54|204|hex={{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
|{{Composition bar|194|2137|hex={{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
|{{Composition bar|390|7836|hex={{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
| Tsai Ing-wen
|-
![[2010 Taiwanese municipal elections|2010]]&lt;br&gt;{{small|municipalities only}}
|{{Composition bar|2|5|hex={{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
|{{Composition bar|130|314|hex={{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
| {{n/a}}
| {{n/a}}
|{{Composition bar|220|3757|hex={{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
| Tsai Ing-wen
|-
![[2009 Taiwanese local elections|2009]]
|{{Composition bar|4|17|hex={{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
|{{Composition bar|128|587|hex={{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
|{{Composition bar|34|211|hex={{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
| {{n/a}}
| {{n/a}}
| [[Tsai Ing-wen]]
|-
![[2006 Taiwanese municipal elections|2006]]&lt;br&gt;{{small|municipalities only}}
|{{Composition bar|1|2|hex={{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
|{{Composition bar|33|96|hex={{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
| {{n/a}}
| {{n/a}}
| {{n/a}}
| Chen Shui-bian
|-
![[2005 Taiwanese local elections|2005]]
|{{Composition bar|6|23|hex={{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
|{{Composition bar|192|901|hex={{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
|{{Composition bar|35|319|hex={{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
| {{n/a}}
| {{n/a}}
| Chen Shui-bian
|-
![[2002 Taiwanese municipal elections|2002]]&lt;br&gt;{{small|municipalities only}}
|{{Composition bar|1|2|hex={{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
|{{Composition bar|31|96|hex={{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
| {{n/a}}
| {{n/a}}
| {{n/a}}
| Chen Shui-bian
|-
![[2001 Taiwanese local elections|2001-2002]]
|{{Composition bar|9|23|hex={{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
|{{Composition bar|147|897|hex={{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
|{{Composition bar|28|319|hex={{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
| {{n/a}}
| {{n/a}}
| [[Chen Shui-bian]]
|-
![[1998 Taiwanese municipal elections|1998]]&lt;br&gt;{{small|municipalities only}}
|{{Composition bar|1|2|hex={{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
|{{Composition bar|28|96|hex={{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
| {{n/a}}
| {{n/a}}
| {{n/a}}
| [[Lin Yi-hsiung]]
|-
![[1997 Taiwanese local elections|1997-1998]]
|{{Composition bar|12|23|hex={{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
|{{Composition bar|114|886|hex={{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
|{{Composition bar|28|319|hex={{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
| {{n/a}}
| {{n/a}}
| [[Hsu Hsin-liang]]
|-
![[1994 Taiwanese municipal elections|1994]]&lt;br&gt;{{small|province-level only}}
| {{Composition bar|1|3|hex={{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
| {{Composition bar|52|175|hex={{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
| {{n/a}}
| {{n/a}}
| {{n/a}}
| [[Shih Ming-teh]]
|}

===National Assembly elections===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Election
! Total seats won
! Total votes
! Share of votes
! Changes
! Party leader
! Status
! President
|-
![[2005 Taiwan National Assembly election|2005]]
| {{Composition bar|127|300|hex={{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
| 1,647,791
| 42.52%
| {{increase}}28 seats
| Annette Lu Hsiu-lien
| {{partial|Plurality}}
| Chen Shui-bian {{DPP/logo}}
|-
![[1996 Taiwan National Assembly election|1996]]
|{{Composition bar|127|334|hex={{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
| 3,121,423
| 29.9%
|{{increase}}33 seats
| Shih Ming-teh
| {{no|Minority}}
| Lee Teng-hui {{KMT/logo}}
|-
![[1991 Taiwan National Assembly election|1991]]
|{{Composition bar|66|325|hex={{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}}}
| 2,036,271
| 23.3%
|{{increase}}66 seats
| Huang Shin-chieh
| {{no|Minority}}
| [[Lee Teng-hui]] {{KMT/logo}}
|}

==See also==
* [[Anti-Communism]]
* [[Liberalism in Taiwan]]
* [[Human rights in Taiwan]]
* [[Culture of Taiwan]]
* [[Taiwan independence movement]]
* [[Taiwanese people]]
* [[Taiwanese identity]]
* [[Resolution on Taiwan's Future]]
* [[Referendums in Taiwan]]
* [[Foreign relations of Taiwan#International disputes|Foreign relations of Taiwan]]
* [[February 28 Incident]]
* [[Formosa Incident]]
* [[Sunflower Student Movement]]

== Notes ==
=== Words in native languages ===
{{notelist-ur}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Commons category}}
* [http://www.dpp.org.tw/ DPP Official website]
* [http://etd.lib.nsysu.edu.tw/ETD-db/ETD-search/getfile?URN=etd-1223103-143943&amp;filename=etd-1223103-143943.pdf Academic thesis on the factions within DPP]

{{Democratic Progressive Party}}
{{Taiwanese political parties}}
{{interlib}}

[[Category:Democratic Progressive Party| ]]
[[Category:1986 establishments in Taiwan]]
[[Category:Liberal parties in Asia]]
[[Category:Political parties in Taiwan]]
[[Category:Taiwan independence movement]]
[[Category:Political parties established in 1986]]
[[Category:Pro-independence parties]]
[[Category:Social liberal parties]]
[[Category:Populist parties]]</text>
      <sha1>1vmggasb1192y6m1uaa7lzyielclssf</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
