  <page>
    <title>Distributism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8805</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942762414</id>
      <parentid>936217304</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-26T17:54:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>2pou</username>
        <id>13390353</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Doctrine in opposition to both socialism and capitalism}}
{{redirect|Distributivism|the algebraic concept|Distributivity}}
{{use dmy dates|date=July 2013}}
{{economic systems sidebar|expanded=by ideology}}
{{Christian democracy sidebar|expanded=Ideas}}
{{social teachings of the popes}}
{{basic forms of government}}
'''Distributism''' is an economic theory asserting that the world's productive assets should be widely owned rather than concentrated.&lt;ref name=Zwick/&gt;

Developed in Europe in the late 19th and early 20th centuries, distributism was based upon the principles of [[Catholic social teaching]], especially the teachings of [[Pope Leo XIII]] in his [[encyclical]] ''[[Rerum novarum]]'' (1891) and [[Pope Pius XI]] in ''[[Quadragesimo anno]]'' (1931).&lt;ref&gt;Coulter, Michael (2007). ''Encyclopedia of Catholic Social Thought, Social Science and Social Policy''. [[Scarecrow Press]]. p. 85. {{ISBN|978-0-8108-5906-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;McConkey, Dale; Lawler, Peter (2003). ''Faith, Morality, and Civil Society''. [[Lexington Books]]. p. 50. {{ISBN|978-0-7391-0483-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Patrick Allitt|Allitt, Patrick]] (2000). ''Catholic Converts: British and American Intellectuals Turn to Rome''. [[Cornell University Press]]. p. 206. {{ISBN|978-0-8014-8663-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; It views both [[capitalism]] and [[socialism]] as equally flawed and exploitative, and it favors economic mechanisms such as [[cooperative]]s and member-owned [[mutual organization]]s as well as [[small business]]es, and large-scale [[competition law|antitrust regulations]].

Some [[Christian democratic]] political parties have advocated distributism in their economic policies.
&lt;!-- In the early 21st century, some observers speculated on [[Pope Francis]]'s position on distributism after he denounced unfettered capitalism in his apostolic exhortation ''[[Evangelii gaudium]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theamericanconservative.com/articles/pope-francis-needs-distributism/|title=Pope Francis Needs Distributism|website=theamericanconservative.com|accessdate=8 August 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://blog.acton.org/archives/67566-pope-doesnt-need-distributism-nobody.html|title=No, the Pope Doesn’t Need Distributism (Because Nobody Does)|date=4 April 2014|website=acton.org|accessdate=8 August 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://skellmeyer.blogspot.com/2013/11/pope-francis-condemns-distributism.html|title=The Fifth Column: Pope Francis Condemns Distributism|first=Steve|last=Kellmeyer|date=28 November 2013|website=skellmeyer.blogspot.com|accessdate=8 August 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://catholicozarks.blogspot.com/2013/11/pope-francis-is-distributist.html|title=Catholic in the Ozarks: Is Pope Francis a Distributist?|first=Shane|last=Schaetzel|date=26 November 2013|website=catholicozarks.blogspot.com|accessdate=8 August 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.firstthings.com/web-exclusives/2013/11/lets-listen-to-pope-francis-on-economics|title=Let’s Listen to Pope Francis on Economics – Pascal-Emmanuel Gobry|website=firstthings.com|accessdate=8 August 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.frontporchrepublic.com/2014/04/pope-francis-distributism/|title=Pope Francis and Distributism|website=www.frontporchrepublic.com|accessdate=8 August 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.onreligion.co.uk/neither-capitalism-nor-communism-distributism/Neither|title=Neither Capitalism nor Communism: Distributism|date=15 April 2014|website=onreligion.co.uk|accessdate=8 August 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''[[Evangelii gaudium]]'', quote: &quot;Just as the commandment 'Thou shalt not kill' sets a clear limit in order to safeguard the value of human life, today we also have to say 'thou shalt not' to an economy of exclusion and inequality. Such an economy kills... A new tyranny is thus born, invisible and often virtual, which unilaterally and relentlessly imposes its own laws and rules. To all this we can add widespread corruption and self-serving tax evasion, which has taken on worldwide dimensions. The thirst for power and possessions knows no limits.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

I commented out this section. If there should, one time, be a future &quot;Distributism and the Catholic Magisterium&quot; section, we can put it there; so I have not deleted the sources put here together. Still, all in all the well-sourced statement is that the present Pope has criticized Capitalism (as have all Popes before him, but I digress), and that some observers have taken this as occasion to speculate on his stand towards Distributism. In other words: a rather long sentence with preciously little actual content. &quot;Some observers speculated&quot;. For a ''lead'' it is entirely out of place. !--&gt;

== Overview ==
According to distributists, [[Right to property|property ownership]] is a fundamental right,&lt;ref&gt;Shiach, Morag (2004). ''Modernism, Labour and Selfhood in British Literature and Culture, 1890–1930''. [[Cambridge University Press]]. p. 224. {{ISBN|978-0-521-83459-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[means of production]] should be spread as widely as possible, rather than being centralized under the control of the state ([[state capitalism]]/[[state socialism]]), a few individuals ([[plutocracy]]), or corporations ([[corporatocracy]]). Distributism, therefore, advocates a society marked by widespread property ownership.&lt;ref name=Zwick&gt;Zwick, Mark and Louise (2004). ''The Catholic Worker Movement: Intellectual and Spiritual Origins ''. [[Paulist Press]]. p. 156. {{ISBN|978-0-8091-4315-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Co-operatives|Co-operative]] economist [[Race Mathews]] argues that such a system is key to bringing about a just [[social order]].&lt;ref&gt;Gibson-Graham, J.K. (2006). ''A Postcapitalist Politics''. [[University of Minnesota Press]]. p. 224. {{ISBN|978-0-8166-4804-7}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Distributism has often been described in opposition to both [[socialism]] and [[capitalism]],&lt;ref&gt;Boyle, David; Simms, Andrew (2009). ''The New Economics''. [[Routledge]]. p. 20. {{ISBN|978-1-84407-675-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Novak, Michael; Younkins, Edward W. (2001). ''Three in One: Essays on Democratic Capitalism, 1976–2000''. [[Rowman and Littlefield]]. p. 152. {{ISBN|978-0-7425-1171-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; which distributists see as equally flawed and exploitative.&lt;ref name=&quot;Prentiss, Craig R. 2008 p. 77&quot;&gt;Prentiss, Craig R. (2008). ''Debating God's Economy: Social Justice in America on the Eve of Vatican II''. [[Penn State University Press]]. p. 77. {{ISBN|978-0-271-03341-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, some distributists argue that socialism is the logical conclusion of capitalism as capitalism's concentrated powers eventually capture the state, resulting in a form of socialism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.frontporchrepublic.com/2012/12/why-isnt-romania-rich/|title=Why Isn’t Romania Rich?|website=www.frontporchrepublic.com|accessdate=8 August 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hsnsw.asn.au/Distributism.html|title=Distributism as an equalitarian economic policy.|website=www.hsnsw.asn.au|accessdate=8 August 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thomas Storck argues: &quot;Both socialism and capitalism are products of the [[Age of Enlightenment|European Enlightenment]] and are thus modernizing and anti-traditional forces. In contrast, distributism seeks to subordinate economic activity to human life as a whole, to our spiritual life, our intellectual life, our family life.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Storck, Thomas. &quot;Capitalism and Distributism: two systems at war,&quot; in ''Beyond Capitalism &amp; Socialism''. Tobias J. Lanz, ed. IHS Press, 2008. p. 75&lt;/ref&gt; A few distributists&lt;ref&gt;Dorothy, Day. ''On Pilgrimage''. Wm. B. Eerdmans Publishing Co., 1999. p. 40.&lt;/ref&gt; were influenced by the economic ideas of [[Pierre-Joseph Proudhon]] and his [[Mutualism (economic theory)|mutualist]] economic theory,&lt;ref&gt;McKay, Iain. ''An Anarchist FAQ Volume One''. AK Press, 2007. p. 75&lt;/ref&gt; and therefore the lesser-known [[anarchist]] branch of distributism of [[Dorothy Day]] and the [[Catholic Worker Movement]] could be considered a form of free-market [[libertarian socialism]]&lt;ref&gt;McKay, Iain. ''An Anarchist FAQ Volume One''. AK Press, 2007. p. 23&lt;/ref&gt; due to their opposition to both state capitalism and state socialism.

Some have seen it more as an aspiration, which has been successfully realised in the short term by commitment to the principles of [[subsidiarity]] and [[social solidarity|solidarity]] (these being built into financially independent local [[cooperative]]s and small [[family business]]es), although proponents also cite such periods as the [[Middle Ages]] as examples of the historical long-term viability of distributism.&lt;ref&gt;Hilaire Belloc, &quot;The Servile Institution Dissolved,&quot; ''The Servile State'', (1913; reprint, Indianapolis, IN: Liberty Fund, 1977), 71–83.&lt;/ref&gt; Particularly influential in the development of distributist theory were [[Catholic Church|Catholic]] authors [[G. K. Chesterton]] and [[Hilaire Belloc]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Prentiss, Craig R. 2008 p. 77&quot;/&gt; the [[G. K. Chesterton#.22Chesterbelloc.22|''Chesterbelloc'']], two of distributism's earliest and strongest proponents.&lt;ref&gt;Fitzgerald, Ross et al. (2003). ''The Pope's Battalions: Santamaria, Catholicism and the Labor Split''. [[University of Queensland Press]]. p. 21. {{ISBN|978-0-7022-3389-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Riff, Michael A. 1990 p. 35&quot;&gt;Riff, Michael A. (1990). ''Dictionary of Modern Political Ideologies''. [[Manchester University Press]]. p. 35. {{ISBN|978-0-7190-3289-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Background ==
The mid-to-late 19th century witnessed an increase in popularity of [[political Catholicism]] across [[Europe]].&lt;ref&gt;Adams, Ian (1993). ''Political Ideology Today''. Manchester University Press. pp. 59–60. {{ISBN|978-0-7190-3347-6}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to historian Michael A. Riff, a common feature of these movements was opposition not only to [[secularism]], but also to both capitalism and socialism.&lt;ref name=&quot;Riff, Michael A. 1990 p. 35&quot;/&gt; In 1891 [[Pope Leo XIII]] promulgated ''[[Rerum novarum]]'', in which he addressed the &quot;misery and wretchedness pressing so unjustly on the majority of the working class&quot; and spoke of how &quot;a small number of very rich men&quot; had been able to &quot;lay upon the teeming masses of the laboring poor a yoke little better than that of slavery itself&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Leo XIII, ''Rerum novarum'', 3.&lt;/ref&gt; Affirmed in the encyclical was the right of all men to own property,&lt;ref&gt;Leo XIII, ''Rerum novarum'',  6.&lt;/ref&gt; the necessity of a system that allowed &quot;as many as possible of the people to become owners&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;Leo XIII, Rerum novarum, 46&quot;&gt;Leo XIII, ''Rerum novarum'', 46.&lt;/ref&gt; the duty of employers to provide safe [[working conditions]]&lt;ref&gt;Leo XIII, ''Rerum novarum'', 42.&lt;/ref&gt; and sufficient wages,&lt;ref&gt;Leo XIII, ''Rerum novarum'', 45.&lt;/ref&gt; and the right of workers to [[Trade union|unionise]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Leo XIII, Rerum novarum, 49&quot;&gt;Leo XIII, ''Rerum novarum'', 49.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Common ownership|Common]] and [[government ownership|government]] property ownership was expressly dismissed as a means of helping the poor.&lt;ref&gt;Leo XIII, ''Rerum novarum'', 4.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Leo XIII, ''Rerum novarum'', 15.&lt;/ref&gt;

Around the start of the 20th century, [[G. K. Chesterton]] and [[Hilaire Belloc]] drew together the disparate experiences of the various cooperatives and [[Friendly society|friendly societies]] in Northern England, Ireland, and Northern Europe into a coherent political theory which specifically advocated widespread private ownership of housing and control of industry through owner-operated small businesses and worker-controlled cooperatives. In the United States in the 1930s, distributism was treated in numerous essays by Chesterton, Belloc and others in ''[[The American Review (literary journal)|The American Review]]'', published and edited by [[Seward Collins]]. Pivotal among Belloc's and Chesterton's other works regarding distributism are ''[[The Servile State]]'',&lt;ref&gt;Hilaire Belloc, ''The Servile State'', The Liberty Fund, originally published 1913.&lt;/ref&gt; and ''Outline of Sanity''.&lt;ref&gt;G. K. Chesterton, [http://www.cse.dmu.ac.uk/~mward/gkc/books/Sanity.txt ''The Outline of Sanity''], IHS Press, 2002, originally published 1927.&lt;/ref&gt;

Although a majority of distributism's later supporters were not Catholics and many were in fact former radical socialists who had become disillusioned with socialism, distributist thought was adopted by the [[Catholic Worker Movement]], conjoining it with the thought of [[Dorothy Day]] and [[Peter Maurin]] concerning localized and independent communities. It also influenced the thought behind the [[Antigonish Movement]], which implemented cooperatives and other measures to aid the poor in the Canadian [[Maritimes]]. Its practical implementation in the form of local cooperatives has been documented by [[Race Mathews]] in his 1999 book ''Jobs of Our Own: Building a Stakeholder Society''.

== Position within the political spectrum ==
[[File:Triangle of economic systems.png|thumb|250px|Distributism's relation to [[socialism]] and [[capitalism]]]]
[[File:William Cobbett.JPG|250px|thumb|[[William Cobbett]]'s social views influenced [[G. K. Chesterton]]]]
The position of distributists when compared to other political philosophies is somewhat paradoxical and complicated (see [[Triangulation (politics)|triangulation]]). Strongly entrenched in an [[Organic (model)|organic]] but very [[Catholic Church in England and Wales|English Catholicism]], advocating culturally traditionalist and [[Agrarianism|agrarian]] values, directly challenging the precepts of [[Whig history]]—Belloc was nonetheless an MP for the Liberal Party and Chesterton once stated &quot;As much as I ever did, more than I ever did, I believe in Liberalism. But there was a rosy time of innocence when I believed in Liberals&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;orthodoxy&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last=Chesterton | first=G. K. | title=Orthodoxy | publisher=BiblioBazaar | year=2008 | page=49 | isbn=978-0-554-33475-2 | url=https://books.google.com/books?id=7Wl2QyGUL0EC&amp;pg=PA49 }}&lt;/ref&gt; This [[liberalism]] is different from most modern forms, taking influence from [[William Cobbett]] and [[John Ruskin]], who combined elements of [[Radicalism (historical)|radicalism]], challenging the establishment position, but from a perspective of renovation, not revolution; seeing themselves as trying to restore the traditional liberties of England and her people which had been taken away from them, amongst other things, since the [[Industrial Revolution]].

While converging with certain elements of traditional [[Toryism]], especially an appreciation of the [[Middle Ages]] and organic society, there were several points of significant contention. While many Tories were strongly opposed to reform, the distributists in certain cases saw this not as conserving a legitimate traditional concept of England, but in many cases entrenching harmful errors and innovations. Belloc was quite explicit in his opposition to [[Protestantism]] as a concept and [[Schism (religion)|schism]] from the Catholic Church in general, considering the division of [[Christendom]] in the 16th century one of the most harmful events in European history. Elements of Toryism on the other hand were quite intransigent when it came to the [[Church of England]] as the established church, some even spurning their original [[Legitimists|legitimist]] ultra-royalist principles in regards to [[James II of England|James II]] to uphold it.

Much of [[Dorothy L. Sayers]]' writings on social and economic matters has affinity with distributism. She may have been influenced by them, or have come to similar conclusions on her own. As an [[Anglicanism|Anglican]], the reasonings she gave are rooted in the theologies of [[Genesis creation narrative|Creation]] and [[Incarnation (Christianity)|Incarnation]], and are slightly different{{how?|date=January 2019}} from the Catholic Chesterton and Belloc.

== Economic theory ==
=== Private property ===
[[File:Three acres and a cow.JPG|thumb|180px|Self-portrait of Chesterton based on the distributist slogan &quot;[[Three acres and a cow]]&quot;]]
Under such a system, most people would be able to earn a living without having to rely on the use of the [[property]] of others to do so. Examples of people earning a living in this way would be farmers who own their own land and related machinery, carpenters and plumbers who own their own tools, among others. The cooperative approach advances beyond this perspective to recognise that such property and equipment may be co-owned by local communities larger than a family, e.g. partners in a business.

In ''Rerum novarum'', Leo XIII states that people are likely to work harder and with greater commitment if they themselves possess the land on which they labour, which in turn will benefit them and their families as workers will be able to provide for themselves and their household. He puts forward the idea that when men have the opportunity to possess property and work on it, they will &quot;learn to love the very soil which yields in response to the labor of their hands, not only food to eat, but an abundance of the good things for themselves and those that are dear to them&quot;. &lt;ref&gt;Pope Leo XIII, ''Rerum novarum'' : 47, 1891&lt;/ref&gt; He states also that owning property is not only beneficial for a person and their family, but is in fact a right, due to God having &quot;given the earth for the use and enjoyment of the whole human race&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Pope Leo XIII, ''Rerum novarum'':  8, 1891.&lt;/ref&gt;

Similar views are presented by [[G. K. Chesterton]] in his 1910 book ''What's Wrong with the World''.  Chesterton believes that whilst God has limitless capabilities, man has limited abilities in terms of creation. As such, man therefore is entitled to own property and to treat it as he sees fit, stating: &quot;Property is merely the art of the democracy. It means that every man should have something that he can shape in his own image, as he is shaped in the image of heaven. But because he is not God, but only a graven image of God, his self-expression must deal with limits; properly with limits that are strict and even small.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Chesterton, Gilbert Keith, ''What's Wrong with the World'' (1920), p. 59.&lt;/ref&gt; Chesterton summed up his distributist views in the phrase &quot;[[Three acres and a cow]]&quot;.

According to Belloc, the distributive state (the state which has implemented distributism) contains &quot;an agglomeration of families of varying wealth, but by far the greater number of owners of the means of production&quot;. This broader distribution does not extend to all property, but only to productive property; that is, that property which produces wealth, namely, the things needed for man to survive. It includes land, tools, and so on.&lt;ref&gt;Hilaire Belloc, ''[[The Servile State]]'', 1913.&lt;/ref&gt; Distributism allows for society to have public goods such as parks and transit systems.  Distributists accept that wage labor will remain a small part of the economy, with small business owners hiring employees, usually young, inexperienced people.  &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Baccelli |first1=Zebulon |title=Practical Policies for a Distributist Economy: Part Two |url=https://www.imagodeipolitics.org/2017/08/10/practical-policies-for-a-distributist-economy-part-two/ |website=imagodeipolitics.org |accessdate=25 December 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Aleman |first1=Richard |title=INDUSTRY: THE DISTRIBUTIST SOLUTION |url=https://distributistreview.com/industry-the-distributist-solution/ |website=distributistreview.com |accessdate=25 December 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Guild system ===
The kind of economic order envisaged by the early distributist thinkers would involve the return to some sort of [[guild]] system. The present existence of [[Trade union|labor unions]] does not constitute a realization of this facet of distributist economic order, as labour unions are organized along [[Social class|class]] lines to promote class interests and frequently [[class struggle]], whereas guilds are mixed class syndicates composed of both employers and employees cooperating for mutual benefit, thereby promoting [[class collaboration]].

=== Banks ===
Distributism favors the dissolution of the current [[private bank]] system, or more specifically its [[Profit (economics)|profit]]-making basis in charging interest. Dorothy Day, for example, suggested&lt;ref&gt;Considine, Kevin. [https://www.uscatholic.org/articles/201603/it-sinful-charge-interest-loan-30591 ''Is it sinful to charge interest on a loan?''] ''[[U.S. Catholic]]'', 17 March 2016. Retrieved 18 July 2018.&lt;/ref&gt; abolishing legal enforcement of interest-rate contracts ([[usury]]). It would not entail [[nationalization]] but could involve government involvement of some sort. Distributists look favorably towards financial cooperatives and mutuals such as [[credit union]]s, [[building society|building societies]] and [[mutual savings bank|mutual bank]]s as preferred alternatives to [[private bank|banks]].

=== Antitrust legislation ===
Distributism appears to have one of its greatest influences in [[antitrust legislation]] in America and Europe designed to break up monopolies and excessive concentration of market power in one or only a few companies, [[trust (monopoly)|trust]]s, interests, or [[cartel]]s.  Embodying the philosophy explained by Chesterton, above, that too much capitalism means too few capitalists, not too many, America's extensive system of antitrust legislation seeks to prevent the concentration of market power in a given industry into too few hands.  Requiring that no company gain too great a share of any market is an example of how distributism has found its way into [[Competition law|government policy]].  The assumption behind this legislation is the idea that having economic activity decentralized among many different industry participants is better for the economy than having one or a few large players in an industry. Note that antitrust regulation does take into account cases when only large companies are viable because of the nature of an industry, as in the case of [[Natural monopoly|natural monopolies]] like electricity distribution. It also accepts that mergers and acquisitions may improve consumer welfare; however, it generally prefers more [[Agent (economics)|economic agents]] to fewer, as this generally improves [[Competition (economics)|competition]].

=== Social credit ===
[[Social credit]] is an interdisciplinary distributive philosophy developed by [[C. H. Douglas]] (1879–1952), a British engineer, who wrote a book by that name in 1924. It encompasses the fields of economics, political science, history, accounting, and physics. Its policies are designed, according to Douglas, to disperse economic and political power to individuals.

== Social theory ==
=== Human family ===
Distributism sees the family of two parents and their child or children as the central and primary [[social unit]] of human ordering and the principal unit of a functioning distributist society and civilization. This unit is also the basis of a multi-generational [[extended family]], which is embedded in socially as well as genetically inter-related communities, nations, etc., and ultimately in the whole human family past, present and future. The economic system of a society should therefore be focused primarily on the flourishing of the family unit, but not in isolation: at the appropriate level of family context, as is intended in the principle of subsidiarity. Distributism reflects this doctrine most evidently by promoting the family, rather than the individual, as the basic type of owner; that is, distributism seeks to ensure that most families, rather than most individuals, will be owners of productive property. The family is, then, vitally important to the very core of distributist thought.

=== Subsidiarity ===
{{main|Subsidiarity}}
Distributism puts great emphasis on the principle of subsidiarity.  This principle holds that no larger unit (whether social, economic, or political) should perform a function which can be performed by a smaller unit. In ''[[Quadragesimo anno]]'', [[Pope Pius XI]] provided the classical statement of the principle: &quot;Just as it is gravely wrong to take from individuals what they can accomplish by their own initiative and industry and give it to the community, so also it is an injustice and at the same time a grave evil and disturbance of right order to assign to a greater and higher association what lesser and subordinate organizations can do&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;uywdmd&quot;&gt;Pope Pius XI, ''[http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/pius_xi/encyclicals/documents/hf_p-xi_enc_19310515_quadragesimo-anno_en.html Quadragesimo anno]'', 1931.&lt;/ref&gt;  Thus, any activity of production (which distributism holds to be the most important part of any economy) ought to be performed by the smallest possible unit.  This helps support distributism's argument that smaller units, families if possible, ought to be in control of the means of production, rather than the large units typical of modern economies.

In ''Quadragesimo anno'', Pope Pius XI further stated that &quot;every social activity ought of its very nature to furnish help to the members of the body social, and never destroy and absorb them&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;uywdmd&quot;/&gt; To prevent large private organizations from thus dominating the body politic, distributism applies this principle of subsidiarity to economic as well as to social and political action.

=== Social security ===
Distributists believe in a society that is as self-reliant as possible. Some may advocate that families and charitable organisations ought to provide an alternative to social security as a means of advancing the principles of subsidiary. However, many distributists reject the idea of eliminating [[social security]].

Distributists such as [[Dorothy Day]] did not favour social security when it was introduced by the United States government. This rejection of the new program was due to the direct influence of the ideas of [[Hilaire Belloc]] over American distributists.

The [[Democratic Labour Party (Australia)|Democratic Labour Party of Australia]] espouses distributism and does not hold the view of favouring the elimination of social security who for instance wish to &quot;[r]aise the level of student income support payments to the Henderson poverty line&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://dlp.org.au/policy-students/|title=Policy: Students|last=Cath|publisher=Democratic Labour Party|accessdate=23 February 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[American Solidarity Party]] has a platform of favouring an adequate social security system, whereby they state: &quot;We advocate for social safety nets that adequately provide for the material needs of the most vulnerable in society&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://solidarity-party.org/about-us/platform/|title=Solidarity Party Platform|publisher=American Solidarity Party|accessdate=1 January 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Society of artisans ===
Distributism promotes a society of [[artisan]]s and culture. This is influenced by an emphasis on small business, promotion of local culture, and favoring of small production over capitalistic [[mass production]]. A society of artisans promotes the distributist ideal of the unification of capital, ownership, and production rather than what distributism sees as an [[Social alienation|alienation]] of man from work.

This does not suggest that distributism necessarily favors a technological regression to a pre-[[Industrial Revolution]] lifestyle, but rather a more local ownership of factories and other industrial centers. Products such as food and clothing would be preferably returned to local producers and artisans instead of being mass-produced overseas.

== Geopolitical theory ==
=== Political order ===
Distributism does not favor one political order over another (political accidentalism). While some distributists such as Dorothy Day have been [[Anarchism|anarchists]], it should be remembered that most Chestertonian distributists are opposed to the mere concept of anarchism. Chesterton thought that distributism would benefit from the discipline that theoretical analysis imposes, and that distributism is best seen as a widely encompassing concept inside of which any number of interpretations and perspectives can fit. This concept should fit in a political system broadly characterized by widespread ownership of productive property.&lt;ref&gt;G. K. Chesterton, [http://www.cse.dmu.ac.uk/~mward/gkc/books/Sanity.txt ''The Outline of Sanity''](Norfolk, Va.: IHS Press, 2001), p. 90&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Political parties ===
In the United States, the [[American Solidarity Party]] generally adheres to Distributist principals as its economic model. The Brazilian political party, [[Humanist Party of Solidarity]] is a distributist party, and distributism has influenced [[List of Christian democratic parties|Christian Democratic parties]] in Continental Europe and the [[Democratic Labour Party (Australia)|Democratic Labour Party]] in Australia. [[Ross Douthat]] and [[Reihan Salam]] view their ''Grand New Party'', a roadmap for revising the [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican Party in the United States]], as &quot;a book written in the distributist tradition&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Ross Douthat |url=https://twitter.com/DouthatNYT/statuses/317053001070161920 |title=Twitter post |date=27 March 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Pirate Party of Romania]] is also considered to be a distributist party.

=== War ===
Distributists usually use [[just war theory]] in determining whether a war should be fought or not. Historical positions of distributist thinkers provide insight into a distributist position on war. Both Belloc and Chesterton opposed British imperialism in general as well as specifically opposing the [[Second Boer War]], but they supported British involvement in [[World War I]].

On the other hand, prominent distributists such as Dorothy Day and those involved in the Catholic Worker Movement were/are strict [[Pacifism|pacifists]], even to the point of condemning involvement in [[World War II]] at much personal cost.

== Influence ==
=== E. F. Schumacher ===
Distributism is known to have had an influence on the economist [[E. F. Schumacher]],&lt;ref&gt;Opdebeeck, Hendrik, ed. Frontiers of Business Ethics, Volume 11 : Responsible Economics : E. F. Schumacher and His Legacy for the 21st Century. Oxford, GBR: Peter Lang AG, 2013. p. 12.&lt;/ref&gt; a convert to Catholicism.

=== Mondragon Corporation ===
The [[Mondragon Corporation]], based in the [[Basque Country (historical territory)|Basque Country]] in a region of Spain and France, was founded by a Catholic priest, Father [[José María Arizmendiarrieta]], who seems to have been influenced by the same Catholic social and economic teachings that inspired Belloc, Chesterton, Father [[Vincent McNabb]], and the other founders of distributism.&lt;ref&gt;Mathews, Race. ''Jobs of Our Own: Building a Stakeholder Society.'' Fernwood Publishing. 1999.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Guild of St Joseph and St Dominic ===
Distributist ideas were put into practice by [[The Guild of St Joseph and St Dominic]], a group of artists and craftsmen who established a community in [[Ditchling]], Sussex, England, in 1920, with the motto &quot;Men rich in virtue studying beautifulness living in peace in their houses&quot;. The guild sought to recreate an idealised medieval lifestyle in the manner of the [[Arts and Crafts Movement]]. It survived almost 70 years until 1989.

=== Big Society ===
The [[Big Society]] was the flagship policy idea of the 2010 [[List of UK Conservative Party general election manifestos|UK Conservative Party general election manifesto]]. Some distributists claim that the rhetorical marketing of this policy was influenced by aphorisms of the distributist ideology and promotes distributism.&lt;ref name=DR21Jul&gt;[http://distributistreview.com/mag/2010/07/a-potential-step-in-the-right-direction/ A Potential Step in the Right Direction] 21 July 2010&lt;/ref&gt; It purportedly formed a part of the legislative programme of the [[Conservative – Liberal Democrat Coalition Agreement]].&lt;ref name = BBC18May&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/politics/8688860.stm Cameron and Clegg set out 'big society' policy ideas] [[BBC]] News 18-May-2010&lt;/ref&gt; The stated aim was &quot;to create a climate that empowers local people and communities, building a big society that will 'take power away from politicians and give it to people.'&quot;&lt;ref name=PM18May&gt;[http://www.number10.gov.uk/news/topstorynews/2010/05/big-society-50248 Government launches &quot;Big Society&quot; programme] [[10 Downing Street]] website 18-May-2010&lt;/ref&gt; The idea of the Big Society was suggested by [[Steve Hilton]], who worked as director of strategy for David Cameron during the Coalition government before moving on to live and work in California.

== Notable distributists ==
* [[Herbert Agar]]
* [[Hilaire Belloc]]
&lt;!--* Harold Robbins&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.catholicworker.org/dorothyday/articles/175.pdf &quot;Distributism Versus Capitalism&quot;], Dorothy Day, ''The Catholic Worker'', October 1954.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chesterton.org/shop/last-of-the-realists/|title=Last of the Realists - American Chesterton Society|website=American Chesterton Society|accessdate=8 August 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt;
* [[L. Brent Bozell Jr.]]
* [[Cecil Chesterton]]
* [[G.K. Chesterton]]
* [[Seward Collins]]
* [[Dorothy Day]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.catholicworker.org/dorothyday/daytext.cfm?TextID=160 &quot;Articles on Distributism - 2&quot;] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110726104029/http://www.catholicworker.org/dorothyday/daytext.cfm?TextID=160 |date=26 July 2011 }} by Dorothy Day. ''The Catholic Worker'', July–August 1948, 1, 2, 6&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Peter Maurin]]&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.ca/books?id=9y42CwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT70&amp;dq=peter+maurin+distributism &quot;Dorothy Day, Peter Maurin, &amp; Distributism&quot;], in ''The Hound of Distributism''.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Horacio de la Costa]]
* [[J. P. de Fonseka]]
* [[Eric Gill]]
* [[Douglas Hyde (author)|Douglas Hyde]]
* [[Vincent McNabb]]
* [[Arthur Penty]]
* [[Hilary Pepler]]
* [[William Purcell Witcutt]]
* [[Dorothy L. Sayers]]

=== Contemporary ===
* [[Dale Ahlquist]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://distributistreview.com/mag/author/dale-ahlquist/ |title=The Distributist Review – Dale Ahlquist |publisher=Distributistreview.com |date= |accessdate=2014-06-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Justin Barrett]]
* [[Phillip Blond]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Allan Carlson |url=http://www.frontporchrepublic.com/2009/07/a-distributist-view-of-the-global-economic-crisis-a-report/ |title=&quot;A Distributist View of the Global Economic Crisis&quot;: A Report |publisher=Front Porch Republic |date=2009-07-12 |accessdate=2014-06-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Allan C. Carlson]]
* [[Charles A. Coulombe]]
* [[Christopher Ferrara]]
* [[Derek Holland (activist)|Derek Holland]]
* [[Bill Kauffman]]
* [[Race Mathews]]
* [[Joseph Pearce]]
* [[Douglas Rushkoff]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Mark Stahlman |url=https://www.strategy-business.com/blog/Rocking-the-Bus |title=Rocking the Bus |publisher=Strategy+Business |date= |accessdate=2018-07-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[John Sharpe (publisher)|John Sharpe]]
* [[Richard Williamson (bishop)|Richard Williamson]]&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.ca/books?id=DHglCQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT3&amp;dq=t he+rural+solution+williamson &quot;The Rural Solution: Modern Catholic Voices on Going 'Back to the Land'&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Key texts ==
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20090720021418/http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/leo_xiii/encyclicals/documents/hf_l-xiii_enc_15051891_rerum-novarum_en.html Rerum novarum (1891)], papal encyclical by Pope Leo XIII
* [http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/pius_xi/encyclicals/documents/hf_p-xi_enc_19310515_quadragesimo-anno_en.html Quadragesimo anno (1931)], papal encyclical by Pope Pius XI
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20060114204743/http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/john_paul_ii/encyclicals/documents/hf_jp-ii_enc_01051991_centesimus-annus_en.html Centesimus Annus (1991)], papal encyclical by Pope John Paul II
* [http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/francesco/apost_exhortations/documents/papa-francesco_esortazione-ap_20131124_evangelii-gaudium_en.html Evangelii gaudium (2013)], apostolic exhortation by Pope Francis
* [http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/1717 ''What's Wrong with the World'' (1910)] by G. K. Chesterton {{ISBN|0-89870-489-8}} – [http://www.cse.dmu.ac.uk/~mward/gkc/books/ eText]
* [http://www.cse.dmu.ac.uk/~mward/gkc/books/Sanity.txt ''The Outline of Sanity'' (1927)] by G. K. Chesterton
* [http://www.gutenberg.org/etext/2134 ''Utopia of Usurers'' (1917)] by G. K. Chesterton
* [https://archive.org/details/servilestate00belliala ''The Servile State'' (1912)] by Hilaire Belloc
* ''An Essay on The Restoration of Property'' (1936) by Hilaire Belloc {{ISBN|0-9714894-4-0}}
* ''Jobs of Our Own'' (1999) by [[Race Mathews]] {{ISBN|978-1871204179}}

== See also ==
{{col-begin}}
{{col-2}}
* [[Aleksander Stamboliyski]]
* [[B. A. Santamaria]]
* [[Binary economics]]
* [[Bleeding-heart libertarianism]]
* [[Catholic social teaching]]
* [[Christian anarchism]]
* [[Christian democracy]]
* [[Christian socialism]]
* [[Communitarianism]]
* [[Decentralization]]
* [[Distributed economy]]
* [[Distributive justice]]
* [[Gandhian economics]]
* [[Geolibertarianism]]
* [[Georgism]]
* [[Gini coefficient]]
* [[Guild socialism]]
{{col-2}}
* [[Labour economics]]
* [[Land reform]]
* [[Left-wing market anarchism]]
* [[Market socialism]]
* [[Mixed economy]]
* [[Mutualism (economic theory)]]
* [[Paleoconservatism]]
* [[Paleolibertarianism]]
* [[Political Catholicism]]
* [[Predistribution]]
* [[Red tory#Definition drift and Misnomerization|Red Tory]]
* [[ResPublica]]
* [[Social peer-to-peer processes]]
* [[Solidarism (disambiguation)]]
* [[Traditionalist conservatism#The distributists|Traditionalist conservatism]]
{{col-end}}

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== Further reading ==
* Cooney, Anthony. ''Distributism''. {{ISBN|0-9535077-2-6}}
* Kurland, Norman. [http://www.cesj.org/resources/articles-index/the-just-third-way-basic-principles-of-economic-and-social-justice-by-norman-g-kurland/ ''The Just Third Way: Basic Principles of Economic and Social Justice''], Center for Economic and Social Justice
* Sagar, S. ''Distributism''. {{ISBN|0-905109-20-1}}
* ''[http://www.cse.dmu.ac.uk/~mward/gkc/books/debate.txt Shaw v Chesterton: a Debate between George Bernard Shaw and G. K. Chesterton]''. {{ISBN|0-9679707-7-6}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20110411052804/http://voicesofdemocracy.umd.edu/deliberative-topics/religion-morality-in-public-life/dorothy-day-union-square-speech-6-november-1965/ &quot;Union Square Speech&quot;] by [[Dorothy Day]]
* ''[http://www.hsnsw.asn.au/Distributism.html Distributism as a means of achieving third way economics]'', a paper for the [[Secular Party of Australia]] written by Richard Howard of the [[Humanist Society of New South Wales]]
* Pabst, Adrian. [https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/belief/2009/jul/20/pope-benedict-capitalism-economics &quot;Pope Benedict's call for a civil economy&quot;]. ''The Guardian'', 20 July 2009.

== External links ==
* [http://distributistreview.com/ The Distributist Review]

{{political ideologies}}
{{authority control}}
[[Category:Anti-capitalism]]
[[Category:Economic ideologies]]
[[Category:Political theories]]
[[Category:Syncretic political movements]]</text>
      <sha1>96qbr3oax3394wa8ayrgrrphun0lb85</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
