  <page>
    <title>West Memphis Three</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8832</id>
    <revision>
      <id>936170446</id>
      <parentid>933433031</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-17T03:20:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Grammar nazi 666</username>
        <id>26919429</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Criticism of the investigation */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{redirect|WM3}}
{{redirect|Jason Baldwin|the former Australian rules footballer|Jason Baldwin (footballer)}}
{{short description|three men convicted of the 1993 murders of three boys in West Memphis, Arkansas, United States}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=October 2012}}
{{pp-semi-blp|small=yes}}
[[File:West Memphis Three Mugshot.jpg|thumb|300px|The West Memphis Three photographed after their arrest in June 1993 by the West Memphis Police Department]]

The '''West Memphis Three''' are three men known for being convicted as teenagers in 1994, of the 1993 murders of three boys in [[West Memphis, Arkansas]], United States. '''Damien Echols''' was [[capital punishment|sentenced to death]], '''Jessie Misskelley, Jr.''' to [[life imprisonment]] plus two 20-year sentences, and '''Jason Baldwin''' to [[life imprisonment]]. During the trial, the prosecution asserted that the juveniles killed the children as part of a [[Satanic ritual abuse|Satanic ritual]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Youth Is Convicted In Slaying of 3 Boys In an Arkansas City|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1994/02/05/us/youth-is-convicted-in-slaying-of-3-boys-in-an-arkansas-city.html|newspaper=[[The New York Times]]|date=February 5, 1994|quote=The prosecution said the slayings might have been part of a satanic ritual.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Arguments conclude in 'West Memphis Three' appeals|url=http://www.arkansasonline.com/news/2009/oct/02/appeals-continue-slayings-ark-boys-93|newspaper=[[Arkansas Online]]|date=October 2, 2009|agency=[[The Associated Press]]|quote=Prosecutors claimed the killers sexually mutilated the boy in a satanic ritual.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Not-so-cold Old Cases|url=http://criminalbrief.com/?p=14536|work=Capital Punishment|publisher=Criminal Brief|author=Lundin, Leigh|location=Orlando|date=November 14, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The case generated widespread controversy and was the subject of a number of documentaries that explored its elements. Celebrities and musicians have held fundraisers to support efforts to free the men, who they say are innocent of the charges.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.rollingstone.com/music/news/how-rockers-helped-free-the-west-memphis-three-20110901 |title=How Rockers Helped Free the West Memphis Three |author=Patrick Doyle |work=[[Rolling Stone]] |date=September 1, 2011 |access-date=November 30, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In July 2007, new [[forensic evidence]] was presented in the case. A status report jointly issued by the state and the defense team stated: &quot;Although most of the [[DNA|genetic material]] recovered from the scene was attributable to the victims of the offenses, some of it cannot be attributed to either the victims or the defendants.&quot; On October 29, 2007, the defense filed a ''Second Amended [[Habeas Corpus|Writ of Habeas Corpus]]'', outlining the new evidence.

Following a 2010 decision by the [[Arkansas Supreme Court]] regarding newly produced [[DNA profiling|DNA evidence]] and potential [[juror misconduct]], the West Memphis Three negotiated a [[plea bargain]] with prosecutors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.reuters.com/article/2011/07/28/us-crime-dna-arkansas-idUSTRE76R0D920110728|title=Fresh DNA evidence boosts defense in 1993 Arkansas slayings|date=July 27, 2011|agency=Reuters|publisher=Thompson Reuters|first=Suzi|last=Parker|access-date=January 25, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; On August 19, 2011, they entered [[Alford plea]]s, which allowed them to assert their innocence while acknowledging that prosecutors have enough evidence to convict them. Judge David Laser accepted the pleas and sentenced the three to time served. They were released with 10-year [[suspended sentence]]s, having served 18 years and 78 days in prison.&lt;ref name=ArOnline/&gt;

==The crime==
On May 5, 1993, three eight-year-old boys—Steve Branch, Michael Moore, and Christopher Byers—were reported missing in West Memphis, Arkansas. The first report to the police was made by Byers' adoptive father, John Mark Byers, around 7:00&amp;nbsp;pm.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Devil's Knot: The True Story of the West Memphis Three|last=Leveritt|first=Mara|year=2003|publisher=Simon &amp; Schuster|isbn=0-7434-1760-7|page=5}}&lt;/ref&gt; The boys were allegedly last seen together by three neighbors, who in [[affidavit]]s told of seeing them playing together around 6:30&amp;nbsp;pm the evening they disappeared, and seeing Terry Hobbs, Steve Branch's stepfather, calling them to come home.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Damien Echols asks for new trial in West Memphis 3 murder case|last=Blackstone|first=Ashley|date=September 30, 2010|work=Today's THV&amp;nbsp;– Gannett|publisher=Arkansas Television Company|url=http://www.todaysthv.com/news/story.aspx?storyid=120386|accessdate=January 25, 2012}}; [http://www.todaysthv.com/news/PDF/wm3.pdf Affidavits]&lt;/ref&gt; Initial police searches made that night were limited.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leveritt03&quot;/&gt; Friends and neighbors also conducted a search that night, which included a cursory visit to the location where the bodies were later found.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leveritt03&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title=Devil's Knot: The True Story of the West Memphis Three|last=Leveritt|first=Mara|year=2003| publisher=[[Atria Books|Atria]]|isbn=0-7434-1760-7}} {{Page needed|date=July 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A more thorough police search for the children began around 8:00&amp;nbsp;am on May 6, led by the Crittenden County Search and Rescue personnel. Searchers canvassed all of West Memphis but focused primarily on Robin Hood Hills, where the boys were reported last seen. Despite a shoulder-to-shoulder search of Robin Hood Hills by a human chain, searchers found no sign of the missing boys.{{citation needed|date=October 2015}}

Around 1:45&amp;nbsp;pm, juvenile Parole Officer Steve Jones spotted a boy's black shoe floating in a muddy creek that led to a major drainage canal in Robin Hood Hills. A subsequent search of the ditch revealed the bodies of three boys. They had been stripped naked and were [[hogtie]]d with their own shoelaces: their right ankles tied to their right wrists behind their backs, the same with their left arms and legs. Their clothing was found in the creek, some of it twisted around sticks that had been thrust into the muddy ditch bed.&lt;ref name=Newton1&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=gijG7fSwvjAC&amp;pg=PA391|title=The Encyclopedia of Unsolved Crimes|author=Michael Newton|page=391|publisher=Infobase Publishing|year= 2009|access-date=October 13, 2011|isbn=9781438119144}}&lt;/ref&gt; The clothing was mostly turned inside-out; two pairs of the boys' underwear were never recovered. Christopher Byers had lacerations to various parts of his body, and mutilation of his scrotum and penis.&lt;ref name=ByersAutopsy&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.autopsyfiles.org/reports/Other/west%20memphis%20three/byers,%20christopher.pdf|title=Christopher Byers Autopsy|author=Frank J. Peretti, William Q. Sturner|work=Arkansas State Crime Laboratory|date=May 1993|access-date=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The autopsies, by the forensic pathologist Frank J. Peretti, indicated that Byers died of &quot;multiple injuries&quot;,&lt;ref name=ByersAutopsy/&gt; while Moore and Branch died of &quot;multiple injuries with drowning&quot;.&lt;ref name=BranchAutopsy&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.autopsyfiles.org/reports/Other/west%20memphis%20three/branch,%20steve.pdf|title=Steve Branch Autopsy|author=Frank J. Peretti, William Q. Sturner|work=Arkansas State Crime Laboratory|date=May 1993|access-date=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=MooreAutopsy&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.autopsyfiles.org/reports/Other/west%20memphis%20three/moore,%20james%20michael%20.pdf|title=Michael Moore Autopsy |author=Frank J. Peretti, William Q. Sturner|work=Arkansas State Crime Laboratory|date=May 1993|access-date=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Police initially suspected the boys had been raped;&lt;ref name=Newton1/&gt; however, later expert testimony disputed this finding. Trace amounts of sperm DNA were found on a pair of pants recovered from the scene. Prosecution experts claim Byers' wounds were the results of a knife attack and that he had been purposely [[castration|castrated]] by the murderer; defense experts claim the injuries were more probably the result of post-mortem animal predation. Police believed the boys were assaulted and killed at the location where they were found; critics argued that the assault, at least, was unlikely to have occurred at the creek.

Byers was the only victim with drugs in his system; he was prescribed [[Ritalin]] (methylphenidate) in January 1993, as part of treatment of an [[attention-deficit hyperactivity disorder]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Leveritt03&quot;/&gt; The initial autopsy report describes the drug as [[Carbamazepine]], and that dosage was found to be at sub-therapeutic level. His father John Mark Byers said that Christopher may not have taken his prescription on May 5, 1993.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=GSJ7Ja95oegC&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|title=Criminal profiling:an introduction to behavioral evidence analysis|first=Brent E.|last=Turvey|page=377|publisher=Academic|year=1999|access-date=October 13, 2011|isbn=9780123852441}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Victims==
[[File:Grave of Steve Edward Branch Mount Zion Cemetery Steele MO 2013-05-11 001.jpg|thumb|Grave of Stevie Branch]]
[[File:Grave of Christopher Mark Byers Forest HIll East Cemetery Memphis TN 2013-05-06 001.jpg|thumb|Grave of Christopher Byers]]
[[File:Grave of James Michael Moore Crittenden Memorial Park Cemetery Marion AR 2013-05-06 006.JPG|thumb|Grave of Michael Moore]]
[[File:West Memphis 3 Memorial at Weaver Elementary School West Memphis AR 2013-04-28 005.jpg|thumb|Memorial for the West Memphis Three victims]]
Stevie Edward Branch, Christopher Byers, and Michael Moore, were all second graders at Weaver Elementary School. Each had achieved the rank of &quot;Wolf&quot; in the local Cub Scout pack, and they were best friends.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.commercialappeal.com/photos/galleries/west-memphis-three/362|title=West Memphis Three|work=commercialappeal.com|year=2011|access-date=October 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Steve Edward Branch===
Stevie Branch was the son of Steven and Pamela Branch, who divorced when he was an infant. His mother was awarded custody and later married Terry Hobbs. Branch was eight years old, 4&amp;nbsp;ft. 2 tall, weighed 65&amp;nbsp;lbs, and had blond hair. He was last seen wearing blue jeans and a white T-shirt, and riding a black and red bicycle. He was an honor student. He lived with his mother, Pamela Hobbs, his stepfather, Terry Hobbs, and a four-year-old half-sister, Amanda.&lt;ref name=Beifuss&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.commercialappeal.com/news/1993/may/09/pain-tells-how-much-life-3-slain-boys-had|title=Pain tells how much life 3 slain boys had|first=John|last=Beifuss|work=commercialappeal.com|date=May 9, 1993|accessdate=October 13, 2011|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130522225152/http://www.commercialappeal.com/news/1993/may/09/pain-tells-how-much-life-3-slain-boys-had/|archive-date=May 22, 2013|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; Steve Edward Branch is buried in Mount Zion Cemetery in [[Steele, Missouri]].

===Christopher Mark Byers===
Christopher Byers was born to Melissa DeFir and Ricky Murray. His parents divorced when he was four years old; shortly afterward, his mother married John Mark Byers, who adopted the boy. Byers was eight years old, 4&amp;nbsp;ft. tall, weighed 52&amp;nbsp;lbs, and had light brown hair. He was last seen wearing blue jeans, dark shoes, and a white long-sleeved shirt. He lived with his mother, Sharon Melissa Byers, his adoptive father, John Mark Byers, and his stepbrother, Shawn Ryan Clark, aged 13. According to his mother, Christopher was a typical eight-year-old. &quot;He still believed in the Easter Bunny and Santa Claus&quot;.&lt;ref name=Beifuss/&gt; Christopher Mark Byers is buried in Forest Hill Cemetery East in [[Memphis, Tennessee]].

===James Michael Moore===
Michael Moore was the son of Todd and Dana Moore. He was eight years old, 4&amp;nbsp;ft. 2 tall, weighed 55&amp;nbsp;lbs, and had brown hair. He was last seen wearing blue pants, a blue Boy Scouts of America shirt, and an orange and blue Boy Scout hat, and riding a light green bicycle. Moore enjoyed wearing his scout uniform even when he was not at meetings. He was considered the leader of the three. He lived with his parents and his nine-year-old sister, Dawn.&lt;ref name=Beifuss/&gt; James Michael Moore is buried in Crittenden Memorial Park Cemetery in [[Marion, Arkansas]].

===West Memphis Three victims memorial===
In 1994, a memorial was erected for the three murder victims. The memorial is located in the playground of Weaver Elementary School in West Memphis, where all three victims were second graders at the time of the crime. In May 2013, for the 20th anniversary of the slayings, Weaver Elementary School principal Sheila Grissom raised funds to refurbish the memorial.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.arktimes.com/ArkansasBlog/archives/2013/04/21/help-sought-for-memorial-to-victims-in-west-memphis-3-case |title=Help sought for memorial to victims in West Memphis 3 case |work=Arkansas Times |year=2013 |accessdate=May 10, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Suspects==

===Baldwin, Echols, and Misskelley===

At the time of their arrests, Jessie Misskelley, Jr. was 17 years old, Jason Baldwin was 16 years old, and Damien Echols was 18 years old.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=https://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F00611F8395E0C758CDDAF0894DB494D81 | title=3 Teen-Agers Accused in the Killings of 3 Boys |work=New York Times | date=June 6, 1993 | accessdate =December 4, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Baldwin and Echols had been previously arrested for [[vandalism]] and [[shoplifting]], respectively, and Misskelley had a reputation for his temper and for engaging in fistfights with other teenagers at school. Misskelley and Echols had dropped out of high school; however, Baldwin earned high grades and demonstrated a talent for drawing and sketching, and was encouraged by one of his teachers to study [[graphic design]] in college.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leveritt03&quot;/&gt; Echols and Baldwin were close friends, and bonded over their similar tastes in music and fiction, and over their shared distaste for the prevailing cultural climate of West Memphis, situated in the [[Bible Belt]]. Baldwin and Echols were acquainted with Misskelley from school, but were not close friends with him.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leveritt03&quot;/&gt;

Echols' family was poor and received frequent visits from [[social work]]ers, and he rarely attended school. He and a girlfriend had run off and later broken into a trailer during a rain storm; they were arrested, though only Echols was charged with burglary.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leveritt03&quot;/&gt;

Echols spent several months in a mental institution in Arkansas and afterward received &quot;full disability&quot; status from the [[Social Security Administration]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Leveritt03&quot;/&gt; During Echols' trial, Dr. George W. Woods testified (for the defense) that Echols suffered from:

&lt;blockquote&gt;serious [[mental illness]] characterized by grandiose and persecutory delusions, auditory and visual [[hallucination]]s, disordered thought processes, substantial lack of insight, and chronic, incapacitating mood swings.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leveritt03&quot;/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

At his death penalty sentencing hearing, Echols' psychologist reported that months before the murders, Echols had claimed that he obtained super powers by drinking human blood.&lt;ref&gt;Mark Caro, [http://articles.chicagotribune.com/1996-10-02/features/9610020073_1_victims-families-damien-echols-devil-worship/2 In Search Of Evil], ''[[Chicago Tribune]]'', October 2, 1996.&lt;/ref&gt; At the time of his arrest, Echols was working part-time with a roofing company and expecting a child with his girlfriend, Domini Teer.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leveritt03&quot;/&gt;

===Chris Morgan and Brian Holland===
Early in the investigation, the WMPD briefly regarded two West Memphis teenagers as suspects. Chris Morgan and Brian Holland, both with drug offense histories, had abruptly departed for [[Oceanside, California]], four days after the bodies were discovered.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lp2728&quot;/&gt; Morgan was presumed to be at least casually familiar with all three murdered boys, having previously driven an ice cream truck route in their neighborhood.

Arrested in Oceanside on May 17, 1993, Morgan and Holland both took [[polygraph]] exams administered by California police. Examiners reported that both men's charts indicated deception when they denied involvement in the murders. During subsequent questioning, Morgan claimed a long history of drug and alcohol use, along with blackouts and memory lapses. He claimed that he &quot;might have&quot; killed the victims but quickly recanted this part of his statement.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lp2728&quot;/&gt;

California police sent blood and urine samples from Morgan and Holland to the WMPD, but there is no indication WMPD investigated Morgan or Holland as suspects following their arrest in California. The relevance of Morgan's recanted statement would later be debated in trial, but it was eventually barred from admission as evidence.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lp2728&quot;&gt;Leveritt, 2003, p. 27-28&lt;/ref&gt;

===&quot;Mr. Bojangles&quot;===

The citing of a black male as a possible alternate suspect was implied during the beginning of the Misskelley trial. According to local West Memphis police officers, on the evening of May 5, 1993, at 8:42&amp;nbsp;pm, workers in the [[Bojangles' Famous Chicken 'n Biscuits|Bojangles']] restaurant located about a mile from the crime scene in Robin Hood Hills reported seeing a black male who seemed &quot;mentally disoriented&quot; inside the restaurant's ladies' room. The man was bleeding and had brushed against the restroom walls. Officer Regina Meeks responded to the call, taking the restaurant manager's report through the eatery's [[Drive-through|drive-through window]]. By then, the man had left, and police did not enter the restroom on that date.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leveritt6-174&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=Devil's Knot: The True Story of the West Memphis Three|last=Leveritt|first=Mara|year=2003|publisher=Simon &amp; Schuster|isbn=0-7434-1760-7|pages=6, 174}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The day after the victims' bodies were found, Bojangles' manager Marty King, thinking there was a possible connection to the bloody man found in the bathroom, reported the incident to police officers who then inspected the ladies' room. King gave the officers a pair of sunglasses he thought the man had left behind, and the detectives took some blood samples from the walls and tiles of the restroom. Police detective Bryn Ridge testified that he later lost those blood scrapings. A hair identified as belonging to a black male was later recovered from a sheet wrapped around one of the victims.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leveritt6-174&quot;/&gt;

==Investigation==
===Evidence and interviews===
Police officers James Sudbury and Steve Jones felt that the crime had &quot;cult&quot; overtones, and that Damien Echols might be a suspect because he had an interest in occultism, and Jones felt Echols was capable of murdering children.&lt;ref name=Newton1/&gt; The police interviewed Echols on May 7, two days after the bodies were discovered.&lt;ref name=Newton1/&gt; During a [[polygraph]] examination, he denied any involvement. The polygraph examiner claimed that Echols' chart indicated deception.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leveritt03&quot; /&gt; On May 9, during a formal interview by Detective Bryn Ridge, Echols mentioned that one of the victims had wounds to the genitals; law enforcement viewed this knowledge as incriminating.&lt;ref name=Newton1/&gt;

After a month had passed with little progress in the case, police continued to focus their investigation upon Echols, interrogating him more frequently than any other person. Nonetheless, they claimed he was not regarded as a direct suspect but a source of information.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leveritt03&quot; /&gt;

On June 3, the police interrogated Jessie Misskelley, Jr. Despite his reported [[Intelligence quotient|IQ]] of 72 (categorizing him as [[borderline intellectual functioning]]) and his status as a [[minor (law)|minor]], Miskelley was questioned alone; his parents were not present during the interrogation.&lt;ref name=&quot;CB&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Leveritt03&quot; /&gt; Misskelley's father gave permission for Misskelley to go with police but did not explicitly give permission for his son to be questioned or interrogated.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leveritt03&quot; /&gt; Misskelley was questioned for roughly 12 hours. Only two segments, totaling 46 minutes, were recorded.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/dna/collective/A4387647 |title=collective&amp;nbsp;– paradise lost, revelations dvd |publisher=BBC |date=July 10, 2005 |accessdate=August 19, 2011 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080321133722/http://www.bbc.co.uk/dna/collective/A4387647 |archivedate=March 21, 2008 |df=mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Misskelley quickly recanted his confession, citing intimidation, coercion, fatigue, and veiled threats from police.&lt;ref name=&quot;CB&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Leveritt03&quot; /&gt; Misskelley specifically said he was &quot;scared of the police&quot; during this confession.&lt;ref&gt;Transcript, MissKelley, Jr. Confession&lt;/ref&gt;

Though he was informed of his [[Miranda warning|Miranda]] rights, Misskelley later claimed he did not fully understand them.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leveritt03&quot; /&gt; In 1996, the [[Arkansas Supreme Court]] ruled that Misskelley's confession was voluntary and that he did, in fact, understand the Miranda warning and its consequences.&lt;ref name=autogenerated2&gt;{{cite web |url=http://opinions.aoc.arkansas.gov/weblink8/0/doc/167688/Page1.aspx |title=cr94-848 |publisher=Arkansas Judiciary |accessdate=January 14, 2015 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160829222658/http://opinions.aoc.arkansas.gov/weblink8/0/doc/167688/Page1.aspx |archivedate=August 29, 2016 |df=mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Portions of Misskelley's statements to the police were leaked to the press and reported on the front page of the Memphis ''[[The Commercial Appeal|Commercial Appeal]]'' before any of the trials began.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leveritt03&quot;/&gt;

Shortly after Misskelley's first confession, police arrested Echols and his close friend Baldwin. Eight months after his original confession, on February 17, 1994, Misskelley made another statement to police. His lawyer, Dan Stidham, remained in the room and continually advised Misskelley not to say anything. Misskelley ignored this advice and went on to detail how the boys were abused and murdered. Stidham, who was later elected to a municipal judgeship, has written a detailed critique{{citation needed|date=November 2013|reason=online sources are self-published, including http://murderpedia.org/male.E/e/echols-damien.htm }} of what he asserts are major police errors and misconceptions during their investigation. Stidham made similar comments during a radio show interview in May 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mCwguAueFI0 |title=WM3 Interview With Dan Stidham, Part 1 of 11 |date=May 15, 2010 |access-date=March 10, 2018 |via=YouTube |publisher=Crime Scene Detectives }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Vicki Hutcheson===
Vicki Hutcheson, a new resident of West Memphis, would play an important role in the investigation, though she would later recant her testimony, claiming her statements were fabricated due in part to coercion from police.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leveritt03&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=autogenerated3&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.crimelibrary.com/notorious_murders/famous/memphis/index_1.html|author=Steel, Fiona|title=The West Memphis 3|date=March 17, 2006|publisher=Crimelibrary.com|accessdate=August 19, 2011|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140314174108/http://www.crimelibrary.com/notorious_murders/famous/memphis/index_1.html|archivedate=March 14, 2014|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On May 6, 1993 (before the victims were found later the same day), Hutcheson took a [[polygraph]] exam by Detective Don Bray at the Marion Police Department, to determine whether or not she had stolen money from her West Memphis employer. Hutcheson's young son, Aaron, was also present, and proved such a distraction that Bray was unable to administer the polygraph. Aaron, a playmate of the murdered boys', mentioned to Bray that the boys had been killed at &quot;the playhouse.&quot; When the bodies proved to have been discovered near where Aaron indicated, Bray asked Aaron for further details, and Aaron claimed that he had witnessed the murders committed by Satanists who spoke Spanish. Aaron's further statements were wildly inconsistent, and he was unable to identify Baldwin, Echols, or Misskelley from photo line-ups, and there was no &quot;playhouse&quot; at the location Aaron indicated. A police officer leaked portions of Aaron's statements to the press contributing to the growing belief that the murders were part of a Satanic rite.{{citation needed|date=October 2015}}

On or about June 1, 1993, Hutcheson agreed to police suggestions to place hidden microphones in her home during an encounter with Echols. Misskelley agreed to introduce Hutcheson to Echols. During their conversation, Hutcheson reported that Echols made no incriminating statements. Police said the recording was &quot;inaudible&quot;, but Hutcheson claimed the recording was audible. On June 2, 1993, Hutcheson told police that about two weeks after the murders were committed, she, Echols, and Misskelley attended a [[Wicca]]n meeting in [[Turrell, Arkansas]]. Hutcheson claimed that, at the Wiccan meeting, a drunken Echols openly bragged about killing the three boys. Misskelley was first questioned on June 3, 1993, a day after Hutcheson's purported confession. Hutcheson was unable to recall the Wiccan meeting location and did not name any other participants in the purported meeting. Hutcheson was never charged with theft. She claimed she had implicated Echols and Misskelley to avoid facing criminal charges, and to obtain a reward for the discovery of the murderers.&lt;ref name=&quot;CB&quot;/&gt;

==Trials==
Misskelley was tried separately, and Echols and Baldwin were tried together in 1994. Under the &quot;[[Bruton rule]]&quot;, Misskelley's confession could not be admitted against his co-defendants; thus he was tried separately. All three defendants pleaded not guilty.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://news.google.com/newspapers|title=Teens Plead Innocent In Boys' Deaths|newspaper=[[Times Daily]]|date=August 4, 1993|accessdate=December 4, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Misskelley's trial===
During Misskelley's trial, [[Richard Ofshe]], an expert on [[false confessions]] and police coercion, and Professor of Sociology at [[University of California, Berkeley|UC Berkeley]], testified that the brief recording of Misskelley's interrogation was a &quot;classic example&quot; of police [[coercion]].&lt;ref name=&quot;courttv&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.crimelibrary.com/notorious_murders/famous/memphis/index_1.html|title=The West Memphis Three|first=Fiona|last=Steel|publisher=[[Turner Broadcasting System]]|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140314174108/http://www.crimelibrary.com/notorious_murders/famous/memphis/index_1.html|archivedate=March 14, 2014|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; Critics have also stated that Misskelley's various &quot;confessions&quot; were in many respects inconsistent with each other, as well as with the particulars of the crime scene and murder victims, including (for example) an &quot;admission&quot; that Misskelley watched Damien rape one of the boys.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2011/10/16/magazine/a-death-row-love-story.html |title=A Death-Row Love Story |first=Geoffrey |last=Gray |newspaper=The New York Times |date=October 13, 2011 |access-date=March 10, 2018 |quote=Then a teenager, Jessie Misskelley Jr., told the police that he saw his friend, Jason Baldwin, and another teenager, Damien Echols, go into the woods with the boys and rape them. Misskelley later recanted }}&lt;/ref&gt; Police had initially suspected that the victims had been raped because their anuses were dilated. However, there was no forensic evidence indicating that the murdered boys had been raped. Dilation of the anus is a normal post-mortem condition.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leveritt03&quot;/&gt;

On February 5, 1994, Misskelley was convicted by a jury of one count of first-degree murder and two counts of second-degree murder.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Arkansas Teen Found Guilty On Three Counts Of Murder,&quot; ''Gainesville Sun'', February 5, 1994&lt;/ref&gt; The court sentenced him to life plus 40 years in prison.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=Youth Is Convicted In Slaying of 3 Boys In an Arkansas City|work=The New York Times|date=February 5, 1994|url=https://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE5DA1E39F936A35751C0A962958260&amp;scp=11&amp;sq=west+memphis+3+murder+case&amp;st=nyt}}&lt;/ref&gt; His conviction was appealed, but the Arkansas Supreme Court affirmed the conviction.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.davidjauss.com/miscellaneous_essays_and_interviews_51285.htm|title=Miscellaneous Essays and Interviews – David Jauss|website=www.davidjauss.com|access-date=2017-01-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Echols' and Baldwin's trial===
Three weeks later, Echols and Baldwin went on trial. The prosecution accused the three young men of committing a Satanic murder. The prosecution called Dale W. Griffis, a graduate of the unaccredited [[Columbia Pacific University]], as an expert in the occult to testify the murders were a Satanic ritual.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.commercialappeal.com/news/1994/mar/09/witnesses-call-boys-deaths-work-group-trappings-oc/?print=1|title=Witnesses call boys deaths work of group with trappings of the occult|newspaper=[[The Commercial Appeal]] |date=March 9, 1994|accessdate=2011-02-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; On March 19, 1994 Echols and Baldwin were found guilty on three counts of murder.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=wuYyAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=tQcGAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=5353,3505240&amp;dq=baldwin+echols+and+misskelley&amp;hl=en|title=Teens Found Guilty In Boys' Slayings|work=[[Free Lance-Star]]|date=March 19, 1994|accessdate =December 4, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The court sentenced Echols to death and Baldwin to life in prison.&lt;ref name=&quot;CB&quot;/&gt;

At trial, the defense team argued that news articles from the time could have been the source for Echols' knowledge about the genital mutilation, and Echols said his knowledge was limited to what was &quot;on TV&quot;.

The prosecution claimed that Echols' knowledge was nonetheless too close to the facts, since there was no public reporting of drowning or that one victim had been mutilated more than the others. Echols testified that Detective Ridge's description of their earlier conversation (which was not recorded) regarding those particular details was inaccurate (and indeed that some other claims by Ridge were &quot;lies&quot;). Mara Leveritt, an investigative journalist and the author of ''[[Devil's Knot]]'', argues that Echols' information may have come from police leaks, such as Detective Gitchell's comments to Mark Byers, that circulated amongst the local public.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leveritt03&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;courttv&quot;/&gt; The defense team objected when the prosecution attempted to question Echols about his past violent behaviors, but the defense objections were overruled.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Devil's Knot: The True Story of the West Memphis Three|last=Leveritt|first=Mara|year=2003|publisher=Simon &amp; Schuster|isbn=0-7434-1760-7|page=245}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==

===Criticism of the investigation===
[[File:Free the West Memphis Three.jpg|thumb|Protestors followed the trial]]
There has been widespread criticism of how the police handled the [[crime scene]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Leveritt03&quot; /&gt; Misskelley's former attorney Dan Stidham cites multiple substantial police errors at the crime scene, characterizing it as &quot;literally trampled, especially the creek bed.&quot; The bodies, he said, had been removed from the water before the coroner arrived to examine the scene and determine the state of [[rigor mortis]], allowing the bodies to decay on the creek bank and to be exposed to sunlight and insects. The police did not telephone the coroner until almost two hours after the discovery of the floating shoe, resulting in a late appearance by the coroner. Officials failed to drain the creek in a timely manner and secure possible evidence in the water (the creek was sandbagged after the bodies were pulled from the water).

Stidham calls the coroner's investigation &quot;extremely substandard.&quot; There was a small amount of blood found at the scene that was never tested. According to HBO's documentaries ''[[Paradise Lost: The Child Murders at Robin Hood Hills]]'' (1996) and ''[[Paradise Lost 2: Revelations]]'' (2000), no blood was found at the crime scene, indicating that the location where the bodies were found was not necessarily the location where the murders actually happened. After the initial investigation, the police failed to control disclosure of information and speculation about the crime scene.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Devil's Knot: The True Story of the West Memphis Three |last=Leveritt |first=Mara |year=2003| publisher= Simon &amp; Schuster |isbn=0-7434-1760-7 |page=25 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Leveritt, &quot;Police records were a mess. To call them disorderly would be putting it mildly.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Leveritt03&quot; /&gt; Leveritt speculated that the small local police force was overwhelmed by the crime, which was unlike any they had ever investigated. Police refused an unsolicited offer of aid and consultation from the violent crimes experts of the [[Arkansas State Police]], and critics suggested this was due to the WMPD's being under investigation by the Arkansas State Police for suspected theft from the [[Crittenden County, Arkansas|Crittenden County]] drug task force.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leveritt03&quot; /&gt; Leveritt further noted that some of the physical evidence was stored in paper sacks obtained from a supermarket (with the supermarket's name printed on the bags) rather than in containers of known and controlled origin.

When police speculated about the assailant, the juvenile probation officer assisting at the scene of the murders speculated that Echols was &quot;capable&quot; of committing the murders,&quot; stating: &quot;it looks like Damien Echols finally killed someone.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Leveritt03&quot; /&gt;

Brent Turvey, a forensic scientist and criminal profiler, stated in the film ''Paradise Lost 2'' that human bite marks could have been left on at least one of the victims. However, these potential bite marks were first noticed in photographs years after the trials and were not inspected by a board-certified medical examiner until four years after the murders. The defense's expert testified that the mark in question was not an adult bite mark, while experts put on by the State concluded that there was no bite mark at all.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Devil's Knot: The True Story of the West Memphis Three |last=Leveritt |first=Mara |year=2003 | publisher=Simon &amp; Schuster |isbn=0-7434-1760-7 |pages=399, 404}}&lt;/ref&gt; The State's experts had examined the actual bodies for any marks, and others conducted expert photo analysis of injuries. Upon further examination, it was concluded that if the marks were bite marks, they did not match the teeth of any of the three convicted.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0239894/|title=''Revelations: Paradise Lost 2''. HBO. 28&amp;nbsp;July&amp;nbsp;2000 Broadcast. March 17, 2006|accessdate=February 19, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Appeals and new evidence==
In May 1994, the three defendants appealed their convictions;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title=Appeal puts 3 Ark. boys' murders back in spotlight |newspaper=[[Seattle Post Intelligencer]] | date=May 5, 1993}}&lt;/ref&gt; the convictions were upheld on direct appeal.&lt;ref name=autogenerated2 /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Misskelley v. State'', [http://opinions.aoc.arkansas.gov/weblink8/ElectronicFile.aspx?docid=167688&amp;dbid=0 323 Ark. 449], 915 S.W.2d 702 ([https://scholar.google.com/scholar_case?case=6154971229985931214 Google Scholar]), ''cert. denied'', 519 U.S. 898 (1996); ''Echols &amp; Baldwin v. State'', [http://opinions.aoc.arkansas.gov/weblink8/ElectronicFile.aspx?docid=198989&amp;dbid=0 326 Ark. 917], 936 S.W.2d 509 (1996) ([https://scholar.google.com/scholar_case?case=13878855919587353218 Google Scholar]), ''cert. denied'', 520 U.S. 1244 (1997).&lt;/ref&gt; In June 1996, Misskelley's lawyer, Dan Stidham, was preparing an appeal to the U.S. Supreme Court.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.arktimes.com/arkansas/john-grisham-meet-dan-stidham/Content?oid=1886139 |title=John Grisham, meet Dan Stidham |first=James |last=Morgan |date=June 7, 1996 |newspaper=Arkansas Times |quote=Stidham has sent off for his credentials to argue before the United States Supreme Court. [...] he continues to prepare the appeal he hopes to make before the U.S. Supreme Court. }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2007, Echols petitioned for a retrial, based on a statute permitting post-conviction testing of DNA evidence due to technological advances made since 1994 which might provide [[exoneration]] for the wrongfully convicted.&lt;ref&gt;Henry Weinstein,
[http://articles.latimes.com/2007/oct/30/nation/na-satanic30 Lawyers file DNA motion in Cub Scout murder case], Los Angeles Times October 30, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; However, the original trial judge, Judge [[David Burnett (politician)|David Burnett]], disallowed presentation of this information in his court. This ruling was in turn thrown out by the Arkansas Supreme Court as to all three defendants on November 4, 2010.&lt;ref&gt;''Echols v. State'', [http://opinions.aoc.arkansas.gov/WebLink8/ElectronicFile.aspx?docid=50543&amp;dbid=0 2010 Ark. 417], 373 S.W.3d 892 ([https://scholar.google.com/scholar_case?case=13863772236063736198 Google Scholar]) (reversing and remanding to reconsider trial court's denial of def't's motion for new trial); ''Baldwin v. State'', [http://opinions.aoc.arkansas.gov/WebLink8/ElectronicFile.aspx?docid=50524&amp;dbid=0 2010 Ark. 412] ([https://scholar.google.com/scholar_case?case=17616598448398470432 Google Scholar]) (same); ''Misskelley v. State'', [http://opinions.aoc.arkansas.gov/WebLink8/ElectronicFile.aspx?docid=50543&amp;dbid=0 2010 Ark. 415] ([https://scholar.google.com/scholar_case?case=17315612793394076898 Google Scholar]) (same).&lt;/ref&gt;

===John Mark Byers' knife (1993)===
John Mark Byers, the adoptive father of victim Christopher Byers, gave a knife to cameraman Doug Cooper, who was working with documentary makers [[Joe Berlinger]] and Bruce Sinofsky while filming the first ''[[Paradise Lost: The Child Murders at Robin Hood Hills|Paradise Lost]]'' feature. The knife was a folding [[hunting knife]] manufactured by [[Kershaw Knives|Kershaw]]. According to the statements given by Berlinger and Sinofsky, Cooper informed them of his receipt of the knife on December 19, 1993. After the documentary crew returned to New York, Berlinger and Sinofsky were reported to have discovered what appeared to be blood on the knife. HBO executives ordered them to return the knife to the West Memphis Police Department. The knife was not received at the West Memphis Police Department until January 8, 1994.

Byers initially claimed the knife had never been used. However, after blood was found on the knife, Byers stated that he had used it only once, to cut deer meat. When told the blood matched both his and Chris' blood type, Byers said he had no idea how that blood might have gotten on the knife. During interrogation, West Memphis police suggested to Byers that he might have left the knife out accidentally, and Byers agreed with this.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leveritt03&quot; /&gt; Byers later stated that he may have cut his thumb. Further testing of the knife produced inconclusive results about the source of the blood. Uncertainty remained due to the small amount of blood&lt;ref name=&quot;Leveritt03&quot; /&gt; and because both John Mark Byers and Chris Byers had the same [[Human leukocyte antigen|HLA]]-DQα genotype.

Byers agreed to and passed a polygraph test about the murders during the filming of ''Paradise Lost 2: Revelations'', but the documentary indicated that Byers was under the influence of several [[psychoactive drug|psychoactive prescription]] [[Pharmaceutical drug|medications]] that could have affected the test results.

===Possible teeth imprints (1996–1997)===
Following their convictions, Echols, Misskelley, and Baldwin submitted imprints of their teeth. These were compared to the alleged bite marks on Stevie Branch's forehead that had not been mentioned in the original autopsy or trial. No matches were found.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Devil's Knot: The True Story of the West Memphis Three |last=Leveritt |first=Mara |year=2003 |publisher=Simon &amp; Schuster |isbn=0-7434-1760-7 |pages=334–5}}&lt;/ref&gt; John Mark Byers had his teeth removed in 1997, after the first trial but before an imprint could be made. His stated reasons for the removal are apparently contradictory. He has claimed both that the [[Epileptic seizure|seizure]] medication he was taking caused [[Periodontal pathology|periodontal disease]], and that he planned the removal because of other kinds of dental problems which had troubled him for years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Devil's Knot: The True Story of the West Memphis Three |last=Leveritt |first=Mara |year=2003 |publisher=Simon &amp; Schuster |isbn=0-7434-1760-7 |pages=310}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After an expert examined autopsy photos and noted what he thought might be the imprint of a belt buckle on Byers' corpse, the elder Byers revealed to the police that he had [[spanking|spanked]] his stepson shortly before the boy disappeared.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leveritt03&quot; /&gt;

===Vicki Hutcheson's recantation (2003)===

In October 2003, Vicki Hutcheson, who had played a part in the arrests of Misskelley, Echols, and Baldwin, gave an interview to the ''[[Arkansas Times]]'' in which she stated that every word she had given to the police was a fabrication.&lt;ref name=&quot;AT100704&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|first=Tim|last=Hackler|title=Complete Fabrication|url=https://www.arktimes.com/arkansas/complete-fabrication/Content?oid=1886107|work=[[Arkansas Times]]|date=October 7, 2004|access-date=May 5, 2017 }}&lt;/ref&gt; She further asserted that the police had implied that if she did not cooperate with them they would take away her child.&lt;ref name=&quot;AT100704&quot;/&gt; She said that when she visited the police station, employees had photographs of Echols, Baldwin, and Misskelley on the wall and were using them as [[darts|dart]] targets.&lt;ref name=&quot;AT100704&quot;/&gt; She also claims that an audiotape the police said was &quot;unintelligible&quot; (and that they eventually lost) was perfectly clear and contained no incriminating statements.&lt;ref name=&quot;AT100704&quot;/&gt;
&lt;!-- Do not reinsert the paragraph removed here on James Martin Sr, without first finding a reliable source. The paragraph has been moved to [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk:West_Memphis_3#Potential_Libel this link atTalk] if you wish to discuss the situation. Thanks. --&gt;

===DNA testing and new physical evidence (2007)===
In 2007, DNA collected from the crime scene was tested. None was found to match DNA from Echols, Baldwin, or Misskelley. A hair &quot;not inconsistent with&quot; Stevie Branch's stepfather, Terry Hobbs, was found tied into the knots used to bind one of the victims.&lt;ref&gt;Mara Leveritt and Max Brantley [http://www.arktimes.com/Articles/ArticleViewer.aspx?ArticleID=f1b058c2-82ac-455c-b193-83cfce18215d New evidence in West Memphis murders], ''Arkansas Times'', July 19, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; The prosecutors, while conceding that no DNA evidence tied the accused to the crime scene, said: &quot;The State stands behind its convictions of Echols and his codefendants.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.kait8.com/Global/story.asp?S=6820082&amp;nav=0jsh|title=KAIT: Mother of West Memphis 3 Victim Speaks About New DNA Evidence|publisher=Kait8.com|accessdate=August 19, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Pamela Hobbs' May 5, 2009 declaration in the United States District Court, Eastern District of Arkansas, Western Division indicates that &quot;one hair was consistent with the hair of [Terry's] friend, David Jacoby&quot; (Point 16), and:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Hobbs, Pamela Marie|url=http://callahan.8k.com/wm3/p_hobbs_declaration1.html|title=Declaration of Pamela Marie Hobbs|publisher=THE UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT, EASTERN DISTRICT OF ARKANSAS, WESTERN DIVISION, ''TERRY HOBBS, Plaintiff, v. NATALIE PASDAR, et al., Defendants, CV NO.: 4-09-CV-0008BSM|date=May 20, 2009|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160115020214/http://callahan.8k.com/wm3/p_hobbs_declaration1.html|archivedate=January 15, 2016|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|17. Additionally, after the Murders my sister Jo Lynn McCauhey and I found in Terry's nightstand a knife that Stevie carried with him constantly and which I had believed was with him when he died. It was a pocket knife that my father had given to Stevie, and Stevie loved that knife. I had been shocked that the police did not find it with Stevie when they found his body. I had always assumed that my son's murderer had taken the knife during the crime. I could not believe it was in Terry's things. He had never told me that he had it.

18. Also, my sister Jo Lynn told me that she saw Terry wash clothes, bed linens and curtains from Stevie's room at an odd time around the time of the Murders.

19. There was additional new evidence discovered in 2007 that I cannot now recall.}}

===Foreman and jury misconduct (2008)===
In July 2008, it was revealed that Kent Arnold, the jury foreman on the Echols-Baldwin trial, had discussed the case with an attorney prior to the beginning of deliberations. Arnold was accused of advocating for the guilt of the West Memphis Three and sharing knowledge of inadmissible evidence, like the Jessie Misskelley statements, with other jurors.&lt;ref name=&quot;ForemanArnold&quot;&gt;Beth Warren, &quot;[http://westmemphisthreediscussion.yuku.com/topic/8273/t/Jury-foreman--West-Memphis-Three-trial--Damien-Echols-accus.html Jury foreman in West Memphis Three trial of Damien Echols accused of misconduct],&quot; ''[[Memphis Commercial Appeal]]'', October 13, 2010&lt;/ref&gt; At the time, legal experts agreed that this issue could result in the reversal of the convictions of Jason Baldwin and Damien Echols.&lt;ref name=&quot;ForemanArnold&quot;/&gt;

In September 2008, attorney (now judge) Daniel Stidham, who represented Misskelley in 1994, testified at a postconviction relief hearing. Stidham testified under oath that during the trial, Judge David Burnett erred by making an improper communication with the jury during its deliberations. Stidham overheard Judge Burnett discuss taking a lunch break with the jury foreman and heard the foreman reply that the jury was almost finished. He testified Judge Burnett responded, &quot;You'll need food for when you come back for sentencing,&quot; and that the foreman asked in return what would happen if the defendant was acquitted. Stidham said the judge closed the door without answering. He testified that his own failure to put this incident on the court record and his failure to meet the minimum requirements in state law to represent a defendant in a [[capital murder]] case was evidence of [[ineffective assistance of counsel]] and that Misskelley's conviction should therefore be vacated.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Former lawyer supports effort for a new trial |author=The Associated Press |work=Arkansas Online |publisher=Arkansas Democrat-Gazette, Inc |date=September 30, 2008 |url=http://www.arkansasonline.com/news/2008/sep/30/former-lawyer/ |accessdate=January 24, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Request for retrial (2007–2010)===
On October 29, 2007, papers were filed in federal court by Echols's defense lawyers seeking a [[retrial]] or his immediate release from prison. The filing cited DNA evidence linking Terry Hobbs (stepfather of one of the victims) to the crime scene, and new statements from Hobbs' now ex-wife. Also presented in the filing was new expert testimony that the supposed knife marks on the victims, including the injuries to Byers' genitals, were in fact the result of animal predation after the bodies had been dumped.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.arktimes.com/blogs/arkansasblog/2007/11/west_memphis_3_press_conferenc.aspx Arkansas Blog: West Memphis 3 Press Conference&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071103111907/http://www.arktimes.com/blogs/arkansasblog/2007/11/west_memphis_3_press_conferenc.aspx |date=November 3, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

On September 10, 2008, Circuit Court Judge David Burnett denied the request for a retrial, citing the DNA tests as inconclusive.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.nesting.com/news/national/131401/Judge-rejects-request-for-new-trial-for-3-men-convicted-of-1993-slayings-of-3-Arkansas-boys.html |title=Judge rejects request for new trial for 3 men convicted of 1993 slayings of 3 Arkansas boys |agency=Associated Press |first=Jill |last=Zeman |work=Nesting.com |accessdate=January 25, 2012 |date=September 10, 2008 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://archive.is/20120913182412/http://www.nesting.com/news/national/131401/Judge-rejects-request-for-new-trial-for-3-men-convicted-of-1993-slayings-of-3-Arkansas-boys.html |archivedate=September 13, 2012 |df=mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; That ruling was appealed to the Arkansas Supreme Court, which heard oral arguments in the case on September 30, 2010.

===Arkansas Supreme Court ruling (2010)===
On November 4, 2010, the Arkansas Supreme Court ordered a lower judge to consider whether newly analyzed DNA evidence might exonerate the three.&lt;ref name=ap/&gt; The justices also instructed the lower court to examine claims of misconduct by the jurors who sentenced Damien Echols to death and Jessie Misskelley and Jason Baldwin to life in prison.&lt;ref name=ap&gt;{{cite news|url=http://hosted.ap.org/dynamic/stories/U/US_ARKANSAS_BOYS_SLAIN?SITE=AP&amp;SECTION=HOME&amp;TEMPLATE=DEFAULT |title=New hearing ordered for 3 in Ark. scout deaths|author=Bleed, Jill Zeman|agency=Associated Press|accessdate=November 10, 2010|date= November 4, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In early December 2010, David Burnett was elected to the [[Arkansas Senate#Members of the 89th Senate|Arkansas State Senate]]. Circuit Court Judge David Laser was selected to replace David Burnett and preside in the evidentiary hearings mandated by the successful appeal.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.arkansasonline.com/news/2010/dec/01/new-judge-appointed-west-memphis-appeals/?news|title=New judge appointed for West Memphis appeals|agency=The Associated Press|work=Arkansas Online|publisher=Arkansas Democrat-Gazette, Inc.|date=December 1, 2010|accessdate=January 25, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Plea deal and release (2011)===
After weeks of negotiations, on August 19, 2011, Echols, Baldwin and Misskelley were released from prison as part of a plea deal, making the hearings ordered by the Arkansas Supreme Court unnecessary.&lt;ref name=nyt_alford/&gt; The three entered into unusual [[Alford plea]] deals. The Alford plea is a legal mechanism that allows defendants to plead guilty while still asserting their actual innocence, in cases where defendants concede that prosecutors have sufficient evidence to secure a conviction. Stephen Braga, an attorney with Ropes &amp; Gray who took up Echols's defense on a [[pro bono]] basis beginning in 2009, negotiated the plea agreement with prosecutors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Randazzo|first=Sara|title=The Ropes &amp; Gray Partner Who Helped Free the West Memphis Three|url=http://www.ropesgray.com/files/upload/002081104RopesGray.pdf|publisher=American Lawyer Daily|accessdate=September 21, 2011|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120406021648/http://www.ropesgray.com/files/upload/002081104RopesGray.pdf|archivedate=April 6, 2012|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Under the deal, Judge David Laser vacated the previous convictions, including the capital murder convictions for Echols and Baldwin, and ordered a new trial. Each man then entered an Alford plea to lesser charges of first- and second-degree murder while verbally stating their innocence. Judge Laser then sentenced them to [[time served]], a total of 18 years and 78 days, and they were each given a suspended imposition of sentence for 10 years.&lt;ref name=nyt_alford&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2011/08/20/us/20arkansas.html|newspaper= The New York Times|title=Deal Frees 'West Memphis Three' in Arkansas|first=Campbell|last=Robertson|date=August 19, 2011|accessdate=2011-08-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; If they re-offend they can be sent back to prison for 21 years.&lt;ref name=ArOnline/&gt;

Factors cited by prosecutor Scott Ellington for agreeing to the plea deal included that two of the victims' families had joined the cause of the defense, that the mother of a witness who testified about Echols's confession had questioned her daughter's truthfulness, and that the State Crime Lab employee who collected fiber evidence at the Echols and Baldwin homes after their arrests had died.&lt;ref&gt;Max Brantley, [http://www.arktimes.com/ArkansasBlog/archives/2011/08/19/prosecutors-statement-on-west-memphis-3-plea-deal Prosecutor's statement on West Memphis 3 plea deal] ''[[Arkansas Times]]'' August 19, 2011&lt;/ref&gt; As part of the plea deal, the three men cannot pursue civil action against the state for wrongful imprisonment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://ozarksfirst.com/fulltext?nxd_id=511867 |title=West Memphis Three Attorneys Discuss Alford Plea Details|publisher=Maxwell S. Kennerly |last=Libby |first=Karen |date=August 26, 2011 |accessdate=January 24, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many of the men's supporters, and opponents who still believe them guilty, were unhappy with the unusual plea deal.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Leveritt |first=Mara |title=FLASH: West Memphis 3 freed in plea bargain |work=Arkansas Blog |publisher=Arkansas Times |date=August 19, 2011 |url=http://www.arktimes.com/ArkansasBlog/archives/2011/08/19/flash-west-memphis-3-freed-in-plea-bargain-on-1993-murders |accessdate=January 24, 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2011, supporters pushed Arkansas Governor Mike Beebe to pardon Echols, Baldwin, and Misskelley based on their innocence. Beebe said he would deny the request unless there was evidence showing someone else committed the murders.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=West Memphis 3, locked up 18 years, together in NY |last=Bauder |first=David |date=October 10, 2011 |work=Houston Chronicle |publisher=Hearst Newspapers |url=http://www.chron.com/default/article/West-Memphis-3-locked-up-18-years-together-in-NY-2211385.php |accessdate=January 25, 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Prosecutor Scott Ellington said the Arkansas state crime laboratory would help seek other suspects by running searches on any DNA evidence produced in private laboratory tests during the defense team's investigation. This would include running the results through the FBI's [[CODIS|Combined DNA Index System]] database.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Arkansas crime lab to study 'West Memphis 3' case DNA |last=Demillo |first=Andrew |agency=Associated Press |work=The Commercial Appeal |publisher=Scripps Newspaper Group—Online |date=August 27, 2011 |url=http://www.commercialappeal.com/news/2011/aug/27/ark-crime-lab-to-study-wm3-case-dna/?print=1 |accessdate=January 25, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ellington said that, although he still considered the men guilty, the three would likely be acquitted if a new trial were held because of the powerful legal counsel representing them now, the loss of evidence over time, and the change of heart among some of the witnesses.&lt;ref name=nyt_alford/&gt;

==Family and law enforcement opinions==
The families of the three victims are divided in their opinions as to the guilt or innocence of the West Memphis Three. In 2000, the biological father of Christopher Byers, Rick Murray, expressed his doubts about the guilty verdicts on the West Memphis Three website.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Rick Murray speaks out |work=Free the West Memphis Three |url=http://www.wm3.org/live/thevictims/letter.php |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070703223027/http://www.wm3.org/live/thevictims/letter.php |archivedate=July 3, 2007 |date=May 2000 |last=Rick |first=Murray}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2007, Pamela Hobbs, the mother of victim Stevie Branch, joined those who have publicly questioned the verdicts, calling for a reopening of the verdicts and further investigation of the evidence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |newspaper=Arkansas Times |last1=Leveritt |first1=Mara |last2=Brantley |first2=Max |title=New evidence in West Memphis murders |date=July 19, 2007 |url=http://www.arktimes.com/gyrobase/new-evidence-in-west-memphis-murders/Content?oid=868140&amp;showFullText=true |accessdate=January 24, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In late 2007, John Mark Byers—who was previously vehement in his belief that Echols, Misskelley, and Baldwin were guilty—also announced that he now believes that they are innocent.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Father of Victim to Convicted Killer: &quot;I'm Here for You&quot; |last=Avila |first=Jim |date=November 1, 2007 |url=http://abcnews.go.com/TheLaw/story?id=3808760&amp;page=1#.Tx82L4F9tBk |accessdate=January 24, 2012 |work=ABC News |publisher=ABC News Internet Ventures}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;I had made the comment if it were ever proven the three were innocent, I'd be the first to lead the charge for their freedom,&quot; said Byers, and take &quot;every opportunity that I have to voice that the West Memphis Three are innocent and the evidence and proof prove they're innocent.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;coleman&quot;&gt;Alex Coleman, &quot;[http://www.wreg.com/wreg-mark-byers-story,0,2109569.story Victim's father wants West Memphis 3 set free]&quot;, [[WREG]], February 26, 2010&lt;/ref&gt; Byers has spoken to the media on behalf of the convicted, and has expressed his desire for justice for the families of both the victims and the three accused.&lt;ref name=&quot;coleman&quot; /&gt;

In 2010, district Judge Brian S. Miller ordered Terry Hobbs, the stepfather of victim Stevie Branch, to pay $17,590 to [[Dixie Chicks]] singer [[Natalie Maines]] for legal costs stemming from a [[defamation]] lawsuit he filed against the band. Miller dismissed a suit Hobbs filed over Maines' remarks and writings implying that he was involved in killing his stepson. The judge said Hobbs had chosen to involve himself in public discussion over whether the convictions were just.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cbsnews.com/8301-504083_162-20002775-504083.html Dixie Chicks' Natalie Maines Wins &quot;West Memphis Three&quot; Defamation Suit], ''[[CNN]]'', April 19, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

[[John E. Douglas]], a former longtime FBI agent and current criminal profiler, said that the murders were more indicative of a single murderer intent on degrading and punishing the victims, than of a trio of &quot;unsophisticated&quot; teenagers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.commercialappeal.com/news/2010/nov/07/profiler-convinced-innocence-west-memphis-three/?print=1 |date=November 7, 2010 |title=Professional profiler convinced of innocence of West Memphis Three |work=The Commercial Appeal |location=Memphis, TN |publisher=Scripps Newspaper Group—Online |last=Warren |first=Beth |accessdate=January 24, 2012 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20101112094254/http://www.commercialappeal.com/news/2010/nov/07/profiler-convinced-innocence-west-memphis-three/?print=1 |url-status=dead |archive-date=November 12, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Douglas believed that the perpetrator had a violent history and was familiar with the victims and with local geography. Douglas was formerly FBI Unit Chief for 25 years of the Investigative Support Unit of the [[National Center for the Analysis of Violent Crime]]. He stated in his report for Echols's legal team that there was no evidence the murders were linked to satanic rituals and that post-mortem animal predation could explain the alleged knife injuries. He said that the victims had died from a combination of blunt force trauma and drowning, in a crime which he believed was driven by personal cause.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.eldoradonews.com/news/2017/oct/13/mindhunter-former-fbi-unit-chief-recalls-high-prof/ |newspaper=El Dorado News-Times |title=Mindhunter: Former FBI unit chief recalls high-profile cases |date=October 11, 2017 |first=Brittany |last=Williams |access-date=March 10, 2018 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Documentaries, publications and studies==
Three films, ''[[Paradise Lost: The Child Murders at Robin Hood Hills]]'', ''[[Paradise Lost 2: Revelations]]'', and ''[[Paradise Lost 3: Purgatory]]'', directed by [[Joe Berlinger and Bruce Sinofsky]], have documented this case and are strongly critical of the verdict. The films marked the first time [[Metallica]] allowed their music to be used in a movie, which drew attention to the case.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.mtv.com/news/articles/1432105/19980528/metallica.jhtml | title=Metallica May Give Music To &quot;Paradise Lost&quot; Sequel |publisher=MTV | date=May 28, 1998 | accessdate =November 24, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There have been a number of books about the case, also arguing that the suspects were wrongly convicted: ''[[Devil's Knot]]'' by Mara Leveritt; ''Blood of Innocents'' by Guy Reel; and ''The Last Pentacle of the Sun: Writings in Support of the West Memphis Three'', edited by Brett Alexander Savory &amp; M. W. Anderson, and featuring dark fiction and non-fiction by well-known writers of speculative fiction. In 2005, Damien Echols completed his memoir, ''Almost Home, Vol 1'', offering his perspective of the case.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Almost Home: My Life Story Vol 1|first=Damien|last=Echols|publisher=iUniverse, Inc.|date=June 3, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; A biography of John Mark Byers by Greg Day named ''Untying the Knot: John Mark Byers and the West Memphis Three'' was published in May 2012.&lt;ref&gt;Greg Day, &quot;[http://www.johnmarkbyers.com/Introduction.html Untying The Knot: John Mark Byers and the West Memphis child murders]&quot;. Retrieved August 21, 2011 {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120608082830/http://www.johnmarkbyers.com/Introduction.html |date=June 8, 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many songs were written about the case, and two albums released in support of the defendants. In 2000, The album ''[[Free the West Memphis 3]]'' was released by [[KOCH Records]]. Organized by [[Eddie Spaghetti]] of the band [[Supersuckers]], the album featured a number of original songs about the case and other recordings by artists such as [[Steve Earle]], [[Tom Waits]], [[L7 (band)|L7]], and [[Joe Strummer]]. In 2002, [[Henry Rollins]] worked with other vocalists from various rock, hip hop, punk and metal groups and members of [[Black Flag (band)|Black Flag]] and the [[Rollins Band]] on the compilation album ''[[Rise Above: 24 Black Flag Songs to Benefit the West Memphis Three]]''. All money raised from sales of the album are donated to the legal funds of the West Memphis Three. Metalcore band [[Zao (US band)|Zao]]'s 2002 album ''Parade of Chaos'' included a track inspired by the case named &quot;Free The Three&quot;. On April 28, 2011, the band [[Disturbed (band)|Disturbed]] released a song entitled &quot;3&quot; as a download on their website. The song is about the West Memphis Three, with 100% of the proceeds going to their benefit foundation for their release.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Disturbed Release Benefit Single for West Memphis Three |date=April 30, 2011 |publisher=Starpulse.com |url=http://www.starpulse.com/news/index.php/2011/04/30/disturbed_release_benefit_single_for_w |accessdate=January 24, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A website by Martin David Hill, containing approximately 160,000 words and intending to be a &quot;thorough investigation&quot;, collates and discusses many details surrounding the murders and investigation, including some anecdotal information.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.jivepuppi.com/index.html|title=Murders in West Memphis|author=Martin David Hill|accessdate=August 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Investigative journalist [[Aphrodite Jones]] undertook an exploration of the case on her [[Discovery Network]] show ''True Crime With Aphrodite Jones'' following the DNA discoveries. The episode premiered May 5, 2011, with extensive background information included on the show's page at the Investigation Discovery site. In August 2011, White Light Productions announced that the West Memphis Three would be featured on their new program ''Wrongfully Convicted''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://ireport.cnn.com/docs/DOC-655378 | publisher=CNN | title=West Memphis Three 'Wrongully Convicted Episode Trailer White Light Productions'&amp;nbsp;– CNN iReport}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In January 2010, the CBS television news journal ''[[48 Hours (TV series)|48 Hours]]'' aired &quot;The Memphis 3&quot;, an in-depth coverage of the history of the case including interviews with Echols and supporters. On September 17, 2011, ''48 Hours'' re-aired the episode with the update of their release and interviews from Echols and his wife, and Baldwin. ''[[Piers Morgan Tonight]]'' aired an episode on September 29, 2011, about the three's plans for the future and continued investigations on the case.&lt;ref name=&quot;cnn2011&quot;/&gt;

''[[West of Memphis]]'', directed and written by [[Amy J. Berg]], and produced by [[Peter Jackson]], as well as by Echols himself, premiered at the [[2012 Sundance Film Festival]]. Actor [[Johnny Depp]], a longtime supporter of the West Memphis Three and personal friend of Damien Echols, was on hand to support the film in its premiere at the [[Toronto International Film Festival]] in 2012.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.mtv.com/news/articles/1693481/johnny-depp-west-of-memphis-2012-tiff.jhtml |last=Rosenfield |first=Kat |publisher=MTV |title=Johnny Depp Reveals Anguish Over West Memphis Three Injustice |date=September 9, 2012 |access-date=February 21, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Atom Egoyan]] directed a dramatized feature film of the case, titled ''[[Devil's Knot (film)|Devil's Knot]]'', released in U.S. theaters on May 9, 2014. The film stars [[Reese Witherspoon]] and [[Colin Firth]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine |url=http://insidemovies.ew.com/2014/02/10/devils-knot-reese-witherspoon-west-memphis-three-release-date/ |last=Labrecque |first=Jeff |magazine=Entertainment Weekly |title=West Memphis Three drama 'Devil's Knot' with Reese Witherspoon sets release |date=February 10, 2014 |accessdate=February 21, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Defendants==

===Jessie Misskelley===
Jessie Misskelley Jr. (born July 10, 1975) was arrested in connection to the murders of May 5, 1993. After a reported 12 hours of interrogation by police, Misskelley, who has an IQ of 72, confessed to the murders, and implicated Baldwin and Echols. However, the confession was at odds with facts known by police, such as the time of the murders.&lt;ref name=ArOnline&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.arkansasonline.com/news/2011/aug/19/breaking-plea-reached-west-memphis-murders/?breaking
 |work=ArkansasOnline
 |author=Arkansas Democrat-Gazette
 |title=Plea reached in West Memphis murders
 |date=August 19, 2011
 |accessdate=2011-08-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=nyt_alford/&gt; Under the &quot;''Bruton'' rule&quot;, his confession could not be admitted against his co-defendants and thus he was tried separately. Misskelley was convicted by a jury of one count of first-degree murder and two counts of second-degree murder. The court sentenced him to [[life in prison|life]] plus 40 years in prison. His conviction was appealed and affirmed by the Arkansas Supreme Court.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
 |url=http://www.cnn.com/2010/CRIME/11/04/arkansas.west.memphis.three/
 |title=West Memphis 3 cases to receive hearing, possible new trial
 |publisher=cnn |date=November 4, 2010
 |accessdate=2010-11-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On August 19, 2011, Misskelley, along with Baldwin and Echols, entered an [[Alford plea]]. Judge David Laser then sentenced them to 18 years and 78 days, the amount of time they had served, and also levied a suspended sentence of 10 years. All three were released from prison that same day.&lt;ref name=nyt_alford/&gt; Since his release, Misskelley has become engaged to his high school girlfriend and enrolled in a community college to train as an auto mechanic.

===Charles Jason Baldwin===
Charles Jason Baldwin&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.adc.arkansas.gov/inmate_info/search.php?dcnum=103335&amp;lastname=baldwin&amp;sex=b&amp;agetype=1|title=ADC Inmate Search&amp;nbsp;– Inmate Details|publisher=Arkansas Department of Correction|quote=Information Current as of 08/09/2011|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110809172107/http://adc.arkansas.gov/inmate_info/search.php?dcnum=103335&amp;lastname=baldwin&amp;sex=b&amp;agetype=1 |archivedate=2011-08-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; (born April 11, 1977) along with Misskelley and Echols, entered an Alford plea on August 19, 2011.&lt;ref name=ArOnline/&gt; Baldwin pleaded guilty to three counts of [[first degree murder]] while still asserting his actual innocence. The judge then sentenced the three men to 18 years and 78 days, the amount of time they had served, and also levied a suspended sentence of 10 years.

Baldwin was initially resistant to agree to this deal, insisting as a matter of principle that he would not plead guilty to something he did not do. But, he said, his refusal would have meant that Echols stayed on death row. &quot;This was not justice,&quot; he said of the deal. &quot;However, they're trying to kill Damien.&quot;&lt;ref name=nyt_alford/&gt; Since his release, Baldwin has moved to Seattle to live with friends. He is in a relationship with a woman who befriended him while he was in prison. He has stated that he plans on enrolling in college to become a lawyer in order to help [[miscarriage of justice|wrongfully convicted]] persons prove their innocence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Q&amp;A: Paradise Lost directors Joe Berlinger and Bruce Sinofsky |url=http://www.grantland.com/story/_/id/7456398/child-murders-robin-hood-hills-directors-joe-berlinger-bruce-sinofsky |first=Davy |last=Rothbart |date=January 12, 2012 |work=Grantland |publisher=ESPN Internet Ventures |accessdate=January 24, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Baldwin said in a 2011 interview with [[Piers Morgan]] that he worked for a construction company and he was learning how to drive.&lt;ref name=&quot;cnn2011&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.cnn.com/2011/09/29/justice/piers-morgan-west-memphis-three/index.html?&amp;hpt=hp_c1|title=Decades without daylight: 'West Memphis Three' describe life in prison|publisher=CNN |author=CNN Wire Staff|access-date=September 30, 2011|date=September 29, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Damien Wayne Echols===
Damien Wayne Echols (born Michael Wayne Hutchison,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Perrusquia|first=Marc|title=Damien Echols may be troubled but he's not killer, some say|newspaper=The Commercial Appeal|location=Memphis|date=February 27, 1994|url=http://www.commercialappeal.com/news/1994/feb/27/damien-echols-may-be-troubled-hes-not-killer-some-|accessdate=September 27, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; December 11, 1974) was on death row, locked-down 23 hours per day at the [[Varner Unit]] Supermax.&lt;ref name=&quot;CB&quot;/&gt; On August 19, 2011, Echols, along with Baldwin and Misskelley, was released from prison after their attorneys and the judge handling the upcoming retrial agreed to a deal. Under the terms of the Alford guilty plea, Echols and his co-defendants accepted the sufficiency of evidence supporting the three counts of [[first degree murder]] while maintaining their innocence. DNA evidence at the scene was not found to include any from Echols or his co-defendants.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2007/10/30/us/30satanic.html |title=Defense Offers New Evidence in a Murder Case That Shocked Arkansas |date=October 30, 2007 |newspaper=The New York Times |first=-Shaila |last=Dewan |quote=according to long-awaited new evidence ..., there was no DNA from the three defendants found at the scene }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Echols, ADC# 000931, entered the system on March 19, 1994.&lt;ref name=&quot;ADCProf&quot;/&gt; Until August 2011, he was incarcerated in the [[Arkansas Department of Correction]] (ADC) Varner Unit [[Supermax]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ADCProf&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.adc.arkansas.gov/inmate_info/search.php?dcnum=000931&amp;lastname=Echols&amp;firstname=Damien&amp;sex=b&amp;agetype=1 Echols profile], Arkansas Department of Correction website; retrieved November 25, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Feyerick, Deborah and Stephanie Chen. [http://www.cnn.com/2010/CRIME/09/28/west.memphis.3.damien.echols/index.html?hpt=C1 &quot;Echols of West Memphis 3 talks about appeal, death row&quot;], cnn.com. September 29, 2010; retrieved September 29, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; In prison in 1999, he married [[landscape architect]] Lorri Davis. He moved to New York City after his release.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.arktimes.com/arkansas/the-damien-i-know-the-architect-and-the-inmate/Content?oid=964930|title=The Damien I Know&amp;nbsp;– The Architect and the Inmate|first=Mara|last=Leveritt|work=arktimes.com|year=2011|accessdate=October 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Appeal====
Echols' mental stability during the years immediately prior to the murders and during his trial was the focus of his appellate legal team in their appeal attempts. In his efforts to win a new trial, Echols, 27 at the time of the appeal, claimed he was incompetent to stand trial because of a history of mental illness. The record on appeal spells out a long history of Echols' mental health problems, including a May 5, 1992, Arkansas Department of Youth Services referral for possible mental illness, a year to the day before the murders.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Commercial Appeal&quot;&gt;[http://www.commercialappeal.com/news/2002/apr/21/case-lives-echols-seeks-new-trial/ The Commercial Appeal]&lt;/ref&gt; Hospital records for his treatment in Little Rock 11 months before the killings show a history of self-mutilation and assertions to hospital staff that he gained power by drinking blood, that he had inside him the spirit of a woman who had killed her husband, and that he was having [[hallucinations]]. He also told mental health workers that he was &quot;going to influence the world.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;The Commercial Appeal&quot;/&gt;

The appellate legal team argued that Echols did not waive his assertion that he was not mentally competent before his 1994 trial because he was not competent to waive it. To assist in the appeals process, Echols' appellate legal team retained a [[Berkeley, California]]-based forensic psychiatrist, Dr. George Woods, to make their case.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.google.com/#hl=en&amp;cp=22&amp;gs_id=1v&amp;xhr=t&amp;q=george+woods+affidavit&amp;qe=Z2VvcmdlIHdvb2RzIGFmZmlkYXZpdA&amp;qesig=x8JP9oD_NNAwFulC1e7wdQ&amp;pkc=AFgZ2tkKCrLJL-Gah6Ym1NST-Xj5fA-aJJc-_QUUbthyn6XdbIPD0sjwW1tdvo5rQeW1JhoYqiMazKArIzCXbvsu-uJ5WCPYzQ&amp;pf=p&amp;sclient=ps&amp;fp=1&amp;bav=on.2,or.r_gc.r_pw.,cf.osb&amp;cad=b George Woods Affidavit], google.com; accessed October 5, 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;

Echols' lawyers claimed that his condition worsened during the trial, when he developed a &quot;psychotic euphoria that caused him to believe he would evolve into a superior entity&quot; and eventually be transported to a different world. His psychosis dominated his perceptions of everything going on in court, Woods wrote.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Commercial Appeal&quot;/&gt; Echols's mental state while in prison awaiting trial was also called into question by his appellate team.{{citation needed|date=October 2015}}

====Retrial request====
While in prison, Echols wrote letters to Gloria Shettles, an investigator for his defense team.&lt;ref&gt;[http://transcripts.cnn.com/TRANSCRIPTS/0712/19/lkl.01.html CNN Larry King Live-Damien Echols Death Row Interview]&lt;/ref&gt; Echols sought to overturn his conviction based on trial error, including juror misconduct, as well as the results of a DNA Status Report filed on July 17, 2007, which concluded &quot;none of the [[DNA|genetic material]] recovered at the scene of the crimes was attributable to Mr. Echols, Echols' co-defendant, Jason Baldwin, or defendant Jessie Misskelley .... Although most of the genetic material recovered from the scene was attributable to the victims of the offenses, some of it cannot be attributed to either the victims or the defendants.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://wm3.org/live/newsevents/newsitem.php?index=1&amp;news_Id=131|title=DNA TESTING CONCLUDES|accessdate=2007-07-22|publisher=wm3.org|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070823193448/http://www.wm3.org/live/newsevents/newsitem.php?index=1&amp;news_Id=131 |archivedate=August 23, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Advanced DNA and other scientific evidence&amp;nbsp;– combined with additional evidence from several different witnesses and experts&amp;nbsp;– released in October 2007 had cast strong doubts on the original convictions. A hearing on Echols' petition for a writ of [[habeas corpus]] was held in the Federal District Court for the Eastern District of Arkansas.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.americanchronicle.com/articles/viewArticle.asp?articleID=41551 Echols' Attorneys File New Motion Claiming Wrongful Conviction In 'West Memphis Three' Case], American Chronicles, accessed October 5, 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Release====
On August 19, 2011, Echols, along with Baldwin and Misskelley, entered an [[Alford plea]], while asserting their innocence.&lt;ref name=ArOnline/&gt; The judge sentenced them to 18 years and 78 days, the amount of time they had served, and levied a suspended sentence of 10 years. Echols' sentence was reduced to three counts of [[first degree murder]]. Lawyers representing the West Memphis Three reached the plea deal that allowed the men to be released from prison. They were transferred to the hearing with their possessions. The plea deal did not technically result in a full exoneration; some of the convictions would stand, but the men would not admit guilt. The counsel representing the men said they would continue to pursue full exoneration.&lt;ref name=nyt_alford/&gt;

====Aftermath====
[[File:Damien echols 2012.jpg|thumb|Damien Echols at the 2012 [[Texas Book Festival]]]]
Echols relocated to [[Salem, Massachusetts]] with his wife and has no intentions of returning to Arkansas. In an interview with [[Piers Morgan]], he said that he would like to have a career in writing and [[visual arts]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Piers Morgan – Damien Echols On The Death Penalty – 02/08/2013|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5gv2cMLWykk}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=====Media projects=====
Echols self-published the memoir, ''Almost Home: My Life Story Vol. 1'' (2005), while still in prison.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Echols, Damien|title=Almost Home: My Life Story Vol. 1|date=June 3, 2005|isbn=9780595357017|publisher=iUniverse|url=https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/415488.Almost_Home}}&lt;/ref&gt; After his release, he has worked on a number of additional media projects.
;:Music
::*He co-wrote the lyrics to the song &quot;Army Reserve&quot;, on [[Pearl Jam]]'s [[Pearl Jam (album)|self-titled album]] (2006)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.billboard.com/articles/news/57020/ex-misfits-singer-rocks-with-west-memphis-3s-echols |title=Ex-Misfits Singer Rocks With West Memphis 3's Echols &amp;#124; Billboard.com |work=Billboard |year=2011 |accessdate=October 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
::*Echols and Michale Graves released an album titled ''Illusions'' (October 2007).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Illusions Album: Michale Graves &amp; Damien Echols|url=https://www.amazon.com/Illusions-Michale-Graves-Damien-Echols/dp/B000W04S0G}}&lt;/ref&gt;

;:Art
::*Echols began creating art while on death row as a &quot;side effect of my spiritual, magical practice.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=L.A. Times article on Damien Echols art exhibit at Copro Gallery|url=http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/arts/la-et-cm-damien-echols-art-show-20160323-story.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Copro Gallery in Los Angeles exhibited Echols' artwork (March 19 – April 16, 2016).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=SALEM Exhibit of Echols' Artwork at the Copro Gallery|url=http://www.copronason.com/salemd/}}&lt;/ref&gt; The focus of the exhibit, titled 'SALEM,' draws attention to the comparison between the historical U.S. [[Salem witch trials]] and Echols' own experience during a modern-day U.S. [[witch-hunt]] known for false accusations of [[Satanic ritual abuse]].
::*On March 23, 2016, Echols gave a presentation about his art processes at the [[Rubin Museum of Art]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=DAMIEN ECHOLS ARTISTS ON ART MARCH 25 6:15 – 7:00 PM|url=http://rubinmuseum.org/events/event/damien-echols-03-25-2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

;:Spoken word
::*The transcript of Echols' spoken word performance in ''[[The Moth]]'' is included in a written compilation of 50 stories from the show's archives, published in 2013.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Moth|date=2013|url=https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/17468561-the-moth|publisher=Hachette Books|isbn=9781401311117}}&lt;/ref&gt;

;:Written works
::*[[Punk rock|Punk]] musician [[Michale Graves]], formerly of [[Misfits (band)|The Misfits]], has written music to coincide with Echols' poetry
::*Echols' poetry has appeared in the ''Porcupine Literary Arts'' magazine (Volume 8, Issue 2)
::* He has written non-fiction for the ''Arkansas Literary Forum''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://fac.hsu.edu/beggsm/ALF/2007/2007.html Arkansas Literary Forum] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20081030071414/http://fac.hsu.edu/beggsm/ALF/2007/2007.html |date=October 30, 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
::*Since his release, he has published a non-fiction book about both his childhood and incarceration, ''Life After Death'' (2012), which includes material from his 2005 memoir&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|date=2012|publisher=Blue Rider Press|author=Echols, Damien|title=Life After Death|isbn=9780399160202|url=https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/13513092-life-after-death}}&lt;/ref&gt;
::* He and Lorri Davis, a NYC landscape architect who initiated a correspondence with Echols in 1999 and ultimately became his wife, co-authored ''Yours for Eternity: A Love Story on Death Row'' (2014)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|isbn=9780399166198|url=https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/18693685-yours-for-eternity|date=June 17, 2014|publisher=Blue Rider Press|title= Yours for Eternity: A Love Story on Death Row|authors=Echols, Damien &amp; Davis, Lorri}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|United States|1990s|Biography}}
*[[False confession#Coerced|False confession]]
*[[Moral panic]]
* [[Norfolk Four]]
* [[Witch-hunt#Metaphorical usage|Witch-hunt]] (metaphorical usage)

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
;Article
*&quot;[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DD8Vc8VKR38 WM3&amp;nbsp;– Jason Baldwin].&quot; ''[[Arkansas Times]]''. January 14, 2011.
;Video
*&quot;[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QYKRiGk0r0E WM3: Life after Prison (Complete Series)].&quot; ''[[KATV-TV]]'' (Channel 7). Ran on October 30 – November 1, 2011, video posted to [[YouTube]] on February 7, 2012.

==External links==
{{Commons}}
&lt;!--------------------------{{No more links}}------------------------------
    | PLEASE BE CAUTIOUS IN ADDING MORE LINKS TO THIS ARTICLE. Wikipedia  |
    | is not a collection of links nor should it be used for advertising. |
    |                                                                     |
    |           Excessive or inappropriate links WILL BE DELETED.         |
    | See [[Wikipedia:External links]] &amp; [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for details.  |
    |                                                                     |
    | If there are already plentiful links, please propose additions or   |
    | replacements on this article's discussion page, or submit your link |
    | to the relevant category at the Open Directory Project (dmoz.org)   |
    | and link back to that category using the {{dmoz}} template.         |
    ------------------------{{No more links}}--------------------------------&gt;
*[http://encyclopediaofarkansas.net/encyclopedia/entry-detail.aspx?entryID=3039 The Encyclopedia of Arkansas History &amp; Culture entry (The Butler Center for Arkansas Studies)]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20140314174108/http://www.crimelibrary.com/notorious_murders/famous/memphis/index_1.html West Memphis Three] at the [[Court TV]] Crime Library
*{{curlie|Society/Issues/Crime_and_Justice/Injustice/Individual_Stories/United_States/West_Memphis_Three/|West Memphis 3}}
*[http://www.commercialappeal.com/news/wm3/ Archive of West Memphis Three reports] from ''[[Memphis Commercial Appeal]]''
*Chen, Stephanie. &quot;[http://ac360.blogs.cnn.com/2010/09/29/echols-of-west-memphis-3-talks-about-appeal-death-row/ Echols of West Memphis 3 talks about appeal, death row].&quot; [[CNN]]. September 29, 2010.
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20140626043759/https://sourceforge.net/projects/disclosurevault/files/Investigations%20and%20Reports%20%20-%20Tyrants%2C%20Criminals%2C%20Murders/WEST%20MEMPHIS%203%20(huge)/ Investigation Collection Archive]

{{West Memphis Three}}
{{West Memphis, Arkansas}}
{{Authority control}}

[[Category:1993 in Arkansas]]
[[Category:1993 murders in the United States]]
[[Category:20th-century American people]]
[[Category:20th-century men]]
[[Category:American murderers of children]]
[[Category:American people convicted of murder]]
[[Category:American prisoners sentenced to death]]
[[Category:Crimes involving Satanism or the occult]]
[[Category:False confessions]]
[[Category:History of Arkansas]]
[[Category:People convicted of murder by Arkansas]]
[[Category:People who entered an Alford plea]]
[[Category:Quantified groups of defendants]]
[[Category:Satanic ritual abuse hysteria in the United States]]
[[Category:Trios]]
[[Category:West Memphis, Arkansas]]
[[Category:West Memphis Three| ]]</text>
      <sha1>gyid8qkcuovq0sbyvq8glgoy1yawwix</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
