  <page>
    <title>David Beatty, 1st Earl Beatty</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8837</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942732518</id>
      <parentid>931039315</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-26T14:11:49Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>WFinch</username>
        <id>2477977</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>added [[Category:Recipients of the Navy Distinguished Service Medal]] using [[WP:HC|HotCat]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|19th and 20th-century Royal Navy officer}}
{{EngvarB|date=July 2016}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2016}}
{{Infobox military person
|name= The Earl Beatty
|image_size= 
|caption= The Earl Beatty while a vice admiral|birth_date= {{Birth date|df=yes|1871|01|17}}
|death_date= {{Death date and age|df=yes|1936|03|12|1871|01|17}}
|birth_place= [[Stapeley]], Cheshire, England
|death_place= London, England
|image= Vice Admiral Sir David Beatty.jpg
|nickname= 
|allegiance= United Kingdom
|branch= [[Royal Navy]]
|serviceyears= 1884–1927
|rank= [[Admiral of the Fleet (Royal Navy)|Admiral of the Fleet]]
|commands= [[First Sea Lord]] (1919–27)&lt;br/&gt;[[Grand Fleet]] (1916–18)&lt;br/&gt;[[Battle Cruiser Fleet]] (1915)&lt;br/&gt; [[1st Battlecruiser Squadron]] (1913–16)&lt;br/&gt;{{HMS|Queen|1902|6}}&lt;br/&gt;{{HMS|Suffolk|1903|6}}&lt;br/&gt;[[Arrogant-class cruiser|HMS ''Arrogant'']]&lt;br/&gt;{{HMS|Juno|1895|6}}
|battles= [[Mahdist War]]
* Battle of Dongola
* [[Battle of Omdurman]]
[[Boxer Rebellion]]&lt;br/&gt;[[First World War]]
* [[Battle of Heligoland Bight (1914)|Battle of Heligoland Bight]]
* [[Battle of Dogger Bank (1915)]]
* [[Battle of Jutland]]
|awards= [[Knight Grand Cross of the Order of the Bath]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Member of the Order of Merit]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Knight Grand Cross of the Royal Victorian Order]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Distinguished Service Order]]
|laterwork=
}}
'''David Richard Beatty, 1st Earl Beatty''', {{postnominals|country=GBR|size=100|sep=,|GCB|OM|GCVO|DSO|PC}} (17 January 1871 – 11 March 1936) was a [[Royal Navy]] officer. After serving in the [[Mahdist War]] and then the response to the [[Boxer Rebellion]], he commanded the [[1st Battlecruiser Squadron]] at the [[Battle of Jutland]] in 1916, a tactically indecisive engagement after which his aggressive approach was contrasted with the caution of his commander Admiral [[John Jellicoe, 1st Earl Jellicoe|Sir John Jellicoe]]. He is remembered for his comment at Jutland that &quot;There seems to be something wrong with our bloody ships today&quot;, after two of his ships exploded. Later in the war he succeeded Jellicoe as Commander in Chief of the [[Grand Fleet]], in which capacity he received the surrender of the German [[High Seas Fleet]] at the end of the war. He then followed Jellicoe's path a second time, serving as [[First Sea Lord]]—a position that Beatty held longer (7 years 9 months) than any other First Sea Lord.  While First Sea Lord, he was involved in negotiating the [[Washington Naval Treaty]] of 1922 in which it was agreed that the United States, Britain and Japan should set their navies in a ratio of 5:5:3, with France and Italy maintaining smaller ratio fleets of 1.75 each.

==Family and childhood==
Beatty was born into an [[Anglo-Irish people|Anglo-Irish]] family at Howbeck Lodge in the parish of [[Stapeley]], near [[Nantwich]], Cheshire, on 17 January 1871.&lt;ref&gt;Roskill, p. 20&lt;/ref&gt; He was the second son of five children born to [[Captain (British Army and Royal Marines)|Captain]] David Longfield Beatty and Katherine (or Katrine) Edith Beatty (née Sadleir), both from Ireland: David Longfield had been an officer in the [[4th Queen's Own Hussars|Fourth Hussars]] where he formed a relationship with Katrine, the wife of another officer.&lt;ref name=heath23&gt;Heathcote, p. 23&lt;/ref&gt;

Katrine had fair hair and blue eyes, soft wide lips, and overall an air of command. Beatty's father was {{convert|6|ft|4|in|m|abbr=on}} tall, dark haired with big hands and feet. Both David and his elder brother Charles were short, about {{convert|5|ft|5|in|m|abbr=on}} with small hands and feet. Charles was fair haired taking after his mother's features, whereas David had more the look of his father. After the affair between David Longfield and Katrine became known, David Longfield's father (Beatty's grandfather), David Vandeleur Beatty (1815–1881), arranged for his son to be posted to India in the hope that the scandalous relationship might end. David Longfield resigned from the regiment on 21 November 1865, with the honorary rank of [[Captain (British Army and Royal Marines)|Captain]]. He took up residence with Katrine in Cheshire and in 1869 [[sale of commissions|sold his commission]].&lt;ref&gt;Beatty (1980), pp. 4–5&lt;/ref&gt; David Longfield was unable to marry Katrine until Katrine had obtained a divorce on 21 February 1871, after the birth of their first two sons. Beatty's birth certificate recorded his mother's surname as Beatty, and his parents' eventual marriage at St Michael's Church in [[Liverpool]] was kept secret.&lt;ref&gt;Beatty (1980), pp. 1–3&lt;/ref&gt;

Beatty's early education concentrated on horsemanship, hunting and learning to be a gentleman. Beatty had a close relationship with his elder brother Charles, who became his ally against their oppressive and overbearing father. They remained close throughout life, so much so that the only time Beatty felt despair was at his brother's death. Beatty later wrote to his wife about Charles, ''we lived together, played together, rode together, fought together.''&lt;ref&gt;Beatty (1980), p. 20 citing letter to Beatty's wife&lt;/ref&gt; His brothers would later join the [[British Army]], but early on young David developed an interest in ships and the sea and expressed a desire to join the [[Royal Navy]]. In 1881 Beatty's grandfather died and David Longfield succeeded to the 18th century mansion, '[[Borodale]]', outside [[Enniscorthy]], in [[County Wexford]]. After retiring from the army David Longfield established a business training horses first in Cheshire and then at 'The Mount', near [[Rugby, Warwickshire|Rugby]], Warwickshire. On inheriting and following the death of his wife at 'The Mount', David Longfield returned to Ireland abandoning the training business.&lt;ref&gt;Beatty (1980), p. 31&lt;/ref&gt;

Beatty was educated at [[Kilkenny College]] and in 1882 entered [[Burney's Academy|Burney's Naval Academy]] at [[Gosport]], which was a 'crammer' for boys wishing to take the entrance examinations for the Royal Navy.&lt;ref&gt;Beatty (1980), p. 11&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early career==
[[File:Rear Admiral David Beatty pre-1915.jpg|thumb|right|Captain David Beatty]]
Beatty joined the [[Royal Navy]] as a [[cadet]] passing into the training ship [[HMS Prince of Wales (1860)|HMS ''Britannia'']] tenth out of ninety-nine candidates in January 1884.&lt;ref name=Beatty21&gt;Roskill, p. 21&lt;/ref&gt; During his two years at ''Britannia'', moored at [[Dartmouth, Devon|Dartmouth]], he was beaten three times for various infractions. He passed out of ''Britannia'' eighteenth out of the thirty-three remaining cadets at the end of 1885.&lt;ref name=Beatty21/&gt; Beatty's letters home made no complaint about the poor living conditions in ''Britannia'', and generally he was extrovert, even aggressive, and resented discipline. However, he understood how far he could transgress without serious consequences, and this approach continued throughout his career.&lt;ref&gt;Beatty (1980), pp. 11–12&lt;/ref&gt;

Beatty was given orders to join the [[China Station]] in January 1886, but the posting did not appeal to his mother, who wrote to [[Lord Charles Beresford]], then a senior naval officer, member of parliament and personal friend, to use his influence to obtain something better.&lt;ref&gt;Beatty (1980), p. 14&lt;/ref&gt; Beatty was, in February 1886, instead appointed to {{HMS|Alexandra|1875|6}}, flagship of Admiral the [[Alfred, Duke of Saxe-Coburg and Gotha|Duke of Edinburgh]], Queen Victoria's second son Alfred, who was Commander-in-Chief of the [[Mediterranean Fleet|Mediterranean Squadron]].&lt;ref&gt;Roskill, p. 22&lt;/ref&gt; This proved an excellent social opening for Beatty, who established a longstanding relationship with the Duke's eldest daughter, [[Marie of Edinburgh|Marie]], and with other members of the court. ''Alexandra'' was a three-masted sailing ship with auxiliary steam power, nonetheless, remaining flagship in a navy which was steadily transitioning from sail to steam. Life in the Mediterranean fleet was considerably easier than cadet life, with visits to friendly ports all around the Mediterranean, but Beatty was concerned to work diligently towards naval examinations, which would determine seniority and future promotion prospects.&lt;ref&gt;Beatty (1980), pp. 15, 21&lt;/ref&gt; Beatty was promoted to [[midshipman]] on 15 May 1886&lt;ref name=heath23/&gt; and assigned to assist Lieutenant [[Stanley Colville]] on watchkeeping duties: Colville was to play an important part in Beatty's future career.&lt;ref&gt;Chalmers, p. 12&lt;/ref&gt;

Beatty left HMS ''Alexandra'' in March 1889 and joined the [[cruiser]] {{HMS|Warspite|1884|6}} in July 1889 for manoeuvres before joining the sailing corvette {{HMS|Ruby|1876|6}} in September 1889, in which he was promoted to [[sub-lieutenant]] on 14 May 1890.&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=26253|page=544|date=2 February 1892}}&lt;/ref&gt; Next he attended courses at the [[Royal Naval College (Greenwich)|Royal Naval College, Greenwich]] during which he was somewhat distracted from his naval career by the delights of London. Beatty scored a first-class examination pass in Torpedoes, but only seconds in Seamanship, Gunnery and Pilotage, and a third in Navigation. A biography states that &quot;his cabin at Greenwich was full of photographs of actresses, some of which were signed in the most endearing terms&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Roskill, p. 24 citing Shane Leslie draft biography of Beatty which was discontinued at the request of the family&lt;/ref&gt; After attending the gunnery school, {{HMS|Excellent|shore establishment|6}}, he undertook a posting to a torpedo boat in July 1891 and then a tour in {{HMS|Nile|1839|6}} from 19 January 1892.&lt;ref name=heath23/&gt;

Beatty joined the Royal Yacht ''Victoria and Albert'' in July 1892 while [[Queen Victoria]] was holidaying in the Mediterranean: Victoria was in mourning for her grandson, [[Prince Albert Victor, Duke of Clarence and Avondale|Albert Duke of Clarence]], who had died January 1892.&lt;ref&gt;Beatty (1980), p. 22&lt;/ref&gt; Promoted to lieutenant on 25 August 1892,&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=26322|page=5016|date=2 September 1892}}&lt;/ref&gt; he rejoined HMS ''Ruby'' in August 1892 and then transferred to the battleship {{HMS|Camperdown|1885|6}} in September 1893 (which had only recently been involved in the fleet accident where she had rammed and sunk the battleship {{HMS|Victoria|1887|6}}).&lt;ref name=heath23/&gt; He transferred to the battleship {{HMS|Trafalgar|1887|6}} in September 1895.&lt;ref name=heath23/&gt;

==Sudan Campaign==
Beatty gained recognition during the [[Mahdist War]] for his actions in the campaign to recapture the [[Sudan]]. Stanley Colville was placed in command of the gunboats attached to the British expeditionary force in Egypt and as Beatty's former commander in HMS ''Trafalgar'' and superior in HMS ''Alexandra'' he requested that Beatty join him. Control of the river Nile was considered vitally important for any expedition into Egypt and the Sudan. Beatty was seconded to the Egyptian government on 3 June 1896 and appointed second in command of the river flotilla.&lt;ref name=heath23/&gt; Colville was wounded during the operation, leaving Beatty in command of the gunboats for the successful attack on [[Dongola]].&lt;ref name=heath23/&gt; The campaign halted at [[Dongola]] to regroup and Beatty returned to Britain on leave. He was commended by Kitchener for his part in the campaign and as a result was awarded the [[Distinguished Service Order]].&lt;ref&gt;Roskill, pp. 26–27, 29&lt;/ref&gt;

Beatty was again seconded to the Egyptian government for the next phase of the campaign. This was now at [[Horatio Kitchener, 1st Earl Kitchener|Lord Kitchener]]'s specific request, for the [[Khartoum]] expedition. Beatty first commanded the gunboat ''El Teb'' but this was capsized attempting to ascend the Fourth Cataract.&lt;ref name=heath23/&gt; Beatty then took command of gunboat ''Fateh'' between October 1897 and August 1898:&lt;ref name=heath23/&gt; the gunboats were frequently in action advancing along the Nile ahead of the army and saw action at the [[Battle of Omdurman]], where Beatty made the acquaintance of [[Winston Churchill]] who had become a cavalry officer in Beatty's father's old regiment, the 4th Hussars, and had there learnt his family history. In a few hours 10,000 Dervishes were killed by rifle and machine gun fire without any of them getting within 600 yards of the British force.&lt;ref&gt;Beatty (1980), pp. 29–30&lt;/ref&gt; This battle marked the effective end of resistance to the expeditionary force, but the gunboats were called into service to transport troops to [[Fashoda]], {{convert|400|mi|km}} south along the White Nile, where a small force of French troops had made a difficult land crossing and staked a claim to the area. Despite [[Fashoda Crisis|the ensuing crisis]], the French were persuaded to withdraw without incident.&lt;ref name=heath24&gt;Heathcote, p. 24&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/world/war/fashoda-incident.htm |title=Fashoda Incident – 1898|publisher=Global Security|accessdate=4 August 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Kitchener commended Beatty for his efforts in the campaign&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=27009|page=5731|date=30 September 1898}}&lt;/ref&gt; and as a result Beatty was promoted to [[commander]], ahead of 400 other lieutenants,&lt;ref name=heath24/&gt; on 15 November 1898.&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=27023|page=6692|date=15 November 1898}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Boxer Rebellion==
Beatty was appointed executive officer of the small battleship {{HMS|Barfleur|1892|6}}, flagship of the [[Commander-in-Chief, China|China Station]], on 20 April 1899.&lt;ref name=heath24/&gt; The first year of his tour of duty was uneventful, but unrest against foreigners was growing in China. The [[Boxer Rebellion|Boxer]] movement was a secret Chinese peasant society committed to resisting oppression both from foreigners and from the Chinese government. The [[Empress Dowager Cixi|Empress Dowager Tzu-hsi]] partly encouraged the Boxer's opposition to foreigners in an attempt to turn their attention away from herself. The name was derived from ritual exercises supposed to make their users immune to bullets, which resembled boxing.&lt;ref&gt;Roskill, p. 30&lt;/ref&gt;

In the summer of 1900 the rebellion reached [[Beijing|Peking]], where the German legation was attacked and foreign nationals withdrew to the relative safety of the Legation Quarter. Government troops joined forces with the rebels and the railway to the Treaty Port of [[Tianjin|Tientsin]] was interrupted. Admiral [[Edward Hobart Seymour|Sir Edward Seymour]], then the Commander-in-Chief of the China Station, sent reinforcements to Peking, but they were insufficient to defend the Legation. An attempt was therefore made to send more troops from Tientsin, where British ships had been joined by French, German, Russian, American, Austrian, Italian and Japanese. The international [[naval brigade]] force of naval marines placed itself under the senior officer present, which was Seymour. After an urgent call for help from the Legation, Seymour set out on 10 June 1900 with 2,000 troops to attempt to break through to Peking in the [[Seymour Expedition]]. The force got about half way before abandoning the attempt because the railway line had been torn up. By now rebels had begun destroying the track behind the force, cutting it off from Tientsin.&lt;ref&gt;Roskill, pp. 31–32&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:SeymourTianjin.jpg|thumb|right|Admiral Seymour returning to Tientsin with wounded men]]
On 11 June 1900, Beatty and 150 men from HMS ''Barfleur'' landed as part of a force of 2,400 defending Tientsin from 15,000 Chinese troops plus Boxers. On 16 June 1900 the [[Battle of Dagu Forts (1900)|Taku forts were bombarded]] and captured to ensure ships could still reach the port. Fierce fighting broke out throughout the foreign areas and railway station, and Beatty was injured.&lt;ref name=heath24/&gt; He later took part in the successful relief of the naval brigade and was promoted to [[Captain (Royal Navy)|captain]] on 8 November 1900.&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=27245|page=6855|date=9 November 1900}}&lt;/ref&gt; Beatty returned to Britain, where he required an operation to restore proper use of his left arm.&lt;ref&gt;Roskill, pp. 32–33&lt;/ref&gt;

==Marriage==
Beatty had returned from leave after the Sudan campaign, but finding life in Ireland at the family home not to his taste, stayed instead with his brother at [[Newmarket, Suffolk]]. The location allowed him good hunting, and access to aristocratic houses where his recent heroic reputation from the campaign made him an honoured guest. Out hunting one day he chanced to meet [[Ethel Beatty|Ethel Tree]], daughter of Chicago department store founder [[Marshall Field]]. Beatty was immediately taken with her, for her good looks and her ability to hunt. The immediate difficulty with the match was that Ethel was married already to Arthur Tree, with a son, [[Ronald Tree]].&lt;ref&gt;Beatty (1980), pp. 31–35&lt;/ref&gt;

After the Boxer Campaign, the couple had at first exchanged letters, which Beatty signed 'Jack', as Ethel was still a married woman and discretion was advised. Ethel became involved with another man and the exchange of letters ceased but on Beatty's return she sent him a telegram and letter inviting him to resume their friendship. Beatty did not respond until after surgery on his arm in September 1900 when he wrote, &quot;I landed from China with my heart full of rage, and swore I did not care if I ever saw you again, or if I were killed or not. And now I have arrived with the firm determination not to see you at all in my own mind... Unfortunately I shall go on loving you to the bitter end... To me always a Queen, if not always mine, Good-bye.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Beatty (1980), p. 38&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite this estrangement, the couple again met foxhunting and resumed a discreet relationship. Marshall Field was at first unimpressed by the impecunious Beatty as a future son-in-law, but was persuaded by his heroic reputation, impressive record of promotion and future prospects. There was the possibility that Field might revoke the settlement he had made on his daughter at the time of her first marriage and the new couple would have no means of support. Beatty's father was also unhappy about the match, fearing a repeat of the difficulties he had faced with his own relationship with a married woman, but with the added risk of publicity because both Beatty and Ethel were famous and the risk that Beatty's illegitimacy might be exposed. Beatty went so far as to consult a fortune teller, Mrs. Roberts, who predicted a fine outcome to the match. Ethel wrote to Arthur, telling him that it was her firm intention never to live with him again as his wife, though not naming any particular person or reason. Arthur agreed to co-operate, and filed for divorce in America on the grounds of desertion, which was granted 9 May 1901. Beatty and Ethel married on 22 May 1901 at the registry office, St. George's, Hanover Square, London with no family attending. Although Arthur Tree was himself from a wealthy American family, he now had to adjust to reduced circumstances without Ethel's support. He elected to remain in Britain and their son Ronald remained with him. Ronald and his mother were never reconciled from his perception that she had deserted his father, but he visited in later life and became friendly with Beatty. Ronald later became a member of parliament and, during the [[Second World War]] became a link between the British and United States governments, lending his country house, [[Ditchley|Ditchley Park]] near [[Oxford]], to [[Winston Churchill]] for weekend visits when the official residences were considered unsafe. Beatty and Ethel set up home at Hanover Lodge in Regent's Park, London.&lt;ref&gt;Beatty (1980), pp. 38–44&lt;/ref&gt;

The couple had two sons, [[David Beatty, 2nd Earl Beatty|David Field Beatty, 2nd Earl Beatty]] (1905–1972) born at the Capua Palace in [[Malta]], and the Hon. [[Peter Beatty|Peter Randolph Louis Beatty]] (1910–1949). His marriage to a very wealthy [[Beneficiary|heiress]] allowed Beatty an independence that most other officers lacked. She is reputed to have commented after he was threatened with disciplinary action following the straining of his ship's engines, &quot;What? Court-martial my David? I'll buy them a new ship.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Massie, p. 89&lt;/ref&gt;

==Advancement==
In May 1902 he was passed fit for sea duty and was appointed captain of the cruiser {{HMS|Juno|1895|6}} on 2 June,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite newspaper The Times |articlename=Naval &amp; Military intelligence|day_of_week=Thursday |date=22 May 1902 |page_number=8 |issue=36774| }}&lt;/ref&gt; spending two months in exercises with the [[Channel Fleet]] under Admiral [[Arthur Wilson (Royal Navy officer)|Sir Arthur Wilson]] before joining the [[Mediterranean Fleet]].&lt;ref name=heath24/&gt; Beatty worked hard to raise efficiency so that she was highly rated in gunnery and other competitions by the time he left the ship 19 December 1902. Ethel decided not to be left behind so rented the Capua Palace on Malta, home port of the Mediterranean Fleet, where she became part of the island's high society.&lt;ref&gt;Roskill, pp. 40–41&lt;/ref&gt;

Beatty took command of the cruiser {{HMS|Arrogant|1896|6}} in the Mediterranean Fleet in November 1903 and then commanded the cruiser {{HMS|Suffolk|1903|6}} in the Mediterranean Fleet from October 1904.&lt;ref name=heath24/&gt; He then became the naval advisor to the [[Army Council (1904)|Army Council]] in 1906 and, after having been appointed a naval [[Aide-de-Camp]] to [[Edward VII|the King]] on 5 November 1908,&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=28195|page=8165|date=10 November 1908}}&lt;/ref&gt; he became captain of the battleship {{HMS|Queen|1902|6}} in the [[Atlantic Fleet (United Kingdom)|Atlantic Fleet]] in December 1908.&lt;ref name=heath24/&gt; At the request of [[Alfred Winsloe]], the [[Fourth Sea Lord]], he was promoted to [[rear-admiral]] on 1 January 1910 by a special order in council since he had not completed the requisite time as a captain.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Harley|title=The Promotion of David Beatty to Rear-Admiral|pages=215–216}}&lt;/ref&gt; He was offered the post of second-in-command of the [[Atlantic Fleet (United Kingdom)|Atlantic Fleet]], but declined it and asked for one in the [[Home Fleet]].&lt;ref name=heath24/&gt; As the Atlantic Fleet post was a major command, the [[Admiralty]] were very unimpressed and his attitude nearly ruined his career.&lt;ref name=heath24/&gt; Beatty, as a rapidly promoted war hero, with no financial worries and with a degree of support in Royal circles, felt more confident than most naval officers in standing firm on requesting a posting nearer home. He was approaching two years on half pay (which would trigger automatic retirement from the navy) when on 8 January 1912 his career was saved by the new [[Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty|First Lord of the Admiralty]], [[Winston Churchill]].&lt;ref&gt;Roskill, pp. 48–52&lt;/ref&gt; Churchill had met Beatty when Beatty was commander of a gunboat on the Nile supporting the army at the [[Battle of Omdurman]], in which Churchill took part as a cavalry officer. A &quot;probably [[apocryphal]]&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Massie, p. 92&lt;/ref&gt; story relates that as Beatty walked into Churchill's office at the Admiralty, Churchill looked him over and said, &quot;You seem very young to be an Admiral.&quot;  Unfazed, Beatty replied, &quot;And you seem very young to be First Lord.&quot; Churchill – who was himself only thirty-eight years old in 1912 – took to him immediately and he was appointed [[Naval Secretary]].&lt;ref&gt;Gordon, p. 381&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:LionSP 001672.jpg|thumb|right|{{HMS|Lion|1910|6}}, flagship of the battlecruiser squadron]]
Beatty became Rear-Admiral Commanding the [[1st Battlecruiser Squadron]] on 1 March 1913.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Beatty Papers |volume=I |page=57 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Beatty was late taking up his new post, choosing not to cut short a holiday in [[Monte Carlo]]. On his eventual arrival, he set about drafting standing orders regarding how the squadron was to operate. He noted, &quot;Captains...to be successful must possess, in a marked degree, initiative, resource, determination, and no fear of accepting responsibility&quot;. He went on &quot;...as a rule instructions will be of a very general character so as to avoid interfering with the judgement and initiative of captains...The admiral will rely on captains to use all the information at their disposal to grasp the situation quickly and anticipate his wishes, using their own discretion as to how to act in unforeseen circumstances...&quot; The approach outlined by Beatty contradicted the views of many within the navy, who felt that ships should always be closely controlled by their commanding admiral, and harked back to reforms attempted by Admiral [[George Tryon]]. It is argued that Tryon had attempted to introduce greater independence and initiative amongst his captains, which he believed would be essential in the confusion of a real war situation, but had ironically been killed in an accident caused by captains rigorously obeying incorrect but precise orders issued by Tryon himself.&lt;ref&gt;Gordon pp. 381–382. For a rebuttal of Gordon's thesis on tactics in the late-nineteenth century Royal Navy see {{Cite journal|doi=10.1177/0968344508091324 |last=Allen |first=Matthew |date=July 2008 |title=The Deployment of Untried Technology: British Naval Tactics in the Ironclad Era |journal=War in History |volume=15 |issue=3 |pages= 269–293 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Beatty chose Lieutenant [[Ralph Seymour (naval officer)|Ralph Seymour]] as his flag lieutenant, despite Seymour being unknown to him. Seymour had aristocratic connections, which may have appealed to Beatty since he sought connections in society, but it was also the case that Seymour's sister was a longstanding close friend of Churchill's wife. Appointments by influence were common in the navy at this time, but the significance of Beatty's choice lay in Seymour's relative inexperience as a signals officer, which later resulted in difficulties in battle.&lt;ref&gt;Gordon pp. 384–385&lt;/ref&gt;

==First World War==
[[File:John Lavery - David Richard Beatty.jpg|thumbnail|David Beatty in 1917, by [[John Lavery]]]]
On the eve of the [[First World War]] in 1914, Beatty was appointed a [[Order of the Bath|Knight Commander of the Order of the Bath]]&lt;ref name=&quot;London Gazette&quot;&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=28842|page=4876 |date=19 June 1914 |supp=y}}&lt;/ref&gt; and promoted to acting [[vice-admiral]] in February 1915 and given command of the [[Battle Cruiser Fleet]] a month later. He was confirmed in the rank of vice-admiral on 9 August 1915.&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=29262|page=8016|date=9 August 1915}}&lt;/ref&gt; He led the 1st Battlecruiser Squadron at the actions at [[Battle of Heligoland Bight (1914)|Heligoland Bight]] (1914), [[Battle of Dogger Bank (1915)|Dogger Bank]] (1915) and [[Battle of Jutland|Jutland]] (1916).&lt;ref name=heath25&gt;Heathcote, p. 25&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Wikiquote}}
[[Battle of Jutland|Jutland]] proved to be decisive in Beatty's career, despite the loss of two of his [[battlecruiser]]s. Beatty is reported to have remarked (to his Flag Captain, [[Ernle Chatfield, 1st Baron Chatfield|Ernle Chatfield]], later First Sea Lord in the early 1930s), &quot;there seems to be something wrong with our bloody ships today&quot;, after two of them had exploded within half an hour during the battle.&lt;ref name=heath25/&gt; In any case Beatty's actions succeeded in drawing the German [[High Seas Fleet]] into action against the British [[Grand Fleet]].&lt;ref name=heath25/&gt;

Beatty succeeded Admiral [[John Jellicoe, 1st Earl Jellicoe|John Jellicoe]] as commander-in-chief of the Grand Fleet and received promotion to the acting rank of [[admiral]] in December 1916.&lt;ref name=heath25/&gt; With his dashing style, he was the antithesis of his predecessor.&lt;ref name=heath25/&gt; Beatty's marriage was failing disastrously at the time, and the result was to be a decade-long love affair between Beatty and Eugénie Godfrey-Faussett, wife of Captain [[Bryan Godfrey-Faussett]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=The Shane Leslie-Godfrey Faussett Archive | url=http://janus.lib.cam.ac.uk/db/node.xsp?id=EAD%2FGBR%2F0014%2FSLGF | accessdate=11 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Under Beatty's command the Grand Fleet maintained its dominance of the North Sea until the end of the War.&lt;ref name=heath25/&gt;

Beatty escorted the German High Seas Fleet to internment at [[Scapa Flow]] in November 1918 giving the order from his flagship {{HMS|Queen Elizabeth|1913|6}} that &quot;the German Flag will be hauled down at sunset and will not be raised again without permission&quot;.&lt;ref name=heath25/&gt; This was not a lawful order, as the fleet remained the property of the German Government having been interned rather than having surrendered, but nevertheless Beatty enforced it.&lt;ref name=heath26&gt;Heathcote, p. 26&lt;/ref&gt;

==First Sea Lord==
[[File:William Orpen David Beatty, 1st Earl Beatty.jpg|thumb |right |Portrait of Beatty by [[William Orpen]]]]
[[File:Général Pierre Berdoulat et Amiral David Beatty (15224217527).jpg|thumb|Admiral of the Fleet David Beatty in Paris, with French General Pierre Berdoulat]]
Beatty was promoted to substantive full [[admiral]] on 1 January 1919&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=31104|page=199|date=3 January 1919}}&lt;/ref&gt; and to [[Admiral of the Fleet (Royal Navy)|Admiral of the Fleet]] on 1 May 1919.&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=31327|page=5653|date=6 May 1919}}&lt;/ref&gt; He was created 1st [[Earl Beatty]], Viscount Borodale and Baron Beatty of the North Sea and Brooksby on 18 October 1919.&lt;ref name=&quot;london-gazette.co.uk&quot;&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=31610|page=12889|date=21 October 1919}}&lt;/ref&gt; He became [[First Sea Lord]] on 1 November 1919.&lt;ref name=heath26/&gt; In this capacity he was involved in negotiating the [[Washington Naval Treaty]] of 1922 in which it was agreed that the United States, Britain and Japan should set their navies in a ratio of 5:5:3, with France and Italy maintaining smaller fleets.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ibiblio.org/pha/pre-war/1922/nav_lim.html |title=Conference on the Limitation of Armament|accessdate=11 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the [[First MacDonald ministry|First Labour Government]] of 1924, with Japan increasingly hostile to the UK, Beatty lobbied the [[John Robert Clynes|Clynes]] Committee for construction of the [[Singapore Naval Base]] to continue. Beatty wrote out, but did not send, a threat of resignation. The government were trying to cut back on the numbers of cruisers constructed; the other Sea Lords attributed the building of the [[County-class cruiser|''Kent'' class]] to Beatty's lobbying, but government desire to alleviate shipyard unemployment was probably a more important factor.&lt;ref&gt;Roskill 1980, pp. 343–5&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite further rumours that he would resign, Beatty remained in office when the [[Second Baldwin ministry|Conservatives took power]] in the autumn of 1924.&lt;ref&gt;Roskill 1980, pp. 343–8&lt;/ref&gt; Supported by the First Lord of the Admiralty [[William Bridgeman, 1st Viscount Bridgeman|William Bridgeman]], he clashed with the new Chancellor of the Exchequer, Winston Churchill, once again over the number of cruisers required by the Royal Navy. At this stage of his career Churchill was opposed to what he saw as excessive defence spending. This may seem odd in light of his previous and subsequent reputation, but in the 1920s no major war seemed to be on the horizon.&lt;ref&gt;Roskill 1980, pp. 351–3&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www-archives.chu.cam.ac.uk/perl/node?a=a;reference=CHAR%201%2F179%2F8-9|title=Churchill Archives|publisher=Churchill College, Cambridge|accessdate=11 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Beatty also at this time pressed hard for the return of responsibility for naval aviation from the newly formed [[Royal Air Force]] to the Royal Navy.&lt;ref name=heath26/&gt;

In 1926 Beatty was considered for the post of [[Governor General of Canada]] but was rejected by the [[Secretary of State for the Colonies|Colonial Secretary]] [[Leo Amery]] as he had &quot;no manners and an impossible American wife&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Roskill 1980, pp355&lt;/ref&gt;

By the time of his retirement from the Royal Navy in July 1927&lt;ref name=heath27&gt;Heathcote, p. 27&lt;/ref&gt; a great deal of time was being spent preparing for the [[Calvin Coolidge|Coolidge]] Conference in Geneva, although Beatty did not himself attend as he had to remain in London to supervise the deployment of naval and [[Royal Marines|marine]] forces against nationalist unrest in China and Egypt. On his last day in office (30 July) he attended a Cabinet at which Bridgeman reported the breakdown of the [[Geneva Naval Conference|Geneva Conference]] as the Americans refused to accept any gun smaller than 8-inch for their cruisers, and after leaving office he congratulated Bridgeman that the Americans had not been able to achieve &quot;command of the sea at any cost&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Roskill 1980, pp358&lt;/ref&gt; Beatty was appointed a member of the Privy Council on 25 July 1927.&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=33298|page=4903|date=29 July 1927}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Stephen Roskill]] wrote that whilst Beatty and his disciple Chatfield deserve some praise for the Royal Navy's comparative readiness in 1939, his main achievement was to maintain the morale of the Navy at a time of serious defence cuts, and that without his strong leadership the Royal Navy might have suffered more events like the [[Invergordon Mutiny]] of 1931.&lt;ref&gt;Roskill 1980, pp360&lt;/ref&gt;

==Retirement and death==
Beatty spent much of his life (when not at sea) in [[Leicestershire]], and lived at [[Brooksby Hall]] and [[Dingley, Northamptonshire#Dingley Hall|Dingley Hall]]. In July 1930 he denounced the [[London Naval Treaty]] in the House of Lords as &quot;a great and deplorable blunder to which we are about to be committed by signing away the sea power by which the British Empire came into being&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[https://api.parliament.uk/historic-hansard/lords/1930/jul/01/london-naval-treaty#column_186 HL Deb 01 July 1930 vol 78 c. 186]&lt;/ref&gt; Beatty also claimed: &quot;If any sane man erects an edifice, or has great possessions, he protects them by insurance. The Navy is the insurance company of the economic unity of the Empire. Under the Naval Treaty of London the Navy will be totally and entirely inadequate to provide that insurance&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[https://api.parliament.uk/historic-hansard/lords/1930/jul/01/london-naval-treaty#column_194 HL Deb 01 July 1930 vol 78 c. 194]&lt;/ref&gt;

Beatty's old commander Admiral John Jellicoe died on 19 November 1935.&lt;ref name=dnb2&gt;Andrew Lambert, 'Jellicoe, John Rushworth, first Earl Jellicoe (1859–1935)', Oxford Dictionary of National Biography, Oxford University Press, 2004; online edn, May 2013 [http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/34171, accessed 16 Oct 2013]&lt;/ref&gt; Already suffering from heart failure, and sick with [[influenza]], Beatty defied doctors' orders and left his bed to act as a pallbearer, saying, &quot;What will the Navy say if I fail to attend Jellicoe's funeral?&quot; He was so obviously ill that, as the funeral procession passed up Fleet Street, a bystander sent a glass of brandy out to him. He also insisted on attending the funeral of [[George V of the United Kingdom|King George V]] in January 1936. These acts hastened his own death.&lt;ref&gt;Roskill 1980, pp. 365–8&lt;/ref&gt;
Beatty died at around 1&amp;nbsp;am on 12 March 1936.&lt;ref name=&quot;Roskill 1980, pp368&quot;&gt;Roskill 1980, pp368&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=dnb1&gt;Bryan Ranft, 'Beatty, David, first Earl Beatty (1871–1936)', Oxford Dictionary of National Biography, Oxford University Press, 2004; online edn, Jan 2012 [http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/30661 accessed 16 Oct 2013]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Beatty's biographer Stephen Roskill discusses his last words with his son on the evening of 11 March, before stating that he died at around 1&amp;nbsp;am. Heathcote (2002, p27) gives the date of his death as 11 March, which appears to be an error.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Bust Of Earl Beatty-Trafalgar Square.jpg|thumb|right |Bust of Beatty by William McMillan in Trafalgar Square, London. The two fountains were redesigned as memorials to Beatty and Jellicoe]]
At Beatty's funeral his coffin was draped in the Union Flag flown by his flagship {{HMS|Queen Elizabeth|1913|6}} in 1919. The [[Archbishop of Canterbury]], [[Cosmo Lang]], said &quot;In him something of the spirit of [[Horatio Nelson, 1st Viscount Nelson|Nelson]] seemed to have come back&quot;. The Prime Minister, [[Stanley Baldwin]], called in the House of Commons for a public memorial to Beatty to be erected, but no action was taken until after the [[Second World War]], when busts of Beatty and Jellicoe were unveiled in [[Trafalgar Square]] on 21 October ([[Trafalgar Day]]) 1948.&lt;ref name=&quot;Roskill 1980, pp368&quot;/&gt;

Beatty had requested in his will that he would like to be buried next to his wife Ethel at Dingley: however he was actually buried at [[St Paul's Cathedral]] and therefore the double grave at Dingley Church contains only his wife's body.&lt;ref&gt;Roskill, p. 366&lt;/ref&gt;

==Assessment==
A number of serious errors have been identified in Beatty's handling of his [[naval squadron|squadron]] at the Battle of Jutland:
*He failed to engage the German battlecruiser squadron with all his ships, thus throwing away a two-to-one numerical superiority and instead fighting one-to-one. Beatty was given command of the [[5th Battle Squadron]] to replace a squadron of battlecruisers away for training. These were four of the most powerful ships in the world, but he positioned them so far away from his six battlecruisers that they were unable to take part in most of the engagement with [[Franz von Hipper|Admiral Hipper's]] squadron of five battlecruisers.&lt;ref&gt;Brooks pp. 232–234&lt;/ref&gt;
*Beatty did not take advantage of the time available to him between sighting the enemy and the start of fighting to position his battlecruisers to most effectively attack the enemy. At the point the German ships opened fire with accurately determined ranges for their [[naval artillery|guns]], Beatty's ships were still manoeuvring, some could not see the enemy because of their own smoke, and hardly any had the opportunity of a period of steady course as they approached to [[gun laying|properly determine target range]]. As a result, the German ships had a significant advantage in early hits, with obvious benefit. During this time he also lost the potential advantage of the larger guns on his ships: they could commence firing at a longer range than the German ships.&lt;ref&gt;Brooks pp. 234–240&lt;/ref&gt;
*He did not ensure that signals sent to his ships were handled properly and received by the intended ships. Lost signals added to the confusion and lost opportunities during the battle. This issue had already arisen in previous battles, where the same signals officer had been involved, but no changes had been made.&lt;ref&gt;Brooks pp. 232–233, 237&lt;/ref&gt; Although Beatty was supposed to act as a fast armoured scout and report to Jellicoe the exact position of the German ships he encountered, or to keep in contact with the German fleet while he retreated to the main British Grand Fleet, he failed to do so. This information was important to Jellicoe to know how best to position the main fleet to make the most of its eventual engagement with the German High Seas Fleet. Despite this, Jellicoe succeeded in positioning his ships to good advantage, relying on other closer [[cruiser]]s for final knowledge of the German's position, but necessitating last-minute decisions.&lt;ref&gt;Brooks pp. 232–240&lt;/ref&gt; 
*Additionally, the gunnery of Beatty's ships was generally poor compared to the rest of the fleet. This was partly a consequence of his ships being stationed at Rosyth, rather than Scapa Flow with the main fleet, since local facilities at Rosyth were limited, but this was a problem identified months before Jutland which Beatty had failed to correct.&lt;ref&gt;Brooks pp. 226–227&lt;/ref&gt;

After the war a report of the battle was prepared by the Admiralty under First Sea Lord [[Baron Wester Wemyss|Rosslyn Wemyss]]. Before the report was published, Beatty was himself appointed First Sea Lord, and immediately requested amendments to the report. When the authors refused to comply, he ordered it to be destroyed and instead had prepared an alternative report, which proved highly critical of Jellicoe. Considerable argument broke out as a result, with significant numbers of servicemen disputing the published version, including Admiral [[Reginald Bacon]], who wrote his own book about the battle, criticising the version sponsored by Beatty and highly critical of Beatty's own part in the battle.&lt;ref&gt;Bacon, pp. 1–253&lt;/ref&gt;

Besides actively encouraging the publication of books and articles designed to praise his role at the Battle of Jutland and denigrate Jellicoe's, after his retirement Beatty assisted with the preparation of a 5,200 line poem &quot;The Epic of Jutland&quot; by [[Shane Leslie]].&lt;ref&gt;Roskill 1980, pp. 322–29&lt;/ref&gt;

==Honours and awards==

&lt;center&gt;
(ribbon bar, as it would look today)

[[File:Order of the Bath UK ribbon.png|100px]]

[[File:Order of Merit (Commonwealth realms) ribbon.png|100px]]
[[File:Royal Victorian Order ribbon sm.jpg|100px]]
[[File:Dso-ribbon.png|100px]]
[[File:Queens Sudan Medal BAR.svg|100px]]

[[Image:Third China War Medal BAR.svg|100px]]
[[File:1914 1915 Star ribbon bar.svg|100px]]
[[File:British War Medal BAR.svg|100px]]
[[File:Victory Medal ribbon bar.svg|100px]]

[[File:King George V Coronation Medal ribbon.png|100px]]
[[File:GeorgeVSilverJubileum-ribbon.png|100px]]
[[File:Order of the Medjidie lenta.png|100px]]
[[File:OrderStGeorge4cl rib.png|100px]]

[[File:Grande ufficiale OMS BAR.svg|100px]]
[[File:JPN Kyokujitsu-sho 1Class BAR.svg|100px]]
[[File:Legion Honneur GC ribbon.svg|100px]]
[[File:Croix de Guerre 1914-1918 ribbon.svg|100px]]

[[File:Star of Romania Ribbon.PNG|100px]]
[[File:GRE Order Redeemer 1Class.png|100px]]
[[File:Navy Distinguished Service Medal ribbon.svg|100px]]
[[File:JPN Kyokujitsu-sho Paulownia BAR.svg|100px]]

&lt;/center&gt;

===British===
*Companion of the [[Distinguished Service Order]] (DSO)-17 November 1896&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=26795|page=6271|date=17 November 1896}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Knight Grand Cross of the Order of the Bath]] (GCB)-31 May 1916&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=29751|page=9070|date=15 September 1916|supp=y}}&lt;/ref&gt; (KCB: 19 June 1914;&lt;ref name=&quot;London Gazette&quot;/&gt; CB: 19 June 1911)&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=28505|page=4588|date=19 June 1911 |supp=y}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Knight Grand Cross of the Royal Victorian Order]] (GCVO)-25 June 1917&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=30156|page=6409|date=25 June 1917}}&lt;/ref&gt; (KCVO: 17 June 1916&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=29629|page=6063|date=20 June 1916 |supp=y}}&lt;/ref&gt; Member Fourth Class (present-day Lieutenant)(MVO): 28 April 1905)&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=27792|page=3401|date=28 April 1905}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Member of the [[Order of Merit]] (OM)-3 June 1919&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=31379|page=7046|date=3 June 1919 |supp=y}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Earl Beatty]], Viscount Borodale of Wexford in the County of Wexford, Baron Beatty of the North Sea and of Brooksby in the County of Leicester-18 October 1919&lt;ref name=&quot;london-gazette.co.uk&quot;/&gt;

Beatty was granted the [[Freedom of the City of London]] on 16 June 1919 at the same ceremony as [[Douglas Haig, 1st Earl Haig|Lord Haig]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.itnsource.com/shotlist/BHC_RTV/1919/06/16/BGT407052911/?v=0|title=Haig and Beatty made freemen of the City of London|work=itnsource.com|accessdate=3 May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; In June 1920, the [[Great Central Railway]] gave the name ''Earl Beatty'' to one of their newly built [[4-6-0]] express passenger locomotives, no. 1164 of [[GCR Class 9P|class 9P]] (LNER class B3). It carried the name until withdrawal in September 1947.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Boddy|Fry|Hennigan|Proud|1963|p=48}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Boddy|Brown|Fry|Hennigan|1975|pp=21, 23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Foreign===
*[[Order of the Medjidieh|Order of Majid]], 4th Class (''Nishan-i-Majidieh'') of the [[Ottoman Empire]]-3 October 1898&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=27012|page=5863|date=3 October 1898}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Order of St George]], Fourth Class of the [[Russian Empire]]-25 August 1916&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=29727|page=8497|date=25 August 1916}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Grand Officer of the [[Military Order of Savoy]] of the [[Kingdom of Italy]]-11 August 1917&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=30227 |date=10 August 1917 |page=8208 |supp=y}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Grand Cordon of the [[Order of the Rising Sun]] of the [[Empire of Japan]]-29 August 1917&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=30258 |date=28 August 1917 |page=8989 |supp=y}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Grand Cross of the [[Legion d'Honneur]] of France-23 May 1919&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=31360|page=6504|date=23 May 1919 |supp=y}}&lt;/ref&gt; (Grand Officer-15 September 1916)&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=29751|page=9081|date=15 September 1916 |supp=y}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Croix de guerre 1914–1918 (France)|Croix de Guerre]] of France-15 February 1919&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=31182|page=2361|date=15 February 1919 |supp=y}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Grand Cross of the [[Order of the Star of Romania]] of the [[Kingdom of Romania]]-17 March 1919&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=31236|page=3593|date=17 March 1919 |supp=y}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Grand Cross of the [[Order of the Redeemer]] of the [[Kingdom of Greece]]-21 June 1919&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=31413|page=7909|date=21 June 1919 |supp=y}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Navy Distinguished Service Medal|Distinguished Service Medal]] (United States)-16 September 1919&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=31553 |date=16 September 1919 |page=11582 |supp=y}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Grand Cordon with Brilliants of the [[Order of the Precious Brilliant Golden Grain]] of the Republic of China – 22 January 1920&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.london-gazette.co.uk/issues/31748/supplements/950 London Gazette, 22 January 1920]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Grand Cordon of the [[Order of the Paulownia Flowers]] of the [[Empire of Japan]] – 20 January 1922&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.london-gazette.co.uk/issues/32586/pages/641 London Gazette, 24 January 1922]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Quotations==
{{quote|In the afternoon [of 1 June 1916] Beatty came into the ''Lion's'' chart-house. Tired and depressed, he sat down on the settee, and settling himself in a corner he closed his eyes. Unable to hide his disappointment at the result of the battle, he repeated in a weary voice, 'There is something wrong with our ships', then opening his eyes and looking at the writer, he added, 'And something wrong with our system'. Having thus unburdened himself he fell asleep.|Lieutenant W. S. Chalmers, Assistant Navigating Officer of HMS ''Lion'' at Jutland&lt;ref&gt;Chalmers, p. 262&lt;/ref&gt;}}

{{quote|At 4.25, soon after we had resumed our position ahead of the ''Princess Royal'', the third ship in the line, the ''Queen Mary'' (Captain Prowse) blew up exactly as had the ''Indefatigable''. I was standing beside Sir David Beatty and we both turned round in time to see the unpleasant spectacle. The thought of my friends in her flashed through my mind; I thought also how lucky we had evidently been in the ''Lion''. Beatty turned to me and said, &quot;There seems to be something wrong with our bloody ships to-day&quot;, a remark which needed neither comment nor answer.|Captain [[Ernle Chatfield, 1st Baron Chatfield|Ernle Chatfield]], Captain of HMS ''Lion'' at Jutland.&lt;ref name=chatfield&gt;Chatfield, p. 143&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em|}}

==Further reading==
{{Refbegin}}
*{{Cite book|title=The Jutland Scandal |last=Bacon |first=Admiral Sir Reginald Hugh |year=1933 |publisher=Hutchinson |location=London |asin=B008MXL94I}}
*{{Cite book|title=Our Admiral, a biography of Admiral of the Fleet Earl Beatty|last=Beatty |first=Charles| year=1980 |publisher=W. H. Allen |location=London |isbn=978-0-491-02388-7}}
*{{Cite book|title=The Beatty Papers |last=Beatty |first=Admiral of the Fleet David, First Earl Beatty |volume=Volume I |editor=Ranft, Bryan McL. |year=1989 |publisher=Navy Records Society |location=London |isbn=0-85967-807-5 }}
*{{cite book |last1=Boddy |first1=M.G. |last2=Brown |first2=W.A. |last3=Fry |first3=E.V. |last4=Hennigan |first4=W. |last5=Hoole |first5=Ken |authorlink5=Ken Hoole |last6=Manners |first6=F. |last7=Neve |first7=E. |last8=Platt |first8=E.N.T. |last9=Proud |first9=P. |last10=Yeadon |first10=W.B. |authorlink10=Willie Yeadon |title=Locomotives of the L.N.E.R., part 2B: Tender Engines – Classes B1 to B19 |date=March 1975 |publisher=[[Railway Correspondence and Travel Society|RCTS]] |location=Lincoln |isbn=0-901115-73-8 |oclc=655688865 |ref=harv }}
*{{cite book |last1=Boddy |first1=M.G. |last2=Fry |first2=E.V. |last3=Hennigan |first3=W. |last4=Proud |first4=P. |last5=Yeadon |first5=W.B. |authorlink5=Willie Yeadon |editor-last=Fry |editor-first=E.V. |title=Locomotives of the L.N.E.R., part 1: Preliminary Survey |date=July 1963 |publisher=[[Railway Correspondence and Travel Society|RCTS]] |location=Potters Bar |ref=harv }}
*{{Cite book|title=Dreadnought Gunnery at the Battle of Jutland: The Question of Fire Control |last=Brooks |first=John |year=2005 |publisher=Frank Cass Publishers |location=London |isbn=0-7146-5702-6 }}
*{{Cite book|title=The Life and Letters of David, Earl Beatty |last=Chalmers |first=Rear-Admiral W. S. |year=1951 |publisher=Hodder and Stoughton |location=London |asin=B0007ITISK}}
*{{Cite book|last=Chatfield|first=Ernle|title=The Navy and Defence|publisher=Heinemann|year=1942|asin=B0006APX92}}
*{{Cite book|title=The Rules of the Game: Jutland and British Naval Command |last=Gordon |first=Andrew |year=1996 |publisher=John Murray |location=London |isbn=0-7195-5533-7 }}
*{{cite journal|last1=Harley|first1=Simon|title=The Promotion of David Beatty to Rear-Admiral|journal=The Mariner's Mirror|date=May 2017|volume=103|issue=2|pages=213–216|doi=10.1080/00253359.2017.1304709}}
*{{Cite book|title=British Admirals of the Fleet 1734–1995: A Biographical Dictionary |last=Heathcote |first=T. A. |year=2002 |publisher=Leo Cooper |location=Barnsley, South Yorkshire |isbn=0-85052-835-6 }}
*{{Cite book|title=Castles of Steel: Britain, Germany, and the Winning of the Great War at Sea |last=Massie |first=Robert Kinloch | authorlink=Robert K. Massie|year=2003 |publisher=Ballantine Books |location=New York |isbn=0-345-40878-0 |title-link=Castles of Steel: Britain, Germany, and the Winning of the Great War at Sea }}
*{{Cite book|title=The First Sea Lords: From Fisher to Mountbatten |last=Ranft |first=Bryan McL. |editor=Murfett, Malcolm H. |year=1995 |publisher=Praeger Publishers |location=Westport, CT |isbn=0-275-94231-7 }}
*{{Cite book|title=Admiral of the Fleet Earl Beatty – The Last Naval Hero: An Intimate Biography |last=Roskill |first=Captain Stephen Wentworth |location=London |publisher=Collins |year=1980 |isbn=0-689-11119-3 }}
{{Refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|David Beatty}}
{{Wikiquote}}
*{{Hansard-contribs | mr-david-beatty-1 | the Earl Beatty }}
*{{DP-xlink|http://dreadnoughtproject.org/tfs/index.php/David_Richard_Beatty,_First_Earl_Beatty}}
*{{Cite EB1922 |last=Young |first=Filson |authorlink=Filson Young |wstitle=Beatty, David Beatty, 1st Earl |short=x}}
*{{Cite web |url=http://www.admirals.org.uk/admirals/fleet/beattyd.php |accessdate=6 March 2010 |publisher=admirals.org |title=Royal Navy flag Officers service record, David Beatty |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110903082113/http://www.admirals.org.uk/admirals/fleet/beattyd.php |archive-date=3 September 2011 |url-status=dead }}
*[http://www.the-athenaeum.org/art/detail.php?ID=50500 Portrait of Admiral Sir David Beatty] by American artist [[Cecilia Beaux]].
* {{PM20|FID=pe/001234}}

{{S-start}}
{{S-mil}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Ernest Troubridge]]}} 
{{s-ttl|title=[[Naval Secretary]]|years=1912–1913}} 
{{s-aft|after=[[Dudley de Chair]]}}
|-
{{s-bef|before=[[John Jellicoe, 1st Earl Jellicoe|Sir John Jellicoe]]}} 
{{s-ttl|title=[[Grand Fleet|Commander-in-Chief, Grand Fleet]]|years=1916–1919}} 
{{s-non|reason=Fleet disbanded}}
|-
{{s-bef|before=[[Rosslyn Wemyss, 1st Baron Wester Wemyss|The Lord Wester-Wemyss]]}} 
{{s-ttl|title=[[First Sea Lord]]|years=1919–1927}} 
{{s-aft|after=[[Sir Charles Madden, 1st Baronet|Sir Charles Madden]]}}
{{S-aca}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Herbert Kitchener, 1st Earl Kitchener|Earl Kitchener]]}} 
{{s-ttl|title=[[Rector of the University of Edinburgh]]|years=1917–1920}} 
{{s-aft|after=[[David Lloyd George]]}}
{{S-reg|uk}}
{{s-bef|before=New Creation}} 
{{s-ttl|title=[[Earl Beatty]]|years=1919–1936}} 
{{s-aft|after=[[David Field Beatty, 2nd Earl Beatty|David Field Beatty]]}}
{{S-end}}

{{First Sea Lord}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Beatty, David Beatty, 1st Earl}}
[[Category:First Sea Lords]]
[[Category:Lords of the Admiralty]]
[[Category:Royal Navy admirals of the fleet]]
[[Category:Royal Navy personnel of the Mahdist War]]
[[Category:Royal Navy admirals of World War I]]
[[Category:Earls in the Peerage of the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Graduates of the Royal Naval College, Greenwich]]
[[Category:Knights Grand Cross of the Royal Victorian Order]]
[[Category:Knights Grand Cross of the Order of the Bath]]
[[Category:Companions of the Distinguished Service Order]]
[[Category:Rectors of the University of Edinburgh]]
[[Category:Members of the Order of Merit]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of the Medjidie]]
[[Category:Grand Officiers of the Légion d'honneur]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Croix de Guerre 1914–1918 (France)]]
[[Category:Grand Crosses of the Order of the Star of Romania]]
[[Category:People educated at Kilkenny College]]
[[Category:1871 births]]
[[Category:1936 deaths]]
[[Category:Royal Navy personnel of the Boxer Rebellion]]
[[Category:Foreign recipients of the Distinguished Service Medal (United States)]]
[[Category:Members of the Privy Council of the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Beatty family|David]]
[[Category:Freemen of the City of London]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Navy Distinguished Service Medal]]</text>
      <sha1>mkd779e6ap8qf5qggeadzsdwv7h7qrl</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
