  <page>
    <title>Digital cinema</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8844</id>
    <revision>
      <id>934412903</id>
      <parentid>932740199</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-06T11:29:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jerodlycett</username>
        <id>24269494</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>v2.02 - [[WP:WCW]] project (Reference before punctuation - URL without http://)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{hatnote|This article focuses on digital projection and distribution in [[cinemas]]. For digital image capture, see [[digital cinematography]].}}
'''Digital cinema''' refers to the use of [[digital data|digital]] technology to [[film distributor|distribute]] or [[video projector|project]] [[motion picture]]s as opposed to the historical use of reels of [[motion picture film]], such as 35&amp;nbsp;mm film. Whereas film reels have to be shipped to [[movie theater]]s, a digital movie can be distributed to cinemas in a number of ways: over the [[Internet]] or dedicated [[satellite]] links, or by sending [[hard drives]] or [[optical disc]]s such as [[Blu-ray]] discs. Digital movies are projected using a [[video projector|digital video projector]] instead of a [[movie projector|film projector]]. Digital cinema is distinct from [[high-definition television]] and does not necessarily use traditional television or other traditional [[high-definition video]] standards, aspect ratios, or frame rates. In digital cinema, resolutions are represented by the horizontal pixel count, usually [[2K resolution|2K]] (2048×1080 or 2.2 [[megapixel]]s) or [[4K resolution|4K]] (4096×2160 or 8.8 megapixels). As digital-cinema technology improved in the early 2010s, most theaters across the world converted to digital video projection.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://variety.com/2013/film/news/digital-cinema-conversion-nears-end-game-1200500975/|title=Digital Cinema Conversion Nears End Game|author=Leo Barraclough|date=June 23, 2013|work=Variety}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{TOC limit}}

==History==
The transition from film to [[digital video]] was preceded by cinema's transition from analog to [[digital audio]], with the release of the [[Dolby Digital]] (AC-3) [[audio coding standard]] in 1991.&lt;ref name=&quot;Britanak&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Britanak |first1=V. |title=On Properties, Relations, and Simplified Implementation of Filter Banks in the Dolby Digital (Plus) AC-3 Audio Coding Standards |journal=IEEE Transactions on Audio, Speech, and Language Processing |date=2011 |volume=19 |issue=5 |pages=1231–1241 |doi=10.1109/TASL.2010.2087755}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its main basis is the [[modified discrete cosine transform]] (MDCT), a [[lossy compression|lossy]] [[audio compression (data)|audio compression]] algorithm.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Andersen |first1=Robert Loring |last2=Crockett |first2=Brett Graham |last3=Davidson |first3=Grant A. |last4=Davis |first4=Mark Franklin |last5=Fielder |first5=Louis D. |last6=Turner |first6=Stephen C. |last7=Vinton |first7=Mark S. |last8=Williams |first8=Phillip |title=Introduction to Dolby Digital Plus, an Enhancement to the Dolby Digital Coding System |journal=[[Audio Engineering Society|Audio Engineering Society Convention]] |date=October 2004 |issue=117th AES Convention |pages=1-29 |url=https://www.dolby.com/in/en/technologies/aes-convention-paper-intro-to-dolby-digital-plus.pdf |accessdate=17 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is a modification of the [[discrete cosine transform]] (DCT) algorithm, which was first proposed by [[N. Ahmed|Nasir Ahmed]] in 1972 and was originally intended for [[image compression]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Ahmed&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last=Ahmed |first=Nasir |author-link=N. Ahmed |title=How I Came Up With the Discrete Cosine Transform |journal=[[Digital Signal Processing (journal)|Digital Signal Processing]] |date=January 1991 |volume=1 |issue=1 |pages=4–5 |doi=10.1016/1051-2004(91)90086-Z |url=https://www.scribd.com/doc/52879771/DCT-History-How-I-Came-Up-with-the-Discrete-Cosine-Transform}}&lt;/ref&gt; The DCT was adapted into the MDCT by J.P. Princen, A.W. Johnson and Alan B. Bradley at the [[University of Surrey]] in 1987,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Princen |first1=J.P. |last2=Johnson |first2=A.W. |last3=Bradley |first3=Alan B. |title=Subband/Transform coding using filter bank designs based on time domain aliasing cancellation |journal=ICASSP '87. IEEE International Conference on Acoustics, Speech, and Signal Processing |date=1987 |volume=12 |pages=2161–2164 |doi=10.1109/ICASSP.1987.1169405}}&lt;/ref&gt; and then [[Dolby Laboratories]] adapted the MDCT algorithm along with [[perceptual coding]] principles to develop the AC-3 audio format for cinema needs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Britanak&quot;/&gt; [[1990s in film|Cinema in the 1990s]] typically combined analog video with digital audio.

Digital media playback of high-resolution 2K files has at least a 20-year history. Early video data storage units ([[RAID]]s) fed custom frame buffer systems with large memories.  In early digital video units, content was usually restricted to several minutes of material. Transfer of content between remote locations was slow and had limited capacity. It was not until the late 1990s that feature-length films could be sent over the &quot;wire&quot; (Internet or dedicated fiber links). On October 23, 1998, [[Digital Light Processing]] (DLP) projector technology was publicly demonstrated with the release of ''[[The Last Broadcast (film)|The Last Broadcast]]'', the first feature-length movie, shot, edited and distributed digitally.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.upenn.edu/pennnews/current/1998-10-15/editors-pick/live-satellite-first-digital-premiere |title=Live via satellite: the first digital premiere &amp;#124; Penn Current |publisher=Upenn.edu |date=1998-10-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.indiewire.com/article/d_day_for_two_digital_movies_as_the_cruise_and_the_last_broadcast_debut_in_ |title=D Day for Two Digital Movies as &quot;The Cruise&quot; and &quot;The Last Broadcast&quot; Debut in Theaters Today &amp;#124; Filmmakers, Film Industry, Film Festivals, Awards &amp; Movie Reviews |work=Indiewire }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thelastbroadcastmovie.com/tlb99/filmmakersbios.htm |title=The Last Broadcast |publisher=Thelastbroadcastmovie.com |date= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt; In conjunction with Texas Instruments, the movie was publicly demonstrated in five theaters across the United States ([[Philadelphia]], [[Portland, Oregon|Portland (Oregon)]], [[Minneapolis]], [[Providence, Rhode Island|Providence]], and [[Orlando, Florida|Orlando]]).

===Foundations===
[[File:Texas Instruments, DLP Cinema Prototype System, Mark V, Paris, 2000 - Philippe Binant Archives.jpg|thumb|Texas Instruments, DLP Cinema Prototype Projector, Mark V, 2000]]
In the [[United States]], on June 18, 1999, Texas Instruments' ''DLP Cinema'' projector technology was publicly demonstrated on two screens in Los Angeles and New York for the release of Lucasfilm's ''[[Star Wars: Episode I – The Phantom Menace|Star Wars Episode I: The Phantom Menace]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[[Charles S. Swartz]] (editor), ''Understanding digital cinema'', 2005, p. 159.&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Europe]], on February 2, 2000, Texas Instruments' ''DLP Cinema'' projector technology was publicly demonstrated, by Philippe Binant, on one screen in Paris for the release of ''[[Toy Story 2]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.silverscreens.com/ts2digit.php|title=Silver Screens - Toy Story en numérique à Paris|website=www.silverscreens.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

From 1997 to 2000, the [[JPEG 2000]] [[image compression]] standard was developed by a [[Joint Photographic Experts Group]] (JPEG) committee chaired by Touradj Ebrahimi (later the JPEG president).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Taubman |first1=David |last2=Marcellin |first2=Michael |title=JPEG2000 Image Compression Fundamentals, Standards and Practice: Image Compression Fundamentals, Standards and Practice |date=2012 |publisher=[[Springer Science &amp; Business Media]] |isbn=9781461507994 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=y7HeBwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA402}}&lt;/ref&gt; In contrast to the original 1992 [[JPEG]] standard, which is a DCT-based [[lossy compression]] format for static [[digital images]], JPEG 2000 is a [[discrete wavelet transform]] (DWT) based compression standard that could be adapted for motion imaging [[video compression]] with the [[Motion JPEG 2000]] extension. JPEG 2000 technology was later selected as the [[video coding standard]] for digital cinema in 2004.&lt;ref name=&quot;Swartz&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last1=Swartz |first1=Charles S. |title=Understanding Digital Cinema: A Professional Handbook |date=2005 |publisher=[[Taylor &amp; Francis]] |isbn=9780240806174 |page=147 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=tYw3ehoBnjkC&amp;pg=PA147}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Initiatives===
On January 19, 2000, the [[Society of Motion Picture and Television Engineers]], in the United States, initiated the first standards group dedicated towards developing digital cinema.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.mkpe.com/publications/d-cinema/misc/dc28_takes_off.php |title=SMPTE's Digital Cinema Committee Takes Off Running |publisher=MKPE consulting |year=2000 |accessdate=2011-10-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; By December 2000, there were 15 digital cinema screens in the United States and Canada, 11 in Western Europe, 4 in Asia, and 1 in South America.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.europa-distribution.org/files/bruxelles/digital_cinema_figures.pdf |title=DIGITAL CINEMA – KEY FIGURES &amp; FACTS |date=2006-07-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Digital Cinema Initiatives]] (DCI) was formed in March 2002 as a joint project of many motion picture studios ([[Disney]], [[Fox Broadcasting Company|Fox]], [[MGM]], [[Paramount Pictures|Paramount]], [[Sony Pictures Entertainment]], [[Universal Studios|Universal]] and [[Warner Bros. Studios]]) to develop a system specification for digital cinema.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dcimovies.com/ |title=Digital Cinema Initiatives (DCI) - DIGITAL CINEMA SYSTEM SPECIFICATION, VERSION 1.2 |publisher=Dcimovies.com |date= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In April 2004, in cooperation with the [[American Society of Cinematographers]], DCI created standard evaluation material (the ASC/DCI StEM material) for testing of 2K and 4K playback and compression technologies. DCI selected [[JPEG 2000]] as the basis for the compression in the system the same year.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=https://www.imdb.com/title/tt1666288/trivia |title = ASC-DCI StEM (2004)}}&lt;/ref&gt; Initial tests with JPEG 2000 produced [[bit-rate]]s of around 75{{ndash}}125 [[Mbps]] for [[2K resolution]] and 100{{ndash}}200 Mbps for [[4K resolution]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Swartz&quot;/&gt;

===Worldwide deployment===
In China, in June 2005, an e-cinema system called &quot;dMs&quot; was established and was used in over 15,000 screens spread across China's 30 provinces. dMs estimated that the system would expand to 40,000 screens in 2009.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dmcc.gov.cn China Digital Cinema Development Center]&lt;/ref&gt; In 2005 the UK Film Council Digital Screen Network launched in the UK by Arts Alliance Media creating a chain of 250 2K digital cinema systems. The roll-out was completed in 2006. This was the first mass roll-out in Europe. AccessIT/Christie Digital also started a roll-out in the United States and Canada. By mid 2006, about 400 theaters were equipped with 2K digital projectors with the number increasing every month. In August 2006, the [[Malayalam]] digital movie ''[[Moonnamathoral]]'', produced by Benzy Martin, was distributed via satellite to cinemas, thus becoming the first Indian digital cinema. This was done by Emil and Eric Digital Films, a company based at Thrissur using the end-to-end digital cinema system developed by Singapore-based DG2L Technologies.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Hindu&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.hindu.com/2006/08/19/stories/2006081901860200.htm | title= Digital movie in Malayalam released | newspaper=The Hindu | date=2006-08-19 | accessdate=2006-08-23 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In January 2007, ''[[Guru (2007 film)|Guru]]'' became the first [[Indian film]] mastered in the DCI-compliant JPEG 2000 Interop format and also the first Indian film to be previewed digitally, internationally, at the Elgin Winter Garden in Toronto. This film was digitally mastered at Real Image Media Technologies in India. In 2007, the UK became home to Europe's first DCI-compliant fully digital multiplex cinemas; Odeon Hatfield and Odeon Surrey Quays (in London), with a total of 18 digital screens, were launched on 9 February 2007. By March 2007, with the release of Disney's ''[[Meet the Robinsons]]'', about 600 screens had been equipped with digital projectors. In June 2007, Arts Alliance Media announced the first European commercial digital cinema [[Virtual Print Fee]] (VPF) agreements (with [[20th Century Fox]] and [[Universal Pictures]]). In March 2009 [[AMC Theatres]] announced that it closed a $315 million deal with [[Sony]] to replace all of its [[movie projector]]s with 4K digital projectors starting in the second quarter of 2009; it was anticipated that this replacement would be finished by 2012.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news   | last = Taub  | first = Eric A.  | title = AMC to Get Sony Digital Projectors  | newspaper = New York Times  | location = New York  | date = March 29, 2009  | url = https://www.nytimes.com/2009/03/30/technology/companies/30sony.html  | accessdate = November 19, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:Ten Main Center-AMC Bldg-Kansas City MO.jpg|thumb|[[AMC Theatres]] former corporate headquarters in Kansas City, prior to their 2013 move to Leawood, Kansas.]]

In January 2011, the total number of digital screens worldwide was 36,242, up from 16,339 at end 2009 or a growth rate of 121.8 percent during the year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.isuppli.com/media-research/marketwatch/pages/digital-screen-numbers-and-forecasts-to-2015-are-finalised.aspx | title=Digital Screen Numbers and Forecasts to 2015 are Finalised | work=IHS Technology | date=January 26, 2011 | accessdate=September 1, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; There were 10,083 d-screens in Europe as a whole (28.2 percent of global figure), 16,522 in the United States and Canada (46.2 percent of global figure) and 7,703 in Asia (21.6 percent of global figure). Worldwide progress was slower as in some territories, particularly Latin America and Africa.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Romanek |first=Neal |url=http://www.screendaily.com/news/inaugural-uk-digital-cinema-conference-assesses-the-state-of-digital-cinema/5051676.article?blocktitle=ScreenTech&amp;contentID=283 |title=Inaugural UK Digital Cinema Conference assesses the state of digital cinema &amp;#124; News &amp;#124; Screen |publisher=Screendaily.com |date=2013-02-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;nj2012&quot;&gt;{{cite web| title= Newtown's old-time movie house looks for revival in the digital age| url=http://www.nj.com/mercer/index.ssf/2012/03/newtowns_old-time_movie_house.html | date= March 19, 2012 | first=Joyce J. |last=Persico|work= [[The Times (Trenton)|The Times, Trenton]] | publisher= New Jersey On-Line LLC| accessdate=2012-04-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; As of 31 March 2015, 38,719 screens (out of a total of 39,789 screens) in the United States have been converted to digital, 3,007 screens in Canada have been converted, and 93,147 screens internationally have been converted.&lt;ref name=&quot;natoonline.org&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://natoonline.org/initiatives/cinema-technologies/|title=Cinema Technologies|work=natoonline.org| accessdate=September 1, 2016 |date=2013-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the end of 2017, virtually all of the world's cinema screens were digital (98%).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=2017 THEME Report |url=https://www.mpaa.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/MPAA-THEME-Report-2017_Final.pdf |website=[[Motion Picture Association of America]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite the fact that today, virtually all global movie theaters have converted their screens to digital cinemas, some major motion pictures even as of 2019 are shot on film.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.kodak.com/US/en/motion/customers/productions/default.htm|title=StackPath|website=www.kodak.com|access-date=2019-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://filmmakermagazine.com/107353-23-films-35mm-released-in-2018/|title=24 Films Shot on 35mm Released in 2018|last=Rizov|first=Vadim|website=Filmmaker Magazine|language=en-US|access-date=2019-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, [[Quentin Tarantino]] released his latest film ''[[Once Upon a Time in Hollywood]]'' in 70 mm and 35 mm in selected theaters across the United States and [[Canada]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.indiewire.com/2019/07/once-upon-a-time-in-hollywood-35-mm-70-mm-movie-theater-locations-quentin-tarantino-1202160721/|title=Where to See ‘Once Upon a Time in Hollywood’ on Celluloid, Quentin Tarantino’s Preferred Format|last=Brueggemann|first=Tom|last2=Brueggemann|first2=Tom|date=2019-07-24|website=IndieWire|access-date=2019-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Elements==
In addition to the equipment already found in a film-based movie theatre (e.g., a [[sound reinforcement system]], screen, etc.), a DCI-compliant digital cinema requires a digital projector and a powerful computer known as a &quot;[[server (computing)|server]]&quot;. Movies are supplied to the theatre as a digital file called a [[Digital Cinema Package]] (DCP).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.filmjournal.com/filmjournal/content_display/news-and-features/features/technology/e3i6e1af20cf8f6d2fb94cd8d64bc8948e7 |title=The ABCs of DCPs: Unwrapping the Digital Cinema Package |publisher=Filmjournal.com |date=2012-08-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; For a typical feature film, this file will be anywhere between 90 GB and 300 GB of data (roughly two to six times the information of a Blu-ray disc) and may arrive as a physical delivery on a conventional computer hard drive or via satellite or fibre-optic broadband Internet.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.doremilabs.com/downloads/manuals/DCP-2000_and_DCP-2K4_User_Manual_001822_v1_2.pdf|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130319052633/http://www.doremilabs.com/downloads/manuals/DCP-2000_and_DCP-2K4_User_Manual_001822_v1_2.pdf|archivedate=March 19, 2013|title=DCP-2000 and DCP-2K4 User Manual }}&lt;/ref&gt;  As of 2013, physical deliveries of hard drives were most common in the industry. Promotional trailers arrive on a separate hard drive and range between 200 GB and 400 GB in size.

Regardless of how the DCP arrives, it first needs to be copied onto the internal hard drives of the server, usually via a USB port, a process known as &quot;ingesting&quot;. DCPs can be, and in the case of feature films almost always are, encrypted, to prevent illegal copying and piracy. The necessary decryption keys are supplied separately, usually as email attachments and then &quot;ingested&quot; via USB. Keys are time-limited and will expire after the end of the period for which the title has been booked. They are also locked to the hardware (server and projector) that is to screen the film, so if the theatre wishes to move the title to another screen or extend the run, a new key must be obtained from the distributor.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=MKPE Consulting LLC |url=http://www.mkpe.com/digital_cinema/works/dc_technology4.php |title=How Digital Cinema Works: Part 4 |publisher=Mkpe.com |date= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Several versions of the same feature can be sent together. The original version (OV) is used as the basis of all the other playback options. Version files (VF) may have a different sound format (e.g. 7.1 as opposed to [[5.1 surround sound]]) or subtitles. 2D and 3D versions are often distributed on the same hard drive.

The playback of the content is controlled by the server using a &quot;playlist&quot;. As the name implies, this is a list of all the content that is to be played as part of the performance. The playlist will be created by a member of the theatre's staff using proprietary software that runs on the server. In addition to listing the content to be played the playlist also includes automation cues that allow the playlist to control the projector, the sound system, auditorium lighting, tab curtains and screen masking (if present), etc. The playlist can be started manually, by clicking the &quot;play&quot; button on the server's monitor screen, or automatically at pre-set times.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dolby.com/gb/en/professional/hardware/cinema/cinema-servers/dss200.html |title=Dolby Screen Server (DSS200) |publisher=Dolby.com |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140101065704/http://www.dolby.com/gb/en/professional/hardware/cinema/cinema-servers/dss200.html |archivedate=2014-01-01 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Technology and standards==

===Digital Cinema Initiatives===
[[Digital Cinema Initiatives]] (DCI), a joint venture of the six [[major film studios|major studios]], published the first version (V1.0) of a system specification for digital cinema in July 2005.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=DCI Cinema Specification v1.2 |url=http://www.dcimovies.com/specification/ | publisher=Digital Cinema Initiatives |date= March 7, 2008 |accessdate =January 1, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The main declared objectives of the specification were to define a digital cinema system that would ''&quot;present a theatrical experience that is better than what one could achieve now with a traditional 35mm Answer Print&quot;'', to provide global standards for interoperability such that any DCI-compliant content could play on any DCI-compliant hardware anywhere in the world and to provide robust protection for the intellectual property of the content providers.

The DCI specification calls for picture encoding using the ISO/IEC 15444-1 &quot;[[JPEG2000]]&quot; (.j2c) standard and use of the [[CIE 1931 color space|CIE XYZ]] color space at 12 bits per component encoded with a 2.6 [[gamma correction|gamma]] applied at projection. Two levels of resolution for both content and projectors are supported: 2K (2048×1080) or 2.2 MP at 24 or 48 [[Frame rate|frames per second]], and 4K (4096×2160) or 8.85 MP at 24 frames per second. The specification ensures that 2K content can play on 4K projectors and vice versa. Smaller resolutions in one direction are also supported (the image gets automatically centered). Later versions of the standard added additional playback rates (like 25 fps in SMPTE mode). For the sound component of the content the specification provides for up to 16 channels of uncompressed audio using the [[Broadcast Wave Format|&quot;Broadcast Wave&quot; (.wav)]] format at 24 bits and 48&amp;nbsp;kHz or 96&amp;nbsp;kHz sampling.

Playback is controlled by an [[XML]]-format Composition Playlist, into an [[MXF]]-compliant file at a maximum data rate of 250 Mbit/s. Details about encryption, [[key management]], and logging are all discussed in the specification as are the minimum specifications for the projectors employed including the [[color gamut]], the [[contrast ratio]] and the brightness of the image. While much of the specification codifies work that had already been ongoing in the Society of Motion Picture and Television Engineers ([[SMPTE]]), the specification is important in establishing a content owner framework for the distribution and security of first-release motion-picture content.

===National Association of Theatre Owners===
In addition to DCI's work, the National Association of Theatre Owners (NATO) released its Digital Cinema System Requirements.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=NATO Digital Cinema Requirements v2.1 |url=http://www.natoonline.org/pdfs/NATO%20Digital%20Cinema%20System%20Requirements%20-%20release%202%201.pdf |date=December 12, 2008 |accessdate=November 19, 2009 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090326214343/http://www.natoonline.org/pdfs/NATO%20Digital%20Cinema%20System%20Requirements%20-%20release%202%201.pdf |archivedate=March 26, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The document addresses the requirements of digital cinema systems from the operational needs of the exhibitor, focusing on areas not addressed by DCI, including access for the visually impaired and hearing impaired, workflow inside the cinema, and equipment interoperability. In particular, NATO's document details requirements for the Theatre Management System (TMS), the governing software for digital cinema systems within a theatre complex, and provides direction for the development of security key management systems. As with DCI's document, NATO's document is also important to the SMPTE standards effort.

===E-Cinema===
The Society of Motion Picture and Television Engineers ([[SMPTE]]) began work on standards for digital cinema in 2000. It was clear by that point in time that HDTV did not provide a sufficient technological basis for the foundation of digital cinema playback. In Europe, India and Japan however, there is still a significant presence of HDTV for theatrical presentations. Agreements within the ISO standards body have led to these non-compliant systems being referred to as Electronic Cinema Systems (E-Cinema).

==Projectors for digital cinema==
&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Movie theater]] --&gt;
Only four manufacturers make DCI-approved digital cinema projectors; these are [[Sony]], [[Barco NV|Barco]], [[Christie (company)|Christie]] and [[NEC]]. Except for Sony, who use their own SXRD technology, all use the [[Digital Light Processing]] (DLP) technology developed by [[Texas Instruments]] (TI). D-Cinema projectors are similar in principle to digital projectors used in industry, education, and domestic home cinemas, but differ in two important respects. First, projectors must conform to the strict performance requirements of the DCI specification. Second, projectors must incorporate anti-piracy devices intended to enforce copyright compliance such as licensing limits. For these reasons all projectors intended to be sold to theaters for screening current release movies ''must'' be approved by the DCI before being put on sale. They now pass through a process called CTP (compliance test plan). Because feature films in digital form are encrypted and the decryption keys (KDMs) are locked to the serial number of the server used (linking to both the projector serial number and server is planned in the future), a system will allow playback of a protected feature only with the required KDM.

===DLP Cinema===
Three manufacturers have licensed the DLP Cinema technology developed by [[Texas Instruments]] (TI): [[Christie (company)|Christie Digital Systems]], [[Barco NV|Barco]], and [[NEC]]. While NEC is a relative newcomer to Digital Cinema, Christie is the main player in the U.S. and Barco takes the lead in Europe and Asia.{{Citation needed|date=August 2009}} Initially DCI-compliant DLP projectors were available in 2K only, but from early 2012, when TI's 4K DLP chip went into full production, DLP projectors have been available in both 2K and 4K versions. Manufacturers of DLP-based cinema projectors can now also offer 4K upgrades to some of the more recent 2K models.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.christiedigital.co.uk/emea/cinema/cinema-products/digital-cinema-projectors/pages/default.aspx |title=DLP Cinema Projectors&amp;#124;Christie - Visual Display Solutions |publisher=Christiedigital.co.uk |date= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Early [[Digital Light Processing|DLP Cinema projectors]], which were deployed primarily in the United States, used limited 1280×1024 resolution or the equivalent of 1.3 MP (megapixels). Digital Projection Incorporated (DPI) designed and sold a few DLP Cinema units (is8-2K) when TI's 2K technology debuted but then abandoned the D-Cinema market while continuing to offer DLP-based projectors for non-cinema purposes. Although based on the same 2K TI &quot;light engine&quot; as those of the major players they are so rare as to be virtually unknown in the industry. They are still widely used for pre-show advertising but not usually for feature presentations.

TI's technology is based on the use of digital micromirror devices (DMDs).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dlp.com/cinema/dlp-cinema/ |title=What is Digital Cinema – About Digital Theater - DLP Cinema Technology &amp;#124; DLP – Texas Instruments |publisher=Dlp.com |date= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt; These devices are manufactured from silicon using similar technology to that of computer memory chips. The surface of these devices is covered by a very large number of microscopic mirrors, one for each pixel, so a 2K device has about 2.2 million mirrors and a 4K device about 8.8 million. Each mirror vibrates several thousand times a second between two positions: In one, light from the projector's lamp is reflected towards the screen, in the other away from it. The proportion of the time the mirror is in each position varies according to the required brightness of each pixel. Three DMD devices are used, one for each of the primary colors. Light from the lamp, usually a Xenon similar to those used in film projectors with a power between 1&amp;nbsp;kW and 7&amp;nbsp;kW, is split by colored filters into red, green and blue beams which are directed at the appropriate DMD. The 'forward' reflected beam from the three DMMDs is then re-combined and focused by the lens onto the cinema screen.

===Sony SXRD===
Alone amongst the manufacturers of DCI-compliant cinema projectors Sony decided to develop its own technology rather than use TI's DLP technology. SXRD (Silicon X-tal (Crystal) Reflective Display) projectors have only ever been manufactured in 4K form and, until the launch of the 4K DLP chip by TI, Sony SXRD projectors were the only 4K DCI-compatible projectors on the market. Unlike DLP projectors, however, SXRD projectors do not present the left and right eye images of stereoscopic movies sequentially, instead they use half the available area on the SXRD chip for each eye image. Thus during stereoscopic presentations the SXRD projector functions as a sub 2K projector, the same for HFR 3D Content.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=SRX-R515P |url=http://www.sony.co.uk/pro/product/dcinemaproj/srx-r515/specifications#specifications |title=SRX-R515P (SRXR515P) : Specifications : United Kingdom : Sony Professional |publisher=Sony.co.uk |date= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Stereo 3D images===
In late 2005, interest in digital 3-D [[stereoscopy|stereoscopic]] projection led to a new willingness on the part of theaters to co-operate in installing 2K stereo installations to show Disney's ''[[Chicken Little (2005 film)|Chicken Little]]'' in [[3-D film]]. Six more digital 3-D movies were released in 2006 and 2007 (including ''[[Beowulf (2007 film)|Beowulf]]'', ''[[Monster House (film)|Monster House]]'' and ''[[Meet the Robinsons]]''). The technology combines a single digital projector fitted with either a polarizing filter (for use with [[polarized glasses]] and silver screens), a filter wheel or an emitter for LCD glasses. ''[[RealD]]'' uses a &quot;''[[ZScreen]]''&quot; for polarisation and MasterImage uses a filter wheel that changes the polarity of projector's light output several times per second to alternate quickly the left-and-right-eye views. Another system that uses a filter wheel is [[Dolby 3D]]. The wheel changes the wavelengths of the colours being displayed, and tinted glasses filter these changes so the incorrect wavelength cannot enter the wrong eye. ''[[XpanD 3D|XpanD]]'' makes use of an external emitter that sends a signal to the 3D glasses to block out the wrong image from the wrong eye.

===Laser===
RGB laser projection for digital cinema: producing the purest [[rec2020|colors]] and the brightest images.&lt;ref&gt;See Binant, ''Introduction to Laser. From a Physical Point of View'' (in french [http://cst.fr/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/LETTRE_CST_164.pdf ''Introduction au laser. Du point de vue de la physique'', '''La Lettre''', n° 164, Commission Supérieure Technique de l'Image et du Son, Paris, 2017, p. 9-13.])&lt;/ref&gt;

==LED screen for digital cinema==
In [[Asia]], on July 13, 2017, an LED screen for digital cinema developed by [[Samsung Electronics]] was publicly demonstrated on one screen at [[Lotte Cinema]] World Tower in [[Seoul]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://news.samsung.com/us/samsung-debuts-worlds-first-cinema-led-display-harman-audio/|title=Samsung Debuts World’s First Cinema LED Display|date=July 12, 2017|website=Samsung US Newsroom}}&lt;/ref&gt; First installation in Europe is in Arena Sihlcity Cinema in Zürich.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://news.samsung.com/global/samsung-debuts-worlds-first-3d-cinema-led-screen-theater-in-switzerland|title=Samsung Debuts World's First 3D Cinema LED Screen Theater in Switzerland|website=news.samsung.com|language=en|access-date=2018-07-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; These displays do not use a projector; instead they use a [[MicroLED]] [[video wall]], and can offer higher contrast ratios, higher resolutions, and overall improvements in image quality. MicroLED allows for the elimination of display bezels, creating the illusion of a single large screen. This is possible due to the large amount of spacing in between pixels in MicroLED displays. Sony already sells MicroLED displays as a replacement for conventional cinema screens.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.engadget.com/amp/2019/09/13/sony-crystal-cinema-16k-home-theater/&lt;/ref&gt;

==Effect on distribution==
[[Digital distribution]] of movies has the potential to save money for film distributors.  To print an 80-minute feature film can cost US$1,500 to $2,500,&lt;ref&gt;Frazer, Bryant. [http://www.studiodaily.com/filmandvideo/currentissue/9520.html Animating a Personal Flash Epic]. ''Studio Daily''. May 22, 2008. Accessed on: May 22, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; so making thousands of prints for a wide-release movie can cost millions of dollars. In contrast, at the maximum 250 megabit-per-second data rate (as defined by [[Digital Cinema Initiatives|DCI]] for digital cinema), a feature-length movie can be stored on an [[Commercial off-the-shelf|off-the-shelf]] 300&amp;nbsp;[[Gigabyte|GB]] hard drive for $50 and a broad release of 4000 'digital prints' might cost $200,000. In addition hard drives can be returned to distributors for reuse. With several hundred movies distributed every year, the industry saves billions of dollars. The digital-cinema roll-out was stalled by the slow pace at which exhibitors acquired digital projectors, since the savings would be seen not by themselves but by distribution companies. The [[Virtual Print Fee]] model was created to address this by passing some of the saving on to the cinemas.{{citation needed|date=October 2015}} As a consequence of the rapid conversion to digital projection, the number of theatrical releases exhibited on film is dwindling. As of 4 May 2014, 37,711 screens (out of a total of 40,048 screens) in the United States have been converted to digital, 3,013 screens in Canada have been converted, and 79,043 screens internationally have been converted.&lt;ref name=&quot;natoonline.org&quot;/&gt;

===Telecommunication===
Realization and demonstration, on October 29, 2001, of the first digital cinema transmission by [[communications satellite|satellite]] in [[Europe]]&lt;ref&gt;[[France Télécom]], Commission Supérieure Technique de l'Image et du Son, ''Communiqué de presse'', Paris, October 29th, 2001.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.passeursdimages.fr/IMG/pdf/projections13.pdf|title=«Numérique : le cinéma en mutation», ''Projections'', '''13''', CNC, Paris, September 2004, p. 7.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=JhLwPrW8pggC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=olivier+bomsel+mines&amp;hl=fr&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=hKGhUqllpOzSBdulgcgL&amp;ved=0CDMQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=olivier+bomsel+mines&amp;f=false|title=Dernier tango argentique|first1=Olivier|last1=Bomsel|first2=Gilles Le|last2=Blanc|date=December 27, 2002|publisher=Presses des MINES|via=Google Books}}&lt;/ref&gt; of a [[feature film]] by Bernard Pauchon,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.authorstream.com/Presentation/Veronica-45205-france-telecom-DIGITAL-CINEMA-global-leaderin-professional-broadcastingand-Education-ppt-powerpoint/|title=France Telecom|website=authorSTREAM}}&lt;/ref&gt; Alain Lorentz, Raymond Melwig&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://books.google.fr/books?id=drqODwAAQBAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=Critical+Space+Infrastructures&amp;hl=fr&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwjd2LGj9sLhAhXKxYUKHb_aCogQ6AEIKDAA#v=onepage&amp;q=Critical+Space+Infrastructures&amp;f=false|title=Critical Space Infrastructures: Risk, Resilience and Complexity|first1=Alexandru|last1=Georgescu|first2=Adrian V.|last2=Gheorghe|first3=Marius-Ioan|last3=Piso|first4=Polinpapilinho F.|last4=Katina|date=March 25, 2019|publisher=Springer|via=Google Books}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Philippe Binant.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.01net.com/actualites/|title=Actualités|website=01net}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://fr.slideshare.net/desbinwag/datacom-module-1|title=Datacom module 1:  Introduction to Data Communications|date=February 20, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Live broadcasting to cinemas ===
[[File:Broadcasting1.JPG|thumb|right|[[Broadcasting]] antenna in Stuttgart]]
Digital cinemas can deliver live [[Broadcasting|broadcasts]] from performances or events. This began initially with live broadcasts from the New York Metropolitan Opera delivering regular live broadcasts into cinemas and has been widely imitated ever since. Leading territories providing the content are the UK, the USA, France and Germany.  The Royal Opera House, Sydney Opera House, English National Opera and others have found new and returning audiences captivated by the detail offered by a live digital broadcast featuring handheld and cameras on cranes positioned throughout the venue to capture the emotion that might be missed in a live venue situation. In addition these providers all offer additional value during the intervals e.g. interviews with choreographers, cast members, a backstage tour which would not be on offer at the live event itself. Other live events in this field include live theatre from NT Live, Branagh Live, Royal Shakespeare Company, Shakespeare's Globe, the Royal Ballet, Mariinsky Ballet, the Bolshoi Ballet and the Berlin Philharmoniker.

In the last ten years this initial offering of the arts has also expanded to include live and recorded music events such as Take That Live, One Direction Live, Andre Rieu, live musicals such as the recent Miss Saigon and a record-breaking Billy Elliot Live In Cinemas. Live sport, documentary with a live question and answer element such as the recent Oasis documentary, lectures, faith broadcasts, stand up comedy, museum and gallery exhibitions, TV specials such as the record-breaking ''[[Doctor Who]]'' fiftieth anniversary special ''The Day Of The Doctor'', have all contributed to creating a valuable revenue stream for cinemas large and small all over the world.  Subsequently, live broadcasting, formerly known as Alternative Content, has become known as Event Cinema and a trade association now exists to that end. Ten years on the sector has become a sizeable revenue stream in its own right, earning a loyal following amongst fans of the arts, and the content limited only by the imagination of the producers it would seem. Theatre, ballet, sport, exhibitions, TV specials and documentaries are now established forms of Event Cinema. Worldwide estimations put the likely value of the Event Cinema industry at $1bn by 2019.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.eventcinemaassociation.org/assets/eca-screendigestreport2013.pdf | title=Event Cinema in European cinemas | work=IHS Screen Digest | accessdate=September 1, 2016 | type=Report | archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140513093812/http://www.eventcinemaassociation.org/assets/eca-screendigestreport2013.pdf | archivedate=May 13, 2014 | url-status=dead | year=2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Event Cinema currently accounts for on average between 1-3% of overall box office for cinemas worldwide but anecdotally it's been reported that some cinemas attribute as much as 25%, 48% and even 51% (the Rio Bio cinema in Stockholm) of their overall box office. It is envisaged ultimately that Event Cinema will account for around 5% of the overall box office globally. Event Cinema saw 6 worldwide records set and broken over from 2013-15 with notable successes Dr Who ($10.2m in 3 days at the box office - event was also broadcast on terrestrial TV simultaneously), Pompeii Live by the British Museum, Billy Elliot, Andre Rieu, One Direction, Richard III by the Royal Shakespeare Company.

Event Cinema is defined more by the frequency of events rather than by the content itself. Event Cinema events typically appear in cinemas during traditionally quieter times in the cinema week such as the Monday-Thursday daytime/evening slot and are characterised by the One Night Only release, followed by one or possibly more 'Encore' releases a few days or weeks later if the event is successful and sold out. On occasion more successful events have returned to cinemas some months or even years later in the case of NT Live where the audience loyalty and company branding is so strong the content owner can be assured of a good showing at the box office.

==Pros and cons==

=== Pros ===
The digital formation of sets and locations, especially in the time of growing film series and sequels, is that virtual sets, once computer generated and stored, can be easily revived for future films.&lt;ref name=&quot;Creeber 2009&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title = Digital Culture: Understanding New Media|last = Creeber|first = Glen|publisher = Open University Press|year = 2009|isbn = 978-0-335-22197-4|location = |last2 = Martin|first2 = Royston}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|62}}
Considering digital film images are documented as data files on hard disk or flash memory, varying systems of edits can be executed with the alteration of a few settings on the editing console with the structure being composed virtually in the computer's memory. A broad choice of effects can be sampled simply and rapidly, without the physical constraints posed by traditional cut-and-stick editing.&lt;ref name=&quot;Creeber 2009&quot;/&gt;{{rp|63}} Digital cinema allows national cinemas to construct films specific to their cultures in ways that the more constricting configurations and economics of customary film-making prevented. Low-cost cameras and computer-based editing software have gradually enabled films to be produced for minimal cost. The ability of digital cameras to allow film-makers to shoot limitless footage without wasting pricey celluloid has transformed film production in some Third World countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Digital Culture: Understanding New Media|last = Creeber|first = Glen|publisher = Open University Press|year = 2009|isbn = 978-0-335-22197-4|location = |pages = 66|last2 = Martin|first2 = Royston.}}&lt;/ref&gt; From consumers' perspective digital prints don't deteriorate with the number of showings. Unlike celluloid film, there is no projection mechanism or manual handling to add scratches or other physically generated artefacts. Provincial cinemas that would have received old prints can give consumers the same cinematographic experience (all other things being equal) as those attending the premiere.

=== Cons ===
A number of high-profile film directors, including [[Christopher Nolan]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Merchan |first=George |url=http://www.joblo.com/movie-news/christopher-nolan-discusses-why-he-prefers-film-to-digital-his-approach-to-cgi-and-much-more |title=Christopher Nolan talks film vs. digital, his take on CGI, his disinterest in 3D, and much more in insightful DGA interview - Movie News |publisher=JoBlo.com |date=2012-04-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Paul Thomas Anderson]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=//www.youtube.com/watch?v=7npmu9Ge_OY |title=pta on digital vs. film |publisher=YouTube |date=2006-08-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[David O. Russell]]&lt;ref name=&quot;thr2012&quot;&gt;{{cite magazine|url=http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/news/ben-affleck-quentin-tarantino-4-394576 |title=Director Roundtable: 6 Auteurs on Tantrums, Crazy Actors and Quitting While They're Ahead |magazine=The Hollywood Reporter |date=November 28, 2012 |first1=Stephen |last1=Galloway |first2=Matthew |last2=Belloni |accessdate=November 10, 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Quentin Tarantino]]&lt;ref name=&quot;thr2012&quot; /&gt; have publicly criticized digital cinema and advocated the use of film and film prints. Most famously, Tarantino has suggested he may retire because, though he can still shoot on film, because of the rapid conversion to digital, he cannot project from 35&amp;nbsp;mm prints in the majority of American cinemas.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/movies/news/a441960/quentin-tarantino-i-cant-stand-digital-filmmaking-its-tv-in-public.html |title=Quentin Tarantino: 'I can't stand digital filmmaking, it's TV in public' - Movies News |website=Digital Spy |date=2012-11-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Steven Spielberg]] has stated that though digital projection produces a much better image than film if originally shot in digital, it is &quot;inferior&quot; when it has been converted to digital. He attempted at one stage to release ''[[Indiana Jones and the Kingdom of the Crystal Skull]]'' solely on film.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=//www.youtube.com/watch?v=gXhusVVnidY |title=Steven Spielberg on Digital Cinema |publisher=YouTube |date= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Paul Thomas Anderson recently was able to create [[70mm Film|70-mm film]] prints for his film ''[[The Master (2012 film)|The Master]]'' {{citation needed|date=May 2017}}.

Film critic [[Roger Ebert]] criticized the use of DCPs after a cancelled film festival screening of [[Brian DePalma]]'s film ''[[Passion (2012 film)|Passion]]'' at [[New York Film Festival]] as a result of a lockup due to the coding system.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.technologytell.com/entertainment/6748/digital-projection-mishap-derails-premiere-of-de-palmas-passion-at-new-york-film-festival/ |title=Digital Projection Mishap Derails Premiere of De Palma's &quot;Passion&quot; at New York Film Festival - EntertainmentTell |publisher=Technologytell.com |date= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The theoretical resolution of 35&amp;nbsp;mm film is greater than that of 2K digital cinema.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.reduser.net/forum/showthread.php?59036-Resolution-of-35mm-film-and-70mm-IMAX-film |title=Resolution of 35mm film and 70mm IMAX film? |publisher=Reduser.net |date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=TMB1&gt;{{cite book | last =Laemmle | first =Robert | title =The Movie Business Book, Third Edition - The Independent Exhibitor | publisher =[[Simon &amp; Schuster]] | year =2004 | location = | pages = | isbn =0-7432-1937-6}}&lt;/ref&gt; 2K resolution (2048×1080) is also only slightly greater than that of consumer based [[1080p HD]] (1920x1080).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.reduser.net/forum/archive/index.php/t-2398.html |title=2K vs 1080p resolution question [Archive |publisher=REDUSER.net |date= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, since digital post-production techniques became the standard in the early 2000s, the majority of movies, whether photographed digitally or on 35&amp;nbsp;mm film, have been mastered and edited at the 2K resolution. Moreover, 4K post production was becoming more common as of 2013. As projectors are replaced with 4K models&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Boxoffice Media, Llc |url=http://www.boxoffice.com/latest-news/2013-04-16-sonys-digital-cinema-momentum-continues-with-record-number-of-4k-projectors-shipped-eight-years-of-continuous-growth |title=BoxOffice® — SONY'S DIGITAL CINEMA MOMENTUM CONTINUES WITH RECORD NUMBER OF 4K PROJECTORS SHIPPED; EIGHT YEARS OF CONTINUOUS GROWTHBoxOffice® — News |publisher=Boxoffice.com |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131113223151/http://www.boxoffice.com/latest-news/2013-04-16-sonys-digital-cinema-momentum-continues-with-record-number-of-4k-projectors-shipped-eight-years-of-continuous-growth |archivedate=2013-11-13 }}&lt;/ref&gt; the difference in resolution between digital and 35&amp;nbsp;mm film is somewhat reduced.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://pic.templetons.com/brad/photo/pixels.html/ |title=How many pixels are there in a frame of 35mm film? |publisher=Technologytell.com |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150812075520/http://pic.templetons.com/brad/photo/pixels.html |archivedate=2015-08-12 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Digital cinema servers utilize far greater bandwidth over domestic &quot;HD&quot;, allowing for a difference in quality (e.g., Blu-ray colour encoding 4:2:0 48Mbit/s MAX datarate, DCI D-Cinema 4:4:4 250Mbit/s 2D/3D, 500Mbit/s HFR3D). Each frame has greater detail.

Owing to the smaller dynamic range of digital cameras, correcting poor digital exposures is more difficult than correcting poor film exposures during post-production. A partial solution to this problem is to add complex video-assist technology during the shooting process. However, such technologies are typically available only to high-budget production companies.&lt;ref name=&quot;Creeber 2009&quot;/&gt;{{rp|62}} Digital cinemas' efficiency of storing images has a downside. The speed and ease of modern digital editing processes threatens to give editors and their directors, if not an embarrassment of choice then at least a confusion of options, potentially making the editing process, with this 'try it and see' philosophy, lengthier rather than shorter.&lt;ref name=&quot;Creeber 2009&quot;/&gt;{{rp|63}} Because the equipment needed to produce digital feature films can be obtained more easily than celluloid, producers could inundate the market with cheap productions and potentially dominate the efforts of serious directors. Because of the quick speed in which they are filmed, these stories sometimes lack essential narrative structure.&lt;ref name=&quot;Creeber 2009&quot;/&gt;{{rp|66–67}}

The projectors used for celluloid film were largely the same technology as when film/movies were invented over 100 years ago. The evolutions of adding sound and wide screen could largely be accommodated by bolting on sound decoders, and changing lenses. This well proven and understood technology had several advantages 1) The life of a mechanical projector of around 35 years 2) a mean time between failures ([[mean time between failures|MTBF]]) of 15 years and 3) an average repair time of 15 minutes (often done by the projectionist). On the other hand, digital projectors are around 10 times more expensive, have a much shorter life expectancy due to the developing technology (already technology has moved from 2K to 4K) so the pace of obsolescence is higher. The MTBF has not yet been established, but the ability for the projectionist to effect a quick repair has gone.

===Costs===

==== Pros ====
The electronic transferring of digital film, from central servers to servers in cinema projection booths, is an inexpensive process of supplying copies of newest releases to the vast number of cinema screens demanded by prevailing saturation-release strategies. There is a significant saving on print expenses in such cases: at a minimum cost per print of $1200–2000, the cost of celluloid print production is between $5–8 million per film. With several thousand releases a year, the probable savings offered by digital distribution and projection are over $1 billion.&lt;ref name=&quot;Creeber 2009&quot;/&gt;{{rp|67}} The cost savings and ease, together with the ability to store film rather than having to send a print on to the next cinema, allows a larger scope of films to be screened and watched by the public; minority and small-budget films that would not otherwise get such a chance.&lt;ref name=&quot;Creeber 2009&quot;/&gt;{{rp|67}}

==== Cons ====
The initial costs for converting theaters to digital are high: $100,000 per screen, on average. Theaters have been reluctant to switch without a cost-sharing arrangement with [[film distributor]]s. A solution is a temporary ''[[Virtual Print Fee]]'' system, where the distributor (who saves the money of producing and transporting a film print) pays a fee per copy to help finance the digital systems of the theaters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=AAM VPF |url=http://www.artsalliancemedia.com/services/finance |title=AAM VPF |publisher=AAM |date= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt; A theater can purchase a film projector for as little as $10,000&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ebay.com/itm/Westar-CFEC-105X-35mm-Projection-System-NEW-UNUSED-/250750810837 |title=Westar Cfec 105 x 35 mm Projection System New Unused |publisher=eBay |date=2012-04-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; (though projectors intended for commercial cinemas cost two to three times that; to which must be added the cost of a [[Single reel|long-play system]], which also costs around $10,000, making a total of around $30,000–$40,000) from which they could expect an average life of 30–40 years. By contrast, a digital cinema playback system—including server, [[Media Block|media block]], and projector—can cost two to three times as much,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.projectorreviews.com/dlp-3-chip-projectors.php |title=DLP 3 Chip Projectors |publisher=Projector Reviews |date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; and would have a greater risk of component failure and obsolescence. (In Britain the cost of an entry level projector including server, installation, etc., would be £31,000 [$50,000].)

Archiving [[digital master]]s has also turned out to be both tricky and costly. In a 2007 study, the [[Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences]] found the cost of long-term storage of 4K digital masters to be &quot;enormously higher—up to 11 times that of the cost of storing film masters.&quot; This is because of the limited or uncertain lifespan of digital storage: No current digital medium—be it [[optical disc]], magnetic [[hard drive]] or digital tape—can reliably store a motion picture for as long as a hundred years or more (something that film—properly stored and handled—does very well).&lt;ref name=&quot;digital_dilemma&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal | title = The Digital Dilemma. Strategic issues in archiving and accessing digital motion picture materials. | publisher = [[Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences]] |
year = 2007 | postscript = &lt;!--None--&gt; }}&lt;/ref&gt; The short history of digital storage media has been one of innovation and, therefore, of obsolescence. Archived digital content must be periodically removed from obsolete physical media to up-to-date media. The expense of [[digital cinematography|digital image capture]] is not necessarily less than the capture of images onto film; indeed, it is sometimes greater.{{citation needed|date=March 2015}}

== List of companies ==
* [[Barco (manufacturer)|Barco]] &amp;mdash; digital projector manufacturer
* [[Blackmagic Design]] &amp;mdash; digital cinema camera and distribution equipment manufacturer
* [[Christie (company)|Christie]] &amp;mdash; digital projector manufacturer
* [[Cinedigm]] &amp;mdash; Digital Cinema Software, Distribution
* [[CinemaNext]] &amp;mdash; theater system integrator &amp; digital server manufacturer
* [[Cinemeccanica]] &amp;mdash; Laser illumination system, Digital server and theater management system manufacturer
* [[Deluxe Digital Studios]] &amp;mdash; distributor and theater system integrator
* [[Dolby Laboratories]] &amp;mdash; theater system integrator
* [[Doremi Labs]] &amp;mdash; (now purchased by Dolby Labs) Digital server and theater management system manufacturer
* [[IMAX]] &amp;mdash; digital projector manufacturer
* [[K Sera Sera Limited|K Sera Sera Miniplex]]  &amp;mdash; India's third largest digital technology provider
* [[Kinoton]] &amp;mdash; manufacturer of digital projection solutions
* [[Kodak]] &amp;mdash; theater system integrator
* [[NEC]] &amp;mdash; digital projector manufacturer
* [[MasterImage 3D]] &amp;mdash; 3D cinema and mobile display technology
* [[Panavision 3D]] &amp;mdash; 3D cinema display technology
* [[Qube Cinema]] &amp;mdash; Digital Cinema mastering, distribution and server products manufacturer
* [[RealD Cinema]] &amp;mdash; 3D cinema display technology
* [[Red Digital Cinema Camera Company|RED Digital Cinema Camera Company]] &amp;mdash; digital cinema camera manufacturer
* [[Samsung Electronics]] &amp;mdash; developers of LED screen for digital cinema
* [[Silicon Imaging]] &amp;mdash; digital cinema camera manufacturer
* [[Sony]] &amp;mdash; manufacturer of 4K digital projector, cinema camera manufacturer and digital cinema servers and theater system integrator
* [[Technicolor]] &amp;mdash; distributor and theater system integrator
* [[Texas Instruments]] &amp;mdash; developers of [[Digital Light Processing|DLP Cinema]] projector technology
* [[UFO Moviez]] &amp;mdash; India's largest satellite based digital cinema

== See also ==
* [[JPEG 2000]]
*[[4K resolution]]
*[[Digital cinematography]]
*[[Digital projector]]
*[[Digital intermediate]]
*[[Digital Cinema Initiatives]]
*[[Display resolution]]
*[[Digital 3D]]
*[[3-D film]]
*[[Color suite]]
*[[List of movie-related topics|List of film-related topics]] (extensive alphabetical listing)

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Bibliography==
* {{in lang|en}} [[Charles S. Swartz]] (editor), ''Understanding digital cinema. A professional handbook'', Elseiver / Focal Press, Burlington, Oxford, 2005, xvi + 327 p. {{ISBN|0-240-80617-4}}
* {{in lang|fr}} Philippe Binant (propos recueillis par Dominique Maillet), « Kodak. Au cœur de la projection numérique », ''Actions'', n° 29, Division Cinéma et Télévision Kodak, Paris, 2007, p.&amp;nbsp;12–13. {{ISSN|1271-1519}}

==Filmography==
* {{in lang|en}} Christopher Kenneally, ''[[Side by Side (2012 film)|Side by Side]]'', 2012. [https://www.imdb.com/title/tt2014338/ IMDb]

==External links==
* {{in lang|en}} [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=i5BRuUhcFag ''Side by  Side'' : Q &amp; A with Keanu Reeves, Le Royal Monceau, Paris, April 11–12, 2016.]

{{High-definition}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Digital cinema}}
[[Category:Film and video technology]]
[[Category:Digital media]]</text>
      <sha1>pwzdy9j9d22h1ut56ejt89k0cxlar38</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
