  <page>
    <title>Dandy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8859</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942790871</id>
      <parentid>942790847</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-26T21:21:01Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Phuzion</username>
        <id>917354</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contributions/73.237.165.236|73.237.165.236]] ([[User talk:73.237.165.236|talk]]) ([[WP:HG|HG]]) (3.4.9)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Historically, a man who emphasised physical appearance, refined language and leisurely hobbies}}
{{About|the persons}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2020}}
[[File:Dandys 1830.jpg|thumb|right|upright|Sporty Parisian dandies of the 1830s: a tight [[corset]] helped one achieve his silhouette. The man on the left wears a [[frock]], the man on the right wears [[morning dress]].]]

A '''dandy''', historically, is a man who places particular importance upon [[physical appearance]], refined language, and leisurely hobbies, pursued with the appearance of nonchalance in a cult of [[self]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;One who studies ostentatiously to dress fashionably and elegantly; a [[fop]], an exquisite.&quot; (''[[OED]]'').&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | title=Oxford English Dictionary | year = 1989 | url=http://dictionary.oed.com |quote=dude, n. U.S.A name given in ridicule to a man affecting an exaggerated fastidiousness in dress, speech, and deportment, and very particular about what is æsthetically 'good form'; hence, extended to an exquisite, a dandy, 'a swell'. | publisher=Oxford University Press }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Cult de soi-même'', [[Charles Baudelaire]], &quot;Le Dandy&quot;, noted in Susann Schmid, &quot;Byron and Wilde: The Dandy in the Public Sphere&quot; in Julie Hibbard ''et al.'' , eds. ''The Importance of Reinventing Oscar: versions of Wilde during the last 100 years'' 2002&lt;/ref&gt; A dandy could be a [[self-made man]] who strove to imitate an [[Aristocracy|aristocratic]] lifestyle despite coming from a [[middle-class]] background, especially in late 18th- and early 19th-century [[Great Britain|Britain]].

Previous manifestations of the ''petit-maître'' (French for &quot;small master&quot;) and the [[Muscadin]] have been noted by John C. Prevost,&lt;ref&gt;''Le Dandysme en France (1817–1839)'' (Geneva and Paris) 1957.&lt;/ref&gt; but the modern practice of dandyism first appeared in the revolutionary 1790s, both in [[London]] and in [[Paris]]. The dandy cultivated cynical reserve, yet to such extremes that novelist [[George Meredith]], himself no dandy, once defined [[cynicism (contemporary)|cynicism]] as &quot;intellectual dandyism&quot;. Some took a more benign view; [[Thomas Carlyle]] wrote in ''[[Sartor Resartus]]'' that a dandy was no more than &quot;a clothes-wearing man&quot;. [[Honoré de Balzac]] introduced the perfectly worldly and unmoved Henri de Marsay in ''[[La fille aux yeux d'or]]'' (1835), a part of ''[[La Comédie Humaine]]'', who fulfils at first the model of a perfect dandy, until an obsessive love-pursuit unravels him in passionate and murderous jealousy.

[[Charles Baudelaire]] defined the dandy, in the later &quot;metaphysical&quot; phase of dandyism,&lt;ref&gt;See Prevost 1957.&lt;/ref&gt; as one who elevates [[æsthetics]] to a living religion,&lt;ref&gt;Baudelaire, in his essay about painter [[Constantin Guys]], &quot;The Painter of Modern Life&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; that the dandy's mere existence reproaches the responsible citizen of the middle class: &quot;Dandyism in certain respects comes close to spirituality and to [[stoicism]]&quot; and &quot;These beings have no other status, but that of cultivating the idea of beauty in their own persons, of satisfying their passions, of feeling and thinking .... Dandyism is a form of Romanticism. Contrary to what many thoughtless people seem to believe, dandyism is not even an excessive delight in clothes and material elegance. For the perfect dandy, these things are no more than the symbol of the aristocratic superiority of mind.&quot;

The linkage of clothing with political protest had become a particularly English characteristic during the 18th century.&lt;ref&gt;Aileen Ribeiro, &quot;On Englishness in dress&quot; in ''The Englishness of English Dress'', Christopher Breward, Becky Conekin and Caroline Cox, ed., 2002.&lt;/ref&gt; Given these connotations, dandyism can be seen as a political protest against the levelling effect of [[egalitarian]] principles, often including nostalgic adherence to feudal or pre-industrial values, such as the ideals of &quot;the perfect gentleman&quot; or &quot;the autonomous aristocrat&quot;. Paradoxically, the dandy required an audience, as Susann Schmid observed in examining the &quot;successfully marketed lives&quot; of [[Oscar Wilde]] and [[Lord Byron]], who exemplify the dandy's roles in the public sphere, both as writers and as ''personae'' providing sources of gossip and [[scandal]].&lt;ref&gt;Schmid 2002.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Nigel Rodgers]] in ''The Dandy: Peacock or Enigma?'' questions Wilde's status as a genuine dandy, seeing him as someone who only assumed a dandified stance in passing, not a man dedicated to the exacting ideals of dandyism.

== Etymology ==

The origin of the word is uncertain. ''Eccentricity'', defined as taking characteristics such as dress and appearance to extremes, began to be applied generally to human behavior in the 1770s;&lt;ref&gt;Ribeiro 2002:20, under the subheading &quot;Eccentricity, Extremes, and Affectation&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; similarly, the word ''dandy'' first appears in the late 18th century:  In the years immediately preceding the American Revolution, the first verse and chorus of &quot;[[Yankee Doodle]]&quot; derided the alleged poverty and rough manners of American-citizen colonists, suggesting that whereas a fine horse and gold-braided clothing (&quot;[[Maccaroni (fashion)|mac[c]aroni]]&quot;) were required to set a dandy apart from those around him, the average American citizen-colonist's means were so meager that ownership of a mere pony and a few feathers for personal ornamentation would qualify one of them as a &quot;dandy&quot; by comparison to and/or in the minds of his even less sophisticated Eurasian compatriots.&lt;ref&gt;[http://memory.loc.gov/ammem/today/apr19.html#yankee &quot;Yankee Doodle&quot;]; [[Maccaroni (fashion)|Maccaroni]].&lt;/ref&gt; A slightly later [[Border ballad|Scottish border ballad]], circa 1780,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | title=Oxford English Dictionary | year = 1989 | url=http://dictionary.oed.com |quote=dandy 1.a. One who studies above everything to dress elegantly and fashionably; a beau, fop, 'exquisite'.  c1780 Sc. Song (see [[Notes and Queries|N. &amp; Q.]] 8th Ser. IV. 81), I've heard my granny crack O' sixty twa years back When there were sic a stock of Dandies O; Oh they gaed to Kirk and Fair, Wi' their ribbons round their hair, And their stumpie drugget coats, quite the Dandy O.  | publisher=Oxford University Press }}&lt;/ref&gt; also features the word, but probably without all the contextual aspects of its more recent meaning. The original, full form of 'dandy' may have been ''jack-a-dandy''.&lt;ref&gt;''Encyclopædia Britannica'', 1911&lt;/ref&gt; It was a [[vogue word]] during the [[Napoleonic Wars]]. In that contemporary slang, a &quot;dandy&quot; was differentiated from a &quot;[[fop]]&quot; in that the dandy's dress was more refined and sober than the fop's.

In the twenty-first century, the word ''dandy'' is a jocular, often sarcastic adjective meaning &quot;fine&quot; or &quot;great&quot;; when used in the form of a noun, it refers to a well-groomed and well-dressed man, but often to one who is also self-absorbed.&lt;ref&gt;See, for example, the ''Dandyism'' blog by Christian Chensvold, continually since 2004, but with a published record on the subject since the mid-1990s. http://www.dandyism.net&lt;/ref&gt;

== Beau Brummell and early British dandyism ==
[[File:BrummellDighton1805.jpg|right|thumb|upright|Caricature of [[Beau Brummell]] by [[Richard Dighton]] (1805).]]
The model dandy in British society was [[Beau Brummell|George Bryan &quot;Beau&quot; Brummell]] (1778–1840), in his early days, an undergraduate student at [[Oriel College, Oxford]] and later, an associate of the [[George IV of the United Kingdom|Prince Regent]].  Brummell was not from an aristocratic background; indeed, his greatness was &quot;based on nothing at all,&quot; as [[Jules Amédée Barbey d'Aurevilly|J.A. Barbey d'Aurevilly]] observed in 1845.&lt;ref&gt;Barbey d'Aurevilly, &quot;Du dandisme et de George Brummell,&quot; (published 1845, collected in ''Oeuvres complètes'' 1925:87–92).&lt;/ref&gt; Never unpowdered or unperfumed, immaculately bathed and shaved, and dressed in a plain dark blue coat,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;In Regency England, Brummel's fashionable simplicity constituted in fact a criticism of the exuberant French fashions of the eighteenth century&quot; (Schmid 2002:83),&lt;/ref&gt; he was always perfectly brushed, perfectly fitted, showing much perfectly starched linen, all freshly laundered, and composed with an elaborately knotted [[cravat]]. From the mid-1790s, Beau Brummell was the early incarnation of &quot;the celebrity&quot;, a man chiefly famous for ''being'' famous.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Kelly |first1=Ian |title=Beau Brummell: The Ultimate Man of Style |date=2006 |publisher=Free Press |location=New York |isbn=9780743270892 |url-access=registration |url=https://archive.org/details/beaubrummellulti00kell }}&lt;/ref&gt;

By the time [[William Pitt the Younger|Pitt]] [[Duty on Hair Powder Act 1795|taxed hair powder]] in 1795 to help pay for the war against France and to discourage the use of flour (which had recently increased in both rarity and price, owing to bad harvests) in such a frivolous product, Brummell had already abandoned wearing a wig, and had his hair cut in the Roman fashion, &quot;à la Brutus&quot;. Moreover, he led the transition from [[breeches]] to snugly tailored dark &quot;[[Trousers|pantaloons]],&quot; which directly led to contemporary trousers, the sartorial mainstay of men's clothes in the Western world for the past two centuries. In 1799, upon coming of age, Beau Brummell inherited from his father a fortune of thirty thousand pounds, which he spent mostly on costume, gambling, and high living. In 1816 he suffered bankruptcy, the dandy's stereotyped fate; he fled his creditors to France, quietly dying in 1840, in a [[lunatic asylum]] in [[Caen]], aged 61.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson, Scott. ''Resting Places: The Burial Sites of More Than 14,000 Famous Persons'', 3d ed.: 2 (Kindle Locations 6018–6019). McFarland &amp; Company, Inc., Publishers. Kindle Edition.&lt;/ref&gt;

Men of more notable accomplishments than Beau Brummell also adopted the dandiacal pose: [[Lord Byron]] occasionally dressed the part, helping reintroduce the frilled, lace-cuffed and lace-collared &quot;[[poet shirt]]&quot;. In that spirit, he had his portrait painted in Albanian costume.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.bl.uk/collection-items/byron-portrait|title=Portrait of Lord Byron in Albanian Dress, 1813|website=The British Library|access-date=16 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another prominent dandy of the period was [[Alfred Guillaume Gabriel d'Orsay]], the Count d'Orsay, who had been friends with Byron and who moved in the highest social circles of London.

In 1836 [[Thomas Carlyle]] wrote: &lt;blockquote&gt;A Dandy is a clothes-wearing Man, a Man whose trade, office and existence consists in the wearing of Clothes. Every faculty of his soul, spirit, purse, and person is heroically consecrated to this one object, the wearing of Clothes wisely and well: so that the others dress to live, he lives to dress ... And now, for all this perennial [[Martyrdom]], and Poesy, and even [[Prophecy]], what is it that the Dandy asks in return? Solely, we may say, that you would recognise his existence; would admit him to be a living object; or even failing this, a visual object, or thing that will reflect rays of light...&lt;ref&gt;[[Thomas Carlyle]], &quot;The Dandiacal Body&quot;, in ''[[Sartor Resartus]]''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

By the mid-19th century, the English dandy, within the muted palette of male fashion, exhibited minute refinements—&quot;The quality of the fine woollen cloth, the slope of a pocket flap or coat revers, exactly the right colour for the gloves, the correct amount of shine on boots and shoes, and so on. It was an image of a well-dressed man who, while taking infinite pains about his appearance, affected indifference to it. This refined dandyism continued to be regarded as an essential strand of male Englishness.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Ribeira 2002:21.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Dandyism in France ==
[[File:Murat2.jpg|thumb|upright|left|[[Joachim Murat]], the French [[King of Naples]], was dubbed the &quot;Dandy King&quot; because of his highly groomed appearance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=William R. Denslow|title=10,000 Famous Freemasons from K to Z|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=dZbjtGC48-8C&amp;pg=PA247|date=September 2004|publisher=Kessinger Publishing|isbn=978-1-4179-7579-2|page=247}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
[[File:Coat MET 1999.105.2 F2.jpg|alt=A young man's French tailcoat from the 1790s|thumb|A young man's French tailcoat from the 1790s housed in [[Metropolitan Museum of Art|The Metropolitan Museum of Art]].]]
The beginnings of dandyism in France were bound to the politics of the [[French revolution]]; the initial stage of dandyism, the [[jeunesse dorée|gilded youth]], was a political statement of dressing in an aristocratic style in order to distinguish its members from the [[sans-culottes]].

During his heyday, [[Beau Brummell]]'s ''dictat'' on both fashion and etiquette reigned supreme. His habits of dress and fashion were much imitated, especially in France, where, in a curious development, they became the rage, especially in [[bohemianism|bohemian]] quarters. There, dandies sometimes were celebrated in revolutionary terms: self-created men of consciously designed personality, radically breaking with past traditions. With elaborate dress and idle, [[decadence|decadent]] styles of life, French bohemian dandies sought to convey [[contempt]] for and superiority to bourgeois society. In the latter 19th century, this fancy-dress bohemianism was a major influence on the [[Symbolism (arts)|Symbolist movement]] in French literature.&lt;ref&gt;Roman Meinhold, trans. John Irons. &quot;The Ideal-Typical Incarnation of Fashion: The Dandy as...&quot;, in ''Fashion Myths: A Cultural Critique''. Bielefeld, Germany: transcript, 2014. 111-25. 
books.google.com/books?id=1XWiBQAAQBAJ
{{ISBN|9783839424377}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Baudelaire]] was deeply interested in dandyism, and memorably wrote that a dandy aspirant must have &quot;no profession other than elegance... no other status, but that of cultivating the idea of beauty in their own persons... The dandy must aspire to be sublime without interruption; he must live and sleep before a mirror.&quot; Other French intellectuals also were interested in the dandies strolling the streets and [[boulevard]]s of Paris. [[Jules Amédée Barbey d'Aurevilly]] wrote ''[[On Dandyism and George Brummell]]'', an essay devoted, in great measure, to examining the career of Beau Brummell.&lt;ref name=Walden&gt;[[George Walden]], ''Who's a Dandy? – Dandyism and Beau Brummell'', Gibson Square, London, 2002. {{ISBN|1903933188}}. Reviewed by Frances Wilson in [https://www.theguardian.com/books/2002/oct/12/featuresreviews.guardianreview3 Uncommon People], ''The Guardian'', 12 October 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Later dandyism ==
{{more citations needed section|date=December 2010}}
[[File:Montesquiou, Robert de - Boldini.jpg|thumb|right|upright|[[Robert de Montesquiou]] (1855–1921) portrait by [[Giovanni Boldini]]]]
The literary dandy is a familiar figure in the writings, and sometimes the self-presentation, of [[Oscar Wilde]], [[Saki|H.H. Munro]] (Clovis and Reginald), [[P.G. Wodehouse]] ([[Bertie Wooster]]) and [[Ronald Firbank]], writers linked by their subversive air.

The poets [[Algernon Charles Swinburne]] and [[Oscar Wilde]], [[Walter Pater]], the American artist [[James McNeill Whistler]], the Spanish artist [[Salvador Dalí]], [[Joris-Karl Huysmans]], and [[Max Beerbohm]] were dandies of the [[Belle Époque]], as was [[Robert de Montesquiou]] — [[Marcel Proust]]'s inspiration for the Baron de Charlus. In Italy, [[Gabriele d'Annunzio]] and [[Carlo Bugatti]] exemplified the artistic bohemian dandyism of the [[fin de siecle]]. Wilde wrote that, &quot;One should either be a work of Art, or wear a work of Art.&quot;

At the end of the 19th century, American dandies were called [[dude]]s. [[Evander Berry Wall]] was nicknamed the &quot;King of the Dudes&quot;.

[[George Walden]], in the essay ''Who's a Dandy?'', identifies [[Noël Coward]], [[Andy Warhol]], and [[Quentin Crisp]] as modern dandies.&lt;ref name=Walden/&gt; The character [[Psmith]] in the novels of [[P. G. Wodehouse]] is considered a dandy, both physically and intellectually. Agatha Christie's Poirot is said to be a dandy.

The artist [[Sebastian Horsley]] described himself as a &quot;dandy in the underworld&quot; in his [[eponymous]] autobiography.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newstatesman.com/200610160054 Beautiful and damned], ''[[New Statesman]]'', 16 October 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

In Japan, dandyism has become a [[:Category:Japanese subcultures|fashion subculture]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine |last=Pask |first=Bruce |date=16 January 2009 |title=The New Japanese Dandyism |url=https://tmagazine.blogs.nytimes.com/2009/01/16/mens-fashion-the-new-japanese-dandyism/|location=New York City |work=The New York Times|access-date=23 March 2019 }}&lt;br/&gt;{{cite magazine |last=Burton |first=Tara Isabella |date=14 December 2016 |title=Identity and the Rise of Dandyism, From Congo to Kyoto |url=https://www.villagevoice.com/2016/12/14/identity-and-the-rise-of-dandyism-from-congo-to-kyoto/ |magazine=The Village Voice |location=New York City |access-date=23 March 2019 }}&lt;br/&gt;{{cite book|author=Toby Slade|title=Japanese Fashion: A Cultural History|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=zk5png7Z4cQC&amp;pg=PA84|date=1 November 2009|publisher=Berg|isbn=978-1-84788-748-1|pages=84–86}}&lt;/ref&gt; with historical roots dating back to the [[Edo period]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Kikuchi |first=Daisuke |date=2 June 2015 |title=The World of Edo Dandyism: From Swords to Inro |url=https://www.japantimes.co.jp/culture/2015/06/02/arts/openings-in-tokyo/world-edo-dandyism-swords-inro/#.XJaA9SJKhhE |work=The Japan Times |access-date=23 March 2019 }}&lt;br/&gt;{{cite book|author=Masafumi Monden|title=Japanese Fashion Cultures: Dress and Gender in Contemporary Japan|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=p6dOBAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA61|date=20 November 2014|publisher=Bloomsbury Publishing|isbn=978-1-4725-8673-5|page=61}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Spain during the early 19th century a curious phenomenon developed linked to the idea of dandyism. While in England and France individuals from the middle classes adopted aristocratic manners, the Spanish aristocracy adopted the fashions of the lower classes, called [[majos]]. They were characterized by their elaborate outfits and sense of style as opposed to the modern Frenchified &quot;[[afrancesados]]&quot;, as for their cheeky arrogant attitude.
Some famous dandies in later times were amongst other the [[Duke of Osuna]], Mariano Tellez-Girón, artist [[Salvador Dalí]] and poet [[Luis Cernuda|Luís Cernuda]].

== Later thought ==
[[Albert Camus]] said in ''[[The Rebel (book)|L'Homme révolté]]'' (1951) that: &lt;blockquote&gt;The dandy creates his own unity by aesthetic means. But it is an aesthetic of negation. &quot;To live and die before a mirror&quot;: that according to Baudelaire, was the dandy's slogan. It is indeed a coherent slogan. The dandy is, by occupation, always in opposition. He can only exist by defiance. Up to now, man derived his coherence from the Creator. But from the moment that he consecrates his rupture from Him, he finds himself delivered over to the fleeting moment, to the passing days, and to wasted sensibility. Therefore he must take himself in hand. The dandy rallies his forces and creates a unity for himself by the very violence of his refusal. Profligate, like all people without a rule of life, he is only coherent as an actor. But an actor implies a public; the dandy can only play a part by setting himself up in opposition. He can only be sure of his own existence by finding it in the expression of others' faces. Other people are his mirror. A mirror that quickly becomes clouded, it's true, since human capacity for attention is limited. It must be ceaselessly stimulated, spurred on by provocation. The dandy, therefore, is always compelled to astonish. Singularity is his vocation, excess his way to perfection. Perpetually incomplete, always on the fringe of things, he compels others to create him, while denying their values. He plays at life because he is unable to live it.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Albert|last=Camus|authorlink=Albert Camus|title=[[The Rebel (book)|The Rebel: An Essay on Man in Revolt]]|date=2012|publisher=Knopf Doubleday Publishing Group|isbn=9780307827838|page=51|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=t_3yQrhdxwUC&amp;pg=PA51|accessdate=11 October 2014|chapter=II Metaphysical Rebellion}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

[[Jean Baudrillard]] said that dandyism is &quot;an aesthetic form of nihilism&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.egs.edu/faculty/jean-baudrillard/articles/simulacra-and-simulations-xviii-on-nihilism/ |title=Jean Baudrillard – Simulacra and Simulations – XVIII. On Nihilism |publisher=Egs.edu |accessdate=16 February 2013 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130419220351/http://www.egs.edu/faculty/jean-baudrillard/articles/simulacra-and-simulations-xviii-on-nihilism/ |archivedate=19 April 2013  }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!--PLEASE RESPECT ALPHABETICAL ORDER--&gt;

== Quaintrelle ==
[[File:Dandizette.jpg|thumb|upright|An 1819 Dandizette]]
{{More citations needed section|date=May 2008}}
The female counterpart is a quaintrelle, a woman who emphasizes a life of passion expressed through personal style, leisurely pastimes, charm, and cultivation of life's pleasures.

In the 12th century, ''cointerrels'' (male) and ''cointrelles'' (female) emerged, based upon ''coint'',&lt;ref&gt;Old English Dictionary&lt;/ref&gt; a word applied to things skillfully made, later indicating a person of beautiful dress and refined speech.&lt;ref name=&quot;Brooks&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=eQncCwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA57|title=Popular Culture: Global Intercultural Perspectives|last=Brooks|first=Ann|date=15 July 2014|publisher=Macmillan International Higher Education|isbn=9781137426727|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; By the 18th century, ''coint'' became ''quaint'',&lt;ref&gt;Dictionary of Early English&lt;/ref&gt; indicating elegant speech and beauty.  Middle English dictionaries note ''quaintrelle'' as a beautifully dressed woman (or overly dressed), but do not include the favorable personality elements of grace and charm.  The notion of a quaintrelle sharing the major philosophical components of refinement with dandies is a modern development that returns quaintrelles to their historic roots.

Female dandies did overlap with male dandies for a brief period during the early 19th century when ''dandy'' had a derisive definition of &quot;fop&quot; or &quot;over-the-top fellow&quot;; the female equivalents were ''dandyess'' or ''dandizette''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Brooks&quot;/&gt; Charles Dickens, in [https://books.google.com/books?id=VvFIAAAAcAAJ&amp;dq=charles%20dickens%20dandies%20and%20dandizettes&amp;pg=PA189#v=onepage&amp;q=dandies%20and%20dandizettes&amp;f=false ''All the Year Around'' (1869)] comments, &quot;The dandies and dandizettes of 1819–20 must have been a strange race. &quot;Dandizette&quot; was a term applied to the feminine devotees to dress, and their absurdities were fully equal to those of the dandies.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=VvFIAAAAcAAJ&amp;pg=PA189|title=All the Year Round: A Weekly Journal|date=1869|publisher=Chapman &amp; Hall|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1819, [https://books.google.com/books?id=8HopAQAAIAAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false ''Charms of Dandyism'' in three volumes], was published by Olivia Moreland, Chief of the Female Dandies; most likely one of many pseudonyms used by Thomas Ashe. Olivia Moreland may have existed, as Ashe did write several novels about living persons. Throughout the novel, dandyism is associated with &quot;living in style&quot;.  Later, as the word ''dandy'' evolved to denote refinement, it became applied solely to men.  ''Popular Culture and Performance in the Victorian City'' (2003) notes this evolution in the latter 19th century: &quot;...or ''dandizette'', although the term was increasingly reserved for men.&quot;

== See also ==
* ''[[Dandy (song)|Dandy]] and [[Dedicated Follower of Fashion]],'' songs by [[The Kinks]] that parody modern (1960s) dandyism.
* [[Adonis]]
* [[Bishōnen]]
* [[Dude]]
* [[Effeminacy]]
* [[Flâneur]]
* [[Fop]]
* [[Gentleman]]
* [[Hipster (contemporary subculture)]]
* [[Incroyables and Merveilleuses]]
* [[La Sape]]
* [[Macaroni (fashion)|Macaroni]]
* [[Metrosexual]]
* [[Narcissus (mythology)]]
* [[Preppy]]
* [[Sexual suggestiveness|Risqué]]
* [[Swenkas]]

== References ==
{{Reflist|30em}}

== Further reading ==
* [[Jules Barbey d'Aurevilly|Barbey d'Aurevilly, Jules]].  ''[[On Dandyism and George Brummell|Of Dandyism and of George Brummell]]''.  Translated by Douglas Ainslie.  New York: PAJ Publications, 1988.
* Carassus, Émile. ''Le Mythe du Dandy'' 1971.
* Carlyle, Thomas.  ''Sartor Resartus''.  In ''A Carlyle Reader: Selections from the Writings of Thomas Carlyle''.  Edited by G.B. Tennyson.  London: Cambridge University Press, 1984.
* Jesse, Captain William.  ''The Life of Beau Brummell''.  London: The Navarre Society Limited, 1927.
* [[Edward Bulwer-Lytton|Lytton, Edward Bulwer, Lord Lytton]].  ''Pelham or the Adventures of a Gentleman''.  Edited by [[Jerome McGann]].  Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1972.
* Moers, Ellen.  ''The Dandy: Brummell to Beerbohm''.  London: Secker and Warburg, 1960.
* Murray, Venetia.  ''An Elegant Madness: High Society in Regency England''.  New York: Viking, 1998.
* Nicolay, Claire.  ''Origins and Reception of Regency Dandyism: Brummell to Baudelaire''. PhD diss., Loyola U of Chicago, 1998.
* Prevost, John C., ''Le Dandysme en France (1817–1839)'' (Geneva and Paris) 1957.
* [[Nigel Rodgers]]  ''The Dandy: Peacock or Enigma?'' (London) 2012
* Stanton, Domna. ''The Aristocrat as Art'' 1980.
* [[Grace Wharton|Wharton, Grace]] and Philip.  ''Wits and Beaux of Society''.  New York: Harper and Brothers, 1861.

== External links ==
{{wikiquote|Dandy}}
{{Commons category|Dandies}}
*{{cite EB1911|wstitle=Dandy |volume=7 |short=x}}
* [http://www.pierredebonneuil.fr La Loge d'Apollon]
* [http://www.mtholyoke.edu/courses/rschwart/hist255-s01/boheme/dandyism.html &quot;Bohemianism and Counter-Culture&quot;: The Dandy]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20100123093252/http://www.noveporte.it/dandy/ Il Dandy (in Italian)]
* [http://www.dandyism.net Dandyism.net]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20050119043746/http://homepages.ihug.co.nz/~awoodley/regency/dandy.html &quot;The Dandy&quot;]
* Walter Thornbury, [http://www.dandysme.eu Dandysme.eu  &quot;London Parks: IV. Hyde Park&quot;],  ''[[Belgravia: A London Magazine]]'' 1868

[[Category:1790s fashion]]
[[Category:19th-century fashion]]
[[Category:Androgyny]]
[[Category:History of clothing (Western fashion)]]
[[Category:Human appearance]]
[[Category:Middle class culture]]
[[Category:Narcissism]]
[[Category:Terms for men]]
[[Category:Upper class culture]]
[[Category:Art Nouveau]]
[[Category:Male beauty]]
[[Category:Lifestyles]]
[[Category:18th-century neologisms]]</text>
      <sha1>iscxofledz72o2vj7yfk9i7mx4jblco</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
