  <page>
    <title>Chinese philosophy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5822</id>
    <revision>
      <id>938072891</id>
      <parentid>937666445</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-28T23:38:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Danielt998</username>
        <id>7730667</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>clean up, replaced: Of  →  of , （ → (, ） → )</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}
              
{{Infobox Chinese 
|pic     = yin-yang-and-bagua-near-nanning.jpg
|piccap  = [[Yin and Yang]] symbol with the [[bagua]] symbols paved in a clearing outside of Nanning City, [[Guangxi]] province, [[China]].
|picsize = 300px
|t       = 中國哲學
|s       = 中国哲学
|p       = Zhōngguó zhéxué
|w       = Chung-kuo che-hsüeh
|gr      = Jonggwo jershyue
|j       = Zung&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;-gwok&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; zit&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;-hok&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;
|y      = Jūng-gwok jit-hohk
|h       = Zung&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;-get&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt; ziet&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;-hok&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;
|wuu  = Tson-kueʔ tseʔ-ghoʔ
|poj   = Tiong-kok tiat-ha̍k
}}
{{Asian philosophy sidebar}}

'''Chinese philosophy''' originates in the [[Spring and Autumn period]] and [[Warring States period]], during a period known as the &quot;[[Hundred Schools of Thought]]&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;pe&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last= Ebrey |first=Patricia|year=2010 | page= 42|title=The Cambridge Illustrated History of China|publisher=Cambridge University Press}}&lt;/ref&gt; which was characterized by significant intellectual and cultural developments.&lt;ref name=&quot;pe&quot;/&gt; Although much of Chinese philosophy begins in the Warring States period, elements of Chinese philosophy have existed for several thousand years; some can be found in the [[I Ching|Yi Jing]] (the ''Book of Changes''), an ancient compendium of [[divination]], which dates back to at least 672 BCE.&lt;ref&gt;page 60, Great Thinkers of the Eastern World, edited Ian McGreal Harper Collins 1995,  {{ISBN|0-06-270085-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was during the Warring States era that what [[Sima Tan]] termed the major philosophical schools of China: [[Confucianism]], [[Legalism (Chinese philosophy)|Legalism]], and [[Taoism]], arose,  along with philosophies that later fell into obscurity, like [[Agriculturalism]], [[Mohism]], [[School of Naturalists|Chinese Naturalism]], and the [[School of Names|Logicians]].

==Early beliefs==
{{Unreferenced section|date=December 2015}}

Early [[Shang dynasty]] thought was based upon cycles. This notion stems from what the people of the Shang Dynasty could observe around them: day and night cycled, the seasons progressed again and again, and even the moon waxed and waned until it waxed again.  Thus, this notion, which remained relevant throughout [[Chinese history]], reflects the order of nature.  In juxtaposition, it also marks a fundamental distinction from [[western philosophy]], in which the dominant view of time is a linear progression. During the Shang, [[destiny|fate]] could be manipulated by great deities, commonly translated as gods.{{Vague|date=December 2015}} [[Ancestor worship]] was present and universally recognized. There was also human and animal sacrifice.

When the Shang were overthrown by the [[Zhou Dynasty|Zhou]], a new political, religious and philosophical concept was introduced called the &quot;[[Mandate of Heaven]]&quot;. This mandate was said to be taken when rulers became unworthy of their position and provided a shrewd justification for Zhou rule. During this period, archaeological evidence points to an increase in literacy and a partial shift away from the faith placed in [[Shangdi]] (the Supreme Being in [[traditional Chinese religion]]), with ancestor worship becoming commonplace and a more worldly orientation coming to the fore.

==Overview==
Confucianism developed during the [[Spring and Autumn period]] from the teachings of the Chinese philosopher [[Confucius]] (551–479 BCE), who considered himself a retransmitter of Zhou values. His philosophy concerns the fields of ethics and politics, emphasizing personal and governmental morality, correctness of social relationships, justice, traditionalism, and sincerity. The Analects stress the importance of ritual, but also the importance of 'ren', which loosely translates as 'human-heartedness',&lt;ref&gt;Yuli Liu, 'Confucius', in Essentials of Philosophy and Ethics, Hodder Arnold 2006 {{ISBN|0-340-90028-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; Confucianism, along with [[Legalism (Chinese philosophy)|Legalism]], is responsible for creating the world’s first [[meritocracy]], which holds that one's status should be determined by education and character rather than [[ancestry]], [[wealth]], or [[friendship]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Confucius&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Kung Fu Tze (Confucius)|editor=D. C. Lau (Translator)|title=The Analects|publisher=Penguin Classics|year=1998|ISBN=0-14-044348-7|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/analectslunyu00conf}}&lt;/ref&gt; Confucianism was and continues to be a major influence in Chinese culture, the state of [[History of China|China]] and the surrounding areas of [[East Asia]].

Before the Han dynasty the largest rivals to Confucianism were [[Chinese Legalism]], and Mohism. Confucianism largely became the dominant philosophical school of China during the early [[Han dynasty]] following the replacement of its contemporary, the more Taoistic [[Huang-Lao]].&lt;ref&gt;Civilizations of the World: The Human Adventure : To the late 1600s, Richard Greaves p176&lt;/ref&gt; Legalism as a coherent philosophy disappeared largely due to its relationship with the unpopular authoritarian rule of [[Qin Shi Huang]], however, many of its ideas and institutions would continue to influence Chinese philosophy until the end of Imperial rule during the [[Xinhai Revolution]].

Mohism, though initially popular due to its emphasis on brotherly love versus harsh Qin Legalism, fell out of favour during the [[Han Dynasty]] due to the efforts of Confucians in establishing their views as political orthodoxy.  The [[Six Dynasties]] era saw the rise of the [[Xuanxue]] philosophical school and the maturation of Chinese [[Buddhism]], which had entered China from India during the Late Han Dynasties. By the time of the [[Tang dynasty]] five-hundred years after Buddhism's arrival into China, it had transformed into a thoroughly Chinese religious philosophy dominated by the school of [[Zen|Zen Buddhism]]. [[Neo-Confucianism]] became highly popular during the [[Song dynasty]] and [[Ming Dynasty]] due in large part to the eventual combination of Confucian and Zen Philosophy.

During the 19th and 20th centuries, Chinese philosophy integrated concepts from [[Western philosophy]]. Anti-[[Qing dynasty]] revolutionaries, involved in the [[Xinhai Revolution]], saw Western philosophy as an alternative to traditional philosophical schools; students in the [[May Fourth Movement]] called for completely abolishing the old imperial institutions and practices of China.  During this era, Chinese scholars attempted to incorporate Western philosophical ideologies such as [[democracy]], [[Marxism]], [[socialism]], [[liberalism]], [[republicanism]], [[anarchism]] and [[nationalism]] into Chinese philosophy. The most notable examples are [[Sun Yat-Sen]]'s [[Three Principles of the People]] ideology and [[Mao Zedong]]'s [[Maoism]], a variant of [[Marxism–Leninism]].&lt;ref&gt;'Maoism', in Essentials of Philosophy and Ethics, Hodder Arnold 2006 {{ISBN|0-340-90028-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In the modern [[People's Republic of China]], the official ideology is [[Deng Xiaoping]]'s &quot;[[Socialist market economy|market economy socialism]]&quot;.

Although the People's Republic of China has been historically hostile to the philosophy of ancient China, the influences of past are still deeply ingrained in the [[Chinese culture]]. In the post-[[Chinese economic reform]] era, modern Chinese philosophy has reappeared in forms such as the ''[[New Confucianism]]''. As in [[Japan]], philosophy in China has become a melting pot of ideas. It accepts new concepts, while attempting also to accord old beliefs their due. Chinese philosophy still carries profound influence amongst the people of [[East Asia]], and even [[Southeast Asia]].

==Ancient philosophy==

=== Spring and Autumn period ===

{{Main|Hundred Schools of Thought}}
Around 500 BCE, after the Zhou state weakened and China moved into the [[Spring and Autumn period]], the classic period of Chinese philosophy began. This is known as the [[Hundred Schools of Thought]] ({{lang|zh|諸子百家}}; ''zhūzǐ bǎijiā''; &quot;various scholars, hundred schools&quot;). This period is considered the golden age of Chinese philosophy. Of the many schools founded at this time and during the subsequent [[Warring States period]], the four most influential ones were [[Confucianism]], [[Taoism|Daoism]] (often spelled &quot;Taoism&quot;), [[Mohism]] and [[Legalism (philosophy)|Legalism]].

==== Confucianism ====

[[Image:Confucius Statue at the Confucius Temple.jpg|thumb|right|200px|Kong Fuzi ([[Latin Language|Latin]]: [[Confucius]])]]
{{Main|Confucianism}}
Confucianism is a philosophical school developed from the teachings of Confucius collected and written by his disciples after his death in ''[[The Analects]]'', and in the [[Warring States period]], [[Mencius]] in ''[[The Mencius]]'' and [[Xun Kuang|Xunzi]] in ''[[Xunzi (book)|The Xunzi]]''. It is a system of [[morality|moral]], [[social philosophy|social]], [[politics|political]], and [[religion|religious]] thought that has had tremendous influence on Chinese history, thought, and culture down to the 20th century. Some Westerners have considered it to have been the &quot;[[state religion]]&quot; of [[Imperial era of Chinese history|imperial China]] because of its lasting influence on Asian culture. Its influence also spread to Korea, Japan, Vietnam and many other Asian countries.

Confucianism reached its peak of influence during the [[Tang dynasty|Tang]] and [[Song dynasty|Song]] Dynasties under a rebranded Confucianism called [[Neo-Confucianism]]. Confucius expanded on the already present ideas of Chinese religion and culture to reflect the time period and environment of political chaos during the [[Warring States period]]. Because Confucius embedded the Chinese culture so heavily into his philosophy it was able to resonate with the people of China. This high approval of Confucianism can be seen through the reverence of Confucius in modern-day China.

The major Confucian concepts include ''[[Ren (Confucianism)|rén]]'' {{lang|zh|仁}} (humanity or humaneness), ''zhèngmíng'' {{lang|zh|正名}} ([[rectification of names]]; e.g. a ruler who rules unjustly is no longer a ruler and may be dethroned), ''zhōng'' {{lang|zh|忠}} (loyalty), ''xiào'' {{lang|zh|孝}} ([[filial piety]]), and ''[[Li (Confucian)|li]]'' {{lang|zh|禮}} (ritual). Confucius taught both positive and negative versions of the [[Ethic of reciprocity|Golden Rule]]. The concepts [[Yin and Yang]] represent two opposing forces that are permanently in conflict with each other, leading to perpetual contradiction and change. The Confucian idea of &quot;Rid of the two ends, take the middle&quot; is a Chinese equivalent of [[Hegel]]'s idea of &quot;thesis, antithesis, and synthesis&quot;, which is a way of reconciling opposites, arriving at some middle ground combining the best of both. Confucius heavily emphasized the idea of microcosms in society (subunits of family and community) success's were the foundations for a successful state or country. Confucius believed in the use of education to further knowledge the people in ethics, societal behavior, and reverence in other humans. With the combination of education, successful family, and his ethical teachings he believed he could govern a well established society in China.

==== Taoism ====

[[Image:SFEC BritMus Asia 021.JPG|thumb|right|200px|Chinese [[ceramic glaze|glaze]]d [[stoneware]] statue of a [[Daoist]] deity, from the [[Ming Dynasty]], 16th century.]]
{{Main|Taoist philosophy}}
[[File:BatQuaiDo_2.svg|thumb|left|200px|[[Bagua]]: Modern Taijitu with I Ching trigrams]]

Taoism arose as a philosophy and later also developed into a religion based on the texts the ''[[Tao Te Ching]]'' (''Dào Dé Jīng''; ascribed to [[Laozi]]) and the ''[[Zhuangzi (book)|Zhuangzi]]'' (partly ascribed to [[Zhuang Zhou|Zhuangzi]]). The character ''[[Tao|Dao]]'' {{lang|zh|道}} (''Dao'') literally means 'path' or 'way'. However, in Taoism it refers more often to a meta-physical force that encompasses the entire universe but which cannot be described nor felt. All major Chinese philosophical schools have investigated the correct ''Way'' to go about a moral life, but in Taoism it takes on the most abstract meanings, leading this school to be named after it. It advocated nonaction (''[[wu wei]]''), the strength of softness, spontaneity, and relativism. Although it serves as a rival to Confucianism, a school of active morality, this rivalry is compromised and given perspective by the idiom &quot;practise Confucianism on the outside, Taoism on the inside.&quot;

Most of Taoism's focus is on the notion that human attempts to make the world better actually make the world worse. Therefore, it is better to strive for harmony, minimising potentially harmful interference with nature or in human affairs.&lt;ref&gt;A source book in Chinese philosophy, Wing-tsit Chan, p137&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Warring States period ===

==== Legalism ====
{{Main|Legalism (Chinese philosophy)}}
Philosopher [[Han Fei]] synthesized together earlier the methods of his predecessors, which famous historian [[Sima Tan]] posthumously termed Legalism. With an essential principle like &quot;when the epoch changed, the ways changed&quot;, late pre-[[Han Dynasty]] reformers emphasized rule by law.

In Han Fei's philosophy, a ruler should govern his subjects by the following trinity:
#Fa ({{lang|zh|法}} fǎ): law or principle.
#Shu ({{lang|zh|術}} shù): method, tactic, art, or statecraft.
#Shi ({{lang|zh|勢}} shì): legitimacy, power, or charisma.

What has been termed by some as the intrastate Realpolitik of the Warring States period was highly progressive, and extremely critical of the [[Confucianism|Confucian]] and [[Mohism|Mohist]] schools. But that of the [[Qin dynasty]] would be blamed for creating a [[totalitarian]] society, thereby experiencing decline. Its main motto is: &quot;Set clear strict laws, or deliver harsh punishment&quot;. In Han Fei's philosophy the ruler possessed authority regarding reward and penalty, enacted through law. Shang Yang and Han Fei promoted absolute adherence to the law, regardless of the circumstances or the person. Ministers were only to be rewarded if their words were accurate to the results of their proposals. Legalism, in accordance with Shang Yang's interpretation, could encourage the state to be a [[militarism|militaristic]] [[autarky]].

====Naturalists====

{{Main|School of Naturalists}}
The [[School of Naturalists]] or the School of Yin-yang ({{zh|t=陰陽家|s=阴阳家|p=Yīnyángjiā|w=Yin-yang-chia|l=School of Yin-Yang}}) was a [[Warring States]] era philosophy that synthesized the concepts of [[yin-yang]] and the [[Wu Xing]];  [[Zou Yan]] is considered the founder of this school.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopedia|url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/607826/Zou-Yan|title=Zou Yan|encyclopedia=Encyclopædia Britannica|accessdate=1 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; His theory attempted to explain the universe in terms of basic forces in nature: the complementary agents of yin (dark, cold, female, negative) and yang (light, hot, male, positive) and the Five Elements or Five Phases (water, fire, wood, metal, and earth). In its early days, this theory was most strongly associated with the states of [[Yan (state)|Yan]] and [[Qi (state)|Qi]]. In later periods, these epistemological theories came to hold significance in both philosophy and popular belief.  This school was absorbed into Taoism's alchemic and magical dimensions as well as into the Chinese medical framework. The earliest surviving recordings of this are in the [[Mawangdui Silk Texts|Ma Wang Dui]] texts and [[Huang Di Nei Jing]].

==== Mohism ====

{{Main|Mohism}}
Mohism (Moism), founded by [[Mozi]] ({{lang|zh|墨子}}), promotes [[Mohism|universal love]] with the aim of mutual benefit. Everyone must love each other equally and impartially to avoid conflict and war. Mozi was strongly against Confucian ritual, instead emphasizing [[pragmatism|pragmatic]] survival through farming, [[fortification]], and [[Public administration|statecraft]]. Tradition is inconsistent, and human beings need an extra-traditional guide to identify which traditions are acceptable. The moral guide must then promote and encourage social behaviors that maximize general benefit. As motivation for his theory, Mozi brought in the ''Will of Heaven'', but rather than being religious his philosophy parallels [[utilitarianism]].

==== Logicians ====

{{Main|School of Names}}
The logicians (School of Names) were concerned with logic, paradoxes, names and actuality (similar to Confucian rectification of names). The logician [[Hui Shi]] was a friendly rival to [[Zhuang Zhou|Zhuangzi]], arguing against Taoism in a light-hearted and humorous manner. Another logician, [[Gongsun Long]], originated the famous [[When a White Horse is Not a Horse]] dialogue. This school did not thrive because the Chinese regarded [[sophistry]] and [[dialectic]] as impractical.{{Citation needed|date=August 2012}}

==== Agriculturalists ====

{{main|Agriculturalism}}
[[Agriculturalism]] was an early [[Agrarianism|agrarian]] social and political philosophy that advocated peasant [[utopian]] [[communalism]] and [[egalitarianism]].&lt;ref name=&quot;wp&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last= Deutsch |first=Eliot |author2=Ronald Bontekoei|year=1999 | page= 183|title=A companion to world philosophies|publisher=Wiley Blackwell}}&lt;/ref&gt; The philosophy is founded on the notion that human society originates with the development of [[agriculture]], and societies are based upon &quot;people's natural prospensity to farm.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;js&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last= Sellmann |first=James Daryl|year=2010 | page= 76|title=Timing and rulership in Master Lü's Spring and Autumn annals|publisher=SUNY Press}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Agriculturalists believed that the ideal government, modeled after the semi-mythical governance of [[Shennong]], is led by a benevolent king, one who works alongside the people in tilling the fields. The Agriculturalist king is not paid by the government through its treasuries; his livelihood is derived from the profits he earns working in the fields, not his leadership.&lt;ref name=&quot;dw&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last= Denecke|first=Wiebke|year=2011 | page= 38|title=The Dynamics of Masters Literature: Early Chinese Thought from Confucius to Han Feizi|publisher=Harvard University Press}}&lt;/ref&gt; Unlike the Confucians, the Agriculturalists did not believe in the [[division of labour]], arguing instead that the economic policies of a country need to be based upon an egalitarian [[self sufficiency]]. The Agriculturalists supported the [[price fixing|fixing of prices]], in which all similar goods, regardless of differences in quality and demand, are set at exactly the same, unchanging price.&lt;ref name=&quot;dw&quot;/&gt;

==Early Imperial era philosophy==

===History===

==== Qin and Han Dynasties ====
{{multiple image
| align = right
| image1 = Confucius, fresco from a Western Han tomb of Dongping County, Shandong province, China.jpg
| width1 = 200
| alt1 = 
| caption1 = 
| image2 = Confucius and Laozi, fresco from a Western Han tomb of Dongping County, Shandong province, China.jpg
| width2 = 220
| alt2 = 
| caption2 = 
| footer = A [[Western Han]] (202 BC - 9 AD) [[fresco]] depicting [[Confucius]] (and [[Laozi]]), from a tomb of [[Dongping County]], [[Shandong province]], China
}}
The short founder [[Qin dynasty]], where Legalism was the official philosophy, [[To burn the classics and to bury the scholars|quashed Mohist and Confucianist schools]]. Legalism remained influential during the early [[Han Dynasty]] under the Taoist-Realist ideology [[Huang-Lao]] until [[Emperor Wu of Han]] adopted Confucianism as official doctrine. Confucianism and Taoism became the determining forces of Chinese thought until the introduction of [[Buddhism]].

Confucianism was particularly strong during the Han dynasty, whose greatest thinker was [[Dong Zhongshu]], who integrated Confucianism with the thoughts of the Zhongshu School and the theory of the Five Elements. He also was a promoter of the New Text school, which considered Confucius as a divine figure and a spiritual ruler of China, who foresaw and started the evolution of the world towards the Universal Peace. In contrast, there was an Old Text school that advocated the use of Confucian works written in ancient language (from this comes the denomination ''Old Text'') that were so much more reliable. In particular, they refuted the assumption of Confucius as a godlike figure and considered him as the greatest sage, but simply a human and mortal

==== Six Dynasties ====
The 3rd and 4th centuries saw the rise of the ''[[Xuanxue]]'' (mysterious learning), also called ''Neo-Taoism''. The most important philosophers of this movement were [[Wang Bi]], [[Xiang Xiu]] and [[Guo Xiang]]. The main question of this school was whether Being came before Not-Being (in Chinese, ''ming'' and ''wuming''). A peculiar feature of these Taoist thinkers, like the [[Seven Sages of the Bamboo Grove]], was the concept of ''[[feng liu]]'' (lit. wind and flow), a sort of romantic spirit which encouraged following the natural and instinctive impulse.

[[Buddhism]] arrived in China around the 1st century AD, but it was not until the [[Southern and Northern Dynasties|Northern and Southern]], [[Sui Dynasty|Sui]] and [[Tang dynasty|Tang]] dynasties that it gained considerable influence and acknowledgement. At the beginning, it was considered a sort of Taoist sect. [[Mahayana Buddhism]] was far more successful in China than its rival [[Hinayana]], and both Indian schools and local Chinese sects arose from the 5th century. Two chiefly important monk philosophers were [[Sengzhao]] and [[Daosheng]]. But probably the most influential and original of these schools was the [[Chan Buddhism|Chan]] sect, which had an even stronger impact in Japan as the [[Zen]] sect.

In the mid-Tang Buddhism reached its peak, and reportedly there were 4,600 monasteries, 40,000 hermitages and 260,500 monks and nuns. The power of the Buddhist clergy was so great and the wealth of the monasteries so impressive, that it instigated criticism from Confucian scholars, who considered Buddhism as a foreign religion. In 845 Emperor [[Emperor Wuzong of Tang|Wuzong]] ordered the [[Great Anti-Buddhist Persecution]], confiscating the riches and returning monks and nuns to lay life. From then on, Buddhism lost much of its influence.

===Schools of thought===

====Xuanxue====
{{Main|Xuanxue}}
[[Xuanxue]] was a philosophical school that combined elements of [[Confucianism]] and [[Taoism]] to reinterpret the [[I Ching]]'','' [[Tao Te Ching]]'','' and ''[[Zhuangzi (book)|Zhuangzi]].'' The most important philosophers of this movement were [[Wang Bi]], [[Xiang Xiu]] and [[Guo Xiang]]. The main question of this school was whether Being came before Not-Being (in Chinese, ''ming'' and ''wuming''). A peculiar feature of these Taoist thinkers, like the [[Seven Sages of the Bamboo Grove]], was the concept of ''[[feng liu]]'' (lit. wind and flow), a sort of romantic spirit which encouraged following the natural and instinctive impulse.

==== Chan ====
[[Image:Zhang Shengwen. L'enseignement de Bouddha Sakyamuni.jpg|thumb|right|300px|''The [[Gautama Buddha|Sakyamuni Buddha]]'', by artist Zhang Shengwen, 1173-1176 CE, [[Song dynasty]].]]
{{Main|Zen|Buddhism in China}}
[[Buddhism]] is a [[religion]], a [[practical philosophy]], and arguably a [[psychology]], focusing on the teachings of [[Gautama Buddha]], who lived on the [[Indian subcontinent]] most likely from the mid-6th to the early 5th century BCE. When used in a generic sense, a [[Buddhahood|Buddha]] is generally considered to be someone who discovers the true [[Reality in Buddhism|nature of reality]].

Buddhism until the 4th century A.D had little impact on China but in the 4th century its teachings hybridized with those of Taoism.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eichman2000&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Shawn Eichman|title=Taoism and the Arts of China|url=https://archive.org/details/bub_gb_5ame4Rl1RXMC|year=2000|publisher=University of California Press|isbn=978-0-520-22785-9|pages=[https://archive.org/details/bub_gb_5ame4Rl1RXMC/page/n192 45]–}}&lt;/ref&gt; Buddhism brought to China the idea of many hells, where sinners went, but the deceased sinners souls could be saved by pious acts.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eichman2000&quot;/&gt; Since Chinese traditional thought focused more on ethics rather than [[metaphysics]], the merging of Buddhist and Taoist concepts developed several schools distinct from the originating Indian schools.  The most prominent examples with philosophical merit are [[Sanlun]], [[Tiantai]], [[Huayan school|Huayan]], and [[Chán]] (a.k.a. Zen). They investigate [[higher consciousness|consciousness]], levels of truth, whether reality is ultimately empty, and how [[Enlightenment in Buddhism|enlightenment]] is to be achieved. Buddhism has a spiritual aspect that compliments the action of [[Neo-Confucianism]], with prominent Neo-Confucians advocating certain forms of meditation.

==Mid to Late Imperial era philosophy==

=== History ===
[[Neo-Confucianism]] was a revived version of old Confucian principles that appeared around the [[Song dynasty]], with [[Buddhist]], [[Taoist]], and [[Legalism (Chinese philosophy)|Legalist]] features. The first philosophers, such as [[Shao Yong]], [[Zhou Dunyi]] and [[Chang Zai]], were [[cosmologists]] and worked on the [[I Ching|Yi Jing]]. The Cheng brothers, [[Cheng Yi (philosopher)|Cheng Yi]] and [[Cheng Hao]], are considered the founders of the two main schools of thought of Neo-Confucianism: the [[School of Principle]] the first, the [[School of Mind]] the latter. The School of Principle gained supremacy during the Song dynasty with the philosophical system elaborated by [[Zhu Xi]], which became mainstream and officially adopted by the government for the Imperial examinations under the [[Yuan dynasty]]. [[The School of Mind]] was developed by [[Lu Jiuyuan]], Zhu Xi's main rival, but was soon forgotten. Only during the [[Ming dynasty]] was the School of Mind revived by [[Wang Yangming|Wang Shouren]], whose influence is equal to that of Zhu Xi. This school was particularly important in Japan.

During the [[Qing dynasty]] many philosophers objected against Neo-Confucianism and there was a return to the Han Dynasty Confucianism, and also the reprise of the controversy between Old Text and New Text. In this period also started the penetration of Western culture, but most Chinese thought that the Westerners were maybe more advanced in technology and warfare, but that China had primacy in moral and intellectual fields.

===Schools of thought===

==== Neo-Confucianism ====
{{Main|Neo-Confucianism}}
[[File:Zhu-xi1.gif|thumb|left|[[Zhu Xi]] leading figure in Neo-Confucianism]]
[[File:Wang-yang-ming.jpg|thumb|right|[[Wang Yangming]] also an important figure in Neo-Confucianism]]
Despite Confucianism losing popularity to Taoism and Buddhism, [[Neo-Confucianism]] combined those ideas into a more [[metaphysics|metaphysical]] framework. Its concepts include ''[[Li (Neo-Confucianism)|li]]'' (principle, akin to [[Plato]]'s [[Theory of forms|forms]]), ''[[qi]]'' (vital or material force), ''[[Taiji (philosophy)|taiji]]'' (the Great Ultimate), and ''[[Xin (concept)|xin]]'' (mind). [[Song dynasty]] philosopher [[Zhou Dunyi]] (1017–1073) is seen commonly seen as the first true &quot;pioneer&quot; of Neo-Confucianism, using Daoist metaphysics as a framework for his ethical philosophy.&lt;ref name=&quot;CSB&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Chan|2002|p=460}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Neo-Confucianism developed both as a renaissance of traditional Confucian ideas, and as a reaction to the ideas of Buddhism and religious Daoism. Although the Neo-Confucianists denounced Buddhist metaphysics, Neo-Confucianism did borrow Daoist and Buddhist terminology and concepts.&lt;ref name=&quot;huang5&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Huang|first=Siu-chi|title=Essentials of Neo-Confucianism: Eight Major Philosophers of the Song and Ming Periods|location=Westport|publisher=[[Greenwood Press]]|year=1999|page=5}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Neo-Confucianist philosophers like [[Zhu Xi]] and [[Wang Yangming]] are seen as the most important figures of Neo-Confucianism.

== Modern era ==
{{see also|Chinese nationalism|Maoism|Chinese Marxist Philosophy}}
{{POV section|date=June 2017}}
During the Industrial and Modern Ages, Chinese philosophy had also begun to integrate concepts of Western philosophy, as steps toward modernization.  Notably, Chinese philosophy never developed the concept of [[human rights]], so that classical Chinese lacked words for them. In 1864, [[William Alexander Parsons Martin|W.A.P. Martin]] had to invent the word ''quanli''({{zh|s=权利|t=權利}}) to translate the Western concept of &quot;rights&quot; in the process of translating [[Henry Wheaton]]'s ''[[Elements of International Law]]'' into classical Chinese.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Cao|first=Deborah|title=Chinese Law: A Language Perspective|year=2004|publisher=Ashgate Publishing|pages=71–72}}&lt;/ref&gt;

By the time of the [[Xinhai Revolution]] in 1911, there were many calls such as the [[May Fourth Movement]] to completely abolish the old imperial institutions and practices of China.  There have been attempts to incorporate [[democracy]], [[republicanism]], and [[industrialism]] into Chinese philosophy, notably by [[Sun Yat-Sen]] at the beginning of the 20th century. [[Mao Zedong]] added [[Marxism]], [[Stalinism]], [[Chinese Marxist Philosophy]] and other [[Communism|communist]] thought.

When the [[Communist Party of China]] [[Chinese Civil War|took over]] the reign, previous schools of thought, excepting notably [[Legalism (Chinese philosophy)|Legalism]], were denounced as backward, and later even purged during the [[Cultural Revolution]], whereas their influences on Chinese thoughts remain until today. The current government of the [[China|People's Republic of China]] is trying to encourage a form of [[Socialism with Chinese characteristics|market socialism]].

Since the radical movement of the Cultural Revolution, the Chinese government has become much more tolerant with the practice of traditional beliefs. The [[1978 Constitution of the People's Republic of China]] guarantees &quot;freedom of religion&quot; with a number of restrictions. Spiritual and philosophical institutions have been allowed to be established or re-established, as long they are not perceived to be a threat to the power of the [[Communist Party of China|CPC]]. Moreover, those organizations are heavily monitored. The influences of the past are still deeply ingrained in the Chinese culture.

=== New Confucianism ===
{{Main|New Confucianism}}
New Confucianism is an [[intellectual]] movement of [[Confucianism]] that began in the early 20th century in Republican [[China]], and revived in post-[[Mao Zedong|Mao]] era [[People's Republic of China|contemporary China]]. It is deeply influenced by, but not identical with, the  [[Neo-Confucianism]] of the [[Song dynasty|Song]] and [[Ming Dynasty|Ming]] dynasties.

== Philosophers ==
{{Main|List of Chinese philosophers}}
* [[Confucius]], seen as the Great Master but sometimes ridiculed by Taoists.
** [[Mencius]], Confucius' follower having idealist inspiration
** [[Xun Zi]], another Confucius' follower, closer to realism, teacher of Han Fei and Li Si
** [[Zhu Xi]], founder of [[Neo-Confucianism]]
** [[Wang Yangming]], most influential proponent of ''xinxue'' or &quot;state of mind.&quot;
* [[Lao Zi]], the chief of Taoist school.
** [[Zhuang Zhou|Zhuangzi]], said to be the author of the ''Zhuangzi''.
** [[Lie Yukou|Liezi]], said to be the author of the ''[[Liezi]]''.
* [[Mozi]], the founder of Mohist school.
* [[Shang Yang]], Legalist founder and pivotal Qin reformer
* [[Han Fei]], one of the most notable theoreticians of Legalism
* [[Li Si]], major proponent and practitioner of Legalism

== Concepts ==
{{Unreferenced section|date=June 2010}}
Although the individual philosophical schools differ considerably, they nevertheless share a common vocabulary and set of concerns.

Among the terms commonly found in Chinese philosophy are:
* {{lang|zh|道}} [[Tao|Dao]] (the Way, or one's doctrine)
* {{lang|zh|德}} [[De (Chinese)|De]] (virtue, power)
* {{lang|zh|理}} [[Li (Neo-Confucianism)|Li]] (principle)
* {{lang|zh|氣}} [[Qi]] (vital energy or material force)
* The ''[[Taiji (philosophy)|Taiji]]'' (''Great Heavenly Axis'') forms a unity of the two complementary polarities, ''[[Yin and Yang]]''. The word ''Yin'' originally referred to a hillside facing away from the sun. Philosophically, it stands the dark, passive, feminine principle; whereas ''Yang'' (the hillside facing the sun) stands for the bright, active, masculine principle. Yin and Yang are not antagonistic, they alternate in inverse proportion to one another—like the rise and fall of a [[wave]].

Among the commonalities of Chinese philosophies are:
* The tendency not to view man as separate from nature.
* Questions about the nature and existence of a [[Chinese names for the God of Abrahamic religions|monotheistic deity]], which have profoundly influenced Western philosophy, have not been important in Chinese philosophies or a source of great conflict in [[Chinese traditional religion]].
* The belief that the purpose of philosophy is primarily to serve as an ethical and practical guide.
* The political focus: most scholars of the [[Hundred Schools of Thought|Hundred Schools]] were trying to convince the ruler to behave in the way they defended.

== See also ==
{{Portal|Asia|China|Philosophy}}
{| valign=top style=&quot;font-size:95%;&quot;|-
|width=200 valign=top|
* [[Chinese classic texts]]
*[[History of China]]
* [[:Category:Chinese philosophers|Chinese philosophers]]
|width=200 valign=top|
* [[Confucianism]]
* [[Culture of China]]
* [[Eastern philosophy]]
|width=200 valign=top|
* [[Five elements (Chinese philosophy)|Five Elements]]
* [[Hun and po]]
* [[List of Chinese philosophers]]
|width=200 valign=top|
* [[Taoism]]
* [[Thirteen Classics]]
|}

== References ==
{{reflist|30em}}

== Further reading ==
* Bo Mou (Editor), ''History of Chinese Philosophy'', Routledge, 2009.
* [[Antonio Cua|Antonio S. Cua]] (Editor),  ''Encyclopedia of Chinese Philosophy'', Routledge, 2003.
*  [[Feng Youlan]], ''A History of Chinese Philosophy'' (Princeton Paperbacks), tr. [[Derk Bodde]], 1983.
* [[Herrlee Glessner Creel]],  ''Chinese Thought, from Confucius to Mao Zedong'', 1971.
*  A. C. Graham, ''Disputers of the Tao; Philosophical Argument in Ancient China'', 1989.
* Christoph Harbsmeier, ''Logic and Language in Ancient China'', (Joseph Needham, ''Science and Civilisation in China'', Volume 7, Part I, Cambridge University Press, 1998.
* [[Philip J. Ivanhoe]] and [[Bryan W. Van Norden]] (Editors), ''Readings in Classical Chinese Philosophy'', 2nd edition, Indianapolis:  Hackett Publishing, 2005.
* Karyn Lai, ''Introduction to Chinese Philosophy'', Cambridge University Press, 2008.
* [[Lin Yutang]], ''The Importance of Living'', William Morrow Paperbacks, 1998.
* [[Jana S. Rošker]], ''Searching for the Way: Theory of Knowledge in Pre-modern and Modern Chinese Philosophy'' Hong Kong Chinese University Press, 2008.
* [[Roel Sterckx]], ''Chinese Thought. From Confucius to Cook Ding.'' London: Penguin, 2019.
* [[Roel Sterckx]], ''Ways of Heaven. An Introduction to Chinese Thought.'' New York: Basic Books, 2019.
* [[Justin Tiwald]] and [[Bryan W. Van Norden]] (Editors), ''Readings in Later Chinese Philosophy: Han Dynasty to the 20th Century'', Indianapolis: Hackett Publishing, 2014.
* [[Bryan W. Van Norden]],  ''Introduction to Classical Chinese Philosophy'', Indianapolis:  Hackett Publishing, 2011.
* [[Arthur Waley]], ''Three Ways of Thought in Ancient China'', 1983.

== External links ==

*{{cite SEP |url-id=chinese-metaphysics |title=Metaphysics in Chinese Philosophy |last=Perkins  |first=Franklin}}
*{{cite SEP |url-id=comparphil-chiwes |title=Comparative Philosophy: Chinese and Western |last=Wong |first=David}}
*{{cite SEP |url-id=chinese-translate-interpret |title=Translating and Interpreting Chinese Philosophy |author=Henry Rosemont Jr.}}
*{{cite SEP |url-id=chinese-epistemology |title=Epistemology in Chinese Philosophy |last=Rošker  |first=Jana}}
*{{cite IEP |url-id=chin-ovr |title=Chinese Philosophy: Overview of Topics |last=Littlejohn |first=Ronnie}}
*{{cite IEP |url-id=lang-chi |title=Language in Classical Chinese Philosophy |last=Sikri |first=Rohan}}
*{{cite IEP |url-id=mod-chin |title=Modern Chinese Philosophy |last=Yu |first=Yih-Hsien}}
* {{InPho|taxonomy|2420}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20070704160934/http://www.literati-tradition.com/space.html Article &quot;The Chinese Concept of Space&quot;]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20070704160751/http://www.literati-tradition.com/time.html Article &quot;The Chinese Concept of Time&quot;]
* [http://www.chinaknowledge.de/History/Zhou/zhou-literature.html The Hundred Schools of Thought]
* [http://ctext.org Chinese Text Project] - Chinese philosophy texts in classical Chinese with English and modern Chinese translations
* {{curlie|Society/Philosophy/Eastern_Philosophy/|Eastern Philosophy}}
* [http://www.newleftreview.org/?page=article&amp;view=2664 Contesting Confucius] Henry Zhao, New Left Review 44, March–April 2007
* ''Encyclopédie ou Dictionnaire raisonné des sciences, des arts et des métiers'', 1751–1772, &quot;[https://web.archive.org/web/20080605205614/http://ringmar.net/europeanfury/?page_id=1594 &quot;Philosophie des Chinois]&quot; [in French]
* [http://warpweftandway.com Warp Weft and Way] - A Group Blog of Chinese and Comparative Philosophy

{{Philosophy topics}}
{{Chinese philosophy}}
{{China topics|state=autocollapse}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Chinese Philosophy}}
[[Category:Chinese philosophy| ]]
[[Category:Chinese culture]]
[[Category:History of China]]
[[Category:Chinese literature]]
[[Category:Philosophy by culture]]</text>
      <sha1>i11yt5w0s3dylkjuh54cr1ijg1embqh</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
