  <page>
    <title>Cenozoic</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5816</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942958783</id>
      <parentid>942957569</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-27T23:04:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Vsmith</username>
        <id>84417</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contribs/104.254.68.254|104.254.68.254]] ([[User talk:104.254.68.254|talk]]) to last version by Filedelinkerbot</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Third era of the Phanerozoic Eon 66 million years ago to present}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2011}}
{{Geological era}}
[[File:Torre Sant'Andrea.jpg|thumb|Rock deposits from the Cenozoic Era.]]
The '''Cenozoic''' [[Era (geology)|Era]] ({{IPAc-en|ˌ|s|iː|.|n|ə|ˈ|z|oʊ|.|ɪ|k|,_|-|n|oʊ|-|,_|ˌ|s|ɛ|n|.|ə|-|,_|ˌ|s|ɛ|n|.|oʊ|-}} {{respell|see|nə|ZOH|ik|,_|-|noh|-|,_|SEN|ə|-|,_|SEN|oh|-}}){{refn|{{Dictionary.com|Cenozoic}}}}{{refn|{{MerriamWebsterDictionary|Cenozoic}}}} meaning &quot;new life&quot; is the current and most recent of the three [[Phanerozoic]] geological eras, following the [[Mesozoic]] Era and extending from 66 million years ago to the present day. It is generally believed to have started on the day of the [[Cretaceous–Paleogene extinction event]] when an asteroid hit the earth.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url=https://www.pnas.org/content/116/39/19342|title=The first day of the Cenozoic|first1=Sean P. S.|last1=Gulick|first2=Timothy J.|last2=Bralower|first3=Jens|last3=Ormö|first4=Brendon|last4=Hall|first5=Kliti|last5=Grice|first6=Bettina|last6=Schaefer|first7=Shelby|last7=Lyons|first8=Katherine H.|last8=Freeman|first9=Joanna V.|last9=Morgan|first10=Natalia|last10=Artemieva|first11=Pim|last11=Kaskes|first12=Sietze J. de|last12=Graaff|first13=Michael T.|last13=Whalen|first14=Gareth S.|last14=Collins|first15=Sonia M.|last15=Tikoo|first16=Christina|last16=Verhagen|first17=Gail L.|last17=Christeson|first18=Philippe|last18=Claeys|first19=Marco J. L.|last19=Coolen|first20=Steven|last20=Goderis|first21=Kazuhisa|last21=Goto|first22=Richard A. F.|last22=Grieve|first23=Naoma|last23=McCall|first24=Gordon R.|last24=Osinski|first25=Auriol S. P.|last25=Rae|first26=Ulrich|last26=Riller|first27=Jan|last27=Smit|first28=Vivi|last28=Vajda|first29=Axel|last29=Wittmann|first30=the Expedition 364|last30=Scientists|date=24 September 2019|journal=Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences|volume=116|issue=39|pages=19342–19351|via=www.pnas.org|doi=10.1073/pnas.1909479116|pmid=31501350}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Cenozoic is also known as the ''Age of Mammals,'' because the extinction of many groups allowed mammals to greatly diversify so that large [[mammal]]s  dominated the Earth. The continents also moved into their current positions during this era.

Early in the Cenozoic, following the [[K-Pg extinction event]], most of the [[fauna]] was relatively small, and included small mammals, birds, reptiles, and [[amphibian]]s. From a geological perspective, it did not take long for mammals and birds to greatly diversify in the absence of the large reptiles that had dominated during the Mesozoic. A group of avians known as the &quot;[[terror birds]]&quot; grew larger than the average human and were formidable predators. Mammals came to occupy almost every available niche (both marine and terrestrial), and some also grew very large, attaining sizes not seen in most of today's mammals.

The Earth's climate had begun a drying and cooling trend, culminating in the glaciations of the [[Pleistocene Epoch]], and partially offset by the [[Paleocene-Eocene Thermal Maximum]].

==Nomenclature==
''Cenozoic,'' meaning &quot;new life,&quot; is derived from [[Greek language|Greek]] {{lang|grc|καινός}} ''kainós'' &quot;new,&quot; and {{lang|grc|ζωή}} ''zōḗ'' &quot;life.&quot;&lt;ref name=OnlineEtDict&gt;{{cite dictionary|title=Cenozoic|url=http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?term=Cenozoic&amp;allowed_in_frame=0|dictionary=[[Online Etymology Dictionary]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The era is also known as the ''Cænozoic'', ''Caenozoic'', or ''Cainozoic'' ({{IPAc-en|ˌ|k|aɪ|n|ə|ˈ|z|oʊ|ɪ|k|,_|ˌ|k|eɪ|-}}).{{refn|{{Dictionary.com|Cainozoic}}}}&lt;ref&gt;Oxford English Dictionary Second Edition, 1989&lt;/ref&gt;  The name &quot;Cenozoic&quot; (originally: &quot;Kainozoic&quot;) was proposed in 1840 by the British geologist [[John Phillips (geologist)|John Phillips]] (1800–1874).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Phillips |first1=John |title=Penny Cyclopaedia of the Society for the Diffusion of Useful Knowledge |volume= vol. 17 |date=1840 |publisher=Charles Knight and Co. |location=London, England |pages=153–154 |chapter-url=https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=hvd.hn4zr7;view=1up;seq=163 |chapter=Palæozoic series}}  From pp. 153–154: &quot;As many systems or combinations of organic forms as are clearly traceable in the stratified crust of the globe, so many corresponding terms (as Palæozoic, Mesozoic, Kainozoic, &amp;c.) may be made, … &quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Wilmarth |first1=Mary Grace |title=Bulletin 769: The Geologic Time Classification of the United States Geological Survey Compared With Other Classifications, accompanied by the original definitions of era, period and epoch terms |date=1925 |publisher=U.S. Government Printing Office |location=Washington, D.C., U.S.A. |page=8 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=my7x_PBkpm4C&amp;pg=PA8}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The evolution of the spelling of &quot;Cenozoic&quot; is reviewed in: 
* {{cite book |last1=Harland |first1=W. Brian |last2=Armstrong |first2=Richard L. |last3=Cox |first3=Allen V. |last4=Craig |first4=Lorraine E. |last5=Smith |first5=David G. |last6=Smith |first6=Alan G. |title=A Geologic Time Scale 1989 |date=1990 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |location=Cambridge, England, U.K. |page=31 |chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=xbKJV6LSeggC&amp;pg=PA31 |chapter=The Chronostratic Scale}}
Although John Phillips originally (1840) spelled Cenozoic as &quot;Kainozoic&quot;, in 1841 he spelled it as &quot;Cainozoic&quot;:
* {{cite book |last1=Phillips |first1=John |title=Figures and Descriptions of the Palæozoic Fossils of Cornwall, Devon, and West Somerset; … |date=1841 |publisher=Longman, Brown, Green, &amp; Longmans |location=London, England, U.K. |page=[https://archive.org/details/figuresanddescr00philgoog/page/n174 160] |url=https://archive.org/details/figuresanddescr00philgoog}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Divisions==
The Cenozoic is divided into three periods: the [[Paleogene]], [[Neogene]], and [[Quaternary]]; and seven epochs: the [[Paleocene]], [[Eocene]], [[Oligocene]], [[Miocene]], [[Pliocene]], [[Pleistocene]], and [[Holocene]]. The Quaternary Period was officially recognized by the [[International Commission on Stratigraphy]] in June 2009,&lt;ref name=Gibbard&gt;{{cite journal | year = 2010 | last1 = Gibbard | first1 = P. L. | last2 = Head | first2 = M. J. | last3 = Walker | first3 = M. J. C. | title = Formal ratification of the Quaternary System/Period and the Pleistocene Series/Epoch with a base at 2.58 Ma | journal = Journal of Quaternary Science | volume = 25 | issue = 2 | pages = 96–102 | bibcode = 2010JQS....25...96G | doi = 10.1002/jqs.1338}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the former term, [[Tertiary Period]], became officially disused in 2004 due to the need to divide the Cenozoic into periods more like those of the earlier Paleozoic and Mesozoic eras.&lt;ref name=&quot;International Stratigraphic Chart&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.stratigraphy.org/ICSchart/ChronostratChart2014-02.pdf|title=International Stratigraphic Chart}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Why?|date=August 2014}} The common use of epochs during the Cenozoic helps [[paleontologist]]s better organize and group the many significant events that occurred during this comparatively short interval of time. Knowledge of this era is more detailed than any other era because of the relatively young, well-preserved rocks associated with it.

===Paleogene===
The Paleogene spans from the extinction of non-avian dinosaurs, 66 million years ago, to the dawn of the Neogene, 23.03 million years ago. It features three [[epoch (geology)|epoch]]s: the [[Paleocene]], [[Eocene]] and [[Oligocene]].  [[File:Basilosaurus.jpg|thumb|''[[Basilosaurus]]'']]

The [[Paleocene epoch]] lasted from 66 million to 56 million years ago. Modern placental mammals originated during this time. The Paleocene is a transitional point between the devastation that is the [[K-T extinction]], and the rich jungle environment that is the Early Eocene. The Early Paleocene saw the recovery of the earth. The continents began to take their modern shape, but all the continents and the subcontinent of India were separated from each other. [[Afro-Eurasia]] was separated by the [[Tethys Sea]], and the Americas were separated by the strait of Panama, as the isthmus had not yet formed. This epoch featured a general warming trend, with jungles eventually reaching the poles. The oceans were dominated by sharks&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|last=Royal Tyrrell Museum|title=Lamniform sharks: 110 million years of ocean supremacy|date=2012-03-28|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=e4p9EWuVxYQ|accessdate=2017-07-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; as the large reptiles that had once predominated were extinct. Archaic mammals filled the world such as [[creodonts]] (extinct carnivores, unrelated to existing [[Carnivora]]).

The [[Eocene Epoch]] ranged from 56 million years to 33.9 million years ago. In the Early-Eocene, species living in dense forest were unable to evolve into larger forms, as in the Paleocene. All known mammals were under 10 kilograms.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ucmp.berkeley.edu/tertiary/eocene.php|title=Eocene Epoch|author=University of California|work=University of California}}&lt;/ref&gt; Among them were early primates, whales and horses along with many other early forms of mammals. At the top of the food chains were huge birds, such as [[Paracrax]]. The temperature was 30 degrees Celsius with little temperature gradient from pole to pole. In the Mid-Eocene, the Circumpolar-Antarctic current between Australia and Antarctica formed. This disrupted ocean currents worldwide and as a result caused a global cooling effect, shrinking the jungles. This allowed mammals to grow to mammoth proportions, such as whales which, by that time, had become almost fully aquatic. Mammals like ''[[Andrewsarchus]]'' were at the top of the food-chain. The Late Eocene saw the rebirth of seasons, which caused the expansion of savanna-like areas, along with the evolution of [[grass]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ucmp.berkeley.edu/tertiary/eocene.php|title=Eocene Climate|author=University of California|work=University of California}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://science.nationalgeographic.com/science/prehistoric-world/paleogene/|title=Eocene|author=National Geographic Society|work=National Geographic}}&lt;/ref&gt; The end of the Eocene was marked by the [[Eocene-Oligocene extinction event]], the European face of which is known as the [[Grande Coupure]].

The [[Oligocene Epoch]] spans from 33.9 million to 23.03 million years ago. The Oligocene featured the expansion of [[grass]] which had led to many new species to evolve, including the first elephants, cats, dogs, marsupials and many other species still prevalent today. Many other species of plants evolved in this period too. A cooling period featuring seasonal rains was still in effect. Mammals still continued to grow larger and larger.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ucmp.berkeley.edu/tertiary/oligocene.php|title=Oligocene|author=University of California|work=University of California}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Neogene===
The Neogene spans from 23.03 million to 2.58 million years ago.  It features 2 epochs: the Miocene, and the Pliocene.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/408872/Neogene-Period|title=Neogene|author=Encyclopædia Britannica|encyclopedia=Encyclopædia Britannica}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Miocene epoch]] spans from 23.03 to 5.333 million years ago and is a period in which [[grass]] spread further, dominating a large portion of the world, at the expense of forests. [[Kelp]] forests evolved, encouraging the evolution of new species, such as [[sea otter]]s. During this time, [[perissodactyla]] thrived, and evolved into many different varieties. [[Apes]] evolved into 30 species. The [[Tethys Sea]] finally closed with the creation of the [[Arabian Peninsula]], leaving only remnants as the [[Black Sea|Black]], [[Red Sea|Red]], [[Mediterranean Sea|Mediterranean]] and [[Caspian Sea]]s. This increased aridity. Many new plants evolved: 95% of modern [[Spermatophyte|seed plants]] evolved in the mid-Miocene.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ucmp.berkeley.edu/tertiary/miocene.php|title=Miocene|author=University of California|work=University of California}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Pliocene epoch]] lasted from 5.333 to 2.58 million years ago. The Pliocene featured dramatic climactic changes, which ultimately led to modern species of flora and fauna. The Mediterranean Sea dried up for several million years (because the [[ice age]]s reduced sea levels, disconnecting the [[Atlantic ocean|Atlantic]] from the Mediterranean, and evaporation rates exceeded inflow from rivers). ''[[Australopithecus]]'' evolved in [[Africa]], beginning the human branch. The [[isthmus of Panama]] formed, and animals migrated between [[North America|North]] and [[South America]] during the [[great American interchange]], wreaking havoc on local ecologies. Climatic changes brought: [[savanna]]s that are still continuing to spread across the world; Indian [[monsoon]]s; [[desert]]s in central [[Asia]]; and the beginnings of the [[Sahara]] desert. The world map has not changed much since, save for changes brought about by the [[glaciations]] of the Quaternary, such as the [[Great Lakes]], [[Hudson Bay]], and the [[Baltic sea]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ucmp.berkeley.edu/tertiary/pliocene.php|title=Pliocene|author=University of California|work=University of California}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.esd.ornl.gov/projects/qen/pliocene.html|title=Pliocene climate|author=Jonathan Adams|work=Oak Ridge National Library|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150225011508/http://www.esd.ornl.gov/projects/qen/pliocene.html|archivedate=25 February 2015|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Quaternary===
The Quaternary spans from 2.58 million years ago to present day, and is the shortest geological period in the [[Phanerozoic Eon]]. It features modern animals, and dramatic changes in the climate. It is divided into two epochs: the Pleistocene and the Holocene.

[[File:Ice age fauna of northern Spain - Mauricio Antón.jpg|thumb|Megafauna of Pleistocene Europe ([[mammoth]]s, [[Panthera spelaea|cave lions]], [[woolly rhino]], [[reindeer]], [[Wild horse|horses]])]]
The Pleistocene lasted from 2.58 million to 11,700 years ago. This epoch was marked by [[ice ages]] as a result of the cooling trend that started in the Mid-Eocene. There were at least four separate glaciation periods marked by the advance of ice caps as far south as 40° N in mountainous areas. Meanwhile, Africa experienced a trend of [[desiccation]] which resulted in the creation of the [[Sahara desert|Sahara]], [[Namib desert|Namib]], and [[Kalahari desert|Kalahari]] deserts. Many animals evolved including [[mammoth]]s, [[giant ground sloths]], [[dire wolves]], saber-toothed cats, and most famously ''[[Homo sapiens]]''. 100,000 years ago marked the end of one of the worst droughts in Africa, and led to the expansion of primitive humans. As the Pleistocene drew to a close, a major extinction wiped out much of the world's megafauna, including some of the hominid species, such as [[Neanderthal]]s. All the continents were affected, but Africa to a lesser extent. It still retains many large animals, such as hippos.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ucmp.berkeley.edu/quaternary/pleistocene.php|title=Pleistocene|author=University of California|work=University of California}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Holocene began 11,700 years ago and lasts to the present day. All recorded history and &quot;the [[history of the world]]&quot; lies within the boundaries of the Holocene epoch.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ucmp.berkeley.edu/quaternary/holocene.php|title=Holocene|author=University of California|work=University of California}}&lt;/ref&gt; Human activity is blamed for a mass extinction that began roughly 10,000 years ago, though the species becoming extinct have only been recorded since the [[Industrial Revolution]]. This is sometimes referred to as the &quot;[[Sixth Extinction]]&quot;. It is often cited that over 322 recorded species have become extinct due to human activity since the Industrial Revolution,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.scientificamerican.com/article/fact-or-fiction-the-sixth-mass-extinction-can-be-stopped/|title=Sixth Extinction extinctions|author=Scientific American|work=Scientific American}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.iucn.org/?4143/Extinction-crisis-continues-apace|title=Sixth Extinction|author=IUCN|work=IUCN}}&lt;/ref&gt; but the rate may be as high as 500 veterbrate species alone, the majority of which have occurred after 1900.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://advances.sciencemag.org/content/1/5/e1400253.full/|title=Accelerated modern human–induced species losses: Entering the sixth mass extinction|author=Ceballos et al. (2015)|work=Science Advances}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Animal life==
Early in the Cenozoic, following the [[Cretaceous-Paleogene Extinction Event|K-Pg event]], the planet was dominated by relatively small fauna, including small mammals, birds, reptiles, and amphibians. From a geological perspective, it did not take long for mammals and birds to greatly diversify in the absence of the dinosaurs that had dominated during the Mesozoic. Some flightless birds grew larger than humans. These species are sometimes referred to as &quot;[[terror bird]]s,&quot; and were formidable predators. Mammals came to occupy almost every available [[ecological niche|niche]] (both marine and [[terrestrial animal|terrestrial]]), and some also grew very large, attaining sizes not seen in most of today's terrestrial mammals.

Early animals were the [[Entelodon]], [[Paraceratherium]] (a hornless rhinoceros relative) and [[Basilosaurus]] (an early whale). The extinction of many large [[diapsid]] groups, such as flightless [[dinosaurs]], [[Plesiosauria]] and [[Pterosauria]] allowed mammals and birds to greatly diversify and become the world's predominant fauna.

==Tectonics==
[[Geology|Geologically]], the Cenozoic is the era when the [[continent]]s moved into their current positions. [[Australia (continent)|Australia-New Guinea]], having split from [[Pangea]] during the early [[Cretaceous]], drifted north and, eventually, collided with [[South-east Asia]]; [[Antarctica]] moved into its current position over the [[South Pole]]; the [[Atlantic Ocean]] widened and, later in the era (2.8 million years ago), [[South America]] became attached to [[North America]] with the [[isthmus of Panama]].

India collided with Asia {{Ma|55|45}} creating the Himalayas; Arabia collided with Eurasia, closing the [[Tethys Ocean]] and creating the Zagros Mountains, around {{Ma|35}}.&lt;ref name=Allen2008&gt;{{cite journal| first1 = M. B.| first2 = H. A. | title = Arabia-Eurasia collision and the forcing of mid Cenozoic global cooling| last2 = Armstrong  | url =  http://dro.dur.ac.uk/14557/1/14557.pdf| journal = Palaeogeography, Palaeoclimatology, Palaeoecology | volume = 265 | issue = 1–2| pages = 52–58 | year = 2008| last1 = Allen | doi = 10.1016/j.palaeo.2008.04.021 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The break-up of Gondwana in [[Late Cretaceous]] and Cenozoic times led to a shift in the river courses of various large African rivers including the [[Congo River|Congo]], [[Niger River|Niger]], [[Nile]], [[Orange River|Orange]], [[Limpopo River|Limpopo]] and [[Zambezi River|Zambezi]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Goudie |first1=A.S.|author-link=Andrew Goudie (geographer) |date=2005 |title=The drainage of Africa since the Cretaceous |url= |journal=[[Geomorphology (journal)|Geomorphology]] |volume=67 |issue= 3–4|pages=437–456 |doi= 10.1016/j.geomorph.2004.11.008|bibcode=2005Geomo..67..437G}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Climate==
In the Cretaceous, the climate was hot and humid with lush forests at the poles, there was no permanent ice and sea levels were around 300 metres higher than today. This continued for the first 10 million years of the Paleocene, culminating in the [[Paleocene–Eocene Thermal Maximum]] about {{Ma|55.5}}. Around {{Ma|50}} the earth entered a period of long term cooling. This was mainly due to the collision of India with Eurasia, which caused the rise of the [[Himalayas]]: the upraised rocks eroded and reacted with {{CO2}} in the air, causing a long term reduction in the proportion of this greenhouse gas in the atmosphere. Around {{Ma|35}} permanent ice began to build up on Antactica.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Dartnell |first=Lewis |authorlink=Lewis Dartnell |title=Origins:How the Earth Made Us |publisher=Bodley Head |location =London, UK|pages=9-10, 40 |year=2018|isbn=978 1 8479 2435 3 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  The cooling trend continued in the [[Miocene]], with relatively short warmer periods. When South America became attached to North America creating the [[Isthmus of Panama]] around {{Ma|2.8}}, the Arctic region cooled due to the strengthening of the [[Humboldt Current|Humboldt]] and [[Gulf Stream]] currents,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.whoi.edu/oceanus/viewArticle.do?id=2508|title=How the Isthmus of Panama Put Ice in the Arctic|work=Oceanus Magazine}}&lt;/ref&gt; eventually leading to the glaciations of the [[Quaternary glaciation|Quaternary ice age]], the current [[interglacial]] of which is the [[Holocene]] Epoch.
Recent analysis of the geomagnetic reversal frequency, oxygen isotope record, and tectonic plate subduction rate, which are indicators of the changes in the heat flux at the core mantle boundary, climate and plate tectonic activity, shows that all these changes indicate similar rhythms on million years' timescale in the Cenozoic Era occurring with the common fundamental periodicity of ∼13 Myr during most of the time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Chen | first1 = J. | last2 = Kravchinsky | first2 = V.A. | last3 = Liu | first3 = X. | year = 2015 | title = The 13 million year Cenozoic pulse of the Earth | url = | journal = Earth and Planetary Science Letters | volume = 431 | issue = | pages = 256–263 | doi = 10.1016/j.epsl.2015.09.033 | bibcode=2015E&amp;PSL.431..256C}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Life==
During the Cenozoic, [[Mammal evolution#Expansion of ecological niches in the Mesozoic|mammals proliferated]] from a few small, simple, generalized forms into a diverse collection of [[Terrestrial animal|terrestrial]], [[Marine mammal|marine]], and [[bat|flying]] animals, giving this period its other name, the Age of Mammals, despite the fact that there are more than twice as many [[bird]] species as mammal species.  The Cenozoic is just as much the age of [[savanna]]s, the age of co-dependent [[flowering plant]]s and [[insect]]s, and the age of birds.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ucmp.berkeley.edu/cenozoic/cenozoic.php|title=The Cenozoic Era|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Grass]] also played a very important role in this era, shaping the evolution of the birds and mammals that fed on it.  One group that diversified significantly in the Cenozoic as well were the [[snake]]s. Evolving in the Cenozoic, the variety of snakes increased tremendously, resulting in many [[colubrids]], following the evolution of their current primary prey source, the [[rodent]]s.

In the earlier part of the Cenozoic, the world was dominated by the [[Gastornithidae|gastornithid]] birds, terrestrial [[Crocodilia|crocodile]]s like ''[[Pristichampsus]]'', and a handful of primitive large mammal groups like [[uintathere]]s, [[mesonychid]]s, and [[pantodont]]s. But as the forests began to recede and the climate began to cool, other mammals took over.

The Cenozoic is full of mammals both strange and familiar, including [[chalicothere]]s, [[creodont]]s, [[whale]]s, [[primate]]s, [[entelodont]]s, [[saber-toothed cat]]s, [[mastodon]]s and [[mammoth]]s, [[three-toed horse]]s, giant [[rhinoceros]] like ''[[Indricotherium]]'', the rhinoceros-like [[brontothere]]s, various bizarre groups of mammals from South America, such as the vaguely elephant-like [[pyrotheria|pyrothere]]s and the dog-like marsupial relatives called [[borhyaenidae|borhyaenids]] and the [[monotreme]]s and marsupials of Australia.

==See also==
{{Portal|Earth sciences}}
* [[Cretaceous–Paleogene boundary]] (K–T boundary)
* [[Geologic time scale]]
* [[Late Cenozoic Ice Age]]
* [[Mesozoic]]
* [[Paleozoic]]
* [[Phanerozoic Eon]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Bibliography==
* ''British Caenozoic Fossils'', 1975, The Natural History Museum, London.
* ''Geologic Time'', by Henry Roberts.
* ''After the Dinosaurs: The Age of Mammals'', by Donald R. Prothero, Bloomington, Indiana: Indiana University Press, 2006. {{ISBN|978-0-253-34733-6}}.

==External links==
{{Wikisource1911Enc|Cainozoic}}
{{Commons category|Cenozoic}}
* [http://museum.wa.gov.au/explore/dinosaur-discovery/age-mammals Western Australian Museum – The Age of the Mammals]
* [https://ghkclass.com/ghkC.html?cenozoic Cenozoic (chronostratigraphy scale)]

{{Geological history|p|c}}
{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Cenozoic| ]]
[[Category:Geological eras]]
[[Category:Geological history of Earth]]
[[Category:Phanerozoic|*03]]</text>
      <sha1>axfd66uqx69vxxyq0vf8nhiwx86oj7q</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
