  <page>
    <title>Politics of the Czech Republic</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5848</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941569334</id>
      <parentid>940772916</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-19T10:42:19Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bedivere.cs</username>
        <id>10119678</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Legislative branch */ Vystrčil</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Political system of the Czech Republic}}
{{more citations needed|date=August 2016}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=April 2011}}
{{Politics of the Czech Republic}}

The [[Czech Republic]] is a [[Unitary state|unitary]] [[parliamentary system|parliamentary]] constitutional republic, in which the [[President of the Czech Republic|President]] is the [[head of state]] and the [[Prime Minister of the Czech Republic|Prime Minister]] is the [[head of government]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/czech-republic|title=Czech Republic {{!}} World news|website=the Guardian|language=en|access-date=2018-10-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; Executive power is exercised by the [[Government of the Czech Republic]] which reports to the [[lower house]] of [[Parliament of the Czech Republic|Parliament]]. The Legislature is [[bicameral]], with the [[Chamber of Deputies of the Czech Republic|Chamber of Deputies]] (''Poslanecká sněmovna'') consisting of 200 members and the [[Senate of the Czech Republic|Senate]] (''Senát'') consisting of 81 members. Both houses together make up the [[Parliament of the Czech Republic]].

The political system of the Czech Republic is a [[multi-party system]]. Since 1993, the two largest parties were the center-left [[Czech Social Democratic Party]] (ČSSD) and right-wing [[Civic Democratic Party (Czech Republic)|Civic Democratic Party]] (ODS). This model changed in early 2014, with the rise of a new political party [[ANO 2011]] which led to weakening of both major parties. {{Democracy Index rating|Czech Republic|flawed democracy|2019}}

[[File:Czechpolsystem.png|thumbnail|right|450px|The political system of the [[Czech Republic]]]]

==Political developments==
The [[Czech Republic|Czech]] political scene supports a broad spectrum of [[political party|parties]] ranging from the [[Communist Party of Bohemia and Moravia|Communist Party]] on the far left to various [[nationalistic]] parties on the far right.

Czech voters returned a split verdict in the June 2002 parliamentary elections, giving [[Czech Social Democratic Party|Social Democrats]] (ČSSD) and Communists majority, without any possibility to form a functioning government together due to [[Vladimír Špidla]]'s strong anticommunism. The results produced a ČSSD coalition government with [[Christian Democratic Union - Czechoslovak People's Party|Christian Democrats]] (KDU-ČSL) and [[Freedom Union-Democratic Union|Liberals]] (US-DEU), while [[Civic Democratic Party (Czech Republic)|Civic Democrats]] (ODS) and Communists (KSČM) took place in opposition. The MP ratio was the tiniest 101:99. After many buffetings and, finally, after the catastrophic results of the June [[2004 European Parliament election in the Czech Republic|European Parliament election, 2004]] Špidla resigned after a revolt in his own party and the government was reshuffled on the same basis.

[[Image:Flag of the President of the Czech Republic.svg|left|thumb|Flag of the Czech president]]

As the system in the Czech Republic repeatedly produces very weak governments (a specific problem is that about 15% of the electorate support the Communists, who are shunned by all the other parties) there is constant talk about changing it but without much chance of really pushing the reform through. An attempt to increase majority elements by tweaking the system parameters (more smaller districts, [[d'Hondt method]] used) by ČSSD and ODS during their &quot;opposition agreement&quot; of 1998–2002 was vehemently opposed by smaller parties and blocked by the Constitutional Court as going too much against the constitution-stated proportional principle; only a moderated form was adopted. This, however, led to a stalemate in the 2006 elections where both the left and the right each gained exactly 100 seats; as many commentators point out, the earlier system would have given the right a 3–4 seat majority.

In March 2006, the parliament overturned a veto by President Václav Klaus, and the Czech Republic became the first former communist country in Europe to grant legal recognition to same-sex partnerships.

A government formed of a coalition of the ODS, KDU-ČSL, and the [[Green Party (Czech Republic)|Green Party]] (SZ), and led by the leader of the ODS [[Mirek Topolánek]] finally succeeded in winning a [[vote of confidence]] on 19 January 2007. This was thanks to two members of the ČSSD, Miloš Melčák and Michal Pohanka, who abstained.

On 23 March 2009, the government of Mirek Topolánek lost a [[Czech Republic Government Vote of No Confidence, 2009|vote of no-confidence]].

==Executive branch==
The President is the head of state, but the Prime Minister is the head of government.
{{office-table}}
|[[President of the Czech Republic|President]]
|[[Miloš Zeman]]
|[[Party of Civic Rights – Zemanovci|Party of Civic Rights]]
|8 March 2013
|-
|[[Prime Minister of the Czech Republic|Prime Minister]]
|[[Andrej Babiš]]
|[[ANO 2011]]
|6 December 2017
|}

=== President ===
The [[President of the Czech Republic]] is elected by a direct vote (no more than two consecutive) for five years. The president is a formal [[head of state]] with limited specific powers.

==== Powers of President ====
* appoint and recall the Prime Minister and other members of the Government and accept their resignation, recall the Government and accept its resignation;
* convene sessions of the Chamber of Deputies;
* dissolve the Chamber of Deputies when specific conditions described in the constitution are met;
* pardon and mitigate penalties imposed by the court, order not to initiate criminal proceedings and suspend them if they are already initiated, and expunge sentences;
* have the right to return to the Parliament an enacted law with the exception of Constitutional Acts;
* sign enacted laws;
* represent the State with respect to other countries
* negotiate and ratify international treaties; he may delegate the negotiation of international treaties to the Government or, subject to the Government consent, to its individual members;
* be the Commander in Chief of the Armed Forces;
* appoint and recalls heads of diplomatic missions;
* call elections to the Chamber of Deputies and the Senate;
* appoint and promote generals;
* appoint judges

=== Prime Minister ===
{{Main|Prime Minister of the Czech Republic}}

The Prime Minister is the head of government and wields considerable powers, including the right to set the agenda for most foreign and domestic policies, mobilize the parliamentary majority, and choose governmental ministers.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.vlada.cz/en/vlada/premier/|title=Prime Minister {{!}} Government of the Czech Republic|website=www.vlada.cz|language=en|access-date=2018-10-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Garden of Straka Academy, Prague Malá Strana.jpg|thumbnail|right|Straka Academy, the seat of Cabinet in [[Prague]], the Czech Republic capital.]]

=== Cabinet ===
{{Main|Government of the Czech Republic}}

[[Cabinet of the Czech Republic]] is the supreme executive body in the Czech Republic. The Cabinet shall make its decisions as a body. The Cabinet shall consist of the Prime Minister and Ministers. Controls the state and the ministry. Publishes government decree. The Prime Minister shall be appointed by the President of the Republic who shall appoint on the Prime Minister's proposal the other members of the Cabinet and shall entrust them with the direction of individual ministries or other agencies. Within thirty days after its appointment, the Cabinet shall present itself to the Chamber of Deputies and shall ask it for a vote of confidence.

==Legislative branch==
{{Main|Parliament of the Czech Republic}}
[[Image:Zasedací sál Poslanecké sněmovny.jpg|right|thumb|Interior of [[Chamber of Deputies of the Czech Republic|Poslanecká sněmovna]]]]
[[Image:Senat Wallenstein palace Prague 4677.JPG|thumb|[[Wallenstein Palace]] – Seat of the Senate in Prague]]

The [[Parliament of the Czech Republic|Parliament]] (''Parlament České republiky'') has [[bicameralism|two chambers]]. The [[Chamber of Deputies of the Czech Republic|Chamber of Deputies]] (''Poslanecká sněmovna'') has 200 members, elected for a four-year term by [[proportional representation]] with a 5% [[election threshold]]. There are 14 voting districts identical to the country's administrative regions. The Chamber of Deputies, at first the [[Czech National Council]], has the powers and responsibilities of the now defunct federal parliament of the former [[Czechoslovakia]].

The [[Senate of the Czech Republic|Senate]] (''Senát'') has 81 members, in single-seat [[constituency|constituencies]] elected by two-round [[Two-round system|runoff voting]] for a six-year term, with one third renewed every even year in the autumn. The first election was 1996 (for differing terms). This is patterned after the [[United States Senate|U.S. Senate]] but each constituency is of the (roughly) same size and the system used is two-round runoff voting. The Senate is unpopular among the public and suffers from low election turnout (overall roughly 30% in the first round, 20% in the second).

{{office-table}}
|[[Speaker of the Chamber of Deputies (Czech Republic)|Speaker of the Chamber of Deputies]]
|[[Radek Vondráček]]
|[[ANO 2011]]
|22 November 2017
|-
|[[President of the Senate of the Czech Republic|President of the Senate]]
|[[Miloš Vystrčil]]
|[[Civic Democratic Party (Czech Republic)|Civic Democratic Party]]
|19 February 2020
|}

==Political parties and elections==
{{elect|List of political parties in the Czech Republic|Elections in the Czech Republic}}
{{Czech legislative election, 2017}}
{{Composition of the Senate of the Czech Republic}}

==Judicial branch==
{{Main|Judiciary of the Czech Republic}}
The country's highest court of appeals is the [[Supreme Court of the Czech Republic|Supreme Court]]. The [[Constitutional Court of the Czech Republic|Constitutional Court]], which rules on constitutional issues, is appointed by the president with Senate approval, and its 15 members serve 10-year terms. The justices of the Constitutional Court have a mandatory retirement age of 70. The [[Supreme Administrative Court of the Czech Republic|Supreme Administrative Court]] is the third arm of the Czech judiciary.

==Administrative divisions==
{{expand section|date=January 2015}}
The Czech Republic is divided in 14 [[Regions of the Czech Republic|Regions]] including the capital of Prague. The older 73 districts (''okresy'', singular: ''okres'') and 4 municipalities* (města, singular: ''město'') were disbanded in 1999 in an often-criticised administrative reform; however are still traditionally recognized and remain the seats of various branches of state administration:
[[Benešov]], [[Beroun]], [[Blansko]], [[Břeclav]], [[Brno]]-město*, Brno-venkov, [[Bruntál]], [[České Budějovice]], [[Česká Lípa]], [[Český Krumlov]], [[Cheb]], [[Chomutov]], [[Chrudim]], [[Děčín]], [[Domažlice]], [[Frýdek-Místek]], [[Havlíčkův Brod]], [[Hodonín]], [[Hradec Králové]], [[Jablonec nad Nisou]], [[Jeseník]], [[Jičín]], [[Jihlava]], [[Jindřichův Hradec]], [[Karlovy Vary]], [[Karviná]], [[Kladno]], [[Klatovy]], [[Kolín]], [[Kroměříž]], [[Kutná Hora]], [[Liberec]], [[Litoměřice]], [[Louny]], [[Mělník]], [[Mladá Boleslav]], [[Most (Most District)|Most]], [[Náchod]], [[Nový Jičín]], [[Nymburk]], [[Olomouc]], [[Opava]], [[Ostrava]]*, [[Pardubice]], [[Pelhřimov]], [[Písek]], [[Plzeň]]*, Plzeň-jih, Plzeň-sever, [[Prachatice]], [[Prague|Praha]]*, Praha-východ, Praha-západ, [[Přerov]], [[Příbram]], [[Prostějov]], [[Rakovník]], [[Rokycany]], [[Rychnov nad Kněžnou]], [[Semily]], [[Sokolov (Sokolov District)|Sokolov]], [[Strakonice]], [[Šumperk]], [[Svitavy]], [[Tábor]], [[Tachov]], [[Teplice]], [[Trutnov]], [[Třebíč]], [[Uherské Hradiště]], [[Ústí nad Labem]], [[Ústí nad Orlicí]], [[Vsetín]], [[Vyškov]], [[Žďár nad Sázavou]], [[Zlín]], [[Znojmo]]

==International organization participation==
The Czech Republic is member of [[Australia Group]], [[Bank for International Settlements|BIS]], [[Council of Europe|CE]], [[Central European Initiative|CEI]], [[CERN]], [[Euro-Atlantic Partnership Council|EAPC]], [[European Bank for Reconstruction and Development|EBRD]], [[United Nations Economic Commission for Europe|ECE]], EU (among the 10 new members since May 2004), [[Food and Agriculture Organization|FAO]], [[International Atomic Energy Agency|IAEA]], [[World Bank|IBRD]], [[International Civil Aviation Organization|ICAO]], [[International Red Cross and Red Crescent Movement|ICRM]], [[International Development Association|IDA]], [[International Energy Agency|IEA]] (observer), [[International Finance Corporation|IFC]], [[International Federation of Red Cross and Red Crescent Societies|IFRCS]], [[International Labour Organization|ILO]], [[International Monetary Fund|IMF]], [[International Maritime Organization|IMO]], [[Inmarsat]], [[International Telecommunications Satellite Organization|Intelsat]], [[International Criminal Police Organization - Interpol|Interpol]], [[International Olympic Committee|IOC]], [[International Organisation for Migration|IOM]], [[International Organization for Standardization|ISO]], [[International Telecommunication Union|ITU]], [[International Trade Union Confederation|ITUC]], [[NATO]], [[Nuclear Energy Agency|NEA]], [[Nuclear Suppliers Group|NSG]], OAS (observer), [[Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development|OECD]], OIF (Organisation Internationale de la Francophonie) (observer), [[Organisation for the Prohibition of Chemical Weapons|OPCW]], [[Organization for Security and Co-operation in Europe|OSCE]], [[Permanent Court of Arbitration|PCA]], [[Partnership for Peace|PFP]], [[UN]], [[United Nations Conference on Trade and Development|UNCTAD]], [[United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization|UNESCO]], [[United Nations Industrial Development Organization|UNIDO]], [[United Nations Mission in Kosovo|UNMIK]], [[United Nations Mission of Observers in Prevlaka|UNMOP]], [[United Nations Mission of Observers in Tajikistan|UNMOT]], [[United Nations Observer Mission in Georgia|UNOMIG]], [[Universal Postal Union|UPU]], [[Visegrád group]], [[World Customs Organization|WCO]], [[Western European Union|WEU]] (associate), [[World Federation of Trade Unions|WFTU]], [[World Health Organization|WHO]], [[World Intellectual Property Organization|WIPO]], [[World Meteorological Organization|WMO]], [[World Tourism Organization|WToO]], [[World Trade Organization|WTrO]], [[Zangger Committee]]

==See also==
*[[Government of the Czech Republic]]
*[[Ministry of Finance (Czech Republic)]]

==References==
&lt;ref&gt;http://www.mzv.cz/hague/en/general_information_on_the_czech/political_system/index.html&lt;/ref&gt;
{{reflist|30em}}

==External links==
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20081220003426/http://www.hrad.cz/en/ustava_cr/index.shtml Constitution of the Czech Republic]
* [http://www.volby.cz/ – website with results of all elections in Czech and English]
* [http://www.rzb.at/eBusiness/services/resources/lnz_resource_rzb_static/0,7130,1023296711504-1025308884300_1025311539513_1025311893931-65903287614859521-1-NA-NA,00.pdf RZB Group: Czech Republic – Election 2006 Special]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20060718023209/http://www.praguemonitor.com/czech-election-2006/ Czech 2006 Election blog by the Prague Daily Monitor]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20060702103322/http://www.ku.edu/%7Eherron/ Erik Herron's Guide to Politics of East Central Europe and Eurasia]
Government
* [http://www.vlada.cz/en/ Official governmental website] English
* [http://www.hrad.cz/en/ Official presidential website] English
* [http://www.senat.cz/index-eng.php Official Senate website] English
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20120812061745/http://portal.gov.cz/portal/obcan/ Portal of the Public Administration] Czech
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20081210080250/https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/world-leaders-1/world-leaders-c/czech-republic.html Chief of State and Cabinet Members] CIA library on World leaders

{{Czech Republic topics}}
{{Politics of Europe}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Politics Of The Czech Republic}}
[[Category:Politics of the Czech Republic| ]]</text>
      <sha1>jly55fbi13n9yukgyxnmle9coe8hf3p</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
