  <page>
    <title>Climbing</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5857</id>
    <revision>
      <id>932163739</id>
      <parentid>924866839</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-12-23T22:10:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mattg82</username>
        <id>8578499</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>rm tag, has references</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Activity to ascend a steep object}}
{{about|human climbing|climbing in other animals|Arboreal locomotion|other uses}}
{{Climbing sidebar}}
[[File:Escalda en Fitz Roy, Chaltén - Argentina.jpg|thumb|200px|Climber on Mount [[Fitz Roy]], [[Argentina]].]]
[[File:Valkyrie (The Roaches).jpg|thumb|200px|Rock climbers on ''Valkyrie'' at [[The Roaches]] in Staffordshire, England.]]
[[File:Rope Climbing.jpg|thumb|right|200px|A competitor in a [[rope climbing]] event, at [[Lyon]]'s Part-Dieu shopping centre.]]
[[File:Eisklettern kl engstligenfall.jpg|thumb|200px|right| An [[ice climbing|ice climber]] using [[ice axes]] and [[crampons]].]]
&lt;!-- Trying to repair damage from bad moves and cut-n-paste - contact [[User:Stan Shebs]] for a timetable --&gt;

'''Climbing''' is the activity of using one's hands, feet, or any other part of the body to ascend a steep topographical object. It is done for locomotion, recreation and competition, and within trades that rely on ascension; such as emergency rescue and military operations. It is done indoors and out, on natural and man-made structures.

Professional [[mountain guide]]s or rock climbing guides, such as members of the [[UIAGM|IFMGA]], have been known to be a historically significant element of developing the popularity of the sport in the natural environment, and remain so today.

Climbing will be an official sport for the first time in the Olympic Games in 2020. It takes place in Tokyo (see [[Sport climbing at the 2020 Summer Olympics]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.olympic.org/news/from-doha-to-tokyo-onward-and-upward-for-sport-climbing|title=From Doha to Tokyo: onward and upward for sport climbing - Olympic News|date=2019-10-30|website=International Olympic Committee|language=en|access-date=2019-11-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Types==
Climbing activities include:

* [[Bouldering]]: Ascending boulders or small outcrops, often with climbing shoes and a chalk bag or bucket. Usually, instead of using a safety rope from above, injury is avoided using a [[Bouldering mat|crash pad]] and a human spotter (to direct a falling climber on to the pad. They can also give beta, or advice)&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.explore-share.com/blog/what-is-rock-climbing/|title=What is Rock Climbing? Types, Equipment, Top Spots|last=LyleJune 09|first=rew|last2=2018|website=Explore-Share.com|language=en|access-date=2019-11-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Buildering]]: Ascending the exterior skeletons of buildings, typically without protective equipment.
* [[Canyoneering]]: Climbing along [[canyons]] for sport or recreation.
* [[Chalk]] climbing: Ascending chalk cliffs uses some of the same techniques as ice climbing.
* [[climbing competition|Competition climbing]]: A formal, competitive sport of recent origins, normally practiced on artificial walls that resemble natural formations. The International Federation of Sport Climbing ([[International Federation of Sport Climbing|IFSC]]) is the official organization governing competition rock climbing worldwide and is recognized by the [[IOC]] and [[GAISF]] and is a member of the International World Games Association ([[IWGA]]). The UIAA is the official organization governing competition ice climbing worldwide. Competition climbing has three major disciplines: Lead, Bouldering and Speed.
* [[Free climbing]]: a form of [[rock climbing]] in which the climber uses climbing equipment such as [[Climbing rope|ropes]] and other means of [[Protection (climbing)|climbing protection]], but only to protect against injury during falls and not to assist progress.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.evorock.com/blog/2016/07/13/3694/|title=What's the Difference Between &quot;Free Climbing&quot; and &quot;Free Soloing?&quot;|date=2016-07-13|website=EVO Rock|language=en-US|access-date=2019-11-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Ice climbing]]: Ascending ice or hard snow formations using special equipment, usually [[ice axe]]s and [[crampon]]s. Techniques of protecting the climber are similar to those of rock climbing, with protective devices (such as ice screws and snow wedges) adapted to frozen conditions.
* [[Indoor climbing]]: [[Top roping]], [[lead climbing]], and [[bouldering]] artificial walls with bolted holds in a climbing gym.
* [[Ladder|Ladder climbing]]: Climbing ladders for exercise. This may involve climbing up and down the underside of a ladder, or along a horizontally aligned ladder or 'monkey bars'. The ladder may be climbed going forwards, backwards, or sideways.
* [[Lumberjack]] tree-trimming and competitive tree-trunk or pole climbing for speed using spikes and belts.
* [[Mallakhamba]]: A traditional Indian sport which combines climbing a pole or rope with the performance of aerial [[yoga as exercise|yoga]] and gymnastics.
* [[Mountaineering]]: Ascending mountains for sport or recreation. It often involves rock and/or ice climbing (Alpine climbing).
* [[Pole climbing]]: Climbing poles and masts without equipment.
* [[Rock climbing]]: Ascending rock formations, often using climbing shoes and a [[chalk bag]]. Equipment such as ropes, bolts, nuts, hexes and camming devices are normally employed, either as a safeguard or for artificial aid.
* [[Rope access]]: Industrial climbing, usually [[abseiling]], as an alternative to [[scaffolding]] for short works on exposed structures.
* [[Rope climbing]]: Climbing a short, thick rope for speed. Not to be confused with ''roped climbing'', as in rock or ice climbing.
* [[Scrambling]] which includes easy rock climbing, and is considered part of [[hillwalking]].
*[[Stair Climbing]] ascending elevation via stairs.  
* [[Sport climbing]] is a form of [[rock climbing]] that relies on permanent [[anchor (climbing)|anchors]] fixed to the rock, and possibly [[bolt (climbing)|bolt]]s, for [[protection (climbing)|protection]], (in contrast with [[traditional climbing]], where the rock is typically devoid of fixed anchors and bolts, and where climbers must place removable protection as they climb).&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;
* [[Top rope|Top roping]]: Ascending a rock climbing route protected by a rope anchored at the top and protected by a [[belay]]er below&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.theboardroomclimbing.com/faq-items/what-is-top-roping/|title=What is top roping?|website=The Boardroom Climbing|language=en-US|access-date=2019-11-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Traditional climbing]] (more casually known as Trad climbing) is a form of climbing without fixed anchors and bolts. Climbers place removable protection such as camming devices, nuts, and other passive and active protection that holds the rope to the rock (via the use of carabiners and webbing/slings) in the event of a fall and/or when weighted by a climber.
* [[Tower|Tower climbing]]: Climbing up the inside of a narrow tower by applying pressure to the walls with the hands and feet. 
* [[Solo climbing]]: Solo climbing or soloing is a style of climbing in which the climber climbs alone, without somebody [[belaying]] them. When free soloing, an error usually is fatal as no belay systems are being used. Soloing can also be self-belayed, hence minimizing the risks.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.evorock.com/blog/2016/07/13/3694/|title=What's the Difference Between &quot;Free Climbing&quot; and &quot;Free Soloing?&quot;|date=2016-07-13|website=EVO Rock|language=en-US|access-date=2019-11-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Tree climbing]]: Recreationally ascending trees using ropes and other protective equipment.
* A [[tower climber]] is a professional who climbs broadcasting or [[telecommunication tower]]s or masts for maintenance or repair.

Rock, ice and tree climbing all usually utilize ropes for safety or aid. Pole climbing and rope climbing were among the first exercises to be included in the origins of modern gymnastics in the late 18th century and early 19th century.

==Film==
{{main|Mountain film}}
Climbing has been the subject of both film and documentary film with notable examples being ''[[Touching the Void (film)|Touching the Void]]'', ''[[Everest (2015 film)|Everest]]'' and ''[[Free Solo]]''.

== See also ==

* [[Aid climbing]]
* [[Clean climbing]]
* [[Climbing clubs]]
* [[Climbing wall]]
* [[Climbing equipment]]
* [[:Category:Climbing organizations|Climbing organizations]]
* [[Fall factor]]
* [[List of climbers]] – notable rock and ice climbers
* [[List of climbing topics]]
* [[Glossary of climbing terms]]
* [[Glossary of knots common in climbing]]
* [[Outdoor education]]
* [[Outdoor activity]]
* [[Running belay]]
* [[Parkour]]
* [[Scrambling]]
* [[Speed climbing]]

==References==

{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
*{{dmoz|Recreation/Climbing}}
{{portal|Climbing}}
{{commons category|Climbing}}

{{Climbing navbox}}
{{Adventure travel}}
{{Extreme sports}}
{{Orienteering}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Climbing| ]]</text>
      <sha1>bz18z7nszp7f1coom0wrrnjifh78ga8</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
