  <page>
    <title>Bradycardia</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5872</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941852066</id>
      <parentid>939849717</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-21T01:57:06Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Citation bot</username>
        <id>7903804</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Add: doi. Removed URL that duplicated unique identifier. | You can [[WP:UCB|use this bot]] yourself. [[WP:DBUG|Report bugs here]]. | Activated by [[User:Headbomb]] | via #UCB_webform</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Heart rate that is below the normal range}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}
{{Infobox medical condition (new)
 | name           = Bradycardia
 | synonyms       = bradyarrhythmia, brachycardia
 | image          = Sinus bradycardia lead2.svg
 | caption        = [[Sinus bradycardia]] seen in lead II with a heart rate of about 50
 | field          = [[Cardiology]]
 | pronounce      = {{IPAc-en|ˌ|b|r|æ|d|ɪ|ˈ|k|ɑr|d|i|ə}}
}}
'''Bradycardia''' is a condition typically defined wherein an individual has a resting [[heart rate]] of under 60 [[Heart rate|beats per minute]] (BPM) in adults.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Types of Arrhythmia|url=http://www.nhlbi.nih.gov/health/health-topics/topics/arr/types|accessdate=19 March 2015|date=July 1, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bradycardia typically does not cause symptoms until the rate drops below 50 BPM. When symptomatic, it may cause fatigue, weakness, dizziness, sweating, and at very low rates, [[Syncope (medicine)|fainting]].&lt;ref name=SINUS-BRADYCARDIA&gt;[http://www.emedicine.com/emerg/topic534.htm Sinus Bradycardia] – eMedicine&lt;/ref&gt;

During sleep, a slow heartbeat with rates around 40–50&amp;nbsp;BPM is common, and is considered normal.  Highly trained [[sportsperson|athlete]]s  may also have [[athletic heart syndrome]], a very slow resting heart rate that occurs as a sport adaptation and helps prevent [[tachycardia]] during training.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Baggish|first=Aaron L.|last2=Wood|first2=Malissa J.|date=2011-06-14|title=Athlete's heart and cardiovascular care of the athlete: scientific and clinical update|journal=Circulation|volume=123|issue=23|pages=2723–2735|doi=10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.110.981571|issn=1524-4539|pmid=21670241}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The term &quot;relative bradycardia&quot; is used to refer to a heart rate that, although not actually below 60&amp;nbsp;BPM, is still considered too slow for the individual's current medical condition.

The word &quot;bradycardia&quot; is from the [[Ancient Greek|Greek]] βραδύς, ''bradys'' &quot;slow&quot;, and καρδία, ''kardia'', &quot;heart&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Wtp5lg6UVygC&amp;pg=PA371 | title=Design and Development of Medical Electronic Instrumentation | publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons | author=Prutchi, David | year=2005 | pages=371| isbn=9780471681830 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Classification==
[[File:Blausen 0099 bradycardia.png|thumb|Illustration comparing the EKGs of a healthy person (''top'') and a person with bradycardia (''bottom''): The points on the heart where the EKG signals are measured are also shown.]]

===Sinus===
{{see also|Sinus bradycardia|Sick sinus syndrome}}
Atrial bradycardias are divided into three types. The first, [[respiratory sinus arrhythmia]], is usually found in young and healthy adults. Heart rate increases during inhalation and decreases during exhalation.  This is thought to be caused by changes in the [[vagal]] tone during respiration.&lt;ref name=HN&gt;{{cite book|title=Harwood-Nuss' Clinical Practice of Emergency Medicine|editor=Allan B. Wolfson |year=2005 |edition=4th |page=260 |isbn=978-0-7817-5125-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;  If the decrease during exhalation drops the heart rate below 60&amp;nbsp;bpm on each breath, this type of bradycardia is usually deemed benign and a sign of good [[autonomic tone]].

The second, sinus bradycardia, is a [[sinus rhythm]] of less than 60&amp;nbsp;BPM. It is a common condition found in both healthy individuals and those considered well-[[Athletic heart syndrome|conditioned athletes]]. Studies have found that 50–85% of conditioned athletes have [[benign]] sinus bradycardia, as compared to 23% of the general population studied.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Ward|first=Bryan G.|last2=Rippe |first2=J.M.|title=Athletic Heart Syndrome|publisher=Clinical Sports Medicine|year=1992|page=259|chapter=11}}&lt;/ref&gt; The heart muscle of athletes has become conditioned to have a higher stroke volume, so requires fewer contractions to circulate the same volume of blood.&lt;ref name=HN/&gt;

The third, [[sick sinus syndrome]], covers conditions that include severe sinus bradycardia, sinoatrial block, sinus arrest, and bradycardia-tachycardia syndrome (atrial fibrillation, flutter, and [[paroxysmal supraventricular tachycardia]]).&lt;ref name=HN/&gt;

===Atrioventricular nodal===
{{See also|Junctional rhythm}}
An atrioventricular nodal bradycardia or AV junction rhythm is usually caused by the absence of the electrical impulse from the [[sinus node]]. This usually appears on an [[EKG]] with a normal [[QRS complex]] accompanied with an inverted P wave either before, during, or after the QRS complex.&lt;ref name=HN/&gt;

An AV junctional escape is a delayed heartbeat originating from an [[Ectopic beat|ectopic]] focus somewhere in the [[AV junction]]. It occurs when the rate of [[depolarization]] of the SA node falls below the rate of the AV node.&lt;ref name=HN/&gt; This [[Cardiac dysrhythmia|dysrhythmia]] also may occur when the electrical impulses from the SA node fail to reach the AV node because of SA or AV block.&lt;ref name=AHA&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.americanheart.org/presenter.jhtml?identifier=746|title=AV Junctional Rhythm Disturbances (for Professionals)|date=4 December 2008|publisher=American Heart Association|accessdate=15 December 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; This is a protective mechanism for the heart, to compensate for an SA node that is no longer handling the pacemaking activity, and is one of a series of backup sites that can take over pacemaker function when the SA node fails to do so. This would present with a longer [[PR interval]]. A junctional escape complex is a normal response that may result from excessive vagal tone on the SA node. Pathological causes include sinus bradycardia, sinus arrest, sinus exit block, or AV block.&lt;ref name=HN/&gt;

===Ventricular===
{{See also|Atrioventricular block}}
Atrioventricular bradycardia, also known as ventricular escape rhythm or idioventricular rhythm, is a heart rate of less than 50 BPM. This is a safety mechanism when a lack of electrical impulse or stimuli from the atrium occurs.&lt;ref name=HN/&gt; Impulses originating within or below the [[bundle of His]] in the [[atrioventricular node]] will produce a wide QRS complex with heart rates between 20 and 40 BPM. Those above the bundle of His, also known as junctional, will typically range between 40 and 60 BPM with a narrow QRS complex.&lt;ref name=&quot;merck&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.merck.com/mmpe/sec07/ch075/ch075a.html|title=Arrhythmias and Conduction Disorders|date=January 2008|work=The merck Manuals: Online Medical Library|publisher=Merck Sharp and Dohme Corp|accessdate=16 December 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=ajcc/&gt; In a third-degree heart block, about 61% take place at the bundle branch-Purkinje system, 21% at the AV node, and 15% at the bundle of His.&lt;ref name=ajcc&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Adams MG, Pelter MM |title=Ventricular escape rhythms |journal=American Journal of Critical Care |volume=12 |issue=5 |pages=477–8 |date=September 2003 |pmid=14503433 |doi=10.4037/ajcc2003.12.5.477 }}&lt;/ref&gt; AV block may be ruled out with an EKG indicating &quot;a 1:1 relationship between P waves and QRS complexes.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;merck&quot;/&gt; Ventricular bradycardias occurs with sinus bradycardia, sinus arrest, and AV block. Treatment often consists of the administration of [[atropine]] and cardiac pacing.&lt;ref name=HN/&gt;

===Infantile===
For infants, bradycardia is defined as a heart rate less than 100&amp;nbsp;BPM (normal is around 120–160). Premature babies are more likely than full-term babies to have apnea and bradycardia spells; their cause is not clearly understood. The spells may be related to centers inside the brain that regulate breathing which may not be fully developed. Touching the baby gently or rocking the incubator slightly will almost always get the baby to start breathing again, which increases the heart rate. Medications ([[theophylline]] or [[caffeine]]) can be used to treat these spells in babies if necessary. [[Neonatal intensive-care unit]] (NICU) standard practice is to electronically monitor the heart and lungs for this reason.

==Causes==
This [[arrhythmia]] can be underlain by several causes, which are best divided into cardiac and noncardiac causes.
Noncardiac causes are usually secondary, and can involve [[recreational drug use]] or [[drug abuse|abuse]]; [[metabolism|metabolic]] or [[endocrine]] issues, especially in the [[hypothyroidism|thyroid]]; an [[electrolyte]] imbalance; [[:Category:Neurology|neurologic]] factors; [[autonomic reflex]]es; situational factors such as prolonged [[bed rest]]; and [[autoimmune|autoimmunity]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Ye|first=Fan|last2=Hatahet|first2=Mohamad|last3=Youniss|first3=Mohamed A.|last4=Toklu|first4=Hale Z.|last5=Mazza|first5=Joseph J.|last6=Yale|first6=Steven|date=June 2018|title=The Clinical Significance of Relative Bradycardia|journal=WMJ|volume=117|issue=2|pages=73–78|issn=1098-1861|pmid=30048576}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Cardiac causes include acute or chronic [[ischemic heart disease]], vascular [[heart disease]], valvular heart disease, or degenerative primary electrical disease. Ultimately, the causes act by three mechanisms: depressed [[automaticity]] of the heart, conduction block, or escape pacemakers and rhythms.

In general, two types of problems result in bradycardias: disorders of the [[sinoatrial node]] (SA node), and disorders of the [[atrioventricular node]] (AV node).

With sinus node dysfunction (sometimes called [[sick sinus syndrome]]), there may be disordered [[automaticity]] or impaired conduction of the impulse from the sinus node into the surrounding atrial tissue (an &quot;exit block&quot;). Second-degree sinoatrial blocks can be detected only by use of a 12-lead EKG.&lt;ref name=NCBI&gt;{{cite journal|pmid=16308110|title=Bradydysrhythmias and atrioventricular conduction blocks|last=Ufberg |first=JW |last2=Clark |first2=JS|date=February 2006|doi=10.1016/j.emc.2005.08.006|volume=24|issue=1|journal=Emerg. Med. Clin. North Am. |pages=1–9, v}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is difficult and sometimes impossible to assign a mechanism to any particular bradycardia, but the underlying mechanism is not clinically relevant to treatment, which is the same in both cases of sick sinus syndrome: a permanent [[artificial pacemaker|pacemaker]].

Atrioventricular conduction disturbances (AV block; [[First-degree AV block|primary AV block]], [[Second-degree AV block|secondary type I AV block]], [[Second-degree AV block|secondary type II AV block]], [[Third-degree AV block|tertiary AV block]]) may result from impaired conduction in the AV node, or anywhere below it, such as in the [[bundle of His]]. The clinical relevance pertaining to AV blocks is greater than that of sinoatrial blocks.&lt;ref name=NCBI/&gt;

Patients with bradycardia have likely acquired it, as opposed to having it [[congenital]]ly. Bradycardia is more common in older patients.

Beta-blocker medicines also can slow the heart rate and decrease how forcefully the heart contracts. Beta blockers may slow the heart rate to a dangerous level if prescribed with [[calcium channel blocker]]-type medications.

Bradycardia is also part of the [[mammalian diving reflex]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Michael Panneton2013&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Michael Panneton|first1=W.|title=The Mammalian Diving Response: An Enigmatic Reflex to Preserve Life?|journal=Physiology|volume=28|issue=5|year=2013|pages=284–297|issn=1548-9213|doi=10.1152/physiol.00020.2013|pmid=23997188|pmc=3768097}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Diagnosis==
A diagnosis of bradycardia in adults is based on a heart rate less than 60 BPM.  This is determined usually either by palpation or [[electrocardiography]].

If symptoms occur, a determination of [[Electrolyte#Physiological importance|electrolytes]] may be helpful in determining the underlying cause.

===Definition===
Bradycardia in an adult is any heart rate less than {{nowrap|60 beats per minute}} [[Heart rate|(BPM)]], although symptoms usually manifest only for heart rates less than 50 BPM.&lt;ref name=ACLS2010/&gt;

==Management==
The treatment of bradycardia is dependent on whether or not the person is stable or unstable.&lt;ref name=ACLS2010/&gt; If [[oxygen saturations]] are low, supplemental oxygen should be provided.

===Stable===
Emergency treatment is not needed if the person is asymptomatic or minimally symptomatic.&lt;ref name=ACLS2010&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Neumar RW, Otto CW, Link MS |title=Part 8: adult advanced cardiovascular life support: 2010 American Heart Association Guidelines for Cardiopulmonary Resuscitation and Emergency Cardiovascular Care |journal=Circulation |volume=122 |issue=18 Suppl 3 |pages=S729–67 |date=November 2010 |pmid=20956224 |doi=10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.110.970988 |url=|display-authors=etal}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Unstable===
If a person is unstable, the initial recommended treatment is intravenous [[atropine]].&lt;ref name=ACLS2010/&gt; Doses less than 0.5&amp;nbsp;mg should not be used, as this may further decrease the rate.&lt;ref name=ACLS2010/&gt; If this is not effective, intravenous [[inotrope]] infusion ([[dopamine (medication)|dopamine]], [[epinephrine]]) or [[transcutaneous pacing]] should be used.&lt;ref name=ACLS2010/&gt; [[Transvenous pacing]] may be required if the cause of the bradycardia is not rapidly reversible.&lt;ref name=ACLS2010/&gt;

In children, giving oxygen, supporting their breathing, and [[chest compressions]] are recommended.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=de Caen|first1=AR|last2=Berg|first2=MD|last3=Chameides|first3=L|last4=Gooden|first4=CK|last5=Hickey|first5=RW|last6=Scott|first6=HF|last7=Sutton|first7=RM|last8=Tijssen|first8=JA|last9=Topjian|first9=A|last10=van der Jagt|first10=ÉW|last11=Schexnayder|first11=SM|last12=Samson|first12=RA|title=Part 12: Pediatric Advanced Life Support: 2015 American Heart Association Guidelines Update for Cardiopulmonary Resuscitation and Emergency Cardiovascular Care.|journal=Circulation|date=3 November 2015|volume=132|issue=18 Suppl 2|pages=S526–42|pmid=26473000|pmc=6191296|doi=10.1161/cir.0000000000000266}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Atkins|first1=DL|last2=Berger|first2=S|last3=Duff|first3=JP|last4=Gonzales|first4=JC|last5=Hunt|first5=EA|last6=Joyner|first6=BL|last7=Meaney|first7=PA|last8=Niles|first8=DE|last9=Samson|first9=RA|last10=Schexnayder|first10=SM|title=Part 11: Pediatric Basic Life Support and Cardiopulmonary Resuscitation Quality: 2015 American Heart Association Guidelines Update for Cardiopulmonary Resuscitation and Emergency Cardiovascular Care.|journal=Circulation|date=3 November 2015|volume=132|issue=18 Suppl 2|pages=S519–25|pmid=26472999|doi=10.1161/cir.0000000000000265}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Epidemiology==
{{Expand section|1=discussion regarding the threshold of 60 bpm|section=1|date=December 2018}}
CDC reported in 2011 that in the U.S. 15.2% of adult males and 6.9% of adult females had clinically-defined bradycardia (a [[resting pulse rate]] below 60 beats per minute).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/data/nhsr/nhsr041.pdf |title=Resting Pulse Rate Reference Data for Children, Adolescents, and Adults: United States, 1999–2008 |date=August 24, 2011 |work=National Health Statistics Reports |number=41 |publisher=Centers for Disease Control |accessdate=December 15, 2018 |author=Yechiam Ostchega|display-authors=et al}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Society and culture==
===Records===
* Daniel Green holds the world record for the slowest heartbeat in a healthy human, with a heart rate measured in 2014 of 26 BPM.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.worldrecordacademy.com/medical/slowest_heart_rate_Daniel_Green_breaks_Guinness_World_Records_record_214157.html |title=Slowest heart rate: Daniel Green breaks Guinness World Records record |date=29 November 2014 |work=World Record Academy |accessdate=5 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Martin Brady holds the Guinness world record for the slowest heart rate with a certified rate over a minute duration of 27 BPM.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.guinnessworldrecords.com/world-records/lowest-heart-rate |title=Lowest heart rate |date= |work=Guinness World Records |accessdate=5 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Professional cyclist [[Miguel Indurain]] had, during his career, a resting heart rate of 28&amp;nbsp;BPM.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |first=Stefan |last=Lovgren |date=August 20, 2004 |title=Olympic Gold Begins With Good Genes, Experts Say |work=National Geographic News |url=http://news.nationalgeographic.com/news/2004/08/0820_040820_olympics_athletes.html |accessdate=September 8, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* {{annotated link|Bezold–Jarisch reflex}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Medical resources
 | DiseasesDB     = 
 | ICD10          = {{ICD10|R|00|1|r|00}}
 | ICD9           = {{ICD9|427.81}}, {{ICD9|659.7}}, {{ICD9|785.9}}, {{ICD9|779.81}}
 | ICDO           = 
 | OMIM           = 
 | MedlinePlus    = 
 | eMedicineSubj  = 
 | eMedicineTopic = 
 | MeshID         = D001919
}}
{{Heart diseases}}
{{Cardiovascular system symptoms and signs}}

[[Category:Cardiac arrhythmia]]
[[Category:Symptoms and signs: Cardiac]]</text>
      <sha1>4u2noct1q2lpspwgq8bh8nxolhrq8wq</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
