  <page>
    <title>Declaration of Arbroath</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8274</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941660884</id>
      <parentid>941649796</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-19T23:15:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>92.1.141.95</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 941649796 by [[Special:Contributions/92.1.141.95|92.1.141.95]] ([[User talk:92.1.141.95|talk]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{ref improve|date=April 2018}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=April 2018}}
 [[File:Declaration of arbroath.jpg|thumb|300px|The '[[Tyninghame]]' copy of the Declaration from 1320 AD]]
The '''Declaration of Arbroath''' ({{lang-sco|Declaration o Aiberbrothock}}; {{lang-la|Declaratio Arbroathis}}; {{lang-gd|Tiomnadh Bhruis}}) is a declaration of [[Scottish independence]], made in 1320. It is in the form of a letter in [[Latin]] submitted to [[Pope John XXII]], dated 6 April 1320, intended to confirm [[Scotland]]'s status as an [[sovereign state|independent, sovereign state]] and defending Scotland's right to use military action when unjustly attacked.

Generally believed to have been written in the [[Arbroath Abbey]] by [[Bernard of Kilwinning]], then [[Lord Chancellor of Scotland|Chancellor of Scotland]] and [[Abbot of Arbroath]],{{sfn|Scott|1999|p=196}} and sealed by fifty-one [[magnate]]s and [[nobles]], the letter is the sole survivor of three created at the time. The others were a letter from the [[King of Scots]], [[Robert I of Scotland|Robert I]], and a letter from four Scottish bishops which all made similar points.

== Overview ==
The Declaration was part of a broader diplomatic campaign, which sought to assert Scotland's position as an independent kingdom,{{sfn|Barrow|1984}} rather than its being a feudal land controlled by England's Norman kings, as well as lift the [[excommunication]] of [[Robert I of Scotland|Robert the Bruce]].{{sfn|Lynch|1992}} The pope had recognised [[Edward I of England]]'s claim to overlordship of Scotland in 1305 and Bruce was excommunicated by the Pope for murdering [[John III Comyn, Lord of Badenoch|John Comyn]] before the altar in Greyfriars Church in Dumfries in 1306.{{sfn|Lynch|1992}}

The Declaration made a number of points: that Scotland had always been independent, indeed for longer than England; that Edward I of England had unjustly attacked Scotland and perpetrated atrocities; that Robert the Bruce had delivered the Scottish nation from this peril; and, most controversially, that the independence of Scotland was the prerogative of the Scottish people, rather than the King of Scots. (However this should be taken in the context of the time - ‘Scottish People’ refers to the Scottish nobility, rather than commoners.) In fact it stated that the nobility would choose someone else to be king if Bruce proved to be unfit in maintaining Scotland's independence.

==Debates==
Some have interpreted this last point as an early expression of '[[popular sovereignty]]'{{sfn|McLean|2005|p=247}} &amp;ndash; that government is contractual and that kings can be chosen by the community rather than by God alone. Modern Scottish nationalists point to the  “Declaration&quot; as evidence of the long-term persistence of the Scots as a distinct national community, giving a very early date for the emergence of [[nationalism]]. However, &quot;the overwhelming majority of academics challenge this vision. Scholars point out that definitions change with time. The meaning ascribed to words similar to nation during the ancient and medieval periods was often quite different than it is today.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|editor=Mark Bevir|title=Encyclopedia of Political Theory|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=WfFWDAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA921|year=2010|publisher=SAGE Publications|page=921|isbn=9781506332727}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It has also been argued that the Declaration was not a statement of popular sovereignty (and that its signatories would have had no such concept){{sfn|Kellas|1998|p=35}} but a statement of royal propaganda supporting Bruce's faction.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Fugelso|first=Karl|title=Memory and medievalism|year=2007|publisher=D. S. Brewer|isbn=978-1-84384-115-9|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=m542R9ygB3QC&amp;pg=PA138|page=138}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=McCracken-Flesher|first=Caroline|title=Culture, nation, and the new Scottish parliament |year=2006|publisher=Bucknell University Press|isbn=978-0-8387-5547-1|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=YInDkqRVQOwC&amp;pg=PA246|page=246}}&lt;/ref&gt; A justification had to be given for the rejection of [[John of Scotland|King John Balliol]] in whose name [[William Wallace]] and [[Andrew de Moray]] had rebelled in 1297. The reason given in the Declaration is that Bruce was able to defend Scotland from English aggression whereas, by implication, King John could not.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Robert Allan Houston|author2=William Knox|author3=National Museums of Scotland|title=The new Penguin history of Scotland: from the earliest times to the present day|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=HhQTAQAAIAAJ|year=2001|publisher=Allen Lane}}{{page needed|date=April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{quote|To this man, in as much as he saved our people, and for upholding our freedom, we are bound by right as much as by his merits, and choose to follow him in all that he does.}}
Whatever the true motive, the idea of a contract between King and people was advanced to the Pope as a justification for Bruce's coronation whilst John de Balliol still lived in Papal custody.{{sfn|Barrow|1984}}

==Text==
For the full text in Latin and a translation in English, See [[s:Translation:Declaration_of_Arbroath|Declaration of Arbroath]] on [[WikiSource]].

==Signatories==
There are 39 names—eight [[earl]]s and thirty one [[baron]]s—at the start of the document, all of whom may have had their seals appended, probably over the space of some weeks and months, with nobles sending in their seals to be used. On the extant copy of the Declaration there are only 19 seals, and of those 19 people only 12 are named within the document. It is thought likely that at least 11 more seals than the original 39 might have been appended.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = The seals on the Declaration of Arbroath | publisher = National Archives of Scotland  | url = http://www.nas.gov.uk/about/doaSeals.asp | accessdate = 2 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Declaration was then taken to the [[papal court]] at [[Avignon Papacy|Avignon]] by [[Alexander_de_Kininmund_(died_1380)|Bishop Kininmund]], [[Adam_de_Gordon,_Lord_of_Gordon|Sir Adam Gordon]] and Sir Odard de Maubuisson.{{sfn|Barrow|1984}}
{{multiple image|caption_align=center
 | align = right
 | direction = vertical
 | width = 200
 | image1 = Declaration of Arbroath translation 1.JPG
 | caption1 =
 | image2 = Declaration of Arbroath translation 2.JPG
 | caption2 = The most-cited passages of the Declaration, translated from the Latin original as displayed on the walls of the [[National Museum of Scotland]].
}}

The Pope heeded the arguments contained in the Declaration, influenced by the offer of support from the Scots for his long-desired crusade if they no longer had to fear English invasion. He exhorted Edward II in a letter to make peace with the Scots, but the following year was again persuaded by the English to take their side and issued six bulls to that effect.{{sfn|Scott|1999|p=197}}
Not until eight years later, on 1 March 1328 the new [[English king]], [[Edward III of England|Edward III]] signed a [[peace treaty]] between Scotland and [[Kingdom of England|England]], the [[Treaty of Edinburgh-Northampton]]. In this treaty, which was in effect for five years until 1333,  Edward renounced all English claims to Scotland. Eight months later, in October 1328, the interdict on Scotland, and the excommunication of its king, were removed by the Pope.{{sfn|Scott|1999|p=225}}

==Manuscript copies==
The original copy of the Declaration that was sent to Avignon is lost. A copy of the Declaration survives among Scotland's state papers, measuring 540mm wide by 675mm long (including the seals), it is held by the [[National Archives of Scotland]] in [[Edinburgh]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nas.gov.uk/about/090401.asp National Archives of Scotland website feature]&lt;/ref&gt; The most widely known English language translation was made by [[Sir James Fergusson, 8th Baronet|Sir James Fergusson]], formerly [[Keeper of the Records of Scotland]], from text that he reconstructed using this extant copy and early copies of the original draft. 

[[G. W. S. Barrow]] has shown that one passage in particular, often quoted from the Fergusson translation, was carefully written using different parts of ''[[The Conspiracy of Catiline]]'' by the Roman author, [[Sallust]] (86–35 BC) as the direct source:&lt;ref&gt;G. W. S. Barrow, &quot;The idea of freedom&quot;, ''Innes Review'' 30 (1979) 16–34 (reprinted in G. W. S. Barrow, ''Scotland and its Neighbours in the Middle Ages'' (London, Hambledon, 1992), chapter 1)&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|...&amp;nbsp;for, as long as but a hundred of us remain alive, never will we on any conditions be brought under English rule. It is in truth not for glory, nor riches, nor honours that we are fighting, but for freedom – for that alone, which no honest man gives up but with life itself.}}

==List of signatories==

Listed below are the signatories of the Declaration of Arbroath in 1320.{{cn|date=April 2018}}&lt;!--need citation for the list of signers--&gt; 

The declaration itself is written in Latin. It uses the Latin versions of the signatories' titles, and in some cases, the spelling of names has changed over the years.  This list generally uses the titles of the signatories' Wikipedia biographies.

*[[Donnchadh IV, Earl of Fife|Duncan, Earl of Fife]] (changed sides in 1332)
*[[Thomas Randolph, 1st Earl of Moray|Thomas Randolph, Earl of Moray]] (nephew and important supporter of King Robert although briefly fought for the English after being captured by them)
*[[Patrick V, Earl of March|Patrick Dunbar, Earl of March]] (or Earl of Dunbar) (changed sides several times)
*[[Maol Íosa IV, Earl of Strathearn|Malise, Earl of Strathearn]] (King Robert loyalist) 
*[[Maol Choluim II, Earl of Lennox|Malcolm, Earl of Lennox]] (King Robert loyalist)
*[[Uilleam II, Earl of Ross|William, Earl of Ross]] (earlier betrayed King Robert's female relatives to the English)
*[[Magnús Jónsson, Earl of Orkney]]
*[[William de Moravia, 3rd Earl of Sutherland|William de Moravia, Earl of Sutherland]]
*[[Walter Stewart, 6th High Steward of Scotland|Walter, High Steward of Scotland]] (King Robert loyalist)
*[[William II de Soules|William de Soules]], Lord of Liddesdale and Butler of Scotland (later imprisoned for plotting against the King) 
*[[James Douglas, Lord of Douglas|Sir James Douglas]], Lord of Douglas (one of King Robert's leading loyalist)
*[[Roger de Mowbray (d. 1320)|Roger de Mowbray]], Lord of Barnbougle and Dalmeny (later imprisoned for plotting against King Robert)
*[[David, Lord of Brechin]] (later executed for plotting against King Robert)
*[[David de Graham of Kincardine]]
*[[Ingram de Umfraville]] (fought on the English side at Bannockburn but then changed sides to support King Robert)
*[[John de Menteith]], guardian of the earldom of Menteith (earlier betrayed William Wallace to the English)
*[[Alexander Fraser of Touchfraser and Cowie]] 
*[[Gilbert II de la Hay|Gilbert de la Hay]], Constable of Scotland (King Robert loyalist) 
*[[Robert II Keith, Marischal of Scotland|Robert Keith, Marischal of Scotland]] (King Robert loyalist) 
*[[Henry St Clair|Henry St Clair of Rosslyn]]
*[[John de Graham (d. 1337)|John de Graham, Lord of Dalkeith, Abercorn &amp; Eskdale]]
*[[David Lindsay of Crawford]]
*[[William Oliphant, Lord of Aberdalgie|William Oliphant, Lord of Aberdalgie and Dupplin]] (briefly fought for the English) 
*[[Patrick de Graham of Lovat]]
*[[John de Fenton|John de Fenton, Lord of Baikie and Beaufort]]
*[[William de Abernethy, 2nd Baron of Saltoun|William de Abernethy of Saltoun]]
*[[David Wemyss (d. 1332)|David Wemyss of Wemyss]]
*William Mushet
*Fergus of [[Ardrossan]]
*[[Eustace de Maxwell|Eustace Maxwell of Caerlaverock]]
*William Ramsay 
*[[William de Monte Alto (d.1327)|William de Monte Alto]], Lord of Ferne
*Alan Murray
*[[Domhnall mac Cailein|Donald Campbell]]
*John Cameron
*[[Reginald le Chen (d.1345)|Reginald le Chen]], Lord of Inverugie and Duffus
*[[Alexander Seton (Governor of Berwick)|Alexander Seton]] 
*[[Sir Andrew de Leslie|Andrew de Leslie]]
*Alexander Straiton

In addition, the names of the following do not appear in the document's text, but their names are written on seal tags and their seals are present:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nas.gov.uk/about/declarationArbroathSeals.asp|publisher=[[National Archives of Scotland]]|title=Declaration of Arbroath - Seals}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*Alexander de Lamberton (became a supporter of [[Edward Balliol]] after the [[Battle of Dupplin Moor]], 1332)
*[[Edward Keith]] (subsequently [[Marischal of Scotland]]; d. 1346)
*[[Arthur Campbell (Clan Arthur)|Arthur Campbell]] (Bruce loyalist)
*Thomas de Menzies (Bruce loyalist)
*John de Inchmartin (became a supporter of [[Edward Balliol]] after the [[Battle of Dupplin Moor]], 1332; d. after 1334)
*John Duraunt
*Thomas de Morham

== Legacy ==
US Senate Resolution 155 of 10 November 1997 states that the Declaration of Arbroath, the Scottish Declaration of Independence [sic], was signed on 6 April 1320 and the American Declaration of Independence was modelled on that inspirational document.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = Congressional Record Senate Articles|url = https://www.congress.gov/congressional-record/1997/11/10/senate-section/article/s12478-1?q=%257B%2522search%2522%253A%255B%2522resolution+155+tartan%2522%255D%257D&amp;resultIndex=1|website = www.congress.gov|access-date = 15 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, although [[United States Declaration of Independence#Influences and legal status|this influence is accepted by some historians]], it is disputed by others.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url = |title = 'For Freedom Alone': Review|last = Neville|first = Cynthia|date = April 2005|journal = The Scottish Historical Review|volume=84|doi = |pmid = |access-date = }}&lt;/ref&gt; Even advocates of the link concede that it is speculative and not based on any verifiable sources.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Cowan|first=Edward J.|title=For Freedom Alone|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=9wHWoAEACAAJ|year=2014|publisher=Birlinn General|isbn=978-1-78027-256-6}}{{page needed|date=April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2016 the Declaration of Arbroath was placed on [[UNESCO]]'s [[Memory of the World Programme|Memory of the World register]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Declaration of Arbroath awarded Unesco status|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-scotland-tayside-central-36712780|website=www.bbc.co.uk|accessdate=5 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

This year the Scots are celebrating the 700th anniversary of the Declaration of Arbroath with events of various kinds.

== See also ==
{{Campaignbox First War of Scottish Independence}}
{{Campaignbox Second War of Scottish Independence}}
* [[Declaration of independence]]
* [[Claim of Right 1989]]
* [[Barons' Letter of 1301]], refutation of Papal claim to Scottish suzerainty by English barons

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

==Sources==
*{{cite book|last=Barrow|first=G. W. S. |title=Robert the Bruce and the Scottish Identity|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=PQN-AAAACAAJ|year=1984|publisher=Saltire Society|isbn=978-0-85411-027-8|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Kellas|first=James G.|title=The politics of nationalism and ethnicity|year=1998|publisher=Palgrave|isbn=978-0-312-21553-8|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=m542R9ygB3QC&amp;pg=PA35|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Lynch|first=Michael|title=Scotland: A New History|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=x27pG_TShegC|year=1992|publisher=Pimlico|isbn=978-0-7126-9893-1|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=McLean|first=Iain|title=State of the Union: Unionism and the Alternatives in the United Kingdom Since 1707|year=2005|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-925820-8|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=H2u9uOEYruYC&amp;pg=PA247|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Scott|first=Ronald McNair|title=Robert the Bruce: King of Scots|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Zr2lgY1c2JwC|year=1999|publisher=Canongate Books|isbn=978-0-86241-616-4|ref=harv}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category-inline|Declaration of Arbroath}}
{{wikisource|Translation:Declaration of Arbroath}}
* [http://www.nas.gov.uk/about/090401.asp Declaration of Arbroath] on [[National Archives of Scotland]] website (includes full Latin text and English translation)

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Declaration Of Arbroath}}
[[Category:Declarations of independence|Arbroath]]
[[Category:National liberation movements]]
[[Category:Political history of Scotland]]
[[Category:1320 in Scotland]]
[[Category:Wars of Scottish Independence|Arbroath, Declaration of]]
[[Category:Scottish independence]]
[[Category:Avignon Papacy]]
[[Category:1320s in law]]
[[Category:Popular sovereignty]]
[[Category:1328 establishments in Scotland]]
[[Category:1320]]
[[Category:Medieval documents of Scotland]]
[[Category:Elective monarchy]]
[[Category:Arbroath]]</text>
      <sha1>o20uet01dzpuk31s45d8no0zinao398</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
