  <page>
    <title>Deutschlandlied</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8203</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942268969</id>
      <parentid>940711357</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-23T17:36:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>184.146.118.36</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Melody */ 'bars' is another, more widely known, term on the east coast of the Atlantic</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|Über Alles}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2016}}
{{Infobox anthem
 | title         = &quot;Das Lied der Deutschen&quot;
 | english_title = &quot;The Song of the Germans&quot;
 | image         = Deutschlandlied.jpg
 | image_size    =
 | alt           =
 | caption       = [[Facsimile]] of Hoffmann von Fallersleben's manuscript of &quot;{{Lang|de|Das Lied der Deutschen|italic=no}}&quot;
 | prefix        = National
 | country       = [[Germany]]{{Efn|Only the third verse is designated as the official national anthem.}}
----
Former national anthem of the [[Weimar Republic]], [[Nazi Germany]]{{Efn|The first verse combined with the [[Horst Wessel Lied]].}}
 | alt_title     = &quot;{{Lang|de|Deutschlandlied|italic=no}}&quot;
 | en_alt_title  = &quot;The Song of Germany&quot;
 | author        = [[August Heinrich Hoffmann von Fallersleben]]
 | lyrics_date   = 1841
 | composer      = [[Joseph Haydn]]
 | music_date    = 1797
 | adopted       = 1922
 | until         = 1945
 | readopted=1952
 | predecessor=&quot;[[Heil dir im Siegerkranz]]&quot;
}}
{{Listen|type=music|filename=German national anthem performed by the US Navy Band.ogg|title=&quot;Deutschlandlied&quot;|description=Instrumental, one verse, [[United States Navy Band]]}}
[[File:Nationalhymne der Bundesrepublik Deutschland.svg|thumb|upright=1.5|Sheet music]]
The &quot;'''{{lang|de|Deutschlandlied|italic=no}}'''&quot; ({{IPA-de|ˈdɔʏtʃlantˌliːt|-|de-Deutschlandlied.ogg}}; English: &quot;Song of Germany&quot;), officially titled &quot;'''{{lang|de|Das Lied der Deutschen|italic=no}}'''&quot; (English: &quot;The Song of the Germans&quot;), or part of it, has been the [[national anthem]] of [[Germany]] since 1922. In [[East Germany]], the national anthem was &quot;[[Auferstanden aus Ruinen]]&quot; ({{Lang-en|&quot;Risen from Ruins&quot;}}) between 1949 and 1990.

Since [[World War II]] and the fall of [[Nazi Germany]], only the third [[stanza]] has been used as the national anthem. That stanza's incipit &quot;{{Lang|de|[[Wikt:Einigkeit|Einigkeit]] und [[Wikt:Recht|Recht]] und [[Wikt:Freiheit|Freiheit]]|italic=no}}&quot; (&quot;Unity and Justice and Freedom&quot;) is considered the unofficial [[national motto]] of Germany,&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=Y85XAAAAYAAJ&amp;q=einigkeit+und+recht+und+freiheit+motto+federal+republic&amp;dq=einigkeit+und+recht+und+freiheit+motto+federal+republic&amp;hl=de&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=tHSeUt_UCMXbswan34HwCA&amp;ved=0CEQQ6AEwAg ''The Complete Guide to National Symbols and Emblems'', James Minahan, Google Books&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; and is inscribed on modern German Army belt buckles and the rims of some [[German coins]].

The music is the hymn &quot;[[Gott erhalte Franz den Kaiser]]&quot;, written in 1797 by the Austrian composer [[Joseph Haydn]] as an anthem for the birthday of [[Francis II, Holy Roman Emperor|Francis II]], Emperor of the [[Holy Roman Empire]] and later of [[Austrian Empire|Austria]]. In 1841, the German linguist and poet [[August Heinrich Hoffmann von Fallersleben]] wrote the lyrics of &quot;{{Lang|de|Das Lied der Deutschen|italic=no}}&quot; as a new text for that music, counterposing the national unification of Germany to the eulogy of a monarch, lyrics that were considered revolutionary at the time. Along with the [[flag of Germany]], which first appeared in [[Flag of Germany#Principality of Reuss-Greiz|its essentially &quot;modern&quot; form in 1778]]; it was one of the symbols of the [[German revolutions of 1848–1849|March Revolution of 1848]].

In order to endorse its republican and liberal tradition, the song was chosen as the national anthem of Germany in 1922, during the [[Weimar Republic]]. [[West Germany]] adopted the &quot;{{Lang|de|Deutschlandlied|italic=no}}&quot; as its official national anthem in 1952 for similar reasons, with only the third stanza sung on official occasions. Upon [[German reunification]] in 1990, only the third stanza was confirmed as the national anthem.

==Title==
The song is also well known by the beginning and refrain of the first stanza, &quot;{{lang|de|Deutschland, Deutschland über alles|italic=no}}&quot; (&quot;Germany, Germany above all&quot;), but this has never been its title. The line &quot;Germany, Germany above all&quot; originally meant that the most important goal of 19th-century German liberal revolutionaries should be a unified Germany which would overcome loyalties to the local kingdoms, principalities, duchies and palatines (''[[Kleinstaaterei]]'') of then-fragmented Germany.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Toeche-Mittler |first1=Joachim |last2=Probst |first2=Werner |year=2013 |editor1-last=Dean |editor1-first=Antony |editor2-last=Mantle |editor2-first=Robert |editor3-last=Murray |editor3-first=David |editor4-last=Smart |editor4-first=David |translator-last1=Dean |translator-first1=Antony |translator-last2=Mantle |translator-first2=Robert |translator-last3=Murray |translator-first3=David |translator-last4=Smart |translator-first4=David |title=Tunes of Blood &amp; Iron: German Regimental and Parade Marches from the Age of Frederick the Great to the Present Day |volume=1 |publisher=Helion &amp; Company Limited |location=Solihull, England |page=16 |isbn=978-1-909384-23-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Melody ==
[[File:Haydn portrait by Thomas Hardy (small).jpg|upright|thumb|left|Portrait of Haydn by [[Thomas Hardy (English painter)|Thomas Hardy]], 1792]]

The melody of the &quot;{{Lang|de|Deutschlandlied|italic=no}}&quot; was written by [[Joseph Haydn]] in 1797 to provide music to the poem &quot;[[Gott erhalte Franz den Kaiser]]&quot; ({{lang-en|&quot;God save Franz the Emperor&quot;}}) by [[Lorenz Leopold Haschka]]. The song was a birthday anthem honouring [[Francis II, Holy Roman Emperor|Francis II]] (1768–1835), Habsburg emperor, and was intended as a parallel to [[Kingdom of Great Britain|Great Britain]]'s &quot;[[God Save the King]]&quot;. Haydn's work is sometimes called the &quot;Emperor's Hymn&quot;. It is often used as the musical basis for the hymn &quot;[[Glorious Things of Thee Are Spoken]]&quot;.

It has been conjectured that Haydn took the first four measures (bars) of the melody from a Croatian folk song.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.croatianhistory.net/etf/hadow3.html Excerpt from] ''Notes Toward the Study of Joseph Haydn'' by Sir [[William Henry Hadow|William H. Hadow]], London (1897, reprinted New York, 1971)&lt;/ref&gt; This hypothesis has never achieved unanimous agreement; the alternative theory reverses the direction of transmission, positing that Haydn's melody was adapted as a folk tune. For further discussion see [[Haydn and folk music]].

Haydn later used the hymn as the basis for the second [[Movement (music)|movement]] (''poco adagio cantabile'') of his [[String Quartets, Op. 76 (Haydn)#Opus 76, No. 3|Opus 76 No. 3]], a [[string quartet]], often called the &quot;Emperor&quot; or &quot;Kaiser&quot; quartet.

== Historical background ==
{{Main article|Unification of Germany}}
The [[Holy Roman Empire]], stemming from the [[Middle Ages]], was already disintegrating when the [[French Revolution]] and the ensuing [[Napoleonic Wars]] altered the political map of Central Europe. However, hopes for the [[Age of Enlightenment|Enlightenment]], human rights and [[republican government]] after [[Napoleon]]'s defeat in 1815 were dashed when the [[Congress of Vienna]] reinstated many small German principalities. In addition, with the [[Carlsbad Decrees]] of 1819, Austrian Chancellor [[Klemens von Metternich]] and his secret police enforced censorship, mainly in universities, to keep a watch on the activities of teachers and students, whom he held responsible for the spread of [[Political radicalism|radical]] [[liberalism|liberalist]] ideas. Since reactionaries among the monarchs were the main adversaries, demands for [[freedom of the press]] and other liberal rights were most often uttered in connection with the demand for a united Germany, even though many revolutionaries-to-be had different opinions about whether a republic or a [[constitutional monarchy]] would be the best solution for Germany.

The [[German Confederation]] ''(Deutscher Bund'' 1815–1866) was a loose federation of 35 monarchical states and four republican free cities, with a [[Bundesversammlung (German Confederation)|Federal Assembly]] in Frankfurt. They began to remove internal customs barriers during the [[Industrial Revolution]], and the German Customs Union (''[[Zollverein]]'') was formed among the majority of the states in 1834. In 1840 Hoffmann wrote a song about the ''Zollverein'', also to Haydn's melody, in which he praised the free trade of German goods which brought Germans and Germany closer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.von-fallersleben.de/text252.html|title=Schwefelhölzer, Fenchel, Bricken (Der deutsche Zollverein)|work=www.von-fallersleben.de|accessdate=27 June 2010|language=German}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After the 1848 March Revolution, the German Confederation handed over its authority to the [[Frankfurt Parliament]]. For a short period in the late 1840s, Germany was economically united with the borders described in the anthem, and a democratic constitution was being drafted, and with the [[Flag of Germany#Revolution and the Frankfurt Parliament|black-red-gold flag]] representing it. However, after 1849 the two largest German monarchies, Prussia and Austria, put an end to this liberal movement toward national unification.

== Hoffmann's lyrics ==
[[File:August Heinrich Hoffmann von Fallersleben.jpg|thumb|upright| August Heinrich Hoffmann von Fallersleben in 1841]]
[[August Heinrich Hoffmann von Fallersleben]] wrote the text in 1841 on holiday on the [[North Sea]] island of [[Heligoland]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Rüger|first=Jan|title=Heligoland: Britain, Germany, and the Struggle for the North Sea|year=2017|page=37|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=dKyuDQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA37|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=New York|isbn=9780199672462}}&lt;/ref&gt; then a possession of the United Kingdom (now part of Germany).

Hoffmann von Fallersleben intended &quot;{{Lang|de|Das Lied der Deutschen|italic=no}}&quot; to be sung to Haydn's tune, as the first publication of the poem included the music. The first line, &quot;{{Lang|de|Deutschland, Deutschland über alles, über alles in der Welt|italic=no}}&quot; (usually translated into English as &quot;Germany, Germany above all, above all in the world&quot;), was an appeal to the various German monarchs to give the creation of a united Germany a higher priority than the independence of their small states. In the third stanza, with a call for &quot;{{Lang|de|Einigkeit und Recht und Freiheit|italic=no}}&quot; (unity and justice and freedom), Hoffmann expressed his desire for a united and free Germany where the [[rule of law]], not monarchical arbitrariness, would prevail.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bundestag.de/blickpunkt/103_Parlament/0502/0502014.html |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110906081233/http://www.bundestag.de/blickpunkt/103_Parlament/0502/0502014.html |archivedate=6 September 2011 |title=Staatssymbole Zeichen politischer Gemeinschaft |first=Nadja |last=Bareth |work=[[Bundestag|Blickpunt Bundestag]] |date=February 2005 |accessdate=1 December 2009 |language=German}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the era after the [[Congress of Vienna]], influenced by Metternich and his [[secret police]], Hoffmann's text had a distinctly revolutionary and at the same time liberal connotation, since the appeal for a united Germany was most often made in connection with demands for [[freedom of the press]] and other [[civil rights]]. Its implication that loyalty to a larger Germany should replace loyalty to one's local sovereign was then a revolutionary idea.

The year after he wrote &quot;Das Deutschlandlied&quot;, Hoffmann lost his job as a librarian and professor in Breslau, Prussia (now [[Wrocław]], Poland), because of this and other revolutionary works, and was forced into hiding until being pardoned after the revolutions of 1848 in the German states.

== Lyrics ==
&lt;poem lang=&quot;fr&quot; style=&quot;float:left;&quot;&gt;Deutschland, Deutschland über alles,
Über alles in der Welt,
Wenn es stets zu Schutz und Trutze
Brüderlich zusammenhält.
Von der Maas bis an die Memel,
Von der Etsch bis an den Belt,
&amp;nbsp;|: Deutschland, Deutschland über alles,
&amp;nbsp; Über alles in der Welt! :|

Deutsche Frauen, deutsche Treue,
Deutscher Wein und deutscher Sang
Sollen in der Welt behalten
Ihren alten schönen Klang,
Uns zu edler Tat begeistern
Unser ganzes Leben lang.
&amp;nbsp;|: Deutsche Frauen, deutsche Treue,
&amp;nbsp; Deutscher Wein und deutscher Sang! :|

Einigkeit und Recht und Freiheit
Für das deutsche Vaterland!
Danach lasst uns alle streben
Brüderlich mit Herz und Hand!
Einigkeit und Recht und Freiheit
Sind des Glückes Unterpfand;
&amp;nbsp;|: Blüh' im Glanze dieses Glückes,
&amp;nbsp; Blühe, deutsches Vaterland! :|&lt;/poem&gt;
&lt;poem style=&quot;margin-left:2em; float:left;&quot;&gt;Germany, Germany above all,
Above all in the world,
When, for protection and defense, 
It always stands brotherly together.
From the [[Meuse]] to the [[Neman|Memel]],
From the [[Adige]] to the [[Fehmarn Belt|Belt]],
&amp;nbsp;|: Germany, Germany above all,
&amp;nbsp; Above all in the world! :|

German women, German loyalty,
German wine and German song,
Shall retain in the world
Their old beautiful chime
And inspire us to noble deeds
During all of our life.
&amp;nbsp;|: German women, German loyalty,
&amp;nbsp; German wine and German song! :|

Unity and justice and freedom
For the German fatherland!
Towards these let us all strive
Brotherly with heart and hand!
Unity and justice and freedom
Are the safeguards of fortune;
&amp;nbsp;|: Flourish in the radiance of this fortune,
&amp;nbsp; Flourish, German fatherland! :|&lt;/poem&gt;{{clear|left}}

== Use before 1922 ==
The melody of the &quot;Deutschlandlied&quot; was originally written by Joseph Haydn in 1797 to provide music to the poem &quot;[[Gott erhalte Franz den Kaiser]]&quot; (&quot;God save Franz the Emperor&quot;) by Lorenz Leopold Haschka. The song was a birthday anthem to Francis II, Holy Roman Emperor of the House of Habsburg, and was intended to rival in merit the British &quot;[[God Save the King]]&quot;.

After the dissolution of the Holy Roman Empire in 1806, &quot;{{Lang|de|Gott erhalte Franz den Kaiser|italic=no}}&quot; became the official anthem of the emperor of the [[Austrian Empire]]. After the death of Francis II new lyrics were composed in 1854, ''Gott erhalte, Gott beschütze'', that mentioned the Emperor, but not by name. With those new lyrics, the song continued to be the anthem of Imperial Austria and later of Austria-Hungary. Austrian monarchists continued to use this anthem after 1918 in the hope of restoring the monarchy. The adoption of the Austrian anthem's melody by Germany in 1922 was not opposed by Austria.

&quot;{{Lang|de|Das Lied der Deutschen|italic=no}}&quot; was not played at an official ceremony until Germany and the United Kingdom had agreed on the [[Heligoland–Zanzibar Treaty]] in 1890, when it appeared only appropriate to sing it at the ceremony on the now officially German island of [[Heligoland]]. During the time of the German Empire it became one of the most widely known patriotic songs.

The song became very popular after the [[First Battle of Ypres#Battle of Langemarck|1914 Battle of Langemarck]] during [[World War I]], when, supposedly, several German regiments, consisting mostly of students no older than 20, attacked the British lines on the Western front singing the song, suffering heavy casualties. They are buried in the [[Langemark German war cemetery]] in Belgium. The official report of the army embellished the event as one of young German soldiers heroically sacrificing their lives for the Fatherland. In reality the untrained troops were sent out to attack the British trenches and were mown down by machine guns and rifle fire. This report, also known as the &quot;Langemarck Myth&quot;, was printed on the first page in newspapers all over Germany. It is doubtful whether the soldiers would have sung the song in the first place: carrying heavy equipment, they might have found it difficult to run at high speed toward enemy lines while singing the slow song. Nonetheless, the story was widely repeated.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Mosse|first=George L.|title=Fallen Soldiers: Reshaping the Memory of the World Wars|publisher=Oxford University Press|year=1991|pages=70–73|url=https://books.google.com/?id=JwzIUz8aIk4C&amp;pg=PA70|isbn=978-0-19-507139-9|accessdate=25 February 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Official adoption ==
The melody used by the &quot;Deutschlandlied&quot; was still in use as the anthem of the [[Austro-Hungarian Empire]] until its demise in 1918. On 11 August 1922, German President [[Friedrich Ebert]], a Social Democrat, made the ''Deutschlandlied'' the official German national anthem. In 1919 the black, red and gold tricolour, the colours of the 19th century liberal revolutionaries advocated by the political left and centre, was adopted (rather than the previous black, white and red of Imperial Germany). Thus, in a political trade-off, the conservative right was granted a nationalistic composition – though Ebert advocated using only the lyrics' third stanza (which was done after World War II).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|editor-last=Geisler|editor-first=Michael E.|title=National Symbols, Fractured Identities: Contesting the National Narrative|publisher=University Press of New England|year=2005|page=[https://books.google.com/?id=CLVaSxt-sV0C&amp;pg=PA70 70]|isbn=978-1-58465-437-7&lt;!-- |accessdate=25 February 2014 --&gt;|ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the [[Nazism|Nazi]] era, only the first stanza was used, followed by the [[Sturmabteilung|SA]] song &quot;[[Horst-Wessel-Lied]]&quot;.{{sfn|Geisler|2005|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=CLVaSxt-sV0C&amp;pg=PA71 71]}} It was played at occasions of great national significance such as the opening of the [[1936 Summer Olympics]] in Berlin when [[Hitler]] and his entourage, along with Olympic officials, walked into the stadium amid a chorus of three thousand Germans singing &quot;{{Lang|de|Deutschland, Deutschland über alles|italic=no}}&quot;. In this way, the first verse became closely identified with the Nazi regime.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.historyplace.com/worldwar2/triumph/tr-olympics.htm|title=The Triumph of Hitler|work=The History Place|year=2001|accessdate=9 September 2012|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120911233549/http://www.historyplace.com/worldwar2/triumph/tr-olympics.htm|archive-date=11 September 2012|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Use after World War II ==
After its founding in 1949, [[West Germany]] did not have a national anthem for official events for some years, despite the growing need for the purpose of diplomatic procedures. In lieu of an official national anthem, popular German songs such as the &quot;[[Trizonesien-Song]]&quot;, a [[German carnival|carnival]] song mocking the occupying Allied powers, were used at some sporting events. Different musical compositions were discussed or used, such as the fourth movement of [[Ludwig van Beethoven]]'s [[Symphony No. 9 (Beethoven)|Ninth Symphony]], which is a musical setting of [[Friedrich Schiller]]'s poem &quot;An die Freude&quot; (&quot;[[Ode to Joy]]&quot;). Though the black, red and gold colours of the national flag had been incorporated into Article 22 of the [[Basic Law for the Federal Republic of Germany|(West) German constitution]], a national anthem was not specified. On 29 April 1952, Chancellor [[Konrad Adenauer]] asked President [[Theodor Heuss]] in a letter to accept &quot;{{Lang|de|Das Lied der Deutschen|italic=no}}&quot; as the national anthem, with only the third stanza being sung on official occasions. However, the first and second verses were not outlawed, contrary to popular belief. President Heuss agreed to this on 2 May 1952. This exchange of letters was published in the Bulletin of the Federal Government. Since it was viewed as the traditional right of the President as head of state to set the symbols of the state, the &quot;{{Lang|de|Deutschlandlied|italic=no}}&quot; thus became the national anthem.&lt;ref name=briefwechsel1952 /&gt;

Meanwhile, [[East Germany]] adopted its own national anthem, &quot;[[Auferstanden aus Ruinen]]&quot; (&quot;Risen from Ruins&quot;). As the lyrics of this anthem called for &quot;Germany, united Fatherland&quot;, they were no longer officially used, from about 1972,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|page=135|title= Diskursgrenzen: Typen und Funktionen sprachlichen Widerstands auf den Straßen der DDR|trans-title= Boundaries of discourse: Types and functions of linguistic resistance on the streets of the GDR
|first=Philipp|last= Dreesen|isbn=9783110365573|date= 2015|publisher= De Gruyter}}&lt;/ref&gt; after the DDR abandoned its goal of uniting Germany under communism. With slight adaptations, the lyrics of &quot;{{Lang|de|Auferstanden aus Ruinen|italic=no}}&quot; can be sung to the melody of the &quot;{{Lang|de|Deutschlandlied|italic=no}}&quot; and vice versa.

In the [[1974 FIFA World Cup]] in their home country, West German football players remained silent and did not sing their anthem.&lt;ref&gt;{{YouTube|ciSg83OZcmw|Mister X – RFA 74 RFA–RDA 0–1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 1970s and 80s, efforts were made by conservatives in Germany to reclaim all three stanzas for the national anthem. The [[Christian Democratic Union (Germany)|Christian Democratic Union]] of [[Baden-Württemberg]], for instance, attempted twice (in 1985 and 1986) to require German high school students to study all three stanzas, and in 1989 CDU politician {{ill|Christean Wagner|de}} decreed that all high school students in [[Hesse]] were to memorise the three stanzas.{{sfn|Geisler|2005|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=CLVaSxt-sV0C&amp;pg=PA72 72]}}

On 7 March 1990, months before [[German reunification|reunification]], the [[Federal Constitutional Court]] declared only the third stanza of Hoffmann's poem to be legally protected as a national anthem under German criminal law; Section 90a of the Criminal Code (''[[Strafgesetzbuch]]'') makes defamation of the national anthem a crime – but does not specify what the national anthem is.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.utexas.edu/law/academics/centers/transnational/work_new/german/case.php?id=631|title=Case: BVerfGE 81, 298 1 BvR 1215/87 German National Anthem – decision|date=7 March 1990|accessdate=18 January 2015|website=Institute for Transnational Law – Foreign Law Translations|publisher=[[University of Texas School of Law]] / Nomos Verlagsgesellschaft}}&lt;/ref&gt; This did not mean that stanzas one and two were not – at that time – part of the national anthem at all, but that their peculiar status as &quot;part of the [national] anthem but unsung&quot; disqualified them for penal law protection because the penal law must be interpreted in the narrowest manner possible, and was not explicit in their regard.

In November 1991, President [[Richard von Weizsäcker]] and Chancellor [[Helmut Kohl]] agreed in an exchange of letters to declare the third stanza alone to be the national anthem of the reunified republic.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.bundespraesident.de/DE/Amt-und-Aufgaben/Wirken-im-Inland/Repraesentation-und-Integration/repraesentation-und-integration-node.html| title = Repräsentation und Integration | author = Bundespräsidialamt | authorlink = Bundespräsidialamt | language = German | accessdate = 24 May 2013 | quote = Nach Herstellung der staatlichen Einheit Deutschlands bestimmte Bundespräsident von Weizsäcker in einem Briefwechsel mit Bundeskanzler Helmut Kohl im Jahr 1991 die dritte Strophe zur Nationalhymne für das deutsche Volk. }}&lt;/ref&gt; Hence, effective since then, the national anthem of Germany is unmistakably the third stanza of the Deutschlandlied, and only this stanza, with Haydn's music.

[[File:2-EUR-Muenze-de-freiheit.png|thumb|The word &quot;FREIHEIT&quot; (freedom) on Germany's 2-Euro coin]]
The opening line of the third stanza, &quot;{{Lang|de|Einigkeit und Recht und Freiheit|italic=no}}&quot; (&quot;Unity and Justice and Freedom&quot;), is widely considered to be the national motto of Germany, although it was never officially proclaimed as such. It appears on [[Bundeswehr]] soldiers' belt buckles (replacing the earlier &quot;[[Gott mit uns]]&quot; (&quot;God with Us&quot;) of the [[German Army (German Empire)|Imperial German Army]] and the Nazi-era [[Wehrmacht]]). &quot;{{Lang|de|Einigkeit und Recht und Freiheit|italic=no}}&quot; appeared on the rim of 2 and 5 [[Deutsche Mark]] coins and is present on 2 [[Euro coins]] minted in Germany.

== Criticisms ==
===Geographical===
[[File:Maas memel etsch belt.svg|thumb|320px|German linguistic area (green) and political boundaries around 1841 (grey) in comparison to the text’s geographic references (bold blue)]]

The first verse, which is no longer part of the national anthem and is not sung on official occasions, names three rivers and one strait – the [[Meuse]] (''Maas'' in German), [[Adige]] (''Etsch'') and [[Neman]] (''Memel'') Rivers and the [[Little Belt]] strait – as the boundaries of the German ''[[Sprachbund]]''. As the song was written before German unification, there was never an intention to delineate borders of Germany as a nation-state. Nevertheless, these geographical references have been variously criticized as [[irredentism|irredentist]] or misleading.&lt;ref&gt;''A History of Modern Germany: 1800 to the Present'' (2011) M. Kitchen.&lt;/ref&gt; Of these the Meuse and the Adige were parts of the [[German Confederation]] during the time when the song was composed. The Belt (strait) and the Neman later became actual boundaries of Germany (the Belt until 1920, the Neman between 1920 and 1939), whereas the Meuse and Adige were not parts of the [[German Reich]] as of 1871. Today, no part of any of the four places mentioned in the &quot;{{Lang|de|Deutschlandlied|italic=no}}&quot; lies in Germany.

In an ethnic sense, none of these places formed a distinct ethnic border. The [[Duchy of Schleswig]] (to which the Belt refers) was inhabited by both Germans and Danes, with the Danes forming a clear majority near the strait. Around the Adige there was a mix of German, [[Venetian language|Venetian]] and [[Gallo-Italian]] speakers, and the area around the Neman was not homogeneously German, but also accommodated [[Prussian Lithuanians]]. The Meuse (if taken as referencing the [[Duchy of Limburg (1839–67)|Duchy of Limburg]], nominally part of the [[German Confederation]] for 28 years due to the political consequences of the [[Belgian Revolution]]), was ethnically Dutch with few Germans.

Nevertheless, such nationalistic rhetoric was relatively common in 19th-century public discourse. For example: [[Georg Herwegh]] in his poem &quot;The German Fleet&quot; (1841),&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://gedichte.xbib.de/Herwegh_gedicht_Die+deutsche+Flotte.htm|title=HERWEGH: DIE DEUTSCHE FLOTTE|website=gedichte.xbib.de|access-date=2019-10-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; gives the Germans as the people &quot;between the [[Po (river)|Po]] and the Sund ([[Øresund]]),&quot; and in 1832 Philipp Jakob Siebenpfeiffer, a noted journalist, declared at the [[Hambach Festival]] that he considered all &quot;between the [[Alps]] and the [[North Sea]]&quot; to be ''Deutschtum''.&lt;ref&gt;''Music and German National Identity'' (2002) by C. Applegate. pp. 254&lt;/ref&gt;

===Textual===
The song has frequently been criticised for its generally nationalistic tone, the immodest geographic definition of Germany given in the first stanza, and the alleged male-chauvinistic attitude in the second stanza.&lt;ref name=&quot;malzahn&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|last=Malzahn|first=Claus Christian|title=Deutsche Nationalhymne: 'Die blödsinnigste Parole der Welt'|newspaper=[[Der Spiegel]]|language=German|date=24 June 2006|url=http://www.spiegel.de/kultur/literatur/0,1518,422419,00.html|accessdate=1 December 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.dw-world.de/dw/article/0,,2065774,00.html?maca=en-tagesschau_englisch-335-rdf-mp|title=Germans Stop Humming, Start Singing National Anthem|publisher=[[Deutsche Welle]]|date=24 June 2006|accessdate=2 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; A relatively early critic was [[Friedrich Nietzsche]], who called the grandiose claim in the first stanza (&quot;{{Lang|de|Deutschland über alles&quot;) &quot;die blödsinnigste Parole der Welt|italic=no}}&quot; (the most idiotic slogan in the world), and in ''[[Thus Spoke Zarathustra]]'' said, &quot;{{Lang|de|Deutschland, Deutschland über alles|italic=no}} – I fear that was the end of German philosophy.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;malzahn&quot; /&gt; The pacifist [[Kurt Tucholsky]] was also negative about the song, and in 1929 published a photo book sarcastically titled ''Deutschland, Deutschland über alles'', criticising right-wing groups in Germany.

German grammar distinguishes between {{Lang|de|über alles}}, i.e. above all else, and {{Lang|de|über allen}}, meaning &quot;above everyone else.&quot; However, the latter translation was chosen by the Allies during the first World War for propaganda purposes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Falsehood in War Time: Containing an Assortment of Lies Circulated Throughout the Nations During the Great War (Chapter 11)|first=Arthur|last=Ponsonby|isbn=1162798653|publisher=George Allen and Unwin, London|year=1928}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Modern use of the first stanza ===
German president [[Theodor Heuss]], upon request from chancellor [[Konrad Adenauer]], declared the &quot;Lied der Deutschen&quot; the national anthem of the German Federal Republic in May 1952, along with the provision that only the third verse was to be sung at official occasions.&lt;ref name=briefwechsel1952&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.protokoll-inland.de/SharedDocs/Downloads/PI/DE/Allgemeines/briefwechsel1952.html|title=Briefwechsel zur Nationalhymne von 1952, Abdruck aus dem Bulletin der Bundesregierung Nr.&amp;nbsp;51/S. 537 vom 6.&amp;nbsp;Mai 1952|language=German|publisher=[[Federal Ministry of the Interior (Germany)|Bundesministerium des Innern]]|date=6 May 1952|trans-title=Exchange of letters from 1952 regarding the national anthem, as published in the bulletin of the federal government, Nr.&amp;nbsp;51/p. 537, 6 May 1952|access-date=12 September 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150924082940/http://www.protokoll-inland.de/SharedDocs/Downloads/PI/DE/Allgemeines/briefwechsel1952.html|archive-date=24 September 2015|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; The declaration was a compromise between Heuss, who wanted to retain only the third verse, and the [[Cabinet of Germany|Cabinet]]'s wish to keep the first two verses. As a result, the &quot;Lied&quot; (implicitly in its entirety) was declared the national anthem, with the provision that the third verse would have precedence.&lt;ref name=briefwechsel1952 /&gt; This changed in 1991. Since then, the first and second stanza are no longer &quot;official but unsung&quot;, but are solely considered stanzas of a song written by a German poet to a well-known tune which people may sing if they wish (the idea that they have been forbidden is incorrect), but without any official status at all.

In 1977, German pop singer [[Heino]] produced a record of the song, including all three verses, for use in primary schools in [[Baden-Württemberg]]. The inclusion of the first two verses was met with criticism at the time.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Jeismann: &quot;Die Nationalhymne&quot;. In: Etienne Francois, Hagen Schulze (ed.): ''Deutsche Erinnerungsorte. Vol. III''. C.H. Beck, München 2001, {{ISBN|3-406-47224-9}}, p. 663. [http://www.zeit.de/1978/14/natuerliches-verhaeltnis &quot;Natürliches Verhältnis. Deutschlandlied – dritte oder/und erste Strophe?&quot;], ''[[Die Zeit]]'', 31 March 1978.&lt;/ref&gt; 

In 2009, [[Pete Doherty]] started to sing the German national anthem live on radio at [[Bayerischer Rundfunk]] in Munich. As he sang the first verse, he was booed by the audience.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rnw.nl/nl/nederlands/article/rockzanger-pete-doherty-schoffeert-duitsers |title=Rockzanger Pete Doherty schoffeert Duitsers |work=[[Radio Netherlands Worldwide]] |date=29 November 2009 |accessdate=1 December 2009 |language=Dutch |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110607104627/http://www.rnw.nl/nl/nederlands/article/rockzanger-pete-doherty-schoffeert-duitsers |archivedate=7 June 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Three days later Doherty's spokesperson declared that the singer was &quot;not aware of the historical background and regrets the misunderstanding&quot;. A spokesperson for Bayerischer Rundfunk welcomed the response, stating that further cooperation with Doherty would not have been possible otherwise.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title = Deutschlandlied, die erste: Skandalrocker Doherty entschuldigt sich für Patzer|url = http://www.spiegel.de/panorama/leute/deutschlandlied-die-erste-skandalrocker-doherty-entschuldigt-sich-fuer-patzer-a-664418.html|newspaper = Spiegel Online|date = 1 December 2009|access-date = 10 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

When the first verse was played as the German national anthem at the [[canoe sprint]] world championships in Hungary in August 2011, German athletes were reportedly &quot;appalled&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://au.eurosport.com/olympicgames/london-2012/2012/germans-appalled-by-gaffe_sto2916606/story.shtml |title='Nazi anthem' played at canoe championship |publisher=[[Eurosport]] |date=22 August 2011 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131029215213/http://au.eurosport.com/olympicgames/london-2012/2012/germans-appalled-by-gaffe_sto2916606/story.shtml |archivedate=29 October 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
''[[Eurosport]]'', under the headline of &quot;Nazi anthem&quot;, erroneously reported that &quot;the first stanza of the piece [was] banned in 1952.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.nieuwsblad.be/article/detail.aspx?articleid=DMF20110822_110|title=Nazivolkslied op WK kajak|work=[[Het Nieuwsblad]]|date=22 August 2011|language=Dutch}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Similarly, in 2017, the first verse was mistakenly sung by Will Kimble, an American soloist, during the welcome ceremony of the [[2017 Fed Cup World Group|Fed Cup]] tennis match between [[Andrea Petkovic]] (Germany) and [[Alison Riske]] (U.S.) at the Center Court in [[Lahaina, Maui]], Hawaii. In an unsuccessful attempt to drown out the soloist, German tennis players and fans started to sing the third verse instead.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.theguardian.com/sport/2017/feb/12/us-tennis-nazi-era-anthem-germany-fed-cup-match-deutschlandlied &quot;US Tennis says sorry for using Nazi-era anthem before Germany Fed Cup match&quot;], ''[[The Guardian]]'', 2017-02-12&lt;/ref&gt;

== Variants and additions ==

=== Additional or alternative stanzas ===
Hoffmann von Fallersleben also intended the text to be used as a [[drinking song]]; the second stanza's toast to German [[wine, women and song]] are typical of this genre.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.deutschlandfunkkultur.de/hoffmann-von-fallersleben-auf-helgoland-wie-die-deutsche.1001.de.html?dram:article_id=364148 &quot;Wie die deutsche Nationalhymne nach feucht-fröhlicher Runde entstand&quot;] by Claus-Stephan Rehfeld, [[Deutschlandfunk]], 26 August 2016&lt;/ref&gt; The original Heligoland manuscript included a variant ending of the third stanza for such occasions:
&lt;poem lang=&quot;de&quot; style=&quot;float:left;&quot;&gt;Einigkeit und Recht und Freiheit
Für das deutsche Vaterland!
Danach lasst uns alle streben
Brüderlich mit Herz und Hand!
Einigkeit und Recht und Freiheit
Sind des Glückes Unterpfand;
&amp;nbsp;|: Stoßet an und ruft einstimmig,
&amp;nbsp;Hoch, das deutsche Vaterland. :|&lt;/poem&gt;
&lt;poem style=&quot;margin-left:2em; float:left;&quot;&gt;Unity and justice and freedom
For the German fatherland;
This let us all pursue,
Brotherly with heart and hand.
Unity and justice and freedom
Are the pledge of fortune.
&amp;nbsp;|: Lift your glasses and shout together,
&amp;nbsp;Prosper, German fatherland. :|&lt;/poem&gt;{{clear|left}}

An alternative version called &quot;{{Lang|de|Kinderhymne|italic=no}}&quot; ([[Children's Hymn]]) was written by [[Bertolt Brecht]] shortly after his return from exile in the U.S. to a war-ravaged, bankrupt and geographically smaller Germany at the end of World War II and set to music by [[Hanns Eisler]] in the same year. It gained some currency after the 1990 unification of Germany, with a number of prominent Germans opting for his &quot;antihymn&quot; to be made official:{{sfn|Geisler|2005|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=CLVaSxt-sV0C&amp;pg=PA75 Geisler 75]}}
&lt;!-- Please do not change the lyrics here, as they are Geisler's—see the source cited above --&gt;
{|
|&lt;poem&gt;{{Lang|de|Anmut sparet nicht noch Mühe
Leidenschaft nicht noch Verstand
Dass ein gutes Deutschland blühe
Wie ein andres gutes Land.

Dass die Völker nicht erbleichen
Wie vor einer Räuberin
Sondern ihre Hände reichen
Uns wie andern Völkern hin.

Und nicht über und nicht unter
Andern Völkern wolln wir sein
Von der See bis zu den Alpen
Von der Oder bis zum Rhein.

Und weil wir dies Land verbessern
Lieben und beschirmen wir's
Und das Liebste mag's uns scheinen
So wie anderen Völkern ihr's.|italic=no}}&lt;/poem&gt;
|style=&quot;padding-left:2em;&quot;|&lt;poem&gt;Grace spare not and spare no labour
Passion nor intelligence
That a decent German nation
Flourish as do other lands.

That the people give up flinching
At the crimes which we evoke
And hold out their hand in friendship
As they do to other folk.

Neither over or yet under
Other peoples will we be
From the North Sea to the Alps
From the Oder to the Rhine.

And because we'll make it better
Let us guard and love our home
Love it as our dearest country
As the others love their own.&lt;/poem&gt;
|}

=== Notable performances and recordings ===
[[Max Reger]] quotes the tune in the final section of his organ pieces [[Sieben Stücke, Op. 145|''Sieben Stücke'', Op. 145]], composed in 1915/16 when it was a patriotic song but not yet a national anthem.

The German musician [[Nico]] sometimes performed the national anthem at concerts and dedicated it to militant [[Andreas Baader]], leader of the [[Red Army Faction]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|last=Rockwell|first=John|authorlink=John Rockwell|title=Cabaret: Nico is back|work=[[The New York Times]]|date=21 February 1979}}&lt;/ref&gt; She included a version of &quot;{{Lang|de|Das Lied der Deutschen|italic=no}}&quot; on her 1974 album ''[[The End...]]''. In 2006, the Slovenian &quot;industrial&quot; band [[Laibach]] incorporated Hoffmann's lyrics in a song titled &quot;Germania&quot;, on the album ''Volk'', which contains fourteen songs with adaptations of national anthems.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://www.tagesspiegel.de/kultur/art772,1975298 |title=Völker, hört die Fanale! |last=Hesselmann |first=Markus |work=[[Der Tagesspiegel]] |date=7 December 2006 |accessdate=1 December 2009 |language=German}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.popmatters.com/pm/review/laibach-volk/ |title= Rev. of Laibach, ''Volk'' |last=Schiller |first=Mike |work=[[PopMatters]] |date=6 December 2007 |accessdate=1 December 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
==Notes==
{{Notelist}}
== References ==
&lt;references /&gt;

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Deutschlandlied}}
{{Wikisource|Das Deutschlandlied}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20090901203143/http://www.bundesregierung.de/nn_774/Content/DE/StatischeSeiten/Breg/die-nationalhymne-der-bundesrepublik-deutschland.html Die Nationalhymne der Bundesrepublik Deutschland], German Federal Government {{in lang|de}}
* [http://ingeb.org/Lieder/deutschl.html &quot;Das Lied der Deutschen&quot;], ingeb.org
* [http://www.brandenburghistorica.com/page5.html &quot;Das Lied der Deutschen&quot;] at Brandenburg Historica
* {{IMSLP|work=Das Kaiserlied, Hob.XXVIa:43 (Haydn, Joseph)|cname=&quot;Das Kaiserlied&quot; (Haydn)}}
* {{YouTube|VZaW63EJKKc|Singing of the German national anthem}}, during the official [[German Unity Day]] ceremony on 3 October 1990
* {{Cite news|url=http://www.newyorker.com/culture/culture-desk/deutschland-uber-alles-and-america-first-in-song|title='Deutschland über alles' and 'America First', in Song|author=Daniel A. Gross|work=[[The New Yorker]]|date=18 February 2017}}

{{Germany topics}}
{{National Anthems of Europe}}
{{German patriotic songs}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:German-language songs]]
[[Category:1922 establishments in Germany]]
[[Category:German anthems]]
[[Category:Weimar Republic]]
[[Category:West Germany]]
[[Category:National anthems]]
[[Category:Songs about Germany]]
[[Category:Songs based on poems]]
[[Category:National anthem compositions in E-flat major]]</text>
      <sha1>gr7q68v6cd4156juj51mvf3u02tw6ou</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
