  <page>
    <title>Dada</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8240</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941678610</id>
      <parentid>939647687</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-20T01:34:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Coldcreation</username>
        <id>4614035</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* External links */ Cleaning up excessive links</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Other uses}}
{{short description|Avant-garde art movement in the early 20th century}}
[[File:Grand opening of the first Dada exhibition, Berlin, 5 June 1920.jpg|thumb|upright=1.6|Grand opening of the first Dada exhibition: International Dada Fair, Berlin, 5 June 1920. The central figure hanging from the ceiling was an effigy of a German officer with a pig's head. From left to right: [[Raoul Hausmann]], [[Hannah Höch]] (sitting), Otto Burchard, [[Johannes Baader]], [[Wieland Herzfelde]], Margarete Herzfelde, Dr. Oz (Otto Schmalhausen), [[George Grosz]] and [[John Heartfield]].&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.moma.org/learn/moma_learning/themes/dada ''World War I and Dada''], Museum of Modern Art (MoMA).&lt;/ref&gt;]]
[[File:Francis Picabia, 1915, New York..jpg|thumb|upright=1.6|[[Francis Picabia]]: left, ''Le saint des saints c'est de moi qu'il s'agit dans ce portrait'', 1 July 1915; center, ''Portrait d'une jeune fille americaine dans l'état de nudité'', 5 July 1915; right, ''J'ai vu et c'est de toi qu'il s'agit, De Zayas! De Zayas! Je suis venu sur les rivages du Pont-Euxin'', New York, 1915]]
[[File:Dada artists, group photograph, 1920, Paris.jpg|thumb|upright=1.6|Dada artists, group photograph, 1920, Paris. From left to right, Back row: Louis Aragon, Theodore Fraenkel, Paul Eluard, Clément Pansaers, Emmanuel Fay (cut off).&lt;br /&gt;
Second row: Paul Dermée, Philippe Soupault, Georges Ribemont-Dessaignes.&lt;br /&gt;
Front row: Tristan Tzara (with monocle), Celine Arnauld, Francis Picabia, André Breton.]]
'''Dada''' ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|d|ɑː|d|ɑː}}) or '''Dadaism''' was an [[art movement]] of the European [[avant-garde]] in the early 20th century, with early centers in Zürich, Switzerland, at the [[Cabaret Voltaire (Zurich)|Cabaret Voltaire]] (circa 1916); [[New York Dada]] began circa 1915,&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.fr/books?id=SF5QAAAAMAAJ Francis M. Naumann, ''New York Dada, 1915–23''], Abrams, 1994, {{ISBN |0-81093676-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Mario de Micheli (2006). ''Las vanguardias artísticas del siglo XX.'' Alianza Forma. pp. 135–37.&lt;/ref&gt; and after 1920 Dada flourished in Paris. Developed in reaction to [[World War I]], the Dada movement consisted of artists who rejected the [[logic]], [[reason]], and [[aestheticism]] of modern [[capitalist society]], instead expressing [[nonsense]], [[irrationality]], and [[anti-bourgeois]] protest in their works.&lt;ref name= &quot;smith&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last1= Trachtman |first1=Paul|title=A Brief History of Dada|url= http://www.smithsonianmag.com/arts-culture/dada-115169154/ |website=Smithsonian Magazine|accessdate=14 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name= &quot;Schneede&quot;&gt;{{Citation | last= Schneede | first=Uwe M. | year= 1979 | title=George Grosz, His life and work | location = New York | publisher = Universe Books}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name= &quot;Budd&quot;&gt;Budd, Dona, ''The Language of Art Knowledge'', Pomegranate Communications.&lt;/ref&gt; The art of the movement spanned visual, literary, and sound media, including [[collage]], [[sound poetry]], [[cut-up technique|cut-up writing]], and sculpture. Dadaist artists expressed their discontent with violence, war, and nationalism, and maintained political affinities with the [[Far-left politics|radical far-left]].&lt;ref&gt;Richard Huelsenbeck, ''En avant Dada: Eine Geschichte des Dadaismus'', Paul Steegemann Verlag, Hannover, 1920, Erste Ausgabe (Die Silbergäule): English translation in Robert Motherwell, ''The Dada Painters and Poets'', New York, Wittenborn, Schultz, 1951&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tate.org.uk/learn/online-resources/glossary/d/dada Dada, Tate]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?isbn=8876246045 Timothy Stroud, Emanuela Di Lallo, 'Art of the Twentieth Century: 1900–1919, the avant-garde movements'], Volume 1 of ''Art of the Twentieth Century'', Skyra, 2006, {{ISBN|887624604-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |jstor = 40753524 |title = &quot;Bolshevism in Art&quot;: Dada and Politics|journal = Texas Studies in Literature and Language |volume = 4 |issue = 3|pages = 408–30 |last1 = Middleton|first1 = J. C. |year = 1962}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Dada1.jpg|thumb|Cover of the first edition of the publication ''Dada'', [[Tristan Tzara]]; Zürich, 1917.]]

There is no consensus on the origin of the movement's name; a common story is that the German artist [[Richard Huelsenbeck]] slid a [[paper knife]] (letter-opener) at random into a dictionary, where it landed on &quot;dada&quot;, a colloquial French term for a [[Hobby horse (toy)|hobby horse]]. Others note that it suggests the first words of a child, evoking a childishness and absurdity that appealed to the group. Still others speculate that the word might have been chosen to evoke a similar meaning (or no meaning at all) in any language, reflecting the movement's internationalism.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theartstory.org/movement-dada.htm ''Dada''], ''The art history'', retrieved March 13, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt;

The roots of Dada lie in pre-war avant-garde. The term [[anti-art]], a precursor to Dada, was coined by [[Marcel Duchamp]] around 1913 to characterize works which challenge accepted definitions of art.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tate.org.uk/learn/online-resources/glossary/a/anti-art Anti-art, Art that challenges the existing accepted definitions of art, Tate]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Cubism]] and the development of [[collage]] and [[abstract art]] would inform the movement's detachment from the constraints of reality and convention. The work of French poets, Italian [[Futurism|Futurists]] and the [[Expressionism|German Expressionists]] would influence Dada's rejection of the tight correlation between words and meaning.&lt;ref name= oxfordart&gt;[http://www.oxfordartonline.com/groveart/view/10.1093/gao/9781884446054.001.0001/oao-9781884446054-e-7000021094?&amp;mediaType=Article &quot;Dada&quot;], [[Dawn Adès]] and Matthew Gale, ''[[Grove Art Online]]'', Oxford University Press, 2009 {{subscription required}}&lt;/ref&gt; Works such as ''[[Ubu Roi]]'' (1896) by [[Alfred Jarry]], and the ballet [[Parade (ballet)|''Parade'']] (1916–17) by [[Erik Satie]] would also be characterized as proto-Dadaist works.&lt;ref&gt;Roselee Goldberg, Thomas &amp; Hudson, ''L'univers de l'art'', Chapter 4, ''Le surréalisme'', ''Les représentations pré-Dada à Paris'', {{ISBN|978-2-87811-380-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Dada movement's principles were first collected in [[Hugo Ball]]'s [[wikisource:Dada Manifesto (1916, Hugo Ball)|Dada Manifesto]] in 1916.

The Dadaist movement included public gatherings, demonstrations, and publication of art/[[literary journals]]; passionate coverage of art, politics, and culture were topics often discussed in a variety of media. Key figures in the movement included [[Hugo Ball]], [[Marcel Duchamp]], [[Emmy Hennings]], [[Hans Arp]], [[Sophie Taeuber-Arp]], [[Raoul Hausmann]], [[Hannah Höch]], [[Johannes Baader]], [[Tristan Tzara]], [[Francis Picabia]], Huelsenbeck, [[George Grosz]], [[John Heartfield]], [[Man Ray]], [[Beatrice Wood]], [[Kurt Schwitters]], [[Hans Richter (artist)|Hans Richter]], [[Max Ernst]], and [[Elsa von Freytag-Loringhoven]] among others. The movement influenced later styles like the avant-garde and [[downtown music]] movements, and groups including [[Surrealism]], ''[[nouveau réalisme]]'', [[pop art]] and [[Fluxus]].

==Overview==
[[File:Francis Picabia, Dame! Illustration for the cover of the periodical Dadaphone n. 7, Paris, March 1920.jpg|thumb|[[Francis Picabia]], ''Dame!'' Illustration for the cover of the periodical ''Dadaphone'', n. 7, Paris, March 1920]]
Dada was an informal international movement, with participants in Europe and North America. The beginnings of Dada correspond to the outbreak of World War I. For many participants, the movement was a protest against the [[bourgeoisie|bourgeois]] [[nationalism|nationalist]] and [[colonialism|colonialist]] interests, which many Dadaists believed were the root cause of the war, and against the cultural and intellectual conformity—in art and more broadly in society—that corresponded to the war.&lt;ref name=RichterAntiArt&gt;{{Citation | last=Richter | first=Hans | year=1965 | title=Dada: Art and Anti-art | location= New York and Toronto | publisher = Oxford University Press}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Avant-garde circles outside France knew of pre-war Parisian developments. They had seen (or participated in) Cubist exhibitions held at [[Galeries Dalmau]], Barcelona (1912), Galerie [[Der Sturm]] in Berlin (1912), the [[Armory Show]] in New York (1913), [[Mánes Union of Fine Arts|SVU Mánes]] in Prague (1914), several [[Jack of Diamonds (artists)|Jack of Diamonds]] exhibitions in Moscow and at De Moderne Kunstkring, Amsterdam (between 1911 and 1915). [[Futurism]] developed in response to the work of various artists. Dada subsequently combined these approaches.&lt;ref name=oxfordart /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=sPGdBxzaWj0C&amp;pg=RA1-PA6&amp;lpg=RA1-PA6&amp;dq=%22Barcelona+and+developments+in+Zurich%22,+1916%E2%80%9320&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=qbkgGKzLti&amp;sig=WSVSo0NVM_bSoiKAaOMb-e-ez_E&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwjS_IGtzcHRAhUMaxQKHdWzBGwQ6AEIJTAC#v=onepage&amp;q=%22Barcelona%20and%20developments%20in%20Zurich%22%2C%201916%E2%80%9320&amp;f=false Joan M. Marter, ''The Grove Encyclopedia of American Art, Volume 1'', Oxford University Press, 2011], p. 6, {{ISBN|0195335791}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many Dadaists believed that the 'reason' and 'logic' of bourgeois [[capitalism|capitalist]] society had led people into war. They expressed their rejection of that ideology in artistic expression that appeared to reject logic and embrace [[Randomness|chaos]] and [[irrationality]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Schneede&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Budd&quot;/&gt; For example, [[George Grosz]] later recalled that his Dadaist art was intended as a protest &quot;against this world of mutual destruction.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Schneede&quot; /&gt;

According to [[Hans Richter (artist)|Hans Richter]] Dada was not art: it was &quot;[[anti-art]].&quot;&lt;ref name=RichterAntiArt /&gt; Dada represented the opposite of everything which art stood for. Where art was concerned with traditional [[aesthetics]], Dada ignored aesthetics. If art was to appeal to sensibilities, Dada was intended to offend.

As [[Hugo Ball]] expressed it, &quot;For us, art is not an end in itself ... but it is an opportunity for the true perception and criticism of the times we live in.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | title=DADA: Cities | url=http://www.nga.gov/exhibitions/2006/dada/cities/index.shtm | publisher=[[National Gallery of Art]] | accessdate=2008-10-19 | archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20081102003737/http://www.nga.gov/exhibitions/2006/dada/cities/index.shtm | archive-date=2008-11-02 |url-status=dead| df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

A reviewer from the ''[[ARTnews|American Art News]]'' stated at the time that &quot;Dada philosophy is the sickest, most paralyzing and most destructive thing that has ever originated from the brain of man.&quot; Art historians have described Dada as being, in large part, a &quot;reaction to what many of these artists saw as nothing more than an insane spectacle of collective homicide.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;gardners&quot;&gt;{{Citation | author = Fred S. Kleiner | title = Gardner's Art Through the Ages | edition = 12th | year = 2006 | publisher = Wadsworth Publishing | page = 754}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Years later, Dada artists described the movement as &quot;a phenomenon bursting forth in the midst of the postwar economic and moral crisis, a savior, a monster, which would lay waste to everything in its path... [It was] a systematic work of destruction and demoralization... In the end it became nothing but an act of sacrilege.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;gardners&quot;/&gt;

To quote Dona Budd's ''The Language of Art Knowledge'', &lt;blockquote&gt;Dada was born out of negative reaction to the horrors of the [[World War I|First World War]]. This international movement was begun by a group of artists and poets associated with the [[Cabaret Voltaire (Zurich)|Cabaret Voltaire]] in Zürich. Dada rejected reason and logic, prizing nonsense, irrationality and intuition. The origin of the name Dada is unclear; some believe that it is a nonsensical word. Others maintain that it originates from the Romanian artists Tristan Tzara's and Marcel Janco's frequent use of the words &quot;da, da,&quot; meaning &quot;yes, yes&quot; in the Romanian language. Another theory says that the name &quot;Dada&quot; came during a meeting of the group when a [[paper knife]] stuck into a French–German dictionary happened to point to 'dada', a French word for '[[Hobby horse (toy)|hobbyhorse]]'.&lt;ref name=&quot;Budd&quot; /&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; The movement primarily involved [[visual arts]], [[literature]], [[poetry]], [[art manifesto]]s, [[aesthetics|art theory]], [[theatre]], and [[graphic design]], and concentrated its [[anti-war]] politics through a rejection of the prevailing standards in [[art]] through anti-art cultural works.

The creations of Duchamp, Picabia, Man Ray, and others between 1915 and 1917 eluded the term Dada at the time, and &quot;[[New York Dada]]&quot; came to be seen as a post facto invention of Duchamp. At the outset of the 1920s the term Dada flourished in Europe with the help of Duchamp and Picabia, who had both returned from New York. Notwithstanding, Dadaists such as Tzara and Richter claimed European precedence. Art historian David Hopkins notes:

&lt;blockquote&gt;Ironically, though, Duchamp's late activities in New York, along with the machinations of Picabia, re-cast Dada's history. Dada's European chroniclers—primarily Richter, Tzara, and Huelsenbeck—would eventually become preoccupied with establishing the pre-eminence of Zurich and Berlin at the foundations of Dada, but it proved to be Duchamp who was most strategically brilliant in manipulating the genealogy of this avant-garde formation, deftly turning New York Dada from a late-comer into an originating force.&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.fr/books?isbn=1118476182 Hopkins, David, ''A Companion to Dada and Surrealism''], Volume 10 of Blackwell Companions to Art History, John Wiley &amp; Sons, May 2, 2016, p. 83, {{ISBN|1118476182}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==History==

Dada emerged from a period of artistic and literary movements like [[Futurism]], [[Cubism]] and [[Expressionism]]; centered mainly in Italy, France and Germany respectively, in those years. However, unlike the earlier movements Dada was able to establish a broad base of support, giving rise to a movement that was international in scope. Its adherents were based in cities all over the world including New York, Zürich, Berlin, Paris and others. There were regional differences like an emphasis on literature in Zürich and political protest in Berlin.{{sfn|Elger|2004|page=[https://books.google.com/books?id=Y0ES7-5Hp7gC&amp;pg=PA6 6]}}

Prominent Dadaists published manifestos, but the movement was loosely organized and there was no central hierarchy. On 14 July 1916, Ball recited the [[wikisource:Dada Manifesto (1916, Hugo Ball)|manifesto]]; In 1917, Tzara wrote a second [[wikisource:Dada Manifesto|Dada manifesto]], considered one of the most important Dada writings, which was published in 1918.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ujghNFNfDV8C&amp;pg=PA91&amp;dq=Tzara+second+Dada+manifesto,&amp;hl=en&amp;newbks=1&amp;newbks_redir=0&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=2ahUKEwjxtefC6t3lAhWtxFkKHbIaCqgQ6AEwCHoECAQQAg#v=onepage&amp;q=Tzara%20second%20Dada%20manifesto,&amp;f=false|title=A History of Modern Criticism: French, Italian and Spanish criticism, 1900-1950|last=Wellek|first=René|date=1955|publisher=Yale University Press|isbn=9780300054514|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[Tristan Tzara]]'s manifesto articulated the concept of &quot;Dadaist disgust&quot;&amp;mdash;the contradiction implicit in avant-garde works between the criticism and affirmation of modernist reality. In the Dadaist perspective modern art and culture are considered a type of [[Fetishism|fetishization]] where the objects of consumption (including organized systems of thought like philosophy and morality) are chosen, much like a preference for cake or cherries, to fill a void.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Novero |first1=Cecilia |title=Antidiets of the Avant-Garde |date=2010 |publisher=University of Minnesota Press |page=62}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The shock and scandal the movement inflamed was deliberate; Dadist magazines were banned and their exhibits closed. Some of the artists even faced imprisonment. These provocations were part of the entertainment but, over time, audiences' expectations eventually outpaced the movement's capacity to deliver. As the artists' well-known &quot;sarcastic laugh&quot; started to come from the audience, the provocations of Dadaists began to lose their impact. Dada was an active movement during years of political turmoil from 1916 when European countries were actively engaged in World War I, the conclusion of which, in 1918, set the stage for a new political order.{{sfn|Elger|2004|page=[https://books.google.com/books?id=Y0ES7-5Hp7gC&amp;pg=PA7 7]}}

===Zürich===
[[File:Hoch-Cut With the Kitchen Knife.jpg|thumb|left|[[Hannah Höch]], ''Cut with the Dada Kitchen Knife through the Last Weimar Beer-Belly Cultural Epoch in Germany'', 1919, collage of pasted papers, 90×144&amp;nbsp;cm, [[Berlin State Museums|Nationalgalerie, Staatliche Museen zu Berlin]]]]

There is some disagreement about where Dada originated. The movement is commonly identified with the [[Cabaret Voltaire (Zurich)|Cabaret Voltaire]] (housed inside the ''Holländische Meierei'' bar in Zurich) co-founded by poet and [[cabaret]] singer [[Emmy Hennings]] and [[Hugo Ball]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Greeley |first1=Anne |title=Cabaret Voltaire |url=https://www.rem.routledge.com/articles/cabaret-voltaire |publisher=Routledge |accessdate=31 July 2019 |ref=rem}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some sources propose a Romanian origin, arguing that Dada was an offshoot of a vibrant artistic tradition that transposed to Switzerland when a group of Jewish [[Modernism|modernist]] artists, including Tristan Tzara, [[Marcel Janco]], and [[Arthur Segal (painter)|Arthur Segal]] settled in Zürich. Before World War I, similar art had already existed in Bucharest and other Eastern European cities; it is likely that Dada's catalyst was the arrival in Zürich of artists like Tzara and Janco.&lt;ref&gt;Tom Sandqvist, ''DADA EAST: The Romanians of Cabaret Voltaire'', London MIT Press, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;{{page needed|date=July 2019}}

The name ''Cabaret Voltaire'' was a reference to the French philosopher [[Voltaire]], whose novel ''[[Candide]]'' mocked the religious and philosophical [[dogma]]s of the day. Opening night was attended by Ball, Tzara, [[Jean Arp]], and Janco. These artists along with others like [[Sophie Taeuber]], [[Richard Huelsenbeck]] and [[Hans Richter (artist)|Hans Richter]] started putting on performances at the Cabaret Voltaire and using art to express their disgust with the war and the interests that inspired it. Having left Germany and Romania during [[World War I]], the artists arrived in politically neutral Switzerland. They used abstraction to fight against the social, political, and cultural ideas of that time. They used techniques of [[shock art|shock]], provocation and &quot;[[vaudeville]]ian excess&quot; were all tools to subvert the conventions they believed had caused the Great War.&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc2016&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=Cabaret Voltaire: A Night Out at History's Wildest Nightclub |url=http://www.bbc.com/culture/story/20160719-cabaret-voltaire-a-night-out-at-historys-wildest-nightclub |accessdate=31 July 2019 |publisher=BBC |date=2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Dadaists believed those ideas to be a byproduct of bourgeois society that was so apathetic it would wage war against itself rather than challenge the ''status quo'':&lt;ref name=&quot;nga.gov&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Introduction: &quot;Everybody can Dada&quot;|url=http://www.nga.gov/exhibitions/2006/dada/cities/index.shtm|publisher=[[National Gallery of Art]]|accessdate=10 May 2012|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20081102003737/http://www.nga.gov/exhibitions/2006/dada/cities/index.shtm|archive-date=2 November 2008|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|quote=We had lost confidence in our culture. Everything had to be demolished. We would begin again after the ''[[tabula rasa]]''. At the Cabaret Voltaire we began by shocking common sense, public opinion, education, institutions, museums, good taste, in short, the whole prevailing order.&quot;|width=75%|source=Marcel Janco&lt;ref&gt;Marcel Janco, &quot;Dada at Two Speeds,&quot; trans. in Lucy R. Lippard, Dadas on Art (Englewood Cliffs, N.J., 1971), p. 36.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Ball said that Janco's mask and costume designs, inspired by Romanian folk art, made &quot;the horror of our time, the paralyzing background of events&quot; visible.&lt;ref name=bbc2016 /&gt; According to Ball, performances were accompanied by a &quot;balalaika orchestra playing delightful folk-songs.&quot; Influenced by [[African music]], arrhythmic drumming and jazz were common at Dada gatherings.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=World History Encyclopedia|last=Jenkins|first=Ellen Jan|publisher=ABC-CLIO|year=2011|isbn=|editor-last=Andrea|editor-first=Alfred J.|location=|pages=|via=Credo Reference}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Destruction was My Beatrice: Dada and the Unmaking of the Twentieth Century|last=Rasula|first=Jed|publisher=Basic Books|year=2015|isbn=9780465089963|location=New York|pages=145–146}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After the cabaret closed down, Dada activities moved on to a new gallery, and [[Hugo Ball]] left for Bern. Tzara began a relentless campaign to spread Dada ideas. He bombarded French and Italian artists and writers with letters, and soon emerged as the Dada leader and master strategist. The Cabaret Voltaire re-opened, and is still in the same place at the Spiegelgasse 1 in the Niederdorf.

Zürich Dada, with Tzara at the helm, published the art and literature review ''Dada'' beginning in July 1917, with five editions from Zürich and the final two from Paris.

Other artists, such as [[André Breton]] and [[Philippe Soupault]], created &quot;literature groups to help extend the influence of Dada&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Europe of Cultures. [http://fresques.ina.fr/europe-des-cultures-en/fiche-media/Europe00022/tristan-tzara-speaks-about-the-dada-movement.html &quot;Tristan Tzara speaks of the Dada Movement&quot;], September 6, 1963. Retrieved on July 2, 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;

After the fighting of the First World War had ended in the armistice of November 1918, most of the Zürich Dadaists returned to their home countries, and some began Dada activities in other cities. Others, such as the Swiss native [[Sophie Taeuber]], would remain in Zürich into the 1920s.

===Berlin===
[[File:An Anna Blume.jpg|thumb|Cover of ''Anna Blume, Dichtungen'', 1919]]
&quot;Berlin was a city of tightened stomachers, of mounting, thundering hunger, where hidden rage was transformed into a boundless money lust, and men's minds were concentrating more and more on questions of naked existence... Fear was in everybody's bones&quot; – Richard Hülsenbeck

[[Raoul Hausmann]], who helped establish Dada in Berlin, published his [[art manifesto|manifesto]] ''Synthethic Cino of Painting'' in 1918 where he attacked Expressionism and the art critics who promoted it. Dada is envisioned in contrast to art forms, such as Expressionism, that appeal to viewers' emotional states: &quot;the exploitation of so-called echoes of the soul&quot;. In Hausmann's conception of Dada, new techniques of creating art would open doors to explore new artistic impulses. Fragmented use of real world stimuli allowed an expression of reality that was radically different from other forms of art:{{sfn|Elger|2004|page=[https://books.google.com/books?id=Y0ES7-5Hp7gC&amp;pg=PA35 35]}}
{{quote|quote=A child's discarded doll or a brightly colored rag are more necessary expressions than those of some ass who seeks to immortalize himself in oils in finite parlors.|width=75%|source=Raoul Hausmann}}

The groups in Germany were not as strongly [[anti-art]] as other groups. Their activity and art were more political and social, with corrosive [[art manifesto|manifestos]] and propaganda, satire, public demonstrations and overt political activities. The intensely political and war-torn environment of Berlin had a dramatic impact on the ideas of Berlin Dadaists. Conversely, New York's geographic distance from the war spawned its more theoretically-driven, less political nature.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = New York Dada|last = Naumann|first = Francis M.|publisher = Abrams|year = 1994|isbn = 0810936763|location = New York}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to [[Hans Richter (artist)|Hans Richter]], a Dadaist who was in Berlin yet “aloof from active participation in Berlin Dada”, several distinguishing characteristics of the Dada movement there included: “its political element and its technical discoveries in painting and literature”; “inexhaustible energy”; “mental freedom which included the abolition of everything”; and “members intoxicated with their own power in a way that had no relation to the real world”, who would “turn their rebelliousness even against each other”.&lt;ref&gt;Hans Richter, ''Dada: Art and Anti-Art'', London: Thames &amp; Hudson (1997); p. 122&lt;/ref&gt;

In February 1918, while the Great War was approaching its climax, Huelsenbeck gave his first Dada speech in Berlin, and he produced a Dada manifesto later in the year. Following the [[October Revolution]] in [[Russian Empire|Russia]], by then out of the war, [[Hannah Höch]] and [[George Grosz]] used Dada to express communist sympathies. Grosz, together with [[John Heartfield]], Höch and Hausmann developed the [[wikt:technique|technique]] of [[photomontage]] during this period. [[Johannes Baader]], the uninhibited Oberdada, was the “crowbar” of the Berlin movement's [[direct action]] according to [[Hans Richter (artist)|Hans Richter]] and is credited with creating the first giant collages, according to [[Raoul Hausmann]].

After the war, the artists published a series of short-lived political magazines and held the [[First International Dada Fair]], 'the greatest project yet conceived by the Berlin Dadaists', in the summer of 1920.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dada, Dickermann p443&quot;&gt;Dada, Dickermann, National Gallery of Art, Washington, 2006 p443&lt;/ref&gt; As well as work by the main members of Berlin Dada – Grosz, [[Raoul Hausmann]], Hannah Höch, [[Johannes Baader]], Huelsenbeck and Heartfield – the exhibition also included the work of [[Otto Dix]], [[Francis Picabia]], Jean Arp, [[Max Ernst]], [[Rudolf Schlichter]], [[Johannes Theodor Baargeld|Johannes Baargeld]] and others.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dada, Dickermann p443&quot;/&gt; In all, over 200 works were exhibited, surrounded by incendiary slogans, some of which also ended up written on the walls of the Nazi's ''[[Entartete Kunst]]'' exhibition in 1937. Despite high ticket prices, the exhibition lost money, with only one recorded sale.&lt;ref&gt;Dada, Dickermann, National Gallery of Art, Washington, 2006 p99&lt;/ref&gt;

The Berlin group published periodicals such as ''Club Dada'', ''Der Dada'', ''[[Jedermann sein eigner Fussball|Everyman His Own Football]]'', and ''Dada Almanach''. They also established a political party, the [[Central Council of Dada for the World Revolution]].

===Cologne===
In [[Cologne]], Ernst, Baargeld, and Arp launched a controversial Dada exhibition in 1920 which focused on nonsense and anti-bourgeois sentiments. Cologne's Early Spring Exhibition was set up in a pub, and required that participants walk past urinals while being read lewd poetry by a woman in a [[Eucharist|communion]] dress. The police closed the exhibition on grounds of obscenity, but it was re-opened when the charges were dropped.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation
|last=Schaefer
|first=Robert A.
|date=September 7, 2006
|title=Das Ist Dada–An Exhibition at the Museum of Modern Art in NYC
|periodical=Double Exposure
|url=http://www.doubleexposure.com/DadaExhibit.shtml
|access-date=June 12, 2007
|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071009091858/http://www.doubleexposure.com/DadaExhibit.shtml
|archive-date=October 9, 2007
|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===New York===
[[File:Label for the Belle Haleine cropped.png|thumb|upright|[[Rrose Sélavy]], the alter ego of Dadaist [[Marcel Duchamp]]]]
[[File:Marcel Duchamp, 1917, Fountain, photograph by Alfred Stieglitz.jpg|thumb|[[Marcel Duchamp]], ''[[Fountain (Duchamp)|Fountain]],'' 1917; photograph by [[Alfred Stieglitz]]]]
{{main|New York Dada}}

Like Zürich, New York City was a refuge for writers and artists from the First World War. Soon after arriving from France in 1915, [[Marcel Duchamp]] and [[Francis Picabia]] met American artist [[Man Ray]]. By 1916 the three of them became the center of radical [[anti-art]] activities in the United States. American [[Beatrice Wood]], who had been studying in France, soon joined them, along with [[Elsa von Freytag-Loringhoven]]. [[Arthur Cravan]], fleeing conscription in France, was also in New York for a time. Much of their activity centered in [[Alfred Stieglitz]]'s gallery, [[291 (art gallery)|291]], and the home of [[Walter Conrad Arensberg|Walter and Louise Arensberg]].

The New Yorkers, though not particularly organized, called their activities ''Dada,'' but they did not issue manifestos. They issued challenges to art and culture through publications such as ''[[The Blind Man]]'', ''Rongwrong'', and ''New York Dada'' in which they criticized the traditionalist basis for ''museum'' art. New York Dada lacked the disillusionment of European Dada and was instead driven by a sense of irony and humor. In his book ''Adventures in the arts: informal chapters on painters, vaudeville and poets'' [[Marsden Hartley]] included an essay on &quot;[[s:The Importance of Being Dada|The Importance of Being 'Dada']]&quot;.

During this time Duchamp began exhibiting &quot;[[Readymades of Marcel Duchamp|readymades]]&quot; (everyday objects found or purchased and declared art) such as a bottle rack, and was active in the [[Society of Independent Artists]]. In 1917 he submitted the now famous ''[[Fountain (Duchamp)|Fountain]]'', a urinal signed R.&amp;nbsp;Mutt, to the Society of Independent Artists exhibition but they rejected the piece. First an object of scorn within the arts community, the ''Fountain'' has since become almost canonized by some&lt;ref name=&quot;Independent&quot;&gt;[https://www.independent.co.uk/news/uk/this-britain/fountain-most-influential-piece-of-modern-art-673625.html, ''Fountain' most influential piece of modern art''], Independent, December 2, 2004&lt;/ref&gt; as one of the most recognizable modernist works of sculpture. Art world experts polled by the sponsors of the 2004 [[Turner Prize]], Gordon's gin, voted it &quot;the most influential work of modern art&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Independent&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/entertainment/4059997.stm &quot;Duchamp's urinal tops art survey&quot;], [[BBC News]] December&amp;nbsp;1, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; As recent scholarship documents, the work is still controversial. Duchamp indicated in a 1917 letter to his sister that a female friend was centrally involved in the conception of this work: &quot;One of my female friends who had adopted the pseudonym Richard Mutt sent me a porcelain urinal as a sculpture.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Duchamp, Marcel trans. and qtd. in [[Irene Gammel|Gammel, Irene]]. ''Baroness Elsa: Gender, Dada and Everyday Modernity.'' Cambridge, Massachusetts: MIT Press, 2002, 224.&lt;/ref&gt; The piece is in line with the scatological aesthetics of Duchamp's neighbour, the [[Elsa von Freytag-Loringhoven|Baroness Elsa von Freytag-Loringhoven]].&lt;ref&gt;Gammel, ''Baroness Elsa'', 224–225.&lt;/ref&gt; In an attempt to &quot;pay homage to the spirit of Dada&quot; a performance artist named [[Pierre Pinoncelli]] made a crack in a replica of ''The Fountain'' with a hammer in January 2006; he also urinated on it in 1993.

Picabia's travels tied New York, Zürich and Paris groups together during the Dadaist period. For seven years he also published the Dada periodical ''[[391 (magazine)|391]]'' in Barcelona, New York City, Zürich, and Paris from 1917 through 1924.

By 1921, most of the original players moved to Paris where Dada had experienced its last major incarnation.

===Paris===
[[File:Man Ray, Rencontre dans la porte tournante.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Man Ray]], c. 1921–22, ''Rencontre dans la porte tournante'', published on the cover of ''[[Der Sturm]]'', Volume 13, Number 3, 5 March 1922]]
[[File:Man Ray, Dessin.jpg|thumb|upright|Man Ray, c. 1921–22, ''Dessin'' (''Drawing''), published on page 43 of ''Der Sturm'', Volume 13, Number 3, 5 March 1922]]
The French [[avant-garde]] kept abreast of Dada activities in Zürich with regular communications from [[Tristan Tzara]] (whose pseudonym means &quot;sad in country,&quot; a name chosen to protest the treatment of Jews in his native Romania), who exchanged letters, poems, and magazines with [[Guillaume Apollinaire]], [[André Breton]], [[Max Jacob]], [[Clément Pansaers]], and other French writers, critics and artists.

Paris had arguably been the classical music capital of the world since the advent of musical Impressionism in the late 19th century. One of its practitioners, [[Erik Satie]], collaborated with [[Pablo Picasso|Picasso]] and [[Jean Cocteau|Cocteau]] in a mad, scandalous ballet called ''[[Parade (ballet)|Parade]]''. First performed by the [[Ballets Russes]] in 1917, it succeeded in creating a scandal but in a different way than Stravinsky's ''[[Le Sacre du printemps]]'' had done almost five years earlier. This was a ballet that was clearly parodying itself, something traditional ballet patrons would obviously have serious issues with.

Dada in Paris surged in 1920 when many of the originators converged there. Inspired by Tzara, Paris Dada soon issued manifestos, organized demonstrations, staged performances and produced a number of journals (the final two editions of ''Dada'', ''Le Cannibale'', and ''Littérature'' featured Dada in several editions.)&lt;ref&gt;Marc Dachy, {{lang|fr|Dada : La révolte de l'art}}, Paris, Gallimard / Centre Pompidou, collection &quot;[[Découvertes Gallimard]]&quot; (nº 476), 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;

The first introduction of Dada artwork to the Parisian public was at the ''[[Salon des Indépendants]]'' in 1921. [[Jean Crotti]] exhibited works associated with Dada including a work entitled, ''Explicatif'' bearing the word ''Tabu''. In the same year Tzara staged his Dadaist play ''[[The Gas Heart]]'' to howls of derision from the audience. When it was re-staged in 1923 in a more professional production, the play provoked a theatre riot (initiated by [[André Breton]]) that heralded the split within the movement that was to produce [[Surrealism]]. Tzara's last attempt at a Dadaist drama was his &quot;[[Irony|ironic]] [[tragedy]]&quot; ''[[Handkerchief of Clouds]]'' in 1924.

===Netherlands===
In the Netherlands the Dada movement centered mainly around [[Theo van Doesburg]], best known for establishing the [[De Stijl]] movement and magazine of the same name. Van Doesburg mainly focused on poetry, and included poems from many well-known Dada writers in ''De Stijl'' such as [[Hugo Ball]], [[Hans Arp]] and [[Kurt Schwitters]]. Van Doesburg and {{Interlanguage link multi|Thijs Rinsema|nl}} (a [[cordwainer]] and artist in [[Drachten]]) became friends of Schwitters, and together they organized the so-called ''Dutch Dada campaign'' in 1923, where van Doesburg promoted a leaflet about Dada (entitled ''What is Dada?''), Schwitters read his poems, [[Vilmos Huszár]] demonstrated a mechanical dancing doll and Nelly van Doesburg (Theo's wife), played [[avant-garde]] compositions on piano.

[[File:I.K. Bonset Voorbijtrekkende troep 2.jpg|thumb|A Bonset sound-poem, &quot;Passing troop&quot;, 1916]]
Van Doesburg wrote Dada poetry himself in ''De Stijl'', although under a pseudonym, I.K.&amp;nbsp;Bonset, which was only revealed after his death in 1931. 'Together' with I.K.&amp;nbsp;Bonset, he also published a short-lived [[Dutch literature|Dutch]] Dada magazine called ''Mécano'' (1922–3). Another Dutchman identified by [[K. Schippers]] in his study of the movement in the Netherlands&lt;ref&gt;''Holland Dada'', Amsterdam, 1974&lt;/ref&gt; was the [[Groningen]] typographer [[H. N. Werkman]], who was in touch with van Doesburg and Schwitters while editing his own magazine, ''The Next Call'' (1923–6). Two more artists mentioned by Schippers were German-born and eventually settled in the Netherlands. These were Otto van Rees, who had taken part in the liminal exhibitions at the Café Voltaire in Zürich, and [[Paul Citroen]].

===Georgia===
Although Dada itself was unknown in [[Georgia (country)|Georgia]] until at least 1920, from 1917 until 1921 a group of poets called themselves &quot;41st Degree&quot; (referring both to the latitude of [[Tbilisi]], Georgia and to the temperature of a high fever) organized along Dadaist lines. The most important figure in this group was [[Ilia Zdanevich|Iliazd]], whose radical typographical designs visually echo the publications of the Dadaists. After his flight to Paris in 1921, he collaborated with Dadaists on publications and events.

===Yugoslavia===
In [[Yugoslavia]] there was significant Dada activity between 1920 and 1922, run mainly by [[Dragan Aleksić]] and including work by Mihailo S.&amp;nbsp;Petrov, [[Zenitism]]'s two brothers Ljubomir Micić and Branko Ve Poljanski.&lt;ref&gt;[https://monoskop.org/Zenit ''Zenit: International Review of Arts and Culture'']&lt;/ref&gt; Aleksić used the term &quot;Yougo-Dada&quot; and is known to have been in contact with [[Raoul Hausmann]], [[Kurt Schwitters]], and [[Tristan Tzara]].&lt;ref&gt;Dubravka Djurić, Miško Šuvaković. ''Impossible Histories: Historical Avant-gardes, Neo-avant-gardes, and Post-avant-gardes in Yugoslavia, 1918–1991'', [https://books.google.com/books?id=c8ZbINFYdVoC&amp;pg=PA132&amp;lpg=PA132 p. 132], MIT Press, 2003. {{ISBN|9780262042161}}; Jovanov Jasna, Kujundžić Dragan, &quot;Yougo-Dada&quot;. &quot;Crisis and the Arts: The History of Dada&quot;, Vol. IV, The Eastern Orbit: Russia, Georgia, Ukraine, Central Europe and Japan, General Editor Stephen C. Foster, G.K. Hall &amp; Comp. Publishers, New York 1998, 41–62; Jasna Jovanov, ''Demistifikacija apokrifa: dadaizam na jugoslovenskim prostorima 1920–1922'', Novi Sad: Apokrif, 1999.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Italy===
The Dada movement in Italy, based in [[Mantua]], was met with distaste and failed to make a significant impact in the world of art. It published a magazine for a short time and held an exhibition in Rome, featuring paintings, quotations from Tristan Tzara, and original epigrams such as &quot;True Dada is against Dada&quot;. The most notable member of this group was [[Julius Evola]], who went on to become an eminent scholar of [[occultism]], as well as a right-wing philosopher.&lt;ref&gt;[http://sdrc.lib.uiowa.edu/dada/dadas/evola.htm Julius Evola – International Dada Archive]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Japan===
[[File:Dada in Ultraman.jpg|thumb|left|Dada, an iconic character from the Ultra Series. His design draws inspiration from the art movement.]]
A prominent Dada group in Japan was [[Mavo]], founded in July 1923 by [[Tomoyoshi Murayama]] and {{interlanguage link|Yanase Masamu|de||ja|柳瀬正夢}}. Other prominent artists were [[Jun Tsuji]], [[Eisuke Yoshiyuki]], [[Shinkichi Takahashi]] and [[Katué Kitasono]].

In the [[Tsuburaya Productions]]'s ''[[Ultra Series]]'', an alien named Dada was inspired by Dadaism movement, with said character first appearing in episode 28 of the 1966 [[tokusatsu]] series, ''[[Ultraman (1966 TV series)|Ultraman]]'', its design by character artist [[Toru Narita]]. Dada's design is primarily monochromatic, and features numerous sharp lines and alternating black and white stripes, in reference to the movement and, in particular, to [[chessboard]] and [[Go (game)|Go]] patterns. On May 19, 2016, in celebration to the 100 year anniversary of Dadaism in Tokyo, the Ultra Monster was invited to meet the Swiss Ambassador Urs Bucher.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://m-78.jp/news/n-3812/|script-title=ja:「三面怪人 ダダ」が「ダダイズム100周年」を祝福！スイス大使館で開催された記者発表会に登場！|publisher=m-78.jp|language=ja|date=2016-05-19|accessdate=2016-06-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://tokusatsunetwork.com/2016/05/dada-celebrates-dadaisms-birthday/|title=Dada Celebrates Dadaism's 100th Anniversary|publisher=tokusatsunetwork.com|date=2016-05-19|accessdate=2016-06-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Butoh]], the Japanese dance-form originating in 1959, can be considered to have direct connections to the spirit of the Dada movement, as [[Tatsumi Hijikata]], one of Butoh's founders, &quot;was influenced early in his career by Dadaism&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.nytimes.com/1987/11/01/magazine/butoh-dance-of-darkness.html&lt;/ref&gt;

===Russia===
{{unreferenced section|date=October 2017}}
Dada in itself was relatively unknown in Russia, however, avant-garde art was widespread due to the [[Bolshevik]]'s revolutionary agenda. The {{interlanguage link|Nichevoki|ru|Ничевоки}}, a literary group sharing Dadaist ideals achieved infamy after one of its members suggested that [[Vladimir Mayakovsky]] should go to the &quot;Pampushka&quot; (Pameatnik Pushkina – [[Pushkinskaya Square|Pushkin monument]]) on the &quot;Tverbul&quot; ([[Tverskoy Boulevard]]) to clean the shoes of anyone who desired it, after Mayakovsky declared that he was going to cleanse Russian literature. The Russian Orthodox priest [[Seraphim Rose]] considered Dadaism to be a contributor to the growing nihilism of the 20th century.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oodegr.com/english/filosofia/nihilism_root_modern_age.htm Nihilism : The Root of the Revolution of the Modern Age]&lt;/ref&gt; For more information on Dadaism's influence upon Russian avant-garde art, see the book ''Russian Dada 1914–1924''.&lt;ref&gt;''Russian Dada 1914–1924'' by Margarita Tupitsyn (Editor), MIT Press: September 4, 2018]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Poetry==
[[File:Dadaglobe Form Letter to Vagts (Nov 1920).jpg|thumb|Dadaglobe solicitation form letter signed by Francis Picabia, Tristan Tzara, Georges Ribemont-Dessaignes, and Walter Serner, c. week of November 8, 1920. This example was sent from Paris to Alfred Vagts in Munich.]]

Dadists used shock, [[nihilism]], negativity, [[paradox]], [[randomness]], [[subconscious]] forces and [[antinomianism]] to subvert established traditions in the aftermath of the Great War. Tzara's 1920 manifesto proposed cutting words from a newspaper and randomly selecting fragments to write poetry, a process in which the synchronous universe itself becomes an active agent in creating the art. A poem written using this technique would be a &quot;fruit&quot; of the words that were clipped from the article.&lt;ref name=coutinho158&gt;{{Cite book|title=Brazilian Literature as World Literature|last=Coutinho|first=Eduardo|publisher=Bloomsbury Publishing|year=2018|isbn=9781501323263|location=New York|pages=158}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In literary arts Dadaists focused on poetry, particularly the so-called sound poetry invented by [[Hugo Ball]]. Dadaist poems attacked traditional conceptions of poetry, including structure, order, as well as the interplay of sound and the meaning of language. For Dadaists, the existing system by which information is articulated robs language of its dignity. The dismantling of language and poetic conventions are Dadaist attempts to restore language to its purest and most innocent form: &quot;With these sound poem, we wanted to dispense with a language which journalism had made desolate and impossible.&quot;{{sfn|Elger|2004|page=12}}

Simultaneous poems (or ''poèmes simultanés'') were recited by a group of speakers who, collectively, produced a chaotic and confusing set of voices. These poems are considered manifestations of modernity including advertising, technology, and conflict. Unlike movements such as Expressionism, Dadaism did not take a negative view of modernity and the urban life. The chaotic urban and futuristic world is considered natural terrain that opens up new ideas for life and art.&lt;ref name=morrison&gt;{{Cite book|title=Text Into Image, Image Into Text: Proceedings of the Interdisciplinary|last=Morrison|first=Jeffrey|last2=Krobb|first2=Florian|publisher=Rodopi|year=1997|isbn=9042001526|location=Atlanta|pages=234}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Music==
{{unreferenced section|date=July 2019}}
Dada was not confined to the visual and literary arts; its influence reached into sound and music. [[Kurt Schwitters]] developed what he called ''[[Sound poetry|sound poems]]'', while [[Francis Picabia]] and [[Georges Ribemont-Dessaignes]] composed Dada music performed at the Festival Dada in Paris on 26 May 1920. Other composers such as [[Erwin Schulhoff]], Hans Heusser and [[Alberto Savinio]] all wrote ''Dada music'', while members of [[Les Six]] collaborated with members of the Dada movement and had their works performed at Dada gatherings. [[Erik Satie]] also dabbled with Dadaist ideas during his career, although he is primarily associated with musical [[Impressionism]].

==Legacy==
[[File:En hod dada museum.jpg|thumb|The [[Janco Dada Museum]], named after [[Marcel Janco]], in [[Ein Hod]], Israel]]
While broadly based, the movement was unstable. By 1924 in Paris, Dada was melding into Surrealism, and artists had gone on to other ideas and movements, including [[Surrealism]], [[social realism]] and other forms of [[modernism]]. Some theorists argue that Dada was actually the beginning of [[postmodern art]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation| last=Locher| first=David| title=Unacknowledged Roots and Blatant Imitation: Postmodernism and the Dada Movement| journal=Electronic Journal of Sociology| volume=4| issue=1| year=1999| url=http://www.sociology.org/content/vol004.001/locher.html| accessdate=2007-04-25| archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070223045916/http://www.sociology.org/content/vol004.001/locher.html| archive-date=2007-02-23|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

By the dawn of the [[World War II|Second World War]], many of the European Dadaists had emigrated to the United States. Some ([[Otto Freundlich]], [[Walter Serner]]) died in death camps under [[Adolf Hitler]], who actively persecuted the kind of &quot;[[degenerate art]]&quot; that he considered Dada to represent. The movement became less active as post-war optimism led to the development of new movements in art and literature.

Dada is a named influence and reference of various [[anti-art]] and political and cultural movements, including the [[Situationist International]] and [[culture jamming]] groups like the [[Cacophony Society]]. Upon breaking up in July 2012, [[anarchist]] pop band [[Chumbawamba]] issued a statement which compared their own legacy with that of the Dada art movement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Chumbawamba|url=http://www.chumba.com/|accessdate=10 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

At the same time that the Zürich Dadaists were making noise and spectacle at the [[Cabaret Voltaire (Zürich)|Cabaret Voltaire]], [[Vladimir Lenin|Lenin]] was planning his revolutionary plans for Russia in a nearby apartment. [[Tom Stoppard]] used this coincidence as a premise for his play ''[[Travesties]]'' (1974), which includes Tzara, Lenin, and [[James Joyce]] as characters. French writer Dominique Noguez imagined Lenin as a member of the Dada group in his tongue-in-cheek ''Lénine Dada'' (1989).

The former building of the Cabaret Voltaire fell into disrepair until it was occupied from January to March 2002, by a group proclaiming themselves [[Neo-Dada]]ists, led by [[Mark Divo]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.praguepost.com/articles/2006/11/01/a-work-in-process.php 2002 occupation by neo-Dadaists] ''Prague Post''&lt;/ref&gt; The group included [[Leumund Cult|Jan Thieler]], [[Ingo Giezendanner]], Aiana Calugar, [[Lennie Lee]], and Dan Jones. After their eviction, the space was turned into a museum dedicated to the history of Dada. The work of Lee and Jones remained on the walls of the new museum.

Several notable [[retrospective]]s have examined the influence of Dada upon art and society. In 1967, a large Dada retrospective was held in Paris. In 2006, the [[Museum of Modern Art]] in New York City mounted a Dada exhibition in partnership with the [[National Gallery of Art]] in Washington D.C. and the [[Centre Pompidou]] in Paris. The [[LTM Recordings|LTM]] label has released a large number of Dada-related sound recordings, including interviews with artists such as Tzara, Picabia, Schwitters, Arp, and Huelsenbeck, and musical repertoire including Satie, Ribemont-Dessaignes, Picabia, and Nelly van Doesburg.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ltmrecordings.com/fdrcat.html LTM Recordings]&lt;/ref&gt;

Musician [[Frank Zappa]] was a self-proclaimed Dadaist after learning of the movement:&lt;blockquote&gt;In the early days, I didn't even know what to call the stuff my life was made of. You can imagine my delight when I discovered that someone in a distant land had the same idea—AND a nice, short name for it.&lt;ref&gt;Frank Zappa, ''The Real Frank Zappa Book'', p. 162&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Art techniques developed==

Dadaism also blurred the line between literary and visual arts:

&lt;blockquote&gt;Dada is the groundwork to abstract art and sound poetry, a starting point for performance art, a prelude to [[postmodernism]], an influence on [[pop art]], a celebration of antiart to be later embraced for anarcho-political uses in the 1960s and the movement that laid the foundation for [[Surrealism]].&lt;ref&gt;Marc Lowenthal, translator's introduction to [[Francis Picabia]]'s ''I Am a Beautiful Monster: Poetry, Prose, and Provocation''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===Collage===
The Dadaists imitated the techniques developed during the cubist movement through the pasting of cut pieces of paper items, but extended their art to encompass items such as transportation tickets, maps, plastic wrappers, etc. to portray aspects of life, rather than representing objects viewed as still life. They also invented the “chance collage&quot; technique, involving dropping torn scraps of paper onto a larger sheet and then pasting the pieces wherever they landed.

===Cut-up technique===
[[Cut-up technique]] is an extension of collage to words themselves, [[Tristan Tzara]] describes this in the Dada Manifesto:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.391.org/manifestos/19201212tristantzara_dmonflabl.htm |title=manifestos: dada manifesto on feeble love and bitter love by tristan tzara, 12th december 1920 |publisher=391 |date=1920-12-12 |accessdate=2011-06-27}} {{PD-notice}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;poem style=&quot;margin-left: 2em;&quot;&gt;
TO MAKE A DADAIST POEM
Take a newspaper.
Take some scissors.
Choose from this paper an article of the length you want to make your poem.
Cut out the article.
Next carefully cut out each of the words that makes up this article and put them all in a bag.
Shake gently.
Next take out each cutting one after the other.
Copy conscientiously in the order in which they left the bag.
The poem will resemble you.
And there you are – an infinitely original author of charming sensibility, even though unappreciated by the vulgar herd.
&lt;/poem&gt;

===Photomontage===
[[File:ABCD-Hausmann.jpg|thumb|upright|Raoul Hausmann, ''ABCD'' (self-portrait), a photomontage from 1923–24]]
The Dadaists – the &quot;monteurs&quot; (mechanics) – used scissors and glue rather than paintbrushes and paints to express their views of modern life through images presented by the media. A variation on the collage technique, photomontage utilized actual or reproductions of real photographs printed in the press. In Cologne, [[Max Ernst]] used images from the First World War to illustrate messages of the destruction of war.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nga.gov/exhibitions/2006/dada/techniques/index.shtm |title=DADA – Techniques – photomontage |publisher=Nga.gov |date= |accessdate=2011-06-11 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110625072447/http://www.nga.gov/exhibitions/2006/dada/techniques/index.shtm |archive-date=2011-06-25 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:MechanicalHead-Hausmann.jpg|thumb|upright|Raoul Hausmann, ''Mechanischer Kopf (Der Geist unserer Zeit)'' (Mechanical Head [The Spirit of Our Age]), c. 1920]]

===Assemblage===
The [[assemblage (art)|assemblage]]s were three-dimensional variations of the collage – the assembly of everyday objects to produce meaningful or meaningless (relative to the war) pieces of work including war objects and trash. Objects were nailed, screwed or fastened together in different fashions. Assemblages could be seen in the round or could be hung on a wall.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nga.gov/exhibitions/2006/dada/techniques/assemblage.shtm |title=DADA – Techniques – assemblage |publisher=Nga.gov |date= |accessdate=2011-06-11 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110716072920/http://www.nga.gov/exhibitions/2006/dada/techniques/assemblage.shtm |archive-date=2011-07-16 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Readymades===
[[Marcel Duchamp]] began to view the manufactured objects of his collection as objects of art, which he called &quot;[[Readymades of Marcel Duchamp|readymades]]&quot;. He would add signatures and titles to some, converting them into artwork that he called &quot;readymade aided&quot; or &quot;rectified readymades&quot;. Duchamp wrote: &quot;One important characteristic was the short sentence which I occasionally inscribed on the 'readymade.' That sentence, instead of describing the object like a title, was meant to carry the mind of the spectator towards other regions more verbal. Sometimes I would add a graphic detail of presentation which in order to satisfy my craving for alliterations, would be called 'readymade aided.'&quot;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The Writings of Marcel Duchamp&quot; {{ISBN|0-306-80341-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; One such example of Duchamp's readymade works is the urinal that was turned onto its back, signed &quot;R. Mutt&quot;, titled ''[[Fountain (Duchamp)|Fountain]]'', and submitted to the Society of Independent Artists exhibition that year, though it was not displayed.

==Artists==
{{Div col}}
* [[Dragan Aleksić]] (1901–1958), Yugoslavia
* [[Louis Aragon]] (1897–1982), France
* [[Jean Arp]] (1886–1966), Germany, France
* [[Sophie Taeuber-Arp]] (1889–1943) Switzerland, France
* [[Johannes Baader]] (1875–1955) Germany
* [[Hugo Ball]] (1886–1927), Germany, Switzerland
* [[André Breton]] (1896–1966), France
* [[John Covert (painter)]] (1882–1960), US
* [[Jean Crotti]] (1878–1958), France
* [[Otto Dix]] (1891–1969), Germany
* [[Theo van Doesburg]] (1883–1931) Netherlands
* [[Marcel Duchamp]] (1887–1968), France
* [[Suzanne Duchamp]] (1889–1963), France
* [[Paul Éluard]] (1895–1952), France
* [[Max Ernst]] (1891–1976), Germany, US
* [[Julius Evola]] (1898–1974), Italy
* [[George Grosz]] (1893–1959), Germany, France, US
* [[Raoul Hausmann]] (1886–1971), Germany
* [[John Heartfield]] (1891–1968), Germany, USSR, Czechoslovakia, Great Britain
* [[Hannah Höch]] (1889–1978), Germany
* [[Richard Huelsenbeck]] (1892–1974), Germany
* [[Georges Hugnet]] (1906–1974), France
* [[Marcel Janco]] (1895–1984), Romania, Israel
* [[Elsa von Freytag-Loringhoven]] (1874–1927), Germany, US
* [[Clément Pansaers]] (1885–1922), Belgium
* [[Francis Picabia]] (1879–1953), France
* [[Man Ray]] (1890–1976), France, US
* [[Georges Ribemont-Dessaignes]] (1884–1974), France
* [[Hans Richter (artist)|Hans Richter]], Germany, Switzerland
* [[Juliette Roche|Juliette Roche Gleizes]] (1884–1980), France
* [[Kurt Schwitters]] (1887–1948), Germany
* [[Walter Serner]] (1889–1942), Austria
* [[Philippe Soupault]] (1897–1990), France
* [[Sophie Taeuber-Arp]] (1889–1943), Switzerland, France
* [[Tristan Tzara]] (1896–1963), Romania, France
* [[Beatrice Wood]] (1893–1998), US
{{Div col end}}

==See also==
*[[Art intervention]]
*[[The Central Council of Dada for the World Revolution]]
*[[Dadaglobe]]
*[[Épater la bourgeoisie]]
*[[Happening]]
*[[Incoherents]]
*[[Shock art]]
*[[Transgressive art]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}
'''Sources'''
*{{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Elger|2004}}|reference={{interlanguage link|Dietmar Elger|de|lt=Elger, Dietmar}} (2004). {{interlanguage link|Uta Grosenick|de}} (ed.). ''Dadaism''. Taschen. {{ISBN|9783822829462}}.}}

==Bibliography==
{{Div col|colwidth=30em}}
*''The Dada Almanac'', ed Richard Huelsenbeck [1920], re-edited and translated by Malcolm Green et al., [[Atlas Press]], with texts by Hans Arp, Johannes Baader, Hugo Ball, Paul Citröen, Paul Dermée, Daimonides, Max Goth, John Heartfield, Raoul Hausmann, Richard Huelsenbeck, Vincente Huidobro, Mario D'Arezzo, Adon Lacroix, Walter Mehring, Francis Picabia, Georges Ribemont-Dessaignes, Alexander Sesqui, Philippe Soupault, Tristan Tzara. {{ISBN|0-947757-62-7}}
*''Blago Bung, Blago Bung'', Hugo Ball's Tenderenda, Richard Huelsenbeck's Fantastic Prayers, &amp; Walter Serner's Last Loosening – three key texts of Zurich ur-Dada. Translated and introduced by Malcolm Green. [[Atlas Press]], {{ISBN|0-947757-86-4}}
*Ball, Hugo. ''Flight Out Of Time'' (University of California Press: Berkeley and Los Angeles, 1996)
*[[Hanne Bergius|Bergius, Hanne]] ''Dada in Europa - Dokumente und Werke'' (co-ed. Eberhard Roters), in: ''Tendenzen der zwanziger Jahre''. 15. Europäische Kunstausstellung, Catalogue, Vol.III, Berlin: Dietrich Reimer Verlag, 1977. {{ISBN| 978-3-496-01000-5}}
*Bergius, Hanne ''Das Lachen Dadas. Die Berliner Dadaisten und ihre Aktionen''. Gießen: Anabas-Verlag 1989. {{ISBN| 978-3-870-38141-7}} 
*Bergius, Hanne ''Dada Triumphs! Dada Berlin, 1917-1923. Artistry of Polarities. Montages - Metamechanics - Manifestations''. Translated by Brigitte Pichon. Vol. V. of the ten editions of ''Crisis and the Arts: the History of Dada'', ed. by Stephen Foster, New Haven, Conn. u. a., Thomson/ Gale 2003. {{ISBN| 978-0-816173-55-6}}.
*Jones, Dafydd W. ''Dada 1916 In Theory: Practices of Critical Resistance'' (Liverpool: Liverpool University Press, 2014). {{ISBN|978-1-781-380-208}}
*Biro, M. ''The Dada Cyborg: Visions of the New Human in Weimar Berlin''. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 2009. {{ISBN|0-8166-3620-6}}
*Dachy, Marc. Journal du mouvement Dada 1915–1923, Genève, Albert Skira, 1989 (Grand Prix du Livre d'Art, 1990)
*''Dada &amp; les dadaïsmes'', Paris, Gallimard, Folio Essais, n° 257, 1994.
*Jovanov, Jasna. ''Demistifikacija apokrifa: Dadaizam na jugoslovenskim prostorima'', Novi Sad/Apostrof 1999.
*''Dada : La révolte de l'art'', Paris, Gallimard / Centre Pompidou, collection &quot;[[Découvertes Gallimard]]&quot; (nº 476), 2005.
*''Archives Dada / Chronique'', Paris, Hazan, 2005.
*''Dada, catalogue d'exposition'', Centre Pompidou, 2005.
*Durozoi, Gérard. ''Dada et les arts rebelles'', Paris, Hazan, Guide des Arts, 2005
*Gammel, Irene. ''Baroness Elsa: Gender, Dada and Everyday Modernity''. Cambridge, Massachusetts: MIT Press, 2002.
*Hoffman, Irene. [http://www.artic.edu/reynolds/essays/hofmann.php ''Documents of Dada and Surrealism: Dada and Surrealist Journals in the Mary Reynolds Collection''], Ryerson and Burnham Libraries, The Art Institute of Chicago.
*Hopkins, David, ''A Companion to Dada and Surrealism'', Volume 10 of Blackwell Companions to Art History, John Wiley &amp; Sons, May 2, 2016, {{ISBN|1118476182}}
*Huelsenbeck, Richard. ''Memoirs of a Dada Drummer'', (University of California Press: Berkeley and Los Angeles, 1991)
*Jones, Dafydd. ''Dada Culture'' (New York and Amsterdam: Rodopi Verlag, 2006)
*Lavin, Maud. ''Cut With the Kitchen Knife: The Weimar Photomontages of Hannah Höch''. New Haven: Yale University Press, 1993.
*Lemoine, Serge. ''Dada'', Paris, Hazan, coll. L'Essentiel.
*Lista, Giovanni. ''Dada libertin &amp; libertaire'', Paris, L'insolite, 2005.
*Melzer, Annabelle. 1976. ''Dada and Surrealist Performance.'' PAJ Books ser. Baltimore and London: The Johns Hopkins UP, 1994. {{ISBN|0-8018-4845-8}}.
*Novero, Cecilia. &quot;Antidiets of the Avant-Garde: From Futurist Cooking to Eat Art.&quot; (University of Minnesota Press, 2010)
*Richter, Hans. ''Dada: Art and Anti-Art'' (London: Thames and Hudson, 1965)
*Sanouillet, Michel. ''Dada à Paris'', Paris, Jean-Jacques Pauvert, 1965, Flammarion, 1993, CNRS, 2005
*Sanouillet, Michel. ''Dada in Paris'', Cambridge, Massachusetts, The MIT Press, 2009
*Schippers, K. ''Holland Dada'', Amsterdam, Em. Querido, 1974
*Schneede, Uwe M. ''George Grosz, His life and work'' (New York: Universe Books, 1979)
*Verdier, Aurélie. ''L'ABCdaire de Dada'', Paris, Flammarion, 2005.
{{div col end}}

== Filmography ==

* 1968: [https://m.youtube.com/watch?v=RHBw6VwY3Io Germany-DADA: An Alphabet of German DADAism], Documentary by Universal Education, Presented By Kartes Video Communications, 56 Minutes
* 1971: [https://m.youtube.com/watch?v=_FXv68H0O4g DADA] 'Archives du XXe siècle', Une émission produite par Jean José Marchand, réalisée par Philippe Collin et Hubert Knapp, Ce documentaire a été diffusé pour la première fois sur la RTF le 28.03.1971, 267 min.
* 2016: ''[https://www.srf.ch/sendungen/sternstunde-kunst/das-prinzip-dada-3 Das Prinzip Dada]'', Documentary by {{interlanguage link|Marina Rumjanzewa|de}}, [[Schweizer Radio und Fernsehen]] (''{{interlanguage link|Sternstunde Kunst|de}}''), 52 Minutes {{in lang|de}}
* 2016 [https://m.youtube.com/watch?v=2QcemEji-UU Dada Art Movement History - “Dada on Tour”], Bruno Art Group in collaboration with Cabaret Voltaire &amp; Art Stage Singapore 2016, 27 minutes

==External links==
{{Library resources box|by=no|onlinebooks=no|about=yes|wikititle=Dada}}
{{Wikiquote|Dada}}
{{commons category|Dada}}
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20161214211903/http://www.dada-companion.com/ Dada Companion], bibliographies, chronology, artists' profiles, places, techniques, reception
*{{curlie|Arts/Art_History/Periods_and_Movements/Dada/|Dada}}
*The [https://www.lib.uiowa.edu/dada/ International Dada Archive], University of Iowa, early Dada periodicals, online scans of publications
*[http://www.dadart.com/dadaism/dada/index.html Dadart], history, bibliography, documents, and news
*[http://www.ltmrecordings.com/fdrcat.html Dada audio recordings at LTM]
* [http://bibliothequekandinsky.centrepompidou.fr/clientBookline/service/reference.asp?INSTANCE=incipio&amp;OUTPUT=PORTAL&amp;DOCID=0473982&amp;DOCBASE=CGPP New York dada (magazine), Marcel Duchamp and Man Ray, April, 1921], Bibliothèque Kandinsky, Centre Pompidou (access online)
*[https://digital.kunsthaus.ch/dadaismus/en Kunsthaus Zürich], one of the world's largest Dada collections
*[https://www.smithsonianmag.com/arts-culture/dada-115169154/ &quot;A Brief History of Dada&quot;], ''Smithsonian Magazine''
*[https://www.khanacademy.org/humanities/art-1010/wwi-dada/dada1/a/introduction-to-dada Khan Academy Art 1010, Introduction to Dada]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20090114080143/http://www.nga.gov/exhibitions/2006/dada/cities/index.shtm National Gallery of Art 2006 Dada Exhibition]
*[https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Search/Home?lookfor=%22%20Dadaism%22&amp;searchtype=subject&amp;ft=ft&amp;setft=true Hathi Trust full-text Dadaism publications online]

'''Manifestos'''
*[[Wikisource:Dada Manifesto (1916, Hugo Ball)|Text of Hugo Ball's 1916 Dada Manifesto]]
*[http://www.391.org/manifestos/19180323tristantzara_dadamanifesto.htm  Text of Tristan Tzara's 1918 Dada Manifesto]
*[http://www.english.upenn.edu/~jenglish/English104/tzara.html Excerpts of Tristan Tzara's Dada Manifesto (1918) and Lecture on Dada (1922)]
*[http://keever.us/tzaraseven.pdf Seven Dada Manifestos by Tristan Tzara]

{{Dada|state=expanded}}
{{Modernism}}
{{Avant-garde}}
{{Schools of poetry}}
{{Marcel Duchamp}}
{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Dada| ]]
[[Category:Avant-garde art]]
[[Category:Art movements]]
[[Category:20th-century German literature]]
[[Category:Nonsense]]</text>
      <sha1>kyikleijjzn6c36ek7qm8c51ljk5mi8</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
