  <page>
    <title>Drexel University</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8256</id>
    <revision>
      <id>936623083</id>
      <parentid>936618273</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-20T00:30:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ElKevbo</username>
        <id>217538</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>[[WP:NOTNEWS]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Private research university in Pennsylvania, United States}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=December 2018}}
{{Infobox university
|name = Drexel University
|former_names = Drexel Institute (1891–1936)&lt;br /&gt;Drexel Institute of Technology (1936–1970)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Drexel University History|url=http://drexel.edu/about/history/|accessdate=May 8, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|image = Drexel-newseal.png
|image_size = 150px
|motto = ''Ambition Can't Wait''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Tagline |url=https://drexel.edu/identity/drexel/tagline/ |website=Drexel University Identity Guidelines |accessdate=6 July 2019 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|established = {{start date|1891}}&lt;ref name=&quot;facts&quot;/&gt;
|type         = [[Private university|Private]] [[Nonprofit]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Research]] [[Coeducational]]
|affiliations = [[Middle States Association of Colleges and Schools|MSA]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Association of Independent Technological Universities|AITU]]&lt;br /&gt;[[National Association of Independent Colleges and Universities|NAICU]]
|endowment = $779.8 million (2018)&lt;ref&gt;As of June 30, 2018. {{cite web |url=https://www.nacubo.org/-/media/Nacubo/Documents/research/2018-Endowment-Market-Values--Final.pdf |title=U.S. and Canadian Institutions Listed by Fiscal Year (FY) 2018 Endowment Market Value and Change in Endowment Market Value from FY 2017 to FY 2018 |publisher=National Association of College and University Business Officers and Commonfund Institute |year= 2018 |access-date=2019-07-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|president = [[John Anderson Fry]] &lt;ref name=&quot;fry&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.drexel.edu/president/JohnFry/|archive-url=https://wayback.archive-it.org/all/20111019141156/http://www.drexel.edu/president/JohnFry/biography/|url-status=dead|archive-date=October 19, 2011|title=Drexel University Office of the President: Meet John Fry|accessdate=December 2, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|vice-president = 
|provost = [[M. Brian Blake]]
|students = 24,190&lt;ref name=&quot;facts&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.drexel.edu/about/glance/fast-facts/ |title=Drexel University Facts and Figures |accessdate=February 3, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|undergrad = 15,498&lt;ref name=&quot;facts&quot;/&gt;
|postgrad = 8,692&lt;ref name=&quot;facts&quot;/&gt;
|city = [[Philadelphia]]
|state = [[Pennsylvania]]
|country = United States
|coor = {{Coord|39.954|-75.188|display=inline,title|scale:5000}}
|campus = Urban
|colors = Blue and Gold&lt;ref name=colors&gt;{{cite web|title=Graphic Identity Program |url=http://www.drexel.edu/about/communications/policies/ |work=Drexel University |publisher=Office of University Communications |accessdate=March 9, 2012 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120419134803/http://drexel.edu/about/communications/policies/ |archivedate=April 19, 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;{{color box|#07294D}}&amp;nbsp;{{color box|#FFC600}}
|athletics = [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]] -  [[Colonial Athletic Association]]
|athletics_nickname = [[Drexel Dragons|Dragons]]
|mascot = Mario the Magnificent
|sports = 18 varsity teams&lt;br /&gt;31 club teams
|free_label = Newspaper
|free = ''[[The Triangle (newspaper)|The Triangle]]''
|website = {{URL|www.drexel.edu|Drexel.edu}}
|logo = [[File:Drexel-logo.png|250px|Drexel University logo]]
|footnotes =
}}

'''Drexel University''' is a [[private university|private]] [[research university]] with its main campus in [[Philadelphia]], [[Pennsylvania]]. It was founded in 1891 by [[Anthony J. Drexel]], a [[financier]] and [[philanthropist]]. Founded as '''Drexel Institute of Art, Science, and Industry''', it was renamed '''Drexel Institute of Technology''' in 1936, before assuming the name Drexel University in 1970.

{{as of|2015}}, more than 26,000 students were enrolled in over 70 undergraduate programs and more than 100 master's, doctoral, and professional programs at the university.&lt;ref name=&quot;facts&quot; /&gt; Drexel's [[cooperative education]] program (co-op) is a prominent aspect of the school's degree programs, offering students the opportunity to gain up to 18 months of paid, full-time work experience in a field relevant to their undergraduate major or graduate degree program prior to graduation.
{{toclimit|3}}

==History==
[[File:Anthony J. Drexel by Moses Ezekiel (1844-1917) - Drexel University - IMG 7320.JPG|thumb|[[Anthony J. Drexel (Ezekiel)|Statue of Anthony J. Drexel]] by [[Moses J. Ezekiel]], 1904. Moved to the Drexel campus in 1966.]]
[[File:Drexel Main Building c.1892.jpg|right|thumb|The Main Building, dedicated in 1891.]]
[[File:Clock sculpture - Drexel University - IMG 7332.JPG|right|thumb|Monumental conical pendulum clock by [[Eugène Farcot]], sculpture by [[Albert-Ernest Carrier-Belleuse]]. Donated in 1912 to the University. Main building, great court.]]
{{Main|History of Drexel University}}

Drexel University was founded in 1891 as the Drexel Institute of Art, Science and Industry, by Philadelphia financier and philanthropist [[Anthony J. Drexel]]. The original mission of the institution was to provide educational opportunities in the &quot;practical arts and sciences&quot; for women and men of all backgrounds. The institution became known as the Drexel Institute of Technology in 1936, and in 1970 the Drexel Institute of Technology gained university status, becoming Drexel University.

Although there were many changes during its first century, the university's identity has been held constant as a privately controlled, non-sectarian, coeducational center of higher learning, distinguished by a commitment to practical education and hands-on experience in an occupational setting. The central aspect of Drexel University's focus on career preparation, in the form of its cooperative education program, was introduced in 1919. The program became integral to the university's unique educational experience. Participating students alternate periods of classroom-based study with periods of full-time, [[Internship|practical work experience]] related to their academic major and career interests.

Between 1995 and 2009, Drexel University underwent a period of significant change to its programs, enrollment, and facilities under the leadership of Dr. [[Constantine Papadakis]], the university's president during that time. Papadakis oversaw Drexel's largest expansion in its history, with a 471 percent increase in its endowment and a 102 percent increase in student enrollment. His leadership also guided the university toward improved performance in collegiate rankings, a more selective approach to admissions, and a more rigorous academic program at all levels. It was during this period of expansion that Drexel acquired and assumed management of the former MCP Hahnemann University, creating the [[Drexel University College of Medicine]] in 2002. In 2006, the university established the [[Thomas R. Kline School of Law]], and in 2011 the School of Law achieved full accreditation by the [[American Bar Association]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://earlemacklaw.drexel.edu/about/ABA_accreditation/ |title=Drexel University Earle Mack School of Law ABA Accreditation |accessdate=December 2, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Dr. [[Constantine Papadakis]] died of pneumonia in April 2009 while still employed as the university's president. His successor, [[John Anderson Fry]], was formerly the president of [[Franklin &amp; Marshall College]] and served as the Executive Vice President of the [[University of Pennsylvania]].&lt;ref name=&quot;fry&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fandm.edu/past-presidents/john-fry |title=Past Presidents: John Fry |accessdate=December 2, 2011 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120112093452/http://www.fandm.edu/past-presidents/john-fry |archivedate=January 12, 2012  }}&lt;/ref&gt; Under Fry's leadership, Drexel has continued its expansion, including the July 2011 acquisition of [[The Academy of Natural Sciences]].

==Academics==
===Schools and colleges===
====College of Arts and Sciences====
{{main|Drexel University College of Arts and Sciences}}
The College of Arts and Sciences was formed in 1990 when Drexel merged the two existing College of Sciences and College of Humanities together.

====Antoinette Westphal College of Media Arts and Design====
{{main|Antoinette Westphal College of Media Arts and Design}}
The College of Media Arts and Design &quot;fosters the study, exploration and management of the arts: media, design, the performing and visual&quot;. The college offers sixteen undergraduate programs, and 6 graduate programs, in modern art and design fields that range from graphic design and dance to fashion design and television management. Its wide range of programs has helped the college earn full accreditation from the [[National Association of Schools of Art and Design]], the [[National Architectural Accrediting Board]], and the [[Council for Interior Design Accreditation]].

====Bennett S. LeBow College of Business====
{{Main|Bennett S. LeBow College of Business}}
The Bennett S. LeBow College of Business history dates to the founding in 1891 of the Drexel Institute, that later became Drexel University, and of its Business Department in 1896. Today LeBow offers thirteen undergraduate majors, eight graduate programs, and two doctoral programs; 22 percent of Drexel University's undergraduate students are enrolled in a LeBow College of Business program. [[File:SR2015 Drexel Campus 162.jpg|thumb|Gerri C. Lebow Hall, home of the LeBow College of Business]]

The LeBow College of Business has been ranked as the 38th best private business school in the nation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Triangle reports Business Week 2009 Rankings&quot;&gt;{{cite news |date=March 13, 2009 |url=http://media.www.thetriangle.org/media/storage/paper689/news/2009/03/13/News/Business.Week.2009.Ranks.Lebow.In.Top.40-3671549.shtml |title=Business Week 2009 ranks LeBow in top 40 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20101208161215/http://media.www.thetriangle.org/media/storage/paper689/news/2009/03/13/News/Business.Week.2009.Ranks.Lebow.In.Top.40-3671549.shtml |archivedate=December 8, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its online MBA program is ranked 14th in the world by the ''[[Financial Times]]''; the publication also ranks the undergraduate business program at LeBow as 19th in the United States. The part-time MBA program ranks 1st in academic quality in the 2015 edition of ''[[Business Insider|Business Insider's]]'' rankings. Undergraduate and graduate entrepreneurship programs are ranked 19th in the country by the ''[[The Princeton Review|Princeton Review]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;drexel.edu&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|title = Drexel University Rankings - Drexel University|url = http://drexel.edu/about/glance/rankings/|website = Drexel University|access-date = February 18, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=====School of Economics=====
Economics programs at the LeBow College of Business are housed within the School of Economics. In addition to the undergraduate program in economics, the school is home to an M.S. in Economics program as well as a PhD program in economics. Faculty members in the School of Economics have been published in the ''[[The American Economic Review|American Economic Review]]'', ''[[The RAND Journal of Economics|Rand Journal of Economics]]'', and ''[[The Review of Economics and Statistics|Review of Economics and Statistics]].'' The school has been ranked among the best in the world for its extensive research into matters of international trade.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = School of Economics|url = http://www.lebow.drexel.edu/faculty-and-research/disciplines/economics|website = www.lebow.drexel.edu|access-date = February 18, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====College of Engineering====
{{main|Drexel University College of Engineering}}
Drexel's [[Drexel University College of Engineering|College of Engineering]] is one of its oldest and largest academic colleges, and served as the original focus of the career-oriented school upon its founding in 1891. The College of Engineering is home to several notable alumni, including two astronauts; financier [[Bennett S. LeBow]], for whom the university's College of Business is named; and [[Paul Baran]], inventor of the packet-switched network. Today, Drexel University's College of Engineering, which is home to 19 percent of the undergraduate student body,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = Drexel University {{!}} Best College {{!}} US News|url = http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/drexel-university-3256|website = colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com|access-date = February 18, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; is known for creating the world's first engineering degree in [[Appropriate Technology|appropriate technology]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| date = June 1, 2007| url =http://www.drexel.edu/catalog/ug/coe/appropriate-index.htm| title = Appropriate Technology| publisher= Drexel University Catalog| accessdate =September 3, 2007 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090123154051/http://www.drexel.edu/catalog/ug/coe/appropriate-index.htm |archivedate=January 23, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; The college is also one of only 17 U.S. universities to offer a bachelor's degree in architectural engineering, and only one of five private institutions to do so.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.univsource.com/architectural.htm |title=Architectural Engineering Schools/Programs in the United States of America |publisher=Univsource.com |accessdate=December 16, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.drexel.edu/academics/coe/cae/ugarch.asp |title=Drexel University College of Engineering: Architectural Engineering |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090217231017/http://drexel.edu/academics/coe/cae/ugarch.asp |archivedate=February 17, 2009  }}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Bossone Research Enterprese Center - Drexel University - IMG 7528.JPG|thumb|Edmund D. Bossone Research Center, located on Market Street '[[Avenue of Technology (Philadelphia)|Avenue of Technology]]']]

=====The Drexel Engineering Curriculum (tDEC)=====
The 2006 edition of [[U.S. News]] ranks the undergraduate engineering program #57 in the country and the 2007 edition of graduate schools ranks the graduate program #61. The 2008 edition ranks the University Engineering Program at #55 and in the 2009 US News Ranking, the university has moved up to the #52 position.

The engineering curriculum used by the school was originally called E4 (Enhanced Educational Experience for Engineers) which was established in 1986&lt;ref name=&quot;tdec&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|date=February 10, 2006|title=CoE plans to revamp entire engineering curriculum |url=http://media.www.thetriangle.org/media/storage/paper689/news/2006/02/10/News/Coe-Plans.To.Revamp.Entire.Engineering.Curriculum-1608638-page2.shtml |first=Daniel |last=Silva |publisher=The Triangle |accessdate=December 11, 2007 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20101209032607/http://media.www.thetriangle.org/media/storage/paper689/news/2006/02/10/News/Coe-Plans.To.Revamp.Entire.Engineering.Curriculum-1608638-page2.shtml |archivedate=December 9, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and funded in part by the Engineering Directorate of the [[National Science Foundation]].&lt;ref name=&quot;tdec2&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Warnock |first=Scott |author2=Andrew J. McCann |title=Structured, Online Evaluations and the First-Year Design Process |journal=Learning Technology |volume=6 |issue=4 |publisher=IEEE Computer Society |date=October 2004 |url=http://lttf.ieee.org/learn_tech/issues/october2004/index.html |accessdate=December 11, 2007 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070711052015/http://lttf.ieee.org/learn_tech/issues/october2004/index.html |archivedate=July 11, 2007 |url-status=dead  }}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1988 the program evolved into tDEC (the Drexel Engineering Curriculum)&lt;ref name=&quot;tdec2&quot; /&gt; which is composed of two full years of rigorous core engineering courses which encompass the freshman and sophomore years of the engineering student. The College of Engineering hasn't used the tDEC curriculum since approximately 2005.

====College of Computing and Informatics====
{{main|Drexel University College of Computing and Informatics}}
The [[Drexel University College of Computing and Informatics|College of Computing and Informatics]] is a recent addition to Drexel University, though its programs have been offered to students for many years. The college was formed by the consolidation of the former College of Information Science &amp; Technology (often called the &quot;iSchool&quot;), the Department of Computer Science, and the Computing and Security Technology program. Undergraduate and graduate programs in computer science, software engineering, data science, information systems, and computer security are offered by the college.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Frequently Asked Questions - College of Computing &amp; Informatics |url=http://drexel.edu/cci/about/frequently-asked-questions/ |website=College of Computing &amp; Informatics |access-date=February 18, 2016 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160212021744/http://drexel.edu/cci/about/frequently-asked-questions/ |archivedate=February 12, 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

====College of Medicine====
{{main|Drexel University College of Medicine}}
The [[Drexel University College of Medicine]] was added to the colleges and schools of the university in 2002, having been formed upon the acquisition of MCP Hahnemann University. In addition to its M.D. program, the College of Medicine offers more than 40 graduate programs in its Graduate School of Biomedical Sciences and [[Goodwin College of Professional Studies|Professional Studies]].

=====Graduate School of Biomedical Sciences and Professional Studies=====
The Graduate School of Biomedical Sciences and Professional studies offers both Master of Science and Doctor of Philosophy degree programs in fields like biochemistry, biotechnology, clinical research, and forensic science. The school also serves as the center for biomedical research at Drexel University.

====School of Biomedical Engineering, Science and Health Systems====
Founded in 1961 as the United States’ first Biomedical Engineering and Science Institute, the School of Biomedical Engineering, Science and Health Systems focuses on the emerging field of biomedical science at the undergraduate, graduate, and doctoral levels. Primary research areas within the school include [[bioinformatics]], [[biomechanics]], [[biomaterials]], [[neuroengineering]], and [[Cardiovascular medicine|cardiovascular]] engineering.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = Research Areas - School of Biomedical Engineering, Science and Health Systems|url = http://drexel.edu/biomed/research/research-areas/|website = School of Biomedical Engineering, Science and Health Systems|access-date = February 18, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====College of Nursing and Health Professions====
{{main|Drexel University College of Nursing and Health Professions}}
Formed in 2002 along with the College of Medicine, Drexel's [[Drexel University College of Nursing and Health Professions|College of Nursing and Health Professions]] offers more than 25 programs to undergraduate and graduate students in the fields of nursing, nutrition, health sciences, health services, and radiologic technology. The college's research into matters of nutrition and rehabilitation have garnered approximately $2.9 million in external research funding on an annual basis. The physician assistant program at Drexel's College of Nursing and Health Professions is ranked in the top 15 such programs in the United States; its anesthesia programs and physical therapy programs are, respectively, ranked as top-50 programs nationwide.&lt;ref name=&quot;drexel.edu&quot;/&gt;

====Richard C. Goodwin College of Professional Studies====
{{main|Goodwin College of Professional Studies}}
Established in 1892, the department now known as the [[Goodwin College of Professional Studies|College of Professional Studies]] has focused exclusively on educational programs and pursuits for nontraditional adult learners. Today, the Goodwin College of Professional Studies offers several options designed for adult learners at all stages of career and educational development. Bachelor of Science degree completion programs are offered in part-time evening or weekend formats; graduate programs and doctoral programs are offered at the graduate level, as are self-paced &quot;continuing education&quot; courses and nearly a dozen self-paced certification programs.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = Message from the Executive Director - Goodwin College of Professional Studies|url = http://drexel.edu/goodwin/about/message/|website = Goodwin College of Professional Studies|access-date = February 18, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Pennoni Honors College====
{{main|Pennoni Honors College}}
The [[Pennoni Honors College]], named for Drexel alumnus and trustee Dr. C.R. &quot;Chuck&quot; Pennoni '63, '66, Hon. '92, and his wife Annette, recognizes and promotes excellence among Drexel students. Students admitted to the Honors College live together and take many of the same classes; the college provides these students with access to unique cultural and social activities and a unique guest speaker series. Students are also involved in the university's Honors Student Advisory Committee and have the opportunity to take part in Drexel's &quot;Alternative Spring Break&quot;, an international study tour held each spring.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = The Honors Experience - Pennoni Honors College|url = http://drexel.edu/pennoni/honors/honors-experience/|website = Pennoni Honors College|access-date = February 18, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Earle Mack School of Law - Drexel University - IMG 7300.JPG|thumb|[[Thomas R. Kline School of Law]]]]

====Thomas R. Kline School of Law====
{{main|Thomas R. Kline School of Law}}
Upon its founding in 2006, the Thomas R. Kline School of Law, originally known as the Earle Mack School of Law, was the first law school founded in Philadelphia in more than three decades. The School of Law offers L.L.M. and Master of Legal Studies degrees, in addition to the flagship Juris Doctorate program, and uniquely offers cooperative education as part of its curriculum across all programs. In 2015, ''[[Bloomberg Business News|Bloomberg Business]]'' ranked the Kline School of Law as the second most underrated law school in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = Bloomberg Business Names Kline School of Law 2nd Most-Underrated Law School in U.S. - Kline School of Law|url = http://drexel.edu/law/news/articles/overview/2015/June/Law-School-Rankings-06292015/|website = Kline School of Law|access-date = February 18, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====School of Education====
One of the oldest schools within Drexel University, the modern School of Education dates back to the 1891 founding of the school. Originally, the Department of Education offered teacher training to women as one of its original, career-focused degree programs. Today, the School of Education offers a coeducational approach to teacher training at the elementary and secondary levels for undergraduates. Other undergraduate programs include those focused on the intersection between learning and technology, teacher certification for non-education majors, and a minor in education for students with an interest in instruction. Graduate degrees offered by the School of Education include those in administration and leadership, special education, higher education, mathematics education, international education, and educational creativity and innovation. Doctoral degrees are offered in educational leadership and learning technologies. As of right now, the school of education has 1,136 students total, 42 faculty members, 43 programs offered, and 17 degrees. 
[[File:Drexel University School of Education.jpg|thumb|Drexel University's School of Education offices are located on the third floor of the UCity Square building located at 3401 Market street.]]

====Dornsife School of Public Health====
{{main|Drexel University School of Public Health}}
The [[Drexel University School of Public Health|School of Public Health]] states that its mission is to &quot;provide education, conduct research, and partner with communities and organizations to improve the health of populations&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = Overview - Dornsife School of Public Health|url = http://drexel.edu/dornsife/about/overview/|website = Dornsife School of Public Health|access-date = February 18, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; To that end, the school offers both a B.S. and a minor in public health for undergraduate students as well as several options for students pursuing graduate and doctoral degrees in the field. At the graduate level, the Dornsife School offers both a Master of Public Health and an Executive Master of Public Health, as well as an M.S. in biostatistics and an M.S. in epidemiology. Two Doctor of Public Health degrees are also offered, as isa Doctor of Philosophy in epidemiology. The school's graduate and doctoral students are heavily invested in the research activities of the Dornsife School of Public Health, which has helped the school attract annual funding for its four research centers.

====Center for Hospitality and Sport Management====
The Center for Hospitality and Sport Management was formed in 2013, in an effort to house and consolidate academic programs in hospitality, tourism management, the culinary arts, and sport management. Academic programs combine the unique skills required of the sports and hospitality industries with the principles and curriculum espoused by the management programs within Drexel's LeBow College of Business.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = Center for Hospitality and Sport Management &lt; 2015-2016 Catalog {{!}} Drexel University|url = http://catalog.drexel.edu/undergraduate/centerforhospitalityandsportmanagement/|website = catalog.drexel.edu|access-date = February 18, 2016|archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20160318101056/http://catalog.drexel.edu/undergraduate/centerforhospitalityandsportmanagement/|archive-date = March 18, 2016|url-status = dead|df = dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Charles D. Close School of Entrepreneurship====
Focusing specifically on the skills required to successfully start and launch a business, the Charles D. Close School of Entrepreneurship is the first and only freestanding school of entrepreneurship in the United States. Undergraduate students take part in a B.A. program in entrepreneurship and innovation, while graduate students a combined Master of Science degree in biomedicine and entrepreneurship. Minors in entrepreneurship are also offered to undergraduate students.

=====Laurence A. Baiada Institute for Entrepreneurship=====
Housed within the Close School is the Baiada Institute for Entrepreneurship. The institute serves as an incubator for Drexel student startups, providing resources and mentorships to students and some post-graduates who are starting their own business while enrolled in one of the Close School's degree programs or academic minors.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = About - Baiada Institute|url = http://www.drexel.edu/baiada/about/overview/|website = Baiada Institute|access-date = February 18, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Online education===
Drexel University launched its first Internet-based education program, a master's degree in Library &amp; Information Science, in 1996.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://online.drexel.edu/about/accreditation.aspx |title=About Drexel University Online |publisher=Online.Drexel.edu |accessdate=November 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2001, Drexel created its wholly owned, for-profit online education subsidiary, Drexel e-Learning, Inc., better known as Drexel University Online.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://online.drexel.edu/ |title=Drexel University Online - Accredited Online College Degrees &amp; Online MBA Programs |publisher=Online.Drexel.edu |accessdate=November 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://philadelphia.cbslocal.com/2013/03/26/continuing-education/ |title=Continuing Education « CBS Philly |publisher=Philadelphia.cbslocal.com |date=March 26, 2013 |accessdate=December 16, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was announced in October 2013 that Drexel University Online would no longer be a for-profit venture, but rather become an internal division within the university to better serve its online student population.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://technical.ly/philly/2013/10/18/drexel-names-vp-of-online-learning/?amp;co=f000000009816s-1158206718 |title=Drexel Online will no longer be a for-profit venture » Technical.ly Philly |publisher=Technical.ly |date=October 18, 2013 |accessdate=December 16, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although headquartered in Philadelphia, Drexel announced a new Washington, D.C., location in December 2012 to serve as both an academic and outreach center, catering to the online student population.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://thetriangle.org/2013/01/18/drexel-reveals-d-c-expansion/ |title=Drexel reveals D.C. expansion |accessdate=January 23, 2013 |url-status=bot: unknown |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130123023842/http://thetriangle.org/2013/01/18/drexel-reveals-d-c-expansion/ |archivedate=January 23, 2013  }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bizjournals.com/washington/breaking_ground/2013/04/drexel-university-opening-dc-office.html |title=Daily D.C. permits for 2 April 2013: Drexel University opening D.C. office - Washington Business Journal |publisher=Bizjournals.com |date=April 3, 2013 |accessdate=December 16, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In an effort to create greater awareness of distance learning and to recognize exceptional leaders and best practices in the field, Drexel University Online founded National Distance Learning Week, in conjunction with the United States Distance Learning Association, in 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Schumann |first=Anna |url=http://www.onlinecolleges.net/2012/11/08/national-distance-learning-week-celebrates-online-ed-advancements-personnel/ |title=National Distance Learning Week Celebrates Online Ed Advancements, Personnel |publisher=OnlineColleges.net |accessdate=December 16, 2013 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131216184205/http://www.onlinecolleges.net/2012/11/08/national-distance-learning-week-celebrates-online-ed-advancements-personnel/ |archivedate=December 16, 2013  }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://online.drexel.edu/news/ndlw.aspx |title=National Distance Learning Week Drexel Online |publisher=Online.Drexel.edu |accessdate=November 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; In September 2010, Drexel University Online received the Sloan-C award for institution-wide excellence in online education indicating that it had exceptional programs of &quot;demonstrably high quality&quot; at the regional and national levels and across disciplines.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Sloan Consortium Honors Drexel with Excellence in Online Education Award |url=http://www.drexel.edu/news/headlines/sloan-consortium-honors-drexel-with-excellence-in-online-education-award.aspx |publisher=Drexel University |accessdate=February 16, 2011 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110116130244/http://drexel.edu/news/headlines/sloan-consortium-honors-drexel-with-excellence-in-online-education-award.aspx |archivedate=January 16, 2011  }}&lt;/ref&gt; Drexel University Online won the 2008 [[United States Distance Learning Association]]'s Best Practices Awards for Distance Learning Programming.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|year=2008 |title=USDLA Distance Learning Awards - 2008 |url=http://www.usdla.org/index.php?cid=118 |publisher=United states Distance Learning Association |accessdate=September 1, 2010 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100221125027/http://www.usdla.org/index.php?cid=118 |archivedate=February 21, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2007, the online education subsidiary had a revenue of $40 million.&lt;ref name=&quot;DOnline&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|date=August 19, 2007 |title=A coast-to-coast vision – Drexel's Papadakis has driven growth |first=Kathy |last=Boccella |work=The Philadelphia Inquirer |page=A01}}&lt;/ref&gt; In March 2013, Drexel Online had more than 7,000 unique students from all 50 states and more than 20 countries pursuing a bachelor's, master's, or certificate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.drexel.com/news/story.aspx?nid=14140 |title=Drexel University Online - In The News |publisher=Drexel.com |accessdate=December 16, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; {{as of|2013|December}}, Drexel University Online offers more than 100 fully accredited master's degrees, bachelor's degrees and certificate programs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://online.drexel.edu/online-degrees/degrees.aspx |title=Accredited Online Degree Programs Drexel Online |publisher=Online.Drexel.edu |accessdate=November 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Cooperative education program===
Drexel's longstanding cooperative education, or &quot;co-op&quot; program is one of the largest and oldest in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.drexel.edu/scdc/coop/about/index.html |title=Drexel Co-op |publisher=Drexel University |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20101121010812/http://www.drexel.edu/scdc/coop/about/index.html |archive-date=November 21, 2010  }}&lt;/ref&gt; Drexel has a fully [[internet]]-based job database, where students can submit résumés and request interviews with any of the thousands of companies that offer positions. Students also have the option of obtaining a co-op via independent search. A student graduating from Drexel's 5-year degree program typically has a total of 18 months of co-op with up to three different companies. The majority of co-ops are paid, averaging $15,912 per 6-month period, however this figure changes with major.&lt;ref name=&quot;co-op&quot;&gt;{{cite web |year=2006 |url=http://www.drexel.edu/em/ug/coop/employers.html |title=Drexel Co-op Employers |publisher=Drexel University |access-date=March 24, 2006 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20060515002401/http://www.drexel.edu/em/ug/coop/employers.html |archive-date=May 15, 2006 |url-status=dead  }}&lt;/ref&gt; About one third of Drexel graduates are offered full-time positions by their co-op employers right after graduation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/drexel-university-3256 |title=Drexel Co-op |publisher=US News and World Reports}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Research activity===
Drexel's knowledge community of researchers and scholars are socially, professionally and intellectually diverse. The ''[[Carnegie Classification of Institutions of Higher Education]]'' classifies Drexel among &quot;R1: Doctoral Universities – Highest research activity.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://carnegieclassifications.iu.edu/lookup/view_institution.php?unit_id=212054|title=Drexel University|website=Carnegie Classifications|access-date=24 January 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; The university was ranked 51st in the 2018 edition of the &quot;Top 100 Worldwide Universities Granted U.S. Utility Patents&quot; list released by the [[National Academy of Inventors]] and the [[Intellectual Property Owners Association]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://drexel.edu/now/archive/2019/June/Drexel-Patents-Rankings-NAI-IPO/|title=Drexel Moves Forward in Prestigious List of Top 100 International Universities Granted US Utility Patents|website=Drexel University|access-date=17 December 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Research Centers and Institutes at Drexel include:

{{div col|colwidth=30em}}
* '''Arts and Sciences'''
** Center for Interdisciplinary Programs
** Center for Public Policy
** Mobilities and Research Policy
* '''Education'''
** The Center for Labor Markets and Policy
** The Center for the Prevention of School-Aged Violence
** The Math Forum
* '''Information Science'''
** Data Mining &amp; Bioinformatics Lab
** Geographic Information Systems &amp; Spatial Analysis Lab
** Institute for Healthcare Informatics
** Metadata Research Center
* '''Media Arts &amp; Design'''
** Kal and Lucille Rudman Institute for Entertainment Industry Studies
** The RePlay Lab
* '''Business and Leadership'''
** Laurence A. Baiada Institute for Entrepreneurship
** Center for Corporate Governance
** Sovereign Institute for Strategic Leadership
** Center for Corporate Reputation Management
* '''Engineering'''
** [[A.J. Drexel Plasma Institute]]
** A.J. Drexel Applied Communications and Information Networking (ACIN) Institute
** A. J. Drexel Institute of Basic and Applied Protein Science
** A. J. Drexel Nanotechnology Institute (DNI)
** Ben Franklin Technology Partners' Nanotechnology Institute
** Center for Electric Power Engineering
** Center for Telecommunications and Information Networking
** Centralized Research Facilities (CRF)
* '''Public Health'''
** Autism Public Health Research Institute
** Center for Health Equality (CHE)
** Center for Public Health Readiness and Communication (CPHRC)
** Center for Nonviolence and Social Justice
** National Resource Center on Advancing Emergency Preparedness
** Center for Public Health Practice
{{div col end}}

===Rankings===
{{Infobox US university ranking
| GUR =
| ARWU_W = 301–400
| ARWU_N = 95–116
| USNWR_W = 405
| USNWR_NU = 97
| QS_W = 561–570
| THE_WSJ = 96
| THES_W = 401–500
| Wamo_NU = 156
| Forbes = 226
}}

{|class=&quot;infobox&quot; style=&quot;width: 22em;&quot;
|-
! colspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;font-size: 100%; text-align: center;&quot; |
&lt;big&gt;USNWR graduate school rankings&lt;/big&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;USNWR Grad School Rankings&quot;&gt;{{cite magazine|title=Drexel University Graduate School Rankings|magazine=U.S. News &amp; World Report|access-date=September 12, 2019|url=https://www.usnews.com/best-graduate-schools/drexel-university-212054/overall-rankings}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| Business
| 84
|-
| Education
| 172
|-
| Engineering
| 75
|-
| Law
| 100
|-
| Medicine: Primary Care
| 91-120
|-
| Medicine: Research
| 84
|-
| Nursing: Doctorate
| 94
|-
| Nursing: Master's
| 93
|}

{|class=&quot;infobox&quot; style=&quot;width: 22em;&quot;
|-
! colspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;font-size: 100%; text-align: center;&quot; |
&lt;big&gt;USNWR departmental rankings&lt;/big&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;USNWR Grad School Rankings&quot;/&gt;
|-
| Biological Sciences
| 159
|-
| Chemistry
| 122
|-
| Clinical Psychology
| 87
|-
| Computer Science
| 82
|-
| Library &amp; Information Studies
| 11
|-
| Mathematics
| 94
|-
| Nursing-Anesthesia
| 43
|-
| Physical Therapy
| 53
|-
| Physician Assistant
| 10
|-
| Physics
| 91
|-
| Psychology
| 148
|-
| Public Affairs
| 151
|-
| Public Health
| 19
|}
In its 2020 rankings, ''[[U.S. News &amp; World Report]]'' ranked Drexel tied for 97th among national universities in the United States, 23rd in the &quot;Most Innovative Schools&quot; category, and 74th in &quot;Best Value Schools&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;USNWR&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=U.S. News Best Colleges Rankings - Drexel University |url=https://www.usnews.com/best-colleges/drexel-university-3256/overall-rankings |magazine=U.S. News &amp; World Report |access-date=September 12, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In its 2018 rankings, ''[[Times Higher Education World University Rankings]]'' and the ''[[Wall Street Journal]]'' ranked Drexel 74th among national universities and 351st-400th among international universities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Drexel University | url=https://www.timeshighereducation.com/world-university-rankings/drexel-university | work=Times Higher Education | access-date=September 24, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In its 2018 rankings, ''[[Forbes]]'' ranked Drexel 24th among STEM universities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Top 25 STEM Colleges 2018 | url=https://www.forbes.com/sites/cartercoudriet/2018/08/20/top-25-stem-colleges-2018/ | work=Forbes | access-date=August 31, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2019, it also ranked Drexel 226th among 650 national universities, liberal arts colleges and service academies, 120th among research universities, 154th among private universities, and 96th among universities in the Northeast.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Drexel University |url=https://www.forbes.com/colleges/drexel-university/?list=top-colleges |magazine=Forbes |date=August 15, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2016, ''[[Bloomberg Businessweek]]'' ranked the undergraduate business program 78th in the country.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.bloomberg.com/features/2016-best-undergrad-business-schools/ |title=Best Undergraduate Business Schools 2016 |publisher=Bloomberg L.P. |access-date=December 29, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In 2014, Business Insider ranked Drexel's graduate business school 19th in the country for networking.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.businessinsider.com/best-business-schools-for-networking-2014-9 |title= Best Business Schools For Networking - Business Insider |date= September 16, 2014 |work= Business Insider |access-date= April 11, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2014, ''The Princeton Review'' ranked Drexel 20th in its list of worst college libraries.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url= http://www.princetonreview.com/schoolList.aspx?id=757 |title= This is a Library?|date = February 5, 2015 |access-date= February 5, 2015 |website= |publisher= The Princeton Review |last= |first=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Campuses==
{{Main|Campus of Drexel University}}
Drexel University's programs are divided across three Philadelphia-area campuses: the [[Drexel University Main Campus|University City Campus]], the Center City  Campus and the [[Drexel University Queen Lane Campus|Queen Lane College of Medicine Campus]].
[[File:QueenLaneCampus.jpg|thumb|left|The Queen Lane Campus]]

===University City Main Campus===
The {{convert|77|acre|ha|adj=on}} University City Main Campus of Drexel University is located just west of the [[Schuylkill River]] in the [[University City, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania|University City]] district of [[Philadelphia]]. It is Drexel's largest and oldest campus; the campus contains the university's administrative offices and serves as the main academic center for students. The northern, residential portion of the main campus is located in the [[Powelton Village]] section of West Philadelphia. The two prominent performing stages at Drexel University are the Mandell Theater and the Main Auditorium. The Main Auditorium dates back to the founding of Drexel and construction of its main hall. It features over 1000 seats, and a [[pipe organ]] installed in 1928. The organ was purchased by [[Saturday Evening Post]] publisher [[Cyrus H. K. Curtis]] after he had donated a similar organ, the [[Curtis Organ]], to nearby University of Pennsylvania and it was suggested that he do the same for Drexel.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.drexel.edu/univrel/new/alumnimagazine/fall_2004.pdf Drexel Legends and Traditions] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110103201458/http://www.drexel.edu/univrel/new/alumnimagazine/fall_2004.pdf |date=January 3, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The 424-seat Mandell Theater was built in 1973 and features a more performance-oriented stage, including a full [[fly system]], modern stage lighting facilities, stadium seating, and accommodations for wheelchairs. It is used for the semiannual spring musical, as well as various plays and many events.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ucityphila.org/cityguide/go/294 |title=Mandell Theater at Drexel University |accessdate=March 6, 2007 |url-status=bot: unknown |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070306072608/http://www.ucityphila.org/cityguide/go/294 |archivedate=March 6, 2007  }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Queen Lane Campus===
The Queen Lane Campus was purchased by Drexel University as part of its acquisition of MCP Hahnemann University. It is located in the East Falls neighborhood of northwest Philadelphia and is primarily utilized by first- and second-year medical students, and researchers. A free shuttle is available, connecting the Queen Lane Campus to the Center City Hahnemann and University City Main campuses.&lt;ref name=&quot;Queen Lane&quot;&gt;{{Cite news| date = July 23, 2004| url =http://www.thetriangle.org/media/storage/paper689/news/2004/07/23/News/Queen.Lane.Finishes.First.Year.As.Part.Of.U-695370.shtml?norewrite200605201734&amp;sourcedomain=www.thetriangle.org| title =Queen Lane finishes first year as part of U.| publisher =The Triangle| accessdate =May 20, 2006 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20101208184817/http://media.www.thetriangle.org/media/storage/paper689/news/2004/07/23/News/Queen.Lane.Finishes.First.Year.As.Part.Of.U-695370.shtml |archivedate=December 8, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Center City Campus ===
{{Main|Drexel University College of Medicine}}
The Center City Campus is in the middle of Philadelphia, straddling the Vine Street Expressway between Broad and 15th Streets. Shuttle service is offered between the Center City Campus and both the University City and Queen Lane campuses of the university.

===The Academy of Natural Sciences===
[[File:T-rex exhibit Philadelphia.jpg|thumb|A complete ''[[Tyrannosaurus rex]]'' fossil on display with other dinosaur specimens at The Academy of Natural Sciences.]]
{{main|Academy of Natural Sciences of Drexel University}}
In 2011, [[The Academy of Natural Sciences]] entered into an agreement to become a subsidiary of Drexel University. Founded in 1812, the Academy of Natural Sciences is America's oldest natural history museum and is a world leader in biodiversity and environmental research.

===Drexel University Sacramento===
{{Main|Drexel University Sacramento}}
On January 5, 2009, Drexel University opened the Center for Graduate Studies in [[Sacramento, California]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sacramento.drexel.edu/about-drexel/ |title=About Us Overview |publisher=Drexel University |accessdate=November 14, 2010 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20101110122108/http://sacramento.drexel.edu/about-drexel/ |archivedate=November 10, 2010  }}&lt;/ref&gt; Eventually renamed Drexel University Sacramento upon the addition of an undergraduate program in business administration, the campus also offered an Ed.D. program in Educational Leadership and Management and master's degree programs in Business Administration, Finance, Higher Education, Human Resource Development, Public Health, and Interdepartmental Medical Science.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sacramento.drexel.edu/programs/ |title=Graduate Programs in Sacramento |publisher=Drexel University |accessdate=November 14, 2010 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20101113021832/http://sacramento.drexel.edu/programs/ |archivedate=November 13, 2010  }}&lt;/ref&gt; On March 5, 2015, Drexel University announced the closure of the Sacramento campus, with an 18-month &quot;phase out&quot; period designed to allow current students to complete their degrees.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Drexel Closing Sacramento Campus |url=http://www.sacbee.com/news/local/education/article12609713.html |newspaper=The Sacramento Bee |accessdate=March 5, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Student life==
[[File:Buckley Volleyball Courts at Drexel University.JPG|left|thumb|Buckley Volleyball Courts on 33rd and Arch Streets]]

===Student government===
The Undergraduate Student Government Association of Drexel University works with administrators to solve student problems and tries to promote communication between the students and the administration.

===Graduate Students Association===
The Graduate Student Association &quot;advocates the interests and addresses concerns of graduate students at Drexel; strives to enhance graduate student life at the University in all aspects, from academic to campus security; and provides a formal means of communication between graduate students and the University community&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pages.drexel.edu/~dsogsa/ |title=Drexel University Graduate Students Association |accessdate=October 2, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Campus Activities Board===
The Campus Activities Board (CAB) is an undergraduate, student-run event planning organization. CAB creates events for the undergraduate population. To assist with planning and organization, the Campus Activities Board is broken down into 5 committees: Special Events, Traditions, Marketing, Culture and Discovery, and Performing and Fine Arts.

===Jewish Life on Campus===
Drexel has an approximate Jewish population of 5% and has both a Chabad House and a Hillel. Both provide services to Jewish and non-Jewish students at Drexel. Due to the recent influx of Orthodox Jewish students&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.jewishexponent.com/2018/08/22/drexel-expects-influx-of-orthodox-students/|title=Drexel Expects Influx of Orthodox Students|last=Zighelboim|first=Selah Maya|date=2018-08-22|website=Jewish Exponent|language=en-US|access-date=2019-11-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Chabad now has its own daily kosher meal plan. The Hillel also has hot kosher food but only on select nights.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://drexelhillel.com/students/kosher-dining/|title=Kosher Dining|website=Hillel at Drexel University|language=en-US|access-date=2019-11-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; There is also an [[eruv]] which is jointly managed by Jewish students from Drexel and the [[University of Pennsylvania]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.universitycityeruv.org/|title=The University City Eruv Corporation|website=www.universitycityeruv.org|access-date=2019-11-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Press and radio===
====Radio====
{{Main|WKDU}}
WKDU is Drexel's student-run FM radio station, with membership open to all undergraduate students. Its status as an 800-[[watt]], non-commercial station in a major market city has given it a wider audience and a higher profile than many other [[college radio]] stations.

====Television====
DUTV is Drexel's Philadelphia [[cable television]] station. The student operated station is part of the Paul F. Harron Studios at Drexel University. The purpose of DUTV is to provide &quot;the people of Philadelphia with quality educational television, and providing Drexel students the opportunity to gain experience in television management and production&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;DUTV&quot;&gt;[http://dutv.drexel.edu/homepage/DUTV.html DUTV] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090221072637/http://dutv.drexel.edu/homepage/DUTV.html |date=February 21, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The Programing includes an eclectic variety of shows from a bi-monthly news show, DNews, to old films, talk shows dealing with important current issues and music appreciation shows.&lt;ref name=&quot;DUTV&quot; /&gt;

====Publications====
''[[The Triangle (newspaper)|The Triangle]]'' has been the university's newspaper since 1926 and currently publishes on a weekly basis every Friday. The yearbook was first published in 1911 and named the Lexerd in 1913.&lt;ref name=&quot;Timeline&quot;&gt;{{cite web|date=August 29, 2006 |title=Timeline of Drexel University |url=http://www.library.drexel.edu/archives/history/timeline.html |publisher=Drexel University Archives |accessdate=September 22, 2010 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090228204159/http://library.drexel.edu/archives/history/timeline.html |archivedate=February 28, 2009  }}&lt;/ref&gt; Prior to the publishing of a campus wide yearbook in 1911 ''The Hanseatic'' and ''The Eccentric'' were both published in 1896 as class books.&lt;ref name=&quot;DUArch&quot;&gt;{{cite web|year=2008 |url=http://archives.library.drexel.edu/archives/31 |title=Early photographs of the Drexel Institute of Art, Science, and Industry 1885-1936 |publisher=Drexel University Archives |accessdate=December 2, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other publications include ''MAYA'', the undergraduate student literary and artistic magazine; ''D&amp;M Magazine'', Design &amp; Merchandising students crafted magazine; ''The Smart Set from Drexel University'', an online magazine founded in 2005; and ''The Drexelist'' a blog-style news source founded in 2010.

The Drexel Publishing Group serves as a medium for literary publishing on campus. The Drexel Publishing Group oversees ''ASK'' (The Journal of the College of Arts and Sciences at Drexel University), ''[[Painted Bride Quarterly]]'', a 36-year-old national literary magazine housed at Drexel; ''The 33rd'', an annual anthology of student and faculty writing at Drexel; ''DPG Online Magazine'', and ''Maya'', the undergraduate literary and artistic magazine. The Drexel Publishing Group also serves as a pedagogical organization by allowing students to intern and work on its publications.

===Housing===
[[File:North Hall.JPG|thumb|North Hall by architect [[Michael Graves]]]]

Drexel requires all non-commuting first- and second-year students to live in one of its ten residence halls or in &quot;university approved housing&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web 
| url = http://www.drexel.edu/dbs/universityHousing/assignment-policies/2YrsResReq/
| title = Drexel University Housing Policies
}}&lt;/ref&gt; First year students must live in one of the residence halls designated specifically for first-years. These residence halls include Millennium, Bentley, Kelly, Myers, Towers, Van Rensselaer, North, and Race Halls. Kelly, Myers, Towers, and Bentley Halls are traditional residence halls (a bedroom shared with one or more roommate(s) and one bathroom per floor), while Race, North, Caneris, and Van Rensselaer Halls are suite-style residence halls (shared bedrooms, private bathrooms, kitchens, and common area within the suite). Millennium Hall, Drexel's newest residence hall, is a modified suite (a bedroom shared with one roommate, and bathrooms and showers that look like closets with open sinks in the hallway).

Each residence hall is designed to facilitate the Freshman Experience in a slightly different way. Millennium, Kelly, and Towers Halls are all typical residence halls. Myers Hall offers &quot;Living Learning Communities&quot; where a group of students who share common interests such as language or major live together. Most of Bentley Hall is reserved for students of the [[Pennoni Honors College]], although some floors are occupied by other students.

Second-year students have the option of living in a residence hall designated for upperclassmen, or &quot;university approved housing&quot;. The residence halls for upperclassmen are North and Caneris Halls. North Hall operates under the For Students By Students Residential Experience Engagement Model, developed by the Residential Living Office. There are many apartments that are university approved that second-year students can choose to live in. Three of the largest apartment buildings that fit this description are Chestnut Square, University Crossings, and The Summit, all owned by [[American Campus Communities]]. Many other students live in smaller apartment buildings or individual townhouse-style apartments in [[Powelton Village, Philadelphia|Powelton Village]]. A second-year student can choose one of the already listed university approved housing options or petition the university to add a new property to the approved list.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web
 |url         = http://drexel.edu/dbs/universityHousing/upperclassmen/2016approved/
 |title       = 2016-2017 University-Approved Properties - Drexel Business Services
 |website     = Drexel Business Services
 |access-date = February 25, 2016
 |url-status     = dead
 |archiveurl  = https://web.archive.org/web/20160220231054/http://drexel.edu/dbs/universityHousing/upperclassmen/2016approved/
 |archivedate = February 20, 2016
 |df          = dmy-all
}}&lt;/ref&gt; While living in a university approved apartment offers the freedom of living outside a residence hall, due to the Drexel co-op system, many students end up in the residence halls because they operate on a quarter to quarter basis, and don't require students to be locked into leases.

Graduate students can live in Stiles Hall.

All residence halls except Caneris Hall and Stiles Memorial Hall are located north of Arch Street between 34th Street and 32nd Street in the [[Powelton Village, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania|Powelton Village]] area.

===Student organizations===
Drexel University recognizes over 250 student organizations in the following categories:&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.forbes.com/colleges/drexel-university/|title=Drexel University|work=Forbes|access-date=August 22, 2017|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Academic
* Club Sports
* Community Service/Social Action
* Cultural
* Fraternity &amp; Sorority Life
* General Interest
* Honorary
* Media
* Performing and Fine Arts
* Political
* Spiritual &amp; Religious

===Honorary and professional organizations===
The following groups are recognized as honors or professional organizations under the Office of Campus Activities and are not considered part of social Greek life at Drexel University.
* [[Alpha Kappa Psi]] - Eta Psi chapter (est. 2008) - ''Professional Business Fraternity''
* [[Alpha Omega Epsilon]] - ''Social and Professional Sorority for Engineers''
* [[Alpha Phi Omega]], Zeta Theta chapter (est. 1948) - ''National Service Fraternity''
* [[Alpha Phi Sigma]] - ''National Criminal Justice Honor Society''
* [[Beta Alpha Psi]], Delta Tau chapter - ''Honors Fraternity for Accounting, Finance and MIS''
* [[Beta Beta Beta]] - ''National Biological Honor Society''
* [[Beta Gamma Sigma]], - ''International Business Honor Society''
* [[Chi Epsilon]] - ''National Civil Engineering Honors Society''
* [[Delta Epsilon Iota]], Upsilon Delta chapter - ''(Dragons for Excellence and Inspiration) National Honors Society''
* [[Eta Kappa Nu]], Beta Alpha chapter (est. 1935) - ''Electrical Engineering Honor Society''
* [[Gamma Sigma Sigma]] - ''National Service Sorority''
* [[Kappa Delta Pi]] - International Honor Society in Education
* [[Phi Chi Theta]] - Zeta Delta (est. 2008) - ''Professional Business Fraternity''
* [[Phi Eta Sigma]] - ''National Honors Society''
* [[Phi Sigma Pi]], Gamma Xi chapter - ''Honors Fraternity''
* [[Pi Nu Epsilon]] - ''Music and Performing Arts Fraternity''
* [[Pi Sigma Alpha]], Alpha Epsilon Chi chapter - ''The National Political Science Honor Society''
* [[Pi Tau Sigma]], Xi chapter - ''International Mechanical Engineering Fraternity''
* [[Psi Chi]] - ''International Honors Society - Psychology Fraternity''
* [[Tau Beta Pi]], Pennsylvania Zeta chapter - ''Engineering Honor Society''
* [[Upsilon Pi Epsilon]] - ''Computer Science Fraternity''

===Greek life===
Approximately 12 percent of Drexel's undergraduate population are members of a social Greek-letter organization. There are currently fourteen [[North-American Interfraternity Conference|Interfraternity Council]] (IFC) chapters, seven [[National Panhellenic Conference|Panhellenic Council]] (PHC) chapters and thirteen Multi-cultural Greek Council (MGC) chapters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.drexel.edu/studentlife/fsl/chapters.htm |title=Fraternity and Sorority Life |accessdate=October 23, 2004 |url-status=bot: unknown |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20041023100544/http://www.drexel.edu/studentlife/fsl/chapters.htm |archivedate=October 23, 2004  }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Two IFC chapters have been awarded Top Chapters in 2008 by their respective national organizations; [[Pi Kappa Alpha]], and [[Alpha Chi Rho]]. In 2013, [[Sigma Phi Epsilon]] and [[Alpha Epsilon Pi]] were awarded the Top Chapter award by their respective national headquarters.

{{col-start}}
{{col-break}}

====IFC fraternities====
* [[Alpha Chi Rho]], Lambda Chi Phi chapter (est. 1992)
* [[Alpha Epsilon Pi]], Delta Rho chapter (est. 1995)
* Alpha Pi Lambda, local fraternity (est. 1935)
* [[Beta Chi Theta]], Alpha Beta colony (est. 2014)
* [[Beta Theta Pi]], Eta Omicron chapter (est. 2016)
* [[Delta Sigma Phi]], Gamma Chi chapter (est. 1956, Recolonized 2011)
* [[Lambda Chi Alpha]], Epsilon Kappa Zeta chapter, (est. 1941, Recolonized Fall 2009)
* [[Phi Kappa Psi]], PA Upsilon chapter (est. 2002)
* [[Pi Kappa Alpha]], Lambda Zeta chapter (est. 2001)
* [[Pi Kappa Phi]], Alpha Upsilon chapter (est. 1919, Recolonized 2007)
* [[Pi Lambda Phi]], PA Delta Iota chapter (est. 1965, Recolonized 2017)
* [[Sigma Alpha Mu]], Mu Eta chapter, (est. 1947, Recolonized 2009)
* [[Sigma Phi Epsilon]], Pennsylvania Beta Beta chapter (est. 1999)
* [[Theta Chi]], Beta Theta chapter (est. 1927)
{{col-break}}

====MGC organizations====
* [[Alpha Kappa Alpha]] sorority, Gamma Epsilon chapter (est. 1945)&lt;ref&gt;[http://gammaepsilon-akas.org/ Alpha Kappa Alpha] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100518101814/http://gammaepsilon-akas.org/ |date=May 18, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Alpha Phi Alpha]] fraternity, Psi chapter (Recolonized at Drexel in fall 2011)
* [[Delta Epsilon Psi]] fraternity, Xi chapter (est. 2010) 
* [[Delta Phi Omega]] sorority, Gamma chapter (est. 2000)
* [[Delta Sigma Theta]] sorority, (Recolonized 2008)
* [[Iota Nu Delta]] fraternity, Gamma chapter (est. 1997)
* [[Kappa Alpha Psi]] fraternity,
* [[Kappa Phi Gamma]], Nu colony (est. 2011)
* [[Omega Psi Phi]]
* [[Pi Alpha Phi]], Fraternity, Phi chapter (est. 2014)
* [[Sigma Beta Rho]] fraternity, Upsilon chapter, (est. 2002)
* [[Sigma Psi Zeta]] sorority, Nu chapter (est. 2002)
{{col-break}}

====Sororities====
* [[Alpha Sigma Alpha]], Nu Nu chapter (est. 1925)
* [[Delta Gamma]], Eta Upsilon chapter (est. 2016)
* [[Delta Phi Epsilon (social)|Delta Phi Epsilon]], Delta Epsilon chapter (est. 1942, recolonized 2003)
* [[Delta Zeta]], Epsilon Zeta chapter (est. 1928)
* [[Phi Mu]], Beta Tau chapter (est. 1954)
* [[Phi Sigma Sigma]], Beta Rho chapter (est. 1959)
* [[Sigma Sigma Sigma]], Alpha Delta chapter (est. 1926, recolonized 2011)
* [[Zeta Phi Beta]]
{{col-break}}
{{col-end}}

==Athletics==
[[File:Mario the Magnificent.jpg|left|thumb|Mario the Magnificent, mascot of Drexel, by [[Eric Berg]]]]
[[File:Drexel Dragons wordmark.svg|thumb|[[Drexel Dragons]] wordmark]]
{{Main|Drexel Dragons}}
Drexel's school mascot is a [[dragon]] known, as &quot;Mario the Magnificent&quot;, named in honor of alumnus and Board of Trustees member Mario V. Mascioli.&lt;ref name=&quot;dragon&quot;&gt;{{cite web|date=June 5, 2007 |url=http://www.drexel.edu/studentlife/studenthandbook/Handbook.html#traditions |title=Student Handbook - University Traditions &amp; Legends |publisher=Drexel University |accessdate=June 29, 2007 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070701111742/http://www.drexel.edu/studentlife/studenthandbook/Handbook.html |archivedate=July 1, 2007  }}&lt;/ref&gt; The Dragon has been the mascot of the school since around the mid-1920s; the first written reference to the Dragons occurred in 1928, when the football team was called &quot;The Dragons in [[The Triangle (newspaper)|The Triangle]]&quot;. Before becoming known as the Dragons, the athletic teams had been known by such names as the Blue &amp; Gold, the Engineers, and the Drexelites.&lt;ref name=&quot;dragon&quot; /&gt; The school's sports teams, now known as the [[Drexel Dragons]], participate in the [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]]'s Division I as a member of the [[Colonial Athletic Association]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.usnews.com/best-colleges/drexel-university-3256|title=Drexel University|date=2015|website=www.usnews.com|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170316182605/https://www.usnews.com/best-colleges/drexel-university-3256|archive-date=March 16, 2017|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; They do not currently field a varsity football team.&lt;ref&gt;Fry, John [https://www.wsj.com/articles/were-glad-we-say-no-to-college-football-1451855999 We're Glad We Say No to College Football] ''Wall Street Journal''. January 6, 2015&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition to its NCAA Division I teams, Drexel University is home to 33 active club teams including lacrosse, water polo, squash, triathlon, and cycling. Other club teams include soccer, baseball, rugby, field hockey, and roller hockey. The club teams operate under the direction of the Club Sports Council and the Recreational Sports Office.

==Student lore and traditions==
Tradition suggests that rubbing the toe of the [[Bronze sculpture|bronze]] &quot;Waterboy&quot; [[statue]], located in the Main Building atrium, can result in receiving good grades on exams. Although the rest of the bronze statue has developed a dark brown [[patina]] over the years, the toe has remained highly polished and shines like new.&lt;ref name=&quot;dragon&quot; /&gt;

===The 'Drexel Shaft'===
Frustrated by unresponsive university administrators, students throughout Drexel's history have spoken of a &quot;Drexel Shaft&quot; to describe their interactions with the administration during their academic career at the school. The &quot;Drexel Shaft&quot; was once associated with the Flame of Knowledge fountain, now located in front of North Hall. As the legend of the Drexel Shaft grew larger, however, the &quot;shaft&quot; itself grew alongside the legend.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=North Hall Fountain - Drexel university|url= http://www.waymarking.com/waymarks/WM2T64 |publisher=WayMarking |accessdate=June 11, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Eventually, the chimney atop the Amtrak Boiler House in Penn Coach Yard, located just east of 32nd Street on the University City main campus, came to embody the unresponsive treatment that frustrated many students during their time at Drexel. The smokestack was demolished, to cheers by students and faculty members alike, in November 15, 2009, in what the university community hopes will be a transformation of both the campus' aesthetics and the legend of the &quot;Drexel Shaft&quot; itself.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|date=November 6, 2009 |title='Drexel Shaft' to be Imploded|url= http://media.www.thetriangle.org/media/storage/paper689/news/2009/11/06/News/drexel.Shaft.To.Be.Imploded-3825696.shtml|publisher=The Triangle |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100806125321/http://media.www.thetriangle.org/media/storage/paper689/news/2009/11/06/News/drexel.Shaft.To.Be.Imploded-3825696.shtml |archivedate=August 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.newspapers.com/newspage/199978509/|title=The Philadelphia Inquirer from Philadelphia, Pennsylvania on November 16, 2009 · Page B08|author=|date=|website=newspapers.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.5027mac.org/2009/12/04/rip-drexel-shaft|title=R.I.P., Drexel Shaft -|author=|date=December 4, 2009|website=5027mac.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==In popular culture==
[[File:US Open Squash Championship 2011 Drexel University.jpg|thumb|The glass show court used at the 2011 US Open Squash Championships hosted by Drexel University at the [[Daskalakis Athletic Center]]|281x281px]]
Drexel has appeared in news and television media several times. In 2006 Drexel served as the location for ABC Family's reality show &quot;Back on Campus&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Back on Campus |url=https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0791272/ |publisher=IMDB |accessdate=December 12, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Also in 2006, the Epsilon Zeta chapter of [[Delta Zeta]] won ABC Daytime's Summer of Fun contest. As a result, the sorority was featured in national television spots for a week and hosted an ABC party on campus, which was attended by cast members from ''[[General Hospital]]'' and ''[[All My Children]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=March 6, 2006 |title=Drexel Delta Zeta Chapter Wins ABC Campus Invasion Contest |url=http://www.drexel.edu/univrel/digest/archive/030606/index.html |publisher=Drexel Daily Digest |accessdate=November 29, 2007 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070607152623/http://www.drexel.edu/univrel/digest/archive/030606/index.html |archivedate=June 7, 2007  }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[John Langdon (typographer)|John Langdon]], who taught typography in the Antoinette Westphal College of Media Arts &amp; Design from 1988 to 2015, created the ambigram featured on the cover of Dan Brown's Angels &amp; Demons; a number of other ambigrams served as the central focus of the book and its corresponding film. It is believed Prof. Langdon was the inspiration for the name of the lead character, played by Tom Hanks in the film adaptation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://drexel.edu/westphal/news-events/news/2015/November/2015-11-5-farewell/|title=A Farewell to a Man of Letters|website=Drexel University|date=2 November 2015|access-date=18 December 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Howard Benson]], a Drexel alumnus and a music producer associated with [[Hoobastank]], [[Creed (band)|Creed]] and [[Kelly Clarkson]], teaches a music production master class at Drexel.

Drexel University was a sponsor of [[Matthew Quick]]'s novel ''[[Silver Linings Playbook]],'' which was made into a movie in 2012. Matthew Quick held several lectures at Drexel University.

In 2007, Drexel was the host of the 2008 Democratic Presidential candidate debate in Philadelphia, televised by [[MSNBC]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|date=October 23, 2007 |title=Drexel Univ. To Host Presidential Debate |url=http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2007/10/24/politics/uwire/main3400948.shtml |first=LeAnne |last= Matlach| publisher=CBS |accessdate=June 24, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; The university hosted the US Table Tennis Olympic Trials between January 10 and 13, 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|date=August 2007 |title=Phila. will host '08 table tennis trials |url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_kmtpi/is_200708/ai_n19404303 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090123035418/http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_kmtpi/is_200708/ai_n19404303 |url-status=dead |archive-date=January 23, 2009 |newspaper=The Philadelphia Inquirer |accessdate=December 12, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=City of Brotherly Love to Host 2008 U.S. Olympic Team Trials for Table Tennis, January 10–13 |url=http://www.usatt.org/news1/2008_team_trials_drexel.shtml |publisher=USA Table Tennis |accessdate=January 15, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Drexel University also hosted the 2011 U.S. Open Squash Championships from October 1–6, 2011, as well as the 2012 U.S. Open Squash Championships from October 4–12, 2012.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Drexel to Host 2011 U.S. Open Squash Championships |url=http://www.drexeldragons.com/news/2011/1/24/GEN_0124110942.aspx?path=gen}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=U.S. Open Squash returns to the DAC |url=http://www.drexeldragons.com/news/2012/10/3/MSQ_1003120222.aspx?path=msq}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the U.S. TV Series [[House of Cards (U.S. TV series)|''House of Cards'']], Congressman Peter Russo (played by [[Corey Stoll]]) is a graduate of Drexel University.

==Alumni==
{{Main|List of Drexel University alumni}}

Since its founding the university has graduated over 100,000 alumni.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|year=2007 |title=Debate at Drexel: About Drexel University |url=http://www.drexel.edu/debate/drexel.asp |publisher=Drexel University|accessdate=December 31, 2009 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090123154134/http://www.drexel.edu/debate/drexel.asp |archivedate=January 23, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Certificate-earning alumni such as artist [[Violet Oakley]] and illustrator [[Frank Schoonover]] reflect the early emphasis on art as part of the university's curriculum. With [[World War II]], the university's technical programs swelled, and as a result Drexel graduated alumni such as [[Paul Baran]], one of the founding fathers of the Internet and one of the inventors of the [[packet switching]] network, and [[Norman Joseph Woodland]] the inventor of [[barcode]] technology. In addition to its emphasis on technology Drexel has graduated several notable athletes such as [[National Basketball Association]] (NBA) basketball players [[Michael Anderson (basketball)|Michael Anderson]] and [[Malik Rose]], and several notable business people such as [[Rajiv L. Gupta|Raj Gupta]], former President and [[Chief executive officer]] (CEO) of [[Rohm and Haas]], and [[Kenneth C. Dahlberg]], former CEO of [[Science Applications International Corporation]] (SAIC). Alassane Dramane Ouattara President of the Republic of Ivory Coast. In 2018, Tirthak Saha -a 2016 graduate of the ECE school - was named to the [[Forbes 30 Under 30]] list for achievements in the [[Energy]] field.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.forbes.com/profile/tirthak-saha/|title=Tirthak Saha|work=Forbes|access-date=July 9, 2018|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1991, the university's centennial anniversary, Drexel created an association called the Drexel 100, for alumni who have demonstrated excellence work, philanthropy, or public service. After the creation of the association 100 alumni were inducted in 1992 and since then the induction process has been on a biennial basis. In 2006 164 total alumni had been inducted into the association.&lt;ref name=&quot;drexel100&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|title=The Drexel 100 |newspaper=Drexel Blue &amp; Gold |volume=17 |issue=1 |pages=24–25 |date=June 15, 2006 |url=http://www.drexel.edu/univrel/new/alumnimagazine/winter_2006.pdf |format=PDF |accessdate=January 12, 2008 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080410071546/http://www.drexel.edu/univrel/new/alumnimagazine/winter_2006.pdf |archivedate=April 10, 2008  }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Awards==
Drexel University created the annual $100,000 Anthony J. Drexel Exceptional Achievement Award to recognize a faculty member from a U.S. institution whose work transforms both research and the society it serves. The first recipient was bioengineer [[James Collins (bioengineer)|James J. Collins]] of Boston University (now at MIT) and the Howard Hughes Medical Institute.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.drexel.edu/achievement/ |title=Anthony J. Drexel Exceptional Achievement Award: Honoring Researchers Making a Difference |publisher=Drexel.edu |accessdate=December 16, 2013 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130313175423/http://www.drexel.edu/achievement/ |archivedate=March 13, 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2004, in conjunction with [[BAYADA Home Health Care]], Drexel University's College of Nursing and Health Professions created the BAYADA Award for Technological Innovation in Nursing Education and Practice. The award honors nursing educators and practicing nurses whose innovation leads to improved patient care or improved nursing education.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=About BAYADA Awards |url=http://www.drexel.edu/cnhp/newsEvents/events/BayadaAwards/ |publisher=drexel.edu |accessdate=August 26, 2013 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130831190931/http://www.drexel.edu/cnhp/newsEvents/events/BayadaAwards/ |archivedate=August 31, 2013  }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Gallery==
&lt;gallery mode=&quot;packed&quot;&gt;
File:Drexel URBN Center.JPG| The URBN Center, home of the Westphal College of Media Arts and Design
File:Hagerty Library Drexel.JPG| The W.W. Hagerty Library at the University City Main Campus
File:Drexel Rec Center.JPG| The Drexel Recreation Center
File:Drexel Law School.JPG|The Drexel University School of Law
File:Drexel Nesbitt Hall.JPG| Nesbitt Hall located on 33rd and Market Streets
File:Vidas Athletic Field.JPG|Vidas Athletic Field
File:The Drexel Armory.JPG|The Armory at Drexel University
File:Buckley Volleyball Courts at Drexel University.JPG|Beach Volleyball courts at Buckley Green
File:Hess Engineering Labs Drexel University.JPG|Hess Engineering Research Laboratories (Now demolished)
File:Daskalakis Athletic Center Drexel.JPG|John A. Daskalakis Athletic Center
File:Drexel2.JPG|Drexel University Center for Graduate Studies, Sacramento, California
File:Papadakis living wall.jpg|A &quot;living wall&quot; inside the Papadakis Integrated Science Building
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Philadelphia|Pennsylvania}}
* [[Association of Independent Technological Universities]]
{{Clear}}

==Notes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
{{Commons}}
* {{Official website}}
* [http://www.drexeldragons.com/ Drexel Athletics website]
* {{Cite NIE|wstitle=Drexel Institute of Art, Science, and Industry|year=1905 |short=x}}

{{Drexel University}}
{{Navboxes
|titlestyle = {{CollegePrimaryStyle|Drexel Dragons|color=white}}
|list =
{{Colonial Athletic Association navbox}}
{{Colleges and Universities in Pennsylvania}}
{{Colleges and universities in metropolitan Philadelphia}}
}}

[[Category:Drexel University|*]]
[[Category:Eastern Pennsylvania Rugby Union]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1891]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Philadelphia]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Pennsylvania]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Placer County, California]]
[[Category:1891 establishments in Pennsylvania]]
[[Category:University City, Philadelphia]]
[[Category:Technological universities in the United States]]</text>
      <sha1>s0ogjfzweskkki323muz99kake0sksb</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
