  <page>
    <title>Diffusion pump</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8293</id>
    <revision>
      <id>930994236</id>
      <parentid>911282600</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-12-16T07:55:33Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>DMacks</username>
        <id>712163</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* History */ MOS (named for a person)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[Image:M6 Diffusion Pump.jpg|right|250 px|thumb|Six inch oil diffusion pump.]]
'''Diffusion pumps''' use a high speed jet of vapor to direct gas [[molecule]]s in the pump throat down into the bottom of the pump and out the exhaust. They were the first type of high [[vacuum pump]]s operating in the regime of [[free molecular flow]], where the movement of the gas molecules can be better understood as [[diffusion]] than by conventional [[fluid dynamics]]. Invented in 1915 by [[Wolfgang Gaede]], he named it a ''diffusion pump'' since his design was based on the finding that gas cannot diffuse against the vapor stream, but will be carried with it to the exhaust.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = D. G. Avery and R. Witty | title = Diffusion pumps: a critical discussion of existing theories| journal = [[Proc. Phys. Soc.]] | volume = 59 | year = 1947 | pages = 1016–1030 | doi =  10.1088/0959-5309/59/6/313 | issue = 6|bibcode = 1947PPS....59.1016A }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the principle of operation might be more precisely described as '''gas-jet pump''', since diffusion plays a role also in other high vacuum pumps. In modern textbooks, the diffusion pump is categorized as a [[vacuum pump#Momentum transfer|momentum transfer]] pump.

The diffusion pump is widely used in both industrial and research applications. Most modern diffusion pumps use [[silicone oil]] or [[polyphenyl ether]]s as the working fluid. 

==History==
In the late 19th century, most vacuums were creating using a [[Sprengel pump]], which had the advantage of being very simple to operate, and capable of achieving very good vacuum given enough time. Compared to later pumps, however, the pumping speed was very slow.

Following his invention of the [[Holweck pump|molecular pump]], the diffusion pump was invented in 1915 by [[Wolfgang Gaede]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | year = 1915 | journal = [[Annalen der Physik]] | volume = 46 | page = 357 | author = Gaede, W. | doi = 10.1002/andp.19153510304 | title = Die Diffusion der Gase durch Quecksilberdampf bei niederen Drucken und die Diffusionsluftpumpe | issue = 3|bibcode = 1915AnP...351..357G }}&lt;/ref&gt;, and originally used [[Mercury (element)|elemental mercury]] as the working fluid. After its invention, the design was quickly commercialized by [[Leybold GmbH|Leybold]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last=Sella | first=Andrea | title=Classic Kit: Gaede's diffusion pump | website=Chemistry World | date=2009-04-28 | url=https://www.chemistryworld.com/opinion/classic-kit-gaedes-diffusion-pump/3004912.article | access-date=2019-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It was then improved by [[Irving Langmuir]] and W. Crawford. [[Cecil Reginald Burch]] discovered the possibility of using silicone oil in 1928.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = C. R. Burch | title = Oils, greases and high vacua | journal = [[Nature (journal)|Nature]] | volume = 122 | year = 1928 | page = 729 | doi = 10.1038/122729c0 | issue = 3080|bibcode = 1928Natur.122..729B }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Oil diffusion pumps==

An oil diffusion pump is used to achieve higher vacuum (lower pressure) than is possible by use of [[Positive displacement vacuum pump|positive displacement]] pumps alone. Although its use has been mainly associated within the high-vacuum range (down to 10&lt;sup&gt;−9&lt;/sup&gt; mbar), diffusion pumps today can produce pressures approaching 10&lt;sup&gt;−10&lt;/sup&gt; mbar when properly used with modern fluids and accessories. The features that make the diffusion pump attractive for high and ultra-high vacuum use are its high pumping speed for all gases and low cost per unit pumping speed when compared with other types of pump used in the same vacuum range. Diffusion pumps cannot discharge directly into the atmosphere, so a mechanical forepump is typically used to maintain an outlet pressure around 0.1 mbar.

[[Image:Calutron diffusion pumps.jpg|left|thumb|250 px|Diffusion pumps used on the [[Calutron]] [[mass spectrometer]]s during the [[Manhattan Project]].]]

[[Image:Diffusion pump schematic.svg|thumb|right|250 px|Diagram of an oil diffusion pump]]

The oil diffusion pump is operated with an oil of low [[vapor pressure]]. The high speed jet is generated by boiling the fluid and directing the vapor through a jet assembly. Note that the oil is gaseous when entering the nozzles. Within the nozzles, the flow changes from [[laminar flow|laminar]] to [[supersonic]] and [[free molecular flow|molecular]]. Often, several jets are used in series to enhance the pumping action. The outside of the diffusion pump is cooled using either air flow or a water line. As the vapor jet hits the outer cooled shell of the diffusion pump, the working fluid condenses and is recovered and directed back to the boiler. The pumped gases continue flowing to the base of the pump at increased pressure, flowing out through the diffusion pump outlet, where they are compressed to ambient pressure by the secondary mechanical forepump and exhausted. 

Unlike [[turbomolecular pump]]s and [[cryopump]]s, diffusion pumps have no moving parts and as a result are quite durable and reliable. They can function over pressure ranges of 10&lt;sup&gt;−10&lt;/sup&gt; to 10&lt;sup&gt;−2&lt;/sup&gt; mbar. They are driven only by [[convection]] and thus have a very low energy efficiency.

One major disadvantage of diffusion pumps is the tendency to backstream oil into the vacuum chamber. This oil can contaminate surfaces inside the chamber or upon contact with hot filaments or electrical discharges may result in carbonaceous or siliceous deposits. Due to backstreaming, oil diffusion pumps are not suitable for use with highly sensitive analytical equipment or other applications which require an extremely clean vacuum environment, but mercury diffusion pumps may be in the case of ultra high vacuum chambers used for metal deposition. Often [[cold trap]]s and [[Baffle_(heat_transfer)|baffles]] are used to minimize backstreaming, although this results in some loss of pumping ability.

The oil of a diffusion pump cannot be exposed to the atmosphere when hot. If this occurs, the oil will burn and has to be replaced.

===Oil types===
{{See also|Polyphenyl ether#Ultra-high-vacuum fluids}}

The least expensive diffusion pump oils are based on [[hydrocarbon]]s which have been purified by double-distillation. Compared with the other fluids, they are have higher vapor pressure, so are usually limited to a pressure of 1 x 10&lt;sup&gt;-6&lt;/sup&gt; Torr. They are also the most likely to burn or explode if exposed to oxidizers.

The most common [[silicone oil]]s used in diffusion pumps are trisiloxanes, which contain the chemical group Si-O-Si-O-Si, to which various [[phenyl group]]s or [[methyl group]]s are attached. These are available as the so called 702 and 703 blends, which were formerly manufactured by [[Dow Corning]]. These can be further separated into 704 and 705 oils, which are made up of the isomers of  tetraphenyl tetramethyl trisiloxane and pentaphenyl trimethyl trisiloxane respectively.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | title=A User's Guide to Vacuum Technology | chapter=Pump Fluids | publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons, Inc. | publication-place=Hoboken, NJ, USA | date=2004-12-07 | isbn=978-0-471-46716-8 | doi=10.1002/0471467162.ch13 | pages=229–246}}&lt;/ref&gt;

For pumping reactive species, usually a [[polyphenyl ether]] based oil is used. These oils are the most chemical and heat resistant type of diffusion pump oil.

==Steam ejectors==
[[Image:DP_pumping_speed_plot.png|thumb|right|250 px|Plot of pumping speed as a function of pressure for a diffusion pump.]]
{{main|Injector}}
[[Image:Langmuir mercury diffusion pump.jpg|thumb|Early Langmuir mercury diffusion pump ''(vertical column)'' and its backing pump ''(in background)'', about 1920.  The diffusion pump was widely used in manufacturing [[vacuum tube]]s, the key technology which dominated the radio and electronics industry for 50 years.]]  
 
The steam ejector is a popular form of pump for vacuum [[distillation]] and [[freeze-drying]]. A jet of steam entrains the vapour that must be removed from the vacuum chamber. Steam ejectors can have single or multiple stages, with and without [[Condenser (steam turbine)|condensers]] in between the stages. While both steam ejectors and diffusion pumps use jets of vapor to entrain gas, they work on fundamentally different principles - steam ejectors rely on viscous flow and mixing to pump gas, whereas diffusion pumps use molecular diffusion. This has several consequences. In diffusion pumps, the inlet pressure can be much lower than the static pressure of jet, whereas in steam ejectors the two pressures are about the same. Also, diffusion pumps are capable of much higher compression ratios, and cannot discharge directly to atmosphere.

== See also ==
* [[Turbomolecular pump]]
* [[Vacuum pump]]
* [[Aspirator (pump)]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.public.asu.edu/~aomdw/GLASS/DIFFUSION_PUMP.html An oil diffusion pump built from glass by the Arizona State University Main]

==Further reading==
{{cite book
 | last = Hablanian
 | first = M. H. 
 | title = Diffusion Pumps : Performance and Operation
 | origyear = 1983
 | edition = 2nd
 | series = AVS Monograph Series
 | year = 1994
 | publisher = American Vacuum Society
 | location = New York, NY
 | isbn = 1-56396-384-1
 }}

[[Category:Vacuum pumps]]</text>
      <sha1>0w3z29b4k82j642uamjz2rr8t91rqbk</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
