  <page>
    <title>Demon</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8280</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942941618</id>
      <parentid>942780980</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-27T20:49:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>JzG</username>
        <id>760284</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Kabbalah */Addind &quot;self-published source&quot; inside ref tags where tagged inline only</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Paranormal being prevalent in religion, occultism, mythology, and folklore}}
{{about|conceptions of evil spirits from around the world|the semi-divine beings in classical mythology|Daemon (classical mythology)|other uses}}
{{redirect|Evil spirit|the 1928 film|Evil Spirit (film)|the album by The Damned|Evil Spirits (album)}}
{{pp-move-indef}}
&lt;!--
IMPORTANT: Wikipedia is an encyclopedia, not a fan-site. Only notable demons should be posted here – demons are common in fiction, and there could be a countless number of demons. Only add demons that are most notable. For more information see: WP:NOTABILITY
--&gt;
&lt;!--
This is the demon article, not the daimon article. We already have a daimon article; talk about daimons there.
--&gt;
[[File:PazuzuDemonAssyria1stMil 2.jpg|thumb|upright|Bronze statuette of the [[Assyro-Babylonian]] demon king [[Pazuzu]], circa 800 BC – circa 700 BCE, [[Louvre]]]]
[[File:Mephistopheles2.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Mephistopheles]] (A [[Middle Ages|Medieval]] demon from [[German folklore]]) flying over [[Wittenberg]], in a [[lithograph]] by [[Eugène Delacroix]].]]

A '''demon''' is a [[supernatural]] being prevalent historically in [[religion]], [[occultism]], [[literature]], [[fiction]], [[mythology]], and [[folklore]]; as well as in [[Media (communication)|media]] such as [[comics]], [[videogames]], [[movies]] and [[television series]].

The original Greek word ''[[Daemon (classical mythology)|daimon]]'' does not carry negative connotations.&lt;ref name=&quot;Liddell &amp; Scott&quot;&gt;{{cite book |chapter-url=http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.04.0057%3Aentry%3Ddaimo%2Fnion |chapter=δαιμόνιον |last1=Liddell |first1= Henry George |authorlink1=Henry Liddell |last2=Scott |first2=Robert |authorlink2=Robert Scott (philologist) |title=[[A Greek–English Lexicon]] |publisher=Perseus}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Ancient Greek language|Ancient Greek]] word {{lang|grc| δαίμων}} ''[[Daemon (classical mythology)|daimōn]]'' denotes a spirit or divine power, much like the [[Latin]] ''[[Genius (mythology)|genius]]'' or ''[[numen]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;merriam-webster&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Demon|url=http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/demon|work=Merriam-Webster Dictionary|publisher=Encyclopædia Britannica|accessdate=12 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Greek conception of a ''daimōn'' notably appears in the works of [[Plato]], where it describes the divine inspiration of [[Socrates]].

In [[Ancient Near Eastern religions]] and in the [[Abrahamic traditions]], including ancient and medieval [[Christian demonology]], a demon is considered a harmful spiritual entity which may cause [[demonic possession]], calling for an [[exorcism]]. 
In Western [[occultism]] and [[Renaissance magic]], which grew out of an amalgamation of [[Greco-Roman magic]], Jewish [[Aggadah]] and [[Christian demonology]],&lt;ref&gt;See, for example, the course synopsis and bibliography for [http://medievalstudies.ceu.hu/courses/20102011/magic-science-religion-the-development-of-the-western-esoteric-traditions &quot;Magic, Science, Religion: The Development of the Western Esoteric Traditions&quot;] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141129021925/http://medievalstudies.ceu.hu/courses/20102011/magic-science-religion-the-development-of-the-western-esoteric-traditions |date=November 29, 2014 }}, at Central European University, Budapest&lt;/ref&gt; a demon is believed to be a spiritual entity that may be [[conjuration|conjured]] and controlled.

== Etymology ==
{{Further|Daemon (classical mythology)|Agathodaemon|Cacodemon|Daimonic|Eudaimonia}}
The [[Ancient Greek language|Ancient Greek]] word {{lang|grc| δαίμων}} ''[[Daemon (classical mythology)|daemon]]'' denotes a spirit or divine power, much like the [[Latin]] ''[[Genius (mythology)|genius]]'' or ''[[numen]]''. ''Daimōn'' most likely came from the Greek verb ''daiesthai'' (to divide, distribute).&lt;ref name=&quot;merriam-webster&quot; /&gt; The Greek conception of a ''daimōn'' notably appears in the works of [[Plato]], where it describes the divine inspiration of [[Socrates]]. The original Greek word ''[[Daemon (classical mythology)|daimon]]'' does not carry the negative connotation initially understood by implementation of the [[Koine Greek|Koine]] {{lang|grc|δαιμόνιον}} (''daimonion''),&lt;ref name=&quot;Liddell &amp; Scott&quot; /&gt; and later ascribed to any cognate words sharing the root.

The Greek terms do not have any connotations of evil or malevolence. In fact, {{lang|grc|εὐδαιμονία}} ''[[eudaimonia]]'', (literally good-spiritedness) means [[happiness]]. By the early [[Roman Empire]], [[cult image|cult statues]] were seen, by [[Paganism|pagans]] and their Christian neighbors alike, as inhabited by the numinous presence of the gods: &quot;Like pagans, Christians still sensed and saw the gods and their power, and as something, they had to assume, lay behind it, by an easy traditional shift of opinion they turned these pagan ''daimones'' into malevolent 'demons', the troupe of [[Satan]]..... Far into the [[Byzantine Empire|Byzantine period]] Christians eyed their cities' old pagan statuary as a seat of the demons' presence. It was no longer beautiful, it was infested.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=Robin Lane |last=Fox |title=Pagans and Christians |year=1989 |page=137}}&lt;/ref&gt; The term had first acquired its negative connotations in the [[Septuagint]] translation of the [[Hebrew Bible]] into Greek, which drew on the mythology of [[ancient Semitic religions]]. This was then inherited by the Koine text of the [[New Testament]]. The Western medieval and neo-medieval conception of a ''demon''&lt;ref&gt;See the Medieval [[grimoire]] called the ''[[Ars Goetia]]''.&lt;/ref&gt; derives seamlessly from the ambient [[popular culture]] of [[Late Antiquity]]. The [[Hellenistic period|Hellenistic]] &quot;daemon&quot; eventually came to include many Semitic and Near Eastern gods as evaluated by Christianity.{{citation needed|date=June 2016}}

The supposed existence of demons remains an important concept in many modern religions and occultist traditions. Demons are still feared largely due to their alleged power to [[demonic possession|possess]] living creatures. In the contemporary Western occultist tradition (perhaps epitomized by the work of [[Aleister Crowley]]), a demon (such as [[Choronzon]], which is Crowley's interpretation of the so-called 'Demon of the Abyss') is a useful metaphor for certain inner psychological processes (inner demons), though some may also regard it as an objectively real phenomenon. Some scholars&lt;ref&gt;Boyce, 1987; Black and Rowley, 1987; Duchesne-Guillemin, 1988.&lt;/ref&gt; believe that large portions of the [[demonology]] (see [[Asmodai]]) of [[Judaism]], a key influence on [[Christianity]] and [[Islam]], originated from a later form of [[Zoroastrianism]], and were transferred to Judaism during the [[Achaemenid Empire|Persian era]].

== Ancient Egypt ==
[[File:Ram-headed demon.jpg|thumb|upright|Ram-headed demon. The hands probably outstretch to hold two snakes. From a royal tomb in the Valley of the Kings, Thebes, Egypt. End of the 18th Dynasty, around 1325 BCE]]
Both deities and demons can act as intermediaries to deliver messages to humans.&lt;ref&gt;Rita Lucarelli ''Demons (Benevolent and Malevolent'' Ucla Encyclopedia of egyptology 2010 p.3&lt;/ref&gt; Thus they share some resemblance to the Greek daimonion. The exact definition of &quot;demon&quot; in Egyptology posed a major problem for modern scholarship, since the borders between a deity and a demon are sometimes blurred and the ancient Egyptian language lacks a term for the modern English &quot;demon&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rita Lucarelli p. 2&quot;&gt;Rita Lucarelli ''Demons (Benevolent and Malevolent'' Ucla Encyclopedia of egyptology 2010 p. 2&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;Siam Bhayro, Catherine Rider ''Demons and Illness from Antiquity to the Early-Modern Period'' BRILL 2017 {{ISBN|978-9-004-33854-8}} p. 53&lt;/ref&gt; However, magical writings indicate that ancient Egyptians acknowledged the existence of malevolent demons by highlighting the demon names with red ink.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; Demons in this culture appeared to be subordinative and related to a specific deity, yet they may have occasionally acted independent from the divine will. The existence of demons can be related to the realm of chaos, beyond the created world.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rita Lucarelli p. 2&quot;/&gt; But even this negative connotation cannot be denied in light of the magical texts. The role of demons in relation to the human world remains ambivalent and largely depends on context.

Ancient Egyptian demons can be divided into two classes: &quot;guardians&quot; and &quot;wanderers.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Rita Lucarelli ''Demons (Benevolent and Malevolent'' Ucla Encyclopedia of egyptology 2010 p. 3&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Siam Bhayro, Catherine Rider ''Demons and Illness from Antiquity to the Early-Modern Period'' BRILL 2017 {{ISBN|978-9-004-33854-8}} p. 55&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;Guardians&quot; are tied to a specific place; their demonic activity is topographically defined and their function can be benevolent towards those who have the secret knowledge to face them.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rita Lucarelli p. 4&quot;&gt;Rita Lucarelli ''Demons (Benevolent and Malevolent'' Ucla Encyclopedia of egyptology 2010 p. 4&lt;/ref&gt; Demons protecting the underworld may prevent human souls from entering paradise. Only by knowing right charms is the deceased able to enter the ''[[Halls of Osiris]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Dorian Gieseler Greenbaum ''The Daimon in Hellenistic Astrology: Origins and Influence'' BRILL 2015 {{ISBN|9789004306219}} p. 120&lt;/ref&gt; Here, the aggressive nature of the guardian demons is motivated by the need to protect their abodes and not by their evil essence. Accordingly, demons guarded sacred places or the gates to the netherworld. During the [[Ptolemaic Kingdom|Ptolemaic]] and [[Roman period]], the guardians shifted towards the role of [[Genius loci]] and they were the focus of local and private cults.

The &quot;wanderers&quot; are associated with possession, mental illness, death and plagues. Many of them serve as executioners for the major deities, such as [[Ra]] or [[Osiris]], when ordered to punish humans on earth or in the netherworld.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rita Lucarelli p. 4&quot;/&gt; Wanderers can also be agents of chaos, arising from the world beyond creation to bring about misfortune and suffering without any divine instructions, led only by evil motivations. The influences of the wanderers can be warded off and kept at the borders on the human world by the use of magic, but they can never be destroyed. A sub-category of &quot;wanderers&quot; are nightmare demons, which were believed to cause nightmares by entering a human body.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rita Lucarelli p. 2&quot;/&gt;

== Mesopotamia ==
{{Further|Ancient Mesopotamian underworld#Demons}}
[[File:Dumuzi aux enfers.jpg|thumb|left|Ancient Sumerian [[cylinder seal]] impression showing the god [[Dumuzid the Shepherd|Dumuzid]] being tortured in the [[Kur|Underworld]] by ''[[gallu|galla]]'' demons]]

The ancient Mesopotamians believed that the [[Kur|underworld]] was home to many demons,{{sfn|Black|Green|1992|page=180}} which are sometimes referred to as &quot;offspring of ''arali''&quot;.{{sfn|Black|Green|1992|page=180}} These demons could sometimes leave the underworld and terrorize mortals on earth.{{sfn|Black|Green|1992|page=180}} One class of demons that were believed to reside in the underworld were known as ''[[Gallu|galla]]'';{{sfn|Black|Green|1992|page=85}} their primary purpose appears to have been to drag unfortunate mortals back to Kur.{{sfn|Black|Green|1992|page=85}} They are frequently referenced in magical texts,{{sfn|Black|Green|1992|pages=85–86}} and some texts describe them as being seven in number.{{sfn|Black|Green|1992|pages=85–86}} Several extant poems describe the ''galla'' dragging the god Dumuzid into the underworld.{{sfn|Black|Green|1992|page=86}} Like other demons, however, ''galla'' could also be benevolent{{sfn|Black|Green|1992|page=86}} and, in a hymn from King [[Gudea]] of [[Lagash]] ({{circa}} 2144 – 2124 BCE), a minor god named Ig-alima is described as &quot;the great ''galla'' of [[Girsu]]&quot;.{{sfn|Black|Green|1992|page=86}}

[[Lamashtu]] was a demonic goddess with the &quot;head of a lion, the teeth of a donkey, naked breasts, a hairy body, hands stained (with blood?), long fingers and fingernails, and the feet of [[Anzû]].&quot;{{sfn|Black|Green|1992|page=116}} She was believed to feed on the blood of human infants{{sfn|Black|Green|1992|page=116}} and was widely blamed as the cause of [[miscarriages]] and [[Sudden infant death syndrome|cot deaths]].{{sfn|Black|Green|1992|page=116}} Although Lamashtu has traditionally been identified as a demoness,{{sfn|Black|Green|1992|pages=115–116}} the fact that she could cause evil on her own without the permission of other deities strongly indicates that she was seen as a goddess in her own right.{{sfn|Black|Green|1992|page=116}} Mesopotamian peoples protected against her using [[amulet]]s and [[talisman]]s.{{sfn|Black|Green|1992|page=116}} She was believed to ride in her boat on the river of the underworld{{sfn|Black|Green|1992|page=116}} and she was associated with donkeys.{{sfn|Black|Green|1992|page=116}} She was believed to be the daughter of [[Anu|An]].{{sfn|Black|Green|1992|page=116}}

[[Pazuzu]] is a demonic god who was well-known to the Babylonians and Assyrians throughout the first millennium BCE.{{sfn|Black|Green|1992|page=147}} He is shown with &quot;a rather canine face with abnormally bulging eyes, a scaly body, a snake-headed penis, the talons of a bird and usually wings.&quot;{{sfn|Black|Green|1992|page=147}} He was believed to be the son of the god [[Hanbi]].{{sfn|Black|Green|1992|page=148}} He was usually regarded as evil,{{sfn|Black|Green|1992|page=147}} but he could also sometimes be a beneficent entity who protected against winds bearing pestilence{{sfn|Black|Green|1992|page=147}} and he was thought to be able to force Lamashtu back to the underworld.{{sfn|Black|Green|1992|pages=147–148}} Amulets bearing his image were positioned in dwellings to protect infants from Lamashtu{{sfn|Black|Green|1992|page=148}} and pregnant women frequently wore amulets with his head on them as protection from her.{{sfn|Black|Green|1992|page=148}}

[[Šul-pa-e]]'s name means &quot;youthful brilliance&quot;, but he was not envisioned as youthful god.{{sfn|Black|Green|1992|page=173}} According to one tradition, he was the consort of Ninhursag, a tradition which contradicts the usual portrayal of Enki as Ninhursag's consort.{{sfn|Black|Green|1992|page=173}}{{sfn|George|1999|page=225}} In one Sumerian poem, offerings made to Šhul-pa-e in the underworld and, in later mythology, he was one of the demons of the underworld.{{sfn|Black|Green|1992|page=173}}

According to the [[Jewish Encyclopedia]], &quot;In [[Chaldea]]n mythology the seven evil deities were known as ''[[shedu]]'', storm-demons, represented in ox-like form.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;JE-shedim&quot;&gt;{{cite book |chapter-url=http://jewishencyclopedia.com/articles/5085-demonology |chapter=Demonology |title=Jewish Encyclopedia |year=1906 |first1=Emil G. |last1=Hirsch |first2=Richard |last2=Gottheil |first3=Kaufmann |last3=Kohler |first4=Isaac |last4=Broydé}}&lt;/ref&gt; They were represented as [[Sacred bull|winged bulls]], derived from the colossal bulls used as protective [[jinn]] of royal palaces.&lt;ref&gt;See Delitzsch, ''Assyrisches Handwörterbuch''. pp. 60, 253, 261, 646; Jensen, ''Assyr.-Babyl. Mythen und Epen'', 1900, p. 453; [[Archibald Sayce]], l.c. pp. 441, 450, 463; [[François Lenormant|Lenormant]], l.c. pp. 48–51.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Abrahamic religions==
=== Judaism ===
{{See also|Shedim|Dybbuk|Samael}}
[[File:Lilith (John Collier painting).jpg|thumb|upright|In ''[[Lilith (painting)|Lilith]]'' by [[John Collier (Pre-Raphaelite painter)|John Collier]] (1892), the female demon [[Lilith]] is shown personified within the [[Garden of Eden]]]]
As referring to the existence or non-existence of demons (''[[shedim]]'' or ''[[Se'irim]]'') there are converse opinions in Judaism.&lt;ref name=&quot;JE-shedim&quot;/&gt; There are &quot;practically nil&quot; roles assigned to demons in the [[Hebrew Bible]].&lt;ref name=&quot;JVL-Demons&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Demons &amp; Demonology|url=https://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/Judaism/demons.html|website=jewishvirtuallibrary.org|publisher=The Gale Group|accessdate=21 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Judaism today, beliefs in &quot;demons&quot; or &quot;evil spirits&quot; are either ''midot [[hasidic philosophy|hasidut]]'' (Hebr. for &quot;customs of the pious&quot;), and therefore not [[halachah]], or notions based on a [[superstition]] that are non-essential, non-binding parts of Judaism, and therefore not normative Jewish practice. That is to say, Jews are not obligated to believe in the existence of ''[[shedim]]'', as [[posek]] rabbi [[David Bar-Hayim]] points out.&lt;ref name=&quot;YT-eng-source&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last1=Bar-Hayim|first1=David|title=Do Jews Believe in Demons and Evil Spirits?-Interview with Rabbi David Bar-Hayim|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Iia41D_OLSA|website=www.youtube.com|publisher=Tora Nation Machon Shilo|accessdate=20 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Tanakh ====
The Tanakh mentions two classes of demonic spirits, the ''se'irim'' and the ''shedim''. The word ''shedim'' appears in two places in the [[Tanakh]] ({{bibleverse||Psalm|106:37}}, {{bibleverse||Deuteronomy|32:17}}). The ''se'irim'' are mentioned once in {{bibleverse||Leviticus|17:7}},&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/articles/5085-demonology|title=DEMONOLOGY - JewishEncyclopedia.com|website=www.jewishencyclopedia.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; probably a re-calling of [[Assyria]]n demons in shape of goats.&lt;ref&gt;Benjamin W. McCraw, Robert Arp ''Philosophical Approaches to Demonology'' Routledge 2017 {{ISBN|978-1-315-46675-0}} page 9&lt;/ref&gt; The ''shedim'' in return are not pagan demigods, but the foreign gods themselves. Both entities appear in a [[Context (language use)#Verbal context|scriptural context]] of animal or [[child sacrifice]] to &quot;non-existent&quot; [[false god]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;JE-shedim&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;JVL-Demons&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Plaut-Shedoim&quot;&gt;{{cite book |first=W. Gunther |last=Plaut |title=The Torah: A Modern Commentary |publisher=Union for Reform Judaism |year=2005 |page=1403}}&lt;/ref&gt;

From Chaldea, the term ''shedu'' traveled to the Israelites. The writers of the Tanach applied the word as a [[dialogism]] to Canaanite deities.

There are indications that demons in popular Hebrew mythology were believed to come from the nether world.&lt;ref&gt;compare {{bibleverse||Isaiah|38:11}} with {{bibleverse||Job|14:13}}; {{bibleverse||Psalms|16:10}}, {{bibleverse-nb||Psalms|49:16}}, and {{bibleverse-nb||Psalms|139:8}}&lt;/ref&gt; Various diseases and ailments were ascribed to them, particularly those affecting the brain and those of internal nature. Examples include catalepsy, headache, epilepsy and nightmares. There also existed a demon of blindness, &quot;Shabriri&quot; (lit. &quot;dazzling glare&quot;) who rested on uncovered water at night and blinded those who drank from it.&lt;ref name=Isaacs1&gt;{{cite book|last1=Isaacs|first1=Ronald H.|title=Ascending Jacob's Ladder: Jewish Views of Angels, Demons, and Evil Spirits|date=1998|publisher=Jason Aronson|isbn=978-0-7657-5965-8|page=96|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=4iLqceVe7S0C&amp;pg=PA96&amp;lpg=PA96&amp;dq=shabriri+demon+blindness&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=quVL5HVZOY&amp;sig=6LBivAJ52pR9Xp8EGrosJcp9g9A&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=lNQPVNytE7HsiwKtnIDIDw&amp;sqi=2&amp;ved=0CDUQ6AEwAg#v=onepage&amp;q=shabriri%20demon%20blindness&amp;f=false|accessdate=10 September 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Demons supposedly entered the body and caused the disease while overwhelming or &quot;seizing&quot; the victim. To cure such diseases, it was necessary to draw out the evil demons by certain incantations and talismanic performances, at which the [[Essenes]] excelled.&lt;ref name=&quot;JE-shedim&quot;/&gt; [[Josephus]], who spoke of demons as &quot;spirits of the wicked which enter into men that are alive and kill them&quot;, but which could be driven out by a certain root,&lt;ref&gt;''Bellum Judaeorum'' vii. 6, §&amp;nbsp;3&lt;/ref&gt; witnessed such a performance in the presence of the Emperor Vespasian&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Antiquities&quot; viii. 2, §&amp;nbsp;5&lt;/ref&gt; and ascribed its origin to [[King Solomon]]. In mythology, there were few defences against Babylonian demons. The mythical mace [[Sharur (mythological weapon)|Sharur]] had the power to slay demons such as [[Asag]], a legendary [[gallu]] or [[edimmu]] of hideous strength.

==== Talmudic tradition ====
{{See also|Talmud|Jerusalem Talmud}}
In the [[Jerusalem Talmud]] notions of ''shedim'' (&quot;demons&quot; or &quot;spirits&quot;) are almost unknown or occur only very rarely, whereas in the Babylon Talmud there are many references to ''shedim''  and magical incantations. The existence of ''shedim'' in general was not questioned by most of the Babylonian [[Talmudist]]s. As a consequence of the rise of influence of the Babylonian Talmud over that of the Jerusalem Talmud, late rabbis in general took as fact the existence of ''shedim'', nor did most of the medieval thinkers question their reality. However, rationalists like [[Maimonides]], [[Saadia Gaon]] and [[Abraham ibn Ezra]] and others explicitly denied their existence, and completely rejected concepts of demons, evil spirits, negative spiritual influences, attaching and possessing spirits. Their point of view eventually became mainstream Jewish understanding.&lt;ref name=&quot;JE-shedim&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;D-BH-Shedim&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://machonshilo.org/en/eng/component/content/article/34-featured/830-do-jews-believe-in-demons-and-evil-spirits-interview-with-rabbi-david-bar-hayim|title=Do Jews Believe in Demons and Evil Spirits?|publisher=Machon Shilo|last1=Bar-Hayim|first1=David (HaRav)|accessdate=20 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Kabbalah ====
{{See also|Kabbalah|Destroying angel (Bible)||Asmodeus}}
In [[Kabbalah]] demons are regarded a necessary part of the divine emanation in the material world and a byproduct of human sin ([[Qliphoth]]).&lt;ref&gt;Geoffrey W. Dennis ''The Encyclopedia of Jewish Myth, Magic and Mysticism: Second Edition'' Llewellyn Worldwide 2016 {{ISBN|978-0-738-74814-6}}&lt;/ref&gt; However spirits such as the ''shedim'' may also be benevolent and were used in kabbalistic ceremonies (as with the ''[[golem]]'' of Rabbi Yehuda Loevy) and malevolent ''shedim'' (''[[Mazzikin|Mazikin]]'', from the root meaning &quot;to damage&quot;) were often credited with possession.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=T0S9CQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA46&amp;lpg=PA46&amp;dq=Some+benevolent+shedim+were+used+in+kabbalistic+ceremonies+(as+with+the+golem+of+Rabbi+Yehuda+Loevy)+and+malevolent+shedim+(mazikin,+from+the+root+meaning+%22to+damage%22)+were+often+credited+with+possession&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=9MWufwWnd_&amp;sig=RseZI6pPfaUOT6cYhqDVTsfsRCU&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwixtKHv-MbRAhUDMyYKHRLlAbQQ6AEIIzAB#v=onepage&amp;q=Some%20benevolent%20shedim%20were%20used%20in%20kabbalistic%20ceremonies%20(as%20with%20the%20golem%20of%20Rabbi%20Yehuda%20Loevy)%20and%20malevolent%20shedim%20(mazikin,%20from%20the%20root%20meaning%20%22to%20damage%22)%20were%20often%20credited%20with%20possession&amp;f=false|title=The Esoteric Codex: Supernatural Legends|last=Pettigrove|first=Cedrick|date=2017-01-16|publisher=Lulu.com|isbn=9781329053090|language=en}}{{self-published source|date=February 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{self-published inline|date=February 2020}}

==== Aggadah ====
{{See also|Aggadah|Angels in Judaism}}
Aggadic tales from the Persian tradition describe the ''shedim'', the '' [[Mazzikin|mazziḳim]]'' (&quot;harmers&quot;), and the '' ruḥin'' (&quot;spirits&quot;). There were also ''[[lilin]]'' (&quot;night spirits&quot;), '' ṭelane'' (&quot;shade&quot;, or &quot;evening spirits&quot;), '' ṭiharire'' (&quot;midday spirits&quot;), and '' ẓafrire'' (&quot;morning spirits&quot;), as well as the &quot;demons that bring famine&quot; and &quot;such as cause storm and earthquake&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;(Targ. Yer. to Deuteronomy xxxii. 24 and Numbers vi. 24; Targ. to Cant. iii. 8, iv. 6; Eccl. ii. 5; Ps. xci. 5, 6.)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;JE-shedim&quot;/&gt; According to some [[Aggadah|aggadic]] stories, demons were under the dominion of a king or chief, either [[Asmodai]]&lt;ref&gt;Targ. to Eccl. i. 13; Pes. 110a; Yer. Shek. 49b&lt;/ref&gt; or, in the older Aggadah, [[Samael]] (&quot;the angel of death&quot;), who killed via poison.  Stories in the fashion of this kind of folklore never became an essential feature of Jewish theology.&lt;ref name=&quot;D-BH-Shedim&quot; /&gt; Although occasionally an [[Angels in Judaism|angel]] is called ''[[satan]]'' in the Babylon Talmud, this does not refer to a demon: &quot;Stand not in the way of an ox when coming from the pasture, for Satan dances between his horns&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Pes. 112b; compare B. Ḳ. 21a&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Second Temple period texts ====
{{See also|Apotropaic magic|Angels in Judaism}}
To the [[Qumran]] community during the [[Second Temple period]] this apotropaic prayer was assigned, stating: &quot;And, I the Sage, declare the grandeur of his radiance in order to frighten and terri[fy] all the spirits of the ravaging angels and the bastard spirits, demons, Liliths, owls&quot; (''Dead Sea Scrolls'', &quot;Songs of the Sage,&quot; Lines 4–5).&lt;ref&gt;García, Martínez Florentino. The Dead Sea Scrolls Translated: The Qumran Texts in English. Leiden: E.J. Brill, 1994. Print.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Florentino Martinez Garcia, ''Magic in the Dead Sea Scrolls: The Metamorphosis of Magic: From Late Antiquity to the Early Modern Period'', compilers Jan Bremmer and Jan R. Veenstra (Leuven: Peeters, 2003).&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[Dead Sea Scrolls]], there exists a fragment entitled &quot;Curses of Belial&quot; (''Curses of Belial (Dead Sea Scrolls, 394, 4Q286(4Q287, fr. 6)=4QBerakhot)''). This fragment holds much rich language that reflects the sentiment shared between the [[Qumran]] towards [[Belial]]. In many ways this text shows how these people thought Belial influenced sin through the way they address him and speak of him. By addressing &quot;Belial and all his guilty lot,&quot; (4Q286:2) they make it clear that he is not only impious, but also guilty of sins. Informing this state of uncleanliness are both his &quot;hostile&quot; and &quot;wicked design&quot; (4Q286:3,4). Through this design, Belial poisons the thoughts of those who are not necessarily sinners. Thus a dualism is born from those inclined to be wicked and those who aren't.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Frey |first=J. |chapter=Different patterns of dualistic thought in the Qumran library |title=Legal Texts And Legal Issues |year=1984 |page=287 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is clear that Belial directly influences sin by the mention of &quot;abominable plots&quot; and &quot;guilty inclination&quot; (4Q286:8,9). These are both mechanisms by which Belial advances his evil agenda that the Qumran have exposed and are calling upon God to protect them from. There is a deep sense of fear that Belial will &quot;establish in their heart their evil devices&quot; (4Q286:11,12). This sense of fear is the stimulus for this prayer in the first place. Without the worry and potential of falling victim to Belial's demonic sway, the Qumran people would never feel impelled to craft a curse. This very fact illuminates the power Belial was believed to hold over mortals, and the fact that sin proved to be a temptation that must stem from an impure origin.

In [[Jubilees]] 1:20, Belial's appearance continues to support the notion that sin is a direct product of his influence. Moreover, Belial's presence acts as a placeholder for all negative influences or those that would potentially interfere with God's will and a pious existence. Similarly to the &quot;gentiles ... [who] cause them to sin against you&quot; (Jubilees 1:19), Belial is associated with a force that drives one away from God. Coupled in this plea for protection against foreign rule, in this case the Egyptians, is a plea for protection from &quot;the spirit of Belial&quot; (Jubilees 1:19). Belial's tendency is to &quot;ensnare [you] from every path of righteousness&quot; (Jubilees 1:19). This phrase is intentionally vague, allowing room for interpretation. Everyone, in one way or another, finds themselves straying from the path of righteousness and by pawning this transgression off on Belial, he becomes a scapegoat for all misguidance, no matter what the cause. By associating Belial with all sorts of misfortune and negative external influence, the Qumran people are henceforth allowed to be let off for the sins they commit.{{Citation needed|reason=This is speculation and/or a personal opinion.|date=February 2020}} 

Belial's presence is found throughout the War Scrolls, located in the Dead Sea Scrolls, and is established as the force occupying the opposite end of the spectrum of God. In Col. I, verse 1, the very first line of the document, it is stated that &quot;the first attack of the Sons of Light shall be undertaken against the forces of the Sons of Darkness, the army of Belial&quot; (1Q33;1:1).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Nickelsburg |first=George |title=Jewish Literature between the Bible and the Mishna |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; This dichotomy sheds light on the negative connotations that Belial held at the time.{{sfnp|Frey|1984|p=278}} Where God and his Sons of Light are forces that protect and promote piety, Belial and his Sons of Darkness cater to the opposite, instilling the desire to sin and encouraging destruction. This opposition is only reinforced later in the document; it continues to read that the &quot;holy ones&quot; will &quot;strike a blow at wickedness&quot;, ultimately resulting in the &quot;annihilation of the Sons of Darkness&quot; (1Q33:1:13). This epic battle between good and evil described in such abstract terms, however it is also applicable to everyday life and serves as a lens through which the Qumran see the world. Every day is the Sons of Light battle evil and call upon God to help them overcome evil in ways small and large.

Belial's influence is not taken lightly. In Col. XI, verse 8, the text depicts God conquering the &quot;hordes of Belial&quot; (1Q33;11:8). This defeat is indicative of God's power over Belial and his forces of temptation. However the fact that Belial is the leader of hordes is a testament to how persuasive he can be. If Belial was obviously an arbiter of wrongdoing and was blatantly in the wrong, he wouldn't be able to amass an army. This fact serves as a warning message, reasserting God's strength, while also making it extremely clear the breadth of Belial's prowess. Belial's &quot;council is to condemn and convict&quot;, so the Qumran feel strongly that their people are not only aware of his purpose, but also equipped to combat his influence (1Q33;13:11).

In the [[Damascus Document]], Belial also makes a prominent appearance, being established as a source of evil and an origin of several types of sin. In Column 4, the first mention of Belial reads: &quot;Belial shall be unleashed against Israel&quot; (4Q266). This phrase is able to be interpreted myriad different ways. Belial is characterized in a wild and uncontrollable fashion, making him seem more dangerous and unpredictable. The notion of being unleashed is such that once he is free to roam; he is unstoppable and able to carry out his agenda uninhibited. The passage then goes to enumerate the &quot;three nets&quot; (4Q266;4:16) by which Belial captures his prey and forces them to sin. &quot;Fornication ..., riches ..., [and] the profanation of the temple&quot; (4Q266;4:17,18) make up the three nets. These three temptations were three agents by which people were driven to sin, so subsequently, the Qumran people crafted the nets of Belial to rationalize why these specific temptations were so toxic. Later in Column 5, Belial is mentioned again as one of &quot;the removers of bound who led Israel astray&quot; (4Q266;5:20). This statement is a clear display of Belial's influence over man regarding sin. The passage goes on to state: &quot;they preached rebellion against ... God&quot; (4Q266;5:21,22). Belial's purpose is to undermine the teachings of God, and he achieves this by imparting his nets on humans, or the incentive to sin.{{sfnp|Nickelsburg|p=147}}

In the ''[[War of the Sons of Light Against the Sons of Darkness]]'', Belial controls scores of demons, which are specifically allotted to him by God for the purpose of performing evil.&lt;ref&gt;Dead Sea Scrolls 1QS III 20–25&lt;/ref&gt; Belial, despite his malevolent disposition, is considered an [[Angels in Judaism|angel]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first=Dale Basil |last=Martin |authorlink=Dale Basil Martin |title=When did Angels Become Demons? |journal=[[Journal of Biblical Literature]] |year=2010 |volume=129 |issue=4 |pages=657–677 |doi=10.2307/25765960 |jstor=25765960}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Christianity ===

==== Old Testament ====
Demonic entities in the Old Testament of the [[Christian Bible]] are of two classes: the &quot;[[satyr]]s&quot; or &quot;shaggy goats&quot; (from [[Hebrew language|Hebr.]] ''se'irim'' &quot;hairy beings&quot;, &quot;he-goats&quot; or &quot;fauns&quot;; {{bibleverse||Isaiah|13:21|KJV}}, {{bibleverse-nb||Isaiah|34:14|KJV}})&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://biblesuite.com/hebrew/useirim_8163.htm |title=Hebrew Concordance: ū·śə·‘î·rîm – 1 Occurrence |publisher=Biblesuite.com |date= |accessdate=2014-03-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the &quot;demons&quot; (from Hebr. ''[[shedim]]'' first translated as {{lang-grc-gre|δαιμόνιον}} ''daimonion'', &quot;[[daemon]]&quot;; {{bibleverse-nb||Psalms|106:35–39|KJV}}, {{bibleverse-nb||Deuteronomy|32:17|KJV}}).

==== New Testament ====
[[File:Ottheinrich Folio051r Mc5A.jpg|thumb| [[Medieval illumination]] from the Ottheinrich Folio depicting the [[exorcism of the Gerasene demoniac]] by Jesus]]
The term ''demon'' (from the [[Koine Greek]] δαιμόνιον ''daimonion'') appears 63 times in the New Testament of the Christian Bible, mostly if not all relating to occurrences of possession of individuals and [[exorcisms of Jesus|exorcism by Jesus]].&lt;ref name=&quot;BibleHub-Daimonion&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=1140. daimonion|url=http://biblehub.com/greek/1140.htm |publisher=Biblos.com|accessdate=20 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Burton_Grady&quot;&gt;Dan Burton and David Grandy, ''Magic, Mystery, and Science: The Occult in Western Civilization'' (Indiana University Press, 2003), p. 120 [https://books.google.com/books?id=vSWSSBU7EdwC&amp;pg=PA120&amp;dq=%22The+Hebrew+term+for+demons%22&amp;lr=&amp;as_drrb_is=q&amp;as_minm_is=1&amp;as_miny_is=2009&amp;as_maxm_is=12&amp;as_maxy_is=2009&amp;num=100&amp;as_brr=3&amp;as_pt=ALLTYPES online].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Encyclopedia of Spirits: The Ultimate Guide to the Magic of Fairies, Genies, Demons, Ghosts, Gods &amp; Goddesses |first=Judika |last=Illes |publisher=HarperCollins |year=2009 |page=902 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=jDr51XX_YjEC&amp;pg=PA902&amp;dq=shedim#v=onepage&amp;q=shedim&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Pseudepigrapha and Deuterocanonical books ====
{{Main|Pseudepigrapha|Deuterocanonical books}}{{See also|Book of Tobit|Book of Enoch|Book of Jubilees}}
Demons are sometimes included into biblical interpretation. In the story of Passover, the Bible tells the story as &quot;the Lord struck down all the firstborn in Egypt&quot; (Exodus 12:21–29). In the [[Book of Jubilees]], which is considered canonical only by the [[Ethiopian Orthodox Church]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Harris&quot;&gt;[[Stephen L Harris|Harris, Stephen L.]], ''Understanding the Bible''. Palo Alto: Mayfield. 1985. It is considered one of the [[pseudepigrapha]] by [[Protestant]], [[Roman Catholic]], and [[Eastern Orthodox]] Churches&lt;/ref&gt; this same event is told slightly differently: &quot;All the powers of [the demon] Mastema had been let loose to slay all the first-born in the land of Egypt...And the powers of the Lord did everything according as the Lord commanded them&quot; (Jubilees 49:2–4).

In the [[Genesis flood narrative]] the author explains how God was noticing &quot;how corrupt the earth had become, for all the people on earth had corrupted their ways&quot; (Genesis 6:12). In Jubilees the sins of man are attributed to &quot;the unclean demons [who] began to lead astray the children of the sons of Noah, and to make to err and destroy them&quot; (Jubilees 10:1). In Jubilees Mastema questions the loyalty of Abraham and tells God to &quot;bid him offer him as a burnt offering on the altar, and Thou wilt see if he will do this command&quot; (Jubilees 17:16). The discrepancy between the story in Jubilees and the story in Genesis 22 exists with the presence of [[Mastema]]. In Genesis, God tests the will of Abraham merely to determine whether he is a true follower, however; in Jubilees Mastema has an agenda behind promoting the sacrifice of Abraham's son, &quot;an even more demonic act than that of the Satan in Job.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Moshe Berstein, ''Angels at the Aqedah: A Study in the Development of a Midrashic Motif'', (Dead Sea Discoveries, 7, 2000), 267.&lt;/ref&gt; In Jubilees, where Mastema, an angel tasked with the tempting of mortals into sin and iniquity, requests that God give him a tenth of the spirits of the children of the watchers, demons, in order to aid the process.&lt;ref&gt;Jubilees 10:7–9&lt;/ref&gt; These demons are passed into Mastema’s authority, where once again, an angel is in charge of demonic spirits.

[[File:Vrubel Demon.jpg|thumb|''[[The Demon Seated]]'' by [[Mikhail Vrubel]] (1890), a [[Russian symbolism|symbolist]] painting inspired by the Russian [[Romanticism|romantic]] poem ''[[Demon (poem)|demon]]'' by [[Mikhail Lermontov]].&lt;ref&gt;Sara Elizabeth Hecker. ''[http://artinrussia.org/dueling-demons-mikhail-vrubels-demon-seated-and-demon-downcast/ Dueling Demons: Mikhail Vrubel’s Demon Seated and Demon Downcast]. Art in Russia, 2012-05-08. {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150615105547/http://artinrussia.org/dueling-demons-mikhail-vrubels-demon-seated-and-demon-downcast/ |date=2015-06-15 }}''. Art in Russia, the School of Russian and Asian Studies, 2012&lt;/ref&gt;]]
The sources of demonic influence were thought to originate from the [[Watcher (angel)|Watchers]] or [[Nephilim]], who are first mentioned in Genesis 6 and are the focus of 1 Enoch Chapters 1–16, and also in Jubilees 10. The Nephilim were seen as the source of the sin and evil on earth because they are referenced in Genesis 6:4 before the story of the Flood.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Hanneken Henoch|first=T. R.|title=ANGELS AND DEMONS IN THE BOOK OF JUBILEES AND CONTEMPORARY APOCALYPSES|year=2006|pages=11–25}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Genesis 6:5, God sees evil in the hearts of men. The passage states, &quot;the wickedness of humankind on earth was great&quot;, and that &quot;Every inclination of the thoughts of their hearts was only continually evil&quot; (Genesis 5). The mention of the Nephilim in the preceding sentence connects the spread of evil to the Nephilim. Enoch is a very similar story to Genesis 6:4–5, and provides further description of the story connecting the Nephilim to the corruption of humans. In Enoch, sin originates when angels descend from heaven and fornicate with women, birthing giants as tall as 300 cubits. The giants and the angels' departure of Heaven and mating with human women are also seen as the source of sorrow and sadness on Earth. The book of Enoch shows that these fallen angels can lead humans to sin through direct interaction or through providing forbidden knowledge. In Enoch, Semyaz leads the angels to mate with women. Angels mating with humans is against God's commands and is a cursed action, resulting in the wrath of God coming upon Earth. Azazel indirectly influences humans to sin by teaching them divine knowledge not meant for humans. Asael brings down the &quot;stolen mysteries&quot; (Enoch 16:3). Asael gives the humans weapons, which they use to kill each other. Humans are also taught other sinful actions such as beautification techniques, alchemy, astrology and how to make medicine (considered forbidden knowledge at the time). Demons originate from the evil spirits of the giants that are cursed by God to wander the earth. These spirits are stated in Enoch to &quot;corrupt, fall, be excited, and fall upon the earth, and cause sorrow&quot; (Enoch 15:11).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=VanderKam|first=James C.|title=THE ANGEL STORY IN THE BOOK OF JUBILEES IN: Pseudepigraphic Perspectives : The Apocrypha And Pseudepigrapha In Light Of The Dead Sea Scrolls|year=1999|pages=151–170}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Book of Jubilees conveys that sin occurs when Cainan accidentally transcribes astrological knowledge used by the Watchers (Jubilees 8). This differs from Enoch in that it does not place blame on the Angels. However, in Jubilees 10:4 the evil spirits of the Watchers are discussed as evil and still remain on earth to corrupt the humans. God binds only 90 percent of the Watchers and destroys them, leaving 10 percent to be ruled by Mastema. Because the evil in humans is great, only 10 percent would be needed to corrupt and lead humans astray. These spirits of the giants also referred to as &quot;the bastards&quot; in the Apotropaic prayer Songs of the Sage, which lists the names of demons the narrator hopes to expel.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Vermes|first=Geza|title=The complete Dead Sea scrolls in English|year=2011|publisher=Penguin|location=London|page=375}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Christian demonology ====
{{Main|Christian demonology|Exorcism in Christianity|Exorcism in the Catholic Church|Demonic possession#Christianity}}
[[File:Jheronimus Bosch 050 detail 01.jpg|thumb|''[[Death and the Miser]]'' (detail), a [[Hieronymus Bosch]] painting, [[National Gallery of Art]], [[Washington, D.C.]]]]
In Christianity, demons are corrupted spirits carrying the execution of Satan's desires. They are generally regarded as three different types of spirits:
* Souls of the wicked deceased, which roam the earth to torment the living.&lt;ref&gt;Victor I. Ezigbo ''Re-imagining African Christologies: Conversing with the Interpretations and Appropriations of Jesus in Contemporary African Christianity'' Wipf and Stock Publishers 2010 {{ISBN|978-1-630-87803-0}} page 235&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Nephilim]], who came into being by union between angels and human, but their bodily part were wiped out during the [[Flood myth|Great flood]]. Their spiritual part now desires reembodiment.&lt;ref&gt;Juanita Feros Ruys ''Demons in the Middle Ages'' ISD LLC 2017 {{ISBN|978-1-942-40136-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Maijastina Kahlos ''Debate and Dialogue: Christian and Pagan Cultures C. 360–430'' Routledge 2016 {{ISBN|978-1-317-15436-5}} page 174&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Fallen angel]]s, who sided with [[Lucifer]] and were cast out of heaven by [[Michael (archangel)|Michael]] after battle.

Often deities of other [[religion]]s are interpreted or identified as such &quot;demons&quot; (from the [[Greek Old Testament]] δαιμόνιον ''daimonion'').&lt;ref name=&quot;DDD&quot;&gt;van der Toorn, K.; Becking, B.; van der Horst, P. W. (1999), &quot;Demon&quot;. In ''Dictionary of Deities and Demons in The Bible'', Second Extensively Revised Edition, pp. 235–240, William B. Eerdmans Publishing Company, {{ISBN|0-8028-2491-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; The evolution of the [[Devil in Christianity|Christian Devil]] and [[pentagram]] are examples of early rituals and images that showcase evil qualities, as seen by the Christian churches.

Since [[Early Christianity]], demonology has developed from a simple acceptance of demons to a complex study that has grown from the original ideas taken from Jewish demonology and Christian scriptures.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Orlov|first1=Andrei A.|title=Divine Scapegoats: Demonic Mimesis in Early Jewish Mysticism|date=2015|publisher=SUNY Press|location=New York|isbn=9781438455846|page=4}}&lt;/ref&gt; Christian demonology is studied in depth within the [[Roman Catholic Church]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sanctamissa.org/EN/resources/books-1962/rituale-romanum/57-exorcism-introduction.html Exorcism], ''Sancta Missa – Rituale Romanum'', 1962, at [http://www.sanctamissa.org/ sanctamissa.org], Copyright 2007. Canons Regular of St. John Cantius&lt;/ref&gt; although many other Christian churches affirm and discuss the existence of demons.&lt;ref&gt;Hansen, Chadwick (1970), ''Witchcraft at Salem'', p. 132, Signet Classics, Library of Congress Catalog Card Number: 69-15825&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Modica, Terry Ann (1996), ''Overcoming The Power of The Occult'', p. 31, Faith Publishing Company, {{ISBN|1-880033-24-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Building upon the few references to ''daemons'' in the New Testament, especially the poetry of the Book of Revelation, Christian writers of [[apocrypha]] from the 2nd century onwards created a more complicated tapestry of beliefs about &quot;demons&quot; that was largely independent of Christian scripture.

[[File:Schongauer Anthony.jpg|thumb|left|upright=0.8|[[Anthony the Great|St. Anthony the Great]] plagued by demons, [[The Temptation of St Anthony (Schongauer)|engraving]] by [[Martin Schongauer]] in the 1480s.]]
The contemporary Roman Catholic Church unequivocally teaches that angels and demons are real beings rather than just symbolic devices. The Catholic Church has a cadre of officially sanctioned exorcists which perform many [[exorcism]]s each year. The exorcists of the Catholic Church teach that demons attack humans continually but that afflicted persons can be effectively healed and protected either by the formal rite of exorcism, authorized to be performed only by bishops and those they designate, or by prayers of deliverance, which any Christian can offer for themselves or others.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.fathercorapi.com/articledet.asp?articleID=1928275639 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20040405135007/http://www.fathercorapi.com/articledet.asp?articleID=1928275639 |archivedate=2004-04-05 |title=Angels and Demons – Facts not Fiction |website=fathercorapi.com |first=John |last=Corapi |date=February 9, 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;

At various times in Christian history, attempts have been made to classify demons according to various proposed [[demonic hierarchy|demonic hierarchies]].

In the Gospels, particularly the [[Gospel of Mark]], Jesus cast out many demons from those afflicted with various ailments. He also lent this power to some of his disciples ({{bibleref2|Luke|10:17}}).

[[Apuleius]], by [[Augustine of Hippo]], is ambiguous as to whether ''daemons'' had become &quot;demonized&quot; by the early 5th century:
&lt;blockquote&gt;He [Apulieus] also states that the blessed are called in Greek ''eudaimones'', because they are good souls, that is to say, good demons, confirming his opinion that the souls of men are demons.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Augustine of Hippo |authorlink=Augustine of Hippo |title=City of God |chapter= Chapter 11: Of the Opinion of the Platonists, that the Souls of Men Become Demons When Disembodied |url=http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/npnf102.iv.IX.11.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

=== Islam ===
[[File:Kitab al-Bulhan -- devil.jpg|thumb|upright|Demons depicted in the [[Book of Wonders]], a late 14th century Arabic manuscript]]
[[File:Muhammad and &quot;shameless women&quot; in Hell.jpg|thumb|Depiction of a member of the Zabaniyya]]
[[Islam]] and Islam-related beliefs acknowledges the concept of evil spirits known as malevolent [[jinn]], [[Ifrit|afarit]] and [[Shaitan|shayatin]]. Unlike the belief in [[Angels in Islam|angels]], belief in demons is not obligated by [[the six articles of Islamic faith]].&lt;ref&gt;Tobias Nünlist ''Dämonenglaube im Islam'' Walter de Gruyter GmbH &amp; Co KG 2015 {{ISBN|978-3-110-33168-4}} p.&amp;nbsp;48 (German)&lt;/ref&gt; However, the existence of several demonic spirits is generally assumed by [[Islamic theology]] and further elaborated beliefs persist in Islamic folklore. The [[Dev (mythology)|Div]], probably adapted under Zorastrian influences, became another prominent demonic creature in Islamic culture. Just like jinn, they are able to possess humans, but differ from jinn and shayatin in their physical strength&lt;ref name=&quot;Partovi2009&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | last=Partovi | first=P. | date=December 2009 | title=Girls' Dormitory: Women's Islam and Iranian Horror | url=https://www.researchgate.net/publication/230310980_Girls'_Dormitory_Women's_Islam_and_Iranian_Horror |journal=Visual Anthropology Review | volume=25 | issue=2 | pages=186-207 | doi=10.1111/j.1548-7458.2009.01041.x | access-date=2019-10-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; thus also equated with [[Ogre]]s or giants.&lt;ref&gt;Yves Bonnefoy Asian Mythologies University of Chicago Press 1993 {{ISBN|978-0-226-06456-7}} p. 322&lt;/ref&gt; They are in constant war with [[peri]]&lt;ref&gt;Olinthus Gilbert Gregory Pantologia. A new (cabinet) cyclopædia, by J.M. Good, O. Gregory, and N. Bosworth assisted by other gentlemen of eminence, Band 8 Oxford University 1819 digitalized 2006 sec. 17&lt;/ref&gt; a benevolent spirit.&lt;ref&gt;Denise Aigle The Mongol Empire between Myth and Reality: Studies in Anthropological History BRILL, 28.10.2014 {{ISBN|9789004280649}} p. 118&lt;/ref&gt; Among Turks, the term ''In'' relating to demonic spirits, with characteristics comparable to jinn, are found and usually mentioned together.&lt;ref&gt;MacDonald, D.B., Massé, H., Boratav, P.N., Nizami, K.A. and Voorhoeve, P., “Ḏj̲inn”, in: Encyclopaedia of Islam, Second Edition, Edited by: P. Bearman, Th. Bianquis, C.E. Bosworth, E. van Donzel, W.P. Heinrichs. Consulted online on 15 November 2019 &lt;http://dx.doi.org/10.1163/1573-3912_islam_COM_0191&gt; First published online: 2012 First print edition: {{ISBN|978-90-04-16121-4}}, 1960–2007&lt;/ref&gt; [[Nar as-samum]] (''fires of samum'' or ''poisonious fire'') described in the Quran with hell, becomes associated with the minions of the Devil in [[tafsir]].&lt;ref&gt;Reynolds, Gabriel Said, “Angels”, in: Encyclopaedia of Islam, THREE, Edited by: Kate Fleet, Gudrun Krämer, Denis Matringe, John Nawas, Everett Rowson. Consulted online on 10 October 2019 &lt;http://dx.doi.org/10.1163/1573-3912_ei3_COM_23204&gt; First published online: 2009 First print edition: 9789004181304, 2009, 2009-3&lt;/ref&gt;Furthermore the Quran mentions the ''[[Zabaniyya]]'', who torture the damned in hell, who may have originated from a class of Arabian demons.&lt;ref&gt;Christian Lange ''Paradise and Hell in Islamic Traditions'' Cambridge University Press 2015 {{ISBN|978-1-316-41205-3}} page 52&lt;/ref&gt; However, their execution of punishment is in accordance with God’s order, therefore they are not equalized with shayatin, that means they are not devils, who in turn are rebellious against the divine will.

====Jinn and shayatin====
Rather than demonic, jinn are depicted as close to humans regarded as living in societies, in need of dwelling places, eating and drinking, and although their lifespan exceeds those of humans over centuries, they die and also need to procreate, but because they are created from ''smokeless fire'' in contrast to humans made from ''solid earth'', the latter can not see them. As for humans, jinn are also subject to temptations of the shayatin and [[Satan]] therefore may either be good or evil.&lt;ref&gt;A.G. Muhaimin ''The Islamic Traditions of Cirebon: Ibadat and Adat Among Javanese Muslims'' AnU E Press 2006 {{ISBN|978-1-920-94231-1}} page 46&lt;/ref&gt; Evil jinn are comparable to demons, scaring or possessing humans. In folklore some [[Ghoul]] may also lurk on lonely travelers to dissuade them from their paths and eat their corpses. Although not evil, a jinni may haunt a person, because it feels offended by him. Islam has no binding origin story of jinn, but Islamic beliefs commonly assume that the jinn were created on a Thursday thousands of years before mankind. Therefore Islamic medieval narratives often called them ''[[pre-Adamite]]s''.&lt;ref&gt;Amira El-Zein ''Islam, Arabs, and Intelligent World of the Jinn'' Syracuse University Press 2009 {{ISBN|978-0-815-65070-6}} page 39&lt;/ref&gt; However, just like shayatin, jinn are held responsible for various diseases and possession. Further both can be summoned and subjugated by magicians.&lt;ref&gt;Siam Bhayro, Catherine Rider ''Demons and Illness from Antiquity to the Early-Modern Period'' BRILL, 06.02.2017 {{ISBN|9789004338548}} p. 335&lt;/ref&gt; Both are thought to lurk in dirty and desolated places.&lt;ref&gt;Gauvain, Richard (2013). Salafi Ritual Purity: In the Presence of God. Abingdon, England: Routledge. p. 73. {{ISBN|978-0710313560}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Otherwise the shayatin are the Islamic equivalent of &quot;demons&quot; in western usage.&lt;ref&gt;Charles Mathewes ''Understanding Religious Ethics'' John Wiley &amp; Sons {{ISBN|978-1-405-13351-7}}. p.&amp;nbsp;249&lt;/ref&gt;
Islam differs in regard of the origin of demons. They may either be a class of heavenly creatures cast out of [[Jannah|heaven]] or the descendants of [[Iblis]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Robert Lebling&quot;&gt;Robert Lebling ''Legends of the Fire Spirits: Jinn and Genies from Arabia to Zanzibar'' I.B.Tauris 2010 {{ISBN|978-0-857-73063-3}} page 141&lt;/ref&gt; Unlike jinn and humans, shayatin are immortal and will meet their end when the world ceases to exist, however prayers could dissolve or banish them.&lt;ref&gt;Hajjah Amina Adil ''Muhammad the Messenger of Islam: His Life &amp; Prophecy'' BookBaby 2012 {{ISBN|978-1-618-42913-1}} chapter Ezra&lt;/ref&gt; However unlike jinn and human, shayatin can not attain salvation. Further they are thought to attempt to reach to heaven, but are chased away from the angels or shooting stars. The shayatin usually do not possess people, but &quot;whisper&quot; to their minds and seduce them into falsehood and sin. These are called ''waswās'' and may enter the [[Qalb|hearts]] of humans to support negative feelings, especially in states of strong emotion like depression or anger.{{citation needed|date=February 2020}}

====Ifrit====
Another demonic spirit is called ''[[ifrit]]'' and although there are no descriptions regarding an iftrit's behavior found in Islamic canonical texts, [[Folk Islam]] often depicts them with traits of malevolent [[ghost]]s, returning after death or a subcategory of shayatin drawn the life-force of those who were murdered. Moreover, they are not exactly shayatin since they differ in their origin.&lt;ref&gt;A.G. Muhaimin ''The Islamic Traditions of Cirebon: Ibadat and Adat Among Javanese Muslims '' ANU E Press 2006 {{ISBN|978-1-920-94231-1}} page 38&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Bahá'í Faith ===
In the [[Bahá'í Faith]], demons are not regarded as independent evil spirits as they are in some faiths. Rather, evil spirits described in various faiths' traditions, such as Satan, fallen angels, demons and jinn, are metaphors for the base character traits a human being may acquire and manifest when he turns away from God and follows his lower nature. Belief in the existence of ghosts and earthbound spirits is rejected and considered to be the product of superstition.&lt;ref name=&quot;Psmith112&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Smith | first = Peter | year = 2008 | title = An Introduction to the Baha'i Faith | publisher = Cambridge University Press | place = Cambridge | isbn=978-0-521-86251-6 | ref = harv | page = 112}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Ceremonial magic ==
While some people fear demons, or attempt to exorcise them, others willfully attempt to summon them for knowledge, assistance, or power. The ceremonial magician usually consults a [[grimoire]], which gives the names and abilities of demons as well as detailed instructions for conjuring and controlling them. Grimoires are not limited to demons – some give the names of angels or spirits which can be called, a process called [[theurgy]]. The use of ceremonial magic to call demons is also known as [[goetia]], the name taken from a section in the famous grimoire known as the ''[[Lesser Key of Solomon]]''.&lt;ref&gt;A. E. Waite, ''The Book of Black Magic'', (Weiser Books, 2004).&lt;/ref&gt;

== Hinduism ==
{{refimprove section|date=May 2018}}
{{Original research|date=May 2018}}
[[Hinduism|Hindu]] beliefs include numerous varieties of spirits such as [[Vetala]]s, [[Bhoot (ghost)|Bhutas]] and [[Pishachas]]. [[Rakshasas]] and [[Asuras]] are often misunderstood to be demons.

=== Asuras ===
{{See also|Surapadman|Narakasura}}
[[File:The Army of Super Creatures.jpg|thumb|The Army of Super Creatures – from The Saugandhika Parinaya Manuscript (1821 CE)]]
''Asura'', in the earliest hymns of the [[Rigveda]], originally meant any supernatural spirit, either good or bad. Since the /s/ of the Indic linguistic branch is cognate with the /h/ of the Early Iranian languages, the word ''Asura'', representing a category of celestial beings. Ancient Hinduism tells that [[Deva (Hinduism)|Devas]] (also called ''suras'') and [[Asura]]s are half-brothers, sons of the same father [[Kashyapa]]; although some of the Devas, such as [[Varuna]], are also called Asuras. Later, during [[Puranic]] age, [[Asura]] and [[Rakshasa]] came to exclusively mean any of a race of anthropomorphic, powerful, possibly evil beings. Daitya (lit. sons of the mother &quot;Diti&quot;), [[Mayasura|Maya Danava]], Rakshasa (lit. from &quot;harm to be guarded against&quot;), and Asura are incorrectly translated into English as &quot;demon&quot;.

In post-Vedic Hindu scriptures, pious, highly enlightened Asuras, such as [[Prahlada]] and [[Vibhishana]], are not uncommon. The Asura are not fundamentally against the gods, nor do they tempt humans to fall. Many people metaphorically interpret the Asura as manifestations of the ignoble passions in the human mind and as symbolic devices. There were also cases of power-hungry Asuras challenging various aspects of the gods, but only to be defeated eventually and seek forgiveness.

=== Evil spirits ===
Hinduism advocates the reincarnation and transmigration of souls according to one's [[karma]]. Souls ([[Atman (Hinduism)|Atman]]) of the dead are adjudged by the [[Yama]] and are accorded various purging punishments before being reborn. Humans that have committed extraordinary wrongs are condemned to roam as lonely, often mischief mongers, spirits for a length of time before being reborn. Many kinds of such spirits ([[Vetala]]s, [[Pishacha]]s, [[Bhoot (ghost)|Bhūta]]) are recognized in the later Hindu texts.

==Iranian demons==
===Zoroastrianism===
{{Main article|Daeva}}
Evil spirits are the creation of the evil principle [[Ahriman]] in [[Zoroastrianism|Zoroastrian cosmology]], commonly referred to as [[Daeva]]. The first six [[archdemon]]s are produced by Ahriman in direct opposition to the [[Amesha Spenta|holy immortals]] created by [[Ahura Mazda]] the principle of good. This six archdemons (or seven if Ahriman is included) give existence to uncountable malevolent daeva; the Zorastrian demons. They are the embodiment of evil, causing moral imperfection, destroy, kill and torment the wicked souls in the afterlife.&lt;ref&gt;S. A. Nigosian, Solomon Alexander Nigosian ''The Zoroastrian Faith: Tradition and Modern Research'' McGill-Queen's Press - MQUP, 1993 {{ISBN|9780773511446}} p. 86-88&lt;/ref&gt; Some demons are related to specific vices. Humans in the state of such sin might be possessed by a corresponding demon:&lt;ref&gt;Fereshteh Davaran ''Continuity in Iranian Identity: Resilience of a Cultural Heritage'' Routledge, 26.02.2010 {{ISBN|9781134018314}} p. 124-130&lt;/ref&gt;
* Anger (''Kheshm'')
* Lazyness (''Bushyansta'')
* Envy (''Areshk'')
* Gossip (''Spazga'')
* Grief (''Akoman'')

=== Manichaeism ===
{{See also|Asrestar}}
In [[Manichaeism|Manichaean mythology]] demons had a real existence, as they derived from the Kingdom of Darkness, they were not metaphors expressing the absence of good nor are they [[fallen angel]]s, that means they are not originally good, but entities purely evil. The demons came into the world after the [[Prince of darkness (Manichaeism)|Prince of Darkness]] assaulted the Realm of Light. The demons ultimately failed their attack and ended up imprisoned in the structures and matter of the contemporary world.&lt;ref&gt;Willis Barnstone, Marvin Meyer ''The Gnostic Bible: Revised and Expanded Edition Shambhala Publications'' 2009 {{ISBN|978-0-834-82414-0}} page 575-577 &lt;/ref&gt; Lacking virtues and being in constant conflict with both the divine creatures and themselves, they are inferior to the divine entities and overcome by the divine beings at the end of time. They are not sophisticated or inventive creatures, but only driven by their urges.&lt;ref name=&quot;iranicaonline1&quot;&gt;http://www.iranicaonline.org/articles/manicheism-pandaemonium&lt;/ref&gt;

Simultaneously, the Manichaean concept of demons remains abstract and is closely linked to ethical aspects of evil that many of them appear as personified evil qualities such as:&lt;ref name=&quot;iranicaonline1&quot;/&gt;
* ''Greed'' (sexual desire)
* ''Wrath'' (desire for destruction)
* ''Envy''
* ''Grief''

The [[Watcher (angel)|Watcher]], another group of demonic entities, known from the [[Book of Enoch|Enochian writings]], appear in the canonical  [[The Book of Giants|Book of Giants]]. The Watchers came into existence after the demons were chained up in the sky by [[Living Spirit]]. Later, outwitted by [[Jesus the Splendour|Third Messenger]], they fall to earth, there they had intercourse with human women and beget the monstrous [[Nephilim]]. Thereupon they establish a tyrannical rule on earth, suppressing mankind, until they are defeated by the angels of punishment, setting an end to their rule.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.iranicaonline.org/articles/giants-the-book-of&lt;/ref&gt;

== Native North American demons ==

=== Wendigo ===
{{Main|Wendigo|Wechuge}}
The [[Algonquian peoples|Algonquian]] people traditionally believe in a spirit called a [[wendigo]]. The spirit is believed to possess people who then become [[cannibals]]. In [[Athabaskan]] folklore, there is a belief in [[wechuge]], a similar cannibal sprit. 

== Wicca ==
According to [[Rosemary Ellen Guiley]], &quot;Demons are not courted or worshipped in contemporary [[Wicca]] and [[Paganism]]. The existence of negative energies is acknowledged.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=The Encyclopedia of Witches, Witchcraft and Wicca |page=95 |first=Rosemary |last=Guiley |year=2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Modern interpretations ==
[[File:Japanese demon mask.jpg|thumb|upright|The classic [[Oni]], an Japanese ogre-like creature which often has horns and often translated into English as &quot;demon&quot;.]]
Psychologist [[Wilhelm Wundt]] remarked that &quot;among the activities attributed by myths all over the world to demons, the harmful predominate, so that in popular belief bad demons are clearly older than good ones.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvp|Freud|1950|p=65}}, quoting Wundt (1906, 129).&lt;/ref&gt; [[Sigmund Freud]] developed this idea and claimed that the concept of demons was derived from the important relation of the living to the dead: &quot;The fact that demons are always regarded as the spirits of those who have died ''recently'' shows better than anything the influence of mourning on the origin of the belief in demons.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvtxt|Freud|1950}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[M. Scott Peck]], an American psychiatrist, wrote two books on the subject, ''People of the Lie: The Hope For Healing Human Evil''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Peck |first=M. S. |authorlink=M. Scott Peck |year=1983 |title=People of the Lie: The Hope For Healing Human Evil|url=https://archive.org/details/peopleofliehopef00peck |url-access=registration }}&lt;/ref&gt; and ''Glimpses of the Devil: A Psychiatrist's Personal Accounts of Possession, Exorcism, and Redemption''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Peck |first=M. S. |authorlink=M. Scott Peck |year=2005 |title=Glimpses of the Devil: A Psychiatrist's Personal Accounts of Possession, Exorcism, and Redemption|url=https://archive.org/details/glimpsesofdevila00peck |url-access=registration }}&lt;/ref&gt; Peck describes in some detail several cases involving his patients. In ''People of the Lie'' he provides identifying characteristics of an evil person, whom he classified as having a character disorder. In ''Glimpses of the Devil'' Peck goes into significant detail describing how he became interested in [[exorcism]] in order to debunk the ''myth'' of [[Demonic possession|possession]] by evil spirits – only to be convinced otherwise after encountering two cases which did not fit into any category known to [[psychology]] or [[psychiatry]]. Peck came to the conclusion that possession was a rare phenomenon related to evil and that possessed people are not actually evil; rather, they are doing battle with the forces of evil.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.salon.com/2005/01/18/peck_5/ The exorcist], an interview with M. Scott Peck by Rebecca Traister published in [http://www.salon.com/index.html Salon] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20051219102002/http://www.salon.com/news/col/horo/1999/12/13/betty/index.html |date=2005-12-19 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although Peck's earlier work was met with widespread popular acceptance, his work on the topics of evil and possession has generated significant debate and derision. Much was made of his association with (and admiration for) the controversial [[Malachi Martin]], a [[Roman Catholic]] priest and a former [[Jesuit]], despite the fact that Peck consistently called Martin a liar and a manipulator.&lt;ref name=&quot;Woods&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.beliefnet.com/story/159/story_15928.html The Patient Is the Exorcist], an interview with M. Scott Peck by Laura Sheahen&lt;/ref&gt; Richard Woods, a Roman Catholic priest and theologian, has claimed that Dr. Peck misdiagnosed patients based upon a lack of knowledge regarding [[dissociative identity disorder]] (formerly known as multiple personality disorder) and had apparently transgressed the boundaries of [[professional ethics]] by attempting to persuade his patients into accepting Christianity.&lt;ref name=&quot;Woods&quot;&gt;[http://www.natcath.org/NCR_Online/archives2/2005b/042905/042905m.htm The devil you know], ''National Catholic Reporter, April 29, 2005, a commentary on ''Glimpses of the Devil'' by Richard Woods&lt;/ref&gt; Father Woods admitted that he has never witnessed a genuine case of demonic possession in all his years.&lt;ref name=&quot;WoodsInfo&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dom.edu/newsroom/experts/faculty/faculty_w.html#woods|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120829121523/http://www.dom.edu/newsroom/experts/faculty/faculty_w.html#woods|url-status=dead|title=Dominican Newsroom|archivedate=August 29, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;WoodsBio&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://richardwoodsop.net/site/Bio.php |title=RichardWoodsOP.net |publisher=RichardWoodsOP.net |accessdate=2014-03-12 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131228051312/http://richardwoodsop.net/site/Bio.php |archivedate=2013-12-28 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;bustedhalo&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Haarman |first=Susan |url=http://bustedhalo.com/features/the-devil-and-the-details/2 |title=BustedHalo.com |publisher=BustedHalo.com |date=2005-10-25 |accessdate=2014-03-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to S. N. Chiu, God is shown sending a demon against Saul in 1 Samuel 16 and 18 in order to punish him for the failure to follow God's instructions, showing God as having the power to use demons for his own purposes, putting the demon under his divine authority.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first=S. N. |last=Chiu |title=Historical, Religious, and Medical Perspectives of Possession Phenomenon |journal=Hong Kong Journal of Psychiatry |year=2000 |volume=10 |issue=1}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to the ''Britannica Concise Encyclopedia'', demons, despite being typically associated with evil, are often shown to be under divine control, and not acting of their own devices.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Demon&quot; in Britannica Concise Encyclopedia,&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{Div col|colwidth=20em}}
* [[Acheri]]
* [[Classification of demons]]
* [[Empusa]]
* [[Erinyes]]
* [[Folk devil]]
* [[Ghoul]]
* [[Goblin]]
* [[Holy water#Protection against evil]]
* [[Imp]]
* [[List of fictional demons]]
* [[List of theological demons]]
* [[Mara (demon)|Mara]]
* [[Oni]]
* [[Spiritual warfare]]
* [[Theistic Satanism]]
* [[Yaoguai]]
* [[Yokai]]
* [[Zlydzens]]
{{Div col end}}

== References ==
{{Reflist|30em}}

== Sources ==
* {{cite book |last=Freud |first=Sigmund |authorlink=Sigmund Freud |translator=Strachey |title=[[Totem and Taboo:Some Points of Agreement between the Mental Lives of Savages and Neurotics]] |year=1950 |publisher=W. W. Norton &amp; Company |location=New York |isbn=978-0-393-00143-3 |ref=harv}}
* [[Wilhelm Maximilian Wundt|Wundt, W.]] (1906). ''Mythus und Religion'', Teil II (''Völkerpsychologie'', Band II). Leipzig.
* [[Carlos Castaneda|Castaneda, Carlos]] (1998). ''The Active Side of Infinity''. HarperCollins NY {{ISBN|978-0-06-019220-4}}
* {{cite book |first=Thomas Patrick |last=Hughes |title=Dictionary of Islam |publisher=Asian Educational Services |year=1995 |isbn=978-8-120-60672-2 |ref=harv}}

== Further reading ==
* {{cite book |last=Oppenheimer|first=Paul |title=Evil and the Demonic: A New Theory of Monstrous Behavior |year=1996 |publisher=New York University Press |location=New York |isbn=978-0-8147-6193-9 }}
*Walton, John H., and J. Harvey Walton. 2019. ''Demons and Spirits in Biblical Theology: Reading the Biblical Text in its Cultural and Literary Context''.[https://books.google.com/books?id=WvGaDwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PR4&amp;dq=demons+and+spirits+in+biblical+theology+john+walton&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwi12ODXnajjAhUCX80KHUtKCnMQ6AEIKjAA#v=onepage&amp;q=demons%20and%20spirits%20in%20biblical%20theology%20john%20walton&amp;f=false]
;Catholic
* {{cite book|last=Baglio|first=Matt|title=The Rite: The Making of a Modern Exorcist|year=2009|publisher=Doubleday Religion|isbn=0-385-52270-3|url=https://archive.org/details/ritemakingof000bagl}}
* {{cite book|last=Amorth|first=Gabriele|title=An Exorcist Tells His Story|year=1999|publisher=Ignatius Press|isbn=0-89870-710-2}}

== External links ==
{{Wikiquote}}
*{{Wiktionary-inline|δαίμων}}
*{{Wiktionary-inline|demon}}
*{{Commons category-inline|Demons}}
* [http://www.vatican.va/archive/ccc_css/archive/catechism/index/d.htm#Demon Catechism of the Catholic Church'':] Hyperlinked references to demons in the online Catechism of the Catholic Church
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20050330091329/http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/cgi-local/DHI/dhi.cgi?id=dv1-79 ''Dictionary of the History of Ideas'':] Demonology
* [http://www.riverfronttimes.com/2008-08-13/news/demons-among-us-the-rft-paid-a-visit-to-america-s-foremost-demonologist-in-chesterfield-and-came-home-with-our-head-spinning/ Profile of William Bradshaw, American demonologist] Riverfront Times, St. Louis, Missouri, USA. August 2008.

{{Witchcraft|state=collapsed}}

[[Category:Demons| ]]
[[Category:Deities and spirits]]
[[Category:Ghosts]]
[[Category:Occult]]
[[Category:Paranormal terminology]]
[[Category:Religious terminology]]
[[Category:Supernatural]]
[[Category:Supernatural legends]]</text>
      <sha1>pcakh337dvzx6r23wakscqgnl0h2icr</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
