  <page>
    <title>Albert Pike</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2371</id>
    <revision>
      <id>940423178</id>
      <parentid>940422760</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-12T13:12:28Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Lieutcoluseng</username>
        <id>19430894</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* External links */ Adding category</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Confederate States Army general}}
{{Use American English|date=October 2017}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=October 2017}}
{{Infobox military person
|name= Albert Pike
|image= Albert Pike - Brady-Handy.jpg
|caption= Pike in Masonic regalia by [[Mathew Brady]]
|birth_date= {{Birth date|1809|12|29}} 
|death_date= {{Death date and age|1891|4|2|1809|12|29}}
|birth_place= [[Boston]], [[Massachusetts]], U.S.
|death_place= [[Washington, D.C.]], U.S.
|placeofburial= [[Oak Hill Cemetery (Washington, D.C.)|Oak Hill Cemetery]],&lt;br /&gt;Washington, D.C., U.S.
|placeofburial_label= Place of burial
|placeofburial_coordinates = {{coord|38|54|46.4|N|77|03|22.9|W|region:US-DC_type:landmark|display=inline}}
|allegiance= {{flag|United States|1846}}&lt;br /&gt;{{Flag|Confederate States|1861}}
|branch= &lt;!-- EDITORS NOTE: Please do not add the Army flag adopted by the U.S. government in 1956 (65 years after Pike's death) as it would be historically inaccurate. Thank you. --&gt;[[United States Volunteers]]&lt;br /&gt;{{army|CSA|size=23px}}
|serviceyears= 1846–1847 (USV)&lt;br /&gt;1861–1862 (CSA)
|rank= [[File:Union army cpt rank insignia.jpg|35px]] [[Captain (land)|Captain]] (USV)&lt;br /&gt;[[File:Confederate States of America General-collar.svg|35px]] [[Brigadier general|Brigadier-General]] (CSA)
|commands= District of [[Indian Territory in the American Civil War|Indian Territory]]
|battles=  [[Mexican–American War]]
*[[Battle of Buena Vista]]
[[American Civil War]]
*[[Battle of Pea Ridge]]
}}
'''Albert Pike''' (December 29, 1809 – April 2, 1891) was an American author, poet, orator, jurist and prominent member of the [[Freemasonry|Freemasons]]. He was also a senior [[Officer (armed forces)|officer]] of the [[Confederate States Army]] who commanded the District of [[Indian Territory in the American Civil War|Indian Territory]] in the [[Trans-Mississippi Theater of the American Civil War|Trans-Mississippi Theater]] of the [[American Civil War]].

==Early life and education==
Albert Pike was born in [[Boston]], [[Massachusetts]], on December 29, 1809, the son of Benjamin and Sarah (Andrews) Pike, and spent his childhood in [[Byfield, Massachusetts|Byfield]] and [[Newburyport, Massachusetts]]. His colonial ancestors settled the area in 1635,&lt;ref name=mscacw/&gt; and included [[John Pike (settler)|John Pike]] (1613–1688/1689), the founder of [[Woodbridge, New Jersey]].&lt;ref&gt;Albert's descent from his immigrant ancestor John Pike is as follows: John Pike (1572–1654); John Pike (1613–1688/89); Joseph Pike (1638–1694); Thomas Pike (1682–1753/4); John Pike (1710–1755); Thomas Pike (1739–1836); Benjamin Pike (1780–?); Albert Pike (1809–1891).&lt;/ref&gt; He attended school in Newburyport and [[Framingham, Massachusetts|Framingham]] until he was 15. In August 1825, he passed entrance exams at [[Harvard University]], though when the college requested payment of tuition fees for the first two years, he chose not to attend. He began a program of self-education, later becoming a schoolteacher in [[Gloucester, Massachusetts|Gloucester]], [[Bedford, Massachusetts|North Bedford]], [[Fairhaven, Massachusetts|Fairhaven]] and Newburyport.&lt;ref&gt;Hubbell, Jay B. (1954) ''The South in American Literature: 1607–1900''. Durham, North Carolina: Duke University Press. p. 640.&lt;/ref&gt;

Pike was an imposing figure; six feet tall and 300 pounds with hair that reached his shoulders and a long beard.&lt;ref name=smithassoc&gt;[http://civilwarstudies.org/articles/Vol_5/pike.shtm &quot;Albert Pike - Hero or Scoundrel?&quot;, ''The Smithsonian Associates Civil War E-Mail Newsletter'', Volume 5, Number 1, Civil War Studies.org, Smithsonian Associates]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Cutrer/&gt; In 1831, he left Massachusetts to travel west, first stopping in [[Nashville, Tennessee]] and later moving to [[St. Louis, Missouri]].

There he joined an expedition to [[Taos, New Mexico]], devoted to hunting and trading.&lt;ref name=mscacw/&gt; During the excursion his horse broke and ran, forcing Pike to walk the remaining 500 miles to Taos. After this, he joined a trapping expedition to the [[Llano Estacado]] in New Mexico and Texas. Trapping was minimal and, after traveling about 1,300 miles (650 on foot), he finally arrived at [[Fort Smith, Arkansas]].&lt;ref name=Cutrer&gt;[http://www.tshaonline.org/handbook/online/articles/fpi18 Cutrer, Thomas W., &quot;Pike, Albert&quot;, ''The Handbook of Texas'', Texas State Historical Association]&lt;/ref&gt;

Pike's relative, Jacob, married Bethina Jones, daughter of the Chief of the Choctaw Nation. Jacob and Bethina's son, Benjamin M. Pike, was fluent in several Indian dialects and served as representative between the Native American Tribes in Oklahoma and the government of the United States of America.

==Journalist and lawyer==
[[File:AlbertPikeYounger.jpeg|thumb|left]]
Settling in Arkansas in 1833, Pike taught in a school and wrote a series of articles for the [[Little Rock, Arkansas|Little Rock]] ''Arkansas Advocate'' under the pen name of &quot;Casca.&quot;&lt;ref name=moneyhon/&gt; The articles were sufficiently well received for him to be asked to join the newspaper's staff. Under Pike's administration, the ''Advocate'' promoted the viewpoint of the [[Whig Party (United States)|Whig Party]] in a politically volatile and divided Arkansas in December 1832.&lt;ref name=moneyhon/&gt; After marrying Mary Ann Hamilton in 1834, he purchased the newspaper.&lt;ref name=ipw&gt;[http://www.okhistory.org/publications/enc/entry.php?entry=PI006 Westmoreland, Ingrid P., &quot;Pike, Albert&quot;, Oklahoma Historical Society]&lt;/ref&gt;

He was the first reporter for the [[Arkansas Supreme Court]]. He wrote a book (published anonymously), titled ''The Arkansas Form Book'', which was a guidebook for lawyers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Albert Pike (1809–1891)|url=http://www.encyclopediaofarkansas.net/encyclopedia/entry-detail.aspx?entryID=1737|website=Encyclopedia of Arkansas History &amp; Culture (EOA)|accessdate=29 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; Pike began to study law and was admitted to the [[bar (law)|bar]] in 1837, selling the ''Advocate'' the same year.

He also made several contacts among the Native American tribes in the area. He specialized in claims on behalf of Native Americans against the federal government.&lt;ref name=smithassoc/&gt; In 1852, he represented [[Muscogee|Creek Nation]] before the Supreme Court in a claim regarding ceded tribal land. In 1854 he advocated for the [[Choctaw]] and [[Chickasaw]], although compensation later awarded to the tribes in 1856 and 1857 was insufficient.&lt;ref name=ipw/&gt; These relationships were to influence the course of his Civil War service.

Additionally, Pike wrote on several legal subjects. He also continued writing poetry, a hobby he had begun in his youth in Massachusetts. His poems were highly regarded in his day, but are now mostly forgotten. Several volumes of his works were privately published posthumously by his daughter.  In 1859, he received an honorary Master of Arts degree from Harvard.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The Phoenix,&quot; Manly P. Hall&lt;/ref&gt;

==Military service==
[[File:Albert Pike memorial statue.jpg|thumb|''[[Brigadier General Albert Pike]]'' statue, Washington, D.C.]]

===Mexican–American War===
When the [[Mexican–American War]] started, Pike joined the Regiment of Arkansas Mounted Volunteers (a cavalry regiment) and was commissioned as a troop commander with the rank of captain in June 1846.  With his regiment, he fought in the [[Battle of Buena Vista]]. Pike was discharged in June 1847.  He and his commander, Colonel [[John Selden Roane]], had several differences of opinion. This situation led finally to an &quot;inconclusive&quot; [[duel]] between Pike and Roane on July 29, 1847, near Fort Smith, Arkansas.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eicher429&quot;&gt;Eicher, John H., aer (2001) ''Civil War High Commands''. Stanford: Stanford University Press. {{ISBN|0-8047-3641-3}}. p. 429&lt;/ref&gt; Although several shots were fired in the duel, nobody was injured, and the two were persuaded by their seconds to discontinue it.&lt;ref name=allsopp&gt;[https://archive.org/details/lifestoryofalber00allsrich &lt;!-- quote=albert pike. --&gt; Allsopp, Frederick William. ''A Life of Albert Pike'', Parke-Harper news service, 1920]&lt;/ref&gt;

After the war, Pike returned to the practice of law, moving to [[New Orleans, Louisiana|New Orleans]] for a time beginning in 1853.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Moneyhon |first1=Carl H. |title=Albert Pike (1809-1891) |url=https://encyclopediaofarkansas.net/entries/albert-pike-1737/ |website=Encyclopedia of Arkansas |accessdate=4 February 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt; He wrote another book, ''Maxims of the Roman Law and Some of the Ancient French Law, as Expounded and Applied in Doctrine and Jurisprudence''.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title=A life of Albert Pike|last=Brown|first=Walter Lee|publisher=University of Arkansas Press|year=1997|isbn=1557284695|location=Fayetteville|pages=61, 240, 302, 408}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although unpublished, this book increased his reputation among his associates in law. He returned to Arkansas in 1857, gaining some amount of prominence in the legal field.

At the Southern Commercial Convention of 1854, Pike said the South should remain in the Union and seek equality with the North, but if the South &quot;were forced into an inferior status, she would be better out of the Union than in it.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Potter, David Morris and Edward, Don (1976) ''The Impending Crisis, 1848–1861''. HarperCollins. p. 467&lt;/ref&gt;  His stand was that state's rights superseded national law and he supported the idea of a Southern secession. This stand is made clear in his pamphlet of 1861, &quot;State or Province, Bond or Free?&quot;&lt;ref name=moneyhon/&gt;

===American Civil War===
In 1861, Pike penned the lyrics to &quot;Dixie to Arms!&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://chnm.gmu.edu/loudountah/activities/pdf/DixieSongLyrics2.pdf &quot;Dixie to Arms!&quot;, Roy Rosenzweig Center for History and New Media, George Mason University]&lt;/ref&gt; At the beginning of the war, Pike was appointed as Confederate envoy to the Native Americans. In this capacity he negotiated [[List of treaties of the Confederate States of America|several treaties]], one of the most important being with [[Cherokee]] chief [[John Ross (Cherokee chief)|John Ross]], which was concluded in 1861. At the time, Ross agreed to support the Confederacy, which promised the tribes a Native American state if it won the war. Ross later changed his mind and left Indian Territory, but the succeeding Cherokee government maintained the alliance.&lt;ref name=smithassoc/&gt;

Pike was commissioned as a [[Brigadier general (United States)|brigadier general]] on November 22, 1861, and given a command in the [[Indian Territory]]. With Gen. [[Benjamin McCulloch|Ben McCulloch]], Pike trained three Confederate [[regiment]]s of [[Indian cavalry]], most of whom belonged to the &quot;[[Five Civilized Tribes|civilized tribes]]&quot;, whose loyalty to the Confederacy was variable. Although initially victorious at the [[Battle of Pea Ridge]] (Elkhorn Tavern) in March 1862,&lt;ref name=mscacw&gt;[http://www.ma150.org/day-by-day/1862-03-06/massachusetts-born-csa-general-albert-pike-leads-brigade-native-americans-batt &quot;Massachusetts born CSA general Albert Pike leads brigade of Native Americans at the Battle of Pea Ridge&quot;, Massachusetts Sesquicentennial Commission of the American Civil War] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160725142921/http://www.ma150.org/day-by-day/1862-03-06/massachusetts-born-csa-general-albert-pike-leads-brigade-native-americans-batt |date=July 25, 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Pike's unit was defeated later in a counterattack, after falling into disarray. When Pike was ordered in May 1862 to send troops to Arkansas, he resigned in protest.&lt;ref name=ipw/&gt; As in the previous war, Pike came into conflict with his superior officers, at one time drafting a letter to [[Jefferson Davis]] complaining about his direct superior.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Bibliography of the Writings of Albert Pike: Prose, Poetry, Manuscript.|last=Boyden|first=William Llewellyn|publisher=A.A.S.C.|year=1921|isbn=|location=Washington, D.C.|pages=18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After Pea Ridge, Pike was faced with charges that his Native American troops had [[scalping|scalped]] soldiers in the field.&lt;ref&gt;Shea, William, and Earl Hess, ''Pea Ridge: Civil War Campaign in the West''. University of North Carolina Press, 1992. {{ISBN|0-8078-4669-4}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Maj. Gen. [[Thomas C. Hindman]] also charged Pike with mishandling of money and material, ordering his arrest.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smith585&quot;&gt;Smith, Dean E. (1986) &quot;Pike, Albert&quot; in ''Historical Times Illustrated History of the Civil War'', edited by Patricia L. Faust. New York: Harper &amp; Row. {{ISBN|978-0-06-273116-6}}. p. 585&lt;/ref&gt; Both these charges were later found to be considerably lacking in evidence; nevertheless Pike, facing arrest, escaped into the hills of Arkansas, sending his resignation from the [[Confederate States Army]] on July 12.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smith585&quot;/&gt; He was at length arrested on November 3 under charges of [[insubordination]] and [[treason]], and held briefly in [[Warren, Fannin County, Texas|Warren, Texas]]. His resignation was accepted on November 11, and he was allowed to return to Arkansas.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smith585&quot;/&gt;

==Freemasonry==
{{Freemasonry}}
Pike first joined the fraternal [[Independent Order of Odd Fellows]] in 1840. He next joined a [[Masonic Lodge]], where he became extremely active in the affairs of the organization. In 1859 he was elected Sovereign Grand Commander of the [[Scottish Rite]]'s Southern Jurisdiction.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eicher429&quot;/&gt; He remained Sovereign Grand Commander for the remainder of his life (a total of thirty-two years), devoting a large amount of his time to developing the rituals of the order.&lt;ref&gt;Warner, Ezra J. (1959) ''Generals in Gray: Lives of the Confederate Commanders.'' Baton Rouge: Louisiana State University Press. {{ISBN|0-8071-0823-5}}. pp. 240–241&lt;/ref&gt; Notably, he published a book called ''[[Morals and Dogma of the Ancient and Accepted Scottish Rite of Freemasonry]]'' in 1871, of which there were several subsequent editions. This helped the order grow during the nineteenth century. He also researched and wrote the seminal treatise ''Indo-Aryan Deities and Worship as Contained in the Rig-Veda''.

In America, Pike is still considered an eminent&lt;ref name=Pikeeminent&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20061221064805/http://www.freemason.org/cfo/mar_apr_2002/pike.htm ALBERT PIKE AND FREEMASONRY]. ''California Freemason''&lt;/ref&gt; and influential&lt;ref name=&quot;Pikeinfluence&quot;&gt;[http://www.masonicinfo.com/pike.htm Albert Pike], masonicinfo.com&lt;/ref&gt; Freemason, primarily in the Scottish Rite Southern Jurisdiction.&lt;ref&gt;[https://scottishrite.org/headquarters/virtual-tour/albert-pike-museum/ Albert Pike Museum, The Scottish Rite of Freeemasonry]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Death and legacy==
Pike died on April 2, 1891 in Washington, D.C. at the age of 81, and was buried at [[Oak Hill Cemetery (Washington, D.C.)|Oak Hill Cemetery]].  Burial was against his wishes; he had left instructions for his body to be cremated.&lt;ref name= hbtx&gt;[http://www.dcmemorials.com/index_indiv0000360.htm PIKE, Brigadier General Albert: Memorial at the Municipal Center in Washington, D.C.]. dcmemorials.com&lt;/ref&gt; In 1944, his remains were moved to the [[House of the Temple]], headquarters of the Southern Jurisdiction of the Scottish Rite.  A [[Brigadier General Albert Pike|memorial to Pike]] is located in the [[Judiciary Square]] neighborhood of Washington, D.C. He is the only Confederate military officer with an outdoor statue in Washington, D.C., and in 2019 Delegate [[Eleanor Holmes Norton]] called for it to be removed.&lt;ref name=&quot;CurbedNorton&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last1=Glambrone |first1=Andrew |title=Confederate statue near Judiciary Square should be removed, D.C. delegate says |url=https://dc.curbed.com/2019/7/31/20749036/dc-confederate-statue-albert-pike-congress-history |accessdate=1 August 2019 |work=[[Curbed]] |date=July 31, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Q.v.'', [[National Statuary Hall Collection#Confederates|Wikipedia's article on the statues of Confederates in the National Statuary Hall Collection]].&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Albert Pike Memorial Temple]] is an historic Masonic lodge in [[Little Rock, Arkansas]]; the structure is listed on the [[National Register of Historic Places]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.littlerock.com/travel-tools/local-services/detail/historic-albert-pike-masonic-center &quot;Historic Albert Pike Masonic Center&quot;, Little Rock Convention and Visitors Bureau]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Albert Pike Morals and dogma.jpg|''Morals and Dogma'' (1871)
File:Albert Pike portrait.jpg|Pike in Masonic regalia
&lt;/gallery&gt;

===Figure in conspiracy theory===
Pike has become a key figure for [[conspiracy theorists]]. Some people claim that stories about Pike, including his &quot;forecast&quot; of three world wars, are bogus and derive from the [[Taxil hoax]].&lt;ref&gt;Ellis, Bill. ''Lucifer Ascending: The Occult in Folklore and Popular Culture'', University Press of Kentucky, 2004,  p12&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 2007 movie ''[[National Treasure: Book of Secrets]]'', Albert Pike is mentioned as a Confederate general to whom a missive from Queen Victoria is addressed.

==Poetry==
As a young man of letters, Pike wrote poetry, and he continued to do so for the rest of his life. At 23, he published his first poem, &quot;Hymns to the Gods.&quot; Later work was printed in literary journals such as ''[[Blackwood's Magazine|Blackwood's Edinburgh Magazine]]'' and local newspapers. His first collection of poetry, ''Prose Sketches and Poems Written in the Western Country'', was published in 1834.&lt;ref name=Cutrer /&gt; He later gathered many of his poems and republished them in ''Hymns to the Gods and Other Poems'' (1872). After his death these were published again in ''Gen. Albert Pike's Poems'' (1900) and ''Lyrics and Love Songs'' (1916).&lt;ref name=moneyhon&gt;{{Citation |last1=Moneyhon|first1=Carl H. |title=Albert Pike (1809–1891) |work=Encyclopedia of Arkansas History &amp; Culture |date=February 4, 2009 |url=http://www.encyclopediaofarkansas.net/encyclopedia/entry-detail.aspx?entryID=1737 |accessdate=November 14, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The authorship of &quot;[[The Old Canoe]]&quot; was attributed to Pike. He was suggested as author because about the time of its publication, when it was going the rounds of the press, probably without any credit, a [[doggerel]] called &quot;The Old Canoe&quot; was composed about Pike by one of his political foes. The subject was a canoe in which he left [[Columbia, Tennessee]], when a young man practicing law in that place. Pike told Senator [[Edward W. Carmack]] that he was not the author of &quot;The Old Canoe,&quot; and could not imagine how he ever got the credit for it. The rightful author was [[Emily Rebecca Page]].{{sfn|Bob Taylor's Magazine|1910|p=192}}

==Selected works==
* ''Indo-Aryan Deities and Worship as Contained in the Rig-Veda'' (1872)
* ''[[Morals and Dogma of the Ancient and Accepted Scottish Rite of Freemasonry|Morals and Dogma of the Ancient and Accepted Scottish Rite]]'' (1872)
* ''Book of the Words'' (1874)
* ''Reprints of Old Rituals'' (1879)

==See also==&lt;!-- EDITORS NOTE: This section should primarily contain lists linked to the main article which are directly related to the person. Thank you. --&gt;
* [[Arkansas_National_Guard#List_of_adjutants_general|List of Arkansas adjutants general]]
* [[List of American Civil War generals (Confederate)|List of American Civil War generals]]
* [[List of Freemasons (E–Z)|List of Freemasons]]
* [[List of people from Boston]]
* [[List of people from Little Rock, Arkansas]]

==Footnotes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==References==
{{Div col|colwidth=30em}}
* {{cite book | last = Abel | first = Annie | title = The American Indian as Participant in the Civil War | publisher = BiblioBazaar | location = City | year = 2007 | isbn = 1-4264-6170-4 }}
* {{cite book | last = Allsopp | first = Fred | title = Albert Pike a Biography | publisher = Kessinger Publishing | location = City | year = 1997 | isbn = 1-56459-134-4 }}
* {{cite book | last = Brown | first = Walter | title = A Life of Albert Pike | publisher = University of Arkansas Press | location = Fayetteville | year = 1997 | isbn = 1-55728-469-5 }}
* {{cite book | last = Cousin | first = John | title = Short Biographical Dictionary of English Literature | publisher = Kessinger Publishing, LLC | location = City | year = 2003 | isbn = 0-7661-4348-1 }}
* {{cite book |title = The Complete Idiot's Guide to Freemasonry |first = S. Brent |last = Morris |publisher = Alpha Books |year = 2006 |isbn = 1-59257-490-4 |url-access = registration |url = https://archive.org/details/completeidiotsgu00morr }}
* {{A Short Biographical Dictionary of English Literature}}
* {{Source-attribution| {{cite book|ref=harv|author=Bob Taylor's Magazine|title=Bob Taylor's Magazine|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=eOARAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA192|edition=Public domain|volume=11-12|year=1910|publisher=Taylor's Publishing Company}} }}
{{Div col end}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite book | last = Lafferty | first = R.A. | title = Okla Hannali | publisher = [[University of Oklahoma Press]] | location = Oklahoma | year = 1991 | isbn = 0-8061-2349-4 }}
* {{cite book |author=United Daughters of the Confederacy. Memorial Chapter No. 48 (Little Rock, Ark.) |date=n.d. |chapter=Chapter 2: Albert Pike |title=Historical Arkansas. Compliments of the Memorial chapter, U. D. C., Little Rock, Arkansas |url=https://archive.org/details/historicalarkans00unit |location=Little Rock |publisher=Democrat Printing and Lithographing Company |pages=[https://archive.org/details/historicalarkans00unit/page/5 5]–7 |lccn=20018497}}

==External links==
&lt;!--
  ===============================================================================
   WIKIPEDIA IS NOT A COLLECTION OF LINKS. Only a limited number of new links 
   should be added to this article. PLEASE DO NOT ADD external links to sites with
   information already in the article or in its sources.

   See [[Wikipedia:External links]] and [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for further details
  ===============================================================================
--&gt;
* {{Find a Grave|11051}}
* [https://freemasonry.network/famous-freemasons/reformers-of-freemasonry/albert-pike/ Albert Pike] at Freemasonry.network
* [http://albertpike.wordpress.com/albert-pike-lucifer Albert Pike and Lucifer] at Freemasonry and the World (albertpike.wordpress.com)
* [http://www.masonicinfo.com/pikesphilosophy.htm Albert Pike's Philosophy] at Masonicinfo.com
* [http://www.civilwarpoetry.org/confederate/songs/apdixie.html &quot;Everybody's Dixie&quot; by Albert Pike] at Civilwarpoetry.org
* {{Gutenberg author|id=Pike,+Albert|name=Albert Pike}}
* {{Internet Archive author|sname=Albert Pike}}
*{{worldcat id|id=lccn-n85373355}}
&lt;!-- EDITORS NOTE: Please follow the [[WP:EL]] guideline where possible and consider discussing on the talk page. Thank you. --&gt;

{{s-start}}
{{s-mil}}
{{s-bef|before={{Nowrap|Colonel S. H. Hempstead}}}}
{{s-ttl|title={{Nowrap|[[Adjutant general|Adjutant General]] of [[Arkansas]] [[Militia]]}}|years=1845–1846}}
{{s-aft|after={{Nowrap|Colonel [[Solon Borland]]}}}}
{{s-end}}

{{Subject bar|portal1=American Civil War|portal2=Biography|portal3=Journalism|portal4=Law|portal5=Literature|portal6=United States|commons=y|commons-search=Category:Albert Pike|q=y|q-search=Albert Pike|s=y|s-search=Author:Albert Pike|d=y|d-search=Q366639}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Pike, Albert}}
[[Category:1809 births]]
[[Category:1891 deaths]]
[[Category:19th-century American male writers]]
[[Category:19th-century American newspaper editors]]
[[Category:19th-century American non-fiction writers]]
[[Category:19th-century occultists]]
[[Category:Activists from Massachusetts]]
[[Category:American Freemasons]]
[[Category:American military personnel of the Mexican–American War]]
[[Category:American militia officers]]
[[Category:American Odd Fellows]]
[[Category:American political journalists]]
[[Category:Arkansas Know Nothings]]
[[Category:Arkansas lawyers]]
[[Category:Arkansas Whigs]]
[[Category:Burials at Oak Hill Cemetery]]
[[Category:Confederate States Army brigadier generals]]
[[Category:Confederate States diplomats]]
[[Category:Editors of Arkansas newspapers]]
[[Category:Lawyers from Boston]]
[[Category:Northern-born Confederates]]
[[Category:People of Arkansas in the American Civil War]]
[[Category:United States Army officers]]
[[Category:Writers from Boston]]</text>
      <sha1>8zj1bt2rlx58r2cxe8ugajb2fg73igd</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
