  <page>
    <title>Saint Titus</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2304</id>
    <revision>
      <id>934350047</id>
      <parentid>922169884</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-06T02:06:00Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>73.235.171.137</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Life */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox saint
|name=Titus
|birth_date=1st century [[AD]]
|death_date=96 or 107 [[AD]]
|feast_day=August 25 (Eastern Orthodox Liturgical Calendar)&lt;br /&gt;January 26 (General Roman Calendar)
|venerated_in=[[Catholic Church]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Eastern Orthodox Church]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Eastern Catholic Churches]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Lutheranism]]&lt;br /&gt; [[Anglican Communion]]
|image=Saint Titus (Kosovo, 14th c. Pech Patriarch., S. Nicholas church).jpg
|imagesize=
|caption=
|birth_place=
|death_place=[[Gortyn]], [[Crete]]
|titles=Bishop and Martyr
|beatified_date=
|beatified_place=
|beatified_by=
|canonized_date=[[Pre-congregation|Pre-Congregation]]
|canonized_place=
|canonized_by=
|attributes=
|patronage= [[Crete]]
|major_shrine=[[Heraklion]], [[Crete]]
|suppressed_date=
|issues=
|prayer=
|prayer_attrib=
}}

'''Titus''' ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|t|aɪ|t|ə|s}} {{respell|TY|təs}}; {{lang-grc-gre|Τίτος}}) was an early Christian missionary and church leader, a companion and disciple of [[Paul the Apostle]], mentioned in several of the [[Pauline epistles]] including the [[Epistle to Titus]]. He is believed to be a Gentile converted to Christianity by Paul and, according to tradition, he was consecrated as Bishop of the Island of [[Crete]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Smith, William 1975. Pp. 701&quot;&gt;Smith, William. ''Smith’s Bible Dictionary'' 11th printing, November 1975. New Jersey: Fleming H. Revel Company. pp. 701–02.&lt;/ref&gt;

Titus brought a fundraising letter from Paul to [[Corinth]], to collect for the poor in Jerusalem. Later, on Crete, Titus appointed [[presbyter]]&lt;nowiki/&gt;s (elders) in every city and remained there into his old age, dying in [[Gortyna]], near the city of Candia (modern [[Heraklion]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;Smith, William 1975. Pp. 701&quot;/&gt;

==Life==
Titus was a Greek, apparently from [[Antioch]],&lt;ref name=foley&gt;[http://www.americancatholic.org/Features/Saints/saint.aspx?id=1272 Foley O.F.M., Leonard. ''Saint of the Day, Lives, Lessons, and Feast'', (revised by Pat McCloskey O.F.M.), Franciscan Media]&lt;/ref&gt; who is said to have studied Greek philosophy and poetry in his early years.&lt;ref name=cna&gt;[http://www.catholicnewsagency.com/saint.php?n=128 &quot;Timothy and Titus&quot;, Catholic News Agency, January 26, 2015]&lt;/ref&gt; He seems to have been converted by Paul, whereupon he served as Paul's secretary and interpreter. In the year 49, Titus accompanied Paul to the council held at Jerusalem, on the subject of the [[Moses|Mosaic]] rites. &lt;ref name=butler&gt;[http://www.bartleby.com/210/1/041.html Butler, Alban. ''The Lives of the Saints'', Vol. I, (1866)]&lt;/ref&gt;

Towards the close of the year 56, Paul, as he himself departed from Asia, sent Titus from [[Ephesus]] to [[Ancient Corinth|Corinth]], with full commission to remedy the fallout precipitated by Timothy's delivery of 1 Corinthians&lt;ref&gt;{{Bibleverse|1 Corinthians|16:10–11|NIV}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Paul's &quot;Painful Visit&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{Bibleverse|2 Corinthians|2:1|NIV}}&lt;/ref&gt; particularly a significant personal offense and challenge to Paul's authority by one unnamed individual.&lt;ref&gt;{{Bibleverse|2 Corinthians|2:5–11|NIV}}&lt;/ref&gt; During this journey, Titus served as the courier for what is commonly known as the &quot;Severe Letter&quot;, a Pauline missive that has been lost but is referred to in 2 Corinthians.&lt;ref&gt;{{Bibleverse|2 Corinthians|7:8|NIV}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After success on this mission, Titus journeyed north and met Paul in [[Macedonia (ancient kingdom)|Macedonia]]. There the apostle, overjoyed by Titus' success,&lt;ref&gt;{{Bibleverse|2 Corinthians|7:6–15|NIV}}&lt;/ref&gt; wrote 2 Corinthians. Titus then returned to Corinth with a larger entourage, carrying 2 Corinthians with him. Paul joined Titus in Corinth later. From Corinth, Paul then sent Titus to organize the collections of alms for the Christians at Jerusalem. Titus was therefore a troubleshooter, peacemaker, administrator, and missionary.

Early church tradition holds that Paul, after his release from his first imprisonment in Rome, stopped at the island of Crete to preach. Due to the needs of other churches, requiring his presence elsewhere, he ordained his disciple Titus as bishop of that island,&lt;ref&gt;{{Bibleverse|Titus|1:5|NIV}}&lt;/ref&gt; and left him to finish the work he had started. Chrysostom says that this is an indication of the esteem St. Paul held for Titus.&lt;ref name=butler/&gt;

Paul summoned Titus from Crete to join him at Nicopolis in Epirus.&lt;ref&gt;{{Bibleverse|Titus|3:12|NIV}}&lt;/ref&gt; Later, Titus traveled to [[Early centers of Christianity#Salona|Dalmatia]].&lt;ref name=losservatore&gt;[http://www.ewtn.com/library/PAPALDOC/b16ChrstChrch26.HTM Pope Benedict XVI. &quot;Timothy and Titus&quot;, ''L'Osservatore Romano'', p. 11, December 27, 2006]&lt;/ref&gt; The [[New Testament]] does not record his death.

It has been argued that the name &quot;Titus&quot; in 2 Corinthians and Galatians is nothing more than an informal name used by Timothy, implied already by the fact that even though both are said to be long-term close companions of Paul, they never appear in common scenes.&lt;ref&gt;Fellows, Richard G. &quot;Was Titus Timothy?&quot; ''Journal for the Study of the New Testament'' '''81''' (2001):33–58.&lt;/ref&gt; The theory proposes that a number of passages—1 Cor. 4:17, 16.10; 2 Cor. 2:13, 7:6, 13–14, 12:18; and Acts 19.22—all refer to the same journey of a single individual, Titus-Timothy. [[2 Timothy]] seems to dispute this, by claiming that Titus has gone to Dalmatia ({{Bibleverse|2 Timothy|4:10|NIV}}). The fact that Paul made a point of circumcising Timothy ({{Bibleverse|Acts|16:3|NIV}}) but refused to circumcise Titus ({{Bibleverse||Galatians|2:3}}) would indicate that they are different men, although certain manuscripts of Galatians ({{Bibleverse||Galatians|2:4}}) have been taken (by [[Marius Victorinus]],&lt;ref&gt;Cooper, Stephen. ''Marius Victorinus' Commentary on Galatians''. Oxford University Press, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; for example) to indicate that Paul ''did'' circumcise Titus.

==Veneration==
The feast day of Titus was not included in the [[Tridentine Calendar]]. When added in 1854, it was assigned to 6 February.&lt;ref&gt;''Calendarium Romanum'' (Libreria Editrice Vaticana, 1969), p. 86&lt;/ref&gt; In 1969, the [[Catholic Church]] assigned the feast to 26 January so as to celebrate the two disciples of Paul, Titus and Timothy, the day after the feast of the [[Conversion of St. Paul]].&lt;ref&gt;''Calendarium Romanum'' (Libreria Editrice Vaticana, 1969), p. 116&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Evangelical Lutheran Church in America]] celebrates these two, together with [[Silas]], on the same date. The [[Orthodox Church]] commemorates him on 25 August and on 4 January.

His relics, now consisting of only his skull, are venerated in the Church of St. Titus, [[Heraklion]], Crete, to which it was returned in 1966&lt;ref name=&quot;The Orthodox Messenger, v. 8(7/8), July/Aug 1997&quot;&gt;[http://www.orthodoxchristian.info/pages/titus.htm The Orthodox Messenger, v. 8(7/8), July/Aug 1997]&lt;/ref&gt; after being removed to Venice during the Turkish occupation.

St. Titus is the patron saint of the [[United States Army Chaplain Corps]]. The Corps has established the Order of Titus Award, described by the Department of Defense:

{{Quote|text=Order of Titus award is the only award presented by the Chief of Chaplains to recognize outstanding performance of ministry by chaplains and chaplain assistants. The Order of Titus is awarded for meritorious contributions to the unique and highly visible Unit Ministry Team Observer Controller Program. The award recognizes the great importance of realistic, doctrinally guided combat ministry training in ensuring the delivery of prevailing religious support to the American Soldier.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title =Titus Award | url = https://www.army.mil/article/50256}} Retrieved 18 June 2017.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

{{Portal|Christianity}}
{{New Testament people}}
{{Catholic saints}}

{{authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Titus, Apostle}}
[[Category:Seventy disciples]]
[[Category:1st-century births]]
[[Category:107 deaths]]
[[Category:People in the Pauline epistles]]
[[Category:1st-century bishops]]
[[Category:Christian saints from the New Testament]]
[[Category:Saints of Roman Crete]]</text>
      <sha1>h65yr50oiq56q6i5tavinls4yqcaraq</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
