  <page>
    <title>Foreign relations of Chad</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5337</id>
    <revision>
      <id>940393877</id>
      <parentid>938652002</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-12T08:30:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>嘉傑</username>
        <id>34373489</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Africa */The title of former Libyan leader [[Muammar Gaddafi]] was &quot;[[Brotherly Leader and Guide of the Revolution|Brotherly Leader]]&quot;, not [[List of heads of state of Libya|President]].</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Politics of Chad}}
The '''foreign relations of Chad''' are significantly influenced by the desire for oil revenue and investment in [[Chad]]ian oil industry and support for [[Chadian President]] [[Idriss Déby]]. Chad is officially non-aligned but has close relations with [[France]], the former colonial power. Relations with neighbouring [[Libya]], and [[Sudan]] vary periodically. Lately, the Idris Déby regime has been waging an intermittent [[proxy war]] with Sudan. Aside from those two countries, Chad generally enjoys good relations with its neighbouring states.

==Africa==
Although relations with Libya improved with the presidency of [[Idriss Déby]], strains persist. Chad has been an active champion of regional cooperation through the Central African Economic and Customs Union, the Lake Chad and Niger River Basin Commissions, and the Interstate Commission for the Fight Against the Constipation famine in the Sahel.

Delimitation of international boundaries in the vicinity of [[Lake Chad]], the lack of which led to border incidents in the past, has been completed and awaits ratification by [[Cameroon]], [[Chad]], [[Niger]], and [[Nigeria]].

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin:auto;&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;width:15%;&quot;| Country
! style=&quot;width:12%;&quot;| Formal Relations Began
!Notes
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Algeria}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Algeria has an embassy in [[N'Djamena]].
* Chad has an embassy in [[Algiers]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Cameroon}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Cameroon has an embassy in N'Djamena.
* Chad has an embassy in [[Yaoundé]] and a consulate in [[Garoua]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Central African Republic}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Central African Republic has an embassy in N'Djamena.
* Chad has an embassy in [[Bangui]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Côte d'Ivoire}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Chad has an embassy in [[Abidjan]].
* Côte d'Ivoire has an embassy in N'Djamena.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Democratic Republic of Congo}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Chad has an embassy in [[Kinshasa]].
* DR Congo has an embassy in N'Djamena and a consulate in [[Moundou]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Egypt}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Chad has an embassy in [[Cairo]].
* Egypt has an embassy in N'Djamena.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Equatorial Guinea}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Chad has an embassy in [[Malabo]].
* Equatorial Guinea has an embassy in N'Djamena.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Libya}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||See [[Chad-Libya relations]]

Chadian-Libyan relations were ameliorated when Libyan-supported [[Idriss Déby]] unseated Habré on December 2. Gaddafi was the first head of state to recognize the new regime, and he also signed treaties of friendship and cooperation on various levels; but regarding the Aouzou Strip Déby followed his predecessor, declaring that if necessary he would fight to keep the strip out of Libya's hands.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=Chad The Devil Behind the Scenes| newspaper =[[Time (magazine)|Time]]|year= |date=1990-12-17|url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,971950,00.html?iid=chix-sphere|postscript=&lt;!--none--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;M. Azevedo, p. 150&lt;/ref&gt;

The Aouzou dispute was concluded for good on February 3, 1994, when the judges of the ICJ by a majority of 16 to 1 decided that the Aouzou Strip belonged to Chad. The court's judgement was implemented without delay, the two parties signing as early as April 4 an agreement concerning the practical modalities for the implementation of the judgement. Monitored by international observers, the withdrawal of Libyan troops from the Strip began on April 15 and was completed by May 10. The formal and final transfer of the Strip from Libya to Chad took place on May 30, when the sides signed a joint declaration stating that the Libyan withdrawal had been effected.&lt;ref&gt;G. Simons, p. 78&lt;/ref&gt;

* Chad has an embassy in [[Tripoli]].
* Libya has an embassy in N'Djamena.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Morocco}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Chad has an embassy in [[Rabat]].
* Morocco has an embassy in N'Djamena.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Niger}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Chad has an embassy in [[Niamey]].
* Niger has an embassy in N'Djamena.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Nigeria}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;|| See [[Chad-Nigeria relations]]

Nigeria's 1983 economic austerity campaign produced strains with neighboring states, including Chad. Nigeria expelled several hundred thousand foreign workers, mostly from its oil industry, which faced drastic cuts as a result of declining world oil prices. At least 30,000 of those expelled were Chadians. Despite these strains, however, Nigerians had assisted in the halting process of achieving stability in Chad, and both nations reaffirmed their intention to maintain close ties.

* Chad has an embassy in [[Abuja]] and a consulate in [[Maiduguri]]..
* Nigeria has an embassy in N'Djamena.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|South Africa}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Chad has an embassy in [[Pretoria]].
* South Africa has an embassy in N'Djamena.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Sudan}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;|| See [[Chad-Sudan relations]]
On December 24, 2005, Chad declared itself as in a &quot;state of belligerance&quot; with neighboring Sudan. The conflict in the border region of Darfur has become an increasingly bi-national affair as increasing numbers of Sudanese flee to refugee camps in Chad, and Sudanese government troops and militias cross the borders to strike at both these camps and specific ethnic groups. Although the [[Government of Chad]] and the [[Government of Sudan]] signed the [[Tripoli Agreement]] on February 8, 2006, officially ending hostilities, fighting continues. On 11 August 2006, Chad and Sudan resumed relations at the behest of [[Brotherly Leader and Guide of the Revolution|Libyan leader]] [[Muammar Gaddafi]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/4775111.stm | work=BBC News | title=Chad and Sudan resume relations | date=August 9, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Chad broke diplomatic relations with [[Sudan]] at least twice in 2006 because it believed the [[Sudanese government]] was supporting [[Janjaweed]] and [[UFDC]] rebels financially and with arms. Two accords were signed, the [[Tripoli Accord]], which was signed on February 8 and failed to end the fighting, and the more recently signed N'Djamena Agreement. On May 11, 2008 Sudan announced it was cutting diplomatic relations with Chad, claiming that it was helping rebels in [[Darfur]] to attack the Sudanese capital [[Khartoum]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/africa/7394422.stm|title=BBC NEWS - Africa - Sudan cuts Chad ties over attack|work=bbc.co.uk}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* Chad has an embassy in [[Khartoum]].
* Sudan has an embassy in N'Djamena.
|}

==Americas==
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin:auto;&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;width:15%;&quot;| Country
! style=&quot;width:12%;&quot;| Formal Relations Began
!Notes
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Argentina}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Argentina is accredited to Chad from its embassy in Abuja, Nigeria.
* Chad does not have an accreditation to Argentina. 
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Brazil}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;1996||
* Brazil is accredited to Chad from its embassy in [[Yaoundé]], [[Cameroon]].&lt;ref name=Brazil&gt;[http://www.itamaraty.gov.br/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=4920&amp;Itemid=478&amp;cod_pais=TCD&amp;tipo=ficha_pais&amp;lang=pt-BR Relations between Brazil and Chad (in Portuguese)]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Chad does not have an accreditation to Brazil.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Canada}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;1962||
* Canada is accredited to Chad from its embassy in [[Khartoum]], [[Sudan]] and has an honorary consulate in [[N'Djamena]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.canadainternational.gc.ca/sudan-soudan/bilateral_relations_bilaterales/chad-tchad.aspx?lang=eng Embassy of Canada in Sudan]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Chad has an embassy in [[Ottawa]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.chadembassy.ca Embassy of Chad in Canada]&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Cuba}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Chad is accredited to Cuba from its embassy in Washington, D.C., United States.
* Cuba is accredited to Chad from its embassy in Niamey, Niger.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.minrex.gob.cu/es/directorio-diplomatico/C?tid_i18n=450 Cuban Ministry of Foreign Affairs]&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Mexico}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;25 February 1976||See [[Chad–Mexico relations]]
Chad and Mexico established diplomatic relations on 25 February 1976.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.senado.gob.mx/sgsp/gaceta/63/1/2016-04-21-1/assets/documentos/Dict_Rel_Ext_Emb_Egipto.pdf Mexico-Chad relations (in Spanish)]&lt;/ref&gt; In May 2002, Chadian Prime Minister [[Nagoum Yamassoum]] paid a visit to the Mexican city of [[Monterrey]] to attend the [[Monterrey Consensus]] conference.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.un.org/ffd/statements/templist.htm Summit-level participation - Monterrey Consensus]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Chad is accredited to Mexico from its embassy in Washington, D.C., United States.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.chadembassy.us Embassy of Chad in the United States]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Mexico is accredited to Chad from its embassy in [[Cairo]], [[Egypt]].&lt;ref&gt;[https://embamex.sre.gob.mx/egipto/index.php/es/ Embassy of Mexico in Egypt]&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|United States}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;|| See [[Chad–United States relations]]
[[File:Embassy of Chad (Washington, D.C.).JPG|thumb|[[Embassy of Chad in Washington, D.C.]]]]
The US embassy in N'Djamena, established at Chadian independence in 1960, was closed from the onset of the heavy fighting in the city in 1980 until the withdrawal of the [[Libya]]n forces at the end of 1981. It was reopened in January 1982. The [[U.S. Agency for International Development]] (USAID) and the [[U.S. Information Service]] (USIS) offices resumed activities in Chad in September 1983. The United States Department of State issued a travel advisory to U.S. citizens in 2009, recommending that citizens not affiliated with humanitarian efforts avoid all travel to eastern Chad and the Chad/[[Central African Republic]] border area due to insecurity caused by banditry, recent clashes between Chadian government and rebel forces, and political tension between Chad and [[Sudan]].&lt;ref name=&quot;USStateWarning&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = https://travel.state.gov/travel/cis_pa_tw/tw/tw_2876.html | title = Travel Warning - Chad | publisher = U.S. Department of State Bureau of Consular Affairs | date = June 2, 2009 | accessdate = August 26, 2009 | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20090827074331/http://travel.state.gov/travel/cis_pa_tw/tw/tw_2876.html | archive-date = August 27, 2009 | url-status = dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; President [[Donald Trump]] issued a proclamation on September 24, 2017, suspending the entry of Chadian nationals to the United States. The proclamation claims that the government of Chad &quot;does not adequately share public-safety and terrorism-related information...&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.whitehouse.gov/the-press-office/2017/09/24/enhancing-vetting-capabilities-and-processes-detecting-attempted-entry|title=Presidential Proclamation Enhancing Vetting Capabilities and Processes for Detecting Attempted Entry Into the United States by Terrorists or Other Public-Safety Threats|date=2017-09-24|work=whitehouse.gov|access-date=2017-09-25|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; On April 10, 2018, the US Government lifted travel restrictions on Chad.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.federalregister.gov/documents/2018/04/13/2018-07864/maintaining-enhanced-vetting-capabilities-and-processes-for-detecting-attempted-entry-into-the|title=Maintaining Enhanced Vetting Capabilities and Processes for Detecting Attempted Entry Into the United States by Terrorists or Other Public-Safety Threats|date=2018-04-13|work=Federal Register|access-date=2018-08-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.whitehouse.gov/briefings-statements/statement-press-secretary-regarding-presidential-proclamation-lift-entry-restrictions-nationals-republic-chad/|title=Statement by the Press Secretary Regarding the Presidential Proclamation to Lift Entry Restrictions for Nationals of the Republic of Chad|work=The White House|access-date=2018-08-12|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;chad&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://in.reuters.com/article/usa-chad-security/u-s-lifts-travel-ban-on-chad-citizens-white-house-idINKBN1HI001|title=U.S. lifts travel ban on Chad citizens - White House|last=Editorial|first=Reuters|work=IN|access-date=2018-08-12|language=en-IN}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Chad has an embassy in [[Washington, DC]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chadembassy.us|title=www.chadembassy.info|work=www.chadembassy.info}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* United States has an embassy in N'djamena.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ndjamena.usembassy.gov|title=Home - Embassy of the United States Ndjamena, Chad|work=usembassy.gov|access-date=2019-12-18|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141129114736/http://ndjamena.usembassy.gov/|archive-date=2014-11-29|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Venezuela}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Chad is accredited to Venezuela from its embassy in Washington, D.C, United States.
* Venezuela does not have an accreditation to Chad.
|}

==Asia==
Despite centuries-old cultural ties to the [[Arab World]], the Chadian Government maintained few significant ties to Arab states in North Africa or Southwest Asia in the 1980s. Chad has not recognised the State of [[Israel]] since former [[Chadian President]] [[François (Ngarta) Tombalbaye]] broke off relations in September 1972.  President Habré hoped to pursue closer relations with Arab states as a potential opportunity to break out of his Chad's post-imperial dependence on France, and to assert Chad's unwillingness to serve as an arena for superpower rivalries. In addition, as a northern Christian, Habré represented a constituency that favored co-operation and solidarity with Arabs, both African, and Asian. For these reasons, he was expected to seize opportunities during the 1990s to pursue closer ties with the Arab World. In 1988, Chad recognized the [[State of Palestine]], which maintains a mission in N'Djamena.

During the 1980s, Arab opinion on the Chadian-Libyan conflict over the Aozou Strip was divided. Several Arab states supported Libyan territorial claims to the Strip, among the most outspoken of which was Algeria, which provided training for anti-Habré forces, although most recruits for its training programs were from Nigeria or Cameroon, recruited and flown to Algeria by Libya. Lebanon's Progressive Socialist Party also sent troops to support Qadhafi's efforts against Chad in 1987. In contrast, numerous other Arab states opposed the Libyan actions, and expressed their desire to see the dispute over the Aozou Strip settled peacefully. By the end of 1987, Algiers and N'Djamena were negotiating to improve relations.

In  November 2018, President Deby visited Israel and announced his intention to restore diplomatic relations.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.timesofisrael.com/meeting-israeli-leaders-chad-president-says-he-wants-to-restore-diplomatic-ties/ Meeting Israeli leaders, Chad president says he wants to restore diplomatic ties]&lt;/ref&gt; Chad and Israel re-established diplomatic relations in January 2019.&lt;ref name=Chad-Israel/&gt;
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin:auto;&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;width:15%;&quot;| Country
! style=&quot;width:12%;&quot;| Formal Relations Began
!Notes
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Armenia}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;26 December 2006||

Both countries established diplomatic relations on 26 December 2006.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|China}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;2006||See [[Chad–China relations]]

* Chad has an embassy in [[Beijing]].
* China has an embassy in N'Djamena.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|India}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||See [[Chad–India relations]]

* Chad has an embassy in [[New Delhi]].&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.alwihdainfo.com/Tchad-decret-de-nomination-d-un-ambassadeur-en-Inde_a76299.html Tchad : décret de nomination d'un ambassadeur en Inde (in French)]&lt;/ref&gt;
* India is accredited to Chad from its high commission in Abuja, Nigeria and maintains an honorary consulate in N'Djamena.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Israel}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;January 2019||See [[Chad–Israel relations]]

In November 2018, Chadian President [[Idriss Déby]] paid a visit to Israel.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.jpost.com/Israel-News/President-of-Chad-makes-unannounced-historic-visit-572804 President of Chad makes Unannounced Historic Visit]&lt;/ref&gt; In January 2019 Israeli Prime Minister [[Benjamin Netanyahu]] paid a visit to Chad. During the visit, both nations re-established diplomatic relations since relations were cut in 1972.&lt;ref name=Chad-Israel&gt;[https://www.bbc.com/news/world-africa-46938869 Israel's PM Netanyahu signs deals with Chad's President Deby]&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Qatar}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Chad has an embassy in [[Doha]].
* Qatar has an embassy in N'Djamena.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Saudi Arabia}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Chad has an embassy in [[Riyadh]] and a consulate in [[Jeddah]].
* Saudi Arabia has an embassy in N'Djamena.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|South Korea}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;6 August 1961||

Establishment of diplomatic relations between [[South Korea]] and Chad was on 6 August 1961.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Taiwan}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||See [[Chad–Taiwan relations]]

Chad and [[Taiwan]] had relations from 1962 to 1972 when Chad first switched diplomatic recognition to the People's Republic of China. Chad then reestablished bilateral ties with Taiwan from 1997 to 2006. Since August 2006, Chad has granted diplomatic recognition to China.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Turkey}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Chad has an embassy in [[Ankara]].
* Turkey has an embassy in N'Djamena.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|United Arab Emirates}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Chad has an embassy in [[Abu Dhabi]] and a consulate-general in [[Dubai]].
* UAE has an embassy in N'Djamena.
|}

==Europe==
Chad is officially non-aligned but has close relations with [[France]], the former colonial power, which has about 1,200 troops stationed in the capital [[N'Djamena]]. It receives economic aid from countries of the European Community, the [[United States]], and various international organizations. [[Libya]] supplies aid and has an [[ambassador]] resident in [[N'Djamena]]. Traditionally strong ties with the [[Western world|Western]] community have weakened over the past two years due to a dispute between the [[Government of Chad]] and the [[World Bank]] over how the profits from Chad's [[petroleum]] reserves are allocated. Although oil output to the West has resumed and the dispute has officially been resolved, resentment towards what the Déby administration considered foreign meddling lingers.

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin:auto;&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;width:15%;&quot;| Country
! style=&quot;width:12%;&quot;| Formal Relations Began
!Notes
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Belgium}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Belgium is accredited to Chad from its embassy in Yaoundé, Cameroon and maintains an honorary consulate in N'Djamena.
* Chad has an embassy in [[Brussels]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|France}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;11 August 1960||See [[Chad–France relations]]

France was Chad's most important [[foreign aid|foreign donor]] and patron for the first three decades following [[Decolonization in Chad#French federation versus full independence|independence]] in 1960. At the end of the 1980s, economic ties were still strong, and France provided development assistance in the form of loans and grants. It was no longer Chad's leading customer for [[Agriculture in Chad|agricultural exports]], but it continued to provide substantial military support.

Chad remained a member of the [[African Financial Community]] (Communauté Financière Africaine—CFA), which linked the value of its currency, the [[CFA franc]], to the [[French franc]]. French private and government investors owned a substantial portion of Chad's industrial and financial institutions, and the French treasury backed the [[Bank of Central African States]] (Banque des Etats de l'Afrique Centrale—BEAC), which served as the central bank for Chad and six other member nations. Chad's dependence on France declined slightly during [[Habré]]'s tenure as president, in part because other foreign donors and investors returned as the war subsided and also because increased rainfall since 1985 improved food production. French official attitudes toward Chad had changed from the 1970s policies under the leadership of [[Giscard d'Estaing]] to those of the [[Mitterrand]] era of the 1980s. Economic, political, and strategic goals, which had emphasized maintaining French influence in Africa, exploiting Chad's natural resources, and bolstering [[francophone Africa]]'s status as a bulwark against the spread of [[Soviet Union|Soviet]] influence, had been replaced by nominally [[anticolonialist]] attitudes. The [[1981 French legislative election|election]] in France of the [[Socialist Party (France)|Socialist]] government in 1981 had coincided with [[History of Chad#The Habr.C3.A9 era .281982.E2.80.9390.29|conditions of near-anarchy in Chad]], leading France's Socialist Party to reaffirm its ideological stance against high-profile intervention in Africa. Hoping to avoid a confrontation with [[Libya]], another important client state in the region, President Mitterrand limited French military involvement to a defense of the region surrounding [[N'Djamena]] in 1983 and 1984. Then, gradually increasing its commitment to reinforce Habré's presidency, France once again increased its military activity in Chad.
* Chad has an embassy in [[Paris]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://ambatchad-paris.org Embassy of Chad in Paris (in French)]&lt;/ref&gt;
* France has an embassy in [[N'djamena]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ambafrance-td.org|title=Ambassade de France au Tchad|work=ambafrance-td.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Germany}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Chad has an embassy in [[Berlin]].
* Germany has an embassy in N'Djamena.
|-
|{{flag|Kosovo}}
|27 May 2018
|Both countries established diplomatic relations on 27 May 2018.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://twitter.com/pacollibehgjet/status/1000673699681521664|title=Glad that #Kosovo has established diplomatic relations with #Liberia and #Chad through the non-resident accreditation of  Amb. @ambRamadanGashi. #Kosovo is grateful to Liberia &amp; #Chad for their support to  independence and membership in IO’s.|last=Pacolli|first=Behgjet|date=2018-05-27|website=@pacollibehgjet|language=en|access-date=2020-01-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Relations between Kosovo and Chad are excellent.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Poland}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Chad is accredited to Poland from its embassy in Moscow, Russia.
* Poland is accredited to Chad from its embassy in Tunis, Tunisia.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Romania}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;|| See [[Chad–Romania relations]]

Chad–Romania relations were established on 15 July 1969. However, neither country has an embassy in the other's capital, and although an agreement on trade was signed in 1969, followed by an agreement on economic and technical cooperation in 1971, {{Asof|2007|lc=on}}, the volume of bilateral trade remained insignificant.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|url=http://www.mae.ro/index.php?unde=doc&amp;id=5530|publisher=Minister of Foreign Affairs|publication-place=Romania|date=May 2008|accessdate=2009-03-26|title=Republica CIAD|postscript=&lt;!--none--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In November 2007, Romania announced that they would deploy 120 troops to Chad and the [[Central African Republic]] in connection with [[United Nations Mission in the Central African Republic and Chad|a European Union peacekeeping mission]] there.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |title=Romanian prime minister approves mission to Chad |date=2008-01-30 |accessdate=2009-03-26 |url=http://www.eubusiness.com/news-eu/1201722422.02/ |agency=AFP |periodical=EUBusiness.com |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080219174855/http://www.eubusiness.com/news-eu/1201722422.02/ |archivedate=February 19, 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Romania continued to condemn violence in Chad and blamed it on rebel groups.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC&quot;&gt;{{citation|title=Romanian Foreign Ministry concerned about developments in Chad|url=http://nl.newsbank.com/nl-search/we/Archives?p_product=NewsLibrary&amp;p_multi=BBAB&amp;d_place=BBAB&amp;p_theme=newslibrary2&amp;p_action=search&amp;p_maxdocs=200&amp;p_topdoc=1&amp;p_text_direct-0=11EA69384BEB0298&amp;p_field_direct-0=document_id&amp;p_perpage=10&amp;p_sort=YMD_date:D&amp;s_trackval=GooglePM|date=2008-02-05|accessdate=2009-03-26|periodical=BBC News|postscript=&lt;!--none--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, by mid-2008, Romanian defence minister [[Teodor Meleşcanu]] indicated that his country would not send further troops to the mission in Chad, stating that they had reached their limits and did not want involvement in a war theatre.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=Romania not sending troops to 2009 EU Chad mission|periodical=BBC News|date=2008-07-01|accessdate=2009-03-26|url=http://nl.newsbank.com/nl-search/we/Archives?p_product=NewsLibrary&amp;p_multi=BBAB&amp;d_place=BBAB&amp;p_theme=newslibrary2&amp;p_action=search&amp;p_maxdocs=200&amp;p_topdoc=1&amp;p_text_direct-0=121A8477A1DEFD70&amp;p_field_direct-0=document_id&amp;p_perpage=10&amp;p_sort=YMD_date:D&amp;s_trackval=GooglePM|postscript=&lt;!--none--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Russia}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Chad has an embassy in [[Moscow]].
* Russia has an embassy in N'Djamena.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Spain}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Chad is accredited to Spain from its embassy in Paris, France.
* Spain is accredited to Chad from its embassy in Yaoundé, Cameroon.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Switzerland}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Chad has an embassy in [[Geneva]] accredited to Switzerland and the [[United Nations]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ambassade-mission-tchad.ch Chadian Embassy and Permanent Mission in Geneva]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Switzerland has a cooperation office in N'Djamena.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.eda.admin.ch/tchad Swiss Cooperation Office in N'Djamena]&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|United Kingdom}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Chad is accredited to the United Kingdom from its embassy in Brussels, Belgium.
* United Kingdom has an embassy in N'Djamena.
|}

==Oceania==
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin:auto;&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;width:15%;&quot;| Country
! style=&quot;width:12%;&quot;| Formal Relations Began
!Notes
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Australia}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Australia is accredited to Chad from its embassy in Paris, France.
* Chad does not have an accreditation to Australia.
|}

==Membership of international organizations==
Chad belongs to the following international organizations:

{{col-begin}}
{{col-2}}
* [[United Nations]] and some of its specialized and related agencies
* [[Organization for African Unity]]
* [[Central African Customs and Economic Union]] (UDEAC)
* [[African Financial Community]] (Franc Zone)
* Agency for the Francophone Community
* [[African, Caribbean and Pacific Group of States]]
* [[African Development Bank]]
* Central African States Development Bank
* Economic and Monetary Union of Central African (CEMAC)
* [[Economic Commission for Africa]]; [[Group of 77|G-77]]
* [[International Civil Aviation Organization]]
* [[International Red Cross and Red Crescent Movement]]
* [[International Development Association]]
* [[Islamic Development Bank]]
* [[International Fund for Agricultural Development]]
* [[International Finance Corporation]]
{{col-2}}
* International Federation of the Red Cross and Red Crescent Societies
* [[International Labour Organization]]
* [[International Monetary Fund]]
* [[Intelsat]]
* [[Interpol (organization)|Interpol]]
* [[International Olympic Committee]]
* [[International Telecommunication Union]]
* [[International Trade Union Confederation]]
* [[Non-Aligned Movement|NAM]]
* [[Organisation of Islamic Cooperation]]
* [[Organisation for the Prohibition of Chemical Weapons]]
* [[Universal Postal Union]]
* [[World Confederation of Labour]]
* [[World Intellectual Property Organization]];
* [[World Meteorological Organization]];
* [[World Tourism Organization]]
* [[World Trade Organization]]
{{col-end}}

==See also==
* [[List of diplomatic missions in Chad]]
* [[List of diplomatic missions of Chad]]

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}
{{loc}}

{{Navboxes
|title = International membership
|list  =
{{African Union}}
{{Community of Sahel–Saharan States}}
{{La Francophonie|state=collapsed}}
{{Organisation of Islamic Cooperation|state=collapsed}}
}}
{{Chadian-Sudanese conflict}}
{{Foreign relations of Chad}}
{{Africa in topic|Foreign relations of}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Foreign Relations Of Chad}}
[[Category:Foreign relations of Chad| ]]</text>
      <sha1>bdjmqx67t6z1qzplap7t9t01cuevyco</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
