  <page>
    <title>Inflation (cosmology)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5382</id>
    <revision>
      <id>940968214</id>
      <parentid>939692932</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-15T20:02:57Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Rjwilmsi</username>
        <id>203434</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* Criticisms */Journal cites:, added 1 PMID</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect2|Inflation model|Inflation theory|a general rise in the price level|Inflation|other uses|Inflation (disambiguation)}}
{{pp-semi-indef}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2019}} 
{{Cosmology|early}}
In [[physical cosmology]], '''cosmic inflation''', '''cosmological inflation''', or just '''inflation''', is a theory of exponential [[expansion of the universe|expansion of space]] in the early [[universe]]. The [[inflationary epoch]] lasted from 10&lt;sup&gt;−36&lt;/sup&gt; seconds after the conjectured [[Big Bang]] singularity to some time between 10&lt;sup&gt;−33&lt;/sup&gt; and 10&lt;sup&gt;−32&lt;/sup&gt; seconds after the singularity. Following the inflationary period, the universe continued to expand, but the expansion was no longer accelerating.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite serial |title=[[How the Universe Works#Season 3|How The Universe Works 3]] |episode=First Second of the Big Bang |network=Discovery Science |year=2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Inflation theory was developed in the late 1970s and early 80s, with notable contributions by several [[theoretical physics|theoretical physicists]], including [[Alexei Starobinsky]]  at [[Landau Institute for Theoretical Physics]], [[Alan Guth]] at [[Cornell University]], and [[Andrei Linde]] at [[Lebedev Physical Institute]]. Alexei Starobinsky, Alan Guth, and Andrei Linde won the 2014 [[Kavli Prize]] &quot;for pioneering the theory of cosmic inflation.&quot;&lt;ref name=KavliPrize&gt;{{cite web |title=2014 Astrophysics Citation |url=http://www.kavlifoundation.org/2014-astrophysics-citation |website=The Kavli Foundation |publisher=The Kavli Foundation |accessdate=27 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was developed further in the early 1980s. It explains the origin of the [[Observable universe#Large-scale structure|large-scale structure of the cosmos]]. [[Quantum fluctuation]]s in the microscopic inflationary region, magnified to cosmic size, become the seeds for the growth of structure in the Universe (see [[galaxy formation and evolution]] and [[structure formation]]).&lt;ref&gt;Tyson, Neil deGrasse and Donald Goldsmith (2004), ''Origins: Fourteen Billion Years of Cosmic Evolution'', W. W. Norton &amp; Co., pp. 84–5.&lt;/ref&gt; Many physicists also believe that inflation explains why the universe appears to be the same in all directions ([[isotropic]]), why the [[cosmic microwave background]] [[radiation]] is distributed evenly, why the universe is [[flat universe|flat]], and why no [[magnetic monopole]]s have been observed.

The detailed [[particle physics]] mechanism responsible for inflation is unknown. The basic inflationary paradigm is accepted by most physicists, as a number of inflation model predictions have been confirmed by observation;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite arxiv |author=Tsujikawa, Shinji |title=Introductory review of cosmic inflation |date=28 April 2003 |eprint=hep-ph/0304257 |quote=In fact temperature anisotropies observed by the COBE satellite in 1992 exhibit nearly scale-invariant spectra as predicted by the inflationary paradigm. Recent observations of WMAP also show strong evidence for inflation.}}&lt;/ref&gt; however, a substantial minority of scientists dissent from this position.&lt;ref name=Steinhardt2011/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Earman-Mosterín&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hložek&quot;/&gt; The hypothetical [[field (physics)|field]] thought to be responsible for inflation is called the [[inflaton]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Guth, Alan H. |authorlink=Alan Guth |title=The Inflationary Universe: The Quest for a New Theory of Cosmic Origins |date=1997 |publisher=Basic Books |pages=233–234 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=7toILlSQtI0C&amp;pg=PA233 |isbn=978-0201328400}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2002, three of the original architects of the theory were recognized for their major contributions; physicists [[Alan Guth]] of [[Massachusetts Institute of Technology|M.I.T.]], [[Andrei Linde]] of [[Stanford]], and [[Paul Steinhardt]] of [[Princeton University|Princeton]] shared the prestigious [[Dirac Prize]] &quot;for development of the concept of inflation in cosmology&quot;.&lt;ref name= &quot;Dirac Prize&quot; &gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.ictp.it/about-ictp/prizes-awards/the-dirac-medal/the-medallists.aspx |title=The Medallists: A list of past Dirac Medallists |work=ictp.it}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2012, Alan Guth and Andrei Linde were awarded the [[Breakthrough Prize in Fundamental Physics]] for their invention and development of inflationary cosmology.&lt;ref name= &quot;Breakthrough Prize&quot; &gt;{{cite web |url=https://breakthroughprize.org/Laureates/1/P1/Y2012 |title=Laureates of the Breakthrough Prize in Fundamental Physics in 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Overview ==
{{main|Expansion of the universe|Inflaton}}
Around 1930, [[Edwin Hubble]] discovered that light from remote galaxies was [[redshift]]ed; the more remote, the more shifted. This was quickly interpreted as meaning galaxies were receding from Earth. If Earth is not in some special, privileged, central position in the universe, then it would mean all galaxies are moving apart, and the further away, the faster they are moving away. It is now understood that [[expansion of the universe|the universe is expanding]], carrying the galaxies with it, and causing this observation. Many other observations agree, and also lead to the same conclusion. However, for many years it was not clear why or how the universe might be expanding, or what it might signify.

Based on a huge amount of experimental observation and theoretical work, it is now believed that the reason for the observation is that ''space itself is expanding'', and that it expanded very rapidly within the first fraction of a second after the [[Big Bang]]. This kind of expansion is known as a ''&quot;metric&quot;'' expansion. In the terminology of mathematics and physics, a &quot;[[Metric (mathematics)|metric]]&quot; is a measure of distance that satisfies a specific list of properties, and the term implies that ''the sense of distance within the universe is itself changing'', although at this time it is far too small an effect to see on less than an intergalactic scale.

The modern explanation for the metric expansion of space was proposed by physicist [[Alan Guth]] in 1979, while investigating the problem of why no [[magnetic monopoles]] are seen today. He found that if the universe contained a [[field (physics)|field]] in a positive-energy [[false vacuum]] state, then according to [[general relativity]] it would generate an exponential expansion of space. It was very quickly realized that such an expansion would resolve many other long-standing problems. These problems arise from the observation that to look like it does ''today'', the Universe would have to have started from very [[fine tuned universe|finely tuned]], or &quot;special&quot; initial conditions at the Big Bang. Inflation theory largely resolves these problems as well, thus making a universe like ours much more likely in the context of Big Bang theory.

No [[field (physics)|physical field]] has yet been discovered that is responsible for this inflation. However such a field would be [[scalar field#definition|scalar]] and the first relativistic scalar field proven to exist, the [[Higgs field]], was only discovered in 2012–2013 and is still being researched. So it is not seen as problematic that a field responsible for cosmic inflation and the metric expansion of space has not yet been discovered. The proposed field and its [[quantum|quanta]] (the [[subatomic particle]]s related to it) have been named the [[inflaton]]. If this field did not exist, scientists would have to propose a different explanation for all the observations that strongly suggest a metric expansion of space has occurred, and is still occurring (much more slowly) today.

== Theory ==
{{Main|Expansion of the universe}}

An expanding universe generally has a [[Cosmological horizon#Cosmological horizon|cosmological horizon]], which, by analogy with the more familiar [[horizon]] caused by the curvature of [[Earth]]'s surface, marks the boundary of the part of the Universe that an observer can see. Light (or other radiation) emitted by objects beyond the cosmological horizon in an [[accelerating expansion of the universe|accelerating universe]] never reaches the observer, because the space in between the observer and the object is expanding too rapidly.

[[File:History of the Universe.svg |thumb |left |350px |History of the [[Universe]] – [[gravitational wave]]s are hypothesized to arise from cosmic inflation, a [[Faster-than-light#Universal expansion|faster-than-light]] expansion just after the [[Big Bang]] (17 March 2014).&lt;ref name=&quot;BICEP2-2014&quot;&gt;{{cite web |author=Staff |title=BICEP2 2014 Results Release |url=http://bicepkeck.org |date=17 March 2014 |work=[[National Science Foundation]] |accessdate=18 March 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NASA-20140317&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last=Clavin |first=Whitney |title=NASA Technology Views Birth of the Universe |url=http://www.jpl.nasa.gov/news/news.php?release=2014-082 |date=17 March 2014 |work=[[NASA]] |accessdate=17 March 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT-20140317&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Overbye |first=Dennis |authorlink=Dennis Overbye |title=Space Ripples Reveal Big Bang's Smoking Gun |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2014/03/18/science/space/detection-of-waves-in-space-buttresses-landmark-theory-of-big-bang.html |date=17 March 2014 |work=[[The New York Times]]|accessdate=17 March 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt;]]

The [[observable universe]] is one ''causal patch'' of a much larger unobservable universe; other parts of the Universe cannot communicate with Earth yet. These parts of the Universe are outside our current cosmological horizon. In the standard hot big bang model, without inflation, the cosmological horizon moves out, bringing new regions into view.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.ca/books?id=E22mj8ImiKwC&amp;pg=PA65|last=Saul|first=Ernest|publisher=Dorrance Publishing Co.|isbn=978-1434969057|title=The Coded Universe: The Path to Eternity|page=65|year=2013|accessdate=2019-07-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; Yet as a local observer sees such a region for the first time, it looks no different from any other region of space the local observer has already seen: its background radiation is at nearly the same temperature as the background radiation of other regions, and its space-time curvature is evolving lock-step with the others. This presents a mystery: how did these new regions know what temperature and curvature they were supposed to have? They couldn't have learned it by getting signals, because they were not previously in communication with our past [[light cone]].&lt;ref name=&quot;tiny&quot;&gt;[https://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=102715275 Using Tiny Particles To Answer Giant Questions]. Science Friday, 3 April 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;See also [[Faster than light#Universal expansion]].&lt;/ref&gt;

Inflation answers this question by postulating that all the regions come from an earlier era with a big vacuum energy, or [[cosmological constant]]. A space with a cosmological constant is qualitatively different: instead of moving outward, the cosmological horizon stays put. For any one observer, the distance to the [[Observable universe#Cosmological horizon|cosmological horizon]] is constant. With exponentially expanding space, two nearby observers are separated very quickly; so much so, that the distance between them quickly exceeds the limits of communications. The spatial slices are expanding very fast to cover huge volumes. Things are constantly moving beyond the cosmological horizon, which is a fixed distance away, and everything becomes homogeneous.

As the inflationary field slowly relaxes to the vacuum, the cosmological constant goes to zero and space begins to expand normally. The new regions that come into view during the normal expansion phase are exactly the same regions that were pushed out of the horizon during inflation, and so they are at nearly the same temperature and curvature, because they come from the same originally small patch of space.

The theory of inflation thus explains why the temperatures and curvatures of different regions are so nearly equal. It also predicts that the total curvature of a space-slice at constant global time is zero. This prediction implies that the total ordinary matter, [[dark matter]] and residual [[vacuum energy]] in the Universe have to add up to the [[Critical density (cosmology)|critical density]], and the evidence supports this. More strikingly, inflation allows physicists to calculate the minute differences in temperature of different regions from quantum fluctuations during the inflationary era, and many of these quantitative predictions have been confirmed.&lt;ref name=&quot;wmap2&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Spergel |first=D.N. |year=2007 |title=Three-year Wilkinson Microwave Anisotropy Probe (WMAP) observations: Implications for cosmology |journal=The Astrophysical Journal Supplement Series |volume=170 |issue=2 |pages=377–408 |url=http://lambda.gsfc.nasa.gov/product/map/current/map_bibliography.cfm |quote=WMAP... confirms the basic tenets of the inflationary paradigm...|bibcode=2007ApJS..170..377S |arxiv=astro-ph/0603449 |doi=10.1086/513700 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.space.com/14699-universe-inflation-cosmic-expansion-theory.html |title=Our Baby Universe Likely Expanded Rapidly, Study Suggests |work=Space.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Space expands===
In a space that expands exponentially (or nearly exponentially) with time, any pair of free-floating objects that are initially at rest will move apart from each other at an accelerating rate, at least as long as they are not bound together by any force.  From the point of view of one such object, the spacetime is something like an inside-out Schwarzschild black hole—each object is surrounded by a spherical event horizon.  Once the other object has fallen through this horizon it can never return, and even light signals it sends will never reach the first object (at least so long as the space continues to expand exponentially).

In the approximation that the expansion is exactly exponential, the horizon is static and remains a fixed physical distance away.  This patch of an inflating universe can be described by the following [[metric tensor|metric]]:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Melia |first1=Fulvio |year=2008 |title=The Cosmic Horizon |url= |journal=Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society |volume=382 |issue=4 |pages=1917–1921 |doi=10.1111/j.1365-2966.2007.12499.x |bibcode=2007MNRAS.382.1917M |arxiv=0711.4181 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Melia |first1=Fulvio |date=2009 |title=The Cosmological Spacetime |url= |journal=International Journal of Modern Physics D |volume=18 |issue=12 |pages=1889–1901 |doi=10.1142/s0218271809015746 |displayauthors=etal |bibcode=2009IJMPD..18.1889M |arxiv=0907.5394 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

:&lt;math&gt;
ds^2=- (1- \Lambda r^2) \, dt^2 + {1\over 1-\Lambda r^2} \, dr^2 + r^2 \, d\Omega^2.
&lt;/math&gt;

This exponentially expanding spacetime is called a [[de Sitter space]], and to sustain it there must be a [[cosmological constant]], a [[dark energy|vacuum energy]] density that is constant  in space and time and proportional to Λ in the above metric. For the case of exactly exponential expansion, the vacuum energy has a negative pressure ''p'' equal in magnitude to its energy density ''ρ''; the [[Equation of state (cosmology)|equation of state]] is {{nowrap begin}}''p=−ρ''{{nowrap end}}.

Inflation is typically not an exactly exponential expansion, but rather quasi- or near-exponential.  In such a universe the horizon will slowly grow with time as the vacuum energy density gradually decreases.

===Few inhomogeneities remain===
Because the accelerating expansion of space stretches out any initial variations in density or temperature to very large length scales, an essential feature of inflation is that it smooths out [[homogeneity (physics)|inhomogeneities]] and [[anisotropy|anisotropies]], and reduces the [[shape of the universe|curvature of space]]. This pushes the Universe into a very simple state in which it is completely dominated by the [[inflaton]] field and the only significant inhomogeneities are tiny [[quantum fluctuation]]s. Inflation also dilutes exotic heavy particles, such as the [[magnetic monopole]]s predicted by many extensions to the [[Standard Model]] of [[particle physics]]. If the Universe was only hot enough to form such particles ''before'' a period of inflation, they would not be observed in nature, as they would be so rare that it is quite likely that there are none in the [[observable universe]]. Together, these effects are called the inflationary &quot;no-hair theorem&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Kolb and Turner (1988).&lt;/ref&gt; by analogy with the [[no hair theorem]] for [[black hole]]s.

The &quot;no-hair&quot; theorem works essentially because the cosmological horizon is no different from a black-hole horizon, except for philosophical disagreements about what is on the other side. The interpretation of the no-hair theorem is that the Universe (observable and unobservable) expands by an enormous factor during inflation. In an expanding universe, [[energy density|energy densities]] generally fall, or get diluted, as the volume of the Universe increases. For example, the density of ordinary &quot;cold&quot; matter (dust) goes down as the inverse of the volume: when linear dimensions double, the energy density goes down by a factor of eight; the radiation energy density goes down even more rapidly as the Universe expands since the wavelength of each [[photon]] is stretched ([[redshift]]ed), in addition to the photons being dispersed by the expansion. When linear dimensions are doubled, the energy density in radiation falls by a factor of sixteen (see [[Equation of state (cosmology)#Ultra-relativistic matter|the solution of the energy density continuity equation for an ultra-relativistic fluid]]). During inflation, the energy density in the inflaton field is roughly constant. However, the energy density in everything else, including inhomogeneities, curvature, anisotropies, exotic particles, and standard-model particles is falling, and through sufficient inflation these all become negligible. This leaves the Universe flat and symmetric, and (apart from the homogeneous inflaton field) mostly empty, at the moment inflation ends and reheating begins.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ryden2003&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author=Barbara Sue Ryden |title=Introduction to cosmology |date=2003 |publisher=Addison-Wesley |isbn=978-0-8053-8912-8 |quote=Not only is inflation very effective at driving down the number density of magnetic monopoles, it is also effective at driving down the number density of every other type of particle, including photons.}}{{rp |202–207}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Duration===
A key requirement is that inflation must continue long enough to produce the present observable universe from a single, small inflationary [[Hubble volume]]. This is necessary to ensure that the Universe appears flat, homogeneous and isotropic at the largest observable scales. This requirement is generally thought to be satisfied if the Universe expanded by a factor of at least 10&lt;sup&gt;26&lt;/sup&gt; during inflation.&lt;ref&gt;This is usually quoted as 60 ''e''-folds of expansion, where ''e''&lt;sup&gt;60&lt;/sup&gt; ≈ 10&lt;sup&gt;26&lt;/sup&gt;. It is equal to the amount of expansion since reheating, which is roughly ''E''&lt;sub&gt;inflation&lt;/sub&gt;/''T''&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt;, where ''T''&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt;=2.7 [[Kelvin|K]] is the temperature of the cosmic microwave background today. See, ''e.g.'' Kolb and Turner (1998) or Liddle and Lyth (2000).&lt;/ref&gt;

===Reheating===
Inflation is a period of supercooled expansion, when the temperature drops by a factor of 100,000 or so. (The exact drop is model-dependent, but in the first models it was typically from 10&lt;sup&gt;27&lt;/sup&gt; K down to 10&lt;sup&gt;22&lt;/sup&gt; K.&lt;ref&gt;Guth, ''Phase transitions in the very early universe'', in ''The Very Early Universe'', {{ISBN|0-521-31677-4}} eds Hawking, Gibbon &amp; Siklos&lt;/ref&gt;) This relatively low temperature is maintained during the inflationary phase. When inflation ends the temperature returns to the pre-inflationary temperature; this is called ''reheating'' or thermalization because the large potential energy of the inflaton field decays into particles and fills the Universe with [[Standard Model]] particles, including [[electromagnetic radiation]], starting the [[radiation-dominated era|radiation dominated phase]] of the Universe. Because the nature of the inflation is not known, this process is still poorly understood, although it is believed to take place through a [[parametric oscillator|parametric resonance]].&lt;ref&gt;See Kolb and Turner (1988) or Mukhanov (2005).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |title=Reheating after inflation |doi=10.1088/0264-9381/3/5/011 |first=Lev |last=Kofman |journal=Physical Review Letters |volume=73 |issue=5 |date=1994 |pages=3195–3198 |arxiv=hep-th/9405187 |last2=Linde |first2=Andrei |last3=Starobinsky |first3=Alexei |bibcode=1986CQGra...3..811K }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Motivations==
Inflation resolves [[Big Bang#Problems|several problems]] in [[Big Bang]] cosmology that were discovered in the 1970s.&lt;ref&gt;Much of the historical context is explained in chapters 15–17 of Peebles (1993).&lt;/ref&gt; Inflation was first proposed by [[Alan Guth]] in 1979 while investigating the problem of why no [[magnetic monopoles]] are seen today; he found that a positive-energy [[false vacuum]] would, according to [[general relativity]], generate an exponential expansion of space. It was very quickly realised that such an expansion would resolve many other long-standing problems. These problems arise from the observation that to look like it does ''today'', the Universe would have to have started from very [[fine tuned universe|finely tuned]], or &quot;special&quot; initial conditions at the Big Bang. Inflation attempts to resolve these problems by providing a dynamical mechanism that drives the Universe to this special state, thus making a universe like ours much more likely in the context of the Big Bang theory.

===Horizon problem===
{{Main |Horizon problem}}
The [[horizon problem]] is the problem of determining why the Universe appears statistically homogeneous and isotropic in accordance with the [[cosmological principle]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |title=The isotropy of the universe |doi=10.1088/0264-9381/15/2/008 |first=Charles W. |last=Misner |date=1968 |journal=Astrophysical Journal |volume=151 |issue=2 |pages=431 |last2=Coley |first2=A A |last3=Ellis |first3=G F R |last4=Hancock |first4=M |bibcode=1998CQGra..15..331W }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;mtw&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |last=Misner |first=Charles |author2=Thorne, Kip S. |author3=Wheeler, John Archibald |last-author-amp=yes |title=Gravitation |location=San Francisco |publisher=W. H. Freeman |date=1973 |isbn=978-0-7167-0344-0 |pages=489–490, 525–526}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;weinberg&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |first=Steven |last=Weinberg |title=Gravitation and Cosmology |publisher=John Wiley |date=1971 |isbn=978-0-471-92567-5 |pages=[https://archive.org/details/gravitationcosmo00stev_0/page/740 740, 815] |url=https://archive.org/details/gravitationcosmo00stev_0/page/740 }}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, molecules in a canister of gas are distributed homogeneously and isotropically because they are in thermal equilibrium: gas throughout the canister has had enough time to interact to dissipate inhomogeneities and anisotropies. The situation is quite different in the big bang model without inflation, because gravitational expansion does not give the early universe enough time to equilibrate. In a big bang with only the [[matter]] and [[radiation]] known in the Standard Model, two widely separated regions of the observable universe cannot have equilibrated because they move apart from each other faster than the [[speed of light]] and thus have never come into [[causal contact]]. In the early Universe, it was not possible to send a light signal between the two regions. Because they have had no interaction, it is difficult to explain why they have the same temperature (are thermally equilibrated). Historically, proposed solutions included the ''Phoenix universe'' of [[Georges Lemaître]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Lemaître |first=Georges |title=The expanding universe |journal=Annales de la Société Scientifique de Bruxelles |volume=47A |pages=49 |date=1933}}, English in ''Gen. Rel. Grav.'' '''29''':641–680, 1997.&lt;/ref&gt; the related [[oscillatory universe]] of [[Richard Chase Tolman]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |author=R. C. Tolman |title= Relativity, Thermodynamics, and Cosmology |location=Oxford |publisher=Clarendon Press |date=1934 |isbn=978-0-486-65383-9 |lccn=34032023}} Reissued (1987) New York: Dover {{ISBN|0-486-65383-8}}.&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Mixmaster universe]] of [[Charles Misner]]. Lemaître and Tolman proposed that a universe undergoing a number of cycles of contraction and expansion could come into thermal equilibrium. Their models failed, however, because of the buildup of [[entropy]] over several cycles. Misner made the (ultimately incorrect) conjecture that the Mixmaster mechanism, which made the Universe ''more'' chaotic, could lead to statistical homogeneity and isotropy.&lt;ref name=&quot;mtw&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |title=Mixmaster universe |doi=10.1088/1751-8113/41/15/155201 |first=Charles W. |last=Misner |date=1969 |journal=Physical Review Letters |volume=22 |issue=15 |pages=1071–74 |last2=Leach |first2=P G L |bibcode=2008JPhA...41o5201A }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Flatness problem===
{{Main|Flatness problem}}
The [[flatness problem]] is sometimes called one of the [[Dicke]] coincidences (along with the [[cosmological constant problem]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Dicke |first=Robert H. |title=Gravitation and the Universe |location=Philadelphia |publisher=American Philosopical Society |date=1970}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite conference |title=The big bang cosmology – enigmas and nostrums |first=Robert H. |last=Dicke |author2=P. J. E. Peebles |date=1979 |booktitle=General Relativity: an Einstein Centenary Survey |editor=S. W. Hawking |editor2=W. Israel |publisher=Cambridge University Press}}&lt;/ref&gt; It became known in the 1960s that the density of matter in the Universe was comparable to the [[Critical density (cosmology)|critical density]] necessary for a flat universe (that is, a universe whose large scale [[geometry]] is the usual [[Euclidean geometry]], rather than a [[non-Euclidean geometry|non-Euclidean]] [[hyperbolic geometry|hyperbolic]] or [[spherical geometry]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;Lightman1993&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author=Alan P. Lightman |title=Ancient Light: Our Changing View of the Universe |date=1 January 1993 |publisher=Harvard University Press |isbn=978-0-674-03363-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp |61}}

Therefore, regardless of the [[shape of the universe]] the contribution of spatial curvature to the expansion of the Universe could not be much greater than the contribution of matter. But as the Universe expands, the curvature [[redshift]]s away more slowly than matter and radiation. Extrapolated into the past, this presents a [[fine-tuning]] problem because the contribution of curvature to the Universe must be exponentially small (sixteen orders of magnitude less than the density of radiation at [[Big Bang nucleosynthesis]], for example). This problem is exacerbated by recent observations of the cosmic microwave background that have demonstrated that the Universe is flat to within a few percent.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://map.gsfc.nasa.gov/universe/uni_matter.html |title=WMAP- Content of the Universe |work=nasa.gov}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Magnetic-monopole problem===
The [[Big Bang#Magnetic monopoles|magnetic monopole problem]], sometimes called the exotic-relics problem, says that if the early universe were very hot, a large number of very heavy{{why |date=November 2012}}, stable [[magnetic monopole]]s would have been produced. This is a problem with [[Grand Unified Theory|Grand Unified Theories]], which propose that at high temperatures (such as in the early universe) the [[electromagnetic force]], [[strong nuclear force|strong]], and [[weak nuclear force|weak]] [[nuclear force]]s are not actually fundamental forces but arise due to [[spontaneous symmetry breaking]] from a single [[gauge theory]].&lt;ref&gt;Since [[supersymmetry|supersymmetric]] Grand Unified Theory is built into [[string theory]], it is still a triumph for inflation that it is able to deal with these magnetic relics. See, ''e.g.'' Kolb and Turner (1988) and {{cite book |title=Grand Unified Theories |url=https://archive.org/details/arxiv-hep-ph0608183 |first=Stuart |last=Raby |arxiv=hep-ph/0608183 |booktitle=Galapagos World Summit on Physics Beyond the Standard Model |editor=Bruce Hoeneisen |date=2006|bibcode=2006hep.ph....8183R }}&lt;/ref&gt; These theories predict a number of heavy, stable particles that have not been observed in nature. The most notorious is the magnetic monopole, a kind of stable, heavy &quot;charge&quot; of magnetic field.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last='t Hooft |first=Gerard |title=Magnetic monopoles in Unified Gauge Theories |journal=Nuclear Physics B |volume=79 |pages=276–84 |date=1974 |bibcode=1974NuPhB..79..276T |doi=10.1016/0550-3213(74)90486-6 |issue=2 |url=http://dspace.library.uu.nl:8080/handle/1874/4686 |hdl=1874/4686 }}{{Dead link|date=December 2018 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |first=Alexander M. |last=Polyakov |title=Particle spectrum in quantum field theory |journal=JETP Letters |volume=20 |pages=194–5 |date=1974 |bibcode=1974JETPL..20..194P }}&lt;/ref&gt; Monopoles are predicted to be copiously produced following Grand Unified Theories at high temperature,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |first=Alan |last2=Tye |last=Guth |first2=S. |title= Phase Transitions and Magnetic Monopole Production in the Very Early Universe |journal=Physical Review Letters |volume=44 |issue=10 |pages=631–635; Erratum ''ibid.'','''44''':963, 1980 |date=1980 |doi=10.1103/PhysRevLett.44.631 |bibcode=1980PhRvL..44..631G |url=http://repository.ust.hk/ir/bitstream/1783.1-49322/1/PhysRevLett.44.631.pdf }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |first=Martin B |last=Einhorn |title=Are Grand Unified Theories Compatible with Standard Cosmology? |journal=Physical Review D |volume=21 |pages=3295–3298 |date=1980 |bibcode=1980PhRvD..21.3295E |last2=Stein |first2=D. L. |last3=Toussaint |first3=Doug |doi=10.1103/PhysRevD.21.3295 |issue=12}}&lt;/ref&gt; and they should have persisted to the present day, to such an extent that they would become the primary constituent of the Universe.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |title=On the concentration of relic monopoles in the universe |first=Ya. |last=Zel'dovich |first2=M. Yu. |last2=Khlopov |date=1978 |journal=Physics Letters B |volume=79 |pages=239–41 |bibcode=1978PhLB...79..239Z |doi=10.1016/0370-2693(78)90232-0 |url=|issue=3}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |title=Cosmological production of superheavy magnetic monopoles |doi=10.1103/PhysRevLett.43.1365 |date=1979 |journal=Physical Review Letters |volume=43 |issue=19 |pages=1365–1368 |first=John |last=Preskill |bibcode=1979PhRvL..43.1365P |url=https://authors.library.caltech.edu/6133/1/PREprl79.pdf }}&lt;/ref&gt; Not only is that not the case, but all searches for them have failed, placing stringent limits on the density of relic magnetic monopoles in the Universe.&lt;ref&gt;See, ''e.g.'' {{Cite journal |last=Yao |first=W.-M. |title=Review of Particle Physics |doi=10.1088/0954-3899/33/1/001 |journal=Journal of Physics G |volume=33 |issue=1 |pages=1–1232 |url=http://pdg.lbl.gov/ |authorlink=Particle Data Group |date=2006 |arxiv=astro-ph/0601168 |bibcode=2006JPhG...33....1Y |display-authors=etal}}&lt;/ref&gt; A period of inflation that occurs below the temperature where magnetic monopoles can be produced would offer a possible resolution of this problem: monopoles would be separated from each other as the Universe around them expands, potentially lowering their observed density by many orders of magnitude. Though, as cosmologist [[Martin Rees]] has written, &quot;Skeptics about exotic physics might not be hugely impressed by a theoretical argument to explain the absence of particles that are themselves only hypothetical. Preventive medicine can readily seem 100 percent effective against a disease that doesn't exist!&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Rees, Martin. (1998). ''Before the Beginning'' (New York: Basic Books) p. 185 {{ISBN|0-201-15142-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==

===Precursors===
In the early days of [[General Relativity]], [[Albert Einstein]] introduced the [[cosmological constant]] to allow a [[Einstein static universe|static solution]], which was a [[3-sphere|three-dimensional sphere]] with a uniform density of matter. Later, [[Willem de Sitter]] found a highly symmetric inflating universe, which described a universe with a cosmological constant that is otherwise empty.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |first=Willem |last=de Sitter |title=Einstein's theory of gravitation and its astronomical consequences. Third paper |journal=[[Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society]] |volume=78 |pages=3–28 |date=1917 |bibcode=1917MNRAS..78....3D |doi=10.1093/mnras/78.1.3}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was discovered that Einstein's universe is unstable, and that small fluctuations cause it to collapse or turn into a de Sitter universe.

In the early 1970s [[Zeldovich]] noticed the flatness and horizon problems of Big Bang cosmology; before his work, cosmology was presumed to be symmetrical on purely philosophical grounds.{{Citation needed |reason=It's Robert Dicke and Charles Misner who suggested these problems |date=May 2014}} In the Soviet Union, this and other considerations led Belinski and [[Khalatnikov]] to analyze the chaotic [[BKL singularity]] in General Relativity. Misner's [[Mixmaster universe]] attempted to use this chaotic behavior to solve the cosmological problems, with limited success.

====False vacuum====
In the late 1970s, [[Sidney Coleman]] applied the [[instanton]] techniques developed by [[Alexander Markovich Polyakov|Alexander Polyakov]] and collaborators to study the fate of the [[false vacuum]] in [[quantum field theory]]. Like a metastable phase in [[statistical mechanics]]—water below the freezing temperature or above the boiling point—a quantum field would need to nucleate a large enough bubble of the new vacuum, the new phase, in order to make a transition. Coleman found the most likely decay pathway for vacuum decay and calculated the inverse lifetime per unit volume. He eventually noted that gravitational effects would be significant, but he did not calculate these effects and did not apply the results to cosmology.

====Starobinsky inflation====
{{Main|Starobinsky inflation}}
In the Soviet Union, [[Alexei Starobinsky]] noted that quantum corrections to general relativity should be important for the early universe. These generically lead to curvature-squared corrections to the [[Einstein–Hilbert action]] and a form of [[f(R) gravity|''f''(''R'') modified gravity]]. The solution to Einstein's equations in the presence of curvature squared terms, when the curvatures are large, leads to an effective cosmological constant. Therefore, he proposed that the early universe went through an inflationary de Sitter era.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Starobinsky, A. A. |title= Spectrum Of Relict Gravitational Radiation And The Early State Of The Universe |journal=Journal of Experimental and Theoretical Physics Letters |volume=30 |page= 682 |date=December 1979 |bibcode=1979JETPL..30..682S}}; {{cite journal |title=Spectrum of relict gravitational radiation and the early state of the universe |bibcode=1979ZhPmR..30..719S |journal=Pisma Zh. Eksp. Teor. Fiz. |page= 719 |date=December 1979 |volume=30 |author=Starobinskii, A. A. }}&lt;/ref&gt; This resolved the cosmology problems and led to specific predictions for the corrections to the microwave background radiation, corrections that were then calculated in detail. Starobinsky used the action 
:&lt;math&gt;
S=\frac{1}{2} \int d^4 x \left(R + \frac{R^2}{6M^2} \right)
&lt;/math&gt;
which corresponds to the potential
:&lt;math&gt;\quad V(\phi)=\Lambda^4 \left(1 - e^{-\sqrt{2/3} \phi/M^2_p} \right)^2 &lt;/math&gt;
in the Einstein frame. This results in the observables:
&lt;math&gt; n_s=1 - \frac{2}{N}, \quad \quad r=\frac{12}{N^2}. &lt;/math&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |page=17 |title=Planck 2015 results. XX. Constraints on inflation |journal=Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics |volume=594 |arxiv=1502.02114 |doi=10.1051/0004-6361/201525898 |year=2016 |last1=Ade |first1=P. A. R. |display-authors=etal |bibcode=2016A&amp;A...594A..20P}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Monopole problem====
In 1978, Zeldovich noted the monopole problem, which was an unambiguous quantitative version of the horizon problem, this time in a subfield of particle physics, which led to several speculative attempts to resolve it. In 1980 [[Alan Guth]] realized that false vacuum decay in the early universe would solve the problem, leading him to propose a scalar-driven inflation. Starobinsky's and Guth's scenarios both predicted an initial de Sitter phase, differing only in mechanistic details.

===Early inflationary models===
Guth proposed inflation in January 1981 to explain the nonexistence of magnetic monopoles;&lt;ref name=&quot;SLAC&quot;&gt;[[Stanford Linear Accelerator Center|SLAC]] seminar, &quot;10&lt;sup&gt;−35&lt;/sup&gt; seconds after the Big Bang&quot;, 23 January 1980. see Guth (1997), pg 186&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;guth&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1103/PhysRevD.23.347 |title=Inflationary universe: A possible solution to the horizon and flatness problems |url=http://www.astro.rug.nl/~weygaert/tim1publication/cosmo2007/literature/inflationary.universe.guth.physrevd-1981.pdf |date=1981 |last1=Guth |first1=Alan H. |journal=Physical Review D |volume=23 |issue=2 |pages=347–356 |bibcode=1981PhRvD..23..347G }}&lt;/ref&gt; it was Guth who coined the term &quot;inflation&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;peebles 17&quot;&gt;Chapter 17 of Peebles (1993).&lt;/ref&gt; At the same time, Starobinsky argued that quantum corrections to gravity would replace the initial singularity of the Universe with an exponentially expanding de Sitter phase.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |first=Alexei A. |last=Starobinsky |title=A new type of isotropic cosmological models without singularity |journal=Physics Letters B |volume=91 |issue=1 |pages=99–102 |date=1980 |bibcode=1980PhLB...91...99S |doi=10.1016/0370-2693(80)90670-X}}&lt;/ref&gt; In October 1980, Demosthenes Kazanas suggested that exponential expansion could eliminate the [[particle horizon]] and perhaps solve the horizon problem,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |first=D. |last=Kazanas |title=Dynamics of the universe and spontaneous symmetry breaking |journal=Astrophysical Journal |volume=241 |pages=L59–63 |date=1980 |doi=10.1086/183361 |bibcode=1980ApJ...241L..59K }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|editor=Contopoulos, G.|editor2=Patsis, P. A.|author=Kazanas, D.|chapter=Cosmological Inflation: A Personal Perspective|title=Chaos in Astronomy: Conference 2007|journal=Astrophysics and Space Science Proceedings|volume=8|pages=485–496|publisher=Springer Science &amp; Business Media|year=2009|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=QfipHB0XK58C&amp;pg=PA485 |arxiv=0803.2080|bibcode=2009ASSP....8..485K|doi=10.1007/978-3-540-75826-6_49|isbn=978-3-540-75825-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; while Sato suggested that an exponential expansion could eliminate [[Domain wall (string theory)|domain walls]] (another kind of exotic relic).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |first=K. |last=Sato |title=Cosmological baryon number domain structure and the first order phase transition of a vacuum |journal=Physics Letters B |volume=33 |issue=1 |pages=66–70 |date=1981 |bibcode=1981PhLB...99...66S |doi=10.1016/0370-2693(81)90805-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1981 Einhorn and Sato&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |first=Martin B |last=Einhorn |title=Monopole Production In The Very Early Universe In A First Order Phase Transition |journal=Nuclear Physics B |volume=180 |issue=3 |pages=385–404 |date=1981 |doi=10.1016/0550-3213(81)90057-2 |bibcode=1981NuPhB.180..385E |last2=Sato |first2=Katsuhiko }}&lt;/ref&gt; published a model similar to Guth's and showed that it would resolve the puzzle of the [[magnetic monopole]] abundance in Grand Unified Theories. Like Guth, they concluded that such a model not only required fine tuning of the cosmological constant, but also would likely lead to a much too granular universe, i.e., to large density variations resulting from bubble wall collisions.

[[Image:Horizonte inflacionario.svg |thumb |right |300px |The physical size of the [[Hubble radius]] (solid line) as a function of the linear expansion (scale factor) of the universe. During cosmological inflation, the Hubble radius is constant. The physical wavelength of a perturbation mode (dashed line) is also shown. The plot illustrates how the perturbation mode grows larger than the horizon during cosmological inflation before coming back inside the horizon, which grows rapidly during radiation domination. If cosmological inflation had never happened, and radiation domination continued back until a [[gravitational singularity]], then the mode would never have been inside the horizon in the very early universe, and no [[causality (physics)|causal]] mechanism could have ensured that the universe was homogeneous on the scale of the perturbation mode.]]

Guth proposed that as the early universe cooled, it was trapped in a [[false vacuum]] with a high energy density, which is much like a [[cosmological constant]]. As the very early universe cooled it was trapped in a [[metastability|metastable]] state (it was supercooled), which it could only decay out of through the process of [[nucleation|bubble nucleation]] via [[quantum tunneling]]. Bubbles of [[vacuum state|true vacuum]] spontaneously form in the sea of false vacuum and rapidly begin expanding at the [[speed of light]]. Guth recognized that this model was problematic because the model did not reheat properly: when the bubbles nucleated, they did not generate any radiation. Radiation could only be generated in collisions between bubble walls. But if inflation lasted long enough to solve the initial conditions problems, collisions between bubbles became exceedingly rare. In any one causal patch it is likely that only one bubble would nucleate.

{{blockquote|... Kazanas (1980) called this phase of the early Universe &quot;de Sitter's phase.&quot; The name &quot;inflation&quot; was given by Guth (1981). ... Guth himself did not refer to work of Kazanas until he published a book on the subject under the title &quot;The inflationary universe: the quest for a new theory of cosmic origin&quot; (1997), where he apologizes for not having referenced the work of Kazanas and of others, related to inflation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Contopoulos, George|title=Adventures in order and chaos: a scientific autobiography|volume=313|publisher=Springer Science &amp; Business Media|year=2004|pages=88–89|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=3UXak_7yR3MC&amp;pg=PA88|isbn=9781402030406}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

===Slow-roll inflation===
The bubble collision problem was solved by [[Andrei Linde|Linde]]&lt;ref name=&quot;linde&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1016/0370-2693(82)91219-9 |title=A new inflationary universe scenario: A possible solution of the horizon, flatness, homogeneity, isotropy and primordial monopole problems |date=1982 |last1=Linde |first1=A |journal=Physics Letters B |volume=108 |issue=6 |pages=389–393 |bibcode=1982PhLB..108..389L }}&lt;/ref&gt; and independently by [[Andreas Albrecht (cosmologist)|Andreas Albrecht]] and [[Paul Steinhardt]]&lt;ref name=&quot;albrecht&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1103/PhysRevLett.48.1220 |title=Cosmology for Grand Unified Theories with Radiatively Induced Symmetry Breaking |date=1982 |last1=Albrecht |first1=Andreas |last2=Steinhardt |first2=Paul |journal=Physical Review Letters |volume=48 |issue=17 |pages=1220–1223 |bibcode=1982PhRvL..48.1220A |url=http://astrophysics.fic.uni.lodz.pl/100yrs/pdf/07/060.pdf |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120130063002/http://astrophysics.fic.uni.lodz.pl/100yrs/pdf/07/060.pdf |archivedate=30 January 2012  }}&lt;/ref&gt; in a model named ''new inflation'' or ''slow-roll inflation'' (Guth's model then became known as ''old inflation''). In this model, instead of tunneling out of a false vacuum state, inflation occurred by a [[scalar field]] rolling down a potential energy hill. When the field rolls very slowly compared to the expansion of the Universe, inflation occurs. However, when the hill becomes steeper, inflation ends and reheating can occur.

===Effects of asymmetries===
{{Main|Primordial fluctuations}}
Eventually, it was shown that new inflation does not produce a perfectly symmetric universe, but that quantum fluctuations in the inflaton are created. These fluctuations form the primordial seeds for all structure created in the later universe.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hartle&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |author=J.B. Hartle |date=2003 |title=Gravity: An Introduction to Einstein's General Relativity |page=411 |edition=1st |publisher=Addison Wesley |isbn=978-0-8053-8662-2 }}&lt;/ref&gt; These fluctuations were first calculated by [[Viatcheslav Mukhanov]] and G. V. Chibisov in analyzing Starobinsky's similar model.&lt;ref&gt;See Linde (1990) and Mukhanov (2005).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |journal=JETP Letters |volume=33 |pages=532–5 |date=1981 |title=Quantum fluctuation and &quot;nonsingular&quot; universe |first=Viatcheslav F. |last=Chibisov |bibcode=1981JETPL..33..532M |last2=Chibisov |first2=G. V. }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |journal=Soviet Physics JETP |volume=56 |pages=258–65 |date=1982 |title=The vacuum energy and large scale structure of the universe |first=Viatcheslav F. |last=Mukhanov}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the context of inflation, they were worked out independently of the work of Mukhanov and Chibisov at the three-week 1982 Nuffield Workshop on the Very Early Universe at [[University of Cambridge|Cambridge University]].&lt;ref&gt;See Guth (1997) for a popular description of the workshop, or ''The Very Early Universe'', {{ISBN|0-521-31677-4}} eds Hawking, Gibbon &amp; Siklos for a more detailed report&lt;/ref&gt; The fluctuations were calculated by four groups working separately over the course of the workshop: [[Stephen Hawking]];&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |title=The development of irregularities in a single bubble inflationary universe |first=S.W. |last=Hawking |journal=Physics Letters B |volume=115 |pages=295–297 |date=1982 |bibcode=1982PhLB..115..295H |doi=10.1016/0370-2693(82)90373-2 |issue=4}}&lt;/ref&gt; Starobinsky;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |title=Dynamics of phase transition in the new inflationary universe scenario and generation of perturbations |first=Alexei A. |last=Starobinsky |journal=Physics Letters B |volume=117 |pages=175–8 |date=1982 |bibcode=1982PhLB..117..175S |doi=10.1016/0370-2693(82)90541-X |issue=3–4}}&lt;/ref&gt; Guth and So-Young Pi;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |title=Fluctuations in the new inflationary universe |first=A.H. |last=Guth |date=1982 |journal=Physical Review Letters |volume=49 |issue=15 |pages=1110–3 |doi=10.1103/PhysRevLett.49.1110 |bibcode=1982PhRvL..49.1110G }}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[James M. Bardeen|Bardeen]], [[Paul Steinhardt|Steinhardt]] and [[Michael Turner (cosmologist)|Turner]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |title=Spontaneous creation Of almost scale-free density perturbations in an inflationary universe |first=James M. |last=Bardeen |journal=Physical Review D |volume=28 |pages=679–693 |date=1983 |bibcode=1983PhRvD..28..679B |last2=Steinhardt |first2=Paul J. |last3=Turner |first3=Michael S. |doi=10.1103/PhysRevD.28.679 |issue=4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Observational status==
Inflation is a mechanism for realizing the [[cosmological principle]], which is the basis of the standard model of physical cosmology: it accounts for the homogeneity and isotropy of the observable universe. In addition, it accounts for the observed flatness and absence of magnetic monopoles. Since Guth's early work, each of these observations has received further confirmation, most impressively by the detailed observations of the [[cosmic microwave background]] made by the [[Planck (spacecraft)|Planck spacecraft]].&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal |collaboration=Planck Collaboration |last1=Ade |first1=P. A. R. |display-authors=etal |date=2016-10-01 |title=Planck 2015 results. XIII. Cosmological parameters |journal=Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics |volume=594 |pages=A13 |doi=10.1051/0004-6361/201525830 |issn=0004-6361 |bibcode=2016A&amp;A...594A..13P |arxiv=1502.01589}}&lt;/ref&gt; This analysis shows that the Universe is flat to within 0.5 percent, and that it is homogeneous and isotropic to one part in 100,000.

Inflation predicts that the structures visible in the Universe today formed through the [[gravitational collapse]] of perturbations that were formed as quantum mechanical fluctuations in the inflationary epoch. The detailed form of the spectrum of perturbations, called a [[Scale invariance#Cosmology|nearly-scale-invariant]] [[Gaussian random field]] is very specific and has only two free parameters. One is the amplitude of the spectrum and the ''[[spectral index]]'', which measures the slight deviation from scale invariance predicted by inflation (perfect scale invariance corresponds to the idealized de Sitter universe).&lt;ref&gt;Perturbations can be represented by [[Fourier modes]] of a [[wavelength]]. Each Fourier mode is [[Normal distribution|normally distributed]] (usually called Gaussian) with mean zero. Different Fourier components are uncorrelated. The variance of a mode depends only on its wavelength in such a way that within any given volume each wavelength contributes an equal amount of [[Spectral density|power]] to the spectrum of perturbations. Since the Fourier transform is in three dimensions, this means that the variance of a mode goes as ''k''&lt;sup&gt;-3&lt;/sup&gt; to compensate for the fact that within any volume, the number of modes with a given wavenumber ''k'' goes as ''k''&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/ref&gt; The other free parameter is the tensor to scalar ratio. The simplest inflation models, those without [[Fine-tuned universe|fine-tuning]], predict a [[Tensor field|tensor]] to scalar ratio near 0.1.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Boyle |first=Latham A. |last2=Steinhardt |first2=Paul J. |last3=Turok |first3=Neil |date=2006-03-24 |title=Inflationary Predictions for Scalar and Tensor Fluctuations Reconsidered |journal=Physical Review Letters |volume=96 |issue=11 |pages=111301 |doi=10.1103/PhysRevLett.96.111301 |pmid=16605810 |bibcode=2006PhRvL..96k1301B|arxiv=astro-ph/0507455 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Inflation predicts that the observed perturbations should be in [[thermal equilibrium]] with each other (these are called ''[[adiabatic]]'' or ''[[Isentropic process|isentropic]]'' perturbations). This structure for the perturbations has been confirmed by the [[Planck (spacecraft)|Planck spacecraft]], [[Wilkinson Microwave Anisotropy Probe|WMAP]] spacecraft and other cosmic microwave background (CMB) experiments, and [[galaxy survey]]s, especially the ongoing [[Sloan Digital Sky Survey]].&lt;ref name=&quot;sdss2&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Tegmark |first=M. |displayauthors=etal |date=August 2006 |title=Cosmological constraints from the SDSS luminous red galaxies |journal=Physical Review D |volume=74 |issue=12 |pages=123507 |arxiv=astro-ph/0608632 |bibcode=2006PhRvD..74l3507T |doi=10.1103/PhysRevD.74.123507|hdl=1811/48518 }}&lt;/ref&gt; These experiments have shown that the one part in 100,000 inhomogeneities observed have exactly the form predicted by theory. There is evidence for a slight deviation from scale invariance. The ''[[spectral index]]'', ''n''&lt;sub&gt;s&lt;/sub&gt; is one for a scale-invariant Harrison–Zel'dovich spectrum. The simplest inflation models predict that ''n''&lt;sub&gt;s&lt;/sub&gt; is between 0.92 and 0.98.&lt;ref name=&quot;myths2&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Steinhardt |first=Paul J. |date=2004 |title=Cosmological perturbations: Myths and facts |journal=Modern Physics Letters A |volume=19 |issue=13 &amp; 16 |pages=967–82 |bibcode=2004MPLA...19..967S |doi=10.1142/S0217732304014252|url=https://semanticscholar.org/paper/eba085f5040f88a59722600e40a35e19b7113f93 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;boyle2&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Boyle |first=Latham A. |last2=Steinhardt |first2=PJ |last3=Turok |first3=N |date=2006 |title=Inflationary predictions for scalar and tensor fluctuations reconsidered |journal=Physical Review Letters |volume=96 |issue=11 |pages=111301 |arxiv=astro-ph/0507455 |bibcode=2006PhRvL..96k1301B |doi=10.1103/PhysRevLett.96.111301 |pmid=16605810}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;tegmark2&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Tegmark |first=Max |date=2005 |title=What does inflation really predict? |journal= Journal of Cosmology and Astroparticle Physics|volume= 2005|issue=4 |pages=001 |arxiv=astro-ph/0410281 |bibcode=2005JCAP...04..001T |doi=10.1088/1475-7516/2005/04/001}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;This is known as a &quot;red&quot; spectrum, in analogy to [[redshift]], because the spectrum has more power at longer wavelengths.&lt;/ref&gt; This is the range that is possible without [[Fine-tuned universe|fine-tuning]] of the parameters related to energy.&lt;ref name=&quot;tegmark2&quot; /&gt; From Planck data it can be inferred that ''n''&lt;sub&gt;s&lt;/sub&gt;=0.968 ± 0.006,&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |collaboration=Planck Collaboration |last1=Ade |first1=P. A. R. |date=2016-10-01 |title=Planck 2015 results. XX. Constraints on inflation |journal=Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics |volume=594 |pages=A20 |doi=10.1051/0004-6361/201525898 |issn=0004-6361 |bibcode=2016A&amp;A...594A..20P |arxiv=1502.02114}}&lt;/ref&gt; and a [[Tensor field|tensor]] to scalar ratio that is less than 0.11. These are considered an important confirmation of the theory of inflation.&lt;ref name=&quot;wmap2&quot;/&gt;

Various inflation theories have been proposed that make radically different predictions, but they generally have much more [[fine-tuning|fine tuning]] than should be necessary.&lt;ref name=&quot;myths2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;boyle2&quot;/&gt; As a physical model, however, inflation is most valuable in that it robustly predicts the initial conditions of the Universe based on only two adjustable parameters: the spectral index (that can only change in a small range) and the amplitude of the perturbations. Except in contrived models, this is true regardless of how inflation is realized in particle physics.

Occasionally, effects are observed that appear to contradict the simplest models of inflation. The first-year WMAP data suggested that the spectrum might not be nearly scale-invariant, but might instead have a slight curvature.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |first=D. N. |last=Spergel |display-authors=etal |title=First year Wilkinson Microwave Anisotropy Probe (WMAP) observations: determination of cosmological parameters |journal=Astrophysical Journal Supplement Series |volume=148 |issue=1 |pages=175–194 |date=2003 |doi=10.1086/377226 |bibcode=2003ApJS..148..175S |arxiv=astro-ph/0302209}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the third-year data revealed that the effect was a statistical anomaly.&lt;ref name=&quot;wmap2&quot;/&gt; Another effect remarked upon since the first cosmic microwave background satellite, the [[Cosmic Background Explorer]] is that the amplitude of the [[quadrupole moment]] of the CMB is unexpectedly low and the other low multipoles appear to be preferentially aligned with the [[plane of the ecliptic|ecliptic plane]]. Some have claimed that this is a signature of non-Gaussianity and thus contradicts the simplest models of inflation. Others have suggested that the effect may be due to other new physics, foreground contamination, or even [[publication bias]].&lt;ref&gt;See [[cosmic microwave background#Low multipoles]] for details and references.&lt;/ref&gt;

An experimental program is underway to further test inflation with more precise CMB measurements. In particular, high precision measurements of the so-called &quot;B-modes&quot; of the [[Cosmic microwave background radiation#Polarization|polarization]] of the background radiation could provide evidence of the [[gravitational radiation]] produced by inflation, and could also show whether the energy scale of inflation predicted by the simplest models (10&lt;sup&gt;15&lt;/sup&gt;–10&lt;sup&gt;16&lt;/sup&gt; [[GeV]]) is correct.&lt;ref name=&quot;boyle2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;tegmark2&quot;/&gt; In March 2014, the [[BICEP2]] team announced B-mode CMB polarization confirming inflation had been demonstrated. The team announced the tensor-to-scalar power ratio &lt;math&gt;r&lt;/math&gt; was between 0.15 and 0.27 (rejecting the null hypothesis; &lt;math&gt;r&lt;/math&gt; is expected to be 0 in the absence of inflation).&lt;ref name=&quot;five years&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Grant |first1=Andrew |title=Five years after BICEP2 |journal=[[Physics Today]] |date=2019 |doi=10.1063/PT.6.3.20190326a }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, on 19 June 2014, lowered confidence in confirming the findings was reported;&lt;ref name=&quot;PRL-20140619&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last=Ade |first=P.A.R. |collaboration=BICEP2 Collaboration |title=Detection of B-Mode Polarization at Degree Angular Scales by BICEP2 |date=19 June 2014 |journal=[[Physical Review Letters]] |volume=112 |issue=24 |page=241101 |doi=10.1103/PhysRevLett.112.241101 |arxiv=1403.3985 |bibcode=2014PhRvL.112x1101B |displayauthors=etal |pmid=24996078}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT-20140619&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Overbye |first=Dennis |authorlink=Dennis Overbye |title=Astronomers Hedge on Big Bang Detection Claim |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2014/06/20/science/space/scientists-debate-gravity-wave-detection-claim.html |date=19 June 2014 |work=[[The New York Times]] |accessdate=20 June 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC-20140619&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Amos |first=Jonathan |title=Cosmic inflation: Confidence lowered for Big Bang signal |url=https://www.bbc.com/news/science-environment-27935479 |date=19 June 2014 |work=[[BBC News]] |accessdate=20 June 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt; on 19 September 2014, a further reduction in confidence was reported&lt;ref name=&quot;AXV-20140919&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal |author=Planck Collaboration Team |title=Planck intermediate results. XXX. The angular power spectrum of polarized dust emission at intermediate and high Galactic latitudes |journal=Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics |volume=586 |issue=133 |pages=A133 |year=2016 |arxiv=1409.5738 |doi=10.1051/0004-6361/201425034 |bibcode=2016A&amp;A...586A.133P }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT-20140922&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Overbye |first=Dennis |authorlink=Dennis Overbye |title=Study Confirms Criticism of Big Bang Finding |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2014/09/23/science/space/study-confirms-criticism-of-big-bang-finding.html |date=22 September 2014 |work=[[The New York Times]] |accessdate=22 September 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; and, on 30 January 2015, even less confidence yet was reported.&lt;ref name=&quot;NASA-20150130&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last=Clavin |first=Whitney |title=Gravitational Waves from Early Universe Remain Elusive |url=http://www.jpl.nasa.gov/news/news.php?release=2015-46 |date=30 January 2015 |work=[[NASA]] |accessdate=30 January 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT-20150130&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Overbye |first=Dennis |authorlink=Dennis Overbye |title=Speck of Interstellar Dust Obscures Glimpse of Big Bang |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2015/01/31/us/a-speck-of-interstellar-dust-rebuts-a-big-bang-theory.html |date=30 January 2015 |work=[[The New York Times]] |accessdate=31 January 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt; By 2018, additional data suggested, with 95% confidence, that &lt;math&gt;r&lt;/math&gt; is 0.06 or lower: consistent with the null hypothesis, but still also consistent with many remaining models of inflation.&lt;ref name=&quot;five years&quot;/&gt;

Other potentially corroborating measurements are expected from the [[Planck (spacecraft)|Planck spacecraft]], although it is unclear if the signal will be visible, or if contamination from foreground sources will interfere.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite conference |title=Systematic effects in CMB polarization measurements |first=C. |last=Rosset |author2=PLANCK-HFI collaboration |booktitle=Exploring the universe: Contents and structures of the universe (XXXIXth Rencontres de Moriond) |date=2005|arxiv=astro-ph/0502188 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Other forthcoming measurements, such as those of [[21 centimeter radiation]] (radiation emitted and absorbed from neutral hydrogen before the [[population III star|first stars]] formed), may measure the power spectrum with even greater resolution than the CMB and galaxy surveys, although it is not known if these measurements will be possible or if interference with [[radio frequency|radio sources]] on Earth and in the galaxy will be too great.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |first=A. |last=Loeb |title=Measuring the small-scale power spectrum of cosmic density fluctuations through 21 cm tomography prior to the epoch of structure formation |journal=Physical Review Letters |volume=92 |pages=211301 |date=2004 |arxiv=astro-ph/0312134 |doi=10.1103/PhysRevLett.92.211301 |pmid=15245272 |last2=Zaldarriaga |first2=M |issue=21 |bibcode=2004PhRvL..92u1301L |url=http://cds.cern.ch/record/690135 |type=Submitted manuscript }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Theoretical status==
{{unsolved|physics|Is the theory of cosmological inflation correct, and if so, what are the details of this epoch? What is the hypothetical inflaton field giving rise to inflation?}}
In Guth's early proposal, it was thought that the [[inflaton]] was the [[Higgs field]], the field that explains the mass of the elementary particles.&lt;ref name=&quot;guth&quot; /&gt; It is now believed by some that the inflaton cannot be the Higgs field&lt;ref name=&quot;guth97&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |last=Guth |first=Alan |authorlink=Alan Guth |title=The Inflationary Universe |publisher=[[Addison–Wesley]] |date=1997 |isbn=978-0-201-14942-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; although the recent discovery of the Higgs boson has increased the number of works considering the Higgs field as inflaton.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last =Choi |first =Charles |title =Could the Large Hadron Collider Discover the Particle Underlying Both Mass and Cosmic Inflation? |journal=Scientific American |date =29 June 2012 |url =http://www.scientificamerican.com/article/could-lhc-discover-higgs-boson/ |accessdate=25 June 2014 |quote=The virtue of so-called Higgs inflation models is that they might explain inflation within the current Standard Model of particle physics, which successfully describes how most known particles and forces behave. Interest in the Higgs is running hot this summer because CERN, the lab in Geneva, Switzerland, that runs the LHC, has said it will announce highly anticipated findings regarding the particle in early July.}}&lt;/ref&gt; One problem of this identification is the current tension with experimental data at the [[Electroweak interaction|electroweak]] scale,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Salvio |first=Alberto |title=Higgs Inflation at NNLO after the Boson Discovery |journal= Physics Letters B|year=2013 |arxiv=1308.2244 |bibcode=2013PhLB..727..234S |doi=10.1016/j.physletb.2013.10.042 |volume=727 |issue=1–3 |pages=234–239}}&lt;/ref&gt; which is currently under study at the Large Hadron Collider (LHC). Other models of inflation relied on the properties of Grand Unified Theories.&lt;ref name=&quot;albrecht&quot; /&gt; Since the simplest models of [[grand unification]] have failed, it is now thought by many physicists that inflation will be included in a [[supersymmetric]] theory such as [[string theory]] or a supersymmetric grand unified theory. At present, while inflation is understood principally by its detailed predictions of the [[boundary condition|initial conditions]] for the hot early universe, the particle physics is largely ''ad hoc'' modelling. As such, although predictions of inflation have been consistent with the results of observational tests, many open questions remain.

===Fine-tuning problem===
One of the most severe challenges for inflation arises from the need for [[fine tuning]]. In new inflation, the ''slow-roll conditions'' must be satisfied for inflation to occur. The slow-roll conditions say that the inflaton [[scalar potential|potential]] must be flat (compared to the large [[vacuum energy]]) and that the inflaton particles must have a small mass.{{Clarify |reason=the inflaton particle has not been defined. From the note, it seems that the second condition should be that the inflaton potential should be large |date=June 2014}}&lt;ref&gt;Technically, these conditions are that the [[logarithmic derivative]] of the potential, &lt;math&gt;\epsilon=(1/2)(V'/V)^2&lt;/math&gt; and second derivative &lt;math&gt;\eta=V''/V&lt;/math&gt; are small, where &lt;math&gt;V&lt;/math&gt; is the potential and the equations are written in [[reduced Planck units]]. See, ''e.g.'' Liddle and Lyth (2000), pg 42–43.&lt;/ref&gt; New inflation requires the Universe to have a scalar field with an especially flat potential and special initial conditions. However, explanations for these fine-tunings have been proposed. For example, classically scale invariant field theories, where scale invariance is broken by quantum effects, provide an explanation of the flatness of inflationary potentials, as long as the theory can be studied through [[perturbation theory]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Salvio, Strumia |title=Agravity |journal= Journal of High Energy Physics|date=2014-03-17 |arxiv=1403.4226 |bibcode=2014JHEP...06..080S |doi=10.1007/JHEP06(2014)080 |volume=2014 |issue=6 |pages=80}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Andrei Linde|Linde]] proposed a theory known as ''[[Chaotic inflation theory|chaotic inflation]]'' in which he suggested that the conditions for inflation were actually satisfied quite generically. Inflation will occur in virtually [[Multiverse|any universe]] that begins in a chaotic, high energy state that has a scalar field with unbounded potential energy.&lt;ref name=&quot;chaotic&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal |first=Andrei D. |last=Linde |title=Chaotic inflation |doi=10.1016/0370-2693(83)90837-7 |journal=Physics Letters B |volume=129 |issue=3 |pages=171–81 |date=1983 |bibcode=1983PhLB..129..177L }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, in his model the inflaton field necessarily takes values larger than one [[Planck unit]]: for this reason, these are often called ''large field'' models and the competing new inflation models are called ''small field'' models. In this situation, the predictions of [[effective field theory]] are thought to be invalid, as [[renormalization]] should cause large corrections that could prevent inflation.&lt;ref&gt;Technically, this is because the inflaton potential is expressed as a Taylor series in φ/''m''&lt;sub&gt;Pl&lt;/sub&gt;, where φ is the inflaton and ''m''&lt;sub&gt;Pl&lt;/sub&gt; is the Planck mass. While for a single term, such as the mass term ''m''&lt;sub&gt;φ&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;(φ/''m''&lt;sub&gt;Pl&lt;/sub&gt;)&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, the slow roll conditions can be satisfied for φ much greater than ''m''&lt;sub&gt;Pl&lt;/sub&gt;, this is precisely the situation in effective field theory in which higher order terms would be expected to contribute and destroy the conditions for inflation. The absence of these higher order corrections can be seen as another sort of fine tuning. See ''e.g.'' {{Cite journal |first=Laila |last=Alabidi |title=Inflation models and observation |doi=10.1088/1475-7516/2006/05/016 |journal= Journal of Cosmology and Astroparticle Physics|volume= 2006|issue=5 |date=2006 |pages=016 |arxiv=astro-ph/0510441 |last2=Lyth |first2=David H |bibcode=2006JCAP...05..016A }}&lt;/ref&gt; This problem has not yet been resolved and some cosmologists argue that the small field models, in which inflation can occur at a much lower energy scale, are better models.&lt;ref&gt;See, ''e.g.'' {{Cite journal |title=What would we learn by detecting a gravitational wave signal in the cosmic microwave background anisotropy? |doi=10.1103/PhysRevLett.78.1861 |first=David H. |last=Lyth |journal=Physical Review Letters |volume=78 |issue=10 |pages=1861–3 |date=1997 |arxiv=hep-ph/9606387 |url=http://www.slac.stanford.edu/spires/find/hep/www?rawcmd=FIND+EPRINT+HEP-PH/9606387 |archive-url=https://archive.is/20120629010941/http://www.slac.stanford.edu/spires/find/hep/www?rawcmd=FIND+EPRINT+HEP-PH/9606387 |url-status=dead |archive-date=2012-06-29 |bibcode=1997PhRvL..78.1861L }}&lt;/ref&gt; While inflation depends on quantum field theory (and the [[semiclassical gravity|semiclassical approximation]] to [[quantum gravity]]) in an important way, it has not been completely reconciled with these theories.

[[Robert Brandenberger|Brandenberger]] commented on fine-tuning in another situation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite arXiv |title=Challenges for inflationary cosmology (10th International Symposium on Particles, Strings and Cosmology) |first=Robert H. |last=Brandenberger |date=November 2004 |eprint=astro-ph/0411671}}&lt;/ref&gt; The amplitude of the primordial inhomogeneities produced in inflation is directly tied to the energy scale of inflation. This scale is suggested to be around 10&lt;sup&gt;16&lt;/sup&gt; [[GeV]] or 10&lt;sup&gt;−3&lt;/sup&gt; times the [[Planck energy]]. The natural scale is naïvely the Planck scale so this small value could be seen as another form of fine-tuning (called a [[hierarchy problem]]): the energy density given by the scalar potential is down by 10&lt;sup&gt;−12&lt;/sup&gt; compared to the [[Planck density]]. This is not usually considered to be a critical problem, however, because the scale of inflation corresponds naturally to the scale of gauge unification.

===Eternal inflation===
{{Main|Eternal inflation}}

In many models, the inflationary phase of the Universe's expansion lasts forever in at least some regions of the Universe. This occurs because inflating regions expand very rapidly, reproducing themselves. Unless the rate of decay to the non-inflating phase is sufficiently fast, new inflating regions are produced more rapidly than non-inflating regions. In such models, most of the volume of the Universe is continuously inflating at any given time.

All models of eternal inflation produce an infinite, hypothetical multiverse, typically a fractal. The multiverse theory has created significant dissension in the scientific community about the viability of the inflationary model.

[[Paul Steinhardt]], one of the original architects of the inflationary model, introduced the first example of eternal inflation in 1983.&lt;ref name=&quot;steinhardt&quot; &gt;{{cite book |editor1-last=Gibbons |editor1-first= Gary W. |editor1-link= Gary Gibbons |editor2-first=Stephen W. |editor2-last=Hawking |editor3-last=Siklos |editor3-first= S.T.C. |title=&quot;Natural Inflation,&quot; in The Very Early Universe |publisher=Cambridge University Press |pages= 251–66 |year=1983 |isbn=978-0-521-31677-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; He showed that the inflation could proceed forever by producing bubbles of non-inflating space filled with hot matter and radiation surrounded by empty space that continues to inflate. The bubbles could not grow fast enough to keep up with the inflation. Later that same year, [[Alexander Vilenkin]] showed that eternal inflation is generic.&lt;ref name=&quot;vilenkin&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Vilenkin |first1=Alexander |year=1983 |title=Birth of Inflationary Universes |journal=Physical Review D |volume=27 |issue=12 |pages=2848–2855 |doi=10.1103/PhysRevD.27.2848 |bibcode=1983PhRvD..27.2848V }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although new inflation is classically rolling down the potential, quantum fluctuations can sometimes lift it to previous levels. These regions in which the inflaton fluctuates upwards expand much faster than regions in which the inflaton has a lower potential energy, and tend to dominate in terms of physical volume. It has been shown that any inflationary theory with an unbounded potential is eternal. There are well-known theorems that this steady state cannot continue forever into the past. Inflationary spacetime, which is similar to de Sitter space, is incomplete without a contracting region. However, unlike de Sitter space, fluctuations in a contracting inflationary space collapse to form a gravitational singularity, a point where densities become infinite. Therefore, it is necessary to have a theory for the Universe's initial conditions.

In eternal inflation, regions with inflation have an exponentially growing volume, while regions that are not inflating don't. This suggests that the volume of the inflating part of the Universe in the global picture is always unimaginably larger than the part that has stopped inflating, even though inflation eventually ends as seen by any single pre-inflationary observer. Scientists disagree about how to assign a probability distribution to this hypothetical anthropic landscape. If the probability of different regions is counted by volume, one should expect that inflation will never end or applying boundary conditions that a local observer exists to observe it, that inflation will end as late as possible.

Some physicists believe this paradox can be resolved by weighting observers by their pre-inflationary volume. Others believe that there is no resolution to the paradox and that the multiverse is a critical flaw in the inflationary paradigm. Paul Steinhardt, who first introduced the eternal inflationary model,&lt;ref name=&quot;steinhardt&quot;/&gt; later became one of its most vocal critics for this reason.&lt;ref name= &quot;Inflation Debate&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author=Steinhardt, Paul J. |title=Inflation Debate: Is the theory at the heart of modern cosmology deeply flawed? |journal=Scientific American |date=April 2011 |url=http://www.physics.princeton.edu/~steinh/0411036.pdf |doi=10.1038/scientificamerican0411-36 |pmid=21495480 |volume=304 |issue=4 |pages=36–43|bibcode = 2011SciAm.304d..36S }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.physics.princeton.edu/~steinh/vaasrev.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;https://www.cfa.harvard.edu/~loeb/sciam3.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

===Initial conditions===
Some physicists have tried to avoid the initial conditions problem by proposing models for an eternally inflating universe with no origin.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |title=Does inflation provide natural initial conditions for the universe? |first=Sean M. |last=Carroll |journal= General Relativity and Gravitation|volume=37 |issue=10 |pages=1671–4 |date=2005 |arxiv=gr-qc/0505037 |doi=10.1007/s10714-005-0148-2 |last2=Chen |first2=Jennifer |bibcode=2005GReGr..37.1671C }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite arXiv |title=Spontaneous inflation and the origin of the arrow of time |first=Sean M. |last=Carroll |eprint=hep-th/0410270 |author2=Jennifer Chen |date=2004 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first1=Anthony |last1=Aguirre |first2= Steven |last2=Gratton |title=Inflation without a beginning: A null boundary proposal |journal= Physical Review D |volume=67 |date=2003 |page= 083515 |arxiv=gr-qc/0301042 |doi=10.1103/PhysRevD.67.083515 |issue=8 |bibcode=2003PhRvD..67h3515A }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first1=Anthony |last1=Aguirre |first2= Steven |last2=Gratton |title=Steady-State Eternal Inflation |journal= Physical Review D |volume=65 |date=2002 |page= 083507 |arxiv=astro-ph/0111191 |bibcode=2002PhRvD..65h3507A |doi=10.1103/PhysRevD.65.083507 |issue=8 |url=http://cds.cern.ch/record/526126 |type=Submitted manuscript }}&lt;/ref&gt; These models propose that while the Universe, on the largest scales, expands exponentially it was, is and always will be, spatially infinite and has existed, and will exist, forever.

Other proposals attempt to describe the ex nihilo creation of the Universe based on [[quantum cosmology]] and the following inflation. Vilenkin put forth one such scenario.&lt;ref name=&quot;vilenkin&quot; /&gt; [[Hartle–Hawking state|Hartle and Hawking]] offered the [[no-boundary proposal]] for the initial creation of the Universe in which inflation comes about naturally.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1103/PhysRevD.28.2960 |title=Wave function of the universe |date=1983 |last1=Hartle |first1=J. |last2=Hawking |first2=S. |journal=Physical Review D |volume=28 |issue=12 |pages=2960–2975 |bibcode=1983PhRvD..28.2960H }}; See also Hawking (1998).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;PHYS-20180502&quot;&gt;{{cite web |author=Staff ([[University of Cambridge]]) |title=Taming the multiverse—Stephen Hawking's final theory about the big bang |url=https://phys.org/news/2018-05-multiversestephen-hawking-theory-big.html |date=2 May 2018 |work=[[Phys.org]] |accessdate=2 May 2018 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;JHEP-20180420&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Hawking |first1=Stephen |last2=Hertog |first2=Thomas |authorlink1=Stephen Hawking |authorlink2=Thomas Hertog |title=A smooth exit from eternal inflation? |arxiv=1707.07702 |date=20 April 2018 |journal=[[Journal of High Energy Physics]] |volume=2018 |issue=4 |pages=147 |doi=10.1007/JHEP04(2018)147|bibcode=2018JHEP...04..147H }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;JHEP-20180420pdf&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Hawking |first1=Stephen |last2=Hertog |first2=Thomas |authorlink1=Stephen Hawking |authorlink2=Thomas Hertog |title=A smooth exit from eternal inflation |arxiv=1707.07702 |date=20 April 2018 |journal=[[Journal of High Energy Physics]]  |volume=2018 |issue=4 |doi=10.1007/JHEP04(2018)147|bibcode=2018JHEP...04..147H }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Guth described the inflationary universe as the &quot;ultimate free lunch&quot;:&lt;ref&gt;Hawking (1998), p. 129.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[q:Alan Guth|Wikiquote]]&lt;/ref&gt; new universes, similar to our own, are continually produced in a vast inflating background. Gravitational interactions, in this case, circumvent (but do not violate) the [[first law of thermodynamics]] ([[energy conservation]]) and the [[second law of thermodynamics]] ([[entropy]] and the [[arrow of time]] problem). However, while there is consensus that this solves the initial conditions problem, some have disputed this, as it is much more likely that the Universe came about by a [[quantum fluctuation]]. [[Don Page (physicist)|Don Page]] was an outspoken critic of inflation because of this anomaly.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=Inflation does not explain time asymmetry |bibcode=1983Natur.304...39P |doi=10.1038/304039a0 |date=1983 |last1=Page |first1=Don N. |journal=Nature |volume=304 |issue=5921 |pages=39–41}}; see also [[Roger Penrose]]'s book [[The Road to Reality: A Complete Guide to the Laws of the Universe]].&lt;/ref&gt; He stressed that the thermodynamic [[arrow of time]] necessitates low [[entropy]] initial conditions, which would be highly unlikely. According to them, rather than solving this problem, the inflation theory aggravates it – the reheating at the end of the inflation era increases entropy, making it necessary for the initial state of the Universe to be even more orderly than in other Big Bang theories with no inflation phase.

Hawking and Page later found ambiguous results when they attempted to compute the probability of inflation in the Hartle-Hawking initial state.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |title=How probable is inflation? |first=S. W. |last=Hawking |date=1988 |volume=298 |issue=4 |pages=789–809 |journal=Nuclear Physics B |doi=10.1016/0550-3213(88)90008-9 |bibcode=1988NuPhB.298..789H |last2=Page |first2=Don N. }}&lt;/ref&gt; Other authors have argued that, since inflation is eternal, the probability doesn't matter as long as it is not precisely zero: once it starts, inflation perpetuates itself and quickly dominates the Universe.&lt;ref name=Steinhardt2011/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;SteinhardtTurok2007&quot;/&gt;{{rp |223–225}} However, Albrecht and Lorenzo Sorbo argued that the probability of an inflationary cosmos, consistent with today's observations, emerging by a random fluctuation from some pre-existent state is much higher than that of a non-inflationary cosmos. This is because the &quot;seed&quot; amount of non-gravitational energy required for the inflationary cosmos is so much less than that for a non-inflationary alternative, which outweighs any entropic considerations.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |first=Andreas |last=Albrecht |title=Can the universe afford inflation? |journal=Physical Review D |volume=70 |pages=063528 |date=2004 |arxiv=hep-th/0405270 |bibcode=2004PhRvD..70f3528A |doi=10.1103/PhysRevD.70.063528 |last2=Sorbo |first2=Lorenzo |issue=6 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another problem that has occasionally been mentioned is the trans-Planckian problem or trans-Planckian effects.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |first=Jerome |last2=Brandenberger |last=Martin |first2=Robert |title=The trans-Planckian problem of inflationary cosmology |journal=Physical Review D |volume=63 |date=2001 |issue=12 |pages=123501 |arxiv=hep-th/0005209 |doi=10.1103/PhysRevD.63.123501 |bibcode=2001PhRvD..63l3501M }}&lt;/ref&gt; Since the energy scale of inflation and the Planck scale are relatively close, some of the quantum fluctuations that have made up the structure in our universe were smaller than the Planck length before inflation. Therefore, there ought to be corrections from Planck-scale physics, in particular the unknown quantum theory of gravity. Some disagreement remains about the magnitude of this effect: about whether it is just on the threshold of detectability or completely undetectable.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |first=Jerome |last=Martin |title=Superimposed Oscillations in the WMAP Data? |journal=Physical Review D |volume=69 |issue=8 |date=2004 |pages=083515 |arxiv=astro-ph/0310382 |doi=10.1103/PhysRevD.69.083515 |last2=Ringeval |first2=Christophe |bibcode=2004PhRvD..69h3515M }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Hybrid inflation===
Another kind of inflation, called ''hybrid inflation'', is an extension of new inflation. It introduces additional scalar fields, so that while one of the scalar fields is responsible for normal slow roll inflation, another triggers the end of inflation: when inflation has continued for sufficiently long, it becomes favorable to the second field to decay into a much lower energy state.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite conference|last1= Brandenberger|first1= Robert H.|title= A Status Review of Inflationary Cosmology|year= 2001|arxiv=hep-ph/0101119|bibcode=2001hep.ph....1119B}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In hybrid inflation, one scalar field is responsible for most of the energy density (thus determining the rate of expansion), while another is responsible for the slow roll (thus determining the period of inflation and its termination). Thus fluctuations in the former inflaton would not affect inflation termination, while fluctuations in the latter would not affect the rate of expansion. Therefore, hybrid inflation is not eternal.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|arxiv=hep-th/0402051|last1=Linde|first1=Andrei|last2=Fischler|first2=W.|title=Prospects of Inflation|journal=Physica Scripta|volume=117|issue=T117|pages=40–48|year=2005|doi=10.1238/Physica.Topical.117a00056|bibcode = 2005PhST..116...56B }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|arxiv=hep-th/0406230|last1= Blanco-Pillado|first1= J. J.|title= Racetrack Inflation|journal= Journal of High Energy Physics|volume= 2004|issue= 11|pages= 063|last2=  Burgess|first2= C. P.|last3=  Cline|first3= J. M.|last4=  Escoda|first4= C.|last5=  Gomez-Reino|first5= M.|last6=  Kallosh|first6= R.|last7=  Linde|first7= A.|last8=  Quevedo|first8= F.|year= 2004|doi= 10.1088/1126-6708/2004/11/063|bibcode = 2004JHEP...11..063B }}&lt;/ref&gt; When the second (slow-rolling) inflaton reaches the bottom of its potential, it changes the location of the minimum of the first inflaton's potential, which leads to a fast roll of the inflaton down its potential, leading to termination of inflation.

===Relation to dark energy===
[[Dark energy]] is broadly similar to inflation and is thought to be causing the expansion of the present-day universe to accelerate. However, the energy scale of dark energy is much lower, 10&lt;sup&gt;−12&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;nbsp;GeV, roughly 27 [[orders of magnitude]] less than the scale of inflation.

===Inflation and string cosmology===
The discovery of [[Compactification (physics)#Flux compactification|flux compactification]]s opened the way for reconciling inflation and string theory.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |title=Towards inflation in string theory |first=Shamit |last=Kachru |display-authors=etal |date=2003 |journal= Journal of Cosmology and Astroparticle Physics|volume= 2003|pages=013 |arxiv=hep-th/0308055 |bibcode=2003JCAP...10..013K |doi=10.1088/1475-7516/2003/10/013 |issue=10 |citeseerx=10.1.1.264.3396 }}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Brane inflation'' suggests that inflation arises from the motion of [[D-brane]]s&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |arxiv=hep-ph/9812483 |last1=Dvali |first1=Gia |title=Brane Inflation |journal=Physics Letters B |volume=450 |issue=1999 |pages=72–82 |last2= Henry Tye |first2=S. -H. |year=1998 |doi=10.1016/S0370-2693(99)00132-X|bibcode=1999PhLB..450...72D }}&lt;/ref&gt; in the compactified geometry, usually towards a stack of anti-D-branes. This theory, governed by the ''Dirac-Born-Infeld action'', is different from ordinary inflation. The dynamics are not completely understood. It appears that special conditions are necessary since inflation occurs in tunneling between two vacua in the [[string landscape]]. The process of tunneling between two vacua is a form of old inflation, but new inflation must then occur by some other mechanism.

===Inflation and loop quantum gravity===
When investigating the effects the theory of [[loop quantum gravity]] would have on cosmology, a [[loop quantum cosmology]] model has evolved that provides a possible mechanism for cosmological inflation. Loop quantum gravity assumes a quantized spacetime. If the energy density is larger than can be held by the quantized spacetime, it is thought to bounce back.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Big Bang or Big Bounce?: New Theory on the Universe's Birth |url=http://www.scientificamerican.com/article/big-bang-or-big-bounce/ |accessdate=2015-08-31 |date=October 2008 |first=Martin |last=Bojowald}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Alternatives/adjuncts==
Other models explain some of the observations explained by inflation. However none of these &quot;alternatives&quot; has the same breadth of explanation and still require inflation for a more complete fit with observation. They should therefore be regarded as adjuncts to inflation, rather than as alternatives.

=== Big bounce ===
The big bounce hypothesis attempts to replace the cosmic singularity with a cosmic contraction and bounce, thereby explaining the initial conditions that led to the big bang.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |title=Sailing through the big crunch-big bang transition |journal=Physical Review D |volume=89 |issue=6 |pages=061302 |year=2014 |author1=Itzhak Bars |author2=Paul Steinhardt |author3=Neil Turok |arxiv=1312.0739 |quote=In the standard big bang inflationary model, the cosmic singularity problem is left unresolved and the cosmology is geodesically incomplete. Consequently, the origin of space and time and the peculiar, exponentially fine-tuned initial conditions required to begin inflation are not explained. In a recent series of papers, we have shown how to construct the complete set of homogeneous classical cosmological solutions of the standard model coupled to gravity, in which the cosmic singularity is replaced by a bounce: the smooth transition from contraction and big crunch to big bang and expansion. |doi=10.1103/PhysRevD.89.061302 |bibcode=2014PhRvD..89f1302B }}&lt;/ref&gt; The flatness and horizon problems are naturally solved in the [[Einstein–Cartan theory|Einstein-Cartan]]-Sciama-Kibble theory of gravity, without needing an exotic form of matter or free parameters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Poplawski, N. J. |date=2010 |title=Cosmology with torsion: An alternative to cosmic inflation |journal=Physics Letters B |volume=694 |issue=3 |pages=181–185 |doi=10.1016/j.physletb.2010.09.056 |arxiv=1007.0587 |bibcode=2010PhLB..694..181P }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Poplawski, N. |date=2012 |title=Nonsingular, big-bounce cosmology from spinor-torsion coupling |journal=Physical Review D |volume=85 |issue=10 |pages=107502 |doi=10.1103/PhysRevD.85.107502 |arxiv=1111.4595 |bibcode=2012PhRvD..85j7502P }}&lt;/ref&gt; This theory extends general relativity by removing a constraint of the symmetry of the affine connection and regarding its antisymmetric part, the [[torsion tensor]], as a dynamical variable. The minimal coupling between torsion and [[Dirac spinor]]s generates a spin-spin interaction that is significant in fermionic matter at extremely high densities. Such an interaction averts the unphysical Big Bang singularity, replacing it with a cusp-like bounce at a finite minimum scale factor, before which the Universe was contracting. The rapid expansion immediately after the [[Big Bounce]] explains why the present Universe at largest scales appears spatially flat, homogeneous and isotropic. As the density of the Universe decreases, the effects of torsion weaken and the Universe smoothly enters the radiation-dominated era.

=== Ekpyrotic and cyclic models ===
{{unreferenced section|date=November 2016}}
The [[ekpyrotic]] and [[cyclic model]]s are also considered adjuncts to inflation. These models solve the [[horizon problem]] through an expanding epoch well ''before'' the Big Bang, and then generate the required spectrum of primordial density perturbations during a contracting phase leading to a [[Big Crunch]]. The Universe passes through the Big Crunch and emerges in a hot [[Big Bang]] phase. In this sense they are reminiscent of [[Richard Chace Tolman]]'s [[oscillatory universe]]; in Tolman's model, however, the total age of the Universe is necessarily finite, while in these models this is not necessarily so. Whether the correct spectrum of density fluctuations can be produced, and whether the Universe can successfully navigate the Big Bang/Big Crunch transition, remains a topic of controversy and current research. Ekpyrotic models avoid the [[magnetic monopole]] problem as long as the temperature at the Big Crunch/Big Bang transition remains below the Grand Unified Scale, as this is the temperature required to produce magnetic monopoles in the first place. As things stand, there is no evidence of any 'slowing down' of the expansion, but this is not surprising as each cycle is expected to last on the order of a trillion years.

=== Varying ''c'' ===
Another adjunct, the [[varying speed of light]] model was offered by [[Jean-Pierre Petit]] in 1988,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title= An interpretation of cosmological model with variable light velocity |author= J.P. Petit |journal= Modern Physics Letters A|volume= 3 |issue= 16 |year= 1988 |pages= 1527–1532 |doi= 10.1142/S0217732388001823 |bibcode= 1988MPLA....3.1527P |url= http://www.bigravitytheory.com/pdf/modern_physics_letters_a1.pdf |access-date= 24 December 2014 |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20150203223151/http://bigravitytheory.com/pdf/modern_physics_letters_a1.pdf |archive-date= 3 February 2015 |url-status= dead |df= dmy-all |citeseerx= 10.1.1.692.9603 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |title= Cosmological model with variable light velocity: the interpretation of red shifts |author= J.P. Petit |journal= Modern Physics Letters A|volume= 3 |issue= 18 |year= 1988 |pages= 1733–1744 |doi= 10.1142/S0217732388002099 |bibcode= 1988MPLA....3.1733P |url= http://www.bigravitytheory.com/pdf/modern_physics_letters_a2.pdf |access-date= 24 December 2014 |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20140718123926/http://bigravitytheory.com/pdf/modern_physics_letters_a2.pdf |archive-date= 18 July 2014 |url-status= dead |df= dmy-all |citeseerx= 10.1.1.692.9067 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title= Gauge cosmological model with variable light velocity. Comparizon with QSO observational data |author1= J.P. Petit |author2= M. Viton |journal= Modern Physics Letters A|volume= 4 |issue= 23 |year= 1989 |pages= 2201–2210 |doi= 10.1142/S0217732389002471 |bibcode= 1989MPLA....4.2201P |url= http://www.bigravitytheory.com/pdf/modern_physics_letters_a3.pdf |access-date= 24 December 2014 |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20150204010624/http://bigravitytheory.com/pdf/modern_physics_letters_a3.pdf |archive-date= 4 February 2015 |url-status= dead |df= dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title= Scale invariant cosmology |author1= P. Midy |author2= J.P. Petit |issue= 8 |year= 1989 |pages= 271–280 |url= http://www.bigravitytheory.com/pdf/scale_inv.pdf |access-date= 24 December 2014 |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20140717164810/http://bigravitytheory.com/pdf/scale_inv.pdf |archive-date= 17 July 2014 |url-status= dead |df= dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[John Moffat (physicist)|John Moffat]] in 1992,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title= Superluminary Universe: A Possible Solution to the Initial Value Problem in Cosmology |author= J. Moffat |journal= International Journal of Modern Physics D|volume= 2 |issue= 3 |year=1993 |pages=351–366 |doi= 10.1142/S0218271893000246 |arxiv=gr-qc/9211020 |bibcode=1993IJMPD...2..351M |citeseerx= 10.1.1.339.6182 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and the two-man team of [[Andreas Albrecht (cosmologist)|Andreas Albrecht]] and [[João Magueijo]] in 1998.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author= J.D. Barrow |title= Cosmologies with varying light-speed |year= 1998 |doi= 10.1103/PhysRevD.59.043515 |journal= Physical Review D |volume= 59 |issue= 4 |pages= 043515 |arxiv=astro-ph/9811022 |bibcode=1999PhRvD..59d3515B |citeseerx= 10.1.1.256.8442 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title= A time varying speed of light as a solution to cosmological puzzles |author1=A. Albrecht |author2=J. Magueijo |journal= Physical Review D|volume= 59 |issue=4 |pages= 043516 |year= 1999 |arxiv=astro-ph/9811018 |bibcode=1999PhRvD..59d3516A |doi=10.1103/PhysRevD.59.043516 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;local&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author= J. Magueijo |title= Covariant and locally Lorentz-invariant varying speed of light theories |journal= Physical Review D|volume= 62 |issue= 10 |year= 2000 |pages= 103521 |arxiv=gr-qc/0007036 |bibcode=2000PhRvD..62j3521M |doi=10.1103/PhysRevD.62.103521 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author= J. Magueijo |title= Stars and black holes in varying speed of light theories |journal= Physical Review D|volume= 63 |issue= 4 |year= 2001 |pages= 043502 |arxiv=astro-ph/0010591 |bibcode=2001PhRvD..63d3502M |doi=10.1103/PhysRevD.63.043502 |url= http://cds.cern.ch/record/473573 |type= Submitted manuscript }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author= J. Magueijo |title= New varying speed of light theories |journal= Reports on Progress in Physics|volume= 66 |year= 2003 |issue= 11 |pages= 2025–2068 |doi= 10.1088/0034-4885/66/11/R04 |arxiv=astro-ph/0305457 |bibcode=2003RPPh...66.2025M }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title= Faster Than the Speed of Light: The Story of a Scientific Speculation |author= J. Magueijo |publisher= Perseus Books Group |location= Massachusetts |year= 2003 |isbn= 978-0-7382-0525-0 |url= https://archive.org/details/fasterthanspeedo00magu }}&lt;/ref&gt; Instead of superluminal expansion the speed of light was 60 orders of magnitude faster than its current value solving the horizon and homogeneity problems in the early universe.

=== String gas cosmology ===
[[String theory]] requires that, in addition to the three observable spatial dimensions, additional dimensions exist that are curled up or [[compactification (physics)|compactified]] (see also [[Kaluza–Klein theory]]). Extra dimensions appear as a frequent component of [[supergravity]] models and other approaches to [[quantum gravity]]. This raised the contingent question of why four space-time dimensions became large and the rest became unobservably small. An attempt to address this question, called ''string gas cosmology'', was proposed by [[Robert Brandenberger]] and [[Cumrun Vafa]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1016/0550-3213(89)90037-0 |title=Superstrings in the early universe |date=1989 |last1=Brandenberger |first1=R |journal=Nuclear Physics B |volume=316 |issue=2 |pages=391–410 |bibcode=1989NuPhB.316..391B |last2=Vafa |first2=C. |url=http://www.to.infn.it/~gasperin/ps/brown673.ps |citeseerx=10.1.1.56.2356 }}{{dead link|date=January 2018 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt; This model focuses on the dynamics of the early universe considered as a hot gas of strings. Brandenberger and Vafa show that a dimension of [[spacetime]] can only expand if the strings that wind around it can efficiently annihilate each other. Each string is a one-dimensional object, and the largest number of dimensions in which two strings will [[Transversality (mathematics)|generically intersect]] (and, presumably, annihilate) is three. Therefore, the most likely number of non-compact (large) spatial dimensions is three. Current work on this model centers on whether it can succeed in stabilizing the size of the compactified dimensions and produce the correct spectrum of primordial density perturbations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first1=Thorsten |last1=Battefeld |first2= Scott |last2=Watson |title= String Gas Cosmology |journal=Reviews of Modern Physics |volume=78 |pages= 435–454 |date=2006 |arxiv=hep-th/0510022 |doi=10.1103/RevModPhys.78.435 |bibcode=2006RvMP...78..435B |issue=2 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Supporters admit that their model &quot;does not solve the entropy and flatness problems of standard cosmology ..... and we can provide no explanation for why the current universe is so close to being spatially flat&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first=Robert H. |last=Brandenberger |title=String Gas Cosmology and Structure Formation |journal= International Journal of Modern Physics A |volume=22 |pages=3621–3642 |date=2007 |arxiv=hep-th/0608121 |doi=10.1142/S0217751X07037159 |bibcode=2007IJMPA..22.3621B |first2=ALI |last3=Patil |first3=Subodh P. |last4=Vafa |first4=Cumrun |issue=21 |last2=Nayeri|url=http://cds.cern.ch/record/978863 |type=Submitted manuscript }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Criticisms==
Since its introduction by Alan Guth in 1980, the inflationary paradigm has become widely accepted. Nevertheless, many physicists, mathematicians, and philosophers of science have voiced criticisms, claiming untestable predictions and a lack of serious empirical support.&lt;ref name=Steinhardt2011/&gt; In 1999, John Earman and Jesús Mosterín published a thorough critical review of inflationary cosmology, concluding, &quot;we do not think that there are, as yet, good grounds for admitting any of the models of inflation into the standard core of cosmology.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Earman-Mosterín&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Earman |first1= John |first2=Jesús |last2=Mosterín |date=March 1999 |title=A Critical Look at Inflationary Cosmology |journal= Philosophy of Science |volume=66 |issue= 1 |pages= 1–49 |jstor=188736 |doi=10.1086/392675}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In order to work, and as pointed out by [[Roger Penrose]] from 1986 on, inflation requires extremely specific initial conditions of its own, so that the problem (or pseudo-problem) of initial conditions is not solved: &quot;There is something fundamentally misconceived about trying to explain the uniformity of the early universe as resulting from a thermalization process. [...] For, if the thermalization is actually doing anything [...] then it represents a definite increasing of the entropy. Thus, the universe would have been even more special before the thermalization than after.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Penrose, Roger (2004). ''The Road to Reality: A Complete Guide to the Laws of the Universe''. London: Vintage Books, p. 755. See also {{cite journal |last=Penrose |first= Roger |date=1989 |title=Difficulties with Inflationary Cosmology |journal=Annals of the New York Academy of Sciences |volume= 271 |pages= 249–264 |bibcode=1989NYASA.571..249P |doi=10.1111/j.1749-6632.1989.tb50513.x }}&lt;/ref&gt; The problem of specific or &quot;fine-tuned&quot; initial conditions would not have been solved; it would have gotten worse. At a conference in 2015, Penrose said that &quot;inflation isn't falsifiable, it's falsified. [...] [[BICEP and Keck Array|BICEP]] did a wonderful service by bringing all the Inflation-ists out of their shell, and giving them a black eye.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hložek&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |last=Hložek |first=Renée |date=12 June 2015 |title=CMB@50 day three |url=https://storify.com/reneehlozek/cmb-50-day-three |accessdate=15 July 2015 }}&lt;br /&gt;This is a collation of remarks from the third day of the [http://physics.princeton.edu/cmb50/home.shtml &quot;Cosmic Microwave Background @50&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171219102718/http://physics.princeton.edu/cmb50/home.shtml |date=19 December 2017 }} conference held at Princeton, 10–12 June 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;

A recurrent criticism of inflation is that the invoked inflaton field does not correspond to any known physical field, and that its [[potential energy]] curve seems to be an ad hoc contrivance to accommodate almost any data obtainable. [[Paul Steinhardt]], one of the founding fathers of inflationary cosmology, has recently become one of its sharpest critics. He calls 'bad inflation' a period of accelerated expansion whose outcome conflicts with observations, and 'good inflation' one compatible with them: &quot;Not only is bad inflation more likely than good inflation, but no inflation is more likely than either [...] Roger Penrose considered all the possible configurations of the inflaton and gravitational fields. Some of these configurations lead to inflation [...] Other configurations lead to a uniform, flat universe directly – without inflation. Obtaining a flat universe is unlikely overall. Penrose's shocking conclusion, though, was that obtaining a flat universe without inflation is much more likely than with inflation – by a factor of [[googolplex|10 to the googol]] (10 to the 100) power!&quot;&lt;ref name=Steinhardt2011&gt;{{cite journal |last=Steinhardt |first=Paul J. |year=2011 |title=The inflation debate: Is the theory at the heart of modern cosmology deeply flawed? |journal=Scientific American |volume=304 |issue=4 |pages=18–25|doi=10.1038/scientificamerican0411-36 |pmid=21495480 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;SteinhardtTurok2007&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author1=Paul J. Steinhardt |author2=Neil Turok |title=Endless Universe: Beyond the Big Bang |date=2007 |publisher=Broadway Books |isbn=978-0-7679-1501-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; Together with Anna Ijjas and [[Abraham Loeb]], he wrote articles claiming that the inflationary paradigm is in trouble in view of the data from the [[Planck (spacecraft)|Planck satellite]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Steinhardt2013&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Ijjas |first1= Anna |last2=Steinhardt |first2=Paul J. |last3=Loeb |first3=Abraham |title=Inflationary paradigm in trouble after Planck2013 |journal=Physics Letters B |volume=723 |issue= 4–5 |pages=261–266 |doi=10.1016/j.physletb.2013.05.023 |arxiv=1304.2785 |bibcode=2013PhLB..723..261I |year= 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Ijjas |first1= Anna |last2=Steinhardt |first2=Paul J. |last3=Loeb |first3=Abraham |title=Inflationary schism after Planck2013 |journal=Physics Letters B |volume=736 |pages=142–146 |doi=10.1016/j.physletb.2014.07.012 |bibcode=2014PhLB..736..142I |year= 2014 |arxiv=1402.6980 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Counter-arguments were presented by [[Alan Guth]], [[David Kaiser]], and [[Yasunori Nomura]]&lt;ref name=&quot;GKN&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Guth |first1= Alan H. |last2=Kaiser |first2=David I. |last3=Nomura |first3=Yasunori |title=Inflationary paradigm after Planck 2013 |journal=Physics Letters B|volume=733 |pages=112–119 |doi=10.1016/j.physletb.2014.03.020 |arxiv=1312.7619 |bibcode=2014PhLB..733..112G |year= 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and by [[Andrei Linde]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite arXiv |last1=Linde |first1= Andrei |title=Inflationary cosmology after Planck 2013 |eprint=1402.0526 |year= 2014 |class= hep-th }}&lt;/ref&gt; saying that &quot;cosmic inflation is on a stronger footing than ever before&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;GKN&quot;/&gt;

==See also==

* [[Brane cosmology]]
* [[Angular momentum#Conservation of angular momentum|Conservation of angular momentum]]
* [[Cosmology]]
* [[Dark flow]]
* [[Doughnut theory of the universe]]
* [[Hubble's law]]
* [[Non-minimally coupled inflation]]
* [[Nonlinear optics]]
* [[Varying speed of light]]
* [[Warm inflation]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist |30em}}

==References==
* {{Cite book |first=Alan |last=Guth |authorlink=Alan Guth |title=The Inflationary Universe: The Quest for a New Theory of Cosmic Origins |isbn=978-0-201-32840-0 |publisher=Perseus |date=1997|title-link=The Inflationary Universe  }}
* {{Cite book |first=Stephen |last=Hawking |authorlink=Stephen Hawking |title=A Brief History of Time |isbn=978-0-553-38016-3 |publisher=Bantam |date=1998|title-link=A Brief History of Time }}
* {{Cite book |first=Stephen |last=Hawking |author2=Gary Gibbons |authorlink2=Gary Gibbons |title=The Very Early Universe |publisher=Cambridge University Press |date=1983 |isbn=978-0-521-31677-4}}
* {{Cite book |first=Edward |last=Kolb |author2=Michael Turner |title=The Early Universe |publisher=Addison-Wesley |date=1988 |isbn=978-0-201-11604-5 }}
* {{Cite book |last=Linde |first=Andrei |authorlink=Andrei Linde |arxiv=hep-th/0503203 |title=Particle Physics and Inflationary Cosmology |journal=&lt;!-- --&gt;|series=Contemporary Concepts in Physics |volume=5 |pages=1–362 |year=2005 |isbn=978-3-7186-0490-6 |bibcode = 2005hep.th....3203L }}
* {{Cite journal |arxiv=hep-th/0503195 |last1=Linde |first1=Andrei |title=Inflation and String Cosmology |journal=Progress of Theoretical Physics Supplement |volume=163 |pages=295–322 |year=2006 |doi=10.1143/PTPS.163.295|bibcode=2006PThPS.163..295L }}
* {{Cite book |first=Andrew |last=Liddle |author2=David Lyth |title=Cosmological Inflation and Large-Scale Structure |publisher=Cambridge |date=2000 |isbn=978-0-521-57598-0}}
* {{Cite journal |first=David H. |last=Lyth |title=Particle physics models of inflation and the cosmological density perturbation |doi=10.1016/S0370-1573(98)00128-8 |date=1999 |journal= Physics Reports|volume=314 |issue=1–2 |pages=1–146 |arxiv=hep-ph/9807278 |bibcode=1999PhR...314....1L |last2=Riotto |first2=Antonio }}
* {{Cite book |first=Viatcheslav |last=Mukhanov |title=Physical Foundations of Cosmology |publisher=Cambridge University Press |date=2005 |isbn=978-0-521-56398-7 }}
* {{Cite book |first=Alex |last=Vilenkin |authorlink=Alex Vilenkin |title=Many Worlds in One: The Search for Other Universes |publisher=Hill and Wang |date=2006 |isbn=978-0-8090-9523-0 |url=https://archive.org/details/manyworldsinoneo00vile }}
* {{Cite book |first=P. J. E. |last=Peebles |authorlink=Philip James Edwin Peebles |title=Principles of Physical Cosmology |publisher=Princeton University Press |date=1993 |isbn=978-0-691-01933-8 |url=https://archive.org/details/principlesofphys00pjep }}

==External links==
* [http://nedwww.ipac.caltech.edu/level5/Guth/Guth_contents.html Was Cosmic Inflation The 'Bang' Of The Big Bang?], by Alan Guth, 1997
* {{cite journal |arxiv=astro-ph/9901124 |author1=Andrew R Liddle |title=An introduction to cosmological inflation |journal=High Energy Physics and Cosmology |pages=260 |year=1999|bibcode=1999hepc.conf..260L }}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20041120175509/http://www2.iap.fr/Conferences/Colloque/col2004/Docs/20040628_liddle.pdf update 2004] by Andrew Liddle
* {{cite journal |arxiv=hep-ph/0309238 |last1=Covi |first1=Laura |title=Status of observational cosmology and inflation |journal=Physics in Collision |pages=67 |year=2003|bibcode=2003phco.conf...67C }}
* {{cite journal |arxiv=hep-th/0311040 |last1= Lyth |first1= David H. |title= Which is the best inflation model? |journal= String Phenomenology 2003 |pages= 260 |year= 2003|bibcode= 2003stph.conf..260L }}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20061002183844/http://www.symmetrymag.org/cms/?pid=1000045 The Growth of Inflation] ''Symmetry'', December 2004
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20061002193415/http://www.symmetrymag.org/cms/?pid=1000037 Guth's logbook showing the original idea]
* [http://skyandtelescope.com/news/article_1697_1.asp WMAP Bolsters Case for Cosmic Inflation, March 2006]
* [http://www.nasa.gov/home/hqnews/2006/mar/HQ_06097_first_trillionth_WMAP.html NASA March 2006 WMAP press release]
* [[Max Tegmark]]'s ''[[Our Mathematical Universe]]'' (2014), [http://space.mit.edu/home/tegmark/pdf/inflation_excerpt.pdf &quot;Chapter 5: Inflation&quot;]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Inflation (Cosmology)}}
[[Category:Physical cosmology]]
[[Category:Inflation (cosmology)|Inflation (cosmology)]]
[[Category:1980 in science]]</text>
      <sha1>a287373svn8mpuavm3cn5jr4tic2zwj</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
