  <page>
    <title>Wikipedia:Status of the porting of U.S. Dept of State info</title>
    <ns>4</ns>
    <id>5353</id>
    <revision>
      <id>687597661</id>
      <parentid>340327062</parentid>
      <timestamp>2015-10-26T15:44:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Russ3Z</username>
        <id>104996</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>fix link to avoid redirect</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{info|This project is inactive. For a similar effort, see [[WP:LOCPROJ]].}}
Here's a list of the countries with info on [http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/ the Dept of State site].  The information at this site is in the public domain ''unless it explicitly says otherwise'' on whatever page you are viewing there.'' 

The CIA site and the Dept of State site don't cover all of the countries; each of them is missing info on various countries; also they are not in agreement on what name to link to the countries under--that is the source of the various anachronisms on the [[List of countries]] page.  Furthermore, they are not always in agreement on various figures including population and GDP, even (on occasion) when supposedly taken from the same year.  If you notice a discrepancy, it's probably best to use the more cautious figure.

[[user:-- April]] suggested adding bits on contentious relationships between countries, including e.g. the U.S. and Afghanistan, but not including the more U.S.-centric bits about countries with amicable relations (e.g. location of U.S. embassies in Jamaica, Ireland, etc.)

:''If anyone wants to help, please don't hesitate.  :-)''

*[[Afghanistan]] -- bits added under History, Economy, Demographics, Transportation, and Foreign relations
*[[Albania]] -- bits added under History, Politics, Economy, and Foreign relations
*[[Algeria]] -- bits added under History, Geography, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Military, and Foreign relations
*[[Andorra]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, and Foreign relations
*[[Angola]] -- bits added under History, Geography, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Military, and Foreign relations
*[[Antigua and Barbuda]] -- bits added under History, Politics, and Foreign relations
*[[Argentina]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Military, and Foreign relations
*[[Armenia]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Military, and Foreign relations
*[[Australia]] -- bits added under History, Politics, Economy, Military, and Foreign relations
*[[Austria]] -- added bits under Demographics, Politics, Economy, and Foreign relations
*[[Azerbaijan]] -- added bits under History, Politics, Economy, Military, and Foreign relations
*[[Bahamas]] -- added bits under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, and Foreign relations
*[[Bahrain]] -- added bits under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Military, and Foreign relations
*[[Bangladesh]] -- added bits under History, Politics, Economy, Military, and Foreign relations; moved para under &quot;Economy&quot; to &quot;Geography&quot;
*[[Barbados]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, and Foreign relations
*[[Belarus]] -- bits added under History, Politics, Economy, and Foreign relations.  '''did not''' add extensive section on the U.S.' efforts to assist militarily.
*[[Belgium]] -- bits added under History, Politics, Economy, and Foreign relations
*[[Belize]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations
*[[Benin]] -- bits added under History, Geography, Demographics, Politics, Economy, and Foreign Relations, though I suspect the [http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/6761.htm source page] may have been truncated, and so someone knowledgeable about Benin should check that &quot;Demographics&quot; and &quot;Politics&quot; are comprehensive
*[[Bermuda]] -- bits added under History, Politics, Economy, Communications, and Transportation; added parts of &quot;U.S.-Bermuda relations&quot; to Bermuda's main page.
*[[Bolivia]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Government, Foreign relations
*[[Bosnia and Herzegovina]] -- bits added under History, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations
*[[Botswana]] -- bits added under History, Politics, Economy, Transportation, Communications, Military, Foreign relations
*[[Brazil]] -- bits added under History, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations
*[[Brunei]] Darussalam -- bits added under History, Politics, Economy, Military, Foreign relations
*[[Bulgaria]] -- bits added under History, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations
*[[Burkina Faso]] -- bits added under History, Geography, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Transportation; put &quot;Foreign relations&quot; and p. of &quot;U.S.-Burkina Faso relations&quot; under Transnational Issues
*[[Burundi]] -- bits added under History, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations
*[[Cambodia]] -- bits added under History, Politics, Economy; created subpage &quot;Architecture&quot; and bits added there, Foreign relations
*[[Cameroon]] -- bits added under History, Politics, Economy, Military, Foreign relations
*[[Canada]] -- bits added under Government and Economy; put &quot;U.S.-Canada relations&quot; under Transnational Issues
*[[Cape Verde]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Geography, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations
*[[Cayman Islands]] -- not a country, but so what? I'm not keeping several lists to get this done -- bits added under History, Politics, and Economy
*[[Central African Republic]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Military, Foreign relations
*[[Chad]] -- bits added under History, Geography, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Military, Foreign relations
*[[Chile]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Military, Foreign relations
*[[Peoples Republic of China]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Military, Foreign relations. Left quite a lot of info on U.S.-China relations unadded, available [http://www.state.gov/r/pa/bgn/index.cfm?docid=2742 here] if anyone's interested in adding it
*[[Colombia]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, and Military, and created &quot;Foreign relations.&quot; bits from U.S.-Columbia relations in re: trade added to the Economy page.
*[[Comoros]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Military, and Foreign relations
*[[Democratic Republic of the Congo]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations
*[[Republic of the Congo]] -- bits added under History, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations
*[[Costa Rica]] -- bits added under Demographics, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations
*[[Ivory Coast]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations
*[[Croatia]] -- bits added under History, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations
*[[Cuba]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations
*[[Cyprus]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, and Foreign relations
*[[Czech Republic]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, and Military, and created &quot;Foreign relations.&quot;
*[[Denmark]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Military, Foreign relations
*[[Djibouti]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, and Foreign relations
*[[Dominica]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations
**at this point I've quit adding the &quot;current govt officials&quot; bits as they won't generally be timely for long; also I'm not adding the &quot;embassy in U.S. bits&quot; as I haven't added e.g. &quot;embassy in UK&quot; or &quot;embassy in Greenland&quot; bits
*[[Dominican Republic]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations
*[[Ecuador]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations
*[[El Salvador]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations
*[[Equatorial Guinea]] -- bits added under History, Geography, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations
*[[Eritrea]] -- bits added under History, Geography, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Military, Foreign relations
*[[Estonia]] -- bits added under History, Geography, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Military, Foreign relations
*[[Ethiopia]] -- bits added under History, Geography, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Military, Foreign relations
*[[Fiji]] -- bits added under History, Geography, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations
*[[Finland]] -- bits added under History, Politics, Economy, Military, Foreign relations
*[[France]] -- bits added under History, Politics, Economy, Military, Foreign relations
*[[Gabon]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Military, Foreign relations
*[[The Gambia]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Military, Foreign relations
*[[Georgia (country)|Georgia]] -- bits added under History, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations
*[[Germany]] -- bits added under Demographics, Politics, Economony, Transnational issues, [[History of Germany]].
*[[Ghana]] -- bits added under History, Geography, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations
*[[Greece]] -- bits added under History, Geography, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations
*[[Grenada]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations
*[[Guatemala]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Military, Foreign relations
*[[Guinea]] -- bits added under History, Geography, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Military, Foreign relations
*[[Guinea-Bissau]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, and Foreign relations
*[[Guyana]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations
*[[Haiti]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Economy, Foreign relations.  much history of the government of Haiti put under History, not Government.  Also parts of an extensive section on U.S.-Haiti relations were left unadded [http://www.state.gov/r/pa/bgn/index.cfm?docid=1982 here], though some of it was added to Economy and another part of it was added to Military
*[[Holy See]] -- bits added under [[Vatican City]]'s main page, as well as under its Government; put &quot;Foreign relations&quot; under its Transnational issues
*[[Honduras]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Military, Foreign relations
*[[Hong Kong]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations
*[[Hungary]] -- bits added under History, Politics, Economy, Military, Foreign relations
*[[Iceland]] -- bits added under History, Geography, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Transportation, Military, Foreign relations
*[[India]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Military, Foreign relations
*[[Indonesia]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy (including part but not all of U.S.-Indonesian relations), Military, Foreign relations
*[[Iran]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations
*[[Iraq]] -- bits added under History, Geography, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Military, Foreign relations
*[[Ireland]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy
*[[Israel]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Military, Foreign relations
*[[Italy]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Military (including part of U.S.-Italian relations), Foreign relations
*[[Jamaica]] -- bits added under History, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations
*[[Japan]] -- bits added under History, Geography, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations
*[[Jordan]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations
*[[Kazakhstan]] -- bits added under Demographics, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations; bits on environmental concern added to the Kazakhstan article itself
*[[Kenya]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations
*[[Kiribati]] -- bits added under History, Geography, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations
*[[Korea]] -- bits added to history from [http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/2792.htm the Dept of State's page on North Korea]
*[[Kuwait]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Military, and Foreign relations
*[[Kyrgyzstan]] -- bits added under History, Politics, Economy, and Foreign relations
*[[Laos]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations
*[[Latvia]] -- bits added under History, Geography, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Military, Foreign relations
*[[Lebanon]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations
*[[Lesotho]] -- bits added under History, Politics, Economy, Military, Foreign relations
*[[Liberia]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations
*[[Libya]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations
*[[Liechtenstein]] -- bits added under History, Politics, Economy
*[[Lithuania]] -- bits added under History, Geography, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Military, Foreign relations
*[[Luxembourg]] -- bits added under History, Politics, Economy, Military, Foreign relations
*[[Macau]] -- not fully independent, but oh well.  bits added under Demographics, Politics, Economy; section on History added to the subject's main page
*[[Madagascar]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations
*[[Malawi]] -- bits added under History, Geography, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations
*[[Malaysia]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Military, Foreign relations
*[[Maldives]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, and Foreign relations.
*[[Mali]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Military, Foreign relations (the &quot;HISTORICAL AND CULTURAL HIGHLIGHTS&quot; section was split and added into the History, Demographics, and Economy pages as seemed appropriate)
*[[Malta]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations
*[[Marshall Islands]] -- bits added under History, Geography, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations
*[[Mauritania]] -- bits added under History and Politics
*[[Mauritius]] -- bits added under History, Politics, Economy, Military, Foreign relations
*[[Mexico]] -- bits added under History, Politics, Economy, Communications, Transportation, Military, Foreign relations.  quite a bit on U.S.-Mexican relations left out.
*[[Federated States of Micronesia|Micronesia]]  -- bits added under History, Geography, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations
*[[Moldova]] -- bits added under Geography, Politics, Economy, Military, Foreign relations
*[[Monaco]] -- bits added under History, Geography, Politics, Economy, Demographics, Foreign relations
*[[Mongolia (country)|Mongolia]] -- bits added under History, Politics, Economy, Demographics, Foreign relations
*[[Morocco]] -- bits added under History, Politics, Economy, Demographics, Foreign relations
*[[Mozambique]] -- bits added under History, Politics, Economy, Demographics, Foreign relations
*[[Namibia]] -- bits added under History, Politics, Economy, Demographics, Military, Foreign relations
*[[Nepal]] -- bits added under History, Politics, Economy, Demographics, Military, Foreign relations
*[[Netherlands]] -- bits added under History, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations, Drugs policy page
*[[New Zealand]] -- bits added under History, Politics, , Demographics, Economy, Foreign relations; also added bits re: nuclear testing from ''U.S.-New Zealand relations'' page to the foreign relations here
*[[Nicaragua]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations
*[[Niger]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Military, Foreign relations
*[[Nigeria]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Economy, Military, Foreign relations
*[[North Korea]] -- bits added under Demographics, Politics, Economy, Military, Foreign relations; quite a bit of info about U.S.-North Korean relations left unadded for lack of knowledge enough to render it NPOV
*[[Norway]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations
*[[Oman]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Economy, Politics, Foreign relations
*[[Pakistan]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Economy, Politics, Military, Foreign relations
*[[Palau]] -- bits added under History, Geography, Demographics, Economy, Politics, Foreign relations
*[[Panama]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Economy, Politics, Military, Foreign relations
*[[Papua New Guinea]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Economy, Politics; some but not all of the &quot;Foreign relations&quot; section added (parts of it seem too U.S.-centric, and maybe I should have added less of it than I did.  I don't want to bias the 'pedia any more than it's biased already by being written predominantly by people from the U.S.)
*[[Paraguay]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Military, Foreign relations
*[[Peru]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations; part of the ''Demographics'' section broken off into the waiting (empty) page [[Culture of Peru]]
*[[Philippines]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations
*[[Poland]] -- bits added under Politics, Demographics, Economy, Military, Foreign relations; bits under '''History''' left unadded; I see there's been a lot of controversy around this page.  [http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/2875.htm The U.S. Department of State has a writeup of Poland's history] available to anyone who cares to incorporate it.
*[[Portugal]] -- bits added under Economy, Foreign relations
*[[Qatar]] -- bits added under History, Politics, Demographics, Economy, Military, Foreign relations
*[[Romania]] -- bits added under History, Politics, Geography, Economy, Demographics, Foreign relations
*[[Russia]] -- bits added under Politics, Economy, Demographics, Military, Foreign relations; &quot;population aging&quot; and &quot;HIV/AIDS&quot; put under demographics rather than &quot;Economy of&quot; because to follow the Dept of State's example seemed inhumane; &quot;human rights&quot; section put under &quot;politics of&quot; (because tucking it under &quot;foreign relations seemed quite the slight towards Russian residents); many bits available at [http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/3183.htm the Dept of State site] were '''not''' added to the several articles on Russian history and so await a more knowledgeable wikipedian.
*[[Rwanda]] -- bits added under History, Geography, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Military, Foreign relations
*[[Samoa]] -- bits added under History, Geography, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations
*[[San Marino]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations
*[[São Tomé and Príncipe]] -- bits added under History, Geography, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations
*[[Saudi Arabia]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations (including bits from U.S./Saudi relations, put under the heading &quot;human rights&quot;)
*[[Senegal]] -- bits added under History, Geography, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Military, Foreign relations
*[[Seychelles]] -- bits added under History, Geography, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations
*[[Singapore]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Communications, Transportation, Military, Foreign relations
*[[Slovakia]] -- bits added under History, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Military, Foreign relations
*[[Slovenia]] -- bits added under History, Geography, Demographics, Politics, Economy, Military, Foreign relations

----

Copied and pasted (but did not wikify) the text for the remainder (21 Dec 2003):
*[[Solomon Islands]]
*[[Somalia]]
*[[South Africa]]
*[[South Korea]]
*[[Spain]]
*[[Saint Kitts and Nevis]]
*[[Saint Lucia]]
*[[Saint Vincent and the Grenadines]]
*[[Suriname]]
*[[Swaziland]]
*[[Sweden]]
*[[Switzerland]]
*[[Syria]]
*[[Taiwan]]
*[[Tajikistan]]
*[[Tanzania]]
*[[Thailand]]
*[[Togo]]
*[[Tonga]]
*[[Trinidad and Tobago]]
*[[Tunisia]]
*[[Turkey]]
*[[Turkmenistan]] -- bits added under History, Politics, Economy, Foreign relations
*[[Tuvalu]]
*[[Uganda]]
*[[Ukraine]]
*[[United Arab Emirates]]
*[[United Kingdom]]
*[[Uruguay]]
*[[Uzbekistan]]
*[[Vanuatu]]
*[[Venezuela]]
*[[Vietnam]]
*[[Yemen]]
*[[Yugoslavia]]
*[[Zambia]]
*[[Zimbabwe]]

:''See also :'' [[Countries of the world]]

[[Category:Wikipedia maintenance|{{PAGENAME}}]]</text>
      <sha1>0q8gp7pxfltxt7enwa7kbxa8vipity6</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
