  <page>
    <title>Carbon nanotube</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5320</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942420506</id>
      <parentid>941079770</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-24T15:43:00Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Daniel Mietchen</username>
        <id>322970</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>{{Scholia}}</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Distinguish|Carbon fibers}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2016}}
[[Image:Chiraltube.png|thumb|right|A [[scanning tunneling microscopy]] image of a single-walled carbon nanotube.]]
[[Image:Kohlenstoffnanoroehre Animation.gif|right|thumb|Rotating single-walled zigzag carbon nanotube]]
{{Nanomaterials}}

'''Carbon nanotubes (CNTs)''' are tubes made of carbon with diameters typically measured in [[nanometers]].

Carbon nanotubes often refers to '''single-wall''' carbon nanotubes '''(SWCNTs)''' with diameters in the range of a nanometer. They were discovered independently by Iijima and {{thinspace|Ichihashi|&lt;ref name=Iijima2/&gt;}} and Bethune et al.&lt;ref name=Bethune/&gt; in carbon arc chambers similar to those used to produce [[fullerene]]s. Single-wall carbon nanotubes are one of the [[allotropes of carbon]], intermediate between [[fullerene]] cages and flat [[graphene]].

Although not made this way, single-wall carbon nanotubes can be thought of as cutouts from a two-dimensional [[Hexagonal tiling|hexagonal lattice]] of carbon atoms rolled up along one of the [[Bravais lattice]] vectors of the hexagonal lattice to form a hollow cylinder. In this construction, periodic boundary conditions are imposed over the length of this roll up vector to yield a lattice with helical symmetry of seamlessly bonded carbon atoms on the cylinder surface.&lt;ref name=Iijima1 /&gt;

Carbon nanotubes also often refer to '''multi-wall''' carbon nanotubes '''(MWCNTs)''' consisting of nested single-wall carbon nanotubes.&lt;ref name=Iijima1/&gt; If not identical, these tubes are very similar to Oberlin, Endo and Koyama's long straight and parallel carbon layers cylindrically rolled around a hollow tube.&lt;ref name=&quot;endo1&quot;/&gt; Multi-wall carbon nanotubes are also sometimes used to refer to double- and triple-wall carbon nanotubes.

Carbon nanotubes can also refer to tubes with an undetermined carbon-wall structure and diameters less than 100 nanometers. Such tubes were discovered by Radushkevich and Lukyanovich.{{thinspace|&lt;ref name=&quot;CVD&quot; /&gt;|&lt;ref name=&quot;carbon&quot; /&gt;}} While [[nanotube|nanotubes of other compositions]] exist, most research has been focused on the carbon ones. Therefore, the &quot;carbon&quot; qualifier is often left implicit in the acronyms, and the names are abbreviated '''NT''', '''SWNT''', and '''MWNT'''.

Carbon nanotubes can exhibit remarkable [[electrical conductivity]].{{thinspace|&lt;ref name=mintmire1/&gt;|&lt;ref name=Tans/&gt;}} They also have exceptional {{thinspace|[[tensile strength]]|&lt;ref name=&quot;tensile load 2000&quot;/&gt;}} and [[thermal conductivity]],{{thinspace|&lt;ref name=Bever/&gt;|&lt;ref name=Kim/&gt;}} because of their [[nanostructure]] and [[bond strength|strength]] of the bonds between carbon atoms. In addition, they can be chemically modified.&lt;ref name=Nikolaos/&gt; These properties are expected to be valuable in many areas of technology, such as [[electronics]], [[optics]], [[composite materials]] (replacing or complementing [[carbon fibers]]), [[nanotechnology]], and other applications of [[materials science]].

Individual carbon nanotubes naturally align themselves into &quot;ropes&quot; held together by relatively weak [[van der Waals force]]s. The length of a carbon nanotube produced by common production methods is often not reported, but is much larger than its diameter. Although rare, nanotubes half a meter long have been created, with a length-to-diameter ratio of more than 100,000,000:1.&lt;ref name=Zhang/&gt; For many purposes, the length of carbon nanotubes can be assumed to be infinite.

Rolling up a hexagonal lattice along different directions to form different single-wall carbon nanotubes shows that all of these tubes have helical and translational symmetry along the tube axis and many also have nontrivial rotational symmetry about this axis. In addition, most are [[chiral]], meaning the tube and its mirror image cannot be superimposed. This construction also allows single-wall carbon nanotubes to be labeled by a pair of small integers.&lt;ref name=Hamada/&gt;

A special group of achiral single-wall carbon nanotubes are [[metal]]lic,&lt;ref name=mintmire1/&gt; but all the rest are either small or moderate band gap [[semiconductor]]s.&lt;ref name=Hamada/&gt; These electrical properties, however, do not depend on whether the tube is rolled up above or below the graphene plane and hence are the same for a tube and its mirror image.&lt;ref name=Hamada/&gt;

{{toclimit|3}}

== Structure of single-walled tubes {{anchor|Structure}} ==
The structure of an ideal (infinitely long) single-walled carbon nanotube is that of a regular hexagonal lattice drawn on an infinite [[cylinder|cylindrical]] surface, whose vertices are the positions of the carbon atoms. Since the length of the carbon-carbon bonds is fairly fixed, there are constraints on the diameter of the cylinder and the arrangement of the atoms on it.&lt;ref name=&quot;sinnott&quot;&gt;
{{cite journal
 |author1=S. B. Sinnott |author2=R. Andreys
 |lastauthoramp=yes |title=Carbon Nanotubes: Synthesis, Properties, and Applications
 |journal=Critical Reviews in Solid State and Materials Sciences
 |volume=26 |issue=3 |pages=145–249
 |year=2001
 |doi=10.1080/20014091104189
|bibcode = 2001CRSSM..26..145S}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{unreferenced section|date=April 2019}}

===The zigzag and armchair configurations===

In the study of nanotubes, one defines a &quot;zigzag&quot; path on a graphene-like lattice as a [[path (graph theory)|path]] that turns 60 degrees, alternating left and right, after stepping through each bond. It is also conventional to define an &quot;armchair&quot; path as one that makes two left turns of 60 degrees followed by two right turns every four steps.

On some carbon nanotubes, there is a closed zigzag path that goes around the tube. One says that the tube is of the '''zigzag type''' or configuration, or simply is a '''zigzag nanotube'''. If the tube is instead encircled by a closed armchair path, it is said to be of the '''armchair type''', or an '''armchair nanotube'''.

{|
|[[File:ZigzagCNT.png|thumb|Zigzag nanotube]]
|[[File:ArmchairCNT.png|thumb|Armchair nanotube]]
|}

An infinite nanotube that is of the zigzag (or armchair) type consists entirely of closed zigzag (or armchair) paths, connected to each other.

===The (''n'',''m'') notation===
[[File:Nanotube strip +03 +01.pdf|thumb|right|A &quot;sliced and unrolled&quot; representation of a carbon nanotube as a strip of a graphene molecule, overlaid on diagram of the full molecule (faint background). The arrow shows the gap ''A2'' where the atom ''A1'' on one edge of the strip would fit in the opposite edge, as the strip is rolled up.]]
The zigzag and armchair configurations are not the only structures that a single-walled nanotube can have. To describe the structure of a general infinitely long tube, one should imagine it being sliced open by a cut parallel to its axis, that goes through some atom ''A'', and then unrolled flat on the plane, so that its atoms and bonds coincide with those of an imaginary graphene sheet—more precisely, with an infinitely long strip of that sheet.

The two halves of the atom ''A'' will end up on opposite edges of the strip, over two atoms ''A1'' and ''A2'' of the graphene. The line from ''A1'' to ''A2'' will correspond to the circumference of the cylinder that went through the atom ''A'', and will be perpendicular to the edges of the strip.

In the graphene lattice, the atoms can be split into two classes, depending on the directions of their three bonds. Half the atoms have their three bonds directed the same way, and half have their three bonds rotated 180 degrees relative to the first half. The atoms ''A1'' and ''A2'', which correspond to the same atom ''A'' on the cylinder, must be in the same class.

It follows that the circumference of the tube and the angle of the strip are not arbitrary, because they are constrained to the lengths and directions of the lines that connect pairs of graphene atoms in the same class.

[[File:Nanotube strip master.pdf|thumb|left|The basis vectors '''''u''''' and '''''v''''' of the relevant sub-lattice, the (n,m) pairs that define non-isomorphic carbon nanotube structures (red dots), and the pairs that define the enantiomers of the chiral ones (blue dots).]]
Let '''''u''''' and '''''v''''' be two [[linear dependency|linearly independent]] vectors that connect the graphene atom ''A1'' to two of its nearest atoms with the same bond directions. That is, if one numbers consecutive carbons around a graphene cell with C1 to C6, then '''''u''''' can be the vector from C1 to C3, and '''''v''''' be the vector from C1 to C5. Then, for any other atom ''A2'' with same class as ''A1'', the vector from ''A1'' to ''A2'' can be written as a [[linear combination]] ''n'' '''''u''''' + ''m'' '''''v''''', where ''n'' and ''m'' are integers. And, conversely, each pair of integers (''n'',''m'') defines a possible position for ''A2''.&lt;ref name=&quot;sinnott&quot; /&gt;

Given ''n'' and ''m'', one can reverse this theoretical operation by drawing the vector '''''w''''' on the graphene lattice, cutting a strip of the latter along lines perpendicular to '''''w''''' through its endpoints ''A1'' and ''A2'', and rolling the strip into a cylinder so as to bring those two points together. If this construction is applied to a pair (''k'',0), the result is a zigzag nanotube, with closed zigzag paths of 2''k'' atoms. If it is applied to a pair (''k'',''k''), one obtains an armchair tube, with closed armchair paths of 4''k'' atoms.

===Nanotube types===
Moreover, the structure of the nanotube is not changed if the strip is rotated by 60 degrees clockwise around ''A1'' before applying the hypothetical reconstruction above. Such a rotation changes the corresponding pair (''n'',''m'') to the pair (−2''m'',''n''+''m'').

It follows that many possible positions of ''A2'' relative to ''A1'' — that is, many pairs (''n'',''m'') — correspond to the same arrangement of atoms on the nanotube. That is the case, for example, of the six pairs (1,2), (−2,3), (−3,1), (−1,−2), (2,−3), and (3,−1). In particular, the pairs (''k'',0) and (0,''k'') describe the same nanotube geometry.

These redundancies can be avoided by considering only pairs (''n'',''m'') such that ''n'' &gt; 0 and ''m'' ≥ 0; that is, where the direction of the vector '''''w''''' lies between those of '''''u''''' (inclusive) and '''''v''''' (exclusive). It can be verified that every nanotube has exactly one pair (''n'',''m'') that satisfies those conditions, which is called the tube's '''type'''. Conversely, for every type there is a hypothetical nanotube. In fact, two nanotubes have the same type if and only if one can be conceptually rotated and translated so as to match the other exactly.

Instead of the type (''n'',''m''), the structure of a carbon nanotube can be specified by giving the length of the vector '''''w''''' (that is, the circumference of the nanotube), and the angle ''α'' between the directions of '''''u''''' and '''''w''''', which may range from 0 (inclusive) to 60 degrees clockwise (exclusive). If the diagram is drawn with '''''u''''' horizontal, the latter is the tilt of the strip away from the vertical.

Here are some unrolled nanotube diagrams:
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Nanotube strip +03 +01.pdf|Chiral nanotube of the (3,1) type.
File:Nanotube strip +01 +03.pdf|Chiral nanotube of the (1,3) type, mirror image of the (3,1) type.
File:Nanotube strip +02 +02.pdf|Nanotube of the (2,2) type, the narrowest &quot;armchair&quot; one
File:Nanotube strip +03 000.pdf|Nanotube of the (3,0) type, the narrowest &quot;zigzag&quot; one

&lt;!--More examples to come --&gt;
&lt;/gallery&gt;

===Chirality and mirror symmetry===
A nanotube is [[chirality|chiral]] if it has type (''n'',''m''), with ''m'' &gt; 0 and ''m'' ≠ ''n''; then its [[enantiomer]] (mirror image) has type (''m'',''n''), which is different from (''n'',''m''). This operation corresponds to mirroring the unrolled strip about the line ''L'' through ''A1'' that makes an angle of 30 degrees clockwise from the direction of the '''''u''''' vector (that is, with the direction of the vector '''''u'''''+'''''v'''''). The only types of nanotubes that are [[achiral]] are the (''k'',0) &quot;zigzag&quot; tubes and the (''k'',''k'') &quot;armchair&quot; tubes.

If two enantiomers are to be considered the same structure, then one may consider only types (''n'',''m'') with 0 ≤ ''m'' ≤ ''n'' and ''n'' &gt; 0. Then the angle ''α'' between '''''u''''' and '''''w''''', which may range from 0 to 30 degrees (inclusive both), is called the &quot;chiral angle&quot; of the nanotube.

===Circumference and diameter===
From ''n'' and ''m'' one can also compute the circumference ''c'', which is the length of the vector '''''w''''', which turns out to be

: &lt;math&gt; c = \left|\boldsymbol{u}\right| \sqrt{(n^2 + n m + m^2)} \approx 246 \sqrt{((n+m)^2-n m)} &lt;/math&gt;

in [[picometre]]s. The diameter &lt;math&gt;d&lt;/math&gt; of the tube is then &lt;math&gt;c/\pi&lt;/math&gt;, that is

: &lt;math&gt;d \approx 78.3 \sqrt{((n+m)^2-n m)}&lt;/math&gt;

also in picometres. (These formulas are only approximate, especially for small ''n'' and ''m'' where the bonds are strained; and they do not take into account the thickness of the wall.)

The tilt angle ''α'' between '''''u''''' and '''''w''''' and the circumference ''c'' are related to the type indices ''n'' and ''m'' by
: &lt;math&gt; \alpha \;=\; \arg(n + m/2,\, m \sqrt{3}/2) \;=\; \mathop{\mathrm{arc}}\cos\frac{n + m/2}{c} &lt;/math&gt;
where arg(''x'',''y'') is the clockwise angle between the ''X''-axis and the vector (''x'',''y''); a function that is available in many programming languages as &lt;code&gt;atan2&lt;/code&gt;(''y'',''x''). Conversely, given ''c'' and ''α'', one can get the type (''n'',''m'') by the formulas
: &lt;math&gt;m = \frac{2 c}{\sqrt{3}}\sin \alpha \quad\quad n = c \cos\alpha - \frac{m}{2}&lt;/math&gt;
which must evaluate to integers.

==Physical limits==

===Narrowest nanotubes===
If ''n'' and ''m'' are too small, the structure described by the pair (''n'',''m'') will describe a molecule that cannot be reasonably called a &quot;tube&quot;, and may not even be stable. For example, the structure theoretically described by the pair (1,0) (the limiting &quot;zigzag&quot; type) would be just a chain of carbons. That is a real molecule, the [[Linear acetylenic carbon|carbyne]]; which has some characteristics of nanotubes (such as orbital hybridization, high tensile strength, etc.) — but has no hollow space, and may not be obtainable as a condensed phase. The pair (2,0) would theoretically yield a chain of fused 4-cycles; and (1,1), the limiting &quot;armchair&quot; structure, would yield a chain of bi-connected 4-rings. These structures may not be realizable.

The thinnest carbon nanotube proper is the armchair structure with type (2,2), which has a diameter of 0.3&amp;nbsp;nm. This nanotube was grown inside a multi-walled carbon nanotube. Assigning of the carbon nanotube type was done by a combination of [[high-resolution transmission electron microscopy]] (HRTEM), [[Raman spectroscopy]], and [[density functional theory]] (DFT) calculations.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal
 |last1=Zhao |first1=X.
 |year=2004
 |title=Smallest Carbon Nanotube is 3 Å in Diameter
 |journal=[[Phys. Rev. Lett.]]
 |volume=92 |issue=12 |page=125502
 |doi=10.1103/PhysRevLett.92.125502
 |pmid=15089683
 |last2=Liu
 |first2=Y.
 |last3=Inoue
 |first3=S.
 |last4=Suzuki
 |first4=T.
 |last5=Jones
 |first5=R.
 |last6=Ando
 |first6=Y.
 |bibcode = 2004PhRvL..92l5502Z |url=http://juser.fz-juelich.de/record/38262/files/48588.pdf
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The thinnest ''freestanding'' single-walled carbon nanotube is about 0.43&amp;nbsp;nm in diameter.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Torres-Dias |first1=Abraao C. |title=From mesoscale to nanoscale mechanics in single-wall carbon nanotubes |journal=Carbon |date=2017 |volume=123 |pages=145–150 |doi=10.1016/j.carbon.2017.07.036 |url= http://qmro.qmul.ac.uk/xmlui/handle/123456789/25311}}&lt;/ref&gt; Researchers suggested that it can be either (5,1) or (4,2) SWCNT, but the exact type of the carbon nanotube remains questionable.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smallest&quot;&gt;
{{cite journal
 |last1=Hayashi |first1=Takuya
 |year=2003
 |title=Smallest Freestanding Single-Walled Carbon Nanotube
 |journal=[[Nano Letters]]
 |volume=3 |issue=7 |pages=887–889
 |doi=10.1021/nl034080r
 |last2=Kim
 |first2=Yoong Ahm
 |last3=Matoba
 |first3=Toshiharu
 |last4=Esaka
 |first4=Masaya
 |last5=Nishimura
 |first5=Kunio
 |last6=Tsukada
 |first6=Takayuki
 |last7=Endo
 |first7=Morinobu
 |last8=Dresselhaus
 |first8=Mildred S.
|bibcode = 2003NanoL...3..887H}}&lt;/ref&gt; (3,3), (4,3), and (5,1) carbon nanotubes (all about 0.4&amp;nbsp;nm in diameter) were unambiguously identified using aberration-corrected [[high-resolution transmission electron microscopy]] inside double-walled CNTs.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal
 |last1=Guan |first1=L.
 |last2=Suenaga |first2=K.
 |last3=Iijima |first3=S.
 |year=2008
 |title=Smallest Carbon Nanotube Assigned with Atomic Resolution Accuracy
 |journal=[[Nano Letters]]
 |volume=8 |issue=2 |pages=459–462
 |doi=10.1021/nl072396j
 |pmid=18186659
|bibcode = 2008NanoL...8..459G}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Here are some tube types that are &quot;degenerate&quot; for being too narrow:
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Nanotube strip +01 000.pdf|Degenerate &quot;zigzag&quot; tube type (1,0)
File:Nanotube strip +02 000.pdf|Degenerate &quot;zigzag&quot; tube type (2,0)
File:Nanotube strip +01 +01.pdf|Degenerate &quot;armchair&quot; tube type (1,1)
File:Nanotube strip +02 +01.pdf|Possibly degenerate chiral tube type (2,1)
&lt;/gallery&gt;

===Length===
[[File:Cycloparaphenylene.PNG|thumb|Cycloparaphenylene]]

The observation of the ''longest'' carbon nanotubes grown so far, around 1/2&amp;nbsp;meter (550&amp;nbsp;mm long), was reported in 2013.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zhang&quot;/&gt; These nanotubes were grown on [[silicon]] substrates using an improved [[chemical vapor deposition]] (CVD) method and represent electrically uniform arrays of single-walled carbon nanotubes.&lt;ref name=wang2009long/&gt;

The ''shortest'' carbon nanotube can be considered to be the organic compound [[cycloparaphenylene]], which was synthesized in 2008.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal|date=4 December 2008
 |title=Synthesis, Characterization, and Theory of [9]-, [12]-, and [18]Cycloparaphenylene: Carbon Nanohoop Structures
 |journal=Journal of the American Chemical Society
 |doi=10.1021/ja807126u
 |pmid=19055403
 |pmc=2709987
 |volume=130
 |issue=52
 |pages=17646–17647
 |last1=Jasti
 |first1=Ramesh
 |last2=Bhattacharjee
 |first2=Joydeep
 |last3=Neaton
 |first3=Jeffrey B
 |last4=Bertozzi
 |first4=Carolyn R
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Density===
The ''highest density'' of CNTs was achieved in 2013, grown on a conductive [[titanium]]-coated [[copper]] surface that was coated with co-catalysts [[cobalt]] and [[molybdenum]] at lower than typical temperatures of 450&amp;nbsp;°C. The tubes averaged a height of 380&amp;nbsp;nm and a mass density of 1.6 g cm&lt;sup&gt;−3&lt;/sup&gt;. The material showed ohmic conductivity (lowest resistance ∼22 kΩ).&lt;ref name=kurz&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.kurzweilai.net/densest-array-of-carbon-nanotubes-grown-to-date |title=Densest array of carbon nanotubes grown to date |publisher=KurzweilAI |date=27 September 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Sugime | first1 = H. | last2 = Esconjauregui | first2 = S. | last3 = Yang | first3 = J. | last4 = d'Arsié | first4 = L. | last5 = Oliver | first5 = R. A. | last6 = Bhardwaj | first6 = S. | last7 = Cepek | first7 = C. | last8 = Robertson | first8 = J. | doi = 10.1063/1.4818619 | title = Low temperature growth of ultra-high mass density carbon nanotube forests on conductive supports |journal=Applied Physics Letters |volume=103 | issue = 7 | page = 073116 | year = 2013 |pmid= |pmc= |bibcode=2013ApPhL.103g3116S}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Variants ==
There is no consensus on some terms describing carbon nanotubes in scientific literature: both &quot;-wall&quot; and &quot;-walled&quot; are being used in combination with &quot;single&quot;, &quot;double&quot;, &quot;triple&quot;, or &quot;multi&quot;, and the letter C is often omitted in the abbreviation, for example, multi-walled carbon nanotube (MWNT). [[International Standards Organization]] uses single-wall or multi-wall in its documents.

&lt;!--[[Image:CNTnames.svg|thumb|left|The (''n'',''m'') nanotube naming scheme can be thought of as a vector ('''C'''&lt;sub&gt;h&lt;/sub&gt;) in an infinite graphene sheet that describes how to &quot;roll up&quot; the graphene sheet to make the nanotube. '''T''' denotes the tube axis, and '''a'''&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; and '''a'''&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; are the unit vectors of graphene in real space.]]--&gt;

=== Multi-walled ===
[[Image:Multi-walled Carbon Nanotube.png|thumb|upright|Triple-walled armchair carbon nanotube]]

Multi-walled nanotubes (MWNTs) consist of multiple rolled layers (concentric tubes) of graphene. There are two models that can be used to describe the structures of multi-walled nanotubes. In the ''[[Matryoshka doll|Russian Doll]]'' model, sheets of graphite are arranged in concentric cylinders, e.g., a (0,8) single-walled nanotube (SWNT) within a larger (0,17) single-walled nanotube. In the ''[[Scroll (parchment)|Parchment]]'' model, a single sheet of graphite is rolled in around itself, resembling a scroll of parchment or a rolled newspaper. The interlayer distance in multi-walled nanotubes is close to the distance between graphene layers in graphite, approximately 3.4 Å. The Russian Doll structure is observed more commonly. Its individual shells can be described as SWNTs, which can be metallic or semiconducting. Because of statistical probability and restrictions on the relative diameters of the individual tubes, one of the shells, and thus the whole MWNT, is usually a zero-gap metal.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal
 |last1=Das |first1=S.
 |year=2013
 |title=A review on Carbon nano-tubes - A new era of nanotechnology
 |journal=[[International Journal of Emerging Technology and Advanced Engineering]]
 |volume=3 |issue=3 |pages=774–781
 |issn=2250-2459
 |citeseerx=10.1.1.413.7576
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Double-walled carbon nanotubes (DWNTs) form a special class of nanotubes because their [[Morphology (biology)|morphology]] and properties are similar to those of SWNTs but they are more resistant to chemicals.{{Citation needed|date=May 2018}} This is especially important when it is necessary to graft chemical functions to the surface of the nanotubes ([[Surface functionalization|functionalization]]) to add properties to the CNT. Covalent functionalization of SWNTs will break some C=C [[double bond]]s, leaving &quot;holes&quot; in the structure on the nanotube and thus modifying both its mechanical and electrical properties. In the case of DWNTs, only the outer wall is modified. DWNT synthesis on the gram-scale by the [[CCVD]] technique was first proposed in 2003&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal
 |last1=Flahaut |first1=E.
 |year=2003
 |title=Gram-Scale CCVD Synthesis of Double-Walled Carbon Nanotubes
 |journal=[[Chemical Communications]]
 |volume=12 |issue=12 |pages=1442–1443
 |doi=10.1039/b301514a
 |pmid=12841282
 |last2=Bacsa
 |first2=Revathi
 |last3=Peigney
 |first3=Alain
 |last4=Laurent
 |first4=Christophe
 |url=http://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-00926035
}}&lt;/ref&gt; from the selective reduction of oxide solutions in methane and hydrogen.

The telescopic motion ability of inner shells&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal
 |last1=Cumings |first1=J.
 |last2=Zettl |first2=A.
 |year=2000
 |title=Low-Friction Nanoscale Linear Bearing Realized from Multiwall Carbon Nanotubes
 |journal=Science
 |volume=289 |issue=5479 |pages=602–604
 |doi=10.1126/science.289.5479.602
 |pmid=10915618
|bibcode = 2000Sci...289..602C}}&lt;/ref&gt; and their unique mechanical properties&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal
 |last=Treacy |first=M.M.J.
 |last2=Ebbesen |first2=T.W.
 |last3=Gibson |first3=J.M.
 |year=1996
 |title=Exceptionally high Young's modulus observed for individual carbon nanotubes
 |journal=Nature
 |volume=381 |issue=6584 |pages=678–680
 |doi=10.1038/381678a0
|bibcode = 1996Natur.381..678T}}&lt;/ref&gt; will permit the use of multi-walled nanotubes as the main movable arms in upcoming nanomechanical devices.{{Speculation inline|date=May 2018}} The retraction force that occurs to telescopic motion is caused by the [[Lennard-Jones interaction]] between shells, and its value is about 1.5&amp;nbsp;nN.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal
 |last=Zavalniuk |first=V.
 |last2=Marchenko |first2=S.
 |year=2011
 |title=Theoretical analysis of telescopic oscillations in multi-walled carbon nanotubes
 |journal=Low Temperature Physics
 |volume=37 |issue=4 |pages=337–342
 |arxiv=0903.2461
 |doi=10.1063/1.3592692
 |bibcode = 2011LTP....37..337Z |url=http://dspace.nbuv.gov.ua/xmlui/bitstream/123456789/118539/1/12-Zavalniuk.pdf
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Junctions and crosslinking ===

[[File:Nanotube junction.jpg|thumb|Transmission electron microscope image of carbon nanotube junction]] Junctions between two or more nanotubes have been widely discussed theoretically.&lt;ref name=Chernozatonskii &gt;{{cite journal | last = Chernozatonskii | first = L.A. |year=1992 |title=Carbon nanotube connectors and planar jungle gyms |journal=[[Physics Letters A]] | volume = 172 | issue = 3 | pages = 173–176 | doi=10.1016/0375-9601(92)90978-u| bibcode = 1992PhLA..172..173C}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name= Menon &gt;{{cite journal |last=Menon |first = M. | year = 1997| title = Carbon Nanotube &quot;T Junctions&quot;: Nanoscale Metal-Semiconductor-Metal Contact Devices| journal = [[Physical Review Letters]] | volume = 79 | issue = 22 | pages = 4453–4456 | doi=10.1103/physrevlett.79.4453 | bibcode=1997PhRvL..79.4453M}}&lt;/ref&gt; Such junctions are quite frequently observed in samples prepared by [[electric arc|arc discharge]] as well as by [[chemical vapor deposition]]. The electronic properties of such junctions were first considered theoretically by Lambin et al.,&lt;ref name=Lambin&gt;{{cite journal | last = Lambin | first = P. | year = 1996| title = Atomic structure and electronic properties of bent carbon nanotubes | journal = [[Synth. Met.]] | volume = 77 | issue = 1–3 | pages = 249–1254 | doi=10.1016/0379-6779(96)80097-x}}&lt;/ref&gt; who pointed out that a connection between a metallic tube and a semiconducting one would represent a nanoscale heterojunction. Such a junction could therefore form a component of a nanotube-based electronic circuit. The adjacent image shows a junction between two multiwalled nanotubes.
Junctions between nanotubes and graphene have been considered theoretically&lt;ref name=Ma&gt;{{cite journal |last=Ma | first = K.L. | year = 2011| title = Electronic transport properties of junctions between carbon nanotubes and graphene nanoribbons| journal = [[European Physical Journal B]] | volume = 83 | issue = 4 |pages=487–492 | doi=10.1140/epjb/e2011-20313-9| bibcode = 2011EPJB...83..487M}}&lt;/ref&gt; and studied experimentally.&lt;ref name=Harris&gt;{{cite journal |last = Harris | first = P.J.F.| year = 2016| title = The structure of junctions between carbon nanotubes and graphene shells |journal=[[Nanoscale (journal)|Nanoscale]]| volume = 8 | issue = 45| pages = 18849–18854 | doi=10.1039/c6nr06461b |pmid= 27808332 |url=http://centaur.reading.ac.uk/67327/1/NANOSCALE%20FOR%20CENTAUR.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nanotube-graphene junctions form the basis of [[pillared graphene]], in which parallel graphene sheets are separated by short nanotubes.&lt;ref name= Dimitrakakis &gt;{{ cite journal | last = Dimitrakakis| first = G. K. | year = 2008| title = Pillared graphene: a new 3-D network nanostructure for enhanced hydrogen storage| journal = [[Nano Lett.]] | volume = 8 | issue = 10 | pages = 3166–3170 | doi=10.1021/nl801417w | pmid=18800853| bibcode = 2008NanoL...8.3166D}}&lt;/ref&gt; Pillared graphene represents a class of [[Carbon nanotube#Three-dimensional carbon nanotube architectures|three-dimensional carbon nanotube architectures]].
[[Image:3D carbon scaffolds.PNG|thumb|3D carbon scaffolds]]
Recently, several studies have highlighted the prospect of using carbon nanotubes as building blocks to fabricate three-dimensional macroscopic (&gt;100&amp;nbsp;nm in all three dimensions) all-carbon devices. Lalwani et al. have reported a novel radical-initiated thermal crosslinking method to fabricate macroscopic, free-standing, porous, all-carbon scaffolds using single- and multi-walled carbon nanotubes as building blocks.&lt;ref name=&quot;PMID 23436939&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|year=2013|title=Fabrication and characterization of three-dimensional macroscopic all-carbon scaffolds|url=https://www.researchgate.net/publication/235718275|journal=Carbon|volume=53|pages=90–100|doi=10.1016/j.carbon.2012.10.035|pmc=3578711|pmid=23436939|first1=Lalwani, Gaurav, Andrea Trinward Kwaczala, Shruti Kanakia, Sunny C. Patel, Stefan Judex|last1=Balaji Sitharaman.}}&lt;/ref&gt; These scaffolds possess macro-, micro-, and nano-structured pores, and the porosity can be tailored for specific applications. These 3D all-carbon scaffolds/architectures may be used for the fabrication of the next generation of energy storage, supercapacitors, field emission transistors, high-performance catalysis, photovoltaics, and biomedical devices, implants, and sensors.&lt;ref name=&quot;PMID 25788440&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|year=2015|title=Porous three-dimensional carbon nanotube scaffolds for tissue engineering|url=https://www.researchgate.net/publication/273782031|journal=Journal of Biomedical Materials Research Part A|volume=103|issue=10|pages=3212–3225|doi=10.1002/jbm.a.35449|pmc=4552611|pmid=25788440|first1=Lalwani, Gaurav, Anu Gopalan, Michael D'Agati, Jeyantt Srinivas Sankaran, Stefan Judex, Yi-Xian Qin|last1=Balaji Sitharaman.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;noyce2&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | last=Noyce | first=Steven G. | last2=Vanfleet | first2=Richard R. | last3=Craighead | first3=Harold G. | last4=Davis | first4=Robert C. | title=High surface-area carbon microcantilevers | journal=Nanoscale Advances | volume=1 | issue=3 | date=1999-02-22 | doi=10.1039/C8NA00101D | pages=1148–1154 | url=https://pubs.rsc.org/en/content/articlehtml/2019/na/c8na00101d | accessdate=2019-05-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Other morphologies ===
[[Image:NanoBud.JPG|thumb|A stable [[Carbon nanobud|nanobud]] structure]]
[[Carbon nanobud]]s are a newly created material combining two previously discovered allotropes of carbon: carbon nanotubes and [[fullerene]]s. In this new material, fullerene-like &quot;buds&quot; are covalently bonded to the outer sidewalls of the underlying carbon nanotube. This hybrid material has useful properties of both fullerenes and carbon nanotubes. In particular, they have been found to be exceptionally good [[field electron emission|field emitters]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Nasibulin&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | last = Nasibulin | first = Albert G. | year = 2007 | title = A novel hybrid carbon material | journal = [[Nature Nanotechnology]] | volume = 2 | issue = 3 | pages = 156–161 | doi = 10.1038/nnano.2007.37 | url = http://tfy.tkk.fi/nanomat/PDF%20publications/nnano.2007.37.print.pdf | pmid = 18654245 | display-authors = 1 | last2 = Pikhitsa | first2 = Peter V. | last3 = Jiang | first3 = Hua | last4 = Brown | first4 = David P. | last5 = Krasheninnikov | first5 = Arkady V. | last6 = Anisimov | first6 = Anton S. | last7 = Queipo | first7 = Paula | last8 = Moisala | first8 = Anna | last9 = Gonzalez | first9 = David | bibcode = 2007NatNa...2..156N | access-date = 10 October 2016 | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20120226220035/http://tfy.tkk.fi/nanomat/PDF%20publications/nnano.2007.37.print.pdf | archive-date = 26 February 2012 |url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[composite material]]s, the attached fullerene molecules may function as molecular anchors preventing slipping of the nanotubes, thus improving the composite's mechanical properties.

A [[carbon peapod]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last2=Monthioux|first2=Marc|last3=Luzzi|first3=David E.|year=1998|title=Encapsulated C-60 in carbon nanotubes|journal=Nature|volume=396|issue=6709|pages=323–324|bibcode=1998Natur.396R.323S|doi=10.1038/24521|first1=Brian W.|last1=Smith}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last2=Luzzi|first2=D.E.|year=2000|title=Formation mechanism of fullerene peapods and coaxial tubes: a path to large scale synthesis|journal=Chem. Phys. Lett.|volume=321|issue=1–2|pages=169–174|bibcode=2000CPL...321..169S|doi=10.1016/S0009-2614(00)00307-9|last1=Smith|first1=B.W.}}&lt;/ref&gt; is a novel hybrid carbon material which traps fullerene inside a carbon nanotube. It can possess interesting magnetic properties with heating and irradiation. It can also be applied as an oscillator during theoretical investigations and predictions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last2=Goddard|first2=W.A.|last3=Zhao|first3=Y.|year=2006|title=Dynamic friction force in a carbon peapod oscillator|journal=Nanotechnology|volume=17|issue=22|pages=5691–5695|arxiv=cond-mat/0611671|bibcode=2006Nanot..17.5691S|doi=10.1088/0957-4484/17/22/026|last1=Su|first1=H.|url=https://authors.library.caltech.edu/6289/1/SUHnanotech06.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last2=Li|first2=C.M.|year=2010|title=An oscillator in a carbon peapod controllable by an external electric field: A molecular dynamics study|journal=Nanotechnology|volume=21|issue=3|page=035704|bibcode=2010Nanot..21c5704W|doi=10.1088/0957-4484/21/3/035704|pmid=19966399|last1=Wang|first1=M.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In theory, a nanotorus is a carbon nanotube bent into a [[torus]] (doughnut shape). Nanotori are predicted to have many unique properties, such as magnetic moments 1000 times larger than that previously expected for certain specific radii.&lt;ref name=&quot;nanotori&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|first=L.|last2=Guo|first2=G.|last3=Jayanthi|first3=C.|last4=Wu|first4=S.|year=2002|title=Colossal Paramagnetic Moments in Metallic Carbon Nanotori|journal=Phys. Rev. Lett.|volume=88|issue=21|page=217206|bibcode=2002PhRvL..88u7206L|doi=10.1103/PhysRevLett.88.217206|pmid=12059501|last1=Liu|url=http://ntur.lib.ntu.edu.tw/handle/246246/163841}}&lt;/ref&gt; Properties such as [[magnetic moment]], thermal stability, etc. vary widely depending on the radius of the torus and the radius of the tube.&lt;ref name=&quot;nanotori&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last2=Kuronen|first2=A.|last3=Kaski|first3=K.|year=2002|title=Carbon nanotube structures: Molecular dynamics simulation at realistic limit|url=http://www.princeton.edu/~msammalk/publications/cpc146_02.pdf|journal=[[Computer Physics Communications]]|volume=146|issue=1|pages=30–37|bibcode=2002CoPhC.146...30H|doi=10.1016/S0010-4655(02)00432-0|last1=Huhtala|first1=M.|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080627183309/http://www.princeton.edu/~msammalk/publications/cpc146_02.pdf|archivedate=27 June 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Graphenated carbon nanotube]]s are a relatively new hybrid that combines [[Graphite|graphitic]] foliates grown along the sidewalls of multiwalled or bamboo style CNTs. The foliate density can vary as a function of deposition conditions (e.g., temperature and time) with their structure ranging from a few layers of [[graphene]] (&lt; 10) to thicker, more [[graphite]]-like.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Parker|first=Charles B.|author2=Akshay S. Raut |author3=Billyde Brown |author4=Brian R. Stoner |author5=Jeffrey T. Glass |title=Three-dimensional arrays of graphenated carbon nanotubes|journal=J. Mater. Res.|year=2012|volume=27|series=7|pages=1046–1053 |doi=10.1557/jmr.2012.43|issue=7|bibcode = 2012JMatR..27.1046P}}&lt;/ref&gt; The fundamental advantage of an integrated [[graphene]]-CNT structure is the high surface area three-dimensional framework of the CNTs coupled with the high edge density of graphene. Depositing a high density of graphene foliates along the length of aligned CNTs can significantly increase the total [[Capacitance|charge capacity]] per unit of nominal area as compared to other carbon nanostructures.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Stoner|first=Brian R.|author2=Jeffrey T. Glass|title=Carbon nanostructures: a morphological classification for charge density optimization|journal=Diamond and Related Materials|year=2012|volume=23|pages=130–134|doi=10.1016/j.diamond.2012.01.034|bibcode = 2012DRM....23..130S}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Cup-stacked carbon nanotubes (CSCNTs) differ from other quasi-1D carbon structures, which normally behave as quasi-metallic conductors of electrons. CSCNTs exhibit semiconducting behavior because of the stacking microstructure of graphene layers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last2=Ren|first2=Wencai|last3=Chen|first3=Zhi-Gang|last4=Yin|first4=Lichang|last5=Li|first5=Feng|last6=Cong|first6=Hongtao|last7=Cheng|first7=Hui-Ming|year=2009|title=Semiconducting properties of cup-stacked carbon nanotubes|url=http://carbon.imr.ac.cn/file/Journal/2009/1249016438117.pdf|journal=Carbon|volume=47|issue=3|pages=731–736|doi=10.1016/j.carbon.2008.11.005|last1=Liu|first1=Q.|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150109002837/http://carbon.imr.ac.cn/file/Journal/2009/1249016438117.pdf|archivedate=2015-01-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Properties ==
Many properties of single-walled carbon nanotubes depend significantly on the (''n'',''m'') type, and this dependence is non-monotonic (see [[Optical properties of carbon nanotubes#Kataura plot|Kataura plot]]). In particular, the [[band gap]] can vary from zero to about 2 eV and the electrical conductivity can show metallic or semiconducting behavior.

=== Mechanical ===
{{Main|Mechanical properties of carbon nanotubes}}
[[Image:CNTSEM.JPG|thumb|A [[scanning electron microscopy]] image of carbon nanotube bundles]]
Carbon nanotubes are the strongest and stiffest materials yet discovered in terms of [[tensile strength]] and [[elastic modulus]]. This strength results from the covalent sp&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; bonds formed between the individual carbon atoms. In 2000, a multiwalled carbon nanotube was tested to have a tensile strength of {{convert|63|GPa}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;Strength and Breaking&quot;&gt;{{cite journal
 |last=Yu |first=M.-F.
 |year=2000
 |title=Strength and Breaking Mechanism of Multiwalled Carbon Nanotubes Under Tensile Load
 |journal=Science
 |volume=287 |issue=5453 |pages=637–640
 |doi=10.1126/science.287.5453.637
 |pmid=10649994
 |last2=Lourie
 |first2=O
 |last3=Dyer
 |first3=MJ
 |last4=Moloni
 |first4=K
 |last5=Kelly
 |first5=TF
 |last6=Ruoff
 |first6=RS
|bibcode = 2000Sci...287..637Y}}&lt;/ref&gt; (For illustration, this translates into the ability to endure tension of a weight equivalent to {{convert|6422|kgf}} on a cable with cross-section of {{convert|1|mm2}}). Further studies, such as one conducted in 2008, revealed that individual CNT shells have strengths of up to ≈{{convert|100|GPa}}, which is in agreement with quantum/atomistic models.&lt;ref name=&quot;B. Peng&quot;&gt;{{cite journal
 |last1=Peng |first1=B.
 |year=2008
 |title=Measurements of near-ultimate strength for multiwalled carbon nanotubes and irradiation-induced crosslinking improvements
 |journal=[[Nature Nanotechnology]]
 |volume=3 |issue= 10|pages=626–631
 |doi=10.1038/nnano.2008.211
 |pmid=18839003
 |last2=Locascio
 |first2=Mark
 |last3=Zapol
 |first3=Peter
 |last4=Li
 |first4=Shuyou
 |last5=Mielke
 |first5=Steven L.
 |last6=Schatz
 |first6=George C.
 |last7=Espinosa
 |first7=Horacio D.
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Because carbon nanotubes have a low density for a solid of 1.3 to 1.4&amp;nbsp;g/cm&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;,&lt;ref name=&quot;nanotubes for electronics&quot;&gt;{{cite journal
 |last=Collins |first=P.G.
 |year=2000
 |title=Nanotubes for Electronics
 |journal=[[Scientific American]]
 |volume=283
 |issue=6
 |pages=67–69
 |doi=10.1038/scientificamerican1200-62
 |pmid=11103460
 |bibcode=2000SciAm.283f..62C
}}&lt;/ref&gt; its [[specific strength]] of up to 48,000&amp;nbsp;kN·m·kg&lt;sup&gt;−1&lt;/sup&gt; is the best of known materials, compared to high-carbon steel's 154&amp;nbsp;kN·m·kg&lt;sup&gt;−1&lt;/sup&gt;.

Although the strength of individual CNT shells is extremely high, weak shear interactions between adjacent shells and tubes lead to significant reduction in the effective strength of multiwalled carbon nanotubes and carbon nanotube bundles down to only a few GPa.&lt;ref name=&quot;T. Filleter, R. A 2011&quot;&gt;{{cite journal
 |last1=Filleter |first1=T.
 |year=2011
 |title=Ultrahigh Strength and Stiffness in Cross-Linked Hierarchical Carbon Nanotube Bundles
 |journal=[[Advanced Materials]]
 |volume= 23|issue= 25|pages=2855–2860
 |doi=10.1002/adma.201100547
 |pmid=21538593
 |last2=Bernal
 |first2=R.
 |last3=Li
 |first3=S.
 |last4=Espinosa
 |first4=H.D.
}}&lt;/ref&gt; This limitation has been recently addressed by applying high-energy electron irradiation, which crosslinks inner shells and tubes, and effectively increases the strength of these materials to ≈60 GPa for multiwalled carbon nanotubes&lt;ref name=&quot;B. Peng&quot; /&gt; and ≈17 GPa for double-walled carbon nanotube bundles.&lt;ref name=&quot;T. Filleter, R. A 2011&quot; /&gt; CNTs are not nearly as strong under compression. Because of their hollow structure and high aspect ratio, they tend to undergo [[buckling]] when placed under compressive, torsional, or bending stress.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal
 |last1=Jensen |first1=K.
 |year=2007
 |title=Buckling and kinking force measurements on individual multiwalled carbon nanotubes
 |journal=[[Physical Review B]]
 |volume=76 |issue=19 |page=195436
 |doi=10.1103/PhysRevB.76.195436
 |last2=Mickelson
 |first2=W.
 |last3=Kis
 |first3=A.
 |last4=Zettl
 |first4=A.
|bibcode = 2007PhRvB..76s5436J}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On the other hand, there was evidence that in the radial direction they are rather soft. The first [[Transmission electron microscopy|transmission electron microscope]] observation of radial elasticity suggested that even [[van der Waals force]]s can deform two adjacent nanotubes. Later, [[nanoindentation]]s with an [[atomic force microscope]] were performed by several groups to quantitatively measure radial elasticity of multiwalled carbon nanotubes and tapping/contact mode [[atomic force microscopy]] was also performed on single-walled carbon nanotubes. Young's modulus of on the order of several GPa showed that CNTs are in fact very soft in the radial direction.

=== Electrical ===
[[Image:Carbon nanotube bands.gif|thumb|Band structures computed using tight binding approximation for (6,0) CNT (zigzag, metallic), (10,2) CNT (semiconducting) and (10,10) CNT (armchair, metallic).]]
Unlike graphene, which is a two-dimensional semimetal, carbon nanotubes are either metallic or semiconducting along the tubular axis. For a given (''n'',''m'') nanotube, if ''n'' = ''m'', the nanotube is metallic; if ''n'' − ''m'' is a multiple of 3 and n ≠ m and nm ≠ 0, then the nanotube is quasi-metallic with a very small band gap, otherwise the nanotube is a moderate [[semiconductor]].&lt;ref name=&quot;QuantumTransport&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|first=Edward A.|last=Laird|first2=Ferdinand|last2=Kuemmeth|first3=Gary A.|last3=Steele|first4=Kasper|last4=Grove-Rasmussen|first5=Jesper|last5=Nygård|first6=Karsten|last6=Flensberg|first7=Leo P.|last7=Kouwenhoven|title=Quantum Transport in Carbon Nanotubes|journal=[[Reviews of Modern Physics]]|volume=87|issue=3|pages=703–764|year=2015|doi=10.1103/RevModPhys.87.703|arxiv = 1403.6113 |bibcode = 2015RvMP...87..703L |url=https://repository.tudelft.nl/islandora/object/uuid%3A6a686f0b-1314-42ad-b6c1-7f3cc5edddb8/datastream/OBJ/download}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Thus, all armchair (''n'' = ''m'') nanotubes are metallic, and nanotubes (6,4), (9,1), etc. are semiconducting.&lt;ref name=&quot;Curvature&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|first=X.|last=Lu|first2=Z.|title=Curved Pi-Conjugation, Aromaticity, and the Related Chemistry of Small Fullerenes (C&lt;sub&gt;60&lt;/sub&gt;) and Single-Walled Carbon Nanotubes|journal=[[Chemical Reviews]]|volume=105|pages=3643–3696|year=2005|doi=10.1021/cr030093d|issue=10|last2=Chen|pmid=16218563}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Carbon nanotubes are not semimetallic because the degenerate point (the point where the π [bonding] band meets the π* [anti-bonding] band, at which the energy goes to zero) is slightly shifted away from the ''K'' point in the Brillouin zone because of the curvature of the tube surface, causing hybridization between the σ* and π* anti-bonding bands, modifying the band dispersion.

The rule regarding metallic versus semiconductor behavior has exceptions because curvature effects in small-diameter tubes can strongly influence electrical properties. Thus, a (5,0) SWCNT that should be semiconducting in fact is metallic according to the calculations. Likewise, zigzag and chiral SWCNTs with small diameters that should be metallic have a finite gap (armchair nanotubes remain metallic).&lt;ref name=&quot;Curvature&quot;/&gt; In theory, metallic nanotubes can carry an electric current density of 4 × 10&lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt; A/cm&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, which is more than 1,000 times greater than those of metals such as [[copper]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|first=Seunghun|last=Hong|year=2007|title=Nanotube Electronics: A flexible approach to mobility|journal=Nature Nanotechnology|volume=2|pages=207–208|doi=10.1038/nnano.2007.89|pmid=18654263|last2=Myung|first2=S |issue=4 |bibcode=2007NatNa...2..207H}}&lt;/ref&gt; where for [[copper interconnects]], current densities are limited by [[electromigration]]. Carbon nanotubes are thus being explored as [[Carbon nanotubes in interconnects|interconnects]] and conductivity-enhancing components in composite materials, and many groups are attempting to commercialize highly conducting electrical wire assembled from individual carbon nanotubes. There are significant challenges to be overcome however, such as undesired current saturation under voltage,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Vasylenko|first=Andrij|last2=Wynn|first2=Jamie|last3=Medeiros|first3=Paulo V. C.|last4=Morris|first4=Andrew J.|last5=Sloan|first5=Jeremy|last6=Quigley|first6=David|year=2017|title=Encapsulated nanowires: Boosting electronic transport in carbon nanotubes|journal=Physical Review B|volume=95|issue=12|pages=121408|doi=10.1103/PhysRevB.95.121408|arxiv=1611.04867|bibcode = 2017PhRvB..95l1408V}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the much more resistive nanotube-to-nanotube junctions and impurities, all of which lower the electrical conductivity of the macroscopic nanotube wires by orders of magnitude, as compared to the conductivity of the individual nanotubes.

Because of its nanoscale cross-section, electrons propagate only along the tube's axis. As a result, carbon nanotubes are frequently referred to as one-dimensional conductors. The maximum [[electrical conductance]] of a single-walled carbon nanotube is 2''G''&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt;, where ''G''&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt; = 2''e''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;/''h'' is the [[Conductance quantum|conductance of a single ballistic quantum channel]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | doi = 10.1103/RevModPhys.79.677| title = Electronic and transport properties of nanotubes| journal = Reviews of Modern Physics| volume = 79| issue = 2| pages = 677–732| year = 2007| last1 = Charlier | first1 = J. C. | last2 = Blase | first2 = X. | last3 = Roche | first3 = S. |bibcode = 2007RvMP...79..677C}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Because of the role of the π-electron system in determining the [[Graphene#Electronic|electronic properties of graphene]], [[Doping (semiconductor)|doping]] in carbon nanotubes differs from that of bulk crystalline semiconductors from the same group of the periodic table (e.g., silicon). Graphitic substitution of carbon atoms in the nanotube wall by boron or nitrogen dopants leads to p-type and n-type behavior, respectively, as would be expected in silicon. However, some non-substitutional (intercalated or adsorbed) dopants introduced into a carbon nanotube, such as alkali metals and electron-rich metallocenes, result in n-type conduction because they donate electrons to the π-electron system of the nanotube. By contrast, π-electron acceptors such as FeCl&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; or electron-deficient metallocenes function as p-type dopants because they draw π-electrons away from the top of the valence band.

Intrinsic [[superconductivity]] has been reported,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |journal = Science|volume = 292|year = 2001| doi = 10.1126/science.1060470| title = Superconductivity in 4 Angstrom Single-Walled Carbon Nanotubes|pmid=11431560|issue=5526 |last1 = Tang |first1 = Z. K. |last2 = Zhang |first2 = L |last3 = Wang |first3 = N |last4 = Zhang |first4 = XX |last5 = Wen |first5 = GH |last6 = Li |first6 = GD |last7 = Wang |first7 = JN |last8 = Chan |first8 = CT |last9 = Sheng |first9 = P |pages = 2462–2465|bibcode = 2001Sci...292.2462T}}&lt;br/&gt;{{cite journal|title=Superconductivity in Entirely End-Bonded Multiwalled Carbon Nanotubes|journal=Phys. Rev. Lett.|volume=96|page=057001|year=2006|doi=10.1103/PhysRevLett.96.057001|url=http://www.ee.aoyama.ac.jp/Labs/j-haru-www/paper/Haruyama%20SuperCNT%20PRL%20publication.pdf |pmid=16486971|issue=5|arxiv = cond-mat/0509466|last1=Takesue|first1=I.|last2=Haruyama|first2=J.|last3=Kobayashi|first3=N.|last4=Chiashi|first4=S.|last5=Maruyama|first5=S.|last6=Sugai|first6=T.|last7=Shinohara|first7=H.|bibcode = 2006PhRvL..96e7001T}}&lt;br/&gt;{{cite journal |journal = Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences|volume = 106|year = 2009| doi = 10.1073/pnas.0813162106| title =Superconducting characteristics of 4-A carbon nanotube–zeolite composite|issue=18 |last1 = Lortz |first1 = R. |last2 = Zhang |first2 = Q |last3 = Shi |first3 = W |last4 = Ye |first4 = J. T. |last5 = Qiu |first5 = C. Y. |last6 = Wang |first6 = Z. |last7 = He |first7 = H. T. |last8 = Sheng |first8 = P |last9 = Qian |first9 = T. Z. |last10 = Tang |first10 = Z. K. |last11 = Wang |first11 = N. |last12 = Zhang |first12 = X. X. |last13 = Wang |first13 = J |last14 = Chan |first14 = C. T. |pages = 7299–7303|bibcode = 2009PNAS..106.7299L |pmid=19369206 |pmc=2678622}}&lt;/ref&gt; although other experiments found no evidence of this, leaving the claim a subject of debate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal| author = Bockrath, M. |journal = Nature Physics|volume = 2|year = 2006|pages = 155–156|doi = 10.1038/nphys252|title = Carbon nanotubes: The weakest link| issue = 3|bibcode = 2006NatPh...2..155B}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Optical ===
{{Main|Optical properties of carbon nanotubes}}Carbon nanotubes have useful [[Absorption spectroscopy|absorption]], [[photoluminescence]] ([[fluorescence]]), and [[Raman spectroscopy]] properties. Spectroscopic methods offer the possibility of quick and non-destructive characterization of relatively large amounts of carbon nanotubes. There is a strong demand for such characterization from the industrial point of view: numerous parameters of [[Carbon nanotube#Synthesis|nanotube synthesis]] can be changed, intentionally or unintentionally, to alter the nanotube quality. As shown below, optical absorption, photoluminescence, and Raman spectroscopies allow quick and reliable characterization of this &quot;nanotube quality&quot; in terms of non-tubular carbon content, structure (chirality) of the produced nanotubes, and structural defects. These features determine nearly any other properties such as optical, mechanical, and electrical properties.

[[Carbon nanotubes]] are unique &quot;one-dimensional systems&quot; which can be envisioned as rolled single sheets of [[graphite]] (or more precisely [[graphene]]). This rolling can be done at different angles and curvatures resulting in different nanotube properties. The diameter typically varies in the range 0.4–40&amp;nbsp;nm (i.e., &quot;only&quot; ~100 times), but the length can vary ~100,000,000,000 times, from 0.14&amp;nbsp;nm to 55.5&amp;nbsp;cm.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last2=Zhang|first2=Y.|last3=Zhang|first3=Q.|last4=Xie|first4=H.|last5=Qian|first5=W.|last6=Wei|first6=F.|year=2013|title=Growth of Half-Meter Long Carbon Nanotubes Based on Schulz–Flory Distribution|journal=ACS Nano|volume=7|issue=7|pages=6156–6161|doi=10.1021/nn401995z|pmid=23806050|last1=Zhang|first1=R.|url=https://figshare.com/articles/Growth_of_Half_Meter_Long_Carbon_Nanotubes_Based_on_Schulz_Flory_Distribution/2393992}}&lt;/ref&gt; The nanotube [[aspect ratio]], or the length-to-diameter ratio, can be as high as 132,000,000:1,&lt;ref name=&quot;Longest2&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|year=2009|title=Fabrication of Ultralong and Electrically Uniform Single-Walled Carbon Nanotubes on Clean Substrates|journal=Nano Letters|volume=9|issue=9|pages=3137–3141|bibcode=2009NanoL...9.3137W|doi=10.1021/nl901260b|pmid=19650638|author=Xueshen Wang|display-authors=etal|url=http://www.chem.pku.edu.cn/page/liy/labhomepage/publications/2009/2009NL.pdf|citeseerx=10.1.1.454.2744|access-date=24 October 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170808164154/http://www.chem.pku.edu.cn/page/liy/labhomepage/publications/2009/2009NL.pdf|archive-date=8 August 2017|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; which is unequalled by any other material. Consequently, all the properties of the carbon nanotubes relative to those of typical semiconductors are extremely [[anisotropic]] (directionally dependent) and tunable.

Whereas mechanical, electrical, and electrochemical ([[supercapacitor]]) properties of the carbon nanotubes are well established and have immediate [[Carbon nanotube#Potential and current applications|applications]], the practical use of optical properties is yet unclear. The aforementioned tunability of properties is potentially useful in [[optics]] and [[photonics]]. In particular, light-emitting diodes ([[LED]]s)&lt;ref name=&quot;led1&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|year=2003|title=Electrically Induced Optical Emission from a Carbon Nanotube FET|journal=[[Science (journal)|Science]]|volume=300|issue=5620|pages=783–786|bibcode=2003Sci...300..783M|doi=10.1126/science.1081294|pmid=12730598|author=J. A. Misewich|display-authors=etal}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;led2&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|year=2005|title=Bright Infrared Emission from Electrically Induced Excitons in Carbon Nanotubes|journal=[[Science (journal)|Science]]|volume=310|issue=5751|pages=1171–1174|bibcode=2005Sci...310.1171C|doi=10.1126/science.1119177|pmid=16293757|author=J. Chen|display-authors=etal}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Photodiode|photo-detectors]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|year=2003|title=Photoconductivity of Single Carbon Nanotubes|journal=[[Nano Letters]]|volume=3|issue=8|pages=1067–1071|bibcode=2003NanoL...3.1067F|doi=10.1021/nl034313e|author=M. Freitag|display-authors=etal}}&lt;/ref&gt; based on a single nanotube have been produced in the lab. Their unique feature is not the efficiency, which is yet relatively low, but the narrow selectivity in the [[wavelength]] of emission and detection of light and the possibility of its fine tuning through the nanotube structure. In addition, [[bolometer]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|year=2006|title=Bolometric Infrared Photoresponse of Suspended Single-Walled Carbon Nanotube Films|journal=[[Science (journal)|Science]]|volume=312|issue=5772|pages=413–416|bibcode=2006Sci...312..413I|doi=10.1126/science.1125695|pmid=16627739|author=M. E. Itkis|display-authors=etal}}&lt;/ref&gt; and optoelectronic memory&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|year=2004|title=Nanotube Optoelectronic Memory Devices|journal=[[Nano Letters]]|volume=4|issue=9|pages=1587–1591|bibcode=2004NanoL...4.1587S|doi=10.1021/nl049337f|author=A. Star|display-authors=etal|url=https://figshare.com/articles/Nanotube_Optoelectronic_Memory_Devices/3325894}}&lt;/ref&gt; devices have been realised on ensembles of single-walled carbon nanotubes.

Crystallographic defects also affect the tube's electrical properties. A common result is lowered conductivity through the defective region of the tube. A defect in armchair-type tubes (which can conduct electricity) can cause the surrounding region to become semiconducting, and single monatomic vacancies induce magnetic properties.&lt;ref&gt;''Carbon-Based Magnetism: An Overview of the Magnetism of Metal Free Carbon-based Compounds and Materials'', Tatiana Makarova and Fernando Palacio (eds.), Elsevier, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Thermal ===
{{Main|Thermodynamics of nanostructures#Carbon nanotubes}}

All nanotubes are expected to be very good [[thermal conductor]]s along the tube, exhibiting a property known as &quot;[[ballistic conduction]]&quot;, but good insulators lateral to the tube axis. Measurements show that an individual SWNT has a room-temperature thermal conductivity along its axis of about 3500 W·m&lt;sup&gt;−1&lt;/sup&gt;·K&lt;sup&gt;−1&lt;/sup&gt;;&lt;ref name=&quot;Pop&quot;&gt;
{{cite journal
|title = Thermal conductance of an individual single-wall carbon nanotube above room temperature
|journal=Nano Letters
|date=22 December 2005
|volume=6
|issue=1
|pages= 96–100
|doi =10.1021/nl052145f
|pmid = 16402794|arxiv = cond-mat/0512624
|last1 = Pop
|first1 = Eric
|last2 = Mann
|first2 = David
|last3 = Wang
|first3 = Qian
|last4 = Goodson
|first4 = Kenneth
|last5 = Dai
|first5 = Hongjie |bibcode = 2006NanoL...6...96P}}&lt;/ref&gt; compare this to copper, a metal well known for its good [[thermal conductivity]], which transmits 385 W·m&lt;sup&gt;−1&lt;/sup&gt;·K&lt;sup&gt;−1&lt;/sup&gt;. An individual SWNT has a room-temperature thermal conductivity across its axis (in the radial direction) of about 1.52 W·m&lt;sup&gt;−1&lt;/sup&gt;·K&lt;sup&gt;−1&lt;/sup&gt;,&lt;ref name=&quot;Sinha&quot;&gt;
{{cite journal
|title = Off-axis thermal properties of carbon nanotube films
|journal=Journal of Nanoparticle Research
|date=5 June 2005
|volume=7
|issue=6
|pages= 651–657
|doi =10.1007/s11051-005-8382-9
|last1 = Sinha
|first1 = Saion
|last2 = Barjami
|first2 = Saimir
|last3 = Iannacchione
|first3 = Germano
|last4 = Schwab
|first4 = Alexander
|last5 = Muench
|first5 = George
|bibcode = 2005JNR.....7..651S}}&lt;/ref&gt; which is about as thermally conductive as soil. Macroscopic assemblies of nanotubes such as films or fibres have reached up to 1500 W·m&lt;sup&gt;−1&lt;/sup&gt;·K&lt;sup&gt;−1&lt;/sup&gt; so far.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Koziol|first=Krzysztof K.|last2=Janas|first2=Dawid|last3=Brown|first3=Elisabetta|last4=Hao|first4=Ling|date=2017-04-01|title=Thermal properties of continuously spun carbon nanotube fibres|url= |journal=Physica E: Low-dimensional Systems and Nanostructures|volume=88|pages=104–108|doi=10.1016/j.physe.2016.12.011|bibcode = 2017PhyE...88..104K}}&lt;/ref&gt; Networks composed of nanotubes demonstrate different values of thermal conductivity, from the level of thermal insulation with the thermal conductivity of 0.1 W·m&lt;sup&gt;−1&lt;/sup&gt;·K&lt;sup&gt;−1&lt;/sup&gt; to such high values.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Kumanek|first=Bogumiła|last2=Janas|first2=Dawid|date=May 2019|title=Thermal conductivity of carbon nanotube networks: a review|journal=Journal of Materials Science|volume=54|issue=10|pages=7397–7427|doi=10.1007/s10853-019-03368-0|issn=0022-2461|bibcode=2019JMatS..54.7397K}}&lt;/ref&gt; That is dependent on the amount of contribution to the thermal resistance of the system caused by the presence of impurities, misalignments and other factors. The temperature stability of carbon nanotubes is estimated to be up to 2800&amp;nbsp;°C in [[vacuum]] and about 750&amp;nbsp;°C in air.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|first=Erik|last=Thostenson|year=2005|title=Nanocomposites in context|journal=Composites Science and Technology|volume=65|pages=491–516|doi=10.1016/j.compscitech.2004.11.003|last2=Li|first2=C|last3=Chou|first3=T|issue=3–4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Crystallographic defects strongly affect the tube's thermal properties. Such defects lead to [[phonon]] scattering, which in turn increases the relaxation rate of the phonons. This reduces the [[mean free path]] and reduces the thermal conductivity of nanotube structures. Phonon transport simulations indicate that substitutional defects such as nitrogen or boron will primarily lead to scattering of high-frequency optical phonons. However, larger-scale defects such as [[Stone Wales defect]]s cause phonon scattering over a wide range of frequencies, leading to a greater reduction in thermal conductivity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|first=N.|last=Mingo|year=2008|title=Phonon transmission through defects in carbon nanotubes from first principles|journal=Phys. Rev. B|volume=77|page=033418|doi=10.1103/PhysRevB.77.033418|last2=Stewart|first2=D. A.|last3=Broido|first3=D. A.|last4=Srivastava|first4=D.|issue=3|bibcode = 2008PhRvB..77c3418M |url=http://ecommons.cornell.edu/bitstream/1813/10898/1/phonon_transmission_through_defects_in_nanotubes.pdf|hdl=1813/10898}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Synthesis ==
{{Main|Synthesis of carbon nanotubes}}

Techniques have been developed to produce nanotubes in sizable quantities, including arc discharge, laser ablation, [[chemical vapor deposition]] (CVD) and high-pressure carbon monoxide disproportionation (HiPCO). Among these arc discharge, laser ablation, [[chemical vapor deposition]] (CVD) are batch by batch process and HiPCO is gas phase continuous process.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Nikolaev|first=Pavel|date=April 2004|title=Gas-phase production of single-walled carbon nanotubes from carbon monoxide: a review of the hipco process|journal=Journal of Nanoscience and Nanotechnology|volume=4|issue=4|pages=307–316|issn=1533-4880|pmid=15296221|doi=10.1166/jnn.2004.066}}&lt;/ref&gt; Most of these processes take place in a vacuum or with process gases. The CVD growth method is popular, as it yields high quantity and has a degree of control over diameter, length and morphology. Using particulate catalysts, large quantities of nanotubes can be synthesized by these methods, but achieving the repeatability becomes a major problem with CVD growth.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=L_zVa647-80C&amp;pg=PA476&amp;lpg=PA476|title=Nanomedicine Design of Particles, Sensors, Motors, Implants, Robots, and Devices|last=Schulz|first=Mark J.|last2=Shanov|first2=Vesselin N.|last3=Yun|first3=Yeoheung|date=2009|publisher=Artech House|isbn=9781596932807}}&lt;/ref&gt; The HiPCO process advances in catalysis and continuous growth are making CNTs more commercially viable.&lt;ref&gt;Takeuchi, K.; Hayashi, T.; Kim, Y. A.; Fujisawa, K. and Endo, M. (February 2014) [http://nanojournal.ifmo.ru/en/articles-2/volume5/5-1/paper01/ &quot;The state-of-the-art science and applications of carbon nanotubes&quot;], nanojournal.ifmo.ru. Volume 5, Issue 1, p. 15&lt;/ref&gt; The HiPCO process helps in producing high purity single walled carbon nanotubes in higher quantity. The HiPCO reactor operates at high [[temperature]] 900-1100&amp;nbsp;°C and high [[pressure]] ~30-50 bar.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Bronikowski|first=Michael J.|last2=Willis|first2=Peter A.|last3=Colbert|first3=Daniel T.|last4=Smith|first4=K. A.|last5=Smalley|first5=Richard E.|date=2001-07-01|title=Gas-phase production of carbon single-walled nanotubes from carbon monoxide via the HiPco process: A parametric study|journal=Journal of Vacuum Science &amp; Technology A: Vacuum, Surfaces, and Films|volume=19|issue=4|pages=1800–1805|doi=10.1116/1.1380721|issn=0734-2101|bibcode=2001JVSTA..19.1800B}}&lt;/ref&gt; It uses [[carbon monoxide]] as the carbon source and Nickel/ iron penta carbonyl as catalyst. These catalyst acts as the [[nucleation]] site for the nanotubes to grow.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

[[Vertically aligned carbon nanotube arrays]] are also grown by thermal chemical vapor deposition. A substrate (quartz, silicon, stainless steel, etc.) is coated with a catalytic metal (Fe, Co, Ni) layer. Typically that layer is iron, and is deposited via sputtering to a thickness of 1–5&amp;nbsp;nm. A 10–50&amp;nbsp;nm underlayer of alumina is often also put down on the substrate first. This imparts controllable wetting and good interfacial properties.
When the substrate is heated to the growth temperature (~700&amp;nbsp;°C), the continuous iron film breaks up into small islands... each island then nucleates a carbon nanotube. The sputtered thickness controls the island size, and this in turn determines the nanotube diameter. Thinner iron layers drive down the diameter of the islands, and they drive down the diameter of the nanotubes grown. The amount of time that the metal island can sit at the growth temperature is limited, as they are mobile, and can merge into larger (but fewer) islands. Annealing at the growth temperature reduces the site density (number of CNT/mm&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;) while increasing the catalyst diameter.

The as-prepared carbon nanotubes always have impurities such as other forms of carbon (amorphous carbon, fullerene, etc.) and non-carbonaceous impurities (metal used for catalyst).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Itkis|first=M. E.|last2=Perea|first2=D. E.|last3=Niyogi|first3=S.|last4=Rickard|first4=S. M.|last5=Hamon|first5=M. A.|last6=Hu|first6=H.|last7=Zhao|first7=B.|last8=Haddon|first8=R. C.|date=2003-03-01|title=Purity Evaluation of As-Prepared Single-Walled Carbon Nanotube Soot by Use of Solution-Phase Near-IR Spectroscopy|journal=Nano Letters|volume=3|issue=3|pages=309–314|doi=10.1021/nl025926e|issn=1530-6984|bibcode = 2003NanoL...3..309I}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Wang|first=Lu|last2=Pumera|first2=Martin|date=2014-09-25|title=Residual metallic impurities within carbon nanotubes play a dominant role in supposedly &quot;metal-free&quot; oxygen reduction reactions|journal=Chemical Communications|volume=50|issue=84|doi=10.1039/C4CC03271C|pmid=25204561|issn=1364-548X|pages=12662–12664}}&lt;/ref&gt; These impurities need to be removed to make use of the carbon nanotubes in applications.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Eatemadi|first=Ali|last2=Daraee|first2=Hadis|last3=Karimkhanloo|first3=Hamzeh|last4=Kouhi|first4=Mohammad|last5=Zarghami|first5=Nosratollah|last6=Akbarzadeh|first6=Abolfazl|last7=Abasi|first7=Mozhgan|last8=Hanifehpour|first8=Younes|last9=Joo|first9=Sang Woo|date=2014-08-13|title=Carbon nanotubes: properties, synthesis, purification, and medical applications|journal=Nanoscale Research Letters|volume=9|issue=1|pages=393|doi=10.1186/1556-276X-9-393|issn=1931-7573|pmc=4141964|pmid=25170330|bibcode = 2014NRL.....9..393E}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Modeling ==
[[File:Computer simulated microstructure of nanocomposite.jpg|thumb|Computer simulated microstructures with agglomeration regions]]
Carbon nanotubes are modelled in a similar manner as traditional composites in which a reinforcement phase is surrounded by a matrix phase. Ideal models such as cylindrical, hexagonal and square models are common. The size of the micromechanics model is highly function of the studied mechanical properties. The concept of representative volume element (RVE) is used to determine the appropriate size and configuration of computer model to replicate the actual behavior of CNT reinforced nanocomposite. Depending on the material property of interest (thermal, electrical, modulus, creep), one RVE might predict the property better than the alternatives. While the implementation of ideal model is comutationally efficient, they do not represent microstructural features observed in scanning electron microscopy of actual nanocomposites. To incorporate realistic modeling, computer models are also generated to incorporate variability such as waviness, orientation and agglomeration of multiwall or single wall carbon nanotubes.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal
 |last1=Sanei |first1=S.
 |year=2019
 |title=Effect of Nanocomposite Microstructure on Stochastic Elastic Properties: an FEA Study
 |journal=[[ASCE-ASME Journal of Risk and Uncertainty in Engineering Systems, Part B: Mechanical Engineering]]
 |volume=5 |issue=3 |pages=6 pages
 |doi=10.1115/1.4043410
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1115/1.4043410 |title=Effect of Nanocomposite Microstructure on Stochastic Elastic Properties: An Finite Element Analysis Study |journal=ASCE-ASME Journal of Risk and Uncertainty in Engineering Systems, Part B: Mechanical Engineering |volume=5 |issue=3 |pages=030903 |year=2019 |last1=Sanei |first1=Seyed Hamid Reza |last2=Doles |first2=Randall |last3=Ekaitis |first3=Tyler}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Metrology ==
There are many [[metrology]] standards and [[reference material]]s available for carbon nanotubes.&lt;ref name=&quot;:02&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=Metrology and Standardization of Nanotechnology|last=Stefaniak|first=Aleksandr B.|date=2017|publisher=Wiley-VCH Verlag|isbn=9783527800308|editor-last=Mansfield|editor-first=Elisabeth|location=|pages=151–174|chapter=Principal Metrics and Instrumentation for Characterization of Engineered Nanomaterials|doi=10.1002/9783527800308.ch8|editor2-last=Kaiser|editor2-first=Debra L.|editor3-last=Fujita|editor3-first=Daisuke|editor4-last=Van de Voorde|editor4-first=Marcel}}&lt;/ref&gt;

For single-wall carbon nanotubes, [[International Organization for Standardization|ISO]]/TS 10868 describes a measurement method for the diameter, purity, and fraction of metallic nanotubes through [[Optical radiation|optical]] [[absorption spectroscopy]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.iso.org/standard/69547.html|title=ISO/TS 10868:2017 – Nanotechnologies – Characterization of single-wall carbon nanotubes using ultraviolet-visible-near infrared (UV-Vis-NIR) absorption spectroscopy|website=[[International Organization for Standardization]]|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170907032921/https://www.iso.org/standard/69547.html|archive-date=2017-09-07|url-status=dead|accessdate=2017-09-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; while ISO/TS 10797 and ISO/TS 10798 establish methods to characterize the morphology and elemental composition of single-wall carbon nanotubes, using [[transmission electron microscopy]] and [[Scanning electron microscope|scanning electron microscopy]] respectively, coupled with energy dispersive [[X-ray spectroscopy|X-ray spectrometry]] analysis.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.iso.org/standard/46127.html|title=ISO/TS 10797:2012 – Nanotechnologies – Characterization of single-wall carbon nanotubes using transmission electron microscopy|website=International Organization for Standardization|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170907033223/https://www.iso.org/standard/46127.html|archive-date=2017-09-07|url-status=dead|access-date=2017-09-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.iso.org/standard/46128.html|title=ISO/TS 10798:2011 – Nanotechnologies – Characterization of single-wall carbon nanotubes using scanning electron microscopy and energy dispersive X-ray spectrometry analysis|website=International Organization for Standardization|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170907033356/https://www.iso.org/standard/46128.html|archive-date=2017-09-07|url-status=dead|accessdate=2017-09-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[National Institute of Standards and Technology|NIST]] SRM 2483 is a soot of single-wall carbon nanotubes used as a reference material for [[elemental analysis]], and was characterized using [[thermogravimetric analysis]], [[prompt gamma activation analysis]], induced [[neutron activation analysis]], [[Inductively coupled plasma mass spectrometry|inductively coupled plasma mass spectroscopy]], resonant [[Raman scattering]], [[Optical radiation|UV-visible-near infrared]] [[fluorescence spectroscopy]] and absorption spectroscopy, scanning electron microscopy, and transmission electron microscopy.&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nist.gov/programs-projects/carbon-nanotube-reference-materials|title=Carbon Nanotube Reference Materials|last=Fagan|first=Jeffrey|date=2009-03-05|work=U.S. [[National Institute of Standards and Technology]]|access-date=2017-09-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www-s.nist.gov/srmors/view_detail.cfm?srm=2483|title=SRM 2483 – Single-Wall Carbon Nanotubes (Raw Soot)|website=U.S. National Institute of Standards and Technology|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130218233137/https://www-s.nist.gov/srmors/view_detail.cfm?srm=2483|archive-date=2013-02-18|url-status=dead|access-date=2017-09-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[National Research Council (Canada)|Canadian National Research Council]] also offers a certified reference material SWCNT-1 for elemental analysis using neutron activation analysis and inductively coupled plasma mass spectroscopy.&lt;ref name=&quot;:02&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.nrc-cnrc.gc.ca/eng/solutions/advisory/crm/certificates/swcnt_1.html|title=SWCNT-1: Single-Wall Carbon Nanotube Certified Reference Material – National Research Council Canada|last=|first=|date=2014-11-07|website=Canadian [[National Research Council (Canada)|National Research Council]]|accessdate=2017-09-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; NIST RM 8281 is a mixture of three lengths of single-wall carbon nanotube.&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www-s.nist.gov/srmors/view_detail.cfm?srm=8281|title=RM 8281 – Single-Wall Carbon Nanotubes (Dispersed, Three Length-Resolved Populations)|website=U.S. National Institute of Standards and Technology|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150401143054/https://www-s.nist.gov/srmors/view_detail.cfm?srm=8281|archive-date=2015-04-01|url-status=dead|accessdate=2017-09-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

For multiwall carbon nanotubes, ISO/TR 10929 identifies the basic properties and the content of impurities,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.iso.org/standard/46424.html|title=ISO/TR 10929:2012 – Nanotechnologies – Characterization of multiwall carbon nanotube (MWCNT) samples|website=International Organization for Standardization|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170907034138/https://www.iso.org/standard/46424.html|archive-date=2017-09-07|url-status=dead|access-date=2017-09-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; while ISO/TS 11888 describes morphology using scanning electron microscopy, transmission electron microscopy, [[Viscometer|viscometry]], and [[light scattering]] analysis.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.iso.org/standard/69549.html|title=ISO/TS 11888:2017 –Nanotechnologies – Characterization of multiwall carbon nanotubes – Mesoscopic shape factors|website=International Organization for Standardization|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170907032855/https://www.iso.org/standard/69549.html|archive-date=2017-09-07|url-status=dead |accessdate=2017-09-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; ISO/TS 10798 is also valid for multiwall carbon nanotubes.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt;

== Chemical modification ==
{{Main|Carbon nanotube chemistry|Selective chemistry of single-walled nanotubes}}
Carbon nanotubes can be functionalized to attain desired properties that can be used in a wide variety of applications. The two main methods of carbon nanotube functionalization are covalent and non-covalent modifications. Because of their apparent hydrophobic nature,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Stando |first=Grzegorz |last2=Łukawski |first2=Damian |last3=Lisiecki |first3=Filip |last4=Janas |first4=Dawid |date=January 2019 |title=Intrinsic hydrophilic character of carbon nanotube networks|journal=Applied Surface Science |volume=463 |pages=227–233 |doi=10.1016/j.apsusc.2018.08.206|issn=0169-4332|bibcode=2019ApSS..463..227S}}&lt;/ref&gt; carbon nanotubes tend to agglomerate hindering their dispersion in solvents or viscous polymer melts. The resulting nanotube bundles or aggregates reduce the mechanical performance of the final composite. The surface of the carbon nanotubes can be modified to reduce the [[Hydrophobe|hydrophobicity]] and improve interfacial [[adhesion]] to a bulk [[polymer]] through chemical attachment.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|title = Current Progress on the Chemical Modification of Carbon Nanotubes|journal = Chemical Reviews|date = 14 June 2010|pages = 5366–5397|volume = 110|issue = 9|doi = 10.1021/cr100018g|first = Nikolaos|last = Karousis|first2 = Nikos|last2 = Tagmatarchis|first3 = Dimitrios|last3 = Tasis|pmid=20545303}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Also surface of carbon nanotubes can be fluorinated or halofluorinated by CVD-method with fluorocarbons, hydro- or halofluorocarbons by heating while in contact of such carbon material with fluoroorganic substance to form partially fluorinated carbons (so called Fluocar materials) with grafted (halo)fluoroalkyl functionality.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite patent|title=United States Patent: 10000382 - Method for carbon materials surface modification by the fluorocarbons and derivatives|url=http://patft.uspto.gov/netacgi/nph-Parser?Sect1=PTO1&amp;Sect2=HITOFF&amp;d=PALL&amp;p=1&amp;u=/netahtml/PTO/srchnum.htm&amp;r=1&amp;f=G&amp;l=50&amp;s1=10000382.PN.&amp;OS=PN/10000382&amp;RS=PN/10000382|patent-number=10000382|issue-date=June 19, 2018|access-date=2018-09-17|inventor-last=Zaderko|inventor2-last=UA|inventor3-last=UA|inventor-first=Alexander|inventor3-first=Vasyl}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://patentscope.wipo.int/search/en/detail.jsf?docId=WO16072959|title=WO16072959 Method for Carbon Materials Surface Modification by the Fluorocarbons and Derivatives|website=patentscope.wipo.int|accessdate=2018-09-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Applications ==
A primary obstacle for applications of carbon nanotubes has been their cost. Prices for single-walled nanotubes declined from around $1500 per gram as of 2000 to retail prices of around $50 per gram of as-produced 40–60% by weight SWNTs as of March 2010. As of 2016, the retail price of as-produced 75% by weight SWNTs was $2 per gram.&lt;ref&gt;[http://ocsial.com/en/product/tuball/ Single wall carbon nanotubes] at OCSiAl web site&lt;/ref&gt; SWNTs are forecast to make a large impact in electronics applications by 2020 according to ''The Global Market for Carbon Nanotubes'' report.

=== Current ===
Current use and application of nanotubes has mostly been limited to the use of bulk nanotubes, which is a mass of rather unorganized fragments of nanotubes. Bulk nanotube materials may never achieve a tensile strength similar to that of individual tubes, but such composites may, nevertheless, yield strengths sufficient for many applications. Bulk carbon nanotubes have already been used as composite fibers in [[polymers]] to improve the mechanical, thermal and electrical properties of the bulk product.
* [[Easton-Bell Sports, Inc.]] have been in partnership with [[Zyvex Performance Materials]], using CNT technology in a number of their [[bicycle]] components – including flat and riser handlebars, cranks, forks, seatposts, stems and aero bars.
* [[Amroy Europe Oy]] manufactures [[Hybtonite]] carbon nanoepoxy resins where carbon nanotubes have been chemically activated to bond to [[epoxy]], resulting in a composite material that is 20% to 30% stronger than other composite materials. It has been used for wind turbines, marine paints and a variety of sports gear such as skis, ice hockey sticks, baseball bats, hunting arrows, and surfboards.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pagni&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Pagni |first=John |title=Amroy aims to become nano-leader |publisher=European Plastics News |date=5 March 2010 |url=http://www.europeanplasticsnews.com/subscriber/headlines2.html?cat=1&amp;id=1267781513 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110710204854/http://www.europeanplasticsnews.com/subscriber/headlines2.html?cat=1&amp;id=1267781513 |archivedate=10 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Surrey NanoSystems]] synthesises carbon nanotubes to create [[vantablack]].

Other current applications include:
* tips for [[Atomic Force Microscopy|atomic force microscope]] probes&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Nanotube Tips |url=http://www.nanoscience.com/store/pc/viewCategories.asp?idCategory=9 |publisher=nanoScience instruments |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20111027064700/http://www.nanoscience.com/store/pc/viewCategories.asp?idCategory=9 |archivedate=27 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* in tissue engineering, carbon nanotubes can act as scaffolding for bone growth&lt;ref name=&quot;bone&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Haddon|first=Robert C.|year=2006|title=Bone Cell Proliferation on Carbon Nanotubes|journal=Nano Letters &lt;!-- This bit needs correcting --&gt;|volume=6|issue=3|pages=562–567|bibcode=2006NanoL...6..562Z|doi=10.1021/nl051861e|pmid=16522063|author2=Laura P. Zanello|author3=Bin Zhao|author4=Hui Hu|url=https://figshare.com/articles/Bone_Cell_Proliferation_on_Carbon_Nanotubes/3234403}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Under development===
Current research for modern applications include:
* using carbon nanotubes as a scaffold for diverse microfabrication techniques.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://nano.byu.edu/publications.php |title=Publications on carbon nanotube applications including scaffold microfabrication |date=27 May 2014 |website=nano.byu.edu}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
* energy dissipation in self-organized nanostructures under influence of an electric field.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Belkin|first1=A.|last2=et.|first2=al.|title=Self-Assembled Wiggling Nano-Structures and the Principle of Maximum Entropy Production|journal=Sci. Rep.|volume=5|pages=8323|date=2015|doi=10.1038/srep08323|pmid=25662746|pmc=4321171|bibcode=2015NatSR...5E8323B}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
* using carbon nanotubes for environmental monitoring due to their active surface area and their ability to absorb gases.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Tan|first=Chin Wei|last2=Tan|first2=Kok Hong|last3=Ong|first3=Yit Thai|last4=Mohamed|first4=Abdul Rahman|last5=Zein|first5=Sharif Hussein Sharif|last6=Tan|first6=Soon Huat|date=2012-09-01|title=Energy and environmental applications of carbon nanotubes|journal=Environmental Chemistry Letters|volume=10|issue=3|pages=265–273|doi=10.1007/s10311-012-0356-4|issn=1610-3653}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Jack Andraka used carbon nanotubes in his pancreatic cancer test. His method of testing won the Intel International Science and Engineering Fair Gordon E. Moore Award in the spring of 2012.[https://www.smithsonianmag.com/science-nature/jack-andraka-the-teen-prodigy-of-pancreatic-cancer-135925809 Jack Andraka, the Teen Prodigy of Pancreatic Cancer]
* [[The Boeing Company]] has patented the use of carbon nanotubes for structural health monitoring&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.google.com/patents/US9329021]{{cite patent|title=System and methods for use in monitoring a structure|date=May 3, 2016|url=http://www.google.com/patents/US9329021|inventor-last=DeLuca|inventor2-last=Felker|inventor3-last=Heider|inventor-first=Michael J.|inventor2-first=Christopher J.|inventor3-first=Dirk|issue=US9329021 B1|accessdate=2017-10-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; of composites used in aircraft structures. This technology will greatly reduce the risk of an in-flight failure caused by structural degradation of aircraft.
* [[Zyvex Technologies]] has also built a 54' maritime vessel, the [[Piranha Unmanned Surface Vessel]], as a technology demonstrator for what is possible using CNT technology. CNTs help improve the structural performance of the vessel, resulting in a lightweight 8,000&amp;nbsp;lb boat that can carry a payload of 15,000&amp;nbsp;lb over a range of 2,500 miles.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.reinforcedplastics.com/view/7467/pirahna-usv-built-using-nanoenhanced-carbon-prepreg/ |title=Pirahna USV built using nano-enhanced carbon prepreg |date=19 February 2009 |publisher=ReinforcedPlastics.com |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120303141747/http://www.reinforcedplastics.com/view/7467/pirahna-usv-built-using-nanoenhanced-carbon-prepreg/ |archivedate=3 March 2012 |df=dmy}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Carbon nanotubes can serve as additives to various structural materials. For instance, nanotubes form a tiny portion of the material(s) in some (primarily [[carbon fiber]]) baseball bats, golf clubs, car parts, or [[damascus steel]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.nationalgeographic.com/news/2006/11/061116-nanotech-swords.html|title=Legendary Swords' Sharpness, Strength From Nanotubes, Study Says|website=news.nationalgeographic.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal
 |last1=Gullapalli
 |first1=S.
 |last2=Wong
 |first2=M.S.
 |year=2011
 |title=Nanotechnology: A Guide to Nano-Objects
 |url=http://www.aiche.org/uploadedFiles/Publications/CEPMagazine/051128_public.pdf
 |journal=Chemical Engineering Progress
 |volume=107
 |issue=5
 |pages=28–32
 |access-date=24 November 2011
 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120813180046/http://www.aiche.org/uploadedFiles/Publications/CEPMagazine/051128_public.pdf
 |archive-date=13 August 2012
 |url-status=dead
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

IBM expected carbon nanotube transistors to be used on Integrated Circuits by 2020.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.technologyreview.com/s/528601/ibm-commercial-nanotube-transistors-are-coming-soon/|title=IBM Expects Nanotube Transistor Computer Chips Ready Soon After 2020|first=Tom|last=Simonite|website=MIT Technology Review}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Potential ===
{{Main|Potential applications of carbon nanotubes}}
The strength and flexibility of carbon nanotubes makes them of potential use in controlling other nanoscale structures, which suggests they will have an important role in [[nanotechnology]] engineering. The highest tensile strength of an individual multi-walled carbon nanotube has been tested to be 63&amp;nbsp;[[GPa]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Strength and Breaking&quot; /&gt; Carbon nanotubes were found in [[Damascus steel]] from the 17th century, possibly helping to account for the legendary strength of the swords made of it.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Sanderson, K. |title=Sharpest cut from nanotube sword |journal=Nature News |doi=10.1038/news061113-11| year=2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first=M. |last=Reibold |date=16 November 2006 |title=Materials: Carbon nanotubes in an ancient Damascus sabre |journal=Nature |volume=444 |page=286 |doi=10.1038/444286a |pmid=17108950 |last2=Paufler |first2=P |last3=Levin |first3=AA |last4=Kochmann |first4=W |last5=Pätzke |first5=N |last6=Meyer |first6=DC |issue=7117 |bibcode=2006Natur.444..286R}}&lt;/ref&gt; Recently, several studies have highlighted the prospect of using carbon nanotubes as building blocks to fabricate three-dimensional macroscopic (&gt;1mm in all three dimensions) all-carbon devices. Lalwani et al. have reported a novel radical initiated thermal crosslinking method to fabricated macroscopic, free-standing, porous, all-carbon scaffolds using single- and multi-walled carbon nanotubes as building blocks.&lt;ref name=&quot;PMID 23436939&quot; /&gt; These scaffolds possess macro-, micro-, and nano- structured pores and the porosity can be tailored for specific applications. These 3D all-carbon scaffolds/architectures may be used for the fabrication of the next generation of energy storage, supercapacitors, field emission transistors, high-performance catalysis,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=Co-axial heterostructures integrating palladium/titanium dioxide with carbon nanotubes for efficient electrocatalytic hydrogen evolution |year=2016 |last1=Valenti |first1=G. |last2=Boni |first2=A. |last3=Melchionna |first3=M. |last4=Cargnello |first4=M. |last5=Nasi |first5=L. |last6=Bertoli |first6=G. |last7=Gorte |first7=R. J. |last8=Marcaccio |first8=M. |last9=Rapino |first9=S. |last10=Bonchio |first10=M. |last11=Fornasiero |first11=P. |last12=Prato |first12=M. |last13=Paolucci |first13=F. |journal=Nature Communications |volume=7 |pages=13549|bibcode=2016NatCo...713549V |doi=10.1038/ncomms13549 |pmid=27941752 |pmc=5159813}}&lt;/ref&gt; photovoltaics, and biomedical devices and implants.

CNTs are potential candidates for future via and wire material in nano-scale VLSI circuits. Eliminating electromigration reliability concerns that plague today's [[Cu interconnects]], isolated (single and multi-wall) CNTs can carry current densities in excess of 1000&amp;nbsp;MA/cm&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; without electromigration damage.&lt;ref name=&quot;EM_book&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author1=J. Lienig|author2= M. Thiele|title=Fundamentals of Electromigration-Aware Integrated Circuit Design|pp=138–140|chapter=Mitigating Electromigration in Physical Design|publisher=Springer|date=2018|doi=10.1007/978-3-319-73558-0|isbn=978-3-319-73557-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Single-walled nanotubes are likely candidates for miniaturizing electronics. The most basic building block of these systems is an electric wire, and SWNTs with diameters of an order of a nanometer can be excellent conductors.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal |last1=Mintmire|first1=J.W.|last2=Dunlap|first2=B.I.|last3=White|first3=C.T.|year=1992|title=Are Fullerene Tubules Metallic? |journal=Phys. Rev. Lett.|volume=68|issue=5|pages=631–634 |bibcode=1992PhRvL..68..631M|doi=10.1103/PhysRevLett.68.631|pmid=10045950}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal|last=Dekker|first=C.|year=1999|title=Carbon nanotubes as molecular quantum wires|journal=[[Physics Today]] |volume=52 |issue=5 |pages=22–28|bibcode=1999PhT....52e..22D|doi=10.1063/1.882658}}&lt;/ref&gt; One useful application of SWNTs is in the development of the first intermolecular [[field-effect transistor]]s (FET). The first intermolecular [[logic gate]] using SWCNT FETs was made in 2001.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal|last1=Martel|first1=R.|last2=Derycke|first2=V.|last3=Lavoie|first3=C.|last4=Appenzeller|first4=J.|last5=Chan|first5=K.|last6=Tersoff|first6=J.|last7=Avouris|first7=Ph.|year=2001|title=Ambipolar Electrical Transport in Semiconducting Single-Wall Carbon Nanotubes|journal=Phys. Rev. Lett.|volume=87|issue=25|page=256805|bibcode=2001PhRvL..87y6805M|doi=10.1103/PhysRevLett.87.256805|pmid=11736597}}&lt;/ref&gt; A logic gate requires both a p-FET and an n-FET. Because SWNTs are p-FETs when exposed to oxygen and n-FETs otherwise, it is possible to expose half of an SWNT to oxygen and protect the other half from it. The resulting SWNT acts as a ''not'' logic gate with both p- and n-type FETs in the same molecule.
Large quantities of pure CNTs can be made into a freestanding sheet or film by surface-engineered tape-casting (SETC) fabrication technique which is a scalable method to fabricate flexible and foldable sheets with superior properties.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Susantyoko|first=Rahmat Agung|last2=Karam|first2=Zainab|last3=Alkhoori|first3=Sara|last4=Mustafa|first4=Ibrahim|last5=Wu|first5=Chieh-Han|last6=Almheiri|first6=Saif|date=2017|title=A surface-engineered tape-casting fabrication technique toward the commercialisation of freestanding carbon nanotube sheets|journal=Journal of Materials Chemistry A|volume=5|issue=36|pages=19255–19266|doi=10.1039/c7ta04999d|issn=2050-7488}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Karam|first=Zainab|last2=Susantyoko|first2=Rahmat Agung|last3=Alhammadi|first3=Ayoob|last4=Mustafa|first4=Ibrahim|last5=Wu|first5=Chieh-Han|last6=Almheiri|first6=Saif|date=2018-02-26|title=Development of Surface-Engineered Tape-Casting Method for Fabricating Freestanding Carbon Nanotube Sheets Containing Fe2 O3 Nanoparticles for Flexible Batteries|journal=Advanced Engineering Materials|volume=20|issue=6|pages=1701019|doi=10.1002/adem.201701019|issn=1438-1656}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another reported form factor is CNT fiber (a.k.a. filament) by wet [[Spinning (polymers)|spinning]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Behabtu|first=Natnael|last2=Young|first2=Colin C.|last3=Tsentalovich|first3=Dmitri E.|last4=Kleinerman|first4=Olga|last5=Wang|first5=Xuan|last6=Ma|first6=Anson W. K.|last7=Bengio|first7=E. Amram|last8=Waarbeek|first8=Ron F. ter|last9=Jong|first9=Jorrit J. de, Hoogerwerf, R.E., Fairchild, S.B., Ferguson, J.B., Maruyama, B., Kono, J., Talmon, Y., Cohen, Y., Otto, M.J., Pasquali, M.|date=2013-01-11|title=Strong, Light, Multifunctional Fibers of Carbon Nanotubes with Ultrahigh Conductivity|journal=Science|volume=339|issue=6116|pages=182–186|doi=10.1126/science.1228061|issn=0036-8075|pmid=23307737|hdl=1911/70792|bibcode=2013Sci...339..182B}}&lt;/ref&gt; The fiber is either directly spun from the synthesis pot or spun from pre-made dissolved CNTs. Individual fibers can be turned into a [[yarn]]. Apart from its strength and flexibility, the main advantage is making an [[electrically conducting yarn]]. The electronic properties of individual CNT fibers (i.e. bundle of individual CNT) are governed by the two-dimensional structure of CNTs. The fibers were measured to have a [[Electrical resistivity and conductivity|resistivity]] only one order of magnitude higher than metallic conductors at 300K. By further optimizing the CNTs and CNT fibers, CNT fibers with improved electrical properties could be developed.&lt;ref name=&quot;EM_book&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Piraux|first1=L.|last2=Abreu Araujo|first2=F.|last3=Bui|first3=T. N.|last4=Otto|first4=M. J.|last5=Issi|first5=J.-P.|title=Two-dimensional quantum transport in highly conductive carbon nanotube fibers|journal=Physical Review B|date=26 August 2015|volume=92|issue=8|pages=085428|doi=10.1103/PhysRevB.92.085428|bibcode=2015PhRvB..92h5428P}}&lt;/ref&gt;

CNT-based yarns are suitable for applications in energy and electrochemical water treatment when coated with an [[Ion-exchange membranes|ion-exchange membrane]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Liu|first1=F.|last2=Wagterveld|first2=R.M.|last3=Gebben|first3=B.|last4=Otto|first4=M.J.|last5=Biesheuvel|first5=P.M.|last6=Hamelers|first6=H.V.M.|title=Carbon nanotube yarns as strong flexible conductive capacitive electrodes|journal=Colloid and Interface Science Communications|date=November 2014|volume=3|pages=9–12|doi=10.1016/j.colcom.2015.02.001}}&lt;/ref&gt; Also, CNT-based yarns could replace copper as a [[Electromagnetic coil|winding]] material. Pyrhönen et al. (2015) have built a motor using CNT winding.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Pyrhönen|first=Juha|last2=Montonen|first2=Juho|last3=Lindh|first3=Pia|last4=Vauterin|first4=Johanna Julia|last5=Otto|first5=Marcin|date=2015-02-28|title=Replacing Copper with New Carbon Nanomaterials in Electrical Machine Windings|journal=International Review of Electrical Engineering (IREE)|volume=10|issue=1|pages=12|doi=10.15866/iree.v10i1.5253|issn=1827-6679|citeseerx=10.1.1.1005.8294}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fg_QZuVKWws Carbon Nanotube Yarn Rotates Electric Motors at LUT]. Youtube&lt;/ref&gt;

== Safety and health ==
{{Main|Health and safety hazards of nanomaterials|Health impact of fullerenes}}

The [[National Institute for Occupational Safety and Health]] (NIOSH) is the leading United States federal agency conducting research and providing guidance on the occupational safety and health implications and applications of nanotechnology. Early scientific studies have indicated that some of these nanoscale particles may pose a greater health risk than the larger bulk form of these materials. In 2013, NIOSH published a Current Intelligence Bulletin detailing the potential hazards and recommended exposure limit for carbon nanotubes and fibers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=https://www.cdc.gov/niosh/docs/2013-145/default.html|title=CDC – NIOSH Publications and Products – Current Intelligence Bulletin 65: Occupational Exposure to Carbon Nanotubes and Nanofibers (2013–145)|website=www.cdc.gov|access-date=2017-02-01|doi=10.26616/NIOSHPUB2013145|year=2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As of October 2016, single wall carbon nanotubes have been registered through the European Union's [[Registration, Evaluation, Authorization and Restriction of Chemicals]] (REACH) regulations, based on evaluation of the potentially hazardous properties of SWCNT. Based on this registration, SWCNT commercialization is allowed in the EU up to 10 metric tons. Currently, the type of SWCNT registered through REACH is limited to the specific type of single wall carbon nanotubes manufactured by [[OCSiAl]], which submitted the application.&lt;ref name=&quot;reach&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pcimag.com/articles/102634-reach-registration-completed-for-single-wall-carbon-nanotubes|title=REACH Registration Completed for Single-Wall Carbon Nanotubes|date=16 October 2016|website=pcimag.com|publisher=PCI Mag|accessdate=24 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
{{See also|Timeline of carbon nanotubes|Fullerene#History}}
The true identity of the discoverers of carbon nanotubes is a subject of some controversy.&lt;ref name=&quot;carbon1&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=Carbon Nanotubes as Platforms for Biosensors with Electrochemical and Electronic Transduction|first=Mercè|last=Pacios Pujadó|publisher=Springer Heidelberg|year=2012|pages=xx, 208|doi=10.1007/978-3-642-31421-6|isbn=978-3-642-31421-6|series=Springer Theses|hdl=10803/84001}}&lt;/ref&gt; A 2006 editorial written by Marc Monthioux and Vladimir Kuznetsov in the journal ''Carbon'' described the interesting and often-misstated origin of the carbon nanotube.&lt;ref name=&quot;carbon&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|title=Who should be given the credit for the discovery of carbon nanotubes?|doi=10.1016/j.carbon.2006.03.019|first=Marc|last=Monthioux|journal=Carbon|volume=44|year=2006|url=http://nanotube.msu.edu/HSS/2006/1/2006-1.pdf |pages=1621–1623|last2=Kuznetsov|first2=V|issue=9}}&lt;/ref&gt; A large percentage of academic and popular literature attributes the discovery of hollow, nanometer-size tubes composed of graphitic carbon to [[Sumio Iijima]] of [[NEC]] in 1991. He published a paper describing his discovery which initiated a flurry of excitement and could be credited by inspiring the many scientists now studying applications of carbon nanotubes. Though Iijima has been given much of the credit for discovering carbon nanotubes, it turns out that the timeline of carbon nanotubes goes back much further than 1991.&lt;ref name=&quot;carbon1&quot; /&gt;

In 1952, L. V. Radushkevich and V. M. Lukyanovich published clear images of 50 nanometer diameter tubes made of carbon in the Soviet ''Journal of Physical Chemistry''.&lt;ref name=&quot;CVD&quot;/&gt; This discovery was largely unnoticed, as the article was published in Russian, and Western scientists' access to Soviet press was limited during the [[Cold War]]. Monthioux and Kuznetsov mentioned in their ''Carbon'' editorial:&lt;ref name=&quot;carbon&quot; /&gt; {{quote|text=The fact is, Radushkevich and Lukyanovich [..] should be credited for the discovery that carbon filaments could be hollow and have a nanometer- size diameter, that is to say for the discovery of carbon nanotubes.}}

In 1976, [[Morinobu Endo]] of [[Centre national de la recherche scientifique|CNRS]] observed hollow tubes of rolled up graphite sheets synthesised by a chemical vapour-growth technique.&lt;ref name=&quot;endo1&quot;/&gt; The first specimens observed would later come to be known as single-walled carbon nanotubes (SWNTs).&lt;ref name=&quot;carbon2&quot;&gt;{{cite report|title=WTEC Panel Report on 'International Assessment of Research and Development of Carbon Nanotube Manufacturing and Applications' Final Report|author=Eklund, Peter C. |publisher=World Technology Evaluation Center (WTEC)|year=2007|url=http://www.wtec.org/cnm/CNM_final_report.pdf|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt; Endo, in his early review of vapor-phase-grown carbon fibers (VPCF), also reminded us that he had observed a hollow tube, linearly extended with parallel carbon layer faces near the fiber core.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Endo, M.|title=Grow carbon fibers in the vapor phase|url=http://nanotube.msu.edu/nt05/abstracts/NT05_MEndo.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; This appears to be the observation of multi-walled carbon nanotubes at the center of the fiber.&lt;ref name=&quot;carbon2&quot; /&gt; The mass-produced MWCNTs today are strongly related to the VPGCF developed by Endo.&lt;ref name=&quot;carbon2&quot; /&gt; In fact, they call it the &quot;Endo-process&quot;, out of respect for his early work and patents.&lt;ref name=&quot;carbon2&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Koyama, T. and Endo, M.T. (1983) &quot;Method for Manufacturing Carbon Fibers by a Vapor Phase Process,&quot; Japanese Patent, 1982-58, 966.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1979, John Abrahamson presented evidence of carbon nanotubes at the 14th Biennial Conference of Carbon at [[Pennsylvania State University]]. The conference paper described carbon nanotubes as carbon fibers that were produced on carbon anodes during arc discharge. A characterization of these fibers was given as well as hypotheses for their growth in a nitrogen atmosphere at low pressures.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Structure of Carbon Fibers Found on Carbon Arc Anodes|journal=Carbon|volume=37|year=1999|pages=1873–1874|last=Abrahamson|first=John|last2=Wiles|first2=Peter G.|last3=Rhoades|first3=Brian L.|doi=10.1016/S0008-6223(99)00199-2|issue=11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1981, a group of Soviet scientists published the results of chemical and structural characterization of carbon nanoparticles produced by a thermocatalytical disproportionation of carbon monoxide. Using TEM images and [[X-ray scattering techniques|XRD]] patterns, the authors suggested that their &quot;carbon multi-layer tubular crystals&quot; were formed by rolling graphene layers into cylinders. They speculated that by rolling graphene layers into a cylinder, many different arrangements of graphene hexagonal nets are possible. They suggested two possibilities of such arrangements: circular arrangement (armchair nanotube) and a spiral, helical arrangement (chiral tube).&lt;ref&gt;Izvestiya Akademii Nauk SSSR, Metals. 1982, #3, pp. 12–17 (in Russian)&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1987, Howard G. Tennent of Hyperion Catalysis was issued a U.S. patent for the production of &quot;cylindrical discrete carbon fibrils&quot; with a &quot;constant diameter between about 3.5 and about 70&amp;nbsp;nanometers..., length 10&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; times the diameter, and an outer region of multiple essentially continuous layers of ordered carbon atoms and a distinct inner core....&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Ref patent|country=US|number=4663230|title=Carbon fibrils, method for producing same and compositions containing same|gdate=1987-05-05|fdate=1984-12-06|invent1=Tennent, Howard G.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Iijima's discovery of multi-walled carbon nanotubes in the insoluble material of arc-burned graphite rods in 1991&lt;ref name=Iijima1/&gt; and Mintmire, Dunlap, and White's independent prediction that if single-walled carbon nanotubes could be made, then they would exhibit remarkable conducting properties&lt;ref name=mintmire1/&gt; helped create the initial excitement associated with carbon nanotubes. Nanotube research accelerated greatly following the independent discoveries&lt;ref name=Iijima2/&gt;&lt;ref name=Bethune/&gt; by Iijima and Ichihashi at NEC and Bethune ''et al.'' at IBM of ''single-walled'' carbon nanotubes and methods to specifically produce them by adding transition-metal catalysts to the carbon in an arc discharge. The arc discharge technique was well known to produce the famed Buckminster fullerene on a preparative scale,&lt;ref name=&quot;Kratschmer-C60&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|first=W.|last=Krätschmer|year=1990|title=Solid C60: a new form of carbon|journal=Nature|volume=347|pages=354–358|doi=10.1038/347354a0|last2=Lamb|first2=Lowell D.|last3=Fostiropoulos|first3=K.|last4=Huffman|first4=Donald R.|issue=6291|bibcode = 1990Natur.347..354K}}&lt;/ref&gt; and these results appeared to extend the run of accidental discoveries relating to fullerenes. The discovery of nanotubes remains a contentious issue. Many believe that Iijima's report in 1991 is of particular importance because it brought carbon nanotubes into the awareness of the scientific community as a whole.&lt;ref name=&quot;carbon1&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;carbon2&quot; /&gt;

==See also==
{{columns-list|colwidth=20em|

* [[BCN nanotube]]
* [[Boron nitride#Boron nitride nanotubes|Boron nitride nanotube]]
* [[Buckypaper]]
* [[Carbide-derived carbon]]
* [[Carbon nanocone]]
* [[Carbon nanofibers]]
* [[Carbon nanoparticles]]
* [[Carbon nanoscrolls]]
* [[Carbon nanotube chemistry]]
* [[Carbon nanotube computer]]
* [[Carbon nanotube field-effect transistor]]
* [[Colossal carbon tube]]
* [[Diamond nanothread]]
* [[DNA nanotechnology#DNA nanotubes|DNA nanotube]]
* [[Filamentous carbon]]
* [[Gallium nitride nanotube]]
* [[Geodesic polyarene]]
* [[Graphene oxide paper]]
* [[Inorganic nanotube]]
* [[List of software for nanostructures modeling]]
* [[Molecular modelling]]
* [[Nanoflower]]
* [[Nitrogen-doped carbon nanotube]]
* [[Ninithi]] (nanotube modelling software)
* [[Organic semiconductor]]
* [[SAMSON]] (software platform for integrated computational nanoscience)
* [[Selective chemistry of single-walled nanotubes]]
* [[Silicon nanotubes]]
* [[Timeline of carbon nanotubes]]
* [[Titanium dioxide#Nanotubes|Titania nanotubes]]
* [[Tunneling nanotube]]
* [[Tungsten(IV) sulfide#Nanotubes|Tungsten(IV) sulfide Nanotubes]]
* [[Vertically aligned carbon nanotube arrays]]
}}

== References ==
''This article incorporates public domain text from National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences (NIEHS) as quoted.''

&lt;references&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;CVD&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Радушкевич|first=Л. В.|year=1952|script-title=ru:О Структуре Углерода, Образующегося При Термическом Разложении Окиси Углерода На Железном Контакте|journal=Журнал Физической Химии|volume=26|pages=88–95|url=http://nanotube.msu.edu/HSS/2006/4/2006-4.pdf|language=Russian}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=Iijima1&gt;{{cite journal|first=Sumio|last=Iijima|title=Helical microtubules of graphitic carbon|journal=Nature|volume=354|pages=56–58|date=7 November 1991|doi=10.1038/354056a0|issue=6348 |bibcode=1991Natur.354...56I}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=Iijima2&gt;{{cite journal|first=Sumio|last=Iijima|year=1993|title=Single-shell carbon nanotubes of 1-nm diameter|journal=Nature|volume=363|pages=603–605|doi=10.1038/363603a0|last2=Ichihashi|first2=Toshinari|issue=6430|bibcode = 1993Natur.363..603I}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=Bethune&gt;{{cite journal| title=Cobalt-catalyzed growth of carbon nanotubes with single-atomic-layer walls|journal=Nature|volume=363|pages=605–607|year=1993|doi=10.1038/363605a0|issue=6430| last1=Bethune| first1=D. S.| last2=Kiang| first2=C. H.| last3=De Vries| first3=M. S.| last4=Gorman| first4=G.| last5=Savoy| first5=R.| last6=Vazquez| first6=J.| last7=Beyers| first7=R.|bibcode = 1993Natur.363..605B}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;endo1&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|title=Filamentous growth of carbon through benzene decomposition|doi=10.1016/0022-0248(76)90115-9|first=A.|last=Oberlin|year=1976 |volume=32|pages=335–349|journal=Journal of Crystal Growth|issue=3|last2=Endo|first2=M.|last3=Koyama|first3=T. |bibcode=1976JCrGr..32..335O |url=http://www.kroto.info/wp-content/uploads/2015/10/1.M.ENdoJCrystalGrowth1976.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;--&lt;ref name=wang2009long&gt;{{cite journal | last1=Wang | first1=X. | year=2009 |title=Fabrication of Ultralong and Electrically Uniform Single-Walled Carbon Nanotubes on Clean Substrates | journal=[[Nano Letters]] |volume=9 |issue=9 |pages=3137–3141 |doi=10.1021/nl901260b |pmid=19650638 |last2=Li |first2=Qunqing |last3=Xie |first3=Jing |last4=Jin |first4=Zhong |last5=Wang |first5=Jinyong |last6=Li |first6=Yan |last7=Jiang |first7=Kaili |last8=Fan |first8=Shoushan |bibcode=2009NanoL...9.3137W |citeseerx=10.1.1.454.2744}}&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt;

&lt;ref name=mintmire1&gt;{{cite journal|first=J.W.|last=Mintmire|title=Are fullerene tubules metallic?|journal=Phys. Rev. Lett.|volume=68|pages=631–634|year=1992|doi=10.1103/PhysRevLett.68.631|pmid=10045950|last2=Dunlap|first2=B.I.|last3=White|first3=C.T.|issue=5|bibcode = 1992PhRvL..68..631M}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=Tans&gt;{{cite journal|first=S.J.|last=Tans|first2=M.H.|last2=Devoret|first3=H.|last3=Dai.|first4=A.|last4=Thess|first5=R.E.|last5=Smalley|first6=L.J.|last6=Geerligs|first7=C.|last7=Dekker|title=Individual single-wall carbon nanotubes as quantum wires|journal=Nature|volume=386|issue=6624|pages=374–377|year=1997|doi=10.1038/386474a0|bibcode=1997Natur.386..474T|url=http://resolver.tudelft.nl/uuid:4e58e2bc-5f69-4dbe-9942-aabcc9eaad35}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;tensile load 2000&quot;&gt;{{cite journal| author=Yu, M.-F|author2=Lourie, O.|author3=Dyer, M.J.|author4=Moloni, K.|author5=Kelley, T.F.|author6=Ruoff, R.S.|journal=Science| volume=287 |pages=637–40| year=2000| title=Strength and breaking mechanism of multiwalled carbon nanotubes under tensile load |doi=10.1126/science.287.5453.637| pmid=10649994| bibcode=2000Sci...287..637Y| issue=5453}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=Bever&gt;{{cite journal|author=Bever, S.|author2=Kwon, Y.-K.|author3=Tomanek, D.|title=Unusually high thermal conductivity of carbon nanotubes|journal=Phys. Rev. Lett.|volume=84|issue=20|pages=4613–4616|year=2000|doi=10.1103/PhysRevLett.84.4613|arxiv=cond-mat/0002414|bibcode=2000PhRvL..84.4613B|pmid=10990753}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=Kim&gt;{{cite journal|author=Kim, P.|author2=Shi, L.|author3=Majumdar, A.|author4=McEuen, P.L.|title=Thermal transport measurements of individual multi walled nanotubes|journal=Phys. Rev. Lett.|volume=87|issue=21|pages=215502|year=2001|doi=10.1103/PhysRevLett.87.215502|arxiv=cond-mat/0106578|pmid=11736348}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=Nikolaos&gt;{{cite journal|title = Current progress on the chemical modification of carbon nanotubes|journal = Chemical Reviews|date = 2010-06-14|pages = 5366–5397|volume = 110|issue = 9|doi = 10.1021/cr100018g|first = Nikolaos|last = Karousis|first2 = Nikos|last2 = Tagmatarchis|first3 = Dimitrios|last3 = Tasis|pmid=20545303}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=Zhang&gt;{{cite journal | doi = 10.1021/nn401995z| pmid = 23806050| title = Growth of Half-Meter Long Carbon Nanotubes Based on Schulz–Flory Distribution| journal = ACS Nano| volume = 7| issue = 7| pages = 6156–6161| year = 2013| last1 = Zhang | first1 = R. | last2 = Zhang | first2 = Y. | last3 = Zhang | first3 = Q. | last4 = Xie | first4 = H. | last5 = Qian | first5 = W. | last6 = Wei | first6 = F. | url = https://figshare.com/articles/Growth_of_Half_Meter_Long_Carbon_Nanotubes_Based_on_Schulz_Flory_Distribution/2393992}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=Hamada&gt;{{cite journal|author=Hamada, N.|author2=Sawada, S.|author3=Oshiyama, A.|title=New one-dimensional conductors: graphitic microtubules|journal=Phys. Rev. Lett.|volume=68|issue=10|pages=1579–1581|year=1992|doi=10.1103/PhysRevLett.68.1579|bibcode=1992PhRvL..68.1579H|pmid=10045167}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!--&lt;ref name=jana2013extr&gt;{{cite journal|last=Janas|first=Dawid|last2=Vilatela|first2=Andrea C.|last3=Koziol|first3=Krzysztof K.K.|date=October 2013|title=Performance of carbon nanotube wires in extreme conditions|journal=Carbon|volume=62|pages=438–446|doi=10.1016/j.carbon.2013.06.029}}&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt;

&lt;!--&lt;ref name=jana2018chir&gt;{{cite journal|last=Janas|first=Dawid|date=2018|title=Towards monochiral carbon nanotubes: a review of progress in the sorting of single-walled carbon nanotubes|journal=Materials Chemistry Frontiers|volume=2|issue=1|pages=36–63|doi=10.1039/C7QM00427C|issn=2052-1537}}&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt;

&lt;/references&gt;

== External links ==
{{external links|date=September 2015}}
{{Commons|Carbon nanotube}}
{{Scholia}}
* {{Britannica|956965|Carbon nanotube (chemical compound)}}
* [https://www.wecanfigurethisout.org/VL/Nanocarbon.htm Nanocarbon: From Graphene to Buckyballs]. Interactive 3D models of cyclohexane, benzene, graphene, graphite, chiral &amp; non-chiral nanotubes, and C60 Buckyballs - WeCanFigureThisOut.org. 
* [http://www.pa.msu.edu/cmp/csc/nanotube.html The Nanotube site]. Last updated 2013.04.12
* [http://www.carbio.eu/ EU Marie Curie Network CARBIO: Multifunctional carbon nanotubes for biomedical applications]
* [http://xstructure.inr.ac.ru/x-bin/theme3.py?level=2&amp;index1=127236 Carbon nanotube on arxiv.org]
* [http://www.vega.org.uk/video/programme/223 C&lt;sub&gt;60&lt;/sub&gt; and Carbon Nanotubes a short video explaining how nanotubes can be made from modified graphite sheets and the three different types of nanotubes that are formed]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20160303220044/http://education.mrsec.wisc.edu/143.htm Carbon Nanotubes &amp; Buckyballs].
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20140610030921/http://students.chem.tue.nl/ifp03/Wondrous%20World%20of%20Carbon%20Nanotubes_Final.pdf The Wondrous World of Carbon Nanotubes]
* Learning module for [http://nanohub.org/resources/2762 Bandstructure of Carbon Nanotubes and Nanoribbons]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20110601211511/http://www.safeworkaustralia.gov.au/AboutSafeWorkAustralia/WhatWeDo/Publications/Pages/DurabilityCarbonNanotubes.aspx Durability of carbon nanotubes and their potential to cause inflammation] by Dr Megan Osmond and others. (SafeWork Australia, May 2011). This was a collaboration between the [[Institute of Occupational Medicine]], Edinburgh University and CSIRO in Australia.
* [http://stacks.iop.org/1367-2630/5/i=1/a=E04 Selection of free-download articles on carbon nanotubes]
* [https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/science-environment-24232896 First computer made of carbon nanotubes is unveiled], [[BBC News]] 2013-09-25
* [http://nano.byu.edu/projects.php Research using carbon nanotubes for microfabrication and in other applications]
* [https://demonstrations.wolfram.com/ElectronicBandStructureOfASingleWalledCarbonNanotubeByTheZon/ WOLFRAM Demonstrations Project: Electronic Band Structure of a Single-Walled Carbon Nanotube by the Zone-Folding Method]
* [http://www.demonstrations.wolfram.com/ElectronicStructureOfASingleWalledCarbonNanotubeInTightBindi/ WOLFRAM Demonstrations Project: Electronic Structure of a Single-Walled Carbon Nanotube in Tight-Binding Wannier Representation]

{{Allotropes of carbon}}
{{Emerging technologies in materials science}}
{{Space elevator}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Carbon Nanotube}}
[[Category:Carbon forms]]
[[Category:Carbon nanotubes| ]]
[[Category:Emerging technologies]]
[[Category:Transparent electrodes]]
[[Category:Refractory materials]]
[[Category:Space elevator]]</text>
      <sha1>drdjb60zm6rjvc9861wfjf808hmzw08</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
