  <page>
    <title>Commentary</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5342</id>
    <revision>
      <id>935256317</id>
      <parentid>934674984</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-11T14:45:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>A-NEUN</username>
        <id>35805243</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/2001:8004:C82:9D5A:9C4F:5DF8:6D6E:C409|2001:8004:C82:9D5A:9C4F:5DF8:6D6E:C409]] identified as test/vandalism using [[WP:STiki|STiki]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{wiktionary|commentary|commentaries}}
'''Commentary''' or '''commentaries''' may refer to:

==Publications==
* [[Commentary (magazine)|''Commentary'' (magazine)]], a U.S. public affairs journal, founded in 1945 and formerly published by the American Jewish Committee
* [[Caesar's Commentaries (disambiguation)]], a number of works by or attributed to Julius Caesar
* ''Commentaries'' of [[Ishodad of Merv]], set of ninth-century Syriac treatises on the Bible
* ''[[Commentaries on the Laws of England]]'', a 1769 treatise on the common law of England by Sir William Blackstone
* ''[[Commentaries on Living]]'', a series of books by Jiddu Krishnamurti originally published in 1956, 1958 and 1960
* ''[[Commentary on Job]]'', a sixth-century treatise by Saint Gregory
* ''[[Commentary of Zuo]]'', one of the earliest Chinese works of narrative history, covering the period from 722 to 468 BCE
* ''Commentaries'', a work attributed to [[Taautus]]

==Other uses==
* Published [[opinion piece]] material, in any of several forms:
** An [[editorial]], written by the editorial staff or board of a newspaper, magazine, or other periodical
** [[Column (periodical)]], a regular feature of such a publication in which usually the same single writer offers advice, observation, or other commentary 
** An [[op-ed]], an opinion piece by an author unaffiliated with the publication
** [[Letters to the editor]], written by readers of such a publication
** Posts made in the [[comments section]] of an online publication, serving a similar function to paper periodicals' letters to the editor
* [[Commentary (philology)]], a line-by-line or even word-by-word explication (and usually translation) of a text
* [[Audio commentary]] track for DVDs and Blu-Rays – an additional audio track that plays in real-time with the video material, and comments on that video
* [[Sports commentary]] or play-by-play,  a running description of a game or event in real time, usually during a live broadcast
** [[Color commentary]], supplementing play-by-play commentary, often filling in any time when play is not in progress
* [[Atthakatha]], commentaries on the Pāli Canon in Theravāda Buddhism
* [[Criticism]], the practice of judging the merits and faults of something or someone
* ''Commentary! The Musical'', the musical commentary accompanying ''[[Dr. Horrible's Sing-Along Blog]]''
* Commentary or narration, the words in a [[documentary film]]
* [[Exegesis]], a critical explanation or interpretation of a text, especially a religious text (e.g. a Bible commentary)
* [[Literary criticism]], the study, evaluation, and interpretation of literature
** [[Close reading]] in literary criticism, the careful, sustained interpretation of a brief passage of text
* [[Political criticism]] or political commentary, criticism that is specific of or relevant to politics
** [[Public comment]]ary received by governmental and other bodies, e.g. in response to proposals, reports, etc.

==See also==
* [[Commentry]], a place in central France
* [[Comment (disambiguation)]]
* [[List of biblical commentaries]]
* [[Jewish commentaries on the Bible]]

{{disambiguation}}</text>
      <sha1>i7wijp3cyk6f8dzf9l69g4p4bro5f8g</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
