  <page>
    <title>History of Chad</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5329</id>
    <revision>
      <id>940391296</id>
      <parentid>928756818</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-12T08:00:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>嘉傑</username>
        <id>34373489</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* The Tombalbaye era (1960&amp;ndash;1975) */ The title of former Libyan leader [[Muammar Gaddafi]] was &quot;[[Brotherly Leader and Guide of the Revolution|Brotherly Leader]]&quot;, not [[List of heads of state of Libya|President]].</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{History of Chad}}
'''Chad''' ({{lang-ar|تشاد }}; {{lang-fr|Tchad}}), officially the '''Republic of Chad''', is a [[landlocked]] country in [[West Africa]]. It borders [[Libya]] to the north, [[Sudan]] to the east, the [[Central African Republic]] to the south, [[Cameroon]] and [[Nigeria]] to the southwest, and [[Niger]] to the west. Due to its distance from the sea and its largely [[desert]] climate, the country is sometimes referred to as the &quot;Dead Heart of Africa&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.guernicamag.com/features/199/swarms_at_the_border/|title=Swarms at the Border: The Dead Heart of Africa|date=2006-07-10|website=Guernica Magazine|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080720105047/http://www.guernicamag.com/features/199/swarms_at_the_border/|archive-date=2008-07-20|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Prehistory==
[[Image:Sahelanthropus tchadensis - TM 266 location.jpg|thumb|Location of ''Sahelanthropus tchadensis'' find in 2002.]]The territory now known as [[Chad]] possesses some of the richest [[archaeological site]]s in [[Africa]].&lt;ref name=&quot;locchad&quot;&gt;{{Citation
 | editor-last =Collier
 | editor-first =John L.
 | title =Chad : A Country Study
 | series =Library of Congress Country Studies
 | url =http://lcweb2.loc.gov/frd/cs/tdtoc.html
|accessdate=2011-02-08
|edition=2nd
|year=1990
|publisher=Library of Congress
|location=Washington, D.C.
|isbn=0-16-024770-5
|chapter=Historical Setting
|page=13
}}&lt;/ref&gt; A [[hominid skull]] was found by [[Michel Brunet (paleontologist)|Michel Brunet]] in 2002, in [[Borkou]], that is more than 7 million years old, the oldest discovered anywhere in the world; it has been given the name [[Sahelanthropus tchadensis]]. In 1996 Michel Brunet had unearthed a hominid [[jaw]] which he named [[Australopithecus bahrelghazali]], and unofficially dubbed [[Abel (hominid)|Abel]]. It was dated using [[Beryllium]] based [[Radiometric dating]] as living circa. 3.6 million years ago.

During the [[7th millennium BC]], the northern half of Chad was part of a broad expanse of land, stretching from the [[Indus River]] in the east to the [[Atlantic Ocean]] in the west, in which [[ecology|ecological]] conditions favored early human settlement. [[Rock art]] of the &quot;Round Head&quot; style, found in the [[Ennedi]] region, has been dated to before the 7th millennium BC and, because of the tools with which the rocks were carved and the scenes they depict, may represent the oldest evidence in the [[Sahara]] of [[Neolithic]] industries. Many of the [[pottery]]-making and Neolithic activities in Ennedi date back further than any of those of the [[Nile]] Valley to the east.&lt;ref name=&quot;locchad&quot; /&gt;

In the [[prehistory|prehistoric]] period, Chad was much wetter than it is today, as evidenced by large game animals depicted in [[Cave painting|rock paintings]] in the [[Tibesti]] and Borkou regions.&lt;ref name=&quot;locchad&quot; /&gt;

Recent linguistic research suggests that all of [[Africa]]'s major language groupings south of the Sahara Desert (except [[Khoisan languages|Khoisan]], which is not considered a valid genetic grouping anyway), i. e. the [[Afro-Asiatic languages|Afro-Asiatic]], [[Nilo-Saharan languages|Nilo-Saharan]] and [[Niger–Congo languages|Niger–Congo]] [[Language family#Subdivision|phyla]], originated in prehistoric times in a narrow band between [[Lake Chad]] and the Nile Valley. The origins of Chad's peoples, however, remain unclear. Several of the proven archaeological sites have been only partially studied, and other sites of great potential have yet to be mapped.&lt;ref name=&quot;locchad&quot; /&gt;

==Era of Empires (AD 900&amp;ndash;1900)==
At the end of the 1st millennium AD, the formation of states began across central Chad in the [[sahel]]ian zone between the [[desert]] and the [[savanna]]. For almost the next 1,000 years, these states, their relations with each other, and their effects on the peoples who lived in stateless societies along their peripheries dominated Chad's political history. Recent research suggests that indigenous [[History of Africa|Africans]] founded of these states, not migrating [[Arabic language|Arabic-speaking]] groups, as was believed previously. Nonetheless, immigrants, [[Arab]]ic-speaking or otherwise, played a significant role, along with [[Islam]], in the formation and early evolution of these states.&lt;ref name=&quot;locchad14&quot;&gt;Collier 1990 p.14&lt;/ref&gt;

Most states began as [[monarchy|kingdoms]], in which the [[monarch|king]] was considered divine and endowed with temporal and spiritual powers. All states were [[militarism|militaristic]] (or they did not survive long), but none was able to expand far into southern Chad, where forests and the [[tsetse fly]] complicated the use of [[cavalry]]. Control over the [[trans-Saharan trade]] routes that passed through the region formed the economic basis of these kingdoms. Although many states rose and fell, the most important and durable of the empires were [[Kanem Empire|Kanem-Bornu]], [[Kingdom of Baguirmi|Baguirmi]], and [[Ouaddai Empire|Ouaddai]], according to most written sources (mainly [[Noble court|court]] [[chronicle]]s and writings of Arab [[merchant|traders]] and travelers).&lt;ref name=&quot;locchad14&quot; /&gt;[http://countrystudies.us/chad/5.htm]

===Kanem-Bornu===
{{main|Kanem-Bornu Empire}}
The Kanem Empire originated in the 9th century AD to the northeast of [[Lake Chad]]. Historians agree that the leaders of the new state were ancestors of the [[Kanem Empire|Kanembu]] people. Toward the end of the 11th century the [[Sayfawa dynasty|Sayfawa]] king (or ''mai'', the title of the Sayfawa rulers) [[Hummay]], converted to Islam. In the following century the Sayfawa rulers expanded southward into [[Kanem (region)|Kanem]], where was to rise their first capital, [[Njimi]]. Kanem's expansion peaked during the long and energetic reign of Mai [[Dunama Dabbalemi]] (c. 1221&amp;ndash;1259).&lt;ref name=&quot;locchad15&quot;&gt;Collier 1990 p. 15&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:Group of Kanem-Bu warriors.jpg|thumb|200px|left|Group of Kanem-Bu warriors]]

By the end of the 14th century, internal struggles and external attacks had torn Kanem apart. Finally, around 1396 the [[Bulala]] invaders forced ''Mai'' [[Umar Idrismi]] to abandon Njimi and move the Kanembu people to [[Borno State|Bornu]] on the western edge of Lake Chad. Over time, the intermarriage of the Kanembu and Bornu peoples created a new people and language, the [[Kanuri people|Kanuri]], and founded a new capital, [[Ngazargamu]].&lt;ref name=&quot;locchad15&quot; /&gt;

Kanem-Bornu peaked during the reign of the outstanding statesman ''Mai'' [[Idris Aluma]] (c. 1571&amp;ndash;1603). Aluma is remembered for his military skills, administrative reforms, and Islamic piety. The administrative reforms and military brilliance of Aluma sustained the empire until the mid-17th century, when its power began to fade. By the early 19th century, Kanem-Bornu was clearly an empire in decline, and in 1808 [[Fulani Empire|Fulani]] warriors conquered Ngazargamu. Bornu survived, but the Sayfawa dynasty ended in 1846 and the Empire itself fell in 1893.&lt;ref name=&quot;locchad15&quot; /&gt;

===Baguirmi and Ouaddai===
{{main|Kingdom of Baguirmi|Ouaddai Kingdom}}
In addition to Kanem-Bornu, two other states in the region, [[Kingdom of Baguirmi|Baguirmi]] and [[Ouaddai Kingdom|Ouaddai]], achieved historical prominence. Baguirmi emerged to the southeast of Kanem-Bornu in the 16th century. [[Islam]] was adopted, and the state became a [[sultan]]ate. Absorbed into Kanem-Bornu, Baguirmi broke free later in the 17th century, only to be returned to [[tribute|tributary]] status in the mid-18th century. Early in the 19th century, Baguirmi fell into decay and was threatened militarily by the nearby kingdom of Ouaddai. Although Baguirmi resisted, it accepted tributary status in order to obtain help from Ouaddai in putting down internal dissension. When the capital was burned in 1893, the sultan sought and received [[protectorate]] status from the [[French colonial empires|French]].&lt;ref name=&quot;locchad16&quot;&gt;Collier 1990 p. 16&lt;/ref&gt;

Located in northeast of Baguirmi, Ouaddai was a non-Muslim kingdom that emerged in the 16th century as an offshoot of the state of [[Darfur]] (in present-day [[Sudan]]). Early in the 12th century, groups in the region rallied to [[Abd al-Karim Sabun]], who overthrew the ruling [[Tunjur]] group, transforming Ouaddai into an Islamic [[sultan]]ate. During much of the 18th century, Ouaddai resisted reincorporation into Darfur.&lt;ref name=&quot;locchad16&quot; /&gt;

In about 1804, under the rule of Sabun, the sultanate began to expand its power. A new trade route north was discovered, and Sabun outfitted royal caravans to take advantage of it. He began minting his own coinage and imported [[chain mail]], [[firearm]]s, and military advisers from [[North Africa]]. Sabun's successors were less able than he, and Darfur took advantage of a disputed political succession in 1838 to put its own candidate in power. This tactic backfired when Darfur's choice, [[Muhammad Sharif of Ouaddai|Muhammad Sharif]], rejected Darfur and asserted his own authority. In doing so, he gained acceptance from Ouaddai's various factions and went on to become Ouaddai's ablest ruler. Sharif eventually established Ouaddai's hegemony over Baguirmi and kingdoms as far away as the [[Chari River]]. The Ouaddai opposed French domination until well into the 20th century.&lt;ref name=&quot;locchad16&quot; /&gt;

==Colonialism (1900&amp;ndash;1940)==
{{main|French Chad|French Equatorial Africa}}
[[Image:Mort du Commandant Lamy.jpg|thumb|200px|Death of Commander Lamy of France, 1900]]The [[France|French]] first penetrated Chad in 1891, establishing their authority through military expeditions primarily against the Muslim kingdoms. The decisive colonial battle for Chad was fought on April 22, 1900 at [[Battle of Kousséri]] between forces of French [[Major]] [[Amédée-François Lamy]] and forces of the [[Sudan]]ese warlord [[Rabih az-Zubayr]]. Both leaders were killed in the battle.

In 1905, administrative responsibility for Chad was placed under a [[governor-general]] stationed at [[Brazzaville]], capital of [[French Equatorial Africa]] (AEF). Chad did not have a separate colonial status until 1920, when it was placed under a [[lieutenant-governor]] stationed in [[Fort-Lamy]] (today N'Djamena).&lt;ref name=&quot;locchad17&quot;&gt;Collier 1990 p. 17&lt;/ref&gt;

Two fundamental themes dominated Chad's colonial experience with the French: an absence of policies designed to unify the territory and an exceptionally slow pace of [[modernization]]. In the French scale of priorities, the [[colony]] of Chad ranked near the bottom, and the French came to perceive Chad primarily as a source of raw [[cotton]] and [[manual labour|untrained labour]] to be used in the more productive colonies to the south.&lt;ref name=&quot;locchad17&quot; /&gt;

Throughout the colonial period, large areas of Chad were never governed effectively: in the huge [[BET Prefecture]], the handful of French military administrators usually left the people alone, and in central Chad, French rule was only slightly more substantive. Truly speaking, France managed to govern effectively only the south.&lt;ref name=&quot;locchad17&quot; /&gt;

==Decolonization (1940&amp;ndash;1960)==
{{main|Decolonization in Chad}}
[[Image:Eboue wwII prop 03-0118a.jpg|thumb|200px|Félix Éboué in a contemporary World War II cartoon]]During [[World War II]], Chad was the first French [[colony]] to rejoin the [[Allies of World War II|Allies]] (August 26, 1940), after the [[Battle of France|defeat of France by Germany]]. Under the administration of [[Félix Éboué]], France's first black colonial governor, a military column, commanded by Colonel [[Philippe Leclerc de Hauteclocque]], and including two battalions of [[Sara people|Sara]] troops, moved north from [[N'Djamena]] (then Fort Lamy) to engage [[Axis powers of World War II|Axis]] forces in [[Libya]], where, in partnership with the British Army's [[Long Range Desert Group]], they captured [[Kufra]]. On 21 January 1942, N'Djamena was [[Sonderkommando Blaich|bombed]] by a German aircraft.

After the war ended, local parties started to develop in Chad. The first to be born was the radical [[Chadian Progressive Party]] (PPT) in February 1947, initially headed by Panamanian born [[Gabriel Lisette]], but from 1959 headed by [[François Tombalbaye]]. The more conservative [[Chadian Democratic Union]] (UDT) was founded in November 1947 and represented French commercial interests and a bloc of traditional leaders composed primarily of Muslim and [[Ouaddai Kingdom|Ouaddaïan]] nobility.  The confrontation between the PPT and UDT was more than simply ideological; it represented different regional identities, with the PPT representing the Christian and [[Animism|animist]] south and the UDT the Islamic north.

The PPT won the May 1957 pre-independence elections thanks to a greatly expanded franchise, and Lisette led the government of the Territorial Assembly until he lost a confidence vote on 11 February 1959. After a referendum on territorial autonomy on 28 September 1958, French Equatorial Africa was dissolved, and its four constituent states &amp;ndash; [[Gabon]], [[Republic of the Congo|Congo (Brazzaville)]], the [[Central African Republic]], and Chad became autonomous members of the [[French Community]] from 28 November 1958. Following Lisette's fall in February 1959 the opposition leaders [[Gontchome Sahoulba]] and [[Ahmed Koulamallah]] could not form a stable government, so the PPT was again asked to form an administration - which it did under the leadership of François Tombalbaye on 26 March 1959. On 12 July 1960 France agreed to Chad becoming fully independent.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=https://select.nytimes.com/mem/archive/pdf?res=F00D1FFA3D581A7A93C1A8178CD85F448685F9 | work=The New York Times | first=W. Granger | last=Blair | title=3 More Nations Gain Freedom Through Pacts Signed by France; Congo, Central African and Chad Republics Are Given Sovereignty in Paris | date=July 13, 1960}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 11 August 1960, Chad became an independent country and François Tombalbaye became its first president.

==The Tombalbaye era (1960&amp;ndash;1975)==
{{main|The Tombalbaye Regime}}
One of the most prominent aspects of Tombalbaye's rule to prove itself was his authoritarianism and distrust of democracy. Already in January 1962 he banned all political parties except his own PPT, and started immediately concentrating all power in his own hands. His treatment of opponents, real or imagined, was extremely harsh, filling the prisons with thousands of political prisoners.

What was even worse was his constant discrimination against the central and northern regions of Chad, where the southern Chadian administrators came to be perceived as arrogant and incompetent. This resentment at last exploded in a tax revolt on November 1, 1965, in the [[Guéra Prefecture]], causing 500 deaths. The year after saw the birth in [[Sudan]] of the [[FROLINAT|National Liberation Front of Chad]] (FROLINAT), created to militarily oust Tombalbaye and the Southern dominance. It was the start of a bloody civil war.

Tombalbaye resorted to calling in French troops; while moderately successful, they were not fully able to quell the insurgency. Proving more fortunate was his choice to break with the French and seek friendly ties with [[Libya]]n [[Brotherly Leader and Guide of the Revolution|Brotherly Leader]] [[Muammar Gaddafi|Gaddafi]], taking away the rebels' principal source of supplies.

But while he had reported some success against the rebels, Tombalbaye started behaving more and more irrationally and brutally, continuously eroding his consensus among the southern elites, which dominated all key positions in the army, the civil service and the ruling party. As a consequence on April 13, 1975, several units of N'Djamena's [[gendarmerie]] [[Chadian coup of 1975|killed Tombalbaye during a coup]].

==Military rule (1975&amp;ndash;1978)==
{{main|Malloum's military government}}
The [[coup d'état]] that terminated Tombalbaye's government received an enthusiastic response in [[N'Djamena]]. The southerner [[General]] [[Félix Malloum]] emerged early as the chairman of the new ''[[Military dictatorship|junta]]''.

The new military leaders were unable to retain for long the popularity that they had gained through their overthrow of Tombalbaye. Malloum proved himself unable to cope with the [[FROLINAT]] and at the end decided his only chance was in coopting some of the rebels: in 1978 he allied himself with the insurgent leader [[Hissène Habré]], who entered the government as prime minister.

==Civil war (1979-1982)==
{{main|Transitional Government of National Unity}}
Internal dissent within the government led Prime Minister Habré to send his forces against Malloum's national army in the capital in February 1979. Malloum was ousted from the presidency, but the resulting civil war amongst the 11 emergent factions was so widespread that it rendered the central government largely irrelevant. At that point, other African governments decided to intervene.

A series of four international conferences held first under Nigerian and then [[Organization of African Unity]] (OAU) sponsorship attempted to bring the Chadian factions together. At the fourth conference, held in [[Lagos]], [[Nigeria]], in August 1979, the Lagos Accord was signed. This accord established a transitional government pending national elections. In November 1979, the [[Transitional Government of National Unity]] (GUNT) was created with a mandate to govern for 18 months. [[Goukouni Oueddei]], a northerner, was named president; Colonel [[Wadel Abdelkader Kamougué|Kamougué]], a southerner, Vice President; and Habré, Minister of Defense. This coalition proved fragile; in January 1980, fighting broke out again between Goukouni's and Habré's forces. With assistance from [[Libya]], Goukouni regained control of the capital and other urban centers by year’s end. However, Goukouni’s January 1981 statement that Chad and [[Libya]] had agreed to work for the realization of complete unity between the two countries generated intense international pressure and Goukouni's subsequent call for the complete withdrawal of external forces.

==The Habré era (1982&amp;ndash;1990)==
:''see: [[Chadian-Libyan conflict]]''
Libya's partial withdrawal to the [[Aozou Strip]] in northern Chad cleared the way for Habré's forces to enter N’Djamena in June. French troops and an OAU peacekeeping force of 3,500 Nigerian, [[Senegal]]ese, and [[Zaire|Zairian]] troops (partially funded by the [[United States]]) remained neutral during the conflict.
[[File:Tschad GUNT.jpg|thumb|The [[Aozou Strip]] (dark green), claimed and occupied by Libya between 1976 and 1987, and territories held by Libyan-backed GUNT-forces (light green)]]

Habré continued to face armed opposition on various fronts, and was brutal in his repression of suspected opponents, massacring and torturing many during his rule. In the summer of 1983, GUNT forces launched an offensive against government positions in northern and eastern Chad with heavy Libyan support. In response to Libya's direct intervention, French and Zairian forces intervened to defend Habré, pushing Libyan and rebel forces north of the [[16th parallel north|16th parallel]]. In September 1984, the French and the Libyan governments announced an agreement for the mutual withdrawal of their forces from Chad. By the end of the year, all French and Zairian troops were withdrawn. Libya did not honor the withdrawal accord, and its forces continued to occupy the northern third of Chad.

Rebel commando groups ([[Codos]]) in southern Chad were broken up by government massacres in 1984. In 1985 Habré briefly reconciled with some of his opponents, including the [[Democratic Front of Chad]] (FDT) and the [[Coordinating Action Committee of the Democratic Revolutionary Council]]. Goukouni also began to rally toward Habré, and with his support Habré successfully expelled Libyan forces from most of Chadian territory. A cease-fire between Chad and Libya held from 1987 to 1988, and negotiations over the next several years led to the 1994 International Court of Justice decision granting Chad sovereignty over the Aouzou strip, effectively ending Libyan occupation.

==The Déby era==

===Rise to power===
However, rivalry between [[Hadjerai]], [[Zaghawa people|Zaghawa]] and [[Gorane]] groups within the government grew in the late 1980s. In April 1989, [[Idriss Déby]], one of Habré's leading generals and a Zaghawa, defected and fled to [[Darfur]] in Sudan, from which he mounted a Zaghawa-supported series of attacks on Habré (a Gorane). In December 1990, with Libyan assistance and no opposition from French troops stationed in Chad, Déby’s forces successfully marched on N’Djamena. After 3 months of provisional government, Déby’s [[Patriotic Salvation Movement]] (MPS) approved a national charter on February 28, 1991, with Déby as president.

During the next two years, Déby faced at least two coup attempts. Government forces clashed violently with rebel forces, including the Movement for Democracy and Development, MDD, National Revival Committee for Peace and Democracy (CSNPD), Chadian National Front (FNT) and the Western Armed Forces (FAO), near [[Lake Chad]] and in southern regions of the country. Earlier French demands for the country to hold a National Conference resulted in the gathering of 750 delegates representing political parties (which were legalized in 1992), the government, trade unions and the army to discuss the creation of a pluralist democratic regime.

However, unrest continued, sparked in part by large-scale killings of civilians in southern Chad. The CSNPD, led by [[Kette Moise]] and other southern groups entered into a peace agreement with government forces in 1994, which later broke down. Two new groups, the [[Armed Forces for a Federal Republic]] (FARF) led by former Kette ally [[Laokein Barde]] and the Democratic Front for Renewal (FDR), and a reformulated MDD clashed with government forces from 1994 to 1995.

===Multiparty elections===
{{see also|Elections in Chad}}
Talks with political opponents in early 1996 did not go well, but Déby announced his intent to hold presidential elections in June. Déby won the country’s first multi-party presidential elections with support in the second round from opposition leader Kebzabo, defeating General Kamougue (leader of the 1975 coup against Tombalbaye). Déby’s MPS party won 63 of 125 seats in the January 1997 legislative elections. International observers noted numerous serious irregularities in presidential and legislative election proceedings.

By mid-1997 the government signed peace deals with FARF and the MDD leadership and succeeded in cutting off the groups from their rear bases in the Central African Republic and Cameroon. Agreements also were struck with rebels from the National Front of Chad (FNT) and Movement for Social Justice and Democracy in October 1997. However, peace was short-lived, as FARF rebels clashed with government soldiers, finally surrendering to government forces in May 1998. Barde was killed in the fighting, as were hundreds of other southerners, most civilians.

Since October 1998, Chadian Movement for Justice and Democracy (MDJT) rebels, led by [[Youssuf Togoimi]] until his death in September 2002, have skirmished with government troops in the Tibesti region, resulting in hundreds of civilian, government, and rebel casualties, but little ground won or lost. No active armed opposition has emerged in other parts of Chad, although Kette Moise, following senior postings at the Ministry of Interior, mounted a smallscale local operation near [[Moundou]] which was quickly and violently suppressed by government forces in late 2000.

Déby, in the mid-1990s, gradually restored basic functions of government and entered into agreements with the [[World Bank]] and [[International Monetary Fund|IMF]] to carry out substantial economic reforms. Oil exploitation in the southern Doba region began in June 2000, with World Bank Board approval to finance a small portion of a project, the [[Chad-Cameroon Petroleum Development Project]], aimed at transport of Chadian crude through a 1000-km buried pipeline through Cameroon to the [[Gulf of Guinea]]. The project established unique mechanisms for World Bank, private sector, government, and civil society collaboration to guarantee that future oil revenues benefit local populations and result in poverty alleviation. Success of the project depended on [http://go.worldbank.org/5MGHQ1ZQ01 multiple monitoring efforts]&lt;ref&gt;International Advisory Group, External Compliance Monitoring Group, Collège de Contrôle et de Surveillance des Revenues Pétroliers (CCSRP),  World Bank Inspection Panel, Comité Technique National de Suivi et de Contrôle (CTNSC).&lt;/ref&gt; to ensure that all parties keep their commitments. These &quot;unique&quot; mechanisms for monitoring and revenue management have faced intense criticism from the beginning.&lt;ref&gt;[http://crs.org/publications/showpdf.cfm?pdf_id=187 Gary, Ian (Catholic Relief Services) and Nikki Reisch (Bank Information Center). Chad's Oil: Miracle or Mirage?] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090208080840/http://crs.org/publications/showpdf.cfm?pdf_id=187 |date=2009-02-08 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Debt relief was accorded to Chad in May 2001.

Déby won a flawed 63% first-round victory in May 2001 presidential elections after legislative elections were postponed until spring 2002. Having accused the government of fraud, six opposition leaders were arrested (twice) and one opposition party activist was killed following the announcement of election results. However, despite claims of government corruption, favoritism of Zaghawas, and abuses by the security forces, opposition party and labor union calls for general strikes and more active demonstrations against the government have been unsuccessful. Despite movement toward democratic reform, power remains in the hands of a northern ethnic oligarchy.

In 2003, Chad began receiving refugees from the [[Darfur]] region of western Sudan. More than 200,000 refugees fled the fighting between two rebel groups and government-supported militias known as [[Janjaweed]]. A number of border incidents led to the [[Chadian-Sudanese War]].

===War in the East===
{{main|Chadian Civil War (2005–2010)}}
[[Image:Civil war in Chad.png|thumb|200px|Hot spots in the present civil war.]]The war started on December 23, 2005, when the [[Politics of Chad|government of Chad]] declared a [[war|state of war]] with [[Sudan]] and called for the citizens of [[Chad]] to mobilize themselves against the &quot;common enemy,&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/africa/4556576.stm Chad in 'state of war' with Sudan] by Stephanie Hancock, [[BBC News]].&lt;/ref&gt; which the Chadian government sees as the [[Rally for Democracy and Liberty]] (RDL) militants, Chadian rebels, backed by the [[Sudan]]ese government, and Sudanese militiamen. Militants have attacked villages and towns in eastern Chad, stealing cattle, murdering citizens, and burning houses. Over 200,000 refugees from the [[Darfur]] region of northwestern Sudan currently claim asylum in eastern Chad. Chadian president [[Idriss Déby]] accuses Sudanese President [[Omar Hasan Ahmad al-Bashir]] of trying to &quot;destabilize our country, to drive our people into misery, to create disorder and export the war from Darfur to Chad.&quot;

An attack on the Chadian town of [[Adre, Chad|Adre]] near the Sudanese border led to the deaths of either one hundred rebels, as every news source other than [[CNN]] has reported, or three hundred rebels. The Sudanese government was blamed for the attack, which was the second in the region in three days,&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/africa/4544352.stm Chad fightback 'kills 300 rebels'], [[BBC News]].&lt;/ref&gt; but Sudanese foreign ministry spokesman [[Jamal Mohammed Ibrahim]] denies any Sudanese involvement, &quot;We are not for any escalation with Chad. We technically deny involvement in Chadian internal affairs.&quot; This attack was the final straw that led to the declaration of war by Chad and the alleged deployment of the Chadian airforce into Sudanese airspace, which the Chadian government denies.&lt;ref&gt;Al Jazeera&lt;/ref&gt;

An attack on N'Djamena was defeated on April 13, 2006 in the [[Battle of N'Djamena (2006)|Battle of N'Djamena]]. The President on national radio stated that the situation was under control, but residents, diplomats and journalists reportedly heard shots of weapons fire.

On November 25, 2006, rebels captured the eastern town of [[Abeche]], capital of the [[Ouaddaï Region]] and center for humanitarian aid to the [[Darfur]] region in [[Sudan]]. On the same day, a separate rebel group [[Rally of Democratic Forces]] had captured [[Biltine, Chad|Biltine]]. On November 26, 2006, the Chadian government claimed to have recaptured both towns, although rebels still claimed control of [[Biltine, Chad|Biltine]]. Government buildings and humanitarian aid offices in Abeche were said to have been looted. The Chadian government denied a warning issued by the French Embassy in [[N'Djamena]] that a group of rebels was making its way through the [[Batha Prefecture]] in central Chad. Chad insists that both rebel groups are supported by the Sudanese government.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title= Chad denies rebel move on capital| date=November 26, 2006 | publisher=[[BBC]] | url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/6185074.stm }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===International orphanage scandal===
Nearly 100 children at the center of an international scandal that left them stranded at an orphanage in remote eastern Chad returned home after nearly five months March 14, 2008. The 97 children were taken from their homes in October 2007 by a then-obscure French charity, [[Zoé's Ark]], which claimed they were orphans from [[Sudan]]'s [[War in Darfur|war-torn Darfur region]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title=  Kidnapped Chadian kids reunited with their families| date=March 14, 2008 | publisher=[[CNN]] | url=http://edition.cnn.com/2008/WORLD/africa/03/14/chad.children/index.html }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Rebel attack on Ndjamena ===
{{Main|Battle of N'Djamena (2008)}}
On Friday, February 1, 2008, rebels, an opposition alliance of leaders [[Mahamat Nouri]], a former defense minister, and [[Timane Erdimi]], a nephew of [[Idriss Déby]] who was his chief of staff, attacked the Chadian capital of [[Ndjamena]] - even surrounding the Presidential Palace. But Idris Deby with government troops fought back. French forces flew in ammunition for Chadian government troops but took no active part in the fighting. UN has said that up to 20,000 people left the region, taking refuge in nearby [[Cameroon]] and [[Nigeria]]. Hundreds of people were killed, mostly civilians. The rebels accuse Deby of corruption and embezzling millions in oil revenue. While many Chadians may share that assessment, the uprising appears to be a power struggle within the elite that has long controlled [[Chad]]. The French government believes that the opposition has regrouped east of the capital. Déby has blamed [[Sudan]] for the current unrest in Chad.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title=  Chad's leader asserts he is control| date=February 6, 2008 | publisher=[[Associated Press|AP]] | url=https://news.yahoo.com/s/ap/20080206/ap_on_re_af/chad }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[2010 Sahel famine]]
*[[History of Africa]]
*[[List of heads of government of Chad]]
*[[List of heads of state of Chad]]
*[[List of human evolution fossils]]
*[[Politics of Chad]]
*[[Neolithic Subpluvial]]
* {{illm|Timeline of Chad|fr|Chronologie du Tchad}}

==Further reading==
*Gibbons, Ann.  ''The First Human : The Race to Discover our Earliest Ancestor''. Anchor Books (2007). {{ISBN|978-1-4000-7696-3}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://lcweb2.loc.gov/frd/cs/tdtoc.html The Library of Congress - A Country Study: Chad]

{{Chad topics}}
{{History of Africa}}
{{Former French colonies}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:History Of Chad}}
[[Category:History of Chad| ]]
[[Category:History of Central Africa|*]]
[[Category:History of Africa by country|Chad]]

[[he:צ'אד#היסטוריה]]</text>
      <sha1>q3vjnvkjga6a8687xlifgq0m7k2hqyi</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
