  <page>
    <title>Digital Equipment Corporation</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7952</id>
    <revision>
      <id>939145743</id>
      <parentid>935593189</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-04T17:25:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rescuing 1 sources and tagging 0 as dead.) #IABot (v2.0</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|U.S. computer manufacturer 1957-1998}}
{{distinguish|Digital Research|Western Digital}}
{{Infobox company
| name          = Digital Equipment Corporation
| logo          = [[File:Digital 556-flattened4.svg|Digital Equipment Corporation Logo|frameless]]
| fate          = Acquired by [[Compaq]], after divestiture of major assets.
| successor     = [[Compaq]]&lt;br /&gt;(1998–2002)&lt;br /&gt;[[Hewlett-Packard]]&lt;br /&gt;(2002–2015)&lt;br /&gt;[[HP Inc.]] and [[Hewlett Packard Enterprise]]&lt;br /&gt;(2015–present)
| foundation    = {{Start date and age|1957}}
| defunct       = 1998
| location      = [[Maynard, Massachusetts]], United States
| industry      = [[Computer hardware]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Computer software]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Computer services]]
| key_people    = [[Ken Olsen]] (founder, president, and chairman)&lt;br /&gt;[[Harlan Anderson]] (co-founder)&lt;br /&gt;[[C. Gordon Bell]] (VP Engineering, 1972–83)
| products      = [[Programmed Data Processor|PDP]] minicomputers&lt;br /&gt;[[VAX]] minicomputers&lt;br /&gt;[[DEC Alpha|Alpha]] servers and workstations&lt;br /&gt;[[DECnet]]&lt;br /&gt;[[VT100]] terminal&lt;br /&gt;[[Local Area Transport|LAT]] and [[Terminal server]]&lt;br /&gt;[[StrongARM]] microprocessors&lt;br /&gt;[[Digital Linear Tape]]
| num_employees = over 140,000 (1987)
| parent        =
| subsid        =
}}
'''Digital Equipment Corporation''' ('''DEC''' {{IPAc-en|d|ɛ|k}}), using the [[trademark]] '''Digital''', was a major American company in the [[computer industry]] from the 1960s to the 1990s. The company was co-founded by [[Ken Olsen]] and [[Harlan Anderson]] in 1957. Olsen was president until forced to resign in 1992, after the company had gone into precipitous decline.

DEC was a leading vendor of computer systems, including computers, software, and [[computer peripheral|peripherals]]. Their [[Programmed Data Processor|PDP]] and successor [[VAX]] products were the most successful of all [[minicomputer]]s in terms of sales.

DEC was acquired in June 1998 by [[Compaq]] in what was at that time the largest merger in the history of the computer industry. At the time, Compaq was focused on the [[Enterprise software|enterprise market]] and had recently purchased several other large vendors. DEC was a major player overseas where Compaq had less presence. However, Compaq had little idea what to do with its acquisitions,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Dell topples Compaq in U.S. market share
|url=https://www.cnet.com/news/dell-topples-compaq-in-u-s-market-share}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;What was left was a stalled engine with a very expensive head count.&quot; &quot;Buying Digital played into Eckhard's fantasy, but it's turning out to be a beast that's consuming the company,&quot; said one former executive who left before the acquisition. {{cite web
|title=Compaq Message Board - Msg: 9675868 |url=http://www.siliconinvestor.com/readmsg.aspx?msgid=9675868}}&lt;/ref&gt; and soon found itself in financial difficulty of its own. The company subsequently merged with [[Hewlett-Packard]] (HP) in May 2002. {{As of|2007}}, PDP-11, VAX, and [[AlphaServer]] systems were still produced under the HP name.

==History==
{{main|History of Digital Equipment Corporation}}

From 1957 until 1992, DEC's headquarters were located in a former wool mill in [[Maynard, Massachusetts]]. The headquarter buildings were vacated in 1993, renamed Clock Tower Place,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web  |website=TownOfMaynard-MA.gov
   |url=https://www.townofmaynard-ma.gov/projects/millandmain
   |title=Mill &amp; Main Place Development Project}}&lt;/ref&gt; and subsequently redeveloped as Mill &amp; Main Place, a 1.1 million square foot facility for offices and light industry.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web 
 |url=https://maynard.wickedlocal.com/news/20180806/multi-million-dollar-capital-improvements-completed-on-mill-amp-main
 |title=Multi-million dollar capital improvements completed on Mill &amp; Main  |date=Aug 6, 2018 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Initially focusing on the small end of the computer market allowed DEC to grow without its potential competitors making serious efforts to compete with them. Their PDP series of machines became popular in the 1960s, especially the [[PDP-8]], widely considered to be the first successful [[minicomputer]]. Looking to simplify and update their line, DEC replaced most of their smaller machines with the [[PDP-11]] in 1970, eventually selling over 600,000 units and cementing DEC's position in the industry.

Originally designed as a follow-on to the PDP-11, DEC's [[VAX|VAX-11]] series was the first widely used [[32-bit]] minicomputer, sometimes referred to as &quot;[[Superminicomputer|superminis]]&quot;. These systems were able to compete in many roles with larger [[mainframe computer]]s, such as the [[IBM System/370]]. The VAX was a best-seller, with over 400,000 sold, and its sales through the 1980s propelled the company into the second largest computer company in the industry. At its peak, DEC was the second largest employer in Massachusetts, second only to the Massachusetts State Government.

The rapid rise of the business [[microcomputer]] in the late 1980s, and especially the introduction of powerful 32-bit systems in the 1990s, quickly eroded the value of DEC's systems. DEC's last major attempt to find a space in the rapidly changing market was the [[DEC Alpha]] [[64-bit]] [[RISC]] [[instruction set architecture]]. DEC initially started work on Alpha as a way to re-implement their VAX series, but also employed it in a range of high-performance [[workstation]]s. Although the Alpha processor family met both of these goals, and, for most of its lifetime, was the fastest processor family on the market, extremely high asking prices&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://alasir.com/articles/alpha_history/dec_collapse.shtml|title=Alpha: The History in Facts and Comments - The Collapse of DEC |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120629072105/http://alasir.com/articles/alpha_history/dec_collapse.shtml |archivedate=2012-06-29 |website=Alasir.com |accessdate=2013-07-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{better source|date=April 2013}} were outsold by lower priced x86 chips from Intel and clones such as AMD.

DEC was acquired in June 1998 by [[Compaq]], in what was at that time the largest merger in the history of the computer industry.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Schultz|first1=Randy|title=Compaq to buy DEC|url=http://money.cnn.com/1998/01/26/technology/compaq/|website=CNN Money|accessdate=19 June 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the time, Compaq was focused on the enterprise market and had recently purchased several other large vendors. DEC was a major player overseas where Compaq had less presence. However, Compaq had little idea what to do with its acquisitions, and soon found itself in financial difficulty of its own. The company subsequently merged with [[Hewlett-Packard]] (HP) in May 2002. {{As of|2007}}, some of DEC's product lines were still produced under the HP name.

==Products==
[[File:DEC VAXstation 4000 96 OpenVMS 6.1.jpeg|thumb|right|DEC [[VAXstation]]]]
Beyond DECsystem-10/20, PDP, VAX and Alpha, DEC was well respected for its communication subsystem designs, such as [[Ethernet]], DNA ([[DIGITAL Network Architecture]]:  predominantly DECnet products), DSA (Digital Storage Architecture: disks/tapes/controllers), and its &quot;dumb terminal&quot; subsystems including VT100 and DECserver products.&lt;ref&gt;For in-depth articles regarding DEC technologies, refer to the archived [http://www.hpl.hp.com/hpjournal/dtj/past.htm Digital Technical Journal]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Research==
DEC's Research Laboratories (or Research Labs, as they were commonly known) conducted DEC's corporate research. Some of them were operated by [[Compaq]] and are still operated by [[Hewlett-Packard]]. The laboratories were:

* Western Research Laboratory (WRL) in [[Palo Alto, California]], US
* [[DEC Systems Research Center|Systems Research Center]] (SRC) in [[Palo Alto, California]], US
* Network Systems Laboratory (NSL) in [[Palo Alto, California]], US
* Cambridge Research Laboratory (CRL) in [[Cambridge, Massachusetts]], US
* Paris Research Laboratory (PRL) in [[Paris]], [[France]]
* MetroWest Technology Campus (MTC) in [[Maynard, Massachusetts]], US

Some of the former employees of DEC's Research Labs or DEC's R&amp;D in general include:
* [[Gordon Bell]]: technical visionary, VP Engineering 1972–83; [[Microsoft Research]]
* [[Leonard Bosack]]
* [[Michael Burrows|Mike Burrows]]
* [[Luca Cardelli]]
* [[Dave Cutler]]: led [[RSX-11M]] and [[VAX/VMS]] [[operating system]]s development; then led [[Windows NT]] development at [[Microsoft]]{{discuss|unsourced/exaggerated synopses of notable people}}
* [[Edson deCastro|Ed deCastro]]: co-founder of [[Data General|Data General Corporation]]
* [[Alan Eustace]]
* [[Jim Gettys]]: early developer of [[X Window System]]{{discuss|unsourced/exaggerated synopses of notable people}}
* [[Henri Gouraud (computer scientist)|Henri Gouraud]]
* [[Jim Gray (computer scientist)|Jim Gray]]
*[[Alan Kotok]]
* [[Leslie Lamport]]
* [[Butler Lampson]]
* [[Louis Monier]]
* [[Isaac Nassi]]
* [[Radia Perlman]]
* [[Marcus J. Ranum|Marcus Ranum]]
* [[Brian Reid (computer scientist)|Brian Reid]]
* [[Paul Vixie]]

Some of the former employees of Digital Equipment Corp who were responsible for developing Alpha and StrongARM:
* [[Daniel W. Dobberpuhl]]
* [[Jim Keller (engineer)|Jim Keller]]
* Rich Witek

Some of the work of the Research Labs was published in the ''Digital Technical Journal'',&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hpl.hp.com/hpjournal/dtj/past.htm Digital Technical Journal&amp;nbsp;– Online Issues]&lt;/ref&gt; which was in published from 1985 until 1998.&lt;ref&gt;At least some of the research reports are available online at [ftp://ftp.digital.com/pub/DEC/ ftp.digital.com]{{Dead link|date=January 2020 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }} {{cite web |url=http://ftp.digital.com/pub/DEC/ |title=Unknown |access-date=January 10, 2020}}{{dead link|date=January 2020|bot=medic}}{{cbignore|bot=medic}}, in the subdirectories WRL, SRC, NSL, CRL, PRL (see [[Digital Equipment Corporation#Research|Research]] section). Verified July 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

==Accomplishments and legacy==
DEC supported the [[American National Standards Institute|ANSI]] standards, especially the [[ASCII]] character set, which survives in [[Unicode]] and the [[ISO 8859]] character set family. DEC's own [[Multinational Character Set]] also had a large influence on [[ISO 8859-1]] (Latin-1) and, by extension, Unicode.

===Software===
* The first versions of the [[C (programming language)|C]] language and the [[Unix]] operating system ran on DEC's [[Programmed Data Processor|PDP]] series of computers (first on a PDP-7, then the [[PDP-11]]'s), which were among the first commercially viable [[minicomputer]]s, although for several years DEC itself did not encourage the use of Unix.
* DEC produced widely used and influential interactive operating systems, including [[OS/8|OS-8]], [[TOPS-10]], [[TOPS-20]], [[RSTS/E]], [[RSX-11]], [[RT-11]], and [[OpenVMS]]. PDP computers, in particular the [[PDP-11]] model, inspired a generation of programmers and software developers. Some PDP-11 systems more than 25 years old (software and hardware) are still being used to control and monitor factories, transportation systems and nuclear plants. DEC was an early champion of [[time-sharing]] systems.
* The command-line interfaces found in DEC's systems, eventually codified as [[DIGITAL Command Language|DCL]], would look familiar to any user of modern microcomputer CLIs; those used in earlier systems, such as [[Compatible Time-Sharing System|CTSS]], [[IBM]]'s [[Job Control Language|JCL]], or [[Univac]]'s time-sharing systems, would look utterly alien. Many features of the [[CP/M]] and MS-DOS [[Command-line interface|CLI]] show a recognizable family resemblance to DEC's OSes, including command names such as DIR and HELP and the &quot;name-dot-extension&quot; file naming conventions.
* [[Notes-11]] and its follow-on product, {{anchor|VAX_Notes}}[[VAX Notes]], were two of the first examples of online collaboration software, a category that has become to be known as [[Collaborative software|groupware]]. [[Len Kawell]], one of the original Notes-11 developers later joined [[Lotus Development Corporation]] and contributed to their [[Lotus Notes]] product.
* The [[MUMPS]] programming language, with its built-in database, was developed on the PDP-7, 9, and 15 series machines. MUMPS is still widely used in [[Health informatics|medical informations systems]], such as those provide by [[Meditech]] and [[Epic Systems]].

===Hardware===
* VAX and [[MicroVAX]] computers (very widespread in the 1980s) running [[Virtual Memory System|VMS]] formed one of the most important proprietary networks, [[DECnet]], which linked business and research facilities. The [[DECnet]] protocols formed one of the first peer-to-peer networking standards, with DECnet phase I being released in the mid-1970s. Email, file sharing, and distributed collaborative projects existed within the company long before their value was recognized in the market.
* The LA36 and LA120 [[dot matrix printer]]s became industry standards and may have hastened the demise of the [[Teletype Corporation]].
* The [[VT100]] [[computer terminal]] became the industry standard, implementing a useful subset of the [[ANSI X3.64]] standard, and even today terminal emulators such as [[HyperACCESS|HyperTerminal]], [[PuTTY]] and [[Xterm]] still emulate a VT100 (or its more capable successor, the [[VT220]]).

* DEC invented [[Digital Linear Tape]] (DLT), formerly known as CompacTape, which began as a compact backup medium for MicroVAX systems, and later grew to capacities of 800 gigabytes.
* Work on the first hard-disk-based MP3-player, the [[Personal Jukebox]], started at the [[DEC Systems Research Center]]. (The project was started about a month before the merger into [[Compaq]] was completed.)
* DEC's Western Research Lab created the [[Itsy Pocket Computer]]. This was developed into the Compaq [[iPaq]] line of [[Personal digital assistant|PDAs]], which replaced the [[Compaq Aero]] PDA.

===Networking===
* DEC, [[Intel]] and [[Xerox]] through their collaboration to create the DIX standard, were champions of [[Ethernet]], but DEC is the company that made Ethernet commercially successful. Initially, Ethernet-based DECnet and [[Local Area Transport|LAT]] protocols interconnected VAXes with [[DECserver]] [[terminal server]]s. Starting with the [[Unibus]] to Ethernet adapter, multiple generations of Ethernet hardware from DEC were the de facto standard. The CI &quot;computer interconnect&quot; adapter was the industry's first network interface controller to use separate transmit and receive &quot;rings&quot;.
* DEC also invented [[Computer cluster|clustering]], an operating system technology that treated multiple machines as one logical entity. Clustering permitted sharing of pooled disk and tape storage via the HSC50/70/90 and later series of Hierarchical Storage Controllers (HSC). The HSCs delivered the first hardware [[RAID 0]] and [[RAID 1]] capabilities and the first serial interconnects of multiple storage technologies. This technology was the forerunner to architectures such as [[Network of Workstations]] which are used for massively cooperative tasks such as web-searches and drug research.
* The [[X Window System]] is the network transparent window system used on [[Unix]] and [[Linux]] and available on other operating systems such as [[MacOS]]. It was developed at [[Massachusetts Institute of Technology|MIT]] jointly between [[Project Athena]] and the [[Laboratory for Computer Science]]. DEC was the primary sponsor for the project, which was a contemporary of the [[GNU Project]] but not associated with it.
* In the period 1994–99 [[Linus Torvalds]] developed versions of Linux on early [[AlphaServer]] systems provided by the engineering department.{{Disputed inline|Linux_not_DEC-accomplishment|date=August 2014}} Compaq software engineers developed special Linux kernel modules.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.informatica.co.cr/linux/research/1999/0302-a.htm Compaq was actively participating during the period 1994–99 into the Linux development], verified July 2014&lt;/ref&gt; A well-known [[Linux distribution]] that ran on AlphaServer systems was [[Red Hat]] 7.2.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.informatica.co.cr/linux/research/2002/0108.htm Red Hat and Compaq Announce Port of Red Hat Linux 7.2 to Compaq's Alpha Processors (8 January 2002)], verified July 2014&lt;/ref&gt; Another distribution that ran on Alpha was [[Gentoo Linux]].
* DEC was one of the first businesses connected to the Internet, with ''dec.com'', registered in 1985,&lt;ref&gt;[http://research.microsoft.com/Users/gbell/Digital/timeline/1985-6.htm dec.com&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; being one of the first of the now ubiquitous ''.com'' domains. DEC's ''gatekeeper.dec.com'' was a well-known [[software repository]] during the pre-[[World Wide Web]] days, and DEC was also the first computer vendor to open a public website, on 1 October 1993.&lt;ref&gt;[http://listserv.acsu.buffalo.edu/cgi-bin/wa?A2=ind9402&amp;L=dectei-l&amp;T=0&amp;P=200 DECTEI-L Archives&amp;nbsp;– February 1994 (#2)&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; The popular [[AltaVista]], created by DEC, was one of the first comprehensive Internet [[Search engine (computing)|search engines]]. (Although [[Lycos]] was earlier, it was much more limited.)
* DEC once held the [[Classful network|Class A]] [[IP address]] block 16.0.0.0/8.&lt;ref&gt;[[List of assigned /8 IPv4 address blocks]]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Corporate===
* [[Digital Federal Credit Union]] (DCU) is a [[credit union]] which was chartered in 1979 for employees of DEC. Today its field of membership is open to existing family members, over 900 different sponsors, several communities in Massachusetts and several organizations. Many of the sponsors are companies that had acquired pieces of DEC.{{cn|date=November 2019}}
* [[Matrix management]]

==User organizations==
[[File:DECUS-logo.svg|thumb|DECUS - Logo&lt;br&gt;Digital Equipment Corporation&lt;br&gt;Users Society]]
Originally the [[users' group]] was called [[DECUS]] (Digital Equipment Computer User Society) during the 1960s to 1990s. When [[Compaq]] acquired DEC in 1998, the users group was renamed CUO, the Compaq Users' Organisation. When [[Hewlett-Packard|HP]] acquired [[Compaq]] in 2002, CUO became [[HP-Interex]], although there are still DECUS groups in several countries. In the United States, the organization is represented by the [[Encompass]] organization; currently [[Connect (users group)|Connect]].

=={{visible anchor|Small Computer Handbook}}==
Several editions of the '''Small Computer Handbook''' were published by DEC, giving information about their PDP line of computers.  The editions were:
* Small Computer Handbook (1973)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
   |url=https://archive.org/details/bitsavers_decpdp8hanHandbook1973_79671711
   |title=Small Computer Handbook (1973)}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* PDP8/e, PDP8/m &amp; PDP8/f, Small Computer Handbook&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
   |title=PDP8/e, PDP8/m &amp; PDP8/f, Small Computer handbook (1973)
   |url=https://www.amazon.com/digital-pdp8-small-computer-handbook/dp/B000VAOH4O}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* SMALL COMPUTER HANDBOOK (1970 EDITION)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
   |url=http://www.bitsavers.org/pdf/dec/pdp8/handbooks/SmallComputerHandbook_1970.pdf
   |title=SMALL COMPUTER HANDBOOK (1970 EDITION)}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Web sites with photos of their covers include:
* [http://www.computinghistory.org.uk/det/19232/Digital-Small-Computer-Handbook-1967-Edition  1967 edition (PDP 8/i)]
* [https://www.amazon.com/Small-Computer-Handbook-Various/dp/B000RFA4FE SMALL COMPUTER HANDBOOK]
* [http://dustyoldcomputers.com/pdp-common/books.html pdp-8/e] 
* [https://archive.org/details/bitsavers_decpdp8hanHandbook1973_79671711 1973 edition]
* [http://apple1computer.blogspot.com/2010/03/alleged-woz-bible-small-computer.html Apple Woz  SMALLCOMPUTER HANDBOOK snapshot]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==References==
{{refbegin|30em}}
* (''Present''), [http://research.microsoft.com/en-us/um/people/gbell/digital/DEC%201957%20to%20Present%201978.pdf &quot;Digital Equipment Corporation: Nineteen Fifty-Seven to the Present&quot;], DEC Press, 1978
* {{cite book| author = David Donald Miller| title = Open Vms Operating System Concepts| url = https://books.google.com/?id=FSX5qUthRL8C| year = 1997| publisher = Elsevier| isbn = 978-1-55558-157-2 }}
* {{cite book| author = Alan R. Earls| title = Digital Equipment Corporation| date = 2004-06-30| publisher = Arcadia Publishing| isbn = 978-0-7385-3587-6 }}
* {{cite book| author = Edgar H Schein | author2= with P. DeLisi|author3= P. Kampas |author4= M. Sonduck  |title = DEC is dead, long live DEC| date = 2003-07-01| publisher = Berrett-Koehler Pub| isbn = 978-1-57675-225-8 }}
* {{cite book| author = Jamie Parker Pearson| title = Digital at work: snapshots from the first thirty-five years| date = September 1992| publisher = Digital Press| isbn = 1-55558-092-0 }}
* {{cite book| author = Glenn &amp; George Harrar Rifkin| author2 = George Harrar| title = The Ultimate Entrepreneur: The Story of Ken Olsen and Digital Equipment Corporation| year = 1988| publisher = McGraw-Hill/Contemporary| isbn = 978-0-8092-4559-8| url-access = registration| url = https://archive.org/details/ultimateentrepre00rifk}}
* {{cite book| author = C. Gordon Bell| author2 = J. Craig Mudge| author3 = John E. McNamara| author4 = Digital Equipment Corporation| title = Computer engineering: A DEC view of hardware systems design| year = 1978| isbn = 0-932376-00-2| url-access = registration| url = https://archive.org/details/computerengineer00bell}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Commonscat}}
* [https://research.microsoft.com/users/gbell/Digital/DECMuseum.htm GBell's CyberMuseum for Digital Equipment Corp (DEC)]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20120216082420/http://www.technikum29.de/en/devices/dec-history.shtm Rise and Fall of Digital (Equipment Corporation)], a company chronicle at a German computer museum
* [https://www.economicadventure.org/decision/olsen.pdf Ken Olsen], New England Economic Adventure
* {{Gutenberg author | id=Digital+Equipment+Corporation | name=Digital Equipment Corporation}}
* {{Internet Archive author |sname=Digital Equipment Corporation |sopt=t}}

{{DEC hardware}}
{{DEC operating systems}}
{{DEC video terminals}}
{{Hard disk drive manufacturers}}

[[Category:Digital Equipment Corporation| ]]
[[Category:Companies based in Middlesex County, Massachusetts]]
[[Category:Defunct computer companies based in Massachusetts]]
[[Category:Defunct computer hardware companies]]
[[Category:Hewlett-Packard]]
[[Category:Manufacturing companies based in Massachusetts]]
[[Category:Computer companies disestablished in 1998]]
[[Category:Computer companies established in 1957]]
[[Category:1998 mergers and acquisitions]]
[[Category:1957 establishments in Massachusetts]]
[[Category:1998 disestablishments in Massachusetts]]
[[Category:1960s initial public offerings]]</text>
      <sha1>hc1m3s4qzj6fr2zr0uaxi9v1zzavxvi</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
