  <page>
    <title>Vladimir Harkonnen</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7901</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942436694</id>
      <parentid>942369805</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-24T17:43:49Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>TAnthony</username>
        <id>1808194</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Analysis */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox character
| colour      = #DAA520
| series      = [[Dune (franchise)|Dune]]
| creator     = [[Frank Herbert]]
| name        = Baron Vladimir Harkonnen
| image       = Baron Harkonnen-John Schoenherr-Illustrated Dune (1978).jpg
| caption     = Baron Vladimir Harkonnen by [[John Schoenherr]], from ''[[The Illustrated Dune]]'' (1978)
| children    = [[Lady Jessica]]
| relatives   = {{Plainlist|
* '''Original series:'''
* [[Glossu Rabban]] (nephew)
* [[Feyd-Rautha]] (nephew)
* [[Paul Atreides]] (grandson)
* [[Alia Atreides]] (granddaughter)
* [[Abulurd Harkonnen|Abulurd Harkonnen II]] (brother)
* '''Prequel series:'''
* Dmitri Harkonnen (father)&lt;ref name=&quot;Prelude&quot;&gt;{{cite serial |last1=Herbert |first1=Brian |authorlink1=Brian Herbert|first2=Kevin J.|last2=Anderson |authorlink2=Kevin J. Anderson |title=[[Prelude to Dune]] |date=1999–2001 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Victoria Harkonnen (mother)&lt;ref name=&quot;Prelude&quot;/&gt;
}}
| family      = [[House Harkonnen]]
| portrayer   = {{Plainlist|
* [[Kenneth McMillan (actor)|Kenneth McMillan]] ([[Dune (1984 film)|1984 film]])
* [[Ian McNeice]] ([[Frank Herbert's Dune|2000 series]] / [[Frank Herbert's Children of Dune|2003 series]])
* [[Stellan Skarsgård]] ([[Dune (2020 film)|2020 film]])
}}
| first       = ''[[Dune (novel)|Dune]]'' (1965)
| last        = ''[[Dune: House Corrino]]'' (2001) {{efn|A [[ghola]] of Baron Harkonnen is created in ''[[Hunters of Dune]]'' (2006) and also appears in ''[[Sandworms of Dune]]'' (2007); these may or may not be considered appearances of the original character.}}
}}
[[File:McMillan as Harkonnen.jpg|thumb|right| [[Kenneth McMillan (actor)|Kenneth McMillan]] as Vladimir Harkonnen in ''[[Dune (1984 film)|Dune]]'' (1984)]]

The '''Baron Vladimir Harkonnen''' ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|h|ɑːr|k|oʊ-|n|ən}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Pronunciation&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.usul.net/books/sounds.htm |title=Audio excerpts from a reading of ''Dune'' by Frank Herbert |via=Usul.net |accessdate=October 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; or {{IPAc-en|h|ɑːr|ˈ|k|oʊ|n|ən}}) is a fictional character from the [[Dune (franchise)|''Dune'' franchise]] created by [[Frank Herbert]]. He is primarily featured in the 1965 novel ''[[Dune (novel)|Dune]]'' and is also a prominent character in the ''[[Prelude to Dune]]'' prequel trilogy (1999–2001) by [[Brian Herbert]] and [[Kevin J. Anderson]]. The character is brought back as a [[ghola]] in the Herbert/Anderson sequels which conclude the original series, ''[[Hunters of Dune]]'' (2006) and ''[[Sandworms of Dune]]'' (2007).

Baron Harkonnen is portrayed by [[Kenneth McMillan (actor)|Kenneth McMillan]] in [[David Lynch]]'s 1984 film ''[[Dune (1984 film)|Dune]]''. [[Ian McNeice]] plays the role in the 2000 [[Syfy|Sci-Fi Channel]] [[miniseries]] ''[[Frank Herbert's Dune]]'' and its sequel, 2003's ''[[Frank Herbert's Children of Dune|Children of Dune]]''. Harkonnen will be portrayed by [[Stellan Skarsgård]] in the 2020 [[Denis Villeneuve]] film ''[[Dune (2020 film)|Dune]]''.

==Conception==
[[File:Harkonnen Griffin.svg|thumb|right|160px|The blue griffin emblem of House Harkonnen.]]
Frank Herbert wanted a harsh-sounding name for the antagonistic family opposing [[House Atreides]] in ''[[Dune (novel)|Dune]]''. He came across the name &quot;Härkönen&quot; in a California telephone book and thought that it sounded &quot;Soviet&quot;, though it is in fact Finnish.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Brian Herbert|year=2003 |title=Dreamer of Dune: The Biography of Frank Herbert |publisher=Macmillan |isbn=9781429958448 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; In earlier drafts of ''Dune'', the character was called &quot;Valdemar Hoskanner&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first1=Brian|last1=Herbert|first2=Kevin J.|last2=Anderson|chapter=Spice Planet|title=The Road to Dune|chapter-url=https://archive.org/details/roadtodune00fran|chapter-url-access=registration|publisher=Hodder &amp; Stoughton|location=London, England|date=2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Description==
Herbert's &quot;Appendix IV: The Almanak en-Ashraf (Selected Excerpts of the Noble Houses)&quot; in ''Dune'' says of Harkonnen (in part):
{{quote|VLADIMIR HARKONNEN (10,110–10,193) Commonly referred to as Baron Harkonnen, his title is officially Siridar (planetary governor) Baron. Vladimir Harkonnen is the direct-line male descendant of the Bashar [[Abulurd Harkonnen]] who was banished for cowardice after the [[Battle of Corrin]]. The return of [[House Harkonnen]] to power generally is ascribed to adroit manipulation of the [[whale fur]] market and later consolidation with [[Melange (fictional drug)|melange]] wealth from [[Arrakis]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Appendix&quot;&gt;{{cite book|first=Frank |last=Herbert |authorlink=Frank Herbert |title=Dune |chapter=Appendix IV: The Almanak en-Ashraf (Selected Excerpts of the Noble Houses): Vladimir Harkonnen |year=1965 |publisher=Hodder &amp; Stoughton |location=London, England|isbn=978-0441172719|title-link=Dune (novel) }}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

The character is usually described as the primary antagonist of the novel.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://io9.gizmodo.com/denis-villeneuves-dune-has-found-its-baron-harkonnen-1831616603|title=Denis Villeneuve's ''Dune'' Has Found Its Baron Harkonnen|first=James|last=Whitbrook|website=[[io9]]|date=January 9, 2019|accessdate=April 29, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.indiewire.com/2019/02/dune-denis-villeneuve-timothee-chalamet-full-details-plot-cast-release-1202041809/|title=''Dune'': Everything to Know About Denis Villeneuve and Timothée Chalamet's Sci-Fi Epic|first=Zack|last=Sharf|work=[[IndieWire]]|date=February 8, 2019|accessdate=April 29, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Paste&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.pastemagazine.com/articles/2019/01/stellan-skarsgard-is-dunes-villain.html|last=Martin|first=Clare|date=January 9, 2019|title=Stellan Skarsgård Is the Villain of Denis Villeneuve's ''Dune''|website=[[Paste (magazine)|Paste]]|accessdate=April 29, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Comicon&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.comicon.com/2019/01/09/stellan-skarsgard-accepts-his-destiny-as-dunes-baron-vladimir-harkonnen/|title=Stellan Skarsgard Accepts His Destiny As ''Dune''{{'s}} Baron Vladimir Harkonnen|first=Erik|last=Amaya|website=Comicon.com|date=January 9, 2019|accessdate=April 29, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Herbert writes in ''Dune'' that the Baron possesses a &quot;[[Basso profondo|basso]] voice&quot; and is so &quot;grossly and immensely fat&quot; that he requires [[anti-gravity]] devices known as [[suspensor (Dune)|suspensors]] to support his weight.&lt;ref name=&quot;sf.com&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://sciencefiction.com/2019/01/12/stellan-skarsgard-will-play-baron-vladimir-harkonnen-dune/|title=Stellan Skarsgård Will Play Baron Vladimir Harkonnen In ''Dune''|website=ScienceFiction.com|first=Stuart|last=Conover|date=January 12, 2019|accessdate=April 26, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Screen Rant&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://screenrant.com/dune-movie-reboot-stellan-skarsgard-cast/|title=''Dune'' Movie Reboot Casts Stellan Skarsgård As Its Villain|date=January 9, 2019|website=[[Screen Rant]]|first=Sandy|last=Schaefer|accessdate=April 26, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Frank |last=Herbert |authorlink=Frank Herbert |title=Dune |year=1965 |publisher=Hodder &amp; Stoughton |location=London, England|isbn=978-0441172719|quote=As [Baron Vladimir Harkonnen] emerged from the shadows, his figure took on dimension — grossly and immensely fat. And with subtle bulges beneath folds of his dark robes to reveal that all this fat was sustained partly by portable suspensors harnessed to his flesh. He might weigh two hundred Standard kilos in actuality, but his feet would carry no more than fifty of them.|title-link=Dune (novel) }}&lt;/ref&gt; He is one of the wealthiest members of the Landsraad and a bitter rival of [[Leto I Atreides|Leto Atreides]],&lt;ref name=&quot;IGN&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.ign.com/articles/2019/03/18/new-dune-movie-explained-what-to-know-about-the-classic-sci-fi-novel|title=''Dune'' Remake Movie Explained: What to Know About the Classic Sci-Fi Novel|website=[[IGN]]|first=Jesse|last=Schedeen|date=March 18, 2019|accessdate=April 26, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the Baron's &quot;legendary evil and intellect&quot; are unmatched by anyone else from House Harkonnen.&lt;ref name=&quot;sf.com&quot;/&gt; In the novel, the Baron feigns outrage over losing control of Arrakis to Leto, but is actually conspiring to use the situation as an opportunity to destroy the Atreides once and for all.&lt;ref name=&quot;IGN&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;IGN 2&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.ign.com/articles/2019/02/15/dune-movie-reboot-cast-zendaya-oscar-isaac-javier-bardem|title=''Dune'' Movie: Every Actor in the Sci-Fi Reboot|first=Jesse|last=Schedeen|website=IGN|date=February 14, 2019|accessdate=April 29, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://comicbook.com/movies/2019/01/09/dune-movie-reboot-stellan-skarsgard-baron-harkonnen/|title=Stellan Skarsgard to Play Baron Harkonnen in ''Dune'' Reboot|website=Comicbook.com|first=Jamie|last=Lovett|date=January 9, 2019|accessdate=April 29, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; William Hughes of ''[[The A.V. Club]]'' describes the Baron as &quot;a decadent, monstrous gasbag of depravity and evil&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;AV&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://news.avclub.com/ladies-and-gentlemen-stellan-skarsgard-is-your-new-bar-1831622192|title=Ladies and gentlemen, Stellan Skarsgård is your new Baron Harkonnen|first=William|last=Hughes|website=[[The A.V. Club]]|date=January 9, 2019|accessdate=April 26, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; As ruthless and cruel as he is intelligent and cunning, the Baron is &quot;crafty and power-hungry&quot; and has a talent for manipulating others and exploiting their weaknesses,&lt;ref name=&quot;Screen Rant&quot;/&gt; as well as a propensity for torture and blackmail.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nerdist&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://nerdist.com/article/denis-villeneuve-new-dune-whos-playing-who/|title=Who's Playing Who in Denis Villeneuve's ''Dune''|website=[[Nerdist]]|first=Lindsey|last=Romain|date=February 13, 2019|accessdate=April 29, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[IGN]]'' describes the character as &quot;cruel, sadistic and hedonistic&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;IGN&quot;/&gt; Travis Johnson of Flicks.com.au explains that Harkonnen is written as &quot;a predatory homosexual given to pederasty and incest, an unrepentant rapist and murderer.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Flicks&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.flicks.com.au/features/why-denis-villenueves-upcoming-version-of-dune-has-us-crazy-excited/|title=Why Denis Villenueve's upcoming version of ''Dune'' has us crazy excited|website=Flicks.com.au|first=Travis|last=Johnson|date=February 13, 2019|accessdate=April 26, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Baron's sexual preference for young men is implied in ''Dune'' and ''Children of Dune''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Dune|first=Frank|last=Herbert|date=1965|quote='I'll be in my sleeping chambers,' the Baron said. 'Bring me that young fellow we bought on Gamont, the one with the lovely eyes. Drug him well. I don't feel like wrestling.'}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Dune|first=Frank|last=Herbert|date=1965|quote='Why haven't you ever bought a Bene Gesserit, Uncle?' Feyd-Rautha asked. 'With a Truthsayer at your side—'&lt;br&gt;'You know my tastes!' the Baron snapped.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Dune|first=Frank|last=Herbert|date=1965|quote=Baron to Feyd: 'This old fool saw through the shielded needle you'd planted in that slave boy's thigh. Right where I'd put my hand on it, eh?'}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is noted, however, that he &quot;once permitted himself to be seduced&quot; by a [[Bene Gesserit]] in the liaison which produced his secret daughter.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jessica's father&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=Dune|first=Frank|last=Herbert|date=1965|quote=Paul to Jessica: 'There's a thing you don't know and should—we are Harkonnens...You're the Baron's own daughter...The Baron sampled many pleasures in his youth, and once permitted himself to be seduced. But it was for the genetic purposes of the Bene Gesserit'.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Plotlines ==

=== ''Dune'' ===
As ''Dune'' begins, a longstanding feud exists between the Harkonnens of [[Giedi Prime]] and the [[House Atreides|Atreides]] of [[Caladan]]. The Baron's intent to exterminate the Atreides line seems close to fruition as Duke Leto Atreides is lured to the [[desert planet]] Arrakis on the pretense of taking over the valuable melange operation there. The Baron has an agent in the Atreides household: Leto's own physician, the trusted [[Suk School|Suk doctor]] [[Wellington Yueh]]. Though Suk Imperial Conditioning supposedly makes the subject incapable of inflicting harm, the Baron's twisted [[Mentat]] [[Piter De Vries]] notes:

{{quote|It's assumed that ultimate conditioning cannot be removed without killing the subject. However, as [[Archimedes|someone]] once observed, given the right lever you can move a planet. We found the lever that moved the doctor.}}

The Baron has taken Yueh's wife [[Wanna (Dune)|Wanna]] prisoner, threatening her with interminable torture unless Yueh complies with his demands. Harkonnen also distracts Leto's Mentat [[Thufir Hawat]] from discovering Yueh by guiding Hawat toward another suspect: Leto's [[Bene Gesserit]] [[concubinage|concubine]] [[Lady Jessica]], of whom Hawat is already distrustful. The Atreides are soon attacked by Harkonnen forces (secretly supplemented by the seemingly unstoppable Imperial [[Sardaukar]]) as Yueh disables the protective shields around the Atreides palace on Arrakis. As instructed, Yueh takes Leto prisoner; however, desiring to slay the Baron, Yueh provides the captive Leto with a fake tooth filled with poisonous gas as a means of simultaneous [[assassination]] and [[suicide]]. De Vries kills Yueh but he also dies with Leto in the assassination attempt; however Harkonnen survives. The Baron then manipulates Hawat into his service, by convincing Hawat that Lady Jessica was the traitor and using Hawat's desire for revenge on Lady Jessica and the Emperor as motivation to assist House Harkonnen.

Leto and Jessica's son [[Paul Atreides]] flee into the desert with Jessica, and both are presumed dead. Paul's [[prescience]] helps him determine the identity of Jessica's father, the &quot;maternal grandfather who cannot be named&quot; — the Baron himself.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jessica's father&quot;/&gt; Over the next two years, Harkonnen learns that his nephews [[Glossu Rabban]] and [[Feyd-Rautha]] are conspiring against him to usurp his throne; he lets them continue to do so, reasoning that they have to somehow learn to organize a [[conspiracy (political)|conspiracy]]. As punishment for a failed assassination attempt against him, Harkonnen forces Feyd to single-handedly slaughter all the female slaves who serve as Feyd's lovers. He explains that Feyd has to learn the price of failure.

The Baron's plan to assure Feyd's power is to install him as ruler of Arrakis after a period of tyrannical misrule by Rabban, making Feyd appear to be the savior of the people. However, a crisis on Arrakis begins when the mysterious [[Muad'Dib]] emerges as a leader of the native [[Fremen]] tribes against the rule of the Harkonnens. Eventually, a series of Fremen victories against Beast Rabban threaten to disrupt the trade of the spice. The [[Padishah Emperor]] [[Shaddam IV]] decides to intervene himself and arrives on Arrakis along with legions of Sardaukar forces.  Shaddam and the Baron are shocked to learn that Muad'Dib is, of course, a very-much-alive Paul Atreides. The Imperial forces fall prey to a surprise attack by the Fremen.  Part of the Fremen/Atreides strategy is to wait until a sandstorm shorts out the force field shields of the Harkonnen/Imperial transport ships, disable them with projectile weapons, and then attack with a vast assault force, using [[sandworm (Dune)|sandworm]]s under cover of the severe weather to break the enemy lines.  The Sardaukar and Harkonnen forces are trapped on the planet, astonished at the sandworm mounts and vast numbers of their attackers. Their past ruthlessness gives them little hope of quarter from the enraged Fremen.

Rabban dies in the initial part of the battle; the Harkonnen army is massacred to the last man and almost all the Imperial Sardaukar are killed. Baron Harkonnen himself is poisoned with a [[gom jabbar]] by Paul's young sister [[Alia Atreides]], his own granddaughter, and dies at the age of 83, with the latter also revealing her direct lineage to him just beforehand. Paul then kills Feyd in ritual combat. House Harkonnen's virtual extermination removes it as a galactic power, but Paul's ascension to the Imperial throne in Shaddam's place guarantees that Vladimir's descendants will long reign as the Imperial House Atreides.

=== ''Children of Dune'' ===
Alia had been born with her ancestral memories in the womb, a circumstance the Bene Gesserit refer to as [[abomination (Dune)|Abomination]], because in their experience it is inevitable that the individual will become possessed by the personality of one of their ancestors. In ''[[Children of Dune]]'', Alia falls victim to this prediction when she shares control of her body with the ego-memory of the Baron Harkonnen, and eventually falls under his power. Alia eventually commits [[suicide]], realizing that Harkonnen's [[consciousness]] has surpassed her abilities to contain him.

=== ''Prelude to Dune'' ===
In the ''Prelude to Dune'' prequel series by Brian Herbert and Anderson, it is established that Baron Vladimir Harkonnen is the son and heir of Dmitri Harkonnen and his wife Victoria. Harkonnen's father had been the head of House Harkonnen and ruled the planet Giedi Prime. Trained since youth as a possible successor,  Vladimir had been eventually chosen over his half-brother [[Abulurd Harkonnen|Abulurd]] (namesake of the original). Unhappy with his brother's doings, Abulurd eventually marries Emmi Rabban and renounces the family name and his rights to the title. Under the name Abulurd Rabban, he reigns as governor of the secondary Harkonnen planet [[Lankiveil]]. Abulurd and his wife have two sons: Glossu Rabban (later nicknamed &quot;Beast Rabban&quot; after he murders his own father) and Feyd-Rautha; Vladimir later adopts the boys back into House Harkonnen, and Feyd becomes his designated heir. The Baron's most prominent political rival is Duke Leto Atreides; the Harkonnens and the Atreides have been bitter enemies for millennia, since the [[Battle of Corrin]] that ended the [[Butlerian Jihad]]. When Emperor Shaddam IV orchestrates a plot to destroy the &quot;Red Duke&quot; Leto, the Baron eagerly lends his aid.

The young Baron Vladimir Harkonnen is described as an exceedingly handsome man, possessing red hair and a near-perfect physique. The Bene Gesserit [[Reverend Mother (Dune)|Reverend Mother]] [[Gaius Helen Mohiam]] is instructed by the Sisterhood to collect his genetic material (through conception) for their breeding program. As the Baron's homosexuality is something of an open secret, Mohiam blackmails him into having sexual relations with her and conceives his child. When that daughter proves genetically undesirable, Mohiam kills her and returns to Harkonnen for a second try; at this point he drugs and viciously rapes her. She exacts her retribution by infecting him with a rare, incurable disease that later causes his obesity. Mohiam's second child with the Baron is Jessica.{{efn|According to the authors, the revelation that Mohiam is Jessica's mother was pulled directly from Frank Herbert's working notes for the original ''Dune'' series.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.scifi.com/transcripts/2000/herbertandanderson.html  |title=Chat with Brian Herbert and Kevin J. Anderson: ''Dune: House Harkonnen'' |year=2000 |publisher=[[SyFy|Sci-Fi Channel]] |via=SciFi.com |accessdate=February 7, 2019 |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20071105073412/http://www.scifi.com/transcripts/2000/herbertandanderson.html |archivedate = November 5, 2007 |url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}&gt; In ''[[Dune: House Harkonnen]]'', the deteriorating Baron at first walks with the assistance of a cane, then relies on belt-mounted suspensors to retain mobility. He consults numerous doctors in the expanse of time between the ''[[Dune: House Atreides]]'' and ''Dune: House Harkonnen'', up to and including his future instrument Dr. Yueh, all of whom are ultimately no help. To conceal this debilitation, he pretends that his obesity is due to intentional overindulgence, lest the Landsraad remove him from power. When he determines that Mohiam inflicted him with the disease, he attempts to coerce her into revealing the cure, but soon discovers that there is none. The Baron, Duke Leto, and Jessica herself are unaware that Jessica is secretly the Baron's daughter or that he has even fathered one. In the year 10,176, the Baron's grandson Paul is born to Leto and Jessica.

=== ''Hunters of Dune'' ===
In ''[[Hunters of Dune]]'' (2006), the continuation of the original series by Brian Herbert and Kevin J. Anderson, the Baron is resurrected as a ghola (5,029 years after the death of Alia) by the [[Lost Tleilaxu]] [[Uxtal]], acting on orders from the [[Face Dancer]] [[Khrone]]. Khrone intends to use the Baron ghola to manipulate a ghola of Paul Atreides, named [[Paolo (Dune)|Paolo]]. Khrone tries various torture techniques for three years to awaken the 12-year-old Baron's genetic memories; these methods fail due to the Baron's [[sadomasochism|sadomasochistic]] nature. Khrone is successful when he imprisons the Baron in a sensory deprivation tank for a prolonged period; the Baron's memories of his former life return. The reincarnated Baron is soon haunted by the voice of Alia in his mind; the source of this inner Alia is never explained.

==In adaptations==
[[File:McNeice as Harkonnen (2000).jpg|thumb|upright|[[Ian McNeice]] as Baron Harkonnen in the [[Frank Herbert's Dune|''Dune'' miniseries]] (2000)]]
[[File:Stellan Skarsgård at the 2017 Berlinale.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Stellan Skarsgård]] will portray Baron Harkonnen in the 2020 film ''[[Dune (2020 film)|Dune]]''.]]

===1984 film===
Baron Harkonnen is portrayed by [[Kenneth McMillan (actor)|Kenneth McMillan]] in [[David Lynch]]'s [[Dune (1984 film)|1984 film]].&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT 1984-12&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://movies.nytimes.com/movie/review?res=9F06E2D71238F937A25751C1A962948260|title=Movie Review: ''Dune'' (1984) |last=Maslin|first=Janet|date=December 14, 1984|work=[[The New York Times]]|accessdate=March 15, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The obese and disheveled Baron is overtly unstable, and covered in oozing [[pustule]]s. William Hughes of ''[[The A.V. Club]]'' deemed McMillan's facial prosthetics &quot;very memorable&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;AV&quot;/&gt; Emmet Asher-Perrin of ''[[Tor.com]]'' wrote that &quot;Lynch's attempt is infamous for really leaning on [the] codified aspects of the Baron, to the point where his sore-ridden appearance has been called out as a likely connection to the [[AIDS]] epidemic, which was a prevalent health crisis while the film was in production.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Tor.com&quot;/&gt; Travis Johnson of Flicks.com.au noted that the Lynch film embraced &quot;the archetype of the depraved gay sadist&quot;, which would not be acceptable in 2019.&lt;ref name=&quot;Flicks&quot;/&gt; Asher-Perrin added, &quot;Lynch also makes a point of connecting the Baron's desire for men to deviancy and violence, deliberately juxtaposing his assault of a young man with a tender love scene between Duke Leto and Lady Jessica Atreides.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Tor.com&quot;/&gt;

===2000 miniseries===
[[Ian McNeice]] plays the Baron in the 2000 [[Syfy|Sci-Fi Channel]] [[miniseries]] ''[[Frank Herbert's Dune]]'',&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT Stasio&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2000/12/03/tv/cover-story-future-myths-adrift-in-the-sands-of-time.html?src=pm |title=Cover Story: Future Myths, Adrift in the Sands of Time |first=Marilyn |last=Stasio |work=The New York Times |date=December 3, 2000 |accessdate=August 21, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; and its [[sequel]], 2003's ''[[Frank Herbert's Children of Dune|Children of Dune]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT Wertheimer&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2003/03/15/arts/television-review-a-stormy-family-on-a-sandy-planet.html |title=Television Review: A Stormy Family on a Sandy Planet |first=Ron |last=Wertheimer |work=The New York Times|date=March 15, 2003 |accessdate=January 19, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Asher-Perrin notes that the miniseries played down the negative aspects emphasized by the Lynch film, and writes, &quot;[The Baron's] appearance was not altered to make him seem ill, he never physically attacks anyone, and the miniseries paid more attention to the fact that the Baron was a rapist, his preference for men being incidental.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Tor.com&quot;/&gt; She also praises McNeice as a standout among the cast, writing that he &quot;manages to make the Baron Harkonnen—easily one of the most despicable characters in science fiction literature—every bit as conniving and vicious as he needs to be...and every bit as fascinating. McNeice has a superb sense of how to make the baron mesmerizing to watch no matter how odiously he behaves&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tor 2000&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.tor.com/2017/05/09/syfys-dune-miniseries-is-the-most-okay-adaptation-of-the-book-to-date/|title=Syfy's ''Dune'' Miniseries is the Most Okay Adaptation of the Book to Date|first=Emmet|last=Asher-Perrin|date=May 9, 2017|website=Tor.com|accessdate=February 20, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===2020 film===
Baron Harkonnen will be portrayed by [[Stellan Skarsgård]] in the 2020 [[Denis Villeneuve]] film ''[[Dune (2020 film)|Dune]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.hollywoodreporter.com/heat-vision/stellan-skarsg-play-villain-legendarys-dune-1174870|title=Stellan Skarsgård to Play Villain in Legendary's ''Dune''|website=[[The Hollywood Reporter]]|first=Borys|last=Kit|date=January 9, 2019|accessdate=April 26, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://variety.com/2019/film/news/stellan-skarsgard-playing-villain-in-dune-movie-1203104276/|title=Stellan Skarsgard to Play Villain in ''Dune'' Movie|first=Dave|last=McNary|work=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|date=January 9, 2019|accessdate=January 11, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Skarsgård called the role &quot;small but important&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.cinemablend.com/news/2467370/stellan-skarsgard-compares-the-dune-cast-to-the-avengers|title=Stellan Skarsgård Compares the ''Dune'' Cast to the Avengers|date=February 23, 2019|website=CinemaBlend|first=Sarah|last=El-Mahmoud|accessdate=April 26, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; and noted &quot;I had seven hours in make-up every day because I had to be really fat.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://collider.com/dune-movie-details-stellan-skarsgard/|title=Stellan Skarsgard Says Denis Villeneuve Had 'Pretty Free Hands' Directing ''Dune''|first=Perri|last=Nemiroff|website=[[Collider (website)|Collider]]|date=September 16, 2019|accessdate=October 30, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Discussing the film in its early stages, Asher-Perrin writes that &quot;Baron Harkonnen needn't be obese for the sole purpose of making misguided points.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Tor.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.tor.com/2019/02/05/how-to-handle-the-baron-harkonnen-in-a-modern-dune-adaptation/|title=How to Handle the Baron Harkonnen in a Modern ''Dune'' Adaptation|first=Emmet|last=Asher-Perrin|website=[[Tor.com]]|date=February 5, 2019|accessdate=February 5, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; She suggests that the film find &quot;a different way to highlight the Baron's obsession with excess&quot;, and argues that the character's iconic suspensors could be presented as &quot;an affectation of laziness rather than a physical necessity.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Tor.com&quot;/&gt; Travis Johnson adds that the novel's depiction of Harkonnen as &quot;a predatory homosexual&quot; is problematic in 2019.&lt;ref name=&quot;Flicks&quot;/&gt; He writes of the new film, &quot;It's going to come down to the writing and filmmaking as to whether this characterization will fly in the current era, or will come across as an unfortunate throwback stereotype.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Flicks&quot;/&gt;

==Merchandising and influence==
A line of ''Dune'' action figures from toy company [[LJN]] was released to lackluster sales in 1984. Styled after David Lynch's film, the collection featured a figure of Baron Harkonnen, as well as other characters.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nerd Bastards toys&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://nerdbastards.com/2014/01/12/toys-we-miss-dune/|title=Toys We Miss: The Long Forgotten Figures From Frank Herbert's ''Dune''|first=James|last=Daniels|website=Nerd Bastards|date=January 12, 2014|accessdate=October 30, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Collectors toys&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.collectorsofdune.com/toys.asp|title=Toys|website=Collectors of Dune|accessdate=October 30, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2006, [[SOTA Toys]] produced a Baron Harkonnen action figure for their &quot;Now Playing Presents&quot; line.&lt;ref name=&quot;Collectors toys&quot;/&gt;

[[H. R. Giger]]'s [[Harkonnen Capo Chair]] is a chair originally designed by the artist as set dressing for an unrealized 1970s adaptation of ''Dune'' by [[Alejandro Jodorowsky]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=H. R. |last=Giger |authorlink=H. R. Giger |title=H.R.Giger's Film Design |publisher=[[Titan Books]] |location=London, England|date=1996 |isbn=9781852867195}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.hrgiger.com/chairs.htm |title=H.R. Giger's Harkonnen Chairs |publisher=HRGiger.com |accessdate=23 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Analysis==
William Hughes calls the Baron &quot;one of the most iconically awful villains in all of science fiction&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;AV&quot;/&gt; and Stuart Conover of ScienceFiction.com describes him as &quot;one of the most insidious villains&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;sf.com&quot;/&gt; Maude Campbell of ''[[Popular Mechanics]]'' writes that the Baron is &quot;one of the most evil characters ever put to paper (including Darth Vader)&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.popularmechanics.com/culture/movies/a25889196/dune-rumors-news/|title=Everything We Know So Far About Denis Villeneuve's ''Dune''|first=Maude|last=Campbell|date=February 15, 2019|website=[[Popular Mechanics]]|accessdate=April 26, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Jon Michaud of ''[[The New Yorker]]'' compares  
&quot;Herbert's scheming, backstabbing villain, the Baron Vladimir Harkonnen&quot; to the villainous Lannister family of [[George R. R. Martin]]'s ''[[A Song of Ice and Fire]]'' series.&lt;ref name=&quot;New Yorker Michaud&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.newyorker.com/books/page-turner/dune-endures |title=''Dune'' Endures |first=Jon |last=Michaud |work=[[The New Yorker]] |date=July 12, 2013 |accessdate=August 18, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Emmet Asher-Perrin suggests that &quot;what makes the Baron truly monstrous [is] the fact that he spends all of his time plotting murder, sowing discord, and destroying populations of people to get his way&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tor.com&quot;/&gt; Hughes writes that the evil Harkonnen is &quot;specifically designed to make the noble Atreides family seem that extra bit more dignified and pure&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;AV&quot;/&gt; with Jesse Schedeen of ''IGN'' agreeing that the Baron is &quot;as cruel and vindictive as Leto is noble and just.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;IGN 2&quot;/&gt; Hughes goes on to say that Herbert &quot;successfully made [the Baron] so vampirically vile that he casts a (sometimes literal) shadow over the entire series.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;AV&quot;/&gt; Sandy Schaefer of ''[[Screen Rant]]'' calls the Baron &quot; a deliciously despicable antagonist&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Screen Rant&quot;/&gt; Travis Johnson points out that in the novel Harkonnen is a predatory homosexual given to pederasty and incest, an unrepentant rapist and murderer, but depicting him as a &quot;depraved gay sadist&quot; is &quot;not a particularly good look in the cold light of 2019.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Flicks&quot;/&gt; Asher-Perrin also notes:

{{quote|''Dune'' was written in the 1960s when certain types of coding were common for villainous characters. In the case of the Baron, there are two primary issues at hand, two characteristics that further argue his odiousness on the story's behalf that are rightly seen as contentious today: the Baron is obese, and he is also [[queer]] ... the Baron Harkonnen being the only fat and only visibly queer person in the novel continues to be a problem for ''Dune''. When a villain is the sole character to occupy certain characteristics, the reader or viewer is made keenly aware that those characteristics are being tied to their moral vacancy ... The physical appearance of the Baron is particularly noticeable in part because nearly everyone else in ''Dune'' is commonly portrayed as lithe and athletic.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tor.com&quot;/&gt;}}

While the novel suggests that the Baron's obesity might be the result of a genetic disease, the ''[[Prelude to Dune]]'' prequel trilogy by [[Brian Herbert]] and [[Kevin J. Anderson]] explains that Harkonnen was once a fit, attractive but vain man who is given the incurable disease intentionally by the Bene Gesserit [[Reverend Mother Mohiam]] after he drugs and rapes her.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tor.com&quot;/&gt; Asher-Perrin suggests that in this narrative, &quot;the Baron's corpulence is meant to be comeuppance for doing something reprehensible, a physical punishment meant to hurt his vanity by taking away the attractiveness he so prized in himself.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Tor.com&quot;/&gt; He also remarks that this retelling &quot;does nothing to alleviate the connection being drawn between weight and hedonistic sadism&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tor.com&quot;/&gt;

==Notes==
{{notelist}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20170419101847/http://www.imdb.com/character/ch0008386/ Baron Vladimir Harkonnen] on [[IMDb]]

{{Dune franchise}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Harkonnen, Vladimir}}
[[Category:Dune characters]]
[[Category:Fictional gay males]]
[[Category:Fictional dictators]]
[[Category:Fictional barons and baronesses]]
[[Category:Fictional murderers]]
[[Category:Fictional rapists]]
[[Category:Fictional torturers]]
[[Category:Literary characters introduced in 1965]]
[[Category:Fictional LGBT characters in film]]
[[Category:Male literary villains]]
[[Category:LGBT villains]]
[[Category:Fictional LGBT characters in literature]]</text>
      <sha1>mdt9inwlpv0jsbw2ejh5enlfpw1m8mk</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
