  <page>
    <title>David Thompson (explorer)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7994</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942185663</id>
      <parentid>941265282</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-23T03:54:44Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>69.168.161.87</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Later life */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{pp-move-indef}}
{{more citations needed|date=May 2018}}
{{EngvarB|date=May 2018}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2020}}
{{Infobox person
| name = David Thompson
| image = David Thompson (1770-1857).jpg
| caption = 
| birth_date = {{birth date|df=yes|1770|4|30}}
| birth_place = Westminster, England
| death_date = {{death date and age|df=yes|1857|2|10|1770|4|30}}
| death_place = [[Longueuil]], [[Canada East]]
| occupation = Explorer and [[Cartography|Map Maker]]
| spouse = [[Charlotte Small]]
| parents = David and Ann Thompson
| children = Fanny (1801), Samuel (1804), Emma (1806), John (1808), Joshuah (1811), Henry (1813), Charlotte (1815), Elizabeth (1817), William (1819), Thomas (1822), George (1824), Mary (1827), Eliza (1829)
| signature = David Thompson signature.svg
}}

'''David Thompson''' (30 April 1770 – 10 February 1857) was a [[English Canadian|British-Canadian]] [[fur trader]], [[surveying|surveyor]], and [[Cartography|cartographer]], known to some native peoples as ''Koo-Koo-Sint'' or &quot;the Stargazer&quot;. Over Thompson's career, he traveled some {{convert|90000|km}} across [[North America]], mapping {{convert|4.9|e6km2|e6sqmi|abbr=off}} of North America along the way.&lt;ref name=&quot;HBC History Foundation&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=The Country of Adventurers: David Thompson narrated by Rick Hansen|publisher=HBC History Foundation |url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=m_vzybpOiIM}}&lt;/ref&gt; For this historic feat, Thompson has been described as the &quot;greatest land geographer who ever lived.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;tyrrell&quot;/&gt;

==Early life==
David Thompson was born in [[Westminster]], Middlesex, to recent Welsh migrants David and Ann Thompson. When Thompson was two, his father died. Due to the financial hardship with his mother without resources, Thompson, 29 April 1777, the day before his seventh birthday, &lt;ref&gt;Thompson/William E Moreau, ''The Wrtings of David Thompson, Volume 1, The Travels, 1850 version'', The Champlain Society, 2009 p.xx&lt;/ref&gt; and his older brother were placed in the [[Grey Coat Hospital]], a school for the disadvantaged of Westminster.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.hbcheritage.ca/hbcheritage/history/people/explorers/david-thompson |title=David Thompson |publisher=Hudson's Bay Company History Foundation |access-date=9 January 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thompson graduated to the Grey Coat mathematical school, where he had received an education for the Royal Navy: including mathematics of trigonometry and geometry, practical navigation including using of nautical instruments, finding latitudes and longitudes and making navigational calculations from observing the sun, moon and tides and the drawing of maps and charts, taking land measurements and sketching landscapes.&lt;ref&gt;Thompson/Moreau p.xxi&lt;/ref&gt; He later built on these to make his career. In 1784, at the age of 14, the Grey Coat treasurer paid the [[Hudson's Bay Company]] the sum of five pounds, upon which Thompson became the company's indentured servant for a period of seven years to be trained as a clerk.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thompson/Moreau p.xxiii&quot;&gt;Thompson/Moreau p.xxiii&lt;/ref&gt; He set sail on 28 May of that year, and left England for North America.&lt;ref name=&quot;vanherk&quot;&gt;{{cite magazine |url=https://secure.indas.on.ca/canadiangeo/store/index.php?site=default&amp;feature=CG-200704|first=Aritha |last=Van Herk |title=Travels with Charlotte |website=canadiangeographic.ca|publisher=Canadian Geographic Magazine |year=2007|series=July/August|url-access=subscription |access-date=27 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Hudson's Bay Company (HBC)==
On 2 September 1784,&lt;ref name=&quot;Thompson/Moreau p.xxiii&quot;/&gt; Thompson arrived in [[Churchill, Manitoba|Churchill]] (now in [[Manitoba]]) and was put to work as a clerk/secretary, copying the personal papers of the governor of Fort Churchill, [[Samuel Hearne]]. The next year he was transferred to nearby [[York Factory, Manitoba|York Factory]], and over the next few years spent time as a secretary at [[Cumberland House, Saskatchewan]], and [[South Branch House]] before arriving at [[Manchester House]] in 1787. During those years he learned to keep accounts and other records, calculate values of furs (It was noted that he also had several expensive beaver pelts at that time even when a secretary's job would not pay terribly well), track supplies and other duties.

On 23 December 1788, Thompson seriously fractured his tibia, forcing him to spend the next two winters at Cumberland House convalescing. It was during this time that he greatly refined and expanded his mathematical, astronomical, and surveying skills under the tutelage of Hudson's Bay Company surveyor [[Philip Turnor]]. It was also during this time that he lost sight in his right eye.&lt;ref name=&quot;gottfred&quot;&gt;J. &amp; A. Gottfred, &quot;Art. I. The Life of David Thompson&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1790, with his apprenticeship nearing its end, Thompson requested a set of surveying tools in place of the typical parting gift of fine clothes offered by the company to those completing their indenture. He received both. He entered the employ of the Hudson's Bay Company as a [[fur trader]]. In 1792 he completed his first significant survey, mapping a route to [[Lake Athabasca]] (where today's [[Alberta]]/[[Saskatchewan]] border is located). In recognition of his map-making skills, the company promoted Thompson to surveyor in 1794. He continued working for the Hudson's Bay Company until 23 May 1797 when, frustrated with the Hudson's Bay Company's policies over promoting the use of alcohol with indigenous people in the fur trade, he left. He walked {{convert|80|mi|km|order=flip}} in the snow in order to enter the employ of the competition, the [[North West Company]]. There he continued to work as a [[fur trader]] and surveyor.

==North West Company==
[[File:David Thompson (explorer).jpg|thumb|left|An artist's impression of Thompson based on historical accounts]]

Thompson's decision to defect to the [[North West Company]] (NWC) in 1797 without providing the customary one-year notice was not well received by his former employers. But the North West Company was more supportive of Thompson pursuing his interest in surveying and work on mapping the interior of what was to become Canada, as they judged it in the company's long-term interest. In 1797, Thompson was sent south by his employers to survey part of the Canada-US boundary along the water routes from [[Lake Superior]] to [[Lake of the Woods]] to satisfy unresolved questions of territory arising from the [[Jay Treaty]] between Great Britain and the United States after the American Revolutionary War.

By 1798 Thompson had completed a survey of {{convert|6750|km|mi|abbr=on}} from [[Grand Portage]], through [[Lake Winnipeg]], to the [[River source|headwaters]] of the [[Assiniboine River|Assiniboine]] and [[Mississippi River|Mississippi]] rivers, as well as two sides of [[Lake Superior]].&lt;ref name=&quot;vanherk&quot;/&gt; In 1798, the company sent him to Red Deer Lake ([[Lac la Biche (Alberta)|Lac La Biche]] in present-day Alberta) to establish a trading post. (The English translation of Lac la Biche: Red Deer Lake, was first recorded on the Mackenzie map of 1793.)&lt;ref name=AlbertaAtlas&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sunsite.ualberta.ca/Projects/Alberta-Lakes/view/?region=Peace%20and%20Athabasca%20Region&amp;basin=Athabasca%20River%20Basin&amp;lake=Lac%20La%20Biche&amp;number=1|publisher=University of Alberta|location=Edmonton, Alberta|title=Lac La Biche|series=Atlas of Alberta Lakes|year=2004|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150610064531/http://sunsite.ualberta.ca/Projects/Alberta-Lakes/view/?region=Peace%20and%20Athabasca%20Region&amp;basin=Athabasca%20River%20Basin&amp;lake=Lac%20La%20Biche&amp;number=1|archive-date=10 June 2015|access-date=27 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thompson spent the next few seasons trading based in [[Buckingham House (fur-trade post)#Fort George|Fort George]] (now in Alberta), and during this time led several expeditions into the [[Rocky Mountains]].

On 10 July 1804, at the annual meeting of the North West Company in [[Fort Kaministiquia|Kaministiquia]], Thompson was made a full partner of the company. He became a 'wintering partner', who was based in the field rather than Montreal, with two of the 92 NWC's shares worth more than £4,000.&lt;ref&gt;Thompson/Moreau p.xxxv&lt;/ref&gt; He spent the next few seasons based there managing the fur trading operations but still finding time to expand his surveys of the waterways around Lake Superior. At the 1806 company meeting, officers decided to send Thompson back out into the interior. Concern over the American-backed expedition of [[Lewis and Clark Expedition|Lewis and Clark]] prompted the North West Company to charge Thompson with the task of finding a route to the Pacific to open up the lucrative trading territories of the [[Pacific Northwest]].

==Columbia River travels==
[[File:Columbiarivermap.png|{{largethumb}}|David Thompson navigated the entire length of Columbia River in 1811. This map of the Columbia and its tributaries shows modern political boundaries.]]

After the general meeting in 1806, Thompson travelled to [[Rocky Mountain House]] and prepared for an expedition to follow the [[Columbia River]] to the Pacific. In June 1807 Thompson crossed the Rocky Mountains and spent the summer surveying the [[Columbia River Drainage Basin|Columbia basin]]; he continued to survey the area over the next few seasons. Thompson mapped and established trading posts in Northwestern [[Montana]], [[Idaho]], [[Washington (state)|Washington]], and [[Western Canada]]. Trading posts he founded included [[Kootenae House]], [[Kullyspell House]] and [[Saleesh House]]; the latter two were the first trading posts west of the Rockies in Idaho and Montana, respectively.&lt;ref name=&quot;gottfred&quot;/&gt; These posts established by Thompson extended North West Company fur trading territory into the Columbia Basin drainage area. The maps he made of the Columbia River basin east of the [[Cascade Mountains]] were of such high quality and detail that they continued to be regarded as authoritative well into the mid-20th century.

In early 1810, Thompson was returning eastward toward [[Montreal]] but, while en route at [[Rainy Lake]], received orders to return to the Rocky Mountains and establish a route to the mouth of the Columbia. The North West Company was responding to the plans of American [[John Jacob Astor]] to send a ship around the Americas to establish a fur trading post of the Pacific Fur Company on the Pacific Coast. During his return, Thompson was delayed by an angry group of [[Northern Peigan|Peigan]] natives at [[Howse Pass]]. He was ultimately forced to seek a new route across the [[Rocky Mountains]] and found one through the [[Athabasca Pass]].

David Thompson was the first European to navigate the full length of the Columbia River. During Thompson's 1811 voyage down the Columbia River, he camped at the junction with the [[Snake River]] on 9 July 1811. There he erected a pole and a notice claiming the country for Great Britain and stating the intention of the North West Company to build a [[trading post]] at the site. This notice was found later that year by Astor company workers looking to establish an inland fur post, contributing to their selection of a more northerly site at [[Fort Okanogan]]. The North West Company established its post of [[Fort Nez Percés]] near the Snake River confluence several years later. Continuing down the Columbia, Thompson passed the barrier of [[The Dalles, Oregon|The Dalles]] with much less difficulty than that undergone by [[Lewis and Clark Expedition|Lewis and Clark]], as high water carried his boat over [[Celilo Falls]] and many of the rapids. On 14 July 1811, Thompson reached the partially constructed [[Fort Astoria]] at the mouth of the Columbia, arriving two months after the [[Pacific Fur Company]]'s ship, the ''[[Tonquin (1807)|Tonquin]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| last = Meinig| first = D.W.| authorlink = D.W. Meinig| title = The Great Columbia Plain| edition = Weyerhaeuser Environmental Classic| origyear = 1968| year = 1995| publisher = University of Washington Press| isbn = 978-0-295-97485-9| pages = 37–38, 50 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Before returning upriver and across the mountains, Thompson hired [[Naukane]], a [[Native Hawaiians|Native Hawaiian]] Takane labourer brought to Fort Astoria by the Pacific Fur Company's ship ''Tonquin''. Naukane, known as Coxe to Thompson, accompanied Thompson across the continent to [[Lake Superior]] before journeying on to England.

Thompson wintered at Saleesh House before beginning his final journey back to Montreal in 1812, where the North West Company was based.

In his published journals, Thompson recorded seeing large footprints near what is now [[Jasper, Alberta]], in 1811. It has been suggested that these prints were similar to what has since been called the [[sasquatch]]. However, Thompson noted that these tracks showed &quot;a small Nail at the end of each [toe]&quot;, and stated that these tracks &quot;very much resembles a large Bear's Track&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Thompson, David. ''Columbia Journals''. Edited by Barbara Belyea. McGill-Queen's University Press, 1994, p. 135&lt;/ref&gt;

==Appearance and personality==
[[File:DavidThompson.png|thumb|left|David Thompson late in life]]
In 1820, the English geologist, [[John Jeremiah Bigsby]], attended a dinner party given by The Hon. [[William McGillivray]] at his home, Chateau St. Antoine, one of the early estates in [[Montreal]]'s [[Golden Square Mile]]. He describes the party and some of the guests in his entertaining book ''The Shoe and Canoe'', giving an excellent description of David Thompson:

{{quote|text=I was well placed at table between one of the Miss McGillivray's and a singular-looking person of about fifty. He was plainly dressed, quiet, and observant. His figure was short and compact, and his black hair was worn long all round, and cut square, as if by one stroke of the shears, just above the eyebrows. His complexion was of the gardener's ruddy brown, while the expression of his deeply-furrowed features was friendly and intelligent, but his cut-short nose gave him an odd look. His speech betrayed the [[Wales|Welshman]], although he left his native hills when very young. I might have been spared this description of Mr David Thompson by saying he greatly resembled [[John Philpot Curran|Curran]] the Irish Orator...&lt;ref name=Bigsby&gt;{{cite book |first=John Jeremiah |last=Bigsby |title=The Shoe and Canoe: or Pictures of Travel in the Canadas; with Facts and Opinions on Emigration, State Policy, and Other Points of Public Interest |url=https://archive.org/details/shoeandcanoeorp01bigsgoog |year=1850 |publisher=Chapman and Hall |pages=[https://archive.org/details/shoeandcanoeorp01bigsgoog/page/n125 113]–114}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

{{quote|text=I afterwards travelled much with him, and have now only to speak of him with great respect, or, I ought to say, with admiration... No living person possesses a [[tithe]] of his information respecting the Hudson's Bay countries... Never mind his Bunyan-like face and cropped hair; he has a very powerful mind, and a singular faculty of picture-making. He can create a wilderness and people it with warring savages, or climb the [[Rocky Mountains]] with you in a snow-storm, so clearly and palpably, that only shut your eyes and you hear the crack of the rifle, or feel the snow-flakes melt on your cheeks as he talks.&lt;ref name=Bigsby/&gt;}}

==Marriage and children==
On 10 June 1799 at [[Île-à-la-Crosse, Saskatchewan|Île-à-la-Crosse]], Thompson married [[Charlotte Small]], a thirteen-year-old [[Métis people (Canada)|Métis]] daughter of Scottish fur trader Patrick Small and a [[Cree]] mother.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite DCB |last=Nicks |first=John |title=Thompson, David (1770–1857) |url=http://www.biographi.ca/en/bio/thompson_david_1770_1857_8E.html |volume=8}}&lt;/ref&gt; Their marriage was formalised thirteen years later at the Scotch Presbyterian Church in [[Montreal]] on 30 October 1812. He and Charlotte had 13 children together;&lt;ref&gt;Sterling, Keir B. &quot;David Thompson.&quot; Science and Its Times, edited by Neil Schlager and Josh Lauer, vol. 4: 1700 to 1799, Gale, 2000, p. 74. Gale Virtual Reference Library, http://link.galegroup.com/apps/doc/CX3408501666/GVRL?u=lond95336&amp;sid=GVRL&amp;xid=df137bb4. Accessed 20 January 2019.&lt;/ref&gt; five of them were born before he left the fur trade. The family did not adjust easily to life in [[Eastern Canada]]; they lived in Montreal while he was traveling. Two of the children, John (aged 5) and Emma (aged 7), died of [[Ascariasis|round worms]], a common parasite.&lt;ref name=&quot;vanherk&quot;/&gt; By the time of Thompson's death, the couple had been married 57 years, the longest marriage known in Canada pre-[[Canadian Confederation|Confederation]].&lt;ref name=&quot;vanherk&quot;/&gt;

==Later life==
[[File:1814ThompsonMap.jpg|thumb|left|Map of the North-West Territory of the Province of Canada, stretching from the [[Fraser River]] on the west to [[Lake Superior]] on the east. By David Thompson, 1814.]]
Upon his arrival back in Montreal, Thompson retired with a generous pension from the North West Company. He settled in nearby [[Terrebonne, Quebec|Terrebonne]] and worked on completing his great map, a summary of his lifetime of exploring and surveying the interior of North America. The map covered the wide area stretching from Lake Superior to the Pacific, and was given by Thompson to the North West Company. Thompson's 1814 map, his greatest achievement, was so accurate that 100 years later it was still the basis for many of the maps issued by the Canadian government. It now resides in the [[Archives of Ontario]].&lt;ref&gt;[https://archive.today/20070802143042/http://www.archives.gov.on.ca/english/exhibits/thompson/records.htm ] David Thompson Records Held by the [[Archives of Ontario]]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1815, Thompson moved his family to [[Williamstown, Ontario|Williamstown, Upper Canada]], and a few years later was employed to survey the newly established borders with the United States from Lake of the Woods to the [[Eastern Townships]] of [[Quebec]], established by [[Treaty of Ghent]] after the [[War of 1812]]. In 1843 Thompson completed his atlas of the region from [[Hudson Bay]] to the Pacific Ocean.

Afterwards, Thompson returned to a life as a land owner, but soon financial misfortune would ruin him. By 1831 he was so deeply in debt he was forced to take up a position as a surveyor for the British American Land Company to provide for his family. His luck continued to worsen and he was forced to move in with his daughter and son-in-law in 1845. He began work on a manuscript chronicling his life exploring the continent, but this project was left unfinished when his sight failed him completely in 1851.

==Death and afterward==
[[File:Stamp-Thompson-1957.jpg|thumb|upright|Postage stamp commemorating David Thompson's life]]

The land mass mapped by Thompson amounted to {{convert|3.9|e6km2|e6sqmi|abbr=off}} of wilderness (one-fifth of the continent). His contemporary, the great explorer [[Alexander Mackenzie (explorer)|Alexander Mackenzie]], remarked that Thompson did more in ten months than he would have thought possible in two years.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://archive.org/details/davidthompsonsna12thom|page=[https://archive.org/details/davidthompsonsna12thom/page/297 297]|title=David Thompson's Narrative of His Explorations in Western America, 1784–1812|last=Thompson|first=David|date=1916|publisher=Champlain Society|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite these significant achievements, Thompson died in Montreal in near obscurity on 10 February 1857, his accomplishments almost unrecognised. He never finished the book of his 28 years in the fur trade, based on his 77 field notebooks, before he died.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine |url=https://secure.indas.on.ca/canadiangeo/store/index.php?site=default&amp;feature=CG-200704|first=Rick |last=Boychuk |title=David Thompson's living legacy |website=canadiangeographic.ca|publisher=Canadian Geographic Magazine  |year= 2007 |series=July/August|volume=127 |issue=4 |p=13|url-access=subscription |access-date=27 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the 1890s geologist [[Joseph Tyrrell|J.B. Tyrrell]] resurrected Thompson's notes and in 1916 published them as ''David Thompson's Narrative'', as part of the General Series of the [[Champlain Society]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = David Thompson's Narrative of His Explorations in Western America, 1784–1812.|url = http://champlainsociety.utpjournals.press/doi/book/10.3138/9781442618114|doi = 10.3138/9781442618114|first = David|last = Thompson|editor-last = Tyrrell|editor-first = Joseph|publisher = Champlain Society|year = 1916}}&lt;/ref&gt; Further editions and re-examinations of Thompson's life and works were published in 1962 by Richard Glover, in 1971 by Victor Hopwood, and in 2015 by William Moreau.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = David Thompson's Narrative, 1784–1812 (volume II).|url = http://champlainsociety.utpjournals.press/doi/book/10.3138/9781442618237|doi = 10.3138/9781442618237|first = David|last = Thompson|publisher = Champlain Society|year = 1962|editor-last = Glover|editor-first = Richard}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:LLB Thompson statue.jpg|thumb|left|upright|David Thompson and two First Nations guides on the shore of [[Lac la Biche (Alberta)|Lac la Biche]], where he landed on 4 October 1798.]]
Thompson's body was interred in Montreal's [[Mount Royal Cemetery]] in an unmarked grave. It was not until 1926 that efforts by [[Joseph Tyrrell|J.B. Tyrrell]] and the Canadian Historical Society resulted in the placing of a tombstone to mark his grave. The next year, Thompson was named a [[Persons of National Historic Significance|National Historic Person]] by the federal government, one of the earliest such designations.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pc.gc.ca/apps/dfhd/page_nhs_eng.aspx?id=899 David Thompson National Historic Person], Directory of Federal Heritage Designations, Parks Canada&lt;/ref&gt; A federal plaque reflecting that status is located at [[Jasper National Park]], Alberta. Meantime, Thompson's achievements are central reasons for other national historic designations:
* David Thompson on the Columbia River [[Events of National Historic Significance|National Historic Event]], marked at [[Castlegar, BC]]
* [[Athabasca Pass]] [[National Historic Sites of Canada|National Historic Site]] (NHS), at Jasper National Park
* Boat Encampment NHS, BC
* [[Howse Pass]] NHS, [[Banff National Park]], Alberta
* [[Kootenae House]] NHS, BC
* [[Rocky Mountain House]] NHS, Alberta

[[File:David n Charlotte Thompson grave Montreal QC IMG 6598.jpg|thumb|right|upright|David &amp; Charlotte Thompson's gravestone in Mount Royal Cemetery]]

In 1957, one hundred years after his death, Canada's [[Canada Post|post office department]] honoured him with his image on a [[List of people on stamps of Canada|postage stamp]]. The [[David Thompson Highway]] in Alberta was named in his honour, along with David Thompson High School situated on the side of the highway near [[Leslieville, Alberta]]. His prowess as a geographer is now well-recognized. He has been called &quot;the greatest land geographer that the world has produced.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;tyrrell&quot;&gt;''[http://link.library.utoronto.ca/champlain/item_record.cfm?Idno=9_96855&amp;lang=eng&amp;query=thompson%20AND%20david&amp;searchtype=Author&amp;startrow=1&amp;Limit=All David Thompson's narrative of his explorations in western America, 1784–1812]{{Dead link|date=July 2018 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}'' (edited by J.B. Tyrrell)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;vanherk&quot;/&gt;

There is a monument dedicated to David Thompson (maintained by the state of [[North Dakota]]) near the former town site of the ghost town, [[Verendrye, North Dakota]], located approximately {{convert|2|mi}} north and {{convert|1|mi}} west of [[Karlsruhe, North Dakota]]. [[Thompson Falls, Montana]], and British Columbia's [[Thompson River]] are also named after the explorer.

[[File:David Thompson Monument.JPG|thumb|right|upright|David Thompson Memorial, Verendrye, North Dakota]]
The year 2007 marked the 150th year of Thompson's death and the 200th anniversary of his first crossing of the Rocky Mountains. Commemorative events and exhibits were planned across Canada and the United States from 2007 to 2011 as a celebration of his accomplishments.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.davidthompson200.org/ David Thompson Bicentennials]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2007, a commemorative plaque was placed on a wall at the Grey Coat Hospital, the school for the disadvantaged of Westminster David Thompson attended as a boy, by English author and TV presenter [[Ray Mears]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url = https://www.independent.co.uk/news/uk/this-britain/britain-who-charted-canada-honoured-at-home-455181.html | title = Briton who charted Canada honoured at home | newspaper = [[The Independent]] | date = 29 June 2007 | accessdate = 12 January 2009 | first = Ian | last = Herbert}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;HBC History Foundation&quot;/&gt;

Thompson was the subject of a 1964 [[National Film Board of Canada]] short film ''David Thompson: The Great Mapmaker '',&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nfb.ca/film/david_thompson_the_great_mapmaker/ ''David Thompson: The Great Mapmaker '', National Film Board of Canada]&lt;/ref&gt; as well as the [[BBC2]] programme ''[[Ray Mears' Northern Wilderness]]'' (Episode 5), broadcast in November 2009.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/wales/8354658.stm BBC Wales news report]. Retrieved 25 November 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

He is referenced in the 1981 [[folk music|folk]] song [[Northwest Passage (song)|&quot;Northwest Passage&quot;]] by [[Stan Rogers]].

The national park service, [[Parks Canada]], announced in 2018 that it had named its new research vessel {{ship|RV|David Thompson}}, to be used for underwater archaeology, including sea floor mapping, and for marine science in the Pacific, Atlantic, Arctic Oceans, and the Great Lakes. It will be the main platform for research on the [[Franklin's lost expedition|Wrecks of HMS ''Erebus'' and HMS ''Terror'' National Historic Site]].&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.canada.ca/en/parks-canada/news/2018/03/rv-david-thompson---parks-canadas-new-research-vessel.html RV David Thompson – Parks Canada’s New Research Vessel], Parks Canada backgrounder, 16 March 2018&lt;/ref&gt;

The David Thompson Astronomical Observatory at [[Fort William Historical Park]] was named to commemorate David Thompson and his discoveries.&lt;ref&gt;[http://fwhp.ca/observatory]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Exploration of North America]]
* [[Fur trade]]
* [[Jack Nisbet]] (author of several books on David Thompson)

==Works==
* 1814: Map of the North-West Territory of the Province of Canada
* 1897: ''[http://www.canadiana.org/ECO/ItemRecord?id=3de1bded3c9598b4 New light on the early history of the greater Northwest: the manuscript journals of Alexander Henry, fur trader of the North West Company, and of David Thompson, official geographer and explorer of the same company, 1799–1814 : exploration and adventure among the Indians on the Red, Saskatchewan, Missouri and Columbia Rivers]'' (edited by Elliott Coues)
* 1916: ''[http://link.library.utoronto.ca/champlain/item_record.cfm?Idno=9_96855&amp;lang=eng&amp;query=thompson%20AND%20david&amp;searchtype=Author&amp;startrow=1&amp;Limit=All David Thompson's narrative of his explorations in western America, 1784–1812]{{Dead link|date=July 2018 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}'' (edited by J.B. Tyrrell)
* 1950: ''David Thompson's journals relating to Montana and adjacent regions, 1808–1812'' (edited by M. Catherine White)
* 1962: ''[https://archive.today/20130101104245/http://link.library.utoronto.ca/champlain/item_record.cfm?Idno=9_96867&amp;lang=eng&amp;query=9_96867&amp;searchtype=Bibrecord&amp;startrow=1&amp;Limit=All David Thompson's narrative, 1784–1812]'' (edited by Richard Glover)
* 1974: ''David Thompson's journal of the international boundary survey, 1817–1827 : western Lake Erie, August–September 1819'' (edited by Clarke E. Leverette)
* 1993: ''Columbia Journals'' (edited by Barbara Belyea)
* 2006: &quot;[http://www.arcturusconsulting.net/products.htm Moccasin Miles – The Travels of Charlotte Small Thompson 1799–1812]&quot; Contemporary and Historical Maps: Charlotte Small (S. Leanne Playter/Andreas N. Korsos|Publisher: Arcturus Consulting)
* 2006/2007: [http://www.arcturusconsulting.net/products.htm &quot;David Thompson in Alberta 1787–1812&quot;; &quot;David Thompson on the Columbia River 1807–1812&quot;; &quot;The Explorations and Travels of David Thompson 1784–1812&quot;; &quot;Posts and Forts of the North American Fur Trade 1600–1870&quot;] Contemporary and Historical Maps: David Thompson (Andreas N. Korsos|Publisher: Arcturus Consultin
* 2010 : Official Documentary of Thompson was released by national geographic, ca.

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Notes==
* {{cite book| last = Jenish| first = D'Arcy| title = Epic wanderer: David Thompson and the mapping of the Canadian West| year = 2003| publisher = Doubleday Canada| location = Toronto| isbn = 978-0-385-65973-4 }}
* {{cite book| last = Thompson| first = David| title = Columbia Journals| year = 1994| publisher = McGill-Queen's University Press| location = Montreal| isbn = 978-0-7735-0989-4 }}
* {{cite web  | title = David Thompson Canada's greatest Geographer  | work = David Thompson Things  | publisher = David Thompson Things  | url = http://www.davidthompsonthings.com/geog1.html  | accessdate = 23 June 2007  | url-status = dead  | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20080123095015/http://www.davidthompsonthings.com/geog1.html  | archivedate = 23 January 2008  }}
* {{cite map |title=The Explorations and Travels of David Thompson 1784–1812 |work=Andreas N. Korsos |publisher=Arcturus Consulting |url=http://www.arcturusconsulting.net/shop.htm |year=2007 |isbn=978-0-9783707-2-5 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090228103922/http://www.arcturusconsulting.net/shop.htm |archivedate=28 February 2009  }}
* 2006: &quot;Moccasin Miles – The Travels of Charlotte Small Thompson 1799–1812&quot; Contemporary and Historical Maps: Charlotte Small (S. Leanne Playter/Andreas N. Korsos|Publisher: Arcturus Consulting)

==Further reading==
* {{cite book|author=Flandrau, Grace|title=Koo-koo-sint, the Star Man: a chronicle of David Thompson|publisher=Great Northern Railway|year=1925}} [https://archive.today/20121214120528/http://www.secstate.wa.gov/history/publications_detail.aspx?p=86 Available online through the Washington State Library's Classics in Washington History collection]
* {{cite book|author=Haywood, Carl W.|title=Sometime Only Horses to Eat: David Thompson; The Saleesh House Period 1807–1812: Tracking David Thompson Across Western North America|publisher=Stonydale Press Publishing Co.|year=2008}}
* {{cite book|author=Jenish, D'Arcy|title=Epic Wanderer: David Thompson and the Mapping of the Canadian West|publisher=Doubleday Canada|year=2003}}
* {{cite book|author=McCart, Joyce and Peter|title=On the Road with David Thompson|publisher=Fifth House|year=2000}}
* {{cite book|author=Nisbet, Jack|title=Sources of the River: Tracking David Thompson Across Western North America|publisher=Sasquatch Books|year=1994}}
* {{cite book|author=Andra-Warner, Elle|title=David Thompson: A Life of Adventure and Discovery|publisher=Heritage House Publishing Co. Ltd.|year=2010}}

==External links==
{{commons category}}
* David Thompson's Narrative of His Explorations in Western America 1784–1812 Vol's I and II, Champlain Society 1916, [https://archive.org/download/davidthompsonsna00thom/davidthompsonsna00thom_bw.pdf PDF (B/W) 25.1 MB]
* [http://link.library.utoronto.ca/champlain/item_record.cfm?Idno=9_96855&amp;lang=eng&amp;query=thompson%20AND%20david&amp;searchtype=Author&amp;startrow=1&amp;Limit=All Complete text of David Thompson's ''Narrative'' (Tyrrell edition)]{{Dead link|date=December 2018 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }} Champlain Society digital collection
* [https://champlainsociety.utpjournals.press/doi/book/10.3138/9781442618237 Complete text of David Thompson's ''Narrative'' (Glover edition)] Champlain Society digital collection
* {{Oregon Encyclopedia|thompson_david|David Thompson}}
* [http://www.biographi.ca/009004-119.01-e.php?&amp;id_nbr=4218 Biography at the ''Dictionary of Canadian Biography Online'']
* ''[https://web.archive.org/web/20170825122926/http://www.archives.gov.on.ca/en/explore/online/thompson/index.aspx David Thompson: Map Maker, Explorer and Visionary]'', online exhibit on Archives of Ontario website
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20060719085105/http://www.davidthompson200.org/cms/ DavidThompson200]: bicentennial commemorations of Thompson's explorations
* [https://champlainsociety.utpjournals.press/doi/book/10.3138/9781442620766 The Writings of David Thompson] edited by William E. Moreau. Three volumes.
* [http://www.library.utoronto.ca/fisher/collections/findaids/thompson_david.pdf David Thompson Papers, Thomas Fisher Rare Book Library]

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Thompson, David}}
[[Category:Canadian people of Welsh descent]]
[[Category:English cartographers]]
[[Category:English explorers]]
[[Category:English surveyors]]
[[Category:Canadian cartographers]]
[[Category:Canadian male canoeists]]
[[Category:Canadian explorers]]
[[Category:Canadian surveyors]]
[[Category:English emigrants to pre-Confederation Canada]]
[[Category:Explorers of British Columbia]]
[[Category:Explorers of Canada]]
[[Category:North West Company people]]
[[Category:People from Westminster]]
[[Category:People from Montreal]]
[[Category:Pre-Confederation Quebec people]]
[[Category:Interior of British Columbia]]
[[Category:Hudson's Bay Company people]]
[[Category:1770 births]]
[[Category:1857 deaths]]
[[Category:History of the Pacific Northwest]]
[[Category:Persons of National Historic Significance (Canada)]]
[[Category:Explorers of Washington (state)]]
[[Category:People educated at Grey Coat Hospital]]
[[Category:English explorers of North America]]
[[Category:Welsh topographers]]
[[Category:Mount Royal Cemetery burials]]</text>
      <sha1>7dedq5ms3jb2kknqrcs4dxrc31xhmct</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
