  <page>
    <title>Double jeopardy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7941</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942745133</id>
      <parentid>942744413</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-26T15:49:28Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Hairy Dude</username>
        <id>274535</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* United States */copy edit</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{about||the clause in the U.S. Constitution|Double Jeopardy Clause|other uses}}
{{Use British English|date=October 2017}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}
{{Criminal procedure (trial)}}

'''Double jeopardy''' is a [[procedural defense|procedural defence]]&lt;!-- please do not alter to &quot;defense&quot; - this article uses British spelling --&gt; that prevents an accused person from being [[Trial|tried]] again on the same (or similar) charges following a valid acquittal or conviction.&lt;ref name=historyOf5&gt;{{cite journal|title=A Brief History of the Fifth Amendment Guarantee Against Double Jeopardy|author=David S. Rudstein|url=http://scholarship.law.wm.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1209&amp;context=wmborj|year=2005|journal=William &amp; Mary Bill of Rights Journal|volume=14|issue=1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

If this issue is raised, evidence will be placed before the court, which will normally rule as a preliminary matter whether the plea is substantiated; if it is, the projected trial will be prevented from proceeding. In some countries certain exemptions are permitted, such as in the United Kingdom, where in Scotland a new trial can be initiated if, for example, the acquitted has made a credible admission of guilt, and in England and Wales, where serious offences may be re-tried following an acquittal if new and compelling evidence is found and for the trial to be in the public's interest. In some countries, including Canada, Mexico and the United States, the guarantee against being &quot;twice put in jeopardy&quot; is a constitutional right.&lt;ref&gt;''[http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/const/page-15.html Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160110221331/http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/const/page-15.html |date=10 January 2016 }}'', s 11 (h), Part I of the ''Constitution Act, 1982'', being Schedule B to the ''Canada Act 1982'' (UK), 1982, c 11.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''[https://www.archives.gov/exhibits/charters/bill_of_rights_transcript.html U.S. Constitution]''. Amend. V.&lt;/ref&gt; In other countries, the protection is afforded by [[statute]].&lt;ref&gt;For example, in Western Australia:  &quot;It is a defence to a charge of any offence to show that the accused person has already been tried, and convicted or acquitted upon an indictment or prosecution notice on which he might have been convicted of the offence with which he is charged, or has already been convicted or acquitted of an offence of which he might be convicted upon the indictment or prosecution notice on which he is charged.&quot;{{mdash}}[http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/legis/wa/consol_act/ccaca1913252/ Criminal Code Act Compilation Act 1913], Appendix B, Sch &quot;The Criminal Code&quot; s 17(1).&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[common law]] countries, a defendant may enter a [[peremptory plea]] of ''autrefois acquit'' (formerly acquitted) or ''autrefois convict'' (formerly convicted), with the same effect.&lt;ref name=&quot;Benét1864p97&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=A Treatise on Military Law and the Practice of Courts-martial |last=Benét |first=Stephen Vincent |year=1864 |page=[https://books.google.com/books?id=Gq00AAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA97 97] |url=https://books.google.com/?id=Gq00AAAAIAAJ }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The terminology is a mixture of French (''autrefois'', &quot;at another time [in the past]&quot;) and English, apparently derived from [[Law French]].  See {{cite book|title=A History of English Law |last=Holdsworth |first=Sir William |location=London |publisher=Methuen and Sweet &amp; Maxwell |date=1942 |edition=5 |volume=3 |pages=611, 614}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The doctrine appears to have originated in Roman law, in the principle ''[[non bis in idem]]'' (&quot;an issue once decided must not be raised again&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Buckland|first=W.W.|title=A Text-book of Roman Law from Augustus to Justinian|url=https://archive.org/details/textbookofromanl0000buck|url-access=registration|edition=3|date=1963|location=Cambridge|publisher=Cambridge UP| pages=[https://archive.org/details/textbookofromanl0000buck/page/695 695–6]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights==
The 72 [[Signature|signatories]] and 166 parties to the [[International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights]] recognise, under Article 14 (7): &quot;No one shall be liable to be tried or punished again for an offence for which he has already been finally [[convicted]] or [[acquitted]] in accordance with the law and penal procedure of each country.&quot;

==European Convention on Human Rights==
{{Expand section|date=June 2008}}
All members of the [[Council of Europe]] (which includes nearly all European countries and every member of the [[European Union]]) have adopted the [[European Convention on Human Rights]].{{Citation needed|date=February 2018}} The optional Protocol No. 7 to the Convention, Article 4, protects against double jeopardy: &quot;No one shall be liable to be tried or punished again in criminal proceedings under the jurisdiction of the same State for an [[Offence (law)|offence]] for which he or she has already been finally [[acquittal|acquitted]] or [[conviction|convicted]] in accordance with the law and penal procedure of that State.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;ECHR-COE&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=European Convention on Human Rights, as amended by Protocols Nos. 11 and 14, supplemented by Protocols Nos. 1, 4, 6, 7, 12 and 13|url=https://www.echr.coe.int/Documents/Convention_ENG.pdf|publisher=Council of Europe|accessdate=31 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

This optional protocol has been ratified by all EU states except three: [[Germany]], the [[United Kingdom]], and the [[Netherlands]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://conventions.coe.int/Treaty/Commun/ChercheSig.asp?NT=117&amp;CM=8&amp;DF=4/11/2007&amp;CL=ENG|title= Protocol No. 7 to the Convention for the Protection of Human Rights and Fundamental Freedoms|publisher=Council of Europe}}&lt;/ref&gt; In those member states, national rules governing double jeopardy may or may not comply with the provision cited above.

Member states may, however, implement legislation which allows reopening of a case in the event that new evidence is found or if there was a fundamental defect in the previous proceedings:

&lt;blockquote&gt;The provisions of the preceding paragraph shall not prevent the reopening of the case in accordance with the law and penal procedure of the State concerned, if there is evidence of new or newly discovered facts, or if there has been a fundamental defect in the previous proceedings, which could affect the outcome of the case.&lt;ref name=&quot;ECHR-COE&quot; /&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In many European countries, the prosecution may appeal an acquittal to a higher court.{{Citation needed|date=February 2018}} This is not regarded as double jeopardy, but as a continuation of the same case. The European Convention on Human Rights permits this by using the phrase &quot;''finally'' acquitted or convicted&quot; (emphasis added) as the trigger for prohibiting subsequent prosecution.

==By country==

===Australia===
In contrast to other common law nations, Australian double jeopardy law has been held to further prevent the prosecution for [[perjury]] following a previous acquittal where a finding of perjury would controvert the acquittal. This was confirmed in the case of ''[[R v Carroll]]'', where the police found new evidence convincingly disproving Carroll's sworn [[alibi]] two decades after he had been acquitted of murder charges in the death of [[Ipswich, Queensland|Ipswich]] child Deidre Kennedy, and successfully prosecuted him for perjury. Public outcry following the overturn of his conviction (for perjury) by the [[High Court of Australia|High Court]] has led to widespread calls for reform of the law along the lines of the England and Wales legislation.

During a [[COAG|Council of Australian Governments (COAG)]] meeting of 2007, model legislation to rework double jeopardy laws was drafted,&lt;ref name=&quot;premier.vic.gov.au&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Coalition Government to introduce double jeopardy reforms|url=http://www.premier.vic.gov.au/media-centre/media-releases/2427-coalition-government-to-introduce-double-jeopardy-reforms.html|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120322221443/http://www.premier.vic.gov.au/media-centre/media-releases/2427-coalition-government-to-introduce-double-jeopardy-reforms.html|url-status=dead|archive-date=22 March 2012|work=Victoria's double jeopardy laws to be reworked|accessdate=4 February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; but there was no formal agreement for each state to introduce it. All states have now chosen to introduce legislation that mirrors COAG's recommendations on &quot;fresh and compelling&quot; evidence.

In [[New South Wales]], retrials of serious cases with a minimum sentence of 20 years or more are now possible, whether or not the original trial preceded the 2006 reform.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.abc.net.au/worldtoday/content/2006/s1735450.htm|title=NSW seeks to scrap double jeopardy principle|newspaper=The World Today|author=Duffy, Conor|date=7 September 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 17 October 2006, the [[New South Wales Parliament]] passed legislation abolishing the rule against double jeopardy in cases where:
*an acquittal of a &quot;life sentence offence&quot; ([[murder]], violent [[gang rape]], large commercial supply or production of [[illegal drug trade|illegal drugs]]) is debunked by &quot;fresh and compelling&quot; evidence of guilt;
*an acquittal of a &quot;15 years or more sentence offence&quot; was tainted (by perjury, [[bribery]], or perversion of the course of justice).

On 30 July 2008, [[South Australia]] also introduced legislation to scrap parts of its double jeopardy law, legalising retrials for serious offences with &quot;fresh and compelling&quot; evidence, or if the acquittal was tainted.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Criminal Law Consolidation (Double Jeopardy) Amendment Act 2008|url=http://www.legislation.sa.gov.au/LZ/V/A/2008/CRIMINAL%20LAW%20CONSOLIDATION%20(DOUBLE%20JEOPARDY)%20AMENDMENT%20ACT%202008_28/2008.28.UN.RTF|work=Criminal Law Consolidation (Double Jeopardy) Amendment Act 2008|accessdate=16 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Western Australia]], on 8 September 2011 amendments were introduced that would allow also retrial if &quot;new and compelling&quot; evidence was found. It would apply to serious offences where the penalty was life imprisonment or imprisonment for 14 years or more. Acquittal because of tainting ([[witness intimidation]], [[jury tampering]], or perjury) would also allow retrial.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Attorney General Christian Porter welcomes double jeopardy law reform|url=http://www.perthnow.com.au/news/western-australia/attorney-general-christian-porter-welcomes-double-jeopardy-law-reform/story-e6frg13u-1226132121880|work=Attorney General Christian Porter welcomes double jeopardy law reform|accessdate=16 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=WA the next state to axe double jeopardy|url=http://news.smh.com.au/breaking-news-national/wa-the-next-state-to-axe-double-jeopardy-20110908-1jyu3.html|work=WA the next state to axe double jeopardy|accessdate=16 October 2011|date=8 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Tasmania]], on 19 August 2008, amendments were introduced to allow retrial in serious cases, if there is &quot;fresh and compelling&quot; evidence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Double Jeopardy Law Reform |url=http://www.media.tas.gov.au/print.php?id=24539 |work=Double Jeopardy Law Reform |publisher=Tasmanian Government Media Releases |accessdate=16 October 2011 }}{{dead link|date=June 2016|bot=medic}}{{cbignore|bot=medic}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Victoria (Australia)|Victoria]] on 21 December 2011, legislation was passed allowing new trials where there is &quot;fresh and compelling DNA evidence, where the person acquitted subsequently admits to the crime, or where it becomes clear that key witnesses have given false evidence&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;premier.vic.gov.au&quot;/&gt; Retrial applications however could only be made for serious offences such as murder, manslaughter, arson causing death, serious drug offences and aggravated forms of rape and armed robbery.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Criminal Procedure Amendment (Double Jeopardy and Other Matters) Bill 2011|url=http://www.parliament.vic.gov.au/publications/research-papers/bills-backgrounders/8100-criminal-procedure-amendment-double-jeopardy-and-other-matters-bill-2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Queensland]] on 18 October 2007, the double jeopardy laws were modified to allow a retrial where fresh and compelling evidence becomes available after an acquittal for murder or a &quot;tainted acquittal&quot; for a crime carrying a 25-year or more sentence. A &quot;tainted acquittal&quot; requires a conviction for an administration of justice offence, such as perjury, that led to the original acquittal. Unlike reforms in the United Kingdom, New South Wales, Tasmania, Victoria, South Australia, Western Australia, this law does not have a retrospective effect, which is unpopular with some advocates of the reform.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.brisbanetimes.com.au/news/queensland/double-jeopardy-changes-insufficient/2007/04/20/1176697080260.html|title=Double Jeopardy Changes Insufficient|newspaper=The Brisbane Times|date=20 April 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Canada===
The [[Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms]] includes provisions such as [[Section Eleven of the Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms|section 11(h)]] prohibiting double jeopardy. However, the prohibition applies only after an accused person has been &quot;finally&quot; convicted or acquitted. [[Canadian law]] allows the prosecution to appeal an acquittal, and if the acquittal is thrown out, the new trial is not considered to be double jeopardy since the verdict of the first trial is annulled. In rare circumstances, a [[court of appeal]] might also substitute a conviction for an acquittal. That is not considered to be double jeopardy, since the appeal and the subsequent conviction are then deemed to be a continuation of the original trial.

For an appeal from an acquittal to be successful, the [[Supreme Court of Canada]] requires the [[Crown of Canada|Crown]] to show that an error in law was made during the trial and that the error contributed to the verdict. It has been suggested that this test is unfairly beneficial to the prosecution. For instance, lawyer [[Martin Friedland]], in his book ''My Life in Crime and Other Academic Adventures'', contends that the rule should be changed so that a retrial is granted only when the error is shown to be ''responsible'' for the verdict, not just a factor.

A notable example is [[Guy Paul Morin]], who was wrongfully convicted in his second trial after the acquittal in his first trial was vacated by the Supreme Court of Canada.

In the [[Guy Turcotte]] case, for instance, the Quebec Court of Appeal overturned Turcotte's [[insanity defense|not criminally responsible]] verdict and ordered a second trial after it found that the judge committed an error in the first trial while instructions were given to the jury. Turcotte was later convicted of second-degree murder in the second trial.

===France===
Once all appeals have been exhausted on a case, the judgement is final and the action of the prosecution is closed (code of penal procedure, art. 6), except if the final ruling was [[forgery|forged]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.legifrance.gouv.fr/affichCodeArticle.do?idArticle=LEGIARTI000006574827&amp;cidTexte=LEGITEXT000006071154|title=Code of penal procedure, article 6|publisher=Legifrance|accessdate=2 January 2012|language=fr}}&lt;/ref&gt; Prosecution for a crime already judged is impossible even if incriminating evidence has been found. However, a person who has been convicted may request another trial on grounds of new [[Exculpatory evidence|exculpating]] evidence through a procedure known as ''révision''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.legifrance.gouv.fr/affichCode.do?idSectionTA=LEGISCTA000006138099&amp;cidTexte=LEGITEXT000006071154|title=Code of penal procedure, articles 622–626|publisher=Legifrance|accessdate=2 January 2012|language=fr}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Germany===
The [[Basic Law of the Federal Republic of Germany|Basic Law]] (''Grundgesetz'') for the Federal Republic of Germany does provide protection against double jeopardy if a final verdict is pronounced. A verdict is final if nobody appeals against it.

{{quotation|Nobody shall be punished multiple times for the same crime on the basis of general criminal law.|Art. 103 (3) GG&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.gesetze-im-internet.de/bundesrecht/gg/gesamt.pdf|title=Grundgesetz für die Bundesrepublik Deutschland|trans-title=Basic Law for the Federal Republic of Germany|language=de}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://germanlawjournal.com/pdfs/Vol09No12/PDF_Vol_09_No_12_2179-2222_Articles_Currie%202.pdf |author=Currie, David |title=Lochner Abroad: Substantive Due Process and Equal Protection in the Federal Republic of Germany |volume=9 |number=12 |journal=German Law Journal |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120425232851/http://germanlawjournal.com/pdfs/Vol09No12/PDF_Vol_09_No_12_2179-2222_Articles_Currie%202.pdf |archivedate=25 April 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

However, each trial party can appeal against a verdict in the first instance. This means the prosecution and/or the defendants can appeal against a judgement if they do not agree with it. In this case the trial starts again in the second instance, the court of appeal (''Berufungsgericht''), which considers the facts and reasons again and delivers the final judgement then.

If one of the parties disagrees with the judgement of the second instance, he or she can appeal it, but only on formal judicial reasons. The case will checked in the third instance (''Revisionsgericht''), whether all laws are applied correctly.

The rule applies to the whole &quot;historical event, which is usually considered a single historical course of actions the separation of which would seem unnatural&quot;. This is true even if new facts occur that indicate other and/or much serious crimes.

The Penal Procedural Code (''Strafprozessordnung'') permits a retrial (''Wiederaufnahmeverfahren''), if it is in favor of the defendant or if following events had happened:

{{quotation|A retrial not in favour of the defendant is permissible after a final judgement,
#if a document that was considered authentic during the trial was actually not authentic or forged,
#if a witness or authorised expert wilfully or negligently made a wrong deposition or wilfully gave a wrong simple testimony,
#if a professional or lay judge, who made the decision, had committed a crime by violating his or her duties as a judge in the case
#if an acquitted defendant makes a credible confession in court or out of court.|§ 362 StPO}}

In the case of an order of [[summary punishment]], which can be issued by the court without a trial for lesser misdemeanours, there is a further exception:
{{quotation|A retrial not in favour of the defendant is also permissible if the defendant has been convicted in a final order of summary punishment and new facts or evidence have been brought forward, which establish grounds for a conviction of a felony by themselves or in combination with earlier evidence.|§ 373a StPO}}
In Germany, a felony is defined by § 12 (1) StGB as a crime which has a minimum of one year of imprisonment.

===India===
A partial protection against double jeopardy is a [[Fundamental Rights in India|Fundamental Right]] guaranteed under Article 20 (2) of the [[Constitution of India]], which states &quot;No person shall be prosecuted and punished for the same offence more than once&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;constitution&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |url=http://indiacode.nic.in/coiweb/fullact1.asp?tfnm=00%2023 |title=Article 20, Section 2 |work=Constitution of India |quote=No person shall be prosecuted and punished for the same offence more than once. |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20101124001157/http://indiacode.nic.in/coiweb/fullact1.asp?tfnm=00%2023 |archivedate=24 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; This provision enshrines the concept of ''autrefois convict'', that no one convicted of an offence can be tried or punished a second time. However, it does not extend to ''autrefois acquit'', and so if a person is acquitted of a crime he can be retried. In India, protection against ''autrefois acquit'' is a [[statutory right]], not a fundamental one. Such protection is provided by provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure rather than by the Constitution.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Sharma|author2=Sharma B.k.|title=Introduction to the Constitution of India|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=srDytmFE3KMC|year=2007|publisher=PHI Learning Pvt. Ltd.|isbn=978-81-203-3246-1|pages=[https://books.google.com/books?id=srDytmFE3KMC&amp;pg=PA94&amp;lpg=PA94 94]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Japan===
{{Expand section|date=June 2008}}
The [[Constitution of Japan]] states in Article 39 that

{{quote|No person shall be held criminally liable for an act which was lawful at the time it was committed, or of which he has been acquitted, nor shall he be placed in double jeopardy.}}

In practice, however, if someone is acquitted in a lower District Court, then the prosecutor can appeal to the High Court, and then to the Supreme Court. Only the acquittal in the Supreme Court is the final acquittal which prevents any further retrial. This process sometimes takes decades.

The above is not considered a violation of the constitution. Because of Supreme Court precedent, this process is all considered part of a single proceeding.&lt;ref&gt;[http://blog.livedoor.jp/plltakano/archives/54254570.html 刑事裁判を考える：高野隆＠ブログ:二重の危険]. Blog.livedoor.jp (14 May 2007). Retrieved on 2 January 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

===The Netherlands===
In the Netherlands, the state prosecution can appeal a not-guilty verdict at the bench. New evidence can be brought to bear during a retrial at a district court. Thus one can be tried twice for the same alleged crime. If one is convicted at the district court, the defence can make an appeal on procedural grounds to the supreme court. The supreme court might admit this complaint, and the case will be reopened yet again, at another district court. Again, new evidence might be introduced by the prosecution.

On 9 April 2013 the Dutch senate voted 36 &quot;yes&quot; versus 35 &quot;no&quot; in favor of a new law that allows the prosecutor to re-try a person who was found not guilty in court. This new law is limited to crimes where someone died and new evidence must have been gathered. The new law also works retroactively.{{citation needed|date=April 2013}}

===Pakistan===
{{Expand section|date=April 2011}}
Article 13 of the [[Constitution of Pakistan]] protects a person from being punished or prosecuted more than once for the same offence.

===Serbia===
{{Expand section|date=April 2011}}
This principle is incorporated into the Constitution of the Republic of Serbia and further elaborated in its Criminal Procedure Act.&lt;ref&gt;Article 6. of the Criminal Procedure Act – ZAKONIK O KRIVIČNOM POSTUPKU (&quot;Sl. list SRJ&quot;, br. 70/2001 i 68/2002 i &quot;Sl. glasnik RS&quot;, br. 58/2004, 85/2005, 115/2005, 85/2005 – dr. zakon, 49/2007, 20/2009 – dr. zakon i 72/2009)&lt;/ref&gt;

===South Africa===
The [[Bill of Rights (South Africa)|Bill of Rights]] in the [[Constitution of South Africa]] forbids a retrial when there has already been an acquittal or a conviction.
{{quotation|Every accused person has a right to a fair trial, which includes the right ... not to be tried for an offence in respect of an act or omission for which that person has previously been either acquitted or convicted ...|Constitution of the Republic of South Africa, 1996, s. 35(3)(m)}}

===South Korea===
Article 13 of the South Korean constitution provides that no citizen shall be placed in double jeopardy.&lt;ref&gt;[https://archive.is/20130218201252/http://korea.assembly.go.kr/res/low_01_read.jsp CHAPTER Ⅱ Rights and Duties of the Citizens], Constitution of the republic of Korea.&lt;/ref&gt;

===United Kingdom===
{{see also|Criminal Justice Act 2003}}

====England and Wales====
Double jeopardy has been permitted in [[England and Wales]] in certain (exceptional) circumstances since the [[Criminal Justice Act 2003]].

===== Pre-2003 =====

The doctrines of ''[[Peremptory plea|autrefois acquit]]'' and ''autrefois convict'' persisted as part of the [[common law]] from the time of the [[Norman conquest of England]]; they were regarded as essential elements for protection of the subject's liberty and respect for [[due process]] of law in that there should be finality of proceedings.&lt;ref name=&quot;Benét1864p97&quot; /&gt; There were only three exceptions, all relatively recent, to the rules:
*The prosecution has a right of appeal against acquittal in summary cases if the decision appears to be wrong in law or in excess of jurisdiction.&lt;ref&gt;Magistrates' Courts Act 1980 ss.28, 111; Supreme Court Act 1981 s.28&lt;/ref&gt;
*A retrial is permissible if the interests of justice so require, following appeal against conviction by a defendant.&lt;ref&gt;Criminal Appeal Act 1968 s.7&lt;/ref&gt;
*A &quot;tainted acquittal&quot;, where there has been an offence of interference with, or intimidation of, a juror or witness, can be challenged in the High Court.&lt;ref name=&quot;CPIA96&quot;&gt;Criminal Procedure and Investigations Act 1996 s.54&lt;/ref&gt;

In ''[[Connelly v DPP]]'' [1964] AC 1254, the [[Law Lords]] ruled that a defendant could not be tried for any offence arising out of substantially the same set of facts relied upon in a previous charge of which he had been acquitted, unless there are &quot;special circumstances&quot; proven by the prosecution. There is little case law on the meaning of &quot;special circumstances&quot;, but it has been suggested that the emergence of new evidence would suffice.&lt;ref&gt;''Attorney-General for Gibraltar v Leoni'', Court of Appeal, 1999 (unreported); see Law Com CP No 156, para 2.24&lt;/ref&gt;

A defendant who had been convicted of an offence could be given a second trial for an aggravated form of that offence if the facts constituting the aggravation were discovered after the first conviction.&lt;ref&gt;''R v Thomas'' [1950] 1 KB 26&lt;/ref&gt; By contrast, a person who had been acquitted of a lesser offence could not be tried for an aggravated form even if new evidence became available.&lt;ref&gt;''R v Beedie'' [1998] QB 356, Dingwall, 2000&lt;/ref&gt;

=====Post-2003=====

Following the [[murder of Stephen Lawrence]], the Macpherson Report recommended that the double jeopardy rule should be [[Repeal|abrogated]] in murder cases, and that it should be possible to subject an acquitted murder suspect to a second trial if &quot;fresh and viable&quot; new evidence later came to light. The [[Law Commission]] later added its support to this in its report &quot;Double Jeopardy and Prosecution Appeals&quot; (2001). A parallel report into the [[criminal justice system]] by [[Robin Auld|Lord Justice Auld]], a past [[Senior Presiding Judge]] for England and Wales, had also commenced in 1999 and was published as the Auld Report six months after the Law Commission report. It opined that the Law Commission had been unduly cautious by limiting the scope to murder and that &quot;the exceptions should [...] extend to other grave offences punishable with life and/or long terms of imprisonment as Parliament might specify.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=A Review of the Criminal Courts of England and Wales by The Right Honourable Lord Justice Auld |url=http://www.criminal-courts-review.org.uk/ |archive-url=http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20090607141016/http://www.criminal-courts-review.org.uk/ |url-status=dead |archive-date=2009-06-07 |accessdate=5 January 2012 |date=September 2001 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Both [[Jack Straw]] (then [[Home Secretary]]) and [[William Hague]] (then [[Leader of the Opposition]]) favoured this measure.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/uknews/1373237/Straw-moves-to-scrap-Magna-Carta-double-jeopardy-law.html|title=telegraph.co.uk: &quot;Straw moves to scrap Magna Carta double jeopardy law&quot; 5 Nov 2000|date=5 November 2000|work=Telegraph.co.uk|accessdate=13 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;  These recommendations were implemented—not uncontroversially at the time—within the [[Criminal Justice Act 2003]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Broadbridge |first=Sally |title=Research paper 02/74: The Criminal Justice Bill:  Double jeopardy and prosecution appeals |url=http://www.parliament.uk/commons/lib/research/rp2002/rp02-074.pdf |publisher=UK parliament |accessdate=5 January 2012 |date=2 December 2002 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20061120235713/http://www.parliament.uk/commons/lib/research/rp2002/rp02-074.pdf |archivedate=20 November 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2003/44/part/10/enacted |title=Criminal Justice Act 2003 (c. 44) Part 10: Retrial for serious offences |publisher=Her Majesty’s Stationery Office |date=20 November 2003 |accessdate=5 June 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and this provision came into force in April 2005.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/4406129.stm Double jeopardy law ushered out], ''BBC News''. 3 April 2005&lt;/ref&gt; It opened certain serious crimes (including murder, [[manslaughter]], [[kidnapping]], rape, [[robbery|armed robbery]], and serious drug crimes) to a retrial, regardless of when committed, with two conditions: the [[retrial]] must be approved by the [[Director of Public Prosecutions]], and the [[Court of Appeal of England and Wales|Court of Appeal]] must agree to quash the original acquittal due to &quot;new and compelling evidence&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20080915092707/http://www.cps.gov.uk/legal/section19/chapter_j.html Retrial of Serious Offences]. The CPS. Retrieved on 2 January 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; Pressure by Ann Ming, the mother of 1989 murder victim Julie Hogg—whose killer, William Dunlop, was initially acquitted in 1991 and subsequently confessed—also contributed to the demand for legal change.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Wright|first=Stephen|title=Stephen Lawrence suspects to face murder charges in months'|url=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-1295792/Stephen-Lawrence-suspects-face-murder-charges-months.html|accessdate=5 January 2012|newspaper=[[Daily Mail]]|date=18 July 2010|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ming&quot;&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/tees/5150346.stm Murder conviction is legal first], ''BBC News''. 11 September 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

On 11 September 2006, Dunlop became the first person to be convicted of murder following a prior acquittal for the same crime, in his case his 1991 acquittal of Julie Hogg's murder. Some years later he had confessed to the crime, and was convicted of perjury, but was unable to be retried for the killing itself. The case was re-investigated in early 2005, when the new law came into effect, and his case was referred to the Court of Appeal in November 2005 for permission for a new trial, which was granted.&lt;ref name=&quot;ming&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/tees/4426038.stm Man faces double jeopardy retrial], ''BBC News''. 10 November 2005&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/5333230.stm The law of 'double jeopardy'], BBC News. 11 September 2006&lt;/ref&gt; Dunlop pleaded guilty to murdering Julie Hogg and was sentenced to life imprisonment, with a recommendation he serve no less than 17 years.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/tees/5412264.stm Double jeopardy man is given life], ''BBC News''. 6 October 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

On 13 December 2010, Mark Weston became the first person to be retried and found guilty of murder by a jury (Dunlop having confessed). In 1996 Weston had been acquitted of the murder of Vikki Thompson at [[Ascott-under-Wychwood]] on 12 August 1995, but following the discovery in 2009 of compelling new evidence (Thompson's blood on Weston's boots) he was arrested and tried for a second time. He was sentenced to life imprisonment, to serve a minimum of 13 years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-oxfordshire-11982681 |title='Double jeopardy' man guilty of Vikki Thompson murder |date=13 December 2010 |work=BBC News Oxford |accessdate=13 December 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 14 November 2019, Michael Weir became the first person to be twice found guilty of a murder. He was originally convicted of the murder of Leonard Harris and Rose Seferian in 1999, but was the conviction was quashed in 2000 by the Court of Appeal on a technicality. In 2018, new DNA evidence had been obtained and palm prints from both murder scenes were matched to Weir. Twenty years after the original conviction, Weir was convicted for the murders for a second time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-london-50418212 |title=Michael Weir guilty of 1998 'double jeopardy' murders |date=14 November 2019 |work=BBC News |accessdate=14 November 2019 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Scotland====
The double jeopardy rule no longer applies absolutely in [[Scotland]] since the [[Double Jeopardy (Scotland) Act 2011]] came into force on 28 November 2011. The Act introduced three broad exceptions to the rule: where the acquittal had been tainted by an attempt to pervert the course of justice; where the accused admitted their guilt after acquittal; and where there was new evidence.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.legislation.gov.uk/asp/2011/16 &quot;Double Jeopardy (Scotland) Act 2011&quot;] legislation.gov.uk retrieved 6 January 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Northern Ireland====
In [[Northern Ireland]] the [[Criminal Justice Act 2003]], effective 18 April 2005,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nio.gov.uk/media-detail.htm?newsID=11277 &quot;Commencement of Provisions – Criminal Justice Act of 2003,&quot;] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110928112743/http://www.nio.gov.uk/media-detail.htm?newsID=11277 |date=28 September 2011 }} Northern Ireland Office.&lt;/ref&gt; makes certain &quot;qualifying offence&quot; (including murder, rape, kidnapping, specified sexual acts with young children, specified drug offences, defined acts of terrorism, as well as in certain cases attempts or conspiracies to commit the foregoing)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.opsi.gov.uk/acts/acts2003/ukpga_20030044_en_32#sch5 Schedule 5 Part 2] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100702233813/http://www.opsi.gov.uk/acts/acts2003/ukpga_20030044_en_32#sch5 |date=2 July 2010 }} of the Criminal Justice Act of 2003.&lt;/ref&gt; subject to retrial after acquittal (including acquittals obtained before passage of the Act) if there is a finding by the Court of Appeal that there is &quot;new and compelling evidence.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.opsi.gov.uk/acts/acts2003/ukpga_20030044_en_10#pt10 &quot;Retrial for serious offences,&quot;] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100123041757/http://www.opsi.gov.uk/acts/acts2003/ukpga_20030044_en_10#pt10 |date=23 January 2010 }} Part 10 of Criminal Justice Act of 2003.&lt;/ref&gt;

===United States===
{{main|Double Jeopardy Clause}}
The ancient protection of the [[Common Law]] against double jeopardy is maintained in its full rigour in the United States, beyond the reach of any change save that of a Constitutional Amendment. The [[Fifth Amendment to the United States Constitution]] provides:
{{quote|...&amp;nbsp;nor shall any person be subject for the same offence to be twice put in jeopardy of life or limb;&amp;nbsp;...&lt;ref name=&quot;fifth amendment double jeopardy&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Harper |first=Timothy |title=The Complete Idiot's Guide to the U.S. Constitution |publisher=Penguin Group |date=2 October 2007 |page=109 |isbn=978-1-59257-627-2 |quote= However, the Fifth Amendment contains several other important provisions for protecting your rights. It is the source of the double jeopardy doctrine, which prevents authorities from trying a person twice for the same crime&amp;nbsp;...}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Conversely, double jeopardy comes with a key exception. Under the dual sovereignty doctrine, multiple sovereigns can indict a defendant for the same crime. The federal and state governments can have overlapping criminal laws, so a criminal offender may be convicted in individual states and federal courts for exactly the same crime or for different crimes arising out of the same facts.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Gamble v. United States]]'', {{Ussc|587||2019|docket=17-646}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  However, in 2016, the Supreme Court [[Puerto Rico v. Sanchez Valle|held]] that [[Puerto Rico]] is not a separate sovereign for purposes of the Double Jeopardy Clause.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Puerto Rico v. Sanchez Valle]]'', {{Ussc|579||2016|docket=15-108}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The dual sovereignty doctrine has been the subject of substantial scholarly criticism.&lt;ref&gt;Adler, Adam J. &quot;Dual Sovereignty, Due Process, and Duplicative Punishment: A New Solution to an Old Problem&quot;. ''Yale Law Journal''. N.p., Nov. 2014. Web. 15 Nov. 2015. [http://www.yalelawjournal.org/note/dual-sovereignty-due-process-and-duplicative-punishment-a-new-solution-to-an-old-problem]&lt;/ref&gt;

As described by the U.S. Supreme Court in its unanimous decision concerning ''[[Ball v. United States]]'' 163 U.S. 662 (1896), one of its earliest cases dealing with double jeopardy, &quot;the prohibition is not against being twice punished, but against being twice put in jeopardy; and the accused, whether convicted or acquitted, is equally put in jeopardy at the first trial.&quot;&lt;ref name=USvBall&gt;{{cite court|litigants=United States v. Ball |vol=163 |reporter= |opinion= 662 |pinpoint= |court= |date=1896 |url=https://supreme.justia.com/cases/federal/us/163/662/case.html |accessdate=2 May 2018 |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;!-- Included this quote so that the reader will know why it's called &quot;double jeopardy&quot; --&gt; The Double Jeopardy Clause encompasses four distinct prohibitions: subsequent prosecution after acquittal, subsequent prosecution after conviction, subsequent prosecution after certain mistrials, and multiple punishment in the same indictment.&lt;ref&gt;''[[North Carolina v. Pearce]]'', {{Ussc|395|711|1969}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Jeopardy &quot;attaches&quot; when the jury is impanelled, the first witness is sworn, or a plea is accepted.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Crist v. Bretz]]'', {{Ussc|437|28|1978}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Prosecution after acquittal====
With two exceptions, the government is not permitted to appeal or retry the defendant once jeopardy attaches to a trial unless the case does not conclude. Conditions which constitute &quot;conclusion&quot; of a case include
* After the entry of an acquittal,
** whether a directed verdict before the case is submitted to the jury,&lt;ref&gt;''[[Fong Foo v. United States]]'', {{Ussc|369|141|1962}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''[[Sanabria v. United States]]'', {{Ussc|437|54|1978}}.&lt;/ref&gt;
** a directed verdict after a deadlocked jury,&lt;ref&gt;''[[United States v. Martin Linen Supply Co.]]'', {{Ussc|430|564|1977}}.&lt;/ref&gt;
** an appellate reversal for sufficiency (except by direct appeal to a higher appellate court),&lt;ref&gt;''[[Burks v. United States]]'', {{Ussc|437|1|1978}}.&lt;/ref&gt;
** or an &quot;implied acquittal&quot; via conviction of a [[lesser included offence]].&lt;ref&gt;''[[Green v. United States]]'', {{Ussc|355|184|1957}}.&lt;/ref&gt;
* re-litigating against the same defense a fact necessarily found by the jury in a prior acquittal,&lt;ref&gt;''[[Ashe v. Swenson]]'', {{Ussc|397|436|1970}}.&lt;/ref&gt; even if the jury hung on other counts.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Yeager v. United States]]'', {{Ussc|557|110|2009}}.&lt;/ref&gt; In such a situation, the government is barred by [[collateral estoppel]].
In these cases, the trial is concluded and the prosecution is precluded from appealing or retrying the defendant over the offence to which they were acquitted.

This principle does not prevent the government from appealing a pre-trial motion to dismiss&lt;ref&gt;''[[Serfass v. United States]]'', {{Ussc|420|377|1973}}.&lt;/ref&gt; or other non-merits dismissal,&lt;ref&gt;''[[United States v. Scott]],'' {{Ussc|437|82|1978}}.&lt;/ref&gt; or a directed verdict after a jury conviction,&lt;ref&gt;''[[Wilson v. United States]]'', {{Ussc|420|332|1975}}.&lt;/ref&gt; nor does it prevent the trial judge from entertaining a motion for reconsideration of a directed verdict, if the jurisdiction has so provided by rule or statute.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Smith v. Massachusetts]]'', {{Ussc|543|462|2005}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Nor does it prevent the government from retrying the defendant after an appellate reversal other than for sufficiency,&lt;ref&gt;''[[Ball v. United States]]'', {{Ussc|163|662|1896}}.&lt;/ref&gt; including ''[[habeas corpus]]'',&lt;ref&gt;''[[United States v. Tateo]]'', {{Ussc|377|463|1964}}.&lt;/ref&gt; or &quot;thirteenth juror&quot; appellate reversals notwithstanding sufficiency&lt;ref&gt;''[[Tibbs v. Florida]]'', {{Ussc|457|31|1982}}.&lt;/ref&gt; on the principle that jeopardy has not &quot;terminated&quot;.

The &quot;dual sovereignty&quot; doctrine allows a federal prosecution of an offence to proceed regardless of a previous state prosecution for that same offence&lt;ref&gt;''[[Abbate v. United States]]'', {{Ussc|359|187|1959}}.&lt;/ref&gt; and vice versa&lt;ref&gt;''[[Bartkus v. Illinois]]'', {{Ussc|359|121|1959}}.&lt;/ref&gt; because &quot;an act denounced as a crime by both national and state sovereignties is an offence against the peace and dignity of both and may be punished by each&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;''[[United States v. Lanza]]'', {{Ussc|260|377|1922}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The doctrine is solidly entrenched in the law, but there has been a traditional reluctance in the federal executive branch to gratuitously wield the power it grants, due to public opinion being generally hostile to such action.&lt;ref&gt;Wayne R. LaFave, et al., ''Criminal Procedure'' § 25.5(a) (4th ed. 2004).&lt;/ref&gt;

====Exceptions====
The first exception to a ban on retrying a defendant is if, in a trial, the defendant bribed the judge into acquitting him or her, since the defendant was not in jeopardy.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite court|litigants=[[Aleman v. Judges of the Circuit Court of Cook County]]||vol=138|reporter=F.3d|opinion=302|court=7th Cir.|date=1998|url=https://scholar.google.com/scholar_case?case=12470920553407736097&amp;hl=en&amp;as_sdt=80000006|accessdate=September 7, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The other exception to a ban on retrying a defendant is that a member of the armed forces can be retried by [[court-martial]] in a military court, even if he or she has been previously acquitted by a civilian court.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=SBM Blog |url=http://sbmblog.typepad.com/sbm-blog/2012/02/double-jeopardy-and-the-military-a-lurid-case-in-point.html |title=Double Jeopardy and the Military: A Sensational Case In Point - SBM Blog |publisher=Sbmblog.typepad.com |date=14 November 2011 |accessdate=14 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Multiple punishment, including prosecution after conviction====
In ''[[Blockburger v. United States]]'' (1932), the Supreme Court announced the following test: the government may separately try and punish the defendant for two crimes if each crime contains an element that the other does not.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Blockburger v. United States]]'', {{Ussc|284|299|1932}} See, e.g., ''[[Brown v. Ohio]]'', {{Ussc|432|161|1977}}.&lt;/ref&gt; ''Blockburger'' is the default rule, unless the governing statute legislatively intends to depart; for example, [[Continuing Criminal Enterprise]] (CCE) may be punished separately from its predicates,&lt;ref&gt;''[[Garrett v. United States]]'', {{Ussc|471|773|1985}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''[[Rutledge v. United States]],'' {{Ussc|517|292|1996}}.&lt;/ref&gt; as can conspiracy.&lt;ref&gt;''[[United States v. Felix]]'', {{Ussc|503|378|1992}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''Blockburger'' test, originally developed in the multiple punishments context, is also the test for prosecution after conviction.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Missouri v. Hunter]]'', {{Ussc|459|359|1983}}.&lt;/ref&gt; In ''[[Grady v. Corbin]]'' (1990), the Court held that a double jeopardy violation could lie even where the ''Blockburger'' test was not satisfied,&lt;ref&gt;''[[Grady v. Corbin]]'', {{Ussc|495|508|1990}}.&lt;/ref&gt; but ''Grady'' was overruled in ''[[United States v. Dixon]]'' (1993).&lt;ref&gt;''[[United States v. Dixon]]'', {{Ussc|509|688|1993}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Prosecution after mistrial====
The rule for [[mistrial]]s depends upon who sought the mistrial. If the defendant moves for a mistrial, there is no bar to retrial, unless the prosecutor acted in &quot;bad faith&quot;, i.e. goaded the defendant into moving for a mistrial because the government specifically wanted a mistrial.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Oregon v. Kennedy]]'', {{Ussc|456|667|1982}}.&lt;/ref&gt; If the prosecutor moves for a mistrial, there is no bar to retrial if the trial judge finds &quot;manifest necessity&quot; for granting the mistrial.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Arizona v. Washington]]'', {{Ussc|434|497|1978}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The same standard governs mistrials granted [[sua sponte]].

Retrials are not common, due to the legal expenses to the government. However, in the mid-1980s Georgia antique dealer [[James Arthur Williams]] was tried a record four times for the murder of Danny Hansford and (after three mistrials) was finally acquitted on the grounds of self-defense.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.law.umich.edu/special/exoneration/Pages/casedetail.aspx?caseid=4195|title=James Williams - National Registry of Exonerations|website=www.law.umich.edu|access-date=2020-01-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; The case is recounted in the book ''[[Midnight in the Garden of Good and Evil]],''&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.savannahmagazine.com/25-years-after-midnight/|title=25 Years After Midnight|last=Domet|first=Sarah|date=2019-09-13|website=Savannah Magazine|language=en-US|access-date=2020-01-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; which was adapted into a film directed by [[Clint Eastwood]] (the movie omits the first three murder trials).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.rogerebert.com/reviews/midnight-in-the-garden-of-good-and-evil-1997|title=Midnight In The Garden Of Good And Evil movie review (1997) {{!}} Roger Ebert|last=Ebert|first=Roger|website=www.rogerebert.com|language=en|access-date=2020-01-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Law}}
*[[Sam Sheppard]]
*[[Emmett Till]]

==Footnotes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
*{{cite book |last1=Sigler |first1=Jay |title=Double jeopardy; the development of a legal and social policy |url=https://archive.org/details/doublejeopardyde0000sigl |url-access=registration |date=1969 |publisher=Cornell University Press [1969] |ref=Double jeopardy -- United States}}

==External links==

===Australia===
; In favour of current rule prohibiting retrial after acquittal
*[http://www.agd.nsw.gov.au/lawlink/pdo/ll_pdo.nsf/pages/PDO_ruleagainstdoublejeopardy NSW Public Defenders Office]

; Opposing the rule that prohibits retrial after acquittal
*[http://www.autrefoisacquit.info/index.html Questioning Double Jeopardy]
*[http://www.doublejeopardyreform.org DoubleJeopardyReform.Org]

===United Kingdom===
Research and Notes produced for the UK Parliament, summarising the history of legal change, views and responses, and analyses:
* {{cite web|last=Broadbridge |first=Sally |title=Research paper 02/74: The Criminal Justice Bill: Double jeopardy and prosecution appeals |url=http://www.parliament.uk/commons/lib/research/rp2002/rp02-074.pdf |publisher=UK parliament |accessdate=5 January 2012 |date=2 December 2002 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20061120235713/http://www.parliament.uk/commons/lib/research/rp2002/rp02-074.pdf |archivedate=20 November 2006 |df=dmy }}
* {{cite web|last=Broadbridge|first=Sally|title=Double jeopardy|url=http://www.parliament.uk/briefing-papers/SN01082|publisher=UK Parliament|accessdate=5 January 2012|date=28 January 2009}} ([http://www.parliament.uk/briefing-papers/SN01082.pdf direct download link])

===United States===
*[http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/data/constitution/amendment05/ FindLaw Annotation of the Fifth Amendment to the Constitution]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20060110030555/http://www.uscourts.gov/outreach/DJ/index.htm Double Jeopardy Game on uscourts.gov] (archived from [http://www.uscourts.gov/outreach/DJ/index.htm the original] on 2006-01-10)
*[[Jack McCall]] (famous murder case involving a claim of double jeopardy)

===Other countries===
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20071119043436/http://www.lawreform.ie/publications/data/lrc119/lrc_119.html Law Reform Commission of Ireland Consultation Paper on Prosecution Appeals Brought on Indictment]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Double Jeopardy}}
[[Category:Criminal procedure]]
[[Category:Legal terminology]]</text>
      <sha1>c7528pjulyxtjh33pgx7rt0ei20lrct</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
