  <page>
    <title>Dead Kennedys</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7954</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941450704</id>
      <parentid>940811114</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-18T17:23:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>2606:A000:ED89:2D00:25AA:2B1A:7FFB:C623</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|American hardcore punk band}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=June 2018}}
{{Infobox musical artist
| name            = Dead Kennedys
| image           = Dead kennedys.png
| caption         = From left to right: East Bay Ray, Jello Biafra, D. H. Peligro and Klaus Flouride
| background      = group_or_band
| alt             = 
| alias           = 
| origin          = [[San Francisco]], [[California]], U.S.
| genre           = {{hlist|[[Punk rock]]|[[hardcore punk]]}}
| years_active    = {{flatlist|
* 1978–1986
* 2001–present}}
| label           = {{hlist|[[Cherry Red Records|Cherry Red]]|{{nowrap|[[Faulty Products]]}}|{{nowrap|[[Alternative Tentacles]]}}|[[Manifesto Records|Manifesto]]/Decay}}
| associated_acts = {{flatlist|
* [[Jello Biafra]] (solo career)
* Skrapyard
* The Jungle Studs
* [[Jello Biafra and the Guantanamo School of Medicine]]
* [[Lard (band)|Lard]]
* [[False Alarm (band)|False Alarm]]
* [[Melvins]]
* [[D.O.A. (band)|D.O.A.]]
* [[Against All Will]]}}
| website         = {{URL|http://www.deadkennedys.com/}}
| current_members = [[East Bay Ray]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Klaus Flouride]]&lt;br /&gt;[[D. H. Peligro]]&lt;br /&gt;Ron &quot;Skip&quot; Greer
| past_members    = [[Jello Biafra]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Brandon Cruz]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Carlos Cadona|6025]]&lt;br&gt;[[Bruce Slesinger|Ted]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Jeff Penalty]]&lt;br /&gt;Dave Scheff&lt;br /&gt;Greg Reeves
}}
 
'''Dead Kennedys''' are&lt;!-- Proper nouns that are plural in form take a plural verb in both American English and British English. Please do not change &quot;are&quot; to &quot;is&quot;. --&gt; an American [[punk rock]] band that formed in [[San Francisco]], [[California]], in 1978. The band was one of the defining [[hardcore punk]] bands during its initial eight-year run.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.allmusic.com/artist/dead-kennedys-mn0000786613/biography|title=Dead Kennedys {{!}} Biography &amp; History|website=AllMusic|language=en-us|access-date=2019-06-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Dead Kennedys' lyrics were usually political in nature, satirizing establishment political figures (liberal and conservative) and authority in general, as well as popular culture and even the punk movement itself. During their initial incarnation between 1978 and 1986, they attracted considerable controversy for their provocative lyrics and artwork. Several stores refused to stock their recordings, provoking debate about censorship in rock music; in the mid-1980s, vocalist and primary lyricist [[Jello Biafra]] became an active campaigner against the [[Parents Music Resource Center]]. This culminated in an obscenity trial between 1985 and 1986, which resulted in a [[hung jury]].

The group released a total of four studio albums and one EP before disbanding in 1986. Following the band's dissolution, Biafra continued to collaborate and record with other artists including [[D.O.A. (band)|D.O.A.]], [[NoMeansNo]] and his own bands [[Lard (band)|Lard]] and the [[Guantanamo School of Medicine]], as well as releasing several spoken word performances.

In 2000 (upheld on appeal in 2003), Biafra lost an acrimonious legal case initiated by his former Dead Kennedys band mates over songwriting credits and unpaid royalties. In 2001, the band reformed without Biafra; various singers have since been recruited for vocal duties.

==History==

===Formation of the band (1978–79)===
Dead Kennedys formed in June 1978 in [[San Francisco, California]], when [[East Bay Ray]] (Raymond Pepperell) advertised for bandmates in the newspaper ''[[The Recycler]]'', after seeing a [[ska-punk]] show at [[Mabuhay Gardens]] in San Francisco. The original band lineup consisted of [[Jello Biafra]] (Eric Reed Boucher) on vocals, East Bay Ray on guitar, [[Klaus Flouride]] (Geoffrey Lyall) on bass, [[Carlos Cadona|6025]] (Carlos Cadona) on rhythm guitar and [[Ted (musician)|Ted]] (Bruce Slesinger) on drums and percussion. This lineup recorded their [[The 1978 Demos|first demos]]. Their first live show was on July 19, 1978 at Mabuhay Gardens in San Francisco, California. They were the opening act on a bill that included DV8 and Negative Trend with The Offs headlining.

Dead Kennedys played numerous shows at local venues afterwards. Due to the provocative name of the band, they sometimes played under pseudonyms, including &quot;The DK's&quot;, &quot;The Sharks&quot;, &quot;The Creamsicles&quot; and &quot;The Pink Twinkies&quot;. The band's real name generated controversy. ''[[San Francisco Chronicle]]'' columnist [[Herb Caen]] wrote in November 1978, &quot;Just when you think tastelessness has reached its [[nadir]], along comes a punk rock group called 'The Dead Kennedys', which will play at Mabuhay Gardens on Nov. 22, the 15th anniversary of [[John F. Kennedy's assassination]].&quot; Despite mounting protests, the owner of Mabuhay declared, &quot;I can't cancel them NOW—there's a contract. Not, apparently, the kind of contract some people have in mind.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Caen, Herb (November 17, 1978) &quot;On the Rotunda.&quot; ''San Francisco Chronicle.''&lt;/ref&gt; However, despite popular belief, the name was not meant to insult the Kennedy family, but according to Biafra, &quot;to bring attention to the end of the American Dream&quot;.

6025 left the band in March 1979 under somewhat unclear circumstances, generally considered to be musical differences. In June, the band released their first single, &quot;[[California Über Alles]]&quot;, on Biafra and East Bay Ray's [[independent label]], [[Alternative Tentacles]]. The band followed with a poorly attended [[East Coast of the United States|East Coast]] tour, being a new and fairly unknown band at the time, without a full album release.

===''Fresh Fruit for Rotting Vegetables'' (1980–81)===
[[File:Dead-kennedys-live.jpg|thumb|right|200px|A live performance photo.]]
In early 1980, they recorded and released the single &quot;[[Holiday in Cambodia]]&quot;. In June, the band recorded their debut album, ''[[Fresh Fruit for Rotting Vegetables]]'', released in September of that year on the UK label Cherry Red. The album reached number 33 on the [[UK Albums Chart]]. Since its initial release, it has been re-released by several other labels, including IRS, Alternative Tentacles, and Cleopatra. The newest reissue-- the special 25th anniversary edition-- features the original artwork and a bonus 55-minute DVD documenting the making of the album as well as the band's early years &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://pitchfork.com/reviews/albums/2626-fresh-fruit-for-rotting-vegetables/|title=Dead Kennedys: Fresh Fruit for Rotting Vegetables|website=Pitchfork|language=en|access-date=2019-03-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;. 

&lt;!-- Commented out: [[File:Pullmystrings.jpg|thumb|left|150px|Dead Kennedys at the Bay Area Music Awards]] --&gt;On March 25, 1980, Dead Kennedys were invited to perform at the [[Bay Area Music Awards]] in an effort to give the event some &quot;new wave credibility&quot;, in the words of the organizers. The day of the performance was spent practicing the song they were asked to play, the underground hit &quot;California Über Alles&quot;. The band became the talking point of the ceremony when after about 15 seconds into the song, Biafra stopped the band—in a manner reminiscent of [[Radio Radio#1977 Saturday Night Live appearance|Elvis Costello's ''Saturday Night Live'' appearance]]—and said, &quot;Hold it! We've gotta prove that we're adults now. We're not a punk rock band, we're a [[New wave music|new wave]] band.&quot; The band, all wearing white shirts with a big, black S painted on the front, pulled black ties from around the backs of their necks to form a dollar sign, then started playing a new song titled &quot;Pull My Strings&quot;, a barbed, [[Satire|satirical]] attack on the ethics of the mainstream music industry, which contained the lyrics, &quot;Is my cock big enough, is my brain small enough, for you to make me a star?&quot;. The song also referenced [[The Knack]]'s song &quot;[[My Sharona]]&quot;. &quot;Pull My Strings&quot; was never recorded for a studio release, though the performance at the Bay Area Music Awards, which was the only time the song was ever performed, was released on the band's compilation album ''[[Give Me Convenience or Give Me Death]]''.

In January 1981, Ted announced that he wanted to leave to pursue a career in architecture and would help look for a replacement. He played his last concert in February 1981. His replacement was [[D.H. Peligro]] (Darren Henley). Around the same time, East Bay Ray had tried to pressure the rest of the band to sign to the major record label [[Polydor Records]]; Biafra stated that he was prepared to leave the group if the rest of the band wanted to sign to the label,&lt;ref name=&quot;polydor&quot;&gt;Nardwuar the Human Serviette, December 2005 interview with Jello Biafra and The Melvins, as reproduced in [http://www.alternativetentacles.com/batcasts/batcast-013-2006_04_25.m4a Alternative Tentacles Batcast No.&amp;nbsp;15, April 25, 2006] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110603233500/http://www.alternativetentacles.com/batcasts/batcast-013-2006_04_25.m4a |date=June 3, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; though East Bay Ray asserts that he recommended against signing with Polydor. Polydor decided not to sign the band after they learned that Dead Kennedys' next single was to be entitled &quot;[[Too Drunk to Fuck]]&quot;.

When &quot;Too Drunk to Fuck&quot; came out in May 1981, the song caused much controversy in the UK as the BBC feared the single would reach the Top 30; this would require a mention of the song on ''[[Top of the Pops]]''. It was never played although it was called &quot;'Too Drunk' by the Kennedys&quot; by presenter [[Tony Blackburn]].

===''In God We Trust, Inc.'', ''Plastic Surgery Disasters'' and Alternative Tentacles Records (1981–85)===
After Peligro joined the band, the extended play ''[[In God We Trust, Inc.]]'' (1981) saw them move toward a more aggressive hardcore/thrash sound. In addition to the EP's controversial artwork depicting a gold Christ figure on a cross of dollar bills, the lyrics contained Biafra's most biting social and political commentary yet, and songs such as &quot;[[Moral Majority]]&quot;, &quot;[[Nazi Punks Fuck Off!]]&quot; and &quot;[[California Über Alles|We've Got a Bigger Problem Now]]&quot; placed Dead Kennedys as the spokesmen of social protest, while &quot;Dog Bite&quot;, a cover version of ''[[Rawhide (song)|Rawhide]]'' and various joke introductions showed a much more whimsical side. In 1982, they released their second studio album, ''[[Plastic Surgery Disasters]]''. The album's cover features a withered starving African child's hand being held and dwarfed by a white man's hand, a picture that had won the World Press Photo award in 1980, taken in Karamoja district in Uganda by Mike Wells.

The band's music had evolved considerably in a short time, moving away from hardcore formulae toward a more innovative jazz-informed style, featuring musicianship and dynamics far beyond other bands in the genre (thus effectively removing the music from that genre). By now the group had become a de facto political force, pitting itself against rising elements of American social and political life such as the religious right, Ronald Reagan and the idle rich. The band continued touring all over the United States, as well as Europe and Australia, and gained a large underground following. While they continued to play live shows during 1983 and 1984, they took a break from releasing new records to concentrate on the [[Alternative Tentacles]] record label, which would become synonymous with DIY alternative culture. The band continued to write and perform new material during this time, which would appear on their next album (some of these early performances can be seen in the ''[[DMPO's on Broadway]]'' video, originally released by [[Dirk Dirksen]] and later reissued on Rhino).

===''Frankenchrist'' and obscenity trial (1985–86)===
The release of the album ''[[Frankenchrist]]'' in 1985 showed the band had grown in musical proficiency and lyrical maturity. While there were still a number of loud/fast songs, much of the music featured an eclectic mix of instruments including trumpets and synthesizers. Around this time [[Klaus Flouride]] released the similarly experimental solo EP ''[[Cha Cha Cha With Mr. Flouride]]''. Lyrically, the band continued their trademark social commentary, with songs such as &quot;MTV Get Off The Air&quot; and &quot;Jock-O-Rama (Invasion of the Beef Patrol)&quot; poking fun at mainstream America.

However, the controversy that erupted over H.R. Giger's &quot;[[Penis Landscape]]&quot;, included as an insert with the album, dwarfed the notoriety of its music. The artwork caused a furor with the newly formed [[Parents Music Resource Center]] (PMRC). In December 1985 a teenage girl purchased the album at the Wherehouse Records store in [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles County]].&lt;ref name=WishniaNation&gt;Wishnia, Steven. &quot;Of Punk and Pornography: Rockin' With the First Amendment&quot;. ''The Nation''. October 24, 1987.&lt;/ref&gt; The girl's mother wrote letters of complaint to the [[California Attorney General]] and to Los Angeles [[prosecutors]].&lt;ref name=WishniaNation/&gt; In 1986, members of the band, along with other parties involved in the distribution of ''Frankenchrist'', were charged criminally with distribution of harmful matter to minors. The store where the teen actually purchased the album was never named in the lawsuit.&lt;ref name=WishniaNation/&gt; The criminal charges focused on an illustration by [[H.R. Giger]], titled &quot;Work 219: Landscape XX&quot; (also known as ''[[Penis Landscape]]''). Included as a poster with the album, ''Penis Landscape'' depicts nine copulating penises and vaginas.&lt;ref&gt;Deflem, Mathieu. 2020. [https://deflem.blogspot.com/2019/07/music-censorship-labeling.html &quot;Popular Culture and Social Control: The Moral Panic on Music Labeling.&quot;] ''American Journal of Criminal Justice'' 45(1):2-24 (First published online July 24, 2019).&lt;/ref&gt;

Members of the band and others in the chain of distribution were charged with violating the California Penal Code&lt;ref name=&quot;penalcode&quot;&gt;[http://www.leginfo.ca.gov/calaw.html California Penal Code] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090714132609/http://www.leginfo.ca.gov/calaw.html |date=July 14, 2009 }} at leginfo.ca.gov&lt;/ref&gt; on a [[misdemeanor]] charge carrying a maximum penalty of up to a year in county jail and a base fine of up to $2,000. Biafra says that during this time government agents invaded and searched his home. The prosecution tried to present the poster to the jury in isolation for consideration as obscene material, but Judge Susan Isacoff ruled that the poster must be considered along with the music and lyrics.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.metnews.com/articles/2004/reti052804.htm &quot;Judge Isacoff, Commissioner Duffey Slate July Retirements&quot;] ''Metropolitan News-Enterprise''. May 28, 2004&lt;/ref&gt; The charges against three of the original defendants, Ruth Schwartz (owner of [[Mordam Records]]), Steve Boudreau (a distributor involved in supplying ''Frankenchrist'' to the Los Angeles Wherehouse store), and Salvatore Alberti (owner of the factory where the record was pressed), were dismissed for lack of evidence.&lt;ref name=WishniaNation/&gt;

In August 1987, the case went to the jury with two remaining defendants: Jello Biafra and Michael Bonanno (former Alternative Tentacles label manager).&lt;ref name=WishniaNation/&gt; However, the criminal trial ended with a hung jury, split 7 to 5 in favor of acquittal. [[District Attorney]]s Michael Guarino and Ira Riener made a motion for a retrial which was denied by Judge Isacoff, [[Superior Court]] Judge for the County of Los Angeles.&lt;ref&gt;Drozdowski, Ted. [https://web.archive.org/web/20010423020902/http://www.geocities.com/CapitolHill/Congress/2503/interview06.html &quot;Jello Biafra cuts to the politics of pop&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; The album, however, was banned from many record stores nationwide.

After the break up of the band, Jello Biafra brought up the court case on ''[[The Oprah Winfrey Show]]''. Biafra was on the show with [[Tipper Gore]] as part of a panel discussion on the issues of &quot;controversial music lyrics&quot; and censorship.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|publisher=[[YouTube]]|title=Jello Biafra The Oprah Winfrey Show|date=2017-05-13|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TNoEWol1wbg|access-date=2018-08-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===''Bedtime for Democracy'' and break-up (1986)===
In addition to the obscenity lawsuit, the band became increasingly disillusioned with the underground scene as well. The hardcore scene, which had been a haven for free-thinking intellectuals and downtrodden nonconformists, was attracting a more violent audience that imposed an increasing level of brutality on other concertgoers and began to alienate many of the bands and individuals who had helped pioneer the movement in the early 1980s{{citation needed|date=August 2017}}. In earlier years the band had criticized neo-Nazi skinheads for trying to ruin the punk scene, but just as big a problem was the popularity of increasingly macho hardcore bands, which brought the group (and their genre) an audience that had little to do with the ideas/ideals they stood for{{citation needed|date=August 2017}}. In January 1986, frustrated and alienated from their own scene, Dead Kennedys decided to break up to pursue other interests and played their last concert on February 21. The band continued to work on songs, with Biafra penning songs such as &quot;[[Bedtime for Democracy|Chickenshit Conformist]]&quot; and &quot;[[Bedtime for Democracy|Anarchy for Sale]]&quot;, which articulated their feelings about the &quot;dumbing down&quot; of punk rock.

During the summer they recorded these songs for their final album, ''[[Bedtime for Democracy]]'', which was released in November. The artwork, depicting a defaced [[Statue of Liberty]] overrun with Nazis, media, opportunists, Klan members, corrupt government officials, and religious zombies, echoed the idea that neither America itself or the punk scene were safe havens any more for &quot;your tired, your poor, your huddled masses yearning to breathe free&quot;. The album contains a number of fast/short songs interspersed with jazz (&quot;D.M.S.O.&quot;), spoken word (&quot;A Commercial&quot;) and psychedelia (&quot;Cesspools In Eden&quot;). The lyrical focus is more introspective and earnest (&quot;Where Do Ya Draw The Line?&quot;), with an anti-war, anti-violence (&quot;Rambozo The Clown&quot;) bend, moving away from the violent imagery of their early records, while remaining as subversive as ever (&quot;I Spy&quot;, &quot;D.M.S.O.&quot;). In December, the band announced their split. Biafra went on to speak about his political beliefs on numerous television shows and he released a number of [[spoken-word]] albums. Ray, Flouride, and Peligro also went on to solo careers.

===Reforming of new band line-up===
In 2001, Ray, Peligro, and Flouride reformed the Dead Kennedys, with former [[Dr. Know (band)|Dr. Know]] singer [[Brandon Cruz]] replacing Biafra on vocals. The band played under the name &quot;DK Kennedys&quot; for a few concerts, but later reverted to &quot;Dead Kennedys&quot; permanently. They played across the continental United States, Europe, Asia, South America, and Russia. Brandon Cruz left the band in May 2003 and was replaced by [[Jeff Penalty]]. The band has released two live albums of archival performances on Manifesto Records: ''[[Mutiny on the Bay]]'', compiled from various live shows including a recording from their last show with Biafra in 1986, and ''[[Live at the Deaf Club]]'', a recording of a 1979 performance at the Deaf Club in [[San Francisco]] which was greeted with more enthusiasm.

On October 9, 2007, a [[greatest hits album|best of album]] titled ''[[Milking the Sacred Cow]]'' was released. It includes two previously unreleased live versions of &quot;Soup Is Good Food&quot; and &quot;Jock-O-Rama&quot;, originally found on ''Frankenchrist''.

Jeff Penalty left the band in March 2008 in what he describes as a &quot;not amicable split.&quot;&lt;ref name=Penalty&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.punknews.org/article/28168 |title=Jeff Penalty leaves the Dead Kennedys |work=Punknews.org |date= |accessdate=July 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a statement released, Jeff said that, following a series of disputes, the band had secretly recruited a new singer and played a gig in his neighbourhood, although he also stated he was &quot;really proud of what we were able to accomplish with Dead Kennedys&quot;.&lt;ref name=Penalty/&gt; He was replaced by former [[Wynona Riders]] singer Ron &quot;Skip&quot; Greer. D.H. also left the band to &quot;take some personal time off&quot;. He was replaced for a tour by [[Translator (band)|Translator]] drummer Dave Scheff.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.deadkennedys.com/news.html#032408 |title=Welcome To The Official Website For Dead Kennedys |publisher=Deadkennedys.com |date= |accessdate=June 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Break from touring===
On August 21, 2008, the band announced an extended break from touring due to the health-related issues of Flouride and Peligro. They stated their plans to collaborate on new projects. The band performed a gig in [[Santa Rosa, California]] in June 2009, with Peligro returning to the drum kit.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.deadkennedys.com/tours.html |title=Official Dead Kennedys web site |publisher=Deadkennedys.com |date= |accessdate=June 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 2010, Dead Kennedys announced plans for a short East Coast tour. The lineup assembled for this tour contained East Bay Ray, Peligro, Greer, and bassist Greg Reeves replacing Flouride, who was taking &quot;personal time off&quot; from the band.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.deadkennedys.com/news.html#081110 |title=Official web page news section |publisher=Deadkennedys.com |date= |accessdate=June 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://serviette.ca/radio_show/2011/nw20110211.mp3 Nardwuar interview with Jello Biafra], Serviette.ca, February 11, 2011, accessed April 5, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; The tour dates included performances in [[Philadelphia]], [[New York City]], [[Boston]], [[Washington, D.C.]], [[Portland, Maine]] and [[Hawaii]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.punknews.org/article/39114 |title=Dead Kennedy's 2010 tour |publisher=Punknews.org |date= |accessdate=June 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The band has played a reworked version of their song &quot;MTV Get Off the Air&quot;, re-titled &quot;MP3 Get Off the Web&quot;, with lyrics criticizing music piracy during their October 16, 2010, concert at the Rock and Roll Hotel in [[Washington, D.C.]].&lt;ref name=&quot;newmaterial&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://dcheavymetal.com/2010/10/18/a-post-about-the-dead-kennedys |title=A Post About The Dead Kennedys |publisher=Dcheavymetal.com |date=October 18, 2010 |accessdate=June 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Back on the road===
[[File:Dead Kennedys live in Chicago at Bottom Lounge on west Lake June 27, 2014 23-32 -01 (14530182562).jpg|thumb|Dead Kennedys at the [[Bottom Lounge]] in Chicago, June 2014]]
Dead Kennedys had world tours in 2013 and in 2014, the latter mostly in North American cities. In 2015 and 2016 they toured again, including South America, where they had not played since 2001.

In 2017, East Bay Ray revealed that the band and Jello Biafra had been approached by the Punk-oriented music festival [[Riot Fest]] about a potential reunion. While Ray and the rest of the band expressed interest in the concept, Biafra refused.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.axs.com/dead-kennedys-turn-down-reunion-gig-at-riot-fest-remaining-100-percent-114890|title=Dead Kennedys turn down reunion gig at Riot Fest, remaining 100 percent punk|website=Axs.com|accessdate=October 14, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On April 26, 2019, the group released ''DK40'', a live compilation album celebrating 40 years since the band formed.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.billboard.com/articles/columns/rock/8506510/dead-kennedys-east-bay-ray-dk40-live|title=Dead Kennedys' East Bay Ray on Their Explosive Live Legacy -- And His Hopes for Jello Biafra|website=Billboard.com|accessdate=October 14, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Conflicts between members==
=== Royalties lawsuit ===
In the late 1990s, former band members discovered problems with the payment of royalties they had received from [[Alternative Tentacles]]. East Bay Ray, Klaus Flouride, and D. H. Peligro claimed that Jello Biafra had conspired to pay lower royalty rates. Although both sides agreed that the failure to pay these royalties was an accounting mistake, the other members were upset that Biafra failed to inform them of the mistake after he and his co-workers discovered it and additionally claimed he intended to use the money against them.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |quote=Biafra concealed from the other Decay Music partners an underpayment of royalties (totaling over $110,000, with interest) by ATR to Decay Music dating back to 1989.  When, in early 1998, ATR’s then-General Manager, Kristin Von Till, brought the underpayment directly to his attention, Biafra hid the indebtedness from his partners and embarked on a course intended to prevent them from learning or confirming that ATR owed Decay Music these monies. |url=http://www.deadkennedysnews.com/news082802_2.htm#f |title=Biafra’s Deception About Underpayment of Royalties. |accessdate=February 21, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A jury found Biafra and Alternative Tentacles &quot;guilty of [[malice (legal term)|malice]], oppression and [[fraud]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.blabbermouth.net/news/jello-biafra-gets-shot-down-by-dead-kennedys/|title=Jello Biafra Gets Shot Down By Dead Kennedys|date=June 19, 2003|work=blabbermouth.net}}&lt;/ref&gt; Malice was defined for the jury as &quot;conduct which is intended to cause injury or despicable conduct which is carried with a willful and conscious disregard for the rights of others&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;bs1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mi2n.com/press.php3?press_nb=17130 |title=''Music Industry News Network'' |publisher=Mi2n.com |date= |accessdate=June 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Biafra's appeal was denied; he had to pay the outstanding royalties and punitive damages,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.phillaw.com/casepdfs/Dead%20Kennedys%20Superior%20Court.pdf Dead Kennedys v. Jello Biafra Verdict] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120227000532/http://www.phillaw.com/casepdfs/Dead%20Kennedys%20Superior%20Court.pdf |date=February 27, 2012 }}, Cal.App.1 Dist.,2003 A094272&lt;/ref&gt; and was forced to hand over the rights to the majority of Dead Kennedys' back catalogue to the Decay Music partnership. The jury and judges also noted, in their words, that Biafra &quot;lacked credibility&quot; on the songwriting issue and found from evidence presented by both sides that the songwriting credits were due to the entire band.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.phillaw.com/casepdfs/Dead%20Kennedys%20Superior%20Court.pdf Dead Kennedys v. Jello Biafra Verdict] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120227000532/http://www.phillaw.com/casepdfs/Dead%20Kennedys%20Superior%20Court.pdf |date=February 27, 2012 }}, Cal.App.1 Dist., 2003 A094272&lt;/ref&gt;

This dispute was hotly contested by all concerned who felt passionately for their cause, and the case caused minor waves within punk circles. Biafra claims that East Bay Ray had long expressed displeasure with Alternative Tentacles and with the amount of money he received from them, thus the original incentive for the discovery of the back payments. It was found out that Alternative Tentacles was paying Dead Kennedys less per CD than all the other bands, including Biafra himself, and not informing his other bandmates, which was the fraud. Biafra accused the band of wanting to license the famous Dead Kennedys song &quot;[[Holiday in Cambodia]]&quot; for use in a [[Levi's]] jeans commercial, which the band denied.&lt;ref name=&quot;morphizm.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.morphizm.com/recommends/jello2.html |title=&quot;I'm Not an Ad Man:&quot; Interview with Jello Biafra (con.) |publisher=Morphizm.com |date= |accessdate=February 7, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, an instrumental loop from &quot;Holiday in Cambodia&quot; was part of the 1981 movie &quot;Neighbors,&quot; but wasn't included on the soundtrack.

Biafra's former bandmates maintain that they sued because of Jello Biafra's deliberate withholding of money, though when pressed they have acknowledged that the payment was an accounting mistake, but insist that Biafra was wrong in failing to inform the band directly. Details about this issue remain scarce. The band also maintains that the Levi's story was completely fictitious and invented by Biafra to discredit them.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.punknews.org/article/48637/interviews-jello-biafra |title=''Punk News Network Interviews: Jello Biafra'' |publisher=punknews.org |date=August 24, 2012 |accessdate=August 25, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Disputes over new commercial activities===

Matters were stirred up even further when the three bandmates invited Jello Biafra to &quot;bury the hatchet&quot; in the form of a band reunion. Jello Biafra felt it was unprofessional because no one contacted him directly. In addition, Biafra was disdainful of the reunion, and having long expressed his disdain for nostalgia and rock reunion/oldies tours in particular, argued that the whole affair was motivated by greed.&lt;ref name=&quot;morphizm.com&quot;/&gt;

Several DVDs, re-issues, and live albums have been released since the departure of Biafra most recently on Manifesto Records. According to Biafra, the live albums are &quot;cash-ins&quot; on Dead Kennedys' name and his music. Biafra also accused the releases of the new live material of having poor sound quality. Furthermore he has stated he is not receiving any royalties from the sale of any Manifesto Records releases. Consequently, he has discouraged fans from buying any Dead Kennedy reissues. The other band members denied Biafra's accusations regarding the live releases, and have defended the mixes as an effort of hard work. Biafra dismissed the new group as &quot;the world's greediest karaoke band.&quot; Nevertheless, in 2003, [[Klaus Flouride]] said of performances without the band's former frontman: &quot;There hasn't been a show yet that people didn't really like.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.citizinemag.com/music/music-0309_klausflouride.htm &quot;Interview with Dead Kennedys' Klaus Flouride&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110608062512/http://www.citizinemag.com/music/music-0309_klausflouride.htm |date=June 8, 2011 }} by Mark Prindle, ''Citizine'', September 1, 2003&lt;/ref&gt;

Biafra further criticized them for advertising shows using his own image taken from the original 1980s incarnation of the band, which he labeled as false advertising. He attacked the reformed Dead Kennedys in a song called &quot;[[Those Dumb Punk Kids (Will Buy Anything)]]&quot;, which appears on his second collaboration with sludge metal band the [[Melvins]], ''[[Sieg Howdy!]]''

Biafra told an audience at a speaking gig in [[Trenton, New Jersey|Trenton]], [[New Jersey]], that the remaining Dead Kennedys have licensed their single &quot;Too Drunk to Fuck&quot; to be used in a rape scene in a [[Robert Rodriguez]] movie. The reference is to a lounge cover of the song, recorded by the band [[Nouvelle Vague (band)|Nouvelle Vague]], played during a scene in the ''[[Planet Terror]]'' segment of ''[[Grindhouse (film)|Grindhouse]]'', although no rape takes place, and in fact the would-be rapist is killed by the would-be victim. The scene in ''Planet Terror'' has would-be rapist, &quot;Rapist No.&amp;nbsp;1&quot; ([[Quentin Tarantino]]) order one-legged stripper &quot;Cherry Darlin&quot; ([[Rose McGowan]]) to get up off the floor and dance. At this point Tarantino hits play on a cassette recorder and Nouvelle Vague's cover of &quot;Too Drunk To Fuck&quot; plays. Biafra, disapproving of the situation, later wrote, &quot;This is their lowest point since Levi's... This goes against everything the Dead Kennedys stands for in spades... The terrified woman later 'wins' by killing Tarantino, but that excuse does not rescue this at all. I wrote every note of that song and this is not what it was meant for.... Some people will do anything for money. I can't help but think back to how prudish Klaus Flouride was when he objected to H.R. Giger's painting on the &quot;[[Frankenchrist]]&quot; (sic) poster, saying he couldn't bear to show it to his parents. I'd sure love to be a fly on the wall when he tries to explain putting a song in a rape scene for money to his teenage daughter... The deal was pushed through by a new business manager the other three hired.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.alternativetentacles.com/news.php?page=3&amp;news_section=JELLO&amp;window_size=15&amp;sd=iIdfyzSpZwkE0A3pVRu &quot;Greedy ex-DKs okay song for rape scene in new Tarantino Movie&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160312232417/http://www.alternativetentacles.com/news.php?news_section=jello&amp;page=3&amp;sd=iidfyzspzwke0a3pvru&amp;window_size=15 |date=March 12, 2016 }} Alternative Tentacles news page, March 15, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

The reformed Dead Kennedys followed their court victory by releasing reissues of all Dead Kennedys albums (except ''[[Fresh Fruit for Rotting Vegetables]]'', to which they did not have the rights until 2005), releasing several new archival concert DVDs, and licensing several songs to ''[[The Manchurian Candidate (2004 film)|The Manchurian Candidate]]'' remake and the [[Tony Hawk Pro Skater]] video game. [[East Bay Ray]] claims he received a fax from Alternative Tentacles purporting Biafra approved the licensing for the game.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.deadkennedysnews.com/images/tonyhawk.jpg Fax from Uli Elser], previous manager of Alternative Tentacles, May 5, 1999&lt;/ref&gt;

The band claims on their website that they still pay close attention to an [[anti-corporate]] ideology, despite performing on September 5, 2003 at a festival in Turkey that was sponsored by [[Coca-Cola]], noting that they have since pulled out of a show in Los Angeles when they found that it was being sponsored by [[Coors Brewing Company|Coors]]. However, Biafra claims the previous licensing deals prove otherwise.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.deadkennedys.com/news.htm#100605 DKs Pull Out of &quot;Waking the Dead&quot; Show] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20060216103405/http://www.deadkennedys.com/news.htm#100605 |date=February 16, 2006 }}&quot; ''DeadKennedys.com''. October 6, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Logo==
[[File:Dead Kennedys (logo).jpg|thumb|right|70px|&quot;DK&quot; logo]]The original logo was created by [[Winston Smith (artist)|Winston Smith]]. He later contributed artwork for the covers of ''[[In God We Trust, Inc.]]'', ''[[Plastic Surgery Disasters]]'', ''[[Frankenchrist]]'', ''[[Bedtime for Democracy]]'', ''[[Give Me Convenience or Give Me Death]]'', the back cover of the &quot;[[Kill the Poor]]&quot; single and the [[Alternative Tentacles]] logo. When asked about the &quot;DK&quot; logo in an interview, Jello Biafra explained, &quot;...I wanted to make sure it was something simple and easy to spray-paint so people would graffiti it all over the place, and then I showed it to Winston Smith. He played around with it, came back with a bunch of designs that had the circle and slightly 3-D looking letters and he had ones with different patterns behind it. I liked the one with bricks, but ultimately I thought simple red behind it was the boldest and the best.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://trembleunderboomlights.blogspot.com/2007/05/interview-with-jello-biafra.html |title=Tremble Under Boom Lights: Interview with Jello Biafra |publisher=Trembleunderboomlights.blogspot.com |date=May 6, 2007 |accessdate=June 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Music and lyrics==
Dead Kennedys have been described as one of the first [[hardcore punk]] bands.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.allmusic.com/artist/dead-kennedys-mn0000786613/biography |title=Dead Kennedys {{!}} Biography &amp; History |website=[[AllMusic]] |last=Erlewine |first=Stephen Thomas |authorlink=Stephen Thomas Erlewine}}&lt;/ref&gt; They were noted for the harshness of their lyrics, which generally combined biting social satire while expressing a staunchly left-wing view of contemporary America.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://music.msn.com/music/artist/dead-kennedys.1/ |title=Dead Kennedys on MSN Music |publisher=Music.msn.com |date= |accessdate=June 13, 2011 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110429030833/http://music.msn.com/music/artist/dead-kennedys.1/ |archive-date=April 29, 2011 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; Unlike other leftist punk bands who use more direct sloganeering, Dead Kennedys' lyrics were often snide. For example, &quot;[[Holiday in Cambodia]]&quot; is a multi-layered satire targeting both yuppies and Cambodia's recently deposed [[Khmer Rouge]] regime.

Dead Kennedys have influenced multiple acts such as [[System of a Down]], [[Green Day]], [[Faith No More]], [[Rage Against the Machine]], [[Anthrax (American band)|Anthrax]], [[Sepultura]], [[Descendents (band)|Descendents]], [[Bad Religion]], [[X (American band)|X]], [[Minutemen (band)|Minutemen]], [[The Hives]], [[Saves the Day]] and [[Screeching Weasel]] among others.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.allmusic.com/artist/dead-kennedys-mn0000786613/related |title=Dead Kennedys {{!}} Similar Artists |website=[[AllMusic]] |last=Erlewine |first=Stephen Thomas |authorlink=Stephen Thomas Erlewine}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Members==
{{col-begin}}
{{col-2}}
'''Current members'''
* [[East Bay Ray]]&amp;nbsp;– guitars (1978–1986, 2001–present)
* Ron &quot;Skip&quot; Greer&amp;nbsp;– lead vocals (2008–present)
* [[D.H. Peligro]]&amp;nbsp;– drums, backing vocals (1981–1986, 2001–2008, 2009–present)
* [[Klaus Flouride]]&amp;nbsp;– bass, backing vocals (1978–1986, 2001–2010, 2011–present)
{{col-2}}

'''Former members'''
* [[Jello Biafra]]&amp;nbsp;– lead vocals (1978–1986)
* [[Carlos Cadona|6025]]&amp;nbsp;– rhythm guitar (1978–1979)
* [[Bruce Slesinger|Ted]]&amp;nbsp;– drums (1978–1981)
* [[Brandon Cruz]]&amp;nbsp;– lead vocals (2001–2003)
* [[Jeff Penalty]]&amp;nbsp;– lead vocals (2003–2008)
* Dave Scheff&amp;nbsp;– drums (2008)
* Greg Reeves&amp;nbsp;– bass (2010–2011)
{{col-end}}


'''Timeline'''
&lt;timeline&gt;
ImageSize = width:800 height:auto barincrement:20
PlotArea = left:90 bottom:110 top:05 right:20
Alignbars = justify
DateFormat  = dd/mm/yyyy
Period = from:01/06/1978 till:31/12/2017
TimeAxis = orientation:horizontal format:yyyy
Legend = orientation:vertical position:bottom
ScaleMajor = increment:5 start:1980
ScaleMinor = increment:1 start:1979

Colors =
  id:Vocals  value:red            legend:Lead_vocals
  id:BVocals value:pink           legend:Backing_vocals
  id:Guitar1  value:teal          legend:Lead_guitar
  id:Guitar2 value:brightgreen legend:Rhythm_guitar
  id:Bass    value:blue           legend:Bass
  id:Drums   value:orange         legend:Drums
  id:studio  value:black          legend:Studio_album
  id:other   value:gray(0.7)      legend:Other_releases

LineData =
 layer:back
  at:01/09/1980 color:studio
  at:01/12/1981 color:other
  at:01/11/1982 color:studio
  at:01/10/1985 color:studio
  at:01/11/1986 color:studio
  at:01/06/1987 color:other
  at:24/04/2001 color:other
  at:27/01/2004 color:other
  at:09/10/2007 color:other

BarData =
  bar:Biafra text:&quot;Jello Biafra&quot;
  bar:Cruz text:&quot;Brandon Cruz&quot;
  bar:Penalty text:&quot;Jeff Penalty&quot;
  bar:Greer text:&quot;Ron Greer&quot;
  bar:Ray text:&quot;East Bay Ray&quot;
  bar:6025 text:&quot;6025&quot;
  bar:Flouride text:&quot;Klaus Flouride&quot;
  bar:Reeves text:&quot;Greg Reeves&quot;
  bar:Slesinger text:&quot;Ted&quot;
  bar:Peligro text:&quot;D. H. Peligro&quot;
  bar:Scheff text:&quot;Dave Scheff&quot;

PlotData=
  width:11 textcolor:black align:left anchor:from shift:(10,-4)
  bar:Biafra from:01/06/1978 till:01/12/1986 color:Vocals width:11
  bar:Cruz from:01/01/2001 till:01/05/2003 color:Vocals width:11
  bar:Penalty from:01/05/2003 till:01/03/2008 color:Vocals width:11
  bar:Greer from:01/03/2008 till:end color:Vocals width:11
  bar:Ray from:01/06/1978 till:01/12/1986 color:Guitar1 width:11
  bar:Ray from:01/01/2001 till:end color:Guitar1 width:11
  bar:Ray from:01/01/2001 till:end color:Guitar2 width:3
  bar:Ray from:03/03/1979 till:01/12/1986 color:Guitar2 width:3
 bar:6025 from:01/07/1978 till:03/03/1979 color:Guitar2 width:11
  bar:Flouride from:01/06/1978 till:01/12/1986 color:Bass width:11
  bar:Flouride from:01/06/1978 till:01/12/1986 color:BVocals width:3
  bar:Flouride from:01/01/2001 till:01/01/2010 color:Bass width:11
  bar:Flouride from:01/01/2001 till:01/01/2010 color:BVocals width:3
  bar:Reeves from:01/01/2010 till:01/01/2011 color:Bass width:11
  bar:Flouride from:01/01/2011 till:end color:Bass width:11
  bar:Flouride from:01/01/2011 till:end color:BVocals width:3
  bar:Slesinger from:01/06/1978 till:01/02/1981 color:Drums width:11
  bar:Peligro from:01/02/1981 till:01/12/1986 color:Drums width:11
  bar:Peligro from:01/01/2001 till:01/03/2008 color:Drums width:11
  bar:Peligro from:01/01/1984 till:01/12/1986 color:BVocals width:3
  bar:Peligro from:01/01/2001 till:01/03/2008 color:BVocals width:3
  bar:Scheff from:01/03/2008 till:01/06/2009 color:Drums width:11
  bar:Peligro from:01/06/2009 till:end color:Drums width:11
  bar:Peligro from:01/06/2009 till:end color:BVocals width:3
&lt;/timeline&gt;

==Discography==
{{Main|Dead Kennedys discography}}
* ''[[Fresh Fruit for Rotting Vegetables]]'' (1980)
* ''[[Plastic Surgery Disasters]]'' (1982)
* ''[[Frankenchrist]]'' (1985)
* ''[[Bedtime for Democracy]]'' (1986)

==Bibliography==
* {{cite book |last=Kester |first=Marian |title=Dead Kennedys: The Unauthorized Version |publisher=[[Last Gasp]] |year=1983 |isbn=978-0-86719-312-1 |ref=harv |url-access=registration |url=https://archive.org/details/deadkennedysunau00kest }}
* {{cite book |last1=Ogg |first1=Alex |last2=Smith |first2=Winston |last3=Ray |first3=Ruby |title=Dead Kennedys: Fresh Fruit for Rotting Vegetables: The Early Years |publisher=PM Press |year=2014 |isbn=9781604864892 |ref=harv}}

==See also==
* [[List of bands from the San Francisco Bay Area]]
* [[Ronald Reagan in music]]

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

==External links==
{{Wikiquote}}
{{sisterlinks|d=Q208211|n=no|b=no|v=no|voy=no|m=no|s=no|mw=no|wikt=no|species=no|c=Category:Dead Kennedys|q=no}}
* {{Official website}}
* {{DMOZ|Arts/Music/Styles/R/Rock/Punk/Bands_and_Artists/D/Dead_Kennedys/}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20160311042325/http://www.alternativetentacles.com/bandinfo.php?band=deadkennedys&amp;sd=kkxjjpq55vuxbeda%40fa Alternative Tentacles's Dead Kennedys Biography]

{{Dead Kennedys|state=expanded}}
{{Jello Biafra}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Dead Kennedys}}
[[Category:Dead Kennedys| ]]
[[Category:Musical groups established in 1978]]
[[Category:Musical groups disestablished in 1986]]
[[Category:Musical groups reestablished in 2001]]
[[Category:Hardcore punk groups from California]]
[[Category:Musical groups from San Francisco]]
[[Category:Musical quartets]]
[[Category:Obscenity controversies in music]]
[[Category:Alternative Tentacles artists]]
[[Category:1978 establishments in California]]
[[Category:1986 disestablishments in California]]
[[Category:2001 establishments in California]]
[[Category:Articles which contain graphical timelines]]
[[Category:Political music]]
[[Category:American satirists]]</text>
      <sha1>fefn5gp8stiykiecwrif8c781ej1pg7</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
