  <page>
    <title>Dracula</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7923</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942991343</id>
      <parentid>942941546</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-28T04:24:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>UniAce</username>
        <id>83116</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>replaced one instance of unnecessarily gendered language</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{about|the novel|the character|Count Dracula|other uses}}
{{pp|small=yes}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2019}}
{{Use British English|date=October 2019}}

{{Infobox book
| name         = 
| image        = Dracula1st.jpeg
| image_size = 200px
| caption      = The cover of the first edition
| author       = [[Bram Stoker]]
| cover_artist = 
| country      = United Kingdom
| language     = English
| genre        = [[Horror fiction|Horror]], [[Gothic fiction|Gothic]]
| publisher    = [[Constable &amp; Robinson|Archibald Constable and Company (UK)]]
| release_date = {{release date|1897|5|26|df=yes|UK}}
| oclc         = 1447002
}}
'''''Dracula''''' is an 1897 [[Gothic fiction|Gothic horror]] novel by Irish author [[Bram Stoker]]. It introduced the character of [[Count Dracula]] and established many conventions of subsequent [[Vampire literature|vampire fantasy]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bramstoker.org/novels.html|title=Bram Stoker - Novels|website=Bramstoker.org|accessdate=8 October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; The novel tells the story of Dracula's attempt to move from [[Transylvania]] to England so that he may find new blood and spread the undead curse, and of the battle between Dracula and a small group of people led by Professor [[Abraham Van Helsing]].

''Dracula'' has been assigned to many [[literary genre]]s including [[vampire literature]], [[horror fiction]], [[gothic fiction]], and [[invasion literature]]. The novel has spawned numerous theatrical, film, and television interpretations.

==Plot==
[[File:Stoker Dracula Notes Personal.jpg|thumb|upright|Stoker's handwritten notes on the characters in the novel]]

The story is told in an [[Epistolary novel|epistolary]] format, as a series of letters, [[diary]] entries, newspaper articles, and ships' log entries, whose narrators are the novel's protagonists, and occasionally supplemented with newspaper clippings relating events not directly witnessed. The events portrayed in the novel take place chronologically and largely in England and [[Transylvania]] within the same year between 3 May and 6 November. A short note at the end of the final chapter is written 7 years after the events outlined in the novel.

The tale begins with [[Jonathan Harker]], a newly qualified English [[solicitor]], visiting Count Dracula at [[Castle Dracula|his castle]] in the [[Carpathian Mountains]] on the border of [[Transylvania]], [[Bukovina]], and [[Moldavia]], to provide legal support for a [[real estate]] transaction overseen by Harker's employer, Mr Peter Hawkins of [[Exeter]]. Initially impressed by Dracula's gracious manners, Harker soon realizes that he is Dracula's prisoner. Wandering the Count's castle against Dracula's admonition, Harker encounters three vampire sisters, from whom he is rescued by Dracula. Harker soon realizes that Dracula himself is also a vampire. After the preparations are made, Dracula leaves Transylvania and abandons Harker to the sisters. Harker barely escapes from the castle with his life.

Dracula boards a Russian ship, the ''Demeter'', taking with him boxes of Transylvanian soil, which he requires in order to regain his strength. The ship [[Weigh anchor|weighs anchor]] at [[Varna]] and eventually runs aground on the shores of [[Whitby]] in north-east England. The captain's [[Logbook|log]] narrates the gradual disappearance of the entire crew, until the captain alone remained, himself bound to the helm to maintain course. An animal resembling &quot;a large dog&quot; is seen leaping ashore. It is later learned that Dracula successfully purchased multiple estates under the alias 'Count De Ville' throughout London and devised to distribute the boxes to each of them utilizing transportation services as well as moving them himself. He does this to secure for himself lairs and the boxes of earth would be used as his graves which would grant safety and rest during times of feeding and replenishing his strength.

Harker's fiancée, [[Mina Murray]], is staying with her friend [[Lucy Westenra]], who is holidaying in [[Whitby]]. Lucy receives three marriage proposals from [[John Seward|Dr. John Seward]], [[Quincey Morris]], and [[Arthur Holmwood]] (the son of Lord Godalming who later succeeds to the title himself&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Stoker|first1=Bram|title=Dracula|location=Chapter 6, Mina Murray's Journal, 26 July|page=105|url=http://www.planetebook.com/ebooks/Dracula.pdf|quote=Mr. Holmwood, he is the Hon. Arthur Holmwood, only son of Lord Godalming}}&lt;/ref&gt;). Lucy accepts Holmwood's proposal while turning down Seward and Morris, but all remain friends. Dracula communicates with Seward's patient, [[Renfield]], an insane man who wishes to consume insects, spiders, birds, and rats to absorb their life force. Renfield is able to detect Dracula's presence and supplies clues accordingly.

Soon Dracula is indirectly shown to be stalking Lucy. As time passes she begins to suffer from episodes of sleepwalking and dementia, as witnessed by Mina. When Lucy begins to waste away suspiciously, Seward invites his old teacher, [[Abraham Van Helsing]], who immediately determines the true cause of Lucy's condition. He refuses to disclose it but diagnoses her with acute blood-loss. Van Helsing prescribes numerous [[blood transfusion]]s to which he, Seward, Quincey, and Arthur all contribute over time. Van Helsing also prescribes garlic flowers to be placed throughout her room and weaves a necklace of withered [[Allium|garlic blossoms]] for her to wear. However she continues to waste away – appearing to lose blood every night. 

Van Helsing attempts to protect Lucy with [[Garlic#Spiritual and religious uses|garlic]] but fate thwarts him each night, whether Lucy's mother removes the garlic from her room, or Lucy herself does so in her restless sleep. While both doctors are absent, Lucy and her mother are attacked by a [[wolf]] and Mrs Westenra, who has a heart condition, dies of fright. The doctors find two small puncture marks about Lucy's neck, which Dr Seward is at a loss to understand. After Lucy also dies, Van Helsing places a golden crucifix over her mouth, ostensibly to delay or prevent Lucy's vampiric conversion.  Fate conspires against him again when Van Helsing finds the crucifix in the possession of one of the servants who stole it off Lucy's corpse.

Following Lucy's death and burial, the newspapers report children being stalked in the night by a &quot;bloofer lady&quot; (i.e., &quot;beautiful lady&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;[[Leonard Wolf]] (2004). ''The Essential Dracula'', Chapter 13, Note 31. &quot;Bloofer lady&quot; is explained as baby-talk for &quot;beautiful lady&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; Van Helsing, knowing Lucy has become a vampire, confides in Arthur, Seward, and Morris. The suitors and Van Helsing track her down and, after a confrontation with her, stake her heart, [[Decapitation|behead]] her, and fill her mouth with garlic. Around the same time, Jonathan Harker arrives from [[Budapest]], where Mina marries him after his escape, and he and Mina join the campaign against Dracula.

The vampire hunters stay at Dr. Seward's residence, holding nightly meetings and providing reports based on each of their various tasks. Mina discovers that each of their journals and letters collectively contain clues through which they can track Dracula down. She tasks herself with collecting them, researching newspaper clippings, fitting the most relevant entries into chronological order and typing out copies to distribute to each of the party which they are to study. Jonathan Harker tracks down the shipments of boxed graves and the estates which Dracula has purchased in order to store them. 

Van Helsing conducts research along with Dr. Seward to analyze the behaviour of their patient Renfield who they learn is directly influenced by Dracula. They also research historical events, folklore, and superstitions from various cultures to understand Dracula's powers and weaknesses. Van Helsing also establishes a criminal profile on Dracula in order to better understand his actions and predict his movements. Arthur Holmwood's fortune assists in funding the entire operation. 

As they discover the various properties Dracula had purchased, the male protagonists team up to raid each property and are several times confronted by Dracula. Locating each of the boxed graves scattered throughout London, they pry them open to place and seal wafers of [[sacramental bread]] within. This act renders the boxes of earth completely useless to Dracula as he is unable to open, enter or further transport them.

After Dracula learns of the group's plot against him, he attacks Mina on three occasions, and feeds Mina his own blood to control her. This curses Mina with vampirism and changes her but does not completely turn her into a vampire. Van Helsing attempts to bless Mina through prayer and by placing a wafer of sacrament against her forehead, but it burns her upon contact leaving a wretched scar. Under this curse, Mina oscillates from consciousness to a semi-trance during which she perceives Dracula's surroundings and actions. Van Helsing is able to use hypnotism twice a day, at dawn and at sunset, to put her into this trance to further track Dracula's movements. Mina, afraid of Dracula's link with her, urges the team not to tell her their plans out of fear that Dracula will be listening. After the protagonists discover and sterilize 49 boxes found throughout his lairs in London, they learn that Dracula has fled with the missing 50th box back to his castle in Transylvania. They pursue him under the guidance of Mina. 

They split up into teams once they reach Europe; Van Helsing and Mina go to Dracula's castle, while the others attempt to ambush the boat Dracula is using to reach his home. Van Helsing raids the castle and destroys the vampire sisters. Upon discovering Dracula being transported by [[Romani people|Gypsies]], the three teams converge and attack the caravan carrying Dracula in the 50th box of earth. After dispatching many Gypsies who were sworn to protect the Count, Harker shears Dracula through the throat with a [[Kukri|kukri knife]], while the mortally wounded Quincey stabs the Count in the heart with a [[Bowie knife]]. Dracula crumbles to dust, and Mina is freed from her curse of vampirism, as the scar on her forehead disappears. Soon after, Quincey dies from his wounds.

The book closes with a note left by Jonathan Harker seven years after the events of the novel, detailing his married life with Mina and the birth of their son, whom they name after all four members of the party, but address as Quincey. Young Quincey is depicted sitting on the knee of Van Helsing as they recount their adventure. Seward and Arthur have each gotten married.

=== Deleted ending ===
A small section was removed from a draft of the final chapter, in which Dracula's castle falls apart as he dies, hiding the fact that vampires were ever there.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |website=listverse.com| url=http://listverse.com/2013/01/14/deleted-book-chapters/|date=14 January 2013| title=10 Deleted Chapters that Transformed Famous Books|last=Symon|first= Evan V.}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{quotation|    As we looked there came a terrible convulsion of the earth so that we seemed to rock to and fro and fell to our knees. At the same moment with a roar which seemed to shake the very heavens the whole castle and the rock and even the hill on which it stood seemed to rise into the air and scatter in fragments while a mighty cloud of black and yellow smoke volume on volume in rolling grandeur was shot upwards with inconceivable rapidity.

    Then there was a stillness in nature as the echoes of that thunderous report seemed to come as with the hollow boom of a thunder-clap – the long reverberating roll which seems as though the floors of heaven shook. Then down in a mighty ruin falling whence they rose came the fragments that had been tossed skywards in the cataclysm.

    From where we stood it seemed as though the one fierce volcano burst had satisfied the need of nature and that the castle and the structure of the hill had sunk again into the void. We were so appalled with the suddenness and the grandeur that we forgot to think of ourselves. |Deleted excerpt from the original Dracula manuscript&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Miller|first1=Elizabeth|title=Original (deleted) ending of Bram Stoker's Dracula|url=http://dracula.cc/literature/bram_stoker_original_ending/|website=dracula.cc|accessdate=November 18, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==Characters==
* [[Count Dracula]]: A Transylvanian noble who has purchased a house in London.
* [[Jonathan Harker]]: A solicitor sent to do business with Count Dracula; Mina's fiancé and prisoner in Dracula's castle. 
* [[Mina Harker|Wilhelmina &quot;Mina&quot; Harker]] (née Murray): A schoolteacher and Jonathan Harker's fiancée (later his wife). 
* [[Arthur Holmwood]]: Lucy's suitor and later fiancé. He inherits the title of Lord Godalming upon his father's death.
* [[Quincey Morris]]: An American cowboy and explorer; and one of Lucy's suitors.
* [[Renfield]]: A patient at Seward's insane asylum who has come under the influence of Dracula.
* [[John Seward]]: A doctor; one of Lucy's suitors and a former student of Van Helsing.
* [[Abraham Van Helsing]]: A Dutch doctor, lawyer and professor; John Seward's teacher. &lt;!--DO NOT ADD VAMPIRE HUNTER. Although he is depicted as hunting vampires in the novel, he has only hunted the same vampires as the other characters. He is not known to have hunted vampires beyond this capacity--&gt;
* [[Lucy Westenra]]: A 19-year-old aristocrat; Mina's best friend; Arthur's fiancée and Dracula's first victim.
* Three siren-like vampire women who serve Dracula. In some of the later adaptations to stage and screen, they are referred to as the [[Brides of Dracula]].

==Background==
Between 1879 and 1898, Stoker was a business manager for the [[Lyceum Theatre, London|Lyceum Theatre]] in London, where he supplemented his income by writing many sensational novels, his most successful being the vampire tale ''Dracula'' published on 26 May 1897.&lt;ref name=&quot;Belford2002&quot;/&gt;{{rp|269}} Parts of it are set around the town of [[Whitby]], where he spent summer holidays.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bramstokerestate.com/Bram-Stoker-By-and-About-Bram-Stoker-Himself-Abraham-Stoker-Jr-Dracula-author-Dublin-London.html|title=Abraham Stoker, Jr. A Collection By and About Bram Stoker, Himself|publisher= Bram Stoker LLC for Bram Stoker Estate|accessdate=13 September 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Throughout the 1880s and 1890s, authors such as [[Henry Rider Haggard|H. Rider Haggard]], [[Rudyard Kipling]], [[Robert Louis Stevenson]], [[Arthur Conan Doyle]], and [[H. G. Wells]] wrote many tales in which fantastic creatures threatened the British Empire. [[Invasion literature]] was at a peak, and Stoker's formula was very familiar by 1897 to readers of fantastic adventure stories, of an invasion of England by continental European influences. Victorian readers enjoyed ''Dracula'' as a good adventure story like many others, but it did not reach its legendary status until later in the 20th century when film versions began to appear.&lt;ref&gt;[[Nina Auerbach]] and [[David Skal]], editors. (1997). ''Dracula''. Norton Critical Edition. {{ISBN|0-393-97012-4}}. Preface, first paragraph.&lt;/ref&gt;
 
[[File:Henry Irving portrait.jpg|thumb|right|upright|Shakespearean actor and friend of Stoker's [[Henry Irving|Sir Henry Irving]] was a possible real-life inspiration for the character of Dracula. The role was tailor-made to his dramatic presence, gentlemanly mannerisms, and affinity for playing villain roles. Irving, however, never agreed to play the part on stage.]]

Before writing ''Dracula'', Stoker spent seven years researching European folklore and stories of vampires, being most influenced by [[Emily Gerard]]'s 1885 essay &quot;Transylvania Superstitions&quot; which includes content about a vampire myth.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bl.uk/collection-items/the-land-beyond-the-forest-source-material-for-dracula|title=The Land beyond the forest: source material for Dracula|website=The British Library|accessdate=8 October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Davison|1997|p=142}} Some historians are convinced that a historic figure, Vlad III Dracula, often called [[Vlad the Impaler]], was the model for Stoker's Count although there is no supporting evidence.&lt;ref name=&quot;books.google.ca&quot;&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=cm36CwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA67&amp;dq=Dracula+bram+stoker+vlad+the+impaler#v=onepage&amp;q=Dracula+bram+stoker+vlad+the+impaler|title=Dracula by Bram Stoker The Mystery of The Early Editions|first=Simone|last=Berni|date=2016|publisher=Lulu.com|accessdate=8 October 2017|via=Google Books|isbn=978-1326621797}}{{self-published source|date=February 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{self-published inline|date=February 2020}} Stoker borrowed only &quot;scraps of miscellaneous information&quot;, according to one expert, about this bloodthirsty tyrant of [[Wallachia]] and there are no comments about him in Stoker's working notes.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=VomtVOkkPDwC&amp;pg=PA182&amp;dq=Dracula+bram+stoker+vlad+the+impaler#v=onepage&amp;q=Dracula+bram+stoker+vlad+the+impaler|title=Bram Stoker and Russophobia: Evidence of the British Fear of Russia in Dracula and The Lady of the Shroud|first=Jimmie E. Cain|last=Jr|date=2006|publisher=McFarland|accessdate=8 October 2017|via=Google Books|isbn=978-0786424078}}&lt;/ref&gt; Dracula scholar [[Elizabeth Miller (academic)|Elizabeth Miller]] has remarked that aside from the name and some mention of Romanian history, the background of Stoker's Count bears no resemblance to that of Vlad III Dracula.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.pbs.org/frontlineworld/stories/romania/miller.html|title=Romania – My Old Haunts. Dracula: The Metamorphosis of a Fiend. Interview with the Vampire Queen|author= Elizabeth Miller |website=Frontine/World Pbs.org|accessdate=8 October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; From 1890 to 1897 Stoker was a member of the [[London Library]], where markings in Sabine Baring-Gould's “''Book of Were-Wolves''”,  Thomas Browne's “''[[Pseudodoxia Epidemica|Pseudodoxica Epidemica]]''”, AF Crosse's “''Round About the Carpathians''” and Charles Boner's “''Transylvania''” are attributed to Stoker's research for ''Dracula''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.londonlibrary.co.uk/dracula|title=Dracula|website=www.londonlibrary.co.uk|accessdate=31 March 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Later he also claimed that he had a nightmare, caused by eating too much crab meat, about a &quot;vampire king&quot; rising from his grave.{{sfn|Davison|1997|p=24}}

Although it is a widely known vampire novel, ''Dracula'' was not the first. [[Johann Wolfgang von Goethe]] published ''The Bride of Corinth'' in 1797. (&quot;From my grave to wander I am forc’d  Still to seek The God’s long-sever’d link,  Still to love the bridegroom I have lost,  And the life-blood of his heart to drink;)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.poets.org/poetsorg/poem/bride-corinth-my-grave-wander|title=The Bride of Corinth [From my grave to wander]|last=aapone|date=20 October 2009|website=The Bride of Corinth [From my grave to wander]|accessdate=8 October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Later  [[Sheridan Le Fanu]]'s 1871 ''[[Carmilla]]'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/10007|title=Carmilla|first=Joseph Sheridan Le|last=Fanu|date=2003|website=Gutenberg.org|accessdate=8 October 2017|via=Project Gutenberg}}&lt;/ref&gt; about a [[lesbian vampire]] could have inspired Bram Stoker's Dracula, or ''[[Varney the Vampire]]'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=wwVyHwAACAAJ&amp;dq=Varney+the+Vampire+Rymer|title=Varney the Vampire; Or, the Feast of Blood|first=James Malcolm|last=Rymer|date=2007|publisher=Zittaw Press|accessdate=8 October 2017|via=Google Books|isbn=978-0979587153}}&lt;/ref&gt; a lengthy [[penny dreadful]] serial from the mid-Victorian period by [[James Malcolm Rymer]]. [[John Polidori]] created the image of a vampire portrayed as an aristocratic man, like the character of Dracula, in his tale &quot;[[The Vampyre]]&quot; (1819). (He wrote ''Vampyre'' during a summer which he spent with ''[[Frankenstein]]'' creator [[Mary Shelley]], her husband poet [[Percy Bysshe Shelley]], and [[Lord Byron]] in 1816.)

The Lyceum Theatre where Stoker worked between 1878 and 1898 was headed by actor-manager [[Henry Irving]], who was Stoker's real-life inspiration for Dracula's mannerisms and who Stoker hoped would play Dracula in a stage version.&lt;ref name=&quot;warren&quot;&gt;Lewis S Warren, [http://www.historycooperative.org/journals/ahr/107.4/ah0402001124.html ''Buffalo Bill Meets Dracula: William F. Cody, Bram Stoker, and the Frontiers of Racial Decay''] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130506083906/http://www.historycooperative.org/journals/ahr/107.4/ah0402001124.html |date=6 May 2013 }}, [[American Historical Review]], Vol. 107, No. 4, October 2002, paragraph 18&lt;/ref&gt; Irving never did agree to do a stage version, but Dracula's dramatic sweeping gestures and gentlemanly mannerisms drew their living embodiment from Irving.&lt;ref name=&quot;warren&quot;/&gt;

''The Dead Un-Dead'' was one of Stoker's original titles for ''Dracula'', and the manuscript was entitled simply ''The Un-Dead'' up until a few weeks before publication. Stoker's notes for ''Dracula'' show that the name of the count was originally &quot;Count Wampyr&quot;, but Stoker became intrigued by the name &quot;Dracula&quot; while doing research, after reading [[William Wilkinson (diplomat)|William Wilkinson]]'s book ''An Account of the Principalities of Wallachia and Moldavia with Political Observations Relative to Them'' (London 1820),&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=RogMAQAAMAAJ ''An account of the principalities of Wallachia and Moldavia''] – William Wilkinson, Longman, 1820 (Google Free eBook)&lt;/ref&gt; which he found in the Whitby Library and consulted a number of times during visits to Whitby in the 1890s.&lt;ref&gt;[[Radu R. Florescu]] and [[Raymond T. McNally]] ''Dracula, Prince of Many Faces''. Little Brown. 1989. {{ISBN|0316286567}}. pp. 229–31.&lt;/ref&gt; The name Dracula was the [[Patronymic|patronym]] (''Drăculea'') of the descendants of [[Vlad II Dracul|Vlad II]] of [[Wallachia]], who took the name &quot;Dracul&quot; after being invested in the [[Order of the Dragon]] in 1431. In the Old Romanian language, the word ''dracul'' (Romanian ''drac'' &quot;dragon&quot; + ''-ul'' &quot;the&quot;) meant &quot;the dragon&quot; and Dracula meant &quot;son of the dragon&quot;. In the present day however, dracul means  &quot;the devil&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[Raymond T. McNally]] and [[Radu R. Florescu]] ''In Search of Dracula, The History of Dracula and Vampires (Completely Revised)''. Houghton Mifflin. 1994. {{ISBN|0-395-65783-0}}. pp. 8–9.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=BRl1sWYShpcC&amp;pg=PA220&amp;lpg=PA220&amp;dq=dracul+Old+romanian+meant+the+dragon#v=onepage&amp;q=dracul+Old+romanian+meant+the+dragon|title=Events That Formed the Modern World|first1=Frank W.|last1=Thackeray|first2=John E.|last2=Findling|date=2012|publisher=ABC-CLIO|accessdate=8 October 2017|via=Google Books|isbn=978-1598849011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Publication==
''Dracula'' was published in London in May 1897 by Archibald Constable and Company. Costing six shillings, the novel was bound in yellow cloth and titled in red letters.{{sfn|Davison|1997|p=19}} It was copyrighted in the United States in 1899 with the publication by Doubleday &amp; McClure of New York.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Wood|first1=Margaret|title=Copyright and Dracula|url=http://blogs.loc.gov/law/2013/02/copyright-and-dracula/|website=Library of Congress|publisher=Library of Congress|accessdate=29 November 2015|date=6 February 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; But when Universal Studios purchased the rights, it came to light that Bram Stoker had not complied with a portion of US copyright law, placing the novel into the public domain.&lt;ref name=&quot;StokerHolt2009&quot;&gt;{{cite book|first1=Dacre |last1=Stoker|first2=Ian |last2=Holt|title=Dracula The Un-Dead|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=dMaiiODpsyQC&amp;pg=PT312|year=2009|publisher=Penguin Publishing Group|isbn=978-0-525-95129-2|pages=312–13}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the United Kingdom and other countries following the [[Berne Convention for the Protection of Literary and Artistic Works|Berne Convention]] on copyrights, the novel was under copyright until April 1962, fifty years after Stoker's death.&lt;ref&gt;''Lugosi v. Universal Pictures'', 70 Cal.App.3d 552 (1977), note 4.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Reaction and scholarly criticism==
===Reaction===
[[File:Dracamer99.jpg|thumb|upright|1899 first American edition, Doubleday &amp; McClure, New York]]
''Dracula'' was not an immediate [[bestseller]] when it was first published, although reviewers were unstinting in their praise. The contemporary ''[[Daily Mail]]'' ranked Stoker's powers above those of [[Mary Shelley]] and [[Edgar Allan Poe]], as well as [[Emily Brontë]]'s ''[[Wuthering Heights]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Cited in Paul Murray's ''From the Shadow of Dracula: A Life of Bram Stoker''. 2004. pp. 363–64.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to literary historians [[Nina Auerbach]] and [[David J. Skal]] in the Norton Critical Edition, the novel has become more significant for modern readers than it was for Victorian readers, most of whom enjoyed it just as a good adventure story. It reached its broad and iconic status only later in the 20th century when the movie versions appeared.&lt;ref&gt;Nina Auerbach and David Skal, editors. ''Dracula''. Norton Critical Edition. 1997. {{ISBN|0-393-97012-4}}. Preface, first paragraph.&lt;/ref&gt; A. Asbjørn Jøn has also noted that ''Dracula'' has had a significant impact on the image of the vampire in popular culture, folklore, and legend.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url = https://www.researchgate.net/publication/283318599|title = Vampire Evolution|last = Jøn|first = A. Asbjørn|date = 2003|journal = METAphor|doi = |pmid = |accessdate = 26 November 2015|pages = 19–23|issue = 3}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url = https://www.researchgate.net/publication/280805194|title = From Nosteratu to Von Carstein: shifts in the portrayal of vampires|last = Jøn|first = A. Asbjørn|date = 2001|journal = Australian Folklore: A Yearly Journal of Folklore Studies|doi = |pmid = |accessdate = 26 November 2015|issue = 16|publisher = University of New England|pages = 97–106}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It did not make much money for Stoker. In the last year of his life, he was so poor that he had to petition for a compassionate grant from the [[Royal Literary Fund]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.todayinliterature.com/stories.asp?Event_Date=4/20/1912 |title=Bram Stoker – Stoker, Irving &amp; Count Vlad |publisher=Today in Literature |date=20 April 1912 |accessdate=17 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; and his widow was forced to sell his notes and outlines of the novel at a [[Sotheby's]] auction in 1913, where they were purchased for a little over £2.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://irishphiladelphia.com/2011/06/bram-stokers-dracula-by-gothic-candlelight/ |title=Bram Stoker's &quot;Dracula&quot; by Gothic Candlelight |publisher=Irishphiladelphia.com |date=10 June 2011 |accessdate=17 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; But then F. W. Murnau's unauthorized adaptation of the story was released in theatres in 1922 in the form of ''[[Nosferatu]]''. Stoker's widow took affront and, during the legal battle that followed, the novel's popularity started to grow.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://collegefilmandmediastudies.com/2014/04/23/sympathy-for-the-vampire-on-friedrich-wilhelm-murnaus-nosferatu/|title=Sympathy for the Vampire: On &quot;Nosferatu&quot;|date=23 April 2014|work=College Film &amp; Media Studies|accessdate=23 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''Nosferatu'' was followed by a highly successful stage adaptation, touring the UK for three years before arriving in the US where Stoker's creation caught Hollywood's attention and, after the American 1931 movie version was released, the book has never been out of print.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Stoker |first=Bram |url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/cult/vampires/classicstory/dracula_p1.shtml |title=Cult Vampires – Extract from Dracula by Bram Stoker |publisher=BBC |date= |accessdate=17 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, some Victorian fans were ahead of the time, describing it as &quot;the sensation of the season&quot; and &quot;the most blood-curdling novel of the paralysed century&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Richard Dalby &quot;Bram Stoker&quot;, in Jack Sullivan (ed) ''The Penguin Encyclopedia of Horror and the Supernatural'', 1986, Viking, pp. 404–06 [405].&lt;/ref&gt; [[Sherlock Holmes]] author [[Sir Arthur Conan Doyle]] wrote to Stoker in a letter, &quot;I write to tell you how very much I have enjoyed reading ''Dracula''. I think it is the very best story of diablerie which I have read for many years.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Klinger, p. xxxii&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Daily Mail'' review of 1 June 1897 proclaimed it a classic of [[Gothic horror]], &quot;In seeking a parallel to this weird, powerful, and horrorful story our mind reverts to such tales as ''[[The Mysteries of Udolpho]]'', ''[[Frankenstein]]'', ''[[The Fall of the House of Usher]]'' ... but Dracula is even more appalling in its gloomy fascination than any one of these.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Cited in Nina Auerbach and David Skal, editors, ''Dracula'', Norton Critical Edition, 1997, pp. 363–64.&lt;/ref&gt;

Similarly good reviews appeared when the book was published in the U.S. in 1899. The first American edition was published by [[Doubleday (publisher)|Doubleday &amp; McClure]] in New York.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://bramstoker.org/novels/05dracula.html|title=Bram Stoker-Dracula|accessdate=13 September 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In his long essay, &quot;[[Supernatural Horror in Literature]]&quot;, American horror author and historian of the genre, [[H. P. Lovecraft]], acclaimed the novel saying, &quot;But best of all is the famous ''Dracula'', which has become almost the standard modern exploitation of the frightful vampire myth … How an Englishman fares within Dracula’s stronghold of terrors, and how the dead fiend’s plot for domination is at last defeated, are elements which unite to form a tale now justly assigned a permanent place in English letters.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hplovecraft.com/writings/texts/essays/shil.aspx|title=&quot;Supernatural Horror in Literature&quot; by H. P. Lovecraft|website=www.hplovecraft.com|accessdate=16 September 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Scholarly criticism===
In the last several decades, literary and cultural scholars have offered diverse analyses of Stoker's novel and the character of Count Dracula.  C.F. Bentley reads Dracula as an embodiment of the [[Freudian]] [[Id (psychology)|id]].&lt;ref&gt;C.F. Bentley's. ''The Monster in the Bedroom: Sexual Symbolism in Bram Stoker's Dracula''&lt;/ref&gt; [[Carol Senf|Carol A. Senf]] reads the novel as a response to the [[New Woman]] archetype,&lt;ref&gt;Senf, Carol A. ''The Vampire in Nineteenth-Century English Literature''. Bowling Green: Popular Press,&lt;/ref&gt; while Christopher Craft sees Dracula as embodying latent homosexuality and sees the text as an example of a 'characteristic, if hyperbolic instance of Victorian anxiety over the potential fluidity of gender roles'.&lt;ref&gt;Christopher Craft (1984). ''&quot;Kiss Me with Those Red Lips&quot;: Gender and Inversion in Bram Stoker's Dracula''&lt;/ref&gt; Stephen D. Arata interprets the events of the novel as anxiety over [[colonialism]] and [[racial mixing]],&lt;ref&gt;Arata, Stephen D. ''The Occidental Tourist:  Dracula and the Anxiety of Reverse Colonization'', Victorian Studies 33.4 (1990).&lt;/ref&gt; and Talia Schaffer construes the novel as an indictment of [[Oscar Wilde]].&lt;ref&gt;Schaffer, Talia (1994). ''A Wilde Desire Took Me: the Homoerotic History of Dracula'', ELH 61 (1994), 381–425&lt;/ref&gt; [[Franco Moretti]] reads Dracula as a figure of [[monopoly]] [[capitalism]],&lt;ref&gt;Franco Moretti, &quot;The Dialectic of Fear,&quot; New Left Review 136 (1982): 67–85&lt;/ref&gt; though [[Hollis Robbins]] suggests that Dracula's inability to participate in social conventions and to forge business partnerships undermines his power.&lt;ref name=&quot;Killing Time 2014&quot;&gt;&quot;Killing Time: Dracula and Social Discoordination&quot; in ''Economics of the Undead'' Eds. Glen Whitman and James Dow (Rowman &amp; Littlefield, 2014), chapter 23&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Bram Stoker's Notes for Dracula: A Facsimile Edition'' by [[Robert Eighteen-Bisang]] &amp; [[Elizabeth Miller (academic)|Elizabeth Miller]] (McFarland, 2008)&lt;/ref&gt; Richard Noll reads ''Dracula'' within the context of 19th century [[Psychiatry|alienism]] ([[psychiatry]]) and [[History of psychiatric institutions|asylum]] medicine.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Noll |first=Richard |url=https://www.academia.edu/6793535 |title=Vampires Werewolves and Demons: Twentieth Century Case Reports in the Psychiatric Literature (1991) &amp;#124; Richard Noll |volume=30 |publisher=Academia.edu |date= |accessdate=17 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; D. Bruno Starrs understands the novel to be a pro-[[Catholic]] pamphlet promoting [[proselytization]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://blooferland.com/drc/index.php?title=Journal_of_Dracula_Studies#Number_6_.282004.29]  {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140216132353/http://www.blooferland.com/drc/index.php?title=Journal_of_Dracula_Studies|date=16 February 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Dracula is one of Five Books' most recommended books,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=https://fivebooks.com/book/dracula-by-bram-stoker/ |title= Dracula by Bram Stoker| website=Five Books| accessdate= 17 January 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt; with literary scholars, science writers and novelists citing it as an influential text for topics such as sex in Victorian Literature,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://fivebooks.com/best-books/sex-in-victorian-literature/|title=The Best Books on Sex in Victorian Literature {{!}} Claire Jarvis on Five Books|last=Books|first=Five|website=Five Books|accessdate=31 March 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; best horror books&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://fivebooks.com/best-books/darryl-jones-horror-stories/|title=The Best Books on Horror Stories {{!}} Five Books Expert Recommendations|last=Books|first=Five|website=Five Books|accessdate=31 March 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; and criminology.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://fivebooks.com/best-books/douglas-starr-on-the-pioneers-of-criminology/|title=The Best Books on The Pioneers of Criminology {{!}} Five Books Expert Recommendations|last=Books|first=Five|website=Five Books|accessdate=31 March 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Historical and geographical references==
''Dracula'' is a work of fiction, but it does contain some historical references; although it is a matter of conjecture and debate as to how much historical connection was deliberate on Stoker's part.

Attention was drawn to the supposed connections between the historical [[Transylvania]]n-born [[Vlad the Impaler|Vlad III Dracula]] (also known as Vlad Tepes) of [[Wallachia]] and Bram Stoker's fictional Dracula, following the publication of ''In Search of Dracula'' by [[Radu Florescu]] and [[Raymond McNally]] in 1972.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.independent.co.uk/news/people/radu-florescu-dead-legacy-of-the-romanian-dracula-professor-remembered-9401744.html|title=Radu Florescu dead: Legacy of the Romanian 'Dracula professor'|date=20 May 2014|website=Independent.co.uk|accessdate=8 October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During his main reign (1456–1462), &quot;Vlad the Impaler&quot; is said to have killed from 40,000 to 100,000 European civilians (political rivals, criminals, and anyone that he considered &quot;useless to humanity&quot;), mainly by impaling. The sources depicting these events are records by [[Transylvanian Saxons|Saxon]] settlers in neighbouring Transylvania who had frequent clashes with Vlad III. Vlad III is revered as a folk hero by [[Romanians]] for driving off the invading [[Ottoman Turks]], of whom his [[impalement|impaled]] victims are said to have included as many as 100,000.&lt;ref name=Andreescu&gt;{{cite book|title = Vlad the Impaler (Dracula)|last = Andreescu |first = Stefan|year = 1999|publisher = The Romanian Cultural Foundation Publishing House|isbn=978-9735771973}}&lt;/ref&gt; There is no solid evidence that the Count in the novel was modelled on Vlad the Impaler of Wallachia.&lt;ref name=&quot;books.google.ca&quot;/&gt; At most, Stoker borrowed only the name Dracula and &quot;scraps of miscellaneous information&quot; about Romanian history, according to one expert, [[Elizabeth Miller (academic)|Elizabeth Miller]]; as well, and there are no comments about him in the author's working notes.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=v-3OCwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT73&amp;lpg=PT73&amp;dq=Elizabeth+Miller+stoker's+working+notes+No+mention+of+Vlad#v=onepage&amp;q=Elizabeth+Miller+stoker's+working+notes+No+mention+of+Vlad|title=The Dracula Dilemma: Tourism, Identity and the State in Romania|first=Duncan|last=Light|date=2016|publisher=Routledge|accessdate=8 October 2017|via=Google Books|isbn=978-1317035312}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Vlad Tepes 002.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Vlad the Impaler]].]]

Historically, the name &quot;Dracula&quot; is derived from a [[Chivalric order]] called the [[Order of the Dragon]], founded by [[Sigismund, Holy Roman Emperor|Sigismund of Luxembourg]] (then king of [[Hungary]]) to uphold [[Christianity]] and defend the Holy Roman Empire against the [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman Turks]]. [[Vlad II Dracul]], father of Vlad III, was admitted to the order around 1431, after which Vlad II wore the emblem of the order and later, as ruler of Wallachia, his [[coin]]age bore the dragon symbol, from which the name &quot;Dracula&quot; is derived since &quot;dracul&quot; in Romanian means &quot;the dragon&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=WYZSAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT28&amp;dq=Dracula+dragon+coinage#v=onepage&amp;q=Dracula+dragon+coinage|title=Dracula|first=Brian|last=Ripley|date=2013|publisher=Strategic Book Publishing|accessdate=8 October 2017|via=Google Books|isbn=978-1628570298}}&lt;/ref&gt; People of Wallachia only knew ''voievod'' (prince) Vlad III as Vlad Țepeș (the Impaler). The name &quot;Dracula&quot; became popular in Romania after publication of Stoker's book. Contrary to popular belief, the name Dracula does not translate to &quot;son of the devil&quot; in [[Romanian language|Romanian]], which would be &quot;fiul diavolului&quot;.

Stoker came across the name Dracula in his reading on [[History of Romania|Romanian history]], and chose this to replace the name (''Count Wampyr'') originally intended for his villain.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Onion|first1=Rebecca|title=Bram Stoker's Ever-Evolving List of Characters for Dracula|url=http://www.slate.com/blogs/the_vault/2013/04/23/bram_stoker_s_dracula_how_dracula_van_helsing_and_other_characters_came.html|website=Slate|accessdate=10 January 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some Dracula scholars led by [[Elizabeth Miller (academic)|Elizabeth Miller]] argue that Stoker knew little of the historic Vlad III except for the name &quot;Dracula&quot; in addition to a few bits of Romanian history.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; Stoker mentions that his Dracula fought against the Turks and was later betrayed by his brother, historical facts in the novel which point to Vlad III:

{{quote|Who was it but one of my own race who as Voivode crossed the Danube and beat the Turk on his own ground? This was a Dracula indeed! Woe was it that his own unworthy brother, when he had fallen, sold his people to the Turk and brought the shame of slavery on them! Was it not this Dracula, indeed, who inspired that other of his race who in a later age again and again brought his forces over the great river into Turkey-land; who, when he was beaten back, came again, and again, though he had to come alone from the bloody field where his troops were being slaughtered, since he knew that he alone could ultimately triumph! (Chapter 3, pp. 19)}}

The Count's identity is later speculated on by Professor Van Helsing:

{{quote|He must, indeed, have been that Voivode Dracula who won his name against the Turk, over the great river on the very frontier of Turkey-land. (Chapter 18, p. 145)}}

Many of Stoker's biographers and literary critics have found strong similarities to the earlier Irish writer [[Sheridan Le Fanu]]'s classic of the vampire genre ''[[Carmilla]]''. In writing ''Dracula'', Stoker may also have drawn on stories about the [[Aos Sí|sídhe]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.ca/books?id=mo_FAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA12|first1=Marc|last1=Blake|first2=Sara|last2=Bailey |publisher=Bloomsbury|isbn=978-1441196187|title=Writing the Horror Movie|page=12|year=2013|accessdate=11 July 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; some of which feature blood-drinking women. The Irish legend of [[Abhartach]] has also been suggested as a source.&lt;ref name=curran&gt;{{cite journal|last = Curran |first = Bob |title = Was Dracula an Irishman? | journal = History Ireland |volume = 8 |issue = 2 |date = Summer 2000 }}&lt;/ref&gt; It is also thought probable that his mothers stories of events during the severe [[1832 Sligo cholera outbreak|cholera outbreak]] in [[Sligo]] in 1832 were influential. Particularly themes of being buried while alive.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=https://www.independent.ie/entertainment/books/the-sligo-epidemic-that-stoked-brams-interest-in-all-things-26845703.html | title=The Sligo epidemic that stoked Bram's interest in all things}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1983, McNally additionally suggested that Stoker was influenced by the history of [[Kingdom of Hungary|Hungarian]] Countess [[Elizabeth Bathory]], who allegedly tortured and killed between 36 and 700 young women.&lt;ref&gt;McNally, Raymund. ''Dracula was a Woman''. New York: McGraw-Hill, 1983{{page needed|date=April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was later a commonly believed rumor that she committed these crimes to bathe in their blood, believing that this preserved her youth.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first=Dennis | last=Bathory-Kitsz |url=http://bathory.org/miller02.html |title=Báthory Erzsébet – Elizabeth Bathory: Bram Stoker, Elizabeth Bathory, and Dracula (Elizabeth Miller) |publisher=Bathory.org |date= |accessdate=17 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Čachtice Castle|Báthory's castle]] was also located in the [[Carpathian Mountains]], just as Dracula's, albeit in a [[Upper Hungary|different region]].

In her book ''The Essential Dracula'', Clare Haword-Maden suggested that the castle of Count Dracula was inspired by [[New Slains Castle|Slains Castle]], at which Bram Stoker was a guest of the 19th [[Earl of Erroll]].&lt;ref&gt;Haword-Maden, Clare. ''The Essential Dracula''. London: Bison Books, 1992 {{page needed|date=April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to Miller, he first visited Cruden Bay in 1893, three years after work had begun on ''Dracula''. Haining and Tremaine maintain that, during this visit, Stoker was especially impressed by Slains Castle's interior and the surrounding landscape. Miller and Leatherdale question the stringency of this connection.&lt;ref&gt;Haining, Peter and Tremayne, Peter. The Un-Dead: The Legend of Bram Stoker and Dracila. London: Constable 1997, quoted by Miller, Elizabeth. Dracula – Sense &amp; Nonsense, 2nd ed. Westcliff-on-Sea, UK: Desert Island Books, 2006, p. 19. See also Leatherdale, Clive. Dracula Unearthed. Westcliff-on-Sea, UK: Desert Island Books, 1998, p. 13&lt;/ref&gt;

Possibly, Stoker was not inspired by a real edifice at all, but by [[Jules Verne]]'s novel ''[[The Carpathian Castle]]'' (1892) or [[Anne Radcliffe]]'s ''[[The Mysteries of Udolpho]]'' (1794).&lt;ref&gt;Elizabeth Miller, ''Dracula: Sense &amp; Nonsense''. 2nd ed. Westcliff-on-Sea, UK: Desert Island Books, 2006, p. 141&lt;/ref&gt; A third possibility is that he copied information about [[Kemény Castle (Brâncovenești)|Kemény Castle]] at [[Brâncovenești, Mureș|Vécs]] from one of his sources on Transylvania, the book by Major E.C. Johnson.&lt;ref&gt;Major E.C. Johnson, ''On the Track of the Crescent: Erratic Notes from the Piraeus to Pesth.'' London: Hurst and Blackett, 1885. pp. 256–257, quoted by Marius Crișan, ''The Models for Castle Dracula in Stoker's Sources on Transylvania'', Journal of Dracula Studies Nr 10 (2008); also referred to by Miller, 2006, p. 141&lt;/ref&gt; A further option is that Stoker saw an illustration of Castle Bran (Törzburg) in the book on Transylvania by [[Charles Boner]], or read about it in the books by [[Elizabeth Sarah Mazuchelli|Mazuchelli]] or Crosse.&lt;ref&gt;[[Charles Boner]], ''Transylvania: Its Products and Its People.'' London: Longmans, 1865. Referred to by Marius Crișan, ''The Models for Castle Dracula in Stoker's Sources on Transylvania'', Journal of Dracula Studies Nr 10 (2008). As indicated by Crişan, Crosse's book ''Round About the Carpathians'' and [[Elizabeth Sarah Mazuchelli|Mazuchelli]]'s ''Magyarland'' describe Törzburg as well.&lt;/ref&gt;

Many of the scenes in [[Whitby]] and London are based on real places that Stoker frequently visited, although he distorts the geography for the sake of the story in some cases.  One scholar has suggested that Stoker chose [[Whitby]] as the site of Dracula's first appearance in England because of the [[Synod of Whitby]], given the novel's preoccupation with timekeeping and calendar disputes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Killing Time 2014&quot;/&gt;

Daniel Farson, Leonard Wolf, and Peter Haining have suggested that Stoker received much historical information from [[Ármin Vámbéry]], a [[Hungary|Hungarian]] professor whom he met at least twice. Miller argues, &quot;there is nothing to indicate that the conversation included Vlad, vampires, or even Transylvania&quot;, and &quot;furthermore, there is no record of any other correspondence between Stoker and Vámbéry, nor is Vámbéry mentioned in Stoker's notes for Dracula.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Elizabeth Miller, [http://www.blooferland.com/drc/images/Divorce.rtf Filing for Divorce Count Dracula vs Vlad Tepes] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110708073221/http://www.blooferland.com/drc/images/Divorce.rtf |date=8 July 2011 }} Dracula: The Shade and the Shadow, ed. Elizabeth Miller (Westcliff-on-Sea: Desert Island Books, 1998; cf. Miller, Elizabeth. Dracula – Sense &amp; Nonsense, 2nd ed. Westcliff-on-Sea, UK: Desert Island Books, 2006, pp. 25–27)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Official derivative publications==
&lt;!-- Only add official Dracula books here, as written or mandated by the Stoker family. --&gt;

===&quot;Dracula's Guest&quot;===
{{Main|Dracula's Guest}}
[[File:Draculasguest.jpg|thumb|upright|Cover of ''[[Dracula's Guest and Other Weird Stories]]'', a collection of short stories authored by [[Bram Stoker]]]]
The short story &quot;Dracula's Guest&quot; was posthumously published in 1914, two years after Stoker's death. It was, according to most contemporary critics, the deleted first (or second) chapter from the original manuscript&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |url=https://books.google.com/?id=As8cClbbGqgC&amp;pg=PA27&amp;lpg=PA27&amp;dq=%22dracula%27s+guest%22|first=James Craig | last=Holte |page=27 |title=''Dracula Film Adaptations'' |accessdate=4 June 2010|isbn=9780313292156 |year=1997 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and the one which gave the volume its name,&lt;ref name=&quot;Belford2002&quot;&gt;{{cite book |url=https://books.google.com/?id=hfzy5UPjAr0C |first=Barbara | last=Belford |title=Bram Stoker and the Man Who Was Dracula |isbn=0-306-81098-0 |year=2002|accessdate=4 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|325}} but which the original publishers deemed unnecessary to the overall story.

&quot;Dracula's Guest&quot; follows an unnamed Englishman traveller as he wanders around [[Munich]] before leaving for Transylvania. It is [[Walpurgis Night]] and the young Englishman foolishly leaves his hotel, in spite of the coachman's warnings, and wanders through a dense forest alone. Along the way, he feels that he is being watched by a tall and thin stranger (possibly Count Dracula).

The short story climaxes in an old graveyard where the Englishman, caught in a blizzard, takes refuge in the marble tomb of &quot;Countess Dolingen of Gratz&quot;. Within the tomb, he sees the Countess—apparently asleep and healthy—but before he can investigate further, a mysterious force throws him clear of the tomb. A lightning bolt then strikes the tomb, destroying it and incinerating the undead screaming countess. The Englishman then loses consciousness.  He awakens to find a &quot;gigantic&quot; wolf lying on his chest and licking at his throat; however, the wolf merely keeps him warm and protects him until help arrives.

When the Englishman is finally taken back to his hotel, a telegram awaits him from his expectant host Dracula, with a warning about &quot;dangers from snow and wolves and night&quot;. The Swedish scholar Rickard Berghorn noted that the description of the blonde countess in ''Dracula's Guest'' closely resembled the description of Josephine in the ''[[Powers of Darkness]]'', which he used to argue that the countess and Josephine were meant to be the same character.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |last        = Berghorn
 |first       = Rickard
 |title       = Dracula's Way to Sweden 
 |publisher   = Weird Webzine
 |date        = 2017
 |url         = http://weirdwebzine.com/draculitz.html
 |doi         =
 |accessdate  = 2 September 2019
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===''Powers of Darkness''===
{{Main|Powers of Darkness}}
In 1901, ''Dracula'' was translated into Icelandic by Valdimar Ásmundsson under the title ''Makt Myrkranna'' (''Powers of Darkness'') with a preface written by Stoker.&lt;ref name=&quot;Escher&quot;&gt;{{cite web
 |last        = Escher
 |first       = Kat
 |title       = The Icelandic Translation of 'Dracula' Is Actually a Different Book
 |publisher   = Smithsonian 
 |date        = 19 May 2017
 |url         = https://www.smithsonianmag.com/smart-news/icelandic-translation-dracula-actually-different-book-180963346/
 |doi         =
 |accessdate  = 2 September 2019
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Not until 2014 was it noticed that ''Makt Myrkranna'' differed significantly from Stoker's version of ''Dracula''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Escher&quot;/&gt; The characters had different names, the book was shorter and there was more emphasis on sex than in the English version.&lt;ref name=&quot;Escher&quot;/&gt; The Dutch scholar Hans Corneel de Roos wrote: &quot;Although ''Dracula'' received positive reviews in most newspapers of the day...the original novel can be tedious and meandering....''Powers of Darkness'', by contrast, is written in a concise, punchy style; each scene adds to the progress of the plot.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Escher&quot;/&gt; In ''Makt Myrkranna'', Dracula is in contact with various ambassadors in what is hinted at is a bid for world domination.&lt;ref name=&quot;Melgaard&quot;&gt;{{cite web
 |last        = Melgaard
 |first       = Michael 
 |title       = Counted out: An alternative version of Dracula with an obscure preface appears over a century later
 |publisher   = The National Post 
 |date        = 13 March 2017
 |url         = https://nationalpost.com/entertainment/books/book-reviews/counted-out-an-alternative-version-of-dracula-with-an-obscure-preface-appears-over-a-century-later
 |doi         =
 |accessdate  = 2 September 2019
}}&lt;/ref&gt; The majority of ''Makt Myrkranna'' concerns Thomas Harker's (as Jonathan Harker is called here) stay at Dracula's castle in Transylvania, with the rest of novel being a rushed and barely fleshed out story.&lt;ref name=&quot;Melgaard&quot;/&gt;

De Roos has argued that the differences between the English original of ''Dracula'' and the Icelandic version were not due to changes made by Ásmundsson, but rather that he was using a different, older manuscript of ''Dracula'' provided to him by Stoker, which the latter had discarded for the English version.&lt;ref name=&quot;Escher&quot;/&gt; De Roos has argued that some aspects  ''Makt Myrkranna'' were due to Ásmundsson and other aspects were parts of ''Dracula'' that Stoker had removed due to concerns about British censorship.&lt;ref name=&quot;Melgaard&quot;/&gt;

===''Dracula the Un-dead''===
{{main|Dracula the Un-dead}}
In 2009, an official sequel was published, written by Bram Stoker's great grand-nephew [[Dacre Stoker]] and Ian Holt.

===''Dracul''&lt;!-- NOT a typo. Do not change to &quot;Dracula&quot;.--&gt;===
Dacre Stoker and [[J. D. Barker]] will write a prequel to ''Dracula'' titled ''[[Dracul (book)|Dracul]]''. An interpretation of the missing 101 pages of the original novel, it was pieced together from Bram Stoker's editorial notes, artifacts, and journals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ew.com/books/2018/03/27/dracul-cover-reveal-excerpt/|title=Missing original pages of Dracula are pieced together in Dracul: See the haunting cover|website=[[Entertainment Weekly]]|accessdate=28 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Adaptations==
&lt;!--NOTE: DO NOT ADD POPULAR CULTURE DERIVATIVES HERE. USE THE MAIN ARTICLE [[Dracula in popular culture]]--&gt;
{{details|Dracula in popular culture}}
[[File:Bela Lugosi as Dracula, anonymous photograph from 1931, Universal Studios.jpg|left|thumb|upright|[[Bela Lugosi]] as [[Count Dracula]] in the [[Dracula (1931 English-language film)|1931 film]].]]
The story of ''Dracula'' has been the basis for numerous films and plays. Stoker himself wrote the first theatrical adaptation, which was presented at the Lyceum Theatre on 18 May 1897 under the title ''Dracula, or The Undead'' shortly before the novel's publication and performed only once, in order to establish his own copyright for such adaptations. This adaption was first published only a century later in October 1997.&lt;ref&gt;Stoker, Bram, (1997). ''Dracula: or The Undead – A Play in Prologue and Five Acts'', Ed. Sylvia Starshine, Pumpkin Books, Nottingham. {{ISBN|1901914046}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first motion picture to feature Dracula was ''[[Dracula's Death]]'', produced in [[Hungary]] in 1921.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.silentera.com/PSFL/data/D/DrakulaHalala1921.html|title=Silent Era: Progressive Silent Film List|last=|first=|date=|website=|archive-url=|archivedate=|accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The now-[[lost film]], however, was not an adaptation of Stoker's novel, but featured an original story.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.ca/books?id=cEAvDwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT66|last=Bills|first=E.R.|publisher=History Press Library Editions|isbn=978-1540227089|title=Texas Far &amp; Wide: The Tornado with Eyes, Gettysburg's Last Casualty, the Celestial Skipping Stone &amp; Other Tales|page=66|year=2017|accessdate=11 July 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[F. W. Murnau]]'s unauthorised film adaptation ''[[Nosferatu]]'' was released in 1922, and the popularity of the novel increased considerably, owing to an attempt by Stoker's widow to have the film removed from public circulation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Stoker |first=Bram |url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/cult/vampires/classicstory/dracula_p1.shtml |title=Article at the BBC Cult website |publisher=BBC |date= |accessdate=17 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Prana Film, the production company, had been unable to obtain permission to adapt the story from Bram's widow [[Florence Balcombe|Florence Stoker]], so screenwriter [[Henrik Galeen]] was told to alter numerous details to avoid legal trouble. Galeen transplanted the action of the story from 1890s England to 1830s Germany and reworked several characters, dropping some (such as Lucy and all three of her suitors), and renaming others (Dracula became [[Count Orlok|Orlok]], Jonathan Harker became Thomas Hutter, Mina became Ellen, and so on). This attempt failed to avoid a court case, however; Florence Stoker sued Prana Film, and all copies of the film were ordered to be destroyed. However, the company was bankrupt, and Stoker only recovered her legal fees in damages. Some copies survived and found their way into theatres. Eventually, Florence Stoker gave up the fight against public displays of the film.&lt;ref name=&quot;StokerHolt2009&quot; /&gt; Subsequent rereleases of the film have typically undone some of the changes, such as restoring the original character names (a practice also followed by [[Werner Herzog]] in his 1979 remake of Murnau's film ''[[Nosferatu the Vampyre]]'').{{citation needed|date=May 2017}}

Florence Stoker licensed the story to playwright [[Hamilton Deane]], whose [[Dracula (1924 play)|1924 stage play adaptation]] toured England for several years before settling down in London.{{citation needed|date=May 2017}} In 1927, American stage producer [[Horace Liveright]] hired [[John L. Balderston]] to revise Deane's script in advance of its American premiere. Balderston significantly compressed the story, most notably consolidating or removing several characters. The Deane play and its Balderston revisions introduced an expanded role and history for Renfield, who now replaced Jonathan Harker as Dracula's solicitor in the first part of the story; combined [[Mina Harker]] and [[Lucy Westenra]] into a single character named Lucy (though both Mina and Lucy would appear in the subsequent film); and omitted both [[Arthur Holmwood]] and [[Quincey Morris]] entirely. When the play premiered in New York, it was with [[Bela Lugosi]] in the title role, and with [[Edward van Sloan]] as [[Abraham Van Helsing]],{{citation needed|date=May 2017}} roles which both actors (as well as [[Herbert Bunston]] as [[John Seward|Dr. Seward]]) reprised for the English-language version of the 1931 [[Universal Studios]] [[Dracula (1931 English-language film)|film production]]. The 1931 film was one of the most commercially successful adaptations of the story to date; it and the Deane/Balderston play that preceded it set the standard for film and television adaptations of the story, with the alterations to the novel becoming standard for later adaptations for decades to come.{{citation needed|date=May 2017}} Universal Studios continued to feature the character of Dracula in many of their [[Universal monsters|horror films from the 1930s and 1940s]].

[[File:Dracula 1958 c.jpg|thumb|right|[[Christopher Lee]] as the title character in ''[[Dracula (1958 film)|Dracula]]'' (1958)]]
In 1958, British film company [[Hammer Film Productions]] followed the success of its ''[[The Curse of Frankenstein]]'' from the previous year with ''[[Dracula (1958 film)|Dracula]]'', released in the US as ''Horror of Dracula'', directed by [[Terence Fisher]]. Fisher's production featured [[Christopher Lee]] as Dracula and [[Peter Cushing]] as Van Helsing. It was an international hit for Hammer Film, and Lee fixed the image of the fanged vampire in popular culture.&lt;ref&gt;J Gordon Melton (2010). &quot;The Vampire Book: The Encyclopedia of the Undead&quot;. p. 247. Visible Ink Press&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Fangs for the memories: The A–Z of vampires|url=https://www.independent.co.uk/news/uk/this-britain/fangs-for-the-memories-the-a-z-of-vampires-1810987.html|issue=31 October 2009|newspaper=The Independent}}&lt;/ref&gt; Both Lee and Cushing reprised their roles multiple times over the next decade and a half, concluding with ''[[The Legend of the 7 Golden Vampires]]'' (with Cushing but not Lee) in 1974. Christopher Lee also took on the role of Dracula in ''[[Count Dracula (1970 film)|Count Dracula]]'', a 1970 Spanish-Italian-German co-production notable for its adherence to the plot of the original novel. Playing the part of Renfield in that version was [[Klaus Kinski]], who later played Dracula himself in 1979's ''Nosferatu the Vampyre''.

In 1977, the [[BBC]] made ''[[Count Dracula (1977 film)|Count Dracula]]'', a 155-minute adaptation for television starring [[Louis Jourdan]]. Later film adaptations include [[John Badham]]'s 1979 ''[[Dracula (1979 film)|Dracula]]'', starring [[Frank Langella]] and inspired by the [[Dracula (1977 play)|1977 Broadway revival]] of the Deane/Hamilton play, and [[Francis Ford Coppola]]'s 1992 ''[[Bram Stoker's Dracula (1992 film)|Bram Stoker's Dracula]]'', starring [[Gary Oldman]]. The character of Count Dracula has remained popular over the years, and many films have used the character as a villain, while others have named him in their titles, including ''[[Dracula's Daughter]]'' and ''[[The Brides of Dracula]]''.

==See also==
{{Portal|Speculative fiction/Horror}}
*[[Vampire literature]]
*[[Church of Saint Mary, Whitby]]
*[[List of contemporary epistolary novels]]
*[[Bloodline (Cary novel)|''Bloodline'' (Cary novel)]]
*''[[The Book of Renfield|The Book of Renfield: A Gospel of Dracula]]'', a fictional diary written by Renfield
*[[List of works by Fred Saberhagen#Dracula sequence|Dracula sequence]], stories from Dracula's point of view
*[[Clinical vampirism]]
* [[Bibliography of works on Dracula]]

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==Bibliography==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book | last=Davison | first=Carol Margaret |title=Bram Stoker's Dracula: Sucking Through the Century, 1897–1997 | year=1997 | isbn=9781554881055 | publisher=Dundurn | location=Toronto, Ontario | ref=harv}}
* Dalby, Richard and Hughes, William. ''Bram Stoker: A Bibliography'' (Westcliff-on-Sea: Desert Island Books, 2005)
* [[Christopher Frayling|Frayling, Christopher]]. ''Vampyres: Lord Byron to Count Dracula'' (1992) {{ISBN|0-571-16792-6}}
* Eighteen-Bisang, Robert and Miller, Elizabeth. ''Bram Stoker's Notes for Dracula: A Facsimile Edition'' Toronto: McFarland, 2008, {{ISBN|978-0-7864-3410-7}}
* Hughes, William. ''Beyond Dracula: Bram Stoker's Fiction and its Cultural Contexts'' (Basingstoke: Macmillan, 2000)
* McNally, Raymond T. &amp; Florescu, Radu. ''In Search of Dracula''. Houghton Mifflin Company, 1994. {{ISBN|0-395-65783-0}}
* Miller, Elizabeth. ''Dracula: Sense &amp; Nonsense''. 2nd ed. Desert Island Books, 2006. {{ISBN|1-905328-15-X}}
* Schaffer, Talia. ''A Wilde Desire Took Me: the Homoerotic History of Dracula'', in: ELH – Volume 61, Number 2 (1994), pp.&amp;nbsp;381–425.
* Senf, Carol. ''Science and Social Science in Bram Stoker's Fiction'' (Greenwood, 2002).
* Senf, Carol. ''Dracula: Between Tradition and Modernism'' (Twayne, 1998).
* Spencer, Kathleen. ''Purity and Danger: Dracula, the Urban Gothic, and the Late Victorian Degeneracy Crisis'', in: ELH – Volume 59, Number 1 (1992), pp.&amp;nbsp;197–225.
* [[Leonard Wolf|Wolf, Leonard]]. ''The Essential Dracula''. ibooks, inc., 2004. {{ISBN|0-7434-9803-8}}
* [[Leslie S. Klinger|Klinger, Leslie S.]] ''The New Annotated Dracula''. W.W. Norton &amp; Co., 2008. {{ISBN|0-393-06450-6}}
* [[Colin Waters.|Waters, Colin]] ''Gothic Whitby''. History Press, 2009 – {{ISBN|0-7524-5291-6}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{wikisource|Dracula|''Dracula''}}
* {{gutenberg|no=345|name=Dracula}}, text version of 1897 edition.
* {{librivox book | title=Dracula | author=Bram Stoker}}
* [http://news.bbc.co.uk/local/york/hi/people_and_places/arts_and_culture/newsid_8121000/8121579.stm Bram Stoker, ''Dracula'' and Whitby BBC article]
* [http://www.themythoftransylvania.ro/ ''The Myth of Transylvania''], Romanian Website dealing with the Dracula myth and the Western perception of Romania.
* [http://dractravel.com/drc/ ''Journal of Dracula Studies'']
* [http://www.thewhitbyguide.co.uk/whitby-dracula/ ''Links between Dracula, Bram Stoker and the Yorkshire town of Whitby'']

{{Dracula}}
{{Bram Stoker}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Dracula| ]]
[[Category:1897 British novels]]
[[Category:19th-century Irish novels]]
[[Category:British novels adapted into plays]]
[[Category:Constable &amp; Co. books]]
[[Category:Dracula novels]]
[[Category:England in fiction]]
[[Category:Epistolary novels]]
[[Category:Irish Gothic novels]]
[[Category:British horror novels]]
[[Category:Hungary in fiction]]
[[Category:Irish novels adapted into films]]
[[Category:Irish novels adapted into plays]]
[[Category:Fiction about mind control]]
[[Category:Novels adapted into comics]]
[[Category:Novels adapted into radio programs]]
[[Category:Novels adapted into television programs]]
[[Category:Novels adapted into video games]]
[[Category:Novels by Bram Stoker]]
[[Category:Novels set in London]]
[[Category:Novels set in Romania]]
[[Category:Fiction about shapeshifting]]
[[Category:Transylvania in fiction]]
[[Category:Vampire novels]]
[[Category:Victorian novels]]</text>
      <sha1>fpkpzw8cntpfbcjp03v31vjknd02026</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
