  <page>
    <title>Dill</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7985</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943125923</id>
      <parentid>943125808</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-29T00:29:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Plantdrew</username>
        <id>14423536</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>taxonbar from</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Species of flowering plant in the celery family Apiaceae}}
{{about|the herb}}
{{Speciesbox
|name = Dill
|image = Illustration Anethum graveolens clean.jpg
|image_caption=1885 illustration&lt;ref&gt;Prof. Dr. Otto Wilhelm Thomé Flora von Deutschland, Österreich und der Schweiz 1885, Gera, Germany&lt;/ref&gt;
|display_parents = 3
|parent_authority = [[Carl Linnaeus|L.]]
|taxon = Anethum graveolens
|authority = [[Carl Linnaeus|L.]]
|synonyms_ref=&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theplantlist.org/tpl1.1/record/kew-2638934 The Plant List, ''Anethum graveolens'' L. ]&lt;/ref&gt;
| synonyms ={{collapsible list|bullets = true
|title=&lt;small&gt;Synonymy&lt;/small&gt;
|''Anethum arvense'' &lt;small&gt;Salisb.&lt;/small&gt;
|''Angelica graveolens'' &lt;small&gt;(L.) Steud.&lt;/small&gt;
|''Ferula graveolens'' &lt;small&gt;(L.) Spreng.&lt;/small&gt;
|''Pastinaca anethum'' &lt;small&gt;Spreng.&lt;/small&gt;
|''Peucedanum anethum'' &lt;small&gt;Jess.&lt;/small&gt;
|''Peucedanum graveolens'' &lt;small&gt;(L.) Hiern&lt;/small&gt;
|''Peucedanum sowa'' &lt;small&gt;(Roxb. ex Fleming) Kurz&lt;/small&gt; 
|''Selinum anethum'' &lt;small&gt;Roth&lt;/small&gt; 
|''Selinum graveolens'' &lt;small&gt;(L.) Vest&lt;/small&gt;
}}}}

'''Dill''' (''Anethum graveolens'') is an [[annual plant|annual]] [[herbaceous|herb]] in the celery family [[Apiaceae]]. It is the only species in the genus ''Anethum''. Dill is grown widely in [[Eurasia]] where its leaves and seeds are used as a herb or spice for flavouring food.

==Growth==
Dill grows up to {{convert|40|-|60|cm|in|0|abbr=on}}, with slender hollow stems and alternate, finely divided, softly delicate [[leaf|leaves]] {{convert|10|-|20|cm|in|0|abbr=on}} long. The ultimate leaf divisions are {{convert|1|-|2|mm|in|2|abbr=on}} broad, slightly broader than the similar leaves of [[fennel]], which are threadlike, less than {{convert|1|mm|in|2|abbr=on}} broad, but harder in texture. The [[flower]]s are white to yellow, in small [[umbel]]s {{convert|2|-|9|cm|in|1|abbr=on}} diameter. The [[seed]]s are {{convert|4|-|5|mm|in|2|abbr=on}} long and {{convert|1|mm|in|2|abbr=on}} thick, and straight to slightly curved with a longitudinally ridged surface.

==Etymology==
The word &quot;dill&quot; and its close relatives are found in most of the Germanic languages; its ultimate origin is unknown.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Oxford English Dictionary]]'', 1896, [http://www.oed.com/view/Entry/52792 ''s.v.''] (subscription)&lt;/ref&gt; The generic name ''Anethum'' is the [[Latin language|Latin]] form of the [[Greek language|Greek]] ἄνῑσον / ἄνησον / ἄνηθον / ἄνητον, which meant both &quot;dill&quot; and &quot;[[anise]]&quot;. The form ''anīsum'' came to be used for anise, ''anēthum'' for dill. The Latin word is the origin of dill's names in the [[Western Romance languages]] (''anet'', ''aneldo'', etc.), and also of the obsolete English ''anet''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oed.com/view/Entry/7811 ''s.v.'' 'anise']&lt;/ref&gt; Most [[Slavic language]] names come from [[Proto-Slavic]] ''*koprъ''.&lt;ref&gt;R.H. Derksen, ''Etymological Dictionary of the Slavic Inherited Lexicon'', 2008, as quoted in [http://www.proto-slavic.ru/dic-derksen-inh/sil-k.html]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Culinary use==
{{Nutritional value  
| name            = Dill weed, fresh 
| kJ              = 180 
| carbs           = 7 g 
| fiber           = 2.1 g 
| fat             = 1.1 g 
| protein         = 3.5 g 
| vitA_iu         = 7717 (154%) 
| thiamin_mg      = 0.1 
| riboflavin_mg   = 0.3 
| niacin_mg       = 1.6 
| pantothenic_mg  = 0.4 
| vitB6_mg        = 0.2 
| folate_ug       = 150 
| vitB12_ug       = 0 
| vitC_mg         = 85 
| calcium_mg      = 208 
| iron_mg         = 6.6 
| magnesium_mg    = 55 
| manganese_mg    = 1.3 
| phosphorus_mg   = 66 
| potassium_mg    = 738 
| sodium_mg       = 61 
| zinc_mg         = 0.9 
| opt1n           = [[Copper]] 667
| opt1v           = 0.14 mg (7%) 
| source_usda = 1 
}}

[[Image:DillEssOil.png|thumb|upright|Dill (''Anethum graveolens'') essential oil in clear glass vial]]
Fresh and dried dill leaves (sometimes called &quot;dill weed&quot; to distinguish it from dill seed) are widely used as [[herb]]s in [[Europe]] and central Asia.

Like [[caraway]], the fernlike leaves of dill are aromatic and are used to flavor many [[food]]s such as [[gravlax]] (cured [[salmon]]) and other [[Fish (food)|fish]] dishes, [[borscht]], and other [[soup]]s, as well as [[pickled cucumber|pickle]]s (where the dill flower is sometimes used). Dill is best when used fresh, as it loses its flavor rapidly if dried, however, [[Freeze drying|freeze-dried]] dill leaves retain their flavor relatively well for a few months.

[[Dill oil]] is extracted from the leaves, stems, and seeds of the plant. The oil from the seeds is distilled and used in the manufacturing of soaps.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Culinary Herbs: Their Cultivation Harvesting Curing and Uses|year=1912|publisher=Orange Judd Company|url=http://www.gutenberg.org/files/21414/21414-h/21414-h.htm#Page_87|author=M. G. Kains|editor=American Agriculturist|format=English}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Dill is the [[eponymous]] ingredient in dill [[Pickled cucumber|pickles]].&lt;ref&gt;''The Cultural History of Plants'' (Routledge, 2005: eds. Sir [[Ghillean Prance]] &amp; Mark Nesbitt), pp. 102-03.&lt;/ref&gt;

===European cuisine===
In [[Central Europe|central]] and [[eastern Europe]], [[Scandinavia]], [[Baltic states]], [[Ukraine]], [[Russia]], and [[Finland]], dill is a popular [[herb#culinary herbs|culinary herb]] used in the kitchen along with chives or parsley. Fresh, finely cut dill leaves are used as a topping in soups, especially the hot red [[borsht]] and the cold borsht mixed with curds, kefir, yogurt, or sour cream, which is served during hot summer weather and is ` [[okroshka]]. It  also is popular in summer to drink fermented milk (curds, kefir, yogurt, or buttermilk) mixed with dill (and sometimes other herbs).

In the same way, prepared dill is used as a topping for boiled potatoes covered with fresh butter&amp;nbsp;– especially in summer when there are so-called &quot;new&quot;, or young, potatoes. The dill leaves may be mixed with butter, making a dill butter, to serve the same purpose. Dill leaves mixed with [[tvorog]], form one of the traditional cheese spreads used for sandwiches. Fresh dill leaves are used throughout the year as an ingredient in salads, ''e.g.'', one made of lettuce, fresh cucumbers, and tomatoes, as [[basil]] leaves are used in Italy and Greece.

[[Russian cuisine]] is noted for liberal use of dill, where it is known as {{Lang|ru|укроп|italic=yes}}. Its supposed [[antiflatulent]] activity caused some Russian cosmonauts to recommend its use in [[manned spaceflight]] due to the confined quarters and closed air supply.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Kelly|first1=Scott|title=Endurance: A Year in Space, a Lifetime of Discovery|date=October 2017|publisher=Alfred A. Knopf|isbn=978-1524731595}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Polish cuisine]], fresh dill leaves mixed with sour cream are the basis for dressings. It is especially popular to use this kind of sauce with freshly cut cucumbers, which practically are wholly immersed in the sauce, making a salad called [[mizeria]]. The dill leaves serve as a basis for cooking dill sauce, used hot for baked freshwater fish and for chicken or turkey breast, or used hot or cold for hard-boiled eggs. A dill-based soup, (zupa koperkowa), served with potatoes and hard-boiled eggs, is popular in Poland. Whole stems including roots and flower buds are used traditionally to prepare Polish-style pickled cucumbers ([[ogórki kiszone]]), especially the so-called low-salt cucumbers (&quot;ogórki małosolne&quot;). Whole stems of dill (often including the roots) also are cooked with potatoes, especially the potatoes of autumn and winter, so they resemble the flavor of the newer potatoes found in summer. Some kinds of fish, especially trout and salmon, traditionally are baked with the stems and leaves of dill.

In the [[Czech Republic]], white dill sauce made of cream (or milk), butter, flour, vinegar, and dill is called ''koprová omáčka'' (also ''koprovka'' or ''kopračka'') and is served either with boiled eggs and potatoes, or with dumplings and boiled beef. Another Czech dish with dill is a soup called, ''kulajda'', that contains mushrooms (traditionally wild ones).

In Germany, dill is popular as a seasoning for fish and many other dishes, chopped as a garnish on potatoes, and as a flavoring in pickles.

In the UK, dill may be used in [[fish pie]].

In [[Bulgaria]] dill is widely used in traditional vegetable salads, and most notably the yogurt-based cold soup [[Tarator]]. It is also used in the preparation of sour pickles, cabbage, and other dishes.

In [[Romania]] dill (''mărar'') is widely used as an ingredient for soups such as ''borş'' (pronounced &quot;borsh&quot;), pickles, and other dishes, especially those based on peas, beans, and cabbage. It is popular for dishes based on potatoes and mushrooms and may be found in many summer salads (especially cucumber salad, cabbage salad and lettuce salad). During springtime, it is used in omelets with spring onions. It often complements sauces based on sour cream or yogurt and is mixed with salted cheese and used as a filling. Another popular dish with dill as a main ingredient is dill sauce, which is served with eggs and fried sausages.

In [[Hungary]], dill is very widely used. It is popular as a sauce or filling, and mixed with a type of cottage cheese. Dill is also used for [[pickling]] and in salads. The Hungarian name for dill is ''kapor''.

In [[Serbia]], dill is known as ''mirodjija'' and is used as an addition to soups, potato and cucumber salads, and French fries. It features in the Serbian proverb, &quot;бити мирођија у свакој чорби&quot; /biti mirodjija u svakoj čorbi/ (to be a dill in every soup), which corresponds to the English proverb &quot;to have a finger in every pie&quot;.

In [[Greece]], dill is known as 'άνηθος' (anithos). In antiquity it was used as an ingredient in wines that were called &quot;anithites oinos&quot; (wine with anithos-dill). In modern days, dill is used in salads, soups, sauces, and fish and vegetable dishes.

In [[Santa Maria Island (Azores)|Santa Maria]], [[Azores]], dill (''endro'') is the most important ingredient of the traditional Holy Ghost soup (''sopa do Espírito Santo''). Dill is found ubiquitously in Santa Maria, yet curiously, is rare in the other Azorean Islands.

In [[Sweden]], dill is a common spice or herb. The top of fully grown dill is called ''krondill'' (English: Crown dill); this is used when cooking [[crayfish]]. The ''krondill'' is put into the water after the crayfish is boiled, but still in hot and salt water. Then the entire dish is refrigerated for at least 24 hours before being served (with toasted bread and butter). ''Krondill'' also is used for [[cucumber]] [[pickled cucumber|pickles]]. Small cucumbers, sliced or not, are put into a solution of hot water, mild acetic [[Vinegar#Spirits|white vinegar]] (made from vodka, not wine), sugar, and ''krondill''. After a month or two of fermentation, the cucumber pickles are ready to eat, for instance, with pork, brown sauce, and potatoes, as a &quot;sweetener&quot;. The thinner part of dill and young plants may be used with boiled fresh potatoes (especially the first potatoes for the year, &quot;new potatoes&quot;, which usually are small and have a very thin skin). It is used together with, or instead of other green herbs, such as [[parsley]], [[chives]], and [[basil]], in salads. It often is paired up with chives when used in food. Dill often is used to flavour fish and seafood in Sweden, for example, gravlax and various herring pickles, among them the traditional, '''sill i dill''' (literally &quot;herring in dill&quot;). In contrast to the various fish dishes flavoured with dill, there is also a traditional Swedish dish called, dillkött, which is a meaty stew flavoured with dill. The dish commonly contains either pieces of veal or lamb that are boiled until tender and then served together with a vinegary dill sauce. Dill seeds may be used in breads or [[akvavit]]. A newer, non-traditional use of dill is when it is paired up with chives as a flavouring of potato chips. This flavour of potato chips called, &quot;dillchips&quot;, is quite popular in Sweden.

===Asian and Middle Eastern cooking===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;

|-
| India || Marathi, Konkani || Shepu || Shepuchi Bhaji, Shepu Pulao, Ashe Mast

|-Bangladesh	Bangla	শলুক	মসলা
| India || Hindi || Soa / Soya ||Soa Sabzi(with potato).As a flavor in:- Green Kheema, Kheema samosa
|-
| India || Kannada || sabbasige soppu || Curry
|-
| India || Telugu || Soa-Kura (శత పుష్పం) ||
 |-
| India || Tamil || Sadakuppi (சதகுப்பி) || Curry 
|-
| India || Manipuri || Pakhon || chagem pomba
|-
| India || Punjabi || Soa ||
|-
| India || Gujarati || Suva ||Suvaa ni Bhaji(with potato)
|-India Bengali Sholpa
| Iran || Persian|| Shevid || Aash, Baghali Polo, Shevid Polo, Mast O Khiar
|-India   Kannada   sabbasige soppu || Curry
|Arab world || Arabic|| شبت، شبث (shabat, shabath) || As flavoring in various dishes
|-
| Thailand|| Thai|| phak chee Lao(ผักชีลาว) || Gaeng om(แกงอ่อม)
|-
| India || Malayalam|| Chatakuppa ||
|-
| Vietnam || Vietnamese|| Thì là ||Many fish dishes in Northern Vietnam
|-
| China || Chinese || shiluo || baozi
|}

In [[Iran]], dill is known as ''shevid'' and sometimes, is used with rice and called ''shevid-polo''. It also is used in Iranian ''aash'' recipes, and similarly, is called ''sheved'' in [[Persian Language|Persian]].

In [[India]], dill is known as &quot;Sholpa&quot; in Bengali, ''shepu'' (शेपू) in Marathi, and Konkani, ''savaa'' in Hindi, or ''soa'' in Punjabi. In Telugu, it is called ''Soa-kura'' (for herb greens). It also is called ''sabbasige soppu'' (&lt;big&gt;ಸಬ್ಬಸಿಗೆ ಸೊಪ್ಪು&lt;/big&gt;) in [[Kannada language|Kannada]]. In [[Tamil language|Tamil]] it is known as ''sada kuppi''(சதகுப்பி). In [[Malayalam]], it is ചതകുപ്പ (''chathakuppa'') or ശതകുപ്പ (''sathakuppa''). In Sanskrit, this herb is called ''shatapushpa''. In Gujarati, it is known as ''suva'' (સૂવા). In India, dill is prepared in the manner of yellow ''moong dal'', as a main-course dish. It is considered to have very good antiflatulant properties, so it is used as ''mukhwas'', or an after-meal digestive. Traditionally, it is given to mothers immediately after childbirth. In the state of Uttar Pradesh in India, a small amount of fresh dill is cooked along with cut potatoes and fresh fenugreek leaves (Hindi आलू-मेथी-सोया). 

In [[Manipur]], dill, locally known as ''pakhon'', is an essential ingredient of ''chagem pomba'' – a traditional Manipuri dish made with fermented soybean and rice.

In [[Laos]] and parts of northern [[Isan|Thailand]], dill is known in English as Lao coriander ({{lang-lo|ຜັກຊີ}} or {{lang-th|ผักชีลาว}}),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = Davidson, A. | year = 2003 | page = 216 | isbn = 978-1-58008-452-9 | url = https://books.google.com/?id=8nhfSFs79fUC&amp;pg=PA216&amp;lpg=PA216&amp;dq=laotian+coriander#v=onepage&amp;q=laotian%20coriander&amp;f=false | title = Seafood of South-East Asia | edition = 2nd | publisher = Ten Speed Press }}&lt;/ref&gt; and served as a side with salad yum or papaya salad. In the [[Lao language]], it is called ''phak see'', and in [[Thai language|Thai]], it is known as ''phak chee Lao''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ediblyasian.info/glossary-thailand.php|title=Thai names|work=ediblyasian.info}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = Ling, K. F. | year = 2002 | page = 155| url = https://books.google.com/?id=oNPaeFOk7ykC&amp;pg=RA1-PA155&amp;lpg=RA1-PA155&amp;dq=laotian+coriander#v=onepage&amp;q=laotian%20coriander&amp;f=false | title = The Food of Asia | publisher = Periplus editions (HK) | location = Singapore | isbn = 978-0-7946-0146-1 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Lao cuisine]], Lao coriander is used extensively in traditional Lao dishes such as ''[[mok pa]]'' (steamed fish in banana leaf) and several coconut milk curries that contain fish or [[prawn]]s.

In [[China]] dill is called colloquially, ''huíxiāng'' ({{lang|zh|茴香}}, perfums of Hui people), or more properly ''shíluó'' ({{lang|zh|莳萝}}). It is a common filling in [[baozi]] and [[bing (bread)|xianbing]] and may be used as vegetarian with rice vermicelli, or combined with either meat or eggs. Vegetarian dill baozi are a common part of a Beijing breakfast. In baozi and xianbing, it often is interchangeable with non-bulbing [[fennel]] and the term {{lang|zh|茴香}} also may refer to fennel, similarly to caraway and coriander leaf, sharing a name in Chinese as well. Dill also may be [[stir fried]] as a potherb, often with egg, in the same manner as [[Chinese chives]]. It commonly is used in [[Taiwan]] as well. In Northern China, [[Beijing]], [[Inner-Mongolia]], [[Ningxia]], [[Gansu]], and [[Xinjiang]], dill seeds commonly are called ''zīrán'' ({{lang|zh|孜然}}), but also ''kūmíng'' ({{lang|zh|枯茗}}), ''kūmíngzi'' ({{lang|zh|枯茗子}}), ''shíluózi'' ({{lang|zh|莳萝子}}), ''xiǎohuíxiāngzi'' ({{lang|zh|小茴香子}})  and are used with pepper for lamb meat. In the whole of China, ''yángchuàn'' ({{lang|zh|羊串}}) or ''yángròu chuàn'' ({{lang|zh|羊肉串}}), lamb [[brochette]], a speciality from [[Uyghurs]], uses cumin and pepper.

In [[Vietnam]], the use of dill in cooking is regional. It is used mainly in northern Vietnamese cuisine.

===Middle East uses===

In Arab countries, dill seed, called ''ain jaradeh'' (grasshopper's eye), is used as a spice in cold dishes such as ''[[fattoush]]'' and pickles. In Arab countries of the [[Persian Gulf]], dill is called ''shibint'' and is used mostly in fish dishes. In [[Egypt]], dillweed is commonly used to flavor [[cabbage]] dishes, including ''[[cabbage roll|mahshi koronb]]'' (stuffed cabbage leaves).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Egyptian Style Stuffed Cabbage Leaves (Mashy Crump)|url=http://www.food.com/recipe/egyptian-style-stuffed-cabbage-leaves-mashy-crump-194768|accessdate=1 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In Israel, dill seed is used to spice in salads and also to flavor omelettes, alongside parsley, and is called &quot;Shamir&quot;.

==Cultivation==
Successful cultivation requires warm to hot summers with high sunshine levels; even partial shade will reduce the yield substantially.{{Citation needed|date=May 2018}} It also prefers rich, well-drained soil. The seeds are viable for three to ten years.{{Citation needed|date=June 2010}} The plants are somewhat [[monocarpic]] and quickly die after &quot;bolting&quot; (producing seeds). Hot temperatures may quicken bolting.{{Citation needed|date=May 2018}}

The seed is harvested by cutting the flower heads off the stalks when the seed is beginning to ripen. The seed heads are placed upside down in a paper bag and left in a warm, dry place for a week. The seeds then separate from the stems easily for storage in an airtight container.

These plants, like their fennel and parsley relatives, often are eaten by [[Papilio polyxenes|Black swallowtail caterpillars]] in areas where that species occurs.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://edis.ifas.ufl.edu/in906|title=Eastern Black Swallowtail: Papilio polyxenes asterius (Stoll) (Insecta: Lepidoptera: Papilionidae)|last=Hall|first=Donald|date=2017-10-23|website=edis.ifas.ufl.edu|language=en|access-date=2017-11-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; For this reason, they may be included in some [[Butterfly gardening|butterfly gardens]].

==Companion planting==
[[File:Anethum graveolens 001.JPG|thumb|Dill plants]]
When used as a [[companion plant]], dill attracts many beneficial insects as the umbrella flower heads go to seed. It makes a good companion plant for cucumbers and broccoli. 

It is a poor companion plant for carrots and tomatoes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url = http://theselfsufficientgardener.com/episode-17-my-favorite-herbs-dill/|title=The Self-Sufficient Gardener Podcast Episode 17 My Favorite Herbs - Dill}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aroma profile==
* [[Apiole]] and [[dillapiole]]&lt;ref name=eocc&gt;
{{cite journal
| last1 = Bailer    | first1 = J.
| last2 = Aichinger | first2 = T.
| last3 = Hackl     | first3 = G. 
| last4 = de Hueber | first4 = K.
| last5 = Dachler   | first5 = M.
| title = Essential oil content and composition in commercially available dill cultivars in comparison to caraway
| journal = [[Industrial Crops and Products]]
| volume = 14
| issue = 3
| pages = 229–239
| year  = 2001
| doi   = 10.1016/S0926-6690(01)00088-7
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=hrca&gt;
{{cite journal
| last1 = Santos     | first1 = P. A. G. 
| last2 = Figueiredo | first2 = A. C.
| last3 = Lourenço   | first3 = P. M. L.
| last4 = Barroso    | first4 = J. G.
| last5 = Pedro      | first5 = L. G.
| last6 = Oliveira   | first6 = M. M.
| last7 = Schripsema | first7 = J.
| last8 = Deans      | first8 = S. G.
| last9 = Scheffer   | first9 = J. J. C.
| title = Hairy root cultures of Anethum graveolens (dill): establishment, growth, time-course study of their essential oil and its comparison with parent plant oils
| journal = [[Biotechnology Letters]]
| volume = 24
| issue = 12
| pages = 1031–1036
| year  = 2002
| doi   = 10.1023/A:1015653701265
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Carvone]]&lt;ref name=ccai /&gt;&lt;ref name=esmq /&gt;
*[[Limonene]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Huopalahti|first=Rainer|last2=Linko|first2=Reino R.|date=March 1983|title=Composition and content of aroma compounds in dill, Anethum graveolens L., at three different growth stages|journal=Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry|language=EN|volume=31|issue=2|pages=331–333|doi=10.1021/jf00116a036|issn=0021-8561}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Myristicin]]&lt;ref name=esmq&gt;
{{cite journal
| last1 = Dhalwal  | first1 = K. 
| last2 = Shinde   | first2 = V. M.
| last3 = Mahadik  | first3 = K. R. 
| title = Efficient and Sensitive Method for Quantitative Determination and Validation of Umbelliferone, Carvone and Myristicin in ''Anethum graveolens'' and ''Carum carvi'' Seed
| journal = [[Chromatographia]]
| volume = 67
| issue = 1–2
| pages = 163–167
| year = 2008
| doi = 10.1365/s10337-007-0473-6
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=epod&gt;
{{cite journal
| last1 = Blank  | first1 = I.
| last2 = Grosch | first2 = W.
| title = Evaluation of Potent Odorants in Dill Seed and Dill Herb (''Anethum graveolens'' L.) by Aroma Extract Dilution Analysis
| journal = [[Journal of Food Science]]
| volume = 56
| issue = 1
| pages = 63–67
| year  = 1991
| doi   = 10.1111/j.1365-2621.1991.tb07976.x
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Umbelliferone]]&lt;ref name=esmq /&gt;

==Toxicology==
* Antibacterial activity against ''[[Staphylococcus aureus]]''&lt;ref name=ccai&gt;
{{cite journal
| last1 = Singh     | first1 = G.
| last2 = Maurya    | first2 = S.
| last3 = Lampasona | first3 = M. P.
| last4 = Catalan   | first4 = C. 
| title = Chemical Constituents, Antimicrobial Investigations, and Antioxidative Potentials of Anethum graveolens L. Essential Oil and Acetone Extract: Part 52
| journal = [[Journal of Food Science]]
| volume = 70
| issue = 4
| pages = M208–M215
| year  = 2005
| doi   = 10.1111/j.1365-2621.2005.tb07190.x
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Antimicrobial activity against ''[[Saccharomyces cerevisiae]]''&lt;ref name=aaim&gt;
{{cite journal
| last1 = Delaquis | first1 = P. J. 
| last2 = Stanich  | first2 = K.
| last3 = Girard   | first3 = B. 
| last4 = Mazza    | first4 = G.
| title = Antimicrobial activity of individual and mixed fractions of dill, cilantro, coriander and eucalyptus essential oils
| journal = [[International Journal of Food Microbiology]]
| volume = 74
| issue = 1–2
| pages = 101–109
| year  = 2002
| pmid  = 11929164
| doi   = 10.1016/S0168-1605(01)00734-6
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=cqca&gt;
{{cite journal
| last1 = Jirovetz  | first1 = L.
| last2 = Buchbauer | first2 = G.
| last3 = Stoyanova | first3 = A. S.
| last4 = Georgiev  | first4 = E. V.
| last5 = Damianova | first5 = S. T. 
| title = Composition, Quality Control, and Antimicrobial Activity of the Essential Oil of Long-Time Stored Dill (Anethum graveolens L.) Seeds from Bulgaria
| journal = [[Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry]]
| volume = 51
| issue = 13
| pages = 3854–3857
| year  = 2003
| doi   = 10.1021/jf030004y
| pmid  = 12797755
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[List of Indian spices|''Indian Spices names]]

== References ==
{{Reflist|35em}}

==External links==
{{Commons|Anethum graveolens}}
* [http://www.pfaf.org/user/Plant.aspx?LatinName=Anethum%20graveolens Plants for a Future: ''Anethum graveolens'']
* [http://botanical.com/botanical/mgmh/d/dill--13.html 'A Modern Herbal' (Grieves, 1931)]
* [http://ucjeps.berkeley.edu/cgi-bin/get_JM_treatment.pl?329,335,336 Jepson Manual Treatment]
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2011}}

{{Herbs &amp; spices}}
{{Edible Apiaceae}}
{{Taxonbar|from1=Q26686|from2=Q2542121}}

[[Category:Arab cuisine]]
[[Category:Edible Apiaceae]]
[[Category:Flora of Asia]]
[[Category:Flora of Europe]]
[[Category:Herbs]]
[[Category:Iranian cuisine]]
[[Category:Iraqi cuisine]]
[[Category:Medicinal plants]]
[[Category:Monoamine oxidase inhibitors]]
[[Category:Plants described in 1753]]
[[Category:Plants used in Ayurveda]]
[[Category:Spices]]
[[Category:Apioideae]]</text>
      <sha1>nyd6vjrnw5yc4iqv9nosq7c9mpg087x</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
