  <page>
    <title>The Evil Dead</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9294</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941155750</id>
      <parentid>940518812</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-16T22:45:42Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>DJordan18</username>
        <id>32410730</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{about|the 1981 film|the video game|The Evil Dead (video game)|the franchise|Evil Dead|other uses|The Evil Dead (disambiguation)}}
{{short description|1981 American supernatural horror film by Sam Raimi}}

&lt;!--===========================({{Unsourced additions}})========================================--&gt;
&lt;!--|             DO NOT ADD ANY MORE UNSOURCED ADDITIONS TO THIS ARTICLE.                    |--&gt;
&lt;!--| If you think that your addition might be useful, ensure you have a reliable source.     |--&gt;
&lt;!--| If you don't have a reliable source put it on this article's discussion page first       |--&gt;
&lt;!--|                                                                                          |--&gt;
&lt;!--|           Additions that do not have a reliable source WILL BE DELETED.                 |--&gt;
&lt;!--|                See [[Wikipedia:Citing sources]] for details                              |--&gt;
&lt;!--===========================({{Unsourced additions}})========================================--&gt;
{{Use American English|date=October 2019}}
{{Use mdy dates|date = March 2019}}

{{Infobox film
| name           = The Evil Dead
| image          = Evil dead ver1.jpg
| image_size     = 220px
| alt            = 
| caption        = Original theatrical release poster
| director       = [[Sam Raimi]]
| producer       = [[Robert Tapert]]
| writer         = Sam Raimi
| starring       = {{Plainlist|
* [[Bruce Campbell]]
* [[Ellen Sandweiss]]
* Hal Delrich
* [[Betsy Baker]]
* Theresa Tilly
}}
| music          = [[Joseph LoDuca]]
| cinematography = Tim Philo
| editing        = Edna Ruth Paul
| studio         = [[Renaissance Pictures]]
| distributor    = [[New Line Cinema]]
| released       = {{Film date|1981|10|15|[[Redford Theatre]]|ref1=&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://bloody-disgusting.com/editorials/3410143/35th-anniversary-evil-dead/|title=&quot;Join Us&quot; in Celebrating the 35th Anniversary of ''The Evil Dead''!|last=Thurman|first=Trace|work=[[Bloody Disgusting]]|date=October 15, 2016|accessdate=August 21, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
| runtime        = 85 minutes&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=''THE EVIL DEAD'' (X) (!)|url=https://bbfc.co.uk/releases/evil-dead-3|work=[[British Board of Film Classification]]|date=October 4, 1982|accessdate=March 28, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| country        = United States
| language       = English
| budget         = $350,000–400,000&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://articles.latimes.com/2013/apr/05/entertainment/la-et-mn-evil-dead-remake-movie-reviews-critics-20130404|title='Evil Dead': Blood-soaked remake scares up mixed reviews|last=Gettell|first=Oliver|work=[[Los Angeles Times]]|date=April 5, 2013|accessdate=July 10, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://empireonline.com/reviews/reviewcomplete.asp?FID=132788|title=EMPIRE ESSAY: Evil Dead II|last=Collins|first=Andrew|date=January 1, 2000|work=[[Empire (film magazine)|Empire]]|accessdate=July 10, 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150714194035/http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/reviewcomplete.asp?FID=132788|archive-date=July 14, 2015|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| gross          = $2.7 million&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://boxofficemojo.com/movies/?id=evildead.htm|title=The Evil Dead (1983)|website=[[Box Office Mojo]]|publisher=[[IMDb]]|accessdate=March 28, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://boxofficemojo.com/movies/?page=intl&amp;id=evildead.htm|title=The Evil Dead (1983) – International Box Office Results|website=[[Box Office Mojo]]|publisher=[[IMDb]]|accessdate=March 28, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; or $29.4 million&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.the-numbers.com/movie/Evil-Dead-The#tab=summary|title=The Evil Dead (1983)|work=[[The Numbers (website)|The Numbers]]|accessdate=October 23, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
'''''The Evil Dead''''' is a 1981 American [[supernatural horror film]] written and directed by [[Sam Raimi]] and executive produced by Raimi and [[Bruce Campbell]], who also starred alongside [[Ellen Sandweiss]] and [[Betsy Baker]]. The film focuses on five college students vacationing in an isolated cabin in a remote wooded area. After they find an audio tape that, when played, releases a legion of [[demon]]s and [[spirit]]s, members of the group suffer from [[demonic possession]], leading to increasingly gory mayhem. Raimi and the cast produced the [[short film]] ''[[Within the Woods]]'' as a &quot;prototype&quot; to build the interest of potential investors, which secured US$90,000 to produce ''The Evil Dead''. The film was shot on location in a remote cabin located in [[Morristown, Tennessee]], in a difficult filming process that proved extremely uncomfortable for the cast and crew.

The low-budget horror film attracted the interest of producer [[Irvin Shapiro]], who helped screen the film at the [[1982 Cannes Film Festival]]. Horror author [[Stephen King]] gave a rave review of the film, which helped convince [[New Line Cinema]] to serve as its distributor. It grossed $2.4 million in the US and a total of $2.7 million worldwide. Both early and later critical reception were universally positive and in the years since its release, ''The Evil Dead'' has developed a reputation as one of the most significant [[cult film]]s, cited among the greatest horror films of all time and one of the most successful independent films. ''The Evil Dead'' launched the careers of Campbell and Raimi, who collaborated on several films together, including Raimi's [[Spider-Man in film#Sam Raimi films|''Spider-Man'' trilogy]].

The film spawned a [[Evil Dead (franchise)|media franchise]], beginning with two [[sequel]]s written and directed by Raimi, ''[[Evil Dead II]]'' (1987) and ''[[Army of Darkness]]'' (1992), as well as video games, [[Army of Darkness (comics)|comic books]], and a television series. The film's protagonist [[Ash Williams]] (Campbell) is regarded as a cult icon. The fourth film, serving as a soft reboot and continuation, was titled ''[[Evil Dead (2013 film)|Evil Dead]]'' and was released in 2013. Raimi co-produced the film alongside Campbell and the franchise producer, [[Robert Tapert]]. As with the films, the follow-up television series ''[[Ash vs Evil Dead]]'' was created and produced by [[Sam Raimi|Sam]] and [[Ivan Raimi]], with Campbell also executive producing.

==Plot==
&lt;!-- Per [[WP:FILMPLOT]], plot summaries should be between 400 and 700 words. This one is currently 694 words long. --&gt;
Five [[Michigan State University]] students—[[Ash Williams]], his girlfriend, Linda; Ash's sister, Cheryl; their friend Scott; and his girlfriend Shelly—vacation at an isolated cabin in rural [[Tennessee]]. Approaching the cabin, the group notices the porch swing move on its own but suddenly stop as Scott grabs the doorknob. While Cheryl draws a picture of a clock, the clock stops, and she hears a faint, demonic voice tell her to &quot;Join us&quot;. Her hand becomes possessed, turns pale and draws a picture of a book with a demonic face on its cover. Although shaken, she does not mention the incident.

When the cellar trapdoor flies open during dinner, Shelly, Linda, and Cheryl remain upstairs as Ash and Scott investigate. They find the ''[[Necronomicon#In popular culture|Naturan Demanto]]'', a [[Sumer]]ian version of the Egyptian ''[[Book of the Dead]]'', along with an archaeologist's [[tape recorder]]. Scott and Ash joke around with the items and take them upstairs. Scott plays a tape of [[incantation]]s that resurrect a demonic entity. Cheryl yells for Scott to turn off the tape recorder, and a tree branch breaks one of the cabin's windows. Later that evening, an agitated Cheryl goes into the woods to investigate strange noises. She gets attacked, stripped, pinned to the ground, and raped by [[Demonic possession|demonically possessed]] trees. When she manages to escape and returns to the cabin bruised and anguished, Ash agrees to take her back into town, only to discover that the bridge to the cabin has been destroyed. Cheryl panics as she realizes that they are now trapped and the demonic entity will not let them leave. Back at the cabin, Ash listens to more of the tape, learning that the only way to kill the entity is to dismember a possessed host. As Linda and Shelly play Spades, Cheryl correctly calls out the cards, succumbs to the entity, and levitates. In a raspy, demonic voice, she demands to know why they disturbed her sleep and threatens to kill everyone. After she falls to the floor, the group checks on her; Cheryl stabs Linda in the ankle and throws Ash into a shelf. Scott knocks Cheryl into the cellar and locks her inside.

Everyone fights about what to do. Shelly becomes paranoid upon seeing Cheryl's demonic transformation. She lies down in her room but is drawn to look out of her window, where a demon crashes through and attacks her. Shelly becomes a Deadite and scratches Scott's face. Scott throws her into the fireplace, briefly burning Shelly's face. As she attacks him again, Scott bisects part of her wrist with a knife and then she bites off her own mangled hand. Scott stabs her in the back with a Sumerian dagger, apparently killing her. When she reanimates, Scott dismembers her with an axe and buries the remains. Shaken by the experience, he leaves to find a way back to town. He shortly returns mortally wounded; he dies while warning Ash that the trees will not let them escape alive. When Ash checks on Linda, he is horrified to find that she has become possessed. She attacks him, but he stabs her with a Sumerian dagger. Unwilling to dismember her, he buries her instead. She revives and attacks him, forcing him to decapitate her with a shovel. Her headless body bleeds on his face as it tries to rape him, but he pushes it off and retreats to the cabin.

Back inside, Ash is attacked by Cheryl, who has escaped the cellar, and the reanimated Scott. He shoots Cheryl several times, gouges Scott's eyes out, and pulls out a branch lodged in Scott's stomach, causing him to bleed out. The Deadites attack, bite, and beat Ash with a fire iron. Ash throws the Naturan Demanto into the fireplace, and the Deadites stop their attack. As the book burns, Scott, Cheryl, and the book gruesomely decompose. Demonic hands protrude from both corpses, and Cheryl's decomposed body falls and splatters in front of Ash, leaving him covered in her and Scott's entrails. He hears a voice say &quot;Join Us&quot; but relaxes when it dies away. As day breaks, Ash stumbles outside. Before he can leave, an unseen surviving entity rapidly trails the forest and runs through the cabin, breaking the cabin doors and attacks him from behind.

==Cast==
*[[Bruce Campbell]] as [[Ash Williams]]
*[[Ellen Sandweiss]] as Cheryl Williams
*Hal Delrich as Scott
*[[Betsy Baker]] as Linda
*Theresa Tilly as Shelly

==Production==
[[File:Sam Raimi by Gage Skidmore.jpg|alt=A man sitting next to a microphone placed on a table.|[[Sam Raimi]] directed the short film ''[[Within the Woods]]'' to generate the interest of investors for ''The Evil Dead''. |thumb|right|upright]]

===Background and writing===
Raimi and Campbell grew up together, and have been friends from an early age.&lt;ref name=&quot;early2&quot;&gt;[[#Winston Dixon|Winston Dixon (2010)]], p. 161&lt;/ref&gt; The duo made several low-budget [[Super 8 mm film]] projects together.&lt;ref name=&quot;early&quot;&gt;[[#Campbell|Campbell (2002)]], p. 65&lt;/ref&gt; Several were comedies, including ''[[Clockwork (film)|Clockwork]]'' and ''[[It's Murder!]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;def&quot;&gt;[[#Egan|Egan (2011)]], p. 16&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;writing&quot;/&gt; Shooting a suspense scene in ''It's Murder!'' inspired Raimi to approach a career in the horror genre, and after researching horror cinema at [[drive-in theater]]s, Raimi was set on directing a horror film{{Citation needed|date=May 2019}}. Shooting a short film first to attract the interest of financiers, and use the funds raised to shoot a full-length project.&lt;ref name=&quot;writing&quot;&gt;[[#Campbell|Campbell (2002)]], p. 66&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;becker&quot;&gt;[[#Becker|Becker (2002)]], p. 64&lt;/ref&gt; The [[short film]] that Raimi created was called ''[[Within the Woods]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;proto&quot;&gt;[[#Lamberson|Lamberson (2008)]], p. 84&lt;/ref&gt; Within the Woods was produced for $1,600. For ''The Evil Dead'' Raimi required over $100,000.&lt;ref name=&quot;money&quot;&gt;[[#Campbell|Campbell (2002)]], pp.&amp;nbsp;85–88&lt;/ref&gt;

To generate funds to produce the film, Raimi approached Phil Gillis, a lawyer to one of his friends.&lt;ref name=&quot;money&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;reinforced&quot;/&gt; Raimi showed him ''Within the Woods'', and although Gillis was not impressed by the short film, he offered Raimi legal advice on how to produce ''The Evil Dead''. With his advice in mind, Raimi asked a variety of people for donations, and even eventually &quot;begged&quot; some.&lt;ref name=&quot;money&quot;/&gt; Campbell had to ask several of his own family members, and Raimi asked every individual he thought might be interested.&lt;ref name=&quot;money&quot;/&gt; He eventually raised enough money to produce a full-length film, though not the full amount he originally wanted.&lt;ref name=&quot;money&quot;/&gt;

With enough money to produce the film, Raimi and Campbell set out to make what was then titled ''Book of the Dead'', a name inspired by Raimi's interest in the fiction of [[H. P. Lovecraft]].&lt;ref name=&quot;writing&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;thingstoknow&quot;/&gt;{{Dead link|date=March 2019}} The film was supposed to be a remake of ''Within the Woods'', with higher production values and a full-length running time. Raimi turned 20 just before shooting began, and he considered the project his &quot;[[rite of passage]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;ninety five&quot;&gt;[[#Campbell|Campbell (2002)]], p. 95&lt;/ref&gt;

===Pre-production and casting===
{| class=&quot;infobox&quot; style=&quot;font-size:100%;&quot;
|-
! Actor
! class=&quot;unsortable&quot; |&lt;!--non-semantic mimicry of film credit look --&gt;
! Role &lt;!-- or &quot;Character&quot; --&gt;
|-
| {{sortname|Bruce |Campbell}} 
| ...
| [[Ash Williams|Ash]]
|-
| {{sortname|Ellen|Sandweiss}} 
| ...
| [[List of The Evil Dead characters#Cheryl Williams|Cheryl]]
|-
| [[imdbname:0217822|Hal Delrich]]
| ...
| [[List of The Evil Dead characters#Scotty|Scotty]]
|-
| {{sortname|Betsy |Baker}} 
| ...
| [[List of The Evil Dead characters#Linda|Linda]]
|-
| [[imdbname:0863462|Theresa Tilly]]
| ...
| [[List of The Evil Dead characters#Shelly|Shelly]]
|-
|}
[[File:Betsy Baker, Ellen Sandweiss, and Theresa Tilly.jpg|thumb|[[Betsy Baker]], [[Ellen Sandweiss]], and [[Theresa Tilly]] in 2009]]
Raimi asked for help and assistance from several of his friends and past collaborators to make ''The Evil Dead''.&lt;ref name=&quot;ninety five&quot;/&gt; Campbell was cast as [[Ash Williams]], the main character.&lt;ref name=&quot;EVIL2&quot;&gt;[[#Kenneth Muir|Kenneth Muir (2004)]], pp.&amp;nbsp;23–24&lt;/ref&gt; To acquire more actors for the project, Raimi put an ad in ''[[The Detroit News]]''. [[Betsy Baker]] was one of the actresses who responded, and [[Ellen Sandweiss]], who appeared in ''Within the Woods'', was also cast.&lt;ref name=&quot;ninety five&quot;/&gt; The crew consisted almost entirely of Raimi and Campbell's friends and family. The special make-up effects artist for ''Within the Woods'', [[Tom Sullivan (special effects artist)|Tom Sullivan]], was brought on to compose the effects after expressing a positive reaction to working with Raimi.&lt;ref name=&quot;EVIL2&quot;/&gt; He helped create many of the film's [[foam latex]] and [[fake blood]] effects, and added coffee as an extra ingredient to the traditional fake blood formula of [[corn syrup]] and [[food coloring]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.tested.com/art/movies/462662-how-evil-deads-tom-sullivan-mastered-low-budget-effects/|title=How The Evil Dead's Tom Sullivan Mastered Low-Budget Effects|last=Konow|first=David|date=July 21, 2014|website=Tested.com|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190217220311/https://www.tested.com/art/movies/462662-how-evil-deads-tom-sullivan-mastered-low-budget-effects/|archive-date=February 17, 2019|access-date=February 17, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://medium.com/applaudience/evil-dead-effects-master-tom-sullivan-honored-39568ab07b21|title=&quot;Evil Dead&quot; Effects Master Tom Sullivan Honored|last=Grabowski|first=William|date=January 19, 2017|website=[[Medium (website)|Medium]]|access-date=February 17, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Without any formal assistance from location scouts, the cast had to find filming locations on their own. The crew initially attempted to shoot the film in Raimi's hometown of [[Royal Oak, Michigan]], but instead chose [[Morristown, Tennessee]], as it was the only state that expressed enthusiasm for the project. The crew quickly found a remote cabin located several miles away from any other buildings. During pre-production, the 13 crew members had to stay at the cabin, leading to several people sleeping in the same room. The living conditions were notoriously difficult, with several arguments breaking out between crew members.&lt;ref name=&quot;cabin&quot;/&gt;

Steve Frankel was the only carpenter on set, which made him the art direction's sole contributor.&lt;ref name=&quot;weird&quot;&gt;[[#Campbell|Campbell (2002)]], pp.&amp;nbsp;93–94&lt;/ref&gt; For exterior shots, Frankel had to produce several elaborate props with a circular saw. Otherwise, the cabin mostly remained the way it was found during production. The cabin had no plumbing, but phone lines were connected to it.&lt;ref name=&quot;cabin&quot;&gt;[[#Campbell|Campbell (2002)]], pp.&amp;nbsp;96–98&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Egan|Egan (2011)]], p. 14&lt;/ref&gt;

===Principal photography===
Because of the crew's inexperience, filming was a &quot;comedy of errors&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;errors&quot;/&gt; The first day of filming led to them getting lost in the woods during a scene shot on a bridge.&lt;ref name=&quot;errors&quot;&gt;[[#Campbell|Campbell (2002)]], p. 101&lt;/ref&gt; Several crew members were injured during the shoot, and because of the cabin's remoteness, securing medical assistance was difficult.&lt;ref name=&quot;reinforced2&quot;&gt;[[#Konow|Konow (2012)]], pp.&amp;nbsp;419–422&lt;/ref&gt; One notably gruesome moment on set involved ripping off Baker's eyelashes during removal of her face-mask.&lt;ref name=&quot;weird&quot;/&gt; Because of the low budget, contact lenses as thick as glass had to be applied to the actors to achieve the &quot;demonic eyes&quot; effect.&lt;ref name=&quot;weird&quot;/&gt; The lenses took 10 minutes to apply, and could only be left on for about 15 minutes because eyes could not &quot;breathe&quot; with them applied.&lt;ref name=&quot;weird&quot;/&gt; Campbell later commented that to get the effect of wearing these lenses, they had to put &quot;[[Tupperware]]&quot; over their eyes.&lt;ref name=&quot;weird&quot;/&gt;

Raimi developed a sense of ''[[mise en scène]]'', coming up with ideas for scenes at a fast rate.&lt;ref name=&quot;reinforced&quot;/&gt; He had drawn several crude illustrations to help him break down the flow of scenes. The crew was surprised when Raimi began using [[dutch angle]]s during shots to build atmosphere during scenes.&lt;ref name=&quot;raimi&quot;/&gt; To accommodate Raimi's style of direction, several elaborate, low-budget rigs had to be built, since the crew could not afford a [[camera dolly]]. One involved the &quot;vas-o-cam&quot;, which relied on a mounted camera that was slid down long wooden platforms to create a more fluid sense of motion.&lt;ref name=&quot;raimi&quot;/&gt;

[[File:WW Chicago 2015 - Evil Dead 15 (21037548012).jpg|Sam Raimi's brother [[Ted Raimi]] was the &quot;[[fake shemp]]&quot; in several scenes.|thumb|left|upright]]

A camera trick used to emulate a [[Steadicam]] inexpensively was the &quot;[[shaky camera|shaky cam]]&quot;, which involved mounting the camera to a piece of wood and having two camera operators sprint around the swamp.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tested.com/art/movies/454928-low-budget-camera-tech-sam-raimis-evil-dead/|title=The Low Budget Camera Tech of Sam Raimi's Evil Dead|last=Konow|first=David|date=April 18, 2013|website=Tested.com|accessdate=May 7, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; During scenes involving the unseen force in the woods watching the characters, Raimi had to run through the woods with the makeshift rig, jumping over logs and stones.&lt;ref name=&quot;raimi&quot;/&gt; This often proved difficult due to mist in the swamp.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Kenneth Muir|Kenneth Muir (2004)]], p. 309&lt;/ref&gt; The film's final scene was shot with the camera mounted to a bike, while it was quickly driven through the cabin to create a seamless [[long take]].&lt;ref name=&quot;raimi&quot;&gt;[[#Campbell|Campbell (2002)]], p.&amp;nbsp;102–103&lt;/ref&gt;

Raimi had been a big fan of ''[[The Three Stooges]]'' during his youth, which inspired him to use &quot;[[Fake Shemp]]s&quot; during production.&lt;ref name=&quot;def&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;reinforced&quot;&gt;[[#Konow|Konow (2012)]], pp.&amp;nbsp;412–413&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Kenneth Muir|Kenneth Muir (2004)]], p. 115&lt;/ref&gt; In any scene that required a background shot of a character, he used another actor as a substitute if the original actor was preoccupied.&lt;ref name=&quot;shemp&quot;/&gt; During a [[close-up]] involving Richard DeManicor's hand opening a curtain, Raimi used his own hand in the scene since it was more convenient{{Citation needed|date=May 2019}}. His brother [[Ted Raimi]] was used as a &quot;fake shemp&quot; in many scenes when the original actor was either busy or preoccupied.&lt;ref name=&quot;shemp&quot;&gt;[[#Campbell|Campbell (2002)]], p.&amp;nbsp;111–112&lt;/ref&gt;

Raimi enjoyed &quot;torturing&quot; his actors.&lt;ref name=&quot;ouch&quot;&gt;{{cite video|title=One by One We Will Take You: The Untold Saga of The Evil Dead|type=documentary|location=''The Evil Dead'' Ultimate Edition DVD|year=2007|publisher=Anchor Bay Entertainment}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Kenneth Muir2|Kenneth Muir (2007)]], p. 507&lt;/ref&gt; Raimi believed that to capture pain and anger in his actors, he had to abuse them a little at times, saying, &quot;if everyone was in extreme pain and misery, that would translate into a horror&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;ouch&quot;/&gt; Producer [[Robert Tapert]] agreed with Raimi, commenting that he &quot;enjoyed when an actor bleeds.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;ouch&quot;/&gt; While shooting a scene with Campbell running down a hill, Campbell tripped and injured his leg.&lt;ref name=&quot;torture&quot;/&gt; Raimi enjoyed poking Campbell's injury with a stick he found in the woods. Because of the copious amounts of blood in the film, the crew produced gallons of fake blood with [[Associated British Foods|karo syrup]].&lt;ref name=&quot;reinforced2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;torture&quot;/&gt; It took Campbell hours to remove the sticky substance from himself.&lt;ref name=&quot;torture&quot;/&gt; Several actors had inadvertently been stabbed or thrown into objects during production.&lt;ref name=&quot;ouch&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;torture&quot;/&gt;
During the last few days on set the conditions had become so extreme the crew began burning furniture to stay warm. Since at that point only exterior shots needed to be filmed, they burned nearly every piece of furniture left.&lt;ref name=&quot;furniture&quot;&gt;[[#Campbell|Campbell (2002)]], pp.&amp;nbsp;116–117&lt;/ref&gt; Several actors went days without showering, and because of the freezing conditions, several caught colds and other illnesses. Campbell later described the filming process as nearly &quot;twelve weeks of mirthless exercise in agony&quot;, though he allowed that he did manage to have fun while on set.&lt;ref name=&quot;torture&quot;&gt;[[#Campbell|Campbell (2002)]], pp.&amp;nbsp;107–109&lt;/ref&gt; On January 23, 1980, filming was finished and almost every crew member left the set to return home, with Campbell staying with Raimi.&lt;ref name=&quot;furniture&quot;/&gt; While looking over the footage that had been shot, Raimi discovered that a few [[Pick-up (filmmaking)|pickups]] were required to fill in missing shots. Four days of re-shoots were then done to complete the film.&lt;ref name=&quot;reshot&quot;/&gt; The final moment involved Campbell having &quot;monster-guts&quot; splattered on him in the basement.&lt;ref name=&quot;reshot&quot;&gt;[[#Campbell|Campbell (2002)]], p. 128&lt;/ref&gt;

===Editing===
[[File:COEN Brothers (cannesPH).jpg|alt=Two men in button-up shirts smiling.|Joel Coen ''(pictured right'') of the [[Coen brothers]] helped to edit the film.|thumb|right]]
After the extensive filming process, Raimi had a &quot;mountain of footage&quot; that he had to put together.&lt;ref name=&quot;reinforced2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;editing&quot;/&gt; He chose a Detroit editing association, where he met Edna Paul, to cut the film. Paul's assistant was Joel Coen of the [[Coen brothers]], who helped with the film's editing.&lt;ref name=&quot;editing&quot;&gt;[[#Campbell|Campbell (2002)]], pp.&amp;nbsp;129–132&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;eddie&quot;&gt;[[#Eddie|Eddie (2010)]], p. 15&lt;/ref&gt; Paul edited a majority of the film, although Coen notably edited the shed sequence. Coen had been inspired by Raimi's ''Within the Woods'' and liked the idea of producing a prototype film to help build the interest of investors.&lt;ref name=&quot;eddie&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;pool&quot;/&gt; Joel used the concept to help make ''[[Blood Simple]]'' with his brother Ethan, and he and Raimi became friends following the editing process.&lt;ref name=&quot;thingstoknow&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://blogs.amctv.com/movie-blog/2010/10/evil-dead-facts.php|title=Ten Things You Might Not Know About the Evil Dead Trilogy|author=AMC staff|date=October 28, 2008|website=[[AMC (TV channel)|Filmcritic.com]]|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20111227054237/http://blogs.amctv.com/movie-blog/2010/10/evil-dead-facts.php|archivedate=December 27, 2011|url-status=dead|accessdate=July 12, 2012}} &lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;pool&quot;&gt;[[#Pooley|Pooley (1987)]], p. 44&lt;/ref&gt;

The film's first cut ran at around 117 minutes, which Campbell called an impressive achievement in light of the 65-minute length of the screenplay. The cut scenes were to focus on the main character's lamentation of not being able to save the victims from their deaths, but was edited down to make the film less &quot;grim and depressing&quot; and to be a more marketable 85 minutes.&lt;ref name=&quot;editing&quot;/&gt;  Raimi was inspired by the fact that [[Brian De Palma]] was editing his own film ''[[Blow Out]]'' with [[John Travolta]] at the same sound facility.&lt;ref name=&quot;editing&quot;/&gt; One of the most intricate moments during editing was the [[Stop motion|stop-motion animation]] sequence where the corpses &quot;melted&quot;, which took hours to cut properly.&lt;ref name=&quot;editing&quot;/&gt; The film had unique sounds that required extensive recording from the crew.&lt;ref name=&quot;editing&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;kawin&quot;&gt;[[#Egan|Egan (2011)]], p. 17&lt;/ref&gt; Several sounds were not recorded properly during shooting, which meant the effects had to be redone in the editing rooms. Dead chickens were stabbed to replicate the sounds of mutilated flesh, and Campbell had to scream into a microphone for several hours.&lt;ref name=&quot;editing&quot;/&gt;

Much like ''Within the Woods'', ''The Evil Dead'' needed to be blown up to 35mm, then the industry standard, to be played at movie theaters.&lt;ref name=&quot;editing&quot;/&gt; The relatively large budget made this a much simpler process with ''The Evil Dead'' than it had been with the short film.&lt;ref name=&quot;editing&quot;/&gt;

==Promotion and distribution rights==
[[File:RedfordTheatreMarquee.jpg|alt=View of a movie theater marquee.|thumb|right|''The Evil Dead'' premiered at the [[Redford Theatre]] because Bruce Campbell watched films there as a child.]]
With the film completed, Raimi and the crew decided to celebrate with a &quot;big premiere&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;premiere&quot;/&gt; They chose to screen the film at Detroit's [[Redford Theatre]], which Campbell had often visited as a child.&lt;ref name=&quot;reinforced2&quot;/&gt; Raimi opted to have the most theatrical premiere possible, using custom tickets and wind tracks set in the theater, and ordering ambulances outside the theater to build atmosphere.&lt;ref name=&quot;premiere&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#F. Kawin|F. Kawin (2012)]], p. 13&lt;/ref&gt; The premiere setup was inspired by horror director [[William Castle]], who would often attempt to scare his audiences by using gimmicks. Local turnout for the premiere exceeded the cast's expectations, with a thousand patrons showing up. The audiences responded enthusiastically to the premiere, which led to Raimi's idea of &quot;touring&quot; the film to build hype.&lt;ref name=&quot;premiere&quot;&gt;[[#Campbell|Campbell (2002)]], pp.&amp;nbsp;125–126&lt;/ref&gt;

Raimi showed the film to anyone willing to watch it, booking meetings with distribution agents and anyone with experience in the film industry.&lt;ref name=&quot;casa&quot;&gt;[[#Campbell|Campbell (2002)]], pp.&amp;nbsp;136–137&lt;/ref&gt; Eventually Raimi came across [[Irvin Shapiro]], the man who was responsible for the distribution of [[George A. Romero]]'s ''[[Night of the Living Dead]]'' and other famous horror films.&lt;ref name=&quot;reinforced3&quot;&gt;[[#Konow|Konow (2012)]], pp.&amp;nbsp;422–425&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Warren|Warren (2000)]], pp.&amp;nbsp;125–126&lt;/ref&gt; Upon first viewing the film, he joked that while it &quot;wasn't ''[[Gone with the Wind (film)|Gone with the Wind]]''&quot;, it had commercial potential, and he expressed an interest in distributing it.&lt;ref name=&quot;casa&quot;/&gt; It was his idea not to use the then-title ''Book of the Dead'', because it made the film sound boring. Raimi brainstormed several ideas, eventually going with ''The Evil Dead'', deemed the &quot;least worst&quot; title.&lt;ref name=&quot;casa&quot;/&gt; Shapiro also advised distributing the film worldwide to garner a larger income, though it required a further financial investment by Raimi, who managed to scrape together what little money he had.&lt;ref name=&quot;casa&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Stephen King, Comicon.jpg|alt=Close-up of a man wearing glasses.|thumb|left|upright|[[Stephen King]] cited ''The Evil Dead'' as one of his favorite films, which brought the interest of [[New Line Cinema]].]]
Shapiro was a founder of the [[Cannes Film Festival]], and allowed Raimi to screen the film at the [[1982 Cannes Film Festival|1982 festival]] out of competition.&lt;ref name=&quot;fuckyeah&quot;&gt;[[#Egan|Egan (2011)]], p. 24&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;cannes&quot;/&gt; [[Stephen King]] was present at its screening and gave the film a rave review. ''[[USA Today]]'' released an article about King's favorite horror films; the author cited ''The Evil Dead'' as his fifth favorite film of the genre.&lt;ref name=&quot;cannes&quot;&gt;[[#R. Collings|R. Collings (2008)]], p. 26&lt;/ref&gt; The film severely affected King, who commented that while watching the film at Cannes, he was &quot;registering things [he] had never seen in a movie before&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;gyu&quot;&gt;[[#Egan|Egan (2011)]], p. 20&lt;/ref&gt; He became one of the film's largest supporters during the early efforts to find a distributor, eventually describing it as the &quot;most ferociously original film of the year&quot;, a quote used in the film's promotional pieces.&lt;ref name=&quot;thingstoknow&quot;/&gt;{{Dead link|date=March 2019}}&lt;ref&gt;[[#R. Collings|R. Collings (2007)]], p. 157&lt;/ref&gt; King's comments attracted the interest of critics, who otherwise would likely have dismissed the low-budget thriller.&lt;ref name=&quot;gyu&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;LATIMES&quot;&gt;[[#Campbell|Campbell (2002)]], pp.&amp;nbsp;151–152&lt;/ref&gt;

The film's press attracted the attention of British film distribution agent [[Stephen Woolley]].&lt;ref&gt;[[#Finney|Finney (1997)]], p. 58&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;bannedyo&quot;&gt;[[#Chibnall|Chibnall (2001)]], p. 184&lt;/ref&gt; Though he considered the film a big risk, Woolley decided to take on the job of releasing the film in the United Kingdom.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Finney|Finney (1997)]], p. 55&lt;/ref&gt; The film was promoted in an unconventional manner for a film of its budget, receiving marketing on par with that of larger budget films.&lt;ref name=&quot;LATIMES&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;charming&quot;&gt;[[#Egan|Egan (2011)]], p. 19&lt;/ref&gt; Dozens of promotional pieces, including film posters and trailers, were showcased in the UK, heavy promotion rarely expended on such a low-budget film.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Egan|Egan (2011)]], p. 27&lt;/ref&gt; Woolley was impressed by Raimi, whom he called &quot;charming&quot;, and was an admirer of the film, which led to his taking more risks with the film's promotion than he normally would have.&lt;ref name=&quot;charming&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Newman|Newman (2011)]], p. 38&lt;/ref&gt;

''[[Fangoria]]'' started covering the film in late 1982, writing several articles about the film's long production history.&lt;ref name=&quot;twentyone&quot;&gt;[[#Egan|Egan (2011)]], p. 21&lt;/ref&gt; Early critical reception at the time was very positive, and along with ''Fangoria'', King, and Shapiro's approval, the film generated an impressive amount of interest before its commercial premiere.&lt;ref name=&quot;LATIMES&quot;/&gt; [[New Line Cinema]], one of the distributors interested in the film, negotiated an agreement to distribute it domestically.&lt;ref name=&quot;reinforced3&quot;/&gt; The film had several &quot;sneak previews&quot; before its commercial release, including screenings in New York and Detroit. Audience reception at both screenings was widely enthusiastic, and interest was built for the film to such an extent that wider distribution was planned. New Line Cinema wrote Raimi a check large enough to pay off all the investors, and decided to release the film in a unique manner:&lt;ref name=&quot;reinforced3&quot;/&gt; simultaneously into both cinemas and onto [[VHS]], with substantial domestic promotion.&lt;ref name=&quot;fuckyeah&quot;/&gt;

==Commercial release==
===Theaters===
Because of its large promotional campaign, the film performed above expectations at the box office.&lt;ref name=&quot;fuckyeah&quot;/&gt; It grossed a total of $2,400,000 in the United States, nearly eight times its production budget.&lt;ref name=&quot;BOM&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://boxofficemojo.com/movies/?id=evildead.htm|title=The Evil Dead|website=[[Box Office Mojo]]|publisher=[[IMDb]]|accessdate=May 19, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the initial domestic gross was described as &quot;disappointing.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;stacks&quot;/&gt; It opened in 15 theaters and grossed $108,000 in its opening weekend.&lt;ref name=&quot;stacks&quot;/&gt; Word of mouth later spread, and the film became a &quot;[[sleeper hit]]&quot;, making over $600,000 domestically and nearly $2 million overseas, for a worldwide gross of approximately $2.7 million.&lt;ref name=&quot;stacks&quot;/&gt; In its first week of video release in 1983 two years later, the film made £100,000 in the UK. It quickly became that week's bestselling video release, and later became the year's bestselling video in the UK, out-grossing large-budget horror releases such as ''[[The Shining (film)|The Shining]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;LATIMES&quot;/&gt; Its impressive European performance was chalked up to its heavy promotion there and the more open-minded nature of European audiences.&lt;ref name=&quot;stacks&quot;&gt;[[#Egan|Egan (2011)]], pp.&amp;nbsp;26–28&lt;/ref&gt;

===Rating===
The film's release was met with controversy. Raimi made the film as gruesome as possible with neither interest in nor fear of censorship, which led to the film's receiving an [[X rating]] and being named a &quot;[[video nasty]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;nasty&quot;/&gt; Films with this label were quite violent and disturbing, and the rating was often held by [[pornographic film|pornographic]] and other X-rated films.&lt;ref name=&quot;nasty&quot;&gt;[[#Hantke|Hantke (2004)]] p. 160&lt;/ref&gt; While ''The Evil Dead'' was not pornographic in nature, it was considered one of the most violent films of its time, and censors had issues with the film's content, which impacted some of its commercial potential.&lt;ref name=&quot;stacks&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Kerekes|Kerekes (2000)]]&lt;/ref&gt; The film was called the &quot;number one nasty&quot; in a nod to its status as both a nasty and the year's bestselling video release.&lt;ref name=&quot;bannedyo&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Hantke|Hantke (2004)]] p. 162&lt;/ref&gt; Writer Bruce Kawin described ''The Evil Dead'' as one of the most notorious [[splatter film]]s of its day, along with ''[[Cannibal Holocaust]]'' and ''[[I Spit on Your Grave]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;kawin&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Staiger|Staiger (2005)]], p. 125&lt;/ref&gt; The film was and is still [[List of banned films|banned]] either theatrically or on video in some countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.independent.co.uk/arts-entertainment/films/features/banned-the-most-controversial-films-1768299.html?action=gallery&amp;ino=10|title=BANNED: The most controversial films|last=Davis|first=Laura|date=October 5, 2010|work=[[The Independent]]|accessdate=August 11, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Xavier|Xavier (2004)]], p. 195&lt;/ref&gt;

===Home video release===
The first VHS release of ''The Evil Dead'' was by [[Thorn EMI]] in 1983, and Thorn's successor company [[HBO]] &lt;small&gt;([[WarnerMedia]])&lt;/small&gt; / [[The Cannon Group, Inc.|Cannon]] &lt;small&gt;([[Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer|MGM]])&lt;/small&gt; Video later repackaged the film. Congress Video, a company notable for [[public domain]] films, issued its version in 1989.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The gorehound's guide to splatter films of the 1980s|author=Stine, Scott Aaron|publisher=McFarland|year=2003|page=114|isbn=0-7864-1532-0|quote=The Evil Dead (ABE; 85m); The Evil Dead (CNG; 89(85)m); The Evil Dead (EMI; 85m)}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Bowker's Complete Video Directory 1994|publisher=[[R.R. Bowker]]|page=266|year=1994|isbn=978-0-8352-3391-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The resurgence of ''The Evil Dead'' in the home-video market came through two companies that restored the film from its negatives and issued special editions in 1998: [[Anchor Bay Entertainment]] on VHS, and Elite Entertainment on [[laserdisc]]. Anchor Bay was responsible for the film's first [[DVD]] release in 1999, and between them, Elite and Anchor Bay have released six different DVD versions of ''The Evil Dead'', most notably the 2002 &quot;Book Of The Dead&quot; edition, packaged in a latex replica of the ''Necronomicon'' sculpted by Tom Sullivan and the 2007 three disc &quot;Ultimate Edition&quot; which contained the widescreen and original full frame versions of the movie.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Egan|Egan (2011)]], p. 52-3&lt;/ref&gt; The film's high-definition debut was in a 2010 [[Blu-ray]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://ign.com/articles/2010/09/03/the-evil-dead-blu-ray-review|title=The Evil Dead Blu-ray Review|last=White|first=Cindy|date=September 3, 2010|website=[[IGN]]|accessdate=May 7, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Lionsgate Films]] released a 4K [[Ultra HD Blu-ray]] edition of ''The Evil Dead'' on October 9, 2018.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://bloody-disgusting.com/home-video/3514073/lionsgate-gives-evil-dead-4k-treatment-october/|title=Lionsgate Gives 'The Evil Dead' the 4K Treatment This October!|last1=Miska|first1=Brad|website=[[Bloody Disgusting]]|accessdate=August 8, 2018|date=August 6, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.blu-ray.com/movies/The-Evil-Dead-4K-Blu-ray/211492/|title=The Evil Dead 4K Blu-ray|website=Blu-ray.com|accessdate=August 8, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Reception==

===Early reception===
Upon its release, contemporary critical opinion was largely positive.&lt;ref name=&quot;reinforced3&quot;/&gt; Bob Martin, editor of ''Fangoria'', reviewed the film before its formal premiere and proclaimed that it &quot;might be the exception to the usual run of low-budget horror films&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;twentyone&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Martin|first=Bob|date=November 1982|title=Evil Dead|url=https://archive.org/details/Fangoria_023_c2c_1982_Evil_Dead_scan_by_SproutHatesWatermarks_S/page/n19|journal=[[Fangoria]]|volume=|issue=23|pages=20–23|via=[[Internet Archive]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; He followed up on this praise after the film's premiere, stating: &quot;Since I started editing this magazine, I have not seen ''any'' new film that I could recommend to our readers with more confidence that it would be loved, embraced and hailed as a new milestone in graphic horror&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Martin|first=Bob|date=May 1983|title=The FX of Evil Dead|url=https://archive.org/details/Fangoria_027/page/n21|journal=[[Fangoria]]|volume=|issue=27|pages=19–22|via=[[Internet Archive]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ''[[Los Angeles Times]]'' called the film an &quot;instant classic&quot;, proclaiming it as &quot;probably the grisliest well-made movie ever.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;LATIMES&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;bloody&quot;/&gt; In a 1982 review, staff from the [[trade magazine]] ''[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]'' wrote that the film &quot;emerges as the ''[[ne plus ultra]]'' of low-budget gore and shock effect&quot;, commenting that the &quot;powerful&quot; and inventive camerawork was key to creating a sense of dread.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://variety.com/review/VE1117790757?refcatid=31|title=The Evil Dead|date=December 31, 1982|work=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120104083311/https://variety.com/review/VE1117790757?refcatid=31|archive-date=January 4, 2012|url-status=dead|accessdate=January 31, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

British press for the film was positive; [[Kim Newman]] of ''[[Monthly Film Bulletin]]'', Richard Cook of ''[[NME]]'', and Julian Petley of ''Film and Filming'' all gave the film good reviews during its early release.&lt;ref name=&quot;bloody&quot;&gt;[[#Egan|Egan (2011)]], p. 22&lt;/ref&gt; Petley and Cook compared the film to other contemporary horror films, writing that the film expressed more imagination and &quot;youthful enthusiasm&quot; than an average horror film.&lt;ref name=&quot;bloody&quot;/&gt; Cook described the camera work by Raimi as &quot;audacious&quot;, stating that the film's visceral nature was greatly helped by the style of direction.&lt;ref name=&quot;bloody&quot;/&gt; Woolley, Newman, and several critics complimented the film for its unexpected use of [[black comedy]], which elevated the film above its genre's potential trappings.&lt;ref name=&quot;bloody&quot;/&gt; All three critics compared the film to the surrealistic work of [[Georges Franju]] and [[Jean Cocteau]], noting the cinephilic references to Cocteau's film ''[[Orpheus (film)|Orpheus]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;bloody&quot;/&gt; Writer Lynn Schofield Clark in his novel ''From Angels to Aliens'' compared the film to better-known horror films such as ''[[The Exorcist (film)|The Exorcist]]'' and ''[[The Omen]]'', citing it as a key supernatural thriller.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Schofield Clark|Schofield Clark (2005)]], pp.&amp;nbsp;26–28&lt;/ref&gt;

===Later reception===
The [[review aggregator]] website [[Rotten Tomatoes]] reports a 95% approval rating and an average rating of 8.04/10 based on an aggregation of 59 reviews. It summarizes the film: &quot;This classic low budget horror film combines just the right amount of gore and black humor, giving ''The Evil Dead'' an equal amount of thrills and laughs.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;RottenTomatoes&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://rottentomatoes.com/m/the-evil-dead/|title=The Evil Dead|website=[[Rotten Tomatoes]]|publisher=[[Fandango (company)|Fandango]]|accessdate=June 28, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Empire (film magazine)|Empire]]'' magazine stated the film's &quot;reputation was deserved&quot;, writing that the film was impressive considering its low budget and the cast's inexperience. He commented that the film successfully blended the &quot;bizarre&quot; combination of ''Night of the Living Dead'', ''[[The Texas Chain Saw Massacre]]'' and ''The Three Stooges''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://empireonline.com/reviews/reviewcomplete.asp?DVDID=7240|title=The Evil Dead|author=Empire Staff|date=September 24, 2007|work=[[Empire (film magazine)|Empire]]|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121106053201/https://empireonline.com/reviews/reviewcomplete.asp?DVDID=7240|archive-date=November 6, 2012|url-status=dead|accessdate=January 31, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; A reviewer for [[Film4]] rated ''The Evil Dead'' four-and-a-half stars out of five, musing that the film was &quot;energetic, original and icky&quot; and concluding that Raimi's &quot;splat-stick debut is a tight little horror classic that deserves its cult reputation, despite the best efforts of the censors.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.film4.com/reviews/1983/the-evil-dead|title=The Evil Dead review|work=[[Film4]]|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100830204151/http://www.film4.com/reviews/1983/the-evil-dead|archive-date=August 30, 2010|url-status=dead|access-date=October 11, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''[[Slant Magazine]]''{{'}}s Ed Gonzales compared the film to [[Dario Argento]]'s work, citing Raimi's &quot;unnerving wide angle work&quot; as an important factor to the film's atmosphere. He mused that Raimi possessed an &quot;almost unreal ability to suggest the presence of intangible evil&quot;, which was what prevented the movie from being &quot;B-movie schlock&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Gonzales, Ed (March 6, 2002). [https://slantmagazine.com/film/review/the-evil-dead/112 Review: ''The Evil Dead'']. ''[[Slant Magazine]]''. Retrieved on November 20, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; [[BBC]] critic Martyn Glanville awarded the film four stars out of five, writing that for Raimi, it served as a better debut film than Tobe Hooper's ''The Texas Chainsaw Massacre'' or [[Wes Craven]]'s ''[[The Last House on the Left (1972 film)|The Last House on the Left]]''. Glanville noted that other than the &quot;ill-advised trees-that-rape scene&quot;, the film is &quot;one of the great modern horror films, and even more impressive when one considers its modest production values.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/films/2001/03/02/the_evil_dead_1982_review.shtml|title=The Evil Dead (1982)|last=Glanville|first=Martyn|date=March 5, 2001|website=|publisher=[[BBC]]|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20010305142803/http://www.bbc.co.uk/films/2001/03/02/the_evil_dead_1982_review.shtml|archive-date=March 5, 2001|url-status=dead|accessdate=July 12, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[AMC (TV channel)|Filmcritic.com]]'s [[Christopher Null]] gave the film the same rating as Glanville, writing that &quot;Raimi's biggest grossout is schlock horror done the right way&quot; and comparing it to Romero's ''Night of the Living Dead'' in its ability to create stark atmosphere.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://movies.amctv.com/movie/1983/The+Evil+Dead|title=The Evil Dead (1983)|last=Null|first=Christopher|date=January 1, 2001|website=Movies.AMCTV.com|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120818042106/http://movies.amctv.com/movie/1983/The+Evil+Dead|archive-date=August 18, 2012|url-status=dead|access-date=July 12, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Chicago Reader]]'' writer Pat Graham commented that the film featured several &quot;clever&quot; turns on the standard horror formula, adding that Raimi's &quot;anything-for-an-effect enthusiasm pays off in lots of formally inventive bits.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chicagoreader.com/chicago/the-evil-dead/Film?oid=1736507|title=The Evil Dead|last=Graham|first=Pat|date=January 1, 2001|work=[[Chicago Reader]]|publisher=Wrapports|accessdate=July 12, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Time Out (magazine)|Time Out]]'' critic Stephen Garrett, referred to the make-up effects in the climax as &quot;amazing&quot;, and commented that although the film was light on character development, it &quot;blends comic fantasy&quot; with &quot;atmospheric horror ... to impressive effect&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://timeout.com/film/reviews/64080/the_evil_dead.html|title=The Evil Dead (1981)|last=Graham|first=Pat|date=January 26, 2005|work=[[Time Out (magazine)|Time Out]]|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141106005731/https://timeout.com/film/reviews/64080/the_evil_dead.html|archive-date=November 6, 2014|url-status=dead|accessdate=July 12, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The same site later cited the film as the 41st greatest horror movie ever made.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://timeout.com/london/feature/2420/100-best-horror-films-the-list/6|title=The 100 best horror films|last=Adams|first=Derek|last2=Calhoun|first2=Dave|work=[[Time Out (magazine)|Time Out]]|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120629120148/https://timeout.com/london/feature/2420/100-best-horror-films-the-list/6|archive-date=June 29, 2012|url-status=dead|access-date=July 12, 2012|last3=Clarke|first3=Cath|last4=Cohen|first4=Sarah|last5=Floyd|first5=Nigel|last6=Huddleston|first6=Tom}}&lt;/ref&gt; Phelim O'Neill of ''[[The Guardian]]'' combined ''The Evil Dead'' and its sequel ''[[Evil Dead II]]'' and listed them as the 23rd best horror film ever made, announcing that the former film &quot;stands above its mostly forgotten peers in the 80s horror boom.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;O'Neill, Phelim (October 22, 2010). [https://www.theguardian.com/film/2010/oct/22/evil-dead-raimi-horror The Evil Dead/Evil Dead II: No 23 best horror film of all time]. ''[[The Guardian]]''. Retrieved on November 19, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Don Summer, in his book ''Horror Movie Freak'', and writer Kate Egan have both cited the film as a horror classic.&lt;ref name=&quot;stacks&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;extra&quot;&gt;[[#Summer|Summer (2007)]], p. 165&lt;/ref&gt;

J.C. Maçek III of ''[[PopMatters]]'' said, &quot;What is unquestionable is that the Raimis and their pals created a monster in ''The Evil Dead''. It started as a disastrous failure to obtain a big break with a too long, too perilous shoot (note Campbell's changing hairstyle in the various scenes of the one-day plot). The film went through name changes and bannings only to survive as not only 'the ultimate experience in grueling horror' but as an oft-imitated and cashed-in-on classic, with 30 years of positive reviews to prove it.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;PM&quot;/&gt;

==Aftermath==
[[File:Bruce Campbell .jpg|alt=A man sitting at a table with a VHS on the table.|[[Bruce Campbell]] at a fan convention, signing a [[VHS]] copy of ''The Evil Dead''. |thumb|right|upright]]
While ''The Evil Dead'' received favorable critical comment when it was initially released, it failed to establish Raimi's reputation.&lt;ref name=&quot;bloody&quot;/&gt; It was, however, a box-office success, which led to Campbell and Raimi teaming up again for the release of another movie.&lt;ref name=&quot;flop&quot;&gt;[[#Campbell|Campbell (2002)]], pp.&amp;nbsp;161–163&lt;/ref&gt; [[The Coen Brothers|Joel Coen]] and his brother [[The Coen Brothers|Ethan]] had collaborated as directors and released the film ''Blood Simple'', to critical acclaim.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Žižek|Žižek (2000)]], p. 111&lt;/ref&gt; According to Campbell, Ethan, then an accountant, expressed surprise when the duo succeeded.&lt;ref name=&quot;flop&quot;/&gt; The Coen brothers and Raimi collaborated on a screenplay, which was released shortly after ''The Evil Dead''. The film, ''[[Crimewave]]'', was a box-office failure.&lt;ref name=&quot;flop&quot;/&gt; The film's production was a &quot;disaster&quot; according to Campbell, who stated that &quot;missteps&quot; like ''Crimewave'' usually lead to the end of a director's career.&lt;ref name=&quot;flop2&quot;&gt;[[#Campbell|Campbell (2002)]], p. 171&lt;/ref&gt; Other people involved with the film expressed similar disappointment with the project.&lt;ref name=&quot;flop&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Paul|Paul (2007)]], p. 121&lt;/ref&gt; Fortunately, Raimi had the studio support to make a sequel to ''The Evil Dead'', which he initially decided to make out of desperation.&lt;ref name=&quot;flop2&quot;/&gt;

===Sequels===
''[[Evil Dead II]]'' was filmed and released in 1987, and was also a box-office success.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Kenneth Muir|Kenneth Muir (2004)]], p. 101&lt;/ref&gt; A second sequel was released in 1993, ''[[Army of Darkness]]''. Campbell returned as the lead character Ash Williams in both films.&lt;ref name=&quot;sequel&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;reinforced4&quot;/&gt; At that time, Raimi had become a successful director, attracting Hollywood's interest.&lt;ref name=&quot;sequel&quot;&gt;[[#Campbell|Campbell (2002)]], p. 207&lt;/ref&gt; His 1990 [[superhero film]] ''[[Darkman]]'' was another box-office success, which led to an increased budget for ''Army of Darkness''.&lt;ref name=&quot;reinforced4&quot;&gt;[[#Konow|Konow (2012)]], pp.&amp;nbsp;429–434&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Harris|Harris (2002)]], pp.&amp;nbsp;51–52&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Kenneth Muir|Kenneth Muir (2004)]], p. 138&lt;/ref&gt; ''Army of Darkness'' had 22.8 times the budget of the original ''Evil Dead'', though it was not considered to be a box-office success like its two predecessors.&lt;ref name=&quot;sequel&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Campbell|Campbell (2002)]], pp.&amp;nbsp;217–218&lt;/ref&gt; ''Evil Dead II'' received general acclaim from critics and is often considered to be better than the original, and ''Army of Darkness'' received mostly positive reviews.&lt;ref name=&quot;reinforced4&quot;/&gt; The series has often attracted attention because each sequel featured more comedic qualities than the last, progressing into &quot;weirder&quot; territory with each film.&lt;ref name=&quot;reinforced4&quot;/&gt;

Unofficial sequels were also made in Italy—where the film was known as ''La Casa'' (&quot;The House&quot;)—by [[Joe D'Amato]]'s Filmirage. In 1988, D'Amato produced two films labeled as sequels to ''Evil Dead II'', [[Umberto Lenzi]]'s ''[[Ghosthouse (film)|Ghosthouse]]'' (''La Casa 3''), and ''[[Witchery (film)|Witchery]]'' (''La Casa 4''), starring [[Linda Blair]] and [[David Hasselhoff]]. In 1990, D'Amato produced his final ''La Casa'' film, ''[[Beyond Darkness]]'' (''La Casa 5'').&lt;ref name=&quot;PM&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Erotismo, orrore e pornografia secondo Joe D'Amato|language=Italian|page=168|first=Gordiano|last=Lupi|publisher=Mondo Ignoto|year=2004|isbn=88-89084-49-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[House II: The Second Story|House II]]'' was reissued in Italy as ''La Casa 6'', and ''[[The Horror Show]]'' was then released in Italy as ''La Casa 7''.&lt;ref name=&quot;PM&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://popmatters.com/pm/column/170551-books-of-the-dead-the-followers-and-clones-of-the-evil-dead/|title=Books of the Dead: The Followers and Clones of 'The Evil Dead'|last=Maçek III|first=J. C.|date=April 26, 2013|work=[[PopMatters]]|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Legacy===
''The Evil Dead'' and its sequels have become one of the largest [[cult film]] [[Film trilogy|trilogies]] in history.&lt;ref name=&quot;stacks&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Campbell|Campbell (2002)]], p. 319&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;cult&quot;/&gt; David Lavery, in his book ''The Essential Cult TV Reader'', surmised that Campbell's &quot;career is a practical guide to becoming a cult idol&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;cult&quot;&gt;[[#Lavery|Lavery (2009)]], pp.&amp;nbsp;217–218&lt;/ref&gt; The film launched the careers of Raimi and Campbell, who have since collaborated frequently.&lt;ref name=&quot;spiderman&quot;/&gt; Raimi has worked with Campbell in virtually all of his films since, and Campbell has appeared in cameo roles in all three of Raimi's [[Spider-Man in film|''Spider-Man'' films]],&lt;ref name=&quot;spiderman&quot;&gt;[[#Campbell|Campbell (2002)]], p. 337&lt;/ref&gt; (as well as a very brief appearance at the end of ''Darkman''), which have become some of the highest-grossing films in history.&lt;ref name=&quot;spiderman&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;BOMINT&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://boxofficemojo.com/movies/?page=intl&amp;id=spiderman.htm|title=Spider-Man (2002) – International Box Office Results|website=[[Box Office Mojo]]|publisher=[[IMDb]]|accessdate=April 8, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Though it has often been considered an odd choice for Raimi—a director known for his violent horror films—to direct a family-friendly franchise, the hiring was mostly inspired by Raimi's passion for comic books as a kid.&lt;ref name=&quot;spiderman&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;HBO&quot;&gt;{{cite video | title = [[HBO]] Making-Of ''[[Spider-Man (2002 film)|Spider-Man]]'' | medium = DVD | publisher = Sony |date = 2002}}&lt;/ref&gt; Raimi returned to the horror-comedy genre in 2009 with ''[[Drag Me to Hell]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20090603/REVIEWS/906079997/1001|title='Drag Me to Hell' Review|last=Ebert|first=Roger|authorlink=Roger Ebert|date=June 3, 2009|work=[[RogerEbert.com]]|accessdate=June 28, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Critics have often compared Campbell's later performances to his role in ''Evil Dead'', which has been called his defining role.&lt;ref name=&quot;EVIL&quot;&gt;[[#Kenneth Muir|Kenneth Muir (2004)]], p. 112&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;BLEND&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://cinemablend.com/dvdnews/FlixWorthy-Celebrates-Ash-Wednesday-With-Best-Streaming-Bruce-Campbell-30581.html|title=FlixWorthy Celebrates Ash Wednesday With The Best Of Streaming Bruce Campbell|last=Wharton|first=David|date=March 9, 2011|work=Cinema Blend|accessdate=November 28, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Campbell's performance as Ash has been compared to roles ranging from his performance of [[Elvis Presley]] in the film ''[[Bubba Ho-tep]]'' to the bigamous demon in ''[[The X-Files]]'' episode &quot;[[Terms of Endearment (The X-Files)|Terms of Endearment]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;sixth&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ca.ign.com/articles/2008/07/18/top-10-x-files-guest-stars?page=3|title=Top 10 X-Files Guest Stars|last=Seghers|first=Christine|date=July 17, 2008|work=[[IGN]]|accessdate=August 11, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/films/2004/09/20/bubba_ho_tep_2004_review.shtml|title=Bubba Ho-Tep (2004)|last=Russell|first=Jamie|date=October 4, 2001|website=[[BBC]]|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120502172623/http://www.bbc.co.uk/films/2004/09/20/bubba_ho_tep_2004_review.shtml|archive-date=May 2, 2012|url-status=dead|accessdate=July 12, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Campbell's fan base gradually developed after the release of ''Evil Dead II'' and his short-lived series ''[[The Adventures of Brisco County, Jr.]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;fan&quot;/&gt; He is a regular favorite at most fan conventions and often draws sold-out auditoriums at his public appearances.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Lowry|Lowry (1995)]], pp.19–21&lt;/ref&gt; ''The Evil Dead'' developed a substantial cult following throughout the years, and has often been cited as a defining cult classic.&lt;ref name=&quot;stacks&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;fan&quot;&gt;[[#Campbell|Campbell (2002)]], pp.&amp;nbsp;245–248&lt;/ref&gt;

''The Evil Dead'' has spawned a media empire. A video game adaptation [[The Evil Dead (video game)|of the same name]] was for the [[Commodore 64]] in 1984, as was a trilogy of survival horror games in the 1990s and early 2000s: ''[[Evil Dead: Hail to the King]]'', ''[[Evil Dead: A Fistful of Boomstick]]'' and ''[[Evil Dead: Regeneration]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;retro&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |title=Horror Movie Licenses |journal=[[Retro Gamer]] |author=Staff |page=71 |issue=1 |date=January 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ted Raimi did voices for the trilogy, and Campbell returned as the voice of Ash. The character Ash became the main character of a [[Army of Darkness (comics)|comic book franchise]].&lt;ref name=&quot;what&quot;&gt;[http://forum.newsarama.com/showthread.php?t=125014 WW: Chicago – ''Freddy vs. Jason vs. Ash'' Coming in November] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070925035550/http://forum.newsarama.com/showthread.php?t=125014|date=September 25, 2007|title=}}, August 12, 2007, [[Newsarama]]&lt;/ref&gt; Ash has fought both [[Freddy Krueger]] and [[Jason Voorhees]] in the ''[[Freddy vs. Jason vs. Ash]]'' series, [[Herbert West]] in ''Army of Darkness vs. [[Re-Animator (film series)|Re-Animator]]'', zombie versions of the [[Marvel Comics]] superheroes in ''[[Marvel Zombies vs. The Army of Darkness]]'', and has even saved the life of a [[Barack Obama in comics|fictional]] [[Barack Obama]] in ''[[Army of Darkness (comics)#Army of Darkness: Ash Saves Obama (#1-4)|Army of Darkness: Ash Saves Obama]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://splashpage.mtv.com/2009/05/27/army-of-darkness-ash-saves-obama-artist-todd-nauck-on-spider-man-barack-celebrity-team-ups/|title='Army Of Darkness: Ash Saves Obama' Artist Todd Nauck On Spider-Man, Barack &amp; Celebrity Team-Ups|last=Phegley|first=Kiel|date=May 27, 2009|website=[[MTV]]|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120509071212/http://splashpage.mtv.com/2009/05/27/army-of-darkness-ash-saves-obama-artist-todd-nauck-on-spider-man-barack-celebrity-team-ups/|archive-date=May 9, 2012|url-status=dead|accessdate=July 12, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://marvel.com/news/story/922/marvel_zombies_vs_army_of_darkness_1_goes_back_to_press|title=Marvel Zombies vs. Army of Darkness #1 Goes Back to Press|date=March 27, 2007|website=[[Marvel Comics]]|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120910224439/http://marvel.com/news/story/922/marvel_zombies_vs_army_of_darkness_1_goes_back_to_press|archive-date=September 10, 2012|url-status=dead|accessdate=July 12, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In January 2008, [[Dark Horse Comics]] began releasing a four-part monthly comic book [[Limited series (comics)|mini-series]], written by [[Mark Verheiden]] and drawn by [[John Bolton (illustrator)|John Bolton]], based on ''The Evil Dead''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.heroesassemble.com/the-evil-dead-1-movie-adaptation-dark-horse-comics-1606-p.asp|title=The Evil Dead #1 Movie Adaptation Dark Horse Comics|website=HeroesAssemble.com|accessdate=July 12, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The film has also inspired a [[Broadway musical|stage musical]], ''[[Evil Dead: The Musical]]'', which was produced with the permission of Raimi and Campbell. The musical has run on and off since its inception in 2003.&lt;ref name=&quot;HoboTrashCan&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hobotrashcan.com/hangingaround/evildead.php|title=Hanging Around&amp;nbsp;... Evil Dead: The Musical|last=Murphy|first=Joel|date=November 2006|work=HoboTrashcan.com|accessdate=July 18, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A [[Evil Dead (2013 film)|remake of the film]] was released in 2013, directed by Fede Alvarez and produced by Raimi and Campbell. It features actress [[Jane Levy]] as the main character, with Ash not appearing.&lt;ref name=&quot;evil&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=https://dreadcentral.com/news/54953/jane-levy-talks-evil-dead-remake|title=Jane Levy Talks Evil Dead Remake|last=Barton|first=Steve|date=April 24, 2012|newspaper=[[Dread Central]]|accessdate=April 24, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://deadline.com/2012/02/jane-levy-is-new-star-of-evil-dead-remake/|title=Jane Levy Is New Star Of 'Evil Dead' Remake|last=Fleming Jr|first=Mike|date=February 3, 2012|website=[[Deadline Hollywood]]|publisher=[[Penske Media Corporation]]|accessdate=March 19, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Campbell does make a brief, uncredited [[cameo appearance]] at the end of the film in a short [[post-credits scene]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://insidemovies.ew.com/2013/03/09/evil-dead-sequel/|title='Evil Dead' director reveals sequel plans|last=Hibberd|first=James|date=March 9, 2013|work=[[Entertainment Weekly]]|publisher=[[Meredith Corporation]]|accessdate=April 28, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2015, an ongoing television continuation of the films called ''[[Ash vs Evil Dead]]'' premiered on the Starz Network. Sam Raimi wrote and directed the [[Television pilot|pilot]], and served as an executive producer; Campbell reprised his role as Ash during the series' three-season run.

After the film was released, many people began to trespass onto the filming location in Morristown. In 1982, the cabin was burned down by drunken trespassers. Although the cabin is now gone, the chimney remains, which many people now take stones from when they trespass onto the location.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.bookofthedead.ws/website/the_evil_dead_locations.html|title=Locations|website=www.bookofthedead.ws|access-date=January 20, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
===Notes===
{{Reflist}}

===Bibliography===
{{refbegin|2}}
*{{cite book
| year = 2002
| last = Campbell
| first = Bruce
| title = If Chins Could Kill: Confessions of a B Movie Actor
| publisher = L.A. Weekly Books
| isbn = 978-0-312-29145-7
| ref = Campbell}}
*{{cite book
| year = 2008
| last = Lamberson
| first = Gregory
| title = Cheap Scares!: Low Budget Horror Filmmakers Share Their Secrets
| publisher = McFarland
| isbn = 978-0-7864-3706-1
| ref = Lamberson}}
*{{cite book
| year = 2010
| last = Winston Dixon
| first = Wheeler
| title = A History of Horror 
| publisher = Rutgers University Press
| isbn = 978-0-8135-4796-1
| ref = Lamberson}}
*{{cite book
| year = 2006
| last = Becker
| first = Josh
| title = The Complete Guide to Low-Budget Feature Filmmaking
| publisher = Point Blank
| isbn = 978-0-8095-5690-8
| ref = Becker}}
*{{Cite book
| year = 2004
| first = John
| last = Kenneth Muir
| title = The Unseen Force: the Films of Sam Raimi
| publisher = Applause Theatre &amp; Cinema Books
| isbn = 978-1-55783-607-6
| ref = Kenneth Muir
| url-access = registration
| url = https://archive.org/details/unseenforcefi00muir
}}
*{{Cite book
| year = 2010
| first = Robson
| last = Eddie
| title = Coen Brothers (Virgin Film)
| publisher = Virgin Books
| isbn = 978-0-7535-1268-5
| ref = Eddie}}
*{{Cite book
| year = 2007
| first = John
| last = Kenneth Muir
| title = Horror Films of the 1980s
| publisher = Virgin Books
| isbn = 978-0-7864-2821-2
| ref = Kenneth Muir2}}
*{{Cite book
| year = 1987
| first = Eric
| last = Pooley
| title = Warped in America: The Dark Visions of Joel and Ethan Coen
| publisher = [[New York (magazine)|New York]] 
| isbn = 978-0-7864-2821-2
| ref = Pooley}}
*{{cite book
| year = 2000
| first = Bill
| last = Warren
| title = The Evil Dead Companion
| publisher = Titan Books
| isbn= 1-84023-187-4
| ref = Warren}}
*{{cite book
| year = 2008
| first = Michael 
| last = R. Collings
| title = The Films of Stephen King: From Carrie to Secret Window
| publisher = Palgrave Macmillan
| isbn= 978-0-230-60131-4
| ref = R. Collings}}
*{{cite book
| year = 2011
| first = Kate 
| last = Egan
| title = The Evil Dead
| publisher = Wallflower Press
| isbn= 978-1-906660-34-5
| ref = Egan}}
*{{cite book
| year = 2007
| first = Michael
| last = R Collings
| title = Scaring Us to Death: The Impact of Stephen King on Popular Culture
| publisher = Borgo Press
| isbn= 978-0-930261-37-5
| ref = R Collings}}
*{{cite book
| year = 2000
| first = David
| last = Kerekes
| title = See No Evil: Banned Films and Video Controversy
| publisher = Critical Vision
| isbn= 978-1-900486-10-1
| ref = Kerekes}}
*{{cite book
| year = 2004
| first = Steffen 
| last = Hantke
| title = University Press of Mississippi
| publisher = Critical Vision
| isbn= 978-1-57806-692-6
| ref = Hantke}}
*{{cite book
| year = 2004
| first = Mendik 
| last = Xavier
| title = Alternative Europe: Eurotrash and Exploitation Cinema Since 1945
| publisher = Wallflower Press
| isbn= 978-1-903364-93-2
| ref = Hantke}}
*{{cite book
| year = 2012
| first = Bruce
| last = F. Kawin
| title = Horror and the Horror Film (New Perspectives on World Cinema)
| publisher = Anthem Press
| isbn= 978-0-85728-450-1
| ref = Hantke}}
*{{cite book
| year = 2005
| first = Janet
| last = Staiger
| title = Media Reception Studies 
| publisher = [[NYU Press]]
| isbn= 978-0-8147-8135-7
| ref = Staiger}}
*{{cite book
| year = 1997
| first = Angus
| last = Finney
| title = The Egos Have Landed: Rise and Fall of Palace Pictures
| publisher = Arrow Books Ltd
| isbn= 978-0-7493-1946-5
| ref = Finney}}
*{{cite book
| year = 2001
| first = Steve
| last = Chibnall
| title = British Horror Cinema
| publisher = Routledge
| isbn= 978-0-415-23004-9
| ref = Chibnall}}
*{{cite book
| year = 2011
| first = Kim
| last = Newman
| title = Nightmare Movies: Horror on Screen Since the 1960s
| publisher = Bloomsbury Publishing
| isbn= 978-1-4088-0503-9
| ref = Newman}}
*{{cite book
| year = 2005
| first = Lynn
| last = Schofield Clark
| title = From Angels to Aliens: Teenagers, the Media, and the Supernatural
| publisher = [[Oxford University Press]]
| isbn= 978-0-19-530023-9
| ref = Schofield Clark}}
*{{cite book
| year = 2007
| first = Don
| last = Summer
| title = Horror Movie Freak
| publisher = Unknown Binding
| asin = B004434G7M
| ref = Summer}}
*{{cite book
| year = 2000
| first = Slavoj
| last = Žižek
| title = The Ticklish Subject: The Absent Centre of Political Ontology
| publisher = Verso
| isbn = 978-1-85984-291-1
| ref = Žižek}}
*{{cite book
| year = 2007
| first = Louis 
| last = Paul
| title = Tales from the Cult Film Trenches: Interviews with 36 Actors from Horror, Science Fiction and Exploitation Cinema
| publisher = McFarland &amp; Company
| isbn =  978-0-7864-2994-3
| ref = Paul}}
*{{cite book
| year = 2002
| first = J. P. Harris
| last = Harris
| title = Time Capsule: Reviews of horror, science fiction and fantasy films and TV shows from 1987 to 1991
| publisher = iUniverse
| isbn =  978-0-595-21336-8
| ref = Harris}}
*{{cite book
| year = 2009
| first = David 
| last = Lavery
| title = The Essential Cult TV Reader (Essential Readers in Contemporary Media)
| publisher = The University Press of Kentucky
| isbn =  978-0-8131-2568-8
| ref = Lavery}}
*{{Cite book
|year = 1995
|first = Brian
|last = Lowry
|title = The Truth is Out There: The Official Guide to the X-Files
|publisher = Harper Prism 5
|isbn = 978-0-06-105330-6
| ref = Lowry}}
*{{Cite book
|year = 2008
|first = Glenn
|last = Kay
|title = Zombie Movies: The Ultimate Guide
|publisher = Chicago Review Press
|isbn = 978-1-55652-770-8
| ref = Kay}}
*{{Cite book
|year = 2008
|first = David Konow
|last = Konow
|title = Reel Terror: The Scary, Bloody, Gory, Hundred-Year History of Classic Horror Films
|publisher = [[St. Martin's Press]]
|isbn = 978-0-312-66883-9
| ref = Kay}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{wikiquote}}
* ''[http://www.deadites.net/the-evil-dead-films/the-evil-dead/ The Evil Dead]'' at Deadites Online.
* {{IMDb title|0083907}}
* {{allmovie title}}
* {{mojo title|evildead}}
* {{Rotten Tomatoes|the-evil-dead}}

{{Evil Dead}}
{{Sam Raimi}}
{{Renaissance Pictures}}
{{Good article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Evil Dead. The}}
[[Category:The Evil Dead (franchise) films|1 1981]]
[[Category:1981 films]]
[[Category:1981 horror films]]
[[Category:1980s horror thriller films]]
[[Category:1980s independent films]]
[[Category:1980s teen horror films]]
[[Category:American films]]
[[Category:American haunted house films]]
[[Category:American splatter films]]
[[Category:American supernatural horror films]]
[[Category:American teen horror films]]
[[Category:Archaeology in popular culture]]
[[Category:Censored films]]
[[Category:Dark fantasy films]]
[[Category:Demons in film]]
[[Category:Directorial debut films]]
[[Category:English-language films]]
[[Category:Features based on short films]]
[[Category:Films directed by Sam Raimi]]
[[Category:Films set in Tennessee]]
[[Category:Films shot in Michigan]]
[[Category:Films shot in Tennessee]]
[[Category:Films using stop-motion animation]]
[[Category:Films about rape]]
[[Category:Renaissance Pictures productions]]
[[Category:Films with screenplays by Sam Raimi]]
[[Category:Films about spirit possession]]
[[Category:Films shot in Detroit]]
[[Category:Video nasties]]
[[Category:American exploitation films]]</text>
      <sha1>jh2f1kfll7ha3lafpyt3b7uvoot5cj6</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
