  <page>
    <title>Compact disc</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6429</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943322495</id>
      <parentid>940748987</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-03-01T06:04:42Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bluelink 1 book for [[Wikipedia:Verifiability|verifiability]]. [goog]) #IABot (v2.0) ([[User:GreenC bot|GreenC bot]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Optical disc for storage and playback of digital audio}}
{{Redirect|CD}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=April 2015}}
{{Use American English|date=December 2019}}

{{Infobox storage medium
| name          = Compact disc
| logo          = Compact Disc wordmark.svg
| logo_size     = 150px
| image         = OD Compact disc.svg
| caption       = The readable surface of a compact disc includes a spiral track wound tightly enough to cause light to [[diffraction grating|diffract]] into a full [[visible spectrum]].
| type          = [[Optical disc]]
| encoding      = Various
| capacity      = Typically up to 700 [[Mebibyte|MiB]] (up to 80 minutes audio)
| read          = 780 [[Nanometre|nm]] wavelength ([[infrared]] and [[red]] edge) semiconductor laser, 1200 [[Kibibit|Kibit]]/s (1×)
| write         = 780 [[Nanometre|nm]] wavelength ([[infrared]] and [[red]] edge) semiconductor laser in recordable formats CD-R and CD-RW, pressed mold in readonly formats
| released      = {{start date and age|1982|10|1|df=yes}} (Japan)&lt;br /&gt;{{start date and age|1983|3|df=yes}} (Europe and North America)
| standard      = [[Rainbow Books]]
| owner         = [[Philips]], [[Sony]]
| use           = Audio and data storage
| extended from = [[LaserDisc]]
| extended to   = [[CD-RW]]&lt;br/&gt;[[DVD]]
}}
{{Optical disc authoring}}

'''Compact disc''' ('''CD''') is a [[Digital media|digital]] [[optical disc]] [[data storage device|data storage]] format that was co-developed by [[Philips]] and [[Sony]] and released in 1982. The format was originally developed to store and play only sound recordings ([[CD-DA]]) but was later adapted for storage of data ([[CD-ROM]]). Several other formats were further derived from these, including write-once audio and data storage ([[CD-R]]), rewritable media ([[CD-RW]]), Video Compact Disc ([[VCD]]), Super Video Compact Disc ([[SVCD]]), [[Photo CD]], PictureCD, Compact Disc-Interactive ([[CD-i]]), and [[Enhanced Music CD]]. The first commercially available audio [[CD player]], the [[Sony CDP-101]], was released October 1982 in [[Japan]].

Standard CDs have a diameter of {{convert|120|mm|in}} and can hold up to about 80 minutes of uncompressed audio or about 700&amp;nbsp;[[MiB]] of data. The [[Mini CD]] has various diameters ranging from {{convert|60|to|80|mm|in}}; they are sometimes used for CD singles, storing up to 24 minutes of audio, or delivering [[device driver]]s.

At the time of the technology's introduction in 1982, a CD could store much more data than a [[personal computer]] [[hard drive]], which would typically hold 10 MB. By 2010, hard drives commonly offered as much storage space as a thousand CDs, while their prices had plummeted to commodity level. In 2004, worldwide sales of audio CDs, CD-ROMs and CD-Rs reached about 30 billion discs. By 2007, 200 billion CDs had been sold worldwide.&lt;ref name=&quot;AutoMR-1&quot; /&gt;

From the early 2000s, CDs were increasingly being replaced by other forms of digital storage and distribution, with the result that by 2010 the number of audio CDs being sold in the U.S. had dropped about 50 percent from their peak; however, they remained one of the primary distribution methods for the [[music industry]].&lt;ref name=&quot;AutoMR-2&quot; /&gt;  In 2014, revenues from digital music services matched those from physical format sales for the first time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=IFPI publishes Digital Music Report 2015|url=http://www.ifpi.org/news/Global-digital-music-revenues-match-physical-format-sales-for-first-time|access-date=1 July 2016|date=14 April 2015|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150414194629/http://www.ifpi.org/news/Global-digital-music-revenues-match-physical-format-sales-for-first-time|archivedate=14 April 2015|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
American inventor [[James Russell (inventor)|James T. Russell]] has been credited with inventing the first system to record digital information on an optical [[transparency and translucency|transparent]] [[foil (metal)|foil]] that is lit from behind by a high-power halogen lamp.&lt;ref&gt;{{US patent|3,501,586}} Analog to digital to optical photographic recording and playback system, March 1970.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{US patent|3,795,902}} Method and apparatus for synchronizing photographic records of digital information, March 1974.&lt;/ref&gt; Russell's patent application was filed in 1966, and he was granted a patent in 1970. Following litigation, Sony and Philips licensed Russell's patents (then held by a Canadian company, Optical Recording Corp.) in the 1980s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |newspaper=The Seattle Times |url=http://seattletimes.com/html/businesstechnology/2002103322_cdman29.html |author=Brier Dudley |title=Scientist's invention was let go for a song |date=29 November 2004 |access-date=24 July 2014 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140810225444/http://seattletimes.com/html/businesstechnology/2002103322_cdman29.html |archivedate=10 August 2014 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release |date=2000 |publisher=Reed College public affairs office |title=Inventor and physicist James Russell '53 will receive Vollum Award at Reed's convocation |access-date=24 July 2014 |url=http://reed.edu/news_center/press_releases/2000-2001/288.html |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131009170700/http://www.reed.edu/news_center/press_releases/2000-2001/288.html |archivedate=9 October 2013 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://web.mit.edu/invent/iow/russell.html |title=Inventor of the Week - James T. Russell - The Compact Disc |date=December 1999 |publisher=[[MIT]] |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20030417162935/http://web.mit.edu/invent/iow/russell.html |archivedate=17 April 2003 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The compact disc is an evolution of [[LaserDisc]] technology, where a focused [[laser]] beam
is used that enables the high information density required for high-quality digital audio signals.
Prototypes were developed by [[Philips]] and [[Sony]] independently in the late 1970s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The History of the CD|url=https://www.philips.com/a-w/research/technologies/cd/beginning.html|publisher=Philips Research|access-date=7 June 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although originally dismissed by [[Philips Research]] management as a trivial pursuit,&lt;ref name=&quot;Immink2&quot; /&gt; the CD became the primary focus for Philips as the [[LaserDisc]] format struggled.&lt;ref name=&quot;AndItsEnd&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Straw|first=Will|date=2009|title=The Music CD and Its Ends|url=|journal=Design and Culture|volume=1|issue=1|doi=|pmid=|access-date=|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1979, Sony and Philips set up a joint task force of engineers to design a new digital audio disc. After a year of experimentation and discussion, the ''[[Rainbow Books|Red Book]]'' [[Compact Disc Digital Audio|CD-DA]] standard was published in 1980. After their commercial release in 1982, compact discs and their players were extremely popular. Despite costing up to $1,000, over 400,000 CD players were sold in the United States between 1983 and 1984.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.spin.com/1985/05/compact-discs-sound-of-the-future/|title=Compact Discs: Sound of the Future|first=Edward|last=Rasen|work=Spin|access-date=9 January 2016|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20151216064105/http://www.spin.com/1985/05/compact-discs-sound-of-the-future/|archivedate=16 December 2015|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; By 1988, CD sales in the United States surpassed those of vinyl LPs, and by 1992 CD sales surpassed those of prerecorded music cassette tapes.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=|title=CD Unit Sales Pass Cassettes, Majors Say|last=Billboard|first=|date=March 1992|work=Billboard|access-date=|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=|title=Have Compact Disks Become Too Much of a Good Thing?|last=Kozinn|first=Allan|date=December 1988|work=The New York Times|access-date=|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The success of the compact disc has been credited to the cooperation between [[Philips]] and [[Sony]], which together agreed upon and developed compatible hardware. The unified design of the compact disc allowed consumers to purchase any disc or player from any company, and allowed the CD to dominate the at-home music market unchallenged.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite AV media|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_Tx6TYnPat8|title=Introducing the amazing Compact Disc (1982)|date=10 June 2015|publisher=Australian Broadcasting Corporation|access-date=9 January 2016|via=YouTube|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20151123170700/https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_Tx6TYnPat8|archivedate=23 November 2015|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Digital audio laser-disc prototypes ===
In 1974, Lou Ottens, director of the audio division of [[Philips]], started a small group with the aim to develop an analog&lt;ref name=&quot;Immink&quot; /&gt; optical audio disc with a diameter of {{cvt|20|cm}} and a sound quality superior to that of the vinyl record.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.laweekly.com/music/why-cds-may-actually-sound-better-than-vinyl-5352162 Why CDs may actually sound better than vinyl] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160409132701/http://www.laweekly.com/music/why-cds-may-actually-sound-better-than-vinyl-5352162 |date=9 April 2016 }},
Chris Kornelis, 27 January 2015&lt;/ref&gt; However, due to the unsatisfactory performance of the analog format, two Philips research engineers recommended a digital format in March 1974.&lt;ref name=&quot;Immink&quot; /&gt; In 1977, Philips then established a laboratory with the mission of creating a digital audio disc. The diameter of Philips's prototype compact disc was set at {{cvt|11.5|cm}}, the diagonal of an audio cassette.&lt;ref name=&quot;Immink&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=peek /&gt;

[[Heitaro Nakajima]], who developed an early digital audio recorder within Japan's national public broadcasting organization [[NHK]] in 1970, became general manager of [[Sony]]'s audio department in 1971. His team developed a digital [[PCM adaptor]] audio tape recorder using a [[Betamax]] video recorder in 1973. After this, in 1974 the leap to storing digital audio on an optical disc was easily made.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=https://books.google.com/books?id=kw0EAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA68 | title=Heitaro Nakajima | work=Billboard | date=8 January 2000 | access-date=4 November 2014 | author=McClure, Steve | pages=68 | url-status=live | archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150319065246/http://books.google.com/books?id=kw0EAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA68 | archivedate=19 March 2015 | df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Sony]] first publicly demonstrated an optical digital audio disc in September 1976. A year later, in September 1977, Sony showed the press a {{cvt|30|cm}} disc that could play 60 minutes of digital audio (44,100&amp;nbsp;Hz sampling rate and 16-bit resolution) using [[Run-length limited|MFM]] modulation.&lt;ref name=&quot;SonyHistorical&quot; /&gt; In September 1978, the company demonstrated an optical digital audio disc with a 150-minute playing time, 44,056&amp;nbsp;Hz sampling rate, 16-bit linear resolution, and [[Cross-interleaved Reed-Solomon coding|cross-interleaved]] [[error correction]] code—specifications similar to those later settled upon for the standard compact disc format in 1980. Technical details of Sony's digital audio disc were presented during the 62nd [[Audio Engineering Society|AES]] Convention, held on 13–16 March 1979, in [[Brussels]].&lt;ref name=&quot;SonyHistorical&quot; /&gt; Sony's AES technical paper was published on 1 March 1979. A week later, on 8 March, Philips publicly demonstrated a prototype of an optical digital audio disc at a press conference called &quot;Philips Introduce Compact Disc&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC6950933&quot; /&gt; in [[Eindhoven]], [[Netherlands]].&lt;ref name=&quot;PhilipsHistorical&quot; /&gt;

=== Collaboration and standardization ===
[[File:schouhamerimmink.jpg|thumb|upright|Dutch inventor and Philips chief engineer [[Kees Schouhamer Immink]] was part of the team that produced the standard compact disc in 1980]]
Sony executive [[Norio Ohga]], later CEO and chairman of Sony, and [[Heitaro Nakajima]] were convinced of the format's commercial potential and pushed further development despite widespread skepticism.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ohgaobituary&quot; /&gt;

As a result, in 1979, Sony and Philips set up a joint task force of engineers to design a new digital audio disc. Led by engineers [[Kees Schouhamer Immink]] and [[Toshitada Doi]], the research pushed forward [[laser]] and [[optical disc]] technology.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC6950933&quot; /&gt; After a year of experimentation and discussion, the task force produced the ''[[Rainbow Books|Red Book]]'' [[Compact Disc Digital Audio|CD-DA]] standard. First published in 1980, the standard was formally adopted by the [[International Electrotechnical Commission|IEC]] as an international standard in 1987, with various amendments becoming part of the standard in 1996.

Philips coined the term ''compact disc'' in line with another audio product, the [[Compact Cassette]],&lt;ref name=peek /&gt; and contributed the general [[manufacturing]] [[Industrial process|process]], based on video LaserDisc technology. Philips also contributed [[eight-to-fourteen modulation]] (EFM), which offers a certain resilience to defects such as scratches and fingerprints, while Sony contributed the [[error-correction]] method, [[Cross-Interleaved Reed-Solomon Coding|CIRC]].

The ''Compact Disc Story'',&lt;ref name=&quot;Immink&quot; /&gt; told by a former member of the task force, gives background information on the many technical decisions made, including the choice of the sampling frequency, playing time, and disc diameter. The task force consisted of around four to eight persons,&lt;ref name=&quot;Immink2&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Knopper&quot; /&gt; though according to Philips, the compact disc was &quot;invented collectively by a large group of people working as a team.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;PhilDoss&quot; /&gt;

=== Initial launch and adoption ===
Philips established the Polydor Pressing Operations plant in [[Langenhagen]] near [[Hannover]], [[Germany]], and quickly passed a series of milestones.
* The first ''test pressing'' was of a recording of [[Richard Strauss]]'s ''[[An Alpine Symphony|Eine Alpensinfonie]]'' (''An Alpine Symphony'') played by the [[Berlin Philharmonic]] and conducted by [[Herbert von Karajan]], who had been enlisted as an ambassador for the format in 1979.&lt;ref name=&quot;Karajan&quot; /&gt;
* The first ''public demonstration'' was on the [[BBC]] television programme ''[[Tomorrow's World]]'' in 1981, when the [[Bee Gees]]' album ''[[Living Eyes (Bee Gees album)|Living Eyes]]'' (1981) was played.&lt;ref name=&quot;AutoMR-4&quot; /&gt;
* The first ''commercial'' compact disc was produced on 17 August 1982, a 1979 recording of Chopin waltzes by [[Claudio Arrau]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.chonday.com/16551/decbucdkl3/|title=Debut of the Compact Disc|date=2015-08-14|website=www.chonday.com|language=en-US|access-date=2019-02-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The first 50 titles were ''released'' in Japan on 1 October 1982,&lt;ref name=&quot;AutoMR-6&quot; /&gt; the very first of which was a re-release of the [[Billy Joel]] album ''[[52nd Street (album)|52nd Street]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ultimateclassicrock.com/the-first-compact-disc-released/|title=How Billy Joel's '52nd Street' Became the First Compact Disc released|first=Jeff|last=Giles|work=[[Ultimate Classic Rock]]|publisher=[[Townsquare Media|Townsquare Media, LLC]]|date=October 1, 2012|accessdate=October 13, 2017|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170706021629/http://ultimateclassicrock.com/the-first-compact-disc-released/|archivedate=6 July 2017|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The first CD played on BBC Radio was in October 1982 on BBC Radio Scotland (Jimmy Mack programme, Followed by Ken Bruce and Eddie Mair all BBC Scotland), with the first CD ''played'' on UK independent radio station shortly after (Radio Forth, Jay Crawford Show). The CD was [[Dire Straits]] album ''[[Love Over Gold]]''.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.hificorner.co.uk {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171004211808/http://www.hificorner.co.uk/ |date=4 October 2017 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
The Japanese launch was followed in March 1983 by the introduction of CD players and discs to Europe&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newscenter.philips.com/main/standard/about/news/press/20070816_25th_anniversary_cd.wpd &quot;Philips celebrates 25th anniversay of the Compact Disc&quot;] {{webarchive|url=https://wayback.archive-it.org/all/20150817154431/http://www.newscenter.philips.com/main/standard/about/news/press/20070816_25th_anniversary_cd.wpd |date=17 August 2015 }}, Philips Media Release, 16 August 2007. Retrieved 6 October 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; and North America (where CBS Records released sixteen titles).&lt;ref name=&quot;G&amp;M 1983-03-05&quot;&gt;{{cite news
 | last      = Kaptainis
 | first     = Arthur
 | title     = Sampling the latest sound: should last a lifetime
 | newspaper = The Globe and Mail
 | date      = 5 March 1983
 | location  = Toronto
 | page      = E11
}}&lt;/ref&gt; This 1983 event is often seen as the &quot;Big Bang&quot;{{By whom|date=October 2017}} of the digital audio revolution. The new audio disc was enthusiastically received, especially in the early-adopting [[European classical music|classical music]] and [[audiophile]] communities, and its handling quality received particular praise. As the price of players gradually came down, and with the introduction of the portable [[Discman]] the CD began to gain popularity in the larger popular and rock music markets. With the rise in CD sales, pre-recorded [[cassette tape]] sales began to decline in the late 1980s; CD sales overtook cassette sales in the early 1990s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Record and prerecorded tape stores|publisher=Gale Encyclopedia of American Industries|year=2005|url=http://www.answers.com/topic/record-and-prerecorded-tape-stores|accessdate=20 September 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Harlow |first1=Oliva |title=When Did the CD Replace the Cassette Tape? |url=https://southtree.com/blogs/artifact/when-did-the-cd-replace-the-cassette-tape |website=artifact |accessdate=13 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The first artist to sell a million copies on CD was [[Dire Straits]], with their 1985 album ''[[Brothers in Arms (album)|Brothers in Arms]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;AutoMR-7&quot; /&gt; One of the first CD markets was devoted to reissuing popular music whose commercial potential was already proven. The first major artist to have their entire catalog converted to CD was [[David Bowie]], whose first fourteen studio albums of (then) sixteen were made available by [[RCA Records]] in February 1985, along with four greatest hits albums; his fifteenth and sixteenth albums had already been issued on CD by [[EMI Records]] in 1983 and 1984, respectively.&lt;ref name=&quot;AutoMR-8&quot; /&gt; On February 26, 1987, the first four UK albums by [[The Beatles]] were released in mono on compact disc.&lt;ref name=&quot;BeatlesCD&quot; /&gt; In 1988, 400 million CDs were manufactured by 50 pressing plants around the world.&lt;ref name=&quot;AutoMR-9&quot; /&gt;

=== Further development and decline ===
[[File:Sony CD Walkman D-E330 (cropped).jpg|thumb|Sony CD Walkman D-E330]]
The CD was planned to be the successor of the [[vinyl record]] for playing music, rather than primarily as a data storage medium. From its origins as a musical format, CDs have grown to encompass other applications. In 1983, following the CD's introduction, [[Kees Schouhamer Immink|Immink]] and [[Joseph Braat|Braat]] presented the first experiments with erasable compact discs during the 73rd [[Audio Engineering Society|AES]] Convention.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal 
|journal=J. Audio Eng. Soc.
|volume=32 
|date=1984
|title=Experiments Toward an Erasable Compact Disc
|author=K. Schouhamer Immink and J. Braat
|url=https://www.researchgate.net/publication/237764745
|pages=531–538
|accessdate=2018-02-02
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In June 1985, the computer-readable [[CD-ROM]] (read-only memory) and, in 1990, [[CD-R]]ecordable were introduced, also developed by both Sony and Philips.&lt;ref name=&quot;AutoMR-10&quot; /&gt; Recordable CDs were a new alternative to tape for recording music and copying music albums without defects introduced in compression used in other digital recording methods. Other newer video formats such as [[DVD]] and [[Blu-ray]] use the same physical geometry as CD, and most DVD and Blu-ray players are [[backward compatible]] with audio CD.

U.S. CD sales peaked in 2000.&lt;ref name=&quot;statista&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last1=Richter |first1=Felix |title=The Rise and Fall of the Compact Disc |url=https://www.statista.com/chart/12950/cd-sales-in-the-us/ |website=Statista |accessdate=13 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; By the early 2000s, the CD player had largely replaced the [[Compact Cassette|audio cassette]] player as standard equipment in new automobiles, with 2010 being the final model year for any car in the United States to have a factory-equipped cassette player.&lt;ref name=&quot;nyt20120718&quot; /&gt;  With the increasing popularity of portable digital audio players, such as mobile phones, and solid state music storage, CD players are being phased out of automobiles in favor of [[minijack]] auxiliary inputs, wired connection to USB devices and wireless [[Bluetooth]] connection.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |title=As Digital Content Moves into Cars, CD Players Begin to Move Out. |work=Journal of Transportation |date=November 8, 2008 |url=https://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-189276198.html |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20161008194548/https://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-189276198.html |archivedate=8 October 2016 |df=dmy-all |access-date=24 August 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Meanwhile, with the advent and popularity of [[Digital distribution|Internet-based distribution]] of files in [[Lossy compression|lossily-compressed]] [[audio format]]s such as [[MP3]], sales of CDs began to decline in the 2000s. For example, between 2000 and 2008, despite overall growth in music sales and one anomalous year of increase, major-label CD sales declined overall by 20 percent,&lt;ref name=&quot;AutoMR-11&quot; /&gt; although independent and DIY music sales may be tracking better according to figures released 30 March 2009, and CDs still continue to sell greatly.&lt;ref name=&quot;AutoMR-12&quot; /&gt;  As of 2012, CDs and DVDs made up only 34 percent of music sales in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tokyotimes.com/buying-cds-continues-to-be-a-tradition-in-japan/|title=Buying CDs continues to be a tradition in Japan - Tokyo Times|date=23 August 2013|access-date=30 December 2016|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20161220150903/http://www.tokyotimes.com/buying-cds-continues-to-be-a-tradition-in-japan/|archivedate=20 December 2016|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;  {{As of|2015|alt=By 2015}}, only 24 percent of music in the United States was purchased on physical media, ⅔ of this consisting of CDs;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://riaa.com/media/238E8AC7-3810-A95C-44DC-B6DEB46A3C6E.pdf|title=News and Notes on 2015 Mid-Year RIAA Shipment and Revenue Statistics|last=Friedlander|first=Joshua P.|year=2015|website=|publisher=Recording Industry Association of America|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150930135150/http://riaa.com/media/238E8AC7-3810-A95C-44DC-B6DEB46A3C6E.pdf|archive-date=30 September 2015|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; however, in the same year in Japan, over 80 percent of music was bought on CDs and other physical formats.&lt;ref&gt;Sisaro, Ben.  ''New York Times'' 11 June 2015:  {{cite web|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2015/06/12/business/media/line-music-a-new-streaming-service-aims-at-japanese-market.html?_r=0|title=Music Streaming Service Aims at Japan, Where CD Is Still King|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20171020191923/https://www.nytimes.com/2015/06/12/business/media/line-music-a-new-streaming-service-aims-at-japanese-market.html?_r=0|archivedate=20 October 2017|url-status=live|accessdate=2017-08-26|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2018, U.S. CD sales were 52 million units — less than 6% of the peak sales volume in 2000.&lt;ref name=&quot;statista&quot;/&gt;

Despite the rapidly declining sales year-over-year, the pervasiveness of the technology remained for a time, with companies placing CDs in pharmacies, supermarkets, and filling station convenience stores targeting buyers least able to use Internet-based distribution.&lt;ref name=&quot;AndItsEnd&quot; /&gt; In 2018 [[Best Buy]] announced plans to decrease their focus on CD sales, however, while continuing to sell records, sales of which are growing during the [[vinyl revival]].&lt;ref name=&quot;bestverge&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.theverge.com/2018/2/6/16973538/bestbuy-target-cd-sales-vinyl-cassette|title=Best Buy will stop selling CDs as digital music revenue continues to grow|first=Thuy|last=Ong|date=February 6, 2018|accessdate=February 6, 2018|website=[[The Verge]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.forbes.com/sites/bobbyowsinski/2018/07/07/best-buy-cd-sales/amp/|title=Best Buy, Winding Down CD Sales, Pounds Another Nail Into The Format's Coffin|first=Bobby|last=Owsinski|date=July 7, 2018|work=Forbes}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://fortune.com/2018/07/02/best-buy-ends-cd-sales/|title=End of a Era: Best Buy Significantly Cuts Back on CDs|author=Chris Morris|date=July 2, 2018|work=Fortune}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Awards and accolades ===
Sony and Philips received praise for the development of the compact disc from professional organizations. These awards include
* Technical [[Grammy Award]] for Sony and Philips, 1998.&lt;ref name=grammy /&gt;
* [[IEEE]] Milestone award, 2009, for Philips only with the citation: &quot;On 8 March 1979, N.V. Philips' Gloeilampenfabrieken demonstrated for the international press a Compact Disc Audio Player. The demonstration showed that it is possible by using digital optical recording and playback to reproduce audio signals with superb stereo quality. This research at Philips established the technical standard for digital optical recording systems.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;IEEE_CD_Milestone&quot; /&gt;

== Physical details ==
{{Refimprove section|date=May 2016|talk=Numbers in the Physical Details section}}
[[File:CD layers.svg|thumb|Diagram of CD layers. {{ordered list |list_style_type=upper-alpha
    |1=&lt;!--A--&gt;A polycarbonate disc layer has the data encoded by using bumps.
    |2=&lt;!--B--&gt;A shiny layer reflects the laser.
    |3=&lt;!--C--&gt;A layer of lacquer protects the shiny layer.
    |4=&lt;!--D--&gt;Artwork is [[Screen printing|screen printed]] on the top of the disc.
    |5=&lt;!--E--&gt;A laser beam reads the CD and is reflected back to a sensor, which converts it into electronic data
}}]]

A CD is made from {{convert|1.2|mm|in}} thick, [[polycarbonate]] plastic and weighs 15–20 grams.&lt;ref name=&quot;AutoMR-13&quot; /&gt;{{better source|date=May 2016}} From the center outward, components are: the center spindle hole (15&amp;nbsp;mm), the first-transition area (clamping ring), the clamping area (stacking ring), the second-transition area (mirror band), the program (data) area, and the rim. The inner program area occupies a radius from 25 to 58&amp;nbsp;mm.

A thin layer of aluminum or, more rarely, [[Gold compact disc|gold]] is applied to the surface, making it reflective. The metal is protected by a film of lacquer normally [[spin coated]] directly on the reflective layer. The label is printed on the lacquer layer, usually by [[screen printing]] or [[offset printing]].

CD data is represented as tiny indentations known as ''pits'', encoded in a spiral track moulded into the top of the polycarbonate layer. The areas between pits are known as ''lands''. Each pit is approximately 100&amp;nbsp;[[Nanometre|nm]] deep by 500&amp;nbsp;nm wide, and varies from 850&amp;nbsp;nm to 3.5&amp;nbsp;[[Micrometre|µm]] in length.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.laesieworks.com/digicom/Storage_CD.html |title=Compact Disc|access-date=6 May 2016 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160512100137/http://www.laesieworks.com/digicom/Storage_CD.html |archivedate=12 May 2016 |df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; The distance between the tracks (the ''pitch'') is 1.6&amp;nbsp;µm.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.multimediadirector.com/help/technology/downloads/tech_docs/cdintroduction.pdf |title=Introduction to CD and CD-ROM |last=Sharpless |first=Graham |date=July 2003 |publisher=Deluxe Global Media Services Ltd|access-date=3 May 2016 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160309135812/http://www.multimediadirector.com/help/technology/downloads/tech_docs/cdintroduction.pdf |archivedate=9 March 2016 |df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;IEC908&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=https://webstore.iec.ch/publication/3885 |title=IEC 60908 Audio recording - Compact disc digital audio system |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160506194944/https://webstore.iec.ch/publication/3885 |archivedate=6 May 2016 |df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;IEC10149&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=https://webstore.iec.ch/publication/9362 |title=ISO/IEC 10149 Information technology -- Data interchange on read-only 120 mm optical data disks (CD-ROM) |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160506194949/https://webstore.iec.ch/publication/9362 |archivedate=6 May 2016|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

When playing an audio CD, a motor within the CD player spins the disc to a scanning velocity of 1.2–1.4&amp;nbsp;m/s ([[constant linear velocity]])&amp;nbsp;– equivalent to approximately 500&amp;nbsp;RPM at the inside of the disc, and approximately 200&amp;nbsp;RPM at the outside edge. The track on the CD begins at the inside and spirals outward so a disc played from beginning to end slows its rotation rate during playback.

[[File:Comparison CD DVD HDDVD BD.svg|thumb|upright=1.35|left|Comparison of various optical storage media&lt;!-- parameters: track pitch (p), pit width (w) and minimum length (l), and laser spot size (⌀) and wavelength (λ). --&gt;]]
The program area is 86.05&amp;nbsp;cm&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; and the length of the recordable spiral is {{no wrap|86.05 cm&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; / 1.6 µm {{=}}}} {{no wrap|5.38 km.}} With a scanning speed of 1.2&amp;nbsp;m/s, the playing time is 74 minutes, or 650&amp;nbsp;MiB of data on a CD-ROM. A disc with data packed slightly more densely is tolerated by most players (though some old ones fail). Using a linear velocity of 1.2&amp;nbsp;m/s and a narrower track pitch of 1.5&amp;nbsp;µm increases the playing time to 80 minutes, and data capacity to 700&amp;nbsp;MiB.

[[File:CD Pits at 6.25x Magnification.jpg|alt=This is a photomicrograph of the pits at the inner edge of a CD-ROM; 2-second exposure under visible fluorescent light.|thumb|The pits in a CD are 500 [[nanometre|nm]] wide, between 830 nm and 3,000 nm long and 150 nm deep]]
A CD is read by focusing a 780&amp;nbsp;nm [[wavelength]] ([[near infrared]]) [[semiconductor laser]] through the bottom of the polycarbonate layer. The change in height between pits and lands results in a difference in the way the light is reflected. By measuring the reflection intensity change with a [[photodiode]], data is read from the disc. In order to accommodate the spiral pattern of data, the laser is placed on a mobile mechanism within the disc tray of any CD player. This mechanism typically takes the form of a sled that slides across a rail driven by a [[worm gear]], though some CD drives (particularly those manufactured by Philips during the 1980s and early 1990s) use a swing arm similar to that seen on a gramophone. This mechanism allows the laser to read information from the center to the edge of a disc without having to interrupt the spinning of the disc itself.

[[File:CDM210 cd laufwerk.jpg|thumb|Philips CDM210 CD Drive]]

The pits and lands do ''not'' directly represent the 0's and 1's of [[binary data]]. Instead, [[non-return-to-zero, inverted]] encoding is used: a change from either pit to land or land to pit indicates a 1, while no change indicates a series of 0's. There must be at least two, and no more than ten 0's between each 1, which is defined by the length of the pit. This, in turn, is decoded by reversing the [[eight-to-fourteen modulation]] used in mastering the disc, and then reversing the [[cross-interleaved Reed–Solomon coding]], finally revealing the raw data stored on the disc. These encoding techniques (defined in the ''[[Compact Disc Digital Audio#Data encoding|Red Book]]'') were originally designed for [[Compact Disc Digital Audio|CD Digital Audio]], but they later became a standard for almost all CD formats (such as [[CD-ROM]]).

=== Integrity ===
CDs are susceptible to damage during handling and from environmental exposure. Pits are much closer to the label side of a disc, enabling defects and contaminants on the clear side to be out of focus during playback. Consequently, CDs are more likely to suffer damage on the label side of the disc. Scratches on the clear side can be repaired by refilling them with similar refractive plastic or by careful polishing.  The edges of CDs are sometimes incompletely sealed, allowing gases and liquids to enter the CD and corrode the metal reflective layer and/or interfere with the focus of the laser on the pits, a condition known as [[disc rot]].&lt;ref name=&quot;clir&quot;&gt;Council on Library and Information Resources: [http://www.clir.org/pubs/reports/pub121/sec5.html Conditions that Affect CDs and DVDs] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160915012213/https://www.clir.org/pubs/reports/pub121/sec5.html |date=15 September 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The fungus ''[[Geotrichum candidum]]'' has been found—under conditions of high heat and humidity—to consume the polycarbonate plastic and aluminium found in CDs.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url=http://www.nature.com/news/1998/010628/full/news010628-11.html|title=Fungus eats CD|year=2001|journal=Nature|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131212044729/http://www.nature.com/news/1998/010628/full/news010628-11.html|archivedate=12 December 2013|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/science/nature/1402533.stm|title=Fungus 'eats' CDs|date=June 2001|publisher=BBC|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131212220948/http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/science/nature/1402533.stm|archivedate=12 December 2013|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Disc shapes and diameters ===
[[File:Comparison disk storage.svg|thumb|upright=1.35|Comparison of several forms of disk storage showing tracks (not-to-scale); green denotes start and red denotes end.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;*&lt;/nowiki&gt; Some CD-R(W) and DVD-R(W)/DVD+R(W) recorders operate in ZCLV, CAA or CAV modes.]]

The digital data on a CD begins at the center of the disc and proceeds toward the edge, which allows adaptation to the different size formats available. Standard CDs are available in two sizes. By far, the most common is {{convert|120|mm|in}} in diameter, with a 74- or 80-minute audio capacity and a 650 or 700&amp;nbsp;MiB (737,280,000-byte) data capacity. The official Philips history says this capacity was specified by Sony executive [[Norio Ohga]] so as to be able to contain the entirety of [[Beethoven's Ninth Symphony]] on one disc.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ohgaobituary&quot; /&gt; This is a myth according to [[Kees Schouhamer Immink|Kees Immink]], as the code format had not yet been decided in December 1979. The adoption of [[Eight-to-fourteen modulation|EFM]] in June 1980 would have allowed a playing time of 97 minutes for 120&amp;nbsp;mm diameter or 74 minutes for a disc as small as 100&amp;nbsp;mm, but instead the information density was lowered by 30 percent to keep the playing time at 74 minutes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Imminknature&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal 
|journal=Nature Electronics
|volume=1
|date=2018
|title=How we made the compact disc
|author=K.A. Schouhamer Immink
|authorlink=Kees Schouhamer Immink
|url=https://www.researchgate.net/publication/324571504
|accessdate=2018-04-16
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Immink2&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Tim Buthe and Walter Mattli, The New Global Rulers: The Privatization of Regulation in the World Economy, Princeton University Press, Feb. 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; The 120&amp;nbsp;mm diameter has been adopted by subsequent formats, including [[Super Audio CD]], [[DVD]], [[HD DVD]], and [[Blu-ray Disc]]. The 80&amp;nbsp;mm diameter discs (&quot;[[Mini CD]]s&quot;) can hold up to 24 minutes of music or 210&amp;nbsp;MiB.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Physical size
! Audio capacity
! CD-ROM data capacity
! Definition
|-
| 120&amp;nbsp;mm || 74–80 min || 650–700&amp;nbsp;[[Mebibyte|MiB]] || Standard size
|-
| 80&amp;nbsp;mm || 21–24 min || 185–210&amp;nbsp;MiB || Mini-CD size
|-
| 80x54&amp;nbsp;mm&amp;nbsp;– 80x64&amp;nbsp;mm  || ~6 min || 10-65&amp;nbsp;MiB || &quot;Business card&quot; size
|}

== Logical format ==
{{Unreferenced section|date=May 2018}}

=== Audio CD ===
{{Main|Compact Disc Digital Audio}}
The logical format of an audio CD (officially Compact Disc Digital Audio or CD-DA) is described in a document produced in 1980 by the format's joint creators, Sony and Philips. The document is known colloquially as the ''Red Book'' [[Compact Disc Digital Audio|CD-DA]] after the colour of its cover. The format is a two-channel 16-bit [[Pulse-code modulation|PCM]] encoding at a [[44.1 kHz|44.1&amp;nbsp;kHz]] [[sampling rate]] per channel. [[Four-channel Compact Disc Digital Audio|Four-channel sound]] was to be an allowable option within the ''Red Book'' format, but has never been implemented. [[Monaural]] audio has no existing standard on a ''Red Book'' CD; thus, mono source material is usually presented as two identical channels in a standard ''Red Book'' stereo track (i.e., [[mono sound#Mirrored mono|mirrored mono]]); an [[MP3 CD]], however, can have audio file formats with mono sound.

[[CD-Text]] is an extension of the ''Red Book'' specification for an audio CD that allows for the storage of additional text information (e.g., album name, song name, artist) on a standards-compliant audio CD. The information is stored either in the [[Lead-in (CD)|lead-in area]] of the CD, where there is roughly five kilobytes of space available or in the [[Compact Disc subcode|subcode]] channels R to W on the disc, which can store about 31 megabytes.

[[Compact Disc + Graphics]] is a special audio compact disc that contains graphics data in addition to the audio data on the disc. The disc can be played on a regular audio CD player, but when played on a special CD+G player, it can output a graphics signal (typically, the CD+G player is hooked up to a television set or a computer monitor); these graphics are almost exclusively used to display lyrics on a television set for [[karaoke]] performers to sing along with. The CD+G format takes advantage of the channels R through W. These six bits store the graphics information.

[[CD + Extended Graphics]] (CD+EG, also known as CD+XG) is an improved variant of the [[#CD + Graphics|Compact Disc + Graphics]] (CD+G) format. Like CD+G, CD+EG uses basic CD-ROM features to display text and video information in addition to the music being played. This extra data is stored in [[Compact Disc subcode|subcode]] channels R-W. Very few, if any, CD+EG discs have been published.

=== Super Audio CD ===
{{Main|Super Audio CD}}
Super Audio CD (SACD) is a high-resolution read-only [[optical disc|optical]] [[audio storage|audio disc]] format that was designed to provide [[high fidelity|higher fidelity]] digital audio reproduction than the ''Red Book''. Introduced in 1999, it was developed by Sony and Philips, the same companies that created the ''Red Book''. SACD was in a [[format war]] with [[DVD-Audio]], but neither has replaced audio CDs. The SACD standard is referred to the ''Scarlet Book'' standard.

Titles in the SACD format can be issued as hybrid discs; these discs contain the SACD audio stream as well as a standard audio CD layer which is playable in standard CD players, thus making them backward compatible.

=== CD-MIDI ===
CD-[[Musical Instrument Digital Interface|MIDI]] is a format used to store music-performance data, which upon playback is performed by electronic instruments that synthesize the audio. Hence, unlike the original ''Red Book'' CD-DA, these recordings are not digitally sampled audio recordings. The CD-MIDI format is defined as an extension of the original ''Red Book''.

=== CD-ROM ===
{{Main|CD-ROM}}
For the first few years of its existence, the CD was a medium used purely for audio. However, in 1988, the ''Yellow Book'' [[CD-ROM]] standard was established by Sony and Philips, which defined a non-volatile optical data [[computer data storage]] medium using the same physical format as audio compact discs, readable by a computer with a CD-ROM drive.

=== Video CD (VCD) ===
{{Main|Video CD}}
Video CD (VCD, View CD, and Compact Disc digital video) is a standard [[Digital data|digital]] format for storing video media on a CD. VCDs are playable in dedicated VCD players, most modern [[DVD-Video]] players, personal computers, and some video game consoles.

The VCD standard was created in 1993 by Sony, Philips, [[Panasonic Corporation|Matsushita]], and [[JVC]] and is referred to as the ''White Book'' standard.

Overall picture quality is intended to be comparable to [[VHS]] video. Poorly compressed VCD video can sometimes be lower quality than VHS video, but VCD exhibits block artifacts rather than analog noise and does not deteriorate further with each use.

352x240 (or [[Source Input Format|SIF]]) resolution was chosen because it is half the vertical and half the horizontal resolution of NTSC video. 352x288 is similarly one quarter PAL/SECAM resolution. This approximates the (overall) resolution of an analog VHS tape, which, although it has double the number of (vertical) scan lines, has a much lower horizontal resolution.

=== Super Video CD ===
{{Main|Super Video CD}}
Super Video CD (Super Video Compact Disc or SVCD) is a format used for storing video media on standard compact discs. SVCD was intended as a successor to VCD and an alternative to DVD-Video and falls somewhere between both in terms of technical capability and picture quality.

SVCD has two thirds the [[display resolution|resolution]] of DVD, and over 2.7 times the resolution of VCD. One CD-R disc can hold up to 60 minutes of standard quality SVCD-format video. While no specific limit on SVCD video length is mandated by the specification, one must lower the video bit rate, and therefore quality, to accommodate very long videos. It is usually difficult to fit much more than 100 minutes of video onto one SVCD without incurring significant quality loss, and many hardware players are unable to play video with an instantaneous bit rate lower than 300 to 600 [[kilobits]] per second.

=== Photo CD ===
{{Main|Photo CD}}
Photo CD is a system designed by [[Kodak]] for digitizing and storing photos on a CD. Launched in 1992, the discs were designed to hold nearly 100 high-quality images, scanned prints and slides using special proprietary encoding. Photo CDs are defined in the ''Beige Book'' and conform to the [[CD-ROM XA]] and CD-i Bridge specifications as well. They are intended to play on CD-i players, Photo CD players and any computer with suitable software (irrespective of [[operating system]]). The images can also be printed out on photographic paper with a special Kodak machine. This format is not to be confused with Kodak [[Picture CD]], which is a consumer product in CD-ROM format.

=== CD-i ===
{{Main|Philips CD-i}}
The Philips ''[[Green Book (CD standard)|Green Book]]'' specifies a standard for interactive multimedia compact discs designed for [[Philips CD-i|CD-i]] players (1993). CD-i discs can contain audio tracks that can be played on regular [[CD player]]s, but CD-i discs are not compatible with most [[CD-ROM]] drives and software. The [[CD-i Ready]] specification was later created to improve compatibility with audio CD players, and the [[CD-i Bridge]] specification was added to create CD-i compatible discs that can be accessed by regular CD-ROM drives.

=== CD-i Ready ===
{{Main|CD-i Ready}}
Philips defined a format similar to CD-i called [[CD-i Ready]], which puts CD-i software and data into the [[Pregap#Computer data in pregap|pregap]] of track 1. This format was supposed to be more compatible with older audio CD players.

=== Enhanced Music CD (CD+) ===
{{Main|Blue Book (CD standard)}}
Enhanced Music CD, also known as CD Extra or CD Plus, is a format which combines [[CD-DA|audio tracks]] and [[CD-ROM|data tracks]] on the same disc by putting audio tracks in a first [[Session (CD)|session]] and data in a second session. It was developed by Philips and Sony, and it is defined in the ''[[Blue Book (CD standard)|Blue Book]]''.

=== VinylDisc ===
{{Main|VinylDisc}}
VinylDisc is the hybrid of a standard audio CD and the [[Gramophone record|vinyl record]]. The vinyl layer on the disc's label side can hold approximately three minutes of music.

== Manufacture ==
{{Main|CD manufacturing}}
[[File:Compact disk data layer 2d 3d.PNG|thumb|right|Individual pits are visible on the micrometre scale]]
In 1995, material costs were 30 cents for the jewel case and 10 to 15 cents for the CD. Wholesale cost of CDs was $0.75 to $1.15, while the typical retail price of a prerecorded music CD was $16.98.&lt;ref name=&quot;cd costs&quot;&gt;{{cite news |author=Neil Strauss |date=5 July 1995 |url=https://www.nytimes.com/1995/07/05/arts/pennies-that-add-up-to-16.98-why-cd-s-cost-so-much.html?pagewanted=all&amp;src=pm |title=Pennies That Add Up to $16.98: Why CD's Cost So Much – New York Times |publisher=Nytimes.com |access-date=25 July 2013 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130811000713/http://www.nytimes.com/1995/07/05/arts/pennies-that-add-up-to-16.98-why-cd-s-cost-so-much.html?pagewanted=all&amp;src=pm |archivedate=11 August 2013 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; On average, the store received 35 percent of the retail price, the record company 27 percent, the artist 16 percent, the manufacturer 13 percent, and the distributor 9 percent.&lt;ref name=&quot;cd costs&quot; /&gt; When 8-track tapes, cassette tapes, and CDs were introduced, each was marketed at a higher price than the format they succeeded, even though the cost to produce the media was reduced. This was done because the apparent value increased. This continued from vinyl to CDs but was broken when [[Apple Inc.|Apple]] marketed MP3s for $0.99, and albums for $9.99. The incremental cost, though, to produce an MP3 is very small.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author=Amy HarmonPublished: 12 October 2003 |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2003/10/12/arts/music-what-price-music.html?pagewanted=all&amp;src=pm |title=MUSIC; What Price Music? |publisher=Nytimes.com |date=12 October 2003 |access-date=25 July 2013 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130512175059/http://www.nytimes.com/2003/10/12/arts/music-what-price-music.html?pagewanted=all&amp;src=pm |archivedate=12 May 2013 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Writable compact discs ==

=== Recordable CD ===
[[File:Maxell CD-R 700MB 40x 20040321.jpg|thumb|700&amp;nbsp;[[Mebibyte|MiB]] CD-R next to a [[mechanical pencil]] for scale]]
{{Main|CD-R}}
Recordable Compact Discs, [[CD-R]]s, are injection-molded with a &quot;blank&quot; data spiral. A photosensitive dye is then applied, after which the discs are metalized and lacquer-coated. The write laser of the [[CD recorder]] changes the color of the dye to allow the read laser of a standard [[CD player]] to see the data, just as it would with a standard stamped disc. The resulting discs can be read by most CD-ROM drives and played in most audio CD players. CD-Rs follow the ''Orange Book'' standard.

CD-R recordings are designed to be permanent. Over time, the dye's physical characteristics may change causing read errors and data loss until the reading device cannot recover with error correction methods. The design life is from 20 to 100 years, depending on the quality of the discs, the quality of the writing drive, and storage conditions. However, testing has demonstrated such degradation of some discs in as little as 18 months under normal storage conditions.&lt;ref name=&quot;AutoMR-14&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AutoMR-15&quot; /&gt; This failure is known as [[disc rot]], for which there are several, mostly environmental, reasons.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.clir.org/pubs/reports/pub121/sec5.html|title=5. Conditions That Affect CDs and DVDs — Council on Library and Information Resources|website=www.clir.org|access-date=2016-07-05|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160915012213/https://www.clir.org/pubs/reports/pub121/sec5.html|archivedate=15 September 2016|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The recordable audio CD is designed to be used in a consumer audio CD recorder. These consumer audio CD recorders use SCMS ([[Serial Copy Management System]]), an early form of [[digital rights management]] (DRM), to conform to the AHRA ([[Audio Home Recording Act]]). The Recordable Audio CD is typically somewhat more expensive than CD-R due to lower production volume and a 3 percent [[Audio Home Recording Act#AHRA royalties|AHRA royalty]] used to compensate the music industry for the making of a copy.&lt;ref name=&quot;McFadden&quot; /&gt;

High-capacity recordable CD is a higher-density recording format that can hold 20% more data than of conventional discs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.osta.org/technology/cdqa7.htm |title=Understanding CD-R &amp; CD-RW |publisher=Osta.org |access-date=25 July 2013 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130801123221/http://www.osta.org/technology/cdqa7.htm |archivedate=1 August 2013 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; The higher capacity is incompatible with some recorders and recording software.&lt;ref name=&quot;cdrfaq&quot;&gt;{{cite web
 |url         = http://www.cdrfaq.org/faq03.html
 |title       = CD-Recordable FAQ – Section 3
 |date        = 9 January 2010
 |access-date = 25 November 2013
 |quote       = Small quantities of 90-minute and 99-minute blanks have appeared [...] Indications are that many recorders and some software don't really work with the longer discs.
 |url-status     = live
 |archiveurl  = https://web.archive.org/web/20131118040105/http://www.cdrfaq.org/faq03.html
 |archivedate = 18 November 2013
 |df          = dmy-all
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== ReWritable CD ===
{{Main|CD-RW}}
[[CD-RW]] is a re-recordable medium that uses a metallic alloy instead of a dye. The write laser, in this case, is used to heat and alter the properties (amorphous vs. crystalline) of the alloy, and hence change its reflectivity. A CD-RW does not have as great a difference in reflectivity as a pressed CD or a CD-R, and so many earlier CD audio players ''cannot'' read CD-RW discs, although ''most'' later CD audio players and stand-alone [[DVD]] players can. CD-RWs follow the ''Orange Book'' standard.

The ReWritable Audio CD is designed to be used in a consumer audio CD recorder, which will not (without modification) accept standard CD-RW discs. These consumer audio CD recorders use the [[Serial Copy Management System]] (SCMS), an early form of [[digital rights management]] (DRM), to conform to the United States' [[Audio Home Recording Act]] (AHRA). The ReWritable Audio CD is typically somewhat more expensive than CD-RW due to (a) lower volume and (b) a 3 percent [[Audio Home Recording Act#AHRA royalties|AHRA royalty]] used to compensate the music industry for the making of a copy.&lt;ref name=&quot;McFadden&quot; /&gt;

== Copy protection ==
{{Main|Compact Disc and DVD copy protection}}
The ''Red Book'' audio specification, except for a simple &quot;anti-copy&quot; statement in the subcode, does not include any [[copy protection]] mechanism. Known at least as early as 2001,&lt;ref name=&quot;BadCDs&quot; /&gt; attempts were made by record companies to market &quot;copy-protected&quot; non-standard compact discs, which cannot be [[Ripping|ripped]], or copied, to hard drives or easily converted to other formats (like [[FLAC]], [[MP3]] or [[Vorbis]]). One major drawback to these copy-protected discs is that most will not play on either computer CD-ROM drives or some standalone CD players that use CD-ROM mechanisms. Philips has stated that such discs are not permitted to bear the trademarked ''Compact Disc Digital Audio'' logo because they violate the ''Red Book'' specifications. Numerous copy-protection systems have been countered by readily available, often free, software, or even by simply turning off automatic [[AutoPlay]] to prevent the running of the DRM [[executable]] program.

== See also ==
{{Columns-list|colwidth=20em|

* [[5.1 Music Disc]]
* [[Compact disc bronzing]]
* [[Digipak]]
* [[DualDisc]]
* [[Extended Resolution Compact Disc]]
* [[GD-ROM]]
* [[Hidden Track]]
* [[High Definition Compatible Digital]]
* [[Longbox]]
* [[SPARS code]]
* [[Video Single Disc]]
}}


== References ==
{{reflist|30em|refs=
&lt;ref name=&quot;grammy&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.grammy.org/recording-academy/producers-and-engineers/awards |title=Technical Grammy Award |access-date=5 November 2014 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20141026094809/http://www.grammy.org/recording-academy/producers-and-engineers/awards |archivedate=26 October 2014 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;AutoMR-1&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/technology/6950845.stm |title=Compact Disc Hits 25th birthday |work=BBC News |date=17 August 2007 |access-date=1 December 2009 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100218031404/http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/technology/6950845.stm |archivedate=18 February 2010 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;AutoMR-2&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url=https://www.nytimes.com/2010/05/31/business/media/31bestbuy.html | work=The New York Times | title=As CD Sales Wane, Music Retailers Diversify | first=Joseph | last=Plambeck | date=30 May 2010 | url-status=live | archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170501175846/http://www.nytimes.com/2010/05/31/business/media/31bestbuy.html | archivedate=1 May 2017 | df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;peek&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |first=Hans B. |last=Peek |title=The Emergence of the Compact Disc |journal=IEEE Communications Magazine |date=January 2010 |pages=10–17 |volume=48 |number=1 |issn=0163-6804 |doi=10.1109/MCOM.2010.5394021 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;SonyHistorical&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.aes.org/e-lib/browse.cfm?elib=2912 | title = A Long Play Digital Audio Disc System | publisher = AES | access-date = 14 February 2009 | url-status = live | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20090725223113/http://www.aes.org/e-lib/browse.cfm?elib=2912 | archivedate = 25 July 2009 | df = dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC6950933&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/technology/6950933.stm | title = How the CD Was Developed | work = BBC News | date = 17 August 2007 | access-date = 17 August 2007 | url-status = dead | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20071222035025/http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/technology/6950933.stm | archivedate = 22 December 2007 | df = dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;PhilipsHistorical&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.philipsmuseumeindhoven.nl/phe/products/e_cd.htm | title = Philips Compact Disc | publisher = Philips | access-date = 14 February 2009 | url-status = dead | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20090319141821/http://www.philipsmuseumeindhoven.nl/phe/products/e_cd.htm | archivedate = 19 March 2009 | df = dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;IEEE_CD_Milestone&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.ieeeghn.org/wiki/index.php/Milestones:Compact_Disc_Audio_Player,_1979 | title = IEEE CD Milestone | publisher = IEEE Global History Network | access-date = 14 October 2010 | url-status = live | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20091126195434/http://www.ieeeghn.org/wiki/index.php/Milestones:Compact_Disc_Audio_Player,_1979 | archivedate = 26 November 2009 | df = dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Ohgaobituary&quot;&gt;{{ citation | url = http://www.foxnews.com/world/2011/04/24/sony-chairman-credited-developing-cds-dies/ | title = Sony chairman credited with developing CDs dies | access-date = 14 October 2012 | work = Fox News | date = 24 April 2011 | url-status = live | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20130521044524/http://www.foxnews.com/world/2011/04/24/sony-chairman-credited-developing-cds-dies/ | archivedate = 21 May 2013 | df = dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Immink2&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal 
|journal=IEEE Information Theory Society Newsletter
|volume=57 
|date=2007
|title=Shannon, Beethoven, and the Compact Disc
|author=K. Schouhamer Immink 
|authorlink=Kees Schouhamer Immink 
|url=https://www.researchgate.net/publication/322951358
|pages=42–46
|accessdate=2018-02-06
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Immink&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal 
|journal=Journal of the Audio Engineering Society
|volume=46 |issue=5
|date=1998
|title=Compact Disc Story
|author=K. Schouhamer Immink
|authorlink=Kees Schouhamer Immink
|url=https://www.researchgate.net/publication/294484774
|pages=458–460
|accessdate=2018-02-06
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Knopper&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | title = Appetite for Self-Destruction: The Rise and Fall of the Record Industry in the Digital Age | author = Knopper, Steve | publisher = Free Press/[[Simon &amp; Schuster]] | date = 7 January 2009 | access-date = &lt;!-- 2009-038-17 --&gt; }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;PhilDoss&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.research.philips.com/newscenter/dossier/optrec/beethoven.html | title = The Inventor of the CD | work = Philips Research | access-date = 16 January 2009 | archiveurl = https://archive.today/20080129201342/http://www.research.philips.com/newscenter/dossier/optrec/beethoven.html | archivedate = 29 January 2008 | url-status = dead | df = dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Karajan&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url= http://www.cnn.com/2012/09/28/tech/innovation/compact-disc-turns-30 | title= Rock on! The compact disc turns 30 | date= September 29, 2012 | first= Heather |last=Kelly | publisher= CNN| accessdate=2012-09-30| quote= The first test CD was Richard Strauss's ''Eine Alpensinfonie'', and the first CD actually pressed at a factory was ABBA's ''[[The Visitors (ABBA album)|The Visitors]]'', but that disc wasn't released commercially until later.}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;AutoMR-4&quot;&gt;{{cite book| last = Bilyeu|first = Melinda|author2=Hector Cook |author3=Andrew Môn Hughes  |publisher = Omnibus Press| location = |year = 2004| isbn = 978-1-84449-057-8| title = The Bee Gees:tales of the brothers Gibb| page = 519 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!-- unused  &lt;ref name=&quot;AutoMR-5&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.geekzone.co.nz/content.asp?contentid=7304|title=And 25 Years Ago Philips Introduced the CD|work=GeekZone|access-date=11 January 2008|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070912175820/http://www.geekzone.co.nz/content.asp?ContentId=7304|archivedate=12 September 2007|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;AutoMR-6&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sony.net/Fun/SH/1-20/h5.html|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080802133849/http://www.sony.net/Fun/SH/1-20/h5.html|archivedate=2 August 2008|title=Sony History: A Great Invention 100 Years On|publisher=[[Sony]]|access-date=28 February 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;AutoMR-7&quot;&gt;''[[Maxim (magazine)|Maxim]]'', 2004&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;AutoMR-8&quot;&gt;The New Schwann Record &amp; Tape Guide Volume 37 No. 2 February 1985&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;AutoMR-9&quot;&gt;MAC Audio News. No. 178, November 1989. pp 19-21 Glenn Baddeley. ''November 1989 News Update''. Melbourne Audio Club Inc.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;AutoMR-10&quot;&gt;The world's first CD-R was made by the Japanese firm [[Taiyo Yuden]] Co., Ltd. in 1988 as part of the joint Philips-Sony development effort.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=nyt20120718&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2011/02/06/automobiles/06AUDIO.html|title=For Car Cassette Decks, Play Time Is Over|last=Williams|first=Stephen|newspaper=New York Times|date=4 February 2011|access-date=18 July 2012|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20121110105333/https://www.nytimes.com/2011/02/06/automobiles/06AUDIO.html|archivedate=10 November 2012|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;AutoMR-11&quot;&gt;{{cite news |first=Ethan |last=Smith |title=Music Sales Decline for Seventh Time in Eight Years: Digital Downloads Can't Offset 20% Plunge in CD Sales |url=https://www.wsj.com/articles/SB123075988836646491?mod=rss_whats_news_technology&amp;mg=com-wsj |newspaper=Wall Street Journal |date=2 January 2009 |access-date=4 March 2009 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20171020191140/https://www.wsj.com/articles/SB123075988836646491?mod=rss_whats_news_technology&amp;mg=com-wsj |archivedate=20 October 2017 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;AutoMR-12&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://indiemusicstop.wordpress.com/2009/04/01/cd-baby-payouts-surge/ |title=CD Baby Payouts Surge « Indie Music Stop |publisher=Indiemusicstop.wordpress.com |date=30 March 2009 |access-date=1 December 2009 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110718100639/http://indiemusicstop.wordpress.com/2009/04/01/cd-baby-payouts-surge/ |archivedate=18 July 2011 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;AutoMR-13&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cd-testing.com/#i17 |title=Q. How Do You Calculate Moment of Inertia? |access-date=19 August 2009 |quote=a typical disc with ... weight of 15 grams ... maximum allowed weight (20&amp;nbsp;g) |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090417000316/http://www.cd-testing.com/ |archivedate=17 April 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;AutoMR-14&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.cdfreaks.com/news/CD-Recordable-discs-unreadable-in-less-than-two-years.html | title = CD-R Unreadable in Less Than Two Years | publisher = cdfreaks.com | access-date = 1 February 2007 | url-status = dead | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20070214195603/http://www.cdfreaks.com/news/CD-Recordable-discs-unreadable-in-less-than-two-years.html | archivedate = 14 February 2007 | df = dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;AutoMR-15&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.pc-active.nl/toonArtikel.asp?artikelID=508 | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20050204065340/http://www.pc-active.nl/toonArtikel.asp?artikelID=508 | archivedate = 4 February 2005 | title = CD-R ROT | access-date = 1 February 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;McFadden&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.cdrfaq.org/ | title = CD-Recordable FAQ | author = Andy McFadden | date = 8 August 2007 | access-date = 20 September 2007 | url-status = live | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20070920211018/http://www.cdrfaq.org/ | archivedate = 20 September 2007 | df = dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;BadCDs&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://uk.eurorights.org/issues/cd/bad/ | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20011205101807/http://uk.eurorights.org/issues/cd/bad/ | archivedate = 5 December 2001 | title = Copy Protected CDs (via Archive.org) | author = Campaign For Digital Rights | date = 5 December 2001 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;BeatlesCD&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = https://www.nytimes.com/1987/02/25/arts/now-on-cd-s-first-4-beatles-albums.html |title=NOW ON CD'S, FIRST 4 BEATLES ALBUMS |author=JON PARELES |date=February 25, 1987 |work=New York Times}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

== Further reading ==
* [[Ecma International]]. [http://www.ecma-international.org/publications/standards/Ecma-130.htm ''Standard ECMA-130: Data Interchange on Read-only 120&amp;nbsp;mm Optical Data Disks (CD-ROM)''], 2nd edition (June 1996).
* Pohlmann, Kenneth C. (1992). [https://archive.org/details/compactdischandb0000pohl ''The Compact Disc Handbook'']. Middleton, Wisconsin: A-R Editions. {{ISBN|0-89579-300-8}}.
* Peek, Hans et al. (2009) [https://www.springer.com/engineering/electronics/book/978-1-4020-9552-8 ''Origins and Successors of the Compact Disc'']. Springer Science+Business Media B.V. {{ISBN|978-1-4020-9552-8}}.
* Peek, Hans B., [https://www.philips.com/c-dam/corporate/research/technologies/cd/The-Emergence-of-the-Compact-Disc_v2.pdf ''The emergence of the compact disc''], IEEE Communications Magazine, Jan. 2010, pp.&amp;nbsp;10–17.
* [[Heitaro Nakajima|Nakajima, Heitaro]]; Ogawa, Hiroshi (1992) [https://books.google.com/books?id=9G9Nu9n0DJQC''Compact Disc Technology''], Tokyo, Ohmsha Ltd. {{ISBN|4-274-03347-3}}.

== External links ==
{{Commons and category|Compact disc|Compact discs}}
* [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ut_40U0t9pU Video] How Compact Discs are Manufactured
* [http://www.cdrfaq.org/ CD-Recordable FAQ] Exhaustive basics on CD-Recordable's
* [https://archive.today/20080129201342/http://www.research.philips.com/newscenter/dossier/optrec/beethoven.html Philips history of the CD (cache)]
* [https://archive.today/20121216094847/http://www.ip.philips.com/licensing/licensingprogramshistory/history_cdplayer_joint.html Patent History (CD Player)]&amp;nbsp;– published by [[Philips]] in 2005
* [https://archive.today/20121206014421/http://www.ip.philips.com/licensing/licensingprogramshistory/history_cddisc_joint.html Patent History CD Disc]&amp;nbsp;– published by [[Philips]] in 2003
* [http://www.sony.co.jp/SonyInfo/CorporateInfo/History/SonyHistory/2-08.html Sony History, Chapter 8, This is the replacement of Gramophone record ! (第8章 レコードに代わるものはこれだ)]&amp;nbsp;– [[Sony]] website in Japanese
* [http://www.soundfountain.com/amb/cd25years.html Popularized History on Soundfountain]

{{Compact disc}}
{{Audio formats}}
{{Music technology}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Compact disc| ]]
[[Category:120 mm discs]]
[[Category:Rotating disc computer storage media]]
[[Category:Audio storage]]
[[Category:Digital audio storage]]
[[Category:Video storage]]
[[Category:Consumer electronics]]
[[Category:Audiovisual introductions in 1982]]
[[Category:Joint ventures]]
[[Category:Dutch inventions]]
[[Category:Japanese inventions]]
[[Category:Information technology in the Netherlands]]
[[Category:Science and technology in the Netherlands]]
[[Category:Science and technology in Japan]]</text>
      <sha1>3dpl7xjmba1fttu6mnjq5naxly9506l</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
