  <page>
    <title>Clock</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6449</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943097146</id>
      <parentid>943097121</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-28T20:26:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>NomadicNom</username>
        <id>33382622</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/156.3.154.33|156.3.154.33]] ([[User talk:156.3.154.33|talk]]) to last revision by Tymon.r ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Instrument for measuring, keeping or indicating time.}}
{{redirect|Timepiece|other uses|Clock (disambiguation)|and|Timepiece (disambiguation)}}
{{pp-move|small=yes}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=November 2013}}

[[File:Greenwich clock.jpg|thumb|upright=1.1|The [[Shepherd Gate Clock]] at the [[Royal Observatory, Greenwich]]]]
[[File:Digital-clock-oven.jpg|thumb|Digital clock on an oven]]
[[File:Old port Montreal Clock Tower.jpg|thumb|upright|Montreal Clock Tower]]
[[File:Florence-Duomo-Clock.jpg|thumb|24-hour clock face in Florence]]

A '''clock''' is a device used to measure, keep,&lt;!-- Per [[WP:RETAIN]] and [[MOS:OXFORD]], please do not remove comma without consensus on the talk page --&gt; and indicate [[time]]. The clock is one of the oldest human [[invention]]s, meeting the need to measure intervals of time shorter than the natural units: the [[day]], the [[lunar month]],&lt;!-- Per WP:RETAIN and MOS:OXFORD, please do not remove comma without consensus on the talk page --&gt; and the [[year]]. Devices operating on several physical processes have been used over the millennia.

Some predecessors to the modern clock may be considered as &quot;clocks&quot; that are based on movement in nature: A [[sundial]] shows the time by displaying the position of a shadow on a flat surface. There is a range of duration timers, a well-known example being the [[hourglass]]. [[Water clock]]s, along with the sundials, are possibly the oldest time-measuring instruments.  A major advance occurred with the invention of the [[verge escapement]], which made possible the first mechanical clocks around 1300 in [[Europe]], which kept time with oscillating timekeepers like [[balance wheel]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dohrn&quot;&gt;{{cite book
|last=Dohrn-van Rossum
|first=Gerhard
|title=History of the Hour: Clocks and Modern Temporal Orders
|year=1996
|publisher=Univ. of Chicago Press
|url=https://books.google.com/?id=xYhlNoUu-toC&amp;dq=verge+escapement+technology
|isbn=978-0-226-15511-1}}, pp. 103–104&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Marrison&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Marrison|first=Warren|title=The Evolution of the Quartz Crystal Clock|journal=Bell System Technical Journal|year=1948|volume=27|issue=3|pages=510–588|url=http://timepieceperfection.com/THE-BELL-SYSTEM.pdf|accessdate=10 November 2014|doi=10.1002/j.1538-7305.1948.tb01343.x|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20141110143908/http://timepieceperfection.com/THE-BELL-SYSTEM.pdf|archivedate=November 10, 2014|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Cipolla&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Cipolla|first=Carlo M.|title=Clocks and Culture, 1300 to 1700|year=2004|publisher=W.W. Norton &amp; Co.|isbn=978-0-393-32443-3|url=https://books.google.com/?id=YSf9MVxa2JEC&amp;pg=PA31&amp;dq=verge+escapement+technology}}, p. 31&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;White&quot;&gt;{{cite book
 | last = White
 | first = Lynn, Jr.
 | title = Medieval Technology and Social Change
 | publisher = Oxford Univ. Press
 | year = 1962
 | location = UK
 | pages = 119
 | url =
 | doi =
 | isbn = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Traditionally in [[horology]], the term ''clock'' was used for a [[striking clock]], while a clock that did not strike the hours audibly was called a '''timepiece'''.&lt;ref&gt;see Baillie et al., p. 307; Palmer, p. 19; Zea &amp; Cheney, p. 172&lt;/ref&gt; In general usage today, a &quot;clock&quot; refers to any device for measuring and displaying the time. [[Watch]]es and other timepieces that can be carried on one's person are often distinguished from clocks.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Cambridge Advanced Learner's Dictionary |url=https://dictionary.cambridge.org/dictionary/english/clock |accessdate=2018-01-29 |quote=a device for measuring and showing time, which is usually found in or on a building and is not worn by a person}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Spring-driven clocks appeared during the 15th century. During the 15th and 16th centuries, clockmaking flourished. The next development in accuracy occurred after 1656 with the invention of the [[pendulum clock]] by [[Christiaan Huygens]]. A major stimulus to improving the accuracy and reliability of clocks was the importance of precise time-keeping for navigation. The [[electric clock]] was patented in 1840. The development of [[electronics]] in the 20th century led to clocks with no clockwork parts at all.

The timekeeping element in every modern clock is a [[harmonic oscillator]], a physical object ([[resonator]]) that vibrates or [[oscillate]]s at a particular [[frequency]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Marrison&quot; /&gt;
This object can be a [[pendulum]], a [[tuning fork]], a [[crystal oscillator|quartz crystal]], or the vibration of [[electron]]s in [[atom]]s as they emit [[microwave]]s.

Clocks have different ways of displaying the time. Analog clocks indicate time with a traditional [[clock face]], with moving hands. Digital clocks display a numeric representation of time. Two numbering systems are in use; [[24-hour time]] notation and 12-hour notation. Most digital clocks use electronic mechanisms and [[LCD]], [[LED]], or [[Vacuum fluorescent display|VFD]] displays. For the blind and use over telephones, [[speaking clock]]s state the time audibly in words.  There are also clocks for the blind that have displays that can be read by touch. The study of timekeeping is known as [[horology]].

==Etymology==
The word ''clock'' derives from the medieval [[Latin]] word for &quot;bell&quot;; ''clogga'', and has [[cognate]]s in many European languages.  Clocks spread to England from the [[Low Countries]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Wedgwood&quot;&gt;{{cite book
 | last1  = Wedgwood
 | first1 = Hensleigh 
 | title  = A Dictionary of English Etymology: A{{Snd}} D, Vol. 1
 | publisher = Trübner and Co.
 | date   = 1859
 | location = London
 | pages  = 354
 | url    = https://books.google.com/books?id=AGdJAAAAcAAJ&amp;pg=PA354&amp;dq=clock
 | doi    = 
 | id     = 
 | isbn   = 
 }}&lt;/ref&gt; so the English word came from the Middle Low German and Middle Dutch ''Klocke''.&lt;ref name=&quot;OED&quot;&gt;{{cite book
 | last1  = Stevenson
 | first1 = Angus
 | last2  = Waite
 | first2 = Maurice
 | title  = Concise Oxford English Dictionary: Luxury Edition
 | publisher = Oxford University
 | date   = 2011
 | pages  = 269–270
 | url    = https://books.google.com/books?id=sYScAQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA270&amp;dq=clock+clogga
 | doi    = 
 | id     = 
 | isbn   = 9780199601110
 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History of time-measuring devices==
{{main|History of timekeeping devices}}
&lt;!--Linked from [[Template:Time topics]]--&gt;

===Sundials===
[[File:Garden sundial MN 2007.JPG|thumb|left|Simple horizontal sundial]]
{{Main|Sundial}}
The apparent position of the [[Sun]] in the sky moves over the course of each day, reflecting the rotation of the [[Earth]]. Shadows cast by stationary objects move correspondingly, so their positions can be used to indicate the time of day. A [[sundial]] shows the time by displaying the position of a shadow on a (usually) flat surface, which has markings that correspond to the hours.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=How Sundials Work|url=http://sundialsoc.org.uk/discussions/how-do-sundials-work/|publisher=The British Sundial Society|access-date=10 November 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sundials can be horizontal, vertical, or in other orientations. Sundials were widely used in [[Ancient history|ancient times]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Ancient Sundials|url=http://sundials.org/index.php/all-things-sundial/ancient-sundials|publisher=North American Sundial Society|access-date=10 November 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; With the knowledge of latitude, a well-constructed sundial can measure local [[solar time]] with reasonable accuracy, within a minute or two. Sundials continued to be used to monitor the performance of clocks until the 1830s, with the use of the telegraph and train to standardize time and time zones between cities.&lt;ref&gt;Sara Schecner Genuth, &quot;Sundials&quot;, in John Lankford and Marc Rothenberg, eds., ''History of Astronomy: An Encyclopedia'' (London: Taylor &amp; Francis, 1997), 502-3. 
{{ISBN|9780815303220}}
books.google.com/books?id=Xev7zOrwLHgC&amp;pg=PA502&lt;/ref&gt;

===Devices that measure duration, elapsed time and intervals===
[[File:Wooden hourglass 3.jpg|thumb|upright|The flow of [[sand]] in an [[hourglass]] can be used to keep track of elapsed time.]]
Many devices can be used to mark passage of time without respect to reference time (time of day, minutes, etc.) and can be useful for measuring duration or intervals. Examples of such duration timers are [[candle clock]]s, [[incense clock]]s and the [[hourglass]]. Both the candle clock and the incense clock work on the same principle wherein the consumption of resources is more or less constant allowing reasonably precise and repeatable estimates of time passages. In the hourglass, fine [[sand]] pouring through a tiny hole at a constant rate indicates an arbitrary, predetermined, passage of time. The resource is not consumed but re-used.

===Water clocks===
{{main|Water clock}}
[[File:MandalayWaterClock.jpg|thumb|upright|A water clock for [[goldbeating]] [[goldleaf]] in [[Mandalay]] ([[Myanmar]]).]]

Water clocks, also known as clepsydrae (sg: ''clepsydra''), along with the sundials, are possibly the oldest time-measuring instruments, with the only exceptions being the vertical [[gnomon]] and the day counting [[tally stick]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Turner|1984|p=1}}&lt;/ref&gt; Given their great antiquity, where and when they first existed is not known and perhaps unknowable. The bowl-shaped outflow is the simplest form of a water clock and is known to have existed in [[Babylon]] and in [[Egypt]] around the 16th century BC. Other regions of the world, including [[India]] and [[China]], also have early evidence of water clocks, but the earliest dates are less certain. Some authors, however, write about water clocks appearing as early as 4000 BC in these regions of the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Cowan|1958|p=58}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Ancient Greece|Greek]] astronomer [[Andronicus of Cyrrhus]] supervised the construction of the [[Tower of the Winds]] in Athens in the 1st century B.C.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sailingissues.com/yachting-guide/tower-of-winds-1.html Tower of the Winds – Athens]&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Ancient Greece|Greek]] and [[Ancient Rome|Roman]] civilizations advanced water clock design with improved accuracy. These advances were passed on through [[Byzantium]] and [[Islamic]] times, eventually making their way back to [[Europe]]. Independently, the Chinese developed their own advanced water clocks（水鐘）in 725 AD, passing their ideas on to [[Korea]] and [[Japan]].

Some water clock designs were developed independently and some knowledge was transferred through the spread of trade. [[Pre-modern]] societies do not have the same precise timekeeping requirements that exist in modern [[industrialism|industrial]] societies, where every hour of work or rest is monitored, and work may start or finish at any time regardless of external conditions. Instead, water clocks in ancient societies were used mainly for [[astrology|astrological]] reasons. These early water clocks were calibrated with a [[sundial]]. While never reaching the level of accuracy of a modern timepiece, the water clock was the most accurate and commonly used timekeeping device for millennia, until it was replaced by the more accurate [[pendulum clock]] in 17th-century Europe.

Islamic civilization is credited with further advancing the accuracy of clocks with elaborate engineering. In 797 (or possibly 801), the [[Abbasid]] [[caliph]] of [[Baghdad]], [[Harun al-Rashid]], presented [[Charlemagne]] with an [[Asian Elephant]] named [[Abul-Abbas]] together with a &quot;particularly elaborate example&quot; of a water&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = James | first = Peter | title = Ancient Inventions | year = 1995 | location = New York | isbn = 978-0-345-40102-1 | page = [https://archive.org/details/ancientinvention00jame/page/126 126] | publisher = Ballantine Books | url = https://archive.org/details/ancientinvention00jame/page/126 }}&lt;/ref&gt; clock. [[Pope Sylvester II]] introduced clocks to northern and western Europe around 1000 AD.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |url=https://archive.org/details/livesnecromance04godwgoog|title=Lives of the Necromancers|author=William Godwin|year=1876|page=232|publisher=London, F.J. Mason}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Mechanical water clocks===
The first [[gear]]ed clock was invented in the 11th century by the [[Inventions in medieval Islam|Arab engineer]] [[al-Muradi|Ibn Khalaf al-Muradi]] in [[Al-Andalus|Islamic Iberia]]; it was a water clock that employed a complex [[gear train]] mechanism, including both segmental and [[epicyclic gearing]],&lt;ref name=Hassan/&gt;&lt;ref name=Hill-1996/&gt; capable of transmitting high [[torque]]. The clock was unrivalled in its use of sophisticated complex gearing, until the mechanical clocks of the mid-14th century.&lt;ref name=Hill-1996&gt;{{Cite book|title=A history of engineering in classical and medieval times|author=Donald Routledge Hill|publisher=[[Routledge]]|year=1996|isbn=0-415-15291-7|pages=203, 223, 242|ref=harv|postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;|author-link=Donald Routledge Hill}}&lt;/ref&gt; Al-Muradi's clock also employed the use of mercury in its hydraulic [[Linkage (mechanical)|linkages]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title=Arabic Mechanical Engineering: Survey of the Historical sources|author=Donald Routledge Hill|journal=[[Arabic Sciences and Philosophy: A Historical Journal]]|year=1991|volume=1|pages=167–186 [173]|publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]]|doi=10.1017/S0957423900001478|ref=harv|postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;|issue=2|author-link=Donald Routledge Hill}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Leonardo/&gt; which could function mechanical [[Automaton|automata]].&lt;ref name=Leonardo/&gt; Al-Muradi's work was known to scholars working under [[Alfonso X of Castile]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author1=Juan Vernet |author2=Julio Samso |contribution=Development of Arabic Science in Andalusia|editor1=Roshdi Rashed |editor2=Régis Morelon |title=Encyclopedia of the History of Arabic Science|volume=1|pages=243–275 [260–1]|publisher=[[Routledge]]|isbn=0-415-12410-7|ref=harv|postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;|date=1996-01-01 }}&lt;/ref&gt; hence the mechanism may have played a role in the development of the European mechanical clocks.&lt;ref name=Hill-1996/&gt; Other monumental water clocks constructed by medieval Muslim engineers also employed complex gear trains and arrays of [[Automaton|automata]].&lt;ref name=Hill-794/&gt; Arab engineers at the time also developed a liquid-driven [[escapement]] mechanism which they employed in some of their water clocks. Heavy floats were used as weights and a constant-head system was used as an [[escapement]] mechanism,&lt;ref name=Hassan&gt;[[Ahmad Y Hassan|Hassan, Ahmad Y]], [http://www.history-science-technology.com/Articles/articles%2071.html Transfer Of Islamic Technology To The West, Part II: Transmission Of Islamic Engineering], ''History of Science and Technology in Islam''&lt;/ref&gt; which was present in the hydraulic controls they used to make heavy floats descend at a slow and steady rate.&lt;ref name=Hill-794&gt;[[Donald Routledge Hill]] (1996), &quot;Engineering&quot;, p. 794, in Rashed &amp; Morelon (1996) pp. 751–95&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:SuSongClock1.JPG|thumb|upright|A [[scale model]] of [[Su Song]]'s [[Astronomical]] Clock Tower, built in 11th-century [[Kaifeng]], [[China]]. It was driven by a large [[waterwheel]], [[chain drive]], and [[escapement]] mechanism.]]

A water-powered cogwheel clock was created in [[History of Science and Technology in China|China]] by [[Yi Xing]] and [[Liang Lingzan]]. This is not considered an [[escapement]] mechanism clock as it was unidirectional, the [[Song dynasty]] [[polymath]] and [[genius]] [[Su Song]] (1020–1101) incorporated it into his monumental innovation of the astronomical clock-tower of [[Kaifeng]] in 1088.&lt;ref&gt;History of Song 宋史, Vol. 340&lt;/ref&gt;{{Page needed|date=July 2011}} His astronomical clock and rotating [[armillary sphere]] still relied on the use of either flowing water during the spring, summer, autumn seasons and [[mercury (element)|liquid mercury]] during the freezing temperature of winter (i.e. [[hydraulics]]). A mercury clock, described in the ''Libros del saber'', a Spanish work from 1277 consisting of translations and paraphrases of Arabic works, is sometimes quoted as evidence for Muslim knowledge of a mechanical clock. A mercury-powered cogwheel clock was created by [[al-Muradi|Ibn Khalaf al-Muradi]].&lt;ref name=Leonardo&gt;{{cite web|title=The Book of Secrets is coming to the world after a thousand years: Automata existed already in the eleventh century!|author=Mario Taddei|publisher=Leonardo3|url=http://www.leonardo3.net/leonardo/qma/img/Press_release_Secrets_UK.pdf|accessdate=2010-03-31|author-link=Mario Taddei}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title=Arabic Mechanical Engineering: Survey of the Historical sources|author=Donald Routledge Hill|journal=[[Arabic Sciences and Philosophy]]|year=1991|volume=1|pages=167–186 [173]|doi=10.1017/S0957423900001478|ref=harv{{inconsistent citations}}|issue=2|author-link=Donald Routledge Hill}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Al-jazari elephant clock.png|thumb|upright|An [[elephant clock]] in a manuscript by [[Al-Jazari]] (1206 AD) from ''The Book of Knowledge of Ingenious Mechanical Devices''.&lt;ref&gt;[[Ibn al-Razzaz Al-Jazari]] (ed. 1974), ''The Book of Knowledge of Ingenious Mechanical Devices''. Translated and annotated by [[Donald Routledge Hill]], Dordrecht/[[D. Reidel]].&lt;/ref&gt;]]
In the 13th century, [[Al-Jazari]], an engineer from Mesopotamia (lived 1136–1206) who worked for [[Artuqid]] king of Diyar-Bakr, [[Nasrudin|Nasir al-Din]], made numerous clocks of all shapes and sizes. A book on his work described 50 mechanical devices in 6 categories, including water clocks. The most reputed clocks included [[Elephant clock|the Elephant]], Scribe and [[Castle clock]]s, all of which have been successfully reconstructed. As well as telling the time, these grand clocks were symbols of status, grandeur and wealth of the Urtuq State.{{citation needed|date=May 2010}}

===Fully mechanical===
{{Expert needed|Time|section|talk=Early mechanical clocks – flag|date=August 2016}}
[[File:Clock that changed the world (H4, 1759) - Flickr - Tatters ❀.jpg|thumb|left|A mechanical clock]]
The word ''horologia'' (from the Greek ὥρα, hour, and λέγειν, to tell) was used to describe early mechanical clocks,&lt;ref name=wmsmith1875&gt;{{cite book |last2=Smith |first2=William |title=A Dictionary of Greek and Roman Antiquities |year=1875 |publisher=John Murray |location=London |pages=615‑617 |url=http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/secondary/SMIGRA*/Horologium.html |author1=Leonhard Schmitz }}&lt;/ref&gt; but the use of this word (still used in several [[Romance languages]])&lt;ref&gt;Modern French &quot;horloge&quot; is very close; Spanish &quot;reloj&quot; and Portuguese &quot;relógio&quot; drop the first part of the word.&lt;/ref&gt; for all timekeepers conceals the true nature of the mechanisms. For example, there is a record that in 1176 [[Cathédrale Saint-Étienne de Sens|Sens Cathedral]] installed an '[[horologe]]'&lt;ref&gt;''Bulletin de la société archéologique de Sens'', year 1867, vol. IX, p. 390, available at www.archive.org. See also [[:fr:Discussion:Horloge]]&lt;/ref&gt; but the mechanism used is unknown. According to [[Jocelin of Brakelond]], in 1198 during a fire at the abbey of St Edmundsbury (now [[Bury St Edmunds]]), the monks 'ran to the clock' to fetch water, indicating that their water clock had a reservoir large enough to help extinguish the occasional fire.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | title=The Chronicle of Jocelin of Brakelond, Monk of St. Edmundsbury: A Picture of Monastic and Social Life on the XIIth Century |year=1910 |location=London |publisher=Chatto and Windus. Translated and edited by L.C. Jane}}&lt;/ref&gt; The word ''clock'' (from the Celtic words ''clocca'' and ''clogan'', both meaning &quot;bell&quot;), which gradually supersedes &quot;horologe&quot;, suggests that it was the sound of bells which also characterized the prototype mechanical clocks that appeared during the 13th century in [[Europe]].

[[File:Läckö slott interior 27.jpg|thumb|A 17th century weight-driven clock]]
In Europe, between 1280 and 1320, there was an increase in the number of references to clocks and horologes in church records, and this probably indicates that a new type of clock mechanism had been devised. Existing clock mechanisms that used [[Hydropower|water power]] were being adapted to take their driving power from falling weights. This power was controlled by some form of oscillating mechanism, probably derived from existing bell-ringing or alarm devices. This controlled release of power—the [[escapement]]—marks the beginning of the true mechanical clock, which differed from the previously mentioned cogwheel clocks. [[Verge escapement]] mechanism derived in the surge of true mechanical clocks, which didn't need any kind of fluid power, like water or mercury, to work.

These mechanical clocks were intended for two main purposes: for signalling and notification (e.g. the timing of services and public events), and for modeling the [[solar system]]. The former purpose is administrative, the latter arises naturally given the scholarly interests in astronomy, science, astrology, and how these subjects integrated with the religious philosophy of the time. The [[astrolabe]] was used both by astronomers and astrologers, and it was natural to apply a clockwork drive to the rotating plate to produce a working model of the solar system.

Simple clocks intended mainly for notification were installed in towers, and did not always require faces or hands. They would have announced the [[canonical hours]] or intervals between set times of prayer. Canonical hours varied in length as the times of sunrise and sunset shifted. The more sophisticated astronomical clocks would have had moving dials or hands, and would have shown the time in various time systems, including [[Hour#Counting from sunset|Italian hours]], canonical hours, and time as measured by astronomers at the time. Both styles of clock started acquiring extravagant features such as [[automata]].

In 1283, a large clock was installed at [[Dunstable Priory]]; its location above the [[rood screen]] suggests that it was not a water clock.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.crystalinks.com/clocks.html|title=Clocks{{Snd}} Crystalinks|website=www.crystalinks.com|access-date=2019-06-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1292, [[Canterbury Cathedral]] installed a 'great horloge'. Over the next 30 years there are mentions of clocks at a number of ecclesiastical institutions in England, Italy, and France. In 1322, a [[Norwich cathedral astronomical clock|new clock was installed in Norwich]], an expensive replacement for an earlier clock installed in 1273. This had a large (2 metre) astronomical dial with automata and bells. The costs of the installation included the full-time employment of two [[clockkeeper]]s for two years.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

===Astronomical===
[[File:Abbot Richard Wallingford.jpg|thumb|right|[[Richard of Wallingford]] pointing to a clock, his gift to [[St Albans Abbey]].]]
[[File:Clock machine 16th century-Convent of Christ,Tomar, Portugal.jpg|thumb|16th-century clock machine [[Convent of Christ]], Tomar, Portugal]]
Besides the Chinese astronomical clock of Su Song in 1088 mentioned above, contemporary [[Islamic astronomy|Muslim astronomers]] also constructed a variety of highly accurate astronomical clocks for use in their mosques and [[Observatory|observatories]],&lt;ref name=Ajram&gt;{{Cite book|last=Ajram|first=K.|year=1992|title=Miracle of Islamic Science|chapter=Appendix B|publisher=Knowledge House Publishers|isbn=0-911119-43-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; such as the water-powered astronomical clock by [[Al-Jazari]] in 1206,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Hill|first=Donald R.|authorlink=Donald Routledge Hill|title=Mechanical Engineering in the Medieval Near East|journal=[[Scientific American]]|date=May 1991|pages=64–69|ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the astrolabic clock by [[Ibn al-Shatir]] in the early 14th century.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|first=David A.|last=King|year=1983|title=The Astronomy of the Mamluks|journal=[[Isis (journal)|Isis]] |volume=74 |issue=4|pages=531–555 [545–546]|doi=10.1086/353360|ref=harv|url=https://semanticscholar.org/paper/f6d729951791821ed435a9819edbc6726650c3fe}}&lt;/ref&gt; The most sophisticated timekeeping astrolabes were the [[gear]]ed astrolabe mechanisms designed by [[Abū Rayhān Bīrūnī]] in the 11th century and by Muhammad ibn Abi Bakr in the 13th century. These devices functioned as timekeeping devices and also as [[calendar]]s.&lt;ref name=Hassan/&gt;

A sophisticated water-powered astronomical clock was built by [[Al-Jazari]] in 1206. This [[castle clock]] was a complex device that was about {{convert|11|ft|m}} high, and had multiple functions alongside timekeeping. It included a display of the [[zodiac]] and the solar and lunar paths, and a pointer in the shape of the [[Lunar phase|crescent moon]] which travelled across the top of a gateway, moved by a hidden cart and causing doors to open, each revealing a [[mannequin]], every hour.&lt;ref name=Hill2&gt;[[Donald Routledge Hill|Routledge Hill, Donald]], &quot;Mechanical Engineering in the Medieval Near East&quot;, ''[[Scientific American]]'', May 1991, pp. 64–9 ([[cf.]] [[Donald Routledge Hill]], [http://home.swipnet.se/islam/articles/HistoryofSciences.htm Mechanical Engineering]) {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080305162155/http://home.swipnet.se/islam/articles/HistoryofSciences.htm |date=March 5, 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Howard R. Turner (1997), ''Science in Medieval Islam: An Illustrated Introduction'', p. 184. [[University of Texas Press]], {{ISBN|0-292-78149-0}}.&lt;/ref&gt; It was possible to reset the length of day and night in order to account for the changing lengths of day and night throughout the year. This clock also featured a number of [[Automaton|automata]] including falcons and musicians who automatically played music when moved by levers operated by a hidden [[camshaft]] attached to a [[water wheel]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Ancient Discoveries&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title=Ancient Discoveries, Episode 11: Ancient Robots|publisher=[[History (U.S. TV channel)|History Channel]]|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rxjbaQl0ad8|accessdate=September 6, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Europe, there were the clocks constructed by [[Richard of Wallingford]] in [[St Albans]] by 1336, and by Giovanni [[Giovanni Dondi dell'Orologio|de Dondi]] in [[Padua, Italy|Padua]] from 1348 to 1364. They no longer exist, but detailed descriptions of their design and construction survive,&lt;ref name=&quot;north&quot;&gt;North, John. God's Clockmaker: Richard of Wallingford and the Invention of Time. London: Hambledon and London (2005).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;king&quot;&gt;King, Henry &quot;Geared to the Stars: the evolution of planetariums, orreries, and astronomical clocks&quot;, University of Toronto Press, 1978&lt;/ref&gt; and modern reproductions have been made.&lt;ref name=&quot;king&quot;/&gt; They illustrate how quickly the theory of the mechanical clock had been translated into practical constructions, and also that one of the many impulses to their development had been the desire of astronomers to investigate celestial phenomena.

Wallingford's clock had a large astrolabe-type dial, showing the sun, the moon's age, phase, and node, a star map, and possibly the planets. In addition, it had a [[Rota Fortunae|wheel of fortune]] and an indicator of the state of the tide at [[London Bridge]]. Bells rang every hour, the number of strokes indicating the time.&lt;ref name=&quot;north&quot;/&gt; Dondi's clock was a seven-sided construction, 1 metre high, with dials showing the time of day, including minutes, the motions of all the known planets, an automatic calendar of fixed and [[Moveable feast|movable feasts]], and an eclipse prediction hand rotating once every 18 years.&lt;ref name=&quot;king&quot;/&gt; It is not known how accurate or reliable these clocks would have been. They were probably adjusted manually every day to compensate for errors caused by wear and imprecise manufacture. Water clocks are sometimes still used today, and can be examined in places such as ancient castles and museums. The [[Salisbury cathedral clock|Salisbury Cathedral clock]], built in 1386, is considered to be the world's oldest surviving mechanical clock that strikes the hours.&lt;ref&gt;Singer, Charles, et al. ''Oxford History of Technology: volume II, from the Renaissance to the Industrial Revolution'' (OUP 1957) pp. 650–651&lt;/ref&gt;

===Spring-driven===

[[File:Renaissance Turret Clock.jpg|thumb|left|Renaissance Turret Clock, German, circa 1570]]
[[File:Matthew Norman carriage clock with winding key.jpg|thumb|Spring driven Matthew Norman carriage clock with winding key]]
Clockmakers developed their art in various ways. Building smaller clocks was a technical challenge, as was improving accuracy and reliability. Clocks could be impressive showpieces to demonstrate skilled craftsmanship, or less expensive, mass-produced items for domestic use. The escapement in particular was an important factor affecting the clock's accuracy, so many different mechanisms were tried.

Spring-driven clocks appeared during the 15th century,&lt;ref name=&quot;White2&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=White|first=Lynn Jr.|title=Medieval Technology and Social Change|publisher=Oxford Univ. Press|year=1966|location=New York|isbn=978-0-19-500266-9|pages=[https://archive.org/details/medievaltechnolo00whit/page/126 126–127]|url=https://archive.org/details/medievaltechnolo00whit/page/126}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Usher|first=Abbot Payson|title=A History of Mechanical Inventions|year=1988|publisher=Courier Dover|isbn=978-0-486-25593-4|url=https://books.google.com/?id=xuDDqqa8FlwC&amp;pg=PA305|page=305}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Rossum&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Dohrn-van Rossum|first=Gerhar|title=History of the Hour: Clocks and Modern Temporal Orders|publisher=Univ. of Chicago Press|year=1997|url=https://books.google.com/?id=53K32RiEigMC&amp;pg=PA121|isbn=978-0-226-15510-4|page=121}}&lt;/ref&gt; although they are often erroneously credited to [[Nuremberg]] watchmaker [[Peter Henlein]] (or Henle, or Hele) around 1511.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Milham|first=Willis I.|title=Time and Timekeepers |year=1945 |publisher=MacMillan|location=New York|isbn=978-0-7808-0008-3|page=121}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopedia|title=Clock|encyclopedia=The New Encyclopædia Britannica|volume=4|page=747|publisher=Univ. of Chicago|year=1974|url=https://books.google.com/?id=Eb0qAAAAMAAJ&amp;dq=Peter+Henlein+mainspring&amp;q=peter+Henlein#search|isbn=978-0-85229-290-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Anzovin|first=Steve|author2=Podell, Janet|title=Famous First Facts: A record of first happenings, discoveries, and inventions in world history|year=2000|publisher=H.W. Wilson|isbn=978-0-8242-0958-2|page=[https://archive.org/details/famousfirstfacts00anzo/page/440 440]|url=https://archive.org/details/famousfirstfacts00anzo/page/440}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The earliest existing spring driven clock is the chamber clock given to Phillip the Good, Duke of Burgundy, around 1430, now in the [[Germanisches Nationalmuseum]].&lt;ref name=&quot;White&quot; /&gt; Spring power presented clockmakers with a new problem: how to keep the clock [[movement (clockwork)|movement]] running at a constant rate as the spring ran down. This resulted in the invention of the ''[[stackfreed]]'' and the [[fusee (horology)|fusee]] in the 15th century, and many other innovations, down to the invention of the modern ''going [[barrel (horology)|barrel]]'' in 1760.

Early clock dials did not indicate minutes and seconds. A clock with a dial indicating minutes was illustrated in a 1475 manuscript by Paulus Almanus,&lt;ref name=haencyc&gt;p. 529, &quot;Time and timekeeping instruments&quot;, ''History of astronomy: an encyclopedia'', John Lankford, Taylor &amp; Francis, 1997, {{ISBN|0-8153-0322-X}}.&lt;/ref&gt; and some 15th-century clocks in [[Germany]] indicated minutes and seconds.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://books.google.com/?id=xuDDqqa8FlwC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=A+history+of+mechanical+inventions,+Abbott+Payson+Usher#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|page=209|title=A history of mechanical inventions |first=Abbott Payson|last=Usher|publisher=Courier Dover Publications|year=1988|isbn=978-0-486-25593-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;
An early record of a seconds hand on a clock dates back to about 1560 on a clock now in the Fremersdorf collection.&lt;ref name=Landes&gt;{{cite book | first1=David S. |last1=Landes |title=Revolution in Time | location=Cambridge, Massachusetts| publisher= Harvard University Press |year= 1983 | isbn = 978-0-674-76802-4 |title-link=Revolution in Time }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|417–418}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first1=Johann |last1=Willsberger |title=Clocks &amp; watches |location=New York |publisher=Dial Press |year=1975 |isbn=978-0-8037-4475-2 |url=https://archive.org/details/clockswatchessix0000will }} full page color photo: 4th caption page, 3rd photo thereafter (neither pages nor photos are numbered).&lt;/ref&gt;

During the 15th and 16th centuries, clockmaking flourished, particularly in the metalworking towns of [[Nuremberg]] and [[Augsburg]], and in [[Blois]], France. Some of the more basic table clocks have only one time-keeping hand, with the dial between the hour markers being divided into four equal parts making the clocks readable to the nearest 15 minutes. Other clocks were exhibitions of craftsmanship and skill, incorporating astronomical indicators and musical movements. The [[escapement#Cross-beat escapement|cross-beat escapement]] was invented in 1584 by [[Jost Bürgi]], who also developed the [[remontoire]]. Bürgi's clocks were a great improvement in accuracy as they were correct to within a minute a day.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |editor1=Lance Day |editor2=Ian McNeil |title=Biographical dictionary of the history of technology |publisher=[[Routledge]] (Routledge Reference) |year=1996 |page=116 |isbn=978-0-415-06042-4 |url=https://books.google.com/?id=nqAOAAAAQAAJ&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PA116#v=onepage}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=Table clock c. 1650 attributed to Hans Buschmann that uses technical inventions by Jost Bürgi |publisher=[[The British Museum]] |url=https://www.britishmuseum.org/explore/highlights/highlight_objects/pe_mla/t/table_clock_attributed_to_hans.aspx |accessdate=2010-04-11 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; These clocks helped the 16th-century astronomer [[Tycho Brahe]] to observe astronomical events with much greater precision than before.{{citation needed|date=November 2014}}{{how|date=November 2014}}

=== Pendulum ===
[[File:Christiaan Huygens-painting.jpeg|thumb|right|180px|The Dutch polymath and [[horologist]] [[Christiaan Huygens]], the inventor of first [[precision timekeeping|precision timekeeping devices]] ([[pendulum clock]] and [[History of timekeeping devices#Spiral-hairspring watch|spiral-hairspring watch]]).&lt;ref&gt;Macey, Samuel L. (ed.): ''Encyclopedia of Time''. (NYC: Garland Publishing, 1994, {{ISBN|0-8153-0615-6}}); in ''Clocks and Watches: The Leap to Precision'' by William J.H. Andrewes, pp. 123–127&lt;/ref&gt;]]
{{multiple image
| footer = From its invention in 1656 by Christiaan Huygens until the 1930s, the [[pendulum clock]] was the world's most precise timekeeper, accounting for its widespread use.
| image1 = Huygens first pendulum clock - front view.png
| width1 = 120
| image2 = Huygens first pendulum clock.png
| width2 = 112
}}
The next development in accuracy occurred after 1656 with the invention of the [[pendulum clock]]. [[Galileo Galilei|Galileo]] had the idea to use a swinging bob to regulate the motion of a time-telling device earlier in the 17th century. [[Christiaan Huygens]], however, is usually credited as the inventor. He determined the mathematical formula that related pendulum length to time (about 99.4&amp;nbsp;cm or 39.1&amp;nbsp;inches for the one second movement) and had the first pendulum-driven clock made. The first model clock was built in 1657 in [[the Hague]], but it was in [[England]] that the idea was taken up.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.historyworld.net/wrldhis/PlainTextHistories.asp?groupid=2324&amp;HistoryID=ac08&amp;gtrack=pthc|title=History of Clocks}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[longcase clock]] (also known as the ''grandfather clock'') was created to house the pendulum and works by the English clockmaker William Clement in 1670 or 1671. It was also at this time that clock cases began to be made of wood and [[clock face]]s to utilize [[Vitreous enamel|enamel]] as well as hand-painted ceramics.

In 1670, William Clement created the [[anchor escapement]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://inventors.about.com/library/weekly/aa072801a.htm |title=The History of Mechanical Pendulum Clocks and Quartz Clocks |work=about.com |year=2012 |accessdate=16 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; an improvement over Huygens' crown escapement. Clement also introduced the pendulum suspension spring in 1671. The concentric minute hand was added to the clock by [[Daniel Quare]], a London clockmaker and others, and the second hand was first introduced.

===Hairspring===
In 1675, Huygens and [[Robert Hooke]] invented the [[spiral balance|spiral balance spring]], or the hairspring, designed to control the oscillating speed of the [[balance wheel]]. This crucial advance finally made accurate pocket watches possible. The great English clockmaker, [[Thomas Tompion]], was one of the first to use this mechanism successfully in his [[pocket watch]]es, and he adopted the minute hand which, after a variety of designs were trialled, eventually stabilised into the modern-day configuration.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=History Of Clocks|url=http://www.historyworld.net/wrldhis/PlainTextHistories.asp?groupid=2324&amp;HistoryID=ac08&amp;gtrack=pthc}}&lt;/ref&gt; The rack and snail striking mechanism for [[striking clock]]s, was introduced during the 17th century and had distinct advantages over the 'countwheel' (or 'locking plate') mechanism. During the 20th century there was a common misconception that [[Edward Barlow (priest)|Edward Barlow]] invented ''[[rack and snail]]'' striking. In fact, his invention was connected with a repeating mechanism employing the rack and snail.&lt;ref&gt;Horological Journal, September 2011, pp. 408–412.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[repeater (horology)|repeating clock]], that chimes the number of hours (or even minutes) on demand was invented by either Quare or Barlow in 1676. [[George Graham (clockmaker)|George Graham]] invented the [[Escapement#Deadbeat escapement|deadbeat escapement]] for clocks in 1720.

===Marine chronometer===
A major stimulus to improving the accuracy and reliability of clocks was the importance of precise time-keeping for navigation. The position of a ship at sea could be determined with reasonable accuracy if a navigator could refer to a clock that lost or gained less than about 10 seconds per day. This clock could not contain a pendulum, which would be virtually useless on a rocking ship. In 1714, the British government offered large [[longitude prize|financial rewards]] to the value of 20,000 pounds,&lt;ref name=&quot;Rigden2003&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=John S. Rigden|title=Hydrogen: The Essential Element|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=FhFxn_lUvz0C|year=2003|publisher=Harvard University Press|isbn=978-0-674-01252-3|page=185}}&lt;/ref&gt; for anyone who could determine longitude accurately. [[John Harrison]], who dedicated his life to improving the accuracy of his clocks, later received considerable sums under the Longitude Act.

In 1735, Harrison built his first [[marine chronometer|chronometer]], which he steadily improved on over the next thirty years before submitting it for examination. The clock had many innovations, including the use of bearings to reduce friction, weighted balances to compensate for the ship's pitch and roll in the sea and the use of two different metals to reduce the problem of expansion from heat. The chronometer was tested in 1761 by Harrison's son and by the end of 10 weeks the clock was in error by less than 5 seconds.&lt;ref name=gould&gt;{{cite book|author=Gould, Rupert T.|authorlink=Rupert Gould|title=The Marine Chronometer. Its History and Development|location=London|publisher=J.D. Potter|pages=66|year=1923|isbn=978-0-907462-05-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Mass production===
[[File:Vintage Elgin Gold-Filled Pocket Watch, Hunter Case, Size 16s, Pendant Set, 15 Jewels, Circa 1909 (15244052313).jpg|thumb|left|An Elgin Pocket watch]]
[[File:Vintage Elgin Gold-Filled Pocket Watch, Hunter Case, Size 16s, Pendant Set, 15 Jewels, Circa 1909 (15676168588).jpg|thumb|The same opened up pocket watch]]
The British had predominated in watch manufacture for much of the 17th and 18th centuries, but maintained a system of production that was geared towards high quality products for the elite.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/?id=cVUSauNST8EC&amp;dq=British+Watch+Company+mass+production|title=Manufacturing Time: Global Competition in the Watch Industry, 1795–2000|author=Glasmeier, Amy|year=2000|publisher=Guilford Press|accessdate=2013-02-07|isbn=978-1-57230-589-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although there was an attempt to modernise clock manufacture with [[mass production]] techniques and the application of duplicating tools and machinery by the British Watch Company in 1843, it was in the [[United States]] that this system took off. In 1816, [[Eli Terry]] and some other Connecticut clockmakers developed a way of mass-producing clocks by using [[interchangeable parts]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Eli Terry Mass-Produced Box Clock.&quot; Smithsonian The National Museum of American History. Web. 21 Sep. 2015.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Aaron Lufkin Dennison]] started a factory in 1851 in [[Massachusetts]] that also used interchangeable parts, and by 1861 was running a successful enterprise incorporated as the [[Waltham Watch Company]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Roe1916&quot;&gt;{{citation | last = Roe | first = Joseph Wickham | title = English and American Tool Builders | publisher = Yale University Press | year = 1916 | location = New Haven, Connecticut | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=X-EJAAAAIAAJ&amp;printsec=titlepage | lccn = 16011753}}. Reprinted by McGraw-Hill, New York and London, 1926 ({{LCCN|27024075}}); and by Lindsay Publications, Inc., Bradley, Illinois, ({{ISBN|978-0-917914-73-7}}).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Structures of Change in the Mechanical Age: Technological Invention in the United States 1790–1865 |last=Thomson |first=Ross |year=2009 |publisher=The Johns Hopkins University Press |location=Baltimore, MD |isbn=978-0-8018-9141-0 |page=[https://archive.org/details/structuresofchan0000thom/page/34 34] |url=https://archive.org/details/structuresofchan0000thom/page/34 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{breakafterimages}}

===Early electric===
{{main|Electric clock}}
[[File:Pendule electrique l maitrier 05117.jpg|thumb|upright=0.6|Early French electromagnetic clock]]
In 1815, [[Francis Ronalds]] published the [[Electric clock#History|first electric clock]] powered by [[Voltaic pile#Dry pile|dry pile]] batteries.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Sir Francis Ronalds: Father of the Electric Telegraph|last=Ronalds|first=B.F.|publisher=Imperial College Press|year=2016|isbn=978-1-78326-917-4|location=London|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Alexander Bain (inventor)|Alexander Bain]], Scottish clockmaker, patented the [[electric clock]] in 1840. The electric clock's mainspring is wound either with an [[electric motor]] or with an [[electromagnet]] and armature. In 1841, he first patented the [[Electromagnetism|electromagnetic]] pendulum. By the end of the nineteenth century, the advent of the dry cell battery made it feasible to use electric power in clocks. Spring or weight driven clocks that use electricity, either [[alternating current]] (AC) or [[direct current]] (DC), to rewind the spring or raise the weight of a mechanical clock would be classified as an [[electromechanical clock]]. This classification would also apply to clocks that employ an electrical impulse to propel the pendulum. In electromechanical clocks the electricity serves no time keeping function. These types of clocks were made as individual timepieces but more commonly used in synchronized time installations in schools, businesses, factories, railroads and government facilities as a [[master clock]] and [[slave clocks]].

Electric clocks that are powered from the [[Alternating current|AC]] supply often use [[synchronous motor]]s. The supply current alternates with a frequency of 50&amp;nbsp;[[hertz]] in many countries, and 60&amp;nbsp;hertz in others. The [[Rotor (electric)|rotor]] of the motor rotates at a speed that is related to the alternation frequency. Appropriate gearing converts this rotation speed to the correct ones for the hands of the analog clock. The development of [[electronics]] in the 20th century led to clocks with no clockwork parts at all. Time in these cases is measured in several ways, such as by the alternation of the AC supply, vibration of a [[tuning fork]], the behaviour of [[quartz]] crystals, or the quantum vibrations of atoms. Electronic circuits divide these high-frequency oscillations to slower ones that drive the time display. Even mechanical clocks have since come to be largely powered by batteries, removing the need for winding.

===Quartz===
[[File:Inside QuartzCrystal-Tuningfork.jpg|thumb|Picture of a quartz crystal resonator, used as the timekeeping component in quartz watches and clocks, with the case removed. It is formed in the shape of a tuning fork. Most such quartz clock crystals vibrate at a frequency of {{val|32768|u=Hz}}.]]
The [[piezoelectric]] properties of crystalline [[quartz]] were discovered by [[Jacques Curie|Jacques]] and [[Pierre Curie]] in 1880.&lt;ref name=nistrevolution&gt;{{cite web|url= http://physics.nist.gov/GenInt/Time/revol.html |title= A Revolution in Timekeeping |accessdate= 30 April 2008 |publisher= NIST| archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20080409174853/http://physics.nist.gov/GenInt/Time/revol.html | archivedate = April 9, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aip.org/history/curie/pierre.htm |title=Pierre Curie |accessdate=8 April 2008|publisher=[[American Institute of Physics]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first crystal oscillator was invented in 1917 by [[Alexander M. Nicholson]] after which, the first quartz crystal oscillator was built by [[Walter Guyton Cady|Walter G. Cady]] in 1921.&lt;ref name=Marrison /&gt; In 1927 the first [[quartz clock]] was built by Warren Marrison and J.W. Horton at [[Bell Telephone Laboratories]] in Canada.&lt;ref name=&quot;Marrison2&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Marrison|first=W.A.|author2=Horton, J.W. |title=Precision determination of frequency|journal=I.R.E. Proc.|volume=16|pages=137–154|date=February 1928|doi=10.1109/JRPROC.1928.221372|ref=harv|issue=2}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Marrison&quot; /&gt; The following decades saw the development of quartz clocks as precision time measurement devices in laboratory settings—the bulky and delicate counting electronics, built with [[vacuum tube]]s, limited their practical use elsewhere. The National Bureau of Standards (now [[NIST]]) based the time standard of the United States on quartz clocks from late 1929 until the 1960s, when it changed to atomic clocks.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sullivan&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Sullivan|first=D.B.|year=2001|title=Time and frequency measurement at NIST: The first 100&amp;nbsp;years|publisher=Time and Frequency Division, National Institute of Standards and Technology|url=http://tf.nist.gov/timefreq/general/pdf/1485.pdf|page=5|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110927062444/http://tf.nist.gov/timefreq/general/pdf/1485.pdf|archivedate=September 27, 2011|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1969, [[Seiko]] produced the world's first quartz [[Watch|wristwatch]], the [[Astron (wristwatch)|Astron]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| publisher = IEEE History Center | title = Electronic Quartz Wristwatch, 1969 | url=http://ethw.org/Milestones:Electronic_Quartz_Wristwatch,_1969 | accessdate = 11 July 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Their inherent accuracy and low cost of production resulted in the subsequent proliferation of quartz clocks and watches.&lt;ref name=nistrevolution /&gt;

===Atomic===
Currently, [[atomic clock]]s are the most accurate clocks in existence. They are considerably more accurate than [[quartz clock]]s as they can be accurate to within a few seconds over trillions of years.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/?id=DNwfG5hQ7-YC&amp;printsec=frontcover#PRA1-PA484,M1|title=Sky and Ocean Joined: The U.S. Naval Observatory, 1830–2000|last=Dick|first=Stephen|page=484|publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]]|isbn=978-0-521-81599-4|year=2002}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.nist.gov/pml/div688/clock-082213.cfm |title=NIST Ytterbium Atomic Clocks Set Record for Stability |first=Laura |last=Ost |date=22 August 2013 |website= |publisher=NIST |accessdate=30 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Atomic clocks were first theorized by [[Lord Kelvin]] in 1879.&lt;ref&gt;Sir William Thomson (Lord Kelvin) and Peter Guthrie Tait, ''Treatise on Natural Philosophy'', 2nd ed. (Cambridge, England: Cambridge University Press, 1879), vol. 1, part 1, [https://books.google.com/books?id=naXkAAAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA227&amp;lpg=PA227&amp;dq=atoms#v=onepage&amp;q=atoms&amp;f=false p. 227].&lt;/ref&gt; In the 1930s the development of [[Nuclear magnetic resonance|Magnetic resonance]] created practical method for doing this.&lt;ref name=Lombardi&gt;{{Cite journal|author1=M.A. Lombardi |author2=T.P. Heavner |author3=S.R. Jefferts |year=2007|title=NIST Primary Frequency Standards and the Realization of the SI Second|url=http://tf.nist.gov/general/pdf/2039.pdf|journal=Journal of Measurement Science|volume=2|issue=4|page=74|doi=}}&lt;/ref&gt; A prototype [[ammonia]] [[maser]] device was built in 1949 at the U.S. [[National Bureau of Standards]] (NBS, now [[National Institute of Standards and Technology|NIST]]). Although it was less accurate than existing [[quartz clock]]s, it served to demonstrate the concept.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite conference|author=Sullivan, D.B.|year=2001|title=Time and frequency measurement at NIST: The first 100 years|url=http://tf.nist.gov/timefreq/general/pdf/1485.pdf|work=2001 IEEE International Frequency Control Symposium|pages=4–17|publisher=[[National Institute of Standards and Technology|NIST]]|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110927062444/http://tf.nist.gov/timefreq/general/pdf/1485.pdf|archivedate=September 27, 2011|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NISTshistorymeasuring&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://tf.nist.gov/general/museum/847history.htm|title=Time and Frequency Division|publisher=National Institute of Standards and Technology|accessdate=1 April 2008|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080415135733/http://tf.nist.gov/general/museum/847history.htm|archivedate=April 15, 2008|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=nistatomic&gt;{{cite web|url=http://physics.nist.gov/GenInt/Time/atomic.html |title=The &quot;Atomic Age&quot; of Time Standards |accessdate=2 May 2008 |publisher=National Institute of Standards and Technology| archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20080412040352/http://physics.nist.gov/GenInt/Time/atomic.html| archivedate = April 12, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first accurate atomic clock, a [[caesium standard]] based on a certain transition of the [[caesium-133]] atom, was built by [[Louis Essen]] in 1955 at the [[National Physical Laboratory, UK|National Physical Laboratory]] in the UK.&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite journal | last1 = Essen | first1 = L. | authorlink1 = Louis Essen| last2 = Parry | first2 = J.V.L. | doi = 10.1038/176280a0  |bibcode=1955Natur.176..280E| title = An Atomic Standard of Frequency and Time Interval: A Cæsium Resonator | journal = Nature | volume = 176 | issue = 4476 | page = 280 | year = 1955 | pmid =  | pmc = }}&lt;/ref&gt; Calibration of the caesium standard atomic clock was carried out by the use of the astronomical time scale ''[[ephemeris time]]'' (ET).&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite journal|author1=W. Markowitz |author2=R.G. Hall |author3=L. Essen |author4=J.V.L. Parry |year=1958|title=Frequency of cesium in terms of ephemeris time|journal=[[Physical Review Letters]]|volume=1|issue=3 |pages=105–107|doi=10.1103/PhysRevLett.1.105|bibcode=1958PhRvL...1..105M}}&lt;/ref&gt; As of 2013, the most stable atomic clocks are [[ytterbium]] clocks, which are stable to within less than two parts in 1 quintillion ({{val|2|e=-18}}).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.nist.gov/pml/div688/clock-082213.cfm |title=NIST Ytterbium Atomic Clocks Set Record for Stability |first=Laura |last=Ost |date=22 August 2013 |website= |publisher=NIST |accessdate=30 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Operation==
[[File:A chiming clock's mechanism.jpg|thumb|A chiming clock's mechanism.]]
The invention of the mechanical clock in the 13th century initiated a change in timekeeping methods from [[Continuous function|continuous]] processes, such as the motion of the [[gnomon]]'s shadow on a [[sundial]] or the flow of liquid in a [[water clock]], to periodic [[oscillatory]] processes, such as the swing of a [[pendulum]] or the vibration of a [[crystal oscillator|quartz crystal]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Cipolla&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Marrison1&quot;&gt;{{cite journal
 | last1  = Warren A.
 | first1 = Marrison
 | title = The Evolution of the Quartz Crystal Clock
 | journal = Bell System Tech. J.
 | volume = 27
 | issue = 3
 | pages = 511–515
 | date = July 1948
 | url = https://archive.org/details/bstj27-3-510
 | issn =
 | doi = 10.1002/j.1538-7305.1948.tb01343.x
 | id =
 | accessdate = February 25, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; which had the potential for more accuracy. All modern clocks use oscillation.

Although the mechanisms they use vary, all oscillating clocks, mechanical, digital and atomic, work similarly and can be divided into analogous parts.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jespersen&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Jespersen|first=James|author2=Fitz-Randolph, Jane |author3=Robb, John |title=From Sundials to Atomic Clocks: Understanding Time and Frequency|publisher=Courier Dover|year=1999|location=New York|url=https://books.google.com/?id=Z7chuo4ebUAC&amp;pg=PA42&amp;dq=clock+resonance+pendulum|isbn=978-0-486-40913-9|page=39}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=How clocks work|work=InDepthInfo|publisher=W. J. Rayment|year=2007|url=http://www.indepthinfo.com/clocks/index.shtml|accessdate=2008-06-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Milham&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Milham|first=Willis I.|title=Time and Timekeepers|publisher=MacMillan|year=1945|location=New York|isbn=978-0-7808-0008-3|page=74}}&lt;/ref&gt; They consist of an object that repeats the same motion over and over again, an ''[[oscillator]]'', with a precisely constant time interval between each repetition, or 'beat'. Attached to the oscillator is a ''controller'' device, which sustains the oscillator's motion by replacing the energy it loses to [[friction]], and converts its oscillations into a series of pulses. The pulses are then counted by some type of ''counter'', and the number of counts is converted into convenient units, usually seconds, minutes, hours, etc. Finally some kind of ''indicator'' displays the result in human readable form.

===Power source===

[[File:Mainspring wind-up keys.jpg|thumb|left|Keys of various sizes for winding up mainsprings on clocks.]]
* In mechanical clocks, the power source is typically either a weight suspended from a cord or chain wrapped around a [[pulley]], [[sprocket]] or drum; or a spiral [[Spring (device)|spring]] called a [[mainspring]].  Mechanical clocks must be ''wound'' periodically, usually by turning a knob or key or by pulling on the free end of the chain, to store [[energy]] in the weight or spring to keep the clock running.
* In [[electric clock]]s, the power source is either a [[Battery (electricity)|battery]] or the [[Mains power|AC power line]]. In clocks that use AC power, a small [[backup battery]] is often included to keep the clock running if it is unplugged temporarily from the wall or during a power outage.  Battery powered analog wall clocks are available that operate over 15 years between battery changes.
{{breakafterimages}}

===Oscillator===
[[File:Split-flap clock.jpg|thumb|This clock used the 60&amp;nbsp;Hz of electrical power, and features a split-flap physical for displaying the time numbers]]
The timekeeping element in every modern clock is a [[harmonic oscillator]], a physical object ([[resonator]]) that vibrates or [[oscillate]]s repetitively at a precisely constant [[frequency]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Marrison&quot; /&gt;
* In mechanical clocks, this is either a [[pendulum]] or a [[balance wheel]].
* In some early electronic clocks and watches such as the [[Accutron]], it is a [[tuning fork]].
* In [[quartz clock]]s and watches, it is a [[crystal oscillator|quartz crystal]].
* In [[atomic clock]]s, it is the vibration of [[electron]]s in [[atom]]s as they emit [[microwave]]s.
* In early mechanical clocks before 1657, it was a crude balance wheel or [[Verge escapement|foliot]] which was not a harmonic oscillator because it lacked a [[balance spring]]. As a result, they were very inaccurate, with errors of perhaps an hour a day.&lt;ref&gt;Milham, 1945, p. 85&lt;/ref&gt;
The advantage of a harmonic oscillator over other forms of oscillator is that it employs [[resonance]] to vibrate at a precise natural [[resonant frequency]] or &quot;beat&quot; dependent only on its physical characteristics, and resists vibrating at other rates. The possible precision achievable by a harmonic oscillator is measured by a parameter called its [[Q factor|Q]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Quality factor, Q|work=Glossary|publisher=Time and Frequency Division, NIST (National Institute of Standards and Technology)|year=2008|url=http://tf.nist.gov/general/enc-q.htm|accessdate=2008-06-04|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080504160852/http://tf.nist.gov/general/enc-q.htm|archivedate=May 4, 2008|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=Z7chuo4ebUAC&amp;pg=PA44&amp;sig=iBunChocEtJoeKS5p5IgJ1oyl4U Jespersen 1999, pp. 47–50]&lt;/ref&gt; or quality factor, which increases (other things being equal) with its resonant frequency.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Riehle|first=Fritz|title=Frequency Standards: Basics and Applications|journal=Frequency Standards: Basics and Applications|publisher=Wiley VCH Verlag &amp; Co.|year=2004|location=Germany|page=9|url=https://books.google.com/?id=WZ34pQV-DXMC&amp;pg=PA9&amp;dq=Q+linewidth+%22split+the+line%22|isbn=978-3-527-40230-4|bibcode=2004fsba.book.....R}}&lt;/ref&gt; This is why there has been a long term trend toward higher frequency oscillators in clocks. Balance wheels and pendulums always include a means of adjusting the rate of the timepiece. Quartz timepieces sometimes include a rate screw that adjusts a [[capacitor]] for that purpose. Atomic clocks are [[Standard (technical)|primary standards]], and their rate cannot be adjusted.

====Synchronized or slave clocks====
[[Image:Greenwich clock 1-manipulated.jpg|thumb|Shepherd Gate Clock received its timing signal from within the observatory]]
Some clocks rely for their accuracy on an external oscillator; that is, they are automatically [[Synchronization|synchronized]] to a more accurate clock:
* [[Slave clock]]s, used in large institutions and schools from the 1860s to the 1970s, kept time with a pendulum, but were wired to a [[master clock]] in the building, and periodically received a signal to synchronize them with the master, often on the hour.&lt;ref&gt;Milham, 1945, pp. 325–328&lt;/ref&gt; Later versions without pendulums were triggered by a pulse from the master clock and certain sequences used to force rapid synchronization following a power failure.
* [[Electric clock|Synchronous electric clocks]] do not have an internal oscillator, but count cycles of the 50 or 60 [[Hertz|Hz]] oscillation of the [[Mains power|AC power line]], which is synchronized by the utility to a precision oscillator. The counting may be done electronically, usually in clocks with digital displays, or, in analog clocks, the AC may drive a [[synchronous motor]] which rotates an exact fraction of a revolution for every cycle of the line voltage, and drives the gear train.  Although changes in the [[Electric grid|grid]] line frequency due to load variations may cause the clock to temporarily gain or lose several seconds during the course of a day, the total number of cycles per 24 hours is maintained extremely accurately by the utility company, so that the clock keeps time accurately over long periods.
* Computer [[real time clock]]s keep time with a quartz crystal, but can be periodically (usually weekly) synchronized over the [[Internet]] to atomic clocks ([[Coordinated Universal Time|UTC]]), using the [[Network Time Protocol]] (NTP). Sometimes computers on a [[local area network]] (LAN) get their time from a single local server which is maintained accurately.
* [[Radio clock]]s keep time with a quartz crystal, but are periodically synchronized to [[radio time signal|time signals]] transmitted from dedicated [[Radio clock#List of radio time signal stations|standard time radio stations]] or [[satellite navigation]] signals, which are set by [[atomic clock]]s.

===Controller===
This has the dual function of keeping the oscillator running by giving it 'pushes' to replace the energy lost to [[friction]], and converting its vibrations into a series of pulses that serve to measure the time.
* In mechanical clocks, this is the [[escapement]], which gives precise pushes to the swinging pendulum or balance wheel, and releases one gear tooth of the ''escape wheel'' at each swing, allowing all the clock's wheels to move forward a fixed amount with each swing.
* In electronic clocks this is an [[Electronic oscillator|electronic oscillator circuit]] that gives the vibrating quartz crystal or tuning fork tiny 'pushes', and generates a series of electrical pulses, one for each vibration of the crystal, which is called the [[clock signal]].
* In [[atomic clock]]s the controller is an evacuated [[microwave]] [[Cavity resonator|cavity]] attached to a microwave [[Electronic oscillator|oscillator]] controlled by a [[microprocessor]]. A thin gas of [[caesium]] atoms is released into the cavity where they are exposed to [[microwaves]]. A laser measures how many atoms have absorbed the microwaves, and an electronic [[feedback]] control system called a [[phase-locked loop]] tunes the microwave oscillator until it is at the frequency that causes the atoms to vibrate and absorb the microwaves. Then the microwave signal is divided by [[digital counter]]s to become the [[clock signal]].&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=Z7chuo4ebUAC&amp;pg=PA61&amp;sig=r7PLMbI4rhAgfGkfBS-MCJEBkVs Jespersen 1999, pp. 52–62]&lt;/ref&gt;
In mechanical clocks, the low [[Q factor|Q]] of the balance wheel or pendulum oscillator made them very sensitive to the disturbing effect of the impulses of the escapement, so the escapement had a great effect on the accuracy of the clock, and many escapement designs were tried. The higher Q of resonators in electronic clocks makes them relatively insensitive to the disturbing effects of the drive power, so the driving oscillator circuit is a much less critical component.&lt;ref name=&quot;Marrison&quot; /&gt;

===Counter chain===
This counts the pulses and adds them up to get traditional time units of [[second]]s, [[minute]]s, [[hour]]s, etc. It usually has a provision for ''setting'' the clock by manually entering the correct time into the counter.
* In mechanical clocks this is done mechanically by a [[gear train]], known as the [[wheel train (horology)|wheel train]]. The gear train also has a second function; to transmit mechanical power from the power source to run the oscillator. There is a friction coupling called the 'cannon pinion' between the gears driving the hands and the rest of the clock, allowing the hands to be turned to set the time.&lt;ref&gt;Milham, 1945, p. 113&lt;/ref&gt;
* In digital clocks a series of [[integrated circuit]] [[counter (digital)|counters]] or dividers add the pulses up [[Digital data|digitally]], using [[binary numeral system|binary]] logic. Often pushbuttons on the case allow the hour and minute counters to be incremented and decremented to set the time.

===Indicator===
[[File:Cuckoo strikes the 8th hour.ogv|thumb|right|A [[Cuckoo clock]] with mechanical [[automaton]] and sound producer striking on the 8th hour on the analog dial.]]
This displays the count of seconds, minutes, hours, etc. in a human readable form.
* The earliest mechanical clocks in the 13th century didn't have a visual indicator and signalled the time [[wikt:audible|audibly]] by striking [[bell (instrument)|bells]]. Many clocks to this day are [[striking clock]]s which strike the hour.
* Analog clocks display time with an analog [[clock face]], which consists of a dial with the numbers 1 through 12 or 24, the hours in the day, around the outside.   The hours are indicated with an [[hour hand]], which makes one or two revolutions in a day, while the minutes are indicated by a [[Clock face|minute hand]], which makes one revolution per hour.  In mechanical clocks a gear train drives the hands; in electronic clocks the circuit produces pulses every second which drive a [[stepper motor]] and gear train, which move the hands.
* [[Digital clock]]s display the time in periodically changing [[numerical digit|digits]] on a digital [[display device|display]].  A common misconception is that a digital clock is more accurate than an analog wall clock, but the indicator type is separate and apart from the accuracy of the timing source.
* [[Talking clock]]s and the [[speaking clock]] services provided by telephone companies speak the time audibly, using either recorded or digitally [[Voice synthesis|synthesized voices]].

==Types==
Clocks can be classified by the type of time display, as well as by the method of timekeeping.

===Time display methods===

====Analog====
{{See also|Clock face}}
[[File:Rew17h09 1977.jpg|thumb|A modern quartz clock with a 24-hour face]]
[[File:Picadillycircuslinearclock.jpg|thumb|right|A linear clock at [[London]]'s [[Piccadilly Circus tube station]]. The 24 hour band moves across the static map, keeping pace with the apparent movement of the sun above ground, and a pointer fixed on London points to the current time.]]

Analog clocks usually use a [[clock face]] which indicates time using rotating pointers called &quot;hands&quot; on a fixed numbered dial or dials.  The standard clock face, known universally throughout the world,  has a short &quot;hour hand&quot; which indicates the [[hour]] on a circular dial of 12 [[hour]]s, making two revolutions per day, and a longer &quot;minute hand&quot; which indicates the minutes in the current hour on the same dial, which is also divided into 60 minutes. It may also have a &quot;second hand&quot; which indicates the [[second]]s in the current minute. The only other widely used clock face today is the [[24 hour analog dial]],  because of the use of [[24 hour time]] in [[military]] organizations and timetables.  Before the modern clock face was standardized during the [[Industrial Revolution]], many other face designs were used throughout the years, including dials divided into 6, 8, 10, and 24 hours.  During the [[French Revolution]] the French government tried to introduce a [[10-hour clock]], as part of their decimal-based [[metric system]] of measurement, but it didn't catch on.  An Italian 6 hour clock was developed in the 18th century, presumably to save power (a clock or watch striking 24 times uses more power).

Another type of analog clock is the [[sundial]], which tracks the sun continuously, registering the time by the shadow position of its [[gnomon]]. Because the sun does not adjust to daylight saving time, users must add an hour during that time. Corrections must also be made for the [[equation of time]], and for the difference between the longitudes of the sundial and of the central meridian of the [[time zone]] that is being used (i.e. 15 degrees east of the [[prime meridian]] for each hour that the time zone is ahead of [[GMT]]). Sundials use some or part of the 24 hour analog dial. There also exist clocks which use a digital display despite having an analog mechanism—these are commonly referred to as [[flip clock]]s. Alternative systems have been proposed. For example, the &quot;Twelv&quot; clock &lt;!-- not a typo, see http://www.gizmag.com/go/6312/ --&gt;indicates the current hour using one of twelve colors, and indicates the minute by showing a proportion of a circular disk, similar to a [[Lunar phase|moon phase]].&lt;ref&gt;{{US Patent|7079452}}, {{US Patent|7221624}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Digital====
{{main|Digital clock}}
Digital clocks display a numeric representation of time. Two numeric display formats are commonly used on [[Digital data|digital]] clocks:
* the [[24-hour notation]] with hours ranging 00–23;
* the [[12-hour notation]] with AM/PM indicator, with hours indicated as 12AM, followed by 1AM–11AM, followed by 12PM, followed by 1PM–11PM (a notation mostly used in domestic environments).

Most digital clocks use electronic mechanisms and [[LCD]], [[LED]], or [[Vacuum fluorescent display|VFD]] displays; many other display technologies are used as well ([[cathode ray tube]]s, [[nixie tube]]s, etc.). After a reset, battery change or power failure, these clocks without a backup [[battery (electricity)|battery]] or [[capacitor]] either start counting from 12:00, or stay at 12:00, often with blinking digits indicating that the time needs to be set. Some newer clocks will reset themselves based on radio or Internet [[time server]]s that are tuned to national [[atomic clock]]s. Since the advent of digital clocks in the 1960s, the use of analog clocks has declined significantly.{{Citation needed|date=February 2020}}

Some clocks, called '[[flip clock]]s', have digital displays that work mechanically. The digits are painted on sheets of material which are mounted like the pages of a book. Once a minute, a page is turned over to reveal the next digit. These displays are usually easier to read in brightly lit conditions than LCDs or LEDs. Also, they do not go back to 12:00 after a power interruption. Flip clocks generally do not have electronic mechanisms. Usually, they are driven by [[Alternating current|AC]]-[[synchronous motor]]s.
&lt;gallery mode=&quot;packed&quot; heights=&quot;150px&quot; caption=&quot;Examples of digital clocks&quot;&gt;
Kanazawa Station Water Clock.jpg|Digital clock outside [[Kanazawa Station]] displaying the time by controlling valves on a fountain
Digital-clock-radio-basic hf.jpg|Basic digital clock radio
Analog clock with digital display.png|Diagram of a mechanical digital display of a [[flip clock]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;

====Hybrid (analog-digital)====
Clocks with analog quadrants, with a digital component, usually minutes and hours displayed analogously and seconds displayed in digital mode.

====Auditory====
{{Main|Talking clock}}
For convenience, distance, telephony or [[blindness]], auditory clocks present the time as sounds. The sound is either spoken [[natural language]], (e.g. &quot;The time is twelve thirty-five&quot;), or as auditory codes (e.g. number of sequential bell rings on the hour represents the number of the hour like the bell, [[Big Ben]]). Most telecommunication companies also provide a [[speaking clock]] service as well.

====Word====
[[File:Word clock wallpaper with comic speech bubble style.png|thumb|Software word clock]]
Word clocks are clocks that display the time visually using sentences. E.g.: &quot;It's about three o'clock.&quot; These clocks can be implemented in hardware or software.

====Projection====
{{Main|Projection clock}}
Some clocks, usually digital ones, include an optical [[Image projector|projector]] that shines a magnified image of the time display onto a screen or onto a surface such as an indoor ceiling or wall. The digits are large enough to be easily read, without using glasses, by persons with moderately imperfect vision, so the clocks are convenient for use in their bedrooms. Usually, the timekeeping circuitry has a battery as a backup source for an uninterrupted power supply to keep the clock on time, while the projection light only works when the unit is connected to an A.C. supply. Completely battery-powered portable versions resembling [[flashlight]]s are also available.

====Tactile====
Auditory and projection clocks can be used by people who are blind or have limited vision. There are also clocks for the blind that have displays that can be read by using the sense of touch. Some of these are similar to normal analog displays, but are constructed so the hands can be felt without damaging them. Another type is essentially digital, and uses devices that use a code such as [[Braille]] to show the digits so that they can be felt with the fingertips.

====Multi-display====
Some clocks have several displays driven by a single mechanism, and some others have several completely separate mechanisms in a single case. Clocks in public places often have several faces visible from different directions, so that the clock can be read from anywhere in the vicinity; all the faces show the same time. Other clocks show the current time in several time-zones. Watches that are intended to be carried by travellers often have two displays, one for the local time and the other for the time at home, which is useful for making pre-arranged phone calls. Some [[equation clock]]s have two displays, one showing [[Local mean time|mean time]] and the other [[Solar time#Apparent solar time|solar time]], as would be shown by a sundial. Some clocks have both analog and digital displays. Clocks with Braille displays usually also have conventional digits so they can be read by sighted people.

==Purposes==
[[File:Robbins NC Clock.jpg|thumb|upright|Many cities and towns traditionally have public clocks in a prominent location, such as a [[town square]] or [[city center]].  This one is on display at the center of the town of [[Robbins, North Carolina]].]]
[[File:Restoran Pozoj, Čakovec - stara ura.jpg|thumb|upright|An old clock in a restaurant in [[Croatia]]]]
Clocks are in homes, offices and many other places; smaller ones ([[watch]]es) are carried on the wrist or in a pocket; larger ones are in public places, e.g. a [[railway station]] or [[Church (building)|church]]. A small clock is often shown in a corner of [[computer display]]s, [[mobile phone]]s and many [[MP3 player]]s.

The primary purpose of a clock is to ''display'' the time. Clocks may also have the facility to make a loud alert signal at a specified time, typically to waken a sleeper at a preset time; they are referred to as ''alarm clocks''. The alarm may start at a low volume and become louder, or have the facility to be switched off for a few minutes then resume. Alarm clocks with visible indicators are sometimes used to indicate to children too young to read the time that the time for sleep has finished; they are sometimes called ''training clocks''.

A clock mechanism may be used to ''control'' a device according to time, e.g. a [[central heating]] system, a [[VCR]], or a [[time bomb]] (see: [[digital counter]]). Such mechanisms are usually called [[timer]]s. Clock mechanisms are also used to drive devices such as [[Solar tracker#Chronological tracker|solar trackers]] and [[Telescope mount#Equatorial mounts|astronomical telescopes]], which have to turn at accurately controlled speeds to counteract the rotation of the Earth.

Most [[digital computer]]s depend on an internal signal at constant frequency to synchronize processing; this is referred to as a [[clock signal]]. (A few research projects are developing CPUs based on [[asynchronous circuit]]s.) Some equipment, including computers, also maintains time and date for use as required; this is referred to as time-of-day clock, and is distinct from the system clock signal, although possibly based on counting its cycles.

In Chinese culture, [[Homophonic puns in Mandarin Chinese#Gifts|giving a clock]] ({{zh|t=送鐘|s=送钟|first=t|p=sòng zhōng}}) is often taboo, especially to the elderly as the term for this act [[Faux pas derived from Chinese pronunciation#Clock|is a homophone]] with the term for the act of attending another's funeral ({{zh|t={{linktext|送終}}|s={{linktext|送终}}|first=t|p={{linktext|sòngzhōng}}}}).&lt;ref name=&quot;Brown(2006)&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Brown|first=Ju|title=China, Japan, Korea Culture and Customs|year=2006|pages=57}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Seligman|first=Scott D.|title=Chinese business etiquette:: a guide to protocol, manners, and culture in the People's Republic of China|year=1999|publisher=Hachette Digital, Inc.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.sohu.com/a/160882715_578225 {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180105233649/http://www.sohu.com/a/160882715_578225 |date=January 5, 2018 }} 别人过节喜庆的时候，不送钟表。送终和送钟谐音。&lt;/ref&gt; A UK government official [[Susan Kramer]] gave a watch to [[Taipei]] mayor [[Ko Wen-je]] unaware of such a taboo which resulted in some professional embarrassment and a pursuant apology.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=BBC Staff|title=UK minister apologises for Taiwan watch gaffe|url=https://www.bbc.com/news/world-asia-30994307|date=26 January 2015|accessdate=29 January 2018|work=BBC News}}&lt;/ref&gt;

This homonymic pair works in both Mandarin and Cantonese, although in most parts of China only clocks and large bells, and not watches, are called &quot;''zhong''&quot;, and watches are commonly given as gifts in China.

However, should such a gift be given, the &quot;unluckiness&quot; of the gift can be countered by exacting a small monetary payment so the recipient is buying the clock and thereby counteracting the {{lang|zh|'送'}} (&quot;give&quot;) expression of the phrase.

===Time standards===
{{Main|Time standard|Atomic clock}}
For some scientific work timing of the utmost accuracy is essential. It is also necessary to have a standard of the maximum accuracy against which working clocks can be calibrated. An ideal clock would give the time to unlimited accuracy, but this is not realisable. Many physical processes, in particular including some [[Electronic transition|transitions]] between atomic [[energy level]]s, occur at exceedingly stable frequency; counting cycles of such a process can give a very accurate and consistent time—clocks which work this way are usually called [[atomic clock]]s. Such clocks are typically large, very expensive, require a controlled environment, and are far more accurate than required for most purposes; they are typically used in a [[Metrology#Laboratories|standards laboratory]].

===Navigation===
Until advances in the late twentieth century, [[navigation]] depended on the ability to measure [[latitude]] and [[longitude]]. Latitude can be determined through [[celestial navigation]]; the measurement of [[longitude]] requires accurate knowledge of time. This need was a major motivation for the development of accurate mechanical clocks. [[John Harrison]] created the first highly accurate [[marine chronometer]] in the mid-18th century. The [[Noon gun]] in [[Cape Town]] still fires an accurate signal to allow ships to check their [[marine chronometer|chronometers]]. Many buildings near major ports used to have (some still do) a large [[Time ball|ball]] mounted on a tower or mast arranged to drop at a pre-determined time, for the same purpose. While [[satellite navigation]] systems such as the [[Global Positioning System]] (GPS) require unprecedentedly accurate knowledge of time, this is supplied by equipment on the satellites; vehicles no longer need timekeeping equipment.

==Specific types==
[[File:Clock sculpture - Drexel University - IMG 7332.JPG|thumb|upright|A monumental conical pendulum clock by [[Eugène Farcot]], 1867. Drexel University, Philadelphia, USA.]]
{|
| By mechanism
| By function
| By style
|-
|style=&quot;width:30%;vertical-align:top&quot;| &lt;!-- by mechanism --&gt;
* [[Astronomical clock]]
* [[Atomic clock]]
* [[Candle clock]]
* [[Congreve clock]]
* [[Conical pendulum]] clock
* [[Digital clock]]
* [[Electric clock]]
* [[Analog clock with digital display|Flip clock]]
* [[Hourglass]]
* [[Incense clock]]
* [[Mechanical watch]]
* [[Oil-lamp clock]]
* [[Pendulum clock]]
* [[Pipe organ clock]]
* [[Projection clock]]
* [[Pulsar clock]]
* [[Quantum clock]]
* [[Quartz clock]]
* [[Radio clock]]
* [[Rolling ball clock]]
* [[Spring Drive|Spring drive watch]]
* [[Steam clock]]
* [[Sundial]]
* [[Torsion pendulum clock]]
* [[Water clock]]
|style=&quot;width:30%;vertical-align:top&quot;| &lt;!-- by function --&gt;
* [[10-hour clock]]
* [[Alarm clock]]
* [[Binary clock]]
* [[Chiming clock]]
* [[Chronometer watch]]
* [[Cuckoo clock]]
* [[Equation clock]]
* [[Game clock]]
* [[Japanese clock]]
* [[Master clock]]
* [[Musical clock]]
* [[Railroad chronometer]]
* [[Slave clock]]
* [[Speaking clock]]
* [[Stopwatch]]
* [[Striking clock]]
* [[Talking clock]]
* [[Tide clock]]
* [[Time ball]]
* [[Time clock]]
* [[World clock]]
|style=&quot;width:30%;vertical-align:top&quot;| &lt;!-- by form factor --&gt;
* [[American clock]]
* [[Automaton clock]]
* [[Balloon clock]]
* [[Banjo clock]]
* [[Bracket clock]]
* [[Carriage clock]]
* [[Cartel clock]]
* [[Kit-Cat Klock|Cat clock]]
* [[Chariot clock]]
* [[Clock tower]]
* [[Cuckoo clock]]
* [[Doll's head clock]]
* [[Floral clock]]
* [[French Empire mantel clock]]
* [[Granddaughter clock]]
* [[Grandfather clock]]
* [[Grandmother clock]]
* [[Lantern clock]]
* [[Lighthouse Clock|Lighthouse clock]]
* [[Longcase clock|Longcase (Tall-case) clock]]
* [[Mantel clock]]
* [[Skeleton clock]]
* [[Turret clock]]
* [[Watch]]
|}

==See also==
{{Portal|Technology}}

{{clear}}
{{div col |colwidth=22em}}
* [[24-hour analog dial]]
* [[Allan variance]]
* [[American Watchmakers-Clockmakers Institute]]
* [[BaselWorld]]
* [[Circadian rhythm|Biological clock]]
* [[Castle clock]]
* [[Clockarium]]
* [[Lewis Mumford#The clock as herald of the Industrial Revolution|Clock as herald of the Industrial Revolution]] (Lewis Mumford)
* [[Clock face]]
* [[Clock drift]]
* [[Clock ident]]
* [[Clock network]]
* [[Clock of the Long Now]]
* [[Clock signal]] (digital circuits)
* [[Clockkeeper]]
* [[Clockmaker]]
* [[Colgate Clock (Indiana)]]
* [[Colgate Clock (New Jersey)]], largest clock in USA
* [[Corpus Clock]]
* [[Cosmo Clock 21]], world's largest clock
* [[Cox's timepiece]]
* [[Cuckooland Museum]]
* [[Date and time representation by country]]
* [[Debt clock]]
* [[Le Défenseur du Temps]] (automata)
* [[Department of Defense master clock]] (U.S.)
* [[Doomsday Clock]]
* [[Earth clock]]
* [[Equation clock]]
* [[Federation of the Swiss Watch Industry FH]]
* [[Guard tour patrol system]] (watchclocks)
* [[Iron Ring Clock]]
* [[Jens Olsen's World Clock]]
* [[Jewel bearing]]
* [[List of biggest clock faces]]
* [[List of clocks]]
* [[List of international common standards]]
* [[List of world's largest cuckoo clocks]]
* [[Metrology]]
* [[Mora clock]]
* [[National Association of Watch and Clock Collectors]]
* [[Replica watch]]
* [[Rubik's Clock]]
* [[Star clock]]
* [[Singing bird box]]
* [[System time]]
* [[Time to digital converter]]
* [[Timeline of time measurement technology]]
* [[Timer]]
* [[Watch]]
* [[Watchmaker]]
{{div col end}}

===Newsgroup===
* [[alt.horology]]

==Notes and references==
{{reflist}}

==Bibliography==
* Baillie, G.H., O. Clutton, &amp; C.A. Ilbert. ''Britten's Old Clocks and Watches and Their Makers'' (7th ed.). Bonanza Books (1956).&lt;!-- Yes, the title (Britten's) is accurate --&gt;
* Bolter, David J. ''Turing's Man: Western Culture in the Computer Age''. The University of North Carolina Press, Chapel Hill, NC (1984). {{ISBN|0-8078-4108-0}} pbk. Summary of the role of &quot;the clock&quot; in its setting the direction of philosophic movement for the &quot;Western World&quot;. Cf. picture on p.&amp;nbsp;25 showing the ''verge'' and ''foliot''. Bolton derived the picture from Macey, p.&amp;nbsp;20.
* {{cite book | last = Bruton | first = Eric | title = ''The History of Clocks and Watches'' | publisher = Crescent Books Distributed by Crown | location = New York | year = 1982 | isbn = 978-0-517-37744-4 }}
* {{cite book | last = Dohrn-van Rossum | first = Gerhard | others = Trans. Thomas Dunlap | title = History of the Hour: Clocks and Modern Temporal Orders | year = 1996 | publisher = The University of Chicago Press | location = Chicago | isbn = 978-0-226-15510-4}}
* Edey, Winthrop. ''French Clocks''. New York: Walker &amp; Co. (1967).
* Kak, Subhash, Babylonian and Indian Astronomy: Early Connections. 2003.
* Kumar, Narendra &quot;Science in Ancient India&quot; (2004). {{ISBN|81-261-2056-8}}.
* Landes, David S. ''Revolution in Time: Clocks and the Making of the Modern World''. Cambridge: Harvard University Press (1983).
* Landes, David S. ''Clocks &amp; the Wealth of Nations'', [[Daedalus (journal)|Daedalus Journal]], Spring 2003.
* Lloyd, Alan H. &quot;Mechanical Timekeepers&quot;, ''A History of Technology,'' Vol. III. Edited by Charles Joseph Singer et al. Oxford: Clarendon Press (1957), pp.&amp;nbsp;648–675.
* Macey, Samuel L., ''Clocks and the Cosmos: Time in Western Life and Thought'', Archon Books, Hamden, Conn. (1980).
* {{cite book | last = Needham | first = Joseph | authorlink = Joseph Needham | title = Science &amp; Civilisation in China, Vol. 4, Part 2: Mechanical Engineering | origyear = 1965 | year = 2000 | publisher = Cambridge University Press | location = Cambridge | isbn = 978-0-521-05803-2}}
* North, John. ''God's Clockmaker: Richard of Wallingford and the Invention of Time''. London: Hambledon and London (2005).
* Palmer, Brooks. ''The Book of American Clocks'', The Macmillan Co. (1979).
* Robinson, Tom. ''The Longcase Clock''. Suffolk, England: Antique Collector's Club (1981).
* Smith, Alan. ''The International Dictionary of Clocks''. London: Chancellor Press (1996).
* Tardy. ''French Clocks the World Over''. Part I and II. Translated with the assistance of Alexander Ballantyne. Paris: Tardy (1981).
* Yoder, Joella Gerstmeyer. ''Unrolling Time: Christiaan Huygens and the Mathematization of Nature''. New York: Cambridge University Press (1988).
* Zea, Philip, &amp; Robert Cheney. ''Clock Making in New England: 1725–1825''. Old Sturbridge Village (1992).

==External links==
{{Spoken Wikipedia|Clock.ogg|2019-7-16}}
{{wiktionary}}
{{commons category|Clocks}}
{{EB1911 poster|Clock}}
* [http://www.nawcc.org National Association of Watch &amp; Clock Collectors Museum]

{{Time topics}}
{{Time measurement and standards}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Clocks| ]]
[[Category:Articles containing video clips]]
[[Category:Time measurement systems]]</text>
      <sha1>99hvglcjkueljk8zk2prytgb0uhr5rg</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
