  <page>
    <title>Carcinogen</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6445</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941445482</id>
      <parentid>941443225</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-18T16:46:27Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ghinga7</username>
        <id>31867537</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/120.56.72.49|120.56.72.49]] ([[User talk:120.56.72.49|talk]]) to last revision by Citation bot ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">A '''carcinogen''' is any substance, [[radionuclide]], or [[radiation]] that promotes [[carcinogenesis]], the formation of [[cancer]]. This may be due to the ability to damage the [[genome]] or to the disruption of cellular [[metabolic]] processes. Several radioactive substances are considered carcinogens, but their carcinogenic activity is attributed to the radiation, for example [[gamma ray]]s and [[alpha particle]]s, which they emit. Common examples of non-radioactive carcinogens are inhaled [[asbestos]], certain [[Dioxins and dioxin-like compounds|dioxins]], and [[tobacco]] smoke.  Although the public generally associates carcinogenicity with synthetic chemicals, it is equally likely to arise in both natural and synthetic substances.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | doi = 10.1016/S0027-5107(99)00194-3 | pmid = 10686303 | title = Paracelsus to parascience: The environmental cancer distraction | year = 2000 | last1 = Ames | first1 = Bruce N | last2 = Gold | first2 = Lois Swirsky| journal = Mutation Research/Fundamental and Molecular Mechanisms of Mutagenesis | volume = 447 | issue = 1 | pages = 3–13}}&lt;/ref&gt; Carcinogens are not necessarily immediately [[Toxicity|toxic]]; thus, their effect can be insidious.

Cancer is any disease in which normal cells are damaged and do not undergo [[programmed cell death]] as fast as they divide via [[mitosis]]. Carcinogens may increase the risk of cancer by altering cellular metabolism or damaging [[DNA]] directly in [[cell (biology)|cells]], which interferes with [[biology|biological]] processes, and induces the uncontrolled, malignant division, ultimately leading to the formation of tumors. Usually, severe DNA damage leads to programmed cell death, but if the programmed cell death pathway is damaged, then the cell cannot prevent itself from becoming a cancer cell.

There are many natural carcinogens. [[Aflatoxin]] B&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;, which is produced by the [[fungus]] ''[[Aspergillus flavus]]'' growing on stored [[cereal|grains]], [[nut (fruit)|nuts]] and [[peanut butter]], is an example of a potent, naturally occurring [[microbe|microbial]] carcinogen. Certain viruses such as [[hepatitis B]] and [[human papilloma virus]] have been found to cause cancer in humans. The first one shown to cause cancer in animals is [[Rous sarcoma virus]], discovered in 1910 by [[Peyton Rous]].  Other [[infection|infectious]] organisms which cause cancer in humans include some [[bacteria]] (e.g. ''[[Helicobacter pylori]]'' &lt;ref name=&quot;pmid16367902&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Hatakeyama M, Higashi H | title = Helicobacter pylori CagA: a new paradigm for bacterial carcinogenesis | journal = Cancer Science | volume = 96 | issue = 12 | pages = 835–43 | date = December 2005 | pmid = 16367902 | doi = 10.1111/j.1349-7006.2005.00130.x }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid24011243&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = González CA, Sala N, Rokkas T | title = Gastric cancer: epidemiologic aspects | journal = Helicobacter | volume = 18 | issue = Supplement 1 | pages = 34–8 | date = September 2013 | pmid = 24011243 | doi = 10.1111/hel.12082 }}&lt;/ref&gt;) and [[helminth]]s (e.g. ''[[Opisthorchis viverrini]]'' &lt;ref name=&quot;pmid17622191 &quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Sripa B, Kaewkes S, Sithithaworn P, Mairiang E, Laha T, Smout M, Pairojkul C, Bhudhisawasdi V, Tesana S, Thinkamrop B, Bethony JM, Loukas A, Brindley PJ | title = Liver fluke induces cholangiocarcinoma | journal = PLoS Medicine | volume = 4 | issue = 7 | pages = 1148–1155  | date = July 2007 | pmid = 17622191 | pmc = 1913093 | doi = 10.1371/journal.pmed.0040201 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and ''[[Clonorchis sinensis]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Rustagi T, Dasanu CA | title = Risk factors for gallbladder cancer and cholangiocarcinoma: similarities, differences and updates | journal = Journal of Gastrointestinal Cancer | volume = 43 | issue = 2 | pages = 137–47 | date = June 2012 | pmid = 21597894 | doi = 10.1007/s12029-011-9284-y }}&lt;/ref&gt;).

[[Dioxins and dioxin-like compounds]], [[benzene]], [[kepone]], [[1,2-Dibromoethane|EDB]], and [[asbestos]] have all been classified as carcinogenic.&lt;ref name=&quot;roc&quot; /&gt; As far back as the 1930s, Industrial smoke and [[tobacco]] smoke were identified as sources of dozens of carcinogens, including [[benzo(a)pyrene|benzo[''a'']pyrene]], tobacco-specific [[nitrosamine]]s such as [[N-Nitrosonornicotine|nitrosonornicotine]], and reactive [[aldehyde]]s such as [[formaldehyde]], which is also a hazard in [[embalming]] and making [[plastic]]s. [[Vinyl chloride]], from which [[Polyvinyl chloride|PVC]] is manufactured, is a carcinogen and thus a hazard in PVC production.

[[Co-carcinogen]]s are chemicals that do not necessarily cause cancer on their own, but promote the activity of other carcinogens in causing cancer.

After the carcinogen enters the body, the body makes an attempt to eliminate it through a process called [[biotransformation]]. The purpose of these reactions is to make the carcinogen more [[water-soluble]] so that it can be removed from the body. However, in some cases, these reactions can also convert a less toxic carcinogen into a more toxic carcinogen.

DNA is [[nucleophile|nucleophilic]]; therefore, soluble carbon electrophiles are carcinogenic, because DNA [[nucleophilic attack|attacks]] them. For example, some [[alkene]]s are [[Toxication|toxicated]] by human enzymes to produce an [[Electrophile|electrophilic]] [[epoxide]]. DNA attacks the epoxide, and is bound permanently to it. This is the mechanism behind the carcinogenicity of [[benzo(a)pyrene|benzo[''a'']pyrene]] in tobacco smoke, other aromatics, aflatoxin and mustard gas.

{{Quote box
 |title = [[International Union of Pure and Applied Chemistry|IUPAC]] definition
 |quote = '''Carcinogenicity''': Ability or tendency to produce [[cancer]].

Note: In general, polymers are not known as carcinogens or mutagens,&lt;br /&gt;however, residual monomers or additives can cause genetic mutations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Terminology for biorelated polymers and applications (IUPAC Recommendations 2012)|journal=[[Pure and Applied Chemistry]]|year=2012|volume=84|issue=2|pages=377–410|doi=10.1351/PAC-REC-10-12-04|url=http://pac.iupac.org/publications/pac/pdf/2012/pdf/8402x0377.pdf|last1=Vert|first1=Michel|last2=Doi|first2=Yoshiharu|last3=Hellwich|first3=Karl-Heinz|last4=Hess|first4=Michael|last5=Hodge|first5=Philip|last6=Kubisa|first6=Przemyslaw|last7=Rinaudo|first7=Marguerite|last8=Schué|first8=François}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

== Radiation ==
{{Main|radiation-induced cancer}}
[[CERCLA]] identifies all [[radionuclide]]s as carcinogens, although the nature of the emitted [[Radioactive decay|radiation]] ([[alpha particle|alpha]], [[beta particle|beta]], [[gamma ray|gamma]], or [[Neutron radiation|neutron]] and the radioactive strength), its consequent capacity to cause [[ionization]] in tissues, and the magnitude of radiation exposure, determine the potential hazard. Carcinogenicity of radiation depends on the type of radiation, type of exposure, and penetration. For example, [[alpha particle|alpha radiation]] has low penetration and is not a hazard outside the body, but emitters are carcinogenic when inhaled or ingested.  For example, [[Thorotrast]], a (incidentally radioactive) [[suspension (chemistry)|suspension]] previously used as a [[Radiocontrast|contrast]] medium in [[x-ray]] diagnostics, is a potent human carcinogen known because of its retention within various [[organ (biology)|organs]] and persistent emission of alpha particles.  Low-level ionizing radiation may induce irreparable DNA damage (leading to replicational and transcriptional errors needed for neoplasia or may trigger viral interactions) leading to pre-mature aging and [[cancer]].&lt;ref&gt;Acharya, PVN; The Effect of Ionizing Radiation on the Formation of Age-Correlated Oligo Deoxyribo Nucleo Phosphoryl Peptides in Mammalian Cells; 10th International Congress of Gerontology, Jerusalem. Abstract No. 1; January 1975. Work was done while employed by Dept. of Pathology, University of Wisconsin, Madison.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Acharya, PVN; Implications of The Action of Low-Level Ionizing Radiation on the Inducement of Irreparable DNA Damage Leading to Mammalian Aging and Chemical Carcinogenesis.; 10th International Congress of Biochemistry, Hamburg, Germany. Abstract No. 01-1-079; July 1976. Work was done while employed by Dept. of Pathology, University of Wisconsin, Madison.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Acharya, PV Narasimh; Irreparable DNA-Damage by Industrial Pollutants in Pre-mature Aging, Chemical Carcinogenesis, and Cardiac Hypertrophy:  Experiments and Theory; 1st International Meeting of Heads of Clinical Biochemistry Laboratories, Jerusalem, Israel. April 1977. Work conducted at Industrial Safety Institute and Behavioral Cybernetics Laboratory, University of Wisconsin, Madison.&lt;/ref&gt;

Not all types of electromagnetic radiation are carcinogenic. Low-energy waves on the [[electromagnetic spectrum]] including [[radio wave]]s, [[microwave]]s, [[infrared radiation]] and [[visible light]] are thought not to be, because they have insufficient energy to break chemical bonds. Evidence for carcinogenic effects of non-ionizing radiation is generally [[Electromagnetic radiation and health|inconclusive]], though there are some documented cases of radar technicians with prolonged high exposure experiencing significantly higher cancer incidence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Richter E, Berman T, Ben-Michael E, Laster R, Westin JB | title = Cancer in radar technicians exposed to radiofrequency/microwave radiation: sentinel episodes | journal = International Journal of Occupational and Environmental Health | volume = 6 | issue = 3 | pages = 187–93 | year = 2000 | pmid = 10926722 | doi = 10.1179/oeh.2000.6.3.187 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Higher-energy radiation, including [[ultraviolet radiation]] (present in [[sunlight]]), x-rays, and [[gamma radiation]], generally ''is'' carcinogenic, if received in sufficient doses.   For most people, ultraviolet radiations from sunlight is the most common cause of skin cancer.  In Australia, where people with pale skin are often exposed to strong sunlight, [[melanoma]] is the most common cancer diagnosed in people aged 15–44 years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cancer.org.au/cancersmartlifestyle/SunSmart/Skincancerfactsandfigures.htm| title=Skin Cancer Facts and Figures|access-date= 2010-07-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.newscientist.com/article/dn13922-skintone-gene-could-predict-cancer-risk.html Skin-tone gene could predict cancer risk]&lt;/ref&gt;

Substances or [[Food irradiation|foods]] irradiated with electrons or electromagnetic radiation (such as microwave, X-ray or gamma) are not carcinogenic.{{Citation needed|date=July 2010}} In contrast, non-electromagnetic [[neutron radiation]] produced inside nuclear reactors can produce secondary radiation through [[nuclear transmutation]].

== In prepared food ==
{{See also|Cooking#Carcinogens|Raw foodism}}
Chemicals used in processed and cured meat such as some brands of bacon, sausages and ham may produce carcinogens.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/health-34615621 |title=Processed meats do cause cancer - WHO|date= 26 October 2015 |work=BBC }}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, nitrites used as food preservatives in cured meat such as bacon have also been noted as being carcinogenic with demographic links, but not causation, to colon cancer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Scanlan RA | title = Formation and occurrence of nitrosamines in food | journal = Cancer Research | volume = 43 | issue = 5 Suppl | pages = 2435s–2440s | date = May 1983 | pmid = 6831466 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Cooking food at high temperatures, for example [[grilling]] or [[barbecuing]] meats, may also lead to the formation of minute quantities of many potent carcinogens that are comparable to those found in cigarette smoke (i.e., [[benzo(a)pyrene|benzo[''a'']pyrene]]).&lt;ref&gt;Wei Zheng, Deborah R Gustafson, Rashmi Sinha, James R Cerhan, ''et al.'' &quot;Well-done meat intake and the risk of breast cancer.&quot; ''Journal of the National Cancer Institute''. Oxford: Nov 18, 1998.Vol. 90, Iss. 22; pg. 1724, 6 pgs.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Charring]] of food looks like [[coking]] and tobacco [[pyrolysis]], and produces carcinogens. There are several carcinogenic pyrolysis products, such as polynuclear aromatic hydrocarbons, which are converted by human [[enzyme]]s into [[epoxide]]s, which attach permanently to DNA. Pre-cooking meats in a [[microwave oven]] for 2–3 minutes before grilling shortens the time on the hot pan, and removes heterocyclic amine (HCA) precursors, which can help minimize the formation of these carcinogens.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cancer.gov/cancertopics/factsheet/Risk/heterocyclic-amines |title=National Cancer Institute, 2004 analysis and recommendations |publisher=Cancer.gov |date=2004-09-15 |access-date=2010-09-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Reports from the [[Food Standards Agency]] have found that the known animal carcinogen [[acrylamide]] is generated in fried or overheated [[carbohydrate]] foods (such as [[french fries]] and [[potato chip]]s).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.food.gov.uk/safety-hygiene/acrylamide|title=Acrylamide}}&lt;/ref&gt; Studies are underway at the [[US Food and Drug Administration|FDA]] and [[Europe]] regulatory agencies to assess its potential risk to humans.

== In cigarettes ==
{{Main|Tobacco and health}}
There is a strong association of smoking with lung cancer; the [[lifetime risk]] of developing lung cancer increases significantly in smokers.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid7895211&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Villeneuve PJ, Mao Y | title = Lifetime probability of developing lung cancer, by smoking status, Canada | journal = Canadian Journal of Public Health | volume = 85 | issue = 6 | pages = 385–8 | year = 1994 | pmid = 7895211 }}&lt;/ref&gt; A large number of known carcinogens are found in cigarette smoke. Potent carcinogens found in cigarette smoke include [[polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbon]]s (PAH, such as [[Benzo(a)pyrene|benzo[a]pyrene]]), [[Benzene]], and [[Nitrosamine]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Harms of Cigarette Smoking and Health Benefits of Quitting|url=http://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/causes-prevention/risk/tobacco/cessation-fact-sheet|work=National Cancer Institute|date=2017-12-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://oehha.ca.gov/prop65/hazard_ident/pdf_zip/FinalMJsmokeHID.pdf
| last = Tomar
| first = Rajpal C.
|author2=Beaumont and Hsieh
| date = August 2009
| title = Evidence on the carcinogenicity of marijuana smoke
| publisher = Reproductive and Cancer Hazard Assessment Branch Office of Environmental Health Hazard Assessment, California Environmental Protection Agency
| access-date = 23 June 2012
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Mechanisms of carcinogenicity ==
Carcinogens can be classified as genotoxic or nongenotoxic. [[Genotoxin]]s cause irreversible genetic damage or mutations by binding to [[DNA]]. Genotoxins include chemical agents like [[N-nitroso-N-methylurea]] (NMU) or non-chemical agents such as [[ultraviolet light]] and [[ionizing radiation]]. Certain viruses can also act as carcinogens by interacting with DNA.

Nongenotoxins do not directly affect DNA but act in other ways to promote growth. These include hormones and some organic compounds.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title=The Gale Encyclopedia of Cancer: A guide to Cancer and its Treatments, Second Edition. Page no. 137 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Classification ==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;  style=&quot;margin:0 0 0 0.5em; float:right;&quot;
|+ Approximate equivalences&lt;br /&gt;between classification schemes
|-
! IARC
! GHS
! NTP
! ACGIH
! EU
|-
| Group 1
| Cat. 1A
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| Known
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| A1
| Cat. 1
|-
| Group 2A
| rowspan=2 | Cat. 1B
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| Reasonably&lt;br /&gt;suspected
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| A2
| rowspan=2 | Cat. 2
|-
| rowspan=2 | Group 2B
|-
| rowspan=2 | Cat. 2
| rowspan=4 | &amp;nbsp;
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| A3
| rowspan=2 | Cat. 3
|-
| rowspan=2 | Group 3
|-
| rowspan=2 | &amp;nbsp;
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| A4
| rowspan=2 | &amp;nbsp;
|-
| Group 4
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| A5
|}

=== International Agency for Research on Cancer ===
The [[International Agency for Research on Cancer]] (IARC) is an intergovernmental agency established in 1965, which forms part of the [[World Health Organization]] of the [[United Nations]]. It is based in [[Lyon]], [[France]]. Since 1971 it has published a series of ''Monographs on the Evaluation                          of Carcinogenic Risks to Humans''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://monographs.iarc.fr/ |title=IARC Monographs |publisher=Monographs.iarc.fr |date= |access-date=2010-09-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; that have been highly influential in the classification of possible carcinogens.
* [[List of IARC Group 1 carcinogens|Group 1]]: the agent (mixture) is definitely carcinogenic to humans. The exposure circumstance entails exposures that are carcinogenic to humans.
* [[List of IARC Group 2A carcinogens|Group 2A]]: the agent (mixture) is probably carcinogenic to humans. The exposure circumstance entails exposures that are probably carcinogenic to humans.
* [[List of IARC Group 2B carcinogens|Group 2B]]: the agent (mixture) is possibly carcinogenic to humans. The exposure circumstance entails exposures that are possibly carcinogenic to humans.
* [[List of IARC Group 3 carcinogens|Group 3]]: the agent (mixture or exposure circumstance) is not classifiable as to its carcinogenicity to humans.
* [[List of IARC Group 4 carcinogens|Group 4]]: the agent (mixture) is probably not carcinogenic to humans.

=== Globally Harmonized System ===
The [[Globally Harmonized System of Classification and Labelling of Chemicals]] (GHS) is a [[United Nations]] initiative to attempt to harmonize the different systems of assessing chemical risk which currently exist (as of March 2009) around the world. It classifies carcinogens into two categories, of which the first may be divided again into subcategories if so desired by the competent regulatory authority:
* Category 1: known or presumed to have carcinogenic potential for humans
** Category 1A: the assessment is based primarily on human evidence
** Category 1B: the assessment is based primarily on animal evidence
* Category 2: suspected human carcinogens

=== U.S. National Toxicology Program ===
The [[National Toxicology Program]] of the [[United States Department of Health and Human Services|U.S. Department of Health and Human Services]] is mandated to produce a biennial ''Report on Carcinogens''.&lt;ref&gt;Section 301(b)(4) of the Public Health Service Act, as amended by Section 262, Pub.&amp;nbsp;L. 95–622.&lt;/ref&gt; As of June 2011, the latest edition was the 12th report (2011).&lt;ref name=&quot;roc&quot;&gt;[http://ntp.niehs.nih.gov/go/roc12 ''Report on Carcinogens, Eleventh Edition''] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090420224714/http://ntp.niehs.nih.gov/index.cfm?objectid=32BA9724-F1F6-975E-7FCE50709CB4C932 |date=April 20, 2009 }}; U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, Public Health Service, National Toxicology Program (2011).&lt;/ref&gt; It classifies carcinogens into two groups:
* Known to be a human carcinogen
* Reasonably anticipated being a human carcinogen

=== American Conference of Governmental Industrial Hygienists ===
The [[American Conference of Governmental Industrial Hygienists]] (ACGIH) is a private organization best known for its publication of [[threshold limit value]]s (TLVs) for occupational exposure and monographs on workplace chemical hazards. It assesses carcinogenicity as part of a wider assessment of the occupational hazards of chemicals.
* Group A1: Confirmed human carcinogen
* Group A2: Suspected human carcinogen
* Group A3: Confirmed animal carcinogen with unknown relevance to humans
* Group A4: Not classifiable as a human carcinogen
* Group A5: Not suspected as a human carcinogen

=== European Union ===
The European Union classification of carcinogens is contained in the [[Dangerous Substances Directive (67/548/EEC)|Dangerous Substances Directive]] and the [[Dangerous Preparations Directive]]. It consists of three categories:
* Category 1: Substances known to be carcinogenic to humans.
* Category 2: Substances which should be regarded as if they are carcinogenic to humans.
* Category 3: Substances which cause concern for humans, owing to possible carcinogenic effects but in respect of which the available information is not adequate for making a satisfactory assessment.
This assessment scheme is being phased out in favor of the GHS scheme (see above), to which it is very close in category definitions.

=== Safe Work Australia ===
Under a previous name, the NOHSC, in 1999 [[Safe Work Australia]] published the Approved Criteria for Classifying Hazardous Substances [NOHSC:1008(1999)].&lt;ref name=&quot;Safe Work Australia3&quot;&gt;[http://www.safeworkaustralia.gov.au/AboutSafeWorkAustralia/WhatWeDo/Publications/Documents/504/Approved_Criteria_classifying_Hazardous_Substances_NOHSC1008_1999_2nd_Edition.pdf Safe Work Australia] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20101201103328/http://safeworkaustralia.gov.au/AboutSafeWorkAustralia/WhatWeDo/Publications/Documents/504/Approved_Criteria_classifying_Hazardous_Substances_NOHSC1008_1999_2nd_Edition.pdf |date=2010-12-01 }}, NOHSC. (1999). Approved criteria for classifying hazardous substances [NOHSC:1008(1999)] §&amp;nbsp;4.76. Accessed 21/05/2011&lt;/ref&gt;
Section 4.76 of this document outlines the criteria for classifying carcinogens as approved by the Australian government. This classification consists of three categories:
* Category 1: Substances known to be carcinogenic to humans.
* Category 2: Substances that should be regarded as if they were carcinogenic to humans.
* Category 3: Substances that have possible carcinogenic effects in humans but about which there is insufficient information to make an assessment.

== Common carcinogens ==

=== Occupational carcinogens ===
Occupational carcinogens are agents that pose a risk of cancer in several specific work-locations:

{|class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Carcinogen !! Associated cancer sites or types !! Occupational uses or sources
|-
! [[Arsenic]] and its compounds
|
* [[Lung]]
* [[Skin]]
* [[Hemangiosarcoma]]
|
* [[Smelting]] byproduct
* Component of:
**Alloys
**Electrical and [[semiconductor]] devices
**Medications (e.g. [[melarsoprol]])
**Herbicides
**Fungicides
**Animal dips
**Drinking water from contaminated aquifers.
|-
! [[Asbestos]]
|
* [[Lung cancer|Lungs]]
* [[Asbestosis]]
* [[Gastrointestinal cancer|Gastrointestinal tract]]
* [[Pleural]] Mesothelioma
* [[Peritoneal Mesothelioma]]
|
Not in widespread use, but found in:
* Constructions
**Roofing papers
**Floor tiles
* Fire-resistant textiles
* Friction linings (brake pads) (only outside Europe)
** Replacement friction linings for automobiles still may contain asbestos
|-
! [[Benzene]]
|
* [[Leukemia]]
* [[Hodgkin's lymphoma]]
|
* Light [[fuel oil]]
* Former use as [[solvent]]
* [[commodity chemical]]
|-
! [[Beryllium]] and its compounds&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.1007/s00204-008-0313-y|pmid=18496671|title=Carcinogenic metal compounds: Recent insight into molecular and cellular mechanisms|journal=Archives of Toxicology|volume=82|issue=8|pages=493–512|year=2008|last1=Beyersmann|first1=Detmar|last2=Hartwig|first2=Andrea}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|
* Lung
|
* Lightweight alloys
**Aerospace applications
**Nuclear reactors
|-
! [[Cadmium]] and its compounds&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last1 = Hartwig | first1 = Andrea | editor = Astrid Sigel, Helmut Sigel and Roland K. O. Sigel | title = Cadmium: From Toxicology to Essentiality | series = Metal Ions in Life Sciences | volume = 11 | year = 2013 | publisher = Springer | pages = 491–507 | chapter = Chapter 15. Cadmium and cancer | doi = 10.1007/978-94-007-5179-8_15 | pmid = 23430782 | isbn = 978-94-007-5178-1 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|
* [[Prostate cancer|Prostate]]
|
* Yellow pigments
* [[Phosphor]]s
* [[Solder]]s
* Batteries
* Metal paintings and coatings
|-
! Hexavalent [[chromium]](VI) compounds
|
* Lung
|
* Paints
* Pigments
* Preservatives
|-
! [[Nitrosamine]]s&lt;ref name=Tricker&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.1016/0165-1218(91)90123-4|pmid=2017213|title=Carcinogenic N-Nitrosamines in the Diet: Occurrence, Formation, Mechanisms and Carcinogenic Potential|journal=Mutation Research/Genetic Toxicology|volume=259|issue=3–4|pages=277–289|year=1991|last1=Tricker|first1=A.R.|last2=Preussmann|first2=R.}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|
* Lung
* Esophogus
* Liver
|
* [[cigarette smoke]] [[nitrite]]-treated foods (cured meats)
|-
! [[Ethylene oxide]]
|
* Leukemia
|
* [[commodity chemical]]
* [[Sterilant]] for hospital equipment
|-
! [[Nickel]]
|
* [[Nose]]
* Lung
|
* Nickel plating
* Ferrous alloys
* Ceramics
* Batteries
* Stainless-steel welding byproduct
|-
! [[Radon]] and its decay products
|
* Lung
|
* Uranium decay
**Quarries and mines
**Cellars and poorly ventilated places
|-
! [[Vinyl chloride]]
|
* Hemangiosarcoma
* [[liver cancer|Liver]]
|
* Production of [[polyvinyl chloride]]
|-
! Shift work that involves
[[circadian]] disruption&lt;ref name=&quot;IARC180&quot;&gt;{{Cite web
| title = IARC Monographs Programme finds cancer hazards associated with shiftwork, painting and firefighting, International Agency for Research on Cancer
| access-date = 2011-07-01
| url = http://www.iarc.fr/en/media-centre/pr/2007/pr180.html
| archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20110721001355/http://www.iarc.fr/en/media-centre/pr/2007/pr180.html
| archive-date = 2011-07-21
| url-status = dead
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|
* [[breast cancer|Breast]]
|
|-
! Involuntary smoking ([[Passive smoking]])&lt;ref&gt;[http://monographs.iarc.fr/ENG/Monographs/vol83/ Tobacco Smoke and Involuntary Smoking] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150315135351/http://monographs.iarc.fr/ENG/Monographs/vol83/ |date=2015-03-15 }}, IARC Monographs on the Evaluation of Carcinogenic Risks to Humans, Volume 83 (2004).&lt;/ref&gt;
|
* Lung
|
*
|-

! [[Radium-226]], [[Radium-224]],&lt;br /&gt; [[Plutonium-238]], [[Plutonium-239]]&lt;ref name=Durbin75&gt;''[http://www.osti.gov/energycitations/purl.cover.jsp?purl=/4136654-rOiaqY/Survival,causesofdeath,andestimatedtissuedosesinagroupofhumanbeingsinjectedwithplutonium.pdf Survival, causes of death, and estimated tissue doses in a group of human beings injected with plutonium]'', [http://www.osti.gov/energycitations/servlets/purl/4136654-rOiaqY/4136654.pdf 751053], R. E. Rowland and Patricia W. Durbin, 1975.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt; and other [[alpha particle]]&lt;br /&gt; emitters with high atomic weight
|
* [[Bone cancer|Bone]] (they are [[bone seeker]]s)
* [[Liver cancer|Liver]]
|
* [[Nuclear fuel]] processing
* [[Radium dial]] manufacturing
|-

|col span=3| &lt;small&gt;Unless otherwise specified, ref is:&lt;ref name=Kumar6-2&gt;Table 6-2 in: {{cite book |author1=Mitchell, Richard Sheppard |author2=Kumar, Vinay |author3=Abbas, Abul K. |author4=Fausto, Nelson |title=Robbins Basic Pathology|publisher=Saunders |location=Philadelphia |year= 2007|pages= |isbn=978-1-4160-2973-1 |oclc= |doi=}} 8th edition.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
|}

=== Others ===
* [[Gasoline]] (contains aromatics)
* [[Lead]] and its compounds
* [[Alkylating antineoplastic agent]]s (e.g. [[mechlorethamine]])
*[[Styrene]]
*Other [[alkylating agent]]s (e.g. [[dimethyl sulfate]])
* [[Ultraviolet radiation]] from the sun and UV lamps
* [[Alcoholic beverage|Alcohol]] (causing head and neck cancers)
* Other [[ionizing radiation]] (X-rays, gamma rays, etc.)

==Major carcinogens implicated in the four most common cancers worldwide==
In this section, the carcinogens implicated as the main causative agents of the four most common cancers worldwide are briefly described. These four cancers are lung, breast, colon, and stomach cancers.  Together they account for about 41% of worldwide cancer incidence and 42% of cancer deaths (for more detailed information on the carcinogens implicated in these and other cancers, see references&lt;ref&gt;Bernstein H, Payne CM, Bernstein C, Garewal H, Dvorak K (2008).  Cancer and aging as consequences of un-repaired DNA damage. In: New Research on DNA Damages (Editors: Honoka Kimura and Aoi Suzuki) [[Nova Science Publishers, Inc.]], New York, Chapter 1, pp. 1-47. open access, but read only https://www.novapublishers.com/catalog/product_info.php?products_id=43247 {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141025091740/https://www.novapublishers.com/catalog/product_info.php?products_id=43247 |date=2014-10-25 }} {{ISBN|978-1604565812}}&lt;/ref&gt;).

===Lung cancer===
[[Lung cancer]] (pulmonary carcinoma) is the most common cancer in the world, both in terms of cases (1.6 million cases; 12.7% of total cancer cases) and deaths (1.4 million deaths; 18.2% of total cancer deaths).&lt;ref name=Ferlay&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Ferlay J, Shin HR, Bray F, Forman D, Mathers C, Parkin DM | title = Estimates of worldwide burden of cancer in 2008: GLOBOCAN 2008 | journal = International Journal of Cancer | volume = 127 | issue = 12 | pages = 2893–917 | date = December 2010 | pmid = 21351269 | doi = 10.1002/ijc.25516 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Lung cancer is largely caused by tobacco smoke. Risk estimates for lung cancer in the United States indicate that tobacco smoke is responsible for 90% of lung cancers. Other factors are implicated in lung cancer, and these factors can interact synergistically with [[smoking]] so that total attributable risk adds up to more than 100%. These factors include occupational exposure to carcinogens (about 9-15%), [[radon]] (10%) and outdoor air pollution (1-2%).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Alberg AJ, Ford JG, Samet JM | title = Epidemiology of lung cancer: ACCP evidence-based clinical practice guidelines (2nd edition) | journal = Chest | volume = 132 | issue = 3 Suppl | pages = 29S–55S | date = September 2007 | pmid = 17873159 | doi = 10.1378/chest.07-1347 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Tobacco smoke is a complex mixture of more than 5,300 identified chemicals. The most important carcinogens in tobacco smoke have been determined by a “Margin of Exposure” approach.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Cunningham FH, Fiebelkorn S, Johnson M, Meredith C | title = A novel application of the Margin of Exposure approach: segregation of tobacco smoke toxicants | journal = Food and Chemical Toxicology | volume = 49 | issue = 11 | pages = 2921–33 | date = November 2011 | pmid = 21802474 | doi = 10.1016/j.fct.2011.07.019 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Using this approach, the most important tumorigenic compounds in tobacco smoke were, in order of importance, acrolein, formaldehyde, acrylonitrile, 1,3-butadiene, cadmium, acetaldehyde, ethylene oxide, and isoprene. Most of these compounds cause DNA damage by forming DNA adducts or by inducing other alterations in DNA.{{Citation needed|date=December 2019|reason=removed citation to book from predatory publisher}}  DNA damages are subject to error-prone DNA repair or can cause replication errors. Such errors in repair or replication can result in mutations in tumor suppressor genes or oncogenes leading to cancer.

===Breast cancer===
[[Breast cancer]] is the second most common cancer [(1.4 million cases, 10.9%), but ranks 5th as cause of death (458,000, 6.1%)].&lt;ref name=Ferlay /&gt;  Increased risk of breast cancer is associated with persistently elevated blood levels of [[estrogen]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Yager JD, Davidson NE | title = Estrogen carcinogenesis in breast cancer | journal = The New England Journal of Medicine | volume = 354 | issue = 3 | pages = 270–82 | date = January 2006 | pmid = 16421368 | doi = 10.1056/NEJMra050776 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Estrogen appears to contribute to breast carcinogenesis by three processes; (1) the metabolism of estrogen to genotoxic, mutagenic carcinogens, (2) the stimulation of tissue growth, and (3) the repression of phase II [[detoxification]] enzymes that metabolize ROS leading to increased oxidative DNA damage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Ansell PJ, Espinosa-Nicholas C, Curran EM, Judy BM, Philips BJ, Hannink M, Lubahn DB | title = In vitro and in vivo regulation of antioxidant response element-dependent gene expression by estrogens | journal = Endocrinology | volume = 145 | issue = 1 | pages = 311–7 | date = January 2004 | pmid = 14551226 | doi = 10.1210/en.2003-0817 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Belous AR, Hachey DL, Dawling S, Roodi N, Parl FF | title = Cytochrome P450 1B1-mediated estrogen metabolism results in estrogen-deoxyribonucleoside adduct formation | journal = Cancer Research | volume = 67 | issue = 2 | pages = 812–7 | date = January 2007 | pmid = 17234793 | doi = 10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-06-2133 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Bolton JL, Thatcher GR | title = Potential mechanisms of estrogen quinone carcinogenesis | language = EN | journal = Chemical Research in Toxicology | volume = 21 | issue = 1 | pages = 93–101 | date = January 2008 | pmid = 18052105 | pmc = 2556295 | doi = 10.1021/tx700191p }}&lt;/ref&gt;  The major estrogen in humans, estradiol, can be metabolized to quinone derivatives that form [[DNA adduct|adducts]] with DNA.&lt;ref name=Yue&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Yue W, Santen RJ, Wang JP, Li Y, Verderame MF, Bocchinfuso WP, Korach KS, Devanesan P, Todorovic R, Rogan EG, Cavalieri EL | title = Genotoxic metabolites of estradiol in breast: potential mechanism of estradiol induced carcinogenesis | journal = The Journal of Steroid Biochemistry and Molecular Biology | volume = 86 | issue = 3–5 | pages = 477–86 | date = September 2003 | pmid = 14623547 | doi = 10.1016/s0960-0760(03)00377-7 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  These derivatives can cause dupurination, the removal of bases from the phosphodiester backbone of DNA, followed by inaccurate repair or replication of the apurinic site leading to mutation and eventually cancer.  This genotoxic mechanism may interact in synergy with estrogen receptor-mediated, persistent cell proliferation to ultimately cause breast cancer.&lt;ref name=Yue /&gt; Genetic background, dietary practices and environmental factors also likely contribute to the incidence of DNA damage and breast cancer risk.

===Colon cancer===

[[Colorectal cancer]] is the third most common cancer [1.2 million cases (9.4%), 608,000 deaths (8.0%)].&lt;ref name=Ferlay /&gt; Tobacco smoke may be responsible for up to 20% of colorectal cancers in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Giovannucci E, Martínez ME | title = Tobacco, colorectal cancer, and adenomas: a review of the evidence | journal = Journal of the National Cancer Institute | volume = 88 | issue = 23 | pages = 1717–30 | date = December 1996 | pmid = 8944002 | doi = 10.1093/jnci/88.23.1717 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  In addition, substantial evidence implicates [[bile acid]]s as an important factor in colon cancer.  Twelve studies (summarized in Bernstein et al.&lt;ref name=Bernstein2009&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Bernstein H, Bernstein C, Payne CM, Dvorak K | title = Bile acids as endogenous etiologic agents in gastrointestinal cancer | journal = World Journal of Gastroenterology | volume = 15 | issue = 27 | pages = 3329–40 | date = July 2009 | pmid = 19610133 | pmc = 2712893 | doi = 10.3748/wjg.15.3329 }}&lt;/ref&gt;) indicate that the bile acids deoxycholic acid (DCA) and/or lithocholic acid (LCA) induce production of DNA-damaging reactive oxygen species and/or reactive nitrogen species in human or animal colon cells.  Furthermore, 14 studies showed that DCA and LCA induce DNA damage in colon cells.  Also 27 studies reported that bile acids cause programmed cell death ([[apoptosis]]).  Increased apoptosis can result in selective survival of cells that are resistant to induction of apoptosis.&lt;ref name=Bernstein2009 /&gt;  Colon cells with reduced ability to undergo apoptosis in response to DNA damage would tend to accumulate mutations, and such cells may give rise to colon cancer.&lt;ref name=Bernstein2009 /&gt;  Epidemiologic studies have found that fecal bile acid concentrations are increased in populations with a high incidence of colon cancer.  Dietary increases in total fat or saturated fat result in elevated DCA and LCA in feces and elevated exposure of the colon epithelium to these bile acids.  When the bile acid DCA was added to the standard diet of wild-type mice invasive colon cancer was induced in 56% of the mice after 8 to 10 months.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Bernstein C, Holubec H, Bhattacharyya AK, Nguyen H, Payne CM, Zaitlin B, Bernstein H | title = Carcinogenicity of deoxycholate, a secondary bile acid | journal = Archives of Toxicology | volume = 85 | issue = 8 | pages = 863–71 | date = August 2011 | pmid = 21267546 | pmc = 3149672 | doi = 10.1007/s00204-011-0648-7 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Overall, the available evidence indicates that DCA and LCA are centrally important DNA-damaging carcinogens in colon cancer.

===Stomach cancer===
[[Stomach cancer]] is the fourth most common cancer [990,000 cases (7.8%), 738,000 deaths (9.7%)].&lt;ref name=Ferlay /&gt;  ''[[Helicobacter pylori]]'' infection is the main causative factor in stomach cancer.  Chronic gastritis (inflammation) caused by ''H. pylori'' is often long-standing if not treated.  Infection of gastric epithelial cells with ''H. pylori'' results in increased production of reactive oxygen species (ROS).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Ding SZ, Minohara Y, Fan XJ, Wang J, Reyes VE, Patel J, Dirden-Kramer B, Boldogh I, Ernst PB, Crowe SE | title = Helicobacter pylori infection induces oxidative stress and programmed cell death in human gastric epithelial cells | journal = Infection and Immunity | volume = 75 | issue = 8 | pages = 4030–9 | date = August 2007 | pmid = 17562777 | pmc = 1952011 | doi = 10.1128/IAI.00172-07 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Handa O, Naito Y, Yoshikawa T | title = Redox biology and gastric carcinogenesis: the role of Helicobacter pylori | journal = Redox Report | volume = 16 | issue = 1 | pages = 1–7 | year = 2011 | pmid = 21605492 | doi = 10.1179/174329211X12968219310756 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  ROS cause oxidative DNA damage including the major base alteration 8-hydroxydeoxyguanosine (8-OHdG).  8-OHdG resulting from ROS is increased in chronic gastritis.  The altered DNA base can cause errors during DNA replication that have mutagenic and carcinogenic potential.  Thus ''H. pylori''-induced ROS appear to be the major carcinogens in stomach cancer because they cause oxidative DNA damage leading to carcinogenic mutations.  Diet is thought to be a contributing factor in stomach cancer - in Japan where very salty pickled foods are popular, the incidence of stomach cancer is high.  Preserved meat such as bacon, sausages, and ham increases the risk while a diet high in fresh fruit and vegetables may reduce the risk. The risk also increases with age.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.cancerresearchuk.org/about-cancer/type/stomach-cancer/about/stomach-cancer-risks-and-causes |title=Stomach cancer risks and causes |work=Cancer Research UK }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{cmn|colwidth=30em|
* [[History of cancer]]
* [[Mutagen]]
* [[Possible carcinogen]]
* [[Safe handling of carcinogens]]
* [[Teratogen]]
}}

== References ==
{{reflist|30em}}

== External links ==
{{Wiktionary|carcinogen}}
{{Commons category|Carcinogens}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20051028174523/http://ntp.niehs.nih.gov/index.cfm?objectid=03C9B512-ACF8-C1F3-ADBA53CAE848F635 U.S. National Toxicology Program's Report on Carcinogens]
* [https://www.cdc.gov/niosh/topics/cancer/npotocca.html CDC – Occupational Cancer – Carcinogen List – NIOSH Safety and Health Topic]
* [http://www.scorecard.org/health-effects/chemicals.tcl?short_hazard_name=cancer&amp;all_p=t Recognized Carcinogens]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20080317051133/http://www.cancer.org/docroot/PED/content/PED_1_3x_Known_and_Probable_Carcinogens.asp?sitearea=PED American Cancer Society]
* [http://potency.berkeley.edu/ Database of Rodent Carcinogens]
* [http://potency.berkeley.edu/MOE.html Comparing Possible Cancer Hazards from Human Exposures to Rodent Carcinogens]

{{Carcinogen|state=uncollapsed}}
{{Tumors}}
{{Toxicology}}
{{Genotoxicity}}
{{HealthIssuesOfPlastics}}

[[Category:Carcinogens| ]]
[[Category:Carcinogenesis]]
[[Category:Radiation health effects]]</text>
      <sha1>efji5mt6az94qaul4d45jad2aj4bkkm</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
