  <page>
    <title>Catalysis</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5914</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943115567</id>
      <parentid>943083981</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-28T22:54:54Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Smokefoot</username>
        <id>698909</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Crespilho spam</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|chemical process}}
{{Redirect|Catalyst}}
{{Hatnote|Not to be confused with [[catabolism]] (often catalysis aids catabolism).}}

[[Image:Low Temperature Oxidation Catalyst.jpeg|thumb|An [[air filter]] that utilizes a low-temperature oxidation catalyst to convert [[carbon monoxide]] to less toxic [[carbon dioxide]] at room temperature. It can also remove [[formaldehyde]] from the air.]]

'''Catalysis''' ({{IPAc-en|k|ə|ˈ|t|æ|l|ə|s|ɪ|s}}) is the process of increasing the [[reaction rate|rate]] of a [[chemical reaction]] by adding a substance known as a '''catalyst'''&lt;ref name=&quot;IUPACc&quot;&gt;{{Cite book | chapter-url=http://goldbook.iupac.org/C00876.html | doi=10.1351/goldbook.C00876| chapter=Catalyst| title=IUPAC Compendium of Chemical Terminology| year=2009| isbn=978-0-9678550-9-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|k|æ|t|əl|ɪ|s|t}}), which is not consumed in the catalyzed reaction and can continue to act repeatedly. Because of this, only very small amounts of catalyst are required to alter the reaction rate in principle.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.anl.gov/articles/7-things-you-may-not-know-about-catalysis 7 things you may not know about catalysis] Louise Lerner, [[Argonne National Laboratory]] (2011)&lt;/ref&gt;

In general, chemical reactions occur faster in the presence of a catalyst because the catalyst provides an alternative reaction pathway with a lower [[activation energy]] than the non-catalyzed mechanism. In catalyzed mechanisms, the catalyst usually reacts to form a temporary [[reaction intermediate|intermediate]], which then regenerates the original catalyst in a cyclic process. A substance which provides a mechanism with a higher activation energy does not decrease the rate because the reaction can still occur by the non-catalyzed route.&lt;ref name=LM82/&gt; An added substance which does reduce the reaction rate is not considered a catalyst&lt;ref name=&quot;IUPACc&quot;/&gt; but a [[reaction inhibitor]] ([[#Inhibitors, poisons, and promoters|see below]]).

Catalysts may be classified as either [[Homogeneity and heterogeneity|homogeneous or heterogeneous]].  A homogeneous catalyst is one whose [[molecule]]s are dispersed in the same phase (usually gaseous or liquid) as the [[reactant]]'s molecules. A heterogeneous catalyst is one whose molecules are not in the same phase as the reactant's, which are typically gases or liquids that are [[adsorption|adsorbed]] onto the surface of the solid catalyst. [[Enzyme]]s and other biocatalysts are often considered as a third category.

==Technical perspective==

In the presence of a catalyst, less [[Thermodynamic free energy|free energy]] is required to reach the [[transition state]], but the total free energy from reactants to products does not change.&lt;ref name=&quot;IUPACc&quot; /&gt; A catalyst may participate in multiple chemical transformations. The effect of a catalyst may vary due to the presence of other substances known as inhibitors or [[Catalyst poisoning|poisons]] (which reduce the catalytic activity) or promoters (which increase the activity and also affect the temperature of the reaction).&lt;ref name=&quot;IUPACc&quot; /&gt;

Catalyzed reactions have a lower [[activation energy]] (rate-limiting free energy of activation) than the corresponding uncatalyzed reaction, resulting in a higher reaction rate at the same temperature and for the same reactant [[concentration]]s. However, the detailed mechanics of catalysis is complex. Catalysts may bind to the reagents to polarize bonds, e.g. [[acid catalyst]]s for reactions of [[carbonyl]] compounds, or form specific intermediates that are not produced naturally, such as osmate [[ester]]s in [[osmium tetroxide]]-catalyzed [[dihydroxylation]] of [[alkene]]s, or cause [[Dissociation (chemistry)|dissociation]] of reagents to reactive forms, such as [[chemisorption|chemisorbed hydrogen]] in [[catalytic hydrogenation]].

[[Chemical kinetics|Kinetically]], catalytic reactions are typical [[chemical reaction]]s; i.e. the reaction rate depends on the frequency of contact of the reactants in the rate-determining step.  Usually, the catalyst participates in this slowest step, and rates are limited by amount of catalyst and its &quot;activity&quot;.  In [[heterogeneous catalysis]], the diffusion of reagents to the surface and diffusion of products from the surface can be rate determining. A [[nanomaterial-based catalyst]] is an example of a heterogeneous catalyst. Analogous events associated with [[substrate (chemistry)|substrate]] binding and product dissociation apply to homogeneous catalysts.

Although catalysts are not consumed by the reaction itself, they may be inhibited, deactivated, or destroyed by secondary processes.  In [[heterogeneous]] catalysis, typical secondary processes include [[coking]] where the catalyst becomes covered by [[polymer]]ic side products.  Additionally, heterogeneous catalysts can dissolve into the solution in a solid–liquid system or sublimate in a solid–gas system.

==Background==

The production of most industrially important chemicals involves catalysis. Similarly, most biochemically significant processes are catalysed.  Research into catalysis is a major field in [[applied science]] and involves many areas of chemistry, notably [[organometallic chemistry]] and [[materials science]].  Catalysis is relevant to many aspects of [[environmental science]], e.g. the [[catalytic converter]] in automobiles and the dynamics of the [[ozone hole]]. Catalytic reactions are preferred in environmentally friendly [[green chemistry]] due to the reduced amount of waste generated,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=The 12 Principles of Green Chemistry | work=[[United States Environmental Protection Agency]] | url=http://www.epa.gov/sciencematters/june2011/principles.htm | accessdate=2012-04-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; as opposed to [[stoichiometric]] reactions in which all reactants are consumed and more side products are formed. Many [[transition metal]]s and transition metal [[Complex (chemistry)|complexes]] are used in catalysis as well. Catalysts called [[enzyme]]s are important in [[biology]].

A catalyst works by providing an alternative reaction pathway to the reaction product. The rate of the reaction is increased as this alternative route has a lower [[activation energy]] than the reaction route not mediated by the catalyst. The [[disproportionation]] of [[hydrogen peroxide]] creates water and [[oxygen]], as shown below.
:2 H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;  →   2 H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O  +  O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;
This reaction is preferable in the sense that the reaction products are more stable than the starting material, though the uncatalysed reaction is slow. In fact, the decomposition of hydrogen peroxide is so slow that hydrogen peroxide solutions are commercially available. This reaction is strongly affected by catalysts such as [[manganese dioxide]], or the enzyme [[peroxidase]] in organisms. Upon the addition of a small amount of [[manganese dioxide]], the hydrogen peroxide reacts rapidly. This effect is readily seen by the [[Effervescence (chemistry)|effervescence]] of oxygen.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|publisher=[[University of Minnesota]] |title=Genie in a Bottle |url=http://www.chem.umn.edu/services/lecturedemo/info/genie.htm |date=2005-03-02 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080405195443/http://www.chem.umn.edu/services/lecturedemo/info/genie.htm |archivedate=2008-04-05 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The manganese dioxide is not consumed in the reaction, and thus may be recovered unchanged, and re-used indefinitely. Accordingly, manganese dioxide ''catalyses'' this reaction.&lt;ref&gt;Masel, Richard I. (2001) ''Chemical Kinetics and Catalysis''. Wiley-Interscience, New York. {{ISBN|0-471-24197-0}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

==General principles==

===Units===

Catalytic activity is usually denoted by the symbol ''z'' &lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Dybkaer | first1 = R. | year = 2001 | title = Unit &quot;katal&quot; for catalytic activity (IUPAC Technical Report) | url = https://media.iupac.org/publications/pac/2001/pdf/7306x0927.pdf | journal = Pure Appl. Chem. | volume = 73 | issue = 6| page = 929 | doi=10.1351/pac200173060927}}&lt;/ref&gt; and measured in [[Mole (unit)|mol]]/s, a unit which was called [[katal]] and defined the SI unit for catalytic activity since 1999. Catalytic activity is not a kind of reaction rate, but a property of the [[catalyst]] under certain conditions, in relation to a specific [[chemical reaction]]. Catalytic activity of one katal (Symbol 1 kat = 1&amp;nbsp;mol/s) of a catalyst means one mole of that catalyst (substance, in [[Mole (unit)|Mol]]) will catalyse 1 mole of the reactant to product in one second. A catalyst may and usually will have different catalytic activity for distinct reactions. See [[katal]] for an example.

There are further derived SI units related to catalytic activity, see the above reference for details.

===Typical mechanism===
{{Main|catalytic cycle}}

Catalysts generally react with one or more reactants to form [[reaction intermediate|intermediates]] that subsequently give the final reaction product, in the process regenerating the catalyst. The following is a typical reaction scheme, where '''''C''''' represents the catalyst, X and Y are reactants, and Z is the product of the reaction of X and Y:
{{NumBlk|:|X + '''''C''''' → X'''''C'''''   |{{EquationRef|1}}}}
{{NumBlk|:|Y + X'''''C''''' → XY'''''C''''' |{{EquationRef|2}}}}
{{NumBlk|:|XY'''''C''''' → '''''C'''''Z     |{{EquationRef|3}}}}
{{NumBlk|:|'''''C'''''Z → '''''C''''' + Z   |{{EquationRef|4}}}}

Although the catalyst is consumed by reaction {{EquationNote|1}}, it is subsequently produced by reaction {{EquationNote|4}}, so it does not occur in the overall reaction equation:
:X + Y → Z
As a catalyst is regenerated in a reaction, often only small amounts are needed to increase the rate of the reaction. In practice, however, catalysts are sometimes consumed in secondary processes.

The catalyst does usually appear in the [[rate equation]]. For example, if the [[rate-determining step]] in the above reaction scheme is the first step &lt;br /&gt;  X + C → XC, the catalyzed reaction will be [[Order of reaction|second order]] with rate equation v = k&lt;sub&gt;cat&lt;/sub&gt;[X] [C], which is proportional to the catalyst concentration [C]. However [C] remains constant during the reaction so that the catalyzed reaction is [[Order of reaction#Pseudo-first order|pseudo-first order]]:
v = k&lt;sub&gt;obs&lt;/sub&gt;[X],   where k&lt;sub&gt;obs&lt;/sub&gt; = k&lt;sub&gt;cat&lt;/sub&gt;[C].

As an example of a detailed mechanism at the microscopic level, in 2008 Danish researchers first revealed the sequence of events when [[oxygen]] and [[hydrogen]] combine on the surface of [[titanium dioxide]] (TiO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, or ''titania'') to produce water.  With a time-lapse series of [[scanning tunneling microscopy]] images, they determined the molecules undergo [[adsorption]], [[dissociation (chemistry)|dissociation]] and [[diffusion]] before reacting.  The intermediate reaction states were: HO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, then H&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and the final reaction product ([[Water dimer|water molecule dimers]]), after which the water molecule [[desorption|desorbs]] from the catalyst surface.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
| first = Mitch
| last = Jacoby
| date = 16 February 2009
| title = Making Water Step by Step
| newspaper = [[Chemical &amp; Engineering News]]
| page = 10
| url = http://pubs.acs.org/cen/news/87/i07/8707notw6.html
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal
| vauthors = Matthiesen J, Wendt S, Hansen JØ, Madsen GK, Lira E, Galliker P, Vestergaard EK, Schaub R, Laegsgaard E, Hammer B, Besenbacher F
| year = 2009
| title = Observation of All the Intermediate Steps of a Chemical Reaction on an Oxide Surface by Scanning Tunneling Microscopy
| journal = [[ACS Nano]]
| volume = 3
| issue = 3
| pages = 517–26
| issn = 1520-605X
| doi = 10.1021/nn8008245
| pmid = 19309169
| citeseerx = 10.1.1.711.974
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Reaction energetics===

[[Image:CatalysisScheme.png|thumb|upright=1.25|Generic potential energy diagram showing the effect of a catalyst in a hypothetical exothermic chemical reaction X + Y to give Z. The presence of the catalyst opens a different reaction pathway (shown in red) with a lower activation energy. The final result and the overall thermodynamics are the same.]]
Catalysts work by providing an (alternative) mechanism involving a different [[transition state]] and lower [[activation energy]]. Consequently,  more molecular collisions have the energy needed to reach the transition state. Hence, catalysts can enable reactions that would otherwise be blocked or slowed by a kinetic barrier.  The catalyst may increase reaction rate or selectivity, or enable the reaction at lower temperatures. This effect can be illustrated with an [[Energy profile (chemistry)|energy profile]] diagram.

In the catalyzed [[elementary reaction]], catalysts do '''not''' change the extent of a reaction: they have '''no''' effect on the [[chemical equilibrium]] of a reaction because the rate of both the forward and the reverse reaction are both affected (see also [[thermodynamics]]).  The [[second law of thermodynamics]] describes why a catalyst does not change the chemical equilibrium of a reaction.  Suppose there was such a catalyst that shifted an equilibrium. Introducing the catalyst to the system would result in a reaction to move to the new equilibrium, producing energy. Production of energy is a necessary result since reactions are spontaneous only if [[Gibbs free energy]] is produced, and if there is no energy barrier, there is no need for a catalyst. Then, removing the catalyst would also result in reaction, producing energy; i.e. the addition and its reverse process, removal, would both produce energy. Thus, a catalyst that could change the equilibrium would be a [[perpetual motion machine]], a contradiction to the laws of thermodynamics.&lt;ref&gt;Robertson, A.J.B. (1970) ''Catalysis of Gas Reactions by Metals''. Logos Press, London.&lt;/ref&gt; Thus, catalyst '''does not''' alter the equilibrium constant. (A catalyst can however change the equilibrium concentrations by reacting in a subsequent step. It is then consumed as the reaction proceeds, and thus it is also a reactant. Illustrative is the base-catalysed [[hydrolysis]] of [[ester]]s, where the produced [[carboxylic acid]] immediately reacts with the base catalyst and thus the reaction equilibrium is shifted towards hydrolysis.)

The [[SI derived unit]] for measuring the '''catalytic activity''' of a catalyst is the [[katal]], which is moles per second. The productivity of a catalyst can be described by the [[turnover number]] (or TON) and the catalytic activity by the ''turn over frequency'' (TOF), which is the TON per time unit. The biochemical equivalent is the [[enzyme unit]].  For more information on the efficiency of enzymatic catalysis, see the article on ''[[Enzyme#Kinetics|enzymes]]''.

The catalyst stabilizes the transition state more than it stabilizes the starting material.  It decreases the kinetic barrier by decreasing the ''difference'' in energy between starting material and transition state. It '''does not''' change the energy difference between starting materials and products (thermodynamic barrier), or the available energy (this is provided by the environment as heat or light).

===Materials===

The chemical nature of catalysts is as diverse as catalysis itself, although some generalizations can be made.  Proton [[acid]]s are probably the most widely used catalysts, especially for the many reactions involving water, including hydrolysis and its reverse.  Multifunctional solids often are catalytically active, e.g. [[zeolite]]s, [[alumina]], higher-order oxides, graphitic carbon, nanoparticles, nanodots, and facets of bulk materials.  [[Transition metals]] are often used to catalyze [[redox]] reactions (oxidation, hydrogenation). Examples are [[nickel]], such as [[Raney nickel]] for hydrogenation, and [[vanadium(V) oxide]] for oxidation of [[sulfur dioxide]] into [[sulfur trioxide]] by the so-called [[contact process]].  Many catalytic processes, especially those used in organic synthesis, require &quot;late transition metals&quot;, such as [[palladium]], [[platinum]], [[gold]], [[ruthenium]], [[rhodium]], or [[iridium]].

Some so-called catalysts are really '''precatalysts'''.  Precatalysts convert to catalysts in the reaction. For example, [[Wilkinson's catalyst]] RhCl(PPh&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;)&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; loses one triphenylphosphine ligand before entering the true catalytic cycle. Precatalysts are easier to store but are easily activated [[in situ#Chemistry and chemical engineering|in situ]]. Because of this preactivation step, many catalytic reactions involve an [[induction period]].

Chemical species that improve catalytic activity are called '''co-catalysts''' ('''cocatalysts''') or '''promoters''' in '''cooperative catalysis'''.

==Types==

Catalysts can be [[heterogeneous]] or [[wikt:Homogeneous|homogeneous]], depending on whether a catalyst exists in the same [[phase (matter)|phase]] as the [[substrate (chemistry)|substrate]]. [[Biocatalysts]] (enzymes) are often seen as a separate group.

===Heterogeneous catalysts===
{{Main|Heterogeneous catalysis}}

[[File:Zeolite-ZSM-5-vdW.png|thumb|right|The microporous molecular structure of the [[zeolite]] ZSM-5 is exploited in catalysts used in refineries]]
[[File:Ceolite nax.JPG|thumb|Zeolites are extruded as pellets for easy handling in catalytic reactors.]]
Heterogeneous catalysts act in a different [[phase (matter)|phase]] than the [[reactants]]. Most heterogeneous catalysts are [[solid]]s that act on substrates in a [[liquid]] or gaseous [[reaction mixture]]. Diverse mechanisms for [[reactions on surfaces]] are known, depending on how the adsorption takes place ([[Langmuir-Hinshelwood-Hougen-Watson|Langmuir-Hinshelwood]], [[Eley–Rideal mechanism|Eley-Rideal]], and Mars-van Krevelen).&lt;ref&gt;Knözinger, Helmut and Kochloefl, Karl (2002) &quot;Heterogeneous Catalysis and Solid Catalysts&quot; in Ullmann's ''Encyclopedia of Industrial Chemistry'', Wiley-VCH, Weinheim. {{DOI|10.1002/14356007.a05_313}}&lt;/ref&gt; The total surface area of solid has an important effect on the reaction rate. The smaller the catalyst particle size, the larger the surface area for a given mass of particles.

A heterogeneous catalyst has '''active sites''', which are the atoms or crystal faces where the reaction actually occurs. Depending on the mechanism, the active site may be either a planar exposed metal surface, a crystal edge with imperfect metal valence or a complicated combination of the two. Thus, not only most of the volume, but also most of the surface of a heterogeneous catalyst may be catalytically inactive. Finding out the nature of the active site requires technically challenging research. Thus, empirical research for finding out new metal combinations for catalysis continues.

For example, in the [[Haber process]], finely divided [[iron]] serves as a catalyst for the synthesis of [[ammonia]] from [[nitrogen]] and [[hydrogen]]. The reacting [[gas]]es [[adsorb]] onto active sites on the iron particles. Once physically adsorbed, the reagents undergo [[chemisorption]] that results in dissociation into adsorbed atomic species, and new bonds between the resulting fragments form in part due to their close proximity. In this way the particularly strong [[triple bond]] in nitrogen is broken, which would be extremely uncommon in the gas phase due to its high activation energy. Thus, the activation energy of the overall reaction is lowered, and the rate of reaction increases.{{citation needed|date=September 2014}} Another place where a heterogeneous catalyst is applied is in the oxidation of sulfur dioxide on [[vanadium(V) oxide]] for the production of [[sulfuric acid]].

Heterogeneous catalysts are typically &quot;[[catalyst support|supported]],&quot; which means that the catalyst is dispersed on a second material that enhances the effectiveness or minimizes their cost. Supports prevent or reduce agglomeration and sintering small catalyst particles, exposing more surface area, thus catalysts have a higher specific activity (per gram) on a support. Sometimes the support is merely a surface on which the catalyst is spread to increase the surface area. More often, the support and the catalyst interact, affecting the catalytic reaction. Supports can also be used in nanoparticle synthesis by providing sites for individual molecules of catalyst to chemically bind. Supports are porous materials with a high surface area, most commonly [[alumina]], [[zeolites]] or various kinds of [[activated carbon]]. Specialized supports include [[silicon dioxide]], [[titanium dioxide]], [[calcium carbonate]], and [[barium sulfate]].

====Electrocatalysts====
{{Main|Electrocatalyst}}

In the context of [[electrochemistry]], specifically in [[fuel cell]] engineering, various metal-containing catalysts are used to enhance the rates of the [[half reaction]]s that comprise the fuel cell. One common type of fuel cell electrocatalyst is based upon [[nanoparticles]] of [[platinum]] that are supported on slightly larger [[carbon]] particles. When in contact with one of the [[electrodes]] in a fuel cell, this platinum increases the rate of [[oxygen]] reduction either to water, or to [[hydroxide]] or [[hydrogen peroxide]].

===Homogeneous catalysts===
{{Main|Homogeneous catalysis}}

Homogeneous catalysts function in the same phase as the reactants, but the mechanistic principles involved in heterogeneous catalysis are generally applicable. Typically homogeneous catalysts are dissolved in a solvent with the substrates.  One example of homogeneous catalysis involves the influence of [[hydrogen|H]]&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; on the [[esterification]] of carboxylic acids, such as the formation of [[methyl acetate]] from [[acetic acid]] and [[methanol]].&lt;ref&gt;Behr, Arno (2002) &quot;Organometallic Compounds and Homogeneous Catalysis&quot; in Ullmann's ''Encyclopedia of Industrial Chemistry'', Wiley-VCH, Weinheim. {{DOI|10.1002/14356007.a18_215}}&lt;/ref&gt; One high-volume process requiring a homogeneous catalyst is [[hydroformylation]], which adds [[carbon monoxide]] to an [[alkene]] to produce an alkyl [[aldehyde]]. The aldehyde can be converted to various products such as alcohols or acids (for e.g. detergents) or [[polyol]]s (for plastics such as [[polycarbonate]] or [[polyurethane]]). For inorganic chemists, homogeneous catalysis is often synonymous with [[organometallic chemistry|organometallic catalysts]].&lt;ref&gt;Elschenbroich, C. (2006) ''Organometallics''. Wiley-VCH: Weinheim. {{ISBN|978-3-527-29390-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Organocatalysis====
{{Main|Organocatalysis}}

Whereas transition metals sometimes attract most of the attention in the study of catalysis, small organic molecules without metals can also exhibit catalytic properties, as is apparent from the fact that many [[enzyme]]s lack transition metals.  Typically, organic catalysts require a higher loading (amount of catalyst per unit amount of reactant, expressed in [[mol%]] [[amount of substance]]) than transition metal(-ion)-based catalysts, but these catalysts are usually commercially available in bulk, helping to reduce costs.  In the early 2000s, these organocatalysts were considered &quot;new generation&quot; and are competitive to traditional [[metal]](-ion)-containing catalysts.  Organocatalysts are supposed to operate akin to metal-free enzymes utilizing, e.g., non-covalent interactions such as [[hydrogen bonding]]. The discipline organocatalysis is divided in the application of covalent (e.g., [[proline]], [[4-Dimethylaminopyridine|DMAP]]) and non-covalent (e.g., [[thiourea organocatalysis]]) organocatalysts referring to the preferred catalyst-[[Substrate (chemistry)|substrate]] [[binding (molecular)|binding]] and interaction, respectively.

===Photocatalysts===

[[Photocatalysis]] is the phenomenon where the catalyst can receive light (such as visible light), be promoted to an excited state, and then undergo [[intersystem crossing]] with the starting material, returning to ground state without being consumed. The excited state of the starting material will then undergo reactions it ordinarily could not if directly illuminated. For example, [[singlet oxygen]] is usually produced by photocatalysis. Photocatalysts are also the main ingredient in [[dye-sensitized solar cell]]s.

===Enzymes and biocatalysts===
{{Main|enzyme catalysis}}

In biology, [[enzyme]]s are protein-based catalysts in [[metabolism]] and [[catabolism]]. Most biocatalysts are enzymes, but other non-protein-based classes of biomolecules also exhibit catalytic properties including [[ribozyme]]s, and synthetic [[deoxyribozyme]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Nelson, D.L. and Cox, M.M. (2000) ''Lehninger, Principles of Biochemistry'' 3rd Ed. Worth Publishing: New York. {{ISBN|1-57259-153-6}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Biocatalysts can be thought of as intermediate between homogeneous and heterogeneous catalysts, although strictly speaking soluble enzymes are homogeneous catalysts and [[Biological membrane|membrane]]-bound enzymes are heterogeneous. Several factors affect the activity of enzymes (and other catalysts) including temperature, pH, concentration of enzyme, substrate, and products.  A particularly important reagent in enzymatic reactions is water, which is the product of many bond-forming reactions and a reactant in many bond-breaking processes.

In [[biocatalysis]], enzymes are employed to prepare many commodity chemicals including [[high-fructose corn syrup]] and [[acrylamide]].

Some [[monoclonal antibodies]] whose binding target is a stable molecule which resembles the transition state of a chemical reaction can function as weak catalysts for that chemical reaction by lowering its activation energy.&lt;ref&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20130821044547/http://www.documentroot.com/2010/03/catalytic-antibodies-simply-explained.html Catalytic Antibodies Simply Explained]. Documentroot.com (2010-03-06). Retrieved on 2015-11-11.&lt;/ref&gt;  Such catalytic antibodies are sometimes called &quot;[[abzymes]]&quot;.

===Nanocatalysts===
{{Main|Nanomaterial-based catalyst}}

Nanocatalysts are nanomaterials with catalytic activities. They have been extensively explored for wide range of applications. Among them, the nanocatalysts with enzyme mimicking activities are collectively called as [[Artificial enzyme#Nanozymes|nanozymes]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Wei|first=Hui|last2=Wang|first2=Erkang|date=2013-06-21|title=Nanomaterials with enzyme-like characteristics (nanozymes): next-generation artificial enzymes|journal=Chemical Society Reviews|language=en|volume=42|issue=14|pages=6060–93|doi=10.1039/C3CS35486E|pmid=23740388|issn=1460-4744|bibcode=2012ChSRv..41.6507P}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Tandem catalysis===

In [[tandem catalysis]] two or more different catalysts are coupled in a one-pot reaction.

===Autocatalysis===
{{Main|Autocatalysis}}

In autocatalysis, the catalyst ''is'' a product of the overall reaction, in contrast to all other types of catalysis considered in this article. The simplest example of autocatalysis is a reaction of type A + B → 2 B, in one or in several steps. The overall reaction is just A → B, so that B is a product. But since B is also a reactant, it may be present in the rate equation and affect the reaction rate. As the reaction proceeds, the concentration of B increases and can accelerate the reaction as a catalyst. In effect, the reaction accelerates itself or is autocatalyzed.

A real example is the hydrolysis of an [[ester]] such as [[aspirin]] to a [[carboxylic acid]] and an [[alcohol]]. In the absence of added acid catalysts, the carboxylic acid product catalyzes the hydrolysis.

==Significance==

[[File:Verbrennung eines Zuckerwürfels.png|thumb|Left: Partially caramelised [[cube sugar]], Right: burning cube sugar with ash as catalyst]]
[[File:TiCrPt micropump3.webm|thumb|A Ti-Cr-Pt tube (~40 μm long) releases oxygen bubbles when immersed in [[hydrogen peroxide]] (via catalytic decomposition), forming a [[micropump]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.1039/C1CP20542K|pmid=21505711|url= http://nanomem.fudan.edu.cn/79solovev2011.pdf |title=Tunable catalytic tubular micro-pumps operating at low concentrations of hydrogen peroxide|journal=Physical Chemistry Chemical Physics|volume=13|issue=21|pages=10131–35|year=2011|last1=Solovev|first1=Alexander A.|last2=Sanchez|first2=Samuel|last3=Mei|first3=Yongfeng|last4=Schmidt|first4=Oliver G.|bibcode=2011PCCP...1310131S}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]

Estimates are that 90% of all commercially produced chemical products involve catalysts at some stage in the process of their manufacture.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Recognizing the Best in Innovation: Breakthrough Catalyst&quot;. ''R&amp;D Magazine'', September 2005, p. 20.&lt;/ref&gt; In 2005, catalytic processes generated about $900 billion in products worldwide.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.climatetechnology.gov/library/2005/tech-options/tor2005-143.pdf 1.4.3 Iindustrial Process Efficiency] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080517071700/http://www.climatetechnology.gov/library/2005/tech-options/tor2005-143.pdf |date=2008-05-17 }}. climatetechnology.gov&lt;/ref&gt;  Catalysis is so pervasive that subareas are not readily classified.  Some areas of particular concentration are surveyed below.

===Energy processing===

[[Petroleum]] refining makes intensive use of catalysis for [[alkylation]], [[catalytic cracking]] (breaking long-chain hydrocarbons into smaller pieces), [[Petroleum naphtha|naphtha]] reforming and [[steam reforming]] (conversion of [[hydrocarbon]]s into [[synthesis gas]]).  Even the exhaust from the burning of fossil fuels is treated via catalysis: [[Catalytic converter]]s, typically composed of [[platinum]] and [[rhodium]], break down some of the more harmful byproducts of automobile exhaust.
:2 CO  +  2 NO  →   2 CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;  +  N&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;

With regard to synthetic fuels, an old but still important process is the [[Fischer-Tropsch synthesis]] of hydrocarbons from [[synthesis gas]], which itself is processed via [[water gas shift reaction|water-gas shift reactions]], catalysed by iron.  [[Biodiesel]] and related biofuels require processing via both inorganic and biocatalysts.

[[Fuel cell]]s rely on catalysts for both the anodic and cathodic reactions.

[[Catalytic heater]]s generate flameless heat from a supply of combustible fuel.

===Bulk chemicals===

Some of the largest-scale chemicals are produced via catalytic oxidation, often using [[oxygen]].  Examples include [[nitric acid]] (from ammonia), [[sulfuric acid]] (from [[sulfur dioxide]] to [[sulfur trioxide]] by the [[contact process]]), [[terephthalic acid]] from p-xylene, [[acrylic acid]] from [[propylene]] or [[propane]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Kinetic studies of propane oxidation on Mo and V based mixed oxide catalysts |date=2011 |url=https://pure.mpg.de/rest/items/item_1199619_5/component/file_1199618/content}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=Surface chemistry of phase-pure M1 MoVTeNb oxide during operation in selective oxidation of propane to acrylic acid |journal=Journal of Catalysis |date=2012 |volume=285 |pages=48–60 |url=https://pure.mpg.de/rest/items/item_1108560_8/component/file_1402724/content|doi=10.1016/j.jcat.2011.09.012 |last1=Hävecker |first1=Michael |last2=Wrabetz |first2=Sabine |last3=Kröhnert |first3=Jutta |last4=Csepei |first4=Lenard-Istvan |last5=Naumann d'Alnoncourt |first5=Raoul |last6=Kolen'Ko |first6=Yury V. |last7=Girgsdies |first7=Frank |last8=Schlögl |first8=Robert |last9=Trunschke |first9=Annette |hdl=11858/00-001M-0000-0012-1BEB-F }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=The reaction network in propane oxidation over phase-pure MoVTeNb M1 oxide catalysts |journal=Journal of Catalysis |date=2014 |volume=311 |pages=369–385 |url=https://pure.mpg.de/rest/items/item_1896844_6/component/file_1896843/content|doi=10.1016/j.jcat.2013.12.008 |last1=Naumann d'Alnoncourt |first1=Raoul |last2=Csepei |first2=Lénárd-István |last3=Hävecker |first3=Michael |last4=Girgsdies |first4=Frank |last5=Schuster |first5=Manfred E. |last6=Schlögl |first6=Robert |last7=Trunschke |first7=Annette |hdl=11858/00-001M-0000-0014-F434-5 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[acrylonitrile]] from propane and ammonia.

Many other chemical products are generated by large-scale reduction, often via [[hydrogenation]].  The largest-scale example is [[ammonia]], which is prepared via the [[Haber process]] from [[nitrogen]].  [[Methanol]] is prepared from [[carbon monoxide]] or carbon dioxide.

Bulk polymers derived from [[ethylene]] and [[propylene]] are often prepared via [[Ziegler-Natta catalysis]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Mokrani |first1=Touhami |last2=van Reenen |first2=Albert |last3=Amer |first3=Ismael |last4=Mokrani |first4=Touhami |last5=van Reenen |first5=Albert |last6=Amer |first6=Ismael |title=Molecular weight and tacticity effect on morphological and mechanical properties of Ziegler–Natta catalyzed isotactic polypropylenes |journal=Polímeros |date=December 2015 |volume=25 |issue=6 |pages=556–563 |doi=10.1590/0104-1428.2158 |language=en |issn=0104-1428}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Polyesters, polyamides, and [[isocyanate]]s are derived via [[acid-base catalysis]].

Most [[carbonylation]] processes require metal catalysts, examples include the [[Monsanto acetic acid process]] and [[hydroformylation]].

===Fine chemicals===

Many [[fine chemicals]] are prepared via catalysis; methods include those of heavy industry as well as more specialized processes that would be prohibitively expensive on a large scale.  Examples include the [[Heck reaction]], and [[Friedel–Crafts reaction]]s.

Because most bioactive compounds are [[Chirality (chemistry)|chiral]], many pharmaceuticals are produced by enantioselective catalysis (catalytic [[asymmetric synthesis]]).

===Food processing===

One of the most obvious applications of catalysis is the [[hydrogenation]] (reaction with [[hydrogen]] gas) of fats using [[nickel]] catalyst to produce [[margarine]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | publisher = Chemguide | title = Types of catalysis | url = http://www.chemguide.co.uk/physical/catalysis/introduction.html | accessdate =|first = Jim|last = Clark|date = October 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Many other foodstuffs are prepared via biocatalysis (see below).

===Environment===

Catalysis impacts the environment by increasing the efficiency of industrial processes, but catalysis also plays a direct role in the environment. A notable example is the catalytic role of [[chlorine]] [[free radical]]s in the breakdown of [[ozone]]. These radicals are formed by the action of [[ultraviolet]] [[radiation]] on [[chlorofluorocarbon]]s (CFCs).
:Cl&lt;sup&gt;'''·'''&lt;/sup&gt;  +  O&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;  →   ClO&lt;sup&gt;'''·'''&lt;/sup&gt;  +  O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;
:ClO&lt;sup&gt;'''·'''&lt;/sup&gt;  +  O&lt;sup&gt;·&lt;/sup&gt;  →  Cl&lt;sup&gt;'''·'''&lt;/sup&gt;  +  O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;

==History==

Generally speaking,&lt;ref&gt;Bård Lindström and Lars J. Petterson (2003) &quot;[http://image.sciencenet.cn/olddata/kexue.com.cn/upload/blog/file/2008/10/200810102212944318.pdf A brief history of catalysis]&quot; ''Cattech'', '''7''' (4) : 130–38.&lt;/ref&gt; anything that increases the rate of a process is a &quot;catalyst&quot;, a term derived from [[Greek language|Greek]] [[wikt:καταλύω|καταλύειν]], meaning &quot;to annul,&quot; or &quot;to untie,&quot; or &quot;to pick up.&quot;  The concept of catalysis was invented by chemist [[Elizabeth Fulhame]] and described in a 1794 book, based on her novel work in oxidation-reduction experiments.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Women in Chemistry: Their Changing Roles from Alchemical Times to the Mid-Twentieth Century|publisher = American Chemical Society|date = 2001|isbn = 978-0-8412-3522-9|first = Marelene|last = Rayner-Canham|first2 = Geoffrey William|last2 = Rayner-Canham|url-access = registration|url = https://archive.org/details/womeninchemistry0000rayn}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first chemical reaction in organic chemistry that utilized a catalyst was studied in 1811 by [[Gottlieb Kirchhoff]] who discovered the acid-catalyzed conversion of starch to glucose. The term ''catalysis'' was later used by [[Jöns Jakob Berzelius]] in 1835&lt;ref&gt;Berzelius, J.J. (1835) ''Årsberättelsen om framsteg i fysik och kemi'' [Annual report on progress in physics and chemistry]. Stockholm, Sweden:  Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences.  After reviewing Eilhard Mitscherlich's research on the formation of ether, Berzelius coins the word ''katalys'' (catalysis) on [https://books.google.com/books?id=1DM1AAAAcAAJ&amp;pg=PA245#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false p. 245]:
&lt;blockquote&gt;Original:  ''Jag skall derföre, för att begagna en i kemien välkänd härledning, kalla den kroppars'' katalytiska kraft, ''sönderdelning genom denna kraft ''katalys, ''likasom vi med ordet analys beteckna åtskiljandet af kroppars beståndsdelar medelst den vanliga kemiska frändskapen.''&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;''Translation'':  I shall, therefore, to employ a well-known derivation in chemistry, call [the catalytic] bodies [i.e., substances] the ''catalytic force'' and the decomposition of [other] bodies by this force ''catalysis'', just as we signify by the word ''analysis'' the separation of the constituents of bodies by the usual chemical affinities.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; to describe reactions that are accelerated by substances that remain unchanged after the reaction. [[Elizabeth Fulhame|Fulhame]], who predated Berzelius, did work with water as opposed to metals in her reduction experiments. Other 18th century chemists who worked in catalysis were [[Eilhard Mitscherlich]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Mitscherlich, E. |year=1834|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=wCUAAAAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA273 |title=Ueber die Aetherbildung|trans-title=On the formation of ether|journal=Annalen der Physik und Chemie|volume=31|issue=18|pages=273–82|bibcode=1834AnP...107..273M|doi=10.1002/andp.18341071802}}&lt;/ref&gt; who referred to it as ''contact'' processes, and [[Johann Wolfgang Döbereiner]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author= Döbereiner |year=1822|url=http://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=nyp.33433069069148;view=1up;seq=107 |title=Glühendes Verbrennen des Alkohols durch verschiedene erhitzte Metalle und Metalloxyde|trans-title=Incandescent burning of alcohol by various heated metals and metal oxides|journal=Journal für Chemie und Physik|volume=34|pages= 91–92}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Döbereiner |year=1823|url=http://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=nyp.33433069069189;view=1up;seq=341 |title=Neu entdeckte merkwürdige Eigenschaften des Platinsuboxyds, des oxydirten Schwefel-Platins und des metallischen Platinstaubes|trans-title=Newly discovered remarkable properties of platinum suboxide, oxidized platinum sulfide and metallic platinum dust|journal=Journal für Chemie und Physik|volume=38|pages=321–26}}&lt;/ref&gt; who spoke of ''contact action. ''He developed [[Döbereiner's lamp]], a [[Lighter (fire starter)|lighter]] based on [[hydrogen]] and a [[platinum]] sponge, which became a commercial success in the 1820s that lives on today. [[Humphry Davy]] discovered the use of platinum in catalysis.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Davy, Humphry |year=1817|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=xohJAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA77|title=Some new experiments and observations on the combustion of gaseous mixtures, with an account of a method of preserving a continued light in mixtures of inflammable gases and air without flame|doi=10.1098/rstl.1817.0009|journal=Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London|volume=107|pages= 77–85}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In the 1880s, [[Wilhelm Ostwald]] at [[Leipzig University]] started a systematic investigation into reactions that were catalyzed by the presence of [[acid]]s and bases, and found that chemical reactions occur at finite rates and that these rates can be used to determine the strengths of acids and bases. For this work, Ostwald was awarded the 1909 [[Nobel Prize in Chemistry]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author =Roberts, M.W.  | title = Birth of the catalytic concept (1800–1900) | journal = [[Catalysis Letters]] | volume = 67 | issue = 1
 | year = 2000 | doi = 10.1023/A:1016622806065 | pages= 1–4}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Vladimir Ipatieff]] performed some of the earliest industrial scale reactions, including the discovery and commercialization of oligomerization and the development of catalysts for hydrogenation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Nicholas |first1=Christopher P. |title=Dehydration, Dienes, High Octane, and High Pressures: Contributions from Vladimir Nikolaevich Ipatieff, a Father of Catalysis |journal=ACS Catalysis |volume=8 |issue=9 |date=21 August 2018 |pages=8531–39 |doi=10.1021/acscatal.8b02310}}{{open access}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Inhibitors, poisons, and promoters==

Substances that reduce the action of catalysts are called [[Reaction inhibitor|catalyst inhibitors]] if reversible, and [[Catalyst poisoning|catalyst poisons]] if irreversible. Promoters are substances that increase the catalytic activity, even though they are not catalysts by themselves.

Inhibitors are sometimes referred to as &quot;negative catalysts&quot; since they decrease the reaction rate.&lt;ref name=Laidler78/&gt; However the term inhibitor is preferred since they do not work by introducing a reaction path with higher activation energy; this would not reduce the rate since the reaction would continue to occur by the non-catalyzed path. Instead they act either by deactivating catalysts, or by removing reaction intermediates such as free radicals.&lt;ref name=Laidler78&gt;Laidler, K.J. (1978) ''Physical Chemistry with Biological Applications'', Benjamin/Cummings. pp. 415–17. {{ISBN|0-8053-5680-0}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=LM82&gt;Laidler, K.J. and Meiser, J.H. (1982) ''Physical Chemistry'', Benjamin/Cummings, p. 425. {{ISBN|0-618-12341-5}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

The inhibitor may modify selectivity in addition to rate. For instance, in the reduction of [[alkyne]]s to [[alkene]]s, a [[palladium]] (Pd) catalyst partly &quot;poisoned&quot; with [[lead(II) acetate]] (Pb(CH&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;)&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;) can be used.&lt;ref name=Lindlar&gt;{{OrgSynth | author = Lindlar, H. and Dubuis, R. | title = Palladium Catalyst for Partial Reduction of Acetylenes | collvol = 5 | collvolpages = 880 | year = 2016 | doi=10.15227/orgsyn.046.0089}}&lt;/ref&gt; Without the deactivation of the catalyst, the alkene produced would be further reduced to [[alkane]].&lt;ref&gt;Jencks, W.P. (1969) ''Catalysis in Chemistry and Enzymology'' McGraw-Hill, New York. {{ISBN|0-07-032305-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bender, Myron L; Komiyama, Makoto and Bergeron, Raymond J (1984) ''The Bioorganic Chemistry of Enzymatic Catalysis'' Wiley-Interscience, Hoboken, U.S. {{ISBN|0-471-05991-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The inhibitor can produce this effect by, e.g., selectively poisoning only certain types of active sites. Another mechanism is the modification of surface geometry. For instance, in hydrogenation operations, large planes of metal surface function as sites of [[hydrogenolysis]] catalysis while sites catalyzing [[hydrogenation]] of unsaturates are smaller. Thus, a poison that covers surface randomly will tend to reduce the number of uncontaminated large planes but leave proportionally more smaller sites free, thus changing the hydrogenation vs. hydrogenolysis selectivity. Many other mechanisms are also possible.

Promoters can cover up surface to prevent production of a mat of coke, or even actively remove such material (e.g., rhenium on platinum in [[catalytic reforming|platforming]]). They can aid the dispersion of the catalytic material or bind to reagents .

==Current market==

The global demand for catalysts in 2010 was estimated at approximately US$29.5 billion. With the rapid recovery in the automotive and chemical industries overall, the global catalyst market is expected to experience fast growth in the coming years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Market Report: Global Catalyst Market | edition = 2nd | publisher = Acmite Market Intelligence | url = http://www.acmite.com/market-reports/chemicals/global-catalyst-market-report.html }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==

{{Portal|Chemistry|Biology}}
{{colbegin}}
* [[Chemical reaction]]
** [[Substrate (chemistry)|Substrate]]
** [[Reagent]]
** [[Enzyme]]
** [[Product (chemistry)|Product]]
* [[Abzyme]]
* [[Acid catalysis]] (includes Base catalysis)
* [[Autocatalysis]]
* [[BIG-NSE]] (Berlin Graduate School of Natural Sciences and Engineering)
* ''[[Catalysis Science &amp; Technology]]'' (a chemistry journal)
* [[Catalytic resonance theory]]
* [[Environmental triggers]]
* [[Enzyme catalysis]]
* [[Industrial catalysts]]
* [[Kelvin probe force microscope]]
* [[Limiting reagent]]
* [[Pharmaceutic adjuvant]]
* [[Phase-boundary catalysis]]
* [[Phase transfer catalyst]]
* [[Photocatalysis]]
* [[Ribozyme]] (RNA biocatalyst)
* [[SUMO enzymes]]
* [[Temperature-programmed reduction]]
* [[Thermal desorption spectroscopy]]
{{colend}}

==References==
* {{GoldBookRef | title = catalyst | file = C00876}}
{{reflist}}

==External links==

{{Wiktionary|catalysis}}
{{Commons category|Catalysis}}
{{EB1911 poster|Catalysis}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20080530162951/http://scienceaid.co.uk/chemistry/inorganic/catalysis.html Science Aid: Catalysts] Page for high school level science
* [http://aci.anorg.chemie.tu-muenchen.de/wah/vortraege/catalysis.pdf W.A. Herrmann Technische Universität presentation]
* [http://www.tuat.ac.jp/~kameyama/ Alumite Catalyst, Kameyama-Sakurai Laboratory, Japan]
* [http://www.inorganic-chemistry-and-catalysis.eu/ Inorganic Chemistry and Catalysis Group, Utrecht University, The Netherlands]
* [http://www.biw.kuleuven.be/ifc/cok/home.htm Centre for Surface Chemistry and Catalysis]
* [http://www.udec.cl/~carbocat Carbons &amp; Catalysts Group, University of Concepcion, Chile]
* [http://www.nsfcentc.org Center for Enabling New Technologies Through Catalysis, An NSF Center for Chemical Innovation, USA]
* [http://www.sciencenews.org/view/generic/id/42507/title/Bubbles_turn_on_chemical_catalysts &quot;Bubbles turn on chemical catalysts&quot;], Science News magazine online, April 6, 2009.

{{Reaction mechanisms}}
{{Galvanic cells}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Chemical kinetics]]
[[Category:Catalysis| ]]
[[Category:Articles containing video clips]]</text>
      <sha1>3r63lodivcf36ch8lvxbzw9w4uwf9d4</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
