  <page>
    <title>Carbon sink</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5980</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942560425</id>
      <parentid>942106647</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-25T12:21:09Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Kku</username>
        <id>5846</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>link overgrazing</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Natural reservoir storing carbon-containing molecules}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2012}}
[[File:Carbon cycle.jpg|thumb|right|upright=2|This diagram of the fast carbon cycle shows the movement of carbon between land, atmosphere, soil and oceans in billions of tons of carbon per year. Yellow numbers are natural fluxes, red are human contributions in billions of tons of carbon per year. White numbers indicate stored carbon.]]
[[File:CO2 pump hg.svg|thumb|upright=2|Air-sea exchange of CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;]]

A '''carbon sink''' is a natural reservoir that stores [[carbon]]-containing chemical compounds accumulated over an indefinite period of time. Public awareness of the significance of CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; sinks has grown since passage of the [[Kyoto Protocol]], which promotes their use as a form of [[carbon offset]]. There are also different strategies used to enhance this process.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1111/gcbb.12401|title=Investigating the biochar effects on C-mineralization and sequestration of carbon in soil compared with conventional amendments using the stable isotope (δ 13 C) approach|journal=GCB Bioenergy|volume=9|issue=6|pages=1085–1099|year=2017|last1=Yousaf|first1=Balal|last2=Liu|first2=Guijian|last3=Wang|first3=Ruwei|last4=Abbas|first4=Qumber|last5=Imtiaz|first5=Muhammad|last6=Liu|first6=Ruijia}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Toclimit|3}}&lt;br /&gt;
==General==
Increase in atmospheric [[carbon dioxide]] means increase in global temperature. The amount of carbon dioxide varies naturally in a dynamic equilibrium with photosynthesis of land plants. The natural sinks are:
* Soil is the Earth's greatest carbon store and active carbon sink&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Blakemore, R.J. |title=Non-Flat Earth Recalibrated for Terrain and Topsoil |journal=Soil Systems |volume=2 |issue=4 |pages=64 |year=2018 |doi=10.3390/soilsystems2040064 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Photosynthesis]] by terrestrial plants with grass and trees serving as carbon sinks during growing seasons.
* [[Ocean storage of carbon dioxide|Absorption of carbon dioxide by the oceans]] via [[solubility pump|physicochemical]] and minor [[biological pump|biological]] processes

While the creation of artificial sinks has been discussed, no major artificial systems [[carbon dioxide removal|remove carbon from the atmosphere]] on a material scale.

Carbon sources include the combustion of fossil fuels (coal, natural gas, and oil) by humans for energy and transportation &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Environmental Protection Agency|first1=United States|title=Overview of Greenhouse Gases|url=http://www.epa.gov/climatechange/ghgemissions/gases/co2.html|website=EPA Climate Change|publisher=US EPA|accessdate=17 May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; and farmland (by animal respiration), although there are proposals for improvements in farming practices to reverse this.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://articles.extension.org/pages/69145/sources-of-agricultural-greenhouse-gases|title=Sources of Agricultural Greenhouse Gases|last=Powers|first=Crystal|date=January 26, 2016|work=Extension|access-date=2018-02-27|language=en|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180228041151/http://articles.extension.org/pages/69145/sources-of-agricultural-greenhouse-gases|archive-date=28 February 2018|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Kyoto Protocol ==
{{update section|reason=Paris Agreement|date=November 2019}}
Because growing vegetation takes in [[carbon dioxide]], the [[Kyoto Protocol]] allows [[United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change#Annex I countries|Annex I countries]] with large areas of growing forests to issue [[Removal Units]] to recognize the sequestration of carbon. The additional units make it easier for them to achieve their target emission levels. It is estimated that forests absorb between 10 and 20 [[ton]]s of [[carbon dioxide]] per [[hectare]] each year, through photosynthetic conversion into [[starch]], [[cellulose]], [[lignin]], and other components of wooden [[biomass]]. While this has been well documented for temperate forests and plantations, the [[fauna]] of the tropical forests place some limitations for such global estimates. {{Citation needed|date=February 2017}}

Some countries seek to trade emission rights in carbon emission markets, purchasing the unused carbon emission allowances of other countries. If overall limits on greenhouse gas emission are put into place, [[cap and trade]] market mechanisms are purported to find cost-effective ways to reduce emissions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.rff.org/Documents/RFF-RPT-Renewables.pdf | archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070604191032/http://www.rff.org/Documents/RFF-RPT-Renewables.pdf | archivedate=4 June 2007 | title=Electricity, Renewables, and Climate Change: Searching for a Cost-Effective Policy |author1=Karen Palmer |author2=Dallas Burtraw | publisher=[[Resources for the Future]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;  There is as yet no [[carbon audit regime]] for all such markets globally, and none is specified in the Kyoto Protocol.  National carbon emissions are self-declared.

In the [[Clean Development Mechanism]], only [[afforestation]] and [[reforestation]] are eligible to produce [[certified emission reduction]]s (CERs) in the first commitment period of the Kyoto Protocol (2008–2012). Forest conservation activities or activities avoiding [[deforestation]], which would result in emission reduction through the conservation of existing carbon stocks, are not eligible at this time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|vauthors=((Manguiat MSZ)), Verheyen R, Mackensen J, Scholz G|title=Legal aspects in the implementation of CDM forestry projects |journal=IUCN Environmental Policy and Law Papers |id=Number 59 |year=2005 |url=http://data.iucn.org/dbtw-wpd/edocs/EPLP-059.pdf |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100716142612/http://data.iucn.org/dbtw-wpd/edocs/EPLP-059.pdf |archivedate=16 July 2010 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt; Also, agricultural carbon sequestration is not possible yet.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Rosenbaum KL, Schoene D, Mekouar A|title=Climate change and the forest sector. Possible national and subnational legislation |journal=FAO Forestry Papers |id=Number 144 |year=2004 |url=http://www.fao.org/docrep/007/y5647e/y5647e00.HTM}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Storage in terrestrial and marine environments ==

=== Soils ===
{{update section|reason=IPCC Climate Change and Land report|date=November 2019}}
[[Soils]] represent a short to long-term carbon storage medium, and contain more carbon than all terrestrial vegetation and the atmosphere combined.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |journal=Soil Science |volume=166 |issue=11 |pages=858–71 |last=Swift |first=Roger S. |title=Sequestration of Carbon by soil |date=November 2001 |doi=10.1097/00010694-200111000-00010 |bibcode=2001SoilS.166..858S }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Batjes |first=Niels H. |journal=European Journal of Soil Science |volume=47 |issue=2 |pages=151–63 |title=Total carbon and nitrogen in the soils of the world  |year=1996 |doi=10.1111/j.1365-2389.1996.tb01386.x }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;BatjesGeoderma2016&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|author-last1=Batjes|author-first14=Niels H.|year=2016|title=Harmonised soil property values for broad-scale modelling (WISE30sec) with estimates of global soil carbon stocks |journal=Geoderma|volume=269|pages= 61–68 | doi=10.1016/j.geoderma.2016.01.034|bibcode=2016Geode.269...61B}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Plant litter]] and other [[biomass]] including [[charcoal]] accumulates as [[Soil organic matter|organic matter]] in soils, and is degraded by [[chemical weathering]] and biological [[biodegradation|degradation]].  More recalcitrant [[organic material|organic]] [[Biopolymer|carbon polymers]] such as [[cellulose]], [[hemi-cellulose]], [[lignin]], aliphatic compounds, waxes and [[terpenoid]]s are collectively retained as [[humus]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author1=Klaus Lorenza |author2=Rattan Lala |author3=Caroline M. Prestonb |author4=Klaas G.J. Nieropc |title=Strengthening the soil organic carbon pool by increasing contributions from recalcitrant aliphatic bio(macro)molecules |journal=Geoderma |volume=142 |issue=1–2 |pages=1–10 |date=15 November 2007 |doi=10.1016/j.geoderma.2007.07.013 |url=https://zenodo.org/record/896885 |bibcode=2007Geode.142....1L }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Organic matter tends to accumulate in litter and soils of colder regions such as the [[boreal forest]]s of North America and the [[Taiga]] of [[Russia]]. [[Leaf litter]] and [[humus]] are rapidly oxidized and poorly retained in [[sub-tropical]] and tropical [[climate]] conditions due to high temperatures and extensive leaching by rainfall. Areas where [[shifting cultivation]] or [[slash and burn]] agriculture are practiced are generally only fertile for two to three years before they are abandoned.  These tropical jungles are similar to coral reefs in that they are highly efficient at conserving and circulating necessary nutrients, which explains their lushness in a nutrient desert.{{Citation needed|date=May 2007}}  Much [[soil carbon|organic carbon]] retained in many agricultural areas worldwide has been severely depleted due to [[intensive farming]] practices.

[[Grassland]]s contribute to [[soil organic matter]], stored mainly in their extensive fibrous root mats. Due in part to the climatic conditions of these regions (e.g. cooler temperatures and semi-arid to arid conditions), these soils can accumulate significant quantities of organic matter. This can vary based on rainfall, the length of the winter season, and the frequency of naturally occurring lightning-induced [[Wildfire|grass-fires]].  While these fires release carbon dioxide, they improve the quality of the grasslands overall, in turn increasing the amount of carbon retained in the humic material.  They also deposit carbon directly to the soil in the form of [[Biochar|char]] that does not significantly degrade back to carbon dioxide.

Forest fires release absorbed carbon back into the atmosphere,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Mooney|first1=Chris|title=The really scary thing about wildfires is how they can worsen climate change|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/energy-environment/wp/2015/05/14/how-massive-wildfires-can-actually-warm-the-planet/|accessdate=24 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; as does deforestation due to rapidly increased oxidation of soil organic matter.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Deforestation &amp; Carbon Emission|url=http://deforestation.geologist-1011.net/|website=Consulting Geologist|accessdate=24 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Organic matter in [[peat]] bogs undergoes slow [[anaerobic decomposition]] below the surface.  This process is slow enough that in many cases the bog grows rapidly and [[Carbon fixation|fixes]] more carbon from the atmosphere than is released.  Over time, the peat grows deeper.  Peat bogs hold approximately one-quarter of the carbon stored in land plants and soils.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web  |last=Chester  |first=Bronwyn |title=The case of the missing sink  |publisher=[[McGill University|McGill]] Reporter  |date=20 April 2000 |url=https://www.mcgill.ca/reporter/32/15/roulet/ |accessdate=8 July 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Under some conditions, forests and peat bogs may become sources of CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, such as when a forest is flooded by the construction of a hydroelectric dam. Unless the forests and peat are harvested before flooding, the rotting vegetation is a source of CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and [[methane]] comparable in magnitude to the amount of carbon released by a fossil-fuel powered plant of equivalent power.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine | url=https://www.newscientist.com/article.ns?id=dn7046 | title=Hydroelectric power's dirty secret revealed | magazine=[[New Scientist]] | date=24 February 2005 | accessdate=8 July 2008 | author=Duncan Graham-Rowe}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Regenerative agriculture ===
{{See also|Biosequestration}}

Current agricultural practices lead to carbon loss from soils. It has been suggested that improved farming practices could return the soils to being a carbon sink. Present worldwide practises of [[overgrazing]] are substantially reducing many grasslands' performance as carbon sinks.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=C. Michael Hogan|date=December 28, 2009|url=http://www.eoearth.org/article/Overgrazing|title=Overgrazing|work=Encyclopedia of Earth|others=Sidney Draggan (Topic Editor)|editor=Cutler J. Cleveland|publisher=Environmental Information Coalition, National Council for Science and the Environment|location=Washington DC|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100711111015/http://www.eoearth.org/article/Overgrazing|archive-date=2010-07-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[The Rodale Institute]] says that [[regenerative agriculture]], if practiced on the planet’s tillable land of {{convert|3.6|e9acre|e6km2|order=flip|abbr=unit}}, could sequester up to 40% of current CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; emissions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite report|url=http://www.rodaleinstitute.org/files/Rodale_Research_Paper.pdf|title=Regenerative 21st Century Farming: A Solution to Global Warming|author=Timothy J. LaSalle|author2=Paul Hepperly|date=2008|accessdate=2008-05-19|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080910213832/http://www.rodaleinstitute.org/files/Rodale_Research_Paper.pdf|archivedate=10 September 2008|publisher=The Rodale Institute}}&lt;/ref&gt; They claim that agricultural carbon sequestration has the potential to mitigate global warming. When using biologically-based regenerative practices, this dramatic benefit can be accomplished with no decrease in yields or farmer profits.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Farming Systems Trial|url=http://66.147.244.123/~rodalein/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/FSTbookletFINAL.pdf|archive-url=https://wayback.archive-it.org/all/20130222094119/http://66.147.244.123/~rodalein/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/FSTbookletFINAL.pdf|url-status=dead|archive-date=22 February 2013|publisher=Rodale Institute|accessdate=20 November 2013|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; Organically managed soils can convert carbon dioxide from a greenhouse gas into a food-producing asset.

In 2006, U.S. carbon dioxide emissions, largely from fossil fuel combustion, were estimated at nearly {{convert|6.5|e9short ton|e9t|order=flip|abbr=off}}.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.pmel.noaa.gov/pubs/PDF/feel2899/feel2899.pdf|title=Carbon Dioxide and Our Ocean Legacy, by Richard A. Feely et. al}}&lt;/ref&gt; If a {{convert|2000|lb/acre|t/km2|order=flip}} per year sequestration rate was achieved on all {{convert|434|e6acre|e6km2|order=flip|abbr=unit}} of cropland in the United States, nearly {{convert|1.6|e9short ton|e9t|order=flip|abbr=unit}} of carbon dioxide would be sequestered per year, mitigating close to one quarter of the country's total fossil fuel emissions.

=== Oceans ===
{{update section|reason=IPCC Special Report on the Ocean and Cryosphere in a Changing Climate|date=November 2019}}
Presently, oceans are CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; sinks, and represent the largest active carbon sink on Earth, absorbing more than a quarter of the carbon dioxide that humans put into the air.&lt;ref name=EarthInst&gt;[http://www.earth.columbia.edu/articles/view/2586 ''Earth Institute News''], Columbia University, 18 Nov. 2009&lt;/ref&gt; The [[solubility pump]] is the primary mechanism responsible for the CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; absorption by the oceans.

The [[biological pump]] plays a negligible role, because of the limitation to pump by ambient light and nutrients required by the [[phytoplankton]] that ultimately drive it. [[Total inorganic carbon]] is not believed to limit [[primary production]] in the oceans, so its increasing availability in the ocean does not directly affect production (the situation on land is different, since enhanced atmospheric levels of [[CO2 fertilization effect|CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; essentially &quot;fertilize&quot;]] land plant growth to some threshold). However, [[ocean acidification]] by invading anthropogenic CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; may affect the biological pump by negatively impacting [[calcium carbonate|calcifying]] organisms such as [[coccolithophore]]s, [[foraminiferans]] and [[pteropod]]s. [[Climate change]] may also affect the biological pump in the future by warming and [[stratification (water)|stratifying]] the surface ocean, thus reducing the supply of limiting nutrients to surface waters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|vauthors=Doney S, Fabry V, Feely R, Kleypas J|year=2009|title=Ocean Acidification: The Other CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; Problem|journal=Annual Review of Marine Science|volume= 1|pages= 169–192|doi=10.1146/annurev.marine.010908.163834|bibcode = 2009ARMS....1..169D |url=http://www.nrdc.org/oceans/acidification/files/NRDC-OceanAcidFSWeb.pdf|pmid=21141034}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2008 study found that CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; could potentially increase primary productivity, particularly in eel grasses in coastal and estuarine habitats.&lt;ref&gt;Buridge et al. 2008. Rates of carbon dissolution in permeable sediments estimated from pore-water profiles: The role of sea grasses. Journal Limnology and Oceanography.&lt;/ref&gt;

In January 2009, the [[Monterey Bay Aquarium Research Institute]] and the [[National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration]] announced a joint study to determine whether the ocean off the California coast was serving as a carbon source or a carbon sink.  Principal instrumentation for the study will be self-contained CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; monitors placed on [[buoy]]s in the ocean.  They will measure the partial pressure of CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; in the ocean and the atmosphere just above the water surface.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=Battelle announces CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; Monitor |journal=[[Chemical &amp; Engineering News]] |pages=66 |date=19 January 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In February 2009, Science Daily reported that the Southern Indian Ocean is becoming less effective at absorbing carbon dioxide due to changes to the region's climate which include higher wind speeds.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=CNRS (Délégation Paris Michel-Ange) |title=Ocean Less Effective At Absorbing Carbon Dioxide Emitted By Human Activity |date=23 February 2009|work=ScienceDaily |url=https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2009/02/090216092937.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On longer timescales, oceans may be both sources and sinks – during [[ice age]]s {{CO2}} levels decrease to ≈180 ppmv, and much of this is believed to be stored in the oceans. As ice ages end, {{CO2}} is released from the oceans and {{CO2}} levels during previous interglacials have been around ≈280 ppmv. This role as a sink for CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; is driven by two processes, the [[solubility pump]] and the [[biological pump]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Raven |first=J. A. |first2=P. G. |last2=Falkowski |title=Oceanic sinks for atmospheric CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; |journal=Plant, Cell &amp; Environment |volume=22 |pages=741–55 |year=1999  |doi=10.1046/j.1365-3040.1999.00419.x |issue=6}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The former is primarily a function of differential CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; solubility in [[seawater]] and the [[thermohaline circulation]], while the latter is the sum of a series of biological processes that transport carbon (in [[organic chemistry|organic]] and [[inorganic chemistry of carbon|inorganic]] forms) from the surface [[photic zone|euphotic zone]] to the ocean's interior.  A small fraction of the organic carbon transported by the biological pump to the [[seabed|seafloor]] is buried in [[anoxic sea water|anoxic]] conditions under sediments and ultimately forms [[fossil fuel]]s such as [[petroleum|oil]] and natural gas.

At the end of glacials with sea level rapidly rising, corals tend to grow slower due to increased ocean temperature as seen on the Showtime series &quot;Years of Living Dangerously&quot;.  The calcium carbonate from which coral skeletons are made is just over 60% carbon dioxide.  If we postulate that coral reefs were eroded down to the glacial sea level, then coral reefs have grown 120m upward since the end of the recent glacial.{{citation needed|date=May 2013}}

== Enhancing natural sequestration ==

=== Forests ===
{{See also|Biosequestration}}

Forests can be carbon stores,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=https://www.sciencenews.org/article/tropical-forests-have-flipped-sponges-sources-carbon-dioxide |title=Tropical forests have flipped from sponges to sources of carbon dioxide; A closer look at the world's trees reveals a loss of density in the tropics |author=Carolyn Gramling |date=September 28, 2017 |journal=[[Sciencenews.org]] |volume=358 |issue=6360 |pages=230–234 |doi=10.1126/science.aam5962 |access-date=6 October 2017|bibcode=2017Sci...358..230B |pmid=28971966 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=Tropical forests are a net carbon source based on aboveground measurements of gain and loss |vauthors=Baccini A, Walker W, Carvalho L, Farina M, Sulla-Menashe D, Houghton RA |date=13 October 2017 |journal= Science|volume=358 |issue=6360 |pages=230–234 |doi=10.1126/science.aam5962 |pmid = 28971966|bibcode=2017Sci...358..230B }}&lt;/ref&gt; and they are carbon dioxide sinks when they are increasing in density or area. In [[Boreal forest of Canada|Canada's boreal forests]] as much as 80% of the total carbon is stored in the soils as dead organic matter.&lt;ref name=&quot;cfs.nrcan.gc.ca&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Does harvesting in Canada's forests contribute to climate change? |date=May 2007 |work=Canadian Forest Service Science-Policy Notes |publisher=Natural Resources Canada |url=http://www.sfmcanada.org/CMFiles/PublicationLibrary/CFS_DoesHarvestingInCanadasForestsContributeToClimateChange_English1OVA-25012010-8256.pdf }}{{dead link|date=December 2017 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt; A 40-year study of African, Asian, and South American [[tropical forest]]s by the University of Leeds shows that tropical forests absorb about 18% of all carbon dioxide added by fossil fuels. Truly mature tropical forests, by definition, grow rapidly, with each tree producing at least 10 new trees each year. Based on studies by [[FAO]] and [[UNEP]], it has been estimated that Asian forests absorb about 5 tonnes of carbon dioxide per hectare each year. The global cooling effect of carbon sequestration by forests is partially counterbalanced in that reforestation can decrease the reflection of sunlight ([[albedo]]). Mid-to-high-latitude forests have a much lower [[albedo]] during snow seasons than flat ground, thus contributing to warming. Modeling that compares the effects of albedo differences between forests and grasslands suggests that expanding the land area of forests in temperate zones offers only a temporary cooling benefit.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/sci/tech/6184577.stm | title=Care needed with carbon offsets | author=Jonathan Amos |publisher=BBC | accessdate=8 July 2008 | date=15 December 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |url=https://publicaffairs.llnl.gov/news/news_releases/2005/NR-05-12-04.html
 |title=Models show growing more forests in temperate regions could contribute to global warming
 |date=5 December 2005
 |publisher=Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory
 |accessdate=8 July 2008
 |url-status=dead
 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100527212654/https://publicaffairs.llnl.gov/news/news_releases/2005/NR-05-12-04.html
 |archivedate=27 May 2010
 |df=dmy
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author1=S. Gibbard |author2=K. Caldeira |author3=G. Bala |author4=T. J. Phillips |author5=M. Wickett |title=Climate effects of global land cover change | journal=Geophysical Research Letters | volume=32 |date=December 2005 | doi=10.1029/2005GL024550 | pages=L23705 | bibcode=2005GeoRL..3223705G | issue=23|url=https://digital.library.unt.edu/ark:/67531/metadc874513/ }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1098/rsta.2002.1020 |title=Forests, carbon and global climate |year=2002 |last1=Malhi |first1=Yadvinder |last2=Meir |first2=Patrick |last3=Brown |first3=Sandra |journal=Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society A: Mathematical, Physical and Engineering Sciences |volume=360 |issue=1797 |pages=1567–91 |pmid=12460485|bibcode = 2002RSPTA.360.1567M }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the United States in 2004 (the most recent year for which EPA statistics&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://epa.gov/climatechange/emissions/usinventoryreport.html | title=U.S. Greenhouse Gas Inventory Reports | publisher=[[United States Environmental Protection Agency|EPA]] | accessdate=8 July 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; are available), forests sequestered 10.6% (637&amp;nbsp;[[megatonne]]s)&lt;ref name=epa1&gt;{{cite web|url=http://epa.gov/climatechange/emissions/downloads06/06LULUCF.pdf |title=Land Use, Land-Use Change, and Forestry |publisher=[[United States Environmental Protection Agency|EPA]] |accessdate=8 July 2008 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080523085328/http://epa.gov/climatechange/emissions/downloads06/06LULUCF.pdf |archivedate=23 May 2008 |url-status=dead |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt; of the carbon dioxide released in the United States by the combustion of fossil fuels (coal, oil, and natural gas; 5,657 megatonnes&lt;ref name=epa2&gt;{{cite web|url=http://epa.gov/climatechange/emissions/downloads06/06ES.pdf |title=Executive Summary |publisher=[[United States Environmental Protection Agency|EPA]] |accessdate=8 July 2008 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080718165541/http://www.epa.gov/climatechange/emissions/downloads06/06ES.pdf |archivedate=18 July 2008 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;). Urban trees sequestered another 1.5% (88&amp;nbsp;megatonnes).&lt;ref name=epa1 /&gt;  To further reduce U.S. carbon dioxide emissions by 7%, as stipulated by the [[Kyoto Protocol]], would require the planting of &quot;an area the size of Texas [8% of the area of Brazil] every 30 years&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;William H. Schlesinger, dean of the Nicholas School of the Environment and Earth Sciences at Duke University, in Durham, North Carolina.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Carbon offset]] programs are planting millions of fast-growing trees per year to reforest tropical lands, for as little as $0.10 per tree; over their typical 40-year lifetime, one million of these trees will fix 1 to 2 megatonnes of carbon dioxide.{{citation needed|date=May 2016}} In Canada, reducing timber harvesting would have very little impact on carbon dioxide emissions because of the combination of harvest and stored carbon in manufactured wood products along with the regrowth of the harvested forests. Additionally, the amount of carbon released from harvesting is small compared to the amount of carbon lost each year to forest fires and other natural disturbances.&lt;ref name=&quot;cfs.nrcan.gc.ca&quot;/&gt;

The [[Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change]] concluded that &quot;a sustainable forest management strategy aimed at maintaining or increasing forest carbon stocks, while producing an annual sustained yield of timber fibre or energy from the forest, will generate the largest sustained mitigation benefit&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.ipcc.ch/pdf/assessment-report/ar4/wg3/ar4-wg3-chapter9.pdf | publisher=International Panel on Climate Change | title=Fourth Assessment Report (AR4): Mitigation of Climate Change (Working Group III) | pages=549 | access-date=11 August 2009 | archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090804123802/http://www.ipcc.ch/pdf/assessment-report/ar4/wg3/ar4-wg3-chapter9.pdf | archive-date=4 August 2009 | url-status=dead | df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Sustainable management practices keep forests growing at a higher rate over a potentially longer period of time, thus providing net sequestration benefits in addition to those of unmanaged forests.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Ruddell |first=Steven |date=September 2007 |title=The Role for Sustainably Managed Forests in Climate Change Mitigation |journal=Journal of Forestry |volume=105 |issue=6|pages=314–319 |display-authors=etal}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Life expectancy of forests varies throughout the world, influenced by tree species, site conditions and natural disturbance patterns. In some forests, carbon may be stored for centuries, while in other forests, carbon is released with frequent stand replacing fires. Forests that are harvested prior to stand replacing events allow for the retention of carbon in manufactured forest products such as lumber.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=J. Chatellier |title=The Role of Forest Products in the Global Carbon Cycle: From In-Use to End-of-Life |publisher=Yale School of Forestry and Environmental Studies |date=January 2010 |url=http://gisf.research.yale.edu/forest_carbon_report/Chapter_13.pdf |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100705163108/http://gisf.research.yale.edu/forest_carbon_report/Chapter_13.pdf |archivedate=5 July 2010 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, only a portion of the carbon removed from logged forests ends up as durable goods and buildings. The remainder ends up as sawmill by-products such as pulp, paper and pallets, which often end with incineration (resulting in carbon release into the atmosphere) at the end of their lifecycle. For instance, of the 1,692&amp;nbsp;megatonnes of carbon harvested from forests in [[Oregon]] and [[Washington (state)|Washington]] from 1900 to 1992, only 23% is in long-term storage in forest products.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | last1 = Harmon | first1 = M. E. | last2 = Harmon | first2 = J. M. | last3 = Ferrell | first3 = W. K. | last4 = Brooks | first4 = D. | title = Modeling carbon stores in Oregon and Washington forest products: 1900?1992 | doi = 10.1007/BF00141703 | journal = Climatic Change | volume = 33 | issue = 4 | pages = 521 | year = 1996 | pmid =  | pmc = | bibcode = 1996ClCh...33..521H | url = https://zenodo.org/record/1232389 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Oceans ===
{{See also|Iron fertilization|Enhanced weathering|Ocean nourishment}}
One way to increase the carbon sequestration efficiency of the oceans is to add micrometre-sized iron particles in the form of either [[hematite]] (iron oxide) or [[melanterite]] (iron sulfate) to certain regions of the ocean. This has the effect of stimulating growth of [[plankton]].  Iron is an important nutrient for [[phytoplankton]], usually made available via upwelling along the [[continental shelves]], inflows from rivers and streams, as well as deposition of dust suspended in the [[Earth's atmosphere|atmosphere]]. Natural sources of ocean iron have been declining in recent decades, contributing to an overall decline in ocean productivity (NASA, 2003).{{citation needed|date=May 2013}}  Yet in the presence of iron nutrients plankton populations quickly grow, or 'bloom', expanding the base of [[biomass]] productivity throughout the region and removing significant quantities of CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; from the atmosphere via [[photosynthesis]].  A test in 2002 in the [[Southern Ocean]] around [[Antarctica]] suggests that between 10,000 and 100,000 carbon atoms are sunk for each iron atom added to the water.{{citation needed|date=May 2013}}  More recent work in Germany (2005){{cn|date=June 2019}} suggests that any biomass carbon in the oceans, whether exported to depth or recycled in the [[euphotic zone]], represents long-term storage of carbon.  This means that application of iron nutrients in select parts of the oceans, at appropriate scales, could have the combined effect of restoring ocean productivity while at the same time mitigating the effects of human caused emissions of carbon dioxide to the atmosphere.{{citation needed|date=October 2013}}

Because the effect of periodic small scale phytoplankton blooms on ocean ecosystems is unclear, more studies would be helpful.  Phytoplankton have a complex effect on cloud formation via the release of substances such as [[dimethyl sulfide]] (DMS) that are converted to sulfate aerosols in the atmosphere, providing [[cloud condensation nuclei]], or CCN.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Roelofs, G.|year=2008|title= A GCM study of organic matter in marine aerosol and its potential contribution to cloud drop activation|journal=Atmospheric Chemistry and Physics|volume= 8|issue=3|pages=709–719|doi=10.5194/acp-8-709-2008|hdl=2066/34516}}&lt;/ref&gt; But the effect of small scale plankton blooms on overall DMS production is unknown.

Other nutrients such as nitrates, phosphates, and silica as well as iron may cause ocean fertilization.  There has been some speculation that using pulses of fertilization (around 20 days in length) may be more effective at getting carbon to ocean floor than sustained fertilization.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.netl.doe.gov/publications/proceedings/01/carbon_seq/p25.pdf | title=Sequestration of CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; by ocean fertilization | author1=Michael Markels, Jr | author2=Richard T. Barber | publisher=NETL Conference on Carbon Sequestration | date=14–17 May 2001 | accessdate=8 July 2008 | archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080910213905/http://www.netl.doe.gov/publications/proceedings/01/carbon_seq/p25.pdf | archive-date=10 September 2008 | url-status=dead | df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

There is some controversy over seeding the oceans with iron however, due to the potential for increased toxic phytoplankton growth (e.g. &quot;[[red tide]]&quot;), declining water quality due to overgrowth, and increasing anoxia in areas harming other sea-life such as zooplankton, fish, coral, etc.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.greenseaventure.com/Questions_Concerns.html |title=Questions and Concerns |publisher=GreenSea Venture |accessdate=8 July 2008 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080415163507/http://www.greenseaventure.com/Questions_Concerns.html |archivedate=15 April 2008 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1016/j.jembe.2004.08.014 |title=Effects of selenium, iron and cobalt addition to growth and yessotoxin production of the toxic marine dinoflagellate Protoceratium reticulatum in culture |year=2004 |last1=Mitrovic |first1=Simon M. |last2=Fernández Amandi |first2=Monica |last3=McKenzie |first3=Lincoln |last4=Furey |first4=Ambrose |last5=James |first5=Kevin J. |journal=Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and Ecology |volume=313 |issue=2 |pages=337–51}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Soils ===
Since the 1850s, a large proportion of the world's grasslands have been tilled and converted to croplands, allowing the rapid oxidation of large quantities of soil organic carbon.  However, in the United States in 2004 (the most recent year for which EPA statistics are available), agricultural soils including pasture land sequestered 0.8% (46 megatonne)&lt;ref name=epa1 /&gt; as much carbon as was released in the United States by the combustion of fossil fuels (5,988 megatonne).&lt;ref name=epa2 /&gt; The annual amount of this sequestration has been gradually increasing since 1998.&lt;ref name=epa1 /&gt;

Methods that significantly enhance carbon sequestration in soil include [[no-till farming]], residue mulching, [[cover crop]]ping, and [[crop rotation]], all of which are more widely used in [[organic farming]] than in conventional farming.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.news.cornell.edu/stories/July05/organic.farm.vs.other.ssl.html | title=Organic farming produces same corn and soybean yields as conventional farms, but consumes less energy and no pesticides, study finds | author=Susan S. Lang | date=13 July 2005 | accessdate=8 July 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Pimentel |first1=David |title=Environmental, Energetic, and Economic Comparisons of Organic and Conventional Farming Systems |journal=BioScience |volume=55 |issue=7 |pages=573–82 |year=2005 |doi=10.1641/0006-3568(2005)055[0573:EEAECO]2.0.CO;2 |last2=Hepperly |first2=Paul |last3=Hanson |first3=James |last4=Douds |first4=David |last5=Seidel |first5=Rita }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Because only 5% of US farmland currently uses no-till and residue mulching, there is a large potential for carbon sequestration.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1126/science.1093079 |title=Ecology: Managing Soil Carbon |year=2004 |last1=Lal |first1=Rattan |journal=Science |volume=304 |issue=5669 |pages=393 |pmid=15087532 |last2=Griffin |first2=Michael |last3=Apt |first3=Jay |last4=Lave |first4=Lester |last5=Morgan |first5=M. Granger|url=https://semanticscholar.org/paper/74cc21770b9c10b2e4370818bb660af027e675fc }}&lt;/ref&gt; Conversion to pastureland, particularly with good management of grazing, can sequester even more carbon in the soil.

[[Terra preta]], an [[human impact on the environment|anthropogenic]], high-carbon soil, is also being investigated as a sequestration mechanism.
By [[pyrolysis|pyrolysing]] biomass, about half of its carbon can be reduced to [[charcoal]], which can persist in the soil for centuries, and makes a useful soil amendment, especially in tropical soils (''[[biochar]]'' or ''agrichar'').&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.css.cornell.edu/faculty/lehmann/biochar/Biochar_home.htm |title=Biochar: the new frontier |author=Johannes Lehmann |accessdate=8 July 2008 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080618231424/http://www.css.cornell.edu/faculty/lehmann/biochar/Biochar_home.htm |archivedate=18 June 2008 |url-status=dead |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name='abc.net.au/catalyst/s2012892'&gt;{{cite news | first=Mark | last=Horstman | title=Agrichar – A solution to global warming? | date=23 September 2007 | publisher=Australian Broadcasting Corporation |url=http://www.abc.net.au/catalyst/stories/s2012892.htm |work=ABC TV Science: Catalyst |accessdate=8 July 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Savanna ===

[[Controlled burn]]s on far north Australian [[savanna]]s can result in an overall carbon sink. One working example is the West Arnhem Fire Management Agreement, started to bring &quot;strategic fire management across 28,000 km² of Western Arnhem Land&quot;. Deliberately starting controlled burns early in the dry season results in a mosaic of burnt and unburnt country which reduces the area of burning compared with stronger, late dry season fires. In the early dry season there are higher moisture levels, cooler temperatures, and lighter wind than later in the dry season; fires tend to go out overnight. Early controlled burns also results in a smaller proportion of the grass and tree biomass being burnt.&lt;ref name='savanna.ntu.edu.au/arnhem_fire_proj'&gt; {{cite web|url=http://savanna.ntu.edu.au/information/arnhem_fire_project.html |title=West Arnhem Land Fire Abatement Project |accessdate=8 July 2008 |work=Savanna Information |publisher=Tropical Savannas Cooperative Research Centre |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080703184208/http://savanna.ntu.edu.au/information/arnhem_fire_project.html |archivedate=3 July 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Emission reductions of 256,000 tonnes of CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; have been made as of 2007.&lt;ref name='savanna.ntu.edu.au/Eureka_arnhem_fire_proj'&gt; {{cite web|url=http://savanna.ntu.edu.au/news/topical_savannas109.html |title=Eureka Win for West Arnhem Land Fire Project |accessdate=8 July 2008 |work=Savanna Information |publisher=Tropical Savannas Cooperative Research Centre |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080703184154/http://savanna.ntu.edu.au/news/topical_savannas109.html |archivedate=3 July 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Artificial sequestration ==

For  carbon to be sequestered artificially (i.e. not using the natural processes of the carbon cycle) it must first be captured, ''or'' it must be significantly delayed or prevented from being re-released into the atmosphere (by combustion, decay, etc.) from an existing carbon-rich material, by being incorporated into an enduring usage (such as in construction). Thereafter it can be passively stored ''or'' remain productively utilized over time in a variety of ways.

For instance, upon harvesting, wood (as a carbon-rich material) can be immediately burned or otherwise serve as a fuel, returning its carbon to the atmosphere, ''or'' it can be incorporated into construction or a range of other durable products, thus sequestering its carbon over years or even centuries.

Indeed, a very carefully designed and durable, energy-efficient and energy-capturing building has the potential to sequester (in its carbon-rich construction materials), as much as or more carbon than was released by the acquisition and incorporation of all its materials and than will be released by building-function &quot;energy-imports&quot; during the structure's (potentially multi-century) existence.  Such a structure might be termed &quot;carbon neutral&quot; or even &quot;carbon negative&quot;. Building construction and operation (electricity usage, heating, etc.) are estimated to contribute nearly ''half'' of the annual human-caused carbon additions to the atmosphere.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web  | title=Climate Change, Global Warming, and the Built Environment – Architecture 2030 |url=http://www.architecture2030.org |accessdate=23 February 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Natural-gas]] purification plants often already have to remove carbon dioxide, either to avoid [[dry ice]] clogging gas tankers or to prevent carbon-dioxide concentrations exceeding the 3% maximum permitted on the natural-gas distribution grid.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://naturalgas.org/naturalgas/processing-ng/|title=Processing Natural Gas|website=NaturalGas.org|access-date=2018-02-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Beyond this, one of the most likely early applications of carbon capture is the capture of carbon dioxide from [[flue gas]]es at [[power station]]s (in the case of coal, this [[coal pollution mitigation]] is sometimes known as &quot;clean coal&quot;). A typical new 1000 MW [[coal-fired power station]] produces around 6 million tons of carbon dioxide annually. Adding carbon capture to existing plants can add significantly to the costs of energy production; scrubbing costs aside, a 1000 MW coal plant will require the storage of about {{convert|50|Moilbbl|m3}} of carbon dioxide a year. However, scrubbing is relatively affordable when added to new plants based on [[coal gasification]] technology, where it is estimated to raise energy costs for households in the United States using only coal-fired electricity sources from 10 cents per kW·h to 12 cents.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | title=Can We Bury Global Warming? |first=Robert H. |last=Socolow | journal=[[Scientific American]] |date=July 2005 | pages=42}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Carbon capture ===
{{Main|Carbon capture and storage}}

Currently, capture of carbon dioxide is performed on a large scale by absorption of carbon dioxide onto various [[Amine gas treating|amine-based solvents]]. Other techniques are currently being investigated, such as [[pressure swing adsorption]], [[Gas separation#Temperature swing adsorption|temperature swing adsorption]], [[membrane gas separation|gas separation membranes]], [[Distillation#Industrial distillation|cryogenics]] and [[Flue gas|flue capture]].

In coal-fired power stations, the main alternatives to retrofitting amine-based absorbers to existing power stations are two new technologies: [[Integrated Gasification Combined Cycle|coal gasification combined-cycle]] and [[oxy-fuel combustion]]. Gasification first produces a &quot;[[syngas]]&quot; primarily of [[hydrogen]] and [[carbon monoxide]], which is burned, with carbon dioxide filtered from the flue gas. Oxy-fuel combustion burns the coal in [[oxygen]] instead of [[Air#Composition|air]], producing only carbon dioxide and [[water vapour]], which are relatively easily separated. Some of the combustion products must be returned to the combustion chamber, either before or after separation, otherwise the temperatures would be too high for the turbine.

Another long-term option is carbon capture directly from the air using [[hydroxide]]s. The air would literally be scrubbed of its CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; content.  This idea offers an alternative to non-[[Fossil fuel|carbon-based fuels]] for the transportation sector.

Examples of carbon sequestration at coal plants include converting carbon from smokestacks into baking soda,{{refn|1=Utility company [http://www.luminant.com/ Luminant]'s pilot version at its [http://www.luminant.com/plants/big_brown.aspx Big Brown Steam Electric Station] in [[Fairfield, Texas]].{{cn|date=January 2020}}}}{{refn|1=[https://web.archive.org/web/20071218003544/http://www.skyonic.com/theCompany.php Skyonic] plans to circumvent storage problems of [[Supercritical carbon dioxide|liquid {{CO2}}]] by storing baking soda in mines, landfills, or simply to be sold as industrial or food-grade [[baking soda]].{{cn|date=January 2020}} }} and algae-based carbon capture, circumventing storage by converting algae into fuel or feed.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.greenfuelonline.com/index.html|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080116170736/http://www.greenfuelonline.com/index.html|url-status=dead|title=GreenFuel Technologies Corp.|archivedate=16 January 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Oceans ===

Another proposed form of carbon sequestration in the ocean is direct injection.  In this method, carbon dioxide is pumped directly into the water at depth, and expected to form &quot;lakes&quot; of liquid CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; at the bottom. Experiments carried out in moderate to deep waters (350–3600 m) indicate that the liquid CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; reacts to form solid CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; [[clathrate hydrate]]s, which gradually dissolve in the surrounding waters.{{citation needed|date=May 2013}}

This method, too, has potentially dangerous environmental consequences.  The carbon dioxide does react with the water to form [[carbonic acid]], H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;CO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;; however, most (as much as 99%) remains as dissolved molecular CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;. The equilibrium would no doubt be quite different under the high pressure conditions in the deep ocean. In addition, if deep-sea bacterial [[methanogen]]s that reduce carbon dioxide were to encounter the carbon dioxide sinks, levels of [[methane]] gas may increase, leading to the generation of an even worse greenhouse gas.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.csmonitor.com/2008/0428/p01s04-wogi.html|title=Potent greenhouse-gas methane has been rising|author=The Christian Science Monitor|journal=The Christian Science Monitor|date=2008-04-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The resulting environmental effects on [[benthic]] life forms of the [[bathypelagic]], [[abyssopelagic]] and [[hadopelagic]] zones are unknown. Even though life appears to be rather sparse in the deep ocean basins, energy and chemical effects in these deep basins could have far-reaching implications. Much more work is needed here to define the extent of the potential problems.

Carbon storage in or under oceans may not be compatible with the [[Convention on the Prevention of Marine Pollution by Dumping of Wastes and Other Matter]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=https://www.theyworkforyou.com/wrans/?id=2005-07-04a.7044.h | title=Carbon Sequestration |author1=Norman Baker |author2=Ben Bradshaw | accessdate=8 July 2008 | date=4 July 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

An additional method of long-term ocean-based sequestration is to gather [[crop residue]] such as corn stalks or excess hay into large weighted bales of biomass and deposit it in the [[alluvial fan]] areas of the deep [[ocean basin]].  Dropping these residues in alluvial fans would cause the residues to be quickly buried in silt on the sea floor, sequestering the biomass for very long time spans.  Alluvial fans exist in all of the world's oceans and seas where river deltas fall off the edge of the [[continental shelf]] such as the [[Mississippi Delta|Mississippi alluvial fan]] in the [[gulf of Mexico]] and the [[Nile Delta|Nile alluvial fan]] in the [[Mediterranean Sea]]. A downside, however, would be an increase in aerobic bacteria growth due to the introduction of biomass, leading to more competition for oxygen resources in the deep sea, similar to the [[oxygen minimum zone]].{{citation needed|date=May 2013}}

=== Geological sequestration ===

The  method of  ''geo-sequestration'' or ''geological storage'' involves injecting carbon dioxide directly into underground geological formations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite report|title=Negative Emissions Technologies and Reliable Sequestration: A Research Agenda|authors=National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine|chapter=Sequestration of Supercritical CO2 in Deep Sedimentary Geological Formations|year=2019|page=319-350|publisher=The National Academies Press|place=Washington, DC|doi=10.17226/25259}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Declining [[oil field]]s, saline [[aquifer]]s, and unminable [[coal seam]]s have been suggested as storage sites.  Caverns and old mines that are commonly used to store natural gas are not considered, because of a lack of storage safety.

CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; has been injected into declining oil fields for more than 40 years, to increase oil recovery.  This option is attractive because the storage costs are offset by the sale of additional oil that is recovered. Typically, 10–15% additional recovery of the original oil in place is possible. Further benefits are the existing infrastructure and the geophysical and geological information about the oil field that is available from the oil exploration. Another benefit of injecting CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; into Oil fields is that CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; is soluble in oil.  Dissolving CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; in oil lowers the viscosity of the oil and reduces its interfacial tension which increases the oils mobility. All oil fields have a geological barrier preventing upward migration of oil. As most oil and gas has been in place for millions to tens of millions of years, depleted oil and gas reservoirs can contain carbon dioxide for millennia. Identified possible problems are the many 'leak' opportunities provided by old oil wells, the need for high injection pressures and acidification which can damage the geological barrier. Other disadvantages of old oil fields are their limited geographic distribution and depths, which require high injection pressures for sequestration.  Below a depth of about 1000 m, carbon dioxide is injected as a supercritical fluid, a material with the density of a liquid, but the viscosity and diffusivity of a gas.
Unminable coal seams can be used to store CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, because CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; absorbs to the coal surface, ensuring safe long-term storage.  In the process it releases methane that was previously adsorbed to the coal surface and that may be recovered.  Again the sale of the methane can be used to offset the cost of the CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; storage. Release or burning of methane would of course at least partially offset the obtained sequestration result – except when the gas is allowed to escape into the atmosphere in significant quantities: methane has a higher [[global warming potential]] than CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;.

Saline aquifers contain highly mineralized brines and have so far been considered of no benefit to humans except in a few cases where they have been used for the storage of chemical waste.  Their advantages include a large potential storage volume and relatively common occurrence reducing the distance over which CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; has to be transported. The major disadvantage of saline aquifers is that relatively little is known about them compared to oil fields. Another disadvantage of saline aquifers is that as the salinity of the water increases, less CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; can be dissolved into aqueous solution. To keep the cost of storage acceptable the geophysical exploration may be limited, resulting in larger uncertainty about the structure of a given aquifer. Unlike storage in oil fields or coal beds, no side product will offset the storage cost. Leakage of CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; back into the atmosphere may be a problem in saline-aquifer storage.  However, current research shows that several ''trapping mechanisms'' immobilize the CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; underground, reducing the risk of leakage.{{Citation needed|date=September 2011}}

A major research project examining the geological sequestration of carbon dioxide is currently being performed at an oil field at [[Weyburn, Saskatchewan|Weyburn]] in south-eastern [[Saskatchewan]]. In the [[North Sea]], Norway's [[Equinor]] natural-gas platform [[Sleipner A|Sleipner]] strips carbon dioxide out of the natural gas with amine solvents and disposes of this carbon dioxide by geological sequestration. Sleipner reduces emissions of carbon dioxide by approximately one million tonnes a year. The cost of geological sequestration is minor relative to the overall running costs. As of April 2005, [[BP]] is considering a trial of large-scale sequestration of carbon dioxide stripped from power plant emissions in the [[Miller oilfield]] as its reserves are depleted.

In October 2007, the [[Bureau of Economic Geology]] at [[The University of Texas at Austin]] received a 10-year, $38 million subcontract to conduct the first intensively monitored, long-term project in the United States studying the feasibility of injecting a large volume of CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; for underground storage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Bureau of Economic Geology Receives $38 Million for First Large-Scale U.S. Test Storing Carbon Dioxide Underground|date= October 24, 2007|publisher=Jackson School of Geosciences, The University of Texas at Austin|url=http://www.jsg.utexas.edu/news/rels/102407.html|accessdate=2010-04-14|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100611182402/http://www.jsg.utexas.edu/news/rels/102407.html|archivedate=11 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The project is a research program of the [https://web.archive.org/web/20080719035649/http://www.sseb.org/currentprograms/cpa_cmi.htm Southeast Regional Carbon Sequestration Partnership (SECARB)], funded by the [[National Energy Technology Laboratory]] of the [[United States Department of Energy|U.S. Department of Energy (DOE)]]. The SECARB partnership will demonstrate CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; injection rate and storage capacity in the [[Tuscaloosa-Woodbine]] geologic system that stretches from Texas to Florida. Beginning in fall 2007, the project will inject CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; at the rate of one million tons{{Vague|which tons?|date=February 2009}} per year, for up to 1.5 years, into brine up to {{convert|10000|ft|m}} below the land surface near the [[Cranfield oil field]] about {{convert|15|mi|km}} east of [[Natchez, Mississippi]]. Experimental equipment will measure the ability of the subsurface to accept and retain CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;.

=== Mineral sequestration ===

Mineral sequestration aims to trap carbon in the form of solid [[carbonate]] salts. This process occurs slowly in nature and is responsible for the deposition and accumulation of [[limestone]] over geologic time. [[Carbonic acid]] in groundwater slowly reacts with complex [[silicate]]s to dissolve [[calcium]], [[magnesium]], [[alkali]]s and [[silica]] and leave a residue of [[clay minerals]]. The dissolved calcium and magnesium react with [[bicarbonate]] to precipitate calcium and magnesium carbonates, a process that organisms use to make shells. When the organisms die, their shells are deposited as sediment and eventually turn into limestone. Limestones have accumulated over billions of years of geologic time and contain much of Earth's carbon. Ongoing research aims to speed up similar reactions involving alkali carbonates.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Carbon-capture Technology To Help UK Tackle Global Warming |date=27 July 2007 |work=ScienceDaily |url=https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2007/07/070727091001.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Several serpentinite deposits are being investigated as potentially large scale CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; storage sinks such as those found in NSW, Australia, where the first mineral carbonation pilot plant project is underway.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Mineral carbonation project for NSW |date=9 June 2010 |url=http://www.sustainabilitymatters.net.au/articles/41409-Mineral-carbonation-project-for-NSW}}&lt;/ref&gt; Beneficial re-use of magnesium carbonate from this process could provide feedstock for new products developed for the built environment and agriculture without returning the carbon into the atmosphere and so acting as a carbon sink.

One proposed reaction is that of the olivine-rich rock [[dunite]], or its hydrated equivalent [[serpentinite]] with carbon dioxide to form the carbonate mineral [[magnesite]], plus silica and iron oxide ([[magnetite]]).

Serpentinite sequestration is favored because of the non-toxic and stable nature of magnesium carbonate. The ideal reactions involve the magnesium endmember components of the [[olivine]] (reaction 1) or [[Serpentine group|serpentine]] (reaction 2), the latter derived from earlier olivine by hydration and silicification (reaction 3). The presence of iron in the olivine or serpentine reduces the efficiency of sequestration, since the iron components of these minerals break down to iron oxide and silica (reaction 4).

==== Serpentinite reactions ====

{{NumBlk|:| {{overset|Mg-olivine|Mg&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;SiO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;}} + {{overset|carbon dioxide|2CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;}} → {{overset| magnesite |2MgCO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;}} + {{overset| silica |SiO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;}} + {{overset| water |H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O}}|{{EquationRef|Reaction 1}}}}

{{NumBlk|:| {{overset| Serpentine |Mg&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;[Si&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt;(OH)&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;]}} + {{overset|carbon dioxide|3CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;}} → {{overset| magnesite | 3MgCO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;}} + {{overset| silica |2SiO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;}} + {{overset| water |2H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O}}|{{EquationRef|Reaction 2}}}}

{{NumBlk|:| {{overset|Mg-olivine|3Mg&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;SiO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;}} + {{overset| silica |2SiO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;}} + {{overset| water |4H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O}} → {{overset| serpentine |2Mg&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;[Si&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt;(OH)&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;]}}|{{EquationRef|Reaction 3}}}}

{{NumBlk|:| {{overset|Fe-olivine|3Fe&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;SiO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;}} + {{overset| water |2H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O}} → {{overset| magnetite |2Fe&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;}} + {{overset| silica |3SiO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;}} + {{overset| hydrogen |2H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;}}|{{EquationRef|Reaction 4}}}}

==== Zeolitic imidazolate frameworks ====
{{Main|Zeolitic imidazolate frameworks}}

Zeolitic imidazolate frameworks is a [[metal-organic framework]] carbon dioxide sink which could be used to keep industrial emissions of [[carbon dioxide]] out of the [[atmosphere]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url= http://www.cbc.ca/technology/story/2008/02/15/tech-carbon-capture.html|work=CBC News|title=New materials can selectively capture CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, scientists say|date=15 February 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Trends in sink performance ==

One study in 2009 found that the fraction of fossil-fuel emissions absorbed by the oceans may have declined by up to 10% since 2000, indicating oceanic sequestration may be sublinear.&lt;ref name=EarthInst/&gt; Another 2009 study found that the fraction of {{CO2}} absorbed by terrestrial ecosystems and the oceans has not changed since 1850, indicating undiminished capacity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Knorr, W. |title=Is the airborne fraction of anthropogenic {{CO2}} emissions increasing? |journal=Geophysical Research Letters |volume=36 |issue=21 |pages=L21710 |year=2009 |doi=10.1029/2009GL040613 |lay-url=http://www.bris.ac.uk/news/2009/6649.html|lay-date=9 November 2009 |bibcode=2009GeoRL..3621710K}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{Portal|Energy}}
* [[Azolla event]]
* [[Biochar]]
* [[Bio-energy with carbon capture and storage]]
* [[Carbon capture and storage]]
* [[Carbon cycle]]
* [[Carbon sequestration in terrestrial ecosystems]]
* [[Fluxnet-Canada Research Network]], research initiative on post forest disturbance carbon sinking

== References ==
{{Reflist|33em}}

== External links ==
* [http://sequestration.mit.edu/  Carbon Capture and Sequestration Technologies Program at MIT]

{{Global warming}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Carbon Sink}}
[[Category:Carbon dioxide]]
[[Category:Carbon capture and sequestration]]
[[Category:Climate forcing]]
[[Category:Photosynthesis]]
[[Category:Gas technologies]]</text>
      <sha1>k0pxqi1x623k7j6e19cds28ja7ao3s3</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
