  <page>
    <title>Cycling</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5931</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942751731</id>
      <parentid>942157705</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-26T16:35:01Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rescuing 1 sources and tagging 0 as dead.) #IABot (v2.0</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{pp|small=y}}
{{about||the hockey strategy|Cycling (ice hockey)|the magazine|Cycling Weekly}}
{{redirect|Bicycling|the magazine|Bicycling (magazine)}}
{{redirect2|Biking|Cyclist|the Frank Ocean song|Biking (song)|the 1987 Iranian film|The Cyclist}}

{{cuic|wording=y|date=June 2017}}
[[File:Vélocourse.jpg|thumb|[[Tro-Bro Léon]] racing, 2009]]
[[File:Police cyclists London Olympic Torch Relay.jpg|thumb|Police cyclists in [[London]].]]
[[File:Bicycling Tamil girl, Batticaloa.JPG|thumb|Village cycling in [[Sri Lanka]].]]
[[File:Cycling Amsterdan 04.jpg|thumb|Along the ''Fietspad'' in [[Amsterdam]], safe from traffic.]]
'''Cycling''', also called '''biking''' or '''bicycling''', is the use of [[bicycle]]s for [[transport]], [[recreation]], [[Physical exercise|exercise]] or [[sport]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| title = Oxford English Dictionary| url = https://archive.org/details/oxfordenglishdic0015unse| url-access = registration| edition = Second| year = 1989| publisher = Oxford University Press| quote = cycling: The action or activity of riding a bicycle etc.}}&lt;/ref&gt; People engaged in cycling are referred to as &quot;cyclists&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
| title = Oxford English Dictionary| edition = Second| year = 1988| publisher = Oxford University Press| quote = cyclist: One who rides a cycle or practises cycling.}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;bikers&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oed.com/view/Entry/250990?redirectedFrom=biker+#eid | title = Oxford English Dictionary|quote = biker: A cyclist, a person who rides a bicycle.&quot; |publisher= www.oed.com |accessdate=2013-09-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; or less commonly, as &quot;bicyclists&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| title = Oxford English Dictionary| url = https://archive.org/details/oxfordenglishdic0006unse| url-access = registration| edition = Second| year = 1989| publisher = Oxford University Press| quote = bicyclist: One who rides a bicycle.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Apart from two-wheeled bicycles, &quot;cycling&quot; also includes the riding of [[unicycle]]s, [[tricycle]]s, [[quadracycle]]s, [[recumbent bicycle|recumbent]] and similar [[human-powered transport|human-powered vehicles]] (HPVs).

Bicycles were introduced in the 19th century and now number approximately one billion worldwide.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |publisher=Worldometers |url=http://www.worldometers.info/bicycles/ |title=Bicycles produced in the world |accessdate=2014-04-25 }}&lt;/ref&gt; They are the principal means of transportation in many parts of the world.

Cycling is widely regarded as a very effective and efficient mode of transportation&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://auto.howstuffworks.com/question527.htm |title=HowStuffWorks &quot;Is there a way to compare a human being to an engine in terms of efficiency?&quot; |publisher=Auto.howstuffworks.com |accessdate=2009-09-29|date=2000-12-05 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Komanoff |first1=Charles |editor1-last=Cleveland |editor1-first=Cutler J. |year=2004 |title=Encyclopedia of Energy |publisher=Elsevier |isbn=978-0-12-176480-7 |doi=10.1016/B0-12-176480-X/00185-6 |chapter=Bicycling |pages=141–50}}&lt;/ref&gt; optimal for short to moderate distances.

Bicycles provide numerous benefits in comparison with motor vehicles, including the sustained physical exercise involved in cycling, easier parking, increased maneuverability, and access to roads, [[bike path]]s and rural trails. Cycling also offers a reduced consumption of [[fossil fuel]]s, less [[air pollution|air]] or [[noise pollution]], and much reduced [[traffic congestion]]. These lead to less financial cost to the user as well as to society at large (negligible damage to roads, less road area required). By fitting bicycle racks on the front of buses, transit agencies can significantly increase the areas they can serve.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author1=Flamm, B. |author2=Rivasplata, C. |date=2014 |title=Perceptions of Bicycle-Friendly Policy Impacts on Accessibility to Transit Services: The First and Last Mile Bridge |journal= MTI Report |publisher=Mineta Transportation Institute |url=http://transweb.sjsu.edu/PDFs/research/1104-bicycle-policy-transit-accessibility-first-last-mile.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition, cycling provides a variety of health benefits. The World Health Organization (WHO) states that cycling can reduce the risk of cancers, heart disease, and diabetes that are prevalent in sedentary lifestyles.&lt;ref name=&quot;WHO&quot; /&gt; Cycling on [[Stationary bicycle|stationary bikes]] have also been used as part of rehabilitation for lower limb injuries, particularly after hip surgery.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt; Individuals who cycle regularly have also reported mental health improvements, including less perceived stress and better vitality.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt;

Among the disadvantages of cycling are the requirement of bicycles (excepting tricycles or quadracycles) to be balanced by the rider in order to remain upright, the reduced protection in crashes in comparison to motor vehicles,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Wardlaw MJ |title=Three lessons for a better cycling future |journal=BMJ |volume=321 |issue=7276 |pages=1582–5 |year=2000 |pmid=11124188 |pmc=1119262 |doi=10.1136/bmj.321.7276.1582 }}&lt;/ref&gt; often longer travel time (except in densely populated areas), vulnerability to weather conditions, difficulty in transporting passengers, and the fact that a basic level of fitness is required for cycling moderate to long distances.

==History==
{{Main|History of cycling}}

Cycling quickly became an activity after [[bicycles]] were introduced in the 19th century. Today, over 50 percent of the human population knows how to ride a bike.&lt;ref&gt;SIBILSKI, LESZEK J. [https://blogs.worldbank.org/publicsphere/cycling-everyone-s-business/ &quot;Cycling Is Everyone’s Business&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180612142147/https://blogs.worldbank.org/publicsphere/cycling-everyone-s-business/ |date=2018-06-12 }}, ''[[The World Bank]]'', 02/04/2015&lt;/ref&gt;

==Equipment==
{{Main|Bicycle}}
[[File:Cycling in Alabama.webm|thumb|Cycling in Alabama]]
In many countries, the most commonly used vehicle for road transport is a [[utility bicycle]]. These have frames with relaxed geometry, protecting the rider from shocks of the road and easing steering at low speeds. Utility bicycles tend to be equipped with accessories such as mudguards, pannier racks and lights, which extends their usefulness on a daily basis. As the bicycle is so effective as a means of transportation various companies have developed methods of carrying anything from the weekly shop to children on bicycles. Certain countries rely heavily on bicycles and their culture has developed around the bicycle as a primary form of transport. In Europe, Denmark and the Netherlands have the most bicycles per capita and most often use bicycles for everyday transport.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ecf.com/press-corner/cycling-facts-and-figures/|title=European Cyclists' Federation – Cycling facts and figures|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20151120213149/http://www.ecf.com/press-corner/cycling-facts-and-figures/|archivedate=2015-11-20|df=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ec.europa.eu/public_opinion/flash/fl_312_en.pdf |title=This version of the web site is now archived - Cette version du site web est archivée. |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150205185930/http://ec.europa.eu/public_opinion/flash/fl_312_en.pdf |archivedate=February 5, 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Road bikes tend to have a more upright shape and a shorter wheelbase, which make the bike more mobile but harder to ride slowly. The design, coupled with low or dropped handlebars, requires the rider to bend forward more, making use of stronger muscles (particularly the [[Gluteus maximus muscle|gluteus maximus]]) and reducing air resistance at high speed.

The price of a new bicycle can range from US$50 to more than US$20,000 (the highest priced bike in the world is the custom Madone by [[Damien Hirst]], sold at US$500,000&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.trekbikes.com/us/en/stages/hirst/ |archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20120226083113/http://www.trekbikes.com/us/en/stages/hirst |archivedate= February 26, 2012 |title=Trek Bicycle: The world's best bikes for road, mountain, or town |publisher=Trekbikes.com |accessdate=2012-06-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |archivedate= February 25, 2007 |url= http://www.bicycling.com/article/1,6610,s1-1-2-15285-1,00.html |title= Custom Bike Builders: Groupe de Tete |publisher=bicycling.com |archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20070225094609/http://www.bicycling.com/article/1%2C6610%2Cs1-1-2-15285-1%2C00.html }}&lt;/ref&gt; depending on quality, type and weight (the most exotic road bicycles can weigh as little as 3.2&amp;nbsp;kg (7&amp;nbsp;lb)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |archivedate=November 14, 2011 |url=http://www.light-bikes.com/bikegallery/BikeListing.asp?id=1507 |title= SPIN Custom...7.04 lbs |archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20111114120218/http://www.light-bikes.com/bikegallery/BikeListing.asp?id=1507 }}&lt;/ref&gt;). However, [http://www.uci.ch/Templates/UCI/UCI5/layout.asp?MenuID=MTYxNw&amp;LangId=1 UCI] regulations stipulate a legal [[Racing bicycle|race bike]] cannot weigh less than 6.8&amp;nbsp;kg (14.99&amp;nbsp;lbs). Being measured for a bike and taking it for a test ride are recommended before buying.

The [[bicycle#Drivetrain and gearing|drivetrain]] components of the bike should also be considered. A middle grade [[dérailleur]] is sufficient for a beginner, although many utility bikes are equipped with [[hub gear]]s. If the rider plans a significant amount of [[hillclimbing (cycling)|hillclimbing]], a triple-chainrings [[crankset]] [[bicycle gearing|gear system]] may be preferred. Otherwise, the relatively lighter and less expensive double chainring may be better. Much simpler fixed wheel bikes are also available.

Many road bikes, along with mountain bikes, include [[clipless pedal]]s to which special shoes attach, via a [[cleat (shoe)|cleat]], enabling the rider to pull on the pedals as well as push. Other possible accessories for the bicycle include front and rear lights, [[Bicycle bell|bells]] or horns, child carrying seats, cycling computers with GPS, locks, bar tape, fenders (mud-guards), baggage racks, baggage carriers and pannier bags, water bottles and bottle cages.

For basic maintenance and repairs cyclists can carry a [[bicycle pump|pump]] (or a [[carbon dioxide|CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; cartridge]]), a puncture repair kit, a spare inner tube, and [[tire levers]] and a set of [[allen keys]]. Cycling can be more efficient and comfortable with special [[cycling shoe|shoes]], [[cycling gloves|gloves]], and [[cycling shorts|shorts]]. In wet weather, riding can be more tolerable with waterproof clothes, such as cape, jacket, trousers (pants) and overshoes and high-visibility clothing is advisable to reduce the risk from motor vehicle users.

Items legally required in some jurisdictions, or voluntarily adopted for safety reasons, include [[bicycle helmet]]s,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.yescycling.com/bicycle-helmet-laws-in-the-us/|title=Bicycle Helmet Laws In The US - The Complete List - Yes Cycling|date=2017-03-25|work=Yes Cycling|access-date=2018-02-25|language=en-GB}}&lt;/ref&gt; generator or battery operated lights, [[retroreflector|reflectors]], and audible signalling devices such as a bell or horn. Extras include [[studded tires]] and a [[cyclocomputer|bicycle computer]].

Bikes can also be heavily customized, with different seat designs and handle bars, for example.

==Skills==
Many schools and police departments run educational programs to instruct children in bicycle handling skills, especially to introduce them to the [[Traffic#Rules of the road|rules of the road]] as they apply to cyclists. In some countries these may be known as [[bicycle rodeo]]s, or operated as schemes such as [[Bikeability]]. Education for adult cyclists is available from organizations such as the [[League of American Bicyclists]].

Beyond simply riding, another skill is riding efficiently and safely in traffic. One popular approach to riding in [[motor vehicle]] traffic is [[vehicular cycling]], occupying road space as car does. Alternately, in countries such as Denmark and the Netherlands, where cycling is popular, cyclists are often segregated into bike lanes at the side of, or more often separate from, main highways and roads. Many primary schools participate in the national road test in which children individually complete a circuit on roads near the school while being observed by testers.

==Infrastructure==
{{See also|Cycling infrastructure}}
[[File:Bicycle Parking Lot Niigata.jpg|thumb|A parking lot for bicycles in [[Niigata, Niigata]], Japan.|alt=Hundreds of bicycles, grouped in rectangular parking places with driving paths in between.]]
[[File:Cambridge CMS Bicycle Racks.jpg|thumb|[[Bicycle stand]]s outside the Centre for Mathematical Sciences at the [[University of Cambridge]]. Many students at the university opt to travel by bicycle.]]
Cyclists, pedestrians and motorists make different demands on road design which may lead to conflicts. Some jurisdictions give priority to motorized traffic, for example setting up one-way street systems, free-right turns, high capacity roundabouts, and [[interchange (road)|slip roads]]. Others share priority with cyclists so as to encourage more cycling by applying varying combinations of [[traffic calming]] measures to limit the impact of motorized transport, and by building [[bike lane]]s, [[bike path]]s and [[cycle track]]s.

In jurisdictions where motor vehicles were given priority, cycling has tended to decline while in jurisdictions where cycling infrastructure was built, cycling rates have remained steady or increased.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=https://bicyclenewengland.com/2018/12/18/economic-benefits-of-cycling/ |title = Why are Fewer People Bicycling if the Economic Benefits are so Clear?|date = 2018-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; Occasionally, extreme measures against cycling may occur. In Shanghai, where bicycles were once the dominant [[mode of transport]], bicycle travel on a few city roads was banned temporarily in December 2003.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/asia-pacific/3303655.stm | title=Shanghai ends reign of the bicycle| date=2003-12-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In areas in which cycling is popular and encouraged, cycle-parking facilities using [[bicycle stand]]s, lockable mini-garages, and patrolled cycle parks are used in order to reduce theft. Local governments promote cycling by permitting bicycles to be carried on public transport or by providing external [[Bicycle carrier|attachment devices]] on public transport vehicles. Conversely, an absence of secure cycle-parking is a recurring complaint by cyclists from cities with low [[modal share]] of cycling.

Extensive cycling infrastructure may be found in some cities. Such dedicated paths in some cities often have to be shared with in-line skaters, scooters, skateboarders, and pedestrians. Dedicated cycling infrastructure is treated differently in the [[bikeway and legislation|law]] of every jurisdiction, including the question of liability of users in a collision. There is also some debate about the [[bikeway safety|safety]] of the various types of separated facilities.

Bicycles are considered a sustainable mode of transport, especially suited for urban use and relatively shorter distances when used for transport (compared to recreation). Case studies and good practices (from European cities and some worldwide examples) that promote and stimulate this kind of functional cycling in cities can be found at [[Eltis]], Europe's portal for local transport.

A number of cities, including Paris, London and [[Bicing|Barcelona]], now have successful [[bicycle sharing|bike hire schemes]] designed to help people cycle in the city. Typically these feature utilitarian city bikes which lock into docking stations, released on payment for set time periods. Costs vary from city to city. In London, initial hire access costs £2 per day. The first 30 minutes of each trip is free, with £2 for each additional 30 minutes until the bicycle is returned.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url = https://tfl.gov.uk/modes/cycling/santander-cycles
 | title = Santander Cycles: London's self-service, bike-sharing scheme
 | website =tfl.gov.uk
 | access-date = 26 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Utrecht-IMG 7481.JPG|thumb|The safe physically separated ''Fietspad'' in the Netherlands, keeping cyclists away from traffic as seen in [[Utrecht (city)|Utrecht]].]]

In the Netherlands, many roads have one or two separate [[cycleway]]s alongside them, or cycle lanes marked on the road. On roads where adjacent bike paths or cycle tracks exist, the use of these facilities is compulsory, and cycling on the main carriageway is not permitted.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://wetten.overheid.nl/BWBR0004825/HoofdstukII/i1/Artikel5/geldigheidsdatum_01-10-2012|title=wetten.nl - Wet- en regelgeving - Reglement verkeersregels en verkeerstekens 1990 (RVV 1990) - BWBR0004825|work=overheid.nl}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some 35,000&amp;nbsp;km of cycle-track has been physically segregated from motor traffic,&lt;ref name=&quot;fietsberaad&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fietsberaad.nl/index.cfm?lang=nl&amp;section=nieuws&amp;mode=newsArticle&amp;repository=The+Netherlands+boast+almost+35.000+km+of+cycling+paths|title=The Netherlands boast almost 35.000 km of cycling paths|work=fietsberaad.nl|access-date=2017-11-17|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140717230921/http://www.fietsberaad.nl/index.cfm?lang=nl&amp;section=nieuws&amp;mode=newsArticle&amp;repository=The+Netherlands+boast+almost+35.000+km+of+cycling+paths|archive-date=2014-07-17|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.cbs.nl/NR/rdonlyres/9F9F3F71-9324-46D3-AD7E-076C59F8392D/0/2015factsheetnederlandfietsland_ENG.pdf {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20151113154603/http://www.cbs.nl/NR/rdonlyres/9F9F3F71-9324-46D3-AD7E-076C59F8392D/0/2015factsheetnederlandfietsland_ENG.pdf |date=2015-11-13 }} Factsheet The Netherlands: cycling country — [[Statistics Netherlands|CBS]]]&lt;/ref&gt; equal to a quarter of the country's entire 140,000&amp;nbsp;km road network.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/fields/2085.html#nl |title=CIA World Factbook &amp;#124; Field listing: Roadways  |date=2014 |website=www.cia.gov |publisher=U.S. Central Intelligence Agency |accessdate=2015-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; A quarter of all the trips in the country made on bicycles, one quarter of them to work. Even the prime minister is going to work by bicycle, when weather permits. This saves the life of 6,000 citizens per year, prolong the life expectancy by 6 months, save the country 20 million dollars per year, and prevent 150 grams of CO2 to be emitted per kilometer of cycling, on each bicycle&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Why I Ride My Bike to Work, by the Prime Minister of the Netherlands |url=https://www.ecowatch.com/mark-rutte-bikes-to-work-2640672478.html |accessdate=29 September 2019 |agency=Ecowatch |publisher=World Economic Forum}}&lt;/ref&gt;.

==Types==

===Utility===
[[File:Coconut bunch.jpg|thumb|A bicycle loaded with [[tender coconut]]s for sale. [[Karnataka]], India.|alt=A bicycle loaded with so many green fruits that the rear wheel can not be seen.]]
{{Main|Utility cycling}}

Utility cycling refers both to cycling as a mode of daily [[commuting]] transport as well as the use of a bicycle in a commercial activity, mainly to transport goods, mostly accomplished in an [[Urban area|urban environment]].

The [[mail|postal services]] of many countries have long relied on bicycles. The British [[Royal Mail]] first started using bicycles in 1880; now bicycle delivery fleets include 37,000 in the UK, 25,700 in Germany, 10,500 in Hungary and 7000 in Sweden. In Australia, Australia Post has also reintroduced bicycle postal deliveries on some routes due to an inability to recruit sufficient licensed riders willing to use their uncomfortable motorbikes. The [[London Ambulance Service]] has recently introduced bicycling [[paramedic]]s, who can often get to the scene of an incident in [[Central London]] more quickly than a motorized ambulance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.londonambulance.nhs.uk/calling_999/who_will_treat_you/single_responder/cycle_responder.aspx |title=Cycle Responder |work=London Ambulance Service |publisher=London Ambulance Service NHS Trust |accessdate=2016-05-05 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160402031208/http://www.londonambulance.nhs.uk/calling_999/who_will_treat_you/single_responder/cycle_responder.aspx |archivedate=2016-04-02 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The use of [[Police bicycle|bicycles by police]] has been increasing, since they provide greater accessibility to bicycle and pedestrian zones and allow access when roads are  congested.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal
 | last =Rantatalo
 | first =Oscar
 | title =Using police bicycle patrols to manage social order in bicycle and pedestrian traffic networks
 | journal =The Police Journal
 | volume =89
 | issue =1
 | pages =18–30
 | publisher =SAGE Journals
 | date =March 2016
 | doi =10.1177/0032258X16639426
 }}{{Dead link|date=July 2019 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Bicycles enjoy substantial use as general delivery vehicles in many countries. In the UK and North America, as their first jobs, generations of teenagers have worked at delivering newspapers by bicycle. London has many delivery companies that use bicycles with trailers. Most cities in the West, and many outside it, support a sizeable and visible industry of [[Bicycle messenger|cycle couriers]] who deliver documents and small packages. In India, many of Mumbai's [[Dabbawala]]s use bicycles to deliver home cooked lunches to the city's workers. In [[Bogotá]], Colombia the city's largest bakery recently replaced most of its delivery trucks with bicycles. Even the car industry uses bicycles. At the huge [[Mercedes-Benz]] factory in [[Sindelfingen]], Germany workers use bicycles, color-coded by department, to move around the factory.{{citation needed|date=March 2015}}

===Recreational===

====Bicycle touring====
{{Main|Bicycle touring}}
[[File:WhiteBikesVeluwe.jpg|thumb|In the Netherlands, bicycles are freely available for use in the [[Hoge Veluwe National Park]].|alt=A white bicycle parked in the grass.]] [[File:Bikes in Portland.jpg|thumb|Tour de Fat group ride in [[Portland, Oregon]]|alt=Many bicyclists with colorful clothes]]

Bicycles are used for recreation at all ages. [[Bicycle touring]], also known as cyclotourism, involves touring and exploration or sightseeing by bicycle for leisure. Bicycle tourism has been one of the most popular sports for recreational benefit.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Yeh|last2=Lin|last3=Hsiao|last4=Huang|date=2019-09-17|title=The Effect of Improving Cycleway Environment on the Recreational Benefits of Bicycle Tourism|journal=International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health|language=en|volume=16|issue=18|pages=3460|doi=10.3390/ijerph16183460|issn=1660-4601|pmc=6765930|pmid=31533371}}&lt;/ref&gt; A [[brevet (cycling)|brevet]] or randonnée is an organized long-distance ride.

One popular Dutch pleasure is the enjoyment of relaxed cycling in the [[rural|countryside]] of the Netherlands. The land is very flat and full of public [[bike path|bicycle trails]] and [[cycle track]]s where cyclists are not bothered by cars and other traffic, which makes it ideal for cycling recreation. Many [[Dutch people]] subscribe every year to an event called ''[[fietsvierdaagse]]''&amp;nbsp;— four days of organised cycling through the local environment. [[Paris–Brest–Paris]] (PBP), which began in 1891, is the oldest bicycling event still run on a regular basis on the open road, covers over {{convert|1200|km|0|abbr=on}} and imposes a 90-hour time limit. Similar if smaller institutions exist in many countries.

A study conducted in Taiwan improved the environmental quality for bicyclist tourists which demonstrated greater health benefits in tourists and even in natives. The number of bicyclists in Taiwan increased from 700,000 in 2008 to 5.1 million in 2017. Thus, this resulted in more and safer bicycle routes to be established. When cycling, cyclists take into account the safety on the road, bicycle lanes, smooth roads, diverse scenery, and ride length. Thus, the environment plays a huge role in people's decision factor to utilize bicycle touring more. This study utilized many questionnaires and conducted statistical analysis to come up with the conclusion of cyclists' top 5 factors that they consider before making a decision to bike are: safety, lighting facility, design of lanes, the surrounding landscape, and how clean the environment is. Thus, after improving these 5 factors, they found much more recreational benefits to bicycle tourism. &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Yeh|last2=Lin|last3=Hsiao|last4=Huang|date=2019|title=The Effect of Improving Cycleway Environment on the Recreational Benefits of Bicycle Tourism|journal=International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health|language=en|volume=16|issue=18|pages=3460|doi=10.3390/ijerph16183460|issn=1660-4601|pmc=6765930|pmid=31533371}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Organized rides====
Many [[cycling club]]s hold organized rides in which bicyclists of all levels participate. The typical organized ride starts with a large group of riders, called the mass, bunch or even [[peloton]]. This will thin out over the course of the ride. Many riders choose to ride together in groups of the same skill level to take advantage of [[drafting (racing)|drafting]].

Most organized rides, for example [[cyclosportive]]s (or gran fondos), [[Challenge riding|Challenge Rides]] or [[reliability trial]]s, and [[Hillclimbing (cycling)|hill climbs]] include registration requirements and will provide information either through the mail or online concerning start times and other requirements. Rides usually consist of several different routes, sorted by mileage, and with a certain number of rest stops that usually include refreshments, first aid and maintenance tools. Routes can vary by as much as {{convert|100|mi|km}}.

[[File:Kluft-photo-2019-07-19-SJBP-regroup2a.jpg|right|thumb|San Jose Bike Party in San Jose, California (July 2019)]]
Some organized rides are entirely social events. One example is the monthly [[San Jose Bike Party]] which can reach attendance of one to two thousand riders in Summer months.

====Mountain====
[[Mountain biking]] began in the 1970s, originally as a downhill sport, practised on customized [[cruiser bicycle]]s around [[Mount Tamalpais]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sonic.net/~ckelly/Seekay/clunker.htm |title=Clunkers Among the Hills |publisher=Sonic.net |accessdate=2012-06-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; Most mountain biking takes place on dirt roads, trails and in purpose-built parks. Downhill mountain biking has just evolved in the recent years and is performed at places such as Whistler Mountain Bike Park. Slopestyle, a form of downhill, is when riders do tricks such as tailwhips, 360s, backflips and front flips.
There are several disciplines of mountain biking besides downhill. Cross country, often referred to as XC, all mountain, trail, free ride, and newly popular enduro.

====Other====
The [[Marching and Cycling Band HHK]] from [[Haarlem]] (the Netherlands) is one of the few marching bands around the world which also performs on bicycles.

===Racing===
[[File:Leon Georget 1909.jpg|thumb|Bicycle racing in 1909.|alt=A black-and-white picture of a man on an old bicycle. Another man is holding or pushing the bicycle.]]
[[File:Peloton on GGB.jpg|thumb|A [[peloton]] of professional bicycle racers on the [[Golden Gate Bridge]]|alt=A group of bicyclist following a car.]]

{{Main|Cycle sport}}
Shortly after the introduction of bicycles, competitions developed independently in many parts of the world. Early races involving [[Boneshaker (bicycle)|boneshaker]] style bicycles were predictably fraught with injuries. Large races became popular during the 1890s &quot;Golden Age of Cycling&quot;, with events across Europe, and in the U.S. and Japan as well. At one point, almost every major city in the US had a [[velodrome]] or two for [[Track cycling|track racing]] events, however since the middle of the 20th century cycling has become a minority sport in the US whilst in Continental Europe it continues to be a major sport, particularly in the United Kingdom, France, Belgium, Italy and Spain. The most famous of all bicycle races is the [[Tour de France]]. This began in 1903, and continues to capture the attention of the sporting world.

In 1899, [[Charles Minthorn Murphy]] became the first man to ride his bicycle a mile in under a minute (hence his nickname, Mile-a-Minute Murphy), which he did by drafting a [[locomotive]] at [[New York (state)|New York]]'s [[Long Island]].

As the bicycle evolved its various forms, different racing formats developed. Road races may involve both team and individual competition, and are contested in various ways. They range from the one-day road race, [[criterium]], and time trial to multi-stage events like the Tour de France and its sister events which make up cycling's [[Grand Tour (cycling)|Grand Tours]]. [[Recumbent bicycle]]s were banned from bike races in 1934 after Marcel Berthet set a new [[hour record]] in his ''Velodyne streamliner'' (49.992&amp;nbsp;km on November 18, 1933). [[Track bicycle]]s are used for [[track cycling]] in [[Velodrome]]s, while [[cyclo-cross]] races are held on outdoor terrain, including pavement, grass, and mud. Cyclocross races feature man-made features such as small barriers which riders either [[Bunny hop (cycling)|bunny hop]] over or dismount and walk over. [[Individual time trial|Time trial]] races, another form of road racing require a rider to ride against the clock. Time trials can be performed as a team or as a single rider. Bikes are changed for time trial races, using [[aero bars]]. In the past decade, [[mountain biking|mountain bike racing]] has also reached international popularity and is even an Olympic sport.

Professional racing organizations place limitations on the bicycles that can be used in the races that they sanction. For example, the Union Cycliste Internationale, the governing body of international cycle sport (which sanctions races such as the Tour de France), decided in the late 1990s to create additional rules which prohibit racing bicycles weighing less than 6.8 kilograms (14.96 pounds). The UCI rules also effectively ban some [[bicycle frame]] innovations (such as the [[recumbent bicycle]]) by requiring a double triangle structure.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://oldsite.uci.ch/english/about/rules/ch01_general.pdf |title=UCI Cycling Regulations |accessdate=2006-08-04 |author=Union Cycliste International |year=2003 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120304223058/http://oldsite.uci.ch/english/about/rules/ch01_general.pdf |archive-date=2012-03-04 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===War===
{{Main|Bicycle infantry}}
The bicycle has been used as a method of reconnaissance as well as transporting soldiers and supplies to combat zones. In this it has taken over many of the functions of [[horses in warfare]]. In the [[Second Boer War]], both sides used bicycles for scouting. In World War I, France, Germany, Australia and New Zealand used bicycles to move troops. In its 1937 invasion of China, Japan employed some 50,000 bicycle troops, and similar forces were instrumental in Japan's [[Malayan Campaign|march or &quot;roll&quot; through Malaya]] in [[World War II]]. Germany used bicycles again in World War II, while the British employed airborne &quot;Cycle-commandos&quot; with [[folding bike]]s.

In the [[Vietnam War]], communist forces used bicycles extensively as cargo carriers along the [[Ho Chi Minh Trail]].

The last country known to maintain a regiment of bicycle troops was Switzerland, which disbanded its last unit in 2003.

==Activism==
Two broad and correlated themes run in bicycle activism: one is about [[bicycle advocacy|advocating the bicycle]] as an alternative mode of transport, and the other is about the creation of conditions to permit and/or encourage bicycle use, both for utility and recreational cycling.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=One Less Car: Bicycling and the Politics of Automobility |url=http://www.temple.edu/tempress/titles/1899_reg.html |last=Furness |first=Zack |year=2010 |publisher=Temple University Press |location=Philadelphia |isbn=978-1-59213-613-1 |access-date=2010-07-08 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100527225405/http://www.temple.edu/tempress/titles/1899_reg.html |archive-date=2010-05-27 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; Although the first, which emphasizes the potential for energy and resource conservation and health benefits gained from cycling versus automobile use, is relatively undisputed, the second is the subject of much debate.

[[File:Critical Mass, San Francisco, April 29, 2005.jpg|thumb|San Francisco [[Critical Mass (cycling)|Critical Mass]], April 29, 2005.|alt=Many cyclists on a road, all going in the same direction.]]

It is generally agreed that improved local and [[inter-city rail]] services and other methods of mass transportation (including greater provision for cycle carriage on such services) create conditions to encourage bicycle use. However, there are different opinions on the role of various types of [[cycling infrastructure]] in building [[bicycle-friendly]] cities and roads.

Some bicycle activists (including some traffic management advisers) seek the construction of [[bike path]]s, [[cycle track]]s and [[bike lane]]s for journeys of all lengths and point to their success in promoting [[bike safety|safety]] and encouraging more people to cycle. Some activists, especially those from the [[vehicular cycling]] tradition, view the safety, practicality, and intent of such facilities with suspicion. They favor a more holistic approach based on [[Traffic psychology#Accident prevention and improvement of traffic safety|the 4 'E's]]; ''education'' (of everyone involved), ''encouragement'' (to apply the education), ''enforcement'' (to protect the rights of others), and ''engineering'' (to facilitate travel while respecting every person's equal right to do so). Some groups offer [[Vehicular cycling#Education|training courses]] to help cyclists integrate themselves with other traffic.

[[Critical Mass (cycling)|Critical Mass]] is an event typically held on the last Friday of every month in [[city|cities]] around the world where bicyclists take to the streets ''en masse''. While the ride was founded with the idea of drawing attention to how unfriendly the city was to bicyclists, the leaderless structure of Critical Mass makes it impossible to assign it any one specific goal. In fact, the purpose of Critical Mass is not formalized beyond the [[direct action]] of meeting at a set location and time and traveling as a group through city streets.

There is a long-running [[Bicycle helmet#Opinions for and against the use of helmets|cycle helmet debate]] among activists. The most heated controversy surrounds the topic of [[Bicycle helmet#Legislation and culture|compulsory helmet use]].&lt;ref&gt;Robinson, Dorothy L. &quot;Bicycle helmet legislation: can we reach a consensus?.&quot; Accident Analysis &amp; Prevention 39.1 (2007): 86-93.&lt;/ref&gt;

Other concerns have also arisen about the behavior of militant cyclists and their imposition of pro-cyclist laws and accommodations at the expense of other commuters and citizens.&lt;ref&gt;https://nypost.com/2017/06/01/as-city-panders-to-militant-cyclists-everyone-else-pays/&lt;/ref&gt; The concerns also extend to the disruption to other forms of transportation by militant cyclists and endangering their own safety as well as others including pedestrians through constant intrusion, imposition and violations of traffic laws.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.heraldscotland.com/opinion/13166177.bullying-cyclists-are-a-menace-to-society/&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;https://www.warringtonguardian.co.uk/news/columnists/the_fly_in_the_ointment/17719644.militant-cyclists-must-learn-highway-code-but-safer-cycling-lanes-would-help/&lt;/ref&gt;

==Associations==
{{main|Cycling association}}
[[File:World Cycling Centre - Aigle Switzerland.jpg|thumb|Headquarters of the [[Union Cycliste Internationale]] in Switzerland]]
Cyclists form associations, both for specific interests (trails development, road maintenance, bike maintenance, urban design, racing clubs, touring clubs, etc.) and for more global goals ([[energy conservation]], pollution reduction, promotion of fitness). Some bicycle clubs and national associations became prominent advocates for improvements to roads and highways. In the United States, the [[League of American Wheelmen]] lobbied for the improvement of roads in the last part of the 19th century, founding and leading the national [[Good Roads Movement]]. Their model for political organization, as well as the paved roads for which they argued, facilitated the growth of the automobile.

As a sport, cycling is governed internationally by the [[Union Cycliste Internationale]] in Switzerland, [[USA Cycling]] (merged with the United States Cycling Federation in 1995) in the United States, (for [[upright bicycle]]s) and by the [[International Human Powered Vehicle Association]] (for other HPVs, or human-powered vehicles). Cycling for transport and touring is promoted on a European level by the [[European Cyclists' Federation]], with associated members from Great Britain, Japan and elsewhere. Regular conferences on cycling as transport are held under the auspices of [[Velo City]]; global conferences are coordinated by Velo Mondial.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.velomondial.net
| title = Velo Mondial: The premier global sustainable mobility and cycling network
| accessdate = 2010-04-29
| url-status=dead
| archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20100423080541/http://www.velomondial.net/
| archivedate = 2010-04-23
| df = 
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Health effects==

The health benefits of cycling outweigh the risks, when cycling is compared to a sedentary lifestyle. A Dutch study found that cycling can extend lifespans by up to 14 months, but the risks equated to a reduced lifespan of 40 days or less.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |pmc=2920084 |doi=10.1289/ehp.0901747 |pmid=20587380 |year=2010 |last1=De Hartog |first1=J. J. |title=Do the Health Benefits of Cycling Outweigh the Risks? |journal=Environmental Health Perspectives |volume=118 |issue=8 |pages=1109–1116 |last2=Boogaard |first2=H |last3=Nijland |first3=H |last4=Hoek |first4=G }}&lt;/ref&gt; Mortality rate reduction was found to be directly correlated to the average time spent cycling, totaling to approximately 6500 deaths prevented by cycling.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Fishman|first=Elliot|last2=Schepers|first2=Paul|last3=Kamphuis|first3=Carlijn Barbara Maria|date=2015|title=Dutch Cycling: Quantifying the Health and Related Economic Benefits|journal=American Journal of Public Health|volume=105|issue=8|pages=e13–e15|doi=10.2105/ajph.2015.302724|pmid=26066942|pmc=4504332|issn=0090-0036}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Cycling in the Netherlands]] is often safer than in other parts of the world, so the [[risk-benefit ratio]] will be different in other regions.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation
| last1 = Schepers | first1 = Paul
 | last2 = Twisk | first2 = Divera
 | last3 = Fishman | first3 = Elliot
 | last4 = Fyhri | first4 = Aslak
 | last5 = Jensen | first5 = Anne
 | title =The Dutch road to a high level of cycling safety
 | journal =Safety Science
 | volume =92
 | pages =264–273
 | date =February 2017
 | language =English

 | doi =10.1016/j.ssci.2015.06.005
 | url = https://eprints.qut.edu.au/120431/1/SchepersetalTheDutchroadtoahighlevelofcyclingsafety.pdf
 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Overall, benefits of cycling or walking have been shown to exceed risks by ratios of 9:1 to 96:1 when compared with no exercise at all, including a wide variety of physical and mental outcomes.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |url=https://ubcmedicaljournal.files.wordpress.com/2015/11/ubcmj_3_2_2012_6-11.pdf |title=Bicycling: Health Risk or Benefit? |author1=Kay Teschke |author2=Conor C.O. Reynolds |author3=Francis J. Ries |author4=Brian Gouge |author5=Meghan Winters |journal=University of British Columbia Medical Journal |date=March 2012 |access-date=2016-10-19 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161020050801/https://ubcmedicaljournal.files.wordpress.com/2015/11/ubcmj_3_2_2012_6-11.pdf |archive-date=2016-10-20 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url= |title=The effects of transport mode use on self-perceived health, mental health, and social contact measures: A cross-sectional and longitudinal study |author1=IoneAvila-Palencia |journal=Environment International|date=2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Leyland|first=Louise-Ann|last2=Spencer|first2=Ben|last3=Beale|first3=Nick|last4=Jones|first4=Tim|last5=Reekum|first5=Carien M. van|date=2019-02-20|title=The effect of cycling on cognitive function and well-being in older adults|journal=PLOS ONE|language=en|volume=14|issue=2|pages=e0211779|doi=10.1371/journal.pone.0211779|issn=1932-6203|pmc=6388745|pmid=30785893|bibcode=2019PLoSO..1411779L}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Exercise===
[[File:Cyclist-189.JPG|thumb|left|Heavily equipped London cyclist: specialist cycle clothing, pollution mask, dark glasses and helmet.|alt=A man with sports clothes and a white helmet on a bicycle on a road.]]
The [[physical exercise]] gained from cycling is generally linked with increased health and 

well-being. According to the [[World Health Organization]] (WHO), physical inactivity is second only to [[tobacco smoking]] as a health risk in developed countries,&lt;ref name=&quot;WHO&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.euro.who.int/document/e75662.pdf|title=A Physically Active Life through Everyday Transport |publisher=World health Organisation|accessdate=2009-09-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; and is associated with 20-30% increased risk of various cancers, heart disease, and diabetes&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.who.int/westernpacific/health-topics/physical-activity|title=Physical activity|website=www.who.int|language=en|access-date=2019-10-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; and tens of billions of dollars of healthcare costs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.cdc.gov/nccdphp/dnpa/obesity/economic_consequences.htm|title=Overweight and Obesity: Economic Consequences|publisher=Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (cdc.gov)|accessdate=2009-09-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; The WHO's 2009 report&lt;ref name=&quot;WHO&quot; /&gt; suggests that increasing physical activity is a public health &quot;best buy&quot;, and that cycling is a &quot;highly suitable activity&quot; for this purpose. The charity [[Sustrans]] reports that investment in cycling provision can give a 20:1 return from health and other benefits.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sustrans.org.uk/default.asp?sID=1158137684156|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070312033043/http://www.sustrans.org.uk/default.asp?sID=1158137684156|archivedate=2007-03-12|title=How transport can save the NHS|publisher=sustrans.org.uk}}&lt;/ref&gt; It has been estimated that, on average, approximately 20 life-years are gained from the health benefits of road bicycling for every life-year lost through injury.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author3=British Medical Association |first1=Mayhew |last1=Hillman |first2=David |last2=Morgan |title=Cycling: Towards Health and Safety|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]|isbn=978-0-19-286151-1|year=1992}}{{page needed|date=March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Bicycles are often used by people seeking to improve their fitness and cardiovascular health. Recent studies on the use of cycling for commutes have shown that it reduces the risk of cardiovascular outcomes by 11%, with slightly more risk reduction in women than in men.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Oja|first=P.|last2=Titze|first2=S.|last3=Bauman|first3=A.|last4=Geus|first4=B. de|last5=Krenn|first5=P.|last6=Reger‐Nash|first6=B.|last7=Kohlberger|first7=T.|date=2011|title=Health benefits of cycling: a systematic review|journal=Scandinavian Journal of Medicine &amp; Science in Sports|language=en|volume=21|issue=4|pages=496–509|doi=10.1111/j.1600-0838.2011.01299.x|pmid=21496106|issn=1600-0838}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Shephard|first=Roy J|date=2008|title=Is Active Commuting the Answer to Population Health?|journal=Sports Medicine|volume=38|issue=9|pages=751–758|doi=10.2165/00007256-200838090-00004|pmid=18712942|issn=0112-1642}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, cycling is especially helpful for those with [[arthritis]] of the lower limbs who are unable to pursue sports that cause impact to the knees and other joints. Since cycling can be used for the practical purpose of transportation, there can be less need for self-discipline to exercise.

Cycling while seated is a relatively non-[[weight bearing]] exercise that, like [[Human swimming#As recreation and exercise|swimming]], does little to promote bone density.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1007/s00198-003-1418-z |pmid=12856112 |title=Low bone mineral density in highly trained male master cyclists |journal=Osteoporosis International |volume=14 |issue=8 |pages=644–9 |year=2003 |last1=Palmer |first1=Jacob E. |last2=Levy |first2=Susan S. |last3=Nichols |first3=Jeanne F. }}&lt;/ref&gt; Cycling up and out of the saddle, on the other hand, does a better job by transferring more of the rider's body weight to the legs. However, excessive cycling while standing can cause knee damage&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sheldonbrown.com/pain.html#knees|title=Bicycling and Pain|accessdate=2011-02-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; It used to be thought that cycling while standing was less energy efficient, but recent research has proven this not to be true. Other than air resistance, there is no wasted energy from cycling while standing, if it is done correctly.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.pezcyclingnews.com/?pg=fullstory&amp;id=4512| title=Sit or Stand: Tradeoffs in Efficiency?| publisher=PEZ Cycling News | date=November 21, 2006 | accessdate=2006-11-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Cycling on a [[stationary cycle]] is frequently advocated as a suitable exercise for rehabilitation, particularly for lower limb injury, owing to the low impact which it has on the joints. In particular, cycling is commonly used within knee rehabilitation programs, to strengthen the quadricep muscles with minimal stress on the knee ligaments.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=McLeod|first=William D.|last2=Blackburn|first2=T.A.|date=1980|title=Biomechanics of knee rehabilitation with cycling|journal=The American Journal of Sports Medicine|language=en-US|volume=8|issue=3|pages=175–180|doi=10.1177/036354658000800306|pmid=7377449|issn=0363-5465}}&lt;/ref&gt; Further stress of the knee can be relieved by changing seat heights and pedal position to improve the rehabilitation. Cycling is also used for rehabilitation after hip surgery to manage soft-tissue healing, control swelling and pain, and allow a larger range of motion to the nearby muscles earlier during recovery.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Stalzer|first=Steve|last2=Wahoff|first2=Michael|last3=Scanlan|first3=Molly|last4=Draovitch|first4=Pete|date=2005|title=Rehabilitation After Hip Arthroscopy|journal=Operative Techniques in Orthopaedics|series=Hip Arthroscopy|volume=15|issue=3|pages=280–289|doi=10.1053/j.oto.2005.06.007|issn=1048-6666}}&lt;/ref&gt; As a result, many institutions have established a rehabilitation protocol that involves stationary cycling as part of the recovery process. One such protocol offered by Mayo Clinic recommends 2-4 weeks of cycling on an upright stationary bike following [[hip arthroscopy]], starting from 5 minutes per session and slowly increasing to 30 minutes per session.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Spencer-Gardner|first=Luke|last2=Eischen|first2=Joseph J.|last3=Levy|first3=Bruce A.|last4=Sierra|first4=Rafael J.|last5=Engasser|first5=William M.|last6=Krych|first6=Aaron J.|date=2013|title=A comprehensive five-phase rehabilitation programme after hip arthroscopy for femoroacetabular impingement|journal=Knee Surgery, Sports Traumatology, Arthroscopy|volume=22|issue=4|pages=848–859|doi=10.1007/s00167-013-2664-z|pmid=24077689|issn=0942-2056}}&lt;/ref&gt; The goal of these sessions are to reduce joint [[inflammation]] and maintain the widest range of motion possible with limited pain. 
[[File:Bike at Prins hendrikkade Amsterdam centraal.JPG|thumb|Bike at Prins Hendrikkade [[Amsterdam]].]]

As a response to the increased global sedentary lifestyles and consequent overweight and [[obesity]], one response that has been adopted by many organizations concerned with health and environment is the promotion of [[Active travel]], which seeks to promote walking and cycling as safe and attractive alternatives to motorized transport. Given that many journeys are for relatively short distances, there is considerable scope to replace car use with walking or cycling, though in many settings this may require some infrastructure modification, particularly to attract the less experienced and confident.

An Italian study assessed the impact of cycling for commute on major non-communicable diseases and public healthcare costs. Using a health economic assessment model, the study found a lower incidence of type 2 diabetes, acute myocardial infarction, and stroke in individuals that cycled compared to those that did not actively commute. This model estimated that public healthcare costs would reduce by 5% over a 10-year period.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Taddei|first=Cristina|last2=Gnesotto|first2=Roberto|last3=Forni|first3=Silvia|last4=Bonaccorsi|first4=Guglielmo|last5=Vannucci|first5=Andrea|last6=Garofalo|first6=Giorgio|date=2015-04-30|title=Cycling Promotion and Non-Communicable Disease Prevention: Health Impact Assessment and Economic Evaluation of Cycling to Work or School in Florence|journal=PLOS ONE|language=en|volume=10|issue=4|pages=e0125491|doi=10.1371/journal.pone.0125491|issn=1932-6203|pmc=4415918|pmid=25928421|bibcode=2015PLoSO..1025491T}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Illinois designated cycling as its [[List of Illinois state symbols|official state exercise]] in 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |title= Cats and dogs, bikes and milkweed: Illinois adds more state symbols beginning in the new year |last= Herrmann |first= Brett |date= December 28, 2017 |work= News Tribune |url= http://www.newstrib.com/free/illinois-adds-more-state-symbols-beginning-in-the-new-year/article_462130f2-ebe1-11e7-8d9b-a7468edb679d.html |accessdate= 2019-05-22 }}{{Dead link|date=September 2019 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Mental Health ===
The effects of cycling on overall mental health has often been studied. A European study surveying participants from seven cities about self-perceived health based on primary modes of transportation reported favorable results in the bicycle use population.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Avila-Palencia|first=Ione|last2=Int Panis|first2=Luc|last3=Dons|first3=Evi|last4=Gaupp-Berghausen|first4=Mailin|last5=Raser|first5=Elisabeth|last6=Götschi|first6=Thomas|last7=Gerike|first7=Regine|last8=Brand|first8=Christian|last9=de Nazelle|first9=Audrey|last10=Orjuela|first10=Juan Pablo|last11=Anaya-Boig|first11=Esther|date=2018-11-01|title=The effects of transport mode use on self-perceived health, mental health, and social contact measures: A cross-sectional and longitudinal study|journal=Environment International|volume=120|pages=199–206|doi=10.1016/j.envint.2018.08.002|pmid=30098553|issn=0160-4120|hdl=10044/1/62973}}&lt;/ref&gt; The bicycle use group reported predominantly good self-perceived health, less perceived stress, better mental health, better vitality, and less loneliness. The study attributed these results to possible economic benefits and senses of both independence and identity as a member of a cyclist community. An English study recruiting non-cyclist older adults aged 50 to 83 to participate as either conventional pedal bike cyclists, electrically assisted e-bike cyclists, or a non-cyclist control group in outdoor trails measured cognitive function through executive function, spatial reasoning, and memory tests and well-being through questionnaires.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Leyland|first=Louise-Ann|last2=Spencer|first2=Ben|last3=Beale|first3=Nick|last4=Jones|first4=Tim|last5=van Reekum|first5=Carien M.|date=2019|title=The effect of cycling on cognitive function and well-being in older adults|journal=PLOS ONE|volume=14|issue=2|pages=e0211779|doi=10.1371/journal.pone.0211779|issn=1932-6203|pmc=6388745|pmid=30785893|bibcode=2019PLoSO..1411779L}}&lt;/ref&gt; The study did not find significant differences in spatial reasoning or memory tests. It did however find that both cyclists groups had improved executive function and well-being, both with greater improvement in the e-bike group. This suggested that non-physical factors of cycling such as independence, engagement with the outdoor environment, and mobility play a greater role in improving mental health.

A 15 month randomized controlled trial in the U.S. examined the impact of self-paced cycling on cognitive function in institutionalized older adults without cognitive impairment.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Varela|first=Silvia|last2=Cancela|first2=José M.|last3=Seijo-Martinez|first3=Manuel|last4=Ayán|first4=Carlos|date=2018-10-01|title=Self-Paced Cycling Improves Cognition on Institutionalized Older Adults Without Known Cognitive Impairment: A 15-Month Randomized Controlled Trial|journal=Journal of Aging and Physical Activity|volume=26|issue=4|pages=614–623|doi=10.1123/japa.2017-0135|pmid=29431549|issn=1063-8652}}&lt;/ref&gt; Researchers used three cognitive assessments: Mini-Mental State Examination (MMSE), Fuld object memory evaluation, and symbol digit modality test. The study found that long-term cycling for at least 15 minutes per day in older adults without cognitive impairment had a protective effect on cognition and attention. 

Cycling has also been shown to be effective adjunct therapy in certain mental health conditions.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Karssemeijer|first=E. G. A.|last2=Bossers|first2=W. J. R.|last3=Aaronson|first3=J. A.|last4=Kessels|first4=R. P. C.|last5=Olde Rikkert|first5=M. G. M.|date=March 21, 2017|title=The effect of an interactive cycling training on cognitive functioning in older adults with mild dementia: study protocol for a randomized controlled trial|journal=BMC Geriatrics|volume=17|issue=1|pages=73|doi=10.1186/s12877-017-0464-x|issn=1471-2318|pmc=5361710|pmid=28327083}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Ryu|first=Jehkwang|last2=Jung|first2=Jae Hoon|last3=Kim|first3=Jiheon|last4=Kim|first4=Chan-Hyung|last5=Lee|first5=Hwa-Bock|last6=Kim|first6=Do-Hoon|last7=Lee|first7=Sang-Kyu|last8=Shin|first8=Ji-Hyeon|last9=Roh|first9=Daeyoung|date=2019-10-21|title=Outdoor cycling improves clinical symptoms, cognition and objectively measured physical activity in patients with schizophrenia: A randomized controlled trial|journal=Journal of Psychiatric Research|volume=120|pages=144–153|doi=10.1016/j.jpsychires.2019.10.015|issn=1879-1379|pmid=31678749}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Bicycle safety===

{{Further|Bicycle safety}}
[[File:Santa-Maria-Patroness-of-bicyclists-4606.jpg|thumb|[[Virgin Mary]] venerated as the holy protector of bicyclists on the roads of the mountainous [[Basque Country (autonomous community)|Basque Country]]|alt=A statue, covered with flowers.]]
Cycling suffers from a perception that it is unsafe.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=On Your Bike! |first=Matt |last=Seaton |page=103 |year=2006 |publisher=[[Black Dog Publishing]] |location=London |isbn=978-1-904772-40-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Horton, D. (2007) Fear of Cycling. In p. Rosen, P. Cox, Horton, D. Cycling and Society. London: Ashgate&lt;/ref&gt; This perception is not always backed by hard numbers, because of under reporting of accidents and lack of bicycle use data (amount of cycling, kilometers cycled) which make it hard to assess the [[risk]] and monitor changes in risks.&lt;ref name=&quot;Vanparijs&quot;&gt;{{cite journal
 | last = Vanparijs
 | first = J
 | title = Exposure measurement in bicycle safety analysis: A review of the literature
 | journal = Accident Analysis &amp; Prevention
 | volume = 84
 | issue = 
 | pages = 9–19
 | date = August 2015
 | url = https://www.researchgate.net/publication/281166893
 | doi = 10.1016/j.aap.2015.08.007
 | pmid = 26296182
 | last2 = Int Panis
 | first2 =L
 | last3 =Meeusen 
 | first3 =R
 | last4 =De Geus
 | first4 = B
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In the UK, fatality rates per mile or kilometre are slightly less than those for walking.&lt;ref name=&quot;UK fatalities by mode&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dft.gov.uk/adobepdf/162469/221412/221549/227755/rcgb2007.pdf|title=Road Casualties Great Britain 2007&amp;nbsp;– Annual Report (page 82, &quot;Fatality rates by mode of travel&quot;)|publisher=Department for Transport}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the US, bicycling fatality rates are less than 2/3 of those walking the same distance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bts.gov/publications/transportation_statistics_annual_report/2004/html/chapter_02/daily_travel_by_walking_and_bicycling.html|title=Daily Travel by Walking and Bicycling|publisher=Bureau of Transportation Statistics|accessdate=2009-09-29|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090710034644/http://www.bts.gov/publications/transportation_statistics_annual_report/2004/html/chapter_02/daily_travel_by_walking_and_bicycling.html|archive-date=2009-07-10|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www-fars.nhtsa.dot.gov/|title=Fatality Analysis Reporting System|publisher=National Highway Traffic Safety Administration|accessdate=2009-09-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, in the UK for example the fatality and serious injury rates ''per hour of travel'' are just over double for cycling than those for walking.&lt;ref name=&quot;UK fatalities by mode&quot; /&gt; Thus if a person is, for example, about to undertake a ten kilometre journey to a given destination it may on average be safer to undertake this journey by bicycle than on foot. However, if a person is intending, for example, to undertake an hour's exercise it may be more dangerous to take that exercise by cycling rather than by walking.

Despite the risk factors associated with bicycling, cyclists have a lower overall mortality rate when compared to other groups. A Danish study in 2000 found that even after adjustment for other risk factors, including leisure time physical activity, those who did not cycle to work experienced a 39% higher mortality rate than those who did.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1001/archinte.160.11.1621 |pmid=10847255 |title=All-Cause Mortality Associated with Physical Activity During Leisure Time, Work, Sports, and Cycling to Work |journal=Archives of Internal Medicine |volume=160 |issue=11 |pages=1621–8 |year=2000 |last1=Andersen |first1=Lars Bo |last2=Schnohr |first2=Peter |last3=Schroll |first3=Marianne |last4=Hein |first4=Hans Ole }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Injuries (to cyclists, from cycling) can be divided into two types:
* [[Physical trauma]] (extrinsic)
* Overuse (intrinsic).

====Physical trauma====
[[Acute (medical)|Acute]] physical trauma includes injuries to the head and extremities resulting from falls and collisions. Most cycle deaths result from a collision with a car or heavy goods vehicle, both motorist and cyclist having been found responsible for collisions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dft.gov.uk/pgr/statistics/datatablespublications/personal/articles/cyclingingreatbritain1|archive-url=http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20100304011242/http://www.dft.gov.uk/pgr/statistics/datatablespublications/personal/articles/cyclingingreatbritain1|url-status=dead|archive-date=2010-03-04|title=Cycling in Great Britain|publisher=Department of Transport|accessdate=2009-09-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.camcycle.org.uk/newsletters/53/article4.html|title=44 tonne articulated trucks and towns don't mix|publisher=Cambridge Cycling Campaign UK|accessdate=2009-09-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://showcase.commedia.org.uk/article/articleview/390/1/13/ |title=Lorries and Towns Don't Mix (video) |publisher=Robert Webb |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090123033954/http://showcase.commedia.org.uk/article/articleview/390/1/13/ |archivedate=January 23, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; A third of collisions between motorists and cyclists are caused by [[car dooring]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Wright |first=Gavin |date=12 July 2011 |title=Cycling for Dummies |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=uNP53v7qNewC&amp;pg=PA16 |publisher=[[John Wiley &amp; Sons]] |page=161 |isbn=978-0-7303-7666-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, around 16% of serious cyclist injuries reported to police in the UK in 2014 did not involve any other person or vehicle.&lt;ref name=&quot;ROSPA&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rospa.com/road-safety/advice/pedal-cyclists/facts-figures/| title =Cycling Accidents Facts &amp; Figures - August 2014|accessdate=2016-11-26|website =www.rospa.com|publisher=The Royal Society for the Prevention of Accidents}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although a majority of bicycle collisions occur during the day,&lt;ref name=&quot;ROSPA&quot;/&gt; [[Bicycle lighting#Safety|bicycle lighting]] is recommended for [[bicycle safety|safety when bicycling]] at night to increase visibility.&lt;ref name=&quot;NHSTA&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url =http://www.nhtsa.gov/staticfiles/nti/pdf/812202-CountermeasuresThatWork8th.pdf | title = National Highway Traffic Safety Administration. Countermeasures that work: A highway safety countermeasures guide for State Highway Safety Offices, 8th edition.| date = 2015| website = www.nhtsa.gov|publisher=National Highway Traffic Safety Administration| access-date =2016-11-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Taiwan 2009 HuaLien Taroko Gorge Biking FRD 5416 Pano Extracted.jpg|thumb|Bicyclist pedals uphill at the [[Taroko National Park|Taroko Gorge]] in Taiwan]]
[[File:Bicycles and winter.jpg|thumb|Bicycles in [[Helsinki]] ([[Finland]])]]

====Overuse injuries====
Of a study of 518 cyclists, a large majority reported at least one overuse injury, with over one third requiring medical treatment. The most common injury sites were the neck (48.8%) and the knees (41.7%), as well as the groin/buttocks (36.1%), hands (31.1%), and back (30.3%). Women were more likely to suffer from neck and shoulder pain than men.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1055/s-2007-972992 |pmid=7649713 |title=An Epidemiological Analysis of Overuse Injuries Among Recreational Cyclists |journal=International Journal of Sports Medicine |volume=16 |issue=3 |pages=201–6 |year=2007 |last1=Wilber |first1=C. |last2=Holland |first2=G. |last3=Madison |first3=R. |last4=Loy |first4=S. }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many cyclists suffer from overuse injuries to the knees, affecting cyclists at all levels. These are caused by many factors:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.biomech.com/db_area/archives/1996/9607sports.bio.html | archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070928070212/http://www.biomech.com/db_area/archives/1996/9607sports.bio.html | archivedate=2007-09-28 | title=Knee Pain in Cycling: New Twist on an old Injury | publisher=BioMechanics | date=July–August 1996 | accessdate=2006-11-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Incorrect bicycle fit or adjustment, particularly the saddle.
*Incorrect adjustment of clipless pedals.
*Too many hills, or too many miles, too early in the training season.
*Poor training preparation for long touring rides.
*Selecting too high a gear. A lower gear for uphill climb protects the knees, even though muscles may be well able to handle a higher gear.

Overuse injuries, including chronic nerve damage at weight bearing locations, can occur as a result of repeatedly riding a bicycle for extended periods of time. Damage to the [[ulnar nerve]] in the palm, [[carpal tunnel syndrome|carpal tunnel]] in the wrist, the genitourinary tract&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1016/j.eururo.2004.10.024 |pmid=15716187 |title=The Vicious Cycling: Bicycling Related Urogenital Disorders |journal=European Urology |volume=47 |issue=3 |pages=277–86; discussion 286–7 |year=2005 |last1=Leibovitch |first1=Ilan |last2=Mor |first2=Yoram }}&lt;/ref&gt; or [[bicycle seat neuropathy]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.emedicine.com/SPORTS/topic12.htm | title=Bicycle Seat Neuropathy, follow up | publisher=[[eMedicine]] | date=February 8, 2006 | accessdate=2006-03-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; may result from overuse. [[Recumbent bicycle]]s are designed on different [[ergonomics|ergonomic]] principles and eliminate pressure from the saddle and handlebars, due to the relaxed riding position.

Note that overuse is a relative term, and capacity varies greatly between individuals. Someone starting out in cycling must be careful to increase length and frequency of cycling sessions slowly, starting for example at an hour or two per day, or a hundred miles or kilometers per week. Bilateral muscular pain is a normal by-product of the training process, whereas unilateral pain may reveal &quot;exercise-induced arterial endofibrosis&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |pmid=15233595 |year=2004 |last1=Abraham |first1=P. |title=Past, present and future of arterial endofibrosis in athletes: A point of view |journal=Sports Medicine |volume=34 |issue=7 |pages=419–25 |last2=Bouyé |first2=P |last3=Quéré |first3=I |last4=Chevalier |first4=J. M. |last5=Saumet |first5=J. L. |doi=10.2165/00007256-200434070-00001}}&lt;/ref&gt; Joint pain and numbness are also early signs of overuse injury.

A Spanish study of top [[triathlete]]s found those who cover more than 186 miles (300&amp;nbsp;km) a week on their bikes have less than 4% normal looking [[sperm]], where normal adult males would be expected to have from 15% to 20%.&lt;ref name=&quot;bmj.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Wilkinson |first=Emma |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/health/8124458.stm |title=BBC: Elite cyclists 'risk infertility' |work=BBC News |date=2009-06-29 |accessdate=2012-06-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Saddle related ====
Much work has been done to investigate optimal [[bicycle saddle]] shape, size and position, and negative effects of extended use of less than optimal seats or configurations.

Excessive saddle height can cause [[Posterior (anatomy)|posterior]] knee pain, while setting the saddle too low can cause pain in the [[anterior]] of the knee. An incorrectly fitted saddle may eventually lead to muscle imbalance. A 25 to 35 degree knee angle is recommended to avoid an overuse injury.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://nationalpti.edu/blog/2015/07/avoiding-repetitive-knee-injuries-while-riding-a-bike/ | title=Avoid Repetitive Knee Injuries While Riding A Bike | access-date=2015-07-13 | archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150713225220/http://nationalpti.edu/blog/2015/07/avoiding-repetitive-knee-injuries-while-riding-a-bike/ | archive-date=2015-07-13 | url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Cycling has been linked to sexual impotence due to pressure on the perineum from the seat, but fitting a proper sized seat prevents this effect.&lt;ref name=&quot;bmj.com&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1136/bmj.g425 |pmid=24524928 |pmc=3923979 |title=Health effects of the London bicycle sharing system: Health impact modelling study |journal=BMJ |volume=348 |pages=g425 |year=2014 |last1=Woodcock |first1=J. |last2=Tainio |first2=M. |last3=Cheshire |first3=J. |last4=O'Brien |first4=O. |last5=Goodman |first5=A. }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/health/149268.stm|title=Cycle of despair|work=BBC News|accessdate=2009-09-29|date=1998-08-12}}{{Unreliable medical source|date=November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/health/363070.stm|title=Cycling linked to impotence|work=BBC News|accessdate=2009-09-29|date=1999-06-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;no nose&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1111/j.1743-6109.2008.00867.x |pmid=18466268 |title=Cutting off the Nose to Save the Penis |journal=Journal of Sexual Medicine |volume=5 |issue=8 |pages=1932–40 |year=2008 |last1=Schrader |first1=Steven M. |last2=Breitenstein |first2=Michael J. |last3=Lowe |first3=Brian D. }}&lt;/ref&gt; In extreme cases, [[pudendal nerve entrapment]] can be a source of intractable perineal pain.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1097/00002060-200306000-00013 |year=2003 |last1=Ramsden |first1=Christopher |journal=American Journal of Physical Medicine &amp; Rehabilitation |volume=82 |issue=6 |pages=479–484 |last2=McDaniel |first2=Michael |last3=Harmon |first3=Robert |last4=Renney |first4=Kenneth |last5=Faure |first5=Alexis |pmid=12820792 |title=Pudendal nerve entrapment as source of intractable perineal pain}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some cyclists with induced pudendal nerve pressure neuropathy gained relief from improvements in saddle position and riding techniques.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |pmid=1821826 |year=1991 |last1=Silbert |first1=P. L. |title=Bicycling induced pudendal nerve pressure neuropathy |journal=Clinical and Experimental Neurology |volume=28 |pages=191–6 |last2=Dunne |first2=J. W. |last3=Edis |first3=R. H. |last4=Stewart-Wynne |first4=E. G. }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[National Institute for Occupational Safety and Health]] (NIOSH) has investigated the potential health effects of prolonged bicycling in police bicycle patrol units, including the possibility that some bicycle saddles exert excessive pressure on the urogenital area of cyclists, restricting blood flow to the genitals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= https://www.cdc.gov/niosh/topics/bike/ |title=NIOSH -Bicycle Saddles and Reproductive Health |accessdate=2007-10-10|publisher=United States National Institute for Occupational Safety and Health}}&lt;/ref&gt; Their study found that using bicycle seats without protruding noses reduced pressure on the groin by at least 65% and significantly reduced the number of cases of urogenital paresthesia. A follow-up found that 90% of bicycle officers who tried the no-nose seat were using it six months later. NIOSH recommends that riders use a no-nose bicycle seat for workplace bicycling.&lt;ref name =&quot;no nose&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;impact niosh&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|url=https://www.cdc.gov/niosh/docs/2010-163/|title=NIOSH Research Demonstrates the Effectiveness of No-Nose Bicycle Seats in Reducing Groin Pressure and Improving Sexual Health (2010-163)|publisher=CDC – The National Institute for Occupational Safety and Health (NIOSH) |date=October 2010|doi=10.26616/NIOSHPUB2010163}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite rumors to the contrary, there is no [[scientific evidence]] linking cycling with [[testicular cancer]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.andrologyaustralia.org/library/TesticlarCancerFactSheet.pdf|title=Testiclar Cancer Fact Sheet|accessdate=2008-09-30|publisher=Monash Institute of Medical Research|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20081003171048/http://www.andrologyaustralia.org/library/TesticlarCancerFactSheet.pdf|archivedate=2008-10-03|df=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Exposure to air pollution====
One concern is that riding in traffic may expose the cyclist to higher levels of air pollution, especially if he or she travels on or along busy roads. Some authors have claimed this to be untrue, showing that the pollutant and irritant count within cars is consistently higher,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1071/HE04063 |last1=Chertok |first1=Michael |last2=Voukelatos |first2=Alexander |last3=Sheppeard |first3=Vicky |last4=Rissel |first4=Chris |year=2004 |title=Comparison of air pollution exposure for five commuting modes in Sydney - car, train, bus, bicycle and walking |journal=Health Promotion Journal of Australia |volume=15 |issue=1 |pages=63–7 |url=http://vadebike.org/wp-content/uploads/2008/08/Comparison-of-air-pollution-exposure-for-five-commuting-modes-in-Sydney-car-train-bus-bicycle-and-walking-HPJA.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; presumably because of limited circulation of air within the car and due to the air intake being directly in the stream of other traffic. Other authors have found small or inconsistent differences in concentrations but claim that exposure of cyclists is higher due to increased minute [[ventilation (physiology)|ventilation]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1016/j.atmosenv.2010.04.028 |title=Exposure to particulate matter in traffic: A comparison of cyclists and car passengers |journal=Atmospheric Environment |volume=44 |issue=19 |pages=2263–2270 |year=2010 |last1=Int Panis |first1=Luc |last2=De Geus |first2=Bas |last3=Vandenbulcke |first3=Grégory |last4=Willems |first4=Hanny |last5=Degraeuwe |first5=Bart |last6=Bleux |first6=Nico |last7=Mishra |first7=Vinit |last8=Thomas |first8=Isabelle |last9=Meeusen |first9=Romain |bibcode=2010AtmEn..44.2263I }}&lt;/ref&gt; and is associated with minor biological changes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1186/1476-069X-9-64 |pmid=20973949 |pmc=2984475 |title=Subclinical responses in healthy cyclists briefly exposed to traffic-related air pollution: An intervention study |journal=Environmental Health |volume=9 |pages=64 |year=2010 |last1=Jacobs |first1=Lotte |last2=Nawrot |first2=Tim S |last3=De Geus |first3=Bas |last4=Meeusen |first4=Romain |last5=Degraeuwe |first5=Bart |last6=Bernard |first6=Alfred |last7=Sughis |first7=Muhammad |last8=Nemery |first8=Benoit |last9=Panis |first9=Luc }}&lt;/ref&gt; A 2010 study estimated that the gained life expectancy from the health benefits of cycling (approximately 3-14 months gained) greatly exceeded the lost life expectancy from air pollution (approximately 0.8-40 days lost).&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt; However, a systematic review comparing the effects of air pollution exposure on the health of cyclists was conducted, but the authors concluded that the differing methodologies and measuring parameters of each study made it difficult to compare results and suggested a more holistic approach was needed to accomplish this.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Raza|first=Wasif|last2=Forsberg|first2=Bertil|last3=Johansson|first3=Christer|last4=Sommar|first4=Johan Nilsson|date=2018-02-05|title=Air pollution as a risk factor in health impact assessments of a travel mode shift towards cycling|journal=Global Health Action|volume=11|issue=1|pages=1429081|doi=10.1080/16549716.2018.1429081|issn=1654-9716|pmc=5804679|pmid=29400262}}&lt;/ref&gt; The significance of the associated health effect, if any, is unclear but probably much smaller than the health impacts associated with accidents and the health benefits derived from additional physical activity.

== See also ==
{{Portal|Sports|Transport}}
* [[Cycling mobility]]
* [[Outline of bicycles]]
* [[Outline of cycling]]
* [[Bicycle culture]]
* [[Cycle sport]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
{{Prone to spam|date=June 2012}}{{Z148}}
&lt;!--{{No more links}} Please be cautious adding more external links. Wikipedia is not a collection of links and should not be used for advertising. Excessive or inappropriate links will be removed. See [[Wikipedia:External links]] and [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for details.If there are already suitable links, propose additions or replacements on the article's talk page, or submit your link to the relevant category at the Open Directory Project (dmoz.org) and link there using {{Dmoz}}.--&gt;

{{Sister project links |wikt=cycling |commons=Category:Cycling |b= |n= |q= |s= |v= |voy=Cycling |species=no |d=no |display=Cycling }}
{{Cycling}}
{{Cycling in different countries and cities}}
{{Physical exercise}}
{{Utility cycling}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Physical exercise]]
[[Category:Sustainable transport]]
[[Category:Cycling| ]]
[[Category:Articles containing video clips]]
[[Category:Symbols of Illinois]]
[[Category:Climate change mitigation]]</text>
      <sha1>5lx2qggm4oz8vpbdrlyjgxr1k96mdx3</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
