  <page>
    <title>Cheers</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5907</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942751662</id>
      <parentid>942577321</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-26T16:34:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rescuing 1 sources and tagging 0 as dead.) #IABot (v2.0</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{About|the American TV series}}
{{short description|American TV sitcom, 1982–1993}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=February 2014}}
{{Infobox television
| show_name                = Cheers
| image                    = Cheers intro logo.jpg
| image_alt                = 
| genre                    = [[Sitcom]]
| creator                  = {{Plainlist|
* [[Glen and Les Charles|Glen Charles&lt;br/&gt;Les Charles]]
* [[James Burrows]]
}}
| starring                 = &lt;!-- Per infobox guidelines, original cast should be listed first followed by additional cast in the order they joined the series. --&gt;{{Plainlist|1=
* [[Ted Danson]]
* [[Shelley Long]]
* [[Nicholas Colasanto]]
* [[Rhea Perlman]]
* [[George Wendt]]
* [[John Ratzenberger]]
* [[Kelsey Grammer]]
* [[Woody Harrelson]]
* [[Kirstie Alley]]
* [[Bebe Neuwirth]]
&lt;!-- Per infobox instructions, [[WP:TVCAST]] and wide consensus, only actors who were credited onscreen in a starring role should be included here. Recurring characters and guest cast should not be included! --&gt;
}}
| theme_music_composer     = {{Plainlist|
* [[Gary Portnoy]]
* Judy Hart Angelo, Julian Williams
}}
| opentheme                = &quot;[[Where Everybody Knows Your Name]]&quot; by [[Gary Portnoy]]
| composer                 = [[Craig Safan]]
| country                  = United States
| language                 = English
| num_seasons              = 11
| num_episodes             = 275 &lt;small&gt;(including three double-length episodes and a triple-length finale)&lt;/small&gt;
| list_episodes            = List of Cheers episodes
| executive_producer       = {{plainlist|1=
* [[James Burrows]]
* [[Glen and Les Charles|Glen Charles&lt;br/&gt;Les Charles]]
* [[Bill and Cheri Steinkellner|Bill Steinkellner]] {{small|(season 9–11)}}
* [[Bill and Cheri Steinkellner|Cherie Steinkellner]] {{small|(season 9–11)}}
* [[Phoef Sutton]] {{small|(season 9–11)}}
* Tom Anderson {{small|(season 11)}}
* [[Dan O'Shannon]] {{small|(season 11)}}
}}
| cinematography           = {{Plainlist|
* John Finger
* [[Kenneth Peach]] &lt;small&gt;(first three episodes)&lt;/small&gt;
}}
| camera                   = {{Plainlist|

*[[Film]] 
*[[Multiple-camera setup|Multi-camera]]
}}
| runtime                  = 30 minutes
| company                  = {{Plainlist|
* Charles/Burrows Productions
* [[Paramount Television|Paramount Network Television]]
}}
| distributor              = {{Plainlist|
* [[Paramount Domestic Television]]&lt;br/&gt;(1987–2006)
* [[CBS Television Studios|CBS Paramount Domestic Television]]&lt;br/&gt;(2006–2007)
* [[CBS Television Distribution]]&lt;br/&gt;(2007–present)
}}
| network                  = [[NBC]]&lt;ref&gt;Wood, Jennifer M. &quot;Bar Trivia: 30 Facts About Cheers&quot;. Mental Floss. http://mentalfloss.com/article/56133/30-things-you-might-not-know-about-cheers&lt;/ref&gt;
| picture_format           = [[NTSC]] ([[480i]]) (original)
4:3 1080i (remastered versions)
| audio_format             = {{Plainlist|
* [[Stereophonic sound|Stereo]] (1982–1987)
* [[Dolby Surround]] (1988–1993)
}}
| first_aired              = {{Start date| 1982|9|30}}
| last_aired               = {{End date| 1993|5|20}}
| followed_by              = ''[[Frasier]]'' (1993–2004)
| related                  = *''[[St. Elsewhere#&quot;Cheers&quot;|St. Elsewhere]]'' (1982–1988)
*''[[The Tortellis]]'' (1987) 
*''[[Wings (1990 TV series)|Wings]]'' (1990–1997)
*[[Cheers (Spanish TV series)|''Cheers'' (Spanish version)]] (2011–2012)
}}
'''''Cheers''''' is an American [[sitcom]] television series that ran on [[NBC]] from September 30, 1982, to May 20, 1993, with a total of 275 half-hour episodes across eleven seasons. The show was produced by Charles/Burrows Productions in association with [[Paramount Television|Paramount Network Television]], and was created by the team of [[James Burrows]], [[Glen and Les Charles|Glen Charles, and Les Charles]]. The show is set in a bar named [[Cheers Beacon Hill|Cheers]] in [[Boston]], [[Massachusetts]], where a group of locals meet to drink, relax, and socialize. The show's main theme song, co-written and performed by [[Gary Portnoy]], lent its refrain &quot;[[Where Everybody Knows Your Name]]&quot; as the show's [[catchphrase]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first=Gary|last= Portnoy|date=2006|url=http://www.garyportnoy.com/|title=Portnoy's personal site|work=garyportnoy.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After premiering on September 30, 1982, it was nearly canceled during its first season when it ranked almost last in ratings for its premiere (74th out of 77 shows). ''Cheers'', however, eventually became a [[Nielsen ratings|highly rated]] television show in the United States, earning a top-ten rating during eight of its eleven seasons, including one season at number one. The show spent most of its run on NBC's Thursday night &quot;[[Must See TV]]&quot; lineup. Its [[List of most watched television broadcasts|widely watched]] [[series finale]] was broadcast on May 20, 1993, and the show's 275 [[List of Cheers episodes|episodes]] have been successfully [[Broadcast syndication|syndicated]] worldwide. Nominated for [[Primetime Emmy Award for Outstanding Comedy Series|Outstanding Comedy Series]] for all eleven of its seasons on the air, it earned 28 [[Primetime Emmy Award]]s from a record of 117 nominations. The character [[Frasier Crane]] ([[Kelsey Grammer]]) was featured in [[Frasier|his eponymous spin-off show]], which aired until 2004 and included guest appearances by virtually all of the major and minor ''Cheers'' characters.

During its run, ''Cheers'' became one of the most popular series of all time and has received critical acclaim from its start to its end. In 1997, the episodes &quot;[[Thanksgiving Orphans]]&quot; and &quot;[[Home Is the Sailor (Cheers)|Home Is the Sailor]]&quot;, aired originally in 1987, were respectively ranked No. 7 and No. 45 on [[TV Guide's 100 Greatest Episodes of All-Time|TV Guide's 100 Greatest Episodes of All Time]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1= |first1= |last2= |first2= |year=1997 |title=Special Collector's Issue: 100 Greatest Episodes of All Time |journal=[[TV Guide]] |issue=June 28 – July 4 |url= }}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2002, ''Cheers'' was ranked No.&amp;nbsp;18 on [[TV Guide's 50 Greatest TV Shows of All Time]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2002/04/26/entertainment/main507388.shtml |title=TV Guide Names Top 50 Shows |publisher=Cbsnews.com |date= |accessdate=September 13, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2013, the [[Writers Guild of America]] ranked it as the eighth-best-written TV series&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://wga.org/content/default.aspx?id=4925|title=101 Best Written TV Series List|work=wga.org|access-date=June 28, 2013|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130607080758/http://www.wga.org/content/default.aspx?id=5246|archive-date=June 7, 2013|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; and ''TV Guide'' ranked it No. 11 on their list of the 60 Greatest Shows of All Time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Fretts |first=Bruce |last2=Roush |first2=Matt |date= |title=The Greatest Shows on Earth |journal=TV Guide Magazine |volume=61 |issue=3194–3195 |pages=16–19 |doi=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Characters==
Before the ''Cheers'' pilot &quot;[[Give Me a Ring Sometime]]&quot; was completed and aired in 1982, the series originally consisted of four employees in the first script.&lt;ref name=scott1982/&gt; Neither [[Norm Peterson]] nor [[Cliff Clavin]], regular customers of Cheers, were featured; later revisions added them as among the regular characters of the series.&lt;ref name=112wendt114&gt;Wendt 2001, pp. 112–114.&lt;/ref&gt;

In later years, [[Woody Boyd]] replaced Coach, after the beloved character died off-screen in season four (1985–86), following actor [[Nicholas Colasanto]]'s death. [[Frasier Crane]] started as a recurring character and became a permanent one. In season six (1987–88), new character [[Rebecca Howe]] was added, having been written into the show after the finale of the previous season (1986–87). [[Lilith Sternin]] started as a one-time character in an episode of season four, &quot;Second Time Around&quot; (1985). After her second season five appearance, she became a recurring character, and was later featured as a permanent one during season ten (1991–92).

===Original main characters===
[[File:Cheers original cast 1982-86 (1983).jpg|thumb|Cast of seasons one through three, ''left to right'': ''(top)'' [[Shelley Long]], [[Ted Danson]]; ''(middle)'' [[Rhea Perlman]], [[Nicholas Colasanto]]; ''(bottom)'' [[George Wendt]], [[John Ratzenberger]] |alt=Background is the bar setting. Top row has a businesswoman and a handsome bartender. Middle row has a brunette perm waitress and an old bartender. Bottom row has a suit-dressed man and a mailman.]]

* [[Ted Danson]] as [[Sam Malone]]: &lt;br/&gt;A [[bartender]] of Cheers. Sam is also a [[lothario]]. Before the series began, he was a baseball [[relief pitcher]] for the [[Boston Red Sox]] nicknamed &quot;Mayday Malone&quot; until he became an [[alcoholic]], harming his career. He has an [[on-again, off-again relationship]] with [[Sam and Diane|Diane Chambers]], his class opposite, in the first five seasons (1982–1987). During their off-times, Sam has flings with many not-so-bright &quot;sexy women&quot;,&lt;ref name=honey264/&gt; yet fails to pursue a meaningful relationship&lt;ref name=honey264/&gt; and fails to seduce other women, such as intellectuals. After Diane is written out of the series, he tries to pursue Rebecca Howe, with varying results. At the end of the series, he is still unmarried and faces [[sexual addiction]] with the help of Dr. Robert Sutton's ([[Gilbert Lewis (actor)|Gilbert Lewis]]) group meetings, advised by Frasier.
* [[Shelley Long]] as [[Diane Chambers]]: &lt;br/&gt;An academic, sophisticated graduate student attending Boston University.&lt;ref name=scott1982/&gt; In the pilot, Diane is abandoned by her fiancé, leaving her without a job, a man, or money. Realizing that one of her few practical skills is memorization, which comes in handy when dealing with drink orders, she reluctantly becomes a barmaid. Later, she becomes a close friend of Coach&lt;ref name=10anniversary/&gt; and [[Sam and Diane|has an on-and-off relationship with bartender Sam Malone]], her class opposite. During their off-relationship times, Diane dates men who fit her upper-class ideals, such as Frasier Crane. In 1987, she leaves Boston behind for a writing career and to live in [[Los Angeles, California]]. Diane returns to Cheers to cure Sam of his drinking. Diane's biggest enemy is Carla but Diane doesn't insult Carla the way Carla does to Diane, which serves to annoy Carla even more.
* [[Nicholas Colasanto]] as [[Coach Ernie Pantusso]]: &lt;br/&gt;A &quot;borderline senile&quot;&lt;ref name=honey264/&gt; co-bartender, widower, and retired baseball coach. Coach is also a friend of Sam and a close friend of Diane. He has a daughter, [[Lisa Pantusso|Lisa]] ([[Allyce Beasley]]). Coach listens to people's problems and solves them. However, other people also help resolve his own problems. In 1985, Coach died without explicit explanation, as Colasanto died of a heart attack.&lt;ref name=colasantodeath/&gt;
* [[Rhea Perlman]] as [[Carla Tortelli]]: &lt;br/&gt;A &quot;wisecracking, cynical&quot;&lt;ref name=scott1982/&gt; cocktail waitress, who treats customers badly. She is also highly fertile and matrimonially inept. When the series premiered, she is the mother of four children by her ex-husband [[Nick Tortelli]] ([[Dan Hedaya]]). Over the course of the series, she bears four more, the depiction of which incorporated Perlman's real-life pregnancies.&lt;ref name=top10preggerstime&gt;&quot;[http://www.time.com/time/specials/packages/article/0,28804,1878293_1878320_1878375,00.html Top 10 Pregnant Performers: Where Everybody Knows You're Pregnant (or Not)].&quot; ''[[Time (magazine)|Time]]''. Web. June 2, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; All of her children are notoriously ill-behaved, except Ludlow, whose father is a prominent academic. She flirts with men, including ones who are not flattered by her ways, and believes in [[superstition]]s. Later she marries [[Eddie LeBec]], an [[ice hockey]] player, who later becomes a penguin mascot for ice shows. After he died in an ice show accident by an [[ice resurfacer]], Carla later discovers that Eddie had committed [[bigamy]] with another woman, whom he had gotten pregnant. Carla sleeps with Sam's enemy John Allen Hill to Sam's annoyance and anger.
* [[George Wendt]] as [[Norm Peterson]]: &lt;br/&gt;A bar regular and occasionally-employed [[accountant]]. A recurrent joke on the show, especially in the earlier seasons, was that the character was such a popular and constant fixture at the bar that anytime he entered through the front door everyone present would yell out his name (&quot;NORM!&quot;) in greeting; usually this cry would be followed by one of the present bartenders asking Norm how he was, usually receiving a sardonic response and a request for a beer. (&quot;It's a dog-eat-dog world, and I'm wearing Milkbone underwear.&quot;) He has infrequent accounting jobs and a troubled marriage with (but is still in love with and married to) Vera, an [[unseen character]], though is occasionally heard. Later in the series, he becomes a [[house painter]] and an [[interior decorator]]. Even later in the series, Norm secures his dream job, tasting beer at a brewery. The character was not originally intended to be a main cast role;&lt;ref name=112wendt114/&gt; Wendt auditioned for a minor role of George for the [[Give Me a Ring Sometime|pilot episode]]. The role was only to be Diane Chambers' first customer and had only one word: &quot;Beer!&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Wendt 2009, p. 112.&lt;/ref&gt; After he was cast in a more permanent role, the character was renamed Norm.&lt;ref&gt;Wendt 2009, p. 113.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[John Ratzenberger]] as [[Cliff Clavin]]: &lt;br/&gt;A [[know-it-all]] bar regular and [[postal worker|mail carrier]]. He lives with his mother [[Esther Clavin]] ([[Frances Sternhagen]]) in first the family house and later an apartment. In the bar, Cliff continuously spouts nonsensical and annoying trivia, making him an object of derision to the bar patrons. Ratzenberger auditioned for the role of a minor character George, but it went to Wendt, evolving the role into Norm Peterson.&lt;ref name=&quot;wendt113-114&quot;/&gt; The producers decided they wanted a resident bar know-it-all,&lt;ref name=&quot;wendt113-114&quot;&gt;Wendt 2009, pp.&amp;nbsp;113–114.&lt;/ref&gt; so the security guard Cliff Clavin was added for the pilot. The producers changed his occupation into a mail carrier as they thought such a man would have wider knowledge than a guard.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|date=June 28, 1985|url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=BH9WAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=SkENAAAAIBAJ&amp;dq=cheers%20cliff%20norm%20john%20wendt%20auditioned&amp;pg=3002%2C3299013|author=Buck, Jerry|title=''Cheers'' mailman describes 10 years in Britain|newspaper=[[The Leader-Post]]|at=TV Times|location=[[Canada]]|accessdate=May 5, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Subsequent main characters===
[[File:Cheers cast 1991.jpg|Cast of ''Cheers'' since season six. ''(left to right)'': ''(top)'' [[Rhea Perlman|Perlman]], [[Woody Harrelson]], [[Kelsey Grammer]], [[Bebe Neuwirth]]; (bottom) [[George Wendt|Wendt]], [[Kirstie Alley]], [[Ted Danson|Danson]], [[John Ratzenberger|Ratzenberger]] |thumb|upright=1.36|alt=Background is bar setting. Top row has a waitress, a young handsome bartender, and married opposite-sex psychiatrists. Bottom row has a suit-dressed man, a blonde, a middle-aged handsome bartender, and a mailman.]]
* [[Kelsey Grammer]] as [[Frasier Crane]]: &lt;br/&gt;A psychiatrist and bar regular. Frasier started out as Diane Chambers' love interest in the third season (1984–85). In the fourth season (1985–86), after Diane jilts him at the altar in Europe, Frasier ends up frequenting Cheers and becomes a regular. He later marries [[Lilith Sternin]] and has a son, Frederick. After the series ends the character becomes the focus of the spin-off ''[[Frasier]]'', in which he is divorced from Lilith and living in [[Seattle]].
* [[Woody Harrelson]] as [[Woody Boyd]]: &lt;br/&gt;A not-so-bright&lt;ref name=honey264/&gt; bartender. He arrives from his Midwest hometown of [[Hanover, Indiana]] to Boston, to see Coach, his &quot;[[pen pal]]&quot; (as referring to exchanging &quot;pens&quot;, not letters). When Sam tells Woody that Coach died, Sam hires Woody in Coach's place. Later, he marries his girlfriend Kelly Gaines ([[Jackie Swanson]]), also not-so-bright but raised in a rich family. In the final season, he runs for political office and, surprisingly, wins.
* [[Bebe Neuwirth]] as [[Lilith Sternin]]: &lt;br/&gt;A psychiatrist and bar regular. She is often teased by bar patrons about her uptight personality and appearance. In &quot;Second Time Around&quot; (1986), her first episode, also her only one of the fourth season, her date with Frasier does not go well because they constantly argue. In the fifth season, with help from Diane, Lilith and Frasier begin a relationship. Eventually, they marry and have a son, Frederick. In the eleventh and final season, she leaves Frasier to live with another man in an experimental underground environment called the &quot;Eco-pod.&quot; She returns later in the season and reconciles with Frasier. However, in the spinoff ''Frasier'', Lilith divorces Frasier and bears the custody of Frederick.
* [[Kirstie Alley]] as [[Rebecca Howe]]: &lt;br/&gt;She starts out as a strong independent woman, manager of the bar for the corporation that bought Cheers from Sam after his on-off relationship with Diane ended. Eventually, when Sam regains ownership, she begs him to let her remain as cocktail waitress. She repeatedly has romantic failures with mainly rich men and becomes more and more &quot;neurotic, insecure, and sexually frustrated&quot;.&lt;ref name=neurotic&gt;{{cite web|date=July 8, 2011|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130121110517/http://kenlevine.blogspot.com/2011/07/my-favorite-kirstie-alley-scene.html|author=Levine, Ken|url=http://kenlevine.blogspot.com/2011/07/my-favorite-kirstie-alley-scene.html|authorlink=Ken Levine (TV personality)|archivedate=January 21, 2013|url-status=live|accessdate=July 21, 2012|work=... by Ken Levine on [[Blogspot]]|title=My favorite Kirstie Alley scene}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the start, Sam frequently attempts to seduce Rebecca without success.&lt;ref name=craig&gt;{{cite journal|volume=2 |author=Craig, Steve |page=15 |accessdate=July 31, 2012 |year=1993 |title=Selling Masculinities, Selling Femininities: Multiple Genders and the Economics of Television |url=http://www.rtvf.unt.edu/html/craig/pdfs/gender.PDF |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070625104942/http://www.rtvf.unt.edu/html/craig/pdfs/gender.PDF |archivedate=June 25, 2007 |journal=The Mid-Atlantic Almanack |url-status=dead |df=mdy }}&lt;/ref&gt; As her personality changes,&lt;ref name=neurotic/&gt; he loses interest in her. In the series finale, after failed relationships with rich men, Rebecca marries a plumber and quits working for the bar. In the ''Frasier'' episode &quot;[[The Show Where Sam Shows Up]]&quot;, she is revealed to be divorced and back at the bar. When Frasier asks whether this means that she is working there again, Sam says &quot;no, she's just at the bar.&quot;

* {{note|a|a}} Before production of [[Cheers (season 3)|season 3]] was finished, Nicholas Colasanto died. Therefore, his character Coach was written out as deceased in season 4.&lt;ref name=colasantodeath/&gt;
* {{note|b|b}} In season 11, Bebe Neuwirth is given &quot;starring&quot; credit only when she appears.

===Character table===
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; style=&quot;font-size: 86%&quot;
|-
!! rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | Name
!! rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | Actress / Actor
!! rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | Role at Cheers
!! rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | Occupation
!! colspan=&quot;11&quot; | Seasons
|-
!! style=&quot;width:5%;&quot; | [[Cheers (season 1)|1]]
!! style=&quot;width:5%;&quot; | [[Cheers (season 2)|2]]
!! style=&quot;width:5%;&quot; | [[Cheers (season 3)|3]]
!! style=&quot;width:5%;&quot; | [[Cheers (season 4)|4]]
!! style=&quot;width:5%;&quot; | [[Cheers (season 5)|5]]
!! style=&quot;width:5%;&quot; | [[Cheers (season 6)|6]]
!! style=&quot;width:5%;&quot; | [[Cheers (season 7)|7]]
!! style=&quot;width:5%;&quot; | [[Cheers season 8|8]]
!! style=&quot;width:5%;&quot; | [[Cheers season 9|9]]
!! style=&quot;width:5%;&quot; | [[Cheers season 10|10]]
!! style=&quot;width:5%;&quot; | [[Cheers season 11|11]]
|-
| [[Sam Malone]]
| [[Ted Danson]]
| style=&quot;white-space:nowrap;&quot;| Owner/Bartender
| Former [[relief pitcher|baseball player]]
| colspan=&quot;11&quot; {{cMain}}
|-
| [[Diane Chambers]]
| [[Shelley Long]]
| Cocktail Waitress
| Graduate student, writer
| colspan=&quot;5&quot; {{cMain}}
| colspan=&quot;5&quot; {{n/a|}}
| {{cGuest}}
|-
| style=&quot;white-space:nowrap;&quot;| [[Coach Ernie Pantusso|Ernie &quot;Coach&quot; Pantusso]]
| style=&quot;white-space:nowrap;&quot;| [[Nicholas Colasanto]]
| Bartender
| Former baseball player and [[coach (baseball)|coach]]
| colspan=&quot;3&quot; {{cMain}}{{ref|a|a}}
| colspan=&quot;8&quot; {{n/a|}}
|-
| [[Carla Tortelli]]
| [[Rhea Perlman]]
| Waitress
| Mother, divorcee
| colspan=&quot;11&quot; {{cMain}}
|-
| [[Norm Peterson]]
| [[George Wendt]]
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | Customer
| style=&quot;white-space:nowrap;&quot;|Accountant; [[house painter and decorator|house painter]]; [[interior design|interior decorator]]
| colspan=&quot;11&quot; {{cMain}}
|-
| [[Cliff Clavin]]
| [[John Ratzenberger]]
| [[Postal worker|Mailman]]
| {{cRecurring}}
| colspan=&quot;10&quot; {{cMain}}
|-
| [[Woody Boyd]]
| [[Woody Harrelson]]
| style=&quot;white-space:nowrap;&quot;|Assistant Bartender&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite episode|title=Don't Shoot...I'm Only the Psychiatrist|episodelink=List of Cheers episodes#ep233|series=Cheers|network=[[NBC]]|airdate=January 2, 1992|season=10|number=13|minutes=14:55|quote=It's your assistant bartender, good old Woody}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| Actor; politician
| colspan=&quot;3&quot; {{n/a|}}
| colspan=&quot;8&quot; {{cMain}}
|-
| [[Frasier Crane]]
| [[Kelsey Grammer]]
| Customer
| [[Psychiatrist]]
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; {{n/a|}}
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; {{cRecurring}}
| colspan=&quot;7&quot; {{cMain}}
|-
| [[Rebecca Howe]]
| [[Kirstie Alley]]
| Owner/Manager
| [[Superintendent (building)|Superintendent]]&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Look Before You Sleep&quot;. Cheers. episode 20. season 11. April 1, 1993. 19:10 minutes in. (Sam goes to Rebecca's apartment and they both get locked outside) Rebecca: &quot;Now we're locked out.&quot; Sam: &quot;So What?! Call the Super!&quot; Rebecca: &quot;I AM the Super.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
| colspan=&quot;5&quot; {{n/a|}}
| colspan=&quot;6&quot; {{cMain}}
|-
| [[Lilith Sternin]]
| [[Bebe Neuwirth]]
| Customer
| [[Psychiatrist]]
| colspan=&quot;3&quot; {{n/a|}}
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; {{cGuest}}
| colspan=&quot;4&quot; {{cRecurring}}
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; {{cMain}}{{ref|b|b}}
|}

===Recurring characters===
{{main list|List of Cheers characters}}
Although ''Cheers'' operated largely around that main ensemble cast, guest stars and recurring characters did occasionally supplement them. Notable repeat guests included [[Dan Hedaya]] as [[Nick Tortelli]] and [[Jean Kasem]] as [[Loretta Tortelli]], who were the main characters in the first spin-off ''[[The Tortellis]]'', [[Fred Dryer]] as Dave Richards, [[Annie Golden]] as Margaret O'Keefe, [[Derek McGrath]] as Andy Schroeder (also referred to as ''Andy Andy''), interchangeably [[Joel Polis]] and [[Robert Desiderio]] as rival bar owner Gary, [[Jay Thomas]] as [[Eddie LeBec]], [[Roger Rees]] as [[Robin Colcord]], [[Tom Skerritt]] as [[Evan Drake]], [[Frances Sternhagen]] as Esther Clavin, [[Richard Doyle (actor)|Richard Doyle]] as Walter Gaines, [[Keene Curtis]] as John Allen Hill, [[Anthony Cistaro]] as Henri, Michael McGuire as Professor Sumner Sloan, and [[Harry Anderson]] as Harry 'The Hat' Gittes. [[Jackie Swanson]], who played the recurring role of Woody's girlfriend and eventual wife &quot;Kelly Gaines-Boyd&quot;, appeared in 24 episodes from 1989 to 1993. The character is as equally dim and naive—but ultimately as sweet-natured—as Woody.

[[Paul Willson]] played the recurring barfly character of &quot;Paul Krapence&quot;. (In one early appearance in the first season he was called &quot;Glen&quot;, and was later credited on-screen as &quot;Gregg&quot; and &quot;Tom&quot;, but he was playing the same character throughout.) [[Thomas Babson]] played &quot;Tom&quot;, a law student often mocked by [[Cliff Clavin]], for continually failing to pass the Massachusetts bar exam. &quot;Al&quot;, played by [[Al Rosen (actor)|Al Rosen]], appeared in 38 episodes, and was known for his surly quips. Rhea Perlman's father Philip Perlman played the role of &quot;Phil&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine|date=September 16, 1991|title=Cheers, Dad!|url=https://people.com/archive/cheers-dad-vol-36-no-10|magazine=People|accessdate=August 16, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Celebrity appearances===
Other celebrities guest-starred in single episodes as themselves throughout the series. Sports figures appeared on the show as themselves with a connection to Boston or Sam's former team, the Red Sox, such as [[Luis Tiant]], [[Wade Boggs]] and [[Kevin McHale (basketball)|Kevin McHale]] (of the [[Boston Celtics]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;nba&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nba.com/history/players/mchale_bio.html |title=Kevin McHale Bio |accessdate=December 20, 2009 |publisher=NBA }}&lt;/ref&gt; Some television stars also made guest appearances as themselves such as [[Alex Trebek]], [[Arsenio Hall]], [[Dick Cavett]], [[Robert Urich]], [[George &quot;Spanky&quot; McFarland]] and [[Johnny Carson]]. Various political figures even made appearances on ''Cheers'' such as then-[[Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff]] [[Admiral (United States)|Admiral]] [[William J. Crowe]], former [[Colorado]] [[United States Senate|Senator]] [[Gary Hart]], then-[[Speaker of the United States House of Representatives|Speaker of the House]] [[Tip O'Neill]], then-Senator [[John Kerry]], then-[[Governor of Massachusetts|Governor]] [[Michael Dukakis]], [[Ethel Kennedy]] (widow of [[Robert F. Kennedy]]), and then-[[Mayor of Boston]] [[Raymond Flynn]], the last five of whom all represented Cheers' home state and city.

In maternal roles, [[Glynis Johns]], in a guest appearance in 1983, played Diane's mother, Helen Chambers. [[Nancy Marchand]] played Frasier's mother, Hester Crane, in an episode that aired in 1985. In an episode that aired in 1992, [[Celeste Holm]] played Kelly's jokester of a paternal grandmother. [[Melendy Britt]] appeared in the episode &quot;''Woody or Won't He''&quot; (1990) as Kelly's mother, Roxanne Gaines, a very attractive high-society lady and a sexy, flirtatious upper-class cougar who tries to seduce Woody.

The musician [[Harry Connick Jr.]] appeared in an episode as Woody's cousin and plays a song from his Grammy-winning album ''[[We Are in Love]]'' ({{Circa|1991}}). [[John Cleese]] won a [[Primetime Emmy Award]] for his guest appearance as &quot;Dr. Simon Finch-Royce&quot; in the fifth-season episode, &quot;Simon Says&quot;. [[Emma Thompson]] guest-starred as [[Minor characters on Frasier|Nanny G/Nannette Guzman]], a famous singing nanny and Frasier's ex-wife. [[Christopher Lloyd]] guest-starred as a tortured artist who wanted to paint Diane. [[Marcia Cross]] portrayed Rebecca's sister Susan in the season 7 episode ''Sisterly Love''. [[John Mahoney]] once appeared as an inept jingle writer, which included a brief conversation with Frasier Crane, whose father he later portrayed on the spin-off ''Frasier''. [[Peri Gilpin]], who later played [[Roz Doyle]] on ''Frasier,'' also appeared in one episode of ''Cheers'', in its 11th season, as Holly Matheson, a reporter who interviews Woody. [[The Righteous Brothers]], [[Bobby Hatfield]] and [[Bill Medley]], also guest-starred in different episodes. In &quot;The Guy Can't Help It&quot; Rebecca, meets a plumber played by [[Tom Berenger]] who came to fix one of the beer keg taps. They marry in the series finale, triggering her resignation from Cheers.

Notable guest appearances of actresses portraying Sam's sexual conquests or potential sexual conquests include: [[Kate Mulgrew]] in the three-episode finale of season four, portraying Boston councilwoman Janet Eldridge; [[Donna McKechnie]] as Debra, Sam's ex-wife (with whom he is on good terms), who pretends to be an intellectual in front of Diane; [[Barbara Babcock]] as Lana Marshall, a talent agent who specializes in representing male athletes, her clients with whom she routinely sleeps on demand; [[Julia Duffy]] as Rebecca Prout, a depressed intellectual friend of Diane's; [[Alison LaPlaca]] as magazine reporter Paula Nelson; [[Carol Kane]] as Amanda, who Sam eventually learns was a fellow patient at the sanitarium with Diane; [[Barbara Feldon]] as Lauren Hudson, Sam's annual Valentine's Day fling (in an homage to ''[[Same Time, Next Year (play)|Same Time, Next Year]]''); [[Sandahl Bergman]] as Judy Marlowe, a longtime casual sex partner and whose now grown daughter, Laurie Marlowe ([[Chelsea Noble]]), who has always considered Sam a pseudo-father figure, Sam falls for; [[Madolyn Smith|Madolyn Smith-Osborne]] as Dr. Sheila Rydell, a colleague of Frasier and Lilith; [[Valerie Mahaffey]] as Valerie Hill, John Allen Hill's daughter who Sam pursues if only to gain an upper hand in his business relationship with Hill; and [[Alexis Smith]] as Alice Anne Volkman, Rebecca's much older ex-professor. In season 9, episode 17, ''I'm Getting My Act Together and Sticking It in Your Face'', Sam, believing Rebecca wants a more serious relationship, pretends to be gay, his lover being a casual friend named Leon ([[Jeff McCarthy]])—the plan ultimately leads to a kiss between Sam and Leon.

===Death of Nicholas Colasanto===
Near the end of production of the third season, the writers of ''Cheers'' had to deal with the death of one of the main actors. During the third season, [[Nicholas Colasanto]]'s heart condition (which had been diagnosed in the mid-1970s) had worsened. He had lost weight and was having trouble breathing during filming. Shortly before third season filming wrapped, Colasanto was hospitalized due to fluid in his lungs. Though he recovered, he was not cleared to return to work. While visiting the set in January 1985 to watch the filming of several episodes, co-star [[Shelley Long]] commented, &quot;I think we were all in denial. We were all glad he was there, but he lost a lot of weight.&quot; Co-star [[Rhea Perlman]] added, &quot;[He] wanted to be there so badly. He didn't want to be sick. He couldn't breathe well. It was hard. He was laboring all the time.&quot; Colasanto ultimately died of a [[heart attack]] at his home on February 12, 1985.&lt;ref name=showmust/&gt;

The third-season episodes of ''Cheers'' were filmed out of order, partly to accommodate the pregnancy of cast member Long. As a result, they already completed filming the season finale at the time of his death, which had scenes with Colasanto in it. In the third-season episodes that had not been filmed at this point, Coach is said to be &quot;away&quot; for various reasons.

The ''Cheers'' writing staff assembled in June 1985, at the start of the production of the fourth season, to discuss how to deal with the absence of Coach. They quickly discarded the idea that he might have moved away, as they felt he would never abandon his friends. In addition, as most viewers were aware of Colasanto's death, the writing staff decided to handle the situation more openly. The season four opener, &quot;Birth, Death, Love and Rice&quot;, dealt with Coach's death as well as introduced [[Woody Harrelson]], Colasanto's replacement.&lt;ref name=showmust&gt;{{cite book|title=The Show Must Go On: How the Deaths of Lead Actors Have Affected Television Series|author=Snauffer, Douglas|year=2008|isbn=978-0-7864-3295-0|publisher=McFarland|location=Jefferson, North Carolina}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.movpod.in/gp3w6smdjos9 |title=Birth, Death, Love and Rice|publisher=Movpod.in |date= |accessdate=September 13, 2012}}{{dead link|date=November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Episodes==
{{main|List of Cheers episodes}}
{{:List of Cheers episodes}}

==Themes==
Nearly all of ''Cheers'' took place in the front room of the bar, but the characters often went into the rear pool room or the bar's office.&lt;ref name=why&gt;{{cite news|title= Why 'Cheers' Looks Sharp Each Week |work=Chicago Tribune|url= http://articles.chicagotribune.com/1986-03-30/entertainment/8601230357_1_ted-danson-kiss-les-and-glen-charles|accessdate=October 30, 2010|date=March 30, 1986}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Cheers'' did not show any action outside the bar until the first episode of the second season, which took place in Diane's apartment.

The show's main [[Theme (narrative)|theme]] in its early seasons was the romance between intellectual waitress Diane Chambers and the bar's owner Sam Malone, a former [[Major League Baseball|major league]] [[Pitcher|baseball pitcher]] for the [[Boston Red Sox]] and a recovering [[alcoholic]].&lt;ref&gt;''Television Heaven'' (2002)(2006). [https://web.archive.org/web/20020826054040/http://www.televisionheaven.co.uk/cheers.htm ''Cheers''&amp;nbsp;– A Television Heaven Review]&lt;/ref&gt; After Shelley Long (Diane) left the show, the focus shifted to Sam's new relationship with [[Rebecca Howe]], a neurotic corporate-ladder climber.

Many ''Cheers'' scripts centered or touched upon a variety of [[social issues]], albeit humorously. As ''Toasting Cheers'' puts it, &quot;The script was further strengthened by the writers' boldness in successfully tackling controversial issues such as alcoholism, [[homosexuality]], and adultery.&quot;&lt;ref name=Bix&gt;Bjorklund, p. ix&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Social class]] was a subtext of the show. The &quot;upper class&quot;—represented by characters like Diane Chambers, [[Frasier Crane]] and [[Lilith Sternin]]—rubbed shoulders with middle- and working-class characters—Sam Malone, Carla Tortelli, Norm Peterson and Cliff Clavin. An extreme example of this was the relationship between Woody Boyd and a millionaire's daughter, [[List of recurring characters in Cheers|Kelly Gaines]]. Many viewers enjoyed ''Cheers'' in part because of this focus on character development in addition to plot development.&lt;ref name=&quot;chardevelop&quot;/&gt;

[[Feminism]] and the role of women were also recurring themes throughout the show, with some critics seeing each of the major female characters portraying an aspect as a flawed feminist in her own way.&lt;ref name=fem&gt;Dr. Caren Deming. &quot;Talk: Gender Discourse in ''Cheers''!&quot;, in ''Television Criticism: Approaches and Applications'' edited by Leah R. Vande Berg and Lawrence A Wenner. White Plains, NY: Longman, 1991. 47–57. The essay is co-authored by Mercilee M. Jenkins, who teaches at San Francisco State University.&lt;/ref&gt; Diane was a vocal feminist, and Sam was the epitome of everything she hated: a [[Promiscuity|womanizer]] and a [[Chauvinism|male chauvinist]]. (See &quot;[[Sam and Diane]]&quot;.)

Homosexuality was dealt with from the first season, which was rare in the early [[List of years in television|1980s on American television]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Becker|first=Ron|title=Gay TV And Straight America|url=https://archive.org/details/gaytvstraightame0000beck|url-access=registration|year=2006|publisher=Rutgers University Press|location=New Brunswick (N.J.)|isbn=978-0-8135-3689-7|page=[https://archive.org/details/gaytvstraightame0000beck/page/5 5]}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the first-season episode &quot;[[The Boys in the Bar]]&quot; (the title being a reference to the [[The Boys in the Band (play)|play]] and subsequent movie ''[[The Boys in the Band (1970 film)|The Boys in the Band]]''), a friend and former teammate of Sam's [[Coming out|comes out]] in his autobiography. Some of the male regulars pressure Sam to take action to ensure that Cheers does not become a [[gay bar]]. The episode won a [[GLAAD]] [[GLAAD Media Award|Media Award]], and the script's writers, [[Ken Levine (screenwriter)|Ken Levine]] and David Isaacs, were nominated for a [[Primetime Emmy Award]].

[[Substance use disorder|Addiction]] also plays a role in ''Cheers'', almost exclusively through Sam. He is a recovering [[alcoholic]] who had bought a bar during his drinking days. Frasier has a notable bout of drinking in the fourth-season episode &quot;The Triangle&quot;, while Woody develops a [[problem gambling|gambling]] problem in the seventh season's &quot;Call Me Irresponsible&quot;.

==Cheers owners==
[[File:Boston5808.JPG|thumb|The Cheers sign in 2005]]
Cheers had several owners before Sam, as the bar was opened in 1889. The &quot;Est. 1895&quot; on the bar's sign is a made-up date chosen by Carla for [[numerology|numerological]] purposes, revealed in season 8, episode 6, &quot;The Stork Brings a Crane&quot;, which also revealed the bar's address as 112{{Frac|1|2}} Beacon Street and that it originated under the name Mom's. In the series' second episode, &quot;Sam's Women&quot;, Coach tells a customer looking for Gus, the owner of Cheers, that Gus was dead. In a later episode, Gus O'Mally comes back from Arizona for one night and helps run the bar.

The biggest storyline surrounding the ownership of Cheers begins in the fifth-season finale, &quot;[[I Do, Adieu]]&quot;, when Sam and Diane part ways, due to Shelley Long's departure from the series. In addition, Sam leaves on a trip to [[Circumnavigation|sail around the world]]. Before he leaves, Sam sells Cheers to the Lillian Corporation. He returns in the sixth-season premiere, &quot;Home is the Sailor&quot;, having sunk his boat, to find the bar under the new management of Rebecca Howe. He begs for his job back and is hired by Rebecca as a bartender. In the seventh-season premiere, &quot;How to Recede in Business&quot;, Rebecca is fired and Sam is promoted to manager. Rebecca is allowed to keep a job at Lillian vaguely similar to what she had before, but only after Sam had Rebecca ([[wikt:in absentia|in absentia]]) &quot;agree&quot; to a long list of demands that the corporation had for her.

From there Sam occasionally attempted to buy the bar back with schemes that usually involved the wealthy executive [[Robin Colcord]]. Sam acquired Cheers again in the eighth-season finale, when it was sold back to him for 85¢ by the Lillian Corporation, after he alerted the company to Colcord's [[insider trading]]. Fired by the corporation because of her silence on the issue, Rebecca is hired by Sam as a hostess/office manager. For the rest of the episode, to celebrate Sam's reclaiming the bar, a huge banner hung from the staircase, reading &quot;Under OLD Management&quot;!

Sam had two main battles, one with Gary's Olde Towne Tavern, trying to beat them at some activity or another but always failing, extending to the practical jokes they played on each other. The second was with Melville's Owner John Hill who kept annoying Sam with his pettiness and ego. Hill had an ongoing relationship with Carla.

==Production==
[[File:Cheers Street Boston 2005.jpg|thumb|left|upright|The [[Cheers Beacon Hill]], formerly the Bull &amp; Finch Pub, in Boston in 2005]]

===Creation and concept===
Three men developed and created the ''Cheers'' television series: The [[Glen and Les Charles|Charles brothers]]—Glen and Les—and [[James Burrows]],&lt;ref name=Kerr_11_29_1983/&gt; who identified themselves as &quot;two Mormons and a Jew.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.yahoo.com/entertainment/cheers-co-creator-looks-back-series-finale-ted-dansons-decision-quit-caught-us-surprise-120020648.html|title='Cheers' co-creator looks back at series finale: 'Ted Danson's decision to quit caught us by surprise'|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; They aimed at &quot;creating a show around a [[Spencer Tracy]]-[[Katharine Hepburn]]-type relationship&quot; between their two main characters, [[Sam and Diane|Sam Malone and Diane Chambers]].&lt;ref name=Kerr_11_29_1983/&gt; Malone represents the average man, while Chambers represents class and sophistication.&lt;ref name=Kerr_11_29_1983/&gt; The show revolves around characters in a bar under &quot;humorous adult themes&quot; and &quot;situations.&quot;&lt;ref name=Kerr_11_29_1983/&gt;

The original idea was a group of workers who interacted like a family, the goal being a concept similar to ''[[The Mary Tyler Moore Show]]''. The creators considered making an American version of the British ''[[Fawlty Towers]],'' set in a hotel or an inn. When the creators settled on a bar as their setting, the show began to resemble the [[Radio programming|radio show]] ''[[Duffy's Tavern]],'' a program originally written and co-created by James Burrows' father [[Abe Burrows]]. They liked the idea of a [[tavern]], as it provided a continuous stream of new people, for a variety of characters.&lt;ref name=B3&gt;Bjorklund, p. 3.&lt;/ref&gt;

Early discussions about the location of the show centered on [[Barstow, California]], then [[Kansas City, Missouri]]. They eventually turned to the [[East Coast of the United States|East Coast]] and finally Boston. The [[Bull &amp; Finch Pub]] in Boston, which was the model for Cheers, was chosen from a [[phone book]].&lt;ref name=B4&gt;Bjorklund, p. 4.&lt;/ref&gt; When Glen Charles asked the bar's owner, Tom Kershaw, to shoot exterior and interior photos, he agreed, charging $1. Kershaw has since gone on to make millions of dollars, licensing the pub's image and selling a variety of ''Cheers'' memorabilia. The Bull &amp; Finch became the 42nd-busiest outlet in the American food and beverage industry in 1997.&lt;ref name=B3/&gt; During initial casting, Shelley Long, who was in Boston at the time filming ''[[A Small Circle of Friends]]'', remarked that the bar in the script resembled a bar she had come upon in the city, which turned out to be the Bull &amp; Finch.&lt;ref name=B7&gt;Bjorklund, p. 7.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Production team===
The crew of ''Cheers'' numbered in the hundreds. The three creators—[[James Burrows]] and [[Glen and Les Charles|the Charles brothers, Glen and Les]]—kept offices on Paramount's lot for the duration of the ''Cheers'' run. The Charles Brothers remained in overall charge throughout the show's run, frequently writing major episodes, though starting with the third season they began delegating the day-to-day running of the writing staff to various [[showrunner]]s. [[Ken Estin]] and [[Sam Simon]] were appointed as showrunners for the third season, and succeeded by [[David Angell]], [[Peter Casey (screenwriter)|Peter Casey]] and [[David Lee (screenwriter)|David Lee]] the following year. Angell, Casey and Lee would remain as showrunners until the end of the seventh season when they left to develop their own sitcom, ''[[Wings (1990 TV series)|Wings]]'', and were replaced by Cheri Eichen, Bill Steinkellner and [[Phoef Sutton]] for the eighth through tenth seasons. For the final season, Tom Anderson and [[Dan O'Shannon]] acted as the showrunners.

James Burrows is regarded as being a factor in the show's longevity, directing 243 of the 270 episodes and supervising the show's production.&lt;ref name=B2&gt;Bjorklund, p. 2.&lt;/ref&gt; Among the show's other directors were [[Andy Ackerman]], Thomas Lofaro, Tim Berry, [[Tom Moore (director)|Tom Moore]], Rick Beren, as well as cast members John Ratzenberger and George Wendt.&lt;ref name=&quot;chardevelop&quot;&gt;The Museum of Broadcast Communications (2006).&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Craig Safan]] provided the series' original music for its entire run except the theme song. His extensive compositions for the show led to his winning numerous [[ASCAP]] Top TV Series awards for his music.

===Casting===
The character of [[Sam Malone]] was originally intended to be a retired football player and was slated to be played by [[Fred Dryer]], but, after casting Ted Danson, it was decided that a former baseball player (Sam &quot;Mayday&quot; Malone) would be more believable.&lt;ref name=audition&gt;Meade, Peter. &quot;[https://news.google.com/newspapers?nid=SFOYbPikdlgC&amp;dat=19840427&amp;printsec=frontpage We'll Cry In Our Beers As Sam, Diane Split].&quot; ''[[Spartanburg Herald-Journal]] TV Update'' [Spartanburg, NC] April 29, 1984: 14. ''Google News''. Web. January 21, 2012. Editions of April 27–29, 1984, are inside the webpage. Article in ''Google News'' is located in page 85.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Balk, Quentin, and Ben Falk. ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=4L7pA2tKumsC&amp;lpg=PA166&amp;pg=PA166#v=onepage Television's Strangest Moments: Extraordinary but True Tales from the History of Television]''. London: Robson–Chrysalis, 2005. 166. ''Google Books''. Web. February 10, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; Dryer, however, would go on to play sportscaster Dave Richards, an old friend of Sam, in three episodes. The character of [[Cliff Clavin]] was created for John Ratzenberger after he auditioned for the role of [[Norm Peterson]], which eventually went to George Wendt. While chatting with producers afterward, he asked if they were going to include a &quot;bar know-it-all&quot;, the part which he eventually played.&lt;ref&gt;Newport Under the Stars (2005)(2006). [https://web.archive.org/web/20071114112730/http://newportunderthestars.com/newport/johnsbio.html John Ratzenberger's Newport Under the Stars]&lt;/ref&gt; Alley joined the cast when [[Shelley Long]] left, and Woody Harrelson joined when Nicholas Colasanto died. Danson, Perlman and Wendt were the only actors to appear in every episode of the series; Ratzenberger appears in all but one (and his name wasn't part of the opening credit montage during the first season).

===Filming styles and locations===
[[File:Cheers Beacon Hill interior 2.jpg|thumb|Interior of the bar]]
{{Quote box|width=25em|align=right|quote=&quot;On ''Cheers'', we never did everything twice. On ''Cheers'', we went through the scene and I only reshot jokes that didn't work or I went back and picked up shots I missed.&quot;|source=[[James Burrows]]&lt;ref name=Multicamera&gt;{{cite book|last=Jacobson|first=Mitch|title=Mastering multicamera techniques : from preproduction to editing and deliverables|year=2010|publisher=Focal Press/Elsevier|location=Amsterdam|isbn=978-0-240-81176-5|edition=1st}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Most ''Cheers'' episodes were, as a voiceover stated at the start of each, &quot;filmed before a live [[studio audience]]&quot; on Paramount Stage 25 in Hollywood, generally on Tuesday nights. Scripts for a new episode were issued the Wednesday before for a [[read-through]], Friday was [[rehearsal]] day, and final scripts were issued on Monday. Burrows, who directed most episodes, insisted on using [[film stock]] rather than [[videotape]]. He was also noted for using motion in his directorial style, trying to constantly keep characters moving rather than standing still.&lt;ref name=&quot;B7-8&quot;&gt;Bjorklund, p.&amp;nbsp;7–8.&lt;/ref&gt; During the first season when ratings were poor Paramount and NBC asked that the show use videotape to save money, but a poor test taping ended the experiment and ''Cheers'' continued to use film.&lt;ref name=&quot;levine20120318&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://kenlevine.blogspot.com/2012/03/another-thing-about-cheers-you-didnt.html | title=Another thing about CHEERS you didn't know | work=...by Ken Levine | date=March 18, 2012 | accessdate=March 18, 2012 | author=Levine, Ken}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Due to a decision by Glen and Les Charles, the [[cold open]] was often not connected to the rest of the episode, with the lowest-ranked writers assigned to create the jokes for them. Some cold opens were taken from episodes that ran too long.&lt;ref name=levine20110128&gt;{{cite news|last=Levine|first=Ken|title=My favorite CHEERS teaser|url=http://kenlevine.blogspot.com/2011/01/my-favorite-cheers-teaser.html|accessdate=January 28, 2011|newspaper=...by Ken Levine|date=January 28, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The first year of the show took place entirely within the confines of the bar, the first location outside the bar being Diane's apartment. When the series became a hit, the characters started venturing further afield, first to other sets and eventually to an occasional exterior location. The exterior location shots of the bar were of the Bull &amp; Finch Pub, located directly north of the [[Boston Public Garden]]. The pub has become a [[tourist attraction]] because of its association with the series, and draws nearly one million visitors annually.&lt;ref name=B3/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;synd1&quot;/&gt; It has since been renamed [[Cheers Beacon Hill]]; its interior is different from the TV bar. The pub itself is at 84 Beacon Street (on the corner of Brimmer Street). In August 2001, there was a replica made of the bar in [[Faneuil Hall]] to capitalize on the popularity of the show.

===Theme song===
Before &quot;[[Where Everybody Knows Your Name]]&quot;, written by [[Gary Portnoy]] and [[Judy Hart Angelo]], became the show's theme song, ''Cheers''{{'}} producers rejected two of Portnoy's and Hart Angelo's songs. The songwriters had collaborated to provide music for ''Preppies'', an unsuccessful Broadway musical. When told they could not appropriate &quot;People Like Us&quot;, ''Preppies''{{'}} opening song, the pair wrote another song &quot;My Kind of People&quot;, which resembled &quot;People Like Us&quot; and intended to satirize &quot;the lifestyle of old decadent old-money [[White Anglo-Saxon Protestant|WASPs]],&quot; but, to meet producers' demands, they rewrote the lyrics to be about &quot;likeable losers&quot; in a Boston bar. The show's producers rejected this song, as well. After they read the script of the series pilot, they created another song &quot;Another Day&quot;. When Portnoy and Hart Angelo heard that NBC had commissioned thirteen episodes, they created an official theme song &quot;Where Everybody Knows Your Name&quot; and rewrote the lyrics.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|archivedate=January 18, 2013|url=http://www.garyportnoy.com/|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130118024640/http://www.garyportnoy.com/ |work=GaryPortnoy.com|url-status=live|title=The Story Behind the Cheers Theme}} Click &quot;The Cheers Story&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; On syndicated airings of ''Cheers'', the theme song was shortened to make room for commercials.

==Reception==

===Critical reception===
''Cheers'' was critically acclaimed in its first season, though it landed a disappointing 74th out of 77 shows in that year's ratings.&lt;ref name=groove3&gt;{{cite web|last=Anscher|first=Matthew|title=Part III: Brandon at the Bat|url=http://www.tvparty.com/80nbc3.html|work=How NBC Got Its Groove Back|publisher=tvparty.com|accessdate=July 6, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; This critical support, the early success at the [[Primetime Emmy Award]]s, and the support of the president of NBC's entertainment division [[Brandon Tartikoff]], are thought to be the main reasons for the show's survival and eventual success.&lt;ref&gt;''Variety'' (May 20, 2003) (2006). [https://www.variety.com/review/VE1117921154?categoryid=1023&amp;cs=1 Review&amp;nbsp;– ''Cheers''] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121109013112/http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117921154?categoryid=1023&amp;cs=1 |date=November 9, 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Tartikoff stated in 1983 that ''Cheers'' was a sophisticated adult comedy and that NBC executives &quot;never for a second doubted&quot; that the show would be renewed.&lt;ref name=Kerr_11_29_1983/&gt; Writer Levine believes that the most important reason was that the network recognized that it did not have other hit shows to help promote ''Cheers''; as he later wrote, &quot;[NBC] had nothing else better to replace it with.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;levine20120406&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://kenlevine.blogspot.com/2012/04/how-to-find-writing-partner.html | title=How to find a writing partner | work=...by Ken Levine | date=April 6, 2012 | accessdate=April 6, 2012 | author=Levine, Ken}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2013, ''[[GQ]]'' magazine held an online competition to find the best TV comedy. ''Cheers'' was voted the greatest comedy show of all time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.gq.com/entertainment/movies-and-tv/201210/cheers-oral-history-extended?printable=true|title=Cheers: The Best TV Show That's Ever Been – GQ|author=Brian Raftery|work=GQ}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2017, James Charisma of ''[[Paste (magazine)|''Paste'']]'' magazine ranked the show's opening sequence No. 5 on a list of ''The 75 Best TV Title Sequences of All Time''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Paste&quot;&gt;{{cite magazine|author=Charisma, James|date=January 4, 2017|title=The 75 Best TV Title Sequences of All Time|url=https://www.pastemagazine.com/articles/2017/01/the-75-best-tv-title-sequences-of-all-time.html|magazine=[[Paste (magazine)|Paste]]|accessdate=January 16, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ratings===

Ratings improved for the summer reruns after the first season.&lt;ref name=&quot;gqraftery201210&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url=https://www.gq.com/entertainment/movies-and-tv/201210/cheers-oral-history-extended?printable=true | title=The Best TV Show That's Ever Been | work=GQ | date=October 2012 | accessdate=September 27, 2012 | author=Raftery, Brian}}&lt;/ref&gt; The cast went on various talk shows to try to further promote the series after its first season. By the second season ''Cheers'' was competitive with CBS's top-rated show ''[[Simon &amp; Simon]]''.&lt;ref name=Kerr_11_29_1983/&gt; With the growing popularity of ''[[Family Ties]]'', which ran in the slot ahead of ''Cheers'' from January 1984 until ''Family Ties'' was moved to Sundays in 1987, and the placement of ''[[The Cosby Show]]'' in front of both at the start of their third season (1984), the line-up became a runaway ratings success that NBC eventually dubbed &quot;[[Must See TV|Must See Thursday]]&quot;. The next season, ''Cheers'' ratings increased dramatically after Woody Boyd became a regular character as well. By the end of its final season, the show had a run of eight consecutive seasons in the top ten of the [[Nielsen ratings]]; seven of them were in the top five.&lt;ref name=B16&gt;Bjorklund, p. 16.&lt;/ref&gt;

NBC dedicated a whole night to the [[One for the Road (Cheers)|final episode of ''Cheers'']], following the [[The Pilot (Seinfeld)|one-hour season finale]] of ''[[Seinfeld]]'' (which was its lead-in). The show began with a &quot;pregame&quot; show hosted by [[Bob Costas]], followed by the final 98-minute episode itself. NBC affiliates then aired tributes to ''Cheers'' during their local newscasts, and the night concluded with a special ''[[The Tonight Show with Jay Leno|Tonight Show]]'' broadcast live from the Bull &amp; Finch Pub. Although the episode fell short of its hyped ratings predictions to become the [[List of most-watched television broadcasts|most-watched television episode]], it was the most watched show that year, bringing in 93.5&amp;nbsp;million viewers (64 percent of all viewers that night), and ranked 11th all time in entertainment programming. The 1993 final broadcast of ''Cheers'' also emerged as the highest rated broadcast of [[NBC]] to date, as well as the most watched single episode from any television series throughout the decade 1990s on U.S. television.&lt;ref name=NYT&gt;&quot;A Repeat of 'Cheers' Finale.&quot; ''[[The New York Times]]'' May 22, 1993. Web. January 7, 2012. &lt;https://www.nytimes.com/1993/05/22/arts/a-repeat-of-cheers-finale.html&gt;. &quot;One rating point equals 931,000 households.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Tampa Bay&quot;&gt;Stevenson, Jennifer L. &quot;Cheers LAST CALL! Series: ENTERTAINMENT.&quot; ''[[Tampa Bay Times]]'' May 20, 1993: 8B. Print. {{subscription required}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Newsday&gt;&quot;Tops on TV.&quot; ''[[Newsday]]'' [Long Island, NY] May 26, 1993, Nassau and Suffolk ed.: 58. Print. {{subscription required}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group=N&gt;The article, &quot;''Cheers'' Finale Most-Watched Show of Season,&quot; from May 22, 1993, edition of ''[[Rocky Mountain News]]'' said that the share of viewing audience was 62. The 2009 article, &quot;[http://articles.orlandosentinel.com/2009-02-01/entertainment/dvdtv0201_1_diane-chambers-shelley-long-rhea-perlman The gang gathers for one last round],&quot; by Hal Boedeker, claims that the finale drew over 80 million viewers in 1993.&lt;/ref&gt;

The episode originally aired in the usual ''Cheers'' spot of Thursday night, and was then rebroadcast on Sunday. While the original broadcast did not outperform the [[Goodbye, Farewell and Amen|''M*A*S*H'' finale]], the combined non-repeating audiences for the Thursday and Sunday showings did. Television had greatly changed between the two finales, leaving ''Cheers'' with a broader array of competition for ratings.&lt;ref name=B17&gt;Bjorklund, p. 17.&lt;/ref&gt;

NBC timeslots:
* Season 1 Episodes 1–12: Thursday at 9:00&amp;nbsp;pm
* Season 1 Episode 13 – Season 2 Episode 10: Thursday at 9:30&amp;nbsp;pm
* Season 2 Episode 11 – Season 11 Episode 28: Thursday at 9:00&amp;nbsp;pm

===Serialized storylines===

''Cheers'' was perhaps the first sitcom with a [[Serial (radio and television)|serialized storyline]],&lt;ref name=&quot;levine20121109&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://kenlevine.blogspot.com/2012/11/more-stuff-you-wanted-to-know.html | title=More stuff you wanted to know | work=...by Ken Levine | date=November 9, 2012 | accessdate=November 10, 2012 | author=Levine, Ken}}&lt;/ref&gt; starting with the third season. The show's success helped make such multi-episode story arcs popular on television, which Les Charles regrets.
&lt;blockquote&gt;[W]e may have been partly responsible for what's going on now, where if you miss the first episode or two, you are lost. You have to wait until you can get the whole thing on DVD and catch up with it. If that blood is on our hands, I feel kind of badly about it. It can be very frustrating.&quot;{{r|gqraftery201210}}&lt;/blockquote&gt;

''Cheers'' began with a limited five-character ensemble consisting of Ted Danson, Shelley Long, Rhea Perlman, Nicholas Colasanto and George Wendt. By the time season 10 began, the show had eight front characters in its roster. ''Cheers'' was also able to gradually phase in characters such as Cliff, Frasier, Lilith, Rebecca, and Woody.

===Awards and honors===
{{main list|List of awards and nominations received by Cheers}}
Over its eleven-season run, the ''Cheers'' cast and crew earned many awards. The show garnered a record 111 [[Primetime Emmy Award]] nominations, with a total of 28 wins. In addition, ''Cheers'' earned 31 [[Golden Globe Award|Golden Globe]] nominations, with a total of six wins. Danson, Long, Alley, Perlman, Wendt, Ratzenberger, Harrelson, Grammer, Neuwirth, and Colasanto all received Emmy nominations for their roles. ''Cheers'' won the [[Golden Globe Award]] for &quot;Best TV-Series&amp;nbsp;– Comedy/Musical&quot; in 1991 and the [[Primetime Emmy Award for Outstanding Comedy Series]] in 1983, 1984, 1989, and 1991. The series was presented with the &quot;Legend Award&quot; at the 2006 [[TV Land Award]]s, with many of the surviving cast members attending the event.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sitcomsonline.com/blog/2006/02/tv-land-honors-cheers-dallas-good.html &quot;TV Land Honors Cheers, Dallas, Good Times, and Batman&quot;] for SitcomsOnline on February 22, 2006. Retrieved March 21, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

The following are awards that have been earned by the ''Cheers'' cast and crew over its 11-season run:
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|+
! rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | Winner
! colspan=&quot;4&quot; | Award
|-
! Emmy
! Year
! Golden Globe
! Year
|-
| Kirstie Alley
| Outstanding Lead Actress in a Comedy Series
| 1991
| Best Performance by an Actress in a TV-Series&amp;nbsp;– Comedy/Musical
| 1991
|-
| Ted Danson
| Outstanding Lead Actor in a Comedy Series
| 1990 &lt;br/&gt; 1993
| Best Performance by an Actor in a TV-Series&amp;nbsp;– Comedy/Musical
| 1990 &lt;br/&gt; 1991
|-
| Woody Harrelson
| Outstanding Supporting Actor in a Comedy Series
| 1989
|colspan=&quot;2&quot; {{n/a}}
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot;| Shelley Long
| Outstanding Lead Actress in a Comedy Series
| 1983
| Best Performance by an Actress in a TV-Series&amp;nbsp;– Comedy/Musical
| 1985
|-
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; {{n/a}}
| Best Performance by an Actress in a Supporting Role in a Series, Mini-Series, or Motion Picture Made for TV
| 1983
|-
| Bebe Neuwirth
| Outstanding Supporting Actress in a Comedy Series
| 1990 &lt;br/&gt; 1991
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; rowspan=&quot;10&quot; {{n/a}}
|-
| Rhea Perlman
| Outstanding Supporting Actress in a Comedy Series
| 1984 &lt;br/&gt; 1985 &lt;br/&gt; 1986 &lt;br/&gt; 1989
|-
| John Cleese
| Outstanding Guest Actor in a Comedy Series
| 1987
|-
| rowspan=&quot;7&quot; | '''''Production Awards'''''
| Outstanding Directing in a Comedy Series
| 1983 &lt;br/&gt; 1991
|-
| Outstanding Writing in a Comedy Series
| 1983 1984
|-
| Outstanding Individual Achievement in Graphic Design and Title Sequences
| 1983
|-
| Outstanding Film Editing for a Series
| 1984
|-
| Outstanding Editing for a Series&amp;nbsp;– Multi-Camera Production
| 1988 &lt;br/&gt; 1993
|-
| Outstanding Live and Tape Sound Mixing and Sound Effects for a Series
| 1985
|-
| Outstanding Sound Mixing for a Comedy Series or Special
| 1986 &lt;br/&gt; 1987 &lt;br/&gt; 1990
|}

==Distribution==

===Syndication===
''Cheers'' grew in popularity as it aired on American television and entered into off-network syndication in 1987, initially distributed by [[Paramount Domestic Television]]. When the show went off the air in 1993, ''Cheers'' was syndicated in 38 countries with 179 American television markets and 83&amp;nbsp;million viewers.&lt;ref name=B18&gt;Bjorklund, p. 18.&lt;/ref&gt; When the quality of some earlier footage of ''Cheers'' began to deteriorate, it underwent a careful restoration in 2001 due to its continued success.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|accessdate=December 27, 2011|date=October 2001|work=Kodak|url=http://www.kodak.com/country/US/en/motion/newsletters/inCamera/oct2001/cheers.shtml|archive-url=https://archive.today/20120905211554/http://www.kodak.com/country/US/en/motion/newsletters/inCamera/oct2001/cheers.shtml|url-status=dead|archive-date=2012-09-05|title=Cheers restored for a new generation of laughs}}&lt;/ref&gt; The series aired on [[Nick at Nite]] from 2001 to 2004 and on [[TV Land]] from 2004 to 2008&lt;ref name=&quot;synd1&quot;&gt;International Real Estate Digest (August 20, 2001) (2006). [https://www.ired.com/news/2001/0108/cheers.htm Boston Gets a Hollywood ''Cheers'' Pub] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20060113032715/http://www.ired.com/news/2001/0108/cheers.htm |date=January 13, 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt; with Nick at Nite airing week long ''Cheers'' &quot;Everybody Knows Your Name&quot; marathons. The show was removed from the lineup in 2004.
The series began airing on [[Hallmark Channel]] in the United States in October 2008, and [[WGN America]] in 2009, where it continues to air on both channels. In January 2011, [[Reelz]] Channel began airing the series in hour-long blocks. [[MeTV]] began airing ''Cheers'' weeknights in 2010. More recently, [[USA Network]] is rerunning the series on Sunday early mornings and weekday mornings to allow it to show extended length films of 2½ hours and maintain symmetric schedules.

As of April 2011, [[Netflix]] began including ''Cheers'' as one of the titles on its &quot;watch instantly&quot; streaming service. [[Amazon (company)|Amazon]] added it to its Prime service in July.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://deadline.com/2011/07/cbs-licenses-2000-tv-episodes-to-amazon-streaming-service-148396/|title=CBS Licenses 2,000 TV Episodes To Amazon Streaming Service|author=David Lieberman|work=Deadline|date=2011-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A ''Cheers'' rerun notably replaced the September 4, 1992 airing of ''[[Australia's Naughtiest Home Videos]]'' on Australia's [[Nine Network]]. The latter was canceled mid-episode on its only broadcast by [[Kerry Packer]], who pulled the plug after a phone call. It was repeated several years later on Nine shortly after Packer's death in 2005. ''Cheers'' currently airs on [[10 Peach|Eleven]] (a digital channel of [[Network Ten]]) starting January 11, 2011 in Australia. When ''Cheers'' was aired by [[NCRV]] in the [[Netherlands]], they showed all 275 episodes in sequence, once per night, repeating the series a total of three times.

As of 2012, ''Cheers'' has been repeated on UK satellite channel [[CBS Drama]]. It is also shown on the UK free-to-air channel [[ITV4]], where it is shown two episodes every weeknight. Because of the ITV syndication it is also available to watch on the online ITV Player for seven days after broadcast. On March 16, 2015, the series began airing on UK subscription channel [[Gold (UK TV channel)|Gold]] on weekdays at 9:30&amp;nbsp;am and 10:00&amp;nbsp;am. ''Cheers'' then aired again in 2019 on [[Channel 4]], which had previously aired the sitcom in 2002.

It is also currently airing on [[Reelz]] Channel.

====High definition====
A high-definition transfer of ''Cheers'' began running on [[HDNet]] in the United States in August 2010. Originally shot on film (but transferred to and edited on videotape) the program was broadcast in a 4:3 [[Aspect ratio (image)|aspect ratio]], the newly transferred versions are in 16:9.{{original research inline|date=December 2011}} However, in the United Kingdom, the HD repeats on ITV4 HD, and later Channel 4 HD are shown in the original 4:3 aspect ratio.

===Home media===
[[Paramount Home Media Distribution|Paramount Home Entertainment]] and (from 2006 onward) [[CBS Home Entertainment]] have released all 11 seasons of ''Cheers'' on [[DVD-Video|DVD]] in Region 1, Region 2 and Region 4.
In the US, the last three seasons had music substitutions. In one example, for the episode &quot;Grease&quot;, &quot;I Fought the Law&quot; was replaced; its removal affected the comedic value of the scenes it was originally in. Along with that the original 73 minute long finale (without commercials) is presented in its 3 part syndicated cut with a total runtime of all three parts estimating 70 minutes.

On March 6, 2012, they released ''Fan Favorites: The Best of Cheers''. Based on the 2012 [[Facebook]] poll, the selected episodes are:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.dvdtalk.com/reviews/55524/fan-favorites-the-best-of-cheers/ |date=April 8, 2012 |title=Fan Favorites: The Best of Cheers |work=[[DVD Talk]] |last=Hartel |first=Nick }}&lt;/ref&gt;

# &quot;[[Give Me a Ring Sometime]]&quot; (season 1, episode 1)
# &quot;Diane's Perfect Date&quot; (season 1, episode 17)
# &quot;Pick a Con, Any Con&quot; (season 1, episode 19)
# &quot;Abnormal Psychology&quot; (season 5, episode 4)
# &quot;[[Thanksgiving Orphans]]&quot; (season 5, episode 9)
# &quot;Dinner at Eight-ish&quot; (season 5, episode 20)
# &quot;Simon Says&quot; (season 5, episode 21)
# &quot;An Old Fashioned Wedding&quot;, parts one and two (season 10, episodes 25)

On May 5, 2015, CBS DVD released ''Cheers - The Complete Series'' on DVD in Region 1.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://tvshowsondvd.com/news/Cheers-The-Complete-Series/20744|title=Cheers DVD news: Announcement for Cheers - The Complete Series - TVShowsOnDVD.com|work=tvshowsondvd.com|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150210025845/http://tvshowsondvd.com/news/Cheers-The-Complete-Series/20744|archivedate=February 10, 2015|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Digital media distribution===
The complete eleven seasons of ''Cheers'' are available through the United States [[Netflix]] streaming service, the [[iTunes]] Store, Amazon [[Prime Video]], and [[Hulu]]. In Canada all seasons are available on streaming service [[Crave TV]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cravetv.ca/show/32500|title=CraveTV|website=www.cravetv.ca}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Licensing==
The series lent itself naturally to the development of ''Cheers'' bar-related merchandise, culminating in the development of a chain of ''Cheers'' themed pubs. Paramount's licensing group, led by [[Tom McGrath (media executive)|Tom McGrath]], developed the ''Cheers'' pub concept initially in partnership with Host Marriott, which placed ''Cheers'' themed pubs in over 15 airports around the world.&lt;ref name=&quot;BF&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m3469/is_n31_v46/ai_17364989/|title=Host Marriot now has eight airport &quot;micro&quot; pubs, more on the way|date=July 31, 1995|publisher=Business Journals, Inc|accessdate=February 16, 2012}}{{dead link|date=November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Boston boasts the original ''Cheers'' bar, historically known to Boston insiders as the Bull and Finch, as well as a Cheers restaurant in the Faneuil Hall marketplace, and Sam's Place, a spin-off sports bar concept also located at Faneuil Hall. In 1997 Europe's first officially licensed ''Cheers'' bar opened in London's Regent's Street W1. Like Cheers Faneuil Hall, Cheers London is a replica of the set. The gala opening was attended by James Burrows and cast members George Wendt and John Ratzenberger.&lt;ref&gt;''USA Today'' (September 23, 1997).&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Cheers'' bar in London closed on 31 December 2008. The actual bar set had been on display at the Hollywood Entertainment Museum until the museum's closing in early 2006.&lt;ref&gt;Hollywood Entertainment Museum (2006). [http://www.seeing-stars.com/Museums/HollywoodEntertainment.shtml Hollywood Entertainment Museum] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20060329042637/http://www.seeing-stars.com/Museums/HollywoodEntertainment.shtml |date=March 29, 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The theme song to the show was eventually licensed to a Canadian restaurant, [[Kelseys Original Roadhouse|Kelsey's Neighbourhood Bar &amp; Grill]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release |url=http://www.newswire.ca/fr/story/310551/kelsey-s-launches-ad-campaign-with-cheers-tv-theme-song|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121014102951/http://www.newswire.ca/fr/story/310551/kelsey-s-launches-ad-campaign-with-cheers-tv-theme-song|url-status=dead|archive-date=October 14, 2012|title=Kelsey's Launches Ad Campaign with Cheers TV Theme Song |date=February 3, 2008|publisher=CNW|accessdate=August 16, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[CBS]] currently holds the rights to the ''Cheers'' franchise as the result of the 2006 [[Viacom (1952–2006)|Viacom]] split which saw Paramount transfer its entire television studio to CBS.

==Spin-offs, crossovers, and cultural references==
[[File:Cheers on the simpsons.jpg|thumb|Woody, Cliff, and Norm on ''The Simpsons'']]
Some of the actors and actresses from ''Cheers'' brought their characters into other television shows, either in a guest appearance or in a new spin-off series. The most successful ''Cheers'' spin-off was ''[[Frasier]]'', which featured Frasier Crane following his relocation back to [[Seattle]], [[Washington (state)|Washington]]. Sam, Diane, and Woody all individually appeared in ''Frasier'' episodes, with Lilith appearing as a guest on multiple episodes. In the [[Frasier (season 9)|season nine]] episode &quot;Cheerful Goodbyes&quot;, Frasier returns to Boston and meets up with the Cheers gang, later attending Cliff's retirement party.

Although ''[[Frasier]]'' was more successful, ''[[The Tortellis]]'' was the first series to spin off from ''Cheers'', premiering in 1987. The show featured Carla's ex-husband [[List of recurring characters in Cheers|Nick Tortelli and his wife Loretta]], but was canceled after 13 episodes and drew protests for its stereotypical depictions of Italian Americans.

In addition to direct spin-offs, several ''Cheers'' characters had guest appearance crossovers with other shows, including ''[[Wings (1990 TV series)|Wings]]'' and ''[[St. Elsewhere]]'' (episode &quot;[[St. Elsewhere#.22Cheers.22|Cheers]]&quot;). ''Cheers'' has also been spoofed or referenced in other media, including ''[[The Simpsons]]'' (spoofing the title sequence and theme song in &quot;[[Flaming Moe's]]&quot;; actually visiting the place with vocal role reprises of the majority of the principal cast in &quot;[[Fear of Flying (The Simpsons)|Fear of Flying]]&quot;), ''[[Scrubs (TV series)|Scrubs]]'' (episode &quot;My Life in Four Cameras&quot;), ''[[Adventure Time]]'' (episode &quot;[[Simon &amp; Marcy]]&quot;), the 2012 comedy film ''[[Ted (film)|Ted]]'', and the 2011 [[video game]] ''[[Dragon Age II]]''.

In one episode of ''[[Becker (TV series)|Becker]]'', Becker (Ted Danson), stops in at a bar, preferring to have a few drinks and get home in time to watch the Knicks game instead of attending his ex-wife's wedding in Connecticut. George Wendt is the bartender.

In the season 4 episode of ''[[Seinfeld]]'' entitled &quot;[[The Pitch (Seinfeld)|The Pitch]]&quot;, Jerry and George are presenting their idea for a sitcom to NBC executives. George is unhappy with their offer and feels that he deserves the same salary as Ted Danson which he claims was $800,000 per episode, being that ''Cheers'' is also an NBC show. Danson's reported salary was actually $250,000 per episode. At this point Cheers was in its 10th season and Ted Danson had won an Emmy and a Golden Globe the year before.

In the 2015 video game ''[[Fallout 4]]'', set in Boston, there is a bar named 'Prost Bar' near Boston Common which, when entered, is an almost exact replica of the bar used in the series. It includes two dead bodies sat at the end of the bar, with one of them wearing a mail carrier's uniform, a direct reference to regular barfly [[Cliff Clavin]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://kotaku.com/theres-a-pretty-great-cheers-easter-egg-in-fallout-4-1741952100 There's a Pretty Great Cheers Easter Egg in Fallout 4]&lt;/ref&gt;

The eighth anniversary special of ''[[Late Night with David Letterman]]'', airing in 1990, began with a scene at Cheers, in which the bar's TV gets stuck on NBC, and all of the bar patrons decide to go home instead of staying to watch [[David Letterman]]. The scene was re-used to open Letterman's final episode in 1993. A similar scene aired in the [[Super Bowl XVII]] Pregame Show on NBC, in which the characters briefly discuss the upcoming game.

In the second-season episode &quot;[[Swarley]]&quot; of the sitcom ''[[How I Met Your Mother]]'', in the final scene, [[Barney Stinson|Barney]] walks into the bar and everyone shouts &quot;Swarley,&quot; same as when the characters traditionally yelled &quot;Norm!&quot; whenever [[Norm Peterson]] entered the Cheers bar, and he turns and walks out dejectedly as Carl the bartender plays &quot;Where Everybody Knows Your Name.&quot; The camera angle also changes to show the same bar set-up and framing for the main interior bar shots featured in ''Cheers''. Additionally, the end credits are done in the gold &quot;Cooper Black&quot; font of the ''Cheers'' credits (which was a highly popular font for sitcoms of the early to mid-1980s).

The ''[[Star Trek: Deep Space Nine]]'' [[List of recurring Star Trek: Deep Space Nine characters#Morn|character Morn]] is named for Norm Peterson due to [[Armin Shimerman]] calling the originally nameless character &quot;Norm&quot; between takes.

The theatrical play ''Cheers: Live On Stage'' reenacts a condensed version of the first two seasons of the show.&lt;ref name=liveonstage&gt;[http://cheersliveonstage.com/ ''Cheers Live On Stage''] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160918161014/http://cheersliveonstage.com/ |date=September 18, 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

One episode of ''Cheers'' has a crossover reference to ''[[Spenser: For Hire]]'' (a Cheers bartender has a cameo appearance as an unspeaking extra).

In ''[[Guardians of the Galaxy Vol. 2]]'', [[Peter Quill]] makes numerous references to the show ''Cheers.''

In the [[The Good Place (season 2)|season 2 finale]] of the NBC sitcom ''[[The Good Place]]'', Ted Danson's character Michael appears as a bartender while wearing a blue plaid button-down, in a clear homage to Danson's character in ''Cheers''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.vulture.com/2018/02/the-good-place-season-2-finale-ted-danson-cheers.html|title=The Good Place Finally Gave Ted Danson His Cheers Moment|last=Ivie|first=Devon|work=Vulture|access-date=2018-02-02|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In ''[[A Night at the Roxbury]]'', [[Dan Hedaya]]'s character Kamehl Butabi and his friends are listening to Emily ([[Molly Shannon]]) play the piano. She was playing the song &quot;Where Everybody Knows Your Name&quot; which is clearly a reference to Hedaya's past as [[Nick Tortelli]] on ''Cheers''.

In 2019 members of the ''Cheers'' cast, Rhea Perlman, George Wendt, John Ratzenberger and Kirstie Alley reprised their characters in an episode of [[The Goldbergs (2013 TV series)|''The Goldbergs'']] where they play customers of Geoff's short-lived food delivery business.

==Remake==
In September 2011, Plural Entertainment debuted a remake of the series on [[Spain|Spanish]] television, also titled ''[[Cheers (Spanish TV series)|Cheers]]''. Set at an Irish pub, it starred [[Alberto San Juan]] as Nicolás &quot;Nico&quot; Arnedo, the equivalent of Sam Malone in the original series. It also used the original theme song, rerecorded in Spanish by [[Dani Martín]], under the title of &quot;[[Where Everybody Knows Your Name|Dónde la gente se divierte]].&quot;

In December 2012, The Irish Film and Television Network announced that casting was underway on an [[Irish-language]] version of ''Cheers'' produced by production company Sideline. The new show, tentatively titled ''Teach Seán'', would air on Ireland's TG4 and features a main character who, like Sam Malone, is a bar owner, a retired athlete and a recovering alcoholic. However, because of being set in Ireland, the barman is a &quot;former [[hurling]] star&quot; rather than an ex-baseball player.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://ew.com/article/2012/12/19/irish-cheers/|title= Irish TV channel to remake 'Cheers'|work=Entertainment Weekly}}&lt;/ref&gt; As of August 2019, the Irish remake has not occurred.

==''Cheers: Live On Stage''==
On September 9, 2016, a stage adaptation called, ''Cheers: Live On Stage'', opened at the [[Shubert Theatre (Boston)|Shubert Theatre]] in Boston. Comprising pieces of the original TV series, the play was adapted by Erik Forrest Jackson. It was produced by Troika/Stageworks. The director was Matt Lenz. It starred Grayson Powell as Sam Malone, Jillian Louis as Diane Chambers, [[Barry Pearl]] as Ernie 'Coach' Pantusso, Sarah Sirotta as Carla Tortelli, Paul Vogt as Norm Peterson, and Buzz Roddy as Cliff Clavin. The production was scheduled to tour through 2017, but was cancelled in 2016.&lt;ref name=liveonstage/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.stltoday.com/entertainment/arts-and-theatre/culture-club/cheers-live-on-stage-tour-is-canceled/article_e67d566f-9680-5d07-b358-d601dbcad5ff.html|title='Cheers Live On Stage' tour is canceled|last=Newmark|first=Judith|website=stltoday.com|language=en|access-date=2019-08-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=liveChicagoTribune/&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Television|United States}}
* ''[[Park Street Under]]'' (1979)
* ''[[Early Doors]]'' (2003)
{{-}}

==Notes==
{{reflist|group=N}}

==References==
{{reflist|30em|refs=
&lt;ref name=scott1982&gt;Scott, Vernon. &quot;[https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=HJFSAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=wNAMAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=6811%2C1282379 Series Producers Working Now to Get 'Cheers'].&quot; Telegraph Herald [Dubuque, IA] July 11, 1982: 20. Google News. Web. June 2, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=colasantodeath&gt;&quot;[https://www.nytimes.com/1985/02/14/arts/nick-colasanto-dead-at-61-played-bartender-in-cheers.html?scp=2&amp;sq=Nicholas%20Colasanto&amp;st=cse Nick Colasanto Dead at 61; Played Bartender in 'Cheers']&quot;. ''[[The New York Times]]'' February 14, 1985. Web. June 2, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=honey264&gt;Jones 1992, p. 264.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=10anniversary&gt;Ross, Jeremy. &quot;[https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=Hi1iAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=xHYNAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=2422%2C5715436 A toast to 'Cheers' on its anniversary].&quot; ''[[Observer-Reporter]]'' [Washington, PA] September 17, 1992. ''[[Google News]]''. Web. June 2, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=Kerr_11_29_1983&gt;{{cite news |last=Kerr |first=Peter |title=NBC Comedy 'Cheers' Turns into A Success |newspaper=The New York Times |url=https://www.nytimes.com/1983/11/29/arts/nbc-comedy-cheers-turns-into-a-success.html |date=November 29, 1983 |accessdate=October 31, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=liveChicagoTribune&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.chicagotribune.com/entertainment/theater/reviews/ct-cheers-live-review-ent-0923-20160922-column.html|title=Cheers: Live On Stage|work=Chicago Tribune}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

==Bibliography==
* {{cite book|year=1997|url=https://books.google.com/?id=hKbxOW2ONGEC&amp;pg=PA15&amp;lpg=PA15&amp;dq=cheers+ranked+77th|title = Toasting Cheers: An Episode Guide to the 1982–1993 Comedy Series, with cast biographies and character profiles|first= Dennis A.|last = Bjorklund | publisher=McFarland &amp; Company, Inc., Jefferson, North Carolina|isbn = 978-0-89950-962-4 }}
* {{cite book|author=Jones, Gerald|title=Honey, I'm Home! Sitcoms: Selling the American Dream|location=New York|publisher=[[Grove Weidenfeld]]—[[Grove Press]]|year=1992|isbn=978-0-8021-1308-5|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/honeyimhomesitco00jone}}
* {{cite book|authorlink=George Wendt|author=Wendt, George|year=2009|title=Drinking with George|location=New York|publisher=Simon Spotlight Entertainment|isbn=978-1-4391-4958-4|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/drinkingwithgeor00wend}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite book|last1=Andrews|first1=Bart|last2=Blythe|first2=Cheryl|title=Cheers : the official scrapbook|year=1987|publisher=[[New American Library]]|location=New York, N.Y.|isbn=978-0-451-82160-7|page=209}}
* {{cite news|last=Carter|first=Bill|title=The Tonic That Keeps 'Cheers' Bubbling Along|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1990/04/29/arts/television-the-tonic-that-keeps-cheers-bubbling-along.html|newspaper=[[The New York Times]]|date=April 29, 1990|page=6}}
* {{cite news|last=Carter|first=Bill|title=Why 'Cheers' Proved So Intoxicating|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1993/05/09/arts/television-why-cheers-proved-so-intoxicating.html|newspaper=[[The New York Times]]|date=May 9, 1993|page=6}}
* Darowski, Joseph J.; Darowski, Kate (2019) ''Cheers: A Cultural History''. Lanham, MD: Rowman &amp; Littlefield.
* {{cite journal|last=Fallows|first=Randall|title=The Enneagram of ''Cheers'': Where Everybody Knows Your Number|journal=[[The Journal of Popular Culture]]|date=September 1, 2000|volume=34|issue=2|pages=169–179|doi=10.1111/j.0022-3840.2000.3402_169.x}}
* {{cite journal|last=Hundley|first=Heather L.|title=The naturalization of beer in ''Cheers''|journal=Journal of Broadcasting &amp; Electronic Media|date=June 1, 1995|volume=39|issue=3|pages=350–359|doi=10.1080/08838159509364311}}
* {{cite web|title='Cheers' - the TV Series|url=http://www.h2g2.com/approved_entry/A1084619|work=[[h2g2]]|accessdate=December 27, 2011|date=July 4, 2003}}
* {{cite book|title=Encyclopedia of television|year=2005|publisher=[[Fitzroy Dearborn]]|location=New York|isbn=978-1-57958-394-1|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=CFXgj7a55agC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PA497#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|last=Bird|first=J.B.|edition=2nd|editor=Horace Newcomb|pages=497–499|chapter=Cheers}}
* Snauffer, Douglas (2008). ''The Show Must Go On: How the Deaths of Lead Actors Have Affected Television Series''. Jefferson, North Carolina: McFarland. {{ISBN|978-0-7864-3295-0}}.
* {{cite web|title=Cheers|url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/860764/Cheers|work=Encyclopædia Britannica|publisher=Encyclopædia Britannica Inc|accessdate=December 27, 2011}}
* {{cite book|title=St. James encyclopedia of popular culture.|url=https://archive.org/details/stjamesencyclope00tomp|url-access=registration|year=1999|publisher=[[St. James Press]]|location=Farmington Hills, MI|isbn=978-1-55862-400-9|edition=1st|editor=Tom Pendergast, Sara Pendergast|page=[https://archive.org/details/stjamesencyclope00tomp/page/488 488]}}

==External links==
{{Wikiquote}}
* {{Official website}}
* {{Commons category-inline|Cheers (television series)}}
* {{IMDb title|title=Cheers|id=0083399}}
* {{tv.com show|cheers|Cheers}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20151110034050/http://www.museum.tv/eotv/cheers.htm ''Cheers''] at [[Museum of Broadcast Communications]]
* [http://cheersboston.com/ Cheers Boston], an official website of a bar that tributes to and is also a production set of ''Cheers''

{{Cheers}}
{{Navboxes
|title = [[List of awards and nominations received by Cheers|Awards for ''Cheers'']]
|list =
{{EmmyAward ComedySeries 1976-2000}}
{{EmmyAward MainTitleDesign}}
{{GoldenGlobeTVComedy 1990-2009}}
{{People's Choice Award for Favorite New TV Comedy}}
{{TCA Heritage Award}}
}}
{{Frasier}}
{{TopUSTVShows}}

{{authority control}}

[[Category:Cheers| ]]
[[Category:1982 American television series debuts]]
[[Category:1993 American television series endings]]
[[Category:1980s American sitcoms]]
[[Category:1990s American sitcoms]]
[[Category:20th century in Boston]]
[[Category:Best Musical or Comedy Series Golden Globe winners]]
[[Category:Boston Red Sox]]
[[Category:Cultural history of Boston]]
[[Category:English-language television programs]]
[[Category:Fictional drinking establishments]]
[[Category:Alcohol abuse in television]]
[[Category:NBC original programming]]
[[Category:Nielsen ratings winners]]
[[Category:Primetime Emmy Award for Outstanding Comedy Series winners]]
[[Category:Primetime Emmy Award-winning television series]]
[[Category:Television series by CBS Television Studios]]
[[Category:Television shows set in Boston]]
[[Category:1980s American workplace comedy television series]]
[[Category:1990s American workplace comedy television series]]</text>
      <sha1>1gl89u02hcnea7a49puaqlhngmdecny</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
