  <page>
    <title>Church of England</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5955</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942678108</id>
      <parentid>941407680</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-26T04:08:31Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Pbritti</username>
        <id>33299132</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Overseas developments */Typos addressed</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|C of E||Council of Europe}}
{{short description|Anglican state church of England}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=February 2019}}
{{Use British English|date=August 2017}}
{{Infobox religion
| name                = Church of England
| image               = Logo of the Church of England.svg
| imagewidth          = 200px
| abbreviation        = C of E 
| main_classification = [[Anglican]]
| theology            = [[Anglican doctrine|Anglicanism]]
| orientation         = 
| polity              = [[Episcopal polity|Episcopal]]
| structure           = 
| leader_title        = [[Supreme Governor of the Church of England|Supreme Governor]]
| leader_name         = [[Queen Elizabeth II]]
| leader_title1       = [[Primates in the Anglican Communion|Primate]]
| leader_name1        = [[Archbishop of Canterbury|Archbishop]] [[Justin Welby]]
| area                = [[England]], [[Wales]] &lt;small&gt;(cross-border parishes)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[[Isle of Man]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Channel Islands]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Continental Europe]]
| headquarters        = [[Church House, Westminster]], [[England]], [[United Kingdom]]
| separated_from      = [[Catholic Church in England and Wales|Roman Catholic Church]]&lt;br /&gt;(1534)
| separations         = [[English Dissenters]]&lt;br /&gt;(1534 onwards)&lt;br /&gt;[[Puritans]] (16th century)&lt;br /&gt;[[Methodists]] (18th century)&lt;br /&gt;[[Plymouth Brethren]] (1820s)&lt;br /&gt;[[Free Church of England]] (1844)
| congregations       = 
| members             = 25 million&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Church of England|url=https://www.oikoumene.org/en/member-churches/church-of-england|website=oikoumene.org|publisher=World Council of Churches|accessdate=8 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.episcopalcafe.com/exactly-how-big-is-the-anglican-communion/|title=Exactly how big is the Anglican Communion?|date=13 November 2015|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| ministers           = 
| missionaries        =
| primary_schools     = 
| secondary_schools   = 
| tax_status          =
| tertiary            = 
| other_names         = ''Anglican Church''
| publications        = 
| website             = [http://www.churchofengland.org/ churchofengland.org]
| footnotes           = 
| associations        = [[Anglican Communion]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Porvoo Communion]]&lt;br/&gt;[[World Council of Churches]]&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.oikoumene.org/en/member-churches/church-of-england Church of England] at World Council of Churches&lt;/ref&gt;}}
{{Anglicanism}}

The '''Church of England''' ('''C of E''') is the [[State religion#Protestantism|established church]] of [[England]].&lt;ref name=Eberle&gt;{{cite book|title=Church and State in Western Society|first=Edward J.|last=Eberle|publisher=[[Ashgate Publishing, Ltd.]]|year=2011|isbn=978-1-4094-0792-8|page=2|accessdate=9 November 2012|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=oYkzkVc_sG0C&amp;pg=PA2&amp;dq=%22church%20of%20england%22%20official%20state%20religion#v=onepage|quote=The Church of England later became the official state Protestant church, with the monarch supervising church functions.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Fox&gt;{{cite book|title=A World Survey of Religion and the State|first=Jonathan|last=Fox|publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]]|year=2008|isbn=978-0-521-88131-9|page=120|accessdate=9 November 2012|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=rE0NcgxNaKEC&amp;pg=PA120&amp;dq=%22church%20of%20england%22%20official%20state%20religion#v=onepage|quote=The Church of England (Anglican) and the Church of Scotland (Presbyterian) are the official religions of the UK.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Ferrante&gt;{{cite book|title=Sociology: A Global Perspective|first=Joan|last=Ferrante|publisher=[[Cengage Learning]]|year=2010|isbn=978-0-8400-3204-1|page=408|accessdate=9 November 2012|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=AwnIIXI6y38C&amp;pg=PA408&amp;dq=%22church%20of%20england%22%20official%20state%20religion#v=onepage&amp;q=%22church%20of%20england%22%20official%20state%20religion|quote=the Church of England [Anglican], which remains the official state church}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Archbishop of Canterbury]] is the most senior cleric, although the [[Monarchy of the United Kingdom|monarch]] is the [[Supreme Governor of the Church of England|supreme governor]]. The Church of England is also the [[mother church]] of the international [[Anglican Communion]]. It traces its history to the Christian church recorded as existing in the Roman province of Britain by the third century, and to the 6th-century [[Gregorian mission]] to [[Kingdom of Kent|Kent]] led by [[Augustine of Canterbury]].&lt;ref name='DetailedHistory' /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |authors=John E. Booty, Stephen Sykes, Jonathan Knight |title=Study of Anglicanism|edition= |publisher=Fortress Books |location= London|year=1998 | isbn = 0-281-05175-5 |page= 477}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Delaney, John P. |title=Dictionary of Saints |edition=Second |publisher=Doubleday |location=Garden City, NY |year=1980 |isbn=978-0-385-13594-8 |pages=[https://archive.org/details/dictionaryofsain00dela/page/67 67–68] |url-access=registration |url=https://archive.org/details/dictionaryofsain00dela/page/67 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The English church renounced [[papal]] authority when [[Henry VIII of England|Henry&amp;nbsp;VIII]] failed to secure an [[annulment]] of his marriage to [[Catherine of Aragon]] in 1534.&lt;ref name=&quot;KH8-RC-00&quot;/&gt; The [[English Reformation]] accelerated under [[Edward VI of England|Edward&amp;nbsp;VI]]'s regents, before a brief [[Second Statute of Repeal|restoration of papal authority]] under [[Mary I of England|Queen Mary I]] and [[Philip II of Spain|King Philip]]. The [[Act of Supremacy 1558]] renewed the breach, and the [[Elizabethan Settlement]] charted a course enabling the English church to describe itself as both catholic and reformed:
* ''Catholic'' in that it views itself as a part of the universal church of [[Jesus Christ]] in unbroken continuity with the early [[Apostolic Age|apostolic]] church. This is expressed in its emphasis on the teachings of the early [[Church Fathers]], as formalised in the [[Apostles' Creed|Apostles']], [[Nicene Creed|Nicene]], and [[Athanasian Creed|Athanasian]] creeds.&lt;ref name=&quot;cofeCanons&quot;&gt;{{Citation|title=Canons of the Church of England|url=https://www.churchofengland.org/more/policy-and-thinking/canons-church-england/section-a#b5| edition = 7| chapter =Section A: The Church of England| chapter-url = https://www.churchofengland.org/more/policy-and-thinking/canons-church-england/section-a |publisher=Church of England|accessdate=1 February 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
* ''Reformed'' in that it has been shaped by some of the doctrinal principles of the 16th-century [[Protestant Reformation]], in particular in the [[Thirty-Nine Articles of Religion]] and the [[Book of Common Prayer]].&lt;ref name=&quot;cofeCanons&quot;/&gt;

In the earlier phase of the [[English Reformation]] there were both [[List of Catholic martyrs of the English Reformation|Catholic martyrs]] and [[List of Protestant martyrs of the English Reformation|radical Protestant]] martyrs. The later phases saw the [[English Penal Laws|Penal Laws]] punish Roman Catholic and [[Nonconformist (Protestantism)|nonconforming Protestants]]. In the 17th century, the [[Puritan]] and [[Presbyterian]] factions continued to challenge the leadership of the Church which under the Stuarts veered towards a more catholic interpretation of the Elizabethan Settlement especially under Archbishop Laud and the rise of the concept of Anglicanism as the [[via media]]. After the victory of the Parliamentarians the Prayer Book was abolished and the Presbyterian and Independent factions dominated. The Episcopacy was abolished. The [[Restoration (1660)|Restoration]] restored the Church of England, episcopacy and the Prayer Book. Papal recognition of [[George III of England|George&amp;nbsp;III]] in 1766 led to greater religious tolerance.

Since the English Reformation, the Church of England has used a [[liturgy]] in English. The church contains several doctrinal strands, the main three known as [[Anglo-Catholic]], [[evangelical Anglicanism|evangelical]], and [[broad church]]. Tensions between theological conservatives and progressives find expression in debates over the [[ordination of women in the Anglican Communion|ordination of women]] and [[homosexuality and Anglicanism|homosexuality]]. The church includes both [[liberal Christianity|liberal]] and conservative clergy and members.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2014/jul/13/church-of-england-power-shifts-laity-liberalism|title=Liberalism increases as power shifts to the laity in the Church of England|last=Brown|first=Andrew|date=13 July 2014|newspaper=The Guardian|language=en-GB|issn=0261-3077|access-date=1 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The governing structure of the church is based on [[diocese]]s, each presided over by a bishop. Within each diocese are local parishes. The [[General Synod of the Church of England]] is the legislative body for the church and comprises bishops, other clergy and [[laity]]. Its measures must be approved by both [[Parliament of the United Kingdom|Houses of Parliament]].

==History==
{{Main|History of the Church of England}}

===Early Christianity in England===
{{Main|History of Christianity in England|Anglo-Saxon Christianity}}
According to tradition, Christianity arrived in Britain in the [[Christianity in the 1st century|1st]] or [[Christianity in the 2nd century|2nd century]], during which time southern Britain became part of the [[Roman Empire]]. The earliest historical evidence of Christianity among the native [[Britons (historical)|Britons]] is found in the writings of such early Christian Fathers as [[Tertullian]] and [[Origen]] in the first years of the [[Christianity in the 3rd century|3rd century]]. Three [[Romano-British]] bishops, including [[Restitutus]], are known to have been present at the [[Council of Arles (314)|Council of Arles in 314]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Rahner|first=Karl|title=Encyclopedia of theology: a concise Sacramentum mundi|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=WtnR-6_PlJAC&amp;pg=PA301|year=1975|publisher=Herder|location=Freiburg|isbn=978-0-86012-006-3|pages=301–302}}&lt;/ref&gt; Others attended the [[Council of Serdica]] in 347 and that of [[Council of Ariminum|Ariminum]] in 360, and a number of references to the church in [[Roman Britain]] are found in the writings of [[Christianity in the 4th century|4th century]] Christian fathers. Britain was the home of [[Pelagius]], who opposed [[Augustine of Hippo]]'s doctrine of [[original sin]].&lt;ref&gt;Paula K. Byers; 1998, ''Encyclopedia of World Biography'', Page 189 – Pelagius, {{ISBN|0-7876-2553-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While Christianity was long established as the religion of the Britons at the time of the [[Anglo-Saxon invasion of Britain|Anglo-Saxon invasion]], Christian Britons made little progress in converting the newcomers from their [[Anglo-Saxon paganism|native paganism]]. Consequently, in 597, [[Pope Gregory I]] sent the [[prior]] of the [[San Gregorio Magno al Celio|Abbey of St Andrew's]] (later canonised as [[Augustine of Canterbury]]) from Rome to evangelise the [[Angles]]. This event is known as the [[Gregorian mission]] and is the date the Church of England generally marks as the beginning of its formal history. With the help of Christians already residing in [[Kingdom of Kent|Kent]], Augustine established his church at [[Canterbury]], the capital of the [[Kingdom of Kent]], and became the first in the series of [[Archbishops of Canterbury]] in 598. A later archbishop, the Greek [[Theodore of Tarsus]], also contributed to the organisation of Christianity in England. The Church of England has been in continuous existence since the days of St Augustine, with the Archbishop of Canterbury as its episcopal head. Despite the various disruptions of the Reformation and the [[English Civil War]], the Church of England considers itself to be the same church which was more formally organised by Augustine.&lt;ref name='DetailedHistory'&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.churchofengland.org/about-us/history/detailed-history.aspx |title=An Ancient Church - Detailed History |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |date=2016 |website= |publisher=Church of England |access-date=24 October 2016 |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While some Celtic Christian practices were changed at the [[Synod of Whitby]], the Christian in the British Isles was under papal authority from earliest times.&lt;ref&gt;Marcus Holden and Andrew Pinsent, ''The Catholic Gift to Civilisation'' (London: CTS), p. 13ff&lt;/ref&gt;  Queen [[Bertha of Kent]] was among the Christians in England who recognised papal authority before Augustine arrived,&lt;ref&gt;D. Attwater, &quot;Ethelbert of Kent&quot; in ''The Penguin Dictionary of Saints'' (Harmondsworth: Penguin Books), p.118&lt;/ref&gt; and Celtic Christians were carrying out missionary work with papal approval long before the Synod of Whitby.

[[File:Hereford Cathedral Interior May 2004.jpg|right|thumb|[[Hereford Cathedral|Hereford]] is one of the church's 43 cathedrals; many have histories stretching back centuries.]]
The Synod of Whitby established the Roman date for Easter and the Roman style of monastic tonsure in England. This meeting of the ecclesiastics with Roman customs with local bishops was summoned in 664 at Saint Hilda's double monastery of Streonshalh (Streanæshalch), later called [[Whitby Abbey]]. It was presided over by [[Oswiu|King Oswiu]], who did not engage in the debate but made the final ruling. The final ruling was decided in favor of Roman tradition because St. Peter holds the keys to the gate of Heaven.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.britannica.com/event/Synod-of-Whitby|title=Synod of Whitby &amp;#124; English Church history|website=Encyclopedia Britannica}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Separation from Rome===
{{Main|English Reformation}}
In 1534, [[Henry VIII of England|King Henry VIII]] separated the English Church from Rome.&lt;ref name=&quot;KH8-RC-00&quot;&gt;[https://www.bbc.co.uk/history/british/tudors/english_reformation_01.shtml The English Reformation by Professor Andrew Pettegree]. Bbc.co.uk.&lt;/ref&gt; A theological separation had been foreshadowed by various movements within the English Church, such as [[Lollardy]], but the English Reformation gained political support when Henry VIII wanted an [[annulment]] of his marriage to [[Catherine of Aragon]] so he could marry [[Anne Boleyn]]. [[Pope Clement VII]], considering that the earlier marriage had been entered under a [[Dispensation (canon law)|papal dispensation]] and how Catherine's nephew, [[Charles V, Holy Roman Emperor|Emperor Charles V]], might react to such a move, refused the annulment. Eventually, Henry, although theologically opposed to Protestantism, took the position of [[Supreme Governor of the Church of England|Protector and Supreme Head of the English Church and Clergy]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite EB1911 |wstitle=England, The Church of |volume=9 |page=448 |first=William |last=Hunt}}&lt;/ref&gt; to ensure the annulment of his marriage. He was [[excommunicated]] by [[Pope Paul III]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.historymole.com/cgi-bin/main/results.pl?theme=10026153 King Henry VIII (1491–1547)]. HistoryMole (18 September 2010).&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1536–40 Henry VIII engaged in the [[Dissolution of the Monasteries]], which controlled much of the richest land. He disbanded [[monastery|monasteries]], [[priory|priories]], [[convent]]s and [[friary|friaries]] in England, Wales and Ireland, appropriated their income, disposed of their assets, and provided pensions for the former residents. The properties were sold to pay for the wars.  Bernard argues:
:The dissolution of the monasteries in the late 1530s was one of the most revolutionary events in English history. There were nearly 900 religious houses in England, around 260 for monks, 300 for regular canons, 142 nunneries and 183 friaries; some 12,000 people in total, 4,000 monks, 3,000 canons, 3,000 friars and 2,000 nuns....one adult man in fifty was in religious orders.&lt;ref&gt;G. W. Bernard, &quot;The Dissolution of the Monasteries,&quot; ''History'' (2011) 96#324 p 390&lt;/ref&gt;

Henry maintained a strong preference for traditional Catholic practices and, during his reign, Protestant reformers were unable to make many changes to the practices of the Church of England. Indeed, this part of Henry's reign saw trials for heresy of Protestants as well as Roman Catholics.

Under his son, [[Edward VI of England|King Edward VI]], more Protestant-influenced forms of worship were adopted. Under the leadership of the Archbishop of Canterbury, [[Thomas Cranmer]], a more radical reformation proceeded. A new pattern of worship was set out in the [[Book of Common Prayer]] (1549 and 1552). These were based on the older liturgy in particular the Prayer Book of 1549, but both influenced by Protestant doctrines such as justification by faith alone, the rejection of the sacrifice of the Mass, and the Real Presence understood as physical presence (Cranmer was Calvinist in that he believed Christ was truly and really present in the Eucharist but after a spiritual manner, although the Words of Administration at the time of Communion were a straightforward statement in the Real Presence as taken from the 1549 BCP and attached to the 1559 book). The confession of the reformed Church of England was set out in the [[Forty-two Articles]] (later revised to thirty-nine). The reformation however was cut short by the death of the king. [[Mary I of England|Queen Mary I]], who succeeded him, returned England again to the authority of the papacy, thereby ending the first attempt at an independent Church of England. During her co-reign with her husband, [[Philip II of Spain|King Philip]], many leaders and common people were burnt for their refusal to recant of their reformed faith. These are known as the [[Marian martyrs]] and the persecution led to her nickname of &quot;Bloody Mary&quot;.

[[File:Rochester cathedral stained glass 2.jpg|left|thumb|Stained glass window in [[Rochester Cathedral]], Kent]]
Mary also died childless and so it was left to the new regime of her half-sister Elizabeth to resolve the direction of the church. The settlement under [[Elizabeth I of England|Queen Elizabeth I]] (from 1558), known as the [[Elizabethan Settlement]], tried to find a middle way between radical Protestantism and Roman Catholicism, the ''via media'' (a term that actually only became current in the 1620s), as the character of the Church of England, a church moderately Reformed in doctrine, as expressed in the [[Thirty-Nine Articles]], but also emphasising continuity with the Catholic and Apostolic traditions of the [[Church Fathers]]. Kneeling reverently to receive communion was the custom. The three-fold ministry in the  Apostolic Succession was maintained; the institutional continuity of the Church was preserved without break (at her accession almost all clergy had been ordained in Catholic Orders using the Roman Pontifical) by consecration of bishops in Catholics Orders, although the character of the organization was changed by the adoption of some reformed doctrines, the simplification of the outwards forms of worship and the abandonment of traditional vestments and art work; the retention of medieval Canon Law, liturgical music and a much shortened Calendar of Saints and Feast Days. It was a most peculiar situation: the same organization but with a modified face to the world without much particular character of its own until the notion of Anglicanism as a distinct variety of Christianity emerged very late in her reign and during the reigns of the early Stuart Kings.  It was also an [[established church]] (constitutionally established by the state with the Head of State as its [[Supreme Governor of the Church of England|supreme governor]]).  The exact nature of the relationship between church and state would be a source of continued friction into the next century.

===Stuart period===
{{further|Stuart period}}
{{Refimprove section|date=January 2020}}
For the next century, through the reigns of [[James VI and I|James I]], who ordered the translation of the Bible known as the King James Version (authorized to be used in parishes which does not mean it was the official version),&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=tC1kuaetNqoC&amp;dq=The+Diary+Of+Samuel+Ward,+A+Translator+Of+The+1611+King+James+Bible%E2%80%8E The Diary Of Samuel Ward: A Translator Of The 1611 King James Bible], edited by [[John Wilson Cowart]] and M. M. Knappen&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Charles I of England|Charles I]], culminating in the [[English Civil War]] and the Protectorate of [[Oliver Cromwell]], there were significant swings back and forth between two factions: the [[Puritans]] (and other radicals) who sought more far-reaching Protestant reforms, and the more conservative churchmen who aimed to keep closer to traditional beliefs and Catholic practices. The failure of political and ecclesiastical authorities to submit to Puritan demands for more extensive reform was one of the causes of open warfare. By Continental standards the level of violence over religion was not high, since the Civil War was mainly about politics, but the casualties included King Charles I and the Archbishop of Canterbury, [[William Laud]] and tens of thousands of civilians who died from the unsettled conditions. Under the Commonwealth and the Protectorate of England from 1649 to 1660, the bishops were dethroned and former practices were outlawed, and [[Presbyterian polity|Presbyterian]] ecclesiology was introduced in place of the episcopate. The 39 Articles were replaced by the [[Westminster Confession]], the Book of Common Prayer by the Directory of Public Worship. Despite this, about one quarter of English clergy refused to conform to this form of State Presbyterianism.

[[File:CANTEBURY ALTAR HORIZONTAL 7424.jpg|thumb|Major repairs were done to Canterbury Cathedral after the Restoration in 1660.]]

With the Restoration of Charles II, Parliament restored the Church of England to a form not far removed from the Elizabethan version. One difference was that the ideal of encompassing all the people of England in one religious organisation, taken for granted by the Tudors, had to be abandoned. The religious landscape of England assumed its present form, with the Anglican established church occupying the middle ground, and those Puritans and Protestants who [[English Dissenters|dissented]] from the Anglican establishment having to continue their existence outside the national church rather than trying to influence or trying to gain control of it. One result of the Restoration was the ousting of 2,000 parish ministers who had not been ordained by bishops in the Apostolic Succession or who had been ordained by ministers in presbyter's orders. Official suspicion and legal restrictions continued well into the 19th century. Roman Catholics, perhaps 5% of the English population (down from 20% in 1600) were grudgingly tolerated, having had little or no official representation after the Pope's excommunication of Queen Elizabeth in 1570, though the Stuarts were sympathetic to them. By the end of 18th century they had dwindled to 1% of the population mostly among eccentric upper middle-class gentry and their tenants and extended families.

===Union with Church of Ireland===
By the Fifth Article of the [[Acts of Union 1800|Union with Ireland 1800]], the Church of England and [[Church of Ireland]] were united into &quot;one Protestant Episcopal church, to be called, the United Church of England and Ireland&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Pickering |first1=Danby |title=The Statutes at Large from the Magna Charta, to the End of the Eleventh Parliament of Great Britain, Anno 1761 [continued to 1806]. By Danby Pickering |date=1799 |publisher=J. Bentham |page=653 |url=https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=R1pRAQAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA653 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although this union was declared &quot;an essential and fundamental Part of the Union&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.rahbarnes.co.uk/Union/ActOfUnion%28Ireland%29.php | title=An Act for the Union of Great Britain and Ireland 1800 – Article Fifth (sic) | url-status=dead | archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20180324152426/http://www.rahbarnes.co.uk/Union/ActOfUnion(Ireland).php | archivedate=24 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; the [[Irish Church Act 1869]] separated the Irish part of the church again and disestablished it, the Act coming into effect on 1 January 1871.

===Overseas developments===
[[File:John Smith 1624 map of Bermuda with Forts 01.jpg|thumb|right|upright=0.9|Captain [[John Smith of Jamestown|John Smith's]] 1624 map of Bermuda, showing St Peter's at centre, left]]
{{main|Anglican Communion}}
{{further|Historical development of Church of England dioceses#Colonial dioceses}}
As the [[British Empire]] expanded, British colonists and colonial administrators took the established church doctrines and practices together with ordained ministry and formed overseas branches of the Church of England. As they developed or, beginning with the United States of America, became sovereign or independent states, many of their churches became separate organisationally but remained linked to the Church of England through the [[Anglican Communion]].  In the provinces that made up Canada, the Church operated as the &quot;Church of England in Canada&quot; until 1955 when it became the [[Anglican Church of Canada]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Miranda Threlfall-Holmes|title=The Essential History of Christianity|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=hGipAwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT133|year=2012|publisher=SPCK|pages=133–34}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Bermuda, the oldest remaining English colony (now designated a [[British Overseas Territory]]), the first Church of England services were performed by the Reverend Richard Buck, one of the survivors of the 1609 wreck of the ''[[Sea Venture]]'' which initiated Bermuda's permanent settlement. The nine parishes of the Church of England in [[Bermuda]], each with its own church and [[Glebe|glebe land]], rarely had more than a pair of ordained ministers to share between them until the Nineteenth Century. From 1825 to 1839, Bermuda's parishes were attached to the [[Diocese of Nova Scotia and Prince Edward Island|See of Nova Scotia]]. Bermuda was then grouped into the new Diocese of Newfoundland and Bermuda from 1839. In 1879, the Synod of the Church of England in Bermuda was formed. At the same time, a Diocese of Bermuda became separate from the [[Diocese of Newfoundland]], but both continued to be grouped under the ''Bishop of Newfoundland and Bermuda'' until 1919, when Newfoundland and Bermuda each received its own Bishop.

The Church of England in Bermuda was renamed in 1978 as the [[Anglican Church of Bermuda]], which is an [[Extra-provincial Anglican churches|extra-provincial diocese]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.anglicancommunion.org/tour/index.cfm|title=Member Churches|work=anglicancommunion.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; with both [[Metropolitan bishop|metropolitan]] and [[Primate (bishop)|primatial]] authority coming directly from the Archbishop of Canterbury. Among its parish churches is [[St. Peter's Church, St. George's|St Peter's Church]] in the [[UNESCO World Heritage Site]] of [[St. George's, Bermuda|St George's Town]], which is both the oldest Anglican and the oldest non-Roman Catholic church in the New World.

The first Anglican missionaries arrived Nigeria in 1842. The first Anglican Nigerian was consecrated a bishop in 1864. However, the arrival of a rival group of Anglican missionaries in 1887 led to infighting that slowed the growth. In this large African colony by 1900 there were only 35,000 Anglicans, about 1/5 of one percent of the population. However, in the late 20th century the [[Church of Nigeria]] became the fastest growing of all the Anglican churches, reaching about 18 percent of the local population by 2000.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Miranda Threlfall-Holmes|title=The Essential History of Christianity|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=hGipAwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT133|year=2012|publisher=SPCK|page=134}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===21st century===

====Deposition from holy orders overturned====

Under the guidance of [[Rowan Williams]] and with significant pressure from clergy union representatives, the ecclesiastical penalty for convicted felons to be defrocked was set aside from the [[List of Church of England Measures|Clergy Discipline Measure 2003]].  The clergy union argued that the penalty was unfair to victims of hypothetical miscarriages of criminal justice, because the ecclesiastical penalty is considered irreversible. Although clerics can still be banned for life from ministry, they remain ordained as priests.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Bingham |first=John |url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/religion/11735289/Church-of-England-could-return-to-defrocking-rogue-priests-after-child-abuse-scandals.html |title=Church of England could return to defrocking rogue priests after child abuse scandals |work=The Daily Telegraph |date=13 July 2015 |accessdate=4 February 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Continued decline in attendance, and church response====
[[File:Holy trinity front 8809.jpg|thumb|One of the now &quot;redundant&quot; buildings, [[Holy Trinity Church, Wensley]], in North Yorkshire; much of the current structure was built in the 14th and 15th Centuries]]

Bishop [[Sarah Mullally]] has insisted that declining numbers at services should not necessarily be a cause of despair for churches, because people may still encounter God without attending a service in a church; for example hearing the Christian message through social media sites or in a café run as a community project.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/religion/11663692/Empty-pews-not-the-end-of-the-world-says-Church-of-Englands-newest-bishop.html &quot;Empty pews not the end of the world, says Church of England's newest bishop&quot;], ''The Daily Telegraph'', 9 June 2015.&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, 9.7 million people visit at least one of its churches every year and 1 million students are educated at Church of England schools (which number 4,700).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Facts and Stats of The Church of England|url=https://www.churchofengland.org/about-us/facts-stats.aspx|website=churchofengland.org|publisher=Church of England|accessdate=8 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, the archbishops of [[Justin Welby|Canterbury]] and [[John Sentamu|York]] warned in January 2015 that the Church of England would no longer be able to carry on in its current form unless the downward spiral in membership were somehow to be reversed, as typical Sunday attendance had halved to 800,000 in the previous 40 years:&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/religion/11340590/Church-of-England-cannot-carry-on-as-it-is-unless-decline-urgently-reversed-Welby-and-Sentamu.html &quot;Church of England cannot carry on as it is unless decline 'urgently' reversed – Welby and Sentamu&quot;], ''The Daily Telegraph'', 12 January 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;
{{quote|The urgency of the challenge facing us is not in doubt. Attendance at Church of England services has declined at an average of one per cent per annum over recent decades and, in addition, the age profile of our membership has become significantly older than that of the population... Renewing and reforming aspects of our institutional life is a necessary but far from sufficient response to the challenges facing the Church of England. ... The age profile of our clergy has also been increasing. Around 40 per cent of parish clergy are due to retire over the next decade or so.}}

Between 1969 and 2010, almost 1,800 church buildings, roughly 11% of the stock, were closed; the majority (70%) in the first half of the period; only 514 being closed between 1990 and 2010.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cofe.anglican.org/about/churchcommissioners/pastoralandclosedchurches/closedchurches/ Closed Churches Division]&lt;/ref&gt; Some active use was being made of about half of the closed churches.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.theheritagealliance.org.uk/hrba/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/churches-and-closure-in-cofe-mar-2010.pdf,|title=p=2}}&lt;/ref&gt;  By 2019 the rate of closure had steadied at around 20 to 25 per year (0.2%); some being replaced by new places of worship.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.churchofengland.org/more/parish-reorganisation-and-closed-church-buildings/closed-churches&lt;/ref&gt;  Additionally, in 2018 the church announced a £27 million growth programme to create 100 new churches.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.anglicannews.org/news/2018/07/church-of-england-announces-100-new-churches-in-27-million-pound-growth-programme.aspx&lt;/ref&gt;

====Low salaries====
In 2015 the Church of England admitted that it was embarrassed to be paying staff under the living wage. The Church of England had previously campaigned for all employers to pay this minimum amount. The archbishop of Canterbury acknowledged it was not the only area where the church &quot;fell short of its standards&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-31591075|title=Church of England: Justin Welby says low pay 'embarrassing'|work=BBC News}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Doctrine and practice==
{{See also|Anglicanism|Anglican doctrine}}
[[File:Hooker-Statue.jpeg|thumb|right|[[Richard Hooker (theologian)|Richard Hooker]] (1554–1600), one of the most influential figures in shaping Anglican theology and self-identity]]
The [[canon law]] of the Church of England identifies the [[Bible|Christian scriptures]] as the source of its doctrine. In addition, doctrine is also derived from the teachings of the [[Church Fathers]] and [[ecumenical councils]] (as well as the [[ecumenical creeds]]) in so far as these agree with scripture. This doctrine is expressed in the [[Thirty-Nine Articles of Religion]], the [[Book of Common Prayer]], and the Ordinal containing the rites for the ordination of [[deacon#Anglicanism|deacons]], [[Anglican priest|priests]], and the consecration of bishops.&lt;ref name=CanonA5&gt;Canon A5. [http://www.cofe.anglican.org/about/churchlawlegis/canons/church.pdf Canons of the Church of England] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090325141800/http://www.cofe.anglican.org/about/churchlawlegis/canons/church.pdf |date=25 March 2009 }}.&lt;/ref&gt; Unlike other traditions, the Church of England has no single theologian that it can look to as a founder. However, [[Richard Hooker]]'s appeal to scripture, [[Christian tradition|church tradition]], and [[reason]] as sources of authority continue to inform Anglican identity.&lt;ref name=&quot;EncRelg349-350&quot;&gt;Massey H. Shepherd, Jr. and Dale B. Martin, &quot;Anglicanism&quot; in ''Encyclopedia of Religion'', vol. 1, 2nd. ed., edited by Lindsay Jones (Detroit:Macmillan Reference USA, 2005), pp. 349–350.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Canterbury Cathedral - Portal Nave Cross-spire.jpeg|thumb|left|[[Canterbury Cathedral]] houses the ''[[cathedra]]'' or episcopal chair of the [[Archbishop of Canterbury]] and is the cathedral of the [[Diocese of Canterbury]] and the [[mother church]] of the Church of England as well as a focus for the [[Anglican Communion]]]]
The Church of England's doctrinal character today is largely the result of the Elizabethan Settlement, which sought to establish a comprehensive middle way between Roman Catholicism and Protestantism. The Church of England affirms the Protestant Reformation principle that scripture contains all things necessary to salvation and is the final arbiter in doctrinal matters. The Thirty-nine Articles are the church's only official confessional statement. Though not a complete system of doctrine, the articles highlight areas of agreement with [[Lutheran]] and [[Calvinism|Reformed]] positions, while differentiating Anglicanism from Roman Catholicism and [[Anabaptism]].&lt;ref name=&quot;EncRelg349-350&quot;/&gt;

While embracing some themes of the Protestant Reformation, the Church of England also maintains Catholic traditions of the ancient church and teachings of the Church Fathers, unless these are considered contrary to scripture. It accepts the decisions of the first four ecumenical councils concerning the [[Trinity]] and the [[Incarnation (Christianity)|Incarnation]]. The Church of England also preserves Catholic Order by adhering to [[episcopal polity]], with ordained orders of bishops, priests and deacons. There are differences of opinion within the Church of England over the necessity of episcopacy. Some consider it essential, while others feel it is needed for the proper ordering of the church.&lt;ref name=&quot;EncRelg349-350&quot;/&gt; In sum these express the 'Via Media' viewpoint that the first five centuries of doctrinal development and church order as approved as acceptable be a kind of yardstick by which to gauge authentic catholicity, as minimum and sufficient; Anglicanism did not emerge as the result of charismatic leaders with particular doctrines. It is light on details compared to Roman Catholic, Reformed and Lutheran teachings. The Bible, the Creeds, Apostolic Order, and the administration of the Sacraments are sufficient to establish Catholicity. Indeed, not one major doctrinal development emerged from the English reformation, per Diarmid MacCulloch, The Later Reformation in England, 1990, p.&amp;nbsp;55. The Reformation in England was initially much concerned about doctrine but the Elizabethan Settlement tried to put a stop to doctrinal contentions. The proponents of further changes, nonetheless, tried to get their way by making changes in Church Order (abolition of bishops), governance (Canon Law) and liturgy ('too Catholic'). They did not succeed because the Monarchy, the Church and resisted and the majority of the population were indifferent. Moreover, &quot;despite all the assumptions of the Reformation founders of that Church, it had retained a catholic character.&quot; The Elizabethan Settlement had created a cuckoo in a nest...&quot; a Protestant theology and program within a largely pre-Reformation Catholic structure whose continuing life would arouse a theological interest in the Catholicism that had created it; and would result in the rejection of predestinarian theology in favor of sacraments, especially the eucharist, ceremonial, and anti-Calvinist doctrine&quot; (ibid pp.&amp;nbsp;78–86). The existence of cathedrals &quot;without substantial alteration&quot; and  &quot;where the &quot;old devotional world cast its longest shadow for the future of the ethos that would become Anglicanism,&quot; p.&amp;nbsp;79. This is &quot;One of the great mysteries of the English Reformation,&quot; ibid that there was no complete break with the past but a muddle that was per force turned into a virtue. The story of the English Reformation is the tale of retreat from the Protestant advance of 1550 which could not proceed further in the face of the opposition of the institution which was rooted in the medieval past, ibid. p.&amp;nbsp;142 and the adamant opposition of Queen Elizabeth I.

The Church of England has, as one of its distinguishing marks, a breadth and &quot;open-mindedness&quot;. This tolerance has allowed Anglicans who emphasise the Catholic tradition and others who emphasise the Reformed tradition to coexist. The three &quot;parties&quot; (see [[Churchmanship]]) in the Church of England are sometimes called [[high church]] (or [[Anglo-Catholic]]), [[low church]] (or [[evangelical Anglican]]) and [[broad church]] (or [[Liberal Christianity|liberal]]). The high church party places importance on the Church of England's continuity with the pre-Reformation Catholic Church, adherence to ancient liturgical usages and the sacerdotal nature of the priesthood. As their name suggests, Anglo-Catholics maintain many traditional Catholic practices and liturgical forms.&lt;ref name=HighChurch&gt;&quot;High Church&quot;, ''New Catholic Encyclopedia'', 2nd ed., vol. 6 (Detroit: Gale, 2003), pp. 823–824.&lt;/ref&gt; The low church party is more Protestant in both ceremony and theology.&lt;ref name=LowChurch&gt;&quot;Low Church&quot;, ''New Catholic Encyclopedia'', 2nd ed., vol. 8 (Detroit: Gale, 2003), p. 836.&lt;/ref&gt; Historically, broad church has been used to describe those of middle-of-the-road ceremonial preferences who lean theologically towards liberal Protestantism.&lt;ref name=BroadChurch&gt;E. McDermott, &quot;Broad Church&quot;, ''New Catholic Encyclopedia'', 2nd ed., vol. 2 (Detroit: Gale, 2003), pp. 624–625.&lt;/ref&gt;  The balance between these strands of churchmanship is not static: in 2013, 40% of Church of England worshippers attended evangelical churches (compared with 26% in 1989), and 83% of very large congregations were evangelical. Such churches were also reported to attract higher numbers of men and young adults than others.&lt;ref&gt;'New Directions', May 2013&lt;/ref&gt;

===Worship and liturgy===
The Church of England's official book of liturgy as established in English Law is the ''[[Book of Common Prayer]]'' (BCP). In addition to this book the General Synod has also legislated for a modern [[liturgical book]], ''[[Common Worship]]'', dating from 2000, which can be used as an alternative to the BCP. Like its predecessor, the 1980 ''[[Alternative Service Book]]'', it differs from the ''Book of Common Prayer'' in providing a range of alternative services, mostly in modern language, although it does include some BCP-based forms as well, for example Order Two for Holy Communion. (This is a revision of the BCP service, altering some words and allowing the insertion of some other liturgical texts such as the ''[[Agnus Dei (liturgy)|Agnus Dei]]'' before communion.) The Order One rite follows the pattern of more modern liturgical scholarship.

The liturgies are organised according to the traditional [[liturgical year]] and the [[Calendar of saints (Church of England)|calendar of saints]]. The [[Anglican sacraments|sacraments]] of [[baptism]] and the [[Eucharist]] are generally thought necessary to salvation. [[Infant baptism]] is practised. At a later age, individuals baptised as infants receive [[confirmation]] by a bishop, at which time they reaffirm the baptismal promises made by their parents or sponsors. The Eucharist, consecrated by a thanksgiving prayer including Christ's [[Words of Institution]], is believed to be &quot;a memorial of Christ's once-for-all redemptive acts in which Christ is objectively present and effectually received in faith&quot;.&lt;ref name=EncRelg350&gt;Shepherd, Jr. and Martin, &quot;Anglicanism&quot;, p. 350.&lt;/ref&gt;

The use of hymns and [[Anglican church music|music in the Church of England]] has changed dramatically over the centuries. Traditional [[Evening Prayer (Anglican)|Choral evensong]] is a staple of most cathedrals.{{Citation needed|date=June 2010}} The style of [[psalm]] chanting harks back to the Church of England's pre-reformation roots. During the 18th century, clergy such as [[Charles Wesley]] introduced their own styles of worship with poetic hymns.

In the latter half of the 20th century, the influence of the [[Charismatic Movement]] significantly altered the worship traditions of numerous Church of England parishes, primarily affecting those of [[evangelical]] persuasion. These churches now adopt a [[contemporary worship]] form of service, with minimal liturgical or ritual elements, and incorporating [[contemporary worship music]].

Just as the Church of England has a large conservative or &quot;traditionalist&quot; wing, it also has many [[Liberal Christianity|liberal]] members and clergy. Approximately one third of clergy &quot;doubt or disbelieve in the physical resurrection&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/uknews/1403106/One-third-of-clergy-do-not-believe-in-the-Resurrection.html|title=One third of clergy do not believe in the Resurrection|last=Petre|first=Jonathan|work=The Daily Telegraph|access-date=1 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Others, such as the Revd [[Giles Fraser]], a contributor to ''The Guardian'', have argued for an allegorical interpretation of the [[virgin birth of Jesus]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2015/dec/24/story-virgin-birth-christianity-mary-sex-femininity|title=The story of the virgin birth runs against the grain of Christianity|date=24 December 2015|newspaper=The Guardian|language=en-GB|issn=0261-3077|access-date=1 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''The Independent'' reported in 2014 that, according to a YouGov survey of Church of England clergy, &quot;as many as 16 per cent are unclear about God and two per cent think it is no more than a human construct.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.independent.co.uk/news/uk/home-news/survey-finds-2-of-anglican-priests-are-not-believers-9821899.html|title=Survey finds 2 per cent of Anglican priests are not believers|date=27 October 2014|website=The Independent|language=en-GB|access-date=1 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cdn.yougov.com/cumulus_uploads/document/5f5s31fk47/Results-for-Anglican-Clergy-Survey-08092014.pdf|title=YouGov / University of Lancaster and Westminster Faith Debates|date=23 October 2014|website=YouGov|language=en-GB|access-date=2 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, many congregations are seeker-friendly environments. For example, one report from the [[Church Mission Society]] suggested that the church open up &quot;a pagan church where Christianity [is] very much in the centre&quot; to reach out to spiritual people.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/religion/10133906/Church-of-England-creating-pagan-church-to-recruit-members.html|title=Church of England creating 'pagan church' to recruit members|work=The Daily Telegraph|access-date=1 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Women's ministry ===
Women were appointed as deaconesses from 1861, but they could not function fully as deacons and were not considered ordained clergy. Women have been [[lay reader]]s for a long time. During the First World War, some women were appointed as lay readers, known as &quot;[[bishop's messenger]]s&quot;, who also led missions and ran churches in the absence of men. After that no more lay readers were appointed until 1969.

Legislation authorising the ordination of women as deacons was passed in 1986 and they were first ordained in 1987. The [[ordination of women]] as priests was passed by the [[General Synod of the Church of England|General Synod]] in 1992 and [[List of the first 32 women ordained as Church of England priests|began in 1994]]. In 2010, for the first time in the history of the Church of England, more women than men were ordained as priests (290 women and 273 men).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/religion/9060296/More-new-women-priests-than-men-for-first-time.html|title=More new women priests than men for first time|work=The Daily Telegraph |date=4 February 2012 |accessdate=11 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In July 2005, the synod voted to &quot;set in train&quot; the process of allowing the consecration of women as bishops. In February 2006, the synod voted overwhelmingly for the &quot;further exploration&quot; of possible arrangements for parishes that did not want to be directly under the authority of a bishop who is a woman.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ekklesia.co.uk/content/news_syndication/article_060210women.shtml Church votes overwhelmingly for compromise on women bishops]. ''Ekklesia''.&lt;/ref&gt; On 7 July 2008, the synod voted to approve the ordination of women as bishops and rejected moves for alternative episcopal oversight for those who do not accept the ministry of bishops who are women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Church will ordain women bishops|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/7494517.stm|work=BBC News|date=7 July 2008|accessdate=7 July 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Actual ordinations of women to the episcopate required further legislation, which was narrowly rejected in a vote at General Synod in November 2012.&lt;ref&gt;Pigott, Robert. (14 February 2009) [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/7889946.stm Synod struggles on women bishops]. BBC News.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-20415689 &quot;Church of England general synod votes against women bishops&quot;], BBC News, 20 November 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; On 20 November 2013, the General Synod voted overwhelmingly in support of a plan to allow the ordination of women as bishops, with 378 in favour, 8 against and 25 abstentions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://descrier.co.uk/uk/2013/11/church-england-synod-votes-overwhelmingly-support-women-bishops/|title=Church of England Synod votes overwhelmingly in support of women bishops|work=The Descrier |date=20 November 2013 |accessdate=20 November 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 14 July 2014, the General Synod approved the ordination of women as bishops. The House of Bishops recorded 37 votes in favour, two against with one abstention. The House of Clergy had 162 in favour, 25 against and four abstentions. The House of Laity voted 152 for, 45 against with five abstentions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-28298250|title=LIVE: Vote backs women bishops|work=BBC |date=14 July 2014 |accessdate=14 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; This legislation had to be approved by the Ecclesiastical Committee of the Parliament before it could be finally implemented at the November 2014 synod. In December 2014, [[Libby Lane]] was announced as the first woman to become a bishop in the Church of England. She was consecrated as a bishop in January 2015.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.reuters.com/article/2015/01/26/us-religion-anglican-women-idUSKBN0KZ0Z820150126|title=After turmoil, Church of England consecrates first woman bishop|work=Reuters}}&lt;/ref&gt; In July 2015, [[Rachel Treweek]] was the first woman to become a diocesan bishop in the Church of England when she became the [[Bishop of Gloucester]].&lt;ref name=&quot;anglicannews1&quot;&gt;[http://www.anglicannews.org/news/2015/07/first-female-diocesan-bishop-in-c-of-e-consecrated.aspx First female diocesan bishop in C of E consecrated]. Anglicannews.org. Retrieved on 23 July 2015.&lt;/ref&gt; She and [[Sarah Mullally]], Bishop of Crediton, were the first women to be ordained as bishops at [[Canterbury Cathedral]].&lt;ref name=&quot;anglicannews1&quot;/&gt; Treweek later made headlines by calling for gender-inclusive language, saying that &quot;God is not to be seen as male. God is God.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2015/oct/24/bishop-rachel-treweek-gods-not-a-he-or-a-she|title='God is not a he or a she', says first female bishop to sit in House of Lords|last=Sherwood|first=Harriet|date=24 October 2015|newspaper=The Guardian|language=en-GB|issn=0261-3077|access-date=30 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In May 2018, the Diocese of London consecrated [[Dame Sarah Mullally]] as the first woman to serve as the [[Bishop of London]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.churchtimes.co.uk/articles/2018/18-may/news/uk/first-woman-bishop-of-sarah-mullally-london-installed|title=First woman Bishop of London installed|website=www.churchtimes.co.uk|access-date=20 May 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bishop Sarah Mullally occupies the third most senior position in the Church of England.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.bbc.com/news/uk-england-london-44095112|title=First female Bishop of London installed|date=12 May 2018|work=BBC News|access-date=20 May 2018|language=en-GB}}&lt;/ref&gt; Mullally has described herself as a feminist and will ordain both men and women to the priesthood.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.thetimes.co.uk/article/new-woman-bishop-goes-to-war-for-female-vicars-7q28wqkdf|title=New woman bishop goes to war for female vicars|last=Social Affairs Editor|first=Nicholas Hellen|date=13 May 2018|work=The Sunday Times|access-date=20 May 2018|language=en|issn=0956-1382}}&lt;/ref&gt; She is also considered by some to be a theological liberal.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.ft.com/content/d2042694-e3f1-11e7-8b99-0191e45377ec|title=Subscribe to read|website=Financial Times|language=en-GB|access-date=20 May 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; On women's [[reproductive rights]], Mullally describes herself as [[Abortion-rights movements|pro-choice]] while also being personally [[Anti-abortion movements|pro-life]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://sarahmullally.wordpress.com/2012/03/09/choice/|title=Choice|date=9 March 2012|work=Contemplation in the shadow of a carpark|access-date=20 May 2018|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt; On marriage, she supports the current stance of the Church of England that marriage is between a man and a woman, but also said that: &quot;It is a time for us to reflect on our tradition and scripture, and together say how we can offer a response that is about it being inclusive love.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.churchtimes.co.uk/articles/2017/22-december/news/uk/sarah-mullally-to-be-the-next-bishop-of-london|title=Former Chief Nursing Officer to be first woman Bishop of London|website=www.churchtimes.co.uk|access-date=20 May 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Same-sex unions and LGBT clergy ===
{{See also|Same-sex marriage in the United Kingdom|LGBT rights in the United Kingdom|Homosexuality and the Anglican Communion}}
The Church of England has been discussing [[Same-sex marriage in the United Kingdom|same-sex marriages]] and LGBT clergy.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://uk.reuters.com/article/uk-britain-religion-samesex/church-of-england-proposes-celebrating-gay-marriage-idUKBRE9AR0CP20131128|title=Church of England proposes celebrating gay marriage|last=Editorial|first=Reuters|work=U.K.|access-date=1 October 2017|language=en-GB}}&lt;/ref&gt; The church holds that marriage is a union of one man with one woman.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.churchofengland.org/media/1657614/ssmarriagebillbriefing.pdf |title=Archived copy |access-date=22 October 2017 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171023012119/https://www.churchofengland.org/media/1657614/ssmarriagebillbriefing.pdf |archive-date=23 October 2017 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the church teaches &quot;Same-sex relationships often embody genuine mutuality and fidelity.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Bingham|first1=John|title=Church offers prayers after same-sex weddings – but bans gay priests from marrying|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/religion/10640144/Church-offers-prayers-after-same-sex-weddings-but-bans-gay-priests-from-marrying.html|work=The Daily Telegraph|accessdate=25 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.churchofengland.org/more/media-centre/news/house-bishops-pastoral-guidance-same-sex-marriage|title=House of Bishops Pastoral Guidance on Same Sex Marriage|website=The Church of England|language=en|access-date=2020-01-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; The church also officially supports [[Celibacy|celibate]] civil partnerships; &quot;We believe that Civil Partnerships still have a place, including for some Christian [[Intersex and LGBT|LGBTI]] couples who see them as a way of gaining legal recognition of their relationship.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.premier.org.uk/News/UK/Keep-civil-partnerships-Church-of-England-urges-Government|title=Keep civil partnerships, Church of England urges Government|date=18 May 2018|work=Premier|access-date=20 May 2018|language=en-GB}}&lt;/ref&gt; The &quot;Church of England does not conduct Civil Partnership Ceremonies or Same Sex Marriages but individual churches can conduct a service of thanksgiving after a ceremony.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.christchurchshootershill.org.uk/weddings|title=cc-shooters-hill|website=cc-shooters-hill|access-date=27 September 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; The church says &quot;clergy in the Church of England are permitted to offer prayers of support on a pastoral basis for people in same-sex relationships;&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.churchofengland.org/media-centre/news/2016/11/secretary-general-responds-to-gafcon-uk.aspx|title=Church of England News: Secretary General responds to GAFCON UK|work=Church of England News|access-date=2 May 2017|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; As such, many Anglican churches, with clergy open to it, &quot;already bless same-sex couples on an unofficial basis.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Christian attitudes to same-sex marriage|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/religions/christianity/christianethics/samesexmarriage.shtml|website=bbc.co.uk|publisher=BBC|accessdate=14 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/uknews/1410695/Vicars-bless-hundreds-of-gay-couples-a-year.html|title=Vicars bless hundreds of gay couples a year|authors=Chris Hastings, Fiona Govan and Susan Bisset|work=The Daily Telegraph|access-date=31 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Civil partnership in the United Kingdom|Civil partnerships]] for clergy have been allowed since 2005,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/england/beds/bucks/herts/5236132.stm|title=Gay cleric's 'wedding' to partner|work=BBC News|access-date=27 March 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.thecourier.co.uk/fp/news/local/angus-mearns/663064/gay-cleric-in-running-for-brechin-position/|title=Gay cleric in running for Brechin position|last=Alex|first=Stewart|last2=er|website=The Courier|language=en-GB|access-date=2019-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/jan/04/church-of-england-gay-bishops|title=Church of England rules gay men in civil partnerships can become bishops|last=Walker|first=Peter|date=4 January 2013|newspaper=The Guardian|language=en-GB|issn=0261-3077|access-date=24 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the church extends pensions to clergy in same-sex civil partnerships.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title = Church of England General Synod extends pension rights for gay partners|url = https://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/feb/11/anglican-synod-gay-pension-rights|newspaper = The Guardian|date = 11 February 2010|access-date = 25 February 2016|issn = 0261-3077|language = en-GB|first = Stephen|last = Bates}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a missive to clergy, the church communicated that &quot;there was a need for committed same-sex couples to be given recognition and 'compassionate attention' from the Church, including special prayers.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/religion/9983121/Church-of-England-gives-blessing-to-recognising-civil-partnerships.html|title=Church of England gives blessing to recognising civil partnerships|newspaper=Telegraph.co.uk|access-date=23 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;There is no prohibition on prayers being said in church or there being a 'service'&quot; after a civil union.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.churchtimes.co.uk/articles/2012/2-march/comment/letters-to-the-editor/civil-partnerships-and-defining-marriage|title=Civil partnerships and defining marriage|website=www.churchtimes.co.uk|access-date=3 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; After same-sex marriage was legalised, the church asked for the government to continue to offer civil unions saying &quot;The Church of England recognises that same-sex relationships often embody fidelity and mutuality. Civil partnerships enable these Christian virtues to be recognised socially and legally in a proper framework.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.christiantoday.com/article/church.of.england.says.civil.partnerships.should.not.be.abolished.following.gay.marriage.legalisation/36731.htm|title=Church of England says civil partnerships should not be abolished following gay marriage legalisation|website=www.christiantoday.com|access-date=21 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2014, the bishops released guidelines that permit &quot;more informal kind of prayer&quot; for couples.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.churchofengland.org/media-centre/news/2014/02/house-of-bishops-pastoral-guidance-on-same-sex-marriage.aspx|title=Church of England News: House of Bishops Pastoral Guidance on Same Sex Marriage|website=Church of England News|access-date=7 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the guidelines, &quot;gay couples who get married will be able to ask for special prayers in the Church of England after their wedding, the bishops have agreed.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/religion/10640144/Church-offers-prayers-after-same-sex-weddings-but-bans-gay-priests-from-marrying.html|title=Church offers prayers after same-sex weddings - but bans gay priests from marrying|access-date=5 September 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2016, The Bishop of Grantham, the Rt Revd [[Nicholas Chamberlain]], announced that he is gay, in a same-sex relationship and celibate, becoming the first bishop to do so in the church.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/sep/02/nicholas-chamberlain-bishop-of-grantham-c-of-e-gay-relationship|title=Bishop of Grantham first C of E bishop to declare he is in gay relationship|last=correspondent|first=Harriet Sherwood Religion|date=2 September 2016|newspaper=The Guardian|language=en-GB|issn=0261-3077|access-date=2 September 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The church had decided in 2013 that gay clergy in civil partnerships could become bishops.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.cnn.com/2013/01/05/world/uk-same-sex-bishops/index.html|title=Priests in same-sex relationships may become Anglican Bishops|first=Ben|last=Brumfield|work=CNN|access-date=1 June 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;The House [of Bishops] has confirmed that clergy in civil partnerships, and living in accordance with the teaching of the church on human sexuality, can be considered as candidates for the episcopate.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2013/01/05/world/europe/anglicans-open-a-path-to-bishopric-for-gay-men.html|title=Anglicans Open a Path to Bishopric for Gay Men|last=Lyall|first=Sarah|date=2013|work=The New York Times|access-date=27 September 2017|language=en-US|issn=0362-4331}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2017, the House of Clergy voted against the motion to &quot;take note&quot; of the bishops' report defining marriage as between a man and a woman.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.christiantoday.com/article/church.of.englands.clergy.issue.shock.rebuke.to.bishops.conservative.view.on.sexuality/104738.htm|title=Church Of England's Clergy Issue Shock Rebuke To Bishops' View On Sexuality |website=www.christiantoday.com|language=en|access-date=17 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Due to passage in all three houses being required, the motion was rejected.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/2017/02/15/church-england-votes-reject-controversial-gay-marriage-report/|title=Church takes step towards gay marriage after vote rejects controversial report|newspaper=The Daily Telegraph|access-date=17 February 2017|language=en-GB}}&lt;/ref&gt; After General Synod rejected the motion, the archbishops of Canterbury and York called for &quot;radical new Christian inclusion&quot; that is &quot;based on good, healthy, flourishing relationships, and in a proper 21st century understanding of being human and of being sexual.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.christiantoday.com/article/archbishops.call.for.radical.new.christian.inclusion.after.synod.blocks.sexuality.report/104775.htm|title=Archbishops Call For 'Radical New Christian Inclusion' After Synod Blocks Sexuality Report|website=www.christiantoday.com|language=en|access-date=17 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; The church officially opposes &quot;[[conversion therapy]]&quot;, a practice which attempts to change a gay or lesbian person's sexual orientation, calling it unethical and supports the [[Conversion therapy ban|banning]] of &quot;conversion therapy&quot; in the UK.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.churchofengland.org/more/media-centre/news/general-synod-backs-ban-conversion-therapy|title=General Synod backs ban on conversion therapy|website=www.churchofengland.org|language=en|access-date=5 July 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.christianpost.com/news/church-of-england-warmly-welcomes-uk-plan-ban-gay-conversion-therapy-225724/|title=Church of England 'Warmly Welcomes' UK's Plan to Ban Gay Conversion Therapy|access-date=5 July 2018|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Diocese of Hereford]] approved a motion calling for the church &quot;to create a set of formal services and prayers to bless those who have had a same-sex marriage or civil partnership.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.thetimes.co.uk/article/landmark-vote-piles-pressure-on-anglicans-over-same-sex-marriage-jwrzs6qbs|title=Landmark vote piles pressure on Anglicans over same-sex marriage|last=Burgess|first=Kaya|date=20 October 2017|work=The Times|access-date=22 October 2017|issn=0140-0460}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Regarding [[Christianity and transgender people|transgender issues]], the 2017 General Synod voted in favour of a motion saying that transgender people should be &quot;welcomed and affirmed in their parish church&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2017/jul/09/anglican-church-set-to-offer-special-services-for-transgender-people|title=Anglican church set to offer special services for transgender people|last=Sherwood|first=Harriet|date=9 July 2017|work=The Guardian|access-date=10 July 2017|language=en-GB|issn=0261-3077}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://metro.co.uk/2017/07/09/church-of-england-to-hold-special-services-for-transgender-people-6766501/|title=Church of England to hold special services for transgender people|last=Metro.co.uk|first=Fiona Parker for|date=9 July 2017|website=Metro|access-date=10 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; The motion also asked the bishops &quot;to look into special services for transgender people.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.bbc.com/news/uk-40546644|title=Church of England votes to explore transgender services|date=9 July 2017|work=BBC News|access-date=10 July 2017|language=en-GB}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.churchtimes.co.uk/articles/2015/29-may/news/uk/diocese-of-blackburn-seeks-new-liturgy-for-trans-service|title=Diocese of Blackburn seeks new liturgy for trans service|website=www.churchtimes.co.uk|access-date=28 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The bishops initially said &quot;the House notes that the Affirmation of Baptismal Faith, found in ''Common Worship'', is an ideal liturgical rite which trans people can use to mark this moment of personal renewal.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.churchofengland.org/sites/default/files/2018-01/GS%20Misc%201178%20-%20An%20update%20on%20Welcoming%20Transgender%20People%20%28003%29.pdf|title=An update on 'Welcoming Transgender People'|last=|first=|date=January 2018|website=churchofengland.org|access-date=27 January 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Bishops also authorised services of celebration to mark a gender transition that will be included in formal liturgy.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.bbc.com/news/uk-46516299|title=Church service to mark gender transition|date=11 December 2018|work=BBC News|access-date=12 December 2018|language=en-GB}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.churchtimes.co.uk/articles/2018/14-december/news/uk/adapted-baptism-liturgy-can-celebrate-gender-transition|title=Adapted baptism liturgy can celebrate gender transition|website=www.churchtimes.co.uk|access-date=12 December 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; Transgender people may marry in the Church of England after legally making a transition.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.express.co.uk/news/uk/820105/church-england-transgender-baptism-services-worshippers-naming|title=Church of England to consider re-naming services for transgender worshippers|last=Mansfield|first=Katie|date=24 June 2017|work=Express.co.uk|access-date=27 May 2018|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;Since the Gender Recognition Act [2004], trans people legally confirmed in their gender identity under its provisions are able to marry someone of the opposite sex in their parish church.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2017/jul/11/church-of-england-trans-gay-clergy-parishioners|title=The church's trans epiphany will ease the way for others like me |last=Beardsley|first=Tina|date=11 July 2017|website=the Guardian|language=en|access-date=27 May 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; The church further decided that same-gender couples may remain married when one spouse experiences [[Transitioning (transgender)|gender transition]] provided that the spouses identified as opposite genders at the time of the marriage.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.thetimes.co.uk/article/church-of-england-accepts-same-sex-marriage-with-a-catch-3nq6j0zjh|title=Church accepts marriage between people of the same gender — with a catch|last=Religious Affairs Correspondent|first=Kaya Burgess|date=2019-07-04|work=The Times|access-date=2019-07-06|language=en|issn=0140-0460}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/2019/07/04/church-england-will-condone-gay-couples-first-time-long-man/|title=Church of England will condone gay couples for first time - as long as they were man and wife when they took vows|last=Swerling|first=Gabriella|date=2019-07-04|work=The Telegraph|access-date=2019-07-06|language=en-GB|issn=0307-1235}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since 2000, the church has allowed priests to undergo gender transition and remain in office.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/1052786.stm|title=Sex-change vicar back in pulpit|work=BBC News|access-date=1 December 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The church has ordained openly transgender clergy since 2005.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.stuff.co.nz/national/72804951/transgender-priest-sings-praises-of-understanding|title=Transgender priest sings for change|website=Stuff|access-date=30 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Bioethics issues===
The Church of England is generally opposed to abortion but recognises that &quot;there can be - strictly limited - conditions under which it may be morally preferable to any available alternative&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.churchofengland.org/our-views/medical-ethics-health-social-care-policy/abortion.aspx|title=The Church of England's position on abortion|website=www.churchofengland.org|access-date=14 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The church also opposes euthanasia. Its official stance is that &quot;While acknowledging the complexity of the issues involved in assisted dying/suicide and voluntary euthanasia, the Church of England is opposed to any change in the law or in medical practice that would make assisted dying/suicide or voluntary euthanasia permissible in law or acceptable in practice.&quot; It also states that &quot;Equally, the Church shares the desire to alleviate physical and psychological suffering, but believes that assisted dying/suicide and voluntary euthanasia are not acceptable means of achieving these laudable goals.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.churchofengland.org/media/57990/assisteddyingpdfmar09.pdf &quot;Assisted Dying/Suicide and Voluntary Euthanasia&quot;], Church of England official website.&lt;/ref&gt; In 2014, George Carey, a former Archbishop of Canterbury, announced that he had changed his stance on euthanasia and now advocated legalising &quot;assisted dying&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.theguardian.com/society/2014/jul/12/archbishop-canterbury-carey-support-assisted-dying-proposal|title=Former archbishop lends his support to campaign to legalise right to die|last=Watt|first=Nicholas|date=11 July 2014|work=The Guardian|access-date=31 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; On embryonic stem-cell research, the church has announced &quot;cautious acceptance to the proposal to produce cytoplasmic hybrid embryos for research&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.churchofengland.org/our-views/medical-ethics-health-social-care-policy/hfea.aspx|title=The Church of England and human fertilisation &amp; embryology|website=www.churchofengland.org|access-date=31 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 19th century, English law required the burial of people who had committed suicide to occur only [[Interments (felo de se) Act 1882|between the hours of 9 p.m. and midnight and without religious rites]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.christiantoday.com/article/suicides-can-receive-anglican-funerals-says-general-synod/47997.htm|title=Suicides can receive Anglican funerals, says General Synod|last=Gledhill|first=Ruth|date=12 Feb 2015|website=www.christiantoday.com|language=en|access-date=2019-08-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Church of England permitted the use of alternative burial services for people who had committed suicide. In 2017, the Church of England changed its rules to permit the full, standard Christian burial service regardless of whether a person had committed suicide.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.premier.org.uk/News/UK/Church-ends-ban-on-full-Christian-funerals-for-suicides|title=Church ends ban on full Christian funerals for suicides|last=Adeogun|first=Eno|date=2017-07-11|website=Premier|language=en-GB|access-date=2019-08-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Poverty==

===Church Urban Fund===
{{Main|Church Urban Fund}}
The Church of England set up the [[Church Urban Fund]] in the 1980s to tackle poverty and [[Social deprivation|deprivation]].  They see poverty as trapping individuals and communities with some people in urgent need. This leads to [[Dependant|dependency]], [[homelessness]], [[hunger]], [[social isolation|isolation]], [[low income]], [[mental health]] problems, [[social exclusion]] and violence. They feel that poverty reduces confidence and [[life expectancy]] and that people born in poor conditions have difficulty escaping their disadvantaged circumstances.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.cuf.org.uk/about|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131214051036/http://www.cuf.org.uk/about|url-status=dead|title=About Church Urban Fund|archivedate=14 December 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Child poverty====
In parts of [[Liverpool]], Manchester and [[Newcastle upon Tyne|Newcastle]] two-thirds of babies are born to poverty and have poorer life chances, also life expectancy 15 years lower than babies born in most fortunate communities. [[South Shore, Blackpool]], has lowest life expectancy at 66 years for men.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-18137739|title=Church Urban Fund finds 'poorest' in north-west England|work=BBC News}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{quote|The deep-rooted unfairness in our society is highlighted by these stark statistics. Children being born in this country, just a few miles apart, couldn't witness a more wildly differing start to life. In child poverty terms, we live in one of the most unequal countries in the western world. We want people to understand where their own community sits alongside neighbouring communities. The disparity is often shocking but it's crucial that, through greater awareness, people from all backgrounds come together to think about what could be done to support those born into poverty. [Paul Hackwood, the Chair of Trustees at Church Urban Fund]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.churchofengland.org/media-centre/news/2012/09/child-poverty-in-the-uk.aspx|title=Child poverty in the UK|work=Church of England News}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

===Action on hunger===
Many prominent people in the Church of England have spoken out against poverty and welfare cuts in the United Kingdom. Twenty-seven bishops are among 43 Christian leaders who signed a letter which urged [[David Cameron]] to make sure people [[Poverty#Hunger|have enough to eat]].
{{quote|We often hear talk of hard choices. Surely few can be harder than that faced by the tens of thousands of older people who must 'heat or eat' each winter, harder than those faced by families whose wages have stayed flat while food prices have gone up 30% in just five years.  Yet beyond even this we must, as a society, face up to the fact that over half of people using food banks have been put in that situation by cutbacks to and failures in the benefit system, whether it be payment delays or punitive sanctions.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC20/02/14&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.bbc.com/news/uk-politics-26261700|title=Bishops demand action over hunger|date=20 February 2014|via=www.bbc.co.uk}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

[[Welfare state in the United Kingdom|Benefit]] cuts, failures and &quot;punitive sanctions&quot; force thousands of UK citizens to use [[food bank]]s. The campaign to end hunger considers this &quot;truly shocking&quot; and called for a national day of [[fasting]] on 4 April 2014.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC20/02/14&quot;/&gt;

==Membership==
Official figures from 2005 showed there were 25 million baptised Anglicans in England and Wales.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://metro.co.uk/2007/02/15/catholicism-set-to-be-uks-top-religion-85991/|title=Catholicism set to be UK's top religion |work=Metro News}}&lt;/ref&gt; Due to its status as the [[state religion|established]] church, in general, anyone may be married, have their children baptised or their funeral in their local [[Church of England parish church|parish church]], regardless of whether they are baptised or regular churchgoers.&lt;ref&gt;See the pages linked from the [http://www.cofe.anglican.org/lifeevents/ Life Events page on the Church of England website] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20101122050046/http://www.cofe.anglican.org/lifeevents/ |date=22 November 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Between 1890 and 2001, churchgoing in the United Kingdom declined steadily.&lt;ref&gt;Peter J. Bowler, ''Reconciling science and religion: the debate in early-twentieth-century Britain'' (University of Chicago Press, 2001), page 194.&lt;/ref&gt; In the years 1968 to 1999, Anglican Sunday church attendances almost halved, from 3.5 per cent of the population to 1.9 per cent.&lt;ref&gt;Robin Gill, ''The Empty Church Revisited'', (Ashgate Publishing, 2003) page 161.&lt;/ref&gt; By the year 2014, Sunday church attendances had declined further to 1.4 per cent of the population.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/religion/12095251/Church-of-England-attendance-plunges-to-record-low.html Church of England attendance plunges to record low] 12 January 2016 The Telegraph&lt;/ref&gt; One study published in 2008 suggested that if current trends were to continue, Sunday attendances could fall to 350,000 in 2030 and just 87,800 in 2050.&lt;ref&gt;Christian Research, ''Religious Trends'' (2008), cited in [[Ruth Gledhill]], &quot;Churchgoing on its knees as Christianity falls out of favour&quot;, ''The Times'', 8 May 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2011, the Church of England published statistics showing 1.7 million people attending at least one of its services each month, a level maintained since the turn of the millennium; approximately one million participating each Sunday and three million taking part in a Church of England service on Christmas Day or Christmas Eve. The church also claimed that 30% attend Sunday worship at least once a year; more than 40% attend a wedding in their local church and still more attend a funeral there.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.churchofengland.org/about-us/facts-stats.aspx Church of England website]. Churchofengland.org.&lt;/ref&gt; Nationally the Church of England baptises one child in ten (2011).&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.bbc.com/news/magazine-24565994 10 ways christening has changed] 23 October 2013 BBC News&lt;/ref&gt; In 2015, the church's statistics showed that 2.6 million people attended a special Advent service, 2.4 million attended a Christmas service, 1.3 million attended an Easter service, and 980,000 attended service during an average week.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.christiantoday.com/article/church.of.england.weekly.attendance.falls.below.one.million.for.first.time/76373.htm|title=Church of England weekly attendance falls below one million for first time |website=www.christiantoday.com|language=en|access-date=9 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2016, 2.6 million people attended a Christmas service, 1.2 million attended an Easter service, 1.1 million people attended a service in the Church of England each month, an average of 930,000 people attended a weekly service, an additional 180,000 attended a service for school each week, and an average of 740,000 people attended Sunday service. In 2017 Cathedral statistics showed that a total of 135,000 attended a Christmas service, an increase of 13% and overall Sunday attendance has risen from 7000 in 2000 to 18,000 in 2017 which had increased over the past 10 years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.churchofengland.org/sites/default/files/2017-10/2016statisticsformission.pdf|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180213092145/https://www.churchofengland.org/sites/default/files/2017-10/2016statisticsformission.pdf|url-status=dead|archive-date=13 February 2018|title=Statistics for Mission 2016|date=2017|website=churchofengland.org|access-date=6 November 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Also in 2017, approximately 1.14 million people were a part of the regular worshiping community, meaning those attending church once a month or more, 6.8 million were reached in the Advent campaign, and 2.68 million people attended a Christmas service, representing a slight increase.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.christiantoday.com/article/mixed-picture-for-cofe-in-latest-attendance-figures/130939.htm|title=Mixed picture for CofE in latest attendance figures|access-date=14 November 2018|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Church of England has 18,000 active ordained clergy and 10,000 licensed lay ministers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.churchofengland.org/about-us/facts-stats/research-statistics.aspx Church of England Research &amp; Statistics link page]. Churchofengland.org (9 May 2012).&lt;/ref&gt; In 2009, 491 people were recommended for ordination training, maintaining the level at the turn of the millennium, and 564 new clergy (266 women and 298 men) were ordained. More than half of those ordained (193 men and 116 women) were appointed to full-time paid ministry.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.churchofengland.org/about-us/facts-stats.aspx Facts and stats]. Churchofengland.org.&lt;/ref&gt; In 2011, 504 new clergy were ordained, including 264 to paid ministry, and 349 [[lay reader]]s were admitted to ministry; and the mode age-range of those recommended for ordination training had remained 40–49 since 1999.&lt;ref&gt;Church of England Year Book, 2012&lt;/ref&gt;

==Structure==
{{see also|Anglican ministry|List of Church of England dioceses}}
[[File:Dioceses of Church of England.svg|thumb|right|Dioceses of the Church of England {{legend|#ff3|outline=#00|[[Province of Canterbury]]}}{{legend|#f99|outline=#00|[[Province of York]]}}]]

Article XIX ('Of the Church') of the 39 Articles defines the church as follows:

{{quote|The [[Church visible|visible Church of Christ]] is a congregation of faithful men, in which [[Marks of the Church|the pure Word of God is preached, and the sacraments be duly ministered]] according to Christ's ordinance in all those things that of necessity are requisite to the same.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.churchsociety.org/issues_new/doctrine/39a/iss_doctrine_39A_Arts19-22.asp 39 Articles – 19–22]. Church Society.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

[[Monarchy of the United Kingdom|The British monarch]] has the constitutional title of [[Supreme Governor of the Church of England]]. The canon law of the Church of England states, &quot;We acknowledge that the Queen's most excellent Majesty, acting according to the laws of the realm, is the highest power under God in this kingdom, and has supreme authority over all persons in all causes, as well ecclesiastical as civil.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Canon A 7 &quot;Of the Royal Supremacy&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; In practice this power is often exercised through [[Parliament of the United Kingdom|Parliament]] and on the advice of the [[Prime Minister of the United Kingdom|Prime Minister]].

The [[Church of Ireland]] and the [[Church in Wales]] separated from the Church of England in 1869&lt;ref name=irishchurchact&gt;{{cite web|title=Irish Church Act 1869|url=http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/1869/42/enacted|publisher=Parliament of the United Kingdom|accessdate=10 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; and 1920&lt;ref name=&quot;wales-heritage&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Our Heritage: Facing Difficulties|url=http://www.churchinwales.org.uk/life/heritage/awi/part7.php|work=Church in Wales website|accessdate=10 October 2012|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130325125108/http://www.churchinwales.org.uk/life/heritage/awi/part7.php|archivedate=25 March 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; respectively and are autonomous churches in the Anglican Communion; Scotland's national church, the [[Church of Scotland]], is [[Presbyterianism|Presbyterian]], but the [[Scottish Episcopal Church]] is in the Anglican Communion.&lt;ref name=&quot;episcopal-history&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=History: The Revolution|url=http://www.scotland.anglican.org/index.php/about/history_chapter/8_the_revolution/|work=Scottish Episcopal Church website|accessdate=10 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition to England, the jurisdiction of the Church of England extends to the [[Isle of Man]], the [[Channel Islands]] and a few parishes in [[Flintshire]], [[Monmouthshire]], [[Powys]] and [[Radnorshire]] in Wales [[Church of England border polls 1915–1916|which voted to remain with the Church of England rather than joining the Church in Wales]].&lt;ref&gt;Cross, F. L. (ed.) (1957) Oxford Dictionary of the Christian Church; p. 1436&lt;/ref&gt; Expatriate congregations on the continent of Europe have become the [[Diocese of Gibraltar in Europe]].

The church is structured as follows (from the lowest level upwards):
[[File:TootBaldon StLawrence ParishChurch.JPG|thumb|right|The parish church of St Lawrence in [[Toot Baldon]] is typical of many small English village churches]]
* [[Parish]] is the most local level, often consisting of one church building and community, although many parishes are joining forces in a variety of ways for financial reasons. The parish is looked after by a parish [[Anglican priest|priest]] who for historical or legal reasons may be called by one of the following offices: [[vicar]], [[Rector (ecclesiastical)|rector]], [[priest in charge]], team rector, team vicar. The first, second, and fourth of these may also be known as the 'incumbent'. The running of the parish is the joint responsibility of the incumbent and the [[parochial church council]] (PCC), which consists of the parish clergy and elected representatives from the congregation. The Diocese of Gibraltar in Europe is not formally divided into parishes.
* There are a number of local churches that do not have a parish. In urban areas there are a number of [[proprietary chapel]]s (mostly built in the 19th century to cope with urbanisation and growth in population). Also in more recent years there are increasingly [[church plant]]s and [[fresh expression]]s of church, whereby new congregations are planted in locations such as schools or pubs to spread the Gospel of Christ in non-traditional ways.
[[File:Diocese of Gibraltar in Europe.PNG|thumb|right|Map showing the Diocese of Gibraltar in Europe with the archdeaconries colour-coded]]
* [[Deanery]], ''e.g.'', Lewisham or Runnymede. This is the area for which a [[Rural Dean]] (or area dean) is responsible. It consists of a number of parishes in a particular district. The rural dean is usually the incumbent of one of the constituent parishes. The parishes each elect lay (non-ordained) representatives to the deanery [[synod]]. Deanery synod members each have a vote in the election of representatives to the diocesan synod.
* Archdeaconry, ''e.g.'', the seven in the [[Diocese of Gibraltar in Europe]]. This is the area under the jurisdiction of an [[archdeacon]]. It consists of a number of deaneries.
* [[Diocese]], ''e.g.'', [[Diocese of Durham]], [[Diocese of Guildford]], [[Diocese of St Albans]]. This is the area under the jurisdiction of a diocesan bishop, ''e.g.'', the Bishops of Durham, Guildford and St Albans, and will have a cathedral. There may be one or more assisting bishops, usually called [[suffragan bishop]]s, within the diocese who assist the diocesan bishop in his ministry, ''e.g.'', in Guildford diocese, the Bishop of Dorking. In some very large dioceses a legal measure has been enacted to create &quot;episcopal areas&quot;, where the diocesan bishop runs one such area himself and appoints &quot;area bishops&quot; to run the other areas as mini-dioceses, legally delegating many of his powers to the area bishops. Dioceses with episcopal areas include [[Diocese of London|London]], [[Diocese of Chelmsford|Chelmsford]], [[Diocese of Oxford|Oxford]], [[Diocese of Chichester|Chichester]], [[Anglican Diocese of Southwark|Southwark]], and [[Diocese of Lichfield|Lichfield]]. The bishops work with an elected body of [[Laity|lay]] and [[ordained]] representatives, known as the [[Diocesan Synod]], to run the diocese. A diocese is subdivided into a number of archdeaconries.
* [[Ecclesiastical province|Province]], ''i.e.'', Canterbury or York. This is the area under the jurisdiction of an [[archbishop]], ''i.e.'' the Archbishops of Canterbury and York. Decision-making within the province is the responsibility of the [[General Synod]] (see also above). A province is subdivided into dioceses.
* [[Primacy of Canterbury|Primacy]], ''i.e.'', Church of England. In addition to his specific authority in his own province, each archbishop is &quot;Primate of All England&quot; (Canterbury) or &quot;Primate of England&quot; (York) and has powers that extend over the whole country—for example his licence to marry without the [[banns]] (marriage licence).
* [[Royal Peculiar]], a small number of churches which are more closely associated with [[the Crown]], and, a very few more closely associated with the law, and are outside the usual church hierarchy though conforming to the rite. These are outside episcopal jurisdiction.

All [[Vicar#Anglican|rectors and vicars]] are [[advowson|appointed by patrons]], who may be private individuals, corporate bodies such as cathedrals, colleges or trusts, or by the bishop or directly by the Crown. No clergy can be instituted and inducted into a parish without swearing the Oath of Allegiance to Her Majesty, and taking the Oath of Canonical Obedience &quot;in all things lawful and honest&quot; to the bishop. Usually they are instituted to the benefice by the bishop and then inducted by the archdeacon into the possession of the benefice property—church and parsonage. [[Curate]]s (assistant clergy) are appointed by rectors and vicars, or if priests-in-charge by the bishop after consultation with the patron. Cathedral clergy (normally a [[List of deans in the Church of England|dean]] and a varying number of residentiary canons who constitute the cathedral chapter) are appointed either by the Crown, the bishop, or by the dean and chapter themselves. Clergy officiate in a diocese either because they hold office as beneficed clergy or are licensed by the bishop when appointed, or simply with permission.

===Primates===
[[File:Archbishop of Canterbury (32195477582) (cropped).jpg|upright=0.8|thumb|right|[[Justin Welby]], [[Archbishop of Canterbury]]]]

The most senior bishop of the Church of England is the [[Archbishop of Canterbury]], who is the [[Metropolitan bishop|metropolitan]] of the southern province of England, the Province of Canterbury. He has the status of [[Primate (bishop)|Primate]] of All England. He is the focus of unity for the worldwide Anglican Communion of independent national or regional churches. [[Justin Welby]] has been Archbishop of Canterbury since the confirmation of his election on 4 February 2013.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-21315054|title=Justin Welby becomes Archbishop of Canterbury|work=BBC News}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The second most senior bishop is the [[Archbishop of York]], who is the metropolitan of the northern province of England, the Province of York. For historical reasons (relating to the time of York's control by the [[Danelaw|Danes]]) he is referred to as the Primate of England. [[John Sentamu]] became Archbishop of York in 2005. The Bishop of London, the Bishop of Durham and the Bishop of Winchester are ranked in the next three positions.

===Diocesan bishops===
The process of appointing diocesan bishops is complex, due to historical reasons balancing hierarchy against democracy, and is handled by the [[Appointment of Church of England bishops|Crown Nominations Committee]] which submits names to the Prime Minister (acting on behalf of the Crown) for consideration.

===Representative bodies===
{{Main|General Synod of the Church of England}}
The Church of England has a legislative body, the [[General Synod of the Church of England|General Synod]]. Synod can create two types of legislation, [[List of Church of England Measures|measures]] and [[canon law|canons]]. Measures have to be approved but cannot be amended by the [[Parliament of the United Kingdom|British Parliament]] before receiving the [[Royal Assent]] and becoming part of the law of England.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cofe.anglican.org/about/churchlawlegis/measures/|title=Summary of Church Assembly and General Synod Measures|date=November 2007|work=Church of England website|publisher=Archbishops' council of the Church of England}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although it is the [[state religion|established]] church in England only, its measures must be approved by both Houses of Parliament including the non-English members. Canons require Royal Licence and Royal Assent, but form the law of the church, rather than the law of the land.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cofe.anglican.org/about/gensynod/|title=General Synod|work=Church of England website|publisher=Archbishops' council of the Church of England|access-date=5 June 2010|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20041112052103/http://www.cofe.anglican.org/about/gensynod/|archive-date=12 November 2004|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another assembly is the [[Convocations of Canterbury and York|Convocation of the English Clergy]], which is older than the General Synod and its predecessor the Church Assembly. By the 1969 Synodical Government Measure almost all of the Convocations' functions were transferred to the General Synod. Additionally, there are [[Diocesan Synod]]s and [[Deanery#Anglican usage|deanery synods]], which are the governing bodies of the divisions of the Church.

===House of Lords===
{{Main|Lords Spiritual}}
Of the 42 diocesan [[archbishop]]s and bishops in the Church of England, 26 are permitted to sit in the [[House of Lords]]. The Archbishops of [[Archbishop of Canterbury|Canterbury]] and [[Archbishops of York|York]] automatically have seats, as do the Bishops of [[Bishop of London|London]], [[Bishop of Durham|Durham]] and [[Bishop of Winchester|Winchester]]. The remaining 21 seats are filled in order of seniority by [[consecration]]. It may take a diocesan bishop a number of years to reach the House of Lords, at which point he becomes a [[Lords Spiritual|Lord Spiritual]]. The [[Bishop of Sodor and Man]] and the [[Bishop of Gibraltar in Europe]] are not eligible to sit in the House of Lords as their dioceses lie outside the United Kingdom.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.parliament.uk/directories/house_of_lords_information_office/alphabetical_list_of_members.cfm House of Lords: alphabetical list of Members] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080702053341/http://www.parliament.uk/directories/house_of_lords_information_office/alphabetical_list_of_members.cfm |date=2 July 2008 }}. Retrieved 12 December 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Crown dependencies===
Although they are not part of [[England]] or the [[United Kingdom]], the Church of England is also the [[State religion|Established Church]] in the [[Crown dependencies]] of the [[Isle of Man]], the [[Jersey|Bailiwick of Jersey]] and the [[Bailiwick of Guernsey]]. The [[Isle of Man]] has its own diocese of [[Sodor and Man]], and the [[Bishop of Sodor and Man]] is an ex officio member of the [[Legislative Council of the Isle of Man|Legislative Council]] of the [[Tynwald]] on the island.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Gell|first1=Sir James|title=Gell on Manx Church|url=http://www.isle-of-man.com/manxnotebook/manxsoc/msvol31/gell.htm|website=Isle Of Man Online|publisher=IOM Online|accessdate=7 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Channel Islands]] are part of the [[Diocese of Winchester]], and in [[Jersey]] the [[Dean of Jersey]] is a non-voting member of the [[States of Jersey]]. In [[Guernsey]] the Church of England is the [[State religion|Established Church]], although the [[Dean of Guernsey]] is not a member of the [[States of Guernsey]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=About|url=http://www.churchofengland.org.gg/about|website=Guernsey Deanery|publisher=Church of England}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Sex abuse==
{{undue|date=December 2019}}
{{See also|Anglican Communion sexual abuse cases}}
The Archbishop of Canterbury, [[Justin Welby]], has made some effort to prevent complaints of [[Anglican Church sexual abuse cases|sex abuse cases]] being covered up. Independent investigators are examining files as far back as the 1950s and Welby hopes this independence will prevent any possibility of a [[cover-up]].&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-22498734 &quot;Inquiry into CofE cleric abuse claim set up&quot;], BBC.&lt;/ref&gt; 
{{quote|We will systematically bring those transparently and openly first of all working with the survivors where they are still alive and then seeing what they want.  The rule is survivors come first, not our own interests, and however important the person was, however distinguished, however well-known, survivors come first. (Justin Welby)}}

The personal files of all Church of England clergy since the 1950s are being audited in an effort to ensure no cover-up. Welby emphasised repeatedly that no cover-up would be acceptable.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/2014/oct/27/justin-welby-1950s-personnel-files-clergy-child-abuse-investigation-confessional-confidentiality &quot;Church of England to examine 1950s records in child abuse investigation&quot;], ''The Guardian'', 27 October 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite such assurances there is concern that not enough may be done and historic abuse may still sometimes be covered up. [[Keith Porteous Wood]] of the [[National Secular Society]] stated:
{{quote|The problem wasn't that bishops weren't trained in such matters, it is the institutional culture of denial and the bullying of the abused and whistleblowers into silence. One report suggests that 13 bishops ignored letters written in the 1990s warning of abuse by Ball on behalf of a victim who later committed suicide. I have seen evidence that such bullying persists to this day. I hope that the Archbishop's review into the case of Peter Ball will deal with such bullying and what appears to be the undue influence exerted on the police and CPS by the Church in dealing with this case. The total failure of procedures, outlined by Ian Elliott, echoes that revealed in the totally damning Cahill Report about the conduct of the Archbishop Hope of York in respect of Robert Waddington. The current Archbishop of York has decided that this report should remain in printed form rather than be more widely available on the web.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.secularism.org.uk/news/2016/03/church-cut-contact-with-child-abuse-victim-on-order-of-insurers|title=Church cut contact with child abuse victim on order of insurers|date=16 March 2016|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Bishop [[Peter Ball (bishop)|Peter Ball]] was convicted in October 2015 on several charges of indecent assault against young adult men.&lt;ref name=sentence2015&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/2015/oct/07/bishop-peter-ball-escaped-charges-mps-royal-family-intervened-court|title=Bishop escaped abuse charges after MPs and a royal backed him, court told |date=7 October 2015|accessdate=27 November 2015|newspaper=The Guardian|last=Laville|first=Sandra}}&lt;/ref&gt; There are allegations of large-scale earlier cover-ups involving many British establishment figures which prevented Ball's earlier prosecution. There have also been allegations of [[child sex abuse]], for example [[Robert Waddington#Allegations of abuse|Robert Waddington]]. A complainant, known only as &quot;Joe&quot;, tried for decades to have action taken over sadistic sex abuse which Garth Moore perpetrated against him in 1976 when &quot;Joe&quot; was 15 years old. None of the high ranking clergy who &quot;Joe&quot; spoke to recall being told about the abuse, which &quot;Joe&quot; considers incredible.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/mar/15/damning-report-reveals-church-of-england-failure-to-act-on-abuse &quot;Damning report reveals Church of England's failure to act on abuse&quot;], ''[[The Guardian]]'', 26 March 2015.&lt;/ref&gt; A representative of the solicitors firm representing &quot;Joe&quot; said: 
{{quote|The Church of England wants to bury and discourage allegations of non-recent abuse. They know how difficult it is for survivors to come forward, and it appears from this case that the Church has a plan of making it hard for these vulnerable people to come forward. This survivor has had the courage to press his case. Most do not. Most harbour the psychological fallout in silence. We need to find a way to make the system more approachable for survivors.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.churchtimes.co.uk/articles/2015/4-december/news/uk/survivor-reaches-settlement-with-diocese-on-historic-abuse &quot;Survivor reaches settlement with diocese on historic abuse&quot;], ''Church Times'', 4 December 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==Financial situation==
{{Main|Properties and finances of the Church of England}}
Although an [[established church]], the Church of England does not receive any direct government support. Donations comprise its largest source of income, and it also relies heavily on the income from its various historic endowments. In 2005, the Church of England had estimated total outgoings of around £900&amp;nbsp;million.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cofe.anglican.org/info/funding/ outgoings] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20061112115720/http://www.cofe.anglican.org/info/funding/ |date=12 November 2006 }}. Cofe.anglican.org.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Church of England manages an [[investment portfolio]] which is worth more than £8&amp;nbsp;billion.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Citing ethics, Anglicans sell stake in News Corp&quot; by Eric Pfanner, ''[[The New York Times]]'', 8 August 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Online church directory==
The Church of England supports ''A Church Near You'', an [[online]] directory of churches. A user-edited resource, it currently lists 16,400 churches and has 7,000 editors in 42 dioceses.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=A Church Near You Help|url=http://www.achurchnearyou.com/help/|website=achurchnearyou.com|publisher=A Church Near You|accessdate=25 December 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The directory enables parishes to maintain accurate location, contact and event information which is shared with other websites and [[mobile app]]s. In 2012, the directory formed the data backbone of Christmas Near You&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bristol.anglican.org/event/find-christmas-events-near-you/ Christmas Near You Announcement] {{webarchive|url=https://archive.is/20140807162230/http://www.bristol.anglican.org/event/find-christmas-events-near-you/ |date=7 August 2014 }} Accessed: 6 August 2014&lt;/ref&gt; and in 2014 was used to promote the church's Harvest Near You initiative.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.churchofengland.org/media-centre/news/2014/08/connect-with-food,-farming-countryside-at-a-harvest-near-you.aspx Harvest Near You announcement], Accessed 6 August 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Christianity|England}}
* [[List of the largest Protestant bodies]]
* [[Appointment of Church of England bishops]]
* [[Architecture of the medieval cathedrals of England]]
* [[Church Commissioners]]
* [[Church of England Newspaper]]
* [[Church of England parish church]]
* [[Mothers' Union]]
* [[Historical development of Church of England dioceses]]
* [[List of bishops in the Church of England]]
* [[List of archdeacons in the Church of England]]
* [[Ritualism in the Church of England]]
* [[List of the first 32 women ordained as Church of England priests]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
* Buchanan, Colin. ''Historical Dictionary of Anglicanism'' (2nd ed. 2015) [https://www.amazon.com/Historical-Dictionary-Anglicanism-Dictionaries-Philosophies/dp/1442250151 excerpt]
* Garbett, Cyril, Abp. ''The Church of England Today''. London: Hodder and Stoughton, 1953. 128 p.
* Hardwick, Joseph. ''An Anglican British world: The Church of England and the expansion of the settler empire, c. 1790–1860'' (Manchester UP, 2014).
* Hodges, J. P. ''The Nature of the Lion: Elizabeth I and Our Anglican Heritage''. London: Faith Press, 1962. 153 pp.
* Kirby, James. ''Historians and the Church of England: Religion and Historical Scholarship, 1870–1920'' (2016) online at {{DOI|10.1093/acprof:oso/9780198768159.001.0001}}
* Lawson, Tom. ''God and War: The Church of England and Armed Conflict in the Twentieth Century'' (Routledge, 2016).
* Maughan Steven S. ''Mighty England Do Good: Culture, Faith, Empire, and World in the Foreign Missions of the Church of England, 1850–1915'' (2014)
* Picton, Hervé. ''A Short History of the Church of England: From the Reformation to the Present Day''. Newcastle upon Tyne: Cambridge Scholars Publishing, 2015. 180 p.
* Rowlands, John Henry Lewis. ''Church, State, and Society, 1827–1845: the Attitudes of John Keble, Richard Hurrell Froude, and John Henry Newman''. (1989). xi, 262 p. {{ISBN|1-85093-132-1}}
* Tapsell, Grant. ''The later Stuart Church, 1660–1714'' (2012).

==External links==
{{Commons category|Church of England}}
* {{Official website}}
* [http://anglicanhistory.org/england/ Historical resources on the Church of England]
* [http://www.anglican.bb/hist Church of England history in the West Indies]
* The History Files: [http://www.historyfiles.co.uk/MainChurchesIndex.htm Churches of the British Isles], a gallery of church photos and information.

{{Archbishop of Canterbury}}
{{Anglican dioceses in UK}}
{{Anglican Bishops &amp; Archbishops - Great Britain}}
{{Anglican Communion Churches}}
{{Anglicanism (footer)}}
{{Porvoo Communion}}
{{Christianity footer}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=February 2019}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Church Of England}}
[[Category:Church of England]]
[[Category:Anglo-Catholicism]]
[[Category:Anglican Communion church bodies|England]]
[[Category:Anglicanism]]
[[Category:Members of the World Council of Churches|England]]
[[Category:National churches]]
[[Category:Christian denominations founded in Great Britain]]
[[Category:Christian organizations established in the 16th century]]
[[Category:Independent Catholic denominations]]
[[Category:State churches (Christian)|England]]</text>
      <sha1>bkzb004hja6enhgisc0qvp0lsyxxm9q</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
