  <page>
    <title>Capital punishment</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5902</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942463480</id>
      <parentid>942382329</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-24T20:52:45Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Iridescent</username>
        <id>937705</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Cleanup and [[WP:AWB/T|typo fixing]], [[WP:AWB/T|typo(s) fixed]]: 5-4 → 5–4 (2)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Death penalty as punishment for a crime}}
{{other uses|Capital punishment (disambiguation)|Letter case#Case styles}}
{{redirect-multi|3|Death penalty|Death sentence|Execution}}
{{pp-semi-indef}}
{{pp-move-indef}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2012}}
{{Criminal procedure (trial)}}

'''Capital punishment''', also known as the '''death penalty''', is a government-sanctioned practice whereby a person is put to [[death]] by the state as a punishment for a crime. The [[sentence (law)|sentence]] ordering that someone be punished in such a manner is referred to as a '''death sentence''', whereas the act of carrying out such a sentence is known as an '''execution'''. A prisoner who has been sentenced to death and is awaiting execution is referred to as '''condemned''', and is said to be on [[death row]]. Crimes that are punishable by death are known as '''capital crimes''', '''capital offences''' or '''capital felonies''', and vary depending on the jurisdiction, but commonly include serious offences such as [[murder]], [[mass murder]], aggravated cases of [[rape]], [[child rape]], [[child sexual abuse]], [[terrorism]], [[treason]], [[espionage]], [[sedition]], [[piracy]], [[aircraft hijacking]], [[drug trafficking]] and [[drug dealing]], [[war crime]]s, [[crimes against humanity]] and [[genocide]], and in some cases, the most serious acts of [[recidivism]], [[aggravated robbery]], and [[kidnapping]].

Etymologically, the term ''capital'' (lit. &quot;of the head&quot;, derived via the [[Latin]] ''{{lang|la|capitalis}}'' from ''{{lang|la|caput}}'', &quot;head&quot;) in this context alluded to execution by [[Decapitation|beheading]].&lt;ref name=&quot;KronenwetterP202&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Kronenwetter|2001|p=202}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Fifty-six countries retain capital punishment, 106 countries have completely abolished it ''[[de jure]]'' for all crimes, eight have abolished it for ordinary crimes (while maintaining it for special circumstances such as war crimes), and 28 are abolitionist in practice.&lt;ref name=&quot;Amnesty2018&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Abolitionist and Retentionist Countries as of July 2018 |url=https://www.amnesty.org/download/Documents/ACT5066652017ENGLISH.pdf |publisher=Amnesty International |accessdate=3 December 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Capital punishment is a matter of active controversy in several countries and states, and positions can vary within a single [[political ideology]] or cultural region. In the [[European Union]], Article 2 of the [[Charter of Fundamental Rights of the European Union]] prohibits the use of capital punishment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.europarl.europa.eu/charter/pdf/text_en.pdf |title=Charter of Fundamental Rights of the European Union |publisher=[[European Union]] |accessdate=23 August 2010 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100529042731/http://www.europarl.europa.eu/charter/pdf/text_en.pdf |archivedate=29 May 2010 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Council of Europe]], which has 47 member states, has sought to abolish the use of the death penalty by its members absolutely, through [[European Convention on Human Rights#Convention protocols|Protocol 13]] of the [[European Convention on Human Rights]]. However, this only affects those member states which have signed and ratified it, and they do not include [[Capital punishment in Armenia|Armenia]], [[Capital punishment in Russia|Russia]], and [[Capital punishment in Azerbaijan|Azerbaijan]].

The [[United Nations General Assembly]] has adopted, in 2007, 2008, 2010, 2012 and 2014,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.worldcoalition.org/united-nations-resolution-moratorium-death-penalty-executions-general-assembly.html |title=117 countries vote for a global moratorium on executions |work=World Coalition against the Death Penalty |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150402095919/http://www.worldcoalition.org/united-nations-resolution-moratorium-death-penalty-executions-general-assembly.html |archivedate=2 April 2015 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; non-binding resolutions calling for a [[UN moratorium on the death penalty|global moratorium on executions]], with a view to eventual abolition.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.un.org/apps/news/story.asp?NewsID=24679&amp;Cr=general&amp;Cr1=assembly |title=moratorium on the death penalty |publisher=[[United Nations]] |date=15 November 2007 |accessdate=23 August 2010 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110127183625/http://www.un.org/apps/news/story.asp?NewsID=24679&amp;Cr=general&amp;Cr1=assembly |archivedate=27 January 2011 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Although most nations have abolished capital punishment, over 60% of the world's population live in countries where the death penalty is retained, such as [[Capital punishment in China|China]], [[Capital punishment in India|India]], the [[Capital punishment in the United States|United States]], [[Capital punishment in Indonesia|Indonesia]], [[Capital punishment in Pakistan|Pakistan]], [[Capital punishment in Bangladesh|Bangladesh]], [[Capital punishment in Nigeria|Nigeria]], [[Capital punishment in Ethiopia|Ethiopia]], [[Capital punishment in Egypt|Egypt]], [[Capital punishment in Saudi Arabia|Saudi Arabia]], [[Capital punishment in Iran|Iran]], among almost all mostly [[Islamic countries]], as is maintained in [[Capital punishment in Japan|Japan]], [[Capital punishment in South Korea|South Korea]], [[Capital punishment in Taiwan|Taiwan]], and [[Capital punishment in Sri Lanka|Sri Lanka]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.amnesty.org/en/what-we-do/death-penalty/ |title=Death Penalty |publisher=[[Amnesty International]] |access-date=2016-08-23 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160822235316/https://www.amnesty.org/en/what-we-do/death-penalty/ |archivedate=22 August 2016 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.atimes.com/atimes/South_Asia/FH13Df03.html |title=India: Death penalty debate won't die out soon |work=Asia Times |date=13 August 2004 |accessdate=23 August 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.worldcoalition.org/modules/smartsection/item.php?itemid=325&amp;sel_lang=english |title=Indonesian activists face upward death penalty trend |publisher=World Coalition against the Death Penalty |accessdate=23 August 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.iht.com/articles/2009/03/14/america/death.php |title=Legislators in U.S. state vote to repeal death penalty |date=29 March 2009 |work=[[International Herald Tribune]] |accessdate=23 August 2010 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090316003328/http://www.iht.com/articles/2009/03/14/america/death.php |archivedate=16 March 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.fidh.org/THE-DEATH-PENALTY-IN-JAPAN |title=The Death Penality in Japan |publisher=[[International Federation for Human Rights]] |accessdate=23 August 2010 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100828065156/http://www.fidh.org/THE-DEATH-PENALTY-IN-JAPAN |archivedate=28 August 2010 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;  China is believed to execute more people than all other countries combined.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Canadian's death sentence in China 'horrific', family says |url=https://www.bbc.com/news/amp/world-asia-china-46872651 |accessdate=15 January 2019 |work=BBC |date=15 January 2019 |quote=China is believed to execute more people annually than any other country, but is highly secretive about the number.  Human rights group Amnesty International puts the figure in the thousands - more than the rest of the world's nations put together.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
[[File:Auguste Vaillant execution.jpg|thumb|upright|Anarchist [[Auguste Vaillant]] guillotined in France in 1894]]

Execution of [[criminal]]s and [[dissident]]s has been used by nearly all societies since the [[beginning of civilizations]] on Earth.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title= Criminal Justice: Capital Punishment Focus |url= https://www.criminaljusticedegreeschools.com/criminal-justice-resources/criminal-justice-capital-punishment-focus/ |publisher= criminaljusticedegreeschools.com |accessdate= 27 August 2017 |url-status=live |archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20170827171830/https://www.criminaljusticedegreeschools.com/criminal-justice-resources/criminal-justice-capital-punishment-focus/ |archivedate= 27 August 2017 |df= dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Until the nineteenth century, without developed prison systems, there was frequently no workable alternative to ensure deterrence and incapacitation of criminals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title= Furman v. Georgia – MR. JUSTICE BRENNAN, concurring. |url= https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/408/238#writing-USSC_CR_0408_0238_ZC1 |publisher= law.cornell.edu |quote= When this country was founded, memories of the Stuart horrors were fresh and severe corporal punishments were common. Death was not then a unique punishment. The practice of punishing criminals by death, moreover, was widespread and by and large acceptable to society. Indeed, without developed prison systems, there was frequently no workable alternative. Since that time, successive restrictions, imposed against the background of a continuing moral controversy, have drastically curtailed the use of this punishment. |accessdate= 19 July 2017 |url-status=live |archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20170718190721/https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/408/238#writing-USSC_CR_0408_0238_ZC1 |archivedate= 18 July 2017 |df= dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[pre-modern]] times the executions themselves often involved torture with cruel and painful methods, such as the [[breaking wheel]], [[keelhauling]], [[death by sawing|sawing]], [[Hanged, drawn and quartered|hanging, drawing, and quartering]], [[brazen bull]], [[burning at the stake]], [[flaying]], [[slow slicing]], [[boiling alive]], [[impalement]], [[mazzatello]], [[blowing from a gun]], [[schwedentrunk]], [[blood eagle]], and [[scaphism]].

The use of formal execution extends to the beginning of recorded history. Most historical records and various primitive tribal practices indicate that the death penalty was a part of their justice system. Communal punishments for wrongdoing generally included [[Blood money (restitution)|blood money]] compensation by the wrongdoer, [[corporal punishment]], [[shunning]], [[exile|banishment]] and execution. In tribal societies, compensation and shunning were often considered enough as a form of justice.&lt;ref&gt;So common was the practice of compensation that the word ''murder'' is derived from the French word ''mordre'' (bite) a reference to the heavy compensation one must pay for causing an unjust death. The &quot;bite&quot; one had to pay was used as a term for the crime itself: &quot;Mordre wol out; that se we day by day.&quot; – [[Geoffrey Chaucer]] (1340–1400), [[The Canterbury Tales]], ''The Nun's Priest's Tale'', l. 4242 (1387–1400), repr. In ''The Works of Geoffrey Chaucer'', ed. Alfred W. Pollard, et al. (1898).&lt;/ref&gt; The response to crimes committed by neighbouring tribes, clans or communities included a formal apology, compensation, blood [[feud]]s, and [[tribal warfare]].

A [[Feud|blood feud]] or vendetta occurs when arbitration between families or tribes fails or an arbitration system is non-existent. This form of justice was common before the emergence of an arbitration system based on state or organized religion. It may result from crime, land disputes or a code of honour. &quot;Acts of retaliation underscore the ability of the social collective to defend itself and demonstrate to enemies (as well as potential allies) that injury to property, rights, or the person will not go unpunished.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Translated from Waldmann, ''op.cit.'', p. 147.&lt;/ref&gt;

In most countries that practise capital punishment, it is now reserved for [[murder]], [[terrorism]], [[war crimes]], [[espionage]], [[treason]], or as part of military justice.  In some countries [[sexual crime]]s, such as [[rape]], [[fornication]], [[adultery]], [[incest]], [[sodomy]], and [[bestiality]] carry the death penalty, as do religious crimes such as [[Hudud]], [[Zina]], and [[Qisas]] crimes, such as [[Apostasy from Islam|apostasy]] (formal renunciation of the [[state religion]]), [[Islam and blasphemy|blasphemy]], [[moharebeh]], [[hirabah]], [[Fasad]], [[Mofsed-e-filarz]] and [[witchcraft]]. In many [[Use of capital punishment by nation|countries that use the death penalty]], [[drug trafficking]] and often [[drug possession]] is also a capital offence. In China, [[Trafficking in human beings|human trafficking]] and serious cases of [[Political corruption|corruption]] and [[financial crime]]s are punished by the death penalty. In militaries around the world [[courts-martial]] have imposed death sentences for offences such as [[cowardice]], [[desertion]], [[insubordination]], and [[mutiny]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.shotatdawn.org.uk/ |title=Shot at Dawn, campaign for pardons for British and Commonwealth soldiers executed in World War I |accessdate=20 July 2006 |publisher=Shot at Dawn Pardons Campaign |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20060703143147/http://www.shotatdawn.org.uk/ |archivedate=3 July 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ancient history===
[[File:Jean-Léon Gérôme - The Christian Martyrs' Last Prayer - Walters 37113.jpg|thumb|left|''The Christian Martyrs' Last Prayer'', by [[Jean-Léon Gérôme]] (1883). [[Roman Empire|Roman]] [[Colosseum]].]]
Elaborations of tribal arbitration of [[feud]]s included peace settlements often done in a religious context and compensation system. Compensation was based on the principle of ''substitution'' which might include material (for example, cattle, slaves, land) compensation, exchange of brides or grooms, or payment of the blood debt. Settlement rules could allow for animal blood to replace human blood, or transfers of property or [[Blood money (term)|blood money]] or in some case an offer of a person for execution. The person offered for execution did not have to be an original perpetrator of the crime because the social system was based on tribes and clans, not individuals. Blood feuds could be regulated at meetings, such as the [[Norsemen]] ''[[Thing (assembly)|things]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Lindow, ''op.cit.'' (primarily discusses Icelandic ''things'').&lt;/ref&gt; Systems deriving from blood feuds may survive alongside more advanced legal systems or be given recognition by courts (for example, [[trial by combat]] or blood money). One of the more modern refinements of the blood feud is the [[duel]].
[[File:Schnorr_von_Carolsfeld_Bibel_in_Bildern_1860_187.png|thumbnail|[[Beheading of John the Baptist]], woodcut by [[Julius Schnorr von Karolsfeld]], 1860]]
In certain parts of the world, nations in the form of ancient republics, monarchies or tribal oligarchies emerged. These nations were often united by common linguistic, religious or family ties. Moreover, expansion of these nations often occurred by conquest of neighbouring tribes or nations. Consequently, various classes of royalty, nobility, various commoners and slaves emerged. Accordingly, the systems of tribal arbitration were submerged into a more unified system of justice which formalized the relation between the different &quot;[[social class]]es&quot; rather than &quot;tribes&quot;. The earliest and most famous example is [[Code of Hammurabi]] which set the different punishment and compensation, according to the different class/group of victims and perpetrators. The [[Torah]] (Jewish Law), also known as the [[Pentateuch]] (the first five books of the Christian [[Old Testament]]), lays down the death penalty for murder, [[kidnapping]], practicing [[Magic (paranormal)|magic]], violation of the [[Shabbat|Sabbath]], [[blasphemy]], and a wide range of sexual crimes, although evidence suggests that actual executions were rare.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|first=William|last=Schabas|year=2002|title=The Abolition of the Death Penalty in International Law|publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=978-0-521-81491-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A further example comes from [[Ancient Greece]], where the [[Athenian]] legal system replacing [[customary law|customary]] [[oral law]] was first written down by [[Draco (lawgiver)|Draco]] in about 621 BC: the death penalty was applied for a particularly wide range of crimes, though [[Solon]] later repealed Draco's code and published new laws, retaining capital punishment only for intentional [[homicide]], and only with victim's family permission.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Robert|url=http://history-world.org/draco_and_solon_laws.htm|title=Greece, A History of Ancient Greece, Draco and Solon Laws|publisher=History-world.org|accessdate=23 August 2010|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20101021023919/http://history-world.org/draco_and_solon_laws.htm|archivedate=21 October 2010|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; The word [[wikt:draconian|draconian]] derives from Draco's laws. The [[Ancient Rome|Romans]] also used death penalty for a wide range of offences.&lt;ref name=britannica&gt;{{cite encyclopedia|url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/93902/capital-punishment|title=capital punishment (law) – Britannica Online Encyclopedia|encyclopedia=Britannica.com|accessdate=12 December 2012|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20121122091559/http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/93902/capital-punishment|archivedate=22 November 2012|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Tang dynasty===
Although many are executed in the [[Capital punishment in China|People's Republic of China]] each year in the present day, there was a time in the [[Tang dynasty]] (618–907) when the death penalty was abolished.&lt;ref name=&quot;benn 8&quot;&gt;Benn, p. 8.&lt;/ref&gt; This was in the year 747, enacted by [[Emperor Xuanzong of Tang]] (r. 712–756). When abolishing the death penalty Xuanzong ordered his officials to refer to the nearest regulation by analogy when sentencing those found guilty of crimes for which the prescribed punishment was execution. Thus depending on the severity of the crime a punishment of severe scourging with the thick rod or of exile to the remote Lingnan region might take the place of capital punishment. However, the death penalty was restored only 12 years later in 759 in response to the [[An Lushan Rebellion]].&lt;ref&gt;Benn, pp. 209–210&lt;/ref&gt; At this time in the Tang dynasty only the emperor had the authority to sentence criminals to execution. Under [[Emperor Xuanzong of Tang|Xuanzong]] capital punishment was relatively infrequent, with only 24 executions in the year 730 and 58 executions in the year 736.&lt;ref name=&quot;benn 8&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Lingchi (cropped).jpg|thumb|upright=0.95|Ling Chi – execution by [[slow slicing]] – was a form of torture and execution used in China from roughly AD 900 ([[Tang dynasty|Tang]] era) until it was banned in 1905.]]
The two most common forms of execution in the Tang dynasty were strangulation and decapitation, which were the prescribed methods of execution for 144 and 89 offences respectively. Strangulation was the prescribed sentence for lodging an accusation against one's parents or grandparents with a magistrate, scheming to kidnap a person and sell them into slavery and opening a coffin while desecrating a tomb. Decapitation was the method of execution prescribed for more serious crimes such as treason and sedition. Despite the great discomfort involved, most of the Tang Chinese preferred strangulation to decapitation, as a result of the traditional Tang Chinese belief that the body is a gift from the parents and that it is, therefore, disrespectful to one's ancestors to die without returning one's body to the grave intact.

Some further forms of capital punishment were practised in the Tang dynasty, of which the first two that follow at least were extralegal.{{Clarify|if they were extra-legal, they fail the definition of CapPun|date=July 2016}} The first of these was scourging to death with the thick rod{{Clarify|what is scourging with a thick rod? Anal?|date=July 2016}} which was common throughout the Tang dynasty especially in cases of gross corruption. The second was truncation, in which the convicted person was cut in two at the waist with a fodder knife and then left to bleed to death.&lt;ref name=Benn210&gt;Benn, p. 210&lt;/ref&gt; A further form of execution called Ling Chi ([[slow slicing]]), or death by/of a thousand cuts, was used from the close of the Tang dynasty (around 900) to its abolition in 1905.

When a minister of the fifth grade or above received a death sentence the emperor might grant him a special dispensation allowing him to commit suicide in lieu of execution. Even when this privilege was not granted, the law required that the condemned minister be provided with food and ale by his keepers and transported to the execution ground in a cart rather than having to walk there.

Nearly all executions under the Tang dynasty took place in public as a warning to the population. The heads of the executed were displayed on poles or spears. When local authorities decapitated a convicted criminal, the head was boxed and sent to the capital as proof of identity and that the execution had taken place.&lt;ref name=Benn210 /&gt;

===Middle Ages===
[[File:Rohrbach-verbrennung-1525.jpg|thumb|upright|The burning of Jakob Rohrbach, a leader of the peasants during the [[German Peasants' War]].]]
[[File:Lamanie kolem L 001xx.jpg|thumb|left|upright|The [[breaking wheel]] was used during the Middle Ages and was still in use into the 19th century.]]

In [[Middle Age|medieval]] and early modern Europe, before the development of modern [[prison]] systems, the death penalty was also used as a generalized form of punishment. During the reign of [[Henry VIII of England]], as many as 72,000 people are estimated to have been executed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/frontline/shows/execution/readings/history.html|title=History of the Death Penalty|publisher=Public Broadcasting Service|accessdate=12 December 2012|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20121113123001/http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/frontline/shows/execution/readings/history.html|archivedate=13 November 2012|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In early modern Europe, a massive [[moral panic]] regarding [[witchcraft]] swept across Europe and later the European colonies in North America. During this period, there were widespread claims that malevolent [[Satanism|Satanic]] [[witchcraft|witches]] were operating as an organized threat to [[Christendom]]. As a result, tens of thousands of women were prosecuted for witchcraft and executed through the [[witch trials in the early modern period|witch trials of the early modern period]] (between the 15th and 18th centuries).

The death penalty also targeted sexual offences such as [[sodomy]]. In England, the [[Buggery Act 1533]] stipulated hanging as punishment for &quot;[[buggery]]&quot;. [[James Pratt and John Smith]] were the last two Englishmen to be executed for sodomy in 1835.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | title=A Gay History of Britain: Love and Sex Between Men Since the Middle Ages | publisher=[[Greenwood World Publishing]] | last1=Cook |first1=Matt | last2=Mills |first2=Robert | last3=Trumback |first3=Randolph | last4=Cocks |first4=Harry | year=2007 |page=109| isbn=978-1846450020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite the wide use of the death penalty, calls for reform were not unknown. The 12th century [[Jewish]] legal scholar, Moses [[Maimonides]], wrote, &quot;It is better and more satisfactory to acquit a thousand guilty persons than to put a single innocent man to death.&quot; He argued that executing an accused criminal on anything less than absolute certainty would lead to a slippery slope of decreasing [[Legal burden of proof|burdens of proof]], until we would be convicting merely &quot;according to the judge's caprice&quot;. Maimonides's concern was maintaining popular respect for law, and he saw errors of commission as much more threatening than errors of omission.&lt;ref name=&quot;Moses Maimonides 1967&quot;&gt;Moses Maimonides, ''The Commandments, Neg. Comm. 290'', at 269–71 (Charles B. Chavel trans., 1967).&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Abbasid]] [[Caliph]]s in [[Baghdad]], such as [[Al-Mu'tadid]], were often cruel in their punishments.&lt;ref&gt;''The Caliphate: Its Rise, Decline, and Fall.'', [[William Muir]]&lt;/ref&gt;{{Page needed|date=December 2017}}

===Modern era===
[[File:Beccaria - Dei delitti e delle pene - 6043967 A.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Wikt:antiporta|''Antiporta'']] of ''Dei delitti e delle pene'' (''On Crimes and Punishments''), 1766 ed.]]

In the last several centuries, with the emergence of modern [[nation state]]s, justice came to be increasingly associated with the concept of [[natural and legal rights]]. The period saw an increase in standing police forces and permanent penitential institutions. [[Rational choice theory (criminology)|Rational choice theory]], a [[utilitarian]] approach to [[criminology]] which justifies punishment as a form of deterrence as opposed to retribution, can be traced back to [[Cesare, Marquis of Beccaria|Cesare Beccaria]], whose influential treatise ''[[Dei delitti e delle pene|On Crimes and Punishments]]'' (1764) was the first detailed analysis of capital punishment to demand the abolition of the death penalty.&lt;ref&gt;Marcello Maestro, &quot;A pioneer for the abolition of capital punishment: Cesare Beccaria.&quot; ''Journal of the History of Ideas'' 34.3 (1973): 463-468. [https://www.jstor.org/stable/2708966 online]&lt;/ref&gt;  In England [[Jeremy Bentham]] (1748-1832), the founder of modern utilitarianism, called for the abolition of the death penalty.&lt;ref name=&quot;deathpenalty&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|doi=10.2307/1143143|author1=Bedau, Hugo Adam|title=Bentham's Utilitarian Critique of the Death Penalty|journal=The Journal of Criminal Law and Criminology|volume=74|issue=3|date=Autumn 1983|pages=1033–65|jstor=1143143|ref=harv|url=http://scholarlycommons.law.northwestern.edu/jclc/vol74/iss3/12|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170831041015/http://scholarlycommons.law.northwestern.edu/jclc/vol74/iss3/12/|archivedate=31 August 2017|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; Beccaria, and later [[Charles Dickens]] and [[Karl Marx]] noted the incidence of increased violent criminality at the times and places of executions. Official recognition of this phenomenon led to executions being carried out inside prisons, away from public view.

In England in the 18th century, when there was no police force, Parliament drastically increased the number of capital offences to more than 200. These were mainly property offences, for example cutting down a cherry tree in an orchard.&lt;ref name=&quot;JonesJohnstone2011&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author1=Mark Jones|author2=Peter Johnstone|title=History of Criminal Justice|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=qhPdaCJWQikC&amp;pg=PA152|date=22 July 2011|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-1-4377-3491-1|pages=150–}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1820, there were 160, including crimes such as shoplifting, petty theft or stealing cattle.&lt;ref&gt;Durant, Will and Ariel, ''The Story of Civilization, Volume IX: The Age of Voltaire'' New York, 1965, p. 71&lt;/ref&gt; The severity of the so-called [[Bloody Code]] was often tempered by juries who refused to convict, or judges, in the case of petty theft, who arbitrarily set the value stolen at below the statutory level for a capital crime.&lt;ref&gt;Durant, p. 72,&lt;/ref&gt;

===20th century===
[[File:Mexican execution, 1914.jpg|left|thumb|Mexican execution by firing squad, 1916]]

In [[Nazi Germany#Law|Nazi Germany]] there were three types of capital punishment; hanging, decapitation and death by shooting.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=gN0QgcW4Td0C&amp;pg=PA289|page= 289|title=The criminal law of Japan: the general part|author=Dando Shigemitsu|year=1999|isbn= 9780837706535}}&lt;/ref&gt; Also, modern military organisations employed capital punishment as a means of maintaining military discipline. In the past, [[cowardice]], absence without leave, [[desertion]], [[insubordination]], shirking under enemy fire and disobeying orders were often crimes punishable by death (see [[Decimation (Roman army)|decimation]] and [[running the gauntlet]]). One method of execution, since firearms came into common use, has also been [[firing squad]], although some countries use execution with a single shot to the head or neck.
[[File:German announcement General Government Poland 1944.jpg|thumb|50 Poles tried and sentenced to death by a ''[[drumhead court-martial|Standgericht]]'' in retaliation for the assassination of 1 German policeman in [[Nazi crimes against the Polish nation|Nazi-occupied Poland]], 1944]]
[[File:Antanas Smetona 2.jpg|thumb|right|upright|[[President of Lithuania|Lithuanian President]] [[Antanas Smetona]]'s regime was the first in Europe to sentence [[Nazis]] and [[Communists]] to death; both were seen as a threat to the [[Act of Independence of Lithuania|Independence]] of [[Lithuania]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| first=Alfonsas |last=Eidintas |year=2015 | title=Antanas Smetona and His Lithuania: From the National Liberation Movement to an Authoritarian Regime (1893–1940) |translator=[[Alfred Erich Senn]] |publisher=Brill Rodopi |series=On the Boundary of Two Worlds |isbn=9789004302037 |page=301 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
Various authoritarian states—for example those with Fascist or Communist governments—employed the death penalty as a potent means of [[political repression|political oppression]]. According to [[Robert Conquest]], the leading expert on [[Joseph Stalin#Famine and the Great Terror: 1932–1939|Joseph Stalin's purges]], more than one million [[Soviet Union#Stalin era|Soviet citizens were executed]] during [[the Great Terror]] of 1937–38, almost all by a bullet to the back of the head.&lt;ref&gt;Conquest, Robert, ''[[The Great Terror]]: A Reassessment'', New York, pp. 485–86&lt;/ref&gt; [[Mao Zedong]] publicly stated that &quot;800,000&quot; people had been executed in China during the [[Cultural Revolution]] (1966–1976). Partly as a response to such excesses, civil rights organizations started to place increasing emphasis on the concept of [[human rights]] and an abolition of the death penalty.

===Contemporary era===

Among countries around the world, all European (except [[Capital punishment in Belarus|Belarus]]) and many [[Oceania]]n states (including [[Capital punishment in Australia|Australia]] and [[Capital punishment in New Zealand|New Zealand]]), and [[Capital punishment in Canada|Canada]] have abolished capital punishment. In [[Latin America]], most states have completely abolished the use of capital punishment, while some countries such as [[Capital punishment in Brazil|Brazil]] and [[Capital punishment in Guatemala|Guatemala]] allow for capital punishment only in exceptional situations, such as treason committed during wartime. The [[Capital punishment in the United States|United States]] (the federal government and 29 of the states), some [[Caribbean]] countries and the majority of countries in Asia (for example, [[Capital punishment in Japan|Japan]] and [[Capital punishment in India|India]]) retain capital punishment. In Africa, less than half of countries retain it, for example [[Capital punishment in Botswana|Botswana]] and [[Zambia]]. South Africa [[Capital punishment in South Africa|abolished the death penalty]] in 1995.

Abolition was often adopted due to political change, as when countries shifted from authoritarianism to democracy, or when it became an entry condition for the European Union. The United States is a notable exception: some states have had bans on capital punishment for decades, the earliest being [[Michigan]] where it was abolished in 1846, while other states still actively use it today. The death penalty in the United States remains a contentious issue which is [[Capital punishment debate in the United States|hotly debated]].

In retentionist countries, the debate is sometimes revived when a miscarriage of justice has occurred though this tends to cause legislative efforts to improve the judicial process rather than to abolish the death penalty. In abolitionist countries, the debate is sometimes revived by particularly brutal murders though few countries have brought it back after abolishing it. However, a spike in serious, violent crimes, such as murders or terrorist attacks, has prompted some countries to effectively end the moratorium on the death penalty. One notable example is [[Capital punishment in Pakistan|Pakistan]] which in December 2014 lifted a six-year moratorium on executions after the [[2014 Peshawar school massacre|Peshawar school massacre]] during which 132 students and 9 members of staff of the Army Public School and Degree College Peshawar were killed by [[Taliban]] terrorists. Since then, Pakistan has executed over 400 convicts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title= 465 prisoners sent to gallows since 2014, says report |url= https://tribune.com.pk/story/1451615/465-prisoners-sent-gallows-since-2014-says-report/ |publisher= tribune.com.pk |accessdate= 19 July 2017 |url-status=live |archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20170706181850/https://tribune.com.pk/story/1451615/465-prisoners-sent-gallows-since-2014-says-report/ |archivedate= 6 July 2017 |df= dmy-all |date= 2017-07-06 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2017 two major countries, [[Capital punishment in Turkey|Turkey]] and the [[Capital punishment in the Philippines|Philippines]], saw their executives making moves to reinstate the death penalty.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.presstv.com/Detail/2017/03/19/514877/turkey-erdogan-referendum-death-penalty|title=PressTV-Erdogan vows to reinstate death penalty|publisher=|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170412143142/http://presstv.com/Detail/2017/03/19/514877/turkey-erdogan-referendum-death-penalty|archivedate=12 April 2017|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;dpnythouse&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2017/03/01/world/asia/philippines-death-penalty.html|title=Philippines Moves Closer to Reinstating Death Penalty|first=Felipe|last=Villamor|date=1 March 2017|publisher=|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170302103805/https://www.nytimes.com/2017/03/01/world/asia/philippines-death-penalty.html|archivedate=2 March 2017|df=dmy-all|newspaper=The New York Times}}&lt;/ref&gt;  {{as of|2017|3&lt;!-- per the date of the cited supporting source --&gt;}}, passage of the law in the Philippines awaits the Senate's approval.&lt;ref name=&quot;dpnythouse&quot;/&gt;

==Modern-day public opinion==
The public opinion on the death penalty varies considerably by country and by the crime in question. Countries where a majority of people are against execution include Norway, where only 25% are in favour.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://usatoday30.usatoday.com/news/world/2011-07-27-Norway-punishment-lenient-death-penalty_n.htm |title=Can Norwegian punishment fit the crime? |work=USA Today |date= |accessdate=2014-07-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; Most French, Finns, and Italians also oppose the death penalty.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.deathpenaltyinfo.org/international-polls-and-studies |title=International Polls and Studies &amp;#124; Death Penalty Information Center |publisher=Deathpenaltyinfo.org |date= |accessdate=2014-07-09 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140519112648/http://www.deathpenaltyinfo.org/international-polls-and-studies |archivedate=19 May 2014 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; A 2016 Gallup poll shows that 60% of Americans support the death penalty, down from 64% in 2010, 65% in 2006, and 68% in 2001.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.gallup.com/poll/196676/death-penalty-support.aspx|title=U.S. Death Penalty Support at 60%|last=Inc.|first=Gallup|date=|work=Gallup.com|access-date=2017-05-20|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170319132515/http://www.gallup.com/poll/196676/death-penalty-support.aspx|archive-date=2017-03-19|url-status=|language=en-us}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-15028665|work=BBC News|title=Troy Davis' execution and the limits of Twitter|date=23 September 2011|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110923093611/http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-15028665|archivedate=23 September 2011|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gallup.com/poll/144284/support-death-penalty-cases-murder.aspx|title=In U.S., 64% Support Death Penalty in Cases of Murder|publisher=Gallup.com|accessdate=30 April 2012|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120429084914/http://www.gallup.com/poll/144284/Support-Death-Penalty-Cases-Murder.aspx|archivedate=29 April 2012|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The support and sentencing of capital punishment has been growing in India in the 2010s&lt;ref name=&quot;slate.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last=Keating |first=Joshua |url=http://www.slate.com/blogs/the_world_/2014/04/04/gang_rapists_sentenced_to_death_in_india_is_capital_punishment_starting.html |title=Gang rapists sentenced to death in India: Is capital punishment making a global comeback? |publisher=Slate.com |date=2014-04-04 |accessdate=2014-07-09 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140706073215/http://www.slate.com/blogs/the_world_/2014/04/04/gang_rapists_sentenced_to_death_in_india_is_capital_punishment_starting.html |archivedate=6 July 2014 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; due to anger over several recent brutal cases of rape, even though actual executions are comparatively rare.&lt;ref name=&quot;slate.com&quot;/&gt; While support for the death penalty for murder is still high in China, executions have dropped precipitously, with 3,000 executed in 2012 versus 12,000 in 2002.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.economist.com/news/china/21582557-most-worlds-sharp-decline-executions-can-be-credited-china-strike-less-hard |title=The death penalty: Strike less hard – Most of the world's sharp decline in executions can be credited to China |newspaper=The Economist |date=2013-08-03 |accessdate=2014-07-09 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140803145708/http://www.economist.com/news/china/21582557-most-worlds-sharp-decline-executions-can-be-credited-china-strike-less-hard |archivedate=3 August 2014 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; A poll in South Africa, where slavery is abolished, found that 76% of [[millennial]] South Africans support re-introduction of the death penalty due to increasing incidents of rape and murder.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Location Settings |url=http://www.news24.com/SouthAfrica/News/Youth-want-death-penalty-reinstated-20130222 |title=Youth 'want death penalty reinstated' |publisher=News24 |date=2013-02-22 |accessdate=2014-07-09 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140519221606/http://www.news24.com/southafrica/news/youth-want-death-penalty-reinstated-20130222 |archivedate=19 May 2014 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://businesstech.co.za/news/government/86844/why-the-death-penalty-wont-solve-sas-crime-problem/|title=Why the death penalty won't solve SA's crime problem|last=|first=|date=2015-05-09|website=BusinessTech|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
A 2017 poll found younger [[Mexicans]] are more likely to support capital punishment than older ones.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://phys.org/news/2017-03-death-penalty-mexico.html |title=Study examines death penalty support in Mexico |date=28 March 2017 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20171228172630/https://phys.org/news/2017-03-death-penalty-mexico.html |archivedate=28 December 2017 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; 57% of Brazilians support the death penalty. The age group that shows the greatest support for execution of those condemned is the 25 to 34-year-old category, in which 61% say they are in favor.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www1.folha.uol.com.br/internacional/en/brazil/2018/01/1949074-support-for-death-penalty-at-record-levels-among-brazilians-datafolha-finds.shtml/ |title=Folha de S.Paulo: Notícias, Imagens, Vídeos e Entrevistas |accessdate=2018-01-10 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20180109153132/http://www1.folha.uol.com.br/internacional/en/brazil/2018/01/1949074-support-for-death-penalty-at-record-levels-among-brazilians-datafolha-finds.shtml |archivedate=9 January 2018 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Movements towards non-painful execution==
{{Further|Cruel and unusual punishment}}
[[File:SQ Lethal Injection Room.jpg|thumb|upright=1.35|A gurney at [[San Quentin State Prison]] in [[California]] formerly used for executions by [[lethal injection]]]]
Trends in most of the world have long been to move to private and less painful executions. France developed the [[guillotine]] for this reason in the final years of the 18th century, while Britain banned [[Hanged, drawn and quartered|hanging, drawing, and quartering]] in the early 19th century. [[Hanging]] by turning the victim off a ladder or by kicking a stool or a bucket, which causes death by suffocation, was replaced by [[hanging|long drop &quot;hanging&quot;]] where the subject is dropped a longer distance to [[Cervical dislocation|dislocate the neck]] and sever the [[spinal cord]]. [[Mozaffar ad-Din Shah Qajar]], [[Qajar dynasty#Qajar Shahs of Persia, 1794–1925|Shah of Persia (1896–1907)]] introduced throat-cutting and [[blowing from a gun]] (close-range cannon fire) as quick and relatively painless alternatives to more torturous methods of executions used at that time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|chapter-url=http://explorion.net/ride-india-across-persia-and-baluchistan/chapter-vii-ispahan-shiraz?page=3&amp;quicktabs_3=1|title=A Ride to India across Persia and Baluchistan|year=1901|chapter=Ispahan – Shiraz|publisher=Explorion.net|accessdate=23 February 2011|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110718200923/http://explorion.net/ride-india-across-persia-and-baluchistan/chapter-vii-ispahan-shiraz?page=3&amp;quicktabs_3=1|archivedate=18 July 2011|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the United States, [[electrocution]] and [[gas chamber|gas inhalation]] were introduced as more humane alternatives to hanging, but have been almost entirely superseded by [[lethal injection]]. A small number of countries still employ slow hanging methods, [[decapitation]], and [[stoning]].

A study of executions carried out in the United States between 1977 and 2001 indicated that at least 34 of the 749 executions, or 4.5%, involved &quot;unanticipated problems or delays that caused, at least arguably, unnecessary agony for the prisoner or that reflect gross incompetence of the executioner&quot;. The rate of these &quot;botched executions&quot; remained steady over the period of the study.&lt;ref&gt;Borg and Radelet, pp. 144–47&lt;/ref&gt; A separate study published in ''[[The Lancet]]'' in 2005 found that in 43% of cases of lethal injection, the blood level of [[hypnotic]]s was insufficient to guarantee unconsciousness.&lt;ref&gt;Van Norman p. 287&lt;/ref&gt; However, the [[Supreme Court of the United States|U.S. Supreme Court]] ruled in 2008 (''[[Baze v. Rees]]'') and again in 2015 (''[[Glossip v. Gross]]'') that lethal injection does not constitute [[cruel and unusual punishment]].&lt;ref&gt;Paternoster, R. (2012-09-18). Capital Punishment. Oxford Handbooks Online. Retrieved 15 June 2016, from {{cite book |title=Capital Punishment |journal=The Oxford Handbook of Crime and Criminal Justice |df=dmy-all |doi=10.1093/oxfordhb/9780195395082.001.0001 |date=2011-09-29 |last1=Paternoster |first1=Ray |isbn=9780195395082 }}.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Abolition of capital punishment==
{{See also|Use of capital punishment by country#Abolition chronology}}
[[File:Leopold II as Grand Duke of Tuscany by Joseph Hickel 1769.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Leopold II, Holy Roman Emperor|Peter Leopold II]], Grand Duke of Tuscany, by {{Interlanguage link multi|Joseph Hickel|de}}, 1769]]
The oldest surviving de facto abolitionist state is [[San Marino]]. Many countries have abolished capital punishment either in law or in practice. Since [[World War II]] there has been a trend toward abolishing capital punishment. Capital punishment has been completely abolished by 102 countries, a further six have done so for all offences except under special circumstances and 32 more have abolished it in practice because they have not used it for at least 10 years and are believed to have a policy or established practice against carrying out executions.&lt;ref name=&quot;amnesty2015&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.amnesty.org/en/documents/act50/3487/2016/en/ |title=Death Sentences and Executions Report 2015 |publisher=[[Amnesty International]] |access-date=10 August 2016 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160814003146/https://www.amnesty.org/en/documents/act50/3487/2016/en/ |archivedate=14 August 2016 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The death penalty was banned in China between 747 and 759. In Japan, [[Emperor Saga]] abolished the death penalty in 818 under the influence of Shinto and it lasted until 1156.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://eos.kokugakuin.ac.jp/modules/xwords/entry.php?entryID=1472|title=Encyclopedia of Shinto|publisher=kokugakuin.ac.jp|accessdate=5 September 2011|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110519153543/http://eos.kokugakuin.ac.jp/modules/xwords/entry.php?entryID=1472|archivedate=19 May 2011|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[Post-classical history|post classical]] [[Republic of Poljica]] life was ensured as a basic right in its [[Poljica Statute]] of 1440.

In England, a public statement of opposition was included in [[The Twelve Conclusions of the Lollards]], written in 1395. Sir [[Thomas More]]'s ''[[Utopia (book)|Utopia]]'', published in 1516, debated the benefits of the death penalty in dialogue form, coming to no firm conclusion.  More was himself executed for treason in 1535. More recent opposition to the death penalty stemmed from the book of the Italian [[Cesare Beccaria]] ''Dei Delitti e Delle Pene'' (&quot;[[On Crimes and Punishments]]&quot;), published in 1764. In this book, Beccaria aimed to demonstrate not only the injustice, but even the futility from the point of view of [[social policy|social welfare]], of [[torture]] and the death penalty. Influenced by the book, [[Leopold II, Holy Roman Emperor|Grand Duke Leopold II]] of Habsburg, the future Emperor of Austria, abolished the death penalty in the then-independent [[Grand Duchy of Tuscany]], the first permanent abolition in modern times.  On 30 November 1786, after having ''de facto'' blocked executions (the last was in 1769), Leopold promulgated the reform of the [[penal code]] that abolished the death penalty and ordered the destruction of all the instruments for capital execution in his land. In 2000, Tuscany's regional authorities instituted an annual holiday on 30 November to commemorate the event. The event is commemorated on this day by 300 cities around the world celebrating [[Cities for Life Day]].

The [[Roman Republic (19th century)|Roman Republic]] banned capital punishment in 1849. [[Venezuela]] followed suit and abolished the death penalty in 1863&lt;ref&gt;Roger G. Hood. ''The death penalty: a worldwide perspective'', [[Oxford University Press]], 2002. p10&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!-- previous cite was for 1854 but this article doesn't even mention the death penalty as far as I can see.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://countrystudies.us/venezuela/5.htm|title=Venezuela: A Country Study (The Century of Caudillismo)|publisher=countrystudies.us|accessdate=4 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt; and [[Use of capital punishment by nation|San Marino]] did so in 1865. The last execution in San Marino had taken place in 1468. In Portugal, after legislative proposals in 1852 and 1863, the death penalty was abolished in 1867. The last execution of the death penalty in Brazil was 1876, from there all the condemnations were commuted by the Emperor [[Pedro II of Brazil|Pedro II]] until its abolition for civil offences and military offences in peacetime in 1891. The penalty for crimes committed in peacetime was then reinstated and abolished again twice (1938–53 and 1969–78), but on those occasions it was restricted to acts of terrorism or subversion considered &quot;internal warfare&quot; and all sentence were commuted and were not carried out.

Abolition occurred in [[Capital punishment in Canada#History|Canada in 1976 (except for some military offences, with complete abolition in 1998)]], in [[Capital punishment in France#Abolition|France in 1981]], and in [[Capital punishment in Australia#Commonwealth|Australia in 1973]] (although the state of [[Capital punishment in Australia#Western Australia|Western Australia]] retained the penalty until 1984). In 1977, the United Nations General Assembly affirmed in a formal resolution that throughout the world, it is desirable to &quot;progressively restrict the number of offences for which the death penalty might be imposed, with a view to the desirability of abolishing this punishment&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newsbatch.com/deathpenalty.htm|title=Death Penalty|publisher=Newsbatch.com|date=1 March 2005|accessdate=23 August 2010|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100724130457/http://www.newsbatch.com/deathpenalty.htm|archivedate=24 July 2010|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the United Kingdom, it was abolished for murder (leaving only [[treason]], [[piracy with violence]], [[arson in royal dockyards]] and a number of wartime military offences as capital crimes) for a five-year experiment in 1965 and permanently in 1969, the last execution having taken place in 1964. It was abolished for all peacetime offences in 1998.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.stephen-stratford.co.uk/capital_hist.htm|title=History of Capital Punishment|publisher=Stephen-stratford.co.uk|accessdate=23 August 2010|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100808063231/http://www.stephen-stratford.co.uk/capital_hist.htm|archivedate=8 August 2010|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the United States, Michigan was the first state to ban the death penalty, on 18 May 1846.&lt;ref&gt;See Caitlin [http://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?c=micounty;cc=micounty;rgn=full%20text;idno=APK1036.0001.001;didno=APK1036.0001.001;view=image;seq=00000444 pp. 420–22] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110520203016/http://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?c=micounty;cc=micounty;rgn=full%20text;idno=APK1036.0001.001;didno=APK1036.0001.001;view=image;seq=00000444 |date=20 May 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The death penalty was declared unconstitutional between 1972 and 1976 based on the ''[[Furman v. Georgia]]'' case, but the 1976 ''[[Gregg v. Georgia]]'' case once again permitted the death penalty under certain circumstances. Further limitations were placed on the death penalty in ''[[Atkins v. Virginia]]'' (death penalty unconstitutional for people with an [[intellectual disability]]) and ''[[Roper v. Simmons]]'' (death penalty unconstitutional if defendant was under age 18 at the time the crime was committed). In the United States, 21 states and the [[District of Columbia]] ban capital punishment.

Abolitionists believe capital punishment is the worst violation of [[human rights]], because the [[right to life]] is the most important, and capital punishment violates it without necessity and inflicts to the condemned a [[psychological torture]]. Human rights activists oppose the death penalty, calling it &quot;cruel, inhuman, and degrading punishment&quot;. [[Amnesty International]] considers it to be &quot;the ultimate, irreversible denial of Human Rights&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Abolish the death penalty&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.amnesty.org/en/death-penalty|title=Abolish the death penalty|publisher=Amnesty International|accessdate=23 August 2010|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100830062328/http://www.amnesty.org/en/death-penalty|archivedate=30 August 2010|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Contemporary use==

===Capital punishment by country{{anchor|Global distribution}}===
{{main|Capital punishment by country}}
[[File:Capital punishment in the world.svg|thumb|right|upright=2.25|{{center|World map of the use of capital punishment {{as of|2019|March|26|lc=y}}{{citation needed|date=December 2018}}}}
'''Legend'''
{{legend|#FF0000|Retentionist countries: 56}}
{{legend|#E0A040|Abolitionist in practice countries (have not executed anyone during the last 10 years and are believed to have a policy or established practice of not carrying out executions): 29}}
{{legend|#80E000|Abolitionist countries except for crimes committed under exceptional circumstances (such as crimes committed in wartime): 7}}
{{legend|#008080|Abolitionist countries: 106}}
]]

Most countries, including almost all [[First World]] nations, have abolished capital punishment either in law or in practice. Notable exceptions are the [[Capital punishment in the United States|United States]], [[Capital punishment in the People's Republic of China|China]], [[Capital punishment in India|India]], [[Capital punishment in Japan|Japan]], [[Capital punishment in South Korea|South Korea]], [[Taiwan]] and most [[Religion and capital punishment#Islam|Islamic states]]. The United States is the only [[Western world#Cultural definition|Western country]] to still use the death penalty.&lt;ref name=&quot;Amnesty2014&quot;&gt;{{Cite web | url=https://www.amnesty.org/en/documents/act50/001/2013/en/ | title=Document}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bienen2010&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Leigh B. Bienen|title=Murder and Its Consequences: Essays on Capital Punishment in America|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=vmpEQUhpNXUC&amp;pg=PA143|edition=2|date=201|publisher=Northwestern University Press|isbn=978-0-8101-2697-8|page=143}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Tonry2000&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Michael H. Tonry|title=The Handbook of Crime &amp; Punishment|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=7MePbzYyZ2YC&amp;pg=PA3|year=2000|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-514060-6|page=3}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Reichert2011&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Elisabeth Reichert|title=Social Work and Human Rights: A Foundation for Policy and Practice|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=2LylU2Yp6NYC&amp;pg=PA89|year=2011|publisher=Columbia University Press|isbn=978-0-231-52070-6|page=89}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Durrant2013&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Russil Durrant|title=An Introduction to Criminal Psychology|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=mIpMUpsoy90C&amp;pg=PA268|year=2013|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-1-136-23434-7|page=268}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;BryantPeck2009&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author1=Clifton D. Bryant|author2=Dennis L. Peck|title=Encyclopedia of Death &amp; Human Experience |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=LFOn7rpkVdQC&amp;pg=PA144|year=2009|publisher=Sage Publications|isbn=978-1-4129-5178-4|page=144}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Roberson2015&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Cliff Roberson|title=Constitutional Law and Criminal Justice, Second Edition|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=oHu9CgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA188|year=2015|publisher=CRC Press|isbn=978-1-4987-2120-2|page=188}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Since [[World War II]], there has been a trend toward abolishing the death penalty. 58 countries retain the death penalty in active use, 102 countries have abolished capital punishment altogether, six have done so for all offences except under special circumstances, and 32 more have abolished it in practice because they have not used it for at least 10 years and are believed to have a policy or established practice against carrying out executions.&lt;ref name=&quot;amnesty2015&quot;/&gt;

According to Amnesty International, 23 countries are known to have performed executions in 2016.&lt;ref name=&quot;amnesty.org.uk&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.amnesty.org/en/documents/act50/5740/2017/en/|title=Document|website=www.amnesty.org|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20171011071624/https://www.amnesty.org/en/documents/act50/5740/2017/en/|archivedate=11 October 2017|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; There are countries which do not publish information on the use of capital punishment, most significantly China and [[Capital punishment in North Korea|North Korea]]. As per Amnesty International, around 1000 prisoners were executed in 2017.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.aljazeera.com/news/2018/04/amnesty-1000-prisoners-executed-worldwide-2017-180411131143832.html|title=Amnesty: Almost 1,000 prisoners executed worldwide in 2017|website=www.aljazeera.com|access-date=2018-08-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;
|-
! Country !! Total executed&lt;br /&gt;(2018)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://www.amnesty.org/download/Documents/ACT5098702019ENGLISH.PDF|title=Death sentences and executions 2018|last=|first=|publisher=Amnesty International|year=2019|isbn=|location=London|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | {{flag|China}} || {{nts|1000}}+
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | {{flag|Iran}} || {{nts|253}}+
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | {{flag|Saudi Arabia}} || {{nts|149}}
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | {{flag|Vietnam}} || {{nts|85}}+
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | {{flag|Iraq}} || {{nts|52}}+
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | {{flag|Egypt}} || {{nts|43}}+
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | {{flag|United States}} || {{nts|25}}
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | {{flag|Japan}} || {{nts|15}}
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | {{flag|Pakistan}} || {{nts|14}}+
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | {{flag|Singapore}} || {{nts|13}}
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | {{flag|Somalia}} || {{nts|13}}
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | {{flag|South Sudan}} || {{nts|7}}+
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | {{flag|Belarus}} || {{nts|4}}+
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | {{flag|Yemen}} || {{nts|4}}+
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | {{flag|Afghanistan}} || {{nts|3}}
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | {{flag|Botswana}} || {{nts|2}}
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | {{flag|Sudan}} || {{nts|2}}
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | {{flag|Taiwan}} || {{nts|1}}
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | {{flag|Thailand}} || {{nts|1}}
&lt;!-- |-
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | {{flag|Bangladesh}} || {{nts|10}}
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | {{flag|Malaysia}} || {{nts|9}}
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | {{flag|Indonesia}} || {{nts|4}}
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | {{flag|Nigeria}} || {{nts|3}}
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | {{flag|Palestine}} || {{nts|3}} --&gt;
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | {{flag|North Korea}} || Unknown
|}

{{Anchor|Legend}}
[[File:Death penalty in the United States.svg|thumb|upright=1.15|A map showing the use of the death penalty in the United States by individual states. Note that the death penalty is used throughout the United States for certain federal crimes (cf. [[Dzhokhar Tsarnaev]]).
{{legend|#FF0000|States with a valid death penalty statute}}
{{legend|#008080|States without the death penalty}}]]

The use of the death penalty is becoming increasingly restrained in some [[retentionist]] countries including [[Taiwan]] and [[Singapore]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Martin Luther King, Jr |url=http://yoursdp.org/index.php/news/singapore/3493-heroin-smuggler-challenges-singapore-death-sentence |title=Heroin smuggler challenges Singapore death sentence |publisher=Yoursdp.org |date=16 March 2010 |accessdate=30 April 2012 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120323124649/http://yoursdp.org/index.php/news/singapore/3493-heroin-smuggler-challenges-singapore-death-sentence |archivedate=23 March 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Indonesia carried out no executions between November 2008 and March 2013.&lt;ref name=&quot;hrw-ind&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Indonesia: First Execution in 4 Years a Major Setback|url=https://www.hrw.org/news/2013/03/21/indonesia-first-execution-4-years-major-setback|work=Human Rights Watch|publisher=www.hrw.org|accessdate=17 May 2013|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130528043848/http://www.hrw.org/news/2013/03/21/indonesia-first-execution-4-years-major-setback|archivedate=28 May 2013|df=dmy-all|date=2013-03-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Singapore]], Japan and the United States are the only developed countries that are classified by Amnesty International as 'retentionist' (South Korea is classified as 'abolitionist in practice').&lt;ref name=&quot;amnesty.org&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.amnesty.org/en/death-penalty/abolitionist-and-retentionist-countries |title=Abolitionist and retentionist countries &amp;#124; Amnesty International |publisher=Amnesty.org |accessdate=11 February 2014 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140209075925/http://www.amnesty.org/en/death-penalty/abolitionist-and-retentionist-countries |archivedate=9 February 2014 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/research/2015/02/death-sentences-and-executions-2014/|title=Error – Amnesty International|website=www.amnesty.org|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20151231222052/https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/research/2015/02/death-sentences-and-executions-2014/|archivedate=31 December 2015|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nearly all retentionist countries are situated in Asia, Africa and the [[Caribbean]].&lt;ref name=&quot;amnesty.org&quot;/&gt; The only retentionist country in Europe is [[Capital punishment in Belarus|Belarus]]. The death penalty was overwhelmingly practised in poor and authoritarian states, which often employed the death penalty as a tool of political oppression. During the 1980s, the democratisation of Latin America swelled the ranks of abolitionist countries.

This was soon followed by the fall of [[Communism]] in Europe. Many of the countries which restored democracy aspired to enter the [[European Union|EU]]. The [[European Union]] and the [[Council of Europe]] both strictly require [[List of European Union member states|member states]] not to practise the death penalty (see [[Capital punishment in Europe]]). Public support for the death penalty in the EU varies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.deathpenaltyinfo.org/article.php?did=2165 |title=International Polls &amp; Studies |publisher=The [[Death Penalty Information Center]] |accessdate=1 April 2008 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070927203428/http://www.deathpenaltyinfo.org/article.php?did=2165 |archivedate=27 September 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The last execution in a member state of the present-day Council of Europe took place in 1997 in [[Ukraine]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://hub.coe.int/what-we-do/human-rights/death-penalty |title=Death Penalty – Council of Europe |publisher=Hub.coe.int |accessdate=11 February 2014 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140205224923/http://hub.coe.int/what-we-do/human-rights/death-penalty |archivedate=5 February 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.handsoffcain.info/bancadati/schedastato.php?idcontinente=20&amp;nome=ukraine |title=HANDS OFF CAIN against death penalty in the world |publisher=Handsoffcain.info |accessdate=11 February 2014 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140203235754/http://www.handsoffcain.info/bancadati/schedastato.php?idcontinente=20&amp;nome=ukraine |archivedate=3 February 2014 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; In contrast, the rapid industrialisation in Asia has seen an increase in the number of developed countries which are also retentionist. In these countries, the death penalty retains strong public support, and the matter receives little attention from the government or the media; in China there is a small but significant and growing movement to abolish the death penalty altogether.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cadpnet.com/show.asp?id=689 |title=China Against Death Penalty (CADP) |publisher=Cadpnet.com |date=31 March 2012 |accessdate=12 December 2012 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20121027173245/https://www.cadpnet.com/show.asp?id=689 |archivedate=27 October 2012 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt; This trend has been followed by some African and Middle Eastern countries where support for the death penalty remains high.

Some countries have resumed practising the death penalty after having previously suspended the practice for long periods. The United States suspended executions in 1972 but resumed them in 1976; there was no execution in India between 1995 and 2004; and [[Sri Lanka]] declared an end to its [[Moratorium (law)|moratorium]] on the death penalty on 20 November 2004,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.amnesty.org.uk/news_details_p.asp?NewsID=16269 |title=AIUK : Sri Lanka: President urged to prevent return to death penalty after 29-year moratorium |publisher=Amnesty.org.uk |accessdate=23 August 2010 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110605115738/http://www.amnesty.org.uk/news_details_p.asp?NewsID=16269 |archivedate=5 June 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; although it has not yet performed any further executions. The [[Philippines]] re-introduced the death penalty in 1993 after abolishing it in 1987, but again abolished it in 2006.

The United States and Japan are the only developed countries to have recently carried out executions. The U.S. federal government, the U.S. military, and 31 states have a valid death penalty statute, and over 1,400 executions have been carried in the United States since it reinstated the death penalty in 1976. Japan has 112 inmates with finalized death sentences {{as of|2019|December|26|lc=y|df=US}}, after executing Wei Wei, a former student from China who was charged with killing and robbing the Japanese family of four, including children aged 8 and 11, in 2003.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|date=2019-12-26|url=https://www3.nhk.or.jp/nhkworld/en/news/20191226_09/|title=Chinese man executed in Japan for killing four|publisher=NHK|accessdate=2019-12-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!--15 inmates&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|date=2018-12-27|url=https://english.kyodonews.net/news/2018/12/535aa7751911-urgent-japan-executes-2-death-row-inmates-thursday-morning-sources.html|title=Japan hangs 2 inmates, matching highest-ever year's total of 15|publisher=Kyodo News|accessdate=2018-12-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; including [[Shoko Asahara]] and six other senior members of [[Aum Shinrikyo]], a cult group which carried out multiple atrocities involving thousands of victims such as [[Tokyo subway sarin attack|the Tokyo subway sarin attack,]] which took place on 20 March 1995, on 6 July 2018&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|date=6 July 2018|url=https://www.japantimes.co.jp/news/2018/07/06/national/crime-legal/aum-founders-execution-paves-way-debate-japan-death-penalty/|title=Aum founder Shoko Asahara's execution leads to renewed debate in Japan on death penalty|publisher=Japan Times|accessdate=24 July 2018|newspaper=The Japan Times Online}}&lt;/ref&gt; followed by the executions of the remaining six senior members on 26 July 2018.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|date=26 July 2018|url=https://mainichi.jp/english/articles/20180726/p2g/00m/0dm/035000c|title=Japan hangs 6 remaining AUM death row inmates|newspaper=Mainichi|accessdate=26 July 2018|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180726043459/https://mainichi.jp/english/articles/20180726/p2g/00m/0dm/035000c|archive-date=26 July 2018|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt;

The most recent country to abolish the death penalty was [[Burkina Faso]] in June 2018.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.news24.com/Africa/News/burkina-faso-abolishes-death-penalty-in-new-penal-code-20180601|title=Burkina Faso abolishes death penalty in new penal code|date=1 June 2018|accessdate=1 June 2018|work=Associated Press|publisher=News 24|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20180605033710/https://www.news24.com/Africa/News/burkina-faso-abolishes-death-penalty-in-new-penal-code-20180601|archivedate=5 June 2018|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Juvenile offenders===
{{category see also|Executed juvenile offenders}}

The death penalty for [[Adolescence|juvenile]] offenders (criminals aged under 18 years at the time of their crime although the legal or accepted definition of ''juvenile offender'' may vary from one jurisdiction to another) has become increasingly rare. Considering the [[Age of Majority]] is still not 18 in some countries or has not been clearly defined in law, since 1990 ten countries have executed offenders who were considered juveniles at the time of their crimes: The People's Republic of China (PRC), [[Bangladesh]], [[Democratic Republic of Congo]], [[Iran]], [[Iraq]], Japan, [[Nigeria]], [[Pakistan]], [[Saudi Arabia]], [[Sudan]], the United States, and [[Yemen]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.internationaljusticeproject.org/juvWorld.cfm |title=Juvenile executions (except US) |publisher=Internationaljusticeproject.org |accessdate=23 August 2010 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110726182207/https://www.internationaljusticeproject.org/juvWorld.cfm |archivedate=26 July 2011 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt; The PRC&lt;!--Refer to it as PRC to avoid confusion with the ROC on Taiwan--&gt;, Pakistan, the United States, Yemen and Iran have since raised the minimum age to 18.&lt;ref name=autogenerated2&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.iranwpd.com/index.php?option=com_k2&amp;view=item&amp;id=3066:iran-changes-law-for-execution-of-juveniles&amp;Itemid=64 |title=Iran changes law for execution of juveniles |publisher=Iranwpd.com |date=10 February 2012 |accessdate=30 April 2012 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120429231704/http://iranwpd.com/index.php?option=com_k2&amp;view=item&amp;id=3066%3Airan-changes-law-for-execution-of-juveniles&amp;Itemid=64 |archivedate=29 April 2012 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ghanoononline.ir/NSite/FullStory/News/?Serv=19&amp;Id=16270 |title=مجازات قصاص برای افراد زیر 18 سال ممنوع شد |publisher=Ghanoononline.ir |accessdate=12 December 2012 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120213111337/http://www.ghanoononline.ir/NSite/FullStory/News/?Serv=19&amp;Id=16270 |archivedate=13 February 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Amnesty International has recorded 61 verified executions since then, in several countries, of both juveniles and adults who had been convicted of committing their offences as juveniles.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.amnesty.org/en/death-penalty/executions-of-child-offenders-since-1990 |title=Executions of juveniles since 1990 |publisher=Amnesty International |accessdate=12 December 2012 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20121204044639/http://www.amnesty.org/en/death-penalty/executions-of-child-offenders-since-1990 |archivedate=4 December 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The PRC does not allow for the execution of those under 18, but child executions have reportedly taken place.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.amnesty.org/en/documents/act50/015/2004/en/|title=Stop Child Executions! Ending the death penalty for child offenders|publisher=Amnesty International|year=2004|accessdate=12 February 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Martyrs_of_Guernsey.jpg|thumb|Mother Catherine Cauchés (center) and her two daughters Guillemine Gilbert (left) and Perotine Massey (right) with her infant son burning for heresy]]

One of the youngest children ever to be executed was the infant son of Perotine Massey on or around 18 July 1556. His mother was one of the [[Guernsey Martyrs]] who was executed for heresy, and his father had previously fled the island. At less than one day old, he was ordered to be burned by Bailiff Hellier Gosselin, with the advice of priests nearby who said the boy should burn due to having inherited moral stain from his mother, who had given birth during her execution.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Butler|first=Sara M.|date=2018-03-21|title=Pleading the Belly: A Sparing Plea? Pregnant Convicts and the Courts in Medieval England|url=https://brill.com/view/book/edcoll/9789004364950/B9789004364950_009.xml|journal=Crossing Borders: Boundaries and Margins in Medieval and Early Modern Britain|language=en|pages=131–152|doi=10.1163/9789004364950_009|isbn=9789004364950}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Starting in 1642 within the then British American colonies until present day, an estimated 365&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.deathpenaltyinfo.org/article.php?scid=27&amp;did=203#execsus |title=Execution of Juveniles in the U.S. and other Countries |publisher=Deathpenaltyinfo.org |accessdate=23 August 2010 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080513015221/http://www.deathpenaltyinfo.org/article.php?scid=27&amp;did=203 |archivedate=13 May 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt; juvenile offenders were executed by the British Colonial authorities and subsequently by State authorities and the federal government of the United States.&lt;ref&gt;Rob Gallagher,{{cite web|url=http://users.bestweb.net/~rg/execution/JUVENILE.htm |title=Table of juvenile executions in British America/United States, 1642–1959 |accessdate=2006-02-05 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20060615094320/http://users.bestweb.net/~rg/execution/JUVENILE.htm |archivedate=15 June 2006 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt; The United States Supreme Court abolished capital punishment for offenders under the age of 16 in ''[[Thompson v. Oklahoma]]'' (1988), and for all juveniles in ''[[Roper v. Simmons]]'' (2005).

Between 2005 and May 2008, Iran, Pakistan, Saudi Arabia, Sudan and Yemen were reported to have executed child offenders, the largest number occurring in Iran.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.hrw.org/pub/2008/children/HRW.Juv.Death.Penalty.053008.pdf|title=HRW Report|publisher=Human Rights Watch|accessdate=23 August 2010|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20081113084648/http://www.hrw.org/pub/2008/children/HRW.Juv.Death.Penalty.053008.pdf|archivedate=13 November 2008|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During [[Hassan Rouhani]]'s current tenure as president of Iran since 2013, at least 3,602 death sentences have been carried out. This includes the executions of 34 juvenile offenders.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=https://iran-hrm.com/index.php/2018/10/08/cruel-and-inhuman-executions-in-iran/ | title=Annual report on the death penalty in Iran, October 2018| date=2018-10-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=https://irannewswire.org/iran-executes-female-juvenile-offender-despite-grossly-unfair-legal-process/ | title=Iran executes female juvenile offender despite grossly unfair legal process| date=2018-10-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[United Nations]] [[Convention on the Rights of the Child]], which forbids capital punishment for juveniles under article 37(a), has been signed by all countries and subsequently [[ratification|ratified]] by all signatories with the exceptions of [[Somalia]] and the United States (despite the [[Supreme Court of the United States|US Supreme Court]] decisions abolishing the practice).&lt;ref&gt;UNICEF, [http://www.unicef.org/crc/index_30229.html Convention of the Rights of the Child – FAQ] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160125094459/http://www.unicef.org/crc/index_30229.html |date=25 January 2016 }}: &quot;The Convention on the Rights of the Child is the most widely and rapidly ratified human rights treaty in history. Only two countries, Somalia and the United States, have not ratified this celebrated agreement. Somalia is currently unable to proceed to ratification as it has no recognised government. By signing the Convention, the United States has signaled its intention to ratify but has yet to do so.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; The [[United Nations Human Rights Council|UN Sub-Commission on the Promotion and Protection of Human Rights]] maintains that the death penalty for juveniles has become contrary to a [[jus cogens]] of [[customary international law]]. A majority of countries are also party to the U.N. [[International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights]] (whose Article 6.5 also states that &quot;Sentence of death shall not be imposed for crimes committed by persons below eighteen years of age...&quot;).

Iran, despite its ratification of the [[Convention on the Rights of the Child]] and [[International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights]], was the world's largest executioner of juvenile offenders, for which it has been the subject of broad international condemnation; the country's record is the focus of the [[Stop Child Executions Campaign]]. But on 10 February 2012, Iran's parliament changed controversial laws relating to the execution of juveniles. In the new legislation the age of 18 (solar year) would be applied to accused of both genders and juvenile offenders must be sentenced pursuant to a separate law specifically dealing with juveniles.&lt;ref name=autogenerated2 /&gt;&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt; Based on the Islamic law which now seems to have been revised, girls at the age of 9 and boys at 15 of lunar year (11 days shorter than a solar year) are deemed fully responsible for their crimes.&lt;ref name=autogenerated2 /&gt; Iran accounted for two-thirds of the global total of such executions, and currently{{update after|2014|8|15}} has approximately 140 people considered as juveniles awaiting execution for crimes committed (up from 71 in 2007).&lt;ref name=AP&gt;[http://usatoday30.usatoday.com/news/world/2008-09-17-child-executions_N.htm Iranian activists fight child executions], Ali Akbar Dareini, [[Associated Press]], 17 September 2008. Retrieved 2008-09-22.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=O'Toole|first=Pam|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/6244126.stm|title=Iran rapped over child executions|work=BBC News|date=27 June 2007|accessdate=12 December 2012|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20121204021152/http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/6244126.stm|archivedate=4 December 2012|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; The past executions of [[Mahmoud Asgari and Ayaz Marhoni|Mahmoud Asgari, Ayaz Marhoni]] and Makwan Moloudzadeh became the focus of Iran's child capital punishment policy and the judicial system that hands down such sentences.&lt;ref name=Fox&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,297982,00.html|title=Iran Does Far Worse Than Ignore Gays, Critics Say|publisher=Foxnews.com|date=25 September 2007|accessdate=12 December 2012|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20121022014203/http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,297982,00.html|archivedate=22 October 2012|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/7130380.stm Iranian hanged after verdict stay] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071207005203/http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/7130380.stm |date=7 December 2007 }}; BBCnews.co.uk; 2007-12-06; Retrieved 2007-12-06&lt;/ref&gt;

Saudi Arabia also executes criminals who were minors at the time of the offence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.amnesty.org/en/news-and-updates/news/juveniles-among-five-men-beheaded-saudi-arabia-20090512 |title=Juveniles among five men beheaded in Saudi Arabia &amp;#124; Amnesty International |publisher=Amnesty.org |accessdate=11 February 2014 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140311042739/http://www.amnesty.org/en/news-and-updates/news/juveniles-among-five-men-beheaded-saudi-arabia-20090512 |archivedate=11 March 2014 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-21767667 |title=BBC News – Saudi Arabia executes seven men for armed robbery |publisher=Bbc.co.uk |date=13 March 2013 |accessdate=11 February 2014 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131027024755/http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-21767667 |archivedate=27 October 2013 |df=dmy-all |work=BBC News }}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2013, Saudi Arabia was the center of an international controversy after it executed [[Execution of Rizana Nafeek|Rizana Nafeek]], a [[Sri Lanka]]n domestic worker, who was believed to have been 17 years old at the time of the crime.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-20959228 |title=BBC News – Sri Lankan maid Rizana Nafeek beheaded in Saudi Arabia |publisher=Bbc.co.uk |date=9 January 2013 |accessdate=11 February 2014 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170116033909/http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-20959228 |archivedate=16 January 2017 |df=dmy-all |work=BBC News }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Japan has not executed juvenile criminals after August 1997, when they executed [[Norio Nagayama]], a [[spree killer]] who had been convicted of shooting four people dead in the late 1960s. Nagayama's case created the eponymously named [[Norio Nagayama|''Nagayama'' ''standards'']], which take into account factors such as the number of victims, brutality and social impact of the crimes. The standards have been used in determining whether to apply the death sentence in murder cases. [[Teruhiko Seki]], convicted of murdering four family members including a 4-year-old daughter and raping a 15-year-old daughter of a family in 1992, became the second inmate to be hanged for a crime committed as a minor in the first such execution in 20 years after Nagayama on 19 December 2017.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|date=19 December 2017|url=https://english.kyodonews.net/news/2017/12/881eeda07930-japan-hangs-2-death-row-inmates-sources.html |title=Japan hangs 2 inmates including man who killed 4 as minor |publisher=Kyodo News|accessdate=24 July 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Takayuki Fukuda|Takayuki Otsuki]], who was convicted of raping and strangling a 23-year-old woman and subsequently strangling her 11-month-old daughter to death on 14 April 1999, when he was 18, is another inmate sentenced to death, and his request for retrial has been rejected by the [[Supreme Court of Japan]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|date=30 October 2012|url=https://japantoday.com/category/crime/man-sentenced-to-death-for-killing-mother-baby-daughter-in-1999-seeks-retrial |title=Man sentenced to death for killing mother, baby daughter in 1999 seeks retrial |newspaper=Japan Today|accessdate=24 July 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There is evidence that child executions are taking place in the parts of Somalia controlled by the [[Islamic Courts Union]] (ICU). In October 2008, a girl, [[Stoning of Aisha Ibrahim Duhulow|Aisha Ibrahim Dhuhulow]] was buried up to her neck at a [[Soccer-specific stadium|football stadium]], then [[stoning|stoned]] to death in front of more than 1,000 people. Somalia's established [[Transitional Federal Government]] announced in November 2009 (reiterated in 2013)&lt;ref name=&quot;Somalia to Ratify UN Child Rights Treaty&quot;&gt;[http://allafrica.com/stories/201311210066.html &quot;Somalia to Ratify UN Child Rights Treaty&quot;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131203012729/http://allafrica.com/stories/201311210066.html |date=3 December 2013 }}, allAfrica.com, 20 November 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; that it plans to ratify the [[Convention on the Rights of the Child]]. This move was lauded by [[UNICEF]] as a welcome attempt to secure children's rights in the country.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.xinhuanet.com/english/2009-11/20/content_12510818.htm|title=UNICEF lauds move by Somalia to ratify child convention|agency=Xinhua News Agency|date=20 November 2009|accessdate=23 August 2010|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100113110138/http://news.xinhuanet.com/english/2009-11/20/content_12510818.htm|archivedate=13 January 2010|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Methods===
{{Main|List of methods of capital punishment}}

The following methods of execution were used by various countries in 2019:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nutzworld.com/amerikaarticles/methods_of_execution_by_country.htm|title=Methodes of execution by country|publisher=Nutzworld.com|accessdate=23 February 2011|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110714212707/http://www.nutzworld.com/amerikaarticles/methods_of_execution_by_country.htm|archivedate=14 July 2011|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.deathpenaltyinfo.org/methods-execution|title=Methods of execution – Death Penalty Information Center|publisher=Deathpenaltyinfo.org|accessdate=23 February 2011|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110225054450/http://www.deathpenaltyinfo.org/methods-execution|archivedate=25 February 2011|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://translate.google.no/translate?js=n&amp;prev=_t&amp;layout=2&amp;eotf=1&amp;u=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.amnesty.no%2Fd%25C3%25B8dsstraffbulletin-nr-4-2010&amp;act=url|title=Death penalty Bulletin No. 4-2010|language=no|publisher=Translate.google.no|accessdate=23 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://translate.google.no/translate?u=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.amnesty.no%2Faktuelt%2Fflere-nyheter%2Farkiv-bakgrunn%2Fopplysninger-om-d%25C3%25B8dsstraff|title=INFORMATION ON DEATH PENALTY|language=no|publisher=Amnesty International|accessdate=23 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://executions.justsickshit.com/execution-methods-by-country/|title=execution methods by country|publisher=Executions.justsickshit.com|accessdate=23 February 2011|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20101114045725/http://executions.justsickshit.com/execution-methods-by-country/|archivedate=14 November 2010|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Hanging]] ([[Capital punishment in Afghanistan|Afghanistan]], [[Capital punishment in Iran|Iran]], [[Capital punishment in Iraq|Iraq]], [[Capital punishment in Japan|Japan]], [[Capital punishment in Malaysia|Malaysia]], [[Nigeria]], [[Sudan]], [[Capital punishment in Pakistan|Pakistan]], Palestinian National Authority, [[Capital punishment in Yemen|Yemen]], [[Capital punishment in Egypt|Egypt]], [[Capital punishment in India|India]], [[Myanmar]], [[Capital punishment in Singapore|Singapore]], [[Capital punishment in Sri Lanka|Sri Lanka]], [[Capital punishment in Syria|Syria]], UAE, Zimbabwe, Malawi, Liberia, Chad)
* [[Execution by shooting|Shooting]] (the [[Capital punishment in the People's Republic of China|People's Republic of China]], [[Capital punishment in the Republic of China|Republic of China]], [[Capital punishment in Vietnam|Vietnam]], [[Capital punishment in Belarus|Belarus]], Ethiopia, Nigeria, [[Capital punishment in Somalia|Somalia]], [[Capital punishment in North Korea|North Korea]], [[Capital punishment in Indonesia|Indonesia]], [[Capital punishment in the United Arab Emirates|UAE]], [[Capital punishment in Saudi Arabia|Saudi Arabia]], Bahrain, [[Capital punishment in Qatar|Qatar]], [[Capital punishment in Yemen|Yemen]], and in the US states of [[Capital punishment in Oklahoma|Oklahoma]] and [[Capital punishment in Utah|Utah]]).
* [[Lethal injection]] ([[Capital punishment in the United States|United States]], [[Capital punishment in Guatemala|Guatemala]], [[Capital punishment in Thailand|Thailand]], the [[Capital punishment in the People's Republic of China|People's Republic of China]], [[Capital punishment in Vietnam|Vietnam]])
* [[Decapitation|Beheading]] ([[Capital punishment in Saudi Arabia|Saudi Arabia]])
* [[Stoning]] ([[Capital punishment in Saudi Arabia|Saudi Arabia]], [[Capital punishment in the United Arab Emirates|UAE]], [[Qatar]], [[Capital punishment in Nigeria|Nigeria]], [[Capital punishment in Sudan|Sudan]], [[Capital punishment in Iran|Iran]])
* [[Electric chair|Electrocution]] and [[Gas chamber|gas inhalation]] (some U.S. states, but only if the prisoner requests it or if lethal injection is unavailable)
*[[Inert gas asphyxiation]] (Some U.S states, [[Capital punishment in Oklahoma|Oklahoma]], Mississippi, Alabama)

===Public execution===
{{main|Public execution}}
A public execution is a form of capital punishment which &quot;members of the general public may voluntarily attend&quot;. This definition excludes the presence of a small number of witnesses randomly selected to assure executive accountability.&lt;ref name=blum&gt;{{cite journal |last=Blum |first=Steven A. |date=Winter 1992 |title=Public Executions: Understand the &quot;Cruel and Unusual Punishments&quot; Clause |url=http://www.hastingsconlawquarterly.org/archives/V19/I2/Blum.pdf |journal=Hastings Constitutional Law Quarterly |volume=19 |issue=2 |page=415 |doi= |accessdate= |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140326225628/http://www.hastingsconlawquarterly.org/archives/V19/I2/Blum.pdf |archivedate=26 March 2014 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; While today the great majority of the world considers public executions to be distasteful and most countries have outlawed the practice, throughout much of history executions were performed publicly as a means for the state to demonstrate &quot;its power before those who fell under its jurisdiction be they criminals, enemies, or political opponents&quot;. Additionally, it afforded the public a chance to witness &quot;what was considered a great spectacle&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Cawthorne |first=Nigel |date=2006 |title=Public Executions: From Ancient Rome to the Present Day |url=https://archive.org/details/publicexecutions0000cawt/page/6 |location= |publisher= |pages=[https://archive.org/details/publicexecutions0000cawt/page/6 6–7] |isbn=978-0-7858-2119-9 |accessdate= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Social historians note that beginning in the 20th century in the U.S. and western Europe death in general became increasingly shielded from public view, occurring more and more behind the closed doors of the hospital.&lt;ref name=chambliss&gt;{{cite book|author=William J. Chambliss|title=Corrections|publisher=SAGE Publications|year=2011|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=NMF1AwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA4|pages=4–5|isbn=9781452266435}}&lt;/ref&gt; Executions were likewise moved behind the walls of the penitentiary.&lt;ref name=chambliss/&gt; The last formal public executions occurred in 1868 in Britain, in 1936 in the U.S. and in 1939 in France.&lt;ref name=chambliss/&gt;

According to [[Amnesty International]], in 2012, &quot;public executions were known to have been carried out in [[Iran]], [[North Korea]], [[Saudi Arabia]] and [[Somalia]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |date=12 April 2013 |title=Death penalty statistics, country by country |url=https://www.theguardian.com/news/datablog/2011/mar/29/death-penalty-countries-world |newspaper=The Guardian |accessdate= |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20151231222052/http://www.theguardian.com/news/datablog/2011/mar/29/death-penalty-countries-world |archivedate=31 December 2015 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; There have been reports of public executions carried out by state and non-state actors in [[Hamas]]-controlled [[Gaza Strip|Gaza]], Syria, Iraq, Afghanistan, and Yemen.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |date=22 August 2014 |title=Haunting Images Emerge of Hamas Public Execution of 18 Alleged Collaborators |url=http://www.algemeiner.com/2014/08/22/haunting-images-emerge-of-hamas-public-execution-of-18-alleged-collaborators-photos/ |newspaper=The Algemeiner |accessdate=14 September 2014 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140915072828/http://www.algemeiner.com/2014/08/22/haunting-images-emerge-of-hamas-public-execution-of-18-alleged-collaborators-photos/ |archivedate=15 September 2014 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.foxnews.com/world/2016/01/08/isis-extremist-executes-his-mother-in-syria-for-urging-him-to-flee-group.html |title=ISIS extremist reportedly kills his mother in public execution in Syria |publisher=Fox News |date=2016-01-08 |accessdate=2016-05-30 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160531212145/http://www.foxnews.com/world/2016/01/08/isis-extremist-executes-his-mother-in-syria-for-urging-him-to-flee-group.html |archivedate=31 May 2016 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.cnn.com/2012/07/08/world/asia/afghanistan-public-execution/ |title=Video: Taliban shoot woman 9 times in public execution as men cheer |publisher=CNN |date=2012-07-09 |accessdate=2016-05-30 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160602090138/http://www.cnn.com/2012/07/08/world/asia/afghanistan-public-execution/ |archivedate=2 June 2016 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Executions which can be classified as public were also carried out in the U.S. states of Florida and Utah as of 1992.&lt;ref name=blum/&gt;

==Capital crime==

===Crimes against humanity===
Crimes against humanity such as [[genocide]] are usually punishable by death in countries retaining capital punishment. Death sentences for such crimes were handed down and carried out during the [[Nuremberg Trials]] in 1946 and the [[Tokyo Trials]] in 1948, but the current [[International Criminal Court]] does not use capital punishment. The maximum penalty available to the International Criminal Court is [[life imprisonment]].

===Murder===
Intentional homicide is punishable by death in most countries retaining capital punishment, but generally provided it involves an [[aggravating factor]] required by statute or judicial precedents.

===Drug trafficking===
{{main|Capital punishment for drug trafficking}}
[[File:CKS Airport drugs sign.JPG|thumb|A sign at the [[Taiwan Taoyuan International Airport]] warns arriving travelers that drug trafficking is a capital crime in the Republic of China (photo taken in 2005)]]
Many countries provide the death penalty for [[drug trafficking]], [[drug dealing]], [[drug possession]] and related offences, mostly in [[West Asia]], [[South Asia]], [[Southeast Asia]], [[East Asia]], and some [[Africa]]n countries.{{citation needed|date=January 2019}} Among countries who regularly execute drug offenders are China, Indonesia, Saudi Arabia, Iran and Singapore.

===Other offences===
{{See also|Capital punishment for non-violent offenses|Capital punishment by country}}
Other crimes that are punishable by death in some countries include [[terrorism]], [[treason]], [[espionage]], crimes against the state, such as attempting to overthrow government (most countries with the death penalty), [[political protest]]s (Saudi Arabia),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.independent.co.uk/News/world/middle-east/saudi-arabia-death-penalty-executions-capital-punishment-six-killed-one-day-outcry-a7834726.html|title=Saudi Arabia executed six people yesterday|date=11 July 2017|publisher=|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170825123739/http://www.independent.co.uk/News/world/middle-east/saudi-arabia-death-penalty-executions-capital-punishment-six-killed-one-day-outcry-a7834726.html|archivedate=25 August 2017|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[rape]] (China, India, Pakistan, Bangladesh, Iran, Saudi Arabia, UAE, Qatar, Brunei, etc.), economic crimes (China), [[Political corruption|corruption]] (China, Iran), [[kidnapping]] (China, Bangladesh etc.), [[separatism]] (China), [[Zina|adultery]] (Saudi Arabia, UAE, Iran, Qatar, Brunei, etc.), [[bestiality]] (Saudi Arabia, UAE, Qatar, Iran), [[Zina|sodomy]] (Saudi Arabia, Iran, Brunei, Nigeria etc.),&lt;!--Adultery, rape, and sodomy fall under the same criminal category in sharia.--&gt; and religious [[Hudud]] offences such as [[Apostasy in Islam|apostasy]] (Saudi Arabia, Iran, Sudan, etc.), [[Islam and blasphemy|blasphemy]] (Saudi Arabia, Iran, Pakistan, Nigeria), [[Hirabah|Moharebeh]] (Iran), drinking [[alcohol (drug)|alcohol]] (Iran), [[Witchcraft]] and [[Magic (paranormal)|Sorcery]] (Saudi Arabia),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.theatlantic.com/international/archive/2013/08/saudi-arabias-war-on-witchcraft/278701/|title=Saudi Arabia's War on Witchcraft|first=Ryan|last=Jacobs|publisher=|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20161218084707/http://www.theatlantic.com/international/archive/2013/08/saudi-arabias-war-on-witchcraft/278701/|archivedate=18 December 2016|df=dmy-all|date=2013-08-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mysteriousuniverse.org/2015/07/the-anti-sorcery-squad-of-saudi-arabia/|title=The Anti-Sorcery Squad of Saudi Arabia – Mysterious Universe|website=mysteriousuniverse.org|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170102081146/http://mysteriousuniverse.org/2015/07/the-anti-sorcery-squad-of-saudi-arabia/|archivedate=2 January 2017|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[arson]] (Algeria, Tunisia, Mali, Mauritania etc.), and [[hirabah]]/[[brigandage]]/[[armed robbery|armed]] and/or [[aggravated robbery]], (Algeria, Saudi Arabia, Kenya, Zambia, Ghana, Ethiopia, etc.).&lt;ref name=&quot;Amnesty2014&quot;/&gt;

==Controversy and debate==
{{See also|Capital punishment debate in the United States}}
Capital punishment is controversial. Death penalty opponents regard the death penalty as inhumane&lt;ref name=&quot;amnesty-ill&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|title=Cruel and Unusual: Executing the mentally ill|url=http://www.amnestyusa.org/page.do?id=1105184In|author=Dan Malone|publisher=Amnesty International Magazine|date=Fall 2005|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090116081317/http://www.amnestyusa.org/page.do?id=1105184In|archivedate=16 January 2009|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; and criticize it for its irreversibility.&lt;ref name=&quot;amnesty-irreversible&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.amnestyusa.org/Our_Issues/Death_Penalty/page.do?id=1011005&amp;n1=3&amp;n2=28|title=Abolish the death penalty|publisher=Amnesty International|accessdate=25 January 2008|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080119233113/http://www.amnestyusa.org/Our_Issues/Death_Penalty/page.do?id=1011005&amp;n1=3&amp;n2=28|archivedate=19 January 2008|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; They argue also that capital punishment lacks deterrent effect,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.amnestyusa.org/issues/death-penalty/death-penalty-facts/the-death-penalty-and-deterrence/ |title=The Death Penalty and Deterrence |publisher=Amnestyusa.org |date=22 February 2008 |accessdate=23 May 2009 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170823161110/https://www.amnestyusa.org/issues/death-penalty/death-penalty-facts/the-death-penalty-and-deterrence/ |archivedate=23 August 2017 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.math.dartmouth.edu/~lamperti/capitalpunishment.html |archive-url=https://archive.today/20010813164705/http://www.math.dartmouth.edu/~lamperti/capitalpunishment.html |url-status=dead |archive-date=13 August 2001 |title=John W. Lamperti &amp;#124; Capital Punishment |publisher=Math.dartmouth.edu |date=10 March 1973 |accessdate=23 May 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.deathpenaltyinfo.org/discussion-recent-deterrence-studies |title=Discussion of Recent Deterrence Studies &amp;#124; Death Penalty Information Center |publisher=Deathpenaltyinfo.org |accessdate=23 May 2009 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090429191414/http://www.deathpenaltyinfo.org/discussion-recent-deterrence-studies |archivedate=29 April 2009 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; discriminates against minorities and the poor, and that it encourages a &quot;culture of violence&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;deathPenaltyFocus&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.deathpenalty.org/article.php?id=42|title=The High Cost of the Death Penalty|publisher=[[Death Penalty Focus]]|accessdate=27 June 2008|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080428180241/http://www.deathpenalty.org/article.php?id=42|archivedate=28 April 2008|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; There are many organizations worldwide, such as [[Amnesty International]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url =http://www.amnestyusa.org/pdfs/DeathPenaltyFactsMay2012.pdf|title =Death Penalty Facts|date =|accessdate =|website =|publisher =|last =|first =|url-status=live|archiveurl =https://web.archive.org/web/20151026041955/http://www.amnestyusa.org/pdfs/DeathPenaltyFactsMay2012.pdf|archivedate =26 October 2015|df =dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; and country-specific, such as the [[American Civil Liberties Union]] (ACLU), that have abolition of the death penalty as a fundamental purpose.&lt;ref&gt;Brian Evans, [http://blog.amnestyusa.org/us/the-death-penalty-in-2011-three-things-you-should-know/ &quot;The Death Penalty In 2011: Three Things You Should Know&quot;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130731081723/http://blog.amnestyusa.org/us/the-death-penalty-in-2011-three-things-you-should-know/ |date=31 July 2013 }}, [[Amnesty International]], 26 March 2012, in particular the map, [http://betablog.amnestyusa.org/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/death_penalty_world_map.jpg &quot;Executions and Death Sentences in 2011&quot;]  {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130217160324/http://betablog.amnestyusa.org/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/death_penalty_world_map.jpg |date=17 February 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.aclu.org/capital-punishment |title=ACLU Capital Punishment Project (CPP) |publisher=Aclu.org |accessdate=14 April 2013 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130412231652/http://www.aclu.org/capital-punishment |archivedate=12 April 2013 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Advocates of the death penalty argue that it deters crime,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.stanfordlawreview.org/sites/default/files/articles/sunstein1.pdf|title=Home – Stanford Law Review|first=Stanford Law|last=Review|website=www.stanfordlawreview.org|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150903214330/http://www.stanfordlawreview.org/sites/default/files/articles/sunstein1.pdf|archivedate=3 September 2015|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2007/11/18/us/18deter.html|title=Does Death Penalty Save Lives? A New Debate|first=Adam|last=Liptak|date=18 November 2007|publisher=|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20151117190641/http://www.nytimes.com/2007/11/18/us/18deter.html|archivedate=17 November 2015|df=dmy-all|newspaper=The New York Times}}&lt;/ref&gt; is a good tool for police and prosecutors in [[plea bargain]]ing,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=James Pitkin|url=http://wweek.com/editorial/3411/10288/|title=&quot;Killing Time&quot; &amp;#124; January 23rd, 2008|publisher=Wweek.com|accessdate=23 August 2010|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080124040746/http://wweek.com/editorial/3411/10288/|archivedate=24 January 2008|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; makes sure that convicted criminals do not offend again, and is a just penalty.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.nytimes.com/roomfordebate/2014/04/06/what-it-means-if-the-death-penalty-is-dying/the-death-penalty-needs-to-be-an-option-for-punishment|title=The Death Penalty Needs to Be an Option for Punishment|publisher=|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20161207140843/http://www.nytimes.com/roomfordebate/2014/04/06/what-it-means-if-the-death-penalty-is-dying/the-death-penalty-needs-to-be-an-option-for-punishment|archivedate=7 December 2016|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Film ''Robert Blecker want me dead'', about retributive justice and capital punishment&lt;/ref&gt;

===Retribution===
[[File: Karl Morgenschweis prays for condemned prisoner.jpg|thumb|Execution of a [[war crimes|war criminal]] in 1946]]
Supporters of the death penalty argued that death penalty is morally justified when applied in murder especially with aggravating elements such as for murder of [[police officers]], [[child murder]], [[torture murder]], multiple [[homicide]] and [[mass killing]] such as [[terrorism]], [[massacre]] and [[genocide]]. This argument is strongly defended by [[New York Law School]]'s Professor [[Robert Blecker Wants Me Dead|Robert Blecker]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nyls.edu/faculty/faculty_profiles/robert_blecker/ |title=New York Law School :: Robert Blecker |publisher=Nyls.edu |access-date=14 April 2013 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130902231929/http://www.nyls.edu/faculty/faculty_profiles/robert_blecker/ |archivedate=2 September 2013 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; who says that the punishment must be painful in proportion to the crime. Eighteenth-century philosopher [[Immanuel Kant]] defended a more extreme position, according to which every murderer deserves to die on the grounds that loss of life is incomparable to any jail term.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www1.american.edu/dgolash/Kant_on_Punishment.html/ |title=Immanuel Kant, The Philosophy of Right |publisher=American.edu |access-date=6 July 2014 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140217232041/http://www1.american.edu/dgolash/Kant_on_Punishment.html |archive-date=17 February 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some abolitionists argue that retribution is simply revenge and cannot be condoned. Others while accepting retribution as an element of criminal justice nonetheless argue that [[life without parole]] is a sufficient substitute. It is also argued that the punishing of a killing with another death is a relatively unique punishment for a violent act, because in general violent crimes are not punished by subjecting the perpetrator to a similar act (e.g. rapists are not punished by [[judicial corporal punishment|corporal punishment]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/ethics/capitalpunishment/against_1.shtml#section_4 |title=Ethics – Capital punishment: Arguments against capital punishment |publisher=BBC |date=1 January 1970 |access-date=11 February 2014 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140209003504/http://www.bbc.co.uk/ethics/capitalpunishment/against_1.shtml#section_4 |archivedate=9 February 2014 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Human rights===
Abolitionists believe capital punishment is the worst violation of [[human rights]], because the [[right to life]] is the most important, and capital punishment violates it without necessity and inflicts to the condemned a [[psychological torture]]. Human rights activists oppose the death penalty, calling it &quot;[[cruel and unusual punishment|cruel, inhuman and degrading punishment]]&quot;. [[Amnesty International]] considers it to be &quot;the ultimate irreversible denial of Human Rights&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Abolish the death penalty&quot;/&gt; [[Albert Camus]] wrote in a 1956 book called ''Reflections on the Guillotine, Resistance, Rebellion &amp; Death'':

{{Quote|An execution is not simply death. It is just as different from the privation of life as a concentration camp is from prison. [...] For there to be an equivalency, the death penalty would have to punish a criminal who had warned his victim of the date at which he would inflict a horrible death on him and who, from that moment onward, had confined him at his mercy for months. Such a monster is not encountered in private life.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://people.smu.edu/rhalperi/ |title=Death Penalty News &amp; Updates |publisher=People.smu.edu |accessdate=14 April 2013 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130413081015/http://people.smu.edu/rhalperi/ |archivedate=13 April 2013 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

In the classic doctrine of [[natural rights]] as expounded by for instance [[John Locke|Locke]] and [[William Blackstone|Blackstone]], on the other hand, it is an important idea that the right to life can be forfeited.&lt;ref name=feinberg&gt;Joel Feinberg: [http://www.tannerlectures.utah.edu/lectures/documents/feinberg80.pdf Voluntary Euthanasia and the Inalienable Right to Life] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121021073901/http://www.tannerlectures.utah.edu/lectures/documents/feinberg80.pdf |date=21 October 2012 }} [[Tanner Lectures on Human Values|The Tanner Lecture on Human Values]], 1 April 1977.&lt;/ref&gt; As [[John Stuart Mill]] explained in a speech given in Parliament against an amendment to abolish capital punishment for murder in 1868:

{{Quote|And we may imagine somebody asking how we can teach people not to inflict suffering by ourselves inflicting it? But to this I should answer – all of us would answer – that to deter by suffering from inflicting suffering is not only possible, but the very purpose of penal justice. Does fining a criminal show want of respect for property, or imprisoning him, for personal freedom? Just as unreasonable is it to think that to take the life of a man who has taken that of another is to show want of regard for human life. We show, on the contrary, most emphatically our regard for it, by the adoption of a rule that he who violates that right in another forfeits it for himself, and that while no other crime that he can commit deprives him of his right to live, this shall.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://ethics.sandiego.edu/books/Mill/Punishment/ |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130508233912/http://ethics.sandiego.edu/Books/Mill/Punishment/ |url-status=dead |archive-date=8 May 2013 |title=John Stuart Mill, Speech on Capital Punishment |publisher=Sandiego.edu |accessdate=6 July 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

===Wrongful execution===
[[File:Timothy Evans Grave.JPG|thumb|Capital punishment was abolished in the United Kingdom in part because of the case of [[Timothy Evans]], an innocent man who was hanged in 1950 after being wrongfully convicted of two murders that had been committed by his neighbour.]]
{{Main|Wrongful execution}}

It is frequently argued that capital punishment leads to [[miscarriage of justice]] through the wrongful execution of innocent persons.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.deathpenaltyinfo.org/article.php?did=412|title=Innocence and the Death Penalty|publisher=Deathpenaltyinfo.org|accessdate=23 August 2010|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080701205425/http://www.deathpenaltyinfo.org/article.php?did=412|archivedate=1 July 2008|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many people have been proclaimed innocent victims of the death penalty.&lt;ref&gt;[http://capitaldefenseweekly.com/innocent.html Capital Defense Weekly&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070804222621/http://capitaldefenseweekly.com/innocent.html |date=4 August 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.justicedenied.org/executed.htm|title=Executed Innocents|publisher=Justicedenied.org|accessdate=23 August 2010|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20101124184742/http://justicedenied.org/executed.htm|archivedate=24 November 2010|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mitglied.lycos.de/PeterWill/penal9.htm|archive-url=http://arquivo.pt/wayback/20090522224521/http://mitglied.lycos.de/PeterWill/penal9.htm|url-status=dead|archive-date=22 May 2009|title=Wrongful executions|publisher=Mitglied.lycos.de|accessdate=23 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some have claimed that as many as 39 executions have been carried out in the face of compelling evidence of innocence or serious doubt about guilt in the US from 1992 through 2004. Newly available [[DNA evidence]] prevented the pending execution of more than 15 [[death row]] inmates during the same period in the US,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.innocenceproject.org/Content/575.php |title=The Innocence Project – News and Information: Press Releases |publisher=Innoccenceproject.org |accessdate=23 August 2010 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100702223208/http://www.innocenceproject.org/Content/575.php |archivedate=2 July 2010 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt; but DNA evidence is only available in a fraction of capital cases.&lt;ref name=&quot;CB2&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Lundin|first=Leigh|title=Casey Anthony Trial– Aftermath|url=http://criminalbrief.com/?p=17459|work=Capital Punishment|publisher=Criminal Brief|location=Orlando|date=10 July 2011|quote=With 400 condemned on death row, Florida is an extremely aggressive death penalty state, a state that will even execute for drug trafficking.|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110911200202/http://criminalbrief.com/?p=17459|archivedate=11 September 2011|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; {{as of|2017}}, 159 prisoners on death row have been exonerated by DNA or other evidence, which is seen as an indication that innocent prisoners have almost certainly been executed.&lt;ref&gt;Van Norman p. 288&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=DPIC2015&gt;{{cite web|title=Facts about the Death Penalty|url=http://www.deathpenaltyinfo.org/documents/FactSheet.pdf|publisher=Death Penalty Information Center|accessdate=23 December 2015|date=9 December 2015|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20151212150147/http://www.deathpenaltyinfo.org/documents/FactSheet.pdf|archivedate=12 December 2015|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; The National Coalition to
Abolish the Death Penalty claims that between 1976 and 2015, 1,414 prisoners in the United States have been executed while 156 sentenced to death have had their death sentences vacated, indicating that more than one in ten death row inmates were wrongly sentenced.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.ncadp.org/pages/innocence#_ftn6| title=Innocence| publisher=National Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty| accessdate=July 26, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is impossible to assess how many have been wrongly executed, since courts do not generally investigate the innocence of a dead defendant, and defense attorneys tend to concentrate their efforts on clients whose lives can still be saved; however, there is strong evidence of innocence in many cases.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.deathpenaltyinfo.org/executed-possibly-innocent#also|title=Executed But Possibly Innocent &amp;#124; Death Penalty Information Center|publisher=Deathpenaltyinfo.org|accessdate=30 April 2012|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120413152426/http://www.deathpenaltyinfo.org/executed-possibly-innocent#also|archivedate=13 April 2012|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Improper procedure may also result in unfair executions. For example, [[Amnesty International]] argues that in [[Singapore]] &quot;the [[Misuse of Drugs Act (Singapore)|Misuse of Drugs Act]] contains a series of presumptions which shift the burden of proof from the prosecution to the accused. This conflicts with the universally guaranteed right to be presumed innocent until proven guilty&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Amnesty International, [https://www.amnesty.org/documents/asa36/001/2004/en &quot;Singapore – The death penalty: A hidden toll of executions&quot;] (January 2004)&lt;/ref&gt; Singapore's Misuse of Drugs Act presumes one is guilty of possession of drugs if, as examples, one is found to be present or escaping from a location &quot;proved or presumed to be used for the purpose of smoking or administering a controlled drug&quot;, if one is in possession of a key to a premises where drugs are present, if one is in the company of another person found to be in possession of illegal drugs, or if one tests positive after being given a mandatory [[drug test|urine drug screening]]. Urine drug screenings can be given at the discretion of police, without requiring a search warrant. The onus is on the accused in all of the above situations to prove that they were not in possession of or consumed illegal drugs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Misuse of Drugs Act (CHAPTER 185)|page=PART III EVIDENCE, ENFORCEMENT AND PUNISHMENT|url=http://statutes.agc.gov.sg/aol/search/display/view.w3p;page=0;query=Id%3A%223f9aff0b-a3bd-41da-be16-66daab867d04%22%20Status%3Apublished%20%20TransactionTime%3A20151123000000;rec=0|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160305015714/http://statutes.agc.gov.sg/aol/search/display/view.w3p;page=0;query=Id%3A%223f9aff0b-a3bd-41da-be16-66daab867d04%22%20Status%3Apublished%20%20TransactionTime%3A20151123000000;rec=0|url-status=dead|archive-date=5 March 2016|accessdate=1 April 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Racial, ethnic and social class bias===
Opponents of the death penalty argue that this punishment is being used more often against perpetrators from racial and ethnic minorities and from lower socioeconomic backgrounds, than against those criminals who come from a privileged background; and that the background of the victim also influences the outcome.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.amnestyusa.org/our-work/issues/death-penalty/us-death-penalty-facts/death-penalty-and-race |title=Death Penalty and Race &amp;#124; Amnesty International USA |publisher=Amnestyusa.org |accessdate=11 February 2014 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140209235831/http://www.amnestyusa.org/our-work/issues/death-penalty/us-death-penalty-facts/death-penalty-and-race |archivedate=9 February 2014 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.eji.org/deathpenalty/racialbias |title=Racial Bias &amp;#124; Equal Justice Initiative |publisher=Eji.org |accessdate=11 February 2014 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20121001080516/http://www.eji.org/deathpenalty/racialbias |archivedate=1 October 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ncadp.org/pages/racial-bias |title=Racial Bias &amp;#124; National Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty |publisher=Ncadp.org |date=1999-03-18 |accessdate=2014-07-09 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140602161510/http://www.ncadp.org/pages/racial-bias |archivedate=2 June 2014 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Researchers have shown that white Americans are more likely to support the death penalty when told that it is mostly applied to African Americans,&lt;ref name=&quot;peffley-2007&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Peffley|first=Mark|last2=Hurwitz|first2=Jon|title=Persuasion and Resistance: Race and the Death Penalty in America|journal=American Journal of Political Science|year=2007|volume=51|issue=4|pages=996–1012|url=http://www.unc.edu/~fbaum/teaching/articles/AJPS-20007-Peffley.pdf|accessdate=3 May 2014|doi=10.1111/j.1540-5907.2007.00293.x|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140503085353/http://www.unc.edu/~fbaum/teaching/articles/AJPS-20007-Peffley.pdf|archivedate=3 May 2014|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; and that more stereotypically black-looking or darkskinned defendants are more likely to be sentenced to death if the case involves a white victim.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Eberhardt|first1=J. L.|last2=Davies|first2=P. G.|last3=Purdie-Vaughns|first3=V. J.|last4=Johnson|first4=S. L.|title=Looking Deathworthy: Perceived Stereotypicality of Black Defendants Predicts Capital-Sentencing Outcomes|journal=Psychological Science|date=1 May 2006|volume=17|issue=5|pages=383–386|doi=10.1111/j.1467-9280.2006.01716.x|pmid=16683924|url=http://works.bepress.com/sheri_johnson/12|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170831043144/https://works.bepress.com/sheri_johnson/12/|archivedate=31 August 2017|df=dmy-all|citeseerx=10.1.1.177.3897}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Alabama in 2019, a death row inmate named Domineque Ray was denied his imam in the room during his execution, instead only offered a Christian chaplain.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.npr.org/2019/02/08/692605056/supreme-court-lets-alabama-execute-muslim-murderer-without-imam-by-his-side|title=Justices Let Alabama Execute Death Row Inmate Who Wanted Imam By His Side|website=NPR.org|language=en|access-date=2019-02-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; After filing a complaint, a federal court of appeals ruled 5–4 against Ray's request. The majority cited the &quot;last-minute&quot; nature of the request, and the dissent stated that the treatment went against the core principle of denominational neutrality.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

In July 2019, two [[Shiite]] men, Ali Hakim al-Arab, 25, and Ahmad al-Malali, 24, were executed in Bahrain, despite the protests from the [[United Nations]] and rights group. [[Amnesty International]] stated that the executions were being carried out on confessions of “terrorism crimes” that were obtained through torture.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite_web|url=https://dailysunpost.com/bahrain-executes-3-men/|title=Bahrain executes 3 men|accessdate=28 July 2019|publisher=Daily Sun Post|date=28 July 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===International views===
{{anchor|International organisations}}
[[File:World laws pertaining to homosexual relationships and expression.svg|thumb|Same-sex intercourse illegal: {{legend|#800000|[[Death penalty for homosexuality]]}}
{{legend|#cc6633|Death penalty on books but not applied}}
]] 
The [[United Nations]] introduced [[UN moratorium on the death penalty|a resolution]] during the General Assembly's 62nd sessions in 2007 calling for a universal ban.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.worldcoalition.org/modules/news/article.php?storyid=10|title=Journée contre la peine de mort : le monde décide!|author=Thomas Hubert|date=29 June 2007|language=French|publisher=Coalition Mondiale|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070915094641/http://www.worldcoalition.org/modules/news/article.php?storyid=10|archivedate=15 September 2007|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://web.amnesty.org/pages/deathpenalty-index-eng |title=Abolish the death penalty &amp;#124; Amnesty International |publisher=Web.amnesty.org |accessdate=12 December 2012 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20081011062214/http://web.amnesty.org/pages/deathpenalty-index-eng |archivedate=11 October 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The approval of a draft resolution by the Assembly's third committee, which deals with human rights issues, voted 99 to 52, with 33 abstentions, in favour of the resolution on 15 November 2007 and was put to a vote in the Assembly on 18 December.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.amnesty.org/en/news-and-updates/news/un-set-key-death-penalty-vote-20071209|title=UN set for key death penalty vote|publisher=Amnesty International|date=9 December 2007|accessdate=12 February 2008|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080215001040/http://www.amnesty.org/en/news-and-updates/news/un-set-key-death-penalty-vote-20071209|archivedate=15 February 2008|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://wcd.coe.int/ViewDoc.jsp?id=1212297|title=Directorate of Communication – The global campaign against the death penalty is gaining momentum – Statement by Terry Davis, Secretary General of the Council of Europe|publisher=Wcd.coe.int|date=16 November 2007|accessdate=12 December 2012|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20121028025126/https://wcd.coe.int/ViewDoc.jsp?id=1212297|archivedate=28 October 2012|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.un.org/ga/news/news.asp?NewsID=24679&amp;Cr=general&amp;Cr1=assembly |title=UN General Assembly – News Stories |publisher=Un.org |accessdate=12 December 2012 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090109035000/http://www.un.org/ga/news/news.asp?NewsID=24679&amp;Cr=general&amp;Cr1=assembly |archivedate=9 January 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Again in 2008, a large majority of states from all regions adopted, on 20 November in the UN General Assembly (Third Committee), a second resolution calling for a moratorium on the use of the death penalty; 105 countries voted in favour of the draft resolution, 48 voted against and 31 abstained.

A range of amendments proposed by a small minority of pro-death penalty countries were overwhelmingly defeated. It had in 2007 passed a non-binding resolution (by 104 to 54, with 29 abstentions) by asking its member states for &quot;a moratorium on executions with a view to abolishing the death penalty&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.reuters.com/article/topNews/idUSN1849885920071218|title=U.N. Assembly calls for moratorium on death penalty|agency=Reuters|date=18 December 2007|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090417030913/http://www.reuters.com/article/topNews/idUSN1849885920071218|archivedate=17 April 2009|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:04CFREU-Article2-Crop.jpg|thumb|left|Article 2 of the [[Charter of Fundamental Rights of the European Union]] affirms the prohibition on capital punishment in the [[European Union|EU]]]]

A number of regional conventions prohibit the death penalty, most notably, the Sixth Protocol (abolition in time of peace) and the 13th Protocol (abolition in all circumstances) to the [[European Convention on Human Rights]]. The same is also stated under the Second Protocol in the [[American Convention on Human Rights]], which, however has not been ratified by all countries in the Americas, most notably Canada and the United States. Most relevant operative international treaties do not require its prohibition for cases of serious crime, most notably, the [[International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights]]. This instead has, in common with several other treaties, an optional protocol prohibiting capital punishment and promoting its wider abolition.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www2.ohchr.org/english/law/ccpr-death.htm |title=Second Optional Protocol to the ICCPR |accessdate=8 December 2007 |publisher=Office of the UN High Commissioner on Human Rights |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071121143327/http://www.ohchr.org/english/law/ccpr-death.htm |archivedate=21 November 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Several international organizations have made the abolition of the death penalty (during time of peace) a requirement of membership, most notably the [[European Union]] (EU) and the [[Council of Europe]]. The EU and the Council of Europe are willing to accept a [[Moratorium (law)|moratorium]] as an interim measure. Thus, while [[Capital punishment in Russia|Russia]] is a member of the Council of Europe, and the death penalty remains codified in its law, it has not made use of it since becoming a member of the Council – Russia has not executed anyone since 1996. With the exception of Russia (abolitionist in practice), [[Capital punishment in Kazakhstan|Kazakhstan]] (abolitionist for ordinary crimes only), and [[Capital punishment in Belarus|Belarus]] (retentionist), all European countries are classified as abolitionist.&lt;ref name=&quot;amnesty.org&quot;/&gt;

[[Capital punishment in Latvia|Latvia]] abolished ''de jure'' the death penalty for war crimes in 2012, becoming the last EU member to do so.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.amnesty.org/en/death-penalty/death-sentences-and-executions-in-2012 |title=The Death Penalty in 2012 &amp;#124; Amnesty International |publisher=Amnesty.org |date=9 April 2013 |accessdate=11 February 2014 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131029232445/http://www.amnesty.org/en/death-penalty/death-sentences-and-executions-in-2012 |archivedate=29 October 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Protocol no.13 calls for the abolition of the death penalty in all circumstances (including for war crimes). The majority of European countries have signed and ratified it. Some European countries have not done this, but all of them except Belarus and Kazakhstan have now abolished the death penalty in all circumstances (''de jure'', and Russia ''de facto''). [[Capital punishment in Poland|Poland]] is the most recent country to ratify the protocol, on 28 August 2013.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|language=Polish |url=http://wiadomosci.gazeta.pl/wiadomosci/1,114877,14507593,Prezydent_podpisal_ustawy_dot__zniesienia_kary_smierci.html |archive-url=https://archive.today/20130830201321/http://wiadomosci.gazeta.pl/wiadomosci/1,114877,14507593,Prezydent_podpisal_ustawy_dot__zniesienia_kary_smierci.html |url-status=dead |archive-date=30 August 2013 |title=Prezydent podpisał ustawy dot. zniesienia kary śmierci |trans-title=The President signed the Bill. the abolition of the death penalty |publisher=gazeta.pl |accessdate=7 September 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:ICCPR-OP2 members.svg|thumb|right|upright=1.15|Signatories to the Second Optional Protocol to the ICCPR: parties in dark green, signatories in light green, non-members in grey]]

The Protocol no.6 which prohibits the death penalty during peacetime has been ratified by all members of the European Council, except Russia (which has signed, but not ratified).

There are also other international abolitionist instruments, such as the [[Second Optional Protocol to the International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights]], which has 81 parties;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://treaties.un.org/Pages/ViewDetails.aspx?src=TREATY&amp;mtdsg_no=IV-12&amp;chapter=4 |title=UNTC |publisher=Treaties.un.org |accessdate=11 February 2014 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140104212752/https://treaties.un.org/Pages/ViewDetails.aspx?src=TREATY&amp;mtdsg_no=IV-12&amp;chapter=4 |archivedate=4 January 2014 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt; and the Protocol to the American Convention on Human Rights to Abolish the Death Penalty (for the Americas; ratified by 13 states).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Francisco J Montero |url=http://www.oas.org/juridico/english/sigs/a-53.html |title=:: Multilateral Treaties – Department of International Law – |publisher=OAS |accessdate=11 February 2014 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140507100541/http://www.oas.org/juridico/english/sigs/a-53.html |archivedate=7 May 2014 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Turkey]], over 500 people were sentenced to death after the [[1980 Turkish coup d'état]]. About 50 of them were executed, the last one 25 October 1984.&lt;!--- Hidir Aslan ---&gt; Then there was a ''de facto'' moratorium on the death penalty in Turkey.    As a move [[Accession of Turkey to the European Union|towards EU membership]], Turkey made some legal changes. The death penalty was removed from peacetime law by [[Grand National Assembly of Turkey|the National Assembly]] in August 2002, and in May 2004 Turkey amended [[Constitution of Turkey|its constitution]] in order to remove capital punishment in all circumstances. It ratified Protocol no. 13 to the European Convention on Human Rights in February 2006. As a result, Europe is a continent free of the death penalty in practice, all states but Russia, which has entered a moratorium, having ratified the Sixth Protocol to the European Convention on Human Rights, with the sole exception of [[Capital punishment in Belarus|Belarus]], which is not a member of the Council of Europe. The [[Parliamentary Assembly of the Council of Europe]] has been lobbying for Council of Europe observer states who practise the death penalty, the U.S. and Japan, to abolish it or lose their observer status. In addition to banning capital punishment for EU member states, the EU has also banned detainee transfers in cases where the receiving party may seek the death penalty.

[[Sub-Saharan Africa]]n countries that have recently abolished the death penalty include [[Burundi]], which abolished the death penalty for all crimes in 2009,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.amnesty.org/en/news-and-updates/news/burundi-abolishes-death-penalty-bans-homosexuality-20090427 |title=Burundi abolishes the death penalty but bans homosexuality &amp;#124; Amnesty International |publisher=Amnesty.org |accessdate=11 February 2014 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140218040338/http://www.amnesty.org/en/news-and-updates/news/burundi-abolishes-death-penalty-bans-homosexuality-20090427 |archivedate=18 February 2014 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Gabon]] which did the same in 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.handsoffcain.info/archivio_news/index.php?iddocumento=15302086&amp;mover=0 |title=Death Penalty: Hands Off Cain Announces Abolition In Gabon |publisher=Handsoffcain.info |accessdate=11 February 2014 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140225204443/http://www.handsoffcain.info/archivio_news/index.php?iddocumento=15302086&amp;mover=0 |archivedate=25 February 2014 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; On 5 July 2012, [[Benin]] became part of the Second Optional Protocol to the International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights (ICCPR), which prohibits the use of the death penalty.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.handsoffcain.info/bancadati/schedastato.php?idstato=17000190 |title=HANDS OFF CAIN against death penalty in the world |publisher=Handsoffcain.info |accessdate=11 February 2014 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140225204334/http://www.handsoffcain.info/bancadati/schedastato.php?idstato=17000190 |archivedate=25 February 2014 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The newly created [[South Sudan]] is among the 111 UN member states that supported the resolution passed by the United Nations General Assembly that called for the removal of the death penalty, therefore affirming its opposition to the practice. South Sudan, however, has not yet abolished the death penalty and stated that it must first amend its Constitution, and until that happens it will continue to use the death penalty.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.sudantribune.com/spip.php?article46452 |title=South Sudan says death penalty remains until constitution amended – Sudan Tribune: Plural news and views on Sudan |publisher=Sudan Tribune |accessdate=11 February 2014 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140228053742/http://www.sudantribune.com/spip.php?article46452 |archivedate=28 February 2014 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Among non-governmental organizations (NGOs), Amnesty International and [[Human Rights Watch]] are noted for their opposition to capital punishment. A number of such NGOs, as well as trade unions, local councils and bar associations formed a [[World Coalition Against the Death Penalty]] in 2002.

==Religious views==
{{Main|Religion and capital punishment}}
The world's major faiths have differing views depending on the religion, denomination, [[sect]] and/or the individual adherent. As an example, the world's largest [[Christianity|Christian]] denomination, [[Catholicism]], opposes capital punishment in all cases, whereas both the Baha'i and Islamic faiths support capital punishment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://reference.bahai.org/en/t/b/KA/ka-103.html|title=Bahá'í Reference Library – The Kitáb-i-Aqdas, Pages 203–204|website=reference.bahai.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Siting the Death Penalty Internationally|first1=David F.|last1=Greenberg|first2=Valerie|last2=West|date=2 May 2008|journal=Law &amp; Social Inquiry|volume=33|issue=2|pages=295–343|doi=10.1111/j.1747-4469.2008.00105.x}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==

* [[Death in custody]]
* [[Judicial dissolution]] aka &quot;The Corporate Death Penalty&quot;
* [[Mandatory death sentence]]
* [[World Coalition Against the Death Penalty]]
* [[UN moratorium on the death penalty]]
* ''[[The Death Penalty: Opposing Viewpoints]]'' (book)
* [[List of methods of capital punishment]]
* [[Revenge#Revenge dynamics|Revenge dynamics]]
* [[Shame culture]]
* [[Guilt-Shame-Fear spectrum of cultures]]
* [[List of wrongful convictions in the United States]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

'''Bibliography'''
* {{Cite book|last=Kronenwetter|first=Michael|title=Capital Punishment: A Reference Handbook|year=2001|edition=2|publisher=ABC-CLIO|isbn=978-1-57607-432-9|ref=harv}}
* Marian J. Borg and Michael L. Radelet. (2004). On botched executions. In: Peter Hodgkinson and William A. Schabas (eds.) Capital Punishment. pp.&amp;nbsp;143–68. [Online]. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press. Available from: Cambridge Books Online {{doi|10.1017/CBO9780511489273.006}}.
* Gail A. Van Norman. (2010). Physician participation in executions. In: Gail A. Van Norman et al. (eds.) Clinical Ethics in Anesthesiology. pp.&amp;nbsp;285–91. [Online]. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press. Available from: Cambridge Books Online {{doi|10.1017/CBO9780511841361.051}}.
{{Wikinews category|Death penalty}}
{{Commons category|Death penalty}}
{{Wikiquote|Capital punishment}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin|30em}}
* {{cite book|doi=10.4324/9781315673998|year=2016|title=Death ''Quest''|last1=Bohm|first1=Robert M.|isbn=9781315673998}}
* Curry, Tim. &quot;[http://www.wcl.american.edu/hrbrief/13/3curry.pdf Cutting the Hangman's Noose: African Initiatives to Abolish the Death Penalty].&quot; ([https://web.archive.org/web/20120720121914/http://www.wcl.american.edu/hrbrief/13/3curry.pdf Archive]) [[American University]] [[Washington College of Law]].
* Davis, David Brion. &quot;The movement to abolish capital punishment in America, 1787-1861.&quot; ''American Historical Review'' 63.1 (1957): 23–46. [https://www.jstor.org/stable/1847110 online]
* {{Cite book|last=Gaie|first=Joseph B. R|year=2004|title=The ethics of medical involvement in capital punishment : a philosophical discussion|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=FaUNdNuVjJYC&amp;pg=PP1|publisher=Kluwer Academic|isbn=978-1-4020-1764-3|ref=harv}}
* Hammel, A. ''Ending the Death Penalty: The European Experience in Global Perspective'' (2014).  
* {{cite journal|doi=10.1177/1462474501003003001|volume=3|issue=3|pages=331–354|title=Capital Punishment|journal=Punishment &amp; Society|year=2001|last1=Hood|first1=Roger}}
* {{cite book|last=Johnson|first=David T.|title=The Next Frontier: National Development, Political Change, and the Death Penalty in Asia|year=2009|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-533740-2|url=https://books.google.com/books/about/The_next_frontier.html?id=nZY8E6n-JAAC|author2=Zimring, Franklin E.}}
* {{Cite book|last=Kronenwetter|first=Michael|edition=2nd|year=2001|title=Capital punishment: a reference handbook|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=SOiuzOv061EC&amp;pg=PP1|publisher=ABC-CLIO|isbn=978-1-57607-432-9|ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book|last=McCafferty|first=James A|year=2010|title=Capital Punishment|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=n8P0BYf62wAC&amp;pg=PP1|publisher=AldineTransaction|isbn=978-0-202-36328-8|ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book|last=Mandery|first=Evan J|authorlink=Evan Mandery|year=2005|title=Capital punishment: a balanced examination|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=KPIf6dPJ_jQC&amp;pg=PP1|publisher=Jones and Bartlett Publishers|isbn=978-0-7637-3308-7|ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book|last=Marzilli|first=Alan|edition=2nd|year=2008|title=Capital Punishment – Point-counterpoint|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=nlOU4fUaiV8C&amp;pg=PP1|publisher=Chelsea House|isbn=978-0-7910-9796-0|ref=harv}}
* O’Brien, Doireann. &quot;Investigating the Origin of Europe and America’s Diverging Positions on the Issue of Capital Punishment.&quot; ''Social and Political Review'' (2018): 98+. [https://static1.squarespace.com/static/5a0c4a46c027d8d6e4f77763/t/5ab178a1f950b71e2a211f6b/1521580198095/SPR+Volume+XXVIII.pdf#page=99 online]
* [[Jed S. Rakoff|Rakoff, Jed S.]], &quot;The Last of His Kind&quot; (review of John Paul Stevens, ''The Making of a Justice: Reflections on My First 94 Years'', Little, Brown, 549 pp.), ''[[The New York Review of Books]]'', vol. LXVI, no. 14 (26 September 2019), pp.&amp;nbsp;20, 22, 24. [[John Paul Stevens]], &quot;a throwback to the postwar liberal Republican [U.S. Supreme Court] appointees&quot;, questioned the validity of &quot;the doctrine of [[sovereign immunity]], which holds that you cannot sue any state or federal government agency, or any of its officers or employees, for any wrong they may have committed against you, unless the state or federal government consents to being sued&quot; (p.&amp;nbsp;20); the propriety of &quot;the increasing resistance of the [[U.S. Supreme Court]] to most meaningful forms of [[gun control]]&quot; (p.&amp;nbsp;22); and &quot;the constitutionality of the death penalty... because of incontrovertible evidence that innocent people have been sentenced to death.&quot; (pp.&amp;nbsp;22, 24.)  
* Sarat, Austin and Juergen Martschukat, eds. ''Is the Death Penalty Dying?: European and American Perspectives'' (2011)
* {{Cite book|last=Woolf|first=Alex|year=2004|title=World issues – Capital Punishment
|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=U3McAciWdWYC&amp;pg=PA1|publisher=Chrysalis Education|isbn=978-1-59389-155-8|ref=harv}} for middle school students
* {{Cite book|last=Simon|first=Rita |year=2007|title=A comparative analysis of capital punishment : statutes, policies, frequencies, and public attitudes the world over|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=tpmQDVdv3UgC&amp;pg=PP1|publisher=Lexington Books|isbn=978-0-7391-2091-0|ref=harv}}
* Steiker, Carol S. &quot;Capital punishment and American exceptionalism.&quot; ''Oregon Law Review''. 81 (2002): 97+  [https://capitalpunishmentincontext.org/files/resources/international/CP%20and%20Amer%20Exceptionalism.pdf  online]
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{div col|colwidth=30em}}
* [http://usliberals.about.com/od/deathpenalty/i/DeathPenalty.htm About.com's Pros &amp; Cons of the Death Penalty and Capital Punishment]
* [http://www.iep.utm.edu/cap-puni/ Capital Punishment] article in the ''[[Internet Encyclopedia of Philosophy]]''.
* [http://www.clarkprosecutor.org/html/links/dplinks.htm 1000+ Death Penalty links all in one place]
* [http://www.capitaldefenseweekly.com/ Updates on the death penalty generally and capital punishment law specifically]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20061108150222/http://www.tdcj.state.tx.us/stat/executedoffenders.htm Texas Department of Criminal Justice: list of executed offenders and their last statements]
* [http://www.deathpenaltyworldwide.org/index.cfm Death Penalty Worldwide:] Academic research database on the laws, practice, and statistics of capital punishment for every death penalty country in the world.
* [http://www.answers.com/topic/capital-punishment Answers.com entry on capital punishment]
* [https://www.bbc.co.uk/sn/tvradio/programmes/horizon/broadband/tx/executions/ &quot;How to Kill a Human Being&quot;], [[Horizon (BBC TV series)|BBC Horizon]] TV programme documentary, 2008
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20060614135521/http://www.megalaw.com/top/deathpenalty.php U.S. and 50 State death penalty/capital punishment law and other relevant links] Megalaw
* Two audio documentaries covering execution in the United States: [https://web.archive.org/web/20070102134352/http://www.soundportraits.org/on-air/witness_to_an_execution/ Witness to an Execution] [https://web.archive.org/web/20070118082741/http://www.soundportraits.org/on-air/execution_tapes/ The Execution Tapes]
* [https://jurisoffice.com/blog/wrongfully-convicted-citizens/ Wrongfully Convicted Citizens:] capital punishment of wrongfully convicted citizens in the US, 2017
{{div col end}}

===In favour===
{{externalvideo|video1=[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wwYTDVRmGnc Singapore's Mandatory Death Penalty on Drug Trafficking]}}
{{div col|colwidth=30em}}
* [http://www.cjlf.org/deathpenalty/dpdeterrencefull.htm Studies showing the death penalty saves lives]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20170504000359/http://www.cjlf.org/deathpenalty/deathpenalty.htm Criminal Justice Legal Foundation]
* [http://www.recordnet.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20090805/A_OPINION0619/908050306/-1/NEWSMAP Keep life without parole and death penalty intact]
* [http://www.explorernews.com/articles/2009/08/26/opinion/doc4a9478dabc9be260176264.txt Why the death penalty is needed]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20050404011836/http://www.prodeathpenalty.com/ Pro Death Penalty.com]
* [http://www.wesleylowe.com/cp.html Pro Death Penalty Resource Page]
* [http://www.geometry.net/basic_c/capital_punishment_pro_death_penalty.php 119 Pro DP Links]
* [http://constitution.now77.com/ The Death Penalty is Constitutional]
* [https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2005/06/03/AR2005060301450.html The Paradoxes of a Death Penalty Stance] by [[Charles Lane (journalist)|Charles Lane]] in the [[Washington Post]]
* [http://www.clarkprosecutor.org/html/death/death.htm Clark County, Indiana, Prosecutor's Page on capital punishment]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20150407063507/http://www.capital-punishment.us/search/label/Pro In Favor of Capital Punishment] – Famous Quotes supporting Capital Punishment
* [http://www.nbcnews.com/id/19160965 Studies spur new death penalty debate]
{{div col end}}

===Opposing===
{{div col|colwidth=30em}}
* [http://www.worldcoalition.org/ World Coalition Against the Death Penalty]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20170512201234/http://deathwatchinternational.org/ Death Watch International] International anti-death penalty campaign group
* [http://www.nodeathpenalty.org/ Campaign to End the Death Penalty]
* [http://www.antideathpenalty.org/ Anti-Death Penalty Information]: includes a monthly watchlist of upcoming executions and death penalty statistics for the United States.
* [http://www.deathpenaltyinfo.org/ The Death Penalty Information Center]: Statistical information and studies
* [https://www.amnesty.org/en/death-penalty Amnesty International – Abolish the death penalty Campaign]: Human Rights organisation
* [http://eeas.europa.eu/human_rights/adp/index_en.htm European Union]: Information on anti-death penalty policies
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20061024192722/http://www.ipsnews.net/new_focus/deathpenalty/index.asp IPS Inter Press Service] International news on capital punishment
* [http://www.deathpenalty.org/ Death Penalty Focus]: American group dedicated to abolishing the death penalty
* [http://www.reprieve.org/ Reprieve.org]: United States-based volunteer program for foreign lawyers, students, and others to work at death penalty defense offices
* [https://www.aclu.org/DeathPenalty/DeathPenaltyMain.cfm American Civil Liberties Union]: Demanding a Moratorium on the Death Penalty
* [http://www.ncadp.org/ National Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty]
* [http://www.nswccl.org.au/nswccl_policy_on_the_death_penalty NSW Council for Civil Liberties]: an Australian organisation opposed to the Death Penalty in the Asian region
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20100506030411/http://www.thesomnambulist.org/2008/01/winning-a-war-on-terror-eliminating-the-death-penalty/ Winning a war on terror: eliminating the death penalty]
* [http://pennreview.com/2011/12/electric-chair-at-sing-sing Electric Chair at Sing Sing], a 1900 photograph by William M. Vander Weyde, accompanied by a poem by [[Jared Carter]].
* [http://www.shreveporttimes.com/longform/opinion/readers/2015/03/20/lead-prosecutor-offers-apology-in-the-case-of-exonerated-death-row-inmate-glenn-ford/25049063/?from=global&amp;sessionKey=&amp;autologin= Lead prosecutor apologizes for role in sending man to death row] Shreveport Times, 2015
{{div col end}}

===Religious views===
{{div col|colwidth=30em}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20020122104520/http://www.deathpenaltyreligious.org/education/perspectives/dalailama.html The Dalai Lama] – Message supporting the moratorium on the death penalty
* [http://www.engaged-zen.org/articles/Damien_P_Horigan-Buddhism_Capital_Punishment.html Buddhism &amp; Capital Punishment] from The Engaged Zen Society
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20060105042354/http://www.ou.org/torah/savannah/5760/behaalotcha60.htm Orthodox Union website: Rabbi Yosef Edelstein: Parshat Beha'alotcha: A Few Reflections on Capital Punishment]
* [http://www.priestsforlife.org/deathpenalty Priests for Life] – Lists several Catholic links
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20010614045347/http://americancatholic.org/Newsletters/CU/ac0195.asp The Death Penalty: Why the Church Speaks a Countercultural Message] by Kenneth R. Overberg, S.J., from [http://www.americancatholic.org/ AmericanCatholic.org]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20030812072150/http://www.americancatholic.org/Newsletters/YU/ay0696.asp Wrestling with the Death Penalty] by Andy Prince, from ''Youth Update'' on [http://www.americancatholic.org/ AmericanCatholic.org]
* {{CathEncy|wstitle=Capital Punishment}}
* [http://www.cacp.org/ Catholics Against Capital Punishment]: offers a Catholic perspective and provides resources and links
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20101202000306/http://kashifshahzada.com/2010/11/20/why-the-death-penalty-is-un-islamic/ Kashif Shahzada 2010]: Why The Death Penalty Is un-Islamic?
{{div col end}}
{{Capital punishment}}
{{Navboxes|list=
{{Europe topic|Capital punishment in}}
{{Asia topic|Capital punishment in}}
{{Africa topic|Capital punishment in}}
{{North America topic|Capital punishment in}}
{{South America topic|Capital punishment in}}
{{Oceania topic|Capital punishment in}}
{{CapPun-US}}
{{Law country lists}}
}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2012}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Capital Punishment}}
[[Category:Capital punishment| ]]
[[Category:Ethically disputed judicial practices]]
[[Category:Penology]]
[[Category:Social policy]]</text>
      <sha1>kys4gnjwpwrt0if3eyb5u8is4inc5bg</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
