  <page>
    <title>Casuistry</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5946</id>
    <revision>
      <id>932739040</id>
      <parentid>932368091</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-12-27T23:05:32Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Monkbot</username>
        <id>20483999</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* Early modern times */[[User:Monkbot/task 15: normalize lang icon templates|Task 15]]:  language icon template(s) replaced (1×);</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Reasoning by extrapolation}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}
'''Casuistry''' ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|k|æ|zj|u|ᵻ|s|t|r|i}}) is a process of reasoning that seeks to resolve moral problems by extracting or extending theoretical rules from a particular case, and reapplying those rules to new instances.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Philosophy-Dictionary.org|url=http://www.philosophy-dictionary.org/casuistry|work=casuistry|accessdate=7 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  This method occurs in [[applied ethics]] and [[jurisprudence]]. The term is also commonly used as a pejorative to criticize the use of clever but unsound reasoning, especially in relation to moral questions (as in [[sophistry]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/cgi-local/DHI/dhi.cgi?id=dv1-35 |title=Casuistry |website=Dictionary of the History of Ideas |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20060618095059/http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/cgi-local/DHI/dhi.cgi?id=dv1-35 |archive-date=18 June 2006 |publisher=[[University of Virginia Library]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The word ''casuistry'' derives from the [[Latin]] noun ''casus'' (&quot;case&quot; or &quot;occurrence&quot;).

The ''[[Oxford English Dictionary]]'' says, quoting Viscount Bolingbroke, Viscount (1749), that the word &quot;[o]ften (and perhaps originally) applied to a quibbling or evasive way of dealing with difficult cases of duty.&quot; Its textual references, except for certain technical usages, are consistently pejorative (e.g., &quot;Casuistry destroys by distinctions and exceptions, all morality, and effaces the essential difference between right and wrong&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopedia|title=Oxford English Dictionary|url=http://www.oed.com/view/Entry/28642|article=Casuistry|accessdate=21 September 2017}}, quoting {{cite book|url=https://archive.org/stream/lettersonspirit01boligoog#page/n175/mode/2up|title=Letters on the Spirit of Patriotism and on the Idea of a Patriot King|last=Bolingbroke|first=Viscount|year=1749|location=London|p=170}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Definition==
Casuistry is the &quot;[s]tudy of cases of conscience and a method of solving conflicts of obligations by applying general principles of ethics, religion, and moral theology to particular and concrete cases of human conduct. This frequently demands an extensive knowledge of natural law and equity, civil law, ecclesiastical precepts, and an exceptional skill in interpreting these various norms of conduct.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Runes|first=Dagobert D.|title=Dictionary of Philosophy|url=http://www.ditext.com/runes/c.html|accessdate=7 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; It remains a common tool for applied ethics.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Philosophy Pages|url=http://www.philosophypages.com/dy/c.htm#casu|work=Casuistry|accessdate=7 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
Casuistry dates from [[Aristotle]] (384–322 BC), yet the zenith of casuistry was from 1550 to 1650, when the [[Society of Jesus]] used case-based reasoning, particularly in administering the [[Sacrament of Penance]] (or &quot;confession&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Science of Conjecture: Evidence and Probability Before Pascal|last=Franklin|first=James|publisher=Johns Hopkins University Press|year=2001|location=Baltimore|pages=83–88}}&lt;/ref&gt; The term ''casuistry'' or '''Jesuitism''' quickly became pejorative with [[Blaise Pascal]]'s attack on the misuse of casuistry. Some Jesuit theologians,{{who|date=November 2018}} in view of promoting personal responsibility and the respect of [[freedom of conscience]], stressed the importance of the 'case by case' approach to personal moral decisions and ultimately developed and accepted a casuistry (the study of ''cases of consciences'') where at the time of decision, individual inclinations were more important than the moral law itself.

In ''[[Provincial Letters]]'' (1656–7)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://ebooks.adelaide.edu.au/p/pascal/blaise/|title=The Provincial Letters of Blaise Pascal|last=Pascal|first=Blaise|publisher=Chatto &amp; Windus|others=M'Crie, Thomas (trans.)|year=1898|series=eBooks@Adelaide|location=London|origyear=1657}}&lt;/ref&gt; the  French [[mathematician]], religious philosopher and [[Jansenist]] sympathiser, [[Blaise Pascal]] vigorously attacked the moral [[laxism]] of such Jesuits scolded the Jesuits for using casuistic reasoning in confession to placate wealthy Church donors, while punishing poor penitents. Pascal charged that aristocratic penitents could confess their sins one day, re-commit the sin the next day, generously donate the following day, then return to re-confess their sins and only receive the lightest punishment; Pascal's criticisms darkened casuistry's reputation.

A British encyclopedia of 1900 claimed that it was &quot;popularly regarded as an attempt to achieve holy ends by unholy means.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fromoldbooks.org/Wood-NuttallEncyclopaedia/j/jesuitism.html Nuttall Encyclopædia of General Knowledge]&lt;/ref&gt;

It was not until publication of ''The Abuse of Casuistry: A History of Moral Reasoning'' (1988), by Albert Jonsen and [[Stephen Toulmin]],&lt;ref&gt;Albert Jonsen and [[Stephen Toulmin]], ''The Abuse of Casuistry: A History of Moral Reasoning'', Berkeley, U. California Press (1990, {{ISBN|0-520-06960-9}}).&lt;/ref&gt; that a revival of casuistry occurred. They argue that the abuse of casuistry is the problem, not casuistry ''per se'' (itself an example of casuistic reasoning). Properly used, casuistry is powerful reasoning. Jonsen and Toulmin offer casuistry in dissolving the contradictory tenets of [[moral absolutism]] and the common secular [[moral relativism]]: &quot;the form of reasoning constitutive of classical casuistry is [[rhetorical reason]]ing&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Jonsen, 1991, p. 297.&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, the ethical philosophies of [[Utilitarianism]] (especially [[preference utilitarianism]]) and [[Pragmatism]] commonly are identified as greatly employing casuistic reasoning.

==Early modern times==
The casuistic method was popular among [[Catholic Church|Catholic]] thinkers in the early modern period, and not only among the [[Jesuits]], as it is commonly thought. &lt;section end=Alleged corruption in the Catholic Church transclusion/&gt;Famous casuistic authors include [[Antonio Escobar y Mendoza]], whose ''Summula casuum conscientiae'' (1627) enjoyed a great success, [[Thomas Sanchez]], [[Vincenzo Filliucci]] (Jesuit and [[Apostolic Penitentiary|penitentiary]] at [[St Peter]]'s), [[Antonino Diana]], [[Paul Laymann]] (''Theologia Moralis'', 1625), [[John Azor]] (''Institutiones Morales'', 1600), [[Etienne Bauny]], [[Louis Cellot]], [[Valerius Reginaldus]], [[Hermann Busembaum]] (d. 1668), etc. &lt;section begin=Alleged corruption in the Catholic Church transclusion/&gt;One of the main theses of casuists was the necessity to adapt the rigorous morals of the [[Church Fathers|Early Fathers]] of [[Christianity]] to modern morals, which led in some extreme cases to justify what [[Innocent XI]] later called &quot;laxist moral&quot; (i.e. justification of [[usury]], [[homicide]], [[regicide]], [[lie|lying]] through &quot;[[Doctrine of mental reservation|mental reservation]]&quot;, [[Catholic teachings on sexual morality|adultery and loss of virginity before marriage]], etc.—all due cases registered by [[Blaise Pascal|Pascal]] in the ''[[Provincial Letters]]'').{{fact|date=November 2019}}

The progress of casuistry was interrupted toward the middle of the 17th century by the controversy which arose concerning the [[Catholic probabilism|doctrine of probabilism]], which stipulated that one could choose to follow a &quot;probable opinion&quot;, that is, supported by a theologian or another, even if it contradicted a more probable opinion or a quotation from one of the [[Fathers of the Church]].&lt;ref&gt;Franklin, ''Science of Conjecture'', p. 74–6, 83.&lt;/ref&gt; The controversy divided Catholic theologians into two camps, Rigorists and Laxists.

&lt;section begin=Alleged corruption in the Catholic Church transclusion/&gt;Certain kinds of casuistry were criticized by early [[Protestant Reformation|Protestant theologians]], because it was used in order to justify many of the abuses that they sought to reform. It was famously attacked by the Catholic and [[Jansenist]] philosopher [[Blaise Pascal|Pascal]], during the [[formulary controversy]] against the Jesuits, in his [[Lettres provinciales|Provincial Letters]] as the use of [[rhetorics]] to justify moral laxity, which became identified by the public with [[Jesuitism]]; hence the everyday use of the term to mean complex and [[sophist]]ic reasoning to justify moral laxity.&lt;ref&gt;170 &quot;Casuistry..destroys, by distinctions and exceptions, all morality, and effaces the essential difference between right and wrong.&quot; Henry St. John, Viscount Bolingbroke, ''Letters on the Spirit of Patriotism 1736'' (pub. 1749), quoted in Oxford English Dictionary, 1989 ed.&lt;/ref&gt; By the mid-18th century, &quot;casuistry&quot; had become a synonym for specious moral reasoning.&lt;ref&gt;Jonsen, Albert R., The Abuse of Casuistry: A History of Moral Reasoning, University of California Press, 1988. {{ISBN|0-52-006063-6}} (p. 2).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;section end=Alleged corruption in the Catholic Church transclusion/&gt; However, [[Puritan casuistry|Puritans]] were known for their own development of casuistry.{{fact|date=November 2019}}

In 1679 [[Pope Innocent&amp;nbsp;XI]] publicly condemned sixty-five of the more radical propositions (''stricti mentalis''), taken chiefly from the writings of Escobar, [[Francisco Suarez|Suarez]] and other casuists as ''propositiones laxorum moralistarum'' and forbade anyone to teach them under penalty of [[excommunication]].&lt;ref&gt;Kelly, J.N.D., The Oxford History of the Popes, Oxford University Press, 1986. {{ISBN|0-19-282085-0}} (p. 287).&lt;/ref&gt; Despite this papal condemnation, both Catholicism and Protestantism permit the use of ambiguous and equivocal statements in specific circumstances.&lt;ref&gt;J.-P. Cavaillé, ''[http://dossiersgrihl.revues.org/document281.html Ruser sans mentir, de la casuistique aux sciences sociales: le recours à l’équivocité, entre efficacité pragmatique et souci éthique]'', in [[Serge Latouche]], P.-J. Laurent, O. Servais &amp; M. Singleton, ''Les Raisons de la ruse. Une perspective anthropologique et psychanalytique'', Actes du colloque international «La raison rusée», Louvain la Neuve, mars 2001, Paris, La Découverte, 2004, pp. 93–118 {{in lang|fr}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Modern times==
[[George Edward Moore|G.&amp;nbsp;E. Moore]] dealt with casuistry in chapter 1.4 of his ''[[Principia Ethica]]'', in which he claims that &quot;the defects of casuistry are not defects of principle; no objection can be taken to its aim and object. It has failed only because it is far too difficult a subject to be treated adequately in our present state of knowledge&quot;. Furthermore, he asserted that &quot;casuistry is the goal of ethical investigation. It cannot be safely attempted at the beginning of our studies, but only at the end&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/?id=ZLpcgAQvr_gC&amp;pg=PA57&amp;lpg=PA57&amp;dq=%22the+defects+of+casuistry+are+not+defects+of+principle+no+objection+can+be+taken+to+its+aim+and+object+it+has+failed+only+because+it+is+far+too+difficult+a+subject+to%22|title=Principia Ethica|last=Moore|first=George Edward|publisher=Cambridge University Press|year=1993|isbn=0-521-44848-4|editor-last=Baldwin|editor-first=Thomas|editor-link=Thomas Baldwin (philosopher)|edition=2|location=Cambridge|page=57|authorlink=George Edward Moore|origyear=1903}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Since the 1960s, [[applied ethics]] has revived the ideas of casuistry in applying ethical reasoning to particular cases in [[law]], [[bioethics]], and [[business ethics]], so the reputation of casuistry is somewhat rehabilitated.

[[Pope Francis]], a Jesuit, has criticised utilizing casuistry &quot;the practice of setting general laws on the basis of exceptional cases&quot; in instances where a more wholistic approach would be more appropriate.&lt;ref&gt;[https://archive.is/20140527185002/http://www.catholicnews.com/data/stories/cns/1402173.htm &quot;Pope to meet with sex abuse victims for first time in June&quot;, Francis X. Rocca]. Catholic News Service. Online.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Philosophy|Psychology}}
* {{annotated link|Applied ethics}}
* {{annotated link|Case-based reasoning}}
* {{annotated link|Case-based evidence}}
* {{annotated link|Consequentialism}}
* {{annotated link|Dispensation (canon law)}}
* {{annotated link|First principle}}
* {{annotated link|List of thought processes}}
* {{annotated link|Qiyas|''Qiyas''}}
* {{annotated link|Rhetoric}}
* {{annotated link|Rhetorical reason}}
* {{annotated link|School of Salamanca}}
* {{annotated link|Situational ethics}}
* {{annotated link|Talmudical hermeneutics}}

==References==
{{Reflist|32em}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin|3}}
* {{cite journal|doi=10.1093/jmp/16.1.29|pmid=2010719|title=Getting Down to Cases: The Revival of Casuistry in Bioethics|journal=Journal of Medicine and Philosophy|volume=16|issue=1|pages=29–51|year=1991|last1=Arras|first1=J. D.|url=https://semanticscholar.org/paper/069ddd49c823d791c9c09eb0eaec38e97f636c63}}
* {{cite journal|doi=10.1111/j.1468-0025.1989.tb00206.x|title=A Case for Casuistry in the Church|journal=Modern Theology|volume=6|pages=29–51|year=1989|last1=Biggar|first1=Nigel}}
* {{cite journal|doi=10.2307/3562714|pmid=1544801|jstor=3562714|title=The Hospital Ethics Committee Health Care's Moral Conscience or White Elephant?|journal=The Hastings Center Report|volume=22|issue=1|pages=6–11|year=1992|last1=Blake|first1=David C.}}
* Bliton, Mark J. (1993). The Ethics of Clinical Ethics Consultation: On the Way to Clinical Philosophy (Diss. Vanderbilt)
* {{cite journal|doi=10.1207/s15327728jmme0702_4|title=Casuistry: A Case-Based Methods for Journalists|journal=Journal of Mass Media Ethics|volume=7|issue=2|pages=107–120|year=1992|last1=Boeyink|first1=David E.}}
* {{cite journal|doi=10.1093/jmp/16.5.475|pmid=1779208|title=Who is Entitled to Double Effect?|journal=Journal of Medicine and Philosophy|volume=16|issue=5|pages=475–494|year=1991|last1=Boyle|first1=J.}}
* {{cite journal|doi=10.2307/3562015|jstor=3562015|title=Ethical Questions Raised by the Persistent Vegetative Patient|journal=The Hastings Center Report|volume=18|issue=1|pages=33–37|year=1988|last1=Brody|first1=Baruch A.}}
* {{cite book|doi=10.1007/978-94-015-7838-7_3|chapter=A Historical Introduction to Jewish Casuistry on Suicide and Euthanasia|title=Suicide and Euthanasia|volume=35|pages=39–75|series=Philosophy and Medicine|year=1989|last1=Brody|first1=Baruch A.|isbn=978-90-481-4039-8}}
* {{cite journal|doi=10.1080/00335639209383979|title=Creative casuistry and feminist consciousness: The rhetoric of moral reform|journal=Quarterly Journal of Speech|volume=78|pages=16–32|year=1992|last1=Carlson|first1=A. Cheree}}
* Carney, Bridget Mary. (1993). Modern Casuistry: An Essential But Incomplete Method for Clinical Ethical Decision-Making. (Diss., Graduate Theological Union).
* {{cite journal|doi=10.1007/BF00489238|pmid=2339334|title=Interpretive bioethics: The way of discernment|journal=Theoretical Medicine|volume=11|issue=1|pages=51–59|year=1990|last1=Carson|first1=Ronald A.}}
* Carson, Ronald A. (1988). &quot;Paul Ramsey, Principled Protestant Casuist: A Retrospective.&quot; Medical Humanities Review, Vol. 2, pp. 24-35.
* Chidwick, Paula Marjorie (1994). Approaches to Clinical Ethical Decision-Making: Ethical Theory, Casuistry and Consultation. (Diss., U of Guelph)
* {{cite journal|doi=10.1093/jaarel/LX.2.313|title=Abortion in Jewish Thought: A Study in Casuistry|journal=Journal of the American Academy of Religion|issue=2|pages=313–324|year=1992|last1=Davis|first1=Dena S.}}
* {{cite journal|doi=10.1093/jmp/17.5.511|pmid=1431667|title=Moving Forward in Bioethical Theory: Theories, Cases, and Specified Principlism|journal=Journal of Medicine and Philosophy|volume=17|issue=5|pages=511–539|year=1992|last1=Degrazia|first1=D.}}
* {{cite journal|doi=10.1136/jme.18.2.61|pmid=1619625|pmc=1376108|title=Health care ethics and casuistry|journal=Journal of Medical Ethics|volume=18|issue=2|pages=61–66|year=1992|last1=Downie|first1=R.}}
* Drane, J.F. (1990). &quot;Methodologies for Clinical Ethics.&quot; Bulletin of the Pan American Health Organization, Vol. 24, pp. 394-404.
* Dworkin, R.B. (1994). &quot;Emerging Paradigms in Bioethics: Symposium.&quot; Indiana Law Journal, Vol. 69, pp. 945-1122.
* Elliot, Carl (1992). &quot;Solving the Doctor's Dilemma?&quot; New Scientist, Vol. 133, pp. 42-43.
* Emanuel, Ezekiel J. (1991). The Ends of Human Life: Medical Ethics in a Liberal Polity (Cambridge).
* Franklin, James (2001). The Science of Conjecture: Evidence and Probability Before Pascal (Johns Hopkins), ch. 4.
* Gallagher, Lowell (1991). Medusa's Gaze: Casuistry and Conscience in the Renaissance (Stanford)
* {{cite journal|doi=10.1097/00012272-199503000-00006|pmid=7778890|title=Casuistry, care, compassion, and ethics data analysis|journal=Advances in Nursing Science|volume=17|issue=3|pages=47–57|year=1995|last1=Gaul|first1=Alice Leveille}}
* Green, Bryan S. (1988). Literary Methods and Sociological Theory: Case Studies of Simmel and Weber (Albany)
* {{cite journal|doi=10.1016/0277-9536(94)90348-4|pmid=7801153|title=The forms and limits of medical ethics|journal=Social Science &amp; Medicine|volume=39|issue=9|pages=1155–1164|year=1994|last1=Hoffmaster|first1=Barry}}
* Houle, Martha Marie (1983). The Fictions of Casuistry and Pascal's Jesuit in &quot;Les Provinciales&quot; (Diss. U California, San Diego)
* {{cite journal|doi=10.1017/S0022046900010216|title=Casuistry in Action: Robert Boyle's Confessional Interviews with Gilbert Burnet and Edward Stillingfleet, 1691|journal=The Journal of Ecclesiastical History|volume=44|pages=80–98|year=1993|last1=Hunter|first1=Michael}}
* {{cite journal|doi=10.1093/jmp/14.2.193|pmid=2769113|title=A Science of Individuals: Medicine and Casuistry|journal=Journal of Medicine and Philosophy|volume=14|issue=2|pages=193–212|year=1989|last1=Hunter|first1=K. M.}}
* {{cite journal|doi=10.1093/jmp/16.1.113|pmid=2010718|title=American Moralism and the Origin of Bioethics in the United States|journal=Journal of Medicine and Philosophy|volume=16|issue=1|pages=113–130|year=1991|last1=Jonsen|first1=A. R.}}
* {{cite journal|doi=10.1007/BF00489424|pmid=3704959|title=Casuistry and clinical ethics|journal=Theoretical Medicine|volume=7|issue=1|pages=65–74|year=1986|last1=Jonsen|first1=Albert R.}}
* Jonsen, Albert R. (1986). &quot;Casuistry&quot; in J.F. Childress and J. Macgvarrie, eds. Westminster Dictionary of Christian Ethics (Philadelphia)
* {{cite journal|doi=10.1007/BF00489890|pmid=1801300|title=Casuistry as methodology in clinical ethics|journal=Theoretical Medicine|volume=12|issue=4|pages=295–307|year=1991|last1=Jonsen|first1=Albert R.}}
* {{cite journal|doi=10.2307/3562885|jstor=3562885|title=Of Balloons and Bicycles; or, the Relationship between Ethical Theory and Practical Judgment|journal=The Hastings Center Report|volume=21|issue=5|pages=14–16|year=1991|last1=Jonsen|first1=Albert R.}}
* Jonsen, Albert R. and Stephen Toulmin (1988). The Abuse of Casuistry: A History of Moral Reasoning (California).
* Keenan, James F., S.J. and Thomas A. Shannon. (1995). The Context of Casuistry (Washington).
* Kirk, K. (1936). Conscience and Its Problems, An Introduction to Casuistry (London)
* {{cite journal|doi=10.1111/j.1467-9833.1990.tb00263.x|title=How is Applied Philosophy to be Applied?|journal=Journal of Social Philosophy|volume=21|pages=16–26|year=1990|last1=Klinefelter|first1=Donald S.}}
* {{cite journal|doi=10.1007/BF00999217|pmid=8059430|title=Case method and casuistry: The problem of bias|journal=Theoretical Medicine|volume=15|issue=1|pages=21–37|year=1994|last1=Kopelman|first1=Loretta M.}}
* {{cite journal|doi=10.1093/jmp/15.2.199|pmid=2351894|title=What is Applied About &quot;Applied&quot; Philosophy?|journal=Journal of Medicine and Philosophy|volume=15|issue=2|pages=199–218|year=1990|last1=Kopelman|first1=L. M.}}
* {{cite journal|doi=10.1353/ken.0.0082|pmid=11645267|title=Casuistry and Its Communitarian Critics|journal=Kennedy Institute of Ethics Journal|volume=4|issue=2|pages=99–116|year=1994|last1=Kuczewski|first1=Mark G.}}
* Kuczewski, Mark G. (1994). Fragmentation and Consensus in Contemporary Neo-Aristotelian Ethics: A Study in Communitarianism and Casuistry (Diss., Duquesne U).
* {{cite book|doi=10.1017/CBO9780511521430|title=Conscience and Casuistry in Early Modern Europe|year=1988|isbn=9780521520201|last1=Leites|first1=Edmund}}
* {{cite journal|doi=10.1111/j.1540-6253.1974.tb00146.x|title=Conscience, Casuistry, and Moral Decision: Some Historical Perspectives|journal=Journal of Chinese Philosophy|volume=2|pages=41–58|year=1974|last1=Leites|first1=Edmund}}
* Long, Edward LeRoy, junior (1954). Conscience and Compromise: an Approach to Protestant Casuistry (Philadelphia, Penn.: Westminster Press)
* {{cite journal|doi=10.1353/hph.1990.0086|title=The Abuse of Casuistry: A History of Moral Reasoning (Review)|journal=Journal of the History of Philosophy|volume=28|issue=4|pages=634–635|year=1990|last1=MacIntyre|first1=Alasdair C.}}
* {{cite journal|doi=10.5840/monist198467438|title=Does Applied Ethics Rest on a Mistake?|journal=Monist|volume=67|issue=4|pages=498–513|year=1984|last1=MacIntyre|first1=Alasdair}}
* Mackler, Aaron Leonard. Cases of Judgments in Ethical Reasoning: An Appraisal of Contemporary Casuistry and Holistic Model for the Mutual Support of Norms and Case Judgments (Diss., Georgetown U).
* {{cite journal|doi=10.1017/S0963180100005223|pmid=7994464|title=Anchor and Course for the Modern Ship of Casuistry|journal=Cambridge Quarterly of Healthcare Ethics|volume=3|issue=3|pages=391–402|year=1994|last1=Macpherson-Smith|first1=Malcolm}}
* {{cite book|doi=10.1075/sc.6.09mah|chapter=Collaboration and Casuistry|title=Peirce and Value Theory|volume=6|pages=61|series=Semiotic Crossroads|year=1994|last1=Mahowald|first1=Mary B.|isbn=978-90-272-1947-3}}
* McCready, Amy R. (1992). &quot;Milton's Casuistry: The Case of 'The Doctrine and Discipline of Divorce.' &quot; Journal of Medieval and Renaissance Studies, Vol. 22, pp. 393-428.
* {{cite journal|doi=10.1093/jmp/14.6.617|pmid=2614282|title=On Transplanting Human Fetal Tissue: Presumptive Duties and the Task of Casuistry|journal=Journal of Medicine and Philosophy|volume=14|issue=6|pages=617–640|year=1989|last1=Miller|first1=R. B.}}
* {{cite book|doi=10.1017/CBO9780511627842.008|chapter=Medical ethics, moral philosophy and moral tradition|title=Medicine and Moral Reasoning|pages=91–105|year=1994|last1=Murray|first1=Thomas H.|isbn=9780521459464}}
* {{cite journal|doi=10.1111/j.1540-4560.1993.tb00927.x|pmid=17167922|title=Moral Reasoning in Social Context|journal=Journal of Social Issues|volume=49|issue=2|pages=185–200|year=1993|last1=Murray|first1=Thomas H.}}
* Odozor, Paulinus Ikechukwu (1989). Richard A. McCormick and Casuistry: Moral Decision-Making in Conflict Situations (M.A. Thesis, St. Michael's College).
* Pack, Rolland W. (1988). Case Studies and Moral Conclusions: The Philosophical Use of Case Studies in Biomedical Ethics (Diss., Georgetown U).
* Pascal, Blaise (1967). The Provincial Letters (London).
* {{cite journal|doi=10.1007/BF00999885|title=Feminist cautions about casuistry: The Supreme Court's abortion decisions as paradigms|journal=Policy Sciences|volume=27|issue=2–3|pages=143–160|year=1994|last1=Peach|first1=Lucinda Joy}}
* Río Parra, Elena del (2008). Cartografías de la conciencia española en la Edad de Oro (Mexico).
* {{cite journal|doi=10.1177/004057369405100204|title=Thinking Through the Ethics of Abortion|journal=Theology Today|volume=51|issue=2|pages=235–248|year=1994|last1=Rudy|first1=Kathy}}
* Seiden, Melvin (1990). Measure for Measure: Casuistry and Artistry (Washington).
* {{cite journal|doi=10.5840/thought199267223|title=Women and the New Casuistry|journal=Thought|volume=67|issue=2|pages=148–157|year=1992|last1=Sichol|first1=Marcia}}
* {{cite journal|doi=10.1111/j.1467-9744.1980.tb00374.x|title=Is Ethics a Science? Ought It to Be?|journal=Zygon|volume=15|pages=29–42|year=1980|last1=Singer|first1=Marcus G.}}
* Smith, David H. (1991). &quot;Stories, Values, and Patient Care Decisions.&quot; in Charles Conrad, ed. The Ethical Nexus: Values in Organizational Decision Making. (New Jersey).
* {{cite journal|doi=10.1007/BF01305396|title=Everyone's conforming to a rule|journal=Philosophical Studies|volume=48|issue=3|pages=375–387|year=1985|last1=Sobel|first1=Jordan Howard}}
* {{cite journal|doi=10.1177/004056399305400105|title=Notes on Moral Theology: 1992|journal=Theological Studies|volume=54|pages=95–159|year=1993|last1=Keenan|first1=James F.}}
* Starr, G. (1971). Defoe and Casuistry (Princeton).
* {{cite book|doi=10.1007/978-94-009-2715-5_14|chapter=Justification in Ethics|title=Moral Theory and Moral Judgments in Medical Ethics|volume=32|pages=193–211|series=Philosophy and Medicine|year=1988|last1=Strong|first1=Carson|isbn=978-94-010-7723-1}}
* Tallmon, James Michael (2001). &quot;Casuistry&quot; in The Encyclopedia of Rhetoric. Ed. Thomas O. Sloane. New York: Oxford University Press, pp. 83-88.
* Tallmon, James Michael (1993). Casuistry and the Quest for Rhetorical Reason: Conceptualizing a Method of Shared Moral Inquiry (Diss., U of Washington).
* {{cite journal|doi=10.1093/jmp/19.1.103|pmid=8201287|title=How Jonsen Really Views Casuistry: A Note on the Abuse of Father Wildes|journal=Journal of Medicine and Philosophy|volume=19|issue=1|pages=103–113|year=1994|last1=Tallmon|first1=J. M.}}
* Taylor, Richard (1984). Good and Evil - A New Direction: A Foreceful Attack on the Rationalist Tradition in Ethics (Buffalo).
* {{cite journal|doi=10.1007/BF00994019|pmid=7997974|title=Clinical ethics as medical hermeneutics|journal=Theoretical Medicine|volume=15|issue=2|pages=93–111|year=1994|last1=Thomasma|first1=David C.}}
* {{cite journal|doi=10.1007/BF00999216|pmid=8059432|title=Casuistry in medical ethics: Rehabilitated, or repeat offender?|journal=Theoretical Medicine|volume=15|issue=1|pages=5–20|year=1994|last1=Tomlinson|first1=Tom}}
* {{cite journal|doi=10.1353/pbm.1982.0064|pmid=11643854|title=How Medicine Saved the Life of Ethics|journal=Perspectives in Biology and Medicine|volume=25|issue=4|pages=736–750|year=1982|last1=Toulmin|first1=Stephen}}
* Toulmin, Stephen (1988). &quot;The Recovery of Practical Philosophy.&quot; The American Scholar, Vol. 57, pp. 337-352.
* {{cite journal|doi=10.2307/3560542|jstor=3560542|title=The Tyranny of Principles|journal=The Hastings Center Report|volume=11|issue=6|pages=31–39|year=1981|last1=Toulmin|first1=Stephen}}
* {{cite journal|doi=10.1007/BF00138918|title=The issue of generality in ethics|journal=The Journal of Value Inquiry|volume=26|issue=4|pages=511–524|year=1992|last1=Van Der Steen|first1=Wim J.|last2=Musschenga|first2=Bert}}
* {{cite journal|doi=10.1007/BF02382593|title=Courage, relativism and practical reasoning|journal=Philosophia|volume=20|issue=1–2|pages=227–240|year=1990|last1=Walton|first1=Douglas N.}}
* {{cite journal|doi=10.2307/2870893|jstor=2870893|title=Measure for Measure: Casuistry and Artistry|journal=Shakespeare Quarterly|volume=43|issue=2|pages=242|year=1992|last1=Watson|first1=Robert N.|last2=Seiden|first2=Melvin}}
* Weinstein, Bruce David (1989). The Possibility of Ethical Expertise (Diss. Georgetown U).
* {{cite journal|doi=10.5840/monist198467440|title=Drawing Lines|journal=Monist|volume=67|issue=4|pages=589–604|year=1984|last1=Weston|first1=Anthony}}
* {{cite journal|doi=10.1093/jmp/18.1.33|pmid=8433047|title=The Priesthood of Bioethics and the Return of Casuistry|journal=Journal of Medicine and Philosophy|volume=18|issue=1|pages=33–49|year=1993|last1=Wildes|first1=K. Wm.}}
* Wildes, Kevin Wm., S.J. (1993). The View for Somewhere: Moral Judgment in Bioethics (Diss. Rice U).
* {{cite journal|doi=10.5840/teachphil199013220|title=Ethics Committee Simulations|journal=Teaching Philosophy|volume=13|issue=2|pages=127–140|year=1990|last1=Winston|first1=Morton E.}}
* Zacker, David J. (1991). Reflection and Particulars: Does Casuistry Offer Us Stable Beliefs About Ethics? (M.A. Thesis, Western Michigan U).
* {{cite journal|doi=10.1093/jmp/18.1.9|pmid=8433050|title=Voices and Time: The Venture of Clinical Ethics|journal=Journal of Medicine and Philosophy|volume=18|issue=1|pages=9–31|year=1993|last1=Zaner|first1=R. M.}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{wikiquote}}
{{EB1911 poster|Casuistry}}
{{CE1913 poster|Casuistry}}
{{wiktionary}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20060618095059/http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/cgi-local/DHI/dhi.cgi?id=dv1-35 ''Dictionary of the History of Ideas'']: &quot;Casuistry&quot;
* [http://www.maths.unsw.edu.au/~jim/accountancy.html Accountancy as computational casuistics], article on how modern compliance regimes in accountancy and law apply casuistry
* [http://www.thegreatideas.org/apd-casu.html Mortimer Adler's Great Ideas – Casuistry]
* [http://www.jeramyt.org/papers/casuistry.html Summary of casuistry by Jeramy Townsley]
* [http://caae.phil.cmu.edu/Cavalier/80130/part2/casuistry/Casuistry.html Casuistry – Online Guide to Ethics and Moral Philosophy]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20160411043635/http://www.she-philosopher.com/library/tallmon.html Casuistry – Oxford Encyclopedia of Rhetoric] catalogued at she-philosopher.com

{{Ethics}}

[[Category:Catholic casuists| ]]
[[Category:Scholasticism]]
[[Category:Applied ethics]]
[[Category:Common law]]
[[Category:Legal reasoning]]</text>
      <sha1>rdeegwhl4xw3e8mcu6qcoqymh77enxp</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
