  <page>
    <title>Compost</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5966</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943098261</id>
      <parentid>938047000</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-28T20:34:49Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Wikijen026</username>
        <id>38516938</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Improved readability, added formatting, added citation</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|organic matter that has been decomposed}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}
[[File:Compost site germany.JPG|thumb|upright=1.3|Community-level composting in a rural area in Germany]][[File:ComposterRollingDesign.jpg|thumb|Backyard composter]]

'''Compost''' ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|k|ɒ|m|p|ɒ|s|t}} or {{IPAc-en|ˈ|k|ɒ|m|p|oʊ|s|t}}) is [[organic matter]] that has been [[Biodegradation|decomposed]] in a process called composting. This process [[Recycling|recycles]] various [[Organic matter|organic materials]] otherwise regarded as waste products and produces a [[soil conditioner]] (the ''compost'').

Compost is rich in nutrients. It is used, for example, in [[garden]]s, [[landscaping]], [[horticulture]], [[urban agriculture]] and [[organic farming]]. The compost itself is beneficial for the land in many ways, including as a soil conditioner, a [[fertilizer]], addition of vital [[humus]] or [[humic acids]], and as a natural [[pesticide]] for soil. In [[ecosystems]], compost is useful for erosion control, land and stream reclamation, wetland construction, and as landfill cover (see [[compost uses]]).

At the simplest level, the process of composting requires making a heap of wet organic matter (also called [[green waste]]), such as leaves, grass, and food scraps, and waiting for the materials to break down into [[humus]] after a period of months. However, composting can also take place as a multi-step, closely monitored process with measured inputs of water, air, and carbon- and nitrogen-rich materials. The [[decomposition]] process is aided by shredding the plant matter, adding water and ensuring proper aeration by regularly turning the mixture when open piles or &quot;windrows&quot; are used. [[Fungus|Fungi]], [[earthworm]]s and other [[detritivore]]s further break up the material. Bacteria requiring oxygen to function ([[aerobic bacteria]]) and fungi manage the chemical process by converting the inputs into heat, [[carbon dioxide]], and [[ammonium]].
{{TOC limit|3}}

==Fundamentals==
[[File:Composting in the Escuela Barreales.jpg|thumb|Home compost barrel]]
[[File:Compost pile.JPG|thumb|Materials in a compost pile]]
[[File:Food-scraps-compost.jpg|thumb|Food scraps compost heap]]

Composting is an ''aerobic method'' (meaning that it requires the presence of air) of decomposing organic solid wastes.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/?id=3BhSAAAAMAAJ&amp;q=Human+waste+can+also+be+added+as+an+input+to+the+composting+process+since+human+waste+is+a+nitrogen-rich+organic+material&amp;dq=Human+waste+can+also+be+added+as+an+input+to+the+composting+process+since+human+waste+is+a+nitrogen-rich+organic+material|title=Introduction to Environmental Engineering and Science|last=Masters|first=Gilbert M.|date=1997|publisher=Prentice Hall|isbn=9780131553842|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; It can therefore be used to recycle organic material. The process involves decomposition of organic material into a [[humus]]-like material, known as compost, which is a good [[fertilizer]] for plants. Composting requires the following three components: human management, aerobic conditions, and development of internal biological heat.

Composting organisms require four equally important ingredients to work effectively:
*'''Carbon —''' for energy; the microbial [[oxidation]] of carbon produces the heat, if included at suggested levels.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://web.extension.illinois.edu/homecompost/science.html |title=Composting for the Homeowner - University of Illinois Extension |publisher=Web.extension.illinois.edu |date= |accessdate=2013-07-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; High carbon materials tend to be brown and dry.
*'''Nitrogen —''' to grow and reproduce more organisms to oxidize the carbon. High nitrogen materials tend to be green (or colorful, such as fruits and vegetables) and wet.
*'''Oxygen —''' for oxidizing the carbon, the decomposition process.
*'''Water —''' in the right amounts to maintain activity without causing anaerobic conditions.&lt;ref name=&quot;uiuc-mat&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://web.extension.uiuc.edu/homecompost/materials.html|title=Composting for the Homeowner -Materials for Composting|work=uiuc.edu|access-date=13 April 2010|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20091225014318/http://web.extension.uiuc.edu/homecompost/materials.html|archive-date=25 December 2009|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Certain ratios of these materials will provide microorganisms to work at a rate that will heat up the pile. Active management of the pile (e.g. turning) is needed to maintain sufficient supply of oxygen and the right moisture level. The air/water balance is critical to maintaining high temperatures {{convert|130–160|F}} until the materials are broken down.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Lal|first=Rattan|date=2003-11-30|title=Composting|url=http://link.galegroup.com/apps/doc/CX3408100055/GVRL?sid=GVRL&amp;xid=54515a57|journal=Pollution a to Z|language=English|volume=1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The most efficient composting occurs with an optimal carbon:nitrogen ratio of about 25:1.&lt;ref name=&quot;tilley2&quot;&gt;{{cite book|url=http://www.eawag.ch/en/department/sandec/publications/compendium/|title=Compendium of Sanitation Systems and Technologies|last1=Tilley|first1=Elizabeth|last2=Ulrich|first2=Lukas|last3=Lüthi|first3=Christoph|last4=Reymond|first4=Philippe|last5=Zurbrügg|first5=Chris|publisher=Swiss Federal Institute of Aquatic Science and Technology (Eawag)|year=2014|isbn=978-3-906484-57-0|edition=2nd|location=Duebendorf, Switzerland|pages=|chapter=Septic tanks|chapter-url=http://ecompendium.sswm.info/sanitation-technologies/septic-tank?group_code=s}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Hot container composting]] focuses on retaining the heat to increase decomposition rate and produce compost more quickly. Rapid composting is favored by having a C/N ratio of ~30 or less. Above 30 the substrate is nitrogen starved, below 15 it is likely to outgas a portion of nitrogen as ammonia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Haug|first1=Roger|title=The Practical Handbook of Compost Engineering|url=https://books.google.com/?id=MX_jbemODmAC&amp;pg=PA249&amp;lpg=PA249&amp;dq=ammonium+phosphate+compost#v=onepage&amp;q=ammonium%20phosphate%20compost&amp;f=false|publisher=CRC Press|accessdate=26 October 2015|isbn=9780873713733|date=1993-07-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Nearly all plant and animal materials have both carbon and nitrogen, but amounts vary widely, with characteristics noted above (dry/wet, brown/green).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.klickitatcounty.org/SolidWaste/fileshtml/organics/compostCalc.htm Klickitat County WA, USA Compost Mix Calculator] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20111117112037/http://www.klickitatcounty.org/solidwaste/fileshtml/organics/compostCalc.htm |date=17 November 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Fresh grass clippings have an average ratio of about 15:1 and dry autumn leaves about 50:1 depending on species. Mixing equal parts by volume approximates the ideal C:N range. Few individual situations will provide the ideal mix of materials at any point. Observation of amounts, and consideration of different materials as a pile is built over time, can quickly achieve a workable technique for the individual situation.

===Microorganisms===
With the proper mixture of water, oxygen, carbon, and nitrogen, micro-organisms are able to break down organic matter to produce compost.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://aggie-horticulture.tamu.edu/earthkind/landscape/dont-bag-it/chapter-1-the-decomposition-process/|title=Chapter 1, The Decomposition Process|publisher=aggie-horticulture.tamu.edu|accessdate=11 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.asthegardenturns.com/composting/how-to-make-compost-at-home/|title=How to Make Compost at Home|publisher=asthegardenturns.com|accessdate=11 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The composting process is dependent on micro-organisms to break down organic matter into compost. There are many types of microorganisms found in active compost of which the most common are:&lt;ref name=&quot;cornell&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://compost.css.cornell.edu/microorg.html|title=Composting - Compost Microorganisms|work=[[Cornell University]]|accessdate=6 October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Bacteria]]- The most numerous of all the [[microorganism]]s found in compost.  Depending on the phase of composting, [[mesophile|mesophilic]] or [[thermophile|thermophilic]] bacteria may predominate.
* [[Actinobacteria]]- Necessary for breaking down paper products such as newspaper, [[Bark (botany)|bark]], etc.
* [[Fungi]]- [[Mold|molds]] and [[yeast]] help break down materials that bacteria cannot, especially [[lignin]] in woody material.
* [[Protozoa]]- Help consume bacteria, fungi and micro organic particulates.
* [[Rotifers]]- Rotifers help control populations of bacteria and small protozoans.

In addition, [[earthworm]]s not only ingest partly composted material, but also continually re-create aeration and drainage tunnels as they move through the compost.

===Phases of composting===
[[File:Komposztáló.JPG|thumb|Three years old household compost]]
Under ideal conditions, composting proceeds through three major phases:&lt;ref name=&quot;cornell&quot; /&gt;
*'''Mesophilic phase:''' An initial, mesophilic phase, in which the decomposition is carried out under moderate temperatures by mesophilic microorganisms.
*'''Thermophilic phase:''' As the temperature rises, a second, thermophilic phase starts, in which the decomposition is carried out by various thermophilic bacteria under high temperatures.
*'''Maturation phase:''' As the supply of high-energy compounds dwindles, the temperature starts to decrease, and the mesophiles once again predominate in the maturation phase.

===Slow and rapid composting===
{{More citations needed section|date=April 2017}}
There are many proponents of rapid composting that attempt to correct some of the perceived problems associated with traditional, slow composting. Many advocate that compost can be made in 2 to 3 weeks.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://vric.ucdavis.edu/pdf/compost_rapidcompost.pdf|title=The Rapid Compost Method by Robert Raabe, Professor of Plant Pathology, Berkeley|publisher=|accessdate=21 December 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many such short processes involve a few changes to traditional methods, including smaller, more homogenized pieces in the compost, controlling carbon-to-nitrogen ratio (C:N) at 30 to 1 or less, and monitoring the moisture level more carefully. However, none of these parameters differ significantly from the early writings of compost researchers, suggesting that, in fact, modern composting has not made significant advances over the traditional methods that take a few months to work. For this reason and others, many scientists who deal with carbon transformations are skeptical that there is a &quot;super-charged&quot; way to get nature to make compost rapidly. {{citation needed|reason=Very old reference, find a better one|date=May 2015}}

Both sides may be right to some extent. The bacterial activity in rapid high heat methods breaks down the material to the extent that pathogens and seeds are destroyed, and the original feedstock is unrecognizable. At this stage, the compost can be used to prepare fields or other planting areas.  However, most professionals recommend that the compost be given time to cure before using in a nursery for starting seeds or growing young plants. The curing time allows fungi to continue the decomposition process and eliminating [[phytotoxic]] substances.{{citation needed|date=March 2012}}

An alternative approach is anaerobic fermentation, known as [[#Bokashi|bokashi]]. It retains carbon bonds, is faster than decomposition, and for application to soil requires only rapid but thorough aeration rather than curing. It depends on sufficient carbohydrates in the treated material.

===Pathogen removal===
{{More citations needed section|date=April 2017}}
Composting can destroy [[pathogen]]s or unwanted [[seed]]s. Unwanted living plants (or [[weed]]s) can be discouraged by [[Mulch#Mulching (composting) over unwanted plants|covering with mulch/compost]]. The &quot;[[biopesticide|microbial pesticides]]&quot; in compost may include [[thermophile]]s and [[mesophile]]s.

Thermophilic (high-temperature) composting is well known to destroy many seeds and nearly all types of pathogens (exceptions may include [[prion]]s). The [[Disinfection|sanitizing]] qualities of ([[thermophilic]]) composting are desirable where there is a high likelihood of pathogens, such as with [[manure]].

== Materials that can be composted ==
Composting is a process used for [[resource recovery]]. It can [[recycle]] an unwanted by-product from another process (a [[waste]]) into a useful new product.

=== Organic solid waste (green waste) ===
[[File:Spontaneous combustion of compost pile.jpg|thumb|A large compost pile that is steaming with the heat generated by [[thermophile|thermophilic]] microorganisms.]]

Composting is a process for converting decomposable organic materials into useful stable products. Therefore, valuable [[landfill]] space can be used for other wastes by composting these materials rather than dumping them on landfills. It may however be difficult to control inert and plastics contamination from [[municipal solid waste]].

Co-composting is a technique that processes organic solid waste together with other input materials such as dewatered [[fecal sludge]] or [[sewage sludge]].&lt;ref name=&quot;tilley2&quot; /&gt;

Industrial composting systems are being installed to treat organic solid waste and recycle it rather than landfilling it. It is one example of an [[advanced waste processing systems|advanced waste processing system]]. Mechanical sorting of mixed waste streams combined with [[Anaerobic respiration|anaerobic]] digestion or in-vessel composting is called [[mechanical biological treatment]]. It is increasingly being used in developed countries due to regulations controlling the amount of organic matter allowed in landfills. Treating [[biodegradable waste]] before it enters a landfill reduces [[global warming]] from fugitive [[methane]]; untreated waste breaks down anaerobically in a landfill, producing [[landfill gas]] that contains [[atmospheric methane|methane]], a potent [[greenhouse gas]].

===Animal manure and bedding===
On many farms, the basic composting ingredients are animal [[manure]] generated on the farm and bedding. Straw and sawdust are common bedding materials. Non-traditional bedding materials are also used, including newspaper and chopped cardboard. The amount of manure composted on a livestock farm is often determined by cleaning schedules, land availability, and weather conditions. Each type of manure has its own physical, chemical, and biological characteristics. Cattle and horse manures, when mixed with bedding, possess good qualities for composting. Swine manure, which is very wet and usually not mixed with bedding material, must be mixed with straw or similar raw materials. Poultry manure also must be blended with carbonaceous materials - those low in nitrogen preferred, such as sawdust or straw.&lt;ref&gt;Dougherty, Mark. (1999). Field Guide to On-Farm Composting. Ithaca, New York: Natural Resource, Agriculture, and Engineering Service.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Human waste and sewage sludge ===
{{Further|Reuse of human waste}}
[[Human waste]] can  be added as an input to the composting process since human excreta is a nitrogen-rich organic material. It can be either composted directly, as in [[composting toilets]], or indirectly (as [[sewage sludge]]), after it has undergone treatment in a [[Sewage treatment|sewage treatment plant]].  Feces contain a wide range of microorganisms including bacteria, viruses and parasitic worms and its use in home composting can pose significant health risks.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Domestic waste composting facilities: a review of human health risks.|journal = Environment International|volume = 35|issue = 2|pages = 382–9|date = August 2012|pmid = 18701167|last1 = Domingo|first1 = J. L.|last2 = Nadal|first2 = M.|doi = 10.1016/j.envint.2008.07.004}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Urine]] can be put on compost piles or directly used as fertilizer.&lt;ref&gt;[http://esa.un.org/iys/docs/san_lib_docs/ESR2web%5B1%5D.pdf Stockholm Environment Institute - EcoSanRes - Guidelines on the Use of Urine and Feces in Crop Production]&lt;/ref&gt; Adding urine to compost can increase temperatures and therefore increase its ability to destroy pathogens and unwanted seeds. Unlike feces, urine does not attract disease-spreading flies (such as [[Housefly|houseflies]] or [[Calliphoridae|blowflies]]), and it does not contain the most hardy of pathogens, such as [[parasitic worm]] eggs. Urine usually does not smell for long, particularly when it is fresh, diluted, or put on [[sorbent]]s. &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.davidwolfe.com/8-reasons-use-urine-garden/|title=This Natural Fertilizer Deters Pests, Kills Weeds &amp; Makes Your Garden Grow Like Crazy!|last=DavidWolfe.com|date=2017-02-14|website=David Avocado Wolfe|language=en-US|access-date=2019-11-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Uses==
{{Main|Uses of compost}}
Compost can be used as an additive to soil, or other matrices such as [[coir]] and [[peat]], as a [[tilth]] improver, supplying humus and nutrients. It provides a rich ''growing medium'', or a porous, absorbent material that holds moisture and soluble minerals, providing the support and [[nutrient]]s in which plants can flourish, although it is rarely used alone, being primarily mixed with [[soil]], [[sand]], grit, bark chips, [[vermiculite]], [[perlite]], or [[clay]] granules to produce [[loam]]. Compost can be tilled directly into the soil or growing medium to boost the level of organic matter and the overall fertility of the soil. Compost that is ready to be used as an additive is dark brown or even black with an earthy smell.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.epa.gov/wastes/conserve/rrr/greenscapes/pubs/asla-soil.pdf|title=Reduce, Reuse, Recycle - US EPA|first=US|last=EPA,OSWER,ORCR|website=US EPA|accessdate=21 December 2017|date=2013-04-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Generally, direct seeding into a compost is not recommended due to the speed with which it may dry and the possible presence of [[phytotoxin]]s in immature compost that may inhibit germination,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Morel | first1 = P. | last2 = Guillemain | first2 = G. | year = 2004 | title = Assessment of the possible phytotoxicity of a substrate using an easy and representative biotest | url = | journal = Acta Horticulturae | volume = | issue = 644| pages = 417–423 | doi = 10.17660/ActaHortic.2004.644.55 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Itävaara et al. Compost maturity - problems associated with testing. in Proceedings of Composting. Innsbruck Austria 18-21.10.2000&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Development of models for predicting carbon mineralization and associated phytotoxicity in compost-amended soil. |vauthors=Aslam DN, etal | pmid=18585031 | doi=10.1016/j.biortech.2008.04.074 |volume=99 |issue=18 |journal=Bioresour Technol |pages=8735–8741|year=2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and the possible tie up of nitrogen by incompletely decomposed lignin.&lt;ref name=&quot;compost.css.cornell.edu&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://compost.css.cornell.edu/calc/lignin.html|title=The Effect of Lignin on Biodegradability - Cornell Composting|work=cornell.edu}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is very common to see blends of 20–30% compost used for transplanting [[seedlings]] at [[cotyledon]] stage or later.

Compost can be used to increase plant immunity to diseases and pests.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Bahramisharif|first=Amirhossein|last2=Rose|first2=Laura E.|title=Efficacy of biological agents and compost on growth and resistance of tomatoes to late blight|journal=Planta|volume=249|issue=3|pages=799–813|doi=10.1007/s00425-018-3035-2|issn=1432-2048|pmid=30406411|year=2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Composting technologies==
Various approaches have been developed to handle different ingredients, locations, throughput and applications for the composted product.

=== Industrial-scale  ===
Industrial-scale composting can be carried out in the form of [[in-vessel composting]], [[aerated static pile composting]], [[vermicomposting]], or [[windrow composting]].{{Citation needed|date=December 2017}}

=== {{anchor|Vermicompost}}Vermicomposting ===
[[File:Worm.bin.jpg|right|thumb|Worms in a bin being harvested]]
{{Main|Vermicompost}}
[[Vermicompost]] is the product or process of organic material degradation using various species of worms, usually [[Eisenia fetida|red wigglers]], [[Enchytraeus buchholzi|white worms]], and [[earthworm]]s, to create a heterogeneous mixture of decomposing vegetable or food waste (excluding meat, dairy, fats, or oils), bedding materials, and vermicast. Vermicast, also known as [[worm castings]], worm humus or worm manure, is the end-product of the breakdown of organic matter by [[species]] of earthworm.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://southwoodsforestgardens.blogspot.com/2009/01/paper-on-invasive-european-worms.html |title=Paper on Invasive European Worms |accessdate=22 February 2009|date=2009-01-21 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Vermicomposting can also be applied for  [[Sewage sludge treatment|treatment of sewage sludge]].{{Citation needed|date=December 2019|reason=removed citation to predatory publisher content}}

=== Composting toilets{{anchor|Humanure}} ===
{{Main|Composting toilet}}
[[File:TerraNova Sitzdichtung (6211343544).jpg|thumb|upright|[[Composting toilet]] with a seal in the lid in Germany]]

A [[composting toilet]] collects human excreta. These are added to a compost heap that can be located in a chamber below the toilet seat. [[Sawdust]] and straw or other carbon rich materials are usually added as well. Some [[compost toilet|composting toilet]]s do not require water or electricity; others may. If they do not use water for flushing they fall into the category of [[dry toilets]]. Some composting toilet designs use [[urine diversion]], others do not. When properly managed, they do not smell. The composting process in these toilets destroys pathogens to some extent. The amount of pathogen destruction depends on the temperature (mesophilic or thermophilic conditions) and composting time.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot;&gt;Stenström, T.A., Seidu, R., Ekane, N., Zurbrügg, C. (2011). [http://www.susana.org/en/resources/library/details/1236 Microbial exposure and health assessments in sanitation technologies and systems] - EcoSanRes Series, 2011-1. Stockholm Environment Institute (SEI), Stockholm, Sweden, page 88&lt;/ref&gt;

Composting toilets with a large composting container (of the type [[Clivus Multrum]] and derivations of it) are popular in United States, Canada, Australia, New Zealand and Sweden. They are available as commercial products, as designs for self builders or as &quot;design derivatives&quot; which are marketed under various names.

=== Black soldier fly larvae ===
{{Main|Hermetia illucens#Uses in composting or as food for animals}}
[[Hermetia illucens|Black soldier fly]] (''Hermetia illucens'') larvae are able to rapidly consume large amounts of organic material when kept at around 30&amp;nbsp;°C.&lt;ref name=&quot;DienerStudt Solano2011&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Diener|first1=Stefan|last2=Studt Solano|first2=Nandayure M.|last3=Roa Gutiérrez|first3=Floria|last4=Zurbrügg|first4=Christian|last5=Tockner|first5=Klement|year=2011|title=Biological Treatment of Municipal Organic Waste using Black Soldier Fly Larvae|journal=Waste and Biomass Valorization|volume=2|issue=4|pages=357–363|doi=10.1007/s12649-011-9079-1|issn=1877-2641}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Booth|first=Donald C.|last2=Sheppard|first2=Craig|date=1984-04-01|title=Oviposition of the Black Soldier Fly, ''Hermetia illucens'' (Diptera: Stratiomyidae): Eggs, Masses, Timing, and Site Characteristics|journal=Environmental Entomology|language=en|volume=13|issue=2|pages=421–423|doi=10.1093/ee/13.2.421|issn=0046-225X}}&lt;/ref&gt; Black soldier fly larvae can reduce the dry matter of the organic waste by 73%  and convert 16–22% of the dry matter in the waste to biomass.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Lalander|first=Cecilia|last2=Diener|first2=Stefan|last3=Magri|first3=Maria Elisa|last4=Zurbrügg|first4=Christian|last5=Lindström|first5=Anders|last6=Vinnerås|first6=Björn|title=Faecal sludge management with the larvae of the black soldier fly (''Hermetia illucens'') — From a hygiene aspect |journal=Science of the Total Environment|volume=458–460|pages=312–318|doi=10.1016/j.scitotenv.2013.04.033|pmid=23669577|year=2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Banks|first=Ian J.|last2=Gibson|first2=Walter T.|last3=Cameron|first3=Mary M.|authorlink3=Mary Cameron (entomologist)|date=2014-01-01|title=Growth rates of black soldier fly larvae fed on fresh human faeces and their implication for improving sanitation|journal=Tropical Medicine &amp; International Health|language=en|volume=19|issue=1|pages=14–22|doi=10.1111/tmi.12228|pmid=24261901|issn=1365-3156}}&lt;/ref&gt; The resulting compost still contains nutrients and can be used for [[biogas]] production, or further traditional composting or [[vermicompost]]ing &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Lalander|first=Cecilia|last2=Nordberg|first2=Åke|last3=Vinnerås|first3=Björn|title=A comparison in product-value potential in four treatment strategies for food waste and faeces – assessing composting, fly larvae composting and anaerobic digestion|journal=GCB Bioenergy|volume=10|issue=2|language=en|pages=84–91|doi=10.1111/gcbb.12470|issn=1757-1707|year=2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; The larvae are rich in fat and protein, and can be used as, for example, animal feed or [[biodiesel]] production.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Li|first=Qing|last2=Zheng|first2=Longyu|last3=Cai|first3=Hao|last4=Garza|first4=E.|last5=Yu|first5=Ziniu|last6=Zhou|first6=Shengde|title=From organic waste to biodiesel: Black soldier fly, ''Hermetia illucens'', makes it feasible|journal=Fuel|volume=90|issue=4|pages=1545–1548|doi=10.1016/j.fuel.2010.11.016|year=2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Enthusiasts have experimented with a large number of different waste products.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=E|url=http://www.esrint.com/pages/bioconversion.html|website=Bio-Conversion of Putrescent Waste|publisher=ESR International|accessdate=17 April 2015|url-status=dead|archiveurl=http://arquivo.pt/wayback/20160516163727/http%3A//www.esrint.com/pages/bioconversion.html|archivedate=16 May 2016|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== {{anchor|Bokashi}}Bokashi ===
{{Main|Bokashi (horticulture)}}

Bokashi is not composting as defined earlier, rather an alternative technology. It [[Homolactic fermentation|ferments]] (rather than decomposes) the input organic matter and feeds the result to the [[soil food web]] (rather than producing a soil conditioner). The process involves adding [[Lactobacillus|''Lactobacilli'']] to the input in an airtight container kept at normal room temperature. These bacteria ferment [[carbohydrate]]s to [[lactic acid]], which preserves the input. After this is complete the preserve is mixed into soil, converting the lactic acid to [[pyruvate]], which enables soil life to consume the result.

Bokashi is typically applied to [[food waste]] from households, workplaces and catering establishments, because such waste normally holds a good proportion of carbohydrates; it is also applied to other organic waste by supplementing carbohydrates. Household containers (&quot;bokashi bins&quot;) typically give a batch size of {{convert|5–10|kg}}, accumulated over a few weeks. In horticultural settings batches can be orders of magnitude greater.[[File:Bokashi bin - inside.JPG|thumb|Inside a recently started bokashi bin. Food scraps are raised on a perforated plate (to drain runoff) and are partly covered by a layer of bran inoculated with ''Lactobacilli'']]

Bokashi offers several advantages:
* Fermentation retains all the original carbon and energy. (In comparison, composting loses at least 50% of these and 75% or more in amateur use; composting also loses nitrogen, a [[Plant nutrition|macronutrient]] of plants, by emitting ammonia and the potent greenhouse gas nitrous oxide.)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Practical Handbook of Compost Engineering|last=Haug|first=Roger Tim|publisher=Lewis Publishers|year=1993|isbn=0-87371-373-7|location=|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Virtually the full range of food waste is accepted, without the exclusions of composting. The exception is large bones.
* Being airtight, the container inherently traps smells, and when opened the smell of fermentation is far less offensive than decomposition. Hence bokashi bins usually operate indoors, in or near kitchens.
* Similarly the container neither attracts insect pests nor allows them ingress.
* The process is inherently hygienic because lactic acid is a natural [[bactericide]] and anti-[[pathogen]]; even its own fermentation is self-limiting.
* Both preservation and consumption complete within a few weeks rather than months.
* The preserve can be stored until needed, for example if ground is frozen or waterlogged.
* The increased activity of the soil food web improves the soil texture, especially by worm action - in effect this is in-soil [[vermicomposting]].

The importance of the first advantage should not be underestimated: the mass of any [[ecosystem]] depends on the energy it captures. Plants depend upon the soil ecosystem making nutrients available within [[Soil#Water|soil water]]. Therefore, the richer the ecosystem, the richer the plants. (Plants can also take up nutrients from added chemicals, but these are at odds with the purpose of composting).

=== Other systems at household level===
==== {{anchor|Hügelkultur}}Hügelkultur (raised garden beds or mounds) ====
[[File:End point (4315712587).jpg|thumb|upright|An almost completed Hügelkultur bed; the bed does not have soil on it yet.]]
{{Main|Hügelkultur}}
The practice of making raised garden beds or mounds filled with rotting wood is also called ''hügelkultur'' in German.&lt;ref name=&quot;richsoil.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.richsoil.com/hugelkultur/ |title=hugelkultur: the ultimate raised garden beds |publisher=Richsoil.com |date=2007-07-27 |accessdate=2013-07-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;permaculture.org.au&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://permaculture.org.au/2010/08/03/the-art-and-science-of-making-a-hugelkultur-bed-transforming-woody-debris-into-a-garden-resource/ |title=The Art and Science of Making a Hugelkultur Bed - Transforming Woody Debris into a Garden Resource Permaculture Research Institute - Permaculture Forums, Courses, Information &amp; News |date= 2010-08-03|accessdate=2013-07-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is in effect creating a [[nurse log]] that is covered with soil.

Benefits of ''hügelkultur'' garden beds include water retention and warming of soil.&lt;ref name=&quot;richsoil.com&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://permaculture.org.au/2012/01/04/hugelkultur-composting-whole-trees-with-ease/#more-6825 |title=Hugelkultur: Composting Whole Trees With Ease Permaculture Research Institute - Permaculture Forums, Courses, Information &amp; News |date= 2012-01-04|accessdate=2013-07-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; Buried wood acts like a [[sponge (material)|sponge]] as it decomposes, able to capture water and store it for later use by crops planted on top of the ''hügelkultur'' bed.&lt;ref name=&quot;richsoil.com&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hemenway, Toby (2009). Gaia's Garden: A Guide to Home-Scale Permaculture. Chelsea Green Publishing. pp. 84–85. {{ISBN|978-1-60358-029-8}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

==== {{anchor|Compost tea}}Compost tea ====
Compost teas are defined as water extracts leached from composted materials.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sinha&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Gómez-Brandón, M|last2=Vela, M|last3=Martinez Toledo, MV|last4=Insam, H|last5=Domínguez, J|editor1-last=Sinha, S|editor2-last=Plant, KK|editor3-last=Bajpai, S|title=Advances in Fertilizer Technology: Synthesis (Vol1)| chapter=12: Effects of Compost and Vermiculture Teas as Organic Fertilizers|date=2015|publisher=Stadium Press LLC|isbn=978-1-62699-044-9|pages=300–318}}&lt;/ref&gt; Compost teas are generally produced from adding one volume of compost to 4–10 volumes of water, but there has also been debate about the benefits of aerating the mixture.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sinha&quot; /&gt; Field studies have shown the benefits of adding compost teas to crops due to the adding of organic matter, increased nutrient availability and increased microbial activity.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sinha&quot; /&gt; They have also been shown to have an effect on plant pathogens.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last=Santos, M| last2= Dianez, F| last3=Carretero, F| chapter=12: Suppressive Effects of Compost Tea on Phytopathogens| pages= 242–262| editor-last = Dubey, NK | title = Natural products in plant pest management | publisher = CABI | location = Oxfordshire, UK Cambridge, MA | year = 2011 | isbn = 9781845936716 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Worm Hotels ====
[[File:Worm Hotel.jpg|thumb|Worm Hotel in Amsterdam]]
Worm Hotels accommodate useful worm in ideal conditions.

=== Related technologies ===
Organic ingredients intended for composting can also be used to generate [[biogas]] through [[anaerobic digestion]]. This process stabilizes organic material. The residual material, sometimes in combination with [[sewage sludge]] can be treated by a composting process before selling or giving away the compost.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.politico.com/news/magazine/2019/11/21/food-waste-fuel-energy-sustainability-070265|title=How Cities Are Turning Food Into Fuel|last=Dawson|first=Lj|website=POLITICO|language=en|access-date=2020-02-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Regulations ==
{{Further|Uses of compost#Regulation and voluntary standards}}
There are process and product guidelines in Europe that date to the early 1980s (Germany, the Netherlands, Switzerland) and only more recently in the UK and the US. In both these countries, private trade associations within the industry have established loose standards, some say as a stop-gap measure to discourage independent government agencies from establishing tougher consumer-friendly standards.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.compostingcouncil.org/|title=US Composting Council|date=|publisher=Compostingcouncil.org|accessdate=2013-07-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The USA is the only Western country that does not distinguish sludge-source compost from green-composts, and by default in the USA 50% of states expect composts to comply in some manner with the federal EPA 503 rule promulgated in 1984 for sludge products.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ecfr.gov/cgi-bin/text-idx?c=ecfr&amp;SID=ef0e4bc903a2845519f1d9129ad7eef7&amp;rgn=div5&amp;view=text&amp;node=40:31.0.1.2.42&amp;idno=40|title=Electronic Code of Federal Regulations. Title 40, part 503. Standards for the use or disposal of sewage sludge|year=1998|work=U.S. Government Printing Office|accessdate=30 March 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Compost is regulated in Canada&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ccme.ca/files/Resources/waste/compost_quality/compostgdlns_1340_e.pdf|title=Canadian Council of Ministers of the Environment - Guidelines for Compost Quality|date=2005|publisher=CCME Documents|accessdate=2017-09-04|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20151018085550/http://www.ccme.ca/files/Resources/waste/compost_quality/compostgdlns_1340_e.pdf|archive-date=18 October 2015|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Australia&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.biocycle.net/2011/01/25/organics-recycling-in-australia/|title=Organics Recycling In Australia|date=2011|publisher=BioCycle|accessdate=2017-09-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well.

Many countries such as [[Wales]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gwynedd.gov.uk/gwy_doc.asp?doc=25454&amp;language=1&amp;p=1&amp;c=1|title=Gwynedd Council food recycling|accessdate=21 December 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140501141531/http://www.gwynedd.gov.uk/gwy_doc.asp?doc=25454&amp;language=1&amp;p=1&amp;c=1|archive-date=1 May 2014|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.edie.net/news/5/Anglesey-households-achieve-100-food-waste-recycling/19101/|title=Anglesey households achieve 100% food waste recycling|work=edie.net}}&lt;/ref&gt; and some individual cities such as Seattle and [[San Francisco Mandatory Recycling and Composting Ordinance|San Francisco]] require food and yard waste to be sorted for composting ([[San Francisco Mandatory Recycling and Composting Ordinance]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://sfenvironment.org/recycling-composting-faqs|title=Recycling &amp; Composting in San Francisco - Frequently Asked Questions|date=2016|publisher=San Francisco Dept. of the Environment|accessdate=4 September 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.boston.com/bostonglobe/magazine/articles/2010/03/21/the_case_for_mandatory_composting/|title=The case for mandatory composting|last=Tyler|first=Aubin|date=21 March 2010|work=[[The Boston Globe]]|accessdate=19 September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Examples ==
[[File:MRF_Composter03.jpg|thumb|Edmonton Composting Facility]]
Large-scale composting systems are used by many urban areas around the world.

* The world's largest municipal co-composter for [[municipal solid waste]] (MSW) is the [[Edmonton Composting Facility]] in [[Edmonton]], [[Alberta]], Canada, which turns 220,000 tonnes of municipal solid waste and 22,500 dry tonnes of [[sewage sludge]] per year into 80,000 tonnes of compost. The facility is {{convert|38690|m2|abbr=on}} in area, equivalent to 4½ [[Canadian football]] fields, and the operating structure is the largest [[stainless steel]] building in [[North America]].{{citation needed|date=April 2018}}
* In 2006, [[Qatar]] awarded Keppel Seghers Singapore, a subsidiary of [[Keppel Corporation]], a contract to begin construction on a 275,000 tonne/year [[anaerobic digestion]] and composting plant licensed by Kompogas Switzerland. This plant, with 15 independent anaerobic digesters, will be the world's largest composting facility once fully operational in early 2011 and forms part of Qatar's Domestic Solid Waste Management Centre, the largest integrated [[waste management]] complex in the [[Middle East]].{{citation needed|date=April 2018}}
* Another large municipal solid waste composter is the [[Lahore Composting Facility]] in [[Lahore]], Pakistan, which has a capacity to convert 1,000 tonnes of municipal solid waste per day into compost. It also has a capacity to convert substantial portion of the intake into [[refuse-derived fuel]] (RDF) materials for further combustion use in several energy consuming industries across Pakistan, for example in cement manufacturing companies where it is used to heat [[cement kiln]]s. This project has also been approved by the Executive Board of the [[United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change]] for reducing [[methane emissions]], and has been registered with a capacity of reducing 108,686 tonnes [[carbon dioxide equivalent]] per annum.&lt;ref&gt;Details on project design and its validation and monitoring reports are available at: [http://cdm.unfccc.int/Projects/DB/SGS-UKL1248265320.71/view Project 2778 : Composting of Organic Content of Municipal Solid Waste in Lahore]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Kew Gardens]] in London has one of the biggest non-commercial compost heaps in Europe.{{citation needed|reason=broken link|date=May 2015}}
*Compost is used as a soil amendment in [[organic farming]].
*Within an EU project conducted in Portugal and Spain, organic compost has been successfully used to revive degraded landscapes by improving the quality of soil.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.euronews.com/2020/01/20/degraded-land-begins-to-bloom-thanks-to-european-composting-project|title=Degraded land begins to bloom thanks to European composting project|last=Velez|first=Aurora|date=2020-01-20|website=euronews|language=en|access-date=2020-01-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
[[File:Compost Basket.jpg|thumb|upright|Compost Basket]]
Composting as a recognized practice dates to at least the early Roman Empire, and was mentioned as early as [[Cato the Elder]]'s 160 BCE piece ''[[De Agri Cultura]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|chapter-url=http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Cato/De_Agricultura/A*.html|title=De Agri Cultura|last=Cato|first=Marcus|publisher=|year=160 BCE|isbn=|location=|pages=|chapter=37.2; 39.1}}&lt;/ref&gt; Traditionally, composting involved piling organic materials until the next planting season, at which time the materials would have decayed enough to be ready for use in the soil. The advantage of this method is that little working time or effort is required from the composter and it fits in naturally with agricultural practices in temperate climates. Disadvantages (from the modern perspective) are that space is used for a whole year, some nutrients might be leached due to exposure to rainfall, and disease-producing organisms and insects may not be adequately controlled.

Composting was somewhat modernized beginning in the 1920s in Europe as a tool for [[organic farming]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://web.extension.illinois.edu/homecompost/history.cfm|title=History of Composting|publisher=illinois.edu|accessdate=11 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first industrial station for the transformation of urban organic materials into compost was set up in [[Wels]], Austria in the year 1921.&lt;ref&gt;Welser Anzeiger vom 05. Januar 1921, 67. Jahrgang, Nr. 2, S. 4&lt;/ref&gt; Early frequent citations for propounding composting within farming are for the German-speaking world [[Rudolf Steiner]], founder of a farming method called [[biodynamics]], and [[Annie Francé-Harrar]], who was appointed on behalf of the government in [[Mexico]] and supported the country 1950–1958 to set up a large humus organization in the fight against erosion and [[soil degradation]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/?id=gETbAwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA86&amp;lpg=PA86&amp;dq=Annie+Franc%C3%A9-Harrar+compost#v=onepage&amp;q=Annie%20Franc%C3%A9-Harrar%20compost&amp;f=false|title=A History of the Garden in Fifty Tools|last=Laws|first=Bill|date=2014-06-19|publisher=University of Chicago Press|isbn=9780226139937|location=|pages=86|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the English-speaking world it was [[Sir Albert Howard]] who worked extensively in [[India]] on sustainable practices and [[Lady Eve Balfour]] who was a huge proponent of composting. Composting was imported to America by various followers of these early European movements by the likes of [[Jerome Irving Rodale|J.I. Rodale]] (founder of Rodale Organic Gardening), E.E. Pfeiffer (who developed scientific practices in biodynamic farming), [[Paul K. Keene|Paul Keene]] (founder of Walnut Acres in Pennsylvania), and [[Scott Nearing|Scott]] and [[Helen Nearing]] (who inspired the [[back-to-the-land movement]] of the 1960s). Coincidentally, some of the above met briefly in India - all were quite influential in the U.S. from the 1960s into the 1980s.

== Society and culture ==
=== Terminology ===
The term &quot;composting&quot; is used worldwide with differing meanings.

&quot;Humanure&quot; is a [[portmanteau]] of ''human'' and ''manure'', designating human excrement ([[feces]] and [[urine]]) that is recycled via composting for agricultural purposes. The term was first used in 1994 in a book by Joseph Jenkins that advocates the use of this [[organic material|organic]] soil amendment.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{cite book|url=http://www.humanurehandbook.com|title=The Humanure Handbook: A Guide to Composting Human Manure|last=Jenkins|first=J.C.|publisher=Joseph Jenkins, Inc.; 3rd edition|year=2005|isbn=978-0-9644258-3-5|location=Grove City, PA|page=255|accessdate=April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The term humanure is used by compost enthusiasts in the United States but not widely used elsewhere.&lt;ref name=&quot;tilley2&quot; /&gt; Because the term &quot;humanure&quot; has no authoritative definition it is subject to various uses. News reporters may use the term also for [[sewage sludge]] or [[biosolids]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.yourottawaregion.com/feature/article/1224782--humanure-dumping-sickens-homeowner|title='Humanure' dumping sickens homeowner|author=Courtney Symons|date=13 October 2011|work=YourOttawaRegion|publisher=Metroland Media Group Ltd.|accessdate=16 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{div col}}
* [[Carbon farming]]
* [[Organic farming]]
* [[Permaculture]]
* [[Soil science]]
* [[Sustainable agriculture]]
* [[Terra preta]]
* [[Urban agriculture]]
* [[Waste sorting]]

===Related lists===
* [[List of composting systems]]
* [[List of environment topics]]
* [[List of sustainable agriculture topics]]
* [[List of organic gardening and farming topics]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{commons category|Compost}}
{{Wikibooks|Category:Composting}}

{{Portal bar|Agriculture and Agronomy|Gardening|Ecology|Environment}}
{{recycling}}
{{waste}}
{{Horticulture and Gardening}}
{{PlantMineralDeficiency}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Composting| ]]
[[Category:Organic fertilizers]]
[[Category:Waste management]]
[[Category:Gardening aids]]
[[Category:Sanitation]]
[[Category:Soil improvers]]
[[Category:Soil]]
[[Category:Sustainable food system]]</text>
      <sha1>lf647olkbg8dfo7id9gm7zevyy2g9ww</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
