  <page>
    <title>Braille</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3933</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942478081</id>
      <parentid>940756288</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-24T22:38:01Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bluelink 1 book for [[Wikipedia:Verifiability|verifiability]]. [goog]) #IABot (v2.0) ([[User:GreenC bot|GreenC bot]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{About|the writing system used by people who are blind or have low vision|the person who created Braille|Louis Braille|other uses}}
{{short description|Tactile writing system for blind and visually impaired people}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=February 2011}}
{{Infobox writing system
| name = ''' Braille'''
| altname = {{Braille cell|type=6dot|b|r|a|i|l|l|e|size=20px}}
| type = [[Alphabet]]
| typedesc = ([[non-linear writing|nonlinear]])
| time = 1824 to the present
| languages = Several
| fam1 = [[Night writing]]
| fam2 = [[1829 braille|Early braille]]
| sisters = [[New York Point]]
| children = [[French Braille]]&lt;br /&gt;[[English Braille]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Bharati Braille]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Mainland Chinese Braille|Chinese Braille]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Japanese Braille]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Korean Braille]]&lt;br /&gt;''[[:Category:French-ordered braille alphabets|etc.]]''
| creator = [[Louis Braille]]
| sample = Braille closeup.jpg{{!}}alt=finger tip touching page with raised dots
| imagesize = 312px
| unicode = [https://www.unicode.org/charts/PDF/U2800.pdf U+2800–U+28FF]
| iso15924 = Brai
| note = none
}}

{{BrailleChars}}

'''Braille''' (Braille: ⠃⠗⠁⠊⠇⠇⠑) ({{IPAc-en|b|r|eɪ|l}}; {{IPA-fr|bʁaj|lang}}) is a tactile [[writing system]] used by people who are [[visually impaired]]. It is traditionally written with embossed paper. Braille users can read computer screens and other electronic supports using [[refreshable braille display]]s. They can write braille with the original [[slate and stylus]] or type it on a [[braille writer]], such as a portable [[braille notetaker]] or computer that prints with a [[braille embosser]].

Braille is named after its creator, [[Louis Braille]], a Frenchman who lost his sight as a result of a childhood accident. In 1824, at the age of fifteen, he developed a code for the [[French alphabet]] as an improvement on [[night writing]]. He published his system, which subsequently included [[musical notation]], in 1829.&lt;ref&gt;[[Louis Braille|Braille, Louis]] (1829). ''Method of Writing Words, Music, and Plain Songs by Means of Dots, for Use by the Blind and Arranged for Them''.&lt;/ref&gt; The second revision, published in 1837, was the first [[Binary numeral system|small binary]] form of writing developed in the modern era.

These characters have rectangular blocks called ''cells''  that have tiny bumps called ''raised dots''. The number and arrangement of these dots distinguish one character from another. Since the various braille alphabets originated as [[Transcription (linguistics)|transcription]] codes for printed writing, the mappings (sets of character designations) vary from language to language, and even within one; in [[English Braille]] there are three levels of encoding: Grade 1 – a letter-by-letter transcription used for basic literacy; Grade 2 – an addition of abbreviations and contractions; and Grade 3 – various non-standardized personal stenography.

Braille cells are not the only thing to appear in braille text. There may be embossed illustrations and graphs, with the lines either solid or made of series of dots, arrows, bullets that are larger than braille dots, etc. A full braille cell includes six raised dots arranged in two columns, each column having three dots.&lt;ref name=&quot;Raised Dots&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.afb.org/info/living-with-vision-loss/braille/what-is-braille/123 |title=The Dot Positions Are Identified by Numbers from One Through Six |website=AFB.org |access-date=19 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The dot positions are identified by numbers from one to six.&lt;ref name=&quot;Raised Dots&quot;/&gt; There are 64 possible combinations, including no dots at all for a [[word space]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Braille System&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.duxburysystems.com/braille.asp |title=Louis Braille and the Braille System |access-date=16 August 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; A cell can be used to represent a letter, digit, punctuation mark, or even a word.&lt;ref name=&quot;Raised Dots&quot;/&gt;

Braille literacy is a social-justice issue.&lt;ref name=NPR/&gt; Early braille education is crucial to literacy, education and employment among the blind. However, in the face of changes in education policy and [[screen reader]] software, braille usage has declined in recent decades, despite the fact that technologies such as [[braille display]]s have also made braille more accessible and practical.

==History==
[[File:DSC 4050-MR-Braille.jpg|thumb|The Braille code where the word {{lang|fr-Brai|{{bc|⠏|⠗|⠑|⠍|⠊|⠑|⠗}}}} ({{wiktfr|premier}}, [[French language|French]] for &quot;first&quot;) can be read.]]
Braille was based on a tactile military [[code]] called [[night writing]], developed by [[Charles Barbier]] in response to [[Napoleon]]'s demand for a means for soldiers to communicate silently at night and without a light source.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=What is Braille|url=http://www.afb.org/info/living-with-vision-loss/braille/what-is-braille/123|website=American Foundation for the Blind}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Barbier's system, sets of 12 embossed dots encoded 36 different sounds. It proved to be too difficult for soldiers to recognize by touch and was rejected by the military. In 1821 Barbier visited the Royal Institute for the Blind in [[Paris]], where he met Louis Braille. Braille identified two major defects of the code: first, by representing only sounds, the code was unable to render the orthography of the words; second, the human finger could not encompass the whole 12-dot symbol without moving, and so could not move rapidly from one symbol to another. Braille's solution was to use 6-dot cells and to assign a specific pattern to each letter of the alphabet.&lt;ref name=&quot; Noëlle Roy &quot;&gt;{{Citation
 | url = http://www.avh.asso.fr/download.php?chemin=rubriques/association/dwnld/&amp;filename=Bio_Br_Paris_GB_060109.pdf
 | title = Louis Braille 1809–1852, a French genius
 | last = Roy |first = Noëlle
 | website = Valentin Haüy Association
 | accessdate = 2011-02-05
 | url-status = dead
 | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20101010054505/http://www.avh.asso.fr/download.php?chemin=rubriques%2Fassociation%2Fdwnld%2F&amp;filename=Bio_Br_Paris_GB_060109.pdf
 | archivedate = 10 October 2010
 | df = dmy-all
 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
At first, Braille was a one-to-one transliteration of French orthography, but soon various abbreviations, contractions, and even [[logogram]]s were developed, creating a system much more like shorthand.&lt;ref name=digital/&gt; The expanded English system, called [[Grade-2 Braille]], was completed by 1905. For blind readers, Braille is an independent writing system, rather than a code of printed orthography.&lt;ref name=&quot;D&amp;B&quot;/&gt;

=== Derivation ===
Braille is derived from the Latin alphabet, albeit indirectly. In Braille's original system, the dot patterns were assigned to letters according to their position within the [[collating sequence|alphabetic order]] of the French alphabet, with [[diacritic|accented]] letters and ''w'' sorted at the end.&lt;ref&gt;Madeleine Loomis (1942). ''The Braille Reference Book [for Grades I, I½, and II].''&lt;/ref&gt;

The first ten letters of the alphabet, ''a–j,'' use the upper four dot positions: {{Braille cell|type=text|⠁|⠃|⠉|⠙|⠑|⠋|⠛|⠓|⠊|⠚}} (black dots in the table below). These stand for the ten digits ''1–9'' and ''0'' in a system parallel to Hebrew [[gematria]] and Greek [[isopsephy]]. (Though the dots are assigned in no obvious order, the cells with the fewest dots are assigned to the first three letters (and lowest digits), ''abc = 123'' ({{Braille cell|type=text|⠁|⠃|⠉}}), and to the three vowels in this part of the alphabet, ''aei'' ({{Braille cell|type=text|⠁|⠑|⠊}}), whereas the even digits, ''4, 6, 8, 0'' ({{Braille cell|type=text|⠙|⠋|⠓|⠚}}), are corners/right angles.)

The next ten letters, ''k–t,'' are identical to ''a–j,'' respectively, apart from the addition of a dot at position 3 (red dots in the table below): {{Braille cell|type=text|⠅|⠇|⠍|⠝|⠕|⠏|⠟|⠗|⠎|⠞}}:

{|class=wikitable
|+Derivation (colored dots) of the 26 braille letters of the [[ISO basic Latin alphabet|Basic Latin alphabet]]&lt;br /&gt;from the 10 numeric digits (black dots)
|- align=center
|[[File:Braille A1.svg|40px]]||[[File:Braille B2.svg|40px]]||[[File:Braille C3.svg|40px]]||[[File:Braille D4.svg|40px]]||[[File:Braille E5.svg|40px]]||[[File:Braille F6.svg|40px]]||[[File:Braille G7.svg|40px]]||[[File:Braille H8.svg|40px]]||[[File:Braille I9.svg|40px]]||[[File:Braille J0.svg|40px]]
|- align=center
|[[a]]/[[1 (number)|1]]||[[b]]/[[2 (number)|2]]||[[c]]/[[3 (number)|3]]||[[d]]/[[4 (number)|4]]||[[e]]/[[5 (number)|5]]||[[f]]/[[6 (number)|6]]||[[g]]/[[7 (number)|7]]||[[h]]/[[8 (number)|8]]||[[i]]/[[9 (number)|9]]||[[j]]/[[0 (number)|0]]
|- align=center
|[[File:Braille K colored.svg|40px]]||[[File:Braille L colored.svg|40px]]||[[File:Braille M colored.svg|40px]]||[[File:Braille N colored.svg|40px]]||[[File:Braille O colored.svg|40px]]||[[File:Braille P colored.svg|40px]]||[[File:Braille Q colored.svg|40px]]||[[File:Braille R colored.svg|40px]]||[[File:Braille S colored.svg|40px]]||[[File:Braille T colored.svg|40px]]
|- align=center
|[[k]]||[[l]]||[[m]]||[[n]]||[[o]]||[[p]]||[[q]]||[[r]]||[[s]]||[[t]]
|- align=center
|[[File:Braille U colored.svg|40px]]||[[File:Braille V colored.svg|40px]]||[[File:Braille X colored.svg|40px]]||[[File:Braille Y colored.svg|40px]]||[[File:Braille Z colored.svg|40px]]|| colspan=&quot;4&quot; rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | ||[[File:Braille W colored.svg|40px]]
|- align=center
|[[u]]||[[v]]||[[x]]||[[y]]||[[z]]||[[w]]
|}

The next ten letters (the next &quot;[[wikt:decade#English|decade]]&quot;) are the same again, but with dots also at both position 3 and position 6 (green dots in the table above). Here ''w'' was left out as not being a part of the official French alphabet at the time of Braille's life; the French braille order is ''u v x y z ç é à è ù'' ({{Braille cell|type=text|⠥|⠧|⠭|⠽|⠵|⠯|⠿|⠷|⠮|⠾}}).{{NoteTag|The values of the Latin letters after ''z'' differ from language to language; these are Braille's assignments for rendering French.}}

The next ten letters, ending in ''w'', are the same again, except that for this series position 6 (purple dot in the table above) is used without a dot at position 3. In French braille these are the letters ''â ê î ô û ë ï ü ö w'' ({{Braille cell|type=text|⠡|⠣|⠩|⠹|⠱|⠫|⠻|⠳|⠪|⠺}}). ''W'' had been tacked onto the end of 39 letters of the French alphabet to accommodate English.

The ''a–j'' series shifted down by one dot space ({{Braille cell|type=text|⠂|⠆|⠒|⠲|⠢|⠖|⠶|⠦|⠔|⠴}}) is used for punctuation.  Letters ''a'' {{bc|a}} and ''c'' {{bc|c}}, which only use dots in the top row, were shifted two places for the apostrophe and hyphen: {{Braille cell|type=text|⠄|⠤}}. (These are also the decade diacritics, at left in the table below, of the second and third decade.)

In addition, there are ten patterns that are based on the first two letters ({{bc|a|b}}) with their dots shifted to the right; these were assigned to non-French letters (''ì ä ò'' {{Braille cell|type=text|⠌|⠜|⠬}}), or serve non-letter functions: {{Braille cell|type=text|⠈}} (superscript; in English the accent mark), {{Braille cell|type=text|⠘}} (currency prefix), {{Braille cell|type=text|⠨}} (capital, in English the decimal point), {{Braille cell|type=text|⠼}} (number sign), {{Braille cell|type=text|⠸}} (emphasis mark), {{Braille cell|type=text|⠐}} (symbol prefix).

:{| class=wikitable
|+ The 64 modern braille cells{{anchor|upper-half cells}}{{NoteTag|The characters have been arranged by decade, with decade diacritics listed at left, and supplementary characters included on the right according to their diacritic. See [[1829 braille]], where the 12 characters listed in the first line are used for shorthand and are found in this order for the 12 notes of plainsong notation, and [[French Braille]], where the 'final' form of Braille's alphabet is laid out in the same way. However, modern tables often organize the supplementary characters differently: Those with a dot 3 are listed as a 6th group of 6 characters, and those with dots only on the right side are listed as a 7th group of 7, without anything in common with the other characters in the columns they are listed under.}}
!colspan=2|decade|| ||colspan=10|numeric sequence || ||colspan=2|shift right
|- align=center
!1st
|[[File:Braille NULL.svg|40px]] ||
|[[File:Braille A1.svg|40px]]
|[[File:Braille B2.svg|40px]]
|[[File:Braille C3.svg|40px]]
|[[File:Braille D4.svg|40px]]
|[[File:Braille E5.svg|40px]]
|[[File:Braille F6.svg|40px]]
|[[File:Braille G7.svg|40px]]
|[[File:Braille H8.svg|40px]]
|[[File:Braille I9.svg|40px]]
|[[File:Braille J0.svg|40px]] ||
|[[File:Braille Accent.svg|40px]]
|[[File:Braille Currency.svg|40px]]
|- align=center
!2nd
|[[File:Braille Apostrophe colored.svg|40px|' (Apostrophe)]] ||
|[[File:Braille K colored.svg|40px]]
|[[File:Braille L colored.svg|40px]]
|[[File:Braille M colored.svg|40px]]
|[[File:Braille N colored.svg|40px]]
|[[File:Braille O colored.svg|40px]]
|[[File:Braille P colored.svg|40px]]
|[[File:Braille Q colored.svg|40px]]
|[[File:Braille R colored.svg|40px]]
|[[File:Braille S colored.svg|40px]]
|[[File:Braille T colored.svg|40px]] ||
|[[File:Braille ST colored.svg|40px]]
|[[File:Braille Ä colored.svg|40px]]
|- align=center
!3rd
|[[File:Braille Hyphen colored.svg|40px|- (Hyphen)]] ||
|[[File:Braille U colored.svg|40px]]
|[[File:Braille V colored.svg|40px]]
|[[File:Braille X colored.svg|40px]]
|[[File:Braille Y colored.svg|40px]]
|[[File:Braille Z colored.svg|40px]]
|[[File:Braille Ç colored.svg|40px]]
|[[File:Braille É colored.svg|40px]]
|[[File:Braille À colored.svg|40px]]
|[[File:Braille È colored.svg|40px]]
|[[File:Braille Ù colored.svg|40px]] ||
|[[File:Braille Ò colored.svg|40px]]
|[[File:Braille Number colored.svg|40px|# (Number)]]
|- align=center
!4th
|[[File:Braille Capital colored.svg|40px|UPPERCASE (Capital)]] ||
|[[File:Braille Â colored.svg|40px]]
|[[File:Braille Ê colored.svg|40px]]
|[[File:Braille Î colored.svg|40px]]
|[[File:Braille Ô colored.svg|40px]]
|[[File:Braille Û colored.svg|40px]]
|[[File:Braille Ë colored.svg|40px]]
|[[File:Braille Ï colored.svg|40px]]
|[[File:Braille Ü colored.svg|40px]]
|[[File:Braille Ö colored.svg|40px]]
|[[File:Braille W colored.svg|40px]] ||
|[[File:Braille Decimal colored.svg|40px|. (Decimal Point)]]
|[[File:Braille Cursive colored.svg|40px]]
|- align=center
!5th
! &lt;span style=&quot;color:#006060&quot;&gt;shift&lt;br /&gt;down&lt;/span&gt;
|
|[[File:Braille Comma colored.svg|40px|, (Comma)]]
|[[File:Braille Semicolon colored.svg|40px|; (Semicolon)]]
|[[File:Braille Colon colored.svg|40px|: (Colon)]]
|[[File:Braille Period colored.svg|40px|. (Period)]]
|[[File:Braille QuestionMark colored.svg|40px|? (Question Mark)]]
|[[File:Braille ExclamationPoint colored.svg|40px|! (Exclamation Point)]]
|[[File:Braille Bracket colored.svg|40px]]
|[[File:Braille QuoteOpen colored.svg|40px|“ (Quote Open)]]
|[[File:Braille Asterisk colored.svg|40px|* (Asterisk)]]
|[[File:Braille QuoteClose colored.svg|40px|” (Quote Close)]] ||
|[[File:Braille ContractionPrefix colored.svg|40px]]
|[[File:Braille Correction colored.svg|40px]]
|}

Originally there had been nine decades. The fifth through ninth used dashes as well as dots, but proved to be impractical and were soon abandoned. These could be replaced with what we now know as the number sign ({{Braille cell|type=text|⠼}}), though that only caught on for the digits (old 5th decade → modern 1st decade). The dash occupying the top row of the original sixth decade was simply dropped, producing the modern fifth decade. (See [[1829 braille]].)

===Assignment===
Historically, there have been three principles in assigning the values of a [[Linear writing|linear script]] (print) to Braille:  Using Louis Braille's original French letter values; reassigning the braille letters according to the [[sort order]] of the print alphabet being transcribed; and reassigning the letters to improve the efficiency of writing in braille.

Under international consensus, most braille alphabets follow the French sorting order for the 26 letters of the [[ISO basic Latin alphabet|basic Latin alphabet]], and there have been attempts at unifying the letters beyond these 26 (see [[international braille]]), though differences remain, for example in [[German Braille]] and the contractions of [[English Braille]]. This unification avoids the chaos of each nation reordering the braille code to match the sorting order of its print alphabet, as happened in [[Algerian Braille]], where braille codes were numerically reassigned to match the order of the Arabic alphabet and bear little relation to the values used in other countries (compare modern [[Arabic Braille]], which uses the French sorting order), and as happened in an early American version of English Braille, where the letters ''w, x, y, z'' were reassigned to match English alphabetical order.  A convention sometimes seen for letters beyond the basic 26 is to exploit the physical symmetry of braille patterns iconically, for example, by assigning a reversed ''n'' to ''ñ'' or an inverted ''s'' to ''sh''. (See [[Hungarian Braille]] and [[Bharati Braille]], which do this to some extent.)

A third principle was to assign braille codes according to frequency, with the simplest patterns (quickest ones to write with a stylus) assigned to the most frequent letters of the alphabet. Such frequency-based alphabets were used in Germany and the United States in the 19th century (see [[American Braille]]), but with the invention of the braille typewriter their advantage disappeared, and none are attested in modern use – they had the disadvantage that the resulting small number of dots in a text interfered with following the alignment of the letters, and consequently made texts more difficult to read than Braille's more arbitrary letter-assignment. Finally, there are braille scripts which don't order the codes numerically at all, such as [[Japanese Braille]] and [[Korean Braille]], which are based on more abstract principles of syllable composition.

Academic texts are sometimes written in a script of eight dots per cell rather than six, enabling them to encode a greater number of symbols. (See [[Gardner–Salinas braille codes]].) [[Luxembourgish Braille]] has adopted eight-dot cells for general use; for example, it adds a dot below each letter to derive its capital variant.

==Form==
[[File:Alianca braille.JPG|thumb|Silver wedding bands with names ''Henri(que)'' and ''Tita'' written in braille]]
Braille was the first writing system with [[Binary numeral system|binary]] [[Character encoding|encoding]].&lt;ref name=digital&gt;Daniels, Peter (1996). &quot;Analog and Digital Writing&quot;, in ''The World's Writing Systems,'' p.&amp;nbsp;886&lt;/ref&gt; The system as devised by Braille consists of two parts:&lt;ref name=&quot;D&amp;B&quot;&gt;Daniels &amp; Bright, 1996, ''The World's Writing Systems'', pp.&amp;nbsp;817–818&lt;/ref&gt;
#[[Character encoding]] that mapped characters of the [[French alphabet]] to [[tuple]]s of six [[bit]]s (the dots),
#The physical representation of those six-bit characters with raised dots in a braille cell.

Within an individual cell, the dot positions are arranged in two columns of three positions. A raised dot can appear in any of the six positions, producing sixty-four (2&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;) possible patterns, including one in which there are no raised dots. For reference purposes, a pattern is commonly described by listing the positions where dots are raised, the positions being universally numbered, from top to bottom, as 1 to 3 on the left and 4 to 6 on the right. For example, dot pattern 1-3-4 describes a cell with three dots raised, at the top and bottom in the left column and at the top of the right column:  that is, the letter {{Braille cell|type=text|⠍}} ''m''. The lines of horizontal Braille text are separated by a space, much like visible printed text, so that the dots of one line can be differentiated from the braille text above and below. Different assignments of braille codes (or [[code page]]s) are used to map the character sets of different printed scripts to the six-bit cells. Braille assignments have also been created for mathematical and musical notation. However, because the six-dot braille cell allows only 64 (2&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;) patterns, including space, the characters of a braille script commonly have multiple values, depending on their context. That is, character mapping between print and braille is not one-to-one.  For example, the character {{bc|d}} corresponds in print to both the letter ''d'' and the digit ''4''.

In addition to simple encoding, many braille alphabets use contractions to reduce the size of braille texts and to increase reading speed. (See [[English Braille#Contractions|Contracted braille]])

==Writing braille==
[[File:Braille Writer.jpg|thumb|Braille typewriter]]
Braille may be produced by hand using a [[slate and stylus]] in which each dot is created from the back of the page, writing in mirror image, or it may be produced on a [[braille typewriter]] or [[Perkins Brailler]], or an electronic Brailler or eBrailler. Because braille letters cannot be effectively erased and written over if an error is made, an error is overwritten with all six dots ({{bc|⠿}}). ''Interpoint'' refers to braille printing that is offset, so that the paper can be embossed on both sides, with the dots on one side appearing between the divots that form the dots on the other.
Using a computer or other electronic device, Braille may be produced with a [[braille embosser]] (printer) or a [[refreshable braille display]] (screen).

{{anchor|Eight-dot braille}}Braille has been extended to an 8-dot code, particularly for use with braille embossers and refreshable braille displays. In 8-dot braille the additional dots are added at the bottom of the cell, giving a matrix 4 dots high by 2 dots wide. The additional dots are given the numbers 7 (for the lower-left dot) and 8 (for the lower-right dot). Eight-dot braille has the advantages that the case of an individual letter is directly coded in the cell containing the letter and that all the printable [[ASCII]] characters can be represented in a single cell. All 256 (2&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt;) possible combinations of 8 dots are encoded by the [[Unicode]] standard. Braille with six dots is frequently stored as [[Braille ASCII]].

===Letters===
The first 25 braille letters, up through the first half of the 3rd decade, transcribe ''a–z'' (skipping ''w''). In English Braille, the rest of that decade is rounded out with the ligatures ''and, for, of, the,'' and ''with''. Omitting dot 3 from these forms the 4th decade, the ligatures ''ch, gh, sh, th, wh, ed, er, ou, ow'' and the letter ''w''.

{|class=wikitable
|- align=center
|{{Braille cell|type=6dot|ch}}
|{{Braille cell|type=6dot|sh}}
|{{Braille cell|type=6dot|th}}
|- align=center
|ch
|sh
|th
|}
(See [[English Braille]].)

===Formatting===
Various formatting marks affect the values of the letters that follow them. They have no direct equivalent in print. The most important in English Braille are:

{|class=wikitable
|- align=center
|{{Braille cell|type=6dot|size=40px|CAP}}
|{{Braille cell|type=6dot|size=40px|#}}
|- align=center
|[[Capital letter|Capital]]&lt;br /&gt;follows
|[[Number]]&lt;br /&gt;follows
|}
That is, {{Braille cell|type=text|cap|a}} is read as capital 'A', and {{Braille cell|type=text|num|a}} as the digit '1'.

===Punctuation===
Basic punctuation marks in English Braille include:

{|class=wikitable
|- align=center
|{{Braille cell|type=6dot|size=40px|,}}
|{{Braille cell|type=6dot|size=40px|;}}
|{{Braille cell|type=6dot|size=40px|'}}
|{{Braille cell|type=6dot|size=40px|:}}
|{{Braille cell|type=6dot|size=40px|-}}
|{{Braille cell|type=6dot|size=40px|decimal}}
|- align=center
|[[Comma]]
|[[Semicolon]]
|[[Apostrophe]]
|[[Colon (punctuation)|Colon]]
|[[Hyphen]]
|[[Decimal point]]
|- align=center
|{{Braille cell|type=6dot|size=40px|dd}}
|{{Braille cell|type=6dot|size=40px|!}}
|{{Braille cell|type=6dot|size=40px|hh}}
|{{Braille cell|type=6dot|size=40px|356}}
|{{Braille cell|type=6dot|size=40px|gg}}
|{{Braille cell|type=6dot|size=40px|st}}
|- align=center
|[[Full stop|Full stop &lt;br /&gt;(Period)]]
|[[Exclamation point|Exclamation &lt;br /&gt;point]]
|Open [[quotation mark|quote]], &lt;br /&gt;[[question mark]]
|Close &lt;br /&gt;[[quotation mark|quote]]
|[[Bracket|Bracket &lt;br /&gt;(Parentheses)]]
|[[Slash (punctuation)|Slash&lt;br /&gt;(Fraction)]]
|}

{{Braille cell|type=text|hh}} is both the question mark and the opening quotation mark. Its reading depends on whether it occurs before a word or after.

{{Braille cell|type=text|()}} is used for both opening and closing parentheses. Its placement relative to spaces and other characters determines its interpretation.

Punctuation varies from language to language. For example, [[French Braille]] uses {{Braille cell|26|type=text}} for its question mark and swaps the quotation marks and parentheses (to {{Braille cell|type=unicode|()}} and {{Braille cell|type=unicode|hh|jj}}); it uses the period ({{Braille cell|type=unicode|dd}}) for the decimal point, as in print, and the decimal point ({{Braille cell|type=unicode|decimal}}) to mark capitalization.

===Contractions===
{{For|a full list of abbreviations and contractions in English|English Braille#Contractions}}

Braille contractions are words and affixes that are shortened so that they take up fewer cells. In English Braille, for example, the word ''afternoon'' is written with just three letters, {{bc|⠁|⠋|⠝}} {{angle bracket|afn}}, much like [[stenoscript]]. There are also several abbreviation marks that create what are effectively [[logogram]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;D&amp;B&quot;/&gt; The most common of these is dot 5, which combines with the first letter of words. With the letter {{bc|⠍}} ''m'', the resulting word is {{bc|⠐|⠍}} ''mother''. There are also [[ligature (typography)|ligatures]] (&quot;contracted&quot; letters), which are single letters in braille but correspond to more than one letter in print. The letter {{bc|⠯}} ''and'', for example, is used to write words with the sequence ''a-n-d'' in them, such as {{bc|⠓|⠯}} ''hand''.

{|class=wikitable
|{{Braille cell|type=6dot|a|f|n}}||{{Braille cell|type=6dot|5|m}}||{{Braille cell|type=6dot|h|and}}
|-
|''afternoon&lt;br /&gt;(a-f-n)''||''mother&lt;br /&gt;(dot 5–m)''||''hand&lt;br /&gt;(h-and)''
|}

===Page dimensions===
Most [[braille embosser]]s support between 34 and 40 cells per line, and 25 lines per page.

A manually operated Perkins braille typewriter supports a maximum of 42 cells per line (its margins are adjustable), and typical paper allows 25 lines per page.

A large interlining Stainsby has 36 cells per line and 18 lines per page.

An A4-sized Marburg braille frame, which allows interpoint braille (dots on both sides of the page, offset so they do not interfere with each other) has 30 cells per line and 27 lines per page.

===Braille writing machine===
[[File:An aesthetic braille typewriter video.ogv|thumb|Braille typewriter]]
[[File:Máquina Stainsby.jpg|thumb|alt=sliding carriage with keys on a metal plate|Stainsby Braille writer]]
A Braille writing machine is a typewriter with six keys that allow to write in Braille alphabet on a regular white page.

The first Braille typewriter to gain general acceptance was invented by [[Frank Haven Hall]] (Superintendent of the [[Illinois School for the Blind]]), and was presented to the public in 1892.&lt;ref&gt;History of the Perkins Brailler www.perkins.org/assets/downloads/research/history-of-brailler-11-17-09.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;https://www.antiquetypewriters.com/typewriter/hall-braille-writer-1/&lt;/ref&gt;

The Stainsby Brailler, developed by Henry Stainsby in 1903, is a mechanical writer with a sliding carriage that moves over an aluminium plate as it embosses Braille characters. An improved version was introduced around 1933.&lt;ref name=&quot;edman&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last1=Edman |first1=Polly |title=Tactile Graphics |date=1992 |publisher=American Foundation for the Blind |isbn=9780891281948 |page=[https://archive.org/details/tactilegraphics15poll/page/153 153] |url=https://archive.org/details/tactilegraphics15poll |quote=Stainsby brailler. |accessdate=23 October 2019 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Object - Stainsby Braille writer - Victorian Collections |url=https://victoriancollections.net.au/items/58e2df01d0ce3c27d8c75cdb |website=Victorian Collections |publisher=Museums Australia Victoria |accessdate=23 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1951 David Abraham, a woodworking teacher at the [[Perkins School for the Blind]] produced a more advanced Braille typewriter, the [[Perkins Brailler]].{{citation needed|date=October 2019}}

[[Braille embosser|Braille printers or embosser]] were produced in 1950s.
In 1960 Robert Mann, a teacher in MIT, wrote DOTSYS, a software that allowed automatic [[Braille translator|braille translation]], and another group created an [[Braille translator|embossing]] device called &quot;M.I.T. Braillemboss.&quot;. The Mitre Corporation team of Robert Gildea, Jonathan Millen, Reid Gerhart and Joseph Sullivan (now president of Duxbury Systems) developed [[DOTSYS III]], the first braille translator written in a portable programming language. DOTSYS III was developed for the [[Atlanta Public Schools]] as a [[Public domain|public domain program]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.duxburysystems.org/downloads/library/history/1961_ibm.pdf Braille Translation System for the IBM 704 by Ann S. Schack and R.T. Mertz, 1961] retrieved 3/30/2016&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.duxburysystems.org/downloads/library/history/schack_1969.pdf Computer Translation: Grade 2 from Print; Report of American Printing House of the Blind, by Ann Schack, et al., June 1969] retrieved 3/30/2016&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.duxburysystems.com/duxhist.asp History of Duxbury Systems], retrieved 3/29/2012&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1991 Ernest Bate developed the [[Mountbatten Brailler]], an electronic machine used to type braille on braille paper, giving it a number of additional features such as word processing, audio feedback and embossing. This version was improved in 2008 with a quiet writer that had an erase key.{{citation needed|date=October 2019}}

In 2011 David S. Morgan produced the first SMART Brailler machine, with added [[text to speech]] function and allowed digital capture of data entered.{{citation needed|date=October 2019}}

==Braille reading==

Braille is usually read in printed forms such as paper books written in braille, braille public signals and also on [[Braille e-book]]s. Currently more than 1% of all printed books have been translated into braille.

Although the finger can read only one braille character at a time, the brain chunks braille at a higher level, processing words a digraph, root or suffix at a time. The processing largely takes place in the [[visual cortex]].&lt;ref name=NPR&gt;[https://www.houstonpublicmedia.org/articles/shows/houston-matters/2018/03/05/271315/experts-gathering-in-houston-to-discuss-how-braille-is-taught-and-what-it-can-teach-us-about-the-brain/ Experts Gathering In Houston To Discuss How Braille Is Taught – And What It Can Teach Us.] National Public Radio, 05 May 2018&lt;/ref&gt;

==Literacy==
{{Main|Braille literacy}}

Children who are blind not only have the educational disadvantage of not being able to see – they also miss out on fundamental parts of early and advanced education if not provided with the necessary tools. Children who are blind or visually impaired can begin learning pre-braille skills from a very young age to become fluent braille readers as they get older.

===U.S. braille literacy statistics===

In 1960, 50% of [[legally blind]], school-age children were able to read braille in the U.S.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation
 | url = http://www.braille.org/papers/jvib0696/vb960329.htm
 | url-status = dead
 | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20080907214004/http://www.braille.org/papers/jvib0696/vb960329.htm
 | archive-date = 2008-09-07
 | title = Estimated Number of Adult Braille Readers in the United States
 | website = International Braille Research Center (IBRC)
 | author = American Foundation for the Blind
 | accessdate = 2009-04-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Ranalli2008&gt;{{Citation
 | url = http://www.boston.com/news/local/articles/2008/01/05/a_boost_for_braille/
 | title = A Boost for Braille
 | last = Ranalli | first = Ralph
 | work = [[The Boston Globe]]
 | accessdate = 2009-04-17
 | date=2008-01-05
}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to the 2015 ''Annual Report'' from the [[American Printing House for the Blind]], there were 61,739 legally blind students registered in the U.S. Of these, 8.6% (5,333) were registered as braille readers, 31% (19,109) as visual readers, 9.4% (5,795) as auditory readers, 17% (10,470) as pre-readers, and 34% (21,032) as non-readers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Blind2013&quot;&gt;{{Citation|title=Annual Report 2015|url=http://www.aph.org/files/annual-reports/APH-Annual-Report-FY15.pdf|year=2016|author=American Printing House for the Blind|accessdate=2016-10-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are numerous causes for the decline in braille usage, including school budget constraints, technology advancements such as screen-reader software, and different philosophical views over how blind children should be educated.&lt;ref name = &quot;Ruby Riles&quot;&gt;{{Citation
 | url = http://www.braille.org/papers/jvib0696/vb960311.htm
 | url-status = dead
 | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20090528035928/http://www.braille.org/papers/jvib0696/vb960311.htm
 | archive-date = 2009-05-28
 | title = The Impact of Braille Reading Skills on Employment, Income, Education, and Reading Habits
 | last = Riles | first = Ruby
 | journal = Braille Research Center
 | accessdate = 2009-04-15
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Wiazowski|first=Jaroslaw|date=2014|title=Can Braille Be Revived? A Possible Impact of High-End Braille and Mainstream Technology on the Revival of Tactile Literacy Medium|url=|journal=Assistive Technology|volume=26 (4)|pages=227|via=Taylor &amp; Francis Online}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A key turning point for braille literacy was the passage of the [[Rehabilitation Act of 1973]], an [[act of Congress]] that moved thousands of children from specialized schools for the blind into [[mainstreaming (education)|mainstream]] public schools.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ranalli2008&quot;/&gt; Because only a small percentage of public schools could afford to train and hire braille-qualified teachers, braille literacy has declined since the law took effect.{{Clarify|date=November 2011}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Ranalli2008&quot;/&gt; Braille literacy rates have improved slightly since the bill was passed,{{Clarify|date=November 2011}} in part because of pressure from consumers and advocacy groups that has led 27 states to pass legislation mandating that children who are legally blind be given the opportunity to learn braille.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ruby Riles&quot; /&gt;

In 1998 there were 57,425 legally blind students registered in the United States, but only 10% (5,461) of them used braille as their primary reading medium.&lt;ref name=&quot;Blind1999&quot;&gt;{{Citation|title=APH maintains an annual register of legally blind students below the college level |url=http://www.aph.org/fedquotpgm/dist99.html |year=1999 |author=American Printing House for the Blind (APH) |accessdate=2016-10-27 |url-status=bot: unknown |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20020131020657/http://www.aph.org/fedquotpgm/dist99.html |archivedate=31 January 2002 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Ebnet2001&gt;{{Citation
 | url = http://articles.latimes.com/2001/jun/30/local/me-16960
 | title = Braille Challenge Gives Young Blind Students a Chance to Shine
 | last = Ebnet | first = Matthew
 | accessdate = 2009-04-15
 | work = [[The Los Angeles Times]]
 | date = 2001-06-30
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Early Braille education is crucial to literacy for a blind or low-vision child. A study conducted in the state of Washington found that people who learned braille at an early age did just as well, if not better than their sighted peers in several areas, including vocabulary and comprehension. In the preliminary adult study, while evaluating the correlation between adult literacy skills and employment, it was found that 44% of the participants who had learned to read in braille were unemployed, compared to the 77% unemployment rate of those who had learned to read using print.&lt;ref name=Ph2004&gt;{{Citation
 | url = http://www.nfb.org/Images/nfb/Publications/fr/fr14/fr04se22.htm
 | title = Research Study: Early Braille Education Vital
 | year = 2004
 | last = Riles | first = Ruby
 | journal = Future Reflections
 | accessdate = 2009-04-15
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Currently, among the estimated 85,000 blind adults in the United States, 90% of those who are braille-literate are employed. Among adults who do not know braille, only 33% are employed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ranalli2008&quot;/&gt; Statistically, history has proven that braille reading proficiency provides an essential skill set that allows blind or low-vision children to compete with their sighted peers in a school environment and later in life as they enter the workforce.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ruby Riles&quot; /&gt;

===United Kingdom===

Though braille is thought to be the main way blind people read and write, in Britain (for example) out of the reported two million blind and low vision population, it is estimated that only around 15,000–20,000 people use braille.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-16984742 |title=Braille is spreading but who's using it? |first=Damon |last=Rose |year=2012 |work=BBC News |accessdate=14 October 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Younger people are turning to electronic text on computers with [[screen reader]] software instead, a more portable communication method that they can use with their friends. A debate has started on how to make braille more attractive and for more teachers to be available to teach it.

==Braille transcription==
{{anchor|keyboard}}
[[File:Braille on tablet box.JPG|thumb|right|Braille on a box of tablets. The raised Braille reads 'plavix'.]]
[[File:Braille book.JPG|thumb|right|Braille book and the same book in inkprint]]

Although it is possible to transcribe print by simply substituting the equivalent braille character for its printed equivalent, in English such a character-by-character transcription (known as ''uncontracted braille'') is only used by beginners.

Braille characters are much larger than their printed equivalents, and the standard 11&quot; by 11.5&quot; (28&amp;nbsp;cm &amp;times; 30&amp;nbsp;cm) page has room for only 25 lines of 43 characters. To reduce space and increase reading speed, most braille alphabets and orthographies use ligatures, abbreviations, and contractions. Virtually all English Braille books are transcribed in this ''contracted braille,'' which adds an additional layer of complexity to English orthography: The Library of Congress's ''Instruction Manual for Braille Transcribing''&lt;ref&gt;Risjord, Constance (2009). [https://nfb.org/images/nfb/documents/pdf/nls-5th-ed-electronicversion.pdf Instruction Manual for Braille Transcribing], Library of Congress, 5th ed. {{ISBN|0-8444-1227-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; runs to over 300 pages and braille transcribers must pass certification tests.

Fully contracted braille is known as ''Grade 2 Braille''. There is an intermediate form, called Grade 1 Braille, that is between Computer Braille (one-for-one identity with print) and Grade 2 Braille. In Grade 1 Braille, the capital sign and number sign are used, and most punctuation marks are shown using their Grade 2 values.

The system of [[contraction (grammar)|contractions]] in English Braille begins with a set of 23 words which are contracted to single characters. Thus the word ''but'' is contracted to the single letter ''b,'' ''can'' to ''c'', ''do'' to ''d'', and so on. Even this simple rule creates issues requiring special cases; for example, ''d'' is, specifically, an abbreviation of the verb ''do;'' the noun ''do'' representing the note of the musical scale is a different word, and must be spelled out.

Portions of words may be contracted, and many rules govern this process. For example, the character with dots 2-3-5 (the letter &quot;f&quot; lowered in the Braille cell) stands for &quot;ff&quot; when used in the middle of a word. At the beginning of a word, this same character stands for the word &quot;to&quot;; the character is written in braille with no space following it. (This contraction was removed in the [[Unified English Braille Code]].) At the end of a word, the same character represents an exclamation point.

Some contractions are more similar than their print equivalents. For example, the contraction {{angle bracket|lr}}, meaning 'letter', differs from {{angle bracket|ll}}, meaning 'little', only by one dot in the second letter: {{bc|⠇|⠇}} ''little'', {{bc|⠇|⠗}} ''letter''. This causes greater confusion between the braille spellings of these words and can hinder the learning process of contracted braille.&lt;ref&gt;Hampshire, Barry. ''Working with Braille.'' Paris: Unesco, 1981.&lt;/ref&gt;

The contraction rules take into account the linguistic structure of the word; thus, contractions are generally not to be used when their use would alter the usual braille form of a base word to which a prefix or suffix has been added. Some portions of the transcription rules are not fully codified and rely on the judgment of the transcriber. Thus, when the contraction rules permit the same word in more than one way, preference is given to &quot;the contraction that more nearly approximates correct pronunciation.&quot;

''Grade 3 Braille''&lt;ref&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20050329073830/http://www.geocities.com/jyyne_2000/grade3.htm Grade 3 Braille]. geocities.com (June 2000). Retrieved on 2012-12-21.&lt;/ref&gt; is a variety of non-standardized systems that include many additional shorthand-like contractions. They are not used for publication, but by individuals for their personal convenience.

==Braille translation software==
When people produce braille, this is called braille transcription. When computer software produces braille, this is called braille
translation. Braille translation software exists to handle most of the common languages of the world, and many technical areas,
such as [[mathematics]] ([[mathematical notation]]), for example [[WIMATS]], [[music]] ([[musical notation]]), and tactile graphics.

==Braille-reading techniques==
Since Braille is one of the few writing systems where tactile perception is used, as opposed to visual perception, a braille reader must develop new skills.  One skill important for Braille readers is the ability to create smooth and even pressures when running one's fingers along the words. There are many different styles and techniques used for the understanding and development of braille, even though a study by B. F. Holland&lt;ref&gt;Holland, B. F. (1934). &quot;Speed and Pressure Factors in Braille Reading&quot;, ''Teachers Forum,'' Vol. 7. pp.&amp;nbsp;13–17&lt;/ref&gt; suggests that there is no specific technique that is superior to any other.

Another study by Lowenfield &amp; Abel&lt;ref&gt;Lowenfield, B.; Abel, and G. L. (1977). ''Methods of Teaching Braille Reading Efficiency of Children in Lower Senior Classes.'' Birmingham, Research Centre for the Education of the Visually Handicapped&lt;/ref&gt; shows that braille can be read &quot;the fastest and best... by students who read using the index fingers of both hands&quot;. Another important reading skill emphasized in this study is to finish reading the end of a line with the right hand and to find the beginning of the next line with the left hand simultaneously. One final conclusion drawn by both Lowenfield and Abel is that children have difficulty using both hands independently where the right hand is the dominant hand.  But this hand preference does not correlate to other activities.

==International uniformity==
{{Main|International uniformity of braille}}
{{anchor|Grade 1 braille}}
[[File:Rapperswil - Duftrosengarten 20080222 005.jpg|thumb|Braille plate at ''[[Duftrosengarten]]'' in [[Rapperswil]], Switzerland]]

When Braille was first adapted to languages other than French, many schemes were adopted, including mapping the native alphabet to the alphabetical order of French – e.g. in English W, which was not in the French alphabet at the time, is mapped to braille X, X to Y, Y to Z, and Z to the first French-accented letter – or completely rearranging the alphabet such that common letters are represented by the simplest braille patterns. Consequently, mutual intelligibility was greatly hindered by this state of affairs. In 1878, the International Congress on Work for the Blind, held in Paris, proposed an international braille standard, where braille codes for different languages and scripts would be based, not on the order of a particular alphabet, but on phonetic correspondence and transliteration to Latin.&lt;ref name=IntlBraille&gt;{{cite web|title=International Meeting on Braille Uniformity|url=http://unesdoc.unesco.org/images/0007/000711/071103eb.pdf|publisher=UNESCO|accessdate=2012-04-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

This unified braille has been applied to the languages of India and Africa, Arabic, Vietnamese, Hebrew, Russian, and Armenian, as well as nearly all Latin-script languages. Greek, for example, ''gamma'' is written as Latin ''g'', despite the fact that it has the alphabetic position of ''c''; Hebrew ''bet'', the second letter of the alphabet and [[cognate]] with the Latin letter ''b'', is sometimes pronounced /b/ and sometimes /v/, and is written ''b'' or ''v'' accordingly; Russian ''ts'' is written as ''c'', which is the usual letter for /ts/ in those [[Slavic languages]] that use the Latin alphabet; and Arabic ''f'' is written as ''f'', despite being historically ''p'', and occurring in that part of the Arabic alphabet (between historic ''o'' and ''q'').

==Other braille conventions==

Other systems for assigning values to braille patterns are also followed beside the simple mapping of the alphabetical order onto the original French order. Some braille alphabets start with [[unified braille]], and then diverge significantly based on the phonology of the target languages, while others diverge even further.

In the various Chinese systems, traditional braille values are used for initial consonants and the simple vowels. In both [[Mainland Chinese Braille|Mandarin]] and [[Cantonese Braille]], however, characters have different readings depending on whether they are placed in syllable-initial (onset) or syllable-final (rime) position. For instance, the cell for Latin ''k'', {{Braille cell|type=text|K}}, represents Cantonese ''k'' (''g'' in [[Yale romanization of Cantonese|Yale]] and other modern romanizations) when initial, but ''aak'' when final, while Latin ''j'', {{Braille cell|type=text|J}}, represents Cantonese initial ''j'' but final ''oei''.

Novel systems of braille mapping include Korean, which adopts separate syllable-initial and syllable-final forms for its consonants, explicitly grouping braille cells into syllabic groups in the same way as [[hangul]]. Japanese, meanwhile, combines independent vowel dot patterns and modifier consonant dot patterns into a single braille cell – an [[abugida]] representation of each Japanese [[Mora (linguistics)#Japanese|mora]].

==Uses==
[[File:Braille wine label.jpg|thumb|A bottle of [[Chapoutier]] wine, with braille on the label]]
[[File:Bahnhofsplan für Blinde, Hannover Hbf, Ausschnitt Eingangsbereich.jpg|thumb|An embossed map of a German train station, with braille text]]
The current series of [[Banknotes of the Canadian dollar|Canadian banknotes]] has a [[Canadian currency tactile feature|tactile feature]] consisting of raised dots that indicate the denomination, allowing bills to be easily identified by blind or low vision people. It does not use standard braille; rather, the feature uses a system developed in consultation with blind and low vision Canadians after research indicated that braille was not sufficiently robust and that not all potential users read braille. [[Mexican peso#Series D|Mexican bank notes]], [[Australian dollar|Australian bank notes]], [[Indian rupee]] notes, [[Israeli new shekel]] notes &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.boi.org.il/en/Currency/BanknoteSecurityFeatures/Pages/intaglio.aspx Bank of Israel – Banknote Security Features – Raised print (intaglio)]. boi.org.il. Retrieved on 2013-01-11.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Russian ruble]] notes also have special raised symbols to make them identifiable by persons who are blind or low vision.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Banknotes {{!}} Банк России |url=https://www.cbr.ru/eng/Bank-notes_coins/banknotes_itm/?PrtId=banknotes_itm&amp;nominal=5000 |website=www.cbr.ru |publisher=[[Central Bank of Russia]] |accessdate=9 December 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[India]] there are instances where the parliament acts have been published in braille, such as ''The Right to Information Act''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hindu.com/2006/07/04/stories/2006070402351200.htm National : Right to Information Act in Braille]. The Hindu (2006-07-04). Retrieved on 2012-12-21.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the United States, the [[Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ada.gov/ ada.gov]. Retrieved on 2012-12-21.&lt;/ref&gt; requires various building signage to be in braille.

In the United Kingdom, it is required that medicines have the name of the medicine in Braille on the labeling.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.gov.uk/medicines-packaging-labelling-and-patient-information-leaflets#braille-on-labelling-and-in-pils Medicines: packaging, labeling, and patient information leaflets]. gov.uk. Retrieved on 2015-05-05.&lt;/ref&gt;

Australia also recently introduced the tactile feature onto their five-dollar banknote&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.abc.net.au/news/2016-08-31/new-tactile-$5-note-coming-into-circulation/7797160|title=Australia's new $5 notes to be more accessible to blind and vision-impaired people |first=Nicole |last=Mills |date=30 August 2016 |work=[[ABC News (TV channel)|ABC News]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

U.K. September 2017 – On the front of the £10 polymer note (the side with raised print), there are two clusters of raised dots in the top left hand corner. This tactile feature helps blind and partially sighted people identify the value of the note.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bankofengland.co.uk/banknotes/Pages/about/faqs.aspx|title=Questions about polymer banknotes and the new £10 note|date=August 2017|website=Bank of England}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Unicode==
{{Main|Unicode braille patterns}}

Braille was added to the [[Unicode]] Standard in September 1999 with the release of version 3.0.

Most [[braille embosser]]s and [[refreshable braille display]]s do not support Unicode, using instead 6-dot [[braille ASCII]].  Some embossers have proprietary control codes for 8-dot braille or for full graphics mode, where dots may be placed anywhere on the page without leaving any space between braille cells so that continuous lines can be drawn in diagrams, but these are rarely used and are not standard.

The Unicode standard encodes 8-dot braille glyphs according to their binary appearance, rather than following their assigned numeric order. Dot 1 corresponds to the [[least significant bit]] of the low byte of the Unicode scalar value, and dot 8 to the high bit of that byte.

The Unicode block for braille is U+2800 ... U+28FF:

{{Unicode chart Braille Patterns}}

==Observation==
Every year on January 4th, [[World Braille Day]] is observed internationally to commemorate the birth of [[Louis Braille]] and to recognize his efforts, but the event is not considered a public holiday.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=World Braille Day: 4th January|url=http://www.calendarlabs.com/holidays/international/world-braille-day.php|website=www.calendarlabs.com|accessdate=2 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{div col|colwidth=30em}}

*[[Accessible publishing]]
*[[Braille literacy]]
*[[Braille music]]
*[[Braille technology]]
*[[Braille translator]]
*[[Braille watch]]
*[[English Braille]]
*[[List of binary codes]]
*[[List of international common standards]]
*[[Moon type]]
*[[Needle punch]]
*[[Nemeth Braille]] (for mathematics)
*[[Refreshable Braille display]]
*[[Tactile alphabets for the blind]]
*[[Tactile graphic]]
*[[Tangible symbol systems]]
*[[Unified English Braille]]
{{div col end}}

== Notes ==
{{NoteFoot}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Braille}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20100403215834/http://www.avh.asso.fr/rubrics/association/association.php?langue=eng&amp; Association Valentin Haüy]
* [http://www.atpc.net/ Alternate Text Production Center]

{{-}}
{{Braille}}
{{ISO 15924/footer}}
{{list of writing systems}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Braille| ]]
[[Category:1824 introductions]]
[[Category:Assistive technology]]
[[Category:Augmentative and alternative communication]]
[[Category:Character sets]]
[[Category:Digital typography]]
[[Category:French inventions]]
[[Category:Latin-script representations]]
[[Category:Scripts encoded in Unicode 3.0]]
[[Category:Writing systems introduced in the 19th century]]</text>
      <sha1>pg0x3guxxoanf7hg28ikfhoo1c9iswa</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
