  <page>
    <title>Biopolymer</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3974</id>
    <revision>
      <id>939353664</id>
      <parentid>931063234</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-05T23:09:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>184.195.170.169</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Sugars */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|Biopolymers|the scientific journal|Biopolymers (journal)}}
[[File:DNA animation.gif|thumb|right|220px|In the structure of [[DNA]] is a pair of '''biopolymers''', [[polynucleotide]]s, forming the [[double helix]]]]

'''Biopolymers''' are [[polymer]]s produced by [[Organism|living organisms]]; in other words, they are polymeric [[biomolecule]]s. Biopolymers contain [[monomer]]ic units that are covalently bonded to form larger structures. There are three main classes of biopolymers, classified according to the monomeric units used and the structure of the biopolymer formed: [[polynucleotide]]s ([[RNA]] and [[DNA]]), which are long polymers composed of 13 or more [[nucleotide]] [[monomer]]s; [[polypeptides]], which are short polymers of [[amino acid]]s; and [[polysaccharides]], which are often linear bonded polymeric [[carbohydrate]] structures.&lt;ref&gt;
Mohanty, A.K., et al., ''Natural Fibers, Biopolymers, and Biocomposites'' (CRC Press, 2005)
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
Chandra, R., and Rustgi, R., &quot;Biodegradable Polymers&quot;, ''Progress in Polymer Science'', Vol. 23, p. 1273 (1998)
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
Meyers, M.A., et al., &quot;Biological Materials: Structure &amp; Mechanical Properties&quot;, ''Progress in Materials Science'', Vol. 53, p. 1 (2008)
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
Kumar, A., et al., &quot;Smart Polymers: Physical Forms &amp; Bioengineering Applications&quot;, ''Progress in Polymer Science'', Vol. 32, p. 1205 (2007)
&lt;/ref&gt; Other examples of biopolymers include [[rubber]], [[suberin]], [[melanin]] and [[lignin]].
{{Quote box
 |title =[[International Union of Pure and Applied Chemistry|IUPAC]] definition
 |quote = Substance composed of one type of ''biomacromolecules''.

''Note 1'': Modified from the definition given in ref.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Compendium of Chemical Terminology: IUPAC Recommendations (the &quot;Gold Book&quot;)|year=1997|publisher=Blackwell Science|isbn=0865426848|edition=2nd|editor=Alan D. MacNaught, Andrew R. Wilkinson}}&lt;/ref&gt; in order&lt;br/&gt;to avoid confusion between ''polymer'' and ''macromolecule'' in&lt;br/&gt;the fields of proteins, polysaccharides, polynucleotides, and bacterial&lt;br/&gt;aliphatic polyesters.

''Note 2'': The use of the term “biomacromolecule” is recommended&lt;br/&gt;when molecular characteristics are considered.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Terminology for biorelated polymers and applications (IUPAC Recommendations 2012)|journal=[[Pure and Applied Chemistry]]|year=2012|volume=84|issue=2|pages=377–410|doi=10.1351/PAC-REC-10-12-04|url=http://pac.iupac.org/publications/pac/pdf/2012/pdf/8402x0377.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
}}
[[Cellulose]] is the most common organic compound and biopolymer on Earth. About 33 percent of all plant matter is cellulose. The cellulose content of cotton is 90 percent, for wood it is 50 percent.&lt;ref&gt;
Klemm, D., Heublein, B., Fink, H., and Bohn, A., &quot;Cellulose: 
Fascinating Biopolymer / Sustainable Raw Material&quot;, Ang. Chemie (Intl. Edn.) Vol. 44, p. 3358 (2004) 
&lt;/ref&gt;

== Biopolymers versus synthetic polymers ==

A major defining difference between '''biopolymers''' and '''synthetic''' polymers can be found in their structures. All polymers are made of repetitive units called [[monomer]]s. Biopolymers often have a well-defined structure, though this is not a defining characteristic (example: [[lignocellulose]]): 
The exact chemical composition and the sequence in which these units are arranged is called the [[primary structure]], in the case of proteins. Many biopolymers spontaneously fold into characteristic compact shapes (see also &quot;[[protein folding]]&quot;  as well as [[secondary structure]] and [[tertiary structure]]), which determine their biological functions and depend in a complicated way on their primary structures. [[Structural biology]] is the study of the structural properties of the biopolymers.
In contrast, most ''synthetic polymers''' have much simpler and more random (or stochastic) structures. This fact leads to a molecular mass distribution that is missing in biopolymers.
In fact, as their synthesis is controlled by a template-directed process in most ''in vivo'' systems, all biopolymers of a type (say one specific protein) are all alike: they all contain the similar sequences and numbers of monomers and thus all have the same mass. This phenomenon is called [[monodispersity]] in contrast to the [[polydispersity]] encountered in synthetic polymers. As a result, biopolymers have a [[polydispersity index]] of 1.&lt;ref&gt;
Stupp, S.I and Braun, P.V., &quot;Role of Proteins in Microstructural Control: Biomaterials, Ceramics &amp; Semiconductors&quot;, Science, Vol. 277, p. 1242 (1997)
&lt;/ref&gt;

== Conventions and nomenclature ==

=== Polypeptides ===

The convention for a [[polypeptide]] is to list its constituent amino acid residues as they occur from the amino terminus to the carboxylic acid terminus. The amino acid residues are always joined by [[peptide bond]]s. [[Protein]], though used colloquially to refer to any polypeptide, refers to larger or fully functional forms and can consist of several polypeptide chains as well as single chains. Proteins can also be modified to include non-peptide components, such as [[saccharide]] chains and [[lipid]]s.

=== Nucleic acids ===
The convention for a [[nucleic acid]] sequence is to list the nucleotides as they occur from the 5' end to the 3' end of the [[polymer chain]], where 5' and 3' refer to the numbering of carbons around the ribose ring which participate in forming the phosphate diester linkages of the chain. Such a sequence is called the primary structure of the biopolymer.

=== Sugar ===
Sugar-based biopolymers are often difficult with regards to convention. Sugar polymers can be linear or branched and are typically joined with [[glycosidic bond]]s. The exact placement of the linkage can vary, and the orientation of the linking functional groups is also important, resulting in α- and β-glycosidic bonds with numbering definitive of the linking carbons' location in the ring. In addition, many saccharide units can undergo various chemical modifications, such as [[amination]], and can even form parts of other molecules, such as [[glycoprotein]]s.

== Structural characterization ==
There are a number of [[biophysics|biophysical]] techniques for determining sequence information. [[Peptide sequence|Protein sequence]] can be determined by [[Edman degradation]], in which the N-terminal residues are hydrolyzed from the chain one at a time, derivatized, and then identified. Mass [[spectrometer]] techniques can also be used. Nucleic acid sequence can be determined using gel [[electrophoresis]] and capillary electrophoresis. Lastly, mechanical properties of these biopolymers can often be measured using [[optical tweezers]] or [[atomic force microscopy]]. [[Dual-polarization interferometry]] can be used to measure the conformational changes or self-assembly of these materials when stimulated by pH, temperature, ionic strength or other binding partners.

== As materials ==
Some biopolymers- such as  [[Polylactic acid|PLA]], naturally occurring [[zein]], and [[poly-3-hydroxybutyrate]] can be used as plastics, replacing the need for [[polystyrene]] or [[polyethylene]] based plastics.

Some plastics are now referred to as being 'degradable', 'oxy-degradable' or 'UV-degradable'. This means that they break down when exposed to light or air, but these plastics are still primarily (as much as 98 per cent) [[oil]]-based and are not currently certified as 'biodegradable' under the [[European Union directive]] on Packaging and Packaging Waste (94/62/EC). Biopolymers will break down, and some are suitable for domestic [[composting]].&lt;ref name=&quot;nnfcc&quot;&gt;[http://www.nnfcc.co.uk/publications/nnfcc-renewable-polymers-factsheet-bioplastics NNFCC Renewable Polymers Factsheet: Bioplastics]&lt;/ref&gt;

Biopolymers (also called renewable polymers) are produced from [[biomass]] for use in the packaging industry. Biomass comes from crops such as sugar beet, potatoes or wheat: when used to produce biopolymers, these are classified as [[non food crops]]. These can be converted in the following pathways:

[[Sugar beet]] &amp;gt; Glyconic acid &amp;gt; Polyglyconic acid

[[Starch]] &amp;gt; (fermentation) &amp;gt; [[Lactic acid]] &amp;gt; [[Polylactic acid]] (PLA)

[[Biomass]] &amp;gt; (fermentation) &amp;gt; [[Bioethanol]] &amp;gt; [[Ethene]] &amp;gt; [[Polyethylene]]

Many types of packaging can be made from biopolymers: food trays, blown starch pellets for shipping fragile goods, thin films for wrapping.

===Environmental impacts===
Biopolymers can be sustainable, carbon neutral and are always [[renewable]], because they are made from plant materials which can be grown indefinitely. These plant materials come from agricultural [[non food crops]]. Therefore, the use of biopolymers would create a [[sustainable]] industry. In contrast, the feedstocks for polymers derived from petrochemicals will eventually deplete. In addition, biopolymers have the potential to cut [[carbon emissions]] and reduce CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; quantities in the atmosphere: this is because the CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; released when they degrade can be reabsorbed by crops grown to replace them: this makes them close to [[carbon neutral]].

Biopolymers are biodegradable, and some are also compostable. Some biopolymers are [[biodegradable]]: they are broken down into CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and water by [[microorganisms]]. Some of these biodegradable biopolymers are [[compostable]]: they can be put into an industrial composting process and will break down by 90% within six months. Biopolymers that do this can be marked with a 'compostable' symbol, under European Standard EN 13432 (2000). Packaging marked with this symbol can be put into industrial composting processes and will break down within six months or less. An example of a compostable polymer is PLA film under 20μm thick: films which are thicker than that do not qualify as compostable, even though they are &quot;biodegradable&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nnfcc.co.uk/publications/nnfcc-newsletter-issue-5-biopolymers-a-renewable-resource-for-the-plastics-industry NNFCC Newsletter – Issue 5. Biopolymers: A Renewable Resource for the Plastics Industry]&lt;/ref&gt; In Europe there is a home composting standard and associated logo that enables consumers to identify and dispose of packaging in their compost heap.&lt;ref name=&quot;nnfcc&quot; /&gt;

==See also==
* [[Biomaterial]]s
* [[Bioplastic]]
* ''[[Biopolymers &amp; Cell]]'' (journal)
* [[Condensation polymer]]s
* [[Condensed tannin]]s
* [[DNA sequence]]
* {{slink|Food microbiology|Microbial biopolymers}}
* [[Melanin]]
* [[Non food crops]]
* [[Phosphoramidite]]
* [[Polymer chemistry]]
* [[Sequence-controlled polymer]]s
* [[Sequencing]]
* [[Small molecule]]s
* [[Worm-like chain]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Commonscat|Biopolymers}}
*[http://www.nnfcc.co.uk/ NNFCC: The UK's National Centre for Biorenewable Energy, Fuels and Materials]
*[http://www.bioplasticsmagazine.com/ Bioplastics Magazine]
*[http://www.biopolymer.net/ Biopolymer group]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20081023075853/http://biopol.free.fr/ Bio-Polym Blog]
*[https://archive.is/20121209011537/http://boldlygo.org/blog/whats-stopping-bioplastic/ What’s Stopping Bioplastic?]

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Biomolecules]]
[[Category:Polymers]]
[[Category:Molecular biology]]
[[Category:Molecular genetics]]
[[Category:Biotechnology products]]
[[Category:Bioplastics]]
[[Category:Biomaterials]]</text>
      <sha1>lir74ed65jsh24wytcct5bvow6abinh</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
