  <page>
    <title>Benoit Mandelbrot</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3999</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943020230</id>
      <parentid>941772778</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-28T09:51:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Citation bot</username>
        <id>7903804</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Alter: author. Add: author-link. | You can [[WP:UCB|use this bot]] yourself. [[WP:DBUG|Report bugs here]]. | Activated by [[User:Andcentra]] | [[Category:Harvard University people]] | via #UCB_Category</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{See also|Mandelbrot set}}
{{Short description|French/American mathematician}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=February 2020}}
{{Infobox scientist
| name          = Benoit&lt;span style=&quot;font-size:80%;font-weight:normal&quot;&gt;&lt;!-- The following syntax required to permit nested refs: --&gt;&amp;#8201;{{#tag:ref|In his autobiography, Mandelbrot did not add a [[circumflex]] to the &quot;i&quot; (i.e. &quot;î&quot;) in his first name, as is usual for [[Benoît|the French given name]]. He included &quot;B&quot; as a [[middle initial]]. His ''New York Times'' obituary stated that &quot;he added the middle initial himself, though it does not stand for a middle name&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;nyt_obit&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2010/10/17/us/17mandelbrot.html |title=Benoît Mandelbrot, Mathematician, Dies at 85 |last=Hoffman |first=Jascha |date=16 October 2010 |work=The New York Times |accessdate=16 October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; an assertion that is supported by his obituary in ''The Guardian''.&lt;ref name=&quot;guardian_obit&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.theguardian.com/science/2010/oct/17/benoit-mandelbrot-obituary |title=Benoît Mandelbrot obituary |last=Lesmoir-Gordon |first=Nigel |date=17 October 2010 |work=[[The Guardian]] | accessdate=17 October 2010 |location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;|group=n|name=Mandelbrot's_name}}&lt;/span&gt; Mandelbrot
| image         = Benoit Mandelbrot, TED 2010.jpg
| caption       = Mandelbrot at a [[TED (conference)|TED conference]] in 2010 shortly before his death.
| birth_date    = {{birth date|1924|11|20|df=y}}
| birth_place   = [[Warsaw]], [[Second Polish Republic|Poland]] 
| death_date    = {{death date and age|2010|10|14|1924|11|20|df=y}} 
| death_place   = [[Cambridge, Massachusetts]], United States
| nationality   = {{hlist | Polish | French | American}}
| fields        = {{hlist | [[Mathematics]] | [[Aerodynamics]]}}
| alma_mater    = {{br list | [[École Polytechnique]] | {{nowrap|[[California Institute of Technology]]}} | [[University of Paris]]}}
| doctoral_students = {{hlist |class=nowraplinks |list_style=line-height:1.25em | [[Laurent-Emmanuel Calvet|L-E. Calvet]] | [[Eugene Fama]] | [[Ken Musgrave]] | [[Murad Taqqu]] &lt;!--Red link: | [[Daniel Zajdenweber]]--&gt;}}
| known_for     = {{hlist |class=nowraplinks |list_style=line-height:1.25em | [[Mandelbrot set]] | [[Chaos theory]] | [[Fractal]]s | [[Zipf–Mandelbrot law]]}}
| influences    = [[Johannes Kepler]], [[Szolem Mandelbrojt]]
| influenced    = [[Nassim Nicholas Taleb]]
| spouse        = {{longitem|Aliette Kagan&lt;br /&gt;{{smaller|married 1955–2010 (his death)}}}}
| work_institutions = {{hlist | [[Yale University]] | [[IBM]]}} {{longitem|[[Pacific Northwest National Laboratory]]}}
| prizes        = {{longitem|style=line-height:1.15em;white-space:nowrap |''[[Légion d'honneur]]''&lt;br /&gt;{{smaller|(''Chevalier'' 1990{{dot}}''Officier'' 2006)}}}} {{Br list | 2003 &amp;nbsp;[[Japan Prize]] | 1993 &amp;nbsp;[[Wolf Prize]] | 1989 &amp;nbsp;[[Harvey Prize]] | 1986 &amp;nbsp;[[Franklin Medal]] | 1985 &amp;nbsp;[[Barnard Medal for Meritorious Service to Science|Barnard Medal]]}}
}}

'''Benoit B.'''&amp;#8201;&lt;ref group=&quot;n&quot; name=&quot;Mandelbrot's_name&quot; /&gt; '''Mandelbrot'''&amp;#8201;{{#tag:ref|Pronounced {{IPAc-en|ˈ|m|æ|n|d|əl|b|r|ɒ|t}} {{respell|MAN|dəl-brot}} in English.&lt;ref&gt;{{OED|Mandelbrot}}&lt;/ref&gt; When speaking in French, Mandelbrot pronounced his name {{IPA-fr|bənwa mɑ̃dɛlbʁot|}}.&lt;ref&gt;Recording of the ceremony on 11 September 2006 at which Mandelbrot received the insignia for an Officer of the ''[[Legion of Honour|Légion d'honneur]]''.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=n}} (20 November 1924&amp;nbsp;– 14 October 2010) was a Polish-born, French and American [[mathematician]] and [[polymath]] with broad interests in the practical sciences, especially regarding what he labeled as &quot;the art of [[Benoit Mandelbrot#Fractals and the .22theory of roughness.22|roughness]]&quot; of physical phenomena and &quot;the uncontrolled element in life&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.insidescience.org/news/remembering-father-fractals&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.ted.com/talks/benoit_mandelbrot_fractals_the_art_of_roughness?language=en Benoit Mandelbrot: Fractals and the art of roughness]. ted.com (February 2010)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Hudson|Hudson &amp; Mandelbrot]], Prelude, page xviii&lt;/ref&gt; He referred to himself as a &quot;fractalist&quot;&lt;ref name=Mandelbrot/&gt; and is recognized for his contribution to the field of [[fractal geometry]], which included coining the word &quot;fractal&quot;, as well as developing a theory of &quot;roughness and [[self-similarity]]&quot; in nature.&lt;ref name=nature&gt;{{Cite journal 
| last1 = Gomory | first1 = R. 
| authorlink1 = Ralph E. Gomory
| title = Benoît Mandelbrot (1924–2010) 
| doi = 10.1038/468378a 
| journal = Nature 
| volume = 468 
| issue = 7322 
| pages = 378 
| year = 2010 
| pmid =  21085164
|bibcode = 2010Natur.468..378G }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1936, while he was a child, Mandelbrot's family emigrated to France from [[Warsaw]], Poland. After [[World War II]] ended, Mandelbrot studied mathematics, graduating from universities in Paris and the United States and receiving a master's degree in [[aeronautics]] from the [[California Institute of Technology]]. He spent most of his career in both the United States and France, having [[Multiple citizenship|dual]] [[French nationality law|French]] and [[United States nationality law#Dual citizenship|American]] citizenship. In 1958, he began a 35-year career at [[IBM]], where he became an [[IBM Fellow]], and periodically took leaves of absence to teach at [[Harvard University]].  At Harvard, following the publication of his study of U.S. commodity markets in relation to cotton futures, he taught economics and applied sciences.

Because of his access to IBM's computers, Mandelbrot was one of the first to use computer graphics to create and display fractal geometric images, leading to his discovery of the [[Mandelbrot set]] in 1980. He showed how visual complexity can be created from simple rules. He said that things typically considered to be &quot;rough&quot;, a &quot;mess&quot; or &quot;chaotic&quot;, like clouds or shorelines, actually had a &quot;degree of order&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wolfram&quot; /&gt; His math and geometry-centered research career included contributions to such fields as [[statistical physics]], [[meteorology]], [[hydrology]], [[geomorphology]], [[anatomy]], [[taxonomy (biology)|taxonomy]], [[neurology]], [[linguistics]], [[information technology]], [[computer graphics]], [[economics]], [[geology]], [[medicine]], [[physical cosmology]], [[engineering]], [[chaos theory]], [[econophysics]], [[metallurgy]] and the [[social science]]s.&lt;ref&gt;list includes specific sciences mentioned in [[#Hudson|Hudson &amp; Mandelbrot]], the Prelude, p.&amp;nbsp;xvi, and p.&amp;nbsp;26&lt;/ref&gt;

Toward the end of his career, he was [[Sterling Professor]] of Mathematical Sciences at [[Yale University]], where he was the oldest professor in Yale's history to receive tenure.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Steve Olson | url=http://archives.yalealumnimagazine.com/issues/2004_11/mandelbrot.html |title=The Genius of the Unpredictable |publisher=Yale Alumni Magazine |date=November–December 2004 |accessdate=22 July 2014| author-link=Steve Olson (writer) }}&lt;/ref&gt; Mandelbrot also held positions at the [[Pacific Northwest National Laboratory]], [[Université Lille Nord de France]], [[Institute for Advanced Study]] and [[Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique]]. During his career, he received over 15 honorary doctorates and served on many science journals, along with winning numerous awards. His autobiography, ''The Fractalist:  Memoir of a Scientific Maverick'', was published posthumously in 2012.

== Early years ==
Mandelbrot was born in a [[Jews|Jewish]] family, in [[Warsaw]] during the [[Second Polish Republic]]. His father made his living trading clothing; his mother was a dental surgeon. During his first two school years, he was tutored privately by an uncle who despised rote learning: &quot;Most of my time was spent playing chess, reading maps and learning how to open my eyes to everything around me.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;wolf&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last=Mandelbrot |first=Benoît |title=The Wolf Prizes for Physics, ''A Maverick's Apprenticeship''|publisher=Imperial College Press |year=2002 |url=http://users.math.yale.edu/~bbm3/web_pdfs/mavericksApprenticeship.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; Later, the family's move to France, the [[World War II|war]], and his acquaintance with his father's brother, the mathematician [[Szolem Mandelbrojt]] who had moved to Paris around 1920, further prevented a standard education.

The family emigrated from Poland to France in 1936, when he was 11. &quot;The fact that my parents, as economic and political refugees, joined Szolem in France saved our lives,&quot; he writes.&lt;ref name=Mandelbrot /&gt;{{rp|17}}&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc_obit&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-11560101|title=BBC News&amp;nbsp;– 'Fractal' mathematician Benoît Mandelbrot dies aged 85|date=17 October 2010|work=[[BBC Online]] | accessdate=17 October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Mandelbrot attended the Lycée Rolin in Paris until the start of [[World War II]], when his family moved to [[Tulle]], France. He was helped by [[Rabbi]] [[David Feuerwerker]], the Rabbi of [[Brive-la-Gaillarde]], to continue his studies.&lt;ref name=Mandelbrot/&gt;{{rp|62–63}}&lt;ref&gt;Hemenway P. (2005) ''Divine proportion: Phi in art, nature and science''. Psychology Press. {{isbn|0-415-34495-6}}&lt;/ref&gt; Much of France was occupied by the Nazis at the time, and Mandelbrot recalls this period:

{{quote|Our constant fear was that a sufficiently determined foe might report us to an authority and we would be sent to our deaths. This happened to a close friend from Paris, Zina Morhange, a physician in a nearby county seat. Simply to eliminate the competition, another physician denounced her&amp;nbsp;... We escaped this fate. Who knows why?&lt;ref name=Mandelbrot /&gt;{{rp|49}}}}

In 1944, Mandelbrot returned to Paris, studied at the [[Lycée du Parc]] in [[Lyon]], and in 1945 to 1947 attended the [[École Polytechnique]], where he studied under [[Gaston Julia]] and [[Paul Lévy (mathematician)|Paul Lévy]]. From 1947 to 1949 he studied at California Institute of Technology, where he earned a master's degree in aeronautics.&lt;ref name=&quot;guardian_obit&quot; /&gt; Returning to France, he obtained his [[Doctor of Philosophy|PhD degree]] in Mathematical Sciences at the [[University of Paris]] in 1952.&lt;ref name=&quot;wolf&quot; /&gt;

==Research career==
From 1949 to 1958, Mandelbrot was a staff member at the [[Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique]]. During this time he spent a year at the [[Institute for Advanced Study]] in [[Princeton, New Jersey]], where he was sponsored by [[John von Neumann]]. In 1955 he married Aliette Kagan and moved to [[Geneva, Switzerland]] (to collaborate with [[Jean Piaget]] at the International Centre for Genetic Epistemology) and later to the [[Université Lille Nord de France]].&lt;ref name=&quot;people&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Barcellos|first=Anthony|title=Mathematical People, ''Interview of B. B. Mandelbrot''|publisher=Birkhaüser|year=1984|url=http://users.math.yale.edu/~bbm3/web_pdfs/inHisOwnWords.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1958 the couple moved to the United States where Mandelbrot joined the research staff at the [[International Business Machines|IBM]] [[Thomas J. Watson Research Center]] in [[Yorktown Heights, New York]].&lt;ref name=&quot;people&quot; /&gt; He remained at IBM for 35 years, becoming an IBM Fellow, and later Fellow [[Emeritus]].&lt;ref name=&quot;wolf&quot; /&gt;

&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:Mandelbrot-IBM.jpg|thumb|left|Mandelbrot working at IBM]] --&gt;
From 1951 onward, Mandelbrot worked on problems and published papers not only in mathematics but in applied fields such as [[information theory]], economics, and [[fluid dynamics]].

===Randomness in financial markets===

Mandelbrot saw [[financial market]]s as an example of &quot;wild randomness&quot;, characterized by concentration and long range dependence. He developed several original approaches for modelling financial fluctuations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author= Rama Cont |title= Mandelbrot, Benoit |journal= Encyclopedia of Quantitative Finance |publisher= Wiley |date= 19 April 2010 |doi= 10.1002/9780470061602.eqf01006 |isbn = 9780470057568|author-link= Rama Cont }}&lt;/ref&gt;
In his early work, he found that the price changes in [[financial market]]s did not follow a [[Gaussian distribution]], but rather [[Paul Lévy (mathematician)|Lévy]] [[stable distributions]] having infinite [[variance]]. He found, for example, that cotton prices followed a Lévy stable distribution with parameter ''α'' equal to 1.7 rather than 2 as in a Gaussian distribution. &quot;Stable&quot; distributions have the property that the sum of many instances of a random variable follows the same distribution but with a larger [[scale parameter]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.newscientist.com/article/mg15420784.700-flight-over-wall-st.html |title=''New Scientist'', 19 April 1997 |publisher=Newscientist.com |date=19 April 1997 |accessdate=17 October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Developing &quot;fractal geometry&quot; and the Mandelbrot set===

As a visiting professor at [[Harvard University]], Mandelbrot began to study fractals called [[Julia set]]s that were invariant under certain transformations of the [[complex plane]]. Building on previous work by [[Gaston Julia]] and [[Pierre Fatou]], Mandelbrot used a computer to plot images of the Julia sets. While investigating the topology of these Julia sets, he studied the [[Mandelbrot set]] which was introduced by him in 1979. In 1982, Mandelbrot expanded and updated his ideas in ''[[The Fractal Geometry of Nature]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=xJ4qiEBNP4gC&amp;printsec=frontcover ''The Fractal Geometry of Nature''], by Benoît Mandelbrot; W H Freeman &amp; Co, 1982; {{isbn|0-7167-1186-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; This influential work brought fractals into the mainstream of professional and popular mathematics, as well as silencing critics, who had dismissed fractals as &quot;[[Artifact (observational)|program artifacts]]&quot;.

[[File:Mandelbrot p1130876.jpg|thumb|right|Mandelbrot speaking about the [[Mandelbrot set]], during his acceptance speech for the [[Légion d'honneur]] in 2006]]

In 1975, Mandelbrot coined the term ''[[fractal]]'' to describe these structures and first published his ideas, and later translated, ''Fractals: Form, Chance and Dimension''.&lt;ref&gt;''Fractals: Form, Chance and Dimension'', by Benoît Mandelbrot; W H Freeman and Co, 1977; {{isbn|0-7167-0473-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to computer scientist and physicist [[Stephen Wolfram]], the book was a &quot;breakthrough&quot; for Mandelbrot, who until then would typically &quot;apply fairly straightforward mathematics … to areas that had barely seen the light of serious mathematics before&quot;.&lt;ref name=Wolfram&gt;Wolfram, Stephen. [https://www.wsj.com/articles/SB10001424127887324439804578107271772910506 &quot;The Father of Fractals&quot;], ''Wall Street Journal'', 22 November 2012&lt;/ref&gt; Wolfram adds that as a result of this new research, he was no longer a &quot;wandering scientist&quot;, and later called him &quot;the father of fractals&quot;:

{{quote|Mandelbrot ended up doing a great piece of science and identifying a much stronger and more fundamental idea—put simply, that there are some geometric shapes, which he called &quot;fractals&quot;, that are equally &quot;rough&quot; at all scales. No matter how close you look, they never get simpler, much as the section of a rocky coastline you can see at your feet looks just as jagged as the stretch you can see from space.&lt;ref name=Wolfram /&gt;}}

Wolfram briefly describes fractals as a form of geometric repetition, &quot;in which smaller and smaller copies of a pattern are successively nested inside each other, so that the same intricate shapes appear no matter how much you zoom in to the whole. Fern leaves and Romanesco broccoli are two examples from nature.&quot;&lt;ref name=Wolfram /&gt; He points out an unexpected conclusion:

{{quote|One might have thought that such a simple and fundamental form of regularity would have been studied for hundreds, if not thousands, of years. But it was not. In fact, it rose to prominence only over the past 30 or so years—almost entirely through the efforts of one man, the mathematician Benoit Mandelbrot.&lt;ref name=Wolfram /&gt;}}

Mandelbrot used the term &quot;fractal&quot; as it derived from the Latin word &quot;fractus&quot;, defined as broken or shattered glass. Using the newly developed IBM computers at his disposal, Mandelbrot was able to create fractal images using graphic computer code, images that an interviewer described as looking like &quot;the delirious exuberance of the 1960s [[psychedelic art]] with forms hauntingly reminiscent of nature and the human body&quot;. He also saw himself as a &quot;would-be Kepler&quot;, after the 17th-century scientist [[Johannes Kepler]], who calculated and described the orbits of the planets.&lt;ref&gt;Ivry, Benjamin. [http://forward.com/articles/166094/benoit-mandelbrot-influenced-art-and-mathematics/?p=all &quot;Benoit Mandelbrot Influenced Art and Mathematics&quot;], ''Forward'', 17 November 2012&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Newton-lplane-Mandelbrot.jpg|thumb|A Mandelbrot set]]
Mandelbrot, however, never felt he was inventing a new idea. He describes his feelings in a documentary with science writer Arthur C. Clarke:

{{quote|Exploring this set I certainly never had the feeling of invention. I never had the feeling that my imagination was rich enough to invent all those extraordinary things on discovering them. They were there, even though nobody had seen them before. It's marvelous, a very simple formula explains all these very complicated things. So the goal of science is starting with a mess, and explaining it with a simple formula, a kind of dream of science.&lt;ref name=Clarke&gt;[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Lk6QU94xAb8 &quot;Arthur C Clarke – Fractals – The Colors Of Infinity&quot;], video interviews, 54 min.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

According to Clarke, &quot;the [[Mandelbrot set]] is indeed one of the most astonishing discoveries in the entire history of mathematics. Who could have dreamed that such an incredibly simple equation could have generated images of literally ''infinite'' complexity?&quot; Clarke also notes an &quot;odd coincidence&lt;blockquote&gt;the name Mandelbrot, and the word &quot;[[mandala]]&quot;—for a religious symbol—which I'm sure is a pure coincidence, but indeed the Mandelbrot set does seem to contain an enormous number of mandalas.&lt;ref name=Clarke /&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Mandelbrot left IBM in 1987, after 35 years and 12 days, when IBM decided to end pure research in his division.&lt;ref name=&quot;wos44&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.webofstories.com/play/10483|title=Web of Stories • Benoît Mandelbrot • IBM: background and policies|last=Mandelbrot|first=Benoît|author2=Bernard Sapoval|author3=Daniel Zajdenweber|date=May 1998|publisher=[[Web of Stories]] | accessdate=17 October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; He joined the Department of Mathematics at [[Yale]], and obtained his first [[tenure]]d post in 1999, at the age of 75.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tenner&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2010/10/benoit-mandelbrot-the-maverick-1924-2010/64684/|title=Benoît Mandelbrot the Maverick, 1924–2010|last=Tenner|first=Edward|date=16 October 2010|work=[[The Atlantic]] | accessdate=16 October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the time of his retirement in 2005, he was Sterling Professor of Mathematical Sciences.

===Fractals and the &quot;theory of roughness&quot;===
Mandelbrot created the first-ever &quot;theory of roughness&quot;, and he saw &quot;roughness&quot; in the shapes of mountains, [[coastline]]s and [[river basin]]s; the structures of plants, [[blood vessel]]s and [[lung]]s; the clustering of [[galaxy|galaxies]]. His personal quest was to create some mathematical formula to measure the overall &quot;roughness&quot; of such objects in nature.&lt;ref name=Mandelbrot /&gt;{{rp|xi}} He began by asking himself various kinds of questions related to nature:
{{quote|Can [[geometry]] deliver what the Greek root of its name [geo-] seemed to promise—truthful measurement, not only of cultivated fields along the Nile River but also of untamed Earth?&lt;ref name=Mandelbrot&gt;Mandelbrot, Benoit (2012). ''The Fractalist: Memoir of a Scientific Maverick'', Pantheon Books. {{isbn|978-0-307-38991-6}}.&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|xii}}}}

In his paper titled [[How Long Is the Coast of Britain? Statistical Self-Similarity and Fractional Dimension]] published in [[Science (journal)|''Science'']] in 1967 Mandelbrot discusses [[self-similarity|self-similar]] curves that have [[Hausdorff dimension]] that are examples of ''fractals'', although Mandelbrot does not use this term in the paper, as he did not coin it until 1975. The paper is one of Mandelbrot's first publications on the topic of fractals.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Dr. Mandelbrot traced his work on fractals to a question he first encountered as a young researcher: how long is the coast of Britain?&quot;: Benoit Mandelbrot (1967). &quot;[https://www.nytimes.com/2010/10/17/us/17mandelbrot.html?adxnnl=1&amp;adxnnlx=1332064840-/vD0Sjafcl9t9BNghRf8Qw Benoît Mandelbrot, Novel Mathematician, Dies at 85]&quot;, ''The New York Times''.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Mandelbrot_Science_1967&quot;&gt;{{cite journal| title=How long is the coast of Britain? Statistical self-similarity and fractional dimension | journal=Science | date=5 May 1967 | author=Mandelbrot, Benoit B. | pages=636–638 | volume=156 | issue=3775 |doi=10.1126/science.156.3775.636 | pmid=17837158|url=http://users.math.yale.edu/~bbm3/web_pdfs/howLongIsTheCoastOfBritain.pdf | bibcode=1967Sci...156..636M }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Mandelbrot emphasized the use of fractals as realistic and useful models for describing many &quot;rough&quot; phenomena in the real world. He concluded that &quot;real roughness is often fractal and can be measured.&quot;&lt;ref name=Mandelbrot /&gt;{{rp|296}} Although Mandelbrot coined the term &quot;fractal&quot;, some of the mathematical objects he presented in ''[[The Fractal Geometry of Nature]]'' had been previously described by other mathematicians. Before Mandelbrot, however, they were regarded as isolated curiosities with unnatural and non-intuitive properties. Mandelbrot brought these objects together for the first time and turned them into essential tools for the long-stalled effort to extend the scope of science to explaining non-smooth, &quot;rough&quot; objects in the real world. His methods of research were both old and new:
{{quote|The form of geometry I increasingly favored is the oldest, most concrete, and most inclusive, specifically empowered by the eye and helped by the hand and, today, also by the computer … bringing an element of unity to the worlds of knowing and feeling … and, unwittingly, as a bonus, for the purpose of creating beauty.&lt;ref name=Mandelbrot /&gt;{{rp|292}}}}

Fractals are also found in human pursuits, such as music, painting, architecture, and [[stock market]] prices. Mandelbrot believed that fractals, far from being unnatural, were in many ways more intuitive and natural than the artificially smooth objects of traditional [[Euclidean geometry]]: &lt;blockquote&gt;Clouds are not spheres, mountains are not cones, coastlines are not circles, and bark is not smooth, nor does lightning travel in a straight line.&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;—Mandelbrot, in his introduction to ''[[The Fractal Geometry of Nature]]''&lt;/blockquote&gt;
[[File:Mandel zoom 08 satellite antenna.jpg|thumb|right|Section of a Mandelbrot set]]

Mandelbrot has been called a work of art, and a visionary&lt;ref name=&quot;RLD&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=Devaney, Robert L.|authorlink= Robert L. Devaney |title=&quot;Mandelbrot's Vision for Mathematics&quot; in ''Proceedings of Symposia in Pure Mathematics''. Volume 72.1 |publisher=American Mathematical Society |year=2004 |url=http://www.math.yale.edu/mandelbrot/web_pdfs/jubileeletters.pdf |access-date=5 January 2007 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20061209093734/http://www.math.yale.edu/mandelbrot/web_pdfs/jubileeletters.pdf |archive-date=9 December 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and a maverick.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.pbs.org/wgbh/nova/fractals/mandelbrot.html|title=A Radical Mind|last=Jersey|first=Bill|date=24 April 2005|work=Hunting the Hidden Dimension|publisher=NOVA/ PBS|accessdate=20 August 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; His informal and passionate style of writing and his emphasis on visual and geometric intuition (supported by the inclusion of numerous illustrations) made ''The Fractal Geometry of Nature'' accessible to non-specialists. The book sparked widespread popular interest in fractals and contributed to chaos theory and other fields of science and mathematics.

Mandelbrot also put his ideas to work in cosmology. He offered in 1974 a new explanation of [[Olbers' paradox]] (the &quot;dark night sky&quot; riddle), demonstrating the consequences of fractal theory as a [[Necessity and sufficiency|sufficient, but not necessary]], resolution of the paradox. He postulated that if the [[star]]s in the universe were fractally distributed (for example, like [[Cantor dust]]), it would not be necessary to rely on the [[Big Bang]] theory to explain the paradox. His model would not rule out a Big Bang, but would allow for a dark sky even if the Big Bang had not occurred.&lt;ref&gt;''Galaxy Map Hints at Fractal Universe'', by Amanda Gefter; New Scientist; 25 June 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

==Awards and honors==
Mandelbrot's awards include the [[Wolf Prize]] for Physics in 1993, the [[Lewis Fry Richardson]] Prize of the [[European Geophysical Society]] in 2000, the [[Japan Prize]] in 2003,&lt;ref name=jp&gt;[http://www.japanprize.jp/en/laureates_by_year2000.html Laureates of the Japan Prize]. japanprize.jp&lt;/ref&gt; and the Einstein Lectureship of the [[American Mathematical Society]] in 2006.

The small asteroid [[27500 Mandelbrot]] was named in his honor. In November 1990, he was made a Chevalier in France's [[Legion of Honour]]. In December 2005, Mandelbrot was appointed to the position of Battelle Fellow at the [[Pacific Northwest National Laboratory]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pnl.gov/news/release.asp?id=141 |title=PNNL press release: Mandelbrot joins Pacific Northwest National Laboratory |publisher=Pnl.gov |date=16 February 2006 |accessdate=17 October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Mandelbrot was promoted to an Officer of the Legion of Honour in January 2006.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.legifrance.gouv.fr/WAspad/UnTexteDeJorf?numjo=PREX0508911D |title=''Légion d'honneur'' announcement of promotion of Mandelbrot to ''officier'' |language=fr |publisher=Legifrance.gouv.fr |accessdate=17 October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; An honorary degree from [[Johns Hopkins University]] was bestowed on Mandelbrot in the May 2010 commencement exercises.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://gazette.jhu.edu/2010/06/07/six-granted-honorary-degrees-society-of-scholars-inductees-recognized-2/ |title=Six granted honorary degrees, Society of Scholars inductees recognized |publisher=Gazette.jhu.edu |date=7 June 2010 |accessdate=17 October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A partial list of awards received by Mandelbrot:&lt;ref name=&quot;Vita&quot;&gt;{{cite web | author=Mandelbrot, Benoit B. | title=Vita and Awards (Word document) | date=2 February 2006 | url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070601000000*/http://math.yale.edu/mandelbrot/web_docs/VitaSeveralPage.doc | accessdate=6 January 2007}} Retrieved from Internet Archive 15 December 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;
{{div col|colwidth=25em}}
* 2004 Best Business Book of the Year Award
* AMS Einstein Lectureship
* Barnard Medal
* Caltech Service
* [[Casimir Funk]] Natural Sciences Award
* [[Charles Proteus Steinmetz]] Medal
* Fellow, American Geophysical Union
* [[Fellow of the American Statistical Association]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.amstat.org/awards/fellowslist.cfm View/Search Fellows of the ASA], accessed 20 August 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[The Franklin Institute Awards|Franklin Medal]]
* [[Harvey Prize]] (1989)
* Honda Prize
* Humboldt Preis
* IBM Fellowship
* Japan Prize (2003)
* [[John Scott Award]]
* Légion d'honneur ([[Legion of Honour]])
* Lewis Fry Richardson Medal
* Medaglia della Presidenza della Repubblica Italiana
* Médaille de Vermeil de la Ville de Paris
* Nevada Prize
* Member of the [[Norwegian Academy of Science and Letters]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dnva.no/c26849/artikkel/vis.html?tid=40116|title=Gruppe 1: Matematiske fag|publisher=[[Norwegian Academy of Science and Letters]] | language=Norwegian|accessdate=7 October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Science for Art
* Sven Berggren-Priset
* Władysław Orlicz Prize
* [[Wolf Foundation Prize]] for Physics (1993)
{{div col end}}

== Legacy ==
Mandelbrot died from [[pancreatic cancer]] at the age of 85 in a [[hospice]] in [[Cambridge, Massachusetts]] on 14 October 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;nyt_obit&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Benoît Mandelbrot, fractals pioneer, dies |url=http://www.upi.com/Science_News/2010/10/16/Benoit-Mandelbrot-fractals-pioneer-dies/UPI-11551287266964/ |accessdate=17 October 2010 |newspaper=United Press International |date=16 October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Reacting to news of his death, mathematician [[Heinz-Otto Peitgen]] said: &quot;[I]f we talk about impact inside mathematics, and applications in the sciences, he is one of the most important figures of the last fifty years.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;nyt_obit&quot; /&gt;

[[Chris Anderson (entrepreneur)|Chris Anderson]], [[TED (conference)|TED conference]] curator, described Mandelbrot as &quot;an icon who changed how we see the world&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://montrealgazette.com/technology/Mandelbrot+father+fractal+geometry+dies/3682961/story.html |title=Mandelbrot, father of fractal geometry, dies |work=[[The Gazette (Montreal)|The Gazette]] |access-date=16 October 2010 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20101019233754/http://www.montrealgazette.com/technology/Mandelbrot%2Bfather%2Bfractal%2Bgeometry%2Bdies/3682961/story.html |archive-date=19 October 2010  }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Nicolas Sarkozy]], [[President of France]] at the time of Mandelbrot's death, said Mandelbrot had &quot;a powerful, original mind that never shied away from innovating and shattering preconceived notions&amp;nbsp;[… h]is work, developed entirely outside mainstream research, led to modern information theory.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.lefigaro.fr/flash-actu/2010/10/16/97001-20101016FILWWW00611-sarkozy-rend-hommage-a-mandelbrot.php |title=Sarkozy rend hommage à Mandelbrot |language=French |trans-title=Sarkozy pays homage to Mandelbrot |work=[[Le Figaro]] | accessdate=17 October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Mandelbrot's obituary in ''The Economist'' points out his fame as &quot;celebrity beyond the academy&quot; and lauds him as the &quot;father of fractal geometry&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.economist.com/node/17305197 Benoît Mandelbrot's obituary]. ''The Economist'' (21 October 2010)&lt;/ref&gt;

Best-selling essayist-author [[Nassim Nicholas Taleb]] has remarked that Mandelbrot's book ''The (Mis)Behavior of Markets'' is in his opinion &quot;The deepest and most realistic finance book ever published&quot;.&lt;ref name=nature/&gt;

==Bibliography==
===in English===

*[[Fractals: Form, Chance and Dimension]], 1977
* [[The Fractal Geometry of Nature]], 1982
* [[Fractals and Scaling in Finance: Discontinuity, Concentration, Risk. Selecta Volume E]], 1997 by Benoit B. Mandelbrot and [[R.E. Gomory]]
* [[Fractales, hasard et finance, 1959-1997]], 1 November 1998
* [[Multifractals and 1/ƒ Noise: Wild Self-Affinity in Physics (1963–1976)]] (Selecta; V.N) 18 January 1999 by [[J.M. Berger]] and Benoit B. Mandelbrot
* [[Gaussian Self-Affinity and Fractals: Globality, The Earth, 1/f Noise, and R/S (Selected Works of Benoit B. Mandelbrot)]] 14 December 2001 by Benoit Mandelbrot and F.J. Damerau
* [[Fractals and Chaos: The Mandelbrot Set and Beyond]], 9 January 2004
* [[The Misbehavior of Markets: A Fractal View of Financial Turbulence]], 2006 by Benoit Mandelbrot and [[Richard L. Hudson]]
* [[The Fractalist: Memoir of a Scientific Maverick]], 2014

===In French===
* [[La forme d'une vie. Mémoires (1924-2010)]] by Benoît Mandelbrot (Author), Johan-Frédérik Hel Guedj (Translator)

==References in popular culture==
* In 2004, the American singer-songwriter [[Jonathan Coulton]] wrote &quot;Mandelbrot Set&quot;. Formerly, it contained the lines &quot;Mandelbrot’s in heaven / at least he will be when he’s dead / right now he’s still alive and teaching math at Yale&quot;. Live performances after Mandelbrot's passing in 2010 feature only the first line and a brief rock instrumental. 
* In 2007, the author [[Laura Ruby]] published &quot;The Chaos King,&quot; which includes a character named Mandelbrot and discussion of chaos theory.
* In 2017, [[Zach Weinersmith]]' webcomic, [[Saturday Morning Breakfast Cereal]], portrayed Mandelbrot.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=http://www.smbc-comics.com/comic/mandelbrot | title=Saturday Morning Breakfast Cereal – Mandelbrot}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In 2017, Liz Ziemska published a novella, Mandelbrot The Magnificent, a fictional account of how Mandelbrot saved his family during WWII

== See also ==
{{External media |align=right | width=210px |headerimage=[[File:Mandelbrot p1130861.jpg|210px]] | video1=[http://www.webofstories.com/play/benoit.mandelbrot/1;jsessionid=E8EB8E149375B3987E49D5E4F02FCB57 Family background and early education], (4:11) Benoit Mandelbrot interview, Part 1 of 144, [[Web of Stories]]&lt;ref name=&quot;wos1&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.webofstories.com/play/9596 |title=Web of Stories – Benoît Mandelbrot – Family background and early education |last=Mandelbrot |first=Benoît |author2=Bernard Sapoval |author3=Daniel Zajdenweber |date=May 1998 |publisher=[[Web of Stories]] | accessdate=19 October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
{|
|- style=&quot;vertical-align:top&quot;
| style=&quot;padding-right:2em&quot;|
* &quot;[[How Long Is the Coast of Britain? Statistical Self-Similarity and Fractional Dimension|How Long is the Coast of Britain?]]&quot;
* [[Louis Bachelier]]
* [[Zipf–Mandelbrot law]]
* [[Seven states of randomness]]
* [[Skewness risk]]
* [[Kurtosis risk]]
* [[Fractal dimension]]
* [[Lacunarity]]
|
* [[Self-similarity]]
* [[Self-affinity]]
* [[Hurst exponent]]
* [[Fractional Brownian motion]]
* [[Multifractal system]]
* [[1/f noise]]
* [[Mandelbrot Competition]]
|}

== Notes ==
{{Reflist|group=n|colwidth=50em}}

== References ==
{{Reflist|25em}}

==Bibliography==
* {{cite book |ref=Hudson|last1=Hudson |first1=Richard L. |last2=Mandelbrot |first2=Benoît B. |title=The (Mis)Behavior of Markets: A Fractal View of Risk, Ruin, and Reward |url=https://archive.org/details/misbehaviorofmar00beno|url-access=registration|year=2004 |publisher=Basic Books |location=New York |isbn=978-0-465-04355-2}}

== Further reading ==
* Mandelbrot, Benoit B. (2010). [https://www.amazon.com/Fractalist-Memoir-Scientific-Maverick/dp/030738991X ''The Fractalist, Memoir of a Scientific Maverick.'']  New York: [http://www.randomhouse.com/highschool/catalog/display.pperl?isbn=9780307389916&amp;view=email_prep Vintage Books], Division of Random House. {{isbn|978-0-307-38991-6}}
* {{cite book |last1=Mandelbrot |first1=Benoît B. |title=The Fractal Geometry of Nature | year=1983 |publisher=W.H. Freeman |location=San Francisco |isbn=978-0-7167-1186-5|title-link=The Fractal Geometry of Nature }}
* [[Heinz-Otto Peitgen]], [[Hartmut Jürgens]], [[Dietmar Saupe]] and Cornelia Zahlten: ''Fractals: An Animated Discussion'' (63 min video film, interviews with Benoît Mandelbrot and Edward Lorenz, computer animations), W.H. Freeman and Company, 1990. {{isbn|0-7167-2213-5}} (re-published by Films for the Humanities &amp; Sciences, {{isbn|978-0-7365-0520-8}})
* Mandelbrot, Benoit B. (1997) ''Fractals and Scaling in Finance: Discontinuity, Concentration, Risk'', Springer.
* {{cite journal |last=Mandelbrot |first=Benoît |date=February 1999 |title=A Multifractal Walk down Wall Street |journal=[[Scientific American]] | bibcode=1999SciAm.280b..70M |volume=280 |page=70 |doi=10.1038/scientificamerican0299-70 |issue=2}}
* Mandelbrot, Benoit B., ''Gaussian Self-Affinity and Fractals'', Springer: 2002.
* {{cite news |url=http://www.ft.com/cms/s/2/5372968a-ba82-11da-980d-0000779e2340,dwp_uuid=77a9a0e8-b442-11da-bd61-0000779e2340.html |title=A focus on the exceptions that prove the rule |last1=Mandelbrot |first1=Benoît |first2=Nassim |last2=Taleb |date=23 March 2006 |work=[[Financial Times]] |access-date=17 October 2010 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20101023201028/http://www.ft.com/cms/s/2/5372968a-ba82-11da-980d-0000779e2340,dwp_uuid=77a9a0e8-b442-11da-bd61-0000779e2340.html |archive-date=23 October 2010  }}
* [https://www.pbs.org/wgbh/nova/fractals/ &quot;Hunting the Hidden Dimension: mysteriously beautiful fractals are shaking up the world of mathematics and deepening our understanding of nature&quot;], ''[[Nova (American TV series)|NOVA]]'', WGBH Educational Foundation, Boston for PBS, first aired 28 October 2008.
* {{cite book |last1=Frame |first1=Michael |last2=Cohen |first2=Nathan |title=Benoit Mandelbrot: A Life in Many Dimensions |year=2015 |publisher=World Scientific Publishing Company |location=Singapore |isbn=978-981-4366-06-9 }}
* Mandelbrot, B. (1959) Variables et processus stochastiques de Pareto-Levy, et la repartition des revenus. Comptes rendus de l'Académie des Sciences de Paris, 249, 613–615.
* Mandelbrot, B. (1960) The Pareto-Levy law and the distribution of income. International Economic Review, 1, 79–106.
* Mandelbrot, B. (1961) Stable Paretian random functions and the multiplicative variation of income. Econometrica, 29, 517–543.
* Mandelbrot, B. (1964) Random walks, fire damage amount and other Paretian risk phenomena. Operations Research, 12, 582–585.

== External links ==
{{Commons|Benoît Mandelbrot}}
{{Wikiquote}}
* {{MathGenealogy|id=60791}}
* [http://users.math.yale.edu/mandelbrot/ Mandelbrot's page at Yale]
* [http://www.ted.com/talks/benoit_mandelbrot_fractals_the_art_of_roughness.html &quot;Benoît Mandelbrot: Fractals and the art of roughness&quot;] (TED address).
* [http://video.mit.edu/watch/fractals-in-science-engineering-and-finance-roughness-and-beauty-9893/ Fractals in Science, Engineering and Finance] (lecture).
* [http://video.ft.com/v/63078298001/Why-efficient-markets-collapse-Mandelbrot FT.com interview] on the subject of the financial markets which includes his critique of the &quot;efficient market&quot; hypothesis.
* {{cite journal |journal=[[Physics Today]] |year=2011 |title=Obituaries: Benoit Mandelbrot |first1=Richard |last1=Taylor |volume=64 |issue=6 |url=http://ptonline.aip.org/journals/doc/PHTOAD-ft/vol_64/iss_6/63_1.shtml?type=PTALERT |doi=10.1063/1.3603925 |page=63 |bibcode=2011PhT....64f..63T }}{{dead link|date=December 2017 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}
* [http://www.webofstories.com/people/benoit.mandelbrot/1 Mandelbrot relates his life story] ([[Web of Stories]]).
* [http://dynkincollection.library.cornell.edu/biographies/882 Interview (1 January 1981, Ithaca, NY)] held by the [[Eugene Dynkin]] Collection of Mathematics Interviews, [[Cornell University Library]].
* [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1o5FMTHkLQg Video animation of Mandelbrot set], zoom factor 10&lt;sup&gt;342&lt;/sup&gt;.
* {{YouTube|82xDvdgrzx0|Video animation of Mandelbulb}}, a three-dimensional Mandelbrot-set projection.
* {{YouTube|VB-XUoDqYfs|Video fly-through an animated Mandelbulb world}}
* {{IMDb name|541707}}
* {{TED speaker}}

{{Wolf Prize in Physics}}
{{Chaos theory}}
{{Fractals}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Mandelbrot, Benoit}}
[[Category:1924 births]]
[[Category:2010 deaths]]
[[Category:Jewish French scientists]]
[[Category:20th-century mathematicians]]
[[Category:21st-century mathematicians]]
[[Category:20th-century American economists]]
[[Category:21st-century American economists]]
[[Category:American people of Polish-Jewish descent]]
[[Category:Alexander von Humboldt Fellows]]
[[Category:California Institute of Technology alumni]]
[[Category:Deaths from cancer in Massachusetts]]
[[Category:Chaos theorists]]
[[Category:Deaths from pancreatic cancer]]
[[Category:École Polytechnique alumni]]
[[Category:Fellows of the American Geophysical Union]]
[[Category:Fellows of the American Statistical Association]]
[[Category:French emigrants to the United States]]
[[Category:French Jews]]
[[Category:French mathematicians]]
[[Category:French people of Polish-Jewish descent]]
[[Category:French scientists]]
[[Category:Harvard University people]]
[[Category:IBM employees]]
[[Category:IBM Fellows]]
[[Category:Members of the Norwegian Academy of Science and Letters]]
[[Category:Members of the United States National Academy of Sciences]]
[[Category:IBM Research computer scientists]]
[[Category:Officiers of the Légion d'honneur]]
[[Category:People from Warsaw]]
[[Category:Polish emigrants to France]]
[[Category:Polish emigrants to the United States]]
[[Category:Polish Jews]]
[[Category:Polish mathematicians]]
[[Category:University of Paris alumni]]
[[Category:Wolf Prize in Physics laureates]]
[[Category:Institute for Advanced Study visiting scholars]]
[[Category:Yale University faculty]]
[[Category:Yale Sterling Professors]]
[[Category:Fellows of the Econometric Society]]</text>
      <sha1>oeg5muep0kzj77gmt9awz5rtrxemb3b</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
