  <page>
    <title>Bass guitar</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3916</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943100291</id>
      <parentid>943100256</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-28T20:51:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Nyook</username>
        <id>37345946</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/Zhenlong552|Zhenlong552]] ([[User talk:Zhenlong552|talk]]) ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|electric instrument}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=February 2019}}
{{Use American English|date=September 2017}}
{{Multiple issues|
{{more citations needed|date=May 2017}}
{{Original research|date=May 2017}}
{{Example farm|date=May 2017}}
}}
{{Infobox Instrument
|name                   = Bass guitar
|names                  = Bass, electric bass guitar, electric bass
|image                  = 70's Fender Jazz Bass.png
|image_capt             = [[Fender Jazz Bass]]
|background             = string
|classification         = [[String instrument]] ([[pizzicato|fingered]] or [[plectrum|picked]]; [[strum]]med)
|hornbostel_sachs       = 321.322
|hornbostel_sachs_desc  = Composite [[chordophone]]
|inventors              = [[Paul Tutmarc]], [[Leo Fender]]
|developed              = 1930s
|range                  = [[File:Range contrabass.png|110px|center]]&lt;div class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;(a standard tuned 4-string bass guitar)&lt;/div&gt;
|related                =
* [[Electric guitar]]
* [[Double bass]]
* [[Acoustic bass guitar]]
* [[Ukulele bass]]
}}
&lt;!-- Please do NOT add any more PICTURES of bass players. Three notable bass players, Paul McCartney and James Jamerson are enough. If we allow more, then soon editors will want to add a picture of each of the 60 players referred to in the article. See talk page for discussion. --&gt;

The '''bass guitar''', '''electric bass''' (or simply '''bass''') is the lowest pitched member of the guitar family. It is a [[plucked string instrument]] similar in appearance and construction to an [[Electric guitar|electric]] or an [[acoustic guitar]], except with a longer [[neck (music)|neck]] and [[Scale length (string instruments)|scale length]], and typically four to six [[string (music)|strings]] or [[Course (music)|courses]]. Since the mid-1950s, the electric bass has largely replaced the [[double bass]] in [[popular music]]. 

The four-string bass is usually tuned the same as the [[double bass]], which corresponds to pitches one [[octave]] lower than the four lowest-pitched strings of a guitar (E, A, D, and G). It is played primarily with the fingers or thumb, or [[guitar pick|striking]] with a [[plectrum|pick]]. The electric bass guitar has [[pickup (music technology)|pickups]] and must be connected to an [[Bass amplifier|amplifier and speaker]] to be loud enough to compete with other instruments.

==Terminology==
According to the ''New Grove Dictionary of Music and Musicians'', an &quot;Electric bass guitar [is] a Guitar, usually with four heavy strings tuned E&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;'–A&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;'–D&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;–G&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;.&quot;{{sfn|Sadie|Tyrrell|2001|p=}} It also defines ''bass'' as &quot;Bass (iv). A contraction of Double bass or Electric bass guitar.&quot; According to some authors the proper term is &quot;electric bass&quot;.{{sfn|Wheeler|1978|pp=101–102}}{{sfn|Evans|Evans|1977|p=342}} Common names for the instrument are &quot;bass guitar&quot;, &quot;electric bass guitar&quot;, and &quot;electric bass&quot;{{citation needed|date=February 2019}} and some authors claim that they are historically accurate.{{sfn|Roberts|2001|loc=References Appendix}}
As the electric alternative to a double bass (which is not a guitar), many manufacturers such as [https://shop.fender.com/en-US/electric-basses/?rl=en_US Fender] list the instrument in the electric bass category rather than guitar. 

The bass guitar is a [[transposing instrument]], as it is notated in [[bass clef]] an octave higher than it sounds, to reduce the need for [[ledger lines]] in music written for the instrument, and simplify reading.{{citation needed|date=February 2020}}

== History ==
=== 1930s–1940s ===
[[File:Paul tutmarc.jpg|thumb|right|upright|Musical instrument inventor [[Paul Tutmarc]] outside his music store in Seattle, Washington]]
In the 1930s, musician and inventor [[Paul Tutmarc]] of [[Seattle]], Washington, developed the first electric bass guitar in its modern form, a [[fret]]ted instrument designed to be played horizontally. The 1935 sales catalog for Tutmarc's company Audiovox featured his &quot;Model 736 Bass Fiddle&quot;, a solid-bodied electric bass [[guitar]] with four strings, a {{convert|30+1/2|in|mm|0|adj=on|abbr=off}} scale length, and a single [[Pickup (music technology)|pickup]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.vintageguitar.com/1782/audiovox-736/ |title=Audiovox #736: The World's First Electric Bass Guitar! |last=Blecha |first=Peter |website = [[Vintage Guitar (magazine)|Vintage Guitar]] |accessdate=February 17, 2019|date=December 11, 2001 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Around 100 were made during this period.{{sfn|Roberts|2001|pp=28–29}} Audiovox also sold their “Model 236” bass amplifier.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.vintageguitar.com/1869/audiovox-and-serenader-amps/ |title=Audiovox and Serenader Amps – An Interview with Bud Tutmarc |website=[[Vintage Guitar (magazine)|Vintage Guitar]] |accessdate=February 17, 2019|date=February 19, 2002 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Around 1947, Tutmarc's son Bud began marketing a similar bass under the Serenader brand name, advertised in the nationally distributed [[L.&amp;nbsp;D. Heater Music Company]] wholesale jobber catalogue of 1948. However, the Tutmarc family inventions did not achieve market success.{{citation needed|date=October 2019}}

=== 1950s ===
[[File:Fender '51 Precision Bass, FGF museum.jpg|thumb|upright|left|An early [[Fender Precision Bass]]]]
In the 1950s, [[Leo Fender]] and [[George William Fullerton|George Fullerton]] developed the first mass-produced electric bass guitar.{{sfn|Slog|Coryat|1999|p=154}} The [[Fender Electric Instrument Manufacturing Company]] began producing the [[Fender Precision Bass|Precision Bass]], or P-Bass, in October 1951. The design featured a simple un-contoured &quot;slab&quot; body design and a [[single coil pickup]] similar to that of a [[Fender Telecaster|Telecaster]]. By 1957 the Precision more closely resembled the [[Fender Stratocaster]] with the body edges beveled for comfort, and the pickup was changed to a [[humbucker|split coil]] design.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Owens |first1=Jeff |title=Legendary Lows: The Precision Bass Story |url=https://www.fender.com/articles/gear/legendary-lows-the-precision-bass-story |website=www.fender.com |accessdate=7 January 2020 |date=13 March 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Fender Bass Guitar Patent.jpg|thumb|right|upright|Design patent issued to Leo Fender for the second-generation Precision Bass.]]
The Fender Bass was a revolutionary instrument for gigging musicians. In comparison with the large, heavy [[upright bass]], which had been the main bass instrument in popular music from the early 20th century to the 1940s, the bass guitar could be easily transported to shows. When amplified, the bass guitar was also less prone than acoustic basses to unwanted [[audio feedback]].{{sfn|Roberts|2001|p=}} The addition of [[Fret|frets]] enabled bassists to play in tune more easily than on fretless acoustic or [[electric upright bass]]es, and allowed guitarists to more easily transition to the instrument.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Rogers |first1=Dave |last2=Braithwaite |first2=Laun |last3=May 13 |first3=Tim Mullally |title=1952 Fender Precision Bass |url=https://www.premierguitar.com/articles/1952_Fender_Precision_Bass |website=www.premierguitar.com |accessdate=7 January 2020 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1953, [[Monk Montgomery]] became the first bassist to tour with the Fender bass, in [[Lionel Hampton]]'s postwar [[big band]].{{sfn|George|1998|p=91}} Montgomery was also possibly the first to record with the electric bass, on July 2, 1953, with [[the Art Farmer Septet]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Bass heroes : styles, stories &amp; secrets of 30 great bass players : from the pages of Guitar player magazine|last=Mulhern|first=Tom|date=1993|publisher=GPI Books|isbn=0-585-34936-3|location=San Francisco|pages=165|oclc=47008985}}&lt;/ref&gt; Roy Johnson (with Lionel Hampton), and [[Shifty Henry]] (with [[Louis Jordan]] and His [[Tympany Five]]), were other early Fender bass pioneers.{{sfn|Slog|Coryat|1999|p=154}} [[Bill Black]], who played with [[Elvis Presley]], switched from upright bass to the Fender Precision Bass around 1957.{{sfn|Bacon|2010|p=}} The bass guitar was intended to appeal to guitarists as well as upright bass players, and many early pioneers of the instrument, such as [[Carol Kaye]], [[Joe Osborn]], and [[Paul McCartney]] were originally guitarists.{{sfn|Roberts|2001|p=}}

Also in 1953, [[Gibson Guitar Corporation|Gibson]] released the first short-scale [[violin]]-shaped electric bass, with an extendable end pin so a bassist could play it upright or horizontally. Gibson renamed the bass the [[Gibson EB-1|EB-1]] in 1958.{{citation needed|date=October 2019}} In 1958, Gibson released the maple arched-top [[Gibson EB-2|EB-2]] described in the Gibson catalog as a &quot;hollow-body electric bass that features a Bass/Baritone pushbutton for two different tonal characteristics&quot;.{{citation needed|date=February 2020}} In 1959, these were followed by the more conventional-looking [[Gibson EB-0|EB-0 Bass]].{{citation needed|date=October 2019}} The EB-0 was very similar to a [[Gibson SG]] in appearance (although the earliest examples have a slab-sided body shape closer to that of the double-cutaway [[Les Paul]] Special).  Whereas Fender basses had pickups mounted in positions in between the base of the neck and the top of the bridge, many of Gibson's early basses featured one [[humbucker|humbucking]] pickup mounted directly against the neck pocket.{{citation needed|date=October 2019}}  The Fender and Gibson versions used [[Bolt-on neck|bolt-on]] and [[Set-in neck|glued-on]] necks.

A number of other companies also began manufacturing bass guitars during the 1950s. 1956 saw the appearance at the German trade fair &quot;Musikmesse Frankfurt&quot; of the distinctive [[Höfner 500/1]] violin-shaped bass made using violin construction techniques by Walter [[Höfner]], a second-generation violin luthier.{{citation needed|date=October 2019}} The design was eventually known popularly as the &quot;[[The Beatles|Beatle Bass]]&quot;, due to its endorsement and use by Beatles bassist [[Paul McCartney]]. In 1957, [[Rickenbacker]] introduced the model 4000,the first bass to feature a [[neck-through]]-body design in which the neck is part of the body wood.{{citation needed|date=October 2019}} [[Kay Musical Instrument Company]] began production of the K-162 in 1952, [[Danelectro]] released the Longhorn in 1956, and [[Burns London]]/Supersound in 1958.{{sfn|Bacon|2010|p=}}

=== 1960s ===
[[File:Gibson eb3 67.jpg|thumb|upright|right|[[Gibson EB-3]]]]
With the explosion of the popularity of [[rock music]] in the 1960s, many more manufacturers began making electric basses, including [[Yamaha Corporation|Yamaha]], [[Teisco]] and [[Guyatone]]. Introduced in 1960, the [[Fender Jazz Bass]], initially known as the &quot;Deluxe Bass&quot;, was intended to accompany the [[Jazzmaster]] guitar.{{citation needed|date=October 2019}} The &quot;J-bass&quot; featured two single-coil pickups, one close to the bridge and one in the Precision bass's split coil pickup position. The earliest production Jazz basses had a &quot;stacked&quot;{{explain|date=February 2019}} volume and tone control for each pickup; this was soon changed to the familiar configuration of a volume control for each pickup, and a single passive tone control. 

The Jazz Bass's neck was narrower at the nut than the Precision bass — {{convert|1+1/2|in|mm|0}} versus {{convert|1+3/4|in|mm|0}} — allowing for easier access to the lower strings and an overall spacing and feel closer to that of an electric guitar, allowing trained guitarists to transition to the bass guitar more easily.{{citation needed|date=October 2019}} Another visual difference that set the Jazz Bass apart from the Precision is its &quot;offset-waist&quot; body.{{explain|date=February 2019}}

Pickup shapes on electric basses are often referred to as &quot;P&quot; or &quot;J&quot; pickups in reference to the visual and electrical differences between the Precision Bass and Jazz Bass [[pick up (music technology)|pickups]].{{citation needed|date=October 2019}} In the 1950s and 1960s, all bass guitars were often called the &quot;Fender bass&quot;, due to [[Fender Musical Instruments Corporation|Fender]]'s early dominance in the market.

Providing a more &quot;Gibson-scale&quot; instrument, rather than the {{convert|34|in|mm|0}} Jazz and Precision, Fender produced the [[Fender Mustang Bass|Mustang Bass]], a {{convert|30|in|mm|0|adj=on}} scale-length instrument.{{Citation needed|date=October 2019}}  The [[Fender VI]], a 6 string bass, was tuned one octave lower than standard guitar tuning. It was released in 1961, and was briefly favored by [[Jack Bruce]] of [[Cream (band)|Cream]].{{citation needed|date=October 2019}}

Gibson introduced its short-scale {{convert|30+1/2|in|mm|0|adj=on}} [[Gibson EB-3|EB-3]] in 1961, also used by Bruce.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.vintageguitar.com/3568/the-gibson-eb-3/ |title=The Gibson EB-3 |last=Moseley |first=Willie G. |website=[[Vintage Guitar (magazine)|Vintage Guitar]] |accessdate= September 5, 2017|date=March 10, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The EB-3 had a &quot;mini-humbucker&quot; at the bridge position. Gibson basses tended to be smaller, sleeker instruments with a shorter [[Scale length (string instruments)|scale length]] than the Precision; Gibson did not produce a {{convert|34|in|mm|0|adj=on}}-scale bass until 1963 with the release of the [[Gibson Thunderbird|Thunderbird]], which was also the first Gibson bass to use two humbucking pickups in a more traditional position, about halfway between the neck and bridge.{{citation needed|date=October 2019}}

=== 1970s ===
[[File:Rickenbacker Bass 4001JG.jpg|thumb|upright|left|[[Rickenbacker 4001]] bass]]
In 1971, [[Alembic Inc|Alembic]] established what became known as &quot;boutique&quot; or &quot;high-end&quot; electric bass guitars.{{citation needed|date=October 2019}} These expensive, custom-tailored instruments, as used by [[Phil Lesh]], [[Jack Casady]], and [[Stanley Clarke]], featured unique designs, premium hand-finished wood bodies, and innovative construction techniques such as multi-laminate [[Neck-thru|neck-through-body]] construction and [[Carbon fiber reinforced polymer|graphite]] necks. Alembic also pioneered the use of onboard electronics for pre-amplification and equalization.{{citation needed|date=October 2019}} Active electronics increase the output of the instrument, and allow more options for controlling tonal flexibility, giving the player the ability to amplify as well as to attenuate certain frequency ranges while improving the overall frequency response (including more low-register and high-register sounds). 1973 saw the UK company [[Wal (bass)|Wal]] begin production of a their own range of active basses.{{citation needed|date=October 2019}} In 1974 [[Music Man (company)|Music Man]] Instruments, founded by Tom Walker, [[Forrest White]] and [[Leo Fender]], introduced the [[Music Man StingRay|StingRay]], the first widely produced bass with active (powered) electronics built into the instrument.{{citation needed|date=October 2019}} Basses with active electronics can include a [[preamplifier]] and [[equalizer (audio)|knobs]] for boosting and cutting the low and high frequencies.

In the mid-1970s, Alembic and other high-end manufacturers, such as [[Tobias (bass guitar company)|Tobias]], began offering five-string basses, with a very low &quot;B&quot; string.{{citation needed|date=October 2019}} In 1975, bassist [[Anthony Jackson (musician)|Anthony Jackson]] commissioned luthier [[Carl Thompson (luthier)|Carl Thompson]] to build a six-string bass tuned (low to high) B0, E1, A1, D2, G2, C3, adding a low B string and a high C string.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=https://bassmagazine.com/artists/partners-anthony-jackson-fodera-guitars |title = Partners: Anthony Jackson &amp; Fodera Guitars}}&lt;/ref&gt; These five- and six-string &quot;[[extended-range bass]]es&quot; would become popular with [[Session musician|session bassists]], reducing the need for re-tuning to alternate detuned configurations like &quot;drop D&quot;, and also allowing the bassist to play more notes from the same fretting position with fewer shifts up and down the fingerboard, a crucial benefit for a session player [[sightreading]] [[bassline]]s at a recording session.{{citation needed|date=October 2019}}

=== 1980s–present ===
[[File:Steinberger bass.jpg|thumb|right|upright|Early 1980s-era Steinberger headless bass. The tuning machines are at the heel of the instrument, where the bridge is usually located.]]
In the 1980s, bass designers continued to explore new approaches. [[Ned Steinberger]] introduced a headless bass in 1979 and continued his innovations in the 1980s, using graphite and other new materials and (in 1984) introducing the [[TransTrem]] [[tremolo arm|tremolo bar]]. In 1982, Hans-Peter Wilfer founded [[Warwick (company)|Warwick]], to make a European bass, as the market at the time was dominated by Asian and American basses. Their first bass was the [[Streamer Bass]], which is similar to the Spector NS. In 1987, the Guild Guitar Corporation launched the fretless [[Ashbory bass]], which used silicone rubber strings and a piezoelectric pickup to achieve an &quot;upright bass&quot; sound with a short {{convert|18|in|mm|0|adj=on}} scale length. In the late 1980s, [[MTV Unplugged|MTV's &quot;Unplugged&quot;]] show, which featured bands performing with acoustic instruments, helped to popularize hollow-bodied [[acoustic bass guitar]]s amplified with [[piezoelectricity|piezoelectric]] pickups built into the bridge of the instrument.{{cn|date=October 2019}}

During the 1990s, as five-string basses became more widely available and more affordable, an increasing number of bassists in genres ranging from [[heavy metal music|metal]] to [[gospel music|gospel]] began using five-string instruments for added lower range—a low &quot;B&quot; string. As well, onboard battery-powered electronics such as preamplifiers and equalizer circuits, which were previously only available on expensive &quot;boutique&quot; instruments, became increasingly available on mid-priced basses. From 2000 to the 2010s, some bass manufacturers included [[digital signal processing|digital]] modelling circuits inside the instrument on more costly instruments to recreate tones and sounds from many models of basses (e.g., [[Line 6 (company)|Line 6's]] Variax bass). A modelling bass can digitally emulate the tone and sound of many famous basses, ranging from a vintage Fender Precision to a Rickenbacker. However, as with the electric guitar, traditional &quot;passive&quot; bass designs, which include only pickups, tone and volume knobs (without a preamp or other electronics) remained popular. Reissued versions of vintage instruments such as the [[Fender Precision Bass]] and [[Fender Jazz Bass]] remained popular among new instrument buyers up to the 2010s. In 2011, a 60th Anniversary P-bass was introduced by [[Fender Musical Instruments Corporation|Fender]], along with the re-introduction of the short-scale [[Fender Jaguar Bass]].{{cn|date=October 2019}}

== Fretless basses ==
[[File:Flatwound 01.JPG|thumb|right|A fretless bass with flatwound strings; markers are inlaid into the side of the fingerboard, to aid the performer in finding the correct pitch.]]
While electric bass guitars are traditionally fretted instruments, fretless basses are used by some players to achieve different tones.  [[the Rolling Stones|Rolling Stones]] bassist [[Bill Wyman]] is sometimes identified as the first to make a fretless bass.  In 1961, he converted a used UK-built Dallas Tuxedo bass by removing the frets and filling in the slots with wood putty.{{sfn|Roberts|2001|p=}} Wyman used it to record  songs such as &quot;[[Paint It, Black]]&quot; and &quot;[[Mother's Little Helper]]&quot; in 1966.

In 1966, [[Ampeg]] introduced the AUB-1, the first production fretless bass. Fender followed with a fretless Precision Bass in 1970. Some fretless basses have &quot;fret line&quot; markers inlaid in the fingerboard as a guide, while others only use guide marks on the side of the neck. In the early 1970s, fusion-jazz bassist [[Jaco Pastorius]] coated the fingerboard of his de-fretted Fender Jazz Bass in [[epoxy resin]], allowing him to use roundwound strings for a brighter sound without damaging the fretboard.

== Strings and tuning ==
{{Main|Bass guitar tuning}}
Traditional electric bass guitars have four strings, tuned the same as [[double bass]]es: E&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;–A&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;–D&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;–G&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;. However, now there are many options, with five-, six-, and more string designs, with many approaches to tuning.  In addition to traditional [[flatwound]] strings, choices now include various windings and materials.

== Pickups and amplification ==
{{Main|Pickup (music technology)}}
=== Magnetic pickups ===
[[File:Precision Bass pickup.jpg|thumb|left|P-style, split-coil pickups]]

* '''&quot;Precision&quot; pickups''' (as introduced with the Fender Precision Bass) or &quot;P-style&quot; are two [[single-coil]] pickups, each offset a small amount along the length of the body so that each half is underneath two strings. The pair is considered a single pickup, as they are wired together in a [[humbucker|humbucking]] configuration, greatly reducing noise from nearby electronic equipment and mains power. (Less common is the &quot;single-coil P&quot; pickup, as used on the original 1951 Precision bass. This is also known as the 'Vintage P' due to it being found on old vintage basses made before the invention of the split coil pickup. The &quot;single-coil P&quot; pickup is also used in the reissue and the Sting signature model.) P-style pickups are generally placed in the &quot;neck&quot; or &quot;middle&quot; position, but they are occasionally placed in the bridge position, or between two Jazz-style pickups.

[[File:Jazz Style PickUps.JPG|thumb|right|Dual &quot;J&quot;-style pickups]]
* '''&quot;Jazz&quot; pickups''' (as introduced with the Fender Jazz Bass) or &quot;J-style&quot;, are wide eight-pole pickups that lie underneath all four strings. J pickups are typically [[single-coil]] designs, though there are a large number of humbucking designs. Traditionally, two of them are used, one near the bridge and another closer to the neck. As with the halves of P-pickups, the J-type pickups are wired in a humbucking manner so that, when used together, mains noise is greatly eliminated. J-type pickups tend to have a lower output and a thinner sound than P-type pickups. Many bassists combine a 'J' pickup at the bridge and a 'P' pickup at the neck and blend the two sounds.

* '''Dual coil &quot;[[humbucker]]&quot;''' pickups each have two signal-producing coils. Humbuckers also produce a higher output level than single-coil pickups, though many dual-coil pickups are marketed as retrofits for single-coil designs like the J pickup and advertise a similar output and tonal character to the stock single-coils.

=== Non-magnetic pickups ===
The use of non-magnetic pickups allows bassists to use non-ferrous strings such as nylon, brass, polyurethane and [[Ashbory bass|silicone rubber]]. These materials produce different tones and, in the case of the polyurethane or silicone rubber strings, allow much shorter scale lengths.
* [[piezoelectricity|Piezoelectric]] (or &quot;piezo&quot;) pickups (also called &quot;piezo&quot; pickups) use a [[transducer]] to convert vibrations in the instrument's body or bridge into an electrical signal. They are typically mounted under the bridge saddle or near the bridge and produce a different tone from magnetic pickups, often similar to that of an acoustic bass. Piezo pickups are often used in acoustic bass guitars to allow for amplification without a microphone.
* [[Pick up (music technology)#Optical|Optical pickups]] use an infrared [[LED]] to optically track the movement of the string, which allows them to reproduce low-frequency tones at high volumes without the &quot;hum&quot; or excessive resonance associated with conventional magnetic pickups. Since optical pickups do not pick up high frequencies or percussive sounds well, they are commonly paired with piezoelectric pickups to fill in the missing frequencies.

[[File:Elbas.jpg|thumb|right|Bass-stack amp and speaker configuration]]
=== Amplification and effects ===
{{Main|Bass instrument amplification|Bass effects}}
Similar to the electric guitar, the typical electric bass guitar requires an external amplifier in order to be heard in performance settings. Additionally, various electronic effects, such as [[preamplifier]]s, &quot;stomp box&quot;-style pedals and signal processors are available to allow for further shaping of the sound.

== See also ==
* [[Bass guitar techniques]]
* [[Bass guitar tuning]]
* [[List of bass guitar manufacturers]]
* [[List of bass guitarists]]
{{clear}}
== References ==
{{reflist}}
===Sources===
*{{cite book |last=Bacon |first=Tony |title=60 Years of Fender: Six Decades of the Greatest Electric Guitars |year=2010 |publisher=[[Backbeat Books]] |isbn=978-0879309664 |ref=harv}}
*{{cite book |last1=Bacon |first1=Tony |last2=Moorhouse |first2=Barry |year=2016 |title=The Bass Book: A Complete Illustrated History of Bass Guitars |publisher=[[Backbeat Books]] |isbn=978-1-4950-0150-5 |ref=harv}}
*{{cite book |last=Black |first=J. W. |year=2001 |title=The Fender Bass: An Illustrated History |publisher=[[Hal Leonard]] |isbn = 0-634-02640-2 |ref=harv}}
*{{cite book |last=Boyer |first=Paul |year=2013 |title=The Rickenbacker Electric Bass: 50 Years As Rock's Bottom |publisher=[[Hal Leonard]] |isbn=978-1-4768-8680-0 |ref=harv}}
*{{cite book |last1=Evans |first1=Tom |last2=Evans |first2=Mary Ann |title=Guitars: From the Renaissance to Rock |year=1977 |publisher=[[Facts On File]] |isbn=0-87196-636-0 |ref=harv}}
*{{cite book| last=George |first=Nelson |authorlink=Nelson George |year=1998 |title=Hip Hop America | url=https://archive.org/details/hiphopamerica00georg | url-access=registration |publisher=[[Viking Press]] |isbn=978-0-670-87153-7 |ref=harv}}
*{{cite book |last=Roberts |first=Jim |title=How The Fender Bass Changed the World |year=2001 |publisher=[[Backbeat Books]] |location = San Francisco, California |isbn = 0-87930-630-0 |ref=harv}}
*{{cite book |last1=Sadie |first1=Stanley |last2=Tyrrell |first2=John |title=The New Grove Dictionary of Music and Musicians |edition=Second |year=2001 |publisher= |location=London |isbn= |ref=harv}}
*{{cite book |last1=Slog |first1=John J. |last2=Coryat |first2=Karl |year=1999 |title=The Bass Player Book: Equipment, Technique, Styles and Artists |publisher=[[Backbeat Books]] |isbn=0-87930-573-8 |ref=harv}}
*{{cite book |last=Trynka |first=Paul |title=Rock Hardware |year=1996 |publisher=[[Hal Leonard]] |isbn=0-87930-428-6 |ref=harv |url-access=registration |url=https://archive.org/details/rockhardware40ye00tryn }}
* {{cite book |last=Wheeler |first=Tom |year=1978 |title=The Guitar Book: A Handbook for Electric and Acoustic Guitarists |publisher=[[Harper &amp; Row]] |isbn=0-06-014579-X |ref=harv}}

== External links ==

{{Commons category|Bass guitars}}
{{Wikibooks|Guitar|Bass Guitar}}

{{Bass (sound)}}
{{Guitars|Strings}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:American inventions]]
[[Category:American musical instruments]]
[[Category:Amplified instruments]]
[[Category:Bass guitars]]
[[Category:Bass (sound)]]
[[Category:Blues instruments]]
[[Category:Contrabass instruments]]
[[Category:Electric bass guitars]]
[[Category:Folk music instruments]]
[[Category:Guitars]]
[[Category:Jazz instruments]]
[[Category:Rhythm section]]
[[Category:Rock music instruments]]
[[Category:String instruments]]</text>
      <sha1>tn7acfscktswpihzq4e7on45a3wdqld</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
