  <page>
    <title>Buckingham Palace</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3969</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942555686</id>
      <parentid>942151405</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-25T11:34:33Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>146.66.63.75</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* 21st century: Royal use and public access */ updated to remove ref to Sussexes</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{pp-move|small=yes}}
{{short description|Official London residence and principal workplace of the British monarch}}
{{Featured article}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2019}}
{{EngvarB|date=July 2019}}
{{coord|display=title|51|30|3|N|0|8|31|W|type:landmark_region:GB}}

[[File:Buckingham Palace from gardens, London, UK - Diliff (cropped).jpg|thumb|upright=1.6|alt=A wide, rectangular facade displaying two rows of 23 windows; columns stand out at each end and in the centre. |The principal [[Facade|façade]] of Buckingham Palace, the East Front, was originally constructed by [[Edward Blore]] and completed in 1850. It was remodelled by [[Sir Aston Webb]] in 1913.]]

'''Buckingham Palace''' ({{IPAc-en|uk|ˈ|b|ʌ|k|ɪ|ŋ|ə|m}}&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.collinsdictionary.com/dictionary/english/buckingham?showCookiePolicy=true |title=Buckingham |date=n.d. |publisher=Collins Dictionary |access-date=23 September 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.collinsdictionary.com/dictionary/english/palace?showCookiePolicy=true |title=Palace |date=n.d. |publisher=Collins Dictionary |access-date=23 September 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;) is the [[London]] [[official residence|residence]] and administrative headquarters of the [[monarchy of the United Kingdom]].{{efn|By tradition, the [[Court of St James's|British Royal Court]] is officially resident at [[St James's Palace]], which means that, while foreign [[ambassador]]s assuming their new position are received by the [[British sovereign]] at Buckingham Palace, they are accredited to the &quot;Court of St James's Palace&quot;. This anomaly continues for the sake of tradition, as Buckingham Palace is to all intents and purposes the [[official residence]]. See [https://web.archive.org/web/20100529122601/http://www.royal.gov.uk/TheRoyalResidences/StJamessPalace/History.aspx History of St James's Palace] (Official website of the British Monarchy).}}&lt;ref name=&quot;royal.uk&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.royal.uk/royal-residences-buckingham-palace |title=Buckingham Palace |last=Royal Household |date=12 November 2015 |website=Royal Family website |access-date=21 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Located in the [[City of Westminster]], the palace is often at the centre of state occasions and royal hospitality. It has been a focal point for the [[British people]] at times of national rejoicing and mourning.

Originally known as '''Buckingham House''', the building at the core of today's palace was a large [[townhouse (Great Britain)|townhouse]] built for the [[John Sheffield, 1st Duke of Buckingham and Normanby|Duke of Buckingham]] in 1703 on a site that had been in private ownership for at least 150 years. It was acquired by [[King George&amp;nbsp;III]] in 1761&lt;ref name=&quot;rob14&quot;&gt;Robinson, p. 14.&lt;/ref&gt; as a private residence for [[Queen Charlotte]] and became known as ''The Queen's House''. During the 19th&amp;nbsp;century it was enlarged, principally by architects [[John Nash (architect)|John Nash]] and [[Edward Blore]], who constructed three wings around a central courtyard. Buckingham Palace became the London residence of the British monarch on the accession of [[Queen Victoria]] in 1837.

The last major structural additions were made in the late 19th and early 20th centuries, including the East Front, which contains the well-known balcony on which the royal family traditionally congregates to greet crowds. A German bomb destroyed the palace chapel during [[World War II]]; the [[Queen's Gallery]] was built on the site and opened to the public in 1962 to exhibit works of art from the [[Royal Collection]].

The original early 19th-century interior designs, many of which survive, include widespread use of brightly coloured [[scagliola]] and blue and pink [[Lapis lazuli|lapis]], on the advice of [[Charles Long, 1st Baron Farnborough|Sir&amp;nbsp;Charles Long]]. [[King Edward&amp;nbsp;VII]] oversaw a partial redecoration in a ''[[Belle Époque]]'' cream and gold colour scheme. Many smaller reception rooms are furnished in the Chinese [[Chinoiserie|regency]] style with furniture and fittings brought from the [[Royal Pavilion]] at [[Brighton]] and from [[Carlton House, London|Carlton House]]. The palace has 775 rooms, and [[Buckingham Palace Garden|the garden]] is the largest private garden in London. The state rooms, used for official and state entertaining, are open to the public each year for most of August and September and on some days in winter and spring.

==History==

===Site===
[[File:Buckingham House 1710.jpeg|thumb|Buckingham House, c. 1710, was designed by [[William Winde]] for the 1st Duke of Buckingham and Normanby.&lt;!--note - &quot;Normanby&quot; is correct spelling, do not change please --&gt; This façade evolved into today's Grand Entrance on the west (inner) side of the quadrangle, with the Green Drawing Room above it.]]
In the [[Middle Ages]], the site of the future palace formed part of the [[Manor of Ebury]] (also called Eia). The marshy ground was watered by the river [[Tyburn (stream)|Tyburn]], which still flows below the courtyard and south wing of the palace.&lt;ref&gt;Goring, p. 15.&lt;/ref&gt; Where the river was fordable (at Cow Ford), the village of Eye Cross grew. Ownership of the site changed hands many times; owners included [[Edward the Confessor]] and his [[queen consort]] [[Edith of Wessex]] in late Saxon times, and, after the [[Norman conquest of England|Norman Conquest]], [[William the Conqueror]]. William gave the site to [[Geoffrey de Mandeville (11th&amp;nbsp;century)|Geoffrey de Mandeville]], who bequeathed it to the monks of [[Westminster Abbey]].{{efn|The topography of the site and its ownership are dealt with in Wright, chapters 1–4.}}

In 1531, [[Henry VIII of England|Henry&amp;nbsp;VIII]] acquired the Hospital of St&amp;nbsp;James, which became [[St&amp;nbsp;James's Palace]],&lt;ref&gt;Goring, p. 28.&lt;/ref&gt; from [[Eton College]], and in 1536 he took the Manor of Ebury from Westminster Abbey.&lt;ref&gt;Goring, p. 18.&lt;/ref&gt; These transfers brought the site of Buckingham Palace back into royal hands for the first time since William the Conqueror had given it away almost 500 years earlier.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=The Grosvenor Estate in Mayfair |work=[[Survey of London]] |publisher=London County Council |year=1977 |volume=39 |pages=1–5 |chapter=Chapter 1: The Acquisition of the Estate |access-date=3 February 2009 |chapter-url=http://www.british-history.ac.uk/report.aspx?compid=41820}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Various owners leased it from royal landlords, and the [[Freehold (law)|freehold]] was the subject of frenzied speculation during the 17th&amp;nbsp;century. By then, the old village of Eye Cross had long since fallen into decay, and the area was mostly wasteland.&lt;ref&gt;Wright, pp. 76–78.&lt;/ref&gt; Needing money, [[James&amp;nbsp;I]] sold off part of the Crown freehold but retained part of the site on which he established a {{convert|4|acre|ha|adj=on}} mulberry garden for the production of silk. (This is at the north-west corner of today's palace.)&lt;ref&gt;Goring, pp. 31, 36.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Clement Walker]] in ''Anarchia Anglicana'' (1649) refers to &quot;new-erected sodoms and spintries at the Mulberry Garden at S. James's&quot;; this suggests it may have been a place of debauchery. Eventually, in the late 17th&amp;nbsp;century, the freehold was inherited from the property tycoon Sir&amp;nbsp;[[Hugh Audley]] by the great heiress Mary Davies.{{efn|Audley and Davies were key figures in the development of Ebury Manor and also the Grosvenor Estate (see [[dukes of Westminster]]), which still exists today. They are remembered in the streetnames North Audley Street, [[South Audley Street]], and Davies Street, all in [[Mayfair]].}}

===First houses on the site===

====Goring House====
Possibly the first house erected within the site was that of a Sir&amp;nbsp;William Blake, around 1624.&lt;ref&gt;Wright, p. 83.&lt;/ref&gt; The next owner was [[George Goring, 1st Earl of Norwich|Lord Goring]], who from 1633 extended Blake's house and developed much of today's garden, then known as Goring Great Garden.&lt;ref&gt;Goring, Chapter V&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Harris, p.21&quot;&gt;Harris, p. 21.&lt;/ref&gt; He did not, however, obtain the freehold interest in the mulberry garden. Unbeknown to Goring, in 1640 the document &quot;failed to pass the [[Great Seal of the Realm|Great Seal]] before [[Charles I of England|King Charles&amp;nbsp;I]] fled London, which it needed to do for legal execution&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Wright, p. 96.&lt;/ref&gt; It was this critical omission that helped the British royal family regain the freehold under [[King George&amp;nbsp;III]].&lt;ref&gt;Goring, p. 62.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Arlington House====
The improvident Goring defaulted on his rents;&lt;ref&gt;Goring, p. 58.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Henry Bennet, 1st Earl of Arlington]] obtained the mansion and was occupying it, now known as Goring House, when it burned down in 1674.&lt;ref name=&quot;Harris, p.21&quot; /&gt; Arlington House rose on the site—the location of the southern wing of today's palace—the next year.&lt;ref name=&quot;Harris, p.21&quot; /&gt; In 1698, [[John Sheffield, 1st Duke of Buckingham and Normanby|John Sheffield]], later the first [[Duke of Buckingham and Normanby]], acquired the lease.&lt;ref name=&quot;who built&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.royalcollection.org.uk/visit/buckinghampalace/about/who-built-the-palace |title=Who built Buckingham Palace? |publisher=Royal Collection Trust |access-date=8 March 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Buckingham House====
[[File:Buckingham Palace engraved by J.Woods after Hablot Browne &amp; R.Garland publ 1837 edited.jpg|thumb|The palace c. 1837, depicting the [[Marble Arch]], which served as the ceremonial entrance to the Palace precincts. It was moved to make way for the east wing, built in 1847, which enclosed the quadrangle.]]
The house which forms the architectural core of the palace was built for the first [[John Sheffield, 1st Duke of Buckingham and Normanby|Duke of Buckingham and Normanby]]&lt;!--note - &quot;Normanby&quot; is correct spelling, do not change please --&gt; in 1703 to the design of [[William Winde]]. The style chosen was of a large, three-floored central block with two smaller flanking service wings.&lt;ref&gt;Harris, p. 22.&lt;/ref&gt; Buckingham House was eventually sold by Buckingham's illegitimate son, [[Sir Charles Herbert Sheffield, 1st Baronet|Sir Charles Sheffield]], in 1761&lt;ref name=&quot;rob14&quot; /&gt; to George&amp;nbsp;III for [[Pound (currency)|£]]21,000.&lt;ref&gt;Mackenzie, p. 12 and Nash, p. 18.&lt;/ref&gt;{{efn|The purchase price is given by Wright p. 142 as £28,000.}} Sheffield's [[leasehold]] on the mulberry garden site, the freehold of which was still owned by the royal family, was due to expire in 1774.&lt;ref&gt;Mackenzie, p. 12&lt;/ref&gt;

===From Queen's House to palace===
{{anchor|Queen's House}}&lt;!-- [[Queen's House (disambiguation)]] links here--&gt;
Under the new Crown ownership, the building was originally intended as a private retreat for King George&amp;nbsp;III's wife, [[Queen Charlotte]], and was accordingly known as '''The Queen's House'''. Remodelling of the structure began in 1762.&lt;ref&gt;Harris, p. 24.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1775, an Act of Parliament settled the property on Queen Charlotte, in exchange for her rights to [[Somerset House]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Old and New&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |url=http://www.british-history.ac.uk/report.aspx?compid=45183 |title=Old and New London |publisher=Cassell, Petter &amp; Galpin |year=1878 |volume=4 |pages=61–74}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{efn|The tradition persists of foreign ambassadors being formally accredited to &quot;the [[Court of St James's]]&quot;, even though it is at Buckingham Palace that they present their credentials and staff to the Monarch upon their appointment.}} and 14 of her 15 children were born there. Some furnishings were transferred from [[Carlton House, London|Carlton House]], and others had been bought in France after the French Revolution&lt;ref&gt;Jones, p. 42.&lt;/ref&gt; of 1789. While [[St&amp;nbsp;James's Palace]] remained the official and ceremonial royal residence,&lt;ref name=&quot;Old and New&quot; /&gt; the name &quot;Buckingham-palace&quot; was used from at least 1791.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=0Zg-AAAAYAAJ |title=The Annual Register |year=1791 |editor-last=Burke |editor-first=Edmund |page=8 |quote=Buckingham-palace was the dwelling house of the king. |access-date=25 September 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After his accession to the throne in 1820, [[King George&amp;nbsp;IV]] continued the renovation with the idea in mind of a small, comfortable home. However, in 1826, while the work was in progress, the King decided to modify the house into a palace with the help of his architect [[John Nash (architect)|John Nash]].&lt;ref&gt;Harris, pp. 30–31.&lt;/ref&gt; The external façade was designed, keeping in mind the French neo-classical influence preferred by George&amp;nbsp;IV. The cost of the renovations grew dramatically, and by 1829 the extravagance of Nash's designs resulted in his removal as the architect. On the death of George&amp;nbsp;IV in 1830, his younger brother [[King William&amp;nbsp;IV]] hired [[Edward Blore]] to finish the work.&lt;ref&gt;Harris, p. 33.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.royal.gov.uk/TheRoyalResidences/BuckinghamPalace/History.aspx |title=The Royal Residences &gt; Buckingham Palace &gt; History |publisher=www.royal.gov.uk |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100328161802/http://www.royal.gov.uk/TheRoyalResidences/BuckinghamPalace/History.aspx |archive-date=28 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; After the destruction of the [[Palace of Westminster]] by fire in 1834, William considered converting the palace into the new Houses of Parliament.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=King William IV |last=[[Philip Ziegler|Ziegler, Philip]] |publisher=Collins |year=1971 |isbn=978-0-00-211934-4 |page=280}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Home of the monarch==
{{multiple image
| footer  = The east wing of Buckingham Palace, the public façade, enclosing the courtyard, was a later addition, built between 1847 and 1850; it was remodelled to its present form in 1913 (shown on the right).
| align = right
| image1 = 1910_Buckingham_Palace.png
| width1 = 220
| image2 = Buckingham Palace from side, London, UK - Diliff.jpg
| width2 = 220
}}

Buckingham Palace finally became the principal royal residence in 1837, on the accession of Queen Victoria,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.royal.gov.uk/TheRoyalResidences/BuckinghamPalace/BuckinghamPalace.aspx |title=The Royal Residences &gt; Buckingham Palace |publisher=www.royal.gov.uk |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100327220845/http://www.royal.gov.uk/TheRoyalResidences/BuckinghamPalace/BuckinghamPalace.aspx |archive-date=27 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; who was the first monarch to reside there; her predecessor William&amp;nbsp;IV had died before its completion.&lt;ref&gt;Hedley, p. 10.&lt;/ref&gt; While the [[state room]]s were a riot of gilt and colour, the necessities of the new palace were somewhat less luxurious. For one thing, it was reported the chimneys smoked so much that the fires had to be allowed to die down, and consequently the court shivered in icy magnificence.&lt;ref name=&quot;ws249&quot;&gt;Woodham-Smith, p. 249.&lt;/ref&gt; Ventilation was so bad that the interior smelled, and when it was decided to install gas lamps, there was a serious worry about the build-up of gas on the lower floors. It was also said that staff were lax and lazy and the palace was dirty.&lt;ref name=&quot;ws249&quot; /&gt; Following the Queen's marriage in 1840, her husband, [[Albert, Prince Consort|Prince Albert]], concerned himself with a reorganisation of the [[Royal Household|household]] offices and staff, and with addressing the design faults of the palace.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rappaport&quot;&gt;Rappaport, p. 84.&lt;/ref&gt; By the end of 1840, all the problems had been rectified. However, the builders were to return within the decade.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rappaport&quot;&gt;Rappaport, p. 84.&lt;/ref&gt;

By 1847, the couple had found the palace too small for court life and their growing family,&lt;ref&gt;Harris, de Bellaigue &amp; Miller, p. 33.&lt;/ref&gt; and consequently the new wing, designed by Edward Blore, was built by [[Thomas Cubitt]],&lt;ref&gt;''Holland &amp; Hannen and Cubitts&amp;nbsp;– The Inception and Development of a Great Building Firm'', published 1920, p. 35.&lt;/ref&gt; enclosing the central quadrangle. The large East Front, facing [[The Mall, London|The Mall]], is today the &quot;public face&quot; of Buckingham Palace, and contains the balcony from which the [[British Royal Family|royal family]] acknowledge the crowds on momentous occasions and after the annual [[Trooping the Colour]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.historyextra.com/article/feature/history-buckingham-palace-balcony-appearance-focal-point-national-celebration |title=Buckingham Palace's balcony: a focal point for national celebration |last=Owens |first=Ed |publisher=Immediate Media/BBC |access-date=12 June 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[ballroom]] wing and a further suite of state rooms were also built in this period, designed by Nash's student [[James Pennethorne|Sir&amp;nbsp;James Pennethorne]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Twilight&quot;&gt;King, p. 217.&lt;/ref&gt;

Before Prince Albert's death, the palace was frequently the scene of musical entertainments,&lt;ref&gt;Hedley, p. 19.&lt;/ref&gt; and the most celebrated contemporary musicians entertained at Buckingham Palace. The composer [[Felix Mendelssohn]] is known to have played there on three occasions.&lt;ref&gt;Healey, pp. 137–138.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Johann Strauss&amp;nbsp;II]] and his orchestra played there when in England.&lt;ref&gt;Healey, p. 122.&lt;/ref&gt; Under Victoria, Buckingham Palace was frequently the scene of lavish costume balls, in addition to the usual royal ceremonies, investitures and presentations.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.royalcollection.org.uk/visit/buckinghampalace/about/who-has-lived-at-the-palace |title=Who has lived at Buckingham Palace? |publisher=Royal Collection Trust |url-status=live |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170623215833/https://www.royalcollection.org.uk/visit/buckinghampalace/about/who-has-lived-at-the-palace |archive-date=23 June 2017 |access-date=12 June 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Widowed in 1861, the grief-stricken Queen withdrew from public life and left Buckingham Palace to live at [[Windsor Castle]], [[Balmoral Castle]] and [[Osborne House]]. For many years the palace was seldom used, even neglected. In 1864, a note was found pinned to the fence of Buckingham Palace, saying: &quot;These commanding premises to be let or sold, in consequence of the late occupant's declining business.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Gardiner2006&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Dipe9nVHV3cC&amp;pg=PA142 |title=The Victorians: An Age in Retrospect |last=John Gardiner |publisher=A&amp;C Black |year=2006 |isbn=978-1-85285-560-4 |page=142}}&lt;/ref&gt; Eventually, public opinion persuaded the Queen to return to London, though even then she preferred to live elsewhere whenever possible. Court functions were still held at Windsor Castle, presided over by the sombre Queen habitually dressed in mourning black, while Buckingham Palace remained shuttered for most of the year.&lt;ref name=&quot;rob9&quot;&gt;Robinson, p. 9.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Interior===
[[File:Plan of Buckingham palace.gif|thumb|left|''[[Piano nobile]]'' of Buckingham Palace. The areas defined by shaded walls represent lower minor wings. {{paragraph break}}'''Note''': This is an unscaled sketch plan for reference only. Proportions of some rooms may slightly differ in reality.]]
The front of the palace measures {{convert|108|m|ft|order=flip|round=5}} across, by {{convert|120|m|ft|abbr=on|order=flip}} deep, by {{convert|24|m|ft|abbr=on|order=flip|-1}} high and contains over {{convert|77000|m2|sqft|abbr=on|order=flip}} of floorspace.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.royal.uk/royal-residences-buckingham-palace |title=Royal Residences: Buckingham Palace |publisher=British Monarchy website |access-date=28 July 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; There are 775 rooms, including 188 staff bedrooms, 92 offices, 78 bathrooms, 52 principal bedrooms, and 19 state rooms. It also has a [[post office]], cinema, swimming pool, doctor's surgery,&lt;ref name=&quot;fact&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.royal.gov.uk/LatestNewsandDiary/Factfiles/40factsaboutBuckinghamPalace.aspx |title=40 facts about Buckingham Palace |publisher=British Monarchy website |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20111104182150/http://www.royal.gov.uk/latestnewsanddiary/factfiles/40factsaboutbuckinghampalace.aspx |archive-date=4 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and jeweller's workshop.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.timesoftunbridgewells.co.uk/queen-honours-jeweller-with-top-personal-award/ |title=Queen honours jeweller with top personal award |date=6 January 2016 |work=Times of Tunbridge Wells |access-date=2 June 2016 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160701021803/https://www.timesoftunbridgewells.co.uk/queen-honours-jeweller-with-top-personal-award/ |archive-date=1 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The principal rooms are contained on the ''[[piano nobile]]'' behind the west-facing garden façade at the rear of the palace. The centre of this ornate suite of state rooms is the Music Room, its large bow the dominant feature of the façade. Flanking the Music Room are the Blue and the White Drawing Rooms. At the centre of the suite, serving as a corridor to link the state rooms, is the Picture Gallery, which is top-lit and {{convert|55|yd|m}} long.&lt;ref name=&quot;Harris, p.41&quot;&gt;Harris, p. 41.&lt;/ref&gt; The Gallery is hung with numerous works including some by [[Rembrandt]], [[Anthony van Dyck|van Dyck]], [[Peter Paul Rubens|Rubens]] and [[Johannes Vermeer|Vermeer]];&lt;ref&gt;Harris, pp. 78–79 and Healey, pp. 387–388.&lt;/ref&gt; other rooms leading from the Picture Gallery are the [[Throne Room]] and the Green Drawing Room. The Green Drawing Room serves as a huge anteroom to the Throne Room, and is part of the ceremonial route to the throne from the Guard Room at the top of the Grand Staircase.&lt;ref name=&quot;Harris, p.41&quot; /&gt; The Guard Room contains white marble statues of Queen Victoria and Prince Albert, in Roman costume, set in a [[Tribune (architecture)|tribune]] lined with tapestries. These very formal rooms are used only for ceremonial and official entertaining but are open to the public every summer.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.royalcollection.org.uk/visit/the-state-rooms-buckingham-palace |title=Visit the State Rooms, Buckingham Palace |publisher=Royal Collection Trust |access-date=7 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Directly underneath the [[State room|State Apartments]] are the less grand semi-state apartments. Opening from the Marble Hall, these rooms are used for less formal entertaining, such as luncheon parties and private [[Head of state|audiences]]. Some of the rooms are named and decorated for particular visitors, such as the ''1844 Room'', decorated in that year for the state visit of [[Tsar]] [[Nicholas&amp;nbsp;I of Russia]], and the ''1855 Room'', in honour of the visit of Emperor [[Napoleon&amp;nbsp;III of France]].&lt;ref&gt;Harris, p. 81.&lt;/ref&gt; At the centre of this suite is the Bow Room, through which thousands of guests pass annually to the Queen's [[garden parties]].&lt;ref&gt;Harris, p. 40.&lt;/ref&gt; The Queen and Prince Philip use a smaller suite of rooms in the north wing.&lt;ref name=&quot;Packard1982&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=dfk_5uIFtqIC |title=The Queen and Her Court: A Guide to the British Monarchy Today |last=Jerrold M. Packard |publisher=Simon &amp; Schuster |year=1982 |isbn=978-0-684-17648-2 |page=48}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Duke of Edinburgh 9 Allan Warren.jpg|thumb|upright|The Duke of Edinburgh in the Chinese Luncheon Room]]
Between 1847 and 1850, when Blore was building the new east wing, the [[Brighton Pavilion]] was once again plundered of its fittings. As a result, many of the rooms in the new wing have a distinctly oriental atmosphere. The red and blue Chinese Luncheon Room is made up from parts of the Brighton Banqueting and Music Rooms with a large oriental chimney piece designed by [[Robert Jones (designer)|Robert Jones]] and sculpted by [[Richard Westmacott]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Harris, de Bellaigue &amp; Miller, p. 87.&quot;&gt;Harris, de Bellaigue &amp; Miller, p. 87.&lt;/ref&gt; It was formerly in the Music Room at the Brighton Pavilion.&lt;ref name=&quot;Harris, de Bellaigue &amp; Miller, p. 87.&quot; /&gt; The ornate clock, known as the [[Qilin|Kylin Clock]], was made in Jingdezhen, Jiangxi Province, China, in the second half of the 18th century; it has a later movement by [[Benjamin Vulliamy]] circa 1820.&lt;ref&gt;Harris, de Bellaigue &amp; Miller, p. 135.&lt;/ref&gt; The Yellow Drawing Room has wallpaper supplied in 1817 for the Brighton Saloon, and a chimney piece which is a European vision of how the Chinese chimney piece may appear. It has nodding [[Mandarin (bureaucrat)|mandarins]] in [[Niche (architecture)|niches]] and fearsome winged [[Chinese dragon|dragons]], designed by Robert Jones.&lt;ref&gt;Healey, pp. 159–160.&lt;/ref&gt;

At the centre of this wing is the famous balcony with the Centre Room behind its glass doors. This is a Chinese-style saloon enhanced by Queen Mary, who, working with the designer [[Sir&amp;nbsp;Charles Allom]], created a more &quot;binding&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Harris, de Bellaigue &amp; Miller, p. 93.&lt;/ref&gt; Chinese theme in the late 1920s, although the [[lacquer]] doors were brought from Brighton in 1873. Running the length of the ''piano nobile'' of the east wing is the Great Gallery, modestly known as the Principal Corridor, which runs the length of the eastern side of the quadrangle.&lt;ref&gt;Harris, de Bellaigue &amp; Miller, p. 91.&lt;/ref&gt; It has mirrored doors and mirrored cross walls reflecting [[porcelain]] pagodas and other oriental furniture from Brighton. The Chinese Luncheon Room and Yellow Drawing Room are situated at each end of this gallery, with the Centre Room in between.&lt;ref name=&quot;HarrisBellaigue1968&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=pscQAQAAMAAJ |title=Buckingham Palace and its Treasures |last=John Harris |last2=Geoffrey De Bellaigue |last3=Oliver Millar |publisher=Viking Press |year=1968 |page=90}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The original early 19th-century interior designs, many of which still survive, included widespread use of brightly coloured [[scagliola]] and blue and pink [[Lapis lazuli|lapis]], on the advice of Sir&amp;nbsp;Charles Long. [[King Edward&amp;nbsp;VII]] oversaw a partial redecoration in a [[Belle Époque|Belle époque]] cream and gold colour scheme.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones43&quot;&gt;Jones, p. 43.&lt;/ref&gt;

When paying a state visit to Britain, foreign [[heads of state]] are usually entertained by the Queen at Buckingham Palace. They are allocated an extensive  suite of rooms known as the Belgian Suite, situated at the foot of the Minister's Staircase, on the ground floor of the north-facing Garden Wing. Narrow corridors link the rooms of the suite, one of them is given extra height and perspective by [[saucer dome]]s designed by Nash in the style of Soane.&lt;ref name=&quot;harrisp82&quot;&gt;Harris, p. 82.&lt;/ref&gt; A second corridor in the suite has Gothic-influenced [[Vault (architecture)|cross-over vaulting]].&lt;ref name=&quot;harrisp82&quot; /&gt; The Belgian Rooms themselves were decorated in their present style and named after King [[Leopold I of Belgium]], uncle of Queen Victoria and Prince Albert. In 1936, the suite briefly became the private apartments of the palace when [[King Edward&amp;nbsp;VIII]] occupied them.&lt;ref name=&quot;fact&quot; /&gt;

===Court ceremonies===

====Investitures====
[[Investiture]]s, which include the conferring of [[knight]]hoods by dubbing with a sword, and other awards take place in the palace's Ballroom, built in 1854. At {{convert|36.6|m|ft|abbr=on|order=flip}} long, {{convert|18|m|ft|abbr=on|order=flip|-1}} wide and {{convert|13.5|m|ft|abbr=on|order=flip|round=5}} high,&lt;ref name=&quot;fact&quot; /&gt; it is the largest room in the palace. It has replaced the throne room in importance and use. During investitures, the Queen stands on the throne dais beneath a giant, domed velvet canopy, known as a [[shamiana]] or a [[baldachin]], that was used at the [[Delhi Durbar]] in 1911.&lt;ref&gt;Harris, p. 72.&lt;/ref&gt; A military band plays in the musicians' gallery as award recipients approach the Queen and receive their [[honour]]s, watched by their families and friends.&lt;ref name=&quot;Healey, p.364&quot;&gt;Healey, p. 364.&lt;/ref&gt;

====State banquets====
{{ external media&lt;!-- Do not move to external links. Per template documentation: &quot;This template is normally placed in the main body of the article, in the same place that you would normally have placed the image...if it had been available on Wikimedia Commons.&quot; --&gt;
| float = right
| width = 230px
| video1 = [https://vimeo.com/133655898 Transforming the Ballroom for a State Banquet] (timelapse)
}}
State [[banquet]]s also take place in the Ballroom; these formal dinners are held on the first evening of a state visit by a foreign head of state.&lt;ref name=&quot;Healey, p.364&quot; /&gt; On these occasions, for up to 170 guests in formal &quot;white tie and decorations&quot;, including tiaras, the dining table is laid with the Grand Service, a collection of silver-gilt plate made in 1811 for the Prince of Wales, later George&amp;nbsp;IV.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/uknews/theroyalfamily/2457467/Royal-seal-of-approval-for-state-banquet-exhibition.html |title=Royal seal of approval for state banquet exhibition |date=25 July 2008 |work=The Telegraph |access-date=31 January 2016 |location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; The largest and most formal reception at Buckingham Palace takes place every November when the Queen entertains members of the [[diplomatic corps]].&lt;ref&gt;Healey, p. 362.&lt;/ref&gt; On this grand occasion, all the state rooms are in use, as the royal family proceed through them,&lt;ref&gt;Hedley, p. 16.&lt;/ref&gt; beginning at the great north doors of the Picture Gallery. As Nash had envisaged, all the large, double-mirrored doors stand open, reflecting the numerous crystal chandeliers and sconces, creating a deliberate optical illusion of space and light.&lt;ref&gt;Robinson, p. 18.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Other ceremonies and functions====
Smaller ceremonies such as the reception of new ambassadors take place in the &quot;1844 Room&quot;. Here too, the Queen holds small lunch parties, and often meetings of the [[Her Majesty's Most Honourable Privy Council|Privy Council]]. Larger lunch parties often take place in the curved and domed Music Room or the State Dining Room.&lt;ref name=&quot;Healey, pp. 363–365&quot;&gt;Healey, pp. 363–365.&lt;/ref&gt; Since the bombing of the palace chapel in World War&amp;nbsp;II, royal christenings have sometimes taken place in the Music Room. The Queen's first three children were all baptised there.&lt;ref&gt;Robinson, p. 49.&lt;/ref&gt; On all formal occasions, the ceremonies are attended by the [[Yeomen of the Guard]], in their historic uniforms, and other officers of the court such as the [[Lord Chamberlain]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Healey, pp. 363–365&quot; /&gt;

===Former ceremonial at the Palace===

====Court dress====
[[File:Obama and Duke Duchess of Cambridge.jpg|thumb|right|The 1844 Room, a sitting room of the Belgium Suite, also serves as an audience room and is often used for personal investitures.]]
[[File:President Nixon visiting Buckingham Palace with Britain's royal family - NARA - 194606.tif|thumb|President Nixon with members of the royal family in the ground floor Marble Hall]]
Formerly, men not wearing [[military uniform]] wore knee [[breeches]] of 18th-century design. Women's evening dress included trains and [[tiara]]s or feathers in their hair (often both). The dress code governing formal [[Court uniform and dress in the United Kingdom|court uniform and dress]] has progressively relaxed. After the [[First World War]], when [[Mary of Teck|Queen Mary]] wished to follow fashion by raising her skirts a few inches from the ground, she requested a [[lady-in-waiting]] to shorten her own skirt first to gauge the King's reaction. [[King George&amp;nbsp;V]] was horrified, so the Queen kept her hemline unfashionably low.&lt;ref&gt;Healey, p. 233, quoting ''The Memoirs of Mabell, Countess of Airlie'', edited and arranged by Jennifer Ellis, London: Hutchinson, 1962.&lt;/ref&gt; Following his accession in 1936, [[King George&amp;nbsp;VI]] and [[Queen Elizabeth The Queen Mother|Queen Elizabeth]] allowed the hemline of daytime skirts to rise. Today, there is no official dress code.&lt;ref name=&quot;fact&quot; /&gt; Most men invited to Buckingham Palace in the daytime choose to wear [[service uniform]] or [[lounge suit]]s;&lt;ref name=&quot;fact&quot; /&gt; a minority wear [[morning coat]]s, and in the evening, depending on the formality of the occasion, [[black tie]] or [[white tie]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Seldon1999&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=jj2AAAAAIAAJ |title=10 Downing Street: The Illustrated History |last=Anthony Seldon |publisher=Harper Collins Illustrated |year=1999 |isbn=978-0-00-414073-5 |page=202}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Court presentation of débutantes====
[[Débutante]]s were aristocratic young ladies making their first entrée into society through a presentation to the monarch at court. These occasions, known as &quot;coming out&quot;, took place at the palace from the reign of Edward&amp;nbsp;VII. The débutantes entered—wearing full court dress, with three ostrich feathers in their hair—curtsied, performed a backwards walk and a further curtsey, while manoeuvring a dress train of prescribed length. The ceremony, known as an evening court, corresponded to the &quot;court [[drawing room]]s&quot; of Victoria's reign.&lt;ref&gt;Peacocke, pp. 178–179, 244–247.&lt;/ref&gt; After World War&amp;nbsp;II, the ceremony was replaced by less formal afternoon receptions, usually omitting curtsies and court dress.&lt;ref&gt;Peacocke, pp. 264–265.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1958, the Queen abolished the presentation parties for débutantes,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.royal.gov.uk/output/page5299.asp |title=Mailbox |website=Royal Insight Magazine |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080123231607/http://www.royal.gov.uk/output/page5299.asp |archive-date=23 January 2008 |access-date=23 January 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; replacing them with [[Garden at Buckingham Palace#Garden parties|Garden Parties]],{{efn|[[Princess Margaret]] is reputed to have remarked of the débutante presentations: &quot;We had to put a stop to it, every tart in London was getting in.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=You look awfully like the Queen |last=Blaikie |first=Thomas |publisher=Harper Collins |year=2002 |isbn=978-0-00-714874-5 |location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;}} for up to 8,000 invitees in the Garden. They are the largest functions of the year.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.royal.gov.uk/RoyalEventsandCeremonies/GardenParties/TheGuests.aspx |title=Garden parties: The guests |last=Royal Household |website=Official Website of the British Monarchy |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130117060104/http://www.royal.gov.uk/RoyalEventsandCeremonies/GardenParties/TheGuests.aspx |archive-date=17 January 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Security breaches====
[[The boy Jones]] was an intruder who gained entry to the palace on three occasions between 1838 and 1841.&lt;ref&gt;[[Punch (magazine)|Punch]], [http://www.gutenberg.org/dirs/1/7/2/1/17216/17216.txt Volume 1: July–December 1841].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;dickens&quot;&gt;[[Charles Dickens|Dickens, Charles]] (5 July 1885) &quot;[http://john-adcock.blogspot.com/2008/10/boy-jones.html The boy Jones]&quot;, ''[[All the Year Round]]'', pp. 234–37.&lt;/ref&gt; At least 12 people have managed to gain unauthorised entry into the palace or its grounds since 1914,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/morning-mix/wp/2014/09/24/remember-the-visitor-to-the-queens-bedroom-when-it-comes-to-intruders-buckingham-palace-beats-the-white-house-any-day/ |title=Remember the guy who got into the Queen’s bedroom? |last=Tobey, Pam |date=24 September 2014 |work=[[The Washington Post]] |access-date=21 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; including [[Michael Fagan incident|Michael Fagan]], who broke into the palace twice in 1982 and entered the Queen's bedroom on the second occasion. At the time, news media reported that he had a long conversation with the Queen while she waited for security officers to arrive, but in a 2012 interview with ''[[The Independent]]'', Fagan said the Queen ran out of the room, and no conversation took place.&lt;ref name=&quot;independent&quot;&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.independent.co.uk/news/people/profiles/michael-fagan-her-nightie-was-one-of-those-liberty-prints-down-to-her-knees-7179547.html |title=Michael Fagan: 'Her nightie was one of those Liberty prints, down to her knees' |last=Dugan |first=Emily |date=19 February 2012 |work=The Independent on Sunday |access-date=4 January 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was only in 2007 that trespassing on the palace grounds became a specific criminal offence.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/6492003.stm |title=Trespass law targets royal sites |date=24 March 2007 |work=[[BBC News]] |access-date=27 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{efn|Under section 128(1) of the [[Serious Organised Crime and Police Act 2005]], &quot;A person commits an offence if he enters, or is on, any designated site in England and Wales or Northern Ireland as a trespasser&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2005/15/part/4/crossheading/trespass-on-designated-site |title=Serious Organised Crime and Police Act 2005 |date=7 January 2005 |publisher=Legislation.gov.uk |access-date=11 June 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Buckingham Palace is a designated site under the Serious Organised Crime and Police Act 2005 (Designated Sites under Section 128) Order 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2007/930/made |title=The Serious Organised Crime and Police Act 2005 (Designated Sites under Section 128) Order 2007 |date=1 June 2007 |publisher=Legislation.gov.uk |access-date=11 June 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

===Garden and surroundings===
[[File:Buckingham Palace west facade.jpg|thumb|The west façade of Buckingham Palace, faced in [[Bath stone]], seen from the [[Buckingham Palace Garden|palace garden]]]]
{{details|Garden at Buckingham Palace}}
At the rear of the palace is the large and park-like garden, which together with its lake is the largest private garden in London.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.museumoflondon.org.uk/English/Collections/OnlineResources/X20L/Themes/1381/1092/ |title=''Buckingham Palace'' |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080502231028/http://www.museumoflondon.org.uk/English/Collections/OnlineResources/X20L/Themes/1381/1092/ |archive-date=2 May 2008 |access-date=3 February 2009}} ([[Museum of London]].) Retrieved 2 May 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; There, the Queen hosts her annual garden parties each summer and also holds large functions to celebrate royal milestones, such as jubilees. It covers {{convert|40|acres|abbr=on}} and includes a helicopter landing area, a lake, and a tennis court.&lt;ref name=&quot;fact&quot; /&gt;

Adjacent to the palace is the [[Royal Mews]], also designed by Nash, where the royal carriages, including the [[Gold State Coach]], are housed. This [[rococo]] gilt coach, designed by [[Sir&amp;nbsp;William Chambers]] in 1760, has painted panels by [[Giovanni Battista Cipriani|G. B. Cipriani]]. It was first used for the State Opening of Parliament by George&amp;nbsp;III in 1762 and has been used by the monarch for every coronation since George&amp;nbsp;IV. It was last used for the [[Golden Jubilee of Elizabeth&amp;nbsp;II]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Royal Collection|5000048|Gold State Coach}}&lt;/ref&gt; Also housed in the mews are the coach horses used at royal ceremonial processions.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.royal.gov.uk/TheRoyalResidences/TheRoyalMews/TheRoyalMews.aspx |title=The Royal Residences &gt; The Royal Mews |publisher=www.royal.gov.uk |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090710044631/http://www.royal.gov.uk/TheRoyalResidences/TheRoyalMews/TheRoyalMews.aspx |archive-date=10 July 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[The Mall, London|The Mall]], a ceremonial approach route to the palace, was designed by Sir&amp;nbsp;[[Aston Webb]] and completed in 1911 as part of a grand memorial to [[Queen Victoria]]. It extends from [[Admiralty Arch]], across [[St&amp;nbsp;James's Park]] to the [[Victoria Memorial (London)|Victoria Memorial]]. This route is used by the cavalcades and motorcades of visiting heads of state, and by the royal family on state occasions—such as the annual [[Trooping the Colour]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=London |last=Nicholson, Louise |publisher=Frances Lincoln |year=1998 |isbn=978-0-7112-1187-2 |location=London |page=56 |author-link=Louise Nicholson}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Modern history==
[[File:Barack Obama Michelle Obama Queen Elizabeth II Buckingham Palace London.jpg|thumb|Visiting heads of state are received by the Queen at either Buckingham Palace or Windsor Castle. Here, United States President [[Barack Obama]] and [[Michelle Obama]] are greeted in 2009 in the first-floor audience chamber in the private apartments in the north wing.]]
In 1901, the accession of Edward&amp;nbsp;VII saw new life breathed into the palace. The King and his wife, [[Queen Alexandra]], had always been at the forefront of London high society, and their friends, known as &quot;the [[Marlborough House]] Set&quot;, were considered to be the most eminent and fashionable of the age. Buckingham Palace—the Ballroom, Grand Entrance, Marble Hall, Grand Staircase, vestibules and galleries redecorated in the [[Belle Époque]] cream and gold colour scheme they retain today—once again became a setting for entertaining on a majestic scale but leaving some to feel King Edward's heavy redecorations were at odds with Nash's original work.&lt;ref&gt;Robinson (Page 9) asserts that the decorations, including plaster swags and other decorative motifs, are &quot;finicky&quot; and &quot;at odds with Nash's original detailing&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt;

The last major building work took place during the reign of King George&amp;nbsp;V when, in 1913, Sir&amp;nbsp;Aston Webb redesigned Blore's 1850 East Front to resemble in part [[Giacomo Leoni]]'s [[Lyme Park]] in Cheshire. This new, refaced principal façade (of [[Portland stone]]) was designed to be the backdrop to the [[Victoria Memorial (London)|Victoria Memorial]], a large memorial statue of Queen Victoria, placed outside the main gates.&lt;ref&gt;Harris, p. 34.&lt;/ref&gt; George&amp;nbsp;V, who had succeeded Edward&amp;nbsp;VII in 1910, had a more serious personality than his father; greater emphasis was now placed on official entertaining and royal duties than on lavish parties.&lt;ref&gt;Healey, p. 185.&lt;/ref&gt; He arranged a series of [[Royal Command Performance|command performances]] featuring [[jazz]] musicians such as the [[Original Dixieland Jazz Band]] (1919; the first jazz performance for a head of state), [[Sidney Bechet]], and [[Louis Armstrong]] (1932), which earned the palace a nomination in 2009 for a [[Brecon Jazz Festival#(Kind of) Blue Plaque|(Kind of) Blue Plaque]] by the [[Brecon Jazz Festival]] as one of the venues making the greatest contribution to jazz music in the United Kingdom.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://www.thisislondon.co.uk/standard/article-23727267-buckingham-palace-hits-right-note-with-jazz-fans.do |title=Buckingham Palace hits right note with jazz fans |date=3 August 2009 |work=London Evening Standard |access-date=11 August 2010 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100426000757/http://www.thisislondon.co.uk/standard/article-23727267-buckingham-palace-hits-right-note-with-jazz-fans.do |archive-date=26 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.theguardian.com/music/2009/aug/03/buckingham-palace-jazz-plaque-brecon |title=By royal approval: Buckingham Palace's place in jazz history |last=Stephen Bates |date=3 August 2009 |work=[[The Guardian]] |access-date=11 August 2010 |location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; King George&amp;nbsp;V's wife, Queen Mary, was a [[connoisseur]] of the arts, and took a keen interest in the Royal Collection of furniture and art, both restoring and adding to it. Queen Mary also had many new fixtures and fittings installed, such as the pair of marble [[Empire style]] chimneypieces by Benjamin Vulliamy, dating from 1810, which the Queen had installed in the ground floor Bow Room, the huge low room at the centre of the garden façade. Queen Mary was also responsible for the decoration of the Blue Drawing Room.&lt;ref&gt;Healey pp. 221–222.&lt;/ref&gt; This room, {{convert|69|ft|m|abbr=off}} long, previously known as the South Drawing Room, has a ceiling designed by Nash, coffered with huge gilt console brackets.&lt;ref&gt;Harris, p. 63.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Victoria Memorial from within Buckingham Palace.jpg|thumb|Sculptor Sir [[Thomas Brock]] created the [[Victoria Memorial (London)|Victoria Memorial]] in 1911; it was erected in front of the main gates at the palace on a surround constructed by architect Sir Aston Webb.]]
During World War&amp;nbsp;I, the palace, then the home of King George&amp;nbsp;V and Queen Mary, escaped unscathed. Its more valuable contents were evacuated to Windsor, but the royal family remained in residence. The King imposed [[Rationing in the United Kingdom|rationing]] at the palace, much to the dismay of his guests and household.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=King George V |last=Rose |first=Kenneth |publisher=Weidenfeld and Nicolson |year=1983 |isbn=978-0-297-78245-2 |location=London |pages=176–177 |author-link=Kenneth Rose}}&lt;/ref&gt; To the King's later regret, [[David Lloyd George]] persuaded him to go further and ostentatiously lock the wine cellars and refrain from alcohol, to set a good example to the supposedly inebriated working class. The workers continued to imbibe, and the King was left unhappy at his enforced abstinence.&lt;ref&gt;Rose, pp. 178–179.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1938, the north-west pavilion, designed by Nash as a conservatory, was converted into a swimming pool.&lt;ref&gt;Allison and Riddell, p. 69.&lt;/ref&gt;

During World War&amp;nbsp;II, the palace was bombed nine times;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.royalcollection.org.uk/exhibitions/letter-from-queen-elizabeth-to-queen-mary-describing-the-bombing-of-buckingham-palace-13 |title=Letter from Queen Elizabeth to Queen Mary describing the bombing of Buckingham Palace, 13 September 1940 |publisher=Royal Collection Trust |access-date=31 March 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; the most serious and publicised incident destroyed the palace chapel in 1940. This event was shown in cinemas throughout the UK to show the common suffering of rich and poor. One bomb fell in the palace quadrangle while King George&amp;nbsp;VI and Queen Elizabeth were in the palace, and many windows were blown in and the chapel destroyed.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=Royal Feud |last=Thornton |first=Michael |publisher=M. Joseph |year=1984 |page=216}}&lt;/ref&gt; War-time coverage of such incidents was severely restricted, however. The King and Queen were filmed inspecting their bombed home, the smiling Queen, as always, immaculately dressed in a hat and matching coat seemingly unbothered by the damage around her. It was at this time the Queen famously declared: &quot;I'm glad we have been bombed. Now I can look the [[East End]] in the face.&quot; The royal family were seen as sharing their subjects' hardship, as ''[[The Sunday Graphic]]'' reported:

{{quotation|By the Editor: The King and Queen have endured the ordeal which has come to their subjects. For the second time a German bomber has tried to bring death and destruction to the home of Their Majesties&amp;nbsp;... When this war is over the common danger which King George and Queen Elizabeth have shared with their people will be a cherished memory and an inspiration through the years.&lt;ref&gt;''[[The Sunday Graphic]]'', 18 September 1939, p. 1.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

On 15 September 1940, known as the [[Battle of Britain Day]], an RAF pilot, [[Ray Holmes]] of [[No. 504 Squadron RAF]] rammed a German [[Dornier Do 17]] bomber he believed was going to bomb the Palace. Holmes had run out of ammunition and made the quick decision to ram it. Holmes bailed out and the aircraft crashed into the forecourt of [[London Victoria station]].&lt;ref&gt;Price, Alfred. ''The Battle of Britain Day'', Greenhill Books, London, 1990, pp. 49–50 and [[Stephen Bungay]], ''The Most Dangerous Enemy: A History of the Battle of Britain''. Aurum Press, London, 2000, p. 325.&lt;/ref&gt; The bomber's engine was later exhibited at the [[Imperial War Museum]] in London. The British pilot became a [[Queen's Messenger|King's Messenger]] after the war and died at the age of 90 in 2005.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/leicestershire/4398484.stm |title=Pilot who 'saved Palace' honoured |date=2 November 2005 |work=BBC News |access-date=18 March 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On [[Victory in Europe Day|VE Day]]—8 May 1945—the palace was the centre of British celebrations. The King, the Queen, Princess Elizabeth (the future Queen), and [[Princess Margaret, Countess of Snowdon|Princess Margaret]] appeared on the balcony, with the palace's blacked-out windows behind them, to cheers from a vast crowd in [[The Mall, London|The Mall]].&lt;ref&gt;''[http://news.bbc.co.uk/onthisday/hi/dates/stories/may/8/newsid_3580000/3580163.stm 1945: Rejoicing at end of war in Europe]'' (BBC ''On this day''.) Retrieved 3 February 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; The damaged Palace was carefully restored after the war by [[Mowlem|John Mowlem &amp; Co.]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/obituaries/1351908/Sir-Edgar-Beck.html |title=Sir Edgar Beck |date=9 August 2000 |work=The Telegraph |access-date=5 June 2012 |location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was designated a Grade I [[listed building]] in 1970.&lt;ref name=&quot;NHLE&quot;&gt;{{National Heritage List for England| num=1239087 |desc=Buckingham Palace |grade=I |accessdate=18 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===21st century: Royal use and public access===
[[File:Entrance of Queen's Gallery, Buckingham Palace (cropped).jpg|left|thumb|Entrance of the Queen's Gallery]]

Every year, some 50,000 invited guests are entertained at [[garden parties]], receptions, audiences, and banquets. [[Garden at Buckingham Palace#Garden parties|Three garden parties]] are held in the summer, usually in July.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.royalcollection.org.uk/visit/buckinghampalace/about |title=About Buckingham Palace |date=8 March 2016 |publisher=Royal Collection Trust |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20151002102536/https://www.royalcollection.org.uk/visit/buckinghampalace/about |archive-date=2 October 2015 |access-date=8 March 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The forecourt of Buckingham Palace is used for the [[Changing the Queen's Life Guard|Changing of the Guard]], a major ceremony and tourist attraction (daily from April to July; every other day in other months).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.royalcollection.org.uk/visit/buckinghampalace/what-to-see-and-do/changing-the-guard |title=Changing the Guard |publisher=Royal Collection Trust |access-date=8 March 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The palace, like Windsor Castle, is owned by the reigning monarch in right of [[the Crown]]. It is not the monarch's personal property, unlike [[Sandringham House]] and [[Balmoral Castle]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite Hansard |jurisdiction=United Kingdom |house=House of Commons |title=Royal Property |url=http://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_answers/1995/jan/16/royal-property#S6CV0252P0_19950116_CWA_187 |date=16 January 1995 |volume=252 |column=301W }}&lt;/ref&gt; Many of the contents of Buckingham Palace, Windsor Castle, [[Kensington Palace]], and St&amp;nbsp;James's Palace are part of the Royal Collection, held in trust by the Sovereign; they can, on occasion, be viewed by the public at the [[Queen's Gallery]], near the Royal Mews. Unlike the palace and the castle, the purpose-built gallery is open continually and displays a changing selection of items from the collection.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.royalcollection.org.uk/collection/about |title=About the Royal Collection |publisher=[[Royal Collection Trust]] |access-date=8 March 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; It occupies the site of the chapel destroyed by an [[airstrike|air raid]] in World War&amp;nbsp;II.&lt;ref name=&quot;who built&quot; /&gt; The palace's [[state room]]s have been open to the public during August and September and on some dates throughout the year since 1993. The money raised in entry fees was originally put towards the rebuilding of Windsor Castle after the [[1992 Windsor Castle fire|1992 fire]] devastated many of its state rooms.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/special_report/31069.stm |title=Windsor Castle&amp;nbsp;– five years from disaster to triumph |date=17 November 1997 |access-date=8 March 2016 |publisher=BBC}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the year to 31 March 2017, 580,000 people visited the palace, and 154,000 visited the gallery.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://beta.companieshouse.gov.uk/company/02778486/filing-history |title=Full accounts made up to 31 March 2017 |last=Royal Collection Enterprises Limited |date=28 September 2017 |publisher=Companies House |page=3 |access-date=6 February 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Her Majesty's Government]] is responsible for maintaining the palace in exchange for the profits made by the [[Crown Estate]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.hm-treasury.gov.uk/leg_sovereign_grant_faq.htm |title=Sovereign Grant Act: frequently asked questions relating to the Act and on general issues |last=HM Treasury |publisher=The National Archives |url-status=dead |archive-url=http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20130129110402/http:/www.hm-treasury.gov.uk/leg_sovereign_grant_faq.htm |archive-date=29 January 2013 |access-date=22 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; In November 2015, the State Dining Room was closed for six months because its ceiling had become potentially dangerous.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/2015/nov/30/buckingham-palace-dining-room-closed-ceiling-safety |title=Buckingham Palace dining room closed over ceiling safety concerns |date=30 November 2015 |work=The Guardian |access-date=28 May 2018 |agency=Press Association}}&lt;/ref&gt; A 10-year schedule of maintenance work, including new plumbing, wiring, boilers, and radiators, and the installation of [[solar panels]] on the roof, has been estimated to cost £369&amp;nbsp;million and was approved by the [[Prime Minister of the United Kingdom|prime minister]] in November 2016. It will be funded by a temporary increase in the [[Sovereign Grant]] paid from the income of the Crown Estate and is intended to extend the building's working life by at least 50 years.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/2016/11/18/buckingham-palace-to-get-369m-facelift-over-10-years/ |title=Queen to remain in residence as Buckingham Palace gets £369m taxpayer-funded facelift to avert 'catastrophic building failure' |last=Gordon Rayner |date=18 November 2016 |work=The Telegraph |access-date=18 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-38025513 |title=Buckingham Palace to get £369m refurbishment |date=18 November 2016 |work=BBC News |access-date=18 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; In March 2017, the [[House of Commons of the United Kingdom|House of Commons]] backed funding for the project by 464 votes to 56.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-politics-39280770 |title=Buckingham Palace repairs funding approved by MPs |date=15 March 2017 |work=BBC News}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Buckingham Palace is a symbol and home of the British monarchy, an art gallery, and a tourist attraction. Behind the gilded railings and gates that were completed by the [[Bromsgrove Guild]] in 1911&lt;ref name=&quot;rob9&quot; /&gt; and Webb's famous façade, which has been described in a book published by the [[Royal Collection Trust]] as looking &quot;like everybody's idea of a palace&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;rob9&quot; /&gt; is not only a weekday home of [[Queen Elizabeth II]] and [[Prince Philip]] but also the London residence of the [[Prince Andrew, Duke of York|Duke of York]] and the [[Prince Edward, Earl of Wessex|Earl]] and [[Sophie, Countess of Wessex|Countess of Wessex]]. The palace also houses [[Royal Households of the United Kingdom|their offices]], as well as those of the [[Anne, Princess Royal|Princess Royal]] and [[Princess Alexandra, The Honourable Lady Ogilvy|Princess Alexandra]], and is the workplace of more than 800 people.&lt;ref name=&quot;fact&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite magazine |last=Hill |first=Erin |date=14 March 2019 |title=Meghan Markle and Prince Harry Have Split Royal Households from Kate Middleton and Prince William |url=https://people.com/royals/meghan-markle-prince-harry-split-households-kate-middleton-prince-william/ |magazine=People |access-date=14 March 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|London||Architecture}}
* [[Flags at Buckingham Palace]]
* [[List of British royal residences]]
* [[Queen's Guard]]

==Notes==
{{Noteslist}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Bibliography==
{{Refbegin|30em}}
* Allison, Ronald; Riddell, Sarah (1991). ''The Royal Encyclopedia''. London: Macmillan. {{ISBN|0-333-53810-2}}
* Blaikie, Thomas (2002). ''You Look Awfully Like the Queen: Wit and Wisdom from the House of Windsor''. London: Harper Collins. {{ISBN|0-00-714874-7}}.
* Goring, O. G. (1937). ''From Goring House to Buckingham Palace''. London: Ivor Nicholson &amp; Watson.
* Harris, John; de Bellaigue, Geoffrey; &amp; Miller, Oliver (1968). ''Buckingham Palace''. London: Nelson. {{ISBN|0-17-141011-4}}.
* Healey, Edma (1997). ''The Queen's House: A Social History of Buckingham Palace''. London: Penguin Group. {{ISBN|0-7181-4089-3}}.
* Hedley, Olwen (1971) ''The Pictorial History of Buckingham Palace''. Pitkin, {{ISBN|0-85372-086-X}}.
* {{Cite book |title=Architecture of England, Scotland, and Wales |last=Jones |first=Nigel R. |publisher=Greenwood Publishing Group |year=2005 |isbn=978-0-313-31850-4}}
* {{Cite book |title=Twilight of Splendor: The Court of Queen Victoria During Her Diamond Jubilee Year |last=King |first=Greg |publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons |year=2007 |isbn=978-0-470-04439-1}}
* [[Compton Mackenzie|Mackenzie, Compton]] (1953). ''The Queen's House''. London: Hutchinson.
* Nash, Roy (1980). ''Buckingham Palace: The Place and the People''. London: Macdonald Futura. {{ISBN|0-354-04529-6}}.
* {{Cite book |title=The Story of Buckingham Palace |last=Peacocke, M. D. |publisher=Odhams Press |year=1951 |location=London}}
* {{Cite book |title=Queen Victoria: A Biographical Companion |last=Rappaport |first=Helen |publisher=ABC-CLIO |year=2003 |isbn=978-1-85109-355-7}}
* Robinson, John Martin (1999). ''Buckingham Palace''. Published by The [[Royal Collection]], St&amp;nbsp;James's Palace, London {{ISBN|1-902163-36-2}}.
* Williams, Neville (1971). ''Royal Homes''. The Lutterworth Press. {{ISBN|0-7188-0803-7}}.
* [[Cecil Woodham-Smith|Woodham-Smith, Cecil]] (1973). ''Queen Victoria'' ''(vol 1)'' Hamish Hamilton Ltd.
* Wright, Patricia (1999; first published 1996). ''The Strange History of Buckingham Palace''. Stroud, Gloucs.: Sutton Publishing Ltd. {{ISBN|0-7509-1283-9}}.
{{Refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Buckingham Palace}}
{{Wikivoyage}}
* [https://www.royal.uk/royal-residences-buckingham-palace Buckingham Palace] at the Royal Family website
* [http://www.british-history.ac.uk/report.asp?compid=45183 Account of Buckingham Palace, with prints of Arlington House and Buckingham House] from ''Old and New London'' (1878)
* [http://www.british-history.ac.uk/report.asp?compid=41820 Account of the acquisition of the Manor of Ebury] from ''Survey of London'' (1977)
* [https://www.rct.uk/visit/the-state-rooms-buckingham-palace The State Rooms, Buckingham Palace] at the [[Royal Collection Trust]]
* {{osmrelation|5208404}}

{{Royal palaces in the United Kingdom}}
{{London landmarks}}

[[Category:Buckingham Palace| ]]
[[Category:1837 establishments in England]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures on The Mall, London]]
[[Category:Edward Blore buildings]]
[[Category:Edwardian architecture in London]]
[[Category:Georgian architecture in London]]
[[Category:Grade I listed buildings in the City of Westminster]]
[[Category:Grade I listed palaces]]
[[Category:Historic house museums in London]]
[[Category:Houses completed in 1703]]
[[Category:Houses completed in 1762]]
[[Category:John Nash buildings]]
[[Category:Museums in the City of Westminster]]
[[Category:Neoclassical architecture in London]]
[[Category:Neoclassical palaces]]
[[Category:Palaces in London]]
[[Category:Regency architecture in London]]
[[Category:Royal buildings in London]]
[[Category:Royal residences in the City of Westminster]]
[[Category:Terminating vistas in the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Tourist attractions in the City of Westminster]]</text>
      <sha1>3deu8k07hdfm7ihqr96uqnpgrj9ebzf</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
