  <page>
    <title>Bodhisattva</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3968</id>
    <revision>
      <id>940728165</id>
      <parentid>934789700</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-14T06:31:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>103.105.239.9</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Just like in english.. It tibetan some words pronounced different to its spelling....</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{About|Buddhism|the 2010 film|Bodhisattva (film)|the song by Steely Dan|Countdown to Ecstasy}}
{{short description|Any person who is on the path towards Buddhahood but has not yet attained it}}

[[File:Prajnaparamita Java.jpg|thumb|[[Prajnaparamita]] bodhisattva statue, [[Java, Indonesia]]]]

{{Buddhist term
|title=Bodhisattva
|en=Bodhisattva
|pi=बोधिसत्त
|ta=போதிசத்துவர்
|sa=बोधिसत्त्व
|bn=বোধিসত্ত্ব
|si= [[:si:බෝධිසත්ත්ව|බෝධි සත්ත්ව]]
|vi=Bồ Tát
|hn=菩薩
|zh=菩提薩埵（菩薩）, 菩提萨埵（菩萨）
|zh-Latn=pútísàduǒ (púsà) )&lt;br /&gt;([[Wade–Giles]]: p'u&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;-sa&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;)&lt;br/&gt;([[Jyutping]]: pou4 tai4 saat3 do3)
|ja=菩薩
|ja-Latn=bosatsu
|ko=보살, 菩薩
|ko-Latn=bosal
|my=ဗောဓိသတ်
|my-Latn=bɔ́dḭθaʔ
|mnw=တြုံလၟောဝ်ကျာ်
|mnw-Latn=kraoh kəmo caik
|th=โพธิสัตว์&lt;br/&gt;phothisat
|km=ពោធិសត្វ
|km-Latn=Pothisat
|bo=བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་
|bo-Latn=chang chub sems dpa
}}
{{Buddhism}}
In [[Buddhism]], a '''bodhisattva''' ({{IPAc-en|ˌ|b|oʊ|d|iː|ˈ|s|ʌ|t|v|ə}} {{respell|BOH|dee|SUT|və}})&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.collinsdictionary.com/dictionary/english/bodhisattva &quot;Bodhisattva&quot;]. ''[[Collins English Dictionary]]''.&lt;/ref&gt; is any person who is on the path towards [[Buddhahood]].

In the [[Early Buddhist schools]] as well as modern [[Theravada|Theravada Buddhism]], a bodhisattva (Pali: ''bodhisatta'') refers to anyone who has made a resolution to become a [[Buddha (title)|Buddha]] and has also received a confirmation or prediction from a living Buddha that this will be so.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

In [[Mahayana|Mahayana Buddhism]], a bodhisattva refers to anyone who has generated ''[[bodhicitta]]'', a spontaneous wish and compassionate mind to attain Buddhahood for the benefit of all [[Sentient beings (Buddhism)|sentient beings]].&lt;ref&gt;''The Bodhisattva Vow'': A Practical Guide to Helping Others, page 1, [[Tharpa Publications]] (2nd. ed., 1995) {{ISBN|978-0-948006-50-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Early Buddhism and the Nikāya schools ==
&lt;!-- &quot;Merit § Merit and Nirvana&quot; links here --&gt;
&lt;!-- &quot;Filial_piety_in_Buddhism&quot;  links here --&gt;
[[Image:Gandhara, rilievo col buddha shakyamuni che medita nella grotta indrashala e il buddha dipankara, II-III secolo.jpg|thumb|right|[[Greco-Buddhist art|Gandharan relief]] depicting the bodhisatta (future [[Gautama Buddha]]) taking a vow at the foot of [[Dipankara Buddha]], [[Art Institute of Chicago]].]]
[[Image:DevoteeDetail.JPG|thumb|150px|upright|Probable early image of a bodhisattva ([[Bimaran casket]], 50 CE).&lt;ref name=&quot;Crossroads&quot;&gt;&quot;The crossroads of Asia&quot;, edited by Ellizabeth Errington and [[Joe Cribb]], The ancient India and Iran Trust, 1992, {{ISBN|0951839918}}, pp. 189–190&lt;/ref&gt;]]
[[Image:Ascetic Sumedha and Dipankara Buddha.jpg|thumb|right|Modern depiction of the bodhisatta resolution (''praṇidhāna'') in front of [[Dipankara Buddha|Dipankara]].]][[File:Bodhisattva Avalokitesvara-BMA.jpg|thumb|upright|Bronze statue of the bodhisatta [[Avalokiteśvara]]. [[Sri Lanka]], c. 750 CE. ]]

In [[early Buddhism]], the term ''bodhisatta'' is used in the [[Early Buddhist Texts|early texts]] to refer to Gautama Buddha in his previous lives&lt;ref&gt;Basham, A.L. (1981). The evolution of the concept of the bodhisattva. In: Leslie S Kawamura, The bodhisattva doctrine in Buddhism, Published for the Canadian Corporation for Studies in Religion by Wilfrid Laurier University Press, p. 19&lt;/ref&gt; and as a young man in his current life in the period during which he was working towards his own [[moksha|liberation]]. During his discourses, to recount his experiences as a young aspirant he regularly uses the phrase &quot;When I was an unenlightened bodhisatta...&quot; The term therefore connotes a being who is &quot;bound for enlightenment&quot;, in other words, a person whose aim is to become fully enlightened. In the [[Pāli Canon|Pāli canon]], the bodhisatta is also described as someone who is still subject to birth, illness, death, sorrow, defilement, and delusion. Some of the previous lives of the Buddha as a bodhisattva are featured in the [[Jataka tales]].

According to the [[Theravada|Theravāda]] monk [[Bhikkhu Bodhi]], the bodhisattva path is not taught in the earliest strata of Buddhist texts such as the Pali [[Nikayas]] (and their counterparts such as the Chinese [[Āgama (Buddhism)|Āgamas]]) which instead focus on the ideal of the [[Arahant]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.accesstoinsight.org/lib/authors/bodhi/arahantsbodhisattvas.html|title=Arahants, Bodhisattvas and Buddhas}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The oldest known story about how [[Gautama Buddha]] becomes a bodhisattva is the story of his encounter with the previous Buddha, [[Dīpankara Buddha|Dīpankara]]. During this encounter, a previous incarnation of Gautama, variously named [[Sumedha|Sumedha, Megha, or Sumati]] offers five blue lotuses and spreads out his hair or entire body for [[Dīpankara Buddha|Dīpankara]] to walk on, resolving to one day become a Buddha. [[Dīpankara Buddha|Dīpankara]] then confirms that they will attain [[Buddhahood]].&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;Drewes, David, ''[https://www.academia.edu/34935437/Mahayana_Sutras_and_the_Opening_of_the_Bodhisattva_Path_Updated_2019_?email_work_card=title Mahāyāna Sūtras and Opening of the Bodhisattva Path]'', Paper presented at the XVIII the IABS Congress, Toronto 2017, Updated 2019.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; Early Buddhist authors saw this story as indicating that the making of a resolution (''abhinīhāra'') in the presence of a living Buddha and his prediction/confirmation of one's future Buddhahood was necessary to become a bodhisattva. According to Drewes, &quot;all known models of the path to Buddhahood developed from this basic understanding.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

The path is explained differently by the various [[Nikaya Buddhism|Nikaya schools]]. In the Theravāda ''[[Buddhavamsa|Buddhavaṃsa]]'' (1st-2nd century BCE), after receiving the prediction, Gautama took four [[Asaṃkhyeya|''asaṃkheyyas'']] (&quot;incalculable aeons&quot;) and a hundred thousand, shorter [[Kalpa (aeon)|''kalpas'']] (aeons) to reach Buddhahood.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

The [[Sarvastivada|Sarvāstivāda]] school had similar models about how the Buddha Gautama became a bodhisattva. They held it took him three [[Asaṃkhyeya|''asaṃkhyeyas'']] and ninety one ''kalpas'' (aeons) to become a Buddha after his resolution (''praṇidhāna'') in front of a past Buddha. During the first ''[[asaṃkhyeya]]'' he is said to have encountered and served 75,000 Buddhas, and 76,000 in the second, after which he received his first prediction (''vyākaraṇa'') of future Buddhahood from [[Dīpankara Buddha|Dīpankara]], meaning that he could no longer fall back from the path to Buddhahood.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt; Thus, the presence of a living Buddha is also necessary for [[Sarvastivada|Sarvāstivāda]]. The [[Mahavibhasa|''Mahāvibhāṣā'']] explains that its discussion of the bodhisattva path is partly meant &quot;to stop those who are in fact not bodhisattvas from giving rise to the self-conceit that they are.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

The ''[[Mahāvastu]]'' of the [[Mahāsāṃghika]]-[[Lokottaravāda|Lokottaravādins]] presents four stages of the bodhisattva path without giving specific time frames (though its said to take various [[Asaṃkhyeya|''asaṃkhyeya kalpas'']]):&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

# Natural (''prakṛti''), one first plants the roots of merit in front of a Buddha to attain Buddhahood.
# Resolution (''praṇidhāna''), one makes their first resolution to attain Buddhahood in the presence of a Buddha.
# Continuing (''anuloma''), one continues to practice until one meets a Buddha who confirms one's future Buddhahood.
# Irreversible (''anivartana''), at this stage, one cannot fall back.

=== Later Theravāda ===
The [[Sri Lankan Buddhism|Sri Lankan]] commentator [[Dhammapāla|Dhammapala]] in his commentary on the ''[[Cariyapitaka|Cariyāpiṭaka]]'', a text which focuses on the bodhisatta path, notes that to become a bodhisatta one must make a valid resolution in front of a living Buddha, which confirms that one is irreversible (''anivattana'') from the attainment of Buddhahood. The [[Jataka tales|''Nidānakathā'']], as well as the ''[[Buddhavamsa|Buddhavaṃsa]]'' and ''[[Cariyapitaka|Cariyāpiṭaka]]'' commentaries makes this explicit by stating that one cannot use a substitute (such as a [[Bodhi Tree|Bodhi tree]], [[Buddharupa|Buddha statue]] or [[Stupa]]) for the presence of a living Buddha, since only a Buddha has the knowledge for making a reliable prediction. This is the generally accepted view maintained in orthodox [[Theravada]] today.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt; The idea is that any resolution to attain Buddhahood may easily be forgotten or abandoned during the aeons ahead. The Burmese monk [[Ledi Sayadaw]] (1846–1923) explains that though it is easy to make vows for future Buddhahood by oneself, it is very difficult to maintain the necessary conduct and views during periods when the Dharma has disappeared from the world. One will easily fall back during such periods and this is why one is not truly a full bodhisatta until one receives recognition from a living Buddha.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

Because of this, it was and remains a common practice in Theravada to attempt to establish the necessary conditions to meet the future Buddha [[Maitreya]] and thus receive a prediction from him. Medieval Theravada literature and inscriptions report the aspirations of monks, kings and ministers to meet Maitreya for this purpose. Modern figures such as [[Anagarika Dharmapala]] (1864–1933), and [[U Nu]] (1907–1995) both sought to receive a prediction from a Buddha in the future and believed meritorious actions done for the good of Buddhism would help in their endeavor to become bodhisattas in the future.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

Over time the term came to be applied to other figures besides Gautama Buddha in Theravada lands, possibly due to the influence of [[Mahayana]]. The Theravada [[Abhayagiri vihāra|Abhayagiri]] tradition of Sri Lanka practiced Mahayana Buddhism and was very influential until the 12th century.&lt;ref&gt;Hoiberg, Dale H., ed. (2010). &quot;Abhayagiri&quot;. ''Encyclopædia Britannica''. I: A–ak Bayes (15th ed.). Chicago, Illinois: Encyclopædia Britannica Inc. p. 30. {{ISBN|978-1-59339-837-8}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Kings of [[Sri Lanka]] were often described as bodhisattvas, starting at least as early as [[Siri Sangha Bodhi I of Anuradhapura|Sirisanghabodhi]] (r. 247–249), who was renowned for his compassion, took vows for the welfare of the citizens, and was regarded as a [[Mahāsattva|mahāsatta]] (Sanskrit ''mahāsattva''), an epithet used almost exclusively in [[Mahayana|Mahayana Buddhism]].&lt;ref&gt;Holt, John. ''Buddha in the Crown : Avalokitesvara in the Buddhist Traditions of Sri Lanka.'' 1991. p. 59&lt;/ref&gt; Many other Sri Lankan kings from the 3rd until the 15th century were also described as bodhisattvas and their royal duties were sometimes clearly associated with the practice of the [[Pāramitā|Ten Pāramitās]].&lt;ref&gt;Holt, John. ''Buddha in the Crown : Avalokitesvara in the Buddhist Traditions of Sri Lanka.'' 1991. pp. 59–60&lt;/ref&gt; In some cases, they explicitly claimed to have received predictions of Buddhahood in past lives.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

Theravadin [[bhikkhu]] and scholar [[Walpola Rahula]] stated that the bodhisattva ideal has traditionally been held to be higher than the state of a ''[[śrāvaka]]'' not only in Mahayana but also in Theravada Buddhism. He also quotes the 10th century king of Sri Lanka, [[List of Sri Lankan monarchs#House of Lambakanna II .28691.E2.80.931017.29|Mahinda IV]] (956–972 CE), who had the words inscribed &quot;none but the bodhisattvas will become kings of a prosperous Lanka,&quot; among other examples.&lt;ref&gt;Holt, John. ''Buddha in the Crown : Avalokitesvara in the Buddhist Traditions of Sri Lanka.'' 1991. p.  60&lt;/ref&gt;
{{quote|But the fact is that both the Theravada and the Mahayana unanimously accept the Bodhisattva ideal as the highest...Although the Theravada holds that anybody can be a Bodhisattva, it does not stipulate or insist that all must be Bodhisattva which is considered not practical.|Walpola Rahula, ''Bodhisattva Ideal in Buddhism''&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.budsas.org/ebud/ebdha126.htm|title=Bodhisattva Ideal in Buddhism (from ''Gems of Buddhist Wisdom'')|author=Rahula, Walpola|publisher=Buddhist Missionary Society, 1996}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Jeffrey Samuels echoes this perspective, noting that while in Mahayana Buddhism the bodhisattva path is held to be universal and for everyone, in Theravada it is &quot;reserved for and appropriated by certain exceptional people.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Samuels, J. THE BODHISATTVA IDEAL IN THERAVAADA, BUDDHIST THEORY AND PRACTICE: A REEVALUATION OF THE BODHISATTVA-`SRAAVAKA OPPOSITION; Philosophy East and West Volume 47, Number 3 July 1997 pp. 399–415, University of Hawai'i Press&lt;/ref&gt; Paul Williams writes that some modern Theravada meditation masters in [[Thailand]] are popularly regarded as bodhisattvas.&lt;ref&gt;Williams, Paul. ''Mahāyāna Buddhism: The Doctrinal Foundations.'' Taylor &amp; Francis, 1989, p. 328.&lt;/ref&gt;

==In Mahāyāna Buddhism==
[[Image:Liao Dynasty Avalokitesvara Statue Clear.jpeg|thumb|right|upright|Wood carving of [[Avalokiteśvara]]. [[Liao dynasty|Liao China]], 907–1125]]
[[Image:Ajanta Padmapani.jpg|thumb|right|upright|Mural of [[Padmapani]] in [[Ajanta Caves]]. India, 5th century]]
[[Image:Bodhisattva Ghorband Musée Guimet 2418.jpg|thumb|right|upright|Clay sculpture of a bodhisattva. [[Afghanistan]], 7th century]]

===Early Mahāyāna===
[[Image:Twenty-Five Bodhisattvas Descending from Heaven, c. 1300.jpg|thumb|right|''Twenty-five Bodhisattvas Descending from Heaven''. Japanese painting, {{circa}}{{nbsp}}1300]]
[[Mahayana|Mahāyāna]] Buddhism (often also called ''Bodhisattvayāna'', or the &quot;Bodhisattva Vehicle&quot;) is based principally upon the path of a bodhisattva.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nattier, Jan 2003 p. 174&quot;&gt;Nattier, Jan (2003), ''A few good men: the Bodhisattva path according to the Inquiry of Ugra'': p. 174&lt;/ref&gt; This path was seen as nobler than becoming an [[arhat]] or a [[Pratyekabuddha|solitary Buddha]]. According to David Drewes, &quot;Mahayana sutras unanimously depict the path beginning with the first arising of the thought of becoming a Buddha (''prathamacittotpāda''), or the initial arising of ''[[bodhicitta]]'', typically aeons before one first receives a Buddha’s prediction, and apply the term bodhisattva from this point.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

The ''{{IAST|[[Aṣṭasāhasrikā Prajñāpāramitā Sūtra]]}}'', one of the earliest known Mahayana texts, contains a simple and brief definition for the term ''bodhisattva'', which is also the earliest known Mahāyāna definition.&lt;ref&gt;Mall, Linnart. ''Studies in the Astasahasrika Prajnaparamita and Other Essays.'' Motilal Banarsidass. 2005. pp. 53–54.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hirakawa, Akira. ''A history of Indian Buddhism: from Śākyamuni to Early Mahāyāna.'' Motilal Banarsidass. 2007. p. 297.&lt;/ref&gt; This definition is given as the following: &quot;Because he has [[bodhi]] as his aim, a bodhisattva-[[mahāsattva]] is so called.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Conze, Edward. ''The Perfection of Wisdom in Eight Thousand Lines and its Verse Summary.'' Grey Fox Press. 2001. p. 89.&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''Aṣṭasāhasrikā'', also divides the path into three stages. The first stage is that of bodhisattvas who “first set out in the vehicle” (''prathamayānasaṃprasthita''), then there is the “irreversible” (''avinivartanīya'') stage, and finally the third “bound by one more birth” (''ekajātipratibaddha''), as in, destined to become a Buddha in the next life.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt; Drewes also notes that:&lt;blockquote&gt;When Mahāyāna sūtras present stories of Buddhas and bodhisattvas’ first arising of the thought of attaining Buddhahood, they invariably depict it as taking place in the presence of a Buddha, suggesting that they shared with all known nikāya traditions the understanding that this is a necessary condition for entering the path. In addition, though this key fact is often obscured in scholarship, they apparently never encourage anyone to become a bodhisattva or present any ritual or other means of doing so. Like nikāya texts, they also regard the status of new or recent bodhisattvas as largely meaningless. The ''Aṣṭasāhasrikā'', for instance, states that as many bodhisattvas as there grains of sand in the Ganges turn back from the pursuit of Buddhahood and that out of innumerable beings who give rise to bodhicitta and progress toward Buddhahood, only one or two will reach the point of becoming irreversible.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;

Drewes also adds that early texts like the ''Aṣṭasāhasrikā'' treat bodhisattvas who are beginners (''ādikarmika'') or &quot;not long set out in the [great] vehicle&quot; with scorn, describing them as &quot;blind&quot;, &quot;unintelligent&quot;, &quot;lazy&quot; and &quot;weak&quot;. Early Mahayana works identify them with those who reject Mahayana or who abandon Mahayana, and they are seen as likely to become ''[[śrāvaka]]s''  (those on the ''[[arhat]]'' path). Rather than encouraging them to become bodhisattvas, what early Mahayana sutras like the ''Aṣṭa'' do is to help individuals determine if they have already received a prediction in a past life, or if they are close to this point.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt; The ''Aṣṭa'' provides a variety of methods, including forms of ritual or [[divination]], [[Dream interpretation|methods dealing with dreams]] and various tests, especially tests based on one's reaction to the hearing of the content in the ''Aṣṭasāhasrikā'' itself. The text states that encountering and accepting its teachings mean one is close to being given a prediction and that if one does not &quot;shrink back, cower or despair&quot; from the text, but &quot;firmly believes it&quot;, one is irreversible. Many other Mahayana sutras such as the ''Akṣobhyavyūha'' and the ''[[Śūraṅgama Samādhi Sūtra|Śūraṃgamasamādhi Sūtra]]'' present textual approaches to determine one's status as an advanced bodhisattva. These mainly consist in one's attitude towards listening to, believing, preaching, proclaiming, copying or memorizing and reciting the sutra.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt; According to Drewes, this claim that merely having faith in Mahāyāna sūtras meant that one was an advanced bodhisattva, was a departure from previous Nikaya views about bodhisattvas. It created new groups of Buddhists who accepted each other's bodhisattva status.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

Some of early depictions of the Bodhisattva path in texts such as the ''[[Ugraparipṛcchā Sūtra]]'' describe it as an arduous, difficult monastic path suited only for the few which is nevertheless the most glorious path one can take. Three kinds of bodhisattvas are mentioned: the forest, city, and monastery bodhisattvas—with forest dwelling being promoted a superior, even necessary path in sutras such as the ''Ugraparipṛcchā'' and the [[Samadhiraja Sutra|''Samadhiraja'']] sutras.&lt;ref&gt;Ray, Reginald. Buddhist saints in India, p. 252.&lt;/ref&gt; The early ''Rastrapalapariprccha sutra'' also promotes a solitary life of meditation in the forests, far away from the distractions of the householder life. The ''Rastrapala'' is also highly critical of monks living in monasteries and in cities who are seen as not practicing meditation and morality.&lt;ref&gt;Ray, Reginald. Buddhist saints in India, p. 265.&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Ratnagunasamcayagatha'' also says the bodhisattva should undertake ascetic practices (''[[dhutanga]]''), &quot;wander freely without a home&quot;, practice the [[paramitas]] and train under a guru in order to perfect his meditation practice and realization of [[prajnaparamita|''prajñaparamita'']].&lt;ref&gt;Ray, Reginald. Buddhist saints in India, p. 255.&lt;/ref&gt; Some scholars have used these texts to argue for &quot;the forest hypothesis&quot;, the theory that the initial Bodhisattva ideal was associated with a strict forest [[asceticism]]. But other scholars point out that many other Mahayana sutras do not promote this ideal, focusing on sutra based practices.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot;&gt;Drewes, David, Early Indian Mahayana Buddhism II: New Perspectives, ''Religion Compass'' 4/2 (2010): 66–74, {{doi|10.1111/j.1749-8171.2009.00193.x}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some Mahayana sutras promoted another revolutionary doctrinal turn, claiming that the three vehicles of the ''[[Śrāvakayāna]], [[Pratyekabuddhayāna]]'' and the ''[[Bodhisattvayāna]]'' were really just one vehicle (''[[Ekayāna|ekayana]]''). This is most famously promoted in the ''[[Lotus Sūtra]]'' which claims that the very idea of three separate vehicles is just an ''[[upaya]]'', a skillful device invented by the Buddha to get beings of various abilities on the path. But ultimately, it will be revealed to them that there is only one vehicle, the ''[[Ekayāna|ekayana]]'', which ends in Buddhahood.&lt;ref&gt;Silk, Jonathan; Hinüber, Oskar von; Eltschinger, Vincent; eds. (2016). &quot;Lotus Sutra&quot;, in Brill's Encyclopedia of Buddhism, Volume 1: Literature and Languages. Leiden: Brill. p.&amp;nbsp;147&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Mature Mahāyāna ===
Over time, Mahayana Buddhists developed mature systematized doctrines about the bodhisattva path. The authors of the various [[Madhyamaka]] shastras (treatises) often presented the view of the [[Ekayāna|''ekayana'']]. The texts and sutras associated with the [[Yogachara|Yogacara]] school developed a different theory of three separate ''gotras'' or lineages, that inherently predisposed a person to either the vehicle of the ''[[arhat]]'', ''[[pratyekabuddha]]'' or [[Buddhahood|''samyak-saṃbuddha'']] (fully self awakened one).&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt; However, the term was also used in a broader sense. According to the eight century Mahāyāna philosopher [[Haribhadra (Buddhist philosopher)|Haribhadra]], the term &quot;bodhisattva&quot; can refer to those who follow any of the three vehicles, since all are working towards ''[[Enlightenment in Buddhism|bodhi]]'' (awakening). Therefore, the specific term for a Mahāyāna bodhisattva is a ''mahāsattva'' (great being) ''bodhisattva''.&lt;ref name=&quot;:11&quot;&gt;Williams, Paul, ''Mahayana Buddhism: The Doctrinal Foundations,'' Routledge, 2008, p. 55.&lt;/ref&gt; According to [[Atiśa]]'s 11th century ''[[Bodhipathapradīpa]],'' the central defining feature of a Mahāyāna bodhisattva is the universal aspiration to end suffering for all sentient beings, which is termed ''[[bodhicitta]]'' (the heart set on awakening).&lt;ref name=&quot;:13&quot;&gt;Williams, Paul, ''Mahayana Buddhism: The Doctrinal Foundations,'' Routledge, 2008, pp. 195–196.&lt;/ref&gt; Later Sanskrit Mahayana Buddhists also developed specific rituals and devotional acts for the arising of this absolutely central quality of ''bodhicitta'', such as the &quot;seven part worship&quot; (''Saptāṇgapūjā'' or ''Saptavidhā Anuttarapūjā''). This ritual form is visible in the works of [[Shantideva]] (8th century) and includes:&lt;ref&gt;Har Dayal, ''The Bodhisattva Doctrine in Buddhist Sanskrit Literature,'' Motilal Banarsidass Publ., 1999, p. 54.&lt;/ref&gt;

* ''Vandana'' (obeisance, bowing down)
* ''[[Puja (Buddhism)|Puja]]'' (worship of the Buddhas)
* ''Sarana-gamana'' (going for [[Refuge (Buddhism)|refuge]])
* ''Papadesana'' (confession of bad deeds)
* ''Punyanumodana'' (rejoicing in merit of the good deeds of oneself and others) 
* ''Adhyesana'' (prayer, entreaty) and ''yacana'' (supplication) – request to Buddhas and Bodhisattvas to continue preaching Dharma
* ''Atmabhavadi-parityagah'' (surrender)

Contemporary Mahāyāna Buddhism follows this model and encourages everyone to give rise to bodhicitta and ceremonially take [[bodhisattva vows]]. With these vows, one makes the promise to work for the complete enlightenment of all [[Sentient beings (Buddhism)|sentient beings]] by practicing the transcendent virtues or [[Pāramitā|paramitas]].&lt;ref&gt;''The Bodhisattva Vow: A Practical Guide to Helping Others'', pp. 4–12, [[Tharpa Publications]] (2nd. ed., 1995) {{ISBN|978-0-948006-50-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Related to the different views on the different types of [[Yana (Buddhism)|''yanas'']] or vehicles is the question of a bodhisattva's relationship to [[Nirvana (Buddhism)|nirvāṇa]]. In the various Mahāyāna texts, two theories can be discerned. One view is the idea that a bodhisattva must postpone their awakening until full Buddhahood is attained (at which point one ceases to be reborn, which is the classical view of [[Nirvana (Buddhism)|nirvāṇa]]). This view is promoted in some sutras like the ''Pañcavimsatisahasrika-prajñaparamita-sutra.&lt;ref name=&quot;:10&quot;&gt;Williams, Paul, ''Mahayana Buddhism: The Doctrinal Foundations,'' Routledge, 2008, pp. 59–60.&lt;/ref&gt;'' The second theory is the idea that there are two kinds of [[Nirvana (Buddhism)|nirvāṇa]], the [[Nirvana (Buddhism)|nirvāṇa]] of an arhat and a superior type of [[Nirvana (Buddhism)|nirvāṇa]] called [[Nirvana (Buddhism)#Apratiṣṭhita nirvāna|''apratiṣṭhita (''non-abiding)]] that allows a Buddha to remain engaged in the world. This doctrine developed in [[Yogachara|Yogacara]]. As noted by Paul Williams, the idea of ''apratiṣṭhita [[Nirvana (Buddhism)|nirvāṇa]]'' may have taken some time to develop and is not obvious in some of the early Mahāyāna literature, therefore while earlier sutras may sometimes speak of &quot;postponement&quot;, later texts saw no need to postpone the &quot;superior&quot; ''apratiṣṭhita [[Nirvana (Buddhism)|nirvāṇa]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;:10&quot; /&gt;

In this Yogacara model, the bodhisattva definitely rejects and avoids the liberation of the ''śravaka'' and ''pratyekabuddha'', described in Mahāyāna literature as either inferior or &quot;[[Hinayana|''Hina'']]&quot; (as in [[Asaṅga]]'s fourth century ''[[Yogācārabhūmi]]'') or as ultimately false or illusory (as in the ''Lotus Sūtra'').&lt;ref&gt;&quot;bodhisattva&quot; In ''The Princeton Dictionary of Buddhism'' (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 2013), 135.&lt;/ref&gt; That a bodhisattva has the option to pursue such a lesser path, but instead chooses the long path towards Buddhahood is one of the five criteria for one to be considered a bodhisattva. The other four are: being human, being a man, making a vow to become a Buddha in the presence of a previous Buddha, and receiving a prophecy from that Buddha.

Over time, a more varied analysis of bodhisattva careers developed focused on one's motivation. This can be seen in the [[Tibetan Buddhism|Tibetan Buddhist]] teaching on three types of motivation for generating bodhicitta. According to [[Patrul Rinpoche]]'s 19th century ''Words of My Perfect Teacher'' (''Kun bzang bla ma'i gzhal lung''), a bodhisattva might be motivated in one of three ways. They are:

# King-like bodhicitta – To aspire to become a Buddha first in order to then help sentient beings.
# Boatman-like bodhicitta – To aspire to become a Buddha at the same time as other sentient beings.
# Shepherd-like bodhicitta – To aspire to become a Buddha only after all other sentient beings have done so.

These three are not types of people, but rather types of motivation. According to Patrul Rinpoche, the third quality of intention is most noble though the mode by which Buddhahood actually occurs is the first; that is, it is only possible to teach others the path to enlightenment once one has attained enlightenment oneself.&lt;ref&gt;''Words of My Perfect Teacher: A Complete Translation of A Classic Introduction to Tibetan Buddhism.'' Translated by The Padmakara Translation Group. (Walnut Creek: Altamira, 1994), 218.&lt;/ref&gt; The ritualized formulation of the bodhisattva vow also reflects this order (becoming a buddha so that one can then teach others to do the same). A bodhisattva vow ritual text attributed to [[Nāgārjuna]], of the second-third century CE, states the vow as follows: &quot;Just as the past tathāgata arhat samyaksambuddhas, when engaging in the behavior of a bodhisattva, generated the aspiration to unsurpassed complete enlightenment so that all beings be liberated, all beings be freed, all beings be relieved, all beings attain complete nirvana, all beings be placed in omniscient wisdom, in the same way, I whose name is so-and-so, from this time forward, generate the aspiration to unsurpassed complete enlightenment so that all beings be liberated, all beings be freed, all beings be relieved, all beings attain complete nirvana, all beings be placed in omniscient wisdom.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Nagārjuna. ''Byang chub mchog tu sems bskyed pa'i cho ga (Bodhicittotpadaviddhi, Ritual for Generating the Intention for Supreme Buddhahood).'' Toh. 3966 Tengyur, mdo, ''gi''. (sems can thams cad bsgral ba dang/ sems can thams cad dgrol ba dang/ sems can thams cad dbugs dbyung ba dang/ sems can thams cad yongs su mya ngan las 'da' ba dang/ sems can thams cad thams cad mkhyen pa'i ye shes la dgod pa'i slad du ci ltar bla na med pa yang dag par rdzogs pa'i byang chub tu thugs bskyed pa de bzhin du bdag ming 'di zhes bgyi ba yang dus 'di nas bzung)&lt;/ref&gt;

The six perfections that constitute bodhisattva practice should not be confused with the actual acts of benefiting beings that the bodhisattva vows to accomplish once he or she is a buddha. The six perfections are a mental transformation and need not actually benefit anyone. This is seen in the story of [[Vessantara]], an incarnation of Śākyamuni Buddha while he was still a bodhisattva, who commits the ultimate act of generosity by giving away his children to an evil man who mistreats them. Vessantara's generous act causes indirect harm, however, the merit from the perfection of his generosity fructifies when he attains complete enlightenment as Śākyamuni Buddha.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Vessantara&quot; In ''The Princeton Dictionary of Buddhism'' (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 2013), 965.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Bodhisattva grounds or levels===

According to many traditions within Mahāyāna Buddhism, on the way to becoming a Buddha, a bodhisattva proceeds through ten, or sometimes fourteen, grounds or ''[[Bhumi (Buddhism)|bhūmis]].'' Below is the list of the ten ''bhūmis'' and their descriptions according to the ''[[Avatamsaka Sutra|Avataṃsaka Sūtra]]'' and ''The Jewel Ornament of Liberation,'' a treatise by [[Gampopa]], an influential teacher of the [[Tibetan Buddhism|Tibetan]] [[Kagyu]] school. (Other schools give slightly variant descriptions.)

Before a bodhisattva arrives at the first ground, he or she first must travel the first two of five paths:
#the path of accumulation
#the path of preparation

The ten grounds of the bodhisattva then can be grouped into the next three paths:
#''bhūmi'' 1 the path of insight
#''bhūmis'' 2–7 the path of meditation
#''bhūmis'' 8–10 the path of no more learning

The chapter of ten grounds in the ''Avataṃsaka Sūtra'' refers to 52 stages. The 10 grounds are:

#'''Great Joy:''' It is said that being close to enlightenment and seeing the benefit for all [[Sentient beings (Buddhism)|sentient beings]], one achieves great joy, hence the name. In this ''bhūmi'' the bodhisattvas practice all [[paramita|perfections]] (''pāramitās''), but especially emphasizing [[dana (Buddhism)|generosity]] (''dāna'').
#'''Stainless:''' In accomplishing the second ''bhūmi'', the bodhisattva is free from the stains of immorality, therefore, this ''bhūmi'' is named &quot;stainless&quot;. The emphasized perfection is [[śila|moral discipline]] (''śīla'').
#'''Luminous:''' The light of Dharma is said to radiate for others from the bodhisattva who accomplishes the third ''bhūmi''. The emphasized perfection is [[kṣanti|patience]] (''{{IAST|kṣānti}}'').
#'''Radiant:''' This ''bhūmi'' it is said to be like a radiating light that fully burns that which opposes enlightenment. The emphasized perfection is [[vīrya|vigor]] (''vīrya'').
#'''Very difficult to train:''' Bodhisattvas who attain this ground strive to help sentient beings attain maturity, and do not become emotionally involved when such beings respond negatively, both of which are difficult to do. The emphasized perfection is [[Dhyāna in Buddhism|meditative concentration]] (''dhyāna'').
#'''Obviously Transcendent:''' By depending on the perfection of wisdom, [the bodhisattva] does not abide in either ''[[saṃsāra|{{IAST|saṃsāra}}]]'' or ''[[nirvāṇa|{{IAST|nirvāṇa}}]]'', so this state is &quot;obviously transcendent&quot;.  The emphasized perfection is [[Wisdom in Buddhism|wisdom]] (''prajñā'').
#'''Gone afar:''' Particular emphasis is on the perfection of [[upaya|skillful means]] (''upāya''), to help others.
#'''Immovable:''' The emphasized virtue is aspiration. This &quot;immovable&quot; ''bhūmi'' is where one becomes able to choose his place of rebirth.
#'''Good Discriminating Wisdom:''' The emphasized virtue is the understanding of self and non-self.
#'''Cloud of Dharma:''' The emphasized virtue is the practice of primordial wisdom.

After the ten ''bhūmis'', according to Mahāyāna Buddhism, one attains complete enlightenment and becomes a Buddha.

With the 52 stages, the ''[[Shurangama Sutra|Śūraṅgama Sūtra]]'' recognizes 57 stages. With the 10 grounds, various [[Vajrayana|Vajrayāna]] schools recognize 3–10 additional grounds, mostly 6 more grounds with variant descriptions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://read.goodweb.cn/news/news_more.asp?lm2=603|title=大圆满心性休息 – 显密文库 佛教文集|accessdate=21 August 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150908080747/http://read.goodweb.cn/news/news_more.asp?lm2=603|archive-date=8 September 2015|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://akanistha.blogspot.com/2009/08/blog-post_4818.html|title=吉祥鄔金密嚴寺|author=鄔金旺度|publisher=|accessdate=21 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A bodhisattva above the 7th ground is called a ''[[mahāsattva]]''. Some bodhisattvas such as [[Samantabhadra]] are also said to have already attained buddhahood.&lt;ref&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20111105090211/http://wisdom.buddhistdoor.com/alankwan/2009/09/13/459-%E5%9B%A0%E5%9C%B0%E8%8F%A9%E8%96%A9%E5%92%8C%E6%9E%9C%E5%9C%B0%E8%8F%A9%E8%96%A9/ 459 因地菩薩和果地菩薩]&lt;/ref&gt;

===School doctrines===

Some sutras said a beginner would take 3–22 countless eons (''[[asaṃkhyeya|mahāsaṃkhyeya]] kalpas'') to become a buddha.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.chinawts.com/list/budedu1/082718255.htm 三大阿僧祇劫] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20081121061430/http://www.chinawts.com/list/budedu1/082718255.htm |date=November 21, 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://aaa.org.tw/Chen_voice/a_2008_11_25.pdf 成佛的目的是到每 – 個世界去度眾生.] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090411014117/http://aaa.org.tw/Chen_voice/a_2008_11_25.pdf |date=April 11, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hwayue.org.tw/lama/question4_08.htm 即身成就與三大阿僧祇劫之修行] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130526210637/http://www.hwayue.org.tw/lama/question4_08.htm |date=May 26, 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Pure Land Buddhism]] suggests buddhists go to the [[pure land]]s to practice as bodhisattvas. [[Tiantai]], [[Huayan school|Huayan]], [[Zen]] and [[Vajrayana|Vajrayāna]] schools say they teach ways to attain buddhahood within one karmic cycle.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bukon.idv.tw/mantra/b11.htm|title=顯教與密教|publisher=|accessdate=21 August 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110911110810/http://www.bukon.idv.tw/mantra/b11.htm|archive-date=11 September 2011|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.yinshun.org/Enlightenment/1997/1997oct/1999oct1.htm 「無諍之辯」導讀]&lt;/ref&gt;

Various traditions within Buddhism believe in specific bodhisattvas. Some bodhisattvas appear across traditions, but due to language barriers may be seen as separate entities. For example, [[Tibetan Buddhism|Tibetan Buddhists]] believe in various forms of [[Chenrezig]], who is [[Avalokitesvara|Avalokiteśvara]] in Sanskrit, [[Guanyin]] in China, Gwan-eum in Korea, Quan Am in Vietnam, and [[Kannon]] in Japan. Followers of Tibetan Buddhism consider the [[Dalai Lama]]s and the [[Karmapa]]s to be an emanation of Chenrezig, the Bodhisattva of Compassion.

The place of a bodhisattva's earthly deeds, such as the achievement of [[enlightenment (Buddhism)|enlightenment]] or the acts of [[Dharma]], is known as a ''[[bodhimaṇḍa]]'', and may be a site of [[pilgrimage]]. Many temples and monasteries are famous as bodhimaṇḍas. Perhaps the most famous bodhimaṇḍa of all is the [[Bodhi Tree]] under which [[Shakyamuni|Śākyamuṇi]] achieved buddhahood. In the tradition of [[Chinese Buddhism]], there are four mountains that are regarded as bodhimaṇḍas for bodhisattvas, with each site having major monasteries and being popular for pilgrimages by both monastics and laypeople. These four bodhimandas are:

* [[Putuoshan|Mount Putuo]]:  [[Avalokiteśvara]], Bodhisattva of Compassion. ({{zh|s=觀自在菩薩, 觀世音菩薩, 觀音菩薩|p=Guānzìzài Púsà, Guānshìyīn Púsà, Guānyīn Púsà|}})
* [[Mount Emei]]: Samantabhadra Bodhisattva
* [[Mount Wutai]]: [[Mañjuśrī]], Bodhisattva of Wisdom. ({{zh|s=文殊菩薩, 文殊师利菩薩, 曼殊室利菩薩, 妙吉祥菩薩|p=Wénshū Púsà, Wénshūshīlì Púsà, Mànshūshìlì Púsà,Miàojíxiáng Púsà}})
* [[Mount Jiuhua]]: [[Kṣitigarbha]] Bodhisattva of the Great Vow ({{zh|s=地藏菩薩 地藏菩萨|p=Dìzàng Púsà}}) 
*[[Samantabhadra]] Bodhisattva of Practice. ({{zh|s=普賢菩薩 普贤菩萨|p=Pǔxián Púsà}})

==Iconography and the popular mind==
Gender variant representations of some bodhisattvas, most notably [[Avalokiteśvara]], has prompted conversation regarding the nature of a bodhisattva's appearance. Chan master [[Sheng Yen]] has stated that [[Mahāsattva]]s such as Avalokiteśvara (known as [[Guanyin]] in Chinese) are androgynous (Ch. 中性; [[pinyin]]: &quot;zhōngxìng&quot;), which accounts for their ability to manifest in masculine and feminine forms of various degrees.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Sheng Yen |title=圣严法师《观世音菩萨的性别》 |url=http://fodizi.net/qt/shengyanfashi/1299.html |website=佛弟子文库 |accessdate=2019-08-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While bodhisattvas tend to be depicted as conventionally [[beauty|beautiful]], there are instances of their manifestation as wrathful and [[monstrous]] beings. A notable example is [[Guanyin]]'s manifestation as a [[preta]] named &quot;Flaming Face&quot; ([[:zh:面燃大士|面燃大士]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author1=Master Yan Shou of Yong Ming Monastery |title=四十四世永明延壽大師 Patriarchs of the Forty-fourth Generation |url=http://www.drbachinese.org/vbs/publish/424/vbs424p012.htm |website=Vajra Bodhi Sea |accessdate=2019-10-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; This trope is commonly employed among the [[Wisdom King]]s, among whom [[Mahamayuri|Mahāmāyūrī Vidyārājñī]] stands out with a feminine title and benevolent expression. In some depictions, her [[Vahana|mount]] takes on a wrathful appearance. This variation is also found among images of [[Vajrapani]].

== Gallery ==
&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:Standing Bodhisattva Gandhara Musee Guimet.jpg|Standing bodhisattva. [[Gandhara|Gandhāra]], 2nd–3rd century.
Image:Museum für Indische Kunst Dahlem Berlin Mai 2006 006.jpg|Standing bodhisattva. Gandhāra, 2nd–3rd century.
Image:Mural Worshipping Bodhisattva.jpg|Gathering of bodhisattvas. China, 6th century.
Image:Mural Avolokitesvara.jpg|Mural of bodhisattvas. China, [[Tang Dynasty]], 7th–9th century.
Image:COLLECTIE TROPENMUSEUM Boeddhistisch beeld van mogelijk acoliet in de tempel Tjandi Mendoet rechts. TMnr 60004721.jpg|Boddhisattva [[Vajrapani]]. [[Mendut]] near [[Borobudur Temple Compounds|Borobudur]], Central Java, Indonesia. Sailendran art c. 8th century.
Image:Maitreya Komering Srivijaya Front.JPG|A bronze boddhisattva [[Maitreya]]. Komering, [[Palembang]], Indonesia. Srivijayan art c. 9th–10th century.
Image:Kokūzō Bosatsu.jpg|[[Akasagarbha|Ākāśagarbha]] Bodhisattva. Japan, 9th century.
Image:Chinese mural of a bodhisattva, ink and color on plaster, c. 952, Honolulu Academy of Arts.jpg|Mural of a bodhisattva. China, 10th century.
Image:Bangkok National Museum - 2017-04-22 (053).jpg|9th century CE [[Srivijaya]]n art, Chaiya, Surat Thani, Southern Thailand.
Image:Guanyin 00.jpg|Seated Bodhisattva Avalokitesvara ([[Guanyin]]), wood and pigment, 11th century, Chinese [[Northern Song dynasty]], [[St. Louis Art Museum]].
Image:WLA brooklynmuseum Seated Avalokitesvara black chlorite.jpg|[[Avalokitesvara|Avalokiteśvara]] Bodhisattva. India, 11th–12th century.
Image:Avalokiteçvara, Malayu Srivijaya style.jpg|Gold coated bronze statue of Avalokitesvara in [[Melayu Kingdom|Malayu]]-[[Srivijaya]]n style c. 11th century, [[Jambi]], Sumatra, Indonesia.
Image:Mahasthamaprapta.jpg|[[Mahasthamaprapta|Mahāsthāmaprāpta]] Bodhisattva. China, 13th century.
Image:COLLECTIE TROPENMUSEUM Zilveren Manjusri beeld afkomstig uit Ngemplak Semongan TMnr 10016132.jpg|Youthful [[Manjusri|Mañjuśrī]] Bodhisattva silver statue. Java, 9th century Indonesia.
Image:Monju crossing the sea.jpg|[[Manjusri|Mañjuśrī]] Bodhisattva crossing the sea. Japan, 14th century.
Image:Jizo, the Bodhisattva of the Earth Matrix.jpg|[[Ksitigarbha|Kṣitigarbha]] Bodhisattva. Japan, 15th century.
Image:Samantabhadra.jpg|[[Samantabhadra]] Bodhisattva. Japan.
Image:Maitreya Buddha the next Buddha.jpg|[[Maitreya]] Bodhisattva. Thiksey Monastery, Ladakh, India.
Image:&quot;Standing Bodhisattva&quot; in Brooklyn Museum IMG 3868.JPG|&quot;Standing Bodhisattva&quot; (pre-1234). [[Brooklyn Museum]], [[New York City]].
Image:Daizuigu Mahapratisara.jpg|Daizuigu [[Mahapratisara]] Bodhisattva. [[Guimet Museum]].
Image:Shrine with an Image of a Bodhisattva.jpg|Shrine with an Image of a Bodhisattva. [[Brooklyn Museum]].
&lt;/gallery&gt;

== See also ==
*[[Bodhicharyavatara]] ''(A Guide to the Bodhisattva Way of Life)''
*[[Bodhisattvas of the Earth]]
*[[Bodhisattva vows]]
*[[Buddhist holidays]]
*[[Junzi]]
*[[Karuṇā|Karuna]] (''[[compassion]]'' in [[Sanskrit]])
*[[List of bodhisattvas]]
*[[Vegetarianism in Buddhism]]

== Notes ==
{{reflist}}

== References ==
{{refbegin}}
* Analayo, [https://web.archive.org/web/20110911101206/http://www.buddhismuskunde.uni-hamburg.de/fileadmin/pdf/publikationen/HamburgUP_HBS01_Analayo.pdf The Genesis of the Bodhisattva Ideal], Hamburg Buddhist Studies 1, Hamburg University Press 2010
*Gampopa; The Jewel Ornament of Liberation; Snow Lion Publications; {{ISBN|1-55939-092-1}}
*White, Kenneth R.; The Role of Bodhicitta in Buddhist Enlightenment: Including a Translation into English of Bodhicitta-sastra, Benkemmitsu-nikyoron, and Sammaya-kaijo; The Edwin Mellen Press, 2005; {{ISBN|0-7734-5985-5}}
*Lampert, K.; Traditions of Compassion: From Religious Duty to Social Activism. Palgrave-Macmillan; {{ISBN|1-4039-8527-8}}
* Gyatso, [[Geshe Kelsang Gyatso]], ''The Bodhisattva Vow: A Practical Guide to Helping Others'', [[Tharpa Publications]] (2nd. ed., 1995) {{ISBN|978-0-948006-50-0}}
* [[Shantideva]]: ''Guide to the Bodhisattva's Way of Life'': How to Enjoy a Life of Great Meaning and Altruism, a translation of Shantideva's ''Bodhisattvacharyavatara'' with Neil Elliott, Tharpa Publications (2002) {{ISBN|978-0-948006-88-3}}
*{{Google books|WpyiqKZISw0C&amp;d|The Making of a Savior Bodhisattva: Dizang in Medieval China, by Zhiru (Kuroda Institute Studies in East Asian Buddhism series no. 21), University of Hawaii Press, 2007}}; {{ISBN|978-0-8248-3045-8}}
{{refend}}

== External links ==
{{Wikiquote}}
{{Commons}}
{{Wiktionary|bodhisattva}}

* [http://info-buddhism.com/Ethical_Discipline_Bodhisattvas-Geshe_Sonam_Rinchen.html The Ethical Discipline of Bodhisattvas], by Geshe Sonam Rinchen (Tibetan Gelug Tradition)
* [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8jFxkEQacVA Bodhisattva, probably Avalokiteshvara (Guanyin), Northern Qi dynasty, c. 550--60], video, [[Smarthistory]].
* [https://www.37practices.info/ The 37 Practices of Bodhisattvas online with commentaries].
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20070610212029/http://dhechen.com/pub/spiritual/37prac.htm The Thirty-Seven Practices of Bodhisattvas], all-in-one page with memory aids &amp; collection of different versions.
* [http://dhechen.com/pub/spiritual/pdf/MP3-The_Thirty-Seven_Practices_of_Bodhisattvas.zip Audio recitation of 'The 37 Practices of Bodhisattvas' in MP3 format] (Paul &amp; Lee voices).
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20060715041706/http://sealevel.ns.ca/bodhi/index.html What A Bodhisattva Does: Thirty-Seven Practices by Ngulchu Thogme] with slide show format.
* [http://www.accesstoinsight.org/lib/authors/bodhi/wheel409.html Access to Insight Library: Bodhi's Wheel409]
*[http://info-buddhism.com/Arahants-Buddhas-Bodhisattvas_Bhikkhu_Bodhi.html Arahants, Buddhas and Bodhisattvas] by Bhikkhu Bodhi
*[http://info-buddhism.com/Bodhisattva-Ideal-Theravada_JeffreySamuels.html The Bodhisattva Ideal in Theravāda Theory and Practice] by Jeffrey Samuels
* [http://exhibits.uflib.ufl.edu/harnkoreanart/bodhisattva.html Online exhibition analyzing a Korean Bodhisattva sculpture]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20120103093104/http://www.buddhanet.net/e-learning/history/tstang-txt.htm Buddhanet.net Ksitigarbha Bodhisattva]
*[http://libmma.contentdm.oclc.org/cdm/ref/collection/p15324coll10/id/101557 ''Sacred visions : early paintings from central Tibet''], fully digitized text from The Metropolitan Museum of Art libraries

{{Buddhism topics}}
{{Bodhisattvas}}
{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Bodhisattvas| ]]
[[Category:Gender and Buddhism]]
[[Category:Buddhist philosophical concepts]]
[[Category:Buddhist titles]]</text>
      <sha1>7t2xh9mp2b9e6brovwv6eskaz2yqisw</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
