  <page>
    <title>Bram Stoker</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3992</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943342943</id>
      <parentid>943342730</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-03-01T10:04:32Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Favonian</username>
        <id>7007500</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contribs/188.223.150.106|188.223.150.106]] ([[User talk:188.223.150.106|talk]]) to last version by SeoR</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Irish novelist and short story writer}}
{{Use Irish English|date=February 2017}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=November 2016}}
{{Infobox writer
| name = Bram Stoker
| image = Bram Stoker 1906.jpg
| caption = Stoker, {{circa|1906}}
| birth_date = {{birth date|1847|11|8|df=y}}
| birth_place = [[Clontarf, Dublin]], Ireland
| birth_name = Abraham Stoker
| death_date = {{death date and age|1912|4|20|1847|11|8|df=y}}
| death_place = [[London]], England
| occupation = [[Novelist]]
| alma_mater = [[Trinity College Dublin]]
| nationality = Irish
| citizenship = British
| period = [[Victorian era]], [[Edwardian era]]
| genre = [[Gothic fiction]], [[Romance novel|romantic fiction]]
| movement = [[Dark romanticism]]
| notableworks = ''[[Dracula]]''
| spouse = {{marriage|[[Florence Balcombe]]|1878|1912}}
| children = 1
| signature = Bram Stoker signature.svg
| website = 
}}

'''Abraham &quot;Bram&quot; Stoker''' (8 November 1847&amp;nbsp;– 20 April 1912) was an [[Irish people|Irish]]&lt;!--Go to talk page and open discussion before changing again--&gt; author, best known today for his 1897 [[Gothic fiction|Gothic]] horror novel ''[[Dracula]]''. During his lifetime, he was better known as the personal assistant of actor Sir [[Henry Irving]] and business manager of the [[Lyceum Theatre, London|Lyceum Theatre]], which Irving owned.

==Early life==
Stoker was born on 8 November 1847 at 15 Marino Crescent, [[Clontarf, Dublin|Clontarf]], on the northside of [[Dublin]], Ireland.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=Bram Stoker and the Man Who Was Dracula |last=Belford |first=Barbara |publisher=Da Capo Press |year=2002 |isbn=978-0-306-81098-5 |location=Cambridge, Massachusetts |page=17}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!-- Note, as location has led to multiple edits: The location was, and is, in the Civil Parish of Clontarf.  Clontarf extends to the east side of the Malahide Road and borders Marino.  Fairview is further west commencing just after Marino Mart.--&gt; His parents were Abraham Stoker (1799–1876) from Dublin and Charlotte Mathilda Blake Thornley (1818–1901), who was raised in [[County Sligo]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=From the Shadow of Dracula: A Life of Bram Stoker |last=Murray, Paul |publisher=Random House |year=2004 |isbn=978-0224044622 |page=11}}&lt;/ref&gt; Stoker was the third of seven children, the eldest of whom was [[Thornley Stoker|Sir Thornley Stoker]], 1st [[Baronet|Bt.]].&lt;ref&gt;His siblings were: Sir (William) Thornley Stoker, born in 1845; Mathilda, born 1846; Thomas, born 1850; Richard, born 1852; Margaret, born 1854; and George, born 1855&lt;/ref&gt; Abraham and Charlotte were members of the [[Church of Ireland Parish of Clontarf]] and attended the parish church with their children, who were baptised there,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.eneclann.ie/wp-content/uploads/2012/04/Stoker-family-tree.pdf |title=Stoker Family Tree |date=2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Abraham was a senior civil servant.

Stoker was bedridden with an unknown illness until he started school at the age of seven, when he made a complete recovery. Of this time, Stoker wrote, &quot;I was naturally thoughtful, and the leisure of long illness gave opportunity for many thoughts which were fruitful according to their kind in later years.&quot; He was educated in a private school run by the Rev. William Woods.&lt;ref name=&quot;obit&quot;&gt;Obituary, Irish Times, 23 April 1912&lt;/ref&gt;

After his recovery, he grew up without further serious illnesses, even excelling as an athlete (he was named University Athlete, participating in multiple sports) at [[Trinity College, Dublin]], which he attended from 1864 to 1870.  He graduated with a BA in 1870, and pursued his MA in 1875. Though he later in life recalled graduating &quot;with honours in mathematics,&quot; this appears to have been a mistake.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.tcd.ie/trinitywriters/writers/bram-stoker/ Bram Stoker (1847–1912)] Trinity College Dublin Writers by Jarlath Killeen&lt;/ref&gt; He was auditor of the [[College Historical Society (Trinity College, Dublin)|College Historical Society]] (''the Hist'') and president of the [[University Philosophical Society (Trinity College, Dublin)|University Philosophical Society]], where his first paper was on ''Sensationalism in Fiction and Society''.

==Early career==
Stoker became interested in the theatre while a student through his friend Dr. Maunsell. While working for the [[Irish Civil Service]], he became the theatre critic for the ''[[Dublin Evening Mail]]'',&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.history.com/this-day-in-history/dracula-creator-bram-stoker-born |title=Dracula creator Bram Stoker born |last=History.com Editors |date=August 21, 2018 |website=HIstory.com |publisher=A&amp;E Television Networks |language=English |access-date=November 8, 2018 |quote=He then worked for the Irish Civil Service while writing theater reviews for a Dublin newspaper on the side.}}&lt;/ref&gt; which was co-owned by [[Sheridan Le Fanu]], an author of Gothic tales. Theatre critics were held in low esteem, but he attracted notice by the quality of his reviews. In December 1876, he gave a favourable review of Henry Irving's ''[[Hamlet]]'' at the [[Theatre Royal, Dublin|Theatre Royal]] in Dublin. Irving invited Stoker for dinner at the [[Shelbourne Hotel]] where he was staying, and they became friends. Stoker also wrote stories, and &quot;The Crystal Cup&quot; was published by the London Society in 1872, followed by &quot;[http://bramstoker.org/pdf/stories/04other/destinyts.pdf The Chain of Destiny]&quot; in four parts in ''The Shamrock''. In 1876 while a [[civil servant]] in Dublin, Stoker wrote the non-fiction book ''The Duties of Clerks of Petty Sessions in Ireland'' (published 1879) which remained a standard work.&lt;ref name=&quot;obit&quot; /&gt; Furthermore, he possessed an interest in art, and was a founder of the Dublin Sketching Club in 1879.

==Lyceum Theatre==
[[File:Bram Stoker's Home.jpg|thumb|left|Bram Stoker's former home, [[Kildare Street]], Dublin]]
In 1878 Stoker married [[Florence Balcombe]], daughter of [[Lieutenant-colonel (British Army)|Lieutenant-Colonel]] James Balcombe of 1 Marino Crescent.  She was a celebrated beauty whose former suitor had been [[Oscar Wilde]].&lt;ref&gt;Irish Times, 8 March 1882, p. 5&lt;/ref&gt; Stoker had known Wilde from his student days, having proposed him for membership of the university's Philosophical Society while he was president. Wilde was upset at Florence's decision, but Stoker later resumed the acquaintanceship, and after Wilde's fall visited him on the Continent.&lt;ref name=&quot;irtimes&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/weekend/2009/0328/1224243595688.html |title=Why Dracula never loses his bite |date=28 March 2009 |website=Irish Times}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Dracula1st.jpeg|thumb|upright|The first edition cover of ''Dracula'']]
The Stokers moved to London, where Stoker became acting manager and then business manager of [[Henry Irving|Irving]]'s [[Lyceum Theatre, London]], a post he held for 27 years. On 31 December 1879, Bram and Florence's only child was born, a son whom they christened Irving Noel Thornley Stoker. The collaboration with Henry Irving was important for Stoker and through him he became involved in London's [[upper class|high society]], where he met [[James Abbott McNeill Whistler]] and [[Arthur Conan Doyle|Sir Arthur Conan Doyle]] (to whom he was distantly related). Working for Irving, the most famous actor of his time, and managing one of the most successful theatres in London made Stoker a notable if busy man. He was dedicated to Irving and his memoirs show he idolised him. In London, Stoker also met [[Hall Caine]], who became one of his closest friends – he dedicated ''Dracula'' to him.

In the course of Irving's tours, Stoker travelled the world, although he never visited [[Eastern Europe]], a setting for his most famous novel. Stoker enjoyed the United States, where Irving was popular. With Irving he was invited twice to the [[White House]], and knew [[William McKinley]] and [[Theodore Roosevelt]]. Stoker set two of his novels in America, and used Americans as characters, the most notable being [[Quincey Morris]]. He also met one of his literary idols, [[Walt Whitman]].

== Bram Stoker in Cruden Bay ==
[[File:SlainsCastleCrudenBay.jpg|thumb|Slains Castle, Cruden Bay. The early chapters of Dracula were written in Cruden Bay, and Slains Castle plausibly provided visual inspiration for Bram Stoker during the writing phase. ]]
Stoker was a regular visitor to [[Cruden Bay]] in Scotland between 1893 and 1910. His month-long holidays to the Aberdeenshire coastal village provided a large portion of available time for writing his books. Two novels were set in Cruden Bay: ''[[The Watter's Mou']] ''(1895) and ''[[The Mystery of the Sea]]'' (1902). He started writing ''Dracula'' here in 1895 while in residence at the Kilmarnock Arms Hotel. The guest book with his signatures from 1894 and 1895 still survives. The nearby Slains Castle (also known as [[New Slains Castle]]) is linked with Bram Stoker and plausibly provided the visual palette for the descriptions of Castle Dracula during the writing phase. A distinctive room in Slains Castle,  the octagonal hall, matches the description of the octagonal room in Castle Dracula.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=When Brave Men Shudder; the Scottish origins of Dracula. |last=Shepherd |first=Mike |publisher=Wild Wolf Publishing |year=2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Writings==
[[File:Bram Stoker Plaque Whitby England.jpg|right|thumb|Bram Stoker Commemorative Plaque, [[Whitby]], England]]
Stoker visited the English coastal town of [[Whitby]] in 1890, and that visit was said to be part of the inspiration for ''[[Dracula]]''. He began writing novels while working as manager for [[Henry Irving]] and secretary and director of London's Lyceum Theatre, beginning with ''[[The Snake's Pass]]'' in 1890 and ''Dracula'' in 1897. During this period, Stoker was part of the literary staff of ''[[The Daily Telegraph]]'' in London, and he wrote other fiction, including the horror novels ''[[The Lady of the Shroud]]'' (1909) and ''[[The Lair of the White Worm]]'' (1911).&lt;ref name=WorldBio/&gt;  He published his ''[[Personal Reminiscences of Henry Irving]]'' in 1906, after Irving's death, which proved successful,&lt;ref name=obit /&gt; and managed productions at the [[Prince of Wales Theatre]].

Before writing ''Dracula'', Stoker met [[Ármin Vámbéry]], a Hungarian-Jewish writer and traveller (born in Szent-György, [[Kingdom of Hungary]]  now [[Svätý Jur]], [[Slovakia]]). Dracula likely emerged from Vámbéry's dark stories of the [[Carpathian mountains]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://www.time.com/time/specials/packages/article/0,28804,1916160_1916151_1916132,00.html |title=Vampires – Top 10 Famous Mysterious Monsters |date=14 August 2009 |website=Tone.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; Stoker then spent several years researching Central and East European folklore and mythological stories of [[vampire]]s.

The 1972 book ''In Search of Dracula'' by [[Radu Florescu]] and [[Raymond McNally]] claimed that the Count in Stoker's novel was based on Vlad III Dracula.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.independent.co.uk/news/people/radu-florescu-dead-legacy-of-the-romanian-dracula-professor-remembered-9401744.html |title=Radu Florescu dead: Legacy of the Romanian 'Dracula professor' remembered |last=Lizzie Dearden |date=2014-05-20 |work=The Independent |access-date=2018-11-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; At most however, Stoker borrowed only the name and &quot;scraps of miscellaneous information&quot; about Romanian history, according to one expert, [[Elizabeth Miller (academic)|Elizabeth Miller]]; further, there are no comments about Vlad III in the author's working notes.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://books.google.com/?id=VomtVOkkPDwC&amp;pg=PA182&amp;dq=Dracula+bram+stoker+vlad+the+impaler#v=onepage&amp;q=Dracula%20bram%20stoker%20vlad%20the%20impaler&amp;f=false |title=Bram Stoker and Russophobia: Evidence of the British Fear of Russia in Dracula and the Lady of the Shroud |last=Jimmie e. Cain |first=Jr |year=2006 |isbn=978-0786424078 |page=182}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://books.google.com/?id=CMRfXDFrBuUC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=Elizabeth+Miller+Bram+Stoker+Vlad+III#v=onepage&amp;q=Bram%20Stoker%20Vlad%20III&amp;f=false |title=A Dracula Handbook |last=Miller |first=Elizabeth |date=2005 |isbn=978-1465334008 |pages=112–113}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://books.google.com/?id=v-3OCwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT73&amp;lpg=PT73&amp;dq=Elizabeth+Miller+stoker%27s+working+notes+No+mention+of+Vlad#v=onepage&amp;q=Elizabeth%20Miller%20stoker's%20working%20notes%20No%20mention%20of%20Vlad&amp;f=false |title=The Dracula Dilemma: Tourism, Identity and the State in Romania |last=Light |first=Duncan |date=2016 |isbn=978-1317035312}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''Dracula'' is an [[epistolary novel]], written as a collection of realistic but completely fictional diary entries, telegrams, letters, ship's logs, and newspaper clippings, all of which added a level of detailed realism to the story, a skill which Stoker had developed as a newspaper writer. At the time of its publication, ''Dracula'' was considered a &quot;straightforward horror novel&quot; based on imaginary creations of [[supernatural]] life.&lt;ref name=WorldBio/&gt; &quot;It gave form to a universal fantasy ... and became a part of popular culture.&quot;&lt;ref name=WorldBio/&gt;

Stoker was a deeply private man, but his almost sexless marriage, intense adoration of [[Walt Whitman]], [[Henry Irving]] and [[Hall Caine]], and shared interests with [[Oscar Wilde]], as well as the homoerotic aspects of ''[[Dracula]]'' have led to scholarly speculation that he was a repressed homosexual who used his fiction as an outlet for his sexual frustrations.&lt;ref&gt;Skal, David J ''Something in the Blood: The Untold Story of Bram Stoker'', Liveright, 2016, p. 564; [https://thenewinquiry.com/coming-out-of-the-coffin/] &quot;Coming Out Of The Coffin&quot;, ''The New Inquiry'', 24 August 2012&lt;/ref&gt; In 1912, he demanded imprisonment of all homosexual authors in Britain: it has been suggested that this was due to self-loathing and to disguise his own vulnerability.&lt;ref name=&quot;thenewinquiry.com&quot;&gt;[https://thenewinquiry.com/coming-out-of-the-coffin/] &quot;Coming Out Of The Coffin&quot;, ''The New Inquiry'', 24 August 2012&lt;/ref&gt; Possibly fearful, and inspired by the monstrous image and threat of otherness that the press coverage of his friend Oscar's trials generated, Stoker began writing ''Dracula'' only weeks after Wilde's conviction.&lt;ref name=&quot;thenewinquiry.com&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Schaffer, Talia &quot;A Wilde Desire Took Me: The Homoerotic History of Dracula&quot;, ELH, Vol. 61, No. 2 (Summer, 1994), pp. 381–425&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the ''Encyclopedia of World Biography'', Stoker's stories are today included in the categories of &quot;horror fiction&quot;, &quot;romanticized Gothic&quot; stories, and &quot;melodrama.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;WorldBio&quot;&gt;''Encyclopedia of World Biography'', Gale Research (1998) vol 8. pp. 461–464&lt;/ref&gt; They are classified alongside other &quot;works of popular fiction&quot; such as [[Mary Shelley]]'s ''[[Frankenstein]]'',&lt;ref name=Latham/&gt;{{rp|394}} which also used the &quot;myth-making&quot; and story-telling method of having [[multiperspectivity|multiple narrators]] telling the same tale from different perspectives. According to historian Jules Zanger, this leads the reader to the assumption that &quot;they can't all be lying&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zanger&quot;&gt;Zanger, Jules (1997). ''Blood Read: The Vampire as Metaphor in Contemporary Culture'' ed. Joan Gordon. Univ. of Pennsylvania Press, pp. 17–24&lt;/ref&gt;

The original 541-page typescript of ''Dracula'' was believed to have been lost until it was found in a barn in northwestern Pennsylvania in the early 1980s.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.wsj.com/articles/SB122514491757273633 |title=What a Tax Lawyer Dug Up on 'Dracula' |last=John J. Miller |date=28 October 2008 |website=WSJ}}&lt;/ref&gt; It consisted of typed sheets with many emendations and handwritten on the title page was &quot;THE UN-DEAD.&quot; The author's name was shown at the bottom as Bram Stoker. Author Robert Latham remarked: &quot;the most famous horror novel ever published, its title changed at the last minute.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Latham&quot;&gt;Latham, Robert. ''Science Fiction &amp; Fantasy Book Review Annual'', Greenwood Publishing (1988) p. 67&lt;/ref&gt; The typescript was purchased by [[Microsoft]] co-founder [[Paul Allen]].

Stoker's inspirations for the story, in addition to Whitby, may have included a visit to [[New Slains Castle|Slains Castle]] in [[Aberdeenshire]], a visit to the crypts of [[St. Michan's Church]] in Dublin, and the novella ''[[Carmilla]]'' by [[Sheridan Le Fanu]].&lt;ref name=&quot;boy&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |title=A Dictionary of Irish Biography, 3rd Edition |last=Boylan |first=Henry |publisher=Gill and MacMillan |year=1998 |isbn=978-0-7171-2945-4 |location=Dublin |page=412}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Stoker's original research notes for the novel are kept by the [[Rosenbach Museum &amp; Library|Rosenbach Museum and Library]] in [[Philadelphia]]. A facsimile edition of the notes was created by [[Elizabeth Miller (academic)|Elizabeth Miller]] and [[Robert Eighteen-Bisang]] in 1998.

== Stoker at The London Library ==
Stoker was a member of The [[London Library]] and it is here that he conducted much of the research for ''Dracula.''&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.londonlibrary.co.uk/dracula |title=The Books That Made Dracula |publisher=The London Library |access-date=14 February 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2018 the Library discovered some of the books that Stoker used for his research, complete with notes and marginalia.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.londonlibrary.co.uk/about-us/latest-news |title=Latest News |date=15 January 2019 |publisher=The London Library |access-date=15 February 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Death==
[[File:Golders Green crematorium (pictures) 002.jpg|thumb|Urn which contains Stoker's ashes in [[Golders Green Crematorium]]]]
After suffering a number of strokes, Stoker died at No. 26 [[St George's Square]], London on 20 April 1912.&lt;ref name=&quot;mc&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.victorianweb.org/authors/stoker/bio.html |title=Bram Stoker |date=30 April 2008 |publisher=Victorian Web |access-date=12 December 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some biographers attribute the cause of death to [[tertiary syphilis]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Gibson&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |title=The Capital Companion |last=Gibson |first=Peter |publisher=Webb &amp; Bower |year=1985 |isbn=978-0-86350-042-8 |pages=365–366}}&lt;/ref&gt; others to overwork.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Discussion&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |title=The Discussion |publisher=Oberon Books (for The London Academy of Music and Dramatic Art) |year=2004 |isbn=978-1-84002-431-9 |edition=Third |location=Grade Eight – Bram Stoker |page=97}}&lt;/ref&gt; He was [[Cremation|cremated]], and his ashes were placed in a display urn at [[Golders Green Crematorium]] in north London. The ashes of Irving Noel Stoker, the author's son, were added to his father's urn following his death in 1961. The original plan had been to keep his parents' ashes together, but after Florence Stoker's death, her ashes were scattered at the Gardens of Rest.

==Beliefs and philosophy==
Stoker was raised a Protestant in the [[Church of Ireland]]. He was a strong supporter of the [[Liberal Party (UK)|Liberal Party]] and took a keen interest in Irish affairs.&lt;ref name=obit /&gt; As a &quot;philosophical home ruler,&quot; he supported [[Irish Home Rule bills|Home Rule]] for Ireland brought about by peaceful means. He remained an ardent monarchist who believed that Ireland should remain within the British Empire, an entity that he saw as a force for good. He was an admirer of Prime Minister [[William Ewart Gladstone]], whom he knew personally, and supported his plans for Ireland.&lt;ref&gt;Murray, Paul. ''From the Shadow of Dracula: A Life of Bram Stoker''. 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;

Stoker believed in progress and took a keen interest in [[science]] and science-based [[medicine]]. Some Stoker novels represent early examples of [[science fiction]], such as ''[[The Lady of the Shroud]]'' (1909). He had a writer's interest in the occult, notably [[mesmerism]], but despised fraud and believed in the superiority of the [[scientific method]] over superstition. Stoker counted among his friends J.W. Brodie-Innis, a member of the [[Hermetic Order of the Golden Dawn]], and hired member [[Pamela Colman Smith]] as an artist for the Lyceum Theatre, but no evidence suggests that Stoker ever joined the Order himself.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.shadowplayzine.com/Articles/hermetic_horrors.htm |title=Shadowplay Pagan and Magick webzine – Hermetic Horrors |date=16 September 1904 |publisher=Shadowplayzine.com |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20091109074626/http://shadowplayzine.com/Articles/hermetic_horrors.htm |archive-date=9 November 2009 |access-date=18 June 2012 |df=dmy}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://archive.org/details/spearofdestinyoc0000rave/page/165 |title=The occult power behind the spear which pierced the side of Christ |last=Ravenscroft |first=Trevor |publisher=Red Wheel |year=1982 |isbn=978-0-87728-547-2 |page=[https://archive.org/details/spearofdestinyoc0000rave/page/165 165] |url-access=registration}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=The Templar Revelation: Secret Guardians of the True Identity of Christ |last=Picknett |first=Lynn |publisher=Simon and Schuster |year=2004 |isbn=978-0-7432-7325-1 |page=201}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although Irving was an active [[Freemason]], no evidence has been found of Stoker taking part in Masonic activities in London.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.theirvingsociety.org.uk/the-ripper-and-the-lyceum-the-significance-of-irvings-freemasonry/ |title=The Ripper and The Lyceum: The Significance of Irving's Freemasonry |date=24 November 2002 |access-date=2019-06-04}}  John Pickamp; Robert Protheroug ‘The Ripper and The Lyceum: The Significance of Irving’s Freemasonry ’  The Irving Society website&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Grand Lodge of Ireland]] also has no record of his membership.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://freemasonry.bcy.ca/biography/stoker_b/stoker_b.html |title=Bram Stoker |website=freemasonry.bcy.ca}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Posthumous==
The short story collection ''[[Dracula's Guest and Other Weird Stories]]'' was published in 1914 by Stoker's widow, Florence Stoker, who was also his literary executrix. The first film adaptation of ''Dracula'' was [[F. W. Murnau]]'s ''[[Nosferatu]]'', released in 1922, with [[Max Schreck]] starring as Count Orlok. Florence Stoker eventually sued the filmmakers, and was represented by the attorneys of the British Incorporated Society of Authors. Her chief legal complaint was that she had neither been asked for permission for the adaptation nor paid any royalty. The case dragged on for some years, with Mrs. Stoker demanding the destruction of the negative and all prints of the film. The suit was finally resolved in the widow's favour in July 1925. A single print of the film survived, however, and it has become well known. The first authorised film version of ''Dracula'' did not come about until almost a decade later when [[Universal Studios]] released [[Tod Browning]]'s ''[[Dracula (1931 English-language film)|Dracula]]'' starring [[Bela Lugosi]].

===Dacre Stoker===
[[Canadians|Canadian]] writer [[Dacre Stoker]], a great-grandnephew of Bram Stoker, decided to write &quot;a sequel that bore the Stoker name&quot; to &quot;reestablish creative control over&quot; the original novel, with encouragement from screenwriter Ian Holt, because of the Stokers' frustrating history with ''Dracula's'' copyright. In 2009, ''[[Dracula the Un-dead|Dracula: The Un-Dead]]'' was released, written by Dacre Stoker and Ian Holt. Both writers &quot;based [their work] on Bram Stoker's own handwritten notes for characters and plot threads excised from the original edition&quot; along with their own research for the sequel. This also marked Dacre Stoker's writing debut.&lt;ref&gt;''Dracula: The Un-Dead'' by Dacre Stoker and Ian Holt&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://draculatheundead.com/stoker-book-overview.htm |title=Overview |website=www.DraculaTheUnDead.com |url-status=live |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100103131805/http://www.draculatheundead.com/stoker-book-overview.htm |archive-date=3 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In spring 2012, Dacre Stoker (in collaboration with Prof. Elizabeth Miller) presented the &quot;lost&quot; Dublin Journal written by Bram Stoker, which had been kept by his great-grandson Noel Dobbs. Stoker's diary entries shed a light on the issues that concerned him before his London years. A remark about a boy who caught flies in a bottle might be a clue for the later development of the Renfield character in ''Dracula''.&lt;ref&gt;Stoker, Bram. ''Bram Stoker’s Lost Dublin Journal'', ed. by Stoker, Dacre and Miller, Elizabeth. London: Biteback Press, 2012&lt;/ref&gt;

==Commemorations==
On 8 November 2012, Stoker was honoured with a [[Google Doodle]] on Google's homepage commemorating the 165th anniversary of his birth.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.google.com/doodles/bram-stokers-165th-birthday |title=Bram Stoker's 165th Birthday}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://www.siliconrepublic.com/digital-life/item/30113-bram-stoker-books-gothic/ |title=Bram Stoker books: gothic Google Doodle honours Dracula author |last=Doyle |first=Carmel |date=8 November 2012 |work=Silicon Republic |access-date=8 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

An annual festival takes place in Dublin, the birthplace of Bram Stoker, in honour of his literary achievements. The 2014 Bram Stoker Festival encompassed literary, film, family, street, and outdoor events, and ran from 24–27 October in Dublin.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.bramstokerfestival.com |title=Bram Stoker Festival 28–31 Oct 2016, Day &amp; Night Events |website=Bram Stoker Festival 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.visitdublin.com/event/bram_stoker_festival |title=What's on in Dublin – Dublin Events, Festivals, Concerts, Theatre, family events |publisher=Visit Dublin |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141019034645/http://www.visitdublin.com/event/bram_stoker_festival |archive-date=19 October 2014 |access-date=21 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; The festival is supported by the Bram Stoker Estate&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.bramstokerestate.com/The_Bram_Stoker_Festival_in_Dublin-_2013_Events.html |title=The Bram Stoker Festival in Dublin – 2013 Events |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140808090430/http://www.bramstokerestate.com/The_Bram_Stoker_Festival_in_Dublin-_2013_Events.html |archive-date=8 August 2014 |access-date=21 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; and funded by [[Dublin City Council]] and [[Fáilte Ireland]].

==Bibliography==

===Novels===

*[[The Primrose Path (Stoker novel)|''The Primrose Path'']] (1875)
*''[[The Snake's Pass]]'' (1890)
* ''[[The Watter's Mou']] '' (1895)
* ''[[The Shoulder of Shasta]]'' (1895)
* ''[[Dracula]]'' (1897)
* ''[[Miss Betty]]'' (1898)
* ''[[The Mystery of the Sea]]'' (1902)
* ''[[The Jewel of Seven Stars]]'' (1903, revised 1912)
* ''[[The Man (Stoker novel)|The Man]]'' (1905); issued also as ''The Gates of Life''
* ''[[Lady Athlyne]]'' (1908)
* ''[[The Lady of the Shroud]]'' (1909)
* ''[[The Lair of the White Worm]]'' (1911, posthumously abridged 1925); issued also as ''The Garden of Evil''
* ''Seven Golden Buttons'' (written in 1891, much material reused in ''Miss Betty''; posthumously published in 2015)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.bramstoker.org/novels/06betty.html |title=Bram Stoker - Miss Betty |website=www.bramstoker.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Short story collections===
* ''[[Under the Sunset]]'' (1881) – eight fairy tales for children
* ''[[Snowbound: The Record of a Theatrical Touring Party]]'' (1908)
* ''[[Dracula's Guest and Other Weird Stories]]'' (1914)

===Uncollected stories===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Title
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Date of earliest appearance
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Earliest appearance
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Novelisation
|-
|&quot;The Crystal Cup&quot;
|xx/09/1872
|''[[London Society]]'' (London)
|
|-
|&quot;Buried Treasures&quot;
|13 March 1875 and 20 March 1875
|''[[The Shamrock]]'' (Dublin)
|
|-
|&quot;The Chain of Destiny&quot;
|1 May 1875 and 22 May 1875
|''[[The Shamrock]]'' (Dublin)
|
|-
|&quot;The Dualitists; or, The Death Doom of the Double Born&quot;
|xx/xx/1887
|''The Theatre Annual'' (London)
|
|-
|&quot;The Gombeen Man&quot;
|xx/xx/1889 – xx/xx/1890
|''[[The People]]'' (London)
|Chapter 3 of ''[[The Snake's Pass]]''
|-
|&quot;Lucky Escapes of Sir Henry Irving&quot;
|xx/xx/1890
|
|
|-
|&quot;The Night of the Shifting Bog&quot;
|xx/01/1891
|''Current Literature: A Magazine of Record and Review Vol. VI. No. 1.'' ([[New York City|New York]])
|
|-
|&quot;Lord Castleton Explains&quot;
|30 January 1892
|''[[The Gentlewoman|The Gentlewoman: The Illustrated Weekly Journal for Gentlewomen]]'' ([[London]])
|Chapter 10 of ''[[The Fate of Fenella]]'' ([[Hutchinson (publisher)|Hutchinson]], 1892)
|-
|&quot;Old Hoggen: A Mystery&quot;
|xx/xx/1893
|
|
|-
|&quot;The Man from Shorrox&quot;
|xx/02/1894
|''[[The Pall Mall Magazine]]'' ([[London]])
|
|-
|&quot;The Red Stockade&quot;
|xx/09/1894
|''The Cosmopolitan: An Illustrated Monthly Magazine'' ([[London]])
|
|-
|&quot;When the Sky Rains Gold&quot;
|xx/xx/1894
|
|
|-
|&quot;At the Watter's Mou&quot;
|xx/11/1895
|''Current Literature: A Magazine of Record and Review Vol. XVIII. No. 5.'' ([[New York City|New York]])
|
|-
|&quot;Our New House&quot;
|20 December 1895
|''[[Boston Herald]]'' (Boston)
|
|-
|&quot;Bengal Roses&quot;
|xx/xx/1898
|
|
|-
|&quot;A Yellow Duster&quot;
|7 May 1899
|''[[Lloyd's Weekly Newspaper]]'' ([[London]])
|
|-
|&quot;A Young Widow&quot;
|xx/xx/1899
|
|
|-
|&quot;A Baby Passenger&quot;
|xx/xx/1899
|
|
|-
|&quot;The Seer&quot;
|xx/xx/1902
|''[[The Mystery of the Sea]]'' ([[New York City|New York]]: [[Doubleday (publisher)|Doubleday]], Page &amp; Co.)
|Chapters 1 and 2 of ''[[The Mystery of the Sea]]''
|-
|&quot;The Bridal of Death&quot;
|xx/xx/1903
|''The Jewel of the Seven Stars'' ([[London]]: [[William Heinemann]])
|Alternate ending to ''[[The Jewel of Seven Stars]]''
|-
|&quot;What They Confessed: A Low Comedian's Story&quot;
|xx/xx/1908
|
|
|-
|&quot;The Way of Peace&quot;
|xx/xx/1909
|''Everybody's Story Magazine'' ([[London]])
|
|-
|&quot;The 'Eroes of the Thames&quot;
|xx/10/1908
|''[[The Royal Magazine]]'' ([[London]])
|
|-
|&quot;Greater Love&quot;
|xx/10/1914
|''[[The London Magazine]]'' ([[London]])
|
|}

===Non-fiction===
* ''The Duties of Clerks of Petty Sessions in Ireland'' (1879)
* ''A Glimpse of America'' (1886)
* ''[[Personal Reminiscences of Henry Irving]]'' (1906)
* ''[[Famous Impostors]]'' (1910)
* ''Great Ghost Stories'' (1998) (Compiled by Peter Glassman, Illustrated by [[Barry Moser]])
* ''Bram Stoker's Notes for Dracula: A Facsimile Edition'' (2008) Bram Stoker Annotated and Transcribed by [[Robert Eighteen-Bisang]] and [[Elizabeth Miller (academic)|Elizabeth Miller]], Foreword by Michael Barsanti. Jefferson, NC &amp; [[London]]: [[McFarland &amp; Company|McFarland]]. {{ISBN|978-0-7864-3410-7}}

===Articles===
*[https://archive.org/stream/twentiethcentury63londuoft#page/734/mode/2up &quot;The Question of a National Theatre&quot;] ''The Nineteenth Century and After,'' Vol. LXIII, January/June 1908.
*[https://archive.org/stream/worldswork01pagegoog#page/n188/mode/2up &quot;Mr. De Morgan's Habits of Work&quot;] ''The World's Work,'' Vol. XVI, May/October 1908.
*[https://archive.org/stream/twentiethcentury64londuoft#page/478/mode/2up &quot;The Censorship of Fiction&quot;] ''The Nineteenth Century and After,'' Vol. LXIV, July/December 1908.
*[https://archive.org/stream/twentiethcentury66londuoft#page/974/mode/2up &quot;The Censorship of Stage Plays&quot;] ''The Nineteenth Century and After,'' Vol. LXVI, July/December 1909.
*[https://archive.org/stream/twentiethcentury69londuoft#page/902/mode/2up &quot;Irving and Stage Lightning&quot;] ''The Nineteenth Century and After,'' Vol. LXIX, January/June 1911.

===Critical works on Stoker===
*[[William Hughes (professor)|William Hughes]], ''Beyond Dracula'' (Palgrave, 2000) {{ISBN|0-312-23136-9}}&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://muse.jhu.edu/login?uri=%2Fjournals%2Fvictorian_studies%2Fv044%2F44.2glover.html# |title=Archived copy |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160304130814/http://muse.jhu.edu/login?uri=%2Fjournals%2Fvictorian_studies%2Fv044%2F44.2glover.html# |archive-date=4 March 2016 |access-date=24 November 2018 |df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Belford, Barbara. ''Bram Stoker: A Biography of the Author of Dracula''. London: Weidenfeld and Nicolson, 1996.
*Senf, Carol. ''Science and Social Science in Bram Stoker's Fiction'' (Greenwood, 2002).
*Senf, Carol. ''Dracula: Between Tradition and Modernism'' (Twayne, 1998).
*Senf, Carol A. ''Bram Stoker'' (University of Wales Press, 2010).  Shepherd, Mike. ''When Brave Men Shudder: the Scottish origins of Dracula'' (Wild Wolf Publishing 2018) 
*Shepherd, Mike. When Brave Men Shudder: the Scottish origins of Dracula (Wild Wolf Publishing, 2018)
*Skal, David J. ''Something in the Blood: The Untold Story of Bram Stoker'' (Liveright, 2016)

===Bibliographies===
*William Hughes [http://www.victoriansecrets.co.uk/victorian-fiction-research-guides/bram-stoker/ Bram Stoker – Victorian Fiction Research Guide]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
{{Library resources box}}
{{Sister project links |wikt=no |commons=Bram Stoker |b=no |n=no |q=Bram Stoker |s=no |v=no |voy=no |d=no |species=no |display=Bram Stoker}}
* {{Gutenberg author|id=190}}
* {{Librivox author |id=138}}

* {{OL author}}
*{{Dmoz|Arts/Literature/Authors/S/Stoker,_Bram}}
*[https://www.bbc.co.uk/dna/h2g2/A588233 h2g2 article on Bram Stoker]
* {{isfdb name|650}}
* Archival material at {{wikidata|qualifier|property|P485|Q24568958|P856|format=\[%q %p\]}}
* {{IMDB name|0831290}}
* {{LCAuth|n79061014|Bram Stoker|219|ue}}

{{Bram Stoker|state=expanded}}
{{Dracula}}
{{The Jewel of Seven Stars}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Stoker, Bram}}
[[Category:Bram Stoker| ]]
[[Category:Dracula]]
[[Category:1847 births]]
[[Category:1912 deaths]]
[[Category:Auditors of the College Historical Society]]
[[Category:Irish horror writers]]
[[Category:Irish male short story writers]]
[[Category:Irish short story writers]]
[[Category:Irish Anglicans]]
[[Category:Alumni of Trinity College Dublin]]
[[Category:People from Dublin (city)]]
[[Category:19th-century Irish novelists]]
[[Category:20th-century Irish novelists]]
[[Category:20th-century Irish male writers]]
[[Category:Irish male novelists]]
[[Category:Victorian novelists]]
[[Category:Golders Green Crematorium]]
[[Category:Irish fantasy writers]]
[[Category:19th-century short story writers]]
[[Category:Writers of Gothic fiction]]</text>
      <sha1>bvktl75mij2bkxv4959p9gopi883991</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
