  <page>
    <title>Bastille Day</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3936</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943139357</id>
      <parentid>939286480</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-29T02:35:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bluelink 1 book for [[Wikipedia:Verifiability|verifiability]]. [goog]) #IABot (v2.0) ([[User:GreenC bot|GreenC bot]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{About|the French national holiday}}
{{redirect|fête nationale française|other French language fêtes nationales|fête nationale}}
{{Short description|National holiday in France}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2018}}
{{Infobox holiday
| image        = Feu d'artifice du 14 juillet 2017 depuis le champ de Mars à Paris, devant la Tour Eiffel, Bastille day 2017 (35118978683).jpg
| caption      = Fireworks at the [[Eiffel Tower]], [[Paris]], 2017
[[File:Bastille Day, Paris, 2017 (36127738205).jpg|240px]]&lt;br /&gt;The [[Patrouille de France|aerobatic team]] of the [[French Air Force]]
| holiday_name = Bastille Day
| nickname     = French National Day&lt;br /&gt;(''Fête nationale'')&lt;br /&gt;The Fourteenth of July&lt;br /&gt;(''Quatorze juillet'')
| significance = Commemorates the [[Storming of the Bastille]] on 14 July 1789,&lt;ref name=&quot;FranceOfficialWebsite&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ElyseeOfficialWebsite&quot; /&gt; and the unity of the French people at the [[Fête de la Fédération]] on 14 July 1790
| observedby   = [[France]]
| date         = 14 July
| frequency    = annual
| celebrations = [[Military parade]]s, [[fireworks]], concerts, [[Ball (dance)|ball]]s
| type         = [[National day]]
}}

'''Bastille Day''' is the common name given in English-speaking countries to the [[national day]] of [[France]], which is celebrated on 14 July each year. In French, it is formally called '''{{lang|fr|la Fête nationale}}''' ({{IPA-fr|la fɛt nasjɔnal}}; &quot;The National Celebration&quot;) and commonly and legally '''{{lang|fr|le 14 juillet}}''' ({{IPA-fr|lə katɔʁz(ə) ʒɥijɛ}}; &quot;the 14th of July&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.legifrance.gouv.fr/affichCodeArticle.do?idArticle=LEGIARTI000006902611&amp;cidTexte=LEGITEXT000006072050 Article L. 3133-3 of French labour code] on www.legifrance.gouv.fr.&lt;/ref&gt;

The French National Day is the anniversary of [[Storming of the Bastille]] on 14 July 1789,&lt;ref name=&quot;FranceOfficialWebsite&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Bastille Day – 14th July|url=https://www.france.fr/en/happening-now-in-france/happy-bastille-day-where-better-to-celebrate-than-in-paris|website=Official Website of France|quote=A national celebration, a re-enactment of the storming of the Bastille ... Commemorating the storming of the Bastille on 14th July 1789, Bastille Day takes place on the same date each year. The main event is a grand military parade along the Champs-Élysées, attended by the President of the Republic and other political leaders. It is accompanied by fireworks and public dances in towns throughout the whole of France.|url-status = dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140715082859/http://www.france.fr/en/celebrations-and-festivals/bastille-day-14th-july.html|archivedate=15 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ElyseeOfficialWebsite&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=La fête nationale du 14 juillet|url=http://www.elysee.fr/la-presidence/la-fete-nationale-du-14-juillet/|website=Official Website of Elysée}}&lt;/ref&gt; a turning point of the [[French Revolution]],&lt;ref name=&quot;EyeWitness&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=The Beginning of the French Revolution, 1789 |url= http://www.eyewitnesstohistory.com/frenchrevolution.htm|website=EyeWitness to History| quote= [[Thomas Jefferson]] was America's minister to France in 1789. As tensions grew and violence erupted, Jefferson traveled to Versailles and Paris to observe events first-hand. He reported his experience in a series of letters to America's Secretary of State, [[John Jay]]. We join Jefferson's story as tensions escalate to violence on July 12: &lt;br&gt; July 12 &lt;br&gt; In the afternoon a body of about 100 German cavalry were advanced and drawn up in the Palace Louis XV. and about 300 Swiss posted at a little distance in their rear. This drew people to that spot, who naturally formed themselves in front of the troops, at first merely to look at them. But as their numbers increased their indignation arose: they retired a few steps, posted themselves on and behind large piles of loose stone collected in that Place for a bridge adjacent to it, and attacked the horse with stones. The horse charged, but the advantageous position of the people, and the showers of stones obliged them to retire, and even to quit the field altogether, leaving one of their number on the ground. The Swiss in their rear were observed never to stir. This was the signal for universal insurrection, and this body of cavalry, to avoid being massacred, retired towards Versailles. &lt;br&gt; The people now armed themselves with such weapons as they could find in Armourer's shops and private houses, and with bludgeons, and were roaming all night through all parts of the city without any decided and practicable object. &lt;br&gt; July 13 &lt;br&gt; ...A Committee of magistrates and electors of the city are appointed, by their bodies, to take upon them its government. &lt;br&gt; The mob, now openly joined by the French guards, force the prisons of St. Lazare, release all the prisoners, and take a great store of corn, which they carry to the corn market. Here they get some arms, and the French guards begin to form and train them. The City committee determines to raise 48,000 Bourgeois, or rather to restrain their numbers to 48,000.'}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as the [[Fête de la Fédération]] which celebrated the unity of the French people on 14 July 1790. Celebrations are held throughout France. The oldest and largest regular [[Bastille Day military parade|military parade]] in Europe{{Citation needed|date=July 2019}} is held on 14 July on the [[Champs-Élysées]] in Paris in front of the [[President of France|President of the Republic]], along with other French officials and foreign guests.&lt;ref name=&quot;paris1&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.paris.com/paris_city_guide/city_visits_of_paris/champs_elysees_arc_de_triomphe |title=Champs-Élysées city visit in Paris, France&amp;nbsp;– Recommended city visit of Champs-Élysées in Paris |publisher=Paris.com |accessdate=27 July 2011 |url-status = dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110807091009/http://www.paris.com/paris_city_guide/city_visits_of_paris/champs_elysees_arc_de_triomphe |archivedate=7 August 2011  }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;paris-attractions1&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://paris-attractions.net/celebrate-bastille-day-in-paris-this-year/ |title=Celebrate Bastille Day in Paris This Year |publisher=Paris Attractions |date=3 May 2011 |accessdate=27 July 2011 |url-status = dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120326174027/http://paris-attractions.net/celebrate-bastille-day-in-paris-this-year/ |archivedate=26 March 2012  }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
[[Jacques Necker]], the Finance Minister, who was sympathetic to the [[Estates of the realm#Third Estate|Third Estate]], was dismissed on 11 July 1789. The people of Paris then stormed the [[Bastille]], fearful that they and their representatives would be attacked by the royal army or by foreign regiments of mercenaries in the king's service, and seeking to gain ammunition and gunpowder for the general populace. The Bastille was a fortress-prison in Paris which had often held people jailed on the basis of ''[[lettre de cachet|lettres de cachet]]'' (literally &quot;signet letters&quot;), arbitrary royal indictments that could not be appealed and did not indicate the reason for the imprisonment. The Bastille held a large cache of ammunition and gunpowder, and was also known for holding political prisoners whose writings had displeased the royal government, and was thus a symbol of the [[political absolutism|absolutism]] of the monarchy. As it happened, at the time of the attack in July 1789 there were only seven inmates, none of great political significance.&lt;ref&gt;G A Chevallaz, Histoire générale de 1789 à nos jours, p. 22, Payot, Lausanne 1974&lt;/ref&gt; Preceding this on 14 July itself, was the siege of Hôtel des Invalides; [[Les Invalides]], for firearms, muskets and canons, stored in its cellars, by rioting Parisians.&lt;ref&gt;[https://time.com/4402553/bastille-day-history-july-14/ What Actually Happened on the Original Bastille Day]&lt;/ref&gt;

The crowd was eventually reinforced by mutinous ''[[Gardes Françaises]]'' (&quot;French Guards&quot;), whose usual role was to protect public buildings. They proved a fair match for the fort's defenders, and [[Bernard-René de Launay|Governor de Launay]], the commander of the Bastille, capitulated and opened the gates to avoid a mutual massacre. However, possibly because of a misunderstanding, fighting resumed. According to the official documents, about 200 attackers and just one defender died in the initial fighting, but in the aftermath, de Launay and seven other defenders were killed, as was [[Jacques de Flesselles]], the ''prévôt des marchands'' (&quot;provost of the merchants&quot;), the elected head of the city's guilds, who under the feudal monarchy also had the competences of a present-day mayor.&lt;ref&gt;J Isaac, L'époque révolutionnaire 1789–1851, p. 60, Hachette, Paris 1950&lt;/ref&gt;

Shortly after the storming of the Bastille, late in the evening of 4 August, after a very stormy session of the ''Assemblée constituante'', [[feudalism]] was abolished. On 26 August, the [[Declaration of the Rights of Man and of the Citizen]] (''Déclaration des Droits de l'Homme et du Citoyen'') was proclaimed (''Homme'' with an uppercase h meaning &quot;human&quot;, while ''homme'' with a lowercase h means &quot;man&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;J Isaac, L'époque révolutionnaire 1789–1851, p. 64, Hachette, Paris 1950.&lt;/ref&gt;

===''Fête de la Fédération''===
{{main|Fête de la Fédération}}
[[File:Fête de la Fédération 1790, Musée de la Révolution française - Vizille.jpg|thumb|''Fête de la Fédération'', [[Musée de la Révolution française]]]]
As early as 1789, the year of the storming of the Bastille, preliminary designs for a national festival were underway. These designs were intended to strengthen the country's national identity through the celebration of the events of 14 July 1789.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Bastille: A History of a Symbol of Despotism and Freedom|last=Lüsebrink|first=Hans-Jürgen|publisher=Duke Press University|year=1997|isbn=9780822382751|location=|pages=151}}&lt;/ref&gt; One of the first designs was proposed by Clément Gonchon, a French textile worker, who presented his design for a festival celebrating the anniversary of the storming of the Bastille to the French city administration and the public on 9 December 1789.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Bastille: A History of a Symbol of Despotism and Freedom|last=Lüsebrink|first=Hans-Jürgen|last2=Reichardt|first2=Rolf|publisher=Duke University Press|year=1997|isbn=9780822382751|location=|pages=152}}&lt;/ref&gt; There were other proposals and unofficial celebrations of 14 July 1789, but the official festival sponsored by the National Assembly was called the Fête de la Fédération.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Bastille: A History of a Symbol of Despotism and Freedom|last=Lüsebrink|first=Hans-Jürgen|last2=Reichardt|first2=Rolf|publisher=Duke University Press|year=1997|isbn=9780822382751|location=|pages=153}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''Fête de la Fédération'' on 14 July 1790 was a celebration of the unity of the French nation during the French Revolution. The aim of this celebration, one year after the [[Storming of the Bastille]], was to symbolise peace. The event took place on the [[Champ de Mars]], which was located far outside of Paris at the time. The work needed to transform the Champ de Mars into a suitable location for the celebration was not on schedule to be completed in time. On the day recalled as the Journée des brouettes (&quot;The Day of the Wheelbarrow&quot;), thousands of Parisian citizens gathered together to finish the construction needed for the celebration.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Fourteenth of July|last=Prendergast|first=Christopher|publisher=Profile Books Ltd.|year=2008|isbn=9781861979391|location=|pages=[https://archive.org/details/fourteenthofjuly0000pren/page/105 105–106]|url=https://archive.org/details/fourteenthofjuly0000pren/page/105}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The day of the festival, the National Guard assembled and proceeded along the boulevard du Temple in the pouring rain, and were met by an estimated 260,000 Parisian citizens at the Champ de Mars.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Fourteenth of July|last=Prendergast|first=Christopher|publisher=Profile Books Ltd|year=2008|isbn=9781861979391|location=|pages=[https://archive.org/details/fourteenthofjuly0000pren/page/106 106–107]|url=https://archive.org/details/fourteenthofjuly0000pren/page/106}}&lt;/ref&gt; A [[mass (liturgy)|mass]] was celebrated by [[Charles Maurice de Talleyrand-Périgord|Talleyrand]], [[bishop of Autun]]. The popular [[Gilbert du Motier, marquis de La Fayette|General Lafayette]], as captain of the National Guard of Paris and a confidant of the king, took his oath to the constitution, followed by King [[Louis XVI of France|Louis XVI]]. After the end of the official celebration, the day ended in a huge four-day popular feast and people celebrated with fireworks, as well as fine wine and running nude through the streets in order to display their great freedom.{{Citation needed|date=July 2019}}

===Origin of the current celebration===
[[File:Monet-montorgueil.JPG|thumb|[[Claude Monet]], ''Rue Montorgueil, Paris, Festival of 30 June 1878'']]
On 30 June 1878, a feast was officially arranged in Paris to honour the French Republic (the event was commemorated in a painting by [[Claude Monet]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Adamson|first=Natalie|title=Painting, politics and the struggle for the École de Paris, 1944–1964|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=EgNGAQAAIAAJ|accessdate=13 July 2011|date=15 August 2009|publisher=Ashgate|isbn=978-0-7546-5928-0|page=68}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 14 July 1879, there was another feast, with a semi-official aspect. The day's events included a reception in the Chamber of Deputies, organised and presided over by [[Léon Gambetta]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Nord|first=Philip G.|title=Impressionists and politics: art and democracy in the nineteenth century|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=cNSVHrVlGMQC&amp;pg=PA37|accessdate=13 July 2011|year=2000|publisher=Psychology Press|isbn=978-0-415-20695-2|page=37}}&lt;/ref&gt; a military review at Longchamp{{Fix|test=which Longchamp?}}, and a Republican Feast in the [[Bois de Boulogne|Pré Catelan]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Nord|first=Philip G.|title=The republican moment: struggles for democracy in nineteenth-century France|url=https://archive.org/details/republicanmoment0000nord|url-access=registration|accessdate=13 July 2011|year=1995|publisher=Harvard University Press|isbn=978-0-674-76271-8|page=[https://archive.org/details/republicanmoment0000nord/page/205 205]}}&lt;/ref&gt; All through France, ''[[Le Figaro]]'' wrote, &quot;people feasted much to honour the storming of the Bastille&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Paris Au Jour Le Jour|url=http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/bpt6k277157p/f4.image|accessdate=15 January 2013|newspaper=Le Figaro|date=16 July 1879|page=4|quote=On a beaucoup banqueté avant-hier, en mémoire de la prise de la Bastille, et comme tout banquet suppose un ou plusieurs discours, on a aussi beaucoup parlé.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1880, the government of the [[French Third Republic|Third Republic]] wanted to revive the 14 July festival. The campaign for the reinstatement of the festival had been underway for nearly a decade, sponsored by the notable politician [[Léon Gambetta]] and scholar [[Henri Baudrillart|Henri Baudrillant]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Fourteenth of July|last=Prendergast|first=Christopher|publisher=Profile Books Ltd|year=2008|isbn=9781861979391|location=|pages=[https://archive.org/details/fourteenthofjuly0000pren/page/127 127]|url=https://archive.org/details/fourteenthofjuly0000pren/page/127}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 21 May 1880, [[Benjamin Raspail]] proposed a law, signed by sixty-four members of government, to have &quot;the Republic adopt 14 July as the day of an annual national festival&quot;. There were many disputes over which date to be remembered as the national holiday, including 4 August (the commemoration of the [[The Abolition of Feudalism|end of the feudal system]]), 5 May (when the [[Estates General of 1789|Estates-General]] first assembled), 27 July (the fall of [[Maximilien Robespierre|Robespierre]]), and 21 January (the date of [[Louis XVI of France|Louis XVI]]'s execution).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Fourteenth of July|last=Prendergast|first=Christopher|publisher=Profile Books Ltd|year=2008|isbn=9781861979391|location=|pages=[https://archive.org/details/fourteenthofjuly0000pren/page/129 129]|url=https://archive.org/details/fourteenthofjuly0000pren/page/129}}&lt;/ref&gt; The government decided that the date of the holiday would be 14 July, but it was still somewhat problematic. The events of 14 July 1789 were illegal under the previous government, which contradicted the Third Republic's need to establish legal legitimacy.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Fourteenth of July|last=Prendergast|first=Christopher|publisher=Profile Books Ltd|year=2008|isbn=9781861979391|location=|pages=[https://archive.org/details/fourteenthofjuly0000pren/page/130 130]|url=https://archive.org/details/fourteenthofjuly0000pren/page/130}}&lt;/ref&gt; French politicians also did not want the sole foundation of their national holiday to be rooted in a day of bloodshed and class-hatred as the day of storming the Bastille was. Instead, they based the establishment of the holiday as a dual celebration of the Fête de la Fédération, a festival celebrating the one year anniversary of 14 July 1789, and the storming of the Bastille.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schofield&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.bbc.com/news/world-europe-23280120|title=Bastille Day: How peace and revolution got mixed up|last=Schofield|first=Hugh|date=14 July 2013|website=BBC News|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Assembly voted in favor of the proposal on 21 May and 8 June, and the law was approved on 27 and 29 June. The law was made official on 6 July 1880.{{Citation needed|date=September 2019}}

In the debate leading up to the adoption of the holiday, Senator [[Henri Martin (historian)|Henri Martin]], who wrote the National Day law,&lt;ref name=&quot;Schofield&quot;/&gt; addressed the chamber on 29 June 1880:

{{quote|text=Do not forget that behind this 14&amp;nbsp;July, where victory of the new era over the [[Ancien Régime]] was bought by fighting, do not forget that after the day of 14&amp;nbsp;July 1789, there was the day of 14&amp;nbsp;July 1790&amp;nbsp;(...) This [latter] day cannot be blamed for having shed a drop of blood, for having divided the country. It was the consecration of the unity of France&amp;nbsp;(...) If some of you might have scruples against the first 14&amp;nbsp;July, they certainly hold none against the second. Whatever difference which might part us, something hovers over them, it is the great images of national unity, which we all desire, for which we would all stand, willing to die if necessary.|sign=[[Henri Martin (historian)|Henri Martin]], 1880&lt;ref&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20130309015033/http://blog.greetingcarduniverse.com/2011/07/le-quatorze-juillet/ Le Quatorze Juillet] at the [https://web.archive.org/web/20090802114707/http://blog.greetingcarduniverse.com/ Greeting Card Universe Blog]&lt;/ref&gt;}}

===Bastille Day military parade===
{{main|Bastille Day military parade}}
[[File:French Republican Guard Bastille Day 2007 n1.jpg|thumb|Horseman of the [[Republican Guard (France)|Republican Guard]] during the 2007 [[Bastille Day military parade|military parade on the Champs-Élysées]]]]
[[File:Dominique Vallet-IMG 5734.JPG|thumb|Surgeon general inspector Dominique Vallet, head of the Laveran military medical school, at the ceremonies for Bastille Day in [[Marseille]], 2012]]
The Bastille Day military parade is the French [[military parade]] that has been held on the morning of 14 July each year in Paris since 1880. While previously held elsewhere within or near the capital city, since 1918 it has been held on the [[Champs-Élysées]], with the participation of the Allies as represented in the Versailles Peace Conference, and with the exception of the period of German occupation from 1940 to 1944 (when the ceremony took place in London under the command of General [[Charles de Gaulle]]).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.garnison-paris.terre.defense.gouv.fr/14juillet2008/les-coulisses/historique-du-defile.htm Défilé du 14 juillet, des origines à nos jours] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110224003154/http://www.garnison-paris.terre.defense.gouv.fr/14juillet2008/les-coulisses/historique-du-defile.htm |date=24 February 2011 }} (14 July Parade, from its origins to the present)&lt;/ref&gt; The parade passes down the Champs-Élysées from the [[Arc de Triomphe]] to the [[Place de la Concorde]], where the [[President of the French Republic]], his government and foreign ambassadors to France stand. This is a popular event in France, broadcast on French TV, and is the oldest and largest regular military parade in Europe.&lt;ref name=&quot;paris1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;paris-attractions1&quot;/&gt; In some years, invited detachments of foreign troops take part in the parade and foreign statesmen attend as guests{{Citation needed|date=July 2019}}

Smaller military parades are held in French garrison towns, including [[Toulon]] and [[Belfort]], with local troops.{{Citation needed|date=July 2019}}

==Bastille Day celebrations in other countries==
===Belgium===
[[Liège]] celebrates the Bastille Day each year since the end of the [[World War I|First World War]], as Liège was decorated by the [[Légion d'Honneur]] for its unexpected resistance during the [[Battle of Liège]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Reuters-Bastille Day&quot;&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.reuters.com/article/us-travel-picks-bastilleday/travel-picks-top-10-bastille-day-celebrations-idUSBRE86C0IT20120713 |title=Travel Picks: Top 10 Bastille Day celebrations |date=13 July 2012 |work=Reuters |access-date=13 July 2018 |language=en-US }}&lt;/ref&gt; The city also hosts a fireworks show outside of Congress Hall. Specifically in Liège, celebrations of Bastille Day have been known to be bigger than the celebrations of the Belgian National holiday.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/travel/destinations/europe/france/galleries/Bastille-Day-world-celebrations/liege-belgium/|title=Bastille Day: world celebrations|last=|first=|date=12 July 2012|website=The Telegraph|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Around 35,000 people gather to celebrate Bastille Day. There is a traditional festival dance of the French consul that draws large crowds, and many unofficial events over the city celebrate the relationship between France and the city of Liège.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://eurofluence.com/en/an-unusual-bastille-day-in-liege-belgium/|title=An unusual Bastille Day: in Liège, Belgium|last=|first=|date=19 July 2014|website=Eurofluence|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Canada===
[[Vancouver]], British Columbia, holds a celebration featuring exhibits, food and entertainment.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.bastilledayfestival.ca/ |title=Bastille Day Festival Vancouver |website=Bastille Day Festival Vancouver |language=en |access-date=13 July 2018 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The Toronto Bastille Day festival is also celebrated in [[Toronto]], [[Ontario]]. The festival is organized by the French community in Toronto and sponsored by the Consulate General of France. The celebration includes music, performances, sport competitions, and a French Market. At the end of the festival, there is also a traditional French bal populaire.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.frenchstreet.ca/toronto-bastille-day/|title=Toronto Bastille Day|website=French Street|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Czech Republic===
Since 2008, [[Prague]] has hosted a French market &quot;{{lang|fr|Le marché du 14 juillet}}&quot; (&quot;Fourteenth of July Market&quot;) offering traditional French food and wine as well as music. The market takes place on [[Kampa Island]], it is usually between 11 and 14 July.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.prague.eu/en/event/6896/french-market-at-kampa-le-marche-du-14-juillet |title=French Market at Kampa – Le marché du 14 Juillet |website=Prague.eu |language=en |access-date=13 July 2018 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180713200950/https://www.prague.eu/en/event/6896/french-market-at-kampa-le-marche-du-14-juillet |archive-date=13 July 2018 |url-status = dead|df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; It acts as an event that marks the relinquish of the EU presidency from France to the Czech Republic. Traditional selections of French produce, including cheese, wine, meat, bread and pastries, are provided by the market. Throughout the event, live music is played in the evenings, with lanterns lighting up the square at night.&lt;ref name=&quot;:04&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.worldfirst.com/uk/blog/economic-updates/daily-update/7-places-outside-france-bastille-day-celebrated/|title=7 places outside France where Bastille Day is celebrated|last=Trumper|first=David|date=11 July 2014|website=WorldFirst|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Fireworks on the Danube Bastille Day 2008.jpg|thumb|Bastille Day fireworks in [[Budapest]], [[Hungary]]]]

===Hungary===
[[Budapest]]'s two-day celebration is sponsored by the [[Institut de France]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.budapestresources.com/node/447 |title=Bastille Day 2007 – Budapest |publisher=Budapestresources.com |date=14 July 2011 |accessdate=27 July 2011| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20110708104413/http://www.budapestresources.com/node/447| archivedate= 8 July 2011 |url-status = live}}&lt;/ref&gt; The festival is hosted along the [[Danube|Danube River]], with streets filled with music and dancing. There are also local markets dedicated to French foods and wine, mixed with some traditional Hungarian specialties. At the end of the celebration, a fireworks show is held on the river banks.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.reuters.com/article/us-travel-picks-bastilleday-idUSBRE86C0IT20120713|title=Travel Picks: Top 10 Bastille Day celebrations|newspaper=Reuters|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=|date=13 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===India===
Bastille Day is celebrated with great festivity in [[Pondicherry]], a former French colony, every year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.py.gov.in/knowpuducherry/puduculture.html|title=Puducherry Culture|publisher=Government of Puducherry|accessdate=14 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; On the eve of the Bastille Day, retired soldiers parade and celebrate the day with Indian and French National Anthems. On the day, uniformed war soldiers march through the street to honor the French soldiers who were killed in the battles. One can perceive French and the Indian flag flying alongside that project the mishmash of cultures and heritages.{{Citation needed|date=July 2019}}

===Ireland===
The Embassy of France in Ireland organizes several events around [[Dublin]], [[Cork (city)|Cork]] and [[Limerick]] for Bastille Day; including evenings of French music and tasting of French food. Many members of the French community in Ireland take part in the festivities.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://ie.ambafrance.org/https-ie-ambafrance-org-Bastille-Day-2018 |title=Bastille Day 2018 |publisher=French Embassy in Ireland |language=en |access-date=13 July 2018 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180713205853/https://ie.ambafrance.org/https-ie-ambafrance-org-Bastille-Day-2018 |archive-date=13 July 2018 |url-status = dead|df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Events in Dublin include live entertainment, speciality menus on French cuisine, and screenings of popular French films.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://babylonradio.com/july-14th-bastille-day-celebrations-dublin/|title=July 14th Bastille Day Celebrations in Dublin|last=|first=|date=14 July 2016|website=Babylon Radio|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===New Zealand===
The [[Auckland]] suburb of [[Remuera]] hosts an annual French-themed Bastille Day street festival.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.remuera.org.nz/|title=Array|website=Remuera Business Association}}&lt;/ref&gt; Visitors enjoy mimes, dancers, music, as well as French foods and drinks. The budding relationship between the two countries, with the establishment of a Maori garden in France and exchange of their analyses of cave art, resulted in the creation of an official reception at the Residence of France. There is also an event in Wellington for the French community held at the Residence of France.&lt;ref name=&quot;:04&quot;/&gt;

===South Africa===
[[Franschhoek]]'s weekend festival&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.franschhoek.co.za/bastille.html |title=Bastille Day Festival at Franschhoek |publisher=Franschhoek.co.za |accessdate=27 July 2011| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20110725190720/http://www.franschhoek.co.za/bastille.html| archivedate= 25 July 2011 |url-status = live}}&lt;/ref&gt; has been celebrated since 1993. (Franschhoek, or 'French Corner,' is situated in the [[Western Cape]].) As South Africa's gourmet capital, French food, wine and other entertainment is provided throughout the festival. The French Consulate in South Africa also celebrates their national holiday with a party for the French community.&lt;ref name=&quot;:04&quot;/&gt; Activities also include dressing up in different items of French clothing.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.sahistory.org.za/dated-event/bastille-day-celebrated-across-world-and-franchhoek-south-africa|title=Bastille Day is celebrated across the world and in Franchhoek, South Africa|last=|first=|date=12 November 2017|website=South African History Online|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== French Polynesia===
Following colonial rule, [[France]] annexed a large portion of what is now [[French Polynesia]]. Under French rule, [[Tahiti]]ans were permitted to participate in sport, singing, and dancing competitions one day a year: Bastille Day.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://xdaysiny.com/heiva-festival-tahiti-french-polynesia/|title=The Best Festival You've Never Heard Of: The Heiva in Tahiti|last=|first=|date=7 July 2017|website=X Days in Y|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The single day of celebration evolved into the major [[Heiva]] i Tahiti festival in [[Papeete]] Tahiti, where traditional events such as canoe races, tattooing, and fire walks are held. The singing and dancing competitions continued, with music composed with traditional instruments such as a nasal flute and ukulele.&lt;ref name=&quot;:04&quot;/&gt;

===United Kingdom===
Within [[England]], [[London]] has a large French contingent, and celebrates Bastille Day at various locations across the city including [[Battersea Park]], [[Camden Town]] and [[Kentish Town]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.viewlondon.co.uk/whatson/bastille-day-london-feature-1130.html |title=Bastille Day London&amp;nbsp;– Bastille Day Events in London, Bastille Day 2011 |publisher=Viewlondon.co.uk |accessdate=27 July 2011| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20110617102403/http://www.viewlondon.co.uk/whatson/bastille-day-london-feature-1130.html| archivedate= 17 June 2011 |url-status = live}}&lt;/ref&gt; Live entertainment is performed at [[Canary Wharf]], with weeklong performances of French theatre at the Lion and Unicorn Theatre in Kentish Town. Restaurants feature cabarets and special menus across the city, and other celebrations include garden parties and sports tournaments. There is also a large event at the Bankside and Borough Market, where there is live music, street performers, and traditional French games are played.&lt;ref name=&quot;:04&quot;/&gt;

===United States===
The United States has over 20 cities that conduct annual celebrations of Bastille Day. The different cities celebrate with many French staples such as food, music, games, and sometimes the recreation of famous French landmarks.&lt;ref name=&quot;france-amerique.com&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://france-amerique.com/en/where-to-celebrate-bastille-day-in-the-united-states/|title=Where to Celebrate Bastille Day in the United States?|last=|first=|date=6 July 2017|website=France-Amérique|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

;Northeastern States
[[Baltimore]], [[Maryland]] has a large Bastille Day celebration each year at Petit Louis in the Roland Park area of [[Baltimore City]]. [[Boston]] has a celebration annually, hosted by the French Cultural Center for 40 years. The street festival occurs in Boston's [[Back Bay]] neighborhood, near the Cultural Center's headquarters. The celebration includes [[wikt:francophone|francophone]] musical performers, dancing, and [[French cuisine]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Telegraph-Bastille Day&quot;&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/travel/destinations/europe/france/galleries/Bastille-Day-world-celebrations/ |title=Bastille Day: world celebrations |date=4 February 2016 |work=[[The Daily Telegraph|The Telegraph]] |access-date=13 July 2018 |language=en-GB |issn=0307-1235 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[New York City]], [[New York (state)|New York]] has numerous Bastille Day celebrations each July, including ''Bastille Day on 60th Street'' hosted by the [[French Institute Alliance Française]] between Fifth and Lexington Avenues on the Upper East Side of [[Manhattan]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bastilledayny.com|title=Bastille Day on 60th Street, New York City, Sunday, July 15, 2012 &amp;#124; 12–5pm &amp;#124; Fifth Avenue to Lexington Avenue|date=10 July 2011|publisher=Bastilledayny.com|accessdate=27 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bastille Day on Smith Street in [[Brooklyn]], and Bastille Day in [[Tribeca]]. There is also the annual Bastille Day Ball, taking place since 1924.&lt;ref name=&quot;france-amerique.com&quot;/&gt; [[Philadelphia]], [[Pennsylvania]]'s Bastille Day, held at [[Eastern State Penitentiary]], involves [[Marie Antoinette]] throwing locally manufactured [[Tastykake]]s at the Parisian [[militia]], as well as a re-enactment of the storming of the Bastille.&lt;ref name=&quot;Telegraph-Bastille Day&quot; /&gt;

;Southern States
In [[Dallas]], [[Texas]] the Bastille Day celebration, &quot;Bastille On Bishop&quot;, began in 2010 and is held annually on 14 July in the [[Bishop Arts District, Dallas|Bishop Arts District]] of the [[Oak Cliff, Texas|North Oak Cliff]] neighborhood, southwest of [[Downtown Dallas|downtown]] just across the [[Trinity River (Texas)|Trinity River]].  Dallas' French roots are tied to the short lived socialist Utopian community [[La Reunion (Dallas)|La Réunion]], formed in 1855 and incorporated into the City of Dallas in 1860.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.bastilleonbishop.com/|title=Bastille on Bishop|publisher=Go Oak Cliff|language=en|access-date=13 July 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Miami]], [[Florida]]'s celebration is organized by &quot;French &amp; Famous&quot; in partnership with the French American Chamber of Commerce, the Union des Français de l'Etranger and many French brands. The event gathers over 1,000 attendees to celebrate &quot;La Fête Nationale&quot;. The location and theme change every year. In 2017, the theme was &quot;Guinguette Party&quot; and attracted 1,200 francophiles at The River Yacht Club.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://courrierdefloride.com/2017/06/26/bastille-day-party-french-famous-14-juillet-miami-beach/|title=Le 14 juillet à Miami : Bastille Day Party de &quot;French &amp; Famous&quot; !|date=26 June 2017|work=Le Courrier de Floride|access-date=13 July 2018|language=fr-FR}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[New Orleans]], [[Louisiana]] has multiple celebrations, the largest in the historic [[French Quarter]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nola.com/news/index.ssf/2009/07/only_in_new_orleans_watch_loca.html|title=Only in New Orleans: Watch locals celebrate Bastille Day in the French Quarter|last=Carr|first=Martha|date=13 July 2009|work=The Times-Picayune|accessdate=27 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[St. Louis]], [[Missouri]] has annual festivals in  the [[Soulard]] neighborhood, the former French village of [[Carondelet, Missouri]], and in the [[Benton Park, St. Louis|Benton Park]] neighborhood. [[Chatillon–DeMenil House|The Chatillon-DeMenil Mansion]] in the Benton Park neighborhood,  holds an annual Bastille Day festival with reenactments of the beheading of [[Marie Antoinette]] and [[Louis XVI]], traditional dancing, and artillery demonstrations. Carondelet also began hosting an annual [[bar crawl|saloon crawl]] to celebrate Bastille Day in 2017.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.demenil.org/bastille-day-history/|title=Bastille Day|website=Chatillon-DeMenil Mansion|language=en-US|access-date=13 July 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Washington, D.C.|Washington D.C.]], food, music, and auction events are sponsored by the Embassy of France. There is also a French Festival within the city, where families can meet period entertainment groups set during the time of the French Revolution. Restaurants host parties serving traditional French food.&lt;ref name=&quot;france-amerique.com&quot;/&gt;

; Midwestern States
[[Chicago]], [[Illinois]] has hosted a variety of Bastille Day celebrations in a number of locations in the city, including [[Navy Pier]] and [[Oz Park]].  The recent incarnations have been sponsored in part by the Chicago branch of the French-American Chamber of Commerce and by the [[List of diplomatic missions of France|French Consulate-General]] in Chicago.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.bastilledaychicago.org/ |title=Bastille Day Chicago |publisher=Consulate General of France |language=en |access-date=13 July 2018 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Milwaukee]], [[Wisconsin]]'s four-day street festival begins with a &quot;Storming of the Bastille&quot; with a 43-foot replica of the [[Eiffel Tower]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.easttown.com/categories/4-bastilledays|title=Bastille Days &amp;#124; Milwaukee, WI|date=12 July 2014|publisher=East Town Association|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110226195450/http://easttown.com/categories/4-bastilledays|archivedate=26 February 2011|url-status = dead|accessdate=23 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Minneapolis]], [[Minnesota]] has a celebration with wine, French food, pastries, a flea market, circus performers and bands. Also in the Twin Cities area, the local chapter of the [[Alliance Française]] has hosted an annual event for years at varying locations with a competition for the &quot;Best [[Baguette]] of the [[Minneapolis–Saint Paul|Twin Cities]].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Read To 2009&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.yelp.com/events/minneapolis-2009-bastille-day-celebration-alliance-fran%C3%A7aise|title=2009 Bastille Day Celebration – Alliance Française, Minneapolis|date=11 July 2009|website=Yelp|accessdate=18 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.consulfrance-chicago.org/IMG/html/FMEX/FMEX06-11/FeteNationale2011.htm#MINNESOTA|title=Bastille Day celebrations, 2011|date=14 July 2011|website=Consulat Général de France à Chicago|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131030101428/http://www.consulfrance-chicago.org/IMG/html/FMEX/FMEX06-11/FeteNationale2011.htm|archivedate=30 October 2013|url-status = dead|accessdate=18 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Montgomery, Ohio]] has a celebration with wine, beer, local restaurants' fare, pastries, games and bands.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.montgomeryohio.org/bastille-day-celebration/|title=Bastille Day Celebration!|date=31 May 2018|website=City of Montgomery, Ohio|language=en-US|access-date=13 July 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

; Western States
[[Portland, Oregon]] has celebrated Bastille Day with crowds up to 8,000, in public festivals at various public parks, since 2001. The event is coordinated by the Alliance Française of Portland.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.afportland.org/2018/07/bastille-day-july-14-at-jamison-square/|title=Bastille Day July 14 at Jamison Square|publisher=Alliance Française de Portland|language=en-US|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180713205348/https://www.afportland.org/2018/07/bastille-day-july-14-at-jamison-square/|archive-date=13 July 2018|url-status = dead|access-date=13 July 2018|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Seattle]], [[Washington (state)|Washington]]'s Bastille Day celebration, held at the [[Seattle Center]], involves performances, picnics, wine and shopping.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://afseattle.org/events/2018/07/bastille-day-celebration/|website=Alliance Française de Seattle|publisher=Bastille Day celebration|language=en-US|access-date=13 July 2018|title=Bastille Day celebration - Alliance Française de Seattle}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Sacramento, California]] conducts annual &quot;waiter races&quot; in the midtown restaurant and shopping district, with a street festival.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://sacramentobastilleday.com/|title=Waiters' Race &amp; Street Festival|website=Sacramento Bastille Day|language=en-US|access-date=13 July 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==One-time celebrations==
[[File:Bastille Day, 14 July 1880 (Monument to the Republic) 2010-03-23 02.jpg|thumb|right|200px|Bronze relief of a memorial dedicated to Bastille Day.]]
* 1979: A concert with [[Jean Michel Jarre]] on the [[Place de la Concorde]] in Paris was the first concert to have one million attendees.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite magazine |last=Yelton |first=Geary |date=10 April 2017 |title=On Tour with Jean-Michel Jarre |url=https://www.keyboardmag.com/artists/on-tour-with-jean-michel-jarre |magazine=Keyboard |language=en-us |access-date=12 July 2018 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1989: France celebrated the 200th anniversary of the French Revolution, notably with a monumental show on the [[Champs-Élysées]] in Paris, directed by French designer [[Jean-Paul Goude]]. President [[François Mitterrand]] acted as host for invited world leaders.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://articles.chicagotribune.com/1989-07-15/news/8902170553_1_bicentennial-bastille-day-president-francois-mitterrand |title=French Shoot The Works With Soaring Bicentennial French |last=Longworth |first=R.C. |date=15 July 1989 |work=[[Chicago Tribune]] |access-date=12 July 2018 |language=en }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1990: A concert with Jarre was held at [[La Défense]] near Paris.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://jeanmicheljarre.com/live/paris-la-defense|title=Paris La Défense – Jean-Michel Jarre {{!}} Official Site|website=jeanmicheljarre.com|language=en-US|access-date=3 February 2018 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1994: The [[Bastille Day Military Parade|military parade]] was opened by [[Eurocorps]], a newly created European army unit including German soldiers. This was the first time German troops paraded in France since 1944, as a symbol of [[France–Germany relations|Franco-German reconciliation]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://articles.latimes.com/1994-07-15/news/mn-15833_1_bastille-day |title=German Troops Join Bastille Day Parade in Paris |last=Kraft |first=Scott |date=15 July 1994 |work=[[Los Angeles Times]] |access-date=12 July 2018 |language=en-US |issn=0458-3035 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1995: A concert with Jarre was held at the [[Eiffel Tower]] in Paris.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://jeanmicheljarre.com/live/concert-for-tolerance|title=Concert For Tolerance |website=Jean-Michel Jarre Official Site|language=en-US|access-date=3 February 2018 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1998: Two days after the [[France national football team|French football team]] became [[1998 FIFA World Cup Final|World Cup champions]], huge celebrations took place nationwide.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.theglobeandmail.com/sports/soccer/france-1998-the-giddiness-and-glory-of-the-greatest-fifa-world-cup-ever-played/article19063894/ |title=World Cup: Remembering the giddiness and glory of France '98 |last=Young |first=Chris |date=8 June 2014 |work=[[The Globe and Mail]] |access-date=12 July 2018 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 2004: To commemorate the centenary of the [[Entente Cordiale]], the British led the [[Bastille Day Military Parade|military parade]] with the [[Red Arrows]] flying overhead.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/france/1467100/Best-of-British-lead-the-way-in-parade-for-Bastille-Day.html |title=Best of British lead the way in parade for Bastille Day |last=Broughton |first=Philip Delves |date=14 July 2004 |work=[[The Daily Telegraph|The Telegraph]] |access-date=12 July 2018 |language=en-GB |issn=0307-1235 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 2007: To commemorate the 50th anniversary of the [[Treaty of Rome]], the military parade was led by troops from the 26 other [[EU member states]], all marching at the French time.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.diplomatie.gouv.fr/en/coming-to-france/france-facts/symbols-of-the-republic/article/the-14th-of-july-bastille-day |title=The 14th of July : Bastille Day |website=French Ministry for Europe and Foreign Affairs |language=en-EN |access-date=12 July 2018 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 2014: To commemorate the 100th anniversary of the beginning to the [[First World War]], representatives of 80 countries who fought during this conflict were invited to the ceremony. The military parade was opened by 76 flags representing each of these countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/picturegalleries/worldnews/10966218/Bastille-Day-in-pictures-Soldiers-from-76-countries-march-down-Champs-Elysees.html |title=Bastille Day in pictures: Soldiers from 76 countries march down Champs-Elysees |date=14 July 2014 |work=[[The Daily Telegraph|The Telegraph]] |access-date=12 July 2018 |language=en-GB |issn=0307-1235 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 2017: To commemorate the 100th anniversary of the [[United States|United States of America]]'s entry into the [[First World War]], French President [[Emmanuel Macron]] invited American President [[Donald Trump]] to celebrate a centuries-long transatlantic tie between the two countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2017/06/27/world/europe/emmanuel-macron-trump-bastille-day-syria-chemical-weapons.html |title=Macron Invites Trump to Paris for Bastille Day |last=Breeden |first=Aurelien |date=27 June 2017 |work=[[The New York Times]] |access-date=12 July 2018 |language=en }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Incidents during Bastille Day==
* In 2002, [[Maxime Brunerie]] attempted to shoot French President [[Jacques Chirac]] during the Champs-Élysées parade.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2002/07/15/world/chirac-unhurt-as-man-shoots-at-him-in-paris.html|title=Chirac Unhurt As Man Shoots At Him in Paris|last=Riding|first=Alan|date=15 July 2002|work=The New York Times|access-date=3 February 2018|language=en-US|issn=0362-4331}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In 2009, Paris youths [[2009 French riots|set fire]] to more than 300 cars on Bastille Day.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |date=14 July 2009 |title=French youths burn 300 cars to mark Bastille Day |url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/france/5824629/French-youths-burn-300-cars-to-mark-Bastille-Day.html |newspaper=The Telegraph |access-date=15 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In 2016, [[Mohamed Lahouaiej-Bouhlel]] [[2016 Nice truck attack|drove a truck into crowds]] during celebrations in the city of [[Nice]]. 86 people were killed and 434 injured along the [[Promenade des Anglais]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.bbc.com/news/world-europe-36800730 |title=Lorry attacks people on Bastile Day Celebrations |date=14 July 2016 |access-date=14 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* &quot;[[Bastille Day (song)|Bastille Day]]&quot;, a song by Canadian progressive rock band [[Rush (band)|Rush]]
* [[Bastille Day event]]
* [[Opération 14 juillet]]
* [[Place de la Bastille]]
* [[Public holidays in France]]
* Other national holidays in July:
** [[Independence Day (United States)|Independence Day/Fourth of July]] in the [[United States of America]]
** [[Canada Day]] in [[Canada]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Bastille Day}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20130329041343/http://www.france.fr/en/celebrations-and-festivals/bastille-day-%E2%80%93-14th-july 14 July] – Official French website (in English)

{{French Revolution navbox}}
{{Portal bar|France|Holidays}}

[[Category:Culture of the French Revolution]]
[[Category:July observances]]
[[Category:Parades in France]]
[[Category:Storming of the Bastille|Day]]
[[Category:National days]]
[[Category:French culture]]
[[Category:Recurring events established in 1880]]
[[Category:1880 establishments in France]]
[[Category:Annual events in France]]
[[Category:Summer events in France]]
[[Category:French-Australian culture]]</text>
      <sha1>qja516oj7g3m1u3n3tbstlvd2a6yab0</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
