  <page>
    <title>Baroque</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3957</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942439786</id>
      <parentid>942439775</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-24T18:06:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ClueBot NG</username>
        <id>13286072</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverting possible vandalism by [[Special:Contribs/168.235.222.101|168.235.222.101]] to version by DavidBrooks. [[WP:CBFP|Report False Positive?]] Thanks, [[WP:CBNG|ClueBot NG]]. (3702541) (Bot)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Artistic style in Europe and colonies, c. 1600–1750}}
{{Other uses}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=February 2017}}
{{Infobox art movement
| name = The Baroque 
|image = {{photomontage
|photo1a=WLA metmuseum Venus and Adonis by Peter Paul Rubens.jpg
|photo2a=Teresabernini.JPG
|photo3a= Wieskirche 1.2.jpg
|size = 250
|color_border = #AAAAAA
|color = #F9F9F9
}}
| caption = Top:  ''Venus and Adonis'' by [[Peter Paul Rubens]] (1635–40); Centre: ''The Ecstasy of Saint Teresa'' by [[Bernini]] (1651); Bottom: The [[Wieskirche]] in Bavaria (1754)
| yearsactive = 17th–18th centuries
|countries = Europe and Latin America
}}
The '''Baroque''' ({{IPAc-en|UK|b|ə|ˈ|r|ɒ|k}}, {{IPAc-en|US|b|ə|ˈ|r|oʊ|k}}; {{IPA-fr|baʁɔk|lang}}) is a [[Style (visual arts)|style]] of [[Baroque architecture|architecture]], [[Baroque music|music]], [[Baroque dance|dance]], [[Baroque painting|painting]], [[Baroque sculpture|sculpture]] and other arts that flourished in Europe from the early 17th century until the 1740s. In the territories of the Spanish and Portuguese empires including the Iberian Peninsula it continued, together with new styles, until the first decade of the 1800s.  It followed [[Renaissance art]] and [[Mannerism]] and preceded the [[Rococo]] (in the past often referred to as &quot;late Baroque&quot;) and [[Neoclassicism|Neoclassical]] styles. It was encouraged by the [[Catholic Church]] as a means to counter the simplicity and austerity of [[Protestant]] architecture, art and music, though [[Lutheran art#Baroque period|Lutheran Baroque art]] developed in parts of Europe as well.&lt;ref name=&quot;Heal2011&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Heal|first=Bridget|date=1 December 2011|title=‘Better Papist than Calvinist’: Art and Identity in Later Lutheran Germany|journal=German History|publisher=German History Society|volume=29|issue=4|language=English}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The Baroque style used contrast, movement, exuberant detail, deep colour, grandeur and surprise to achieve a sense of awe. The style began at the start of the 17th century in Rome, then spread rapidly to France, northern Italy, Spain and Portugal, then to Austria, southern Germany and Russia. By the 1730s, it had evolved into an even more flamboyant style, called ''[[rocaille]]'' or ''[[Rococo]]'', which appeared in France and Central Europe until the mid to late 18th century.

==Origin of the word==
The English word ''baroque'' comes directly from the French. While some scholars have claimed that the word was adapted from the Portuguese term ''barroco'', a flawed pearl, pointing to the Latin voice ''verruca'',&lt;ref&gt; https://www.dicionarioetimologico.com.br/barroco/ &lt;/ref&gt; mole or a Pre-Roman suffix ''ǒccu'',&lt;ref&gt; https://www.cnrtl.fr/etymologie/baroque &lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Encyclopedia&quot;&gt;{{cite EB1911|wstitle=Baroque|volume=3|short=x}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Wictionary&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/baroque#Etymology |title=Baroque – Etymolohy |author=Wictionary |accessdate=2019-06-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; new research suggests that the syllogism [[baroco]] is the most likely etymon.&lt;ref&gt;Robert Hudson Vincent, {{Cite web|url=https://read.dukeupress.edu/modern-language-quarterly/article-abstract/80/3/233/139274|title=Baroco: The Logic of English Baroque Poetics|}} [[Modern Language Quarterly]], Volume 80, Issue 3 (September 2019)&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 16th century the Medieval Latin word [[baroco]] moved beyond scholastic logic and began to be used to describe anything that was absurdly complex. The French philosopher [[Michel de Montaigne]] associated the term 'baroco' with &quot;Bizarre and uselessly complicated.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;BAROQUE : Etymologie de BAROQUE&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.cnrtl.fr/etymologie/baroque|title=BAROQUE : Etymologie de BAROQUE|website=www.cnrtl.fr|access-date=2019-01-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; In &quot;Baroco: The Logic of English Baroque Poetics,&quot; Robert Hudson Vincent traces other early modern associations of the word 'baroco' with magic, complexity, confusion, and excess.&lt;ref&gt;Robert Hudson Vincent, {{Cite web|url=https://read.dukeupress.edu/modern-language-quarterly/article-abstract/80/3/233/139274|title=Baroco: The Logic of English Baroque Poetics|}} [[Modern Language Quarterly]], Volume 80, Issue 3 (September 2019)&lt;/ref&gt;

The word 'baroque' was also associated with irregular pearls before the 18th century. The French ''baroque'' and Portuguese ''barroco'' were terms exclusively associated with jewelry. An example from 1531 uses the term to describe pearls in an inventory of [[Charles V of France|Charles V's]] treasures.&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=CMdwCgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PR28&amp;lpg Michael Meere, ''French Renaissance and Baroque Drama: Text, Performance, Theory''], Rowman &amp; Littlefield, 2015, {{ISBN|1611495490}}&lt;/ref&gt; Later, the word appears in a 1694 edition of ''Le Dictionnaire de l'Académie Française,'' which describes ''baroque'' as &quot;only used for pearls that are imperfectly round.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;se dit seulement des perles qui sont d'une rondeur fort imparfaite.&quot; [https://artflsrv03.uchicago.edu/philologic4/publicdicos/navigate/3/1385/ Le Dictionnaire de l'Académie Française (1694)]&lt;/ref&gt; A 1728 Portuguese dictionary similarly describes ''barroco'' as relating to a &quot;coarse and uneven pearl.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://dicionarios.bbm.usp.br/pt-br/dicionario/1/barroca|title=Vocabulario Portuguez &amp; Latino|last=Bluteau|first=Raphael|publisher=|year=1728|isbn=|volume=2|location=|pages=58}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 18th century, the term was also used to describe music, and was not flattering.  In an anonymous satirical review of the première of [[Jean-Philippe Rameau]]'s ''[[Hippolyte et Aricie]]'' in October 1733, which was printed in the ''[[Mercure de France]]'' in May 1734, the critic wrote that the novelty in this opera was &quot;du barocque&quot;, complaining that the music lacked coherent melody, was unsparing with dissonances, constantly changed key and meter, and speedily ran through every compositional device.&lt;ref&gt;Claude V. Palisca, &quot;Baroque&quot;. ''The New Grove Dictionary of Music and Musicians'', second edition, edited by [[Stanley Sadie]] and [[John Tyrrell (professor of music)|John Tyrrell]] (London: Macmillan Publishers, 2001).&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1762,  ''Le Dictionnaire de l'Académie Française'' wrote that the term could be used figuratively to describe something &quot;irregular, bizarre or unequal.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;se dit aussi au figuré, pour irrégulier, bizarre, inégale.&quot; [https://artflsrv03.uchicago.edu/philologic4/publicdicos/navigate/8/3310/ Le Dictionnaire de l'Académie Française (1762)]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Jean-Jacques Rousseau]], who was a musician and composer as well as philosopher,  wrote in 1768 in the ''[[Encyclopédie]]'':  &quot;Baroque music is that in which the harmony is confused, and loaded with modulations and dissonances. The singing is harsh and unnatural, the intonation difficult, and the movement limited. It appears that term comes from the word 'baroco' used by logicians.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;BAROQUE : Etymologie de BAROQUE&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Encyclopedie&quot;&gt;''Encyclopedie''; ''Lettre sur la Musique Francaise'' under the direction of [[Denis Diderot]]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1788, the term was defined by [[Quatremère de Quincy]] in the ''[[Encyclopédie Méthodique]]'' as  &quot;an architectural style that is highly adorned and tormented&quot; .&lt;ref&gt;Quatremère de Quincy, ''Encyclopédie Méthodique'', 'Architecture'', volume 1, cited by , B. Migliorini, ''Manierismo, baròcco, rococò'', Rome, 1962, p. 46&lt;/ref&gt;

The terms &quot;style baroque&quot; and &quot;musique baroque&quot; appeared in ''Le Dictionnaire de l'Académie Française'' in 1835''.''&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://artflsrv03.uchicago.edu/philologic4/publicdicos/navigate/12/4108/?byte=1867064|title=dictionnaires d'autrefois public access collection|website=artflsrv03.uchicago.edu|access-date=2019-01-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; By the mid-19th century, art critics and historians had adopted the term as a way to ridicule post-Renaissance art. This was the sense of the word as used in 1855 by the leading art historian Jacob Burkhardt, who wrote that baroque artists &quot;despised and abused detail&quot; because they lacked &quot;respect for tradition.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Der Cicerone : eine Anleitung zum Genuss der Kunstwerke Italiens|last=Burckhardt |first=Jacob |date=1855|publisher=Schweighauser |page=356|oclc=315796790}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Alternatively, a derivation from the name of the Italian painter [[Federico Barocci]] (1528–1612) has been suggested.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite dictionary |url=https://www.etymonline.com/word/baroque#etymonline_v_5258|title=Baroque |dictionary=Online Etymological Dictionary |access-date=December 31, 2018}}: &quot;But Klein suggests the name may be from Italian painter Federico Barocci (1528–1612), whose work influenced the style.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1888, the art historian [[Heinrich Wölfflin]] published the first serious academic work on the style, ''Renaissance und Barock'', which described the differences between the painting, sculpture, and architecture of the Renaissance and the Baroque.&lt;ref&gt;Hopkins, Owen, ''Les Styles en Architecture'' (2014), p. 70&lt;/ref&gt;

==Architecture: origins and characteristics==
{{Main|Baroque architecture}}
[[File:Triumph of the Name of Jesus.jpg|thumb|right|upright|''Quadratura'' or [[trompe-l'œil]]  ceiling of the Church of the Jesu, Rome, by [[Giovanni Battista Gaulli]] (1669–1683)]]
The Baroque style of architecture was a result of doctrines adopted by the [[Catholic Church]] at the [[Council of Trent]] in 1545–63, in response to the [[Protestant Reformation]]. The first phase of the [[Counter-Reformation]] had imposed a severe, academic style on religious architecture, which had appealed to intellectuals but not the mass of churchgoers.  The Council of Trent decided instead to appeal to a more popular audience, and declared that the arts should communicate religious themes with direct and emotional involvement.&lt;ref&gt;Hughes, J. Quentin (1953). [http://melitensiawth.com/incoming/Index/Melita%20Historica/MH.01(1952-55)/MH.1(1953)2/orig05.pdf The Influence of Italian Mannerism Upon Maltese Architecture]. ''Melitensiawath''. Retrieved 8 July 2016. pp. 104–110.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Helen Gardner, Fred S. Kleiner, and Christin J. Mamiya, ''Gardner's Art Through the Ages'' (Belmont, CA: [[Thomson/Wadsworth]], 2005), p. 516.&lt;/ref&gt; Lutheran Baroque art developed as a confessional marker of identity, in response to the [[Iconoclastic Fury|Great Iconoclasm]] of [[Calvinist]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;2018Heal&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://blog.oup.com/2018/02/reformation-lutheran-baroque/|title=The Reformation and Lutheran Baroque|last=Heal|first=Bridget|date=20 February 2018|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]|language=English|accessdate=1 May 2018|quote=However, the writings of theologians can go only so far towards explaining the evolution of confessional consciousness and the shaping of religious identity. Lutheran attachment to religious images was a result not only of Luther’s own cautious endorsement of their use, but also of the particular religious and political context in which his Reformation unfolded. After the reformer’s death in 1546, the image question was fiercely contested once again. But as Calvinism, with its iconoclastic tendencies, spread, Germany’s Lutherans responded by reaffirming their commitment to the proper use of religious images. In 1615, Berlin’s Lutheran citizens even rioted when their Calvinist rulers removed images from the city’s Cathedral.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Baroque churches were designed with a large central space, where the worshippers could be close to the altar, with a dome or cupola high overhead, allowing light to illuminate the church below. The dome was one of the central symbolic features of Baroque architecture illustrating the union between the heavens and the earth, The inside of the cupola was lavishly decorated with paintings of angels and saints, and with stucco statuettes of angels, giving the impression to those below of looking up at heaven.&lt;ref&gt;Ducher, pg. 102&lt;/ref&gt;
Another feature of Baroque churches are the ''quadratura''; [[trompe-l'œil]] paintings on the ceiling in stucco frames, either real or painted, crowded with paintings of saints and angels and connected by architectural details with the balustrades and consoles. ''Quadratura'' paintings of [[Atlas (architecture)|Atlantes]] below the cornices appear to be supporting the ceiling of the church.  Unlike the painted ceilings of Michelangelo in the Sistine Chapel, which combined different scenes, each with its own perspective,  to be looked at one at a time, the Baroque ceiling paintings were carefully created so the viewer on the floor of the church would see the entire ceiling in correct perspective, as if the figures were real.

The interiors of Baroque churches became more and more ornate in the High Baroque,  and focused around the altar, usually placed under the dome.  The most celebrated baroque decorative works of the High Baroque are the [[Chair of Saint Peter]] (1647–53) and the [[St. Peter's Baldachin|Baldachino of St. Peter]] (1623–34), both by [[Gian Lorenzo Bernini]], in [[St. Peter's Basilica]] in Rome. The Baldequin of St. Peter is an example of the balance of opposites in Baroque art; the gigantic proportions of the piece, with the apparent lightness of the canopy; and the contrast between the solid twisted columns, bronze, gold and marble of the piece with the flowing draperies of the angels on the canopy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ducher pages 106-107&quot;&gt;Ducher (1988) p. 106-107&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Dresden Frauenkirche]] serves as a prominent example of Lutheran Baroque art, which was completed in 1743 after being commissioned by the Lutheran city council of Dresden and was &quot;compared by eighteenth-century observers to St Peter’s in Rome&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Heal2011&quot;/&gt;

The twisted column in the interior of churches is one of the signature features of the Baroque. It gives both a sense of motion and also a dramatic new way of reflecting light.
The [[cartouche (design)|cartouche]] was another characteristic feature of Baroque decoration.  These were large plaques carved of marble or stone, usually oval and with a rounded surface, which carried images or text in gilded letters, and were placed as interior decoration or above the doorways of buildings, delivering messages to those below. They showed a wide variety of invention, and were found in all types of buildings, from cathedrals and palaces to small chapels.&lt;ref&gt;Ducher (1988), pg. 102&lt;/ref&gt;

Baroque architects sometimes used forced perspective to create illusions.  For the [[Palazzo Spada]] in Rome, Borromini used columns of diminishing size, a narrowing floor and a miniature statue in the garden beyond to create the illusion that a passageway was thirty meters long, when it was actually only seven meters long. A statue at the end of the passage appears to be life-size, though it is only sixty centimeters high. Borromini designed the illusion with the assistance of a mathematician.

===Italian Baroque architecture===
[[File:Lazio Roma SIgnazio tango7174.jpg|thumb|left|upright|[[Sant'Ignazio Church, Rome|Saint Ignatius, Rome]] (1626–1650)]]
The first building in Rome to have a Baroque facade was the [[Church of the Gesù]] in 1584; it was plain by later Baroque standards, but marked a break with the traditional Renaissance facades that preceded it. The interior of this church remained very austere until the high Baroque, when it was lavishly ornamented.

In Rome in 1605, [[Paul V]] became the first of series of [[popes]] who commissioned basilicas and church buildings designed to inspire emotion and awe through a proliferation of forms, and a richness of colours and dramatic effects.&lt;ref&gt;Cabanne (1988) page 12&lt;/ref&gt; Among the most influential monuments of the Early Baroque were the facade of [[St. Peter's Basilica]] (1606–1619), and the new nave and loggia which connected the facade to Michelangelo's dome in the earlier church. The new design created a dramatic contrast between the soaring dome and the disproportionately wide facade, and the contrast on the facade itself between the Doric columns and the great mass of the portico.&lt;ref&gt;Ducher (1988)&lt;/ref&gt;

In the mid to late 17th century the style reached its peak, later termed the High Baroque. Many monumental works were commissioned by Popes [[Urban VIII]] and [[Alexander VII]]. The sculptor and architect [[Gian Lorenzo Bernini]] designed a new quadruple colonnade around St. Peter's Square (1656 to 1667). The three galleries of columns in a giant ellipse balance the oversize dome and give the Church and square a unity and the feeling of a giant theatre.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ducher page 104&quot;&gt;Ducher (1988) p. 104.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Santa Maria della Salute in Venice 001.jpg|thumb|right|[[Santa Maria della Salute]], Venice (1631–1687)]]

Another major innovator of the Italian High Baroque was [[Francesco Borromini]], whose major work was the Church of [[San Carlo alle Quattro Fontane]] or Saint Charles of the Four Fountains (1634–46).  The sense of movement is given not by the decoration, but by the walls themselves, which undulate and by concave and convex elements, including an oval tower and balcony inserted into a concave traverse. The interior was equally revolutionary; the main space of the church was oval, beneath an oval dome.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ducher page 104&quot;/&gt;

Painted ceilings, crowded with angels and saints and [[trompe-l'œil]] architectural effects, were an important feature of the Italian High Baroque. Major works included ''The Entry of Saint Ignace into Paradise'' by [[Andrea Pozzo]] (1685–1695) in the [[Sant'Ignazio Church, Rome|Church of Saint Ignatius]] in Rome, and ''The triumph of the name of Jesus'' by [[Giovanni Battista Gaulli]] in the [[Church of the Gesù]] in Rome (1669–1683), which featured figures spilling out of the picture frame and dramatic oblique lighting and light-dark contrasts.&lt;ref&gt;Cabanne (1988) page 15&lt;/ref&gt;
The style spread quickly from Rome to other regions of Italy:  It appeared in Venice in the church of [[Santa Maria della Salute]] (1631–1687) by [[Baldassare Longhena]], a highly original octagonal form crowned with an enormous cupola.  It appeared also in Turin, notably in the [[Chapel of the Holy Shroud]]  (1668–1694) by [[Guarino Guarini]]. The style also began to be used in palaces;  Guarini designed the [[Palazzo Carignano]] in Turin, while Longhena designed the [[Ca' Rezzonico]] on the [[Grand Canal (Venice)|Grand Canal]], (1657), finished by [[Giorgio Massari]] with decorated with paintings by [[Giovanni Battista Tiepolo]].&lt;ref&gt;Cabanne (1988), pages 18–19.&lt;/ref&gt;  A series of massive earthquakes in [[Sicily]] required the rebuilding of most of them and several were built in the exuberant late Baroque or Rococo style.

===Spanish Baroque architecture===
{{Main|Spanish Baroque architecture}}
[[File:Catedral de Santiago de Compostela agosto 2018 (cropped).jpg|thumb|right|The towers of the Cathedral of [[Santiago de Compostela]] by [[Fernando de Casas Novoa]] (1680 (centre tower) and 1738–1750)]]
The Catholic Church in Spain, and particularly the Jesuits, were the driving force of Spanish Baroque architecture.  The first major work in the style was the San Isidro Chapel in [[Madrid]], begun in 1643 by [[Pedro de la Torre]].  It contrasted an extreme richness of ornament on the exterior with simplicity in the interior, divided into multiple spaces and using effects of light to create a sense of mystery.&lt;ref&gt;Cabanne (1988) page 48-49&lt;/ref&gt;  The Cathedral in [[Santiago de Compostela]] was modernized with a series of Baroque additions beginning at the end of the 17th century, starting with a highly ornate bell tower (1680), then flanked by two even taller and more ornate towers, called the ''Obradorio'', added between 1738 and 1750 by [[Fernando de Casas Novoa]]. Another landmark of the Spanish Baroque is the chapel tower of the [[Palace of San Telmo]] in [[Seville]] by [[Leonardo de Figueroa]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Cabanne pages 48-51&quot;&gt;Cabanne (1988) pgs. 48–51&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Palacio San Telmo facade Seville Spain.jpg|thumb|left|[[Palace of San Telmo]], [[Seville]] (1682)]]

[[Granada]] had only been liberated from the Moors in the 15th century, and had its own distinct variety of Baroque.  The painter, sculptor and architect [[Alonso Cano]] designed the Baroque interior of [[Granada Cathedral]] between 1652 and his death in 1657.  It features dramatic contrasts of the massive white columns and gold decor.

The most ornamental and lavishly decorated architecture of the Spanish Baroque is called [[Churrigueresque]] style, named after the brothers [[Churriguera]], who worked primarily in Salamanca and Madrid. Their works include the buildings on the city's main square, the [[Plaza Mayor, Salamanca|Plaza Mayor of Salamanca]] (1729).&lt;ref name=&quot;Cabanne pages 48-51&quot; /&gt; This highly ornamental Baroque style was very influential in many churches and cathedrals built by the Spanish in the Americas.

Other notable Spanish baroque architects of the late Baroque include [[Pedro de Ribera]], a pupil of Churriguera, who designed the Royal Hospice of San Fernando in Madrid, and [[Narciso Tomé]], who designed the celebrated [[El Transparente]] altarpiece at [[Toledo Cathedral]] (1729–32) which gives the illusion, in certain light, of floating upwards.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cabanne pages 48-51&quot; /&gt;

The architects of the Spanish Baroque had an effect far beyond Spain;  their work was highly influential in the churches built in the Spanish colonies in Latin America and the Philippines. The Church built by the Jesuits for a college in [[Tepotzotlán]], with its ornate Baroque facade and tower, is a good example.&lt;ref&gt;Cabanne (1988) pg. 63&lt;/ref&gt;

===Central Europe and ''Rococo'' (1740s–1770s)===
{{Main|Rococo}}
[[File:Fresco with Trompe l'oeuil - Andrea Pozzo -Jesuit Church Vienna.jpg|thumb|left|upright|''Quadratura''; a painted dome by [[Andrea Pozzo]] for the [[Jesuit Church, Vienna]], giving the illusion of looking upwards at heavenly figures around a nonexistent dome (1703)]]
From 1680 to 1750, many highly ornate cathedrals, abbeys, and pilgrimage churches were built in Central Europe, in Bavaria, Austria, Bohemia and southwestern Poland. Some were in [[Rococo]] style, a distinct, more flamboyant and asymmetric style which emerged from the Baroque, then replaced it in Central Europe in the first half of the 18th century, until it was replaced in turn by classicism.{{sfnp|Ducher|2014|p=92}}

The princes of the multitude of states in that region also chose Baroque or Rococo for their palaces and residences, and often used Italian-trained architects to construct them.&lt;ref&gt;Cabanne (1988), pp. 89–94.&lt;/ref&gt;  Notable architects included Johann Fischer von Erlach, [[Lukas von Hildebrandt]] and [[Dominikus Zimmermann]] in Bavaria, [[Balthasar Neumann]] in [[Brühl (Rhineland)|Bruhl]], and [[Matthäus Daniel Pöppelmann]] in Dresden. In Prussia, [[Frederic II of Prussia]] was inspired the [[Grand Trianon]] of the [[Palace of Versailles]], and used it as the model for his summer residence, [[Sanssouci]], in [[Potsdam]], designed for him by [[Georg Wenzeslaus von Knobelsdorff]] (1745–1747). Another work of Baroque palace architecture is the [[Zwinger (Dresden)|Zwinger]] in [[Dresden]], the former orangerie of the palace of the Dukes of [[Saxony]] in the 18th century.

One of the best examples of a rococo church is the Basilika Vierzehnheiligen, or [[Basilica of the Fourteen Holy Helpers]], a pilgrimage church located near the town of [[Bad Staffelstein]] near Bamberg, in [[Bavaria]], southern Germany. The Basilica was designed by [[Balthasar Neumann]] and was constructed between 1743 and 1772, its plan a series of interlocking circles around a central oval with the altar placed in the exact centre of the church. The interior of this church illustrates the summit of Rococo decoration.&lt;ref&gt;Ducher (1988) pp. 104–105.&lt;/ref&gt;

Another notable example of the style is the Pilgrimage Church of Wies ({{lang-de|Wieskirche}}). It was designed by the brothers [[Johann Baptist Zimmermann|J. B.]] and [[Dominikus Zimmermann]]. It is located in the foothills of the [[Alps]], in the municipality of [[Steingaden]] in the [[Weilheim-Schongau]] district, [[Bavaria]], [[Germany]]. Construction took place between 1745 and 1754, and the interior was decorated with frescoes and with stuccowork in the tradition of the [[Wessobrunner School]]. It is now a UNESCO World Heritage Site.

[[File:Church of Saint Nicholas in Malá Strana 03(js).jpg|thumb|right|upright|[[St. Nicholas Church (Malá Strana)]], Prague, (1704–1755)]]
Another notable example is the [[St. Nicholas Church (Malá Strana)]] in Prague (1704–55), built by [[Christoph Dientzenhofer]] and his son [[Kilian Ignaz Dientzenhofer]]. Decoration covers all of walls of interior of the church. The altar is placed in the nave beneath the central dome, and surrounded by chapels,  Light comes down from the dome above and from the surrounding chapels. The altar is entirely surrounded by arches, columns, curved balustrades and pilasters of coloured stone, which are richly decorated with statuary, creating a deliberate confusion between the real architecture and the decoration.  The architecture is transformed into a theatre of light, colour and movement.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ducher pages 106-107&quot; /&gt;

In Poland, the Italian-inspired [[Baroque in Poland|Polish Baroque]] lasted from the early 17th to the mid-18th century and emphasised richness of detail and colour. The first Baroque building in present-day Poland and probably one of the most recognizable is the [[Saints Peter and Paul Church, Kraków|Church of St. Peter and Paul]] in [[Kraków]], designed by [[Giovanni Battista Trevano]]. [[Sigismund's Column]] in [[Warsaw]], erected in 1644, was the world's first secular Baroque monument built in the form of a column.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://culture.pl/pl/dzielo/kolumna-zygmunta-iii-wazy-w-warszawie|title=Kolumna Zygmunta III Wazy w Warszawie|website=Culture.pl|accessdate=24 June 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; The palatial residence style was exemplified by the [[Wilanów Palace]], constructed between 1677 and 1696.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.anothertravelguide.com/destinations/europe/poland/warsaw/culture/muzeji/wilanow_palace/|title=WILANÓW PALACE|website=www.anothertravelguide.com|accessdate=24 June 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; The most renowned Baroque architect active in Poland was [[Dutch people|Dutchman]] [[Tylman van Gameren]] and his notable works include Warsaw's [[St. Kazimierz Church]] and [[Krasiński Palace]], [[Church of St. Anne, Kraków|St. Anne's in Kraków]] and [[Branicki Palace, Białystok|Branicki Palace]] in [[Bialystok]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.codart.nl/guide/agenda/tylman-z-gameren-architekt-warszawy-polak-z-wyboru-holender-z-pochodzenia/|title=Tylman z Gameren – architekt Warszawy: Polak z wyboru, Holender z pochodzenia -|website=CODART|accessdate=24 June 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the most celebrated work of Polish Baroque is the [[Poznań Fara|Fara Church]] in [[Poznań]], with details by [[Pompeo Ferrari]].

===French Baroque or ''Classicism''===
{{main|French Baroque architecture}}
[[File:Château de Balleroy 25.JPG|thumb|right|[[Chateau de Balleroy]] by [[François Mansart]] (1626–1636)]]
France largely resisted the ornate Baroque style of Italy, Spain, Vienna and the rest of Europe. The French Baroque style (often termed ''Grand Classicism'' or simply ''Classicism''  in France) is closely associated with the works built for [[Louis XIV]] and [[Louis XV]]; it features more geometric order and measure than Baroque, and less elaborate decoration on the facades and in the interiors.  Louis XIV invited the master of Baroque, Bernini, to submit a design for the new wing of the Louvre, but rejected it in favor of a more classical design by [[Claude Perrault]] and [[Louis Le Vau]].&lt;ref&gt;Cabanne (1988) pages 25–32.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Château de Versailles 04 2016 5737.jpg|thumb|left|[[Palace of Versailles]] (begun by [[Louis Le Vau]] in 1661)]]
The principal architects of the style included [[François Mansart]] ([[Chateau de Balleroy]], 1626–1636), [[Pierre Le Muet]] (Church of [[Val-de-Grace]], 1645–1665), [[Louis Le Vau]] ([[Vaux-le-Vicomte]], 1657–1661) and especially [[Jules Hardouin Mansart]] and [[Robert de Cotte]], whose work included the [[Galerie des Glaces]] and the [[Grand Trianon]] at Versailles (1687–1688). Mansart was also responsible for the Baroque classicism of the [[Place Vendôme]] (1686–1699).&lt;ref&gt;Cabanne (1988), pgs. 25–28.&lt;/ref&gt;

The major royal project of the period was the expansion of [[Palace of Versailles]], begun in 1661 by Le Vau with decoration by the painter [[Charles Le Brun]]. The gardens were designed by [[André Le Nôtre]] specifically to complement and amplify the architecture. The Galerie des Glaces (Hall of Mirrors), the centerpiece of the château, with paintings by Le Brun, was constructed between 1678 and 1686. Mansart completed the Grand Trianon in 1687. The chapel, designed by de Cotte, was finished in 1710. Following the death of Louis XIV, Louis XV added the more intimate [[Petit Trianon]] and the highly ornate theatre. The fountains in the gardens were designed to be seen from the interior, and to add to the dramatic effect. The palace was admired and copied by other monarchs of Europe, particularly [[Peter the Great]] of Russia, who visited Versailles early in the reign of Louis XV, and built his own version at [[Peterhof Palace]] near Saint Petersburg, between 1705 and 1725.&lt;ref&gt;Cabanne (1988), pgs. 28–33.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Portuguese Baroque===
[[File:Neptune's glory (29838154532).jpg|thumb|left|Neptune's glory, [[Palace of Queluz]], 1747]]
[[File:Tibaes Church Interior.JPG|thumb|Interior of [[Monastery of São Martinho de Tibães]], [[Braga]], 1757]]
[[File:Torre de los Clérigos, Oporto, Portugal, 2012-05-09, DD 01.JPG|thumb|right|[[Clérigos Church]], Porto 1732-1750]]

Baroque architecture in Portugal lasted about two centuries (the late seventeenth century and eighteenth century). 
The reigns of [[John V of Portugal|John V]] and [[Joseph I of Portugal|Joseph I]] had increased imports of gold and diamonds, in a period called Royal Absolutism, which allowed the Portuguese Baroque to flourish.

Baroque architecture in Portugal enjoys a special situation and different timeline from the rest of Europe. 

It is conditioned by several political, artistic and economic factors, that originate several phases, and different kinds of outside influences, resulting in a unique blend,&lt;ref&gt;https://www.nga.gov/research/publications/pdf-library/age-of-the-baroque-in-portugal.html&lt;/ref&gt; often misunderstood by those looking for Italian art, find instead specific forms and character which give it a uniquely Portuguese variety.
Another key factor is the existence of the Jesuitical architecture, also called &quot;plain style&quot; (Estilo Chão or Estilo Plano)&lt;ref&gt; http://www.resumos.net/files/caracterizacaodaarquiteturacha.doc &lt;/ref&gt; which like the name evokes, is plainer and appears somewhat austere.

The buildings are single-room basilicas, deep main chapel, lateral chapels (with small doors for communication), without interior and exterior decoration, very simple portal and windows. 
It is a very practical building, allowing it to be built throughout the empire with minor adjustments, and prepared to be decorated later or when economic resources are available. 

In fact, the first Portuguese Baroque does not lack in building because &quot;plain style&quot;” is easy to be transformed, by means of decoration (painting, tiling, etc.), turning empty areas into pompous, elaborate baroque scenarios. The same could be applied to the exterior. 
Subsequently, it is easy to adapt the building to the taste of the time and place and add on new features and details. Practical and economical.

With more inhabitants and better economic resources, the north, particularly the areas of Porto and [[Braga]],&lt;ref&gt;https://www.jstor.org/stable/987760?seq=1&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt; https://tastebraga.com/um-roteiro-pelo-barroco-bracarense/ &lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt; https://culturanorte.gov.pt/pt/noticias/apresentacao-do-livro-itinerarios-barrocos/ &lt;/ref&gt;witnessed an architectural renewal, visible in the large list of churches, convents and palaces built by the aristocracy.

[[Porto]] is the city of Baroque in Portugal. Its historical centre is part of [[UNESCO]] [[World Heritage List]].&lt;ref&gt; https://whc.unesco.org/en/list/755/ &lt;/ref&gt;

Many of the Baroque works in the historical area of the city and beyond, belong to [[Nicolau Nasoni]] an Italian architect living in Portugal, drawing original buildings with scenographic emplacement such as the [[Clérigos Church|church and tower of Clérigos]],&lt;ref&gt; http://www.torredosclerigos.pt/en/history-and-architecture/architecture-and-baroque/ &lt;/ref&gt; the logia of the [[Porto Cathedral]], the church of Misericórdia, the [[Palácio de São João Novo|Palace of São João Novo]],&lt;ref&gt; https://www.upt.pt/page.php?p=654 &lt;/ref&gt; the [[Palácio do Freixo|Palace of Freixo]],&lt;ref&gt; http://www.patrimoniocultural.gov.pt/pt/patrimonio/patrimonio-imovel/pesquisa-do-patrimonio/classificado-ou-em-vias-de-classificacao/geral/view/70403/ &lt;/ref&gt; the [[Episcopal Palace of Porto|Episcopal Palace]] ([[Portuguese language|Portuguese]]: ''Paço Episcopal do Porto'')&lt;ref&gt; http://www.patrimoniocultural.gov.pt/en/patrimonio/patrimonio-imovel/pesquisa-do-patrimonio/classificado-ou-em-vias-de-classificacao/geral/view/70404 &lt;/ref&gt; along with many others.

===Russian Baroque===
{{Main|Naryshkin Baroque|Petrine Baroque|Elizabethan Baroque|Siberian Baroque}}
[[File:Catherine Palace in Tsarskoe Selo 02.jpg|thumb|left|upright=1.0|The [[Catherine Palace]] (1752–1756) by [[Francesco Bartolomeo Rastrelli|Bartolomeo Rastrelli]]]]
The debut of Russian Baroque, or [[Petrine Baroque]], followed a long visit of [[Peter the Great]] to western Europe in 1697–98, where he visited the Chateaux of Fontainebleu and the Versailles as well as other architectural monuments. He decided, on his return to Russia, to construct similar monuments in [[St. Petersburg]], which became the new capital of Russia in 1712. Early major monuments in the Petrine Baroque include the [[Peter and Paul Cathedral]] and [[Menshikov Palace]].

During the reign of [[Empress Anna]] and [[Elizaveta Petrovna]], Russian architecture was dominated by the luxurious Baroque style of Italian-born [[Francesco Bartolomeo Rastrelli|Bartolomeo Rastrelli]], which developed into [[Elizabethan Baroque]]. Rastrelli's signature buildings include the [[Winter Palace]], the [[Catherine Palace]] and the [[Smolny Cathedral]]. Other distinctive monuments of the Elizabethan Baroque are the bell tower of the [[Troitse-Sergiyeva Lavra]] and the [[Red Gate]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=William Craft Brumfield|title=A History of Russian Architecture|place=Cambridge|publisher=Cambridge University Press|year=1993|ISBN=978-0-521-40333-7|chapter=Chapter Eight: The Foundations of the Baroque in Saint Petersburg|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/historyofrussian0000brum}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

In [[Moscow]], [[Naryshkin Baroque]] became widespread, especially in the architecture of [[Eastern Orthodox]] churches in the late 17th century. It was a combination of western European Baroque with traditional [[Russian architecture|Russian]] folk styles.

===Baroque in the Spanish and Portuguese Colonial Americas===
{{main|Mexican art#Mexican Baroque|Baroque in Brazil|Andean Baroque|Churrigueresque|Spanish missions in the Americas}}
Due to the colonization of the Americas by European countries, the Baroque naturally moved to the [[New World]], finding especially favorable ground in the regions dominated by Spain and Portugal, both countries being centralized and irreducibly Catholic monarchies, by extension subject to Rome and adherents of the Baroque [[Counter-Reformation|Counter-reformist]] most typical. European artists migrated to America and made school, and along with the widespread penetration of [[Christian mission|Catholic missionaries]], many of whom were skilled artists, created a multiform Baroque often influenced by popular taste. The [[Criollo (people)|Criollo]] and [[Indigenous peoples of the Americas|Indidenous]] craftsmen did much to give this Baroque unique features. The main centres of American Baroque cultivation, that are still standing, are (in this order) [[Mexico]], [[Brazil]], [[Peru]], [[Ecuador]], [[Cuba]], [[Colombia]], [[Bolivia]], [[Guatemala]] and [[Puerto Rico]].

Of particular note is the so-called &quot;Missionary Baroque&quot;, developed in the framework of the Spanish reductions in areas extending from Mexico and southwestern portions of current-day United States to as far south as Argentina and Chile, indigenous settlements organized by Spanish Catholic missionaries in order to convert them to the Christian faith and acculturate them in the Western life, forming a hybrid Baroque influenced by Native culture, where flourished [[Criollo (people)|Criollos]] and many Indian artisans and musicians, even literate, some of great ability and talent of their own. Missionaries' accounts often repeat that Western art, especially music, had a hypnotic impact on foresters, and the images of saints were viewed as having great powers. Many Indians were converted, and a new form of devotion was created, of passionate intensity, laden with mysticism, superstition, and theatricality, which delighted in festive masses, sacred concerts, and mysteries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Thomas da Costa Kaufmann|chapter-url=http://books.google.com/books?id=Hzbsz3TOsZAC&amp;pg=PA274#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|chapter=12 / East and West: Jesuit Art and Artists in Central Europe, and Central European Art in the Americas|title=The Jesuits: Cultures, Sciences, and the Arts, 1540–1773, Volume 1|editor=John W. O'Malley|editor2=Gauvin Alexander Bailey|editor3=Steven J. Harris|editor4=T. Frank Kennedy|publisher=University of Toronto Press|year=1999|pp=274–304}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Gauvin Alexander Bailey|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=6-sWGjwVmEQC&amp;pg=PA1&amp;dq=missions+jesuits&amp;lr=&amp;as_drrb_is=q&amp;as_minm_is=0&amp;as_miny_is=&amp;as_maxm_is=0&amp;as_maxy_is=&amp;as_brr=3&amp;hl=pt-BR#v=onepage&amp;q=missions%20jesuits&amp;f=false|title=Art on the Jesuit Missions in Asia and Latin America, 1542–1773|publisher=University of Toronto Press|year=1999|pp=4–10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Colonial Baroque architecture in the Spanish America is characterized by a profuse decoration (portal of [[Church of San Felipe Neri &quot;La Profesa&quot;|La Profesa Church]], [[Mexico City]]; facades covered with [[Talavera pottery|Puebla-style]] [[azulejo]]s, as in the [[Church of San Francisco Acatepec]] in [[San Andrés Cholula]] and [[Convent Church of San Francisco, Puebla|Convent Church of San Francisco]] of [[Puebla (city)|Puebla]]), which will be exacerbated in the so-called [[Churrigueresque|Churrigueresque style]] (Facade of the Tabernacle of the [[Mexico City Metropolitan Cathedral|Mexico City Cathedral]], by [[Lorenzo Rodríguez]]; [[Church of San Francisco Javier, Tepotzotlán|Church of San Francisco Javier]], [[Tepotzotlán]]; [[Church of Santa Prisca de Taxco|Church of Santa Prisca]] of [[Taxco]]). In [[Peru]], the constructions mostly developed in the cities of [[Lima]], [[Cusco]], [[Arequipa]] and [[Trujillo, Peru|Trujillo]] since 1650 show original characteristics that are advanced even to the European Baroque, as in the use of [[Wall padding|cushioned walls]] and [[solomonic column]]s ([[Iglesia de la Compañía de Jesús, Cusco|Church of la Compañía de Jesús]], [[Cusco]]; [[Basilica and Convent of San Francisco, Lima|Basilica and Convent of San Francisco]], [[Lima]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.iberlibro.com/Historia-Arte-Cou-Jos%C3%A9-Maria-Azcarate/30142498322/bd|author1=José Maria Azcarate Ristori|author2=Alfonso Emilio Perez Sanchez|author3=Juan Antonio Ramirez Dominguez|title=Historia Del Arte|year=1983}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other countries include: the [[Metropolitan Cathedral of Sucre]] in [[Bolivia]]; [[Cathedral Basilica of Esquipulas]] in [[Guatemala]]; [[Tegucigalpa Cathedral]] in [[Honduras]]; [[León Cathedral, Nicaragua|León Cathedral]] in [[Nicaragua]]; the [[Church of la Compañía de Jesús, Quito|Church of la Compañía de Jesús]] in [[Quito]], [[Ecuador]]; the [[Church of San Ignacio, Bogotá|Church of San Ignacio]] in [[Bogotá]], [[Colombia]]; the [[Caracas Cathedral]] in [[Venezuela]]; the [[Cabildo of Buenos Aires]] in [[Argentina]]; the [[Santo Domingo Church, Santiago de Chile|Church of Santo Domingo]] in [[Santiago]], [[Chile]]; and [[Havana Cathedral]] in [[Cuba]]. It is also worth remembering the quality of the churches of the [[Jesuit Missions of Chiquitos|Spanish Jesuit Missions in Bolivia]], [[Jesuit Missions of La Santísima Trinidad de Paraná and Jesús de Tavarangue|Spanish Jesuit missions in Paraguay]], the [[Spanish missions in Mexico]] and the [[Spanish missions in California|Spanish Franciscan missions in California]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://www.iberlibro.com/DICCIONARIO-ENCICLOPEDICO-LAROUSSE-12-TOMOS-VV.AA/1337306759/bd|title=DICCIONARIO ENCICLOPEDICO LAROUSSE. 12 TOMOS.|author=Larousse|publisher=Editorial Planeta|year=1990|location=Barcelona}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Brazil]], as in the metropolis, [[Portugal]], the architecture has a certain [[Italian Baroque architecture|Italian influence]], usually of a [[Francesco Borromini|Borrominesque]] type, as can be seen in the [[Co-Cathedral of Recife]] (1784) and [[Church of Nossa Senhora da Glória do Outeiro]] in [[Rio de Janeiro]] (1739). In the region of [[Minas Gerais]], highlighted the work of [[Aleijadinho]], author of a group of churches that stand out for their curved planimetry, facades with concave-convex dynamic effects and a plastic treatment of all architectural elements ([[Church of São Francisco de Assis, Ouro Preto|Church of São Francisco de Assis]] in [[Ouro Preto]], 1765–1788).

===Baroque in the Spanish and Portuguese Colonial Asia===
{{see also|Earthquake Baroque}}
In the Portuguese colonies of [[India]] ([[Goa]], [[Daman and Diu]]) an architectural style of Baroque forms mixed with Hindu elements flourished, such as the [[Se Cathedral|Goa Cathedral]] and the [[Basilica of Bom Jesus]] of Goa, which houses the tomb of [[Francis Xavier|St. Francis Xavier]]. The set of [[churches and convents of Goa]] was declared a [[World Heritage Site]] in 1986.

In the [[Philippines]], that was part of the Spanish Empire for a long time, a large number of Baroque constructions are preserved, including the [[Baroque Churches of the Philippines]] that four of these, and the Baroque and Neoclassical city of [[Vigan]], are both [[UNESCO]] [[World Heritage Site]]s. It was also very remarkable the [[Intramuros|Walled City of Manila]] (Intramuros). Other city with notable preserved Spanish-era Baroque is [[Tayabas]].

==Painting==
{{Main|Baroque painting}}
[[File:Peter Paul Rubens - De kruisoprichting.JPG|thumb|right|upright|''The Raising of the Cross'' by [[Peter Paul Rubens]] (1610–1611)]]
Baroque painters worked deliberately to set themselves apart from the painters of the Renaissance and the Mannerism period after it. In their palette, they used intense and warm colours, and particularly made use of the [[primary colors|primary colours]] red, blue and yellow, frequently putting all three in close proximity.&lt;ref&gt;Prater and Bauer,  ''La Peinture du baroque'' (1997), pg. 11&lt;/ref&gt; They avoided the even lighting of Renaissance painting and used strong contrasts of light and darkness on certain parts of the picture to direct attention to the central actions or figures. In their composition, they avoided the tranquil scenes of Renaissance paintings, and chose the moments of the greatest movement and drama.  Unlike the tranquil faces of Renaissance paintings, the faces in Baroque paintings clearly expressed their emotions. They often used asymmetry, with action occurring away from the centre of the picture, and created axes that were neither vertical nor horizontal, but slanting to the left or right, giving a sense of instability and movement. They enhanced this impression of movement by having the costumes of the personages blown by the wind, or moved by their own gestures. The overall impressions were movement, emotion and drama.&lt;ref&gt;Prater and Bauer,  ''La Peinture du baroque'' (1997), pgs. 3–15&lt;/ref&gt; Another essential element of baroque painting was allegory; every painting told a story and had a message, often encrypted in symbols and allegorical characters, which an educated viewer was expected to know and read.&lt;ref&gt;Prater and Bauer,  ''La Peinture du baroque'' (1997), pg. 12&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Las Meninas, by Diego Velázquez, from Prado in Google Earth.jpg|thumb|left|upright|''Las Meninas'' (1656) by [[Diego Velázquez]]]]

Early evidence of Italian Baroque ideas in painting occurred in Bologna, where [[Annibale Carracci]], [[Agostino Carracci]] and [[Ludovico Carracci]] sought to return the visual arts to the ordered Classicism of the Renaissance. Their art, however, also incorporated ideas central the Counter-Reformation; these included intense emotion and religious imagery that appealed more to the heart than to the intellect.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Elements of the Baroque Style.&quot; In ''Arts and Humanities Through the Eras'', edited by Edward I. Bleiberg, James Allan Evans, Kristen Mossler Figg, Philip M. Soergel, and John Block Friedman, 466–470. Vol. 5, The Age of the Baroque and Enlightenment 1600–1800. Detroit, MI: Gale, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;

Another influential painter of the Baroque era was [[Michelangelo Merisi da Caravaggio]]. His realistic approach to the human figure, painted directly from life and dramatically spotlit against a dark background, shocked his contemporaries and opened a new chapter in the history of painting. Other major painters associated closely with the Baroque style include [[Artemisia Gentileschi]], [[Guido Reni]], [[Domenichino]], [[Andrea Pozzo]], and [[Paolo de Matteis]] in Italy; [[Francisco de Zurbarán]] and [[Diego Velázquez]] in Spain; [[Adam Elsheimer]] in Germany; and [[Nicolas Poussin]] and [[Georges de La Tour]] in France (though Poussin spent most of his working life in Italy).  Poussin and La Tour adopted a &quot;classical&quot; Baroque style with less focus on emotion and greater attention to the line of the figures in the painting than to colour.

[[File:The Toilet of Venus, by François Boucher.jpg|thumb|right|upright|''The Toilet of Venus'' by [[François Boucher]] (1755)]]

[[Peter Paul Rubens]] was the most important painter of the [[Flemish Baroque painting|Flemish Baroque]] style.  Rubens' highly charged compositions reference erudite aspects of classical and Christian history. His unique and immensely popular Baroque style emphasised movement, colour, and sensuality, which followed the immediate, dramatic artistic style promoted in the [[Counter-Reformation]]. Rubens specialized in making altarpieces, portraits, landscapes, and [[history painting]]s of mythological and allegorical subjects.

One important domain of Baroque painting was ''Quadratura'', or paintings in ''[[trompe-l'oeil]]'', which literally &quot;fooled the eye&quot;.  These were usually painted on the stucco of ceilings or upper walls and balustrades, and gave the impression to those on the ground looking up were that they were seeing the heavens populated with crowds of angels, saints and other heavenly figures, set against painted skies and imaginary architecture.{{sfnp|Ducher|2014|p=92}}

In Italy, artists often collaborated with architects on interior decoration; [[Pietro da Cortona]] was one of the painters of the 17th century who employed this illusionist way of painting. Among his most important commissions were the frescoes he painted for the [[Palazzo Barberini|Palace of the Barberini family]] (1633–39), to glorify the reign of [[Pope Urban VIII]].  Pietro da Cortona's compositions were the largest decorative frescoes executed in Rome since the work of Michelangelo at the [[Sistine Chapel]]. .&lt;ref&gt;Ducher (1988) pages 108–109&lt;/ref&gt;

[[François Boucher]] was an important figure in the more delicate French Rococo style, which appeared during the late Baroque period.  He designed tapestries, carpets and theatre decoration as well as painting.  His work was extremely popular with [[Madame Pompadour]], the Mistress of King [[Louis XV]]. His paintings featured mythological romantic, and mildly erotic themes.&lt;ref&gt;Cabanne (1988) pp. 102–104&lt;/ref&gt;

===Colonial Americas===
In the Spanish Americas, the first influences were from [[Seville|Sevillan]] [[Tenebrism]], mainly from [[Francisco de Zurbarán|Zurbarán]] —some of whose works are still preserved in [[Mexico]] and [[Peru]]— as can be seen in the work of the Mexicans [[José Juárez]] and [[Sebastián López de Arteaga]], and the Bolivian [[Melchor Pérez de Holguín]]. The [[Cusco School|Cusco School of painting]] arose after the arrival of the Italian painter [[Bernardo Bitti]] in 1583, who introduced [[Mannerism]] in the Americas. It highlighted the work of [[Luis de Riaño]], disciple of the Italian [[Angelino Medoro]], author of the murals of the [[Church of San Pedro, Andahuaylillas|Church of San Pedro]] of [[Andahuaylillas]]. It also highlighted the Indian ([[Quechua people|Quechua]]) painters [[Diego Quispe Tito]] and [[Basilio Santa Cruz Pumacallao]], as well as [[Marcos Zapata]], author of the fifty large canvases that cover the high arches of the [[Cusco Cathedral|Cathedral of Cusco]]. In [[Ecuador]], the [[Quito School]] was formed, mainly represented by the [[mestizo]] [[Miguel de Santiago]] and the [[Criollo (people)|criollo]] [[Nicolás Javier de Goríbar]].

In the 18th century sculptural altarpieces began to be replaced by paintings, developing notably the Baroque painting in the Americas. Similarly, the demand for civil works, mainly portraits of the aristocratic classes and the ecclesiastical hierarchy, grew. The main influence was the [[Bartolomé Esteban Murillo|Murillesque]], and in some cases – as in the [[Criollo (people)|criollo]] [[Cristóbal de Villalpando]] – that of [[Juan de Valdés Leal|Valdés Leal]]. The painting of this era has a more sentimental tone, with sweet and softer shapes. It highlight [[Gregorio Vasquez de Arce y Ceballos|Gregorio Vásquez de Arce]] in [[Colombia]], and [[Juan Rodríguez Juárez]] and [[Miguel Cabrera (painter)|Miguel Cabrera]] in [[Mexico]].

==Sculpture==
{{Main|Baroque sculpture}}
[[File:LouisXIV-Bernini.jpg|thumb|right|upright=0.7|Bust of [[Louis XIV]] by Bernini, Versailles (1665)]]
The dominant figure in baroque sculpture was [[Gian Lorenzo Bernini]].  Under the patronage of [[Pope Urban VIII]], he made a remarkable series of monumental statues of saints and figures whose faces and gestures vividly expressed their emotions, as well as portrait busts of exceptional realism, and highly decorative works for the Vatican, including the imposing [[Chair of St. Peter]] beneath the dome in [[St. Peter's Basilica]].  In addition, he designed fountains with monumental groups of sculpture to decorate the major squares of Rome.{{sfnp|Boucher|1998|p=146}}

Baroque sculpture was inspired by ancient Roman statuary, particularly by the famous statue of [[Laocoön]] from the First Century A.D., which was on display in the gallery of the Vatican.  When he visited Paris in 1665, Bernini addressed the students at the Academy of painting and sculpture. He advised the students to work from classical models, rather than from nature.  He told the students, &quot;When I had trouble with my first statue, i consulted the ''Antinous'' like an oracle.&quot;{{sfnp|Boucher|1998|p=16}}

Notable late French baroque sculptors included [[Étienne Maurice Falconet]] and [[Jean Baptiste Pigalle]].  Pigalle was commissioned by [[Frederick the Great]] to make statues for Frederick's own version of Versailles at [[Sanssouci]] in [[Potsdam]], Germany. Falconet also received an important foreign commission, creating the famous statue of [[Peter the Great]] on horseback found in St. Petersburg.

In Spain, the sculptor [[Francisco Salzillo]] worked exclusively on religious themes, using polychromed wood. Some of the finest baroque sculptural craftsmanship was found in the gilded stucco altars of churches of the Spanish colonies of the New World, made by local craftsmen; examples include the Rosary Chapel of the Church of Santo Domingo in Oaxaca, Mexico (1724–31).

==Music and ballet==
{{Main|Baroque music|Baroque dance}}
[[File:Vivaldi.jpg|thumb|left|upright|[[Antonio Vivaldi]], (1678–1741)]]
The term ''Baroque'' is also used to designate the style of music composed during a period that overlaps with that of Baroque art. The first uses of the term 'baroque' for music were criticisms.  In an anonymous, satirical review of the première in October 1733 of Rameau's ''[[Hippolyte et Aricie]],'' printed in the ''Mercure de France'' in May 1734, the critic implied that the novelty in this opera was &quot;du barocque,&quot; complaining that the music lacked coherent melody, was filled with unremitting dissonances, constantly changed key and meter, and speedily ran through every compositional device.{{sfn|Palisca|2001}} [[Jean-Jacques Rousseau]], who was a musician and noted composer as well as philosopher, made a very similar observation in 1768 in the famous ''Encylopedié'' of [[Denis Diderot]]:   &quot;Baroque music is that in which the harmony is confused, and loaded with modulations and dissonances. The singing is harsh and unnatural, the intonation difficult, and the movement limited. It appears that term comes from the word 'baroco' used by logicians.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Encyclopedie&quot;/&gt;

Common use of the term for the music of the period began only in 1919, by [[Curt Sachs]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Sachs |first1=Curt |authorlink1=Curt Sachs |title=Barockmusik |trans-title=Baroque Music |series=Jahrbuch der Musikbibliothek Peters |volume=26 |year=1919 |publisher=Edition Peters |location=Leipzig |language=German|pages=7–15 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and it was not until 1940 that it was first used in English in an article published by [[Manfred Bukofzer]].{{sfn|Palisca|2001}}

[[File:Ballet de la nuit 1653.jpg|thumb|right|upright|Louis XIV in costume for the ''Ballet Royal de la Nuit'' (1653)]]

The baroque was a period of musical experimentation and innovation. New forms were invented, including the [[concerto]] and [[sinfonia]]. [[Opera]] was born in Italy at the end of the 16th century (with [[Jacopo Peri]]'s mostly lost ''[[Dafne]]'', produced in [[Florence]] in 1598) and soon spread through the rest of Europe:   Louis XIV created the first Royal Academy of Music,  In 1669, the poet [[Pierre Perrin]] opened an academy of opera in Paris, the first opera theatre in France open to the public, and premiered ''[[Pomone (opera)|Pomone]]'', the first grand opera in French, with music by [[Robert Cambert]], with five acts, elaborate stage machinery, and a ballet.{{sfnp|Bély|2005|pp=152–54}} [[Heinrich Schütz]] in Germany, [[Jean-Baptiste Lully]] in France, and [[Henry Purcell]] in England all helped to establish their national traditions in the 17th century.

The classical ballet also originated in the Baroque era. The style of court dance was brought to France by [[Marie de Medici]], and in the beginning the members of the court themselves were the dancers. [[Louis XIV]] himself performed in public in several ballets. In March 1662, the [[Académie Royale de Danse]], was founded by the King.  It was the first professional dance school and company,  and set the standards and vocabulary for ballet throughout Europe during the period.{{sfnp|Bély|2005|pp=152–54}}

Several new instruments, including the [[piano]], were introduced during this period. The invention of the piano is credited to [[Bartolomeo Cristofori]] (1655–1731) of [[Padua]], Italy, who was employed by [[Ferdinando de' Medici, Grand Prince of Tuscany]], as the Keeper of the Instruments. .&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Erlich|first=Cyril|title=The Piano: A History|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]], USA; Revised edition|year=1990|isbn=0-19-816171-9 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;metmuseum&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.metmuseum.org/toah/hd/cris/hd_cris.htm|title=The Piano: The Pianofortes of Bartolomeo Cristofori (1655–1731)|work=Heilbrunn Timeline of Art History|place=New York|publisher=The Metropolitan Museum of Art|date=October 2003|last=Powers|first=Wendy|accessdate=2014-01-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cristofori named the instrument ''un cimbalo di cipresso di piano e forte'' (&quot;a keyboard of [[cypress]] with soft and loud&quot;), abbreviated over time as ''pianoforte'', ''fortepiano'', and later, simply, piano.{{sfnp|Isacoff|2012|p=23}}

===Composers and examples===
* [[Giovanni Gabrieli]] (c. 1554/1557–1612) ''[[Sonata pian' e forte]]'' (1597), ''[[In Ecclesiis]]'' (from ''Symphoniae sacrae'' book 2, 1615)
* [[Giovanni Girolamo Kapsperger]] (c.  1580–1651) ''[[Libro primo di villanelle, 20]]'' (1610)
* [[Claudio Monteverdi]] (1567–1643), ''[[L'Orfeo|L'Orfeo, favola in musica]]'' (1610)
* [[Heinrich Schütz]] (1585–1672), ''[[Musikalische Exequien]]'' (1629, 1647, 1650)
* [[Francesco Cavalli]] (1602–1676), ''[[Egisto (opera)|L'Egisto]]'' (1643), ''[[Ercole amante]]'' (1662), ''[[Scipione affricano]]'' (1664)
* [[Jean-Baptiste Lully]] (1632–1687), ''[[Armide (Lully)|Armide]]'' (1686)
* [[Marc-Antoine Charpentier]] (1643–1704), ''[[Te Deum (Charpentier)|Te Deum]]'' (1688–1698)
* [[Heinrich Ignaz Franz Biber]] (1644–1704), ''[[Mystery Sonatas]]'' (1681)
* [[John Blow]] (1649–1708), ''[[Venus and Adonis (opera)|Venus and Adonis]]'' (1680–1687)
* [[Johann Pachelbel]] (1653–1706), ''[[Pachelbel's Canon|Canon in D]]'' (1680)
* [[Arcangelo Corelli]] (1653–1713), [[Twelve concerti grossi, op.6 (Corelli)|12 concerti grossi, Op. 6]] (1714)
* [[Marin Marais]] (1656–1728), ''[[Sonnerie de Ste-Geneviève du Mont-de-Paris]]'' (1723)
* [[Henry Purcell]] (1659–1695), ''[[Dido and Aeneas]]'' (1688)
* [[Alessandro Scarlatti]] (1660–1725), ''[[L'honestà negli amori]]'' (1680), ''[[Il Pompeo]]'' (1683), ''[[Mitridate Eupatore]]'' (1707)
* [[François Couperin]] (1668–1733), ''[[Les barricades mystérieuses]]'' (1717)
* [[Tomaso Albinoni]] (1671–1751), ''[[Didone abbandonata (Albinoni)|Didone abbandonata]]'' (1724)
* [[Antonio Vivaldi]] (1678–1741), ''[[The Four Seasons (Vivaldi)|The Four Seasons]]'' (1725)
* [[Jan Dismas Zelenka]] (1679–1745), ''[[Il Serpente di Bronzo]]'' (1730), ''[[Missa Sanctissimae Trinitatis]]'' (1736)
* [[Georg Philipp Telemann]] (1681–1767), ''[[Der Tag des Gerichts]]'' (1762)
* [[Johann David Heinichen]] (1683–1729)
* [[Jean-Philippe Rameau]] (1683–1764), ''[[Dardanus (opera)|Dardanus]]'' (1739)
* [[George Frideric Handel]] (1685–1759), ''[[Water Music (Handel)|Water Music]]'' (1717), ''[[Messiah (Handel)|Messiah]]'' (1741)
* [[Domenico Scarlatti]] (1685–1757), [[List of solo keyboard sonatas by Domenico Scarlatti|Sonatas for harpsichord]]
* [[Johann Sebastian Bach]] (1685–1750), [[Toccata and Fugue in D minor, BWV 565|Toccata and Fugue in D minor]] (1703–1707), ''[[Brandenburg Concertos]]'' (1721), ''[[St Matthew Passion]]'' (1727)
* [[Nicola Porpora]] (1686–1768), ''[[Semiramide riconosciuta (Porpora)|Semiramide riconosciuta]]'' (1729)
* [[Giovanni Battista Pergolesi]] (1710–1736), ''[[Stabat Mater]]'' (1736)

==Theatre==
[[File:Set design Act5 of Andromède by P Corneille 1650 - Gallica.jpg|thumb|left|Set design for ''Andromedé'' by [[Pierre Corneille]], (1650)]]

The Baroque period was a golden age for theatre in France and Spain;  playwrights included [[Pierre Corneille|Corneille]], [[Jean Racine|Racine]] and [[Moliere]] in France; and [[Lope de Vega]] and [[Pedro Calderón de la Barca]] Spain.

During the Baroque period, the art and style of the theatre evolved rapidly, alongside the development of opera and of ballet.  The design of newer and larger theatres, the invention the use of more elaborate machinery, the wider use of the [[proscenium arch]], which framed the stage and hid the machinery from the audience, encouraged more scenic effects and spectacle.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|work=Encyclopædia Britannica|title=Baroque theatres and staging|url=https://www.britannica.com/art/theater-building/Baroque-theatres-and-staging|access-date=2019-11-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Baroque had a Catholic and conservative character in Spain, following an Italian literary model during the Renaissance.{{sfnp|González Mas|1980|pp=1–2}} The Hispanic Baroque theatre aimed for a public content with an ideal reality that manifested fundamental three sentiments: Catholic religion, monarchist and national pride and honour originating from the chivalric, knightly world.{{sfnp|González Mas|1980|p=8}}

Two periods are known in the Baroque Spanish theatre, with the division occurring in 1630. The first period is represented chiefly by [[Lope de Vega]], but also by [[Tirso de Molina]], [[Gaspar Aguilar]], [[Guillén de Castro]], [[Antonio Mira de Amescua]], [[Luis Vélez de Guevara]], [[Juan Ruiz de Alarcón]], [[Diego Jiménez de Enciso]], [[Luis Belmonte Bermúdez]], [[Felipe Godínez]], [[Luis Quiñones de Benavente]] or [[Juan Pérez de Montalbán]]. The second period is represented by [[Pedro Calderón de la Barca]] and fellow dramatists [[Antonio Hurtado de Mendoza]], [[Álvaro Cubillo de Aragón]], [[Jerónimo de Cáncer]], [[Francisco de Rojas Zorrilla]], [[Juan de Matos Fragoso]], [[Antonio Coello y Ochoa]], [[Agustín Moreto]], and [[Francisco Bances Candamo]].{{sfnp|González Mas|1980|p=13}} These classifications are loose because each author had his own way and could occasionally adhere himself to the formula established by Lope. It may even be that Lope's &quot;manner&quot; was more liberal and structured than Calderón's.{{sfnp|González Mas|1980|p=91}}

Lope de Vega introduced through his ''Arte nuevo de hacer comedias en este tiempo'' (1609) the ''new comedy''. He established a new dramatic formula that broke the three [[Aristotle]] unities of the Italian school of poetry (action, time and place) and a fourth unity of Aristotle which is about style, mixing of tragic and comic elements showing different types of verses and stanzas upon what is represented.&lt;ref&gt;Lope de Vega, 2010, Comedias: El Remedio en la Desdicha. El Mejor Alcalde El Rey, pp.&amp;nbsp;446–447&lt;/ref&gt; Although Lope has a great knowledge of the plastic arts, he did not use it during the major part of his career nor in theatre or scenography. The Lope's comedy granted a second role to the visual aspects of the theatrical representation.{{sfnp|Amadei-Pulice|1990|p=6}}

Tirso de Molina, Lope de Vega, and Calderón were the most important play writers in Golden Era Spain. Their works, known for their subtle intelligence and profound comprehension of a person's humanity, could be considered a bridge between Lope's primitive comedy and the more elaborate comedy of Calderón. Tirso de Molina is best known for two works, ''The Convicted Suspicions'' and ''[[The Trickster of Seville]]'', one of the first versions of the [[Don Juan]] myth.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson, Edward M.; Moir, Duncan (1992). ''Historia de la literatura española: Siglo De Oro: Teatro'' (1492–1700). Editorial Ariel, pp.&amp;nbsp;155–158&lt;/ref&gt;

Upon his arrival to Madrid, [[Cosimo Lotti]] brought to the Spanish court the most advanced theatrical techniques of Europe. His techniques and mechanic knowledge were applied in palace exhibitions called &quot;Fiestas&quot; and in lavish exhibitions of rivers or artificial fountains called &quot;Naumaquias&quot;. He was in charge of styling the Gardens of [[Buen Retiro]], of [[Palace of Zarzuela|Zarzuela]] and of [[Royal Palace of Aranjuez|Aranjuez]] and the construction of the theatrical building of Coliseo del Buen Retiro.{{sfnp|Amadei-Pulice|1990|pp=26–27}} Lope's formulas begin with a verse that it unbefitting of the palace theatre foundation and the birth of new concepts that begun the careers of some play writers like Calderón de la Barca. Marking the principal innovations of the New Lopesian Comedy, Calderón's style marked many differences, with a great deal of constructive care and attention to his internal structure. Calderón's work is in formal perfection and a very lyric and symbolic language. Liberty, vitality and openness of Lope gave a step to Calderón's intellectual reflection and formal precision. In his comedy it reflected his ideological and doctrine intentions in above the passion and the action, the work of [[Autos sacramentales]] achieved high ranks.&lt;ref&gt;Molina Jiménez,  María Belén (2008). El teatro musical de Calderón de la Barca: Análisis textual. EDITUM, p. 56&lt;/ref&gt; The genre of Comedia is political, multi-artistic and in a sense hybrid. The poetic text interweaved with Medias and resources originating from architecture, music and painting freeing the deception that is in the Lopesian comedy was made up from the lack of scenery and engaging the dialogue of action.{{sfnp|Amadei-Pulice|1990|pp=6–9}}

The best known German playwright was [[Andreas Gryphius]], who used the [[Jesuit]] model of the [[Netherlands|Dutch]] [[Joost van den Vondel]] and [[Pierre Corneille]]. There was also [[Johannes Velten]] who combined the traditions of the English comedians and the [[commedia del'arte]]  with the classic theatre of Corneille and [[Molière]]. His touring company was perhaps the most significant and important of the 17th century.

===Spanish colonial Americas===
Following the evolution marked from Spain, at the end of the 16th century, the companies of comedians, essentially transhumant, began to professionalize. With professionalization came regulation and censorship: as in Europe, the theatre oscillated between tolerance and even government protection and rejection (with exceptions) or persecution by the Church. The theatre was useful to the authorities as an instrument to disseminate the desired behavior and models, respect for the social order and the monarchy, school of religious dogma.&lt;ref name=&quot;MayaRamos&quot;&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.es/books?id=JaQTBUKYfSgC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;hl=es&amp;pg=PA77#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|pp=79–80, 85–86, 133–134, 141|title=América y el teatro español del Siglo de Oro. II Congreso Iberoamericano del Teatro – Tercera ponencia: Actores y compañías de América durante la época virreinal|location=Cádiz|year=1996|publisher=Publications Service of the University of Cádiz|isbn=84-7786-536-1|author1=Maya Ramos Smith|author2=Concepción Reverte Bernal|author3=Mercedes de los Reyes Peña}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''corrales'' were administered for the benefit of hospitals that shared the benefits of the representations. The itinerant companies (or &quot;of the [[League (unit)|league]]&quot;), who carried the theatre in improvised open-air stages by the regions that did not have fixed locals, required a viceregal license to work, whose price or ''pinción'' was destined to alms and works pious.&lt;ref name=&quot;MayaRamos&quot;/&gt; For companies that worked stably in the capitals and major cities, one of their main sources of income was participation in the [[Corpus Christi (feast)|festivities of the Corpus Christi]], which provided them with not only economic benefits, but also recognition and social prestige. The representations in the viceregal palace and the mansions of the aristocracy, where they represented both the comedies of their repertoire and special productions with great lighting effects, scenery and stage, were also an important source of well-paid and prestigious work.&lt;ref name=&quot;MayaRamos&quot;/&gt;

Born in the Viceroyalty of [[New Spain]]&lt;ref&gt;According to the playwright's own statements, he was born in Mexico City in 1580 or 1581. However, a baptismal certificate dated December 30, 1572 has been found in Taxco, belonging to a boy named Juan, son of Pedro Ruiz de Alarcón and Leonor de Mendoza, the poet's parents. Despite Alarcón's statements, most critics consider Taxco his birthplace. See Lola Josa, [http://www.cervantesvirtual.com/obra/juan-ruiz-de-alarcn-y-su-nuevo-arte-de-entender-la-comedia-0/ Juan Ruiz de Alarcón y su nuevo arte de entender la comedia], Madrid, International Association of Hispanists, 2008, pp. 7–14.&lt;/ref&gt; but later settled in Spain, [[Juan Ruiz de Alarcón]] is the most prominent figure in the Baroque theatre of New Spain. Despite his accommodation to [[Lope de Vega]]'s new comedy, his &quot;marked secularism&quot;, his discretion and restraint, and a keen capacity for &quot;psychological penetration&quot; as distinctive features of Alarcón against his Spanish contemporaries have been noted. Noteworthy among his works ''[[La verdad sospechosa]]'', a comedy of characters that reflected his constant moralizing purpose.&lt;ref name=&quot;MayaRamos&quot;/&gt; The dramatic production of [[Juana Inés de la Cruz|Sor Juana Inés de la Cruz]] places her as the second figure of the Spanish-American Baroque theatre. It is worth mentioning among her works the [[Autos sacramentales|auto sacramental]] ''[[El divino Narciso (auto sacramental)|El divino Narciso]]'' and the comedy ''[[Los empeños de una casa]]''.

==Gardens==
{{Main|Baroque garden}}
[[File:Orangerie.jpg|thumb|right|Parterre of the Orangerie, [[Palace of Versailles]] (1684)]]
The [[Baroque garden]], also known as the  ''jardin à la française''  or [[French formal garden]], first appeared in Rome in the 16th century, and then most famously in France in the 17th century in the gardens of [[Vaux le Vicomte]] and the [[Palace of Versailles]]. Baroque gardens were built by Kings and princes in Germany, the Netherlands, Austria, Spain, Poland, Italy and Russia until the mid-18th century, when they began to be remade into by the more natural [[English landscape garden]].

The purpose of the baroque garden was to illustrate the power of man over nature, and the glory of its builder,  Baroque gardens were laid out in geometric patterns, like the rooms of a house. They were usually best seen from the outside and looking down, either from a chateau or terrace. The elements of a baroque garden included [[parterres]] of flower beds or low hedges trimmed into ornate Baroque designs,  and straight lanes and alleys of gravel which divided and crisscrossed the garden.  Terraces, ramps, staircases and cascades were placed where there were differences of elevation, and provided viewing points.  Circular or rectangular ponds or basins of water were the settings for fountains and statues. [[Bosquets]] or carefully-trimmed groves or lines of identical trees, gave the appearance of walls of greenery and were backdrops for statues.  On the edges, the gardens usually had pavilions, orangeries and other structures where visitors could take shelter from the sun or rain.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kluckert 2015 pp. 152-160&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Kluckert|first=Ehrenfried|chapter=Les Jardins Baroques|title=L'Art Baroque – Architecture- Sculpture- Peinture|year=2015|pp=152–160|place=Cologne|publisher=H.F. Ulmann|ISBN=978-3-8480-0856-8}} (French translation from German)&lt;/ref&gt;

Baroque gardens required enormous numbers of gardeners, continual trimming, and abundant water.  In the later part of the Baroque period, the formal elements began to be replaced with more natural features, including winding paths, groves of varied trees left to grow untrimmed;  rustic architecture and picturesque structures, such as Roman temples or Chinese pagodas, as well as &quot;secret gardens&quot; on the edges of the main garden, filled with greenery, where visitors could read or have quiet conversations. By the mid-18th century most of the Baroque gardens were partially or entirely transformed into variations of the [[English landscape garden]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Kluckert 2015 pp. 152-160&quot;/&gt;

Besides Versailles and Vaux-le-Vicomte, Celebrated baroque gardens still retaining much of their original appearance include the [[Royal Palace of Caserta]] near Naples; [[Nymphenburg Palace]] and [[Augustusburg and Falkenlust Palaces, Brühl]] in Germany; [[Het Loo Palace]] in the Netherlands; the [[Belvedere Palace]] in [[Vienna]]; the [[Royal Palace of La Granja de San Ildefonso]] in Spain;  and [[Peterhof Palace]] in St. Petersburg, Russia.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kluckert 2015 pp. 152-160&quot;/&gt;

==Differences between Rococo and Baroque==
The following are characteristics that Rococo has and Baroque has not:{{Clarify|date=December 2019|reason=How can this apply to music or gardens?}}
*The partial abandonment of symmetry, everything being composed of graceful lines and curves, similar to the [[Art Nouveau]] ones 
*The huge quantity of asymmetrical curves and C-shaped [[volute]]s
*The very wide use of flowers in ornamentation, an example being [[festoon]]s made of flowers
*Chinese and Japanese motifs
*Warm pastel colours&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1= Graur|first1=Neaga|title=Stiluri în arta decorativă|date=1970|publisher=Cerces|location=Bucharest|page=160 &amp; 163|url=|language=ro}}&lt;/ref&gt; (whitish-yellow, cream-coloured, pearl greys, very light blues)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1= Graur|first1=Neaga|title=Stiluri în arta decorativă|date=1970|publisher=Cerces|location=Bucharest|page=192|url=|language=ro}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==End of the style, condemnation and academic rediscovery==
Madame de Pompadour, the mistress of Louis XV, contributed to the decline of the baroque and rococo style.  In 1750 she sent her nephew, [[Abel-François Poisson|Abel-François Poisson de Vandières]], on a two-year mission to study artistic and archeological developments in Italy.  He was accompanied by several artists, including the engraver [[Nicolas Cochin]] and the architect [[Soufflot]].  They returned to Paris with a passion for classical art. Vandiéres became the Marquis of Marigny, and was named Royal Director of buildings in 1754. He turned official French architecture toward the neoclassical. Cochin became an important art critic;  he denounced the ''petit style'' of Boucher, and called for a grand style with a new emphasis on antiquity and nobility in the academies of painting of architecture.{{sfnp|Cabanne|1988|p=106}}

The pioneer German art historian and archeologist [[Johann Joachim Winckelmann]] also condemned the baroque style, and praised the superior values of classical art and architecture. By the 19th century, Baroque was a target for ridicule and criticism. The neoclassical critic Francesco Milizia wrote: &quot;Borrominini in architecture, Bernini in sculpture, Pietro da Cortona in painting...are a plague on good taste, which infected a large number of artists.&quot;{{sfnp|Boucher|1998|p=9}} In the 19th century, criticism went even further; the British critic [[John Ruskin]] declared that baroque sculpture was not only bad, but also morally corrupt.{{sfnp|Boucher|1998|p=9}}

The Swiss-born art historian Heinrich Wölfflin (1864–1945) started the rehabilitation of the word Baroque in his Renaissance und Barock (1888); Wölfflin identified the Baroque as &quot;movement imported into mass&quot;, an art antithetic to Renaissance art. He did not make the distinctions between Mannerism and Baroque that modern writers do, and he ignored the later phase, the academic Baroque that lasted into the 18th century. Baroque art and architecture became fashionable between the two World Wars, and has largely remained in critical favor.  The term &quot;Baroque&quot; may still be used, usually pejoratively, describing works of art, craft, or design that are thought to have excessive ornamentation or complexity of line.

==Italian Baroque==
{{gallery cleanup}}
&lt;gallery mode=&quot;packed&quot; heights=&quot;150&quot;&gt;
File:Church of the Gesù, Rome.jpg|Facade of the [[Church of the Gesù]], Rome (1584)
File:Dome of Church of the Gesù (Rome).jpg|Ceiling of the [[Church of the Gesù]], Rome {{nowrap|(1674–1679)}}
File:Ca' Rezzonico (Venice) crooped.jpg|The [[Ca Rezzonico]], Venice {{nowrap|(1649–1656)}}
File:Cortile Spada 01.jpg|[[Cartouche]]s decorating courtyard of the [[Palazzo Spada]] in Rome by [[Borromini]] (1632)
File:Forced perspective gallery by Francesco Borromini.jpg|Gallery with forced perspective by [[Francesco Borromini]], creates the illusion that the corridor is much longer than it really is. [[Palazzo Spada]] (1632)
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Spanish Baroque==
{{gallery cleanup}}
&lt;gallery mode=&quot;packed&quot; heights=&quot;150&quot;&gt;
File:Royal Chapel, Palacio Real, Madrid.jpg|Dome of Royal Chapel, [[Palacio Real]], Madrid (1738–1755)
File:Convento de San Esteban, Salamanca. Retablo mayor.jpg|Retable of Convento de San Esteban, [[Salamanca]] (1690)
File:Transparente of Toledo Cathedral - side view 2.JPG|[[El Transparente]] Altarpiece, [[Toledo Cathedral]], (1729–1732)
File:Madrid May 2014-25a.jpg|Hospice of San Fernando, Madrid (1750)
File:Plaza Mayor, Salamanca.JPG|[[Plaza Mayor, Salamanca]] (1729)
File:Granada Kathedrale innen verkl.jpg|[[Granada Cathedral]] (1652–1657)
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Baroque and Rococo in Central Europe==
{{gallery cleanup}}
&lt;gallery mode=&quot;packed&quot; heights=&quot;150&quot;&gt;
File:Mittelbau Sanssouci.jpg|[[Sanssouci]], in [[Potsdam]] by [[Georg Wenzeslaus von Knobelsdorff]] (1745–1747)
File:Ottobeuren-6289110.jpg|Ceiling of [[Ottobeuren Abbey]] in [[Bavaria]] (1711–1725)
File:Vierzehnheiligen-Basilika3-Asio.JPG|The [[Basilica of the Fourteen Holy Helpers|Vierzehnheigen Basilica]], [[Bavaria]] by [[Balthasar Neumann]] (1743–1772)
File:Dresden-Zwinger-Wallpavillion-gp.jpg|Remnant of [[Zwinger (Dresden)|Zwinger Palace]] in [[Dresden]] (1710–1728)
File:Iglesia colegial de Poznan, Poznan, Polonia, 2014-09-18, DD 19-21 HDR.jpg|[[Poznań Fara|Fara Church]] in [[Poznań]], Poland (1651-1701)
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Style Louis XIV==
{{gallery cleanup}}
&lt;gallery mode=&quot;packed&quot; heights=&quot;150&quot;&gt;
File:Vaux-le-Vicomte2.jpg|[[Vaux-le-Vicomte]] (1657–1661)
File:Louvre-facade-est.jpg|East facade of the [[Louvre Palace|Louvre]] by [[Claude Perrault]] and [[Louis Le Vau]] (1668–1680)
File:Chateau Versailles Galerie des Glaces.jpg|[[Hall of Mirrors]] in Versailles (1678–1686)
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Baroque in the Spanish and Portuguese Colonial Americas==
{{gallery cleanup}}
&lt;gallery mode=&quot;packed&quot; heights=&quot;150&quot;&gt;
File:Catedral de Chihuahua - 2013 - 03.JPG|[[Cathedral of Chihuahua|Chihuahua Cathedral]], [[Mexico]] (1725-1792&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://catedraldechihuahua.blogspot.com/2016/04/var-vvideonew-arrayvvideo1-vvideo2_26.html|title=CATEDRAL, TESTIGO DE LA HISTORIA. LA CONSTRUCCIÓN DE LA NUEVA PARROQUIA, HOY CATEDRAL.|website=catedraldechihuahua.blogspot.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;)
File:Kathedrale Leon 2.JPG|[[León Cathedral, Nicaragua]] (1747-1814), an UNESCO World Heritage Site
File:Basilica Menor de San Francisco de Asis in Havana 2016.jpg|[[Basílica Menor de San Francisco de Asís|Minor Basilica of San Francisco de Asís]], [[Havana]], [[Cuba]] (1548-1738&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lahabana.com/guide/basilica-menor-y-convento-de-san-francisco-de-asis/|title=Historia y arquitectura|website=lahabana.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;)
File:Igreja do Rosário dos Pretos em Ouro Preto.jpg|[[Church of Nossa Senhora do Rosário dos Homens Pretos, Ouro Preto|Church of Rosário dos Pretos]], [[Ouro Preto]], [[Brazil]] (1762-1799&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.hpip.org/pt/heritage/details/734|title=Igreja de Nossa Senhora do Rosário dos Pretos|author=Cláudia Damasceno Fonseca|work=Património de influência portuguesa. [[Calouste Gulbenkian Foundation]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;)
File:Iglesia de San Agustín - Quito.JPG|[[Church of San Agustín, Quito|Church of San Agustín]], [[Quito]], [[Ecuador]] (1606-1617&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.co.ve/books/about/Historia_de_Quito.html?id=kwo7AQAAIAAJ&amp;redir_esc=y|title=Historia de Quito, Luz de América. Bicentenario del 10 de agosto de 1809.|location=Quito|pp=124, 125|author=Jorge Salvador Lara|publisher=Fonsal|year=2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;)
File:Torre Tagle Lima.jpg|[[Palacio de Torre Tagle]], [[Lima]], [[Peru]] (1715-1735&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.afsdp.org.pe/una-vista-al-palacio-de-torre-tagle-casa-de-la-diplomacia-peruana/|title=UNA VISITA AL PALACIO DE TORRE TAGLE, CASA DE LA DIPLOMACIA PERUANA|language=Spanish|author=Asociación de Funcionarios del Servicio Diplomático del Perú}}&lt;/ref&gt;), [[Balconies of Lima]]
File:Iglesia de Santo Domingo, Santiago, 2017-09-24.jpg|[[Santo Domingo Church, Santiago de Chile|Santo Domingo Church]], [[Santiago]], [[Chile]] (1747-1808&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.santiagocapital.cl/fichas/home/iglesia-de-santo-domingo/iglesias/|title=Iglesia de Santo Domingo|website=Ministry of Tourism of Chile website|language=Spanish}}&lt;/ref&gt;)
&lt;/gallery&gt;
&lt;gallery mode=&quot;packed&quot; heights=&quot;159&quot;&gt;
File:Retrato de familia Fagoga Arozqueta - Anónimo ca.1730.jpg|Example of [[Mexican art#Mexican Baroque|Mexican painting]]: ''Portrait of the Fagoga Arozqueta family'' (a [[Criollo people|criollo]] couple with their ten sons), anonymous painter, ca. 1735. [[Museo Nacional de San Carlos]], [[Mexico City]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.esteticas.unam.mx/revista_imagenes/imago/ima_curiel03.html|title=Retrato de la familia Fagoaga-Arozqueta|website=electronic magazine Imágenes of the Institute of Aesthetic Research of the [[National Autonomous University of Mexico]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
File:Los tres mulatos de Esmeraldas (Sánchez Galque).jpg|Example of the [[Quito School]]: ''Three mulattomen from [[Esmeraldas, Ecuador|Esmeraldas]]'' by [[Andrés Sánchez Gallque]], ca. 1599. [[Museum of the Americas (Madrid)|Museum of the Americas, Madrid]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Los mulatos de Esmeraldas (ficha completa)|url=http://ceres.mcu.es/pages/ResultSearch?Museo=MAM&amp;txtSimpleSearch=Los%20mulatos%20de%20Esmeraldas&amp;simpleSearch=0&amp;hipertextSearch=1&amp;search=simple&amp;MuseumsSearch=MAM%7C&amp;MuseumsRolSearch=11&amp;listaMuseos=|publisher=Museum of the Americas|website=Digital Network of Collections of Museums of Spain|language=Spanish|location=Madrid}}&lt;/ref&gt;
File:Angel letiel.jpg|Example of Bolivian painting (from the [[Cusco School]]): [[Ángeles arcabuceros|Arquebusier Angels]] (''Angel Letiel Dei'') by the [[Master of Calamarca]], 17th century. Church of [[Calamarca]], [[Bolivia]]
File:Fresque église huaro.JPG|Preserved wall painting of 1802 depicting the Hell,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.co.ve/books?id=A6nutjzmxvkC&amp;pg=PA382&amp;lpg=PA382&amp;dq=historia+colonial+de+cusco&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=x-Br_buZn0&amp;sig=ACfU3U1iEI-TUEcrPFhZwyN56gwJpuy0Og&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;q=historia%20colonial%20de%20cusco&amp;f=false|pp=106|title=The Colonial Andes: Tapestries and Silverwork, 1530–1830|author1=Elena Phipps|author2=Joanna Hecht|author3=Cristina Esteras Martín|year=2004|publisher=[[Metropolitan Museum of Art]]|location=New York|isbn=030010491X}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.co.ve/books?id=Vpi5xwEACAAJ&amp;dq=SEBASTI%C3%81N+L%C3%93PEZ,+Santiago.+El+barroco+iberoamericano+1990&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwihnvSkxqzmAhWtr1kKHasDD6gQ6AEIKjAA|title=El bárroco iberoamericano. Mensaje iconográfico|year=1990|pp=241|publisher=Ediciones Encuentro|location=Madrid|author=Santiago Sebastián López}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://mavcor.yale.edu/conversations/collections/painting-beyond-frame-religious-murals-colonial-peru|title=Painting Beyond the Frame: Religious Murals of Colonial Peru|author=Ananda Cohen Suarez|publisher=MAVCOR of the [[Yale University]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; by the Peruvian [[mestizo]] painter Tadeo Escalante, inside the Church of San Juan Bautista in [[Huaro District|Huaro]], [[Peru]]. The church's interior is full of wall paintings.
File:São Pedro Papa, séc. XVIII.jpg|Example of Brazilian sculpture: ''[[Pope St. Peter]]'', ca. 18th century. [[Museum of Sacred Art of São Paulo]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ipatrimonio.org/?p=31#!/map=38329&amp;loc=-23.519961863383653,-46.584906578063965,14|title=São Paulo – Acervo do Museu de Arte Sacra de São Paulo|website=Ipatrimônio project. Patrimônio cultural brasileiro}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Arts|Christianity}}
{{colbegin|colwidth=20em}}
* [[List of Baroque architecture]]
* [[Baroque in Brazil]]
* [[Czech Baroque architecture]]
* [[Dutch Baroque architecture]]
* [[Earthquake Baroque]]
* [[English Baroque]]
* [[French Baroque architecture]]
* [[Italian Baroque]]
* [[Sicilian Baroque]]
* [[New Spanish Baroque]]
* [[Mexican art#Mexican Baroque]]
* [[Neoclassicism (music)]]
* [[Andean Baroque]]
* [[Baroque in Poland]]
* [[Baroque architecture in Portugal]]
* [[Naryshkin Baroque]]
* [[Siberian Baroque]]
* [[Spanish Baroque literature]]
* [[Ukrainian Baroque]]
{{colend}}

==Notes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Books cited in text==
{{Refbegin|30em}}
* {{cite book|ref=harv|last=Amadei-Pulice|first=María Alicia|title=Calderón y el barroco: exaltación y engaño de los sentidos|place=Amsterdam; Philadelphia|publisher=John Benjamins Publishing Company|year=1990|series=Purdue University monographs in Romance languages|volume=31|language=Italian|ISBN=978-9-02-721747-9}}
* {{cite book|ref=harv|last=Bély|first=Lucien|title=Louis XIV - Le Plus Grand Roi du Monde|year=2005|language=French|publisher=Editions Jean-Paul Gisserot|ISBN=978-2-87-747772-7}}
* {{cite book|ref=harv|last=Boucher|first=Bruce|title=Italian Baroque Sculpture|year=1998|publisher=Thames &amp; Hudson|series=World of Art|ISBN=0-50-020307-5}}
* {{cite book|ref=harv|last=Cabanne|first=Pierre|title=L'Art Classique et le Baroque|year=1988|language=French|publisher=Larousse|place=Paris|ISBN=978-2-03-583324-2}}
* Causa, Raffaello, ''L'Art au XVIII siècle du rococo à Goya'' (1963), (in French) Hachcette, Paris {{ISBN|2-86535-036-3}}
* {{cite book|ref=harv|last=Ducher|first=Robert|year=1988|title=Caractéristique des Styles|place=Paris|publisher=Flammarion|ISBN=2-08-011539-1}}
* {{cite book|ref=harv|last=Ducher|first=Robert|year=2014|title=La Caractéristique des Styles|place=|publisher=|ISBN=}}
* Gardner, Helen, Fred S. Kleiner, and Christin J. Mamiya. 2005. ''[[Gardner's Art Through the Ages]]'', 12th edition. Belmont, CA: [[Thomson/Wadsworth]]. {{ISBN|978-0-15-505090-7}} (hardcover)
* {{cite book|ref=harv|last=González Mas|first=Ezequiel|year=1980|title=Historia de la literatura española: (Siglo XVII). Barroco'', Volumen 3''|publisher=La Editorial, UPR}}
* {{cite book|ref=harv|title=A Natural History of the Piano: The Instrument, the Music, the Musicians&amp;nbsp;– From Mozart to Modern Jazz and Everything in Between|first=Stuart|last=Isacoff|publisher=Knopf Doubleday Publishing|year=2012}}
* Prater, Andreas, and Bauer, Hermann, ''La Peinture du baroque'' (1997), (in French), Taschen, Paris {{ISBN|3-8228-8365-4}}
* Tazartes, Maurizia, ''Fontaines de Rome'', (2004), (in French) Citadelles, Paris {{ISBN|2-85088-200-3}}
{{Refend}}

==Further reading==
{{Refbegin|30em}}
* Andersen, Liselotte. 1969. ''Baroque and Rococo Art'', New York: H. N. Abrams. {{ISBN|978-0-8109-8027-3}}
* [[Gauvin Alexander Bailey|Bailey, Gauvin Alexander]]. 2012. ''Baroque &amp; Rococo'', London: Phaidon Press. {{ISBN|978-0-7148-5742-8}}
* [[Germain Bazin|Bazin, Germain]], 1964. ''Baroque and Rococo''. Praeger World of Art Series. New York: Praeger. (Originally published in French, as ''Classique, baroque et rococo''. Paris: Larousse. English edition reprinted as ''Baroque and Rococo Art'', New York: Praeger, 1974)
* [[Christine Buci-Glucksmann|Buci-Glucksmann, Christine]]. 1994. ''Baroque Reason: The Aesthetics of Modernity''. Sage.
* Downes, Kerry, [http://www.oxfordartonline.com/subscriber/article/grove/art/T006459 &quot;Baroque&quot;], [[Grove Art Online]], Oxford Art Online, Oxford University Press, Web. 23 Oct. 2017.{{vn|date=November 2019|reason=Is this the publication date or the access date/}} {{subscription required}}
* Hills, Helen (ed.). 2011. ''Rethinking the Baroque''. Farnham, Surrey; Burlington, VT: Ashgate. {{ISBN|978-0-7546-6685-1}}.
* Hortolà, Policarp, 2013, ''The Aesthetics of Haemotaphonomy: Stylistic Parallels between a Science and Literature and the Visual Arts''. [[Sant Vicent del Raspeig]]: ECU. {{ISBN|978-84-9948-991-9}}.
* [[Michael Kitson|Kitson, Michael]]. 1966. ''The Age of Baroque''. Landmarks of the World's Art. London: Hamlyn; New York: McGraw-Hill.
* [[Gregg Lambert|Lambert, Gregg]], 2004. ''Return of the Baroque in Modern Culture''. Continuum. {{ISBN|978-0-8264-6648-8}}.
* [[John Rupert Martin|Martin, John Rupert]]. 1977. ''Baroque''. Icon Editions. New York: Harper and Rowe. {{ISBN|0-06-435332-X}} (cloth); {{ISBN|0-06-430077-3}} (pbk.)
* {{cite book |last1=Palisca |first1=Claude V. |title=Baroque Music |edition=3rd |series=Prentice Hall History of Music |year=1991 |origyear=1961 |publisher=Prentice Hall |location=Englewood Cliffs, N.J. |isbn=0-13-058496-7 |oclc=318382784 }}
* {{cite book |last=Riegl |first=Alois |editor-last=Hopkins |editor-first=Andrew |title=The Origins of Baroque Art in Rome (Texts and Documents)|publisher=Getty Research Institute |date=2010|isbn=978-1-6060-6041-4}}
* {{cite book |author-link=Heinrich Wölfflin|last=Wölfflin|first=Heinrich|year=1964|title=Renaissance and Baroque|orig-year=Originally published in German, 1888|translator-last=Simon|translator-first=Kathrin|ISBN=0-0021-7349-2}} 
* [[Vuillemin, Jean-Claude]], 2013. ''Episteme baroque: le mot et la chose''. Hermann. {{ISBN|978-2-7056-8448-8}}.
* Wakefield, Steve. 2004. ''Carpentier's Baroque Fiction: Returning Medusa's Gaze''. Colección Támesis. Serie A, Monografías 208. Rochester, NY: Tamesis. {{ISBN|1-85566-107-1}}.
{{Refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Baroque art}}
* [http://www.baroquelife.org The baroque and rococo culture]
* [http://www.ibiblio.org/wm/paint/glo/baroque/ Webmuseum Paris]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20180902092035/http://www.sentieridelbarocco.it/ barocke in Val di Noto – Sizilien]
* [http://www.all-art.org/history252_contents_Baroque_Rococo.html Baroque in the &quot;History of Art&quot;]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20070624152123/http://www.antiquestopic.com/the-baroque-style-1620-1700/ The Baroque style and Luis XIV influence]
* [http://www.bbc.co.uk/radio4/history/inourtime/inourtime.shtml Melvyn Bragg's BBC Radio 4 program ''In Our Time'': The Baroque]
* {{cite web
 |publisher=[[Victoria and Albert Museum]]
 |url=http://www.vam.ac.uk/vastatic/microsites/british_galleries/bg_styles/Style03b/index.html
 |title=Baroque Style Guide
 |department=British Galleries
 |accessdate=16 July 2007
 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070819090827/http://www.vam.ac.uk/vastatic/microsites/british_galleries/bg_styles/Style03b/index.html
 |archivedate=19 August 2007
 |url-status=live
 |df=dmy
}}

{{Baroque architecture by country}}
{{History of architecture}}
{{History of Europe}}
{{History of the Catholic Church}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Baroque| ]]
[[Category:17th century in art]]
[[Category:17th century in the arts]]
[[Category:18th century in art]]
[[Category:18th century in the arts]]
[[Category:Art movements]]
[[Category:Art movements in Europe]]
[[Category:Decorative arts]]
[[Category:Early Modern period]]</text>
      <sha1>327uqvj5fh576auyybnv8va7634dsyl</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
