  <page>
    <title>Bagpipes</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3950</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942544128</id>
      <parentid>942544092</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-25T09:31:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Carl Tristan Orense</username>
        <id>33115362</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contribs/RISSEN LUMBO|RISSEN LUMBO]] ([[User talk:RISSEN LUMBO|talk]]) to last version by ClueBot NG</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Musical instrument}}
{{About|the general form of bagpipes|specific types of bagpipe|List of bagpipes}}
{{more citations needed|date = November 2017}}
{{Infobox instrument
|name             = Bagpipes
|names            =
|image            = Hendrick ter Brugghen - Bagpipe Player - Google Art Project.jpg
|image_capt       = ''De doedelzakspeler'' (&quot;Bagpipe Player&quot;), [[Hendrick ter Brugghen]], 1624
|background       = woodwind
|classification   =
*[[Aerophone]]
*Wind
*Woodwind
|hornbostel_sachs = 422.112 
|hornbostel_sachs_desc = [[Reed aerophone]] with conical bore
|developed        = 1000 BC by [[Hittites]]
|range            =
|related          =
*[[Oboe]]
*[[Shawm]]
*[[Bassoon]]
|musicians        =
*[[List of bagpipers]]
|articles         =
}}

'''Bagpipes''' are a [[woodwind instrument]] using enclosed [[reed (music)|reeds]] fed from a constant reservoir of air in the form of a bag. The Scottish [[Great Highland bagpipe]]s are the best known in the [[Anglophone world]]; however, bagpipes have been played for a millennium or more throughout large parts of [[Europe]], [[northern Africa]], and [[western Asia]], including [[Anatolia]], the [[Caucasus]], and around the [[Persian Gulf]]. The term ''bagpipe'' is equally correct in the singular or plural, though pipers usually refer to the bagpipes as &quot;the pipes&quot;, &quot;a set of pipes&quot; or &quot;a stand of pipes&quot;.

== Construction ==
{|align=right
|{{Listen|filename=Skye Boat Song.ogg|title=Skye Boat Song|description=An adaptation of the &quot;[[Skye Boat Song]]&quot; for Great Highland bagpipes played by the Clan Stewart Pipe Band.}}
|}
[[File:Cantiga bagpipes 1.jpg|thumb|right|A detail from the [[Cantigas de Santa Maria]]  showing bagpipes with one chanter and a parallel drone (Spain, 13th century).]]
[[File:Hieronymus Bosch 068.jpg|thumb|right|A detail from a painting by [[Hieronymus Bosch]] showing two bagpipers (15th century).]]
A set of bagpipes minimally consists of an air supply, a bag, a [[chanter]], and usually at least one [[Drone (music)|drone]]. Many bagpipes have more than one drone (and, sometimes, more than one chanter) in various combinations, held in place in stocks—sockets that fasten the various pipes to the bag.

=== Air supply ===
The most common method of supplying air to the bag is through blowing into a blowpipe or blowstick. In some pipes the player must cover the tip of the blowpipe with their tongue while inhaling, but most blowpipes have a [[non-return valve]] that eliminates this need. In recent times, there are many instruments that assist in creating a clean air flow to the pipes and assist the collection of condensation.

An innovation, dating from the 16th or 17th century, is the use of a [[bellows]] to supply air. In these pipes, sometimes called &quot;[[cauld wind pipes (disambiguation)|cauld wind pipes]]&quot;, air is not heated or moistened by the player's breathing, so bellows-driven bagpipes can use more refined or delicate reeds. Such pipes include the Irish [[uilleann pipes]]; the [[border pipes|border or Lowland pipes]], [[Scottish smallpipes]], [[Northumbrian smallpipes]], [[pastoral pipes]] in Britain; and the [[musette de cour]], the [[musette bechonnet]] and the [[cabrette]] in France, the [[Dudy wielkopolskie]], [[koziol bialy]] and [[koziol czarny]] in Poland.

=== Bag ===
The bag is an airtight [[reservoir]] that holds air and regulates its flow via arm pressure, allowing the player to maintain continuous even sound. The player keeps the bag inflated by blowing air into it through a blowpipe or pumping air into it with a bellows. Materials used for bags vary widely, but the most common are the skins of local animals such as goats, dogs, sheep, and cows. More recently, bags made of synthetic materials including [[Gore-Tex]] have become much more common. A drawback of the synthetic bag is the potential for fungal spores to colonise the bag because of a reduction in necessary cleaning, with the associated danger of [[Respiratory tract infection|lung infection]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.scotsman.com/scotland-on-sunday/scotland/bagpipe-warning-over-threat-of-fatal-fungus-1-2828835 |title=Bagpipe warning over threat of fatal fungus – Health |newspaper=The Scotsman |date=2013-03-10 |accessdate=2013-08-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; An advantage of a synthetic bag is that it has a zip which allows the user to fit a more effective moisture trap to the inside of the bag.

Bags cut from larger materials are usually [[saddle stitch|saddle-stitched]] with an extra strip folded over the seam and stitched (for skin bags) or glued (for synthetic bags) to reduce leaks. Holes are then cut to accommodate the stocks. In the case of bags made from largely intact animal skins, the stocks are typically tied into the points where the limbs and the head joined the body of the whole animal, a construction technique common in Central Europe.

=== Chanter ===
{{Main|Chanter}}
The chanter is the [[melody]] pipe, played with two hands. Almost all bagpipes have at least one chanter; some pipes have two chanters, particularly those in North Africa, in the Balkans, and in Southwest Asia. A chanter can be bored internally so that the inside walls are parallel (or &quot;cylindrical&quot;) for its full length, or it can be bored in a conical shape.

The chanter is usually open-ended, so there is no easy way for the player to stop the pipe from sounding. Thus most bagpipes share a constant, [[legato]] sound where there are no rests in the music. Primarily because of this inability to stop playing, technical movements are used to break up notes and to create the illusion of articulation and accents. Because of their importance, these embellishments (or &quot;ornaments&quot;) are often highly technical systems specific to each bagpipe, and take many years of study to master. A few bagpipes (such as the musette de cour, the [[uilleann pipes]], the Northumbrian smallpipes, the [[Piva (bagpipe)|piva]] and the left chanter of the [[surdelina]]) have closed ends or stop the end on the player's leg, so that when the player &quot;closes&quot; (covers all the holes) the chanter becomes silent.

A [[practice chanter]] is a chanter without bag or drones, allowing a player to practice the instrument quietly and with no variables other than playing the chanter.

The term ''chanter'' is derived from the Latin ''cantare'', or &quot;to sing&quot;, much like the modern French word ''[[wikt:chanteur#French|chanteur]]''.

==== Chanter reed ====
The note from the chanter is produced by a [[Reed (instrument)|reed]] installed at its top. The reed may be a [[Single-reed instrument|single]] (a reed with one vibrating tongue) or [[double reed]] (of two pieces that vibrate against each other). Double reeds are used with both conical- and parallel-bored chanters while single reeds are generally (although not exclusively) limited to parallel-bored chanters. In general, double-reed chanters are found in pipes of Western Europe while single-reed chanters appear in most other regions.

=== Drone ===
Most bagpipes have at least one [[drone (music)|drone]]: a pipe which is generally not fingered but rather produces a constant harmonizing note throughout play (usually the tonic note of the chanter). Exceptions are generally those pipes which have a double-chanter instead. A drone is most commonly a cylindrically-bored tube with a single reed, although drones with double reeds exist. The drone is generally designed in two or more parts with a sliding joint so that the pitch of the drone can be adjusted.

Depending on the type of pipes, the drones may lie over the shoulder, across the arm opposite the bag, or may run parallel to the chanter. Some drones have a tuning screw, which effectively alters the length of the drone by opening a hole, allowing the drone to be tuned to two or more distinct pitches. The tuning screw may also shut off the drone altogether. In most types of pipes, where there is one drone it is pitched two octaves below the tonic of the chanter. Additional drones often add the octave below and then a drone consonant with the fifth of the chanter.

== History ==

=== Ancient origins ===
The evidence for pre-Roman era bagpipes is still uncertain but several textual and visual clues have been suggested. The ''Oxford History of Music''  says that a sculpture of bagpipes has been found on a [[Hittites|Hittite]] slab at [[Euyuk]] in Anatolia, dated to 1000 BC. Several authors identify the [[ancient Greek]] ''askaulos'' (ἀσκός ''askos'' &amp;ndash; [[wine-skin]], αὐλός ''[[aulos]]'' &amp;ndash; reed pipe) with the bagpipe.&lt;ref name=&quot;google15&quot;&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=DOfuAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA15 William Flood. &quot;The Story of the Bagpipe&quot; p. 15]&lt;/ref&gt;  In the 2nd century AD, [[Suetonius]] described the Roman emperor [[Nero]] as a player of the ''tibia utricularis''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation
 | title       = ''Life of Nero'', 54
 | url         = http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Suetonius/12Caesars/Nero*.html#54
 | publisher   = [[Loeb Classical Library]]
 | work       = Suetonius, The Lives of the Caesars
 | page        = 185
 | date        =
 | accessdate  = 2013-01-02
}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Dio Chrysostom]] wrote in the 1st century of a contemporary sovereign (possibly Nero) who could play a pipe ([[Tibia (instrument)|tibia]], Roman reedpipes similar to Greek and Etruscan instruments) with his mouth as well as by tucking a bladder beneath his armpit.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation
 | title       = Discourses by Dio Chrysostom (Or.&amp;nbsp;71.9)
 | url         = http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Dio_Chrysostom/Discourses/71*.html#9
 | publisher   = [[Loeb Classical Library]]
 | work       = The Seventy-first Discourse: On the Philosopher (Volume V)
 | volume      = V
 | page        = 173
 | date        =
 | accessdate  = 2013-01-02
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Spread and development in Europe ===
[[File:Santes Creus Bagpiper.JPG|thumb|left|Medieval bagpiper at the [[Cistercian]] monastery of [[Santes Creus]], Catalonia, Spain]]
[[File:The Image of Irelande - plate02.jpg|right|thumb|''Image of Irelande'', Military use of the bagpipe dated 1581]]

In the early part of the second millennium, definite clear attestations of bagpipes began to appear with frequency in Western European art and iconography. The [[Cantigas de Santa Maria]], written in [[Galician-Portuguese]] and compiled in [[Kingdom of Castile|Castile]] in the mid-13th century, depicts several types of bagpipes.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation
 | first       = Elizabeth
 | last        = Aubrey
 | title       = The Music of the Troubadours
 | url         = https://books.google.com/?id=1nqgFob3uV0C&amp;pg=PA257 
 | publisher   = [[Indiana University Press]]
 | series      =
 | id          =
 | isbn        = 978-0-253-21389-1
 | location    =
 | year        = 1996
 | date        =
 | accessdate  = 2013-01-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; Several illustrations of bagpipes also appear in the ''Chronique dite de Baudoin d’Avesnes'', a 13th-century manuscript of northern French origin.&lt;ref&gt;Chronique dite de Baudoin d'Avesnes, Arras, BM, ms. 0863, f. 007, 126v, 149v&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Hybride jouant de la cornemuse | publisher=Sorbonne, Paris | url=http://musiconis.paris-sorbonne.fr/fiche/429/Hybride+jouant+de+la+cornemuse | access-date=2017-01-09 | archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170110030957/http://musiconis.paris-sorbonne.fr/fiche/429/Hybride+jouant+de+la+cornemuse | archive-date=2017-01-10 | url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; Although evidence of bagpipes in the British Isles prior to the 14th century is contested, they are explicitly mentioned in ''[[The Canterbury Tales]]'' (written around 1380):&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation
 | first       = Geoffrey
 | last        = Chaucer
 | title       = The Canterbury Tales: Prologue to &quot;The Miller's Tale&quot; (line 565)
 | url         = http://www.bartleby.com/40/0103.html
 | date        =
 | accessdate  = 2013-01-02
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{quote|A baggepype wel coude he blowe and sowne, /And ther-with-al he broghte us out of towne.|Canterbury Tales}}

Bagpipes were also frequent subjects for carvers of wooden choir stalls in the late 15th and early 16th century throughout Europe, sometimes with animal musicians.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Cochon jouant de la cornemuse | publisher=Sorbonne, Paris | url=http://musiconis.paris-sorbonne.fr/fiche/233/Cochon+jouant+de+la+cornemuse | access-date=2017-01-09 | archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170110023950/http://musiconis.paris-sorbonne.fr/fiche/233/Cochon+jouant+de+la+cornemuse | archive-date=2017-01-10 | url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Actual examples of bagpipes from before the 18th century are extremely rare; however, a substantial number of paintings, carvings, engravings, manuscript illuminations, and so on survive. They make it clear that bagpipes varied hugely throughout Europe, and even within individual regions. Many examples of early folk bagpipes in continental Europe can be found in the paintings of Brueghel, Teniers, Jordaens, and Durer.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|title=The Great Highland Bagpipes (an piob-mhor) |url=http://www.northport-bagpipes.org/bagpipes.htm |publisher=The Northport Pipe Band, NY |accessdate=2013-01-02 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130211205152/http://www.northport-bagpipes.org/bagpipes.htm |archivedate=February 11, 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;[[File:Bagpiper in Edinburgh 001.jpg|thumb|right|A bagpiper [[busking]] with the Great Highland bagpipe on the street in [[Edinburgh, Scotland]]]]
The first clear reference to the use of the Scottish [[Highland bagpipes]] is from a French history, which mentions their use at the [[Battle of Pinkie Cleugh]] in 1547. [[George Buchanan]] (1506–82) claimed that they had replaced the trumpet on the battlefield. This period saw the creation of the ''ceòl mór'' (great music) of the bagpipe, which reflected its martial origins, with battle-tunes, marches, gatherings, salutes and laments.&lt;ref&gt;J. E. A. Dawson, ''Scotland Re-Formed, 1488–1587'' (Edinburgh: Edinburgh University Press, 2007), {{ISBN|0-7486-1455-9}}, p. 169.&lt;/ref&gt; The Highlands of the early seventeenth century saw the development of piping families including the [[MacCrimmon (piping family)|MacCrimmonds]], MacArthurs, [[Clan Gregor|MacGregors]] and the Mackays of [[Gairloch]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Porterp35&quot;&gt;J. Porter, &quot;Introduction&quot; in J. Porter, ed., ''Defining Strains: The Musical Life of Scots in the Seventeenth Century'' (Peter Lang, 2007), {{ISBN|3-03910-948-0}}, p. 35.&lt;/ref&gt;

The first probable reference to the Irish bagpipe is from 1544, which mentions their use by Irish troops in Henry VIII's [[Sieges of Boulogne (1544–46)|siege of Boulogne]].&lt;ref&gt;Donnelly, Seán, The Early History of Piping in Ireland (2001), p. 9&lt;/ref&gt; In 1581 ''[[The Image of Irelande]]'' clearly depicts a bagpiper. Derrick's illustrations are considered to be reasonably faithful depictions of the attire and equipment of the English and Irish population of the 16th century.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation
 | first       = John
 | last        = Derrick
 | title       = The Image of Irelande
 | url         = http://www.lib.ed.ac.uk/about/bgallery/Gallery/researchcoll/ireland.html
 | publisher   =
 | place       = London
 | year        = 1581
 | accessdate  =
}}&lt;/ref&gt; The &quot;Battell&quot; sequence from ''[[My Ladye Nevells Booke]]'' (1591) by [[William Byrd]], which probably alludes to the Irish wars of 1578, contains a piece entitled ''The bagpipe: &amp; the drone''. In 1760, the first serious study of the Scottish Highland bagpipe and its music was attempted, in Joseph MacDonald's ''Compleat Theory''. Further south, a manuscript from the 1730s by a [[William Dixon manuscript|William Dixon]] from [[Northumberland]] contains music that fits the [[border pipes]], a nine-note bellows-blown bagpipe whose chanter is similar to that of the modern [[Great Highland bagpipe]]. However the music in Dixon's manuscript varied greatly from modern Highland bagpipe tunes, consisting mostly of extended variation sets of common dance tunes. Some of the tunes in the Dixon manuscript correspond to tunes found in early 19th century published and manuscript sources of [[Northumbrian smallpipe]] tunes, notably the rare book of 50 tunes, many with variations, by John Peacock.''
[[File:Merry brothers 1887.jpg|thumb|right|''[[Happy Brothers]]'' by [[Uroš Predić]] (1887)]]
As Western classical music developed, both in terms of musical sophistication and instrumental technology, bagpipes in many regions fell out of favour due to their limited range and function. This triggered a long, slow decline that continued, in most cases, into the 20th century.

Extensive and documented collections of traditional bagpipes can be found in the [[Metropolitan Museum of Art]] in New York City, the [[International Bagpipe Museum]] in [[Gijón]], Spain, the [[Pitt Rivers Museum]] in Oxford, England and the [[Morpeth Chantry Bagpipe Museum]] in Northumberland, and the [[Musical Instrument Museum (Phoenix)|Musical Instrument Museum]] in Phoenix, Arizona.

[[File:MDF Strakonice 2018 09 Anglie 02.jpg|thumb|left|International Bagpipe Festival, Strakonice, 2018]]

The [[International Bagpipe Festival]] (''Mezinárodní dudácký festival'', '''IBF''', '''MDF''') is held every two years in [[Strakonice]], [[Czech Republic]].

=== Recent history ===
[[File:Afghanistan bagpiper.jpg|thumb|right|A Canadian soldier plays the bagpipes during the War in Afghanistan. Bagpipes are frequently used during funerals and memorials, especially among fire department, military and police forces in the United Kingdom, Ireland, the Commonwealth realms, and the US.]]
During the expansion of the British Empire, spearheaded by British military forces that included [[Scottish regiment#Highland Regiments|Highland regiments]], the Scottish Great Highland bagpipe became well-known worldwide. This surge in popularity was boosted by large numbers of pipers trained for military service in [[World War I]] and [[World War II]]. The surge coincided with a decline in the popularity of many traditional forms of bagpipe throughout Europe, which began to be displaced by instruments from the classical tradition and later by gramophone and radio.

In the United Kingdom and [[Commonwealth Nations]] such as Canada, New Zealand and Australia the [[Great Highland bagpipe]] is commonly used in the military and is often played in formal ceremonies. Foreign militaries patterned after the British Army have also taken the Highland bagpipe into use including Uganda, Sudan, India, Pakistan, Sri Lanka, Jordan, and Oman. Many police and fire services in Scotland, Canada, Australia, New Zealand, Hong Kong, and the United States have also adopted the tradition of fielding pipe bands.

[[File:Bagad Brest.jpg|thumb|left|A [[bagad]] in [[Brest, France]]]]
In recent years, often driven by revivals of native folk music and dance, many types of bagpipes have enjoyed a resurgence in popularity and, in many cases, instruments that were on the brink of obscurity have become extremely popular. In [[Brittany]], the Great Highland bagpipe and concept of the [[pipe band]] were appropriated to create a Breton interpretation, the [[bagad]]. The pipe band idiom has also been adopted and applied to the [[Galician bagpipe|Galician gaita]] as well. Additionally, bagpipes have often been used in various films depicting moments from Scottish and Irish history; the film ''[[Braveheart]]'' and the theatrical show ''[[Riverdance]]'' have served to make the uilleann pipes more commonly known.

Bagpipes are sometimes played at formal events in Commonwealth universities, particularly in Canada. Because of the Scottish influences on the sport of [[curling]], bagpipes are also the official instrument of the [[World Curling Federation]] and are commonly played during a ceremonial procession of teams before major curling championships.

Bagpipe making was once a craft that produced instruments in many distinctive local traditional styles. Today, the world's biggest producer of the instrument is Pakistan, where the industry was worth $6.8 million in 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation
 | first       = Caroline
 | last        = Jaine
 | authorlink  =
 | title       = Doing business with Pakistan
 | url         = http://www.dawn.com/news/663807/doing-business-with-pakistan
 | publisher   = [[Dawn (newspaper)|Dawn]]
 | date        = 2011-10-04
 | accessdate  = 2013-02-02
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
 | last        = Abbas
 | first       = Nosheen
 | title       = The thriving bagpipe business of Pakistan
 | url         = https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-20876096
 | work   = [[BBC News Online]]
 | location    = [[Pakistan]]
 | date        = 2012-12-31
 | accessdate  = 2013-01-02
 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In the late 20th century, various models of [[electronic bagpipes]] were invented. The first custom-built [[MIDI]] bagpipes were developed by the Asturian piper known as [[Hevia]] (José Ángel Hevia Velasco).&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation
 | first       = Susana
 | last        = Roza-Vigil
 | authorlink  =
 | title       = Bagpipes resonate through rugged coastline of... Spain
 | url         = http://www.cnn.com/SHOWBIZ/Music/9911/05/wb.galicia/
 | publisher   = CNN
 | series      = WorldBeat
 | location    = Spain
 | date        = 1999-11-05
 | accessdate  = 2013-01-02
 }}&lt;/ref&gt;[[File:FIL 2016 - The City Of Auckland Pipe Band - 4780.webm|thumb|Bagpipes players from ''The City Of Auckland Pipe Band''.]]
== Modern usage ==
=== Types of bagpipes ===
{{Main|List of bagpipes}}

Dozens of types of bagpipes today are widely spread across Europe and the Middle East, as well as through much of the former [[British Empire]]. The name bagpipe has almost become synonymous with its best-known form, the [[Great Highland bagpipe]], overshadowing the great number and variety of traditional forms of bagpipe. Despite the decline of these other types of pipes over the last few centuries, in recent years many of these pipes have seen a resurgence or revival as musicians have sought them out; for example, the [[Uilleann pipes|Irish piping tradition]], which by the mid 20th century had declined to a handful of master players is today alive, well, and flourishing a situation similar to that of the [[gaita asturiana|Asturian gaita]], the [[Galician gaita]], the Portuguese [[gaita transmontana]], the Aragonese [[gaita de boto]], [[Northumbrian smallpipe]]s, the [[Breton people|Breton]] [[biniou]], the [[Balkan]] [[gaida]], the [[Romanians|Romanian]] [[cimpoi]],  the Black Sea [[Tulum (bagpipe)|tulum]], the [[Scottish smallpipes]] and [[pastoral pipes]], as well as other varieties.[[File:Thechanter.jpg|thumb|A Great Highland bagpipe [[practice chanter]]]]Traditionally, one of the purposes of the bagpipe was to provide music for dancing. This has declined with the growth of dance bands, recordings, and the decline of traditional dance. In turn, this has led to many types of pipes developing a performance-led tradition, and indeed much modern music based on the dance music tradition played on bagpipes is no longer suitable for use as dance music.

====Image gallery====
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:BulgarianKabaGaidaPlayer.jpg|Bulgarian [[Kaba gaida]] player.
File:Bag piper, Padre, Currie Hall, Royal Military College of Canada, fall 2011.jpg|The Scottish Great Highland bagpipe played at a Canadian military function.
File:Baghet suonatore.jpg|A musician with a Northern Italian [[Baghèt]] wearing traditional dress.
File:A modern model of Baghèt.png|Modern Baghèt (made 2000 by Valter Biella) in G.
File:Zampogna.jpg|Central and southern Italian [[zampogna]].
File:Tulumcu.jpg|[[Laz people|Laz]] man from Turkey playing a [[Tulum (bagpipe)|tulum]].
File:Cillian Vallely on Uilleann Pipes.jpg|[[Cillian Vallely]] playing Irish Uilleann pipes.
File:Tickell 2004.jpg|[[Kathryn Tickell]] playing [[Northumbrian smallpipes]].
File:Gaida.jpg|Man from Skopje, North Macedonia playing the [[Gaida]].
File:Seivane1.jpg|[[Galician gaita]].
File:Sruti upanga.jpg|[[Sruti upanga]], a Southern Indian bagpipe.
File:Duda Bagpipe 001.jpg|Hungarian [[duda]].
File:Serbian bagpiper.jpg|Serbian piper.
File:DudyWielkopolskie.jpg|Polish pipers.
File:Bagad.JPG|[[Bagad]] of Lann Bihoué from the French Navy.
File:Ollegallmo.jpg|Swedish [[säckpipa]].
File:Pastoral pipes removable foot joint.JPG|[[Pastoral pipes]] with removable footjoint and bellows.
File:Street-piper.jpg|Street piper from Sofia, Bulgaria.
File:Torupillimängija.jpg|Estonian [[torupill]] player.
File:Lithuanian bagpipes.png|Lithuanian piper.
File:Modern huemmelchen.jpg|Modern German [[huemmelchen]].
File:Lietuviškas dūdmaišis (LNM).jpg|Lithuanian bagpipes.
File:Al son de la gaita.jpg|[[Gaita asturiana]].
File:Pibecwd.jpg|[[Welsh bagpipes]] (double-reed type).
File:Gaiteroscantabria.jpg|Cantabrian pipe band.
File:Bagpipe player damascus.jpg|Syrian piper in Damascus, Syria.
File:Tsambouna.jpg|Various forms of the [[Tsampouna]], found in the Greek islands.
File:Селянін грае на дудзе.jpg|Belarusian piper.
File:A żaqq (bagpipe), made from calf pelt, cane, and animal horn.jpg|Maltese [[Żaqq]].
File:Bagpipe player Dam.jpg|Piper playing by the [[Royal Palace of Amsterdam]].
File:Cimpoi.png|Romanian [[cimpoi]] player.
File:Ľubomír Párička gra na dudach.webm|Ľubomír Párička playing bagpipes, Slovak Republic.
&lt;/gallery&gt;

=== Usage in non-traditional music ===
{{Main|List of nontraditional bagpipe usage}}
[[File:Enter The Haggis Bagpipe.jpg|thumb|right|Celtic rock band [[Enter the Haggis]] featuring Highland bagpipes]]
Since the 1960s, bagpipes have also made appearances in other forms of music, including rock, metal, jazz, hip-hop, punk, and classical music, for example with [[Paul McCartney]]'s &quot;[[Mull of Kintyre (song)|Mull of Kintyre]]&quot;, [[AC/DC]]'s &quot;[[It's a Long Way to the Top (If You Wanna Rock 'n' Roll)]]&quot;, and [[Peter Maxwell Davies]]'s composition ''[[An Orkney Wedding, with Sunrise]]''. &lt;!--STRONGLY RECOMMEND NO MORE THAN THREE EXAMPLES TO BE PLACED IN THIS PARAGRAPH, PARTICULARLY AS THERE IS A LINK TO A COMPREHENSIVE LIST.  IF ADDING ONE, PLEASE THINK CAREFULLY ABOUT WHY IT IS A BETTER EXAMPLE THAN WHAT YOU ARE REMOVING.  TA.--&gt;

== Publications ==
&lt;!--
Note: only put in this section books or journals covering bagpipes in general.  If it is for a specific type of bagpipe (Uilleann, GHB &amp;c) place it in a specific article.--&gt;

=== Periodicals ===
''Periodicals covering specific types of bagpipes are addressed in the article for that bagpipe''
* {{Citation | title = An Píobaire | publisher = Na Píobairí Uilleann | place = Dublin | url = http://pipers.ie/}}.
* {{Citation | title = Chanter | publisher = [[The Bagpipe Society]]}}.
* {{Citation | title = The Piping Times | publisher = The [[College of Piping]] | place = Glasgow}}.
* {{Citation | title = Piping Today | publisher = The National Piping Centre | place = Glasgow}}.
* {{Citation | title = Utriculus | publisher = [[Circolo della Zampogna]] | place = Italy}}.
* {{Citation | title = The Voice | publisher = The [[Eastern United States Pipe Band Association]] | place = Newark, [[Delaware|DL]]}}.

=== Books ===
{{Main|List of bagpipe books}}
* {{Citation | first = Anthony | last = Baines | year = Nov 1991 | title = Woodwind Instruments and Their History | ISBN = 0-486-26885-3 | publisher = Dover Pub | url-access = registration | url = https://archive.org/details/woodwindinstrume00bain }}.
* {{Citation | first = Anthony | last = Baines | year = 1995 | title = Bagpipes | ISBN = 0-902793-10-1 | publisher = Pitt Rivers Museum, Univ. of Oxford | edition = 3rd | author-mask = 3}}, 147 pp. with plates.
* {{Citation | title = The Book of the Bagpipe | first = Hugh | last = Cheape}}.
* {{Citation | title = The Bagpipe, The History of a Musical Instrument | first = Francis | last = Collinson | year = 1975}}.

== See also ==
* [[List of bagpipes]]
* [[List of bagpipers]]
* [[List of pipe makers]]
* [[List of pipe bands]]
* [[List of published bagpipe music]]
* [[List of nontraditional bagpipe usage]]
* [[List of bagpipe technology books]]
* [[List of composers who employed pipe music]]
* [[Glossary of bagpipe terms]]
* [[Practice chanter]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Bagpipes}}
{{Wikisource1911Enc|Bag-pipe}}
* [http://www.prydein.com/pipes/ Bagpipe iconography – Paintings and images of the pipes.]
* [http://musiconis.huma-num.fr/fr/results.html?query=bagpipe Musiconis Database of Medieval Musical Iconography: Bagpipe.]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20091112123617/http://www.researchchannel.org/prog/displayevent.aspx?rID=3365&amp;fID=345 A demonstration of rare instruments including bagpipes]
* [http://www.bagpipehistory.info/ ''The Concise History of the Bagpipe'' by Frank J. Timoney]
* [http://www.bagpipesociety.org.uk/ The Bagpipe Society], dedicated to promoting the study, playing, and making of bagpipes and pipes from around the world
* [http://ludowe.instrumenty.edu.pl/en/instruments-/categories/category/343 Bagpipes from polish collections (''Polish folk musical instruments'')]
* [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TO8ZRZYB16c&amp;list=PL-vEE7TX3aIfca1edpfKRz3Vt6HURNAMf&amp;index=2 Bagpipes (local polish name &quot;Koza&quot;) played by Jan Karpiel-Bułecka] (English subtitles)
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20170709134521/http://www.baghet.info/ Official site of Baghet (bagpipe from North Italy) players.]
* [http://turn.do.am/index/obratnaja_svjaz/0-43# Celtic Music : Scottish Military Bagpipes.]
&lt;!-- before adding back in the link to Hittite bagpipes, please see the talk page --&gt;

{{musical instruments}}

{{authority control}}

[[Category:Bagpipes| ]]
[[Category:Articles containing video clips]]</text>
      <sha1>smm6fo1bm15ymbzkxzainx255ckatgj</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
