  <page>
    <title>Baptists</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3979</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942481653</id>
      <parentid>940444064</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-24T23:07:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>129.174.182.93</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Beliefs that vary among Baptists */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|Baptist|the Christian practice|Baptism|other uses}}
{{short description|Denomination of Protestant Christianity}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2018}} 
{{Baptist}}{{Protestantism}}
'''Baptists''' form a major branch of [[Protestantism]] distinguished by baptizing professing believers only ([[believer's baptism]], as opposed to [[infant baptism]]), and doing so by complete [[Immersion baptism|immersion]] (as opposed to [[affusion]] or [[aspersion]]). Baptist churches also generally subscribe to the [[doctrine]]s of [[soul competency]] (the responsibility and accountability of every person before God), ''[[sola fide]]'' (salvation by faith alone), ''[[sola scriptura]]'' (scripture alone as the rule of faith and practice) and [[Congregationalist polity|congregationalist church government]]. Baptists generally recognize two [[Ordinance (Christianity)|ordinances]]: baptism and [[Eucharist|communion]].

Diverse from their beginning, those identifying as Baptists today differ widely from one another in what they believe, how they worship, their attitudes toward other Christians, and their understanding of what is important in Christian discipleship.&lt;ref name =&quot;Shurden turning&quot;&gt;{{Cite web| last=Shurden |first=Walter |title=Turning Points in Baptist History |publisher=The Center for Baptist Studies, Mercer University|location= Macon, GA |year=2001 |accessdate=16 January 2010 |url = http://www.centerforbaptiststudies.org/pamphlets/style/turningpoints.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Historians trace the earliest &quot;Baptist&quot; church to 1609 in [[Amsterdam]], [[Dutch Republic]] with [[English Dissenters|English Separatist]] [[John Smyth (Baptist minister)|John Smyth]] as its pastor.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gourley&quot; /&gt; In accordance with his reading of the [[New Testament]], he rejected baptism of infants and instituted baptism only of believing adults.&lt;ref name=&quot;ODCC self&quot;&gt;{{citation|contribution=Baptists|editor-last=Cross|editor-first=FL|title=The Oxford dictionary of the Christian church|place=New York|publisher= Oxford University Press|year=2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; Baptist practice spread to England, where the [[General Baptists]] considered Christ's atonement to [[Unlimited atonement|extend to all people]], while the [[Particular Baptists]] believed that it extended only to [[Election (Christianity)|the elect]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Benedict1848&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Benedict|first=David|title=A General History of the Baptist Denomination in America and Other Parts of the World|url=https://archive.org/details/ageneralhistory00benegoog|year=1848|publisher=Lewis Colby|language=English|page=325|quote=It is, however, well known by the community at home and abroad, that from a very early period they have been divided into two parties, which have been denominated ''General'' and ''Particular'', which differ from each other mainly in their doctrinal sentiments; the Generals being Arminians, and the other, Calvinists.}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Thomas Helwys]] formulated a distinctively Baptist request that the [[Baptists in the history of separation of church and state|church and the state be kept separate]] in matters of law, so that individuals might have freedom of religion. Helwys died in prison as a consequence of the religious conflict with [[English dissenters]] under [[James I of England|King James I]]. In 1638, [[Roger Williams]] established the [[first Baptist Church in America|first Baptist congregation in the North American colonies]]. In the 18th and 19th centuries, the [[First Great Awakening|First]] and [[Second Great Awakening]] increased church membership in the United States.&lt;ref name=&quot;EBOself&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/52364/Baptist Baptist].&quot; 2010. Encyclopædia Britannica Online.&lt;/ref&gt;   Baptist missionaries have spread their faith to every continent.&lt;ref name=&quot;ODCC self&quot; /&gt;

==Origins==
Baptist historian Bruce Gourley outlines four main views of Baptist origins:

# the modern scholarly consensus that the movement traces its origin to the 17th century via the [[English Dissenters|English Separatists]],
# the view that it was an outgrowth of [[Anabaptism|Anabaptist]] traditions,
# the perpetuity view which assumes that the Baptist ''faith and practice'' has existed since the time of Christ, and
# the successionist view, or &quot;[[Baptist successionism]]&quot;, which argues that Baptist ''churches'' actually existed in an unbroken chain since the time of Christ.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gourley&quot;&gt;Gourley, Bruce. &quot;A Very Brief Introduction to Baptist History, Then and Now.&quot; ''The Baptist Observer.''&lt;/ref&gt;

===English separatist view===
[[File:John-Smyth.png|thumb|John Smyth is believed to have the first church labeled &quot;Baptist&quot; in Amsterdam in 1609]]
Modern Baptist churches trace their history to the [[English Dissenters|English Separatist]] movement in the 1600s, the century after the rise of the original Protestant denominations.&lt;ref name=&quot;Brackney&quot; /&gt; This view of Baptist origins has the most historical support and is the most widely accepted.&lt;ref name=&quot;ETS&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Anabaptist kinship or English dissent? Papers at ETS examine Baptist origins |newspaper=[[Baptist Press]] |first=Jeff |last=Robinson |date=14 Dec 2009 |url=http://www.bpnews.net/printerfriendly.asp?ID=31878 |url-status = dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130619030031/http://www.bpnews.net/printerfriendly.asp?ID=31878 |archivedate=19 June 2013 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt; Adherents to this position consider the influence of Anabaptists upon early Baptists to be minimal.&lt;ref name = &quot;Gourley&quot; /&gt;  It was a time of considerable political and religious turmoil. Both individuals and churches were willing to give up their theological roots if they became convinced that a more biblical &quot;truth&quot; had been discovered.{{Sfn | Leonard | 2003}}{{Page needed |date=June 2014}}&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Baptist Ways: A History|authorlink1=Bill J. Leonard|last=Leonard|first=Bill J.|publisher=Judson Press|year=2003|isbn=978-0817012311|location=Valley Forge, PA|pages=24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the [[Protestant Reformation]], the [[Church of England]] ([[Anglicanism|Anglicans]]) separated from the [[Roman Catholic Church]]. There were some Christians who were not content with the achievements of the mainstream Protestant Reformation.&lt;ref name= &quot;Shurden turning&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Briggs&quot;&gt;{{Cite web | last = Briggs | first = John | title = Baptist Origins | publisher = Baptist History and Heritage Society | accessdate = 10 January 2010 | url = http://www.baptisthistory.org/contissues/briggs.htm | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20100105221040/http://www.baptisthistory.org/contissues/briggs.htm | archivedate = 5 January 2010 |url-status = dead| df = dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; There also were Christians who were disappointed that the Church of England had not made corrections of what some considered to be errors and abuses. Of those most critical of the Church's direction, some chose to stay and try to make constructive changes from within the Anglican Church. They became known as &quot;[[Puritans]]&quot; and are described by Gourley as cousins of the English Separatists. Others decided they must leave the Church because of their dissatisfaction and became known as the Separatists.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gourley&quot; /&gt;

Historians trace the earliest Baptist church back to 1609 in Amsterdam, with [[John Smyth (Baptist minister)|John Smyth]] as its pastor.&lt;ref name= &quot;Gourley&quot; /&gt;  Three years earlier, while a Fellow of Christ's College, Cambridge, he had broken his ties with the Church of England. Reared in the Church of England, he became &quot;Puritan, English Separatist, and then a Baptist Separatist,&quot; and ended his days working with the Mennonites.{{Sfn | Leonard | 2003 | p = 23}} He began meeting in England with 60–70 English Separatists, in the face of &quot;great danger.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | last = Beale | first = David | title = The Mayflower Pilgrims: roots of Puritan, Presbyterian, Congregationalist, and Baptist heritage | publisher = Emerald House | year = 2000 | isbn = 978-1-889893-51-8 | url = https://archive.org/details/mayflowerpilgrim00beal }}&lt;/ref&gt; The persecution of religious nonconformists in England led Smyth to go into exile in [[Amsterdam]] with fellow Separatists from the congregation he had  gathered in Lincolnshire, separate from the established church (Anglican). Smyth and his lay supporter, [[Thomas Helwys]], together with those they led, broke with the other English exiles because Smyth and Helwys were convinced they should be baptized as believers. In 1609 Smyth first baptized himself and then baptized the others.&lt;ref name=&quot;Briggs&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.reformedreader.org/history/pbh.htm|title=A Primer on Baptist History|last=Traffanstedt|first=Chris|accessdate=23 December 2009| archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20100203160034/http://www.reformedreader.org/history/pbh.htm | archivedate= 3 February 2010 |url-status = live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1609, while still there, Smyth wrote a tract titled &quot;The Character of the Beast,&quot; or &quot;The False Constitution of the Church.&quot; In it he expressed two propositions: first, infants are not to be baptized; and second, &quot;Antichristians converted are to be admitted into the true Church by baptism.&quot;{{Sfn | Leonard | 2003 | p = 24}} Hence, his conviction was that a scriptural church should consist only of regenerate believers who have been baptized on a personal confession of faith. He rejected the Separatist movement's doctrine of infant baptism ([[paedobaptism]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Nettles|first=Tom J. |date=Spring 2009|title=Once Upon a Time, Four Hundred Years Ago... |journal=Founders Journal|volume= 76|pages = 2–8 |url = http://www.founders.org/journal/fj76/article1.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url= http://www.reformedreader.org/history/vedder/ch14.htm|title=A Short History of the Baptists|last=Vedder|first=HC|publisher= The Reformed Reader|accessdate= 23 December 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Shortly thereafter, Smyth left the group, and layman Thomas Helwys took over the leadership, leading the church back to England in 1611.&lt;ref name = &quot;Gourley&quot; /&gt; Ultimately, Smyth became committed to believers' baptism as the only biblical baptism. He was convinced on the basis of his interpretation of Scripture that infants would not be damned should they die in infancy.{{Sfn | Leonard | 2003 | p = 25}}

Smyth, convinced that his self-baptism was invalid, applied with the [[Mennonites]] for membership. He died while waiting for membership, and some of his followers became Mennonites. Thomas Helwys and others kept their baptism and their Baptist commitments.{{Sfn | Leonard | 2003 | p = 25}}  The modern Baptist denomination is an outgrowth of Smyth's movement.&lt;ref name = &quot;Briggs&quot; /&gt;  Baptists rejected the name Anabaptist when they were called that by opponents in derision. McBeth writes that as late as the 18th century, many Baptists referred to themselves as &quot;the Christians commonly—though ''falsely''—called Anabaptists.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;McBeth Bapt Beg&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.baptisthistory.org/baptistbeginnings.htm|title= Baptist Beginnings | last = McBeth| first= H Leon |publisher= Baptist History and Heritage Society |accessdate= 19 October 2007| archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20071021083427/http://baptisthistory.org/baptistbeginnings.htm| archivedate = 21 October 2007 |url-status = live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another milestone in the early development of Baptist doctrine was in 1638 with [[John Spilsbury (Baptist minister)|John Spilsbury]], a Calvinistic minister who helped to promote the strict practice of believer's [[Immersion baptism|baptism by immersion]].&lt;ref name = &quot;ETS&quot;/&gt;  According to Tom Nettles, professor of historical theology at [[Southern Baptist Theological Seminary]], &quot;Spilsbury's cogent arguments for a gathered, disciplined congregation of believers baptized by immersion as constituting the New Testament church gave expression to and built on insights that had emerged within separatism, advanced in the life of John Smyth and the suffering congregation of Thomas Helwys, and matured in Particular Baptists.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;ETS&quot; /&gt;

===Anabaptist influence view===
[[File:TheDippersDipt.jpg|thumb|left|Print from Anglican theologian [[Daniel Featley]]'s book, &quot;The Dippers Dipt, or, The Anabaptists Duck'd and Plung'd Over Head and Ears, at a Disputation in Southwark&quot;, published in 1645.]]
A minority view is that early-17th-century Baptists were influenced by (but not directly connected to) continental [[Anabaptist]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Priest&quot;&gt;{{citation|last=Priest|first=Gerald L PhD|title=Are Baptists Protestants?|publisher=Detroit Baptist Theological Seminary|date=14 October 2010|url=http://www.dbts.edu/pdf/macp/2007/Priest,%20Are%20Baptists%20Protestants.pdf|url-status = bot: unknown|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170620124136/http://www.dbts.edu/pdf/macp/2007/Priest,%20Are%20Baptists%20Protestants.pdf|archivedate=20 June 2017|df=dmy-all}}.&lt;/ref&gt; According to this view, the General Baptists shared similarities with Dutch Waterlander Mennonites (one of many Anabaptist groups) including believer's baptism only, religious liberty, separation of church and state, and [[Arminianism|Arminian]] views of salvation, predestination and original sin. Representative writers including A.C. Underwood and William R. Estep. Gourley wrote that among some contemporary Baptist scholars who emphasize the faith of the community over soul liberty, the Anabaptist influence theory is making a comeback.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gourley&quot; /&gt;

However, the relations between Baptists and Anabaptists were early strained. In 1624, the then five existing Baptist churches of London issued a condemnation of the Anabaptists.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Early English Dissenters in the Light of Recent Research|last=Burrage|first=Champlin|publisher=Cambridge|year=1912|isbn=|volume=2|location=University Press|pages=222}}&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, the original group associated with Smyth and popularly believed to be the first Baptists broke with the Waterlander Mennonite Anabaptists after a brief period of association in the Netherlands.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|last=Melton|first=JG|contribution=Baptists|title=Encyclopedia of American Religions|year= 1994}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Perpetuity and succession view===
{{Main |Baptist successionism}}
Traditional Baptist historians write from the perspective that Baptists had existed since the time of Christ.{{Sfn | Torbet | 1975 | pp = 18–9}} However, the [[Southern Baptist Convention]] passed resolutions rejecting this view in 1859.{{Citation needed|date=April 2018}} Proponents of the Baptist successionist or perpetuity view consider the Baptist movement to have existed independently from [[Roman Catholic Church|Roman Catholicism]] and prior to the [[Protestant Reformation]].&lt;ref name=&quot;H. Leon McBeth pages 59-60&quot;&gt;{{citation|first=H Leon|last=McBeth|title=The Baptist Heritage|pages=59–60| place = Nashville | publisher = Broadman Press|year= 1987}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

The perpetuity view is often identified with ''[[The Trail of Blood]]'', a booklet of five lectures by J.M. Carrol published in 1931.&lt;ref name= &quot;H. Leon McBeth pages 59-60&quot; /&gt;  Other Baptist writers who advocate the successionist theory of Baptist origins are [[John T. Christian]], [[Thomas Crosby (Baptist)|Thomas Crosby]], G. H. Orchard, J. M. Cramp, William Cathcart, Adam Taylor and D. B. Ray&lt;ref name=&quot;H. Leon McBeth pages 59-60&quot; /&gt;{{Sfn | Torbet | 1975 | p = 18}}  This view was also held by English Baptist preacher, [[Charles Spurgeon]]&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |title= The New park Street Pulpit|volume=VII|page= 225}}.&lt;/ref&gt; as well as [[Jesse Mercer]], the namesake of Mercer University.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| first =Jesse | last = Mercer|title= A History of the Georgia Baptist Association|pages = 196–201 | year =1838|url= http://baptisthistoryhomepage.com/1811cl_mercer.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1898 William Whitsitt was pressured to resign his presidency of the Southern Baptist Theological Seminary for denying Baptist successionism &lt;ref name=&quot;James H. Slatton pages 278-293&quot;&gt;{{citation|first=James H.|last=Slatton|title=W.H. Whitsitt - The Man And The Controversy|pages=278–279| place = Macon | publisher = Mercer University Press|year= 2009}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Baptist origins in the United Kingdom===
{{see also|English Dissenters}}
[[File:Title Page A Short Declaration of the Mistery of Iniquity.jpg|right|thumb|''A Short Declaration of the Mistery of Iniquity'' (1612) by [[Thomas Helwys]]. For Helwys, religious liberty was a right for everyone, even for those he disagreed with.]]
In 1612, [[Thomas Helwys]] established a Baptist congregation in London, consisting of congregants from Smyth's church. A number of other Baptist churches sprang up, and they became known as the General Baptists. The Particular Baptists were established when a group of Calvinist Separatists adopted believers' Baptism.{{Sfn | Wright | 2004}}{{Page needed |date=June 2014}} The Particular Baptists consisted of seven churches by 1644 and had created a confession of faith called the First London Confession of Faith.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Southern Baptist Convention: A Sesquicentennial History|last=Fletcher|first=Jesse C.|publisher=Broadman &amp; Holman|year=1994|isbn=978-0805411676|location=Nashville, TN|pages=25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Baptist origins in North America===
{{See also|Baptists in the United States|Baptists in Canada}}
[[File:Saddleback church Lake Forest building2.jpg|280px|thumb|right|Building of [[Saddleback Church]], affiliated to the [[Southern Baptist Convention]], in 2016, in [[Lake Forest, California]], [[United States]]]]
Both [[Roger Williams]] and [[John Clarke (Baptist minister)|John Clarke]], his compatriot and coworker for religious freedom, are variously credited as founding the earliest Baptist church in North America.&lt;ref name=&quot;Newport&quot;&gt;{{citation|url=http://www.redwoodlibrary.org/notables/clarke.htm |title=Newport Notables |publisher=Redwood Library |url-status = dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070927062252/http://www.redwoodlibrary.org/notables/clarke.htm |archivedate=27 September 2007 |df=dmy }}.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1639, Williams established a Baptist church in [[Providence, Rhode Island]], and Clarke began a Baptist church in [[Newport, Rhode Island]]. According to a Baptist historian who has researched the matter extensively, &quot;There is much debate over the centuries as to whether the Providence or Newport church deserved the place of 'first' Baptist congregation in America. Exact records for both congregations are lacking.&quot;&lt;ref name= &quot;Brackney&quot;&gt;{{Cite book| authorlink = William H. Brackney| last = Brackney | first = William H |title= Baptists in North America: an historical perspective| publisher= Blackwell Publishing | year = 2006 | page = 22 | isbn = 978-1-4051-1865-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Thomas S. Kidd and Barry Hankins, ''Baptists in America: A History'' (2015)&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Great Awakening]] energized the Baptist movement, and the Baptist community experienced spectacular growth. Baptists became the largest Christian community in many southern states, including among the black population.&lt;ref name=&quot;ODCC self&quot; /&gt;

Baptist missionary work in Canada began in the British colony of [[Nova Scotia]] (present day Nova Scotia and [[New Brunswick]]) in the 1760s.{{Sfn | Bumstead | 1984 | p = 40}} The first official record of a Baptist church in Canada was that of the Horton Baptist Church (now Wolfville) in Wolfville, Nova Scotia on 29 October 1778.{{Sfn | Bumstead | 1984 | p = 62}}  The church was established with the assistance of the [[New Light]] evangelist [[Henry Alline]]. Many of Alline's followers, after his death, would convert and strengthen the Baptist presence in the Atlantic region.{{Sfn | Bumstead | 1984}}{{Page needed |date=June 2014}}&lt;ref name = &quot;Rawlyk&quot;&gt;{{Cite book | editor-last = Rawlyk | editor-first = George A |title= The Sermons of Henry Alline | publisher = Lancelot Press for Acadia Divinity College and the Baptist Historical Committee of the United Baptist Convention of the Atlantic Provinces | place = Hantsport |year= 1986|page=32}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | last = Bell | first = DG | title = Henry Alline and Maritime Religion | publisher = Canadian Historical Association | place = Ottawa | year = 1993}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  Two major groups of Baptists formed the basis of the churches in the Maritimes. These were referred to as Regular Baptist (Calvinistic in their doctrine) and Free Will Baptists (Arminian in their doctrine).&lt;ref name=&quot;Rawlyk&quot; /&gt;

In May 1845, the Baptist congregations in the United States split over slavery and missions. The [[American Baptist Home Mission Society|Home Mission Society]] prevented slaveholders from being appointed as missionaries.&lt;ref name=Early&gt;{{Citation | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=_ieENRXoO1YC&amp;pg=PA100 | editor-first = Joe | editor-last = Early | title = Readings in Baptist History: Four Centuries of Selected Documents | pages = 100–1 | accessdate = 25 August 2010| isbn = 9780805446746 | year = 2008 }}.&lt;/ref&gt; The split created the [[Southern Baptist Convention]], while the northern congregations formed their own umbrella organization now called the [[American Baptist Churches USA]] (ABC-USA). The [[Methodist Episcopal Church, South]] had recently separated over the issue of slavery, and southern [[Presbyterians]] would do so shortly thereafter.&lt;ref name=&quot;Southern Baptist Beginnings&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.baptisthistory.org/sbaptistbeginnings.htm |title=Southern Baptist Beginnings |first=Robert A. |last=Baker |publisher=Baptist History &amp; Heritage Society |year=1979 |accessdate=28 October 2012 |url-status = dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20121018074627/http://www.baptisthistory.org/sbaptistbeginnings.htm |archivedate=18 October 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Baptist origins in Ukraine===
{{See also|Baptists in Ukraine}}

The Baptist churches in Ukraine were preceded by the German Anabaptist and Mennonite communities, who had been living in the south of Ukraine since the 16th century.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url= http://www.risu.org.ua/eng/major.religions/baptists |title= Archived copy |access-date= 20 April 2005 |archive-url= http://webarchive.loc.gov/all/20050420001102/http://www.risu.org.ua/eng/major.religions/baptists/ |archive-date=20 April 2005 |url-status = dead|df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; The first Baptist [[baptism]] (adult baptism by full immersion) in Ukraine took place in 1864 on the river [[Inhul]] in the Yelizavetgrad region (now [[Kropyvnytskyi]] region), in a [[History of Germans in Russia, Ukraine and the Soviet Union|German settlement]]. In 1867, the first Baptist communities were organized in that area. From there, the Baptist movement spread across the south of Ukraine and then to other regions as well. One of the first Baptist communities was registered in [[Kiev]] in 1907, and in 1908 the First All-[[Russian Empire|Russian]] Convention of Baptists was held there, as Ukraine was still controlled by the Russian Empire. The All-Russian Union of Baptists was established in the town of Yekaterinoslav (now [[Dnipro]]) in Southern Ukraine. At the end of the 19th century, estimates are that there were between 100,000 and 300,000 Baptists in Ukraine.&lt;ref&gt;[http://ecbua.info/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=44&amp;Itemid=29 History of the AUC ECB]  Всеукраїнський Союз Церков Євангельських Християн-Баптистів web site {{in lang|uk}}&lt;/ref&gt; An independent All-Ukrainian Baptist Union of Ukraine was established during the [[Ukrainian People's Republic|brief period of Ukraine's independence]] in early 20th-century, and once again after the fall of the Soviet Union, the largest of which is currently known as the [[Evangelical Baptist Union of Ukraine]].

==Baptist affiliations==
{{Denominations of Christianity}}

Many Baptist churches choose to affiliate with organizational groups that provide fellowship without control.&lt;ref name=&quot;ODCC self&quot; /&gt; The largest such group in the US is the [[Southern Baptist Convention]]. There also are a substantial number of [[List of Baptist sub-denominations|smaller cooperative groups]]. Finally, there are [[Independent Baptist]] churches that choose to remain independent of any denomination, organization, or association.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|last =Moore|first=G Holmes|title=300&amp;nbsp;Years of Baptist History|quote=Bible Baptist Church of St. Louis, MO, is an example of an independent Baptist church that has never been a denominational church in the sense of belonging to some convention or association|date=17 January 2010|url=http://www.reformedreader.org/history/350years.htm}}.&lt;/ref&gt; It has been suggested that a primary Baptist principle is that local Baptist Churches are independent and self-governing,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.londonbaptist.org.uk/about-us/baptists/?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=94:what-is-the-history-of-the-lba&amp;catid=43&amp;Itemid=105 |title=What are Baptists? London Baptist Association |work=LBA official website |accessdate=28 May 2014 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140504153158/http://www.londonbaptist.org.uk/about-us/baptists/ |archivedate=4 May 2014 |url-status = dead|df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt; and if so the term 'Baptist denomination' may be considered somewhat incongruous.

In 1905, Baptists worldwide formed the [[Baptist World Alliance]] (BWA).&lt;ref&gt;J. Gordon Melton, Martin Baumann, ''Religions of the World: A Comprehensive Encyclopedia of Beliefs and Practices'', ABC-CLIO, USA, 2010, p. 297&lt;/ref&gt; The BWA's goals include caring for the needy, leading in world evangelism and defending human rights and religious freedom. Though it played a role in the founding of the BWA, the [[Southern Baptist Convention]] severed its affiliation with BWA in 2004.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/articles/A44658-2004Jun15.html|title=Southern Baptists Vote To Leave World Alliance|last=Cooperman|first=Alan|date=16 June 2004|work=[[Washington Post]]|accessdate=4 November 2009|page=A4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Membership==
[[File:First Baptist Meetinghouse, Providence, RI.jpg|upright=0.9|thumb|right|The [[First Baptist Church in America]] located in [[Providence, Rhode Island]]. [[Baptists in the United States|Baptists in the U.S.]] number 50 million people and constitute roughly one-third of [[Protestantism in the United States|American Protestants]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pewforum.org/2015/05/12/appendix-b-classification-of-protestant-denominations/|title=Appendix B: Classification of Protestant Denominations|date=12 May 2015|work=Pew Research Center's Religion &amp; Public Life Project}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]

===Statistics===
{{See also|List of Christian denominations by number of members|List of Baptist denominations}}
In 2010, 100 million Christians identify themselves as Baptist or belong to Baptist-type churches.&lt;ref&gt;J. Gordon Melton and Martin Baumann, ''Religions of the World: A Comprehensive Encyclopedia of Beliefs and Practices'', ABC-CLIO, USA, 2010, p.299&lt;/ref&gt; In 2017, the [[Baptist World Alliance]] has 47 million people.&lt;ref name=&quot;BWA&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bwanet.org/about-us2/stats|title=Baptist World Alliance – Statistics|publisher=|accessdate= April 6, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Not all Baptist groups cooperate with the Alliance, notably the [[Southern Baptist Convention]] (which actually participated in its founding) does not cooperate with the Alliance, having withdrawn in 2004.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/articles/A44658-2004Jun15.html|title=Southern Baptists Vote To Leave World Alliance|last=Cooperman|first=Alan|date=16 June 2004|work=[[Washington Post]]|accessdate=4 November 2009|page=A4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Baptists are present in almost all continents in large denominations. The largest communities that are part of the [[Baptist World Alliance]] are in Nigeria (3.5 million) and [[Democratic Republic of the Congo]] (2 million) in Africa, India (2.5 million) and [[Myanmar]] (1 million) in Asia, the United States (35 million) and Brazil (1.8 million) in the Americas.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Statistics |publisher=Baptist World Alliance |url=http://www.bwanet.org/about-us2/statistics |url-status = dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120627073219/http://www.bwanet.org/about-us2/statistics |archivedate=27 June 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1991, [[Ukraine]] had the second largest Baptist community in the world, behind only the United States.&lt;ref name=&quot;NCEEER&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | url=http://www.ucis.pitt.edu/nceeer/2006_819_19g_Wanner.pdf | title=EVANGELICALISM AND THE RESURGENCE OF RELIGION IN UKRAINE | author=Wanne, Catherine | journal=The National Council for Eurasian and East European Research | year=2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the Barna Group researchers, Baptists are the largest denominational grouping of [[Born again (Christianity)|born again Christians]] in the USA.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|chapter=Catholics Have Become Mainstream America|date=9 July 2007|accessdate=16 January 2010|chapter-url=http://www.barna.org/barna-update/article/12-faithspirituality/100-catholics-have-become-mainstream-america|title=Born again Christians in US|quote=Barna defines ''Born again Christians'' as &quot;people who said they have made a personal commitment to Jesus Christ that is still important in their life today and who also indicated they believe that when they die they will go to Heaven because they had confessed their sins and had accepted Jesus Christ as their savior|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100113223949/http://www.barna.org/barna-update/article/12-faithspirituality/100-catholics-have-become-mainstream-america|archivedate=13 January 2010|url-status = dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;  A 2009 ABCNEWS/Beliefnet phone poll of 1,022 adults suggests that fifteen percent of Americans identify themselves as Baptists.&lt;ref name= &quot;abcnews.go.com&quot;&gt;{{citation|last= Langer|first= Gary| title= Poll: Most Americans Say They're Christian. Varies Greatly From the World at Large | date = 18 July 2009 | accessdate = 16 January 2010 | url= http://abcnews.go.com/sections/us/DailyNews/beliefnet_poll_010718.html| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20091217102452/http://abcnews.go.com/sections/us/DailyNews/beliefnet_poll_010718.html | archivedate = 17 December 2009 |url-status = live}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

A large percentage of Baptists in North America are found in six bodies—the [[Southern Baptist Convention]] (SBC); [[American Baptist Association]] (ABA); [[National Baptist Convention, USA, Inc.|National Baptist Convention]] (NBC); [[National Baptist Convention of America, Inc.]]; (NBCA); [[American Baptist Churches USA]] (ABC); and [[Baptist Bible Fellowship International]] (BBFI).&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|first=Albert W|last=Wardin|title=Baptists Around the World|place=Nashville|publisher= Broadman &amp; Holman Publishers|year= 1995|page = 367}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are three states in the world with a Baptist majority: [[Mississippi]] and [[Texas]] in USA (over 50 %), and [[Nagaland]] in India (more than 75 %).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=WgnPCwAAQBAJ|title=Progress and Its Impact on the Nagas: A Clash of Worldviews|last=Thong|first=Tezenlo|year=2016|publisher=[[Routledge]] |isbn=9781317075318|page=128}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gc.cuny.edu/Faculty/GC-Faculty-Activities/ARIS--American-Religious-Identification-Survey/Key-findings American Religious Identification Survey] www.gc.cuny.edu {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20111101085057/http://www.gc.cuny.edu/Faculty/GC-Faculty-Activities/ARIS--American-Religious-Identification-Survey/Key-findings |date=1 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Qualification for membership===
Membership policies vary due to the autonomy of churches, but the traditional method by which an individual becomes a member of a church is through [[believer's baptism]] (which is a public profession of faith in Jesus, followed by water baptism).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Church Manual For Baptist Churches | last =Pendleton | first = James Madison |authorlink=James Madison Pendleton |year= 1867 |publisher= The Judson Press |url = http://www.reformedreader.org/rbb/pendleton/churchmanual/bcm01.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Most baptists do not believe that baptism is a requirement for salvation, but rather a public expression of one's inner repentance and faith.&lt;ref name=&quot;Brackney&quot; /&gt;  Therefore, some churches will admit into membership persons who make a profession without believer's baptism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Church's elders cancel vote on membership without baptism |url=http://www.bpnews.net/bpnews.asp?id=23725 |work=Baptist Press |accessdate=8 November 2011 |url-status = dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130619020303/http://www.bpnews.net/bpnews.asp?id=23725 |archivedate=19 June 2013 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In general, Baptist churches do not have a stated age restriction on membership, but believer's baptism requires that an individual be able to freely and earnestly profess their faith.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Baptist Faith and Mission|url = http://www.sbc.net/bfm/ | publisher =Southern Baptist Convention|accessdate=8 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  (See [[Believer's Baptism#Age of accountability|Age of Accountability]])

==Baptist beliefs and principles==
{{Main|Baptist beliefs}}
Baptists, like other Christians, are defined by school of thought—some of it common to all orthodox and evangelical groups and a portion of it distinctive to Baptists.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|author= Nettles, Thomas J |title=A Foundation for the Future: The Southern Baptist Message and Mission |accessdate=17 January 2010 |url=http://www.reformedreader.org/baptists.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; Through the years, different Baptist groups have issued confessions of faith—without considering them to be ''creeds''—to express their particular doctrinal distinctions in comparison to other Christians as well as in comparison to other Baptists.&lt;ref name=&quot;Shurden fragile&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=Shurden, Walter B |title=The Baptist Identity: Four Fragile Freedoms |location=Macon, Georgia |publisher=Smyth &amp; Helwys Publishing |year=1993 |isbn=978-1-880837-20-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; Baptist denominations are traditionally seen as belonging to two parties, [[General Baptist]]s who uphold [[Arminian]] theology and [[Reformed Baptists|Particular Baptist]]s who uphold [[Reformed]] theology.&lt;ref name=&quot;Benedict1848&quot;/&gt; During the [[holiness movement]], some General Baptists accepted the teaching of a [[second work of grace]] and formed denominations that emphasized this belief, such as the [[Ohio Valley Association of the Christian Baptist Churches of God]] and the [[Holiness Baptist Association]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Lewis2002&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last1=Lewis |first1=James R. |title=The Encyclopedia of Cults, Sects, and New Religions |date=2002 |publisher=Prometheus Books |isbn=9781615927388 |language=English}}&lt;/ref&gt; Most Baptists are evangelical in doctrine, but Baptist beliefs can vary due to the congregational governance system that gives autonomy to individual local Baptist churches.&lt;ref name=&quot;Baptist Origins&quot;&gt;Buescher, John. &quot;[http://teachinghistory.org/history-content/ask-a-historian/22329 Baptist Origins].&quot; [http://www.teachinghistory.org/ Teaching History]. Retrieved 23 September 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Historically, Baptists have played a key role in encouraging religious freedom and separation of church and state.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=Religion Facts |url=http://www.religionfacts.com/christianity/denominations/baptists.htm |contribution=Baptists |accessdate=17 January 2010 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100110123654/http://www.religionfacts.com/christianity/denominations/baptists.htm |archivedate=10 January 2010 |url-status = dead|df=dmy }}.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:US Navy 110508-N-DR144-024 Lt. Jeffrey Ross, a chaplain aboard the Nimitz-class aircraft carrier USS Carl Vinson (CVN 70), baptizes Aviation Boatsw.jpg|thumb|left|A Baptist chaplain aboard a US navy aircraft carrier baptizes a [[Mate (naval officer)|mate]]|alt=]]

Shared doctrines would include beliefs about one God; the virgin birth; miracles; atonement for sins through the death, burial, and bodily resurrection of [[Jesus in Christianity|Jesus]]; the [[Trinity]]; the need for salvation (through belief in Jesus Christ as the Son of God, his death and resurrection); grace; the Kingdom of God; last things (eschatology) (Jesus Christ will return personally and visibly in glory to the earth, the dead will be raised, and Christ will judge everyone in righteousness); and evangelism and missions. Some historically significant Baptist doctrinal documents include the [[1689 London Baptist Confession of Faith]], 1742 Philadelphia Baptist Confession, the [[1833 New Hampshire Baptist Confession of Faith]], the [[Southern Baptist Convention]]'s ''[[Baptist Faith and Message]],'' and written [[church covenant]]s which some individual Baptist churches adopt as a statement of their faith and beliefs.

Most Baptists hold that no church or ecclesiastical organization has inherent authority over a Baptist church. Churches can properly relate to each other under this polity only through voluntary cooperation, never by any sort of coercion. Furthermore, this Baptist polity calls for freedom from governmental control.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Pinson William M, Jr |title=Trends in Baptist Polity |publisher=Baptist History and Heritage Society |url=http://www.baptisthistory.org/contissues/pinson.htm |url-status = dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071013130242/http://baptisthistory.org/contissues/pinson.htm |archivedate=13 October 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Exceptions to this local form of local governance include a few churches that submit to the leadership of a body of [[Elder (Christianity)#Baptists|elders]], as well as the [[Episcopal Baptist]]s that have an [[Episcopal polity|Episcopal system]].

Baptists generally believe in the literal [[Second Coming]] of Christ. Beliefs among Baptists regarding the &quot;[[Christian eschatology|end times]]&quot; include [[amillennialism]], [[dispensationalism]], and historic [[premillennialism]], with views such as [[postmillennialism]] and [[preterism]] receiving some support.

Some additional distinctive Baptist principles held by many Baptists:&lt;ref name=&quot;Newman&quot; /&gt;{{rp|2}}
* The supremacy of the canonical Scriptures as a norm of faith and practice. For something to become a matter of faith and practice, it is not sufficient for it to be merely ''consistent with'' and not contrary to scriptural principles. It must be something ''explicitly'' ordained through command or example in the Bible. For instance, this is why Baptists do not practice infant baptism—they say the Bible neither commands nor exemplifies infant baptism as a Christian practice. More than any other Baptist principle, this one when applied to infant baptism is said to separate Baptists from other evangelical Christians.
* Baptists believe that faith is a matter between God and the individual ([[religious freedom]]). To them it means the advocacy of absolute liberty of conscience.
* Insistence on immersion as the only mode of baptism. Baptists do not believe that baptism is necessary for salvation. Therefore, for Baptists, baptism is an [[Ordinance (Christianity)|ordinance]], not a sacrament, since, in their view, it imparts no saving grace.&lt;ref name=&quot;Newman&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|last=Newman|first =Albert Henry |authorlink= |title=A History of the Baptist Churches in the United States |edition=3rd |url= https://books.google.com/?id=F38uAAAAYAAJ |year=1915 |publisher=Christian Literature |isbn=978-0-7905-4234-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Beliefs that vary among Baptists===
[[File:KJV 1611 Rice Baptist Church New Market Alabama 2012-06-13.jpg|thumb|right|Church sign indicating that the congregation uses the Authorized King James Version of 1611]]
Since there is no hierarchical authority and each Baptist church is autonomous, there is no official set of Baptist theological beliefs.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|last1=Hammett|first1=John|first2=John S|last2=Hammett|quote=One thing that all Baptists have in common is that everything is built upon the Bible.|title=Biblical Foundations for Baptist Churches: A Contemporary Ecclesiology|publisher=Kregel Publications|year=2005|isbn= 978-0-8254-2769-5}}.&lt;/ref&gt; These differences exist both among associations, and even among churches within the associations.

Some doctrinal issues on which there is widespread difference among Baptists are:
* [[Eschatology]]
* [[Arminianism]] versus [[Calvinism]] ([[General Baptist]]s uphold Arminian theology while [[Reformed Baptists|Particular Baptists]] teach Reformed theology).&lt;ref name=&quot;Benedict1848&quot;/&gt;
* The [[doctrine of separation]] from &quot;the world&quot; and whether to associate with those who are &quot;of the world&quot;
* Belief in a [[second work of grace]], i.e. [[entire sanctification]] (held by General Baptists in the Holiness tradition)
* [[Glossolalia|Speaking-in-tongues]] and the operation of other [[Spiritual gift|charismatic gifts]] of the [[Holy Spirit]] in the modern church&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|contribution=Position Paper Concerning the IMB Policy on Glossolalia |title=Florida Baptist Witness |accessdate=18 March 2010 |url=http://www.gofbw.com/news.asp?ID=5592 |url-status = dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110728000657/http://www.gofbw.com/news.asp?ID=5592 |archivedate=28 July 2011 |df=dmy }}.&lt;/ref&gt;
* How the Bible should be interpreted ([[hermeneutics]])
* The extent to which [[Mission (Christian)|missionary]] boards should be used to support missionaries
* The extent to which non-members may participate in the [[Eucharist|Lord's Supper]] services
* Which translation of Scripture to use (see [[King-James-Only movement]] in the [[English-speaking world]])&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=An Introduction to Bible Translations|publisher=Trinity Baptist Church Discipleship Training|date=April 2005|accessdate =18 March 2010|url = http://www.trinitybaptistreformed.org/files/Download/Bible%20Translations%20+.pdf}}.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Dispensationalism]] versus [[Covenant theology]]
* The role of [[Christian views of marriage|women in marriage]].
* The [[Ordination of women in Protestant denominations#Baptist|ordination of women]] as deacons or pastors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Beck|first=Rosalie (Response to 'The Ordination of Women Among Texas Baptists' by Ann Miller)|title=Perspectives in Religious Studies|journal = Journal of the NABPR|accessdate =18 March 2010|url= http://www.bgct.org/texasbaptists/Document.Doc?&amp;id=3338}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Attitudes to, and involvement in the [[ecumenical movement]].

==Controversies that have shaped Baptists==
Baptists have faced many controversies in their 400-year history, controversies of the level of crises. Baptist historian Walter Shurden says the word &quot;crisis&quot; comes from the Greek word meaning &quot;to decide.&quot; Shurden writes that contrary to the presumed negative view of crises, some controversies that reach a crisis level may actually be &quot;positive and highly productive.&quot; He claims that even schism, though never ideal, has often produced positive results. In his opinion crises among Baptists each have become decision-moments that shaped their future.&lt;ref name=&quot;Shurden crises&quot;&gt;{{Cite book | last = Shurden | first = Walter B | title = Crises in Baptist Life | accessdate = 16 January 2010 | url = http://www.baptistdistinctives.org/crises.pdf | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20050112160105/http://www.baptistdistinctives.org/crises.pdf | archive-date = 12 January 2005 |url-status = dead| df = dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Some controversies that have shaped Baptists include the &quot;missions crisis&quot;, the &quot;slavery crisis&quot;, the &quot;landmark crisis&quot;, and the &quot;modernist crisis&quot;.

===Missions crisis===
Early in the 19th century, the rise of the modern [[Mission (Christian)|missions]] movement, and the backlash against it, led to widespread and bitter controversy among the American Baptists.{{Sfn | Christian | 1926 | pp = 404–20}}  During this era, the American Baptists were split between missionary and anti-missionary. A substantial secession of Baptists went into the movement led by [[Alexander Campbell (clergyman)|Alexander Campbell]], to return to a more fundamental church.{{Sfn | Christian | 1926 | pp = 421–36}}

===Slavery crisis===
{{see also|Christian views on slavery}}

====United States====
[[File:First Baptist Church, Augusta GA 20160703 1.jpg|thumb|right|upright=0.9|[[First Baptist Church (Augusta, Georgia)|First Baptist Church]] in [[Augusta, Georgia]] where the [[Southern Baptist Convention]] was founded]]
Leading up to the [[American Civil War]], Baptists became embroiled in the controversy over [[slavery in the United States]]. Whereas in the First [[Great Awakening]] [[Methodist]] and Baptist preachers had opposed slavery and urged manumission, over the decades they made more of an accommodation with the institution. They worked with slaveholders in the South to urge a paternalistic institution. Both denominations made direct appeals to slaves and free blacks for conversion. The Baptists particularly allowed them active roles in congregations. By the mid-19th century, northern Baptists tended to oppose slavery. As tensions increased, in 1844 the [[American Baptist Home Mission Society|Home Mission Society]] refused to appoint a slaveholder as a missionary who had been proposed by Georgia. It noted that missionaries could not take servants with them, and also that the board did not want to appear to condone slavery.{{Citation needed|date=July 2018}}

The [[Southern Baptist Convention]] was formed by nine state conventions in 1845. They believed that the Bible sanctions slavery and that it was acceptable for Christians to own slaves. They believed slavery was a human institution which Baptist teaching could make less harsh. By this time many planters were part of Baptist congregations, and some of the denomination's prominent preachers, such as the Rev. [[Basil Manly, Sr.]], president of the [[University of Alabama]], were also [[Plantations in the American South|planters]] who owned slaves.

As early as the late 18th century, black Baptists began to organize separate churches, associations and mission agencies. Blacks set up some independent Baptist congregations in the South before the [[American Civil War]]. White Baptist associations maintained some oversight of these churches.

In the postwar years, [[freedmen]] quickly left the white congregations and associations, setting up their own churches.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|first=Leroy|last=Fitts|title=A History of Black Baptists|pages=43–106|place= Nashville, TN | publisher = Broadman Press|year=1985}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1866 the Consolidated American Baptist Convention, formed from black Baptists of the South and West, helped southern associations set up black state conventions, which they did in [[Alabama]], [[Arkansas]], [[Virginia]], [[North Carolina]], and [[Kentucky]]. In 1880 black state conventions united in the national Foreign Mission Convention, to support black Baptist missionary work. Two other national black conventions were formed, and in 1895 they united as the [[National Baptist Convention, USA, Inc.|National Baptist Convention]]. This organization later went through its own changes, spinning off other conventions. It is the largest black religious organization and the second-largest Baptist organization in the world.&lt;ref&gt;Fitts (1985)&lt;/ref&gt;  Baptists are numerically most dominant in the Southeast.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|publisher=Department of Geography and Meteorology, [[Valparaiso University]] |format=[[GIFF]] |url=http://www.valpo.edu/geomet/pics/geo200/religion/baptist.gif |title=Baptists as a Percentage of all Residents, 2000 |url-status = dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100522053048/http://www.valpo.edu/geomet/pics/geo200/religion/baptist.gif |archivedate=22 May 2010 |df=dmy }}.&lt;/ref&gt;  In 2007, the [[Pew Research Center]]'s Religious Landscape Survey found that 45% of all African Americans identify with Baptist denominations, with the vast majority of those being within the historically black tradition.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=A Religious Portrait of African-Americans| publisher = Pew forum | url= http://www.pewforum.org/A-Religious-Portrait-of-African-Americans.aspx| date = 2009-01-30 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Caribbean islands====
{{quote| A healthy Church kills error, and tears evil in pieces! Not so very long ago our nation tolerated slavery in our colonies. Philanthropists endeavored to destroy slavery, but when was it utterly abolished? It was when [[William Wilberforce|Wilberforce]] roused the Church of God, and when the Church of God addressed herself to the conflict—then she tore the evil thing to pieces! -- [[Charles Spurgeon|C.H. Spurgeon]] an outspoken British Baptist opponent of slavery in 'The Best War Cry' (1883)&lt;ref name=&quot;CHS&quot;&gt;{{cite web| last =Spurgeon |first= Charles | url= http://www.newsforchristians.com/spurgeon/chs1709.html| title= The Best War Cry | date= 4 March 1883 | accessdate= 26 December 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Elsewhere in the Americas, in the Caribbean in particular, Baptist missionaries and members took an active role in the anti-slavery movement. In Jamaica, for example, [[William Knibb]], a prominent British Baptist missionary, worked toward the emancipation of slaves in the [[British West Indies]] (which took place in full in 1838). Knibb also supported the creation of &quot;[[Free Villages]]&quot; and sought funding from English Baptists to buy land for freedmen to cultivate; the Free Villages were envisioned as rural communities to be centred around a Baptist church where emancipated slaves could farm their own land. [[Thomas Burchell]], missionary minister in [[Montego Bay]], also was active in this movement, gaining funds from Baptists in England to buy land for what became known as Burchell Free Village.

Prior to emancipation, Baptist deacon [[Samuel Sharpe]], who served with Burchell, organized a general strike of slaves seeking better conditions. It developed into a major rebellion of as many as 60,000 slaves, which became known as the Christmas Rebellion (when it took place) or the [[Baptist War]]. It was put down by government troops within two weeks. During and after the rebellion, an estimated 200 slaves were killed outright, with more than 300 judicially executed later by prosecution in the courts, sometimes for minor offenses.

Baptists were active after emancipation in promoting the education of former slaves; for example, Jamaica's [[Calabar High School]], named after the port of [[Calabar]] in Nigeria, was founded by Baptist missionaries. At the same time, during and after slavery, slaves and free blacks formed their own [[Spiritual Baptist]] movements - breakaway spiritual movements which theology often expressed resistance to oppression.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|first=Jean|last=Besson|title=Martha Brae's Two Histories | place= Chapel Hill | publisher = University of North Carolina |year=2002}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Memory of slavery===
[[File:Civil Rights March on Washington, D.C. (Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. and Mathew Ahmann in a crowd.) - NARA - 542015 - Restoration.jpg |thumb|[[Martin Luther King Jr.]] at the 1963 civil rights march on Washington, D.C.]]
In the American South, the interpretation of the American Civil War, abolition of slavery and postwar period has differed sharply by race since those years. Americans have often interpreted great events in religious terms. Historian Wilson Fallin contrasts the interpretation of Civil War and Reconstruction in white versus black memory by analyzing Baptist sermons documented in Alabama. Soon after the Civil War, most black Baptists in the South left the Southern Baptist Convention, reducing its numbers by hundreds of thousands or more.{{Citation needed|date=July 2018}} They quickly organized their own congregations and developed their own regional and state associations and, by the end of the 19th century, a national convention.{{Citation needed|date=July 2018}}

White preachers in Alabama after Reconstruction expressed the view that:
{{quote|God had chastised them and given them a special mission – to maintain orthodoxy, strict biblicism, personal piety, and &quot;traditional&quot; race relations. Slavery, they insisted, had not been sinful. Rather, emancipation was a historical tragedy and the end of Reconstruction was a clear sign of God's favor.}}

Black preachers interpreted the Civil War, Emancipation and Reconstruction as:
&quot;God's gift of freedom.&quot; They had a gospel of liberation, having long identified with the [[Book of Exodus]] from slavery in the Old Testament. They took opportunities to exercise their independence, to worship in their own way, to affirm their worth and dignity, and to proclaim the fatherhood of God and the brotherhood of man. Most of all, they quickly formed their own churches, associations, and conventions to operate freely without white supervision. These institutions offered self-help and racial uplift, a place to develop and use leadership, and places for proclamation of the gospel of liberation. As a result, black preachers said that God would protect and help him and God's people; God would be their rock in a stormy land.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson Fallin Jr., ''Uplifting the People: Three Centuries of Black Baptists in Alabama'' (2007) pp. 52-53&lt;/ref&gt;

The Southern Baptist Convention supported white supremacy and its results: [[Disfranchisement after Reconstruction era|disenfranchising most blacks and many poor whites]] at the turn of the 20th century by raising barriers to voter registration, and passage of [[racial segregation]] laws that enforced the system of [[Jim Crow]].{{Citation needed|date=July 2018}} Its members largely resisted the [[civil rights movement]] in the South, which sought to enforce their constitutional rights for public access and voting; and enforcement of midcentury federal civil rights laws.{{Citation needed|date=July 2018}}

On 20 June 1995, the Southern Baptist Convention voted to adopt a resolution renouncing its racist roots and apologizing for its past defense of slavery. More than 20,000 Southern Baptists registered for the meeting in Atlanta. The resolution declared that messengers, as SBC delegates are called, &quot;unwaveringly denounce racism, in all its forms, as deplorable sin&quot; and &quot;lament and repudiate historic acts of evil such as slavery from which we continue to reap a bitter harvest.&quot; It offered an apology to all African Americans for &quot;condoning and/or perpetuating individual and systemic racism in our lifetime&quot; and repentance for &quot;racism of which we have been guilty, whether consciously or unconsciously.&quot;  Although Southern Baptists have condemned racism in the past, this was the first time the convention, predominantly white since the Reconstruction era, had specifically addressed the issue of slavery.

The statement sought forgiveness &quot;from our African-American brothers and sisters&quot; and pledged to &quot;eradicate racism in all its forms from Southern Baptist life and ministry.&quot; In 1995 about 500,000 members of the 15.6-million-member denomination were African Americans and another 300,000 were [[ethnic]] minorities. The resolution marked the denomination's first formal acknowledgment that [[racism]] played a role in its founding.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;SBC renounces racist past – Southern Baptist Convention&quot;, ''The Christian Century.'' 5 July 1995&lt;/ref&gt;

===Landmark crisis===
{{further|Landmarkism}}
Southern Baptist [[Landmarkism]] sought to reset the [[ecclesiastical separation]] which had characterized the old Baptist churches, in an era when inter-denominational union meetings were the order of the day.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Robert|last=Ashcraft | title = Landmarkism Revisited|pages=84–5|publisher=Ashcraft Publications|place=Mabelvale, [[Arkansas|AR]]|year=2003}}.&lt;/ref&gt; [[James Robinson Graves]] was an influential Baptist of the 19th century and the primary leader of this movement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | first = Ben M.|last=Bogard|title=Pillars of Orthodoxy| url = https://archive.org/details/pillarsoforthodo00boga|page=[https://archive.org/details/pillarsoforthodo00boga/page/199 199]|place=Louisville|publisher= Baptist Book Concern|year= 1900}}.&lt;/ref&gt; While some Landmarkers eventually separated from the Southern Baptist Convention, the movement continued to influence the Convention into the 20th and 21st centuries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Smith|last2=Handy|last3=Loetscher|title=American Christianity: An Historical Interpretation With Representative Documents|volume=II: 1820–1960|page= 110|publisher= Charles Scribner's Sons |year= 1963}}.&lt;/ref&gt; For instance, in 2005, the Southern Baptist International Mission Board forbade its missionaries to receive alien immersions for baptism.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |publisher=International Mission Board |title=Guideline on Baptism |url=http://www.imb.org/main/news/details.asp?LanguageID=1709&amp;StoryID=3837 |accessdate= |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110614061746/http://www.imb.org/main/news/details.asp?LanguageID=1709&amp;StoryID=3837 |archive-date=14 June 2011 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Modernist crisis===
{{further|Fundamentalist-Modernist Controversy}}
[[File:Spurgeon.png|right|thumb|upright=0.55|[[Charles Spurgeon]] later in life.]]
The rise of [[Fundamentalist–Modernist Controversy|theological modernism]] in the latter 19th and early 20th centuries also greatly affected Baptists.{{Sfn | Torbet | 1975 | pp = 424–45}}  The Landmark movement, already mentioned, has been described as a reaction among Southern Baptists in the United States against incipient modernism .&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=History of the American Baptist Association|editor1-first=Robert|editor1-last= Ashcraft|pages= 63–6|series= Texarkana|publisher= History and Archives Committee of the American Baptist Association|year=2000}}&lt;/ref&gt; In England, [[Charles Haddon Spurgeon]] fought against modernistic views of the Scripture in the [[Downgrade Controversy]] and severed his church from the Baptist Union as a result.{{Sfn | Torbet | 1975 | p = 114}}&lt;ref name=&quot;downgrade&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|last=Spurgeon |first=Charles |title=The &quot;Down Grade&quot; Controversy |publisher=Pilgrim Publications |location=Pasadena, Texas |page=264 |date=2009 |url=http://www.spurgeon.org/misc/dwngrd.htm |isbn=978-1561862115 |url-status = dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140623204825/http://www.spurgeon.org/misc/dwngrd.htm |archivedate=23 June 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Nettles&quot;&gt;{{Cite book | last = Nettles | first = Tom | title = Living By Revealed Truth The Life and Pastoral Theology of Charles Haddon Spurgeon | publisher = Christian Focus Publishing| location = Ross-shire | pages = 700 | date = 21 July 2013 | isbn =9781781911228 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Northern Baptist Convention]] in the United States had internal conflict over modernism in the early 20th century, ultimately embracing it.{{Sfn | Torbet | 1975 | pp =395, 436}} Two new conservative associations of congregations that separated from the Convention were founded as a result: the [[General Association of Regular Baptist Churches]] in 1933 and the [[Conservative Baptist Association of America]] in 1947.{{Sfn | Torbet | 1975 | pp =395, 436}}

Following similar conflicts over modernism, [[Southern Baptist Convention conservative resurgence|the Southern Baptist Convention adhered to conservative theology]] as its official position.&lt;ref&gt;Hefley, James C., ''The Truth in Crisis, Volume 6: The Conservative Resurgence in the Southern Baptist Convention'', Hannibal Books, 2008. {{ISBN|0-929292-19-7}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;James, Rob B. ''The Fundamentalist Takeover in the Southern Baptist Convention'', 4th ed., Wilkes Publishing, [[Washington, Georgia]].&lt;/ref&gt;  In the late 20th century, Southern Baptists who disagreed with this direction founded two new groups: the liberal [[Alliance of Baptists]] in 1987 and the more moderate [[Cooperative Baptist Fellowship]] in 1991.&lt;ref name = BrackneyBNA138&gt;{{cite book| last =Brackney | first = William H.|title=Baptists in North America: An Historical Perspective|publisher=Wiley |year=2006|isbn=978-1-4051-1865-1 |page=138|url = https://books.google.com/books?id=elSI3WJy1kMC&amp;lpg=PA138&amp;pg=PA138 | accessdate = 16 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| last1 = Mead | first1 = Frank Spencer | first2 = Samuel S | last2 = Hill | first3 = Craig D | last3 = Atwood|title= Handbook of Denominations in the United States|publisher= Abingdon Press |year= 2001 | isbn = 978-0-687-06983-5|page= 46}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last =Leonard | first = Bill J.|title=Baptists in America|publisher=Columbia University Press|year=2007|isbn=978-0-231-12703-5 |page=228}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |accessdate=16 January 2010 |url=http://www.thefellowship.info/About-Us/FAQ |title=CBF History |publisher=Cooperative Baptist Fellowship |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20101130075936/http://thefellowship.info/About-Us/FAQ |archive-date=30 November 2010 |url-status = dead|df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Originally both schisms continued to identify as Southern Baptist, but over time &quot;became permanent new families of Baptists.&quot;&lt;ref name =BrackneyBNA138 /&gt;

==See also==
* [[List of Baptist confessions]]
* [[List of Baptist World Alliance National Fellowships]]
* [[List of Baptist denominations]]
* [[List of Baptists]]
* [[English Dissenters]]
* [[Anabaptists]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Bibliography==
* Beale, David. ''Baptist History in England and America: Personalities, Positions, and Practices.'' Maitland, FL: Xulon Press, 2018. 
* {{Citation | last = Bumstead | first = JM |title=Henry Alline, 1748–1784 |publisher= [[Lancelot Press]] | place = Hantsport, NS |year= 1984}}.
* {{Citation | last = Christian | first = John T | title = History of the Baptists | volume = 2 | place = Nashville | publisher = Broadman Press | year = 1926}}.
* Kidd, Thomas S. and Barry Hankins, ''Baptists in America: A History'' (2015)
* {{Citation | last = Leonard | first = Bill J | title = Baptist Ways: A History |publisher=Judson Press | year = 2003 |isbn= 978-0-8170-1231-1}}, comprehensive international History.
* {{Citation | last = Torbet | first = Robert G | title = A History of the Baptists | location = Valley Forge, PA | publisher = Judson Press | year = 1975 | origyear = 1950 | isbn = 978-0-8170-0074-5 | url = https://archive.org/details/historyofbaptist0000torb }}.
* {{Citation | last = Wright | first = Stephen | title = Early English Baptists 1603–49 | year = 2004}}.

==Further reading==
* Beale, David. ''Baptist History in England and America: Personalities, Positions, and Practices.'' Maitland, FL: Xulon Press, 2018. 
* Bebbington, David. ''Baptists through the Centuries: A History of a Global People'' (Baylor University Press, 2010) emphasis on the United States and Europe; the last two chapters are on the global context.
* Brackney, William H. ''A Genetic History of Baptist Thought: With Special Reference to Baptists in Britain and North America'' (Mercer University Press, 2004), focus on confessions of faith, hymns, theologians, and academics.
* Brackney, William H. ed., ''Historical Dictionary of the Baptists'' (2nd ed. Scarecrow, 2009).
* Cathcart, William, ed. ''The Baptist Encyclopedia'' (2 vols. 1883). [https://archive.org/stream/baptistencyclope02cathuoft#page/n7/mode/2up online]
* Gavins, Raymond. ''The Perils and Prospects of Southern Black Leadership: Gordon Blaine Hancock, 1884–1970.'' Duke University Press, 1977.
* Harrison, Paul M. ''Authority and Power in the Free Church Tradition: A Social Case Study of the American Baptist Convention'' Princeton University Press, 1959.
* Harvey, Paul. ''Redeeming the South: Religious Cultures and Racial Identities among Southern Baptists, 1865–1925'' University of North Carolina Press, 1997.
* Heyrman, Christine Leigh. ''Southern Cross: The Beginnings of the Bible Belt'' (1997).
* Isaac, Rhy. &quot;Evangelical Revolt: The Nature of the Baptists' Challenge to the Traditional Order in Virginia, 1765 to 1775,&quot; ''William and Mary Quarterly,'' 3d ser., XXXI (July 1974), 345–68.
* {{Citation | title = Life &amp; Practice in the Early Church: A Documentary Reader | publisher = New York University press | year = 2001 | pages = 5–7 | isbn = 978-0-8147-5648-5}}.
*Kidd, Thomas S., Barry Hankins, Oxford University Press, 2015
* Leonard, Bill J. ''Baptists in America'' (Columbia University Press, 2005).
* {{cite book|author=Menikoff, Aaron|title=Politics and Piety: Baptist Social Reform in America, 1770-1860|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=2oANBQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PR9|year=2014|publisher=Wipf and Stock Publishers|isbn=9781630872823}}
* Pitts, Walter F. ''Old Ship of Zion: The Afro-Baptist Ritual in the African Diaspora'' Oxford University Press, 1996.
* Rawlyk, George. ''Champions of the Truth: Fundamentalism, Modernism, and the Maritime Baptists'' (1990), Canada.
* Spangler, Jewel L. &quot;Becoming Baptists: Conversion in Colonial and Early National Virginia&quot; ''Journal of Southern History.'' Volume: 67. Issue: 2. 2001. pp.&amp;nbsp;243+
* Stringer, Phil. ''The Faithful Baptist Witness,'' Landmark Baptist Press, 1998.
* Underwood, A. C. ''A History of the English Baptists.'' London: Kingsgate Press, 1947.
* Whitley, William Thomas ''A Baptist Bibliography: being a register of the chief materials for Baptist history, whether in manuscript or in print, preserved in Great Britain, Ireland, and the Colonies''. 2 vols. London: Kingsgate Press, 1916–22 (reissued) Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 1984 {{ISBN|3487074567}}
* {{Cite journal|ref=harv|last=Wilhite|first=David E.|title=The Baptists &quot;And the Son&quot;: The Filioque Clause in Noncreedal Theology|journal=Journal of Ecumenical Studies|year=2009|volume=44|issue=2|pages=285–302|url=https://www.thefreelibrary.com/The+baptists+%22and+the+son%22%3a+the+Filioque+clause+in+noncreedal...-a0205746293}}
* Wills, Gregory A. ''Democratic Religion: Freedom, Authority, and Church Discipline in the Baptist South, 1785–1900,'' Oxford.

===Primary sources===
* McBeth, H. Leon, ed. ''A Sourcebook for Baptist Heritage'' (1990), primary sources for Baptist history.
* McKinion, Steven A., ed. ''Life and Practice in the Early Church: A Documentary Reader'' (2001)
* McGlothlin, W. J., ed. ''Baptist Confessions of Faith.'' Philadelphia: The American Baptist Publication Society, 1911.

==External links==
{{Wikisource portal|Baptists}}
{{commons category|Baptist Christianity}}
{{Portal|Evangelical Christianity|}}
* [https://www.churchfathers.org/infant-baptism/ Early Church Fathers on Baptism]
* [http://www.oxfordbibliographiesonline.com/view/document/obo-9780199730414/obo-9780199730414-0192.xml?rskey=nvgEkL&amp;result=14 Oxford bibliographies: &quot;Baptists&quot; (2015) by Janet Moore Lindman]
* {{Curlie|Society/Religion_and_Spirituality/Christianity/Denominations/Baptist/|Baptists}}

{{Christian History}}
{{Christianity footer}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Baptist Christianity| ]]
[[Category:Christian terminology]]
[[Category:Baptists|*]]
[[Category:Evangelical movement]]</text>
      <sha1>oa7b59enyq3coxzw0m4z54r45gk17i6</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
