  <page>
    <title>Eugenics</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9737</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943043012</id>
      <parentid>943038364</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-28T13:36:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Yaris678</username>
        <id>1210941</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* top */ Remove &quot;by whom&quot; and &quot;cn&quot; on assocition with nazis - The source given talks about the association in Germany. Later sources in the body talk about the association in US.  Remove &quot;major&quot; that was tagged with &quot;quanitify&quot; - I think it is simpler without that word.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{for|the album by Malignancy|Eugenics (album)}}
{{pp-move-indef}}
{{short description| Ethically controversial aims to improve the genetic quality of the human population through selective breeding}}
{{Use dmy dates|date= May 2016}}
[[File:Eugenics congress logo.png|thumb|350px |Logo from the [[Second International Eugenics Conference]], 1921, depicting eugenics as a tree which unites a variety of different fields&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Currell |first= Susan |last2= Cogdell |first2= Christina |title= Popular Eugenics: National Efficiency and American Mass Culture in The 1930s |publisher= [[Ohio University Press]] |date= 2006 |page= 203 |location= Athens, Ohio |isbn= 978-0-8214-1691-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
{{Pseudomedicine sidebar|fringe}}
{{Discrimination sidebar|state=collapsed}}

'''Eugenics''' ({{IPAc-en|j|uː|ˈ|dʒ|ɛ|n|ɪ|k|s}}; from [[Ancient Greek|Greek]] εὐγενής ''eugenes'' - &quot;well-born&quot;)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url= http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/morph?l=eugenes&amp;la=greek#lexicon |title= εὐγενής |work= Greek Word Study Tool |publisher= Tufts University |location= Medford, Massachusetts |date= 2009 |access-date= 19 October 2017}}  Database includes entries from ''[[A Greek–English Lexicon]]'' and other English dictionaries of Ancient Greek.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt; is a set of beliefs and practices that aim to improve  the [[genetics |genetic]] quality of a [[human population]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url= http://ghr.nlm.nih.gov/glossary=eugenics | archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20101016010504/http://ghr.nlm.nih.gov/glossary=eugenics |archive-date= 16 October 2010 |title= Eugenics |work= Unified Medical Language System (Psychological Index Terms) |location= Bethesda, Maryland |publisher= National Library of Medicine |date= 2009&lt;!--Earliest archive date; the &quot;published&quot; date given on the page was auto-generated, ever-changing, and meaningless.--&gt; |url-status= dead |access-date= 19 October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Galton 1904&quot;&gt;{{cite article|title= Eugenics: Its Definition, Scope, and Aims|last= Galton|first= Francis|year= 1904|journal= The American Journal of Sociology |volume= X |issue= 1 |access-date= 1 January 2020 | url= http://galton.org/essays/1900-1911/galton-1904-am-journ-soc-eugenics-scope-aims.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; typically by excluding people and groups judged to be inferior, and promoting those judged to be superior.&lt;ref name=&quot;Spektorowski&quot;/&gt;

The concept predates the term; [[Plato]] suggested applying the principles of [[selective breeding]] to humans around 400&amp;nbsp;BC. Early advocates of eugenics in the 19th century regarded it as a way of improving groups of people. In modern usage, the term ''eugenics'' has close ties to [[scientific racism]] and [[white supremacism]].&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |url= https://www.oxfordbibliographies.com/view/document/obo-9780190280024/obo-9780190280024-0029.xml|title= Eugenics – African American Studies |access-date= 2019-07-25 |website= Oxford Bibliographies}}&lt;/ref&gt; Modern bioethicists who advocate [[new eugenics]] characterise it as a way of enhancing individual traits, regardless of group membership.

While eugenic principles have been practiced as early as [[ancient Greece]], the contemporary [[history of eugenics]] began in the early 20th century, when a popular eugenics movement emerged in the [[United Kingdom]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |jstor= 25054146 |title= Eugenic Ideas, Political Interests and Policy Variance Immigration and Sterilization Policy in Britain and U.S |date= 1 January 2001 |journal= World Politics |doi= 10.1353/wp.2001.0003 |pmid= 18193564 |volume= 53 |issue= 2 |pages= 237–263|last1= Hansen |first1= Randall |last2= King |first2= Desmond }}&lt;/ref&gt; and then spread to many countries, including the [[Eugenics in the United States|United States]], Canada,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url= https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=oBYvAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=TqgFAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=6315,1778929 |title= Sterilization of Unfit Advocated – Feeble-minded Increasing at Disproportionate Rate in Canada – Case for Ungenics |work= The Montreal Gazette |volume= CLXII |issue= 272 |date= 14 November 1933 |via= News.Google.com |access-date= 19 October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; and most European countries. In this period, people from across the political spectrum espoused eugenic ideas. Consequently, many countries adopted eugenic policies, intended to improve the quality of their populations' genetic stock. Such programs included both ''positive'' measures, such as encouraging individuals deemed particularly &quot;fit&quot; to reproduce, and ''negative'' measures, such as marriage prohibitions and [[forced sterilization]] of people deemed unfit for reproduction. Those deemed &quot;unfit to reproduce&quot; often included people with [[Mental disabilites |mental]] or [[physical disabilities]], people who scored in the low ranges on different [[Iq tests |IQ tests]], criminals and &quot;deviants,&quot; and members of disfavored [[minority groups]].

The eugenics movement became associated with [[Nazi Germany]] and the [[Holocaust]] when the defense of many of the defendants at the [[Nuremberg trials]] of 1945 to 1946 attempted to justify their [[human-rights]] abuses by claiming there was little difference between the [[Nazi eugenics]] programs and the [[Eugenics in the United States |U.S. eugenics]] programs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title= The Oxford Handbook of the History of Eugenics |first1= Alison |last1= Bashford |first2= Philippa |last2= Levine |publisher= [[Oxford University Press]] | url= https://books.google.com/?id=g15rfXUA2i8C&amp;pg=PA327&amp;lpg=PA327&amp;dq=eugenics+defense+nuremberg+trials#v=onepage&amp;q=eugenics%20defense%20nuremberg%20trials&amp;f=false |page= 327|isbn= 978-0199706532 |date= 2010-08-03 | access-date = 26 February 2020 | quote = Eugenics was prominent at the Nuremberg trials [...] much was made of the similarity between U.S. and German eugenics by the defense, who argued that German eugenics differed little from that practiced in the United States [...].}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the decades following [[World War II]], with more emphasis on [[human rights]], many countries began to abandon eugenics policies, although some Western countries (the [[Compulsory sterilization#United States| United States]], [[Compulsory sterilization in Canada| Canada]], and [[Sweden]] among them) continued to carry out forced sterilizations.

Since the 1980s and 1990s, with new [[assisted reproductive technology]] procedures available, such as [[gestational surrogacy]] (available since 1985), [[preimplantation genetic diagnosis]] (available since 1989), and [[cytoplasmic transfer]] (first performed in 1996), concern has grown about the possible revival of a more potent form of eugenics after decades of promoting human rights.

A criticism of eugenics policies is that, regardless of whether ''negative'' or ''positive'' policies are used, they are susceptible to abuse because the genetic selection criteria are determined by whichever group has [[political power]] at the time.{{cn|date=February 2020}} Furthermore, many criticize ''negative eugenics'' in particular as a violation of [[basic human rights]], seen (since 1968's Proclamation of Tehran&lt;ref&gt;
[http://www1.umn.edu/humanrts/instree/l2ptichr.htm Proclamation of Tehran, Final Act of the International Conference on Human Rights, Teheran, 22 April to 13 May 1968, U.N. Doc. A/CONF. 32/41 at 3 (1968)], [[United Nations]],  May 1968 - &quot;16. The protection of the family and of the child remains the concern of the international community. Parents have a basic human right to determine freely and responsibly the number and the spacing of their children [...]
&lt;/ref&gt;) as including the [[Reproductive rights | right to reproduce]]. Another criticism is that eugenics policies eventually lead to a loss of [[genetic diversity]], thereby resulting in [[inbreeding depression]] due to a loss of genetic variation. Yet another criticism of contemporary eugenics policies is that they propose to permanently and artificially disrupt millions of years of evolution, and that attempting to create genetic lines &quot;clean&quot; of &quot;disorders&quot; can have far-reaching ancillary downstream effects in the [[genetic ecology]], including negative effects on [[Immunity (medical) | immunity]] and on species [[resilience (disambiguation) | resilience]].

==History==
{{Quote box
 |quote = We put down mad dogs; we kill the wild, untamed ox; we use the knife on sick sheep to stop their infecting the flock; we destroy abnormal offspring at birth; children, too, if they are born weak or deformed, we drown. Yet this is not the work of anger, but of reason – to separate the sound from the worthless.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Seneca |first=Lucius Annaeus |authorlink=Seneca the Younger |year=1995 |title=Seneca: Moral and Political Essays |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=xJmk6NzgawMC |location= |publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]] |page=32  |isbn=978-0-5213-4818-8 |accessdate=2 November 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
 |author = — [[Seneca the Younger]]
 |source =
 |align =
 |width = 20%
}}
{{Main|History of eugenics}}

===Origin and development===

The concept of positive eugenics to produce better human beings has existed at least since [[Plato]] suggested [[Selective breeding|selective mating]] to produce a guardian class.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url= http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/eugenics/ |title=Eugenics |date=2 July 2014 |access-date=2 January 2015 |encyclopedia=Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy |publisher=Center for the Study of Language and Information, Stanford University}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Sparta]], every Spartan child was inspected by the council of elders, the [[Gerousia]], which determined if the child was fit to live or not. In the early years of [[ancient Rome]], a Roman father was [[Twelve Tables|obliged by law]] to immediately kill his child if they were [[Physical disability|physically disabled]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.historyguide.org/ancient/12tables.html The Laws of the Twelve Tables, {{circa|450 BC}}] &quot;A dreadfully deformed child shall be quickly killed&quot;
&lt;/ref&gt; Among the ancient [[Germanic peoples|Germanic]] tribes, people who were cowardly, unwarlike or &quot;stained with abominable vices&quot; were put to death, usually by being drowned in swamps.&lt;ref&gt;[[Tacitus]]. [[s:Germania (Church &amp; Brodribb)#XII|Germania.XII]] &quot;Traitors and deserters are hanged on trees; the coward, the unwarlike, the man stained with abominable vices, is plunged into the mire of the morass, with a hurdle put over him.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Sanders |first=Karin |date=2009 |title=Bodies in the Bog and the Archaeological Imagination |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=FU4H-JKPbhkC&amp;pg=PA62 |location= |publisher=[[University of Chicago Press]] |page=62 |isbn=978-0226734040 |author-link= |quote=Tacitus's Germania, read through this kind of filter, became a manual for racial and sexual eugenics}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Francis Galton 1850s.jpg|thumb|upright|left|[[Francis Galton]] was an early eugenicist, coining the term itself.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first=Francis |last=Galton |authorlink=Francis Galton |date=1874 |url= https://books.google.com/?id=_uE-bpGo2N4C&amp;pg=PA227#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false |title=On men of science, their nature and their nurture |journal=Proceedings of the Royal Institution of Great Britain |volume=7 |pages=227–236}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]

The idea of a modern project of improving the human population through a statistical understanding of [[heredity]] used to encourage good breeding was originally developed by [[Francis Galton]] and, initially, was closely linked to [[Darwinism]] and his theory of [[natural selection]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowler 309&quot;&gt;Bowler, Peter J. (2003). ''Evolution: The History of an Idea,'' 3rd Ed., University of California Press, pp. 308–310.&lt;/ref&gt; Galton had read his half-cousin [[Charles Darwin]]'s theory of [[evolution]], which sought to explain the development of plant and animal species, and desired to apply it to humans. Based on his biographical studies, Galton believed that desirable human qualities were hereditary traits, although Darwin strongly disagreed with this elaboration of his theory.&lt;ref name=&quot;credoreference.com&quot;&gt;{{cite book |chapter=Eugenics |first=Randall |last=Hansen |title=Eugenics: Immigration and Asylum from 1990 to Present |editor-first1=Matthew J. |editor-last1=Gibney |editor-first2=Randall |editor-last2=Hansen |date=2005 |publisher=ABC-CLIO |chapter-url= http://www.credoreference.com/entry/abcmigrate/eugenics |access-date=23 September 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1883, one year after Darwin's death, Galton gave his research a name: ''eugenics''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=DNA: The Secret of Life |first1=Watson |last1=James D. |last2=Berry |first2=Andrew |date=2009 |publisher=Knopf |url= https://www.amazon.com/DNA-The-Secret-Life-ebook/dp/B001PSEQAG}}&lt;/ref&gt; With the introduction of [[genetics]], eugenics became associated with [[genetic determinism]], the belief that human character is entirely or in the majority caused by genes, unaffected by education or living conditions. Many of the early geneticists were not Darwinians, and evolution theory was not needed for eugenics policies based on genetic determinism.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowler 309&quot; /&gt; Throughout its recent history, eugenics has remained controversial.{{sfn|Blom|2008|p=336}}

Eugenics became an academic discipline at many colleges and universities and received funding from many sources.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Allen |first=Garland E. |title=Was Nazi eugenics created in the US? |journal=EMBO Reports |volume=5 |issue=5 |pages=451–452 |date=2004 |doi=10.1038/sj.embor.7400158 |pmc=1299061}}&lt;/ref&gt; Organizations were formed to win public support and sway opinion towards responsible eugenic values in parenthood, including the British [[Galton Institute|Eugenics Education Society]] of 1907 and the [[Society for Biodemography and Social Biology|American Eugenics Society]] of 1921. Both sought support from leading clergymen and modified their message to meet religious ideals.&lt;ref name=&quot;Baker 2014 pp. 281–302&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last=Baker |first=G. J. |title=Christianity and Eugenics: The Place of Religion in the British Eugenics Education Society and the American Eugenics Society, {{circa|1907–1940}} |journal=Social History of Medicine |volume=27 |issue=2 |date=2014 |pages=281–302  |doi=10.1093/shm/hku008 |pmid=24778464 |pmc=4001825 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1909 the Anglican clergymen [[William Inge (priest)|William Inge]] and [[James Peile]] both wrote for the British [[Galton Institute|Eugenics Education Society]]. Inge was an invited speaker at the 1921 [[International Eugenics Conference]], which was also endorsed by the Roman Catholic Archbishop of New York [[Patrick Joseph Hayes]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Baker 2014 pp. 281–302&quot; /&gt; The book ''[[The Passing of the Great Race]]'' (Or, The Racial Basis of European History) by American eugenicist, lawyer, and amateur anthropologist [[Madison Grant]] was published in 1916. Though influential, the book was largely ignored when it first appeared, and it went through several revisions and editions. Nevertheless, the book was used by people who advocated restricted immigration as justification for what became known as “[[scientific racism]]”.&lt;ref&gt;Lindsay, J.A. (1917). [https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2942213/ &quot;''The Passing of the Great Race, or the Racial Basis of European History''{{-&quot;}}], ''The Eugenics Review'' '''9''' (2), pp. 139–141.&lt;/ref&gt;

Three [[International Eugenics Conference]]s presented a global venue for eugenists with meetings in 1912 in London, and in 1921 and 1932 in New York City. Eugenic policies were first implemented in the early 1900s [[Eugenics in the United States|in the United States]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Barrett |first1=Deborah |last2=Kurzman |first2=Charles |title=Globalizing Social Movement Theory: The Case of Eugenics |journal=Theory and Society |volume=33 |issue=5 |pages=487–527 |date=October 2004 |doi=10.1023/b:ryso.0000045719.45687.aa|jstor=4144884 |url= http://kurzman.unc.edu/files/2011/06/Barrett_Kurzman_Eugenics.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; It also took root in France, Germany, and Great Britain.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Hawkins |first=Mike |title=Social Darwinism in European and American Thought |date=1997 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |isbn=978-0-521-57434-1 |pages=62, 292}}&lt;/ref&gt; Later, in the 1920s and 1930s, the eugenic policy of [[compulsory sterilization|sterilizing]] certain mental patients was implemented in other countries including [[Belgium]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=The National Office of Eugenics in Belgium |journal=Science |volume=57 |issue=1463 |page=46 |date=12 January 1923 |doi=10.1126/science.57.1463.46 |bibcode = 1923Sci....57R..46.}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Brazil]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first1=Sales Augusto |last1=dos Santos |first2=Laurence |last2=Hallewell |date=January 2002 |title=Historical Roots of the 'Whitening' of Brazil |journal=Latin American Perspectives |volume=29 |issue=1 |pages=61–82 |jstor=3185072 |doi=10.1177/0094582X0202900104}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Compulsory sterilization in Canada|Canada]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=McLaren |first=Angus |title=Our Own Master Race: Eugenics in Canada, 1885–1945 |publisher=Oxford University Press |date=1990 |isbn=978-0-7710-5544-7 |url-access=registration |url=https://archive.org/details/ourownmasterrace0000mcla }}{{page needed|date=June 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Eugenics in Japan|Japan]] and [[Compulsory sterilisation in Sweden|Sweden]]. [[Frederick Osborn]]'s 1937 journal article &quot;Development of a Eugenic Philosophy&quot; framed it as a [[social philosophy]]—a philosophy with implications for [[social order]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Osborn1937&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Osborn|first=Frederick|author-link=Frederick Osborn|date=June 1937|title=Development of a Eugenic Philosophy|journal=[[American Sociological Review]]|volume=2|issue=3|pages=389–397|doi=10.2307/2084871|jstor=2084871}}&lt;/ref&gt; That definition is not universally accepted. Osborn advocated for higher rates of [[sexual reproduction]] among people with desired traits (&quot;positive eugenics&quot;) or reduced rates of sexual reproduction or [[Sterilization (medicine)|sterilization]] of people with less-desired or undesired traits (&quot;negative eugenics&quot;).

[[File:Gilbert Chesterton.jpg|thumb|upright=.9|[[G. K. Chesterton]], an opponent of eugenics, in 1909, by photographer Ernest Herbert Mills]]

In addition to being practiced in a number of countries, eugenics was internationally organized through the [[International Federation of Eugenics Organizations]].{{sfn|Black|2003|p=240}} Its scientific aspects were carried on through research bodies such as the [[Kaiser Wilhelm Institute of Anthropology, Human Heredity, and Eugenics]],{{sfn|Black|2003|p=286}} the Cold Spring Harbour Carnegie Institution for [[Experimental Evolution]],{{sfn|Black|2003|p=40}} and the [[Eugenics Record Office]].{{sfn|Black|2003|p=45}} Politically, the movement advocated measures such as sterilization laws.{{sfn|Black|2003|loc=Chapter 6: The United States of Sterilization}} In its moral dimension, eugenics rejected the doctrine that all human beings are born equal and redefined moral worth purely in terms of genetic fitness.{{sfn|Black|2003|p=237}} Its racist elements included pursuit of a pure &quot;[[Nordic race]]&quot; or &quot;[[Aryan]]&quot; genetic pool and the eventual elimination of &quot;unfit&quot; races.{{sfn|Black|2003|loc=Chapter 5: Legitimizing Raceology}}{{sfn|Black|2003|loc=Chapter 9: Mongrelization}} Many leading British politicians subscribed to the theories of eugenics. Winston Churchill supported the British Eugenics Society and was an honorary vice president for the organization. Churchill believed that eugenics could solve &quot;race deterioration&quot; and reduce crime and poverty.&lt;ref&gt;Blom, P. (2009). ''The Vertigo Years: Change and Culture in the West, 1900-1914'' (Toronto, ON: McClelland &amp; Stewart).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Jones, S. (1995). ''The Language of Genes: Solving the Mysteries of Our Genetic Past, Present and Future'' (New York, NY: Anchor).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;King, D. (1999). ''In the name of liberalism: illiberal social policy in Britain and the United States'' (Oxford: Oxford University Press).&lt;/ref&gt;

Early critics of the philosophy of eugenics included the American sociologist [[Lester Frank Ward]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=Joan |last=Ferrante |title=Sociology: A Global Perspective |url= https://books.google.com/?id=AwnIIXI6y38C&amp;pg=PA259 |date=2010 |publisher=Cengage Learning |isbn=978-0-8400-3204-1 |pages=259 ff}}&lt;/ref&gt; the English writer [[G. K. Chesterton]], the German-American anthropologist [[Franz Boas]], who argued that advocates of eugenics greatly over-estimate the influence of biology,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Turda |first=Marius |chapter=Race, Science and Eugenics in the Twentieth Century |editor1-last=Bashford |editor1-first=Alison |editor2-last=Levine |editor2-first=Philippa |title=The Oxford Handbook of the History of Eugenics |publisher=Oxford University Press |date=2010 |isbn=978-0-19-988829-0 |pages=72–73}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Scottish tuberculosis pioneer and author [[Halliday Sutherland]]. Ward's 1913 article &quot;[https://archive.org/details/jstor-2763324 Eugenics, Euthenics, and Eudemics]&quot;, Chesterton's 1917 book ''[[s:Eugenics and other Evils|Eugenics and Other Evils]]'', and Boas' 1916 article &quot;[[s:Eugenics|Eugenics]]&quot; (published in ''[[The Scientific Monthly]]'') were all harshly critical of the rapidly growing movement. Sutherland identified eugenists as a major obstacle to the eradication and cure of tuberculosis in his 1917 address &quot;Consumption: Its Cause and Cure&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Consumption: Its Cause and Cure&quot; – an address by Dr Halliday Sutherland on 4 September 1917, published by the Red Triangle Press.&lt;/ref&gt; and criticism of eugenists and Neo-[[Malthusianism|Malthusians]] in his 1921 book ''Birth Control'' led to a writ for libel from the eugenist [[Marie Stopes]]. Several biologists were also antagonistic to the eugenics movement, including [[Lancelot Hogben]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Lancelot Hogben, who developed his critique of eugenics and distaste for racism in the period...he spent as Professor of Zoology at the University of Cape Town&quot;.  Alison Bashford and Philippa Levine, ''The Oxford Handbook of the History of Eugenics''. Oxford; Oxford University Press, 2010 {{ISBN|0199706530}} (p. 200)&lt;/ref&gt; Other biologists such as [[J. B. S. Haldane]] and [[Ronald Fisher|R. A. Fisher]] expressed skepticism in the belief that sterilization of &quot;defectives&quot; would lead to the disappearance of undesirable genetic traits.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Whatever their disagreement on the numbers, Haldane, Fisher, and most geneticists could support Jennings's warning: To encourage the expectation that the sterilization of defectives will solve the problem of hereditary defects, close up the asylums for feebleminded and insane, do away with prisons, is only to subject society to deception&quot;. Daniel J. Kevles (1985). ''In the Name of Eugenics''. University of California Press. {{ISBN|0520057635}} (p. 166).&lt;/ref&gt;

Among institutions, the [[Catholic Church]] was an opponent of state-enforced sterilizations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Congar |first=Yves M.-J. |date=1953 |title=The Catholic Church and the Race Question |url= http://unesdoc.unesco.org/images/0000/000028/002893eo.pdf |location=Paris, France |publisher=UNESCO |access-date=3 July 2015 |quote=4. The State is not entitled to deprive an individual of his procreative power simply for material (eugenic) purposes. But it is entitled to isolate individuals who are sick and whose progeny would inevitably be seriously tainted.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Attempts by the Eugenics Education Society to persuade the British government to legalize voluntary sterilization were opposed by Catholics and by the [[Labour Party (UK)|Labour Party]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Ml4vDwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA105 |title=The Oxford Handbook of the History of Eugenics|first1=Alison|last1=Bashford|first2=Philippa|last2=Levine|date= 2010|publisher=Oxford University Press, US|via=Google Books|isbn=9780195373141}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Society for Biodemography and Social Biology|American Eugenics Society]] initially gained some Catholic supporters, but Catholic support declined following the 1930 papal encyclical ''[[Casti connubii]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Baker 2014 pp. 281–302&quot; /&gt; In this, [[Pope Pius XI]] explicitly condemned sterilization laws: &quot;Public magistrates have no direct power over the bodies of their subjects; therefore, where no crime has taken place and there is no cause present for grave punishment, they can never directly harm, or tamper with the integrity of the body, either for the reasons of eugenics or for any other reason.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/pius_xi/encyclicals/documents/hf_p-xi_enc_31121930_casti-connubii_en.html |title=Casti connubii|author=Pope Pius XI}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As a social movement, eugenics reached its greatest popularity in the early decades of the 20th century, when it was practiced around the world and promoted by governments, institutions, and influential individuals. Many countries enacted&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Ridley |first=Matt |author-link=Matt Ridley |title=Genome: The Autobiography of a Species in 23 Chapters |date=1999 |publisher=HarperCollins |location=New York |isbn=978-0-06-089408-5 |pages=290–291}}&lt;/ref&gt; various eugenics policies, including: genetic screenings, [[birth control]], promoting differential birth rates, [[Marriage law#Marriage restrictions|marriage restrictions]], segregation (both [[racial segregation]] and sequestering the mentally ill), [[compulsory sterilization]], [[forced abortion]]s or [[forced pregnancies]], ultimately culminating in [[genocide]]. By 2014, gene selection (rather than &quot;people selection&quot;) was made possible through advances in [[genome editing]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Reis|first1=Alex|last2=Hornblower|first2=Breton|last3=Robb|first3=Brett|last4=Tzertzinis|first4=George|date=2014|title=CRISPR/Cas9 and Targeted Genome Editing: A New Era in Molecular Biology|url=https://www.neb.com/tools-and-resources/feature-articles/crispr-cas9-and-targeted-genome-editing-a-new-era-in-molecular-biology|journal=NEB Expressions|issue=I|access-date=8 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; leading to what is sometimes called ''[[new eugenics]]'', also known as &quot;neo-eugenics&quot;, &quot;consumer eugenics&quot;, or &quot;liberal eugenics&quot;.

===Nazism and the decline of eugenics===
[[File:Alkoven Schloss Hartheim 2005-08-18 3589.jpg|thumb|[[Schloss Hartheim]], a former euthanasia center (2005)]]
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 146-1973-010-11, Schwester in einem Lebensbornheim.jpg|220px|thumb|upright|A ''[[Lebensborn]]'' birth house in Nazi Germany. Created with the intention of raising the birth rate of &quot;[[Aryan race|Aryan]]&quot; children from the extramarital relations of &quot;racially pure and healthy&quot; parents.]]
{{Main|Nazi eugenics}}

The scientific reputation of eugenics started to decline in the 1930s, a time when [[Ernst Rüdin]] used eugenics as a justification for the [[Racial policy of Nazi Germany|racial policies of Nazi Germany]]. [[Adolf Hitler]] had praised and incorporated eugenic ideas in ''[[Mein Kampf]]'' in 1925 and emulated eugenic legislation for the sterilization of &quot;defectives&quot; that had been pioneered in the United States once he took power.{{sfn|Black|2003|pp=274–295}} Some common early 20th century eugenics methods involved identifying and classifying individuals and their families, including the poor, mentally ill, blind, deaf, developmentally disabled, [[promiscuous women]], homosexuals, and [[Race (classification of human beings)|racial groups]] (such as the [[Romani people|Roma]] and [[Jews in Nazi Germany]]) as &quot;degenerate&quot; or &quot;unfit&quot;, and therefore led to segregation, institutionalization, sterilization, [[euthanasia]], and even [[mass murder]].{{sfn|Black|2003}} The Nazi practice of euthanasia was carried out on hospital patients in the [[Aktion T4]] centers such as [[Hartheim Castle]].

By the end of [[World War II]], many eugenics laws were abandoned, having become associated with [[Nazi Germany]].{{sfn|Black|2003}} [[H. G. Wells]], who had called for &quot;the sterilization of failures&quot; in 1904,&lt;ref name=&quot;jt&quot;&gt;{{cite book |first=Jacky |last=Turner |title=Animal Breeding, Welfare and Society |publisher=Routledge |date=2010 |isbn=978-1844075898 |page=296}}&lt;/ref&gt; stated in his 1940 book ''The Rights of Man: Or What are we fighting for?'' that among the [[human rights]], which he believed should be available to all people, was &quot;a prohibition on [[mutilation]], sterilization, [[torture]], and any bodily punishment&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=Andrew |last=Clapham |title=Human Rights: A Very Short Introduction |publisher=Oxford University Press |date=2007 |isbn=978-0199205523 |pages=[https://archive.org/details/humanrights00andr/page/29 29–31] |url=https://archive.org/details/humanrights00andr/page/29 }}&lt;/ref&gt; After World War II, the practice of &quot;imposing measures intended to prevent births within [a national, ethnical, racial or religious] group&quot; fell within the definition of the new international crime of genocide, set out in the [[Convention on the Prevention and Punishment of the Crime of Genocide]].&lt;ref&gt;Article 2 of the Convention defines genocide as any of the following acts committed with [[Genocide#Genocide as a crime|the intent to destroy, in whole or in part]], a national, ethnic, racial or religious group, as such as:
* Killing members of the group;
* Causing serious bodily or mental harm to members of the group;
* Deliberately inflicting on the group conditions of life calculated to bring about its physical destruction in whole or in part;
* Imposing measures intended to prevent births within the group;
* Forcibly transferring children of the group to another group.
See the [[Convention on the Prevention and Punishment of the Crime of Genocide]].&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Charter of Fundamental Rights of the European Union]] also proclaims &quot;the prohibition of eugenic practices, in particular those aiming at selection of persons&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |url= https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Charter_of_Fundamental_Rights_of_the_European_Union |title=Charter of Fundamental Rights of the European Union |at=Article 3, Section 2}}&lt;/ref&gt; In spite of the decline in discriminatory eugenics laws, some government mandated sterilizations continued into the 21st century. During the ten years President [[Alberto Fujimori]] led Peru from 1990 to 2000, 2,000 persons were allegedly involuntarily sterilized.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.cnn.com/2014/01/25/world/americas/peru-sterilization/ |title= Peru will not prosecute former President over sterilization campaign |first1=Pierre |last1= Meilhan |first2=Ben |last2= Brumfield |lastauthoramp=yes|date=25 January 2014 |website= CNN.com |publisher= [[CNN]] |access-date= 19 October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[China]] maintained its [[one-child policy]] until 2015 as well as a suite of other eugenics based legislation to reduce population size and manage fertility rates of different populations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Dikötter |first=F. |date=1998 |title=Imperfect Conceptions: Medical Knowledge, Birth Defects, and Eugenics in China |publisher=Columbia University Press}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |work=Edge |first=Geoffrey |last=Miller |title=2013: What {{em|Should}} We Be Worried About? Chinese Eugenics |access-date=30 August 2014 |date=2013 |publisher=Edge Foundation |url= http://edge.org/response-detail/23838/}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Dikötter |first=F. |date=1999 |title='The legislation imposes decisions': Laws about eugenics in China |journal=UNESCO Courier |volume=1 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2007 the [[United Nations]] reported coercive sterilizations and hysterectomies in [[Uzbekistan]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |work=BBC News |title=Uzbekistan's policy of secretly sterilizing women |date=12 April 2012 |access-date=30 August 2014 |url= https://www.bbc.com/news/magazine-17612550 |first=Natalia |last=Antelava}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the years 2005 to 2013, nearly one-third of the 144 California prison inmates who were sterilized did not give lawful consent to the operation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Johnson |first=Corey G. |date=20 June 2014 |title=Calif. female inmates sterilized illegally |url= https://www.usatoday.com/story/news/nation-now/2014/06/20/california-female-inmates-sterilized/11037129/ |work=[[USA Today]] |access-date=30 August 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Modern resurgence of interest===
Developments in [[Genetic engineering|genetic]], [[Genetic testing|genomic]], and [[Human cloning|reproductive technologies]] at the end of the 20th century have raised numerous questions regarding the ethical status of eugenics, effectively creating a [[History of eugenics#Modern eugenics, genetic engineering, and ethical re-evaluation|resurgence of interest]] in the subject.
Some, such as [[UC Berkeley]] sociologist [[Troy Duster]], claim that modern genetics is a back door to eugenics.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Epstein |first=Charles J. |title=Is modern genetics the new eugenics? |journal=Genetics in Medicine |date=1 November 2003 |volume=5 |issue=6 |pages=469–475 |doi=10.1097/01.GIM.0000093978.77435.17 |pmid=14614400 }}&lt;/ref&gt; This view is shared by White House Assistant Director for Forensic Sciences, [[Tania Simoncelli]], who stated in a 2003 publication by the Population and Development Program at [[Hampshire College]] that advances in [[pre-implantation genetic diagnosis]] (PGD) are moving society to a &quot;new era of eugenics&quot;, and that, unlike the Nazi eugenics, modern eugenics is consumer driven and market based, &quot;where children are increasingly regarded as made-to-order consumer products&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first=Tania |last=Simoncelli |author-link=Tania Simoncelli |title=Pre-implantation Genetic Diagnosis and Selection: From disease prevention to customised conception |journal=Different Takes |volume=24 |date=2003 |url=http://genetics.live.radicaldesigns.org/downloads/200303_difftakes_simoncelli.pdf |access-date=18 September 2013 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131018034037/http://genetics.live.radicaldesigns.org/downloads/200303_difftakes_simoncelli.pdf |archivedate=18 October 2013 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; In a 2006 newspaper article, [[Richard Dawkins]] said that discussion regarding eugenics was inhibited by the shadow of Nazi misuse, to the extent that some scientists would not admit that breeding humans for certain abilities is at all possible. He believes that it is not physically different from breeding domestic animals for traits such as speed or herding skill. Dawkins felt that enough time had elapsed to at least ask just what the ethical differences were between breeding for ability versus training athletes or forcing children to take music lessons, though he could think of persuasive reasons to draw the distinction.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=From the Afterward |first=Richard |last=Dawkins |author-link=Richard Dawkins |work=[[The Herald (Glasgow)|The Herald]] |location=Glasgow |date=2006 |url= http://www.heraldscotland.com/from-the-afterword-1.836155 |access-date=17 October 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Lee Kuan Yew]], the [[Founding Father]] of [[Singapore]], started promoting eugenics as early as 1983.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.blynkt.com/issue-1/eugenics-in-postcolonial-singapore |title=Eugenics in Postcolonial Singapore |first=Ying-kit |last=Chan |date=4 October 2016 |website=Blynkt.com |location=Berlin |access-date=19 October 2017 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171008232753/http://www.blynkt.com/issue-1/eugenics-in-postcolonial-singapore |archive-date=8 October 2017 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= https://mustsharenews.com/lee-kuan-yew-controversies/ |title=13 Controversies of Lee Kuan Yew |date=10 March 2015 |author=&lt;!--Staff writers; no specific by-line.--&gt; |website=MustShareNews.com |location=Singapore |access-date=19 October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In October 2015, the United Nations' [[International Bioethics Committee]] wrote that the ethical problems of [[human genetic engineering]] should not be confused with the ethical problems of the [[History of eugenics|20th century eugenics movements]]. However, it is still problematic because it challenges the idea of human equality and opens up new forms of discrimination and stigmatization for those who do not want, or cannot afford, the technology.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |publisher=International Bioethics Committee |title=Report of the IBC on Updating Its Reflection on the Human Genome and Human Rights |url= http://unesdoc.unesco.org/images/0023/002332/233258E.pdf |date=2 October 2015 |access-date=22 October 2015 |page=27 |quote=The goal of enhancing individuals and the human species by engineering the genes related to some characteristics and traits is not to be confused with the barbarous projects of eugenics that planned the simple elimination of human beings considered as ‘imperfect’ on an ideological basis. However, it impinges upon the principle of respect for human dignity in several ways. It weakens the idea that the differences among human beings, regardless of the measure of their endowment, are exactly what the recognition of their equality presupposes and therefore protects. It introduces the risk of new forms of discrimination and stigmatization for those who cannot afford such enhancement or simply do not want to resort to it. The arguments that have been produced in favour of the so-called liberal eugenics do not trump the indication to apply the limit of medical reasons also in this case.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Transhumanism]] is often associated with eugenics, although most transhumanists holding similar views nonetheless distance themselves from the term &quot;eugenics&quot; (preferring &quot;[[germinal choice]]&quot; or &quot;[[reprogenetics]]&quot;)&lt;ref name=&quot;Silver 1998&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Silver |first=Lee M. |author-link=Lee M. Silver |title=Remaking Eden: Cloning and Beyond in a Brave New World |publisher=Harper Perennial |date=1998 |isbn=978-0-380-79243-6 |oclc=40094564 |url=https://archive.org/details/remakingeden00leem }}&lt;/ref&gt; to avoid having their position confused with the discredited theories and practices of early-20th-century eugenic movements.

[[Prenatal diagnosis|Prenatal screening]] can be considered a form of contemporary eugenics because it may lead to abortions of children with undesirable traits.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Thomas |first=Gareth M. |last2=Rothman |first2=Barbara Katz |date=April 2016 |title=Keeping the Backdoor to Eugenics Ajar?: Disability and the Future of Prenatal Screening |journal=AMA Journal of Ethics |volume=18 |issue=4 |pages=406–415 |doi= 10.1001/journalofethics.2016.18.4.stas1-1604|pmid=27099190 |quote=We argue that prenatal screening (and specifically NIPT) for Down syndrome can be considered a form of contemporary eugenics, in that it effaces, devalues, and possibly prevents the births of people with the condition.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The State of California Legislature and Governor passed a form of negative eugenics into law via SB 1095 (2016), resulting in a State law requiring the screening for &quot;any disease&quot; (...) &quot;detectable in the blood&quot; prior to birth.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=SB-1095 – Newborn Screening Program |first1=Richard |last1=Pan |publisher=[[State of California]] |url=http://leginfo.legislature.ca.gov/faces/billTextClient.xhtml?bill_id=201520160SB1095 |date=2019-02-18 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The bill, still law in California, has been widely regarded as a form of [[scientific racism]], though its proponents continue to claim that it is necessary.{{citation needed|date=July 2019}} A system was proposed by California Senator Skinner to compensate victims of the well-documented examples of prison sterilizations resulting from California's eugenics programs, but this did not pass by the bill's 2018 deadline in the Legislature.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=SB-1190 – Eugenics Sterilization Compensation Program |first1=Nancy |last1=Skinner |publisher=[[State of California]] |url=https://leginfo.legislature.ca.gov/faces/billTextClient.xhtml?bill_id=201720180SB1190 |date=2019-02-18 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Meanings and types==

The term ''eugenics'' and its modern field of study were first formulated by Francis Galton in 1883,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Galton |first=Francis |author-link=Francis Galton |title=Inquiries into Human Faculty and its Development |url=https://archive.org/details/inquiriesintohu00galtgoog |publisher=[[Macmillan Publishers]] |date=1883 |location=London |page=199}}&lt;/ref&gt; drawing on the recent work of his half-cousin [[Charles Darwin]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://galton.org/letters/darwin/correspondence.htm |title=Correspondence between Francis Galton and Charles Darwin |publisher=Galton.org |access-date=28 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/correspondence-volume-17 |work=Darwin Correspondence Project |title=The Correspondence of Charles Darwin |volume=Volume 17: 1869 |publisher=University of Cambridge |access-date=28 November 2011 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120124215918/http://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/correspondence-volume-17 |archivedate=24 January 2012 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Galton published his observations and conclusions in his book ''[[Inquiries into Human Faculty and Its Development]]''.

The origins of the concept began with certain interpretations of [[Mendelian inheritance]] and the theories of [[August Weismann]].{{sfn|Blom|2008|pp=335–336}} The word ''eugenics'' is derived from the [[Greek language|Greek]] word ''eu'' (&quot;good&quot; or &quot;well&quot;) and the suffix ''-genēs'' (&quot;born&quot;); Galton intended it to replace the word &quot;[[Oneida stirpiculture|stirpiculture]]&quot;, which he had used previously but which had come to be mocked due to its perceived sexual overtones.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first1=Lester Frank |last1=Ward |first2=Emily |last2=Palmer Cape |first3=Sarah Emma |last3=Simons |title=Glimpses of the Cosmos |chapter-url= https://books.google.com/?id=KDEZAQAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA382 |access-date=11 April 2012 |date=1918 |publisher=G.P. Putnam|pages=382 ff|chapter=Eugenics, Euthenics and Eudemics}}&lt;/ref&gt; Galton defined eugenics as &quot;the study of all agencies under human control which can improve or impair the racial quality of future generations&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Cited in {{harvnb|Black|2003|p=18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Historically, the term ''eugenics'' has referred to everything from [[prenatal care]] for mothers to forced sterilization and euthanasia.&lt;ref name=&quot;Spektorowski&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last1=Spektorowski |first1=Alberto |last2=Ireni-Saban |first2=Liza |title=Politics of Eugenics: Productionism, Population, and National Welfare |date=2013 |publisher=Routledge |location=London |isbn=978-0-203-74023-1 |page=24 |url= https://books.google.com/?id=zdkdAAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA24&amp;lpg=PA24&amp;dq=Historically,+the+term+has+referred+to+everything+from+prenatal+care+for+mothers+to+forced+sterilization+and+euthanasia#v=onepage&amp;q=Historically%2C%20the%20term%20has%20referred%20to%20everything%20from%20prenatal%20care%20for%20mothers%20to%20forced%20sterilization%20and%20euthanasia&amp;f=false |access-date=16 January 2017 |quote=As an applied science, thus, the practice of eugenics referred to everything from prenatal care for mothers to forced sterilization and euthanasia.  Galton divided the practice of eugenics into two types—positive and negative—both aimed at improving the human race through selective breeding.}}&lt;/ref&gt; To [[Population genetics|population geneticists]], the term has included the avoidance of [[inbreeding]] without altering [[Allele frequency|allele frequencies]]; for example, [[J. B. S. Haldane]] wrote that &quot;the motor bus, by breaking up inbred village communities, was a powerful eugenic agent.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Haldane |first=J. |title=Lysenko and Genetics |journal=Science and Society |volume=4 |issue=4 |date=1940 |url= http://www.marxists.org/archive/haldane/works/1940s/lysenko.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; Debate as to what exactly counts as eugenics continues today.&lt;ref&gt;A discussion of the shifting meanings of the term can be found in {{cite book |last=Paul |first=Diane |title=Controlling Human Heredity: 1865 to the Present |publisher=Humanities Press |location=New Jersey |date=1995 |isbn=978-1-57392-343-9 |url=https://archive.org/details/controllinghuman00paul }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Edwin Black]], journalist and author of ''War Against the Weak'', claims eugenics is often deemed a [[pseudoscience]] because what is defined as a genetic improvement of a desired trait is often deemed a cultural choice rather than a matter that can be determined through objective scientific inquiry.{{sfn|Black|2004|p=370}} The most disputed aspect of eugenics has been the definition of &quot;improvement&quot; of the human gene pool, such as what is a beneficial characteristic and what is a defect. Historically, this aspect of eugenics was tainted with [[scientific racism]] and pseudoscience.{{sfn|Black|2004|p=370}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Worrall |first=Simon |title=The Gene: Science's Most Dangerous Idea |url= http://news.nationalgeographic.com/2016/07/gene-history-siddhartha-mukherjee-science-eugenics/|work=National Geographic|date=24 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=White |first=Susan |title=LibGuides: The Sociology of Science and Technology: Pseudoscience |url= http://libguides.princeton.edu/c.php?g=84711&amp;p=4441670 |publisher=Library of University of Princeton |access-date=12 September 2017 |date=28 June 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Karl Pearson, 1912.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Karl Pearson]] in 1912]]

Early eugenicists were mostly concerned with factors of perceived [[intelligence (trait)|intelligence]] that often correlated strongly with social class. These included [[Karl Pearson]] and [[Walter Weldon]], who worked on this at the [[University College London]].&lt;ref name=&quot;credoreference.com&quot;/&gt;

Eugenics also had a place in medicine. In his lecture &quot;Darwinism, Medical Progress and Eugenics&quot;, Karl Pearson said that everything concerning eugenics fell into the field of medicine. He basically placed the two words as equivalents. He was supported in part by the fact that Francis Galton, the father of eugenics, also had medical training.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Salgirli |first=S. G. |title=Eugenics for the doctors: Medicine and social control in 1930s Turkey |journal=Journal of the History of Medicine and Allied Sciences |volume=66 |issue=3 |pages=281–312 |date=July 2011 |pmid=20562206 |doi=10.1093/jhmas/jrq040}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Eugenic policies have been conceptually divided into two categories.&lt;ref name=&quot;Spektorowski&quot;/&gt; Positive eugenics is aimed at encouraging reproduction among the genetically advantaged; for example, the reproduction of the intelligent, the healthy, and the successful. Possible approaches include financial and political stimuli, targeted demographic analyses, ''in vitro'' fertilization, egg transplants, and cloning.&lt;ref name=&quot;glad2008&quot;&gt;{{cite book |first=John |last=Glad |author-link=John Glad |title=Future Human Evolution: Eugenics in the Twenty-First Century |publisher=Hermitage Publishers |date=2008 |isbn=978-1-55779-154-2 |url=https://archive.org/details/futurehumanevolu00glad }}&lt;/ref&gt; The movie ''[[Gattaca]]'' provides a fictional example of a dystopian society that uses eugenics to decide what people are capable of and their place in the world. Negative eugenics aimed to eliminate, through sterilization or segregation, those deemed physically, mentally, or morally &quot;undesirable&quot;. This includes abortions, sterilization, and other methods of family planning.&lt;ref name = &quot;glad2008&quot;/&gt; Both positive and negative eugenics can be coercive; abortion for [[Fitness (biology)|fit]] women, for example, was illegal in Nazi Germany.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Pine |first=Lisa |title=Nazi Family Policy, 1933–1945 |url= https://books.google.com/?id=nW2aE5-rAMsC&amp;pg=PA19 |access-date=11 April 2012 |date=1997 |publisher=Berg |isbn=978-1-85973-907-5 |pages=19 ff}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Jon Entine]] claims that ''eugenics'' simply means &quot;good genes&quot; and using it as synonym for genocide is an &quot;all-too-common distortion of the social history of genetics policy in the United States&quot;. According to Entine, eugenics developed out of the [[Progressive Era]] and not &quot;Hitler's twisted [[Final Solution]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.huffingtonpost.com/jon-entine/lets-cautiously-celebrate_b_6070462.html |title=Let's (Cautiously) Celebrate the 'New Eugenics' |first=John |last=Entine |date=30 December 2014 |work=The Huffington Post |access-date=2 May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Scientific and moral legitimacy==
===Scientific validity===
The first major challenge to conventional eugenics based on genetic inheritance was made in 1915 by [[Thomas Hunt Morgan]]. He demonstrated the event of [[Mutation|genetic mutation]] occurring outside of inheritance involving the discovery of the hatching of a [[Drosophila melanogaster|fruit fly (''Drosophila melanogaster'')]] with white eyes from a family with red eyes,{{sfn|Blom|2008|pp=336–337}} demonstrating that major genetic changes occurred outside of inheritance.{{sfn|Blom|2008|pp=336–337}} Additionally, Morgan criticized the view that certain traits, such as intelligence and criminality, were hereditary because these traits were [[Subjectivity|subjective]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.eugenicsarchive.org/html/eugenics/essay5text.html|title=Social Origins of Eugenics|website=Eugenicsarchive.org|accessdate=19 October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite Morgan's public rejection of eugenics, much of his genetic research was adopted by proponents of eugenics.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Scientific Origins of Eugenics |first=Elof Axel |last=Carlson |url= http://www.eugenicsarchive.org/html/eugenics/essay2text.html |access-date=3 October 2013 |work=Image Archive on the American Eugenics Movement |publisher=Dolan DNA Learning Center, Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory |date=2002}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=Retrospectives: Eugenics and Economics in the Progressive Era |first=Thomas C. (Tim) |last=Leonard |journal=Journal of Economic Perspectives |volume=19 |issue=4 |date=Fall 2005 |pages=207–224 |url= https://www.princeton.edu/~tleonard/papers/retrospectives.pdf |access-date=3 October 2013 |doi=10.1257/089533005775196642}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Zygosity|heterozygote]] [[Carrier testing|test]] is used for the early detection of [[Recessive trait|recessive]] hereditary diseases, allowing for couples to determine if they are at risk of passing genetic defects to a future child.&lt;ref name = &quot;drze&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.drze.de/in-focus/predictive-genetic-testing/modules/heterozygote-test-screening-programmes|title=Heterozygote test / Screening programmes — DRZE|website=Drze.de|accessdate=19 October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; The goal of the test is to estimate the likelihood of passing the hereditary disease to future descendants.&lt;ref name = &quot;drze&quot;/&gt;

Recessive traits can be severely reduced, but never eliminated unless the complete genetic makeup of all members of the pool was known, as aforementioned. As only very few undesirable traits, such as Huntington's disease, are dominant, it could be argued{{by whom|date=November 2014}} from certain perspectives that the practicality of &quot;eliminating&quot; traits is quite low.{{citation needed|date=October 2010}}

There are examples of eugenic acts that managed to lower the prevalence of recessive diseases, although not influencing the prevalence of heterozygote carriers of those diseases. The elevated prevalence of certain genetically transmitted diseases among the [[Ashkenazi Jew]]ish population ([[Tay–Sachs disease|Tay–Sachs]], [[cystic fibrosis]], [[Canavan's disease]], and [[Gaucher's disease]]), has been decreased in current populations by the application of genetic screening.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.jewishpress.com/page.do/18624/The_Book_Shelf.html |title=Fatal Gift: Jewish Intelligence and Western Civilization |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20090813162344/http://www.jewishpress.com/page.do/18624/The_Book_Shelf.html |archive-date=13 August 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Pleiotropy]] occurs when one [[gene]] influences multiple, seemingly unrelated [[phenotypic trait]]s, an example being [[phenylketonuria]], which is a human disease that affects multiple systems but is caused by one gene defect.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stearns&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last=Stearns |first=F. W. |date=2010 |title=One Hundred Years of Pleiotropy: A Retrospective |url= http://www.genetics.org/content/186/3/767.abstract |journal=Genetics |volume=186 |issue=3 |pages=767–773 |doi=10.1534/genetics.110.122549 |pmid=21062962 |pmc=2975297}}&lt;/ref&gt; Andrzej Pękalski, from the [[University of Wrocław]], argues that eugenics can cause harmful loss of genetic diversity if a eugenics program selects a pleiotropic gene that could possibly be associated with a positive trait. Pekalski uses the example of a coercive government eugenics program that prohibits people with [[myopia]] from breeding but has the unintended consequence of also selecting against high intelligence since the two go together.&lt;ref name=&quot;pekalski&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last=Jones |first=A. |date=2000 |title=Effect of eugenics on the evolution of populations |journal=European Physical Journal B |volume=17 |issue=2 |pages=329–332 |doi=10.1007/s100510070148 |bibcode=2000EPJB...17..329P}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Loss of genetic diversity===
Eugenic policies may lead to a loss of [[genetic diversity]]. Further, a culturally-accepted &quot;improvement&quot; of the gene pool may result in extinction, due to increased vulnerability to disease, reduced ability to adapt to environmental change, and other factors that may not be anticipated in advance. This has been evidenced in numerous instances, in isolated island populations. A long-term, species-wide eugenics plan might lead to such a scenario because the elimination of traits deemed undesirable would reduce genetic diversity by definition.&lt;ref&gt;(Galton 2001, 48){{full citation needed|date=September 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Edward M. Miller]] claims that, in any one generation, any realistic program should make only minor changes in a fraction of the gene pool, giving plenty of time to reverse direction if [[unintended consequences]] emerge, reducing the likelihood of the elimination of desirable genes.&lt;ref name = &quot;miller&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last=Miller |first=Edward M. |title=Eugenics: Economics for the Long Run |journal=Research in Biopolitics |volume=5 |pages=391–416 |date=1997}}&lt;/ref&gt; Miller also argues that any appreciable reduction in diversity is so far in the future that little concern is needed for now.&lt;ref name = &quot;miller&quot;/&gt;

While the science of genetics has increasingly provided means by which certain characteristics and conditions can be identified and understood, given the complexity of human genetics, culture, and psychology, at this point there is no agreed objective means of determining which traits might be ultimately desirable or undesirable. Some diseases such as [[sickle-cell disease]] and [[cystic fibrosis]] respectively confer immunity to malaria and resistance to [[cholera]] when a single copy of the recessive allele is contained within the genotype of the individual.&lt;ref name=&quot;Withrock et al 2015&quot;&gt;{{ cite journal |last=Withrock |first=Isabelle |title= Genetic diseases conferring resistance to infectious diseases |journal= Genes &amp; Diseases |volume=2(3) |pages=247-254 |date=2015 |url= https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6150079/}}&lt;/ref&gt; Reducing the instance of sickle-cell disease genes in Africa where malaria is a common and deadly disease could have severe consequences.{{original research inline|date=March 2019}}

===Ethics===
Societal and political consequences of eugenics call for a place in the discussion on the ethics behind the eugenics movement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Bentwich |first=M. |date=2013 |title=On the inseparability of gender eugenics, ethics, and public policy: An Israeli perspective |journal=American Journal of Bioethics |volume=13 |issue=10|pages=43–45 |doi=10.1080/15265161.2013.828128|pmid=24024807 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Many of the ethical concerns regarding eugenics arise from its controversial past, prompting a discussion on what place, if any, it should have in the future. Advances in science have changed eugenics. In the past, eugenics had more to do with sterilization and enforced reproduction laws.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Fischer |first=B. A. |date=2012 |title=Maltreatment of people with serious mental illness in the early 20th century: A focus on Nazi Germany and eugenics in America |journal=Journal of Nervous and Mental Disease |volume=200 |issue=12 |pages=1096–1100 |doi=10.1097/NMD.0b013e318275d391|pmid=23197125 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Now, in the age of a progressively mapped genome, embryos can be tested for susceptibility to disease, gender, and genetic defects, and alternative methods of reproduction such as in vitro fertilization are becoming more common.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Hoge |first1=S. K. |last2=Appelbaum |first2=P. S. |date=2012 |title=Ethics and neuropsychiatric genetics: A review of major issues |journal=International Journal of Neuropsychopharmacology |volume=15 |issue=10 |pages=1547–1557 |doi=10.1017/S1461145711001982|pmid=22272758 |pmc=3359421 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Therefore, eugenics is no longer ''ex post facto'' regulation of the living but instead preemptive action on the unborn.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Witzany |first=G. |journal=EMBO Reports |title=No time to waste on the road to a liberal eugenics? |volume=17 |issue=3  |page=281 |date=2016 | doi=10.15252/embr.201541855 | pmid=26882552 | pmc=4772985}}&lt;/ref&gt;

With this change, however, there are ethical concerns which lack adequate attention, and which must be addressed before eugenic policies can be properly implemented in the future. Sterilized individuals, for example, could volunteer for the procedure, albeit under incentive or duress, or at least voice their opinion. The unborn fetus on which these new eugenic procedures are performed cannot speak out, as the fetus lacks the voice to consent or to express his or her opinion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Baird |first=S. L. |date=2007 |title=Designer babies: Eugenics repackaged or consumer options? |url= |journal=Technology Teacher |volume=66 |issue=7 |pages=12–16}}&lt;/ref&gt; Philosophers disagree about the proper framework for reasoning about such actions, which change the very identity and existence of future persons.&lt;ref name=&quot;SEP&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last=Roberts |first=M. A. |title=The Nonidentity Problem |url= http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/nonidentity-problem/|website=Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy |publisher=Stanford University|access-date=18 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Opposition====

[[File:Eugenics Quarterly to Social Biology.jpg|thumb|In the decades after [[World War II]], the term &quot;eugenics&quot; had taken on a negative connotation and became increasingly unpopular within academic science. Many organizations and journals that had their origins in the eugenics movement began to distance themselves from the philosophy, as when ''Eugenics Quarterly'' became ''Social Biology'' in 1969.]]

Some have described potential &quot;eugenics wars&quot; as the worst-case outcome of eugenics. This scenario would mean the return of coercive state-sponsored [[genetic discrimination]] and [[Human rights violations#Human rights violations|human rights violations]] such as [[compulsory sterilization]] of persons with genetic defects, the [[euthanasia|killing of the institutionalized]] and, specifically, [[racial segregation|segregation]] and [[genocide]] of [[Social interpretations of race|races]] perceived as inferior.{{sfn|Black|2003}} Health law professor [[George Annas]] and technology law professor [[Lori Andrews]] are prominent advocates of the position that the use of these technologies could lead to such human-[[posthuman]] [[caste]] warfare.&lt;ref name=&quot;Darnovsky Crossroads&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last=Darnovsky |first=Marcy |title=Health and human rights leaders call for an international ban on species-altering procedures |date=2001 |url= http://www.geneticsandsociety.org/article.php?id=2809 |access-date=21 February 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Annas 2002&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author-link=George Annas |last=Annas |first=George |author2-link=Lori Andrews |last2=Andrews |first2=Lori |author3-link=Rosario Isasi |last3=Isasi |first3=Rosario |title=Protecting the endangered human: Toward an international treaty prohibiting cloning and inheritable alterations |journal=American Journal of Law &amp; Medicine |volume=28 |page=151 |date=2002}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to eugenics advocate [[Richard Lynn]], the criticism of eugenics that &quot;it inevitably leads to measures that are unethical&quot; is a [[slippery slope]] argument.{{sfn|Lynn|2001|p=241|ps=, &quot;A number of the opponents of eugenics have resorted to the slippery slope argument, which states that although a number of eugenic measures are unobjectionable in themselves, they could lead to further measures that would be unethical. This argument is unpersuasive because all sorts of measures that are acceptable might, if taken to extremes, lead to other measures that are unacceptable.&quot;}}

In his 2003 book ''Enough: Staying Human in an Engineered Age'', [[environmental ethics|environmental ethicist]] [[Bill McKibben]] argued at length against [[germinal choice technology]] and other advanced biotechnological strategies for human enhancement. He writes that it would be morally wrong for humans to tamper with fundamental aspects of themselves (or their children) in an attempt to overcome universal human limitations, such as vulnerability to [[aging]], [[maximum life span]] and biological constraints on physical and cognitive ability. Attempts to &quot;improve&quot; themselves through such manipulation would remove limitations that provide a necessary context for the experience of meaningful human choice. He claims that human lives would no longer seem [[Meaning of life|meaningful]] in a world where such limitations could be overcome with technology. Even the goal of using germinal choice technology for clearly therapeutic purposes should be relinquished, since it would inevitably produce temptations to tamper with such things as cognitive capacities. He argues that it is possible for societies to benefit from renouncing particular technologies, using as examples [[Ming Dynasty|Ming China]], [[Tokugawa shogunate|Tokugawa Japan]] and the contemporary [[Amish]].&lt;ref name=&quot;McKibben 2003&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=McKibben |first=Bill |author-link=Bill McKibben |title=Enough: Staying Human in an Engineered Age |publisher=Times Books |date=2003 |isbn=978-0-8050-7096-5 |oclc=237794777}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Endorsement====
Some, for example [[Nathaniel C. Comfort]] from [[Johns Hopkins University]], claim that the change from state-led reproductive-genetic decision-making to individual choice has moderated the worst abuses of eugenics by transferring the decision-making from the state to the patient and their family.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=The Eugenics Impulse|journal=The Chronicle of Higher Education |first=Nathaniel |last=Comfort |date=12 November 2012 |url= http://chronicle.com/article/The-Eugenic-Impulse/135612/|access-date=9 September 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Comfort suggests that &quot;the eugenic impulse drives us to eliminate disease, live longer and healthier, with greater intelligence, and a better adjustment to the conditions of society; and the health benefits, the intellectual thrill and the profits of genetic bio-medicine are too great for us to do otherwise.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Comfort |first=Nathaniel |title=The Science of Human Perfection: How Genes Became the Heart of American Medicine |publisher=Yale University Press |location=New Haven |isbn=978-0-300-16991-1|date=2012-09-25 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Others, such as [[Bioethics|bioethicist]] Stephen Wilkinson of [[Keele University]] and Honorary Research Fellow Eve Garrard at the [[University of Manchester]], claim that some aspects of modern genetics can be classified as eugenics, but that this classification does not inherently make modern genetics immoral. In a co-authored publication by Keele University, they stated that &quot;[e]ugenics doesn't seem always to be immoral, and so the fact that PGD, and other forms of selective reproduction, might sometimes technically be eugenic, isn't sufficient to show that they're wrong.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Eugenics and the Ethics of Selective Reproduction |first1=Stephen |last1=Wilkinson |first2=Eve |last2=Garrard |publisher=Keele University |year=2013 |url= http://eprints.lancs.ac.uk/65644/1/Eugenics_and_the_ethics_of_selective_reproduction_Low_Res_1.pdf |access-date=18 September 2013 |isbn=978-0-9576160-0-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In their book published in 2000, ''From Chance to Choice: Genetics and Justice'', bioethicists Allen Buchanan, Dan Brock, Norman Daniels and Daniel Wikler argued that liberal societies have an obligation to encourage as wide an adoption of eugenic enhancement technologies as possible (so long as such policies do not infringe on individuals' [[reproductive rights]] or exert undue pressures on prospective parents to use these technologies) in order to maximize [[public health]] and minimize the inequalities that may result from both natural genetic endowments and unequal access to genetic enhancements.&lt;ref name=&quot;Buchanan 2000&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last1=Buchanan |first1=Allen |last2=Brock |first2=Dan W. |last3=Daniels |first3=Norman |last4=Wikler |first4=Daniel |title=From Chance to Choice: Genetics and Justice |publisher=Cambridge University Press |year=2000 |isbn=978-0-521-66977-1 |oclc=41211380}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In his book ''[[A Theory of Justice]]'' (1971), American philosopher [[John Rawls]] argued that &quot;Over time a society is to take steps to preserve the general level of natural abilities and to prevent the diffusion of serious defects&quot;.&lt;ref name=Rawls&gt;{{cite book |last=Rawls |first=John |year=1999 |orig-year=1971 |title=A theory of justice |edition=revised |location=Cambridge, Massachusetts |publisher=Harvard University Press |page=92 |isbn=0-674-00078-1 |author-link=John Rawls |quote=In addition, it is possible to adopt eugenic policies, more or less explicit. I shall not consider questions of eugenics, confining myself throughout to the traditional concerns of social justice. We should note, though, that it is not in general to the advantage of the less fortunate to propose policies which reduce the talents of others. Instead, by accepting the difference principle, they view the greater abilities as a social asset to be used for the common advantage. But it is also in the interest of each to have greater natural assets. This enables him to pursue a preferred plan of life. In the original position, then, the parties want to insure for their descendants the best genetic endowment (assuming their own to be fixed). The pursuit of reasonable policies in this regard is something that earlier generations owe to later ones, this being a question that arises between generations. Thus over time a society is to take steps at least to preserve the general level of natural abilities and to prevent the diffusion of serious defects.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Original position]], a hypothetical situation developed by Rawls, has been used as an argument for ''negative eugenics''.&lt;ref&gt;Shaw, p. 147. Quote: &quot;What Rawls says is that &quot;Over time a society is to take steps to preserve the general level of natural abilities and to prevent the diffusion of serious defects.&quot; The key words here are &quot;preserve&quot; and &quot;prevent&quot;. Rawls clearly envisages only the use of negative eugenics as a preventive measure to ensure a good basic level of genetic health for future generations. To jump from this to &quot;make the later generations as genetically talented as possible,&quot; as Pence does, is a masterpiece of misinterpretation. This, then, is the sixth argument against positive eugenics: the Veil of Ignorance argument. Those behind the Veil in Rawls' Original Position would agree to permit negative, but not positive eugenics. This is a more complex variant of the Consent argument, as the Veil of Ignorance merely forces us to adopt a position of hypotethical consent to particular principles of justice.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Harding |first=John R. |date=1991 |title=Beyond Abortion: Human Genetics and the New Eugenics |url= http://digitalcommons.pepperdine.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1677&amp;context=plr |journal=Pepperdine Law Review |volume=18 |issue=3 |pages=489–491 |access-date= 2016-06-02 |quote=Rawls arrives at the difference principle by considering how justice might be drawn from a hypothetical &quot;original position.' A person in the original position operates behind a &quot;veil of ignorance&quot; that prevents her from knowing any information about herself such as social status, physical or mental capabilities, or even her belief system. Only from such a position of universal equality can principles of justice be drawn. In establishing how to distribute social primary goods, for example, &quot;rights and liberties, powers and opportunities, income and wealth&quot; and self-respect, Rawls determines that a person operating from the original position would develop two principles. First, liberties ascribed to each individual should be as extensive as possible without infringing upon the liberties of others. Second, social primary goods should be distributed to the greatest advantage of everyone and by mechanisms that allow equal opportunity to all. ... Genetic engineering should not be permitted merely for the enhancement of physical attractiveness because that would not benefit the least advantaged. Arguably, resources should be concentrated on genetic therapy to address disease and genetic defects. However, such a result is not required under Rawls' theory. Genetic enhancement of those already intellectually gifted, for example, might result in even greater benefit to the least advantaged as a result of the gifted individual's improved productivity. Moreover, Rawls asserts that using genetic engineering to prevent the most serious genetic defects is a matter of intergenerational justice. Such actions are necessary in terms of what the present generation owes to later generations.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== In fiction ==
The film ''[[Gattaca]]'' (1997) provides a fictional example of a [[dystopian]] society that uses eugenics to decide what people are capable of and their place in the world.Although critically acclaimed, ''Gattaca'' was not a box office success, but it is said to have crystallized the debate over the controversial topic of [[human genetic engineering]].&lt;ref name=Jabr&gt;{{Cite journal| last1 = Jabr |first1= Ferris| title = Are We Too Close to Making Gattaca a Reality?| date = 2013 | url = http://www.sfgate.com/movies/article/Gattaca-a-Not-So-Perfect-Specimen-Hawke-only-2799938.php| accessdate = 2014-04-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=popemcroberts&gt;{{cite book|last1=Pope|first1= Marcia |last2=McRoberts |first2= Richard | title = Cambridge Wizard Student Guide Gattaca | publisher = Cambridge University press | date = 2003 | isbn = 0-521-53615-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; The film's [[dystopia]]n depiction of &quot;[[genoism]]&quot; has been cited by many [[bioethicist]]s and laypeople in support of their hesitancy about, or opposition to, eugenics and the societal acceptance of the [[genetic determinism|genetic-determinist]] ideology that may frame it.&lt;ref name=kirby&gt;{{Cite journal| last1 = Kirby |first1= D.A.| title = The New Eugenics in Cinema: Genetic Determinism and Gene Therapy in GATTACA. Science Fiction Studies, 27: 193-215| date = 2000 | url = http://www.depauw.edu/sfs/essays/gattaca.htm| accessdate = 2008-01-08| authorlink = David A. Kirby}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a 1997 review of the film for the journal ''Nature Genetics'', molecular biologist [[Lee M. Silver]] stated that &quot;''Gattaca'' is a film that all geneticists should see if for no other reason than to understand the perception of our trade held by so many of the public-at-large&quot;.&lt;ref name=silver&gt;{{Cite journal| author = Silver, Lee M.| title = Genetics Goes to Hollywood| date = 1997| volume=17| issue=3| doi=10.1038/ng1197-260| authorlink = Lee M. Silver| journal = Nature Genetics| pages = 260–261}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{div col}}
* {{annotated link|Ableism}}
* {{annotated link|Biological determinism}}
* {{annotated link|Culling}}
* {{annotated link|Directed evolution (transhumanism)}}
* {{annotated link|Dor Yeshorim}}
* {{annotated link|Dysgenics}}
* {{annotated link|Eugenic feminism}}
* {{annotated link|Eugenics in Mexico}}
* {{annotated link|Eugenics in the United States}}
* {{annotated link|Euthenics}}
* {{annotated link|Genetic discrimination}}
* {{annotated link|Genetic enhancement}}
* {{annotated link|Human enhancement}}
* {{annotated link|In vitro fertilisation#Embryo selection|''In vitro'' embryo selection}} ({{annotated link|preimplantation genetic diagnosis}})
* {{annotated link|New eugenics}}
* {{annotated link|Life unworthy of life}}
* {{annotated link|Mendelian traits in humans}}
* {{annotated link|Procreative_beneficence}}
* {{annotated link|Rare disease|Prevention of rare diseases}}
* {{annotated link|Compulsory sterilization|Sterilization}}
* {{annotated link|Social Darwinism}}
* {{annotated link|Somatotype and constitutional psychology}}
{{end div col}}

==References==
'''Notes'''
{{Reflist}}

==Bibliography==
* {{cite book |last1=Agar |first1=Nicholas |date=2004 |title=Liberal Eugenics: In Defense of Human Enhancement |publisher=Wiley-Blackwell |url=}}
* {{cite journal| last = Agar | first = Nicholas | title = Why we Should Defend Gene Editing as Eugenics | date = 2019 | publisher = Cambridge Quarterly of Healthcare Ethics | volume = 34 | url = https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/cambridge-quarterly-of-healthcare-ethics/article/why-we-should-defend-gene-editing-as-eugenics/00B15AEB625379F8543C43E286160B87|url-access=subscription}}
* {{cite journal |last1=Anomaly |first1=Jonathan |date=2018 |title=Defending Eugenics: From cryptic choice to conscious selection |volume=35 |issue=1–4 |pages=24–35 |journal=Monash Bioethics Review|doi=10.1007/s40592-018-0081-2 |pmid=29804244 |pmc=6096849 }}
* {{cite book |last=Black |first=Edwin |author-link=Edwin Black |title=War Against the Weak: Eugenics and America's Campaign to Create a Master Race |publisher=Four Walls Eight Windows |date=2003 |isbn=978-1-56858-258-0 |ref=harv |url=https://archive.org/details/isbn_9781568582580 }}
* {{cite book |last1=Buchanan |first1=Allen |date=2017 |title=Better than Human: The Promise and Perils of Deliberate Biomedical Enhancement |publisher=Oxford University Press |url= |isbn=978-0190664046 |series=Philosophy in Action }}
* {{cite journal |last=Cavaliere |first=Giulia |date=2018 |title=Looking into the Shadow: Eugenics arguments in debates about reproductive technologies |volume=36 |issue=1–4 |pages=1–22 |journal=Monash Bioethics Review |doi=10.1007/s40592-018-0086-x |pmid=30535862 |pmc=6336759 }}
* {{cite book |last1=Gyngell |first1=Christopher |last2=Selgelid |first2=Michael |date=2016 |title=Twenty-First Century Eugenics |journal=The Oxford Handbook of Reproductive Ethics |volume=1 |url= http://www.oxfordhandbooks.com/view/10.1093/oxfordhb/9780199981878.001.0001/oxfordhb-9780199981878-e-7|doi=10.1093/oxfordhb/9780199981878.001.0001 |isbn=978-0199981878 |url-access=subscription }}
* {{cite book |last=Lynn |first=Richard |author-link=Richard Lynn |date= 2001 |title=Eugenics: a reassessment |type=Hardcover |location=Westport, CN|publisher=Praeger Publishers |isbn=978-0-275-95822-0 |issn=1063-2158 |lccn=00052459 |postscript=none |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last1=Savulescu |first1=Julian |last2=Kahane |first2=Guy |date=2009 |title=The Moral Obligation to Have Children with the Best Chance of the Best Life |publisher=Bioethics |url= http://faculty.smu.edu/jkazez/PAP/savulescu-kahane.pdf}}
* {{cite book |last=Shaw |first=David |date=2006 |title=Genetic Morality |location=Bern|publisher=Peter Lang |isbn=978-3-03911-149-7}}
* {{cite journal |last=Sparrow |first=Robert |date=2014 |title=In Vitro Eugenics |volume=40 |issue=11 |pages=725–731 |journal=Journal of Medical Ethics |pmid=23557913 |doi=10.1136/medethics-2012-101200 |url=https://semanticscholar.org/paper/29d0884cf4ed6acdb2711f556863a1ef2bd3a908 }}

===Histories of eugenics (academic accounts)===
* {{cite book |last=Carlson |first=Elof Axel |title=The Unfit: A History of a Bad Idea |publisher=Cold Spring Harbor Press |location=Cold Spring Harbor, NY|date=2001 |isbn=978-0-87969-587-3}}
* {{cite book |last=Engs |first=Ruth C. |author-link=Ruth C. Engs |title=The Eugenics Movement: An Encyclopedia |publisher=Greenwood Publishing |location=Westport, CN|date=2005 |isbn=978-0-313-32791-9}}
* {{cite book |last=Farrall |first=Lyndsay |title=The Origins and Growth of the English eugenics movement, 1865–1925 |date=1985 |publisher=Garland Pub |isbn=978-0-8240-5810-4}}
* {{cite book |last=Kevles |first=Daniel J. |author-link=Daniel Kevles |title=In the Name of Eugenics: Genetics and the Uses of Human Heredity |url= https://books.google.com/?id=8esnhRxBomMC |date=1985 |publisher=University of California Press |isbn=978-0-520-05763-0}}
* {{cite book |last=Largent |first=Mark |title=Breeding Contempt: The History of Coerced Sterilization in the United States |publisher=Rutgers University Press |location=New Brunswick |date=2008 |isbn=978-0-8135-4183-9}}
* Leon, Sharon M. (2013). ''An Image of God: The Catholic Struggle with Eugenics.'' Chicago: University of Chicago Press.
* {{cite book |last=Paul |first=Diane | title=Darwin, Social Darwinism, and Eugenics| publisher=Cambridge University Press | date=2006 |url= https://www.dianebpaul.com/uploads/2/3/2/9/23295024/darwin_social_darwinism_and_eugenics.pdf}}
* {{cite book |last=Redman |first=Samuel J. |title=Bone Rooms: From Scientific Racism to Human Prehistory in Museums |publisher=Harvard University Press |location=Cambridge |date=2016 |isbn=978-0674660410}}
* Stepan, Nancy Leys (1991). ''&quot;The Hour of Eugenics&quot;: Race, Gender, and Nation in Latin America''. Ithaca: Cornell University Press.
* {{cite web |publisher=United States Holocaust Memorial Museum |title=Deadly Medicine: Creating the Master Race |date=2004 |url=http://www.ushmm.org/museum/exhibit/online/deadlymedicine |work=USHMM.org |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130904043526/http://www.ushmm.org/museum/exhibit/online/deadlymedicine/ |archivedate=4 September 2013 |df=dmy-all }}
* {{Cite book |last=Wyndham |first=Diana |title=Eugenics in Australia: Striving for national fitness |date=2003 |publisher=Galton Institute |location=London |isbn=978-0-9504066-7-1}}

===Histories of hereditarian thought===
* {{cite book |first=Elazar |last=Barkan |title=The Retreat of Scientific Racism: Changing Concepts of Race in Britain and the United States Between the World Wars |publisher=Cambridge University Press |location=New York |date=1992 |isbn= |pages=}}
* {{cite book |last=Ewen |first=Elizabeth |last2=Ewen |first2=Stuart |title=Typecasting: On the Arts and Sciences of Human Inequality |date=2006 |publisher=Seven Stories Press |location=New York |isbn=978-1-58322-735-0 |edition=1st |url=https://archive.org/details/typecastingonart00eliz }}
* {{cite book |last=Gould |first=Stephen Jay |author-link=Stephen Jay Gould |title=The Mismeasure of Man |url=https://archive.org/details/mismeasureofman00goulrich |url-access=registration |publisher=Norton |location=New York |date=1981 |isbn=978-0-393-01489-1}}
* {{cite book |last=Gillette |first=Aaron |title=The Nature–Nurture Debate in the Twentieth Century |publisher=Palgrave Macmillan |location=New York |date=2007 |isbn=978-0-230-10845-5}}

===Criticisms of eugenics===
* {{cite book |last=Blom |first=Philipp |author-link=Philipp Blom |title=The Vertigo Years: Change and Culture in the West, 1900–1914 |date=2008 |publisher=McClelland &amp; Stewart |location=Toronto |isbn=978-0-7710-1630-1 |pages=[https://archive.org/details/vertigoyearschan0000blom/page/335 335–336] |ref=harv |url=https://archive.org/details/vertigoyearschan0000blom/page/335 }}
* {{cite book |last=Galton |first=David |title=Eugenics: The Future of Human Life in the 21st Century |date=2002 |publisher=Abacus |location=London |isbn=978-0-349-11377-7}}
* {{cite book |last=Goldberg |first=Jonah |title=Liberal Fascism: The Secret History of the American Left, from Mussolini to the Politics of Meaning |date=2007 |publisher=Doubleday |location=New York |isbn=978-0-385-51184-1 |edition=1st |url=https://archive.org/details/liberalfascismse00gold }}
* {{cite book |last=Joseph |first=Jay |date=2004 |url= http://www.jayjoseph.net/GeneIllusion.html |title=The Gene Illusion: Genetic Research in Psychiatry and Psychology Under the Microscope |location=New York |publisher=Algora |isbn=978-0-87586-343-6 |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20090512075255/http://www.jayjoseph.net/GeneIllusion.html |archive-date=12 May 2009}}
* {{cite journal |last=Joseph |first=Jay |title=The 1942 'euthanasia' debate in the ''American Journal of Psychiatry'' |journal=History of Psychiatry |volume=16 |issue=62 Pt. 2 |pages=171–179 |date=June 2005 |pmid=16013119 |doi=10.1177/0957154x05047004|url=https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-00570816/file/PEER_stage2_10.1177%252F0957154X05047004.pdf }}
* {{cite book |last=Joseph |first=Jay |title=The Missing Gene: Psychiatry, Heredity, and the Fruitless Search for Genes |date=2006 |publisher=Algora |location=New York |isbn=978-0-87586-410-5 |url= http://www.jayjoseph.net/MissingGene.html |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20090417170900/http://www.jayjoseph.net/MissingGene.html |archive-date=17 April 2009}}
* {{cite book |last=Kerr |first=Anne |last2=Shakespeare |first2=Tom |title=Genetic Politics: from Eugenics to Genome |date=2002 |publisher=New Clarion |location=Cheltenham |isbn=978-1-873797-25-9}}
* {{cite book |last=Maranto |first=Gina |title=Quest for perfection: the drive to breed better human beings |date=1996 |publisher=Scribner |location=New York |isbn=978-0-684-80029-5 |url=https://archive.org/details/questforperfecti00mara }}
* {{cite book |last=Ordover |first=Nancy |title=American Eugenics: Race, Queer Anatomy, and the Science of Nationalism |date=2003 |publisher=University of Minnesota Press |location=Minneapolis |isbn=978-0-8166-3559-7}}
* {{cite journal |last=Shakespeare |first=Tom |author-link=Tom Shakespeare |title=Back to the Future? New Genetics and Disabled People |journal=Critical Social Policy |volume=46 |issue= 44–45 |pages=22–35 |date=1995 |doi= 10.1177/026101839501504402 |url=}}
* {{cite book |last=Smith |first=Andrea |title=Conquest: Sexual Violence and American Indian Genocide |date=2005 |publisher=South End Press |location=Cambridge, MA |isbn=978-0-89608-743-9}}
* {{cite journal |last=Wahlsten |first=D. |title=Leilani Muir versus the philosopher king: Eugenics on trial in Alberta |journal=Genetica |volume=99 |issue=2–3 |pages=185–198 |date=1997 |pmid=9463073 |doi=10.1007/BF02259522|url=http://libres.uncg.edu/ir/uncg/f/D_Wahlsten_Leilani_1997.pdf |citeseerx=10.1.1.476.9688 }}

==External links==
{{commons category|Eugenics}}
* {{Wikisource-inline}}
* {{Wikiquote-inline}}

{{Genetic engineering}}
{{Historical definitions of race}}
{{Pseudoscience}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Eugenics| ]]
[[Category:Ableism]]
[[Category:Applied genetics]]
[[Category:Bioethics]]
[[Category:Ethically disputed medical practices]]
[[Category:Pseudoscience]]</text>
      <sha1>2f96dzkac3jvbdwb2wf71ad9oetwjfu</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
