  <page>
    <title>Eschatology</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9760</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942943693</id>
      <parentid>942397186</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-27T21:04:07Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>JzG</username>
        <id>760284</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* top */Addind &quot;self-published source&quot; inside ref tags where tagged inline only</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{redirect|Last Things|the C. P. Snow novel| Strangers and Brothers}}
{{short description| Theological views of the end of the world}}
{{more citations needed|date=May 2018}}
[[File:Durer Revelation Four Riders.jpg|200px|right|thumb|[[Four horsemen of the apocalypse]], as depicted in the ''[[Apocalypse (Dürer)|Apocalypse]]'' work by [[Albrecht Dürer]]]]
{{Eschatology |width=18.75em}}

'''Eschatology''' {{IPAc-en|audio=En-uk-eschatology.ogg|ˌ|ɛ|s|k|ə|ˈ|t|ɒ|l|ə|dʒ|i}} is a part of [[theology]] concerned with the final events of [[history of the world|history]], or the ultimate [[destiny]] of humanity. This concept is commonly referred to as the &quot;[[end of the world (civilization)|end of the world]]&quot; or &quot;[[end time]]s&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= http://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/religions/christianity/beliefs/endtimes_1.shtml |title= BBC - Religions - Christianity: End Times |work= [[BBC Online]] |date= 2011-07-19 |accessdate= 2017-11-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The word arises from the [[Ancient Greek|Greek]] {{lang|grc|[[wikt:ἔσχατος|ἔσχατος]]}} ''eschatos'' meaning &quot;last&quot; and ''[[-logy]]'' meaning &quot;the study of&quot;, and first appeared in English around 1844.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/eschatology Dictionary – Definition of Eschatology]. [[Webster's Online Dictionary]].&lt;/ref&gt; The ''[[Oxford English Dictionary]]'' defines eschatology as &quot;the part of theology concerned with death, judgment, and the final destiny of the soul and of humankind&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Eschatology, ''n.''&quot;, def. a, ''[[Oxford English Dictionary]]''. Retrieved 2016-05-18.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the context of [[mysticism]], the term refers metaphorically to the end of ordinary [[reality]] and to reunion with [[the Divine]]. Many{{quantify|date=November 2018}} [[religion]]s treat eschatology as a future event [[prophecy|prophesied]] in [[sacred text]]s or in [[folklore]].

Most{{quantify|date=November 2018}} modern eschatology and [[apocalypticism]], both religious and secular, involve the violent disruption or destruction of the world; whereas Christian and Jewish eschatologies view the end times as the consummation or perfection of God's creation of the world,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last= Williams |first= Sean |title= The Big Picture. Making Sense Out of Life and Religion |url= https://books.google.com/?id=QYyIAgAAQBAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover |date= 2009 |publisher= Lulu.com |isbn= 9780578015231 |page= [https://books.google.com/?id=QYyIAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA91&amp;dq=%22Christian+and+Jewish+eschatologies+view+the+end+times+as+the+consummation+or+perfection+of+God's+creation+of+the+world%22 91]}}{{self-published source|date=February 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{self-published inline|date=February 2020}} albeit with violent overtures, such as the [[Great Tribulation]]. For example, according to some ancient Hebrew worldviews, reality unfolds along a linear path (or rather, a spiral path, with cyclical components that nonetheless have a linear trajectory); the world began with God and is ultimately headed toward God's final goal for creation, the world to come.&lt;ref&gt;
Sofroniou, Andreas (2017). p. [https://books.google.com/?id=7Vc1DwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA77&amp;dq=%22For+example,+according+to+some+ancient+Hebrew+worldviews,+reality+unfolds+along+a+linear+path+(or+rather,+a+spiral+path,+with+cyclical+components+that+nonetheless+have+a+linear+trajectory)%22 77].
&lt;/ref&gt;

Eschatologies vary as to their degree of optimism or pessimism about the future. In some eschatologies, conditions are better for some and worse for others, e.g. &quot;heaven and hell&quot;. They also vary as to [[time frame]]s. Groups claiming ''imminent'' eschatology are also referred to as [[Doomsday cults]].

== Religion ==
=== Bahá'í ===
{{See also|Bahá'í Faith on life after death|Bahá'í teachings}}

In [[Bahá'í Faith|Bahá'í]] belief, creation has neither a beginning nor an end.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Smith |first=Peter |title=An Introduction to the Baha'i Faith |url=https://books.google.com/?id=z7zdDFTzNr0C&amp;printsec=frontcover|year=2008 |publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]] |isbn=0-521-86251-5 |page=[https://books.google.com/?id=z7zdDFTzNr0C&amp;pg=PA112&amp;dq=%22the+physical+universe+asa+totality+has+always+existed+in+some+form,+having+neither+beginning+nor+end.%22 112]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Instead, the eschatology of other religions is viewed as symbolic. In Bahá'í belief, human time is marked by a series of [[Progressive revelation (Bahá'í)|progressive revelations]] in which successive [[Manifestation of God|messengers]] or prophets come from God.&lt;ref name=&quot;PSmith&quot;&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |last=Smith |first=Peter |encyclopedia=A concise encyclopedia of the Bahá'í Faith |title=Eschatology |year=2000 |publisher=Oneworld Publications |location=Oxford |isbn=1-85168-184-1 |pages=[https://archive.org/details/conciseencyclope0000smit/page/133 133–134] |url=https://archive.org/details/conciseencyclope0000smit/page/133 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The coming of each of these messengers is seen as the day of judgment to the adherents of the previous religion, who may choose to accept the new messenger and enter the &quot;heaven&quot; of belief, or denounce the new messenger and enter the &quot;hell&quot; of denial. In this view, the terms &quot;heaven&quot; and &quot;hell&quot; are seen as symbolic terms for the person's spiritual progress and their nearness to or distance from God.&lt;ref name=&quot;PSmith&quot; /&gt; In Bahá'í belief, the coming of [[Bahá'u'lláh]], the founder of the Bahá'í Faith, signals the fulfilment of previous eschatological expectations of [[Islam]], [[Christianity]] and other major religions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Studies in Modern Religions, Religious Movements and the Bābī-Bahā'ī Faiths |editor=Sharon, Moshe |first=Christopher |last= Buck |chapter=The Eschatology of Globalization: The Multiple Messiahship of Bahá'u'lláh Revisited (pp. 143–178) |chapterurl=http://bahai-library.com/buck_eschatology_globalization |year=2004 |publisher=[[Brill Publishers|Brill]] |location=Boston |isbn=9004139044}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Buddhism ===
{{Main|Buddhist eschatology}}

=== Christianity ===
{{Christian eschatology}}
{{Main|Christian eschatology|Christian eschatological views}}
Christian eschatology is the study concerned with the ultimate destiny of the individual soul and the entire created order, based primarily upon biblical texts within the Old and New Testament.

Christian eschatology looks to study and discuss matters such as death and the [[afterlife]], [[Heaven in Christianity|Heaven]] and [[Christian views on Hell|Hell]], the [[Second Coming|Second Coming of Jesus]], the [[resurrection of the dead]], the [[Rapture]], the [[Tribulation]], [[Millennialism]], the end of the world, the [[Last Judgment]], and the New Heaven and [[New Earth (Christianity)|New Earth]] in the [[world to come]].

Eschatological passages are found in many places in the Bible, both in the [[Old Testament|Old]] and the [[New Testament]]s. In the Old Testament, apocalyptic eschatology can be found notably in [[Isaiah]] 24–27, Isaiah 56–66, [[Book of Joel|Joel]], [[Book of Zechariah|Zechariah]] 9–14 as well as closing chapters of [[Book of Daniel|Daniel]], and [[Book of Ezekiel|Ezekiel]].&lt;ref name=NBD&gt;Bauckham, R. J. (1996). Apocalyptic. In D. R. W. Wood, I. H. Marshall, A. R. Millard, J. I. Packer, &amp; D. J. Wiseman (Eds.), New Bible Dictionary (3rd ed., p. 53). Leicester, England; Downers Grove, IL: InterVarsity Press.&lt;/ref&gt; In the New Testament, applicable passages include [[Matthew 24]], [[Mark 13]], the [[parable]] of &quot;[[The Sheep and the Goats]]&quot; and in the [[Book of Revelation]]—although Revelation often occupies a central place in Christian eschatology.

The [[Second Coming]] of Christ is the central event in Christian eschatology within the broader context of the fullness of the [[Kingdom of God (Christianity)|Kingdom of God]]. Most Christians believe that death and suffering will continue to exist until Christ's return. There are, however, various views concerning the order and significance of other eschatological events.

The Book of Revelation is at the core of Christian eschatology. The study of Revelation is usually divided into four interpretative methodologies or [[hermeneutic]]s. In the [[Futurism (Christian eschatology)|Futurist]] approach, Revelation is treated mostly as unfulfilled prophecy taking place in some yet undetermined future. In the [[Preterism|Preterist]] approach, Revelation is chiefly interpreted as having prophetic fulfillment in the past, principally the events of the first century CE.

In the [[Historicism (Christian eschatology)|Historicist]] approach, Revelation provides a broad view of history, and passages in Revelation are identified with major historical people and events. This is view the Jewish scholars held, along with the early Christian church, and it was prevalent in Wycliffe's writings,&lt;ref&gt;Tyndale, William, ''Parable of the Wicked Mammon'', c. 1526, (facsimile copy of later printing, no ISBN number, Benediction Classics, 2008)at pages 4-5&lt;/ref&gt; and other Reformers such as Martin Luther,&lt;ref&gt;Luther, Martin, ″Sermon for the Twenty-Fifth Sunday after Trinity; Matthew 24:15-28″, ''Church Postil'', 1525&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;J. H. Merle D’aubigne’s  History of the Reformation of the Sixteen Century, book vi, chapter xii, p. 215.&lt;/ref&gt; John Calvin,&lt;ref&gt;Calvin, John, ″Lecture Fifty-Second&quot;, ''Commentary on Daniel'', Volume&lt;/ref&gt; 
John Wesley,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sacred-texts.com/bib/cmt/wesley/mat024.htm|title=Explanatory Notes on the Whole Bible: Matthew: Matthew Chapter 24|website=www.sacred-texts.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Sir Isaac Newton,&lt;ref&gt;All Roads Lead to Rome,  by Michael de Semlyen. Dorchestor House Publications, p. 205. 1991&lt;/ref&gt; and many others.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Steven|last=Gregg|title=Revelation: Four Views|publisher=[[Thomas Nelson Publishing]]|location=Nashville, Tennessee|date=1997|ISBN=978-0840721280|page=34}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[Idealism (Christian eschatology)|Idealist]] approach, the events of Revelation are neither past nor future, but are purely symbolic, dealing with the ongoing struggle and ultimate triumph of good over evil.

==== Messianic Judaism ====
{{Main|Messianic Jewish theology#Eschatology}}

=== Hinduism ===
{{Main|Hindu eschatology}}
Contemporary Hindu eschatology is linked in the [[Vaishnavite]] tradition to the figure of [[Kalki]], the tenth and last [[avatar]] of [[Vishnu]] before the age draws to a close who will reincarnate as [[Shiva]] and simultaneously dissolve and regenerate the universe.

Most Hindus believe that the current period is the [[Kali Yuga]], the last of four ''Yuga'' that make up the current age. Each period has seen successive degeneration in the moral order, to the point that in the Kali Yuga quarrel and hypocrisy are the norm. In Hinduism, time is cyclic, consisting of cycles or &quot;[[Kalpa (aeon)|kalpas]]&quot;. Each kalpa lasts 4.1 – 8.2 billion years, which is one full day and night for [[Brahma]], who in turn will live for 311 trillion, 40 billion years. The cycle of [[Brahma|birth]], [[Vishnu|growth]], [[Shiva|decay]], and renewal at the individual level finds its echo in the cosmic order, yet is affected by vagaries of divine intervention in Vaishnavite belief. Some Shaivites hold the view that Shiva is incessantly destroying and creating the world.

=== Islam ===
{{Main|Islamic eschatology}}
[[Islamic eschatology]] is documented in the [[Hadith|sayings]] of the [[Prophet of Islam|Prophet]] [[Muhammad]], regarding the Signs of the Day of Judgement. [[File:Ibn arabi judgement day.svg|alt=|thumb|upright=1.2|Diagram of &quot;Plain of Assembly&quot;(''Ard al-Hashr)'' on the Day of Judgment, from autograph manuscript of ''Futuhat al-Makkiyya'' by [[Sufism|Sufi]] mystic and philosopher [[Ibn Arabi]], ca. 1238. Shown are the 'Arsh ([[Throne of God]]), pulpits for the righteous (al-Aminun), seven rows of [[angel]]s, [[Gabriel]] (al-Ruh), A'raf (the Barrier), the [[Pond of Abundance]], al-Maqam al-Mahmud (the Praiseworthy Station; where the prophet Muhammad will stand to intercede for the faithful), Mizan (the Scale), [[As-Sirāt]] (the Bridge), [[Jahannam]] (Hell) and Marj al-[[Jannat]] (Meadow of Paradise).&lt;ref&gt;Begley, Wayne E. The Garden of the Taj Mahal: A Case Study of Mughal Architectural Planning and Symbolism, in: Wescoat, James L.; Wolschke-Bulmahn, Joachim (1996). ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=96ec98LieGsC Mughal Gardens: Sources, Places, Representations, and Prospects]'' Dumbarton Oaks, Washington D.C., {{ISBN|0884022358}}. pp. 229-231.&lt;/ref&gt;]]

The Prophet's sayings on the subject have been traditionally divided into Major and Minor Signs. He spoke about several Minor Signs of the approach of the Day of Judgment, including:
* [[Abu Hurairah]] reported that [[Muhammad]] said: &quot;If you survive for a time you would certainly see people who would have whips in their hands like the tail of an ox. They would get up in the morning under the wrath of God and they would go into the evening with the anger of God.&quot;{{citation needed|date=August 2015}}
* [[Abu Hurairah]] narrated that Muhammad said, &quot;When honesty is lost, then wait for the Day of Judgment.&quot; It was asked, &quot;How will honesty be lost, O Messenger of God?&quot; He said, &quot;When authority is given to those who do not deserve it, then wait for the Day of Judgment.&quot;{{citation needed|date=August 2015}}
* [[Umar|'Umar ibn al-Khattāb]], in a long narration, relating to the questions of the angel [[Gabriel#Islamic references|Gabriel]], reported: &quot;Inform me when the Day of Judgment will be.&quot; He [the Prophet Muhammad] remarked: &quot;The one who is being asked knows no more than the inquirer.&quot; He [the inquirer] said: &quot;Tell me about its indications.&quot; He [the Prophet Muhammad] said: &quot;That the slave-girl gives birth to her mistress and master, and that you would find barefooted, destitute shepherds of goats vying with one another in the construction of magnificent buildings.&quot;{{citation needed|date=August 2015}}
* &quot;Before the Day of Judgment there will be great liars, so beware of them.&quot;{{citation needed|date=August 2015}}
* &quot;When the most wicked member of a tribe becomes its ruler, and the most worthless member of a community becomes its leader, and a man is respected through fear of the evil he may do, and leadership is given to people who are unworthy of it, expect the Day of Judgment.&quot;{{citation needed|date=August 2015}}

Regarding the Major Signs, a [[Sahaba|Companion of the Prophet]] narrated: &quot;Once we were sitting together and talking amongst ourselves when the Prophet appeared. He asked us what it was we were discussing. We said it was the Day of Judgment. He said: 'It will not be called until ten signs have appeared: Smoke, [[Dajjal]] (the [[Antichrist]]), the creature (that will wound the people), the rising of the sun in the West, the [[Second Coming#Islam|Second Coming]] of [[Jesus in Islam|Jesus]], the emergence of [[Gog and Magog#Qur'an|Gog and Magog]], and three sinkings (or cavings in of the earth): one in the East, another in the West and a third in the [[Arabian Peninsula]].'&quot; (note: the previous events were not listed in the chronological order of appearance){{citation needed|date=August 2015}}

=== Judaism ===
{{Main|Jewish eschatology}}
Jewish eschatology is concerned with events that will happen in the [[End time|end of days]], according to the [[Hebrew Bible]] and Jewish thought. This includes the ingathering of the exiled [[Jewish diaspora|diaspora]], the coming of the [[Jewish messianism|Jewish Messiah]], [[afterlife]], and the [[Techiyat hamaysim|revival of the dead Tzadikim]].

In Judaism, the end times are usually called the &quot;end of days&quot; (''aḥarit ha-yamim'', אחרית הימים), a phrase that appears several times in the [[Tanakh]]. The idea of a [[messianic age]] has a prominent place in Jewish thought and is incorporated as part of the end of days.

[[Judaism]] addresses the [[end time]]s in the [[Book of Daniel]] and numerous other prophetic passages in the Hebrew scriptures, and also in the [[Talmud]], particularly Tractate [[Avodah Zarah]].

=== Zoroastrianism ===
{{Main|Frashokereti}}
Frashokereti is the [[Zoroastrian]] doctrine of a final renovation of the universe when evil will be destroyed, and everything else will then be in perfect unity with God ([[Ahura Mazda]]). The doctrinal premises are (1) good will eventually prevail over evil; (2) creation was initially perfectly good, but was subsequently corrupted by evil; (3) the world will ultimately be restored to the perfection it had at the time of creation; (4) the &quot;salvation for the individual depended on the sum of [that person's] thoughts, words and deeds, and there could be no intervention, whether compassionate or capricious, by any divine being to alter this.&quot; Thus, each human bears the responsibility for the fate of his own soul, and simultaneously shares in the responsibility for the fate of the world.&lt;ref name=&quot;Boyce&quot;&gt;{{citation|last=Boyce|first=Mary|authorlink=Mary Boyce|title=Zoroastrians: Their Religious Beliefs and Practices|year=1979|location=London|publisher=Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul|isbn=978-0-415-23902-8|pages=27–29|url=https://books.google.com/?id=a6gbxVfjtUEC&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Analogies in science and philosophy ==
{{Main|Global catastrophic risk}}

=== Futures studies and transhumanism ===
Researchers in [[futures studies]] and [[transhumanists]] investigate how the accelerating rate of scientific progress may lead to a &quot;[[technological singularity]]&quot; in the future that would profoundly and unpredictably change the course of human history, and result in ''Homo sapiens'' no longer being the dominant life form on Earth.&lt;ref name=&quot;agi-conf&quot;&gt;[[Anders Sandberg|Sandberg, Anders]]. [http://agi-conf.org/2010/wp-content/uploads/2009/06/agi10singmodels2.pdf An overview of models of technological singularity]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;hplusmagazine&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.hplusmagazine.com/articles/nano/singularity-nanotech-or-ai |title=h+ Magazine &amp;#124; Covering technological, scientific, and cultural trends that are changing human beings in fundamental ways |publisher=Hplusmagazine.com |date= |accessdate=2011-09-09 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20101223170126/http://www.hplusmagazine.com/articles/nano/singularity-nanotech-or-ai |archive-date=2010-12-23 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{synthesis inline|reason=sources do not appear to have the word &quot;Eschatology&quot; in them|date=September 2016}}

=== Astronomy ===
[[File:Solar Life Cycle.svg|right|thumb|upright=1.75|A diagram showing the life cycle of the [[Sun]]]]
{{See also|Future of Earth|Future of an expanding universe|Ultimate fate of the universe}}

Occasionally the term &quot;physical eschatology&quot; is applied to the long-term predictions of astrophysics.&lt;ref&gt;Ćirković, Milan M. &quot;Resource letter: PEs-1: physical eschatology.&quot; American Journal of Physics 71.2 (2003): 122–133.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Baum, Seth D. &quot;Is humanity doomed? Insights from astrobiology.&quot; Sustainability 2.2 (2010): 591–603.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Sun#Life cycle|Sun]] will turn into a [[red giant]] in approximately 6 billion years.  Life on Earth will become impossible due to a rise in temperature long before the planet is actually swallowed up by the Sun.&lt;ref name=&quot;zeilik&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |last=Zeilik |first=M.A. |last2=Gregory |first2=S.A.|title=Introductory Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics |edition=4th |page=322 |publisher=Saunders College Publishing |year=1998 |isbn=0-03-006228-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; Even later, the Sun will become a [[white dwarf]].

== See also ==
{{portal|Philosophy|Religion}}
{{div col|content=&lt;!---Alphabetical (linkname):---&gt;
* [[Abomination of Desolation]]
* [[Ancient Aztec eschatology]]
* [[Apocalypse]]
* [[Armageddon]]
* [[Cosmogony]]
* [[The Day of the Lord]]
* [[List of dates predicted for apocalyptic events]]
* [[Doomsday cult]]
* [[Eschatology (religious movement)]]
* ''[[Götterdämmerung]]''
* [[Judgment day]]
* [[Millennialism]]
* [[Millenarianism]]
* [[Messianism]]
* [[Ragnarök]]
* [[Realized eschatology]]
* [[Ussher chronology]]
* [[Whore of Babylon]]
* [[List of eschatological topics]]
}}

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== Further reading ==
* Craig C. Hill, ''In God's Time: The Bible and the Future'', Grand Rapids: Eerdmans 2002. {{ISBN|0-8028-6090-7}}
* [[Dave Hunt (Christian apologist)|Dave Hunt]], ''A Cup of Trembling'', Harvest House Publishers, Eugene, (Oregon) 1995 {{ISBN|1-56507-334-7}}.
* Jonathan Menn, ''Biblical Eschatology'', Eugene, Oregon, Wipf &amp; Stock 2013. {{ISBN|978-1-62032-579-7}}.
* [[Joseph Ratzinger]]., ''Eschatology: Death and Eternal Life'', Washington D.C.: [[Catholic University of America Press]] 1985. {{ISBN|978-0-8132-1516-7}}.
* Robert Sungenis, Scott Temple, David Allen Lewis, ''Shock Wave 2000!'' subtitled ''The [[Harold Camping]] 1994 Debacle'', New Leaf Press, Inc. 2004 {{ISBN|0-89221-269-1}}
* Stephen Travis, ''Christ Will Come Again: Hope for the Second Coming of Jesus'', Toronto: Clements Publishing 2004. {{ISBN|1-894667-33-6}}
* Jerry L. Walls (ed.), ''The Oxford Handbook of Eschatology'', New York: Oxford University Press 2008. {{ISBN|978-0-19-973588-4}}

== External links ==
*[http://www.catholic.com/encyclopedia/eschatology Catholic Encyclopedia: Eschatology]
*[http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/articles/5849-eschatology Jewish Encyclopedia: Eschatology]
 
{{Subject bar|q=y|wikt=y|s=y|s-search=Portal:Eschatology|commons=y|d=y|d-search=Q170337}}

{{Doomsday}}
{{Time in religion and mythology}}
{{Theology |eschatology}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Eschatology| ]]
[[Category:Prophecy]]
[[Category:Mythology]]</text>
      <sha1>lkk3vvc7ilyq0rr8lochh3mdue8xl7m</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
