  <page>
    <title>Excalibur</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9717</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943385909</id>
      <parentid>942229547</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-03-01T16:31:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>130.105.53.23</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Arthur's other weapons */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Legendary sword of King Arthur}}
{{Other uses}}
{{Infobox fictional artifact
|name            = Excalibur
|image           = File:Arthur-Pyle Excalibur the Sword.JPG
|caption         = ''Excalibur the Sword'' by [[Howard Pyle]] (1903)
|alt             =
|source          = [[Arthurian legend]]
|first           = 
|type            = [[Legendary sword]]
|owner           = [[King Arthur]], [[Gawain]], [[Merlin]]
|traits          = 
|uses            = 
|}}

'''Excalibur''' ({{IPAc-en|ɛ|k|ˈ|s|k|æ|l|ɪ|b|ər}}) is the [[Legendary swords|legendary sword]] of [[King Arthur]], sometimes also [[magic sword|attributed with magical powers]] or associated with the rightful [[sovereignty]] of Britain. Excalibur and the [[#Excalibur and the Sword in the Stone|Sword in the Stone]] (the proof of Arthur's lineage) are sometimes said to be the same weapon, but in most versions they are considered separate. Excalibur was associated with the [[Arthurian legend]] very early on. In [[Welsh language|Welsh]], it is called ''Caledfwlch''; in [[Cornish language|Cornish]], ''Calesvol''; in [[Breton language|Breton]], ''Kaledvoulc'h''; and in [[Latin language|Latin]], ''Caliburnus''.

==Forms and etymologies==
The name ''Excalibur'' ultimately derives from the [[Welsh language|Welsh]] ''Caledfwlch'' (and [[Breton language|Breton]] ''Kaledvoulc'h'', [[Middle Cornish]] ''Calesvol''), which is a [[Compound (linguistics)|compound]] of ''{{lang|cy|caled}}'' &quot;hard&quot; and ''{{Lang|cy|bwlch}}'' &quot;breach, cleft&quot;.{{sfn|Bromwich|Simon Evans|1992|pp=64–65}} Caledfwlch appears in several early Welsh works, including the prose tale ''[[Culhwch and Olwen]]''. The name was later used in Welsh adaptations of foreign material such as the ''Brut''s (chronicles), which were based on [[Geoffrey of Monmouth]]. It is often considered to be related to the phonetically similar ''[[Caladbolg]]'', a sword borne by several figures from [[Irish mythology]], although a borrowing of ''Caledfwlch'' from Irish ''Caladbolg'' has been considered unlikely by [[Rachel Bromwich]] and D. Simon Evans. They suggest instead that both names &quot;may have similarly arisen at a very early date as generic names for a sword&quot;. This sword then became exclusively the property of Arthur in the British tradition.{{sfn|Bromwich|Simon Evans|1992|pp=64–65}}{{sfn|Green|2007|p=156}}

Geoffrey of Monmouth, in his ''[[Historia Regum Britanniae]]'' (''The History of the Kings of Britain'', c. 1136), [[Latinisation (literature)|Latinised]] the name of Arthur's sword as ''Caliburnus'' (potentially influenced by the Medieval Latin spelling ''calibs'' of [[Classical Latin]] ''chalybs'', from [[Greek language|Greek]] ''chályps'' [''χάλυψ''] &quot;steel&quot;). Most Celticists consider Geoffrey's ''Caliburnus'' to be derivative of a [[Lost works|lost]] [[Old Welsh]] text in which ''bwlch'' (Old Welsh ''bulc[h]'') had not yet been [[Lenition|lenited]] to ''fwlch'' ([[Middle Welsh]] ''vwlch'' or ''uwlch'').{{sfn|Ford|1983|p=271}}{{sfn|MacKillop|1998|pp=64–65, 174}}{{sfn|Bromwich|Simon Evans|1992|pp=64–65}} In the late 15th/early 16th-century Middle Cornish play ''[[Beunans Ke]]'', Arthur's sword is called ''Calesvol'', which is etymologically an exact Middle Cornish cognate of the Welsh ''Caledfwlch''. It is unclear if the name was borrowed from the Welsh (if so, it must have been an early loan, for phonological reasons), or represents an early, [[Common Brittonic|pan-Brittonic]] traditional name for Arthur's sword.&lt;ref&gt;Koch, John. ''Celtic Culture: A Historical Encyclopedia'', Volume 1, ABC-CLIO, 2006, p. 329.&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Old French]] sources this then became ''Escalibor'', ''Excalibor'', and finally the familiar ''Excalibur''. [[Geoffrey Gaimar]], in his Old French ''[[L'Estoire des Engleis]]'' (1134-1140), mentions Arthur and his sword: &quot;this Constantine was the nephew of Arthur, who had the sword Caliburc&quot; (&quot;''Cil Costentin, li niès Artur, Ki out l'espée Caliburc''&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;Hardy, T.D. and Martin, C. T. (eds./trans.), Gaimar, Geoffrey. ''L'Estoire des Engles'' (lines 45-46), Eyre and Spottiswoode, London, 1889, p. 2.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Wright, T. (ed.); Gaimar, Geoffrey. ''Gaimar, Havelok et Herward'', [[Caxton Society]], London, 1850, p. 2&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Wace]]'s ''[[Roman de Brut]]'' (c. 1150-1155), an Old French translation and versification of Geoffrey's ''Historia'', the sword is called ''Calabrum'', ''Callibourc'', ''Chalabrun'', and ''Calabrun'' (with alternate spellings such as ''Chalabrum'', ''Calibore'', ''Callibor'', ''Caliborne'', ''Calliborc'', and ''Escaliborc'', found in various manuscripts of the ''Brut'').&lt;ref&gt;De Lincy, Roux (ed.), Wace, ''Roman de Brut'', v. II, Edouard Frère, Rouen, 1838, pp. 51, 88, 213, 215.&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Chrétien de Troyes]]' late 12th-century Old French [[Perceval, the Story of the Grail|''Perceval'']], Arthur's knight [[Gawain]] carries the sword ''Escalibor'' and it is stated, &quot;for at his belt hung Escalibor, the finest sword that there was, which sliced through iron as through wood&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Bryant, Nigel (trans., ed.). ''Perceval: The Story of the Grail'', DS Brewer, 2006, p. 69.&lt;/ref&gt; (''&quot;Qu'il avoit cainte Escalibor, la meillor espee qui fust, qu'ele trenche fer come fust&quot;''&lt;ref&gt;Roach, William. ''Chrétien De Troyes: Le Roman De Perceval ou Le Conte Du Graal'', Librairie Droz, 1959, p. 173.&lt;/ref&gt;). This statement was probably picked up by the author of the ''Estoire Merlin'', or Vulgate Merlin, where the author (who was fond of fanciful folk etymologies) asserts that Escalibor &quot;is a [[Hebrew language|Hebrew]] name which means in French 'cuts iron, steel, and wood'&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Loomis, R. S. ''Arthurian Tradition and Chrétien de Troyes'', Columbia, 1949, p. 424.&lt;/ref&gt; (&quot;''c'est non Ebrieu qui dist en franchois trenche fer &amp; achier et fust''&quot;; note that the word for &quot;steel&quot; here, achier, also means &quot;blade&quot; or &quot;sword&quot; and comes from medieval Latin ''aciarium'', a derivative of ''acies'' &quot;sharp&quot;, so there is no direct connection with Latin ''chalybs'' in this etymology). It is from this fanciful etymological musing that [[Thomas Malory]] got the notion that Excalibur meant &quot;cut steel&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Vinaver, Eugene (ed.) ''The works of Sir Thomas Malory'', Volume 3. Clarendon, 1990, p. 1301.&lt;/ref&gt; (&quot;{{'}}''the name of it,' said the lady, 'is Excalibur, that is as moche to say, as Cut stele''{{'}}&quot;).

==Excalibur and the Sword in the Stone==
{{multiple image
| width = 
| align = left
| image2 = An island story; a child's history of England (1906) (14801002423).jpg
| image3 = CRANE King Arthur asks the lady of the lake for the sword Excalibur.jpg
| footer = 
| direction = vertical
| caption2 = The drawing of the sword from the stone as depicted in [[Henrietta Elizabeth Marshall]]'s ''[[Our Island Story]]'' (1906)
| caption3 = &quot;King Arthur asks the [[Lady of the Lake]] for the sword Excalibur.&quot; [[Walter Crane]]'s illustration for [[Henry Gilbert]]'s ''King Arthur's Knights: The Tales Retold for Boys and Girls'' (1911)
}}

In Arthurian romance, a number of explanations are given for Arthur's possession of Excalibur. In [[Robert de Boron]]'s ''[[Merlin (poem)|Merlin]]'', the first tale to mention the &quot;sword in the stone&quot; motif, Arthur obtained the British throne by pulling a sword from an anvil sitting atop a stone that appeared in a churchyard on Christmas Eve.&lt;ref&gt;Bryant, Nigel (ed, trans), Merlin and the Grail: Joseph of Arimathea, Merlin, Perceval : the Trilogy of Prose Romances Attributed to Robert de Boron, DS Brewer, 2001, p. 107ff.&lt;/ref&gt; In this account, as foretold by [[Merlin]], the act could not be performed except by &quot;the true king,&quot; meaning the divinely appointed king or true heir of [[Uther Pendragon]]. As Malory writes: &quot;''Whoso pulleth out this sword of this stone and anvil, is rightwise king born.''&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Sir Thomas Malory, William Caxton &quot;Morte Darthur: Sir Thomas Malory's Book of King Arthur and of His Noble Knights of the Round Table&quot;. p. 28. J.B. Lippincott and Company, 1868.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group=note&gt;This version also appears in the 1938 Arthurian novel ''[[The Sword in the Stone (novel)|The Sword in the Stone]]'' by British author [[T. H. White]], and the [[The Sword in the Stone (1963 film)|Disney adaptation]]; they both quote the line from Thomas Malory in the 15th century.&lt;/ref&gt; The identity of this sword as Excalibur is made explicit in the later Prose ''Merlin'', part of the [[Lancelot-Grail]] cycle (the Vulgate Cycle).&lt;ref&gt;Micha, Alexandre (ed.). ''Merlin: roman du XIIIe siècle'' (Geneva: Droz, 1979).&lt;/ref&gt;

However, in the most famous English-language version of the Arthurian tales, Malory's 15th-century ''[[Le Morte d'Arthur]]'', early in his reign Arthur breaks the Sword from the Stone while in combat against King [[Pellinore]], and is given Excalibur by the Lady of the Lake in exchange for a later boon. Similarly, in the [[Post-Vulgate Cycle]], Excalibur was given to Arthur by the [[Lady of the Lake]] sometime after he began to reign. In the [[Lancelot-Grail|Vulgate ''Mort Artu'']], Arthur is at the brink of death and so orders [[Griflet]] to throw the sword into the enchanted lake; after two failed attempts (as he felt such a great sword should not be thrown away), Griflet finally complies with the wounded king's request and a hand emerges from the lake to catch it. This tale becomes attached to [[Bedivere]] instead of Griflet in Malory and the English tradition.{{sfn|Lacy|1996}} Malory records both versions of the legend in his ''Le Morte d'Arthur'', naming both swords as Excalibur.{{sfn|Malory|1997|p=[http://quod.lib.umich.edu/c/cme/MaloryWks2/1:2?rgn=div1;view=fulltext 7]}}{{sfn|Malory|1997|p=[http://quod.lib.umich.edu/c/cme/MaloryWks2/1:3.7?rgn=div2;view=fulltext 46]}}

==Other roles and attributes==
===Welsh stories===
In Welsh legends, Arthur's sword is known as ''Caledfwlch''. In ''Culhwch and Olwen'', it is one of Arthur's most valuable possessions and is used by Arthur's warrior [[Llenlleawg]] the Irishman to kill the Irish king Diwrnach while stealing his magical cauldron. Irish mythology mentions a weapon ''Caladbolg'', the sword of [[Fergus mac Róich]], which was also known for its incredible power and was carried by some of Ireland's greatest heroes. The name, which can also mean &quot;hard cleft&quot; in [[Irish language|Irish]], appears in the plural, ''caladbuilc'', as a generic term for &quot;great swords&quot; in ''Togail Troi'' (&quot;The Destruction of [[Troy]]&quot;), a 10th-century Irish translation of the classical tale.&lt;ref&gt;Thurneysen, R. &quot;Zur Keltischen Literatur und Grammatik&quot;, ''Zeitschrift für celtische Philologie'', Volume 12, p. 281ff.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;O'Rahilly, T.  F. ''Early Irish history and mythology'', Dublin Institute for Advanced Studies, 1957, p. 68.&lt;/ref&gt;

Though not named as Caledfwlch, Arthur's sword is described vividly in ''[[The Dream of Rhonabwy]]'', one of the tales associated with the ''Mabinogion'' (as translated by Jeffrey Gantz): &quot;Then they heard [[Cador|Cadwr Earl of Cornwall]] being summoned, and saw him rise with Arthur's sword in his hand, with a design of two [[Chimera (mythology)|chimeras]] on the golden hilt; when the sword was unsheathed what was seen from the mouths of the two chimeras was like two flames of fire, so dreadful that it was not easy for anyone to look.&quot;{{sfn|Gantz|1987|p=184}}

===Other versions===
Geoffrey's ''Historia'' is the first non-Welsh source to speak of the sword. Geoffrey says the sword was forged in [[Avalon]] and Latinises the name &quot;Caledfwlch&quot; as ''Caliburnus''. When his influential pseudo-history made it to [[Continental Europe]], writers altered the name further until it finally took on the popular form ''Excalibur'' (various spellings in the medieval Arthurian romance and chronicle tradition include: ''Calabrun'', ''Calabrum'', ''Calibourne'', ''Callibourc'', ''Calliborc'', ''Calibourch'', ''Escaliborc'', and ''Escalibor''&lt;ref&gt;Zimmer, Heinrich. &quot;Bretonische Elemente in der Arthursage des Gottfried von Monmouth&quot;, ''Zeitschrift für französische Sprache und Literatur'', Volume 12, E. Franck's, 1890, p. 236.&lt;/ref&gt;). The legend was expanded upon in the Vulgate Cycle and in the Post-Vulgate Cycle which emerged in its wake. Both included the work known as the ''Prose Merlin'', but the Post-Vulgate authors left out the ''Merlin'' continuation from the earlier cycle, choosing to add an original account of Arthur's early days including a new origin for Excalibur.

{{multiple image
| width = 
| align = 
| image1 = 326 The Romance of King Arthur.jpg
| image2 = Arthur-Pyle Queen Morgana loses Excalibur His Sheath.JPG
| footer = 
| direction = vertical
| caption1 = &quot;How [[Galahad]] drew out the sword from the floating stone at [[Camelot]].&quot; [[Arthur Rackham]]'s illustration for [[Alfred W. Pollard]]'s ''The Romance of King Arthur'' (1917)
| caption2 = &quot;[[Morgan le Fay|Queen Morgana]] Loses Excalibur His Sheath.&quot; [[Howard Pyle]]'s illustration for ''[[The Story of King Arthur and His Knights]]'' (1903)
}}

In several early French works, such as [[Chrétien de Troyes]]' ''[[Perceval, the Story of the Grail]]'' and the Vulgate ''Lancelot Proper'' section, Excalibur is used by Gawain, Arthur's nephew and one of his best knights. This is in contrast to later versions, where Excalibur belongs solely to the king. The challenge of drawing a sword from a stone also appears in the later Arthurian stories of [[Galahad]], whose achievement of the task indicates that he is destined to find the [[Holy Grail]].

In many versions, Excalibur's blade was engraved with phrases on opposite sides: &quot;Take me up&quot; and &quot;Cast me away&quot; (or similar). In addition, when Excalibur was first drawn, in the first battle testing Arthur's sovereignty, its blade blinded his enemies. Malory&lt;ref&gt;Book I, 19, from ''The Works of Sir Thomas Malory,'' Ed. [[Eugène Vinaver|Vinaver, Eugène]], 3rd ed. Field, Rev. P. J. C. (1990). 3 vol. Oxford: Oxford University Press. {{ISBN|0-19-812344-2}}, {{ISBN|0-19-812345-0}}, {{ISBN|0-19-812346-9}}. (This is taken from the [[Le Morte d'Arthur|Winchester Manuscript]]).&lt;/ref&gt; writes: &quot;''thenne he drewe his swerd Excalibur, but it was so breyght in his enemyes eyen that it gaf light lyke thirty torchys.''&quot;&lt;ref group=note&gt;Nineteenth-century poet [[Alfred Tennyson, 1st Baron Tennyson|Alfred, Lord Tennyson]], described the sword in full [[Romanticism|Romantic]] detail in his poem &quot;Morte d'Arthur&quot;, later rewritten as &quot;The Passing of Arthur&quot;, one of the ''[[Idylls of the King]]'': &quot;There drew he forth the brand Excalibur, / And o’er him, drawing it, the winter moon, / Brightening the skirts of a long cloud, ran forth / And sparkled keen with frost against the hilt / For all the haft twinkled with [[diamond]] sparks, / Myriads of [[topaz]]-lights, and [[jacinth]]-work / Of subtlest jewellery.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

In some tellings, Excalibur's [[scabbard]] was said to have powers of its own, as the one wearing it would not lose even a drop of blood. Any wounds received while wearing the scabbard would not bleed at all, thus preventing the death of the wearer. For this reason, Merlin chides Arthur for preferring the sword over the scabbard, saying that the latter was the greater treasure. In the later romance tradition, including ''Le Morte d'Arthur'', the scabbard is stolen from Arthur by his half-sister [[Morgan le Fay]] in revenge for the death of her beloved [[Accolon]] and thrown into a lake, never to be found again. This act later enables the death of Arthur at the [[Battle of Camlann]].

==Arthur's other weapons==
Other weapons have been associated with Arthur. Welsh tradition also knew of a dagger named [[Carnwennan]] and a spear named Rhongomyniad that belonged to him. Carnwennan (&quot;little white-hilt&quot;) first appears in ''Culhwch and Olwen'', where Arthur uses it to slice the witch Orddu in half.{{sfn|Bromwich|Simon Evans|1992|pp=64–65}}{{sfn|Jones|Jones|1949|p=136}} Rhongomyniad (&quot;spear&quot; + &quot;striker, slayer&quot;) is also mentioned in ''Culhwch'', although only in passing; it appears as simply ''Ron'' (&quot;spear&quot;) in Geoffrey's ''Historia''. Geoffrey also names Arthur's shield as ''Pridwen'', but in ''Culhwch'', ''Prydwen'' (&quot;fair face&quot;) is the name of Arthur's ship while his shield is named ''Wynebgwrthucher'' (&quot;face of evening&quot;).{{sfn|Bromwich|Simon Evans|1992|pp=64–65}}{{sfn|Ford|1983|p=271}}

The [[Alliterative Morte Arthure|Alliterative ''Morte Arthure'']], a [[Middle English]] poem, mentions Clarent, a sword of peace meant for knighting and ceremonies as opposed to battle, which [[Mordred]] stole and then used to kill Arthur at Camlann.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lib.rochester.edu/camelot/teams/alstint.htm ''Alliterative Morte Arthure''], TEAMS, retrieved 26-02-2007&lt;/ref&gt; The Prose ''Lancelot'' of the Vulgate Cycle mentions a sword called Seure, or Secace in some manuscripts, which belonged to the king but was used by [[Lancelot]] in one battle.&lt;ref&gt;Warren, Michelle. ''History On The Edge: Excalibur and the Borders of Britain, 1100-1300'' (Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press) p. 212.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Similar weapons==
{{see also|List of magical weapons}}

In [[Welsh mythology]], the ''Dyrnwyn'' (&quot;White-Hilt&quot;), one of the [[Thirteen Treasures of the Island of Britain]], is said to be a powerful sword belonging to [[Rhydderch Hael]],&lt;ref&gt;Tri Thlws ar Ddeg, ed. and tr. Bromwich (1978): pp. 240–1.&lt;/ref&gt; one of the Three Generous Men of Britain mentioned in the [[Welsh Triads]]. When drawn by a worthy or well-born man, the entire blade would blaze with fire. Rhydderch was never reluctant to hand the weapon to anyone, hence his nickname Hael &quot;the Generous&quot;, but the recipients, as soon as they had learned of its peculiar properties, always rejected the sword.

There are other similar weapons described in other mythologies. In particular, [[Claíomh Solais]], which is an Irish term meaning &quot;Sword of Light&quot;, or &quot;Shining Sword&quot;, appears in a number of orally transmitted Irish folk-tales. The Sword in the Stone has an analogue in some versions of the story of [[Sigurd]], whose father, [[Sigmund]], draws the sword [[Gram (mythology)|Gram]] out of the tree [[Barnstokkr]] where it is embedded by the Norse god [[Odin]]. A sword in the stone legend is also associated with the 12th-century Italian [[Galgano Guidotti|Saint Galgano]]. {{clear left}}

==Notes==
{{reflist|group=note}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

===Sources===
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book|last1=Bromwich|first1=R.|last2=Simon Evans|first2=D.|title=Culhwch and Olwen. An Edition and Study of the Oldest Arthurian Tale|url=https://archive.org/details/culhwcholwenedit00brom|url-access=registration|location=Cardiff|publisher=University of Wales Press|year=1992|ref=harv}}
* {{cite journal|last=Ford|first=P.K.|title=On the Significance of some Arthurian Names in Welsh|journal=[[Bulletin of the Board of Celtic Studies]]|volume=30|year=1983|pages=268–73|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Gantz|first=Jeffrey|title=The Mabinogion|year=1987|location=New York|publisher=Penguin|isbn=0-14-044322-3|ref=harv|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/mabinogion0000gant}}
* {{cite book|last=Green|first=T.|title=Concepts of Arthur|url=http://www.arthuriana.co.uk/concepts|location=Stroud|publisher=Tempus|year=2007|ISBN=978-0-7524-4461-1|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last1=Jones|first1=T.|last2=Jones|first2=G.|title=The Mabinogion|location=London|publisher=Dent|year=1949|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Lacy|first=Norris J.|title=Lancelot-Grail: The Old French Arthurian Vulgate and Post-Vulgate in Translation|location=New York|publisher=Garland|year=1996|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=MacKillop|first=James|title=Dictionary of Celtic Mythology|location=Oxford|publisher=Oxford University Press|year=1998|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Malory|first=Thomas|authorlink=Thomas Malory|title=Le Morte D'Arthur|publisher=University of Michigan Humanities Text Initiative|year=1997|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Micha|first=Alexandre|title=Merlin: roman du XIIIe siècle|location=Geneva|publisher=Droz|year=1979|ref=harv}}
{{refend}}

==Further reading==
*Lacy, N. J (ed). ''The New Arthurian Encyclopedia.'' (London: Garland. 1996). {{ISBN|0-8153-2303-4}}.

==External links==
{{Commons category|Excalibur}}
*[http://www.lib.rochester.edu/camelot/swrdmenu.htm The Camelot Project at the University of Rochester: Excalibur and the Sword in the Stone]

{{Arthurian Legend}}
{{Celtic mythology (Welsh)}}
{{Geoffrey of Monmouth}}
{{Notable swords}}

[[Category:Arthurian legend]]
[[Category:Fictional swords]]
[[Category:Geoffrey of Monmouth]]
[[Category:Medieval legends]]
[[Category:Mythological swords]]</text>
      <sha1>oz4v96tmz9wuvgz22hekl2gl2dq80td</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
