  <page>
    <title>List of recently extinct bird species</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9731</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942610116</id>
      <parentid>941811422</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-25T18:54:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Iridescent</username>
        <id>937705</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* References */Cleanup and [[WP:AWB/T|typo fixing]], [[WP:AWB/T|typo(s) fixed]]: 75-93 → 75–93</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Wikimedia list article}}
{{pp-pc1}}
 
:''This page refers only to birds that have gone extinct since 1500; for the list of birds known only from fossils, see [[List of fossil bird genera]]. For birds extinct in Late Quaternary prehistoric times and usually known from specimens not completely fossilized, see [[List of Late Quaternary prehistoric bird species]].''

Over 190 species of [[bird]]s have become [[Extinction|extinct]] since 1500, and the rate of extinction seems to be increasing. The situation is exemplified by [[Hawaii]], where 30% of all known recently extinct bird [[taxa]] originally lived. Other areas, such as [[Guam]], have also been hit hard; Guam has lost over 60% of its native bird taxa in the last 30 years, many of them due to the introduced [[brown tree snake]].

Currently there are approximately 10,000 living species of birds, with an estimated 1,200 considered to be under threat of extinction.

Island species in general, and flightless island species in particular, are most at risk. The disproportionate number of [[Rallidae|rails]] in the list reflects the tendency of that family to lose the ability to fly when geographically isolated. Even more rails became extinct before they could be described by scientists; these taxa are listed in [[List of Late Quaternary prehistoric bird species]].

The extinction dates given below are usually approximations of the actual date of extinction. In some cases, more exact dates are given as it is sometimes possible to pinpoint the date of extinction to a specific year or even day (the [[San Benedicto rock wren]] is possibly the most extreme example&amp;mdash;its extinction could be timed with an accuracy of maybe half an hour). Extinction dates in the literature are usually the dates of the last verified record (credible observation or specimen taken); for many Pacific birds that became extinct shortly after European contact, however, this leaves an uncertainty period of over a century, because the islands on which they lived were only rarely visited by scientists.

[[File:Edwards' Dodo.jpg|thumb|alt=Painting of a dodo, with a red parrot on its left side, and a blue one at its right|The famous &quot;Edwards' [[Dodo]]&quot;, painted by [[Roelant Savery]] in 1626]]

==Extinct bird species==

===[[Aepyornithiformes]]===
* [[Elephant bird]], ''Aepyornis maximus'' and/or ''A. medius'' (Madagascar, 16th century?)

===[[Dinornithiformes]]===
* [[Upland moa]], ''Megalapteryx didinus'' (South Island, New Zealand, late 15th century?)
===[[Apterygiformes]]===

* West Coast spotted kiwi, ''Apteryx occidentalis'' (South Island, New Zealand, c.&amp;nbsp;1900)
*:A doubtful form known from a single bird; may be a [[little spotted kiwi]] subspecies or a hybrid between that species and the [[rowi]].

===[[Anseriformes]]===
[[Image:Camptorynchus labradoriusNHDP078CB.jpg|thumb|[[Labrador duck]]]]
[[Duck]]s, [[goose|geese]] and [[swan]]s
* [[Crested shelduck]], ''Tadorna cristata'' (Northeastern Asia, late 20th century?)
*:A [[Relict (biology)|relict species]] from northeastern Asia. Officially [[Endangered species|critically endangered]] due to recent unconfirmed reports.
* [[Réunion sheldgoose]], ''Alopochen kervazoi'' (Réunion, Mascarenes, c.1690s)
* [[Mauritius sheldgoose]], ''Alopochen mauritianus'' (Mauritius, Mascarenes, c.1695)
* [[Amsterdam wigeon]], ''Mareca marecula'' (Amsterdam Island, South Indian Ocean, c.1800)
* Saint Paul Island duck, ''Anas'' sp. (Saint Paul Island, South Indian Ocean, c.1800)
*: Only known by a painting from 1793. Might be identical with the Amsterdam wigeon or a distinct species or subspecies.
* [[Mascarene teal]], ''Anas theodori'' (Mauritius and Réunion, Mascarenes, late 1690s)
* [[Mariana mallard]], ''Anas oustaleti'' (Marianas, West Pacific, 1981)
* [[Finsch's duck]], ''Chenonetta finschi'' (New Zealand, possibly survived to 1870)
* [[Pink-headed duck]], ''Rhodonessa caryophyllacea'' (East India, Bangladesh, North Myanmar, 1945?)– a reclassification into the genus ''Netta'' is recommended, but not generally accepted.
*:Officially [[Endangered species|critically endangered]]; recent surveys have failed to rediscover it.
* Réunion pochard, ''Aythya'' cf. ''innotata'' (Réunion, Mascarenes, c.1690s)
*:A bone of a pochard found on Réunion seems to resolve the reports of ''canards'' other than the [[Mauritian duck]] having occurred on the island. The taxonomic status of this form cannot be resolved until more material is found, however.
* [[Labrador duck]],  ''Camptorhynchus labradorius'' (Northeastern North America, ca. 1878)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://datazone.birdlife.org/species/factsheet/22680418|title=Labrador Duck (Camptorhynchus labradorius) - BirdLife species factsheet|website=datazone.birdlife.org|access-date=2017-03-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[New Zealand merganser]], ''Mergus australis'' (New Zealand, Auckland Islands, Southwest Pacific, c.1902)

===[[Galliformes]]===
[[Image:Coturnix novaezelandiae.jpg|thumb|[[New Zealand quail]]]]
[[Quail]]s and relatives&lt;br /&gt;
See also Bokaak &quot;bustard&quot; under [[#Gruiformes|Gruiformes]] below
* The [[pile-builder megapode]], ''Megapodius molistructor'' may have survived on New Caledonia to the late 18th century as evidenced by descriptions of the bird named ''&quot;Tetrao australis&quot;'' and later ''&quot;Megapodius andersoni&quot;''.
* The [[Viti Levu scrubfowl]], ''Megapodius amissus'' of [[Viti Levu]] and possibly [[Kadavu Island|Kadavu]], [[Fiji]], may have survived to the early 19th or even the 20th century as suggested by circumstantial evidence.
* Raoul Island scrubfowl, ''Megapodius'' sp. (Raoul, Kermadec Islands, 1876)
*:A megapode is said to have inhabited Raoul Island until the population was wiped out in a volcanic eruption. It is not clear whether the birds represent a distinct taxon or derive from a prehistoric introduction by Polynesian seafarers.&lt;!-- Notornis 51(2):61 --&gt;
* [[New Zealand quail]], ''Coturnix novaezelandiae'' (New Zealand, 1875)
* [[Himalayan quail]], ''Ophrysia superciliosa'' (North India, late 19th century?)
*:Officially [[endangered species|critically endangered]]. Not recorded with certainty since 1876, but thorough surveys are still required, and there was a recent set of possible (though unlikely) sightings around [[Naini Tal]] in 2003. A little-known native name from Western [[Nepal]] probably refers to this bird, but for various reasons, no survey for ''Ophrysia'' has ever been conducted in that country, nor is it generally assumed to occur there (due to the native name being overlooked).

===[[Charadriiformes]]===
[[Image:greatauk-london.jpg|thumb|[[Great auk]] (''Pinguinus impennis''), [[Natural History Museum, London|Natural History Museum]], London, England]]
[[Shorebird]]s, [[gull]]s and [[auk]]s
* [[Javan lapwing]], ''Vanellus macropterus'' (Java, Indonesia, mid-20th century)
*:Officially classified as [[endangered species|critically endangered]], but as this conspicuous bird has not been recorded since 1940, it is almost certainly extinct.
*[[Christmas sandpiper]], ''Prosobonia cancellata'' ([[Kiritimati]] Island, [[Kiribati]], 1850s)
* [[Tahiti sandpiper]], ''Prosobonia leucoptera'' (Tahiti, Society Islands, 19th century)
* [[White-winged sandpiper]], ''Prosobonia ellisi'' (Moorea, Society Islands, 19th century)
*:Doubtfully distinct from ''P. leucoptera''.
* [[North Island snipe]], ''Coenocorypha barrierensis'' ([[North Island]], New Zealand, 1870s)
* [[South Island snipe]], ''Coenocorypha iredalei'' (South and Stewart Islands, New Zealand, 1964)
* [[Eskimo curlew]], ''Numenius borealis'' (Northern North America, late 20th century?)
*:May still exist; officially classified as [[Endangered species|critically endangered, possibly extinct]].
* [[Slender-billed curlew]], ''Numenius tenuirostris'' (Western Siberia, early first decade of the 21st century?)
*:May still exist; officially classified as [[Endangered species|critically endangered]]. A few birds were recorded in 2004, following several decades of increasing rarity. There was an unconfirmed sighting in Albania in 2007. A survey to find out whether this bird still exists is currently being undertaken by the RSPB ([[BirdLife International|BirdLife]] in the [[United Kingdom|UK]]).
* [[Great auk]], ''Pinguinus impennis'' (Newfoundland, 1852)
* [[Canary Islands oystercatcher]], ''Haematopus meadewaldoi'' (Eastern Canary Islands, E Atlantic, c.&amp;nbsp;1940?)
*:Later sightings of black oystercatchers off [[Senegal]] were not likely to be of this sedentary species, but two records from [[Tenerife]] - the last in 1981 - may be.

===[[Gruiformes]]===
[[Rallidae|Rail]]s and allies - probably [[paraphyletic]]

* [[Antillean cave rail]], ''Nesotrochis debooyi'', known by pre-Columbian bones from Puerto Rico and the Virgin Islands. Stories of an easy-to-catch bird named carrao heard by Alexander Wetmore in 1912 on Puerto Rico might refer to this species.
* [[Hawkins's rail|Hawkins' rail]], ''Diaphorapteryx hawkinsi'' (Chatham Islands, SW Pacific, 19th century)
* [[Red rail]], ''Aphanapteryx bonasia'' (Mauritius, Mascarenes, c.&amp;nbsp;1700)
* [[Rodrigues rail]], ''Erythromachus leguati'' (Rodrigues, Mascarenes, mid-18th century)
* [[Bar-winged rail]], ''Nesoclopeus poecilopterus'' (Fiji, Polynesia, c.&amp;nbsp;1980)
* [[Dieffenbach's rail]], ''Gallirallus dieffenbachii'' (Chatham Islands, SW Pacific, mid-19th century)
* [[Image:Gallirallus.pacificus.jpg|thumb|[[Tahiti rail]]]][[Tahiti rail]], ''Hypotaenidia pacificus'' (Tahiti, Society Islands, late 18th – 19th century)
* [[Wake Island rail]], ''Hypotaenidia wakensis'' (Wake Island, Micronesia, 1945)
* [[Tongatapu rail]], ''Gallirallus hypoleucus'' (Tongatapu, Tonga, late 18th - 19th century)
* [[New Caledonian rail]], ''Gallirallus lafresnanayanus'' (New Caledonia, Melanesia, c.&amp;nbsp;1900?)
*:Officially classified as [[Endangered species|critically endangered]], the last records were in 1984 and it seems that all available habitat is overrun by feral pigs and dogs, which prey on this bird.
* Vava'u rail, ''Gallirallus'' cf. ''vekamatolu'' (Vava'u, Tonga, early 19th century?)
*:This bird is known only from a drawing by the 1793 [[Alessandro Malaspina|Malaspina]] expedition, apparently depicting a species of ''Gallirallus''. The 'Eua rail, ''Gallirallus vekamatolu'', is known from prehistoric bones found on [['Eua]], but this species is almost certainly not ''G. vekamatolu'', as that bird was flightless and hence is unlikely to have settled three distant islands. However, it probably was a close relative.
* Norfolk Island rail, ''Gallirallus'' sp., may be the bird shown on a bad watercolor illustration made around 1800.
* [[Chatham rail]], ''Cabalus modestus'' (Chatham Islands, SW Pacific, c.&amp;nbsp;1900)
* [[Réunion rail]] or Dubois' wood-rail, ''Dryolimnas augusti'' (Réunion, Mascarenes, late 17th century)
* [[Ascension crake]], ''Mundia elpenor'' (Ascension, Island, Atlantic, late 17th century)– formerly ''Atlantisia''
* [[Saint Helena crake]], ''Porzana astrictocarpus'' (Saint Helena, Atlantic, early 16th century)
* [[Image:Laysanralle.jpg|thumb|The [[Laysan rail]] was an omnivore]][[Laysan rail]], ''Porzana palmeri'' (Laysan Island, Hawaiian Islands, 1944)
* [[Image:Hawaiirail.jpg|thumb|[[Hawaiian rail]]]][[Hawaiian rail]], ''Porzana sandwichensis'' (Big Island, Hawaiian Islands, c.&amp;nbsp;1890)
* [[Kosrae crake]], ''Porzana monasa'' (Kosrae, Carolines, c. mid-late 19th century)
* [[Miller's rail]], ''Porzana nigra'' (Tahiti, Society Islands, c.&amp;nbsp;1800)
*:Known only from paintings and descriptions; taxonomic status uncertain, as the material is often believed to refer to the extant [[spotless crake]].
* [[Saint Helena swamphen]], ''Aphanocrex podarces'' (Saint Helena, Atlantic, 16th century)– formerly ''Atlantisia''
* [[Image:PorphyrioAlbus.jpg|thumb|[[Lord Howe swamphen]]]][[Lord Howe swamphen]], ''Porphyrio albus'' ([[Lord Howe Island]], SW Pacific, early 19th century)
* [[Réunion swamphen]] or ''Oiseau bleu'', ''Porphyrio coerulescens'' (Réunion, Mascarenes, 18th century)
*:Known only from descriptions. Former existence of a ''Porphyrio'' on Réunion is fairly certain, but not proven to date.
* [[Marquesas swamphen]], ''Porphyrio paepae'' (Hiva Oa and Tahuata, Marquesas)
*:May have survived to c.&amp;nbsp;1900. In the lower right corner of [[Paul Gauguin]]'s 1902 painting ''Le Sorcier d'Hiva Oa ou le Marquisien à la cape rouge'' there is a bird which resembles native descriptions of ''P. paepae''.
* [[North Island takahē]], ''Porphyrio mantelli'', known from subfossil bones found in New Zealand's North Island; may have survived to 1894 or later.
* [[New Caledonian gallinule]], ''Porphyrio kukwiedei'' from New Caledonia, Melanesia, may have survived into historic times. The native name ''n'dino'' is thought to refer to this bird.
* [[Samoan wood rail]], ''Gallinula pacifica'' (Savai'i, Samoa, 1907?)
*:Probably better placed in the genus ''Pareudiastes'', unconfirmed reports from the late 20th century suggest it still survives in small numbers and therefore it is officially classified as [[Endangered species|critically endangered]].
* [[Makira woodhen]], ''Gallinula silvestris'' (Makira, Solomon Islands, mid-20th century?)
*:Only known from a single specimen, this rail is probably better placed in its own genus, ''Edithornis''. There are some unconfirmed recent records that suggest it still survives, and thus it is officially classified as [[Endangered species|critically endangered]].
* [[Tristan moorhen]], ''Gallinula nesiotis'' (Tristan da Cunha, Atlantic, late 19th century)
* [[Mascarene coot]], ''Fulica newtonii'' (Mauritius and Réunion, Mascarenes, c.&amp;nbsp;1700)
* Fernando de Noronha rail, Rallidae gen. et sp. indet. (Fernando de Noronha, W. Atlantic, 16th century?)
*:A distinct species of rail inhabited Fernando de Noronha island, but it has not been formally described yet. Probably was extant at first Western contact.
* Tahitian &quot;goose&quot;, Rallidae gen. et sp. indet. (Tahiti, late 18th century?)
*:Early travelers to Tahiti reported a &quot;goose&quot; that was found in the mountains. Altogether, a species of rail in the genus ''Porphyrio'' seems to be the most likely choice.
* Bokaak &quot;bustard&quot;, Rallidae? gen. et sp. indet. 'Bokaak'
*:An unidentified terrestrial bird is mentioned in an early report from Bokaak in the Marshall Islands. It is described as a &quot;[[bustard]]&quot; and may have been a rail or a [[megapode]]. In the former case it may have been a vagrant of an extant species; in any case, no bird that could be described as &quot;bustard-like&quot; is found on Bokaak today.&lt;ref name = spennemann2006&gt;Spennemann (2006)&lt;/ref&gt;
* Rallidae gen. et sp. indet. 'Amsterdam Island'
*:Unknown rail from [[Île Amsterdam|Amsterdam Island]]; one specimen found, but not recovered. Extinct by 1800, or it may have been a vagrant of an extant species.

===[[Podicipediformes]]===
[[Grebe]]s
* [[Colombian grebe]], ''Podiceps andinus'' (Bogotá area, Colombia, 1977)
* [[Alaotra grebe]], ''Tachybaptus rufolavatus'' (Lake Alaotra, Madagascar, 1985)
*:Officially declared extinct in 2010, 25 years after the last official sighting. Declined through habitat destruction and hybridization with the [[little grebe]]. Disappeared from only known location in the 1980s.
* [[Atitlán grebe]], ''Podilymbus gigas'' (Lake Atitlán, Guatemala, 1989)

=== [[Cathartiformes]] ===

* &quot;Painted vulture&quot;, ''Sarcoramphus sacra'' (Florida, United States, late 18th century?)
** A bird supposedly similar to the king vulture identified by [[William Bartram]] on his travels in the 1770s. Skeptics have stated that it is likely based on a misidentification of the [[northern caracara]], although evidence has increasingly shifted towards it being a valid species that existed, based on an independent illustration of a near-identical bird made several decades earlier by [[Eleazar Albin]]. See [[King vulture]] article for discussion.

===[[Pelecaniformes]]===
[[Pelican|Pelicans]] and related birds

* [[Bermuda night heron]], ''Nyctanassa carcinocatactes'' (Bermuda, West Atlantic, 17th century)
*:Sometimes assigned to the genus ''Nycticorax''.
*[[Réunion night heron]], ''Nycticorax duboisi'' (Réunion, Mascarenes, late 17th century)
*[[Mauritius night heron]], ''Nycticorax mauritianus'' (Mauritius, Mascarenes, c.&amp;nbsp;1700)
*[[Rodrigues night heron]], ''Nycticorax megacephalus'' (Rodrigues, Mascarenes, mid-18th century)
*[[Ascension night heron]], ''Nycticorax olsoni'' (Ascension Island, Atlantic, late 16th century?)
*:Known only from subfossil bones, but the description of a flightless Ascension bird by [[André Thévet]] cannot be identified with anything other than this species.
*[[New Zealand little bittern]], ''Ixobrychus novaezelandiae'' (New Zealand, late 19th century)
*:Long considered to be vagrant individuals of the Australian [[little bittern]], bones recovered from Holocene deposits indicate that this was indeed a distinct taxon, but it might not be a separate species.&lt;!-- Notornis 10(7):317 --&gt;
*[[Réunion ibis]], ''Threskiornis solitarius'' (Réunion, Mascarenes, early 18th century)
*:This species was the basis of the &quot;Réunion solitaire&quot;, a supposed relative of the [[dodo]] and the [[Rodrigues solitaire]]. Given the fact that ibis (but no dodo-like) bones were found on [[Réunion]] and that old descriptions match a flightless [[sacred ibis]] quite well, the &quot;Réunion solitaire&quot; hypothesis has been refuted.

===[[Suliformes]]===
[[Booby|Boobies]] and related birds

*[[Spectacled cormorant]], ''Phalacrocorax perspicillatus'' (Komandorski Islands, North Pacific, c.&amp;nbsp;1850)
*Mascarene booby, ''Papasula'' sp. (Mauritius and Rodrigues, Mascarenes, mid-19th century)
**An undescribed booby species that was formerly considered a population of [[Abbott's booby]]. Known physically only from subfossil bones, but is likely the bird referred to as a &quot;boeuf&quot; by early settlers. The &quot;boeuf&quot; was last recorded on Rodrigues in 1832 and likely went extinct following the deforestation of the island.

===[[Procellariiformes]]===
[[Petrel]]s, [[shearwater]]s, [[albatross]]es and [[storm petrel]]s.
* [[Olson's petrel]], ''Bulweria bifax'' (Saint Helena, Atlantic, early 16th century)
* [[Bermuda shearwater]], ''Puffinus parvus'' ([[Bermuda]], West Atlantic, 16th century)
* [[Saint Helena petrel]], ''Pseudobulweria rupinarum'' (Saint Helena, Atlantic, early 16th century)
* [[Jamaica petrel]], ''Pterodroma caribbaea'' (Jamaica, Caribbean)
*:Possibly a subspecies of the [[black-capped petrel]]; unconfirmed reports suggest it might survive. Officially classified as [[Endangered species|critically endangered, possibly extinct]].
* ''Pterodroma'' cf. ''leucoptera'' ([[Mangareva]], [[Gambier Islands]], 20th century?)
*:A wing of a carcass similar to [[Gould's petrel]] was recovered on Mangareva in 1922, where it possibly bred. No such birds are known to exist there today.
* [[Guadalupe storm petrel]], ''Oceanodroma macrodacyla'' (Guadalupe, East Pacific, 1910s)
*:Officially [[Endangered species|critically endangered, possibly extinct]], but a thorough survey in 2000 concluded the species was certainly extinct.
* [[Imber's petrel]], ''Pterodroma imberi''
*:Described from subfossil remains from the Chatham Islands, became apparently extinct in the early 19th century.

===[[Sphenisciformes]]===
[[Penguins]]
* The [[Chatham penguin]], ''Eudyptes'' sp. (Chatham Islands, SW Pacific), is only known from subfossil bones, but a bird kept captive at some time between 1867 and 1872 might refer to this taxon.&lt;!-- Notornis 41(S):165 --&gt;

===[[Columbiformes]]===
[[Image:Ectopistes migratoriusMCN2P28CA.jpg|thumb|Male [[passenger pigeon]]]]
[[Pigeon]]s, doves and [[dodo]]s&lt;br /&gt;
For the &quot;Réunion solitaire&quot;, see [[Réunion ibis]].
* [[Saint Helena dove]], ''Dysmoropelia dekarchiskos'', possibly survived into the Modern Era.
* [[Passenger pigeon]], ''Ectopistes migratorius'' (Eastern North America, 1914)
*:The passenger pigeon was once among the most common birds in the world, a single flock numbering up to 2.2 billion birds. It was hunted close to extinction for food and sport in the late 19th century. The last individual, [[Martha (passenger pigeon)|Martha]], died in the [[Cincinnati Zoo]] in 1914.
* [[Bonin wood pigeon]], '' Columba versicolor'' (Nakodo-jima and Chichi-jima, Ogasawara Islands, c.&amp;nbsp;1890)
* [[Ryukyu wood pigeon]], ''Columba jouyi'' (Okinawa and Daito Islands, Northwest Pacific, late 1930s)
* [[Réunion pink pigeon]], ''Nesoenas duboisi'' (Réunion, Mascarenes, c.&amp;nbsp;1700)
*:Formerly in ''Streptopelia''. There seems to have been at least another species of pigeon on Réunion (probably an ''Alectroenas''), but bones have not yet been found. It disappeared at the same time.
* [[Rodrigues pigeon]], ''Nesoenas rodericana'' (Rodrigues, Mascarenes, before 1690?)
*:Formerly in ''Streptopelia''. A possible subspecies of the [[Madagascar turtle dove]] (''N. picturata''), this seems not to be the bird observed by [[François Leguat|Leguat]]. Introduced rats might have killed it off in the late 17th century.
* [[Liverpool pigeon]], ''&quot;Caloenas&quot; maculata''
*:Also known as the spotted green pigeon, the only known specimen has been in [[Liverpool]] Museum since 1851 and was probably collected on a [[Pacific]] island for [[Edward Stanley, 13th Earl of Derby]]. It has been suggested that this bird came from [[Tahiti]] based on native lore about a somewhat similar extinct bird called the ''titi'', but this has not been verified.
*[[Purple-winged ground dove]], ''Claravis geoffroyi'' (Pampas, East-central South America, 2007?&lt;ref name=BLEX&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;)
* [[Sulu bleeding-heart]], ''Gallicolumba menagei'' (Tawitawi, Philippines, late 1990s?)
*:Officially listed as [[endangered species|critically endangered]]. Only known from two specimens taken in 1891. There have been a number of unconfirmed reports from all over the [[Sulu Archipelago]] in 1995, however, these reports stated that the bird had suddenly undergone a massive decline, and by now, habitat destruction is almost complete. If not extinct, this species is very rare, but the ongoing [[Moro Islamic Liberation Front|civil war]] prevents comprehensive surveys.
* [[Norfolk ground dove]], ''Gallicolumba norfolciensis'' (Norfolk Island, Southwest Pacific, c.&amp;nbsp;1800)
* [[Tanna ground dove]], ''Gallicolumba ferruginea'' (Tanna, Vanuatu, late 18th-19th century)
*:Only known from descriptions of two now-lost specimens.
* [[Thick-billed ground dove]], ''Gallicolumba salamonis'' (Makira and Ramos, Solomon Islands, mid-20th century?)
*:Last recorded in 1927, only two specimens exist. Declared extinct in 2005.
* [[Image:Microgoura meeki.jpg|thumb|[[Choiseul crested pigeon]]]][[Choiseul pigeon]], ''Microgoura meeki'' (Choiseul, Solomon Islands, early 20th century)
* [[Red-moustached fruit dove]], ''Ptilinopus mercierii'' (Nuku Hiva and Hiva Oa, Marquesas, mid-20th century)
*:Two subspecies, the little-known ''P. m. mercierii'' of Nuku Hiva (extinct mid-late 19th century) and ''P. m. tristrami'' of Hiva Oa.
* [[Negros fruit dove]], ''Ptilinopus arcanus'' (Negros, Philippines, late 20th century?)&lt;!-- Condor58:283 --&gt;
*:Known only from one specimen taken at the only documented sighting in 1953, the validity of this species has been questioned, but no good alternative to distinct species status has been proposed. Officially [[Endangered species|critically endangered]], it might occur on Panay, but no survey has located it. One possible record in 2002 does not seem to have been repeated.
* [[File:Extinctbirds1907 P22 Alectroenas nitidissima0325.png|thumb|[[Mauritius blue pigeon]]]][[Mauritius blue pigeon]], ''Alectroenas nitidissima'' (Mauritius, Mascarenes, c.&amp;nbsp;1830s)
* Farquhar blue pigeon, ''Alectroenas'' sp. (Farquhar Group, Seychelles, 19th century)
*:Only known from early reports; possibly a subspecies of the [[Comoros blue pigeon|Comoros]] or [[Seychelles blue pigeon]].
* [[Rodrigues grey pigeon]], ''&quot;Alectroenas&quot; rodericana'' (Rodrigues, Mascarenes, mid-18th century)
*:A mysterious bird of unknown affinities, known from a few bones and, as it seems, two historical reports.
* [[Dodo]], ''Raphus cucullatus'' (Mauritius, Mascarenes, late 17th century)
*:Called ''Didus ineptus'' by [[Carl Linnaeus|Linnaeus]]. A metre-high flightless bird found on [[Mauritius]]. Its forest habitat was lost when Dutch settlers moved to the island and the dodo's nests were destroyed by the monkeys, pigs and cats that the Dutch brought with them. The last specimen was killed in 1681, only 80 years after the arrival of the new predators.
* [[Rodrigues solitaire]], ''Pezophaps solitaria'' (Rodrigues, Mascarenes, c.&amp;nbsp;1730)

===[[Psittaciformes]]===
[[Parrot]]s
[[Image:Karolinasittich 01.jpg|thumb|Mounted specimen of ''[[Conuropsis carolinensis]]'', [[Museum Wiesbaden]], Germany]]
* [[New Caledonian lorikeet]], ''Charmosyna diadema'' (New Caledonia, Melanesia, mid-20th century?)
*:Officially [[Endangered species|critically endangered]], there have been no reliable reports of this bird since the early 20th century. It is, however, small and inconspicuous.
* [[Image:John-Gould-001.jpg|thumb|[[Norfolk kaka]]]][[Norfolk kaka]], '' Nestor productus'' (Norfolk and Philip Islands, SW Pacific, 1851?)
* [[Society parakeet]], ''Cyanoramphus ulietanus'' (Raiatea, Society Islands, late 18th century)
* [[Black-fronted parakeet]], ''Cyanoramphus zealandicus'' (Tahiti, Society Islands, c.&amp;nbsp;1850)
* [[Paradise parrot]], ''Psephotus pulcherrimus'' (Rockhampton area, Australia, late 1920s)
* [[Oceanic eclectus parrot]], ''Eclectus infectus'', known from subfossil bones found on Tonga, Vanuatu, and possibly Fiji, may have survived until the 18th century: a bird which seems to be a male ''Eclectus'' parrot was drawn in a report on the Tongan island of [[Vava'u|Vavaʻu]] by the [[Alessandro Malaspina|Malaspina]] expedition. Also a 19th-century Tongan name ''ʻāʻā'' (&quot;parrot&quot;) for &quot;a beautiful bird found only at [['Eua|ʻEua]]&quot; is attested (see here&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nzetc.org/tm/scholarly/tei-TreMaor-c1-5.html nzetc.org]&lt;/ref&gt; under &quot;kaka&quot;). This seems to refer either ''E. infectus'' which in Tonga is only known from Vavaʻu and ʻEua, or the extirpated population of the [[collared lory]] which also occurred there. It is possible but unlikely that the species survived on ʻEua until the 19th century.
* [[Image:Psittacula.wardi.jgk.jpg|thumb|[[Seychelles parakeet]]]][[Seychelles parakeet]], ''Psittacula wardi'' (Seychelles, W Indian Ocean, 1883)
* [[Newton's parakeet]], ''Psittacula exsul'' (Rodrigues, Mascarenes, c.&amp;nbsp;1875)
* [[Mascarene grey parakeet]], ''Psittacula bensoni'' (Mauritius, possible Réunion as ''Psittacula cf bensoni''). Formerly described as Mauritius grey parrot, ''Lophopsittacus bensoni''.  Known from a 1602 sketch by Captain Willem van Westzanen and by subfossil bones described by [[David Thomas Holyoak]] in 1973. Might have survived to the mid-18th century.
* [[Mascarene parrot]], ''Mascarinus mascarin'' (Réunion and possibly Mauritius, Mascarenes, 1834?)
*:Last known individual was a captive bird which was alive before 1834.
* [[Broad-billed parrot]], ''Lophopsittacus mauritianus'' (Mauritius, Mascarenes, 1680?)
*:May have survived to the late 18th century.
* [[Rodrigues parrot]], ''Necropsittacus rodericanus'' (Rodrigues, Mascarenes, late 18th century)
*:The species ''N. francicus'' is fictional, ''[[Réunion red and green parakeet|N. borbonicus]]'' most likely so.
* [[Glaucous macaw]], ''Anodorhynchus glaucus'' (N Argentina, early 20th century)
*:Officially [[Endangered species|critically endangered]] due to persistent rumors of wild birds, but probably extinct.
* [[Cuban macaw]], ''Ara tricolor'' (Cuba, West Indies, late 19th century)
*:A number of related species have been described from the West Indies, but are not based on good evidence. Several prehistoric forms are now known to have existed in the region, however.
* [[Carolina parakeet]], ''Conuropsis carolinensis'' (SE North America, c. 1930?)
*:Although the date of the last captive bird's death in the Cincinnati Zoo, 1918, is generally given as its extinction date, there are convincing reports of some wild populations persisting until later. Two subspecies, ''C. c. carolinensis'' (Carolina parakeet, east and south of the Appalachian range–extinct 1918 or c. 1930) and ''C. c. ludovicianus'' (Louisiana parakeet, west of the Appalachian range–extinct c. 1912).
* [[Guadeloupe parakeet]], ''Aratinga labati'' (Guadeloupe, West Indies, late 18th century)
*:Only known from descriptions, the former existence of this bird is likely for biogeographic reasons and because details as described cannot be referred to known species.
* [[Martinique amazon]], ''Amazona martinica'' (Martinique, West Indies, mid-18th century)
* [[Guadeloupe amazon]], ''Amazona violacea'' (Guadeloupe, West Indies, mid-18th century)
*:These extinct amazon parrots were originally described after travelers' descriptions. Both are now considered valid extinct species that are closely related to the [[imperial amazon]].

===[[Cuculiformes]]===
[[Cuckoo]]s
* [[Delalande's coua]], ''Coua delalandei'' (Madagascar, late 19th century?)
* [[Saint Helena cuckoo]], ''Nannococcyx psix'' (Saint Helena, Atlantic, 18th century)

===[[Falconiformes]]===
[[Bird of prey|Birds of prey]]
* [[Guadalupe caracara]], ''Caracara lutosa'' (Guadalupe, E Pacific, 1900 or 1903)
* [[Réunion kestrel]], ''Falco duboisi'' (Réunion, Mascarenes, c.&amp;nbsp;1700)

===[[Strigiformes]]===
[[Image:Keulemans Laughing Owl.jpg|thumb|[[Laughing owl]]]]
[[Typical owl]]s and [[barn owl]]s.
* [[Pernambuco pygmy owl]], ''Glaucidium mooreorum'' (Pernambuco, Brazil, 2001?&lt;ref name=BLEX&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Butchart |first1=Stuart |last2=Wheatley |first2=Hannah |last3=Lowe |first3=Stephen |last4=Westrip |first4=James |last5=Symes |first5=Andy |last6=Martin |first6=Rob |title=Data for: Which bird species have gone extinct? A novel quantitative classification approach |journal=Mendley Data |date=2018 |volume=v1 |url=https://data.mendeley.com/datasets/vvjhpmyxb4/1 |accessdate=29 May 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;)
*:Might still exist, classified as critically endangered. A 2018 [[BirdLife]] study citing extinction patterns recommended reclassifying this species as possibly extinct.
* [[Réunion owl]], ''Mascarenotus grucheti'' (Réunion, Mascarenes, late 17th century?)
* [[Mauritius owl]], ''Mascarenotus sauzieri'' (Mauritius, Mascarenes, c.&amp;nbsp;1850)
* [[Rodrigues owl]], ''Mascarenotus murivorus'' (Rodrigues, Mascarenes, mid-18th century)
*:The preceding three species were variously placed in ''Bubo'', ''Athene'', ''&quot;Scops&quot;'' (=''Otus''), ''Strix'' and ''Tyto'' before their true affinity was realized.
* New Caledonian boobook, ''Ninox'' cf. ''novaeseelandiae'' (New Caledonia, Melanesia)
*:Known only from prehistoric bones, but might still survive.
* [[Laughing owl]], ''Sceloglaux albifacies'' (New Zealand, 1914?)
*:Two subspecies, ''S. a. albifacies'' (South Island and Stewart Island, extinct 1914?) and ''S. a. rufifacies'' (North Island, extinct c.&amp;nbsp;1870s?); circumstantial evidence suggests that small remnants survived until the early/mid-20th century.
* The [[Puerto Rican barn owl]], ''Tyto cavatica'', known from prehistoric remains found in caves of Puerto Rico, West Indies; may still have existed in 1912, given reports of the presence of cave-roosting owls.
* The Andros Island barn owl, ''[[Tyto pollens]]'', known from prehistoric remains found on Andros (Bahamas); may have survived to the 16th century, as indicated by the &quot;[[chickcharney]]&quot; legend.
* [[Siau scops owl]], ''Otus siaoensis'' (20th century?)
*: Only known from the holotype collected in 1866. Endemic to the small volcanic island of [[Siau Island|Siau]] north of [[Sulawesi]] in [[Indonesia]]; might still survive, as there are ongoing rumors of scops owls at Siau.

===[[Caprimulgiformes]]===
'''[[Caprimulgidae]]''' - nightjars and nighthawks&lt;br /&gt;
Reclusive ground-nesting birds that sally out at night to hunt for large [[insects]] and similar prey. They are easily located by the males' song, but this is not given all year. Habitat destruction represents currently the biggest threat, while island populations are threatened by introduced mammalian predators, notably dogs, cats, pigs and mongooses.
* [[Jamaican poorwill]], ''Siphonorhis americana'' (Jamaica, West Indies, late 19th century?)
*:Reports of unidentifiable nightjars from the 1980s in habitat appropriate for ''S. americana'' suggest that this cryptic species may still exist. Research into this possibility is currently underway; pending further information, it is classified as [[Endangered species|critically endangered, possibly extinct]].
* [[Cuban pauraque]], ''Siphonorhis daiquiri'' (Cuba, West Indies, prehistoric?)
*:Described from [[subfossil]] bones in 1985. There are persistent rumors that this bird, which was never seen alive by scientists, may still survive. Compare [[Puerto Rican nightjar]] and preceding.
* [[Vaurie's nightjar]] (''Caprimulgus centralasicus'') is only known from a single 1929 specimen from [[Xinjiang]], China. It has never been found again, but the validity of this supposed species is seriously disputed. It was never refuted to be an immature female desert [[European nightjar]].

===[[Apodiformes]]===
[[Swift]]s and [[hummingbird]]s
* [[Coppery thorntail]], ''Discosura letitiae'' (Bolivia?)
*:Known only from three trade specimens of unknown origin. Might still exist.
* [[Brace's emerald]], ''Chlorostilbon bracei'' (New Providence, Bahamas, late 19th century)&lt;!-- Auk104:296 --&gt;
* [[Gould's emerald]], ''Chlorostilbon elegans'' (Jamaica or northern Bahamas, West Indies, late 19th century)
* [[Turquoise-throated puffleg]], ''Eriocnemis godini'' (Ecuador, 20th century?)
*:Officially classified as [[Endangered species|critically endangered, possibly extinct]]. Known only from six pre-1900 specimens, the habitat at the only known site where it occurred has been destroyed. However, the bird's distribution remains unresolved.

===[[Coraciiformes]]===
[[Kingfisher]]s and related birds
* [[Saint Helena hoopoe]], ''Upupa antaois'' (Saint Helena, Atlantic, early 16th century)

===[[Piciformes]]===
[[Woodpecker]]s and related birds
* [[Bermuda flicker]] (''Colaptes oceanicus'') (Bermuda, 17th century?)
:Known only from fossils found in Bermuda and dated to the [[Late Pleistocene]] and the [[Holocene]]; however, a 17th century report written by explorer Captain [[John Smith (explorer)|John Smith]] may refer to this species.
* [[Imperial woodpecker]], ''Campephilus imperialis'' (Mexico, late 20th century)
:This 60-centimetre-long woodpecker is officially listed as [[Endangered species|critically endangered, possibly extinct]]. Occasional unconfirmed reports come up, the most recent was in late 2005.
* [[Ivory-billed woodpecker]], ''Campephilus principalis'' (Southeastern U.S. and Cuba, late 20th century)
*:The [[Ivory-billed woodpecker|American ivory-billed woodpecker]] (''Campephilus principalis principalis'') is critically endangered, and considered possibly extinct by some authorities.
*:The [[Cuban ivory-billed woodpecker]] (''Campephilus principalis bairdii'') is generally considered extinct, but a few patches of unsurveyed potential habitat remain.

===[[Passeriformes]]===
[[Perching bird]]s

'''[[Furnariidae]]'''- Ovenbirds
* [[Cryptic treehunter]], ''Cichlocolaptes mazarbarnetti'' (E Brazil, 2007?)
* [[Alagoas foliage-gleaner]], ''Philydor novaesi'' (E Brazil, 2011?)
[[Image:Xenicus lyalli.jpg|thumb|[[Lyall's wren]], victim of feral cats]]
'''[[Acanthisittidae]]'''– New Zealand &quot;wrens&quot;
* [[Lyall's wren]], ''Traversia lyalli'' (New Zealand, 1895?)
*:The species famously (but erroneously) claimed to have been made extinct by a single cat named &quot;Tibbles&quot;.
* [[Bushwren]], ''Xenicus longipes'' (New Zealand, 1972)
*:Three subspecies: ''X. l. stokesi'' (North Island, extinct 1955); ''X. l. longipes'' (South Island, extinct 1968); ''X. l. variabilis'' (Stewart Island, extinct 1972).

'''[[Mohoidae]]''' &amp;ndash; Hawaiian &quot;honeyeaters&quot;. Family established in 2008, previously in Meliphagidae.
* [[Kioea]], ''Chaetoptila angustipluma'' (Big Island, Hawaiian Islands, 1860s)
* [[Image:Moho nobilis-Keulemans.jpg|thumb|[[Hawaiʻi ʻōʻō]]]][[Hawaiʻi ʻōʻō]], ''Moho nobilis'' (Big Island, Hawaiian Islands, 1930s)
* [[Oʻahu ʻōʻō]], ''Moho apicalis'' (Oʻahu, Hawaiian Islands, mid-19th century)
* [[Moloka‘i ‘ō‘ō|Molokaʻi ʻōʻō]], ''Moho bishopi'' (Molokaʻi and probably Maui, Hawaiian Islands, c.&amp;nbsp;1910 or 1980s)
* [[Kauaʻi ʻōʻō]], ''Moho braccatus'' (Kauaʻi, Hawaiian Islands, 1987)

'''[[Meliphagidae]]''' &amp;ndash; honeyeaters and Australian chats
* [[Chatham bellbird]], ''Anthornis melanocephala'' (Chatham Islands, Southwest Pacific, c.&amp;nbsp;1910)
*:Sometimes regarded as a subspecies of the [[New Zealand bellbird]], ''Anthornis melanura''. Unconfirmed records exist from the early-mid-1950s.
* The identity of ''&quot;[[Strigiceps leucopogon]]&quot;'' (an [[junior homonym|invalid name]]),&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Extinct Birds|last=Hume|first=Julian P.|publisher=Bloomsbury Publishing|year=2017|isbn=9781472937469|location=|pages=479}}&lt;/ref&gt; described by Lesson in 1840, is unclear. Apart from the holotype supposedly from &quot;[[New Holland (Australia)|New Holland]]&quot;, a second specimen from the &quot;[[Himalaya]]&quot; may have existed (or still exist). Lesson tentatively allied it to the Meliphagidae, and Rothschild felt reminded of the [[kioea]].

'''[[Acanthizidae]]''' &amp;ndash; scrubwrens, thornbills, and gerygones
* [[Lord Howe gerygone]], ''Gerygone insularis'' (Lord Howe Island, Southwest Pacific, c.&amp;nbsp;1930)

'''[[Pachycephalidae]]''' &amp;ndash; whistlers, shrike-thrushes, pitohuis and allies
* [[Mangarevan whistler]], ?''Pachycephala gambierana'' (Mangareva, Gambier Islands, late 19th century?)
*:Tentatively placed here. A mysterious bird of which no specimens exist today. It was initially described as a shrike, then classified as an ''Eopsalteria'' &quot;robin&quot; and may actually be an ''Acrocephalus'' warbler.

'''[[Dicruridae]]''' &amp;ndash; monarch flycatchers and allies
* [[Maupiti monarch]], ''Pomarea pomarea'' (Maupiti, Society Islands, mid-19th century)
* [[Eiao monarch]], ''Pomarea fluxa'' (Eiao, Marquesas, late 1970s)
*:Previously considered a subspecies of the [[Iphis monarch]], this is an early offspring of the Marquesan stock.
* [[Nuku Hiva monarch]], ''Pomarea nukuhivae'' (Nuku Hiva, Marquesas, mid-late 20th century)
*:Previously considered a subspecies of the [[Marquesas monarch]], this is another early offspring of the Marquesan stock.
* [[Ua Pou monarch]], ''Pomarea mira'' (Ua Pou, Marquesas, c.&amp;nbsp;1986)
*:Previously considered another subspecies of the [[Marquesas monarch]], this was a distinct species most closely related to that bird and the [[Fatuhiva monarch]].
* [[Guam flycatcher]], ''Myiagra freycineti'' (Guam, Marianas, 1983)

'''[[Oriolidae]]''' &amp;ndash; Old World orioles and allies
* [[North Island piopio]], ''Turnagra tanagra''	(North Island, New Zealand, c.&amp;nbsp;1970?)
*:Not reliably recorded since about 1900.
* [[South Island piopio]], ''Turnagra capensis'' (South Island, New Zealand, 1960s?)
*:Two subspecies, ''T. c. minor'' from [[Stephens Island, New Zealand|Stephens Island]] (extinct c.&amp;nbsp;1897) and the nominate ''T. c. capensis'' from the South Island mainland (last specimen taken in 1902, last unconfirmed record in 1963)

'''[[Callaeidae]]''' &amp;ndash; New Zealand wattlebirds
[[Image:Huia Buller.jpg|thumb|Male (front) and female (back) [[Huia]]]]
* [[Huia]], ''Heteralocha acutirostris'' (North Island, New Zealand, early 20th century)

'''[[Hirundinidae]]''' &amp;ndash; swallows and martins
* [[White-eyed river martin]], ''Pseudochelidon sirintarae'' (Thailand, late 1980s?)
*:Officially classified as [[Endangered species|critically endangered]], this enigmatic species is only known from migrating birds and it was last seen in 1986 at its former roost site. Recent unconfirmed reports suggest that it may occur in [[Cambodia]].
* [[Red Sea cliff swallow]], ''Petrochelidon perdita'' (Red Sea area, late 20th century?)
*:Known from a single specimen, this enigmatic swallow probably still exists, but the lack of recent records is puzzling. It is alternatively placed in the genus ''Hirundo''.

'''[[Acrocephalidae]]''' &amp;ndash;  marsh and tree warblers
* [[Nightingale reed warbler]], ''Acrocephalus luscinius'' (Guam, c.&amp;nbsp;1970's)
* [[Aguiguan reed warbler]], ''Acrocephalus nijoi'' (Aguiguan, Marianas, c.&amp;nbsp;1997)
* [[Mangareva reed warbler]], ''Acrocephalus astrolabii'' (Marianas?, mid-19th century?)
*: Known from just two specimens found from [[Mangareva Island]] in the western Pacific.
* [[Pagan reed warbler]], ''Acrocephalus yamashinae'' (Pagan, Marianas, 1970s)
* [[Garrett's reed warbler]], ''Acrocephalus musae'' (Society Islands, 19th century?)
* [[Moorea reed warbler]],'' Acrocephalus longirostris'' (Moorea, Society Islands, 1980s?)
*:Last reliable sighting was in 1981. Survey in 1986/1987 remained unsuccessful. A photograph of a warbler from Moorea in 1998 or 1999 taken by Philippe Bacchet remains uncertain, as do reports from 2003 and 2010.        


'''[[Muscicapidae]]''' &amp;ndash; Old World flycatchers and chats
* [[Rück's blue flycatcher]], ''Cyornis ruckii'' (Malaysia or Indochina, 20th century?)
*:An enigmatic bird known from two or four possibly migrant specimens, last recorded in 1918. Might exist in northeast Indochina and might be a subspecies of the [[Hainan blue flycatcher]].

'''[[Megaluridae]]''' &amp;ndash; megalurid warblers or grass warblers
* [[Chatham fernbird]], ''Bowdleria rufescens'' (Chatham Islands, New Zealand, c.&amp;nbsp;1900)
*:Often placed in genus ''Megalurus'', but this is based on an incomplete review of the evidence.

'''[[Cisticolidae]]''' &amp;ndash; cisticolas and allies
* [[Tana River cisticola]], ''Cisticola restrictus'' (Kenya, 1970s?)
*:A mysterious bird, found in the Tana River basin in small numbers at various dates, but not since 1972. Probably invalid, based on aberrant or hybrid specimens. An unconfirmed sighting was apparently made in 2007 in the Tana River Delta.

'''[[White-eye|Zosteropidae]]''' &amp;ndash; white-eyes - probably belonging to Timaliidae
* [[Marianne white-eye]], ''Zosterops semiflavus'' (Marianne Island, Seychelles, late 19th century)
* [[Lord Howe white-eye]], ''Zosterops strenuus'' (Lord Howe Island, Southwest Pacific, c.&amp;nbsp;1918)
* [[White-chested white-eye]], ''Zosterops albogularis'' (Norfolk Island, between 2006 and 2010)

'''[[Timaliidae]]''' &amp;ndash; Old World babblers
* [[Black-browed babbler]], ''Malacocincla perspicillata'' (Borneo?, Indonesia, 20th century?)
*:Known from a single mid-19th century specimen, this bird may be extinct or could still exist. If the specimen label, usually considered erroneous in claiming &quot;Java&quot; as the bird's origin, is correct, it may have gone extinct earlier.

'''[[Pycnonotidae]]''' &amp;ndash; bulbuls
* [[Rodrigues bulbul]], ''Hypsipetes cowlesi'' (Rodrigues, Mascarenes, extinction date unknown, 17th century or 18th century might be possible)&lt;!-- Hume (Ostrich September 2015)--&gt;
*:Known only from subfossil bones.

'''[[Sylvioidea]] ''[[incertae sedis]]'''''
* [[Aldabra brush warbler]], ''Nesillas aldabrana'' (Aldabra, Indian Ocean, c.&amp;nbsp;1984)
* [[Rodrigues babbler|Rodrigues &quot;babbler&quot;]] (Rodrigues, Mascarenes, 17th century?)
*:Known from [[subfossil]] bones. Provisionally assigned to [[Timaliidae]], but placement highly doubtful.

'''[[Sturnidae]]''' &amp;ndash; starlings
[[Image:Fregilupus varius - John Gerrard Keulemans.jpg|thumb|[[Hoopoe starling]]]]
* [[Kosrae starling]], ''Aplonis corvina'' (Kosrae, Carolines, mid-19th century)
* [[Mysterious starling]], ''Aplonis mavornata'' (Mauke, Cook Islands, mid-19th century)
* [[Tasman starling]], ''Aplonis fusca'' (Norfolk Island and Lord Howe Island, Southwest Pacific, c.&amp;nbsp;1923)
*:Two subspecies, ''A. f. fusca''– [[Norfolk starling]] (extinct c.&amp;nbsp;1923); ''A. fusca hulliana''– [[Lord Howe starling]] (extinct c.&amp;nbsp;1919).
* [[Pohnpei starling]], ''Aplonis pelzelni'' (Pohnpei, Micronesia, c.&amp;nbsp;2000)
*:Only one reliable record since 1956, in 1995, leaves the species' survival seriously in doubt.
* [[Bay starling]], ''Aplonis? ulietensis'' (Raiatea, Society Islands, between 1774 and 1850)
*:Usually called &quot;bay thrush&quot; (''Turdus ulietensis''); a mysterious bird from [[Raiatea]], now only known from a painting and some descriptions of a (now lost) specimen. Its [[Alpha taxonomy|taxonomic]] position is thus unresolvable at present, although for [[Biogeography|biogeographic]] reasons and because of the surviving description, it has been suggested to have been a [[honeyeater]]. However, with the discovery of fossils of the prehistorically extinct [[starling]] ''[[Aplonis diluvialis]]'' on neighboring [[Huahine]], it seems likely that this bird also belonged to this genus.
* [[Hoopoe starling]], ''Fregilupus varius'' (Réunion, Mascarenes, 1850s)
*:Tentatively assigned to Sturnidae.
* [[Rodrigues starling]], ''Necropsar rodericanus'' (Rodrigues, Mascarenes, mid-18th century?)
*:Tentatively assigned to Sturnidae. The bird variously described as ''Necropsar leguati'' or ''Orphanopsar leguati'' and considered to be identical with ''N. rodericanus'' (which is only known from [[subfossil]] bones) was found to be based on a misidentified [[albinistic]] specimen of the [[Martinique trembler]] (''Cinclocerthia gutturalis'')

'''[[Thrush (bird)|Turdidae]]''' &amp;ndash; thrushes and relatives
* [[Grand Cayman thrush]], ''Turdus ravidus'' (Grand Cayman, West Indies, late 1940s)
* [[Bonin thrush]], ''Zoothera terrestris'' (Chichi-jima, Ogasawara Islands, c.&amp;nbsp;1830s)
* [[ʻĀmaui]], ''Myadestes woahensis'' (Oʻahu, Hawaiian Islands, mid-19th century)
* [[Image:Zzzkamao.jpg|thumb|[[Kāmaʻo]]]][[Kāmaʻo]], ''Myadestes myadestinus'' (Kauaʻi, Hawaiian Islands, 1990s)
* [[Olomaʻo]], ''Myadestes lanaiensis'' (Hawaiian Islands, 1980s?)
*:Officially classified as [[Endangered species|critically endangered]] because a possible location on Molokaʻi remains unsurveyed. Two subspecies are known from Lanaʻi (''M. l. lanaiensis'', extinct early 1930s), Molokaʻi (''M. l. rutha'', extinct 1980s?) and a possible third subspecies from Maui (extinct before late 19th century).

'''[[Mimidae]]''' &amp;ndash; mockingbirds and thrashers
*[[Cozumel thrasher]], ''Toxostoma guttatum'' (Cozumel, Caribbean, early first decade of the 21st century?)
*:It is still unknown whether the tiny population rediscovered in 2004 survived Hurricanes [[Hurricane Emily (2005)|Emily]] and [[Hurricane Wilma|Wilma]] in 2005. Unconfirmed records in April 2006 and October and December 2007.

'''[[Estrildidae]]'''– estrildid finches (waxbills, munias, etc.
* [[Black-lored waxbill]], ''Estrilda nigriloris'' (D.R. Congo, Africa, late 20th century?)
*:An enigmatic waxbill not seen since 1950; because part of its habitat is in [[Upemba National Park]], it may survive.

'''[[Icteridae]]''' &amp;ndash; grackles
* [[Slender-billed grackle]], ''Quiscalus palustris'' (Mexico, 1910)

'''[[Parulidae]]''' &amp;ndash; New World warblers
* [[File:Bachman's Warbler.jpg|thumb|[[Bachman's warbler]]]][[Bachman's warbler]], ''Vermivora bachmanii'' (southern US, c.&amp;nbsp;1990?)
*:Officially classified as [[Endangered species|critically endangered]].
* [[Semper's warbler]], ''Leucopeza semperi'' (Saint Lucia, Caribbean, 1970s?)
*:Officially classified as [[Endangered species|critically endangered]]. Suitable habitat remains and there have been unconfirmed records within the last decade.
'''[[Ploceidae]]''' &amp;ndash; weavers
* [[Réunion fody]], ''Foudia delloni''
*:Formerly ''Foudia bruante'', which might refer to a color morph of the [[red fody]].

'''[[Fringillidae]]''' &amp;ndash; true finches and Hawaiian honeycreepers
* [[Bonin grosbeak]], ''Chaunoproctus ferreorostris'' (Chichi-jima, Ogasawara Islands, 1830s)
* [[ʻŌʻū]], ''Psittirostra psittacea'' (Hawaiian Islands, c.&amp;nbsp;2000?)
*:Officially classified as [[Endangered species|critically endangered]], this was once the most widespread species of Hawaiian honeycreeper. It has not been reliably recorded since 1987 or 1989.
* [[Lanaʻi hookbill]], ''Dysmorodrepanis munroi'' (Lanaʻi, Hawaiian Islands, 1918)
* [[Kauai palila|Pila's palila]], ''Loxioides kikuichi'' (Kauaʻi, Hawaiian Islands), possibly survived to the early 18th century.
* [[Lesser koa finch]], ''Rhodacanthus flaviceps'' (Big Island, Hawaiian Islands, 1891)
* [[Greater koa finch]], ''Rhodacanthus palmeri'' (Big Island, Hawaiian Islands, 1896)
* [[Kona grosbeak]], ''Psittirostra kona'' (Big Island, Hawaiian Islands, 1894)
* [[Greater ʻamakihi]], ''Hemignathus sagittirostris'' (Big Island, Hawaiian Islands, 1901)
* [[Maui nukupuʻu]], ''Hemignathus affinis'' (Maui, Hawaiian Islands, 1990s)
* [[Kauaʻi nukupuʻu]], ''Hemignathus hanapepe'' (Kauaʻi, Hawaiian Islands, late 1990s)
* [[Oʻahu nukupuʻu]], ''Hemignathus lucidus'' (Oʻahu, Hawaiian Islands, late 19th century)
* [[Hawaiʻi ʻakialoa]] or lesser ʻakialoa, ''Akialoa obscurus'' (Big Island, Hawaiian Islands, 1940)
* [[Maui Nui ʻakialoa]], ''Akialoa lanaiensis'' (Lanaʻi and, prehistorically, probably Maui and Molokaʻi, Hawaiian Islands, 1892)
* [[Oʻahu ʻakialoa]], ''Akialoa ellisiana'' (Oʻahu, Hawaiian Islands, early 20th century)
* [[Kauaʻi ʻakialoa]], ''Akialoa stejnegeri'' (Kauaʻi, Hawaiian Islands, 1969)
* [[Image:Paroreomyza.flammea.jpg|thumb|[[Molokai creeper]] (kākāwahie)]][[Kakawahie]], ''Paroreomyza flammea'' (Molokaʻi, Hawaiian Islands, 1963)
* [[Oʻahu ʻalauahio]], ''Paroreomyza maculata'' (Oʻahu, Hawaiian Islands, early 1990s?)
*:Officially classified as [[Endangered species|critically endangered]]. Last reliable record was in 1985, with an unconfirmed sighting in 1990.
* [[Maui akepa|Maui {{okina}}akepa]], ''Loxops ochraceus'' (Maui, Hawaiian Islands, 1988)
* [[Oahu akepa|Oʻahu {{okina}}akepa]], ''Loxops wolstenholmei'' (Oʻahu, Hawaiian Islands, 1900s)
* [[ʻUla-ʻai-hawane]], ''Ciridops anna'' (Big Island, Hawaiian Islands, 1892 or 1937)
* [[Black mamo]], ''Drepanis funerea'' (Molokaʻi, Hawaiian Islands, 1907)
* [[Image:Drepanis pacifica-Keulemans.jpg|thumb|[[Hawaiʻi mamo]]]][[Hawaiʻi mamo]], ''Drepanis pacifica'' (Big Island, Hawaiian Islands, 1898)
* [[Laysan honeycreeper]], ''Himatione fraithii'' (Laysan, Hawaiian Islands, 1923)
* [[Poʻo-uli]], ''Melamprosops phaeosoma'' (Maui, Hawaiian Islands, 2004?)
*:What was the last known bird died in captivity on 28 November 2004.

'''[[Emberizidae]]''' &amp;ndash; buntings and American sparrows
* [[Hooded seedeater]], ''Sporophila melanops'' (Brazil, 20th century?)
*:Officially classified as [[Endangered species|critically endangered]]. It is known only from a single male collected in 1823 and has variously been considered an aberrant [[yellow-bellied seedeater]] or a hybrid.
*[[Bermuda towhee]], ''Pipilo naufragus''. Known by subfossil remains and possibly from a travel report by [[William Strachey]] in 1610.

==Possibly extinct bird subspecies or status unknown==
Extinction of [[subspecies]] is a subject very dependent on guesswork. National and international conservation projects and research publications such as [[IUCN Red List|redlists]] usually focus on species as a whole. Reliable information on the status of threatened subspecies usually has to be assembled piecemeal from published observations, such as regional checklists. Therefore, the following listing contains a high proportion of taxa that may still exist, but are listed here due to any combination of absence of recent records, a known threat such as habitat destruction, or an observed decline.

===[[Ostrich|Struthioniformes]]===
[[Ratites]] and related birds

* [[Arabian ostrich]], ''Struthio camelus syriacus'' (Arabia, 1966)
:The last record of this [[ostrich]] subspecies was a bird found dead in Jordan in 1966.

=== [[Kiwi|Apterygiformes]] ===

* [[North Island little spotted kiwi]], ''Apteryx owenii iredalei'' (North Island, New Zealand, late 19th century)
:A doubtfully distinct [[little spotted kiwi]] subspecies.

===[[Emu|Casuariiformes]]===

[[Image:Dromaius parvulus.jpg|thumb|[[Kangaroo Island emu]]]]

*[[King Island emu]], ''Dromaius novaehollandiae minor'' (King Island, Australia, 1822)
:A dwarf subspecies of the emu; extinct in the wild c.&amp;nbsp;1805, the last captive specimen died in 1822 in the [[Jardin des Plantes]].
*[[Kangaroo Island emu]], ''Dromaius novaehollandiae baudinianus'' (Kangaroo Island, Australia, 1827)
:A dwarf subspecies of the emu; extinct since c. 1827.
*[[Tasmanian emu]], ''Dromaius novaehollandiae diemenensis'' (Tasmania, Australia, mid-19th century)
:A dwarf subspecies of the emu; the last wild bird was collected in 1845. It may have persisted in captivity until 1884. It may be invalid.

===[[Tinamiformes]]===
Tinamous
* [[Magdalena tinamou]], ''Crypturellus (erythropus) saltuarius'' (Colombia, late 20th century?)
:Variously considered a [[red-legged tinamou]] subspecies or a distinct species, this bird is currently only known with certainty from the 1943 [[type specimen]]. An additional specimen exists (or existed), but its present whereabouts is unknown. Recent research suggest that it is still extant and there was a likely – although as yet unconfirmed – record near the [[Type locality (biology)|type locality]] by Colombian [[ornithologist]] Oswaldo Cortés in late 2008.

===[[Anseriformes]]===
[[Duck]]s, [[Goose|geese]] and [[swan]]s
* [[Bering cackling goose]], ''Branta hutchinsii asiatica'' (Komandorski and Kuril Islands, N Pacific, c.&amp;nbsp;1914 or 1929)
:A subspecies of the [[cackling goose]] (formerly called the Bering [[Canada goose]] (''Branta canadensis asiatica'')) which is doubtfully distinct from the [[Aleutian cackling goose|Aleutian subspecies]].
* Rennell Island teal, ''Anas gibberifrons remissa'' (Rennell, Solomon Islands, c.&amp;nbsp;1959)
:A doubtfully distinct subspecies of the [[Sunda teal]], which disappeared due to predation on young birds by introduced [[tilapia]] (''[[Oreochromis mossambicus]]'').&lt;!-- AmMusNovit486; Auk59:90 --&gt;
* Niceforo's pintail, ''Anas georgica niceforoi'' (Colombia, 1950s)
:A [[yellow-billed pintail]] subspecies that has not been recorded since the 1950s.
* Borrero's cinnamon teal, ''Anas cyanoptera borreroi'' (Colombia, mid-20th century?)
:A subspecies of the [[cinnamon teal]] known only from a restricted area in the Cordillera Occidental of Colombia, with a couple of records from Ecuador. It was discovered in 1946 and thought to be extinct by 1956.
* Coues' gadwall, ''Anas strepera couesi'' (Teraina, Kiribati, c.1900)
:This island subspecies of the [[gadwall]] was discovered in 1874 and has not been recorded since, with none found by a 1924 expedition from Honolulu's Bishop Museum.

===[[Galliformes]]===
[[Quail]]s and relatives
* Italian grey partridge, ''Perdix perdix italica'' (Italy, 1980s)
:A subspecies of the [[grey partridge]] whose validity has been questioned; the last purebred individuals disappeared during the late 1980s due to hybridization with introduced birds.
* [[Lake Amik]] black francolin, ''Francolinus francolinus billypayni'' (S Turkey, possibly Lebanon, 1960s)
:A doubtfully distinct subspecies of the [[black francolin]].
* Sicilian black francolin, ''Francolinus francolinus'' ssp. (Sicily, Mediterranean, c.1869)
:Another doubtfully distinct [[black francolin]] subspecies.
* [[Heath hen]], ''Tympanuchus cupido cupido'', (New England, North America, 1932)
:A subspecies of the [[greater prairie-chicken]] or possibly a distinct species.
* New Mexico sharp-tailed grouse, ''Tympanuchus phasianellus hueyi'' (New Mexico, North America, 1950s)
:A [[sharp-tailed grouse]] subspecies, last recorded in Colfax County in 1952.
* Moroccan guineafowl, ''Numida meleagris sabyi'' (Morocco, mid-late 20th century?)
:A subspecies of the [[helmeted guineafowl]]. Reportedly still kept in captivity in Morocco in the late 1990s. Possibly extinct in the wild by 1950, three records from the 1970s may refer to feral-domestic hybrids.

===[[Charadriiformes]]===
[[Shorebird]]s, [[gull]]s and [[auk]]s
* Kiritimati sandpiper, ''Prosobonia cancellata cancellata'' (Kiritimati, Kiribati, 19th century?)
:The doubtfully distinct nominate subspecies of the [[Tuamotu sandpiper]], sometimes considered a distinct species, but only known from a painting.
* Andalusian hemipode, ''Turnix sylvatica sylvatica'' (Mediterranean region, extant)
:The nominate subspecies of the [[small buttonquail]] has been considered likely extinct, having last been recorded in [[Spain]] in 1981. However, it was confirmed extant with the discovery of a population in [[Morocco]] in 2007.
* Tawitawi small buttonquail, ''Turnix sylvatica suluensis'' (Tawitawi, Philippines, mid-20th century?)
:A [[small buttonquail]] subspecies. It has not been recorded since the 1950s, but there have been few surveys and it is likely to persist.
* New Caledonia painted buttonquail, ''Turnix varius novaecaledoniae'' (New Caledonia, Melanesia, early 20th century?)
:A subspecies of the [[painted buttonquail]] that has been variously considered anything from a hybrid between introduced species to a full species. Plentiful subfossil bones indicate that it was indeed a good endemic form. The last specimen was taken in 1912 and surveys since have failed to record it.

===[[Gruiformes]]===
[[Rallidae|Rail]]s and allies - probably [[paraphyletic]]
* Goldman's yellow rail, ''Coturnicops noveboracensis goldmani'' (Mexico, late 20th century?) 
:A [[yellow rail]] subspecies that has not been recorded since 1964 and lost much of its wetland habitat.
* [[Macquarie rail]], ''Gallirallus philippensis macquariensis'' (Macquarie Islands, southwest Pacific, 1880s)
:[[Buff-banded rail]] subspecies.
* Raoul Island banded rail, ''Gallirallus philippensis'' ssp. (Raoul, Kermadec Islands, southwest Pacific, late 19th century?)
:Reports of the former occurrence of the species on Raoul seem plausible enough, but they may relate to vagrant individuals of another [[buff-banded rail]] subspecies.&lt;!-- Notornis 51(2):61 --&gt;
* Peruvian rail, ''Rallus semiplumbeus peruvianus'' (Peru, 20th century?)
:A subspecies of the [[Bogota rail]] which is known from a single specimen collected in the 1880s. It may still be extant.
* [[Western Lewin's rail]], ''Lewinia pectoralis clelandi'' (SW Australia, late 1930s?)
:A subspecies of [[Lewin's rail]] not recorded since 1932 despite multiple surveys in the late 20th century.
* Assumption white-throated rail, ''Dryolimnas cuvieri abbotti'' (Assumption, Astove and Cosmoledo, Aldabra Islands, early 20th century)
:A [[white-throated rail]] subspecies.
* Jamaican uniform crake, ''Amaurolimnas concolor concolor'' (Jamaica, West Indies, late 19th century)
:The [[uniform crake]]'s nominate subspecies declined rapidly to extinction following the introduction of the [[small Asian mongoose]] to Jamaica in 1872.
* Intact rail, ''Gymnocrex plumbeiventris intactus'' (Melanesia, 20th century?)
:A doubtfully distinct subspecies of the [[bare-eyed rail]] known from a single specimen, c. mid-19th century, from the Solomon Islands or New Ireland. The taxon may be extant.
* Bornean Baillon's crake, ''Porzana pusilla mira'' (Borneo, 20th century?)
:A subspecies of [[Baillon's crake]] known from a single 1912 specimen and not found since; may be extinct, but the species is hard to find.
* Moroccan bustard, ''Ardeotis arabs lynesi'' (Morocco, late 20th century?)
:A subspecies of the [[Arabian bustard]]. Last observed in 1993 at Lac Merzouga/Lac Tamezguidat.
* Luzon sarus crane, ''Antigone antigone luzonica'' (Luzon, Philippines, late 1960s)
:A subspecies of the [[sarus crane]] which is not always accepted as valid, possibly because the existing specimens have not been thoroughly studied since it was described.

===[[Ciconiiformes]]===
[[Heron]]s and related birds - possibly [[paraphyletic]]
* [[Bonin nankeen night heron]], ''Nycticorax caledonicus crassirostris'' (Nakoudo-jima and [[Chichi-jima]], Ogasawara Islands, c.&amp;nbsp;1890)
:A [[nankeen night heron]] subspecies.
* Principe olive ibis, ''Bostrychia olivacea rothschildi'' (Principe, Gulf of Guinea, extant)
:A subspecies of the [[olive ibis]] or (as ''B. bocagei rothschildi'') the São Tomé ibis if this is considered a distinct species. It was unrecorded through most of the 20th century and has been considered extinct, but was recorded on multiple occasions in the 1990s and should now be considered extant.

===[[Pterocliformes]]===
[[Sandgrouse]]s
*Fayyum sandgrouse, ''Pterocles exustus floweri'' (Fayyum area, Egypt, late 20th century?)
:This subspecies of the [[chestnut-bellied sandgrouse]] was last recorded in 1979 and is likely to have gone extinct since.

===[[Columbiformes]]===
[[Pigeon]]s, doves and [[dodo]]s
* [[Madeiran wood pigeon]], ''Columba palumbus maderensis'' (Madeira, East Atlantic, early 20th century)
:A subspecies of the [[Common wood pigeon|wood pigeon]].
* Ogasawara Japanese wood pigeon, ''Columba janthina nitens'' (Ogasawara Islands, Northwest Pacific, extant)
:[[Japanese wood pigeon]] subspecies thought to have gone extinct in the 1980s, but there have been recent reports and photographs and the taxon is now considered extant, though very rare.
* [[Lord Howe pigeon]], ''Columba vitiensis godmanae'' (Lord Howe Island, Southwest Pacific, 1853)
:[[Metallic pigeon]] subspecies last recorded in 1853 and almost certainly extinct by 1869.
* Tongan metallic pigeon, ''Columba vitiensis'' ssp. (Vava'u, Tonga, late 18th century?)
:This subspecies of the metallic pigeon is only known from a footnote in [[John Latham (ornithologist)|John Latham]]'s ''General History of Birds'' and seems to have died out some time before 1800; possibly, the location is erroneous and the note really refers to the extant population on Fiji.
*Amirante turtle-dove, ''Nesoenas picturata aldabrana'' (Amirante Islands, Seychelles, late 20th century)
:This subspecies of the [[Malagasy turtle dove]] persisted until at least 1974, after which it was hybridised out of existence through breeding with the introduced nominate subspecies.
* Catanduanes bleeding-heart, ''Gallicolumba luzonica rubiventris'' (Catanduanes, Philippines, late 20th century?)
:A subspecies of the [[Luzon bleeding-heart]] known from a single specimen collected in 1971. There have been recent reports of the taxon and, as much of its forest habitat remains, it is likely to be extant.
* Basilan bleeding-heart, ''Gallicolumba crinigera bartletti'' (Basilan, Philippines, mid-20th century?)
:A subspecies of the [[Mindanao bleeding-heart]], it was last reported in 1925 and given the massive habitat destruction is likely extinct.
* Vella Lavella ground dove, ''Gallicolumba jobiensis chalconota'' (Vella Lavella, Makira and Guadalcanal, Solomon Islands, late 20th century?)
:A subspecies of the [[white-breasted ground dove]] or possibly a distinct species. Known from only four specimens, there are no recent records and the local population report it has disappeared.
* White-headed Polynesian ground dove, ''Gallicolumba erythroptera albicollis'' (Central Tuamotu Islands, 20th century?)
:The Central Tuamotu subspecies of the [[Polynesian ground dove]], often referred to as ''G. e. pectoralis'', disappeared at an undetermined date, but might still exist on some unsurveyed atolls. The identity of northern Tuamotu populations, possibly still extant, is undetermined.
* Ebon crimson-crowned fruit dove, ''Ptilinopus porphyraceus marshallianus'' (Ebon?, Marshall Islands, late 19th century?)
:[[Crimson-crowned fruit dove]] subspecies of doubtful validity. Known from a single specimen collected in 1859; it is not certain whether this bird actually occurred on Ebon. All that can be said is that this subspecies is no longer found anywhere.
* Mauke fruit dove, ''Ptilinopus rarotongensis &quot;byronensis&quot;'' (Mauke, Cook Islands, mid- or late 19th century)
:A subspecies of the [[lilac-crowned fruit dove]], known only from the description of a now-lost specimen. The prehistorically extinct population on [[Mangaia]] is likely to belong to another distinct subspecies too.
* Negros spotted imperial pigeon, ''Ducula carola nigrorum'' (Negros and probably Siquijor, late 20th century?)
:[[Spotted imperial pigeon]] subspecies not recorded since the 1950s.
* [[Norfolk pigeon]], ''Hemiphaga novaeseelandiae spadicea'' (Norfolk Island, Southwest Pacific, early 20th century)
:A subspecies of the [[New Zealand pigeon]] not recorded since 1900. Similar birds were reported from Lord Howe Island; these seem to represent another extinct subspecies, but are undescribed to date.
* Raoul Island kereru, ''Hemiphaga novaeseelandiae'' ssp. nov. (Raoul, Kermadec Islands, 19th century)
:Another undescribed subspecies (or possibly species) of the [[New Zealand pigeon]], known from bones and a brief report.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | url=https://www.notornis.osnz.org.nz/new-zealand-pigeon-hemiphaga-novaeseelandiae-raoul-island-kermadec-group | title=New Zealand pigeon ( Hemiphaga novaeseelandiae ) on Raoul Island, Kermadec Group| journal=Notornis| volume=47| issue=1| pages=36–38| year=2000| last1=Worthy| first1=Trevor}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===[[Psittaciformes]]===
[[Parrot]]s
* Sangir red and blue lory, ''Eos histrio histrio'' (Sangir Archipelago, Indonesia, 1990s?)
:The nominate subspecies of the [[red-and-blue lory]] was hybridized out of existence by escaped trade individuals of the subspecies ''talautensis'', the last purebred individuals disappearing in the 1990s or even much earlier.
* [[Sinú parakeet]], ''Pyrrhura picta subandina'' (Colombia, mid-20th century?)
:Formerly recognized as a distinct species, this bird has a very restricted distribution and was last reliably recorded in 1949. It was not found during searches in 2004 and 2006 and seems to be extinct; efforts to find it again continue, but are hampered by the threat of armed conflict.
* Challenger's lory, ''Eos histrio challengeri'' (Nenusa Islands, Talaud Archipelago, early 20th century?)
:A supposed subspecies of the [[red and blue lory]], but probably invalid.&lt;!--The identity of Eos histrio challengeri Salvadori 1891. BOC bulletin Vol. 118, 1998--&gt;
* [[Macquarie parakeet]], ''Cyanoramphus novaezelandiae erythrotis'' (Macquarie Islands, SW Pacific, 1890s)
:[[Red-crowned parakeet]] subspecies last recorded in 1890 and not found by surveys in 1894.
* [[Lord Howe parakeet]], ''Cyanoramphus novaezelandiae subflavescens'' (Lord Howe Island, SW Pacific, c.&amp;nbsp;1870)
:[[Red-crowned parakeet]] subspecies.
* [[Réunion parakeet]], ''Psittacula eques eques'' (Réunion, Mascarenes, mid-18th century)
:Known only from a painting and descriptions; if it is accepted as valid, it would become the nominate subspecies of the [[Mauritius parakeet]], extant on Mauritius, which would then have to be called ''P. eques echo''.
* Siquijor colasisi, ''Loriculus philippensis siquijorensis'' (Siquijor, Philippines, 20th century?)
:A subspecies of the [[colasisi]] or Philippine hanging parrot, either very rare or already extinct.
* [[Puerto Rican conure]], ''Aratinga chloroptera maugei'' (Mona and possibly Puerto Rico, West Indies, 1890s)
:A weakly differentiated subspecies of the [[Hispaniolan parakeet]].
* Sinú brown-throated parakeet, ''Aratinga pertinax griseipecta'' (Colombia, mid- or late 20th century?)
:A subspecies of the [[brown-throated parakeet]] known from only two specimens collected in 1949 and of unclear taxonomical and conservation status.
* Culebra amazon, ''Amazona vittata gracilipes'' (Culebra, West Indies, early 20th century)
:A weakly differentiated subspecies of the [[Puerto Rican amazon]], which is itself highly endangered.

===[[Cuculiformes]]===
[[Cuckoo]]s
* Greater crested coua, ''Coua cristata maxima'' (SE Madagascar, late 20th century?)
:[[Crested coua]] subspecies, known only from a single specimen taken in 1950. It may be a hybrid, but if not it is probably extinct.
* Assumption Island coucal, ''Centropus toulou assumptionis'' (Assumption Island, Seychelles, early 20th century)
:A [[Madagascar coucal]] subspecies last recorded in 1906. It is often considered synonymous with the Aldabra form ''insularis'', which has since recolonized Assumption Island.
* Cabo San Lucas groove-billed ani, ''Crotophaga sulcirostris pallidula'' (Mexico, c.&amp;nbsp;1940)
:A weakly differentiated and probably invalid subspecies of the [[groove-billed ani]].
* Bahia rufous-vented ground cuckoo, ''Neomorphus geoffroyi maximiliani'' (E Brazil, mid-20th century?)
:[[Rufous-vented ground cuckoo]] subspecies.

===[[Falconiformes]]===
[[Bird of prey|Birds of prey]]
* [[Cape Verde kite]], ''Milvus ''(''milvus'')'' fasciicauda'' (Cape Verde Islands, E Atlantic, 2000)
:Considered either a subspecies of the [[red kite]], a distinct species, or a hybrid between [[Red kite|red]] and [[black kite]]s, the validity of this taxon has recently been questioned on the basis of molecular analysis. However, hybridization and a confusing molecular phylogeny of red kite populations, coupled with the distinct phenotype of the Cape Verde birds, suggest that the taxonomic status of this form is far from resolved.
* Car Nicobar sparrowhawk, ''Accipiter butleri butleri'' (Car Nicobar, Nicobar Islands, 20th century?)
: The nominate subspecies of the [[Nicobar sparrowhawk]]– which is currently listed as [[endangered species|vulnerable]]– is possibly extinct. It was last reliably recorded in 1901 and despite searches, has not been sighted after an unconfirmed record in 1977. However, the species is known for being very shy and a population may persist unrecorded.
* Volcano Islands peregrine falcon,  ''Falco peregrinus furuitii''. (Ogasawara Islands, 1940s)
:[[Peregrine falcon]] subspecies from the [[Ogasawara Islands]]. No sightings since 1945. A survey in 1982 failed to find this bird. Only known from [[Iwo Jima]] and [[Torishima (Izu Islands)|Torishima]].&lt;!-- Uncertain distinctness as there is a phylogenetic relationship with Peale's peregrine falcon (''F. p. pealei''). [no, they just look somewhat similar.] --&gt;

===[[Strigiformes]]===
[[Typical owl]]s and [[barn owl]]s
* Sulu reddish scops owl, ''Otus rufescens burbidgei'' (Sulu, Philippines, mid-20th century)
:A subspecies of the [[reddish scops owl]]. Known from a single questionable specimen and may not be valid.
* Virgin Islands screech owl, ''Megascops nudipes newtoni'' (Virgin Islands, Caribbean, 20th century?)
:A subspecies of the [[Puerto Rican screech owl]], of somewhat doubtful validity, which occurred on several of the Virgin Islands, West Indies. The last reliable records are in 1860; there were a number of unconfirmed reports during the 20th century, but it was not found in thorough surveys in 1995.
* Socorro elf owl, ''Micrathene whitneyi graysoni'' (Socorro, Revillagigedo Islands, mid-20th century?)
:A subspecies of the [[elf owl]]. Officially listed as [[Endangered species|critically endangered]], the last specimen was taken in 1932, but there was apparently still a large population in 1958; it was not found by subsequent searches and it appears to be extinct.
* Antiguan burrowing owl, ''Athene cunicularia amaura'' (Antigua, St Kitts and Nevis, West Indies, c. 1900)
:[[Burrowing owl]] subspecies, last collected in 1890 and extinct by 1903.
* Guadeloupe burrowing owl, ''Athene cunicularia guadeloupensis'' (Guadeloupe and Marie-Galante, West Indies, c.&amp;nbsp;1890)
:[[Burrowing owl]] subspecies. Extinct by 1890.
* [[Lord Howe boobook]], ''Ninox novaeseelandiae albaria'' (Lord Howe Island, Southwest Pacific, 1950s)
:[[Southern boobook]] subspecies last recorded in the 1950s.
* [[Norfolk boobook]], ''Ninox novaeseelandiae undulata'' (Norfolk Island, Southwest Pacific, 1990s)
:Individuals of the [[Southern boobook|nominate subspecies]] were introduced in a last-ditch effort to save the local owl population. There now exists a hybrid population of a few dozen birds; the last individual of ''N. n. undulata'', a female named ''Miamiti'', died in 1996, though individuals descended from her remain.
* Cave-nesting masked owl, ''Tyto novaehollandiae troughtoni'' (Nullarbor Plain, Australia, 1960s)
:Doubtfully distinct from [[Australian masked owl|nominate subspecies]], but differed behaviorally.
* Buru masked owl, ''Tyto sororcula cayelii'' (Buru, Indonesia, mid-20th century?)
:Subspecies of the [[lesser masked owl]]. Last recorded in 1921; the identity of a similar bird found on Seram remains to be determined. Seems to survive, as an owl matching this bird's description was encountered in August 2006.&lt;!-- http://extinctanimals.proboards22.com/index.cgi?board=rediscoveredbirds&amp;action=display&amp;thread=1118209580 --&gt;
* Peleng masked owl, ''Tyto rosenbergii pelengensis'' (Peleng, Banggai Islands, mid-20th century)
:Subspecies of the [[Sulawesi owl]] or a separate species. Possibly extant, but the only specimen known was taken in 1938 and there have been no further records.
* Samar bay owl, ''Phodilus badius riverae'' (Samar, Philippines, mid-20th century)
:Subspecies of the [[Oriental bay owl]] or a possibly distinct species. Taxonomy doubtful, but only specimen lost in 1945 bombing raid, so validity cannot be verified; no population exists on Samar today.

===[[Caprimulgiformes]]===
[[Nightjar]]s and allies
* New Caledonian white-throated nightjar, ''Eurostopodus mystacalis exsul'' (New Caledonia, Melanesia, mid-20th century)
:This distinct subspecies of the [[white-throated nightjar]] is possibly a separate species. It was found only once; due to its cryptic habits, it possibly still exists, but this is now considered unlikely.

===[[Apodiformes]]===
[[Swift]]s and [[hummingbird]]s
* Miravalles hummingbird, ''Amazilia cyanifrons alfaroana'' (Costa Rica, Central America, 20th century?)
:This subspecies of the [[indigo-capped hummingbird]] is only known from a specimen collected in Costa Rica in 1895. It is likely to have gone extinct since
* Alejandro Selkirk firecrown, ''Sephanoides fernandensis leyboldi'' (Alejandro Selkirk Island, Juan Fernández Islands, Southeast Pacific, 1908)
:[[Juan Fernández firecrown]] subspecies last recorded in 1908.
* Luzon Whitehead's swiftlet, ''Collocalia whiteheadi whiteheadi'' (Luzon, Philippines, 20th century?)
:The nominate subspecies of [[Whitehead's swiftlet]] is only known from four specimens collected at [[Mount Data]] in 1895. From the lack of further records and the massive habitat destruction, it is usually considered extinct. Given the size of the island, it might still exist though.

===[[Coraciiformes]]===
[[Kingfisher]]s and related birds
* Sangihe dwarf kingfisher, ''Ceyx fallax sangirensis'' ([[Sangihe Islands|Sangihe]], Indonesia, 1998?)
:This subspecies of the [[Sulawesi dwarf kingfisher]] was last seen in 1997 but not during a thorough survey one year later; it is either close to extinction or already extinct. Sometimes it is said to occur on Talaud Islands also, but this is erroneous.
* Rarotonga kingfisher, ''Todiramphus'' cf. ''tutus'' (Rarotonga, Cook Islands, mid-1980s?)
:There exist reports of locals that kingfishers–probably a subspecies of the [[chattering kingfisher]] which is found on neighboring islands, but possibly vagrants from there–were found until around 1979 and there is a last record from 1984. Presently, no kingfishers are known to exist on Rarotonga.&lt;!-- Notornis 28 (1) p.84 --&gt;
* Mangareva kingfisher, ''Todiramphus gambieri gambieri'' (Mangareva, Gambier Islands, late 19th century)
:Only known from a single 1844 specimen, the nominate subspecies of the [[Tuamotu kingfisher]] was not found again when it was next searched for in 1922.
*Guam kingfisher, ''Todiramphus cinnamominus cinnamominus'' (Guam, West Pacific, 1986)
:This subspecies of the [[Micronesian kingfisher]] became extinct in the wild in 1986 when 29 birds were taken for a captive breeding programme, which is ongoing. Its decline was caused by the depredations of introduced [[brown tree snake]]s.
* [[Ryūkyū kingfisher]], ''Todiramphus cinnamominus miyakoensis'' (Miyako-jima, Ryukyu Islands, late 19th century)
:Previously considered as a full species, but better regarded as a subspecies of the [[Micronesian kingfisher]] (''Todiramphus cinnamominus''). Only seen once by scientists, in 1887; the specimen taken is somewhat damaged, making identification by other than molecular analysis difficult. It is now thought likely that the specimen came from Guam, where the nominate subspecies was distributed, rather than Miyako, which would make this subspecies invalid.
* Javan blue-banded kingfisher, ''Alcedo euryzona euryzona'' (Java, Indonesia, extant)
:The nominate subspecies of the [[blue-banded kingfisher]]; the last specimen was taken in 1937 and the taxon has been considered extinct, but it was mist-netted five times in 2000-2001 at Halimun National Park, which has not undergone much change since.
* Guadalcanal little kingfisher, ''Alcedo pusilla aolae'' (Guadalcanal, Solomon Islands, ?)
:[[Little kingfisher]] subspecies.
* Sakarha pygmy kingfisher, ''Ispidina madagascariensis dilutus'' (Southwest Madagascar, late 20th century?)
:This subspecies of the [[Madagascar pygmy kingfisher]] is only known from one specimen taken in 1974 in an area where most habitat had already been lost. However, there have been records of the species (uncertain subspecies) from near the type locality, suggesting it is likely to be extant.
* Ticao hornbill, ''Penelopides panini ticaensis'' (Ticao, Philippines, 1970s)
:A subspecies of the [[Visayan hornbill]] of somewhat uncertain status–possibly a distinct species, possibly a color morph–the last confirmed report was in 1971 and it became extinct shortly thereafter.

===[[Piciformes]]===
[[Woodpecker]]s and related birds
* Grand Bahama West Indian woodpecker, ''Melanerpes superciliaris bahamensis'' (Grand Bahama, Bahamas, 1950s)
:A [[West Indian woodpecker]] subspecies of somewhat uncertain validity.
* Javan buff-rumped woodpecker, ''Meiglyptes tristis tristis'' (Java, Indonesia, c.&amp;nbsp;1920?)
:The nominate subspecies of the [[buff-rumped woodpecker]] became rare during the 19th century due to destruction of habitat. The last confirmed record was in 1880, and it is now considered at least very rare.
* Guadalupe red-shafted flicker, ''Colaptes auratus rufipileus'' (Guadalupe, East Pacific, c.&amp;nbsp;1910)
:A subspecies of the [[northern flicker]] (or the red-shafted flicker, as ''C. cafer rufipileus''), it was last recorded in 1906 and not found again in both 1911 and 1922. It may be invalid. Recently, vagrant birds of a mainland red-shafted subspecies have begun recolonizing the island as the habitat improves after the removal of [[feral]] [[goats]].
* Northern white-mantled barbet, ''Capito hypoleucus hypoleucus'' (Colombia, extant)
:The nominate subspecies of the [[white-mantled barbet]] has been considered extinct, but has been recorded recently.
* Botero white-mantled barbet, ''Capito hypoleucus carrikeri'' (Colombia, extant)
:Another subspecies of the [[white-mantled barbet]], also considered extinct by some sources, but confirmed extant by researchers in Colombia.
* Todd's jacamar, ''Brachygalba lugubris phaeonota'' (Brazil, late 20th century?)
:A subspecies of the [[brown jacamar]], or possibly a hybrid, color morph or full species. Might survive, as it is only known from a remote and seldom-visited area.
* Cebu white-bellied woodpecker, ''Dryocopus javensis cebuensis'' (Cebu, Philippines, 20th century)
:Only known by three specimens collected before 1900.

===[[Passeriformes]]===
[[Perching bird]]s

'''[[Pittidae]]''' &amp;ndash; pittas
* Bougainville black-faced pitta, ''Pitta anerythra pallida'' (Bougainville, Solomon Islands, mid-20th century?)
:A subspecies of the [[black-faced pitta]]. Once common on Bougainville; not recorded since 1938, but likely to have been overlooked.
* Choiseul black-faced pitta, ''Pitta anerythra nigrifrons'' (Choiseul, Solomon Islands, late 20th century?)
:Another subspecies of the [[black-faced pitta]]. Not found during recent searches; doubtful records from nearby islands. Also may have been overlooked by observers.

'''[[Tyrannidae]]''' &amp;ndash; tyrant flycatchers
* Bogotá bearded tachuri, ''Polystictus pectoralis bogotensis'' (C Colombia, 20th century)
:A [[bearded tachuri]] subspecies, or possibly a distinct species, that has not been recorded for some time and is now extinct.
* Grenadan Euler's flycatcher, ''Lathrotriccus euleri flaviventris'' (Grenada, West Indies, 1950s?)
:A subspecies of [[Euler's flycatcher]], formerly known as ''Empidonax euleri johnstonei''. It has not been recorded since the 1950s.
* [[San Cristóbal vermilion flycatcher]], ''Pyrocephalus rubinus dubius'' (San Cristóbal, Galapagos, late 20th century)
:A subspecies of the [[vermilion flycatcher]], described as extremely rare by David W. Steadman in the 1980s and not found despite a six-month survey in 1998. Sometimes considered a full species.

'''[[Furnariidae]]''' &amp;ndash; ovenbirds
* Peruvian scale-throated earthcreeper, ''Upucerthia dumetaria peruana'' (Peru, 20th century?)
:A subspecies of the [[scale-throated earthcreeper]], it is only known from two specimens taken in the early 1950s at Puno, Peru, and has never been found since. It may well persist, as there is no obvious reason why it should have become extinct.
* Northern stripe-crowned spinetail, ''Cranioleuca pyrrhophia rufipennis'' (N Bolivia, 20th century?)
:A [[stripe-crowned spinetail]] subspecies known from a few specimens and not recorded since the 1950s; may be endangered or possibly extinct.

'''[[Formicariidae]]''' &amp;ndash; antpittas and antthrushes
* Northern giant antpitta, ''Grallaria gigantea lehmanni'' (Colombia, 20th century?)
:A [[giant antpitta]] (or possibly [[great antpitta]]) subspecies apparently not recorded since the 1940s. Might still survive in [[Puracé National Natural Park]], where there is plentiful habitat remaining.
* Antioquia brown-banded antpitta, ''Grallaria milleri gilesi'' (Antioquia, Colombia, 20th century?)
:A [[brown-banded antpitta]] subspecies recently described from a specimen collected in 1878. It has not been recorded since, despite surveys at a number of likely locations.

'''[[Maluridae]]''' &amp;ndash; Australasian &quot;wrens&quot;
* Macdonnell Ranges grasswren, ''Amytornis modestus modestus'' (Northern Territory, Australia, 1936)
:[[Thick-billed grasswren]] subspecies. The last record was a clutch of eggs taken in 1936.
* Namoi grasswren, ''Amytornis modestus inexpectatus'' (New South Wales, Australia, 1886)
:Another [[thick-billed grasswren]] subspecies, last recorded in 1886.
* Large-tailed grasswren, ''Amytornis textilis macrourus'' (Western Australia, 1910)
:[[Western grasswren]] subspecies, last collected in 1910 and since extinct.

'''[[Pardalotidae]]''' &amp;ndash; pardalotes, scrubwrens, thornbills and gerygones
* [[Western rufous bristlebird]], ''Dasyornis broadbenti littoralis'' (Australia, mid-20th century)
:[[Rufous bristlebird]] subspecies not recorded since 1940, despite a number of surveys since, beginning in the 1970s.
* King Island brown thornbill, ''Acanthiza pusilla archibaldi'' (King Island, Australia, extant)
:A [[brown thornbill]] subspecies which has only been recorded c.10 times since its discovery and considered extinct by some sources. The latest record comes from 2002, suggesting a population is likely to be extant, but very rare.

'''[[Petroicidae]]'''{{spaced ndash}}Australasian &quot;robins&quot;
* Tiwi Island hooded robin, ''Melanodryas cucullata melvillensis'' (Tiwi Islands, Australia, 1992)
:Subspecies of the [[hooded robin]], last observed in 1992 and not found in exhaustive searches later in the 1990s.

'''[[Cinclosomatidae]]''' &amp;ndash; whipbirds and allies
* Mount Lofty spotted quail-thrush, ''Cinclosoma punctatum anachoreta'' (Australia, mid-1980s?)
:A subspecies of the [[spotted quail-thrush]], last recorded in 1983 and not found in a survey the following year.

'''[[Artamidae]]''' &amp;ndash; woodswallows, currawongs and allies
* Western pied currawong, ''Strepera graculina ashbyi'' (Victoria, Australia, 1927)
:This [[pied currawong]] subspecies has been swamped by other subspecies, which probably came into contact following habitat destruction in the 1830s. The last certainly distinct individuals were recorded in 1927.

'''[[Monarchidae]]''' &amp;ndash; monarch flycatchers
* Negros celestial monarch, ''Hypothymis coelestis rabori'' (Negros and possibly Sibuyan, Philippines, late 20th century?)
:A subspecies of the [[celestial monarch]], not uncommon on Negros in 1959, but not recorded since. A single Sibuyan specimen from an unspecified locality taken in the 19th century is the only record for this island.
* Hiva Oa monarch, ''Pomarea mendozae mendozae'' (Hiva Oa and Tahuata, Marquesas, late 20th century)
:[[Marquesas monarch]] nominate subspecies, which was very rare by 1974 and not found during multiple surveys in the 1990s.

'''[[Rhipiduridae]] &amp;ndash; fantails
* Lord Howe fantail, ''Rhipidura fuliginosa cervina'' (Lord Howe Island, Southwest Pacific, c.&amp;nbsp;1925)
:[[New Zealand fantail]] subspecies that was considered virtually extinct in 1924 and not found by surveys four years later.
* Guam rufous fantail, ''Rhipidura rufifrons uraniae'' (Guam, Marianas, 1984)
:[[Rufous fantail]] subspecies, a conspicuous bird which has not been recorded since 1984.

'''[[Campephagidae]]''' &amp;ndash; cuckoo-shrikes and trillers
* Cebu bar-bellied cuckoo-shrike, ''Coracina striata cebuensis'' (Cebu, Philippines, early 20th century)
:[[Bar-bellied cuckoo-shrike]] subspecies not recorded since its collection in 1906.
* Maros cicadabird, ''Coracina tenuirostris edithae'' (Sulawesi, mid-20th century)
:A subspecies of the [[cicadabird]] known from a single specimen collected in 1931; quite possibly just a vagrant individual.
* Cebu blackish cuckoo-shrike, ''Coracina coerulescens altera'' (Cebu, Philippines, 20th century?)
:A [[blackish cuckoo-shrike]] subspecies; could be extant as the birds are rather unmistakable and a 1999 record therefore likely to be valid, though surveys since then have failed to find it/
* Marinduque blackish cuckoo-shrike, ''Coracina coerulescens deschauenseei'' (Marinduque, Philippines, late 20th century?)
:Another [[blackish cuckoo-shrike]] subspecies, described from specimens collected in 1971, but apparently not seen since. As few ornithologists have visited Marinduque and forest remains on the island, it is thought likely to remain extant.
* Norfolk long-tailed triller, ''Lalage leucopyga leucopyga'' (Norfolk Island, Southwest Pacific, 1942)
:A subspecies of the [[long-tailed triller]], possibly a distinct species.

'''[[Oriolidae]]''' &amp;ndash; orioles and figbird
* Cebu dark-throated oriole, ''Oriolus xanthonotus assimilis'' (Cebu, Philippines, 20th century?)
:[[Dark-throated oriole]] subspecies not confirmed since 1906, though there were unconfirmed reports around 2001, suggesting a possibility of survival.

'''[[Corvidae]]''' &amp;ndash; crows, ravens, magpies and jays
* [[Pied raven]], ''Corvus corax varius'' morpha ''leucophaeus'' (Faroe Islands, 1948)
:A distinct local white-with-black-markings color morph of the Icelandic subspecies of the [[common raven]].

'''[[Callaeidae]]''' &amp;ndash; New Zealand wattlebirds
* [[South Island kōkako]], ''Callaeas cinereus cinereus'' (South Island, New Zealand, 1960s?)
:This subspecies of the [[kōkako]] is usually considered extinct, as it has not been reliably recorded since 1967. However, recent reports from Fiordland suggest that a population could exist.

'''[[Regulidae]]''' &amp;ndash; kinglets
* Guadalupe ruby-crowned kinglet, ''Regulus calendula obscurus'' (Guadalupe, East Pacific, 20th century)
:A subspecies of the [[ruby-crowned kinglet]] that has not been recorded since 1953.

'''[[Hirundinidae]]''' &amp;ndash; swallows and martins
* Jamaican golden swallow, ''Tachycineta euchrysea euchrysea'' (Jamaica, West Indies, c.&amp;nbsp;1990?)
:The nominate subspecies of the [[Golden swallow (bird)|golden swallow]], endemic to Jamaica. The last major roost site was destroyed in 1987 and the last confirmed sighting was in 1989. May still exist in the [[Cockpit Country]].

'''[[Phylloscopidae]]''' &amp;ndash; phylloscopid warblers or leaf-warblers
* [[Eastern Canary Islands chiffchaff]], ''Phylloscopus canariensis exsul'' (Lanzarote and possibly Fuerteventura, Canary Islands, 20th century?)
:A subspecies of the [[Canary Islands chiffchaff]], it was probably extinct by 1986.

'''[[Cettiidae]]''' &amp;ndash; cettiid warblers or typical bush-warblers
* Babar stubtail, ''Urosphena subulata advena'' (Babar, Indonesia, extant)
:[[Timor stubtail]] subspecies that has been considered extinct, but was recorded as common on Babar in 2009 and 2011.
* Western Turner's eremomela, ''Eremomela turneri kalindei'' (Congo Basin, late 20th century?)
:The West African subspecies of [[Turner's eremomela]] has not been recorded since the end of the 1970s, but there is unsurveyed habitat in its range where it is likely to survive. Placement in Cettiidae requires confirmation.

'''[[Acrocephalidae]]''' &amp;ndash; acrocephalid warblers or marsh- and tree warblers
* Marshall Islands reed warbler, ''Acrocephalus rehsei'' ssp.? (Marshall Islands, Micronesia, c.1880?)
:Oral tradition and some early reports mention a bird called ''annañ'' which inhabited some of the Marshall Islands. The best match is the [[Nauru reed warbler]]; the ''annañ'' might have been an undescribed subspecies of that species, or a distant but related species of reed warbler.&lt;ref name = spennemann2006 /&gt;
* [[Laysan millerbird]], ''Acrocephalus familiaris familiaris'' (Laysan Island, Hawaiian Islands, late 1910s)
:The [[Millerbird|millerbird]]'s nominate subspecies.
* Huahine Polynesian warbler, ''Acrocephalus caffer garretti'' (Huahine, Society Islands, c.1900)
:A poorly known subspecies of the [[Tahiti reed warbler]]. Specimens were collected in the late 1800s, but the Whitney Expedition in 1921 found none.

'''[[Pycnonotidae]]''' &amp;ndash; bulbuls
* Sumatra blue-wattled bulbul, ''Pycnonotus nieuwenhuisii inexspectatus'' (Sumatra, Indonesia, late 20th century?)
:A subspecies of the [[blue-wattled bulbul]] known from a single 1937 specimen. The entire &quot;species&quot; may be a hybrid.

'''[[Cisticolidae]]''' &amp;ndash; cisticolas and allies
* Northern white-winged apalis, ''Apalis chariessa chariessa'' (Kenya, late 20th century?)
:The nominate subspecies of the [[white-winged apalis]] remains known only from the Tana River, a center of endemism. It was last recorded in 1961.

'''[[Sylviidae]]''' &amp;ndash; sylviid (&quot;true&quot;) warblers and parrotbills
* Vanua Levu long-legged warbler, ''Trichocichla rufa clunei'' (Vanua Levu, Fiji, late 20th century?)
:A subspecies of the [[long-legged warbler]]; it was only found once, but there was an unconfirmed sighting in 1990, suggesting it is likely to remain extant. Placement in Sylviidae doubtful.
* Fayyum warbler, ''Sylvia melanocephala/momus norissae'' (Egypt, 1939)
:A doubtfully distinct [[Sardinian warbler]] subspecies. It has not been recorded since 1939.

'''[[Zosteropidae]]''' &amp;ndash; white-eyes. Probably belong into Timaliidae
* Guam bridled white-eye, ''Zosterops conspicillatus conspicillatus'' (Guam, Marianas, 1983)
:[[Bridled white-eye]] nominate subspecies or possibly monotypic species. Last recorded in 1983.
* [[Mukojima white-eye]], ''Apalopteron familiare familiare'' (Mukojima Group, Ogasawara Islands, 20th century?)
:[[Bonin white-eye]] (&quot;Bonin honeyeater&quot;) subspecies not recorded since its last specimen was collected in 1930.

'''[[Timaliidae]]''' &amp;ndash; Old World babblers
* Vanderbilt's babbler, ''Malacocincla sepiarium vanderbilti'' (Sumatra, Indonesia, late 20th century?)
:An enigmatic subspecies of [[Horsfield's babbler]], known from a single specimen. Not seen since the 1940s at the latest.
* Burmese Jerdon's babbler, ''Chrysomma altirostre altirostre'' (Myanmar, 20th century?)
:The nominate subspecies of [[Jerdon's babbler]] was last confirmed in 1941, but as there has been little fieldwork in its range and a possible sighting in 1994, it is considered likely to persist.

'''&quot;[[Old World warbler|African warblers]]&quot;'''
* Chapin's crombec, ''Sylvietta leucophrys chapini'' (Congo Basin, late 20th century?)
:A subspecies of the [[white-browed crombec]], sometimes listed as a separate species. Restricted to the Lendu Plateau, it is probably rare, though unsurveyed forest remains where it is likely to persist.

'''[[Sylvioidea]] ''[[incertae sedis]]'''''
* [[Lake Amik]] bearded reedling, ''Panurus biarmicus kosswigi'' (S Turkey, extant)
:[[Bearded reedling]] subspecies, which has been considered extinct owing to the drainage of [[Lake Amik]], but is still extant in the area.

'''[[Troglodytidae]]''' &amp;ndash; wrens
* [[San Benedicto rock wren]], ''Salpinctes obsoletus exsul'' (San Benedicto, Revillagigedo Islands, 1952)
:A subspecies of the [[rock wren]] which became extinct around 9:00 AM, August 1, 1952, when its island habitat was devastated by a massive volcanic eruption.
* Guadalupe Bewick's wren, ''Thryomanes bewickii brevicauda'' (Guadalupe, East Pacific, late 1890s?)
:[[Bewick's wren]] subspecies. An extinction date of &quot;1903&quot; seems to be in error;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Extinct Birds|last=Hume|first=Julian P.|publisher=Bloomsbury Publishing|year=2017|isbn=9781472937469|location=|pages=307}}&lt;/ref&gt;the last unquestionable record dates from 1897 and a thorough search in 1901 failed to find it.
* San Clemente Bewick's wren, ''Thryomanes bewickii leucophrys'' (San Clemente, East Pacific, 1941)
:Another Bewick's wren subspecies, last recorded in 1941.
* [[Daito wren]], ''Troglodytes troglodytes orii'' (Daito Islands, Northwest Pacific, c.&amp;nbsp;1940)
:A disputed [[Eurasian wren]] subspecies; as it is known from a single specimen that may have been a vagrant individual; it is possibly invalid.
* Guadeloupe house wren, ''Troglodytes aedon guadeloupensis'' (Guadeloupe, Caribbean, late 20th century?)
:Found in 1914, 1969 and the 1970s; now very rare or already extinct. Taxonomy unresolved. Part of the [[house wren]] complex; other scientific names include ''T. musculus guadeloupensis'' and ''T. guadeloupensis''
* Martinique house wren, ''Troglodytes aedon martinicensis'' (Martinique, Caribbean, c.&amp;nbsp;1890)
:Last found in 1886. Another [[house wren]] complex taxon; other scientific names include ''T. musculus martinicensis'' and ''T. martinicensis''.

'''[[Paridae]]''' &amp;ndash; tits, chickadees and titmice
* [[Daito varied tit]], ''Poecile varia orii'' (Daito Islands, Northwest Pacific, 1938)
:A [[varied tit]] subspecies, variously placed in [[genus]] ''Sittiparus'' and ''Parus'' also. Last recorded in 1938 and not found in subsequent surveys in 1984 and 1986.
* Zagros coal tit, ''Periparus ater phaeonotus'' ([[Zagros Mountains]], Southwestern Iran)
:A [[coal tit]] subspecies, only known by the type specimen from 1870.

'''[[Cinclidae]]''' &amp;ndash; dippers
* [[Cyprus dipper]], ''Cinclus cinclus olympicus'' (Cyprus, Northeast Mediterranean, 1945)
:A subspecies of the [[white-throated dipper]] of questionable validity. It became extinct in 1945.

'''[[Muscicapidae]]''' &amp;ndash; Old World flycatchers and chats
* Tonkean henna-tailed jungle flycatcher, ''Rhinomyias colonus subsolanus'' (Sulawesi, Indonesia, late 20th century?)
:A [[henna-tailed jungle flycatcher]] subspecies that is known from a single specimen; it may not be valid.
* Chinijo chat, ''Saxicola dacotiae murielae'' (Chinijo Archipelago, canary Islands, early 20th century)
:[[Canary Islands stonechat]] subspecies.

'''[[Turdidae]]''' &amp;ndash; thrushes and allies
* Norfolk thrush, ''Turdus poliocephalus poliocephalus'' (Norfolk Island, Southwest Pacific, c.&amp;nbsp;1975)
:[[Island thrush]] subspecies last seen in 1975.
* Maré thrush, ''Turdus poliocephalus mareensis'' (Maré, Melanesia, early 20th century)
:Another subspecies of the island thrush, last collected in 1911 or 1912 and not found anymore in 1939.
* [[Lord Howe thrush]], ''Turdus poliocephalus vinitinctus'' (early 20th century)
:Yet another island thrush subspecies, last recorded in 1913 and extinct by 1928.
* Lifou thrush, ''Turdus poliocephalus pritzbueri'' (Lifou, Melanesia, extant)
:Yet another subspecies of the island thrush. birds surviving on Tanna, New Hebrides, are presently considered the same subspecies. However, given the fact that the species readily differentiates into subspecies and that the distance between Tanna and Lifou is considerable, these birds may belong to a different subspecies, in which case the Lifou thrush would be considered extinct.
* Peleng red-and-black thrush, ''Zoothera mendeni mendeni'' (Peleng, Indonesia, mid-20th century?)
:[[Red-and-black thrush]] nominate subspecies; little known.
* Kibale black-eared ground thrush, ''Zoothera camaronensis kibalensis'' (SW Uganda, late 20th century?)
:A [[black-eared ground thrush]] subspecies known only from two 1966 specimens. Likely to survive in suitable habitat but could be already extinct.
* Choiseul russet-tailed thrush, ''Zoothera heinei choiseuli'' (Choiseul, Solomon Islands, mid-20th century?)
:A subspecies of the [[russet-tailed thrush]] known from a single specimen found in 1924. It could have been killed off by introduced cats, but the island is poorly known and so it should not be presumed extinct.
* Saint Lucia forest thrush, ''Cichlherminia lherminieri sanctaeluciae'' (St Lucia, West Indies, extant)
:A subspecies of the [[forest thrush]]. It has been thought extinct, but the taxon was recorded at Des Chassin in 2007.
* Pines solitaire, ''Myadestes elisabeth retrusus'' (Isla de la Juventud, West Indies, 20th century)
:A subspecies of the [[Cuban solitaire]]. The last confirmed records were in the 1930s, with unconfirmed reports in the early 1970s.

'''[[Mimidae]]''' &amp;ndash; mockingbirds and thrashers
* Barbados scaly-breasted thrasher, ''Allenia fusca atlantica'' (Barbados, West Indies, 1987?)
:[[Scaly-breasted thrasher]] subspecies last recorded in 1987. Most of its range has been searched since then, with no records.

'''[[Estrildidae]]''' &amp;ndash; estrildid finches (waxbills, munias, etc.)
* Southern star finch, ''Neochmia ruficauda ruficauda'' (Australia, 1995)
:A subspecies of the [[star finch]]; last recorded in 1995 and not found during searches later in the 1990s. Not known to survive in captivity.

'''[[Fringillidae]]''' &amp;ndash; true finches and Hawaiian honeycreepers
* San Benito house finch, ''Carpodacus mexicanus mcgregori'' (San Benito, East Pacific, c.&amp;nbsp;1940s)
:[[House finch]] subspecies.
* Lanaʻi ʻalauahio, ''Paroreomyza montana montana'' (Lanaʻi, Hawaiian Islands, 1937)
:A subspecies of the [[Maui ʻalauahio]] (or, more properly, the Maui Nui ʻalauahio). Last recorded in 1937 and certainly extinct by 1960.

[[Image:Dusky Seaside Sparrow.jpg|thumb|[[Dusky seaside sparrow]]]]
'''[[Icteridae]]''' &amp;ndash; grackles
* Grand Cayman oriole, ''Icterus leucopteryx bairdi'' (Grand Cayman, West Indies, late 20th century)
:A subspecies of the [[Jamaican oriole]], last recorded in 1967.

'''[[Parulidae]]''' &amp;ndash; New World warblers
* New Providence yellowthroat, ''Geothlypis rostrata rostrata'' (New Providence, Bahamas, 1990?)
:The nominate subspecies of the [[Bahama yellowthroat]] is either almost or completely extinct.

'''[[Thraupidae]]''' &amp;ndash; tanagers
* Gonâve western chat-tanager, ''Calyptophilus tertius abbotti'' (Gonâve, West Indies, c.&amp;nbsp;1980?)
:A [[western chat-tanager]] subspecies last recorded in 1977 and probably extinct.
* Samaná eastern chat-tanager, ''Calyptophilus frugivorus frugivorus'' (E Hispaniola, West Indies, late 20th century)
:An [[eastern chat-tanager]] subspecies; the last (unconfirmed?) record was in 1982 and concerted efforts to find it since have failed.
* Darwin's large ground finch, ''Geospiza magnirostris magnirostris'' (Floreana?, Galapagos Islands, 1957?)
:A doubtful subspecies of the [[large ground finch]] collected by [[Charles Darwin]] in 1835; he gave no precise locality. A similar bird was found in 1957, but no others have ever been seen.
* Saint Kitts bullfinch, ''Loxigilla portoricensis grandis'' (Saint Kitts and prehistorically Barbuda, West Indies, 1930)
:[[Puerto Rican bullfinch]] subspecies.

'''[[Emberizidae]]''' &amp;ndash; buntings and American sparrows
* Todos Santos rufous-crowned sparrow, ''Aimophila ruficeps sanctorum'' (Islas Todos Santos, E Pacific, 1970s?)
:[[Rufous-crowned sparrow]] subspecies, once common but not recorded during surveys in the 1970s or since.
* Santa Barbara song sparrow, ''Melospiza melodia graminea'' (Santa Barbara Island, late 1960s). Last seen in 1967, became extinct due to a severe wildfire in 1959 and subsequent feral cat predation. Officially declared extinct by the USFWS in 1983.
* [[Dusky seaside sparrow]], ''Ammospiza maritima nigrescens'' (Florida, 1980s)
:[[Seaside sparrow]] subspecies, last recorded in the wild in 1987.
* Guadalupe spotted towhee, ''Pipilo maculatus consobrinus'' (Guadalupe Island, East Pacific, c.&amp;nbsp;1900)
:[[Spotted towhee]] subspecies.&lt;!-- NOT found in 1897, but survey not all too thorough (only one caracara found, but at least half a dozen must have been still extant) --&gt;

==See also==
* [[Bird extinction]]
* [[Holocene extinction]]
* [[Dinosaur]]s
* [[Flightless birds]]
* [[Fossil birds]]
* [[Late Quaternary prehistoric birds]]
* [[Lazarus species]]
* [[List of bird extinctions by year]]
* [[List of extinct animals]]
* [[Origin of birds]]

==Footnotes==
{{Reflist}}

==References==
* [[BirdLife International]] (BLI) (2008): Globally Threatened Forums  &amp;ndash; [http://metropolis229.webcrossing.com/WebX/.2cba657e Sharpe's Rail (''Gallirallus sharpei''): no longer recognised taxonomically]{{dead link|date=January 2018 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}. Version of 2008-NOV-24. Retrieved 2008-DEC-16.
* Fuller, Errol (2000): ''Extinct Birds'' (2nd ed.). Oxford University Press, Oxford, New York. &lt;small&gt;{{ISBN|0-19-850837-9}}&lt;/small&gt;
* Gutiérrez Expósito, Carlos; Copete, José Luis; Crochet, Pierre-André; Qninba, Abdeljebbar and Garrido, Héctor (2011): History, status and distribution of Andalusian Buttonquail in the WP. ''Dutch Birding'' '''33''' (#2): 75–93.
* Spennemann, Dirk H.R. (2006): Extinctions and extirpations in Marshall Islands avifauna since European contact &amp;ndash; a review of historic evidence. ''Micronesica'' '''38'''(#2): 253–266. [https://web.archive.org/web/20110615003304/http://www.uog.edu/up/micronesica/dynamicdata/assetmanager/images/vol38/spennemann.pdf PDF fulltext]
* Szabo, Judit K.; Khwaja, Nyil; Garnett, Stephen T. and Butchart, Stuart H.M. (2012): Global patterns and drivers of avian extinctions at the species and subspecies level. ''PLoS One'' '''7''' (#10): e47080. [http://www.plosone.org/article/info%3Adoi%2F10.1371%2Fjournal.pone.0047080 fulltext]

==External links==
{{Wikispecies|Category:IUCN Extinct species|IUCN Extinct species}}
* [http://www.redlist.org/ The IUCN Red List of Threatened Species]
* [http://www.birdlife.org/community/2010/05/list-of-extinct-bird-species/ The BirdLife Extinct Birds species list]
* [http://www.birdlife.org/datazone/species/search The BirdLife Data Zone containing factsheets for all Birds species]
* [http://www.stockpix.com/stock/animals/birds/extinctbirds/ Extinct Birds Stock Photography]
* [http://www.abirdshome.com/Audubon/extinct.html Extinct Birds from John James Audubon's Birds of America]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20041018052716/http://www.kcc.org.nz/birds/extinct/list.asp New Zealand Extinct Birds List]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20111013123736/http://extinct.petermaas.nl/ The Extinction Website]
* [http://nlbif.eti.uva.nl/naturalis/index.php?lang=uk Naturalis{{spaced ndash}}Extinct Birds]: 3D images of extinct bird species in the collection of the National Museum of Natural History (Leiden, Netherlands).
* [http://news.mongabay.com/2014/0818-hance-birds-extinct-iucn.html 13 newly-discovered birds declared extinct], August 2014
{{Commons category|position=left|Extinct birds}}


{{Birds|state=collapsed}}


[[Category:Bird extinctions since 1500| 01]]
[[Category:Extinct birds|.]]
[[Category:Lists of birds|Extinct, Recent]]
[[Category:Lists of extinct animals|Bird]]
[[Category:Lists of animal species|Birds, Recently extinct]]
[[Category:Lists of animals by conservation status|Recently extinct birds]]
[[Category:Birds by classification|Extinct, Recent]]</text>
      <sha1>drx1irx3gmj9oio9mqly02wnivt7jp7</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
