  <page>
    <title>Edvard Munch</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9779</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942566098</id>
      <parentid>942296058</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-25T13:16:59Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bluelink 1 book for [[Wikipedia:Verifiability|verifiability]]. [goog]) #IABot (v2.0) ([[User:GreenC bot|GreenC bot]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{for|the 1974 film|Edvard Munch (film)}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2012}}
{{Infobox artist
| name = Edvard Munch
| image = Portrett av Edvard Munch (cropped).jpg
| caption = Munch in an undated photo
| birth_date = {{Birth date|1863|12|12|df=y}}
| birth_place = [[Ådalsbruk]], [[Løten]], [[Union between Sweden and Norway|Norway]]
| death_date = {{Death date and age|1944|1|23|1863|12|12|df=y}}
| death_place = [[Oslo]], [[Norway]]
| nationality = [[Norwegians|Norwegian]]
| field = [[Painting]] and graphic artist
| training =
| movement = [[Expressionism]], [[Symbolism (arts)|Symbolism]]
| works = {{plainlist|
* ''[[The Scream]]''
* ''[[Madonna (Edvard Munch)|Madonna]]''
* ''[[The Sick Child (Munch)|The Sick Child]]''
}}
| patrons =
| influenced by =
| influenced =
| awards =
}}
'''Edvard Munch''' ({{IPAc-en|m|ʊ|ŋ|k}} {{Respell|MUUNK}},{{sfn|Wells|2008|p=}} {{IPA-no|ˈɛ̀dvɑʈ ˈmʊŋk|lang|Edvard_Munch_pronunciation.ogg}}; 12 December 1863 – 23 January 1944) was a [[Norwegians|Norwegian]] [[painting|painter]]. His best known work, ''[[The Scream]]'', has become one of the most iconic images of world art.

His childhood was overshadowed by illness, bereavement and the dread of inheriting a mental condition that ran in the family. Studying at the [[Norwegian National Academy of Fine Arts|Royal School of Art and Design]] in Kristiania (today's Oslo), Munch began to live a bohemian life under the influence of nihilist [[Hans Jæger]], who urged him to paint his own emotional and psychological state ('soul painting'). From this emerged his distinctive style.

Travel brought new influences and outlets. In Paris, he learned much from [[Paul Gauguin]], [[Vincent van Gogh]] and [[Henri de Toulouse-Lautrec]], especially their use of colour. In Berlin, he met Swedish dramatist [[August Strindberg]], whom he painted, as he embarked on his major canon ''The Frieze of Life'', depicting a series of deeply-felt themes such as love, anxiety, jealousy and betrayal, steeped in atmosphere.

''The Scream'' was conceived in Kristiania. According to Munch, he was out walking at sunset, when he ‘heard the enormous, infinite scream of nature’. The painting's agonised face is widely identified with the ''angst'' of the modern person. Between 1893 and 1910, he made two painted versions and two in pastels, as well as a number of prints. One of the pastels would eventually command the fourth highest nominal price paid for a painting at auction.

As his fame and wealth grew, his emotional state remained insecure. He briefly considered marriage, but could not commit himself. A breakdown in 1908 forced him to give up heavy drinking, and he was cheered by his increasing acceptance by the people of Kristiania and exposure in the city’s museums. His later years were spent working in peace and privacy. Although his works were banned in Nazi Germany, most of them survived World War II, ensuring him a secure legacy.

==Life==
=== Childhood ===
Edvard Munch was born in a farmhouse in the village of [[Ådalsbruk]] in [[Løten]], [[Union between Sweden and Norway|Norway]], to Laura Catherine Bjølstad and Christian Munch, the son of a priest. Christian was a doctor and medical officer who married Laura, a woman half his age, in 1861. Edvard had an elder sister, Johanne Sophie, and three younger siblings: Peter Andreas, Laura Catherine, and Inger Marie. Laura was artistically talented and may have encouraged Edvard and Sophie. Edvard was related to painter [[Jacob Munch]] and to historian [[Peter Andreas Munch]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Eggum|1984|p=15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The family moved to Christiania (renamed Kristiania in 1877, and now [[Oslo]]) in 1864 when Christian Munch was appointed medical officer at [[Akershus Fortress]]. Edvard's mother died of [[tuberculosis]] in 1868, as did Munch's favorite sister Johanne Sophie in 1877.&lt;ref name=Eg_p16&gt;{{harvnb|Eggum|1984|p=16}}&lt;/ref&gt; After their mother's death, the Munch siblings were raised by their father and by their aunt Karen. Often ill for much of the winters and kept out of school, Edvard would draw to keep himself occupied. He was tutored by his school mates and his aunt. Christian Munch also instructed his son in history and literature, and entertained the children with vivid ghost-stories and the tales of American writer [[Edgar Allan Poe]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Prideaux|2005|p=17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As Edvard remembered it, Christian's positive behavior toward his children was overshadowed by his morbid [[pietism]]. Munch wrote, &quot;My father was temperamentally nervous and obsessively religious—to the point of psychoneurosis. From him I inherited the seeds of madness. The angels of fear, sorrow, and death stood by my side since the day I was born.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Prideaux|2005|p=2}}&lt;/ref&gt; Christian reprimanded his children by telling them that their mother was looking down from heaven and grieving over their misbehavior. The oppressive religious milieu, Edvard's poor health, and the vivid ghost stories helped inspire his macabre visions and nightmares; the boy felt that death was constantly advancing on him.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Prideaux|2005|p=19}}&lt;/ref&gt; One of Munch's younger sisters, Laura, was diagnosed with mental illness at an early age. Of the five siblings, only Andreas married, but he died a few months after the wedding. Munch would later write, &quot;I inherited two of mankind's most frightful enemies—the heritage of consumption and insanity.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Eggum|1984|p=137}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Christian Munch's military pay was very low, and his attempts to develop a private side practice failed, keeping his family in genteel but perennial poverty.&lt;ref name=Eg_p16/&gt; They moved frequently from one cheap flat to another. Munch's early drawings and watercolors depicted these interiors, and the individual objects, such as medicine bottles and drawing implements, plus some landscapes. By his teens, art dominated Munch's interests.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Eggum|1984|p=22}}&lt;/ref&gt; At thirteen, Munch had his first exposure to other artists at the newly formed Art Association, where he admired the work of the Norwegian landscape school. He returned to copy the paintings, and soon he began to paint in oils.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Prideaux|2005|pp=22–23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Studies and influences===
[[File:Edvard Munch - Self-Portrait (1895) G0192-59 - Google Art Project.jpg|thumb|right|''Self-Portrait with Skeleton Arm'', 1895]]
In 1879, Munch enrolled in a [[Institute of technology|technical college]] to study engineering, where he excelled in physics, chemistry and math. He learned scaled and perspective drawing, but frequent illnesses interrupted his studies.&lt;ref name=Pr_p35&gt;{{harvnb|Prideaux|2005|p=35}}&lt;/ref&gt; The following year, much to his father's disappointment, Munch left the college determined to become a painter. His father viewed art as an &quot;unholy trade&quot;, and his neighbors reacted bitterly and sent him anonymous letters.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Prideaux|2005|p=40}}&lt;/ref&gt; In contrast to his father's rabid pietism, Munch adopted an undogmatic stance toward art. He wrote his goal in his diary: &quot;in my art I attempt to explain life and its meaning to myself.&quot;&lt;ref name=Pr_p35/&gt;

In 1881, Munch enrolled at the [[Norwegian National Academy of Fine Arts|Royal School of Art and Design]] of Kristiania, one of whose founders was his distant relative Jacob Munch. His teachers were sculptor [[Julius Middelthun]] and the [[Naturalism (painting)|naturalistic]] painter [[Christian Krohg]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Prideaux|2005|p=41}}&lt;/ref&gt; That year, Munch demonstrated his quick absorption of his figure training at the Academy in his first portraits, including one of his father and his first self-portrait. In 1883, Munch took part in his first public exhibition and shared a studio with other students.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Eggum|1984|p=34}}&lt;/ref&gt; His full-length portrait of Karl Jensen-Hjell, a notorious bohemian-about-town, earned a critic's dismissive response: &quot;It is impressionism carried to the extreme. It is a travesty of art.&quot;&lt;ref name=Pr_p34&gt;{{harvnb|Prideaux|2005|p=34}}&lt;/ref&gt; Munch's nude paintings from this period survive only in sketches, except for ''Standing Nude'' (1887). They may have been confiscated by his father.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Eggum|1984|p=41}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During these early years, Munch experimented with many styles, including [[Naturalism (painting)|Naturalism]] and [[Impressionism]]. Some early works are reminiscent of [[Édouard Manet|Manet]]. Many of these attempts brought him unfavorable criticism from the press and garnered him constant rebukes by his father, who nonetheless provided him with small sums for living expenses.&lt;ref name=Pr_p34/&gt; At one point, however, Munch's father, perhaps swayed by the negative opinion of Munch's cousin Edvard Diriks (an established, traditional painter), destroyed at least one painting (likely a nude) and refused to advance any more money for art supplies.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Eggum|1984|p=43}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Munch also received his father's ire for his relationship with [[Hans Jæger]], the local nihilist who lived by the code &quot;a passion to destroy is also a creative passion&quot; and who advocated suicide as the ultimate way to freedom.&lt;ref name=&quot;Prideaux&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Prideaux|2005|pp=71, 74}}&lt;/ref&gt; Munch came under his malevolent, anti-establishment spell. &quot;My ideas developed under the influence of the [[Bohemianism|bohemians]] or rather under Hans Jæger. Many people have mistakenly claimed that my ideas were formed under the influence of [[Strindberg]] and the Germans…but that is wrong. They had already been formed by then.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Prideaux|2005|p=71}}&lt;/ref&gt; At that time, contrary to many of the other bohemians, Munch was still respectful of women, as well as reserved and well-mannered, but he began to give in to the binge drinking and brawling of his circle. He was unsettled by the sexual revolution going on at the time and by the independent women around him. He later turned cynical concerning sexual matters, expressed not only in his behavior and his art, but in his writings as well, an example being a long poem called ''The City of Free Love''.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Prideaux|2005|p=72}}&lt;/ref&gt; Still dependent on his family for many of his meals, Munch's relationship with his father remained tense over concerns about his bohemian life.

After numerous experiments, Munch concluded that the Impressionist idiom did not allow sufficient expression. He found it superficial and too akin to scientific experimentation. He felt a need to go deeper and explore situations brimming with emotional content and expressive energy. Under Jæger's commandment that Munch should &quot;write his life&quot;, meaning that Munch should explore his own emotional and psychological state, the young artist began a period of reflection and self-examination, recording his thoughts in his &quot;soul's diary&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Prideaux|2005|p=83}}&lt;/ref&gt; This deeper perspective helped move him to a new view of his art. He wrote that his painting ''[[The Sick Child (Munch)|The Sick Child]]'' (1886), based on his sister's death, was his first &quot;soul painting&quot;, his first break from Impressionism. The painting received a negative response from critics and from his family, and caused another &quot;violent outburst of moral indignation&quot; from the community.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Prideaux|2005|p=88}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Only his friend Christian Krohg defended him:
&lt;blockquote&gt;He paints, or rather regards, things in a way that is different from that of other artists. He sees only the essential, and that, naturally, is all he paints. For this reason Munch's pictures are as a rule &quot;not complete&quot;, as people are so delighted to discover for themselves. Oh, yes, they are complete. His complete handiwork. Art is complete once the artist has really said everything that was on his mind, and this is precisely the advantage Munch has over painters of the other generation, that he really knows how to show us what he has felt, and what has gripped him, and to this he subordinates everything else.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Eggum|1984|pp=52–53}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Munch continued to employ a variety of brushstroke techniques and color palettes throughout the 1880s and early 1890s, as he struggled to define his style.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Eggum|1984|p=46}}&lt;/ref&gt; His idiom continued to veer between [[Naturalism (arts)|naturalistic]], as seen in ''Portrait of Hans Jæger'', and [[Impressionism|impressionistic]], as in ''Rue Lafayette''. His ''[[Inger On the Beach]]'' (1889), which caused another storm of confusion and controversy, hints at the simplified forms, heavy outlines, sharp contrasts, and emotional content of his mature style to come.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Eggum|1984|p=59}}&lt;/ref&gt; He began to carefully calculate his compositions to create tension and emotion. While stylistically influenced by the [[Post-Impressionism|Post-Impressionists]], what evolved was a subject matter which was [[symbolism (arts)|symbolist]] in content, depicting a state of mind rather than an external reality. In 1889, Munch presented his first one-man show of nearly all his works to date. The recognition it received led to a two-year state scholarship to study in Paris under French painter [[Léon Bonnat]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Eggum|1984|p=55}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Munch seems to have been an early critic of photography as an art form, and remarked that it &quot;will never compete with the brush and the palette, until such time as photographs can be taken in Heaven or Hell!&quot;{{sfn|Berman|1986|p=106}}

Munch's younger sister Laura was the subject of his 1899 interior ''Melancholy: Laura''. Amanda O'Neill says of the work, &quot;In this heated claustrophobic scene Munch not only portrays Laura's tragedy, but his own dread of the madness he might have inherited.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|O'Neill|1996|p=44}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Paris===
Munch arrived in Paris during the festivities of the [[Exposition Universelle (1889)]] and roomed with two fellow Norwegian artists. His picture ''Morning'' (1884) was displayed at the Norwegian pavilion.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Prideaux|2005|p=49}}&lt;/ref&gt; He spent his mornings at Bonnat's busy studio (which included live female models) and afternoons at the exhibition, galleries, and museums (where students were expected to make copies as a way of learning technique and observation).&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Eggum|1984|p=108}}&lt;/ref&gt; Munch recorded little enthusiasm for Bonnat's drawing lessons—&quot;It tires and bores me—it's numbing&quot;—but enjoyed the master's commentary during museum trips.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Prideaux|2005|p=110}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Eg_p61&gt;{{harvnb|Eggum|1984|p=61}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Munch was enthralled by the vast display of modern European art, including the works of three artists who would prove influential: [[Paul Gauguin]], [[Vincent van Gogh]], and [[Henri de Toulouse-Lautrec]]—all notable for how they used color to convey emotion.&lt;ref name=Eg_p61/&gt; Munch was particularly inspired by Gauguin's &quot;reaction against realism&quot; and his credo that &quot;art was human work and not an imitation of Nature&quot;, a belief earlier stated by [[James Abbott McNeill Whistler|Whistler]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Eggum|1984|p=9}}&lt;/ref&gt; As one of his Berlin friends said later of Munch, &quot;he need not make his way to Tahiti to see and experience the primitive in human nature. He carries his own Tahiti within him.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Eggum|1984|p=12}}&lt;/ref&gt; Influenced by Gauguin, as well as the etchings of German artist [[Max Klinger]], Munch experimented with prints as a medium to create graphic versions of his works. In 1896 he created his first woodcuts—a medium that proved ideal to Munch's symbolic imagery.&lt;ref name=&quot;TaurisBlog&quot; /&gt; Together with his contemporary [[Nikolai Astrup]], Munch is considered an innovator of the woodcut medium in Norway.&lt;ref name=&quot;KODE&quot; /&gt;

In December 1889 his father died, leaving Munch's family destitute. He returned home and arranged a large loan from a wealthy Norwegian collector when wealthy relatives failed to help, and assumed financial responsibility for his family from then on.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Prideaux|2005|p=114}}&lt;/ref&gt; Christian's death depressed him and he was plagued by suicidal thoughts: &quot;I live with the dead—my mother, my sister, my grandfather, my father…Kill yourself and then it's over. Why live?&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Prideaux|2005|p=115}}&lt;/ref&gt; Munch's paintings of the following year included sketchy tavern scenes and a series of bright cityscapes in which he experimented with the [[Pointillism|pointillist]] style of [[Georges Seurat]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Eggum|1984|pp=64–68}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Berlin===
[[File:Edvard Munch - Evening. Melancholy (1891).jpg|thumb|''Melancholy'', 1891, oil, pencil and crayon on canvas, 73 × 101 cm, [[Munch Museum]], Oslo]]
[[File:Edvard Munch im Lindeschen Garten, Lübeck 1902.jpg|thumb|Munch in 1902, in the garden of his patron [[Max Linde|Dr. Max Linde]] in [[Lübeck]]; in the background is a cast of [[Auguste Rodin]]'s sculpture ''Iron Era''.]]
By 1892, Munch formulated his characteristic, and original, [[synthetism|Synthetist]] [[aesthetic]], as seen in ''[[Melancholy (Edvard Munch)|Melancholy]]'' (1891), in which color is the symbol-laden element. Considered by the artist and journalist [[Christian Krohg]] as the first [[Symbolism (art)|Symbolist]] painting by a Norwegian artist, ''Melancholy'' was exhibited in 1891 at the Autumn Exhibition in Oslo.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eggum75&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Eggum|1984|p=75}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1892, [[Adelsteen Normann]], on behalf of the Union of Berlin Artists, invited Munch to exhibit at its November exhibition,&lt;ref name=&quot;Pr_135&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Prideaux|2005|pp=135–137}}&lt;/ref&gt; the society's first one-man exhibition. However, his paintings evoked bitter controversy (dubbed &quot;The Munch Affair&quot;), and after one week the exhibition closed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pr_135&quot;/&gt; Munch was pleased with the &quot;great commotion&quot;, and wrote in a letter: &quot;Never have I had such an amusing time—it's incredible that something as innocent as painting should have created such a stir.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Eggum|1984|p=91}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Berlin, Munch became involved in an international circle of writers, artists and critics, including the Swedish dramatist and leading intellectual [[August Strindberg]], whom he painted in 1892.{{sfn|Morehead|2019|pp=19-34}} He also met Danish writer and painter [[Holger Drachmann]], whom he painted in 1898. Drachmann was 17 years Munch's senior and a drinking companion at [[Zum schwarzen Ferkel]] in 1893–94.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Munch|2005|p=119}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1894 Drachmann wrote of Munch: &quot;He struggles hard. Good luck with your struggles, lonely Norwegian.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Munch|2005|p=7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During his four years in Berlin, Munch sketched out most of the ideas that would comprise his major work, ''The Frieze of Life'', first designed for book illustration but later expressed in paintings.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Eggum|1984|p=77}}&lt;/ref&gt; He sold little, but made some income from charging entrance fees to view his controversial paintings.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Prideaux|2005|p=153}}&lt;/ref&gt; Already, Munch was showing a reluctance to part with his paintings, which he termed his &quot;children&quot;.

His other paintings, including casino scenes, show a simplification of form and detail which marked his early mature style.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Eggum|1984|p=79}}&lt;/ref&gt; Munch also began to favor a shallow pictorial space and a minimal backdrop for his frontal figures. Since poses were chosen to produce the most convincing images of states of mind and psychological conditions, as in ''Ashes'', the figures impart a monumental, static quality. Munch's figures appear to play roles on a theatre stage (''Death in the Sick-Room''), whose pantomime of fixed postures signify various emotions; since each character embodies a single psychological dimension, as in ''The Scream'', Munch's men and women began to appear more symbolic than realistic. He wrote, &quot;No longer should interiors be painted, people reading and women knitting: there would be living people, breathing and feeling, suffering and loving.&quot;&lt;ref name=Eg_p10&gt;{{harvnb|Eggum|1984|p=10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===''The Scream''===
{{Main|The Scream}}
[[File:Edvard Munch, 1893, The Scream, oil, tempera and pastel on cardboard, 91 x 73 cm, National Gallery of Norway.jpg|thumb|''[[The Scream]]'' (1893)]]
''The Scream'' exists in four versions: two pastels (1893 and 1895) and two paintings (1893 and 1910). There are also several lithographs of ''The Scream'' (1895 and later).

The 1895 pastel sold at auction on 2 May 2012 for [[US$]]119,922,500, including commission. It is the most colorful of the versions&lt;ref name=&quot;Vogel2012&quot; /&gt; and is distinctive for the downward-looking stance of one of its background figures. It is also the only version not held by a Norwegian museum.

The 1893 version was stolen from the [[National Museum of Art, Architecture and Design|National Gallery]] in Oslo in 1994 and recovered. The 1910 painting was stolen in 2004 from The Munch Museum in Oslo, but recovered in 2006 with limited damage.

''The Scream'' is Munch's most famous work, and one of the most recognizable paintings in all art. It has been widely interpreted as representing the universal anxiety of modern man.&lt;ref name=Eg_p10/&gt; Painted with broad bands of garish color and highly simplified forms, and employing a high viewpoint, it reduces the agonized figure to a garbed skull in the throes of an emotional crisis.

With this painting, Munch met his stated goal of &quot;the study of the soul, that is to say the study of my own self&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Faerna|1995|p=16}}&lt;/ref&gt; Munch wrote of how the painting came to be: &quot;I was walking down the road with two friends when the sun set; suddenly, the sky turned as red as blood. I stopped and leaned against the fence, feeling unspeakably tired. Tongues of fire and blood stretched over the bluish black fjord. My friends went on walking, while I lagged behind, shivering with fear. Then I heard the enormous, infinite scream of nature.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Faerna|1995|p=17}}&lt;/ref&gt; He later described the personal anguish behind the painting, &quot;for several years I was almost mad… You know my picture, 'The Scream?' I was stretched to the limit—nature was screaming in my blood… After that I gave up hope ever of being able to love again.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Prideaux|2005|p=152}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In summing up the painting's effects, author Martha Tedeschi has stated:
&lt;blockquote&gt;''[[Whistler's Mother]]'', Wood's ''[[American Gothic]]'', Leonardo da Vinci's ''[[Mona Lisa]]'' and Edvard Munch's ''The Scream'' have all achieved something that most paintings—regardless of their art historical importance, beauty, or monetary value—have not: they communicate a specific meaning almost immediately to almost every viewer. These few works have successfully made the transition from the elite realm of the museum visitor to the enormous venue of popular culture.{{sfn|MacDonald|2003|p=80}}&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===''Frieze of Life—A Poem about Life, Love and Death''===
[[File:Edvard Munch - Madonna - Google Art Project.jpg|thumb|Although it is a highly unusual representation, this painting might be of the [[Mary (mother of Jesus)|Virgin Mary]]. Whether the painting is specifically intended as a representation of Mary is disputed. Munch used more than one title, including both '''''Loving Woman''''' and ''Madonna''.&lt;ref name = &quot;bis&quot;&gt;Bischoff, Ulrich, [https://books.google.com/books?id=ETahibk334cC&amp;pg=PA43&amp;dq=Munch+Madonna+1892&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=nsUrUYDHFK2a0QXMooGADA&amp;ved=0CC4Q6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=Munch%20Madonna%201892&amp;f=false ''Edvard Munch: 1863-1944''], p. 42, Taschen, 2000, {{ISBN|3822859710}}, 9783822859711&lt;/ref&gt; Munch is not famous for religious artwork and was not known as a Christian. The affinity to Mary might as well be intended nevertheless, as an emphasis on the beauty and perfection of his friend [[Dagny Juel-Przybyszewska]], the model for the work, and an expression of his worship of her as an ideal of womanhood.&lt;ref&gt;Cornelia Gerner, ''Die &quot;Madonna&quot; in Edvard Munchs Werk – Frauenbilder und Frauenbild im ausgehenden 19. Jahrhundert'' Knut Brynhildsvoll, Literaturverlag Norden Mark Reinhard, Morsbach, 1993, {{ISBN|978-3-927153-40-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
In December 1893, [[Unter den Linden]] in Berlin was the location of an exhibition of Munch's work, showing, among other pieces, six paintings entitled ''Study for a Series: Love.'' This began a cycle he later called the ''Frieze of Life—A Poem about Life, Love and Death''. ''Frieze of Life'' motifs, such as ''The Storm'' and ''Moonlight'', are steeped in atmosphere. Other motifs illuminate the nocturnal side of love, such as ''Rose and Amelie'' and ''Vampire''. In ''Death in the Sickroom'', the subject is the death of his sister Sophie, which he re-worked in many future variations. The dramatic focus of the painting, portraying his entire family, is dispersed in the separate and disconnected figures of sorrow. In 1894, he enlarged the spectrum of motifs by adding ''Anxiety'', ''Ashes'', ''[[Madonna (Edvard Munch)|Madonna]]'' and ''Women in Three Stages'' (from innocence to old age).&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Faerna|1995|p=28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Around the start of the 20th century, Munch worked to finish the &quot;Frieze&quot;. He painted a number of pictures, several of them in bigger format and to some extent featuring the [[Art Nouveau]] aesthetics of the time. He made a wooden frame with carved reliefs for the large painting ''Metabolism'' (1898), initially called ''Adam and Eve''. This work reveals Munch's preoccupation with the &quot;fall of man&quot; and his pessimistic philosophy of love. Motifs such as ''The Empty Cross'' and ''Golgotha'' (both {{circa|1900}}) reflect a metaphysical orientation, and also reflect Munch's pietistic upbringing. The entire ''Frieze'' was shown for the first time at the [[Berlin Secession|secessionist]] exhibition in Berlin in 1902.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Prideaux|2005|p=211}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&quot;The Frieze of Life&quot; themes recur throughout Munch's work but he especially focused on them in the mid-1890s. In sketches, paintings, pastels and prints, he tapped the depths of his feelings to examine his major motifs: the stages of life, the femme fatale, the hopelessness of love, anxiety, infidelity, jealousy, sexual humiliation, and separation in life and death.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Eggum|1984|pp=116–118}}&lt;/ref&gt; These themes are expressed in paintings such as ''[[The Sick Child (Munch)|The Sick Child]]'' (1885), ''Love and Pain'' (retitled ''Vampire''; 1893–94), ''Ashes'' (1894), and ''The Bridge''. The latter shows limp figures with featureless or hidden faces, over which loom the threatening shapes of heavy trees and brooding houses. Munch portrayed women either as frail, innocent sufferers (see ''[[Puberty (Edvard Munch)|Puberty]]'' and ''Love and Pain'') or as the cause of great longing, jealousy and despair (see ''Separation'', ''Jealousy'', and ''Ashes'').

Munch often uses shadows and rings of color around his figures to emphasize an aura of fear, menace, anxiety, or sexual intensity.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Eggum|1984|p=122}}&lt;/ref&gt; These paintings have been interpreted as reflections of the artist's sexual anxieties, though it could also be argued that they represent his turbulent relationship with love itself and his general pessimism regarding human existence.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Faerna|1995|p=6}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many of these sketches and paintings were done in several versions, such as ''Madonna'', ''Hands'' and ''Puberty'', and also transcribed as wood-block prints and lithographs. Munch hated to part with his paintings because he thought of his work as a single body of expression. So to capitalize on his production and make some income, he turned to graphic arts to reproduce many of his paintings, including those in this series.&lt;ref name=Fa_p5&gt;{{harvnb|Faerna|1995|p=5}}&lt;/ref&gt; Munch admitted to the personal goals of his work but he also offered his art to a wider purpose, &quot;My art is really a voluntary confession and an attempt to explain to myself my relationship with life—it is, therefore, actually a sort of egoism, but I am constantly hoping that through this I can help others achieve clarity.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Eggum|1984|p=118}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While attracting strongly negative reactions, in the 1890s Munch began to receive some understanding of his artistic goals, as one critic wrote, &quot;With ruthless contempt for form, clarity, elegance, wholeness, and realism, he paints with intuitive strength of talent the most subtle visions of the soul.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Eggum|1984|p=121}}&lt;/ref&gt; One of his great supporters in Berlin was [[Walther Rathenau]], later the German [[foreign minister]], who strongly contributed to his success.

===Paris, Berlin and Kristiania===
[[File:Edvard Munch - The sick child (1907) - Tate Modern.jpg|right|thumb|''[[The Sick Child (Munch)|The Sick Child]]'' (1907)]]
In 1896, Munch moved to Paris, where he focused on graphic representations of his ''Frieze of Life'' themes. He further developed his woodcut and lithographic technique. Munch's ''Self-Portrait with Skeleton Arm'' (1895) is done with an etching needle-and-ink method also used by [[Paul Klee]].&lt;ref name=Eg_p141&gt;{{harvnb|Eggum|1984|p=141}}&lt;/ref&gt; Munch also produced multi-colored versions of ''The Sick Child'', [[Tuberculosis in human culture|concerning tuberculosis]], which sold well, as well as several nudes and multiple versions of ''Kiss'' (1892).&lt;ref name=Eg_p141/&gt; Many of the Parisian critics still considered Munch's work &quot;violent and brutal&quot; but his exhibitions received serious attention and good attendance.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Eggum|1984|p=152}}&lt;/ref&gt; His financial situation improved considerably and in 1897, Munch bought himself a summer house facing the fjords of Kristiania, a small fisherman's cabin built in the late 18th century, in the small town of [[Åsgårdstrand]] in Norway. He dubbed this home the &quot;Happy House&quot; and returned here almost every summer for the next 20 years.&lt;ref name=Eg_p153/&gt; It was this place he missed when he was abroad and when he felt depressed and exhausted. &quot;To walk in Åsgårdstrand is like walking among my paintings—I get so inspired to paint when I am here&quot;.

[[File:Aase and Harald Nørregaard.jpeg|thumb|[[Harald Nørregaard]] (painted by Munch in 1899, [[National Gallery (Norway)|National Gallery]]) was one of Munch's closest friends since adolescence, adviser and lawyer{{sfn|Thiis|1933|p=279}}]]
In 1897 Munch returned to Kristiania, where he also received grudging acceptance—one critic wrote, &quot;A fair number of these pictures have been exhibited before. In my opinion these improve on acquaintance.&quot;&lt;ref name=Eg_p153&gt;{{harvnb|Eggum|1984|p=153}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1899, Munch began an intimate relationship with Tulla Larsen, a &quot;liberated&quot; upper-class woman. They traveled to Italy together and upon returning, Munch began another fertile period in his art, which included landscapes and his final painting in &quot;The Frieze of Life&quot; series, ''The Dance of Life'' (1899).&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Eggum|1984|p=168}}&lt;/ref&gt; Larsen was eager for marriage, and Munch begged off. His drinking and poor health reinforced his fears, as he wrote in the third person: &quot;Ever since he was a child he had hated marriage. His sick and nervous home had given him the feeling that he had no right to get married.&quot;&lt;ref name=Eg_p174&gt;{{harvnb|Eggum|1984|p=174}}&lt;/ref&gt; Munch almost gave in to Tulla, but fled from her in 1900, also turning away from her considerable fortune, and moved to Berlin.&lt;ref name=Eg_p174/&gt; His ''Girls on the Jetty'', created in eighteen different versions, demonstrated the theme of feminine youth without negative connotations.&lt;ref name=Fa_p5/&gt; In 1902, he displayed his works thematically at the hall of the Berlin Secession, producing &quot;a symphonic effect—it made a great stir—a lot of antagonism—and a lot of approval.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Eggum|1984|p=176}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Berlin critics were beginning to appreciate Munch's work even though the public still found his work alien and strange.

The good press coverage gained Munch the attention of influential patrons Albert Kollman and [[Max Linde]]. He described the turn of events in his diary, &quot;After twenty years of struggle and misery forces of good finally come to my aid in Germany—and a bright door opens up for me.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Eggum|1984|p=181}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, despite this positive change, Munch's self-destructive and erratic behavior involved him first with a violent quarrel with another artist, then with an accidental shooting in the presence of Tulla Larsen, who had returned for a brief reconciliation, which injured two of his fingers. Munch later sawed a self-portrait depicting him and Larsen in half as a consequence of the shooting and subsequent events.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thorpe2019&quot; /&gt; She finally left him and married a younger colleague of Munch. Munch took this as a betrayal, and he dwelled on the humiliation for some time to come, channeling some of the bitterness into new paintings.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Eggum|1984|p=183}}&lt;/ref&gt; His paintings ''Still Life (The Murderess)'' and ''The Death of Marat I'', done in 1906–07, clearly reference the shooting incident and the emotional after effects.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Eggum|1984|p=214}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1903–04, Munch exhibited in Paris where the coming [[Fauvism|Fauvists]], famous for their boldly false colors, likely saw his works and might have found inspiration in them. When the Fauves held their own exhibit in 1906, Munch was invited and displayed his works with theirs.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Eggum|1984|p=190}}&lt;/ref&gt; After studying the sculpture of [[Auguste Rodin|Rodin]], Munch may have experimented with plasticine as an aid to design, but he produced little sculpture.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Eggum|1984|p=195}}&lt;/ref&gt; During this time, Munch received many commissions for portraits and prints which improved his usually precarious financial condition.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Eggum|1984|pp=196, 203}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1906, he painted the screen for an [[Ibsen]] play in the small Kammerspiele Theatre located in Berlin's [[Deutsches Theater (Berlin)|Deutsches Theater]], in which the ''Frieze of Life'' was hung. The theatre's director [[Max Reinhardt]] later sold it; it is now in the Berlin [[Nationalgalerie]].{{sfn|Bernau|2005|pp=65-78}} After an earlier period of landscapes, in 1907 he turned his attention again to human figures and situations.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Eggum|1984|p=228}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Breakdown and recovery===
[[File:Edvard Munch 1933.jpg|thumb|left|Munch in 1933]]
In the autumn of 1908, Munch's anxiety, compounded by excessive drinking and brawling, had become acute. As he later wrote, &quot;My condition was verging on madness—it was touch and go.&quot;&lt;ref name=Eg_p236&gt;{{harvnb|Eggum|1984|p=236}}&lt;/ref&gt; Subject to hallucinations and feelings of persecution, he entered the clinic of Daniel Jacobson. The [[psychotherapy|therapy]] Munch received for the next eight months included diet and &quot;electrification&quot; (a treatment then fashionable for nervous conditions, not to be confused with [[electroconvulsive therapy]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Eggum|1984|pp=235–236}}&lt;/ref&gt; Munch's stay in hospital stabilized his personality, and after returning to Norway in 1909, his work became more colorful and less pessimistic. Further brightening his mood, the general public of Kristiania finally warmed to his work, and museums began to purchase his paintings. He was made a Knight of the Royal Order of St. Olav &quot;for services in art&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Eggum|1984|p=239}}&lt;/ref&gt; His first American exhibit was in 1912 in New York.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Prideaux|2005|p=373}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As part of his recovery, Dr. Jacobson advised Munch to only socialize with good friends and avoid [[drinking in public]]. Munch followed this advice and in the process produced several full-length portraits of high quality of friends and patrons—honest portrayals devoid of flattery.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Eggum|1984|p=240}}&lt;/ref&gt; He also created landscapes and scenes of people at work and play, using a new optimistic style—broad, loose brushstrokes of vibrant color with frequent use of white space and rare use of black—with only occasional references to his morbid themes. With more income, Munch was able to buy several properties giving him new vistas for his art and he was finally able to provide for his family.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Eggum|1984|p=259}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The outbreak of World War I found Munch with divided loyalties, as he stated, &quot;All my friends are German but it is France I love.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Prideaux|2005|p=285}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the 1930s, his German patrons, many Jewish, lost their fortunes and some their lives during the rise of the Nazi movement.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Prideaux|2005|p=288}}&lt;/ref&gt; Munch found Norwegian printers to substitute for the Germans who had been printing his graphic work.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Prideaux|2005|p=290}}&lt;/ref&gt; Given his poor health history, during 1918 Munch felt himself lucky to have survived a bout of the [[Spanish flu]], the worldwide pandemic of that year.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Prideaux|2005|p=299}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Later years===
[[File:Munch grave 2.JPG|thumb|Munch's grave at the [[Cemetery of Our Saviour]], Oslo]]
Munch spent most of his last two decades in solitude at his nearly self-sufficient estate in Ekely, at [[Skøyen]], Oslo.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Prideaux|2005|p=291}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many of his late paintings celebrate farm life, including several in which he used his work horse &quot;Rousseau&quot; as a model.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Prideaux|2005|p=292}}&lt;/ref&gt; Without any effort, Munch attracted a steady stream of female models, whom he painted as the subjects of numerous nude paintings. He likely had sexual relationships with some of them.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Prideaux|2005|p=297}}&lt;/ref&gt; Munch occasionally left his home to paint murals on commission, including those done for the [[Freia (chocolate)|Freia]] chocolate factory.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Prideaux|2005|p=374}}&lt;/ref&gt;

To the end of his life, Munch continued to paint unsparing self-portraits, adding to his self-searching cycle of his life and his unflinching series of takes on his emotional and physical states. In the 1930s and 1940s, the [[Nazis]] labeled Munch's work &quot;[[degenerate art]]&quot; (along with that of [[Pablo Picasso|Picasso]], [[Paul Klee|Klee]], [[Henri Matisse|Matisse]], [[Paul Gauguin|Gauguin]] and many other modern artists) and removed his 82 works from German museums.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Eggum|1984|p=287}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Adolf Hitler]] announced in 1937, &quot;For all we care, those prehistoric Stone Age culture barbarians and art-stutterers can return to the caves of their ancestors and there can apply their primitive international scratching.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Prideaux|2005|p=313}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1940, the [[Occupation of Norway by Nazi Germany|Germans invaded Norway]] and the Nazi party took over the government. Munch was 76 years old. With nearly an entire collection of his art in the second floor of his house, Munch lived in fear of a Nazi confiscation. Seventy-one of the paintings previously taken by the Nazis had been returned to Norway through purchase by collectors (the other eleven were never recovered), including ''The Scream'' and ''The Sick Child'', and they too were hidden from the Nazis.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Prideaux|2005|p=319}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Munch died in his house at Ekely near Oslo on 23 January 1944, about a month after his 80th birthday. His Nazi-orchestrated funeral suggested to Norwegians that he was a Nazi sympathizer, a kind of appropriation of the independent artist.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Prideaux|2005|p=328}}&lt;/ref&gt; The city of Oslo bought the Ekely estate from Munch's heirs in 1946; his house was demolished in May 1960.{{sfn|Altern|1961|pp=5-19}}

==Legacy==
[[File:Une des salles du musée Munch (Oslo) (4857491003).jpg|thumb|300px|[[Munch Museum]], Oslo]]
[[File:Atelier de restauration du musée Munch (Oslo) (4858110206).jpg|thumb|300px|Munch Museum, Oslo]]
{{Quote box |width=200px |align=right |quoted=true |bgcolor=#FFFFF0 |salign=right |quote =
&lt;poem&gt;From my rotting body,
flowers shall grow
and I am in them
and that is eternity.&lt;/poem&gt; |source = Edvard Munch{{sfn|Thompson|Sorvig |2008|p=30}} }}

When Munch died, his remaining works were bequeathed to the city of Oslo, which built the [[Munch Museum]] at [[Tøyen]] (it opened in 1963). The museum holds a collection of approximately 1,100 paintings, 4,500 drawings, and 18,000 prints, the broadest collection of his works in the world.&lt;ref name=&quot;aboutmuseum&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=The Museum and the collection |publisher=Munch Museum |url=http://www.munch.museum.no/content.aspx?id=2 |accessdate=6 May 2012 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120519121248/http://www.munch.museum.no/content.aspx?id=2 |archive-date=19 May 2012 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; The Munch Museum serves as Munch's official estate,&lt;ref name=&quot;aboutmuseum&quot;/&gt; and has been active in responding to copyright infringements, as well as clearing copyright for the work, such as the appearance of Munch's ''The Scream'' in a 2006 [[M&amp;M's]] advertising campaign.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release |title= M&amp;M's® Responds to Consumer Demand and Introduces the Fun Way to Eat Dark Chocolate |url= http://www.prnewswire.com/news-releases/mmsr-responds-to-consumer-demand-and-introduces-the-fun-way-to-eat-dark-chocolate-56208762.html |publisher=PR Newswire |author=Masterfoods USA |date=21 August 2006 |accessdate=6 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The U.S. copyright representative for the Munch Museum and the Estate of Edvard Munch is the [[Artists Rights Society]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Our Most Frequently Requested Artists |url=http://arsny.com/requested.html |work=Artists Represented |publisher=Artists Rights Society |accessdate=6 May 2012 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150206001342/http://www.arsny.com/requested.html |archivedate=6 February 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Munch's art was highly personalized and he did little teaching. His &quot;private&quot; symbolism was far more personal than that of other Symbolist painters such as [[Gustave Moreau]] and [[James Ensor]]. Munch was still highly influential, particularly with the [[German Expressionism|German Expressionists]], who followed his philosophy, &quot;I do not believe in the art which is not the compulsive result of Man's urge to open his heart.&quot;&lt;ref name=Eg_p10/&gt; Many of his paintings, including ''The Scream'', have universal appeal in addition to their highly personal meaning.

Munch's works are now represented in numerous major museums and galleries in Norway and abroad. His cabin, &quot;the Happy House&quot;, was given to the municipality of Åsgårdstrand in 1944; it serves as a small Munch Museum. The inventory has been maintained exactly as he left it.

One version of ''The Scream'' was stolen from the National Gallery in 1994. In 2004, another version of ''The Scream'', along with one of ''Madonna'', was stolen from the Munch Museum in a daring daylight robbery. All were eventually recovered, but the paintings stolen in the 2004 robbery were extensively damaged. They have been meticulously restored and are on display again. Three Munch works were stolen from the Hotel [[Refsnes Gods]] in 2005; they were shortly recovered, although one of the works was damaged during the robbery.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Arts, Briefly; Munch Theft Confessions|work=The New York Times|date=10 March 2005 |url=https://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03EFD7163CF933A25750C0A9639C8B63 |accessdate=4 March 2010 | first=Walter | last=Gibbs}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In October 2006, the color [[woodcut]] ''Two people. The lonely'' (''To mennesker. De ensomme'') set a new record for his prints when it was sold at an auction in Oslo for 8.1&amp;nbsp;million [[Norwegian krone|kroner]] (US$1.27&amp;nbsp;million {{Inflation|index=US|start_year=2006|value=1270000|cursign=$|fmt=eq|r=-5}}). It also set a record for the highest price paid in auction in Norway.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Noen høyere? |newspaper=Aftenposten |date=27 December 2006 |url=http://www.aftenposten.no/kul_und/article1581669.ece |accessdate=25 December 2007 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071012214738/http://www.aftenposten.no/kul_und/article1581669.ece |archive-date=12 October 2007 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; On 3 November 2008, the painting ''Vampire'' set a new record for his paintings when it was sold for US$38,162,000 ({{Inflation|index=US|start_year=2008|value=38162000|cursign=$|fmt=eq|r=-5}}) at [[Sotheby's]] New York.

Munch's image appears on the Norwegian [[Banknotes of the Norwegian krone#1000 kroner note|1,000-kroner note]], along with pictures inspired by his artwork.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=1000-krone note|url=http://www.norges-bank.no/en/notes-and-coins/banknotes/1000-krone-note/|work=Notes and coins|publisher=Norges Bank|accessdate=6 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In February 2012, a major Munch exhibition, ''Edvard Munch. The Modern Eye'', opened at the [[Schirn Kunsthalle Frankfurt]]; the exhibition was opened by [[Mette-Marit, Crown Princess of Norway]].&lt;ref name=&quot;YT&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite press release |url=http://www.e-flux.com/announcements/edvard-munch-the-modern-eye/ |title=Edvard Munch. The Modern Eye |publisher=e-flux |year=2012 |accessdate=16 June 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In May 2012, ''The Scream'' sold for US$119.9&amp;nbsp;million ({{Inflation|index=US|start_year=2012|value=119900000|cursign=$|fmt=eq|r=-5}}), and is the [[List of most expensive paintings|second most expensive artwork ever sold]] at an open auction. (It was surpassed in November 2013 by ''[[Three Studies of Lucian Freud]]'', which sold for US$142.4&amp;nbsp;million).&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones2013&quot; /&gt;

In 2013, four of Munch's paintings were depicted in a series of stamps by the [[Posten Norge|Norwegian postal service]], to commemorate in 2014 the 150th anniversary of his birth.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|publisher=[[Norsk Telegrambyrå|NTB]] |url=http://www.dagbladet.no/2013/02/13/nyheter/innenriks/kunst/frimerker/25738056/ |title=Munchs &quot;Skrik&quot; blir frimerke |language=Norwegian |newspaper=Dagbladet |date=13 February 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 14 November 2016 a version of Munch's ''The Girls on the Bridge'' sold for US$54.5&amp;nbsp;million ({{Inflation|index=US|start_year=2016|value=54500000|cursign=$|fmt=eq|r=-5}}) at [[Sotheby's]], New York, making it the second highest price achieved for one of his paintings.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Munch Masterpiece Propels Evening Sale|url=http://www.sothebys.com/en/news-video/slideshows/2016/impressionist-results-november-2016.html|website=Sotheby's|accessdate=29 January 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In April 2019 the [[British Museum]] hosted the exhibition, ''Edvard Munch: Love and Angst'', comprising 83 artworks and including a rare original print of ''The Scream''.{{cn|date=January 2020}}

===University Aula===
[[File:Universitetets Aula (151651).jpg|thumb|upright=1.3|The Aula featuring ''History'' (left), ''The Sun'' (front), ''Alma Mater'' (right), smaller paintings on corners]]
In 1911 the final competition for the decoration of the large walls of the University of Oslo Aula (assembly hall) was held between Munch and [[Emanuel Vigeland]]. The episode is known as the &quot;Aula controversy&quot;. In 1914 Munch was finally commissioned to decorate the Aula and the work was completed in 1916. This major work in Norwegian monumental painting includes 11 paintings covering {{cvt|223|m2}}. ''The Sun'', ''History'' and ''Alma Mater'' are the key works in this sequence. Munch declared: “I wanted the decorations to form a complete and independent world of ideas, and I wanted their visual expression to be both distinctively Norwegian and universally human.” In 2014 it was suggested that the Aula paintings have a value of at least 500&amp;nbsp;million kroner.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uio.no/om/kultur/kunst/aulaen/index.html |title=Edvard Munch i Universitetets aula |publisher=[[University of Oslo]] |date=3 January 2013 |access-date=15 November 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Universitas, 29 October 2014.{{full citation needed|date=September 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Major works==
[[File:La salle Munch dans lhôtel de ville dOslo (4853547949).jpg|thumb|300px|''Life'' by Munch, at the [[Rådhuset]] (City Hall) in Oslo. The room is called ''The Munch room'']]
{{main|List of paintings by Edvard Munch}}
* 1885–86: ''[[The Sick Child (Munch)|The Sick Child]]''
* 1892: ''Evening on Karl Johan''
* 1893: ''[[The Scream]]''
* 1894: ''Ashes''
* 1894–95: ''[[Madonna (Edvard Munch)|Madonna]]''
* 1895: ''[[Puberty (Edvard Munch)|Puberty]]''
* 1895: ''Self-Portrait with Burning Cigarette''
* 1895: ''Death in the Sickroom''
* 1899–1900: ''The Dance of Life''
* 1899–1900: ''The Dead Mother''
* 1903: ''Village in Moonlight''
* 1940–42: ''Self Portrait: Between Clock and Bed''

==Selected works==
&lt;gallery widths=&quot;140px&quot; heights=&quot;140px&quot;&gt;
File:Edvard Munch - Ashes (1895).jpg|''Ashes'', 1894, oil on canvas, {{cvt|120.5|×|141|cm|in|frac=4}}. [[National Gallery of Norway|Nasjonalgalleriet]], Oslo
File:Edvard Munch - The dance of life (1899-1900).jpg|''[[The Dance of Life (painting)|The Dance of Life]]'', 1899–00, oil on canvas, {{cvt|49+1/2|×|75|in|cm|0|order=flip}}, [[National Gallery of Norway|Nasjonalgalleriet]], Oslo
File:Edvard Munch - At the Roulette Table in Monte Carlo - Google Art Project.jpg|''At the Roulette Table in Monte Carlo'', 1892, {{cvt|74.5|×|116|cm|in|frac=4}}, [[Munch Museum]], Oslo
File:Edvard Munch - Death in the Sickroom - Google Art Project.jpg|''Death in the Sickroom'', 1893, {{cvt|134|×|160|cm|in|frac=4}}, [[Munch Museum]], Oslo
File:'Starry Night' by Edvard Munch, 1893, Getty Center.JPG|''[[Starry Night (Munch)|Starry Night]]'', 1893, {{cvt|135.6|×|140|cm|in|frac=4}}, [[J. Paul Getty Museum]]
File:Edvard Munch - Anxiety - Google Art Project.jpg|''Anxiety'', 1894, {{cvt|94|×|74|cm|in|frac=4}}, [[Munch Museum]], Oslo
File:Edvard Munch - Vampire (1895) - Google Art Project.jpg|''[[Vampire (Edvard Munch)|Love and Pain (Vampire)]]'', 1895, {{cvt|91|×|109|cm|in|frac=4}}, [[Munch Museum]], Oslo
File:Munch deathSickroom.jpg|''Death in the Sickroom'', c. 1895, oil on canvas, {{cvt|59|×|66|in|cm|0|order=flip}}, [[National Gallery (Norway)|Nasjonalgalleriet]], Oslo
File:Edvard Munch - Separation - Google Art Project.jpg|''Separation'', 1896, {{cvt|96|×|127|cm|in|frac=4}}, [[Munch Museum]], Oslo
File:Edvard Munch - The Voice , Summer Night - Google Art Project.jpg|''The Voice / Summer Night'', 1896, {{cvt|90|×|119|cm|in|frac=4}}, [[Munch Museum]], Oslo
File:Edvard Munch - Red and White - Google Art Project.jpg|''Red and White'', 1899–1900, {{cvt|93|×|129|cm|in|frac=4}}, [[Munch Museum]], Oslo
File:Edvard Munch - Golgotha (1900).jpg|''Golgotha'', 1900, oil on canvas, [[Munch Museum]], Oslo
File:Edvard Munch - Kiss IV - Google Art Project.jpg|''Kiss IV'', 1902, woodcut print on wood, {{cvt|47|×|47|cm|in|frac=4}}, [[Munch Museum]], Oslo
File:Edvard Munch - Four Girls in Åsgårdstrand - Google Art Project.jpg|''Four Girls in Åsgårdstrand'', 1903, {{cvt|87|×|111|cm|in|frac=4}}, [[Munch Museum]], Oslo
File:Edvard Munch - The Brooch. Eva Mudocci - Google Art Project.jpg|''The Brooch, Eva Mudocci'', 1903, lithograph print on paper, {{cvt|76|×|53.2|cm|in|frac=4}}, [[Munch Museum]], Oslo
File:Friederich Nietzsche.jpg|''Portrait of [[Friedrich Nietzsche]]'', 1906, [[Thielska Galleriet]], Stockholm
File:Edvard Munch - Jealousy - Google Art Project.jpg|''Jealousy'', 1907, {{cvt|75|×|98|cm|in|frac=4}}, [[Munch Museum]], Oslo
File:Edvard Munch - The Sun - Google Art Project.jpg|''The Sun'', 1910–11, {{cvt|450|×|772|cm|in|frac=4}}, [[Munch Museum]], Oslo
File:Edvard Munch - Galloping Horse - Google Art Project.jpg|''Galloping Horse'', 1910–12, {{cvt|148|×|120|cm|in|frac=4}}, [[Munch Museum]], Oslo
File:Edvard Munch - The Yellow Log - Google Art Project.jpg|''The Yellow Log'', 1912, {{cvt|129.5|×|159.5|cm|in|frac=4}}, [[Munch Museum]], Oslo
File:Edvard Munch - Workers on their Way Home - Google Art Project.jpg|''Workers on their Way Home'', 1913–14, {{cvt|227|×|201|cm|in|frac=4}}, [[Munch Museum]], Oslo
&lt;/gallery&gt;

=== Nudes ===
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Edvard_Munch - The Hands (1893).jpg|''The Hands'', 1893, oil on canvas, 91 x 77&amp;nbsp;cm, [[Munch Museum]], Oslo
File:Edvard Munch - Madonna - Google Art Project.jpg|''[[Madonna (Edvard Munch)|Madonna]]'', 1894, oil on canvas, {{cvt|90|×|68|cm|in|frac=4}}, [[Munch Museum]], Oslo
File:Puberty (1894-95) by Edvard Munch.jpg|''[[Puberty (Munch painting)|Puberty]]'', 1894–95, oil on canvas, 151.5 x 110&amp;nbsp;cm, [[National Gallery (Norway)]]
File:Edvard Munch, Lady from the sea.jpg|''Lady From the Sea'' (detail), 1896, oil on canvas. {{cvt|39+1/2|×|126|in|cm|0|order=flip}}
File:Edvard Munch - Metabolism - Google Art Project.jpg|''Metabolism'', 1898–99, {{cvt|172|×|142|cm|in|frac=4}}, [[Munch Museum]], Oslo
File:MunchDerToddesMarat1907.JPG|''Death of Marat I'' 1907, 150 x 199&amp;nbsp;cm, [[Munch Museum]], Oslo
File:Edvard Munch, Gr%C3%A5tende kvinne.JPG|''Weeping Woman'', 1907–09, oil on canvas, private collection
File:%27Morning Yawn%27 by Edvard Munch, 1913, Bergen_Kunstmuseum.JPG|''[[Morning Yawn]]'', 1913, oil on canvas, 108 × 98&amp;nbsp;cm, Art Museums of Bergen
File:Edvard Munch - Weeping Nude - Google Art Project.jpg|''Weeping Nude'', 1913–14, {{cvt|110|×|135|cm|in|frac=4}}, [[Munch Museum]], Oslo
File:Model by the Wicker Chair.jpeg|''[[Model by the Wicker Chair]]'', 1919–21, oil on canvas, 122.5 × 100&amp;nbsp;cm, [[Munch Museum]], Oslo
&lt;/gallery&gt;

===Self-portraits===
&lt;gallery widths=&quot;140px&quot; heights=&quot;140px&quot;&gt;
File:Edvard Munch - Self-Portrait - Google Art Project (533070).jpg|''Self-Portrait'', 1882, {{cvt|26|×|19|cm|in|frac=4}}, [[Munch Museum]], Oslo
File:Edvard Munch - Self-Portrait in Hell - Google Art Project.jpg|''Self-Portrait in Hell'', 1903, {{cvt|82|×|66|cm|in|frac=4}}, [[Munch Museum]], Oslo
File:Edvard Munch - Self-Portrait with Brushes - Google Art Project.jpg|''Self-Portrait with Brushes'', 1904, {{cvt|197|×|91|cm|in|frac=4}}, [[Munch Museum]], Oslo
File:Edvard Munch - Self-Portrait with a Bottle of Wine - Google Art Project.jpg|''Self-Portrait with a Bottle of Wine'', 1906, {{cvt|110|×|120|cm|in|frac=4}}, [[Munch Museum]], Oslo
File:Edvard Munch - Self-Portrait with the Spanish Flu (1919).jpg|''Self-Portrait with the Spanish Flu'', 1919, oil on canvas, 150 x 131&amp;nbsp;cm, [[National Gallery (Norway)]]
File:Edvard Munch, Selvportrett. Mellom klokken og sengen.JPG|''Self-Portrait. Between the Clock and the Bed'', c. 1940-43, [[Munch Museum]], Oslo
&lt;/gallery&gt;

===Landscapes===
&lt;gallery widths=&quot;140px&quot; heights=&quot;140px&quot;&gt;
File:SmallLakewithBoatMunch.jpg|''Small Lake with Boat', 1880, oil on paper on board, 12 x 18&amp;nbsp;cm, [[Munch Museum]], Oslo
File:Edvard Munch - From Sandviken (c. 1882).jpg|''From Sandviken'', c. 1882,  oil on cardboard, 20 x 25&amp;nbsp;cm, Flaten Art Museum
File:Fra Saxegårdsgate - Edvard Munch.jpg|''From Saxegårdsgate'', c. 1882, oil on canvas, [[Lillehammer Art Museum]]'', Lillehammer
File:Sketch for 'Ashes' by Edvard Munch, Bergen Kunstmuseum.JPG|''Sketch for 'Ashes' '', 1894, oil on canvas, Bergen Kunstmuseum
File:Edvard Munch - Train Smoke - Google Art Project.jpg|''Train Smoke'', 1900, {{cvt|84|×|109|cm|in|frac=4}}, [[Munch Museum]], Oslo
File:Edvard Munch - Shore with Red House - Google Art Project.jpg|''Shore with Red House'', 1904, oil on canvas, 69 × 109 cm, [[Munch Museum]], Oslo
File:Edvard Munch, 1918, Coastal Landscape, oil on canvas, 120.9 x 160 cm, Kunstmuseum Basel.jpg|''Landscape at the Sea'', 1918, oil on canvas, 120.9 x 160, [[Kunstmuseum Basel]]
File:Edvard Munch, 1922, Starry Night, Munch Museum, Oslo.jpg|''Starry Night'', 1922-24, oil on canvas, 120.5 x 100 cm, [[Munch Museum]], Oslo
File:'Winter Night, Ekely' by Edvard Munch, 1930-31.JPG|''Winter Night, Ekely'', 1930-31, oil on canvas
&lt;/gallery&gt;

===Photographs===
&lt;gallery widths=&quot;140px&quot; heights=&quot;140px&quot;&gt;
File:Edvard Munch - Self-Portrait at 53 Am Strom in Warnemünde - Google Art Project.jpg|''Self-Portrait at 53 Am Strom in Warnemünde'', 1907, [[Munch Museum]], Oslo
File:Edvard Munch - Edvard Munch at the Beach in Warnemünde - Google Art Project.jpg|''Edvard Munch at the Beach in Warnemünde'', 1907, [[Munch Museum]], Oslo
File:Edvard Munch - Self-Portrait “à la Marat” - Google Art Project.jpg|''Self-Portrait “à la Marat”'', 1908–09, [[Munch Museum]], Oslo
File:Edvard Munch - Self-Portrait Somewhere on the Continent I - Google Art Project.jpg|''Self-Portrait Somewhere on the Continent I'', 1906, [[Munch Museum]], Oslo
File:Portrett av Edvard Munch, 26 år gammel.jpg|Portrait at 26 years
File:Portrait photographique dEdvard Munch (4865295519).jpg|Portrait of Edvard Munch 1902
File:Portrett av Edvard Munch.jpg|Portrait of Edvard Munch
File:Edvard Munch 1912.jpg|Munch in 1912
File:Edvard Munch - Rosa Meissner at the Hotel Rohn in Warnemünde - Google Art Project.jpg|''Rosa Meissner at the Hotel Rohn in Warnemünde'', 1907, photograph, [[Munch Museum]], Oslo
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==See also==

* ''[[Edvard Munch (film)|Edvard Munch]]'', a 1974 biographical film

==Notes==
{{Reflist|2|refs=

&lt;ref name=&quot;TaurisBlog&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://theibtaurisblog.com/2012/08/06/the-graphic-works-and-prints-of-edvard-munch/ |title=The Graphic Works and Prints of Edvard Munch |website=I. B. Tauris Blog |date=6 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;KODE&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://kodebergen.no/en/exhibitions/nikolai-astrup |title=Nikolai Astrup |website=KODE |publisher=Art Museums of Bergen |date=11 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Vogel2012&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url=https://www.nytimes.com/2012/09/18/arts/design/munchs-scream-to-hang-for-six-months-at-moma.html?hpw | work=The New York Times | first=Carol | last=Vogel | title=Munch's 'Scream' to Hang for Six Months at MoMA | date=17 September 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Thorpe2019&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/artanddesign/2019/apr/07/edvard-munch-portrait-fiance-british-museum|title=Edvard Munch 'reunited' with fiancée for British Museum show|last=Thorpe|first=Vanessa|date=2019-04-07|work=The Observer|access-date=2019-04-08|language=en-GB|issn=0029-7712}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones2013&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Why Francis Bacon deserves to beat The Scream's record-breaking pricetag|url=https://www.theguardian.com/artanddesign/2013/nov/12/francis-bacon-triptych-lucian-freud-auction |accessdate=18 May 2014 |newspaper=the Guardian|date=12 November 2013|first=Jonathan|last=Jones}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;YT&quot;&gt;{{YouTube|id=37eQXuinlwA|title=Crown Princess Mette-Marit opens Munch exhibition}}. February 11, 2012. Retrieved 16 June 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;


}}

==References==
{{refbegin|2|indent=yes}}
*{{cite book|last=Altern |first=Arne |date=1961 |entry=Tanker omkring et nedrevet hus |title=St. Hallvard 1961 |ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|editor-first=Patricia G.|editor-last=Berman |date=1986 |title=Edvard Munch: Mirror Reflections |location=West Palm Beach, FL |publisher=Norton Gallery &amp; School of Art |oclc=757178143|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|first=Nikolaus |last=Bernau |entry=Wo hing Munchs ''Lebens-Fries''? Zu dem Bau der Kammerspiele und ihrem berühmtesten Schmuck |editor1-first=Roland |editor1-last=Koberg |editor2-first=Bernd |editor2-last=Stegemann |editor3-first=Henrike |editor3-last=Thomsen |title=Blätter des Deutschen Theaters |publisher=Max Reinhard, Das Deutsche Theater |location=Berlin |date=2005 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Chipp|first=Herschel B. |title=Theories of Modern Art: A Source Book by Artists and Critics |url=https://archive.org/details/theoriesofmodern00chip|url-access=registration|year=1968 |publisher=[[University of California Press]]|location=Berkeley, CA |isbn=0-520-05256-0 |page=[https://archive.org/details/theoriesofmodern00chip/page/114 114]|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Eggum |first=Arne |title=Edvard Munch: Paintings, Sketches, and Studies |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=bxjqAAAAMAAJ |editor-last=Munch |editor-first=Edvard |publisher=[[C.N. Potter]] |location=New York, NY |year=1984 |pages=305 |isbn=0-517-55617-0 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Faerna |first=José María |title=Munch |publisher=Harry N. Abrams |location=New York, NY |year=1995 |isbn=0-8109-4694-7 |page=[https://archive.org/details/munch00munc/page/16 16] |ref=harv |url-access=registration |url=https://archive.org/details/munch00munc/page/16 }}
* {{cite book|editor-last=Holland|editor-first=J. Gill|title=The Private Journals of Edvard Munch: We Are Flames Which Pour Out of the Earth|year=2005|publisher=University of Wisconsin Press|location=Madison, WI|isbn=0-299-19814-6}}
*{{cite book|title=Whistler's Mother: An American Icon|year=2003|publisher=Lund Humphries|location=Burlington, VT|isbn=0-85331-856-5|editor-last=MacDonald|editor-first=Margaret F.|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Morehead|first=Allison|chapter=Hands, Dissection, and Embodied Seeing: Strindberg and Munch|date=2019|title=August Strindberg and Visual Culture: The Emergence of Optical Modernity in Image, Text and Theatre|publisher=Bloomsbury|isbn=9781501338007|editor1-first=Jonathan |editor1-last=Schroeder|editor2-first= Anna |editor2-last=Westerstahl Stenport |editor3-first= Eszter|editor3-last= Szalczer |ref=harv|doi=10.5040/9781501338038.ch-002}}
* {{cite book |last=O'Neill |first=Amanda |title=The Life and Works of Munch |publisher=Parragon Book Service |location=Bristol |year=1996 |isbn=0-75251-690-6 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Prideaux|first=Sue|title=Edvard Munch: Behind the Scream|year=2005|publisher=Yale University Press|location=New Haven, CT|isbn=978-0-300-12401-9|authorlink=Sue Prideaux |url=https://archive.org/details/edvardmunchbehin00prid|url-access=registration|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|last=Thiis|first=Jens |authorlink=Jens Thiis|title=Edvard Munch og hans samtid. Slekten, livet og kunsten, geniet|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=u3BHAQAAIAAJ|year=1933|publisher=Gyldendal|location=Oslo|oclc=637507959}}
*{{cite book |last=Thompson |first=J. William|title=Sustainable Landscape Construction: A Guide to Green Building Outdoors |year=2008 |publisher=Island Press |edition=2nd |location=Washington, DC |isbn=978-1-59726-142-5|last2=Sorvig |first2=Kim|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Wells|first=John|authorlink=John C. Wells|title=Longman Pronunciation Dictionary|publisher=Pearson Longman|edition=3rd|date= 2008|isbn=978-1-4058-8118-0|ref=harv}}
{{refend}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin|2|indent=yes}}
* {{cite book|editor1-last=Black|editor1-first=Peter|editor2-last=Bruteig|editor2-first=Magne |title=Edvard Munch: Prints|year=2009|publisher=Philip Wilson|location=London|isbn=978-0-85667-677-2}} Catalogue of exhibition at the Hunterian Museum and Art Gallery, University of Glasgow and the National Gallery of Ireland, Dublin
* {{cite journal|last=Clarke |first=Jay |date=2014 |title=Munch on Paper |journal=Print Quarterly |volume=31 |pages=237–243}}
* {{cite book|last=Dolnick|first=Edward|title=The Rescue Artist: A True Story of Art, Thieves, and the Hunt for a Missing Masterpiece|year=2005|publisher=HarperCollins Publishers|location=New York, NY|isbn=0-06-053118-5|authorlink=Edward Dolnick}} Recounts the 1994 theft of ''The Scream'' from Norway's National Gallery in Oslo, and its eventual recovery
* {{cite book|title=Munch: His Life and Work|year=1984|publisher=Murray|location=London|editor-last=Heller|editor1-first=Reinhold|isbn=0-7195-4116-6}}
* {{cite journal|last=Morehead |first=Allison |date=2014 |title=Lithographic and Biological Error in Edvard Munch's ''Women in the Hospital'' |journal=Print Quarterly |volume=31 |pages=308–315}}
* {{cite book|last=Schiefler|first=Gustav|title=Verzeichnis des Graphischen Werks Edvard Munchs bis 1906|url=https://archive.org/details/gri_33125010866610|year=1907|publisher=B. Cassirer|location=Berlin|oclc=39789318|language=German}}
* {{cite book|last=Schiefler|first=Gustav|title=Das Graphische Werk von Edvard Munch: 1906–1926|year=1927|publisher=Euphorion Verlag|location=Berlin|oclc=638113186|language=German}}
* {{cite book|last=Woll|first=Gerd|title=Edvard Munch: Complete Paintings: Catalogue Raisonné|year=2009|publisher=Thames &amp; Hudson|location=London|isbn=978-0-500-09345-0|volume=4}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons}}
{{Wikiquote}}
* {{MoMA artist|4164}}
* [http://www.thehindu.com/opinion/op-ed/oslo-goes-high-on-old-munch/article4775730.ece Oslo goes high on ‘Old Munch]
* [http://abcgallery.com/M/munch/munch.html Munch at Olga's Gallery]—large online collection of Munch's works (over 200 paintings)
* [http://www.artcyclopedia.com/artists/munch_edvard.html Munch at artcyclopedia]
* [http://www.wikigallery.org/wiki/artist36535/Edvard-Munch/page-1 Edvard Munch at WikiGallery.org]
* [http://www.moreeuw.com/histoire-art/exposition-munch-pompidou.htm Exhibition &quot;Edvard Munch L'oeil moderne&quot;—Centre Pompidou, Paris 2011]
* [http://samling.nasjonalmuseet.no/en/folder/34 Edvard Munch at Norway's National Museum of Art, Architecture and Design]

{{Edvard Munch}}
{{Post-Impressionism}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Munch, Edvard}}

[[Category:1863 births]]
[[Category:1944 deaths]]
[[Category:19th-century Norwegian painters]]
[[Category:20th-century Norwegian painters]]
[[Category:Art Nouveau painters]]
[[Category:Burials at Vår Frelsers gravlund]]
[[Category:Edvard Munch]]
[[Category:Expressionist painters]]
[[Category:Nude art]]
[[Category:People from Løten]]
[[Category:Symbolist painters]]</text>
      <sha1>gr2o05yhig1dajjeow781xbtlp6l60n</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
