  <page>
    <title>American cuisine</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2175</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942526019</id>
      <parentid>942525550</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-25T05:45:49Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>2605:E000:93C1:5B00:34CB:1563:347D:388E</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Ethnicity-specific and immigrant influence */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Culinary traditions of the United States}}
{{other uses}}
{{Use American English|date=January 2017}}
{{Multiple issues|
{{More citations needed|date=January 2017}}
{{Synthesis|date=July 2016}}
}}
{{Use American English|date=May 2015}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=January 2017}}
[[File:Motherhood and apple pie.jpg|thumb|[[Apple pie]], along with [[baseball]], is one of a number of American [[cultural icon]]s.]]
[[File:Sirloin steak.JPG|thumb|A [[sirloin steak]] dinner served with [[sautéing|sauteed]] [[onion]], [[French fries|potato fries]], [[broccoli|broccoli florets]], [[carrot|cut carrots]], and whole [[snow pea]]s, then [[garnish (food)|garnished]] with [[chive]]s]]
{{American cuisine}}

'''American cuisine''' reflects the [[history of the United States]], blending the culinary contributions of various groups of people from around the world, including [[Native Americans in the United States|indigenous American Indians]], [[African American]]s, [[Asian people|Asians]], [[Ethnic groups in Europe|Europeans]], [[Pacific Islander]]s, and [[Latin Americans]]. Though much of American cuisine is [[fusion cuisine]] reflecting [[global cuisine]], many [[regional cuisines]] have deeply rooted [[Ethnic cuisine|ethnic]] heritages, including [[Cajun cuisine|Cajun]], [[Louisiana Creole cuisine|Louisiana Creole]], [[Native American cuisine|Native American]], [[New Mexican cuisine|New Mexican]], [[Cuisine of the Pennsylvania Dutch|Pennsylvania Dutch]], [[Soul food]], and [[Tlingit cuisine|Tlingit]]. Early Native Americans utilized a number of cooking methods in early American cuisine that have been blended with early European cooking methods to form the basis of what is now American cuisine. The [[European colonization of the Americas|European settlement of the Americas]] introduced a number of ingredients, spices, herbs, and cooking styles to the continent. The various styles of cuisine continued expanding well into the 19th and 20th centuries, proportional to the influx of [[immigrants]] from many different nations; this influx nurtured a rich diversity in food preparation throughout the country.

When the [[American colonist|colonists]] came to [[Thirteen Colonies|the colonies]], they farmed animals for clothing and meat in a similar fashion to what they had done in Europe. They had cuisine similar to their previous [[Dutch cuisine|Dutch]], [[Swedish cuisine|Swedish]], [[French cuisine|French]] and [[British cuisine]]s. The American colonial diet varied depending on the region settled. Commonly hunted [[Game (hunting)|game]] included deer, bear, [[American bison|bison]], and [[wild turkey]]. A number of [[Animal fat|fats]] and [[Cooking oil|oils]] made from animals served to cook much of the colonial foods. Prior to [[American Revolution|the Revolution]], New Englanders consumed large quantities of [[rum]] and [[beer]], as maritime trade provided them relatively easy access to the goods needed to produce these items: rum was the [[Liquor|distilled spirit]] of choice, as the main ingredient, [[molasses]], was readily available from trade with the [[West Indies]]. In comparison to the northern colonies, the southern colonies were quite diverse in their agricultural diet; the growing season was longer.

During the 18th and 19th centuries, Americans developed many new foods. During the [[Progressive Era]] of the late 19th and early 20th centuries, circa 1890s–1920s, food production and presentation became more [[Industrialized food|industrialized]].

One characteristic of American cooking is the [[Fusion cuisine|fusion of multiple ethnic or regional approaches]] into completely new cooking styles. A wave of [[celebrity chef]]s began with [[Julia Child]] and [[Graham Kerr]] in the 1970s, with many more following after the rise of [[cable channel]]s such as the [[Food Network]] and [[Cooking Channel]] in the late 20th century.

==History==

===Pre-colonial cuisine===
{{see also|Native American cuisine}}

====Seafood====
[[File:Blue crab on market in Piraeus - Callinectes sapidus Rathbun 20020819-317.jpg|thumb|right|[[Callinectes sapidus|Blue crab]] was used on the eastern and southern coast of what is now the U.S. mainland.]]
Seafood in the United States originated with the American Indians in the United States, who often ate [[Cod (food)|cod]], [[lemon sole]], [[flounder]], [[Herring (food)|herring]], [[halibut]], [[sturgeon]], [[Smelt (fish)|smelt]], [[drum (fish)|drum]] on the East Coast, and [[Oily fish|olachen]] and [[salmon]] on the West Coast. Whale was hunted by American Indians off the Northwest coast, especially by the [[Makah people|Makah]], and used for their meat and oil.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=y84rc5HGKpEC&amp;pg=PA226&amp;dq=seafood+native+americans+herring+halibut&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwj23rfB8fnZAhVLVrwKHdR6BgsQ6AEIIzAA#v=onepage&amp;q=seafood+native+americans+herring+halibut&amp;f=false|title=Native Americans: Southwest - California - Northwest Coast - Great Basin - Plateau|first=Barry|last=Pritzker|date=August 8, 1998|publisher=ABC-CLIO|via=Google Books}}&lt;/ref&gt; Seal and walrus were also eaten, in addition to eel from New York's [[Finger Lakes]] region. [[Catfish]] was also popular among native people, including the [[Modoc people|Modocs]]. Crustaceans included [[Shrimp (food)|shrimp]], [[lobster]], [[Crayfish (food)|crayfish]], and [[dungeness crab]]s in the Northwest and [[shrimp]], [[lobster]] and [[Callinectes sapidus|blue crabs]] in the East. Other shellfish include [[abalone]] and [[geoduck]] on the West Coast, while on the East Coast the [[Atlantic surf clam|surf clam]], [[quahog]], and the [[soft-shell clam]]. [[Oyster]]s were eaten on both shores, as were [[mussel]]s and [[Common periwinkle|periwinkles]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcolnb|Root|De Rochemont|1981|pp=21,22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Cooking methods====
Early American Indians used a number of cooking methods in early American Cuisine that have been blended with early European cooking methods to form the basis of American Cuisine. [[Grilling]] meats was common. [[Spit roast]]ing over a pit fire was common as well. Vegetables, especially [[root vegetable]]s were often cooked directly in the ashes of the fire. As early Native Americans lacked pottery that could be used directly over a fire, they developed a technique which has caused many [[anthropologist]]s to call them &quot;[[Stone Boilers]]&quot;. They would heat rocks directly in a fire and then add the rocks to a pot filled with water until it came to a boil so that it would cook the meat or vegetables in the boiling water. In what is now the Southwestern United States, they also created [[adobe]] ovens, dubbed ''[[horno]]s'' by the [[Conquistadors|Spanish]], to bake products such as [[cornmeal]] bread. Other parts of America dug pit ovens; these pits were also used to steam foods by adding heated rocks or embers and then seaweed or corn husks placed on top to steam fish and shellfish as well as vegetables; potatoes would be added while still in skin and corn while in-husk, this would later be referred to as a [[New England clam bake|clambake]] by the colonists.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcolnb|Root|De Rochemont|1981|pp=31,32}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Colonial period===
{{Main|Cuisine of the Thirteen Colonies}}
[[File:Our_(Almost_Traditional)_Thanksgiving_Dinner.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Tender, juicy roast turkey - the main attraction - with old-fashioned gravy, cranberry sauce, smashed potatoes, baked green beans, sweet and sour cod, steamed rice, achara (pickled green papaya relish), leche flan, pig in a blanket, apple crisp.]]
[[File:Map of territorial growth 1775.jpg|thumb|left|Map of the 13 American Colonies in 1775.]]

When the colonists came to [[History of Virginia|Virginia]], [[History of Pennsylvania|Pennsylvania]], [[History of Massachusetts|Massachusetts]], or any of the other English colonies on the eastern seaboard of North America, their initial attempts at survival included planting crops familiar to them from back home in England. In the same way, they farmed animals for clothing and meat in a similar fashion. Through hardships and eventual establishment of trade with Britain, the [[West Indies]] and other regions, the colonists were able to establish themselves in the American colonies with a cuisine similar to their previous [[British cuisine]]. There were some exceptions to the diet, such as local vegetation and animals, but the colonists attempted to use these items in the same fashion as they had their equivalents or ignore them entirely if they could. The manner of cooking for the American colonists followed along the line of British cookery up until the Revolution. The British sentiment followed in the cookbooks brought to the New World as well.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcolnb|Smith|2004|p=512}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1796, the first American cookbook was published, and others followed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Stavely|first1=Keith|last2=Fitzgerald|first2=Kathleen|title=Northern Hospitality: Cooking by the Book in New England|year=2011|publisher=[[University of Massachusetts Press]]|pages=7–33|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=pRbJUQMM0ssC|accessdate=August 12, 2016|chapter=Culinarily Colonized: Cookbooks in Colonial New England|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=pRbJUQMM0ssC&amp;lpg=PA7&amp;pg=PA7#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|jstor=j.ctt5vk2dv|isbn=1558498613}}&lt;/ref&gt; There was a general disdain for [[French cuisine|French cookery]], even with the French [[Huguenot]]s in [[South Carolina]] and French-Canadians. One of the cookbooks that proliferated in the colonies was ''[[The Art of Cookery Made Plain and Easy]]'' (1747) by [[Hannah Glasse]], who referred to &quot;the blind folly of this age that would rather be imposed on by a French booby, than give encouragement to a good English cook!&quot; Of the French recipes given in the text, she speaks out flagrantly against the dishes as she &quot;… think[s] it an odd jumble of trash.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcolnb|Glasse|1750}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Reinforcing the anti-French sentiment was the [[French and Indian War]] from 1754 to 1764. This created a large anxiety against the French, which influenced the English to force many of the French to move, as in the [[expulsion of the Acadians]] from Nova Scotia to Louisiana. The Acadians left a French influence in the diet of those settled in Louisiana, and among the Acadian Francophones who settled eastern Maine and parts of what is now northern Vermont at the same time they colonized New Brunswick.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcolnb|Smith|2004|p=512, Vol. 1}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Some of the Jews who fled from the Inquisition with other [[Sephardic Jews]] in the 15th century had previously settled in [[Recife, Brazil]] and the [[West Indies]], where their cuisine was influenced by new local ingredients like [[molasses]], [[rum]], [[sugar]], [[vanilla]], [[chocolate]], [[Capsicum|peppers]], [[Maize|corn]], [[tomato]]es, [[kidney beans]], [[string beans]] and [[turkey (food)|turkey]]. In 1654, twenty three Sephardic Jews arrived in New Amsterdam and they brought this cuisine with them to the early colonial United States. Early American Jewish cuisine was heavily influenced by this branch of Sephardic cuisine. Many of the recipes were bound up in observance of traditional holidays and remained true to their origins. These included dishes such as stew and fish fried in [[olive oil]], beef and bean stews, [[almond pudding]]s, and [[egg custard]]s. The first [[kosher food|kosher]] cookbook in America was the ''Jewish Cookery Book'' by [[Esther Levy]] which was published in 1871 in [[Philadelphia]] and includes many of the traditional recipes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Smith|first=Andrew|title=The Oxford Encyclopedia of Food and Drink in America|url=https://www.google.com/books/edition/The_Oxford_Encyclopedia_of_Food_and_Drin/DOJMAgAAQBAJ?hl=en&amp;gbpv=0|publisher=Oxford University Press|page=375}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Common ingredients====
[[File:New England clam bake.jpg|thumb|A New England clam bake consists of various steamed [[shellfish]].]]
The American colonial diet varied depending on the settled region in which someone lived. Local cuisine patterns had established by the mid-18th century. The [[New England]] colonies were extremely similar in their dietary habits to those that many of them had brought from England. A striking difference for the colonists in New England compared to other regions was seasonality.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcolnb|Oliver|2005|pp=16–19}}.&lt;/ref&gt; While in the southern colonies, they could farm almost year-round, in the northern colonies, the growing seasons were very restricted. In addition, colonists' close proximity to the ocean gave them a bounty of fresh fish to add to their diet, especially in the northern colonies.

[[Wheat]], however, the grain used to bake bread back in England was almost impossible to grow, and imports of wheat were far from cost productive.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcolnb|Pillsbury|1998|p=25}}.&lt;/ref&gt;{{dubious|Clarify timeperiod and location(New England?)|date=July 2015}} Substitutes in cases such as this included cornmeal. The [[Johnnycake]] was a poor substitute to some for wheaten bread, but acceptance by both the northern and southern colonies seems evident.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcolnb|Oliver|2005|p=22}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

As many of the New Englanders were originally from England, game hunting was useful when they immigrated to the [[New World]]. Many of the northern colonists depended upon their ability to hunt, or upon others from whom they could purchase game. Hunting was the preferred method of protein consumption. This was opposed to animal husbandry, which required much more work to defend the kept animals against raids.

=====Livestock and game=====
Commonly hunted game included deer, bear, [[American bison|buffalo]], and wild turkey. The larger muscles of the animals were roasted and served with currant sauce, while the other smaller portions went into [[soup]]s, [[stew]]s, [[sausage]]s, [[pie]]s, and pastries.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcolnb|Smith|2004|pp=546–547, Vol. 1}}.&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to game, colonists' protein intake was supplemented by [[mutton]]. The [[Spanish people|Spanish]] in [[Florida]] originally introduced [[sheep]] to the New World, but this development never quite reached the North, and there they were introduced by the [[Dutch people|Dutch]] and English. The keeping of sheep was a result of the English non-practice of [[animal husbandry]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcolnb|Smith|2004|p=26, Vol. 2}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The animals provided wool when young and mutton upon maturity after wool production was no longer desirable.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcolnb|Root|De Rochemont|1981|pp=176–182}}&lt;/ref&gt; The forage-based diet for sheep that prevailed in the Colonies produced a characteristically strong, gamy flavor and a tougher consistency, which required aging and slow cooking to tenderize.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=R.W. |last=Apple Jr. |title=Much Ado About Mutton, but Not in These Parts |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2006/03/29/dining/29mutt.html |work= [[The New York Times]] |date=March 29, 2006 |accessdate=January 23, 2008 |quote=Until it fell from favor after World War II, it was a favorite of most Britons, who prized [[mutton]] above lamb (from younger animals) for its texture and flavor. It has a bolder taste, a deeper color and a chewier consistency.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=====Fats and oils=====
[[Image:Plate of scrapple.jpg|thumb|200px|A plate of [[scrapple]], a traditional dish of the [[Delaware Valley]] region still eaten today]]
A number of [[fat]]s and [[oil]]s made from animals served to cook much of the colonial foods. Many homes had a sack made of deerskin filled with bear oil for cooking, while solidified bear fat resembled [[shortening]]. Rendered [[pork]] fat made the most popular cooking medium, especially from the cooking of [[bacon]]. Pork fat was used more often in the southern colonies than the northern colonies as the Spanish introduced pigs earlier to the South. The colonists enjoyed [[butter]] in cooking as well, but it was rare prior to the [[American Revolution]], as [[cattle]] were not yet plentiful.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcolnb|Smith|2004|pp=458–459, Vol. 2}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

=====Alcoholic drinks=====
Prior to the [[American Revolution|Revolution]], New Englanders consumed large quantities of [[rum]] and [[beer]], as maritime trade provided them relatively easy access to the goods needed to produce these items. Rum was the distilled spirit of choice, as the main ingredient, [[molasses]], was readily available from trade with the West Indies. Further into the interior, however, one would often find colonists consuming [[whiskey]], as they did not have similar access to [[sugar cane]]. They did have ready access to corn and rye, which they used to produce their whiskey.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcolnb|Pillsbury|1998|p=17}}.&lt;/ref&gt; However, until the Revolution, many considered whiskey to be a coarse alcohol unfit for human consumption, as many believed that it caused the poor to become raucous and unkempt drunkards.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcolnb|Crowgey|1971|pp=18–19}}.&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to these alcohol-based products produced in America, imports were seen on merchant shelves, including [[wine]] and [[brandy]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcolnb|Pillsbury|1998|p=18}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

=====Southern variations=====
In comparison to the northern colonies, the [[Southern Colonies]] were quite diverse in their agricultural diet. The uplands of the [[Piedmont (United States)|Piedmont]] and the [[Atlantic coastal plain|coastal lowlands]] made up the two main parts of the southern colonies. The diet of the uplands often included wild game, [[cabbage]], [[Green bean|string beans]], [[Maize|corn]], [[Cucurbita|squashes]] and white [[potato]]es. People had biscuits as part of their [[breakfast]], along with healthy portions of pork.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcolnb|Pillsbury|1998|pp=47–48}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The lowlands of Louisiana included a varied diet heavily influenced by the French, Spanish, Acadians, Germans, Native Americans, Africans and Caribbeans. Rice played a large part of the diet in Louisiana. In addition, unlike the uplands, the lowlands subsistence of protein came mostly from coastal seafood. Much of the diet involved the use of peppers, as it still does to this day.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcolnb|Pillsbury|1998|pp=48–49}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcolnb|Smith|2004|p=149, Vol. 2}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Post-colonial cuisine===
During the 18th and 19th centuries, Americans developed many new foods. Some, such as [[Rocky Mountain oyster]]s, stayed regional; some spread throughout the nation but with little international appeal, such as [[peanut butter]] (a core ingredient of the [[peanut butter and jelly sandwich]]); and some spread throughout the world, such as [[popcorn]], [[cola]], [[fried chicken]], [[cornbread]], unleavened [[muffin]]s such as the [[poppyseed muffin]], and [[Chocolate brownie|brownies]].

===20th-century American farmhouse===
During the 1920s, [[Agriculture in the United States|American farms]] were mostly self-sufficient; but, certain staples like [[salt]], [[coffee]], [[sugar]] and [[baking soda]] would be purchased at the town general store. If the family didn't grow [[wheat]], then [[flour]] would also be purchased. Another luxury was canned [[salmon]], which was sometimes eaten for Sunday dinner. Items purchased at the general store would be paid for with eggs, [[butter]] or some other food from the farm. Women were responsible for much of the processing of food like straining fresh milk, churning butter, making [[molasses]] from [[sorghum]], grinding [[Maize|corn]] into cornmeal or cleaning whole [[chicken]]s.

Fresh picked [[apple]]s were pressed into [[cider]], which could be [[ferment]]ed to make [[apple cider vinegar]]. [[Fruit]]s and [[vegetable]]s were [[food preservation|preserved]] by various means like canning, drying or [[pickling]]. One contemporary writer from [[Michigan]] described October as cider season, when [[apple butter]] would be made. Her writings mention [[johnnycake]]s; and, as winter fare, [[buckwheat]] cakes.&lt;ref name=&quot;coe&quot;&gt;{{Cite book| publisher = HarperCollins| isbn = 978-0-06-221643-4| last1 = Ziegelman| first1 = Jane| last2 = Coe| first2 = Andrew| title = A Square Meal: A Culinary History of the Great Depression| date = 2016-08-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Typical farmhouse fare included fried chicken, simmered [[green beans]], boiled corn, [[chicken and dumplings]], fried [[ham]], boiled [[beans]] and [[beets]], [[stewed tomatoes]], potatoes, and [[coleslaw]] made of shredded [[cabbage]]. ''Pon haus'', similar to the [[scrapple]] of the [[Pennsylvania Dutch]], was a typical breakfast dish among the Germans who had settled [[Indiana]] in the 19th century. Pork scraps and [[corn meal]] were cooked into a thick [[porridge]] and molded in loaf pans. Once solidified, the mixture would be cut and fried. During the fall months pork might be replaced with fried apples or potatoes. It was served with buttered [[biscuits]], jam, jelly, milk gravy or sorghum syrup. Fruit butter might be made from apples. plums or peaches to accompany the meal.&lt;ref name=&quot;coe&quot; /&gt;

{{Quote box
 |quote  = &quot;A whole new class of city dwellers, harried, worried, furtive, hungry-looking people, have come into being in the wake of the [[kitchenette]], and no modern influence has had so great a part in affecting the morals, health and spiritual well-being of a generation as has this ill-shapen, ill-planned adjunct of modern living&quot;
 |author = Jane Pride
 |source = ''[[New York Herald]]''
 |width  = 30%
 |align  = right
}}

[[Pork]] was a staple of the rural diet through the Southern and Midwestern United States. [[Lard]] was used for baking, frying and even as a seasoning. The cookware of the period was made of [[cast iron]] and these were thoroughly seasoned with pork fat. Fried salt pork with gravy was an indulgent fat-laden dish often served with a side of boiled potatoes. In the [[Appalachian region]] a dish called &quot;killed lettuce&quot; was made with [[pokeweed]], [[dandelion]] and assorted wild greens that were drizzled with hot bacon grease until wilted or &quot;killed&quot;.&lt;ref name=coe /&gt;

[[Pie]] could be served up to three times a day and many varieties were prepared depending on the season. During the spring months, pies would be made of [[rhubarb]] and [[strawberry]]; in summer [[peach]], [[cherry]], [[blackberry]], [[blueberry]], [[elderberry]] and [[grape]]; and in fall [[apple]].&lt;ref name=coe /&gt;

The staples of the urban diet were bread, [[dairy]] and canned goods. Dinner might be tomato bisque from a can topped with [[cream]] or a salad made of canned string beans and [[mayonnaise]]. Many preferred to purchase food at [[delicatessen]]'s, rather than attempt to prepare meals in the cramped kitchenettes. German delicatessens in cities like New York and [[Milwaukee]] sold imported cold cuts, [[potato salad]]s, ''[[schmierkase]]'', ''[[wienerwurst]]'', North Sea [[herring]], assorted pickles and other prepared foods.  [[History of the Jews in the United States|Jewish immigrants]] from Germany soon followed suit, replacing pork dishes with [[corned beef]] and [[pastrami]]. [[Ice cream soda]] was served at soda fountains, along with various other early &quot;soda water&quot; recipes like the Garden Sass Sundae (rhubarb) or the Oh-Oh-Cindy Sundae (strawberry ice cream topped with chocolate syrup, chopped nuts, whipped cream and candied cherries).&lt;ref name=coe /&gt;

===Modern cuisine===
In the 20th century highly [[Industrialized food|industrialized]] [[processed food]]s became a dominant feature of American diets.  Fusion of the food traditions of various [[Immigration to the United States|immigrant groups]] to the US contributed to development of distinct ethnic-American dishes. &quot;Dainty&quot; fare became the norm at fashionable luncheons and teas in areas like [[New York City]] including dishes like grapefruit with cherries, fruit served in cantaloupe, strawberry tarts or egg [[soufflé]], other types of tea sandwiches, small decorated cakes or gelatin based desserts. This style of dainty fare was highly decorated and ladylike and it was intended to be consumed only by women. The decorative and ornate foods were a symbol of distinction between men and women, as the former were associated with less refined foods.&lt;ref&gt;Sherrie A. Inness, Dinner Roles: American Women and Culinary Culture, p. 69&lt;/ref&gt; Tea parties were fashionable for well-to-do women and dainty fare remained a symbol of upper middle class luxury. Dozens of articles published in women's magazines promoted the &quot;dainty&quot; quality of tea parties. From one 1911 issue of ''Good Housekeeping'': &quot;the secret of a successful tea room is daintiness, first in the service, and then in the quality of the food served&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Sherrie A. Inness, Dinner Roles: American Women and Culinary Culture, p. 59&lt;/ref&gt;

====Processed food====
During the [[Progressive Era]] (1890s–1920s) food production and presentation became more industrialized.

From 1888 thru 1908 the machine double-crimped, compound-sealed, open-top, so-called &quot;sanitary can&quot; was perfected (replacing individually crafted and manually soldered hole-in-top style cans).  Also during that time, the can manufacturing industry consolidated.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=IMACS Classification: TIN CANS |url=https://anthro.utah.edu/_documents/imac-s/471-tin-cans.pdf |website=IMACS USER'S GUIDE |publisher=University of Utah, Department of Anthropology |accessdate=23 February 2019 |date=August 2001 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190412101335/https://anthro.utah.edu/_documents/imac-s/471-tin-cans.pdf |archive-date=April 12, 2019 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;  These improvements in [[canning]] made fruits and vegetables increasingly available to chefs outside of the regular harvest season.

During that same time frame, grain-feeding of cattle during low pasture months made milk increasingly available year-round.  The invention of [[Automatic milking|milking machines]] lowered production costs.  [[Pasteurization]], [[Homogenization (chemistry)|homogenization]], [[Evaporated milk|evaporation]], [[Condensed milk|condensation]], and [[refrigeration]] along with glass milk bottles, wax paper cartons, and then plastic bottles made milk increasingly available and safe for urban consumers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Kurlansky |first1=Mark |title=Milk! : a 10,000-year food fracas |date=May 8, 2018 |publisher=Bloomsbury Publishing |isbn=1632863820 |edition=First}}&lt;/ref&gt; Milk became a staple food item and an increasingly important ingredient in American cuisine.  Examples include the [[Root beer float]] and the [[Milkshake]].

Major railroads featured upscale cuisine in their dining cars.&lt;ref&gt;James D. Porterfield, ''Dining by Rail: The History and Recipes of America's Golden Age of Railroad Cuisine'' (1993)&lt;/ref&gt; Restaurant chains emerged with standardized decor and menus, including the [[Fred Harvey Company|Fred Harvey]] restaurants along the route of the Sante Fe Railroad in the Southwest.&lt;ref&gt;Stephen Fried, ''Appetite for America: How Visionary Businessman Fred Harvey Built a Railroad Hospitality Empire That Civilized the Wild West'' (Bantam; 2010)&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Fast food]] restaurants with standardized product and franchised service models began to appear and spread with the development of the [[Federal Aid Highway Act of 1921|highway system]].  [[White Castle (restaurant)|White Castle]] (1916) was one of the first examples.  Franchising was introduced in 1921 by [[A&amp;W Root Beer]].  The [[McDonald's]] brothers created their &quot;Speedee Service System&quot; in 1948.

At the universities, nutritionists and home economists taught a new scientific approach to food.  In the early 1900s [[Muckraker|muckraking]] journalists raised public concern about the wholesomeness of industrialized food products that contained various preservatives and adulterants of unknown safety.  From 1902 to 1912 [[Harvey Washington Wiley]], a chemist at the [[U.S. Department of Agriculture]], supervised &quot;hygienic table trials&quot; to test the safety of food additives and preservatives.  His work contributed to the enactment of the [[Pure Food and Drug Act]] of 1906.  He became the first commissioner of the [[Food and Drug Administration]] and later led the [[Good Housekeeping Seal|laboratories of ''Good Housekeeping'' Magazine]].

During World War I the [[Progressives]]' moral advice about food conservation was emphasized in large-scale state and federal programs designed to educate housewives. Large-scale foreign aid during and after the war brought American standards to Europe.&lt;ref&gt;Helen Zoe Veit, ''Modern Food, Moral Food: Self-Control, Science, and the Rise of Modern American Eating in the Early Twentieth Century'' (2013)&lt;/ref&gt;

From 1912 to the end of the 1930s researchers discovered and popularized the role of various [[Vitamin|vitamins and minerals]] in human health.  Starting with iodized salt in 1924, commercially distributed food began to be [[Food fortification|fortified]] with vitamins and minerals.  In 1932, milk began to be fortified with [[Ergosterol|viosterol]], a purified vitamin D2 product.  Synthetic [[Thiamine|thiamin (vitamin B1)]] first became available after 1936 and bakers began voluntarily enriching bread with high-vitamin yeast or synthetic vitamins in the late 1930s.  The Food and Nutrition Board of the National Academy of Science established the first set of &quot;[[Dietary Reference Intake|Recommended Dietary Allowances]]&quot; in 1941. In 1943, the US War Foods Administration issued the War Food Order No. 1, which made enriched bread the temporary law of the land.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Bishai |first1=David |last2=Nalubola |first2=Ritu |title=The History of Food Fortification in the United States: |journal=Economic Development and Cultural Change |date=October 2002 |volume=51 |issue=1 |pages=37–53 |url=http://web1.sph.emory.edu/users/hpacho2/PartnershipsMaize/Bishai_2002.pdf |accessdate=23 February 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1945 George Stigler published an article on &quot;The cost of subsistence&quot; which described the so-called [[Stigler diet]] - his solution to the problem of providing a diet that met the RDA at a minimum cost.

The logistical requirements of the US military during [[World War II|WW2]] and the [[Korean War]] spurred the development and growth of the processed foods industry in the US.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Twilley |first1=Nicola |title=How Military R&amp;D Created The Food We Eat |url=https://www.popsci.com/how-military-created-food-we-know-it |website=Popular Science |accessdate=12 September 2018 |language=en |date=10 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; These wars encouraged production of shelf-stable ingredients processed on a vast industrial scale.  Examples include [[powdered milk]], [[powdered eggs]], [[Instant mashed potatoes|potato flakes]], and [[Frozen OJ|frozen concentrated orange juice]].

After the war, low cost, highly processed foods became one of the foundational elements of an era of mass prosperity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Maurer |first1=Elizabeth |title=How Highly Processed Foods Liberated 1950s Housewives |url=https://www.womenshistory.org/articles/how-highly-processed-foods-liberated-1950s-housewives |website=National Women's History Museum |accessdate=12 September 2018 |language=en |date=11 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Many companies in the American [[food industry]] developed new products requiring minimal preparation, such as frozen entrees.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/13/business/13conagra.html|title=ConAgra's Chief Is Moving to Revitalize Some Venerable Brands|newspaper=[[The New York Times]]|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; One such example is the [[TV dinner]] in which a multi-course meal was assembled in aluminum packaging in a food factory and flash frozen, then reheated at home in a thermal oven to be served while watching TV.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=1950s TV Turns on America |url=http://adage.com/article/75-years-of-ideas/1950s-tv-turns-america/102703/ |website=AdAge |accessdate=12 September 2018 |language=en |date=28 March 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Convenience food]]s of the era were designed to simplify home preparation.  One example is [[Kraft Dinner|macaroni &amp; cheese]] created using a powdered artificial cheese product that is reconstituted at home with fresh milk.  Newspapers and magazines ran recipe columns, aided by research from corporate kitchens, which were major food manufacturers like [[General Mills]], [[Campbell's]], and [[Kraft Foods]].  For example, the General Mills ''Betty Crocker's Cookbook'', first published in 1950, was a popular book in American homes.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcolnb|Crocker|2005}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qn4188/is_20071003/ai_n21022934|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071114015916/http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qn4188/is_20071003/ai_n21022934|url-status=dead|archive-date=November 14, 2007|title=Face value: Fictional Betty Crocker gives big business a human touch Deseret News (Salt Lake City)|date=November 14, 2007|accessdate=October 14, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Highly processed foods of the mid-twentieth century included novelty elements like multi-colored [[Jell-O]] using various chemical [[food coloring]]s, prepared breakfast cereals marketed to children with large amounts of sugar and artificial colors (e.g. [[Froot Loops]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Pinsker |first1=Joe |title=Americans’ Bizarre Relationship With the Color of Their Food |url=https://www.theatlantic.com/business/archive/2017/05/american-food-coloring-dyes/525666/ |website=The Atlantic |accessdate=12 September 2018 |date=8 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fruit flavored punches made with artificial fruit flavorings (e.g. [[Tang (drink)|Tang]], [[Hi-C]]).  Mid-twentieth century foods also added novelty packaging elements like [[Easy Cheese|spray cheese in an aerosol can]], [[Pimiento|pimento]] stuffed olives, and [[Capri Sun|drink pouches]].

The development of the [[microwave oven]] resulted in the creation of industrial food products and packaging that is intended take advantage of the unique opportunities and overcome the unique challenges of that technology.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Cavolt |first1=Jessie |last2=Dean |first2=Kelsey |last3=White |first3=Madison |last4=Salita |first4=Helen |title=Impact on American Society – The Microwave |url=http://historyoftech.mcclurken.org/microwave/the-impact/ |website=historyoftech.mcclurken.org |accessdate=12 September 2018 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Microwave popcorn]] is an example of such a product.

Throughout the second half of the 20th century the US commercial food system has become increasingly dependent on [[Agricultural subsidy#United States|subsidized]] [[maize]] (corn) production to provide feed for livestock and ingredients for human foods such as [[high-fructose corn syrup]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Foley |first1=Jonathan |title=It’s Time to Rethink America’s Corn System |journal=Scientific American |date=March 5, 2013 |url=https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/time-to-rethink-corn/ |accessdate=23 February 2019 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;  It is estimated that the typical American gets 70 percent of his/her [[carbon]] intake from [[maize]] (corn) sources.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Gupta |first1=Sanjay |title=If we are what we eat, Americans are corn and soy |url=http://www.cnn.com/2007/HEALTH/diet.fitness/09/22/kd.gupta.column/ |accessdate=23 February 2019 |work=www.cnn.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The last half of the 20th century saw the development of controversial technological innovations intended to lower the cost of, improve the quality of, or increase the safety of commercial food including:  [[food irradiation]],&lt;ref name=&quot;maurer&quot;&gt;K.F. Maurer, Zur Keimfreimachung von Gewürzen, Ernährungswirtschaft 5(1958) nr.1, 45-47&lt;/ref&gt; [[genetically modified organism]]s, livestock treated with [[Antibiotic use in livestock|antibiotics]]/[[Beef hormone controversy|hormones]], and [[concentrated animal feeding operation]]s. Activists have raised concerns about the wholesomeness, safety, or humaneness of these innovations and recommend alternatives such as [[Organic food|organic produce]], [[veganism]]/[[vegetarianism]], and [[Local food|locavore]] diets.

====Ethnic influences====
[[File:Cheeseburger (17237580619).jpg|thumb|A [[cheeseburger]] served with [[French fries|fries]] and [[coleslaw]]]]
One signature characteristic of American cooking is the [[Fusion cuisine|fusion]] of multiple ethnic or regional approaches into completely new cooking styles. For example, spaghetti is Italian, while hot dogs are German; a popular meal, especially among young children, is spaghetti containing slices of hot dogs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://food52.com/blog/22718-how-to-make-hot-dog-spaghetti-food-trends|title=Threaded Spaghetti Hot Dogs Were the Best Decision I’ve Ever Made|last=533075974|date=2018-07-16|website=Food52|language=en-us|access-date=2019-01-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.flavorednation.com/zz/lifestyle/20170807/sauce-your-hot-dogs-and-spaghetti-midwest-style|title=Sauce your hot dogs and spaghetti, Midwest-style|last=Now|first=More Content|website=Flavored Nation|language=en|access-date=2019-01-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since the 1960s Asian cooking has played a particularly large role in American fusion cuisine.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.asian-nation.org/asian-food.shtml|title=Asian Cuisine &amp; Foods : Asian-Nation :: Asian American History, Demographics, &amp; Issues|publisher=Asian-nation.org|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Flickr sekimura 2390523527--Smoked salmon eggs Benedict.jpg|thumb|left|[[Eggs Benedict]], an American breakfast dish made with poached eggs and hollandaise sauce, served in this variation with smoked salmon]]

Some dishes that are typically considered American have their origins in other countries. American cooks and chefs have substantially altered these dishes over the years, to the degree that the dishes now enjoyed around the world are considered to be American. [[Hot dog]]s and [[hamburger]]s are both based on traditional [[German cuisine|German]] dishes, but in their modern popular form they can be reasonably considered American dishes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bellaonline.com/articles/art10695.asp|title=Hamburgers &amp; Hot Dogs - All-American Food!|publisher=Bellaonline.com|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Pizza]] is based on the traditional [[Italian cuisine|Italian]] dish, brought by Italian immigrants to the United States, but varies highly in style based on the region of development since its arrival. For example, &quot;Chicago&quot; style has focus on a thicker, taller crust, whereas a &quot;[[New York–style pizza|New York Slice]]&quot; is known to have a much thinner crust which can be folded. These different types of pizza can be advertised throughout the country and are generally recognizable and well-known, with some restaurants going so far as to import New York City tap water from a thousand or more miles away to recreate the signature style in other regions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.eddieandsamspizza.com/index.php|title=Eddie &amp; Sam's Pizza|publisher=Eddieandsamspizza.com|accessdate=January 16, 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150116202005/http://www.eddieandsamspizza.com/index.php|archive-date=January 16, 2015|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some dishes that American's think of as being of &quot;foreign&quot; in origin and/or associated with a particular immigrant group were in fact invented in America and customized to American tastes.  For example [[General Tso's chicken]] was invented by Chinese or Taiwanese chefs working in New York City in the early 1970s.&lt;ref name=&quot;hollywoodreporter.com&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last1=DeFore|first1=John |title='The Search for General Tso': SIFF Review |url=http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/review/search-general-tso-siff-review-708453 |work=[[The Hollywood Reporter]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The dish is unknown in China.  The [[fortune cookie]] was likewise invented in California in the early 1900s and is known in Asia only as an American style food.&lt;ref name=&quot;snopes2&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.snopes.com/food/origins/fortune.asp|title=Origin of Fortune Cookies|date=2008-06-09|work=Snopes.com|access-date=2017-05-30|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Roasted_American_Turkey_(6408110873).jpg|thumb|A modern dish consisting of traditional roasted turkey, [[sweet potato]]es, and grilled vegetables prepared with modern fusion ingredients]]

A wave of [[celebrity chef]]s began with [[Julia Child]] and [[Graham Kerr]] in the 1970s, with many more following after the rise of cable channels like [[Food Network]]. By the beginning of the 21st century regional variations in consumption of meat began to reduce, as more meat was consumed overall.&lt;ref name=&quot;Warren2007&quot;/&gt; Saying they eat too much protein, the ''2015–2020 Dietary Guidelines for Americans'' asked men and teenage boys to increase their consumption of underconsumed foods such as vegetables.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Some individuals, especially teen boys and adult men, also need to reduce overall intake of protein foods by decreasing intakes of meats, poultry, and eggs and increasing amounts of vegetables or other underconsumed food groups.&quot; in {{cite web|publisher=U.S. Department of Health and Human Services and U.S. Department of Agriculture.|title=2015–2020 Dietary Guidelines for Americans: Shifts Needed To Align With Healthy Eating Patterns: A Closer Look at Current Intakes and Recommended Shifts: Protein Foods|edition=8|date=December 2015|url=http://health.gov/dietaryguidelines/2015/guidelines/chapter-2/a-closer-look-at-current-intakes-and-recommended-shifts/|accessdate=January 9, 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160109170222/http://health.gov/dietaryguidelines/2015/guidelines/chapter-2/a-closer-look-at-current-intakes-and-recommended-shifts/|archive-date=January 9, 2016|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====New American====
{{Main|New American cuisine}}
During the 1980s, upscale restaurants introduced a mixing of cuisines that contain Americanized styles of cooking with foreign elements commonly referred as [[New American cuisine]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.studio10.tv/category/recipes/segment.aspx/116055/|title=Foodies|year=2011|publisher=Studio 10|accessdate=March 17, 2014|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140322014046/http://www.studio10.tv/category/recipes/segment.aspx/116055/|archive-date=March 22, 2014|url-status=dead|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; New American cuisine refers to a type of [[fusion cuisine]] which assimilates flavors from the [[melting pot]] of traditional American cooking techniques mixed with flavors from other cultures and sometimes [[molecular gastronomy]] components.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ltcconline.net/voced/culinaryarts/pdfs/ContemporaryCuisine.pdf|title=Characteristics of Contemporary Cuisine|publisher=LTCC Online}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://philipmarie.com/history/|title=Philip Marie Restaurant|publisher=Pulsar Studio|accessdate=March 14, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Regional cuisines==
{{See also|List of American regional and fusion cuisines|List of regional dishes of the United States}}
Generally speaking, in the present day 21st century, the modern cuisine of the United States is very much regional in nature. Excluding [[Alaska]] and [[Hawaii]], the terrain spans {{convert|3,000|mi}} from east to west and more than {{convert|1000|mi}} from north to south.

===Northeast===

====New England====
{{Main|Cuisine of New England}}
[[File:Quail 07 bg 041506.jpg|thumb|New England [[clam chowder]]]]
New England is a Northeastern region of the United States bordering the Maritime Provinces of Canada and portions of Quebec in the north. It includes the six states of [[Connecticut]], [[Maine]], [[Massachusetts]], [[New Hampshire]], [[Rhode Island]], and [[Vermont]], with its largest city and cultural capital [[Boston]], founded in 1630. The Native American cuisine became part of the cookery style that the early colonists brought with them. Tribes like the [[Nipmuck]], [[Wampanoag]],  [[Passamaquoddy]] and other Algonquian cultures were noted for slashing and burning areas to create meadows and bogs that would attract animals like [[Eastern moose|moose]] and [[white tailed deer|deer]], but also encourage the growth of plants like [[black raspberries]], [[lowbush blueberry|blueberries]], and [[Cranberry|cranberries]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.mpm.edu/wirp/ICW-55.html|title=Brothertown Culture - Indian Country Wisconsin|website=Mpm.edu|accessdate=August 12, 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160921102221/https://www.mpm.edu/wirp/ICW-55.html|archive-date=September 21, 2016|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the forest they would have collected nuts of species like the [[shagbark hickory]], [[corylus americana|American hazel]], and [[castanea dentata|American chestnuts]] and fruits like wild [[vitis labrusca|grapes]] and [[prunus serotina|black cherries]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Connole|first1=Dennis A.|title=The Indians of the Nipmuck Country in Southern New England, 1630-1750: An Historical Geography|date=December 15, 2000|publisher=[[McFarland &amp; Company]]|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=QB1Et3yHBxIC|accessdate=August 12, 2016|isbn=9780786450114}}&lt;/ref&gt; All of these eventually showed up in the kitchens of colonial New England women&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.teachervision.com/foods/lesson-plan/3257.html|title=Colonial New England Food &amp; Cooking|website=Teachervision.com|accessdate=August 12, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; and many were sent back to England and other portions of Europe to be catalogued by scientists, collectors, and horticulturalists.

The style of New England cookery originated from its colonial roots, that is to say practical, frugal, and willing to eat anything other than what they were used to from their British roots.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcolnb|Smith|2004|pp=181–182}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Most of the initial colonists came from [[East Anglia]] in England, with other groups following them over the ages like francophone regions of [[Canada]] (this was especially true of Northern New England, where there are still many speakers of a [[New England French|dialect of French]]), from Ireland, from Southern Italy, and most recently from Haiti, Brazil, the Dominican Republic, and Portugal. The oldest forms of the cuisine date to the early 17th century and in the case of Massachusetts, out of the entire country only the state of Virginia can claim recipes that are older. East Anglian cookery would have included recipes for dishes like suet puddings, wheaten breads, and a few shellfish delicacies, like winkles, and would have been at the time of settlement simple Puritan fare quite in contrast to the fineries and excesses expected in London cavalier circles. Most of the cuisine started with one-pot cookery, which resulted in such dishes as [[succotash]], [[chowder]], [[baked beans]], and others.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcolnb|Danforth|Feierabend|Chassman|1998|p=13}}&lt;/ref&gt; Starches are fairly simple, and typically encompass just a handful of classics like [[potato]]es and [[cornmeal]], and a few native breads like [[Anadama bread]], [[johnnycake]]s, [[bulkie roll]]s, [[Parker house roll]]s, [[popover]]s, and [[New England brown bread]]. This region is fairly conservative with its spices, but typical spices include [[nutmeg]], [[ginger]], [[cinnamon]], [[clove]]s, and [[allspice]], especially in desserts, and for savory foods, [[thyme]], [[black pepper]], [[sea salt]], and [[Salvia officinalis|sage]]. Typical condiments include [[maple syrup]], grown from the native [[sugar maple]], [[molasses]], and [[cranberry sauce]].

New England is noted for having a heavy emphasis on seafood, a legacy inherited from coastal tribes like the [[Wampanoag]] and [[Narragansett Indian Tribe of Rhode Island|Narragansett]], who equally used the rich fishing banks offshore for sustenance. Favorite fish include [[Atlantic cod|cod]], [[Atlantic salmon|salmon]], [[winter flounder]], [[haddock]], [[striped bass]], [[pollock]], [[hake]], [[bluefish]], and, in southern New England, [[tautog]]. All of these are prepared numerous ways, such as frying cod for fish fingers, grilling bluefish over hot coals for summertime, smoking salmon or serving a whole poached one chilled for feasts with a dill sauce, or, on cold winter nights, serving haddock baked in casserole dish with a creamy sauce and crumbled breadcrumbs as a top so it forms a crust.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=10595677|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20141211050451/http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=10595677|url-status=dead|title=Recipes: 'The Summer Shack Cookbook'|archivedate=December 11, 2014|website=NPR.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Clam cakes]], a savory fritter based on chopped clams, are a specialty of Rhode Island. Farther inland, [[brook trout]], [[largemouth bass]], and [[herring]] are sought after, especially in the rivers and icy finger lakes in upper New England where New Englanders will [[Fly fishing|fly fish]] for them in summertime.

Meat is present though not as prominent, and typically is either stewed in dishes like [[pot roast|Yankee pot roast]] and [[New England boiled dinner]] or braised, as in a [[picnic ham]]; these dishes suit the weather better as summers are humid and hot but winters are raw and cold, getting below 0&amp;nbsp;°C for most of the winter and only just above it by March.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://discovernewengland.org/about-new-england/new-england-weather|title=New England Weather, Avg Temperatures - Discover New England|website=Discovernewengland.org|accessdate=August 12, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The roasting of whole turkeys began here as a centerpiece for large American banquets, and like all other East Coast tribes, the Native American tribes of New England prized wild turkeys as a source of sustenance and later Anglophone settlers were enamored of cooking them using methods they knew from Europe: often that meant trussing the bird and spinning it on a string or spit roasting. Today turkey meat is a key ingredient in soups, and also a favorite in several sandwiches like the [[Pilgrim (sandwich)|Pilgrim]]. For lunch, hot roast beef is sometimes chopped finely into small pieces and put on a roll with salami and American or provolone cheese to make a [[steak bomb]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.seriouseats.com/2014/07/ideas-in-food-vs-steak-bomb-part-1.html|title=Ideas in Food vs. The Steak Bomb: Reinventing the Bread|website=[[Serious Eats]] |date=July 31, 2014| accessdate=August 12, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bacon is often maple cured, and often bacon or salt pork drippings are an ingredient in [[corn chowder]], a cousin of the clam chowder.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://newengland.com/today/food/soups-stews-chowders/chowders/new-england-corn-chowder/|title=Yankee Magazine Article New England Corn Chowder Recipe}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Veal]] consumption was prevalent in the North Atlantic States prior to [[World War II]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Warren2007&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Wilson J. Warren|title=Tied to the Great Packing Machine: The Midwest and Meatpacking|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=f-CAclXhhCYC&amp;pg=PA143|year=2007|publisher=[[University of Iowa Press]]|isbn=978-1-58729-774-8|pages=143–144}}&lt;/ref&gt; A variety of linguiça is favored as a breakfast food, brought with Portuguese fisherman and Brazilian immigrants.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.timeout.com/boston/restaurants/the-best-brunch-in-boston|title=Brunch in Boston: Top breakfasts and brunches in Boston|work=Time Out Boston|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; In contrast with some parts of the United States, [[lamb and mutton|lamb]] (although less so mutton or goat) is a popular roasted or grilled meat across diverse groups in New England. Dairy farming and its resultant products figure strongly on the ingredient list, and homemade ice cream is a summertime staple of the region: it was a small seasonal roadside stand in Vermont that eventually became the internationally famous [[Ben and Jerry's]] ice cream. Vermont is known for producing farmhouse style cheeses, especially a type of cheddar.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.cheeseandyogurtmaking.com/blog/state-best-cheddar-cheese-vermont-wisconsin/|title=Which State Has The Best Cheddar Cheese - Vermont or Wisconsin? - Cheese and Yogurt Making|date=May 1, 2014|website=Cheeseandyogurtmaking.com|accessdate=August 12, 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160610130332/http://www.cheeseandyogurtmaking.com/blog/state-best-cheddar-cheese-vermont-wisconsin/#|archive-date=June 10, 2016|url-status=dead|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; The recipe goes all the way back to colonial times when English settlers brought the recipe with them from England and found the rocky landscape eminently suitable to making the cheese.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://culturecheesemag.com/blog/distant-cheeses-local-farmers-cheddar-across-continents|title=Distant Cheeses, Local Farmers: Cheddar Across Continents - culture: the word on cheese|date=February 7, 2013|website=Culturecheeesemag.com|accessdate=August 12, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Today Vermont has more artisanal cheese makers per capita than any other state, and diversity is such that interest in goat's milk cheeses has become prominent.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://nutrition.uvm.edu/viac/index.cfm?pg=Mission&amp;section=about|title=VIAC Vermont Institute for Artisan Cheese - cheesemaking at UVM, the University of Vermont|website=Nutrition.uvm.edu|accessdate=August 12, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Crustaceans and mollusks are also an essential ingredient in the regional cookery. Maine and Massachusetts, in more recent years, have taken to harvesting [[peekytoe crab]] and [[Jonah crab]] and making crab bisques, based on cream with 35% milkfat, and crabcakes out of them: often these were overlooked as bycatch of lobster pots by fisherman of the region, but in the past 30 years their popularity has firmly established them as a staple They even appear on the menu as far south as to be out of region in [[New York City]], where they are sold to four star restaurants in the form of cocktail claws. Squid are heavily fished for and eaten as [[fried calamari]], and often are an ingredient in [[Italian American]] cooking in this region. Whelks are eaten in salad, and [[lobster]], which is indigenous to the coastal waters of the region and are a feature of many dishes, baked, boiled, roasted, and steamed, or simply eaten as a [[lobster roll|sandwich]], chilled with mayonnaise and chopped celery in Maine and Massachusetts, or slathered with melted butter on Long Island and in Connecticut.

Shellfish of all sorts are part of the diet, and [[shellfish]] of the coastal regions include [[Cherrystone clam#Alternative names|little neck clams]], [[Scallop|sea scallops]], [[blue mussel]]s, [[oyster]]s, [[Soft-shell clam|soft shell clams]], and [[Atlantic jackknife clam|razor shell clams]]. Much of this shellfish contributes to New England tradition, the [[New England clam bake|clambake]]. The clambake as known today is a colonial interpretation of an American Indian tradition.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcolnb|Danforth|Feierabend|Chassman|1998|pp=12–19}}&lt;/ref&gt; In summer, oysters and clams are dipped in batter and fried, often served in a basket with french fries, or commonly on a wheaten bun as a clam roll. Oysters are otherwise eaten chilled on a bed of crushed ice on the half shell with mignonette sauce, and are often branded on where they were harvested. Large quahogs are stuffed with breadcrumbs and seasoning and baked in their shells, and smaller ones often find their way into [[clam chowder]]. Other preparations include [[clams casino]], clams on the half shell served stuffed with herbs like [[oregano]] and streaky bacon.

The fruits of the region include the ''[[Vitis labrusca]]'' grapes used in [[grape juice]] made by companies such as [[Welch's]], along with [[Fruit preserves|jelly]], [[Kosher wine]] by companies like [[Mogen David]] and [[Manischewitz]] along with other wineries that make higher quality wines

Though not anywhere near as productive a region as the top three apple producing regions, Apples have been a staple of New England foodways since at least the 1640s and it is here that a very high amount of heirloom varieties are found, many of them gaining renewed interest as part of locavore movements and the re-emergence of cider as a beverage of choice. [[Apple]]s from New England would include varieties imported from their earliest in Europe and a few natives, like  [[Baldwin (apple)|Baldwin]], Lady, Mother, Pomme Grise, Porter, [[Roxbury Russet]], [[Rhode Island Greening]], [[Sops of Wine (apple)|Sops of Wine]], Hightop Sweet, Peck's Pleasant, Titus Pippin, [[Westfield-Seek-No-Further]], and [[Duchess of Oldenburg (apple)|Duchess of Oldenburg]]. Historically New England and the other original 13 colonies were major producers of hard cider and the only reason why this changed were that immigrants from Western and Central Europe preferred beer, especially lagers, to apple based alcohol.  In more recent years cider has made a roaring comeback nationwide, with New England being the first to break out of the box and with many pomologists scouring the woods for abandoned apple trees and heirloom varieties to add to the cider press.  [[Angry Orchard]] is a local commercial brand that began in New Hampshire but has since skyrocketed in sales, with other large marques following suit around the land.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://craftynectar.com/blogs/cider/usa-s-hard-cider-revolution|title=USA’S Hard Cider Revolution|website=Crafty Nectar|access-date=2019-03-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Beach plum]]s a small native species with fruits the size of a pinball, are sought after in summer to make into a jam. [[Cranberry|Cranberries]] are another fruit indigenous to the region, often collected in autumn in huge flooded bogs. Thereafter they are juiced so they can be drunk fresh for breakfast, or dried and incorporated into salads and quickbreads.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcolnb|Danforth|Feierabend|Chassman|1998|pp=24–26}}&lt;/ref&gt; Winter squashes like pumpkin and butternut squashes have been a staple for generations owing to their ability to keep for long periods over icy New England winters and being an excellent source of beta carotene; in summer, they are replaced with pattypan and zucchini, the latter brought to the region by immigrants from Southern Italy a century ago. Blueberries are a very common summertime treat owing to them being an important crop, and find their way into [[muffin]]s, [[pie]]s and [[pancake]]s. Typical favorite desserts are quite diverse, and encompass [[hasty pudding]], [[blueberry pie]], [[whoopie pie]]s, [[Boston cream pie]], [[pumpkin pie]], [[Joe Frogger]] cookies, hand crafted [[ice cream]], [[Hermit]] cookies, and the [[chocolate chip cookie]], invented in [[Massachusetts]] in the 1930s.

Southern New England, particularly along the coast, shares many specialties with the Mid-Atlantic, including especially dishes from Jewish and Italian-American cuisine. Coastal Connecticut is known for distinctive kinds of [[pizza]], locally called apizza (pronounced locally as ''abeetz''), differing in texture (thin and slightly blackened) and toppings (such as clams) from pizza further south in the so-called pizza belt, which stretches from [[New Haven, Connecticut]] southward through [[New York City|New York]], [[New Jersey]], and into [[Maryland]].

====Delaware Valley and Mid-Atlantic====
{{Main|Cuisine of Philadelphia|Cuisine of New York City|Cuisine of the Mid-Atlantic United States}}
[[File:NY_Strip_Steak.jpg|thumb|[[strip steak|New York strip steak]] topped with mushrooms and onions]]
The mid-Atlantic states comprise the states of [[New York (state)|New York]], [[New Jersey]], [[Delaware]], [[Pennsylvania]], and Northern [[Maryland]]. The oldest major settlement in this area of the country is found in the most populous city in the nation, [[New York City]], founded in 1625 by the Dutch. Today, it is a major cultural capital of the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/kurt-ellenberger/the-cultural-capital-of-e_b_1512261.html|title=The Cultural Capital of Everywhere|work=The Huffington Post|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The influences on cuisine in this region are extremely eclectic owing to the fact that it has been and continues to be a gateway for international culture as well as a gateway for new immigrants.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.pbs.org/destinationamerica/usim_wn.html|title=Destination America . When did they come? - PBS|publisher=Pbs.org|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Going back to colonial times, each new group has left their mark on homegrown cuisine and in turn the cities in this region disperse trends to the wider United States. In addition, cities like New York and Philadelphia have had the past influence of Dutch,&lt;ref name=&quot;History&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.culinaryhistoriansny.org/files/Newsletters/Newsletter_2002_F.pdf |title=Culinary Historians of New York : Dutch Food in Life and Art |publisher=Culinaryhistoriansny.org |accessdate=January 16, 2015 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131221000513/http://www.culinaryhistoriansny.org/files/Newsletters/Newsletter_2002_F.pdf |archivedate=December 21, 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Italian, German,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.germanheritage.com/publications/cronau/cronau6.html|title=The Life of the German Settlers in Colonial Times|publisher=Germanheritage.com|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Irish,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nydailynews.com/life-style/eats/irish-fare-new-york-st-patrick-day-article-1.1280295|title=Irish fare in New York for St. Patrick's Day|work=NY Daily News|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://nymag.com/listings/bar/mcsorleys/|title=McSorley's Old Ale House|work=NYMag.com|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; British,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.foodtimeline.org/foodschools.html#princeton|title=The Food Timeline: school lunch history|author=Lynne Olver|publisher=Foodtimeline.org|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Jewish cuisines,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2014/05/28/dining/everything-new-is-old-again.html?_r=0|title=Everything New Is Old Again : The New Golden Age of Jewish-American Deli Food|newspaper=[[The New York Times]]|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; and that continues to this day. Baltimore has become the crossroads between North and South, a distinction it has held since the end of the Civil War.

A [[global city|global power city]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.mori-m-foundation.or.jp/english/research/project/6/pdf/GPCI2009_English.pdf |title=Global Power City Index 2009 |publisher=The Mori Memorial Foundation |accessdate=June 1, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; New York City is well known for its diverse and cosmopolitan dining scene.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theworlds50best.com/list/1-50-winners/ |title=The World's 50 Best Restaurants |publisher=The World's 50 Best Restaurants |accessdate=November 29, 2015 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130607141909/http://www.theworlds50best.com/list/1-50-winners/ |archivedate=June 7, 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Its restaurants compete fiercely for good reviews in the Food and Dining section of ''[[The New York Times]]'', online guides, and [[Zagat's]], the last of which is widely considered the premier American dining guide, published yearly and headquartered in New York City.

[[File:Carnegie Deli Strawberry Cheesecake.jpg|thumb|New York–style cheesecake with strawberries. Other variations include blueberry or raspberry sauce.]]
Many of the more complicated dishes with rich ingredients like [[Lobster Newberg]], [[waldorf salad]], [[vichyssoise]], [[eggs benedict]], and the [[New York strip steak]] were born out of a need to entertain and impress the well to do in expensive bygone restaurants like [[Delmonico's]] and still standing establishments like the [[Waldorf-Astoria Hotel]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Was He the Eggman&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/nyregion/thecity/08eggs.html?pagewanted=all|title=Was He the Eggman?|newspaper=[[The New York Times]]|accessdate=November 29, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;The Waldorf - Astoria Hotel&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.historichotels.org/hotels-resorts/the-waldorf-astoria-hotel/history.php|title=The Waldorf - Astoria Hotel|publisher=Historic Hotels of America|accessdate=November 29, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Modern commercial American cream cheese was developed in 1872, when William Lawrence, from [[Chester, Orange County, New York|Chester, New York]], while looking for a way to recreate the soft, French cheese [[Neufchâtel (cheese)|Neufchâtel]], accidentally came up with a way of making an &quot;unripened cheese&quot; that is heavier and creamier; other dairymen came up with similar creations independently.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://whatscookingamerica.net/History/Cakes/Cheesecake.htm|title=History of Cheesecake, History of New York Cheesecake, Cream Cheese History, Whats Cooking America|website=Whatscookingamerica.net|accessdate=August 12, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Since the first reference to an alcoholic mixed drink called a cocktail comes from [[New York State]] in 1803, it is thus not a surprise that there have been many cocktails invented in New York and the surrounding environs. Even today New York City bars are noted for being highly influential in making national trends. [[Cosmopolitan (cocktail)|Cosmopolitans]], [[Long Island iced tea]]s, [[Manhattan (cocktail)|Manhattans]], [[Rob Roy (cocktail)|Rob Roys]], [[Tom Collins]], [[Aviation (cocktail)|Aviations]], and [[Greyhound (cocktail)|Greyhounds]] were all invented in New York bars, and the [[Martini (cocktail)|gin martini]] was popularized in New York in speakeasies during the 1920s, as evidenced by its appearance in the works of New Yorker and American writer F. Scott Fitzgerald. Like its neighbor [[Philadelphia]], many rare and unusual liquors and liqueurs often find their way into a mixologist's cupboard or restaurant wine list. New York State is the third most productive area in the country for wine grapes, just behind [[California]] and [[Washington (state)|Washington]]. It has [[American Viticultural Area|AVA]]'s near the Finger Lakes, the Catskills, and Long Island,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newyorkwines.org/Regions|title=Regions - New York Wine &amp; Grape Foundation|publisher=Newyorkwines.org|accessdate=January 16, 2015|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150106021813/http://www.newyorkwines.org/Regions|archivedate=January 6, 2015|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; and in the [[Hudson Valley]] has the second most productive area in the country for growing apples, making it a center for hard cider production, just like [[New England]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nyapplecountry.com/about/facts|title=NY Apple Industry Facts - NY Apple Association|publisher=Nyapplecountry.com|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2014/09/28/travel/sips-from-a-cider-spree-in-new-york-state.html?_r=0|title=Sips From a Cider Spree in New York State|newspaper=[[The New York Times]]|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Pennsylvania has been growing rye since Germans began to emigrate to the area at the end of the 17th century and required a grain they knew from Germany.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://philly.thedrinknation.com/articles/read/9052-Spirits-Review-Dads-Hat-Rye|title=Spirits Review: Dad's Hat Rye|work=Drink Philly|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Therefore, overall it is not unusual to find New York grown [[Gewürtztraminer]] and [[Riesling]], Pennsylvania rye whiskey, or marques of locally produced ciders like Original Sin on the same menu.

[[File:PatsCheesesteak.jpg|thumb|[[Cheesesteak|Philadelphia cheesesteak]] with cheese whiz]]
Since their formative years, [[New York City]], [[Philadelphia]], and [[Baltimore]] have welcomed immigrants of every kind to their shores, and all three have been an important gateway through which new citizens to the general United States arrive.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.history.com/topics/u-s-immigration-before-1965|title=U.S. Immigration Before 1965|work=HISTORY.com|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Traditionally natives have eaten cheek to jowl with newcomers for centuries as the newcomers would open new restaurants and small businesses and all the different groups would interact. Even in colonial days this region was a very diverse mosaic of peoples, as settlers from Switzerland, Wales, England, Ulster, Wallonia, Holland, Gelderland, the British Channel Islands, and Sweden sought their fortune in this region.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tenement.org/encyclopedia/lower_orchard.htm|title=Lower East Side Tenement Museum|publisher=Tenement.org|accessdate=January 16, 2015|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150228150927/http://www.tenement.org/encyclopedia/lower_orchard.htm|archivedate=February 28, 2015|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.phillyhistory.org/blog/index.php/2008/03/the-jewish-quarter-of-philadelphia/|title=The Jewish Quarter of Philadelphia|work=PhillyHistory Blog|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; This is very evident in many signature dishes and local foods, all of which have evolved to become American dishes in their own right. The original Dutch settlers of New York brought recipes they knew and understood from the Netherlands and their mark on local cuisine is still apparent today: in many quarters of New York their version of apple pie with a streusel top is still baked, while originating in the colony of New Amsterdam their predilection for waffles in time evolved into the American national recipe and forms part of a New York City brunch, and they also made [[coleslaw]], originally a Dutch salad, but today accented with the later 18th-century introduction of [[mayonnaise]].&lt;ref name=&quot;History&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.myfoxny.com/story/4624796/dutch-apple-pie |title=Dutch Apple Pie |publisher=Myfoxny.com |accessdate=January 16, 2015 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150106035726/http://www.myfoxny.com/story/4624796/dutch-apple-pie |archivedate=January 6, 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.culinarylore.com/food-history:where-does-coleslaw-come-from|title=Where Does Coleslaw Come From and What is the Origin of the Term? - CulinaryLore.com|publisher=Culinarylore.com|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[doughnut]] began its life originally as a New York pastry that arrived in the 18th century as the Dutch olykoek, with later additions from other nations of Europe like the Italian zeppole, the Jewish/Polish pączki, and the German Berliner arriving in the 19th century to complete the variety found in modern doughnuts today.&lt;ref&gt;See entries for ''[[oliebol]]'' and ''oliekoek'' in {{cite book
  | author = Frederic Gomes Cassidy
  |author2=Joan Houston Hall
  | title = Dictionary of American Regional English: I-O
  | publisher = Harvard UP
  | year = 1985
  | page = [https://archive.org/details/dictionaryofamer01arie/page/874 874]
  | url = https://archive.org/details/dictionaryofamer01arie
  | url-access = registration
  | isbn = 978-0-674-20519-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:A Delicious Crabcake at the Middleton Tavern.jpg|left|thumb|[[Crab cake]], popular in [[Maryland]], [[Delaware]] and [[New Jersey]] is often served on a roll.]]
[[Crab cake]]s were once a kind of English croquette, but over time as spices have been added they and the [[Crab boil#Maryland|Maryland crab feast]] became two of Baltimore's signature dishes; fishing for the [[Callinectes sapidus|blue crab]] is a favorite summer pastime in the waters off [[Maryland]], [[New Jersey]], and [[Delaware]] where they may grace the table at summer picnics . Other mainstays of the region have been present since the early years of American history, like oysters from Cape May, the Chesapeake Bay, and Long Island, and lobster and tuna from the coastal waters found in New York and New Jersey.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oysterguide.com/maps/|title=Map of Oyster Regions of North America - The Oyster Guide|publisher=Oysterguide.com|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.grownyc.org/greenmarket/farmers|title=Our Farmers and Producers - GrowNYC|publisher=Grownyc.org|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Philadelphia Pepper Pot]], a tripe stew, was originally a British dish but today is a classic of home cooking in Pennsylvania alongside bookbinder soup, a type of [[turtle soup]].

In the winter, New York City pushcarts sell roasted chestnuts, a delicacy dating back to English Christmas traditions,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://gothamist.com/2012/12/18/chestnuts_roasting_on_an_open_stree.php|title=Some Street Cart Vendors Still Delivering On Seasonal Tradition Of Roasting Chestnuts|work=Gothamist|accessdate=January 16, 2015|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150327022217/http://gothamist.com/2012/12/18/chestnuts_roasting_on_an_open_stree.php|archivedate=March 27, 2015|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; and it was in New York and Pennsylvania that the earliest Christmas cookies were introduced: Germans introduced crunchy molasses based gingerbread and sugar cookies in Pennsylvania, and the Dutch introduced cinnamon based cookies, all of which have become part of the traditional Christmas meal.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://whydyoueatthat.wordpress.com/2011/12/20/day-20-gingerbread/|title=Day 20: Gingerbread|work=Why'd You Eat That?|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cookcfb.org/articles/entryid/97/history-of-the-sugar-cookie|title=History of the Sugar Cookie|work=Cook County Farm Bureau|accessdate=January 16, 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150110083343/http://www.cookcfb.org/articles/entryid/97/history-of-the-sugar-cookie|archive-date=January 10, 2015|url-status=dead|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Scrapple]] was originally a type of savory pudding that early Pennsylvania Germans made to preserve the [[offal]] of a pig slaughter.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.globalgourmet.com/food/sleuth/0998/scrapple.html |title=Scrapple: Pork Mush...The Pennsylvania Treat |publisher=Globalgourmet.com |accessdate=January 16, 2015 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/19990503160812/http://www.globalgourmet.com/food/sleuth/0998/scrapple.html |archivedate=May 3, 1999 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The Philadelphia soft pretzel was originally brought to Eastern Pennsylvania in the early 18th century, and later, 19th-century immigrants sold them to the masses from pushcarts to make them the city's best-known bread product, having evolved into its own unique recipe.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://philadelphia.about.com/od/history/fl/The-History-Behind-the-Philadelphia-Soft-Pretzel.htm|title=The History Behind the Philadelphia Soft Pretzel|author=Julie Davis|work=About.com Travel|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:NYPizzaPie.jpg|thumb|[[New York–style pizza]] is the pizza eaten in [[New York (state)|New York]], [[New Jersey]], and [[Connecticut]].]]
After the 1820s, new groups began to arrive and the character of the region began to change. There had been some Irish from Ulster prior to 1820, however largely they had been Protestants with somewhat different culture and (often) a different [[Irish language|language]] than the explosion of emigrants that came to [[Castle Garden]] and Locust Point in Baltimore in their masses starting in the 1840s.

The Irish arrived in America in a rather woeful state, as Ireland at the time was often plagued by some of the worst poverty in Europe and often heavy disenfranchisement among the masses: many of them arrived barely alive having ridden [[coffin ship]]s to the New World, very sick with typhus and gaunt from prolonged starvation. In addition, they were the first to face challenges other groups did not have: they were the first large wave of Catholics. They faced prejudice for their faith and the cities of Philadelphia, New York, and Baltimore were not always set up for their needs. For example, Catholic bishops in the U.S. mandated until the 1960s that all Catholics were forbidden from eating red meat on Fridays and during Lent,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.ncregister.com/blog/steven-greydanus/meatless-fridays|title=Are Meatless Fridays Still a Thing? Does it Matter?|newspaper=National Catholic Register|access-date=January 5, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; and attending Mass sometimes conflicted with work as produce and meat markets would be open on high holy days; this was difficult for Irishmen supporting families since many worked as laborers. Unsurprisingly, many Irishmen also found their fortunes working as longshoremen, which would have given their families access to fish and shellfish whenever a fisherman made berth, which was frequent on the busy docks of Baltimore and New York.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gothamcenter.org/1/post/2016/07/cant-they-be-separated-italian-immigrants-and-irish-workers-in-gilded-age-new-york.html|title=&quot;Can’t They Be Separated?&quot; Italian Immigrants and Irish Workers in Gilded Age New York|website=THE GOTHAM CENTER FOR NEW YORK CITY HISTORY|language=en|access-date=2019-03-31}}{{Dead link|date=September 2019 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cornellpress.cornell.edu/resources/titles/80140100204190/extras/9780801448041_intro.pdf|title=The Irish Waterfront}}&lt;/ref&gt; Though there had been some activity in Baltimore in founding a [[Holy See|see]] earlier by the [[John Carroll (bishop)|Carrolls]], the Irish were the first major wave of Catholic worship in this region, and that meant bishops and cardinals sending away to Europe for wine. Part of the Catholic mass includes every parishioner taking a sip of wine from the chalice as part of the Eucharist. Taverns had existed prior to their emigration to America in the region, though the Irish brought their particular brand of pub culture and founded some of the first saloons and bars that served Dublin style [[stout]] and [[Irish red ale|red ale]]; they brought with them the knowledge of single malt style whiskey and sold it. The Irish were the first immigrant group to arrive in this region in massive millions, and these immigrants also founded some of the earliest saloons and bars in this region, of which [[McSorley's Old Ale House|McSorley's]] is a still operating example.

[[File:Philly style pretzel.JPG|thumb|Philadelphia-style soft pretzel]]
It was also in this region that the Irish introduced something that today is a very important festival in American culture that involves a large amount of food, drink, and merry making: [[Halloween]]. In England and Wales, where prior immigrants had come from, the feast of All Hallows Eve had died out in the [[English Reformation|Reformation]], dismissed as superstition and excess having nothing to do with the Bible and often replaced with the festival of [[Guy Fawkes Night]]. Other immigrant groups like the Germans preferred to celebrate October 31 as [[Reformation Day]], and after the American Revolution all of the above were less and less eager to celebrate the legacy of an English festival when they had fought a very bloody war to leave the British Empire. The Catholicism of the Irish demanded attendance at church on November 1 and charity and deeds, not just faith, as a cornerstone of dogma, and many of their older traditions survived the Reformation and traveled with them. Naturally, they went door-to-door to collect victuals for masked parties as well as gave them out, like nuts to roast on the fire, whiskey, beer, or cider, and [[barmbrack]]s; they also [[Apple bobbing|bobbed for apples]] and made dumb cakes. Later in the century they were joined by Scots going [[Trick-or-treating|guising]], children going door-to-door to ask for sweets and treats in costume. From the Mid Atlantic this trend spread to be nationwide and evolved into American children [[trick-or-treating]] on October 31 wearing costumes and their older counterparts having wild costume parties with lots of food and drink like [[caramel apple]]s, [[candy apple]]s, [[dirt cake]]s, [[Punch (drink)|punch]], [[cocktail]]s, [[cider]] (both alcoholic and [[Apple cider|non]],) [[pumpkin pie]], [[candy corn]], [[Turtles (chocolate)|chocolate turtles]], [[peanut brittle]], [[Taffy (candy)|taffy]], [[tipsy cake]], and copious buckets full of candy; children carving [[Jack-o'-lantern|jack-o-lanterns]] and eating squash derived foods derive from Halloween's heritage as a harvest festival and from Irish and Scottish traditions of carving turnips and eating root vegetables at this time of year. Their bobbing for apples has survived to the present day as a Halloween party classic game, as has a variation on the parlor game of trying to grab an apple hanging from the ceiling blindfolded:&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/?id=R2Y_AQAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA69&amp;lpg=PA69&amp;dq=hang+apple+from+ceiling+scotland#v=onepage&amp;q=hang%2520apple%2520from%2520ceiling%2520scotland&amp;f=false|title=Scenes and Legends of the North of Scotland|last=Miller|first=Hugh|date=January 1, 1851|publisher=W. H. Moore &amp; D. Anderson|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; it has evolved into trying to catch a donut in one's teeth.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.marthastewart.com/269995/doughnuts-on-a-string|title=Doughnuts on a String|date=May 17, 2011|website=Marthastewart.com|accessdate=August 2, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Immigrants from Southern Europe, namely [[Sicily]], [[Campania]], [[Lazio]], and [[Calabria]], appeared between 1880 and 1960 in New York, New Jersey, Pennsylvania, and Eastern Maryland hoping to escape the extreme poverty and corruption endemic to Italy; typically none of them spoke English, but rather dialects of Italian and had a culture that was more closely tied to the village they were born in than the high culture only accessible to those who could afford it at this time; many could not read or write in any language. They were employed in manual labor or factory work but it is because of them that dishes like [[spaghetti with meatballs]], [[New York–style pizza]], [[calzones]], and [[baked ziti]] exist, and Americans of today are very familiar with semolina based pasta noodles. Their native cuisine had less of an emphasis on meat, as evidenced by dishes they introduced like [[pasta e fagioli]] and [[minestrone]], but the dishes they created in America often piled it on as a sign of wealth and newfound prosperity since for the first time even cheap cuts of it were affordable: the American recipe for [[Lasagne|lasagna]] is proof of this, as mostly it is derived from the Neapolitan version of the dish with large amounts of meat and cheese.

[[File:Frankfurter stand LOC det.4a13502.jpg|thumb|left|Carts selling frankfurters, the predecessor to [[hotdog]]s, in New York City circa 1906. The price is listed as &quot;3 cents each or 2 for 5 cents&quot;.]]
New York–style [[hot dog]]s came about with German speaking emigrants from Austria and Germany, particularly with the [[Frankfurter Würstchen|frankfurter sausage]] and the smaller [[Vienna sausage|wiener sausage]]; Jews would also contribute here by introducing the kosher version of these sausages, made of beef rather than pork.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Chowhound |url=https://www.chowhound.com/food-news/204752/the-history-of-the-kosher-hot-dog/ |title=What Makes a Hot Dog Kosher? |publisher=Chowhound |date=2019-07-01 |accessdate=2019-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; Today, the New York–style hot dog with [[sauerkraut]], mustard, and the optional cucumber pickle relish is such a part of the local fabric, that it is one of the favorite comestibles of New York City and both the pork and the beef versions are beloved. Hot dogs are a typical street food sold year round in all by the most inclement weather from thousands of pushcarts. As with all other stadiums in Major League Baseball they are an essential for [[New York Yankees]] and the [[New York Mets]] games though it is the local style of preparation that predominates without exception. Hot dogs are also the focus of a televised eating contest on the Fourth of July in Coney Island,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.cbsnews.com/news/nathans-famous-hot-dog-eating-contest-winners-joey-chestnut-miki-sudo-today-2018-07-04-live-updates/|title=Joey Chestnut devours record 74 hot dogs for 11th win at Nathan's Famous contest|website=www.cbsnews.com|language=en-US|access-date=2019-01-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; at [[Nathan's Famous]], one of the earliest hot dog stands opened in the United States in 1916 by [[Nathan Handwerker]], a Jewish man who emigrated from what is now Ukraine in 1912 and whose influence is felt today around the world: hot dogs are a staple of amusement parks 100 years later.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150915142527/http://www.filmjournal.com/reviews/film-review-famous-nathan |title=Film Review: Famous Nathan &amp;#124; FilmJournal International |publisher=Web.archive.org |date=2015-07-23 |accessdate=2019-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A summertime treat, [[Italian ice]], began its life as a sweeter adaptation of the Sicilain [[granita]] that was strictly lemon flavored and brought to New York and Philadelphia.  Its Hispanic counterpart, [[Piragua (food)|piragua]], is a common and evolving shaved ice treat brought to New York City by Puerto Ricans in the 1930s. Unlike the original dish which included flavors like tamarind, mango, coconut, piragua is evolving to include flavors like grape and cherry, fruits which are impossible to grow in the tropical Puerto Rican climate and get exported back to the island from New York.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.traveljewels.net/the-caribbean/puerto-rico-itinerary-five-days |title=How to Spend 5 Days in Puerto Rico — travelJewels |publisher=Traveljewels.net |date=2018-04-09 |accessdate=2019-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Taylor Ham]], a meat delicacy of [[New Jersey]], first appeared around the time of the Civil War and today is often served for breakfast with eggs and cheese on a kaiser roll, the bread upon which this is served was brought to the area by Austrians in the second half of the nineteenth century and is a very common roll for sandwiches at lunchtime, usually tipped with poppyseeds. This breakfast meat is generally known as pork roll in southern New Jersey and Philadelphia, and Taylor Ham in northern New Jersey.

[[File:Nighthawks by Edward Hopper 1942.jpg|thumb|''[[Nighthawks (painting)|Nighthawks]]'', a painting of a [[diner]], one type of eatery still common in the Mid-Atlantic. Each state of the region has its own signatures, and the range extends from the Canadian border in the North to Delaware Bay in the South.]]
Other dishes came about during the early 20th century and have much to do with delicatessen fare, set up largelyby Jewish immigrants from Eastern Europe who came to America incredibly poor, often illiterate in any other language but Hebrew, and often banished from mainstream society in their place of origin for centuries. Most often they were completely unable to partake in the outdoor food markets that the general population utilized as most of the food for sale was not kosher. The influence of European Jewry before their destruction in the [[The Holocaust|Holocaust]] on modern mid Atlantic cooking remains extremely strong and reinforced by their many descendants in the region.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Leah Koenig |url=https://www.seriouseats.com/jewish-food-new-york-queens-middle-eastern-bukharian-israeli-georgian |title=Beyond the Bagel: Exploring the Many Flavors of New York City’s Jewish Cuisine |publisher=Serious Eats |date=1970-01-01 |accessdate=2019-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; These currently form the largest concentration of Jews outside Tel Aviv and are very much integrated into the local mainstream of New York City in particular. American-style [[dill pickle|pickles]], now a common addition to hamburgers and sandwiches, were brought by Polish Jews,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://forward.com/food/399524/how-did-the-pickle-become-a-jewish-food-staple/ |title=Archived copy |access-date=September 11, 2019 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190618044158/https://forward.com/food/399524/how-did-the-pickle-become-a-jewish-food-staple/ |archive-date=June 18, 2019 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; and Austro-Hungarian Jews brought a recipe for almond horns that now is a common regional cookie, diverting from the original recipe in dipping the ends in dark chocolate.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://forward.com/articles/130404/yiddish-almond-horns/ |title=Archived copy |access-date=September 11, 2019 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150318032919/http://forward.com/articles/130404/yiddish-almond-horns/ |archive-date=March 18, 2015 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Amg_BAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA271&amp;lpg=PA271&amp;dq=jewish+almond+horn&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=812OOrGja0&amp;sig=ACfU3U2b47rzuzi3iyy56QGAXCiehxlEuQ&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=2ahUKEwjN2_D_nMnkAhWBMd8KHZjDD-g4ChDoATAJegQICRAB#v=onepage&amp;q=jewish%20almond%20horn&amp;f=false |title=Modern Jewish Cooking: Recipes &amp; Customs for Today's Kitchen - Leah Koenig - Google Books |publisher=Books.google.com |date=2015-03-17 |accessdate=2019-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; New York–style cheesecake has copious amounts of cream and eggs because animal [[rennet]] is not [[Kashrut|kosher]] and thus could not be sold to a large number of the deli's clientele. New York inherited its bagels and bialys from Jews, as well as Challah bread. [[Pastrami]] first entered the country via Romanian Jews, and is a feature of many sandwiches, often eaten on marble rye, a bread that was born in the mid-Atlantic. [[Whitefish salad]], [[smoked salmon|lox]], and [[matzoh ball soup]] are now standard fare made to order at local diners and delicatessens, but started their life as foods that made up a strict dietary code.  [[Rugelach]] cookies and [[hamentashen]] are sweet staples still sold to the general public, but came to New York over a century ago with Ashkenazi Jews along with [[Jewish rye]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Julia Moskin |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2017/01/10/dining/rye-grain-bread.html |title=Rye, a Grain With Ancient Roots, Is Rising Again - The New York Times |publisher=Nytimes.com |date= |accessdate=2019-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://shop.russanddaughters.com/#history-1-section|title=Russ &amp; Daughters official site|website=shop.russanddaughters.com |access-date=2019-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Buffalo - Wings at Airport Anchor Bar.jpg|thumb|220px|[[Buffalo wing]]s with [[blue cheese dressing]], served with lager beer.]]
Like other groups before them, many of their dishes passed into the mainstream enough so that they became part of diner fare by the end of the 20th century, a type of restaurant that is now more numerous in this region than any other and formerly the subject matter of artist [[Edward Hopper]]. In the past this sort of establishment was the haven of the short order cook grilling or frying simple foods for the working man. Today typical service would include staples from this large region like [[beef on weck]], [[Manhattan clam chowder]], the [[club sandwich]], [[Buffalo wings]], [[Cheesesteak|Philadelphia cheesesteak]], the [[black and white cookie]], [[shoofly pie]], [[turtle soup|snapper soup]], [[Smith Island cake]], [[blackout cake]], [[grape pie]], [[milkshake]]s, and the [[egg cream]], a vanilla or chocolate fountain drink with a frothy top and fizzy taste. As in Hopper's painting from 1942, many of these businesses are open 24 hours a day.

===Midwest===
{{Main|Cuisine of the Midwestern United States}}
Midwestern cuisine today is a very eclectic and odd mix and match of foodways. It covers everything from [[Kansas City-style barbecue|Kansas City-style]] [[barbecue]] to the [[Chicago-style hot dog]], though many of its classics are very simple, hearty fare. Mostly this region was completely untouched by European and American settlers until after the [[American Civil War]], and excepting [[Missouri]] and the heavily forested states near the Great Lakes, was mainly populated by nomadic tribes like the [[Sioux people|Sioux]], [[Osage people|Osage]], [[Arapaho people|Arapaho]], and [[Cheyenne]]. As with most other American Indians tribes, these tribes consumed the [[Three Sisters (agriculture)|Three Sisters]] of beans, maize, and squash, but also for thousands of years followed the herds of [[American bison|bison]] and hunted them first on foot and then, after the spread of mustangs from the Southwest due to the explorations of conquistadors, on horseback, typically using bow and arrow. There are [[buffalo jump]]s dating back nearly ten thousand years and several photographs and written accounts of trappers and homesteaders attesting to their dependence on the buffalo and to a lesser degree [[elk]]. After nearly wiping out the elk and bison to nothingness, this region has taken to raising bison alongside cattle for their meat and at an enormous profit, making them into burgers and steaks.

This region today comprises the states near the Great Lakes and also the Great Plains; much of it is prairie with a very flat terrain where the blue sky meets a neverending horizon. Winters are bitterly cold, windy, and wet. Often that means very harsh blizzards especially near the Great Lakes where Arctic winds blow off of Canada and where the ice on rivers and lakes freezes reliably thick enough for [[ice hockey]] to be a favorite pastime in the region and for ice fishing for [[northern pike|pike]], [[walleye]] and [[panfish]] to be ubiquitous in [[Minnesota]], [[Wisconsin]], and [[Michigan]], where they often there after become part of the local tradition of the [[fish fry]]. Population density is extremely low away from the Great Lakes and very small towns dominated by enormous farms are the rule with larger cities being the exception. [[Detroit]], [[Cleveland]], [[St. Louis]], [[Cincinnati]], [[Indianapolis]], [[Milwaukee]], [[Minneapolis]] and her twin sister city across the river [[St. Paul, Minnesota|St. Paul]] dominate the landscape in wealth and size, owing to their ties with manufacturing, finance, transportation, and meatpacking. Smaller places like [[Omaha, Nebraska|Omaha]], [[Tulsa, Oklahoma|Tulsa]], and [[Kansas City, Missouri|Kansas City]] make up local capitals, but the king of them all is [[Chicago]], third largest city in the country, on the shores of Lake Michigan.

[[File:Persimmon pudding (5180557664).jpg|thumb|Persimmon pudding. This is a dessert staple of the Midwest.]]
Non-American Indian settlement began in [[Illinois]], [[Minnesota]], [[Wisconsin]], [[Ohio]], [[Indiana]], and [[Michigan]] earlier than anywhere else in the region, and thus the food available here ranges from the sublime to the bizarre. As with all of the Midwest, the primary meats here are beef and poultry, since the Midwest has been raising [[Turkey (bird)|turkeys]], [[chicken]]s, and [[Goose|geese]] for over a hundred and fifty years; chickens have been so common for so long that the Midwest has several native breeds that are prized for both backyard farming and for farmer's markets, such as the [[Buckeye chicken|Buckeye]] and [[Wyandotte chicken|Wyandotte]]; one, Billina, appears as a character in the second book of the Oz series by [[L. Frank Baum]]. Favorite fruits of the region include a few native plants inherited from Native American tribes like the [[asimina triloba|pawpaw]] and the [[diospyros virginiana|American persimmons]] are also highly favored. As with the American South, pawpaws are the region's largest native fruit, about the size of a mango, and are often found growing wild in the region come September, whereafter they are made into preserves and cakes and command quite a price at farmer's markets in Chicago.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chicagotribune.com/lifestyles/sns-tns-bc-pawpaw-bread-20171002-story.html|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20171107020605/http://www.chicagotribune.com/lifestyles/sns-tns-bc-pawpaw-bread-20171002-story.html|archivedate=November 7, 2017|title=Let's eat: Pawpaw Bread with Toasted Walnuts - Chicago Tribune|date=2017-11-07|website=web.archive.org|access-date=2019-08-08|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[American persimmon]] is often smaller than it is Japanese cousin, about the size of a small plum, but in the Midwest and portions of the East it is the main ingredient in a steamed pudding called [[persimmon pudding]], topped with crème anglaise. Other crops inherited from the Native Americans include [[wild rice]], which grows on the banks of lakes and is a local favorite for fancy meals and today often used in stuffing for Thanksgiving.

Typical fruits of the region are cold weather crops. Once it was believed that the region had winters that were far too harsh for apple growing, but then a breeder in [[Minnesota]] came forth with the [[Wealthy (apple)|Wealthy apple]] and thence came forth the third most productive region for apple growing in the land, with local varieties comprising [[Wolf River (apple)|Wolf River]], Enterprise, [[Melrose (apple)|Melrose]], [[Paula Red]], [[Rome Beauty]], [[Honeycrisp]], and the [[Red Delicious]]. Cherries are important to [[Michigan]] and [[Wisconsin]] grows many [[Cranberry|cranberries]], a legacy of early-19th-century emigration of New England farmers. [[Crabapple]] jelly is a favorite condiment of the region.

The influence of German, Scandinavian, and Slavic peoples on the northern portion of the region is very strong; many of these emigrated to Wisconsin, Minnesota, Michigan, Ohio, and Illinois in the 19th century to take advantage of jobs in the meatpacking business as well as being homesteaders and tradesmen. Bratwurst is a very common sausage eaten at [[Tailgate party|tailgate parties]] for the [[Green Bay Packers]], [[Chicago Bears]], or [[Detroit Lions]] football teams and is often served boiled in lager beer with sauerkraut, different than many of the recipes currently found in Germany. Polish sausage, in particular a locally invented type of [[kielbasa]], is an essential for sporting events in Chicago: Chicago today has approximately 200,000 speakers of Polish and has had a population of that description for over a hundred years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chicagomag.com/Chicago-Magazine/The-312/January-2013/The-Geography-of-Chicagos-Second-Languages/|title=The Geography of Chicago’s Second Languages|website=Chicagomag.com|accessdate=August 2, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; When Poles came to Chicago and surrounding cities from Europe, they brought with them long ropes of kielbasa, cabbage rolls, and pierogis. Poles that left Poland after the fall of the Berlin Wall and the descendants of earlier immigrants still make all of the above and such comestibles are common in local diners and delis as result.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chicagobusiness.com/article/20160311/BLOGS09/160319972/take-the-pierogi-the-only-guide-to-polish-delis-youll-ever-need|title=Take the pierogi: The only guide to Polish delis you'll ever need|website=Chicagobusinesss.com|accessdate=August 2, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Today alongside the pierogi, the sausage is served on a long roll with mustard like a hot dog or as a [[Maxwell Street Polish]], a sandwich that has caramelized onions as an essential ingredient. In Cleveland, the same sausage is served in the form of the [[Polish Boy|Polish boy]]: this is a weird but tasty sandwich made of french fries, spicy barbecue sauce, and coleslaw; unlike cities in the East where the hot dog alone is traditional fans of the Cleveland Indians, Detroit Tigers, Chicago Cubs, and Milwaukee Brewers favor at least two or three different kinds of sausage sold in the little pushcarts outside the stadium; the hot dogs themselves tend to follow the Chicago style, which is loaded with mustard, and pickled vegetables. In Cincinnati, where the [[Cincinnati Reds]] play, the predilection for sausage has a competitor in [[Cincinnati chili]], invented by Macedonian immigrants: this bizarre but tasty dish includes spaghetti as its base, chili with a Mediterranean-inspired spice mix, and cheddar cheese; the chili itself is often a topping for local hot dogs at games.

In the Midwest and especially Minnesota,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.health.state.mn.us/divs/eh/food/fs/potluck.html|title=Potluck Events: Safe Food is Good Business - EH: Minnesota Department of Health|website=Health.state.mn.us|accessdate=August 2, 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170802163355/http://www.health.state.mn.us/divs/eh/food/fs/potluck.html|archive-date=August 2, 2017|url-status=dead|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; the tradition of the church potluck has become a gathering in which local foods reign, and so it has been since the era of the frontier: pioneers would often need to pool resources together to have a celebration in the 19th century and that simply never changed.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.thekitchn.com/sense-of-place-food-and-cuisin-58653|title=Sense of Place: Food and Cuisine of the Midwest|newspaper=The Kitchn|access-date=November 28, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nowhere is this more clear than with the [[hotdish]]: this is a type of casserole believed to have derived somehow from a Norwegian recipe, and it is usually topped with potatoes or tater tots.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.wisegeek.com/what-is-a-hotdish.htm#didyouknowout|title=What is a Hotdish? (with pictures)|newspaper=wiseGEEK|access-date=November 28, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Next to the hotdish at the potlucks usually is where the [[glorified rice]] is found: this is a dish made of a kind of rice pudding mixed with crushed pineapple and maraschino cherries. Next to that is the [[Booyah (stew)|booyah]], a thick soup made of a number or combinations of meat, vegetables, and seasonings that is meant to simmer on the stove for up to two days. [[Lefse]], traditionally a Scandinavian flatbread, has been handed down to descendants for over a hundred years and is common on the table. Behind that is the venison, a popular meat around the Great Lakes and often eaten in steaks, sandwiches, and crown roasts for special events.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mlive.com/news/grand-rapids/index.ssf/2016/10/arbys_to_offer_venison_sandwic.html|title=Arby's to offer venison sandwiches at 4 Michigan locations|website=Mlive.com|accessdate=August 2, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.twincities.com/2016/11/04/arbys-venison-sandwich-sells-out-fast-in-minnesota-wisconsin/|title=Arby’s venison sandwich sells out fast in Minnesota, Wisconsin|date=November 4, 2016|website=Twincities.com|accessdate=August 2, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Within Wisconsin, Minnesota and the Dakotas, [[tiger meat]], a dish similar to steak tartare, is common. Last on the table are the [[dessert bar]]s and most especially the [[Chocolate brownie|brownies]]: this confection was created originally in 1898 in Chicago and has gone on to become a global food and international favorite.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sweetoothdesign.com/cookie-brownie|title=Sweetooth Design Company - Food &amp; Design - Oakland, USA|website=Sweetoothdesign.com|accessdate=August 2, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Booyah spiced.jpg|thumb|Booyah. A popular chunky stew of the Midwest that is often served to large numbers of people.]]

Further South, barbecue has its own style in places in Kansas and St. Louis that are different to the South and the American West. Kansas City and St. Louis were and remain important hubs for the railroad that connected the plains with the Great Lakes and cities farther east, like Philadelphia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://trn.trains.com/~/media/images/railroad-reference/railroad-maps/kansas-city-tonnage.png?h=332&amp;la=en&amp;mw=600&amp;w=459|title=Kansas train map|website=Trn.trains.com|accessdate=2017-08-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the turn of the 19th century, the St. Louis area, Omaha, and Kansas City had huge stockyards, waystations for cattle and pigs on their way East to the cities of the coast and North to the Great Lakes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.missourilife.com/life/kansas-city-and-st.-louis-stockyards/|title=Wild West Week: Kansas City and St. Louis Stockyards|date=September 9, 2011|website=Missourilife.com|accessdate=August 2, 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170802133633/http://www.missourilife.com/life/kansas-city-and-st.-louis-stockyards/|archive-date=August 2, 2017|url-status=dead|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://digital.omahapubliclibrary.org/earlyomaha/buildings/stockyards.html |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2016-11-29 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170510121319/http://digital.omahapubliclibrary.org/earlyomaha/buildings/stockyards.html |archivedate=May 10, 2017 |df=mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; They all had large growing immigrant and migrant populations from Europe and the South respectively, so this region has developed unique styles of barbecue. [[St. Louis-style barbecue]] favors a heavy emphasis on a sticky sweet barbecue sauce. Its standbys include the [[pork steak]], a cut taken from the shoulder of the pig, grilled, and then slowly stewed in a pan over charcoal, crispy snoots, a cut from the cheek and nose of the pig that is fried up like cracklin and eaten dipped in sauce, pork [[spare ribs]], and a mix of either beer boiled bratwurst or grilled Italian derived sausage, flavored with fennel. Dessert is usually something like [[gooey butter cake]], invented in the city in the 1930s. [[Kansas City-style barbecue]] uses several different kinds of meat, more than most styles of American barbecue- turkey, mutton, pork, and beef just to name a few- but is distinct from St. Louis in that the barbecue sauce adds molasses in with the typical tomato based recipe and typically has a more tart taste. Traditionally, Kansas City uses a low-and-slow method of smoking the meat in addition to just stewing it in the sauce. It also favors using hickory wood for smoking and continual watering or layering of the sauce while cooking to form a glaze; with [[burnt ends]] this step is necessary to create the &quot;bark&quot; or charred outer layer of the brisket.

===Southern United States===
{{Main|Cuisine of the Southern United States}}
When referring to the American South as a region, typically it should indicate Southern Maryland and the states that were once part of the [[Confederate States of America|Old Confederacy]], with the dividing line between the East and West jackknifing about 100 miles west of Dallas, Texas, and mostly south of the old [[Mason–Dixon line]]. Cities found in this area include [[New Orleans]], [[Miami]], [[Atlanta]], [[Washington, D.C.]], [[Memphis, Tennessee|Memphis]], [[Charleston, South Carolina|Charleston]], and [[Charlotte, North Carolina|Charlotte]] with [[Houston|Houston, Texas]] being the largest. These states are much more closely tied to each other and have been part of US territory for much longer than states much farther west than East Texas, and in the case of food, the influences and cooking styles are strictly separated as the terrain begins to change to prairie and desert from bayou and hardwood forest.

This section of the country has some of the oldest known foodways in the land, with some recipes almost 400 years old. Native American influences are still quite visible in the use of [[cornmeal]] as an essential staple&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wrmills.com/indian-head-yellow-corn-meal|title=Indian Head Yellow Corn Meal Recipes - Wilkins Rogers Mills|publisher=Wrmills.com|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; and found in the Southern predilection for hunting wild game, in particular [[wild turkey]], [[white tailed deer|deer]], [[American woodcock|woodcock]], and various kinds of [[waterfowl]]; for example, coastal North Carolina is a place where hunters will seek [[tundra swan]] as a part of Christmas dinner; the original English and Scottish settlers would have rejoiced at this revelation owing to the fact that such was banned amongst the commoner class in what is now the United Kingdom, and naturally, their descendants have not forgotten.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wdtv.com/wdtv.cfm?func=view&amp;section=5-News&amp;item=Fall-Wild-Turkey-Season-Opens-Oct-11- |title=West Virginia Breaking News, Sports, Weather: WDTV.COM |publisher=Wdtv.com |accessdate=January 16, 2015 }}{{dead link|date=April 2017 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.deeranddeerhunting.com/blogs/southern-hunting-for-whitetail-deer|title=Southern Deer Hunting|work=Deer &amp; Deer Hunting - Whitetail Deer Hunting Tips|accessdate=January 16, 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150206235254/http://www.deeranddeerhunting.com/blogs/southern-hunting-for-whitetail-deer|archive-date=February 6, 2015|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; Native Americans also consumed [[turtle]]s and catfish, specifically the [[snapping turtle]] and [[blue catfish]]. Catfish are often [[noodling|caught with one's bare hands]], gutted, breaded, and fried to make a Southern variation on English [[fish and chips]] and turtles are turned into stews and soups.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.arkansasonline.com/news/2014/aug/03/snapping-turtle-makes-delicious-dinner/?f=threerivers|title=Snapping turtle makes for a delicious dinner|work=Arkansas Online|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.southernliving.com/food/kitchen-assistant/fried-catfish-recipes|title=Taste of the South: Fried Catfish|work=Southern Living|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Native American tribes of the region such as the Cherokee or Choctaw often cultivated or gathered local plants like [[asimina triloba|pawpaw]], [[passiflora incarnata|maypop]] and several sorts of [[squash (plant)|squashes]] and [[maize|corn]] as food&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tn.gov/state-symbols.shtml |title=State Symbols |publisher=Tn.gov |accessdate=January 16, 2015 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140625045751/http://www.tn.gov/state-symbols.shtml |archivedate=June 25, 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[spicebush]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.monticello.org/library/exhibits/lucymarks/gallery/spicebush.html|title=Lindera benzoin (spicebush)|publisher=Monticello.org|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[sassafras]] as spices,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.choctawschool.com/home-side-menu/iti-fabvssa/2012-articles/history-and-development-of-choctaw-food.aspx|title=History and development of Choctaw food - School of Choctaw Language|website=www.choctawschool.com|access-date=2019-08-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the aforementioned fruits are still cultivated as food in the South.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.southernmatters.com/native_edibles/|title=Native Edibles|publisher=Southernmatters.com|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Maize is to this day found in dishes for breakfast, lunch and dinner in the form of [[grits]], [[hoecakes]], baked [[cornbread]], and [[spoonbread]], and nuts like the [[hickory]], [[black walnut]] and [[pecan]] are commonly included in desserts and pastries as varied as [[mince pie]]s, [[pecan pie]], pecan rolls and [[honey bun]]s (both are types of [[sticky bun]]), and [[quick bread]]s, which were themselves invented in the South during the American Civil War. Peaches have been grown in this region since the 17th century and are a staple crop as well as a favorite fruit, with [[Cobbler (food)|peach cobbler]] being a signature dessert.

====Early history====
European influence began soon after the settlement of Jamestown in 1607 and the earliest recipes emerged by the end of the 17th century. Specific influences from Europe were quite varied, and remain traditional and essential to the modern cookery overall. German speakers often settled in the [[Piedmont (United States)|Piedmont]] on small farms from the coast, and invented an American delicacy that is now nationally beloved, [[apple butter]], based on their recipe for apfelkraut, and later introduced [[red cabbage]] and [[rye]]. From the British Isles, an enormous amount of influence was bestowed upon the South, specifically foodways found in 17th- and 18th-century [[Ulster]], the borderlands between England and Scotland, the [[Scottish Highlands]], portions of [[Wales]], the [[West Midlands (region)|West Midlands]] and [[Black Country]]. Settlers bound for America fled the tumult of the [[English Civil War|Civil War]], [[Ulster Plantation|Ulster]] and the [[Highland Clearances]]. Often ships' manifests show their belongings nearly always included cookpots or [[bakestone]]s and seed stock for plants like [[peach]]es, [[plum]]s, and [[apple]]s to grow orchards which they planted in their hundreds. Each group brought foods and ideas from their respective regions.

Settlers from Ireland and Scotland were well known for creating [[Peatreek|peatreak]] and [[Poitín (band)|poitín]], strong hard liquor based on fermenting potatoes or barley. In time they came up with a method for distilling a corn mash with [[added sugar]] and aging in charred barrels made of select hardwoods, which created a whiskey with a high proof. This gave birth to [[American whiskey]] and [[Kentucky bourbon]], and its cousins [[moonshine]] and [[Everclear (alcohol)|Everclear]].

Closer to the coast, 18th-century recipes for English [[trifle]] turned into [[tipsy cake]]s, replacing the sherry with whiskey and their recipe for [[pound cake]], brought to the South around the same time, still works with American baking units: 1 pound sugar, one pound eggs, one pound butter, one pound flour.

====Common features====
Pork is the popular choice in 80% of Southern style barbecue and features in other preparations like sausages and sandwiches. For most Southerners in the [[History of the Southern United States#Antebellum era (1781–1860)|antebellum period]], corn and pork were staples of the diet.&lt;ref name=&quot;Warren2007&quot;/&gt; [[Country sausage]] is an ingredient in the Southern breakfast dish of [[biscuits and gravy]]. [[Country ham]] is often served for breakfast and cured with salt or sugar and hickory-smoked.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://pubs.ext.vt.edu/458/458-223/458-223.html#|title=Dry Curing Virginia-Style Ham - Publications and Educational Resources - Virginia Tech|date=December 18, 2012|publisher=Oubs.ext.vt.edu|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Accompanying many meals is the southern style fluffy [[biscuit (bread)|biscuit]], where the leavening agent is [[sodium bicarbonate|baking soda]] and often includes [[buttermilk]], and for breakfast they often accompany country ham, grits, and scrambled eggs.

====Desserts====
Desserts in the South tend to be quite rich and very much a legacy of entertaining to impress guests, since a Southern housewife was (and to a degree still is) expected to show her hospitality by laying out as impressive a banquet as she is able to manage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://m.timesdispatch.com/entertainment-life/traits-of-a-true-southern-woman/article_37092461-fec6-5a6f-b6fb-72da162d360c.html?mode=jqm|title=Traits of a true Southern woman|work=Richmond.com|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Desserts are vast and encompass [[Lane cake]], [[sweet potato pie]], [[peach cobbler]], [[pecan pie]], [[hummingbird cake]], [[Jefferson Davis pie]], [[peanut brittle]], [[coconut cake]], [[fritter|apple fritters]], peanut cookies, [[Moravian spice cookies]], [[chess pie]], [[doberge cake]], [[Lady Baltimore cake]], [[bourbon ball]]s, and [[caramel cake]]. American style sponge cakes tend to be the rule rather than the exception as is American style buttercream, a place where Southern baking intersects with the rest of the United States. Nuts like pecan and hickory tend to be revered as garnishes for these desserts, and make their way into local bakeries as fillings for chocolates.

====Cajun cuisine====
[[File:Shrimp_gumbo.jpg|thumbnail|Shrimp [[gumbo]] is a popular [[Cajun cuisine|Cajun]] and [[Louisiana Creole cuisine|Creole]] dish.]]
In Louisiana, cooking methods have more in common with rustic French cuisines of the 17th and 18th century than anything ever found at the French court in Versailles or the bistros of 19th- and 20th-century Paris; this is especially true of [[Cajun cuisine]].

[[Cajun French]] is more closely related to dialects spoken in Northern [[Maine]], [[New Brunswick]], and to a lesser degree [[Haiti]] than anything spoken in modern France, and likewise their terminology, methodology, and culture concerning food is much more closely related to the styles of these former French colonies even today. Unlike other areas of the South, Cajuns were and still are largely Catholics and thus much of what they eat is seasonal; for example pork is an important component of the Cajun ''boucherie'' (a large community event where the hog is butchered, prepared with a fiery spice mix, and eaten snout to tail) but it is never consumed in the five weeks of Lent, when such would be forbidden. Cajun cuisine tends to focus on what is locally available, historically because Cajuns were often poor, illiterate, independent farmers and not plantation owners but today it is because such is deeply imbedded in local culture. [[Boudin]] is a type of sausage found only in this area of the country, and it is often by far more spicy than anything found in France or Belgium. [[Chaudin]] is unique to the area, and the method of cooking is comparable to the Scottish dish haggis: the stuffing includes onions, rice, bell peppers, spices, and pork sewn up in the stomach of a pig, and served in slices piping hot. [[Procambarus clarkii|Crayfish]] are a staple of the Cajun grandmother's cookpot, as they are abundant in the bayous of Southern Louisiana and a main source of livelihood, as are [[blue crab]]s, [[shrimp]], corn on the cob, and red potatoes, since these are the basic ingredients of the Louisiana crawfish boil.

[[File:CreoleFood.jpg|thumb|left|Dishes typical of [[Louisiana Creole cuisine]]]]
New Orleans has been the capital of Creole culture since before Louisiana was a state; this culture is that of the colonial French and Spanish that evolved in the city of New Orleans, which was and still is quite distinct from the rural culture of Cajuns and dovetails with what would have been eaten in antebellum Louisiana plantation culture long ago. Cooking to impress and show one's wealth was a staple of Creole culture, which often mixed French, Spanish, Italian, German, African, Caribbean and Native American cooking methods, producing rich dishes like [[Oysters Bienville|oysters bienville]], [[pompano en papillote]], and even the [[muffaletta]] sandwich. However, [[Louisiana Creole cuisine]] tends to diverge from the original ideas brought to the region in ingredients: [[profiterole]]s, for example, use a near identical [[choux pastry]] to that which is found in modern Paris but often use vanilla or chocolate ice cream rather than custard as the filling, [[praline]]s nearly always use [[pecan]] and not almonds, and [[bananas foster]] came about when New Orleans was a key port for the import of bananas from the Caribbean Sea.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.neworleansonline.com/neworleans/cuisine/traditionalfoods/bananasfoster.html|title=Bananas Foster|publisher=Neworleansonline.com|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Gumbos tend to be thickened with [[okra]], or the leaves of the [[sassafras albidum|sassafrass tree]]. Andouille is often used, but not the andouille currently known in France, since French andouille uses tripe whereas Louisiana andouille is made from a [[Boston butt]], usually inflected with pepper flakes, and smoked for hours over pecan wood. Other ingredients that are native to Louisiana and not found in the cuisine of modern France would include rice, which has been a staple of both Creole and Cajun cooking for generations, and sugarcane, which has been grown in Louisiana since the early 1800s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.usarice.com/doclib/188/219/3677.PDF |format=PDF |title=Louisiana Rice |publisher=Usarice.com |accessdate=January 16, 2015 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20141222045727/http://www.usarice.com/doclib/188/219/3677.PDF |archivedate=December 22, 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Passiflora incarnata 004.JPG|thumbnail|The maypop plant]]
Ground cayenne pepper is a key spice of the region, as is the meat of the [[American alligator]], something settlers learned from the Choctaws and Houma. The maypop plant has been a favorite of Southerners for 350 years; it gives its name to the Ocoee River in Tennessee, a legacy of the Cherokees, and in Southern Louisiana it is known as liane de grenade, indicating its consumption by Cajuns. It is a close relative of the commercial [[passiflora edulis|passionfruit]], similar in size, and is a common plant growing in gardens all over the South as a source of fresh summertime fruit.

====African American influences====
African American influences came with slaves from [[Ghana]], [[Benin]], [[Mali]], [[Democratic Republic of the Congo|Congo]], [[Angola]], [[Sierra Leone]], [[Nigeria]], and other portions of West Africa, and the mark African Americans and their descendants have made on Southern food is extremely strong today and an essential addition to the Southern table. Crops like [[okra]], [[sorghum]], [[sesame seeds]], [[eggplant]], and many different kinds of [[melon]]s were brought with them from West Africa along with the incredibly important introduction of rice to the [[Carolinas]] and later to [[Texas]] and [[Louisiana]], whence it became a staple grain of the region and still remains a staple today, found in dishes like [[Hoppin John]], purloo, and [[Charleston red rice]]. Like the poorer indentured servants that came to the South, slaves often got the leftovers of what was slaughtered for the consumption of the master of the plantation and so many recipes had to be adapted for offal, like [[pig's ear (food)|pig's ears]] and [[fatback]]s&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/?id=xhpBsIa5yqEC&amp;pg=PA97&amp;lpg=PA97&amp;dq=black+slaves+offal|title=What the Slaves Ate|publisher=Books.google.com|accessdate=January 16, 2015|isbn=9780313374975|year=2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; though other methods encouraged low and slow methods of cooking to tenderize the tougher cuts of meat, like braising, smoking, and pit roasting, the last of which was a method known to West Africans in the preparation of roasting goat.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.smithsonianmag.com/arts-culture/food-historian-reckons-black-roots-southern-food-180964285/|title=Food Historian Reckons With the Black Roots of Southern Food|last=Mansky|first=Jackie|website=Smithsonian|language=en|access-date=2019-01-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Florida cuisine====
Certain portions of the South often have their own distinct subtypes of cuisine owing to local history and landscape, i.e. [[Cajun cuisine]], Floridian cuisine, for example, has a distinct way of cooking that includes ingredients her other Southern sisters do not use, especially points south of Tampa and Orlando. The Spanish Crown had control of the state until the early 19th century and used the southern tip as an outpost to guard the [[Spanish Main]] beginning in the 1500s, but Florida kept and still maintains ties with the [[Caribbean Sea]], including the [[Bahamas]] [[Haiti]], [[Cuba]], [[Puerto Rico]], the [[Dominican Republic]], and [[Jamaica]]. South of Tampa, there are and have been for a long time many speakers of [[Caribbean Spanish]], [[Haitian French]], [[Jamaican Patois]], and [[Haitian Creole]] and each Caribbean culture has a strong hold on cooking methods and spices in Florida. In turn, each mixes and matches with the [[foodways]] of the Seminole tribe and Anglophone settlers. Thus, for almost 200 years, Floridian cooking has had a more tropical flavor than any other Southern state. [[Allspice]], a spice originally from [[Jamaica]], is an ingredient found in spice mixes in summer barbecues along with [[ginger]], [[garlic]], [[Scotch bonnet|scotch bonnet peppers]], sea salt, and nutmeg; in Floridian cooking this is often a variant of Jamaican jerk spice. Coconuts are grown in the areas surrounding Miami and are shipped in daily through its port for consumption of the milk, meat, and water of the coconut. Bananas are not just the yellow Cavendish variety found in supermarkets across America: in Florida they are available as bananitos, colorados, plátanos, and maduros. The first of these is a tiny miniature banana only about 4-5 inches (10–13&amp;nbsp;cm) in length and it is sweet. The second has a red peel and an apple like after taste, and the third and fourth are used as a starch on nearly every Caribbean island as a side dish, baked or fried: all of the above are a staple of Florida outdoor markets when in season and all have been grown in the Caribbean for almost 400 years. Mangoes are grown as a backyard plant in Southern Florida and otherwise are a favorite treat coming in many different shapes in sizes from ''[[Nam Doc Mai]]'', brought to Florida after the Vietnam War, to ''[[Madame Francis]]'', a mango from Haiti. [[Sweetsop]] and [[soursop]] are popular around Miami, but nearly unheard of in other areas of the South.

Citrus is a major crop of Florida, and features at every breakfast table and every market with the height of the season near the first week of January. Hamlin oranges are the main cultivar planted, and from this crop the rest of the United States and to a lesser extent Europe gets orange juice. Other plantings would include [[grapefruits]], [[tangerine]]s, [[clementine|clementine oranges]], [[Lime (fruit)|limes]], and even a few more rare ones, like [[cara cara navel]]s, [[tangelo]]s, and the Jamaican [[Ugli fruit]]. [[Tomato]]es, [[bell pepper]]s, [[Habanero|habanero peppers]], and figs, especially taken from the [[Ficus aurea|Florida strangler fig]], complete the produce menu. [[Blue crab]], [[Queen conch|conch]], [[Florida stone crab]], [[red drum]], [[common dolphinfish|dorado]], and [[marlin]]s tend to be local favorite ingredients. Dairy is available in this region, but it is less emphasized due to the year round warmth. Traditional [[key lime pie]], a dessert from the islands off the coast of Miami, is made with [[condensed milk]] to form the custard with the eye wateringly tart limes native to the [[Florida Keys]] in part because milk would spoil in an age before refrigeration. Pork in this region tends to be roasted in methods similar to those found in Puerto Rico and Cuba, owing to mass emigration from those countries in the 20th century, especially in the counties surrounding Miami.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://southfloridagaynews.com/outEATS/pernil-al-horno-roasted-pork-shoulder.html|title=Pernil Al Horno (Roasted Pork Shoulder)|author=Guest Column|work=South Florida Gay News|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Orange blossom honey is a specialty of the state, and is widely available in farmer's markets.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thomashoney.com/honey.html|title=Honey - from Thomas Honey Company|website=Thomashoney.com|accessdate=January 16, 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141231063142/http://www.thomashoney.com/honey.html|archive-date=December 31, 2014|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Panulirus argus|Caribbean lobster]] is a favorite special meal eagerly sought after by Floridians as it is found as far north as Fort Meyers: spear diving and collecting them from reefs in the Florida Keys and near rocky shoals is a common practice of local scuba divers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.scubadiving.com/bagging-bug-how-to-have-successful-lobster-hunting-season|title=Bagging the Bug: How to Have A Successful Lobster-Hunting Season|website=Scuba Diving|language=en|access-date=2019-01-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Other small game====
[[Ptarmigan]], [[grouse]], [[crow]] blackbirds, dove, ducks and other game fowl are consumed in the United States. In the American state of [[Arkansas]], [[American beaver|beaver]] tail stew is consumed in Cotton town.&lt;ref name=&quot;news.nationalgeographic.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.nationalgeographic.com/2015/12/151220-american-food-cuisine-local-state-ngbooktalk/|title=What’s Best, Worst, and Most Weird About American Food|date=December 20, 2015|website=Nationalgeographic.com|accessdate=August 12, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Tree squirrel#In the US|Squirrel]], [[Cooning|raccoon]], [[Virginia opossum|possum]], [[bear]], [[muskrat]], [[chipmunk]], [[skunk]], [[groundhog]], [[pheasant]], [[armadillo]] and [[rabbit]] are also consumed in the United States.

===Cuisine in the West===
{{Main|Cuisine of the Western United States}}
Cooking in the American West gets its influence from Native American and Hispanophone cultures, as well as later settlers that came in the 19th century: Texas, for example, has some influence from Germany in its choice of barbecue by using sausages. Another instance can be found in the Northwestern region, which encompasses [[Oregon]], [[Washington (state)|Washington]], and Northern California. All of the aforementioned rely on local seafood and a few classics of their own. In [[New Mexico]], [[Colorado]], [[Nevada]], [[Arizona]], [[Utah]], [[West Texas]], and [[Southern California]], Mexican flavors and influences are extremely common, especially from the Mexican states of [[Chihuahua (state)|Chihuahua]], [[Baja California]], and [[Sonora, Mexico|Sonora]].

====Northwest====
The Pacific Northwest as a region generally includes [[Alaska]] and the state of Washington near the Canada–US border and terminates near [[Sacramento, California]]. Here, the terrain is mostly temperate rainforest on the Coast mixed with pine forest as one approaches the Canada–US border inland. One of the core favorite foodstuffs is [[Oncorhynchus|Pacific salmon]], native to many of the larger rivers of the area and often smoked or grilled on cedar planks. In [[Alaska]], wild game like [[Lagopus|ptarmigan]] and [[moose]] meat feature extensively since much of the state is wilderness. Fresh fish like [[Rainbow trout|steelhead trout]], [[Pacific cod]], [[Pacific halibut]], and [[pollock]] are fished for extensively and feature on the menu of many restaurants, as do a plethora of fresh berries and vegetables, like Cameo apples from [[Washington (state)|Washington]] state, the headquarters of the U.S. [[apple]] industry, [[cherry|cherries]] from [[Oregon]], [[blackberry|blackberries]], and [[marionberry|marionberries]], a feature of many pies. [[Hazelnut]]s are grown extensively in this region and are a feature of baking, such as in chocolate hazelnut pie, an Oregon favorite,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oregonlive.com/mix/index.ssf/dessert-recipes/chocolate_bourbon_hazelnut_pie.html|title=Chocolate Bourbon Hazelnut Pie|publisher=Oregonlive.com|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Almond Roca]] is a local candy.

This region is also heavily dominated by some notable wineries producing a high quality product.

Like its counterpart on the opposite coast to the East, there is a grand variety of shellfish in this region. [[Geoduck]]s are a native species of giant clam that have incredibly long necks, and they are eaten by the bucket full as well as shipped to Asia for millions of dollars as they are believed to be an [[aphrodisiac]]. [[Tresus|Gaper clams]] are a favorite food, often grilled or steamed in a sauce, as is the native California [[abalone]], which although protected as a food source is a traditional foodway predating settlement by whites and today features heavily in the cooking of fine restaurants as well as in home cooking, in mirin-flavored soups (the influence of Japanese cooking is strong in the region) noodle dishes and on the barbecue. [[Ostrea lurida|Olympia oysters]] are served on the half shell as well as the [[Pacific oyster|Kumamoto oyster]], introduced by Japanese immigrants and a staple at dinner as an appetizer. [[California mussel]]s are a delicacy of the region, and have been a feature of the cooking for generations: there is evidence that Native American tribes consumed them up and down the California coast for centuries in their masses.

Crabs are a delicacy, and included in this are [[Alaskan king crab]], [[cancer productus|red crab]], [[Metacarcinus anthonyi|yellow crab]], and [[Dungeness crab]]. Californian and Oregonian sportsmen pursue the last three extensively using hoop nets, and prepare them in a multitude of ways. Alaska king crab, able to get up to 10&amp;nbsp;kg, is often served steamed for a whole table with lemon butter sauce or put in chunks of salad with avocado, and native crabs are the base of dishes like the [[California roll]], [[cioppino]], a tomato based fisherman's stew, and [[Crab Louie]], another kind of salad native to San Francisco. Favorite grains are mainly wheat, and the region is known for [[Sourdough|sourdough bread]]. Cheeses of the region include [[Humboldt Fog]], [[Cougar Gold cheese|Cougar Gold]] and [[Teleme cheese|Teleme]].

====Southwest and Southern California====
{{Main|Cuisine of the Southwestern United States}}
[[File:Flickr elisart 324248450--Beef and chicken fajitas.jpg|thumb|Mixed beef and chicken [[fajita]] ingredients, served on a hot iron skillet]]
The states of the Four Corners ([[Arizona]], [[New Mexico]], [[Colorado]], and [[Utah]]) plus [[Nevada]], [[Southern California]], and [[West Texas]] make up a large chunk of the United States and there is a distinct Hispanic accent to the cookery here, with each having cultural capitals in [[Albuquerque]], [[Denver]], [[Las Vegas]], [[Los Angeles]], [[Phoenix, Arizona|Phoenix]], [[Salt Lake City]], [[Santa Fe, New Mexico|Santa Fe]], [[San Francisco, California|San Francisco]], and [[Tucson, Arizona|Tucson]]. For centuries, prior to California's statehood in the 1850s, it was part of the [[Spanish Empire]], namely [[Alta California]] (modern [[California]]), [[Santa Fe de Nuevo México]] (modern [[New Mexico]]), and [[Spanish Texas|Tejas]] (modern [[Texas]]). Today it is home of a large population of [[Native Americans in the United States|Native Americans]], [[Hispanos]], descendants of the [[American frontier]], [[Asian Americans]], and immigrants from [[Mexico]] and [[Latin America]]; California, New Mexico, and Texas continue to hold their unique identities which is reflected in their distinct regional cuisines, the multiple [[Cuisine of California|cuisines of California]], [[New Mexican cuisine]], [[Texan cuisine]], and [[Tex-Mex]]. [[Spanish language|Spanish]] is a commonly spoken secondary language here; the state of [[New Mexico]] has its own distinct [[New Mexican Spanish|dialect]].

With the exception of Southern California, the signature meat is [[beef]], since this is one of the two regions in which cowboys lived and modern cattle ranchers still eke out their living today.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://abcnews.go.com/US/nevada-cattle-rancher-wins-range-war-federal-government/story?id=23302610|title=Nevada Cattle Rancher Wins 'Range War' With Federal Government - ABC News|author=ABC News|work=ABC News|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.utahcattlemen.org |title=Welcome to the Utah Cattlemen's Association |publisher=Utahcattlemen.org |accessdate=January 16, 2015 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20141218091907/https://utahcattlemen.org/ |archivedate=December 18, 2014 |df=mdy }}&lt;/ref&gt; High quality beefstock is a feature that has been present in the region for more than 200 years and the many cuts of beef are unique to the United States. These cuts of meat are different from the related Mexican cuisine over the border in that certain kind of offal, like ''lengua'' (tongue) ''cabeza'' (head) and ''tripas'' (tripe) are considered less desirable and are thus less emphasized. Typical cuts would include the ribs, brisket, sirloin, flank steak, skirt steak, and t-bone.

[[File:Chili with garnishes and tortilla chips.jpg|thumb|[[Chili con carne]], a typical Tex-Mex dish with garnishes and tortilla chips]]
Historically, Spanish settlers that came to the region found it completely unsuitable to the mining operations that much older settlements in [[Mexico]] had to offer as the technology of the age was not yet advanced enough to get at the silver that would later be found in the region. They had no knowledge of the gold to be discovered in California, something nobody would find until 1848, and knew even less about the silver in Nevada, something nobody would find until after the [[American Civil War|Civil War]]. Instead, in order to make the pueblos prosper, they adapted the old rancho system of places like [[Andalusia]] in [[Spain]] and brought the earliest beefstock, among these were breeds that would go feral and become the [[Texas longhorn]], and [[Navajo-Churro sheep]], still used as breeding stock because they are easy to keep and well adapted to the extremely arid and hot climate, where temperatures easily exceed 38&amp;nbsp;°C.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://doublehelixranch.com/History.html|title=History of Texas Longhorns|author=David Hillis|publisher=Doublehelixranch.com|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Later, cowboys learned from their management practices, many of which still stand today, like the practical management of stock on horseback using the [[Western saddle]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.digitalhistory.uh.edu/disp_textbook.cfm?smtID=2&amp;psid=3573|title=Digital History|publisher=Digitalhistory.uh.edu|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Fresh batch of Biscochitos, Albuquerque NM.jpg|thumb|[[Biscochitos]], the [[List of New Mexico state symbols#food|state cookie]] of [[New Mexico]]]]
Likewise, settlers learned the cooking methods of those who came before and local tribes as well: for example, portions of [[Arizona]] and [[New Mexico]] still use the aforementioned beehive shaped clay contraption called an ''[[horno]]'', an outdoor wood fired oven both Native American tribes like the [[Navajo people|Navajo]] and Spaniards used for roasting meat, maize, and baking bread.&lt;ref&gt;Green, Rayna (1999). The British Museum Encyclopedia of Native North America. London: British Museum Press. p. 4. {{ISBN|0-253-33597-3}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Other meats that see frequent use in this region are [[cervus canadensis|elk]] meat, a favorite in crown roasts and burgers, and nearer the Mexican border [[rattlesnake]], often skinned and stewed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fitday.com/fitness-articles/nutrition/healthy-eating/the-nutrition-of-snake.html|title=The Nutrition of Snake|publisher=Fitday.com|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E1DE123EF931A35753C1A9679D8B63|title=How Does Rattlesnake Taste?|date=October 2, 2011|publisher=Query.nytimes.com|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The taste for alcohol in this region tends toward light and clean flavors found in [[tequila]], a staple of this region since the days of the Wild West and a staple in the bartender's arsenal for cocktails, especially in Las Vegas. In Utah, a state heavily populated by [[Mormons]], alcohol is frowned upon by the [[Church of Jesus Christ of Latter Day Saints]] but still available in area bars in Salt Lake City, mainly consumed by the populations of Catholics and other Protestant denominations living there.

Introduction of agriculture was limited prior to the 20th century and the development of better irrigation techniques, but included the addition of [[peach]]es, a crop still celebrated by Native American tribes like the [[Havasupai]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.visitarizona.com/things-to-do/havasupai-tribe-supai-az |title=Havasupai Tribe |publisher=Visitarizona.com |accessdate=January 16, 2015 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150219010128/http://www.visitarizona.com/things-to-do/havasupai-tribe-supai-az |archivedate=February 19, 2015 |df=mdy }}&lt;/ref&gt; and oranges; today in [[Arizona]], [[Texas]], and [[New Mexico]] the favored orange today is the Moro [[blood orange]], which often finds its way into the local cuisine, like cakes and marmalade.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.texasmonthly.com/story/blood-orange-marmalade|title=Blood Orange Marmalade|date=June 1, 2010|work=Texas Monthly|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.texasmonthly.com/story/halloween-blood-orange-cake|title=Halloween Blood Orange Cake|date=October 31, 2013|work=Texas Monthly|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Pine nut]]s are a particular regional specialty and feature often in fine dining and cookies; indeed in Nevada the Native American tribes that live there are by treaty given rights to exclusive harvest.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2011/11/21/pine-nuts|title=Pine Nuts|date=November 21, 2011|work=The New Yorker|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; From Native Americans, Westerners learned the practice of eating cactus fruit from the myriad species of [[opuntia]] that occupy the [[Chihuahuan Desert|Chihuahuan]], [[Sonoran Desert|Sonoran]], and [[Mojave Desert|Mojave desert]] lands. In California, Spanish missionaries brought with them the [[mission fig]]: today this fruit is a delicacy.

[[File:New Mexico green chile.jpg|thumb|left|upright|[[New Mexico green chile]] is a staple of [[New Mexican cuisine]].]]
Cuisine in this region tends to have certain key ingredients: [[tomato]]es, [[onion]]s, [[black turtle bean|black beans]], [[pinto bean]]s, [[rice]], [[bell pepper]]s, [[chile pepper]]s, and [[cheese]], in particular [[Monterey Jack]], invented in Southern California in the 19th century and itself often further altered into pepper Jack where spicy [[jalapeño]] peppers are incorporated into the cheese to create a smoky taste. Chili peppers play an important role in the cuisine, with a few native to the region (such as the [[New Mexico chile]] pepper, knows as [[Hatch, New Mexico]] and [[Anaheim, California|Anaheim]]); these still grown by [[Hispanos of New Mexico]] and [[Pueblo]]. In New Mexico, chile is eaten on a variety of foods, such as the green chile cheeseburger, made popular by fast food chains such as [[Blake's Lotaburger]]. Indeed, even national fast food chains operating in the state, such as [[McDonald's]], offer locally grown chile on many of their menu items. In the 20th century a few more recent additions have arrived like the [[poblano pepper]], [[Capsicum pubescens|rocoto pepper]], [[ghost pepper]], [[thai chili pepper]], and Korean pepper, the last three especially when discussing Southern California and its large population from East and South Asia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.clovegarden.com/ingred/chili.html|title=Chilis &amp; Other Peppers|publisher=Clovegarden.com|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://articles.latimes.com/2009/sep/23/food/fo-calcook23|title=New Mexico's green chile, the real deal|work=Los Angeles Times|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Cornbread]] is consumed in this area, however the recipe differs from ones in the East in that the batter is cooked in a cast iron skillet. Outdoor cooking is popular and still utilizes an old method settlers brought from the East with them, in which a cast iron [[dutch oven]] is covered with the coals of the fire and stacked or hung from a tripod: this is different from the earthenware pots of Mexico. Tortillas are still made the traditional way in this area and form an important component of the spicy [[breakfast burrito]], which contains ham, eggs, and salsa or [[pico de gallo]]. They also comprise the regular [[burrito]], which contains any combination of marinated meats, vegetables, and piquant chilis; The smothered burrito, often both containing and topped with New Mexico chile sauces; the [[quesadilla]], a much loved grilled dish where cheese and other ingredients are stuffed between two tortillas and served by the slice, and the steak [[fajita]], where sliced skirt steak sizzles in a skillet with caramelized onions.

[[File:Goettanachos.jpg|thumb|left|[[Nachos]] with cheese]]
Unlike Mexico, tortillas of this region also may incorporate vegetable matter like spinach into the flatbread dough to make [[wrap (sandwich)|wraps]], which were invented in Southern California. Food here tends to use pungent spices and condiments, typically chili verde sauce, various kinds of [[hot sauce]], [[sriracha sauce]], [[chili powder]], [[cayenne pepper]], [[white pepper]], [[cumin]], [[paprika]], [[onion powder]], [[thyme]] and [[black pepper]]. Nowhere is this fiery mix of spice more evident than in the dishes [[chili con carne]], a meaty stew, and [[cowboy beans]], both of which are a feature of regional cookoffs. Southern California has several additions like [[five spice powder]], [[rosemary]], [[curry powder]], [[kimchi]], and [[lemongrass]], with many of these brought by recent immigration to the region and often a feature of Southern California's fusion cuisine, popular in fine dining.

In Texas, the local barbecue is often entirely made up of beef [[brisket]] or large rib racks, where the meat is seasoned with a [[spice rub]] and cooked over coals of [[mesquite]], and in other portions of the state they smoke their meat and peppery sausages over high heat using [[pecan]], [[apple]], and [[oak]] and served it with a side of pickled vegetables, a legacy of German and Czech settlers of the late 1800s. California is home to [[Santa Maria-style barbecue]], where the spices involved generally are [[black pepper]], [[paprika]], and [[garlic salt]], and grilled over the coals of [[coast live oak]].

[[File:Chimichanga in Bremen 7095.JPG|thumb|A [[chimichanga]]]]
Native American additions may include [[Frybread|Navajo frybread]] and [[corn on the cob]], often roasted on the grill in its husk. A typical accompaniment or appetizer of all these states is the tortilla chip, which sometimes includes cornmeal from cultivars of corn that are blue or red in addition to the standard yellow of sweetcorn, and is served with [[Salsa (sauce)|salsa]] of varying hotness. Tortilla chips also are an ingredient in the Tex Mex dish [[nacho]]s, where these chips are loaded with any combination of ground beef, melted Monterey Jack, cheddar, or Colby cheese, [[guacamole]], [[sour cream]], and salsa, and Texas usually prefers a version of [[potato salad]] as a side dish. For alcohol, a key ingredient is [[tequila]]: this spirit has been made on both sides of the US-Mexican border for generations,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ianchadwick.com/tequila/18-19th%20centuries.htm|title=In Search of the Blue Agave: Tequila History - 18th-19th Centuries|publisher=Ianchadwick.com|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; and in modern cuisine it is a must have in a bartender's arsenal as well as an addition to dishes for sauteeing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.closetcooking.com/2008/06/tequila-lime-shrimp.html?m=1|title=Closet Cooking: Tequila Lime Shrimp|work=Closet Cooking|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Southern California is located more towards the coast and has had more contact with immigration from the [[West Pacific]] and [[Baja California]], in addition to having the international city of [[Los Angeles]] as its capital. Here, the prime mode of transportation is by car. Drive through fast food was invented in this area, but so was the concept of the gourmet burger movement, giving birth to chains like [[In-N-Out Burger]], with many variations of burgers including chili, multiple patties, avocado, special sauces, and angus or wagyu beef; common accompaniments include thick milkshakes in various flavors like mint, chocolate, peanut butter, vanilla, strawberry, and mango. Smoothies are a common breakfast item made with fresh fruit juice, yogurt, and crushed ice. Agua fresca, a drink originated by Mexican immigrants, is a common hot weather beverage sold in many supermarkets and at mom and pop stands, available in citrus, watermelon, and strawberry flavors; the California version usually served chilled without grain in it.

[[File:Pork_machaca_with_eggs,_served_with_potatoes_and_salsa_and_wrapped_in_a_tortilla-_2013-04-07_13-31.jpg|thumbnail|[[Machaca]] with pork, eggs, and potatoes wrapped in a tortilla, served with salsa]]
The weather in Southern California is such that the temperature rarely drops below 12&amp;nbsp;°C in winter, thus, sun loving crops like [[pistachio]]s, [[kiwifruit]], [[avocado]]es, [[Strawberry|strawberries]], and [[tomato]]es are staple crops of the region, the last often dried in the sun and a feature of salads and sandwiches. [[Olive oil]] is a staple cooking oil of the region and has been since the days of [[Junípero Serra]]; today the [[mission olive]] is a common tree growing in a Southern Californian's back garden; as a crop olives are increasingly a signature of the region along with [[Valencia orange]]s and [[Meyer lemon]]s. [[Soybean]]s, [[bok choy]], [[Diospyros kaki|Japanese persimmon]], [[thai basil]], [[Napa cabbage]], [[nori]], [[mandarin orange]]s, [[water chestnut]]s, and [[mung bean]]s are other crops brought to the region from East Asia and are common additions to salads as the emphasis on fresh produce in both Southern and Northern California is strong. Other vegetables and herbs have a distinct Mediterranean flavor which would include [[oregano]], [[basil]], [[summer squash]], [[eggplant]], and [[broccoli]], with all of the above extensively available at farmers' markets all around Southern California. Naturally, salads native to Southern California tend to be hearty affairs, like [[Cobb salad]] and [[Chinese chicken salad]], and dressings like [[Green goddess dressing|green goddess]] and [[ranch dressing|ranch]] are a staple. [[California-style pizza]] tends to have disparate ingredients with an emphasis on vegetables, with any combination of chili oil, prawns, eggs, chicken, shiitake mushrooms, olives, bell pepper, goat cheese, and feta cheese. Peanut noodles tend to include a sweet dressing with lo mein noodles and chopped peanuts.

Fresh fish and shellfish in Southern California tends to be expensive in restaurants, but every year since the end of WWII, the Pismo clam festival has taken place where the local population takes a [[pismo clam|large species of clam]] and bakes, stuffs, and roasts it as it is a regional delicacy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://m.sandiegoreader.com/news/2013/apr/12/digging-pismo-clams-san-diego-beaches/?templates=mobile|title=Digging for Pismo clams at San Diego Beaches - San Diego Reader|publisher=Sandiegoreader.com|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://blog.seacrestpismo.com/2012/10/pismo-beach-clam-festival/|title=Dig Into the 66th Annual Pismo Beach Clam Festival|work=SeaCrest OceanFront Hotel|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fishing for pacific species of octopus and the [[Humboldt squid]] are common, and both are a feature of East Asian and other L.A. fish markets.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://articles.latimes.com/2013/jan/14/local/la-me-fishing-boat-20130114|title=Jumbo squid invasion attracts eager anglers|work=Los Angeles Times|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wideopenfish.com/2011/09/cooking-the-monster-giant-squid-made-easy/|title=Cooking the Monster Giant Squid Made Easy!|work=Wide Open Fishing Los Angeles Orange County Inshore Offshore Fishing|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://m.laweekly.com/squidink/2013/05/15/10-best-octopus-dishes-in-los-angeles|title=10 Best Octopus Dishes in Los Angeles|work=LA Weekly|accessdate=January 16, 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141211084255/http://m.laweekly.com/squidink/2013/05/15/10-best-octopus-dishes-in-los-angeles|archive-date=December 11, 2014|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Lingcod]] is a coveted regional fish that is often caught in the autumn off the coast of [[San Diego]] and in the [[Channel Islands, California|Channel Islands]] and often served baked. [[California sheephead]] are often grilled and are much sought after by spear fishermen and the immigrant Chinese population, in which case it is basket steamed. Most revered of all in recent years is the [[California spiny lobster]], a beast that can grow to be 20&amp;nbsp;kg, and is a delicacy that now rivals the fishery for Dungeness crab in its importance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.boatingmag.com/how-to/california-lobster-battles|title=California Lobster Battles|work=Boating Magazine|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Pacific and Hawaiian cuisine===
{{Main|Cuisine of Hawaii}}
[[File:Lomi lomi salmon.jpg|thumb|[[Lomi salmon|Lomi-lomi]] salmon]]
Hawaii is often considered to be one of the most culturally diverse U.S. states, as well as being the only state with an Asian majority population and being one of the few places where United States territory extends into the tropics. As a result, [[Hawaii regional cuisine|Hawaiian cuisine]] borrows elements of a variety of cuisines, particularly those of Asian and Pacific-rim cultures, as well as traditional native Hawaiian and a few additions from the American mainland. American influence of the last 150 years has brought cattle, goats, and sheep to the islands, introducing cheese, butter, and yogurt products, as well as crops like [[red cabbage]]. Just to name a few, major Asian and Polynesian influences on modern Hawaiian cuisine are from [[Japan]], [[Korea]], [[Vietnam]], [[China]] (especially near the Pearl River delta,) [[Samoa]], and the [[Philippines]]. From Japan, the concept of serving raw fish as a meal with rice was introduced, as was soft tofu, setting the stage for the popular dish called [[Poke (Hawaii)|poke.]] From Korea, immigrants to Hawaii brought a love of spicy garlic marinades for meat and [[kimchi]]. From China, their version of [[char siu baau]] became modern [[manapua]], a type of steamed pork bun with a spicy filling.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.coffeetimes.com/may97.htm|title=Getting to the Roots of Hawaii Regional Cuisine|publisher=Coffeetimes.com|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Filipinos brought vinegar, [[bagoong]], and [[lumpia]], and during the 20th century immigrants from [[American Samoa]] brought the open pit fire [[Earth oven|umu]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.polynesia.com/Umu_Making_Release.html#.VH5chJY8Lv4|title=Polynesian Cultural Center Shares The Flavors Of Samoa With Hands-On Umu Making Activity|publisher=Polynesia.com|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the Vietnamese introduced [[lemongrass]] and [[fish sauce]]. Each East Asian culture brought several different kinds of noodles, including [[udon]], [[ramen]], [[mei fun]], and [[pho]], and today these are common lunchtime meals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://danazia.wordpress.com/2011/03/08/history-of-hawaiis-cuisine/|title=History of Hawaii's cuisine - The Go Lightly Gourmet|work=The Go Lightly Gourmet|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Much of this cuisine mixes and melts into traditions like the [[luau|lu'au]], whose traditional elaborate fare was once the prerogative of kings and queens but today is the subject of parties for both tourists and also private parties for the ''‘ohana'' (meaning family and close friends.) Traditionally, women and men ate separately under the Hawaiian ''[[kapu]]'' system, a system of religious beliefs that honored the Hawaiian gods similar to the [[Māori people|Maori]] tapu system, though in this case had some specific prohibitions towards females eating things like coconut, pork, turtle meat, and bananas as these were considered parts of the male gods. Punishment for violation could be severe, as a woman might endanger a man's mana, or soul, by eating with him or otherwise by eating the forbidden food because doing so dishonored all the male gods. As the system broke down after 1810, introductions of foods from laborers on plantations began to be included at feasts and much cross pollination occurred, where Asian foodstuffs mixed with Polynesian foodstuffs like [[breadfruit]], [[Aleurites moluccanus|kukui nuts]], and purple [[sweet potato]]es.

Some notable Hawaiian fare includes seared ahi tuna, opakapaka (snapper) with passionfruit, Hawaiian island-raised lamb, beef and meat products, Hawaiian [[plate lunch]], and Molokai shrimp. Seafood traditionally is caught fresh in Hawaiian waters, and particular delicacies are [[Panulirus marginatus|''ula poni'']], [[Kona crab|''papaikualoa'']], [[Cellana|''‘opihi'']], and [[haliotis discus|''‘opihi malihini'']], better known as Hawaiian spiny lobster, Kona crab, Hawaiian limpet, and abalone, the last brought over with Japanese immigrants.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.honolulupulse.com/2014/02/food-la-la-kona-abalone/|title=Food La La: Kona Abalone opens at Ala Moana - Honolulu Pulse - Hawaii Entertainment, Food and NightlifeHonolulu Pulse – Hawaii Entertainment, Food and Nightlife|work=Honolulu Pulse - Hawaii Entertainment, Food and Nightlife|accessdate=January 16, 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150116202330/http://www.honolulupulse.com/2014/02/food-la-la-kona-abalone/|archive-date=January 16, 2015|url-status=dead|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some cuisine also incorporates a broad variety of produce and locally grown agricultural products, including [[tomato]]es, sweet Maui onions, taro, and macadamia nuts. Tropical fruits equally play an important role in the cuisine as a flavoring in cocktails and in desserts, including local cultivars of [[banana]]s, [[sweetsop]], [[mango]]es, [[lychee]], [[coconut]]s, [[papaya]]s, and lilikoi ([[passiflora edulis|passionfruit]]). [[Pineapple]]s have been an island staple since the 19th century and figure into many marinades and drinks.

===Common dishes found on a regional level===
{{See also|List of American regional and fusion cuisines}}
&lt;gallery class=&quot;center&quot; caption=&quot;&quot; widths=&quot;200px&quot; heights=&quot;170px&quot;&gt;
File:BBQ Food.jpg|Chicken, pork and corn cooking in a [[barbecue]] [[smoking (cooking)|smoker]]
File: New_York-Style_Pizza.png|[[New York–style pizza]] served at a pizzeria in New York City
File:Giordanos stuffed pizza.jpg|[[Chicago-style pizza|Chicago-style deep-dish pizza]] from the original [[Giordano's]] location
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Ethnicity-specific and immigrant influence==
{{Original research|section|date=February 2008}}
[[File:Fried Fish and French Fries.jpg|thumb|[[Fried fish]] and [[french fries]] in [[San Diego]], California]]

The influence of ethnicity-specific cuisines like [[Italian cuisine]] and [[Mexican cuisine]] was present in the United States by [[World War I]]. There are recipes for Chilean meat pies, chicken [[chop suey]], [[chow mein]], Mexican pork pastries and Italian meatballs going back to at least the 1930s, but many of the recipes were Anglicized and they appeared relatively infrequently compared to Northern European recipes.&lt;ref&gt;Sherrie A. Inness, Dinner roles: American women and culinary culture. p. 89&lt;/ref&gt; 19th century cookbooks bear evidence of diverse influences with some including recipes like Indian pickle, Italian pork and various curries. 19th century literature shows knowledge of [[Jewish cuisine|Jewish]], [[Russian cuisine|Russian]], [[Italian cuisine|Italian]], [[Chinese cuisine|Chinese]] and [[Turkish cuisine]]s, and foreign cookbooks continued to grow more detailed through World War I including recipes like Peruvian chicken, Mexican [[enchilada]]s, Chilean [[corn pudding]] and Hindustan chicken curry.&lt;ref&gt;Sherrie A. Inness, Dinner roles: American women and culinary culture. p. 92&lt;/ref&gt;

Louise Rice, author of ''Dainty Dishes from Foreign Lands'' describes the recipes in her book as &quot;not wholly vegetarian&quot;  though noting at the time of publication in 1911 that most of the recipes would likely be new to average American cooks and likely contain higher proportions of vegetables to meat. She includes Italian pasta recipes like [[macaroni in milk]], soups and [[polenta]]s and German recipes like liver [[dumpling]]s called ''[[Leberknödel]]'' and a variation of [[Sauerbraten]].&lt;ref&gt;Louise Rice, ''[https://archive.org/details/daintydishesfrom00rice/page/n6 Dainty Dishes From Foreign Lands]'', p.7-34&lt;/ref&gt;

The demand for ethnic foods in the United States reflects the nation's changing diversity as well as its development over time. According to the [[National Restaurant Association]], &lt;blockquote&gt;
Restaurant industry sales are expected to reach a record high of $476 billion in 2005, an increase of 4.9 percent over 2004... Driven by consumer demand, the ethnic food market reached record sales in 2002, and has emerged as the fastest growing category in the food and beverage product sector, according to USBX Advisory Services. Minorities in the U.S. spend a combined $142 billion on food and by 2010, America's ethnic population is expected to grow by 40 percent.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcolnb|Oralia|2005}} (par. 6).&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

[[Image:Koreantacos1.jpg|left|thumb|250px|[[Korean tacos]] from the &quot;Seoul on Wheels&quot; truck in San Francisco]]
A movement began during the 1980s among popular leading chefs to reclaim America's ethnic foods within its regional traditions, where these trends originated. One of the earliest was [[Paul Prudhomme]], who in 1984 began the introduction of his influential cookbook, ''Paul Prodhomme's Louisiana Kitchen'', by describing the over 200-year history of [[Louisiana Creole cuisine|Creole]] and Cajun cooking; he aims to &quot;preserve and expand the Louisiana tradition.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcolnb|Prodhomme|1984}} n.p.&lt;/ref&gt; Prodhomme's success quickly inspired other chefs. Norman Van Aken embraced a Floridian type cuisine fused with many ethnic and globalized elements in his ''Feast of Sunlight'' cookbook in 1988. California became swept up in the movement, then seemingly started to lead the trend itself, in, for example, the popular restaurant [[Chez Panisse]] in Berkeley. Examples of the Chez Panisse phenomenon, chefs who embraced a new globalized cuisine, were celebrity chefs like Jeremiah Tower and [[Wolfgang Puck]], both former colleagues at the restaurant. Puck went on to describe his belief in contemporary, new style American cuisine in the introduction to ''The Wolfgang Puck Cookbook'':
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Another major breakthrough, whose originators were once thought to be crazy, is the mixing of ethnic cuisines. It is not at all uncommon to find raw fish listed next to tortillas on the same menu. Ethnic crossovers also occur when distinct elements meet in a single recipe. This country is, after all, a huge melting pot. Why should its cooking not illustrate the American transformation of diversity into unity?&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcolnb|Puck|1986}} n.p.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Puck's former colleague, Jeremiah Tower became synonymous with [[California Cuisine]] and the overall American [[culinary revolution]]. Meanwhile, the restaurant that inspired both Puck and Tower became a distinguished establishment, popularizing its so called &quot;mantra&quot; in its book by [[Paul Bertolli]] and owner [[Alice Waters]], ''Chez Panisse Cooking'', in 1988. Published well after the restaurants' founding in 1971, this new cookbook from the restaurant seemed to perfect the idea and philosophy that had developed over the years. The book embraced America's natural bounty, specifically that of California, while containing recipes that reflected Bertoli and Waters' appreciation of both northern Italian and French style foods.

===Early ethnic influences===
[[File:CornmealProducts.jpg|thumb|Adaptation of [[Mexican food]] tailored for the mainstream American market usually is different from [[Mexican food]] typically served in Mexico.]]
While the earliest cuisine of the United States was influenced by [[Native American cuisine|Native Americans]], the [[Cuisine of the Thirteen Colonies|thirteen colonies]], or the [[Cuisine of Antebellum America|antebellum South]]; the overall culture of the nation, its [[gastronomy]] and the growing [[culinary arts]] became ever more influenced by its changing [[ethnic]] mix and [[immigrant]] patterns from the 18th and 19th centuries unto the present. Some of the ethnic groups that continued to influence the cuisine were here in prior years; while others arrived more numerously during &quot;The Great [[Transatlantic Migration]]&quot; (of 1870—1914) or other [[mass migration]]s.

Some of the ethnic influences could be found across the nation after the [[American Civil War]] and into the [[History of United States continental expansion|continental expansion]] for most of the 19th century. Ethnic influences already in the nation at that time would include the following groups and their respective cuisines:
* Select nationalities of Europe and the respective developments from [[early modern European cuisine]] of the colonial age:
** [[British-American]]s and on-going developments in [[New England cuisine]], the national traditions founded in cuisine of the thirteen colonies and some aspects of other regional cuisine.
** [[Spanish American]]s and early modern [[Spanish cuisine]], as well as [[Basque-American]]s and [[Basque cuisine]].
** Early [[German-American]] or [[Pennsylvania Dutch]] and [[Pennsylvania Dutch cuisine]]
** [[French American]]s and their [[New World]] regional identities such as:
*** [[Acadian]]
*** [[Cajun]] and [[Cajun cuisine]]
** [[Louisiana Creole people|Louisiana Creole]] and [[Louisiana Creole cuisine]]. Louisiana Creole (also called French Créole) refers to native born people of the New Orleans area who are descended from the Colonial French and Spanish settlers of Colonial French Louisiana, before it became part of the United States in 1803 with the [[Louisiana Purchase]].
* The various ethnicities originating from early social factors of [[Race in the United States]] and the [[gastronomy]] and [[cuisine]]s of the [[New World]], [[Latin American cuisine]] and North American cuisine:
** [[Indigenous peoples|Indigenous]] [[Native Americans in the United States]] and [[Native American cuisine|American Indian cuisine]]
** [[African Americans]] and [[Soul food]].
** [[Puerto Rican cuisine]]
** [[Mexican Americans]] and [[Mexican cuisine in the United States|Mexican-American cuisine]]; as well as related regional cuisines:
*** [[Tex-Mex]] (regional Texas and Mexican fusion)
*** Some aspects of &quot;[[Southwestern cuisine]].&quot;
** [[New Mexican cuisine|Cuisine of New Mexico]]

===Later ethnic and immigrant influence===
{{Main|Immigration to the United States}}
Mass migrations of immigrants to the United States came in several waves. Historians identify several waves of migration to the United States: one from 1815 to 1860, in which some five million [[English people|English]], [[Irish people|Irish]], [[Germanic peoples|Germanic]], [[Scandinavia]]n, and others from [[northwestern Europe]] came to the United States; one from 1865 to 1890, in which some 10 million immigrants, also mainly from northwestern Europe, settled, and a third from 1890 to 1914, in which 15 million immigrants, mainly from [[Central Europe|central]], [[Eastern Europe|eastern]], and [[southern Europe]] (many [[Austrian people|Austrian]], [[Hungarian people|Hungarian]], [[Turkish people|Turkish]], [[Lithuanian people|Lithuanian]], [[Russian people|Russian]], [[Jewish people|Jewish]], [[Greek people|Greek]], [[Italian people|Italian]], and [[Romanian people|Romanian]]) settled in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://us.history.wisc.edu/hist102/lectures/lecture08.html|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120313201141/http://us.history.wisc.edu/hist102/lectures/lecture08.html|archivedate=2012-03-13|title=H102 Lecture 08: Foreign Immigrants in Industrial America|date=2012-03-13|website=web.archive.org|access-date=2019-08-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Together with earlier arrivals to the United States (including the indigenous Native Americans, [[Hispanic and Latino Americans]], particularly in the [[Western United States|West]], [[Southwestern United States|Southwest]], and [[Texas]]; [[African American]]s who came to the United States in the [[Atlantic slave trade]]; and early colonial migrants from Britain, France, Germany, Spain, and elsewhere), these new waves of immigrants had a profound impact on national or regional cuisine. Some of these more prominent groups include the following:

{{Div col}}
* [[Arab American]]s, particularly [[Lebanese American]]s (the largest ethnic Arab group in the United States) – [[Arab cuisine]], [[Lebanese cuisine]]
* [[Chinese American]]s – [[American Chinese cuisine]], [[Chinese cuisine]]
* [[Cuban American]]s – [[Cuban cuisine]]
* [[Dominican American]]s – [[Dominican Republic cuisine]]
* [[Ethiopian Americans]]-[[Eritrean Americans]]: [[Ethiopian cuisine]], [[Eritrean cuisine]] in Los Angeles, Washington, D.C., Denver, New York.
* [[German Americans]] – [[German cuisine]] (the [[Pennsylvania Dutch]], although descended from Germans, arrived earlier than the bulk of German migrants and have distinct culinary traditions)
* [[Greek American]]s – [[Greek-American cuisine]], [[Greek cuisine]], [[Mediterranean cuisine]]
* [[Haitian American]]s – [[Haitian cuisine]]
* [[Hungarian American]]s – [[Hungarian cuisine]]
* [[Indian American]]s – [[Indian cuisine]]
* [[Irish American]]s – [[Irish cuisine]]
* [[Italian American]]s – [[Italian-American cuisine]], [[Italian cuisine]]
* [[Japanese American]]s – [[Japanese cuisine]], with influences on the [[Cuisine of Hawaii|Hawaiian cuisine]]
* [[American Jews|Jewish Americans]] – [[Jewish cuisine]], with particular influence on [[Cuisine of New York City#NYC Eastern European Jewish Cuisine|New York City cuisine]]
* [[Korean American]]s - [[Korean cuisine]], with significant influence during the Korean War
* [[Lithuanian American]]s – [[Lithuanian cuisine]], [[Cuisine of the Midwestern United States|Midwest]]
* [[Nicaraguan American]]- [[Nicaraguan cuisine]]
* [[Pakistani American]]s – [[Pakistani cuisine]]
* [[Polish American]]s – [[Polish cuisine]], with particular impact on [[Cuisine of the Midwestern United States|Midwest]]
* [[Polynesian American]]s – [[Cuisine of Hawaii|Hawaiian cuisine]]
* [[Portuguese American]]s – [[Portuguese cuisine]]
* [[Romanian American]]s – [[Romanian cuisine]]
* [[Russian American]]s – [[Russian cuisine]], with particular impact on [[Cuisine of the Midwestern United States|Midwest]]
* [[Salvadoran American]]s – [[Salvadoran cuisine]]
* [[Scottish American]]s – [[Scottish cuisine]]
* [[Thai American]]s - [[Thai cuisine]]
* [[Turkish American]]s - [[Turkish cuisine]], [[Balkan cuisine]]
* [[Vietnamese American]]s – [[Vietnamese cuisine]]
* [[West Indian American]]s – [[Caribbean cuisine]], [[Jamaican cuisine]], [[Trinidad and Tobago cuisine]]{{Div col end}}

&lt;blockquote&gt;Italian, Mexican and Chinese (Cantonese) cuisines have indeed joined the mainstream. These three cuisines have become so ingrained in the American culture that they are no longer foreign to the American palate. According to the study, more than nine out of 10 consumers are familiar with and have tried these foods, and about half report eating them frequently. The research also indicates that Italian, Mexican and Chinese (Cantonese) have become so adapted to such an extent that &quot;authenticity&quot; is no longer a concern to customers.&lt;ref&gt;Hensley, Sue, ''National Restaurant Association.''Article/ News Release, &quot;International Cuisine Reaches America's Main Street,&quot; 10 August 2000.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Contributions from these ethnic foods have become as common as traditional &quot;American&quot; fares such as hot dogs, hamburgers, beef [[steak]], which are derived from [[German cuisine]], ([[chicken-fried steak]], for example, is a variation on German [[schnitzel]]), cherry pie, [[Coca-Cola]], [[milkshake]]s, fried chicken (Fried chicken is of [[Scottish cuisine|Scottish]] and [[African cuisine|African]] influence) and so on. Nowadays, Americans also have a ubiquitous consumption of foods like [[pizza]] and [[pasta]], [[taco]]s and [[burrito]]s to &quot;[[General Tso's chicken]]&quot; and [[fortune cookie]]s. Fascination with these and other ethnic foods may also vary with region.

==Notable American chefs==
{{see also|List of chefs}}
American [[chef]]s have been influential both in the food industry and in popular culture. An important 19th-century American chef was [[Charles Ranhofer]] of [[Delmonico's Restaurant]] in [[New York City]]. American cooking has been exported around the world, both through the global expansion of restaurant chains such as [[T.G.I. Friday's]] and [[McDonald's]] and the efforts of individual restaurateurs such as Bob Payton, credited with bringing American-style pizza to the UK.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Bob Payton, 50, Restaurateur, Dies|newspaper=[[The New York Times]]|date=July 16, 1994|page=28|url=https://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F10611FF355B0C758DDDAE0894DC494D81|accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The first generation of television chefs such as [[Robert Carrier (chef)|Robert Carrier]] and [[Julia Child]] tended to concentrate on cooking based primarily on European, especially French and Italian, cuisines. Only during the 1970s and 1980s did television chefs such as [[James Beard]] and [[Jeff Smith (chef)|Jeff Smith]] shift the focus towards home-grown cooking styles, particularly those of the different ethnic groups within the nation. Notable American restaurant chefs include [[Thomas Keller]], [[Charlie Trotter]], [[Grant Achatz]], [[Alfred Portale]], [[Paul Prudhomme]], [[Paul Bertolli]], [[Jonathan Waxman]], [[Mark Peel (chef)|Mark Peel]], [[Frank Stitt]], [[Alice Waters]], [[Wolfgang Puck]], [[Patrick O'Connell (chef)|Patrick O'Connell]] and [[celebrity chef]]s like [[Mario Batali]], [[David Chang]], [[Alton Brown]], [[Emeril Lagasse]], [[Cat Cora]], [[Michael Symon]], [[Bobby Flay]], [[Ina Garten]], [[Todd English]], [[Anthony Bourdain]], [[Guy Fieri]], [[Colonel Sanders]] and [[Paula Deen]].

Regional chefs are emerging as localized celebrity chefs with growing broader appeal, such as [[Peter Merriman]] (Hawaii Regional Cuisine), [[Jerry Traunfeld]], [[Alan Wong]] (Pacific Rim cuisine), Norman Van Aken (New World Cuisine – fusion Latin, Caribbean, Asian, African and American), and Mark Miller (American Southwest cuisine).

==See also==
{{Culture of the United States}}
* [[Cuisine of Antebellum America]]
* [[Cuisine of New York City]]
* [[List of American desserts]]
* [[List of American breads]]
* [[List of American foods]]
* [[List of American regional and fusion cuisines]]
* [[List of fast food restaurant chains#United States]]
* [[Native American cuisine]]
* [[Tlingit cuisine]]
* [[Cuisine of the Americas]]
* [[Western pattern diet]]
{{Cookbook|position=left}}
{{clear}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

===Works cited===
* {{cite book
  | last = Bertolli
  | first = Paul
  | authorlink =
  |author2=Alice Waters
  | title = Chez Panisse Cooking
  | publisher = Random House
  | year = 1988
  | location = New York
  | pages =
  | url =
  | doi =
  | id =
  | isbn =
}}.
* {{cite book
|last=Crocker
|first= Betty
|title=Betty Crocker Cookbook: Everything You Need to Know to Cook Today
|edition=10, illustrated, revised
|publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons, Incorporated
|year=2005
|isbn=978-0-7645-6877-0
}}.
* {{cite book
|last=Crowgey
|first=Henry G.
|title=Kentucky Bourbon: The Early Years of Whiskeymaking'
|location=Kentucky
|publisher=The [[University Press of Kentucky]]
|year=1971
}}.
* {{cite book
|last1=Danforth
|first1=Randi
|last2=Feierabend
|first2=Peter.
|last3=Chassman
|first3=Gary.
|title=Culinaria The United States: A Culinary Discovery
|location=New York
|publisher=Konemann
|year=1998
}}.
* Fried, Stephen. ''Appetite for America: How Visionary Businessman Fred Harvey Built a Railroad Hospitality Empire That Civilized the Wild West'' (Bantam; 2010)
* {{cite book
|last=Glasse
|first=Hannah
|title=Art of Cookery Made Easy
|url=https://archive.org/details/b30502287
|location=London
|year=1750
}}.
* {{cite book
|last=Oliver
|first=Sandra L.
|title=Food in Colonial and Federal America
|location=London
|publisher=Greenwood Press
|year=2005
}}.
* {{cite web|last=Oralia |first=Michael |title=Demand for Ethnic &amp; International Foods Reflects a Changing America |publisher=National Restaurant Association |date=April 5, 2005 |url=http://www.nationalrestaurantassociation.com/pressroom/print/index.cfm?ID=1073 |accessdate=March 8, 2009 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130403032312/http://www.nationalrestaurantassociation.com/pressroom/print/index.cfm?ID=1073 |archivedate=April 3, 2013 }}.
* {{cite book
|last=Pillsbury
|first=Richard
|title=No Foreign Food: The American Diet in Time and Place
|url=https://archive.org/details/noforeignfoodame00pill_0
|url-access=registration
|publisher=Westview
|year=1998
}}.
* {{cite book|author=Porterfield, James D.
|year=1993
|title=Dining by Rail: The History and Recipes of America's Golden Age of Railroad Cuisine
|publisher=St. Martin's Press
| location = New York
|isbn=0-312-18711-4}}
* {{cite book
  | last = Prodhomme
  | first = Paul
  | authorlink = 
  | title = Paul Prodhomme's Louisiana Kitchen
  | publisher = William Morrow
  | year = 1984
  | location = New York
  | pages = 
  | url = https://archive.org/details/chefpaulprudhomm00prud_2
  | doi = 
  | id = 
  | isbn = 0-688-02847-0
  }}.
* {{cite book
  | last = Puck
  | first = Wolfgang
  | authorlink =
  | title = The Wolfgang Puck Cookbook
  | publisher = Random House
  | year = 1986
  | location = New York
  | pages =
  | url =https://archive.org/details/wolfgangpuckcook00puck
  | url-access = registration
  | doi =
  | id =
  | isbn = }}
* {{cite book|last1=Root|first1=Waverly|last2=De Rochemont|first2=Richard|title=Eating in America: a History|location=New Jersey|pages=|publisher=The Ecco Press|year=1981|isbn=9780912946887}}
* {{cite book
|last=Smith
|first=Andrew F.
|title=The Oxford Encyclopedia of Food and Drink in America
|location=Oxford
|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]
|year=2004
}}.
* {{cite book
  | last = Tower
  | first = Jeremiah
  | authorlink =
  | title = California Dish, What I Saw (and cooked) at the American Culinary Revolution
  | publisher = Free Press/Simon &amp; Schuster
  | year = 2004
  | location = New York
  | pages =
  | url =https://archive.org/details/californiadishwh00towe
  | url-access = registration
  | doi =
  | id =
  | isbn =
}}.
* {{cite book
  | last = Tower
  | first = Jeremiah
  | authorlink =
  | title = New American Classics
  | publisher = Harper &amp; Row
  | year = 1986
  | location =
  | pages =
  | url =https://archive.org/details/jeremiahtowersne00towe
  | url-access = registration
  | doi =
  | id =
  | isbn =
}}.
* {{cite book
  | last = Van Aken
  | first = Norman
  | authorlink = 
  | title = Feast of Sunlight
  | publisher = Ballantine/Random House
  | year = 1988
  | location = New York
  | pages = 
  | url = https://archive.org/details/normanvanakensfe00vana
  | doi = 
  | id = 
  | isbn = 0-345-34582-7
  }}
* Veit, Helen Zoe. ''Modern Food, Moral Food: Self-Control, Science, and the Rise of Modern American Eating in the Early Twentieth Century'' (2013)

==External links==
{{Commons category|Cuisine of the United States}}
{{Wikivoyage|American cuisine}}
* [http://www.keyingredients.org/ Key Ingredients: America by Food] -Educational companion to Smithsonian Institution's exhibit on American food ways.

{{Cuisine of the United States}}
{{North American cuisine}}
{{American cheeses}}
{{United States topics}}
{{Cuisines}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Cuisine Of The United States}}
[[Category:American cuisine| ]]
[[Category:Cultural history of the United States]]
[[Category:North American cuisine]]</text>
      <sha1>0d73wfvz7isbi8cy92q0vo1qdjaldza</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
