  <page>
    <title>Charybdis</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6134</id>
    <revision>
      <id>937764105</id>
      <parentid>936820425</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-27T02:52:59Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jonesey95</username>
        <id>9755426</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Fix [[Category:Pages with ISBN errors|ISBN error]] or other ISBN error using [[WP:AutoEd|AutoEd]] (or wrap invalid ISBN in template to show error message)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Whirlpool in the Strait of Messina named for a figure in Greek mythology}}
{{other uses}}
'''Charybdis''' ({{IPAc-en|k|ə|ˈ|r|ɪ|b|d|ᵻ|s}}; [[Ancient Greek]]: Χάρυβδις, {{IPA-el|kʰárybdis|pron}}, ''Kharubdis'') is a [[sea monster]] in [[Greek mythology]]. Subsequent scholarship has suggested that it was based on a [[whirlpool]] in the [[Strait of Messina]].

==Description==
[[File:Strait of Messina.jpg|thumb|320px|The Strait of Messina, with Scylla (underlined in red) and Charybdis on the opposite shores]]
The sea monster Charybdis was believed to live under a small rock on one side of a narrow channel. Opposite her was [[Scylla]], another sea monster, that lived inside a much larger rock.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Odyssey|last=|first=|year=|isbn=|location=|pages=Book XII}}&lt;/ref&gt; The sides of the strait were within an arrow-shot of each other, and sailors attempting to avoid one of them would come in reach of the other. To be &quot;[[between Scylla and Charybdis]]&quot; therefore means to be presented with two opposite dangers, the task being to find a route that avoids both. Three times a day, Charybdis swallowed a huge amount of water, before belching it back out again, creating large whirlpools capable of dragging a ship underwater. In some variations of the story, Charybdis was simply a large [[whirlpool]] instead of a sea monster.

The theoretical size of Charybdis remains unknown, yet in order to consume [[Greece|Greek]] ships the whirlpool can be estimated to about 23 meters (75&amp;nbsp;ft) across. Through the descriptions of Greek mythical chroniclers and Greek historians such as [[Thucydides]], modern scholars generally agree that Charybdis was said to have been located in the [[Strait of Messina]], off the [[coast]] of [[Sicily]] and opposite a rock on the mainland identified with Scylla.&lt;ref&gt;[[Thucydides]].  ''[[History of the Peloponnesian War]] [http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text.jsp?doc=thuc.%204.24 4.24.5].''&lt;/ref&gt; Were Charybdis to be located in the Strait of Messina, it would in fact have the size to accommodate the whirlpool. A whirlpool does exist there, caused by currents meeting, but it is dangerous only to small craft in extreme conditions.&lt;ref&gt;Andrews, Tamra (2000). ''Dictionary of Nature Myths: Legends of the Earth, Sea, and Sky''. Oxford University Press. p. 171. {{ISBN|978-0-19-513677-7}}. Retrieved 25 May 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Genealogy ==
A later myth makes Charybdis the daughter of [[Poseidon]] and [[Gaia (mythology)|Gaia]]&lt;ref&gt;[[Scholia]]st on Homer's ''Odyssey''&lt;/ref&gt; and living as a loyal servant to her father.[[File:Strait of Messina, cariddi.JPG|thumb|The narrowest point of [[Strait of Messina]] as seen from the village of Torre Faro]]

==Mythology==

=== Origin ===
Charybdis aided her father Poseidon in his feud with her paternal uncle Zeus and, as such, helped him engulf lands and islands in water. Zeus, angry over the land she stole from him, captured and chained her to the sea-bed. Charybdis was then cursed by the god and transformed into a hideous bladder of a monster, with flippers for arms and legs, and an uncontrollable thirst for the sea. As such, she drank the water from the sea thrice a day to quench it, which created whirlpools.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.greekmythology.com/Myths/Monsters/Charybdis/charybdis.html|title=Charybdis|website=www.greekmythology.com|accessdate=5 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theoi.com/Pontios/Kharybdis.html|title=Charybdis (Kharybdis) – Whirlpool Monster of Greek Mythology|website=www.theoi.com|accessdate=5 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; She lingered on a rock with Scylla facing her directly on another rock, making a strait.

===The ''Odyssey''===
[[File:Scylla and Charybdis.jpg|thumb|upright=1.2|A 19th-century engraving of the Strait of Messina, the site associated with Scylla and Charybdis]] [[Odysseus]] faced both Charybdis and Scylla while rowing through a narrow channel. He ordered his men to avoid Charybdis, thus forcing them to pass near Scylla, which resulted in the deaths of six of his men. Later, stranded on a raft, Odysseus was swept back through the strait and passed near Charybdis. His raft was sucked into her maw, but he survived by clinging to a fig tree growing on a rock over her lair. On the next outflow of water, when his raft was expelled, Odysseus recovered it and paddled away safely.&lt;ref&gt;Homer, ''Odyssey'' Book 12, [http://www.poetryintranslation.com/PITBR/Greek/Odyssey12.htm#_Toc90268048 lines 201–59 and 430–50]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Jason and the Argonauts===
The [[Argonauts]] were able to avoid both dangers because [[Hera]] ordered the [[Nereid]] [[nymph]] [[Thetis]], [[Achilles]]' mother, to guide them through the perilous passage.&lt;ref&gt;Apollonius Rhodius , ''Argonautica'' Book 4, [http://www.theoi.com/Text/ApolloniusRhodius4.html lines 821–960]&lt;/ref&gt;

===The ''Aeneid''===
In the ''[[Aeneid]]'' the Trojans are warned by [[Helenus]] of Scylla and Charybdis, and are advised to avoid them by sailing around Pachynus point ([[Cape Passero]]) rather than risk [[Straits of Messina|the Straits]]&lt;ref&gt;Gutenberg Project: ''The Aeneid'' E. F. Taylor translation (1907) [https://www.gutenberg.org/files/18466/18466-h/18466-h.htm#book3line343 Bk 3, 487-504]&lt;/ref&gt; . Later however they find themselves passing [[Mount Etna|Etna]], and have to row for their lives to escape Charybdis.&lt;ref&gt;Gutenberg Project: ''The Aeneid'' E. F. Taylor translation (1907) [https://www.gutenberg.org/files/18466/18466-h/18466-h.htm#book3line577 Bk 3, 636-648]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Aesop===
[[Aristotle]] mentions in his ''Meteorologica'' that [[Aesop]] once [[Aesop and the Ferryman|teased a ferryman]] by telling him a myth concerning Charybdis. With one gulp of the sea, she brought the mountains to view; islands appeared after the next. The third is yet to come and will dry the sea altogether, thus depriving the ferryman of his livelihood.&lt;ref&gt;Gert-Jan van Dijk, ''Ainoi, logoi, mythoi: fables in archaic, classical, and Hellenistic Greek literature'', Brill NL 1997,; [https://books.google.com/books?id=QKQFJduPIdcC&amp;q=charybdis#v=snippet&amp;q=charybdis&amp;f=false pp. 351–53]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{commons category}}
{{reflist}}

==References==
* [[William Smith (lexicographer)|Smith, William]]; ''[[Dictionary of Greek and Roman Biography and Mythology]]'', London (1873). [http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.04.0104%3Aalphabetic+letter%3DS%3Aentry+group%3D10%3Aentry%3Dscylla-bio-1 &quot;Scylla&quot; 1.]

==External links==
* {{cite EB1911|wstitle=Scylla and Charybdis|volume=24|page=519}}

[[Category:Characters in the Odyssey]]
[[Category:Female legendary creatures]]
[[Category:Metamorphoses in Greek mythology]]
[[Category:Monsters in Greek mythology]]
[[Category:Mythology of Argonautica]]
[[Category:Naiads]]
[[Category:Offspring of Gaia]]
[[Category:Offspring of Poseidon]]
[[Category:Sea monsters]]
[[Category:Whirlpools]]</text>
      <sha1>74dyp152k11rtr2jj6ikqdby5xttb11</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
