  <page>
    <title>Convention on Biological Diversity</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6198</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941077654</id>
      <parentid>931935601</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-16T13:23:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Iridescent</username>
        <id>937705</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* National Biodiversity Strategies and Action Plans (NBSAP) */Cleanup and [[WP:AWB/T|typo fixing]], [[WP:AWB/T|typo(s) fixed]]: the USA → the US</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2013}}

{{Infobox treaty
| name                    = Convention on Biological Diversity
| long_name               =
| image                   = Convention on Biological Diversity logo.svg
| image_size              = 
| alt                     = 
| caption                 = 
| type                    = [[Multilateral treaty|Multilateral]] [[International environmental agreement|environmental agreement]]
| context                 = [[Environmentalism]], [[Biodiversity#Conservation|Biodiversity conservation]]
| date_drafted            = {{Start date|1992|05|22|df=yes}}
| date_signed             = 5 June 1992 – 4 June 1993
| location_signed         = Rio de Janeiro, Brazil &lt;br /&gt; New York, United States
| date_effective          = {{Start date|1993|12|29|df=yes}}
| condition_effective     = Ratification by 30 States
| parties                 = {{Collapsible list
 | expand = 
 | framestyle = 
 | titlestyle = 
 | title = 196 States
 | liststyle = 
 | hlist =
 | bullets = 
 | {{flagdeco|UN}} [[Member states of the United Nations|All UN Member States]] except the [[United States]]
 | {{flag|Cook Islands}}
 | {{flag|EU|name=European Union}}
 | {{flag|Niue}}
 | {{flag|State of Palestine}}
}}
| depositor               = [[Secretary-General of the United Nations]]
| languages               = {{plainlist|
* [[Arabic language|Arabic]]
* [[Chinese language|Chinese]]
* [[English language|English]]
* [[French language|French]]
* [[Russian language|Russian]]
* [[Spanish language|Spanish]]
}}
| wikisource              = United Nations Convention on Biological Diversity
| footnotes               =
}}

The '''Convention on Biological Diversity''' ('''CBD'''), known informally as the '''Biodiversity Convention''', is a [[multilateral treaty]]. The Convention has three main goals including: the conservation of biological diversity (or [[biodiversity]]); the sustainable use of its components; and the fair and equitable sharing of benefits arising from [[Germplasm|genetic resource]]s.

In other words, its objective is to develop national strategies for the conservation and sustainable use of biological diversity. It is often seen as the key document regarding [[sustainable development]]. The Convention was opened for signature at the [[Earth Summit]] in Rio de Janeiro on 5 June 1992 and entered into force on 29 December 1993. CBD has two supplementary agreements - [[Cartagena Protocol on Biosafety|Cartagena Protocol]] and [[Nagoya Protocol]].

[[Cartagena Protocol on Biosafety|The Cartagena Protocol on Biosafety to the Convention on Biological Diversity]] is an international treaty governing the movements of living modified organisms (LMOs) resulting from modern biotechnology from one country to another. It was adopted on 29 January 2000 as a supplementary agreement to the Convention on Biological Diversity and entered into force on 11 September 2003.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://bch.cbd.int/protocol/ |title=Archived copy |access-date=13 December 2018 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20181207121019/http://bch.cbd.int/protocol |archive-date=7 December 2018 |url-status=live |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[Nagoya Protocol|The Nagoya Protocol on Access to Genetic Resources and the Fair and Equitable Sharing of Benefits Arising from their Utilization (ABS) to the Convention on Biological Diversity]] is a supplementary agreement to the Convention on Biological Diversity. It provides a transparent legal framework for the effective implementation of one of the three objectives of the CBD: the fair and equitable sharing of benefits arising out of the utilization of genetic resources. 
The Nagoya Protocol on ABS was adopted on 29 October 2010 in Nagoya, Japan and entered into force on 12 October 2014, 90 days after the deposit of the fiftieth instrument of ratification. Its objective is the fair and equitable sharing of benefits arising from the utilization of genetic resources, thereby contributing to the conservation and sustainable use of biodiversity.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.cbd.int/abs/about/default.shtml/ |title=Archived copy |access-date=13 December 2018 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20181129094409/https://www.cbd.int/abs/about/default.shtml/ |archive-date=29 November 2018 |url-status=live |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Origin and scope==

The notion of an international convention on bio-diversity was conceived at a [[United Nations Environment Programme]] (UNEP) Ad Hoc Working Group of Experts on Biological Diversity in November 1988. The subsequent year, the Ad Hoc Working Group of Technical and Legal Experts was established for the drafting of a legal text which addressed the conservation and sustainable use of biological diversity, as well as the sharing of benefits arising from their utilization with sovereign states and local communities.
In 1991, an intergovernmental negotiating committee was established, tasked with finalizing the convention's text.&lt;ref name=&quot;CBDweb01&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.cbd.int/history/|title=History of the Convention|work=Secretariat of the Convention on Biological Diversity (SCBD)|accessdate=14 November 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161204141616/https://www.cbd.int/history/|archive-date=4 December 2016|url-status=live|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A Conference for the Adoption of the Agreed Text of the Convention on Biological Diversity was held in Nairobi, Kenya, in 1992, and its conclusions were distilled in the [[Nairobi Final Act]].&lt;ref name=&quot;nairAct&quot;&gt;[https://www.cbd.int/doc/handbook/cbd-hb-09-en.pdf Nairobi Final Act of the Conference for the adoption of the agreed text of the Convention on Biological Diversity] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150613060118/https://www.cbd.int/doc/handbook/cbd-hb-09-en.pdf |date=13 June 2015 }}, Heinrich, M. (2002). Handbook of the Convention on Biological Diversity: Edited by the Secretariat of the Convention on Biological Diversity, Earthscan, London, 2001. {{ISBN|9781853837371}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Convention's text was opened for signature on 5 June 1992 at the United Nations Conference on Environment and Development (the Rio &quot;Earth Summit&quot;). By its closing date, 4 June 1993, the convention had received 168 signatures. It entered into force on 29 December 1993.&lt;ref name=&quot;CBDweb01&quot; /&gt;

The convention recognized for the first time in international law that the conservation of biodiversity is &quot;a common concern of humankind&quot; and is an integral part of the development process. The agreement covers all [[ecosystem]]s, [[species]], and genetic resources. It links traditional conservation efforts to the economic goal of using biological resources sustainably. It sets principles for the fair and equitable sharing of the benefits arising from the use of genetic resources, notably those destined for commercial use.&lt;ref&gt;Louafi, Sélim and Jean-Frédéric Morin, International governance of biodiversity: Involving all the users of genetic resources, IDDRI, 2004, https://www.academia.edu/3809935/Louafi_S._and_J-F_Morin_2004_International_Governance_of_biodiversity_Involving_all_the_Users_of_Genetic_Resources_Les_synth%C3%A8ses_de_lIddri_n_5._4_p&lt;/ref&gt; It also covers the rapidly expanding field of biotechnology through its [[Cartagena Protocol on Biosafety]], addressing technology development and transfer, benefit-sharing and [[biosafety]] issues. Importantly, the Convention is legally binding; countries that join it ('Parties') are obliged to implement its provisions.

The convention reminds decision-makers that natural resources are not infinite and sets out a philosophy of [[sustainable use]]. While past [[conservation biology|conservation]] efforts were aimed at protecting particular species and habitats, the Convention recognizes that ecosystems, species and genes must be used for the benefit of humans. However, this should be done in a way and at a rate that does not lead to the long-term decline of biological diversity.

The convention also offers decision-makers guidance based on the [[precautionary principle]] which demands that where there is a threat of significant reduction or loss of biological diversity, lack of full scientific certainty should not be used as a reason for postponing measures to avoid or minimize such a threat. The Convention acknowledges that substantial investments are required to conserve [[biodiversity|biological diversity]]. It argues, however, that conservation will bring us significant environmental, economic and social benefits in return.

The Convention on Biological Diversity of 2010 banned some forms of [[climate engineering|geoengineering]].

==Issues==
{{ref section|date=February 2017}}

Some of the many issues dealt with under the convention include:

* Measures the incentives for the conservation and sustainable use of biological diversity.
* Regulated access to genetic resources and [[traditional knowledge]], including Prior Informed Consent of the party providing resources.
* Sharing, in a fair and equitable way, the results of research and development and the benefits arising from the commercial and other utilization of [[Genetics|genetic]] resources with the Contracting Party providing such resources (governments and/or local communities that provided the traditional knowledge or biodiversity resources utilized).
* Access to and transfer of technology, including [[biotechnology]], to the governments and/or local communities that provided traditional knowledge and/or biodiversity resources.
* Technical and scientific cooperation.
* Coordination of a global directory of taxonomic expertise (Global Taxonomy Initiative).
* Impact assessment.
* Education and public [[awareness]].
* Provision of financial resources.
* National reporting on efforts to implement treaty commitments.

==Cartagena Protocol==
{{ref section|date=February 2017}}

{{main|Cartagena Protocol on Biosafety}}
The '''Cartagena Protocol on Biosafety''' of the Convention, also known as the Biosafety Protocol, was adopted in January 2000. The Biosafety Protocol seeks to protect biological diversity from the potential risks posed by living modified organisms resulting from modern biotechnology.

The Biosafety Protocol makes clear that products from new technologies must be based on the [[precautionary principle]] and allow developing nations to balance public health against economic benefits. It will for example let countries ban imports of a [[genetically modified organism]] if they feel there is not enough scientific evidence the product is [[safe]] and requires exporters to label shipments containing [[genetically modified]] commodities such as corn or cotton.

The required number of 50 instruments of ratification/accession/approval/acceptance by countries was reached in May 2003. In accordance with the provisions of its Article 37, the Protocol entered into force on 11 September 2003.

== Global Strategy for Plant Conservation ==
{{ref section|date=February 2017}}

{{main|Global Strategy for Plant Conservation}}

In April 2002, the parties of the UN CBD adopted the recommendations of the Gran Canaria Declaration Calling for a Global Plant Conservation Strategy, and adopted a 16-point plan aiming to slow the rate of plant extinctions around the world by 2010.

==Parties==
[[File:Convention on Biological Diversity2.svg|thumb|right|
{{legend|#00aa00|Parties to the convention}}
{{legend|#926ec6|Signed, but not ratified}}
{{legend|#ff9911|Non-signatory}}
]]

As of 2016, the Convention has 196 parties, which includes 195 states and the [[European Union]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cbd.int/convention/parties/list/|title=CBD List of Parties|access-date=22 September 2009|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110124005746/http://www.cbd.int/convention/parties/list/|archive-date=24 January 2011|url-status=live|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; All UN member states—with the exception of the United States—have ratified the treaty. Non-UN member states that have ratified are the [[Cook Islands]], [[Niue]], and the [[State of Palestine]]. The [[Holy See]] and the [[List of states with limited recognition|states with limited recognition]] are non-parties. The US has signed but not ratified the treaty,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=India Presses U.S. to Pass Biotic Treaty|last=Hazarika|first=Sanjoy|work=[[The New York Times]]|date=23 April 1995|page=1.13}}&lt;/ref&gt; and has not announced plans to ratify it.

==International bodies established==
{{ref section|date=February 2017}}

'''Conference of the Parties:'''
The convention's governing body is the Conference of the Parties (COP), consisting of all governments (and regional economic integration organizations) that have ratified the treaty. This ultimate authority reviews progress under the Convention, identifies new priorities, and sets work plans for members. The COP can also make amendments to the Convention, create expert advisory bodies, review progress reports by member nations, and collaborate with other international organizations and agreements.

The Conference of the Parties (COP) uses expertise and support from several other bodies that are established by the Convention. In addition to committees or mechanisms established on an ad hoc basis, the main organs are:

'''Secretariat:'''
The CBD Secretariat, based in [[Montreal]], Quebec, Canada, operates under UNEP, the [[United Nations Environment Programme]]. Its main functions are to organize meetings, draft documents, assist member governments in the implementation of the programme of work, coordinate with other international organizations, and collect and disseminate information.

'''Subsidiary Body for Scientific, Technical and Technological Advice (SBSTTA):'''  The SBSTTA is a committee composed of experts from member governments competent in relevant fields. It plays a key role in making recommendations to the COP on scientific and technical issues. The next two meetings of the SBSTTA will be 25–29 November 2019 in Montreal, Canada (SBSTTA-23), and 18–23 May 2020 in Montreal, Canada (SBSTTA-24). The current chair of the SBSTTA Bureau is Mr. Hesiquio Benitez Diaz of [[Mexico]].

'''Subsidiary Body on Implementation (SBI)''':  In 2014, the Conference of the Parties to the Convention on Biological Diversity established the Subsidiary Body on Implementation (SBI) to replace the Ad Hoc Open-ended Working Group on Review of Implementation of the Convention. The four functions and core areas of work of SBI are: (a) review of progress in implementation; (b) strategic actions to enhance implementation; (c) strengthening means of implementation; and (d) operations of the convention and the Protocols. The first meeting of the SBI was held on 2–6 May 2016 and the second meeting was held on 9–13 July 2018, both in Montreal, Canada. The third meeting of the SBI will be held on 25–29 May 2020 in Montreal, Canada. The Bureau of the Conference of the Parties serves as the Bureau of the SBI. The current chair of the SBI is Ms. Charlotta Sörqvist of [[Sweden]].

==Country implementation==

===National Biodiversity Strategies and Action Plans (NBSAP)===
&quot;National Biodiversity Strategies and Action Plans (NBSAPs) are the principal instruments for implementing the Convention at the national level (Article 6). The Convention requires countries to prepare a national biodiversity strategy (or equivalent instrument) and to ensure that this strategy is mainstreamed into the planning and activities of all those sectors whose activities can have an impact (positive and negative) on biodiversity. To date [2012-02-01], 173 Parties have developed NBSAPs in line with Article 6.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cbd.int/nbsap/|title=National Biodiversity Strategies and Action Plans (NBSAPs)|access-date=18 March 2012|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120318122304/http://www.cbd.int/nbsap/|archive-date=18 March 2012|url-status=live|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

For example, the United Kingdom, New Zealand and Tanzania have carried out elaborate responses to conserve individual species and specific habitats. The United States of America, a signatory who has not yet ratified the treaty,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2010/oct/27/harrison-ford-conservation-nagoya | location=London | work=[[The Guardian]] | first=Jonathan | last=Watts | title=Harrison Ford calls on US to ratify treaty on conservation | date=27 October 2010 | access-date=11 December 2016 | archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160605113121/http://www.theguardian.com/environment/2010/oct/27/harrison-ford-conservation-nagoya | archive-date=5 June 2016 | url-status=live | df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; has produced one of the most thorough implementation programs through species Recovery Programs and other mechanisms long in place in the US for species conservation.

Singapore has also established a detailed ''National Biodiversity Strategy and Action Plan''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130606095712/http://www.nparks.gov.sg/cms/docs/nbc/NPark-booklet-final-4sep.pdf|title=Wayback Machine|date=6 June 2013|website=web.archive.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ''National Biodiversity Centre'' of Singapore represents Singapore in the Convention for Biological Diversity.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150119041729/https://www.nparks.gov.sg/cms/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=122&amp;Itemid=124|title=404 - Singapore Garden Photographer of the Year Photo Competition (SGPY)|date=19 January 2015|website=web.archive.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===National Reports===
In accordance with Article 26 of the Convention, Parties prepare national reports on the status of implementation of the Convention.

==Executive secretary==
The current acting executive secretary is Elizabeth Maruma Mrema, who took up this post on 1 December 2019.

The previous executive secretaries were:

[[Cristiana Pașca Palmer]] (2017-2019), [[Braulio Ferreira de Souza Dias]] (2012-2017), [[Ahmed Djoghlaf]] (2006-2012), [[Hamdallah Zedan]] (1998-2005), [[Calestous Juma]] (1995-1998), and [[Angela Cropper]] (1993-1995).

==Nagoya Protocol==
{{main|Nagoya Protocol}}

The Nagoya Protocol on Access to Genetic Resources and the Fair and Equitable Sharing of Benefits Arising from their Utilization to the Convention on Biological Diversity&lt;ref name=&quot;nagoya_text&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.cbd.int/abs/text/ |title=Text of the Nagoya Protocol |work=cbd.int |publisher=Convention on Biological Diversity |access-date=16 January 2012 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20111221013124/http://www.cbd.int/abs/text/ |archive-date=21 December 2011 |url-status=live |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; is a supplementary agreement to the Convention on Biological Diversity. It provides a transparent legal framework for the effective implementation of one of the three objectives of the CBD: the fair and equitable sharing of benefits arising out of the utilization of genetic resources. The Protocol was adopted on 29 October 2010 in Nagoya, Aichi Province, Japan, and entered into force on 12 October 2014. Its objective is the fair and equitable sharing of benefits arising from the utilization of genetic resources, thereby contributing to the conservation and sustainable use of biodiversity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.cbd.int/abs/about/|title= Nagoya Protocol|access-date= 31 May 2011|archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20110521005407/http://www.cbd.int/abs/about/|archive-date= 21 May 2011|url-status= live|df= dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Meetings of the parties==
{{expand section|date=December 2013}}

===1994 COP 1===
The first ordinary meeting of the parties to the convention took place in November and December 1994, in [[Nassau, Bahamas]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.cbd.int/doc/?meeting=cop-01 |title=Meeting Documents&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt; |access-date=4 February 2015 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150204073947/http://www.cbd.int/doc/?meeting=cop-01 |archive-date=4 February 2015 |url-status=live |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===1995 COP 2===
The second ordinary meeting of the parties to the convention took place in November 1995, in [[Jakarta]], [[Indonesia]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.cbd.int/doc/?meeting=cop-02 |title=Meeting Documents&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt; |access-date=4 February 2015 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150204070833/http://www.cbd.int/doc/?meeting=cop-02 |archive-date=4 February 2015 |url-status=live |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===1996 COP 3===
The third ordinary meeting of the parties to the convention took place in November 1996, in [[Buenos Aires]], [[Argentina]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.cbd.int/doc/?meeting=cop-03 |title=Meeting Documents&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt; |access-date=4 February 2015 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150204071100/http://www.cbd.int/doc/?meeting=cop-03 |archive-date=4 February 2015 |url-status=live |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===1998 COP 4===
The fourth ordinary meeting of the parties to the convention took place in May 1998, in [[Bratislava]], [[Slovakia]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.cbd.int/doc/?meeting=cop-04 |title=Meeting Documents&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt; |access-date=4 February 2015 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150204073843/http://www.cbd.int/doc/?meeting=cop-04 |archive-date=4 February 2015 |url-status=live |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===1999 EXCOP 1===
The First Extraordinary Meeting of the Conference of the Parties took place in February 1999, in [[Cartagena, Colombia]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.cbd.int/doc/?meeting=excop-01 |title=Meeting Documents&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt; |access-date=4 February 2015 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150204070447/http://www.cbd.int/doc/?meeting=excop-01 |archive-date=4 February 2015 |url-status=live |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===2000 COP 5===
The fifth ordinary meeting of the parties to the convention took place in May 2000, in [[Nairobi]], [[Kenya]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.cbd.int/doc/?meeting=cop-05 |title=Meeting Documents&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt; |access-date=4 February 2015 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150204064900/http://www.cbd.int/doc/?meeting=cop-05 |archive-date=4 February 2015 |url-status=live |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===2002 COP 6===
The sixth ordinary meeting of the parties to the convention took place in April 2002, in [[The Hague]], [[Netherlands]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.cbd.int/doc/?meeting=cop-06 |title=Meeting Documents&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt; |access-date=4 February 2015 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150204071123/http://www.cbd.int/doc/?meeting=cop-06 |archive-date=4 February 2015 |url-status=live |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===2004 COP 7===
The seventh ordinary meeting of the parties to the convention took place in February 2004, in [[Kuala Lumpur]], [[Malaysia]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.cbd.int/doc/?meeting=cop-07 |title=Meeting Documents&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt; |access-date=4 February 2015 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150204070722/http://www.cbd.int/doc/?meeting=cop-07 |archive-date=4 February 2015 |url-status=live |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===2006 COP 8===
The eighth ordinary meeting of the parties to the convention took place in March 2006, in [[Curitiba]], Brazil.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cbd.int/doc/?meeting=cop-08|title=Eighth Ordinary Meeting of the Conference of the Parties to the Convention on Biological Diversity (COP 8)|access-date=12 December 2013|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131217205149/http://www.cbd.int/doc/?meeting=cop-08|archive-date=17 December 2013|url-status=live|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===2008 COP 9===
The ninth ordinary meeting of the parties to the convention took place in May 2008, in [[Bonn]], [[Germany]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.cbd.int/cop9/default.shtml |title=Welcome to COP 9&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt; |access-date=4 February 2015 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150204071922/http://www.cbd.int/cop9/default.shtml |archive-date=4 February 2015 |url-status=live |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===2010 COP 10===
The tenth ordinary meeting of the parties to the convention took place in October 2010, in [[Nagoya]], [[Japan]].&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.cbd.int/cop10/ |title=Welcome to COP 10&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt; |access-date=29 November 2010 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20101204032237/http://www.cbd.int/cop10/ |archive-date=4 December 2010 |url-status=live |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===2012 COP 11===
{{Main|2012 Hyderabad Biodiversity Conference}}
Leading up to the Conference of the Parties (COP 11) meeting on biodiversity in [[Hyderabad, India]] 2012, preparations for a World Wide Views on Biodiversity has begun, involving old and new partners and building on the experiences from the [[World Wide Views on Global Warming]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://biodiversity.wwviews.org/ |title=World Wide Views on Biodiversity |access-date=19 December 2011 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171111151129/http://biodiversity.wwviews.org/ |archive-date=11 November 2017 |url-status=live |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===2014 COP 12===
Under the theme, &quot;Biodiversity for Sustainable Development,&quot; thousands of representatives of governments, NGOs, indigenous peoples, scientists and the private sector gathered in [[Pyeongchang County|Pyeongchang]], Republic of Korea in October 2014 for the 12th meeting of the Conference of the Parties to the Convention on Biological Diversity (COP 12).&lt;ref&gt;http://www.cbd.int/cop2014; Webcasting: {{cite web |url=http://www.liveto.com/cop12/floor/index.html |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2014-10-06 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20141006120510/http://www.liveto.com/cop12/floor/index.html |archivedate=6 October 2014 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

From 6–17 October 2014, Parties discussed the implementation of the Strategic Plan for Biodiversity 2011-2020 and its Aichi Biodiversity Targets, which are to be achieved by the end of this decade. The results of Global Biodiversity Outlook 4, the flagship assessment report of the CBD informed the discussions.

The conference gave a mid-term evaluation to the UN Decade on Biodiversity (2011-2020) initiative, which aims to promote the conservation and sustainable use of nature.
 
At the end of the meeting, the meeting adopted the &quot;Pyeongchang Road Map,&quot; which addresses ways to achieve biodiversity through technology cooperation, funding and strengthening the capacity of developing countries.&lt;ref&gt;(Source http://www.cbd.int/doc/press/2014/pr-2014-10-06-cop-12-en.pdf)&lt;/ref&gt;

===2016 COP 13===
[[File:COP13 Mexico conference.jpg|thumb|COP13 Mexico meeting]]
The thirteenth ordinary meeting of the parties to the convention took place between 2 and 17 December 2016 in Cancun, Mexico.

===2018 COP 14===
The fourteenth ordinary meeting of the parties to the convention took place on 17–29 November 2018, in 
[[Sharm El-Sheikh]], Egypt.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=CBD Secretariat |title=COP 14 - Fourteenth meeting of the Conference of the Parties to the Convention on Biological Diversity |url=https://www.cbd.int/conferences/2018/cop-14/documents |website=Conference of the Parties (COP) |accessdate=8 April 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 2018 UN Biodiversity Conference closed on 29 November 2018 with broad international agreement on reversing the global destruction of nature and [[biodiversity loss]] threatening all forms of life on Earth. Parties adopted the [https://www.cbd.int/doc/publications/cbd-ts-93-en.pdf Voluntary Guidelines] for the design and effective implementation of [[Ecosystem-based adaptation|ecosystem-based approaches to climate change adaptation]] and disaster risk reduction.&lt;ref&gt;CBD/COP/DEC/14/5. 30 November 2018. https://www.cbd.int/decisions/cop/?m=cop-14&lt;/ref&gt; Governments also agreed to accelerate action to achieve the Aichi Biodiversity Targets, agreed in 2010, from now until 2020. Work to achieve these targets will take place at the global, regional, national and subnational levels.

==Commemorative periods==
2010 was the [[International Year of Biodiversity]] and the Secretariat of the CBD was its focal point. Following a recommendation of CBD signatories during COP 10 at [[Nagoya]] in October 2010, the UN, on 22 December 2010, declared 2011 to 2020 as the [[United Nations Decade on Biodiversity]].

==Criticism==
There have been criticisms against CBD that the Convention has been weakened in implementation due to the resistance of Western countries to the implementation of the pro-South provisions of the Convention.&lt;ref&gt;Faizi, S (2004) The Unmaking of a Treaty. Biodiversity 5(3) 2004&lt;/ref&gt; CBD is also regarded as a case of a hard treaty gone soft in the implementation trajectory.&lt;ref&gt;Harrop, Stuart &amp; Pritchard, Diana. (2011). A Hard Instrument Goes Soft: The Implications of the Convention on Biological Diversity's Current Trajectory. Global Environmental Change-human and Policy Dimensions - GLOBAL ENVIRON CHANGE. 21. 474-480. 10.1016/j.gloenvcha.2011.01.014.&lt;/ref&gt; The argument to enforce the treaty as a legally binding multilateral instrument with the Conference of Parties reviewing the infractions and non-compliance is also gaining strength.&lt;ref&gt;Faizi, S (2012) CBD: Putting the focus on enforcement. Square Brackets. Issue No. 7. October, 2012&lt;/ref&gt;

Although the convention explicitly states that all forms of life are covered by its provisions,&lt;ref name=&quot;cbd1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cbd.int/convention/text/|title=Text of the CBD|publisher=www.cbd.int|accessdate=7 November 2014|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170831103213/https://www.cbd.int/convention/text/|archive-date=31 August 2017|url-status=live|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; examination of reports and of national biodiversity strategies and action plans submitted by participating countries shows that in practice this is not happening. The fifth report of the European Union, for example, makes frequent reference to animals (particularly fish) and plants, but does not mention [[bacteria]], [[fungi]] or [[protists]] at all.&lt;ref name=&quot;cbd_eur1&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.cbd.int/doc/world/eur/eur-nr-05-en.pdf |title=Fifth Report of the European Union to the Convention on Biological Diversity. June 2014 |publisher=www.cbd.int |accessdate=7 November 2014 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150903214536/https://www.cbd.int/doc/world/eur/eur-nr-05-en.pdf |archive-date=3 September 2015 |url-status=live |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; The International Society for Fungal Conservation has assessed more than 100 of these CBD documents for their coverage of fungi using defined criteria to place each in one of six categories. No documents were assessed as good or adequate, less than 10% as nearly adequate or poor, and the rest as deficient, seriously deficient or totally deficient.&lt;ref name=&quot;isfc1&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.fungal-conservation.org/micheli.htm |title=The Micheli Guide to Fungal Conservation |publisher=www.fungal-conservation.org |accessdate=7 November 2014 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150219063643/http://www.fungal-conservation.org/micheli.htm |archive-date=19 February 2015 |url-status=live |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
Furthermore, intensive monoculture and human overpopulation are the two most pertinent biodiversity issues to address.

Scientists working with biodiversity and medical research are expressing fears that the Nagoya Protocol is counterproductive, and will hamper disease prevention and conservation efforts,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://science.sciencemag.org/content/360/6396/1405.full|title= When the cure kills—CBD limits biodiversity research|website= science.sciencemag.org|access-date= 2018-11-28|archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20181128212203/http://science.sciencemag.org/content/360/6396/1405.full|archive-date= 28 November 2018|url-status= live|df= dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; and that the threat of imprisonment of scientists will have a chilling effect on research.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.nature.com/news/biopiracy-ban-stirs-red-tape-fears-1.16028|title= Biopiracy ban stirs red-tape fears|access-date= 28 November 2018|archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20171018050656/http://www.nature.com/news/biopiracy-ban-stirs-red-tape-fears-1.16028|archive-date= 18 October 2017|url-status= live|df= dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; Non-commercial researchers and institutions such as [[natural history museum]]s fear maintaining biological reference collections and exchanging material between institutions will become difficult,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title=The Nagoya Protocol on Access and Benefit SharingInternational treaty poses challenges for biological collections|first=Myrna E.|last=Watanabe|date=1 June 2015|journal=BioScience|volume=65|issue=6|pages=543–550|doi=10.1093/biosci/biv056}}&lt;/ref&gt; and medical researchers have expressed alarm at plans to expand the protocol to make it illegal to publicly share genetic information, e.g. via [[GenBank]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://science.sciencemag.org/content/362/6413/404|title= Threats to timely sharing of pathogen sequence data|website= science.sciencemag.org|access-date= 2018-11-28|archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20181128164731/http://science.sciencemag.org/content/362/6413/404|archive-date= 28 November 2018|url-status= live|df= dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

William Y. Brown from Brookings institutions has mentioned that the Convention on Biological Diversity should include the [[Gene bank|preservation of intact genomes and viable cells]] for every known species and for new species as they are discovered.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title=Invest in a DNA bank for all species|first=William Y.|last=Brown|date=3 August 2011|journal=Nature|volume=476|issue=7361|pages=399|doi=10.1038/476399a|pmid=21866143}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also ==
* [[2010 Biodiversity Indicators Partnership]]
* [[2010 Biodiversity Target]]
* [[Agreement on Trade-Related Aspects of Intellectual Property Rights]] (TRIPs)
* [[Biodiversity banking]]
* [[Biological Diversity Act, 2002]]
* [[Biopiracy]]
* [[Bioprospecting]]
* [[Biosphere Reserve]]
* [[Convention on the Conservation of Migratory Species of Wild Animals]]
* [[Convention on the International Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Flora and Fauna]]
* [[Convention on Wetlands of International Importance, especially as Waterfowl Habitat]]
* [[Ecotourism]]
* [[Endangered species]]
* [[Endangered Species Recovery Plan]]
* [[Environmental agreements]]
* [[Environmental Modification Convention]], another ban on [[weather modification]] / [[climate engineering]].
* [[Globally Important Agricultural Heritage Systems|Globally Important Agricultural Heritage Systems (GIAHS)]]
* [[Green Development Initiative (GDI)]]
* [[Holocene extinction]]
* [[Intergovernmental Science-Policy Platform on Biodiversity and Ecosystem Services]]
* [[International Cooperative Biodiversity Group]]s
* [[International Organization for Biological Control]]
* [[International Treaty on Plant Genetic Resources for Food and Agriculture]]
* [[International Year of Biodiversity]]
* [[Migratory Bird Treaty Act of 1918]]
* [[National Biodiversity Centre (Singapore)#Singapore Red Data Book|Red Data Book of Singapore]]
* [[Red Data Book of the Russian Federation]]
* [[Satoyama]]
* [[Sustainable forest management]]
* [[United Nations Convention to Combat Desertification]]
* [[United Nations Decade on Biodiversity]]
* [[United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change]]
* [[World Conservation Monitoring Centre]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

''This article is partly based on the relevant entry in the [[CIA World Factbook]], {{As of|2008|lc=on}} edition.''

==Further reading==
*Davis, K. 2008. A CBD manual for botanic gardens [http://www.bgci.org/files/cbd_manual.pdf English version], [http://www.bgci.org/files/cbd_manual_italian.pdf Italian version] [[Botanic Gardens Conservation International]] (BGCI)
There are indeed several comprehensive publications on the subject, the given reference covers only one small aspect

==External links==
* [https://www.cbd.int/ The Convention on Biological Diversity (CBD)] website
* [https://www.cbd.int/convention/convention.shtml Text of the Convention] from CBD website
*[http://treaties.un.org/pages/ViewDetails.aspx?src=TREATY&amp;mtdsg_no=XXVII-8&amp;chapter=27&amp;lang=en Ratifications] at depositary
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20101231072643/http://www.bgci.org/ourwork/1414/ Case studies on the implementation of the Convention] from BGCI website with links to relevant articles
* [http://legal.un.org/avl/ha/cpbcbd/cpbcbd.html Introductory note by Laurence Boisson de Chazournes, procedural history note and audiovisual material] on the ''Convention on Biological Diversity'' in the [http://legal.un.org/avl/historicarchives.html Historic Archives of the United Nations Audiovisual Library of International Law]

{{Sustainability}}
{{Portal bar|Politics|Environment|Ecology}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Biological Diversity Convention}}
[[Category:Convention on Biological Diversity| 01]]&lt;!--article's eponymous cat always placed first--&gt;
[[Category:Biodiversity|C]]
[[Category:Environmental treaties|Convention]]
[[Category:United Nations treaties]]
[[Category:Treaties concluded in 1992]]
[[Category:Treaties entered into force in 1993]]
[[Category:1992 in the environment|.Convention on Biodiversity]]
[[Category:1993 in the environment|.Convention on Biodiversity]]
[[Category:1992 in the United Nations|Convention on Biodiversity]]
[[Category:1993 in the United Nations|Convention on Biodiversity]]
[[Category:1992 in science|Convention on Biodiversity]]
[[Category:1993 in science|Convention on Biodiversity]]
[[Category:Animal treaties]]
[[Category:Commercialization of traditional medicines|Convention]]
[[Category:International sustainable development|Convention]]
[[Category:Traditional knowledge|Convention]]
[[Category:1992 in biotechnology|Convention on Biodiversity]]
[[Category:1993 in biotechnology|Convention on Biodiversity]]
[[Category:Treaties entered into by the European Union]]
[[Category:Treaties of the Afghan Transitional Administration]]
[[Category:Treaties of Albania]]
[[Category:Treaties of Algeria]]
[[Category:Treaties of Andorra]]
[[Category:Treaties of Angola]]
[[Category:Treaties of Antigua and Barbuda]]
[[Category:Treaties of Argentina]]
[[Category:Treaties of Armenia]]
[[Category:Treaties of Australia]]
[[Category:Treaties of Austria]]
[[Category:Treaties of Azerbaijan]]
[[Category:Treaties of the Bahamas]]
[[Category:Treaties of Bahrain]]
[[Category:Treaties of Bangladesh]]
[[Category:Treaties of Barbados]]
[[Category:Treaties of Belarus]]
[[Category:Treaties of Belgium]]
[[Category:Treaties of Belize]]
[[Category:Treaties of Benin]]
[[Category:Treaties of Bhutan]]
[[Category:Treaties of Bolivia]]
[[Category:Treaties of Bosnia and Herzegovina]]
[[Category:Treaties of Botswana]]
[[Category:Treaties of Brazil]]
[[Category:1992 in Brazil|Convention on Biodiversity]]
[[Category:Treaties of Brunei]]
[[Category:Treaties of Bulgaria]]
[[Category:Treaties of Burkina Faso]]
[[Category:Treaties of Burundi]]
[[Category:Treaties of Cambodia]]
[[Category:Treaties of Cameroon]]
[[Category:Treaties of Canada]]
[[Category:Treaties of Cape Verde]]
[[Category:Treaties of the Central African Republic]]
[[Category:Treaties of Chad]]
[[Category:Treaties of Chile]]
[[Category:Treaties of the People's Republic of China]]
[[Category:Treaties of Colombia]]
[[Category:Treaties of the Comoros]]
[[Category:Treaties of the Republic of the Congo]]
[[Category:Treaties of the Cook Islands]]
[[Category:Treaties of Costa Rica]]
[[Category:Treaties of Ivory Coast]]
[[Category:Treaties of Croatia]]
[[Category:Treaties of Cuba]]
[[Category:Treaties of Cyprus]]
[[Category:Treaties of the Czech Republic]]
[[Category:Treaties of North Korea]]
[[Category:Treaties of Zaire]]
[[Category:Treaties of Denmark]]
[[Category:Treaties of Djibouti]]
[[Category:Treaties of Dominica]]
[[Category:Treaties of the Dominican Republic]]
[[Category:Treaties of Ecuador]]
[[Category:Treaties of Egypt]]
[[Category:Treaties of El Salvador]]
[[Category:Treaties of Equatorial Guinea]]
[[Category:Treaties of Eritrea]]
[[Category:Treaties of Estonia]]
[[Category:Treaties of the Transitional Government of Ethiopia]]
[[Category:Treaties of Fiji]]
[[Category:Treaties of Finland]]
[[Category:Treaties of France]]
[[Category:Treaties of Gabon]]
[[Category:Treaties of the Gambia]]
[[Category:Treaties of Georgia (country)]]
[[Category:Treaties of Germany]]
[[Category:Treaties of Ghana]]
[[Category:Treaties of Greece]]
[[Category:Treaties of Grenada]]
[[Category:Treaties of Guatemala]]
[[Category:Treaties of Guinea]]
[[Category:Treaties of Guinea-Bissau]]
[[Category:Treaties of Guyana]]
[[Category:Treaties of Haiti]]
[[Category:Treaties of Honduras]]
[[Category:Treaties of Hungary]]
[[Category:Treaties of Iceland]]
[[Category:Treaties of India]]
[[Category:Treaties of Indonesia]]
[[Category:Treaties of Iran]]
[[Category:Treaties of Iraq]]
[[Category:Treaties of Ireland]]
[[Category:Treaties of Israel]]
[[Category:Treaties of Italy]]
[[Category:Treaties of Jamaica]]
[[Category:Treaties of Japan]]
[[Category:Treaties of Jordan]]
[[Category:Treaties of Kazakhstan]]
[[Category:Treaties of Kenya]]
[[Category:Treaties of Kiribati]]
[[Category:Treaties of Kuwait]]
[[Category:Treaties of Kyrgyzstan]]
[[Category:Treaties of Laos]]
[[Category:Treaties of Latvia]]
[[Category:Treaties of Lebanon]]
[[Category:Treaties of Lesotho]]
[[Category:Treaties of Liberia]]
[[Category:Treaties of the Libyan Arab Jamahiriya]]
[[Category:Treaties of Liechtenstein]]
[[Category:Treaties of Lithuania]]
[[Category:Treaties of Luxembourg]]
[[Category:Treaties of Madagascar]]
[[Category:Treaties of Malawi]]
[[Category:Treaties of Malaysia]]
[[Category:Treaties of the Maldives]]
[[Category:Treaties of Mali]]
[[Category:Treaties of Malta]]
[[Category:Treaties of the Marshall Islands]]
[[Category:Treaties of Mauritania]]
[[Category:Treaties of Mauritius]]
[[Category:Treaties of Mexico]]
[[Category:Treaties of the Federated States of Micronesia]]
[[Category:Treaties of Monaco]]
[[Category:Treaties of Mongolia]]
[[Category:Treaties of Montenegro]]
[[Category:Treaties of Morocco]]
[[Category:Treaties of Mozambique]]
[[Category:Treaties of Myanmar]]
[[Category:Treaties of Namibia]]
[[Category:Treaties of Nauru]]
[[Category:Treaties of Nepal]]
[[Category:Treaties of the Netherlands]]
[[Category:Treaties of New Zealand]]
[[Category:Treaties of Nicaragua]]
[[Category:Treaties of Niger]]
[[Category:Treaties of Nigeria]]
[[Category:Treaties of Niue]]
[[Category:Treaties of Norway]]
[[Category:Treaties of Oman]]
[[Category:Treaties of Pakistan]]
[[Category:Treaties of Palau]]
[[Category:Treaties of the State of Palestine]]
[[Category:Treaties of Panama]]
[[Category:Treaties of Papua New Guinea]]
[[Category:Treaties of Paraguay]]
[[Category:Treaties of Peru]]
[[Category:Treaties of the Philippines]]
[[Category:Treaties of Poland]]
[[Category:Treaties of Portugal]]
[[Category:Treaties of Qatar]]
[[Category:Treaties of South Korea]]
[[Category:Treaties of Moldova]]
[[Category:Treaties of Romania]]
[[Category:Treaties of Russia]]
[[Category:Treaties of Rwanda]]
[[Category:Treaties of Samoa]]
[[Category:Treaties of San Marino]]
[[Category:Treaties of São Tomé and Príncipe]]
[[Category:Treaties of Saudi Arabia]]
[[Category:Treaties of Senegal]]
[[Category:Treaties of Serbia and Montenegro]]
[[Category:Treaties of Seychelles]]
[[Category:Treaties of Sierra Leone]]
[[Category:Treaties of Singapore]]
[[Category:Treaties of Slovakia]]
[[Category:Treaties of Slovenia]]
[[Category:Treaties of the Solomon Islands]]
[[Category:Treaties of the Transitional Federal Government of Somalia]]
[[Category:Treaties of South Africa]]
[[Category:Treaties of Spain]]
[[Category:Treaties of Sri Lanka]]
[[Category:Treaties of Saint Kitts and Nevis]]
[[Category:Treaties of Saint Lucia]]
[[Category:Treaties of Saint Vincent and the Grenadines]]
[[Category:Treaties of South Sudan]]
[[Category:Treaties of the Republic of the Sudan (1985–2011)]]
[[Category:Treaties of Suriname]]
[[Category:Treaties of Eswatini]]
[[Category:Treaties of Sweden]]
[[Category:Treaties of Switzerland]]
[[Category:Treaties of Syria]]
[[Category:Treaties of Tajikistan]]
[[Category:Treaties of Thailand]]
[[Category:Treaties of North Macedonia]]
[[Category:Treaties of East Timor]]
[[Category:Treaties of Togo]]
[[Category:Treaties of Tonga]]
[[Category:Treaties of Trinidad and Tobago]]
[[Category:Treaties of Tunisia]]
[[Category:Treaties of Turkey]]
[[Category:Treaties of Turkmenistan]]
[[Category:Treaties of Tuvalu]]
[[Category:Treaties of Uganda]]
[[Category:Treaties of Ukraine]]
[[Category:Treaties of the United Arab Emirates]]
[[Category:Treaties of the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Treaties of Tanzania]]
[[Category:Treaties of Uruguay]]
[[Category:Treaties of Uzbekistan]]
[[Category:Treaties of Vanuatu]]
[[Category:Treaties of Venezuela]]
[[Category:Treaties of Vietnam]]
[[Category:Treaties of Yemen]]
[[Category:Treaties of Zambia]]
[[Category:Treaties of Zimbabwe]]
[[Category:Treaties extended to Aruba]]
[[Category:Treaties extended to the Netherlands Antilles]]
[[Category:Treaties extended to Jersey]]
[[Category:Treaties extended to the British Virgin Islands]]
[[Category:Treaties extended to the Cayman Islands]]
[[Category:Treaties extended to Gibraltar]]
[[Category:Treaties extended to Saint Helena, Ascension and Tristan da Cunha]]
[[Category:Treaties extended to the Isle of Man]]
[[Category:Treaties extended to Greenland]]
[[Category:Treaties extended to the Faroe Islands]]
[[Category:Treaties extended to Portuguese Macau]]
[[Category:Treaties extended to Hong Kong]]
[[Category:Treaties extended to the Falkland Islands]]
[[Category:Treaties extended to South Georgia and the South Sandwich Islands]]</text>
      <sha1>3a7xzhu31mjmpruawf6zie7290h93oe</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
