  <page>
    <title>CN Tower</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6112</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942172675</id>
      <parentid>942172620</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-23T01:42:54Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Palaeozoic99</username>
        <id>13052057</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* Structure */ edit punctuation</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{About|the tower in Toronto|the tower in Edmonton|CN Tower (Edmonton)}}
{{pp-vandalism|small=yes}}
{{pp-move-indef|small=yes}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=October 2013}}
{{Infobox building
| name               = CN Tower
| native_name        = ''Tour CN''
| alternate_names    = Canadian National Tower, Canada's National Tower
| status             = Complete
| image              = Toronto - ON - Toronto Harbourfront7.jpg
| caption            = &lt;small&gt; CN Tower is the [[List of tallest freestanding structures|world's 9th&lt;!--See linked article--&gt; tallest free-standing structure]].&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref name=tallest&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.skyscrapercenter.com/x/2897013| title=Compare Data: Results| publisher=[[Council on Tall Buildings and Urban Habitat|The Skyscraper Center]]| }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=https://www.thestar.com/news/gta/article/698968| title=CN Tower retains world record as tallest 'tower'| date=September 22, 2009| work=[[Toronto Star]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| location           = {{nowrap|290 Bremner Boulevard}}&lt;br /&gt;[[Toronto]], [[Ontario]]&lt;br /&gt;M5V 3L9
| coordinates        = {{coord|43|38|33.36|N|79|23|13.56|W|region:CA-ON|display=inline,title}}
| start_date         = 1973&lt;ref name=&quot;skyscraper&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;emporis&quot;/&gt;
| completion_date    = 1976
| architect          = [[WZMH Architects]]: &lt;br /&gt; [[John Andrews (architect)|John Andrews]], Webb Zerafa, Menkes Housden&lt;ref name=&quot;great&quot;/&gt;
| owner              = [[Canada Lands Company]]
| cost               = [[Canadian dollar|CAD $]] 63,000,000&lt;ref name=&quot;emporis&quot;/&gt;
| top_floor          = {{convert|446.5|m|ft|1|abbr=on}}
| floor_count        = Equivalent of a 147 story building
| references         = &lt;ref name=&quot;skyscraper&quot;&gt;{{skyscraperpage|21}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;emporis&quot;&gt;{{emporis|112537}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;great&quot;/&gt;
| highest_prev       = [[Ostankino Tower]]
| highest_start      = 1975&lt;ref name=records/&gt;
| highest_end        = 2007&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=https://www.thestar.com/news/gta/article/256177--cn-tower-no-longer-world-s-tallest| work=Toronto Star| title=CN Tower no longer world's tallest| date=September 13, 2007}}{{Dead link|date=August 2019 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;
| highest_next       = [[Burj Khalifa]]
| building_type      = Mixed use:&lt;br /&gt; Observation, telecommunications, attraction, restaurant
| antenna_spire      = {{convert|553.3|m|ft|1|abbr=on}}
| roof               = {{convert|457.2|m|ft|1|abbr=on}}
| elevator_count     = 9&lt;ref name=&quot;great&quot;/&gt;
| opening            = June 26, 1976
| website            = {{URL|http://www.cntower.ca/}}
}}

The '''CN Tower''' ({{lang-fr|Tour CN}}) is a {{convert|553.3|m|ft|1|abbr=on|adj=mid|-high}} [[concrete]] communications and observation [[tower]] located in [[Downtown Toronto|Downtown]] [[Toronto]], [[Ontario]], Canada.&lt;ref name=&quot;skyscraper&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CNTower&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.cntower.ca/portal/GetPage.aspx?at=848| title=Canada's Wonder of the World| publisher=CN Tower| accessdate=September 26, 2007| archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070723015815/http://www.cntower.ca/portal/GetPage.aspx?at=848| archivedate=July 23, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Built on the former [[Railway Lands]], it was completed in 1976. Its name &quot;CN&quot; originally referred to [[Canadian National Railway|Canadian National]], the railway company that built the tower. Following the railway's decision to [[Divestment|divest]] non-core freight railway assets prior to the company's [[privatization]] in 1995, it transferred the tower to the [[Canada Lands Company]], a federal [[Crown corporations of Canada|Crown corporation]] responsible for real estate development.

The CN Tower held the record for the [[List of tallest freestanding structures|world's tallest free-standing structure]] for 32 years until 2007 when it was surpassed by the [[Burj Khalifa]] and was the [[List of tallest towers|world's tallest tower]] until 2009 when it was surpassed by the [[Canton Tower]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/travel/galleries/tallest-structures-in-the-world-through-history/structures13/|title=The world's tallest structures through history| date=April 20, 2017| work=[[The Daily Telegraph]]| location=[[London]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.theworldwonders.com/modern-cn-tower.html| title=Modern World Wonders-CN Tower| website=www.theworldwonders.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=https://www.reuters.com/article/us-ba-tower-elevator-idUSN0923507720080409| title=CN Tower's glass-floored lift not for faint-hearted| date=April 9, 2008| work=[[Reuters]]| last=Mollins| first=Julie}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;canton&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url=https://skyscraperpage.com/cities/?buildingID=36975| title=Canton Tower, Guangzhou| website=[[SkyscraperPage]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is now the ninth tallest free-standing structure in the world and remains the tallest free-standing structure on land in the [[Western Hemisphere]]. In 1995, the CN Tower was declared one of the modern Seven [[Wonders of the World]] by the [[American Society of Civil Engineers]]. It also belongs to the World Federation of Great Towers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| last=Rosenberg| first=Matt| title=Seven Wonders of the World| url=https://www.thoughtco.com/seven-wonders-of-the-world-1435155| publisher=[[Dotdash#2017–present: Closure of About.com, rebranding to multiple publications under Dotdash|ThoughtCo]]| date=March 3, 2017| accessdate=August 30, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;info&quot;&gt;{{cite web| title=The Seven Wonders of the Modern World| url=http://www.infoplease.com/ipa/A0923082.html|publisher=Infoplease.com| accessdate=January 2, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;great&quot;&gt;{{cite web| title=Facts and visitor information on the CN Tower in Canada| url=http://www.great-towers.com/towers/cn-tower/| publisher=The World Federation of Great Towers| accessdate=January 2, 2013| archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160929223832/http://www.great-towers.com/towers/cn-tower/| archive-date=September 29, 2016| url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It is a signature icon of Toronto's [[skyline]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Plummer|first=Kevin|date=September 4, 2007|title=The CN Tower is Dead. Long Live The CN Tower!|url=http://torontoist.com/2007/09/the_cn_tower_is.php|accessdate=November 17, 2008|work=The Torontoist}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.canada.com/topics/travel/story.html?id=057d78dc-4964-422f-ba85-361425ea8126&amp;k=3499 CN Tower celebrates 30th birthday], Broadcast News/canada.com, June 26, 2006 {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150622034959/http://www.canada.com/topics/travel/story.html?id=057d78dc-4964-422f-ba85-361425ea8126&amp;k=3499|date=June 22, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;  and attracts more than two million international visitors annually.&lt;ref name=&quot;great&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;FACTS&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|title=World Wonders and Facts at a Glance|url=http://www.cntower.ca/en-ca/about-us/architecture/world-wonders-and-facts-at-a-glance.html|format=PDF|publisher=CN Tower|accessdate=August 30, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
[[File:Toronto - ON - CN Tower bei Nacht2.jpg|thumb|left|The CN Tower illuminated, as seen from the Toronto Islands]]
The original concept of the CN Tower originated in 1968 when the [[Canadian National Railway]] wanted to build a large TV and radio communication platform to serve the Toronto area, as well as demonstrate the strength of Canadian industry and CN in particular. These plans evolved over the next few years, and the project became official in 1972.

The tower would have been part of Metro Centre (see [[CityPlace, Toronto|CityPlace]]), a large development south of [[Front Street (Toronto)|Front Street]] on the [[Railway Lands]], a large railway switching yard that was being made redundant by newer yards outside the city. Key project team members were NCK Engineering as structural engineer; [[John Andrews (architect)|John Andrews Architects]]; Webb, Zerafa, Menkes, Housden Architects; Foundation Building Construction; and Canron (Eastern Structural Division).&lt;ref name=&quot;skyscraper&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;emporis&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CNTower&quot; /&gt;

As Toronto grew rapidly during the late 1960s and early 1970s, multiple skyscrapers were constructed in the downtown core, most notably [[First Canadian Place]]. The reflective nature of the new buildings compromised the quality of broadcast signals necessitating new, higher antennas that were at least {{convert|300|m|ft|abbr=on}} tall.

At the time, most data communications took place over [[Microwave#Communication|point-to-point microwave]] links, whose dish antennae covered the roofs of large buildings. As each new skyscraper was added to the downtown, former line-of-sight links were no longer possible. CN intended to rent &quot;hub&quot; space for microwave links, visible from almost any building in the Toronto area.

The original plan for the tower envisioned a tripod consisting of three independent cylindrical &quot;pillars&quot; linked at various heights by structural bridges. Had it been built, this design would have been considerably shorter, with the metal antenna located roughly where the concrete section between the main level and the SkyPod lies today. As the design effort continued, it evolved into the current design with a single continuous hexagonal core to the SkyPod, with three support legs blended into the hexagon below the main level, forming a large Y-shape structure at the ground level.&lt;ref name=&quot;CNTower&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ieee&quot;&gt;{{cite web| author=[[The Hahn Company|TrizecHahn]]| title=A Brief Overview of the CN Tower| url=http://www.ieee.ca/millennium/cntower/cntower_overview.html| publisher=[[Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers]]| accessdate=January 2, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The idea for the main level in its current form evolved around this time, but the Space Deck (later renamed SkyPod) was not part of the plans until some time later. One engineer in particular felt that visitors would feel the higher observation deck would be worth paying extra for, and the costs in terms of construction were not prohibitive. It was also some time around this point that it was realized that the tower could become the world's tallest structure, and plans were changed to incorporate subtle modifications throughout the structure to this end.&lt;ref name=&quot;CNTower&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ieee&quot;/&gt;

=== Construction ===
The CN Tower was built by Canada Cement Company&lt;ref name=&quot;Canada Cement Company&quot;&gt;title=Canada Cement Building| url=https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Canada_Cement_Building,_Montreal_04.jpg | access date=August 22, 2019&lt;/ref&gt; (also known as the Cement Foundation Company of Canada at the time),&lt;ref&gt;Barr, Elinar, Jan. 1, 2015, p. 173 | title=Swedes in Canada: Invisible Immigrants |
publisher=[[University of Toronto Press]], Canada, {{ISBN|978-1442613744}},  576 pages| accessdate=August 22, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; a subsidiary of Sweden's [[Skanska]], a global project-development and construction group.

 [[File:Ripleys Aquarium Toronto map.png|thumb|left|Map showing the location of the CN Tower and nearby buildings and structures]]
Construction began on February 6, 1973, with massive excavations at the tower base for the foundation. By the time the foundation was complete, {{convert|56000|t|ST LT|abbr=on|lk=on}} of [[soil|earth]] and [[shale]] were removed to a depth of {{convert|15|m|ft|1|abbr=on}} in the centre, and a base incorporating {{convert|7000|m3|cuyd|abbr=on}} of concrete with {{convert|450|t|ST LT|0|abbr=on}} of [[rebar]] and {{convert|36|t|ST LT|abbr=on}} of [[wire rope|steel cable]] had been built to a thickness of {{convert|6.7|m|ft|abbr=on}}. This portion of the construction was fairly rapid, with only four months needed between the start and the foundation being ready for construction on top.&lt;ref name=&quot;ieee&quot;/&gt;

To create the main support pillar, workers constructed a hydraulically raised [[Slip forming|slipform]] at the base. This was a fairly unprecedented engineering feat on its own, consisting of a large metal platform that raised itself on jacks at about {{convert|6|m|ft|abbr=on}} per day as the concrete below set. Concrete was poured Monday to Friday (and not continuously) by a small team of people until February 22, 1974, at which time it had already become the tallest structure in Canada, surpassing the recently built [[Inco Superstack]] in Sudbury, which was built using similar methods.

In total, the tower contains {{convert|40500|m3|cuyd|abbr=on}} of concrete, all of which was mixed on-site in order to ensure batch consistency. Through the pour, the vertical accuracy of the tower was maintained by comparing the slip form's location to massive [[plumb bob]]s hanging from it, observed by small telescopes from the ground. Over the height of the tower, it varies from true vertical accuracy by only {{convert|29|mm|in|1|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;CNTower&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ieee&quot; /&gt;

[[File:CN Tower40 construction skycrane March 1975 01c.jpg|thumb|right|upright|Skycrane &quot;Olga&quot; lifting antenna segment]]
In August 1974, construction of the main level commenced. Using 45 hydraulic jacks attached to cables strung from a temporary steel crown anchored to the top of the tower, twelve giant steel and wooden bracket forms were slowly raised, ultimately taking about a week to crawl up to their final position. These forms were used to create the brackets that support the main level, as well as a base for the construction of the main level itself. The Space Deck (currently named SkyPod) was built of concrete poured into a wooden frame attached to rebar at the lower level deck, and then reinforced with a large steel compression band around the outside.&lt;ref name=&quot;ieee&quot;/&gt;

The antenna was originally to be raised by crane as well, but during construction the [[Sikorsky S-64 Skycrane]] helicopter became available when the [[United States Army]] sold one to civilian operators. The helicopter, named &quot;Olga&quot;, was first used to remove the crane, and then flew the antenna up in 36 sections.

The flights of the antenna pieces were a minor tourist attraction of their own, and the schedule was printed in the local newspapers. Use of the helicopter saved months of construction time, with this phase taking only three and a half weeks instead of the planned six months. The tower was topped-off on April 2, 1975, after 26 months of construction, officially capturing the height record from [[Moscow]]'s [[Ostankino Tower]], and bringing the total mass to {{convert|118000|t|ST LT|abbr=on}}.

Two years into the construction, plans for Metro Centre were scrapped, leaving the tower isolated on the Railway Lands in what was then a largely abandoned light-industrial space. This caused serious problems for tourists to access the tower. Ned Baldwin, project architect with John Andrews, wrote at the time that &quot;All of the logic which dictated the design of the lower accommodation has been upset,&quot; and that &quot;Under such ludicrous circumstances Canadian National would hardly have chosen this location to build.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| last=Fulford| first=Robert| date=March 13, 1996| title=Accidental city: the transformation of Toronto| publisher=MacFarlane, Walter &amp; Ross| page=32| isbn=978-0395773079}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{clear}}

==== Phases of construction ====
&lt;gallery mode=&quot;packed&quot; heights=&quot;135px&quot; style=&quot;text-align:left&quot;&gt;
File:CN Tower footings 1973.jpg|Constructing the base, July 1973
File:Cntower1974.jpg|Brackets being raised, August 1974
File:CN Tower50 construction skycrane March 1975 01d.jpg|Helicopter lifting part of antenna, March 1975
File:CN Tower under construction (April 1975).jpg|Main pod construction, April 1975
File:CN Tower under construction.jpg|Nearing completion, December 1975
File:CN Tower 1976.jpg|Two months after opening, August 1976
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==== Architects ====
*[[WZMH Architects]]
*[[John Andrews (architect)|John Hamilton Andrews]]
*Webb Zerafa
*Menkes Housden with the help of E.R. Baldwin

=== Opening ===
[[File:Toronto-view-from-cn-tower.jpg|thumb|right|View of Toronto's [[Financial District, Toronto|Financial District]] from the CN Tower in 2008]]
The CN Tower opened to the public on June 26, 1976.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| title=CN Tower celebrates 40 years as a tourist magnet and lightning rod| date=June 25, 2016| accessdate=June 27, 2016| url=https://www.thestar.com/news/gta/2016/06/25/cn-tower-celebrates-40-years-as-a-tourist-magnet-and-lightning-rod.html| last=Botelho-Urbanski| first=Jessica| work=Toronto Star}}&lt;/ref&gt; The construction costs of approximately {{CAD|63 million|link=yes}} (${{formatprice|{{Inflation|CA|63000000|1976}}}} in {{Inflation-year|CA}} dollars){{inflation-fn|CA}} were repaid in fifteen years. [[Canadian National Railway]] sold the tower prior to taking the company private in 1995, when it decided to divest all operations not directly related to its core freight shipping businesses.

From the mid-1970s to the mid-1980s, the CN Tower was practically the only development along Front Street West; it was still possible to see Lake Ontario from the foot of the CN Tower due to the expansive parking lots and lack of development in the area at the time. As the area around the tower was developed, particularly with the completion of the [[Metro Toronto Convention Centre]] (north building) in 1984 and SkyDome in 1989 (renamed [[Rogers Centre]] in 2005), the former [[Railway Lands]] were redeveloped and the tower became the centre of a newly developing entertainment area. Access was greatly improved with the construction of the [[SkyWalk]] in 1989, which connected the tower and SkyDome to the nearby [[Union Station (Toronto)|Union Station]] railway and subway station,  and, in turn, to the city's [[PATH (Toronto)|PATH]] underground pedestrian system. By the mid-1990s, it was the centre of a thriving tourist district. The entire area continues to be an area of intense building, notably a [[Manhattanization|boom]] in [[condominium]] construction in the first quarter of the 21st century, as well as the 2013 opening of the [[Ripley's Aquarium of Canada|Ripley's Aquarium]] by the base of the tower.&lt;ref name=&quot;great&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CNTower&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ieee&quot;/&gt;

== Events ==
[[File:2015 Toronto Pan American Games-Laslovarga.jpeg|thumb|right|Fireworks display on the CN Tower during [[2015 Pan American Games opening ceremony|the opening ceremony]] of the [[2015 Pan American Games]].]]
*While still under construction, the CN Tower officially became the world's tallest free-standing structure on March 31, 1975.&lt;ref name=records/&gt;
*When the CN Tower opened in 1976, there were three public observation points: the SkyPod (then known as the Space Deck) that stands at {{convert|447|m|ft|abbr=on}}, the Indoor Observation Level (later named Indoor Lookout Level) at {{convert|346|m|ft|abbr=on}}, and the Outdoor Observation Terrace (at the same level as the Glass Floor) at {{convert|342|m|ft|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;great&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ieee&quot;/&gt; One floor above the Indoor Observation Level was the Top of Toronto Restaurant, which completed a revolution once every 72 minutes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=General Information |url=https://www.cntower.ca/site_Files/Content/PDF/Press_Kit/CN_Tower_General_Information_2013_Revised.pdf |publisher=CN Tower |date=2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Stuntman [[Dar Robinson]] jumped off of the CN Tower on two occasions in 1979 and 1980. The first was for a scene from the movie ''[[Highpoint (film)|Highpoint]]'', in which Robinson received $250,000 (${{Inflation|CA|250000|1979|fmt=c}} in {{Inflation-year|CA}} dollars){{inflation-fn|CA}} for the stunt. The second was for a personal documentary. Both stunts used a wire decelerator attached to his back.&lt;ref name=&quot;robinson&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title= Man Jumps From CN Tower With No Parachute (Thirty Years Ago)| url= http://torontoist.com/2010/02/man_jumps_from_cn_tower_with_no_parachute_thirty_years_ago/| first=Steve| last=Kupferman| date=February 26, 2010| work=Torontoist}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*On June 26, 1986, the ten-year anniversary of the tower's opening, [[High-rise building|high-rise]] firefighting and rescue advocate [[Dan Goodwin]], in a sponsored publicity event, used his hands and feet to climb the outside of the tower, a feat he performed twice on the same day. Following both ascents, he used multiple rappels to descend to the ground.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| last=Goodwin| first=Dan| title=Dan Goodwin's Building Climbs| url=http://www.skyscraperdefense.com/building_climbs.html| publisher=Skyscraperdefense.com| accessdate=January 2, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*The Glass Floor, at an elevation of {{convert|342|m|ft|abbr=on}}, opened to the public on June 26, 1994.&lt;ref name=&quot;ieee&quot;/&gt;
*From 1997 to January 2004, [[The Hahn Company|TrizecHahn Corporation]] managed the tower and instituted several expansion projects including a [[Canadian dollar|C$]]26 million entertainment expansion and revitalization that included the 1997 addition of two new elevators (to a total of six) and the consequential relocation of the staircase from the north side leg to inside the core of the building, a conversion that also added nine stairs to the climb. TrizecHahn also owned the [[Willis Tower]] (Sears Tower at the time) in Chicago approximately at the same time.
*In 2007, [[light-emitting diode]] (LED) lights replaced the incandescent lights that lit the CN Tower at night, the reason cited that LED lights are more cost and energy efficient than the incandescent lights. The colour of the LED lights can change, compared to the constant white colour of the incandescent lights.
*On September 12, 2007, [[Burj Khalifa]], then under construction and known as Burj Dubai, surpassed the CN Tower as the world's tallest free-standing structure.&lt;ref name=&quot;CBCSurpassed&quot;&gt;{{cite news| title=CN Tower dethroned by Dubai building |url=http://www.cbc.ca/canada/story/2007/09/12/cntower-surpassed.html |work=[[CBC News]] |date=September 12, 2007 |accessdate=April 9, 2008 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100619095709/http://www.cbc.ca/canada/story/2007/09/12/cntower-surpassed.html |archivedate=June 19, 2010 |url-status=live |df=mdy }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*In 2008, glass panels were installed in one of the CN Tower elevators, which established a world record (346 m) for highest glass floor panelled elevator in the world.
*The CN Tower was closed during the [[2010 G20 Toronto summit|G20 summit]] on June 26–27, 2010, for security reasons, given its proximity to the Metro Toronto Convention Centre.
*In 2011, EdgeWalk (where at an elevation of {{convert|356|m|ft}}, visitors tethered to an overhead rail system can walk on the roof of the main pod) opened to the public.&lt;ref name=&quot;ieee&quot;/&gt;
* On July 10, 2015, the CN Tower was incorporated into [[2015 Pan American Games opening ceremony|the opening ceremony]] of the [[2015 Pan American Games]]. A pre-recorded segment featured [[Bruny Surin]] passing the flame to [[Donovan Bailey]] on the EdgeWalk and parachuting into Rogers Centre. A fireworks display off the tower served as the ceremony's finale.
* On July 1, 2017, as part of the nationwide celebrations for [[150th anniversary of Canada|Canada 150]], fireworks were once again shot from the tower in a five-minute display coordinated with the tower lights and music broadcast on a local radio station.

== Structure ==
[[File:Subindotorrecn.ogv|thumb|left|Elevator going up]]
[[File:Restaurante panoramico na Torre CN.ogv|thumb|left|View from 360 Restaurant]]

The CN Tower consists of several substructures. The main portion of the tower is a hollow concrete hexagonal pillar containing the [[Stairs|stairwells]] and power and plumbing connections. The tower's six [[elevator]]s are located in the three inverted angles created by the Tower's hexagonal shape (two elevators per angle). Each of the three elevator shafts is lined with glass, allowing for views of the city as the glass-windowed elevators make their way through the tower. The stairwell was originally located in one of these angles (the one facing north), but was moved into the central hollow of the tower; the tower's new fifth and sixth elevators were placed in the hexagonal angle that once contained the stairwell. On top of the main concrete portion of the tower is a {{convert|102|m|ft|1|adj=on}} tall metal broadcast antenna, carrying television and radio signals. There are three visitor areas: the Glass Floor and Outdoor Observation Terrace, which are both located at an elevation of {{convert|342|m|ft|0}}, the Indoor Lookout Level (formerly known as &quot;Indoor Observation Level&quot;) located at {{convert|346|m|ft|0}}, and the higher SkyPod (formerly known as &quot;Space Deck&quot;) at {{convert|446.5|m|ft|0}},&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://skyscraperpage.com/cities/?buildingID=21 |title=CN Tower |accessdate=April 9, 2008 |work=SkyscraperPage.com |publisher=Skyscraper Source Media |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080406071501/http://skyscraperpage.com/cities/?buildingID=21 |archivedate=April 6, 2008 |url-status=live |df=mdy }}&lt;/ref&gt; just below the metal [[Antenna (radio)|antenna]]. The hexagonal shape is visible between the two areas; however, below the main deck, three large supporting legs give the tower the appearance of a large [[tripod]].

The main deck level is seven storeys, some of which are open to the public. Below the public areas — at {{convert|338|m|ft|1|abbr=on}} — is a large white donut-shaped [[radome]] containing the structure's [[UHF]] transmitters. The [[glass floor]] and outdoor observation deck are at {{convert|342|m|ft|1}}. The glass floor has an area of {{convert|24|m2|sqft|0|abbr=on}} and can withstand a pressure of {{convert|4100|kPa|psi|0|lk=on}}. The floor's thermal glass units are {{convert|64|mm|in|1|abbr=on}} thick, consisting of a pane of {{convert|25|mm|in|1|adj=on}} laminated glass, {{convert|25|mm|in|1|abbr=on}} airspace and a pane of {{convert|13|mm|in|1|abbr=on|adj=on}} laminated glass. In 2008, one elevator was upgraded to add a glass floor panel, believed to have the highest vertical rise of any elevator equipped with this feature.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Canadian Press |authorlink=Canadian Press |title=CN Tower's glass-floor elevator aims for record |url=https://www.thestar.com/News/GTA/article/412944 |work=Toronto Star |date=April 9, 2008 |accessdate=April 9, 2008 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20091018091131/http://www.thestar.com/News/GTA/article/413153 |archivedate=October 18, 2009 |url-status=live |df=mdy}}  Both linked pages include a video of the elevator with glass floor in operation.&lt;/ref&gt;  The Horizons Cafe and the lookout level are at {{convert|346|m|ft|1}}. The 360 Restaurant, a [[revolving restaurant]] that completes a full rotation once every 72 minutes, is at {{convert|351|m|ft|1|abbr=on}}. When the tower first opened, it also featured a disco named Sparkles (at the Indoor Observation Level), billed as the highest disco and dance floor in the world.&lt;ref&gt;Malcolm, Andrew. [https://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=FA0D10F73F5C11728DDDA90994D8415B898BF1D3 &quot;A New High for Disco in Toronto's Tower&quot;], ''[[The New York Times]]'', October 10, 1979. Accessed February 10, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

The SkyPod was once the highest public [[observation deck]] in the world until it was surpassed by the [[Shanghai World Financial Center]] in 2008.&lt;ref name=swfc-e&gt;{{cite web |title=Shanghai World Financial Center |url=http://www.emporis.com/en/wm/bu/?id=shanghaiworldfinancialcenter-shanghai-china |accessdate=May 22, 2008 |publisher=Emporis.com |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080316224038/http://www.emporis.com/en/wm/bu/?id=shanghaiworldfinancialcenter-shanghai-china |archivedate=March 16, 2008 |url-status=live |df=mdy }}&lt;/ref&gt;

A metal staircase reaches the main deck level after 1,776 steps,&lt;ref name=&quot;great&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=CNSTEPS&gt;{{cite news| title=Man climbs CN Tower steps in wheelchair |url=http://www.cbc.ca/canada/story/2002/09/26/wheelchair_020926.html |work=[[CBC News]] |publisher=[[Canadian Broadcasting Corporation]] |date=September 27, 2002 |accessdate=January 4, 2008 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110130060357/http://www.cbc.ca/canada/story/2002/09/26/wheelchair_020926.html |archivedate=January 30, 2011 |url-status=live |df=mdy }}&lt;/ref&gt; and the SkyPod {{convert|100|m|ft|0|abbr=on}} above after 2,579 steps; it is the tallest metal staircase on Earth. These stairs are intended for emergency use only and are not open to the public, except for twice per year for charity stair-climb events.&lt;ref name=WWFClimb&gt;{{cite web |url=http://wwfcentral.ca/NetCommunity/Page.aspx?pid=500&amp;srcid=500 |title=18th Annual Canada Life CN Tower Climb for WWF Canada |accessdate=March 20, 2008 |publisher=[[World Wide Fund for Nature]] (WWF) Canada |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080324105225/http://wwfcentral.ca/NetCommunity/Page.aspx?pid=500&amp;srcid=500 |archive-date=March 24, 2008 |url-status=dead |df=mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;WWFClimb&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;TorontoStarSteps&quot;&gt;{{cite news |first=Leslie |last=Ferenc |title=Corporate climbers ready to step up for charity |url=https://www.thestar.com/news/2007/10/15/corporate_climbers_ready_to_step_up_for_charity.html |work=Toronto Star |date=October 15, 2007 |accessdate=March 20, 2008 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20081215182839/http://www.thestar.com/News/article/266851 |archivedate=December 15, 2008 |url-status=live |df=mdy }}&lt;/ref&gt; The average climber takes approximately 30 minutes to climb to the base of the radome, but the fastest climb on record is 7 minutes and 52 seconds in 1989 by Brendan Keenoy, an [[Ontario Provincial Police]] officer.&lt;ref name=&quot;TorontoStarSteps&quot;/&gt; In 2002, Canadian Olympian and [[Paralympic Games|Paralympic]] champion [[Jeff Adams]] climbed the stairs of the tower in a specially designed [[wheelchair]]. The stairs were originally on one of the three sides of the tower (facing north), with a glass view, but these were later replaced with the third elevator pair and the stairs were moved to the inside of the core.&lt;ref name=&quot;CNSTEPS&quot;/&gt; Top climbs on the new, windowless stairwell used since around 2003 have generally been over ten minutes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=21st Annual Canada Life CN Tower Climb for WWF-Canada| url=http://assets.wwf.ca/downloads/teamresults2011_overallindividuals.cfm| publisher=WWF| accessdate=January 2, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;gallery mode=&quot;packed&quot; heights=&quot;135px&quot; style=&quot;text-align:left&quot;&gt;
insidecntower360.JPG|Inside 360 Restaurant
Toronto - ON - CN Tower Turmkorb.jpg|Main Pod
CN Tower Turmkorb-Modell-blau.png|Cross-section of Main Pod
CN Tower Glass Floor Walk.jpg|Standing on glass floor
CNTowerNastyFall.jpg|View through glass floor
&lt;/gallery&gt;

=== EdgeWalk ===
[[File:EdgeWalk on the CN Tower.jpg|thumb|right|The EdgeWalk]]
On August 1, 2011, the CN Tower opened the EdgeWalk, an amusement in which thrill-seekers can walk on and around the roof of the main pod of the tower at {{convert|356|m|ft|1|abbr=on}}, which is directly above the 360 Restaurant.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| title=New CN Tower attraction offers a walk on the outside| url=https://www.thestar.com/news/article/988150--new-cn-tower-attraction-offers-a-walk-on-the-outside| work=Toronto Star| accessdate=January 3, 2013| date=May 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is the world's highest full-circle, hands-free walk. Visitors are tethered to an overhead rail system and walk around the edge of the CN Tower's main pod above the 360 Restaurant on a {{convert|1.5|m|ft|adj=on}} metal floor.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.cntower.ca/en-CA/Plan-Your-Visit/Attractions/EdgeWalk/EdgeWalk-Overview.html| title=Toronto's Most Extreme Attraction| accessdate=February 25, 2012| quote=It is the world's highest full circle hands-free walk on a 5 ft (1.5 metres) wide ledge encircling the top of the tower's main pod, 356m/1168ft (116 storeys) above the ground.| publisher=CN Tower}}&lt;/ref&gt; The attraction is closed throughout the winter and during periods of electrical storms and high winds.

One of the notable guests who visited EdgeWalk includes Canadian comedian [[Rick Mercer]] as featured on the ninth season his [[CBC Television]] [[news satire]] show, ''[[Rick Mercer Report]]''. There, he was accompanied by Canadian pop singer [[Jann Arden]]. The episode aired on April 10, 2013.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.cbc.ca/mercerreport/episodes/season-9/season-9-episode-1| title=Season 9 - Episode 1| series=Rick Mercer Report| date=April 10, 2013| publisher=CBC Television}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Falling ice danger ===
[[File:Gardiner Expressway Downtown Toronto.jpg|thumb|right|Looking east at the CN Tower from the [[Gardiner Expressway]]]]
A [[freezing rain]] storm on March 2, 2007, resulted in a layer of ice several centimetres thick forming on the side of the tower and other downtown buildings. The sun thawed the ice, and winds of up to {{convert|90|km/h|mph|0|abbr=on}} blew some of it away from the structure. There were fears that cars and windows of nearby buildings would be smashed by large chunks of ice. In response, police closed some streets surrounding the tower. During morning rush hour on March 5 of the same year, police expanded the area of closed streets to include the [[Gardiner Expressway]] {{convert|310|m|ft|0}} away from the tower as increased winds blew the ice farther away, as far north as [[King Street (Toronto)|King Street West]], {{convert|490|m|ft|0|abbr=on}} away, where a [[taxicab]] window was shattered. Subsequently, on March 6, 2007, the Gardiner Expressway reopened after winds abated.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.citynews.ca/news/features_8415.aspx |title=Video: Falling CN Tower Ice |publisher=[[CITY-DT]] |date=March 2, 2007 |accessdate=June 26, 2007 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090723053310/http://www.citynews.ca/news/features_8415.aspx |archivedate=July 23, 2009 |url-status=dead |df=mdy }}&lt;/ref&gt;

On April 16, 2018, falling ice from the CN Tower punctured the roof of the nearby [[Rogers Centre]], causing the [[Toronto Blue Jays]] to postpone the game that day to the following day as a [[doubleheader (baseball)|doubleheader]]; this was the third doubleheader held at the Rogers Centre. On April 20, the CN Tower reopened.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/toronto/cn-tower-closed-since-monday-due-to-falling-ice-concerns-reopens-1.4628235|title=CN Tower, closed since Monday due to falling ice concerns, reopens|date=20 April 2018|publisher=cbc.ca}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Safety features ===
In August 2000, a fire broke out at the [[Ostankino Tower]] in Moscow killing three people and causing extensive damage. The fire was blamed on poor maintenance and outdated equipment. The failure of the fire-suppression systems and the lack of proper equipment for firefighters allowed the fire to destroy most of the interior and spark fears the tower might even collapse.

The Ostankino Tower was completed nine years before the CN Tower and is only {{convert|13|m|ft|abbr=on}} shorter.&lt;ref name=doom&gt;{{cite news|
 url=https://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/europe/fire-in-1800ft-tv-tower-adds-to-russians-feeling-of-doom-5370409.html| title=Fire in 1,800ft TV tower adds to Russians' feeling of doom| first=Helen| last=Womackin| work=[[The Independent]]| date=August 29, 2000}}&lt;/ref&gt; The parallels between the towers led to some concern that the CN Tower could be at risk of a similar tragedy. However, Canadian officials subsequently stated that it is &quot;highly unlikely&quot; that a similar disaster could occur at the CN Tower, as it has important safeguards that were not present in the Ostankino Tower. Specifically, officials cited:

* the fireproof building materials used in the tower's construction,
* frequent and stringent safety inspections,
* an extensive sprinkler system,
* a 24-hour emergency monitoring operation,
* two 68,160-litre (15,000-imperial gallon; 18,006-US gallon) water reservoirs at the top, which are automatically replenished,
* a fire hose at the base of the structure capable of sending 2725 litres (600 imperial gallons; 720 US Gallon) a minute to any location in the tower,
* a ban on natural gas appliances anywhere in the tower (including the restaurant in the main pod),
* an elevator that can be used during a fire as it runs up the outside of the building and can be powered by three emergency generators at the base of the structure (unlike the elevator at the Ostankino Tower, which malfunctioned).&lt;ref name=&quot;safety&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.cbc.ca/canada/story/2000/08/28/CN000828.html |date=November 10, 2000 |title=What if the CN Tower Caught Fire? |work=[[CBC News]] |publisher=[[Canadian Broadcasting Corporation]] |accessdate=June 26, 2007 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100327142807/http://www.cbc.ca/canada/story/2000/08/28/CN000828.html |archivedate=March 27, 2010 |url-status=live |df=mdy }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Officials also noted that the CN Tower has an excellent safety record, although there was an electrical fire in the antennae on August 16, 2017 — the tower's first fire.&lt;ref name=&quot;safety&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=Doherty&gt;{{cite news| url=https://www.thestar.com/news/gta/2017/08/16/fire-crews-tackle-smouldering-fire-at-cn-tower-antenna.html| title=Fire crews tackle smouldering fire at CN Tower antenna| work=Toronto Star| date=August 16, 2017| first=Brennan| last=Doherty| agency=[[The Canadian Press]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| first=Amara| last=McLaughlin| url=http://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/toronto/cn-tower-fire-1.4249033| title=Fire inside broadcasting antenna atop CN Tower now extinguished| work=[[CBC News]]| date=August 16, 2017| accessdate=August 17, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=CTV&gt;{{cite web| url=http://toronto.ctvnews.ca/cn-tower-open-for-business-after-early-morning-fire-in-antenna-mast-1.3547839| title=CN Tower open for business after early morning fire in antenna mast| work=[[CFTO-DT|CTV Toronto News]]| first=Codi| last=Wilson| date=August 16, 2017| accessdate=August 17, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, other supertall structures built between 1967 and 1976 — such as the [[Willis Tower]] (formerly the Sears Tower), the [[World Trade Center (1973–2001)|World Trade Center]] (until its [[September 11 attacks|destruction on September 11, 2001]]), the [[Fernsehturm Berlin]], the [[Aon Center (Chicago)|Aon Center]], [[875 North Michigan Avenue]] (formerly the John Hancock Center), and [[First Canadian Place]] — also have excellent safety records, which suggests that the Ostankino Tower accident was a rare safety failure, and that the likelihood of similar events occurring at other supertall structures is extremely low.

{{wide image|Toronto panorama.jpg|1000px|Panoramic view from the CN Tower. The [[Toronto Islands]] and the [[Billy Bishop Toronto City Airport|island airport]] on Lake Ontario are visible on the left side of the image while buildings of [[Financial District, Toronto|Toronto's Financial District]] are visible on the right.}}

== Lighting ==
[[File:CN Tower lights in-memoriam to Paris attacks.JPG|thumb|right|The CN Tower illuminated in the colours of the [[Flag of France|French flag]] in memoriam to the [[November 2015 Paris attacks]]]]
The CN Tower was originally lit at night with [[Incandescent light bulb|incandescent]] lights, which were removed in 1997 because they were inefficient and expensive to repair. In June 2007, the tower was outfitted with 1,330 super-bright [[light-emitting diode|LED]] lights inside the elevator shafts, shooting over the main pod and upward to the top of the tower's mast to light the tower from dusk until 2 a.m. The official opening ceremony took place on June 28 before the [[Canada Day]] holiday weekend.

The tower changes its lighting scheme on holidays and to commemorate major events. After the [[95th Grey Cup]] in Toronto, the tower was lit in green and white to represent the colours of the Grey Cup champion [[Saskatchewan Roughriders]].&lt;ref name=&quot;LED&quot;&gt;{{cite press release| title=Highlighting the CN Tower — Testing of Innovative Illumination Technology Begins Early June 2007| publisher=CN Tower| date=June 28, 2007| url=http://www.cntower.ca/site_Files/.../CN_Tower_lighting_facts_2012.pdf| accessdate=April 9, 2008}}{{dead link|date=December 2017 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt; From sundown on August 27, 2011, to sunrise the following day, the tower was lit in orange, the official colour of the [[New Democratic Party]] (NDP), to commemorate the [[Death and state funeral of Jack Layton|death]] of federal NDP leader and leader of the official opposition [[Jack Layton]].&lt;ref name=layton&gt;{{cite news| title=Jack Layton's 'passion, civility' honoured at funeral| url=http://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/story/2011/08/27/jack-layton-state-funeral-toronto.html| publisher=[[CBC News]]| accessdate=August 28, 2011| date=August 27, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; When former [[President of South Africa|South African president]] [[Nelson Mandela]] [[Death of Nelson Mandela|died]], the tower was lit in the colours of the [[Flag of South Africa|South African flag]]. When former [[Minister of Finance (Canada)|federal finance minister]] under [[Stephen Harper]]'s [[Conservative Party of Canada|Conservatives]] [[Jim Flaherty]] died, the tower was lit in green to reflect his [[Irish Canadians|Irish Canadian]] heritage. On the night of the [[November 2015 Paris attacks|attacks on Paris on November 13, 2015]], the tower displayed the colours of the [[Flag of France|French flag]].

Programmed from a [[desktop computer]] with a [[wireless network interface controller]] in [[Burlington, Ontario]], the LEDs use less energy to light than the previous incandescent lights (10% less energy than the dimly lit version and 60% less than the brightly lit version).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.thestar.com/news/2007/05/30/come_canada_day_cn_tower_will_once_again_light_up_the_night.html |title=Come Canada Day, CN Tower will once again light up the night |first=Debra |last=Black |date=May 30, 2007 |work=Toronto Star |accessdate=July 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The estimated cost to use the LEDs is $1,000 per month.

During the spring and autumn [[bird migration]] seasons, the lights would be turned off to comply with the voluntary Fatal Light Awareness Program, which &quot;encourages buildings to dim unnecessary exterior lighting to mitigate bird mortality during spring and summer migration.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ledsmagazine.com/news/4/6/21 |title=CN Tower in Toronto receives LED lighting treatment |work=LEDs Magazine |date=June 18, 2007 |accessdate=July 17, 2011 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20111001092711/http://www.ledsmagazine.com/news/4/6/21 |archive-date=October 1, 2011 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Date !! Colour !! Occasion
|-
| Ongoing || [[Red]] and [[White]] || Top of the hour CN Tower light show
|-
| January 26 || [[Shades of blue|Light Blue]] and [[Yellow]] || World Alzheimer Day
|-
| February 4 || [[Orange (colour)|Orange]] and [[Blue]] || [[World Cancer Day]]
|-
| February 14 || [[Red]] || [[Valentine's Day]]
|-
| March 17 || Green || [[Saint Patrick's Day]]
|-
| March 21–June 20 || Decreased Lighting || [[Spring (season)|Bird Migration - Lighting is decreased during spring bird migration]]
|-
| September 23–December 20 || Decreased Lighting || [[Autumn|Bird Migration - Lighting is decreased during autumn bird migration]]
|-
| December || [[Red]] and [[Green]] || [[Christmas and holiday season|Season's Greetings]]
|-
| December 1 || [[Red]] || [[World AIDS Day]]
|-
| December 6 || [[Purple]] || [[National Day of Remembrance and Action on Violence Against Women|White Ribbon Day]]
|-
| December 10 || [[Yellow]] || [[Human Rights Day]]
|-
| December 21 || [[Blue]] and [[White]] || [[Winter solstice|First Day of Winter]]
|-
| December 31 || Countdown to {{NEXTYEAR}} and Light Show || [[New Year's Eve]]
|}

== Height comparisons ==
[[File:CN Tower seen from its base.jpg|thumb|left|upright|CN Tower as seen from its base.]]
[[File:Dubai-CN-Sears-towers.svg|thumb|upright|• [[Burj Khalifa]], Dubai&lt;br /&gt;• CN Tower, Toronto&lt;br /&gt;• [[Willis Tower]], Chicago]]
{{tallest towers in the world.svg|cu}}
The CN Tower is the tallest freestanding structure in the Western Hemisphere. As of 2013, there are only two other [[List of tallest freestanding structures|freestanding structures in the Western Hemisphere]] which exceed {{convert|500|m|ft|1|abbr=on}} in height; the [[Willis Tower]] in Chicago, which stands at {{convert|527|m|ft|1|abbr=on}} when measured to its pinnacle; and the topped-out [[One World Trade Center]] in New York City, which has a pinnacle height of {{convert|541.33|m|ft|1|abbr=on}}, or approximately {{convert|12|m|ft|1|abbr=on}} shorter than the CN Tower. Due to the symbolism of the number 1776 (the year of the signing of the [[United States Declaration of Independence]]), the height of One World Trade Center is unlikely to be increased. The proposed [[Chicago Spire]] was expected to exceed the height of the CN Tower, but its construction was halted early due to financial difficulties amid the [[Great Recession]], and was eventually cancelled in 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.businessweek.com/innovate/next/archives/2010/02/calatrava_dances_onto_a_new_stage.html| title=Calatrava Dances onto a New Stage| work=[[Bloomberg Businessweek]]| url-status=dead| archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110213045741/http://www.businessweek.com/innovate/next/archives/2010/02/calatrava_dances_onto_a_new_stage.html| archivedate=February 13, 2011| df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Height distinction debate ===

==== &quot;World's Tallest Tower&quot; title ====
''[[Guinness World Records]]'' has called the CN Tower &quot;the world's tallest self-supporting tower&quot; and &quot;the world's tallest free-standing tower&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Guinness 1982&quot;&gt;
{{cite book| last=McWhirter| first=Norris| authorlink=Norris McWhirter| title=Guinness Book of World Records 1982| year= 1981| publisher=[[Sterling Publishing|Sterling Publishing Co., Inc.]]| location= New York| isbn=978-0-8069-0225-8|oclc=7902975| page=704}} Reference is on page 275.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Guinness 2005&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.guinnessworldrecords.com/content_pages/record_subcategory.asp?txtDirection=right&amp;;txtButtonWasHit=true&amp;txtPage=4&amp;subcategoryid=37 |title=Guinness Book of World Records 2005 – Science and Technology &lt;&lt; Buildings |accessdate=2010-01-05 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110826071440/http://www.guinnessworldrecords.com/content_pages/record_subcategory.asp?txtDirection=right&amp;%3BtxtButtonWasHit=true&amp;txtPage=4&amp;subcategoryid=37 |archivedate=August 26, 2011 |df=mdy}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Although Guinness did list this description of the CN Tower under the heading &quot;tallest building&quot; at least once,&lt;ref name=&quot;Guinness 2005&quot;/&gt; it has also listed it under &quot;tallest tower&quot;, omitting it from its list of &quot;tallest buildings.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Guinness 1982&quot;/&gt; In 1996, Guinness changed the tower's classification to &quot;World's Tallest Building and Freestanding Structure&quot;. [[Emporis]] and the [[Council on Tall Buildings and Urban Habitat]] both listed the CN Tower as the [[List of tallest buildings and structures|world's tallest free-standing structure on land]], and specifically state that the CN Tower is not a true building, thereby awarding the title of [[List of tallest buildings|world's tallest building]] to [[Taipei 101]], which is {{convert|44|m|ft|0}} shorter than the CN Tower.&lt;ref name=&quot;info&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=CTBUH&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ctbuh.org/Resources/TallestDatabase/tabid/123/Default.aspx |title=CTBUH Tall Building Database |accessdate=April 10, 2008 |publisher=[[Council on Tall Buildings and Urban Habitat]] |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20081025030731/http://www.ctbuh.org/Resources/TallestDatabase/tabid/123/Default.aspx |archivedate=October 25, 2008 |url-status=dead |df=mdy }}&lt;/ref&gt; The issue of what was tallest became moot when Burj Khalifa, then under construction, exceeded the height of the CN Tower in 2007 (see below).

Although the CN Tower contains a restaurant, a gift shop and multiple observation levels, it does not have floors continuously from the ground, and therefore [[List of tallest buildings and structures#Tallest buildings|it is not considered a building]] by the Council on Tall Buildings and Urban Habitat (CTBUH) or Emporis. CTBUH defines a building as &quot;a structure that is designed for residential, business, or manufacturing purposes. An essential characteristic of a building is that it has floors.&quot;&lt;ref name=CTBUH/&gt; The CN Tower and other similar structures—such as the Ostankino Tower in Moscow, Russia; the [[Oriental Pearl Tower]] in [[Shanghai]], China; the [[Stratosphere Las Vegas|Stratosphere Tower]] in [[Las Vegas]], Nevada, United States; and the [[Eiffel Tower]] in [[Paris]], France—are categorized as &quot;towers&quot;, which are free-standing structures that may have observation decks and a few other habitable levels, but do not have floors from the ground up. The CN Tower was the tallest tower by this definition until 2010 (see below).&lt;ref name=&quot;info&quot;/&gt;

Taller than the CN Tower are numerous [[radio masts and towers]], which are held in place by [[guy-wire]]s, the tallest being the [[KVLY-TV mast]] in [[Blanchard, North Dakota]] in the United States at {{convert|628|m|ft|0}} tall, leading to [[List of tallest structures|a distinction]] between these and &quot;free-standing&quot; structures. Additionally, the [[Petronius (oil platform)|Petronius Platform]] stands {{convert|610|m|ft|0}} above its base on the bottom of the [[Gulf of Mexico]], but only the top {{convert|75|m|ft|0}} of this [[oil platform|oil and natural gas platform]] are above water, and the structure is thus partially supported by its [[buoyancy]]. Like the CN Tower, none of these taller structures are commonly considered buildings.

On September 12, 2007, [[Burj Khalifa]], which is a hotel, residential and commercial building in [[Dubai]], United Arab Emirates, and was formerly known as Burj Dubai before opening, passed the CN Tower's 553.33-metre&lt;ref name=&quot;CNTower&quot;/&gt; height. The CN Tower held the record of tallest freestanding structure on land for over 30 years.&lt;ref name=&quot;CBCSurpassed&quot; /&gt;

After Burj Khalifa had been formally recognized by the Guinness World Records as the world's tallest freestanding structure, Guinness re-certified CN Tower as the world's tallest freestanding tower.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.thestar.com/news/gta/article/698891 |title=CN tower now the 'world's tallest freestanding tower' |last=Daubs |first=Katie |date=September 22, 2009 |work=Toronto Star |accessdate=September 22, 2009 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090927021016/http://www.thestar.com/News/GTA/article/698891 |archivedate=September 27, 2009 |url-status=live |df=mdy }}&lt;/ref&gt; The tower definition used by Guinness was defined by the [[Council on Tall Buildings and Urban Habitat]] as 'a building in which less than 50% of the construction is usable floor space'. ''Guinness World Records'' editor-in-chief Craig Glenday announced that Burj Khalifa was not classified as a tower because it has too much usable floor space to be considered to be a tower.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://network.nationalpost.com/np/blogs/toronto/archive/2009/09/18/326566.aspx| title=CN Tower remains world's tallest tower, Guinness says| work=[[National Post]]| date=September 18, 2009}}{{dead link|date=August 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; CN Tower still held world records for highest above ground wine cellar (in 360 Restaurant) at 351 metres, highest above ground restaurant at 346 metres (Horizons Restaurant),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| date=September 18, 2009| url=http://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/toronto/cn-tower-still-world-s-tallest-guinness-1.813395| title=CN Tower still world's tallest: Guinness| publisher=[[CBC News]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; and tallest free-standing concrete tower during Guinness's recertification. The CN Tower was surpassed in 2009 by the [[Canton Tower]] in [[Guangzhou]], China, which stands at {{convert|604|m|ft}} tall, as the world's tallest tower; which in turn was surpassed by the [[Tokyo Skytree]] in 2011, which currently is the tallest tower at {{convert|634.0|m|ft}} in height.&lt;ref name=canton/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://news.nationalgeographic.com/news/travelnews/2011/11/111128-worlds-tallest-tower-tokyo-travel/| title=World's Tallest Tower Rises in Tokyo| date=November 29, 2011| last=Owen| first=James| work=[[National Geographic|National Geographic News]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The CN Tower, as of 2018, stands as the ninth-tallest free-standing structure on land, remains the tallest free-standing structure in the [[Western Hemisphere]], and is the third-tallest tower.&lt;ref name=tallest/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.worldatlas.com/articles/10-tallest-towers-in-the-world.html|title=Where Is The Largest Tower In The World?|publisher=worldatlas.com|date=4 October 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Height records ====
[[File:Rogers Center-restitched.jpg|thumb|upright|The CN Tower as seen from the interior of the [[Rogers Centre]] baseball stadium]]
Since the construction of the tower had been completed, it has gained the following world height records:&lt;ref name=records&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.cntower.ca/about_us/awards_and_records/records/| title=The Tower, according to Guinness World Records| publisher=CN Tower}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!Record
!Owner
!Value
!Time period
!Succeeded by
|-
|World's tallest free-standing structure||CN Tower||{{convert|553.33|m|ft}}||March 31, 1975 to September 12, 2007||[[Burj Khalifa]]
|-
|World's tallest tower||CN Tower||{{convert|553.33|m|ft}}||1975 to 2009|| rowspan=2 |[[Canton Tower]]
|-
|World's highest public observation gallery||SkyPod||{{convert|447|m|ft}}|||
|-
|World's highest glass floor panelled elevator||CN Tower||{{convert|346|m|ft}}||2008 to present||—
|-
|World's longest metal staircase||CN Tower||2,579 steps||||
|-
|World's highest glass floor||CN Tower||{{convert|342|m|ft}}||2008 to July 2, 2009||[[Willis Tower]]
|-
|World's highest and largest revolving restaurant||360 Restaurant||{{convert|351|m|ft}}||||
|-
|World's highest bar||Horizons Restaurant||{{convert|346|m|ft}}||September 21, 2009 to present||—
|-
|World's highest wine cellar||360 Restaurant||{{convert|351|m|ft}}||||
|}

== Use ==
{{more citations needed section|date=July 2011}}
{{update|section|date=October 2014}}
[[File:Toronto - ON - CN Tower - Antennenspitze.jpg|thumb|upright|Main Pod and broadcast antennas]]
The CN Tower has been and continues to be used as a communications tower for a number of different media and by numerous companies.

=== Television broadcasters ===
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|-
&lt;!-- !Frequency --&gt;
!VHF
!UHF
!Virtual
!Callsign
!Affiliation
!Branding
|-
&lt;!-- |186.31&amp;nbsp;MHz --&gt;
|9
|—
|9.1
|[[CFTO-DT]]
|[[CTV Television Network|CTV]]
|CTV Toronto
|-
&lt;!-- |501.31&amp;nbsp;MHz --&gt;
|—
|19
|19.1
|[[TVOntario|CICA-DT]]
|[[TVOntario]]
|TVO
|-
&lt;!-- |507.31&amp;nbsp;MHz --&gt;
|—
|20
|5.1
|[[CBLT-DT]]
|[[CBC Television]]
|CBC Toronto
|-
&lt;!-- |537.31&amp;nbsp;MHz --&gt;
|—
|25
|25.1
|[[CBLFT-DT]]
|[[Ici Radio-Canada Télé]]
|ICI Toronto
|-
&lt;!-- | *FREQUENCY NEEDED* --&gt;
|—
|40
|40.1
|[[CJMT-DT]]
|[[Omni Television]]
|Omni.2
|-
&lt;!-- |633.31&amp;nbsp;MHz --&gt;
|—
|41
|41.1
|[[CIII-DT|CIII-DT-41]]
|[[Global Television Network|Global]]
|Global Toronto
|-
&lt;!-- |651.31&amp;nbsp;MHz --&gt;
|—
|44
|57.1
|[[CITY-DT]]
|[[Citytv]]
|City Toronto
|-
&lt;!-- |669.31&amp;nbsp;MHz --&gt;
|—
|47
|47.1
|[[CFMT-DT]]
|[[Omni Television]]
|Omni.1
|}

=== Radio ===
There is no [[AM broadcasting]] on the CN Tower.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.fcc.gov/fcc-bin/amq?state=ON&amp;call=&amp;arn=&amp;city=Toronto&amp;freq=530&amp;fre2=1700&amp;type=0&amp;facid=&amp;class=&amp;list=1&amp;dist=15&amp;dlat2=43&amp;mlat2=38&amp;slat2=30.67&amp;NS=N&amp;dlon2=79&amp;mlon2=23&amp;slon2=14.27&amp;EW=W&amp;size=9| title=AM Query &amp; AM List Results| accessdate=April 9, 2008| date=April 9, 2008| publisher=[[Federal Communications Commission]] – Audio Division| archiveurl= https://archive.today/20120801053741/http://www.fcc.gov/fcc-bin/amq?state=ON&amp;call=&amp;arn=&amp;city=Toronto&amp;freq=530&amp;fre2=1700&amp;type=0&amp;facid=&amp;class=&amp;list=1&amp;dist=15&amp;dlat2=43&amp;mlat2=38&amp;slat2=30.67&amp;NS=N&amp;dlon2=79&amp;mlon2=23&amp;slon2=14.27&amp;EW=W&amp;size=9| archivedate=August 1, 2012| url-status=live| df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[FM broadcasting|FM]] transmitters are situated in a 102-metre (334.6 ft) tall metal broadcast antenna, on top of the main concrete portion of the tower at an elevation above 446.5 metres (1,465 ft).

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
!Frequency
!kW
!Callsign&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.fcc.gov/fcc-bin/fmq?state=&amp;call=&amp;city=&amp;arn=&amp;serv=&amp;vac=&amp;freq=0.0&amp;fre2=107.9&amp;facid=&amp;class=&amp;dkt=&amp;list=1&amp;dist=10&amp;dlat2=43&amp;mlat2=38&amp;slat2=30.67&amp;NS=N&amp;dlon2=79&amp;mlon2=23&amp;slon2=14.27&amp;EW=W&amp;size=9| title=FM Query &amp; FM List Results| accessdate=April 9, 2008| date=April 9, 2008| publisher=Federal Communications Commission – Audio Division| archiveurl=https://archive.today/20120802213851/http://www.fcc.gov/fcc-bin/fmq?state=&amp;call=&amp;city=&amp;arn=&amp;serv=&amp;vac=&amp;freq=0.0&amp;fre2=107.9&amp;facid=&amp;class=&amp;dkt=&amp;list=1&amp;dist=10&amp;dlat2=43&amp;mlat2=38&amp;slat2=30.67&amp;NS=N&amp;dlon2=79&amp;mlon2=23&amp;slon2=14.27&amp;EW=W&amp;size=9| archivedate=August 2, 2012| url-status=live| df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
!Branding
!Notes
|-
|91.1&amp;nbsp;MHz
|40
|[[CJRT-FM|CJRT]]
|JAZZ.FM91
|
|-
|94.1&amp;nbsp;MHz
|38
|[[CBL-FM|CBL]]
|[[CBC Music]]
|
|-
|97.3&amp;nbsp;MHz
|28.9
|[[CHBM-FM|CHBM]]
|boom 97.3
|
|-
|98.1&amp;nbsp;MHz
|44
|[[CHFI-FM|CHFI]]
|98.1 CHFI
|
|-
|99.9&amp;nbsp;MHz
|40
|[[CKFM-FM|CKFM]]
|Virgin Radio 99.9FM
|
|-
|100.7&amp;nbsp;MHz
|4
|[[CHIN-FM|CHIN]]
|CHIN Radio
|Primarily in [[Italian language|Italian]] and [[Portuguese language|Portuguese]]
|-
|102.1&amp;nbsp;MHz
|35
|[[CFNY-FM|CFNY]]
|102.1 the Edge
|
|-
|104.5&amp;nbsp;MHz
|40
|[[CHUM-FM|CHUM]]
|104.5 CHUM FM
|
|-
|107.1&amp;nbsp;MHz
|40
|[[CILQ-FM|CILQ]]
|Classic Rock Q 107
|
|}

=== Communications ===
* [[Bell Canada]]
* [[Toronto Transit Commission]]
* [[Amateur radio]] [[repeater]]s &quot;2-Tango&quot; ([[Very high frequency|VHF]]) and &quot;4-Tango&quot; (440/70&amp;nbsp;cm [[Ultra high frequency|UHF]]) — owned and operated by the Toronto FM Communications Society, under callsign VE3TWR&lt;ref name=&quot;ARES&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://ares.meskes.ca/frequencies.html |title=Toronto ARES Channels |accessdate=August 3, 2006 |date=October 26, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== In popular culture==
The CN Tower has been featured in numerous films, television shows, music recording covers, and video games. The tower also has its own official mascot, which resembles the tower itself.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=https://www.thestar.com/news/gta/2017/07/19/a-new-mascot-for-the-cn-tower-is-a-mini-cn-tower.html| title=A new mascot for the CN Tower is a mini CN Tower| last=Fearon| first=Emily| date=July 19, 2017| work=Toronto Star}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!--Before adding a work, please discuss in the talk page; consensus must be reached--&gt;
*''[[Highpoint (film)|Highpoint]]'' is a Canadian 1982 action film starring [[Richard Harris]], [[Christopher Plummer]] and [[Beverly D'Angelo]]. It features a shot of stuntman [[Dar Robinson]] jumping off of the CN Tower in 1979.&lt;ref name=&quot;robinson&quot;/&gt;
*''[[Views (album)|Views]]'' is a 2016 studio album released on April 29, 2016 by Canadian rapper [[Drake (musician)|Drake]]. The cover artwork features Drake sitting atop the CN Tower in Toronto.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.thestar.com/entertainment/2016/04/26/drakes-towering-view-of-the-6.html|title=Drake's towering view of The 6 {{!}} Toronto Star|website=thestar|accessdate=July 11, 2016|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160816134609/https://www.thestar.com/entertainment/2016/04/26/drakes-towering-view-of-the-6.html|archivedate=August 16, 2016|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; Drake appeared significantly larger than life-size on the cover, and CN Tower's [[Twitter]] account later confirmed it to be [[Photo manipulation|photo edited]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite tweet|user=TourCNTower|number=724591858190573568|date=April 28, 2016|title= CN Tower/La Tour CN on Twitter|archiveurl=https://archive.today/20160428111103/https://twitter.com/TourCNTower/status/724591858190573568|archive-date=April 28, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!--Before adding a work, please discuss in the talk page; consensus must be reached--&gt;

== See also ==
{{Commons category|CN Tower}}
* [[Architecture of Toronto]]
* [[List of tallest buildings in Toronto]]
* [[List of tallest structures in Canada]]
* [[List of tallest freestanding structures]]
* [[List of tallest towers]]
* [[List of tallest buildings and structures]]
* [[List of tallest structures]]

{{Portal bar|Architecture|Canada|Ontario}}

{{clear}}

== References ==
{{Reflist|30em}}

== External links ==
* [http://archives.cbc.ca/IDC-1-69-204-1024-11/life_society/cn_tower_opens/ CBC Archives – CN Tower opens to the public. (Multimedia)]
* [http://www.cntower.ca/ Official CN Tower Website]
* [http://www.edgewalkcntower.ca/ Edgewalk]
* [http://www.pastandfuturehistory.com/ The Design, Engineering and Construction of the CN Tower – 1972 through to 1976]
* [https://www.flickr.com/photos/40744368@N04/sets/72157632200955200/ A visual construction history of the CN Tower – at 40th year anniversaries]
* [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=K67j5juf-V4 How the CN Tower was Built] - Art Of Engineering (YouTube documentary)

{{S-start}}
{{S-ach|rec}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Ostankino Tower]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=World's tallest free-standing structure &lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;553.33 m (1,815 ft 5 in)&lt;/small&gt;|years= 1975–2007}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Burj Khalifa]]}}
{{S-end}}
{{Toronto landmarks}}
{{Toronto skyscrapers}}
{{Supertall}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Cn Tower}}
[[Category:Towers completed in 1976]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Toronto]]
[[Category:Towers with revolving restaurants]]
[[Category:Canadian National Railway facilities]]
[[Category:Communication towers in Canada]]
[[Category:Observation towers in Canada]]
[[Category:Towers in Ontario]]
[[Category:Modernist architecture in Canada]]
[[Category:Stairways]]
[[Category:Transmitter sites in Canada]]
[[Category:Tourist attractions in Toronto]]
[[Category:WZMH Architects buildings]]
[[Category:Railway Lands]]
[[Category:Articles containing video clips]]
[[Category:1976 establishments in Ontario]]</text>
      <sha1>41gnh2topn8yaro4yayg8abhh0keix3</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
