  <page>
    <title>Dressed to Kill (1980 film)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8481</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943331418</id>
      <parentid>941799849</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-03-01T07:54:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Carminephone</username>
        <id>38668606</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Production */The filming date was between the late of 1979 until the early of 1980.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|1980 film directed by Brian De Palma}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=March 2015}}
{{Infobox film
| name           = Dressed to Kill
| image          = dressed_to_kill.jpg
| alt            = 
| caption        = Theatrical release poster
| director       = [[Brian De Palma]]
| producer       = [[George Litto]]
| writer         = Brian De Palma
| starring       = {{Plainlist|
* [[Michael Caine]]
* [[Angie Dickinson]]
* [[Nancy Allen (actress)|Nancy Allen]]
* [[Keith Gordon]]}}
| music          = [[Pino Donaggio]]
| cinematography = [[Ralf D. Bode]]
| editing        = [[Gerald B. Greenberg]]
| studio         = {{plainlist|
* Cinema 77
* Film Group
}}
| distributor    = [[Filmways|Filmways Pictures]]
| released       = {{Film date|1980|07|25|ref1=&lt;ref name=afi&gt;{{cite web|work=[[AFI Catalog of Feature Films]]|location=Los Angeles|publisher=[[American Film Institute]]|url=https://catalog.afi.com/Film/67204-DRESSED-TOKILL?sid=684cd007-ed5a-4ba2-9b2f-a9d0f59f4c11&amp;sr=14.010053&amp;cp=1&amp;pos=1|title=''Dressed to Kill''|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190708075328/https://catalog.afi.com/Film/67204-DRESSED-TOKILL?sid=684cd007-ed5a-4ba2-9b2f-a9d0f59f4c11&amp;sr=14.010053&amp;cp=1&amp;pos=1|archive-date=July 8, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
| runtime        = 104 minutes&lt;!-- Theatrical runtime: 104:16 --&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=''DRESSED TO KILL'' (X)|url=http://www.bbfc.co.uk/AFF028365/|work=[[British Board of Film Classification]]|date=1980-09-01|accessdate=2012-03-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| country        = United States
| language       = English
| budget         = $6.5 million&lt;ref name=BOM&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.boxofficemojo.com/movies/?id=dressedtokill.htm|title=Dressed to Kill (1980)|work=[[Box Office Mojo]]|access-date=July 8, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| gross          = $31.9 million&lt;ref name=BOM/&gt;
}}
'''''Dressed to Kill''''' is a 1980 American [[neo-noir]] [[slasher film]] written and directed by [[Brian De Palma]] and starring [[Michael Caine]], [[Angie Dickinson]], [[Nancy Allen (actress)|Nancy Allen]], and [[Keith Gordon]]. A New York City housewife is brutally stabbed to death in an elevator, and the film subsequently follows her psychiatrist, her teenage son, and a prostitute who witnessed her murder. The [[Film score|original music score]] is composed by [[Pino Donaggio]].  The film contains several direct references to [[Alfred Hitchcock]]'s classic 1960 film &lt;i&gt;[[Psycho (1960 film)|Psycho]]&lt;/i&gt;, such as a man dressing as a woman to commit murders, the significant shower scenes in both films, and the murder of the female lead very early in the picture.

Released in the summer of 1980, ''Dressed to Kill'' was a box office hit in the United States, grossing over $30 million. It received largely favorable reviews, and critic [[David Denby]] of ''[[New York (magazine)|New York Magazine]]'' proclaimed it &quot;the first great American movie of the '80s.&quot;{{sfn|Knapp|2003|p=62}} Allen received both a [[Golden Globe Awards|Golden Globe Award]] nomination for New Star of the Year&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.goldenglobes.com/film/dressed-kill Golden Globes]&lt;/ref&gt;, as well as a [[Golden Raspberry Awards|Golden Raspberry Award]] for Worst Actress, while Dickinson received a [[Saturn Award]] for [[Saturn Award for Best Actress|Best Actress]] for her performance.

==Plot==
Kate Miller is a sexually frustrated housewife who is in therapy with New York City psychiatrist Dr. Robert Elliott. During an appointment, Kate attempts to seduce him, but Elliott rejects her advances. Kate goes to the [[Metropolitan Museum of Art]] where she has an unexpected flirtation with a mysterious stranger. Kate and the stranger stalk each other through the museum until they finally wind up outside, where Kate joins him in a taxi. They begin to have sex and continue at his apartment.

Hours later, Kate awakens and decides to discreetly leave while the man, Warren Lockman, is asleep. Kate sits at his desk to leave him a note and finds a document indicating that Warren has contracted a sexually transmitted disease. Mortified, she leaves the apartment. In her haste, she forgets her wedding ring on the nightstand, and she returns to retrieve it. The elevator doors open on the figure of a tall, blond woman in dark sunglasses wielding a straight razor. Kate is violently stabbed to death in the elevator. A high-priced call girl, Liz Blake, happens upon the body. She catches a glimpse of the killer in the elevator's [[Curved mirror|convex mirror]], and subsequently becomes both the prime suspect and the killer's next target.

Dr. Elliott receives a bizarre message on his answering machine from &quot;Bobbi&quot;, a transgender patient. Bobbi taunts the psychiatrist for breaking off their therapy sessions, apparently because Elliott refuses to sign the necessary papers for Bobbi to get [[sex reassignment surgery]]. Elliott tries to convince Dr. Levy, the patient's new doctor, that Bobbi is a danger to herself and others.

Police Detective Marino (Dennis Franz) is skeptical about Liz's story, partly because of her profession, so Liz joins forces with Kate's revenge-minded son Peter (Keith Gordon) to find the killer. Peter, an inventor, uses a series of homemade listening devices and time-lapse cameras to track patients leaving Elliott's office. They catch Bobbi on camera, and soon Liz is being stalked by a tall blonde in sunglasses. Several attempts are subsequently made on Liz's life. One, in the New York City Subway, is thwarted by Peter, who sprays Bobbi with homemade Mace.

Liz and Peter scheme to learn Bobbi's birth name by getting inside Dr. Elliott's office. Liz baits the therapist by stripping to lingerie and coming on to him, distracting him long enough to make a brief exit and leaf through his appointment book. Peter is watching through the window when a blonde pulls him away. When Liz returns, a blonde with a razor confronts her; the blonde outside shoots and wounds the blonde inside, the wig falls off, and it is Dr. Elliott, revealing that he is also Bobbi. The blonde who shot Bobbi is actually a female police officer, revealing herself to be the blonde who has been trailing Liz.

Elliott is arrested and placed in an insane asylum. Dr. Levy explains later to Liz that Elliott wanted to be a woman, but his male side would not allow him to go through with the operation. Whenever a woman sexually aroused Elliott, Bobbi, representing the unstable, female side of the doctor's personality, became threatened to the point that it finally became murderous. When Dr. Levy realized this through his last conversation with Elliott, he called the police on the spot, who then, with his help, did their duty.

In a final sequence, Elliott escapes from the asylum and slashes Liz's throat in a bloody act of vengeance. She wakes up screaming, Peter rushing to her side, realizing that it was
just a nightmare (similar to the ending of ''[[Carrie (1976 film)|Carrie]]'').&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.motionpicturescomics.com/2011/12/30/days-of-de-palma-part-3-dressed-to-kill-1980/ Days of De Palma (Part 3): Dressed to Kill (1980)-motionpicturescomics.com]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Cast==
{{cast listing|
* [[Michael Caine]] as Dr. Robert Elliott/Bobbi
* [[Angie Dickinson]] as Kate Miller
* [[Nancy Allen (actress)|Nancy Allen]] as Liz Blake
* [[Keith Gordon]] as Peter Miller
* [[Dennis Franz]] as Detective Marino
* [[David Margulies]] as Dr. Levy
* Ken Baker as Warren Lockman
* Susanna Clemm as Betty Luce
* [[Brandon Maggart]] as Cleveland Sam
* [[William Finley (actor)|William Finley]] as the voice of Bobbi
}}

==Production==
The nude body in the opening scene, taking place in a shower, was not that of Angie Dickinson, but of 1977 ''[[Penthouse (magazine)|Penthouse]]'' [[List of Penthouse Pets|Pet of the Year]] model Victoria Lynn Johnson.&lt;ref name=victoria&gt;{{cite av media|title=Interview: Victoria Lynn Johnson|year=2014|publisher=[[The Criterion Collection]]|medium=[[Blu-ray]]|work=Dressed to Kill}}&lt;/ref&gt; De Palma originally wanted Norwegian actress [[Liv Ullmann]] to play Kate Miller, but she declined because of the violence. The role then went to Angie Dickinson. [[Sean Connery]] was offered the role of Robert Elliot and was enthusiastic about it, but declined on account of previous commitments.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mell2005&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Eila Mell|title=Casting Might-Have-Beens: A Film by Film Directory of Actors Considered for Roles Given to Others|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=1SqXAAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA76|date=6 January 2005|publisher=McFarland|isbn=978-1-4766-0976-8|page=76}}&lt;/ref&gt; Connery would later work with De Palma on the 1987 Oscar-winning adaptation of ''[[The Untouchables (film)|The Untouchables]]''. De Palma called the elevator killing the best murder scene he has ever done.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Interview with Brian De Palma|url=http://the-talks.com/interviews/brian-de-palma/|publisher=The Talks}}&lt;/ref&gt; Dressed to Kill was filmed between 19 October, 1979 until 18 January, 1980. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://cinephiliabeyond.org/dressed-kill-brian-de-palmas-razor-sharp-dreamlike-erotic-thriller/ |title=‘Dressed to Kill’: Brian De Palma’s Razor-Sharp, Dreamlike Erotic Thriller |website=Cinephilia &amp; Beyond |accessdate=June 10, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Release==
===Box office===
''Dressed to Kill'' premiered in Los Angeles and New York City on July 25, 1980.&lt;ref name=afi/&gt; The film grossed $3,416,000 in its opening weekend from 591 theatres and improved its gross the following weekend with $3,640,000 from 596 theatres.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine|magazine=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|date=August 13, 1980|title=Dressed To Kill Is Showing Its Legs (advertisement)|pages=34-35|}}&lt;/ref&gt; It grossed a total of $31.9 million at the U.S. box office, and was the 21st highest-grossing film of the year.&lt;ref name=BOM/&gt;

===Critical response===
''Dressed to Kill'' currently holds an 83% &quot;fresh&quot; rating on [[Rotten Tomatoes]] based on 47 reviews, with an average rating of 6.63/10. The consensus states, &quot;With arresting visuals and an engrossingly lurid mystery, ''Dressed to Kill'' stylishly encapsulates writer-director Brian De Palma's signature strengths.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{rotten-tomatoes|1006299-dressed_to_kill|Dressed to Kill|accessdate=November 7, 2019|first=|last=|publisher=Rotten Tomatoes}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Roger Ebert]] awarded the film three stars out of four, stating &quot;the museum sequence is brilliant&quot; and adding: &quot;''Dressed to Kill'' is an exercise in style, not narrative; it would rather look and feel like a thriller than make sense, but DePalma has so much fun with the conventions of the thriller that we forgive him and go along.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Ebert, Roger. [http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/19800101/REVIEWS/1010312/1023 &quot;''Dressed to Kill''&quot;]. ''[[Chicago Sun-Times]]''. Retrieved 2012-02-05.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Gene Siskel]] also gave it three stars out of four, writing that there were scenes &quot;that are as exciting and as stylish as any ever put on film. Unfortunately, a good chunk of the film is a whodunit, and its mystery is so easy to solve that we merely end up watching the film's visual pyrotechnics at a distance, never getting all that involved.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Gene Siskel|Siskel, Gene]] (July 25, 1980). &quot;De Palma's sharp 'Dress' almost has it all&quot;. ''[[Chicago Tribune]]''. Section 4 p. 3.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Vincent Canby]] of ''[[The New York Times]]'' called the film &quot;witty, romantic,&quot; and &quot;very funny, which helps to defuse the effect of the graphically photographed violence. In addition, the film is, in its own inside-out way, peculiarly moral.&quot; His review added that &quot;The performers are excellent, especially Miss Dickinson.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Canby |first=Vincent |authorlink=Vincent Canby |date=July 25, 1980 |title=Film: 'Dressed to Kill,' De Palma Mystery: |url= |journal=[[The New York Times]] |page=C10 }}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]'' declared, &quot;Despite some major structural weaknesses, the cannily manipulated combination of mystery, gore and kinky sex adds up to a slick commercial package that stands to draw some rich blood money.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |date=July 23, 1980 |title=Dressed To Kill |url= |journal=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]] |page=18 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[David Denby]] of ''[[New York (magazine)|New York Magazine]]'' proclaimed the film &quot;the first great American movie of the '80s.&quot;{{sfn|Knapp|2003|p=62}}

[[Sheila Benson]] of the ''[[Los Angeles Times]]'' wrote, &quot;The brilliance of 'Dressed to Kill' is apparent within seconds of its opening gliding shot; it is a sustained work of terror—elegant, sensual, erotic, bloody, a directorial tour de force.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Sheila Benson|Benson, Sheila]] (July 25, 1980). &quot;'Dressed to Kill': The Terror is Stunning&quot;. ''[[Los Angeles Times]]''. Part VI, p. 1.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Pauline Kael]] of ''[[The New Yorker]]'' stated of De Palma that &quot;his timing is so great that when he wants you to feel something he gets you every time. His thriller technique, constantly refined, has become insidious, jewelled. It's hardly possible to find a point at which you could tear yourself away from this picture.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Kael |first=Pauline |authorlink=Pauline Kael |date=August 4, 1980 |title=The Current Cinema |url= |journal=[[The New Yorker]] |page=68 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Gary Arnold of ''[[The Washington Post]]'' wrote, &quot;This elegant new murder thriller promises to revive the lagging summer box office and enhance De Palma's reputation as the most exciting and distinctive manipulator of suspense since Alfred Hitchcock.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Arnold |first=Gary |date=July 25, 1980 |title=Mad for Murder |url= |journal=[[The Washington Post]] |page=C1 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In his movie guide, [[Leonard Maltin]] gave the film 3 1/2 stars out of four, calling it a &quot;High-tension melodrama&quot;, and stating &quot;De Palma works on viewers' emotions, not logic, and maintains a fever pitch from start to finish.&quot; He also praised [[Pino Donaggio]]'s &quot;chilling [[Film score|music score]].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;bookref1&quot;&gt;{{cite book| last=Maltin| first=Leonard| authorlink=|title=2013 Movie Guide|publisher=[[Penguin Books]]|date=|location=|pages=385|isbn=978-0-451-23774-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[John Simon (critic)|John Simon]] of the [[National Review]], after taking note of two paged advertisements full of superlatives in [[The New York Times]], wrote 'What Dressed to Kill dispenses liberally, however, is sophomoric soft-core pornography, vulgar manipulation of the emotions for mere sensation, salacious but inept dialogue that is a cross between comic-strip Freudianism and sniggering double entendres, and a plot line so full of holes to be at best a dotted line'.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Reverse Angle: A Decade of American Film|last1=Simon|first1=John |publisher=Crown Publishers Inc. |year=1982 |page=413}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Censorship===
Two versions of the film exist in North America, an [[Motion Picture Association of America film rating system|R-rated]] version and an unrated version. The unrated version is around 30 seconds longer and shows more pubic hair in the shower scene, more blood in the elevator scene (including a close-up shot of the killer slitting Kate's throat), and more explicit dialogue from Liz during the scene in Elliott's office. These scenes were trimmed when the MPAA originally gave the film an [[X rating|&quot;X&quot; rating]].&lt;ref&gt;[https://horrornews.net/101851/film-review-dressed-kill-1980/ Film Review: Dressed to Kill (1980) – Review 2|HNN]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Home media===
The film is currently owned by Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer (successor to Orion Pictures, who bought Filmways and American International Pictures in 1982). The film saw a 1984 VHS release by Warner Home Video, and later another VHS release by Goodtimes under licence from Orion. In 2002, MGM released the film on DVD, including special features. In 2010, MGM released both R-rated and unrated versions on DVD and [[Blu-ray]]. [[The Criterion Collection]] released a deluxe Blu-ray edition of the film on September 8, 2015.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.amazon.com/Dressed-Kill-Criterion-Collection-Blu-ray/dp/B00XV31RZA|work=[[Amazon (company)|Amazon]]|title=Dressed to Kill Blu-ray|access-date=July 8, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Accolades==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Award
! Category
! Subject
! Result
|-
|[[Golden Globe Award]]
|[[Golden Globe Award for New Star of the Year – Actress|New Star of the Year – Actress]]
|rowspan=3|[[Nancy Allen (actress)|Nancy Allen]]
|{{nom}}
|-
|[[Stinkers Bad Movie Awards|Stinkers Bad Movie Award]]
|Worst Actress
|{{nom}}
|-
|rowspan=3|[[Golden Raspberry Awards]]
|[[Golden Raspberry Award for Worst Actress|Worst Actress]]
|{{nom}}
|-
|[[Golden Raspberry Award for Worst Actor|Worst Actor]]
|[[Michael Caine]]
|{{nom}}
|-
|[[Golden Raspberry Award for Worst Director|Worst Director]]
|rowspan=2|[[Brian De Palma]]
|{{nom}}
|-
|rowspan=4|[[Saturn Award]]s
|[[Saturn Award for Best Director|Best Director]]
|{{nom}}
|-
|colspan=2|[[Saturn Award for Best Horror Film|Best Horror Film]]
|{{nom}}
|-
|[[Saturn Award for Best Actress|Best Actress]]
|[[Angie Dickinson]]
|{{won}}
|-
|[[Saturn Award for Best Music|Best Music]]
|[[Pino Donaggio]]
|{{nom}}
|-
|rowspan=2|[[New York Film Critics Circle]] Awards
|colspan=2|Best Film
|{{won|5th place}}
|-
|Best Director
|Brian De Palma
|{{won|4th place}}
|-
|}

==See also==
* [[Transgender in film and television]]
*''[[Cruising (film)|Cruising]]''-[[William Friedkin]]'s controversial 1980 film with similar LBGT themes
* [[Giallo]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Sources==
*{{cite book|last=Knapp|first=Laurence F.|title=Interviews: Brian De Palma|publisher=University Press of Mississippi|location=Jackson, Mississippi|ref=harv|isbn=978-1-578-06516-5|year=2003}}

==External links==
{{wikiquote}}
* {{IMDb title|0080661}}
* {{Tcmdb title|24716}}
* {{mojo title|dressedtokill}}
* {{rotten-tomatoes|1006299-dressed_to_kill}}
* [http://film.virtual-history.com/film.php?filmid=35 Film stills]
* [https://www.criterion.com/current/posts/3691-dressed-to-kill-the-power-of-two ''Dressed to Kill: The Power of Two''] an essay by Michael Koresky at the [[Criterion Collection]]

{{Brian De Palma}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Dressed To Kill}}
[[Category:1980 films]]
[[Category:1980s crime thriller films]]
[[Category:1980s erotic thriller films]]
[[Category:1980s independent films]]
[[Category:1980s LGBT-related films]]
[[Category:1980s mystery thriller films]]
[[Category:1980s slasher films]]
[[Category:Adultery in films]]
[[Category:American crime thriller films]]
[[Category:American erotic thriller films]]
[[Category:American independent films]]
[[Category:American LGBT-related films]]
[[Category:American neo-noir films]]
[[Category:American mystery thriller films]]
[[Category:American slasher films]]
[[Category:Dissociative identity disorder in films]]
[[Category:English-language films]]
[[Category:Erotic slasher films]]
[[Category:Films about murderers]]
[[Category:Films about prostitution in the United States]]
[[Category:Films about psychiatry]]
[[Category:Films directed by Brian De Palma]]
[[Category:Films scored by Pino Donaggio]]
[[Category:Films set in New York City]]
[[Category:Films shot in New York City]]
[[Category:Films shot in Philadelphia]]
[[Category:LGBT-related thriller films]]
[[Category:Trans women in film]]
[[Category:Filmways films]]</text>
      <sha1>s0fi9vjfb6wuglcm1alwooons6i173j</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
