  <page>
    <title>Didgeridoo</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8443</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943235050</id>
      <parentid>942404659</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-29T18:15:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>50.208.102.141</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Playing the didgeridoo */ MOS:HEAD</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{For|the Aphex Twin single|Digeridoo (EP)}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2011}}
{{Use Australian English|date=September 2011}}
{{Infobox Instrument
|name=Didgeridoo
|image=Australiandidgeridoos.jpg
|image_capt =A, B and C: Traditionally made didgeridoos. &lt;br&gt;D and E: Non-traditional didgeridoos. {{Cn|date=July 2019}}
|background=
| names                 =Didjeridu, yiḏaki, mandapul, mago, etc. 
|classification=
*[[Wind instrument|Wind]]
*[[Aerophone]]
|hornbostel_sachs=423.121.11
|hornbostel_sachs_desc=End-blown straight tubular [[natural trumpet]] without mouthpiece
|range=Written range: Fundamental typically A2 to G3
|related=[[Trumpet]], [[Flugelhorn]], [[Cornet]], [[Bugle (instrument)|Bugle]],&lt;br/&gt;[[Natural trumpet]], [[Post horn]], [[Roman tuba]], [[Cornu (horn)|Bucina]], [[Shofar]], [[Conch (instrument)|Conch]], [[Lur]], [[Baritone horn]], Bronze Age Irish Horn
}}
[[File:Didgeridu and clap sticks.jpg|thumb|Didgeridoo and [[clapstick]] players performing at [[Nightcliff, Northern Territory]]]]
[[File:Didgeridoo sound.ogg|thumb|Sound of Didgeridoo]]
The '''didgeridoo''' ({{IPAc-en|ˌ|d|ɪ|dʒ|ər|i|ˈ|d|uː}}; also spelt '''didjeridu''') is a [[wind instrument]]. The didgeridoo was developed by [[Aboriginal Australians|Aboriginal peoples]] of northern Australia, likely within the last 1,000 years, and is now in use around the world. The name for the [[Yolngu]] peoples' instrument is the '''yiḏaki'''  ('''yidaki'''), or more recently by some, '''mandapul'''; in west Arnhem Land it is known as a '''mago'''.

A didgeridoo is usually [[cylindrical]] or [[Cone (geometry)|conical]], and can measure anywhere from {{convert|1|to|3|m|ft|0|abbr=on}} long. Most are around {{convert|1.2|m|ft|0|abbr=on}} long. Generally, the longer the instrument, the lower its pitch or key. However, flared instruments play a higher pitch than unflared instruments of the same length.

==Origin==
There are no reliable sources of the exact age of the didgeridoo. Archaeological studies suggest that people of the [[Kakadu National Park|Kakadu]] region in Northern Australia have been using the didgeridoo for less than 1,000 years, based on the dating of [[rock art]] paintings.&lt;ref name=&quot;PBP&quot;/&gt; A clear rock painting in Ginga Wardelirrhmeng, on the northern edge of the [[Arnhem Land]] plateau, from the freshwater period&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.environment.gov.au/parks/kakadu/culture-history/art/styles.html |title=Kakadu National Park – Rock art styles&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt; |access-date=21 April 2012 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120421050045/http://www.environment.gov.au/parks/kakadu/culture-history/art/styles.html |archive-date=21 April 2012 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; (that had begun 1500 years ago)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1= Sayers |first1= Andrew |author-link1=  |year= 2001 |origyear= 2001 |title= Australian Art (Oxford History of Art) |type= paperback |series= Oxford History of Art |publisher= Oxford University Press, USA |publication-date= 19 July 2001 |page= [https://archive.org/details/australianart00saye/page/19 19] |isbn= 978-0192842145 |url-access= registration |url= https://archive.org/details/australianart00saye/page/19 }}&lt;/ref&gt; shows a didgeridoo player and two songmen participating in an Ubarr Ceremony.&lt;ref&gt;[[George Chaloupka]], ''Journey in Time'', p. 189.&lt;/ref&gt; It is thus thought that it was developed by Aboriginal peoples of northern Australia, possibly in Arnhem Land.

T.B. Wilson's ''Narrative of a Voyage Round the World'' (1835) includes a drawing of an Aboriginal man from Raffles Bay on the [[Cobourg Peninsula]] (about {{convert|350|km}} east of [[Darwin, Northern Territory|Darwin]]) playing the instrument. Others observed such an instrument in the same area, made of [[bamboo]] and about {{convert |3|ft}} long. In 1893, English palaeontologist [[Robert Etheridge, Junior]] observed the use of &quot;three very curious trumpets&quot; made of bamboo in northern Australia. There were then two native species of bamboo growing along the [[Adelaide River, Northern Territory]]&quot;.&lt;ref name =culture/&gt;

According to [[A.P. Elkin]], in 1938 the instrument was &quot;only known in eastern [[Kimberley, Western Australia|Kimberley]] and the northern third of the [[Northern Territory]].&lt;ref name=arts&gt;{{cite web | title=History of the Didgeridoo Yidaki | website=Aboriginal Arts | url=http://www.aboriginalarts.co.uk/historyofthedidgeridoo.html | access-date=21 January 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Etymology==
The name &quot;didgeridoo&quot; is not of [[Aboriginal Australian]] origin and is considered to be an [[onomatopoeia|onomatopoetic]] word. The earliest occurrences of the word in print include a 1908 edition of the ''Hamilton Spectator'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article225891921 |title=Retribution |newspaper=Hamilton Spectator |issue=7567 |location=Victoria, Australia |date=24 October 1908 |accessdate=28 January 2017 |page=8 |via=National Library of Australia}}&lt;/ref&gt; a 1914 edition of ''[[The Northern Territory Times and Gazette]]'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article3281806 |title=Correspondence |newspaper=[[The Northern Territory Times and Gazette]] |volume=XXXVIII |issue=2145 |location=Northern Territory, Australia |date=17 December 1914 |accessdate=28 January 2017 |page=14 |via=National Library of Australia}}&lt;/ref&gt; and a 1919 issue of ''[[Smith's Weekly]]'' where it was referred to as a &quot;didjerry&quot; which produced the sound – (phonic) &quot;didjerry, didjerry, didjerry and so on ad infinitum&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://andc.anu.edu.au/australian-words/meanings-origins/d|title=Meanings and origins of Australian words and idioms: D|publisher=[[Australian National Dictionary Centre]]|accessdate=27 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A rival explanation, that didgeridoo is a [[Corruption (linguistics)|corruption]] of the [[Irish Gaelic language]] phrase ''dúdaire dubh'' or ''dúidire dúth'', is controversial.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.flinders.edu.au/news/articles/?fj09v13s02|title=It's as Irish as – er – didgeridoo|publisher=[[Flinders University]]|work=Flinders Journal|date=10–23 June 2002|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20020819082521/http://www.flinders.edu.au/news/articles/?fj09v13s02 |archivedate=19 August 2002|accessdate=30 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Dúdaire''/''dúidire'' is a noun that, depending on the context, may mean &quot;trumpeter&quot;, &quot;[[hum (sound)|hum]]mer&quot;, &quot;[[croon]]er&quot; or &quot;[[wikt:puff|puff]]er&quot; while ''dubh'' means &quot;black&quot; and ''dúth'' means &quot;[[indigenous peoples|native]]&quot;.

==Other names==
There are numerous names for the instrument among the Aboriginal peoples of [[northern Australia]], none of which closely resemble the word &quot;didgeridoo&quot; (see below). Some didgeridoo enthusiasts, scholars and Aboriginal people advocate using local language names for the instrument.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Are &quot;Didjeridu&quot; and &quot;Yidaki&quot; the same thing? |url=http://www.yirrkala.com/yidaki/dhawu/31samething.html |work=Yidaki Dhawu Miwatjnurunydja |publisher=Buku Larrngay Mulka Centre |accessdate=14 July 2011 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110214193946/http://www.yirrkala.com/yidaki/dhawu/31samething.html |archivedate=14 February 2011 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;

''Yiḏaki'' (transcribed ''yidaki'' in English, sometimes spelt ''yirdaki'') is one of the most commonly used names although, strictly speaking, it refers to a specific type of the instrument made and used by the [[Yolngu]] peoples of north-east [[Arnhem Land]].&lt;ref name=nicholls&gt;{{cite web | last=Nicholls | first=Christine Judith | title=Friday essay: the remarkable yidaki (and no, it's not a 'didge') | website=The Conversation | date=6 April 2017 | url=http://theconversation.com/friday-essay-the-remarkable-yidaki-and-no-its-not-a-didge-74169 | access-date=19 January 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some Yolngu people began using the word ''mandapul'' after 2011, out of respect for the passing of a [[Dhuwal|Manggalili]] man had a name sounding similar to yidaki.&lt;ref name=spirit&gt;{{cite web | title=Yidaki | website=Spirit Gallery| url=https://www.spiritgallery.com.au/yidaki-information | access-date=19 January 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In west Arnhem Land, it is known as a ''mago'', a name popularised by virtuoso player [[David Blanasi]], a [[Bininj]] man, whose language was [[Kunwinjku language|Kunwinjku]], and who brought the didgeridoo to world prominence.&lt;ref name=arts/&gt; However the mago is slightly different from the Yiḏaki: usually shorter, and sounding somewhat different – a slightly fuller and richer sound, but without the &quot;overtone&quot; note.&lt;ref name=spirit/&gt;&lt;ref name=spiritterm&gt;{{cite web | title=Didgeridoo terminology: 5- What is the horn, toot, overtone note?| website=Spirit Gallery| url=https://www.spiritgallery.com.au/didgeridoo-terminology#horn| access-date=19 January 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=arts/&gt;

There are at least 45 names for the didgeridoo, several of which suggest its original construction of bamboo, such as ''bambu'', ''bombo'', ''kambu'', and ''pampu'', which are still used in the ''[[lingua franca]]'' by some Aboriginal people. The following are some of the more common regional names.&lt;ref name =culture&gt;{{cite web |url =http://aboriginalart.com.au/didgeridoo/what_is.html |title =The Didgeridoo and Aboriginal Culture|website =Aboriginal Australia Art &amp; Culture Centre, Alice Springs, Australia |date=2020 |access-date =21 January 2020}} &lt;/ref&gt;
{|  class=wikitable  
!  width=&quot;33%&quot; | People
!  width=&quot;33%&quot; | Region
!  width=&quot;34%&quot; | Local name
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| [[Anindilyakwa]]
| [[Groote Eylandt]]
| ngarrriralkpwina
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| [[Arrernte people|Arrernte]]
| [[Alice Springs]]
| ilpirra
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| [[Djinang people|Djinang]] (a [[Yolngu]] people)
| [[Arnhem Land]]
| yiḏaki
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| [[Gagudju]]
| [[Arnhem Land]] / [[Kakadu National Park|Kakadu]]
| garnbak
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| [[Dhuwal language|Gupapuygu]]
| [[Arnhem Land]]
| yiraka
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| [[Iwaidja]]
| [[Cobourg Peninsula]]
| artawirr
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| [[Jawoyn]]
| [[Katherine, Northern Territory|Katherine]] / [[Nitmiluk National Park|Nitmiluk]] / [[Kakadu National Park|Kakadu]]
| gunbarrk
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| [[Bininj Kunwok language|Kunwinjku]]
| [[Arnhem Land]] / [[Kakadu National Park|Kakadu]]
| mako &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Garde |first1=Murray |title=Bininj Kunwok Online Dictionary |url=https://www.njamed.com/#mako |website=njamed.com |publisher=Bininj Kunwok Regional Language Centre |accessdate=28 May 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| [[Gunwinggu language|Mayali]]
| [[Alligator Rivers]]
| martba
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| [[Ngarluma language|Ngarluma]]
| [[Roebourne, Western Australia|Roebourne, W.A.]]
| kurmur
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| [[Nyulnyul language|Nyul Nyul]]
| [[Kimberleys]]
| ngaribi
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| [[Pintupi]]
| [[Central Australia]]
| paampu
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| [[Warray language|Warray]]
| [[Adelaide River]]
| bambu
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| [[Yolngu]]
| [[Arnhem Land]]
| mandapul (yiḏaki)
|}

==Description and construction==
A didgeridoo is usually [[cylindrical]] or [[Cone (geometry)|conical]], and can measure anywhere from {{convert|1|to|3|m|ft|0|abbr=on}} long. Most are around {{convert|1.2|m|ft|0|abbr=on}} long. Generally, the longer the instrument, the lower its pitch or key. However, flared instruments play a higher pitch than unflared instruments of the same length. &lt;ref&gt;Fletcher, N.H. (1996) The didjeridu (didgeridoo). ''Acoustics Australia'' 24, 11-15.&lt;/ref&gt;

The didgeridoo is classified as a [[wind instrument]] and is similar in form to a straight [[trumpet]], but made of wood. It has also been called a dronepipe.&lt;ref name=eb&gt;{{cite web | title=Didjeridu: Musical instrument | website=Encyclopedia Britannica | url=https://www.britannica.com/art/didjeridu | access-date=19 January 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Traditional===

[[File:Didgeridoo Embout1.jpg|thumb|A wax mouthpiece can soften during play, forming a better seal.]]
Traditional didgeridoos are usually made from [[hardwood]]s, especially the various [[eucalyptus]] species that are [[endemic (ecology)|endemic]] to northern and central Australia.&lt;ref&gt;Taylor R., Cloake J, and Forner J. (2002)  Harvesting rates of a Yolgnu harvester and comparison of selection of didjeridu by the Yolngu and Jawoyn, ''Harvesting of didjeridu by Aboriginal people and their participation in the industry in the Northern Territory'' (ed. R. Taylor) pp. 25–31.  Report to AFFA Australia.  Northern Territory Parks and Wildlife Service, Department of Infrastructure, Planning and Environment, Palmerston, NT.&lt;/ref&gt; Generally the main trunk of the tree is harvested, though a substantial branch may be used instead. Traditional didgeridoo makers seek suitably hollow live trees in areas with obvious [[termite]] activity. Termites attack these living eucalyptus trees, removing only the dead heartwood of the tree, as the living sapwood contains a chemical that repels the insects.&lt;ref&gt;McMahon, Charlie. (2004) The Ecology of Termites and Didjeridus, ''The Didgeridoo: From Ancient Times to the Modern Age'' (ed. David Lindner) Schönau: Traumzeit-Verlag&lt;/ref&gt; Various techniques are employed to find trees with a suitable hollow, including knowledge of landscape and termite activity patterns, and a kind of tap or knock test, in which the bark of the tree is peeled back, and a fingernail or the blunt end of a tool, such as an axe, is knocked against the wood to determine if the hollow produces the right resonance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=How is a Yidaki Made? |url=http://www.yirrkala.com/yidaki/dhawu/08howmade.html |work=Yidaki Dhawu Miwatjnurunydja |publisher=Buku Larrngay Mulka Centre |accessdate=14 July 2011 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110214193750/http://www.yirrkala.com/yidaki/dhawu/08howmade.html |archivedate=14 February 2011 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt; Once a suitably hollow tree is found, it is cut down and cleaned out, the bark is taken off, the ends trimmed, and the exterior is shaped; this results in a finished instrument. A rim of [[beeswax]] may be applied to the [[mouthpiece (brass)|mouthpiece]] end.
===Modern===
{{see also|Modern didgeridoo designs}}
Non-traditional didgeridoos can be made from native or non-native hard woods (typically split, hollowed and rejoined), glass, [[fibreglass]], metal, [[agave]], clay, hemp (in the form of a bioplastic named [[zelfo]]), PVC piping and carbon fibre. These typically have an upper inside diameter of around 1.25&quot; down to a bell end of anywhere between two and eight inches and have a length corresponding to the desired key. The end of the pipe can be shaped and smoothed to create a comfortable mouthpiece or an added mouthpiece can be made of any shaped and smoothed material such as rubber, rubber stopper with a hole or beeswax.

[[Modern didgeridoo designs]] are distinct from the traditional Australian [[Australian Aborigines|Aboriginal]] didgeridoo, and are innovations recognised by [[musicologist]]s.&lt;ref name=Max1&gt;Wade-Matthews, M., Thompson, W., ''The Encyclopedia of Music'', 2011, pp184–185. {{ISBN|0-7607-6243-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; Didgeridoo design innovation started in the late 20th century, using non-traditional materials and non-traditional shapes. The practice has sparked, however, a good deal of debate (aesthetic, ethic, and legal) among indigenous practitioners and non-indigenous people, along a spectrum of amateur appropriation to more-respectful and -sophisticated expertise. &lt;ref&gt;Brian Fitzgerald and Susan Hedge, &quot;Traditional Cultural Expression and the Internet World,&quot; in Christoph Antons, ed., ''Traditional Knowledge, Traditional Cultural Expressions, and Intellectual Property Law in the Asia-Pacific Region'' (Aalphen an den Rijn, Netherlands: 2009), 264-65. {{ISBN|9789041127211}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;Hannah Edgar and Elias Gross, &quot;Earth Sounds: The Didgeridoo Stirs Controversy at the Bang on a Can Summer Festival&quot; (8/8/2019). Available at https://www.newsounds.org/story/earth-sounds-didgeridoo-stirs-controversy-bang-can-summer-festival/&lt;/ref&gt;

===Decoration===
Didgeridoos can be painted by their maker or a dedicated artist using traditional or modern paints while others retain the natural wood grain with minimal or no decoration.

==Playing==
[[File:Didgeridoo (Imagicity 1070).jpg|thumb|An Aboriginal man playing the didgeridoo]]
The didgeridoo is played with continuously vibrating lips to produce the drone while using a special breathing technique called [[circular breathing]]. This requires breathing in through the nose whilst simultaneously expelling stored air out of the mouth using the tongue and cheeks. By use of this technique, a skilled player can replenish the air in their lungs, and with practice can sustain a note for as long as desired. Recordings exist of modern didgeridoo players playing continuously for more than 40 minutes; [[Mark Atkins (musician)|Mark Atkins]] on ''Didgeridoo Concerto'' (1994) plays for over 50 minutes continuously.

The didgeridoo functions &quot;...as an aural kaleidoscope of timbres&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;baines&quot;&gt;A Baines, The Oxford Companion to Musical Instruments OUP 1992&lt;/ref&gt; and that &quot;the extremely difficult virtuoso techniques developed by expert performers find no parallel elsewhere.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;baines&quot; /&gt;

== Physics and operation ==
{{further|Frequency spectrum}}
[[File:Didgeridoo street player-2.jpg|thumb|Didgeridoo street player in Spain]]

A termite-bored didgeridoo has an irregular shape that, overall, usually increases in diameter towards the lower end. This shape means that its resonances occur at frequencies that are not harmonically spaced in frequency. This contrasts with the [[harmonic]] spacing of the resonances in a cylindrical plastic pipe, whose resonant frequencies fall in the ratio 1:3:5 etc. The second resonance of a didgeridoo (the note sounded by overblowing) is usually around an [[eleventh|11th]] higher than the fundamental frequency (a frequency ratio somewhat less than 3:1).

The vibration produced by the player's lips has harmonics, i.e., it has frequency components falling exactly in the ratio 1:2:3 etc. However, the non-harmonic spacing of the instrument's resonances means that the harmonics of the fundamental note are not systematically assisted by instrument resonances, as is usually the case for Western wind instruments (e.g., in the low range of the [[clarinet]], the 1st, 3rd, and 5th harmonics of the reed are assisted by resonances of the bore).

Sufficiently strong resonances of the vocal tract can strongly influence the [[timbre]] of the instrument.
At some frequencies, whose values depend on the position of the player's tongue, resonances of the vocal tract inhibit the oscillatory flow of air into the instrument.
Bands of frequencies that are not thus inhibited produce [[formants]] in the output sound.
These formants, and especially their variation during the inhalation and exhalation phases of circular breathing, give the instrument its readily recognizable sound.

Other variations in the didgeridoo's sound can be made by adding vocalizations to the drone. Most of the vocalizations are related to sounds emitted by Australian animals, such as the [[dingo]] or the [[kookaburra]]. To produce these sounds, the players simply have to use their vocal folds to produce the sounds of the animals whilst continuing to blow air through the instrument. The results range from very high-pitched sounds to much lower sounds involving interference between the lip and vocal fold vibrations.  Adding vocalizations increases the complexity of the playing.

==In popular culture==
Modern performances using the didgeridoo include combining it with [[beatboxing]]. It was featured on the British children's TV series ''[[Blue Peter]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/learningzone/clips/didgeridoo-beat-boxing/10171.html|title=Didgeridoo Beat-boxing|publisher=[[BBC]]|work=[[Blue Peter]]|accessdate=31 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The didgeridoo also became a role playing instrument in the experimental and avant-garde music scene. Industrial music bands like [[Test Department]] generated sounds from this instrument and used them in their industrial performances.

It is very often used in the music project Naakhum which combines Extreme Metal and Ethnic music.

Early songs by the acid jazz band [[Jamiroquai]] featured didgeridoo player Wallis Buchanan (until he left the band in 1999). A notable song featuring a didgeridoo is the band's first single &quot;[[When You Gonna Learn]]&quot;, which features prominent didgeridoo playing in both the introduction and solo sections.

The instrument is commonly used by ambient artist [[Steve Roach (musician)|Steve Roach]] as a complement to his produced soundscapes, in both live and recorded formats.  It features prominently in his collaborative work ''[[Australia: Sound of the Earth]]'' (with Australian Aboriginal artist [[David Hudson (musician)|David Hudson]] and cellist Sarah Hopkins) as well as ''Dreamtime Return''.

It is used in the Indian song &quot;[[Jaane Kyon]]&quot; from the film ''[[Dil Chahta Hai]]''.

Chris Brooks, lead singer of the New Zealand [[hard rock]] band [[Like a Storm]] uses the didgeridoo in some of the band's songs including &quot;Love the Way You Hate Me&quot; from their album ''[[Chaos Theory: Part 1]]''.

[[Kate Bush]] made extensive use of the didgeridoo (played by Australian musician [[Rolf Harris]]) on her album ''[[The Dreaming (album)|The Dreaming]]'', which was written and recorded after a holiday in Australia.

[[Charlie McMahon]], who formed the group [[Gondwanaland (band)|Gondwanaland]], was one of the first non-Aboriginal players to gain fame as a professional didgeridoo player. He has toured internationally with [[Midnight Oil]]. He invented the [[didjeribone]], a sliding didgeridoo made from two lengths of plastic tubing; its playing style is somewhat in the manner of a [[trombone]], hence the [[portmanteau]] name.

==Cultural significance==
[[File:Australia Aboriginal Culture 009.jpg|thumb|upright|An Indigenous Australian man playing a didgeridoo]]
[[File:Reticulated Didjeridoo 2015.jpg|thumb|upright|Musician playing a Travel or Reticulated Didgeridoo]]
Traditionally, the didgeridoo was played as an accompaniment to ceremonial dancing and singing and for solo or recreational purposes. For Aboriginal peoples of northern Australia, the yidaki is still used to accompany singers and dancers in [[Aboriginal Australian ceremony|cultural ceremonies]]. For the Yolngu people, the yidaki is part of their whole physical and cultural landscape and environment, comprising the people and spirit beings which belong to their country, [[Aboriginal kinship|kinship system]] and the [[Yolngu Matha language]]. It is connected to Yolngu Law and underpinned by ceremony, in song, dance, visual art and stories.&lt;ref name=nicholls/&gt; 

Pair sticks, sometimes called [[clapstick]]s (''bilma'' or ''bimla'' by some traditional groups)&lt;ref name=&quot;UniMelbourne&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Clapsticks: Teaching with Unique Objects |url=https://library.unimelb.edu.au/teachingobjects/objects/clapsticks |website=University of Melbourne: Teaching with Unique Collections |accessdate=24 July 2019 |ref=UniMelbourne}}&lt;/ref&gt;, establish the beat for the songs during ceremonies. The rhythm of the didgeridoo and the beat of the clapsticks are precise, and these patterns have been handed down for many generations. In the [[Wangga]] genre, the song-man starts with vocals and then introduces ''bilma'' to the accompaniment of didgeridoo.&lt;ref name=&quot;Elkin&quot;&gt;[[A. P. Elkin|Elkin, A. P.]] (1979) [1938]. ''The Australian Aborigines''. [[Angus &amp; Robertson]]. Sydney, NSW. p. 290. {{ISBN|0-207-13863-X}}. Quoted at [http://www.manikay.com/didjeridu/styles.shtml Manikay.Com]. Retrieved 17 April 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Gender-based traditional prohibition debate===
Traditionally, only men play the didgeridoo and sing during ceremonial occasions and playing by females is sometimes discouraged by Aboriginal communities and elders. In 2008, publisher [[Harper Collins]] apologized for its book ''The Daring Book for Girls'', which openly encouraged girls to play the instrument after some Aboriginal academics described such encouragement as &quot;extreme cultural insensitivity&quot; and &quot;an extreme faux pas{{nbsp}}... part of a general ignorance that mainstream Australia has about Aboriginal culture.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;PBP&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title =The Didjeridu: From Arnhemland to Internet|publisher =Perfect Beat Publishers|pp= 89–98|ISBN=1-86462-003-X|editor-first =	Karl |editor-last =Neuenfeldt|date=1997}} &lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/asia-pacific/7595515.stm Didgeridoo book upsets Aborigines, BBC]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/australasia/daring-book-for-girls-breaks-didgeridoo-taboo-in-australia-917751.html 'Daring Book for Girls' breaks didgeridoo taboo in Australia]&lt;/ref&gt; However, Linda Barwick, an [[Ethnomusicology|ethnomusicologist]], says that though traditionally women have not played the didgeridoo in ceremony, in informal situations there is no prohibition in the [[Dreamtime|Dreaming Law]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.bushcrafts.com.au/Info_pages/Can_women_play_didgeridoo.html |title=Women can play didgeridoo – taboo incites sales&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt; |access-date=25 May 2007 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070604181534/http://www.bushcrafts.com.au/Info_pages/Can_women_play_didgeridoo.html |archive-date=4 June 2007 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, Jemima Wimalu, a Mara woman from the Roper River is very proficient at playing the didgeridoo and is featured on the [[Gramophone record|record]] ''Aboriginal Sound Instruments'' released in 1978. In 1995, musicologist Steve Knopoff observed Yirrkala women performing ''djatpangarri'' songs that are traditionally performed by men and in 1996, ethnomusicologist Elizabeth MacKinley reported women of the Yanyuwa group giving public performances. 

While there is no prohibition in the area of the didgeridoo's origin, such restrictions have been applied by other Indigenous communities. The didgeridoo was introduced to the [[Kimberley (Western Australia)|Kimberleys]] almost a century ago but it is only in the last decade that Aboriginal men have shown adverse reactions to women playing the instrument and prohibitions are especially evident in the South East of Australia. The belief that women are prohibited from playing is widespread among non-Aboriginal people and is also common among Aboriginal communities in Southern Australia; some [[ethnomusicologist]]s believe that the dissemination of the [[taboo]] belief and other misconceptions is a result of commercial agendas and marketing. The majority of commercial didgeridoo recordings available are distributed by multinational recording companies and feature non-Aboriginal people playing a [[New Age]] style of music with [[liner notes]] promoting the instrument's spirituality which misleads consumers about the didgeridoo's secular role in traditional Aboriginal culture.&lt;ref name=&quot;PBP&quot;/&gt;

The taboo is particularly strong among many Aboriginal groups in the South East of Australia, where it is forbidden and considered &quot;cultural theft&quot; for non-Aboriginal women, and especially performers of New Age music regardless of gender, to play or even touch a didgeridoo.&lt;ref name=&quot;PBP&quot;/&gt;

==Health benefits==
A 2005 study reported in the ''[[British Medical Journal]]'' found that learning and practising the didgeridoo helped reduce [[snoring]] and [[obstructive sleep apnea]] by strengthening muscles in the upper airway, thus reducing their tendency to collapse during sleep. In the study, intervention subjects were trained in and practiced didgeridoo playing, including [[circular breathing]] and other techniques. Control subjects were asked not to play the instrument. Subjects were surveyed before and after the study period to assess the effects of intervention.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Puhan MA, Suarez A, Lo Cascio C | title=Didgeridoo playing as alternative treatment for obstructive sleep apnea syndrome: randomised controlled trial | journal=BMJ | year=2005 | volume=332 | pages=266–70 | doi=10.1136/bmj.38705.470590.55 | url=http://bmj.bmjjournals.com/cgi/content/full/332/7536/266 | pmid=16377643 | issue=7536 | pmc=1360393|display-authors=etal}}&lt;/ref&gt; A small 2010 study noted improvements in the asthma management of Aboriginal teens when incorporating didgeridoo playing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Eley|first1=Robert|last2=Gorman|first2=Don|title=Didgeridoo Playing and Singing to Support Asthma Management in Aboriginal Australians|journal=The Journal of Rural Health|volume=26|issue=1|year=2010|pages=100–104|issn=0890-765X|pmid=20105276|doi=10.1111/j.1748-0361.2009.00256.x|url=http://eprints.usq.edu.au/3551/3/Eley_Gorman_JRH_v26n1_SV.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Amateur Didgeridoo Player Using Bamboo Instrument.jpg|thumb|Amateur didgeridoo player using bamboo instrument]]

==See also==
* [[Aboriginal Centre for the Performing Arts]] 
* [[Alphorn]]
* [[Djalu Gurruwiwi]], master maker and player of yiḏaki
* [[Erke]]
* [[Indigenous Australian music]]
* [[List of didgeridoo players]]
* [[Maya_music#Trumpets|Mayan trumpet]]

==Selected bibliography==
{{Refbegin|30em}}
* Ah Chee Ngala, P., Cowell C. (1996): ''How to Play the Didgeridoo – and history''. {{ISBN|0-646-32840-9}}
* Chaloupka, G. (1993): ''Journey in Time''. Reed, Sydney.
* Cope, Jonathan (2000): ''How to Play the Didgeridoo: a practical guide for everyone''. {{ISBN|0-9539811-0-X}}.
* Jones, T. A. (1967): &quot;The didjeridu. Some comparisons of its typology and musical functions with similar instruments throughout the world&quot;. ''Studies in Music'' 1, pp.&amp;nbsp;23–55.
* Kaye, Peter (1987): ''How to Play the Didjeridu of the Australian Aboriginal – A Newcomer's Guide''.
* Kennedy, K. (1933): &quot;Instruments of music used by the Australian Aborigines&quot;. ''Mankind'' (August edition), pp.&amp;nbsp;147–157.
* Lindner, D. (ed) (2005): ''The Didgeridoo Phenomenon. From Ancient Times to the Modern Age''. Traumzeit-Verlag, Germany.
* Moyle, A. M. (1981): &quot;The Australian didjeridu: A late musical intrusion&quot;. in ''World Archaeology'', 12(3), 321–31.
* Neuenfeldt, K. (ed) (1997): ''The didjeridu: From Arnhem Land to Internet''. Sydney: J. Libbey/Perfect Beat Publications.
{{Refend}}

== References ==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
{{Commons+cat|Didgeridoo|Didgeridoos}}
* [http://www.ididj.com.au/ iDIDJ Australian Didgeridoo Cultural Hub]
* [http://www.dreamtime-didjeriduw3server.com/ The Didjeridu W3 Server]
* [http://www.phys.unsw.edu.au/~jw/dij/dij.html The physics of the didj]
* [http://www.phys.unsw.edu.au/jw/didjeridu.html Didgeridoo acoustics] from the [[University of New South Wales]]
* [http://www.manikay.com Database of audio recordings of traditional Arnhem Land music, samples included, many with didgeridoo]
* [http://imaginariumdev.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/10/The-Didjeridu-A-Guide.pdf ''The Didjeridu: A Guide'']  By Joe Cheal – General info on the didgeridoo, with citations and references
* [http://www.biolodidje.com BioloDidje] (translations available)
* [http://www.yidakistory.com/ Yidakiwuy Dhawu Miwatjngurunydja] comprehensive site by traditional owners of the instrument

{{Culture of Oceania}}
{{Indigenous music of Australia}}
{{Natural horns}}

[[Category:Australian Aboriginal music]]
[[Category:Australian English]]
[[Category:Australian musical instruments]]
[[Category:Circular breathing]]
[[Category:Natural horns and trumpets]]
[[Category:Articles containing video clips]]</text>
      <sha1>r9h9rasdxiujg0la0xlp6r7wgskyl6d</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
