  <page>
    <title>Sideroxylon grandiflorum</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8421</id>
    <revision>
      <id>907395286</id>
      <parentid>907325379</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-07-22T16:08:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Elmidae</username>
        <id>23750853</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>auto-size</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{speciesbox
|image = Sideroxylon grandiflorum - Mauritian endemic tree.jpg
|image_caption = Young tree
|taxon = Sideroxylon grandiflorum
|authority = [[A. P. de Candolle|A.DC.]]
|synonyms =
*''Calvaria grandiflora'' (A.DC.) Dubard
*''Sapota lessertii'' A.DC.
*''Sideroxylon annithomae'' Aubrév.
*''Sideroxylon lessertii'' (A.DC.) Baker
|synonyms_ref = &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theplantlist.org/tpl/record/kew-191933|title=The Plant List}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

'''''Sideroxylon grandiflorum''''', known as '''tambalacoque''' or '''dodo tree''', is a long-lived tree in the family [[Sapotaceae]], [[endemic (ecology)|endemic]] to [[Mauritius]]. It is valued for its timber. The ''Sideroxylon grandiflorum'' fruit is analogous to the [[peach]]. They are both termed [[drupes]] because both have a hard [[endocarp]], or pit, surrounding the seed, with the endocarp naturally splitting along a fracture line during germination.

==History==
[[File:DodoTree-Naturalis-PeterMaas2009.jpg|thumb|left|Preserved seeds.]]
In 1973, it was thought that this species was dying out. There were supposedly only 13 specimens left, all estimated to be about 300 years old. The true age could not be determined because tambalacoque has no [[growth ring]]s. [[Stanley Temple]] hypothesized that the [[dodo]], which became extinct in the 17th century, ate tambalacoque fruits, and only by passing through the digestive tract of the dodo could the seeds germinate. Temple (1977) force-fed seventeen tambalacoque fruits to [[wild turkey]]s. Seven of the fruits were crushed by the bird's gizzard. The remaining ten were either regurgitated or passed with the bird's feces. Temple planted the remaining ten fruits and three germinated. Temple did not try to germinate any seeds from control fruits not fed to turkeys so the effect of feeding fruits to turkeys was unclear. Reports made on tambalacoque seed germination by Hill (1941) and King (1946) found the seeds germinated without abrading.

Temple's hypothesis that the tree required the dodo has been contested. Others have suggested the decline of the tree was exaggerated, or that other extinct animals may also have been distributing the seeds, such as [[tortoise]]s, [[fruit bat]]s or the [[broad-billed parrot]]. Wendy Strahm and Anthony Cheke, two experts in [[Mascarene Islands|Mascarene]] [[ecology]], claim that while a rare tree, it has germinated since the demise of the dodo and numbers a few hundred, not 13.{{Citation needed|date=September 2010}} The difference in numbers is because young trees are not distinct in appearance and may easily be confused with similar species. The decline of the tree may possibly be due to [[introduced species|introduction]] of [[domestic pig]]s and [[crab-eating macaque]]s and competition with introduced plants. Catling (2001) in a summary cites Owadally and Temple (1979), and Witmer (1991). Hershey (2004) reviewed the flaws in Temple's dodo-tambalacoque hypothesis.

In 2004, [[Botanical Society of America|Botanical Society of America's]] Plant Science Bulletin disputed Dr. Temple's research as flawed which published evidence as to why the dodo's extinction did not directly cause the increasing disappearance of young trees including suggestion that [[tortoises]] would have been more likely to disperse the seeds than dodo hence discrediting Temple's view as to the dodo and the tree's sole survival relationship.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |url=http://www.botany.org/PlantScienceBulletin/psb-2004-50-4.php#Dodo |title=The Widespread Misconception that the Tambalacoque or ''Calvaria'' Tree Absolutely Required the Dodo Bird for its Seeds to Germinate |first=David R |last=Herhey |journal=Plant Science Bulletin |year=2004 |volume=50 |issue=4 |issn=0032-0919}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Uses==
This dodo tree is highly valued for its wood in Mauritius, which has led some foresters to scrape the pits by hand to make them sprout and grow.&lt;ref name=&quot;EllisNTB&quot;&gt;{{cite book| last = Ellis| first = Richard| authorlink = Richard Ellis (biologist) | title = No Turning Back: The Life and Death of Animal Species| publisher = Harper Perennial | year = 2004| location = New York| pages = 164| isbn =0-06-055804-0 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* ''[[Sideroxylon majus]]'', a species native to [[Réunion]], that has been confounded with ''Sideroxylon grandiflorum'' (particularly under its synonym ''Calvaria major'')

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* '''Catling''', P. M. (2001): Extinction and the importance of history and dependence in conservation. ''Biodiversity'' 2(3): 2-13 [https://web.archive.org/web/20031230211908/http://www.tc-biodiversity.org/sample-extinction.pdf pdf]
* '''Helfferich''', C. (1990): [http://www.gi.alaska.edu/ScienceForum/ASF11/1110.html The Turkey and the Tambalacoque Tree]
* '''Hershey''', D. R. (2004): [http://www.botany.org/PlantScienceBulletin/psb-2004-50-4.php#Dodo The widespread misconception that the tambalacoque absolutely required the dodo for its seeds to germinate.] ''Plant Science Bulletin'' 50: 105-108.
* '''Hill''', A. W. (1941): The genus ''Calvaria'', with an account of the stony endocarp and germination of the seed, and description of the new species. ''Annals of Botany'' '''5'''(4): 587-606. [http://aob.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/reprint/5/4/587 PDF fulltext] (requires user account)
* '''King''', H. C. (1946): ''Interim Report on Indigenous Species in Mauritius''. Port Louis, Mauritius: Government Printer.
* '''Owadally''', A. W. &amp; '''Temple''', Stanley A. (1979): The dodo and the tambalacoque tree. ''[[Science (journal)|Science]]'' '''203'''(4387): 1363-1364.
* '''Quammen''', David (1996): ''The Song of the Dodo: Island Biogeography in an Age of Extinction''. Touchstone, New York. &lt;small&gt;{{ISBN|0-684-82712-3}}&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- 1997 is reprint --&gt;
* '''Temple''', Stanley A. (1977): Plant-animal mutualism: coevolution with Dodo leads to near extinction of plant. ''[[Science (journal)|Science]]'' '''197'''(4306): 885-886. [https://www.jstor.org/stable/1744474 HTML abstract]
* '''Witmer''', M. C. &amp; '''Cheke''', A. S. (1991): The dodo and the tambalacoque tree: an obligate mutualism reconsidered. ''[[Oikos (journal)|Oikos]]'' '''61'''(1): 133-137. [http://cat.inist.fr/?aModele=afficheN&amp;cpsidt=5082004 HTML abstract]

{{Taxonbar|from=Q1027556}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Sideroxylon Grandiflorum}}
[[Category:Sideroxylon|grandiflorum]]
[[Category:Endemic flora of Mauritius]]
[[Category:Trees of Africa]]</text>
      <sha1>lkyrj8yp3r9cob2jamcvsry4rr8f0kp</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
