  <page>
    <title>Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8498</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943358596</id>
      <parentid>943133644</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-03-01T12:32:09Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>92.97.79.0</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Overall */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Psychiatric classification and diagnostic guide}}
[[File:DiagnosticAndStatisticalManualOfMentalDisorders.jpg|thumb|1952 edition of the DSM]]
The '''''Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders''''' ('''DSM''') (latest edition, the [[DSM-5]], published in 2013)  is a publication for the [[classification of mental disorders]] using a common language and standard criteria. It is used by clinicians, researchers, [[psychiatric drug]] regulation agencies, [[health insurance]] companies, [[pharmaceutical companies]], the legal system, and policy makers. It is published by the [[American Psychiatric Association]] (APA).

The DSM evolved from systems for collecting census and [[psychiatric hospital]] statistics, and from a [[United States Army]] manual. Revisions since its first publication in 1952 have incrementally added to the total number of [[mental disorders]], and removed those no longer considered to be mental disorders.

Two alternate classification publications are also widely used. The [[ICD-10 Chapter V: Mental and behavioural disorders|ICD-10 Classification of Mental and Behavioural Disorders]] is produced by the [[World Health Organization|WHO]].&lt;ref&gt;The ICD-10 Classification of Mental and Behavioural Disorders: &quot;Blue Book&quot; ([http://www.who.int/classifications/icd/en/bluebook.pdf Clinical descriptions and diagnostic guidelines]) and &quot;Green Book&quot; ([http://www.who.int/classifications/icd/en/GRNBOOK.pdf Diagnostic criteria for research])&lt;/ref&gt; The [[International Statistical Classification of Diseases and Related Health Problems|International Classification of Diseases]] (ICD) is the other common manual for mental disorders. It has broader scope than the DSM, covering overall health. While the DSM is the most popular diagnostic system for mental disorders in the U.S., the ICD is used more widely in Europe and other parts of the world, giving it a far larger reach than the DSM. The [[DSM-IV-TR codes|DSM-IV-TR]] (4th. ed.) contains specific codes allowing comparisons between the DSM and the ICD manuals, which may not systematically match because revisions are not simultaneously coordinated.&lt;ref&gt;In Appendix G: &quot;ICD-9-CM Codes for Selected General Medical Conditions and Medication-Induced Disorders&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Though recent editions of the DSM and ICD have become more similar due to collaborative agreements, each one contains information absent from the other.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = American Psychological Association | year = 2009 | title = ICD VS. DSM | url = http://www.apa.org/monitor/2009/10/icd-dsm.aspx | journal = Monitor on Psychology | volume = 40 | issue = 9|page = 63 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The DSM has received praise for standardizing psychiatric diagnosis grounded in empirical evidence, as opposed to the theory-bound [[nosology]] used in DSM-III; but it also generated [[#Criticisms|controversy and criticism]]. Criticisms include ongoing questions concerning the [[Reliability (statistics)|reliability]] and [[Validity (statistics)|validity]] of many diagnoses; the use of arbitrary dividing lines between mental illness and &quot;[[Normality (behavior)|normality]]&quot;; possible [[cultural bias]]; and the [[medicalization]] of human distress.&lt;ref name=frana&gt;{{cite web |url=http://annals.org/article.aspx?articleid=1688399 |title=The New Crisis in Confidence in Psychiatric Diagnosis |author=Allen Frances  |date=17 May 2013 |work=Annals of Internal Medicine |author-link=Allen Frances }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;concept&amp;evolution&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Dalal PK, Sivakumar T | year = 2009 | title = Moving towards ICD-11 and DSM-5: Concept and evolution of psychiatric classification | journal = Indian Journal of Psychiatry | volume = 51 | issue = 4| pages = 310–319 | doi = 10.4103/0019-5545.58302 | pmid = 20048461 | pmc = 2802383 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | pmid = 12505793  | doi=10.1176/appi.ajp.160.1.4 | volume=160 | issue=1 |date=January 2003 | pages=4–12 | title = Distinguishing Between the Validity and Utility of Psychiatric Diagnoses | last1 = Kendell | first1 = R. | journal = American Journal of Psychiatry | last2 = Jablensky | first2 = A| url=https://semanticscholar.org/paper/34d5f3ff43453b57f338b149230e3b30d4ed3f1b }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | pmid = 17329740  | doi=10.1192/bjp.bp.106.024026 | volume=190 |date=March 2007 | pages=210–6 | title = Diagnostic stability of psychiatric disorders in clinical practice | last1 = Baca-Garcia | first1 = E. | last2 = Perez-Rodriguez | first2 = M. M. | last3 = Basurte-Villamor | first3 = I. | last4 = Del Moral | first4 = A. L. F. | last5 = Jimenez-Arriero | first5 = M. A. | last6 = De Rivera | first6 = J. L. G. | last7 = Saiz-Ruiz | first7 = J. | last8 = Oquendo | first8 = M. A. | journal = The British Journal of Psychiatry | issue = 3| url=https://semanticscholar.org/paper/1b44c133daa3e1ca320bdbec28386a977e6b2cd0 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Pincus | first1 = H. A. | year = 1998 | title = 'Clinical Significance' and DSM-IV | url = http://archpsyc.ama-assn.org/cgi/content/extract/55/12/1145 | journal = Arch Gen Psychiatry | volume = 55 | issue = 12 | pmid = 9862559 | doi = 10.1001/archpsyc.55.12.1145 | last2 = Zarin | first2 = DA | last3 = First | first3 = M | pages = 1145; author reply 1147–8 | url-status = dead | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20070929134334/http://archpsyc.ama-assn.org/cgi/content/extract/55/12/1145 | archivedate = 2007-09-29 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Uses and definition==
Mental health professionals use the manual to determine and help communicate a patient's diagnosis after an evaluation. Hospitals, clinics, and insurance companies in the United States may require a DSM diagnosis for all patients treated. The DSM can be used clinically, or to categorize patients using diagnostic criteria for research purposes. but they are correlated with the pharmaceutical corps to for profit purposes{{Clarify|date=March 2019}}{{citation needed|date=March 2019}}. Some studies done on specific disorders often recruit patients whose symptoms match the criteria listed in the DSM for that disorder. An international survey of psychiatrists in sixty-six countries compared the use of the [[ICD-10]] and DSM-IV. It  found the former was more often used for clinical diagnosis while the latter was more valued for research.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Mezzich|first=Juan E.|year=2002|title=International Surveys on the Use of ICD-10 and Related Diagnostic Systems|journal=Psychopathology|volume=35|issue=2–3|pages=72–75|doi=10.1159/000065122|pmid=12145487}}&lt;/ref&gt;

DSM-5, and the abbreviations for all previous editions, are [[Trademark#Registration|registered trademarks]] owned by the APA.&lt;ref name=&quot;concept&amp;evolution&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;titleTrademark''' Electronic Search System (TESS)&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://tess2.uspto.gov/|title=Trademark Electronic Search System (TESS)|accessdate=2010-02-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
===Pre-DSM-1 (1840 - 1949)===
{{more citations needed section|date=December 2017}}

====Census data and report (1840 - 1888)====
The initial impetus for developing a classification of mental disorders in the United States was the need to collect statistical information. The first official attempt was the [[United States census, 1840|1840 census]], which used a single category: &quot;[[idiocy]]/[[insanity]]&quot;. Three years later, the [[American Statistical Association]] made an official protest to the [[U.S. House of Representatives]], stating that &quot;the most glaring and remarkable errors are found in the statements respecting [[nosology]], prevalence of insanity, blindness, deafness, and dumbness, among the people of this nation&quot;, pointing out that in many towns [[African-Americans]] were all marked as insane, and calling the statistics essentially useless.

The [[Association of Medical Superintendents of American Institutions for the Insane]] was formed in 1844; it has since changed its name twice before the new millennium: in 1892 to the American Medico-Psychological Association, and in 1921 to the present American Psychiatric Association (APA).

Edward Jarvis and later [[Francis Amasa Walker]] helped expand the census, from two volumes in 1870 to twenty-five volumes in 1880. Frederick H. Wines was appointed to write a 582-page volume called ''Report on the Defective, Dependent, and Delinquent Classes of the Population of the United States, As Returned at the Tenth Census (June 1, 1880)'' (published 1888). Wines used seven categories of mental illness: [[dementia]], [[dipsomania]] (uncontrollable craving for alcohol), [[epilepsy]], [[mania]], [[melancholia]], [[monomania]] and [[paresis]]. These categories were also adopted by the Association.&lt;ref&gt;[https://sites.google.com/site/psych54000/a History of the DSM] Nathaniel Deyoung, Purdue University. Retrieved 9th Sept 2013&lt;/ref&gt;

====American Psychiatric Association Manual (1917)====
In 1917, together with the National Commission on [[Mental health|Mental Hygiene]] (now [[Mental Health America]]), the APA developed a new guide for mental hospitals called the ''Statistical Manual for the Use of Institutions for the Insane''. This included twenty-two diagnoses and would be revised several times by the APA over the years.&lt;ref&gt;[https://archive.org/details/statisticalmanu00assogoog Statistical manual for the use of institutions for the insane (1918)] University of Michigan via Internet Archive&lt;/ref&gt; Along with the [[New York Academy of Medicine]], the APA also provided the psychiatric [[nomenclature]] subsection of the U.S. general medical guide, the ''Standard Classified Nomenclature of Disease'', referred to as the ''Standard''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1=Greenberg | first1=S | last2=Shuman | first2=DW | last3=Meyer | first3=RG | title=Unmasking forensic diagnosis | journal=International Journal of Law and Psychiatry | volume=27 | issue=1 | pages=1–15 | year=2004 | pmid=15019764 | doi=10.1016/j.ijlp.2004.01.001 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Medical 203 (1943)====
[[World War II]] saw the large-scale involvement of U.S. psychiatrists in the selection, processing, assessment, and treatment of soldiers. This moved the focus away from mental institutions and traditional clinical perspectives. Under the direction of [[James Forrestal]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://navymedicine.navylive.dodlive.mil/archives/7192|title=A Brief History of U.S. Navy Psychiatric Diagnoses, Part II – Navy Medicine}}&lt;/ref&gt; a committee headed by psychiatrist [[Brigadier General (United States)|Brigadier General]] [[William C. Menninger]], with the assistance of the Mental Hospital Service&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |pmc = 2015553|year = 1953|last1 = Sandison|first1 = R. A.|title = Mental Hospital Service|journal = British Medical Journal|volume = 1|issue = 4809|pages = 560|last2 = Spencer|first2 = A. M.|doi = 10.1136/bmj.1.4809.560}}&lt;/ref&gt; developed a new classification scheme called Medical 203, that was issued in 1943 as a War Department Technical Bulletin under the auspices of the [[Office of the Surgeon General]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Houts2000&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | author = Houts A.C. | year = 2000 | title = Fifty years of psychiatric nomenclature: Reflections on the 1943 War Department Technical Bulletin, Medical 203 | url = http://www3.interscience.wiley.com/journal/72506618/abstract | archive-url = https://archive.today/20130105054908/http://www3.interscience.wiley.com/journal/72506618/abstract | url-status = dead | archive-date = 2013-01-05 | journal = Journal of Clinical Psychology | volume = 56 | issue = 7| pages = 935–967 | doi = 10.1002/1097-4679(200007)56:7&lt;935::AID-JCLP11&gt;3.0.CO;2-8 | pmid = 10902952 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The foreword to the DSM-I states the [[US Navy|United States Navy]] had itself made some minor revisions but &quot;the Army established a much more sweeping revision, abandoning the basic outline of the Standard and attempting to express present day concepts of mental disturbance. This nomenclature eventually was adopted by all Armed Forces&quot;, and &quot;assorted modifications of the Armed Forces nomenclature [were] introduced into many clinics and hospitals by psychiatrists returning from military duty.&quot; The [[United States Department of Veterans Affairs|Veterans Administration]] also adopted a slightly modified version of Medical 203.{{citation needed|date=August 2013}}

====ICD-6 (1949)====
In 1949, the [[World Health Organization]] published the sixth revision of the [[International Statistical Classification of Diseases]] (ICD), which included a section on mental disorders for the first time. The foreword to DSM-1 states this &quot;categorized mental disorders in rubrics similar to those of the Armed Forces nomenclature.&quot;

===DSM-1 (1952)===
An APA Committee on Nomenclature and Statistics was empowered to develop a version of Medical 203 specifically for use in the United States, to standardize the diverse and confused usage of different documents. In 1950, the APA committee undertook a review and consultation. It circulated an adaptation of Medical 203, the VA system, and the Standard's Nomenclature to approximately 10% of APA members. 46% replied, of which 93% approved, and after some further revisions (resulting in its being called DSM-I), the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders was approved in 1951 and published in 1952. The structure and conceptual framework were the same as in Medical 203, and many passages of text were identical.&lt;ref name=&quot;Houts2000&quot;/&gt; The manual was 130 pages long and listed 106 mental disorders.&lt;ref&gt;Grob, GN. (1991) [https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?db=pubmed&amp;cmd=Retrieve&amp;dopt=AbstractPlus&amp;list_uids=2006685  Origins of DSM-I: a study in appearance and reality] ''Am J Psychiatry.'' April;148(4):421–31.&lt;/ref&gt; These included several categories of &quot;personality disturbance&quot;, generally distinguished from &quot;neurosis&quot; (nervousness, [[egodystonic]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;Oldham&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=John M. Oldham|title=Personality Disorders|journal=FOCUS|year=2005|volume=3|pages=372–382|url=http://focus.psychiatryonline.org/article.aspx?Volume=3&amp;page=372&amp;journalID=21|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://archive.today/20120720080755/http://focus.psychiatryonline.org/article.aspx?Volume=3&amp;page=372&amp;journalID=21|archivedate=2012-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1952, the APA listed homosexuality in the DSM as a [[Antisocial personality disorder|sociopathic]] personality disturbance. ''[[Homosexuality: A Psychoanalytic Study of Male Homosexuals]]'', a large-scale 1962 study of homosexuality by [[Irving Bieber]] and other authors, was used to justify inclusion of the disorder as a supposed pathological hidden fear of the opposite sex caused by traumatic parent–child relationships. This view was very influential in the medical profession.&lt;ref&gt;Edsall, p. 247.&lt;/ref&gt;{{full citation needed|date=August 2016}} In 1956, however, the psychologist [[Evelyn Hooker]] performed a study comparing the happiness and well-adjusted nature of self-identified homosexual men with heterosexual men and found no difference.&lt;ref&gt;Edsall, p. 310.&lt;/ref&gt;{{full citation needed|date=August 2016}} Her study stunned the medical community and made her a heroine to many gay men and lesbians,&lt;ref&gt;Marcus, p. 58–59.&lt;/ref&gt;{{full citation needed|date=August 2016}} but homosexuality remained in the DSM until May 1974.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/?id=drBejRLWkHkC&amp;pg=PA76 |chapter=The Transformation of Mental Disorders in the 1980s: The DSM-III, Managed Care, and &quot;Cosmetic Psychopharmacology&quot; |page=76 |title=Medicating Children: ADHD and Pediatric Mental Health |first1=Rick |last1=Mayes |first2=Catherine |last2=Bagwell |first3=Jennifer L. |last3=Erkulwater |publisher=Harvard University Press |date= 2009 |accessdate=2013-12-03 |isbn=978-0-674-03163-0 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===DSM-II (1968)===
In the 1960s, there were many challenges to the concept of [[mental illness]] itself. These challenges came from psychiatrists like [[Thomas Szasz]], who argued mental illness was a myth used to disguise moral conflicts; from sociologists such as [[Erving Goffman]], who said mental illness was another example of how society labels and controls non-conformists; from [[behavioural psychologist]]s who challenged psychiatry's fundamental reliance on unobservable phenomena; and from gay rights activists who criticised the APA's listing of homosexuality as a mental disorder. A study published in ''Science'' by [[Rosenhan experiment|Rosenhan]] received much publicity and was viewed as an attack on the efficacy of psychiatric diagnosis.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stuart A, Kirk &amp; Herb Kutchins 1994&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.academyanalyticarts.org/kirk&amp;kutchins.htm |title=The Myth of the Reliability of DSM |author1=Stuart A, Kirk |author2=Herb Kutchins |year=1994 |work=Journal of Mind and Behavior, 15(1&amp;2) |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080307115815/http://www.academyanalyticarts.org/kirk%26kutchins.htm |archivedate=2008-03-07 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although the APA was closely involved in the next significant revision of the mental disorder section of the ICD (version 8 in 1968), it decided to go ahead with a revision of the DSM. It was published in 1968, listed 182 disorders, and was 134 pages long. It was quite similar to the DSM-I. The term &quot;reaction&quot; was dropped, but the term &quot;[[neurosis]]&quot; was retained. Both the DSM-I and the DSM-II reflected the predominant [[psychodynamic]] psychiatry,&lt;ref name = &quot;Revolution&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|doi= 10.1002/jhbs.20103|author1=Mayes, R.  |author2=Horwitz, AV.|year=2005|title=DSM-III and the revolution in the classification of mental illness|journal=J Hist Behav Sci|pmid= 15981242|volume=41|issue=3|pages=249–67}}&lt;/ref&gt; although they also included biological perspectives and concepts from [[Kraepelin]]'s system of classification. Symptoms were not specified in detail for specific disorders. Many were seen as reflections of broad underlying conflicts or maladaptive reactions to life problems, rooted in a distinction between neurosis and [[psychosis]] (roughly, anxiety/depression broadly in touch with reality, or [[hallucinations]]/[[delusions]] appearing disconnected from reality). Sociological and biological knowledge was incorporated, in a model that did not emphasize a clear boundary between normality and abnormality.&lt;ref name=&quot;Transformation&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Wilson | first1 = M. | date = March 1993 | title = DSM-III and the transformation of American psychiatry: a history | journal = Am J Psychiatry | volume = 150 | issue = 3| pages = 399–410 | pmid = 8434655 | doi=10.1176/ajp.150.3.399}}&lt;/ref&gt; The idea that personality disorders did not involve emotional distress was discarded.&lt;ref name=Oldham/&gt;

An influential 1974 paper by [[Robert Spitzer (psychiatrist)|Robert Spitzer]] and [[Joseph L. Fleiss]] demonstrated the second edition of the DSM (DSM-II) was an unreliable diagnostic tool.&lt;ref name=SpitzerFleiss1974&gt;{{Cite journal | last= Spitzer | first= Robert L. | last2= Fleiss | first2=Joseph L.| title= A re-analysis of the reliability of psychiatric diagnosis| journal= British Journal of Psychiatry| volume=125|pages= 341–347 |year = 1974 | doi= 10.1192/bjp.125.4.341 | pmid= 4425771 | issue=4}}&lt;/ref&gt; They found different practitioners using the DSM-II rarely agreed when diagnosing patients with similar problems. In reviewing previous studies of eighteen major diagnostic categories, Fleiss and Spitzer concluded &quot;there are no diagnostic categories for which reliability is uniformly high. Reliability appears to be only satisfactory for three categories: mental deficiency, organic brain syndrome (but not its subtypes), and alcoholism. The level of reliability is no better than fair for psychosis and [[schizophrenia]] and is poor for the remaining categories&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kirk &amp; Kutchins&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last=Kirk |first=Stuart A. |author2=Kutchins, Herb |year=1994 |title=The Myth of the Reliability of DSM |journal=Journal of Mind and Behavior |volume=15 |issue=1&amp;2 |pages=71–86 |url=http://www.academyanalyticarts.org/kirk&amp;kutchins.htm |accessdate=2008-03-04 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080307115815/http://www.academyanalyticarts.org/kirk%26kutchins.htm |archivedate=2008-03-07 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Sixth printing of the DSM-II (1974)====
As described by [[Ronald Bayer]], a psychiatrist and gay rights activist, specific protests by [[gay rights]] activists against the APA began in 1970, when the organization held its convention in [[San Francisco]]. The activists disrupted the conference by interrupting speakers and shouting down and ridiculing psychiatrists who viewed homosexuality as a mental disorder. In 1971, gay rights activist [[Frank Kameny]] worked with the [[Gay Liberation Front]] collective to demonstrate against the APA's convention. At the 1971 conference, Kameny grabbed the microphone and yelled: &quot;Psychiatry is the enemy incarnate. Psychiatry has waged a relentless war of extermination against us. You may take this as a declaration of war against you.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Ronald Bayer ''Homosexuality and American Psychiatry: The Politics of Diagnosis'' (1981) Princeton University Press p. 105.&lt;/ref&gt;

This activism occurred in the context of a broader [[anti-psychiatry]] movement that had come to the fore in the 1960s and was challenging the legitimacy of psychiatric diagnosis. Anti-psychiatry activists protested at the same APA conventions, with some shared slogans and intellectual foundations.&lt;ref&gt;McCommon, B. (2006) [https://web.archive.org/web/20070810054520/http://psychservices.psychiatryonline.org/cgi/content/full/57/12/1809 Antipsychiatry and the Gay Rights Movement] Psychiatr Serv 57:1809, December {{DOI|10.1176/appi.ps.57.12.1809}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Rissmiller, DJ, D.O., Rissmiller, J. (2006) [https://web.archive.org/web/20070630022511/http://ps.psychiatryonline.org/cgi/content/full/57/12/1809-a Letter in reply] Psychiatr Serv 57:1809-a-1810, December 2006 {{DOI|10.1176/appi.ps.57.12.1809-a}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Presented with data from researchers such as [[Alfred Kinsey]] and [[Evelyn Hooker]], the sixth printing of the DSM-II, in 1974, no longer listed homosexuality as a category of disorder. After a vote by the APA trustees in 1973, and confirmed by the wider APA membership in 1974, the diagnosis was replaced with the category of &quot;sexual orientation disturbance&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Spitzer | first1 = R.L. | year = 1981 | title = The diagnostic status of homosexuality in DSM-III: a reformulation of the issues | journal = Am J Psychiatry | volume = 138 | issue = 2| pages = 210–215 | pmid = 7457641 | doi=10.1176/ajp.138.2.210}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===DSM-III (1980)===
In 1974, the decision to create a new revision of the DSM was made, and [[Robert Spitzer (psychiatrist)|Robert Spitzer]] was selected as chairman of the task force. The initial impetus was to make the DSM nomenclature consistent with the [[ICD|International Statistical Classification of Diseases and Related Health Problems]] (ICD), published by the [[World Health Organization]]. The revision took on a far wider mandate under the influence and control of Spitzer and his chosen committee members.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Speigel |first=Alix |url=http://www.newyorker.com/fact/content/articles/050103fa_fact?050103fa_fact |title=The Dictionary of Disorder: How one man revolutionized psychiatry |date=3 January 2005 |website=The New Yorker |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20061212180933/http://www.newyorker.com/fact/content/articles/050103fa_fact?050103fa_fact |archive-date=12 December 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt; One goal was to improve the uniformity and validity of psychiatric diagnosis in the wake of a number of critiques, including the famous [[Rosenhan experiment]]. There was also a need to standardize diagnostic practices within the U.S. and with other countries after research showed psychiatric diagnoses differed between Europe and the United States.&lt;ref name=&quot;PMID5774702&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | url = http://ajp.psychiatryonline.org/cgi/reprint/125/10S/30 | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20100824224731/http://ajp.psychiatryonline.org/cgi/reprint/125/10S/30 | url-status = dead | archive-date = 2010-08-24 | pmid = 5774702 | issue = 10 Suppl | date = April 1969 | pages = 21–9 | last1 = Cooper | first1 = JE | last2 = Kendell | first2 = RE | last3 = Gurland | first3 = BJ | last4 = Sartorius | first4 = N | last5 = Farkas | first5 = T | title = Cross-national study of diagnosis of the mental disorders: some results from the first comparative investigation | journal = The American Journal of Psychiatry | volume = 125 | doi = 10.1176/ajp.125.10s.21 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The establishment of these criteria was an attempt to facilitate the pharmaceutical regulatory process.

The criteria adopted for many of the mental disorders were taken from the [[Research Diagnostic Criteria]] (RDC) and [[Feighner Criteria]], which had just been developed by a group of research-orientated psychiatrists based primarily at [[Washington University in St. Louis]] and the [[New York State Psychiatric Institute]]. Other criteria, and potential new categories of disorder, were established by consensus during meetings of the committee, as chaired by Spitzer. A key aim was to base categorization on colloquial English descriptive language (which would be easier to use by federal administrative offices), rather than assumptions of cause, although its categorical approach assumed each particular pattern of symptoms in a category reflected a particular underlying pathology (an approach described as &quot;[[Emil Kraepelin|neo-Kraepelinian]]&quot;). The [[psychodynamic]] or [[physiologic]] view was abandoned, in favor of a [[regulatory]] or [[legislative]] model. A new &quot;multiaxial&quot; system attempted to yield a picture more amenable to a statistical population census, rather than a simple [[medical diagnosis|diagnosis]]. Spitzer argued &quot;mental disorders are a subset of medical disorders&quot; but the task force decided on the DSM statement: &quot;Each of the mental disorders is conceptualized as a clinically significant behavioral or psychological syndrome.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Revolution&quot;/&gt; The [[personality disorders]] were placed on axis II along with mental retardation.&lt;ref name=Oldham/&gt;

The first draft of the DSM-III was prepared within a year. It introduced many new categories of disorder, while deleting or changing others. A number of the unpublished documents discussing and justifying the changes have recently come to light.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| last = Lane| first = Christopher| title = Shyness: How Normal Behavior Became a Sickness| year = 2007| publisher = Yale University Press| isbn = 978-0-300-12446-0| page = [https://archive.org/details/shynesshownormal00lane/page/263 263]| url-access = registration| url = https://archive.org/details/shynesshownormal00lane/page/263}}&lt;/ref&gt; Field trials sponsored by the U.S. [[National Institute of Mental Health]] (NIMH) were conducted between 1977 and 1979 to test the reliability of the new diagnoses. A controversy emerged regarding deletion of the concept of neurosis, a mainstream of [[psychoanalytic]] theory and therapy but seen as vague and unscientific by the DSM task force. Faced with enormous political opposition, the DSM-III was in serious danger of not being approved by the APA Board of Trustees unless &quot;neurosis&quot; was included in some capacity; a political compromise reinserted the term in parentheses after the word &quot;disorder&quot; in some cases. Additionally, the diagnosis of [[Ego-dystonic sexual orientation|ego-dystonic homosexuality]] replaced the DSM-II category of &quot;sexual orientation disturbance&quot;.

Finally published in 1980, the DSM-III was 494 pages and listed 265 diagnostic categories. It rapidly came into widespread international use and has been termed a revolution or transformation in psychiatry.&lt;ref name=&quot;Revolution&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Transformation&quot;/&gt;

When DSM-III was published, the developers made extensive claims about the reliability of the radically new diagnostic system they had devised, which relied on data from special field trials. However, according to a 1994 article by [[Stuart A. Kirk]]:

&lt;blockquote&gt;Twenty years after the reliability problem became the central focus of DSM-III, there is still not a single multi-site study showing that DSM (any version) is routinely used with high reliably by regular mental health clinicians. Nor is there any credible evidence that any version of the manual has greatly increased its reliability beyond the previous version. There are important methodological problems that limit the generalisability of most reliability studies. Each reliability study is constrained by the training and supervision of the interviewers, their motivation and commitment to diagnostic accuracy, their prior skill, the homogeneity of the clinical setting in regard to patient mix and base rates, and the methodological rigor achieved by the investigator ...&lt;ref name=&quot;Stuart A, Kirk &amp; Herb Kutchins 1994&quot;/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===DSM-III-R (1987)===
In 1987, the DSM-III-R was published as a revision of the DSM-III, under the direction of Spitzer. Categories were renamed and reorganized, and significant changes in criteria were made. Six categories were deleted while others were added. Controversial diagnoses, such as pre-menstrual dysphoric disorder and [[Self-defeating personality disorder|masochistic personality disorder]], were considered and discarded. &quot;Ego-dystonic homosexuality&quot; was also removed and was largely subsumed under &quot;sexual disorder not otherwise specified&quot;, which can include &quot;persistent and marked distress about one's sexual orientation.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Revolution&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Spiegel |first1=Alix |date=18 January 2002 |url=http://www.thisamericanlife.org/radio-archives/episode/204/81-words |title=81 Words |first2=Ira |last2=Glass |website=This American Life |location=Chicago |publisher=WBEZ Chicago Public Radio }}&lt;/ref&gt; Altogether, the DSM-III-R contained 292 diagnoses and was 567 pages long. Further efforts were made for the diagnoses to be purely descriptive, although the introductory text stated for at least some disorders, &quot;particularly the Personality Disorders, the criteria require much more inference on the part of the observer&quot; (p. xxiii).&lt;ref name=Oldham/&gt;

===DSM-IV (1994)===
In 1994, DSM-IV was published, listing 410 disorders in 886 pages. The task force was chaired by [[Allen Frances]]. A steering committee of twenty-seven people was introduced, including four psychologists. The steering committee created thirteen  work groups of five to sixteen members. Each work group had about twenty advisers.&lt;!-- .{{clarify|date=July 2013}} --&gt; The work groups conducted a three-step process: first, each group conducted an extensive literature review of their diagnoses; then, they requested data from researchers, conducting analyses to determine which criteria required change, with instructions to be conservative; finally, they conducted multicenter field trials relating diagnoses to clinical practice.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first1=Allen |last1=Frances |first2=Avram H. |last2=Mack |first3=Ruth |last3=Ross |first4=Michael B. |last4=First |date=2000 |orig-year=1995 |chapter-url=http://www.acnp.org/G4/GN401000082/CH081.html |chapter=The DSM-IV Classification and Psychopharmacology |title=Psychopharmacology: The Fourth Generation of Progress |publisher=American College of Neuropsychopharmacology |editor1-first=Floyd E. |editor1-last=Bloom |editor2-first=David J. |editor2-last=Kupfer }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Schaffer David | year = 1996 | title = A Participant's Observations: Preparing DSM-IV | url = https://ww1.cpa-apc.org/Publications/Archives/PDF/1996/Aug/schaffer.pdf | journal = Can J Psychiatry | volume = 41 | issue = 6| pages = 325–329 | doi = 10.1177/070674379604100602 | pmid = 8862851 }}&lt;/ref&gt; A major change from previous versions was the inclusion of a clinical significance criterion to almost half of all the categories, which required symptoms cause &quot;clinically significant distress or impairment in social, occupational, or other important areas of functioning&quot;. Some personality disorder diagnoses were deleted or moved to the appendix.&lt;ref name=Oldham/&gt;

===DSM-IV-TR (2000)===
A &quot;text revision&quot; of the DSM-IV, known as the DSM-IV-TR, was published in 2000. The diagnostic categories and the vast majority of the specific criteria for diagnosis were unchanged.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |website=American Psychiatric Association |url=http://www.psych.org/practice/dsm/summary-of-practice-relevant-changes-to-the-dsm-iv-tr |title=Summary of Practice-Relevant Changes to the DSM-IV-TR |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120513233545/http://www.psych.org/practice/dsm/summary-of-practice-relevant-changes-to-the-dsm-iv-tr |archive-date=13 May 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The text sections giving extra information on each diagnosis were updated, as were some of the diagnostic codes to maintain consistency with the ICD. The DSM-IV-TR was organized into a five-part axial system. The first axis incorporated clinical disorders. The second axis covered [[personality disorders]] and [[intellectual disabilities]]. The remaining axes covered medical, psychosocial, environmental, and childhood factors functionally necessary to provide diagnostic criteria for health care assessments.

The DSM-IV-TR characterizes a mental disorder as &quot;a clinically significant behavioral or psychological syndrome or pattern that occurs in an individual [which] is associated with present distress ... or disability ... or with a significant increased risk of suffering.&quot; It also notes &quot;no definition adequately specifies precise boundaries for the concept of 'mental disorder' ... different situations call for different definitions&quot;. It states &quot;there is no assumption that each category of mental disorder is a completely discrete entity with absolute boundaries dividing it from other mental disorders or from no mental disorder&quot; (APA, 1994 and 2000).

====DSM-IV-TR Categorization====

The DSM-IV is a categorical classification system. The categories are prototypes, and a patient with a close approximation to the prototype is said to have that disorder. DSM-IV states, &quot;there is no assumption each category of mental disorder is a completely discrete entity with absolute boundaries&quot; but isolated, low-grade and non-criterion (unlisted for a given disorder) symptoms are not given importance.&lt;ref&gt;Maser, JD. &amp; Patterson, T. (2002) [https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?db=pubmed&amp;cmd=Retrieve&amp;dopt=AbstractPlus&amp;list_uids=12462864 Spectrum and nosology: implications for DSM-5] ''Psychiatric Clinics of North America'', December, 25(4)p855-885&lt;/ref&gt; Qualifiers are sometimes used, for example mild, moderate or severe forms of a disorder. For nearly half the disorders, symptoms must be sufficient to cause &quot;clinically significant distress or impairment in social, occupational, or other important areas of functioning&quot;, although DSM-IV-TR removed the distress criterion from [[tic disorder]]s and several of the [[paraphilia]]s due to their [[egosyntonic]] nature. Each category of disorder has a numeric code taken from the [[ICD coding system]], used for health service (including insurance) administrative purposes.

====DSM-IV-TR Multi-axial system{{anchor|Multi-axial system}}====

With the advent of the DSM-5 in 2013, the APA eliminated the longstanding multiaxial system for mental disorders.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|date=July 2014|title=The Removal of the Multiaxial System in the DSM-5: Implications and Practice Suggestions for Counselors|url=http://tpcjournal.nbcc.org/the-removal-of-the-multiaxial-system-in-the-dsm-5-implications-and-practice-suggestions-for-counselors/|journal=The Professional Counselor Journal|volume=4|issue=3|pages=191–201|last1=Kress|first1=Victoria|doi=10.15241/vek.4.3.191}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Previously, the DSM-IV organized each psychiatric diagnosis into five dimensions (axes) relating to different aspects of disorder or disability:
* '''''Axis I''':'' All psychological diagnostic categories except mental retardation and personality disorder
* '''''Axis II''':'' [[Personality disorders]] and mental retardation (more appropriately termed &quot;intellectual disability&quot;)
* '''''Axis III''':'' General medical condition; acute medical conditions and physical disorders
* '''''Axis IV''':'' Psychosocial and environmental factors contributing to the disorder
* '''''Axis V''':'' [[Global Assessment of Functioning]] or Child Global Assessment of Functioning [cGAF]  
Mental/Psychiatric/Behavioral/Learning conditions include, but are not limited to: [[Clinical depression|depression]], [[anxiety disorders]], [[bipolar disorder]], [[Attention-deficit hyperactivity disorder|ADHD]], [[autism spectrum disorders]], [[anorexia nervosa]], [[bulimia nervosa]], and [[schizophrenia]].

'''Personality Disorders include, but are not limited to''': [[paranoid personality disorder]], [[schizoid personality disorder]], [[schizotypal personality disorder]], [[borderline personality disorder]], [[antisocial personality disorder]], [[narcissistic personality disorder]], [[histrionic personality disorder]], [[avoidant personality disorder]], [[dependent personality disorder]], [[obsessive-compulsive personality disorder]]; and organic intellectual disabilities.

'''Common medical/physical conditions or diseases''' that may result in and/or exacerbate some of the aforementioned mental/psychiatric conditions OR that may be aggravated by the aforementioned mental/psychiatric conditions include, but are not limited to: brain injuries, terminal diseases, pregnancy, cancer, epilepsy, idiopathic physiological conditions and virtually any other conditions, ailments and/or injuries which may affect the patient's mental health.. Many Biopsychosocial Assessments incorporate multiple factors that adversely affect the patient's, client's and/or subject's overall well-being and homeostasis.

Typical psychosocial influences that are usually listed as having negative impact on life, mentality and health include, but are not limited to: Environmental factors of dysfunction such as those experienced within home, school and work; Social factors such as issues with drug use (not diagnosed), enabling friends and conflicts with coworkers; Family complications such as divorce, social service involvement and court ordered placements; Various stressors such as recent accident, natural disaster and other traumatic occurrences (i.e. assault, death, abuse); Financial problems such as bankruptcy, job loss and debts; and service needs such as lack of medical insurance, inability to find adequate treatment and inaccessibility to necessary state and federal programs.

====Sourcebooks====

The DSM-IV does not specifically cite its sources, but there are four volumes of &quot;sourcebooks&quot; intended to be APA's documentation of the guideline development process and supporting evidence, including literature reviews, data analyses and field trials.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=DSM-IV Sourcebook|date=1994|publisher=American Psychiatric Association|isbn=978-0-89042-065-2|volume=1|location=Washington, DC|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/dsmivsourcebook0000unse}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=DSM-IV Sourcebook|date=1996|publisher=American Psychiatric Association|isbn=978-0-89042-069-0|volume=2|location=Washington, DC|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/dsmivsourcebook0000unse}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=DSM-IV Sourcebook|date=1997|publisher=American Psychiatric Association|isbn=978-0-89042-073-7|volume=3|location=Washington, DC|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/dsmivsourcebook0000unse}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|date=October 1999|title=DSM-IV Sourcebook, vol. 4 (Book Forum: Assessment and Diagnosis)|url=http://ajp.psychiatryonline.org/article.aspx?articleid=173760|journal=American Journal of Psychiatry|volume=156|issue=10|page=1655|doi=10.1176/ajp.156.10.1655|last1=Sadock|first1=Benjamin J.|accessdate=2013-12-03|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131206233357/http://ajp.psychiatryonline.org/article.aspx?articleid=173760|archivedate=2013-12-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Sourcebooks have been said to provide important insights into the character and quality of the decisions that led to the production of DSM-IV, and hence the scientific credibility of contemporary psychiatric classification.&lt;ref name=&quot;Poland01vol1&quot;&gt;Poland, JS. (2001) [http://mentalhelp.net/books/books.php?type=de&amp;id=557 Review of Volume 1 of DSM-IV sourcebook] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20050501182254/http://mentalhelp.net/books/books.php?type=de&amp;id=557|date=May 1, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Poland01vol2&quot;&gt;Poland, JS. (2001) [http://mentalhelp.net/poc/view_doc.php?id=996&amp;type=book&amp;cn=74 Review of vol 2 of DSM-IV sourcebook] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070927005022/http://mentalhelp.net/poc/view_doc.php?id=996&amp;type=book&amp;cn=74|date=September 27, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===DSM-5 (2013)===
{{Main|DSM-5}}
The fifth edition of the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM), the DSM-5, was approved by the Board of Trustees of the APA on December 1, 2012.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |first=Caroline |last=Cassels |date=2 December 2012 |url=http://www.medscape.com/viewarticle/775496 |title=DSM-5 Gets APA's Official Stamp of Approval |publisher=WebMD, LLC |website=Medscape |accessdate=2012-12-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; Published on May 18, 2013,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Explainer: what is the DSM?|url=http://theconversation.com/explainer-what-is-the-dsm-14127|work=The Conversation Australia|publisher=The Conversation Media Group|accessdate=2013-05-21|first=Peter |last=Kinderman|date=20 May 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; the DSM-5 contains extensively revised diagnoses and, in some cases, broadens diagnostic definitions while narrowing definitions in other cases.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Books blast new version of psychiatry's bible, the DSM|url=https://www.usatoday.com/story/news/nation/2013/05/12/dsm-psychiatry-mental-disorders/2150819/|accessdate=2013-05-21|newspaper=USA Today|date=12 May 2013|author=Sharon Jayson}}&lt;/ref&gt; The DSM-5 is the first major edition of the manual in twenty years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=DSM-5 Changes: What Parents Need To Know About The First Major Revision In Nearly 20 Years|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2013/05/20/dsm5-changes-what-parents-need-to-know_n_3294413.html|accessdate=2013-05-21|newspaper=The Huffington Post|date=20 May 2013|author=Catherine Pearson}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A significant change in the fifth edition is the deletion of the subtypes of [[schizophrenia]] ([[paranoid schizophrenia|paranoid]], [[disorganized schizophrenia|disorganized]], [[catatonic schizophrenia|catatonic]], [[undifferentiated schizophrenia|undifferentiated]] and [[residual schizophrenia|residual]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Highlights of Changes from DSM-IV-TR to DSM-5 |website=American Psychiatric Association |date=17 May 2013 |url=http://www.psychiatry.org/File%20Library/Practice/DSM/DSM-5/Changes-from-DSM-IV-TR--to-DSM-5.pdf |accessdate=2015-01-04 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150226050453/http://www.psychiatry.org/File%20Library/Practice/DSM/DSM-5/Changes-from-DSM-IV-TR--to-DSM-5.pdf |archivedate=2015-02-26 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The deletion of the subsets of [[Autism spectrum|autistic spectrum disorder]] (namely, [[Asperger's syndrome]], [[classic autism]], [[Rett syndrome]], [[childhood disintegrative disorder]] and [[pervasive developmental disorder not otherwise specified]]) was also implemented, with specifiers with regard to intensity (mild, moderate and severe). Severity is based on social communication impairments and restricted, repetitive patterns of behaviour, with three levels: 1 (requiring support), 2 (requiring substantial support) and 3 (requiring very substantial support).

During the revision process, the APA website periodically listed several sections of the DSM-5 for review and discussion.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.psychiatry.org/psychiatrists/practice/dsm|title=DSM-5|website=psychiatry.org|access-date=2019-08-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Future revisions and updates===
Beginning with the fifth edition, it is intended that diagnostic guidelines revisions will be added more often to keep up with research in the field.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.psychiatry.org/psychiatrists/practice/dsm/feedback-and-questions/frequently-asked-questions|title=DSM-5 FAQ|website=psychiatry.org|access-date=2019-08-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is notable the DSM-5 is identified with [[Hindu–Arabic numeral system|Arabic]] rather than [[Roman numerals]]. Beginning with DSM-5, the American Psychiatric Association will use decimals to identify incremental updates (e.g., DSM-5.1, DSM-5.2) and whole numbers for new editions (e.g., DSM-5, DSM-6),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release |last1=Harold |first1=Eve |last2=Valora |first2=Jamie |title=APA Modifies ''DSM'' Naming Convention to Reflect Publication Changes |location=Arlington, VA |publisher=American Psychiatric Association |date=9 March 2010 |url=http://psych.org/MainMenu/Newsroom/NewsReleases/2010-News-Releases/DSM-Name-Change.aspx |format=PDF |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100613144808/http://psych.org/MainMenu/Newsroom/NewsReleases/2010-News-Releases/DSM-Name-Change.aspx |archive-date=13 June 2010 |quote=Beginning with the upcoming fifth edition, new versions of the ''Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM)'' will be identified with Arabic rather than Roman numerals, marking a change in how future updates will be created, ... Incremental updates will be identified with decimals, i.e. ''DSM-5.1'', ''DSM-5.2'', etc., until a new edition is required.}}&lt;/ref&gt; similar to the scheme used for [[software versioning]].

== Criticisms ==
===Overall===
Allsopp et al (2019) describe as scientifically meaningless the entire construct of psychiatric diagnoses because of its unsupportable premise of mental distresses being ''caused'' by whatever (putative) disorder(s) being set in contrast to hypothesized-yet-subjective notions about what should be thought normal.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Allsopp |first1=Kate |last2=Read |first2=John |last3=Corcoran |first3=Rhiannon |last4=Kinderman |first4=Peter |title=Heterogeneity in psychiatric diagnostic classification |journal=Psychiatry Research |date=September 2019 |volume=279 |pages=15–22 |doi=10.1016/j.psychres.2019.07.005 |pmid=31279246 |lay-url=https://www.studyfinds.org/study-psychiatric-diagnoses-are-scientifically-meaningless/ |laysource=StudyFinds.org |laydate=July 9, 2019 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Reliability and validity concerns===
The revisions of the DSM from the 3rd Edition forward have been mainly concerned with [[Inter-rater reliability|diagnostic reliability]]—the degree to which different diagnosticians agree on a diagnosis. {Henrik Walter} argued that a science of psychiatry can only advance if diagnosis is reliable. If clinicians and researchers frequently disagree about the diagnosis of a patient, then research into the causes and effective treatments of those disorders cannot advance. Hence, diagnostic reliability was a major concern of DSM-III.{{citation needed|date=November 2014}} When the diagnostic reliability problem was thought to be solved, subsequent editions of the DSM were concerned mainly with &quot;tweaking&quot; the diagnostic criteria.{{citation needed|date=November 2014}} Unfortunately, neither the issue of reliability or validity was settled.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |first1=S. Nassir |last1=Ghaemi |first2=James L., IV |last2=Knoll |first3=Theodore |last3=Pearlman |date=14 October 2013 |title=Why DSM-III, IV, and 5 are Unscientific |website=Psychiatric Times: Couch in Crisis Blog |url=http://www.psychiatrictimes.com/blogs/couch-crisis/why-dsm-iii-iv-and-5-are-unscientific }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Better source|reason=Source is a blog post|date=August 2016}}

In 2013, shortly before the publication of DSM-5, the Director of the [[National Institute of Mental Health]] (NIMH), [[Thomas R. Insel]],  declared that the agency would no longer fund research projects that rely exclusively on DSM diagnostic criteria due to its lack of validity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Insel|first=Thomas |date=29 April 2013 |title=Transforming Diagnosis |url=http://www.nimh.nih.gov/about/director/2013/transforming-diagnosis.shtml|website=Director's Blog |publisher=National Institute of Mental Health|accessdate=2013-09-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; Insel questioned the validity of the DSM classification scheme because &quot;... diagnoses are based on a consensus about clusters of clinical symptoms ....&quot; as opposed to &quot;... collecting the genetic, imaging, physiologic, and cognitive data to see how all the data – not just the symptoms – cluster and how these clusters relate to treatment response.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.nimh.nih.gov/about/directors/thomas-insel/blog/2013/transforming-diagnosis.shtml|title=NIMH » Transforming Diagnosis|website=nimh.nih.gov|language=en|access-date=2019-02-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine|last=Lane|first=Christopher|title=The NIMH Withdraws Support for DSM-5|url=http://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/side-effects/201305/the-nimh-withdraws-support-dsm-5|magazine=Psychology Today}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Field trials of DSM-5 brought the debate of reliability back into the limelight as some disorders showed poor reliability. For example, [[major depressive disorder]], a common mental illness, had a poor reliability [[Cohen's kappa|kappa]] statistic of 0.28, indicating that clinicians frequently disagreed on this diagnosis in the same patients. The most reliable diagnosis was major neurocognitive disorder with a kappa of 0.78.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Freedman |first1=Robert |last2=Lewis |first2=David A. |last3=Michels |first3=Robert |last4=Pine |first4=Daniel S. |last5=Schultz |first5=Susan K. |last6=Tamminga |first6=Carol A. |last7=Gabbard |first7=Glen O. |last8=[[Susan Shur-Fen|Gau]] |first8=[[Susan Shur-Fen]] |last9=Javitt |first9=Daniel C. |last10=Oquendo |first10=Maria A. |last11=Shrout |first11=Patrick E. |last12=Vieta |first12=Eduard |last13=Yager |first13=Joel |date=January 2013 |title=The Initial Field Trials of DSM-5: New Blooms and Old Thorns |journal=American Journal of Psychiatry |volume=170 |issue=1 |pages=1–5 |doi=10.1176/appi.ajp.2012.12091189 |url=http://ajp.psychiatryonline.org/article.aspx?articleid=1555604 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130115024502/http://ajp.psychiatryonline.org/article.aspx?articleID=1555604 |url-status=dead |archive-date=2013-01-15 |pmid=23288382 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Superficial symptoms===
By design, the DSM is primarily concerned with the signs and symptoms of mental disorders, rather than the underlying causes. It claims to collect them together based on statistical or clinical patterns. As such, it has been compared to a naturalist's field guide to birds, with similar advantages and disadvantages.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = McHugh Paul R | year = 2005 | title = Striving for Coherence: Psychiatry's Efforts Over Classification | journal = JAMA | volume = 293 | issue = 20| pages = 2526–2528 | doi=10.1001/jama.293.20.2526 | pmid=15914753}}&lt;/ref&gt; The lack of a causative or explanatory basis, however, is not specific to the DSM, but rather reflects a general lack of pathophysiological understanding of psychiatric disorders. As [[DSM-III]] chief architect [[Robert Spitzer (psychiatrist)|Robert Spitzer]] and [[DSM-IV]] editor Michael First outlined in 2005, &quot;little progress has been made toward understanding the [[pathophysiology|pathophysiological]] processes and cause of mental disorders. If anything, the research has shown the situation is even more complex than initially imagined, and we believe not enough is known to structure the classification of psychiatric disorders according to etiology.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Spitzer, First  | year = 2005 | title = Classification of Psychiatric Disorders | url = http://jama.ama-assn.org/cgi/content/full/294/15/1898 | journal = JAMA | volume = 294 | issue = 15| pages = 1898–1899 | doi=10.1001/jama.294.15.1898| pmc = 1801862 | pmid=20313414}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&quot;The DSM's focus on superficial symptoms is claimed to be largely a result of necessity (assuming such a manual is nevertheless produced), since there is no agreement on a more explanatory classification system. Reviewers note, however, that this approach is undermining research, including in genetics, because it results in the grouping of individuals who have very little in common except superficial criteria as per DSM or ICD diagnosis (Fadul, 2014, p.143).&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;concept&amp;evolution&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Fadul. J. A. (2014) Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders. In ''Encyclopedia of Theory &amp; Practice in Psychopathology &amp; Counseling.'' (p.143). Raleigh, NC: Lulu Press.&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite the lack of consensus on underlying causation, advocates for specific [[psychopathology|psychopathological]] paradigms have nonetheless faulted the current diagnostic scheme for not incorporating evidence-based models or findings from other areas of science. A recent example is [[evolutionary psychology|evolutionary psychologists]]' criticism that the DSM does not differentiate between genuine cognitive malfunctions and those induced by psychological [[adaptations]], a key distinction within evolutionary psychology but one that is widely challenged within general psychology.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |first1=Dominic |last1=Murphy |first2=Stephen |last2=Stich |date=16 December 1998 |url=http://ruccs.rutgers.edu/ArchiveFolder/Research%20Group/Publications/Mad/Madhouse.html |title=Darwin in the Madhouse: Evolutionary Psychology and the Classification of Mental Disorders |accessdate=2013-12-03 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131205122638/http://ruccs.rutgers.edu/ArchiveFolder/Research%20Group/Publications/Mad/Madhouse.html |archive-date=5 December 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author1=Leda Cosmides |author2=John Tooby | year = 1999 | title = Toward an Evolutionary Taxonomy of Treatable Conditions | url = http://www.psych.ucsb.edu/research/cep/papers/taxonomywakefield99.pdf | journal = Journal of Abnormal Psychology | volume = 108 | issue = 3| pages = 453–464 | doi=10.1037/0021-843x.108.3.453 | pmid=10466269}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | pmid = 11227812  | volume=39 | issue=3 |date=March 2001 | pages=309–14 | last1 = McNally | first1 = RJ | title = On Wakefield's harmful dysfunction analysis of mental disorder | journal = Behaviour Research and Therapy | doi = 10.1016/S0005-7967(00)00068-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another example is the strong [[Operationalization|operationalist]] viewpoint, which contends that reliance on [[operational definition]]s, as purported by the DSM, necessitates that intuitive concepts like [[Depression (mood)|depression]] be replaced by specific measurable concepts before they are scientifically meaningful. One critic states of [[psychologists]] that &quot;Instead of replacing 'metaphysical' terms such as 'desire' and 'purpose', they used it to legitimize them by giving them operational definitions ... the initial, quite radical operationalist ideas eventually came to serve as little more than a 'reassurance fetish' (Koch 1992) for mainstream methodological practice.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first=D. Wade |last=Hands |date=December 2004 |title=On Operationalisms and Economics |journal=Journal of Economic Issues |volume=38 |issue=4 |pages=953–968 |doi=10.1080/00213624.2004.11506751 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2013 review published in the ''[[European Archives of Psychiatry and Clinical Neuroscience]]'' states &quot;that psychiatry targets the [[phenomenology (psychology)|phenomena]] of [[consciousness]], which, unlike [[somatic symptom disorder|somatic]] [[symptom]]s and [[medical sign|signs]], cannot be grasped on the analogy with material thing-like objects.&quot; As an example of the problem of the superficial characterization of psychiatric signs and symptoms, the authors gave the example of a [[patient]] saying they &quot;feel depressed, sad, or down&quot;, showing that such a statement could indicate various underlying experiences: &quot;not only [[depression (mood)|depressed mood]] but also, for instance, [[irritability|irritation]], [[anger]], loss of meaning, varieties of [[fatigue (medical)|fatigue]], [[ambivalence]], [[rumination (psychology)|ruminations]] of different kinds, hyper-reflectivity, thought pressure, psychological [[anxiety]], varieties of [[depersonalization]], and even [[auditory hallucination|voices]] with negative content, and so forth.&quot; The [[structured interview]] comes with &quot;danger of over confidence in the face value of the answers, as if a simple 'yes' or 'no' truly confirmed or denied the [[diagnostic criteria|diagnostic criterion]] at issue.&quot; The authors gave an example: A [[patient]] who was being administered the [[Structured Clinical Interview for DSM-IV|Structured Clinical Interview for the DSM-IV Axis I Disorders]] denied [[thought insertion]], but during a &quot;conversational, [[phenomenology (psychology)|phenomenological]] interview&quot;, a [[semi-structured interview]] tailored to the patient, the same [[patient]] admitted to experiencing [[thought insertion]], along with a [[delusion|delusional elaboration]]. The authors suggested 2 reasons for this discrepancy: either the patient did not &quot;recognize his own [[qualia|experience]] in the rather blunt, implicitly either/or formulation of the structured-interview question&quot;, or the [[qualia|experience]] did not &quot;fully articulate itself&quot; until the patient started talking about his experiences.&lt;ref name = nordgaard1&gt;{{Cite journal | title = The psychiatric interview: validity, structure, and subjectivity | journal = [[European Archives of Psychiatry and Clinical Neuroscience]] | volume = 263 | issue = 4 | pages = 353–364 |date=June 2013 | doi = 10.1007/s00406-012-0366-z | pmid = 23001456|author1 = Julie Nordgaard|author2 = Louis A. Sass| authorlink1 = Julie Nordgaard | authorlink2 = Louis Sass | pmc=3668119}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Overdiagnosis ===
Dr. Allen Frances being an outspoken critic of the DSM-5 states that &quot;normality is an endangered species,&quot; for the reason of &quot;fad diagnoses&quot; and an &quot;epidemic&quot; of over-diagnosing, and suggests that the &quot;DSM-5 threatens to provoke several more [epidemics].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://psychcentral.com/blog/overdiagnosis-mental-disorders-and-the-dsm-5/|title=Overdiagnosis, Mental Disorders and the DSM-5|date=2010-07-26|work=World of Psychology|access-date=2018-09-18|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/dsm5-in-distress/201006/psychiatric-fads-and-overdiagnosis|title=Psychiatric Fads and Overdiagnosis|website=Psychology Today|language=en-US|access-date=2018-09-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some researchers state that changes in diagnostic criteria reduce thresholds for a diagnosis, which results in increases in prevalence rates following each published version of the DSM for ADHD&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Thomas |first1=R. |last2=Mitchell |first2=G. K. |last3=Batstra |first3=L. |title=Attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder: are we helping or harming? |journal=BMJ |date=5 November 2013 |volume=347 |issue=nov05 1 |pages=f6172 |doi=10.1136/bmj.f6172 |pmid=24192646 |url=http://www.bmj.com/cgi/content/short/348/jul01_1/g4377 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;bruchmuller 2012&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Bruchmüller |first=Katrin |last2=Margraf |first2=Jürgen |last3=Schneider |first3=Silvia |date=February 2012 |title=Is ADHD diagnosed in accord with diagnostic criteria? Overdiagnosis and influence of client gender on diagnosis |journal=Journal of Consulting and Clinical Psychology |language=en |volume=80 |issue=1 |pages=128–138 |doi=10.1037/a0026582 |pmid=22201328}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Vande Voort |first1=Jennifer L. |last2=He |first2=Jian-Ping |last3=Jameson |first3=Nicole D. |last4=Merikangas |first4=Kathleen R. |title=Impact of the DSM-5 Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder Age-of-Onset Criterion in the U.S. Adolescent Population |journal=Journal of the American Academy of Child &amp; Adolescent Psychiatry |date=July 2014 |volume=53 |issue=7 |pages=736–744 |doi=10.1016/j.jaac.2014.03.005 |pmid=24954823 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Autism spectrum|autism spectrum disorder]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Wing |first1=Lorna |last2=Potter |first2=David |title=The epidemiology of autistic spectrum disorders: is the prevalence rising? |journal=Mental Retardation and Developmental Disabilities Research Reviews |date=2002 |volume=8 |issue=3 |pages=151–161 |doi=10.1002/mrdd.10029 |pmid=12216059 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Bruchmüller suggests that as a factor that may lead to overdiagnosis can be also situations when the diagnostician's clinical judgment regarding a diagnose (ADHD) is affected by heuristics.&lt;ref name=&quot;bruchmuller 2012&quot;/&gt;

===Dividing lines===
Despite caveats in the introduction to the DSM, it has long been argued that its [[Classification of mental disorders|system of classification]] makes unjustified categorical distinctions between disorders and uses arbitrary cut-offs between normal and abnormal. A 2009 psychiatric review noted that attempts to demonstrate natural boundaries between related DSM [[syndromes]], or between a common DSM syndrome and normality, have failed.&lt;ref name=&quot;concept&amp;evolution&quot;/&gt; Some argue that rather than a categorical approach, a fully dimensional, spectrum or complaint-oriented approach would better reflect the evidence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Spitzer |first1=Robert L. |last2=Williams |first2=Janet B.W. |last3=First |first3=Michael B. |last4=Gibbon |first4=Miriam |title=Biometric Research |website= Psychiatric Institute 2001-2002 |publisher=New York State Psychiatric Institute |url=http://nyspi.org/AR2001/Biometrics.htm |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20030307205740/http://nyspi.org/AR2001/Biometrics.htm |archive-date=7 March 2003 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Maser |first1=Jack D. |last2=Akiskal |first2=Hagop S. |title=Spectrum concepts in major mental disorders |journal=Psychiatric Clinics of North America |date=December 2002 |volume=25 |issue=4 |pages=xi–xiii |doi=10.1016/S0193-953X(02)00034-5 |pmid=12462854 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Krueger |first1=Robert F. |last2=Watson |first2=David |last3=Barlow |first3=David H. |title=Introduction to the Special Section: Toward a Dimensionally Based Taxonomy of Psychopathology. |journal=Journal of Abnormal Psychology |date=2005 |volume=114 |issue=4 |pages=491–493 |doi=10.1037/0021-843X.114.4.491 |pmid=16351372 |pmc=2242426 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition, it is argued that the current approach based on exceeding a threshold of symptoms does not adequately take into account the context in which a person is living, and to what extent there is internal disorder of an individual versus a psychological response to adverse situations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Wakefield |first1=Jerome C. |last2=Schmitz |first2=Mark F. |last3=First |first3=Michael B. |last4=Horwitz |first4=Allan V. |title=Extending the Bereavement Exclusion for Major Depression to Other Losses |journal=Archives of General Psychiatry |date=1 April 2007 |volume=64 |issue=4 |pages=433–40 |doi=10.1001/archpsyc.64.4.433 |pmid=17404120 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The DSM does include a step (&quot;Axis IV&quot;) for outlining &quot;Psychosocial and environmental factors contributing to the disorder&quot; once someone is diagnosed with that particular disorder.

Because an individual's degree of impairment is often not correlated with symptom counts and can stem from various individual and social factors, the DSM's standard of distress or disability can often produce false positives.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Spitzer |first1=Robert L. |last2=Wakefield |first2=Jerome C. |title=DSM-IV Diagnostic Criterion for Clinical Significance: Does It Help Solve the False Positives Problem? |journal=American Journal of Psychiatry |date=1 December 1999 |volume=156 |issue=12 |pages=1856–1864 |doi=10.1176/ajp.156.12.1856 |url=https://ajp.psychiatryonline.org/doi/full/10.1176/ajp.156.12.1856 |pmid=10588397 |doi-broken-date=2019-12-07 }}&lt;/ref&gt; On the other hand, individuals who do not meet symptom counts may nevertheless experience comparable distress or disability in their life.

===Cultural bias===
Psychiatrists have argued that published diagnostic standards relied on an exaggerated interpretation of neurophysiological findings and so understate the scientific importance of social-psychological variables.&lt;ref name=Widiger2000/&gt; Advocating a more culturally sensitive approach to psychology, critics such as [[Carl Bell (physician)|Carl Bell]] and Marcello Maviglia contend that researchers and service-providers often discount the cultural and ethnic diversity of individuals.&lt;ref name=&quot;wash-post&quot;&gt;{{cite news | last= Vedantam |first= Shankar |date= June 26, 2005 |title = Psychiatry's Missing Diagnosis: Patients' Diversity Is Often Discounted |url= https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2005/06/25/AR2005062500982.html |newspaper= [[The Washington Post]] |location= |access-date= }}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, current diagnostic guidelines have been criticized{{by whom|date=October 2018}} as having a fundamentally Euro-American outlook. Although these guidelines have been widely implemented, opponents argue that even when a diagnostic criterion-set is accepted across different cultures, it does not necessarily indicate that the underlying constructs have any validity within those cultures; even reliable application can only demonstrate consistency, not legitimacy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Widiger2000&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors= Widiger TA, Sankis LM |title= Adult psychopathology: issues and controversies |journal= Annu Rev Psychol |volume= 51 |issue= 1|pages= 377–404 |year= 2000 |pmid= 10751976 |doi= 10.1146/annurev.psych.51.1.377 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Cross-cultural psychiatry|Cross-cultural]] psychiatrist [[Arthur Kleinman]] contends that the Western bias is ironically illustrated in the introduction of cultural factors to the DSM-IV: the fact that disorders or concepts from non-Western or non-mainstream cultures are described as &quot;culture-bound&quot;, whereas standard psychiatric diagnoses are given no cultural qualification whatsoever, is to Kleinman revelatory of an underlying assumption that Western cultural phenomena are universal.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author= Kleinman A |title= Triumph or pyrrhic victory? The inclusion of culture in DSM-IV |journal= Harv Rev Psychiatry |volume= 4 |issue= 6 |pages= 343–4 |year= 1997 |pmid= 9385013 |doi= 10.3109/10673229709030563 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Other cross-cultural critics largely share Kleinman's negative view toward the [[culture-bound syndrome]], common responses included both disappointment over the large number of documented non-Western mental disorders still left out, and frustration that even those included were often misinterpreted or misrepresented.&lt;ref&gt;Bhugra, D. &amp; Munro, A. (1997) ''Troublesome Disguises: Underdiagnosed Psychiatric Syndromes'' Blackwell Science Ltd {{ISBN missing|date=August 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Page needed|date= August 2016}}

Mainstream psychiatrists have also been dissatisfied with these new culture-bound diagnoses, although not for the same reasons. Robert Spitzer, a lead architect of the DSM-III, has held the opinion that the addition of cultural formulations was an attempt to placate cultural critics, and that they lack any scientific motivation or support. Spitzer also posits that the new culture-bound diagnoses are rarely used in practice, maintaining that the standard diagnoses apply regardless of the culture involved. In general, the mainstream psychiatric opinion remains that if a diagnostic category is valid, cross-cultural factors are either irrelevant or are only significant to specific symptom presentations.&lt;ref name=&quot;Widiger2000&quot; /&gt; One of the results was the development of the Azibo Nosology by Daudi Ajani Ya Azibo as an alternative to the DSM to treat [[African diaspora]] patients.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author1= Atwell Irene |author2= Azibo Daudi A | year = 1991 | title = Diagnosing personality disorder in Africans (Blacks) using the Azibo nosology: Two case studies | url = http://psycnet.apa.org/index.cfm?fa=search.displayRecord&amp;UID=1992-13008-001 | journal = Journal of Black Psychology | volume = 17 | issue = 2| pages = 1–22 | doi= 10.1177/00957984910172002}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last= Azibo |first= Daudi Ajani ya |date= November 2014 |title= The Azibo Nosology II: Epexegesis and 25th Anniversary Update: 55 Culture-focused Mental Disorders Suffered by African Descent People |journal= Journal of Pan African Studies |volume= 7 |issue= 5 |pages= 32–176 |url= http://www.jpanafrican.org/docs/vol7no5/4-Nov-Azibo-Noso.pdf }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last= Zulu |first= Itibari M. |title= The Azibo Nosology: An Interview with Daudi Ajani ya Azibo |journal= Journal of Pan African Studies |volume= 7 |issue =5 |pages= 209–214 |url= http://www.jpanafrican.org/docs/vol7no5/12-Nov-Azibo-Zulu.pdf }}
&lt;/ref&gt;

Historically, the DSM tended to avoid issues involving [[religion]]; the DSM-5 relaxed this attitude somewhat.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal
| last1                 = Chandler
| first1                = Emily
| title                 = Religious and Spiritual Issues in DSM-5: Matters of the Mind and Searching of the Soul
| journal               = Issues in Mental Health Nursing
| date      = 2012
| volume                = 33
| issue                 = 9
| pages                 = 577–582
| doi                   = 10.3109/01612840.2012.704130
| pmid                = 22957950
| quote                 = Given the important role that spirituality and religion play for many people in the experiences of coping with health and illness, it seems odd that such important elements are in the margins of the powerful and commanding nosology of the DSM. Explanations for understanding the glaring absence are complex and impacted by some very powerful political and sociological forces, including contributory elements from within the mental health disciplines. This article invites the reader to explore salient issues in the emergence of a broader recognition of religion, spirituality and psychiatric diagnosis in the DSM-5.
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

===Medicalization and financial conflicts of interest===

There was extensive analysis and comment on DSM-IV (published in 1994) in the years leading up to the 2013 publication of DSM-5.  It was alleged that the way the categories of DSM-IV were structured, as well as the substantial expansion of the number of categories within it, represented increasing [[medicalization]] of human nature, very possibly attributable to [[disease mongering]] by psychiatrists and [[pharmaceutical companies]], the power and influence of the latter having grown dramatically in recent decades.&lt;ref&gt;Healy D (2006) [http://medicine.plosjournals.org/perlserv/?request=get-document&amp;doi=10.1371/journal.pmed.0030185&amp;ct=1 The Latest Mania: Selling Bipolar Disorder] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090212110644/http://medicine.plosjournals.org/perlserv/?request=get-document&amp;doi=10.1371%2Fjournal.pmed.0030185&amp;ct=1 |date=2009-02-12 }} PLoS Med 3(4): e185.&lt;/ref&gt;  In 2005, then APA President [[Steven Sharfstein]] released a statement in which he conceded that psychiatrists had &quot;allowed the biopsychosocial model to become the bio-bio-bio model&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Cosgrove |first1=Lisa |last2=Krimsky |first2=Sheldon |last3=Vijayaraghavan |first3=Manisha |last4=Schneider |first4=Lisa |title=Financial Ties between DSM-IV Panel Members and the Pharmaceutical Industry |journal=Psychotherapy and Psychosomatics |date=2006 |volume=75 |issue=3 |pages=154–160 |doi=10.1159/000091772 |pmid=16636630 }}&lt;/ref&gt; reported that of the authors who selected and defined the DSM-IV psychiatric disorders, roughly half had financial relationships with the pharmaceutical industry during the period 1989-2004, raising the prospect of a direct [[Conflict of interest#Relationship to medical research|conflict of interest]].  The same article concluded that the connections between panel members and the drug companies were particularly strong in those diagnoses where drugs are the first line of treatment, such as schizophrenia and mood disorders, where 100% of the panel members had financial ties with the pharmaceutical industry.

[[William Glasser]] referred to DSM-IV as &quot;phony diagnostic categories&quot;, arguing that &quot;it was developed to help psychiatrists – to help them make money&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://nationalpsychologist.com/2006/11/glasser-headlines-psychotherapy-conference/10879.html |title=(Susan Bowman, 2006) |publisher=The National Psychologist |date=2006-11-01 |accessdate=2013-12-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;  A 2012 article in [[The New York Times]] commented sharply that DSM-IV (then in its 18th year), through copyrights held closely by the APA, had earned the Association over $100&amp;nbsp;million.&lt;ref
    name=&quot;Greenberg&quot;&gt;
{{cite news
    | url=     https://www.nytimes.com/2012/01/30/opinion/the-dsms-troubled-revision.html
    | work= The New York Times
    | first=   Gary
    | last=    Greenberg
    | title=   The D.S.M.'s Troubled Revision
    | date=   January 29, 2012
}}  The article’s closing words: “it [the APA] will be laughing all the way to the bank.”&lt;/ref&gt;

However, although the number of identified diagnoses had increased by more than 300% (from 106 in DSM-I to 365 in DSM-IV-TR), psychiatrists such as Zimmerman and Spitzer argued that this almost entirely represented greater specification of the forms of pathology, thereby allowing better grouping of more similar patients.&lt;ref name=&quot;concept&amp;evolution&quot;/&gt;

===Clients, survivors, and consumer===
A client is a person who accesses psychiatric services and may have been given a diagnosis from the DSM, while a survivor self-identifies as a person who has endured a psychiatric intervention and the mental health system (which may have involved [[involuntary commitment]] and [[involuntary treatment]]).{{citation needed|date=February 2014}} A term adopted by many users of psychiatric services is &quot;consumer.&quot; This term was chosen to eliminate the &quot;patient&quot; label and restore the person to an active role as a user or consumer of services.&lt;ref&gt;Halpern, L, Trachtman, H. and Duckworth, K. &quot;From Within: A Consumer Perspective on Psychiatric Hospitals,&quot; in  Textbook of Hospital Psychiatry, S. Sharfstein, F. Dickerson and J. Oldham eds. American Psychiatric Publishing, 2009, pp.237-244.&lt;/ref&gt; Some individuals are relieved to find that they have a recognized condition that they can apply a name to and this has led to many people [[Self-diagnosis|self-diagnosing]].{{citation needed|date=February 2014}} Others, however, question the accuracy of the diagnosis, or feel they have been given a &quot;[[Labeling theory|label]]&quot; that invites [[social stigma]] and [[discrimination]] (the terms &quot;[[mentalism (discrimination)|mentalism]]&quot; and &quot;sanism&quot; have been used to describe such discriminatory treatment).&lt;ref name=&quot;Sane&quot;&gt;[http://www.socialinequities.ca/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2011/07/Ingram.Sanism-in-Theory-and-Practice.CI_.2011.pdf Sanism in Theory and Practice] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140317045503/http://www.socialinequities.ca/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2011/07/Ingram.Sanism-in-Theory-and-Practice.CI_.2011.pdf |date=2014-03-17 }} May 9/10, 2011. Richard Ingram, Centre for the Study of Gender, Social Inequities and Mental Health. [[Simon Fraser University]], Canada&lt;/ref&gt;

Diagnoses can become [[internalized]] and affect an individual's [[self-identity]], and some psychotherapists have found that the healing process can be inhibited and symptoms can worsen as a result.&lt;ref&gt;[http://jhp.sagepub.com/cgi/content/abstract/41/4/36 &quot;How Using the Dsm Causes Damage: A Client's Report&quot;] ''Journal of Humanistic Psychology'', Vol. 41, No. 4, 36-56 (2001)&lt;/ref&gt; Some members of the [[psychiatric survivors movement]] (more broadly the consumer/survivor/ex-patient movement) actively campaign against their diagnoses, or the assumed implications, and/or against the DSM system in general.&lt;ref name=&quot;CapeTown&quot;&gt;{{cite web
    | url=https://madpridect.wordpress.com/2013/06/08/known-as-the-psychiatric-bible-the-diagnostic-and-statistical-manual-of-mental-disorders-appears-in-a-fifth-edition/
    | title=Known as the 'psychiatric bible', the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders appears in a fifth edition
    | author=Cape Town Mad Pride
    | authorlink=Mad Pride
    | access-date=28 Feb 2019
    | url-status=live
| date=2013-06-08
 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Medscape&quot;&gt;
Michael T. Compton (2007) [http://www.medscape.com/viewarticle/565489_print Recovery: Patients, Families, Communities] Conference Report, Medscape Psychiatry &amp; Mental Health, October 11–14, 2007
&lt;/ref&gt;  Additionally, it has been noted that the DSM often uses definitions and terminology that are inconsistent with a [[recovery model]], and such content can erroneously imply excess psychopathology (e.g. multiple &quot;[[comorbid]]&quot; diagnoses) or [[Chronic (medicine)|chronicity]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Medscape&quot;/&gt;

=== DSM-5 critiques ===
{{undue weight section|date=March 2017}}

Psychiatrist [[Allen Frances]] has been critical of proposed revisions to the DSM-5. In a 2012 ''New York Times'' editorial, Frances warned that if this DSM version is issued unamended by the APA, &quot;it will medicalize normality and result in a glut of unnecessary and harmful drug prescription.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;nyt&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Frances |first=Allen |date=11 May 2012 |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2012/05/12/opinion/break-up-the-psychiatric-monopoly.html?_r=1 |title=Diagnosing the D.S.M. |newspaper=New York Times |edition=New York |page=A19 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In a December 2, 2012 blog post in ''[[Psychology Today]]'', Frances provides his &quot;...{{nbsp}}list of DSM 5's ten most potentially harmful changes&quot;:&lt;ref name=dsm5GuideNotBible&gt;{{cite web|last=Frances|first=Allen J.|title=DSM 5 Is Guide Not Bible—Ignore Its Ten Worst Changes: APA approval of DSM-5 is a sad day for psychiatry|url=http://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/dsm5-in-distress/201212/dsm-5-is-guide-not-bible-ignore-its-ten-worst-changes|accessdate=2013-03-09|website=Psychology Today|date=December 2, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Disruptive Mood Dysregulation Disorder, for temper tantrums
* Major Depressive Disorder, includes normal grief
* Minor Neurocognitive Disorder, for normal forgetting in old age
* Adult Attention Deficit Disorder, encouraging psychiatric prescriptions of stimulants
* Binge Eating Disorder, for excessive eating
* Autism, defining the disorder more specifically, possibly leading to decreased rates of diagnosis and the disruption of school services
* First time drug users will be lumped in with addicts
* Behavioral Addictions, making a &quot;...{{nbsp}}mental disorder of everything we like to do a lot.&quot;&lt;ref name=dsm5GuideNotBible/&gt;
* Generalized Anxiety Disorder, includes everyday worries
* Post-traumatic stress disorder, changes &quot;...{{nbsp}}opened the gate even further to the already existing problem of misdiagnosis of PTSD in forensic settings.&quot;&lt;ref name=dsm5GuideNotBible/&gt;

A group of 25 psychiatrists and researchers, among which Frances and [[Thomas Szasz]], have published debates on what they see as the six most essential questions in psychiatric diagnosis:&lt;ref name=&quot;Phillips&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Phillips |first1=James |last2=Frances |first2=Allen |last3=Cerullo |first3=Michael A |last4=Chardavoyne |first4=John |last5=Decker |first5=Hannah S |last6=First |first6=Michael B |last7=Ghaemi |first7=Nassir |last8=Greenberg |first8=Gary |last9=Hinderliter |first9=Andrew C |last10=Kinghorn |first10=Warren A |last11=LoBello |first11=Steven G |last12=Martin |first12=Elliott B |last13=Mishara |first13=Aaron L |last14=Paris |first14=Joel |last15=Pierre |first15=Joseph M |last16=Pies |first16=Ronald W |last17=Pincus |first17=Harold A |last18=Porter |first18=Douglas |last19=Pouncey |first19=Claire |last20=Schwartz |first20=Michael A |last21=Szasz |first21=Thomas |last22=Wakefield |first22=Jerome C |last23=Waterman |first23=G Scott |last24=Whooley |first24=Owen |last25=Zachar |first25=Peter |title=The six most essential questions in psychiatric diagnosis: a pluralogue part 1: conceptual and definitional issues in psychiatric diagnosis |journal=Philosophy, Ethics, and Humanities in Medicine |date=2012 |volume=7 |issue=1 |pages=3 |doi=10.1186/1747-5341-7-3 |pmid=22243994 |pmc=3305603 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Are they more like theoretical constructs or more like diseases?
* How to reach an agreed definition?
* Should the DSM-5 take a cautious or conservative approach?
* What is the role of practical rather than scientific considerations?
* How should it be used by clinicians or researchers?
* Is an entirely different diagnostic system required?

In 2011, psychologist [[Brent Robbins]] co-authored a national letter for the Society for Humanistic Psychology that has brought thousands into the public debate about the DSM. Over 15,000 individuals and [[mental health]] professionals have signed a petition in support of the letter.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Professor co-authors letter about America's mental health manual|url=http://www.pointpark.edu/news-arts-sciences/professor-coauthors-letter-about-americas-mental-health-manual|website=Point Park University|accessdate=6 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thirteen other [[American Psychological Association]] divisions have endorsed the petition.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.pointpark.edu/NewsArtsSciences.aspx?id=467 |title=Professor co-authors letter about America's mental health manual |date=December 12, 2011 |work=Point Park University |access-date=2012-04-04 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120329184708/http://www.pointpark.edu/NewsArtsSciences.aspx?id=467 |archive-date=2012-03-29 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; Robbins has noted that under the new guidelines, certain responses to grief could be labeled as pathological disorders, instead of being recognized as being normal human experiences.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2011/11/26/MNJJ1M3DFK.DTL |title=Revision of psychiatric manual under fire|first=Erin |last=Allday |date=November 26, 2011 |work=San Francisco Chronicle }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{col div|colwidth=30em}}
* [[Chinese Classification and Diagnostic Criteria of Mental Disorders]]
* [[Classification of mental disorders]]
* [[Diagnostic classification and rating scales used in psychiatry]]
* [[DSM-IV Codes]]
* [[Global Assessment of Functioning|Global Assessment of Functioning (GAF) Scale]]
* [[International Statistical Classification of Diseases and Related Health Problems|International Statistical Classification of Diseases and Related Health Problems (ICD)]]
* [[Kraepelinian dichotomy]]
* [[Psychodynamic Diagnostic Manual]]
* [[Relational disorder]] (proposed DSM-5 new diagnosis)
* [[Research Domain Criteria]] (RDoC), a framework being developed by the National Institute of Mental Health
* [[Rosenhan experiment]]
* [[Structured Clinical Interview for DSM-IV]] ''(SCID)''
* [[Homosexuality in DSM]]
{{colend}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite book| author = American Psychiatric Association| title = Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, Fourth Edition: DSM-IV-TR®| url = https://books.google.com/?id=3SQrtpnHb9MC| year = 2000| publisher = American Psychiatric Pub| isbn = 978-0-89042-025-6 }}
* {{cite book| author = Robert L. Spitzer| title = Dsm-Iv-Tr Casebook: A Learning Companion to the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders| url = https://books.google.com/?id=S_xe-AX4UjMC| year = 2002| publisher = American Psychiatric Pub| isbn = 978-1-58562-059-3 }}

==External links==
* [http://www.dsm5.org/pages/default.aspx Official DSM-5 development website]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20111026155340/http://www.behavenet.com/capsules/disorders/dsm4TRclassification.htm Diagnostic Criteria from DSM-IV-TR]
* [http://www.isko.org/cyclo/dsm Cooper, Rachel (2017): Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM). ISKO Encyclopedia of Knowledge Organization]
* [http://www.psyweb.com/DSM_IV/jsp/dsm_iv.jsp The Multiaxial System of Diagnosis in DSM-IV Criteria]

{{DSM personality disorders}}
{{Medical classification}}

{{italic title}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Diagnostic And Statistical Manual Of Mental Disorders}}
[[Category:American Psychiatric Association]]
[[Category:Data coding framework]]
[[Category:Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders| ]]
[[Category:Medical manuals]]
[[Category:Medical statistics]]
[[Category:Psychiatric assessment]]
[[Category:Psychiatric classification systems]]
[[Category:Psychiatric diagnosis]]
[[Category:Psychopathology]]
[[Category:Publications established in 1952]]
[[Category:Statistical data coding]]</text>
      <sha1>ea5ar75jw081p4hbkcwe0eeilu83umt</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
