  <page>
    <title>Asterales</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>789</id>
    <revision>
      <id>937482685</id>
      <parentid>929022316</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-25T09:14:01Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mark viking</username>
        <id>17698045</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Adding local [[Wikipedia:Short description|short description]]: &quot;Order of flowering plants&quot;, overriding Wikidata description &quot;order of plants&quot; ([[Wikipedia:Shortdesc helper|Shortdesc helper]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Order of flowering plants}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2013}}
{{More footnotes|date=February 2012}}
{{Automatic taxobox
| image = A_sunflower.jpg
| image_caption = [[Sunflower]], ''Helianthus annuus''
| taxon = Asterales
| authority = [[Johann Heinrich Friedrich Link|Link]]&lt;ref name=APGIII2009&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Angiosperm Phylogeny Group |year=2009 |title=An update of the Angiosperm Phylogeny Group classification for the orders and families of flowering plants: APG III |journal=Botanical Journal of the Linnean Society |volume=161 |issue=2 |pages=105–121 |url=http://www3.interscience.wiley.com/journal/122630309/abstract |archive-url=https://wayback.archive-it.org/all/20170525104318/http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/j.1095-8339.2009.00996.x/abstract |url-status = dead|archive-date=2017-05-25 | format= PDF |accessdate=2013-07-06 |doi=10.1111/j.1095-8339.2009.00996.x }}&lt;/ref&gt;
| subdivision_ranks = Families
| subdivision = 
*[[Alseuosmiaceae]]
*[[Argophyllaceae]]
*[[Asteraceae]] - Daisies
*[[Calyceraceae]]
*[[Campanulaceae]] (incl. Lobeliaceae) - Bellflowers
*[[Goodeniaceae]] (incl. Brunoniaceae)
*[[Menyanthaceae]]
*[[Pentaphragmataceae]]
*[[Phellinaceae]]
*[[Rousseaceae]] (incl. Carpodetaceae)
*[[Stylidiaceae]] (incl. Donatiaceae)
}}

'''Asterales''' {{IPAc-en|æ|s|t|ə|ˈ|r|eɪ|l|iː|z}}&lt;ref&gt;''Botanical Latin'', William T Stearn, Timber Press 2004, {{ISBN|0-88192-627-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; is an [[Order (biology)|order]] of [[dicotyledon]]ous [[flowering plant]]s that includes the large [[Family (biology)|family]] [[Asteraceae]] (or Compositae) known for composite flowers made of [[Floret#floret|florets]], and ten families related to the Asteraceae.&lt;ref&gt;The Families and Genera of Vascular Plants, Edited by K. Kubitzki, Volume VIII, Flowering Plants Eudicots Asterales; Springer 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

The order is a [[Cosmopolitan distribution|cosmopolite]] (plants found throughout most of the world including desert and frigid zones), and includes mostly [[Herbaceous plant|herbaceous]] species, although a small number of trees (such as the [[Lobelia deckenii|giant Lobelia]] and the [[Dendrosenecio|giant Senecio]]) and [[shrub]]s are also present.

Asterales are organisms that seem to have evolved from one common [[ancestor]]. Asterales share characteristics on [[Morphology (biology)|morphological]] and biochemical levels.  [[Synapomorphies]] (a character that is shared by two or more groups through evolutionary development) include the presence in the plants of [[oligosaccharide]] [[inulin]], a nutrient storage molecule used instead of [[starch]]; and unique [[stamen]] morphology. The stamens are usually found around the [[Gynoecium|style]], either aggregated densely or fused into a tube, probably an [[adaptation]] in association with the plunger (brush; or secondary) [[pollination]] that is common among the families of the order, wherein pollen is collected and stored on the length of the pistil.

== Taxonomy ==
The name and order Asterales is botanically venerable, dating back to at least 1926 in the [[Hutchinson system| Hutchinson system of plant taxonomy]] when it contained only five families, of which only two are retained in the APG III classification. Under the [[Cronquist system]] of taxonomic classification of flowering plants, [[Asteraceae]] was the only family in the group, but newer systems (such as [[APG II system|APG II]] and [[APG III system|APG III]]) have expanded it to 11. In the classification system of [[Rolf Dahlgren|Dahlgren]] the Asterales were in the [[superorder]] Asteriflorae (also called Asteranae).

The order '''Asterales''' currently includes 11 families, the largest of which are the [[Asteraceae]], with about 25,000 species, and the [[Campanulaceae]] (&quot;bellflowers&quot;), with about 2,000 species. The remaining families count together for less than 1500 species. The two large families are cosmopolitan, with many of their species found in the Northern Hemisphere, and the smaller families are usually confined to Australia and the adjacent areas, or sometimes South America.

Only the Asteraceae have composite flower heads; the other families do not, but share other characteristics such as storage of inulin that define the 11 families as more closely related to each other than to other plant families or orders such as the [[rosids]].

The phylogenetic tree according to APG III for the Campanulid clade is as below.&lt;ref name=apweb&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mobot.org/mobot/research/apweb/ |title=Angiosperm Phylogeny Website |publisher=Mobot.org |date= |accessdate=2012-06-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Clade
|label1=[[Campanulids|Campanulid&amp;nbsp;clade&amp;nbsp;]]&amp;nbsp;(similar&amp;nbsp;to '''Euasterids&amp;nbsp;II'''&amp;nbsp;in&amp;nbsp;APG&amp;nbsp;II)
|1={{Clade
              |1=&amp;nbsp;[[Aquifoliales]]
              |2={{Clade
                 |1={{Clade
                    |1=&amp;nbsp;[[Bruniales]]
                    |2={{Clade
                       |1={{Clade
                          |1=&amp;nbsp;[[Paracryphiales]]
                          |2=&amp;nbsp;[[Dipsacales]]
                          }}
                       |2=&amp;nbsp;[[Apiales]]
                       }}
                    }}
                 |2=&amp;nbsp;[[Escalloniales]]
                 |3=&amp;nbsp;'''Asterales'''
                 }}
              }}
}}

==Biogeography==
The core Asterales are Stylidiaceae (six [[Genus|genera]]), APA [[clade]] (Alseuosmiaceae, Phellinaceae and Argophyllaceae, together 7 genera), MGCA clade (Menyanthaceae, Goodeniaceae, Calyceraceae, in total twenty genera), and Asteraceae (about sixteen hundred genera). Other Asterales are Rousseaceae (four genera), Campanulaceae (eighty four genera) and Pentaphragmataceae (one genus).

All Asterales families are represented in the Southern Hemisphere; however, Asteraceae and Campanulaceae are cosmopolitan and Menyanthaceae nearly so.&lt;ref&gt;J.Lundberg 2009 Asteraceae and relationships within Asterales, Chapter 10 of Systematics, Evolution, and Biogeography of Compositae. IAPT,  Austria, p.159&lt;/ref&gt;

==Evolution==
Although most extant species of Asteraceae are herbaceous, the examination of the basal members in the family suggests that the common ancestor of the family was an arborescent plant, a tree or shrub, perhaps adapted to dry conditions, radiating from South America. Less can be said about the Asterales themselves with certainty, although since several families in Asterales contain trees, the ancestral member is most likely to have been a tree or shrub.

Because all clades are represented in the southern hemisphere but many not in the northern hemisphere, it is natural to conjecture that there is a common southern origin to them. Asterales are [[angiosperms]], flowering plants that appeared about 140 million years ago. The Asterales order probably originated in the [[Cretaceous]] (145 – 66 [[Mya (unit)#Symbols y and yr|Mya]]) on the supercontinent [[Gondwana]] which broke up from 184 – 80 Mya, forming the area that is now Australia, South America, Africa, India and Antarctica.

Asterales contain about 14% of [[eudicot]] diversity. From an analysis of relationships and diversities within the Asterales and with their superorders, estimates of the age of the beginning of the Asterales have been made, which range from 116 Mya to 82Mya.&lt;ref name=apweb/&gt; However few fossils have been found, of the Menyanthaceae-Asteraceae clade in the [[Oligocene]], about 29 Mya.

Fossil evidence of the Asterales is rare and belongs to rather recent epochs, so the precise estimation of the order's age is quite difficult. An Oligocene (34 – 23 Mya) pollen is known for Asteraceae and Goodeniaceae, and seeds from Oligocene and [[Miocene]] (23 – 5.3 Mya)  are known for Menyanthaceae and Campanulaceae respectively.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first1= K. |last1= Bremer |first2= M. H. G. |last2= Gustafsson |year= 1997 |title= East Gondwana ancestry of the sunflower alliance of families |journal= Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America |volume= 94 |issue= 17 |pages= 9188–9190 |doi=10.1073/pnas.94.17.9188|pmid= 9256457 |pmc= 23106 |bibcode= 1997PNAS...94.9188B }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Economic importance==
The Asterales, by dint of being a super-set of the family Asteraceae, include some species grown for food, including the [[sunflower]] (''Helianthus annuus''),  lettuce (''Lactuca sativa'') and [[chicory]] (''Cichorium'').&lt;ref&gt;Compositdb: A Brief Overview of the Compositae
http://compositdb.ucdavis.edu/compositae_overview.php&lt;/ref&gt; Many are also used as spices and traditional medicines.

Asterales are common plants and have many known uses. For example, [[pyrethrum]] (derived from Old World members of the genus ''Chrysanthemum'') is a natural insecticide with minimal environmental impact.{{citation needed|date=October 2014}} [[Artemisia (genus)|Wormwood]], derived from a genus that includes the [[sagebrush]], is used as a source of flavoring for [[absinthe]], a bitter classical liquor of European origin.&lt;ref name=&quot;5best&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Wondrich |first=David |url= http://www.esquire.com/food-drink/drinks/a4816/absinthe-0808/ |title=The Five Best Bottles of Absinthe |work=[[Esquire (magazine)|Esquire]] |date=2008-08-05 |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Commons category|Asterales|Asterales (category)}}
{{Wikispecies|Asterales}}
{{Reflist}}
* W. S. Judd, C. S. Campbell, E. A. Kellogg, P. F. Stevens, M. J. Donoghue (2002). ''Plant Systematics: A Phylogenetic Approach, 2nd edition.'' pp.&amp;nbsp;476–486 (Asterales). Sinauer Associates, Sunderland, Massachusetts. {{ISBN|0-87893-403-0}}.
* [[John Lindley|J. Lindley]] (1833). ''Nixus Plantarum'', 20. Londini.
* Smissen, R. D. (December 2002). Asterales (Sunflower). In: ''Nature Encyclopedia of Life Sciences''. Nature Publishing Group, London. (Available online: [https://dx.doi.org/10.1038/npg.els.0003736 DOI] | [http://www.els.net/ ELS site])
* &quot;Asterales (plant Order) -- Britannica Online Encyclopedia.&quot; Encyclopedia - Britannica Online Encyclopedia. Web. 19 Jan. 2012. &lt;http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/39703/Asterales&gt;.
*&quot;Asterales - Definition and More from the Free Merriam-Webster Dictionary.&quot; Dictionary and Thesaurus - Merriam-Webster Online. Web. 19 Jan. 2012. &lt;http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/asterales&gt;.

{{Taxonbar|from=Q21730}}

[[Category:Asterales| ]]
[[Category:Angiosperm orders]]</text>
      <sha1>fzcgyzb6kcv3iwpxzy1r1qcmiu7k6kc</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
