  <page>
    <title>Aquarius (constellation)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>799</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942919406</id>
      <parentid>942919389</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-27T18:15:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Merlin04</username>
        <id>34846537</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contributions/Therealmcsusy|Therealmcsusy]] ([[User talk:Therealmcsusy|talk]]) ([[WP:HG|HG]]) (3.4.9)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Zodiac constellation which straddles the celestial equator}}
{{about|the astronomical constellation|the astrological sign|Aquarius (astrology)}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2020}}
{{Infobox constellation
| name = Aquarius
| abbreviation = Aqr
| genitive = Aquarii
| pronounce = {{IPAc-en|ə|ˈ|k|w|ɛər|i|ə|s}}, genitive {{IPAc-en|ə|ˈ|k|w|ɛər|i|aɪ}}
| symbolism = the Water-Bearer
| RA = {{RA|20|38|19.1706}}–{{RA|23|56|23.5355}}&lt;ref name=boundary/&gt;
| dec= {{dec|03.3256676}}–{{dec|-24.9040413}}&lt;ref name=boundary&gt;{{Cite journal | title=Aquarius, constellation boundary | journal=The Constellations |url=http://www.iau.org/public/constellations/#aqr | accessdate=30 April 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
| family = [[Zodiac]]
| areatotal = 980
| arearank = 10th
| numbermainstars = 10, 22
| numberbfstars = 97
| numberstarsplanets = 12
| numberbrightstars = 2
| numbernearbystars = 7
| brighteststarname = [[Beta Aquarii|β Aqr]] (Sadalsuud)
| starmagnitude = 2.91
| neareststarname = [[EZ Aquarii|EZ Aqr]]
| stardistancely = 11.27
| stardistancepc = 3.45
| numbermessierobjects = 3
| meteorshowers = March Aquariids &lt;br /&gt;[[Eta Aquariids]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Delta Aquariids]]&lt;br /&gt; Iota Aquariids
| bordering = [[Pisces (constellation)|Pisces]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Pegasus (constellation)|Pegasus]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Equuleus]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Delphinus]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Aquila (constellation)|Aquila]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Capricornus]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Piscis Austrinus]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Sculptor (constellation)|Sculptor]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Cetus]]
| latmax = [[65th parallel north|65]]
| latmin = [[South Pole|90]]
| month = October
| notes= 
}}
'''Aquarius''' is a [[constellation]] of the [[zodiac]], situated between [[Capricornus]] and [[Pisces (constellation)|Pisces]]. Its name is [[Latin]] for &quot;water-carrier&quot; or &quot;cup-carrier&quot;, and its symbol is [[Image:Aquarius.svg|20px]] , a representation of water. Aquarius is one of the oldest of the recognized constellations along the [[zodiac]] (the [[Sun]]'s apparent path).{{sfn|Rogers|1998|pp=9–28}} It was one of the 48 constellations listed by the 2nd century astronomer [[Ptolemy]], and it remains one of the 88 modern constellations. It is found in a region often called the [[Sea (astronomy)|Sea]] due to its profusion of constellations with watery associations such as [[Cetus]] the [[whale]], [[Pisces (constellation)|Pisces]] the [[fish]], and [[Eridanus (constellation)|Eridanus]] the [[river]].{{sfn|Thompson|Thompson|2007}}

At [[apparent magnitude]] 2.9, [[Beta Aquarii]] is the brightest star in the constellation.

==History and mythology==
Aquarius is identified as {{lang|sux-Latn|GU.LA}} &quot;The Great One&quot; in the [[Babylonian star catalogues]] and represents the god [[Ea (god)|Ea]] himself, who is commonly depicted holding an overflowing vase. The Babylonian star-figure appears on entitlement stones and [[cylinder seals]] from the [[2nd millennium BC|second millennium]]. It contained the [[winter solstice]] in the Early Bronze Age.{{sfn|Thurston|1996}} In [[Old Babylonian astronomy]], Ea was the ruler of the southernmost quarter of the Sun's path, the &quot;Way of Ea&quot;, corresponding to the period of 45 days on either side of winter solstice. Aquarius was also associated with the destructive floods that the Babylonians regularly experienced, and thus was negatively connoted.{{sfn|Thompson|Thompson|2007}} In [[Egyptian astronomy#Ancient Egypt|Ancient Egypt astronomy]], Aquarius was associated with the annual [[flood of the Nile]]; the banks were said to flood when Aquarius put his jar into the river, beginning spring.{{sfn|Staal|1988|pp=42–44}}

In the [[Ancient Greek astronomy|Greek tradition]], the constellation came to be represented simply as a single vase from which a stream poured down to [[Piscis Austrinus]]. The name in the [[Hindu zodiac]] is likewise ''kumbha'' &quot;water-pitcher&quot;.{{sfn|Rogers|1998|pp=9–28}}

In Greek mythology, Aquarius is sometimes associated with [[Deucalion]], the son of [[Prometheus]] who built a ship with his wife [[Pyrrha]] to survive an imminent flood. They sailed for nine days before washing ashore on [[Mount Parnassus]].{{sfn|Thompson|Thompson|2007}}{{sfn|Star Tales}} Aquarius is also sometimes identified with beautiful [[Ganymede (mythology)|Ganymede]], a youth in [[Greek mythology]] and the son of [[Troy|Trojan]] king [[Tros (mythology)|Tros]], who was taken to [[Mount Olympus]] by [[Zeus]] to act as cup-carrier to the [[Greek pantheon|gods]].{{sfn|Moore|2000}}{{sfn|Ridpath|2001}}{{sfn|Star Tales}} Neighboring [[Aquila (constellation)|Aquila]] represents the eagle, under Zeus' command, that snatched the young boy;{{sfn|Rogers|1998|pp=79–89}} some versions of the myth indicate that the eagle was in fact Zeus transformed. An alternative version of the tale recounts Ganymede's kidnapping by the goddess of the dawn, [[Eos]], motivated by her affection for young men; Zeus then stole him from Eos and employed him as cup-bearer. Yet another figure associated with the water bearer is [[Cecrops I]], a king of [[Athens]] who [[sacrifice]]d water instead of [[wine]] to the gods.{{sfn|Star Tales}}

===Depictions===
[[File:Sidney Hall - Urania's Mirror - Aquarius, Piscis Australis &amp; Ballon Aerostatique.jpg|left|thumb|350px|A representation of Aquarius printed in 1825 as part of ''[[Urania's Mirror]]'' (including a now-obsolete constellation, [[Ballon Aerostatique]] south of it)]]
In the first century, [[Ptolemy]]'s ''[[Almagest]]'' established the common Western depiction of Aquarius. His water jar, an asterism itself, consists of Gamma, Pi, Eta, and [[Zeta Aquarii]]; it pours water in a stream of more than 20 stars terminating with [[Fomalhaut]], now assigned solely to [[Piscis Austrinus]]. The water bearer's head is represented by 5th magnitude [[25 Aquarii]] while his left shoulder is [[Beta Aquarii]]; his right shoulder and forearm are represented by [[Alpha Aquarii|Alpha]] and [[Gamma Aquarii]] respectively.{{sfn|Star Tales}}

===In Eastern astronomy===
In [[Chinese astronomy]], the stream of water flowing from the Water Jar was depicted as the &quot;Army of Yu-Lin&quot; (''Yu-lin-kiun'' or ''Yulinjun''). The name &quot;Yu-lin&quot; means &quot;feathers and forests&quot;, referring to the numerous light-footed soldiers from the northern reaches of the empire represented by these faint stars.{{sfn|Staal|1988|pp=42–44}}{{sfn|Star Tales}} The constellation's stars were the most numerous of any Chinese constellation, numbering 45, the majority of which were located in modern Aquarius. The celestial army was protected by the wall ''Leibizhen'', which counted Iota, Lambda, Phi, and Sigma Aquarii among its 12 stars.{{sfn|Star Tales}} 88, 89, and 98 Aquarii represent ''Fou-youe'', the axes used as weapons and for hostage executions. Also in Aquarius is ''Loui-pi-tchin'', the ramparts that stretch from 29 and 27 Piscium and 33 and 30 Aquarii through Phi, Lambda, Sigma, and Iota Aquarii to Delta, Gamma, Kappa, and Epsilon Capricorni.{{sfn|Staal|1988|pp=42–44}}

Near the border with [[Cetus]], the axe ''Fuyue'' was represented by three stars; its position is disputed and may have instead been located in [[Sculptor (constellation)|Sculptor]]. ''Tienliecheng'' also has a disputed position; the 13-star castle replete with ramparts may have possessed Nu and Xi Aquarii but may instead have been located south in Piscis Austrinus. The Water Jar asterism was seen to the ancient Chinese as the tomb, ''Fenmu''. Nearby, the emperors' [[mausoleum]] ''Xiuliang'' stood, demarcated by Kappa Aquarii and three other collinear stars. ''Ku'' (&quot;crying&quot;) and ''Qi'' (&quot;weeping&quot;), each composed of two stars, were located in the same region.{{sfn|Star Tales}}

Three of the Chinese [[lunar mansion]]s shared their name with constellations. ''Nu'', also the name for the 10th lunar mansion, was a [[handmaiden]] represented by Epsilon, Mu, 3, and 4 Aquarii. The 11th lunar mansion shared its name with the constellation ''Xu'' (&quot;emptiness&quot;), formed by Beta Aquarii and Alpha Equulei; it represented a bleak place associated with death and funerals. ''Wei'', the rooftop and 12th lunar mansion, was a V-shaped constellation formed by Alpha Aquarii, Theta Pegasi, and Epsilon Pegasi; it shared its name with two other Chinese constellations, in modern-day [[Scorpius (constellation)|Scorpius]] and [[Aries (constellation)|Aries]].{{sfn|Star Tales}}

==Features==
[[Image:AquariusCC.jpg|thumb|256px|The constellation Aquarius as it can be seen by the naked eye]]

{{See also|List of stars in Aquarius}}

===Stars===
Despite both its prominent position on the zodiac and its large size, Aquarius has no particularly bright stars, its four brightest stars being less than magnitude 2.{{sfn|Moore|2000}} However, recent research has shown that there are several stars lying within its borders that possess [[extrasolar planet|planetary systems]].

The two brightest stars, [[Alpha Aquarii|Alpha]] and [[Beta Aquarii]], are luminous yellow supergiants, of spectral types G0Ib and G2Ib respectively,&lt;ref name=mnras402_2_1369/&gt; that were once hot blue-white B-class main sequence stars 5 to 9 times as massive as the Sun. The two are also moving through space perpendicular to the plane of the Milky Way.&lt;ref name=apj627_1_L53&gt;{{cite journal | last1=Ayres | first1=Thomas R. | last2=Brown | first2=Alexander | last3=Harper | first3=Graham M. | title=Chandra Observations of Coronal Emission from the Early G Supergiants α and β Aquarii | journal=The Astrophysical Journal | volume=627 | issue=1 | pages=L53–L56 |date=July 2005 | doi=10.1086/431977 | bibcode=2005ApJ...627L..53A | doi-access=free }}&lt;/ref&gt; Just shading Alpha, Beta Aquarii is the brightest star in Aquarius with an apparent magnitude of 2.91. It also has the proper name of Sadalsuud. Having cooled and swollen to around 50 times the Sun's diameter, it is around 2200 times as luminous as the Sun.&lt;ref name=&quot;kalerbeta&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title=Sadalsuud (Beta Aquarii) | publisher=University of Illinois | first1=James B. | last1=Kaler | work=Stars | url=http://stars.astro.illinois.edu/sow/sadalsuud.html | accessdate=11 October 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt; It is around 6.4 times as massive as the Sun and around 56 million years old.&lt;ref name=leonid&gt;{{cite journal|bibcode=2015MNRAS.446.3447L|arxiv=1411.2722|title=Carbon abundance and the N/C ratio in atmospheres of A-, F- and G-type supergiants and bright giants|journal=Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society|volume=446|issue=4|pages=3447|author1=Lyubimkov|first1=Leonid S.|last2=Lambert|first2=David L.|last3=Korotin|first3=Sergey A.|last4=Rachkovskaya|first4=Tamara M.|last5=Poklad|first5=Dmitry B.|year=2015|doi=10.1093/mnras/stu2299}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sadalsuud is 540 ± 20 light-years from Earth.&lt;ref name=&quot;vanLeeuwen2007&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | first=F. | last=van Leeuwen | title=Validation of the New Hipparcos Reduction | journal=Astronomy and Astrophysics | volume=474 | issue=2 | pages=653–64 | date=2007 | bibcode=2007A&amp;A...474..653V | doi=10.1051/0004-6361:20078357 | arxiv=0708.1752}}&lt;/ref&gt; Alpha Aquarii, also known as Sadalmelik, has an apparent magnitude of 2.94. It is 520 ± 20 light-years distant from Earth,&lt;ref name=&quot;vanLeeuwen2007&quot;/&gt; and is around 6.5 times as massive as the Sun and 3000 times as luminous. It is 53 million years old.&lt;ref name=mnras402_2_1369&gt;{{cite journal | last1=Lyubimkov | first1=Leonid S. | last2=Lambert | first2=David L. | last3=Rostopchin | first3=Sergey I. | last4=Rachkovskaya | first4=Tamara M. | last5=Poklad | first5=Dmitry B. | title=Accurate fundamental parameters for A-, F- and G-type Supergiants in the solar neighbourhood | journal=[[Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society]] | volume=402 | issue=2 | pages=1369–79 |date=2010 | doi=10.1111/j.1365-2966.2009.15979.x | bibcode=2010MNRAS.402.1369L |arxiv = 0911.1335 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Gamma Aquarii|γ Aquarii]], also called Sadachbia,&lt;ref name=&quot;IAU-LSN&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=https://www.iau.org/public/themes/naming_stars/ | title=Naming Stars |publisher=IAU.org |accessdate=30 July 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; is a white main sequence star of spectral type star of spectral type A0V that is between 158 and 315 million years old and is around two and a half times the Sun's mass,&lt;ref name=David2015&gt;{{cite journal | bibcode=2015ApJ...804..146D | doi=10.1088/0004-637X/804/2/146 | arxiv=1501.03154 | title=The Ages of Early-Type Stars: Strömgren Photometric Methods Calibrated, Validated, Tested, and Applied to Hosts and Prospective Hosts of Directly Imaged Exoplanets | journal=The Astrophysical Journal | volume=804 | issue=2 | pages=146 | year=2015 | last1=David | first1=Trevor J. | last2=Hillenbrand | first2=Lynne A. }} [http://vizier.u-strasbg.fr/viz-bin/VizieR-4?-source=J/ApJ/804/146/table5&amp;HIP=102395 Vizier catalog entry]&lt;/ref&gt; and double its radius.&lt;ref name=aaa367_521&gt;{{cite journal | last1=Pasinetti Fracassini | first1=L. E. | last2=Pastori | first2=L. | last3=Covino | first3=S. | last4=Pozzi | first4=A. | title=Catalogue of Apparent Diameters and Absolute Radii of Stars (CADARS) – Third edition – Comments and statistics | journal=Astronomy and Astrophysics | volume=367 | issue=2 | pages=521–524 |date=February 2001 | doi=10.1051/0004-6361:20000451 | bibcode=2001A&amp;A...367..521P | arxiv=astro-ph/0012289}}&lt;/ref&gt; Of magnitude 3.85, it is 164 ± 9 light years away.&lt;ref name=&quot;vanLeeuwen2007&quot;/&gt; It has a luminosity of {{Solar luminosity|50}}.{{sfn|Moore|2000}} The name Sadachbia comes from the Arabic for &quot;lucky stars of the tents&quot;, ''sa'd al-akhbiya''.{{sfn|Star Tales}}

[[delta Aquarii|δ Aquarii]], also known as Skat&lt;ref name=&quot;IAU-LSN&quot;/&gt;{{sfn|Ridpath|2001}} or Scheat{{sfn|Moore|2000}} is a blue-white A2 spectral type star of magnitude 3.27 and luminosity of {{Solar luminosity|105}}.{{sfn|Moore|2000}}

[[epsilon Aquarii|ε Aquarii]], also known as Albali,{{sfn|Staal|1988|pp=42–44}} is a blue-white A1 spectral type star with an apparent magnitude of 3.77, an absolute magnitude of 1.2, and a luminosity of {{Solar luminosity|28}}.{{sfn|Moore|2000}}{{sfn|Ridpath|2001}}

[[zeta Aquarii|ζ Aquarii]] is an F2 spectral type [[double star]]; both stars are white.{{sfn|Ridpath|2001}} Overall, it appears to be of magnitude 3.6 and luminosity of {{Solar luminosity|50}}. The primary has a magnitude of 4.53 and the secondary a magnitude of 4.31, but both have an absolute magnitude of 0.6.{{sfn|Moore|2000}} Its orbital period is 760 years; the two components are currently moving farther apart.{{sfn|Ridpath|2001}}

[[theta Aquarii|θ Aquarii]], sometimes called Ancha,{{sfn|Staal|1988|pp=42–44}} is a G8 spectral type star with an apparent magnitude of 4.16 and an absolute magnitude of 1.4.{{sfn|Moore|2000}}

[[Kappa Aquarii|κ Aquarii]], also called Situla.&lt;ref name=&quot;IAU-LSN&quot;/&gt;

[[lambda Aquarii|λ Aquarii]], also called Hudoor or Ekchusis,{{sfn|Staal|1988|pp=42–44}} is an [[M-type star|M2 spectral type star]] of magnitude 3.74 and luminosity of {{Solar luminosity|120}}.{{sfn|Moore|2000}}

[[xi Aquarii|ξ Aquarii]], also called Bunda,&lt;ref name=&quot;IAU-LSN&quot;/&gt; is an [[A-type star|A7 spectral type star]] with an apparent magnitude of 4.69 and an absolute magnitude of 2.4.{{sfn|Moore|2000}}

[[pi Aquarii|π Aquarii]], also called Seat, is a [[B-type star|B0 spectral type star]] with an apparent magnitude of 4.66 and an absolute magnitude of −4.1.{{sfn|Moore|2000}}

===Planetary systems===
Twelve exoplanet systems have been found in Aquarius as of 2013. [[Gliese 876]], one of the nearest stars to Earth at a distance of 15 light-years,{{sfn|APOD Gliese 876}} was the first [[red dwarf]] star to be found to possess a [[planetary system]]. It is orbited by four planets, including one [[terrestrial planet]] 6.6 times the mass of Earth. The planets vary in orbital period from 2 days to 124 days.{{sfn|Exoplanet Encyclopedia Gliese 876}} [[91 Aquarii]] is an [[orange giant]] star orbited by one planet, [[91 Aquarii b|91&amp;nbsp;Aquarii&amp;nbsp;b]]. The planet's mass is 2.9 times the mass of Jupiter, and its orbital period is 182 days.{{sfn|Exoplanet Encyclopedia 91 Aqr}} [[Gliese 849]] is a red dwarf star orbited by the first known long-period Jupiter-like planet, [[Gliese 849 b|Gliese&amp;nbsp;849&amp;nbsp;b]]. The planet's mass is 0.99 times that of Jupiter and its orbital period is 1,852 days.{{sfn|Exoplanet Encyclopedia Gj 849}}

There are also less-prominent systems in Aquarius. [[WASP-6]], a type G8 star of magnitude 12.4, is host to one exoplanet, [[WASP-6 b]]. The star is 307 [[parsec]]s from Earth and has a mass of 0.888 [[solar mass]]es and a radius of 0.87 [[solar radius|solar radii]]. WASP-6 b was discovered in 2008 by the [[transit method]]. It orbits its parent star every 3.36 days at a distance of 0.042 [[astronomical unit]]s (AU). It is 0.503 [[Jupiter mass]]es but has a proportionally larger radius of 1.224 [[Jupiter radius|Jupiter radii]].{{sfn|Exoplanet Encyclopedia WASP-6}} [[HD 206610]], a K0 star located 194 parsecs from Earth, is host to one planet, [[HD 206610 b]]. The host star is larger than the Sun; more massive at 1.56 solar masses and larger at 6.1 solar radii. The planet was discovered by the radial velocity method in 2010 and has a mass of 2.2 Jupiter masses. It orbits every 610 days at a distance of 1.68 AU.{{sfn|Exoplanet Encyclopedia HD 206610 b}} Much closer to its sun is [[WASP-47 b]], which orbits every 4.15 days only 0.052 AU from its sun, yellow dwarf (G9V) [[WASP-47]]. WASP-47 is close in size to the Sun, having a radius of 1.15 solar radii and a mass even closer at 1.08 solar masses. WASP-47 b was discovered in 2011 by the transit method, like WASP-6 b. It is slightly larger than Jupiter with a mass of 1.14 Jupiter masses and a radius of 1.15 Jupiter masses.{{sfn|Exoplanet Encyclopedia WASP-47 b}}

There are several more single-planet systems in Aquarius. [[HD 210277]], a magnitude 6.63 yellow star located 21.29 parsecs from Earth, is host to one known planet: [[HD 210277 b]]. The 1.23 Jupiter mass planet orbits at nearly the same distance as Earth orbits the Sun{{mdash}}1.1 AU, though its orbital period is significantly longer at around 442 days. HD 210277 b was discovered earlier than most of the other planets in Aquarius, detected by the radial velocity method in 1998. The star it orbits resembles the Sun beyond their similar [[spectral class]]; it has a radius of 1.1 solar radii and a mass of 1.09 solar masses.{{sfn|Exoplanet Encyclopedia HD 210277 b}} [[HD 212771 b]], a larger planet at 2.3 Jupiter masses, orbits host star [[HD 212771]] at a distance of 1.22 AU. The star itself, barely below the threshold of naked-eye visibility at magnitude 7.6, is a G8IV (yellow subgiant) star located 131 parsecs from Earth. Though it has a similar mass to the Sun{{mdash}}1.15 solar masses{{mdash}}it is significantly less dense with its radius of 5 solar radii. Its lone planet was discovered in 2010 by the radial velocity method, like several other exoplanets in the constellation.{{sfn|Exoplanet Encyclopedia HD 212771 b}}

As of 2013, there were only two known multiple-planet systems within the bounds of Aquarius: the Gliese 876 and [[HD 215152]] systems. The former is quite prominent; the latter has only two planets and has a host star farther away at 21.5 parsecs. The HD 215152 system consists of the planets [[HD 215152 b]] and [[HD 215152 c]] orbiting their K0-type, magnitude 8.13 sun. Both discovered in 2011 by the radial velocity method, the two tiny planets orbit very close to their host star. HD 215152 c is the larger at 0.0097 Jupiter masses (still significantly larger than the Earth, which weighs in at 0.00315 Jupiter masses); its smaller sibling is barely smaller at 0.0087 Jupiter masses. The [[error]] in the mass measurements (0.0032 and {{Jupiter mass|0.0049}} respectively) is large enough to make this discrepancy statistically insignificant. HD 215152 c also orbits further from the star than HD 215152 b, 0.0852 AU compared to 0.0652.{{sfn|Exoplanet Encyclopedia HD 215152 b}}{{sfn|Exoplanet Encyclopedia HD 215152 c}}

On 23 February 2017, NASA announced that [[Ultra-cool dwarf|ultracool dwarf star]] [[TRAPPIST-1]] in Aquarius has seven [[Exoplanet|Earth-like rocky planets]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Trappist-1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=NASA Telescope Reveals Largest Batch of Earth-Size, Habitable-Zone Planets Around Single Star|url=https://www.nasa.gov/press-release/nasa-telescope-reveals-largest-batch-of-earth-size-habitable-zone-planets-around|website=NASA|publisher=NASA|accessdate=23 February 2017|date=22 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Of these, three are in the system's habitable zone, and may contain water. The discovery of the TRAPPIST-1 system is seen by astronomers as a significant step toward finding life beyond Earth.

===Deep sky objects===
[[File:The green bean galaxy J2240.jpg|thumb|The [[green bean galaxy]] J2240 lies in the constellation of Aquarius{{sfn|ESO 2012}}]]

Because of its position away from the galactic plane, the majority of deep-sky objects in Aquarius are galaxies, globular clusters, and planetary nebulae.{{sfn|Thompson|Thompson|2007}} Aquarius contains three [[deep sky object]]s that are in the [[Messier object|Messier catalog]]: the globular clusters [[Messier 2|Messier&amp;nbsp;2]], [[Messier 72|Messier&amp;nbsp;72]], and the open cluster [[Messier 73|Messier&amp;nbsp;73]]. Two well-known [[planetary nebula]]e are also located in Aquarius: the [[Saturn Nebula]] (NGC&amp;nbsp;7009), to the southeast of [[Mu Aquarii|μ Aquarii]]; and the famous [[Helix Nebula]] (NGC&amp;nbsp;7293), southwest of [[δ Aquarii|δ&amp;nbsp;Aquarii]].

M2, also catalogued as NGC 7089, is a rich globular cluster located approximately 37,000 light-years from Earth. At magnitude 6.5, it is viewable in small-[[aperture]] instruments, but a 100&amp;nbsp;mm aperture [[telescope]] is needed to resolve any stars. M72, also catalogued as NGC 6981, is a small 9th magnitude globular cluster located approximately 56,000 light-years from Earth.{{sfn|Ridpath|2001}} M73, also catalogued as NGC 6994, is an open cluster with highly disputed status.

Aquarius is also home to several planetary nebulae. [[NGC 7009]], also known as the Saturn Nebula, is an 8th magnitude planetary nebula located 3,000 light-years from Earth. It was given its moniker by the 19th century astronomer [[Lord Rosse]] for its resemblance to the planet [[Saturn]] in a telescope; it has faint protrusions on either side that resemble [[Saturn's rings]]. It appears blue-green in a telescope and has a central star of magnitude 11.3.{{sfn|Ridpath|2001}} Compared to the Helix Nebula, another planetary nebula in Aquarius, it is quite small.{{sfn|Levy|2005|p=132}} [[NGC 7293]], also known as the Helix Nebula, is the closest planetary nebula to Earth at a distance of 650 light-years. It covers 0.25 square degrees, making it also the largest planetary nebula as seen from Earth. However, because it is so large, it is only viewable as a very faint object,{{sfn|Ridpath|2001}} though it has a fairly high [[integrated magnitude]] of 6.0.{{sfn|Levy|2005|p=131}}

One of the visible galaxies in Aquarius is [[NGC 7727]], of particular interest for amateur astronomers who wish to discover or observe [[supernovae]]. A [[spiral galaxy]] ([[galaxy morphological classification|type S]]), it has an [[integrated magnitude]] of 10.7 and is 3 by 3 arcseconds.{{sfn|Sherrod|Koed|2003|p=222}} [[NGC 7252]] is a tangle of stars resulting from the collision of two large galaxies and is known as the Atoms-for-Peace galaxy because of its resemblance to a cartoon atom.{{sfn|APOD Atoms-for-Peace Galaxy}}

===Meteor showers===
There are three major meteor showers with [[radiant (meteor shower)|radiant]]s in Aquarius: the [[Eta Aquariids]], the [[Delta Aquariids]], and the Iota Aquariids.

The Eta Aquariids are the strongest meteor shower radiating from Aquarius. It peaks between 5 and 6 May with a rate of approximately 35 meteors per hour.{{sfn|Ridpath|2001}} Originally discovered by Chinese astronomers in 401, Eta Aquariids can be seen coming from the Water Jar beginning on 21 April and as late as 12 May. The [[parent body]] of the shower is [[Halley's Comet]], a [[periodic comet]]. [[Meteoroid#Fireball|Fireball]]s are common shortly after the peak, approximately between 9 May and 11 May. The normal meteors appear to have yellow trails.{{sfn|Sherrod|Koed|2003|p=52}}

The Delta Aquariids is a double radiant meteor shower that peaks first on 29 July and second on 6 August. The first radiant is located in the south of the constellation, while the second radiant is located in the northern circlet of Pisces asterism. The southern radiant's peak rate is about 20 meteors per hour, while the northern radiant's peak rate is about 10 meteors per hour.{{sfn|Ridpath|2001}}

The Iota Aquariids is a fairly weak meteor shower that peaks on 6 August, with a rate of approximately 8 meteors per hour.{{sfn|Ridpath|2001}}

==Astrology==
{{Main|Aquarius (astrology)}}

{{As of|2002}}, the Sun appears in the constellation Aquarius from 16 February to 11 March. In [[tropical astrology]], the Sun is considered to be in the sign [[Aquarius (astrology)|Aquarius]] from 20 January to 19 February, and in [[sidereal astrology]], from 15 February to 14 March.

Aquarius is also associated with the [[Age of Aquarius]], a concept popular in [[1960s counterculture]]. Despite this prominence, the Age of Aquarius will not dawn until the year 2597, as an astrological age does not begin until the Sun is in a particular constellation on the [[Vernal equinox (Northern Hemisphere)|vernal equinox]].{{sfn|Thompson|Thompson|2007}}{{sfn|Ridpath|2001}}

==Notes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==References==
{{Refbegin|30em}}
* {{citation 
  | url = http://apod.nasa.gov/apod/ap101116.html
  | title = Atoms-for-Peace Galaxy Collision
  | date = 16 November 2010
  | accessdate = 22 August 2014
  | work = Astronomy Picture of the Day
  | publisher = NASA
  | ref = {{sfnRef|APOD Atoms-for-Peace Galaxy}}
  }}
* {{citation 
  | url = http://apod.nasa.gov/apod/ap980626.html
  | title = A Planet for Gliese 876
  | date = 26 June 1998
  | accessdate = 23 April 2012
  | work = Astronomy Picture of the Day
  | publisher = NASA
  | ref = {{sfnRef|APOD Gliese 876}}
  }}
* {{citation
  | title = Galaxy-wide Echoes from the Past
  | url = http://www.eso.org/public/news/eso1249/
  | accessdate = 7 December 2012
  | newspaper = ESO Press Release
  | ref = {{sfnRef|ESO 2012}}
  }}
* {{citation
 |ref={{sfnRef|Exoplanet Encyclopedia WASP-6}} 
 |url=http://voparis-exoplanet-new.obspm.fr/catalog/wasp-6_b/ 
 |title=Planet WASP-6 b 
 |work=The Extrasolar Planet Encyclopedia 
 |publisher=Paris Observatory 
 |accessdate=23 February 2013 
 |date=8 April 2012 
 |url-status=dead 
 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140314060600/http://voparis-exoplanet-new.obspm.fr/catalog/wasp-6_b/ 
 |archivedate=14 March 2014 
}}
* {{citation
 |url         = http://exoplanet.eu/star.php?st=Gliese+876
 |publisher   = The Extrasolar Planets Encyclopaedia
 |title       = Notes for star Gliese 876
 |accessdate  = 23 April 2012
 |ref         = {{sfnRef|Exoplanet Encyclopedia Gliese 876}}
 |url-status     = dead
 |archiveurl  = https://web.archive.org/web/20120426090935/http://exoplanet.eu/star.php?st=Gliese+876
 |archivedate = 26 April 2012

}}
* {{citation
  | url = http://exoplanet.eu/star.php?st=91+Aqr
  | title = Notes for star 91 Aqr
  | accessdate = 23 April 2012
  | publisher = The Extrasolar Planets Encyclopaedia
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Exoplanet Encyclopedia 91 Aqr}}
  }}
* {{citation
  | url = http://exoplanet.eu/star.php?st=Gj+849
  | title = Notes for star Gj 849
  | publisher = The Extrasolar Planets Encyclopaedia
  | accessdate = 23 April 2012
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Exoplanet Encyclopedia Gj 849}}
  }}
* {{citation
 |ref={{sfnRef|Exoplanet Encyclopedia HD 206610 b}} 
 |url=http://voparis-exoplanet-new.obspm.fr/catalog/hd_206610_b/ 
 |title=Planet HD 206610 b 
 |work=The Extrasolar Planet Encyclopedia 
 |publisher=Paris Observatory 
 |accessdate=21 March 2013 
 |date=19 March 2010 
 |url-status=dead 
 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140314061609/http://voparis-exoplanet-new.obspm.fr/catalog/hd_206610_b/ 
 |archivedate=14 March 2014 
}}
* {{citation
 |ref={{sfnRef|Exoplanet Encyclopedia WASP-47 b}} 
 |url=http://voparis-exoplanet-new.obspm.fr/catalog/wasp-47_b/ 
 |title=Planet WASP-47 b 
 |work=The Extrasolar Planet Encyclopedia 
 |publisher=Paris Observatory 
 |accessdate=21 March 2013 
 |date=24 April 2012 
 |url-status=dead 
 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140314061606/http://voparis-exoplanet-new.obspm.fr/catalog/wasp-47_b/ 
 |archivedate=14 March 2014 
}}
* {{citation
 |ref={{sfnRef|Exoplanet Encyclopedia HD 210277 b}} 
 |url=http://voparis-exoplanet-new.obspm.fr/catalog/hd_210277_b/ 
 |title=Planet HD 210277 b 
 |work=The Extrasolar Planet Encyclopedia 
 |publisher=Paris Observatory 
 |accessdate=22 March 2013 
 |date=6 September 2006 
 |url-status=dead 
 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140314072607/http://voparis-exoplanet-new.obspm.fr/catalog/hd_210277_b/ 
 |archivedate=14 March 2014 
}}
* * {{citation
 |ref={{sfnRef|Exoplanet Encyclopedia HD 212771 b}} 
 |url=http://voparis-exoplanet-new.obspm.fr/catalog/hd_212771_b/ 
 |title=Planet HD 212771 b 
 |work=The Extrasolar Planet Encyclopedia 
 |publisher=Paris Observatory 
 |accessdate=22 March 2013 
 |date=19 March 2010 
 |url-status=dead 
 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140314072432/http://voparis-exoplanet-new.obspm.fr/catalog/hd_212771_b/ 
 |archivedate=14 March 2014 
}}
* {{citation
 |ref={{sfnRef|Exoplanet Encyclopedia HD 215152 b}} 
 |url=http://voparis-exoplanet-new.obspm.fr/catalog/hd_215152_b/ 
 |title=Planet HD 215152 b 
 |work=The Extrasolar Planet Encyclopedia 
 |publisher=Paris Observatory 
 |accessdate=22 March 2013 
 |date=12 September 2011 
 |url-status=dead 
 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140314072429/http://voparis-exoplanet-new.obspm.fr/catalog/hd_215152_b/ 
 |archivedate=14 March 2014 
}}
* {{citation
 |ref={{sfnRef|Exoplanet Encyclopedia HD 215152 c}} 
 |url=http://voparis-exoplanet-new.obspm.fr/catalog/hd_215152_c/ 
 |title=Planet HD 215152 c 
 |work=The Extrasolar Planet Encyclopedia 
 |publisher=Paris Observatory 
 |accessdate=22 March 2013 
 |date=12 September 2011 
 |url-status=dead 
 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140314061417/http://voparis-exoplanet-new.obspm.fr/catalog/hd_215152_c/ 
 |archivedate=14 March 2014 
}}
* {{citation
  | first = David H.
  | last = Levy
  | title = Deep Sky Objects
  | publisher = Prometheus Books
  | year = 2005
  | isbn = 978-1-59102-361-6
  | ref = harv
  | url-access = registration
  | url = https://archive.org/details/deepskyobjects00davi
  }}
* {{citation
  | title = Cambridge Guide to Stars and Planets
  | last1 = Moore
  | first1 = Patrick
  | last2 = Tirion
  | first2 = Wil
  | publisher = Cambridge University Press
  | edition = 2nd
  | date = 1997
  | isbn = 978-0-521-58582-8
  | url-access = registration
  | url = https://archive.org/details/cambridgeguideto00moor
  }}
* {{citation
  | title = The Data Book of Astronomy
  | last = Moore
  | first = Patrick
  | date = 2000
  | publisher = Institute of Physics Publishing
  | isbn = 978-0-7503-0620-1
  }}
* {{citation
  | last = Ridpath
  | first = Ian
  | others = Wil Tirion
  | date = 2001
  | title = Stars and Planets Guide
  | edition = 3rd
  | publisher = Princeton University Press
  | isbn = 978-0-691-08913-3
  }}
* {{citation
  | last1 = Ridpath 
  | first1 = Ian
  | last2 = Tirion
  | first2 = Wil
  | date = 2007
  | title = Stars and Planets Guide
  | edition = 4th
  | location = Collins, London
  | isbn = 978-0691135564
  | publisher = Princeton University Press
  }}
* {{citation
  | last = Ridpath
  | first = Ian
  | title = Aquarius
  | work = Star Tales
  | url = http://www.ianridpath.com/startales/aquarius.htm
  | accessdate = 14 March 2013
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Star Tales}}
  }}
* {{citation
  | first = John H.
  | last = Rogers
  | title = Origins of the ancient constellations: I. The Mesopotamian traditions
  | journal = Journal of the British Astronomical Association
  | volume = 108
  | pages = 9
  | date = 1998
  | bibcode = 1998JBAA..108....9R
  }}
* {{citation
  | first = John H.
  | last = Rogers
  | url = http://articles.adsabs.harvard.edu/cgi-bin/nph-iarticle_query?1998JBAA..108...79R&amp;amp;data_type=PDF_HIGH&amp;amp;whole_paper=YES&amp;amp;type=PRINTER&amp;amp;filetype=.pdf
  | title = Origins of the ancient constellations: II. The Mediterranean traditions
  | journal = Journal of the British Astronomical Association
  | volume = 108
  | issue = 2
  | date = 1998
  | pages = 79–89
  | bibcode = 1998JBAA..108...79R
  }}
* {{citation
  | last1 = Sherrod
  | first1 = P. Clay
  | last2 = Koed
  | first2 = Thomas L.
  | date = 2003
  | title =  A Complete Manual of Amateur Astronomy: Tools and Techniques for Astronomical Observations
  | publisher = Courier Dover Publications
  | isbn = 9780486152165
  }}
* {{citation
  | url = http://simbad.u-strasbg.fr/simbad/sim-basic?Ident=alf+aqr
  | title = Sadalmelik
  | accessdate = 23 April 2012
  | publisher = SIMBAD
  | ref = {{sfnRef|SIMBAD Sadalmelik}}
  }}
* {{citation
  | url = http://simbad.u-strasbg.fr/simbad/sim-id?Ident=beta+aquarii&amp;NbIdent=1&amp;Radius=2&amp;Radius.unit=arcmin&amp;submit=submit+id
  | title = bet Aqr
  | accessdate = 24 April 2012
  | publisher = SIMBAD
  | ref = {{sfnRef|SIMBAD Beta Aquarii}}
  }}
* {{citation
  | url = http://simbad.u-strasbg.fr/simbad/sim-id?ident=gamma+aquarii&amp;NbIdent=1&amp;Radius=2&amp;Radius.unit=arcmin&amp;submit=submit+id
  | title = gam Aqr
  | publisher = SIMBAD
  | accessdate = 24 April 2012
  | ref = {{sfnRef|SIMBAD Gamma Aquarii}}
  }}
* {{citation
  | title = The New Patterns in the Sky: Myths and Legends of the Stars
  | last = Staal
  | first = Julius D.W.
  | publisher = The McDonald and Woodward Publishing Company
  | date = 1988
  | edition = 2nd
  | isbn = 978-0-939923-04-5
  }}
* {{citation
  | title = Illustrated Guide to Astronomical Wonders
  | last1 = Thompson
  | first1 = Robert Bruce
  | last2 = Thompson
  | first2 = Barbara Fritchman
  | publisher = O'Reilly Media
  | date = 2007
  | isbn = 978-0-596-52685-6
  }}
* {{citation
  | title = Early Astronomy
  | last = Thurston
  | first = Hugh
  | date=1996
  | publisher = Springer
  | isbn = 978-0-387-94822-5
  }}

{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons and category|Aquarius|Aquarius (constellation)}}
* [http://www.allthesky.com/constellations/aquarius/ The Deep Photographic Guide to the Constellations: Aquarius]
* [http://astrojan.eu5.org/aqua.htm The clickable Aquarius]
* [http://warburg.sas.ac.uk/vpc/VPC_search/subcats.php?cat_1=9&amp;cat_2=71&amp;cat_3=32&amp;cat_4=41&amp;cat_5=52 Warburg Institute Iconographic Database (over 300 medieval and early modern images of Aquarius)]

{{Stars of Aquarius}}
{{navconstel}}
{{Zodiac}}

{{Sky|23|00|00|-|15|00|00|10}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Aquarius (Constellation)}}
[[Category:Aquarius (constellation)| ]]
[[Category:Constellations]]
[[Category:Equatorial constellations]]
[[Category:Constellations listed by Ptolemy]]</text>
      <sha1>cez1q52mziizrszjho9etude0dq00js</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
