  <page>
    <title>Annual plant</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>777</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942701890</id>
      <parentid>942695170</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-26T08:47:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Materialscientist</username>
        <id>7852030</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/86.126.195.70|86.126.195.70]] identified as test/vandalism using [[WP:STiki|STiki]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Plant that completes its life cycle within one growing season, and then dies}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2013}}
[[Image:Doperwt rijserwt peulen Pisum sativum.jpg|right|thumb|240px|[[Pea]]s are an annual plant.]]
An '''annual plant''' is a plant that completes its [[biological life cycle|life cycle]], from [[germination]] to the production of [[seed]]s, within one [[growing season]], and then dies. The length of growing seasons and period in which they take place vary according to geographical location, and may not correspond to the four traditional seasonal divisions of the year. With respect to the traditional seasons annual plants are generally categorized into summer annuals and winter annuals. Summer annuals germinate during spring or early summer and mature by autumn of the same year. Winter annuals germinate during the autumn and mature during the spring or summer of the following calendar year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.illinoiswildflowers.info/files/line_drawings.htm|title=Definitions of Botanical Terminology|website=Illinoiswildflowers.info|accessdate=17 May 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

One seed-to-seed life cycle for an annual can occur in as little as a month in some species, though most last several months. [[Brassica rapa|Oilseed rapa]] can go from seed-to-seed in about five weeks under a bank of [[fluorescent lamp]]s. This style of growing is often used in classrooms for education. Many desert annuals are [[therophyte]]s,&lt;ref name=&quot;introduction_to_world_vegetation&quot;&gt;{{Cite book  | last1 = Collinson | first1 = A. S. | title = Introduction to world vegetation | year = 1988 | publisher = Unwin Hyman | location = London  | isbn = 978-0-04-581031-4 | pages = 23 }}&lt;/ref&gt; because their seed-to-seed life cycle is only weeks and they spend most of the year as seeds to survive dry conditions.
__TOC__

=={{anchor|Cultivation}}Cultivation==
In cultivation, many food plants are, or are grown as, annuals, including virtually all domesticated [[Cereal|grain]]s. Some [[perennial plant|perennials]] and [[biennial plant|biennials]] are grown in gardens as annuals for convenience, particularly if they are not considered [[hardiness (plants)|cold hardy]] for the local climate. [[Carrot]], [[celery]] and [[parsley]] are true biennials (divarsiya) that are usually grown as annual crops for their edible roots, petioles and leaves, respectively. [[Tomato]], [[sweet potato]] and [[bell pepper]] are tender perennials usually grown as annuals. Ornamental perennials commonly grown as annuals are [[impatiens]], [[Mirabilis (plant)|mirabilis]], [[begonia|wax begonia]], [[Antirrhinum|snapdragon]], ''[[pelargonium]]'', [[coleus]] and [[petunia]]. Examples of true annuals include [[maize|corn]], [[wheat]], [[rice]], [[lettuce]], [[pea]]s, [[watermelon]], [[bean]]s, [[zinnia]] and [[Tagetes|marigold]].

=={{anchor|Summer annuals}}Summer==
'''Summer annuals''' sprout, flower, produce seed, and die, during the warmer months of the year.

The lawn weed [[crabgrass]] is a summer annual.

==Winter{{anchor|Winter annuals}}==
'''Winter annuals''' germinate in autumn or winter, live through the winter, then bloom in winter or spring.

The plants grow and bloom during the cool season when most other plants are dormant or other annuals are in seed form waiting for warmer weather to germinate. Winter annuals die after flowering and setting seed. The seeds germinate in the autumn or winter when the soil temperature is cool.

Winter annuals typically grow low to the ground, where they are usually sheltered from the coldest nights by snow cover, and make use of warm periods in winter for growth when the snow melts. Some common winter annuals include [[Lamium amplexicaule|henbit]], [[deadnettle]], [[chickweed]], and [[winter cress]].

Winter annuals are important ecologically, as they provide vegetative cover that prevents soil erosion during winter and early spring when no other cover exists and they provide fresh vegetation for animals and birds that feed on them. Although they are often considered to be weeds in gardens, this viewpoint is not always necessary, as most of them die when the soil temperature warms up again in early to late spring when other plants are still dormant and have not yet leafed out.

Even though they do not compete directly with cultivated plants, sometimes winter annuals are considered a pest in commercial agriculture, because they can be hosts for insect pests or fungal diseases (ovary smut – Microbotryum sp) which attack crops being cultivated.  The property that they prevent the soil from drying out can also be problematic for commercial agriculture.

==Molecular genetics==
In 2008, it was discovered that the inactivation of only two genes in one species of annual plant leads to the conversion into a [[perennial plant]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|pmid=18997783|year=2008|last1=Melzer|first1=S|last2=Lens|first2=F|last3=Gennen|first3=J|last4=Vanneste|first4=S|last5=Rohde|first5=A|last6=Beeckman|first6=T|title=Flowering-time genes modulate meristem determinacy and growth form in Arabidopsis thaliana|volume=40|issue=12|pages=1489–92|doi=10.1038/ng.253|journal=Nature Genetics|url=http://www.repository.naturalis.nl/document/456722}}&lt;/ref&gt; Researchers deactivated the SOC1 and FUL genes in ''[[Arabidopsis thaliana]]'', which control flowering time. This switch established [[phenotypes]] common in perennial plants, such as wood formation.

==See also==
*{{annotated link|Biennial plant}}
*{{annotated link|Perennial plant}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|position=left|Annuals}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Annual plants| ]]
[[Category:Garden plants]]</text>
      <sha1>71ian40g1ubg7v7qyot7h24gzql4a90</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
