  <page>
    <title>Eritrean Defence Forces</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9384</id>
    <revision>
      <id>916663721</id>
      <parentid>910205816</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-09-20T00:46:00Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Monkbot</username>
        <id>20483999</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* National service */[[User:Monkbot/task 16: remove replace deprecated dead-url params|Task 16]]: replaced (2×) / removed (0×) deprecated |dead-url= and |deadurl= with |url-status=;</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2016}}
{{Infobox national military
|country            = Eritrea
| image=Flag of Eritrea.svg
| caption=     EDF
| headquarters=Asmara
| commander-in-chief= President [[Isaias Afewerki]]
| minister= General [[Sebhat Ephrem]]
| minister_title = Minister of Defence
| commander=
| active= 320,000 &lt;ref name=&quot;Conscripts&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.mg.co.za/article/2008-07-18-in-eritrea-youth-frustrated-by-long-service|title=In Eritrea, youth frustrated by long service|accessdate=1 March 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| reserve= 500,000 &lt;ref name=&quot;wri-irg&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wri-irg.org/co/rtba/eritrea.htm|title=Eritrea &amp;#124; War Resisters' International|publisher=wri-irg.org|accessdate=27 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| deployed= 0 (2014 est.)
| budget= US$ 220.1 million (2005 est.)
| percent_GDP= 20.9% (2009 est.)
 US$ 220.1 million
| founded= 1991
| current_form=
| disbanded=
| branches= [[Eritrean Army]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Eritrean Air Force]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Eritrean Navy]]                           &lt;!-- list wikilinked branch names separated by BR --&gt;
| manpower_age       = 18-40&lt;ref name=ciafactbook&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/er.html|title=CIA - World Factbook -- Eritrea|publisher=[[Central Intelligence Agency]]|date=28 October 2009|accessdate=10 November 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;(2004 est.)
| age= 17 Years Old
| available=1,985,023
| available_f=1,980,987
| fit=1,599,979
| fit_f=1,590,899
| reaching=
| conscription = 18 Months
| domestic_suppliers=
| foreign_suppliers= {{IRN}}&lt;br /&gt;{{ISR}}&lt;br /&gt;{{SAU}}&lt;br /&gt;{{EGY}}&lt;br /&gt;{{CHN}}&lt;br /&gt;{{SUD}}&lt;br /&gt;{{RUS}}&lt;br /&gt;{{IND}}&lt;br /&gt;{{flag|Belarus}}
| history= '''[[List of wars involving Eritrea|Military history of Eritrea]]
[[Eritrean War of Independence]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Hanish Islands conflict|Hanish Islands Crisis]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Eritrean–Ethiopian War]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Djiboutian–Eritrean border conflict]]&lt;br/&gt;[[2013 Eritrean Army mutiny]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Battle of Tsorona]]
| ranks=[[Military ranks of Eritrea]]
}}
The '''Eritrean Defence Forces''' military role stems from [[Eritrea]]'s strategic geographical location. It is located on the [[Red Sea]] with a foothold on the [[Bab-el-Mandeb|Straits of Bab al-Mandeb]].

==History==
Military history in [[Eritrea]] stretches back for thousands of years; during ancient times up until the current day, the society of Eritreans has dealt with war and peace. During the kingdom of [[Medri Bahri]], the military fought numerous battles against the invading forces of the Abyssinians to the south and the [[Ottoman Turks]] at the Red Sea.&lt;ref name=&quot;google&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=Eritrea: A Pawn in World Politics|author=Yohannes, O.|date=1991|publisher=University of Florida Press|isbn=9780813010441|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=sG41eDVRDnoC|page=31|accessdate=27 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 16th century the port of [[Massawa]] was used by the Ottomans to protect sea lanes from disruption, while more recently it was used by the Italians during their colonial occupation. The kingdom of Medri Bahri was dissolved and the Colony of Eritrea was founded by the Italians in 1890, shortly after the opening of the [[Suez Canal]]. When Italian troops occupied Ethiopia in 1936, Eritrean native soldiers (known as Askaris or ''Banda'', the latter denotes their &quot;betrayal&quot; and service for the enemy) supported the invading force. However, this was reversed by British and Ethiopian troops in 1941. The Eritrean infantry battalions and cavalry squadrons of the &quot;Regi Corpi Truppe Coloniali&quot; (Royal Colonial Corps) saw extensive service in the various Italian colonial territories between 1888 and 1942.

During the war for Eritrea's independence rebel movements (the [[Eritrean Liberation Front|ELF]] and the [[Eritrean People's Liberation Front|EPLF]]) used volunteers. In the final years of the struggle for independence, the EPLF ranks grew to 110,000 volunteers (some 3% of the total population).

==Manpower==
The Eritrean Defence Forces are among the largest in Africa alongside those of [[Egyptian Armed Forces|Egypt]], [[Military of Algeria|Algeria]], and [[Royal Moroccan Armed Forces|Morocco]]. The size of Eritrea's population is small, particularly when compared to its neighbors. During peacetime the military of Eritrea numbers approximately 45,000&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| last=Killion | first=Tom | title=Historical Dictionary of Eritrea |isbn= 0-8108-3437-5 | publisher=The Scarecrow Press | year=1998 }}&lt;/ref&gt; with a reserve force of approximately 250,000.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Asmara's Finest |url=http://www.africa.upenn.edu/Newsletters/HB7895_ERI.html |accessdate=4 September 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===National service===
Every able bodied man and woman is required to serve ostensibly for 18 months. In this time they receive six months of military training and the balance is spent working on national reconstruction projects. This is outlined in both the Constitution of Eritrea and Proclamation 82 issued by the [[National Assembly of Eritrea|National Assembly]] on 1995-10-23.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.child-soldiers.org/document_get.php?id=772 |title=Eritrea |accessdate=13 October 2006 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070927040220/http://www.child-soldiers.org/document_get.php?id=772 |archivedate=27 September 2007 |url-status=dead |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the period of enlistment may be extended during times of national crisis and the typical period of national service is considerably longer than the minimum. This program allegedly aims to compensate for Eritrea’s lack of capital and to reduce dependence on foreign aid, while welding together an ethnically diverse society, half Christian and half Muslim, representing nine ethnic groups.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fpif.org/briefs/vol2/v2n45eri_body.html |title=Eritrea |accessdate=19 September 2006 |last=Connell |first=Dan |date=September 1997 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20060918214106/http://www.fpif.org/briefs/vol2/v2n45eri_body.html |archivedate=18 September 2006 |url-status=dead |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Military training is given at the [[Sawa Defence Training Centre]] and [[Kiloma Military Training Centre]]. Students, both male and female, are required to attend the Sawa Training Centre to complete the final year of their secondary education, which is integrated with their military service. If a student does not attend this period of training, he or she will not be allowed to attend university - many routes to employment also require proof of military training. However, they may be able to attend a vocational training centre, or to find work in the private sector. At the end of the 1½-year national service, a conscript can elect to stay on and become a career military officer. Conscripts who elect otherwise may, in theory, return to their civilian life but will continue to be reservists. In practice, graduates of military service are often chosen for further national service according to their vocation - for example, teachers may be compulsorily seconded for several years to schools in an unfamiliar region of the country. According to the Government of Eritrea, &quot;The sole objective of the National Service program is thus to cultivate capable, hardworking, and alert individuals.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Conscripts&quot; /&gt;

Eritrean conscripts are used in non-military capacities as well. Soldiers are often used as supplemental manpower in the country's agricultural fields picking crops, though much of the harvested food is used to feed the military rather than the general population.&lt;ref&gt;ERITREAN TROOPS SENT TO HARVEST GRAIN (2008 November 3) https://wikileaks.org/plusd/cables/08ASMARA529_a.html &lt;/ref&gt;

==Branches of the EDF==
The Eritrean Defence Forces (EDF) are composed of three branches: Air Force, Army, and Navy. The Army is by far the largest, followed by the Air Force and Navy. The Commander-in-Chief of the EDF is the [[Heads of State of Eritrea|President of Eritrea]].

The Minister of Defence oversees the EDF on a day-to-day basis.

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

'''Attribution'''
*This article incorporates [[public domain]] text from [[United States Department of State|U.S. State Department]]: ''Background Notes.''

==Further reading==
*{{cite journal |first=Jason |last=Warner |title=Eritrea's military unprofessionalism and US security assistance in the Horn of Africa |journal=Small Wars &amp; Insurgencies |volume=24 |issue=4 |date=October 2013}}

==External links==
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20100201234428/http://www.acig.org/artman/publish/article_189.shtml ACIG]
* [https://archive.is/20080229193601/http://afvid.topcities.com/country/eritrea.html AFVID (Mika Golf's armored vehicles) Eritrean fighting vehicles]
* [http://www.hazegray.org/worldnav/africa/africa.htm#3 Hazegray World Navies Today - Eritrea]
*[http://digilander.libero.it/wrnzla/ Ascari: I Leoni di Eritrea/Ascari: The Lions of Eritrea.]
*[http://www.thecuttingedgenews.com/index.php?article=980&amp;pageid=37&amp;pagename=Page+One: Iran Deploys Troops, Ballistic Missiles To Eritrea]
Eritrea colonial history, Eritrean infantry and cavalry, ascari pictures/photos galleries and videos.
{{Military of Africa}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Military Of Eritrea}}
[[Category:Military of Eritrea| ]]
[[Category:Military units and formations established in 1991]]
[[Category:1991 establishments in Eritrea]]</text>
      <sha1>5ja5pc4vhl6jrka22ujqwrj050hvdqz</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
