  <page>
    <title>Politics of Egypt</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9350</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942441653</id>
      <parentid>940556053</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-24T18:21:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Leah Faith</username>
        <id>38624515</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Corrected grammar and sentence structure</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Copy edit|date=November 2019}}
{{Politics of Egypt}} 
The '''politics of Egypt''' is based on [[republicanism]], with a [[semi-presidential system]] of government. The current political system was established following the [[Egyptian Revolution of 2011]] and the resignation of [[President of Egypt|President]] [[Hosni Mubarak]]. In the current system, the President is elected for a six year term. He then can appoint up to 5% of the parliament and additionally has the power to dissolve parliament; however, the unicameral Parliament can impeach the president. The [[Parliament of Egypt]] is the oldest legislative chamber in Africa and the Middle East.

==Presidency==
{{Main article|President of Egypt}}

The President is elected for a six-year term which can be renewed once. To run for president, candidates must provide 30,001 signatures from at least 15 provinces, provide signatures from 30 members of a chamber of the legislature, or run through nomination by a party holding at least one seat in the legislature.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.egyptindependent.com/news/commission-announces-proposed-changes-egyptian-constitution|title=Commwission announces proposed changes to Egyptian Constitution|publisher=Egypt Independent|date=26 February 2011|accessdate=19 January 2014|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140201210317/http://www.egyptindependent.com/news/commission-announces-proposed-changes-egyptian-constitution|archive-date=1 February 2014|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The position was created after the [[Egyptian Revolution of 1952]], Mohammed Naguib was the first to hold the position. Prior to 2005, the Parliament chose a candidate for the Presidency and the people voted, in a referendum, whether or not they approve the proposed candidate for President. In 2005, the first presidential elections were held, with multiple candidates standing for the position, however the elections was deemed neither fair nor free. After the [[Egyptian Revolution of 2011]], a new presidential elections was held [[Egyptian presidential election, 2012|2012]], it was the first free and fair elections in Egypt's political history.{{cn|date=December 2016}} After a wave of public discontent with autocratic excesses of the [[Muslim Brotherhood]] government of President [[Mohamed Morsi]],&lt;ref name=morsi-think-again&gt;{{cite web|url=https://foreignpolicy.com/2013/01/28/think-again-the-muslim-brotherhood/|title=Think Again: The Muslim Brotherhood|publisher=Al-Monitor|date=28 January 2013|accessdate=2016-12-07|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170202110236/http://foreignpolicy.com/2013/01/28/think-again-the-muslim-brotherhood/|archive-date=2 February 2017|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; on 3 July 2013 [[Egyptian Army ranks|General]] [[Abdel Fattah el-Sisi]] announced the removal of Morsi from office. El-Sisi then was himself elected head of state in the [[Egyptian presidential election, 2014|2014 presidential election]].&lt;ref name=ao8June&gt;{{cite news|url=http://english.ahram.org.eg/News/103147.aspx|title=El-Sisi sworn in as Egypt president|date=8 June 2014|accessdate=8 June 2014|publisher=Ahram Online|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140611133848/http://english.ahram.org.eg/News/103147.aspx|archive-date=11 June 2014|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Egypt adopted the [[semi-presidential system]] in 2012 and under it the President doesn't hold extensive powers. The President can dissolve the Parliament, declare state of emergency and declare wars, but the Parliament must approve any law first. The Parliament can impeach the President after two-thirds votes in favor for [[impeachment]], and then a public referendum is held to whether or not approve the impeachment of the President.

A constitutional referendum was held in Egypt from 20–22 April 2019, with overseas voting taking place between 19 and 21 April. The proposed changes allow President Abdel Fattah el-Sisi to remain in power until 2030; under the previous version of the constitution, he would have been barred from contesting the next elections, which were due in 2022. The changes were approved by 88.83% of voters who voted, with a 44% turnout

==Legislative branch==
{{Life in Egypt}}
{{main article|History of Parliamentary life in Egypt}}
[[Parliament of Egypt|Parliament]] meets for one eight-month session each year; under special circumstances the President of the Republic can call an additional session. Even though the powers of the Parliament have increased since the 1980 Amendments of the Constitution, the Parliament continues to lack the powers to balance the extensive powers of the President.

===The House of Representatives (Magles en Nowwáb)===
The [[House of Representatives (Egypt)|House of Representatives]] is the principal legislative body. It consists of a maximum 596 representatives with 448 are directly elected through [[FPTP]] and another 120 elected through [[proportional representation]] in 4 nationwide districts while the President can appoint up to 28 .&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://en.aswatmasriya.com/news/view.aspx?id=d1c74bd4-fc9f-416d-9507-7c7585506bd4|title=Cabinet preliminarily passes law regulating electoral districts|publisher=Aswat Masriya|date=10 December 2014|accessdate=10 December 2014|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141211105347/http://en.aswatmasriya.com/news/view.aspx?id=d1c74bd4-fc9f-416d-9507-7c7585506bd4|archive-date=11 December 2014|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The House sits for a five-year term but can be dissolved earlier by the President. The Constitution reserves fifty percent of the House may force the resignation of the executive cabinet by voting a motion of censure. For this reason, the [[Prime Minister of Egypt|Prime Minister]] and his cabinet are necessarily from the dominant party or coalition in the assembly. In the case of a president and house from opposing parties, this leads to the situation known as [[cohabitation (government)|cohabitation]].

The most recent elections held in [[Egyptian parliamentary election, 2015|2015]].

===The Consultative Council (Maglis El-Shura)===
The [[Shura Council (Egypt)|Shura Council]] was the 264-member upper house of Parliament created in 1980. In the Shura Council, 176 members were directly elected and 88 members were appointed by the President of the Republic for six-year terms. One half of the Shura Council was renewed every three years.

The Shura Council's legislative powers were limited. On most matters of legislation, the People’s Assembly retained the last word in the event of a disagreement between the two houses.

The Shura Council was abolished in the [[Constitution of Egypt|2014 constitution]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=50 member constitution committee eliminates Shura Council|url=http://english.ahram.org.eg/NewsContent/1/64/87991/Egypt/Politics-/-member-constitution-committee-eliminates-Shura-Co.aspx|publisher=Ahram Online|date=1 December 2013|accessdate=19 January 2014|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160304121653/http://english.ahram.org.eg/NewsContent/1/64/87991/Egypt/Politics-/-member-constitution-committee-eliminates-Shura-Co.aspx|archive-date=4 March 2016|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Parliamentary elections===
Political parties in Egypt are numerous and exceeds 100 parties. The formation of political parties based on religion, race or gender is prohibited by the Constitution. Prior to the revolution in 2011, power was concentrated in the hands of the President of the Republic and the [[National Democratic Party (Egypt)|National Democratic Party]] which retained a [[super-majority]] in the People's Assembly.

Many [[List of political parties in Egypt|new political parties]] that mostly were fragile formed in anticipation of running candidates in the [[Egyptian parliamentary election, 2011–2012]] that was considered the first free one since the 1952 revolution. However the elected Parliament was dissolved by the constitutional court and new elections were held in [[Egyptian parliamentary election, 2015|2015]]

Below the national level, authority is exercised by and through governors and mayors appointed by the central government and by popularly elected local councils.

==Political parties and elections==
{{Main article|List of political parties in Egypt|Elections in Egypt}}
According to the [[Constitution of Egypt|Egyptian Constitution]], political parties are allowed to exist. Religious political parties are not allowed as it would not respect the [[separation of church and state|principle of non-interference of religion in politics]] and that religion has to remain in the private sphere to respect all beliefs. Also forbidden are political parties supporting militia formations or having an agenda that is contradictory to the constitution and its principles, or threatening the country's stability such as national unity between Muslim Egyptians and [[Copts|Christian Egyptians]].

As of 2015, there are more than 100 registered political parties in Egypt. The largest are the [[Free Egyptians Party]], [[New Wafd Party]], [[Conference Party]], and the [[Egyptian Social Democratic Party]].

{{Egyptian parliamentary election, 2015}}

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;'''[[2014 Egyptian presidential election]]'''&lt;/div&gt;
{|class=wikitable style=text-align:right
!colspan=2|Candidate
!Party
!Votes
!%
|-
|
|align=left|[[Abdel Fattah el-Sisi]]||align=left|[[Independent politician|Independent]]||23,780,104||96.91
|-
|style=&quot;background:green;&quot;|
|align=left|[[Hamdeen Sabahi]]||align=left|[[Egyptian Popular Current|Popular Current]]||757,511||3.09
|-
|align=left colspan=3|Invalid/blank votes||1,040,608||–
|-
|align=left colspan=3|'''Total'''||'''25,578,233'''||'''100'''
|-
|align=left colspan=3|Registered voters/turnout|| ||47.45
|-
|align=left colspan=5|Source: [http://english.ahram.org.eg/NewsContent/1/64/102841/Egypt/Politics-/BREAKING-PEC-officially-announces-AbdelFattah-ElSi.aspx Ahram Online]
|}

==Civil society==
{{See also|Emergency law in Egypt}}
[[Egyptians]] lived under emergency law from 1967 until 31 May 2012 (with one 18-month break starting in 1980).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Egypt lifts unpopular emergency law|url=http://edition.cnn.com/2012/05/31/world/africa/egypt-emergency-law/index.html|publisher=CNN|date=2 June 2012|accessdate=19 January 2014|author=CNN Wire Staff|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140202172747/http://edition.cnn.com/2012/05/31/world/africa/egypt-emergency-law/index.html|archive-date=2 February 2014|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; Emergency laws have been continuously extended every three years since 1981. These laws sharply circumscribed any non-governmental political activity: street demonstrations, non-approved political organizations, and un-registered financial donations were formally banned. Nonetheless, since 2000, these restrictions have been violated in practice. In 2003, the agenda shifted heavily towards local democratic reforms, opposition to the succession of [[Gamal Mubarak]] as president, and rejection of violence by state security forces. Groups involved in the latest wave include PCSPI, the Egyptian Movement for Change ([[Kefaya]]), and the Association for Egyptian Mothers.

Substantial peasant activism exists on a variety of issues, especially related to [[land rights]] and [[land reform]]. A major flash point was the 1997 repeal of [[Egyptian land reform|Nasser-era land reform policies]] under pressure for [[structural adjustment]]. A pole for this activity is the Land Center for Human Rights.

The [[Egyptian Revolution of 2011]], inspired by the recent revolution in [[Tunisia]], forced the resignation of President Mubarak and the Military Junta that succeeded him abrogated the Constitution and promised free and fair elections under a new one.

On August 15, 2015 President al-Sisi enacted a new Counter Terrorism Law, which [[Human Rights Watch]] claims &quot;mimics&quot; language &quot;already contained in Egypt’s decades-old Emergency Law&quot;. in article 53 the new law gives the president power to take `appropriate measures to protect the general order and security` to confront the danger of terrorism or in case of an environmental catastrophe. This includes &quot;the power to order six-month curfews or evacuations in defined areas, subject to a majority vote in parliament within seven days, or cabinet approval if parliament is not in session.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web  |title=Egypt: Counterterrorism Law Erodes Basic Rights  |url=https://www.hrw.org/news/2015/08/19/egypt-counterterrorism-law-erodes-basic-rights  |date=August 19, 2015  |website=Human Rights Watch  |accessdate=21 March 2016  |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160404000432/https://www.hrw.org/news/2015/08/19/egypt-counterterrorism-law-erodes-basic-rights  |archive-date=4 April 2016  |url-status=live  }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Political pressure==
Before the revolution, Mubarak tolerated limited political activity by the Brotherhood for his first two terms, but then moved more aggressively to block its influence. Trade unions and professional associations are officially sanctioned. In 2014, in Upper Egypt, several newspapers reported that the region of Upper Egypt wants to secede from Egypt to try to improve living standards.&lt;ref name=&quot;Is Egypt Breaking Apart?&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.iar-gwu.org/content/egypt-breaking-apart | title=Is Egypt Breaking Apart? | publisher=International Affairs Review | date=17 February 2014 | accessdate=18 February 2014 | author=Gratowski,   J. Thomas | archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140222150816/http://www.iar-gwu.org/content/egypt-breaking-apart | archive-date=22 February 2014 | url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Foreign relations==
{{main|Foreign relations of Egypt}}
The permanent headquarters for the [[League of Arab States]] (The Arab League) is located in Cairo. The Secretary General of the League has traditionally been an Egyptian. Former Egyptian Foreign Minister Ahmed Abu El Ghet is the present Secretary General of the Arab League. The Arab League moved out of Egypt to Tunis in 1978 as a protest at the peace treaty with Israel, but returned in 1989.

Egypt was the first Arab state to establish diplomatic relations with the state of Israel, after the signing of the [[Egypt–Israel Peace Treaty]] at the [[Camp David Accords (1978)|Camp David Accords]]. Egypt has a major influence amongst other Arab states, and has historically played an important role as a mediator in resolving disputes between various Arab nations, and in the Israeli–Palestinian dispute. Most Arab nations still give credence to Egypt playing that role, though its effects are often limited.

Former Egyptian Deputy Prime Minister [[Boutros Boutros-Ghali]] served as Secretary General of the United Nations from 1991 to 1996.

A territorial dispute with Sudan over an area known as the [[Hala'ib Triangle]], has meant that diplomatic relations between the two remain strained.

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

===Bibliography===
* Hatem Elliesie: [http://wikis.fu-berlin.de/download/attachments/17138089/Elliesie+Egypt.pdf ''The Rule of Law in Egypt'']. In: Matthias Koetter / Gunnar Folke Schuppert (Eds.), Understanding of the Rule of Law in various Legal Orders of the World: Working Paper Series Nr. 5 of SFB 700: Governance in Limited Areas of Statehood, Berlin 2010.
{{Refbegin}}
*{{cite book|last=Kassem|first=Maye|title=Egyptian Politics: The Dynamics of Authoritarian Rule|publisher=[[Lynne Rienner Publishers]]|year=2004|location=Boulder, Colorado|isbn=1-58826-247-2}}
{{Refend}}

==External links==
*{{dmoz|Regional/Africa/Egypt/Government|Government of Egypt}}
* [http://www.aldokkan.com/government/government.htm Comparison Between Ancient And Modern Egyptian Governments] at Aldokkan
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20080516160058/http://report.globalintegrity.org/Egypt Egypt] at ''Global Integrity Report''
* [http://documentarystorm.com/politics/a-nation-in-waiting/ Egypt: A Nation in Waiting (Al Jazeera documentary focusing on past trends in Egypt's political history and protests.)]

'''General government sites'''
* [http://www.egypt.gov.eg/ Official Egyptian Government Portal]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20040722212059/http://www.investment.gov.eg/ '''E'''gyptian '''I'''nvestment '''P'''ortal] official government site
* [http://www.sis.gov.eg/ Egypt State Information Service] official government site
* [https://web.archive.org/web/19970717103313/http://www.presidency.gov.eg/ The Egyptian Presidency]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20051124110233/http://www.parliament.gov.eg/EPA/en/Index.jsp The People Assembly of Egypt]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20050930195649/http://www.shoura.gov.eg/ Egyptian Shoura Council]

{{Egypt topics}}
{{Africa in topic|Government of}}
{{Asia topic|Government of}}
{{Politics of Africa}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Politics Of Egypt}}
[[Category:Government of Egypt| ]]
[[Category:Politics of Egypt]]</text>
      <sha1>agioy6o98pnt53rwndnge5rcojqeool</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
