  <page>
    <title>Errol Morris</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9332</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942248372</id>
      <parentid>938578025</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-23T15:08:03Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Muddymuck</username>
        <id>37838622</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Not sourced</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|American filmmaker and writer}}
{{Infobox person
| name         = Errol Morris
| image        = Errol Morris by Bridget Laudien.jpg
| imagesize    = 
| caption      = Morris in [[Morristown, New Jersey]] in 2008
| birth_name   = Errol Mark Morris
| birth_date   = {{Birth date and age|1948|2|5}} 
| birth_place  = [[Hewlett, New York]], U.S.
| residence    = [[Cambridge, Massachusetts]], U.S.
| death_date   = 
| death_place  = 
| death_cause  = 
| known        = 
| occupation   = Film director
| years_active = 1978–present 
| title        = 
| salary       = 
| spouse       = {{marriage|Julia Sheehan|1984}} 
| partner      = 
| children     = [[Hamilton Morris]]
| relations    = 
| website      = {{URL|errolmorris.com|ErrolMorris.com}}
| footnotes    = 
| employer     = 
}}

'''Errol Mark Morris''' (born February 5, 1948) is an American [[film director]] primarily of documentaries examining and investigating, among other things, authorities and eccentrics. His 1988 documentary ''[[The Thin Blue Line (1988 film)|The Thin Blue Line]]'' is cited among the best and most influential documentaries ever made. In 2003, his [[documentary]] film ''[[The Fog of War|The Fog of War: Eleven Lessons from the Life of Robert S. McNamara]]'' won the [[Academy Awards|Oscar]] for [[Academy Award for Best Documentary Feature|Best Documentary Feature]]. &lt;ref&gt;[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=g_Hn4SeunPM Documentary Short and Feature Film Oscar® Winners in 2004-Oscars on YouTube]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Biography==
===Early life===
Morris was born on February 5, 1948, and raised in a [[Jewish]] family in [[Hewlett, New York|Hewlett]], [[New York (state)|New York]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|work=[[The Jewish Daily Forward]]|date=September 21, 2012|title=Into Wilderness of Errol|first=Laurie Gwen|last=Shapiro|url=http://blogs.forward.com/the-arty-semite/163179/into-wilderness-of-errol/}}&lt;/ref&gt; He had one older brother, Noel, who was a computer programmer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|work=The New York Times|date=June 17, 2011 |title=Errol Morris: Did My Brother Invent E-Mail With Tom Van Vleck?|url=https://archive.nytimes.com/www.nytimes.com/interactive/2011/06/20/opinion/20110620-who-invented-email.html?pagewanted=all}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

After being treated for [[strabismus]] in childhood, he refused to wear an eye patch. As a consequence, he has limited sight in one eye and lacks normal stereoscopic vision.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.nytimes.com/2011/09/04/books/review/believing-is-seeing-by-errol-morris-book-review.html The New York Times]&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 10th grade, Morris attended [[The Putney School]], a boarding school in Vermont. He began playing the cello, spending a summer in [[France]] studying music under the acclaimed [[Nadia Boulanger]], who also taught Morris's future collaborator [[Philip Glass]]. Describing Morris as a teenager, Mark Singer wrote that he &quot;read with a passion the fourteen-odd [[List of Oz books|''Oz'' books]], watched a lot of television, and on a regular basis went with a doting but not quite right maiden aunt ('I guess you'd have to say that Aunt Roz was somewhat demented') to Saturday matinées, where he saw such films as ''[[This Island Earth]]'' and ''[[Creature from the Black Lagoon]]'' — horror movies that, viewed again 30 years later, still seem scary to him.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;singer1&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|title=Predilections|last=Singer|first=Mark|journal=[[The New Yorker]]|date=February 2, 1989|url=http://www.errolmorris.com/content/profile/singer_predilections.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Morris attended the [[University of Wisconsin–Madison]], graduating in 1969 with a [[Bachelor of Arts|B.A.]] in history. For a brief time Morris held small jobs, first as a cable television salesman and then as a term-paper writer. His unorthodox approach to applying for grad school included &quot;trying to get accepted at different graduate schools just by showing up on their doorstep.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;singer1&quot;/&gt; Having unsuccessfully approached both the [[University of Oxford]] and [[Harvard University]], Morris was able to talk his way into [[Princeton University]], where he began studying the history of science, a topic in which he had &quot;absolutely no background.&quot; His concentration was in the history of physics, and he was bored and unsuccessful in the prerequisite physics classes he had to take. This, together with his antagonistic relationship with his advisor [[Thomas Kuhn]] ('You won't even look through my telescope.' And his response was 'Errol, it's not a telescope, it's a kaleidoscope.')&lt;ref name=&quot;singer1&quot;/&gt; ensured that his stay at Princeton would be short.

Morris left Princeton in 1972, enrolling at [[University of California, Berkeley|Berkeley]] as a Ph.D. student in [[philosophy]]. At Berkeley, he once again found that he was not well-suited to his subject. &quot;Berkeley was just a world of [[pedant]]s. It was truly shocking. I spent two or three years in the philosophy program. I have very bad feelings about it,&quot; he later said.&lt;ref name=&quot;singer1&quot;/&gt; He became a regular at the [[Berkeley Art Museum and Pacific Film Archive|Pacific Film Archive]]. As Tom Luddy, the director of the archive at the time, later remembered: &quot;He was a [[film noir]] nut. He claimed we weren't showing the real film noir. So I challenged him to write the program notes. Then, there was his habit of sneaking into the films and denying that he was sneaking in. I told him if he was sneaking in he should at least admit he was doing it.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;singer1&quot;/&gt;

===Unfinished project on Ed Gein===
Inspired by [[Hitchcock]]'s ''[[Psycho (1960 film)|Psycho]]'', Morris visited [[Plainfield, Wisconsin]], in 1975. While in Wisconsin, he conducted multiple interviews with [[Ed Gein]], the infamous [[serial killer]] who resided at Mendota State Hospital in Madison. He later made plans with German film director [[Werner Herzog]], whom Tom Luddy had introduced to Morris, to return in the summer of 1975 to secretly open the grave of Gein's mother to test their theory that Gein himself had already dug her up. Herzog arrived on schedule, but Morris had second thoughts and was not there. Herzog did not open the grave. Morris later returned to Plainfield, this time staying for almost a year, conducting hundreds of hours of interviews. Although he had plans to either write a book or make a film (which he would call ''Digging up the Past''), Morris never completed his Ed Gein project.

In the fall of 1976, Herzog visited Plainfield again, this time to shoot part of his film ''[[Stroszek]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.austinfilm.org/2016/10/1976-flashback-werner-herzog-errol-morris-plot-to-dig-up-ed-geins-mothers-grave/ Austin Film Society 1976 Flashback: Werner Herzog and Errol Morris Plot to Dig Up Ed Gein's Mother's Grave|Austin Film Society]&lt;/ref&gt;

===First films===
Morris accepted the $2,000 from Herzog and used it to take a trip to [[Vernon, Florida]]. Vernon was nicknamed &quot;Nub City&quot; because its residents participated in a particularly gruesome form of insurance fraud in which they deliberately amputated a limb in order to collect the insurance money. Morris's second documentary would be about the town and bear its name, although it makes no mention of Vernon as &quot;Nub City&quot;, but instead explores other idiosyncrasies of the town's residents. Morris made this omission because he received death threats while doing research; the town's residents were afraid that Morris would reveal their secret.&lt;ref name=&quot;singer1&quot;/&gt;

After spending two weeks in Vernon, Morris returned to Berkeley and began working on a script for a work of fiction that he called ''Nub City''. After a few unproductive months, he happened to read a headline in the ''[[San Francisco Chronicle]]'' that read, &quot;450 Dead Pets Going To Napa Valley&quot;. Morris left for Napa Valley and began working on the film that would become his first feature, ''[[Gates of Heaven]]'', which premiered in 1978. Herzog had said he would eat his shoe if Morris completed the documentary. After the film premiered, Herzog publicly followed through on the bet by cooking and eating his shoe, which was documented in the short film ''[[Werner Herzog Eats His Shoe]]'' by [[Les Blank]].&lt;ref name=&quot;singer1&quot;/&gt;

''Gates of Heaven'' was given a limited release in the spring of 1981. Critic [[Roger Ebert]] was and remained a champion of the film, including it on his all-time top ten best films list. Morris returned to Vernon in 1979 and again in 1980, renting a house in town and conducting interviews with the town's citizens. ''[[Vernon, Florida (film)|Vernon, Florida]]'' premiered at the 1981 [[New York Film Festival]]. ''[[Newsweek]]'' called it, &quot;a film as odd and mysterious as its subjects, and quite unforgettable.&quot; The film, like ''Gates of Heaven'', suffered from poor distribution. It was released on video in 1987, and DVD in 2005.

After finishing ''Vernon, Florida'', Morris tried to get funding for a variety of projects. There was ''Road'', a story about an interstate highway in Minnesota; a project about Robert Golka, the creator of laser-induced fireballs in Utah; and the story of [[Centralia, Pennsylvania]], the coal town in which an inextinguishable subterranean fire ignited in 1962. He eventually got funding in 1983 to write a script about John and Jim Pardue, a pair of [[Missouri]] bank robbers who had killed their father and grandmother and robbed five banks. Morris's pitch went, &quot;The great bank-robbery sprees always take place at a time when something is going wrong in the country. [[Bonnie and Clyde]] were apolitical, but it's impossible to imagine them without [[the Depression]] as a back-drop. The Pardue brothers were apolitical, but it's impossible to imagine them without [[Vietnam]].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;singer1&quot;/&gt; Morris wanted [[Tom Waits]] and [[Mickey Rourke]] to play the brothers, and he wrote the script, but the project eventually failed. Morris worked on writing scripts for various other projects, including a pair of ill-fated [[Stephen King]] adaptations.

In 1984, Morris married Julia Sheehan, whom he had met in Wisconsin while researching Ed Gein and other serial killers. He would later recall an early conversation with Julia: &quot;I was talking to a mass murderer but I was thinking of you,&quot; he said, and instantly regretted it, afraid that it might not have sounded as affectionate as he had wished. But Julia was actually flattered: &quot;I thought, really, that was one of the nicest things anyone ever said to me. It was hard to go out with other guys after that.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;singer1&quot;/&gt;

===''The Thin Blue Line''===
In 1985, Morris became interested in Dr. [[James Grigson]], a psychiatrist in [[Dallas, Texas|Dallas]]. Under [[Texas]] law, the [[Capital punishment|death penalty]] can only be issued if the jury is convinced that the defendant is not only guilty, but will commit further violent crimes in the future if he is not put to death. Grigson had spent 15 years testifying for such cases, and he almost invariably gave the same damning testimony, often saying that it is &quot;one hundred per cent certain&quot; that the defendant would kill again.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://docs.newsbank.com/g/GooglePM/DM/lib00375,103386EA575FCA6A.html | title=Expert psychiatric witness was nicknamed Dr. Death | newspaper=[[The Dallas Morning News]] |date=June 14, 2004 | first= Pat| last= Gillespie| accessdate =2009-03-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; This led to Grigson being nicknamed &quot;Dr. Death&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.ccadp.org/DrDeath.htm |title=Groups Expel Psychiatrist Known for Murder Cases; Witness nicknamed 'Dr. Death' says license won't be affected by allegations |newspaper=[[The Dallas Morning News]] |date=July 26, 1995 |accessdate=2009-03-21 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090307034749/http://ccadp.org/DrDeath.htm |archivedate=2009-03-07 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Through Grigson, Morris met the subject of his next film, 36-year-old [[Randall Dale Adams]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://docs.newsbank.com/g/GooglePM/ST/lib00154,101B1DBE87233DDC.html | title=Study: State relies too much on 'killer shrinks' | newspaper=[[Fort Worth Star-Telegram]] |date=March 31, 2004| accessdate =2008-03-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Adams was serving a life sentence that had been commuted from a death sentence on a legal technicality for the 1976 murder of Robert Wood, a Dallas police officer. Adams told Morris that he had been framed, and that David Harris, who was present at the time of the murder and was the principal witness for the prosecution, had in fact killed Wood. Morris began researching the case because it related to Dr. Grigson. He was at first unconvinced of Adams's innocence. After reading the transcripts of the trial and meeting David Harris at a bar, however, Morris was no longer so sure.

At the time, Morris had been making a living as a [[private investigator]] for a well-known private detective agency that specialized in [[Wall Street]] cases. Bringing together his talents as an investigator and his obsessions with murder, narration, and epistemology, Morris went to work on the case in earnest. Unedited interviews in which the prosecution's witnesses systematically contradicted themselves were used as testimony in Adams's 1986 ''[[habeas corpus]]'' hearing to determine if he would receive a new trial. David Harris famously confessed, in a roundabout manner, to killing Wood.

Although Adams was finally found innocent after years of being processed by the legal system, the judge in the ''habeas corpus'' hearing officially stated that, &quot;much could be said about those videotape interviews, but nothing that would have any bearing on the matter before this court.&quot; Regardless, ''[[The Thin Blue Line (1988 film)|The Thin Blue Line]]'', as Morris's film would be called, was popularly accepted as the main force behind getting its subject, Randall Adams, out of prison. As Morris said of the film, &quot;''The Thin Blue Line'' is two movies grafted together. On one simple level is the question, Did he do it, or didn't he? And on another level, ''The Thin Blue Line'', properly considered, is an [[Essay#Film|essay]] on false history. A whole group of people, literally everyone, believed a version of the world that was entirely wrong, and my accidental investigation of the story provided a different version of what happened.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://bombsite.com/issues/69/articles/2258|title=BOMB Magazine — Errol Morris by Margot Livesey|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''The Thin Blue Line'' ranks among the most critically acclaimed documentaries ever made. According to a survey by ''[[The Washington Post]]'', the film made dozens of critics' top ten lists for 1988, more than any other film that year. It won the documentary of the year award from both the [[New York Film Critics Circle]] and the [[National Society of Film Critics]]. Despite its widespread acclaim, it was not nominated for an Oscar, which created a small scandal regarding the nomination practices of the Academy. The Academy cited the film's genre of &quot;non-fiction&quot;, arguing that it was not actually a documentary.

===Commercials and later films===
Although Morris has achieved fame as a documentary filmmaker, he is also an accomplished director of [[television commercial]]s. In 2002, Morris directed a series of television ads for [[Apple Computer]] as part of a popular &quot;Switch&quot; campaign. The commercials featured ex-[[Microsoft Windows|Windows]] users discussing their various bad experiences that motivated their own personal switches to Macintosh. One commercial in the series, starring Ellen Feiss, a high-schooler friend of his son [[Hamilton Morris]], became an Internet meme. Morris has directed hundreds of commercials for various companies and products, including [[Adidas]], [[American International Group|AIG]], [[Cisco Systems]], [[Citibank]], [[Kimberly-Clark]]'s [[Depend (undergarment)|Depend brand]], [[Levi's]], [[Miller High Life]], [[Nike, Inc.|Nike]], [[PBS]], [[The Quaker Oats Company]], [[Southern Comfort]], [[EA Sports]], [[Toyota]] and [[Volkswagen]]. Many of these commercials are available on his website.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.errolmorris.com/commercials.html|title=Errol Morris: Commercials|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2002, Morris was commissioned to make a short film&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.errolmorris.com/content/shortfilms/oscarmovie.html|title=Errol Morris: Short Films|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; for the [[75th Academy Awards]]. He was hired based on his advertising resume, not his career as a director of feature-length documentaries. Those interviewed ranged from [[Laura Bush]] to [[Iggy Pop]] to [[Kenneth Arrow]] to Morris's 15-year-old son Hamilton. Morris was nominated for an [[Emmy]] for this short film. He considered editing this footage into a feature-length film, focusing&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.errolmorris.com/content/aborted/projects_donald.html Errolmorris.com]&lt;/ref&gt; on [[Donald Trump]] discussing ''[[Citizen Kane]]'' (this segment was later released on the second issue of ''[[Wholphin (DVD)|Wholphin]]''). Morris went on to make a second short for the [[79th Academy Awards]] in 2007, this time interviewing the various nominees and asking them about their Oscar experiences.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BEsoSR2npes Errol Morris's Oscar Short Film: 2002 Oscars]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2003, Morris won the [[Academy Award for Best Documentary Feature|Oscar for Best Documentary]] for ''[[The Fog of War]]'', a film about the career of [[Robert S. McNamara]], the [[Secretary of Defense]] during the [[Vietnam War]] under Presidents [[John F. Kennedy]] and [[Lyndon B. Johnson]]. In the haunting opening about McNamara's relationship with U.S. General [[Curtis LeMay]] during World War II, Morris brings out complexities in the character of McNamara, which shaped McNamara's positions in the [[Cuban missile crisis]] and the Vietnam War. Like his earlier documentary, ''The Thin Blue Line,'' ''The Fog of War'' included extensive use of re-enactments, a technique which many had believed was inappropriate for documentaries prior to his Oscar win.

In July 2004, Morris directed another series of commercials in the style of the &quot;Switch&quot; ads. This campaign featured [[Republican Party (United States)|Republicans]] who voted for [[George W. Bush|Bush]] in the [[2000 United States presidential election|2000 election]] giving their personal reasons for voting for [[John Kerry|Kerry]] in 2004. Upon completing more than 50 commercials, Morris had difficulty getting them on the air. Eventually, the liberal advocacy group [[MoveOn]] [[Political action committee|PAC]] paid to air a few of the commercials. Morris also wrote an editorial&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.errolmorris.com/content/editorial/nytimes105.html|title=Errol Morris: Editorial|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; for ''[[The New York Times]]'' discussing the commercials and Kerry's losing campaign.

In late 2004, Morris directed a series of noteworthy commercials for [[Sharp Electronics]]. The commercials enigmatically depicted various scenes from what appeared to be a short narrative that climaxed with a car crashing into a swimming pool. Each commercial showed a slightly different perspective on the events, and each ended with a cryptic weblink. The weblink was to a fake webpage advertising a prize offered to anyone who could discover the secret location of some valuable urns. It was in fact an [[alternate reality game]]. The original commercials can be found on Morris's website.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.errolmorris.com/commercials/sharp.html|title=Errol Morris: Commercials|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Morris directed a series of commercials for [[Reebok]] that featured six prominent National Football League (NFL) players. The 30-second promotional videos were aired during the 2006 NFL season.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Football Calls, and Reebok Responds|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2006/07/24/business/media/24adco.html|accessdate=28 September 2013|newspaper=[[The New York Times]]|publisher=[[The New York Times Company]]|date=24 July 2006|author=Jane Levere}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2013, Morris stated that he has made around 1,000 commercials during his career.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fast&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=The controversial case of Dr. Jeffrey MacDonald|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5yd7ltZIqFs|work=[[YouTube]]|publisher=Google, Inc|accessdate=28 September 2013|author=FastTheLatestNews|format=Video upload|date=12 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Controversy====

Morris encountered controversy when he agreed to film commercials for disgraced [[meditech|medical technology]] firm [[Theranos]]. The commercials advocate the advantages of Theranos' proposed single drop blood draws, which were being operated in [[Walgreens]] wellness centers in [[California]] and [[Arizona]] and intended to launch nationwide. Theranos was later found to be a fraudulent company, and when asked about his work for the company by [[Alex Gibney]], Morris refused to discuss it at all, even off the record.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.engadget.com/2019/03/09/the-inventor-hbo-theranos/ |title=HBO’s 'The Inventor' explores how Theranos happened, but not why |last=Hardawar |first=Devindra |date=2019-03-09 |work=Engadget |access-date=2019-06-29 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a 2019 ''New Yorker'' interview, Morris reflected, &quot;To me, what really is interesting about [[Elizabeth Holmes|Elizabeth [Holmes]]]...did she really see herself as a fraud? [...] Was it calculation? I have a hard time squaring that with my own experience. Could I have been self-deceived, delusional? You betcha. I’m no different than the next guy. I’d like to think I’m a little different. But I’m still fascinated by her.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.newyorker.com/culture/the-new-yorker-interview/the-world-is-of-course-insane-errol-morris-interview|title='The World Is, of Course, Insane': An Interview with Errol Morris|last=Gross|first=Daniel A.|date=|website=The New Yorker|language=en|url-status=live|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=2020-02-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===2010–present===
In early 2010, a new Morris documentary was submitted to several film festivals, including [[Toronto International Film Festival]], [[Cannes Film Festival]], and [[Telluride Film Festival]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://arts.nationalpost.com/2010/08/04/bruce-springsteen-errol-morris-and-werner-herzog-in-3-d-as-tiff-unveils-2010-docs/|title=TIFF unveils 2010 docs: Bruce Springsteen, Errol Morris and Werner Herzog in 3D|date=4 August 2010|work=National Post|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://archive.is/20120708034453/http://arts.nationalpost.com/2010/08/04/bruce-springsteen-errol-morris-and-werner-herzog-in-3-d-as-tiff-unveils-2010-docs/|archivedate=8 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The film, titled ''[[Tabloid (film)|Tabloid]]'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.collider.com/2010/03/30/new-details-on-errol-morris-next-documentary-tabloid/|title=New Details on Errol Morris' Next Documentary, TABLOID|work=Collider}}&lt;/ref&gt; features interviews with [[Joyce McKinney]], a former [[Miss Wyoming]], who was convicted ''in absentia'' for the kidnap and indecent assault of a [[Mormon sex in chains case|Mormon missionary]] in England during 1977.

Morris has also written long-form journalism, exploring different areas of interest and published on ''The New York Times'' website.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/category/errol-morris/ |title=The New York Times |access-date=2010-08-30 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100817052951/http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/category/errol-morris/ |archive-date=2010-08-17 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; A collection of these essays, titled ''Believing is Seeing: Observations on the Mysteries of Photography,'' was published by Penguin Press on September 1, 2011. In November 2011, Morris premiered a documentary short titled &quot;The Umbrella Man&quot;—featuring [[Josiah Thompson|Josiah &quot;Tink&quot; Thompson]]—about the Kennedy assassination on ''The New York Times'' website.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=The Umbrella Man|url=https://www.nytimes.com/video/2011/11/21/opinion/100000001183275/the-umbrella-man.html|accessdate=28 September 2013|newspaper=[[The New York Times]]|publisher=[[The New York Times]]|date=21 November 2011|author=Errol Morris}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2012, Morris published his second book, ''[[A Wilderness of Error: The Trials of Jeffrey MacDonald]]'', about [[Jeffrey MacDonald]], the [[Green Berets|Green Beret]] physician convicted of killing his wife and two daughters on February 17, 1970. Morris first became interested in the case in the early 1990s and believes that MacDonald is not guilty after undertaking extensive research.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=A Jury Said Jeffrey MacDonald Killed His Wife and Kids. So Did '60 Minutes' and a Bestseller. 40 Years Later, Errol Morris Counters With 500 Pages of Awkward Questions.|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/jesse-kornbluth/a-jury-said-jeffrey-macdo_b_1852292.html|accessdate=28 September 2013|newspaper=[[The Huffington Post]]|date=4 September 2012|author=Jesse Kornbluth}}&lt;/ref&gt; Morris explained in a July 2013 interview, prior to the reopening of the case: &quot;What happened here is wrong. It's wrong to convict a man under these circumstances. And if I can help correct that, I will be a happy camper.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Fast&quot; /&gt;

==Style and legacy==
To conduct interviews, Morris invented a machine, called the '''Interrotron''', which allows Morris and his subject to talk to each other through the camera lens itself. He explains the device as follows:

{{quote|[[Teleprompters]] are used to project an image on a two-way mirror. Politicians and newscasters use them so that they can read text and look into the lens of the camera at the same time. What interests me is that nobody thought of using them for anything other than to display text: read a speech or read the news and look into the lens of the camera. I changed that. I put my face on the Teleprompter or, strictly speaking, my live video image. For the first time, I could be talking to someone, and they could be talking to me and at the same time looking directly into the lens of the camera. Now, there was no looking off slightly to the side. No more faux first person. This was the true first person.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|editor1-last=Rothman|editor1-first=William|title=Three Documentary Filmmakers: Errol Morris, Ross McElwee, Jean Rouch|date=2009|publisher=SUNY Press|location=Albany|isbn=9781438425016|pages=3–4}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Author Marsha McCreadie, in her book ''Documentary Superstars: How Today's Filmmakers Are Reinventing the Form'', had paired Morris with [[Werner Herzog]] as practitioners and visionaries in their approach in documentary filmmaking. &lt;ref&gt;[https://www.documentary.org/column/doc-stars-personality-driven-nonfiction Doc Stars: Personality-Driven Nonfiction|International Documentary Association]&lt;/ref&gt;

Morris employs the use of narrative elements within his films. These include but are not limited to: stylized lighting, musical score, and re-enactment. The use of these elements is rejected by many documentary filmmakers who followed the cinema vérité style of the previous generations. Cinema vérité is characterized by its rejection of artistic additions to documentary film. While Morris faced backlash from many of the older-era filmmakers, his style has been embraced by the younger generations of filmmakers, as the use of re-enactment is present in many contemporary documentary films.

Morris advocates the reflexive style of documentary filmmaking. In [[Bill Nichols]]'s book ''Introduction to Documentary'' he states that reflexive documentary &quot;[speaks] not only about the historical world but about the problems and issues of representing it as well.&quot; Morris uses his films not only to portray social issues and non-fiction events but also to comment on the reliability of documentary making itself.&lt;ref&gt;Nichols, Bill. Introduction to Documentary. Bloomington: IN UP, 2010. Print.&lt;/ref&gt;

His style has been spoofed in the mockumentary series ''[[Documentary Now]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EjEhCcU8jbw Documentary Now! | 5 Ways The Eye Doesn't Lie is Just Like Thin Blue Line | IFC on YouTube]&lt;/ref&gt;

Even when interviewing controversial figures, Morris does not believe in adversarial interviews:&lt;blockquote&gt;I don’t really believe in adversarial interviews. I don’t think you learn very much. You create a theater, a gladiatorial theater, which may be satisfying to an audience, but if the goal is to learn something that you don’t know, that’s not the way to go about doing it. In fact, it’s the way to destroy the possibility of ever hearing anything interesting or new.....  the most interesting and most revealing comments have come not as a result of a question at all, but having set up a situation where people actually want to talk to you, and want to reveal something to you.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://cafe.com/stay-tuned-transcript-bannon-the-f-you-presidency-with-errol-morris/|title=Stay Tuned Transcript: Bannon &amp; The F You Presidency (with Errol Morris)|date=2019-11-07|website=CAFE|language=en-US|access-date=2019-11-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Filmography==
===Feature films===
{{colbegin}}
*''[[Gates of Heaven]]'' (1978)
*''[[Vernon, Florida (film)|Vernon, Florida]]'' (1981)
*''[[The Thin Blue Line (1988 film)|The Thin Blue Line]]'' (1988)
*''[[The Dark Wind (1991 film)|The Dark Wind]]'' (1991), fiction movie
*''[[A Brief History of Time (film)|A Brief History of Time]]'' (1991)
*''[[Fast, Cheap &amp; Out of Control]]'' (1997) &lt;ref&gt;[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wFukiQOvDYs 'Fast, Cheap and Out of Control' | Critics' Picks | The New York Times via official YouTube channel]&lt;/ref&gt;
*''[[Mr. Death: The Rise and Fall of Fred A. Leuchter, Jr.]]'' (1999)
*''[[The Fog of War|The Fog of War: Eleven Lessons from the Life of Robert S. McNamara]]'' (2003)
*''[[Standard Operating Procedure (film)|Standard Operating Procedure]]'' (2008)
*''[[Tabloid (film)|Tabloid]]'' (2010)
*''[[The Act of Killing]]'' (executive producer) (2012)
*''[[The Unknown Known]]'' (2013)
*''[[The Look of Silence]]'' (executive producer) (2014)
*''Happy Father's Day'' (video) (2015)
*''[[Uncle Nick]]'' (executive producer) (2015)
*''[[The B-Side: Elsa Dorfman's Portrait Photography]]'' (2016)
*''[[National Bird (film)|National Bird]]'' (executive producer) (2016)
*''[[American Dharma]]'' (2018)
{{colend}}

===Short films===
*''Survivors'' (2008)
*''[[They Were There]]'' (Documentary short) (2011)&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XrhDaAmn5Uw IBM Centennial Film: They Were There – People who changed the way the world works] Jan 20, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;
*''El Wingador'' (Documentary short) (2012)
*''Three Short Films About Peace'' (2014)
*''Leymah Gbowee: The Dream'' (Documentary short) (2014)

===Television===
*''Errol Morris Interrotron Stories: Digging Up the Past'' (TV miniseries documentary) (1995)
*''[[First Person (2000 TV series)|First Person]]'' (TV series documentary) (17 episodes) (2000)
*''Op-Docs'' (TV series documentary trilogy)
**''The Umbrella Man'' about [[Umbrella man (JFK assassination)]] (2011)&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yznRGS9f-jI The Umbrella Man] Nov 20, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;
**''November 22, 1963'' (2013)
**''A Demon in the Freezer'' (2016)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.indiewire.com/article/errol-morris-a-demon-in-the-freezer-smallpox-documentary-20160517|title=Errol Morris' New Short Documentary 'A Demon in the Freezer' Reveals Smallpox Concerns — Watch|last=Nordine|first=Michael|date=2016-05-17|work=IndieWire|access-date=2018-08-13|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*''P.O.V.'' (executive producer) (2014–2016)
*''It's Not Crazy, It's Sports'' (TV documentary series) (2015)
**''The Subterranean Stadium'' (TV movie) (2015)
**''The Streaker'' (TV movie) (2015)
**''The Heist'' (TV movie) (2015)
**''Most Valuable Whatever'' (TV movie) (2015)
**''Chrome'' (TV movie) (2015)
**''Being Mr. Met'' (TV movie) (2015)
*''Zillow Hiram's Home'' (TV movie) (2016)
*''[[Wormwood (miniseries)|Wormwood]]'' (miniseries) (2017)

==Accolades==
{{colbegin}}
*''[[Gates of Heaven]]'' (1978) was long featured on [http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/19971109/REVIEWS08/401010320/1023 Roger Ebert's list] of the ten greatest films ever made.
*Golden Horse for Best Foreign Film at the Taiwan International Film Festival for ''The Thin Blue Line'' (1988)
*[[New York Film Critics Circle]] and the [[National Society of Film Critics]] Best Documentary for ''The Thin Blue Line'' (1988)
*Washington Post Best Film of the Year for ''The Thin Blue Line'' (1988)
*[[Edgar Award]] for Best Motion Picture, from the [[Mystery Writers of America]], for ''The Thin Blue Line'' (1989)
*[[Guggenheim Fellowship]] (1989)
*[[MacArthur Fellowship]] (1989)
*[[Emmy]] for Best Commercial for [[PBS]] commercial &quot;[http://www.errolmorris.com/commercials/pbs/pbs_photobooth.html Photobooth]&quot; (2001)
*In December 2001, the United States' [[National Film Preservation Foundation]] announced that Morris's ''The Thin Blue Line'' would be one of the 25 films selected that year for preservation in the [[National Film Registry]] at the [[Library of Congress]], bringing the total at the time to 325.
*2002 International Documentary Association list of the 20 all-time best documentaries: ''[[The Thin Blue Line (1988 film)|The Thin Blue Line]]'' (#2), ''[[Fast, Cheap &amp; Out of Control]]'' (#14)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lib.cwu.edu/media/intnationaldoc20.htm|title=International Documentary Association Top Twenty Documentaries of All-Time|publisher=Central Washington University – Brooks Library (at Archive.org)|accessdate=2 September 2011|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080213002531/http://www.lib.cwu.edu/media/intnationaldoc20.htm|archivedate=13 February 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Best Documentary of the Year awards for ''The Fog of War'' (2003): the National Board of Review, the Los Angeles Film Critics Association, the Chicago Film Critics, and the Washington D.C. Area Film Critics.
*In 2003, ''[[The Guardian]]'' put him seventh in its list of the world's 40 best active directors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://film.guardian.co.uk/features/page/0,11456,1082823,00.html|work=[[The Guardian]]|location=London|title=40 Best Directors|accessdate=May 2, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Academy Award for Documentary Feature]] ''[[The Fog of War]]'' (2004)
*Fellow of the [[American Academy of Arts and Sciences]] (2007)&lt;ref name=AAAS&gt;{{cite web|title=Book of Members, 1780–2010: Chapter B|url=http://www.amacad.org/publications/BookofMembers/ChapterB.pdf|publisher=[[American Academy of Arts and Sciences]]|accessdate=June 3, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Jury Grand Prix Silver Bear at the 2008 [[Berlin International Film Festival]] for ''[[Standard Operating Procedure (film)|Standard Operating Procedure]]''
*Columbia Journalism Award (2013)
*In 2019, ''[[The Fog of War]]'' was selected by the [[Library of Congress]] for preservation in the [[National Film Registry]] for being &quot;culturally, historically, or aesthetically significant&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chow&quot;&gt;{{cite magazine |last=Chow |first=Andrew R. |date=December 11, 2019 |title=See the 25 New Additions to the National Film Registry, From Purple Rain to Clerks |url= https://time.com/5747503/national-film-registry-2019-additions/ |magazine=Time |location=New York, NY |access-date=December 11, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{colend}}

===Honorary degrees===
*[[Middlebury College]], Hon. D.F.A. (2010)
*[[Brandeis University]], Hon. D.H.L. (2011)
*[[University of Wisconsin–Madison]], Hon. D.H.L. (2013)

==Bibliography==
{{Expand list|date=May 2016}}

===Books===
*{{cite book|author=Morris, Errol|first=|authormask=|title=Believing Is Seeing: Observations on the Mysteries of Photography|location=New York|pages=|publisher=[[Penguin Press]]|year=2011|isbn=|&lt;!--isbn=1594203016--&gt;}}
*''[[A Wilderness of Error: The Trials of Jeffrey MacDonald]]'' (Penguin Press, 4 September 2012)
*''[[The Ashtray (Or the Man Who Denied Reality)]]'' (University of Chicago Press, 2018)

===Articles===
*{{cite journal|author=Morris, Errol|authormask=|date=April 20, 2015|title=What photography can't prove|department=United States. Crime|journal=Time|edition=South Pacific|volume=185|issue=14|pages=23}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{wikiquote}}
*{{official website|http://www.errolmorris.com/}}
*{{IMDb name|1554|Errol Morris}}
*{{Charlie Rose view|1390}}
*[http://7thavenueproject.com/post/29494340948/errol-morris-confidential-part1 Errol Morris discusses his career on the 7th Avenue Project radio show]
*{{worldcat id|lccn-no94-30802}}
*{{NYTtopic|people/m/errol_morris}}
*{{Rotten Tomatoes person|errol_morris}}
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20110715031043/http://www.allrovi.com/name/errol-morris-p103562 Errol Morris] ([[Jonathan Crow]], [[Allmovie]])
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20060922114812/http://www.greencine.com/article?action=view&amp;articleID=81 Errol Morris] (Nina Rehfeld, [[GreenCine]])
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20071226115908/http://www.ushmm.org/museum/exhibit/focus/antisemitism/voices/transcript/?content=20070816 ''Voices on Antisemitism'' Interview with Errol Morris] from the [[United States Holocaust Memorial Museum]]
*[http://www.believermag.com/issues/200803/?read=interview_herzog Werner Herzog in conversation with Errol Morris] (''[[The Believer (magazine)|The Believer]]'')
*[http://www.democracynow.org/2014/3/27/the_unknown_known_errol_morris_new The Unknown Known: Errol Morris's New Doc Tackles Unrepentant Iraq War Architect Donald Rumsfeld], a video interview on [[Democracy Now!]]
*[https://cafe.com/bannon-the-f-you-presidency-with-errol-morris/ Bannon &amp; The F You Presidency (with Errol Morris)]  (Stay Tuned with Preet)

{{Errol Morris|state=autocollapse}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Morris, Errol}}
[[Category:1948 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:American documentary film directors]]
[[Category:American people with disabilities]]
[[Category:American Jews]]
[[Category:Apple Inc. advertising]]
[[Category:Directors of Best Documentary Feature Academy Award winners]]
[[Category:Edgar Award winners]]
[[Category:Fellows of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences]]
[[Category:MacArthur Fellows]]
[[Category:New York (state) Democrats]]
[[Category:People from Hewlett, New York]]
[[Category:Pupils of Nadia Boulanger]]
[[Category:The Putney School alumni]]
[[Category:San Francisco Art Institute alumni]]
[[Category:Time (magazine) people]]
[[Category:University of Wisconsin–Madison alumni]]</text>
      <sha1>0jjbka93qmxjlbqzjp6w3t4mfyc9uaq</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
