  <page>
    <title>Demographics of Eritrea</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9379</id>
    <revision>
      <id>940764556</id>
      <parentid>940459377</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-14T13:36:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Toby Mitches</username>
        <id>36409754</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Fixed Religion</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{See also|Habesha peoples}}
{{Infobox ethnic group
| group = Eritreans
| native_name = 
| native_name_lang = 
| languages = [[Languages of Eritrea]]
| religions = Predominantly: [[Oriental Orthodox Christianity]] ([[Eritrean Orthodox Tewahedo Church|Eritrean Orthodoxy]]) [[P'ent'ay|P'ent'ay (Ethiopian-Eritrean Evangelicalism)]]/[[Protestantism in Eritrea]] ([[Christianity]])&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Trimingham|first1=J.|title=Islam in Ethiopia|date=2013|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-1136970221|page=23|url=https://www.google.com/books?id=UfrcAAAAQBAJ|accessdate=19 September 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; minority: [[Islam]] ([[Sunni Islam|Sunni]]), · [[Eritrean Catholic Church|Eritrean Catholicism]] · [[Judaism]] .
| related_groups = listed below
| popplace = {{flagcountry|Eritrea}}
| flag = File:Flag of Eritrea.svg
}}
[[Eritrea]] has an estimated population of {{UN_Population|Eritrea}}{{UN_Population|ref}} as of {{UN_Population|Year}}. No reliable census data is available, the best available estimates being published by the Population Division of the [[United Nations Department of Economic and Social Affairs]].
The population has doubled over the past 30 years, with an accelerating growth rate estimated at close to 3.2% p.a. during 2005&amp;ndash;2010. This rate of population growth is sustained despite a high [[emigration rate]]; the [[World Bank]] as of 2010 estimated that close to a million of Eritreans have emigrated.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.worldbank.org/prospects/migrationandremittances Bilateral Estimates of Migrant Stocks in 2010] estimates 942,000 emigrants, of whom 450,000 migrated to [[Sudan]] and 290,000 to [[Ethiopia]]. C.f. the World' Bank's [http://siteresources.worldbank.org/INTLAC/Resources/Factbook2011-Ebook.pdf Migration and Remittances Factbook 2011].&lt;/ref&gt;

The nation has nine recognized ethnic groups.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ciaethn&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/fields/2075.html#er|title=The World Factbook|publisher=|accessdate=31 May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to [[SIL Ethnologue]], Tigriniya make up about 60% of the population; the Tigre people make up about 30% of population, who also speak a [[Semitic languages|Semitic]] language, constitute around 30% of residents. Most of the rest of the population belong to other [[Afroasiatic languages|Afro-Asiatic]]-speaking communities of the [[Cushitic languages|Cushitic]] branch. Additionally, there are a number of [[Nilo-Saharan languages|Nilo-Saharan]]-speaking ethnic minorities and other smaller groups.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ciaethn&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Minahan&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Minahan|first=James|title=Miniature empires: a historical dictionary of the newly independent states|year=1998|publisher=Greenwood Publishing Group|isbn=0-313-30610-9|pages=76|url=https://www.google.com/books?id=RSxt-JB-PDkC&amp;pg=PA76#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|quote=&quot;The majority of the Eritreans speak Semitic or Cushitic languages of the Afro-Asiatic language group. The Kunama, Baria, and other smaller groups in the north and northwest speak Nilotic languages.&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 
A majority of Eritrea's population adheres to [[Abrahamic religions]]. The two most followed religions are [[Christianity]] and [[Islam]], which have an almost equal number of followers.

==Ethno-linguistic groups==
{{further|Languages of Eritrea}}
[[File:Ethno-Demography of Eritrea.png|thumb|400px|Ethno-Demography of Eritrea]]
Eritrea's population comprises nine recognized [[ethnic group]]s, most of whom speak languages from the [[Ethiopian Semitic languages|Ethiopian Semitic]] branch of the [[Afroasiatic languages|Afro-Asiatic]] family.&lt;ref name=&quot;Minahan&quot;/&gt; The East African Semitic languages spoken in Eritrea are [[Tigre language|Tigre]], [[Tigrinya language|Tigrinya]], and the newly recognized [[Dahlik language|Dahlik]]. Other Afro-Asiatic languages belonging to the [[Cushitic languages|Cushitic]] branch are also widely spoken in the country.&lt;ref name=&quot;Minahan&quot;/&gt; The latter include [[Afar language|Afar]], [[Beja language|Beja]], [[Blin language|Blin]], and [[Saho language|Saho]].

In addition, languages belonging to the [[Nilo-Saharan languages|Nilo-Saharan]] language family ([[Kunama language|Kunama]] and [[Nara language|Nara]]) are spoken as a [[mother tongue]] by the Kunama and Nara Nilotic ethnic minorities that live in the north and northwestern part of the country.&lt;ref name=&quot;Minahan&quot;/&gt; The [[Rashaida people|Rashaida]] speak [[Arabic language|Arabic]], while there are also a number of [[Italian people|Italians]] who speak their native [[Italian language]].

===Afro-Asiatic communities===

====Semitic speakers====

=====Tigrinya=====
{{main|Tigrigna}}
[[File:Traditional Eritrean dance.jpg|thumb|A [[Tigrinyas|Tigrigna]] traditional dance.]]
The majority of the Tigrinya inhabit the highlands of Eritrea; however, migration to other parts of the country has occurred. Their language is called [[Tigrinya language|Tigrinya]]. They are the largest ethnic group in the country, constituting about 60% of the population.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ciaethn&quot;/&gt; The predominantly Tigrinya populated urban centers in Eritrea are the capital [[Asmara]], [[Mendefera]], [[Dekemhare]], [[Adi Keyh]], [[Adi Quala]] and [[Senafe]], while there is a significant population of Tigrinya in other cities including [[Keren, Eritrea|Keren]], and [[Massawa]].

The [[Jeberti people]] in Eritrea trace descent from early Muslim adherents. The term ''Jeberti'' is also locally sometimes used to generically refer to all Islamic inhabitants of the [[Ethiopian Highlands|highlands]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Lhrfda&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|first=Abbebe|last=Kifleyesus|journal=L'Homme: revue française d'anthropologie|url=http://www.cairn.info/revue-l-homme-2009-1-page-49.htm|title=Jeberti Women Traders' Innumeracy: Its Impact on Commercial Activity in Eritrea|date=January 2009|issue=189|page=59|accessdate=27 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Jeberti in Eritrea speak [[Arabic language|Arabic]] and [[Tigrinya language|Tigrinya]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Eotpoaatme&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Facts On File, Incorporated|title=Encyclopedia of the Peoples of Africa and the Middle East|year=2009|publisher=Infobase Publishing|isbn=143812676X|page=336|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=stl97FdyRswC}}&lt;/ref&gt; They account for about 4% of the Tigrinya speakers in the nation. The remaining 96% are Christians, so divided: 90% of the [[Eritrean Orthodox]] faith, 5%[Roman Catholic]] and [[Eastern Catholic]] (whose mass is held in [[Ge'ez]] as opposed to Latin), and 5% belonging to various [[Protestant]] and other Christian denominations, the majority of which belong to the (Lutheran) Evangelical Church of Eritrea.

=====Tigre=====
{{main|Tigre people}}

The Tigre reside in the western lowlands in Eritrea. Many also migrated to Sudan at the time of the Ethiopian-Eritrean conflict and lived there since. They are a nomadic and pastoralist people, related to the [[Tigrinya]] and to the [[Beja people]]. They are a predominantly Muslim nomadic people who inhabit the northern, western, and coastal lowlands of Eritrea, where they constitute 30% of local residents.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ciaethn&quot;/&gt; Some also inhabit areas in eastern Sudan. 95% of the Tigre people adhere to the Islamic religion [[Sunni Islam]], but there are a small number of Christians among them as well (often referred to as the Mensaï in Eritrea). Their language is called [[Tigre language|Tigre]].

=====Rashaida=====
{{main|Rashaida people}}
The Rashaida are one of Eritrea's nine recognized ethnic groups. They represent around 2% of the population of Eritrea.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ciaethn&quot;/&gt; The Rashaida reside in the northern coastal lowlands of Eritrea and the northern eastern coasts of Sudan. They are predominantly Muslim and are the only ethnic group in Eritrea to have [[Arabic language|Arabic]] as their communal language, specifically the [[Hejazi Arabic|Hejazi dialect]]. The Rashaida first came to Eritrea in the 19th century from the Arabian Coast.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Alders|first=Anne|url=http://www.eritreanbeauty.com/r.html|title=the Rashaida|accessdate=2006-06-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Cushitic speakers====

=====Afar=====
{{main|Afar people}}
According to the CIA, the Afar constitute under 5% of the nation's population.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ciaethn&quot;/&gt; They live in the [[Debubawi Keyih Bahri Region]] of Eritrea, as well as the [[Afar Region]] in Ethiopia, and [[Djibouti]]. They speak the [[Afar language]] as a mother tongue, and are predominantly Muslim. Afars in Eritrea number about 397,000 individuals, the smallest population out of the countries they reside in. In Djibouti, there are about 780,000 group members, and in Ethiopia, they number approximately 1,300,000.

=====Saho=====
{{main|Saho people}}
[[File:Eritrean Women.jpeg|right|thumb|[[Saho people|Saho]] women in traditional attire.]]
The Saho represent 4% of Eritrea's population.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ciaethn&quot;/&gt; They principally reside in the [[Debubawi Keyih Bahri Region]] and the [[Northern Red Sea Region]] of Eritrea. Their language is called [[Saho language|Saho]]. They are predominantly Muslim, although a few Christians known as the [[Irob people|Irob]] live in the [[Debub Region]] of Eritrea and the [[Tigray region]] of Ethiopia.

=====Bilen=====
{{main|Bilen people}}
The Bilen in Eritrea represent around 2% of the country's population.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ciaethn&quot;/&gt; They are primarily concentrated in the north-central areas, in and around the city of [[Keren, Eritrea|Keren]], and south towards [[Asmara]], the nation's capital. Many of them entered Eritrea from Kush (central Sudan) in the 8th century and settled at Merara, after which they went to Lalibela and Lasta. The Bilen then returned to Axum in Ethiopia's [[Tigray Province]], and battled with the natives; in the resulting aftermath, the Bilen returned to their main base at Merara. The Bilen include adherents of both [[Islam]] and [[Christianity]]. They speak the [[Bilen language|Bilen]] as a mother tongue. Christian adherents are mainly urban and have intermingled with the Tigrinya who live in the area. Muslim adherents are mainly rural and have interbred with the adjacent Tigre.

=====Beja=====
{{main|Beja people}}
The Beja in Eritrea, or [[Hedareb]], constitute under 5% of local residents.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ciaethn&quot;/&gt; They mainly live along the north-western border with Sudan. Group members are predominantly Muslim and communicate in [[Hedareb language|Hedareb]] as a first or second language. The Beja also include the [[Beni-Amer people]], who have retained their native [[Beja language]] alongside Hedareb.

===Nilo-Saharan communities===

====Kunama====

{{main|Kunama people}}
According to the CIA, the Kunama constitute around 2% of Eritrea's population.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ciaethn&quot;/&gt; They mainly live in the country's [[Gash Barka Region]], as well as in adjacent parts of Ethiopia's [[Tigray Region]]. Many of them reside in the contested border village of [[Badme]]. Their language is called [[Kunama language|Kunama]]. Although some Kunama still practice traditional beliefs, most are converts to either Christianity (Roman Catholic and Protestant) or Islam.

====Nara====
{{main|Nara people}}
The Nara represent under 5% of the nation's population.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ciaethn&quot;/&gt; They principally reside along the south-western border with Sudan and Ethiopia. They are generally Muslim, with a few Christians and some practising their indigenous beliefs. Their language is called [[Nara language|Nara]].

===Other communities===

====Italians====
{{main|Italian Eritreans}}
A few monolingual [[Italian Eritreans]] remain. As of 2008, they were estimated at 900 people, down from around 38,000 residents at the end of World War II.

==Religion==
{{Main|Religion in Eritrea}}
{{bar box
|titlebar=#ddd
|title='''Eritrea religious groups'''&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;U.S Department of State 2011&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;webcitation.org&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://2009-2017.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/2854.htm |title=Eritrea |publisher=U.S. State Department |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|left1=religion
|right1=percent
|float=right
|bars=
{{bar percent|[[Christianity]]|purple|55}}
{{bar percent|[[Islam]]|yellow|43}}
{{bar percent|Others|brown|2}}
}}
&lt;imagemap&gt; 
File:Regions of Eritrea.svg|thumb|Regions of Eritrea 1. Maekel 2. Anseba 3. Gash-Barka 4. Debub 5. Northern Red Sea 6. Southern Red Sea
poly 167 182  163 205  179 211  184 203  176 179 [[Maekel Region]]
poly 167 182  176 179  118 108  118  50   59  85   53 133 [[Anseba Region]]
poly 163 205  167 182   53 133   19 258   91 276  135 239  147 206 [[Gash-Barka Region]]
poly 184 203  179 211  147 206  135 239  153 254  221 248  225 226  189 200 [[Debub Region]]
poly 176 179  184 203  189 200  225 226  221 248  271 259  279 220  200 159  155  21  118  50  118 108 [[Northern Red Sea Region]]
poly 279 220  271 259  419 388  442 361  319 241 [[Southern Red Sea Region]]
&lt;/imagemap&gt;
People in Eritrea practice various religions. According to the [[Pew Research Center]] (2010), 62.9% of the population are [[Christianity|Christian]], mostly followers of [[Oriental Orthodoxy]], and to a lesser extent, [[Roman Catholicism]], with the second-largest denomination being [[Muslims]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://features.pewforum.org/global-christianity/total-population-percentage.php|title=Table: Christian Population as Percentages of Total Population by Country|date=19 December 2011|work=Pew Research Center's Religion &amp; Public Life Project|accessdate=31 May 2015|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120107191939/http://features.pewforum.org/global-christianity/total-population-percentage.php|archivedate=7 January 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In general, most local residents who adhere to [[Christianity]] live in the [[Maekel Region|Maekel]] and [[Debub Region|Debub]] regions, whereas those who follow [[Islam]] predominantly inhabit the [[Anseba Region|Anseba]], [[Northern Red Sea Region|Northern Red Sea]], [[Southern Red Sea Region|Southern Red Sea]] and [[Gash-Barka Region|Gash-Barka]] regions. A few adherents of [[Traditional African religion|traditional faiths]] can also be found, particularly in the lowlands.
&lt;center&gt;
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|-
! Region
! align=center colspan=1| '''Population'''
! align=center colspan=1| '''Christians'''60%
! align=center colspan=1| '''Muslims 40%'''
! align=center colspan=1| '''Other'''1%
|-
| [[Maekel Region]], ''ዞባ ማእከል''
| 1,053,254
| 97%
| 3%
| 1%
|-
| [[Debub region ]], ''ዞባ ደቡብ''
| 1,476,765
| 96%
| 3%
| &lt;1%
|-
| [[Gash-Barka Region]], ''ዞባ ጋሽ ባርካ''
| 1,103,742
| 9%
| 90%
| 1%
|-
| [[Anseba Region]], ''ዞባ ዓንሰባ''
| 893,587
| 27%
| 72%
| &lt;1%
|-
| [[Northern Red Sea Region]],&lt;br&gt;''Semienawi Keyih Bahri ዞባ ሰሜናዊ ቀይሕ ባሕሪ''
| 897,454
| 1%
| 99%
| 0%
|-
| [[Southern Red Sea Region]],&lt;br&gt;''Debubawi Keyih Bahri ዞባ ደቡባዊ ቀይሕ ባሕሪ''
| 398,073
| 23%
| 76%
| &lt;1%
|-
|}
&lt;/center&gt;

==Population==
According to {{UN_Population|source}}, the total population of Eritrea was at {{UN_Population|Eritrea}} in {{UN_Population|Year}} (compared to 3.27 million in 1990).
Population growth rate during 2005&amp;ndash;2010 was estimated at 3.2% p.a.

In the 2010s, worsening conditions have fuelled migration pressure, with Eritreans trying to reach Europe illegally in boats reaching desperate proportions in 2013.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.economist.com/news/middle-east-and-africa/21587844-eritreans-are-taking-seas-because-worsening-conditions-home-why-they Why they leave --  Eritreans are taking to the seas because of worsening conditions at home] 12 October 2013. 
&quot;Some 30,000 people reached Italy illegally in boats in the first nine months of 2013, three times as many as in the whole of 2012, according to [[Frontex]], [...] the largest batch came from Eritrea, a country that has supposedly been at peace for the past 13 years.&quot;
[http://www.catholicherald.co.uk/news/2014/06/12/emigration-has-left-eritrea-desolate-say-bishops/ Emigration has left Eritrea ‘desolate’, say bishops]&quot;, ''Catholic Herald'', 6 September 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

The proportion of children below the age of 15 in 2010 was 41.6%, 55.9% was between 15 and 65 years of age, while 2.5% was 65 years or older.&lt;ref name=&quot;WPP 2010&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://esa.un.org/unpd/wpp/index.htm|title=World Population Prospects, the 2012 Revision|publisher=|accessdate=31 May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align: right;&quot;
|-
!
! width=&quot;80pt&quot;|Total population
! width=&quot;80pt&quot;|Population aged 0–14 (%)
! width=&quot;80pt&quot;|Population aged 15–64 (%)
! width=&quot;80pt&quot;|Population aged 65+ (%)
|-
| 1950
|1 141 000||45.3||51.5||3.2
|-
| 1955
|1 264 000||44.9||52.1||3.0
|-
| 1960
|1 424 000||44.8||52.5||2.8
|-
| 1965
|1 619 000||44.7||52.7||2.6
|-
| 1970
|1 847 000||45.3||52.2||2.5
|-
| 1975
|2 115 000||45.4||52.1||2.5
|-
| 1980
|2 469 000||47.1||49.1||3.8
|-
| 1985
|2 806 000||47.8||49.2||3.0
|-
| 1990
|3 158 000||46.3||51.1||2.6
|-
| 1995
|3 213 000||47.0||50.5||2.5
|-
| 2000
|3 668 000||44.9||52.7||2.4
|-
| 2005
|4 486 000||42.0||55.7||2.4
|-
| 2010
|5 254 000||41.6||55.9||2.5
|}

UN medium variant population projections as of 2010 expected a radically reduced growth rate of 2.0% during the 2020s and of 1.8% during the 2030s.&lt;ref name=&quot;WPP 2010&quot;/&gt;
This was corrected as too optimistic an outlook in the 2012 edition, which now expected a more pessimistic, but still declining growth rate of 2.7% during the 2020s (10.3 million in 2030) and of 2.4% during the 2030s (13 million in 2040).&lt;ref&gt;Based on an a-priori assumption of worldwide &quot;convergence towards low fertility&quot;. &quot;World Population Prospects: The 2012 Revision&quot;[http://esa.un.org/unpd/wpp/index.htm], &quot;[http://esa.un.org/unpd/wpp/Documentation/pdf/WPP2012_Methodology.pdf Methodology]&quot;, p. 15: 
&quot;The 2012 Revision drew on new empirical evidence on fertility levels and trends that became available since the publication of the 2010 Revision. The empirical evidence from available surveys and the 2010 round of censuses has provided the basis for a reassessment of fertility levels and trends experienced within the last decade. In a number of countries, particularly in Africa, slower than
expected fertility declines or even stalled fertility was observed. In some cases, increases in total fertility were also recorded. This led to the decision not to apply the additional adjustment that was used in the 2010 Revision for a small number of countries at the very early stage of their fertility transition (for example, Mali, Niger, Nigeria, and Somalia) or that had experienced recent fertility stalling (for example, Congo, Gabon, Kenya, Malawi, Mozambique, Rwanda, Sao Tome and Principe, United Republic of Tanzania, Zambia, and Zimbabwe). For these countries, the recent fertility decline has been much slower than typically experienced in the past decades by other countries at similar levels of fertility, and the additional adjustment would have delayed any potential future decline, implying even more population growth than already anticipated with the standard assumption.&quot;
&lt;/ref&gt;

==Vital statistics==
Registration of vital events in Eritrea is incomplete. The Population Department of the United Nations prepared the following estimates:&lt;ref name=&quot;WPP 2010&quot;/&gt;
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align: right;&quot;
|-
! width=&quot;70pt&quot;|Period
! width=&quot;70pt&quot;|Live births per year
! width=&quot;70pt&quot;|Deaths per year
! width=&quot;70pt&quot;|Natural change per year
! width=&quot;70pt&quot;|CBR*
! width=&quot;70pt&quot;|CDR*
! width=&quot;70pt&quot;|NC*
! width=&quot;70pt&quot;|TFR*
! width=&quot;70pt&quot;|IMR*
|-
| 1950-1955 || 58 000|| 34 000|| 24 000||48.4||28.0||20.4||6.97||176
|-
| 1955-1960 || 66 000|| 35 000|| 31 000||49.2||25.7||23.4||6.97||163
|-
| 1960-1965 || 74 000|| 36 000|| 38 000||48.5||23.6||24.9||6.82||151
|-
| 1965-1970 || 83 000|| 38 000|| 45 000||47.6||21.7||25.9||6.70||139
|-
| 1970-1975 || 91 000|| 39 000|| 52 000||46.1||19.7||26.3||6.52||133
|-
| 1975-1980 || 103 000|| 43 000|| 60 000||45.1||18.9||26.2||6.50||127
|-
| 1980-1985 || 112 000|| 54 000|| 58 000||42.4||20.5||21.9||6.50||116
|-
| 1985-1990 || 123 000|| 52 000|| 71 000||41.1||17.3||23.9||6.31||104
|-
| 1990-1995 || 127 000|| 45 000|| 83 000||40.0||14.1||25.9||6.08||90
|-
| 1995-2000 || 131 000|| 38 000|| 93 000||38.1||11.1||27.0||5.66||73
|-
| 2000-2005 || 157 000|| 39 000|| 118 000||38.4||9.5||28.9||5.19||62
|-
| 2005-2010 || 183 000|| 40 000|| 143 000||37.5||8.3||29.3||4.68||54
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot; colspan=&quot;9&quot; | * &lt;small&gt; CBR = crude birth rate (per 1000); CDR = crude death rate (per 1000); NC = natural change (per 1000); IMR = infant mortality rate per 1000 births; TFR = total fertility rate (number of children per woman)&lt;/small&gt;
|}

===Fertility and Births===
Total Fertility Rate (TFR) (Wanted Fertility Rate) and Crude Birth Rate (CBR):&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://microdata.worldbank.org/index.php/catalog/dhs#_r=&amp;collection=&amp;country=&amp;dtype=&amp;from=1890&amp;page=5&amp;ps=&amp;sk=&amp;sort_by=nation&amp;sort_order=&amp;to=2014&amp;topic=&amp;view=s&amp;vk=|title=MEASURE DHS: Demographic and Health Surveys|publisher=|accessdate=31 May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;width:50pt;&quot;| Year
! style=&quot;width:50pt;&quot;| Total CBR
! style=&quot;width:50pt;&quot;| Total TFR
! style=&quot;width:51pt;&quot;| Urban CBR
! style=&quot;width:50pt;&quot;| Urban TFR
! style=&quot;width:50pt;&quot;| Rural CBR
! style=&quot;width:50pt;&quot;| Rural TFR
|-
| 1995
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;| 37,5
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;| 6,10 (5,7)
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;| 29,3
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;| 4,23 (3,8)
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;| 40,3
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;| 6,99 (6,5)
|-
| 2002
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;| 32
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;| 4,8 (4,4)
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;| 28
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;| 3,5 (3,1)
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;| 35
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;| 5,7 (5,3)
|-
|}

Fertility data as of 2002 (DHS Program):&lt;ref&gt;http://dhsprogram.com/pubs/pdf/FR137/FR137.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;width:100pt;&quot;| Zoba
! style=&quot;width:100pt;&quot;| Total fertility rate
! style=&quot;width:100pt;&quot;| Percentage of women age 15-49 currently pregnant
! style=&quot;width:100pt;&quot;| Mean number of children ever born to women age 40-49
|-
| Debubawi Keih Bahri || 3.9 || 8.9 || 5.1
|-
| Maekel || 3.4 || 7.1 || 4.8
|-
| Semenawi Keih Bahri || 4.5 || 8.9 || 5.8
|-
| Anseba || 5.6 || 8.8 || 6.3
|-
| Gash-Barka || 5.1 || 10.2 || 6.3
|-
| Debub || 5.7 || 9.5 || 6.6
|}

=== Life expectancy ===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;
!Period
!Life expectancy in &lt;br /&gt; Years&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://esa.un.org/unpd/wpp/DataQuery/|title=World Population Prospects - Population Division - United Nations|website=esa.un.org|access-date=2018-08-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|1950–1955
|34.08
|-
|1955–1960
|{{increase}} 36.68 
|-
|1960–1965
|{{increase}} 40.08 
|-
|1965–1970
|{{increase}} 42.15
|-
|1970–1975
|{{increase}} 44.11
|-
|1975–1980
|{{increase}} 45.91
|-
|1980–1985
|{{increase}} 47.33
|-
|1985–1990
|{{increase}} 48.68
|-
|1990–1995
|{{increase}} 50.77
|-
|1995–2000
|{{increase}} 53.96
|-
|2000–2005
|{{increase}} 56.68
|-
|2005–2010
|{{increase}} 60.70
|-
|2010–2015
|{{increase}} 63.42
|}

==Demographic statistics==
Demographic statistics according to the World Population Review in 2019.&lt;ref name=&quot;WPR 2019&quot;&gt;{{cite|url=http://worldpopulationreview.com/countries/eritrea-population/|title=Eritrea Population 2019|website=World Population Review}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*One birth every 3 minutes	
*One death every 16 minutes	
*One net migrant every 55 minutes	
*Net gain of one person every 4 minutes

The following demographic statistics are from the [[CIA World Factbook]].&lt;ref name=&quot;.cia.gov&quot;&gt;{{cite|url=https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/er.html|title= The World FactBook - Eritrea|date=July 12, 2018|work=[[The World Factbook]]}}{{PD-notice}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Population===
:5,970,646 (July 2018 est.)

===Age structure===
[[File:Eritreapop.svg|thumb|350px|Population pyramid of Eritrea in 2017]]
:''0-14 years:'' 39.53% (male 1,186,749 /female 1,173,530)
:''15-24 years:'' 19.94% (male 592,365 /female 598,305)
:''25-54 years:'' 32.88% (male 965,405 /female 997,771)
:''55-64 years:'' 3.7% (male 96,967 /female 123,895)
:''65 years and over:'' 3.95% (male 97,816 /female 137,843) (2018 est.)

:''0–14 years:'' 42.9% (male 1,085,116/female 1,072,262) 
:''15–64 years:'' 53.5% (male 1,332,349/female 1,355,494) 
:''65 years and over:'' 3.6% (male 88,068/female 95,186) (2008 est.)

===[[Total fertility rate]]===
:3.9 children born/woman (2018 est.) Country comparison to the world: 37th
:According to 2002 official survey, fertility rate was 4.8 with 3.5 in urban and 5.7 in rural.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.measuredhs.com/pubs/pdf/FR137/FR137.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

===Birth rate===
:29.1 births/1,000 population (2018 est.) Country comparison to the world: 40th

===Death rate===
:7.1 deaths/1,000 population (2018 est.) Country comparison to the world: 126th

===[[Population growth rate]]===
:0.89% (2018 est.) Country comparison to the world: 123rd
:2.445% (2011 est.)

===Median age===
:total: 19.9 years Country comparison to the world: 194th
:male: 19.4 years 
:female: 20.4 years (2018 est.)

===Mother's mean age at first birth===
:21.3 years (2010 est.)
:note: median age at first birth among women 25-29

===Contraceptive prevalence rate===
:8.4% (2010)

===Net migration rate===
:-13.9 migrant(s)/1,000 population (2017 est.) Country comparison to the world: 215th

===[[Dependency ratio]]s===
:total dependency ratio: 85 (2015 est.)
:youth dependency ratio: 78.3 (2015 est.)
:elderly dependency ratio: 6.8 (2015 est.)
:[[potential support ratio]]: 14.8 (2015 est.)

===Urbanization===
:urban population: 40.1% of total population (2018)
:rate of urbanization: 3.86% annual rate of change (2015-20 est.)

===Sex ratio===
&lt;br&gt;''at birth:''
1.03 male(s)/female
&lt;br&gt;''under 15 years:''
1.01 male(s)/female
&lt;br&gt;''15–64 years:''
0.98 male(s)/female
&lt;br&gt;''65 years and over:''
0.93 male(s)/female
&lt;br&gt;''total population:''
0.99 male(s)/female (2008 est.)

===Life expectancy at birth===
:total population: 65.6 years (2018 est.)
:male: 63 years (2018 est.)
:female: 68.2 years (2018 est.)

===[[Nationality]]===
&lt;br&gt;''noun:''
Eritrean(s)
&lt;br&gt;''adjective:''
Eritrean

===Ethnic groups===
[[Tigrinya]] 55%, [[Tigre people|Tigre]] 30%, [[Saho people|Saho]] 4%, [[Kunama people|Kunama]] 2%, [[Rashaida people|Rashaida]] 2%, [[Bilen people|Bilen]] 2%, other ([[Afar people|Afar]], [[Beni-Amer people|Beni-Amer]], [[Nera people|Nera]]) 5% (2010 est.)&lt;ref name=&quot;CIATONGA&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url= https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/er.html|title= Africa :: ERITREA|publisher= CIA The World Factbook}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Religions===
:Coptic Christian, Roman Catholic, Protestant, Muslim

===Languages===
:[[Afar language|Afar]], [[Arabic language|Arabic]] (spoken by the Rashaida), [[Beja language|Beja]] (spoken by the Hedareb), [[Blin language|Blin]], [[Kunama language|Kunama]], [[Nara language|Nara]], [[Saho language|Saho]], [[Tigre language|Tigre]], [[Tigrinya language|Tigrinya]], as a second language. English, Italian and Arabic are the foremost second languages.
 
===[[Literacy]]===
definition: age 15 and over can read and write (2015 est.)
:total population: 73.8% (2015 est.)
:male: 82.4% (2015 est.)
:female: 65.5% (2015 est.)

===School life expectancy (primary to tertiary education)===
:total: 5 years (2015)
:male: 6 years (2015)
:female: 5 years (2015)

==See also==
{{portal|Eritrea}}
* [[Languages of Eritrea]]
* [[Culture of Eritrea]]
* [[Eritrean diaspora]]

==References==
{{reflist}}
{{CIA World Factbook|year=2008}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Demographics of Eritrea}}
*[http://home.planet.nl/~hans.mebrat/eritrea-languages.htm Languages in Eritrea]
*[http://home.planet.nl/~hans.mebrat/eritrea-people.htm Ethnic groups in Eritrea]
*[http://www.modaina.com Eritrean website featuring resources relevant to Tigre history and culture]

{{Habesha peoples}}
{{Ethnic groups in Eritrea}}
{{Africa in topic|Demographics of}}
{{Eritrea topics}}

[[Category:Eritrean society]]
[[Category:Demographics by country|Eritrea]]
[[Category:Demographics of Africa|Eritrea]]
[[Category:Habesha peoples]]</text>
      <sha1>sfbd1ey1wsyuw5vdcfzs2j50c903gfv</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
