  <page>
    <title>Foreign relations of Egypt</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9355</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941930639</id>
      <parentid>939151755</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-21T14:45:05Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Zakawer</username>
        <id>10444015</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Europe */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Politics of Egypt}}
'''Foreign relations of the [[Egypt]]''' are the Egyptian government's external relations with the outside world. Egypt's foreign policy operates along a non-aligned level. Factors such as population size, historical events, military strength, diplomatic expertise and a strategic geographical position give Egypt extensive political influence in the [[Middle East]], [[Africa]], and within the [[Non-Aligned Movement]] as a whole. [[Cairo]] has been a crossroads of the [[Arab world]]'s commerce and culture for centuries, and its intellectual and [[Islam]]ic institutions are at the center of the region's social and cultural landmarks.

==Bilateral relations==
===Arab relations===
The [[Arab League]] headquarters is in [[Cairo]], and the Secretary General of the League is traditionally an Egyptian. Former [[Egyptian Foreign Minister]] [[Ahmed Aboul Gheit]] is the present Secretary General of the Arab League. Egyptian Deputy Prime Minister [[Boutros Boutros-Ghali]] served as Secretary General of the United Nations from 1991 to 1996..

Egypt is on good terms with [[Libya]], its western neighbor.

Egypt has fairly good relations with [[Sudan]], its southern neighbor, although it has a land dispute with Sudan over the [[Hala'ib Triangle]], a small area of land on the Egypt-Sudan border on the [[Red Sea]] coast. Sudan claims the area. Egypt's policy on Sudan is that it is in favor of a united Sudan. As such Egypt was not directly involved in the Sudan Peace Process that was hosted in Kenya under the auspices of [[IGAD]] and that gave the peoples of south Sudan the right to secede and form an independent state in 2011 after the long and brutal Sudanese civil war that cumulatively lasted more than 40 years and claimed over 2 million lives.

===Israeli–Palestinian conflict===
Egypt has been seeking to play a role in the resolution of the [[Israeli–Palestinian conflict]].

Egypt played an important role in the negotiations leading to the [[Madrid Conference of 1991]], which, under [[United States]] and [[Soviet Union|Soviet]] sponsorship, brought together all parties in the region, including for the first time a Palestinian delegation, to discuss Middle East peace.

This support has continued to the present, with former President [[Hosni Mubarak]] often intervening personally to promote peace negotiations. In 1996, he hosted the Sharm El-Sheikh &quot;Summit of the Peacemakers&quot; attended by President [[Bill Clinton]] and other world leaders.

In 2000, he hosted two summits at [[Sharm El-Sheikh]] and one at [[Taba Summit|Taba]] in an effort to resume the Camp David negotiations suspended in July 2000, and in June 2003, Mubarak hosted President [[George W. Bush]] for another summit on Middle East peace process. Another summit was convened in Sharm El Sheik in early 2005, which was attended by Egypt, [[Israel]], the [[Palestinian Authority]] and [[Jordan]]. The former Egyptian Chief of Intelligence, General [[Omar Suleiman]], played a substantial role in negotiations between the Israeli and Palestinian sides and was highly respected on both sides.

==Africa==
In the 21st-century Egypt has encountered a major problem with immigration, as millions of Africans attempt to enter Egypt fleeing poverty and war.  Border control methods can be &quot;harsh, sometimes lethal.&quot; This has strained relations with Egypt's southern neighbors, and with Israel and the members of the EU as these immigrants attempt to move on to wealthier countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Desperate on the Border|author=Soussi, Alasdair|publisher=Jerusalem Report|date=November 9, 2008|url= http://www.jpost.com/JerusalemReport/Article.aspx?id=119897|accessdate=September 30, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Egypt currently occupies the [[Hala'ib Triangle]] of [[Sudan]], an area of land located on the [[Red Sea]] coast, between the political borders (at the [[22nd parallel north|22nd circle of latitude]]) and the administrative boundary between the two countries.

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin:auto;&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;width:15%;&quot;| Country
! style=&quot;width:12%;&quot;| Formal relations established
! style=&quot;width:50%;&quot;| Notes
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Algeria}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||See [[Algeria–Egypt relations]]

* Algeria has an embassy in [[Cairo]].
* Egypt has an embassy in [[Algiers]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Angola}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||

* Angola has an embassy in Cairo.
* Egypt has an embassy in [[Luanda]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Chad}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||

* Chad has an embassy in Cairo.
* Egypt has an embassy in [[N'Djamena]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Democratic Republic of the Congo}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||

* DR Congo has an embassy in Cairo.
* Egypt has an embassy in [[Kinshasa]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Djibouti}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||

* Djibouti has an embassy in Cairo.
* Egypt has an embassy in [[Djibouti City]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Eritrea}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||

* Egypt has an embassy in [[Asmara]].
* Eritrea has an embassy in Cairo.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Ethiopia}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||See [[Egypt–Ethiopia relations]]

* Egypt has an embassy in [[Addis Ababa]].
* Ethiopia has an embassy in Cairo.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Ghana}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||

* Egypt has an embassy in [[Accra]].
* Ghana has an embassy in Cairo.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Guinea-Bissau}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||

* Egypt is accredited to Guinea-Bissau from its embassy in Conakry, Guinea.&lt;ref name=&quot;mfa.gov.eg&quot;&gt;[https://www.mfa.gov.eg/English/Ministry/PublishingImages/Pages/contacts-egypt-empassys/Africa.doc]&lt;/ref&gt; 
* Guinea-Bissau is accredited to Egypt from its embassy in Algiers, Algeria.
*Both countries are full member of the [[African Union]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Kenya}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||See [[Egypt–Kenya relations]]

* Egypt has an embassy in [[Nairobi]].
* Kenya has an embassy in Cairo.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Libya}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||See [[Egypt–Libya relations]]

* Egypt has an embassy in [[Tripoli]] and a consulate-general in [[Benghazi]].
* Libya has an embassy in Cairo and a consulate-general in Alexandria.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Morocco}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||See [[Egypt–Morocco relations]]

* Egypt has an embassy in [[Rabat]].
* Morocco has an embassy in Cairo.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Namibia}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||

* Egypt has an embassy in [[Windhoek]].
* Namibia has an embassy in Cairo.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Nigeria}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||

* Egypt has an embassy in [[Abuja]] and a consulate-general in [[Lagos]].
* Nigeria has an embassy in Cairo.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Rwanda}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||

* Egypt has an embassy in [[Kigali]].
* Rwanda has an embassy in Cairo.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|São Tomé and Príncipe }}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;
|
*Egypt is represented in São Tomé and Príncipe by its embassy in [[Luanda]], [[Angola]].&lt;ref name=&quot;mfa.gov.eg&quot;/&gt; 
*Both countries are full members of the [[African Union]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Senegal}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||

* Egypt has an embassy in [[Dakar]].
* Senegal has an embassy in Cairo.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Somalia}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||See [[Egypt–Somalia relations]]

* Egypt has an embassy in [[Mogadishu]].
* Somalia has an embassy in Cairo.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|South Africa }}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;1942
|See [[Egypt–South Africa relations]]
* The first South African mission in Egypt was established in 1942 as a consulate-general.
* Egypt has an embassy in [[Pretoria]] and South Africa has an embassy in Cairo.
* Both countries are full members of the [[African Union]], [[Group of 24|G-24]], [[Group of 77]] and [[Non-Aligned Movement]].
*[http://www.dfa.gov.za/foreign/bilateral/egypt.html South African Department of Foreign Affairs about relations with Egypt]
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|South Sudan}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||See [[Egypt–South Sudan relations]]

* Egypt has an embassy in [[Juba]].
* South Sudan has an embassy in Cairo.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Sudan}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||See [[Egypt–Sudan relations]]

* Egypt has an embassy in [[Khartoum]] and a consulate-general in [[Port Sudan]].
* Sudan has an embassy in Cairo and a consulate-general in [[Aswan]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Tanzania}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||

* Egypt has an embassy in [[Dar-es-Salaam]].
* Tanzania has an embassy in Cairo.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Tunisia}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||

* Egypt has an embassy in [[Tunis]].
* Tunisia has an embassy in Cairo.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Zimbabwe}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||

* Egypt has an embassy in [[Harare]].
* Zimbabwe has an embassy in Cairo.
|}

==Americas==
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin:auto;&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;width:15%;&quot;| Country
! style=&quot;width:12%;&quot;| Formal relations established
! style=&quot;width:50%;&quot;| Notes
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Argentina}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt; ||See [[Argentina–Egypt relations]]

* Argentina has an embassy in Cairo.&lt;ref&gt;[http://eegip.cancilleria.gov.ar Embassy of Argentina in Cairo (in English and Spanish)]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Egypt has an embassy in [[Buenos Aires]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mfa.gov.eg/english/embassies/Egyptian_Embassy_Argentina/Pages/default.aspx Embassy of Egypt in Buenos Aires (in Arabic and English)]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20110531181535/http://www.mrecic.gov.ar/portal/seree/ditra/eg.html List of Treaties ruling relations Argentina and Egypt (Argentine Foreign Ministry, in Spanish)]
* [http://www.sis.gov.eg/En/Politics/Foreign/LatinAmerica/EArelations/040312050000000001.htm Egyptian–Argentinean relations – From the Egypt State Information Service]

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Belize}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt; 6 May 1994||
Both countries established diplomatic relations on May 6, 1994.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.mfa.gov.bz/images/documents/DIPLOMATIC%20RELATIONS.pdf |title=Archived copy |access-date=2019-02-23 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171230194831/http://www.mfa.gov.bz/images/documents/DIPLOMATIC%20RELATIONS.pdf |archive-date=2017-12-30 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; 
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Brazil}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt; 1924||See [[Brazil–Egypt relations]]

* Brazil has an embassy in Cairo.
* Egypt has an embassy in [[Brasília]] and a consulate-general in [[Rio de Janeiro]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Canada}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt; ||See [[Canada–Egypt relations]]

Both countries established embassies in their respective capitals in 1954.
* Canada has an embassy in Cairo.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.canadainternational.gc.ca/egypt-egypte/index.aspx?lang=eng |title=Embassy of Canada in Cairo (in Arabic, English and French) |access-date=2019-01-20 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170827044951/http://www.canadainternational.gc.ca/egypt-egypte/index.aspx?lang=eng |archive-date=2017-08-27 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Egypt has an embassy in [[Ottawa]] and a consulate-general in [[Montreal]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mfa.gov.eg/english/embassies/Egyptian_Embassy_Ottawa/Pages/default.aspx Embassy of Egypt in Ottawa (in Arabic and English)]&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Chile}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt; ||

* Chile has an embassy in Cairo.
* Egypt has an embassy in [[Santiago]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Colombia}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt; ||

* Colombia has an embassy in Cairo.
* Egypt has an embassy in [[Bogotá]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Cuba}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||

* Cuba has an embassy in Cairo.
* Egypt has an embassy in [[Havana]].

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Guyana}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;10 September 1971 ||
Both countries established diplomatic relations on September 10, 1971.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.minfor.gov.gy/diplomatic-relations/]&lt;/ref&gt; 
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Mexico}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;31 March 1958 ||See [[Egypt–Mexico relations]]

* Egypt has an embassy in [[Mexico City]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mfa.gov.eg/english/embassies/Egyptian_Embassy_Mexico/Pages/default.aspx Embassy of Egypt in Mexico City (in Arabic, English and Spanish)]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Mexico has an embassy in Cairo.&lt;ref&gt;[http://embamex.sre.gob.mx/egipto/ Embassy of Mexico in Cairo (in Arabic and Spanish)]&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Peru}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt; ||

* Egypt has an embassy in [[Lima]].
* Peru has an embassy in Cairo.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|United States}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;1882 ||See [[Egypt–United States relations]]

After the [[Yom Kippur War]], Egyptian foreign policy began to shift as a result of the change in Egypt's leadership from President [[Gamal Abdel-Nasser]] to [[Anwar Sadat]] and the emerging peace process between Egypt and [[Israel]]. [[Sadat]] realized that reaching a settlement of the [[Arab–Israeli conflict]] is a precondition for Egyptian development. To achieve this goal, Sadat ventured to enhance US–Egyptian relations to foster a peace process with Israel. After a seven-year hiatus, both countries reestablished normal diplomatic relations on February 28, 1974.

===Military cooperation===

Following the peace treaty with Israel, between 1979 and 2003, the US has provided Egypt with about $19 billion in military aid, making Egypt the second largest non-NATO recipient of US military aid after Israel. Also, Egypt received about $30 billion in economic aid within the same time frame. In 2009, the US provided a military assistance of US$1.3 billion (inflation adjusted US$ {{formatnum:{{Inflation|US|1.3|2009|r=2}}}} billion in {{CURRENTISOYEAR}}), and an economic assistance of US$250 million (inflation adjusted US$ {{formatnum:{{Inflation|US|250|2009|r=1}}}} million in {{CURRENTISOYEAR}}).&lt;ref name=&quot;09CAIRO874&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wikileaks.ch/cable/2009/05/09CAIRO874.html|title=Scenesetter: President Mubarak's visit to Washington|date=2009-05-19|publisher=US Department of State|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110127035045/http://www.wikileaks.ch/cable/2009/05/09CAIRO874.html|archivedate=2011-01-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In 1989 both Egypt and Israel became a [[Major non-NATO ally]] of the United States.

Military cooperation between the US and Egypt is probably the strongest aspect of their strategic partnership. General [[Anthony Zinni]], the former Commandant of the [[US Central Command]] (CENTCOM), once said, &quot;Egypt is the most important country in my area of responsibility because of the access it gives me to the region.&quot; Egypt was also described during the [[Clinton Administration]] as the most prominent player in the Arab world and a key US ally in the Middle East. US military assistance to Egypt was considered part of the administration's strategy to maintaining continued availability of Persian Gulf energy resources and to secure the Suez Canal, which serves both as an important international oil route and as critical route for US warships transiting between the [[Mediterranean Sea|Mediterranean]] and either the [[Indian Ocean]] or the [[Persian Gulf]].

The Egyptian military provides indirect support for the foreign policy of Egypt in the region. Egypt is the strongest military power on the African continent, and the whole Middle East

===War on Terror===

Despite differences and periods of friction in relations between the two countries, the US-Egyptian relations under Mubarak have evolved moving beyond the Middle East peace process towards an independent bilateral friendship. It was in the US interest that Egypt was able to present moderate voice in Arab councils and persuade other Arab states to join the peace process and to normalize their relations with the US.

However lately Egyptian-American relations have become a little tense. This is due to a great extent to the Egyptian unwillingness to send troops to Afghanistan and Iraq in peace stabilization missions. Egypt strongly backed the US in its war against international terrorism after the September 11 attacks, but refused to send troops to Afghanistan during the war and after it. Egypt also opposed US military intervention of March 2003 in Iraq, continued to oppose US occupation of the country after the war and further refused to comply with US requests to send troops to the country even under a UN umbrella.

The issue of participation in the post-war construction efforts in Iraq has been controversial in Egypt and in the Arab world as a whole. Opponents say that the war was illegal and it is necessary to wait until Iraq has legal representative government to deal with it. On the other hand, supporters of participation argued that the responsibility to protect Iraqis and to help them in time of crisis should prevail and guide the Egyptian action in [[Iraq]], despite the fact that the Iraqis do not agree.

===Post-Mubarak relations with U.S.===
{{Update|section|date=December 2018}}
On January 21, 2012, the [[United States Secretary of Transportation|U.S. Secretary of Transportation]] [[Ray LaHood]]'s son, Sam, was detained by the Egyptian government and not allowed to leave the country as part of a politically charged criminal investigation by the Egyptian government into the activities of [[Non-governmental organization|non-governmental organizations (NGOs)]] monitoring local elections in [[Egypt]]. LaHood's son is the Egypt director of the [[International Republican Institute]]. The Egyptian government has detained twelve NGO representatives from leaving Egypt.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=As Tensions Rise, Egypt Bars Exit of Six Americans |author=Steven Myers and David Kirkpatrick |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2012/01/27/world/middleeast/egypt-bars-son-of-ray-lahood-from-leaving.html |newspaper=New York Times |date=January 26, 2012 |accessdate=26 January 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On February 5, 2012, Egyptian authorities charged LaHood's son and 42 other individuals with &quot;spending money from organizations that were operating in Egypt without a license.&quot; Nineteen Americans are part of the 42 charged. The U.S. government has made it clear that $1.5 billion in U.S. aid to Egypt could be withheld if the investigation is not finished quickly. Faiza Abu Naga, [[Ministry of International Cooperation (Egypt)|Egypt's Minister of International Cooperation]], is seen as the person pushing the investigation forward, straining U.S. and Egypt relations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Londoño, Ernesto and William Wan |title=Egypt to prosecute Americans in NGO probe; Sam LaHood among those facing criminal charges|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/world/egypt-to-prosecute-americans-in-ngo-probe/2012/02/05/gIQAQRderQ_story.html?tid=pm_pop |work=The Washington Post |date=5 February 2012 |accessdate=7 February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Egypt has an embassy in [[Washington, DC]] and consulates-general in [[Chicago]], [[Houston]], [[Los Angeles]] and [[New York City]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.egyptembassy.net Embassy of Egypt in Washington, DC]&lt;/ref&gt;
* United States has an embassy in Cairo.&lt;ref&gt;[http://egypt.usembassy.gov Embassy of the United States in Cairo (in Arabic and English)] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150307001551/http://egypt.usembassy.gov/ |date=2015-03-07 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Uruguay}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt; ||See [[Egypt–Uruguay relations]]

* Egypt has an embassy in [[Montevideo]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mfa.gov.eg/english/embassies/egyptian_embassy_uruguay/pages/default.aspx Embassy of Egypt in Montevideo (in Arabic and English)]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Uruguay has an embassy in Cairo.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mrree.gub.uy/frontend/page?1,inicio,embajadas,O,es,0, Uruguayan Ministry of Foreign Affairs: Embassy of Uruguay in Cairo (in English and Spanish)]&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Venezuela}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||

* Egypt has an embassy in [[Caracas]].
* Venezuela has an embassy in Cairo.
|}

==Asia==
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin:auto;&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;width:15%;&quot;| Country
! style=&quot;width:12%;&quot;| Formal Relations Began
! style=&quot;width:50%;&quot;| Notes
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Afghanistan}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||

* Afghanistan has an embassy in Cairo.
* Egypt has an embassy in [[Kabul]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Armenia}}||1992-03-01
|See [[Armenia–Egypt relations]]
* Egypt was one of the first countries in the Arab world which recognized the independent Armenia in 1991.
* In May 1992, the first diplomatic mission of the Republic of Armenia in the Arab East was inaugurated in [[Cairo]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.armembegypt.com/ |title=Armenian embassy in Cairo |publisher=Armembegypt.com |date= |accessdate=2011-02-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Egypt has an embassy in [[Yerevan]].
* Egypt had a sizable Armenian community since the 19th century. Many ethnic Armenian Egyptians remain in Egypt to this day.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Azerbaijan}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||

* Azerbaijan has an embassy in Cairo.
* Egypt has an embassy in [[Baku]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Bahrain}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||

* Bahrain has an embassy in Cairo.
* Egypt has an embassy in [[Manama]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Bangladesh }}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||
* Egypt has an embassy in [[Dhaka]], Bangladesh.
* Bangladesh has an embassy in Cairo, Egypt.

Egypt was one of the first Arab states to recognize Bangladesh's independence.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.thebusinessasia.com/newsite/?p=202 |title=Archived copy |access-date=2013-11-18 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130821030916/http://www.thebusinessasia.com/newsite/?p=202 |archive-date=2013-08-21 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; President [[Anwar Al Sadat]] enjoyed a close rapport with Bangladesh's founder [[Sheikh Mujibur Rahman]]. In 1973, Egypt gifted 30 tanks to the Bangladesh Army.

Both nations are members of the [[OIC]] and the [[Developing 8 Countries]], and identified among the [[Jim O'Neill, Baron O'Neill of Gatley#Next Eleven|Next Eleven]] economies. Present-day relations are characterized by a growing trade and economic relationship.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|China}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||See [[China–Egypt relations]]

* China has an embassy in Cairo and a consulate-general in Alexandria.
* Egypt has an embassy in [[Beijing]] and consulates-general in [[Hong Kong]] and [[Shanghai]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Georgia }}||1992-05-11
|
* Egypt is accredited to Georgia from its embassy in Yerevan, Armenia.
* Georgia has an embassy in [[Cairo]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://embassy.mfa.gov.ge/ |title=Georgian embassy in Cairo |publisher=Embassy.mfa.gov.ge |accessdate=2011-02-01 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110501082653/http://www.embassy.mfa.gov.ge/ |archive-date=2011-05-01 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20080903230151/http://www.mfa.gov.ge/index.php?sec_id=358&amp;lang_id=ENG Georgian Ministry of Foreign Affairs about the relation with Egypt]
* [https://archive.today/20121231063748/http://news-en.trend.az/politics/foreign/1451568.html Georgian foreign minister visits Egypt]
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|India }}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||See [[Egypt–India relations]]

Modern Egypt-India relations go back to the contacts between [[Saad Zaghloul]] and [[Mohandas Gandhi]] on the common goals of their respective movements of independence. In 1955, Egypt under [[Gamal Abdul Nasser]] and India under [[Jawaharlal Nehru]] became the founders of the [[Non-Aligned Movement]]. During the 1956 War, Nehru stood supporting Egypt to the point of threatening to withdraw his country from the [[Commonwealth of Nations]]. In 1967, following the [[Six-Day War]], India supported Egypt and the Arabs. In 1977, New Delhi described the visit of President [[Anwar al-Sadat]] to Jerusalem as a &quot;brave&quot; move and considered the peace treaty between Egypt and Israel a primary step on the path of a just settlement of the Middle East problem. Major Egyptian exports to India include raw cotton, raw and manufactured fertilizers, oil and oil products, organic and non-organic chemicals, leather and iron products. Major imports into Egypt from India are cotton yarn, sesame, coffee, herbs, tobacco and lentils. The Egyptian Ministry of Petroleum is also currently negotiating the establishment of a natural gas-operated fertilizer plant with another Indian company. In 2004 the [[Gas Authority of India Limited]], bought 15% of Egypt Nat Gas distribution and marketing company.

In 2008 Egyptian investment in India was worth some 750 million dollars, according to the Egyptian ambassador.&lt;ref&gt;Egypt State Information Service: [http://www.sis.gov.eg/En/Politics/Presidency/President/Activity/000001/0401050400000000000964.htm Mubarak starts historic visit to India to boost strategic partnership between the two countries] {{dead link|date=September 2016|bot=medic}}{{cbignore|bot=medic}}&lt;/ref&gt;

President [[Hosni Mubarak|Mubarak]] of Egypt visited India in 2008. During the visit he met Prime Minister [[Manmohan Singh]].&lt;ref&gt;The Hindu [http://www.hindu.com/2008/11/19/stories/2008111961221200.htm Manmohan: time ripe for transforming ties]&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Indonesia}}||1946
|See [[Egypt–Indonesia relations]]
* Indonesia has an embassy in Cairo and Egypt has an embassy in [[Jakarta]].
* Egypt was one of the first countries to recognize [[Proclamation of Indonesian Independence|Indonesia's independence]].
* [[Gamel Abdel Nasser]] of Egypt and [[Sukarno]] of Indonesia were two of the five founding members of the [[Non-aligned Movement]].
* Both countries are members of the [[OIC]], the Non-aligned Movement, and the [[G20 developing nations]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Iran }}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||See [[Egypt–Iran relations]]

In 1939, diplomatic relations between Egypt and [[Iran]] were upgraded to ambassadorial level, and [[Youssef Zulficar Pasha]] was appointed as Egypt's first ambassador in [[Tehran]]. In the same year, [[Princess Fawzia Fuad of Egypt|Princess Fawzia]] of Egypt, the sister of [[Farouk of Egypt|King Farouk I]], married [[Mohammad Reza Pahlavi]], the then crown prince (later shah) of Iran. However, since the [[Iranian Revolution|1979 Islamic Revolution]], Egypt's relations with Iran have been mostly strained. Egypt is the only Arab country not to have an embassy in Iran.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.alarabiya.net/articles/2009/07/02/77608.html Ahmadinejad unwelcome in Egypt: lawyer], Al Arabiya. July 2, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; Contentious issues include Egypt's signing of the [[Camp David Accords]] with [[Israel]] in 1979, its support for [[Iraq]] in [[Iran–Iraq War|Iran's eight-year conflict]], the Islamic Republic's hailing of [[Khalid Islambouli]], the late [[President of Egypt|President]] [[Anwar Sadat]]'s assassin as a religious hero, seeing as there was both a street and mural named after him (however, the honorer was changed to [[Muhammad al-Durrah]], the 12-year-old [[Palestinian Arab|Palestinian]] boy shot and killed during the outset of the Second Intifada), and close Egyptian relations with the [[United States]], and most of the [[Western Europe]]an countries. In 2007, relations between the two have thawed in the fields of diplomacy and economic trade, only to collapse during the [[Gaza War (2008–09)]] when the Iranian and Egyptian politicians exchanged blames over inaction towards the escalation. Despite wavering tensions between [[Tehran]] and [[Cairo]], the two countries are members of the [[Organisation of Islamic Cooperation|OIC]] and the [[Developing 8]]

In 2010, leaked diplomatic cables revealed that Mubarak expressed animosity toward Iran in private meetings, saying the Iranian leaders are &quot;big, fat liars&quot;, and that Iran's backing of terrorism is &quot;well-known&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://articles.latimes.com/2010/nov/29/world/la-fg-wikileaks-arabs-20101130 &quot;WikiLeaks: Diplomatic cables show Egyptian leader's acrimony with Iran&quot;], ''Los Angeles Times'', November 29, 2010&lt;/ref&gt; According to one American report, Mubarak views Iran as the primary long-term challenge facing Egypt, and an Egyptian official said that Iran is running agents inside Egypt in an effort to subvert the Egyptian regime. he also stated that if Iran will reach a nuclear weapons, Egypt will also consider reaching such weapons.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.wsj.com/articles/SB10001424052748704457604576011643624083766?mod=googlenews_wsj &quot;Iran, Israel and the Arab Contradiction&quot;], by Ronen Bergman, ''Wall Street Journal'', December 11, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Iraq }}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||See [[Egypt-Iraq relations]]

Since 1983, Iraq has repeatedly called for restoration of Egypt's “natural role” among Arab countries.  In January 1984, Iraq successfully led Arab efforts within the OIC to restore Egypt's membership.  However, Iraqi-Egyptian relations were broken in 1990 after Egypt joined the UN coalition that forced Iraq out of Kuwait. Relations have steadily improved in recent years, and Egypt is now one of Iraq's main trade partners (formerly under the [[Oil-for-Food Programme]]).
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Israel }}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||See [[Egypt–Israel relations]]

The state of war between both countries which dated back from the [[1948 Arab–Israeli War]] ended in 1973 with the [[Egypt–Israel Peace Treaty]] a year after the [[Camp David Accords]]. Since then, relations have improved.

Being a pioneer of peace making in the region and driven from its belief that a peaceful Middle East is the best solution for the development of Egypt, the third [[President of Egypt|Egyptian President]] [[Anwar Sadat]]'s groundbreaking trip to [[Israel]] in 1977, the 1978 [[Camp David Accords]], and the 1979 [[Egypt–Israel Peace Treaty]] represented a fundamental shift in the politics of the region; from a strategy of confrontation to one of peace as a strategic choice. Egypt was subsequently ostracized by other Arab states and ejected from the [[Arab League]] from 1979 to 1989.

However, due to circumstances of today's [[Israeli–Palestinian conflict]], full normalization of relations between these two countries is still halted and sometimes fought against in both countries. The Egyptian ambassador to Tel Aviv is often withdrawn, and the peace has been called a cool peace due to the Israeli–Palestinian conflict.
* Egypt has an embassy in [[Tel Aviv]] and a consulate-general in [[Eilat]].
* Israel has an embassy in Cairo and a consulate-general in Alexandria.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Japan }}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||See [[Egypt-Japan relations]]

Egypt-Japan relations are described by the Egyptian ambassador to Japan as a &quot;very strong friendship&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.embassy-avenue.jp/egypt/ |title=Embassy Avenue Index |publisher=Embassy-avenue.jp |accessdate=2011-02-01 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20081009174007/http://www.embassy-avenue.jp/egypt/ |archivedate=2008-10-09 }}&lt;/ref&gt; with embassies mutually established.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.eg.emb-japan.go.jp/e/birateral/japan_egypt/recent_progress/2008/index.htm |title=Embassy of Japan in Egypt |publisher=Eg.emb-japan.go.jp |accessdate=2011-02-01 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110201040701/http://www.eg.emb-japan.go.jp/e/birateral/japan_egypt/recent_progress/2008/index.htm |archive-date=2011-02-01 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; At present, the two nations maintain a cordial relationship with strong economic and trade relations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://weekly.ahram.org.eg/2004/717/ec2.htm|title=Al-Ahram Weekly - Economy - Japan and Egypt open up|author=Gamal Essam El-Din|accessdate=21 February 2015|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130827225102/http://weekly.ahram.org.eg/2004/717/ec2.htm|archivedate=27 August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Egypt has an embassy in [[Tokyo]].
* Japan has an embassy in Cairo.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Jordan }}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||See [[Egypt-Jordan relations]]

Diplomatic relations between the Egyptian and Jordanian government existed since Jordan became independent in 1946. On April 6, 1972 the Egyptian government severed relations in protest for a Jordanian plan for federation with the West Bank, which didn't take PLO interests unto considerations. These relations were restored on September 11, 1973.&lt;ref&gt;[https://aad.archives.gov/aad/createpdf?rid=68652&amp;dt=2472&amp;dl=1345 US diplomatic cable on the resumption of relations]&lt;/ref&gt; They were severed again in 1979, this time by the Jordanian government, in protest for the Israeli-Egyptian peace treaty. Following the outbreak of the Lebanon War of 1982, the US government put pressure on both governments to reach accommodation for the purpose of formulating a joint peace strategy vis-a-vis the Israeli government,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.presidency.ucsb.edu/ws/index.php?pid=39523&amp;st=&amp;st1=|title=Ronald Reagan: Remarks of President Reagan, President Mohammed Hosni Mubarak of Egypt, and King Hussein I of Jordan Following Their Meetings|publisher=|accessdate=21 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; and relations were restored on September 25, 1984.
* Egypt has an embassy in [[Amman]].
* Jordan has an embassy in Cairo.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Kazakhstan }}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;
|
* Egypt has an embassy in [[Almaty]], Kazakhstan.
* Kazakhstan has an embassy in [[Cairo]], Egypt.

In 2006, [[President Mubarak]] of Egypt visited Kazakhstan on the third leg of a three-country tour. During the visit he met with Kazakh President [[Nursultan Nazarbayev|Nazarbayev]]. Mubarak stated that 30 trade and economic cooperation agreements had been concluded between the two countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.sis.gov.eg/VR/kazakhstan/einter5.htm |title=Mubarak, Nazarbayev: Need underlined for pushing peace process, developing bilateral ties |access-date=2009-06-24 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110614002822/http://www.sis.gov.eg/VR/kazakhstan/einter5.htm |archive-date=2011-06-14 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Kuwait}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||

* Egypt has an embassy in [[Kuwait City]].
* Kuwait has an embassy in Cairo.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Lebanon}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||

* Egypt has an embassy in [[Beirut]].
* Lebanon has an embassy in Cairo and a consulate-general in Alexandria.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Malaysia}}||1957&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.gov.eg/English/Embassies/Egyptian_Embassy_Malaysia/bilateralrelations/Pages/History.aspx|title=Bilateral Relations|publisher=Embassy of Egypt in Kuala Lumpur|accessdate=8 January 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|See [[Egypt–Malaysia relations]]
* Egypt has an embassy in [[Kuala Lumpur]] and Malaysia has an embassy in [[Cairo]].
* [[Gamel Abdel Nasser]] gave a headquarters for the Malay Association in Egypt as a gift to Malaysia in 1959.
* Both countries are members of the [[OIC]] and the [[Non-Aligned Movement]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Mongolia }}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;1964&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://nl.newsbank.com/nl-search/we/Archives?p_product=NewsLibrary&amp;p_multi=BBAB&amp;d_place=BBAB&amp;p_theme=newslibrary2&amp;p_action=search&amp;p_maxdocs=200&amp;p_topdoc=1&amp;p_text_direct-0=1025DDF543B4119D&amp;p_field_direct-0=document_id&amp;p_perpage=10&amp;p_sort=YMD_date:D&amp;s_trackval=GooglePM|publisher=The Ulaanbaatar Post|date=2004-05-03|accessdate=2007-10-26|title=Mongolian president discusses cooperation with Egyptian counterpart in Cairo|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110610014723/http://nl.newsbank.com/nl-search/we/Archives?p_product=NewsLibrary&amp;p_multi=BBAB&amp;d_place=BBAB&amp;p_theme=newslibrary2&amp;p_action=search&amp;p_maxdocs=200&amp;p_topdoc=1&amp;p_text_direct-0=1025DDF543B4119D&amp;p_field_direct-0=document_id&amp;p_perpage=10&amp;p_sort=YMD_date:D&amp;s_trackval=GooglePM|archive-date=2011-06-10|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|See [[Egypt–Mongolia relations]]

Cairo currently hosts Mongolia's only embassy on the African continent.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mongolianembassy.us/eng_embassy_info/missions_abroad.php |title=Missions Abroad |publisher=Embassy of Mongolia, Washington D.C. |accessdate=2007-10-26 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071011090744/http://mongolianembassy.us/eng_embassy_info/missions_abroad.php |archivedate=2007-10-11 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|publisher=BBC|title=Mongolian president discusses cooperation with Egyptian counterpart|date=2004-05-03|accessdate=2007-10-26|url=http://docs.newsbank.com/g/GooglePM/BBAB/lib00589,1025DDF543B4119D.html|archive-url=https://archive.today/20120707204143/http://docs.newsbank.com/g/GooglePM/BBAB/lib00589,1025DDF543B4119D.html|url-status=dead|archive-date=2012-07-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|North Korea}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;1963-08-24||[[Egypt–North Korea relations]]

Diplomatic relations were established on 27 August 1963.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Wertz|first1=Daniel|last2=Oh|first2=JJ|last3=Kim|first3=Insung|date=August 2016|title=Issue Brief: DPRK Diplomatic Relations|publisher=The National Committee on North Korea|url=http://www.ncnk.org/resources/publications/NCNK_Issue_Brief_DPRK_Diplomatic_Relations.pdf|access-date=22 February 2019|url-status=live|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161228074114/http://www.ncnk.org/resources/publications/NCNK_Issue_Brief_DPRK_Diplomatic_Relations.pdf|archive-date=28 December 2016|page=8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Oman}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||

* Egypt has an embassy in [[Muscat]].
* Oman has an embassy in Cairo.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Pakistan }}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||See [[Egypt–Pakistan relations]]

[[Pakistan]] and Egypt have diplomatic and trade relations. Both countries are members of the OIC ([[Organisation of Islamic Cooperation]]), &quot;the [[Jim O'Neill, Baron O'Neill of Gatley#Next Eleven|Next Eleven]]&quot; and the &quot;[[Developing 8 Countries|D8]]&quot;. Relations between the two countries were established after Pakistan was established. Pakistan President General Muhammad Ayub Khan, visited Egypt in 1959 and Egyptian President [[Gamal Abdul Nasser]] visited Pakistan in 1960.{{Citation needed|date=April 2009}}
* Egypt has an embassy in [[Islamabad]].
* Pakistan has an embassy in Cairo.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Palestine}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||See [[Egypt–Palestine relations]]

* Egypt has representative offices in [[Ramallah]] and in [[Gaza City]].
* Palestine has an embassy in Cairo.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Philippines}}||1955-01-18||See [[Egypt–Philippines relations]]

* Egypt has an embassy in [[Manila]].
* Philippines has an embassy in Cairo.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Qatar }}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||See [[Egypt-Qatar relations]]

Bilateral relations first began with Egypt in 1972.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mofa.gov.qa/en/ForeignPolicy/BilateralRelations/Pages/Egypt.aspx|title=Bilateral Relations|publisher=Ministry of Foreign Affaris of Qatar|accessdate=15 January 2015|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150124013126/http://www.mofa.gov.qa/en/ForeignPolicy/BilateralRelations/Pages/Egypt.aspx|archivedate=24 January 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lately, relations have not been at its best. Sheikh Tamim bin Hamad Al Thani, Emir of the State of Qatar, has described the 2013 political transition in Egypt as a &quot;military coup&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Islam Hassan&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.academia.edu/12696782/GCCs_2014_Crisis_Causes_Issues_and_Solutions|title=GCC's 2014 Crisis: Causes, Issues and Solutions|author=Islam Hassan|date=31 March 2015|publisher=Al Jazeera Research Center |accessdate=4 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is worth mentioning that the main problem between the two governments is the Qatari support to the Muslim Brotherhood in Egypt.&lt;ref name=&quot;Islam Hassan&quot;/&gt;

The Egyptian government, along with those of Saudi Arabia, Bahrain, and the United Arab Emirates, broke off diplomatic relations with Qatar on 5 June 2017. The Egyptian Foreign Ministry announced it was closing its air and sea ports to Qatari transportation. The Egyptian, Saudi, Bahraini, and Emirati governments cited Qatar's continuing support for &quot;terrorism&quot;, such as the [[Muslim Brotherhood]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.arabianbusiness.com/uae-saudi-bahrain-egypt-cut-ties-with-qatar-676651.html|title=UAE, Saudi, Bahrain and Egypt cut ties with Qatar|work=Arabian Business|access-date=2017-06-05|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; Islam Hassan argues &quot;Egypt has had troubled relations with Qatar for many years, except of Mohamed MorsiÕsperiod in power. The Egyptian government has seen Qatar as a source of instability. TheEgyptian regime also sees that Qatar challenges its rule by financing the Muslim Brotherhood, and other organizations, which the regime has outlawed and consider terrorist organizations. Thus, the Egyptian regime has been trying to push back on Qatar by any means. The current issue between the Saudi bloc and Qatar seemed to be an opportunity to put pressure on Qatar to stop financing the Muslim Brotherhood, its affiliates, and supporters, and to support the Sisi regime.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url= https://www.academia.edu/33408451/Qatar_Pursues_an_Independent_Foreign_Policy_that_Clashes_with_the_Saudis_Strategic_Interests.pdf|title= Qatar Pursues an Independent Foreign Policy that Clashes with the Saudi's Strategic Interests|work=Eurasia Diary|date=8 June 2017|accessdate=11 June 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url= https://www.academia.edu/33408486/Saudi_Diplomatic_Offensive_on_Qatar_to_Barely_Impact_Anti-Terror_Fight_in_Region|title= Saudi Diplomatic Offensive on Qatar to Barely Impact Anti-Terror Fight in Region|work=Sputnik International|date=8 June 2017|accessdate=11 June 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Saudi Arabia}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||See [[Egypt–Saudi Arabia relations]]

* Egypt has an embassy in [[Riyadh]] and a consulate-general in [[Jeddah]].
* Saudi Arabia has an embassy in Cairo and a consulate-general in Alexandria.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|South Korea }}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;1995-04-13&lt;ref name=&quot;mofa.go.kr&quot;&gt;http://www.mofa.go.kr/ENG/countries/middleeast/countries/20070824/1_24453.jsp?menu=m_30_50{{Dead link|date=July 2018 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;
| See [[Egypt–South Korea relations]]
* The establishment of diplomatic relations between Egypt and the Republic of Korea began on 13 April 1995.
* Egypt has an embassy in [[Seoul]], South Korea.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mfa.gov.eg/Missions/southkorea/seoul/embassy/en-GB/default.htm Egyptian embassy in Seoul] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071107162137/http://www.mfa.gov.eg/Missions/southkorea/seoul/embassy/en-GB/default.htm |date=2007-11-07 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* South Korea has an embassy in Cairo.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://egy.mofat.go.kr/eng/index.jsp |title=South Korean embassy in Cairo |publisher=Egy.mofat.go.kr |accessdate=2011-02-01 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20101126095006/http://egy.mofat.go.kr/eng/index.jsp |archive-date=2010-11-26 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Bilateral Trade 2011:
** Exports: 18.1 billion US dollars
** Imports: 802 million US dollars
* The number of South Koreans living in Egypt in 2011 was about 905.
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20080524023101/http://www.mofat.go.kr/english/regions/meafrica/20070824/1_1354.jsp South Korean Ministry of Foreign Affairs and Trade about relations with Egypt]
* [[Foreign relations of South Korea#Europe Foreign relations of South Korea Foreign relations of the Republic of Korea]].&lt;ref name=&quot;mofa.go.kr&quot;/&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Syria}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||See [[Egypt–Syria relations]]

* Egypt has an embassy in [[Damascus]].
* Syria has an embassy in Cairo.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Turkey }}||1925||See [[Egypt–Turkey relations]]

From the time of the Ottoman conquest of Egypt in 1517 until the seizure of power by [[Muhammad Ali of Egypt|Muhammad Ali Pasha]] in 1805, Egypt was ruled by the Ottoman Empire (with brief interruptions owing to native rebellions, and the French invasion of 1798). The seat of the Caliphate in Istanbul and the seat of culture in Cairo. Turkey established diplomatic relations with Egypt in 1925 at the level of Charge d’ Affaires and upgraded its mission in Cairo to Ambassadorial level in 1948. Both countries have embassies and consulate generals in each other's capitals. Both countries have signed a free trade agreement in December 2005. Both countries are full members of the Union for the Mediterranean.
* Egypt has an embassy in [[Ankara]] and a consulate-general in [[Istanbul]].
* Turkey has an embassy in Cairo and a consulate-general in Alexandria.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|United Arab Emirates}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||See [[Egypt–United Arab Emirates relations]]

* Egypt has an embassy in [[Abu Dhabi]] and a consulate-general in [[Dubai]].
* United Arab Emirates has an embassy in Cairo.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Vietnam }}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt; 1963-09-01
|
* Egypt was the first Arab state to establish bilateral relations with Vietnam.&lt;ref name=min&gt;[http://www.mofa.gov.vn/en/cn_vakv/nr040830134623/nr040819101958/ns060726153348 Egypt and Vietnam Relations] {{dead link|date=September 2018|bot=medic}}{{cbignore|bot=medic}} ''Vietnam Ministry of Foreign Affairs''&lt;/ref&gt;
* Vietnam first opened its commercial representative office in Egypt in 1958, and opened an embassy in Cairo in 1963.
* Egypt's embassy in [[Hanoi]] was opened in 1964.
|}

==Europe==
[[European Union]] relations with Egypt are based on a partnership relation within the Euro – Mediterranean and Middle East area, which is of vital strategic importance and a key external relations priority for the EU.

The [[Euro-Mediterranean Partnership]] launched at the 1995 Barcelona Conference between the European Union and its originally 12 [[Mediterranean]] Partners: [[Algeria]], [[Cyprus]], [[Egypt]], [[Israel]], [[Jordan]], [[Lebanon]], [[Malta]], [[Morocco]], [[Syria]], [[Tunisia]], [[Turkey]], and the [[Palestinian Authority]]. [[Libya]] currently has observer status at certain meetings. Since the enlargement, in May 2004 and January 2007, the co-operation and needs covers 35 countries, the EU of 27, including [[Cyprus]] and [[Malta]] and the 10 Mediterranean Partners.

Egypt has also taken an active role regarding Euro-Mediterranean Partnership, such as its participation in the technical meeting of which it was the speaker for the Arab group. Additionally, the first meeting of the Euro-Mediterranean Parliamentary assembly was co-chaired by an Egyptian.

Egypt has been one of the leading recipients among the Mediterranean partners in terms of total funds received from the [[MEDA programme]], the principal financial instrument of the European Union for the implementation of the Euro-Mediterranean Partnership. It is focused on policy-led, national structural reform and liberalisation programmes with a sector-wide approach.

The EU is Egypt's biggest trading partner currently accounting for 42% of Egyptian exports and 37% of imports, with the [[balance of trade]] still in the EU's favour. Trade between the EU and Egypt has risen by more than 5% in the last five years to reach around 11.6 billion euro in 2004. Egypt's main exports to the EU in 2004 were energy (39%), textiles and clothing (15%), agricultural products (9%), and chemicals (5%). Major imports from the EU were power generating machinery (21%), chemicals (16%), transport equipment (16%), and food and agricultural products (10%). Egypt has a serious but improving trade deficit that has put considerable pressure on the [[Egyptian pound]].

Trade relations with the EU are good although there are several outstanding trade and phyto-sanitary issues. These range from specific market access issues and difficulties for businesses facing a highly regulated and complex system through to restrictions in the export of agricultural goods (potatoes) and fishery products because they do not conform with EU quality norms.

Egypt is included in the European Union's [[European Neighbourhood Policy]] (ENP) which aims at bringing the EU and its neighbours closer.

Some time after the starting of the [[Arab Spring]], in March 2011 the [[European Union]] adopted the joint declaration ‘ A partnership for democracy and shared prosperity with the Southern Mediterranean', aimed at making a number of initiatives in the field of civic society support, financial assistance and further access to the EU market dependent upon advancement in the democratization process.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://ec.europa.eu/europeaid/where/neighbourhood/arab_spring/index_en.htm |title=Archived copy |access-date=2014-05-10 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140402172208/http://ec.europa.eu/europeaid/where/neighbourhood/arab_spring/index_en.htm |archive-date=2014-04-02 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

As far as Egypt was concerned this declaration envisioned the further deepening of the previous Free Trade Agreement stipulated in 2004, geared towards the inclusion of areas such as trade in services, government procurement, competition, intellectual property rights, and investment protection. To the 2011 declaration, a preliminary phase of the negotiations followed in June 2013, when the EU and [[Egypt]] began an exploratory dialogue on how to deepen trade and investment relations, in particular through the possible negotiation of a Deep and Comprehensive Free Trade Agreement (DCFTA).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tax-news.com/news/EU_Seeks_To_Resume_Talks_On_DCFTA_With_Egypt____63682.html|title=EU Seeks To Resume Talks On DCFTA With Egypt|publisher=|accessdate=21 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 2014, the [[European Union]] discussed the possibility of revising provision of aid to [[Egypt]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.reuters.com/article/2013/08/19/us-egypt-protests-eu-idUSBRE97I0PU20130819|title=EU foreign ministers to discuss how to press Egypt over bloodshed|work=Reuters|accessdate=21 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;  However, divisions over the appropriate stance to adopt among European diplomats persisted, coupled by the fear that the vacuum might be soon filled by other actors, following a Saudi Foreign Minister's declaration that the Kingdom was ready to step in&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc.co.uk&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-23782685|title=BBC News - EU suspends arms sales to Egypt over crackdown|work=BBC News|accessdate=21 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; and those of Prime Minister Hazem al Beblawi about the possibility to appeal to Russia for foreign aid.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aljazeera.com/news/middleeast/2013/08/201382153414138265.html|title=Egypt PM defiant on threat of aid cut|publisher=|accessdate=21 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Therefore, the only measure upon which the Foreign Ministers agreed was to suspend the sale of arms and materials that could be used for repression,&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc.co.uk&quot;/&gt; but fell short to halt aid program which could damage civil society.

Earlier in July 2013, EU High Representative [[Catherine Ashton]] had visited Egypt in an attempt to promote reconciliation among the parties involved. She is credited for being the only foreign diplomat to get access to deposed president Mohamed Morsi.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.theguardian.com/politics/2013/aug/04/baroness-ashton-morsi-secret-meeting|title=How Baroness Ashton engineered a secret meeting at dead of night with Morsi|author=Elizabeth Day|work=the Guardian|accessdate=21 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In an official statement released at the end of a following visit held in April 2014, the Representative raised the issue of the death penalties and incarceration of journalists and activists.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://eeas.europa.eu/delegations/egypt/press_corner/all_news/news/2014/20140411_en.pdf |title=Archived copy |access-date=2014-05-10 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140512224441/http://eeas.europa.eu/delegations/egypt/press_corner/all_news/news/2014/20140411_en.pdf |archive-date=2014-05-12 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; At the same time, her later declarations about el-Sisi's bid for presidential candidacy as “difficult” but “brave”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://madamasr.com/content/eu-policy-chief-calls-sisi-presidential-bid-brave|title=EU policy chief calls Sisi presidential bid 'brave'|work=Mada Masr|accessdate=21 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; sparked harsh criticism among supporters of the [[Muslim Brotherhood]], who claimed the Representative, who advanced logistical reasons, did not make any efforts to get in touch with them and members of their Anti-Coup Alliance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.worldbulletin.net/haber/133487/egypts-anti-coup-bloc-slams-ashtons-sisi-visit|title=Egypt's anti-coup bloc slams Ashton's Sisi visit - Middle East -  Worldbulletin News|work=World Bulletin|accessdate=21 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In April 2014, the European Union agreed to conduct electoral monitoring, for the first time, in occasion of the Presidential elections scheduled for 26/27 May 2014. Other organizations declined to join, as in their opinion this would legitimize what they called an unlawful take on power.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aljazeera.com/indepth/opinion/2014/04/eu-legitimising-sisi-coup-egypt-20144161181767834.html|title=Is the EU legitimising Sisi's coup?|author=Alastair Sloan|publisher=|accessdate=21 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin:auto;&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;width:15%;&quot;| Country
! style=&quot;width:12%;&quot;| Formal relations established
! style=&quot;width:50%;&quot;| Notes
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Albania}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||See [[Albania–Egypt relations]]
* Egypt has an embassy in [[Tirana]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.mfa.gov.eg/english/embassies/egyptian_embassy_albania/pages/default.aspx&lt;/ref&gt;
* Albania has an embassy in [[Cairo]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.ambasadat.gov.al/egypt/en |title=Archived copy |access-date=2016-09-22 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160923101621/http://www.ambasadat.gov.al/egypt/en |archive-date=2016-09-23 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Bulgaria}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||See [[Bulgaria–Egypt relations]]

*Bulgaria has an embassy in [[Cairo]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mfa.bg/cairo/ Bulgarian embassy in Cairo] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140224182335/http://www.mfa.bg/cairo/ |date=February 24, 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  
* Egypt has an embassy in [[Sofia]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Croatia}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||See [[Croatia–Egypt relations]]

* Croatia has an embassy in Cairo.
* Egypt has an embassy in [[Zagreb]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Cyprus}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||See [[Cyprus–Egypt relations]]

Diplomatic relations between both countries were established soon after Cyprus gained its independence in 1960. 
* Cyprus has an embassy in Cairo.
* Egypt has an embassy in [[Nicosia]].

During an April 2009 meeting at ministerial level, the countries explored ways to develop closer ties, with plans for increased collaboration both on tourism and energy related activities.  There has been talk of Cyprus increasing her imports of natural gas,  Egypt using Cyprus as a bridge for exports to Europe and on prospects for the training of Cypriot engineers by their Egyptian counterparts on techniques for the extraction of oil and natural gas.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |url=http://www.financialmirror.com/News/Cyprus_and_World_News/14835 
 |title=Cyprus and Egypt keep LNG talks secret 
 |work=FinancialMirror 
 |date=April 9, 2009 
 |accessdate=May 1, 2009 
 |url-status=dead 
 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110605040303/http://www.financialmirror.com/News/Cyprus_and_World_News/14835 
 |archivedate=June 5, 2011 
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Denmark}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||See [[Denmark–Egypt relations]]

* Denmark has an embassy in [[Cairo]] and an honorary consulate in [[Alexandria]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ambkairo.um.dk/en |title=Danish embassy in Cairo |publisher=Ambkairo.um.dk |date=2008-01-14 |accessdate=2011-02-01 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20101216093105/http://www.ambkairo.um.dk/en/ |archivedate=2010-12-16 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Egypt has an embassy in [[Copenhagen]].
* Both countries are full members of the [[Union for the Mediterranean]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Finland }}||1947-02-15
|
* Finland recognised Egypt on April 8, 1922.
* Egypt broke off diplomatic relations on January 5, 1942 but diplomatic relations were re-established on February 15, 1947.
* Egypt has an embassy in [[Helsinki]].
* Finland has an embassy in [[Cairo]] (since July 1, 1959) and an honorary consulate general in [[Alexandria]].
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20110820171427/http://formin.finland.fi/public/default.aspx?nodeid=17207&amp;culture=en-US&amp;contentlan=2 Ministry for Foreign Affairs of Finland about Egypt]
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|France}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||See [[Egypt–France relations]]

* Egypt has an embassy in [[Paris]] and a consulate-general in [[Marseille]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.ambassade-egypte.fr/ |title=Embassy of Egypt in Paris (in Arabic and French) |access-date=2018-11-24 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180408224352/http://www.ambassade-egypte.fr/ |archive-date=2018-04-08 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* France has an embassy in Cairo and a consulate-general in [[Alexandria]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ambafrance-eg.org Embassy of France in Cairo (in Arabic and French)]&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Germany }}||1957-12&lt;ref name=&quot;sis&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sis.gov.eg/En/Politics/Foreign/EEurope/EGrelations/040311050000000001.htm |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2008-11-03 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20081118172833/http://www.sis.gov.eg/En/Politics/Foreign/EEurope/EGrelations/040311050000000001.htm |archivedate=2008-11-18 }}&lt;/ref&gt;||See [[Egypt–Germany relations]]
*Egypt has an embassy in [[Berlin]], as well as consulates in [[Frankfurt]] and [[Hamburg]].
*Germany has an embassy in [[Cairo]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Greece }}||1833
|See [[Egypt-Greece relations]]
Both countries share relations since the years [[Before Christ|BC]]  Since the creation of [[Alexandria]] by [[Alexander the Great]], Egypt has had a sizable Greek community, mostly centered around Alexandria, which is today Egypt's second largest city and also the seat of the Greek Orthodox [[Patriarchate of Alexandria]]. In the modern era, both countries enjoy very good and warm diplomatic relations since 1833 and especially after the Greek War Independence, and both countries have signed several defense cooperation agreements, with the heads of states visiting each other in a regular basis.
* Egypt has an embassy in [[Athens]].
* Greece has an embassy in Cairo and a consulate-general in [[Alexandria]].
* Sizable communities of Greeks live in Egypt (Alexandria) and Egyptians in Greece ([[Patras]], Athens).
* Greece and Egypt signed bilateral agreements for trade, tourism and defense cooperations.
* Both countries are members of the [[Union for the Mediterranean]].
* [http://www.mfa.gr/www.mfa.gr/en-US/Policy/Geographic+Regions/Mediterranean+-+Middle+East/Bilateral+Relations/Egypt/  Greek Ministry of Foreign Affairs about relations with Egypt]
* [http://www.mfa.gov.eg/Missions/greece/athens/embassy/en-GB/  Egyptian Ministry of Foreign Affairs about relations with Greece]
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Ireland }}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;
|
* Since 1978, Egypt has an embassy in [[Dublin]], the first embassy of an [[Arab World|Arab country]] in Ireland.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.embegyptireland.ie/the-embassy.htm |title=Egyptian embassy in Dublin |publisher=Embegyptireland.ie |accessdate=2011-02-01 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110201040604/http://www.embegyptireland.ie/the-embassy.htm |archivedate=2011-02-01 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Ireland has an embassy in [[Cairo]] and an honorary consulate in [[Alexandria]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.embassyofireland.org.eg/|title=Department of Foreign Affairs|publisher=|accessdate=21 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Italy }}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;
|See [[Egypt–Italy relations]]
Relations were established during the period of the Roman Empire. However, during [[World War II]], relations were strained as the Italian and German Troops launched a campaign on Egypt but were defeated by Egyptian and British Forces in the battle of [[El Alamein]]. However, after the war, relations were re-established and are close. 
* Egypt has an embassy in [[Rome]] and a consulate-general in [[Milan]].
* Italy has an embassy in Cairo.
* Both nations are members of the [[Union for the Mediterranean]].

See also [[Italian Egyptian]]
|-
|{{KOS}}
|
|See [[Egypt–Kosovo relations]]
Egypt recognised the Republic of Kosovo as an independent state on 26 June 2013.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.mfa.gov.eg/Arabic/Ministry/News/Pages/NewsDetails.aspx?Source=1d5b0202-c337-4794-ab10-342893d069e1&amp;newsID=17393f2d-a0db-471c-bd41-1c1d169b79c2|title=جمهورية مصر العربية – وزارة الخارجية - تفاصيل الأخبار|website=www.mfa.gov.eg|access-date=2017-03-22|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130630231622/http://www.mfa.gov.eg/Arabic/Ministry/News/Pages/NewsDetails.aspx?Source=1d5b0202-c337-4794-ab10-342893d069e1&amp;newsID=17393f2d-a0db-471c-bd41-1c1d169b79c2|archivedate=2013-06-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
* Kosovo has a liaison office in [[Cairo]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Malta }}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;
|
* Malta has an embassy in [[Cairo]] and 2 honorary consulates in [[Alexandria]] and [[Suez]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.gov.mt/images/files/file/EGYPT(1).pdf|title=Sorry. The page you are looking for does not exist|publisher=|accessdate=21 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Egypt has an embassy in [[Valletta]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mfa.gov.eg/Missions/malta/valletta/embassy/en-GB/default.htm Egyptian embassy in Valletta] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100114172217/http://www.mfa.gov.eg/Missions/malta/valletta/embassy/en-GB/default.htm |date=January 14, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|North Macedonia}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;
|
North Macedonia has an embassy in [[Cairo]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mfa.gov.mk/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=428&amp;Itemid=750&amp;lang=en#dkpafrika]&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Poland }}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;
|See [[Egypt–Poland relations]]
* Egypt has an embassy in [[Warsaw]].
* Poland has an embassy in Cairo.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Portugal }}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;
|
* Portugal has an embassy in Cairo.
* Egypt has an embassy in [[Lisbon]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Romania }}||1906
|
* Egypt has an embassy in [[Bucharest]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mfa.gov.eg/Missions/romania/bucharest/embassy/en-GB/default.htm Egyptian embassy in Bucharest]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Romania has an embassy in Cairo.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Russia }}||1943-08-26||See [[Egypt–Russia relations]]

* Egypt has an [[Embassy of Egypt in Moscow|embassy in Moscow]].
* Russia has an embassy in Cairo and a consulate-general in [[Alexandria]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Serbia }}||1908
|
* Egypt has an embassy in [[Belgrade]].
* Serbia has an embassy in [[Cairo]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.serbiaeg.com/ Serbian embassy in Cairo] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090301031336/http://www.serbiaeg.com/ |date=2009-03-01 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [http://www.mfa.gov.rs/Policy/Bilaterala/Egypt/index_e.html Serbian Ministry of Foreign Affairs about relations with Egypt]
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Slovenia }}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||See [[Egypt–Slovenia relations]]

* Since September 2007, Egypt has an embassy in [[Ljubljana]].
* Slovenia has an embassy in [[Cairo]] (opened in 1993).
* Both countries are members of the [[Union for the Mediterranean]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Spain }}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||

* Egypt has an embassy in [[Madrid]].
* Spain has an embassy in Cairo.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Switzerland }}||1909
|
* Official diplomatic relation between both countries date back from 1909, with the opening of a Swiss trade mission in Egypt.
* Egypt has an embassy in [[Bern]] and a general consulate in [[Geneva]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mfa.gov.eg/Missions/switzerland/bern/embassy/en-GB/default.htm Egyptian embassy in Bern]{{dead link|date=October 2017 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Switzerland has an embassy in [[Cairo]].
* [http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home/reps/afri/vegy/bilegy.html Swiss Federal Department of Foreign Affairs about relations with Egypt]
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Ukraine }}||1992
|
* Since 1993, Egypt has an embassy in [[Kiev]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mfa.gov.eg/Missions/ukraine/kiev/embassy/en-GB/default Egyptian embassy in Kiev] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20081112062546/http://www.mfa.gov.eg/Missions/ukraine/kiev/embassy/en-GB/default |date=2008-11-12 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Since 1993, Ukraine has an embassy in [[Cairo]] and an honorary consulate in [[Alexandria]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.mfa.gov.ua/egypt/en/ |title=Ukrainian embassy in Cairo |publisher=Mfa.gov.ua |date= |accessdate=2011-02-01 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110201040616/http://www.mfa.gov.ua/egypt/en/ |archive-date=2011-02-01 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|United Kingdom}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;||See [[Egypt–United Kingdom relations]]

* Egypt has an embassy in [[London]].
* United Kingdom has an embassy in Cairo.
|}

==Oceania==
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin:auto;&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;width:15%;&quot;| Country
! style=&quot;width:12%;&quot;| Formal Relations Began
! style=&quot;width:50%;&quot;| Notes
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Australia}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt; 1950
|See [[Australia–Egypt relations]]
* Australia has an embassy in Cairo.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.egypt.embassy.gov.au/ |title=Australian embassy Cairo |publisher=Egypt.embassy.gov.au |date=2011-01-26 |accessdate=2011-02-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Egypt has an embassy in [[Canberra]] and 2 Consulates-General (in [[Melbourne]] and [[Sydney]]).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mfa.gov.eg/Missions/Australia/canberra/embassy/en-GB/default.htm Egyptian embassy in Canberra]{{dead link|date=January 2017 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mfa.gov.eg/Missions/Australia/Sydney/Consulate/en-GB/default.htm Egyptian Consulate-General in Sydney] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090616113046/http://www.mfa.gov.eg/Missions/Australia/Sydney/Consulate/en-GB/default.htm |date=June 16, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [http://www.dfat.gov.au/geo/egypt/index.html Australian Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade about relations with Egypt]
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|New Zealand}}||&lt;!--Start Date--&gt;1974||See [[Egypt–New Zealand relations]]

* Egypt has an embassy in [[Wellington]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mfa.gov.eg/english/embassies/Egyptian_Embassy_Wellington/Pages/default.aspx Embassy of Egypt in New Zealand]&lt;/ref&gt;
* New Zealand has an embassy in Cairo.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.mfat.govt.nz/en/countries-and-regions/africa/egypt/new-zealand-embassy-cairo-egypt/ Embassy of New Zealand in Egypt]&lt;/ref&gt;
|}

==International involvement==
Egypt played a key role during the 1990-91 [[Gulf War|Persian Gulf crisis]]. President Mubarak helped assemble the international coalition and deployed 35,000 Egyptian troops against Iraq to liberate [[Kuwait]]. The Egyptian contingent was one of the largest in the coalition forces, along with the U.S., [[United Kingdom|U.K.]] and Saudi Arabia.

In the aftermath of the Gulf War, Egypt signed the [[Damascus Declaration]] with [[Syria]] and the Persian Gulf states to strengthen Persian Gulf security. Egypt continues to contribute regularly to [[United Nations]] [[peacekeeping]] missions, most recently in [[East Timor]], [[Sierra Leone]], and [[Liberia]].

Following the September 11, 2001 [[September 11 attacks|terrorist attacks]] on the United States, Egypt, which has itself been the target of terrorist attacks, has been a key supporter of the U.S. war against terrorists and terrorist organizations such as [[Osama bin Laden]] and [[al-Qaeda]], and has supported the Iraqi Governing Council.

On December 25, 2006, the Egyptian Foreign Minister Ahmed Abul Gheit called for end to &quot;nuclear double standards&quot; where sanctions are imposed on [[Iran]] for enriching uranium, but the [[Israel and weapons of mass destruction#Nuclear weapons|Israeli nuclear program]] is not subject to any control by the [[International Atomic Energy Agency]].&lt;ref&gt;[https://news.yahoo.com/s/afp/20061225/wl_africa_afp/egyptirannuclear_061225175118] {{dead link|date=June 2016|bot=medic}}{{cbignore|bot=medic}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Egypt is member of [[ABEDA]], [[Arab Cooperation Council|ACC]], [[Agence de Coopération Culturelle et Technique|ACCT]] (associate), [[African Development Bank|AfDB]], [[Arab Fund for Economic and Social Development|AFESD]], [[Arab League|AL]], [[Arab Monetary Fund|AMF]], [[African Union|AU]], [[Organization of the Black Sea Economic Cooperation|BSEC]] (observer), [[Council of Arab Economic Unity|CAEU]], [[Comprehensive Test Ban Treaty|CTBT]], [[European Bank for Reconstruction and Development|EBRD]], [[United Nations Economic Commission for Africa|ECA]], [[United Nations Economic and Social Commission for Western Asia|ESCWA]], [[Food and Agriculture Organization|FAO]], [[Group of 15|G-15]], G-19, [[Group of 24|G-24]], [[Group of 77|G-77]], [[International Atomic Energy Agency|IAEA]], [[International Bank for Reconstruction and Development|IBRD]], [[International Civil Aviation Organization|ICAO]], [[International Chamber of Commerce|ICC]], [[International Red Cross and Red Crescent Movement|ICRM]], [[International Development Association|IDA]], [[Islamic Development Bank|IDB]], [[International Fund for Agricultural Development|IFAD]], [[International Finance Corporation|IFC]], [[International Red Cross and Red Crescent Movement|IFRCS]], [[International Hydrographic Organization|IHO]], [[International Labour Organization|ILO]], [[International Monetary Fund|IMF]], [[International Maritime Organization|IMO]], [[International Mobile Satellite Organization|Inmarsat]], [[Intelsat]], [[Interpol (organization)|Interpol]], [[IOC]], [[International Organization for Migration|IOM]], [[International Organization for Standardization|ISO]], [[International Telecommunication Union|ITU]], [[United Nations Mission for the Referendum in Western Sahara|MINURSO]], [[United Nations Organization Mission in the Democratic Republic of the Congo|MONUC]], [[Non-Aligned Movement|NAM]], [[Organization of Arab Petroleum Exporting Countries|OAPEC]], [[Organization of American States|OAS]](observer), [[Organisation of African Unity|OAU]], [[Organisation of Islamic Cooperation|OIC]], [[Organization for Security and Co-operation in Europe|OSCE]] (partner), [[Permanent Court of Arbitration|PCA]], [[United Nations|UN]], [[United Nations Mission in Sierra Leone|UNAMSIL]], [[United Nations Conference on Trade and Development|UNCTAD]], [[UNESCO]], [[United Nations Industrial Development Organization|UNIDO]], [[United Nations Institute for Training and Research|UNITAR]], [[United Nations Mission in Bosnia and Herzegovina|UNMIBH]], [[United Nations Interim Administration Mission in Kosovo|UNMIK]], [[United Nations Mission of Observers in Prevlaka|UNMOP]], [[UNOMIG]], [[United Nations Relief and Works Agency for Palestine Refugees in the Near East|UNRWA]], [[United Nations Transitional Administration in East Timor|UNTAET]], [[Universal Postal Union|UPU]], [[World Customs Organization|WCO]], [[World Federation of Trade Unions|EFTU]], [[World Health Organization|WHO]], [[World Intellectual Property Organization|WIPO]], [[World Meteorological Organization|WMO]], [[World Tourism Organization|WToO]], and [[World Trade Organization|WTrO]]. Egypt is one of only seven U.N. members which is not a member of the [[Organisation for the Prohibition of Chemical Weapons]].

==See also==
* [[List of Foreign ministers of Egypt]]
* [[Iran-Arab relations#Egypt|Iran-Arab Relations (Egypt)]]
* [[List of Ambassadors from Egypt]]
* [[List of diplomatic missions in Egypt]]
* [[List of diplomatic missions of Egypt]]
* [[Ministry of Foreign Affairs (Egypt)|Ministry of Foreign Affairs]]
* [[Visa requirements for Egyptian citizens]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
* [https://history.state.gov/countries/egypt History of Egypt - U.S. relations]
* [http://rds.yahoo.com/_ylt=AmF3WMYBWc7Cpc9ElrQGr11XNyoA;_ylu=X3oDMTE2anNnbmViBGNvbG8DZQRsA1dTMQRwb3MDNgRzZWMDc3IEdnRpZANERlg1XzMw/SIG=12er3jl9e/EXP=1135385348/**http://www.ahram.org.eg/acpss/eng/ahram/2004/7/5/STUD8.HTM/  Assessing the United States-Egyptian Military and Security Relations]{{Dead link|date=November 2018 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}
* [http://rds.yahoo.com/_ylt=AhnXpstyX_05uh3.zk8oztNXNyoA;_ylu=X3oDMTE3dHZsZGltBGNvbG8DdwRsA1dTMQRwb3MDMTYEc2VjA3NyBHZ0aWQDREZYNV8zMA--/SIG=12tr1k1a8/EXP=1135385972/**http://commdocs.house.gov/committees/intlrel/hfa94279.000/hfa94279_0f.htm/ The Future of American-Egyptian relations]{{Dead link|date=November 2018 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20070314224208/http://www.diabolicdigest.net/Egypt/Deniers.htm Deniers of Egypt's dark past] An article exploring Egypt's Africanness
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20091101104912/http://www.egyptian-embassy.org.uk/ Embassy of the Arab Republic of Egypt in London] The official website of the Egyptian Embassy in London
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20140104004804/http://www.enpi-info.eu/countrymed.php?country=2 EU Neighbourhood Info Centre: Egypt]

{{Foreign relations of Egypt}}
{{Africa topic|Foreign relations of}}
{{Asia topic|Foreign relations of}}
{{Egypt topics}}

[[Category:Foreign relations of Egypt| ]]</text>
      <sha1>hjicadbyxzfma8q2g7ipbryb3t16vy4</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
