  <page>
    <title>Geography of Estonia</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9388</id>
    <revision>
      <id>922695080</id>
      <parentid>922694609</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-10-23T18:32:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Gilliam</username>
        <id>506179</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contribs/2001:BB6:A908:2B58:75F5:6CC1:1303:8F44|2001:BB6:A908:2B58:75F5:6CC1:1303:8F44]] ([[User talk:2001:BB6:A908:2B58:75F5:6CC1:1303:8F44|talk]]) to last version by El C</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{more footnotes|date=June 2009}}

{{Country geography
| name = Estonia
| map = Satellite image of Estonia in April 2004.jpg
| continent = [[Europe]]
| region = [[Northern Europe]]
| coordinates = {{coord|59|00|N|26|00|E|type:country}}
| km area = 45227
| percent land = 95.55
| km coastline = 3,794
| borders = [[Land borders|Total land borders]]:&lt;br /&gt; {{convert|657|km|mi|abbr=on}}
| highest point = [[Suur Munamägi]] &lt;br /&gt; {{convert|317|m|ft|abbr=on}}
| lowest point = [[Baltic Sea]] &lt;br /&gt; 0 meters
| longest river = [[Võhandu (river)|Võhandu]] &lt;br /&gt; {{convert|162|km|mi|abbr=on}}
| largest lake = [[Lake Peipus]] &lt;br /&gt; {{convert|3555|km2|mi2|abbr=on}}
| exclusive economic zone= {{convert|36,992|km2|mi2|abbr=on}}
}}

Between 57.3 and 59.5 [[latitude]] and 21.5 and 28.1 [[longitude]], [[Estonia]] lies on the eastern shores of the [[Baltic Sea]] on the level northwestern part of the rising [[East-European Platform|East European Platform]]. It borders the [[Gulf of Finland]], between [[Latvia]] and [[Russia]]. Average elevation reaches only {{convert|50|m|ft|0|abbr=on}}.
 
The climate is maritime, wet, with moderate winters and cool summers. [[Oil shale]] and [[limestone]] deposits, along with [[forest]]s which cover 47% of the land, play key economic roles in this generally resource-poor country. Estonia boasts over 1,500 [[lake]]s, numerous [[bog]]s, and 3,794 kilometers of [[coastline]] marked by numerous bays, straits, and inlets. [[Tallinn]]'s [[Port of Muuga|Muuga port]] offers one of Europe's finest [[ice-free port|warm-water harbor]] facilities.

Estonia's strategic location has precipitated many wars that were fought on its territory between other rival powers at its expense. In 1944, under [[Soviet Union|Soviet]] occupation, the [[Ivangorod|Jaanilinn]] and [[Pechory|Petseri]] regions were annexed to [[Russian SFSR]] territory. The legal status of these territories has not been fully settled yet, though neither Estonia or Russia has not any territorial claims.

==Geographic features==
[[Image:Estonia 1999 CIA map.jpg|thumb|right|300px|Map of Estonia.]]
{{See also|List of islands of  Estonia}}
{{See also|List of rivers of  Estonia}}

Estonia is a flat country covering {{convert|45227|km2|mi2|0|abbr=on}}. Estonia has a long, shallow coastline ({{convert|3794|km|mi|0|abbr=on|disp=or}}) along the Baltic Sea, with 2222 &lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|title=Eesti saarte loend|date=2019-07-25|url=https://et.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Eesti_saarte_loend&amp;oldid=5405100|work=Vikipeedia|language=et|access-date=2019-07-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; islands dotting the shore. The two largest islands are [[Saaremaa]] (literally, island land), at {{convert|2673|km2|mi2|0|abbr=on}}, and Hiiumaa, at {{convert|989|km2|mi2|0|abbr=on}}. The two islands are favorite Estonian vacation spots. The country's highest point, Suur Munamägi (Egg Mountain), is in the hilly southeast and reaches {{convert|318|m|ft|0|abbr=on}} above sea level. Estonia is covered by about {{convert|18000|km2|mi2|0|abbr=on}} of forest. Arable land amounts to about {{convert|9260|km2|mi2|0|abbr=on}}. Meadows cover about {{convert|2520|km2|mi2|0|abbr=on}}, and pastureland covers about {{convert|1810|km2|mi2|0|abbr=on}}. There are more than 1,400 natural and artificial lakes in Estonia. The largest of them, [[Lake Peipus]] ({{convert|3555|km2|mi2|0|abbr=on|disp=or}}), forms much of the border between Estonia and Russia. Located in central Estonia, [[Võrtsjärv]] is the second-largest lake ({{convert|270|km2|mi2|0|abbr=on|disp=or}}). The [[Narva River|Narva]] and [[Emajõgi]] are among the most important of the country's many rivers.{{cn|date=September 2019}}

A small, recent cluster of meteorite craters, the largest of which is called [[Kaali crater|Kaali]] are found near [[Saaremaa]], Estonia. It is thought{{by whom|date=September 2019}} that the impact was witnessed by the Iron Age inhabitants of the area.{{cn|date=September 2019}}&lt;!-- need a source --&gt;

Estonia has a temperate climate, with four seasons of near-equal length. Average temperatures range from {{convert|16.3|°C|1|lk=on}} on the Baltic islands to {{convert|17.1|°C|1}} inland in July, the warmest month, and from {{convert|−3.5|°C|1}} on the Baltic islands to {{convert|−7.6|°C|1}} inland in February, the coldest month. Precipitation averages {{convert|568|mm|in|1|abbr=on}} per year and is heaviest in late summer.

Estonia's land border with Latvia runs {{convert|333|km|mi|0|abbr=on}}; [[Estonia-Russia border|the Russian border]] runs {{convert|324|km|mi|0|abbr=on}}. From 1920 to 1945, Estonia's border with Russia, set by the 1920 Tartu Peace Treaty, extended beyond the Narva River in the northeast and beyond the town of [[Petseri]] in the southeast. This territory, amounting to some {{convert|2300|km2|mi2|0|abbr=on}}, was incorporated into Russia by [[Joseph Stalin]] at the end of [[World War II]].{{cn|date=September 2019}}

==Wildlife==
[[File:Laelatu puisniit.jpg|thumb|In Laelatu meadow, there have been found 76 species of plants in 1 m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;. That is the 2nd largest number of species per m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; in the world.]]

There live 65 different species of mammals in the Estonian forests. There are an estimated 700 brown bears, over 150 wolves, 400 lynxes, 14,000–16,000 beavers, 3,400 wild boars, 10,000–11,000 moose and 120,000–130,000 deer. There are also red deer and other wild animals. 

==Environmental issues==
{{See also|Protected areas of Estonia}}
[[File:Suur-Pakri - kaugpommitajate polügoon.JPG|thumb|The Soviet army used the [[Pakri Islands]] as sites for aerial bombardment. The collection and destruction of thousands of Soviet explosive devices was mostly complete by 1997.]]
One of the most burdensome legacies of the [[History of the Soviet Union|Soviet era]] is widespread environmental pollution.&lt;ref&gt;Auer, M.R., Raukas, A. (2002). Determinants of environmental cleanup in Estonia. ''Environment and Planning C: Government and Policy'', 20: 679–698.&lt;/ref&gt; The worst offender in this regard was the Soviet army. Across military installations covering more than 800&amp;nbsp;km² of Estonian territory, the army dumped hundreds of thousands of tons of jet fuel into the ground, improperly disposed of toxic chemicals, and discarded outdated explosives and weapons in coastal and inland waters. In the 1990s, during the army's withdrawal from Estonia, extensive damage was done to discarded buildings and equipment. In October 1993, the Estonian Ministry of Environment issued a preliminary report summing up part of the degradation it had surveyed thus far. The report described the worst damage as having been done to Estonia's topsoil and underground water supply by the systematic dumping of jet fuel at six Soviet army air bases. At the air base near Tapa, site of the worst damage, officials estimated that six square kilometers of land were covered by a layer of fuel; 11 square kilometers of underground water were said to be contaminated. The water in the surrounding area was undrinkable, and was sometimes set fire by locals to provide heat during the winter. With Danish help, Estonian crews began cleaning up the site, although they estimated the likely cost to be as much as 4 million EEK. The Ministry of Environment assigned a monetary cost of more than 10 billion EEK  {{Citation needed|date=January 2017}} to the damage to the country's topsoil and water supply. However, the ministry was able to allocate only 5 million EEK in 1993 for cleanup operations.

In a 1992 government report to the United Nations Conference on the Environment and Development, Estonia detailed other major environmental concerns. For instance, for several consecutive years Estonia had led the world in the production of sulfur dioxide per capita. Nearly 75% of Estonia's air pollution was reported to come from [[Narva Power Plants|two oil shale-based thermal power stations operating near Narva]]. The [[Oil shale in Estonia|mining of oil shale]] in northeastern Estonia has also left large mounds of limestone [[tailings]] and ash dotting the region. Near the town of [[Sillamäe]], site of a former uranium enrichment plant, about 1,200 tons of uranium and about 750 tons of thorium had been dumped into a reservoir on the shore of the Gulf of Finland. This was said to have caused severe health problems among area residents. In the coastal town of Paldiski, the removal of waste left by Soviet army nuclear reactors was also a major concern. The combined cost of environmental cleanup at both towns was put at more than EKR3.5 billion.

'''Natural hazards:''' flooding occurs frequently in the spring in certain areas

'''Environment – current issues:'''  air polluted with sulfur dioxide from oil-shale burning power plants in northeast; however, the amount of pollutants emitted to the air have fallen steadily, the emissions of 2000 were 80% less than in 1980; the amount of unpurified wastewater discharged to water bodies in 2000 was 1/20 the level of 1980; in connection with the start-up of new water purification plants, the pollution load of wastewater decreased; Estonia has more than 1,400 natural and man-made lakes, the smaller of which in agricultural areas need to be monitored; coastal seawater is polluted in certain locations.

'''Environment – international agreements:'''&lt;br /&gt;
''party to:'' Air Pollution, Antarctic Treaty, [[Biodiversity]], Climate Change, Climate Change-[[Kyoto Protocol]], Endangered Species, Hazardous Wastes, [[Law of the Sea]], Ozone Layer Protection, Ship Pollution, Wetlands&lt;br /&gt;
''signed, but not ratified:'' none

==Area and boundaries==
[[File:Hellamaa panoraam.jpg|thumb|300px|Hellamaa bay in [[Hiiumaa]].]]
'''Area:'''&lt;br /&gt;
''total:'' 45,227 km²&lt;br /&gt;
''land:'' 43,432&amp;nbsp;km²&lt;br /&gt;
''water:'' 1,795&amp;nbsp;km²&lt;br /&gt;
''note:'' includes 1,520 islands in the Baltic Sea

'''Land boundaries:'''&lt;br /&gt;
''total:'' 657&amp;nbsp;km&lt;br /&gt;
''border countries:'' Latvia 333&amp;nbsp;km, Russia 324&amp;nbsp;km

'''Coastline:''' 3,794&amp;nbsp;km

'''Maritime claims:'''&lt;br /&gt;
''territorial sea:'' {{convert|12|nmi|km mi|1|abbr=on|lk=in}}
''[[exclusive economic zone]]:'' {{convert|36,992|km2|mi2|abbr=on}}. The limits are fixed in coordination with neighboring states.

'''Elevation extremes:'''&lt;br /&gt;
''lowest point:'' Baltic Sea 0 m&lt;br /&gt;
''highest point:'' [[Suur Munamägi]] 317 m&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.estonica.org/en/Nature/Location_and_natural_conditions/Topography/ Topography] Estonica: Encyclopedia about Estonia&lt;/ref&gt;

==Resources and land use==
[[File:Pine forest in Estonia.jpg|thumb|Forests cover more than half of the territory of Estonia.]]
'''Natural resources:''' [[oil shale]] ([[kukersite]]), [[peat]], [[phosphorite]], [[cambrian blue clay]], [[limestone]], [[sand]], [[Dolomite (mineral)|dolomite]], [[arable land]], [[forest]]

'''Land use:'''&lt;br /&gt;
''arable:'' 14.65%&lt;br /&gt;
''permanent crops:'' 0.14%&lt;br /&gt;
''other:'' 85.21% (2012)

'''Irrigated land:''' 4.58&amp;nbsp;km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;

'''Total renewable water resources:''' 12.81&amp;nbsp;km&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; (2011)

'''Freshwater withdrawal (domestic/industrial/agricultural):'''
&lt;br&gt;''total:'' 1.8&amp;nbsp;km&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;/yr (3%/97%/0%)
&lt;br&gt;''per capita:'' 1,337 m&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;/yr (2009)

== See also ==
* [[Extreme points of Estonia]]
* [[Climate of Estonia]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}
{{commons category}}
*{{loc}}
*{{CIA World Factbook}}

{{Estonia topics|state=autocollapse}}
{{Geography of Europe}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Geography Of Estonia}}
[[Category:Geography of Estonia| ]]</text>
      <sha1>fvq7okjgkwlftet17mxzb9ms22ng9lj</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
