  <page>
    <title>Geography of Ecuador</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9336</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941270333</id>
      <parentid>941267877</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-17T16:03:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Serols</username>
        <id>9929111</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contributions/75.184.24.190|75.184.24.190]] ([[User talk:75.184.24.190|talk]]) ([[WP:HG|HG]]) (3.4.9)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{refimprove|date=August 2017}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}

{{Country geography
|map= Ecuador_Blue_Marble.png
|name= Ecuador
|continent= [[South America]]
|region= [[Americas]]
|km area= 276,841
|percent land= 97.63
|km coastline= 2,237 
|area ranking= 73rd
|largest lake= [[Cuicocha]] ({{convert|3|km2|mi2|abbr=on}}
|highest point= [[Chimborazo]] {{convert|6,267|m|feet|abbr=on}}
|lowest point= [[Pacific Ocean]] (0 m) 
|borders= [[Land borders|Total land borders]]:&lt;br /&gt; {{convert|2237|km|mi|abbr=on}} &lt;br /&gt;[[Colombia]]: {{convert|708|km|mi|abbr=on}}&lt;br /&gt; [[Peru]]:  {{convert|1,529|km|mi|abbr=on}}
|coordinates= {{Coord|2|00|S|77|30|W|type:country}}
|longest river= [[Río Napo]] {{convert|855|km|mi|abbr=on}}
|exclusive economic zone= {{convert|1,077,231|km2|mi2|abbr=on}}
}}

[[Image:Ec-map.png|thumb|Map of Ecuador]]
[[Image:Ecuador Topography.png|thumb|Topographic map of Ecuador]]

'''[[Ecuador]]''' is a country in western [[South America]], bordering the [[Pacific Ocean]] at the [[Equator]], for which the country is named. Ecuador encompasses a wide range of natural formations and climates, from the [[desert]]-like southern coast to the snowcapped peaks of the [[Andes]] [[mountain range]] to the [[plain]]s of the [[Amazon Basin]]. [[Cotopaxi]] in Ecuador is one of the world's highest active [[volcano]]s. It also has a large series of rivers that follow the southern border and spill into the northwest area of [[Peru]].

== Area and borders ==

{{Coord|2|00|S|77|30|W|type:country|display=title}}

Ecuador is located on the west by the Pacific Ocean, and has 2,237 km of [[coastline]]. It has 2237 km of land boundaries, with [[Colombia]] in the north (708&amp;nbsp;km border) and Peru in the east and south (1,529&amp;nbsp;km border). {{convert|276841|km2|sqmi|0|abbr=on}} is land and {{convert|6720|km2|sqmi|0|abbr=on}} water. Ecuador is one of the smaller countries in South America, slightly smaller than the [[U.S. state]] of [[Nevada]]. It has the 29th largest [[exclusive economic zone]] of {{convert|1,077,231|km2|mi2|abbr=on}} which includes the [[Galápagos Islands]].

== Cities ==
The capital and second most-populous city is [[Quito]], with a population of 1.4 million. The most-populous city is [[Guayaquil]] (2 million). Other important cities include [[Cuenca (Ecuador)|Cuenca]] (0.41 million), [[San Juan de Ambato|Ambato]] (0.28 million), [[Portoviejo]] (0.23 million), [[Machala]] (0.21 million), and [[Loja, Ecuador|Loja]] (0.14 million).

== Geographical regions ==

{{Main|Regions of Ecuador}}
[[File:Localisation de l'ile de Clipperton.png|right|thumbnail|Extent of Ecuador's western [[EEZ]] in the Pacific]]

Ecuador is divided into three continental regions&amp;mdash;the Costa (coast), Sierra (mountains), and Oriente (east)&amp;mdash;and one insular region, the Galápagos Islands (officially Archipiélago de Colón). The continental regions extend the length of the country from north to south and are separated by the Andes Mountains.

=== Galápagos Islands ===

The Galápagos are located 1,000&amp;nbsp;km west of the Ecuadorian coast. They are noted for their association with [[Charles Darwin]], whose observation of animals here during the [[Second voyage of HMS Beagle|voyage of the ''Beagle'']] led to his formation of the theory of [[natural selection]] as a means of [[evolution]]. The islands have witnessed a large number of tourists and travelers over recent years. As a result, various hotels and restaurants are now flourishing in the area offering [http://naturegalapagos.com/land-tours/ tour packages] and [http://www.naturegalapagos.com/cruises/ cruise services.] Special species that could be found here include [[blue-footed booby|blue footed boobies]], [[Iguanidae|iguanas]] and many more. Internal flight services from Ecuador to Galápagos are also available for tourists making it more convenient for guests from outside.

[[File:Black Turtle Cove - panorama.jpg|thumb|Panoramic of [[Black Turtle Cove]], Island of Santa Cruz, Galapagos.]]


[[Image:School of Hammerhead sharks.jpg|thumb|right|School of scalloped hammerheads, [[Wolf Island]], [[Galápagos Islands]]]][[Image:Sphyrna lewini galapagos.jpg|thumb|right|Another school of scalloped hammerheads at Wolf Island, Galapagos]]
[[Image:Ecuador aguablanca sulfur laguna.jpg|thumb|Sulfur laguna on the site of AguaBlanca, Machalilla National Park, Ecuador]]
[[File:Gigantic Turtle on the Island of Santa Cruz in the Galapagos.JPG|277px|right|thumb|[[Galápagos tortoise]] on [[Santa Cruz Island (Galápagos)]]]]
[[File:Fresh Water Swimming in the Galapagos on the Island of Santa Cruz.JPG|277px|thumb|right|Fresh water swimming in Puerto Ayora, Galapagos on the Island of Santa Cruz.]]

=== La Costa ===
The western coastal area of Ecuador borders the [[Pacific Ocean]] to the west, encompasses a broad coastal plain, and then rises to the foothills of the [[Andes]] Mountains to the east. It is estimated that 98% of the native forest of coastal Ecuador has been eliminated in favor of cattle ranching and other agricultural production, including [[banana]], [[Cocoa bean|cacao]] and [[coffee]] plantations. The forest fragments that still survive are primarily found along the coastal mountain ranges of Mache-Chindul, [[Jama-Coaque Ecological Reserve|Jama-Coaque]], and Chongon-Colonche, and include tropical dry forest, tropical wet forest, tropical moist evergreen forest, premontane cloud forest, and mangrove forest. Collectively known as the [[Pacific Equatorial Forest]], these forest remnants are considered the most endangered tropical forest in the world, and are part of the Tumbes-Choco-Magdalena biodiversity hotspot.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Biodiversity Hotspots|url=http://www.biodiversityhotspots.org/xp/hotspots/tumbes_choco/Pages/default.aspx|work=Tumbes-Choco-Magdalena|accessdate=13 November 2011|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110809042100/http://www.biodiversityhotspots.org/xp/hotspots/tumbes_choco/Pages/default.aspx|archivedate=9 August 2011|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Guayaquil]], located on the southern part of the coast is the biggest city in the country. On the north coast of Ecuador the port of Balao in [[Esmeraldas (city)|Esmeraldas]] is used for oil export and the port of Manta was formerly used by the [[United States Air Force]] as a control point for narcotics traffic control until 2009.

=== La Sierra ===

[[Image:Imbabura des del sud.JPG|thumb|left|Mount Imbabura (Ecuador) from south-east]]

The central belt of Ecuador that includes the [[Andes]] Mountains, inland from the coast; with volcanoes and mountain peaks that sport year-round snow on the [[equator]]; many areas long since deforested by agriculture; a number of cut-flower growing operations; at a certain altitude zone may be found [[cloud forests]].

The northern Ecuadorian Andes are divided into three parallel [[cordillera]]s which run in what is similar to an S-shape from north to south: the western, central ([[Cordillera Real (Ecuador)|Cordillerra Real]]) and eastern ([[Cordillera Occidental (Ecuador)|Cordillera Occidental]]) cordilleras. The cordilleras were formed earlier in the [[Cenozoic]] era (the current geological era), as the [[Nazca Plate]] has [[subduction|subduct]]ed underneath the [[South American Plate]] and has raised the mountain range. In the south, the cordilleras are not well defined.

[[Quito]], the capital city, is located in a high mountain valley on the foothills of the [[Pichincha (volcano)]. The town of [[Baños de Agua Santa] features [[hot spring]s swimming pools on the foothills of the [[Tungurahua]] in the Central Cordillera. The road from Baños to Puyo has long been known for its narrowness, curves and sheer drops (only one lane in some places, on one area, actually cut into the side of a cliff so that the cliff roofs over it). The most important east-west road across the Andes is the road from Quito to Lago Agrio, which is paved for most of its length yet is heavily traveled by tractor-trailers—and the Trans-Ecuadorian Oil Pipeline serves as the guardrail for long stretches of this road.

==== Notable Mountains and Volcanoes ====
{{Volcanoes in Ecuador}}
[[Image:Ecuador Chimborazo fromnorthwest.JPG|right|thumb|The volcano Chimborazo from the Northwest]]

* [[Chimborazo (volcano)|Chimborazo]] (6,267 m) inactive volcano, the furthest point from the Earth's center.
* [[Cotopaxi]] (5,897 m) is the tallest active volcano in the world.
* [[Illiniza]] 	(5,248 m)
* [[Tungurahua]] (5,023 m) It is an active volcano in eruption since 1998 near Baños-Tunguragua
* [[Pichincha (volcano)|Pichincha]] (4,784 m) volcano overlooking Quito

Partial, incomplete table of volcanoes in the north of the Ecuadorian Andes, from north to south:
{| border cellspacing=0
|-
| West || Interandean || Center || East
|-
| Chiles&lt;br /&gt;[[Yanaurcu (Ecuador)|Yanaurcu]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Pichincha (volcano)|Pichincha]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Atacazo]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Corazón (volcano)|Corazón]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Carihuairazo]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Chimborazo (volcano)|Chimborazo]] || [[Imbabura Volcano|Imbabura]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Mojanda]]&lt;br /&gt;Ilaló&lt;br /&gt;[[Pasochoa]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Rumiñahui (volcano)|Rumiñahui]]&lt;br /&gt; || [[Cayambe (volcano)|Cayambe]]&lt;br /&gt;Saraurcu&lt;br /&gt;Pambamarca&lt;br /&gt;Filocorrales&lt;br /&gt;[[Antisana]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Sincholagua Volcano|Sincholahua]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Cotopaxi]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Tungurahua]]&lt;br /&gt;[[El Altar|Altar]]|| [[Soche]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Sumaco]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Reventador]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Sangay]]
|}

=== El Oriente (the East) Amazon Basin ===

Much of the Oriente is [[tropical moist broadleaf forest]] (Spanish: ''la selva''), on the east slopes of the [[Andes]] Mountains and descending into the [[Amazon Basin]], with strikingly different upland rainforest with steep, rugged ridges and cascading streams (can be seen around [[Puyo, Pastaza|Puyo]]) and lowland rainforest. The oil fields are located in the Amazon basin, headquartered at [[Lago Agrio]]; some of the rainforest has been seriously damaged in this region and environmental degradation is severe, with catastrophic oil pollution in some areas. Some 38% of Ecuador's land is forested,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://rainforests.mongabay.com/deforestation/2000/Ecuador.htm |title=Ecuador Forest Information and Data |publisher=Rainforests.mongabay.com |date= |accessdate=2012-11-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; and despite a 1.5% annual deforestation rate remains one of the most [[biodiversity|biodiverse]] locations on the planet. The Oriente is also home to a large number of Ecuador's indigenous groups, notably the lowland [[Quechuas|Quechua]], [[Siona people|Siona]], [[Secoya people|Secoya]], [[Huaorani]], and [[Cofán]].
[[File:Andes Mountains South America Photograph 022.JPG|thumb|Imbabura Volcano photographed in black and white.]]

== Drainage ==

{{Main|Rivers of Ecuador}}

[[Image:Ecuador Pastazas near Banos.JPG|thumb|left|Pastazas river near Baños, Ecuador]]

Almost all of the rivers in Ecuador rise in the Sierra region and flow east toward the Amazon River or west toward the Pacific Ocean. The rivers rise from snowmelt at the edges of the snowcapped peaks or from the abundant precipitation that falls at higher elevations. In the Sierra region, the streams and rivers are narrow and flow rapidly over precipitous slopes. Rivers may slow and widen as they cross the hoyas yet become rapid again as they flow from the heights of the Andes to the lower elevations of the other regions. The highland rivers broaden as they enter the more level areas of the Costa and the Oriente.

In the Costa region, the Costa Externa has mostly intermittent rivers that are fed by constant rains from December through May and become empty riverbeds during the dry season. The few exceptions are the longer, perennial rivers that flow throughout the Costa Externa from the Costa Internal and the Sierra on their way to the Pacific Ocean. The Costa Internal, by contrast, is crossed by perennial rivers that may flood during the rainy season, sometimes forming swamps.

The Guayas River system, which flows southward to the Gulf of Guayaquil, constitutes the most important of the drainage systems in the Costa Internal. The Guayas River Basin, including land drained by its tributaries, is 40,000 square kilometers in area. The sixty-kilometer-long Guayas River forms just north of Guayaquil out of the confluence of the Babahoyo and Daule rivers. Briefly constricted at Guayaquil by hills, the Guayas widens south of the city and flows through a deltaic network of small islands and channels. At its mouth, the river forms a broad estuary with two channels around Puná Island, the deeper of which is used for navigation.

The second major Costa river system—the Esmeraldas—rises in the Hoya de Quito in the Sierra as the Guayllabamba River and flows westward to empty into the Pacific Ocean near the city of Esmeraldas. The Esmeraldas River is 320 kilometers long and has a 20,000-square-kilometer drainage basin.

Major rivers in the Oriente include the [[Pastaza River|Pastaza]], [[Napo River|Napo]], and [[Putumayo River|Putumayo]]. The Pastaza is formed by the confluence of the Chambo and the Patate rivers, both of which rise in the Sierra. The Pastaza includes the Agoyan waterfall, which at sixty-one meters is the highest waterfall in Ecuador. The Napo rises near Mount Cotopaxi and is the major river used for transport in the Eastern lowlands. The Napo ranges in width from 500 to 1,800 meters. In its upper reaches, the Napo flows rapidly until the confluence with one of its major tributaries, the Coca River, where it slows and levels off. The Putumayo forms part of the border with Colombia. All of these rivers flow into the Amazon River. The Galápagos Islands have no significant rivers. Several of the larger islands, however, have freshwater springs.

== Climate ==

{{Main|Climate of Ecuador}}
[[File:Koppen-Geiger Map ECU present.svg|thumb|300px|Ecuador map of Köppen climate classification zones]]
[[Image:Ecuador ParamosnearAmbato.JPG|thumb|Paramo meadows near Ambato, Ecuador]]

Each region has different factors that affect its climate. The Costa is influenced primarily by proximity to warm or cool ocean currents. By contrast, climate in the Sierra varies more as a function of altitude. The Oriente has a fairly uniform climate that varies only slightly between the two subregions. Climate in the Galápagos Islands is both moderated by the ocean currents and affected by altitude. Throughout Ecuador variation in rainfall primarily determines seasons. Temperature is determined by altitude. With each ascent of {{convert|200|m|ft|0|sp=us}} in altitude, temperature drops {{convert|1|C-change}}. This phenomenon is particularly significant in the Sierra.

=== The Sierra ===

Temperatures in the Sierra do not vary greatly on a seasonal basis; the hottest month averages {{convert|16|°C|1}} and the coolest month, {{convert|13|°C|1}} in the upper elevations. Diurnal temperatures, however, vary dramatically, from cold mornings to hot afternoons. The almost vertical sun and the rarefied air in the higher Sierra region allow the land to warm quickly during the day and lose heat quickly at night. Mornings typically are bright and sunny, whereas afternoons often are cloudy and rainy. In general, rainfall amounts are highest on exposed locations at lower altitudes. Rain can also vary on a local basis. Sheltered valleys normally receive {{convert|500|mm|in|1|sp=us}} per year, whereas annual rainfall is {{convert|1500|mm|in|1|sp=us}} in Quito and can reach {{convert|2500|mm|in|1|sp=us}} on exposed slopes that catch rain-bearing winds. On a seasonal basis, the driest months are June through September.

The climate in the Sierra is divided into levels based on altitude. The tropical level—{{convert|400|to|1800|m|ft|0|sp=us}}—has temperatures ranging from {{convert|20|to|25|°C|°F|1}} and heavy precipitation. The subtropical level—{{convert|1800|to|2500|m|ft|0|sp=us}}—has temperatures from {{convert|15|to|20|°C|°F}} and moderate precipitation. The temperate level—≤{{convert|2500|to|3200|m|ft|0|sp=us}}≥- -has a year-round temperature in the range of {{convert|10|to|15|°C|°F}} and an annual rainfall of {{convert|1000|mm|in|1|sp=us}}. The temperate level experiences rainstorms, hailstorms, and fog. Winter, or the rainy season, lasts from January through June, and the dry season or summer from July through December. Most rain falls in April. There also is a short rainy period in early October caused by moisture penetrating the Sierra from the Oriente. Quito and most other populated areas in the Sierra are located at this temperate level. The cold level extends from the temperate zone to {{convert|4650|m|ft|0|sp=us}}. Here, average temperatures are {{convert|3|to|9|°C|°F|1}}, and the precipitation often appears in the form of rain, hail, and thick fog. Above {{convert|4650|m|ft|0|sp=us}} is the frozen level, where peaks are constantly capped with snow and ice, and temperatures range from below {{convert|0|to|3|°C|°F|1}}. Precipitation frequently is in the form of snow, fog, and rain.

=== The Oriente/Amazon Basin ===

The eastern lowlands in the Oriente experience abundant rainfall, especially in the Andean Piedmont, sometimes exceeding {{convert|5000|mm|in|1|sp=us}} per year. Temperatures average {{convert|25|°C}} in the western parts of this region. The jungle-covered plains of the Eastern lowlands register high levels of rainfall and temperatures surpassing {{convert|28|°C|1}}.

Being located on the equator, the Galápagos Islands would have an equatorial climate were it not for the modifying effects of the [[Humboldt Current|Peruvian Current]]. Instead, climate on the islands follows a pattern more like that of the Sierra than the Costa. At sea level, the land is desertlike with temperatures of {{convert|21|°C|1}}. The eight summer months experience no precipitation, whereas the winter months of January through April have some fog and drizzle. Above sea level to an altitude of {{convert|450|m|ft|0|sp=us}}, the islands have a mixture of tropical, subtropical, and temperate climates. In general, temperatures are around {{convert|17|°C|1}}. There is constant fog and drizzle in the summer and rain in the winter. The cold level above {{convert|450|m|ft|0|sp=us}} has temperatures below {{convert|14|°C|1}}. It is cool along the tropical coast.

== Elevation extremes ==

* lowest point: Pacific Ocean 0 m
* highest point: [[Chimborazo]] 6,267 m

== Natural resources ==
Ecuador has land which is rich in petroleum. Main fishing products include [[herring]] and [[mackerel]]. Other natural resources include timber and hydropower.

== Land use ==
* arable land: 4.62%
* permanent crops: 5.57%
* other: 89.81% (2012 est.)

=== Irrigated land ===
8,534&amp;nbsp;km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; (2003)

=== Total renewable water resources ===
424.4 km&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; (2011)

=== Freshwater withdrawal (domestic/industrial/agricultural) ===
* total: 9.92 km&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;/yr (13%/6%/81%)
* per capita: 716.1 m&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;/yr (2005)

== Natural hazards ==
Natural hazards in Ecuador include frequent [[List of earthquakes in Ecuador|earthquakes]], landslides, [[volcano|volcanic]] activity; periodic droughts and floods.

== Environment - current issues ==

[[deforestation]]; [[soil erosion]]; [[desertification]]; water pollution; pollution from oil production wastes in ecologically sensitive areas of the Amazon Basin and Galápagos Islands.

== Environment - international agreements ==

: '''party to:''' [[Antarctic Treaty]], [[Antarctic-Environmental Protocol]], [[Biodiversity]], [[United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change|Climate Change]], Climate Change-[[Kyoto Protocol]], [[Desertification]], [[Endangered Species]], [[Hazardous Wastes]], [[Nuclear Test Ban]], [[Ozone Layer Protection]], [[Ship Pollution]], [[Tropical Timber 83]], [[Tropical Timber 94]], [[Wetlands]], [[Whaling]]				

== Extreme points ==

* Northernmost point – [[Darwin Island]], [[Galápagos Islands]]
* Northernmost point (mainland) – [[Esmeraldas Province]]
* Southernmost point – Border with [[Peru]], [[Chinchipe Canton]]
* Westernmost point – [[Fernandina Island]], [[Galápagos Islands]]
* Westernmost point (mainland) – [[Cabo Pasado]]
* Easternmost point – border with [[Peru]], [[Orellana Province]]
* Highest point – [[Chimborazo]]: 6,267 m
* Lowest point – Pacific Coast: 0 m

== References ==

{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
{{Portal| Ecuador }}

* {{cite web
| url         = http://lcweb2.loc.gov/frd/cs/ectoc.html
| title       = A Country Study: Ecuador
| year        = 1989
| work        = [[Library of Congress Country Studies]]
| publisher   = [[Library of Congress]]
| location    = Washington, DC
}}

{{Geography of South America}}
{{Ecuador topics}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Geography Of Ecuador}}
[[Category:Geography of Ecuador| ]]</text>
      <sha1>rol20rwp2h8whp3jfz5rlhr62td1ck4</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
