  <page>
    <title>Accusative case</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2251</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942706329</id>
      <parentid>942694947</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-26T09:30:31Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Megaman en m</username>
        <id>7269056</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Armenian */ If the accusative in Armenian is not a morphological category or has a different form, why bother mentioning it?</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Grammatical case used to mark the direct object of a transitive verb}}
{{More citations needed|date=July 2019}}
The '''accusative case''' ([[list of glossing abbreviations|abbreviated]] {{sc|'''acc'''}}) is a linguistics term for a [[grammatical case]] relating to how some languages typically mark a [[direct object]] of a [[transitive verb]]. Among those languages, analogous marking principles often apply to the objects of (some or all) [[preposition]]s. The characteristics of an accusative case often entails (such as in [[Latin]]) what generally is termed the [[nominative case]].

The English term, &quot;accusative,&quot; derives from the Latin {{wikt-lang|la|accusativus}}, which, in turn, is a translation of the Greek {{wikt-lang|grc|αἰτιατική}}. The word may also mean &quot;causative&quot;, and this may have been the Greeks' intention in this name,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?term=accusative Douglas Harper, Online Etymology Dictionary]&lt;/ref&gt; but the sense of the Roman translation has endured and is used in some other modern languages as the grammatical term for this case, for example in Russian ({{wikt-lang|ru|винительный}}).

The accusative case is typical of early [[Indo-European languages]] and still exists in some of them (including [[Latin]], [[Sanskrit]], [[Greek language|Greek]], [[German language|German]], [[Polish language|Polish]], [[Russian language|Russian]]), in the [[Finno-Ugric languages]], and in [[Semitic languages]] (such as [[Arabic language|Arabic]]). [[Balto-Finnic languages]], such as Finnish and Estonian, have two cases to mark objects, the accusative and the [[partitive case]]. In [[morphosyntactic alignment]] terms, both perform the accusative function, but the accusative object is [[Telicity|telic]], while the partitive is not.

Modern [[English language|English]] almost entirely lacks [[declension]] in its nouns; pronouns, however, have an [[oblique case]] as in ''whom'', ''them'', and ''her'', which merges the accusative and dative functions, and originates in old Germanic dative forms (see [[Declension in English]]).

==Example==
In the sentence ''I see '''the car''''', the [[noun phrase]] ''the car'' is the direct object of the verb &quot;see&quot;. In English, which has mostly lost the case system, the definite article and noun&amp;nbsp;– &quot;the car&quot;&amp;nbsp;– remain in the same form regardless of the grammatical role played by the words. One can correctly use &quot;the car&quot; as the subject of a sentence also: &quot;The car is parked here.&quot;

In a declined language, the [[Morphology (linguistics)|morphology]] of the article or noun changes in some way according to the grammatical role played by the noun in a given sentence. For example, in [[German language|German]], one possible translation of &quot;the car&quot; is {{lang|de|der Wagen}}. This is the form in the [[nominative case]], used for the subject of a sentence. If this article/noun pair is used as the object of a verb, it (usually) changes to the accusative case, which entails an article shift in German&amp;nbsp;– {{lang|de|Ich sehe '''den Wagen'''}}. In German, masculine nouns change their definite article from {{lang|de|der}} to {{lang|de|den}} in the accusative case.

{{see also|Morphosyntactic alignment}}

== Latin ==
The accusative case in Latin has minor differences from the accusative case in Proto-Indo-European (PIE). 
Nouns in the accusative case ({{lang|la|accusativus}}) can be used
* as a [[object (grammar)|direct object]].
* to indicate duration of time. E.g., {{lang|la|multos annos}}, &quot;for many years&quot;; ''ducentos annos'', &quot;for 200 years.&quot;  This is known as the '''accusative of duration of time'''.
* to indicate direction towards which. E.g. {{lang|la|domum}}, &quot;homewards&quot;; {{lang|la|Romam}}, &quot;to Rome&quot; with no preposition needed. This is known as the '''accusative of place to which''', and is equivalent to the [[lative case]] found in some other languages.
* as the subject of an [[indirect statement]] (e.g. {{lang|la|Dixit '''me''' fuisse saevum}}, &quot;He said that '''I''' had been cruel;&quot; in later Latin works, such as the [[Vulgate]], such a construction is replaced by ''quod'' and a regularly structured sentence, having the subject in the nominative: e.g., {{lang|la|Dixit quod '''ego''' fueram saevus}}).
* with case-specific prepositions such as {{lang|la|per}} (through), {{lang|la|ad}} (to/toward), and {{lang|la|trans}} (across).
* in exclamations, such as {{lang|la|me miseram}}, &quot;wretched me&quot; (spoken by [[Circe]] to [[Odysseus|Ulysses]] in [[Ovid]]'s {{lang|la|Remedium Amoris}}; note that this is feminine: the masculine form would be {{lang|la|me miser&lt;ins&gt;um&lt;/ins&gt;}}).
*to indicate purpose. E.g. ''ad profiscendum,'' &quot;for the purpose of leaving&quot;; ''ad effēminandōs animōs,'' &quot;for the purpose of weakening [or, effeminating] the spirit.&quot;

For the accusative endings, see [[Latin declension]]s.

== German ==
The accusative case is used for the direct object in a sentence. The masculine forms for [[German articles]], e.g., 'the', 'a/an', 'my', etc., change in the accusative case: they always end in -en. The feminine, neutral and plural forms do not change.
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!
! Masculine
! Feminine
! Neuter
! Plural
|-
| Definite article (the)
| {{lang|de|den}}
| {{lang|de|die}}
| {{lang|de|das}}
| {{lang|de|die}}
|-
| Indefinite article (a/an)
| {{lang|de|einen}}
| {{lang|de|eine}}
| {{lang|de|ein}}
| 
|}

For example, {{lang|de|Hund}} (dog) is a masculine ({{lang|de|der}}) word, so the article changes when used in the accusative case:
*{{lang|de|Ich habe einen Hund}}. (lit., I have a dog.) In the sentence &quot;a dog&quot; is in the accusative case as it is the second idea (the [[Object (grammar)|object]]) of the sentence.

Some [[German pronouns]] also change in the accusative case.

The accusative case is also used after particular German prepositions. These include {{lang|de|bis}}, {{lang|de|durch}}, {{lang|de|für}}, {{lang|de|gegen}}, {{lang|de|ohne}}, {{lang|de|um}}, after which the accusative case is always used, and {{lang|de|an}}, {{lang|de|auf}}, {{lang|de|hinter}}, {{lang|de|in}}, {{lang|de|neben}}, {{lang|de|über}}, {{lang|de|unter}}, {{lang|de|vor}}, {{lang|de|zwischen}} which can govern either the accusative or the dative. The latter prepositions take the accusative when motion or action is specified (being done into/onto the space), but take the dative when location is specified (being done in/on that space). These prepositions are also used in conjunction with certain verbs, in which case it is the verb in question which governs whether the accusative or dative should be used.

Adjective endings also change in the accusative case. Another factor that determines the endings of adjectives is whether the adjective is being used after a definite article (the), after an indefinite article (a/an) or without any article before the adjective (''many'' green apples).
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!
! Masculine
! Feminine
! Neuter
! Plural
|-
| Definite article
| {{lang|de|-en}}
| {{lang|de|-e}}
| {{lang|de|-e}}
| {{lang|de|-en}}
|-
| Indefinite Article
| {{lang|de|-en}}
| {{lang|de|-e}}
| {{lang|de|-es}}
| {{lang|de|-en}}
|-
| No article
| {{lang|de|-en}}
| {{lang|de|-e}}
| {{lang|de|-es}}
| {{lang|de|-e}}
|}

In German, the accusative case is also used for some adverbial expressions, mostly temporal ones, as in {{lang|de|Diesen Abend bleibe ich daheim}} (This evening I'm staying at home), where {{lang|de|diesen Abend}} is marked as accusative, although not a direct object.

== Russian ==
In Russian, accusative is used not only to display the direct object of an action, but also to indicate the destination or goal of motion. It is also used with some prepositions. The prepositions {{lang|ru|в}} and {{lang|ru|на}} can both take accusative in situations where they are indicating the goal of a motion.

In the [[Grammatical gender|masculine]], Russian also distinguishes between [[animacy|animate and inanimate]] nouns with regard to the accusative; only the animates carry a [[marker (linguistics)|marker]] in this case.

In fact Russian almost lost the real PIE accusative case, since only feminine nouns ending in 'a' have a distinct form. Other words use the genitive case in place of the accusative.

== Esperanto ==
[[Esperanto grammar]] involves only two cases, a nominative and an accusative. The accusative is formed by the addition of {{lang|eo|-n}} to the nominative form, and is the case used for direct objects. Other objective functions, including dative functions are achieved with prepositions, all of which normally take the nominative case. Direction of motion can be expressed either by the accusative case, or by the preposition {{lang|eo|al}} (to) with the nominative.
Direct object example: &quot;Red apple&quot;: {{lang|eo|Ruĝa pomo}}; &quot;I have a red apple.&quot;: {{lang|eo|Mi havas ruĝan pomon.}}

== Ido ==
In [[Ido language|Ido]] the {{lang|io|-n}} suffix is optional, as [[subject-verb-object]] order is assumed when it is not present. Note that this is sometimes done in Esperanto, especially by beginners, but it is considered incorrect while in Ido it is the norm.

== Finnish ==
According to traditional Finnish grammars, the accusative is the case of a total object, while the case of a partial object is the [[partitive case|partitive]]. The accusative is identical either to the [[nominative case|nominative]] or the [[genitive case|genitive]], except for [[personal pronoun]]s and the personal [[interrogative pronoun]] {{lang|fi|kuka}}/{{lang|fi|ken}}, which have a special accusative form ending in {{lang|fi|-t}}.

The major new Finnish grammar, {{lang|fi|[[Iso suomen kielioppi]]}}, breaks with the traditional classification to limit the accusative case to the special case of the personal pronouns and {{lang|fi|kuka}}/{{lang|fi|ken}}. The new grammar considers other total objects as being in the nominative or genitive case.

== Semitic languages ==

Accusative case marking existed in [[Proto-Semitic]], [[Akkadian language|Akkadian]], and [[Ugaritic]]. It is  preserved today only in [[Modern Standard Arabic]] and [[Ge'ez]].

'''Accusative in Akkadian'''

:Nominative: {{transl|akk|awīlum}} (a/the man)
:Accusative: {{transl|akk|apaqqid awīlam}} (I trust a/the man)

'''Accusative in Arabic'''

:Nominative: {{transl|ar|rajulun}} (a man)
:Accusative: {{transl|ar|as'alu rajulan}} (I ask a man) {{transl|ar|as'alu ar-rajula}} (I ask the man)

The accusative case is called in Arabic {{lang|ar|النصب}} ({{transl|ar|an-naṣb}}, and it has many other uses in addition to marking the object of a verb.

== Japanese ==
{{expand section|date=April 2019}}
In Japanese, the accusative case is marked by placing を ([[Romanization of Japanese|wo]], pronounced {{IPA|/o̞/}}) between the noun and the verb.

== See also ==
*[[Nota accusativi]]

==Further reading==
* {{cite book |last= Karlsson |first= Fred |year= 2018 |title= Finnish - A Comprehensive Grammar |location= London and New York |publisher= Routledge |isbn= 978-1-138-82104-0}}
* {{cite web |last= Anhava |first= Jaakko |year= 2015 |title= Criteria For Case Forms in Finnish and Hungarian Grammars |location= Helsinki |website= journal.fi |publisher= Finnish Scholarly Journals Online |url= https://journal.fi/store/article/view/52392/16242}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Grammatical cases}}

[[Category:Grammatical cases]]</text>
      <sha1>0a7ibfspmf0kblj2jur7hlgy5emkl8x</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
