  <page>
    <title>Cobble Hill Tunnel</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2244</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942084488</id>
      <parentid>937096861</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-22T14:14:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Djkeddie</username>
        <id>1884088</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* Dormancy */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|Atlantic Avenue Tunnel|the active Long Island Rail Road tunnels|Atlantic Branch}}
{{short description|Railway tunnel in Brooklyn, New York City}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=February 2018}}
{{Infobox NRHP
| name =Cobble Hill Historic District
| nrhp_type = hd  | nocat = yes
| image = Atlantic Ave Tunnel.jpg
| caption = (2009)
| location= [[Brooklyn]], New York City
| coordinates = {{coord|40|41|25.6|N|73|59|42.5|W|display=title}}
| locmapin = New York City#New York#USA
| built = 1844
| architect = Asa Stebbins
| architecture = [[Roman architecture|Roman]], [[Italianate]], [[Queen Anne style architecture in the United States|Queen Anne]]
| added = September 7, 1989
| refnum= 89001388&lt;ref name=&quot;nris&quot;&gt;{{NRISref|2008a|dateform=mdy}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
The '''Cobble Hill Tunnel''' (also known as the '''Atlantic Avenue Tunnel''') is an abandoned [[Long Island Rail Road]] (LIRR) tunnel beneath [[Atlantic Avenue (New York City)|Atlantic Avenue]] in [[Brooklyn]], New York City, running through the neighborhoods of [[Downtown Brooklyn]] and [[Cobble Hill, Brooklyn|Cobble Hill]]. When open, it ran for about {{convert|2517|ft|m}} between Columbia Street and Boerum Place.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.brooklynrail.net/proj_aatunnel.html|date=December 2017|title=The Atlantic Avenue Tunnel}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is the oldest [[railway tunnel]] beneath a city street in North America that was fully devoted to rail.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.psfk.com/2009/03/notes-from-the-underground-the-secret-tunnels-of-brooklyn.html|title=Notes from the Underground: The Secret Tunnels of Brooklyn|last=Hilger|first=James|date=March 23, 2009|publisher=psfk.com|accessdate=April 8, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://citynoise.org/article/8748 Citynoise: Oldest Subway Tunnel in the World] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160303181702/http://citynoise.org/article/8748 |date=March 3, 2016 }} Retrieved April 8, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;{{efn|There are two tunnels on the [[Park Avenue main line]] in Manhattan that are older, but were used by horse-drawn carriages rather than true railways. A tunnel stretching {{Convert|596|feet|meters|abbr=}} was completed through Prospect Hill, one of the highest points on the East Side of Manhattan, between 92nd and 95th Streets, in 1837.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://s-media.nyc.gov/agencies/lpc/lp/2547.pdf|title=Park Avenue Historic District Designation Report|last=|first=|date=April 29, 2014|website=nyc.gov|publisher=New York City Landmarks Preservation Commission|access-date=December 31, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Rp|5–6}} In addition, the [[Park Avenue Tunnel (roadway)|Park Avenue Tunnel]] between 33rd and 40th Streets in Manhattan, was opened in 1834.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=PARK AVENUE TUNNEL | website=Forgotten New York | date=December 6, 2012 | url=http://forgotten-ny.com/2012/12/park-avenue-tunnel/ | access-date=January 21, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

== Construction and operation ==
Originally built as an open cutting, construction began in May 1844, and opened for use on December 3, 1844, but was not completely finished until late Spring 1845. It was built mainly to satisfy public demand for creation of a [[Grade separation|grade-separated]] [[Right-of-way (railroad)|right of way]] for the [[Brooklyn and Jamaica Railroad]] (later Long Island Rail Road) on its way to the [[South Ferry, Brooklyn|South Ferry]] at the foot of Atlantic Street (later Atlantic Avenue), where passengers could catch ferries to [[Manhattan]].&lt;ref name=&quot;BHRA&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.brooklynrail.net/images/aa_tunnel/new_research/oct_09/events_leading_to_tunnel_creation.pdf|title=Events That Led to the Creation of the Atlantic Avenue Tunnel|publisher=Brooklyn Historic Railway Association|accessdate=October 29, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; The construction of the cutting also lowered the LIRR's grade through [[Cobble Hill, Brooklyn|Cobble Hill]]. Around five years after opening the cutting was roofed over, converting it into a tunnel.

In exchange for building the cutting, the [[City of Brooklyn]] granted the B&amp;J permission to operate its steam locomotives on Atlantic Street west of Fifth Avenue (then Parmentier's Garden/Gowanus Lane), all the way to Brooklyn's South Ferry (the present location of Brooklyn's Pier 7). Prior to the cutting being built, the LIRR's western terminus was Atlantic Street at Clinton Street. Train cars were hauled by teams of horses along Atlantic Street from Clinton Street to Parmentier's Garden, where steam locomotives were attached. While the cutting was being built, the railroad operated to a temporary terminal at Pacific Street and Henry Street.

The Cobble Hill Tunnel was part of the first rail link between New York City and [[Boston|Boston, Massachusetts]].{{Citation needed|date=February 2009}} The railroad connected [[Lower Manhattan]] via the South Ferry to [[Greenport, Suffolk County, New York|Greenport]] on the [[North Fork, Suffolk County, New York|North Fork]] of [[Long Island]], where a ferry connected to [[Stonington, Connecticut]], where a rail link continued to Boston. This avoided some difficult construction of bridges over the rivers of southern [[Connecticut]]. In 1848, the [[New York and New Haven Railroad]] Line was completed through Connecticut, providing a direct, faster rail connection from New York City to Boston. The Cobble Hill Tunnel and the Long Island Railroad remained the primary means of access to most of central Long Island from Manhattan and New York City. As originally built, the cutting was {{convert|21|ft|m}} wide and {{convert|2517|ft|m}} long. Once roofed over the interior height of the newly created tunnel was {{convert|17|ft|m}}.

The ends of the tunnel were sealed in the fall of 1861. The similar [[Murray Hill Tunnel]] on the [[New York and Harlem Railroad]] was built as an open cut around 1836, roofed over around the 1850s, and is now in use for automobile traffic.

== Closure controversy ==
In 1861, the [[New York State Legislature]] voted to ban railroad locomotives from within the limits of the [[City of Brooklyn]]. A tax assessment was ordered on all property owners along Atlantic Street (today Atlantic Avenue), to defray the costs of the closure. It was undisclosed at the time that [[New York State]] Governor [[John A. King]] was a major [[shareholder]] in the Brooklyn and [[Jamaica, Queens|Jamaica]] Railroad (later the [[Long Island Rail Road]]) and therefore had a conflict of interest and stood to benefit by the compensation payments to the railroad from the tax assessment.{{Citation needed|date=February 2009}}

== Dormancy ==
[[Walt Whitman]] wrote of the tunnel:&lt;ref name=CB&gt;{{cite web|title=Crossing Brooklyn LIRR Tunnel |work=Forgotten NY |url=http://www.forgotten-ny.com/SUBWAYS/tunnel/tunnel.html |accessdate=February 9, 2009 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20081226062020/http://www.forgotten-ny.com/SUBWAYS/tunnel/tunnel.html |archivedate=December 26, 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;The old tunnel, that used to lie there under ground, a passage of [[Acheron]]-like solemnity and darkness, now all closed and filled up, and soon to be utterly forgotten, with all its reminiscences; however, there will, for a few years yet be many dear ones, to not a few Brooklynites, New Yorkers, and promiscuous crowds besides. For it was here you started to go down the island, in summer. For years, it was confidently counted on that this spot, and the railroad of which it was the terminus, were going to prove the permanent seat of business and wealth that belong to such enterprises. But its glory, after enduring in great splendor for a season, has now vanished—at least its Long Island Railroad glory has. The tunnel: dark as the grave, cold, damp, and silent. How beautiful look earth and heaven again, as we emerge from the gloom! It might not be unprofitable, now and then, to send us mortals—the dissatisfied ones, at least, and that's a large proportion—into some tunnel of several days' journey. We'd perhaps grumble less, afterward, at God's handiwork.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In March 1916, the [[FBI|Bureau of Investigation]] suspected German terrorists were making bombs in the tunnel, and broke through the roof of the tunnel with jackhammers. They found nothing, installed an electric light, and resealed it. In the 1920s, it was rumored to be used for both mushroom growing and bootleg whiskey stills, even though there was no access into the main portion of the tunnel. It became an object of local folklore and legend. In 1936, the [[New York City Police Department]] unsuccessfully attempted to enter the tunnel, in order to look for the body of a hoodlum supposedly buried there. In 1941, it was rumored to have been inspected by the federal [[Works Progress Administration]] to determine its structural strength, but there is no evidence of this. A few years later, it was once again rumored to have been opened, this time by the FBI, in an unsuccessful search for spies; however, there is no evidence of this. During the late 1950s, it was sought by two rail historians, George Horn and Martin Schachne, but they did not gain access to the tunnel itself.

== Rediscovery ==
Having fallen from public notice, the tunnel was rediscovered in 1980 by then 20-year-old Robert Diamond,&lt;ref name=theverge /&gt; who entered from a manhole he located at Atlantic Avenue and Court Street, crawled a distance of {{convert|70|ft|m}} underground through a filled-in section of tunnel less than two feet high, and located the bulkhead wall that sealed off the main portion of the tunnel. With the assistance of a Brooklyn Union Gas Co. (now [[KeySpan|National Grid]]) engineering crew, he then broke through the massive concrete bulkhead wall, which is several feet thick. Diamond thereby opened access to the main portion of the tunnel, and began to popularize the tunnel as an antiquity. He led tours of its interior&lt;ref name=CB /&gt; from 1982 until December 17, 2010,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.nbcnewyork.com/news/local/Brooklyn-Underground-Tunnel-Tours-Are-Now-Six-Feet-Under-112103379.html|title=Brooklyn Underground Tunnel Tours Are Now Six Feet Under|website=NBC New York}}&lt;/ref&gt; when the [[New York State Department of Transportation|Department of Transportation]] terminated his contract, citing safety concerns.&lt;ref name=theverge&gt;[https://www.theverge.com/2014/2/5/5280920/tunnel-vision-bob-diamond-fights-for-the-atlantic-avenue-subway Tunnel vision: how an obsessed explorer found and lost the world's oldest subway]&lt;/ref&gt; The tunnel has been listed on the [[National Register of Historic Places]] since 1989.

The [[History (U.S. TV channel)|History Channel]] series ''[[Cities of the Underworld]]'' ran a segment (&quot;New York's Secret Societies&quot;) on the tunnel in Fall 2008.

== See also ==
{{Portal|Railways|New York City}}
* [[Beach Pneumatic Transit]]
* [[Brooklyn Historic Railway Association]]
* [[Park Avenue main line]], another railroad line in New York City that may have contained the oldest rail tunnels in the U.S.
* [[Track 61 (New York City)]]
* [[National Register of Historic Places listings in Kings County, New York]]

== References ==
'''Notes'''
{{notelist}}

'''Citations'''
{{Reflist}}

'''Further reading'''
{{Refbegin}}
* {{cite web | title=The Atlantic Avenue Tunnel | work=Brooklynrail.net | url=http://www.brooklynrail.net/proj_aatunnel.html| accessdate=July 31, 2009 }}
* {{cite web | title=Urban Underground Passageways An Historical Overview | work=Brooklynrail.net |url=http://www.brooklynrail.net/images/aa_tunnel/new_research/the_urban_underground_tunnel_draft_7_23_2010.pdf | accessdate=July 27, 2010 }}
* {{cite web | title=Early Transit in New York City | work=NYSubway.org | url=http://www.nycsubway.org/faq/earlysubway.html | accessdate=October 29, 2005 }}
* {{cite web | title=The Atlantic Avenue Tunnel | work=New York City Subway Transit Scenes | url=http://wt.mit.edu/Subway/Tunnel/ | accessdate=October 29, 2005 }}
* {{cite web | title=Brooklyn Historic Railway Association and Atlantic Avenue Tunnel | url=http://home.att.net/~Berliner-Ultrasonics/bhra.html | accessdate=October 29, 2005 | archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090418073537/http://home.att.net/~Berliner-Ultrasonics/bhra.html | archive-date=April 18, 2009 | url-status=dead | df=mdy-all }}
* {{cite web |title=A Long-Lost Tunnel in Brooklyn |work=LI History.com |url=http://www.newsday.com/community/guide/lihistory/ny-history-hs515d,0,6961092.story |accessdate=April 17, 2009 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20081013083617/http://www.newsday.com/community/guide/lihistory/ny-history-hs515d%2C0%2C6961092.story |archivedate=October 13, 2008 |df=mdy-all }}
* {{cite web | title=Cobble Hill (Atlantic Avenue) Tunnel History | work=RapidTransit.net | url=http://www.rapidtransit.net/net/faq/nyc/AtlanticTunnel.html | accessdate=October 29, 2005 | url-status=dead | archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20141010080245/http://www.rapidtransit.net/net/faq/nyc/AtlanticTunnel.html | archivedate=October 10, 2014 | df=mdy-all }}
* {{cite news | title=The Tunnel Rats of Atlantic Avenue | work=NYTimes.com | url=https://www.nytimes.com/2009/02/15/nyregion/thecity/15tunn.html | accessdate=April 29, 2009 | first=Yonette | last=Joseph | date=February 15, 2009}}
* {{cite web | title=The New York Moon – Undertone – Music video in the tunnel | work=nymoon.com | url=http://nymoon.com/pubs/undertone/ | accessdate=May 20, 2009 }}
* [http://www.arrts-arrchives.com/tunnel.html The Atlantic Avenue Tunnel (Arrt's Arrchives)]
{{refend}}

{{LIRR}}
{{National Register of Historic Places in New York|state=collapsed}}

[[Category:Transportation buildings and structures in Brooklyn]]
[[Category:Long Island Rail Road]]
[[Category:Railway tunnels on the National Register of Historic Places]]
[[Category:Railroad tunnels in New York City]]
[[Category:History of transportation in New York City]]
[[Category:National Register of Historic Places in New York City]]
[[Category:Historic districts on the National Register of Historic Places in New York (state)]]
[[Category:Tunnels completed in 1844]]
[[Category:Cobble Hill, Brooklyn]]
[[Category:National Register of Historic Places in Brooklyn]]
[[Category:Proposed buildings and structures in New York City]]
[[Category:Railway buildings and structures on the National Register of Historic Places in New York City]]
[[Category:1844 establishments in New York (state)]]</text>
      <sha1>95z869opv54vp5pasjenwu7tcscomo4</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
