  <page>
    <title>Acadia University</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2236</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942207829</id>
      <parentid>939157383</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-23T08:16:33Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>AussieLegend</username>
        <id>612255</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>[[WP:REFPUNCT]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Distinguish|Arcadia University}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2012}}
{{Infobox university
|name         = Acadia University
|native_name  = 
|latin_name   = 
|image        = AcadiaUShield.svg
|image_size   = 150px
|motto        = ''In pulvere vinces''
|mottoeng     = &quot;By effort (literally: in dust), you will conquer&quot;
|established  = {{start date and age|1838}}
|type         = [[Public University|Public]] [[Liberal Arts College|Liberal Arts University]]
|former_names = Queen's College (1838–1841)&lt;br&gt;Acadia College (1841–1891)
|campus       = {{Convert|250|acre|ha|0}}
|endowment    = $96 million
|city         = [[Wolfville, Nova Scotia|Wolfville]], [[Annapolis Valley]]
|state        = [[Nova Scotia]]
|country      = [[Canada]]
|coordinates  = {{Coord|45|05|16|N|64|21|58|W|region:CA-NS_type:edu|display=inline,title}}
|students     = 3,737&lt;ref name=&quot;Atlantic Universities&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.atlanticuniversities.ca/sites/default/files/documents/Full%20Time%20Enrolments%202018-19.pdf|title=Full-time plus Part-time Enrollment|date=2018-10-15|publisher=Association of Atlantic Universities|accessdate=2019-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|undergrad    = 3,549
|postgrad     = 188
|doctoral     = 
|staff        = 211 full-time, 37 part-time (as of 2008)
|president    = Peter Ricketts
|chancellor   = Libby Burnham&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release |title=Acadia Names Libby Burnham New Chancellor |publisher=Acadian university |author=Office of Alumni Affairs |date=6 May 2011 |url=http://www2.acadiau.ca/alumni-friends/alumni/news/alumni-news-reader/acadia-names-libby-burnham-new-chancellor-1518.html |accessdate=21 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|colours      = {{color box|#FF0000}} {{color box|#072B61}} [[Garnet (color)|Garnet]] and [[Blue (color)|blue]]
|mascot       = 
|nickname     = [[Acadia Axemen|Axemen]] and [[Acadia Axewomen|Axewomen]]
|athletics    = [[U Sports]] – [[Atlantic University Sport|AUS]]
|affiliation  = currently non-denominational; initially founded by Baptists
|affiliations = [[Association of Universities and Colleges of Canada|AUCC]], [[International Association of Universities|IAU]], [[Canadian University Society for Intercollegiate Debate|CUSID]], [[Canadian Bureau for International Education|CBIE]], [[Canadian University Press|CUP]]
|logo         = Acadia University Wordmark 2014.svg
|website      = {{url|acadiau.ca}}
}}

'''Acadia University''' is a public, predominantly undergraduate [[university]] located in [[Wolfville]], [[Nova Scotia]], Canada with some graduate programs at the master's level&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |title=Acadia University |encyclopedia=[[The Canadian Encyclopedia]] |publisher=[[Historica Canada]] |edition=online |first=Barry M. |last=Moody |date=13 June 2014 |url=http://www.thecanadianencyclopedia.com/en/article/acadia-university/ |accessdate=21 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; and one at the doctoral level.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.acadiadiv.ca/doctor-of-ministry/ |title=Acadia Doctor of Ministry program |work=Acadia Divinity College |accessdate=21 September 2015 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150925105427/http://www.acadiadiv.ca/doctor-of-ministry/ |archive-date=25 September 2015 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; The enabling legislation consists of Acadia University Act&lt;ref&gt;{{cite report |url=http://board.acadiau.ca/tl_files/sites/board/resources/PDF%20Files/Act_of_Incorporation.pdf |title=Act of Incorporation |author=Board of Governors |date=19 May 1891 |work= |publisher=Acadia University |accessdate=30 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the Amended Acadia University Act 2000.&lt;ref name=&quot;Amendment Act&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Acadia University Act (Amended) - Bill No. 44 |first=Mark |last=Parent |author-link=Mark Parent |date=17 April 2000 |url=http://nslegislature.ca/legc/bills/58th_1st/1st_read/b044.htm |website=Nova Scotia Legislature |publisher=[[General Assembly of Nova Scotia]] |accessdate=21 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Wolfville Campus houses Acadia University Archives&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.museevirtuel-virtualmuseum.ca/GetMuseumProfile.do?lang=en&amp;chinCode=guaarl|archive-url=https://wayback.archive-it.org/all/20100430162327/http://www.museevirtuel-virtualmuseum.ca/GetMuseumProfile.do?lang=en&amp;chinCode=guaarl|url-status=dead|archive-date=30 April 2010|title=Acadia University Archives|website=wayback.archive-it.org|accessdate=16 August 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the Acadia University Art Gallery.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.museevirtuel-virtualmuseum.ca/GetMuseumProfile.do?lang=en&amp;chinCode=guaarm. |title=Acadia University Art Gallery |access-date=30 May 2013 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130925214728/http://www.museevirtuel-virtualmuseum.ca/GetMuseumProfile.do?lang=en |archive-date=25 September 2013 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Acadia offers over 200 degree combinations in the Faculties of Arts, Pure and Applied Science, Professional Studies, and Theology. The student-faculty ratio is 15:1 and the average class size is 28. Open Acadia offers correspondence and distance education courses.&lt;ref name=&quot;Acadia University&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Acadia University |url=http://www.aucc.ca/canadian-universities/our-universities/acadia-university/ |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110925192433/http://www.aucc.ca/canadian-universities/our-universities/acadia-university |archivedate=25 September 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

As of July 2017, Dr. Peter J. Ricketts is Acadia’s current president.

==History==
[[Image:Uhall31.JPG|thumb|right|University Hall at Acadia University]] Acadia began as an extension of Horton Academy (1828), which was founded in [[Horton, Nova Scotia]], by [[Baptists]] from Nova Scotia and Queen's College (1838).&lt;ref name=&quot;Longley, R. S 1938&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Longley |first=Robert Stewart |title=Acadia University, 1838–1938 |location=Wolfville, Nova Scotia |publisher=Acadia University |date=1939}}&lt;/ref&gt; The College was later named Acadia College.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Fitzhenry and Whiteside Book of Canadian Facts and Dates |url={{google books|pX4ZAQAAIAAJ|plainurl=yes|p=177}} |editor-last=Pound |editor-first=Richard W. |publisher=Fitzhenry and Whiteside |year=2005 |p=177 |isbn=978-1-5504-1171-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; Acadia University, established at [[Wolfville, Nova Scotia]] in 1838 has a strong [[Baptist]] religious affiliation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=John George |last=Bourinot |title=The Intellectual Development of the Canadian People |date=September 2004 |orig-year=1881 |edition=e-Text |url=http://www.gutenberg.org/dirs/etext04/tlctd10.txt |publisher=[[Project Gutenberg]] |accessdate=21 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
It was designed to prepare men for the ministry and to supply education for lay members.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |title=University |first1=P. |last1=Anisef |first2=P. |last2=Axelrod |first3=J. |last3=Lennards |date=20 July 2015 |work=The Canadian Enxyclopedia |publisher=Historica Canada |edition=online |url=http://www.thecanadianencyclopedia.com/en/article/university/ |accessdate=21 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The two major Universities of the day in Nova Scotia were heavily controlled by denominational structures. King's College ([[University of King's College]]) was an [[Anglican]] school and [[Dalhousie University]], which was originally non-denominational, had placed itself under the control and direction of the [[Church of Scotland]]. It was the failure of Dalhousie to appoint a prominent Baptist pastor and scholar, Edmund Crawley, to the Chair of [[Classics]], as had been expected, that really thrust into the forefront of Baptist thinking the need for a college established and run by the Baptists.

In 1838, the Nova Scotia Baptist Education Society founded Queen's College (named for Queen Victoria). The college began with 21 students in January 1839. The name &quot;Queen's College&quot; was denied to the Baptist school, so it was renamed &quot;Acadia College&quot; in 1841, in reference to the history of the area as an [[Acadian]] settlement. Acadia College awarded its first degrees in 1843 and became Acadia University in 1891,&lt;ref name=&quot;Longley, R. S 1938&quot;/&gt; established by the Acadia University Act.&lt;ref name=&quot;Amendment Act&quot;/&gt;

The Granville Street Baptist Church (now [[First Baptist Church (Halifax)]]) was an instrumental and determining factor in the founding of the university. It has played a supporting role throughout its history, and shares much of the credit for its survival and development. Many individuals who have made significant contributions to Acadia University, including the first president John Pryor, were members of the First Baptist Church Halifax congregation. Similarly, the adjacent Wolfville United Baptist Church plays a significant role in the life of the university.

The original charter of the college stated:

{{quote|And be it further enacted, that no religious tests or subscriptions shall be required of the Professors Fellows, Scholars, Graduates or Officers of the said College; but that all the privileges and advantages thereof shall be open and free to all and every Person and Persons whomsoever, without regard to religious persuasion&amp;nbsp;... And it shall and may be lawful for the trustees and Governors of the said College to select as Professors, and other Teaches or Officers, competent persons of any religious persuasion whatever, provided such person or persons shall be of moral and religious character.}}

This was unique at the time, and a direct result of Baptists being denied entry into other schools that required religious tests of their students and staff.

In 1851, the power of appointing governors was transferred from the Nova Scotia Baptist Education Society to the Baptist Convention of the Maritime Provinces.&lt;ref name=&quot;gutenberg.org&quot;&gt;{{cite book |editor-first1=Lawrence J. |editor-last1=Burpee |editor-first2=Arthur |editor-last2=Doughty |title=The Makers of Canada: Index and Dictionary of Canadian History |publisher= Morang &amp; Co. |location=Toronto, Ontario |date=1912 |edition=Project Gutenberg |orig-year=2010 |url=http://www.gutenberg.org/files/32699/32699-h/32699-h.htm |access-date=21 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Charles Osborne Wickenden (architect) and J.C. Dumaresq designed the Central Building, Acadia College, 1878–79.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |editor-first=Robert G. |editor-last=Hill |title=Wickenden, Charles Osborne |encyclopedia=Biographical Dictionary of Architects in Canada 1800-1950 |url=http://www.dictionaryofarchitectsincanada.org/architects/view/1277 |access-date=21 September 2015 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120425152711/http://www.dictionaryofarchitectsincanada.org/architects/view/1277 |archivedate=25 April 2012 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Clara Belle Marshall, from [[Mount Hanley, Nova Scotia]], became the first woman to graduate from Acadia University in 1879.&lt;ref&gt;{{CRHP|6947|Mount Hanley School Section Number 10|accessdate=21 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1891, there were changes in the Act of Incorporation.&lt;ref name=&quot;gutenberg.org&quot;/&gt;

[[Andrew R. Cobb]] designed several campus buildings including: Raynor Hall Residence, 1916; [https://web.archive.org/web/20141026194247/http://virtualtour.acadiau.ca/horton-hall.html Horton House], designed by Cobb in the Georgian style, and built by James Reid of [[Yarmouth, Nova Scotia]] was opened in 1915 as Horton Academy. Today, Horton Hall is the home of the Department of Psychology and Research and Graduate Studies.  [[Emmerson Hall]], built in 1913, is particularly interesting for the variety of building stones used. In 1967 Emmerson Hall was converted to classrooms and offices for the School of Education. It is a registered Heritage Property.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |editor-first=Robert G. |editor-last=Hill |title=Taylor, Sir Andrew Thomas |encyclopedia=Biographical Dictionary of Architects in Canada 1800-1950 |url=http://www.dictionaryofarchitectsincanada.org/architects/view/1349 |access-date=21 September 2015 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150203133240/http://www.dictionaryofarchitectsincanada.org/architects/view/1349 |archivedate=3 February 2015 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[File:EmmersonHall.jpg|thumb|Emmerson Hall, Acadia University, was originally built 1913 as Emerson Memorial Library and shows strong Beaux Arts influences. It was erected to honour the memory of the Reverend R. H. Emmerson (1826–1857), father of the former premier of New Brunswick, [[Henry Robert Emmerson|H. R. Emmerson]].]]

Unveiled on 16 August 1963, a wooden and metal organ in Manning Chapel, Acadia University, is dedicated to Acadia University's war dead of the First and Second World Wars and the Korean War.&lt;ref&gt;{{National Inventory of Canadian Military Memorials|id=2787|title=Memorial organ: Manning Memorial Chapel, Acadia University: Memorial 12006-017 Wolfville, NS|access-date=30 December 2016}} {{cite web |url=http://www.cmp-cpm.forces.gc.ca/dhh-dhp/nic-inm/sm-rm/mdsr-rdr-eng.asp?PID=2787 |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2011-01-17 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130517035651/http://www.cmp-cpm.forces.gc.ca/dhh-dhp/nic-inm/sm-rm/mdsr-rdr-eng.asp?PID=2787 |archivedate=17 May 2013 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; A book of remembrance in Manning Chapel, Acadia University was unveiled on 1 March 1998 through the efforts of the Wolfville Historical Society&lt;ref&gt;{{National Inventory of Canadian Military Memorials|id=2847|title=Book of Remembrance: Manning Memorial Chapel, Acadia University: Memorial 12006-016 Wolfville, NS|access-date=30 December 2016}} {{cite web |url=http://www.cmp-cpm.forces.gc.ca/dhh-dhp/nic-inm/sm-rm/mdsr-rdr-eng.asp?PID=2847 |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2011-01-17 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150402161228/http://www.cmp-cpm.forces.gc.ca/dhh-dhp/nic-inm/sm-rm/mdsr-rdr-eng.asp?PID=2847 |archivedate=2 April 2015 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1966, the Baptist denomination relinquished direct control over the University. The denomination maintains nine seats on the University's Board of Governors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Board of Governors of Acadia University - 2015-2016 |url=http://board.acadiau.ca/Board_Members.html |work=Board of Governors |publisher=Acadia University |accessdate=21 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Acadia is a laureate of Washington’s Smithsonian Institution and a part of the permanent research collection of the National Museum of American History. Acadia is also the only Canadian University selected for inclusion in the Education and Academia category if the Computerworld Smithsonian Award. 

===Faculty strikes===

Acadia University's Board of Governors and members of the Acadia University Faculty Association (AUFA) have ratified a new [https://web.archive.org/web/20110706164641/http://www2.acadiau.ca/acadia-news-reader/items/board-and-faculty-sign-new-four-year-contract.html collective agreement news release] covering the period 1 July 2010 to 30 June 2014. The faculty of Acadia University have been on strike twice in the history of the institution. The first was 24 February to 12 March 2004. The second was 15 October to 5 November 2007. The second strike was resolved after the province's labour minister, [[Mark Parent]], appointed a mediator, on 1 November, to facilitate an agreement.

==Academics==
{{Infobox Canadian university rankings
| MAC_undergrad = 4
| MAC_rep = 29
}}

===Rankings===
In ''[[Maclean's]]'' 2020 Guide to Canadian Universities, Acadia was ranked 4th in the publication's &quot;primarily undergraduate&quot; Canadian university category.&lt;ref name=&quot;Macdocu&quot;/&gt; In the same year, the publication ranked Acadia 29th, in its overall national reputation rankings.&lt;ref name=&quot;Macrep&quot;/&gt;

===Faculties===
Acadia is organized into four faculties: Arts, Pure &amp; Applied Science, Professional Studies and Theology. Each faculty is further divided into departments and schools specialized in areas of teaching and research.

==Research==
Acadia has over 15 research centres and 6 research chairs. Undergraduate students have the opportunity to participate in many research opportunities in a small university setting. 

The Division of Research &amp; Graduate Studies is separate from the faculties and oversees graduate students as well as Acadia's research programs.

Acadia's research programs explore coastal environments, ethno-cultural diversity, social justice, environmental monitoring and climate change, organizational relationships, data mining, the impact of digital technologies, and lifestyle choices contributing to health and wellness. Acadia's research centres include the Tidal Energy Institute, the Acadia Institute for Data Analytics, and the Beaubassin Field Station. Applied research opportunities include research with local wineries and grape growers, alternative insect control techniques and technologies.&lt;ref name=&quot;Acadia University&quot;/&gt;

==Innovation==

===The Acadia Advantage===

In 1996, Acadia University pioneered the use of mobile computing technology in a post-secondary educational environment.

This academic initiative, named the Acadia Advantage, integrated the use of notebook computers into the undergraduate curriculum and featured innovations in teaching. By 2000, all full-time, undergraduate Acadia students were taking part in the initiative. The initiative went beyond leasing notebook computers to students during the academic year, and included training, user support and the use of course-specific applications at Acadia that arguably revolutionized learning at the Wolfville, N.S. campus and beyond.

Because of its pioneering efforts, Acadia is a laureate of Washington's Smithsonian Institution and a part of the permanent research collection of the National Museum of American History. It is the only Canadian university selected for inclusion in the Education and Academia category of the Computerworld Smithsonian Award.

In addition, Acadia University received the Pioneer Award for [[Ubiquitous computing|Ubiquitous Computing]]. In 2001, it achieved high rankings in the annual ''[[Maclean's]]'' University Rankings, including Best Overall for Primarily Undergraduate University in their opinion survey, and it received the Canadian Information Productivity Award in 1997 as it was praised as the first university in Canada to fully utilize information technology in the undergraduate curriculum.

In October 2006, Dr. Dinter-Gottlieb established a commission to review the Acadia Advantage learning environment 10 years after inception. The mandate of the commission was to determine how well the current Advantage program meets the needs of students, faculty, and staff and to examine how the role of technology in the postsecondary environment has changed at Acadia, and elsewhere. The commission was asked to recommend changes and enhancements to the Acadia Advantage that would benefit the entire university community and ensure its sustainability.

Some of the recommendations coming from the Acadia Advantage Renewal Report included developing a choice of model specifications and moving from Acadia-issued, student-leased notebook computers to a student-owned computer model. The compelling rationale for this was the integral role technology now plays in our lives, which was not present in 1996.

The University was also advised to unbundle its tuition structure so that the cost of an Acadia education is more detailed and students can understand how their investment in the future of the school is allotted.  In September 2008, Acadia moved to a student-owned notebook computer version of the Acadia Advantage, now named Acadia Advantage 2.0.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.acadiau.ca/advantage |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/19981202144636/http://acadiau.ca/advantage/ |url-status=dead |archive-date=2 December 1998 |title=Acadia Advantage |publisher=Acadia Advantage |accessdate=30 August 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2017, Acadia announced the Huestis Innovation Pavilion as part of its $22.25 million Science Complex renewal project. Named in honour of lead donors, Faye and David Huestis of Saint John, New Brunswick, the Pavilion is a key connection between Elliott and Huggins Halls, providing research and commercialization space. 

The new Agri-Technology Access Centre in the Innovation Pavilion provides companies and industry organizations with better access to specialized technology, lab space, subject-matter expertise and commercialization support services, strengthening their ability to become more productive and innovative. It also enables Acadia to advance its applied research strength in a key priority sector – agriculture – and expand its successful technology transfer and commercialization activities. The Science Complex renewal project was supported by an investment of $15.98 million by the Federal and Provincial governments. 

&lt;br /&gt;

==Athletics==
Acadia's sports teams are called the [[Acadia Axemen|Axemen]] and [[Acadia Axewomen|Axewomen]]. They participate in the Atlantic University Sports conference of [[U Sports]].

School spirit abounds with men's and women's varsity teams that have delivered more conference and national championships than any other institution in Atlantic University Sport. Routinely, more than one-third of Acadia's varsity athletes also achieve Academic All-Canadian designation through Canadian Interuniversity Sport by maintaining a minimum average of 80 per cent.

Expansion and modernization of [[Raymond Field]] was completed in the fall of 2007 and features the installation of an eight-lane all-weather running track and a move to the same premium artificial turf used by the New England Patriots of the [[National Football League]] for its main playing field. The Raymond Field modernization was a gift to the university by friends, alumni, and the province. War Memorial Gymnasium also saw the installation of a new playing floor to benefit its basketball and volleyball teams.

In September 2006, Acadia University announced its partnership with the Wolfville Tritons Swim Club&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.tritons.ca |title=Wolfville Tritons Swim Club |author= |date= |work= |publisher= |accessdate=30 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the Acadia Masters Swim Club&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www3.ns.sympatico.ca/masters/ |archive-url=https://archive.is/20130101074057/http://www3.ns.sympatico.ca/masters/ |url-status=dead |archive-date=1 January 2013 |title=Acadia Masters Swim Clug |accessdate=30 August 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; to form the Acadia Swim Club&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://axe.acadiau.ca/swimclub/ |title=Acadia Swim Club |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071225194540/http://axe.acadiau.ca/swimclub/ |archivedate=25 December 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  and return competitive swimming to the university after a 14-year hiatus. On 26 September 2008, the university announced its intention&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.acadiau.ca/sports/swim_returns.htm |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110523230120/http://www.acadiau.ca/sports/swim_returns.htm |url-status=dead |archive-date=23 May 2011 |title=Varsity Swim team returns to Acadia |date=26 September 2008 |publisher=Acadia Sports Information |accessdate=30 August 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; to return swimming to a varsity status in September 2009.

==Fight song==
Notable among a number of songs commonly played and sung at various events such as [[Graduation|commencement]], [[convocation]], and athletic games are: ''Stand Up and Cheer'', the Acadia University [[fight song]]. According to 'Songs of Acadia College' (Wolfville, NS 1902-3, 1907), the songs include: 'Acadia Centennial Song' (1938); 'The Acadia Clan Song'; 'Alma Mater - Acadia;' 'Alma Mater Acadia' (1938) and 'Alma Mater Song.'&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |title=College Songs and Songbooks |encyclopedia=The Canadian Encyclopedia |publisher=Historica Canada |edition=online |url=http://www.thecanadianencyclopedia.com/en/article/college-songs-and-songbooks-emc/ |first=Rebecca |last=Green |date=7 December 2013 |accessdate=21 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Symbols==
In 1974, Acadia was granted a coat of arms designed by the [[College of Arms]] in London, England. The coat of arms is two-tone, with the school's official colours, garnet and blue, on the shield. The axes represent the school's origins in a rural setting, and the determination of its founders who cleared the land and built the school on donated items and labour. The open books represent the intellectual pursuits of a university, and the wolves heads are a whimsical representation of the University's location in Wolfville.  &quot;In pulvere vinces&quot; (In dust you conquer) is the motto.&lt;ref&gt;[http://library.acadiau.ca/archives/research/fta/oct297.html Acadia University's Coat of Arms] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071225194559/http://library.acadiau.ca/archives/research/fta/oct297.html |date=25 December 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The University seal depicts the Greek goddess of wisdom [[Athena]] in front of the first college hall.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.acadiau.ca/chaplain/window.htm|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080615184810/http://www.acadiau.ca/chaplain/window.htm|url-status=dead|archive-date=15 June 2008|title=The Chancel Window|date=15 June 2008|accessdate=16 August 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The University also uses a stylized &quot;A&quot; as a logo for its sports teams.

Notable among a number of [[fight song]]s commonly played and sung at various events such as [[Graduation|commencement]], [[convocation]], and athletic games are: the Acadia University [[alma mater]] set to the tune of &quot;[[Annie Lisle]]&quot;. The lyrics are:

:Far above the dykes of Fundy
:And its basin blue
:Stands our noble alma mater
:Glorious to view

:Lift the chorus
:Speed it onward
:Sing it loud and free
:Hail to thee our alma mater
:Acadia, hail to thee

:Far above the busy highway
:And the sleepy town
:Raised against the arch of heaven
:Looks she proudly down&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://library.acadiau.ca/archives/sporthistory/sound/Alma_Mater_Exerp.mp3 |title=Alma Mater |author= |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110706164218/http://library.acadiau.ca/archives/sporthistory/sound/Alma_Mater_Exerp.mp3 |publisher=Acadia University |archivedate=July 6, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Historic buildings at Acadia University==
Seminary House, also known as the Ladies' Seminary, is a [[Second Empire architecture|Second Empire]] style-building constructed in 1878 as a home for women attending the university.  It was designated a [[National Historic Sites of Canada|National Historic Site of Canada]] in 1997 as Canada's oldest facility associated with the higher education of women.&lt;ref&gt;{{CRHP|15183|Ladies' Seminary National Historic Site of Canada|24 March 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Carnegie Hall, built in 1909, is a large, two-storey, Neo-classical brick building.  It was designated under the provincial [[Heritage Property Act (Nova Scotia)|Heritage Property Act]] in 1989 as its construction in 1909 signified Acadia's evolution from classical college to liberal university.&lt;ref&gt;{{CRHP|4512|Carnegie Hall|24 March 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The War Memorial House (more generally known as Barrax), which is a residence, and War Memorial Gymnasium&lt;ref&gt;{{National Inventory of Canadian Military Memorials|id=1785|title=War Memorial Gymnasium: Acadia University: Memorial 12006-007 Wolfville, NS|access-date=30 December 2016}} {{cite web |url=http://www.cmp-cpm.forces.gc.ca/dhh-dhp/nic-inm/sm-rm/mdsr-rdr-eng.asp?PID=1785 |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2011-01-17 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150402132928/http://www.cmp-cpm.forces.gc.ca/dhh-dhp/nic-inm/sm-rm/mdsr-rdr-eng.asp?PID=1785 |archivedate=2 April 2015 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AcadiaHistory&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=History of Acadia University |website=Acadia Athletics |publisher=Acadia University |url=http://www.acadiaathletics.ca/about/history |access-date=21 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; are landmark buildings on the campus of Acadia University. The Memorial Hall and Gymnasium honours students who had enlisted and died in the [[First World War]], and in the [[Second World War]]. Two granite shafts, which are part of the War Memorial Gymnasium complex at Acadia University, are dedicated to the university's war dead.&lt;ref name=&quot;AcadiaHistory&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{National Inventory of Canadian Military Memorials|id=1786|title=First World War memorial: Acadia University: Memorial 12006-008 Wolfville, NS|access-date=30 December 2016}} {{cite web |url=http://www.cmp-cpm.forces.gc.ca/dhh-dhp/nic-inm/sm-rm/mdsr-rdr-eng.asp?PID=1786 |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2011-01-17 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150402090115/http://www.cmp-cpm.forces.gc.ca/dhh-dhp/nic-inm/sm-rm/mdsr-rdr-eng.asp?PID=1786 |archivedate=2 April 2015 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; The War Memorial House is dedicated to the war dead from Acadia University during the Second World War.&lt;ref name=&quot;AcadiaHistory&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{National Inventory of Canadian Military Memorials|id=1787|title=War Memorial House: Acadia University: Memorial 12006-009 Wolfville, NS|access-date=30 December 2016}} {{cite web |url=http://www.cmp-cpm.forces.gc.ca/dhh-dhp/nic-inm/sm-rm/mdsr-rdr-eng.asp?PID=1787 |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2012-01-02 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150402160100/http://www.cmp-cpm.forces.gc.ca/dhh-dhp/nic-inm/sm-rm/mdsr-rdr-eng.asp?PID=1787 |archivedate=2 April 2015 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Student life==

At Acadia University, students have access to the Student Union Building which serves as a hub for students and houses many Student Union organizations. The building also houses The Axe Lounge, a convenience store, an information desk and two food outlets. The university press, The Athenaeum, is a member of [[Canadian University Press|CUP]].

===Student government===

All students are represented by the [[Acadia Students' Union]]. 
The Union Executive for the 2018-2019 academic year: President - Kyle Vandertoorn, Vice President Student Life - Robbie Holmes, Vice President Academic &amp; External - Mackenzie Jarvin, Vice President Finance - Brendan MacNeil, Vice President Events &amp; Promotions - Gabrielle Bailey.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://theasu.ca/who-we-are/executive-leadership-team/|title=Executive Leadership Team - Acadia Students' Union|publisher=|accessdate=16 August 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; The student newspaper is ''[[The Athenaeum (Acadia University)|The Athenaeum]].''

===Residences===

Approximately 1500 students live on-campus&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Residence, Meals &amp; Housing |url=https://www2.acadiau.ca/residence-life.html |publisher=Acadia University |accessdate=March 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; in 11 residences:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www2.acadiau.ca/residence-life/residence-options.html|title=Residence Options |publisher=Acadia University|accessdate=March 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Chase Court
* Chipman House
* Christofor Hall
* Crowell Tower (13 Story High-rise)
* Cutten House
* Dennis House - First floor houses student health services
* Eaton House
* Roy Jodrey Hall
* Seminary House - Also houses the School of Education in lower level
* War Memorial (Barrax) House
* Whitman Hall (Tully) - All female residence
* Willett House (former residence)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://admin.acadiau.ca/studentaffairs/residencelife/newsletter0907.html|archiveurl=https://archive.today/20070629073846/http://admin.acadiau.ca/studentaffairs/residencelife/newsletter0907.html|url-status=dead|title=Department of Residence Life|date=29 June 2007|archivedate=29 June 2007|accessdate=16 August 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==People==
{{Refimprove section|date=April 2012}}

===List of Presidents and Vice Chancellors===

* John Pryor, 1846–1850
* [[John Cramp]], 1851–1853 (and 1856–1869)
* [[Edmund Crawley]], 1853–1856
* John Cramp, 1856–1869
* [[Artemas Wyman Sawyer]], 1869–1896
* [[Thomas Trotter (academic)|Thomas Trotter]], 1897–1906
* [[W.B. Hutchinson]], 1907–1909
* [[George Barton Cutten]], 1910–1922
* [[Frederic Patterson]], 1923–1948
* [[Watson Kirkconnell]], 1948–1964
* James Beveridge, 1964–1978
* [[Allan Sinclair (Acadia President)|Allan Sinclair]], 1978–1981
* [[James Perkin (academic)|James Perkin]], 1981–1993
* [[Kelvin Ogilvie]], 1993–2004
* [[Gail Dinter-Gottlieb]], 2004–2008
* [[Tom Herman (Professor)|Tom Herman]] (Acting President), 2008–2009
* [[Raymond Ivany]], 2009 – 2017
* Peter J Ricketts, 2017

===List of Chancellors===

*[[Alex Colville]], 1981–1991&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.macleans.ca/education/uniandcollege/artist-alex-colville-remembered-in-wolfville-n-s/|title=Artist Alex Colville remembered in Wolfville, N.S. - Macleans.ca|date=24 July 2013|publisher=|accessdate=16 August 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[William Feindel]], 1991–1996
*[[Arthur Irving]], 1996–2010
*[[Libby Burnham]], 2011–2018
*Bruce Galloway, 2018- present&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www2.acadiau.ca/home/news-reader-page/acadia-university-names-canadian-business-leader-bruce-galloway-68-as-chancellor.html|title=Acadia University names Canadian business leader Bruce Galloway (’68) as Chancellor - Acadia University|website=www2.acadiau.ca|access-date=2019-01-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Notable alumni===
* [[Edgar Archibald]], scientist and politician
* [[Norman Atkins]], Canadian senator
* [[Ron Barkhouse]], MLA for Lunenburg East (Horton Academy)
* [[Todd Battis]], Correspondent CTV National News 
* [[Gordon Lockhart Bennett]], Lieutenant-Governor of Prince Edward Island
* [[Arthur Bourns]], President of McMaster University
* [[Libby Burnham]], lawyer, Chancellor of Acadia University
* [[Bob Cameron (Canadian football)|Bob Cameron]], football player
* [[Dalton Camp]], journalist, politician and political strategist
* [[M. Elizabeth Cannon]], University of Calgary's President &amp; Vice-Chancellor
* [[Paul Corkum]], physicist and F.R.S.
* [[John Wallace de Beque Farris]], Canadian senator
* [[Mark Day (actor)|Mark Day]], actor
* [[Michael Clarke (musician)|Michael Dick]], CBC-TV Journalist
* [[Charles Aubrey Eaton]] (1868–1953), clergyman and politician &lt;!-- who served in the [[United States House of Representatives]], representing the {{ushr|New Jersey|4}} from 1925 to 1933, and the {{ushr|New Jersey|5|5th district}} from 1933 to 1953.&lt;ref&gt;[http://bioguide.congress.gov/scripts/biodisplay.pl?index=E000023 Charles Aubrey Eaton], ''[[Biographical Directory of the United States Congress]]''. Retrieved 9 September 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; not required - this is simply a hyperlinked list--&gt;
* [[William Feindel]], neurosurgeon
* [[Dale Frail]], astronomer
* [[Rob Ramsay]], actor
* [[Alexandra Fuller]], writer
* [[Gary Graham (musician)|Gary Graham]], musician, choral conductor
* [[Milton Fowler Gregg]], VC laureate, politician
* [[Robbie Harrison]], Nova Scotian politician and educator
* [[Richard Hatfield]], Premier of New Brunswick
* [[Charles Brenton Huggins]], Nobel Laureate
* [[K. C. Irving|Kenneth Colin Irving]], industrialist
* [[Robert Irving (industrialist)|Robert Irving]], industrialist
* [[Ron James (comedian)|Ron James]], Canadian comedian
* [[Lorie Kane]], [[LPGA]] golfer
* [[Gerald Keddy]], Member of Parliament
* [[Joanne Kelly]], Actress
* [[Kenneth Komoski]], Educator
* [[David H. Levy]], astronomer
* [[Peter MacKay]], lawyer, Canadian Minister of National Defence
* [[Henry Poole MacKeen]], Lieutenant-Governor of Nova Scotia
* [[Paul Masotti]], football player
* [[Harrison McCain]], industrialist
* [[Donald Oliver]], Canadian senator
* [[Henry Nicholas Paint]] (1830–1921), member of Parliament, merchant, landowner,
* [[Freeman Patterson]], photographer, writer
* [[Lancelot Press#Robert Pope Foundation|Robert Pope]], Visual artist author,
* [[Keith R. Porter]], Cell Biologist
* [[Heather Rankin (singer)|Heather Rankin]], singer-songwriter, member of [[The Rankin Family]]
* [[Jacob Gould Schurman]], President of Cornell University
* [[Roger Tomlinson]] (1933-2014), geographer and &quot;The Father of [[Geographic Information Systems|GIS]]&quot;
* Stephen Wetmore, Former CEO of Canadian Tire Corporation
* Rev. [[William A. White]], noted black minister and missionary
* [[Lance Woolaver]], playwright

===Honorary graduates===
* [[Jean Béliveau]], professional hockey player and executive&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=List of honorary degree recipients |url=https://www2.acadiau.ca/alumni-friends/alumni/awards/honorary-degrees.html |website=Acadia University Honorary Degrees |publisher=Acadia University |accessdate=15 July 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Kim Campbell|Rt. Hon. Kim Campbell]], former Prime Minister of Canada
* [[Alex Colville]], painter and former University Chancellor
* [[John Diefenbaker|Rt. Hon. John Diefenbaker]], former Prime Minister of Canada
* [[Rick Hansen]], activist and Paralympic athlete
* [[Grace Hopper]], computer scientist and United States Navy rear admiral
* [[Alexa McDonough]], politician and first woman to lead a major, recognized political party in Canada
* [[William Twaits]], Chairman and CEO of [[Imperial Oil]] Limited
* [[William A. White|Rev. William A. White]], noted black minister and missionary

==See also==
*[[Acadia Divinity College]]
*[[Canadian government scientific research organizations]]
*[[Canadian industrial research and development organizations]]
*[[Canadian Interuniversity Sport]]
*[[Canadian university scientific research organizations]]
*[[Higher education in Nova Scotia]]
*[[List of universities in Nova Scotia]]
*[[List of National Historic Sites of Canada in Nova Scotia]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
*Longley, R. S. Acadia University, 1838–1938. Wolfville, N.S.: Acadia University, 1939.

==External links==
{{Commons category|Acadia University}}
*{{Official website|1=http://www.acadiau.ca}}
*[https://campaign.acadiau.ca/ Campaign for Acadia] 

{{Universities in Canada}}
{{Maritime PS}}
{{Kings County}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Acadia University|*]]
[[Category:Education in Kings County, Nova Scotia]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Nova Scotia]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1838]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Kings County, Nova Scotia]]
[[Category:1838 establishments in Nova Scotia]]
[[Category:Higher education in Canada]]
[[Category:Maple League]]</text>
      <sha1>53pbbko9es9dk0uvfxix7mc9xtwtwir</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
