  <page>
    <title>Assault gun</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2284</id>
    <revision>
      <id>913795690</id>
      <parentid>912829576</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-09-03T07:30:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Klemen Kocjancic</username>
        <id>71061</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>clean up</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{distinguish|assault rifle|assault weapon}}
{{More citations needed|date=January 2013}}
[[File:StuG-III-latrun-2.jpg|thumb|right|300px|Decommissioned [[Syrian Army]] [[StuG III]] assault gun with 75mm main armament.]]

An '''assault gun''' is a form of [[self-propelled artillery]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Bull&quot;&gt;{{cite book | first = Stephen| last = Bull| authorlink = | title = Encyclopedia of Military Technology and Innovation|edition= 2004|page= 229 | publisher = Greenwood Publishing Group| isbn= 978-1573565578}}&lt;/ref&gt; which uses an [[infantry support gun]] mounted on a motorized chassis, normally an [[armored fighting vehicle]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Bradford&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Bradford| first = James|title = International Encyclopedia of Military History|edition= 2006|pages= 123–124 | publisher = Routledge Books| isbn= 978-0415936613}}&lt;/ref&gt; Assault guns are designed to provide [[direct fire|direct fire support]] for [[infantry]] attacks, especially against other infantry or [[fortified]] positions.&lt;ref name=Wehrmacht1&gt;{{cite book|last=Blennemann|first=Dirk|title=Hitler's Army: The Evolution And Structure Of German Forces 1933-1945|date=2003|pages=66-63|publisher=Da Capo Press|location=Boston|isbn=978-0306812606}}&lt;/ref&gt; The term is a literal translation of the German word ''Sturmgeschütz'', which was applied to the first purpose-built assault gun, the [[StuG III]], in 1940.&lt;ref name=Wehrmacht1/&gt;

Historically, the concept of assault guns was very similar to that of the [[infantry tank]], as both were combat vehicles intended to accompany infantry formations into battle.&lt;ref name=Gudmundsson&gt;{{cite book|last=Gudmundsson|first=Bruce|title=On Armor|date=2004|pages=114–126|publisher=Prager Books|location=Westport, Connecticut|isbn=978-0812216202}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, during World War II assault guns were more mobile than tanks and could be utilized as both direct and indirect fire artillery.&lt;ref name=Gudmundsson/&gt; Although they could approximate the firepower of a tank, assault guns mostly fired [[Shell (projectile)#HE-Frag|high explosive]] shells at relatively low velocities, which were well suited for their role of knocking out hard points such as fortified positions and buildings.&lt;ref name=Gudmundsson/&gt; They were not intended to be deployed as tank substitutes or dedicated [[tank destroyer]]s.&lt;ref name=Gudmundsson/&gt; Nevertheless, as the conflict progressed, the increasing proliferation of tanks on the battlefield forced many assault gun units to engage armor in defense of the infantry, and led to armies becoming more dependent on multipurpose designs which combined the traditionally separate roles of an assault gun and a tank destroyer.&lt;ref name=Wehrmacht2&gt;{{cite book|last=Tucker-Jones|first=Anthony|title=German Assault Guns and Tank Destroyers 1940 - 1945: Rare Photographs from Wartime Archives|date=2016|page=114|publisher=Pen &amp; Sword Books, Ltd|location=Barnsley, South Yorkshire|isbn=978-1473845992}}&lt;/ref&gt;

German and Soviet assault guns introduced during World War II usually carried their main armament in a fully enclosed [[casemate]] rather than a [[gun turret]].&lt;ref name=Levine&gt;{{cite book|last=Levine|first=Mark|title=D-Day to Berlin: The Northwest Europe Campaign, 1944-45|date=2000|pages=21–22|publisher=Stackpole Books|location=Mechanicsburg|isbn=978-0811733861}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although this limited the [[field of fire (weaponry)|field of fire]] and traverse of the armament, it also had the advantage of a reduced silhouette and simplified the manufacturing process.&lt;ref name=Levine/&gt; The United States never developed a purpose-built assault gun during the war, although it did modify preexisting armored fighting vehicles for that role, including the [[M4 Sherman]] and [[M3 Stuart|M5 Stuart]] tanks and the [[M3 Half-track]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Colt&quot;&gt;{{cite book | title = Camp Colt to Desert Storm: The History of U.S. Armored Forces | date = August 1999 | pages = 149–156, 479–481 | last1 = Gabel | first1 = Christopher | last2=Estes | first2=Kenneth | editor1-last = Hoffman | editor1-first = George | editor2-last = Starry | editor2-first = Donn | location = Lexington, Kentucky | publisher = University Press of Kentucky | isbn = 978-0813121307}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The assault gun concept was largely abandoned during the postwar era in favor of tanks or multipurpose tank destroyers attached to infantry formations which were also capable of providing direct fire support as needed. In the [[United States]] and most Western countries, the assault gun ceased to be recognized as a unique niche, with individual examples being classified either as a self-propelled howitzer or a tank.&lt;ref name=&quot;Knox1&quot;&gt;{{cite journal| last = Underhill| first = Garrett| title = The Story Of Soviet Armor: Assault Guns And Self-Propelled Artillery| journal = [[Armor magazine]]| pages = 28–38| publisher = US Army Armor Center| location = Fort Knox, Kentucky| date = November–December 1972}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Soviet Union continued funding development of new assault guns as late as 1967, although few of its postwar designs were adopted in large numbers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Knox2&quot;&gt;{{cite journal| last = Warford| first = James| title = Armored Vehicle Development Behind The Curtain: The Secret Life Of The Soviet SU-122-54 Assault Gun| journal = [[Armor magazine]]| pages = 12–14| publisher = US Army Armor Center| location = Fort Knox, Kentucky| date = July–September 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Soviet and other Eastern European armies, the traditional assault gun was primarily superseded by tank destroyers such as the [[SU-100]] capable of supporting either infantry or armor.&lt;ref name=&quot;Knox1&quot;/&gt;

==History==

===World War II===
[[Image:Su76 nn.jpg|thumb|The Soviet [[SU-76]] was easily constructed in small factories incapable of producing proper tanks.]]

Assault guns were primarily used during [[World War II]] by the forces of [[Nazi Germany]] and the [[Soviet Union]]. Early in the war, the [[Germans]] began to create makeshift assault guns by mounting their [[infantry support weapon]]s on the bed of a [[truck]] or on obsolete [[tank]]s with the turret removed. Later in the war, both the Germans and the Soviets introduced fully [[armoured warfare|armoured]] purpose-built assault guns into their arsenals.

Early on, the Soviets built the [[KV-2]], a variant of the [[KV-1 (tank)|KV-1]] heavy tank with a short-barrelled [[152 mm howitzer-gun M1937 (ML-20)|152 mm howitzer]] mounted in an oversized turret. This was not a success in battle, and was replaced with a very successful series of turretless assault guns: the [[SU-76]], [[SU-122]], and the heavy [[SU-152]], which were followed by the [[ISU-122]] and [[ISU-152]] on the new [[Iosif Stalin tank|IS]] heavy tank [[chassis]].

[[Image:Germany06 086.jpg|thumb|right|''[[Sturmtiger]]'' in the ''[[Deutsches Panzermuseum]]'' at [[Munster, Lower Saxony]].]]

The primary German assault gun was the ''[[Sturmgeschütz III]]'' (StuG III). At about the same time (March 1942) as the howitzer-like KwK 37 gun was dropped from the Panzer IV's use, its ''Sturmkanone'' equivalent in the StuG III up to that time, was likewise replaced with a longer-barreled, high-velocity dual-purpose [[7.5 cm KwK 40|75mm gun]] that had also been derived from the successful [[PaK 40]] anti-tank towed artillery piece. The Germans also built a number of other fully armoured turretless assault guns, including the [[StuG IV]], [[Sturm-Infanteriegeschütz 33B|StuIG 33B]], ''[[Brummbär]]'' and ''[[Sturmtiger]]''. The latter two were very heavy vehicles, and were built only in small quantities.

[[Battalion]]s of assault guns, usually StuG IIIs, commonly replaced the intended [[panzer]] battalion in the German [[panzergrenadier]] [[division (military)|divisions]] due to the chronic shortage of tanks, and were sometimes used as makeshifts even in the [[panzer division]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas L. Jentz (1996): Panzertruppen: The Complete Guide to the Creation &amp; Combat Employment of Germany's Tank Force, vol.2, 1943-1945, p.68&lt;/ref&gt; Independent battalions were also deployed as &quot;stiffeners&quot; for [[infantry]] divisions, and the StuG III's [[anti-tank]] capabilities bolstered dwindling tank numbers on the Eastern and Western fronts.
[[Image:Sherman Tank WW2.jpg|right|thumb|A preserved Sherman M4 (105).]]
US and UK forces also deployed vehicles designed for a close support role, but these were conventional tanks whose only significant modification was the replacement of the main gun with a howitzer. Two versions of the American  [[M4 Sherman|Sherman tank]] were armed with the [[M101 howitzer|M4 105 mm howitzer]], the M4(105) and the M4A3(105); these were designated assault guns in US usage of the term. The [[M8 Scott]], based on the chassis of the [[M5 Stuart]] light tank, was also an assault cannon and carried a [[M116 howitzer|75 mm short howitzer]]. The [[Churchill tank|Churchill]], [[Cromwell tank|Centaur]] and [[Cromwell tank|Cromwell]] tanks were all produced in versions armed with [[Ordnance QF 95 mm Howitzer|95&amp;nbsp;mm howitzers]]: the Churchill Mark V and Mark VIII, the Centaur Mark IV and the Cromwell Mark VI. Earlier British tanks, such as the [[Crusader tank|Crusader cruiser tank]] and the [[Matilda II|Matilda II Infantry tank]] were produced in versions armed with the [[Ordnance QF 3-inch howitzer|3-inch howitzer]]; the first versions of the Churchill tank also had this gun in a hull mounting. American [[tank destroyer]] units were often used in the assault gun role for infantry support.

The AVRE version of the Churchill Tank was armed with a [[Mortar (weapon)#Spigot mortar|Spigot mortar]] that fired a {{convert|40|lb|kg|abbr=on}} [[High explosive|HE]]-filled projectile (nicknamed the ''Flying Dustbin'') {{convert|150|yd|m}}. Its task was to attack fortified positions such as [[bunker]]s at close range (see [[Hobart's Funnies]]).

=== Post-war use ===

In the post-[[World War II|WWII]] era, vehicles fitting into an &quot;assault gun&quot; category were developed as a light-weight, air-deployable, direct fire weapon for use with airborne troops. Those weapons were either based on [[jeep]]s or small [[Caterpillar track|tracked]] vehicles and the airborne troops thus always fought at a distinct disadvantage in terms of heavy weapons. The Soviet Union and the United States were the most attracted to the idea of providing this capability to traditionally light airborne forces. Their answers to the problem were similar, with the United States developing the [[M56 Scorpion]] and the Soviet Union developing the [[ASU-57]], both essentially air-droppable light anti-tank guns.

The Soviets went on to develop an improved air-droppable assault gun, the [[ASU-85]], which served through the 1980s, while their [[SU-100]] remained in service with Communist countries, including Vietnam and Cuba, years after World War II. The US M56 and another armoured vehicle, the [[Ontos|M50 Ontos]], were to be the last of the more traditional assault guns in US service. Improvised arrangements such as [[M113 Armored Personnel Carrier#Weapons|M113]] personnel carriers with recoilless rifles were quickly replaced by missile carrier vehicles in the anti-tank role.

The only vehicle with the qualities of an assault gun to be fielded after the removal of the M50 and M56 from service within the US military was the [[M551 Sheridan]]. The Sheridan's gun was a low-velocity weapon suitable in the assault role, but with the addition of the [[Shillelagh missile]] could double in the anti-tank role as well. The Sheridan, however, was not developed as an assault gun but as a light reconnaissance vehicle.

Currently there appears to be a move toward wheeled vehicles fitting a &quot;tank destroyer&quot; or &quot;assault gun&quot; role, such as the [[M1128 Mobile Gun System]] of the [[US Army]], the [[Centauro]] Wheeled Tank Destroyer of the [[Italian Army|Italian]] and [[Spanish Army|Spanish Armies]], the Chinese anti-tank gun PTL-02 and ZBL08 assault gun, and the French [[AMX-10 RC]] heavy armoured car. While these vehicles might be useful in a direct fire role, none were developed with this specifically in mind, reminiscent of the use of tank destroyers by the US military in the assault gun role during World War II.

== See also ==
* [[Armoured warfare]]
* [[Sturmgeschütz]]
* [[Tank destroyer]]
* [[Armoured fighting vehicle]]
* [[Infantry support gun]]
* [[List of assault guns]]
* [[Self-propelled gun]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Assault Gun}}
[[Category:Assault guns| ]]</text>
      <sha1>t7o5gfm7jd7percew0ivrzr5i3uxtie</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
