  <page>
    <title>Argentine cuisine</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2222</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942376992</id>
      <parentid>937108482</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-24T08:38:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mike Peel</username>
        <id>214232</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>only need one commonscat - the other is a subcategory of it</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{More citations needed|date=August 2010}}
{{Argentine cuisine}}
{{Culture of Argentina}}
[[File:Argentinean asado.jpg|thumb|Typical Argentine [[asado]] (grill).]]
'''Argentine cuisine''' is described as a cultural blending of  [[Mediterranean cuisine|Mediterranean]] influences (such as those created by [[Italian Argentine|Italian]] and [[Spanish Argentine|Spanish]] immigrants) as well as [[Indigenous peoples of Argentina|Native American]] influences, within the wide scope of  agricultural products that are abundant in the country. Argentine annual consumption of [[beef]] has averaged 100&amp;nbsp;kg (220&amp;nbsp;lbs) per capita,&lt;ref&gt;''National Geographic Magazine''. March 1958.&lt;/ref&gt; approaching 180&amp;nbsp;kg (396&amp;nbsp;lbs) per capita during the 19th century; consumption averaged 67.7&amp;nbsp;kg (149&amp;nbsp;lbs) in 2007.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.comex.infobaeprofesional.com/notas/62697.html] {{dead link|date=August 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Beyond ''[[asado]]'' (the Argentine [[barbecue]]), no other dish more genuinely matches the national identity. Nevertheless, the country's vast area, and its cultural diversity, have led to a local cuisine of various dishes.&lt;ref name=&quot;gastronomy&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.argentina.ar/_en/tourism/gastronomy/index.php |title=Argentina - Tourism - Gastronomy |date=2012-03-23 |access-date=2016-02-26 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120323163849/http://www.argentina.ar/_en/tourism/gastronomy/index.php |archivedate=March 23, 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web
| url = http://gosouthamerica.about.com/od/cuisine/a/ArgChile.htm
| title = Cuisine of Argentina and Chile
| website = About.com Travel
| access-date = 2016-02-26
}}&lt;/ref&gt; The great immigratory waves consequently imprinted a large influence in the Argentine cuisine, after all Argentina was the second country in the world with the most immigrants with 6.6 million, only second to the United States with 27 million, and ahead of other immigratory receptor countries such as Canada, Brazil, Australia, etc.&lt;ref name=&quot;ref1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cels.org.ar/Site_cels/publicaciones/informes_pdf/1998.Capitulo7.pdf|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070610215422/http://www.cels.org.ar/Site_cels/publicaciones/informes_pdf/1998.Capitulo7.pdf|url-status=dead|archive-date=10 June 2007|title=Wayback Machine|date=10 June 2007|accessdate=2 August 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ref2&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://docentes.fe.unl.pt/~satpeg/PapersInova/Labor+and+Immigration+in+LA-2005.pdf|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110814202421/http://docentes.fe.unl.pt/~satpeg/PapersInova/Labor%20and%20Immigration%20in%20LA-2005.pdf|url-status=dead|archive-date=14 August 2011|title=Wayback Machine|date=14 August 2011|accessdate=2 August 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Argentine people]] have a reputation for their love of eating.&lt;ref name=&quot;gastronomy&quot; /&gt; Social gatherings are commonly centered on sharing a meal. Invitations to have dinner at home is generally viewed as a symbol of friendship, warmth, and integration. Sunday family lunch is considered the most significant meal of the week, whose highlights often include asado or [[pasta]].&lt;ref name=&quot;gastronomy&quot; /&gt;

Another feature of Argentine cuisine is the preparation of homemade food such as [[french fries]], [[patty|patties]], and pasta to celebrate a special occasion, to meet friends, or to honor someone. Homemade food is also seen as a way to show affection.&lt;ref name=&quot;gastronomy&quot; /&gt;

Argentine restaurants include a great variety of cuisines, prices, and flavors.&lt;ref name=&quot;gastronomy&quot;/&gt; Large cities tend to host everything from high-end international cuisine, to ''bodegones'' (inexpensive traditional hidden taverns), less stylish restaurants, and bars and canteens offering a range of dishes at affordable prices.&lt;ref name=&quot;gastronomy&quot; /&gt;

==History==
{{Main|History of Argentine cuisine}}
[[Indigenous peoples in Argentina|Native Americans]] lived in Argentina thousands of years before the European explorers arrived. Members of an Indian tribe in the northern part of Argentina were farmers who grew [[Squash (plant)|squash]], [[melon]]s, and [[sweet potato]]es. [[Spanish Argentine|Spanish settlers]] came to Argentina in 1536. Between 1853 and 1955, 6.6 million immigrants came to live in Argentina from diverse sources such as [[Europe]], the [[Near East|Near]] and [[Middle East]], [[Russia]] and [[Japan]], contributing to the development of Argentine cuisine and making Argentina the second country with most immigrants only second to the United States.&lt;ref name=&quot;ref1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ref2&quot;/&gt; Most of the immigrants were from Italy and Spain. The [[Italian Argentine|Italians]] introduced [[pizza]], as well as a variety of [[pasta]] dishes, including [[spaghetti]] and [[lasagna]]. [[English Argentine|British]], [[German Argentine|German]], [[Jewish Argentine|Jewish]], and other immigrants also settled in Argentina, all bringing their styles of cooking and favorite foods with them. The British brought [[tea]], starting the tradition of [[teatime]]. All of these cultures influenced the dishes of Argentina.&lt;ref name=&quot;Food&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.foodbycountry.com/Algeria-to-France/Argentina.html#b|title=Food in Argentina - Argentine Food, Argentine Cuisine - popular, dishes, history, main, people, favorite, make, customs, fruits, country|website=Foodbycountry.com|accessdate=2 August 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Typical foods==
[[File:Dulce de leche 2007.jpg|thumb|lefttext-top|[[Dulce de leche]], a popular national spread used to fill cakes and pancakes, eaten over toast, and as an ice cream flavor.]]
[[File:Empanadas salteñas 1.jpg|thumb|left|Boxed [[Empanada]]s.]]

Most regions of Argentina are known for their beef-oriented diet. [[Grilling|Grilled]] meat from the ''[[asado]]'' (barbecue) is a staple, with [[steak]] and beef [[Ribs (food)|ribs]] especially common. The term asado itself refers to long strips of flank-cut beef ribs. Popular items such as ''[[Chorizo]]'' ([[pork]] [[sausage]]), ''morcilla'' ([[blood sausage]]), ''chinchulines'' ([[chitterlings]]), ''mollejas'' ([[sweetbread]]), and other parts of the animal are also enjoyed. In [[Patagonia]], however, [[Lamb and mutton|lamb]] and [[chivito]] ([[goat]]) are eaten more frequently than beef. Whole lambs and goats are traditionally cooked over an open fire in a technique known as asado a la estaca.

The most common condiment for asado is ''[[Chimichurri]]'', a [[sauce]] of [[herb]]s, garlic and vinegar. Unlike other preparations, Argentines do not include chili in their version of chimichurri.

[[Breading|Breaded]] and [[Frying|fried]] meats — ''[[milanesa]]s'' — are used as [[snack]]s, in [[sandwich]]es, or eaten warm with [[mashed potato]]es — ''[[purée]]''. ''[[Empanada]]s'' — small [[Pastry|pastries]] of meat, [[cheese]], [[sweet corn]], and a hundred other fillings — are a common sight at parties and [[picnic]]s, or as [[Entrée|starters]] to a meal. A variation, the &quot;empanada gallega&quot; (Galician empanada), is a big, round meat pie made most commonly with [[tuna]] and [[Mackerel (food)|mackerel]] (&quot;''caballa''&quot; in Spanish). [[Vegetable]]s and [[salad]]s are also eaten by Argentines; [[tomato]]es, [[onion]]s, [[lettuce]], [[eggplant]]s, [[Squash (plant)|squashes]], and [[zucchini]] are common [[side dish]]es.

Italian staples, such as pizza and pasta, are eaten as commonly as beef. ''Fideos'' ([[noodle]]s), ''tallarines'' (''[[fettuccine]]'' and ''[[tagliatelle]]''), ''ñoquis'' ([[gnocchi]]), ''[[Ravioli|ravioles]]'', and ''canelones'' ([[cannelloni]]) can be bought freshly made in many establishments in the larger cities. Italian-style [[ice cream]] is served in large [[parlour]]s and even drive-through businesses.

In [[Chubut Province|Chubut]], the [[Welsh settlement in Argentina|Welsh community]] is known for its [[teahouse]]s, offering [[scone (bread)|scone]]s and ''torta galesa'', which is rather like ''[[Bara Brith|torta negra]]''.

''[[Sandwiches de miga]]'' are delicate sandwiches made with crustless buttered white bread, very thinly sliced [[Curing (food preservation)|cured]] meat, cheese, and lettuce. They are often purchased from entrepreneurial home cooks and may be eaten for a light evening meal.

A sweet [[Paste (food)|paste]], ''dulce de leche'' is another treasured national food, used to fill [[cake]]s and [[pancake]]s, spread over [[toast]]ed bread for [[breakfast]], or served with ice cream. ''[[Alfajor]]es'' are [[shortbread]] [[cookie]]s sandwiched together with [[chocolate]] and ''dulce de leche'' or a [[fruit]] paste. The &quot;[[police]]man's&quot; or &quot;[[truck]] driver's&quot; sweet is cheese with [[quince]] paste or ''[[dulce de membrillo]]''. ''[[Dulce de batata]]'' is made of [[sweet potato]]/[[yam (vegetable)|yam]]: this with cheese is the ''[[Martin Fierro|Martín Fierro]]'''s [[sweet]]. [[Apple]]s, [[pear]]s, [[peach]]es, [[kiwifruit]]s, [[avocado]]s, and [[plum]]s are major [[export]]s.

A traditional [[drink]] of Argentina is an [[infusion]] called [[mate (beverage)|mate]] (in Spanish, ''mate'', with the accent on the first syllable [MAH-teh]). The name comes from the hollow [[gourd]] from which it is traditionally drunk. The mate (gourd) or other small [[cup]] is filled about three-quarters full with ''yerba mate'', the dried [[Leaf|leaves]] and [[twig]]s of the ''[[Ilex paraguariensis]]''. The drink, which is rather [[bitter (taste)|bitter]], is sipped through a metal or cane [[straw]] called a ''[[bombilla]]''. Mate can be sweetened with [[sugar]], or [[flavor]]ed with [[aroma|aromatic]] herbs or dried [[orange (fruit)|orange]] [[peel (fruit)|peel]]. Hot but not boiling water is poured into the gourd, drunk, then the mate is refilled. The mate is nearly full of leaves, so each refill only makes a small drink, but many refills are possible before the yerba is spent. In small gatherings it is traditional for one ''mate'' to be passed from person to person, filled by whoever has the kettle. It is customary not to thank the refiller routinely; a final ''gracias'' (thank you) implies that the drinker has had enough.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lanacion.com.ar/1156709-se-toma-un-mate-segunda-parte La Nación newspaper: ¿Se toma un mate? (Segunda parte)] Source for everything about mate, including terminal &quot;gracias&quot;. {{in lang|es}}&lt;/ref&gt; Drinking mate together is an important social ritual. ''[[Mate cocido]]'' is the same leaf, which rather than [[Boiling|brewed]] is [[Boiling|boiled]] and served, like [[tea]], with [[milk]] and sugar to taste.

Other typical drinks include [[wine]] (sometimes with [[soda water]] added); tea and coffee are equally important. [[Quilmes]] is the national [[brand]] of [[pale lager]], named after the town of [[Quilmes, Buenos Aires]], where it was first produced.

==Ingredients==
''Argentine Cuisine'' is heavily based on the growth of all kinds of [[cereal]]s, [[grain]]s, [[oil seed]]s, [[fruit]]s and [[vegetable]]s, since [[Argentina]] is a significantly large [[livestock]] and [[agriculture|agricultural]] country. In the [[Mesopotamia, Argentina|Mesopotamia]] waters river fish such as [[silverside (fish)|silverside]], [[Pseudoplatystoma|surubi]], dorado or [[Leporinus obtusidens|boga]] clearly stand out.&lt;ref name=&quot;gastronomy&quot;/&gt;

Meat products have been dominant in the country since the 16th century.&lt;ref name=&quot;sari&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Edelstein|first=Sari|year=2010|title=Food, Cuisine, and Cultural Competency for Culinary, Hospitality, and Nutrition Professionals|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=NQoWQTVcpVIC&amp;pg=PA478&amp;dq=argentine+cuisine&amp;hl=es&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=icQpU_HmLoaUkQf75oDwDw&amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;q=argentina&amp;f=false|location= |publisher=Jones &amp; Bartlett Publishers|isbn=978-0763759650|accessdate=19 March 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; The country is regarded as a major [[beef]], [[pork]] and [[poultry]] producing and consuming country. As a matter of fact, certain areas such as those located in the south are usually engaged in activities involving [[sheep]] and [[lamb and mutton|lamb]] breeding, and [[shellfish]], [[crustacean]]s, [[mollusc]]s and [[salmon]]ides fishing.

The vast breeding activity involving any type of [[cattle]] has given rise to a very developed [[dairy]] industry that includes products like [[cow milk|cow]], [[sheep milk|sheep]] and [[camelide]], [[cheese]], [[dulce de leche]] and [[yogurt]]s. Argentina can also be conceived as a great industry engaged in the production of [[dried fruit]]s, [[olive]]s, all types of [[oil]]s and [[spice]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;gastronomy&quot;/&gt;

When it comes to blending ingredients and readapating other latitude cuisines traditions, the almost unlimited source of raw materials above enables the existence of a great product versatility.&lt;ref name=&quot;gastronomy&quot;/&gt;

== Regional differences ==
Argentine cuisine is heavily influenced by its European roots and has regional variations. ''Asado'', ''dulce de leche'', ''empanadas'', and ''yerba mate'' are found throughout Argentina. In many parts of the country, food is prepared differently and different kinds of foods are made; this includes to a smaller degree food from [[pre-Columbian]] times, as in the Northwest.

=== Central region and la Pampa ===
[[File:Pizza over Fainá.jpg|thumb|left|210px|Sliced pizza served over ''[[fainá]]'', a common combination.]]
[[File:Puchero argentino servido.JPG|thumb|Argentine [[Puchero]]]]
For long periods, urban areas such as [[Buenos Aires]], [[Rosario, Santa Fe|Rosario]], and [[Córdoba, Argentina|Córdoba]] welcomed [[Argentines of European descent|European immigrants]], including, above all, those of [[Italian Argentine|Italian]] and [[Spanish Argentine|Spanish]] descent. Nevertheless, there was also a migratory flow of [[German Argentine|German]], [[Swiss Argentine|Swiss]], and Middle-Eastern immigrants arriving in Argentina. Among the countless changes this melting pot brought was the enrichment of the culinary art. Dishes such as pasta, pizza, [[puchero]]s ([[stew]]s), [[croqueta]]s ([[fritter]])s, [[sauce]]s, [[embutido]]s ([[sausage]]s), and chicken and meat courses brought a wider scope of options to daily menus. Furthermore, the bread-making, dessert, pastry, and dairy industries have achieved considerable development in this region.

The above-mentioned dishes have developed a distinctively Argentine nuance. That is why, for example, Argentine pasta includes a wide variety of dishes ranging from [[spaghetti]], fusiles ([[fusilli]]), ñoquis ([[gnocchi]]), [[ravioli]], cintas (pasta ribbons), and [[lasagne]] to the Argentine-made sorrentinos, agnolottis ([[agnolotti]]), canelones ([[cannelloni]]), and fetuchines ([[fettuccine]]).

Pizza—made with very thin, and sometimes thick, high-rising [[dough]]s, with or without [[cheese]], cooked in the [[oven]] or ''a la piedra'' (on a [[stone oven]]), and stuffed with numerous ingredients -— is a dish which can be found in nearly every corner of the  country. [[Buenos Aires]], [[Rosario]], and [[Córdoba, Argentina|Córdoba]] also serve it with [[fainá]], which is a chick pea-flour dough placed over the piece of pizza. People say that what makes the Argentine pizza unique is the blending of Italian and Spanish cultures. At the turn of the 19th century, immigrants from [[Naples]] and [[Genoa]] opened the first pizza bars, though Spanish residents subsequently owned most of the pizza businesses.

[[File:Alfajores de Argentina.jpg|thumb|235px|Argentine pastry, including ''Rogel'' (a cake of layers of [[hojaldre]] covered with [[meringue]]), [[dulce de leche]], and regional variants of [[Alfajores]] (from [[Mar del Plata]], [[Córdoba Province, Argentina|Córdoba]], [[Tucumán Province|Tucumán]], among others).]]

[[Bread]] products are consumed all around the country. The deeply rooted bread, pastry, and dessert-making tradition derives from blending the above nationalities' products. [[Bakery|Bakeries]] sell not only a wide scope of breads, cookies, and cakes, but also pastries. The latter resembles a sort of roll [[pastry]] whose main dough ingredient is either butter or fat and which may be simple or stuffed with [[dulce de leche]], [[milk]], [[jam]], crema pastelera, or quince or apple jelly, among other fillings. The most popular type of pastry is said to be that of ''mediaslunas'' (singular: ''medialuna,'' literally half moon, that is to say, crescent), based upon [[French cuisine|French]] [[croissant]]s. Furthermore, [[sandwiches de miga]] are another type of bread products; they are made only with thin layers of [[white bread]] (generally referred to as crustless bread) and stuffed with food items ranging from [[ham and cheese]] to other more sophisticated combinations such as raw ham, tomatoes, olives, hard boiled eggs, tuna, lettuce, red pepper, and the like.

Desserts and sweets are usually stuffed or covered with [[dulce de leche]]. The latter can be eaten alone or on top of cakes, [[alfajor]]es, panqueques ([[Crêpe|crepes]]), and pastries, or as a topping spread over [[flan de leche]]. [[Chantilly cream]] is widely consumed and used in preparing sweets and desserts. Additionally, cakes, sponge cakes, and puddings are very popular dishes. [[Italian ice-cream]]s in this region also achieved a significant degree of development by adding local flavors that somehow preserved the local spirit involved in their preparation.

Although asado is eaten all over the country, its origin may be traced back to the [[Pampas]]. It entails manifold types of meat, which are generally eaten as follows: achuras ([[offal]], or the cow's inner parts), morcilla ([[black pudding|blood sausage]]), and sometimes also a [[provoleta]] (a piece of [[provolone]] cheese cooked on the grill with [[oregano]]) are eaten first. Then comes the [[choripán]] (a kind of spiced sausage made with pork or lamb and placed between two slices of bread), and lastly meat such as [[short ribs|asado de tira]], vacío ([[flank steak]]), lomo ([[Beef tenderloin|tenderloin]]), colita de cuadril ([[round steak|rump]]), matambre (rolled stuffed steak cut into slices and served cold), entraña ([[hanger steak]]); the list is never-ending. It is quite common to eat and enjoy a dish known as ''cabrito al asador'' (roast kid or goat) in the [[Córdoba Province, Argentina|province of Córdoba]].

=== Northwest and Cuyo ===
[[File:Locro argentino.JPG|thumb|left|210px|A bowl of ''[[Locro]]'' stew, a traditional standby in northwestern Argentina.]]

This region is regarded as perhaps the one most influenced by Native Americans, and its foods are closely linked to the Andean-Incan tradition. When preparing regional dishes, [[potato]]es and [[maize|corn]] or wheat are almost always used, including [[quinoa]] (a cereal typically used in Incan cuisine), [[Bell pepper|peppers]], [[Squash (plant)|squashes]] and [[tomato]]es. The most celebrated dishes are [[humita]] and [[Tamale|tamal]], in which the corn husk is stuffed with the corn filling itself, seasonings or meat.
 
This region is the most suitable to taste [[empanada]]s, particularly those stuffed with meat and offering different types of tempting varieties such as the ''meat empanada'', salteña also filled with potatoes, or the ''empanada tucumana'', which is stuffed with matambre and cut with a knife, or empanadas made with cheese. Empanadas are individual sized and closed savoury pastries which may be fried or baked in the oven and are generally eaten with the hands.

Stews such as [[locro]], carbonada, [[pollo al disco]], and [[cazuela]]s (casseroles) are also typical dishes characterizing this region, which also include pumpkin or potato pudding stuffed with meat.

=== Mesopotamia ===
[[File:Kaa mate.JPG|thumb|210px|[[Mate (beverage)|Mate]], the [[Mesopotamia, Argentina|northeastern region]]'s best-known contribution to Argentine cuisine.]]

The humid and verdant area of north-east Argentina known as [[Mesopotamia, Argentina|Mesopotamia]], comprising the provinces of Corrientes, Misiones and Entre Ríos is another area influenced by Native Americans, particularly by the [[Guaraní people|Guaraní tribe]]. Abounding in rivers and shores, it offers a wide diversity of fish species, such as dorado, [[Piaractus mesopotamicus|pacú]], [[Pseudoplatystoma|surubi]], [[Leporinus obtusidens|boga]] and [[Atheriniformes|silverside]].

Widely grown in this area, [[cassava]] is typically included in the region's dishes, as are other components of meals, such as the [[chipá]] (a cassava and cheese bread). However, in this area Cassava is cooked alone too, boiled or fried, often as a side dish for asado and empanadas. Sopa Paraguaya and Chipá Guazu (also called Tarta de Choclo) are also commonly eaten and are made with corn. [[Chipá]] from Cassava is often eaten during breakfast with yerba mate, prepared with hot water, or with [[café con leche]]. Sopa Paraguaya and Tarta de Choclo are eaten for lunch or dinner. As regards to products made with sugar, [[Papaya]] (mamón in Argentine Spanish) [[jam]] is typical of the [[Corrientes Province|province of Corrientes]].

The principal product of this region is certainly [[yerba mate]]. Consumed countrywide, this product features a peculiarity of its own in this area: it is not only prepared with hot water, but, driven by the region's high temperatures, it is common to see it prepared with cold water as well, in which case the beverage is known as [[tereré]].

=== Patagonia ===
Foods produced in the large southern region of [[Patagonia]] include [[fish]] and [[seafood]] from the sea and rivers, and the products of the [[sheep]] widely farmed there.

Marine species such as [[Salmon (food)|salmon]], [[Lithodes santolla|spider crab]]s, [[Squid (food)|squid]] and other [[shellfish]] and [[mollusc]]s may be caught in the [[Atlantic Ocean]]. There are [[trout]] in the rivers.

[[File:Tortas en San Martín de los Andes.JPG|thumb|210px|''Chocolate y [[dulce de leche]]'' cakes and other regional favorites in a [[San Martín de los Andes]], [[Neuquen Province|Neuquén]] shop.]]
The many berries grown in the area include [[Cherry|cherries]], [[Bilberry|bilberries]], [[Strawberry|strawberries]], [[Rosa rubiginosa|rosa mosqueta]] and elders, which are made into [[jam]]s.

The [[Northern Europe|Northern]] and [[Central Europe]]an settlements in this region have built up large-scale production of [[chocolate]] and its by-products. Viennese and German cuisine and pastries are also typically associated with this region.

Mutton and lamb, together with wild boar and venison tend to make up the region's meat-based dishes. Also typical of  southern region are smoked products, including salmon, stag, wild boar, and pheasant.

Patagonia has been profoundly influenced by the tribes living there since long before Europeans arrived, in particular, the [[Mapuche]]s and the [[Araucano]]s. A typical dish prepared by the latter is the [[curanto]] (a term meaning &quot;hot stone&quot;). Its preparation involves making a fire in a hole about 150&amp;nbsp;cm deep in the ground, and heating stones in it. A bed of nalca or maqui leaves is arranged on top of the stones, and ingredients are added in turn on top. Ingredients vary, but may include beef, lamb, pork, chicken, [[Chorizo#South America|Argentine chorizos]] (pork sausages), potatoes, sweet potatoes, apples and holed squashes filled with cheese, cream and peas. The food is covered with leaves and damp pieces of cloth to keep the heat in, and covered with plenty of soil.

== Alcoholic beverages ==
{{See also|Argentine wine}}
{{multiple image
| align = right
| image1 = Vino argentino.jpg
| width1 = 170
| alt1 = 
| caption1 = 
| image2 = Vino argentino blanco premium.jpg
| width2 = 157
| alt2 = 
| caption2 = 
| footer = Glasses of Argentine red (left) and white (right) wine.
}}

Though [[wine]] (''vino'') has traditionally been the most popular alcoholic beverage in Argentina, beer (''cerveza''; the Italian ''birra'' is frequently used) in recent decades has competed with wine in popularity. Breweries appeared in Argentina at the end of the 1860s, started by [[Alsace|Alsatian]] colonists. The first were nearly all in the downtown of Buenos Aires (''el égido de la Ciudad Autónoma de Buenos Aires''), and soon [[Poland|Polish]] brewers began industrial production of beer: San Carlos in the province of Santa Fe, [[Río Segundo, Córdoba|Río Segundo]] and Córdoba in the province of Córdoba, [[Cerveza Quilmes|Quilmes]] and [[Llavallol]] on the outskirts of [[La Plata]] (in Buenos Aires Province), [[San Miguel de Tucumán]] in the province of Tucumán and on the outskirts of the cities of [[Mendoza, Argentina|Mendoza]] and [[Salta]].

The local consumption of beer has risen dramatically in the last generation: Argentines consumed 233 million liters in 1980 and 1.57 billion in 2007 (40 liters per capita).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web
 |url          = http://www.mecon.gov.ar/peconomica/basehome/infoeco.html
 |title        = Programación Macroeconómica
 |website      = Mecon.gov.ar
 |access-date  = 2016-02-26
 |archive-url  = https://web.archive.org/web/20150525061254/http://www.mecon.gov.ar/peconomica/basehome/infoeco.html
 |archive-date = 2015-05-25
 |url-status=dead
 |df           = 
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Outpacing that of wine since 2001, the growing production and consumption of beer has supported the existence of related events, for example beer festivals called ''[[Oktoberfest]]s'' or &quot;''Fiestas de la Cerveza''&quot; in locations that have a significant [[Germans|German]] population ([[Villa General Belgrano]] in Córdoba, [[San Carlos, Santa Fe|San Carlos]] and [[Esperanza, Santa Fe|Esperanza]] in the province of Santa Fe, etc.). Such celebrations copy, in an Argentine manner, [[Munich]]'s ''Oktoberfest'', and similarly are tourist attractions. However, the presence of a vigorous population of [[Celt]]ic lineage, principally of Irish origin, has supported the creation of other celebrations of beer, often for marketing purposes, such as [[Saint Patrick's Day]] (''Día de San Patricio''), patron of Ireland, which is celebrated with abundant libations.

The consumption of alcoholic beverages in Argentina is similar to that of the United States and somewhat lower than the Western European average.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.who.int/substance_abuse/publications/global_status_report_2004_overview.pdf|format=PDF|title=Global Status Report on Alcohol 2004|website=Who.int|accessdate=2017-08-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; Argentines enjoy a variety of alcoholic beverages and Argentina can boast a varied array of ''elaboraciones'', whether industrial or [[artisanal]]. Besides beer and wine, Argentines frequently drink [[cider]] (here again, the heritage comes from Spain and Italy, more precisely from [[Asturias]] and [[Campania]]). Cider is the most popular beverage of the middle and lower economic classes at Christmas and [[New Year]] (the upper classes proverbially preferring to celebrate with locally produced [[champagne]], although real old-line &quot;[[Creole peoples|creole]]&quot; aristocrats will still drink cider, which is much more traditional).

Other widely consumed spirits are ''[[aguardiente]]'' (firewater) made from [[sugar cane]], known as ''caña quemada'' (&quot;burnt cane&quot;) or, simply, ''''caña'''&lt;nowiki/&gt;' (&quot;cane&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;Although &quot;caña&quot; in this sense is really derived from &quot;[[cognac]]&quot; and the term was traditionally used in old Argentina for any [[brandy]], but especially for peach brandy, ''caña de durazno''.&lt;/ref&gt; A folkloric note about ''caña quemada'': until June 21 it is traditional to drink ''caña quemada'' with ''ruda macho'' (a variant of [[common rue]]), it is supposed that this mixture prevents the [[flu]] and other illnesses. ''Caña'' competes, mainly in rural areas, with [[gin]] (&quot;ginebra&quot;—as in the [[Netherlands|Dutch]] kind of gin.)

There are many artisanally produced [[liqueur]]s (distilled, flavored [[alcoholic beverage]]s) in Argentina, for example those flavored with [[orange (fruit)|orange]], [[egg (food)|egg]], [[anise]], coffee, cherry and, inevitably, ''dulce de leche''. The ''[[Hesperidina]]'' is a type of liqueur made from orange peels, invented in Argentina around 1890. One may also encounter ''chitronchelo'' or (in Italian) ''[[citroncello]]'', based on lemon. This beverage arrived with immigrants from the [[Mezzogiorno]], and is produced both artisanally and industrially (for example, at [[Mar del Plata]]).

== Non-alcoholic specialties ==
[[File:Tortoni 3 008.jpg|thumb|[[Café Tortoni]], one of the many [[coffehouse]]s in [[Buenos Aires]]. The consumption of coffee is very common (141 cups per capita, annually).&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;{{cite web|url=http://blog.federicosanchez.info/2002/07/20/%C2%BFel-negocio-del-cafe-en-argentina-puede-seguir-creciendo/|title=El negocio del café en la Argentina|website=Blog.federicosanchez.info|accessdate=2 August 2017}}{{Dead link|date=December 2018 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
[[File:Mediaslunas, café en jarrito y agua mineral en Café El Gato Negro.JPG|thumbnail|right|Traditional serving of merienda in Café El Gato Negro, [[Buenos Aires]]. ''Medialunas'' (croissants), ''café en jarrito'' (a double espresso coffee) and a little glass of mineral water.]]
Argentines enjoy a wide variety of non-alcoholic infusions (although now and then both &quot;families&quot; are mixed; the ''yerbiao'' for example, is mate mixed with ''caña'' or gin). Among these, ''mate'' has long been the most widely enjoyed; in 2006, over 700,000 metric tons were harvested in Argentina, mostly for domestic consumption.Mate is also one of the top exports from Argentina, as it is valued all over the world. &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web
 |url=http://www.indec.mecon.ar/ 
 |title=INDEC: Instituto nacional de estadistica y censos de la Republica Argentina 
 |website=Indec.mecon.ar 
 |access-date=2016-02-26 
 |url-status=dead 
 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160221215704/http://www.indec.mecon.ar/ 
 |archivedate=2016-02-21 
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The fact that mate is so prevalent in the ''[[Southern Cone]]'', however, should not necessarily make visitors think that other infusions are rare in the region; in Argentina especially, given the strong European cultural imprint, the consumption of coffee is very common (141 cups per capita, annually).&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt; Chocolate [[infusion]]s are also popular (the eating of chocolate is a Spanish influence, although the plant originated in [[Mesoamerica]]). This consumption grows during autumn and winter, or in the cold regions of the country; there are two dates where consumption of chocolate infusions is traditional in the primary educational centres: 25 May and 9 July, that is, the two national dates of Argentina.

English cultural influence (reinforced at the end of the 19th century and beginnings of the 20th by British contacts with the [[Far East]]) has also made the consumption of [[tea]] very common.

[[Medicinal herb]]s are common in the whole country; among the most popular are: [[chamomile]], [[Salvia reflexa|lanceleaf]], ''[[boldo]]'', ''poleo'', ''[[peperina]]'', ''carqueja'', [[thyme]], ''canchalagua'', [[rue]] (''macho'' and ''hembra'', that is, &quot;male&quot; and &quot;female&quot;), [[Malva|mallow]], [[rosemary]], [[passion flower]], ''bira bira'', ''palán palán'', ''[[Minthostachys mollis|muña muña]]'', to mention only the main ones. Many of these herbs are also used in [[apéritif]]s and [[bitter (taste)|bitter]]s, whether alcoholic or not.

== Popular short-order dishes ==
[[File:BarBritanico.JPG|thumb|210px|''Bar Británico'', Buenos Aires. These &quot;bars&quot; are typically more akin to [[Culture of the United Kingdom|British]] &quot;[[pub]]s&quot; and are popular at lunchtime.]]
Common ''restoranes'' or ''[[restaurant]]es'' and ''rotiserias'' (grill restaurants) nearly anywhere in Argentina today serve (into the small hours) quickly prepared meals that in the course of the 20th century came to be known as ''minutas'', &quot;short-order dishes&quot;. Some of the dishes included in the category of ''minutas'' are ''[[milanesa]]s'', ''churrascos'', ''bifes'' ([[beefsteak]]s), ''[[escalopes]]'', ''[[tallarines]]'', ''ravioles'' ([[ravioli]]), ''ñoquis'' ([[gnocchi]]), although some are very typical of locations that sell food: &quot;''bifes''&quot; and &quot;''milanesas''&quot; are served &quot;''a caballo''&quot; (&quot;on horseback&quot;, with [[fried egg]] on top), &quot;''milanesa completa''&quot; (a ''milanesa'' with two fried eggs and [[French fries]]), &quot;''revuelto Gramajo''&quot;, &quot;''colchón de arvejas''&quot; (an omelette made with peas), &quot;''suprema de pollo''&quot; (chicken [[Supreme (cookery)|supreme]], usually breaded as a ''milanesa''), ''[[matambre]]s'', &quot;''lengua a la vinagreta''&quot; ([[Pickling|pickled]] [[Tongue (foodstuff)|tongue]]), and &quot;[[sandwich]]es&quot; (sandwiches de miga) are made with sliced white bread, rather than, say, rolls.

The most common sandwiches are those made of ''milanesa'', baked ham and cheese, 'pan de miga'', [[toast]], ''[[pebete]]s'', ''panchos'' (hot dogs), ''[[choripan]]es'', ''morcipanes'', etc.; from [[Montevideo]] comes a different species of sandwich called the ''[[chivito (sandwich)|chivito]]'', even though it contains no goat meat.

''[[Picada (Argentina)|Picadas]]'', which are consumed at home or in [[Bar (establishment)|bars]], [[café]]s, &quot;''cafetines''&quot; and &quot;''[[bodegones]]''&quot; are also popular; they consist of an ensemble of plates containing cubes of cheese (typically from [[Mar del Plata]] or [[Chubut Province|Chubut]]), pieces of [[salame]], [[olive]]s in [[brine]], french fries, ''maníes'' ([[peanut]]s), etc.; ''[[picada]]''s are eaten accompanied by an alcoholic beverage (&quot;''[[fernet]]''&quot;, beer, wine with [[Carbonated water|soda]], to give some common examples).

The people of Argentina greatly enjoy ''helado'' ([[ice cream]]s of Italian lineage  or [[sorbet]]s Spanish lineage). In Spanish colonial times a type of [[sorbet]] was made from [[hail]] or snow.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.biblioteca.org.ar/libros/71113.pdf [[Lucio V Mansilla]]: ''Mis Memorias'']&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;gallery class=&quot;center&quot; caption=&quot;&quot; widths=&quot;220px&quot; heights=&quot;160px&quot;&gt; 
File:Picadacordobesa.JPG|A ''picada'', the Italian-influenced between-meals standby
&lt;/gallery&gt;

== Eating habits ==
Breakfast typically is small and consists of coffee (or mate) and pastry. In most parts of Argentina, lunch is the largest meal of the day. Excluding the largest cities, such as Buenos Aires, most towns close for lunch time. This is when most people return home to enjoy a large meal and siesta. Traditional lunches in Argentina are long and well developed. Argentinians often have a light evening snack (called a &quot;merienda&quot; - typically a coffee or mate and a pastry) and it is common to not eat dinner until 9 at night, or even later on weekends.

==See also==
{{portal|Argentina|Food}}
* [[Italian cuisine]]
* [[Spanish cuisine]]
* [[Paraguayan cuisine]]
* [[Uruguayan cuisine]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Cuisine of Argentina}}
* [http://www.saltshaker.net SaltShaker] - Blog on Buenos Aires &quot;food, drink, and life&quot;.
* [http://www.pickupthefork.com Pick Up the Fork] - Fun guide to Buenos Aires' food, restaurant and bar scene
* [http://www.idlewords.com/2006/04/argentina_on_two_steaks_a_day.htm Argentina on two steaks a day]

{{Argentina topics|state=uncollapsed}}
{{South American topic|| cuisine}}
{{cuisine}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Argentine Cuisine}}
[[Category:Argentine cuisine| ]]</text>
      <sha1>mmcxx8hv5orerdv6ax5k2342gdc2zge</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
