  <page>
    <title>Steel-string acoustic guitar</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2237</id>
    <revision>
      <id>940436923</id>
      <parentid>938178264</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-12T14:53:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Gonzo fan2007</username>
        <id>1347436</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Per [[MOS:BOLDAVOID]]: Links should not be placed in the boldface reiteration of the title in the opening sentence of a lead</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{More citations needed|date=February 2017}}
{{For|a general range of acoustic, non-electric guitars|acoustic guitar}}
{{Infobox Instrument
|name=Steel-string acoustic guitar
|image= Gibson_SJ200.jpg
|image_capt= A [[Gibson SJ200]] model
|background=string
|classification= [[String instrument]] ([[Plucked string instrument|plucked]])
|hornbostel_sachs=321.322-6
|hornbostel_sachs_desc=Composite [[chordophone]] sounded by a [[plectrum]]
|range=[[File:Range guitar.svg|130px|center]]
|related=
* '''[[Plucked string instrument|Guitar family]]''' ([[Classical guitar]], [[Electric guitar]], [[Flamenco guitar]], [[Bass guitar|bass]])
* [[Lute]] (distantly related)
|musicians=
|midi=025/026 (Acoustic Steel Guitar)
|articles=
}}

[[File:Playing acoustic guitar.jpg|thumb|right|200px|[[Fingerpicking]] a steel-string guitar]]
[[File:C.F._Martin_000-28EC_Eric_Clapton_model_Acoustic_Guitar.jpg|thumb|right|150px|A [[C. F. Martin &amp; Company|C.F. Martin]] [[Eric Clapton]] model]]
[[File:Fender DG-41SCE Electro-acoustic guitar.JPG|thumb|right|170px|[[Fender Musical Instruments Corporation|Fender]] DG-41SCE]]
[[File:Epiphone PR-5E VS Cutaway Acoustic Electric Guitar (Vintage Sunburst).jpg|thumb|right|170px|[[Epiphone]] PR-5E VS]]

The '''steel-string acoustic guitar''' is a modern form of [[guitar]] that descends from the nylon-strung [[classical guitar]], but is strung with [[steel]] [[String (music)|strings]] for a brighter, louder sound. Like the classical guitar, it is often referred to simply as an '''acoustic guitar'''.

The most common type is often called a [[flat top guitar]], to distinguish it from the more specialized [[archtop guitar]] and other variations.

The [[Standard tuning#Plucked strings|standard tuning]] for an acoustic guitar is E-A-D-G-B-E (low to high), although many players, particularly [[fingerpicking|fingerpickers]], use alternate tunings ([[scordatura]]), such as [[Open G tuning|open G]] (D-G-D-G-B-D), [[open D tuning|open D]] (D-A-D-F{{music|sharp}}-A-D), or [[Drop D tuning|drop D]] (D-A-D-G-B-E).

== Construction ==
Steel-string guitars vary in construction and materials. Different woods and approach to bracing affect the instrument's [[timbre]] or tone. While there is little scientific evidence, many players and [[luthier]]s believe a well-made guitar's tone improves over time. They theorize that a decrease in the content of hemicellulose, crystallization of cellulose, and changes to lignin over time all result in its wood gaining better resonating properties.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.premierguitar.com/articles/19720-acoustic-soundboard-the-sonic-effect-of-time-and-vibration|title=Acoustic Soundboard: The Sonic Effect of Time and Vibration|last=October 02|first=Rick Turner|last2=2013|website=www.premierguitar.com|language=en|access-date=2019-09-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Types ===
Steel-string acoustic guitars are commonly constructed in several body types, varying in size, depth, and proportion. In general, the guitar's soundbox can be thought of as composed of two mating chambers: the ''upper bouts'' (a ''bout'' being the rounded corner of an instrument body) on the neck end of the body,  and ''lower bouts'' (on the bridge end). These meet at the ''waist,'' or the narrowest part of the body face near the soundhole. The proportion and overall size of these two parts helps determine the overall tonal balance and &quot;native sound&quot; of a particular body style – the larger the body, the louder the volume.

* The ''00'', ''double-O'' or ''grand concert'' body type is the major body style most directly derived from the classical guitar. It has the thinnest soundbox and the smallest overall size, making it very comfortable to play but lacking in projection -volume - relative to the larger types. Its smaller size makes it suitable for younger or smaller-framed players. It is commonly called a &quot;parlor steel&quot;, as it is well-suited to smaller rooms. [[C. F. Martin &amp; Company|Martin]]'s 00-xxx series and [[Taylor Guitars|Taylor]]'s x12 series are common examples.
* The ''grand auditorium'' guitar, sometimes called the ''000'' or the ''triple-O'' is very similar in design to the grand concert, but slightly wider and deeper. Many 000-style guitars also have a convex back to increase the physical volume of the soundbox without making it deeper at the edges, which would affect comfort and playability. The result is a very balanced tone, comparable to the 00 but with greater volume and dynamic range and slightly more low-end response, making this Classically shaped body style very popular. [[Eric Clapton]]'s signature Martin, for example, is of this style. Martin's 000-xxx series and Taylor's x14 series are well-known examples of the grand auditorium style.
* The ''[[Dreadnought (guitar type)|dreadnought]]'' is a large-bodied guitar which incorporates a deeper soundbox, but a smaller and less-pronounced upper bout than most styles. Its size and power gave rise to its name, from the most formidable class of warship at the time of its creation in the early 20th century. The style was designed by [[Martin Guitars]]&lt;ref name=&quot;sweetwater1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Acoustic Guitar Buying Guide|url=http://www.sweetwater.com/insync/acoustic-guitar-buying-guide/|publisher=www.sweetwater.com|accessdate=11 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; to produce a deeper sound than &quot;classic&quot;-style guitars, with very resonant bass. Its body's combination of compact profile with a deep sound has since been copied by virtually every major steel-string luthier, making it the most popular body type. [[Martin Guitars|Martin]]'s &quot;D&quot; series guitars, such as the highly prized [[Martin D-28|D-28]], are classic examples of the dreadnought.
* The ''jumbo'' body type is bigger again than a grand auditorium but similarly proportioned, and is generally designed to provide a deep tone similar to a dreadnought's.  It was designed by [[Gibson]] to compete with the dreadnought,&lt;ref name=&quot;sweetwater1&quot;/&gt;) but with maximum resonant space for greater volume and sustain. These come at the expense of being oversized, with a very deep sounding box, and thus somewhat more difficult to play. The foremost example of the style is the [[Gibson J-200]], but like the dreadnought, most guitar manufacturers have at least one jumbo model.

Any of these body type can incorporate a ''[[cutaway (guitar)|cutaway]]'', where a section of the upper Below the neck is scalloped out.  This allows for easier access to the frets located atop the soundbox, at the expense of reduced soundbox volume and altered bracing, which can affect the resonant qualities and resulting tone of the instrument.

* The ''[[Twelve-string guitar|12-string guitar]]'' replaces each string with a [[Course (music)|course]] of two strings. The lower pairs are tuned an octave apart. Its unique sound was made famous by artists such as [[Lead Belly]], [[Pete Seeger]] and [[Leo Kottke]].

All of these relatively traditional looking and constructed instruments are commonly referred to as ''flattop'' guitars. All are commonly used in popular music genres, including [[rock music|rock]], [[blues]], [[Country music|country]], and [[Folk music|folk]].

Other styles of guitar which enjoy moderate popularity, generally in more specific genres, include:
* The ''[[archtop guitar|archtop]]'', which incorporates an arched, [[violin]]-like top either carved out of solid wood or heat-pressed using laminations.  It usually has violin style  f-holes rather than a single round sound hole. It is most commonly used by [[swing (genre)|swing]] and [[jazz]] players and often incorporates an electric [[Pickup (music technology)|pickup]]. 
* The ''[[Selmer-Maccaferri guitar]]'' is usually played by those who follow the style of [[Django Reinhardt]]. It is an unusual-looking instrument, distinguished by a fairly large body with squarish bouts, and either a D-shaped or longitudinal oval soundhole. The strings are gathered at the tail like an archtop guitar, but the top is flatter. It also has a wide fingerboard and slotted head like a nylon-string guitar. The loud volume and penetrating tone make it suitable for single-note [[guitar solo|soloing]], and it is frequently employed as a [[lead guitar|lead instrument]] in [[gypsy swing]].
* The ''[[resonator guitar]]'' or ''[[resophonic guitar]]'', also called the ''[[Dobro]]'' after its most prominent manufacturer, amplifies its sound through one or more metal cone-shaped resonators. It was designed to overcome the problem of conventional acoustic guitars being overwhelmed by horns and percussion instruments in dance orchestras. It became prized for its distinctive sound, however, and gained a place in several musical styles (most notably blues and bluegrass), and retains a niche well after the proliferation of electric amplification.

=== Tonewoods ===
Traditionally, steel-string guitars have been made of a combination of various ''[[tonewood]]s'', or woods considered to have pleasing resonant qualities when used in instrument-making. Note that the term is ill-defined - the wood species that are considered tonewoods have evolved throughout history&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Mottola |first1=R.M. |title=Mottola's Cyclopedic Dictionary of Lutherie Terms |date=1 January 2020 |publisher=LiutaioMottola.com |isbn=978-1-7341256-0-3 |page=165 |url=https://www.liutaiomottola.com/books/dictionary.htm |ref=Mottola's Cyclopedic Dictionary of Lutherie Terms}}&lt;/ref&gt;. Foremost for making steel-string guitar tops are [[Sitka spruce]], the most common, and Alpine and Adirondack spruce. The back and sides of a particular guitar are typically made of the same wood; Brazilian or East Indian [[rosewood]] and Honduras [[mahogany]] are traditional choices, however, [[maple]] has been prized for the figuring that can be seen when it is cut in a certain way (such as ''flame'' and ''quilt'' patterns). A common non-traditional wood gaining popularity is [[sapele]], which is tonally similar to mahogany but slightly lighter in color and possessing a deep grain structure that is visually appealing.

Due to decreasing availability and rising prices of premium-quality traditional tonewoods, many manufacturers have begun experimenting with alternative species of woods or more commonly available variations on the standard species. For example, some makers have begun producing models with [[Thuja plicata|red cedar]] or mahogany tops, or with [[spruce]] variants other than Sitka. Cedar is also common in the back and sides, as is [[basswood]]. Entry-level models, especially those made in East Asia, often use [[nato wood]], which is again tonally similar to mahogany but is cheap to acquire. Some have also begun using non-wood materials, such as [[plastic]] or [[graphite]]. Carbon-fiber and phenolic composite materials have become desirable for building necks, and some high-end luthiers produce all-carbon-fiber guitars.

=== Assembly ===
{{for|more details on the construction of acoustic guitars|Guitar#Construction}}
The steel-string acoustic guitar evolved from the nylon- or gut-string classical guitar, and because steel strings have higher tension, heavier construction is required overall. One innovation is a metal bar called a [[guitar#Truss rod|truss rod]], which is incorporated into the neck to strengthen it and provide adjustable counter-tension to the stress of the strings. Typically, a steel-string acoustic guitar is built with a larger soundbox than a standard classical guitar. A critical structural and tonal component of an acoustic guitar is the [[Guitar bracing|bracing]], a systems of struts glued to the inside of the back and top. Steel-string guitars use different bracing systems from classical guitars, typically using X-bracing instead of fan bracing. (Another simpler system, called ladder bracing, where the braces are all placed across the width of the instrument, is used on all types of flat-top guitars on the back.) Innovations in bracing design have emerged, notably the A-brace developed by British luthier Roger Bucknall of Fylde Guitars.

Most [[luthier]]s and experienced players agree that a good solid top (as opposed to laminated or [[plywood]]) is the most important factor in the tone of the guitar. Solid backs and sides can also contribute to a pleasant sound, although laminated sides and backs are acceptable alternatives, commonly found in mid-level guitars (in the range of US$300–$1000).

From the 1960s through the 1980s, &quot;by far the most significant developments in the design and construction of acoustic guitars&quot; were made by the [[Ovation Guitar Company]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Denyer 1992&quot;&gt;{{Cite book
 | title = The guitar handbook
 | first = Ralph
 | last = Denyer
 | others = Special contributors [[Isaac&amp;nbsp;Guillory]] and &lt;!-- NOT [[Alastair Crawford]] --&gt;Alastair&amp;nbsp;M.&amp;nbsp;Crawford; [[Robert&amp;nbsp;Fripp]] (foreword)
 | pages = 48
 | chapter=Ovation guitars (Acoustic guitars)
 | isbn = 0-330-32750-X
 | location = London and Sydney
 | publisher = Pan Books
 | edition= Fully revised and updated
 | year = 1992
}}&lt;/ref&gt; It introduced a composite ''roundback'' bowl, which replaced the square back and sides of traditional guitars; because of its engineering design, Ovation guitars could be amplified without producing the obnoxious feedback that had plagued acoustic guitars before. Ovation also pioneered with electronics, such as [[Pickup (music technology)|pickup]] systems and electronic tuners.&lt;ref name=&quot;Denyer 1992&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
* {{cite news|last=Anonymous|date=1 October 2004|first=Music Trades|title=Ovation's encore: How a host of product refinements have rekindled growth at Kaman&amp;nbsp;Music's flagship guitar&amp;nbsp;division|series=The Guitar Market|newspaper=[[The Music Trades]]|accessdate=1 May 2012|url=http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-124136480.html|id=(subscription required)|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Carter|first=Walter|year=1996|title=The history of the Ovation guitar|editor-first=Jon|editor-last=Eiche|publisher=[[Hal&amp;nbsp;Leonard Corporation]]|series=Musical Instruments Series|location=Milwaukee, Wisconsin|isbn=978-0-7935-5876-6|edition=first|pages=1–128|id=HL00330187&lt;!-- Hal Leonard --&gt;|ref=harv}}
* {{Cite news|url=https://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F60D15FA3A580C7B8CDDAB0994DE494D81 &lt;!-- alternate link: http://www.nytimes.com/1996/12/08/nyregion/from-the-ratcheting-of-helicopters-to-a-guitar-s-hum.html?pagewanted=all&amp;src=pm --&gt;|title=From the ratcheting of helicopters to a guitar's hum|first=Valerie|last=Cruice|newspaper=[[The New York Times]]|date=December 8, 1996|ref=harv}}
* {{cite news|date=30–31 May 1999|last= Marks|first=Brenda|title=Connecticut&amp;nbsp;firm makes guitars, helicopter&amp;nbsp;blades from same fiberglass|publisher=Knight Ridder/Tribune Business News|location=New Hartford, Conn.|newspaper=[[Waterbury Republican-American]]|accessdate=24 April 2012|url=http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-54758412.html|url-access=subscription |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Amplification ==
A steel-string guitar can be {{em|amplified}} using any of three techniques:
* a [[microphone]], possibly clipped to the guitar body;
* a detachable [[Pickup (music technology)|pickup]], often straddling the soundhole and using the same magnetic principle as a traditional electric guitar; or
* a [[transducer]] built into the body.

The last type of guitar is commonly called an ''acoustic-electric'' or ''[[electro-acoustic guitar|electro-acoustic]]'' guitar, as it can be played either &quot;[[Acoustic music|unplugged]]&quot; as an acoustic, or plugged in as an electric. The most common type is a [[piezoelectric pickup]], which is composed of a thin sandwich of quartz crystal. When compressed, the crystal produces a small electric current, so when placed under the bridge saddle, the vibrations of the strings through the saddle, and of the body of the instrument, are converted to a weak electrical signal. This signal is often sent to a [[pre-amplifier]], which increases the signal strength and normally incorporates an [[Equalization (audio)|equalizer]]. The output of the preamplifier then goes to a separate amplifier system similar to that for an electric guitar.

Several manufacturers produce specialised [[acoustic guitar amplifier]]s, which are designed to give undistorted and full-range reproduction.

== Music and players ==
Until the 1960s, the predominant forms of music played on the flat-top, steel-string guitar remained relatively stable and included acoustic [[blues]], [[American country music|country]], [[bluegrass music|bluegrass]], [[folk music|folk]], and several genres of [[rock music|rock]]. The concept of playing solo steel-string guitar in a concert setting was introduced in the early 1960s by such performers as [[Davey Graham]] and [[John Fahey (musician)|John Fahey]], who used [[country blues]] [[fingerpicking]] techniques to compose original compositions with structures somewhat like [[European classical music]]. Fahey contemporary [[Robbie Basho]] added elements of [[Indian classical music]] and [[Leo Kottke]] used a Faheyesque approach to make the first solo steel-string guitar &quot;hit&quot; record.{{citation needed|date=April 2017}}

Steel-string guitars are also important in the world of [[flatpicking]], as utilized by such artists as [[Clarence White]], [[Tony Rice]], [[Bryan Sutton]], [[Doc Watson]] and [[David Grier]]. Luthiers have been experimenting with redesigning the acoustic guitar for these players. These flat-top, steel-string guitars are constructed and voiced more for classical-like fingerpicking and less for chordal accompaniment (strumming). Some luthiers have increasingly focused their attention on the needs of fingerstylists and have developed unique guitars for this style of playing.

Many other luthiers attempt to recreate the guitars of the &quot;Golden Era&quot; of [[Martin Guitars|C.F. Martin &amp; Co]]. This was started by Roy Noble, who built the guitar played by Clarence White from 1968 to 1972, and was followed by Bill Collings, Marty Lanham, [[Dana Bourgeois]], Randy Lucas, Lynn Dudenbostel and [[Wayne Henderson (luthier)|Wayne Henderson]], a few of the luthiers building guitars today inspired by vintage Martins, the pre–World War II models in particular. As prices for vintage Martins continue to rise exponentially, upscale guitar enthusiasts have demanded faithful recreations and luthiers are working to fill that demand.

== See also ==
* [[Guitar]]
* [[List of guitar manufacturers]]
* [[Charlie Nothing#Dingulator|Dingulator]]
* [[Strumming]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}

{{Guitars|Type}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Steel-String Acoustic Guitar}}
[[Category:Acoustic guitars]]
[[Category:American musical instruments]]
[[Category:Rhythm section]]</text>
      <sha1>3mr7zvm3c4it6bfqcko1qqld6syw1z4</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
