  <page>
    <title>Amorphous solid</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2889</id>
    <revision>
      <id>931455077</id>
      <parentid>931029397</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-12-19T00:29:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ionmars10</username>
        <id>37005538</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 927349911 by [[Special:Contributions/2600:8800:3000:83E9:21CC:C684:660B:CF28|2600:8800:3000:83E9:21CC:C684:660B:CF28]] ([[User talk:2600:8800:3000:83E9:21CC:C684:660B:CF28|talk]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{redirect|Amorphous|amorphousness in computational systems|amorphous computing|amorphousness in set theory|amorphous set}}
{{Condensed matter physics|expanded=Soft matter}}

In [[condensed matter physics]] and [[materials science]], an '''amorphous''' (from the [[Greek language|Greek]] ''a'', without, ''morphé'', shape, form) or '''non-crystalline solid''' is a [[solid]] that lacks the [[long-range order]] that is characteristic of a [[crystal]]. In some older books, the term has been used synonymously with [[glass]]. Nowadays, &quot;glassy solid&quot; or &quot;amorphous solid&quot; is considered to be the overarching concept, and glass the more special case: Glass is an amorphous solid that exhibits a [[glass transition]].&lt;ref&gt;J. Zarzycki: Les verres et l'état vitreux. Paris: Masson 1982. English translation available.&lt;/ref&gt; Polymers are often amorphous. Other types of amorphous solids include [[gel]]s, [[thin film]]s, and nanostructured materials such as glass.
[[File:Bulk Metallic Glass Sample.jpg|thumb|[[Amorphous metal]]s have low [[toughness]], but high strength]]

Amorphous materials have an internal structure made of interconnected structural blocks. These blocks can be similar to the basic structural units found in the corresponding crystalline phase of the same compound.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|first1 = Juraj|last1 = Mavračić|first2 = Felix C.|last2 = Mocanu|first3 = Volker L.|last3 = Deringer|first4 = Gábor|last4 = Csányi|first5 = Stephen R.|last5 = Elliott|title = Similarity Between Amorphous and Crystalline Phases: The Case of TiO₂|journal = [[J. Phys. Chem. Lett.]]|volume = 9|issue = 11|pages = 2985–2990|year = 2018|doi = 10.1021/acs.jpclett.8b01067|pmid = 29763315|url = https://www.repository.cam.ac.uk/handle/1810/283145}}&lt;/ref&gt; Whether a material is [[liquid]] or solid depends primarily on the connectivity between its elementary building blocks so that solids are characterized by a high degree of connectivity whereas structural blocks in fluids have lower connectivity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|first1 = Michael I.|last1 = Ojovan|first2 = William E.|last2 = Lee|title = Connectivity and glass transition in disordered oxide systems|journal = [[J. Non-Cryst. Solids]]|volume = 356|issue = 44–49|pages = 2534–2540|year = 2010|doi = 10.1016/j.jnoncrysol.2010.05.012|bibcode = 2010JNCS..356.2534O }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the pharmaceutical industry, the amorphous drugs were shown to have higher bio-availability than their crystalline counterparts due to the high solubility of amorphous phase. Moreover, certain compounds can undergo precipitation in their amorphous form ''[[In vivo supersaturation|in vivo]]'', and they can decrease each other's bio-availability if administered together.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Hsieh|first=Yi-Ling|last2=Ilevbare|first2=Grace A.|last3=Van Eerdenbrugh|first3=Bernard|last4=Box|first4=Karl J.|last5=Sanchez-Felix|first5=Manuel Vincente|last6=Taylor|first6=Lynne S.|date=2012-05-12|title=pH-Induced Precipitation Behavior of Weakly Basic Compounds: Determination of Extent and Duration of Supersaturation Using Potentiometric Titration and Correlation to Solid State Properties|journal=Pharmaceutical Research|language=en|volume=29|issue=10|pages=2738–2753|doi=10.1007/s11095-012-0759-8|pmid=22580905|issn=0724-8741}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Dengale|first=Swapnil Jayant|last2=Grohganz|first2=Holger|last3=Rades|first3=Thomas|last4=Löbmann|first4=Korbinian|date=May 2016|title=Recent advances in co-amorphous drug formulations|journal=Advanced Drug Delivery Reviews|volume=100|pages=116–125|doi=10.1016/j.addr.2015.12.009|pmid=26805787|issn=0169-409X}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Order and Connectivity.jpg|thumb|States of crystalline and amorphous materials as a function of connectivity]]

==Nano-structured materials==
Even amorphous materials have some shortrange order at the atomic length scale due to the nature of [[chemical bond]]ing (see [[structure of liquids and glasses]] for more information on non-crystalline material structure). Furthermore, in very small [[crystal]]s a large fraction of the [[atom]]s are the crystal; relaxation of the surface and interfacial effects distort the atomic positions, decreasing the structural order. Even the most advanced structural characterization techniques, such as x-ray diffraction and transmission electron microscopy, have difficulty in distinguishing between amorphous and crystalline structures on these length scales.{{citation needed|date=April 2012}}

== Amorphous thin films ==
{{Context|section|date=January 2014}}
Amorphous phases are important constituents of [[thin film]]s, which are solid layers of a few [[nanometre]]s to some tens of [[micrometre]]s thickness deposited upon a substrate. So-called structure zone models were developed to describe the micro structure and ceramics of thin films as a function of the [[homologous temperature]] ''T&lt;sub&gt;h&lt;/sub&gt;'' that is the ratio of deposition temperature over melting temperature.&lt;ref name=MoDe1969&gt;{{cite journal|first1 = B. A.|last1 = Movchan|first2 = A. V.|last2 = Demchishin|title= Study of the structure and properties of thick vacuum condensates of nickel, titanium, tungsten, aluminium oxide and zirconium dioxide|journal = [[Phys. Met. Metallogr.]]|volume = 28|pages = 83–90|year = 1969}}&lt;br /&gt;Russian-language version: ''Fiz. Metal Metalloved'' (1969) '''28''': 653-660.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Thor1974&gt;{{cite journal|first = John A.|last = Thornton|title = Influence of apparatus geometry and deposition conditions on the structure and topography of thick sputtered coatings|journal = [[J. Vac. Sci. Technol.]]|volume = 11|issue = 4|pages = 666–670|year = 1974|doi = 10.1116/1.1312732|bibcode = 1974JVST...11..666T}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to these models, a necessary (but not sufficient) condition for the occurrence of amorphous phases is that ''T&lt;sub&gt;h&lt;/sub&gt;'' has to be smaller than 0.3, that is the deposition temperature must be below 30% of the melting temperature. For higher values, the surface diffusion of deposited atomic species would allow for the formation of crystallites with long range atomic order.

Regarding their applications, amorphous metallic layers played an important role in the discussion of a suspected [[superconductivity]] in [[amorphous metal]]s.&lt;ref name=Buck1961&gt;{{cite conference|last=Buckel|first=W.|title=The influence of crystal bonds on film growth|booktitle=Elektrische en Magnetische Eigenschappen van dunne Metallaagies|place=Leuven, Belgium|date=1961}}&lt;/ref&gt; Today, [[optical coating]]s made from [[Titanium dioxide|TiO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;]], [[Silicon dioxide|SiO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;]], [[Tantalum pentoxide|Ta&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt;]] etc. and combinations of them in most cases consist of amorphous phases of these compounds. Much research is carried out into thin amorphous films as a gas separating [[Biological membrane|membrane]] layer.&lt;ref name=Vos1998&gt;{{cite journal|first1 = Renate M.|last1 = de Vos|first2 = Henk|last2 = Verweij|title = High-Selectivity, High-Flux Silica Membranes for Gas Separation|journal = [[Science (journal)|Science]]|volume = 279|issue = 5357|pages = 1710–1711|year = 1998|pmid = 9497287|doi = 10.1126/science.279.5357.1710|bibcode = 1998Sci...279.1710D}}&lt;/ref&gt; The technologically most important thin amorphous film is probably represented by few nm thin SiO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; layers serving as isolator above the conducting channel of a metal-oxide semiconductor field-effect transistor ([[MOSFET]]). Also, hydrogenated [[amorphous silicon]], a-Si:H in short, is of technical significance for [[thin-film solar cells]]. In case of a-Si:H the missing long-range order between silicon atoms is partly induced by the presence by hydrogen in the percent range.

The occurrence of amorphous phases turned out as a phenomenon of particular interest for studying thin-film growth.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title = Electronic structure and chemical bonding of amorphous chromium carbide thin films|first1 = Martin|last1 = Magnuson|first2 = Matilda|last2 = Andersson|first3 = Jun|last3 = Lu|first4 = Lars|last4 = Hultman|first5 = Ulf|last5 = Jansson|year = 2012|journal = [[J. Phys. Condens. Matter]]|volume = 24|issue = 22|page = 225004|doi = 10.1088/0953-8984/24/22/225004|pmid = 22553115|arxiv = 1205.0678 |bibcode = 2012JPCM...24v5004M }}&lt;/ref&gt; Remarkably, the growth of polycrystalline films is often used and preceded by an initial amorphous layer, the thickness of which may amount to only a few nm. The most investigated example is represented by thin multicrystalline silicon films, where such as the unoriented molecule. An initial amorphous layer was observed in many studies.&lt;ref name=Birk2001&gt;{{cite journal|first1 = M.|last1 = Birkholz|first2 = B.|last2 = Selle|first3 = W.|last3 = Fuhs|first4 = S.|last4 = Christiansen|first5 = H. P.|last5 = Strunk|first6 = R.|last6 = Reich|title = Amorphous-crystalline phase transition during the growth of thin films: The case of microcrystalline silicon|journal = [[Phys. Rev. B]]|volume = 64|issue = 8|pages = 085402|year = 2001|doi = 10.1103/PhysRevB.64.085402|bibcode = 2001PhRvB..64h5402B|url = http://www.mariobirkholz.de/PRB2001.pdf|url-status = live|archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20100331052038/http://www.mariobirkholz.de/PRB2001.pdf|archivedate = 2010-03-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; Wedge-shaped polycrystals were identified by [[transmission electron microscopy]] to grow out of the amorphous phase only after the latter has exceeded a certain thickness, the precise value of which depends on deposition temperature, background pressure and various other process parameters. The phenomenon has been interpreted in the framework of [[Polymorphism (materials science)#Ostwald's rule|Ostwald's rule]] of stages&lt;ref name=Ostw1897&gt;{{cite journal|first = Wilhelm|last = Ostwald|authorlink = Wilhelm Ostwald|title = Studien über die Bildung und Umwandlung fester Körper|language = German|journal = [[Z. Phys. Chem.]]|volume = 22|pages = 289–330|year = 1897|doi = 10.1515/zpch-1897-2233|url = https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Wilhelm_Ostwald_-_Studien_%C3%BCber_die_Bildung_und_Umwandlung_fester_K%C3%B6rper.pdf|url-status = live|archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20170308043723/https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Wilhelm_Ostwald_-_Studien_%C3%BCber_die_Bildung_und_Umwandlung_fester_K%C3%B6rper.pdf|archivedate = 2017-03-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; that predicts the formation of phases to proceed with increasing condensation time towards increasing stability.&lt;ref name=&quot;Buck1961&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Birk2001&quot;/&gt; Experimental studies of the phenomenon require a clearly defined state of the substrate surface and its contaminant density etc., upon which the thin film is deposited.

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Further reading==
*{{cite book
 |author=R. Zallen
 |title=The Physics of Amorphous Solids
 |publisher=[[Wiley Interscience]]
 |date=1969
}}
*{{cite book
 |author=S.R. Elliot
 |title=The Physics of Amorphous Materials
 |edition=2nd
 |publisher=[[Longman]]
 |date=1990
}}
*{{cite book
 |author=N. Cusack
 |title=The Physics of Structurally Disordered Matter: An Introduction
 |publisher=IOP Publishing
 |date=1969
}}
*{{cite book
 |editor=N.H. March
 |editor2=R.A. Street
 |editor3=M.P. Tosi
 |title=Amorphous Solids and the Liquid State
 |publisher=Springer
 |date=1969
}}
*{{cite book
 |editor=D.A. Adler
 |editor2=B.B. Schwartz
 |editor3=M.C. Steele
 |title=Physical Properties of Amorphous Materials
 |publisher=Springer
 |date=1969
}}
*{{cite book
 |editor=A. Inoue
 |editor2=K. Hasimoto
 |title=Amorphous and Nanocrystalline Materials
 |publisher=Springer
 |date=1969
}}

==External links==
* [http://www.elsevier.com/locate/jnoncrysol Journal of non-crystalline solids] (Elsevier)

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Amorphous Solid}}
[[Category:Phases of matter]]
[[Category:Amorphous solids| ]]
[[Category:Unsolved problems in physics]]</text>
      <sha1>4ku9w59htu87x1wlgmarl52b83bo8r2</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
