  <page>
    <title>Active Directory</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2807</id>
    <revision>
      <id>939119700</id>
      <parentid>939117175</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-04T13:45:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>37.139.156.40</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 939117175: remove garbage</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Directory service created by Microsoft for Windows domain networks}}
'''Active Directory''' ('''AD''') is a [[directory service]] developed by [[Microsoft]] for [[Windows domain]] networks. It is included in most [[Windows Server]] [[operating system]]s as a set of [[Process (computing)|processes]] and [[Windows service|services]].{{r|DSA-MSDN|WI4}} Initially, Active Directory was only in charge of centralized domain management. Starting with [[Windows Server 2008]], however, Active Directory became an umbrella title for a broad range of directory-based identity-related services.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt;

A server running Active Directory Domain Service (AD DS) is called a [[domain controller]]. It [[authentication|authenticates]] and [[authorization|authorizes]] all users and computers in a [[Microsoft Windows|Windows]] domain type network—assigning and enforcing security policies for all computers and installing or updating software. For example, when a user [[login|logs into]] a computer that is part of a Windows domain, Active Directory checks the submitted password and determines whether the user is a [[system administrator]] or normal user.&lt;ref name=&quot;adw2k3&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc780036(WS.10).aspx#w2k3tr_ad_over_qbjd|title=Active Directory on a Windows Server 2003 Network|date=13 March 2003|work=Active Directory Collection|publisher=[[Microsoft]]|accessdate=25 December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Also, it allows management and storage of information, provides authentication and authorization mechanisms, and establishes a framework to deploy other related services: Certificate Services, [[Active Directory Federation Services]], Lightweight Directory Services, and [[Active Directory Rights Management Services|Rights Management Services]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://support.rackspace.com/how-to/installing-active-directory-on-windows-server-2012/|title=Install Active Directory Domain Services on Windows Server 2008 R2 Enterprise 64-bit.|last=|first=|date=2016-04-27|website=|publisher=|access-date=2016-09-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Active Directory uses [[Lightweight Directory Access Protocol]] (LDAP) versions 2 and 3, Microsoft's version of [[Kerberos (protocol)|Kerberos]], and [[Domain Name System|DNS]].{{TOC limit}}

==History==
Active Directory, like many information-technology efforts, originated out of a [[Democratization#Design,_products_and_services|democratization of design]] using [[Request for Comments]] or RFCs. The [[Internet Engineering Task Force]] (IETF), which oversees the RFC process, has accepted numerous RFCs initiated by widespread participants. Active Directory incorporates decades of communication technologies into the overarching Active Directory concept then makes improvements upon them.{{Citation needed|date=April 2014}} For example, LDAP underpins Active Directory. Also [[X.500]] directories and the [[Organizational Unit]] preceded the Active Directory concept that makes use of those methods. The LDAP concept began to emerge even before the founding of Microsoft in April 1975, with RFCs as early as 1971. RFCs contributing to LDAP include RFC 1823 (on the LDAP API, August 1995),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc1823.txt|title=The LDAP Application Program Interface|accessdate=2013-11-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;RFC 2307, RFC 3062, and RFC 4533.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2307.txt|title      =An Approach for Using LDAP as a Network Information Service|accessdate=2013-11-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc3062.txt|title=LDAP Password Modify Extended Operation|accessdate=2013-11-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc4533.txt|title=The Lightweight Directory Access Protocol (LDAP) Content Synchronization Operation|accessdate= 2013-11-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Microsoft previewed Active Directory in 1999, released it first with [[Windows 2000]] Server edition, and revised it to extend functionality and improve administration in [[Windows Server 2003]]. Additional improvements came with subsequent versions of [[Windows Server]]. In [[Windows Server 2008]], additional services were added to Active Directory, such as [[Active Directory Federation Services]].&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://www.computerperformance.co.uk/Longhorn/longhorn_new_features.htm|title = Windows Server 2008 - New Features|date = |accessdate = |website = ComputerPerformance.co.uk|publisher = Computer Performance Ltd|last = Thomas|first = Guy}}&lt;/ref&gt; The part of the directory in charge of management of domains, which was previously a core part of the operating system,&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt; was renamed Active Directory Domain Services (ADDS) and became a server role like others.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url = https://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/magazine/2006.11.futureofwindows.aspx|title = The Future Of Windows: Directory Services in Windows Server &quot;Longhorn&quot;|date = November 2006|accessdate = |website = [[TechNet Magazine]]|publisher = [[Microsoft]]|last = Hynes|first = Byron}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;Active Directory&quot; became the umbrella title of a broader range of directory-based services.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = https://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/dn268294.aspx|title = What's New in Active Directory in Windows Server|date = |accessdate = |website = Windows Server 2012 R2 and Windows Server 2012 Tech Center|publisher = [[Microsoft]]|last = |first = }}&lt;/ref&gt; According to Bryon Hynes, everything related to identity was brought under Active Directory's banner.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt;

==Active Directory Services==
Active Directory Services consist of multiple directory services. The best known is Active Directory Domain Services, commonly [[abbreviation|abbreviated]] as AD DS or simply AD.&lt;ref&gt;[https://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/dd578336%28v=ws.10%29.aspx Active Directory Services technet.microsoft.com]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Domain Services===
Active Directory Domain Services (AD DS) is the cornerstone of every [[Windows domain]] network. It stores information about members of the domain, including devices and users, [[authentication|verifies their credentials]] and [[authorization|defines their access rights]]. The server running this service is called a [[domain controller]]. A domain controller is contacted when a user logs into a device, accesses another device across the network, or runs a line-of-business [[Metro-style app]] [[sideloading|sideloaded]] into a device.

Other Active Directory services (excluding [[#ADAM|LDS]], as described below) as well as most of Microsoft server technologies rely on or use Domain Services; examples include [[Group Policy]], [[Encrypting File System]], [[BitLocker]], [[Domain Name Services]], [[Remote Desktop Services]], [[Exchange Server]] and [[SharePoint Server]].

==={{anchor|ADAM}} Lightweight Directory Services===
Active Directory Lightweight Directory Services (''AD LDS''), formerly known as ''Active Directory Application Mode'' (ADAM),&lt;ref name=&quot;Active Directory Lightweight Directory Services&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url=http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/aa705886(VS.85).aspx | title=AD LDS | accessdate=28 April 2009 | publisher=Microsoft }}&lt;/ref&gt; is a light-weight implementation of AD DS.&lt;ref name=&quot;Active Directory Lightweight Directory Services versus AD DS&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url=https://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc755080(v=ws.10).aspx | title=AD LDS versus AD DS | accessdate=25 February 2013 | publisher=Microsoft }}&lt;/ref&gt; AD LDS runs as a [[Windows service|service]] on [[Windows Server]]. AD LDS shares the code base with AD DS and provides the same functionality, including an identical [[API]], but does not require the creation of domains or domain controllers. It provides a ''Data Store'' for storage of directory data and a ''[[Directory (database)|Directory Service]]'' with an LDAP ''Directory Service Interface''. Unlike AD DS, however, multiple AD LDS instances can run on the same server.

===Certificate Services===
Active Directory Certificate Services (AD CS) establishes an on-premises [[public key infrastructure]]. It can create, validate and revoke [[public key certificate]]s for internal uses of an organization. These certificates can be used to encrypt files (when used with [[Encrypting File System]]), emails (per [[S/MIME]] standard), and network traffic (when used by [[virtual private network]]s, [[Transport Layer Security]] protocol or [[IPSec]] protocol).

AD CS predates Windows Server 2008, but its name was simply Certificate Services.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Zacker|first1=Craig|editor1-last=Harding|editor1-first=Kathy|editor2-last=Jean|editor2-first=Trenary|editor3-last=Linda|editor3-first=Zacker|title=Planning and Maintaining a Microsoft Windows server 2003 Network Infrastructure|date=2003|publisher=Microsoft Press|location=Redmond, WA|isbn=0-7356-1893-3|pages=[https://archive.org/details/mcsaselfpacedtra00micr/page/11 11–16&lt;!--This is a single page's number!--&gt;]|chapter=11: Creating and Managing Digital Certificates|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/mcsaselfpacedtra00micr/page/11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

AD CS requires an AD DS infrastructure.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Active Directory Certificate Services Overview|url=https://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc731564%28v=ws.10%29.aspx|website=[[Microsoft TechNet]]|publisher=[[Microsoft]]|accessdate=24 November 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Federation Services===
{{Main article|Active Directory Federation Services}}
Active Directory Federation Services (AD FS) is a [[single sign-on]] service. With an AD FS infrastructure in place, users may use several web-based services (e.g. [[internet forum]], [[blog]], [[online shopping]], [[webmail]]) or network resources using only one set of credentials stored at a central location, as opposed to having to be granted a dedicated set of credentials for each service. AD FS's purpose is an extension of that of AD DS: The latter enables users to authenticate with and use the devices that are part of the same network, using one set of credentials. The former enables them to use the same set of credentials in a different network.

As the name suggests, AD FS works based on the concept of [[federated identity]].

AD FS requires an AD DS infrastructure, although its federation partner may not.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Step 1: Preinstallation Tasks|url=https://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc771806%28v=ws.10%29.aspx|website=[[Microsoft TechNet|TechNet]]|publisher=[[Microsoft]]|accessdate=24 November 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Rights Management Services===
{{Main article|Active Directory Rights Management Services}}
'''Active Directory Rights Management Services''' ('''AD RMS''', known as '''Rights Management Services''' or '''RMS''' before [[Windows Server 2008]]) is a server software for [[information rights management]] shipped with [[Windows Server]]. It uses encryption and a form of selective functionality denial for limiting access to documents such as corporate [[e-mail]]s, [[Microsoft Word]] documents, and [[web page]]s, and the operations authorized users can perform on them.

==Logical structure==
As a directory service, an Active Directory instance consists of a database and corresponding [[executable code]] responsible for servicing requests and maintaining the database. The executable part, known as Directory System Agent, is a collection of [[Windows service]]s and [[process (computing)|processes]] that run on Windows 2000 and later.&lt;ref name=DSA-MSDN&gt;{{cite web|title=Directory System Agent|url=http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ms675902%28v=vs.85%29.aspx|work=[[MSDN#Library|MSDN Library]]|publisher=[[Microsoft]]|accessdate=23 April 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Objects in Active Directory databases can be accessed via LDAP, ADSI (a [[component object model]] interface), [[messaging API]] and [[Security Accounts Manager]] services.&lt;ref name=WI4&gt;{{cite book |title=Microsoft Windows Internals: Microsoft Windows Server 2003, Windows XP, and Windows 2000 |last=Solomon |first=David A. |last2=Russinovich |first2=Mark |authorlink2=Mark Russinovich |date=2005 |publisher=[[Microsoft Press]] |location=Redmond, Washington |isbn=0-7356-1917-4 |page=[https://archive.org/details/isbn_9780735619173/page/840 840] |edition=4th |authorlink=David A. Solomon |chapter=Chapter 13 |url-access=registration |url=https://archive.org/details/isbn_9780735619173/page/840 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Objects===
[[File:Publishing Company Network Diagram.png|thumb|A simplified example of a publishing company's internal network.  The company has four groups with varying permissions to the three shared folders on the network.]]Active Directory structures are arrangements of information about [[Object (computing)|objects]]. The objects fall into two broad categories: resources (e.g., printers) and [[security principal]]s (user or computer accounts and groups). Security principals are assigned unique [[security identifier]]s (SIDs).

Each object represents a single entity—whether a user, a computer, a printer, or a group—and its attributes. Certain objects can contain other objects. An object is uniquely identified by its name and has a set of attributes—the characteristics and information that the object represents— defined by a [[database schema|schema]], which also determines the kinds of objects that can be stored in Active Directory.

The [[schema object]] lets administrators extend or modify the schema when necessary. However, because each schema object is integral to the definition of Active Directory objects, deactivating or changing these objects can fundamentally change or disrupt a deployment. Schema changes automatically propagate throughout the system. Once created, an object can only be deactivated—not deleted. Changing the schema usually requires planning.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Windows Server 2003: Active Directory Infrastructure|year=2003|publisher=Microsoft Press|pages=1–8–1–9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Forests, trees and domains===
The Active Directory framework that holds the objects can be viewed at a number of levels. The forest, tree, and domain are the logical divisions in an Active Directory network.

Within a deployment, objects are grouped into domains. The objects for a single domain are stored in a single database (which can be replicated). Domains are identified by their [[Domain Name System|DNS]] name structure, the [[namespace]].

A domain is defined as a logical group of network objects (computers, users, devices) that share the same Active Directory database.

A tree is a collection of one or more domains and domain trees in a contiguous namespace, and is linked in a transitive trust hierarchy.

At the top of the structure is the ''forest.'' A forest is a collection of trees that share a common global catalog, directory schema, logical structure, and directory configuration. The forest represents the security boundary within which users, computers, groups, and other objects are accessible.

{| style=&quot;width:300px; float:right; border:1px solid #ccc; background:#f9f9f9; font-size:88%; line-height:1.5em; margin:5px;&quot;
|-
|| &lt;!-- Table within a table, starts on next line --&gt;
{|  style=&quot;margin:auto; border:1px solid darkgrey;&quot;
|-

|-
| &amp;nbsp; || &amp;nbsp; || [[File:Icons-mini-page url.gif]] ||| Domain-Boston
|-
| &amp;nbsp; || &amp;nbsp; || [[File:Icons-mini-page url.gif]] ||| Domain-New&amp;nbsp;York
|-
| &amp;nbsp; || &amp;nbsp; || [[File:Icons-mini-page url.gif]] ||| Domain-Philly
|-
| &amp;nbsp; || [[File:Icons-mini-page tree.gif]] || colspan=&quot;2&quot; | Tree-Southern
|-
| &amp;nbsp; || &amp;nbsp; || [[File:Icons-mini-page url.gif]] ||| Domain-Atlanta
|-
| &amp;nbsp; || &amp;nbsp; || [[File:Icons-mini-page url.gif]] ||| Domain-Dallas
|}
|| &lt;!-- Table within a table, starts on next line --&gt;
{|  style=&quot;margin:auto; border:1px solid darkgrey;&quot;
|-
|[[File:Icons-mini-page url.gif]]
| colspan=&quot;3&quot; | Domain-Dallas
|-
| &amp;nbsp; || [[File:Icons-mini-folder.gif]] || colspan=&quot;2&quot; | OU-Marketing
|-
| &amp;nbsp; || &amp;nbsp; || [[File:Icons-mini-icon user.gif]] || Hewitt
|-
| &amp;nbsp; || &amp;nbsp; || [[File:Icons-mini-icon user.gif]] || Aon
|-
| &amp;nbsp; || &amp;nbsp; || [[File:Icons-mini-icon user.gif]] ||  Steve
|-
| &amp;nbsp; || [[File:Icons-mini-folder.gif]] || colspan=&quot;2&quot; | OU-Sales
|-
| &amp;nbsp; || &amp;nbsp; || [[File:Icons-mini-icon user.gif]] || Bill
|-
| &amp;nbsp; || &amp;nbsp; || [[File:Icons-mini-icon user.gif]] || Ralph
|}
|-
| colspan=&quot;2&quot;| Example of the geographical organizing of zones of interest within trees and domains.
|}

====Organizational units====
The objects held within a domain can be grouped into [[organizational unit]]s (OUs).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | title = Organizational Units | url = https://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc978003.aspx | work = Distributed Systems Resource Kit ([[Microsoft TechNet|TechNet]]) | publisher = Microsoft | quote = An organizational unit in '''Active Directory''' is analogous to a directory in the file system | year = 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; OUs can provide hierarchy to a domain, ease its administration, and can resemble the organization's structure in managerial or geographical terms. OUs can contain other OUs—domains are containers in this sense. Microsoft recommends using OUs rather than domains for structure and to simplify the implementation of policies and administration. The OU is the recommended level at which to apply [[group policies]], which are Active Directory objects formally named group policy objects (GPOs), although policies can also be applied to domains or sites (see below). The OU is the level at which administrative powers are commonly delegated, but delegation can be performed on individual objects or attributes as well.

Organizational units do not each have a separate namespace. As a consequence, for compatibility with Legacy NetBios implementations, user accounts with an identical sAMAccountName are not allowed within the same domain even if the accounts objects are in separate OUs. This is because sAMAccountName, a user object attribute, must be unique within the domain.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
        | title      = sAMAccountName is always unique in a Windows domain… or is it?
        | url        = http://blog.joeware.net/2012/01/04/2357/
        | publisher  = Joeware
        | date       = 4 January 2012
        | accessdate = 18 September 2013
        | quote       = examples of how multiple AD objects can be created with the same sAMAccountName}}
&lt;/ref&gt;. However, two users in different OUs can have the same common name (CN), the name under which they are stored in the directory itself such as &quot;fred.staff-ou.domain&quot; and &quot;fred.student-ou.domain&quot;, where &quot;staff-ou&quot; and &quot;student-ou&quot; are the OUs.

In general the reason for this lack of allowance for duplicate names through hierarchical directory placement, is that Microsoft primarily relies on the principles of [[NetBIOS]], which is a flat-namespace method of network object management that for Microsoft software, goes all the way back to [[Windows NT 3.1]] and [[MS-DOS]] [[LAN Manager]]. Allowing for duplication of object names in the directory, or completely removing the use of NetBIOS names, would prevent backward compatibility with legacy software and equipment. However, disallowing duplicate object names in this way is a violation of the LDAP RFCs on which Active Directory is supposedly based.

As the number of users in a domain increases, conventions such as &quot;first initial, middle initial, last name&quot; ([[Name order|Western order]]) or the reverse (Eastern order) fail for common [[family names]] like ''Li'' (李), ''Smith'' or ''Garcia''. Workarounds include adding a digit to the end of the username. Alternatives include creating a separate ID system of unique employee/student id numbers to use as account names in place of actual user's names, and allowing users to nominate their preferred word sequence within an [[acceptable use policy]].

Because duplicate usernames cannot exist within a domain, account name generation poses a significant challenge for large organizations that cannot be easily subdivided into separate domains, such as students in a public school system or university who must be able to use any computer across the network.

=====Shadow groups=====
[[File:Active directory - OUs can not be given rights to objects.png|thumb|In Active Directory, organizational units (OUs) cannot be assigned as owners or trustees. Only groups are selectable, and members of OUs cannot be collectively assigned rights to directory objects.]]
In Microsoft's Active Directory, OUs do not confer access permissions, and objects placed within OUs are not automatically assigned access privileges based on their containing OU. This is a design limitation specific to Active Directory. Other competing directories such as Novell [[Novell eDirectory|NDS]] are able to assign access privileges through object placement within an OU.

Active Directory requires a separate step for an administrator to assign an object in an OU as a member of a group also within that OU. Relying on OU location alone to determine access permissions is unreliable, because the object may not have been assigned to the group object for that OU.

A common workaround for an Active Directory administrator is to write a custom [[PowerShell]] or [[Visual Basic]] script to automatically create and maintain a ''user group'' for each OU in their directory. The scripts are run periodically to update the group to match the OU's account membership, but are unable to instantly update the security groups anytime the directory changes, as occurs in competing directories where security is directly implemented into the directory itself. Such groups are known as ''shadow groups''. Once created, these shadow groups are selectable in place of the OU in the administrative tools.

Microsoft refers to shadow groups in the Server 2008 Reference documentation, but does not explain how to create them. There are no built-in server methods or console snap-ins for managing shadow groups.&lt;ref&gt;Microsoft Server 2008 Reference, discussing shadow groups used for fine-grained password policies: https://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc770394%28WS.10%29.aspx&lt;/ref&gt;

The division of an organization's information infrastructure into a hierarchy of one or more domains and top-level OUs is a key decision. Common models are by business unit, by geographical location, by IT Service, or by object type and hybrids of these. OUs should be structured primarily to facilitate administrative delegation, and secondarily, to facilitate group policy application. Although OUs form an administrative boundary, the only true security boundary is the forest itself and an administrator of any domain in the forest must be trusted across all domains in the forest.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | title = Specifying Security and Administrative Boundaries | url = https://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc755979(WS.10).aspx | publisher = Microsoft Corporation | quote = However, service administrators have abilities that cross domain boundaries. For this reason, the forest is the ultimate security boundary, not the domain. | date = 23 January 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Partitions===
The Active Directory database is organized in ''partitions'', each holding specific object types and following a specific replication pattern. Microsoft often refers to these partitions as 'naming contexts'.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
        | title      = Active Directory Replication Traffic
        | url        = https://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/bb742457.aspx
        | publisher  = Microsoft Corporation
        | author     = Andreas Luther
        | quote      = The Active Directory is made up of one or more naming contexts or partitions.
        | accessdate =26 May 2010    }}&lt;/ref&gt; The 'Schema' partition contains the definition of object classes and attributes within the Forest. The 'Configuration' partition contains information on the physical structure and configuration of the forest (such as the site topology). Both replicate to all domains in the Forest.  The 'Domain' partition holds all objects created in that domain and replicates only within its domain.

==Physical structure==
''Sites'' are physical (rather than logical) groupings defined by one or more [[Internet Protocol|IP]] subnets.&lt;ref&gt;
   {{cite web
        | title     = Sites overview
        | url       = https://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc782048(WS.10).aspx
        | publisher = Microsoft Corporation
        | quote     = A site is a set of well-connected subnets.
        | date      = 21 January 2005
    }}
&lt;/ref&gt; AD also holds the definitions of connections, distinguishing low-speed (e.g., [[Wide area network|WAN]], [[Virtual private network|VPN]]) from high-speed (e.g., [[local area network|LAN]]) links. Site definitions are independent of the domain and OU structure and are common across the forest. Sites are used to control network traffic generated by replication and also to refer clients to the nearest [[domain controller]]s (DCs). [[Microsoft Exchange Server|Microsoft Exchange Server 2007]] uses the site topology for mail routing. Policies can also be defined at the site level.

Physically, the Active Directory information is held on one or more peer [[domain controller]]s, replacing the [[Windows NT|NT]] [[Primary Domain Controller|PDC]]/[[Backup Domain Controller|BDC]] model. Each DC has a copy of the Active Directory. Servers joined to Active Directory that are not domain controllers are called Member Servers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
        | title     = Planning for domain controllers and member servers
        | url       = https://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc737059(WS.10).aspx
        | publisher = Microsoft Corporation
        | quote     = [...] member servers, [...] belong to a domain but do not contain a copy of the Active Directory data.
        | date      = 21 January 2005
    }}
&lt;/ref&gt; A subset of objects in the domain partition replicate to domain controllers that are configured as global catalogs. Global catalog (GC) servers provide a global listing of all objects in the Forest.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
        | title     = What Is the Global Catalog?
        | url       = https://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc728188(WS.10).aspx
        | publisher = Microsoft Corporation
        | date      = 10 December 2009
        | quote     = [...] a domain controller can locate only the objects in its domain. [...] The global catalog provides the ability to locate objects from any domain [...]    }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
        | title     = Global Catalog
        | url       = https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ms676908%28v=vs.85%29.aspx
        | publisher = Microsoft Corporation
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Global Catalog servers replicate to themselves all objects from all domains and hence, provide a global listing of objects in the forest. However, to minimize replication traffic and keep the GC's database small, only selected attributes of each object are replicated. This is called the partial attribute set (PAS). The PAS can be modified by modifying the schema and marking attributes for replication to the GC.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
        | title     = Attributes Included in the Global Catalog
        | url       = http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ms675160%28VS.85%29.aspx
        | publisher = Microsoft Corporation
        | date      = 26 August 2010
        | quote     = The isMemberOfPartialAttributeSet attribute of an attributeSchema object is set to TRUE if the attribute is replicated to the global catalog. [...] When deciding whether or not to place an attribute in the global catalog remember that you are trading increased replication and increased disk storage on global catalog servers for, potentially, faster query performance.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Earlier versions of Windows used [[NetBIOS]] to communicate. Active Directory is fully integrated with DNS and requires [[TCP/IP]]—DNS. To be fully functional, the DNS server must support [[SRV record|SRV resource records]], also known as service records.

===Replication===
Active Directory synchronizes changes using ''[[multi-master replication]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web

        | title     = Directory data store
        | url       = https://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc736627(WS.10).aspx
        | publisher = Microsoft Corporation
        | quote     = Active Directory uses four distinct directory partition types to store [...] data. Directory partitions contain domain, configuration, schema, and application data.
        | date      = 21 January 2005    }}&lt;/ref&gt; Replication by default is 'pull' rather than 'push', meaning that replicas pull changes from the server where the change was effected.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
        | title     = What Is the Active Directory Replication Model?
        | url       = https://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc737314(WS.10).aspx
        | publisher = Microsoft Corporation
        | date      = 28 March 2003
        | quote     = Domain controllers request (pull) changes rather than send (push) changes that might not be needed.
    }}
&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Knowledge Consistency Checker'' (KCC) creates a replication topology of ''site links'' using the defined ''sites'' to manage traffic. Intrasite replication is frequent and automatic as a result of change notification, which triggers peers to begin a pull replication cycle. Intersite replication intervals are typically less frequent and do not use change notification by default, although this is configurable and can be made identical to intrasite replication.

Each link can have a 'cost' (e.g., [[Digital Signal 3|DS3]], [[Digital Signal 1|T1]], [[ISDN]] etc.) and the KCC alters the site link topology accordingly. Replication may occur transitively through several site links on same-protocol ''site link bridges'', if the cost is low, although KCC automatically costs a direct site-to-site link lower than transitive connections. Site-to-site replication can be configured to occur between a ''bridgehead server'' in each site, which then replicates the changes to other DCs within the site. Replication for Active Directory zones is automatically configured when DNS is activated in the domain based by site.

Replication of Active Directory uses [[Remote Procedure Call]]s (RPC) over IP (RPC/IP). Between Sites [[SMTP]] can be used for replication, but only for changes in the Schema, Configuration, or Partial Attribute Set (Global Catalog) GCs. SMTP cannot be used for replicating the default Domain partition.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
        | title     = What Is Active Directory Replication Topology?
        | url       = https://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc775549(WS.10).aspx
        | publisher = Microsoft Corporation
        | date      = 28 March 2003
        | quote     = SMTP can be used to transport nondomain replication [...]    }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Implementation==
In general, a network utilizing Active Directory has more than one licensed Windows server computer. Backup and restore of Active Directory is possible for a network with a single domain controller,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/bb727048.aspx |title=Active Directory Backup and Restore |work=[[Microsoft TechNet|TechNet]] |publisher=[[Microsoft]] |accessdate=5 February 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; but Microsoft recommends more than one domain controller to provide automatic [[failover]] protection of the directory.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=AD DS: All domains should have at least two functioning domain controllers for redundancy |work=[[Microsoft TechNet|TechNet]] |url=https://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/dd378865%28v=ws.10%29.aspx |publisher=[[Microsoft]] |accessdate=5 February 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Domain controllers are also ideally single-purpose for directory operations only, and should not run any other software or role.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |quote=Whenever possible, your domain controllers should run on dedicated servers (physical or virtual). |title=10 tips for effective Active Directory design |first=Brien |last=Posey |work=[[TechRepublic]] |publisher=[[CBS Interactive]] |date=23 August 2010 |url=http://www.techrepublic.com/blog/10-things/10-tips-for-effective-active-directory-design |accessdate=5 February 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Certain Microsoft products such as SQL Server&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=You may encounter problems when installing SQL Server on a domain controller (Revision 3.0) |work=Support |publisher=[[Microsoft]] |url=http://support.microsoft.com/kb/2032911 |date=7 January 2013 |accessdate=5 February 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |quote=For security and performance reasons, we recommend that you do not install a standalone SQL Server on a domain controller. |work=Microsoft SQL Server blog |title=Can I install SQL Server on a domain controller? |last=Degremont |first=Michel |url=http://blogs.technet.com/b/mdegre/archive/2011/07/01/can-i-install-sql-server-on-a-domain-controller.aspx |date=30 Jun 2011 |accessdate=5 February 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Exchange&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Installing Exchange on a domain controller is not recommended |work=[[Microsoft TechNet|TechNet]] |publisher=[[Microsoft]] |date=22 March 2013 |url=https://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ms.exch.setupreadiness.warninginstallexchangerolesondomaincontroller%28v=exchg.150%29.aspx |accessdate=5 February 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; can interfere with the operation of a domain controller, necessitating isolation of these products on additional Windows servers. Combining them can make configuration or troubleshooting of either the domain controller or the other installed software more difficult.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |quote=After SQL Server is installed on a computer, you cannot change the computer from a domain controller to a domain member. You must uninstall SQL Server before you change the host computer to a domain member. |work=[[Microsoft TechNet|TechNet]] |title=Security Considerations for a SQL Server Installation |publisher=[[Microsoft]] |url=https://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ms144228.aspx |accessdate=5 February 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; A business intending to implement Active Directory is therefore recommended to purchase a number of Windows server licenses, to provide for at least two separate domain controllers, and optionally, additional domain controllers for performance or redundancy, a separate file server, a separate Exchange server, a separate SQL Server,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |quote=Running SQL Server on the same computer as a production Exchange mailbox server is not recommended. |title=Exchange Server Analyzer |work=[[Microsoft TechNet|TechNet]] |publisher=[[Microsoft]] |url=https://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/aa997379%28v=exchg.80%29.aspx |accessdate=5 February 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; and so forth to support the various server roles.

Physical hardware costs for the many separate servers can be reduced through the use of [[virtualization]], although for proper failover protection, Microsoft recommends not running multiple virtualized domain controllers on the same physical hardware.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |quote=You should attempt to avoid creating potential single points of failure when you plan your virtual domain controller deployment.frank |title=Running Domain Controllers in Hyper-V |work=[[Microsoft TechNet|TechNet]] |publisher=[[Microsoft]] |url=https://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/d2cae85b-41ac-497f-8cd1-5fbaa6740ffe%28v=ws.10%29#bkmk1_planning_to_virtualize_domain_controllers |at=Planning to Virtualize Domain Controllers |accessdate=5 February 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Database==
The Active-Directory [[database]], the ''directory store'', in Windows 2000 Server uses the [[Microsoft JET Blue|JET Blue]]-based [[Extensible Storage Engine]] (ESE98) and is limited to 16 terabytes and 2 billion objects (but only 1 billion security principals) in each domain controller's database. Microsoft has created NTDS databases with more than 2 billion objects.&lt;ref name=&quot;blogs.technet.com&quot;&gt;
{{cite web|author=efleis |url=http://blogs.technet.com/efleis/archive/2006/06/08/434255.aspx |title=Large AD database? Probably not this large |publisher=Blogs.technet.com |date=8 June 2006 |accessdate=20 November 2011}}
&lt;/ref&gt; (NT4's [[Security Account Manager]] could support no more than 40,000 objects). Called NTDS.DIT, it has two main tables: the ''data table'' and the ''link table''.  Windows Server 2003 added a third main table for [[security descriptor]] single instancing.&lt;ref name=&quot;blogs.technet.com&quot;/&gt;

Programs may access the features of Active Directory&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last=Berkouwer | first=Sander| title=Active Directory basics | url=http://www.veeam.com/wp-active-directory-basics.html | publisher=[[Veeam Software]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; via the [[Component Object Model|COM interfaces]] provided by ''Active Directory Service Interfaces''.&lt;ref&gt;
[http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/aa772170%28VS.85%29.aspx Active Directory Service Interfaces], Microsoft&lt;/ref&gt;

==Trusting==
To allow users in one domain to access resources in another, Active Directory uses trusts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
        | title     = Domain and Forest Trusts Technical Reference
        | url       = https://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc738955(WS.10).aspx
        | publisher = Microsoft Corporation
        | date      = 28 March 2003
        | quote     = Trusts enable [...] authentication and [...] sharing resources across domains or forests}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Trusts inside a forest are automatically created when domains are created. The forest sets the default boundaries of trust, and implicit, transitive trust is automatic for all domains within a forest.

===Terminology===
;One-way trust
:One domain allows access to users on another domain, but the other domain does not allow access to users on the first domain.
;Two-way trust
:Two domains allow access to users on both domains.
;Trusted domain
:The domain that is trusted; whose users have access to the trusting domain.
;Transitive trust
:A trust that can extend beyond two domains to other trusted domains in the forest.
;Intransitive trust
:A one way trust that does not extend beyond two domains.
;Explicit trust
:A trust that an admin creates. It is not transitive and is one way only.
;Cross-link trust
:An explicit trust between domains in different trees or in the same tree when a descendant/ancestor (child/parent) relationship does not exist between the two domains.
;Shortcut
:Joins two domains in different trees, transitive, one- or two-way.
;Forest trust
:Applies to the entire forest. Transitive, one- or two-way.
;Realm
:Can be transitive or nontransitive (intransitive), one- or two-way.
;External
:Connect to other forests or non-AD domains. Nontransitive, one- or two-way.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
        | title      =Domain and Forest Trusts Work
        | url        = https://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc773178(WS.10).aspx
        | publisher  = Microsoft Corporation
        | date       = 11 December 2012
        | accessdate = 29 January 2013
        | quote       = Defines several kinds of trusts. (automatic, shortcut, forest, realm, external)}}&lt;/ref&gt;
;PAM trust
:A one-way trust used by [[Microsoft Identity Manager]] from a (possibly low-level) production forest to a ([[Windows Server 2016]] functionality level) 'bastion' forest, which issues time-limited group memberships.&lt;ref&gt;[https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/microsoft-identity-manager/pam/privileged-identity-management-for-active-directory-domain-services Microsoft Identity Manager: Privileged Access Management for Active Directory Domain Services]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://social.technet.microsoft.com/wiki/contents/articles/33363.mim-2016-privileged-access-management-pam-faq.aspx TechNet: MIM 2016: Privileged Access Management (PAM) - FAQ]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Management solutions==
Microsoft Active Directory management tools include:
*Active Directory Administrative Center (Introduced with Windows Server 2012 and above),
*Active Directory Users and Computers, 
*Active Directory Domains and Trusts, 
*Active Directory Sites and Services, 
*ADSI Edit, 
*Local Users and Groups, 
*Active Directory Schema snap-ins for [[Microsoft Management Console]] (MMC),
*[[SysInternals]] ADExplorer

These management tools may not provide enough functionality for efficient workflow in large environments. Some third-party solutions extend the administration and management capabilities. They provide essential features for a more convenient administration processes, such as automation, reports, integration with other services, etc.

==Unix integration==
Varying levels of interoperability with Active Directory can be achieved on most [[Unix-like]] operating systems  (including [[Unix]], [[Linux]], [[Mac OS X]] or Java and Unix-based programs) through standards-compliant LDAP clients, but these systems usually do not interpret many attributes associated with Windows components, such as [[Group Policy]] and support for one-way trusts.

Third parties offer Active Directory integration for Unix-like platforms, including:
* ''PowerBroker Identity Services'', formerly ''Likewise'' ([[BeyondTrust]], formerly Likewise Software) – Allows a non-Windows client to join Active Directory&lt;ref name=&quot;EMAG&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Edge |first=Charles S., Jr |first2=Zack |last2=Smith |first3=Beau |last3=Hunter |title=Enterprise Mac Administrator's Guide |url=https://archive.org/details/enterprisemacadm0000edge |url-access=registration |year=2009 |publisher=[[Apress]] |location=New York City |isbn=978-1-4302-2443-3 |chapter = Chapter 3: Active Directory}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''ADmitMac'' (Thursby Software Systems)&lt;ref name=&quot;EMAG&quot; /&gt;
* ''[[Samba (software)|Samba]]'' – Can act as a domain controller&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.samba.org/samba/history/samba-4.0.0.html|title=Samba 4.0.0 Available for Download |accessdate=9 August 2016|work=SambaPeople|publisher=SAMBA Project| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20101115160233/http://wiki.samba.org/index.php/Samba4/Releases/4.0.0alpha13| archivedate= 15 November 2010 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Samba Plugfest Report&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://people.samba.org/people/2009/10/05#drs-success | title=The great DRS success! | accessdate=2 November 2009 | date=5 October 2009 | work=SambaPeople | publisher=SAMBA Project | archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20091013094528/http://people.samba.org/people/2009/10/05#drs-success | archivedate=13 October 2009 | url-status=dead | df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The schema additions shipped with [[Windows Server 2003 R2]] include attributes that map closely enough to RFC 2307 to be generally usable. The reference implementation of RFC 2307, nss_ldap and pam_ldap provided by PADL.com, support these attributes directly. The default schema for group membership complies with RFC 2307bis (proposed).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.padl.com/~lukeh/rfc2307bis.txt |title=RFC 2307bis |accessdate=20 November 2011 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110927182939/http://www.padl.com/~lukeh/rfc2307bis.txt |archivedate=27 September 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Windows Server 2003 R2 includes a [[Microsoft Management Console]] snap-in that creates and edits the attributes.

An alternative option is to use another directory service as non-Windows clients authenticate to this while Windows Clients authenticate to AD. Non-Windows clients include [[389 Directory Server]] (formerly Fedora Directory Server, FDS), ViewDS Identity Solutions - ViewDS v7.2 [[XML Enabled Directory]]  and Sun Microsystems [[Sun Java System Directory Server]]. The latter two both being able to perform two-way synchronization with AD and thus provide a &quot;deflected&quot; integration.

Another option is to use [[OpenLDAP]] with its ''translucent'' overlay, which can extend entries in any remote LDAP server with additional attributes stored in a local database. Clients pointed at the local database see entries containing both the remote and local attributes, while the remote database remains completely untouched.{{Citation needed|date=March 2011}}

Administration (querying, modifying, and monitoring) of Active Directory can be achieved via many scripting languages, including [[PowerShell]], [[VBScript]], [[JavaScript|JScript/JavaScript]], [[Perl]], [[Python (programming language)|Python]], and [[Ruby (programming language)|Ruby]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Active Directory Administration with Windows PowerShell|url=https://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/dd378937%28WS.10%29.aspx|publisher=Microsoft|accessdate=7 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Using Scripts to Search Active Directory|url=https://technet.microsoft.com/library/ee692830.aspx|publisher=Microsoft|accessdate=22 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=ITAdminTools Perl Scripts Repository|url=http://www.itadmintools.com/2011/09/itadmintools-perl-script-repository.html|publisher=ITAdminTools.com|accessdate=22 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Win32::OLE|url=https://metacpan.org/module/Win32::OLE|publisher=Perl Open-Source Community|accessdate=22 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Free and non-free AD administration tools can help to simplify and possibly automate AD management tasks.

Since October 2017 Amazon [[Amazon Web Services|AWS]] offers integration with Microsoft Active Directory.&lt;ref&gt;https://aws.amazon.com/blogs/security/introducing-aws-directory-service-for-microsoft-active-directory-standard-edition/&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[AGDLP]] (implementing [[role based access control]]s using nested groups)
* [[Flexible single master operation]]
* [[Apple Open Directory]]
* [[FreeIPA]]
* [[List of LDAP software]]
* [[Univention Corporate Server]]

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

==External links==
{{Wikiversity | Active Directory}}
* Microsoft Technet: White paper: [https://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/bb727030.aspx Active Directory Architecture] (Single technical document that gives an overview about Active Directory.)
* Microsoft Technet: Detailed description of [https://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc782657(WS.10).aspx Active Directory on Windows Server 2003]
* Microsoft MSDN Library: [http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc223122.aspx &lt;nowiki&gt;[MS-ADTS]: Active Directory Technical Specification&lt;/nowiki&gt;] (part of the [[Microsoft Open Specification Promise]])
* [https://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc736765%28v=ws.10%29.aspx Active Directory Application Mode (ADAM)]
* Microsoft MSDN: [https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/bb897400.aspx &lt;nowiki&gt;[AD-LDS]: Active Directory Lightweight Directory Services&lt;/nowiki&gt;]
* Microsoft TechNet: [https://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc754361%28v=ws.10%29.aspx &lt;nowiki&gt;[AD-LDS]: Active Directory Lightweight Directory Services&lt;/nowiki&gt;]
* Microsoft MSDN: [http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ms675085(VS.85).aspx Active Directory Schema]
* Microsoft TechNet: [https://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc739086(WS.10).aspx Understanding Schema]
* Microsoft TechNet Magazine: [https://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/magazine/2008.05.schema.aspx?pr=blog Extending the Active Directory Schema]
* Microsoft MSDN: [https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ff630887.aspx Active Directory Certificate Services]
* Microsoft TechNet: [https://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/windowsserver/dd448615.aspx Active Directory Certificate Services]

{{Microsoft products}}
{{Windows Components}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=March 2012}}

[[Category:Active Directory| ]]
[[Category:Directory services]]
[[Category:Microsoft server technology]]
[[Category:Windows components]]
[[Category:Windows 2000]]</text>
      <sha1>psupsg3vno13hc686vsh3di6vuv3jaf</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
