  <page>
    <title>Akihabara</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2802</id>
    <revision>
      <id>939829258</id>
      <parentid>939506625</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-09T00:05:05Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>69.157.92.246</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* External links */ Remove link of a Paid tool.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{redirect-distinguish|Electric Town|Electric City (disambiguation)}}
[[File:Akhibara_Crossing_(39878694470).jpg|thumb|Akihabara Crossing]]
[[File:Akibaneon.JPG|thumb|Akihabara at night]]
[[File:Akiba denkigai.jpg|thumb|Akihabara in 2007]]
[[File:Akihabara_Night.jpg|thumb|Club Sega in Akihabara]]
{{Nihongo|'''Akihabara'''|秋葉原|lead=yes}} is a common name for the area around [[Akihabara Station]] in the [[Chiyoda, Tokyo|Chiyoda ward]] of [[Tokyo]], Japan. Administratively, the area called Akihabara mainly belongs to the {{nihongo|Sotokanda|外神田}} and [[Sakumachō, Tokyo|Kanda-Sakumachō]] districts in Chiyoda. There exists an administrative district called Akihabara in the [[Taitō]] ward further north of Akihabara Station, but it is not the place people generally refer to as Akihabara.

The name Akihabara is a shortening of {{Nihongo|'''Akibagahara'''|秋葉ヶ原}}, which ultimately comes from {{nihongo|'''Akiba'''|秋葉}}, named after a fire-controlling deity of a firefighting shrine built after the area was destroyed by a fire in 1869.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cybriwsky&quot;&gt;Cybriwsky, Roman. ''Historical dictionary of Tokyo.''Scarecrow Press, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

Akihabara gained the nickname {{nihongo|'''Akihabara Electric Town'''|秋葉原電気街|Akihabara Denki Gai}} shortly after World War II for being a major shopping center for household electronic goods and the post-war black market.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nobuoka&quot;&gt;Nobuoka, Jakob. &quot;User innovation and creative consumption in Japanese culture industries: The case of Akihabara, Tokyo.&quot; ''Geografiska Annaler: Series B, Human Geography'' 92.3 (2010): 205–218.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Yamada&quot;&gt;Yamada, Kazuhito. ''Entrepreneurship in Akihabara.''&lt;/ref&gt; 

Akihabara is considered by many to be the centre of modern [[Japanese popular culture]] and a major shopping district for [[video games]], [[anime]], [[manga]], [[electronics]] and [[computer]]-related goods. Icons from popular anime and manga are displayed prominently on the shops in the area, and numerous [[maid café]]s and some arcades are found throughout the district.

==Geography==
The main area of Akihabara is located on a street just west of [[Akihabara Station]], where most of the major shops are situated. Most of the electronics shops are just west of the station, and the anime and manga shops and the [[cosplay restaurant|cosplay café]]s are north of them.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nobuoka&quot;/&gt;

As mentioned above, the area called Akihabara now ranges over some districts in Chiyoda ward: {{Nihongo|Sotokanda|外神田||the west of the station including electric town}}, {{Nihongo|Kanda-Hanaokachō|神田花岡町||the east of the station}}, and {{Nihongo|[[Sakumachō, Tokyo|Kanda-Sakumachō]]|神田佐久間町||the south and southeast of the station}}. There exists an administrative district called Akihabara in the [[Taitō]] ward further north of the station, but it is not the place which people generally refer to as Akihabara. It borders on Sotokanda in between Akihabara and [[Okachimachi Station|Okachimachi]] stations, but is half occupied by [[Japan Railways Group|JR]] tracks.

==History==
The area that is now Akihabara was once near a city gate of [[Edo]] and served as a passage between the city and northwestern Japan. This made the region a home to many craftsmen and tradesmen, as well as some low class [[samurai]]. One of Tokyo's frequent fires destroyed the area in 1869, and the people decided to replace the buildings of the area with a shrine called Chinkasha (now known as {{nihongo|Akiba Shrine|[[:ja:秋葉神社 (台東区)|秋葉神社]]|Akiba Jinja}}), meaning fire extinguisher shrine, in an attempt to prevent the spread of future fires. The locals nicknamed the shrine Akiba after the deity that could control fire, and the area around it became known as Akibagahara and later Akihabara.&lt;ref name= Cybriwsky/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Nobuoka&quot;/&gt; After Akihabara Station was built in 1888, the shrine was moved to the [[Taitō|Taitō ward]] where it still resides today.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Tokyo Akihabara &quot;Must See&quot; Top Five|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/gail-nakada/tokyo-akihabara-must-see-_b_3863989.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=秋葉神社（台東区松が谷）|url=http://jinja.tokyolovers.jp/tokyo/taito/akibajinja}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=秋葉神社の概要|url=http://www.tesshow.jp/taito/shrine_matsu_akiba.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Since its opening in 1890, [[Akihabara Station]] became a major freight transit point, which allowed a vegetable and fruit market to spring up in the district. Then, in the 1920s, the station saw a large volume of passengers after opening for public transport, and after World War II, the black market thrived in the absence of a strong government. This disconnection of Akihabara from government authority has allowed the district to grow as a market city and given rise to an excellent atmosphere for entrepreneurship.&lt;ref name=Yamada/&gt; In the 1930s, this climate turned Akihabara into a future-oriented market region specializing in household [[electronics]], such as washing machines, refrigerators, televisions, and stereos, earning Akihabara the nickname &quot;Electric Town&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nobuoka&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Akihabara: Electric Town For Tech, Games, Anime!|url=http://japanistas.com/en/archives/18410}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As household electronics began to lose their futuristic appeal in the 1980s, the shops of Akihabara shifted their focus to home computers at a time when they were only used by specialists and hobbyists. This new specialization brought in a new type of consumer, computer nerds or ''otaku''.&lt;ref name=Nobuoka/&gt; The market in Akihabara naturally latched onto their new customer base that was focused on [[anime]], [[manga]], and video games. The connection between Akihabara and otaku has survived and grown to the point that the region is now known worldwide as a center for otaku culture, and some otaku even consider Akihabara to be a sacred place.&lt;ref name=&quot;IMAI&quot;&gt;IMAI, Nobuharu. &quot;The Momentary and Placeless Community: Constructing a New Community with regards to Otaku Culture.&quot; ''Inter Faculty 1'' (2010).&lt;/ref&gt;

==''Otaku'' culture==
[[File:Akihabara Maids.JPG|thumb|[[Maid]]s promoting [[maid café]]s near Akihabara Station]]
The influence of ''[[otaku]]'' culture has shaped Akihabara's businesses and buildings to reflect the interests of ''otaku'' and gained the district worldwide fame for its distinctive imagery. Akihabara tries to create an atmosphere as close as possible to the game and anime worlds of customers' interest. The streets of Akihabara are covered with anime and manga icons, and cosplayers line the sidewalks handing out advertisements, especially for [[maid café]]s. The idol group [[AKB48]], one of Japan's highest selling contemporary musical acts, runs its own theater in Akihabara, from which the group's name is derived.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.tsunagujapan.com/a-beginners-guide-to-the-48group-family/|title=A Beginner's Guide to the 48Group Family|website=www.tsunagujapan.com|access-date=2019-02-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Naruto Cosplayers in Akihabara, Tokyo, Japan.jpg|thumbnail|[[Naruto Uzumaki|Naruto]] cosplayer attracting customers for a Manga and Anime shop]]
Release events, special events, and [[Fan convention|conventions]] in Akihabara give anime and manga fans frequent opportunities to meet the creators of the works they follow and strengthen the connection between the region and ''otaku'' culture. The design of many of the buildings serves to create the sort of atmosphere that draws in ''otaku''. Architects design the stores of Akihabara to be more opaque and closed to reflect the general desire of many ''otaku'' to live in their anime worlds rather than display their interests to the world at large.&lt;ref name=Nobuoka/&gt;&lt;ref name=Morikawa&gt;Morikawa, Kaichiro. &quot;Learning from Akihabara: The birth of a personapolis.&quot; ''Gentosha'', Tokyo (2003).&lt;/ref&gt;

Akihabara's role as a free market has also allowed a large amount of amateur work to find a passionate audience in the otaku who frequent the area. ''[[Doujinshi]]'' (amateur or fanmade manga based on an anime/manga/game) has been growing in Akihabara since the 1970s when publishers began to drop manga that were not ready for large markets.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nobuoka&quot;/&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Tokyo}}
*[[Akiba-kei]]
*[[Akihabara Trilogy]]
*[[Kanda Shrine]], Shinto shrine near Akihabara
*[[Nipponbashi]], in Osaka
*[[Ōsu]], in Nagoya
*[[Tourism in Japan]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Akihabara}}
{{Wikivoyage|Tokyo/Akihabara|Akihabara}}
* [http://akihabara-japan.com/ Akihabara Area Tourism Organization]
* [http://www.akiba.or.jp/english/ Akihabara Electrical Town Organization website]
* [http://www.gotokyo.org/en/tourists/areas/areamap/akihabara.html Go Tokyo Akihabara Guide]

{{Coord|35.69836|139.77313|type:city|display=title}}
{{Taitō, Tokyo}}
{{Chiyoda, Tokyo}}
{{Neighborhoods of Tokyo}}
{{Shopping districts and streets in Japan}}

[[Category:Akihabara| ]]
[[Category:Chiyoda, Tokyo]]
[[Category:Electronics districts]]
[[Category:Neighborhoods of Tokyo]]
[[Category:Otaku]]
[[Category:Shopping districts and streets in Japan]]
[[Category:Taitō]]
[[Category:Tourist attractions in Tokyo]]</text>
      <sha1>n21ntmgonqt3nsvk68uzsdebk74o38a</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
