  <page>
    <title>Amanda Hesser</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2868</id>
    <revision>
      <id>927979026</id>
      <parentid>915162984</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-11-26T00:49:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>UnitedStatesian</username>
        <id>3461395</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Removing link(s) to &quot;Lerer Hippeau Ventures&quot;: rm link(s) to deleted article. ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox person
| name          = 
| image         = Amanda Hesser by James Ransom.jpg
| alt           = 
| caption       = Amanda Hesser in the offices of Food52
| birth_name    = 
| birth_date    =  {{birth year and age|1971}}
| birth_place   = 
| death_date    = &lt;!-- {{Death date and age|YYYY|MM|DD|YYYY|MM|DD}} (death date then birth date) --&gt;
| death_place   = 
| nationality   = [[United States|American]]
| other_names   = 
| occupation    = 
| years_active  = 
| known_for     = 
| notable_works = 
}}
'''Amanda Hesser''' (born 1971) is an American food writer, editor, cookbook author and entrepreneur. Most notably, she was the food editor of ''[[The New York Times Magazine]]'', the editor of ''[[T Living]]'', a quarterly publication of ''[[The New York Times]]'', author of The Essential New York Times Cookbook which was a ''[[The New York Times|New York Times]]'' bestseller, and co-founder and CEO of Food52.

After finishing her first book, in 1997, Hesser was hired as a food reporter for ''[[The New York Times]]'' where she wrote more than 750 stories. While at the ''Times'' Hesser wrote about the influence of [[Costco]] on the wine industry, and how the Farmer Consumer Advisory Committee made decisions for the New York City Greenmarket.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Apple Cart Upset: Who Runs Greenmarket?|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2004/01/14/dining/apple-cart-upset-who-runs-greenmarket.html|date=2004-01-14|first=Amanda|last=Hesser|newspaper=New York Times|accessdate=2019-07-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; She was also among the first to write about [[Ferran Adria]] of [[El Bulli]] in a major American publication.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Hesser|first=Amanda|title=In Spain, A Chef To Rival Dali|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1999/09/15/dining/in-spain-a-chef-to-rival-dali.html#|accessdate=November 22, 2011|newspaper=New York Times|date=September 15, 1999}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Hesser was involved in two cases of conflict of interest while working at the ''Times''. In 2004, she awarded the restaurant Spice Market a three-star rating without disclosing that the year before, the restaurant's owner, Jean-Georges Vongerichten, had provided a complimentary jacket blurb for her book ''Cooking for Mr. Latte''. In 2007, Hesser published a favorable review of ''Vegetable Harvest'' by Patricia Wells, without noting that in 1999, Wells had provided a jacket blurb for Hesser's book ''The Cook and the Gardener''. In both cases, the ''Times'' subsequently pointed out the conflicts of interest with editors’ notes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=https://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/books/review/Hesser-t.html?pagewanted=print&amp;_r=0 | work=The New York Times | first=Amanda | last=Hesser | title=Cooking | date=3 June 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=https://www.nytimes.com/2004/03/31/nyregion/editors-note-editors-note-014850.html | work=The New York Times | title=Editors' Note; Editors' Note | date=31 March 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While Hesser left the ''[[The New York Times|Times]]'' in March 2008 to focus on the development of [[Food52]] she continued to write the &quot;Recipe Redux&quot; feature for the ''Times'' magazine until February 27, 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title = Amanda Hesser Blows Her Own Internet Bubble | date = 3 April 2008 | publisher = [[New York (magazine)|New York]] | url = http://nymag.com/daily/food/2008/04/amanda_hesser_out_at_the_times.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title = Amanda Hesser Sets Us Straight About Her Plans for the Future | date = 7 April 2008 | url = http://nymag.com/daily/food/2008/04/amanda_hesser_sets_us_straight.html | publisher = [[New York (magazine)|New York]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As co-founder and CEO of [[Food52]] she has raised two rounds of investment from parties including Lerer Hippeau Ventures and [[Bertelsmann Digital Media Investments]]. [[Food52]] has won numerous notable awards including the [[James Beard Foundation Award|James Beard Award]] for Publication of the Year (2012)&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=James Beard Foundation 2012 Award Winners |url=http://www.jamesbeard.org/awards/search/food52 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160304002548/http://www.jamesbeard.org/awards/search/food52 |archivedate=2016-03-04 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[International Association of Culinary Professionals|IACP Award]] for Best Website (2013). In February 2017, noting that 92 percent of the company was white, she and her co-founder Merrill Stubbs &quot;issued a statement about the ways in which the company intended to redress a lack of racial equality in its workplace.&quot; By the following January, &quot;they published a follow-up letter updating readers on the progress of their efforts, stating that their staff had been reduced to being 76 percent white.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;https://www.cjr.org/special_report/food-writing-race-identity.php/&lt;/ref&gt;

Hesser was featured in ''[[Food &amp; Wine]]'''s ''40 under 40''&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title = 40 Big Food Thinkers 40 and Under | date = November 2010 | url = http://www.foodandwine.com/articles/40-big-food-thinkers-under-40 | publisher = [[Food &amp; Wine]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; list, was named one of the 50 most influential women in food by ''[[Gourmet (magazine)|Gourmet]]'' Magazine, and had a cameo as herself in the film ''[[Julie &amp; Julia]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title = Julie &amp; Julia | url = https://www.imdb.com/title/tt1135503/fullcredits?ref_=tt_cl_sm#cast}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Hesser lives in [[Brooklyn Heights]] with her husband, [[Tad Friend]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS; Amanda Hesser, Tad Friend|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2002/09/15/style/weddings-celebrations-amanda-hesser-tad-friend.html|work=Weddings - NYTimes.com|publisher=The New York Times|accessdate=31 March 2012|date=September 15, 2002|quote=Amanda Hesser, a reporter for The New York Times, and Tad Friend, a staff writer for The New Yorker, were married yesterday in Wainscott, N.Y., at the summer house of the bridegroom's family.}}&lt;/ref&gt; a staff writer for ''[[The New Yorker]]'', and their two children.

==Bibliography==

===Books===
*''The Cook and the Gardener'' (W. W. Norton &amp; Company, 1999)
*''Cooking for Mr. Latte: A Food Lover's Courtship, with Recipes'' (W. W. Norton &amp; Company, 2004) [Collected ''Food Diary'' columns she wrote from 2000-2002]
*''Eat, Memory: Great Writers at the Table, a Collection of Essays from the New York Times'' (W. W. Norton &amp; Company, 2009) [Edited 26 previously published essays]
*''The Essential New York Times Cookbook: Classic Recipes for a New Century'' (W. W. Norton &amp; Company, 2010)
*''The Food52 Cookbook: 140 Winning Recipes from Exceptional Home Cooks'' (William Morrow Cookbooks, 2011)
*''The Food52 Cookbook, Volume 2: Seasonal Recipes from Our Kitchens to Yours'' (William Morrow Cookbooks, 2012)
*''Food52 Genius Recipes: 100 Recipes That Will Change the Way You Cook'' (Ten Speed Press, 2015)
*''Food52 Vegan: 60 Vegetable-Driven Recipes for Any Kitchen'' (Ten Speed Press, 2015)
*''Food52 Baking: 60 Sensational Treats You Can Pull Off in a Snap'' (Ten Speed Press, 2015)
*''Food52 A New Way to Dinner: A Playbook of Recipes and Strategies for the Week Ahead'' (Ten Speed Press, 2016)
*''Food52 Mighty Salads: 60 New Ways to Turn Salad into Dinner'' (Ten Speed Press, 2017)
*''Food52 Ice Cream and Friends: 60 Recipes and Riffs for Sorbets, Sandwiches, No-Churn Ice Creams, and More'' (Ten Speed Press, 2017)
*''Food52 Any Night Grilling: 60 Ways to Fire Up Dinner (and More)'' (Ten Speed Press, 2018)
*''Food52 Genius Desserts: 100 Recipes That Will Change the Way You Bake'' (Ten Speed Press, 2018)

===eBooks===
* &quot;Food 52 Holiday Recipes &amp; Party Planning Guide: A cookbook, instruction manual, and entertaining battle plan&quot; ([[Open Air Publishing]], 2011)

===Anthologized works===
*''Women Who Eat'' (2003)
*''Best Food Writing'' (2002, 2004)
*''The Art of Eating'' (2004)
*''Alone in the Kitchen with an Eggplant'' (2007)

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Hesser, Amanda}}
[[Category:1972 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:American food writers]]
[[Category:Women food writers]]
[[Category:Women cookbook writers]]
[[Category:People from Brooklyn Heights]]
[[Category:American women chief executives]]
[[Category:American company founders]]</text>
      <sha1>1540gg1t255172luk1dyouq2runon8v</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
