  <page>
    <title>Crossbow</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6948</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942176860</id>
      <parentid>940220330</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-23T02:27:07Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ingratis</username>
        <id>35681141</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* Southeast Asia */ paraphrase</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{About|the weapon}}
{{short description|Type of ranged weapon}}
[[File:Armborst, 1500-tal - Livrustkammaren - 106745.tif|thumb|16th-century crossbow with steel prod (Germany)]]
[[File:Crossbow TenPoint Stealth SS.png|thumb|21st-century hunting crossbow]]
A '''crossbow''' is a type of elastic [[ranged weapon]] in similar principle to a [[Bow (archery)|bow]], consisting of a bow-like assembly called a ''prod'', mounted horizontally on a main frame called a ''tiller'', which is handheld in a similar fashion to the [[stock (firearms)|stock]] of a [[long gun]].  It shoots [[arrow]]-like [[projectile]]s called [[crossbow bolt|bolt]]s or quarrels.  The medieval European crossbow was called by many other names including crossbow itself, most of which were derived from the word ''[[ballista]]'', an [[ancient Greek]] torsion [[siege engine]] similar in appearance.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation |last=Payne-Gallwey |first=Ralph |authorlink=Sir Ralph Frankland-Payne-Gallwey, 3rd Baronet |editor= |others= |title=The Crossbow |origyear=1903 |year=2007 |publisher=Skyhorse Publishing Inc. |isbn=978-1-60239-010-2 |page=2 |chapter= |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although having the same launch principle, crossbows differ from bows in that a bow's [[bow draw|draw]] must be maintained manually by the archer pulling the [[bowstring]] with fingers, arm and back muscles and holding that same [[form (exercise)|form]] in order to aim (which demands significant physical strength and stamina), while a crossbow uses a locking mechanism to maintain the draw, limiting the shooter's exertion to only pulling the string into lock and then releasing the shot via depressing a lever/[[trigger (firearms)|trigger]].  This not only enables a crossbowman to handle stronger draw weight, but also hold for longer with significantly less physical strain, thus capable of better precision.

Historically, crossbows played a significant role in the warfare of [[East Asia]] and [[Medieval]] [[Europe]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Tom Ukinski|title=Drones: Mankind's Always Had Them|url=http://guardianlv.com/2013/05/drones-mankinds-always-had-them/|accessdate=1 March 2015|work=Guardian Liberty Voice|date=23 May 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The earliest crossbows in the world were invented in [[History of Science and Technology in China|ancient China]] and caused a major shift in the role of [[ranged weaponry|projectile weaponry]].  The traditional [[bow and arrow]] had long been a specialized [[weapon]] that required considerable training, physical strength and expertise to operate with any degree of practical efficiency.  In many cultures, [[archer]]s were considered a separate and superior warrior caste, despite usually being drawn from the [[commoner|common]] class, as their [[archery]] skill-set was essentially trained and strengthened from birth (similar to many [[cavalry|horseman]] cultures) and was impossible to reproduce outside a pre-established cultural tradition, which many nations lacked.  In contrast, the crossbow was the first ranged weapon to be simple, cheap and physically undemanding enough to be operated by large numbers of untrained [[conscript]] soldiers, thus enabling virtually any nation to field a potent force of crossbowmen with little expense beyond the cost of the weapons themselves.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Facts and interesting information about Medieval Weapons, Armor and arms, specifically, the Crossbow|url=http://www.medieval-life-and-times.info/medieval-weapons/crossbow.htm|website=medieval-life-and-times.info|accessdate=1 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Firearm]]s have largely supplanted crossbows for use against humans.  Crossbows are still widely used for competitive [[shooting sport]]s and hunting, or for relatively silent shooting.

==Terminology==
A crossbowman or crossbow-maker is sometimes called an ''arbalist'' or ''arbalest''.{{sfn|Loades|2018}}

''Arrow'', ''bolt'' and ''quarrel'' are all suitable terms for crossbow projectiles.{{sfn|Loades|2018}}

The ''lath'', also called the ''prod'', is the bow of the crossbow. According to W.F. Peterson, the ''prod'' came into usage in the 19th century as a result of mistranslating ''rodd'' in a 16th-century list of crossbow effects.{{sfn|Loades|2018}}

The ''stock'' is the wooden body on which the bow is mounted, although the medieval ''tiller'' is also used.{{sfn|Loades|2018}}

The ''lock'' refers to the release mechanism, including the string, sears, trigger lever, and housing.{{sfn|Loades|2018}}

==Construction==
[[File:Han crossbow trigger mechanism.jpg|thumb|Han crossbow trigger pieces.]]
[[File:Noix corde carreau arbalette.svg|thumb|Crossbow nut: {{ordered list| Nut.| String.| Quarrel.| Trigger.}}]]
[[File:Nuss Armbrust.jpg|thumb|16th century crossbow nut excavated at [[Harburger Schloßstraße]], [[Hamburg Harburg]], [[Germany]]]]
A crossbow is essentially a [[bow (weapon)|bow]] mounted on an elongated frame (called a '''tiller''' or '''stock''') with a built-in mechanism that holds the drawn [[bow string]], as well as a [[trigger (firearms)|trigger]] mechanism that allows the string to be released.

===Chinese vertical trigger lock===
The Chinese trigger mechanism was a vertical lever composed of four bronze pieces secured together by two bronze rods.{{sfn|Loades|2018}}

{{quotation|The ''nu'' [crossbow] is so called because it spreads abroad an aura of rage [nu]. Its stock is like the arm of a man, therefore it is called ''bi''. That which hooks the bowstring is called ''ya'', for indeed it is like teeth. The part round about the teeth [i.e. the housing box] is called the 'outer wall' [''guo''], since it surrounds the lug [''gui''] of the teeth [i.e. the nut]. Within [and below] there is the 'hanging knife' [''xuan dao''] [i.e. the trigger] so called because it looks like one. The whole assembly is called ''ji'', for it is just as ingenious as the loom.{{sfn|Needham|1994|p=133}}|''[[Shiming]]''}}

===European rolling nut lock===
The earliest European designs featured a transverse slot in the top surface of the frame, down into which the string was placed. To shoot this design, a vertical rod is thrust up through a hole in the bottom of the notch, forcing the string out.  This rod is usually attached perpendicular to a rear-facing lever called a ''tickler''. A later design implemented a rolling cylindrical pawl called a ''nut'' to retain the string.  This nut has a perpendicular centre slot for the bolt, and an intersecting axial slot for the string, along with a lower face or slot against which the internal trigger sits. They often also have some form of strengthening internal ''sear'' or trigger face, usually of metal.  These ''roller nuts'' were either free-floating in their close-fitting hole across the stock, tied in with a binding of sinew or other strong cording; or mounted on a metal axle or pins. Removable or integral plates of wood, ivory, or metal on the sides of the stock kept the nut in place laterally.  Nuts were made of antler, bone, or metal.  Bows could be kept taut and ready to shoot for some time with little physical straining, allowing crossbowmen to aim better without fatiguing.&lt;ref&gt;Hanafi et al. 2011: 23&lt;/ref&gt;

===Bow===
Chinese crossbow bows were made of composite material from the start.{{sfn|Loades|2018}}

European crossbows from the 10th to 12th centuries used wood for the bow, also called the ''prod'' or ''lath'', which tended to be [[ash tree|ash]] or [[taxus|yew]].{{sfn|Loades|2018}}

Composite bows started appearing in Europe during the 13th century and could be made from layers of different material, often wood, horn, and sinew glued together and bound with animal tendon. These composite bows made of several layers are much stronger and more efficient in releasing energy than simple wooden bows.{{sfn|Loades|2018}}

As steel became more widely available in Europe around the 14th century, steel prods came into use.{{sfn|Loades|2018}}

Traditionally, the prod was often lashed to the stock with rope, [[whipcord]], or other strong cording. This cording is called the ''[[bridle]]''.{{sfn|Loades|2018}}

===Spanning mechanism===
The Chinese used winches for large mounted crossbows. Winches may have been used for hand held crossbows during the Han dynasty but there is only one known depiction of it. The ''[[Wujing Zongyao]]'' mentions types of crossbows using winch mechanisms, but it's not known if these were handheld crossbows or mounted crossbows.{{sfn|Needham|1994|p=150}}

During the medieval period, both Chinese and European crossbows used stirrups as well as belt hooks.{{sfn|Needham|1994|p=150}} In the 13th century European crossbows started using winches, and from the 14th century an assortment of spanning mechanisms such as winch pulleys, cord pulleys, gaffles (such as gaffe levers and goat's foot levers), cranequins, and even screws.{{sfn|Loades|2018}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Ixax|first1=belle|title=Crossbow Reviews 2017|url=http://thetagtech.com/best-crossbow-reviews|website=Archer's Café|accessdate=9 March 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Han winch.png|[[Han dynasty]] crossbowman using what may be a winch drawn crossbow
File:Northern song Cavalry.jpg|[[Song dynasty]] cavalry wielding crossbows with stirrups
File:The Martyrdom of St Sebastian (detail).jpg|Fifteenth century crossbowman using a stirrup along with a belt hook and pulley
File:05-043.png|Detailed illustration of a goat's foot lever mounted on a crossbow that is half-spanned
File:Armborst 2, Nordisk familjebok.png|Illustration of a gaffe lever mounted on a crossbow that is nearly at full-span.
File:CAH 0153r.png|Illustrations of Leonardo da Vinci's [[rapid fire crossbow]] in the 15th Century [[Codex Atlanticus]]. Note the internal lever mechanism is fully extended to catch the draw string.
File:Balester 2.jpg|Internal mechanics illustration of a Balester hunting crossbow's self-spanning mechanism
File:Armborst 4, Nordisk familjebok.png|Twentieth century depiction of a [[windlass]] pulley
File:Altarpiece of St Sebastian (detail).jpg|Fifteenth century crossbowman using a cranequin (rack &amp; pinion)
File:HJRK A 2269 - Crossbow windlass, late 15th century.jpg|Iron cranequin, South German, late 15th century
&lt;/gallery&gt;

=== Variants ===
[[File:Recurve crossbow with bolts.jpg|right|thumb|Modern recurve crossbow]]
[[File:Horton Hunter Supreme by IvE.jpg|right|thumb|Modern compound crossbow]]
[[File:HJRK A 108 - Wallarmbrust c. 1460-70.jpg|thumb|15th-century ''Wallarmbrust'', a heavy crossbow used for siege defense.]]

The smallest crossbows are pistol crossbows. Others are simple long stocks with the crossbow mounted on them. These could be shot from under the arm. The next step in development was stocks of the shape that would later be used [[Stock (firearms)|for firearms]], which allowed better aiming. The [[arbalest]] was a heavy crossbow that required special systems for pulling the sinew via windlasses. For [[siege warfare]], the size of crossbows was further increased to hurl large projectiles, such as rocks, at fortifications. The required crossbows needed a massive base frame and powerful windlass devices.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=O'Connell|first=Robert L|date=1989|title=Of Arms and Men: A History of War, Weapons, and Aggression|url=https://archive.org/details/ofarmsmenhisto00ocon|url-access=registration|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]|isbn=0-19-505359-1|page=[https://archive.org/details/ofarmsmenhisto00ocon/page/65 65]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;gallery class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
File:Zhugenu-springautumn.jpg|Double shot repeating crossbow, also known as the Chu state [[repeating crossbow]] (''chuguo nu'')
File:Repeating crossbow WBZ.jpg|[[Ming dynasty]] repeating crossbow trigger mechanism
File:Two-bow crossbow wjzy.jpg|Mounted double bow crossbow
File:Connected double bed crossbow wbz.jpg|Two connected double bow crossbows
File:Chuangzi Nu1.jpg|Mounted triple bow crossbow
File:Liannu.jpg|Multi-bolt crossbow without a visible nut or cocking aid
File:Gastraphetes - catapult ancestor - antica catapulta.jpg|Cocking of a Greek ''[[gastraphetes]]''
File:Roman crossbow. Pic 02.jpg|Gallo-Roman crossbow
File:B Osma 85v.jpg|Earliest European depiction of cavalry using crossbows, from the [[Catalonia|Catalan]] manuscript ''Four Horsemen of the Apocalypse'', 1086.
File:Martyrium of Saint Sebastian. Pic 03.jpg|[[Late Middle Ages|Late medieval]] crossbowman from ca. 1480
File:FrenchCrossbowMan.JPG|15th-century French soldier carrying an [[arbalest]] and a [[pavise]]
File:Balestra Veloce.jpg|A reconstruction of Leonardo da Vinci's rapid fire crossbow as shown at the World of Leonardo Exhibition in Milan.
File:Ballista-quadrirotis.jpeg|Early modern four-wheeled [[ballista]] drawn by armored horses (1552)
File:FrenchMountedCrossbowman.JPG|16th-century French mounted crossbowman (''cranequinier''). His crossbow is drawn with a rack-and-pinion ''cranequin'', so it can be used while riding.
File:Crossbow pistol IMG 3841.jpg|Pistol crossbow for home recreational shooting. Made by Frédéric Siber in Morges, early 19th century, on display at Morges military museum.
File:French cross-bow grenade thrower Arbalète sauterelle type A d'Imphy circa 1915.jpg|French cross-bow grenade thrower Arbalète sauterelle type A d'Imphy, circa 1915
&lt;/gallery&gt;

===Projectiles===

The arrow-like projectiles of a crossbow are called crossbow bolts. These are usually much shorter than arrows, but can be several times heavier. There is an optimum weight for bolts to achieve maximum kinetic energy, which varies depending on the strength and characteristics of the crossbow, but most could pass through common mail. Crossbow bolts can be fitted with a variety of heads, some with sickle-shaped heads to cut rope or rigging; but the most common today is a four-sided point called a [[Quarrel (projectile)|quarrel]]. A highly specialized type of bolt is employed to collect blubber biopsy samples used in biology research.

Even relatively small differences in arrow weight can have a considerable impact on its drop and, conversely, its flight trajectory.&lt;ref name=&quot;CrossbowArrowDrop&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bestcrossbowsource.com/crossbow-arrow-drop-charted-test-results/|title=Crossbow Arrow Drop - Charted Test Results|access-date=12 July 2019|website=BestCrossbowSource.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Accessories===
[[File:Crossbow telescopic sight reticle.JPG|thumb|200px|right|The reticle of a modern crossbow [[telescopic sight]] allows the shooter to adjust for different ranges]]

The [[History of Science and Technology in China|ancient Chinese]] crossbow often included a metal (i.e. bronze or steel) grid serving as [[iron sights]]. Modern crossbow sights often use similar technology to modern firearm sights, such as [[red dot sight]]s and [[telescopic sight]]s. Many crossbow scopes feature multiple [[crosshairs]] to compensate for the significant effects of [[gravity]] over different ranges. In most cases, a newly bought crossbow will need to be sighted for accurate shooting.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bestcrossbowsource.com/how-to-sight-a-crossbow|title=Sighting a Crossbow|work=Best Crossbow Source|accessdate=28 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A major cause of the sound of shooting a crossbow is vibration of various components. Crossbow silencers are multiple components placed on high vibration parts, such as the string and limbs, to dampen vibration and suppress the sound of loosing the bolt.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Crossbow|url=http://www.reference.com/browse/crossbow|website=[[reference.com]]|publisher=[[Columbia University Press]]|accessdate=1 March 2015|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150402100105/http://www.reference.com/browse/crossbow|archive-date=2 April 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
{{Main|History of crossbows}}

=== East Asia ===
[[File:Warring States or Western Han crossbow.jpg|thumb|A bronze crossbow trigger mechanism and butt plate that were mass-produced in the [[Warring States period]] (475-221 BC)]]
[[File:Earthenware architecture models, Eastern Han Dynasty, 5.JPG|thumb|right|A miniature guard wielding a handheld crossbow from the top balcony of a model watchtower, made of glazed earthenware during the [[Han Dynasty|Eastern Han era]] (25–220 AD) of China, from the [[Metropolitan Museum of Art]].]]
In terms of archaeological evidence, crossbow locks made of [[cast bronze]] have been found in China dating to around 650 BC.{{sfn|Loades|2018}} They have also been found in Tombs 3 and 12 at [[Qufu]], [[Shandong]], previously the capital of [[Lu (state)|Lu]], and date to 6th century BC.&lt;ref name=&quot;you 1994 80&quot;&gt;You (1994), 80.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.atarn.org/chinese/bjng_xbow/bjng_xbow.htm|title=A Crossbow Mechanism with Some Unique Features from Shandong, China|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080518053806/http://www.atarn.org/chinese/bjng_xbow/bjng_xbow.htm |date=18 May 2008|archive-date=18 May 2008|publisher=Asian Traditional Archery Research Network|access-date=2008-08-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bronze crossbow bolts dating from the mid-5th century BC have been found at a [[Chu (state)|Chu]] burial site in Yutaishan, [[Jiangling County]], [[Hubei]] Province.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Wagner| first=Donald B.|year=1993|title=Iron and Steel in Ancient China: Second Impression, With Corrections|publisher=Leiden: E.J. Brill|isbn=90-04-09632-9}} pp. 153, 157–158.&lt;/ref&gt; Other early finds of crossbows were discovered in Tomb 138 at Saobatang, [[Hunan]] Province, and date to mid-4th century BC.&lt;ref&gt;Mao (1998), 109–110.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Wright (2001), 159.&lt;/ref&gt; It is possible that these early crossbows used [[Bullet-shooting crossbow|spherical pellets]] for ammunition. A [[Western Han Dynasty|Western-Han]] mathematician and music theorist, [[Jing Fang]] (78-37 BC), compared the moon to the shape of a round [[bullet-shooting crossbow|crossbow bullet]].&lt;ref name=&quot;needham 1986 vol 3 p227&quot;&gt;Needham, Joseph (1986). ''Science and Civilization in China: Volume 3, Mathematics and the Sciences of the Heavens and the Earth''. Taipei: Caves Books Ltd, p. 227.&lt;/ref&gt;  The ''[[Zhuangzi (book)|Zhuangzi]]'' also mentions crossbow bullets.{{sfn|Needham|1994|p=89}}

The earliest Chinese documents mentioning a crossbow were texts from the 4th to 3rd centuries BC attributed to the [[Mohist|followers]] of [[Mozi]]. This source refers to the use of a giant crossbow between the 6th and 5th centuries BC, corresponding to the late [[Spring and Autumn Period]]. [[Sun Tzu]]'s ''[[The Art of War]]'' (first appearance dated between 500 BC to 300 BC&lt;ref&gt;James Clavell, ''The Art of War'', prelude&lt;/ref&gt;) refers to the characteristics and use of crossbows in chapters 5 and 12 respectively,&lt;ref&gt;https://www.gutenberg.org/files/132/132.txt&lt;/ref&gt; and compares a drawn crossbow to &quot;might&quot;.{{sfn|Needham|1994|p=34}}  The ''[[Huainanzi]]'' advises its readers not to use crossbows in marshland where the surface is soft and it is hard to arm the crossbow with the foot.{{sfn|Needham|1994|p=141}} The ''[[Records of the Grand Historian]]'', completed in 94 BC, mentions that [[Sun Bin]] defeated [[Pang Juan]] by ambushing him with a body of crossbowmen at the [[Battle of Maling]] in 342 BC.{{sfn|Needham|1994|p=139}}  The ''[[Book of Han]]'', finished 111 AD, lists two military treatises on crossbows.{{sfn|Needham|1994|p=22}}&lt;ref name=&quot;wright 2001 42&quot;&gt;Wright (2001), 42.&lt;/ref&gt;

Handheld crossbows with complex bronze trigger mechanisms have also been found with the [[Terracotta Army]] in the tomb of [[Qin Shihuang]] (r. 221–210 BC) that are similar to specimens from the subsequent [[Han Dynasty]] (202 BC–220 AD), while crossbowmen described in the Qin and Han Dynasty learned drill formations, some were even mounted as [[Chariots in ancient China|charioteers]] and [[Cavalry#East Asia|cavalry units]], and Han Dynasty writers attributed the success of numerous [[Han–Xiongnu War|battles against the Xiongnu]] and [[Western Regions]] states to massed crossbow volleys.&lt;ref&gt;Needham (1986), Volume 5, Part 6, 124–128.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Lewis (2000a), 45.&lt;/ref&gt;  The bronze triggers were designed in such a way that they were able to store a large amount of energy within the bow when drawn, but was easily shot with little resistance and recoil when the trigger were pulled.  The trigger nut also had a long vertical spine that could be used like a primitive [[iron sight|rear sight]] for [[elevation (ballistics)|elevation]] adjustment, which allowed precision shooting over longer distances.  The Qin/Han-era crossbow was also an early example of [[modular design]], as the bronze trigger components were also mass-produced with relative high precision so they are interchangeable between different crossbows.  The trigger mechanism from one crossbow can be installed into another simply by dropping into a tiller slot of the same specifications and secured with [[dowel pin]]s.

It is clear from surviving inventory lists in [[Gansu]] and [[Xinjiang]] that the crossbow was greatly favored by the Han dynasty.  For example, in one batch of slips there are only two mentions of bows, but thirty mentions of crossbows.{{sfn|Needham|1994|p=141}} Crossbows were mass-produced in state armories with designs improving as time went on, such as the use of a mulberry wood stock and brass; a crossbow in 1068 could pierce a tree at 140 paces.&lt;ref name=&quot;peers 130 131&quot;&gt;Peers, 130–131.&lt;/ref&gt; Crossbows were used in numbers as large as 50,000 starting from the Qin dynasty and upwards of several hundred thousand during the Han.{{sfn|Needham|1994|p=143}} According to one authority, the crossbow had become &quot;nothing less than the standard weapon of the Han armies&quot;, by the second century BC.{{sfn|Graff|2002|p=22}} Han soldiers were required to pull a crossbow with a draw weight equivalent of 76&amp;nbsp;kg to qualify as a crossbowman.{{sfn|Loades|2018}}

After the Han dynasty, the crossbow lost favor until it experienced a mild resurgence during the Tang dynasty, under which the ideal expeditionary army of 20,000 included 2,200 archers and 2,000 crossbowmen.{{sfn|Graff|2002|p=193}} [[Li Jing (Tang dynasty)|Li Jing]] and Li Quan prescribed 20 percent of the infantry to be armed with crossbows.{{sfn|Graff|2016|p=52}}

During the [[Song dynasty]], the crossbow received a huge upsurge in military usage. The crossbow overshadowed the bow 2 to 1. During this time period, a stirrup was added for ease of loading. The government attempted to restrict the spread of crossbows and sought ways to keep armour and crossbows out of civilian homes.{{sfn|Needham|1994|p=145}}  Despite the ban on certain types of crossbows, the weapon experienced an upsurge in civilian usage as both a hunting weapon and pastime. The &quot;romantic young people from rich families, and others who had nothing particular to do&quot; formed crossbow shooting clubs as a way to pass time.{{sfn|Needham|1994|p=146}}

During the late [[Ming dynasty]], no crossbows were mentioned to have been produced in the three-year period from 1619 to 1622. With 21,188,366 taels, the Ming manufactured 25,134 cannons, 8,252 small guns, 6,425 muskets, 4,090 culverins, 98,547 polearms and swords, 26,214 great &quot;horse decapitator&quot; swords, 42,800 bows, 1,000 great axes, 2,284,000 arrows, 180,000 fire arrows, 64,000 bow strings, and hundreds of transport carts.{{sfn|Swope|2014|p=49}}

Military crossbows were armed by treading, or basically placing the feet on the bow stave and drawing it using one's arms and back muscles. During the Song dynasty, stirrups were added for ease of drawing and to mitigate damage to the bow. Alternatively the bow could also be drawn by a belt claw attached to the waist, but this was done lying down, as was the case for all large crossbows. Winch-drawing was used for the large mounted crossbows as seen below, but evidence for its use in Chinese hand-crossbows is scant.{{sfn|Needham|1994|p=150}}

Other sorts of crossbows also existed, such as the [[repeating crossbow]], multi-shot crossbow, larger field artillery crossbows, and repeating multi-shot crossbow.

===Southeast Asia===
[[File:Ref-chamballista.jpg|right|thumb|Wheelmounted and elephantmounted double-bow-arcuballistae of the [[Champa]] kingdom.]]

In [[Vietnam]]ese historical legend, general [[Thục Phán]], who ruled over the ancient kingdom of [[Âu Lạc]] from 257 to 207&amp;nbsp;BC, is said to have owed his power to a magic crossbow, capable of shooting thousands of bolts at once.

The native [[Montagnard (Vietnam)|Montagnard]]s of Vietnam's Central Highlands were also known to have used crossbows, as both a tool for hunting, and later, an effective weapon against the Viet Cong during the Vietnam War.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Montagnard Crossbow, Vietnam|url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/C364947|website=awm.gov.au|publisher=[[Australian War Memorial]]|access-date=4 February 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Montagnard fighters armed with crossbows proved a highly valuable asset to the US Special Forces operating in Vietnam, and it was not uncommon for the Green Berets to integrate Montagnard crossbowmen into their strike teams.{{citation needed|date=February 2019}}

Crossbow technology for crossbows with more than one prod was transferred from the Chinese to [[Champa]], which Champa used in its invasion of the [[Khmer Empire]]'s [[Angkor]] in 1177.&lt;ref name=&quot;Grant2005&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=R. G. Grant|title=Battle: A Visual Journey Through 5,000 Years of Combat|url=https://books.google.com/?id=Gb8qAQAAMAAJ&amp;q=champa|year=2005|publisher=DK Pub.|isbn=978-0-7566-1360-0|page=100}}&lt;/ref&gt; When the Chams sacked Angkor they used the Chinese siege crossbow.&lt;ref name=&quot;Turnbull2012&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Stephen Turnbull|title=Siege Weapons of the Far East (1): AD 612-1300|url=https://books.google.com/?id=6osQI3ig9UAC&amp;pg=PT42&amp;dq=champa+crossbows+chinese+angkor#v=onepage&amp;q=champa%20crossbows%20chinese%20angkor&amp;f=false|date=20 August 2012|publisher=Osprey Publishing Limited|isbn=978-1-78200-225-3|pages=42–}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Turnbull2012 2&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Stephen Turnbull|title=Siege Weapons of the Far East (1): AD 612–1300|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=OajvCwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT80|date=20 August 2012|publisher=Bloomsbury Publishing|isbn=978-1-78200-225-3|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Crossbows and archery while mounted were instructed to the Cham by a Chinese in 1171.&lt;ref name=&quot;Turnbull2012 3&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Stephen Turnbull|title=Siege Weapons of the Far East (1): AD 612–1300|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=OajvCwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT25|date=20 August 2012|publisher=Bloomsbury Publishing|isbn=978-1-78200-225-3|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Ancient Greece ===
[[File:Gastraphetes Rekonstruktion Saalburg.jpg|thumb|upright|Greek ''[[gastraphetes]]'']]

The earliest crossbow-like weapons in Europe probably emerged around the late 5th century BC when the ''[[gastraphetes]]'', an ancient Greek crossbow, appeared. The device was described by the Greek author [[Hero of Alexandria|Heron of Alexandria]] in his ''Belopoeica'' (&quot;On Catapult-making&quot;), which draws on an earlier account of his compatriot engineer [[Ctesibius]] ([[floruit|fl.]] 285–222 BC). According to Heron, the gastraphetes was the forerunner of the later [[catapult]], which places its invention some unknown time prior to 399 BC.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Campbell|2003|pp=3ff.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The gastraphetes was a crossbow mounted on a stock divided into a lower and upper section. The lower was a case fixed to the bow while the upper was a slider which had the same dimensions as the case.&lt;ref name=&quot;devries 127&quot;&gt;DeVries, Kelly Robert. (2003). ''Medieval Military Technology''. Petersborough: Broadview Press. {{ISBN|0-921149-74-3}}. Page 127.&lt;/ref&gt; Meaning &quot;belly-bow&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;devries 127&quot; /&gt; it was called as such because the concave withdrawal rest at one end of the stock was placed against the stomach of the operator, which he could press to withdraw the slider before attaching a string to the trigger and loading the bolt; this could thus store more energy than regular [[Bow (weapon)|Greek bows]].&lt;ref&gt;DeVries, Kelly Robert. (2003). ''Medieval Military Technology''. Petersborough: Broadview Press. {{ISBN|0-921149-74-3}}. Page 128.&lt;/ref&gt; It was used in the [[Sicilian Wars#The Second Sicilian War (410 BCE–340 BCE)|Siege of Motya]] in 397 BC. This was a key [[Ancient Carthage|Carthaginian]] stronghold in [[Sicily]], as described in the 1st century AD by [[Heron of Alexandria]] in his book ''Belopoeica''.&lt;ref&gt;Stanley M. Burstein, Walter Donlan, Sarah B. Pomeroy, and Jennifer Tolbert Roberts (1999). ''Ancient Greece: A Political, Social, and Cultural History''. Oxford University Press. {{ISBN|0-19-509742-4}}, p. 366&lt;/ref&gt;

Other arrow shooting machines such as the larger [[ballista]] and smaller ''Scorpio'' also existed starting from around 338 BC, but these are [[torsion (mechanics)|torsion]] [[catapult]]s and not considered crossbows.&lt;ref&gt;Duncan B Campbell, ''Ancient Siege Warfare'' 2005 Osprey Publishing {{ISBN|1-84176-770-0}}, p. 26-56&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Duncan Campbell, p.8&quot;&gt;Duncan Campbell: ''Greek and Roman Artillery 399 BC-AD 363'', Osprey Publishing, Oxford 2003, {{ISBN|1-84176-634-8}}, p.8ff.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Eric William Marsden, p.57&quot;&gt;Eric William Marsden: ''Greek and Roman Artillery: Historical Development'', The Clarendon Press, Oxford 1969, {{ISBN|978-0-19-814268-3}}, p.57&lt;/ref&gt; Arrow-shooting machines (''katapeltai'') are briefly mentioned by [[Aeneas Tacticus]] in his treatise on siegecraft written around 350 BC.&lt;ref name=&quot;Duncan Campbell, p.8&quot; /&gt; An Athenian inventory from 330–329 BC includes catapults bolts with heads and flights.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eric William Marsden, p.57&quot; /&gt; Arrow-shooting machines in action are reported from [[Philip II of Macedon|Philip II]]'s siege of [[Marmara Ereğlisi|Perinthos]] in [[Thrace]] in 340 BC.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eric William Marsden, p.60&quot;&gt;Eric William Marsden: ''Greek and Roman Artillery: Historical Development'', The Clarendon Press, Oxford 1969, {{ISBN|978-0-19-814268-3}}, p.60&lt;/ref&gt; At the same time, Greek fortifications began to feature high towers with shuttered windows in the top, presumably to house anti-personnel arrow shooters, as in [[Aigosthena]].&lt;ref&gt;Josiah Ober: ''Early Artillery Towers: Messenia, Boiotia, Attica, Megarid'', ''American Journal of Archaeology'', Vol. 91, No. 4. (1987), S. 569–604 (569)&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Ancient Rome ===
[[File:Roman crossbow.jpg|thumb|upright=0.7|A crossbow based on depictions from a Roman grave in Gaul.]]

The late 4th century author [[Vegetius]] provides the only contemporary account of ancient Roman crossbows. In his ''De Re Militaris'', he describes ''arcubalistarii'' (crossbowmen) working together with archers and artillerymen.{{sfn|Loades|2018}} However it is disputed if arcuballistas were even crossbows or just more torsion powered weapons. The idea that the arcuballista was a crossbow is based on the fact that Vegetius refers to it and the ''manuballista'', which was torsion powered, separately. Therefore, if the arcuballista was not like the manuballista, it may have been a crossbow. Some suggest it was the other way around and manuballistas were crossbows.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=http://tastesofhistory.blogspot.com/2016/12/arcuballista-late-roman-crossbow.html | title=Tastes of History: Arcuballista: A Late Roman Crossbow| date=15 December 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The etymology is not clear and their definitions obscure. According to Vegetius, these were well known devices, and as such didn't make the effort to describe them in depth.{{sfn|Needham|1994|p=172}}

{{quotation|On the textual side, there is almost nothing but passing references in the military historian Vegetius (fl. + 386) to 'manuballistae' and 'arcuballistae' which he said he must decline to describe as they were so well known. His decision was highly regrettable, as no other author of the time makes any mention of them at all. Perhaps the best supposition is that the crossbow was primarily known in late European antiquity as a hunting weapon, and received only local use in certain units of the armies of Theodosius I, with
which Vegetius happened to be acquainted.{{sfn|Needham|1994|p=172}}|Joseph Needham}}

[[Arrian]]'s earlier ''Ars Tactica'', written around 136 AD, does mention 'missiles shot not from a bow but from a machine' and that this machine was used on horseback while in full gallop. It is presumed that this was a crossbow.{{sfn|Loades|2018}}

The only pictorial evidence of Roman arcuballistas comes from sculptural reliefs in [[Roman Gaul]] depicting them in hunting scenes. These are aesthetically similar to both the Greek and Chinese crossbows, but it's not clear what kind of release mechanism they used. Archaeological evidence suggests they were based on the rolling nut mechanism of medieval Europe.{{sfn|Loades|2018}}

=== Medieval Europe ===
[[File:Balestriere1.jpg|upright|thumb|left|A medieval [[Arbalist (crossbowman)|crossbowman]] drawing his bow behind his [[pavise]]. A hook on the end of a strap on his belt engages the bowstring. Holding the crossbow down by putting his foot through the stirrup, he draws the bow by straightening his legs]]
References to the crossbow are basically nonexistent in Europe from the 5th century until the 10th century. There is however a depiction of a crossbow as a hunting weapon on four [[Pictish stones]] from [[Scotland in the Early Middle Ages|early medieval Scotland]] (6th to 9th centuries): [[St Vigeans|St. Vigeans no. 1]], [[Glenferness]], [[Shandwick]], and [[Meigle]].&lt;ref&gt;John M. Gilbert, ''Hunting and Hunting Reserves in Medieval Scotland'' (Edinburgh: John Donald, 1979), p. 62.&lt;/ref&gt;

The crossbow reappeared again in 947 as a French weapon during the siege of [[Senlis]] and again in 984 at the siege of [[Verdun]].{{sfn|Needham|1994|p=170}} They were used at the [[battle of Hastings]] in 1066 and by the 12th century it had become a common battlefield weapon.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sir Ralph Payne-Gallwey 1995 p. 48&quot;&gt;Sir Ralph Payne-Gallwey (1995). &quot;The Book of the Crossbow&quot;. Dover. {{ISBN|0-486-28720-3}}, p. 48&lt;/ref&gt; The earliest extant European crossbow remains to date were found at [[Lake Paladru]] and has been dated to the 11th century.{{sfn|Loades|2018}}

The crossbow superseded hand bows in many European armies during the 12th century, except in England, where the [[longbow]] was more popular. Later crossbows (sometimes referred to as [[arbalest]]s), utilizing all-steel prods, were able to achieve power close (and sometime superior) to longbows, but were more expensive to produce and slower to reload because they required the aid of mechanical devices such as the cranequin or [[windlass]] to draw back their extremely heavy bows. Usually these could only shoot two bolts per minute versus twelve or more with a skilled archer, often necessitating the use of a [[pavise]] to protect the operator from enemy fire.&lt;ref name=&quot;Robert Hardy 1992 p. 75&quot;&gt;Robert Hardy (1992). &quot;Longbow: A Social and Military History&quot;. Lyons &amp; Burford. {{ISBN|1-85260-412-3}}, p. 75&lt;/ref&gt; Along with [[Pole weapon|polearm]] weapons made from farming equipment, the crossbow was also a weapon of choice for insurgent peasants such as the [[Taborite]]s. [[Genoese crossbowmen]] were famous mercenaries hired throughout medieval Europe, while the crossbow also played an important role in anti-personnel defense of ships.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;[http://www.diaspora.uiuc.edu/A-AAnewsletter/newsletter16.html Notes On West African Crossbow Technology]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:DaVinci Crossbow.JPG|thumb|Sketch by [[Leonardo da Vinci]], c. 1500]]
Crossbows were eventually replaced in warfare by [[gunpowder]] weapons, although early guns had slower rates of fire and much worse accuracy than contemporary crossbows. The [[Battle of Cerignola]] in 1503 was largely won by Spain through the use of matchlock firearms, marking the first time a major battle was won through the use of firearms. Later, similar competing tactics would feature [[arquebus|harquebusiers]] or [[musket]]eers in formation with pikemen, pitted against cavalry firing [[pistol]]s or [[carbine]]s. While the military crossbow had largely been supplanted by firearms on the battlefield by 1525, the sporting crossbow in various forms remained a popular hunting weapon in Europe until the eighteenth century.&lt;ref&gt;Sir Ralph Payne-Gallwey (1995). &quot;The Book of the Crossbow&quot;. Dover. {{ISBN|0-486-28720-3}}, p. 48-53&lt;/ref&gt;

===Islamic world===

There are no references to crossbows in [[Islamic]] texts earlier than the 14th century. [[Arabs]] in general were averse to the crossbow and considered it a foreign weapon. They called it ''qaus al-rijl'' (foot-drawn bow), ''qaus al-zanbūrak'' (bolt bow) and ''qaus al-faranjīyah'' (Frankish bow). Although [[Muslims]] did have crossbows, there seems to be a split between eastern and western types. Muslims in [[Spain]] used the typical European trigger while eastern Muslim crossbows had a more complex trigger mechanism.{{sfn|Needham|1994|p=175}}

[[Mamluk]] cavalry used crossbows.{{sfn|Loades|2018}}

===Elsewhere===
In Western Africa and Central Africa,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.photographersdirect.com/buyers/stockphoto.asp?imageid=348455 Baaka pygmy with crossbow]. Photographersdirect.com. Retrieved on 24 June 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; crossbows served as a scouting weapon and for hunting, with African slaves bringing this technology to natives in America.&lt;ref name=&quot;cvplxd&quot;&gt;[http://www.diaspora.uiuc.edu/A-AAnewsletter/newsletter16.html Notes On West African Crossbow Technology]. Diaspora.uiuc.edu. Retrieved on 24 June 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[US South]], the crossbow was used for hunting and warfare when firearms or gunpowder were unavailable because of economic hardships or isolation.&lt;ref name=&quot;cvplxd&quot; /&gt; In the North of Northern America, light hunting crossbows were traditionally used by the [[Inuit]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Hunting Network|title=The Crossbow: Four thousand years of traditional archery|url=http://www.bowhunting.com/publisher/crossbow-information/2009/10/2/future-of-crossbow-hunting|accessdate=1 March 2015|publisher=bowhunting.com|date=10 February 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{tertiary source inline|date=October 2015}} These are technologically similar to the African derived crossbows, but have a different route of influence.

Spanish [[conquistador]]s continued to use crossbows in the Americas long after they were replaced in European battlefields by firearms. Only in the 1570s did firearms became completely dominant among the Spanish in the Americas.&lt;ref name=Espino2012&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Espino López |first1=Antonio |date=2012 |title=El uso táctico de las armas de fuego en las guerras civiles peruanas (1538-1547) |url= |journal=Historica|language=Spanish |volume=XXXVI |issue=2 |pages=7–48 |doi= |access-date= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[French Army|French]], and the [[British Army|British]] used a [[Sauterelle]] (French for [[grasshopper]]) in [[World War I]]. It was lighter and more portable than the [[Leach Trench Catapult]], but less powerful. It weighed {{convert|24|kg|lb|abbr=on}} and could throw an [[F1 grenade (France)|F1 grenade]] or [[Mills bomb]] {{convert|110|-|140|m|yd|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;RE&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|title=The Royal Engineers|journal=The Royal Engineers Journal|publisher=The Institution of Royal Engineers|year=1925|volume=39|page=79}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Sauterelle replaced the Leach Catapult in British service and was in turn replaced in 1916 by the [[2 inch Medium Mortar|2 inch Medium Trench Mortar]] and [[Stokes mortar]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Britannica1922&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=The Encyclopædia Britannica: The New Volumes, Constituting, in Combination with the Twenty-nine Volumes of the Eleventh Edition, the Twelfth Edition of that Work, and Also Supplying a New, Distinctive, and Independent Library of Reference Dealing with Events and Developments of the Period 1910 to 1921 Inclusive, Volume 1|page=470|author=Hugh Chisholm|publisher=Encyclopædia Britannica Company Limited|year=1922}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Modern use ==

=== Hunting, leisure and science ===
{{Main|Bowhunting}}
Crossbows are used for [[shooting sport]]s and bowhunting in modern [[archery]] and for [[blubber]] [[biopsy]] samples in scientific research. In [[Laws on crossbows|some countries]] such as Canada or the United Kingdom, they may be less heavily regulated than firearms, and thus more popular for hunting; some jurisdictions have bow and/or crossbow only seasons.&lt;ref&gt;https://dr6j45jk9xcmk.cloudfront.net/documents/3311/2014-ontario-hunting-regulations.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Crossbow Hunting.jpg|Modern hunting crossbow
File:Fish0293 - Flickr - NOAA Photo Library.jpg|Fisheries scientist obtaining tissue samples from dolphins swimming in the bow wave of a [[National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration|NOAA]] ship 
File:Blubber biopsy sample.jpg|A whale shot by a modified crossbow bolt for a [[blubber]] [[biopsy]] sample
&lt;/gallery&gt;

=== Modern military and paramilitary use ===
In modern times, crossbows are no longer used for war, but there are still some applications. For example, in the Americas, the [[Peru]]vian army (Ejército) equips some soldiers with crossbows and rope, to establish a [[zip-line]] in difficult terrain.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.saorbats.com.ar/GaleriaSaorbats/Peruffaa04/images/b2aBriFFEE2_EP_jpg.jpg Ejercito prepare for deployment.] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090305184249/http://www.saorbats.com.ar/GaleriaSaorbats/Peruffaa04/images/b2aBriFFEE2_EP_jpg.jpg |date=5 March 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In Brazil the CIGS (Jungle Warfare Training Center) also trains soldiers in the use of crossbows.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.militaryphotos.net/forums/showthread.php?t=23940 CIGS information thread].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.segurancaedefesa.com/Besta.jpg CIGS photograph] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090305184249/http://www.segurancaedefesa.com/Besta.jpg |date=5 March 2009 }}.&lt;/ref&gt; In the United States of America, SAA International Ltd manufacture a 150&amp;nbsp;ft·lb crossbow-launched version of the U.S. Army type classified Launched [[Grappling hook|Grapnel Hook]] (LGH), among other mine countermeasure solutions designed for the middle-eastern theatre. It has been successfully evaluated in Cambodia and Bosnia.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.janes.com/articles/Janes-Mines-and-Mine-Clearance/Launched-Grapnel-Hook-LGH-United-States.html Jane's LGH Mine Clearance by US forces Jul 2009]. Janes.com (9 June 2011). Retrieved on 24 June 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; It is used to probe for and detonate tripwire initiated mines and booby traps at up to 50 meters. The concept is similar to the LGH device originally only fired from a rifle, as a plastic retrieval line is attached.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.saa-intl.com/products/images/crossbow2.jpg LGH Plastic Retrieval Line] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100212194101/http://www.saa-intl.com/products/images/crossbow2.jpg |date=12 February 2010 }}. None. Retrieved on 24 June 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Reusable up to 20 times, the line can be reeled back in without exposing oneself. The device is of particular use in tactical situations where noise discipline is important.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.saa-intl.com/products/crossbow.html SAA Crossbow Launched Grapnel Hook] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110715221520/http://www.saa-intl.com/products/crossbow.html |date=15 July 2011 }}. Saa-intl.com. Retrieved on 24 June 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

In Europe, British-based Barnett International supplied crossbows to [[Serbs|Serbian]] forces which according to ''[[The Guardian]]'' were later used &quot;in [[ambushes]] and as a counter-sniper weapon&quot;, against the [[Kosovo Liberation Army]] during the [[Kosovo War]] in the areas of Pec and Djakovica, south west of Kosovo.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.theguardian.com/world/1999/aug/09/balkans The Guardian].&lt;/ref&gt; Whitehall launched an investigation, though the department of trade and industry established that not being &quot;on the military list&quot; crossbows were not covered by such export regulations. Paul Beaver of Jane's defence publications commented that, &quot;They are not only a silent killer, they also have a psychological effect&quot;. On 15 February 2008, Serbian Minister of Defence [[Dragan Sutanovac]] was pictured testing a Barnett crossbow during a public exercise of the Serbian army's Special Forces in Nis, 200&amp;nbsp;km south of capital [[Belgrade]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.daylife.com/photo/04ZU4Zr0xS4IA Day Life Serbia report] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090112045026/http://www.daylife.com/photo/04ZU4Zr0xS4IA |date=12 January 2009 }}. Daylife.com (15 February 2008). Retrieved on 24 June 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Special forces in both Greece and Turkey also continue to employ the crossbow.&lt;ref&gt;[http://i96.photobucket.com/albums/l189/KORNET-E/162.jpg Greek soldiers uses crossbow].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://i96.photobucket.com/albums/l189/KORNET-E/crosbow.jpg Turkish special ops].&lt;/ref&gt; Spain's Green Berets still use the crossbow as well.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.boinasverdes.org/album/bataller/caperez/foto03.JPG Spanish Green Beret 2005 photo] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100212194101/http://www.boinasverdes.org/album/bataller/caperez/foto03.JPG |date=12 February 2010 }}.&lt;/ref&gt;

In Asia, some Chinese armed forces use crossbows, including the [[Special forces|special force]] [[Snow Leopard Commando Unit]] of the [[People's Armed Police]] and the [[People's Liberation Army]]. One justification for this comes in the crossbow's ability to stop persons carrying explosives without risk of causing detonation.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20140202110148/http://english.pladaily.com.cn/site2/militarydatabase/2006-02/05/content_403376.htm | archivedate=2 February 2014| url = http://english.pladaily.com.cn/site2/militarydatabase/2006-02/05/content_403376.htm | title = New crossbow shoots with great accuracy}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the [[July 2009 Ürümqi riots|Xinjiang riots of July 2009]], crossbows were used alongside modern military hardware to quell protests.&lt;ref&gt;Bingham, John. (9 July 2009) [https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/asia/china/5780852/Xinjiang-riots-Modern-Chinese-army-displays-ancient-preference-for-crossbow.html &quot;Xinjiang riots: Modern Chinese army displays ancient preference for crossbow&quot;]. Daily Telegraph (UK). Retrieved on 24 June 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Indian Navy]]'s [[Marine Commando Force]] were equipped until the late 1980s with crossbows supplied with [[cyanide]]-tipped bolts, as an alternative to [[suppressor|suppressed handgun]]s.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bharat-rakshak.com/NAVY/Marines.html Marine Commandos&amp;#91;dead link&amp;#93;&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071025075700/http://www.bharat-rakshak.com/NAVY/Marines.html |date=25 October 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Comparison to conventional bows ==
With a crossbow, archers could release a draw force far in excess of what they could have handled with a bow. Furthermore, the crossbow could hold the tension for a long time, whereas even the strongest longbowman could only hold a drawn bow for a short period of time. The ease of use of a crossbow allows it to be used effectively with little training, while other types of bows take far more skill to shoot accurately.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.wideopenspaces.com/pros-cons-crossbow-hunting/|title=These Are The Pros and Cons of Crossbow Hunting|date=2016-09-01|work=Wide Open Spaces|access-date=2018-01-11|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt; The disadvantage is the greater weight and clumsiness to reload compared to a bow, as well as the slower rate of shooting and the lower efficiency of the acceleration system, but there would be reduced [[Hysteresis#Elastic hysteresis|elastic hysteresis]], making the crossbow a more accurate weapon.

Crossbows have a much smaller draw length than bows. This means that for the same energy to be imparted to the arrow (or bolt), the crossbow has to have a much higher draw weight.

A direct comparison between a fast hand-drawn replica crossbow and a longbow show a 6:10 rate of shooting&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HagCuGXJgUs&amp;feature=grec_index Video comparing longbow and crossbow] Retrieved 16 September 2010&lt;/ref&gt; or a 4:9 rate within 30 seconds and comparable weapons.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7g-0-RK3cjk longbow vs crossbow behind a pavese] Retrieved 16 September 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legal issues==
{{Main|Laws on crossbows}}
[[File:Armbrustschiessen.jpg|thumb|right|Modern competition crossbow]]

Today, the crossbow often has a complicated legal status due to the possibility of lethal use and its similarities to both firearms and archery weapons. While some jurisdictions regard crossbows the same as firearms, many others do not require any sort of license to own a crossbow. The legality of using a crossbow for hunting varies widely around the world, and even within different jurisdictions of some federal countries.

== See also ==
*[[Arbalist (crossbowman)]]
*[[Bow and arrow]]
*[[History of crossbows]]
*[[Master of Crossbowmen]]
*[[Modern competitive archery]] and [[target archery]] for [[bow (weapon)|bow]]s
*[[Shooting sport]]
*[[Sauterelle]]
*[[International Crossbow Shooting Union]]

== References ==
=== Citations ===
{{Reflist|32em}}

=== Sources ===
{{refbegin|32em}}
* {{Citation |last=Andrade |first=Tonio |year=2016 |title=The Gunpowder Age: China, Military Innovation, and the Rise of the West in World History |publisher=Princeton University Press |isbn=9781400874446}}
* {{cite book
|last = Baatz
|first = Dietwulf
|author-link =
|year = 1994
|location = Stuttgart
|title = Bauten und Katapulte des römischen Heeres
|contribution = Die römische Jagdarmbrust
|publisher = Franz Steiner Verlag
|pages = 284–293
|isbn = 3-515-06566-0
}}
*{{Citation
 | last = Campbell
 | first = Duncan 
 | title = Greek and Roman Artillery 399 BCE-CE 363
 | place = Oxford 
 | publisher=Osprey Publishing
 | year = 2003
 | isbn = 1-84176-634-8
}}
*{{Citation|last1=Crombie|first1=Laura|title=Archery and Crossbow Guilds in Medieval Flanders|date=2016|publisher=Boydell and Brewer|location=Woodbridge|isbn=9781783271047}}
*{{Citation|last = Graff |first = David A. |title = Medieval Chinese Warfare, 300-900 |series = Warfare and History |location = London |publisher = Routledge |year = 2002 |isbn = 0415239559}}
* {{cite book |last = Graff |first = David A. |title = Medieval Chinese Warfare, 300-900 |series = Warfare and History |location = London, England |publisher = Routledge |year = 2002 |isbn = 0415239559 }}
*{{citation|last=Graff|first=David A.|year=2016|title=The Eurasian Way of War: Military practice in seventh-century China and Byzantium|publisher=Routledge}}
* {{Citation |last=Liang |first=Jieming |year=2006 |title=Chinese Siege Warfare: Mechanical Artillery &amp; Siege Weapons of Antiquity |place= |publisher=Leong Kit Meng |isbn=981-05-5380-3 |location=Singapore, Republic of Singapore}}
*{{citation|last=Loades|first=Mike|year=2018|title=The Crossbow|publisher=Osprey}}
*{{citation|last=Lu|first=Yongxiang|year=2015|title=A History of Chinese Science and Technology Volume 3|publisher=Springer}}
* {{Citation|last=Needham|first=Joseph|year=1994|title=Science and Civilization in China Volume 5 Part 6|publisher=Cambridge University Press}}
*{{citation|last=Nicolle|first=David|year=2003|title=Medieval Siege Weapons (2): Byzantium, the Islamic World &amp; India AD 476-1526|publisher=Osprey Publishing}}
* Payne-Gallwey, Ralph, Sir, ''The Crossbow: Mediaeval and Modern, Military and Sporting; its Construction, History &amp; Management with a Treatise on the Balista and Catapult of the Ancients and An Appendix on the Catapult, Balista &amp; the Turkish Bow'', New York : Bramhall House, 1958.
*{{citation|last=Peers|first=C. J.|year=1996|title=Imperial Chinese Armies (2): 590-1260AD|publisher=Osprey}}
*{{Citation
 | last = Schellenberg
 | first = Hans Michael 
 | title = Diodor von Sizilien 14,42,1 und die Erfindung der Artillerie im Mittelmeerraum
 | url = http://s145739614.online.de/fera/ausgabe3/Schellenberg.pdf 
 | journal=Frankfurter Elektronische Rundschau zur Altertumskunde
 | volume = 3
 | issue = 
 | pages = 14–23
 | year = 2006
}}
*{{Citation|last=Swope|first=Kenneth|title=The Military Collapse of China's Ming Dynasty|year=2014|publisher=Routledge}}
* {{Citation|last=Turnbull|first=Stephen|year=2001|title=Siege Weapons of the Far East (1) AD 612-1300|publisher=Osprey Publishing}}
* {{Citation|last=Turnbull|first=Stephen|year=2002|title=Siege Weapons of the Far East (2) AD 960-1644|publisher=Osprey Publishing}}
{{Refend}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Crossbows}}
{{Wiktionary}}
* [http://www.iau-crossbow.org/ International Crossbow Shooting Union (IAU)]
* [http://www.worldcrossbow.com/ World Crossbow Shooting Association (WCSA)]
* [https://books.google.com/books?id=wXVPAAAAYAAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq The Crossbow by Sir Ralph Payne-Gallwey, BT]
{{-}}
{{Archery |state = collapsed }}
{{Medieval mechanical artillery and hand-held missile weapons |state = collapsed }}

{{Use dmy dates |date = August 2012 }}

[[Category:Ancient weapons]]
[[Category:Medieval weapons]]
[[Category:Chinese inventions]]
[[Category:Crossbows| ]]
[[Category:Heraldic charges]]
[[Category:Bows (archery)]]
[[Category:Renaissance-era weapons]]
[[Category:Weapons of China]]</text>
      <sha1>c466sf7vbkt19vfxihmsyi544xnk98v</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
