  <page>
    <title>Cyclic adenosine monophosphate</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6988</id>
    <revision>
      <id>940055498</id>
      <parentid>937511318</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-10T07:50:03Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>2601:47:0:1E80:7123:71BB:223D:73A5</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Role in eukaryotic cells */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Chembox
| Watchedfields = changed
| verifiedrevid = 476994238
| ImageFile1 = Cyclic-AMPchemdraw.png
| ImageFile2 = Cyclic-adenosine-monophosphate-3D-balls.png
| IUPACName =
| OtherNames =
| Section1 = {{Chembox Identifiers
| ChemSpiderID_Ref = {{chemspidercite|correct|chemspider}}
| ChemSpiderID = 5851
| ChEMBL_Ref = {{ebicite|correct|EBI}}
| ChEMBL = 316966
| UNII_Ref = {{fdacite|correct|FDA}}
| UNII = E0399OZS9N
| InChI = 1/C10H12N5O6P/c11-8-5-9(13-2-12-8)15(3-14-5)10-6(16)7-4(20-10)1-19-22(17,18)21-7/h2-4,6-7,10,16H,1H2,(H,17,18)(H2,11,12,13)/t4-,6-,7-,10-/m1/s1
| InChIKey = IVOMOUWHDPKRLL-KQYNXXCUBU
| StdInChI_Ref = {{stdinchicite|correct|chemspider}}
| StdInChI = 1S/C10H12N5O6P/c11-8-5-9(13-2-12-8)15(3-14-5)10-6(16)7-4(20-10)1-19-22(17,18)21-7/h2-4,6-7,10,16H,1H2,(H,17,18)(H2,11,12,13)/t4-,6-,7-,10-/m1/s1
| StdInChIKey_Ref = {{stdinchicite|correct|chemspider}}
| StdInChIKey = IVOMOUWHDPKRLL-KQYNXXCUSA-N
| CASNo = 60-92-4
| CASNo_Ref = {{cascite|correct|CAS}}
| PubChem = 6076
| IUPHAR_ligand = 2352
| DrugBank_Ref = {{drugbankcite|correct|drugbank}}
| DrugBank = DB02527
| ChEBI_Ref = {{ebicite|correct|EBI}}
| ChEBI = 17489
| KEGG_Ref = {{keggcite|correct|kegg}}
| KEGG = C00575
| SMILES = c1nc(c2c(n1)n(cn2)[C@H]3[C@@H]([C@H]4[C@H](O3)COP(=O)(O4)O)O)N
| MeSHName = Cyclic+AMP
  }}
| Section2 = {{Chembox Properties
| Formula = C&lt;sub&gt;10&lt;/sub&gt;H&lt;sub&gt;11&lt;/sub&gt;N&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;6&lt;/sub&gt;P
| MolarMass = 329.206 g/mol
| Appearance =
| Density =
| MeltingPt =
| BoilingPt =
  }}
| Section3 = {{Chembox Hazards
| MainHazards =
| FlashPt =
| AutoignitionPt =
  }}
}}
'''Cyclic adenosine monophosphate''' ('''cAMP''', '''cyclic AMP''', or '''3',5'-cyclic [[adenosine monophosphate]]''') is a [[second messenger]] important in many biological processes. cAMP is a derivative of  [[adenosine triphosphate]] (ATP) and used for intracellular [[signal transduction]] in many different organisms, conveying the [[cAMP-dependent pathway]].  It should not be confused with '''5'-'''AMP-activated protein kinase ([[AMP-activated protein kinase]]).

==History==
[[Earl Sutherland]] of [[Vanderbilt University]] won a [[Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine]] in 1971 &quot;for his discoveries concerning the mechanisms of the action of hormones&quot;, especially epinephrine, via [[second messenger]]s (such as cyclic adenosine monophosphate, cyclic AMP).

==Synthesis==
Cyclic [[adenosine monophosphate|AMP]] is synthesized from [[Adenosine triphosphate|ATP]] by [[adenylate cyclase]] located on the inner side of the plasma membrane and anchored at various locations in the interior of the cell.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Rahman N, Buck J, Levin LR | date = Nov 2013 | title = pH sensing via bicarbonate-regulated &quot;soluble&quot; adenylate cyclase (sAC) | journal = Front Physiol | volume = 4 | issue = | page = 343 | pmid = 24324443 | pmc=3838963 | doi=10.3389/fphys.2013.00343}}&lt;/ref&gt; Adenylate cyclase is ''activated'' by a range of signaling molecules through the activation of adenylate cyclase stimulatory G ([[Gs alpha subunit|G&lt;sub&gt;s&lt;/sub&gt;]])-protein-coupled receptors. Adenylate cyclase is ''inhibited'' by agonists of adenylate cyclase inhibitory G (G&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;)-protein-coupled receptors. Liver adenylate cyclase responds more strongly to glucagon, and muscle adenylate cyclase responds more strongly to adrenaline.

cAMP decomposition into [[Adenosine monophosphate|AMP]] is catalyzed by the enzyme [[phosphodiesterase]].

==Functions==
cAMP is a second messenger, used for intracellular signal transduction, such as [[Second messenger system|transferring]] into cells the effects of [[hormone]]s like [[glucagon]] and [[adrenaline]], which cannot pass through the plasma membrane. It is also involved in the activation of [[protein kinase]]s.  In addition, cAMP [[Ligand (biochemistry)|binds to]] and regulates the function of [[ion channels]] such as the [[HCN channel]]s and a few other [[Cyclic nucleotide-binding domain|cyclic nucleotide-binding proteins]] such as [[RAPGEF3|Epac1]] and [[RAPGEF2]].

===Role in eukaryotic cells===
{{Main|function of cAMP-dependent protein kinase}}

cAMP is associated with kinases function in several biochemical processes, including the regulation of [[glycogen]], [[sugar]], and [[lipid]] [[metabolism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Ali ES, Hua J, Wilson CH, Tallis GA, Zhou FH, Rychkov GY, Barritt GJ |title=The glucagon-like peptide-1 analogue exendin-4 reverses impaired intracellular Ca2+ signalling in steatotic hepatocytes |journal=Biochimica et Biophysica Acta (BBA) - Molecular Cell Research |doi=10.1016/j.bbamcr.2016.05.006 |pmid=27178543 |volume=1863 |year=2016 |pages=2135–46}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In eukaryotes, cyclic AMP works by activating protein kinase A (PKA, or [[cAMP-dependent protein kinase]]). PKA is normally inactive as a tetrameric [[holoenzyme]], consisting of two [[catalysis|catalytic]] and two regulatory units (C&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;R&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;), with the regulatory units blocking the catalytic centers of the catalytic units.

Cyclic AMP binds to specific locations on the regulatory units of the protein kinase, and causes dissociation between the regulatory and catalytic subunits, thus enabling those catalytic units to [[phosphorylate]] substrate proteins.

The active subunits catalyze the transfer of phosphate from ATP to specific serine or threonine residues of protein substrates. The phosphorylated proteins may act directly on the cell's ion channels, or may become activated or inhibited enzymes. Protein kinase A can also phosphorylate specific proteins that bind to promoter regions of DNA, causing increases in transcription. Not all protein kinases respond to cAMP. Several classes of [[protein kinase]]s, including protein kinase C, are not cAMP-dependent.

Further effects mainly depend on [[function of cAMP-dependent protein kinase|cAMP-dependent protein kinase]], which vary based on the type of cell.

Still, there are some minor PKA-independent functions of cAMP, e.g., activation of [[calcium channel]]s, providing a minor pathway by which [[growth hormone-releasing hormone]] causes a release of [[growth hormone]].&lt;ref name=GeneGlobe&gt;[https://www1.qiagen.com/GeneGlobe/PathwayView.aspx?pathwayID=199 GeneGlobe -&gt; GHRH Signaling]{{dead link|date=August 2017 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }} Retrieved on May 31, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

However, the view that the majority of the effects of cAMP are controlled by PKA is an outdated one. In 1998 a family of cAMP-sensitive proteins with [[guanine nucleotide exchange factor]] (GEF) activity was discovered. These are termed Exchange proteins activated by cAMP (Epac) and the family comprises [[RAPGEF3|Epac1]] and [[RAPGEF4|Epac2]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Bos|first1=Johannes L.|title=Epac proteins: multi-purpose cAMP targets|journal=Trends in Biochemical Sciences|date=December 2006|volume=31|issue=12|pages=680–686|doi=10.1016/j.tibs.2006.10.002|url=|pmid=17084085}}&lt;/ref&gt; The mechanism of activation is similar to that of PKA: the GEF domain is usually masked by the N-terminal region containing the cAMP binding domain. When cAMP binds, the domain dissociates and exposes the now-active GEF domain, allowing Epac to activate small Ras-like GTPase proteins, such as [[Rap1]].

==== Additional role of secreted cAMP in social amoebas ====
{{See also|Fungal behavior}}
In the species ''[[Dictyostelid|Dictyostelium discoideum]]'', cAMP acts outside the cell as a secreted signal.  The [[chemotaxis|chemotactic]] aggregation of cells is organized by periodic waves of cAMP that propagate between cells over distances as large as several centimetres. The waves are the result of a regulated production and secretion of extracellular cAMP and a spontaneous biological oscillator that initiates the waves at centers of territories.{{citation needed|date=April 2016}}

=== Role in bacteria ===
In [[bacteria]], the level of cAMP varies depending on the medium used for growth.  In particular, cAMP is low when glucose is the carbon source.  This occurs through inhibition of the cAMP-producing enzyme, [[adenylate cyclase]], as a side-effect of glucose transport into the cell.  The transcription factor [[cAMP receptor protein]] (CRP) also called [[Catabolite activator protein|CAP (catabolite gene activator protein)]] forms a complex with cAMP and thereby is activated to bind to DNA.  CRP-cAMP increases expression of a large number of genes, including some encoding [[enzyme]]s that can supply energy independent of glucose.

cAMP, for example, is involved in the positive regulation of the [[lac operon]]. In an environment with a low glucose concentration, cAMP accumulates and binds to the allosteric site on CRP ([[cAMP receptor protein]]), a transcription activator protein. The protein assumes its active shape and binds to a specific site upstream of the lac promoter, making it easier for RNA polymerase to bind to the adjacent promoter to start transcription of the lac operon, increasing the rate of lac operon transcription. With a high glucose concentration, the cAMP concentration decreases, and the CRP disengages from the lac operon.

==Pathology==
Since cyclic AMP is a second messenger and plays vital role in cell signalling, it has been implicated in various disorders but not restricted to the roles given below:

=== Role in human carcinoma ===
Some research has suggested that a deregulation of cAMP pathways and an aberrant activation of cAMP-controlled genes is linked to the growth of some cancers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://cancerres.aacrjournals.org/cgi/content/full/64/4/1338 American Association for Cancer Research (cAMP-responsive Genes and Tumor Progression)]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://cancerres.aacrjournals.org/cgi/content/abstract/66/19/9483 American Association for Cancer Research (cAMP Dysregulation and Melonoma)]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://clincancerres.aacrjournals.org/cgi/content/abstract/2/1/201 American Association for Cancer Research (cAMP-binding Proteins' Presence in Tumors)]&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Role in prefrontal cortex disorders ===
Recent research suggests that cAMP affects the function of higher-order thinking in the [[prefrontal cortex]] through its regulation of ion channels called [[hyperpolarization-activated cyclic nucleotide-gated channels]] (HCN). When cAMP stimulates the HCN, the channels open, closing the brain cell to communication and thus interfering with the function of the [[prefrontal cortex]]. This research, especially the cognitive deficits in age-related illnesses and ADHD, is of interest to researchers studying the brain.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2007/04/070420143324.htm ScienceDaily ::Brain Networks Strengthened By Closing Ion Channels, Research Could Lead To ADHD Treatment ]&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==

* [[Cyclic guanosine monophosphate]] (cGMP)
* [[8-Bromoadenosine 3',5'-cyclic monophosphate]] (8-Br-cAMP)
* [[Acrasin]] specific to chemotactic use in ''Dictyostelium discoideum''.
* [[phosphodiesterase 4]] (PDE 4) which degrades cAMP

==References==
&lt;references /&gt;

==Additional images==
&lt;gallery&gt;
 Image:CAMP.PNG|cAMP represented in three ways
 Image:ATP chemical structure.png|[[Adenosine triphosphate]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;

{{Intracellular signaling peptides and proteins}}
{{Nucleobases, nucleosides, and nucleotides}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Cyclic Adenosine Monophosphate}}
[[Category:Nucleotides]]
[[Category:Signal transduction]]
[[Category:Cell signaling]]
[[Category:Cyclic nucleotides]]</text>
      <sha1>3r23y1z5lipqrulv70n2cfbvlmpcp9p</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
