  <page>
    <title>Crowded House</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6927</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941720261</id>
      <parentid>941705261</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-20T06:54:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Shaidar cuebiyar</username>
        <id>3858451</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Awards */ update/reword lead-in sectn;</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{About|the rock group, Crowded House|their debut album|Crowded House (album)|the racehorse|Crowded House (horse)}}
{{short description|Pop rock band from New Zealand/Australia}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2020}}
{{Use Australian English|date=August 2013}}
{{Infobox musical artist
| name             = Crowded House
| image            = Crowded House.jpg
| alt              = Five men are standing close together on a stage and smiling. First male at left is bearded and has right arm raised to shoulder height. Second male has arms around shoulders of his neighbours and is partly obscured by a microphone stand. Third male has left hand raised overhead. Fourth male has arms at side and is looking to his left. Fifth male has right arm over his neighbour and left arm overhead. Last two are partly obscured by a keyboard and its stand. Behind the five men is more band equipment and the background contains considerable English text.
| caption          = Crowded House, August 2007 (L–R)&lt;br/&gt; Liam Finn, Matt Sherrod, Mark Hart, Neil Finn, Nick Seymour
| landscape        = yes
| background       = group_or_band
| origin           = [[Melbourne]], [[Victoria (Australia)|Victoria]], Australia
| genre            = {{flatlist|
*[[Rock music|Rock]]
*[[pop rock]]
*[[jangle pop]]
*[[indie rock]]
*[[alternative rock]]
*[[new wave music|new wave]]}}
| years_active     = {{Start date|1985}}–1996, {{Start date|2006}}–2011, {{Start date|2016}}, {{Start date|2019}}–{{Start date|present}}
| label            = {{flatlist|
*[[Capitol Records|Capitol]]
*[[ATO Records|ATO]]}}
| associated_acts  = {{flatlist|
*[[Split Enz]]
*[[Finn Brothers]]
*[[Tarmac Adam]]}}
| alias            = [[The Mullanes]] &lt;small&gt;(1985)&lt;/small&gt;
| website          = 
| current_members  = [[Neil Finn]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Nick Seymour]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Mitchell Froom]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Liam Finn]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Elroy Finn]]
| past_members     = [[Craig Hooper]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Paul Hester]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Tim Finn]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Peter Jones (drummer)|Peter Jones]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Mark Hart]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Matt Sherrod]]
}}
'''Crowded House''' is a [[rock music|rock]] band, formed in [[Melbourne]], [[Australia]], in 1985. Its founding members were New Zealander [[Neil Finn]] (vocalist, guitarist, primary songwriter) and Australians [[Paul Hester]] (drums) and [[Nick Seymour]] (bass). Later band members included Neil Finn's brother, [[Tim Finn]], and Americans [[Mark Hart]] and [[Matt Sherrod]].&lt;ref name=&quot;McF&quot;&gt;McFarlane (1999)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=denton&gt;[http://www.abc.net.au/tv/enoughrope/transcripts/s1979899.htm &quot;Neil Finn and Nick Seymour&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110817105338/http://www.abc.net.au/tv/enoughrope/transcripts/s1979899.htm |date=17 August 2011 }} ''[[Australian Broadcasting Corporation]]'' – 16 July 2007&lt;/ref&gt; Neil Finn and Seymour have been the sole constant members of the group since its formation.

Originally active from 1985 to 1996, Crowded House had consistent commercial and critical success in Australia and New Zealand&lt;ref name=&quot;Kent&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title=[[Kent Music Report|Australian Chart Book 1970–1992]]|last=Kent|first=David|authorlink=David Kent (historian)|publisher=Australian Chart Book Ltd|location=St Ives, New South Wales|year=1993|isbn=0-646-11917-6}} (NOTE: Used for Australian Singles and Albums charts from 1974 until [[Australian Recording Industry Association|ARIA]] created their own [[ARIA Charts|charts]] in mid-1988. In 1992, Kent back calculated chart positions for 1970–1974)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AusCharts&quot;&gt;[http://australian-charts.com/showinterpret.asp?interpret=Crowded+House &quot;Discography Crowded House&quot;] australiancharts.com&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NZCharts&quot;&gt;[https://charts.nz/showinterpret.asp?interpret=Crowded+House &quot;Discography Crowded House&quot;] ''charts.org.nz''&lt;/ref&gt; and international chart success in two phases, beginning with a [[Crowded House (album)|self-titled debut album]] that reached number twelve on the [[Billboard 200|US Album Chart]] in 1987 and provided the Top Ten hits &quot;[[Don't Dream It's Over]]&quot; and &quot;[[Something So Strong]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;AllmusicSingle&quot;&gt;[{{Allmusic|class=artist|id=p3998/charts-awards/billboard-singles|pure_url=yes}} &quot;Crowded House &gt; Charts &amp; Awards &gt; Billboard Singles&quot;] [[AllMusic]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AllmusicAlbum&quot;&gt;[{{Allmusic|class=artist|id=p3998/charts-awards/billboard-albums|pure_url=yes}} &quot;Crowded House &gt; Charts &amp; Awards &gt; Billboard Albums&quot;] AllMusic&lt;/ref&gt; Further international success came in the UK, Europe and South Africa with their third and fourth albums (''[[Woodface]]'' and ''[[Together Alone]]'') and the compilation album ''[[Recurring Dream]]'', which included the hits &quot;[[Fall at Your Feet]]&quot;, &quot;[[Weather with You]]&quot;, &quot;[[Distant Sun]]&quot;, &quot;[[Locked Out (song)|Locked Out]]&quot;, &quot;[[Instinct (song)|Instinct]]&quot; and &quot;[[Not the Girl You Think You Are]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;sss&quot;&gt;Bourke (1997)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.officialcharts.com/artists/ &quot;Artists &gt; Crowded House&quot;] ''Chart Stats''&lt;/ref&gt; Neil and Tim Finn were each awarded an [[Order of the British Empire|OBE]] in June 1993 for their contributions to the music of New Zealand.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hunkin&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nzherald.co.nz/entertainment/news/article.cfm?c_id=1501119&amp;objectid=10437512&amp;pnum=1 |title=Finn 'sick' of PM grabbing music glory |author=Hunkin, Joanna |date=3 May 2007 |work=[[The New Zealand Herald]] |accessdate=26 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 1996, Crowded House announced that it would disband. The band played several farewell concerts that year, including the &quot;[[Farewell to the World]]&quot; concerts in Melbourne and Sydney.&lt;ref name=&quot;McF&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;sss&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;linernotes&quot;/&gt; On 26 March 2005, Hester died by suicide, aged 46.&lt;ref name=hessie&gt;Bernard Zuel, Nassim Khadem, Patrick Donovan, James Button [https://www.smh.com.au/articles/2005/03/28/1111862327689.html &quot;Farewell to the clown prince&quot;] ''[[The Sydney Morning Herald]]'' – 29 March 2005&lt;/ref&gt; In 2006, the group re-formed with drummer Matt Sherrod and released two further albums (in 2007 and 2010), each of which reached number one on Australia's [[ARIA Charts|album chart]].&lt;ref name=&quot;AusCharts&quot;/&gt;

As of July 2010, Crowded House had sold 10 million albums.&lt;ref name=&quot;ARIA 2010&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.aria.com.au/pages/documents/ARIA1ChartAwardsareafamilyaffairandARIAcelebratestheAustralianartistsoftheDecade.pdf | title = ARIA #1 Chart Awards Are a Family Affair! | first1 = Rina | last1 = Ferris | first2 = Kristyn | last2 = Brennan | first3 = Ferris | last3 = Davies | publisher = Australian Recording Industry Association | date = 22 July 2010 | accessdate = 28 October 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In November 2016, the band was inducted into the [[ARIA Hall of Fame]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.smh.com.au/entertainment/music/crowded-house-to-enter-aria-hall-of-fame-20160904-gr8n61.html=|title=Crowded House to enter ARIA Hall Of Fame|publisher=Sydney Morning Herald|work=– AAP |date=5 September 2016|accessdate=5 September 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After several years of inactivity, it was announced a revised line-up of Crowded House will tour the UK in 2020. The new line-up features Neil Finn, Nick Seymour, [[Mitchell Froom]], and Finn's sons Liam and Elroy.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.uncut.co.uk/news/crowded-house-reunite-for-2020-uk-tour-122511&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
Neil Finn (vocals, guitar, piano) and drummer Paul Hester (ex-[[The Cheks]], [[Deckchairs Overboard]]) were former members of New Zealand band [[Split Enz]], which spent part of 1975–6 in Australia and several years in England.&lt;ref name=&quot;McF&quot;/&gt; Neil Finn is the younger brother of Split Enz founding member Tim Finn, who joined Crowded House in 1990 on vocals, guitars and keyboards for the album ''[[Woodface]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;McF&quot;/&gt; Bassist Nick Seymour (ex-Plays with Marionettes, Bang, The Horla) is the younger brother of singer-songwriter and guitarist [[Mark Seymour]]&lt;ref name=&quot;McF&quot;/&gt; of Australian rock group [[Hunters &amp; Collectors]].&lt;ref name=&quot;sss&quot;/&gt;

===Formation and name change (1984–1986)===
{{Main|Split Enz|The Mullanes}}
Finn and Hester decided to form a new band during the first Split Enz farewell tour, &quot;Enz with a Bang&quot;, in late 1984.&lt;ref name=&quot;McF&quot;/&gt; Seymour approached Finn during the after party for the Melbourne show and asked if he could audition for the new band.&lt;ref name=&quot;sss&quot;/&gt; '''The Mullanes''' formed in Melbourne in early 1985 with Finn, Hester, Seymour and guitarist [[Craig Hooper]] (ex-[[The Reels]]) and first performed on 11 June.&lt;ref name=&quot;McF&quot;/&gt; They secured a record contract with [[Capitol Records]], but Hooper left the band before the remaining trio moved to Los Angeles to record their debut album.&lt;ref name=&quot;McF&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Howl&quot;&gt;[[Ed Nimmervoll|Nimmervoll, Ed]], [http://pandora.nla.gov.au/pan/14231/20120727-0512/www.howlspace.com.au/en/crowdedhouse/crowdedhouse.htm &quot;Crowded House&quot;]. HowlSpace – The Living History of Our Music (Ed Nimmervoll). Archived from [http://www.howlspace.com.au/en/crowdedhouse/crowdedhouse.htm the original] on 27 July 2012. Retrieved 22 January 2014.&lt;/ref&gt; At Capitol's behest, the band's name was changed to Crowded House, which alluded to the lack of space at the small [[Hollywood Hills]] house they shared during the recording of the album ''[[Crowded House (album)|Crowded House]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;McF&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Howl&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Chris Bourke|title=Crowded House: Something So Strong|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=VW72AwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT128|year=2014|publisher=Pan Macmillan Australia|isbn=978-1-76008-174-4|page=128}}&lt;/ref&gt; Former Split Enz keyboardist Eddie Rayner produced the track &quot;Can't Carry On&quot; and was asked to join the band. He toured with them in 1988, but was unable to become a full member due to family commitments.{{Clear}}

===Early albums (1986–1990)===
{{Main|Crowded House (album)|Temple of Low Men}}
[[File:Crowded-house1.JPG|thumb|alt=Three men are standing in front of posters advertising the band. Man at left is wearing sunglasses, smiling and adjusting his dark jacket. Man in middle is staring to his left and wears a similar dark jacket. Third man is also staring to his left and has a dark jacket.|left|Crowded House, San Francisco, April 1987. L to R: Paul Hester, Neil Finn, Nick Seymour]]Thanks to their Split Enz connection, the newly formed Crowded House had an established [[Australasia]]n fanbase.&lt;ref name=&quot;McF&quot;/&gt; They began by playing at festivals in Australia and New Zealand and released their debut album, ''Crowded House'', in August 1986.&lt;ref name=&quot;McF&quot;/&gt; Capitol Records initially failed to see the band's potential and gave them only low-key promotion,&lt;ref name=&quot;sss&quot;/&gt; forcing the band to play at small venues to try and gain attention. The album's first single, &quot;[[Mean to Me (Crowded House song)|Mean to Me]]&quot;, reached the Australian [[Kent Music Report]] Singles Chart top 30 in June.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kent&quot;/&gt; It failed to chart in the US,&lt;ref name=&quot;AllmusicSingle&quot;/&gt; but moderate American airplay introduced US listeners to the group.

A single, &quot;[[Don't Dream It's Over]]&quot;, was released in December 1986 and proved an international hit, reaching number two on the US [[Billboard Hot 100|''Billboard'' Hot 100]]&lt;ref name=&quot;AllmusicSingle&quot;/&gt; and number one in Canada.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.collectionscanada.gc.ca/rpm/028020-119.01-e.php?&amp;file_num=nlc008388.0804&amp;volume=46&amp;issue=4&amp;issue_dt=May%2002%201987&amp;type=1&amp;interval=24&amp;PHPSESSID=50lgngc1daom80fs32cjjs9ne6 &quot;Top Singles – Volume 46, No.&amp;nbsp;4, May&amp;nbsp;02&amp;nbsp;1987&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121019145310/http://www.collectionscanada.gc.ca/rpm/028020-119.01-e.php?&amp;file_num=nlc008388.0804&amp;volume=46&amp;issue=4&amp;issue_dt=May%2002%201987&amp;type=1&amp;interval=24&amp;PHPSESSID=50lgngc1daom80fs32cjjs9ne6 |date=19 October 2012 }} ''Library and Archives Canada''&lt;/ref&gt; New Zealand radio stations initially gave the song little support until months later when it became successful internationally.{{citation needed|date=November 2014}} Ultimately, the song reached number one on the [[Recording Industry Association of New Zealand|New Zealand singles chart]] and number eight in Australia.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kent&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NZCharts&quot;/&gt; It remains the group's most commercially successful song.

In March 1987, the group were awarded &quot;Best New Talent&quot;, along with &quot;[[ARIA Award for Song of the Year|Song of the Year]]&quot; and &quot;Best Video&quot; awards for &quot;Don't Dream It's Over&quot; at the [[ARIA Music Awards of 1987|inaugural ARIA Music Awards]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ARIA List&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ariaawards.com.au/history-by-artist.php?letter=C&amp;artist=Crowded%20House|title=Artist: Crowded House|publisher=[[Australian Recording Industry Association|ARIA]]|access-date=13 December 2009|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110726203141/http://ariaawards.com.au/history-by-artist.php?letter=C&amp;artist=Crowded%20House|archive-date=26 July 2011|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; The video also earned the group the [[MTV Video Music Award for Best New Artist]] that year.&lt;ref name=mtv87&gt;[http://www.mtv.com/ontv/vma/1987/ &quot;MTV Music Video Awards 1987&quot;] ''[[MTV Video Music Awards|MTV]]'' – NOTE: Click on &quot;winners&quot; tab&lt;/ref&gt; The song has often been [[cover version|covered]] by other artists and gave [[Paul Young (singer and guitarist)|Paul Young]] a hit single in 1991. It was also used for a [[Tourism New Zealand|New Zealand Tourism Board]] advertisement in its &quot;100% Pure New Zealand&quot; worldwide promotion from October 2005.&lt;ref&gt;[http://christchurchcitylibraries.com/Music/AdvertMusic/T/ &quot;Music used in New Zealand Television Commercials: T&quot;] ''[[Christchurch City Libraries]]'' Note: Scroll down to &quot;Tourism New Zealand&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; In May 2001, &quot;Don't Dream it's Over&quot; was voted seventh in a poll of the [[APRA Top 30 Australian songs|best Australian songs]] of all time by the [[Australasian Performing Right Association]].&lt;ref name=&quot;APRA10&quot;&gt;[http://www.apra-amcos.com.au/APRAAwards/MusicAwards/History/2001Top10Songs.aspx &quot;2001 – Top 10 Songs&quot;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100611003021/http://www.apra-amcos.com.au/APRAAwards/MusicAwards/History/2001Top10Songs.aspx |date=11 June 2010 }} [[Australasian Performing Right Association|APRA]] – 28 May 2001&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Ch-montreux.jpg|thumb|right|alt=Three men are sitting at a small table. Man at left is holding sunglasses in his right hand, smiling, leaning forward and looking to his right. Man in middle has elbows on a brief case, gesturing with upraised hands, right hand is holding sunglasses, he is looking to his left. Third man has a small cup held to his lips by his right hand.|The band at the [[Montreux]] Pop Festival, May 1988. L to R: Seymour, Finn, Hester]]In June 1987, nearly a year after its release, ''Crowded House'' finally reached number one on the Kent Music Report Album Charts.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kent&quot;/&gt; It also reached number three in New Zealand&lt;ref name=&quot;NZCharts&quot;/&gt; and number twelve on the US [[Billboard (magazine)|''Billboard'']] album chart.&lt;ref name=&quot;AllmusicAlbum&quot;/&gt; The follow-up to &quot;Don't Dream it's Over&quot;, &quot;[[Something So Strong]]&quot;, was another global smash, reaching the Top 10 in New Zealand,&lt;ref name=&quot;NZCharts&quot;/&gt; America,&lt;ref name=&quot;AllmusicSingle&quot;/&gt; and Canada. &quot;[[World Where You Live]]&quot; and &quot;Now We're Getting Somewhere&quot; were also released as singles with chart success.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kent&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AllmusicSingle&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;sss&quot;/&gt;

As the band's primary songwriter, Neil Finn was under pressure to create a second album to match their debut and the band joked that one potential title for the new release was ''Mediocre Follow-Up''.&lt;ref name=&quot;sss&quot;/&gt; Eventually titled ''Temple of Low Men'', their second album was released in July 1988 with strong promotion by Capitol Records. The album did not fare as well as their debut in the US, only reaching number 40,&lt;ref name=&quot;AllmusicAlbum&quot;/&gt; but it achieved Australasian success, reaching number one in [[ARIA Charts|Australia]]&lt;ref name=&quot;AusCharts&quot;/&gt; and number two in New Zealand.&lt;ref name=&quot;NZCharts&quot;/&gt; The first single &quot;[[Better Be Home Soon]]&quot; peaked at number two on both Australian and New Zealand singles charts&lt;ref name=&quot;AusCharts&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NZCharts&quot;/&gt; and reached top 50 in the US,&lt;ref name=&quot;AllmusicSingle&quot;/&gt; though the following four singles were less successful.&lt;ref name=&quot;AusCharts&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NZCharts&quot;/&gt; Crowded House undertook a short tour of Australia and Canada to promote the album, with Eddie Rayner on keyboards. Multi-instrumentalist Mark Hart, who would eventually become a full band member, replaced Rayner in January 1989. After the tour, Finn fired Seymour from the band.&lt;ref name=denton/&gt; [[Music journalist]] [[Ed Nimmervoll]] claimed that Seymour's temporary departure was because Finn blamed him for causing his [[writer's block]];&lt;ref name=&quot;Howl&quot;/&gt; however, Finn cited &quot;artistic differences&quot; as the reason.&lt;ref name=denton/&gt; Seymour said that after a month he contacted Finn and they agreed that he would return to the band.&lt;ref name=denton/&gt;

===Early nineties (1991–1994)===
{{Main|Tim Finn|Woodface|Together Alone}}
[[File:MarkHartCrop.jpg|thumb|right|Multi-instrumentalist Mark Hart]]

Crowded House took a break after the Canadian leg of the ''Temple of Low Men'' tour. Neil Finn and his brother Tim recorded songs they had co-written for their own album, ''[[Finn (album)|Finn]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;sss&quot;/&gt; Following the recording sessions with Tim, Neil began writing and recording a third Crowded House album with Hester and Seymour, but these tracks were rejected by the record company, so Neil asked Tim if Crowded House could use the ''Finn'' songs. Tim jokingly agreed on the proviso that he become a member, which Neil apparently took figuratively. With Tim as an official member, the band returned to the studio. The new tracks, as well as some from the previously rejected recordings were combined to make ''Woodface'', which was released in July 1991. The album features eight tracks co-written by Neil and Tim,&lt;ref name=&quot;sss&quot;/&gt; which feature the brothers [[harmony|harmonising]] on lead vocals, except on the sombre &quot;All I Ask&quot; on which Tim sang lead. The track was later used on AIDS awareness commercials in Australia.&lt;ref name=&quot;sss&quot;/&gt; Five of the album's tracks were Neil's solo compositions and two were by Hester, the exuberant &quot;Italian Plastic&quot;, which became a crowd favourite at concerts&lt;ref name=&quot;sss&quot;/&gt; and the [[hidden track]] &quot;I'm Still Here&quot;.

&quot;[[Chocolate Cake (song)|Chocolate Cake]]&quot;, a humorous comment on American excesses that was not taken well by some US critics and sections of the American public, was released in June 1991 as the first single. Perhaps unsurprisingly it failed to chart in the US; however, it reached number two on Billboard's [[Alternative Songs|Modern Rock Tracks]] chart.&lt;ref name=&quot;AllmusicSingle&quot;/&gt; The song peaked at number seven in New Zealand and reached the top 20 in Australia.&lt;ref name=&quot;AusCharts&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NZCharts&quot;/&gt; The second single, &quot;[[Fall at Your Feet]]&quot;, was less successful in Australia and New Zealand but did at least reach the US [[Billboard Hot 100|Hot 100]].&lt;ref name=&quot;AllmusicSingle&quot;/&gt; The album reached number one in New Zealand,&lt;ref name=&quot;NZCharts&quot;/&gt; number two in Australia,&lt;ref name=&quot;AusCharts&quot;/&gt; number six in the UK&lt;ref name=&quot;UKCharts&quot;&gt;[https://www.officialcharts.com/artists/ &quot;Chart Stats – Crowded House&quot;] ''Chart Stats''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|first=David|last=Roberts|year=2006|title=[[British Hit Singles &amp; Albums]]|edition=19th|publisher=[[Guinness World Records|Guinness]]|location=London, UK|isbn=1-904994-10-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; and made the top 20 in several European countries.&lt;ref&gt;[http://norwegiancharts.com/showinterpret.asp?interpret=Crowded+House &quot;Discography Crowded House&quot;] norwegiancharts.com&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://swedishcharts.com/showinterpret.asp?interpret=Crowded+House &quot;Discography Crowded House&quot;] swedishcharts.com&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://dutchcharts.nl/showinterpret.asp?interpret=Crowded+House &quot;Discografie Crowded House&quot;] dutchcharts.nl&lt;/ref&gt; The third single from ''Woodface'', &quot;[[Weather With You]]&quot;, peaked at No.&amp;nbsp;7 in early 1992 giving the band their highest UK chart placement. By contrast, the album had limited success in the US, only reaching number 83 on the Billboard 200 Album Chart.&lt;ref name=&quot;AllmusicAlbum&quot;/&gt;

Tim Finn left Crowded House during the ''Woodface'' tour in November 1991, part-way through the UK leg.&lt;ref name=&quot;McF&quot;/&gt; Performances on this tour, at the Town and Country Club in London, were recorded live and given a limited release in Australia, while individual songs from those shows were released as B-sides of singles in some countries.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.amws.com.au/c/crowded-house/discography/discography.html &quot;Crowded House Discography&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110301195153/http://www.amws.com.au/c/crowded-house/discography/discography.html |date=1 March 2011 }} ''amws.com.au'' – 12 January 1994&lt;/ref&gt; In June 1993 the [[Politics of New Zealand|New Zealand Government]] recommended that the Queen award an OBE to Neil and Tim Finn for their contribution to the music of New Zealand.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hunkin&quot;/&gt;

For their fourth album, ''Together Alone'', Crowded House used producer [[Youth (producer)|Martin Glover (aka &quot;Youth&quot;)]] and invited touring musician Mark Hart (guitar and keyboards) to become a permanent band member.&lt;ref name=&quot;McF&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Howl&quot;/&gt; The album was recorded at [[Karekare, New Zealand|Karekare]] Beach, New Zealand, which gave its name to the opening track, &quot;Kare Kare&quot;. The album was released in October 1993 and sold well internationally on the strength of lead single &quot;[[Distant Sun]]&quot; and followup &quot;[[Private Universe]]&quot;. It topped the New Zealand Album Chart,&lt;ref name=&quot;NZCharts&quot;/&gt; reached number 2 in Australia&lt;ref name=&quot;AusCharts&quot;/&gt; and number 4 in the UK.&lt;ref name=&quot;UKCharts&quot;/&gt; &quot;[[Locked Out (song)|Locked Out]]&quot; was the album's first US single and received airplay on MTV and [[VH1]]. This track and &quot;[[My Sharona]]&quot; by [[The Knack]], which were both included on the soundtrack of the film ''[[Reality Bites]]'', were bundled together on a [[jukebox]] single to promote the film soundtrack.&lt;ref name=&quot;sss&quot;/&gt;

===Saying farewell (1994–1996)===
{{Main|Finn (album)|Recurring Dream|Farewell to the World}}
[[File:Crowded kroon.jpg|thumb|right|alt=Two men holding guitars onstage. Man at left is looking downwards, right hand strummings strings, left hand on fret board. Second man is half turned with his left hand high on the fret board.|Crowded House at the Café De Kroon, [[Amsterdam]], June 1996. Neil Finn (left) and Mark Hart]]

Crowded House were midway through a US tour when Paul Hester quit the band on 15 April 1994.&lt;ref name=&quot;Howl&quot;/&gt; He flew home to Melbourne to await the birth of his first child and indicated that he required more time with his family.&lt;ref name=&quot;McF&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Howl&quot;/&gt; [[Wally Ingram]], drummer for support act [[Sheryl Crow]], temporarily filled in&lt;ref name=&quot;Howl&quot;/&gt; until a replacement, [[Peter Jones (drummer)|Peter Jones]] (ex-Harem Scarem, [[Vince Jones]], [[Kate Ceberano]]'s Septet) was found.&lt;ref name=&quot;McF&quot;/&gt; After the tour, the [[Finn Brothers]] released their album ''Finn'' in November 1995. In June 1996, at a press conference to announce the release of their greatest hits album ''[[Recurring Dream (album)|Recurring Dream]]'', Neil revealed that Crowded House were to disband. The June 1996 concerts in Europe and Canada were to be their final performances.&lt;ref name=&quot;sss&quot;/&gt;

''Recurring Dream'' contained four songs from each of the band's studio albums, along with three new songs. The album debuted at number one in Australia,&lt;ref name=&quot;AusCharts&quot;/&gt; New Zealand&lt;ref name=&quot;NZCharts&quot;/&gt; and the UK&lt;ref name=&quot;UKCharts&quot;/&gt; in July 1996. Early copies included a bonus CD of live material. The album's three new songs, which were released as singles, were &quot;[[Instinct (song)|Instinct]]&quot;, &quot;[[Not the Girl You Think You Are]]&quot; and &quot;[[Everything Is Good for You]]&quot;, which featured backing vocals from [[Pearl Jam]]'s [[Eddie Vedder]]. Paul Hester returned to the band to play drums on the three new tracks.&lt;ref&gt;Green, Peter &amp; Post, Liz [http://www.frenz.com/crowdedhouse/timeline.html &quot;Timeline – The Crowded House Refresher Course&quot;] frenz.com&lt;/ref&gt;

Worried that their goodbye had been too low-key and had disregarded their home fans, the band performed the ''Farewell to the World'' concert on the steps of the [[Sydney Opera House]] on 24 November 1996, which raised funds for the [[Sydney Children's Hospital]]. The concert featured the line-up of Neil Finn, Nick Seymour, Mark Hart and Paul Hester. Tim Finn and Peter Jones both made guest appearances. Support bands on the day were [[Custard (band)|Custard]], [[Powderfinger]] and [[You Am I]]. The concert had one of the highest live audiences in Australian history with the crowd being estimated at between 120,000 and 250,000 people.&lt;ref name=&quot;sss&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;linernotes&quot;&gt;{{cite AV media notes|title=Farewell to the World|titlelink=Farewell to the World|others=Crowded House|year=2006|first=David |last=Hepworth |authorlink=David Hepworth |publisher=[[Parlophone]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Farewell to the World'' was released on VHS in December 1996. In 2007, a double CD and a DVD were issued as to commemorate the concert's tenth anniversary. The DVD featured newly recorded audio commentary by Finn, Hart and Seymour and other new bonus material.&lt;ref name=&quot;linernotes&quot;/&gt;

===Between farewell and reunion (1996–2006)===
{{Main|Afterglow (Crowded House album)|Deadstar|7 Worlds Collide|Everyone Is Here|Tarmac Adam}}
[[File:Paul-hester-sf-np1.jpg|thumb|left|Paul Hester (1959–2005)]]Following the 1996 break-up of Crowded House, the members embarked upon a variety of projects. Neil Finn released two solo studio albums, ''[[Try Whistling This]]'' (1998) and ''[[One Nil]]'' (2001), as well as two live albums, ''[[Sessions at West 54th (Neil Finn album)|Sessions at West 54th]]'' (2000) and ''[[7 Worlds Collide (album)|7 Worlds Collide]]'' (2001). ''7 Worlds Collide'' saw him performing with guest musicians including [[Eddie Vedder]], [[Johnny Marr]], [[Ed O'Brien]] and [[Phil Selway]] of [[Radiohead]], Tim Finn, Sebastian Steinberg, [[Lisa Germano]] and Betchadupa (featuring his son [[Liam Finn]]). A double CD and DVD of the shows were released in November 2001.

Tim Finn had resumed his solo career after leaving the group in 1992 and he also worked with Neil on a second [[Finn Brothers]] album, ''[[Everyone Is Here]]'', which was released in 2004. Paul Hester joined The Finn Brothers on stage for three songs at their Palais Theatre show in Melbourne at the end of 2004. Nick Seymour also joined them on stage in Dublin, where he was living, in 2004. Peter Jones and Nick Seymour joined Australian group [[Deadstar]] for their second album, ''Milk'', in 1997. Seymour later worked as a record producer in Dublin, producing Irish group [[Bell X1]]'s debut album, ''[[Neither Am I]]'' in 2000. Mark Hart rejoined [[Supertramp]] in the late 1990s and later toured with [[Ringo Starr &amp; His All-Starr Band]]. In 2001 he released a solo album, ''Nada Sonata''.&lt;ref&gt;[{{AllMusic|class=album|id=r1214006|pure_url=yes}} &quot;Nada Sonata &gt; Overview&quot;] AllMusic&lt;/ref&gt;

Paul Hester worked with children's entertainers [[The Wiggles]], playing &quot;Paul the Cook&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0376988/fullcredits#cast|title=The Wiggles: Yummy Yummy (Video 1994)|publisher=IMDb}}&lt;/ref&gt; He also had his own [[Australian Broadcasting Corporation|ABC]] show ''Hessie's Shed'' in Australia from late 1997.&lt;ref name=&quot;McF&quot;/&gt; He formed the band Largest Living Things,&lt;ref name=&quot;McF&quot;/&gt; which was the name rejected by Capitol Records in favour of Crowded House.&lt;ref name=hessie/&gt; It was on ''Hessie's Shed'' that Finn, Hester and Seymour last shared a stage, on an episode filmed as part of Finn's promotion for his solo album ''Try Whistling This'' in 1998. Finn and Hester performed &quot;[[Not the Girl You Think You Are]]&quot; with Largest Living Things, before being joined by Seymour for &quot;[[Sister Madly]]&quot; and a version of [[Paul Kelly (Australian musician)|Paul Kelly]]'s &quot;[[Leaps and Bounds (song)|Leaps and Bounds]]&quot;, which also featured Kelly on vocals. In late 2003, Hester hosted the series ''Music Max's Sessions''. Hester and Seymour were reunited when they both joined singer-songwriter Matt O'Donnell's Melbourne-based group [[Tarmac Adam]].&lt;ref&gt;Holmgren, Magnus [https://web.archive.org/web/20120220031552/http://hem2.passagen.se/honga/database/h/hesterpaul.html &quot;Paul Hester&quot;] ''[[Australian Rock Database]]'' ''Passagen.se'' (Magnus Holmgren). Archived from [http://hem2.passagen.se/honga/database/h/hesterpaul.html the original] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120220031552/http://hem2.passagen.se/honga/database/h/hesterpaul.html |date=20 February 2012 }} on 20 February 2012. Retrieved 11 February 2014.&lt;/ref&gt; The band released one album, 2003's ''Handheld Torch'', which was produced by Seymour.

In May 1999 Crowded House issued a compilation of unreleased songs, ''[[Afterglow (Crowded House album)|Afterglow]]'', which included the track &quot;Recurring Dream&quot;, recorded when the group were still called The Mullanes and included Craig Hooper on guitar.&lt;ref name=&quot;McF&quot;/&gt; The album's liner notes included information about the songs, written by music journalist [[David Hepworth]]. Some limited-release versions included a second CD with songwriting commentary by Finn. The liner notes confirmed that Crowded House had no plans to reunite at that time.&lt;ref name=&quot;McF&quot;/&gt; A 2003 compilation album, ''[[Classic Masters (Crowded House album)|Classic Masters]]'', was released only in the US, while 2005 saw the release of the album ''[[She Will Have Her Way]]'', a collection of cover versions of Crowded House, Split Enz, Tim Finn and Finn Brothers songs by Australasian female artists. The album reached the top 5 in Australia and New Zealand.&lt;ref&gt;[https://charts.nz/showitem.asp?interpret=&amp;titel=She+Will+Have+Her+Way+%2D+The+Songs+Of+Tim+%26+Neil+Finn&amp;cat=a &quot;She Will Have Her Way – The Songs Of Tim &amp; Neil Finn (Album)&quot;] ''charts.org.nz''&lt;/ref&gt;

On 26 March 2005 Paul Hester was found dead, after hanging himself from a tree in a park near his home in Melbourne. He was 46&amp;nbsp;years old. His obituary in ''[[The Sydney Morning Herald]]'' stated that he had fought &quot;a long battle with depression.&quot;&lt;ref name=hessie/&gt; Following the news of Hester's death, Nick Seymour joined The Finn Brothers on stage at the [[Royal Albert Hall]] in London, where the three played in memory of Paul. A snare drum with a top hat on it stood at the front of the stage as a tribute.&lt;ref&gt;Button, James [http://www.theage.com.au/news/Music/The-show-goes-on/2005/03/29/1111862390124.html &quot;The show goes on in memory of Hester&quot;] ''[[The Age]]'' – 30 March 2005&lt;/ref&gt; Writing in 2010 Neil Finn said, &quot;When we lost Paul it was like someone pulled the rug out from underneath everything, a terrible jolt out of the dark blue. He was the best drummer I had ever played with and for many years, my closest friend.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.concordmusicgroup.com/artists/Crowded-House/ &quot;About Crowded House&quot;] concordmusicgroup.com&lt;/ref&gt;

===Reunion and ''Time on Earth'' (2006–2009)===
{{Main|Time on Earth|Matt Sherrod}}
[[File:Matt Sherrod Crowded House Dublin 220607.jpg|thumb|right|Matt Sherrod, Dublin, 2007]]In 2006 Neil Finn asked Nick Seymour to play bass on his third solo album. Seymour agreed and the two joined up with producer and multi-instrumentalist [[Ethan Johns]] to begin recording.&lt;ref name=&quot;Howl&quot;/&gt; As the recording sessions progressed it was decided that the album would be issued under the Crowded House band name, rather than as a Neil Finn solo album. In January 2007, the group publicly announced their reformation and on 23 February, after 20&amp;nbsp;days of auditions, former [[Beck]] drummer Matt Sherrod joined Finn, Seymour and Mark Hart to complete the new line up.&lt;ref name=&quot;Howl&quot;/&gt; As Sherrod and Hart had not participated in the initial sessions, four new tracks were recorded with producer [[Steve Lillywhite]] including the album's first single &quot;[[Don't Stop Now]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Howl&quot;/&gt;

On 17 March 2007 the band played a live show at their rehearsal studio in front of around fifty fans, friends and family. The performance was streamed live as a [[webcast]]. The two-and-a-half-hour set included some new tracks, including &quot;Silent House&quot; co-written by Finn with the [[Dixie Chicks]]. A concert onboard ''[[The Thekla]]'', moored in [[Bristol]], followed on 19 March. Crowded House played at the Marquee Theatre in Tempe, Arizona on 26 April as a warm-up for their appearance at the [[Coachella Valley Music and Arts Festival|Coachella Festival]] on 29 April in [[Indio, California]]. They also played at the Australian [[Live Earth concert, Sydney|Live Earth]] concert in Sydney on 7 July. The next day, Finn and Seymour were interviewed on ''[[Rove (TV series)|Rove Live]]'' and the band, with Hart and Sherrod, performed &quot;Don't Stop Now&quot; to promote the new album, which was titled ''Time on Earth''. The single was a minor hit in Australia&lt;ref name=&quot;AusCharts&quot;/&gt; and the UK.&lt;ref name=&quot;UKCharts&quot;/&gt; The album was released worldwide in June and July. It topped the album chart in New Zealand&lt;ref name=&quot;NZCharts&quot;/&gt; and made number 2 in Australia&lt;ref name=&quot;AusCharts&quot;/&gt; and number 3 in the UK.&lt;ref name=&quot;UKCharts&quot;/&gt;

On 6 December 2008 Crowded House played the [[Homebake]] festival in Sydney, with warm up gigs at small venues in Hobart, Melbourne and Sydney. For these shows the band were augmented by multi-instrumentalist [[Don McGlashan]] and Neil's younger son, Elroy Finn, on guitar. On 14 March 2009 the band joined Neil's older son, Liam Finn, on stage for three songs at the [[Sound Relief]] concert in Melbourne.

===''Intriguer'' and current status (2009–present)===
{{Main|Intriguer|The Very Very Best of Crowded House|He Will Have His Way}}
[[File:NickSeymour2007.jpg|thumb|left|Nick Seymour, Barcelona, October 2007]]Crowded House began recording their follow-up to ''Time on Earth'' in April 2009, at Finn's own [[Roundhead Studios]]. The album, ''[[Intriguer]]'', was produced by [[Jim Scott (producer)|Jim Scott]] who had worked on ''[[The Sun Came Out]]'' by Neil's 7 Worlds Collide project. In August 2009, Finn travelled to Los Angeles to record some overdubs at Jim Scott's Los Angeles studio before they began mixing tracks. The album was released in June 2010, in time for the band's appearance at the [[West Coast Blues &amp; Roots Festival]] near [[Perth]]. Finn stated that the album contains some, &quot;Unexpected twists and turns&quot; and some songs that, &quot;Sound like nothing we've done before.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Thompson, Jody [http://www.spinnermusic.co.uk/2010/04/21/crowded-house-new-album-intriguer/ &quot;Crowded House Return With New Album Intriguer&quot;] spinnermusic.co.uk – 21 April 2010&lt;/ref&gt; ''Intriguer'' topped the Australian album chart,&lt;ref name=&quot;AusCharts&quot;/&gt; reached number 3 in New Zealand&lt;ref name=&quot;NZCharts&quot;/&gt; and number 12 in the UK.&lt;ref name=&quot;UKCharts&quot;/&gt;

Crowded House undertook an extensive world tour in 2010 in support of ''Intriguer''. This was the first album where the band regularly interacted with fans via the internet on their own re-launched website, Twitter and Facebook. The band sold recordings of the shows on the ''Intriguer'' tour on [[USB flash drive]]s and made individual live tracks available for free download. The band's final concert was at the A Day on the Green festival in Auckland on 27 February 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.setlist.fm/setlist/crowded-house/2011/villa-maria-estate-auckland-new-zealand-6bd20e1a.html|title=Crowded House Setlist at A Day on the Green Auckland 2011 #1|website=setlist.fm|language=en|access-date=2019-06-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A new compilation album, [[The Very Very Best of Crowded House]], was released in October 2010 to celebrate the band's 25th anniversary.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.prnewswire.com/news-releases/crowded-houses-top-hits-and-fan-favorites-gathered-for-the-very-very-best-of-crowded-house-to-be-released-october-26-by-capitolemi-101974448.html &quot;Crowded House's Top Hits and Fan Favorites Gathered for 'The Very Very Best Of Crowded House,' to be Released 26 October by Capitol/EMI&quot;] [[PR Newswire]] – 1 September 2010&lt;/ref&gt; It includes 19 of the band's greatest hits and is also available in a box set with a 25 track DVD of their music videos. A deluxe digital version, available for download only, has 32 tracks including a rare 1987 live recording of the band's version of the [[Hunters &amp; Collectors]] song &quot;[[Throw Your Arms Around Me]]&quot;. No mention of this album has been made on the band's official website or Twitter page, which suggests that they are not involved with its release.

Following the success of the album ''She Will Have Her Way'' in 2005, a second album of cover versions of Finn Brothers songs (including numerous Crowded House songs) was released on 12 November 2010. Entitled ''[[He Will Have His Way]]'', all tracks on this album are performed by Australasian male artists.&lt;ref name=TSFWO&gt;Kara, [http://www.theinsoundfromwayout.com/2010/10/hwhhw/ &quot;He Will Have His Way: The Songs of Tim &amp; Neil Finn – out 12 November&quot;] ''The Sound From Way Out'' – 26 October 2010&lt;/ref&gt; In November 2011, there was an Australian tour by various artists involved with the &quot;She Will Have Her Way&quot; and &quot;He Will Have His Way&quot; projects, including [[Paul Dempsey]], [[Clare Bowditch]], [[Seeker Lover Keeper]] ([[Sarah Blasko]], [[Sally Seltmann]] and [[Holly Throsby]]), Alexander Gow ([[Oh Mercy (band)|Oh Mercy]]) and [[Lior]].&lt;ref&gt;Reid, Poppy [http://www.themusicnetwork.com/music-news/live/2011/07/05/they-will-have-their-way-national-tour/ &quot;They Will Have Their Way national tour&quot;] themusicnetwork.com – 5 July 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

Former Crowded House drummer [[Peter Jones (drummer)|Peter Jones]] died from brain cancer on 18 May 2012 aged 49. A statement issued by the band described him as, &quot;A warm-hearted, funny and talented man, who was a valuable member of Crowded House.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.skynews.com.au/showbiz/article.aspx?id=751940&amp;vId= &quot;Crowded House drummer dies&quot;] [[Sky News Australia]] – 19 May 2012&lt;/ref&gt;

In September 2015, the song &quot;Help is Coming&quot; from the ''[[Afterglow (Crowded House album)|Afterglow]]'' album, was released as a download and limited edition 7&quot; single to raise money for the charity [[Save the Children]]. The B-side, &quot;Anthem&quot;, was a previously unreleased track that was recorded at the same demo session as &quot;Help is Coming&quot; in 1995, with the final vocal added in 2015. [[Peter Jones (drummer)|Peter Jones]] plays drums on both songs. The money will be used to provide shelter, water, sanitation and hygiene for refugees in Syria, Lebanon and Iraq. Neil Finn said of &quot;Help Is Coming&quot;...&quot;It was always a song about refugees, even if at the time I was thinking about the immigrants setting off on ships from Europe to America, looking for a better life for their families. There is such a huge scale and urgency to the current refugee crises that barely a day goes by without some crushing image or news account to confront us. We can't be silent any more.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;William, Helen [https://www.mirror.co.uk/3am/celebrity-news/charity-single-help-coming-syrian-6427826 &quot;Charity single Help Is Coming for Syrian refugees to have VAT waived as celebrities rally for help&quot;] ''[[Daily Mirror|Mirror]] 11 September 2015&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2016, Neil Finn confirmed in an interview with the Dutch newspaper ''[[Volkskrant]]'' that Crowded House are on indefinite hiatus.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.superdeluxeedition.com/news/neil-finn-confirms-crowded-house-reissues-for-2016/|title=Neil Finn confirms Crowded House reissues for 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Later that year however, he and Seymour announced a series of concerts at the Sydney Opera House to mark the 20th anniversary of the ''Farewell to the World'' show (24 November 1996). The band, with the same lineup as in 2007 - 2010 with [[Tim Finn]] as guest performed four shows, 24–27 November 2016.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/tvshowbiz/article-3795893/Crowded-House-release-Opera-House-tour-dates-20-years-famous-Farewell-gig.html|title=Crowded House release Opera House tour dates for November}}&lt;/ref&gt; Around the same time, each of the band's 7 studio albums (including the rarities collection ''Afterglow'') was reissued in deluxe 2-CD format with bonus tracks including demos, live recordings, alternate mixes, b-sides and outtakes.

In April 2018, Neil Finn joined [[Fleetwood Mac]], along with [[Mike Campbell (musician)|Mike Campbell]] of [[Tom Petty and the Heartbreakers]], as a full-time member in the wake of [[Lindsey Buckingham]]'s departure from the band.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.msn.com/en-us/music/news/fleetwood-mac-to-tour-with-neil-finn-mike-campbell-as-lindsey-buckingham-e2-80-99s-replacements-exclusive/ar-AAvGyJz|title=Fleetwood Mac to Tour With Neil Finn, Mike Campbell as Lindsey Buckingham's Replacements (EXCLUSIVE)|website=www.msn.com|language=en-US|access-date=2018-04-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 2019, Crowded House announced an Australian exclusive reunion show at the 2020 edition of [[Byron Bay Bluesfest]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://musicfeeds.com.au/news/crowded-house-dave-matthews-band-top-best-ever-first-bluesfest-2020-lineup-announcement/|title=Crowded House &amp; Dave Matthews Band Top “Best Ever” First Bluesfest 2020 Lineup Announcement|publisher=MusicFeeds}}&lt;/ref&gt; Shortly afterwards, Mark Hart announced he would not be a part of the group's reunion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://twitter.com/MarkHartMusic/status/1162499917597704192|title=MarkHart / Twitter|publisher=Twitter}}&lt;/ref&gt; Finn would confirm Hart's departure on his podcast Fangradio, noting that he &quot;love[s] Hart dearly as a friend, as a contributor and a collaborator&quot; and that &quot;all will be revealed... trust that good thought and good heart gets put into all of these decisions.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Neil Finn allegedly kicked out Mark Hart ahead of Crowded House reunion |url=https://www.stuff.co.nz/entertainment/music/115116831/neil-finn-allegedly-kicked-out-mark-hart-ahead-of-crowded-house-reunion |website=Stuff.co.nz |publisher=Stuff Limited |accessdate=30 August 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In December 2019, Neil Finn announced that the new lineup would consist of himself, Seymour, the band's original producer [[Mitchell Froom]] and his sons [[Liam Finn|Liam]] and [[Elroy Finn|Elroy]].

==Style==
{{listen
|title=&quot;Better Be Home Soon&quot;
|filename=Better Be Home Soon.ogg
|description=The first single from ''[[Temple of Low Men]]'' (1988).
|title2=&quot;Don't Stop Now&quot;
|filename2=Don't Stop Now.ogg
|description2=The first single from ''[[Time on Earth]]'' (2007) and the first to feature Matt Sherrod.
|title3=&quot;Don't Dream It's Over&quot;
|filename3=Don't Dream It's Over.ogg
|description3=The group's most successful international single, taken from ''[[Crowded House (album)|Crowded House]]'' (1986).
|title4=&quot;Distant Sun&quot;
|filename4=Distant Sun.ogg
|description4=The first single from ''[[Together Alone]]'' (1993), and the first to feature Mark Hart.}}

===Songwriting and musical influences===
As the primary songwriter for the band, Neil Finn has always set the tone for the band's sound. Allmusic said that Finn &quot;has consistently proven his knack for crafting high-quality songs that combine irresistible melodies with meticulous lyrical detail.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Woodstra, Chris [{{Allmusic|class=artist|id=p76135|pure_url=yes}} &quot;Neil Finn &gt; Biography&quot;] AllMusic&lt;/ref&gt; Neil's brother Tim was an early and important musical influence. Neil first saw Tim play with Split Enz in 1972, and said &quot;that performance and those first songs made a lasting impression on me.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mushroommusic.com.au/songwriters/78/finn-neil &quot;Neil Finn &gt; Biography&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110221050636/http://mushroommusic.com.au/songwriters/78/finn-neil |date=21 February 2011 }} ''[[Mushroom Records|Mushroom Music Publishing]]''&lt;/ref&gt; His mother was another significant musical influence, encouraging him to listen to a variety of genres, including [[Folk music of Ireland|Irish folk music]] and [[Māori music]]. She would play piano at family parties and encourage Neil and Tim to accompany her.

===Album covers, costumes and set design===
Bassist Nick Seymour, who is also an artist, designed or co-designed all of the band's album covers and interior artwork. He also designed some of the costumes worn by the group, notably those from the cover of the group's debut album ''Crowded House''. Seymour collaborated with Finn and Hester on the set design of some of their early music videos, including &quot;Don't Dream It's Over&quot; and &quot;Better Be Home Soon&quot;. Since the band reunited, Seymour has again designed their album covers.&lt;ref name=denton/&gt;

The majority of the covers for the band's singles were not designed by Seymour. The artwork for &quot;Pineapple Head&quot; was created by [[Reg Mombassa]] of [[Mental As Anything]]. For the first four albums Mombassa and [[Noel Crombie]], who had been the main designer of Split Enz's artwork, assisted Seymour in creating sets and costumes. For the ''Farewell to the World'' concerts Crombie designed the set, while Mombassa and Seymour designed promotional materials and artwork.&lt;ref&gt;Crowded House, ''Farewell to the World'' concert film end credits, released December 1996.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Band members==
{{col-begin}}
{{col-2}}
;Current members
*[[Neil Finn]] – lead vocals, guitar, keyboards &lt;small&gt;(1985–1996, 2006–2011, 2016, 2020–present)&lt;/small&gt;
*[[Nick Seymour]] – bass, backing vocals &lt;small&gt;(1985–1996, 2006–2011, 2016, 2020–present)&lt;/small&gt;
*[[Mitchell Froom]] – keyboards, guitar, backing vocals &lt;small&gt;(1986, 2020–present)&lt;/small&gt;
*[[Liam Finn]] – guitars, keyboards, backing vocals &lt;small&gt;(2007–2008, 2020–present)&lt;/small&gt;
*Elroy Finn – guitars &lt;small&gt;(2008, 2016)&lt;/small&gt;, drums &lt;small&gt;(2020–present)&lt;/small&gt;

{{col-2}}
;Former members
*[[Craig Hooper]] – guitars, backing vocals &lt;small&gt;(1985)&lt;/small&gt;
*[[Paul Hester]] – drums, percussion, keyboards, backing vocals &lt;small&gt;(1985–1994, 1996; died 2005)&lt;/small&gt;
*[[Tim Finn]] – vocals, guitars, keyboards &lt;small&gt;(1990–1991; live guest 1996, 2016)&lt;/small&gt;
*[[Peter Jones (drummer)|Peter Jones]] – drums &lt;small&gt;(1994–1996; died 2012)&lt;/small&gt;
*[[Mark Hart]] – guitars, keyboards, backing vocals &lt;small&gt;(1992–1996, 2007–2011, 2016; touring member 1989–1992)&lt;/small&gt;
*[[Matt Sherrod]] – drums, percussion, backing vocals &lt;small&gt;(2007–2011, 2016)&lt;/small&gt;

;Former touring members
*Gill Civil – keyboards &lt;small&gt;(1986)&lt;/small&gt;
*Miffy Smith – keyboards &lt;small&gt;(1986)&lt;/small&gt;
*[[Eddie Rayner]] – keyboards &lt;small&gt;(1987, 1988)&lt;/small&gt;
*Mike Gubb – keyboards &lt;small&gt;(1988)&lt;/small&gt;
*Wally Ingrim – drums &lt;small&gt;(1994)&lt;/small&gt;
*Jules Bowen – keyboards &lt;small&gt;(1994–1996)&lt;/small&gt;
*[[David Lane (musician)|Davey Lane]] – guitars, keyboards, backing vocals &lt;small&gt;(2007)&lt;/small&gt;
*[[Don McGlashan]] – guitars, keyboards, mandolin, euphonium, vocals &lt;small&gt;(2008)&lt;/small&gt;
*Harper Finn – keyboards &lt;small&gt;(2016, 2020–present)&lt;/small&gt;

{{col-end}}

;Timeline
&lt;div align=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
&lt;timeline&gt;
ImageSize = width:950 height:auto barincrement:33
PlotArea = left:110 bottom:75 top:05 right:10
Alignbars = justify
DateFormat  = dd/mm/yyyy
Period = from:01/01/1985 till:31/12/2020
TimeAxis = orientation:horizontal format:yyyy

Colors =
  id:vocals  value:red     legend:Vocals
  id:guitar  value:green   legend:Guitars
  id:keys    value:purple  legend:Keyboards
  id:bass    value:blue    legend:Bass
  id:drums   value:orange  legend:Drums
  id:studio  value:black   legend:Studio_album

Legend = position:bottom columns:3

ScaleMajor = increment:2 start:1985
ScaleMinor = increment:2 start:1986

BarData =

  bar:Neil  text:&quot;Neil Finn&quot;
  bar:Tim   text:&quot;Tim Finn&quot;
  bar:Craig text:&quot;Craig Hooper&quot;
  bar:Mark  text:&quot;Mark Hart&quot;
  bar:Nick  text:&quot;Nick Seymour&quot;
  bar:Paul  text:&quot;Paul Hester&quot;
  bar:Peter text:&quot;Peter Jones&quot;
  bar:Matt  text:&quot;Matt Sherrod&quot;

PlotData=
 width:11
  bar:Neil  from:01/01/1985 till:24/11/1996 color:vocals
  bar:Neil  from:01/07/2006 till:27/02/2011 color:vocals 
  bar:Neil  from:01/10/2016 till:27/11/2016 color:vocals
  bar:Neil  from:01/04/2020 till:end        color:vocals
  bar:Craig from:01/01/1985 till:01/09/1985 color:guitar
  bar:Paul  from:01/01/1985 till:05/04/1994 color:drums
  bar:Paul  from:15/06/1996 till:24/11/1996 color:drums
  bar:Nick  from:01/01/1985 till:01/08/1989 color:bass
  bar:Nick  from:01/09/1989 till:24/11/1996 color:bass
  bar:Nick  from:01/07/2006 till:27/02/2011 color:bass
  bar:Nick  from:01/10/2016 till:27/11/2016 color:bass
  bar:Nick  from:01/04/2020 till:end        color:bass
  bar:Tim   from:01/08/1990 till:01/11/1991 color:vocals
  bar:Mark  from:01/06/1992 till:24/11/1996 color:guitar
  bar:Mark  from:01/01/2007 till:27/02/2011 color:guitar
  bar:Mark  from:01/10/2016 till:27/11/2016 color:guitar
  bar:Peter from:01/06/1994 till:15/06/1996 color:drums
  bar:Matt  from:23/02/2007 till:27/02/2011 color:drums
  bar:Matt  from:01/10/2016 till:27/11/2016 color:drums

 width:3
  bar:Neil  from:01/01/1985 till:24/11/1996 color:keys
  bar:Neil  from:01/07/2006 till:27/02/2011 color:keys
  bar:Neil  from:01/10/2016 till:27/11/2016 color:keys
  bar:Neil  from:01/04/2020 till:end        color:keys
  bar:Craig from:01/01/1985 till:01/09/1985 color:vocals
  bar:Nick  from:01/01/1985 till:01/08/1989 color:vocals
  bar:Nick  from:01/09/1989 till:24/11/1996 color:vocals
  bar:Nick  from:01/07/2006 till:27/02/2011 color:vocals
  bar:Nick  from:01/10/2016 till:27/11/2016 color:vocals
  bar:Nick  from:01/04/2020 till:end        color:vocals
  bar:Tim   from:01/08/1990 till:01/11/1991 color:keys
  bar:Mark  from:01/06/1992 till:24/11/1996 color:vocals
  bar:Mark  from:01/01/2007 till:27/02/2011 color:vocals
  bar:Mark  from:01/10/2016 till:27/11/2016 color:vocals
  bar:Paul  from:01/01/1985 till:05/04/1994 color:vocals
  bar:Paul  from:15/06/1996 till:24/11/1996 color:vocals
  bar:Matt  from:23/02/2007 till:27/02/2011 color:vocals
  bar:Matt  from:01/10/2016 till:27/11/2016 color:vocals

 width:7
  bar:Neil  from:01/01/1985 till:24/11/1996 color:guitar
  bar:Neil  from:01/07/2006 till:27/02/2011 color:guitar
  bar:Neil  from:01/10/2016 till:27/11/2016 color:guitar
  bar:Neil  from:01/04/2020 till:end        color:guitar
  bar:Tim   from:01/08/1990 till:01/11/1991 color:guitar
  bar:Paul  from:01/01/1990 till:01/01/1992 color:keys
  bar:Mark  from:01/06/1992 till:24/11/1996 color:keys
  bar:Mark  from:01/01/2007 till:27/02/2011 color:keys
  bar:Mark  from:01/10/2016 till:27/11/2016 color:keys

LineData =
 layer:back
  at:01/06/1986 color:studio
  at:01/07/1988 color:studio
  at:02/07/1991 color:studio
  at:18/10/1993 color:studio
  at:29/06/2007 color:studio
  at:11/06/2010 color:studio
&lt;/timeline&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

==Discography==
{{Main|Crowded House discography}}

;Studio albums

*''[[Crowded House (album)|Crowded House]]'' (1986)
*''[[Temple of Low Men]]'' (1988)
*''[[Woodface]]'' (1991)
*''[[Together Alone]]'' (1993)
*''[[Time on Earth]]'' (2007)
*''[[Intriguer]]'' (2010)

==Awards==

{{Main|List of awards and nominations received by Crowded House}}
Crowded House has won several national and international awards. In Australia, the group has won 13 [[ARIA Music Awards|ARIA Awards]] from 36 nominations, including the inaugural [[ARIA Award for Best New Talent|Best New Talent]] in [[ARIA Music Awards of 1987|1987]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ARIA List&quot;/&gt; The majority of their wins were for their first two albums, ''Crowded House'' and ''Temple of Low Men''.&lt;ref name=&quot;ARIA List&quot;/&gt; They won eight [[APRA Awards (Australia)|APRA Awards]] from eleven nominations and were nominated for ''The New Zealand Silver Scroll'' for &quot;Don't Stop Now&quot; in 2007.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.amplifier.co.nz/news/30913/apra_silver_scroll_awards_2007.html &quot;APRA Silver Scroll Awards 2007&quot;] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120403022133/http://www.amplifier.co.nz/news/30913/apra_silver_scroll_awards_2007.html |date=3 April 2012 }} ''Amplifier Magazine'' – 19 July 2007&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;Don't Dream It's Over&quot; was named the seventh best Australian song of all time in 2001.&lt;ref name=&quot;APRA10&quot;/&gt; In 1987, Crowded House won the American [[MTV Video Music Award]] for ''Best New Artist'' for their song &quot;Don't Dream It's Over&quot;, which was also nominated for three other awards.&lt;ref name=mtv87/&gt; In 1994, the group was named ''International Group of the Year'' at the [[BRIT Awards]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://brits.co.uk/winners/1994/|title=The BRIT Awards 1994|publisher=[[British Phonographic Industry]]|accessdate=7 August 2007 |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20070525210709/http://brits.co.uk/winners/1994/ &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 25 May 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2009, &quot;Don't Dream It's Over&quot; was ranked number fifty on the [[Triple J]] ''Hottest 100 of All Time'', voted by the Australian public.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.abc.net.au/triplej/hottest100_alltime/countdown/cd_list.htm &quot;Hottest 100 of All Time&quot;] ''[[Australian Broadcasting Corporation|ABC]]''&lt;/ref&gt;

In November 2016 Crowded House were inducted into the ARIA Hall of Fame, 30 years after their formation.

==See also==
{{Portal|Music|Australia}}
*[[Music of Australia]]
*[[Music of New Zealand]]
*[[Split Enz]]

==Further reading==
*{{Cite book|last=Dix|first=John|title=Stranded in Paradise: New Zealand Rock and Roll, 1955 to the Modern Era|publisher=[[Penguin Books]]|origyear=1988|edition=Revised|location=Auckland, New Zealand|year=2005|isbn=0-14-301953-8}}&lt;ref&gt;[http://nlnzcat.natlib.govt.nz/cgi-bin/Pwebrecon.cgi?v1=1&amp;ti=1,1&amp;Search%5FArg=john%20dix&amp;SL=None&amp;Search%5FCode=FT%2A&amp;CNT=25&amp;PID=9tFGnUAZvbv0q0Jj2fER_-mCuK&amp;SEQ=20091217143100&amp;SID=1 &quot;Stranded in paradise : New Zealand rock and roll, 1955 to the modern era / John Dix&quot;] ''[[National Library of New Zealand]]''&lt;/ref&gt;
*{{Cite book|last=Doole|first=Kerry|author2=Twomey, Chris|title=Crowded House: Private Universe|publisher=[[Music Sales Group|Omnibus Press]]|location=London, UK|year=1996|isbn=0-7119-4816-X}}&lt;ref&gt;[http://nlnzcat.natlib.govt.nz/cgi-bin/Pwebrecon.cgi?v1=1&amp;ti=1,1&amp;Search%5FArg=crowded%20house%20private%20universe&amp;SL=None&amp;Search%5FCode=GKEY%5E%2A&amp;CNT=25&amp;PID=M0ipsBhS2YyiKIBAJEf950g2XC&amp;SEQ=20091217143811&amp;SID=2 &quot;Crowded House : private universe / Kerry Doole and Chris Twomey&quot;] ''National Library of New Zealand''&lt;/ref&gt;
*{{Cite book|last=Bourke|first=Chris|title=Crowded House: Something So Strong|publisher=[[Macmillan Publishers|Macmillan]]|location=South Melbourne, Victoria|year=1997|isbn=0-7329-0886-8}}
*Chunn, Mike, ''Stranger Than Fiction: The Life and Times of Split Enz'', GP Publications, 1992. {{ISBN|1-86956-050-7}}
*Chunn, Mike, ''Stranger Than Fiction: The Life and Times of Split Enz'', (revised, ebook edition), Hurricane Press, 2013. {{ISBN|978-0-9922556-3-3}}

==References==
{{Refbegin}}

;General
*{{Cite book|title=Crowded House: Something So Strong|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=kJCfAAAAMAAJ|last=Bourke|first=Chris|publisher=Macmillan Publishers|location=South Melbourne, Victoria|year=1997|chapterurl= |isbn=0-7329-0886-8|accessdate=17 December 2009}}
*{{Cite encyclopedia|last=McFarlane |first=Ian |authorlink=Ian McFarlane |encyclopedia=[[Encyclopedia of Australian Rock and Pop]] |title=Encyclopedia entry for Crowded House |url=http://www.whammo.com.au/encyclopedia.asp?articleid=237 |accessdate=11 December 2009 |year=1999 |publisher=[[Allen &amp; Unwin]] |location=St Leonards, New South Wales |isbn=1-86508-072-1 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20040406102221/http://www.whammo.com.au/encyclopedia.asp?articleid=237 |archivedate=6 April 2004 }}

;Specific
{{Refend}}

{{Reflist|25em}}

==External links==
{{commons category}}
*[https://www.officialstores.com.au/au_en/crowded-house Official Store]
*[https://myspace.com/crowdedhouse Official MySpace]
*[https://www.facebook.com/crowdedhouse Official Facebook]
*[https://www.youtube.com/user/CrowdedHouseHQ Official YouTube]
*[{{BillboardURLbyName|artist=crowded house|chart=all}} Crowded House] at ''Billboard''

{{Crowded House}}
{{Neil Finn}}
{{ARIA Award for Album of the Year 1980s}}
{{Brit International Group}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Crowded House| ]]
[[Category:1985 establishments in Australia]]
[[Category:1996 disestablishments in Australia]]
[[Category:2006 establishments in Australia]]
[[Category:2011 disestablishments in Australia]]
[[Category:2016 establishments in Australia]]
[[Category:2016 disestablishments in Australia]]
[[Category:APRA Award winners]]
[[Category:ARIA Award winners]]
[[Category:ATO Records artists]]
[[Category:Australian alternative rock groups]]
[[Category:Australian rock music groups]]
[[Category:Brit Award winners]]
[[Category:Capitol Records artists]]
[[Category:Musical groups disestablished in 1996]]
[[Category:Musical groups established in 1985]]
[[Category:Musical groups from Melbourne]]
[[Category:Musical groups reestablished in 2006]]
[[Category:Musical groups disestablished in 2011]]
[[Category:Musical groups reestablished in 2016]]
[[Category:Musical groups disestablished in 2016]]
[[Category:Sibling musical groups]]
[[Category:New Zealand rock music groups]]
[[Category:Articles which contain graphical timelines]]
[[Category:Musical groups reestablished in 2019]]</text>
      <sha1>ofmxr5rvr34kj8oiynvm1z02y2877xd</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
