  <page>
    <title>Channel 4</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6321</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943076701</id>
      <parentid>940321799</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-28T17:59:49Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>82.3.151.146</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Channel 4 actually has two headquarters, one in Leeds and it's main headquarters in London. so I'm removing Leeds and reverting back to London.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{about||the parent company|Channel Four Television Corporation|other uses}}
{{short description|British free-to-air television channel}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=April 2019}}
{{Use British English|date=April 2019}}
{{Infobox TV channel
| name = Channel 4
| logosize = 125px
| logofile = Channel 4 logo 2015.svg
| launch = {{start date and age|1982|11|2|df=y}}
| owner = [[Channel Four Television Corporation]]
| picture format = [[1080i]] [[HDTV]]&lt;br /&gt;{{small|(downscaled to [[16:9]] [[576i]] for the [[SDTV]] feed)}}
| share = 4.83%&lt;br/&gt;0.64% (+1)
| share as of = {{start date|df=yes|2019|6}}
| share source = [https://www.barb.co.uk/viewing-data/monthly-viewing-summary/?_s=4]
| headquarters = [[Leeds]], [[England]], [[United Kingdom|UK]]
| country = United Kingdom
| language = English
| broadcast area = United Kingdom&lt;br/&gt;Ireland
| sister names = [[4seven]]&lt;br&gt;[[Film4]]&lt;br&gt;[[E4 (TV channel)|E4]]&lt;br&gt;[[More4]]&lt;br&gt;[[4Music]]&lt;br&gt;[[The Box (UK and Ireland TV channel)|The Box]]&lt;br&gt;[[Box Hits]]&lt;br&gt;[[Kerrang! TV|Kerrang!]]&lt;br&gt;[[Kiss TV|Kiss]]&lt;br&gt;[[Magic (TV channel)|Magic]]
| timeshift names = Channel 4 +1&lt;br/&gt;Channel 4 +1 HD
| web = [http://www.channel4.com/ www.channel4.com]
| terr serv 1 = [[Freeview (UK)|Freeview]]
| terr chan 1 = Channel 4 (SD)&lt;br&gt;Channel 7 (Wales)&lt;br&gt;Channel 15 (+1)&lt;br&gt;Channel 104 (HD)&lt;br&gt; Channel 109 (+1 HD)
| sat serv 1 = [[Freesat]]
| sat chan 1 = Channel 104 (SD)&lt;br&gt;Channel 120 (Wales)&lt;br&gt;Channel 121 (+1)&lt;br&gt;Channel 974 (SD, London)
| sat serv 2 = [[Sky UK|Sky]] &lt;small&gt;(England, Northern Ireland, Scotland)&lt;/small&gt;
| sat chan 2 = Channel 104 (SD)&lt;br&gt;Channel 138 (HD) &lt;small&gt;(except London)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;Channel 204 (+1)&lt;br /&gt;Channel 804 (SD) &lt;small&gt;(London)&lt;/small&gt;
| sat serv 3 = [[Sky UK|Sky]] &lt;small&gt;(Wales)&lt;/small&gt;
| sat chan 3 = Channel 117 (SD)&lt;br&gt;Channel 138 (HD)&lt;br&gt;Channel 217 (+1)
| sat serv 4 = [[Sky Ireland|Sky]] &lt;small&gt;(Ireland)&lt;/small&gt;
| sat chan 4 = Channel 135&lt;br&gt;Channel 235 (+1)
| sat serv 5 = [[Astra 2E]]
| sat chan 5 = 10714 H 22000 5/6&lt;br&gt;10936 V 22000 5/6 (+1)
| sat serv 6 = [[Astra 2G]]
| sat chan 6 = 11126 V 22000 5/6 (HD)
| sat serv 7       = [[Eutelsat#Satellites|Eutelsat 10A]]&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;(BFBS)&lt;/small&gt;
| sat chan 7       = 8009
| sat serv 8       = [[SES World Skies|NSS 12]]&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;(BFBS)&lt;/small&gt;
| sat chan 8       = 8109
| cable serv 1 = [[Virgin Media]] &lt;small&gt;(UK)&lt;/small&gt;
| cable chan 1 = Channel 104 (HD) &lt;br&gt;Channel 142 (+1)
| cable serv 2 = [[Virgin Media Ireland|Virgin Media]] &lt;small&gt;(Ireland)&lt;/small&gt;
| cable chan 2 = Channel 111 (SD)&lt;br&gt;Channel 142 (HD)&lt;br&gt;Channel 161 (+1)
| cable serv 3 = {{longitem|[[Cablecom]]&lt;br/&gt;{{nobold|(Switzerland)}}}}
| cable chan 3 = Channel 163
| cable serv 4 = [[WightFibre]]
| cable chan 4 = Channel 4

| iptv serv 1 = {{longitem|Swisscom TV&lt;br/&gt;{{nobold|(Switzerland)}}}}
| iptv chan 1 = Channel arbitrary
| iptv serv 2 = [[Eir (telecommunications)|Eir Vision]]

| iptv chan 2 = Channel 204 (SD)&lt;br&gt;Channel 205 (+1)

| online serv 1 = [[All 4]]
| online chan 1 = {{nowrap|[http://www.channel4.com/now/c4 Watch live]}}
| online serv 2 = [[TVPlayer]]
| online chan 2 = [http://www.tvplayer.com/watch/channel4 Watch live] (UK only)
| online serv 3 = [[Sky Go]]
| online chan 3 = {{longitem|[http://go.sky.com/ Watch live]&amp;nbsp;(UK and Ireland only)}}
| online serv 4 = Virgin TV Anywhere
| online chan 4 = [http://anywhere.virginmedia.com/channels/live/channel-4/ Watch live]&amp;nbsp;(UK only)&lt;br&gt;[http://anywhere.virginmedia.com/channels/live/channel-4-plus1/ Watch live]&amp;nbsp;(+1, UK only)
}}
'''Channel 4''' is a [[United Kingdom|British]] [[Public service broadcasting in the United Kingdom|public-service]] [[free-to-air]] television network headquartered in [[London]], [[United Kingdom]]. 
The channel was established to provide a fourth television service to the United Kingdom in addition to the [[television licence|licence]]-funded [[BBC One]] and [[BBC Two]], and the single commercial broadcasting network [[ITV (TV network)|ITV]].
It began transmission on 2 November 1982. Although largely commercially self-funded, it is ultimately publicly owned; originally a subsidiary of the [[Independent Broadcasting Authority]] (IBA),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Catterall |first1=Peter |title=The Making of Channel 4 |date=2013 |publisher=Routledge |isbn=978-1135018870}}&lt;!--|accessdate=18 February 2016--&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; the station is now owned and operated by [[Channel Four Television Corporation]], a public corporation of the [[Department for Digital, Culture, Media and Sport]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Channel 4 |url=https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/channel-4 |publisher=Gov.uk |accessdate=14 April 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; which was established in 1990 and came into operation in 1993. In 2010, Channel 4 extended service into Wales and became a UK-wide television channel.

{{TOClimit|3}}

==History==
{{Further|Timeline of Channel 4}}

===Conception===
{{main|Fourth UK television service}}

Before Channel 4 and S4C, Britain had three terrestrial television services: [[BBC One|BBC1]], [[BBC Two|BBC2]], and [[ITV (TV network)|ITV]]. The [[Broadcasting Act 1980]] began the process of adding a fourth; Channel 4 was formally created, along with its [[S4C|Welsh counterpart]], by an [[Act of Parliament]] in 1982. After some months of test broadcasts, it began scheduled transmissions on 2 November 1982.

The notion of a second commercial broadcaster in the United Kingdom had been around since the inception of ITV in 1954 and its subsequent launch in 1955; the idea of an &quot;ITV2&quot; (which came in 1998) was long expected and pushed for. Indeed, television sets sold throughout the 1970s and early 1980s had a spare tuning button labelled &quot;ITV/IBA 2&quot;. Throughout [[History of ITV|ITV's history]] and until Channel 4 finally became a reality, a perennial dialogue existed between the [[General Post Office|GPO]], [[Government of the United Kingdom|the government]], the ITV companies and other interested parties, concerning the form such an expansion of commercial broadcasting would take. Most likely, politics had the biggest impact in leading to a delay of almost three decades before the second commercial channel became a reality.&lt;ref name=&quot;tbsseefour&quot;/&gt;

One clear benefit of the &quot;late arrival&quot; of the channel was that its frequency allocations at each transmitter had already been arranged in the early 1960s, when the launch of an ITV2 was highly anticipated.&lt;ref name=&quot;tbsseefour&quot;/&gt; This led to very good coverage across most of the country and few problems of interference with other UK-based transmissions; a stark contrast to the problems associated with [[Channel 5 (UK)|Channel 5]]'s launch almost 15 years later.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/entertainment/1231802.stm|title=Channel 5 turns four|last=BBC News|first=|date=March 30, 2001|work=BBC News|access-date=July 20, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Wales===
{{Main|S4C}}
At the time the fourth service was being considered, a movement in Wales lobbied for the creation of dedicated service that would air Welsh-language programmes, then only catered for at &quot;off peak&quot; times on [[BBC Wales]] and [[ITV Wales &amp; West|HTV]]. The campaign was taken so seriously by [[Gwynfor Evans]], former president of [[Plaid Cymru]], that he threatened the government with a hunger strike were it not to honour the plans.&lt;ref name=&quot;seefour_wales&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.transdiffusion.org/tv/seefour/wales |title=A Channel for Wales |author=Dafydd Hancock |publisher=seefour by Electromusications |website=transdiffusion.org |date=11 September 2005 |accessdate=23 March 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The result was that Channel 4 as seen by the rest of the United Kingdom would be replaced in Wales by [[S4C|Sianel Pedwar Cymru]] (S4C) (&quot;Channel Four Wales&quot;). Operated by [[S4C Authority|a specially created authority]], S4C would air programmes in Welsh made by HTV, the BBC and independent companies. Initially limited frequency space meant that Channel 4 could not be broadcast alongside S4C, though some Channel 4 programmes would be aired at less popular times on the Welsh variant; this practice continued until the closure of S4C's analogue transmissions in 2010, at which time S4C became a fully Welsh channel.
With this conversion of the [[Wenvoe transmitting station|Wenvoe]] transmitter group in Wales to digital terrestrial broadcasting on 31 March 2010, Channel 4 became a UK-wide television channel for the first time.

Since then, carriage on digital [[cable television|cable]], [[satellite television|satellite]] and [[digital terrestrial]] has introduced Channel 4 to Welsh homes where it is now universally available.

===Launch and IBA control===
The first voice heard on Channel 4's opening day of Tuesday 2 November 1982 was that of [[continuity announcer]] [[Paul Coia]] who said:

{{quote|Good afternoon. It's a pleasure to be able to say to you, welcome to Channel Four.&lt;ref name=RTC42012&gt;{{cite web|last=Jones|first=Paul|title=Channel 4 turns 30: relive the first day on air|url=https://www.radiotimes.com/news/2012-11-02/channel-4-turns-30-relive-the-first-day-on-air/|work=[[Radio Times]]|date=2 November 2012|accessdate=16 August 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;|sign=|source=}}

Following the announcement, the channel headed into a montage of clips from its programmes set to the station's signature tune, &quot;Fourscore&quot;, written by [[Lord David Dundas|David Dundas]], which would form the basis of the station's jingles for its first decade. The first programme to air on the channel was the teatime game show ''[[Countdown (game show)|Countdown]]'', at 16:45 produced by [[Yorkshire Television]]. The first person to be seen on Channel 4 was [[Richard Whiteley]] with [[Ted Moult]] being the second. The first woman on the channel, contrary to popular belief, was not Whiteley's ''Countdown'' co-host [[Carol Vorderman]] but a lexicographer only ever identified as Mary. Whiteley opened the show with the words:

{{quote|As the countdown to a brand new channel ends, a brand new countdown begins.&lt;ref name=RTC42012/&gt;}}

On its first day, Channel 4 also broadcast soap opera ''[[Brookside]]'', which often ran storylines thought to be controversial; this ran until 2003.

At its launch, Channel 4 committed itself to providing an alternative to the existing channels, an agenda in part set out by its remit which required the provision of programming to minority groups.

In step with its remit, the channel became well received both by minority groups and the arts and cultural worlds during this period, especially under founding chief executive [[Jeremy Isaacs]], where the channel gained a reputation for programmes on the contemporary arts. Channel 4 co-commissioned [[Robert Ashley]]'s ground-breaking television opera ''[[Perfect Lives]]'',&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.robertashley.org/operas/perfectlives.htm Robert Ashley-Perfect Lives&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]{{dead link|date=February 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; which it premiered over several episodes in 1984. The channel often did not receive mass audiences for much of this period, however, as might be expected for a station focusing on minority interest.

Channel 4 also began the funding of independent films, such as the [[Merchant-Ivory]] [[docudrama]] ''[[The Courtesans of Bombay]]'', during this time.

In 1992, Channel 4 also faced its first libel case by [[Jani Allan]], a South African journalist, who objected to her representation in [[Nick Broomfield]]'s documentary ''[[The Leader, His Driver and the Driver's Wife]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/901342.stm |title=Victims of the 'silver fox' |accessdate=20 August 2007 |work=BBC News |date=29 August 2000}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In September 1993, the channel broadcast the [[Television film|direct-to-TV]] documentary film ''[[Beyond Citizen Kane]]'', in which it displayed the dominant position of the [[Rede Globo]] television network, and discussed its influence, power and political connections in Brazil.

===Channel Four Television Corporation===
{{Main|Channel Four Television Corporation}}
[[File:Multi coloured 4, 124 Horseferry Road, London.jpg|thumb|Channel 4 headquarters,&lt;br&gt;[[124 Horseferry Road]], London]]
[[File:Construction work at the Majestyk, City Square, Leeds (23rd December 2018).jpg|thumb|right|In 2020 Channel 4 will move its headquarters into the redeveloped Majestic building on [[Leeds City Square|City Square]], [[Leeds]].]]

After control of the station passed from the Channel Four Television Company to the [[Channel Four Television Corporation]] in 1993, a shift in broadcasting style took place. Instead of aiming for the fringes of society, it began to focus on the edges of the mainstream, and the centre of the mass market itself.&lt;ref&gt;Debrett, Mary. ''[https://books.google.ca/books?id=CtG2HyeBM2IC&amp;pg=PA65&amp;lpg=PA65&amp;dq=Channel+Four+Television+Corporation+mainstream+1993&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=kZZBGO4n4_&amp;sig=ACfU3U3jYo0hy2OkRINFG9YjAc9DvSX72Q&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=2ahUKEwjF0qP_vsTjAhWM6FQKHbfdB1QQ6AEwGHoECAkQAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=Channel%20Four%20Television%20Corporation%20mainstream%201993&amp;f=false Reinventing Public Service Television for the Digital Future].'' Bristol, UK/Chicago, USA: Intellect Ltd., 2010. 64–66. Google Books, retrieved July 20, 2019.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.prospectmagazine.co.uk/arts-and-books/when-channel-4-wasnt-just-bake-off-and-benefits-street|title=When Channel 4 wasn't just Bake Off and Benefits Street: It was once part of a golden era of the popular avant-garde|last=Thompson|first=Sam|date=September 14, 2018|website=Prospect Magazine|access-date=July 20, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; It began to show many US programmes in peak viewing time, far more than it had previously done. It gave such shows as ''[[Friends]]'' and ''[[ER (TV series)|ER]]'' their UK premières.

In the early 2000s, Channel 4 began broadcasting reality formats such as ''[[Big Brother (UK)|Big Brother]]'' and obtained the rights to broadcast mass appeal sporting events like [[cricket]] and [[horse racing]]. This new direction increased ratings and revenues.

In addition, the corporation launched a number of new television channels through its new [[Channel Four Television Corporation#4Ventures|4Ventures]] offshoot, including [[Film4]], [[At the Races]], [[E4 (TV channel)|E4]] and [[More4]].

Partially in reaction to its new &quot;populist&quot; direction, the [[Communications Act 2003]] directed the channel to demonstrate innovation, experimentation and creativity, appeal to the tastes and interests of a culturally diverse society, and to include programmes of an educational nature which exhibit a distinctive character.&lt;ref name=&quot;overview&quot;/&gt;

On 31 December 2004, Channel 4 launched a new look and new idents in which the logo is disguised as different objects and the 4 can be seen in an angle.

Under the leadership of [[Freeview (UK)|Freeview]] founder [[Andy Duncan (executive)|Andy Duncan]], 2005 saw a change of direction for Channel 4's digital channels. Channel 4 made E4 [[free-to-air]] on [[Digital terrestrial television in the United Kingdom|digital terrestrial television]], and launched a new free-to-air digital channel called More4. By October, Channel 4 had joined the Freeview consortium.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.dtg.org.uk/news/news.php?id=1225 |title=DTG News: ITV and Channel 4 confirm Freeview stakes |accessdate=3 April 2007 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131219105350/http://www.dtg.org.uk/news/news.php?id=1225 |archive-date=19 December 2013 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; By July 2006, Film4 had likewise become free-to-air and restarted broadcasting on digital terrestrial.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.channel4sales.com/news/news-article.aspx?year=2006&amp;id=21 |title=CHANNEL4SALES: NEWS |accessdate=3 April 2007 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20060708233806/http://www.channel4sales.com/news/news-article.aspx?year=2006&amp;id=21 |archivedate=8 July 2006 |url-status=live |df=dmy}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Venturing into radio broadcasting, 2005 saw Channel 4 purchase 51% of shares in the now defunct [[Oneword]] radio station with UBC Media holding on to the remaining shares. New programmes such as the weekly, half-hour ''The Morning Report'' news programme were among some of the new content Channel 4 provided for the station, with the name [[#4radio|4Radio]] being used. As of early 2009, however, Channel 4's future involvement in radio remained uncertain.

On 2 November 2007, the station celebrated its 25th birthday. It showed the first episode of ''Countdown'', an anniversary ''Countdown'' special, as well as [[The Big Fat Quiz of the Year#The Big Fat Anniversary Quiz|a special edition of ''The Big Fat Quiz'']] and using the original multicoloured 1982–1996 blocks logo on presentation and idents using the Fourscore jingle throughout the day.

In November 2009, Channel 4 launched a week of [[3D television]], broadcasting selected programmes each night using [[Stereoscopy|stereoscopic]] [[ColorCode 3D]] technology. The accompanying 3D glasses were distributed through [[Sainsbury's]] supermarkets.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.channel4.com/programmes/3d-week |title=3D Week – Channel 4&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 29 September 2015, Channel 4 revamped its presentation for a fifth time; the new branding downplayed the &quot;4&quot; logo from most on-air usage, in favour of using the shapes from the logo in various forms. Four new idents were filmed by [[Jonathan Glazer]], which featured the shapes in various real-world scenes depicting the &quot;discovery&quot; and &quot;origins&quot; of the shapes. The full logo was still occasionally used, but primarily for off-air marketing. Channel 4 also commissioned two new corporate typefaces, &quot;Chadwick&quot;, and &quot;Horseferry&quot; (a variation of Chadwick with the aforementioned shapes incorporated into its letter forms), for use across promotional material and on-air.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.creativereview.co.uk/cr-blog/2015/september/channel-4-rebrands-with-help-from-jonathan-glazer-and-neville-brody/ |first=Eliza |last=Williams |date=30 September 2015 |title=Channel 4 rebrands, with help from Jonathan Glazer and Neville Brody |publisher=[[Creative Review]] |access-date=4 April 2016 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160424113200/https://www.creativereview.co.uk/cr-blog/2015/september/channel-4-rebrands-with-help-from-jonathan-glazer-and-neville-brody/ |archive-date=24 April 2016 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.independent.co.uk/news/media/tv-radio/channel-4-ditches-signature-4-logo-in-brave-and-bizarre-rebrand-a6674156.html|title=Channel 4 ditches signature '4' logo in 'brave and bizarre' rebrand |accessdate=14 February 2017 |work=The Independent |first=Adam |last=Sherwin |date=1 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 31 October 2017, Channel 4 introduced a new series of idents continuing the theme, this time depicting the logo shapes as having formed an [[anthropomorphic]] &quot;giant&quot; character.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.creativereview.co.uk/channel-4-logo-becomes-c4-giant-in-quirky-new-idents/ |title=Channel 4 logo becomes &quot;C4 giant&quot; in quirky new idents |date=31 October 2017 |work=Creative Review |access-date=7 November 2017 |language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Recent history ===
Before [[Digital terrestrial television in the United Kingdom|the digital switch-over]], Channel 4 raised concerns over how it might finance its public service obligations afterward. It was announced in April 2006 that Channel 4's digital switch-over costs would be paid for by licence fee revenues.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.theguardian.com/media/2006/apr/25/citynews.broadcasting1 |title=Media registration promo|accessdate=3 April 2007 |work=The Guardian |location=London |first=John |last=Plunkett |date=26 April 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 28 March 2007, Channel 4 announced plans to launch a music channel &quot;4Music&quot; as a joint venture with British media company [[EMAP]], which would include carriage on the [[Freeview (UK)|Freeview]] platform. On 15 August 2008, [[4Music]] was launched across the UK.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.4music.com/ |title=The Box Plus Network |first=The Box Plus |last=Network |website=www.4music.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; Channel 4 announced interest in launching a high-definition version of Film4 on Freeview, to coincide with the launch of Channel 4 HD,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117962004/?categoryid=18&amp;cs=1 |title=Channel 4 maps music presence |accessdate=7 May 2007 |first=Steve |last=Clarke |date=28 March 2007 |work=Variety}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ukfree.tv/fullstory.php?storyid=1107051220 |title=Channel 4 to join YouTube and add music channel to – ukfree.tv |accessdate=7 May 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the fourth HD slot was given to Channel 5 instead.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/tech/news/a159413/five-awarded-freeview-hd-licence.html |title=Five awarded Freeview HD licence |date=11 June 2009 |website=Digital Spy |accessdate=27 June 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Channel 4 has since acquired a 50% stake in EMAP's TV business for a reported £28 million.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/media/news/a67199/channel-4-takes-50-percent-stake-in-emap-tv.html |title=Channel 4 takes 50% stake in Emap TV |date=23 July 2007 |website=[[Digital Spy]] |author=Neil Wilkes}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Channel 4 was considered for privatisation by the governments of [[Margaret Thatcher]], [[John Major]] and [[Blair ministry|Tony Blair]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Mance&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last1=Mance |first1=Henry |title=Five programmes to secure future of Channel 4 |url=http://www.ft.com/cms/s/0/9f90cc36-c50c-11e5-b3b1-7b2481276e45.html |accessdate=17 February 2016 |work=Financial Times |date=28 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; {{As of|2016}} the future of the channel was again being looked into by the government, with analysts suggesting several options for the channel's future.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mance&quot;/&gt;

In June 2017, it was announced that [[Alex Mahon]] would be the next chief executive, and would take over from [[David Abraham (executive)|David Abraham]], who left in November 2017.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.theguardian.com/media/2017/jun/05/channel-4-alex-mahon-chief-executive-shine-foundry |title=Channel 4 confirms Alex Mahon as chief executive |first=Mark |last=Sweney |date=5 June 2017 |work=The Guardian}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/entertainment-arts-40158084 |title=Alex Mahon named as new Channel 4 chief executive |date=5 June 2017 |work=BBC News}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Public service remit==
Channel 4 was established with, and continues to hold, a remit of public service obligations which it must fulfil. The remit changes periodically, as dictated by various broadcasting and communications acts, and is regulated by the various authorities Channel 4 has been answerable to; originally the IBA, then the [[Independent Television Commission|ITC]] and now [[Ofcom]].

The preamble of the remit as per the [[Communications Act 2003]] states that:

{{quote|
&quot;The public service remit for Channel 4 is the provision of a broad range of high quality and diverse programming which, in particular:
*    demonstrates innovation, experiment and creativity in the form and content of programmes;
*    appeals to the tastes and interests of a culturally diverse society;
*    makes a significant contribution to meeting the need for the licensed public service channels to include programmes of an educational nature and other programmes of educative value; and
*   exhibits a distinctive character.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;overview&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.channel4.com/info/corporate/ | publisher=Channel 4 | title=Channel 4 Overview}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;licence&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://licensing.ofcom.org.uk/tv-broadcast-licences/current-licensees/channel-4/ |publisher=Ofcom |title=Channel 4 Licence |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130301010345/http://licensing.ofcom.org.uk/tv-broadcast-licences/current-licensees/channel-4/ |archivedate=1 March 2013 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

The remit also involves an obligation to provide programming for schools,&lt;ref name=&quot;schools&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ofcom.org.uk/tv/ifi/tvlicensing/c4/c4v2attach.pdf |title=Channel 4 Broadcasting Licence |pages=[http://www.ofcom.org.uk/tv/ifi/tvlicensing/c4/c4v2attach.pdf#page=13 Appendix 2, part 10 (Page 13)] |publisher=Ofcom |date=4 October 2006 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090327121210/http://www.ofcom.org.uk/tv/ifi/tvlicensing/c4/c4v2attach.pdf |archivedate=27 March 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and a substantial amount of programming produced outside of [[Greater London]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ofcom.org.uk/tv/ifi/tvlicensing/c4/c4v2attach.pdf |title=Channel 4 Broadcasting Licence |pages=[http://www.ofcom.org.uk/tv/ifi/tvlicensing/c4/c4v2attach.pdf#page=12 Appendix 2, part 8 (Page 12)] |publisher=Ofcom |date=4 October 2006 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090327121210/http://www.ofcom.org.uk/tv/ifi/tvlicensing/c4/c4v2attach.pdf |archivedate=27 March 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Carriage==
Channel 4 was carried from its beginning on analogue terrestrial, which was practically the only means of television broadcast in the United Kingdom at the time. It continued to be broadcast through these means until the changeover to [[digital terrestrial television in the United Kingdom]] was complete. Since 1998, it has been universally available on digital terrestrial, and the [[Sky (UK &amp; Ireland)|Sky]] platform (initially encrypted, though encryption was dropped on 14 April 2008 and is now free of charge and available on the [[Freesat]] platform) as well as having been available from various times in various areas, on analogue and digital cable networks.

Due to its special status as a public service broadcaster with a specific remit, it is afforded free carriage on the terrestrial platforms,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ofcom.org.uk/tv/psb_review/digitalpsb/digitalpsb.pdf |title=Archived copy |accessdate=30 December 2006 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20091009182737/http://www.ofcom.org.uk/tv/psb_review/digitalpsb/digitalpsb.pdf |archivedate=9 October 2009 |df=dmy }} Digital PSB, Public Service Broadcasting post Digital Switchover, section 1.1&lt;/ref&gt; in contrast with other broadcasters such as ITV.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.itvplc.com/itv/news/releases/pr2005/2005-06-29/ |title=Ofcom determination of financial terms for Channel 3 licences ITV plc response |accessdate=3 April 2007 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20061015170803/http://www.itvplc.com/itv/news/releases/pr2005/2005-06-29/ |archivedate=15 October 2006 |url-status=dead |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Channel 4 is also seen outside the United Kingdom where it is widely available in [[Republic of Ireland|Ireland]], especially in border counties which have been able to receive terrestrial transmissions from [[Northern Ireland]], as well as on Irish cable networks and Switzerland&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.upc.ch/en/television/tv-channels/ |title=Channels – Television &amp;#124; upc cablecom |publisher=Upc-cablecom.ch }}&lt;/ref&gt;.

Since 2019, it has been offered by [[BFBS|British Forces Broadcasting Service (BFBS)]] to members of HM Forces and their families around the world,  [[BFBS#BFBS Television|BFBS Extra]] having previously carried a selection of Channel 4 programmes.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.forces.net/tv BFBS TV – Live TV Schedule]&lt;/ref&gt;

The Channel 4 website allows Internet users in the United Kingdom to watch Channel 4 live on the Internet. In the past some programmes (mostly international imports) were not shown. Channel 4 is also provided by [[Virgin Mobile]]'s [[Digital Audio Broadcasting|DAB]] mobile TV service which has the same restrictions as the Internet live stream had. Channel 4 is also carried by the Internet TV service [[TVCatchup]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=TVCatchup – Channel 4 |url=http://www.tvcatchup.com/watch.html?c=4#4 |accessdate=8 January 2014 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140108154407/http://www.tvcatchup.com/watch.html?c=4 |archivedate=8 January 2014 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;  and was previously carried by [[Zattoo]] until the operator removed the channel from its platform.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Andrews|first=Robert|title=ITV, C4, Five Also Get Yanked From Zattoo|url=http://paidcontent.org/2010/06/15/419-itv-c4-five-also-get-yanked-from-zattoo/|accessdate=8 January 2014|newspaper=paidContent|date=15 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Channel 4 also makes some of its programming available &quot;on demand&quot; via cable and the Internet through [[All 4]].

==Funding==
During the station's formative years, funding came from the ITV companies in return for their right to sell advertisements in their region on the fourth channel.

Nowadays it pays for itself in much the same way as most privately run commercial stations, i.e. through the sale of on-air advertising, programme sponsorship, and the sale of any programme content and merchandising rights it owns, such as overseas sales and video sales. For example, {{as of|2012|lc=y}} its total revenues were £925 million with 91% derived from sale of advertising.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://annualreport.channel4.com/Downloads/Channel4_AR12_financials.pdf |title=Financial report and statements |year=2013 |publisher=Channel 4 |pages=112–114 |accessdate=12 August 2013 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131105030740/http://annualreport.channel4.com/Downloads/Channel4_AR12_financials.pdf |archivedate=5 November 2013 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt; It also has the ability to subsidise the main network through any profits made on the corporation's other endeavours, which have in the past included subscription fees from stations such as [[E4 (TV channel)|E4]] and Film4 (now no longer subscription services) and its &quot;video-on-demand&quot; sales. In practice, however, these other activities are loss-making, and are subsidised by the main network. According to Channel 4's last published accounts, for 2005, the extent of this cross-subsidy was some £30 million.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.channel4.com/about4/pdf/2005_C4_Complete.pdf 11419_11419_C4&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070615192437/http://www.channel4.com/about4/pdf/2005_C4_Complete.pdf |date=15 June 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The change in funding came about under the [[Broadcasting Act 1990]] when the new corporation was afforded the ability to fund itself. Originally this arrangement left a &quot;safety net&quot; guaranteed minimum income should the revenue fall too low, funded by large insurance payments made to the ITV companies. Such a subsidy was never required, however, and these premiums were phased out by the government in 1998. After the link with ITV was cut, the cross-promotion which had existed between ITV and Channel 4 also ended.

In 2007, owing to severe funding difficulties, the channel sought government help and was granted a payment of £14 million over a six-year period. The money was to have come from the television licence fee, and would have been the first time that money from the licence fee had been given to any broadcaster other than the BBC.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.independent.co.uk/news/media/jowell-challenges-channel-4-to-justify-16314m-of-public-funding-454035.html |work=The Independent |location=London |title=Jowell challenges Channel 4 to justify £14m of public funding |first=Ian |last=Burrell |date=21 June 2007 |accessdate=1 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the plan was scrapped by the [[Secretary of State for Culture, Media and Sport]], [[Andy Burnham]], ahead of &quot;broader decisions about the future framework of public service broadcasting&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/entertainment/7750501.stm |work=BBC News |title=Channel 4 switchover cash shelved |date=26 November 2008 |accessdate=1 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The broadcasting regulator [[Ofcom]] released its review in January 2009 in which it suggested that Channel 4 would preferably be funded by &quot;partnerships, joint ventures or mergers&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://stakeholders.ofcom.org.uk/consultations/psb2_phase2/statement/ |title=Ofcom's second Public Service Broadcasting Review – Phase Two: preparing for the digital future |website=Ofcom|date=22 September 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Programming==
Channel 4 is a &quot;publisher-broadcaster&quot;, meaning that it commissions or &quot;buys&quot; all of its programming from companies independent of itself. It was the first broadcaster in the United Kingdom to do so on any significant scale; such commissioning is a stipulation which is included in its licence to broadcast.&lt;ref name=&quot;schools&quot;/&gt; This had the consequence of starting an industry of production companies that did not have to rely on owning an ITV licence to see their programmes air, though since Channel 4, external commissioning has become regular practice on the numerous stations that have launched since, as well as on the [[BBC]] and in ITV (where a quota of 25% minimum of total output has been imposed since the [[Broadcasting Act 1990]] came into force). Although it was the first British broadcaster to commission all of its programmes from third parties, Channel 4 was the last terrestrial broadcaster to outsource its transmission and playout operations (to [[Red Bee Media]]), after 25 years in-house.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.theguardian.com/media/2007/nov/14/channel4.television1 |work=The Guardian |location=London |title=Channel 4 outsources to Red Bee |first=Caitlin |last=Fitzsimmons |date=14 November 2007 |accessdate=1 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The requirement to obtain all content externally is stipulated in its licence.&lt;ref name=&quot;licence&quot;/&gt; Additionally, Channel 4 also began a trend of owning the copyright and distribution rights of the programmes it aired, in a manner that is similar to the major Hollywood studios' ownership of television programmes that they did not directly produce.{{citation needed|date=June 2011}} Thus, although Channel 4 does not produce programmes, many are seen as belonging to it.

It was established with a specific intention of providing programming to groups of minority interests, not catered for by its competitors, which at the time were only the [[BBC]] and [[ITV (TV network)|ITV]].&lt;ref name=&quot;tbsseefour&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.transdiffusion.org/emc/seefour/yes.php |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070124205530/http://www.transdiffusion.org/emc/seefour/yes.php |archivedate=24 January 2007 |title=Yes it's no |author=Russ J Graham |website=transdiffusion.org |date=11 September 2005 |accessdate=23 March 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Channel 4 also pioneered the concept of 'stranded programming', where seasons of programmes following a common theme would be aired and promoted together. Some would be very specific, and run for a fixed period of time; the ''[[4 Mation]]'' season, for example, showed innovative animation. Other, less specific strands, were (and still are) run regularly, such as ''[[T4 (Channel 4)|T4]]'', a strand of programming aimed at teenagers, on weekend mornings (and weekdays during school/college holidays); ''Friday Night Comedy'', a slot where the channel would pioneer its style of comedy commissions, ''4Music'' (now a separate channel) and ''[[4Later]]'', an eclectic collection of offbeat programmes transmitted in the early hours of the morning.

In its earlier years, ''[[Red triangle (Channel 4)|Red Triangle]]'' was the name given to the airing of certain risqué art-house films due to the use of a red triangle [[Digital on-screen graphic|DOG]] in the upper right of the screen, dubbed as being pornographic by many of Channel 4's critics, while general broadcasting of films on the station for many years came under the banner of ''Film on Four'' prior to the launch of the ''FilmFour'' brand and station in the late 1990s.

=== Most watched programmes ===
The following is a list of the 10 most watched shows on Channel 4 since launch, based on Live +28 data supplied by [[BARB]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.barb.co.uk/whats-new/weekly-top-30 |title=Weekly Top 30 Programmes |publisher=Barb.co.uk |date=28 October 2012 |accessdate=7 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; and archival data published by Channel 4.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.channel4.com/media/documents/corporate/foi-docs/4_at_25.pdf |title=Top 50 Programmes on Channel 4 1982 – 2007 |accessdate=9 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Rank !! Programme or film !! Viewers (millions) !! Date
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|1 || ''[[A Woman of Substance (miniseries)|A Woman of Substance]]'' || 13.85 || 4 January 1985
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|2 || ''[[Big Brother 2 (UK)| Big Brother]]'' ||13.74|| 27 July 2001
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|3 || ''[[A Woman of Substance (miniseries)|A Woman of Substance]]'' || 13.20 || 3 January 1985
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|4 || ''[[Four Weddings and a Funeral]]'' || 12.40 || 15 November 1995
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|5 || ''[[A Woman of Substance (miniseries)|A Woman of Substance]]'' || 11.55 || 2 January 1985
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|6 || ''[[Gregory's Girl]]'' ||10.75|| 8 January 1985
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|7|| ''[[The Great British Bake Off]]'' ||10.54 || 30 October 2018
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|8 || ''[[The Great British Bake Off]]'' ||10.13 || 31 October 2017
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|9 || ''[[The Great British Bake Off]]'' ||10.03 || 27 August 2019
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|10 || ''[[Big Brother 3 (UK)|Big Brother]] '' ||10.01 || 26 July 2002
|}

=== Kids Segment === 
*''Take 5'' (Channel 4) (1992–1996)

=== Comedy ===
During the station's early days, the screenings of innovative short one-off [[comedy films]] produced by a rotating line-up of alternative comedians went under the title of ''[[The Comic Strip Presents]]''. ''[[The Tube (TV series)|The Tube]]'' and ''[[Saturday Live (UK TV series)|Saturday Live/Friday Night Live]]'' also launched the careers of a number of comedians and writers. Channel 4 broadcast a number of popular American imports, including ''[[Roseanne]]'', ''[[Friends]]'', ''[[Sex and the City]]'', ''[[South Park]]'' and ''[[Will &amp; Grace]]''. Other significant US acquisitions include ''[[The Simpsons]]'', for which the station was reported to have paid £700,000 per episode for the terrestrial television rights.

In April 2010, Channel 4 became the first UK broadcaster to adapt the American comedy institution of [[Roast (comedy)|roasting]] to British television, with ''[[A Comedy Roast]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Guardian5Apr2010&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.theguardian.com/media/2010/apr/05/comedy-roasts-channel-4 |title=Channel 4 launches comedy roast shows |newspaper=The Guardian |date=5 April 2010 |accessdate=8 April 2010 |location=London |first=Stephen |last=Armstrong}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Channel4AComedyRoastEpisodeGuide&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.channel4.com/programmes/a-comedy-roast/episode-guide |title=A Comedy Roast – Series &amp; Episodes |publisher=Channel 4 |website=www.channel4.com/programmes/a-comedy-roast/episode-guide |date=n.d. |accessdate=8 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2010, Channel 4 organised ''[[Channel 4's Comedy Gala]]'', a comedy [[benefit concert|benefit show]] in aid of [[Great Ormond Street Hospital|Great Ormond Street Children's Hospital]]. With over 25 comedians appearing, it billed it as &quot;the biggest live stand up show in United Kingdom history&quot;. Filmed live on 30 March in front of 14,000 at [[The O2 Arena]] in London, it was broadcast on 5 April.&lt;ref name=&quot;Channel4Sales11Feb2010&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://channel4sales.com/news/11/02/2010/comedy+royalty+unite+for+channel+4s+comedy+gala |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100926195042/http://channel4sales.com/news/11/02/2010/comedy%2Broyalty%2Bunite%2Bfor%2Bchannel%2B4s%2Bcomedy%2Bgala |archivedate=26 September 2010 |title=Comedy Royalty unite for Channel 4's Comedy Gala |publisher=Channel 4 |website=www.channel4sales.com/news |date=11 February 2010 |accessdate=30 March 2010 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; This has continued to 2016.

=== Factual and current affairs ===
Channel 4 has a strong reputation for history programmes and real-life documentaries. It has also courted controversy, for example by broadcasting live the first public [[autopsy]] in the UK for 170 years, carried out by [[Gunther von Hagens]] in 2002, or the 2003 one-off stunt ''[[Derren Brown]] Plays Russian Roulette Live''.

Its news service, ''[[Channel 4 News]]'', is supplied by [[ITN]] whilst its long-standing investigative documentary series, ''[[Dispatches (TV series)|Dispatches]]'', attracts perennial media attention.

=== FourDocs ===
FourDocs is an online documentary site provided by Channel 4. It allows viewers to upload their own documentaries to the site for others to view. It focuses on documentaries of between 3 and 5&amp;nbsp;minutes. [http://www.4docs.org.uk The website] also includes an archive of classic documentaries, interviews with documentary filmmakers and short educational guides to documentary-making. It won a [[Peabody Award]] in 2006.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.peabodyawards.com/award-profile/four-docs 66th Annual Peabody Awards], May 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; The site also includes a strand for documentaries of under 59 seconds, called &quot;Microdocs&quot;.

=== Schools programming ===
Channel 4 is obliged to carry schools programming as part of its remit and licence.&lt;ref name=&quot;schools&quot;/&gt;

==== ITV Schools on Channel 4 ====
{{main|ITV Schools On Channel 4}}

Since 1957 ITV had produced schools programming, which became an obligation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.schoolstv.com/itvschoolsonitv_history.shtml?1 |title=schoolsTV.com – ITV for SCHOOLS &amp; COLLEGES – HISTORY |accessdate=16 February 2008|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070706195151/http://www.schoolstv.com/itvschoolsonitv_history.shtml?1|archivedate=6 July 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1987, five years after the station was launched, the IBA afforded ITV free carriage of these programmes during Channel 4's then-unused weekday morning hours. This arrangement allowed the ITV companies to fulfil their obligation to provide schools programming, whilst allowing ITV itself to broadcast regular programmes complete with advertisements. During the times in which schools programmes were aired [[ITV Central|Central Television]] provided most of the [[continuity (broadcasting)|continuity]] with play-out originating from Birmingham.&lt;ref name=&quot;itvschools&quot;&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20070706195104/http://www.schoolstv.com/itvschoolson4_history.shtml?1 schoolsTV.com] History of ITV Schools on Channel 4. Retrieved at the [[Internet Archive]] on 16 February 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Channel 4 Schools/4Learning ====

After the restructuring of the station in 1993, ITV's obligations to provide such programming on Channel 4's airtime passed to Channel 4 itself, and the new service became Channel 4 Schools, with the new corporation administering the service and commissioning its programmes, some still from ITV, others from independent producers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.schoolstv.com/ch4schools_9397_history.shtml?1 |title=schoolsTV.com – CHANNEL 4 SCHOOLS: 1993–1997 HISTORY|accessdate=16 February 2008 |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20070705142339/http://www.schoolstv.com/ch4schools_9397_history.shtml?1 |archivedate = 5 July 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In March 2008, the 4Learning interactive new media commission [https://web.archive.org/web/20160120045545/http://www.slabovia.tv/ slabovia.tv] was launched. [https://archive.today/20130706142013/http://www.slabovia.tv/SlabPlayer The Slabplayer] online media player showing TV shows for teenagers was launched on 26 May 2008.

The schools programming has always had elements different to its normal presentational package. In 1993, the Channel 4 Schools idents featured famous people in one category, with light shining on them in front of an industrial looking setting supplemented by instrumental calming music. This changed in 1996 with the circles look to numerous children touching the screen, forming circles of information then picked up by other children. The last child would produce the channel 4 logo in the form of three vertical circles, with another in the middle and to the left containing the Channel 4 logo.

A present feature of presentation was a countdown sequence featuring, in 1993 a slide with the programme name, and afterwards an extended sequence matching the channel branding. In 1996, this was an extended ident with timer in top left corner, and in 1999 following the adoption of the squares look, featured a square with timer slowly make its way across the right of the screen with people learning and having fun while doing so passing across the screen. It finished with the Channel 4 logo box on the right of the screen and the name 'Channel 4 Schools' being shown. This was adapted in 2000 when the service's name was changed to '4Learning'.{{citation needed|date=April 2018}}

In 2001, this was altered to various scenes from classrooms around the world and different parts of school life. The countdown now flips over from the top, right, bottom and left with each second, and ends with four coloured squares, three of which are aligned vertically to the left of the Channel 4 logo, which is contained inside the fourth box. The tag 'Learning' is located directly beneath the logo. The final countdown sequence lasted between 2004 and 2005 and featured a background video of current controversial issues, overlaid with upcoming programming information. the video features people in the style of graffiti enacting the overuse of CCTV cameras, fox hunting, computer viruses and pirate videos, relationships, pollution of the seas and violent lifestyles. Following 2005, no branded section has been used for Schools programmes.{{citation needed|date=April 2018}}

=== Religious programmes ===
From the outset, Channel 4 did not conform to the expectations of conventional religious broadcasting in the UK. John Ranelagh, first Commissioning Editor for Religion, made his priority 'broadening the spectrum of religious programming' and more 'intellectual' concerns.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last=Wallis |first=Richard |date=2016-01-27 |title=Channel 4 and the declining influence of organized religion on UK television. The case of Jesus: The Evidence |journal=Historical Journal of Film, Radio and Television |language=en |volume=36 |issue=4 |pages=668–688 |doi=10.1080/01439685.2015.1132821 |issn=0143-9685 |url=http://eprints.bournemouth.ac.uk/22578/4/Wallis._01_02_2016_Channel_4.1.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; He also ignored the religious programme advisory structure that had been put in place by the BBC, and subsequently adopted by ITV. Ranelagh's first major commission caused a furore, a three-part documentary series called ''[[Jesus: The Evidence]]''. The programmes, transmitted during the Easter period of 1984, seemed to advocate the idea that the Gospels were unreliable, Jesus may have indulged in witchcraft, and that he may not have even existed. The series triggered a public outcry, and marked a significant moment in the deterioration in the relationship between the UK's broadcasting and religious institutions.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

=== Film ===
Numerous genres of film-making – such as comedy, drama, documentary, adventure/action, romance and horror/thriller – are represented in the channel's schedule. From the launch of Channel 4 until 1998, film presentations on C4 would often be broadcast under the &quot;Film on Four&quot; banner.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.screenonline.org.uk/film/id/840487/index.html |title=Channel 4 Films/Film on Four/FilmFour |website=BFI Screenonline |access-date=July 20, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.screenonline.org.uk/film/id/1304135/index.html |title=Channel 4 and Film |last=Brooke |first=Michael |website=BFI Screenonline |access-date=July 20, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In March 2005, Channel 4 screened the uncut [[Lars von Trier]] film ''[[The Idiots]]'', which includes unsimulated sexual intercourse, making it the first UK terrestrial channel to do so. The channel had previously screened other films with similar material but censored and with warnings.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.independent.co.uk/news/media/channel-4-faces-investigation-for-breaking-last-sexual-taboo-on-tv-528238.html |title=Channel 4 faces investigation for breaking last sexual taboo on TV: Ofcom inquiry into screening of unpixellated penetrative sex in Lars von Trier's 'The Idiots' |last=Barnes |first=Anthony |date=March 13, 2005 |work=The Independent |access-date=July 20, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.campaignlive.com/article/channel-4-avoids-action-complaints-idiots-orgy/476762 |title=Channel 4 avoids action on complaints about Idiots orgy |last=Farey-Jones |first=Daniel |date=May 24, 2005 |website=Campaign |access-date=July 20, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Since 1 November 1998, Channel 4 has had a digital subsidiary channel dedicated to the screening of films. This channel launched as a paid subscription channel under the name &quot;FilmFour&quot;, and was relaunched in July 2006 as a free-to-air channel under the current name of &quot;[[Film4]]&quot;. The Film4 channel carries a wide range of film productions, including acquired and Film4-produced projects. Channel 4's general entertainment channels [[E4 (TV channel)|E4]] and [[More4]] also screen feature films at certain points in the schedule as part of their content mix.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.tvwhirl.co.uk/presentation/channel-4/film4/ |title=Film4 |last=Burridge |first=Terence |website=TV Whirl |access-date=July 20, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Wank Week ===
{{main|Wank Week}}

A season of television programmes about [[masturbation]], called ''Wank Week'', was to be broadcast in the United Kingdom by Channel 4 in March 2007. The first show was about a [[Masturbate-a-thon]], a public mass masturbation event, organised to raise money for the [[sexual health]] charity [[Marie Stopes International]]. Another film would have focused on compulsive male masturbators and a third was to feature the [[sex education|sex educator]] Dr [[Betty Dodson]].

The series came under public attack from senior television figures, and was pulled amid claims of declining editorial standards and controversy over the channel's [[public broadcasting|public service broadcasting]] credentials.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.theguardian.com/media/2007/feb/02/broadcasting.channel4 |title=Channel 4 postpones 'wank week' programming |work=The Guardian}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Global warming ===
On 8 March 2007, Channel 4 screened a highly controversial documentary, ''[[The Great Global Warming Swindle]]''. The programme states that global warming is &quot;a lie&quot; and &quot;the biggest scam of modern times&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.washingtontimes.com/news/2007/mar/6/20070306-122226-6282r/ |title=Global warming labeled a 'scam' |newspaper=The Washington Times |access-date=10 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; The programme's accuracy has been disputed on multiple points, and several commentators have criticised it for being one-sided, noting that the mainstream position on global warming is supported by the scientific academies of the [[G8|major industrialised nations]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Houghton&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last=Houghton |first=John |title=The Great Global Warming Swindle |publisher=The John Ray Initiative |date= |url=http://www.jri.org.uk/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=137&amp;Itemid=83 |doi= |accessdate=12 March 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; There were 246 complaints to [[Ofcom]] as of 25 April 2007,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.theguardian.com/science/2007/apr/25/controversiesinscience.channel4 |title=Move to block emissions 'swindle' DVD |date=25 April 2007 |accessdate=25 April 2007 |work=The Guardian |location=London |first=David |last=Adam}}&lt;/ref&gt; including allegations that the programme falsified data.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://news.independent.co.uk/media/article2521677.ece |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070510030950/http://news.independent.co.uk/media/article2521677.ece |archivedate=10 May 2007 |title=C4 accused of falsifying data in documentary on climate change |accessdate=20 May 2007 |work=The Independent |location=London |first=Steve |last=Connor |date=8 May 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; The programme has been criticised by scientists and scientific organisations, and various scientists who participated in the documentary claimed their views had been distorted.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.theguardian.com/media/2007/mar/11/broadcasting.science |title=Climate scientist 'duped to deny global warming' |last=Goldcare, Ben and David Adam |first= |date=March 11, 2007 |work=The Guardian |access-date=July 20, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''[[Against Nature (documentary)|Against Nature]]'': An earlier controversial Channel 4 programme made by Martin Durkin which was also critical of the environmental movement and was charged by the Independent Television Commission of the UK for misrepresenting and distorting the views of interviewees by selective editing.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2008/jul/21/climatechange.carbonemissions1 |title=Why does Channel 4 seem to be waging a war against the greens? |last=Monbiot |first=George |date=July 21, 2008 |work=The Guardian |access-date=July 20, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.badscience.net/2007/03/against-nature-channel-4-tonight/ |title=Against Nature – Channel 4 tonight |last=Goldacre |first=Ben |date=March 8, 2007 |website=Bad Science |access-date=July 20, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''[[The Greenhouse Conspiracy]]'': An earlier Channel 4 documentary broadcast on 12 August 1990, as part of the ''[[Equinox (television)|Equinox]]'' series, in which similar claims were made.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://skepticalscience.com/print.php?n=1205 |title=Climate Change Denial and the Media – Banishment of Science Reality |last=Purdue |first=Brian |date=January 12, 2012 |website=Skeptical Science |access-date=July 20, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Three of the people interviewed (Lindzen, Michaels and Spencer) were also interviewed in ''[[The Great Global Warming Swindle]]''.

=== Ahmadinejad's Christmas speech ===
In the ''Alternative Christmas address'' of 2008, a Channel 4 tradition since 1993 with a different presenter each year, Iranian President [[Mahmoud Ahmadinejad]] made a thinly veiled attack on the United States by claiming that Christ would have been against &quot;bullying, ill-tempered and expansionist powers&quot;.

The airing courted controversy and was rebuked by several human rights activists, politicians and religious figures, including [[Peter Tatchell]]&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.belfasttelegraph.co.uk/news/anger-as-ahmadinejad-delivers-christmas-message-on-channel-4-28461412.html |title=Anger as Ahmadinejad delivers Christmas message on Channel 4 |last=Belfast Telegraph |first= |date=December 25, 2008 |work=Belfast Telegraph |access-date=July 20, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;, [[Louise Ellman]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/7799652.stm |title=Ahmadinejad show 'causes offence' |last=BBC News |first= |date=December 25, 2008 |work=BBC News |access-date=July 20, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;, [[Ron Prosor]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.aljazeera.com/news/europe/2008/12/2008122614288623436.html |title=UK criticises Ahmadinejad broadcast |last=Agencies |date=December 26, 2008 |access-date=July 20, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Rabbi Aaron Goldstein&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt;. A spokeswoman for the [[Foreign and Commonwealth Office]] said: &quot;President Ahmadinejad has, during his time in office, made a series of appalling anti-Semitic statements. The British media are rightly free to make their own editorial choices, but this invitation will cause offence and bemusement not just at home but among friendly countries abroad&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.theguardian.com/media/2008/dec/25/channel4-iran |title=Government slams C4 over Ahmadinejad Christmas message |work=The Guardian |location=London |first=Haroon |last=Siddique |date=25 December 2008 |accessdate=14 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

However, some defended Channel 4. [[Stonewall (charity)|Stonewall]] director [[Ben Summerskill]] stated: &quot;In spite of his ridiculous and often offensive views, it is an important way of reminding him that there are some countries where free speech is not repressed...If it serves that purpose, then Channel 4 will have done a significant public service&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.pinknews.co.uk/2008/12/24/channel-4-under-fire-for-allowing-homophobe-mahmoud-ahmadinejad-to-deliver-christmas-message/ |title=Channel 4 under fire for allowing homophobe Mahmoud Ahmadinejad to deliver Christmas message |last=Staff Writer |date=December 24, 2008 |website=Pink News |access-date=July 20, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Dorothy Byrne]], Channel 4's head of news and current affairs, also defended the station, saying: &quot;As the leader of one of the most powerful states in the Middle East, President Ahmadinejad's views are enormously influential... As we approach a critical time in international relations, we are offering our viewers an insight into an alternative world view...Channel 4 has devoted more airtime to examining Iran than any other broadcaster and this message continues a long tradition of offering a different perspective on the world around us&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt;

=== 4Talent ===
4Talent is an editorial branch of Channel 4's commissioning wing, which co-ordinates Channel 4's various talent development schemes for film, television, radio, new media and other platforms and provides a showcasing platform for new talent.

There are bases in London, [[Birmingham]], Glasgow and [[Belfast]], serving editorial hubs known respectively as 4Talent National, 4Talent Central England, 4Talent Scotland and 4Talent Northern Ireland. These four sites include features, profiles and interviews in text, audio and video formats, divided into five zones: TV, Film, Radio, New Media and Extras, which covers other arts such as theatre, music and design. 4Talent also collates networking, showcasing and professional development opportunities, and runs workshops, masterclasses, seminars and showcasing events across the UK.

==== ''4Talent Magazine'' ====
''4Talent magazine'' is the creative industries magazine from 4Talent, which launched in 2005 as TEN4 magazine under the editorship of Dan Jones. ''4Talent Magazine'' is currently edited by Nick Carson. Other staff include deputy editor Catherine Bray and production editor Helen Byrne. The magazine covers rising and established figures of interest in the creative industries, a remit including film, radio, TV, comedy, music, new media and design.

Subjects are usually UK-based, with contributing editors based in Northern Ireland, Scotland, London and Birmingham, but the publication has been known to source international content from Australia, America, continental Europe and the Middle East. The magazine is frequently organised around a theme for the issue, for instance giving half of November 2007's pages over to profiling winners of the annual 4Talent Awards.

An unusual feature of the magazine's credits is the equal prominence given to the names of writers, photographers, designers and illustrators, contradicting standard industry practice of more prominent writer bylines. It is also recognisable for its 'wraparound' covers, which use the front and back as a continuous canvas – often produced by guest artists.

Although ''4Talent Magazine'' is technically a newsstand title, a significant proportion of its readers are subscribers. It started life as a quarterly 100-page title, but has since doubled in size and is now published bi-annually.

==Presentation==
Since its launch in 1982, Channel 4 has used the same logo which consists of a stylised numeral &quot;4&quot; made up of nine differently shaped blocks. The logo was designed by [[Martin Lambie-Nairn]] and his brother Robinson and was the first channel in the UK to depict an ident made using advanced computer generation (the first electronically generated ident was on [[BBC Two]] [[BBC Two 'Computer Generated 2' ident|in 1979,]] but this was two-dimensional). It was designed in conjunction with Bo Gehring Aviation of Los Angeles and originally depicted the &quot;4&quot; in red, yellow, green, blue and purple. The music accompanying the ident was called &quot;Fourscore&quot; and was composed by David Dundas; it was later released as a single alongside a B-side, &quot;Fourscore Two&quot;, although neither reached the UK charts. In November 1992, &quot;Fourscore&quot; was replaced by new music.

In 1996, Channel 4 commissioned Tomato Films to revamp the &quot;4&quot;, which resulted in the &quot;Circles&quot; idents showing four white circles forming up transparently over various scenes, with the &quot;4&quot; logo depicted in white in one of the circles.

In 1999, Spin redesigned the logo to feature in a single square which sat on the right-hand side of the screen, whilst various stripes would move along from left to right, often lighting the squared &quot;4&quot; up. Like previous &quot;Circles&quot; idents from 1996 (which was made by Tomato Films), the stripes would be interspersed with various scenes potentially related to the upcoming programme.

The logo was made three-dimensional again in 2004 when it was depicted in filmed scenes that show the blocks forming the &quot;4&quot; logo for less than a second before the action moves away again.

In 2015, the logo was disassembled completely to allow the blocks to appear as parts of a nature scene, sometimes featuring a strange dancing creature and sometimes being excavated for scientific study, one being studied under a microscope and showing a [[tardigrade]]. The second wave of these idents, launched in 2017, depict a giant creature made of the &quot;4&quot; blocks (made to look almost like a person) interacting with everyday life, sometimes shouting the &quot;Fourscore&quot; theme as a foghorn.

==On-air identity==
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Channel 4 logo 1982.svg|Channel 4 logo from 1982 to 1996.
File:Channel 4 logo 1996.svg|Channel 4 logo from 1996 to 1999.
File:Channel 4 logo 1999.svg|Channel 4 logo from 1999 to 2004.
File:Channel 4 logo 2004.svg|Channel 4 logo from 2004 to 2015.
File:Channel 4 logo 2015.svg|Channel 4 logo from 2015.
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Regions/International ==
Channel 4 has, since its inception, broadcast identical programmes and [[continuity (broadcasting)|continuity]] throughout the United Kingdom (excluding Wales where it did not operate on analogue transmitters). At launch this made it unique, as both the BBC and [[ITV (TV network)|ITV]] had long established traditions of providing [[regional variations]] in their programming in different areas of the country. Since the launch of subsequent British television channels, Channel 4 has become typical in its lack of regional programming variations.

A few exceptions exist to this rule for programming and continuity:

Some of Channel 4's schools' programming (1980s/early '90s) was regionalised due to differences in curricula between different regions.&lt;ref name=&quot;itvschools&quot;/&gt;

Part of Channel 4's remit covers the commissioning of programmes from outside London. Channel 4 has a dedicated director of nations and regions, [[Stuart Cosgrove]], who is based in a regional office in Glasgow. As his job title suggests, it is his responsibility to foster relations with independent producers based in areas of the United Kingdom (including Wales) outside London.

Advertising on Channel 4 does contain regular variation: prior to 1993, when ITV was responsible for selling Channel 4's advertising, each regional ITV company would provide the content of advertising breaks, covering the same transmitter area as themselves, and these breaks were often unique to that area. After Channel 4 became responsible for its own advertising, it continued to offer advertisers the ability to target particular audiences and divided its coverage area into six regions: London, South,  Midlands, North, Northern Ireland and Scotland.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.channel4sales.com/data/macro_map|title=Channel 4's 'Macro Regions' for advertising, including a map |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20081220084700/http://www.channel4sales.com/data/macro_map |archivedate=20 December 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

At present, Wales does not have its own advertising region, instead its viewers receive the southern region on digital platforms intentionally broadcast to the area, or the neighbouring region where terrestrial transmissions spill over into Wales. The Republic of Ireland shares its advertising region with Northern Ireland (referred to by Channel 4 as the 'Ulster Macro') with many advertisers selling products for Ireland here.&lt;ref name=&quot;foursales&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.channel4sales.com/advertising/regions/dublin |title=Channel 4's Dublin Sales Office |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080527224137/http://www.channel4sales.com/advertising/regions/dublin |archivedate=27 May 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[E4 (TV channel)|E4]] has an advertising variant for Ireland, although Northern Ireland receives the UK version of E4.&lt;ref name=&quot;foursales&quot;/&gt; The six regions are also carried on satellite, cable and Digital Terrestrial.

[[Channel 5 (UK)|Channel 5]] and [[ITV Breakfast]] use a similar model to Channel 4 for providing their own advertising regions, despite also having a single national output of programming.

Despite the Republic of Ireland not being in the UK, Channel 4 has a dedicated variant broadcast on Sky Ireland which omits programmes for which broadcast rights are not held in Ireland. For example, the series [[Glee (TV series)|''Glee'']] is not available on Channel 4 on Sky in Ireland. In recent years a Republic of Ireland advertising opt-out has been added to this version.

===Future possibility of regional news===
With [[ITV plc]] pushing for much looser requirements on the amount of regional news and other programming it is obliged to broadcast in its ITV regions, the idea of Channel 4 taking on a regional news commitment has been considered, with the corporation in talks with [[Ofcom]] and ITV over the matter.&lt;ref name=&quot;c4moveregional&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.theguardian.com/media/2008/jul/03/channel4.ofcom |title=Channel 4 ponders move into regional news as ITV retreats |work=The Guardian |author=Leigh Holmwood |date=7 March 2008 |accessdate=30 September 2008 |location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; Channel 4 believe that a scaling-back of such operations on ITV's part would be detrimental to Channel 4's national news operation, which shares much of its resources with ITV through their shared news contractor [[ITN]]. At the same time, Channel 4 also believe that such an additional public service commitment would bode well in on-going negotiations with Ofcom in securing additional funding for its other public service commitments.&lt;ref name=&quot;c4moveregional&quot; /&gt;

==Channel 4 HD==
[[File:Channel 4HD Logo.svg|thumb|upright=0.75|The Channel 4 HD logo used from 2007 until 2015.]]
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:Channel 4 HD trail example.png|thumb|upright=0.75|Trail boards to promote Channel 4 HD.]] --&gt;
In mid-2006 Channel 4 ran a six-month closed trial of [[High-definition television|HDTV]], as part of the wider [[Digital television in the United Kingdom#Freeview HD|Freeview HD]] experiment via the [[Crystal Palace transmitting station|Crystal Palace transmitter]] to London and parts of the [[home counties]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ofcom.org.uk/consult/condocs/ddr/ddr_annexed.pdf Digital Dividend Review Annexes&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070615192453/http://www.ofcom.org.uk/consult/condocs/ddr/ddr_annexed.pdf |date=15 June 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt; including the use of [[Lost (2004 TV series)|''Lost'']] and ''[[Desperate Housewives]]'' as part of the experiment, as US broadcasters such as [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]] already have an HDTV back catalogue.

On 10 December 2007, Channel 4 launched a [[high definition television]] [[simulcast]] of Channel 4 on [[Sky+ HD|Sky]]'s digital satellite platform, after Sky agreed to contribute toward the channel's satellite distribution costs. It was the first full-time high definition channel from a terrestrial UK broadcaster.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dtg.org.uk/dtg/press_releases/dtg_nmm_20100318.pdf|title=BBC HD strategy comes into focus as Five opts for BSkyB, not Freeview|publisher=New Media Markets|date=18 March 2010|access-date=28 April 2010|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110722130613/http://www.dtg.org.uk/dtg/press_releases/dtg_nmm_20100318.pdf|archive-date=22 July 2011|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 31 July 2009, Virgin Media added Channel 4 HD on channel 146 (later on channel 142, now on channel 141) as a part of the M pack.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/tech/news/a168390/c4-hd-coming-to-virgin-media-tomorrow.html|title=C4 HD coming to Virgin Media tomorrow|website=Digital Spy|date=30 July 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 25 March 2010 Channel 4 HD appeared on [[Freeview (UK)|Freeview]] channel 52 with a placeholding caption, ahead of a commercial launch on 30 March 2010, coinciding with the commercial launch of Freeview HD.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/tech/news/a210797/c4-hd-begins-freeview-test-transmissions.html|title=C4 HD begins Freeview test transmissions|website=Digital Spy|date=26 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.reghardware.com/2010/03/30/freeview_hd_launches_gets_channel_4/|title=Freeview HD launches, gets Channel 4|publisher=Register Hardware|date=30 March 2010|access-date=10 February 2013|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130116072206/http://www.reghardware.com/2010/03/30/freeview_hd_launches_gets_channel_4/|archive-date=16 January 2013|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 19 April 2011, Channel 4 HD was added to [[Freesat]] on channel 126.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.joinfreesat.co.uk/channel-4-hd-finally-arrives-on-freesat/|title=Channel 4 HD Finally Arrives on Freesat|publisher=Join Freesat|date=19 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; As a consequence, the channel moved from being [[free-to-view]] to [[free-to-air]] on satellite during March 2011. With the closure of [[S4C|S4C Clirlun]] in Wales on 1 December 2012, on Freeview, Channel 4 HD launched in Wales on 2 December 2012.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://stakeholders.ofcom.org.uk/binaries/spectrum/spectrum-policy-area/projects/dtv/Amendment_to_Determination.pdf|title=Amendment to Determination|date=21 September 2012|website=Ofcom|accessdate=2 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The channel carries the same schedule as Channel 4, broadcasting programmes in HD when available, acting as a simulcast. Therefore, SD programming is broadcast upscaled to HD.   The first true HD programme to be shown was the 1996 [[Adam Sandler]] film [[Happy Gilmore]].  From launch until 2016 the presence of the 4HD logo on screen denoted true HD content.

On 1 July 2014, Channel 4 +1 HD, a HD simulcast of Channel 4 +1, launched on Freeview channel 110.

On 20 February 2018, Channel 4 announced that Channel 4 HD and All 4 will no longer be supplied on Freesat from Thursday 22 February 2018.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.freesat.co.uk/news/all4-4hd-leave-freesat/|title=C4 HD and All4 to leave Freesat|date=20 February 2018|website=Freesat}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==All 4==
{{Main|All 4}}

[[All 4]] is a [[video on demand]] service from Channel 4, launched in November 2006 as 4oD. The service offers a variety of programmes recently shown on Channel 4, [[E4 (TV channel)|E4]], [[More4]] or from their archives, though some programmes and movies are not available due to rights issues.

==Teletext services==

===4-Tel/FourText===
Channel 4 originally licensed an ancillary teletext service to provide schedules, programme information and features. The original service was called 4-Tel, and was produced by Intelfax, a company set up especially for the purpose. It was carried in the 400s on [[ORACLE (teletext)|Oracle]].&lt;ref name=&quot;4Tel&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://teletext.mb21.co.uk/gallery/ancillary/c4-s4c/index.shtml|title=ANCILLARY TELETEXT SERVICES|accessdate=10 June 2007|last=Brown|first=Mike|publisher=MB21}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1993, with Oracle losing its franchise to [[Teletext Ltd]], 4-Tel found a new home in the 300s, and had its name shown in the header row. Intelfax continued to produce the service &lt;ref name=&quot;4Tel&quot; /&gt; and in 2002 it was renamed FourText.

===Teletext on 4===
In 2003, Channel 4 awarded Teletext Ltd a ten-year contract to run the channel's ancillary teletext service, named Teletext on 4.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dmgt.co.uk/news/809/Teletext+and+C4+sign+text+services+deal|title=Teletext and C4 sign text services deal|accessdate=10 June 2007|date=1 July 2003|publisher=Daily Mail and General Trust plc|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130510153934/http://www.dmgt.co.uk/news/809/Teletext+and+C4+sign+text+services+deal|archive-date=10 May 2013|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; The service closed in 2008, and Teletext is no longer available on Channel 4, ITV and Channel 5.

== Awards and nominations ==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot;
|-
! Year !! Association !! Category !! Nominee(s) !! Result
|-
|rowspan=&quot;1&quot;|2017 || rowspan=&quot;1&quot;| Diversity in Media Awards || Broadcaster of the Year || ''Channel 4'' || {{nom}}
|}

==See also==
* [[Annan Committee]]
* [[Channel 4 Sheffield Pitch|Channel 4 Sheffield Pitch competition]]
* [[List of television stations in the United Kingdom]]
* ''[[Big 4 (sculpture)|Big 4]]''
* ''[[3 Minute Wonder]]''
* [[Channel 4 Banned season]]
* [[Renowned Films]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
* {{Official website|http://www.channel4.com}}

{{Channel Four Television Corporation}}
{{Navboxes|list1=
{{Department for Culture, Media and Sport}}
{{Television in Scotland}}
{{Television in Wales}}
{{Media in the United Kingdom|television}}
{{Television in Ireland}}
{{Freeview}}
{{NNN/NNS}}
}}
{{International Emmy Founders Award}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Channel 4| ]]
[[Category:Peabody Award winners]]
[[Category:1982 establishments in the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Television channels and stations established in 1982]]
[[Category:Television channels in the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Publicly funded broadcasters]]
[[Category:International Emmy Founders Award winners]]</text>
      <sha1>gd1njr6hotrnearyed5r6bhx0tsul3t</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
