  <page>
    <title>Blue Jam</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6319</id>
    <revision>
      <id>937160709</id>
      <parentid>931639044</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-23T08:55:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>X201</username>
        <id>1490139</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* External links */Standardise BBC programme template links</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{other uses}}
{{italic title}}
{{Use British English|date=July 2014}}
{{Infobox Radio Show
| show_name          = Blue Jam
| format             = Comedy, horror
| runtime            = 1 hour
| country            = United Kingdom
| language           = English
| home_station       = [[BBC Radio 1]]
| syndicates         =
| television         =
| starring           = [[Chris Morris (satirist)|Chris Morris]]&lt;br&gt;[[Kevin Eldon]]&lt;br&gt;[[Julia Davis]]&lt;br&gt;[[Mark Heap]]&lt;br&gt;[[David Cann]]&lt;br&gt;[[Amelia Bullmore]]
| creator            = [[Chris Morris (satirist)|Chris Morris]]
| director           = [[Chris Morris (satirist)|Chris Morris]]
| writer             = [[Chris Morris (satirist)|Chris Morris]]&lt;br&gt;[[Graham Linehan]]&lt;br&gt;[[Arthur Mathews (writer)|Arthur Mathews]]&lt;br&gt;[[Peter Baynham]]&lt;br&gt;[[David Quantick]]&lt;br&gt;[[Jane Bussmann]]&lt;br&gt;[[Robert Katz]]&lt;br&gt;[[Kevin Eldon]]&lt;br&gt;[[Julia Davis]]&lt;br&gt;[[Mark Heap]]&lt;br&gt;[[David Cann]]&lt;br&gt;[[Amelia Bullmore]]
| producer           = [[Chris Morris (satirist)|Chris Morris]]
| executive_producer =
| narrated           = [[Chris Morris (satirist)|Chris Morris]]
| record_location    = 
| first_aired        = {{start date|df=y|1997|11|14}}
| last_aired         ={{start date|df=y|1999|2|25}}
| num_series         = 3
| num_episodes       = 18
| audio_format       = 
| opentheme          = &quot;Stem/Long Stem/Transmission 2&quot; by [[DJ Shadow]], played in reverse
| endtheme           =
| website            =
| podcast            =
}}

'''''Blue Jam''''' was an [[Ambient music|ambient]], [[Surrealism|surreal]] [[dark comedy]] and [[Horror and terror|horror]] radio programme created and directed by [[Chris Morris (satirist)|Chris Morris]]. It was broadcast on [[BBC Radio 1]] in the early hours of the morning, for three series from 1997 to 1999.

The programme gained cult status due to its unique mix of surreal monologue, ambient soundtrack, synthesised voices, heavily edited broadcasts and recurring sketches. It featured vocal performances of [[Kevin Eldon]], [[Julia Davis]], [[Mark Heap]], David Cann and [[Amelia Bullmore]], with Morris himself delivering disturbing monologues, one of which was revamped and made into the [[British Academy of Film and Television Arts|BAFTA]]-winning short film ''[[My Wrongs 8245–8249 &amp; 117|My Wrongs #8245–8249 &amp; 117]]''. Writers who contributed to the programme included [[Graham Linehan]], [[Arthur Mathews (writer)|Arthur Mathews]], [[Peter Baynham]], [[David Quantick]], [[Jane Bussmann]], Robert Katz and the cast.

The programme was adapted into the TV series ''[[Jam (TV series)|Jam]]'', which aired in 2000. All episodes of ''Blue Jam'' are currently available for streaming and download on the [[Internet Archive]].

== Production ==

On his inspiration for making the show, Morris commented: &quot;It was so singular, and it came from a mood, quite a desolate mood. I had this misty, autumnal, boggy mood anyway, so I just went with that. But no doubt getting to the end of something like Brass Eye, where you've been forced to be a sort of surrogate lawyer, well, that's the most creatively stifling thing you could possibly do.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Plunkett&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.theguardian.com/media/2014/feb/25/chris-morris-blue-jam-repeated-radio-4 |title=Chris Morris's ''Blue Jam'' Back After 17 Years &lt;nowiki&gt;| Media |&lt;/nowiki&gt; The Guardian |last=Plunkett |first=John |date=24 February 2014 |website=[[The Guardian]] |accessdate=11 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Morris also described the show as being &quot;like the nightmares you have when you fall asleep listening to the [[BBC World Service]]&quot; (a reference to the World Service also appears in one of the monologues read by Morris).

Morris originally requested that the show be broadcast at 3 a.m. on Radio 1 &quot;because at that hour, on insomniac radio, the amplitude of terrible things is enormously overblown&quot;. As a compromise, the show was broadcast at midnight without much promotion. Morris reportedly included sketches too graphic or transgressive for radio that he knew would be cut so as to make his other material seem less transgressive in comparison. During the airing of episode 6 of series one, a re-editing of the Archbishop of Canterbury's speech at Princess Diana's funeral was deemed too offensive for broadcast, and was switched with a different episode as it aired.

==Format and style==

Each episode opened (and closed) with a short spoken monologue (delivered by Morris) describing, in surreal, broken language, various bizarre feelings and situations (for example: &quot;when you sick so sad you cry, and in crying cry a whole leopard from your eye&quot;), set to ambient music interspersed with short clips of other songs and sounds. The introduction would always end with &quot;welcome in Blue Jam&quot;, inviting the listener, who is presumably experiencing such feelings, to get lost in the program. (This format was replicated in the television adaptation ''[[Jam (TV series)|Jam]]'', often reusing opening monologues from series 3 of the radio series.) The sketches within dealt with heavy and taboo topics, such as murder, suicide, missing or dead children, and rape.

===Common recurring sketches===
*'''Doctor''' (played by David Cann): &quot;The Doctor&quot; is a seemingly &quot;normal&quot; physician working in a standard British medical practice. However, he has a habit of treating his patients in bizarre and often disturbing ways, such as prescribing heroin for a cold, making a man with a headache jump up and down in order to make his penis swing (while mirroring the patient's bewildered jumping himself) and making a patient leave and go into the next room so he can examine him over the telephone. His name is revealed to be '''Michael Perlin''' in several sketches.
*'''The Monologue Man''' (played by [[Chris Morris (satirist)|Chris Morris]]): Short stories, often up to 10 minutes in length, written from the perspective of a lonely and socially inept man. Each story usually involves the protagonist's acquaintance Suzy in some capacity.
*'''Michael Alexander St. John''': A parody of hyperbolic and pun-laden radio presenting, St. John presents items such as the top 10 singles charts and the weekend's gigs.
*'''Bad Sex''': Short clips of two lovers (played by [[Julia Davis]] and [[Kevin Eldon]]) making increasingly bizarre erotic requests of one another, such as to &quot;shit your leg off&quot; and &quot;make your spunk come out green&quot;.
*'''The Interviewer''' (played by Chris Morris): conducting real interviews with celebrities such as [[Andrew Morton (writer)|Andrew Morton]] and [[Jerry Springer]], Morris confuses and mocks his subjects with ambiguous and odd questions.
*'''Mr. Ventham''' (played by [[Mark Heap]]): An extremely awkward man who requires one-to-one consultations with '''Mr. Reilly''' (played by David Cann), who seems to be his psychologist, for the most banal of matters.

The sketches not listed are often in the style of a documentary; characters speak as if being interviewed about a recent event. In one sketch, a character voiced by Morris describes a man attempting to commit suicide by jumping off a second-story balcony repeatedly; in another, an angry man (Eldon) shouts about how his car, after being picked up from the garage, is only four feet long.

===Radio stings===
Morris included a series of 'radio stings', bizarre sequences of sounds and prose as a parody of modern DJs' own soundbites and self-advertising pieces. Each one revolves around a contemporary DJ, such as [[Chris Moyles]], [[Jo Whiley]] and [[Mark Goodier]], typically involving each DJ dying in a graphic way or going mad in some form – for example, Chris Moyles covering himself in jam and hanging himself from the top of a building.

==Episodes==

Three series were produced, with a total of eighteen episodes. All episodes were originally broadcast weekly on BBC Radio 1. Series 1 was broadcast from 14 November to 19 December 1997; series 2 was broadcast from 27 March to 1 May 1998; and series 3 broadcast from 21 January to 25 February 1999.

*Series 1 – (Fridays) 14 November 1997 to 19 December 1997, from 00:00 to 01:00.
*Series 2 – (Fridays) 27 March 1998 to 1 May 1998, from 01:00 to 02:00.
*Series 3 – (Thursdays) 21 January 1999 to 25 February 1999, from 00:00 to 01:00.

The first five episodes of series 1 of ''Blue Jam'' were repeated by [[BBC Radio 4 Extra]] in February and March 2014, and series 2 was rebroadcast in December.&lt;ref name=&quot;Plunkett&quot;/&gt;

{{Episode table
|background=#1254A4
|overall= 1 |title= 4
|episodes=

{{Episode list
|EpisodeNumber   = 1.1
|Title           = ee arth welcome
|ShortSummary   = Sketches include: The Gun &amp; The Gibbon monologue, babies fighting each other, Radio 1 ''[[Newsbeat]]'', and the Doctor kissing things to make them better. Includes music from [[Björk]], [[Apollo 440]], [[Serge Gainsbourg]] and [[Brigitte Bardot]], [[Eels (band)|Eels]] and [[Massive Attack]].
|LineColor       = 1254A4
}}
{{Episode list
|EpisodeNumber   = 1.2
|Title           = oo ab welcome
|ShortSummary   = Sketches include: a man convinced he's a baby trapped in the body of a man, Conceptual Art monologue, an unusual acupuncture practice, and Bad Sex. Includes music from [[DJ Shadow]], [[Aphex Twin]], Naked Funk, and [[D'Angelo]].
|LineColor       = 1254A4
}}
{{Episode list
|EpisodeNumber   = 1.3
|Title           = oo mug welcome
|ShortSummary   = Sketches include: the Doctor getting very angry over a pulled tendon, a man asking for a pay rise, a builder in a swimming bath with a strange ability, and Crime Reconstruction monologue. Includes music from [[Les Rhythmes Digitales]], [[Dubstar]], [[Baby Fox]], and [[Michael Franti|Spearhead]].
|LineColor       = 1254A4
}}
{{Episode list
|EpisodeNumber   = 1.4
|Title           = oo voof welcome
|ShortSummary   = Sketches include: Elephant monologue, a man very angry over his four-foot car, Michael Alexander St. John reading the dance chart, and a man robbing a store with a gun in his stomach. Includes music from [[Propellerheads]], [[Moloko]], Björk, and [[William Orbit]].
|LineColor       = 1254A4
}}
{{Episode list
|EpisodeNumber   = 1.5
|Title           = voo vak welcome
|ShortSummary   = Sketches include: [[London Dungeon]] monologue, three lawyer skits, the Doctor thinking a man is quite ugly, and an unorthodox children's birthday party. Includes music from [[Common (rapper)|Common]], [[Moby]], [[Beck]], and [[Portishead (band)|Portishead]].
|LineColor       = 1254A4
}}
{{Episode list
|EpisodeNumber   = 1.6
|Title           = oo vudge welcome
|ShortSummary   = This episode was cut short and cross-faded into the first episode during broadcast, as one of the skits - Morris's re-editing of the [[George Carey|Archbishop of Canterbury]]'s speech at [[Funeral of Diana, Princess of Wales|Princess Diana's funeral]] - was apparently deemed too offensive to broadcast. The sketch was replaced and the new re-edited episode was aired as episode 2.1; this episode, 1.6, consists of the first 13 minutes of episode 2.1, the &quot;Bishopslips&quot; skit, and most of episode 1.1.
|LineColor       = 1254A4
}}
{{Episode list
|EpisodeNumber   = 2.1
|Title           = oo vudge welcome
|ShortSummary   = Sketches include: a little girl with the genitals of an older man, The Belt monologue, the Doctor pays a man to go away, and some unemployed Welshmen chat. Includes music from Massive Attack, Moloko, [[Sneaker Pimps]], and [[Ben Harper]].
|LineColor       = 1254A4
}}
{{Episode list
|EpisodeNumber   = 2.2
|Title           = oo thub welcome
|ShortSummary   = Sketches include: a four-year-old gangster girl, a couple has lizards in their television, Michael Alexander St. John reads the club news, and the Suicide Journalist monologue. Includes music from Aphex Twin, Propellerheads, [[Air (band)|Air,]] and [[Jim White (musician)|Jim White]].
|LineColor       = 1254A4
}}
{{Episode list
|EpisodeNumber   = 2.3
|Title           = oo taz welcome
|ShortSummary   = Sketches include: the four-year-old gangster girl returns, Mr Ventham has trouble with his pockets, the Doctor prescribes heroin, and a couple specializes in raising the dead. Includes music from [[Happy Mondays]], [[Jimi Tenor]], Serge Gainsbourg, and Moloko.
|LineColor       = 1254A4
}}
{{Episode list
|EpisodeNumber   = 2.4
|Title           = oo ziz welcome
|ShortSummary   = Sketches include: a penis-shaped nightlight, Rothko monologue, unnecessary operations, and The Gush. Includes music from [[Madonna (entertainer)|Madonna]], Air, [[Brian Eno]], and [[Imagination (band)|Imagination]].
|LineColor       = 1254A4
}}
{{Episode list
|EpisodeNumber   = 2.5
|Title           = ah zim pulz wah welcome
|ShortSummary   = Sketches include: a man with a special ticket for the zoo, more unemployed Welshmen, more Bad Sex, and the Doctor diagnoses symptomless comas. Includes music from Massive Attack, Spearhead, [[R.E.M.]], and [[Biosphere (musician)|Biosphere]].
|LineColor       = 1254A4
}}
{{Episode list
|EpisodeNumber   = 2.6
|Title           = ah ah moorz moorz welcome
|ShortSummary   = Sketches include: an interview with [[Jerry Springer]], a family with pet lions, a man who lives outdoors, and a thing in the sky. Includes music from Dubstar, Massive Attack, [[Akasha (band)|Akasha]], and [[Boards of Canada]].
|LineColor       = 1254A4
}}
{{Episode list
|EpisodeNumber   = 3.1
|Title           = package holiday welcome
|ShortSummary   = Sketches include: unusual foreplay, Sausage Street Vendors monologue, urine transfusions, and the Doctor hides. Includes music from [[Kool and the Gang]], Beck, [[Mr Scruff]], and [[Marvin Gaye]].
|LineColor       = 1254A4
}}
{{Episode list
|EpisodeNumber   = 3.2
|Title           = uh h-hm-hm-hmu welcome
|ShortSummary   = Sketches include: two parents sing a song for their missing child, a restaurant with an Ugly Weirdo policy, Michael Alexander St. John reads the dance news, and a woman calls the plumber. Includes music from [[Low (band)|Low]], [[Esthero]], Moloko, and [[Luke Vibert|Wagon Christ]].
|LineColor       = 1254A4
}}
{{Episode list
|EpisodeNumber   = 3.3
|Title           = oo costrinsi welcome
|ShortSummary   = Sketches include: Cigarettes monologue, someone possessed by [[Beethoven]], a zombie baby, and someone who has trouble starting conversations. Includes music from [[Matthew Herbert|Herbert]], Beck, [[Amon Tobin]], and [[PJ Harvey]].
|LineColor       = 1254A4
}}
{{Episode list
|EpisodeNumber   = 3.4
|Title           = har com plusian bezhley welcome
|ShortSummary   = Sketches include: a man who definitely has a willy, an employment agency for thick people, even more unemployed Welshmen, and open abdomen therapy. Includes music from [[Howie B]], Aphex Twin, [[Mercury Rev]], and [[Broadcast (band)|Broadcast]].
|LineColor       = 1254A4
}}
{{Episode list
|EpisodeNumber   = 3.5
|Title           = al trang un sabers welcome
|ShortSummary   = Sketches include: a man who hasn't cheated on his wife, Michael Alexander St. John reads a list of things that are cool, Suzy's Wedding monologue, and Chris Moyles commits suicide. Includes music from Sie, [[Whale (band)|Whale]], [[The Orb]], and Sons of Silence.
|LineColor       = 1254A4
}}
{{Episode list
|EpisodeNumber   = 3.6
|Title           = oo huxtapaz welcome
|ShortSummary   = The final episode of Blue Jam. Sketches include: more Bad Sex, a man tries to commit suicide with an escape clause, an idiot compound, and a man decapitates himself for art's sake. Includes music from [[Boom Boom Satellites]], [[Sade (singer)|Sade]], [[Black Star Liner]], and Aphex Twin.
|LineColor       = 1254A4
}}
}}

== Music ==

''Blue Jam'' features songs, generally of a [[downtempo]] nature, interspersed between (and sometimes during) sketches. Artists featured includes [[Massive Attack]], [[Air (French band)|Air]], [[Morcheeba]], [[The Chemical Brothers]], [[Björk]], [[Aphex Twin]], [[Everything But the Girl]] and [[Dimitri from Paris]], as well as various non-electronic artists including [[Sly and the Family Stone]], [[Serge Gainsbourg]], [[The Cardigans]] and [[Eels (band)|Eels]].

== Reception ==

''Blue Jam'' was favourably reviewed on several occasions by ''[[The Guardian]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Karpf |first=Anne |date=29 November 1997 |title=Morris After Midnight |newspaper=[[The Guardian]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |date=27 March 1998 |title=Kind of Blue |newspaper=[[The Guardian]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.theguardian.com/theobserver/1999/feb/07/featuresreview.review1 |title=He's Funny, Clever and Original. Why Is He on Radio 1? &lt;nowiki&gt;| From the Observer |&lt;/nowiki&gt; The Guardian |last=Arnold |first=Sue |date=8 February 1999 |website=[[The Guardian]] |accessdate=11 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Karpf |first=Anne |date=21 January 2001 |title=Tuning to Parallel Universe |newspaper=[[The Guardian]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; and also received a positive review by ''[[The Independent]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Lezard |first=Nicholas |date=23 February 1999 |title=Chris Morris – The Spoof Is Out There |newspaper=[[The Independent]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Digital Spy]] wrote in 2014: &quot;It's a heady cocktail that provokes an odd, unsettling reaction in the listener, yet ''Blue Jam'' is still thumpingly and frequently laugh-out-loud hilarious.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.digitalspy.com/showbiz/comedy/feature/a559343/blue-jam-an-ethereal-mix-of-ambient-music-and-detached-reasoning/ |title=''Blue Jam'': An Ethereal Mix of Ambient Music and Detached Reasoning |last=Kennedy |first=Neil |date=March 21, 2014 |website=[[Digital Spy]] |accessdate=May 16, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Hot Press]]'' called it &quot;as odd as comedy gets&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.hotpress.com/Chris-Morris/music/reviews/albums/Blue-Jam/477381.html |title=''Blue Jam'' &lt;nowiki&gt;| Music Review | Album |&lt;/nowiki&gt; Hot Press |last=O'Brien |first=Jonathan |date=23 November 2000 |website=[[Hot Press]] |accessdate=11 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== CD release ==
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:Blue Jam CD cover.jpg|thumb|right|200px|Cover of the ''Blue Jam'' CD.]] --&gt;

A [[Compact disc|CD]] of a number of ''Blue Jam'' sketches was released on 23 October 2000 by record label [[Warp Records|Warp]]. Although the CD claims to have 22 tracks, the last one, &quot;www.bishopslips.com&quot;, is not a track, but rather a reference to the &quot;Bishopslips&quot; sketch, which was cut in the middle of a broadcast. Most of the sketches on the CD were remade for ''[[Jam (TV series)|Jam]]''.

{{album ratings
| rev1 = [[AllMusic]]
| rev1score = {{rating|4.5|5}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.allmusic.com/album/blue-jam-mw0000536868 |title=''Blue Jam'' – Chris Morris &lt;nowiki&gt;| Songs, Reviews, Credits |&lt;/nowiki&gt; AllMusic |last=Carlson |first=Dean |website=[[AllMusic]] |accessdate=11 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| rev2 = ''[[NME]]''
| rev2Score = 8/10&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Segal |first=Victoria |url=https://www.nme.com/reviews/album/reviews-nme-3193 |title=Blue Jam |work=[[NME]] |accessdate=12 September 2005 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20190121170640/https://www.nme.com/reviews/album/reviews-nme-3193 |archivedate=January 21, 2019 |url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| rev3 = ''[[Select (magazine)|Select]]''
| rev3score = {{rating|4|5}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Mullen |first=John |date=November 2000 |title=[''Blue Jam'' review] |magazine=[[Select (magazine)|Select]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

; Track listing

# &quot;Blue Jam Intro&quot;
# &quot;Doc Phone&quot;
# &quot;Lamacq sting&quot;
# &quot;4&amp;nbsp;ft Car&quot;
# &quot;Suicide Journalist&quot;
# &quot;Acupuncture&quot;
# &quot;Bad Sex&quot;
# &quot;Mayo Sting&quot;
# &quot;Unflustered Parents&quot;
# &quot;Moyles Sting&quot;
# &quot;TV Lizards&quot;
# &quot;Doc Cock&quot;
# &quot;Hobbs Sting&quot;
# &quot;Morton Interview&quot;
# &quot;Fix It Girl&quot;
# &quot;Porn&quot;
# &quot;Kids Party&quot;
# &quot;Club News&quot;
# &quot;Whiley Sting&quot;
# &quot;Little Girl Balls&quot;
# &quot;Blue Jam Outro&quot;
# &quot;www.bishopslips.com&quot; (not a real track)

==Derivative shows==

''Blue Jam'' was later made for [[television]] and broadcast on [[Channel 4]] as ''[[Jam (TV series)|Jam]]''. It utilised unusual editing techniques to achieve an unnerving ambience in keeping with the radio show. Many of the sketches were lifted from the radio version, even to the extent of simply setting images to the radio soundtrack. A subsequent &quot;re-mixed&quot; airing, called ''Jaaaaam'' was even more extreme in its use of post-production gadgetry, often heavily distorting the footage.

''Blue Jam'' shares parallels with early editions of a US [[public radio]] show ''Joe Frank: Work in Progress'' from the mid-1980s, that [[Joe Frank]] did on the [[NPR]] affiliate station, [[KCRW]], in [[Santa Monica, California]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= https://curious.kcrw.com/2018/01/kcrw-remembers-radio-artist-joe-frank |title= KCRW remembers radio artist Joe Frank |last1= Artsy |first1= Avishay |date= January 18, 2018 |website= kcrw.com |access-date= June 2, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==

{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* {{Internet Archive|chrismorris_bluejam}}
*[https://www.bbc.co.uk/comedy/bluejam ''Blue Jam''] on the BBC Comedy site
*{{BBC programme}} – series 1 repeats on [[BBC Radio 4 Extra]]

{{Christopher Morris}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2011}}

[[Category:1997 radio programme debuts]]
[[Category:BBC Radio comedy programmes]]</text>
      <sha1>f8ez4ne6zwiek9m3a5mwq2ugdhvoysn</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
