  <page>
    <title>Convention of Kanagawa</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6365</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942952012</id>
      <parentid>936399866</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-27T22:04:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Marcocapelle</username>
        <id>14965160</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* External links */Removed grandparent category of [[Category:1854 in Japan]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|1854 treaty between Japan and the US}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=March 2019}}
{{Infobox treaty
| name                = Treaty of Kanagawa
| long_name           = Japan–US Treaty of Peace and Amity
| image               = Ratification of the Japan USA Treaty of Peace and Amity 21 February 1855.jpg
| image_width         = 180px
| caption             = Japanese copy of the Convention of Kanagawa, ratified February 21, 1855 
| type                = 
| date_drafted        = 
| date_signed         = {{Start date|1854|03|31|df=y}}
| location_signed     = [[Yokohama]], Japan
| date_sealed         = March 31, 1854
| date_effective      = September 30, 1855
| condition_effective = [[Ratification]] by US Congress and signing by [[Emperor Kōmei]] of Japan
| date_expiration     = 
| negotiators         = 
| signatories         = 
* [[Tokugawa shogunate|Japan]]
* [[United States]]
| depositor           = [[Diplomatic Record Office of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs (Japan)]]
| citations           = 
| languages           = 
* Chinese
* Japanese
* English
* Dutch
| wikisource          = Treaty of Kanagawa
}}
On March 31, 1854, the {{Nihongo|'''Convention of Kanagawa'''|日米和親条約|Nichibei Washin Jōyaku|&quot;Japan and US Treaty of Peace and Amity&quot;|lead=yes}} or {{Nihongo|'''Kanagawa Treaty'''|神奈川条約|Kanagawa Jōyaku}} became the first treaty between the United States and the Tokugawa shogunate.

[[Unequal treaty#Japan and Korea|Signed under threat of force]], it effectively meant the end of Japan's 220-year-old policy of national seclusion (''[[sakoku]]'') by opening the ports of [[Shimoda, Shizuoka|Shimoda]] and [[Hakodate]] to American vessels.&lt;ref&gt;Perry, Matthew Calbraith (1856). [http://ebook.lib.hku.hk/CTWE/B36599566/ ''Narrative of the expedition of an American Squadron to the China Seas and Japan, 1856''.]&lt;/ref&gt; It also ensured the safety of American [[castaway]]s and established the position of an American [[consul (representative)|consul]] in Japan. The treaty also precipitated the signing of similar treaties establishing diplomatic relations with other Western powers.

==Isolation of Japan==

Since the beginning of the seventeenth century, the Tokugawa shogunate pursued a policy of isolating the country from outside influences. Foreign trade was maintained only with the [[Netherlands|Dutch]] and the [[Qing Dynasty|Chinese]] and was conducted exclusively at [[Nagasaki, Nagasaki|Nagasaki]] under a strict government monopoly. This policy had two main objectives. One was the fear that trade with western powers and the spread of Christianity would serve as a pretext for the invasion of Japan by imperialist forces, as had been the case with most of the nations of Asia. The second objective was fear that foreign trade and the wealth developed would lead to the rise of a ''[[daimyō]]'' powerful enough to overthrow the ruling [[Tokugawa clan]].&lt;ref name=Beasley1&gt;W. G. Beasley, ''The Meiji Restoration'', pp. 74–77&lt;/ref&gt;

By the early nineteenth century, this policy of isolation was increasingly under challenge. In 1844, King [[William II of the Netherlands]] sent a letter urging Japan to end the isolation policy on its own before change would be forced from the outside. In 1846, an official American expedition led by Commodore [[James Biddle (commodore)|James Biddle]] arrived in Japan asking for ports to be opened for trade, but was sent away.&lt;ref name=Beasley2&gt;W. G. Beasley, ''The Meiji Restoration'', p. 78&lt;/ref&gt;

==Perry expedition==

In 1853, [[United States Navy]] Commodore [[Matthew C. Perry]] was sent with a fleet of warships by US president [[Millard Fillmore]] to force the opening of Japanese ports to American trade, through the use of [[gunboat diplomacy]] if necessary.&lt;ref&gt;J. W. Hall, ''Japan'', p. 207.&lt;/ref&gt; The growing commerce between America and China, the presence of American whalers in waters offshore Japan, and the increasing monopolization of potential [[fuelling station|coaling stations]] by the British and French in Asia were all contributing factors. The Americans were also driven by concepts of [[Manifest Destiny]] and the desire to impose the benefits of western civilization on what they perceived as backward Asian nations. For the Japanese standpoint, increasing contacts with foreign warships and the increasing disparity between western military technology and the Japanese feudal armies created growing concern. The Japanese had been keeping abreast of world events via information gathered from Dutch traders in [[Dejima]] and had been forewarned by the Dutch of Perry's voyage.&lt;ref&gt;W. G. Beasley, ''The Meiji Restoration'', p. 88.&lt;/ref&gt; There was considerable internal debate in Japan on how best to meet this potential threat to Japan's economic and political sovereignty in light of events occurring in China with the [[Opium Wars]].

Perry arrived with four warships at [[Uraga, Kanagawa|Uraga]], at the mouth of [[Edo Bay]] on July 8, 1853. After refusing Japanese demands that he proceed to Nagasaki, which was the designated port for foreign contact, and after threatening to continue directly on to [[Edo]], the nation's capital, and to burn it to the ground if necessary, he was allowed to land at nearby [[Kurihama, Yokosuka|Kurihama]] on July 14 and to deliver his letter.&lt;ref&gt;W. G. Beasley, ''The Meiji Restoration'', p. 89.&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite years of debate on the isolation policy, Perry's letter created great controversy within the highest levels of the Tokugawa shogunate. The ''shōgun'' himself, [[Tokugawa Ieyoshi]], died days after Perry's departure, and was succeeded by his sickly young son, [[Tokugawa Iesada]], leaving effective administration in the hands of the Council of Elders (''[[rōjū]]'') led by [[Abe Masahiro]]. Abe felt that it was currently impossible for Japan to resist the American demands by military force, and yet was reluctant to take any action on his own authority for such an unprecedented situation. Attempting to legitimize any decision taken, Abe polled all of the ''[[daimyō]]'' for their opinions. This was the first time that the Tokugawa shogunate had allowed its decision-making to be a matter of public debate, and had the unforeseen consequence of portraying the shogunate as weak and indecisive.&lt;ref&gt;J. W. Hall, ''Japan'', p. 211.&lt;/ref&gt; The results of the poll also failed to provide Abe with an answer as, of the 61 known responses, 19 were in favor of accepting the American demands and 19 were equally opposed. Of the remainder, 14 gave vague responses expressing concern of possible war, 7 suggested making temporary concessions and two advised that they would simply go along with whatever was decided.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;W. G. Beasley, ''The Meiji Restoration'', pp. 90–95.&lt;/ref&gt;

Perry returned again on February 13, 1854, with an even larger force of eight warships and made it clear that he would not be leaving until a treaty was signed. Negotiations began on March 8 and proceeded for around one month. The Japanese side gave in to almost all of Perry's demands, with the exception of a commercial agreement modeled after previous American treaties with China, which Perry agreed to defer to a later time. The main controversy centered on the selection of the ports to open, with Perry adamantly rejecting Nagasaki. The treaty, written in English, Dutch, Chinese and Japanese, was signed on March 31, 1854 at what is now known as Kaikō Hiroba (Port Opening Square) [[Yokohama]], a site adjacent to the current [[Yokohama Archives of History]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;

==Treaty of Peace and Amity (1854)==
[[File:KanagawaTreaty.gif|thumb|English text of the Kanagawa Treaty]]
The &quot;Japan–US Treaty of Peace and Amity&quot; has twelve articles: 
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Article
! Summary
|-
| § I
| Mutual peace between the United States and the Empire of Japan
|-
| § II
| Opening of the ports of [[Shimoda, Shizuoka|Shimoda]] &amp; [[Hakodate]]
|-
| § III 
| Assistance to be provided to shipwrecked American sailors
|-
| § IV
| Shipwrecked sailors not to be imprisoned or mistreated
|-
| § V
| Freedom of movement for temporary foreign residents in treaty ports (with limitations)&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.nytimes.com/1855/10/18/archives/from-washingtin-the-japanese-treatyits-advantages-and.html  &quot;From Washington; The Japanese Treaty-Its Advantages and Disadvantages-The President and Col. Rinney, &amp;c.,&quot;] ''New York Times.'' October 18, 1855.&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| § VI 
| Trade transactions to be permitted 
|-
| § VII
| Currency exchange to facilitate any trade transactions to be allowed
|-
| § VIII
| Provisioning of American ships to be a Japanese government monopoly 
|-
| § IX
| Japan to also give the United States any favorable advantages which might be negotiated by Japan with any other foreign government in the future
|-
| § X
| Forbids the United States from using any other ports aside from Shimoda and Hakodate
|-
| § XI
| Opening of an American consulate at Shimoda
|-
| § XII
| Treaty to be ratified within 18 months of signing
|}

The final article, Article Twelve, stipulated that the terms of the treaty were to be ratified by the [[President of the United States]] and the &quot;August Sovereign of Japan&quot; within 18 months. At the time, ''[[shōgun]]'' [[Tokugawa Iesada]] was the de facto ruler of Japan; for the [[Emperor of Japan|Emperor]] to interact in any way with foreigners was out of the question. Perry concluded the treaty with representatives of the shogun, led by plenipotentiary {{nihongo|[[Hayashi Akira]]|林韑}} and the text was endorsed subsequently, albeit reluctantly, by [[Emperor Kōmei]].&lt;ref&gt;Cullen, Louis M. (2003). ''A History of Japan, 1582–1941: Internal and External Worlds'', pp. 173–185.&lt;/ref&gt;
The treaty was ratified on February 21, 1855.&lt;ref&gt;[[Diplomatic Record Office of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs (Japan)]] exhibit.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Consequences of the treaty==
{{History of Japan |periods|}}

In the short term, the US was content with the agreement since Perry had achieved his primary objective of breaking Japan's ''sakoku'' policy and setting the grounds for protection of American citizens and an eventual commercial agreement. On the other hand, the Japanese were forced into this trade, and many saw it as a sign of weakness. The Tokugawa shogunate could point out that the treaty was not actually signed by the Shogun, or indeed any of his ''rōjū'', and that it had at least temporarily averted the possibility of immediate military confrontation.&lt;ref&gt;W. G. Beasly, ''The Meiji Restoration'', pp. 96–97&lt;/ref&gt;

Externally, the treaty led to the [[Treaty of Amity and Commerce (United States–Japan)|United States-Japan Treaty of Amity and Commerce]], the &quot;Harris Treaty&quot; of 1858, which allowed the establishment of foreign concessions, [[extraterritoriality]] for foreigners, and minimal import taxes for foreign goods. The Japanese chafed under the &quot;[[unequal treaty]] system&quot; which characterized Asian and western relations during this period.&lt;ref&gt;Bert Edström, Bert. (2000). [https://books.google.com/books?id=ltmXn9rUGD8C&amp;pg=PA101&amp;dq=unequal+treaty+japan&amp;lr=#PPA101,M1  ''The Japanese and Europe: Images and Perceptions,'' pp. 101.]&lt;/ref&gt; The Kanagawa treaty was also followed by similar agreements with the [[United Kingdom]] ([[Anglo-Japanese Friendship Treaty]], October 1854), the [[Russians]] ([[Treaty of Shimoda]], February 7, 1855), and the [[French people|French]] ([[Treaty of Amity and Commerce between France and Japan]], October 9, 1858).

Internally, the treaty had far-reaching consequences. Decisions to suspend previous restrictions on military activities led to re-armament by many domains and further weakened the position of the Shogun.&lt;ref&gt;J. W. Hall, ''Japan'', pp. 211–213.&lt;/ref&gt; Debate over foreign policy and popular outrage over perceived appeasement to the foreign powers was a catalyst for the ''[[sonnō jōi]]'' movement and a shift in political power from Edo back to the Imperial Court in [[Kyoto]]. The opposition of Emperor Kōmei to the treaties further lent support to the ''tōbaku'' (overthrow the Shogunate) movement, and eventually to the [[Meiji Restoration]].

==Kanagawa Treaty House==
The Convention was negotiated and then signed in a purpose-built house in [[Yokohama]], Japan, the site of which is now the [[Yokohama Archives of History]].{{cn|date=March 2019}}

==See also==
* [[Hayashi Akira]]
* [[Sō Yoshiyori]]
* [[Sakoku]]
* [[List of Westerners who visited Japan before 1868]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==References==
*{{cite thesis|author=Arnold, Bruce Makoto|title=Diplomacy Far Removed: A Reinterpretation of the U.S. Decision to Open Diplomatic Relations with Japan|publisher=University of Arizona|year=2005}} [https://www.academia.edu/5461862/Diplomacy_Far_Removed_A_Reinterpretation_of_the_U.S._Decision_to_Open_Diplomatic_Relations_with_Japan]
* [[Michael Auslin|Auslin, Michael R.]] (2004). [https://books.google.com/books?id=bS3w6tGiraEC&amp;dq=   ''Negotiating with Imperialism: The Unequal Treaties and the Culture of Japanese Diplomacy.''] Cambridge: [[Harvard University Press]]. {{ISBN|978-0-674-01521-0}}; {{OCLC|56493769}}
* Bert Edström, Bert. (2000). [https://books.google.com/books?id=ltmXn9rUGD8C  ''The Japanese and Europe: Images and Perceptions.''] London: [[Routledge]]. {{ISBN|978-1-873410-86-8}}
* Cullen, L. M. (2003). [https://books.google.com/books?id=ycY_85OInSoC&amp;client=firefox-a  ''A History of Japan, 1582–1941: Internal and External Worlds.''] Cambridge: [[Cambridge University Press]]. {{ISBN|0-521-52918-2}} (paper)
* [[Matthew Calbraith Perry|Perry]], Matthew Calbraith. (1856). [http://ebook.lib.hku.hk/CTWE/B36599566/ ''Narrative of the expedition of an American Squadron to the China Seas and Japan, 1856.''] New York : D. Appleton and Company. [digitized by [[University of Hong Kong]] Libraries, [http://lib.hku.hk/database/ Digital Initiatives,] [https://web.archive.org/web/20070425165629/http://www.spurgeons.ac.uk/site/pages/ui_college_history.aspx &quot;China Through Western Eyes.&quot;] ]
* [[Bayard Taylor|Taylor]], Bayard. (1855). [http://ebook.lib.hku.hk/CTWE/B29624824/ A visit to India, China, and Japan in the year 1853] New York : G.P. Putnam's sons. digitized by [[University of Hong Kong]] [[University of Hong Kong#Libraries|Libraries]], [http://lib.hku.hk/database/ Digital Initiatives], [https://web.archive.org/web/20070425165629/http://www.spurgeons.ac.uk/site/pages/ui_college_history.aspx &quot;China Through Western Eyes&quot;.]
*{{cite book | last = Beasley| first = William G|authorlink= | year = 1972 | title = The Meiji Restoration| publisher = Stamford University Press | location = |isbn=978-0804708159| id = }}
*{{cite book | last = Hall| first = John Whitney|authorlink= | year = 1991| title = Japan: From Prehistory to Modern Times| publisher = University of Michigan | location = |isbn=978-0939512546| id = }}

==External links==
{{commons category}}
{{Wikisource|Treaty of Kanagawa}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20060910135838/http://web.jjay.cuny.edu/jobrien/reference/ob25.html The Convention of Kanagawa, 1854 (full text)]
* [https://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1525/si.1986.9.1.53?seq=1#page_scan_tab_contents Kitahara, Michio. Commodore Perry and the Japanese: A Study in the Dramaturgy of Power, 1986]
* [http://dl.lib.brown.edu/japan/index.html Perry Visits Japan: A Visual History; Brown University collection]
{{Spoken Wikipedia|En-ConventionofKanagawa-article.ogg|2017-12-02}}

{{Treaties of Japan}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Convention Of Kanagawa}}
[[Category:Japan–United States treaties]]
[[Category:History of the United States (1849–65)]]
[[Category:Unequal treaties]]
[[Category:1854 in Japan]]
[[Category:1854 treaties]]
[[Category:Treaties of the Tokugawa shogunate]]
[[Category:March 1854 events]]</text>
      <sha1>ig7q7kbvb6r5htr0lhpybo5zqp36f76</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
