  <page>
    <title>Blue Steel (missile)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4777</id>
    <revision>
      <id>881831961</id>
      <parentid>881831569</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-02-05T02:45:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>BilCat</username>
        <id>2043601</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 881831569 by [[Special:Contributions/2601:285:400:FA59:65F6:5DFA:34BA:B6E1|2601:285:400:FA59:65F6:5DFA:34BA:B6E1]] ([[User talk:2601:285:400:FA59:65F6:5DFA:34BA:B6E1|talk]]) not used in a hot conflict, better to leave blank</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{refimprove |date=November 2010}}
&lt;!--SCROLL DOWN IN ORDER TO EDIT THE ARTICLE--&gt;
{{Infobox weapon
|is_missile=yes
|is_UK=yes
| image= Blue Steel missile.png
| image_size = 300
|caption=Blue Steel missile
|name=Blue Steel
|type=Nuclear stand-off missile
|origin= United Kingdom
|era=Cold War
|launch_platform=Aircraft
|target=
|manufacturer=[[Avro]]
|design_date=
|production_date=
|service=1963-1970
|used_by=UK [[Royal Air Force]]
|wars=
|spec_type=
|diameter=1.22 m (48 in) minimum
|wingspan={{convert|4|m|ftin|abbr=on}}
|length= {{convert|10.7|m|ftin|abbr=on}}
|weight= {{convert|17,000|lb|kg|abbr=on}} &lt;ref&gt;Barry Jones, ''V-bombers: Valiant, Vulcan and Victor'', Crowood Press, 2000, p.134-139&lt;/ref&gt;
|speed=Mach 3+&lt;ref name=&quot;BCAR_BSM&quot;&gt;{{cite |url=http://www.bcar.org.uk/blue-steel-missile |title=Avro Blue Steel Nuclear Missile | |website=Bomber County Aviation Resource}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|vehicle_range={{convert|926|km|mi|abbr=on}}&lt;ref name=&quot;BCAR_BSM&quot;/&gt;
|ceiling= {{convert|21500|m|ft|abbr=on}}
|filling=[[Red Snow]] ([[W28]]) [[thermonuclear weapon]] (1.1 [[TNT equivalent|megaton]])
|engine=[[Armstrong Siddeley Stentor]] [[Liquid-propellant rocket]]
|steering=Movable [[flight control surfaces]]
|guidance=[[Inertial navigation system]]
|variants=One/mod for low-level delivery
|number=53 operational live rounds
}}

The [[Avro]] '''Blue Steel''' was a British air-launched, rocket-propelled [[nuclear weapon|nuclear armed]] [[standoff missile]], built to arm the [[V bomber]] force. It allowed the bomber to launch the missile against its target while still outside the range of [[surface-to-air missile]]s (SAMs). The missile proceeded to the target at speeds up to [[Mach number|Mach]] 3, and would trigger within 100&amp;nbsp;m of the pre-defined target point.

Blue Steel entered service in 1963, by which point improved SAMs with longer range had greatly eroded the advantages of the design. A longer-range version, Blue Steel II, was considered, but cancelled in favour of the much longer-range [[GAM-87 Skybolt]] system from the US. When development of that system was cancelled in 1962, the V-bomber fleet was considered highly vulnerable. Blue Steel remained the primary British nuclear deterrent weapon until the [[Royal Navy]] started operating [[Polaris missile|Polaris]] ballistic missiles from [[Resolution-class submarine|''Resolution''-class submarines]].

==Development==
[[File:Avro blue steel front 9m07.JPG|right|thumb|Avro Blue Steel nuclear missile (front) at the [[Midland Air Museum]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.midlandairmuseum.co.uk/aircraft.php| title= Midland Air Museum|accessdate = 16 March 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
[[File:Avro blue steel side 9m07.JPG|right|thumb|Avro Blue Steel missile (side view) at the Midland Air Museum behind the wing of an Avro Vulcan bomber]]
[[File:BlueSteelMissileRear.JPG|right|thumb|Rear view of Blue Steel missile at [[RAF Cosford]] aerospace museum, showing the twin-chamber &quot;Stentor&quot; rocket motor]]

Blue Steel was the result of a [[Ministry of Supply (United Kingdom)|Ministry of Supply]] memorandum from 5 November 1954 that predicted that by 1960 [[Soviet Union|Soviet]] air defences would make it impossible for V bombers to attack with nuclear [[gravity bomb]]s. The answer was for a [[rocket engine|rocket-powered]], [[supersonic]] missile capable of carrying a large nuclear (or projected [[thermonuclear]]) [[warhead]] with a range of at least {{convert|50|mi|km|abbr=on}}. This would keep the bombers out of range of Soviet ground-based defences installed around the target area, allowing the missile to &quot;dash&quot; in at high speed.

There would have to be a balance between the size of the warhead, the need for it to be carried by any of the three V-bomber types in use, and that it should be able to reach Mach 3. At the time the only strategic warhead available in the UK was the [[Green Bamboo]], which was very large and so required a large missile fuselage to carry it. The [[Air Staff (United Kingdom)|Air Staff]] issued this requirement for a ''stand-off bomb'' as OR.1132 in September 1954.&lt;ref name=&quot;BSP&quot;&gt;Gibson, Buttler T ''British Secret Projects: Hypersonics, Ramjets and Missiles'' Midland Publishing 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

The Ministry of Supply selected [[Avro]] out of the British manufacturers, although it had no experience in working on guided weapons other than some private venture work; [[Handley Page]] had suggested a {{convert|500|nmi|km|abbr=on}} missile, but the [[Elliott Brothers (computer company)|Elliots]] gyro based guidance system was inaccurate beyond {{convert|100|nmi|km|abbr=on}}. Avro began work proper in 1955, with the assigned [[Rainbow Code]] name of &quot;Blue Steel&quot; which it would keep in service. With Elliots working on the guidance system, [[Armstrong Siddeley]] would develop the liquid fuel engine. The design period was protracted, with various development problems exacerbated by the fact that designers lacked information on the actual size and weight of the proposed [[boosted fission weapon|boosted fission warhead]] Green Bamboo, or its likely thermonuclear successor derived from the Granite series. The large girth of Blue Steel was determined by the {{convert|45|in|m}} implosion sphere diameter of Green Bamboo.

Avro proposed that Blue Steel would evolve over time, subsequent versions increasing speed (to Mach 4.5) and range. The ultimate Blue Steel would be a {{convert|900|nmi|km|abbr=on}} range weapon that could be launched by the supersonic [[Avro 730]] under development. They were told to limit themselves to the specification of OR.1132.&lt;ref name=&quot;BSP&quot;/&gt; The project was delayed by the need to develop the required [[stainless steel]] fabrication techniques; this would have been gained in building the Avro 730 but that had been cancelled by then. The Elliots guidance system was plagued by accuracy problems, delaying test flights.

As it turned out, neither of the originally-proposed UK-designed warheads were actually fitted, being superseded by [[Red Snow]], an Anglicised variant of the U.S. [[B28 nuclear bomb|W-28 thermonuclear warhead]] of 1.1 Mt yield. Red Snow was smaller and lighter than the earlier warhead proposals. The missile was fitted with a state-of-the-art [[inertial navigation]] unit. This system allowed the missile to strike within 100 metres of its designated target. In addition, the pilots of the [[Avro Vulcan]] or [[Handley Page Victor]] bombers could tie their systems into those of the missile and make use of the guidance system to help plot their own flight plan, since the unit in the missile was more advanced than that in the aircraft.

Blue Steel emerged as a pilotless, winged aircraft roughly the size of the experimental [[Saunders-Roe SR.53]] [[interceptor aircraft|interceptor]], with clipped [[delta wing]]s and small [[Canard (aeronautics)|canard]] foreplanes. It was powered by a two-chamber [[Armstrong Siddeley]] [[Armstrong Siddeley Stentor|Stentor Mark 101]] rocket engine, burning a combination of [[hydrogen peroxide]] and [[kerosene]]. The fuel was a considerable operational problem, because fuelling the missile before launch took nearly half an hour, and was quite hazardous.  It required the fuelling site to be flooded with water, and (during the trials campaigns) very early morning preparations because of the heat experienced during Australian summer. Another issue was the very small ground clearance when attached to the Handley Page Victor, and Victor aircrews were especially aware of the dangers when taking off.  (The Vulcan had a much higher ground clearance, and ultimately proved a better platform).

On launch the rocket engine's first chamber developing {{convert|24000|lbf|kN|abbr=on}} thrust would power the missile along a predetermined course to the target at around [[Mach number|Mach]] 1.5. Once close to the target, the second chamber of the engine (6,000&amp;nbsp;lb) would accelerate the missile to Mach 3. Over the target the engine would cut out and the missile would free-fall before detonating its warhead as an [[air burst]].

To speed the trials at [[Woomera Test Range|Woomera]], the test rounds were flown there by Victors and Vulcans in Operation Blue Ranger. The trials began in 1960 about the time the original requirement expected the weapon to be in service.  The missiles were prepared at the Weapons Research Establishment near Salisbury South Australia, and flown to be launched at the Woomera range from RAAF Edinburgh. A specialist RAF unit, 4 JSTU, was established to carry out preparatory and operational tasks.

Blue Steel finally entered service in February [[1963 in aviation|1963]], carried by [[Avro Vulcan|Vulcans]] and [[Handley Page Victor|Victors]], although its limitations were already apparent. The short range of the missile meant that the V bombers were still vulnerable to enemy [[surface-to-air missile]]s. A replacement for Blue Steel, the Mark 2, was planned with increased range and a [[ramjet]] engine, but was cancelled in [[1960 in aviation|1960]] to minimise delays to the Mk.1. The UK sought to acquire the much longer-ranged [[United States Air Force]] [[AGM-48 Skybolt]] air-launched ballistic missile, and was greatly frustrated when that weapon was cancelled in late [[1962 in aviation|1962]].

Blue Steel required up to seven hours of launch preparation, and was highly unreliable. The Royal Air Force estimated in 1963 that half the missiles would fail to fire and would have to be dropped over their targets, contradicting their purpose of serving as standoff weapons. Even as it deployed Blue Steel, a high-altitude weapon, that year the government decided that because of anti-aircraft missiles' increasing effectiveness, V bombers would have to convert from high-altitude to low-altitude attacks.  These trials were conducted in 1964  and concluded in 1965&lt;ref name=&quot;baylis1995&quot;&gt;{{cite book | title=Ambiguity and Deterrence: British Nuclear Strategy 1945-1964 | publisher=Clarendon Press | author=Baylis, John | year=1995 | location=Oxford | isbn=0-19-828012-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|349–351}} With no effective long-range weapon the original Blue Steel served on after a crash programme of minor modifications to permit a low-level launch at {{convert|1000|ft|m|abbr=on}}, even though its usefulness in a hot war was likely limited. A stop-gap weapon ([[WE.177]]B) was quickly produced to extend the life of the V-bomber force in the strategic role until the Polaris missile was deployed. This WE.177 [[Laydown delivery|laydown weapon]] supplemented the remaining modified Blue Steel missiles, using a low-level penetration followed by a pop-up manoeuvre to release the weapon at {{convert|1000|ft|m|abbr=on}}. One live operational round was deployed on each of forty-eight Vulcan and Victor bombers, and a further five live rounds were produced as operational spares. An additional four non-nuclear rounds were produced for various RAF requirements, and there were sixteen other unspecified training rounds.

Blue Steel was officially retired on 31 December 1970, with the United Kingdom's strategic nuclear capacity passing to the [[submarine]] fleet.

==Operator==
; {{UK}}
* [[Royal Air Force]] - ([[V bomber]]s)

==Specifications==
* '''Length''': {{convert|10.7|m|ft|abbr=on}}
* '''Wingspan''': {{convert|4|m|ft|abbr=on}}
* '''Diameter''': 1.22 m (48&amp;nbsp;in) minimum
* '''Launch Weight''': {{convert|7270|lb|kg|abbr=on}}
* '''Speed''': Mach 2.3
* '''Ceiling''': {{convert|21500|m|ft|abbr=on}}
* '''Maximum Range''': {{convert|240|km|mi|abbr=on}}
* '''Guidance''': Inertial
* '''[[circular error probable|CEP]]''': ~100 metres
* '''Warhead''': [[Red Snow]] [[thermonuclear]] (1.1 Mt)

==See also==
*[[Rainbow Codes]]
*[[AGM-28 Hound Dog]]
*[[Raduga Kh-22]]

==References==
;Notes
{{reflist}}
;Bibliography

==External links==
{{Commons category|Blue Steel missile|Blue Steel (missile)}}
*[http://www.sonicbomb.com/v1.php?vid=military/bluesteel.wmv&amp;id=352&amp;ttitle=Avro%20Blue%20steel Video of Blue Steel in operation]{{dead link|date=June 2013}}
*http://www.spaceuk.org/bsteel/bsteel.htm
*https://web.archive.org/web/20040208232113/http://www.skomer.u-net.com/projects/bluesteel.htm
*Official history: RAF Nuclear Deterrent Forces: Author: Wynne. pps 201. 456. {{ISBN|0-11-772833-0}}. Publisher: HMSO, 1994.
*http://www.globalsecurity.org/wmd/world/uk/blue_steel.htm
*https://web.archive.org/web/20061209210406/http://www.vectorsite.net/twcruz.html
*[http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1959/1959%20-%200491.html ''The Vulcan Gets New Striking Power''] an AVRO advertisement for the Vulcan from ''[[Flight International|Flight]]'' in February 1959, showing the (still unnamed) Blue Steel.
*[http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1960/1960%20-%201302.html &quot;Blue Steel And Its Engine&quot;] a 1960 ''Flight'' article on the Blue Steel

{{UKmissiles}}
{{UKColdWarProjects}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2011}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Blue Steel (Missile)}}
[[Category:Cold War air-to-surface missiles of the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Nuclear air-to-surface missiles]]
[[Category:Nuclear weapons of the United Kingdom]]</text>
      <sha1>oj70ncdlpx50ulswn38hy059uns84qm</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
