  <page>
    <title>Ballad of the Green Berets</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4760</id>
    <revision>
      <id>940729685</id>
      <parentid>932159705</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-14T06:50:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>EmmanuelMS</username>
        <id>38544639</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Charts */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=June 2014}}
{{Infobox song
| name
       = 
The Ballad of the Green Berets
| cover      = Ballad of the Green Berets.jpg
| alt        =
| type       = single
| artist     = [[Barry Sadler]]
| album      = Ballads of the Green Berets
| B-side     = Letter from Vietnam
| released   = January 1966
| format     =
| recorded   = December 1965
| studio     =
| venue      =
| genre      = [[Country music|Country]], [[folk music|folk]], [[pop music|pop]]
| length     = 2:27
| label      = [[RCA Victor]]
| writer     = [[Robin Moore]], [[Staff Sergeant|Staff Sgt.]] [[Barry Sadler]]
| producer   = Andy Wiswell&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.discogs.com/SSgt-Barry-Sadler-The-Ballad-Of-The-Green-Berets/release/1472846|title=SSgt. Barry Sadler* - The Ballad Of The Green Berets|work=Discogs}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| prev_title =
| prev_year  =
| next_title = The 'A' Team
| next_year  = 1966
}}

'''&quot;The Ballad of the Green Berets&quot;''' is a patriotic song in the [[ballad (music)|ballad]] style about the [[United States Army Special Forces]]. It is one of the few popular songs of the Vietnam War years to cast the military in a positive light and in 1966 became a major hit, reaching No. 1 for five weeks on the [[Billboard Hot 100|''Billboard'' Hot 100]] and four weeks on [[Cashbox (magazine)|Cashbox]].  It was also a crossover smash, reaching No. 1 on ''Billboard's'' Easy Listening chart and No. 2 on ''Billboard's'' Country survey.  Ultimately, the song was named [[Billboard Year-End Hot 100 singles of 1966|Billboard's #1 single for the year 1966]] in a revised end-of-the-year chart, but the original chart showed &quot;[[California Dreamin']]&quot; by [[The Mamas and the Papas]] at #1 and &quot;Ballad of the Green Berets&quot; at #10.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[https://www.americanradiohistory.com/Archive-Billboard/60s/1966/Billboard%201966-12-24.pdf Top Records of 1966]&quot; [[Billboard (magazine)|Billboard]] December 24, 1966, p. 34. Retrieved March 7, 2019.&lt;/ref&gt;  The two songs tied for #1 on the Cashbox end-of-the-year survey for 1966.

The song was written by then [[Staff Sergeant|Staff Sgt.]] [[Barry Sadler]], beginning when he was training to be a Special Forces medic. The author Robin Moore, who wrote the book, ''The Green Berets'', helped Sadler write the lyrics and get a recording contract with RCA Records.

The lyrics were written, in part, in honor of U.S. Army Specialist 5 James Gabriel, Jr., a Special Forces operator and the first [[native Hawaiian]] to die in Vietnam, who was killed by [[Viet Cong]] gunfire while on a training mission with the South Vietnamese Army on April 8, 1962.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last=Mizutani | first=Ron | title=First Native Hawaiian Killed in Vietnam Conflict Honored | date=May 18, 2010 | work=KHON2.com | publisher=[[KHON-TV]] | url=http://www.khon2.com/content/news/developingstories/story/First-Native-Hawaiian-Killed-in-Vietnam-Conflict/iSrtWYe-DEmrkW4dYH_m2Q.cspx | accessdate=March 12, 2011 | url-status=dead | archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110616211947/http://www.khon2.com/content/news/developingstories/story/First-Native-Hawaiian-Killed-in-Vietnam-Conflict/iSrtWYe-DEmrkW4dYH_m2Q.cspx | archivedate=June 16, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; One verse mentioned Gabriel by name, but it was not used in the recorded version.&lt;ref&gt;''I'm a Lucky One'' by Staff Sgt. Barry Sadler (Macmillan 1967, pp.&amp;nbsp;80–81)&lt;/ref&gt;

Sadler recorded the song and eleven other tunes in New York in December 1965. The song and album, &quot;Ballads of the Green Berets,&quot; were released in January 1966. He performed the song on television on January 30, 1966 on ''[[The Ed Sullivan Show]]'', and on other TV shows including ''Hollywood Palace'' and ''The Jimmy Dean Show''.

== Popularity ==
The song was the No. 1 hit in the U.S. for the five weeks, spanning March 1966 and the No. 1 hit on the ''[[Cashbox (magazine)|Cashbox]]'' end of the year chart for 1966; also the No. 21 song of the 1960s as ranked by [[Joel Whitburn]]. The single sold more than nine million copies; the album, more than two million. 

&quot;The Ballad of the Green Berets&quot; is currently used as one of the four primary [[marching band|marching tunes]] of the [[Fightin' Texas Aggie Band]].

== In film ==
The song is heard in a choral rendition by [[Ken Darby]] in the 1968 [[John Wayne]] film, ''[[The Green Berets (film)|The Green Berets]]'', based on [[Robin Moore]]'s book. The film's score was not released as an album until ''[[Film Score Monthly]]'' released it in 2005. A movie [[tie-in]] featuring artwork from the film and a [[cover version]] by [[Ennio Morricone]] was released in Europe, though the album's other tracks were from ''[[A Fistful of Dollars]]'' and ''[[For a Few Dollars More]]''.

The song appears in the films ''[[More American Graffiti]]'' and ''[[Canadian Bacon]]''. It can also be heard in the gun show scene of the 2002 film ''[[Showtime (film)|Showtime]]'', and in the film ''[[Jesus' Son]]'', in a scene that features a hitch-hiking [[Jack Black]].

A vinyl copy of &quot;The Ballad of the Green Berets&quot; makes a brief appearance in ''[[The Simpsons]]'' episode &quot;[[Homer's Phobia]]&quot;, from the show's eighth season. Guest star and filmmaker [[John Waters (filmmaker)|John Waters]] is seen near the five-minute mark flipping through Homer and Marge's record collection; Sadler's hit is amongst them.

Bill Murray briefly sang &quot;Green Berets&quot; in the 1980 film ''[[Caddyshack]]'' during his final attempt to kill the gopher.

The cast of the 2018 movie ''[[12 Strong]]'' sing the tune as their Chinook helicopter takes off.

== Other versions derivatives ==
Many other American recording artists did their own versions of the song ranging from [[Kate Smith]] and [[Duane Eddy]] to unknown artists singing on various [[drugstore records]].

The punk rock band [[The F.U.'s]] included their version of the song on their album ''[[This Is Boston, Not L.A.]]''

Many versions in other languages are rewritten to reference local units; these include:
* A German version (''Hundert Mann und ein Befehl''), sung by [[Freddy Quinn]] and later again by [[Heidi Brühl]] had considerable success in [[Germany]]. The German version is a song ''against'' the war. It rejects any sacrifice, not only for the son, but for the father as well. [[Freddy Quinn]] sings the song from the point of view of a reluctant but forced soldier,{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}} Heidi Bruhl from the point of view of the crying girlfriend of the soldier.{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}} Freddy Quinn's version was later recorded by [[Welle: Erdball]] and also by [[Cryptic Wintermoon]].
* The Royal Netherlands Army's [[Korps Commandotroepen]] (KCT) use the original lyrics. The only difference is that in the chorus, instead of singing &quot;''These are men, America's best''&quot;, they sing &quot;''These are men, The Netherlands' best''&quot;. Also in the final chorus, referring to the son of a deceased Green Beret, they sing &quot;''Make him one of The Netherlands' best''&quot;. This version of the original ballad is sung to recruits who have successfully completed the harsh Basic Commando Training (ECO), and who receive their Green Beret.
* [[Rhodesian]] singer-songwriter [[John Edmond]] recorded the &quot;Ballad of the Green Berets&quot; with reference to the soldiers of the [[Rhodesian Light Infantry]] (RLI), commando-style [[fireforce]] units of Rhodesian Security Forces who wore [[berets]] of [[green]] [[color]], with a slight difference in the chorus, saying &quot;''These are men, of The Fatherland’s Best.''&quot; &amp; &quot;''Make him one of The Fatherlands best''&quot; A &quot;Ballad of the Red Beret&quot; was sung by the Rhodesian Ministry of Internal Affairs at their battlecamp in [[Chikurubi]]. In [[South Africa]], the &quot;Ballad of the Green Berets&quot; was recorded as the &quot;Ballad of the Maroon Berets&quot;. The [[Maroon beret]] is a symbol of the [[South African Special Forces Brigade]] and the [[South African 44 Parachute Regiment]]. Also this song was re-recorded by South African opera singer Leonore Veenemans as &quot;My Land Suid-Afrika&quot;.
* The Swedish version &quot;Balladen om den blå baskern&quot; is a salute to the Swedish soldiers serving in the United Nations' peace-keeping forces (the Blue Berets). It was sung by [[Anita Lindblom]].
* The Italian version is called ''La Ballata del Soldato'', sung by [[Quartetto Cetra]].
* Since 2004, the Infantry Officer's School of the [[Swiss Armed Forces]] uses a [[Languages of Switzerland|quadrlingual]] (German, French, Italian and Rumansch) version of the song, ''Die Infanterieballade'' (The [[Infantry]] Ballad), as their anthem, in salute to the bonds created by the very harsh training undertaken by the cadets as well as to the sense of duty (and their motto, [[Exemplo Ducemus]]) they vow to respect. The lyrics were written by cadets from all linguistical regions of Switzerland&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.he.admin.ch/internet/heer/de/home/themen/schulen/Kaderschulen/infkader1/inf_ballade.html|title=Die Infanterieballade|website=Admin.ch|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160513081511/http://www.he.admin.ch/internet/heer/de/home/themen/schulen/Kaderschulen/infkader1/inf_ballade.html|archive-date=13 May 2016|url-status=}}&lt;/ref&gt;. It is sung everyday onwards to the morning [[wikt:roll call|roll call]], before the [[National anthem of Switzerland|National Anthem]].
* In 1966, Bernard Tapy (real name [[Bernard Tapie]], businessman and politician), recorded an adaptation in French as &quot;Passeport pour le soleil&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.encyclopedisque.fr/disque/23082.html ≪Passeport pour le soleil. Bernard Tapy. 1966. RCA Victor≫], sur le site Encyclopédisque&lt;/ref&gt;
* The Ukrainian version 2015 ''100 Soldiers''. Lyrics by Oleksa Negrebetskiy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite av media|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=n8wLN79Ii5Q|title=100 бійців|date=29 December 2014|publisher=|via=YouTube}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Supporters of [[Liverpool Football Club]] sing a version with the lyrics adapted to the history of the club called &quot;Liverbird upon my chest&quot;.
* music adapted by the Portuguese paratroopers as an anthem ''Hino dos Boinas Verdes''
* The Lithuanian version of Liepa &quot;Kartu iki pergalės&quot; 2018 in TV show &quot;support for Ukraine&quot; 
* The Finnish version titled &quot;Balladi punaisista bareteista&quot; was released in 1966 by Kivikasvot. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.aanitearkisto.fi/firs2/kappale.php?Id=Balladi+punaisista+bareteista&lt;/ref&gt;

== Parodies ==
{{unreferenced section|date=September 2018}}
* In 1968, The Beach Bums, an ad hoc group featuring a young [[Bob Seger]], recorded &quot;The Ballad of the Yellow Beret&quot;, chronicling the adventures of a [[draft dodger]].  The record was withdrawn after a [[cease and desist]] letter from Sadler.
* [[The Residents]] parodied the song on their ''[[Third Reich &amp; Roll]]'' album.
* Another parody was used on an episode of ''[[Saturday Night Live]]'' that [[William Shatner]] hosted in 1986, called &quot;Ollie North, The Mute Marine&quot;. Shatner participated in the sketch, outfitted in a USMC Class A uniform, alluding to [[Oliver North]]'s refusal to speak about his participation in the [[Iran-Contra Affair]]; Shatner spoke no words.
* The song is used to humorous effect in [[Michael Moore]]'s film ''[[Canadian Bacon (film)|Canadian Bacon]]'' as ill-informed Americans prepare for an invasion by [[Canada]].
* The movie ''[[Wag the Dog]]'' includes the fictitious unit 303 Special Forces' song &quot;The Men of the 303&quot;, which is played to a similar but original tune written by [[Huey Lewis]] for the film.
* In the film ''[[Caddyshack]]'', Carl Spackler, played by [[Bill Murray]], mumbles the song under his breath while he is connecting the wires to the plunger as he prepares for his final battle with his [[gopher (animal)|gopher]] nemesis.
* Comedian Paul Shanklin parodied the song with &quot;Ballad of the Black Beret&quot;, referring to the Clinton sex scandal, on his 1999 album ''[[Simply Reprehensible]]''.
* Though its usage was not a parody, in an episode of ''[[Cheers]]'', Cliff Clavin aborts his plans to emigrate to Canada with his love interest when Sam, Woody, and Frasier appeal to his patriotic side by singing the song.
*  The internet critic SF Debris uses the music with lyrics about the Red Shirts in ''Star Trek'' who regularly die on away missions.

== Charts ==
{{col-begin}}
{{col-2}}
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable plainrowheaders&quot; 
|-
! Chart (1966)
! Peak&lt;br /&gt;position
|-
|Germany ([[GfK Entertainment Charts|Official German Charts]])&lt;ref&gt;[http://swedishcharts.com/showitem.asp?interpret=Staff+Sergeant+Barry+Sadler&amp;titel=The+Ballad+Of+The+Green+Berets&amp;cat=s &quot;Swedishcharts.com – STAFF SERGEANT BARRY SADLER - THE BALLAD OF THE GREEN BERETS&quot;]. [[Sverigetopplistan|Singles Top 100]].&lt;/ref&gt;
|style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;|4
|-
|South Africa (Springbok Radio SA Top 20) &lt;ref&gt;http://www.rock.co.za/files/sa_charts_1969_1989_songs_(A-B).html&lt;/ref&gt;
|style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;|1
|-
{{singlechart|UKsinglesbyname|24|artist=Staff Sergeant Barry Sadler}}
|-
{{singlechart|Billboardhot100|1|artist=SSgt Barry Sadler}}
|-
{{singlechart|Billboardadultcontemporary|1|artist=SSgt Barry Sadler}}
|-
{{singlechart|Billboardcountrysongs|2|artist=SSgt Barry Sadler}}
|}
{{col-2}}

===All-time charts===
{|class=&quot;wikitable plainrowheaders&quot;
|-
! Chart (1958-2018)
! Position
|-
|US ''Billboard'' Hot 100&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.billboard.com/charts/hot-100-60th-anniversary|title=Billboard Hot 100 60th Anniversary Interactive Chart|work=Billboard|accessdate=10 December 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|369
|}
{{col-end}}

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== Further reading ==
* Collins, Ace. ''Songs Sung, Red, White, and Blue: The Stories Behind America's Best-Loved Patriotic Songs''.  HarperResource, 2003.  {{ISBN|0-06-051304-7}}

== External links ==
* ''[http://marcleepson.com/sadler/index.html Ballad of the Green Berets: The Life and Wars of Army Staff Sergeant Barry Sadler]'' by Marc Leepson (Stackpole Books, 2017)
* [{{Allmusic|class=album|id=the-ballads-of-the-green-berets-r67869|pure_url=yes}} Ballads of The Green Berets] at [[AllMusic]]
* [http://joangushin.net/pass.html Soon This Will Pass] sung by Joan Gibbs at Barbara Joan Gushin


{{Billboard Year-End number one singles 1960–1979}}

[[Category:Songs of the Vietnam War]]
[[Category:American patriotic songs]]
[[Category:Pop ballads]]
[[Category:Barry Sadler songs]]
[[Category:Billboard Adult Contemporary number-one singles]]
[[Category:Number-one singles in South Africa]]
[[Category:Songs about the military]]
[[Category:1966 singles]]
[[Category:1966 songs]]
[[Category:Anita Lindblom songs]]</text>
      <sha1>du63atuxe9iqlcl614jaxwgy8kj7m31</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
