  <page>
    <title>Batman: Year One</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4731</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943064969</id>
      <parentid>942318271</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-28T16:22:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>120.56.164.252</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Plot */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|1987 story arc in Batman comic book series}}
{{for|the film|Batman: Year One (film)}}
{{Infobox comics story arc
&lt;!--Wikipedia:WikiProject Comics--&gt;
&lt;!-- |title          = Batman: Year One --&gt;
|image          = Batman-Year One (cover).jpg
|imagesize      = &lt;!-- default 250 --&gt;
|caption        = Cover of the first hardcover printing of ''Batman: Year One''
|publisher      = [[DC Comics]]
|startmo        = February
|startyr        = 1987
|endmo          = May
|endyr          = 1987
|genre          = &lt;!-- covered by the cat paramater --&gt;
|titles         = ''[[Batman (comic book)|Batman]]'' #404–407
|notable = July 2009
|main_char_team = [[Batman]]&lt;br&gt;[[James Gordon (comics)|Jim Gordon]]
|writers        = [[Frank Miller (comics)|Frank Miller]]
|artists        = [[David Mazzucchelli]]
|pencillers     =
|inkers         =
|letterers      = [[Todd Klein]]
|editors        = [[Dennis O'Neil]]
|colorists      = [[Richmond Lewis]]
|TPB            =Batman: Year One
|ISBN           =0-930289-33-1
|TPB1           =Deluxe Edition (softcover)
|ISBN1          =1401207529
|TPB2           =Deluxe Edition (hardcover)
|ISBN2          =1401206905
|cat            = Batman
|sortkey        = Year 1
|nonUS          =
}}
&quot;'''Year One'''&quot;, later referred to as &quot;'''Batman: Year One'''&quot;, is an [[American comic book]] [[story arc]] published by [[DC Comics]] which recounts the superhero [[Batman]]'s first year as a crime-fighter. It was written by [[Frank Miller (comics)|Frank Miller]], illustrated by [[David Mazzucchelli]], colored by [[Richmond Lewis]], and lettered by [[Todd Klein]]. ''Batman: Year One'' originally appeared in issues #404–407 of the comic book title ''[[Batman (comic book)|Batman]]'' in 1987. As well as recounting [[Batman]]'s early crime-fighting career, the story simultaneously examines the life of recently transferred officer [[James Gordon (comics)|James Gordon]]—eventually building towards their partnership.

There have been several reprints of the story: a [[hardcover]], multiple [[Trade paperback (comics)|trade paperback]] editions (one in standard comics paper with simpler coloring and one deluxe version with rich detailing in the colors—both colored by [[Richmond Lewis]]) and it has been included in ''The Complete Frank Miller Batman'' hardcover. The [[story arc]] was adapted into an [[Batman: Year One (film)|animated feature]] in 2011.

==Publication history==
===Background===
[[Batman]] (Bruce Wayne) is a superhero appearing in [[American comic book]]s published by [[DC Comics]] who debuted in &quot;[[The Case of the Chemical Syndicate]]&quot;, a story published in ''[[Detective Comics]]'' #27 (May 1939). He was created by artist [[Bob Kane]] and writer [[Bill Finger]] to capitalize on the success of DC's other superhero [[Superman]] and was inspired by characters from [[pulp magazine|pulp fiction]] stories, such as [[the Shadow]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Batman – The Complete History: The Life and Times of the Dark Knight|author=Les Daniels|url=https://books.google.com/books/about/Batman_The_Complete_History.html?id=73wknu2cVIkC|pages=18–20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Boichel, Bill. &quot;Batman: Commodity as Myth.&quot; ''The Many Lives of the Batman: Critical Approaches to a Superhero and His Media''. Routledge: London, 1991. {{ISBN|978-0-85170-276-6}}, pp. 6–7.&lt;/ref&gt; Batman's origin story was introduced in a two-page, 12-panel story by Kane and Finger from ''Detective Comics'' #33 (Nov. 1939). In the story, a young Bruce witnesses the murder of his parents [[Thomas Wayne|Thomas]] and [[Martha Wayne|Martha]] at the hands of a mugger. Bruce vows to avenge his parents' deaths by fighting crime; he takes the persona of Batman after a [[bat]] flies through his window one night. For the story, Finger lifted elements from tales published in ''[[Popular Detective]]'' and ''[[The Phantom]]'', while Kane traced artwork of [[Tarzan]] and from ''[[Junior G-Men]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;nerd&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Weldon|first1=Glen|authorlink=Glen Weldon|title=The Caped Crusade: Batman and the Rise of Nerd Culture|date=2016|publisher=[[Simon &amp; Schuster]]|isbn=978-1-4767-5669-1|url=https://www.amazon.com/Caped-Crusade-Batman-Rise-Culture/dp/1476756694|accessdate=September 10, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the years afterward, much of DC's continuity became convoluted and contradictory. Examples of this were present in Batman's origin: in a 1948 story, Finger gave the mugger a name ([[Joe Chill]]), and in 1956 wrote that he killed Bruce's parents on behalf of the mob. Finger also went on to suggest that the Batman persona was inspired by a bat costume Thomas wore to a [[masquerade ball]]. Other stories depicted Bruce traveling across the world to learn the skills he would need as Batman.&lt;ref name=&quot;nerd&quot;/&gt; In an effort to resolve continuity errors like these in the [[DC Universe]], [[Marv Wolfman]] and [[George Pérez]] produced the 12-issue [[Limited series (comics)|limited series]] ''[[Crisis on Infinite Earths]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;backissue30&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Greeberger|first1=Robert|title=Crisis at 30: A Look Back at the Most Influential Crossover in Comics History|journal=[[Back Issue!]]|date=August 2015|issue=82}}&lt;/ref&gt; Wolfman's plans for the DC Universe after ''Crisis on Infinite Earths'' included relaunching every DC comic with a new first issue.&lt;ref name=&quot;Slugfest152&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Tucker |first=Reed |date=October 2017 |title=Slugfest |location= [[New York City]]|publisher=[[Da Capo Press]]|page=152 |isbn=0306825473 |url=https://books.google.com/books/about/Slugfest.html?id=hoyYDgAAQBAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=kp_read_button#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the production of ''Crisis on Infinite Earths'', [[Frank Miller (comics)|Frank Miller]] became the writer of [[Marvel Comics]]' ''[[Daredevil (Marvel Comics series)|Daredevil]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;nerd&quot;/&gt; Miller had originally been the series' [[penciller]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last = Sanderson|first = Peter|authorlink = Peter Sanderson|last2= Gilbert|first2= Laura, ed.|chapter= 1970s|title = Marvel Chronicle A Year by Year History|publisher = [[Dorling Kindersley]]|year = 2008|location= London, United Kingdom|page = 189|isbn =978-0-7566-4123-8|quote= In this issue the great longtime ''Daredevil'' artist Gene Colan was succeeded by a new penciller who would become a star himself: Frank Miller.}}&lt;/ref&gt; but editor [[Dennis O'Neil]] soon made him the series' writer.&lt;ref name=&quot;O'NeilInt&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.manwithoutfear.com/daredevil-interviews/ONeil | title = Interview with Dennis O'Neil|first= Kuljit|last= Mithra|date= February 1998 | publisher =  ManWithoutFear.com |accessdate= May 10, 2013 | archivedate= March 21, 2013 | url-status = live | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20130321185605/http://www.manwithoutfear.com/daredevil-interviews/ONeil}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sales rose dramatically after Miller began to write. For one [[Born Again (comics)|critically acclaimed ''Daredevil'' story]], Miller collaborated with artist [[David Mazzucchelli]]. Miller went to work for DC as well, and produced the influential four-issue limited series ''[[The Dark Knight Returns]]'' (1986). O'Neil also made the move to DC.&lt;ref name=&quot;nerd&quot;/&gt;

===Development===
[[File:Frank Miller Fan Expo Wiki.jpg|thumb|left|Frank Miller, the author of &quot;Year One&quot;, at the Fan Expo 2016 in Toronto, Canada]]
The contract Miller signed to produce ''The Dark Knight Returns'' also required him to write a revamped Batman origin story. While Miller handled the writing and artwork of ''The Dark Knight Returns'', he simply wrote &quot;Year One&quot;, while Mazzucchelli joined to pencil.&lt;ref name=&quot;nerd&quot;/&gt; In the past, Miller had been overwhelmed by having to handle both writing and illustration duties.&lt;ref name=&quot;Back21&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last= Cordier|first=Philippe|title=Seeing Red: Dissecting Daredevil's Defining Years|journal=[[Back Issue!]]|issue=21|pages=33–60|publisher= [[TwoMorrows Publishing]]|date= April 2007|location= Raleigh, North Carolina}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Todd Klein]] was the story's [[letterer]], while Mazzucchelli's wife [[Richmond Lewis]] handled coloring. O'Neil edited the issues.&lt;ref name=&quot;nerd&quot;/&gt; According to O'Neil, the contract Miller and Mazzucchelli signed to produce &quot;Year One&quot; in the [[Ongoing series|ongoing]] ''[[Batman (comic book)|Batman]]'' series guaranteed publication within 6 months.&lt;ref name=&quot;ONeil13th&quot;/&gt;

[[File:6.28.12DavidMazzuchelliByLuigiNovi36.jpg|thumb|[[David Mazzucchelli]] autographing a copy of the collected story in 2012]]
&quot;Year One&quot; was originally conceived as a [[graphic novel]]. O'Neil, who had been asked to edit several issues of ''Batman'', was friends with Miller and was able to learn of the story. Reflecting on poor sales of ''Batman'', O'Neil caught Miller one day while on a walk in [[Los Angeles]] and convinced him and Mazzucchelli to serialize the story in the ongoing series.&lt;ref name=&quot;ONeil13th&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last1=Greenfield|first1=Dan|title=The DENNY O’NEIL INTERVIEWS — Batman: Year One|url=https://13thdimension.com/the-denny-oneil-interviews-batman-year-one/|website=13th Dimension|accessdate=May 20, 2018|date=September 22, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Miller was initially reluctant; he felt this would be hard because he had to ensure the story stayed canonical to the DC Universe, something he did not have to worry about when writing ''The Dark Knight Returns''. In addition, Miller's pacing would have to be altered because of ongoing series' relatively small page counts. O'Neil reasoned that ''Crisis on Infinite Earths'' had completely remade the DC Universe, so Miller would be able to have the same creative freedom that ''The Dark Knight Returns'' provided.&lt;ref name=&quot;nerd&quot;/&gt; He also reassured Miller that he and Mazzucchelli &quot;weren’t going to lose anything&quot; by serializing it.&lt;ref name=&quot;ONeil13th&quot;/&gt;

Miller has said he kept Kane and Finger's basic story for &quot;Year One&quot; but expanded it.&lt;ref name=&quot;NPRTalk&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title='Batman' Author Frank Miller|url=https://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=4704766|publisher=[[NPR]]|accessdate=May 22, 2018|date=June 15, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; In writing the story, Miller looked for parts of Batman's origin that were never explored. He left the core elements, such as the murder of Bruce's parents, intact, but reduced them to brief [[Flashback (narrative)|flashbacks]]. Bruce's globe-trotting adventures was something Miller removed, as he found uninteresting. Rather than portraying Batman as a larger-than-life icon as he had in ''The Dark Knight Returns'', Miller chose to characterize &quot;Year One{{&quot;'}}s Batman as an average, inexperienced man trying to make a change in society because Miller believed a superhero is least interesting when most effective. Examples of this include Batman underestimating his opponents, getting shot by police, and his costume being too big. The story's violence was kept street-level and gritty, emphasizing [[Noir fiction|noir]] and realism.&lt;ref name=&quot;nerd&quot;/&gt;

In illustrating, Mazzucchelli sought to make &quot;Year One&quot; look grimy, dark, and muted. His interpretation of [[Gotham City]] was designed to symbolize corruption, featuring muddy colors that gave the impression of the city being dirty and needing a hero. The newsprint paper used in ''Batman'' was unable to reproduce the bright coloring and visual effects of ''The Dark Knight Returns'', so Mazzucchelli took on &quot;Year One&quot; with a more grounded and darker approach.&lt;ref name=&quot;visual&quot;/&gt;

===Publication===
In accordance with Wolfman's plans,&lt;ref name=&quot;Slugfest152&quot;/&gt; O'Neil initially saw &quot;Year One&quot; as the start of the second volume of ''Batman'' and expected the first part to be its first issue. However, Miller rejected this idea. He explained: &quot;I don't need to slash through continuity with as sharp a blade as I thought. Doing the ''Dark Knight'' has shown me there's been enough good material&amp;nbsp;... I didn't feel that fleshing out an unknown part of Batman's history justified wiping out 50 years of [adventures].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;visual&quot;/&gt; Thus, the four &quot;Year One&quot; issues bear no continuity to past issues of ''Batman''.&lt;ref name=&quot;visual&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Manning|first= Matthew K.|last2=Dolan|first2=Hannah, ed.|chapter= 1980s|title = DC Comics Year By Year A Visual Chronicle|publisher=[[Dorling Kindersley]] |year=2010 |isbn= 978-0-7566-6742-9 |page= 227 |quote =  Melding Miller's noir sensibilities, realistic characterization, and gritty action with Mazzucchelli's brilliant iconic imagery, &quot;Year One&quot; thrilled readers and critics alike&amp;nbsp;... as well as being one of the influences for the 2005 film ''Batman Begins''.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Title
! Issue
! Cover date
|-
| &quot;'''Chapter One: Who I Am – How I Come to Be'''&quot;
| ''Batman'' #404
| February 1987
|-
| &quot;'''Chapter Two: War Is Declared'''&quot;
| ''Batman'' #405
| March 1987
|-
| &quot;'''Chapter Three: Black Dawn'''&quot;
| ''Batman'' #406
| April 1987
|-
| &quot;'''Chapter Four: Friend in Need'''&quot;
| ''Batman'' #407
| May 1987
|}

===Collected editions===
One of the earliest collections of &quot;Year One&quot; was released in ''The Complete Frank Miller Batman'', published by [[Longmeadow Press]] in 1989.&lt;ref name=&quot;IGN2012&quot;/&gt; A dedicated collected edition, ''Batman: Year One'', was published as a [[Trade paperback (comics)|trade paperback]] in October 1997 ({{isbn|0-930289-33-1}}). It is 96 pages long and contains the four &quot;Year One&quot; issues.

DC released a hardcover &quot;deluxe edition&quot; of ''Batman: Year One'' ({{isbn|1401206905}}) to coincide with the release of ''[[Batman Begins]]'' in April 2005.&lt;ref name=&quot;IGN2012&quot;/&gt; This release includes introductions by Miller and Mazzucchelli, the original penciled artwork, promotional and unseen Batman art, Lewis's color samples, and some pages of the original script, for a total of 144 pages. This edition was rereleased as a 136-page trade paperback in January 2007, with an introduction by O'Neil ({{isbn|1401207529}}). New versions of this edition were released in 2012&lt;ref name=&quot;IGN2012&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last1=Schedeen|first1=Jesse|title=Batman: Year One – Deluxe Edition Hardcover Review|url=http://www.ign.com/articles/2012/03/28/batman-year-one-deluxe-edition-hardcover-review|website=[[IGN]]|accessdate=May 28, 2018|date=March 28, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; and 2017 ({{isbn|1401272940}}).

To celebrate Batman's 75th anniversary in November 2014, DC released a sample of &quot;Year One&quot; as a part of its ''DC Comics Essentials'' line of promotional comics.&lt;ref name=&quot;DCEssentials&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=DC Comics Essentials – Batman: Year One Special Edition #1|url=https://www.dccomics.com/comics/batman-year-one-1987/dc-comics-essentials-%E2%80%93-batman-year-one-special-edition-1|publisher=[[DC Comics]]|date=November 5, 2014|accessdate=May 28, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2015, a special package was released that contained the story and its [[Batman: Year One (film)|film adaptation]] ({{isbn|1401260047}}).

In November 2016, DC released a 288-page [[DC Comics Absolute Edition]] of ''Batman: Year One''. It comes in a slipcase with two hardcover books: one that reprints a remastered version of the story, with refined coloring; and another that reprints the original, unaltered story from 1987. Both books contain over 60 pages of bonus materials, including Miller's complete scripts.&lt;ref name=&quot;DCAbsolute&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Absolute Batman: Year One|url=https://www.dccomics.com/graphic-novels/batman-year-one-1987/absolute-batman-year-one|publisher=[[DC Comics]]|accessdate=May 28, 2018|date=November 2, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Plot==
The story recounts the beginning of Bruce Wayne's career as [[Batman]] and [[James Gordon (comics)|Jim Gordon]]'s with the [[Gotham City Police Department]]. Bruce Wayne returns home to [[Gotham City]] at the age of twenty-five from training abroad in martial arts, man-hunting, and science for the past 12 years, and James Gordon moves to Gotham City with his wife, Barbara, after a transfer from [[Chicago]]. Both are swiftly acquainted with the corruption and violence of Gotham City, with Gordon witnessing his partner [[Arnold John Flass|Detective Arnold John Flass]] assaulting an African-American teen for fun.

After refusing a proposition from a teenage prostitute [[Holly Robinson (fictional character)|Holly Robinson]], Bruce is reluctantly drawn into a brawl with her violent pimp and is attacked by several prostitutes, including [[dominatrix]] [[Catwoman|Selina Kyle]]. Two police officers shoot and take him in their squad car, but a dazed and bleeding Bruce breaks his handcuffs and causes a crash, dragging the police to a safe distance before fleeing. He reaches [[Wayne Manor]] barely alive and sits before his father's bust, requesting guidance in his war on crime. A bat crashes through a window and settles on the bust, giving him the inspiration to become the Batman.

Gordon soon works to rid corruption from the force, but, on orders from [[Gillian B. Loeb|Commissioner Gillian Loeb]], several officers attack him, including Flass, who personally threatens Gordon's pregnant wife. In revenge, the recovering Gordon tracks Flass down, beats him, and leaves him naked and handcuffed in the snow.

As Gordon becomes a minor celebrity for several brave acts, Batman strikes for the first time, attacking a group of thieves. Batman soon works up the ladder, even attacking Flass while the latter was accepting a drug dealer's bribe. After Batman interrupts a dinner party attended by many of Gotham's corrupt politicians and crime bosses to announce his intention to bring them to justice, including [[Carmine Falcone|Carmine &quot;The Roman&quot; Falcone]], Loeb orders Gordon to bring him in by any means necessary.

As Gordon tries in vain to catch him, Batman attacks Falcone, stripping him naked and tying him up in his bed and dumping his car in the river, infuriating the mob boss. Assistant [[District Attorney]] [[Two-Face|Harvey Dent]] becomes Batman's first ally, while [[Sarah Essen Gordon|Detective Sarah Essen]] and Gordon witness Batman save an old woman from a runaway truck, after Essen suggested Bruce Wayne as a Batman suspect. Essen holds Batman at gunpoint while Gordon is momentarily dazed, but Batman disarms her and flees to an abandoned building.

Claiming the building has been scheduled for demolition, Loeb orders a bomb to be dropped on it, forcing Batman into the fortified basement, where he abandons [[Batman's utility belt|his utility belt]] as it catches fire. A [[SWAT]] team led by trigger-happy officer Branden is sent in and attempts to trap Batman in the basement. After tranquilizing Branden, Batman dodges bullets as Branden's team opens fire on him, barely managing to survive after two bullet wounds. Enraged as the team's carelessly fired bullets injure several people outside, Batman beats the team into submission and, after using a device to attract the bats of his cave to him, he flees amid the chaos. After witnessing him in action, Selina Kyle dons a costume of her own to begin a life of crime.

Gordon has a brief affair with Essen, while Batman intimidates a mob drug dealer for information. The dealer comes to Gordon to testify against Flass, who is brought up on charges. Upset with Gordon's exploits, Loeb blackmails Gordon against pressing charges with proof of his affair. After bringing Barbara with him to interview Bruce Wayne, investigating his connection to Batman, Gordon confesses the affair to her.

Batman sneaks into Falcone's manor, overhearing a plan against Gordon, but is interrupted when Selina Kyle, hoping to build a reputation after her robberies were pinned on Batman, attacks Falcone and his bodyguards, aided from afar by Batman. Identifying Falcone's plan as the morning comes, the uncostumed Bruce leaves to help.

While leaving home, Gordon spots a motorcyclist enter his garage. Suspicious, Gordon enters to see Johnny Vitti, Falcone's nephew, and his thugs holding his family hostage. Gordon decisively shoots the thugs and chases Vitti, who has fled with the baby. The mysterious motorcyclist, now revealed to the reader as Bruce Wayne, rushes out to chase Vitti. Gordon blows out Vitti's car tire on a bridge and the two fight hand-to-hand, with Gordon losing his glasses, before Vitti and James Gordon Jr. fall over the side. Bruce leaps over the railing and saves the baby. Gordon realizes that he is standing before an unmasked Batman, but says that he is &quot;practically blind without [his] glasses&quot;, and lets Bruce go.

In the final scenes of the comic, Flass turns on Loeb, supplying Dent with evidence and testimony, and Loeb resigns. Gordon is promoted to captain and stands on the rooftop waiting to meet Batman to discuss somebody called [[Joker (comics)|the Joker]], who is plotting to poison the reservoir.

==Reception==
DC's post-''Crisis on Infinite Earths'' revamp was a major success, raising sales 22% in the first year, and DC beat Marvel in [[direct market]] sales for the first time in August and September 1987.&lt;ref name=&quot;Slugfest157&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Tucker |first=Reed |date=October 2017 |title=Slugfest |location= [[New York City]]|publisher=[[Da Capo Press]]|page=157 |isbn=0306825473 |url=https://books.google.com/books/about/Slugfest.html?id=hoyYDgAAQBAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=kp_read_button#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt; The four &quot;Year One&quot; issues were no exception to this. Two years before the relaunch, ''Batman'' had all-time low sales of 75,000 copies per month; &quot;Year One&quot; sold an average of 193,000 copies an issue, numbers not seen since the early 1970s. Despite this, it did not outsell other books like ''[[Uncanny X-Men]]'', and the collected edition sold well but never matched the sales of ''The Dark Knight Returns''.&lt;ref name=&quot;nerd&quot;/&gt; The story, with its noir-inspired narrative and dirty violence, quickly caught the attention of readers.&lt;ref name=&quot;ComicsVerseReview&quot;/&gt; The ''[[Los Angeles Times]]'' wrote that &quot;Year One&quot; offered an interesting and entertaining update to the origin of Batman.&lt;ref name=&quot;YearOne2007&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last1=Miller |first1=Frank |last2=Mazzucchelli |first2=Dave |title=Batman: Year One |date=January 10, 2007 |publisher=[[DC Comics]] |isbn=0290204895 |edition=Paperback}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&quot;Year One{{&quot;'}}s characterization, particularly that of Batman and Gordon, has been praised. Hilary Goldstein (''[[IGN]]'') compared their journey to friendship to the plot of the film ''[[Serpico]]''; they found that the two characters' respective story arcs—with Gordon's &quot;illustrat[ing] the corruption in Gotham&quot; and Batman's detailing &quot;the transformation from man to myth&quot;—offered an exploration of Batman's world like no other.&lt;ref name=&quot;IGNReview&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last1=Goldstein |first1=Hilary |title=Batman: Year One Review |url=http://www.ign.com/articles/2005/06/17/batman-year-one-review |website=[[IGN]] |accessdate=May 30, 2018 |date=June 17, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; Glenn Matchett (''ComicsVerse'') wrote that, unlike ''The Dark Knight Returns'', &quot;Year One{{&quot;'}}s Batman is more vulnerable and inexperienced, which made the story more memorable.&lt;ref name=&quot;ComicsVerseReview&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last1=Matchett |first1=Glenn |title=Frank Miller's Batman Part One: YEAR ONE, or How Legends are Made |url=https://comicsverse.com/frank-millers-batman-part-one-year-one-or-how-legends-are-made/ |website=ComicsVerse |accessdate=May 30, 2018 |date=September 4, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nick Roberts (''Geek Syndicate'') thought the characters seemed believable,&lt;ref name=&quot;GeekSyndicateReview&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last1=Roberts |first1=Nick |title=‘Classic Comic’ Review – Batman: Year One |url=https://geeksyndicate.co.uk/reviews/%E2%80%98classic-comic%E2%80%99-review-%E2%80%93-batman-year-one/ |website=Geek Syndicate |accessdate=May 30, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; and comics historian Matthew K. Manning called the characterization realistic.&lt;ref name=&quot;visual&quot;/&gt;

The story's depiction of Gotham and dark tone has also been acclaimed. Journalist James Lovegrove described &quot;Year One&quot; as a &quot;noir-inflected pulp tale of vigilantism and integrity, focused on a good man doing the right thing in a dirty world&quot; and noted the brutality of its fight sequences.&lt;ref name=&quot;100best&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Lovegrove |first1=James |title=Batman: Year One |journal=The 100 Greatest Graphic Novels of All Time |date=2016 |issue=1 |pages=92–93 |url=https://archive.org/stream/The_100_Greatest_Graphic_Novels_Of_All_Time#page/n91/mode/2up/search/Batman+Year+One |publisher=[[Future plc]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Jason Serafino (''[[Complex (magazine)|Complex]]'') wrote that by ignoring many of Batman's trademark gadgets and villains, Miller managed to present Batman in a relatable and thrilling way.&lt;ref name=&quot;Complex25&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last1=Serafino |first1=Jason |title=The 25 Best DC Comics Of All Time |url=https://www.complex.com/pop-culture/the-best-dc-comics-of-all-time/all-star-superman |website=[[Complex (magazine)|Complex]] |accessdate=May 31, 2018 |date=January 17, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; Goldstein found every moment memorable, writing &quot;Miller does not waste a single panel&quot; in presenting a gritty and dark story.&lt;ref name=&quot;IGNReview&quot;/&gt; Matchett agreed; he offered particular praise for the scenes depicting Batman clashing with the police, calling them the moment Batman began to become a legend.&lt;ref name=&quot;ComicsVerseReview&quot;/&gt;

Mazzucchelli's art was noted as a standout.&lt;ref name=&quot;IGNReview&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ComicsVerseReview&quot;/&gt;

==Continuity==
Before [[the New 52]] in 2011, ''Batman: Year One'' existed in the mainstream DC continuity, and in the same continuity as the other storylines in Miller's &quot;Dark Knight Universe&quot;, consisting of ''[[The Dark Knight Returns]]'', its sequel ''[[The Dark Knight Strikes Again]]'', ''[[The Dark Knight III: The Master Race]]'', ''The Dark Knight Returns: The Last Crusade'', ''[[Spawn/Batman]]'', and ''[[All Star Batman and Robin the Boy Wonder]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Sanderson |first=Peter |url=http://comics.ign.com/articles/685/685820p1.html |title=''Comics in Context #119: All-Star Bats'' on IGN |publisher=Comics.ign.com |date=2006-02-06 |accessdate=2011-01-04| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20101213055056/http://comics.ign.com/articles/685/685820p1.html| archivedate= 13 December 2010 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt; Following the New 52 reboot, ''[[Batman: Zero Year]]'' replaced ''Year One'' as the official origin for Batman and ''Year One'' was relegated to the continuity of the other Frank Miller storylines.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dccomics.com/blog/2013/03/11/the-associated-press-announces-batman-zero-year|title=THE ASSOCIATED PRESS Announces BATMAN: ZERO YEAR|date=11 March 2013|website=dccomics.com|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20151022223622/http://www.dccomics.com/blog/2013/03/11/the-associated-press-announces-batman-zero-year|archivedate=22 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After ''[[Crisis on Infinite Earths]]'', DC [[Reboot (fiction)|rebooted]] many of its titles. ''Year One'' was followed by ''[[Batman: Year Two]]'', but the 1994 ''[[Zero Hour: Crisis in Time]]'' crossover erased ''Year Two'' from continuity. In another continuity re-arrangement, ''Catwoman: Year One'' (''Catwoman Annual'' #2, 1995) posited that Selina Kyle had not actually been a prostitute, but, rather, a thief posing as one in order to commit crimes.

Launched in 1989, following the success of the film ''[[Batman (1989 film)|Batman]]'', the title ''[[Batman: Legends of the Dark Knight]]'' examines crime-fighting exploits primarily, not exclusively, from the first four to five years of Batman's career. This title rotated in creative teams and time placement, but several stories directly relate to the events of ''Year One'', especially the first arc &quot;Batman: Shaman&quot;. In 1996 and '99, [[Jeph Loeb]] and [[Tim Sale (artist)|Tim Sale]] created ''[[Batman: The Long Halloween]]'' and ''[[Batman: Dark Victory]]'', two 13-issue maxiseries that recount Batman's early years as a crime-fighter following the events of Miller's original story and retold the origins of [[Two-Face]] and [[Dick Grayson]]. The ''Year One'' story was continued in the 2005 graphic novel ''[[Batman: The Man Who Laughs]]'', following up on Gordon informing Batman about the Joker, and thus recounting their first official encounter. Two other stories, ''[[Batman and the Monster Men]]'' and ''[[Batman and the Mad Monk]]'' tie into the same time period of Batman's career, filling in the gap between Year One and the Man Who Laughs. The comics ''[[Robin: Year One]]'' and ''[[Batgirl: Year One]]'' describe his sidekicks' origin stories.

==Sequels==
Two sequels titled ''[[Batman: Year Two]]'' and ''[[Batman: Year Three]]'' were released in 1987 and 1989.

==Adaptations==
After the critical failure of ''[[Batman &amp; Robin (film)|Batman &amp; Robin]]'', several attempts were made to [[Reboot (fiction)|reboot]] the [[Batman in film|Batman film franchise]] with an adaptation of &quot;Year One&quot;. [[Joss Whedon]] and [[Joel Schumacher]] both pitched their own takes.&lt;ref name=&quot;nerd&quot;/&gt; In 2000, [[Warner Bros.]] hired [[Darren Aronofsky]] to write and direct ''Batman: Year One''. The film was to be written by Miller, who finished an early draft of the script.&lt;ref name=Dana&gt;{{cite news | author = Dana Harris | url = http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117786714 | title = WB sends ''Pi'' guy into the Bat Cave | work = [[Variety (magazine)|Variety]] | date = 2000-09-21 | accessdate = 2008-10-17| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20120117093609/http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117786714| archivedate=January 17, 2012| url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;greenberg20050508&quot;&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://articles.latimes.com/2005/may/08/entertainment/ca-batman8 |title=Rescuing Batman |last=Greenberg |first=James |date=2005-05-08 |work=Los Angeles Times |access-date=2019-05-11 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20081202014002/http://articles.latimes.com/2005/may/08/entertainment/ca-batman8 |archive-date=2008-12-02 |url-status=live |page=E-10 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The script, however, was a loose adaptation, as it kept most of the themes and elements from the graphic novel but shunned other conventions that were otherwise integral to the character.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author = Brian Linder | work = [[IGN]] | title = The Bat-Men Speak | url = http://movies.ign.com/articles/034/034023p1.html | date = 2000-10-16 | accessdate = 2008-10-17 | url-status = live | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20081206080319/http://movies.ign.com/articles/034/034023p1.html | archivedate = 2008-12-06 }}&lt;/ref&gt; It was shelved by the studio in 2001,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author = Dana Harris | url = http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117869140 | title = WB: fewer pix, more punch | work = [[Variety (magazine)|Variety]] | date = 2002-06-30 | accessdate = 2008-10-17| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20120117105000/http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117869140| archivedate=January 17, 2012| url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt; after an individual who claimed to have read Miller's script published a negative review on ''[[Ain't It Cool News]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;nerd&quot;/&gt; In 2016, Miller explained that the film was canceled because of creative differences between him and Aronofsky: &quot;It was the first time I worked on a Batman project with somebody whose vision of Batman was darker than mine. My Batman was too nice for him. We would argue about it, and I'd say, 'Batman wouldn't do that, he wouldn't torture anybody'&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;THRInterview&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last1=Kit|first1=Borys|title=A Rare Interview With Frank Miller: 'Dark Knight,' the Unmade Darren Aronofsky Batman Movie, and Donald Trump|url=https://www.hollywoodreporter.com/heat-vision/a-rare-interview-frank-miller-871654|website=[[The Hollywood Reporter]]|accessdate=May 28, 2018|date=March 3, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2005, [[Christopher Nolan]] began his series, with the reboot film ''[[Batman Begins]]'', which draws inspiration from &quot;Year One&quot; and other stories.&lt;ref name=&quot;nerd&quot;/&gt; ''Batman Begins'' and its sequel ''[[The Dark Knight (film)|The Dark Knight]]'' are set during the same timespan and adopt several elements directly from the graphic novel. Major characters like [[Gillian B. Loeb|Commissioner Loeb]], [[Arnold John Flass|Detective Flass]] and [[Carmine Falcone|Carmine 'The Roman' Falcone]] are featured prominently in ''Batman Begins''. Film critic [[Michael Dodd]] argued that with each major motion picture focused on the Dark Knight's origins, the odes and references to the ''Year One'' comic increased. Comparing ''[[Batman: Mask of the Phantasm|Mask of the Phantasm]]'' with ''[[Batman Begins]]'' he noted that &quot;...Phantasm was a Batman story with ''Year One'' elements, while ''Batman Begins'' was a ''Year One'' story with added features&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Dodd, Michael, &quot;[http://themissingslate.com/2014/08/21/back-to-the-beginning-the-evolving-influence-of-batman-year-one/#.U_jTIvldUgs Back to the Beginning: The Evolving Influence of Batman: Year One] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170712082015/http://themissingslate.com/2014/08/21/back-to-the-beginning-the-evolving-influence-of-batman-year-one/ |date=2017-07-12 }},&quot; The Missing Slate.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2011, an [[Batman: Year One (film)|animated adaptation]] was released as a [[DC Universe Animated Original Movies|DC Universe Animated Original Movie]]. It was produced by [[Bruce Timm]], co-directed by [[Lauren Montgomery]] and [[Sam Liu]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.worldsfinestonline.com/news.php/news.php?action=fullnews&amp;showcomments=1&amp;id=1030|title=Batman: Year One Animated Update|publisher=worldsfinestonline.com|date=June 13, 2010|accessdate=June 13, 2010|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140812210449/http://www.worldsfinestonline.com/news.php/news.php?action=fullnews|archivedate=August 12, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; It features the voices of [[Benjamin McKenzie]] as Bruce Wayne/Batman, [[Bryan Cranston]] as [[James Gordon (comics)|James Gordon]], [[Eliza Dushku]] as Selina Kyle/Catwoman, [[Katee Sackhoff]] as [[Sarah Essen Gordon|Sarah Essen]], [[Grey DeLisle]] as Barbara Gordon, [[Jon Polito]] as Commissioner Loeb, [[Alex Rocco]] as Carmine 'The Roman' Falcone, and [[Jeff Bennett]] as Alfred Pennyworth.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/heat-vision/batman-year-one-lines-up-179942 |title='Batman: Year One' Lines Up Voice Cast, Sets Comic-Con Premiere (Exclusive) |last=Kit |first=Borys |date=April 20, 2011 |work=[[The Hollywood Reporter]] |accessdate=June 18, 2011| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20110721213402/http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/heat-vision/batman-year-one-lines-up-179942| archivedate= 21 July 2011 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt; The movie premiered at [[San Diego Comic-Con International|Comic-Con]], with a Catwoman short shown in October.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.dailyblam.com/news/2011/06/07/batman-year-one-animated-film-sneak-peek-video-character-designs |title=BATMAN: YEAR ONE Animated Film Sneak Peek Video &amp; Character Designs |publisher=The Daily BLAM! |accessdate=2013-01-23 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130125080019/http://www.dailyblam.com/news/2011/06/07/batman-year-one-animated-film-sneak-peek-video-character-designs |archivedate=2013-01-25 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The second half of the [[Gotham (season 4)|fourth season]] of the Batman-based television series ''[[Gotham (TV series)|Gotham]]'' is inspired by ''Batman: Year One''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://screenrant.com/gotham-season-4-long-halloween-batman-year-one-comics/|title=Gotham Season 4 Draws from Long Halloween &amp; Batman: Year One Comics|date=July 27, 2017|website=Screen Rant|accessdate=July 28, 2017|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170728045741/http://screenrant.com/gotham-season-4-long-halloween-batman-year-one-comics/|archivedate=July 28, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
* [http://BatmanYearOneMovie.com Batman: Year One Movie Official Site]
* [http://worldsfinestonline.com/WF/dcuam/batmanyearone/ Batman: Year One @ The World's Finest]
* [http://www.dccomics.com/graphic_novels/?gn=1287 Current edition at DC Comics] {{ISBN|0-930289-33-1}}
* [http://www.dccomics.com/graphic_novels/?gn=2712 Deluxe Hardcover edition at DC Comics] {{ISBN|1-4012-0690-5}}

{{Batman publications}}
{{David Mazzucchelli}}
{{Frank Miller}}

[[Category:Prequel comics]]
[[Category:Adult animated films]]
[[Category:Adultery in comics]]
[[Category:Gotham City Police Department]]
[[Category:Comics by Frank Miller]]</text>
      <sha1>h4738q5susjko16a62btbgpgzfypbw6</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
