  <page>
    <title>Branch Davidians</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4778</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943370372</id>
      <parentid>943251455</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-03-01T14:24:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>2601:2C2:C200:3BC:AD95:EB27:202A:88E9</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Rise of David Koresh */ is there any reason for the form &quot;prophetess&quot;?</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Religious movement}}
{{infobox religious group
| group         = Branch Davidians
| image         = File:Flag_of_Branch_Davidians.svg|border
| image_caption = Branch Davidian flag
| population    =
| founder       = [[Benjamin Roden]]
| regions       = {{flag|Texas}} ({{flag|United States}})
| tablehdr      = Branch Davidian
| region1       = [[Mount Carmel Center|Mount Carmel]]
| pop1          = 12
| ref1          = {{unbulleted list
 |Elk, Texas&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.tshaonline.org/handbook/online/articles/hre15 |title= Elk, Texas |author1= Smyrl, Vivian Elizabeth |publisher= Handbook of Texas – Texas State Historical Association |accessdate= 25 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 |[[Mount Carmel Center|Mount Carmel]], [[Texas]], U.S.
 }}
| region2       =
| pop2          =
| ref2          =
| region3       =
| pop3          =
| ref3          =
| religions     =
| languages     = English
| related-c     =
| notes         = Split from the [[Shepherd's Rod|Shepherd's Rod/Davidians]]
}}
{{Adventism}}
The '''Branch Davidians''' are a religious community which was founded in 1959 by [[Ben Roden]] as an offshoot of the [[Shepherd's Rod|Davidian Seventh-Day Adventist Church]], which was established by [[Victor Houteff]] in the 1930s. Houteff was a [[Bulgaria]]n immigrant to the United States and a [[Seventh-day Adventist Church|Seventh-day Adventist]] who wrote a series of tracts which were titled the &quot;Shepherd’s Rod.&quot; The tracts called for the reform of the Seventh-day Adventist church. His ideas were rejected by Adventist leaders, and in 1935, Houteff and his followers settled near Waco and began preparing for the [[Second Coming]]. Houteff's group eventually moved to a farm near [[Waco]], Texas, but in 1962 Roden and his followers took possession of the settlement, which was known as Mt. Carmel.

The Branch Davidians are most associated with the [[Waco siege]] of 1993, a 51-day standoff between Branch Davidians and federal agents that ended when the group's compound was destroyed in a fire. Nearly 80 people were killed.

== Early history ==
In 1929, [[Victor Houteff]], a [[Bulgaria]]n [[immigrant]] and a [[Seventh-day Adventist]] [[Sabbath School]] teacher in a local church in Southern California, claimed that he had a new message for the entire church. He presented his views in a book, ''[[Shepherd's Rod|The Shepherd's Rod: The 144,000—A Call for Reformation]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=The General Association of Branch Davidian Seventh Day Adventists |url=http://www.the-branch.org/Shepherds_Rod_Volume_1_Houteff |title=The Shepherd's Rod, Vol. 1 |publisher=The-branch.org |date= |accessdate=2011-03-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Adventist leadership rejected Houteff's views as contrary to the Adventists' basic teachings and local church congregations disfellowshipped Houteff and his followers.

In 1934, Houteff established his headquarters to the west of Waco, Texas and his group became known as The [[Shepherd's Rod|Davidians]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.tshaonline.org/handbook/online/articles/ird01 |title= Davidians and Branch Davidians |author1= Pitts, William L |publisher= Handbook of Texas – Texas State Historical Association |accessdate= November 25, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1942, he renamed the group the General Association of Davidian Seventh-day Adventists, 'Davidian' indicating the belief in the restoration of the [[Davidic Kingdom|Davidic Kingdom of Israel]]. Following Houteff's death in 1955, the segment of the group loyal to Houteff continued as the [[Davidian Seventh-day Adventist]]s, led by his wife Florence. Convinced of an imminent apocalypse, in a time frame announced by Florence Houteff which was not found in the original writings of her husband Victor, Florence and her council gathered hundreds of faithful followers together at their [[Mount Carmel Center]] near Waco in 1959 for the fulfillment of [[Ezekiel 9]].&lt;ref name=&quot;melton1&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.britannica.com/topic/Branch-Davidian#ref700562|title=Branch Davidian {{!}} Religious Organization|last=Melton|first=John Gordon|date=|work=Encyclopedia Britannica|access-date=2017-05-17|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The anticipated events did not occur, and following this disappointment, [[Benjamin Roden]] formed another group called the Branch Davidians and succeeded in taking control of Mount Carmel. This name is an allusion to the anointed 'Branch' (mentioned in Zechariah 3:8; 6:12).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bible.com/bible/111/ZEC.3.8|title=Zechariah 3:8; &quot;&amp;#8198;'Listen, High Priest Joshua, you and your associates seated before you, who are men symbolic of things to come: I am going to bring my servant, the Branch.|website=www.bible.com|language=en|access-date=2017-05-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bible.com/bible/111/ZEC.6.12|title=Zechariah 6:12; Tell him this is what the Lord Almighty says: 'Here is the man whose name is the Branch, and he will branch out from his place and build the temple of the Lord.|website=www.bible.com|language=en|access-date=2017-05-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; When Benjamin Roden died in 1978, he was succeeded by his wife [[Lois Roden]]. Members of the Branch Davidians were torn between allegiance to Ben's wife, Lois Roden, and his son, George. After Lois Roden died, George Roden assumed the right to the Presidency. But less than a year later, [[David Koresh|Vernon Howell]] rose to power and became the leader over those in the group who sympathized with him.

== Rise of David Koresh ==
[[David Koresh|Vernon Howell]]'s arrival on the [[Waco]] compound in 1981 was well received by nearly everyone at the Davidian commune. Howell had an affair with the then-[[prophet]] of the Branch Davidians, [[Lois Roden]], while he was in his late 20s and she was in her late 60s. Howell wanted a child with her, who, according to his understanding, would be the Chosen One. When she died, her son [[George Roden]] inherited the positions of prophet and leader of the commune. However, George Roden and Howell began to clash.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Biography: David Koresh|url=https://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/frontline/waco/davidkoresh.html|website=PBS|publisher=Frontline|accessdate=21 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Howell soon enjoyed the loyalty of the majority of the Branch Davidian community.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=David G. Bromley and Edward D. Silver|title=The Davidian Tradition: From Patronal Clan to Prophetic Movement|date=1995|publisher=Chicago: University of Chicago|location=in Stuart A. Wright, Armageddon in Waco: Critical Perspectives on the Branch Davidian Conflict|page=54}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:David koresh.jpg|thumb|upright|David Koresh in a 1987 mug shot]]
As an attempt to regain support, George Roden challenged Howell to raise the dead, going so far as to exhume a corpse in order to demonstrate his spiritual supremacy. This illegal act gave Howell an opportunity to attempt to file charges against Roden; however, he was told he needed evidence. This led to the raid on November 3, 1987, of the [[Mount Carmel Center]] by Howell and 7 of his followers equipped with five .223 caliber semiautomatic rifles, two .22 caliber rifles, two 12-gauge shotguns and nearly 400 rounds of ammunition. Their objective seemed to be to retake the land that Howell had left three years earlier: although they claim to have been trying to obtain evidence of Roden's illegal activity, they did not come equipped with a camera.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=BIOGRAPHY: David Koresh|url=https://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/frontline/waco/davidkoresh.html|publisher=PBS|accessdate=23 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The trial ended with the jury finding the followers of Howell not guilty, but the jury members were unable to agree on a verdict for Howell. After his followers were found not guilty, Howell invited the prosecutors to Mount Carmel for ice cream.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1993/03/10/us/warning-of-violence-was-unheeded-after-cult-leader-s-gun-battle-in-87.html|title=Warning of Violence Was Unheeded After Cult Leader's Gun Battle in '87|last=Nossiter|first=Adam|date=1993-03-10|newspaper=The New York Times|issn=0362-4331|access-date=2016-05-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It is claimed that Howell was never authorized to name his breakaway sect the &quot;Branch Davidians.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;The General Association of Branch Davidians&lt;/ref&gt; and the church which bears that name continues to represent the members of the Branch church who did not follow him.

=== As a spiritual leader ===
Howell, who acquired the position of spiritual leader from Roden, asserted it by changing his name to [[David Koresh]], suggesting that he had ties to the biblical [[King David]] and [[Cyrus the Great]] (Koresh is the [[Hebrew language|Hebrew]] version of the name Cyrus). In 1989 Koresh used his power as spiritual leader to take several &quot;spiritual&quot; wives, some of whom were as young as 12;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-2588106/We-werent-brainwashed-Waco-cult-survivor-claims-new-memoir-Branch-Davidian-leader-David-Koresh-19-wives-slept-girls-young-12.htmlh&lt;/ref&gt; he wanted to create a new lineage of world leaders.&lt;ref name=&quot;melton1&quot;/&gt; This practice later served as the basis for allegations that Koresh was committing [[child abuse]], which contributed to the siege by the [[Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms and Explosives|ATF]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.justice.gov/publications/waco/report-deputy-attorney-general-events-waco-texas-child-abuse|title=Report to the Deputy Attorney General on the Events at Waco, Texas: Child Abuse {{!}} DOJ {{!}} Department of Justice|website=www.justice.gov|language=en|access-date=2017-05-17|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170511015541/https://www.justice.gov/publications/waco/report-deputy-attorney-general-events-waco-texas-child-abuse|archive-date=2017-05-11|url-status=dead|df=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Interpreting [[Revelation 5|Revelation 5:2]], Koresh identified himself with the Lamb mentioned in the verse.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.britannica.com/topic/Branch-Davidian#ref700562|title=Branch Davidian {{!}} religious organization|last=Melton|first=John Gordon|date=|work=Encyclopedia Britannica|access-date=2017-05-17|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bible.com/bible/111/REV.5.NIV|title=Revelation 5, New International Version (NIV) {{!}} Chapter 5 {{!}} The Bible App {{!}} Bible.com|website=www.bible.com|language=en|access-date=2017-05-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; This is traditionally believed to symbolize [[Jesus|Jesus Christ]], however, Koresh suggested that the Lamb would come before Jesus and pave the way for his [[Second Coming]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://bible.org/seriespage/14-when-all-heaven-breaks-loose-revelation-51-14|title=14. When All Heaven Breaks Loose! (Revelation 5:1-14)|last=Krell|first=Keith|date=|work=Live Like You're Leaving: Revelation|access-date=2017-05-17|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180111052810/https://bible.org/seriespage/14-when-all-heaven-breaks-loose-revelation-51-14|archive-date=2018-01-11|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;melton1&quot;/&gt;

By the time of the 1993 Waco siege, Koresh had encouraged his followers to think of themselves as &quot;students of the [[Seven seals|Seven Seals]]&quot; rather than as &quot;Branch Davidians.&quot; During the standoff, one of his followers publicly announced that he wanted them to thereafter be identified by the name &quot;Koreshians&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Mr. Ricks [FBI negotiator] said today that Ms. Schroeder had told him that members of the sect, a renegade offshoot of Seventh-day Adventists, henceforth wanted to be known as Koreshians.&quot; By Robert Reinhold, Published: March 15, 1993, ''New York Times'' [brackets added].&lt;/ref&gt;

== Waco siege ==
{{Main|Waco siege}}
On February 28, 1993, at 9:45 AM, the [[Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms and Explosives|Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, and Firearms]] attempted to execute a search warrant relating to alleged sexual abuse charges and illegal weapons violations.&lt;ref&gt;Affidavit of Davy Aguilera, Special Agent with the U.S Treasury Department, BATF, Austin, Texas, sworn before Dennis G. Green, United States Magistrate Judge Western District of Texas – Waco on the 25 February 1993. Aguilera affirmed: &quot;On January 13, 1993, I interviewed Larry Gilbreath in Waco, Texas, and confirmed the information which had previously been related to me by Lt. Barber. Mr. Gilbreath told me that although he had been making deliveries at the &quot;Mag-Bag&quot; and the Mt. Carmel Center for quite some time, his suspicion about the packages being delivered to those places was never aroused until about February 1992. At that time the invoices accompanying a number of packages reflected that they contained firearm parts and accessories as well as various chemicals. He stated that in May 1992, a package which was addressed to the &quot;Mag-Bag&quot; accidentally broke open while it was being loaded on his delivery truck. He saw that it contained three other boxes, the contents of which were &quot;pineapple&quot; type hand grenades which he believed to be inert. He stated that there were about 50 of the grenades and that he later delivered them to the Mt. Carmel Center.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m1571/is_n26_v9/ai_14021102/|title=ATF's basis for the assault on Waco is shot full of holes - Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco and Firearms fatal attack on the Branch Davidian complex in Waco, Texas|last=Fiddleman|first=Theodore|date=June 28, 1993|work=Insight on the News|archive-url=https://archive.is/20120710211706/http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m1571/is_n26_v9/ai_14021102/|archive-date=2012-07-10|url-status=bot: unknown|last2=Kopel|first2=David}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ATF attempted to breach the compound for approximately two hours until their ammunition ran low.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.cesnur.org/testi/waco97.htm|title=Agents prepared for worst before Waco raid|last=|first=|date=July 5, 2000|agency=Associated Press|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0120472/ |title= Waco: The Rules of Engagement (1997) |author1= Gazecki, William |author2= Gifford, Dan |author3= McNulty, Michael |work= Film Documentary |publisher= [[IMDb]] – Internet Movie Database |accessdate= 25 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Four ATF agents (Steve Willis, Robert Williams, Todd McKeehan, and Conway Charles LeBleu) were killed and another 16 agents were wounded during the raid. The five Branch Davidians killed in the 9:45 AM raid were Winston Blake (British), Peter Gent (Australian), Peter Hipsman, Perry Jones, and Jaydean Wendell; two at the hands of the Branch Davidians themselves.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=No Heroes : Inside the FBI's Secret Counter-Terror Force|last=Elaine.|first=Shannon|date=2001|publisher=Pocket Books|isbn=0671020625|location=|pages=|oclc=46772515}}&lt;/ref&gt; Almost six hours after the ceasefire, Michael Schroeder was shot dead by ATF agents who alleged he fired a pistol at agents as he attempted to re-enter the compound with Woodrow Kendrick and Norman Allison.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot;&gt;Neil Rawles (February 2, 2007). ''Inside Waco'' (Television documentary). Channel 4/HBO.&lt;/ref&gt; His wife claimed that he was merely returning from work and had not participated in the day's earlier altercation.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt; Schroeder had been shot once in the eye, once in the heart, and five times in the back.&lt;ref&gt;Linda Thompson (1993). ''Waco, the Big Lie'' (Documentary short film) US: American Justice Federation&lt;/ref&gt;

After the raid, ATF agents established contact with Koresh and others inside of the compound. The [[FBI]] took command after the deaths of federal agents, and managed to facilitate the release of 19 children (without their parents) relatively early into the negotiations.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot;&gt;Psychotherapy Networker ''(''2007). &quot;Stairway to Heaven; Treating children in the crosshairs of trauma.&quot; Excerpt from the book ''The Boy Who Was Raised as a Dog'' by Bruce Perry and Maia Szalavitz.&lt;/ref&gt; The children were then interviewed by the FBI and the [[Texas Ranger Division|Texas Rangers.]]&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt; Allegedly, the children had been physically and sexually abused long before the raid.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Report_to_the_Deputy_Attorney_General_on_the_Events_at_Waco,_Texas/Child_Abuse|title=Report to the Deputy Attorney General on the Events at Waco, Texas/Child Abuse|last=FBI|date=|website=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Mountcarmelfire04-19-93-n.jpg|thumb|FBI photo of the [[Mount Carmel Center]] engulfed in flames]]
On April 19, 1993, the FBI moved for a final siege of the compound using large weaponry such as [[.50 caliber]] (12.7&amp;nbsp;mm) rifles and armored [[Combat Engineering Vehicle]]s (CEV) to combat the heavily armed Branch Davidians. The FBI attempted to use [[tear gas]] to flush out the Branch Davidians without bloodshed. Officially, FBI agents were only permitted to return any incoming fire, not to actively assault the Branch Davidians. When several Branch Davidians opened fire, the FBI's response was to increase the amount of gas being used.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt; Around noon, three fires broke out simultaneously in different parts of the building, The government maintains the fires were deliberately started by Branch Davidians.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.justice.gov/publications/waco/report-deputy-attorney-general-events-waco-texas-aftermath-april-19-fire|title=Report to the Deputy Attorney General on the Events at Waco, Texas: The Aftermath of the April 19 Fire|last=US Department of Justice|date=1993|website=The U.S. Department of Justice|access-date=|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170511015809/https://www.justice.gov/publications/waco/report-deputy-attorney-general-events-waco-texas-aftermath-april-19-fire|archive-date=2017-05-11|url-status=dead|df=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some Branch Davidian survivors maintain that the fires were started either accidentally or deliberately by the assault.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=A Place Called Waco : A Survivor's Story|last=Leon.|first=Whiteson|date=1999|publisher=PublicAffairs|isbn=1891620428|location=|pages=|oclc=41368317|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/placecalledwacos00davi}}&lt;/ref&gt; Of the 85 Branch Davidians in the compound when the final siege began, 76 died on April 19 in various ways, from falling rubble to suffocating effects of the fire, or by gunshot wound from fellow Branch Davidians.&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot; /&gt; The siege lasted 51 days.

=== Aftermath ===
In all, 4 ATF agents were killed, 16 were wounded, and six Branch Davidians died in the initial raid on February 28. 76 more died in the final assault on April 19.&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot; /&gt; The events at Waco spurred criminal prosecution and civil litigation. A federal grand jury indicted 12 of the surviving Branch Davidians charging them with aiding and abetting in murder of federal officers, and unlawful possession and use of various firearms. Eight Branch Davidians were convicted on firearms charges, 5 convicted of [[voluntary manslaughter]], and four were acquitted of all charges.&lt;ref&gt;p. 7403 of the trial transcripts&lt;/ref&gt; As of July 2007, all Branch Davidians had been released from prison.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.foxnews.com/story/2006/04/19/six-branch-davidians-due-for-release-13-years-after-waco-inferno.html|title=Six Branch Davidians Due for Release 13 Years After Waco Inferno|last=Associated Press|first=|date=April 19, 2006|work=Fox News|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Several civil suits were brought against the [[United States government]], federal officials, former governor of Texas [[Ann Richards]], and members of the [[Texas Army National Guard]]. The bulk of these claims were dismissed because they were insufficient as a matter of law or because the plaintiffs could advance no material evidence in support of them. One case, Andrade v. Chojnacki made it to the [[Fifth Circuit]], which upheld a previous ruling of &quot;take-nothing, denied&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Andrade v. Chojnacki, 338 F.3d 448 (5th Cir. 2003), cert. denied (2004).&lt;/ref&gt;

== Branch Davidians after Waco ==
{{expand section|date=February 2018}}
One modern incarnation of the Branch Davidians exists under the leadership of Charles Pace, a follower of Ben and Lois Roden, who was a member of the Branch Davidians from the mid-1970s. '''The Branch, The Lord Our Righteousness''' is a legally recognized denomination with 12 members. Pace claims that Koresh twisted the Bible's teachings by fathering more than a dozen children with members’ wives.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=The Associated Press|title=Near Waco, a New Fight Over an Old Compound|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/us/15waco.html|newspaper=New York Times|accessdate=12 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Pace believes that the Lord &quot;has anointed me and appointed me to be the leader&quot; but he claims that he is &quot;not a prophet&quot; but &quot;a teacher of righteousness&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last1=Burnett|first1=John|title=Two Decades Later, Some Branch Davidians Still Believe|url=https://www.npr.org/2013/04/20/178063471/two-decades-later-some-branch-davidians-still-believe|accessdate=12 May 2016|publisher=National Public Radio|date=April 20, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Like the Branch Davidians under Koresh, this incarnation is waiting for the end of times.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;/&gt;

== Relationship with Seventh-Day Adventists ==

The [[Seventh-day Adventist Church]], the main church in the [[Adventist]] tradition, rejected [[Victor Houteff]]'s teachings and revoked his membership in 1930. Houteff went on to found the Davidians (a splinter group, otherwise known as the [[Shepherd's Rod]]). Branch Davidians are considered a splinter group from that dissenting group (the Davidians/Shephard's Rod) and the product of a schism among the Davidians/Shepherd's Rod initiated by [[Benjamin Roden]].

Branch Davidian leaders, while still formally members in the Seventh-day Adventist Church, pushed for a reform of the church and when this was met with opposition (from both the common Seventh-day Adventists and also the already excluded Davidians/Shepherd's Rod), they decided to leave that denomination while at the same time widely distancing themselves from the Davidians/Shepherd's Rod (their &quot;parent group&quot; that arose earlier and was also excluded for their own attempts to reform the Seventh-day Adventist Church). The Seventh-day Adventist Church deprived both the Branch Davidians and the Davidians of their membership in the denomination, but in spite of this fact the Branch Davidians actively continued to &quot;hunt&quot; members of the Seventh-day Adventist Church, encouraging them to leave it and join their group instead. The Seventh-day Adventists were reportedly &quot;apprehensive&quot; about the group's views as Branch Davidians claimed to be the &quot;only rightful continuation of the [[Adventism|Adventist message]]&quot;, based on the idea that [[Victor Houteff]] was the divinely selected prophet and successor to [[Ellen G. White]]. Both the Davidians/Shepherd's Rod and the Branch Davidians claimed Houteff as their spiritual inspiration, although he was the founder of the Davidians/Shepherd's Rod. The Seventh-day Adventist Church issued warnings about the Branch Davidian views to its members on a regular basis.&lt;ref&gt;Armageddon in Waco: Critical Perspectives on the Branch Davidian Conflict by Stuart A. Wright, p.22&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Schisms within the Branch Davidian sect ===

There is documented evidence (FBI negotiation transcripts between Kathryn Shroeder and Steve Schneider with interjections from Koresh himself) that David Koresh and his followers did not call themselves Branch Davidians.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://digital.library.txstate.edu/bitstream/handle/10877/1958/507.pdf?sequence=1|title=United States Department of the Treasury: Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco &amp; Firearms (Tape #126 Transcription)|last=|first=|date=March 13, 1993|website=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, David Koresh, through forgery, stole the identity of the Branch Davidian Seventh-day Adventists for the purpose of obtaining the Mount Carmel Center property.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Waco Untold, How David Koresh Stole the Identity of The Branch Davidians|last=Mitchell|first=Douglas|publisher=Ten Strings Publishing|year=2018|isbn=978-0-9998026-0-1|location=USA|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The doctrinal beliefs of the Branch Davidians differ on teachings such as the [[Holy Spirit]] and his nature, and the feast days and their requirements. Both groups have disputed the relevance of the other's spiritual authority based on the proceedings following [[Victor Houteff]]'s death. From its inception in 1930, the Davidians/Shepherd's Rod group believed themselves to be living in a time when [[Bible prophecy|Biblical prophecies]] of a [[Last Judgment]] were coming to pass as a prelude to [[Christ (title)|Christ]]'s [[Second Coming]].

In the late 1980s, Koresh and his followers abandoned many Branch Davidian teachings. Koresh became the group's self-proclaimed final prophet. &quot;Koreshians&quot; were the majority resulting from the schism among the Branch Davidians, but some of the Branch Davidians did not join Koresh's group and instead gathered around [[George Roden]] or became independent. Following a series of violent shootouts between Roden's and Koresh's group, the Mount Carmel compound was eventually taken over by the &quot;Koreshians&quot;.

== See also ==
* [[Cult]]
* [[Apocalypticism]]
* [[List of new religious movements]]
* [[List of Christian denominations]]
* [[Millenarianism]]
* [[Religious violence]]

== References ==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}
37.) https://www.amazon.com/Waco-Untold-Koresh-Identity-Davidians/dp/0999802607/ref=sr_1_1?keywords=Waco+Untold&amp;qid=1583005536&amp;sr=8-1

== External links ==
* [http://www.bdsda.com The General Association of Branch Davidian Seventh Day Adventists]
 
{{Branch Davidians}}
{{Sabbath-Keeping Churches}}
{{Religiously motivated suicides}}
{{Authority control}}

[[Category:1959 establishments in Texas]]
[[Category:Christian organizations established in 1959]]
[[Category:Organizations based in Texas]]
[[Category:Branch Davidianism]]
[[Category:Adventism]]
[[Category:Christian denominations established in the 20th century]]
[[Category:Paramilitary organizations based in the United States]]
[[Category:Religious paramilitary organizations]]
[[Category:Christian new religious movements]]
[[Category:Religious controversies]]
[[Category:Waco siege]]</text>
      <sha1>dmxw55jpkiqa3w4o0xipt16wn4jrk0s</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
