  <page>
    <title>Bohemian</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4716</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942322189</id>
      <parentid>942322121</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-24T00:10:48Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>104.187.97.148</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Etymology */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Other uses}}
{{refimprove|date=May 2015}}
{{Infobox ethnic group
| group        = Bohemians&lt;br/&gt;Češi
| flag         = 
| flag_caption = 
| regions      = 
| tablehdr     = ''Significant [[Czech diaspora|diasporic]] populations in:''
| population   = {{circa|'''6,500,000+'''}}
| popplace     = '''{{CZE}}{{nbsp|2}}&lt;br&gt;6,500,000'''
| region1      = 
| pop1         = 
| region2      = 
| pop2         = 
| region3      = 
| pop3         = 
| region4      = 
| pop4         = 
| region5      =
| pop5         =
| langs        = [[Czech language|Czech]]
| rels         = Traditionally [[Christianity|Christian]]:&lt;br&gt;[[Roman Catholic Church|Roman Catholic]], [[Hussites|Hussite]], [[Lutheranism|Lutheran]] and other&lt;br&gt;Mostly [[irreligious]]
|related = [[Czechs]], [[Moravians]], and other [[West Slavs]] ([[Slovaks]], [[Poles]], [[Silesians]], [[Sorbs]] and [[Kashubs]])
}}

A '''Bohemian''' ({{IPAc-en|b|oʊ|ˈ|h|iː|m|i|ə|n}}) is a resident of [[Bohemia]], a region of the [[Czech Republic]] or the former [[Kingdom of Bohemia]], a region of the former Crown of Bohemia ([[lands of the Bohemian Crown]]). In English, the word &quot;Bohemian&quot; was used to denote the [[Czech people]] as well as the [[Czech language]] before the word &quot;Czech&quot; became prevalent in the early 20th century.&lt;ref name = Oxford/&gt;

In a separate meaning, &quot;Bohemian&quot; may also denote &quot;a socially unconventional person, especially one who is involved in the arts&quot; according to [[OxfordDictionaries.com|Oxford Dictionaries Online]]. (See [[Bohemianism]]).&lt;ref name = Oxford&gt;[http://oxforddictionaries.com/definition/Bohemian &quot;Bohemian&quot;], ''Oxford Dictionaries'' online, Oxford University Press, Retrieved on: 2011-09-14&lt;/ref&gt;

== Etymology ==
[[File:Ottův slovník naučný - 17 České kroje - 2.jpg|thumb|Bohemian traditional costumes]]
The name &quot;Bohemia&quot; derives from the name of the [[Boii]], a [[Celts|Celtic]] tribe who inhabited the area towards the latter [[La Tène period]] (1st century BC). The toponym ''Boiohaemum,'' first attested by [[Tacitus]]&lt;ref&gt;''[[Germania (book)|Germania]]'' 28.&lt;/ref&gt; around AD 98, is taken to mean &quot;home of the Boii&quot; (from the [[Proto-Germanic language|Germanic]] root *''haima-'' &quot;world, home&quot;).

The word &quot;Bohemian&quot; has never been widely used by the Czech population. In [[Czech language]], the region since the early Middle Ages has been called ''Čechy'' but also, especially during the period of restoration/emancipation of the Czech language and nation, as ''Čechie.'' Another term, stressing the importance of the state/nation, was ''Království české'' (&quot;Czech Kingdom&quot;), or ''Böhmen'' (Königreich) in German. Its mainly Czech-speaking inhabitants were called ''Čechové'' (in modern Czech ''Češi'').

In most Western European vernaculars and Latin (as ''Bohemi''), the word &quot;Bohemian&quot; or a derivative was used. If the Czech ethnic origin was to be stressed, combinations such as &quot;Bohemian of Bohemian language&quot; (''Čech českého jazyka''), &quot;a real Bohemian&quot; (''pravý Čech''), etc. were used.

It was not until the [[19th century]] that other European languages began to use words related to &quot;Czechs&quot; (as in English, ''Tschechen'' in [[German language|German]], ''Tchèques'' in [[French language|French]]) in a deliberate (and successful) attempt to distinguish between ethnic Slavic-speaking Bohemians and other inhabitants of Bohemia. The latter were mostly [[ethnic Germans]], who identified as &quot;German Bohemians&quot; (''Deutschböhmen'') or simply as &quot;Bohemians&quot; (''Böhmen''). In many parts of Europe, state citizenship was not identical with ethnicity and language, and the various peoples were usually identified by their language. Ethnic boundaries in Bohemia were not always sharp, and people very often were bilingual. Intermarriages across language borders were also common. Native Czech speakers often spoke German and many native German speakers spoke Czech with varying fluency, particularly in areas with many Czech speakers.

Currently, the word &quot;Bohemians&quot; is sometimes used about persons from Bohemia of all ethnic origins, especially before the year 1918, when the Kingdom of Bohemia ceased to exist formally. It is also used to distinguish between inhabitants of the western part (Bohemia proper) of the state (see [[Czechia]]), and the eastern ([[Moravia]], [[Moravians]]) or north-eastern ([[Czech Silesia|Silesia]]) parts.

The different but distantly related term &quot;[[Bohemianism]]&quot; was associated since early 19th century with &quot;a socially unconventional person, especially one who is involved in the arts&quot;, coming from the French ''bohémien.''&lt;ref name = Oxford/&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Name of the Czech Republic]]
* [[Czech studies|Bohemistics]]

== References ==
{{wiktionary|bohemian}}
;Notes
{{reflist}}
{{Authority control}}
[[Category:Bohemia|Bohemian]]
[[Category:Ethnic groups in the Czech Republic]]
[[Category:West Slavs]]</text>
      <sha1>d9si0blegavc4v9ihblw806tw2se4xa</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
