  <page>
    <title>Borzoi</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4764</id>
    <revision>
      <id>938099970</id>
      <parentid>931285717</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-29T03:09:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>118.46.55.151</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{About|domestic dog breed|the rural locality in the Chechen Republic|Borzoy}}
{{More footnotes|date=March 2014}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}
&lt;!-- Wikipedia:WikiProject Dog breeds/Templates for more info.--&gt;
{{Infobox Dogbreed
| image = Chart rosyjski borzoj rybnik-kamien pl.jpg
| image_caption = A Borzoi
| name = Borzoi
| altname = {{plainlist|
* Barzoï
* Russian wolfhound
* Russian hunting sighthound
* {{transl|ru|Russkaya psovaya borzaya}}
}}

| country = [[Russia]]
&lt;!-----Traits-----&gt;
|weight = 
|maleweight = {{convert|75|-|105|lb|kg|0|abbr=on}}
|femaleweight = {{convert|55|-|90|lb|kg|0|abbr=on}}
|height = 
|maleheight = {{convert|75|-|85|cm|in|0|abbr=on}}
|femaleheight = {{convert|68|-|78|cm|in|0|abbr=on}}
|coat = Medium length, silky and wavy, short length
|color = Any color
|litter_size = 1–11 puppies
|life_span = 11–15 years
&lt;!-----Classification and standards-----&gt;
| fcigroup = 10
| fcisection = 1 Long-haired or fringed Sighthounds
| fcinum = 193
| fcistd = http://www.fci.be/Nomenclature/Standards/193g10-en.pdf
| akcgroup = Hound
| akcstd =http://www.akc.org/breeds/borzoi/breed_standard.cfm
| ankcgroup = Group 4 (Hounds)
| ankcstd = https://web.archive.org/web/20141208202013/http://www.ankc.org.au/Breed_Details.aspx?bid=110
| ckcgroup = Group 2 - Hounds
| ckcstd = https://web.archive.org/web/20141210054819/http://www.ckc.ca/en/Files/Forms/Shows-Trials/Breed-Standards/Group-2-Hounds/BRO-Borzoi
| kcukgroup = Hound
| kcukstd = http://www.thekennelclub.org.uk/services/public/breed/standard.aspx?id=1007
| nzkcgroup = Hound
| nzkcstd = https://web.archive.org/web/20030808204555/http://www.nzkc.org.nz/br424.html
| ukcgroup = [[Sighthound &amp; Pariah Group|Sighthound &amp; Pariah]]
| ukcstd = http://www.ukcdogs.com/Web.nsf/Breeds/SighthoundPariah/Borzoi05012008
}}&lt;!-- End Infobox --&gt;

The '''borzoi''' ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|b|ɔr|z|ɔɪ}}, literally &quot;fast&quot;), also called the '''Russian wolfhound''' ({{lang-ru|Ру́сская псовая борзая|Russkaya psovaya borzaya}}), is a [[dog breed|breed]] of [[domestic dog]]. Descended from dogs brought to Russia from central Asian countries, it is similar in shape to a [[greyhound]], and is also a member of the [[sighthound]] family.

The system by which Russians over the ages named their sighthounds was a series of descriptive terms, not actual names. [[:wiktionary:ru:борзый|{{transl|ru|Borzói}}]] is the masculine singular form of an archaic Russian adjective that means &quot;fast&quot;. {{transl|ru|Borzáya sobáka}} (&quot;fast dog&quot;) is the basic term used by Russians, though {{transl|ru|sobáka}} is usually dropped. The name {{transl|ru|psovaya}} derived from the word {{transl|ru|psovina}}, which means &quot;wavy, silky coat&quot;, just as {{transl|ru|hortaya}} (as in [[hortaya borzaya]]) means shorthaired. In modern Russian, the breed commonly called the borzoi is officially known as {{transl|ru|russkaya psovaya borzaya}}. Other Russian sighthound breeds are {{transl|ru|stepnaya borzaya}} (from the [[steppe]]), called {{transl|ru|stepnoi}}; and {{transl|ru|krimskaya borzaya}} (from the [[Crimean Peninsula|Crimea]]), called {{transl|ru|krimskoi}}.

The most commonly used plural form is the regular formation ''borzois'', which is the only plural cited in most dictionaries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/borzoi?s=t |title=Borzoi |work=Dictionary |date= |accessdate=2014-04-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oxforddictionaries.com/definition/english/borzoi?q=borzoi |title=Definition of borzoi in Oxford dictionary (British &amp; World English) |publisher=Oxford dictionary |date= |accessdate=2014-04-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the Borzoi Club of America and the Borzoi Club UK&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://theborzoiclub.org.uk/ |title=theborzoiclub.org.uk |publisher=theborzoiclub.org.uk |date= |accessdate=2014-04-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; both prefer ''borzoi'' as the form for both singular and plural forms.

== Description ==
[[File:Medalowy borgoj.jpg|thumb|left|Borzoi, red coat]]

=== Appearance ===

Borzois are large Russian [[sighthound]]s that resemble some central Asian breeds such as the [[Afghan hound]], [[Saluki]], and the [[Taigan|Kyrgyz Taigan]]. Borzois can generally be described as &quot;long-haired [[greyhound]]s&quot;.  Borzois come in virtually any colour.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.akc.org/breeds/borzoi/color_markings.cfm|title=Borzoi Colors and Markings|publisher=American Kennel Club|accessdate=19 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The borzoi coat is silky and flat, often wavy or slightly curly. The long top-coat is  quite flat, with varying degrees of waviness or curling. The soft undercoat thickens during winter or in cold climates, but is shed in hot weather to prevent overheating. In its texture and distribution over the body, the borzoi coat is unique. There should be a frill on its neck, as well as feathering on its hindquarters and tail.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.borzoiclubofamerica.org/stand.htm|title=The Borzoi Standard|publisher=Borzoi Club of America|accessdate=19 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Borzoi males frequently weigh more than {{convert|100|lb|kg}}. Males stand at least {{convert|30|in|cm}} at the shoulder, while the height of females is around {{convert|26|in|cm}}. Despite their size, the overall impression is of streamlining and grace, with a curvy shapeliness and compact strength.
{{Clear}}
&lt;gallery widths=&quot;200px&quot; heights=&quot;200px&quot; perrow=&quot;5&quot;&gt;

File:Borzoi black female.png|A black borzoi
File:Three Borzoi.jpg|Yellow and white, and white borzois
File:Rjaska v. Kaluga.jpg|Black and white Borzoi
File:Borzoi 600.jpg|White with brown coated Borzoi

&lt;/gallery&gt;

=== Temperament ===

[[File:Borzoi portrait Flickr.jpg|thumb|Borzoi, white - sandy coloured coat]]
[[File:Borzoj bieg licencyjny 19.09.09 2p.jpg|thumb|Borzoi as race dog]]
[[File:Kidai.jpg|thumb|Male white Borzoi with grey markings]]

The borzoi is an athletic and independent breed of dog. Most borzois are fairly quiet, barking on rare occasions. They do not have strong territorial drives and cannot be relied on to raise the alarm upon sighting a human intruder. The borzoi requires patient, experienced handling.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.akc.org/dog-breeds/borzoi/|title=Borzoi|publisher=American Kennel Club|access-date=November 29, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; They are gentle and highly sensitive dogs with a natural respect for humans, and as adults they are decorative couch potatoes with remarkably gracious house manners. Borzois do not generally display dominance or aggression towards people, but can turn aggressive if handled roughly. Typically, they are rather reserved with strangers but affectionate with people they know well. Their sensitivity to invasion of their personal space can make them nervous around children unless they are brought up with them. Borzois adapt well to [[suburb]]an life, provided they have a spacious yard and regular opportunities for free exercise.{{citation needed|date=March 2014}}

A common misunderstanding about the intelligence of breeds in the [[Hound]] group stems from their independent nature, which conflicts with the frequent confusion between the concepts of &quot;intelligence&quot; and &quot;obedience&quot; in discussions of canine brainpower. [[Stanley Coren]]'s survey of canine obedience trainers published in ''[[The Intelligence of Dogs]]'' reported that borzois obeyed the first command less than 25% of the time. Coren's test, however, was by his own admission heavily weighted towards the &quot;obedience&quot; interpretation of intelligence and based on a better understanding of &quot;working&quot; breeds than hounds. Unfortunately, the publicity given to this report has led to unfair denigration of breeds which are under-represented in obedience clubs and poorly understood by the average obedience trainer.&lt;ref&gt;At a Conformation Judges training session not long after Coren's book was released, I was greeted by the coordinator with the question, &quot;I read something that said Borzois aren't very smart, is that true?&quot; This to the owner of several borzois, one of which knows how to open the refrigerator, and all of which respond instantly to &quot;commands&quot; given in that special owner-dog private language that wouldn't even be noticed by an outsider.&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;Work&quot; for hound breeds is done out of hearing and often out of sight of the human companion; it is an activity for which the dogs are &quot;released&quot;, rather than an activity which is &quot;commanded&quot;.{{citation needed|date=March 2014}}

In terms of obedience, borzois are selective learners who quickly become bored with repetitive, apparently pointless, activity, and they can be very stubborn when they are not properly motivated. For example, food rewards, or &quot;baiting&quot;, may work well for some individuals, but not at all for others. Nevertheless, borzois are definitely capable of enjoying and performing well in [[obedience trial|competitive obedience]] and [[dog agility|agility trials]] with the right kind of [[obedience training|training]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Scott|2002|page=113}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Brunarski/Moyer |url=http://www.nktelco.net/teine/lyric.htm |title=lyric |publisher=Nktelco.net |date= |accessdate=23 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.borzoiclubofamerica.org/ava.htm |title=Borzoi Club of America, Inc |publisher=Borzoiclubofamerica.org |accessdate=23 May 2012 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120229040739/http://www.borzoiclubofamerica.org/ava.htm |archivedate=29 February 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Like other sighthounds, they are very sensitive and do not cope well with harsh treatment or training based on punishment, and will be extremely unhappy if raised voices and threats are a part of their daily life. However, like any intelligent dog, borzois respond extremely well to the guidance, support, and clear communication of a benevolent human leadership.

Borzois were bred to pursue or &quot;course&quot; game and have a powerful instinct to chase things that run from them, including cats and small dogs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.yourpurebredpuppy.com/reviews/borzoi.html|title=Borzoi Temperament - What's Good About 'Em, What's Bad About 'Em|publisher=Your Purebred Puppy|accessdate=19 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Built for speed and endurance, they can cover long distances in a very short time. A fully fenced yard is a necessity for maintaining any [[sighthound]].{{citation needed|date=February 2019}} They are highly independent and will range far and wide without containment, with little regard for road traffic. For off-leash exercise, a borzoi needs a very large field or park, either fully fenced or well away from any roads, to ensure its safety. &lt;!-- Image with unknown copyright status removed: [[Image:Borzoi_in_flight.jpg|thumb|left|A young borzoi at a full run. This spectacular action comes in short bursts of activity; thirty minutes of off lead exercise a day is more than sufficient.]] --&gt;

Borzois are born with specialized coursing skills, but these are quite different from the dog-fighting instincts seen in some breeds. It is quite common for borzois at play to course (i.e., run down) another dog, seize it by the neck and hold it immobile. Young pups do this with their littermates, trading off as to who is the prey. It is a specific hunting behavior, not a fighting or territorial domination behavior.{{citation needed|date=March 2014}}

Borzois can be raised very successfully to live with [[cat]]s and other small animals provided they are introduced to them when they are puppies. Some, however, will possess the hunting instinct to such a degree that they find it impossible not to chase a cat that is moving quickly. The hunting instinct is triggered by movement and much depends on how the cat behaves.{{citation needed|date=March 2014}}

== Health ==
[[File:Borzoi-2ym-body.png|thumb|Borzois vary widely in colour]]

Stated life expectancy is 10 to 12 years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nzkc.org.nz/breed_info/br424.html|title=NZKC - Breed Standard - Borzoi|publisher=New Zealand Kennel Club|accessdate=3 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://animal.discovery.com/breed-selector/dog-breeds/hound/borzoi.html|title=Borzoi: Dog Breed Selector: Animal Planet|publisher=Animal Planet|accessdate=3 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Median lifespan based on a UK Kennel Club survey is 9 years 1 month. 1 in 5 died of old age, at an average of 10 to 11.5 years. The longest lived dog lived to 14 years 3 months.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Individual Breed Results for Purebred Dog Health Survey|url=http://www.thekennelclub.org.uk/item/570}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Dogs that are physically fit and vigorous in their youth through middle age are more vigorous and healthy as elderly dogs, all other factors being equal. In the UK, [[cancer]] and cardiac problems seem to be the most frequent causes of premature death.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thekennelclub.org.uk/cgi-bin/search.cgi?qt=mortality+borzoi&amp;ss=0&amp;search=Search]  {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120214224341/http://www.thekennelclub.org.uk/cgi-bin/search.cgi?qt=mortality%20borzoi&amp;ss=0&amp;search=Search|date=14 February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Like its native relative the [[Hortaya Borzaya]], the borzoi is relatively sound breed. [[Osteochondritis dissecans|OCD]], [[Hip dysplasia (canine)|hip]] and [[elbow dysplasia]] have remained almost unknown, as were congenital eye and heart diseases before the 1970s. However, in some countries modern breeding practices have introduced a few problems.

As with other very deep-chested breeds, [[gastric dilatation volvulus]] (also known as bloat) is the most common serious health problem in the borzoi. This life-threatening condition is believed to be anatomical rather than strictly genetic in origin. One common recommendation in the past has been to raise the food bowl of the dog when it eats. However, studies have shown that this may actually increase the risk of bloat.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Glickman L, Glickman N, Schellenberg D, Raghavan M, Lee T |title=Non-dietary risk factors for gastric dilatation-volvulus in large and giant breed dogs |journal=J. Am. Vet. Med. Assoc. |volume=217 |issue=10 |pages=1492–9 |year=2000 |pmid=11128539 |doi=10.2460/javma.2000.217.1492|url=https://semanticscholar.org/paper/dee4006602d93944ae80c9784913d86387a005d3 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Less common are cardiac problems including [[cardiomyopathy]] and [[cardiac arrhythmia]] disorders. A controversy exists as to the presence of [[progressive retinal atrophy]] in the breed. A condition identified as borzoi retinopathy is seen in some individuals, usually active dogs, which differs from progressive retinal atrophy in several ways. First, it is unilateral, and rarely seen in animals less than three years of age; second, a clear-cut pattern of inheritance has not been demonstrated; and finally, most affected individuals do not go blind.

[[File:Borzoi-2ym-head.png|thumb|right|Borzoi is basically a very sound breed.]]
Correct nutrition during puppyhood is also debatable for borzois. These dogs naturally experience enormous growth surges in the first year or two of their lives. It is now widely accepted that forcing even faster growth by feeding a highly concentrated, high-energy diet is dangerous for skeletal development, causing unsoundness and increased tendency to joint problems and injury. Being built primarily for speed, borzois do not carry large amounts of body fat or muscle, and therefore have a rather different physiology to other dogs of similar size (such as the [[Newfoundland (dog)|Newfoundland]], [[St. Bernard (dog)|St. Bernard]], or [[Alaskan Malamute]]). Laboratory-formulated diets designed for a generic &quot;large&quot; or &quot;giant&quot; breed are unlikely to take the needs of the big sighthounds into account.

The issues involved in [[raw feeding]] may be particularly relevant to tall, streamlined breeds such as the borzoi. The [[Hortaya Borzaya]], a very close relative, is traditionally raised on a meager diet of oats and table scraps. The Hortaya is also said to be intolerant of highly concentrated kibble feeds. A lean body weight in itself is nothing to be concerned about, and force-feeding of healthy young borzoi is definitely not recommended.

== History ==
[[File:1879 Borzoi Flock.jpg|thumb|Borzoi Flock DHSB 325, owned by Max Hartenstein, Berlin Germany, 1879]]
[[File:Tikhmenev (1904) Wolf hunt with borzois.jpg|thumb|''Wolf hunting with borzois'' (1904), Efim A. Tikhmenev.]]
[[File:Sarah Bernhardt Clairin Henderson.jpg|thumb|The famous actress, [[Sarah Bernhardt]], depicted with borzoi, by Georges Clairin, French painter]]

The Borzoi originated in 17&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; Century Russia by crossing Arabian greyhounds with a thick-coated breed.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.akc.org/dog-breeds/borzoi/|title=Borzoi Dog Breed Information|website=American Kennel Club|language=en|access-date=2019-05-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The more modern Psovaya Borzaya was founded on Stepnaya, Hortaya and the Ukrainian-Polish version of the old Hort. There were also imports of Western sighthound breeds to add to the height and weight. It was crossed as well with the Russian Laika specifically and singularly to add resistance against Northern cold and a longer and thicker coat than the Southern sighthounds were equipped with.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://dogs.animal-world.com/Hound-Dog-Breeds/Borzoi.php|title=Borzoi|last=Animal-World|website=Animal World|language=en|access-date=2018-06-01|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180601083847/http://dogs.animal-world.com/Hound-Dog-Breeds/Borzoi.php|archive-date=June 1, 2018 |url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

All of these foundation types—Tazi, Hortaya, Stepnaya, Krimskaya, and Hort—already possessed the instincts and agility necessary for hunting and bringing down wolves.

The Psovoi was popular with the [[Tsar]]s before the [[Russian Revolution of 1917|1917 revolution]]. For centuries, Psovoi could not be purchased but only given as gifts from the Tsar. [[Grand Duke Nicholas Nikolaevich of Russia (1856-1929)|Grand Duke Nicholas Nicolaievich of Russia]] bred countless Psovoi at [[Perchino]], his private estate.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Scott|2002|page=10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Russian concept of hunting trials was instituted during the era of the Tsars. As well as providing exciting sport, the tests were used for selecting borzoi breeding stock; only the quickest and most intelligent hunting dogs went on to produce progeny. For the aristocracy these trials were a well-organized ceremony, sometimes going on for days, with the borzois accompanied by mounted hunters and [[Foxhound]]s on the Russian [[steppe]]. Hares and other small game were by far the most numerous kills, but the hunters especially loved to test their dogs on wolf. If a wolf was sighted, the hunter would release a team of two or three borzois. The dogs would pursue the wolf, attack its neck from both sides, and hold it until the hunter arrived. The classic kill was by the human hunter with a knife. Wolf trials are still a regular part of the hunting diploma for all Russian sightdog breeds of the relevant type, either singly or in pairs or trios, in their native country.

After the [[1917 Revolution]], wolf hunting with sighthounds has soon gone out of fashion as an &quot;aristocratic&quot; and a means- and -time-taking way of hunting.
A necessity in a wolf-catching sighthound didn't exist, in addition to the old proved technique of battue with the use of baits, flags and other appeared new, way more effective—from airplanes, from propeller sleighs, with electronic lure whistles. For decades the generations of few remaining sighthounds were regarded as hunting-suited, when showing enough attacking initiative for fox hunting. The rumours about persecution of sighthounds in post-revolutionary Russia is a legend of modern times, possibly based on similar incidents in [[Maoist China]].

In the late 1940s, a Soviet soldier named [[Constantin Esmont]] made detailed records of the various types of borzoi he found in Cossack villages. Esmont's illustrations were recently published and can be viewed by clicking on the link below.

Esmont was concerned that the distinct types of borzaya were in danger of degenerating without a controlled system of breeding. He convinced the Soviet government that borzois were a valuable asset to the hunters who supported the fur industry and henceforth, their breeding was officially regulated. To this day short-haired [[Hortaya Borzaya]] are highly valued hunting dogs on the steppes, while the long-haired Psovaya Borzaya, is going through a hard period of restoration of its working qualities after decades of shadow, mainly show existence.

Exports of borzois to other countries were extremely rare during the Soviet era. However, enough had been taken to England, Scandinavia, Western Europe, and America in the late 19th century for the breed to establish itself outside its native country.

== Notable borzois ==
[[File:Borzaya.jpg|Borzoi portrait|thumb| 120px]]
* The borzoi is the symbol of [[Alfred A. Knopf]] publishing house.
* ''Tasha'', a female borzoi belonging to the noted vet [[Buster Lloyd-Jones]] (founder of Denes natural pet foods), was born in the UK during the Second World War and is the pedigree ancestor of most British borzoi bloodlines.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Scott|2002|page=14}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''Ben'' was the white male borzoi, beloved of [[Edward Smith (sea captain)|Edward J. Smith]], Captain of the [[RMS Titanic|Titanic]]. There exists a photo of the Captain and his dog outside his cabin on the ship. The dog was not, however, on the maiden voyage.
* ''Kolchak'' has been the mascot of the [[27th Infantry Regiment (United States)|27th Infantry Regiment]] since the Regiment participated in the [[Siberian Intervention]]. The 27th Infantry had been nicknamed &quot;The Wolfhounds&quot; in recognition of their endurance during battles in Siberia.

== In popular culture ==
[[File:Pjatak v. Smetanka.jpg|thumb|A Borzoi in the field with flowers]]
[[File:Borzoi female.jpg|thumb|A female Borzoi]]
* [[Leo Tolstoy]]'s 1869 novel ''[[War and Peace]]'' contains an extensive [[wolf hunting]] scene with borzois in book 7, chapters 3 to 6.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=War and Peace |first=Leo |last=Tolstoy |publisher=Wordsworth Classics |year=2001 |isbn=1-85326-062-2|title-link=War and Peace }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[F. Scott Fitzgerald]]'s second novel, ''[[The Beautiful and Damned]]'' (1922), contains a scene in which Gloria compares Anthony to a Russian wolfhound. Anthony decides to take this as a compliment: &quot;Anthony remembered that they were white and always looked unnaturally hungry. But then they were usually photographed with dukes and princesses, so he was properly flattered.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Fitzgerald|first=F. Scott|title=The Beautiful and Damned|year=1922|publisher=Serenity Publishers|pages=91–92|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=kQJVUID_JV4C|accessdate=9 May 2012|isbn=9781604506259}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[George Bernard Shaw]] in his ''Everybody’s Political What’s What?''(1944) wrote &quot;The future of mankind belongs to its mongrels and not to its handsome but brainless Borzois.&quot;
* Ivan, one of the protagonists of the historical novel by the Cuban writer [[Leonardo Padura Fuentes]], ''El hombre que amaba a los perros'' (The Man Who Loved Dogs), is the editor of a university journal of [[veterinary medicine]], who manages to make a living during the [[Special Period]] in Cuba by helping people take care of their dogs. The novel alludes to Ivan's own dogs as well as to borzoi dogs owned by [[Leon Trotsky]] and his assassin, [[Ramón Mercader]].
* A borzoi features prominently in a [[Music Hall]] [[revue]] in the short story ''Cousin Theresa'' by [[Saki]] (H.H.Munro).
* In the book ''The Romanov Prophecy'' (2004) by [[Steve Berry (novelist)|Steve Berry]]
* In the anime ''[[Kuroshitsuji]]'' (Japanese for Black Butler), Ciel Phantomhive as a child had a black borzoi named Sebastian. He named the demon with which he made a [[Faustian]] contract after this dog.
* The 1968 film version ''[[War and Peace (film series)|War and Peace]]'' contains a hunting scene with borzois from the kennel of Ekhaga, Sweden.
* Uncle Zeke starred as &quot;Digger&quot; in the 2000 Disney film, ''[[102 Dalmatians]]''
* The borzoi brothers, Rocket, Missile, and Jet in ''[[Ginga Densetsu Weed]]''
* Boris in [[Walt Disney]]'s 1955 film ''[[Lady and the Tramp]]''
* D'or's Prince Igor owned by Barbara Todd (Zcerlov) and bred by Andre Legere appears in the 1969 film, ''[[Hello, Dolly! (film)|Hello Dolly!]]''
* When [[Katniss Everdeen]] and [[Peeta Mellark]] arrive at the Capitol in the 2012 film ''[[The Hunger Games (film)|The Hunger Games]]'', a pair of pink borzois are shown on screen—an illustration of the Capitol residents' gaudy lifestyle.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wordofthenerdonline.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/GuCu6.jpg|format=JPG|title=Photographic image of owner and dog in matching pink coloration|website=Worldofthenerdonline.com|accessdate=11 December 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Borzois can also been seen in cameo roles in the films ''[[Love at First Bite]]'', ''[[Legends of the Fall]]'' (&quot;Notchee Boy&quot;),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.picklehillhound.com/notche.htm |title=Pickle Hill's Notchee Boy, JC in &quot;Legends Of The Fall&quot;|accessdate=2007-06-28 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070828033232/http://www.picklehillhound.com/notche.htm |archivedate=28 August 2007 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Excalibur (film)|Excalibur]]'', ''[[All Dogs Go to Heaven]]'' (1989), ''[[Bride of Frankenstein]]'', ''[[Easter Parade (1948 film)|Easter Parade]]'', ''[[Wolfen (film)|Wolfen]]'', ''[[Ziegfeld Follies (film)|Ziegfeld Follies]]'', ''[[Eugene Onegin#Film|Onegin]]'' (1999), ''Gangs of New York'' (2002), ''Chaplin'', ''The Avengers'' (TV series), ''JAG'', ''Maverick'' (1994), ''Sleepy Hollow'', ''Last Action Hero'', and ''A Knights Tale'' (on the DVD deleted scenes).
* &quot;Mademoiselle Nobs&quot; from [[Seamus (song)|Pink Floyd: Live at Pompeii]] (1971) who &quot;sings&quot; a [[Seamus (song)|song]] with the band.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.borzoiclubqld.com/the-versatile-borzoi.asp |title=The Borzoi Club of Queensland Inc |publisher=Borzoiclubqld.com |date= |accessdate=2014-04-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=X1wON-tWm5g |title=Mademoiselle Nobs |author=Pink Floyd |publisher=YouTube |date= |accessdate=2014-04-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Lyndell Ackerman's &quot;Nessie&quot; CH Windyglens Finesse in the TV show ''[[Wings (NBC TV series)|Wings]]''.
* In an [[Second City Television|SCTV]] parody commercial for fictional Poochare dog food, a borzoi dog is seen being taken for a walk by [[Eugene Levy]].
* In episode 2 of the first season of the anime [[Medaka Box]], one of the requests for the student council is to find a missing puppy, which turns out to be a borzoi. It has grown quite large since it was lost. This also happens in the manga version.
* A borzoi is one of the dogs to appear in the film ''[[Cats &amp; Dogs]]''. It is seen during the council session scene.
* The breed is featured in [[Amor Towles]]’ novel ''[[A Gentleman in Moscow]]'', notably in a scene where two borzois create havoc in their unsuccessful attempt to corral the hotel cat in the lobby of a luxury hotel in Moscow.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
 | last = Towles
 | first = Amor
 | editor =
 | title = A Gentleman in Moscow''
 | origyear = 
 | url =
 | format =
 | accessdate =
 | edition =
 | year = 2016
 | publisher = Viking Inc. 
 | location = New York, New York
 | language = English
 | isbn = 9780670026197
 | chapter =
 | chapterurl =
 | quote =
 | page = 111
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==In art==
In 2004, the UK [[The Kennel Club|Kennel Club]] held its fourth temporary exhibition, &quot;The Borzoi in Art,&quot; which offered unique insights into the borzoi and how the breed has been depicted in art throughout the 19th and 20th centuries. The exhibition included paintings, bronzes, and porcelain which had previously not been available to the public. The exhibition ran from 27 September to 3 December. The borzoi is frequently found in [[art deco]]-period works.

===Gallery===

&lt;gallery widths=&quot;200px&quot; heights=&quot;200px&quot; perrow=&quot;5&quot;&gt;

File:Borzo by a Chair-George Hare.jpg |A Borzoi by a Chair, by  [[St. George Hare|George Hare]]
File:Ernst Deutsch-Dryden - Die Suffragette.jpg |Die Suffragette

File:Louis Vorow Zborrowski by Julian Russell Story (1857-1919).jpg |Louis Vorow Zborrowski by [[Julian Russell Story]] (1857-1919)
File:George Barbier La Gazette1.jpg|[[George Barbier (illustrator)|George Barbier]] depicting a woman with a Borzoi in [[La Gazette]]
File:Affiche Steinlen 1.jpg
File:Bartina.jpg|A Borzoi with a Borzoi picture behind.
File:El venedor de tapissos.jpg|El venedor de tapissos, The carpet handler.
File:SerovElizabethDepartingOnAHunt.jpg| Painting by [[Valentin Alexandrovich Serov]]

&lt;!-- File:Chicago Kennel Club's Dog Show, advertising poster, 1902.jpg|Poster of Chicago Kennel Club's Dog Show --&gt;
&lt;!-- File:Statuette Fraureuth 1.jpg --&gt;
&lt;!-- File:Tableau A. Kivchenko.jpg --&gt;
&lt;!-- File:Borzoy Pair.JPG --&gt;
&lt;/gallery&gt;

== Notes ==
{{Reflist}}

== References ==
* ''The Borzoi Handbook'' Winifred E. Chadwick. London: Nicholson &amp; Watson 1952. Including a translation of ''The Perchino Hunt By His Excellency Dmitri Walzoff (1912)''.
* {{cite book|title=Borzoi|first=Gail C.|last=McRae|publisher=TFH Publications; New Ed edition|pages=[https://archive.org/details/borzois00gail/page/191 191 pages]|year=1989|isbn=978-0-86622-676-9|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/borzois00gail/page/191}}
* {{cite book|title=Borzoi - The Russian Wolfhound. Its History, Breeding, Exhibiting and Care|first=Nellie L.|last=Martin|publisher=Read Books|pages=128 pages|year=2005|isbn=978-1-84664-042-1}}
* {{cite book|title=Borzoi (Pet Love)|first=Dr. Desiree|last=Scott|publisher=Interpet Publishing, UK.|pages=160 pages|year=2002|isbn=1-903098-93-9|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|title=Russkaya Psovaya Borzaya|first=Galena V.|last=Zotova|publisher=Moscow|year=2003|isbn=5-94838-095-5}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Borzoi}}
*{{dmoz|Recreation/Pets/Dogs/Breeds/Hound_Group/Borzoi/}}
&lt;!-- DO NOT ADD PRIVATE BREEDERS OR ADVERTISING; IT WILL BE REMOVED --&gt;
&lt;!--Editors: breed registry, club, rescue, and kennel information links are placed on DMOZ, not here--&gt;
{{Hounds}}
{{Russian dogs}}

[[Category:FCI breeds]]
[[Category:Sighthounds]]
[[Category:Wolf hunting]]</text>
      <sha1>opirh4jza7gtcnpl5pfaf6owlh0qqi3</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
