  <page>
    <title>Brit milah</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4768</id>
    <revision>
      <id>938917577</id>
      <parentid>935473315</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-03T04:38:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Graham87</username>
        <id>194203</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contribs/2600:8805:9200:11C0:4E1:1D43:EE36:C03D|2600:8805:9200:11C0:4E1:1D43:EE36:C03D]] ([[User talk:2600:8805:9200:11C0:4E1:1D43:EE36:C03D|talk]]) to last version by InternetArchiveBot</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{redirect|Bris|the Seinfeld episode|The Bris}}
{{Religious text primary|date=June 2018}}
{{Infobox Halacha
| image = [[File:GerrerRebbe.JPG|230px]]
| caption =
| verse = {{bibleverse||Genesis|17:1-14|HE}}&lt;br /&gt;{{bibleverse||Leviticus|12:3|HE}}
| talmud = | mishnah = | rambam = | sa = | codes = }}
{{Judaism|culture}}
The '''''brit milah''''' ({{lang-he-n|בְּרִית מִילָה}}, {{IPA-he|bʁit miˈla|pron}}; [[Ashkenazi Hebrew|Ashkenazi]] pronunciation: {{IPA-he|bʁis ˈmilə|}}, &quot;covenant of [[circumcision]]&quot;; [[Yiddish]] pronunciation: ''bris'' {{IPA-yi|bʀɪs|}}) is a Jewish religious male [[Religious male circumcision|circumcision ceremony]] performed by a [[mohel]] (&quot;circumciser&quot;) on the eighth day of the infant's life. The ''brit milah'' is followed by a celebratory meal (''[[seudat mitzvah]]'').

==Biblical references==
{{main|Religious male circumcision}}
{{see also|Covenant (biblical)#Abrahamic covenant}}
[[File:Isaac's circumcision, Regensburg c1300.jpg|thumb|left|&quot;Isaac's Circumcision&quot;, Regensburg Pentateuch, c1300]]
According to the [[Hebrew Bible]] ({{bibleverse||Genesis|17:10–14|HE}}) [[Names of God in Judaism|God]] commanded the Biblical patriarch [[Abraham]] to be circumcised, an act to be followed by his descendants:
{{quote|10 This is My covenant, which ye shall keep, between Me and you and thy seed after thee: every male among you shall be circumcised. 11 And ye shall be circumcised in the flesh of your foreskin; and it shall be a token of a covenant betwixt Me and you. 12 And he that is eight days old shall be circumcised among you, every male throughout your generations, he that is born in the house, or bought with money of any foreigner, that is not of thy seed. 13 He that is born in thy house, and he that is bought with thy money, must needs be circumcised; and My covenant shall be in your flesh for an everlasting covenant. 14 And the uncircumcised male who is not circumcised in the flesh of his foreskin, that soul shall be cut off from his people; he hath broken My covenant.}}

Also, {{bibleverse||Leviticus|12:3|HE}} provides: &quot;And in the eighth day the flesh of his foreskin shall be circumcised.&quot;

According to the [[Hebrew Bible]], it was &quot;a reproach&quot; for an [[Israelite]] to be uncircumcised ([[Book of Joshua|Joshua]] 5:9.)  The term ''arelim'' (&quot;uncircumcised&quot; [plural]) is used opprobriously, denoting the [[Philistines]] and other non-Israelites ([[Books of Samuel|I Samuel]] 14:6, 31:4; II Samuel 1:20) and used in conjunction with ''tameh'' (unpure) for heathen ([[Book of Isaiah|Isaiah]] 52:1). The word ''arel'' (&quot;uncircumcised&quot; [singular]) is also employed for &quot;impermeable&quot; ([[Leviticus]] 26:41, &quot;their uncircumcised hearts&quot;; compare [[Book of Jeremiah|Jeremiah]] 9:25; [[Book of Ezekiel|Ezekiel]] 44:7, 9); it is also applied to the first three years' fruit of a tree, which is forbidden ([[Leviticus]] 19:23).

However, the Israelites born in the wilderness after the [[Book of Exodus|Exodus]] from Egypt were not circumcised. [[Book of Joshua|Joshua]] 5:2–9, explains, &quot;all the people that came out&quot; of [[Ancient Egypt|Egypt]] were circumcised, but those &quot;born in the wilderness&quot; were not. Therefore, Joshua, before the celebration of the [[Passover]], had them circumcised at [[Gilgal]] specifically before they entered Canaan. Abraham, too, was circumcised when he moved into Canaan.

The prophetic tradition emphasizes that God expects people to be good as well as pious, and that non-Jews will be judged based on their ethical behavior, see [[Noahide Law]]. Thus, Jeremiah 9:25–26 says that circumcised and uncircumcised will be punished alike by the Lord; for &quot;all the nations are uncircumcised, and all the house of Israel are uncircumcised in heart.&quot;

The penalty of non-observance is ''[[kareth]]'' (spiritual excision from the Jewish nation), as noted in {{bibleverse||Genesis|17:1–14|HE}}. [[Conversion to Judaism]] for non-Israelites in Biblical times necessitated circumcision, otherwise one could not partake in the [[Passover]] offering ({{bibleverse||Exodus|12:48|HE}}). Today, as in the time of Abraham, it is required of converts in [[Orthodox Judaism|Orthodox]], [[Conservative Judaism|Conservative]] and [[Reform Judaism]]. ({{bibleverse||Genesis|34:14–16|HE}}).

As found in Genesis 17:1–14, ''brit milah'' is considered to be so important that should the eighth day fall on [[Shabbat|the Sabbath]], actions that would normally be forbidden because of the sanctity of the day are permitted in order to fulfill the requirement to circumcise.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/Talmud/shabbat19.html Tractate Shabbat: Chapter 19, Regulations ordained by R. Eliezer concerning circumcision on the Sabbath] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160425221632/http://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/Talmud/shabbat19.html |date=2016-04-25 }}, accessed on 23 April 2016&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Talmud]], when discussing the importance of Milah, compares it to being equal to all other mitzvot (commandments) based on the [[gematria]] for ''brit'' of 612 (Tractate [[Nedarim (tractate)|Nedarim]] 32a).

Covenants in ancient times were sometimes sealed by severing an animal, with the implication that the party who breaks the covenant will suffer a similar fate. In Hebrew, the verb meaning &quot;to seal a covenant&quot; translates literally as &quot;to cut&quot;. It is presumed by Jewish scholars that the removal of the foreskin symbolically represents such a sealing of the covenant.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Circumcision.&quot; Mark Popovsky. Encyclopedia of Psychology and Religion. Ed. David A. Leeming, Kathryn Madden and Stanton Marlan. New York: Springer, 2010. pp. 153–54.&lt;/ref&gt;

===New Testament===
{{see also|Feast of the Circumcision of Christ}}
Due to [[Jesus]] having [[Circumcision of Jesus|undertaken]] this ceremony as a Jewish child, memory of this tradition has been preserved in traditional Christian churches according to the [[Gospel of Luke]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Bibleref|Luke|2:21}} (King James Version): &quot;And when eight days were accomplished for the circumcising of the child, his name was called JESUS, which was so named of the angel before he was conceived in the womb.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;In the northern European calculation, which abstracts from the day from which the count begins, the interval was of seven days.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Feast of the Circumcision of Christ]] is kept as a feast eight days after [[Nativity of Jesus|Nativity]] in a number of churches including the [[Eastern Orthodox Church]], [[Catholic Church]], [[Lutheran]] and some [[Anglican Communion]] churches.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |url         = http://www.holytrinityorthodox.com/calendar/los/January/01-01.htm
 |title       = The Circumcision (Obrezanie) of the Lord
 |work        = holytrinityorthodox.com
 |url-status     = live
 |archiveurl  = https://web.archive.org/web/20160802014350/http://holytrinityorthodox.com/calendar/los/January/01-01.htm
 |archivedate = 2016-08-02
}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In Orthodox Christian tradition, children are officially named on the eighth day after birth with special naming prayers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |url         = http://www.theologic.com/oflweb/inchurch/namingservice.htm
 |title       = The Prayer for the Naming of a Child on the Eighth Day
 |work        = theologic.com
 |url-status     = live
 |archiveurl  = https://web.archive.org/web/20150212180258/http://www.theologic.com/oflweb/inchurch/namingservice.htm
 |archivedate = 2015-02-12
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.stlukeorthodox.com/html/prayer/information/priestprayerbook.cfm|title=Saint Luke Orthodox Church – Prayer – Prayer Information – Mother Alexandra|website=www.stlukeorthodox.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Significantly, the tradition of [[baptism]] universally replaced circumcision among Christians as the primary [[rite of passage]] as found in [[Paul the Apostle|Paul's]] [[Epistle to the Colossians]] and in [[Acts of the Apostles]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Bibleref|Colossians|2:11–12}}{{Bibleref|Acts|15}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{secondary source needed|date=May 2017}}

==Ceremony==
[[File:Une circoncision, Marco Marcuola, Venise, vers 1870 - Musée d'Art et d'Histoire du Judaïsme.jpg|thumb|275px|Jewish circumcision in Venice around 1780 [[Musée d'Art et d'Histoire du Judaïsme]]]]

===Mohel===
A [[mohel]] is a Jew trained in the practice of ''brit milah'', the &quot;covenant of circumcision.&quot; According to traditional Jewish law, in the absence of a grown free Jewish male expert, anyone who has the required skills is also authorized to perform the circumcision, provided that they are Jewish.&lt;ref&gt;Talmud Avodah Zarah 26b; Menachot 42a; Maimonides' Mishneh Torah, Milah, ii. 1; [[Shulkhan Arukh]], Yoreh De'ah, l.c.&lt;/ref&gt; However, most streams of non-Orthodox Judaism allow female mohels, called ''mohalot'' ({{lang-he|מוֹהֲלוֹת}}, plural of {{lang|he|מוֹהֶלֶת}} ''mohelet'', feminine of ''mohel''), without restriction. In 1984, Deborah Cohen became the first certified Reform mohelet; she was certified by the Berit Mila program of Reform Judaism.&lt;ref&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20131007073323/http://beritmila.org/ Berit Mila Program of Reform Judaism] Retrieved 2 February 2015&lt;/ref&gt;

===Time and place===
[[File:Fauteuil de circoncision (&quot;Fauteuil d'Elie&quot;).jpg|thumb|''Chair of Elijah'' used during the ''brit milah'' ceremony – [[Musée d'Art et d'Histoire du Judaïsme]]]]
It is customary for the brit to be held in a synagogue, but it can also be held at home or any other suitable location. The brit is performed on the eighth day from the baby's birth, taking into consideration that according to the Jewish calendar, the day begins at the sunset of the day before. If the baby is born on Sunday before sunset, the Brit will be held the following Sunday. However, if the baby is born on Sunday night after sunset, the Brit is on the following Monday. The brit takes place on the eighth day following birth even if that day is Shabbat or a holiday. A brit is traditionally performed in the morning, but it may be performed any time during daylight hours.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |url         = http://www.chabad.org/library/article_cdo/aid/144464/jewish/The-Proper-Time-and-Place.htm
 |title       = The Circumcision Procedure and Blessings – Performing the Bris Milah – The Handbook to Circumcision
 |publisher   = Chabad.org
 |accessdate  = 2012-04-25
 |url-status     = live
 |archiveurl  = https://web.archive.org/web/20120116103539/http://www.chabad.org/library/article_cdo/aid/144464/jewish/The-Proper-Time-and-Place.htm
 |archivedate = 2012-01-16
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Postponement for health reasons====
[[File:Circumcision set.jpg|thumb|right|Family circumcision set and trunk, ca. eighteenth century Wooden box covered in cow hide with silver implements: silver trays, clip, pointer, silver flask, spice vessel.]]
The Talmud explicitly instructs that a boy must not be circumcised if he had two brothers who died due to complications arising from their circumcisions,&lt;ref name=&quot;JewEncMor&quot;&gt;{{Jewish Encyclopedia|article=Morbidity|url=http://jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=763&amp;letter=M}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Maimonides]] says that this excluded paternal half-brothers. This may be due to a concern about [[hemophilia]].&lt;ref name=&quot;JewEncMor&quot; /&gt;

An Israeli study found a high rate of [[urinary tract infection]]s if the bandage is left on too long.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |first       = Ofri
 |last        = Ilani
 |title       = Traditional circumcision raises risk of infection, study shows
 |url         = http://www.haaretz.com/hasen/spages/1043807.html
 |publisher   = Haaretz.com
 |date        = 2008-05-12
 |accessdate  = 15 August 2009
 |url-status     = live
 |archiveurl  = https://web.archive.org/web/20090820233703/http://www.haaretz.com/hasen/spages/1043807.html
 |archivedate = 20 August 2009
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

If the child is born [[premature baby|prematurely]] or has other serious medical problems, the brit milah will be postponed until the doctors and mohel deem the child strong enough for his foreskin to be surgically removed.

====Adult circumcision====
In recent years, the circumcision of adult Jews who were not circumcised as infants has become more common than previously thought.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | first      = Susan
  | last       = Kreimer
  | title      = In New Trend, Adult Emigrés Seek Ritual Circumcision
  | url        = http://forward.com/articles/4382/in-new-trend-adult-emigrcas-seek-ritual-circumcis/
  | publisher  = The Jewish Daily Forward
  | date       = 2004-10-22
  | accessdate = 24 August 2015
}}&lt;/ref&gt; In such cases, the brit milah will be done at the earliest date that can be arranged. The actual circumcision will be private, and other elements of the ceremony (e.g., the celebratory meal) may be modified to accommodate the desires of the one being circumcised.

===Anesthetic===
Most prominent ''[[acharonim]]'' rule that the ''[[mitzvah]]'' of brit milah lies in the pain it causes, and anesthetic, sedation, or ointment should generally not be used.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rabbi Yaakov Montrose, 2011, pp. 29-32&quot;&gt;Rabbi Yaakov Montrose. ''Halachic World – Volume 3: Contemporary [[Halakha|Halachic]] topics based on the [[Parshah]]''. &quot;Lech Lecha – No Pain, No Bris?&quot; Feldham Publishers 2011, pp. 29–32&lt;/ref&gt; However, it is traditionally common to feed the infant a drop of wine or other sweet liquid to soothe him.&lt;ref name=&quot;Judaism 101 Brit Milah: Circumcision&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last1=Rich|first1=Tracey|url=http://www.jewfaq.org/birth.htm#Brit|title=Judaism 101 – Birth and the First month of Life|publisher=jewfaq.org|accessdate=22 June 2016|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160601180905/http://www.jewfaq.org/birth.htm#Brit|archivedate=1 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Harris|first1=Patricia|title=Study confirms that wine drops soothe boys during circumcision|url=http://www.jweekly.com/article/full/11033/study-confirms-that-wine-drops-soothe-boys-during-circumcision/|accessdate=22 June 2016|agency=J.|publisher=jweekly.com|date=June 11, 1999|ref=wine drops soothe|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160813013454/http://www.jweekly.com/article/full/11033/study-confirms-that-wine-drops-soothe-boys-during-circumcision/|archivedate=13 August 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Eliezer Waldenberg]], [[Yechiel Yaakov Weinberg]], [[Shmuel Wosner]], [[Moshe Feinstein]] and others agree that the child should not be sedated, although pain relieving ointment may be used under certain conditions; [[Shmuel Wosner]] particularly asserts that the act ought to be painful, per [[Psalms]] 44:23.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rabbi Yaakov Montrose, 2011, pp. 29-32&quot;/&gt;

Regarding an adult circumcision, pain is ideal, but not mandatory.

In a letter to the editor published in ''[[The New York Times]]'' on January 3, 1998, [[Moshe David Tendler|Rabbi Moshe David Tendler]] disagrees with the above and writes, &quot;It is a biblical prohibition to cause anyone unnecessary pain&quot;. Rabbi Tendler recommends the use of an [[analgesic|analgesic cream]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news
 |url         = https://www.nytimes.com/1998/01/03/opinion/l-pain-and-circumcision-909360.html
 |title       = Pain and Circumcision
 |newspaper        = The New York Times
 |publisher   = Nytimes.com
 |date        = January 3, 1998
 |accessdate  = June 11, 2014
 |url-status     = live
 |archiveurl  = https://web.archive.org/web/20140714195348/http://www.nytimes.com/1998/01/03/opinion/l-pain-and-circumcision-909360.html
 |archivedate = July 14, 2014
}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Lidocaine]] should not be used, however, because Lidocaine has been linked to several pediatric near-death episodes.&lt;ref name=&quot;J Child Neurol 2002&quot;&gt;
{{cite journal
  | title   = Neonatal mydriasis: intravenous lidocaine adverse reaction.
  | last    = Berger
  | first   = Itai
  | last2   = Steinberg
  | first2  = Avraham
  | journal = J Child Neurol
  | url     = http://www3.interscience.wiley.com/cgi-bin/fulltext/122668866/PDFSTART
  | volume  = 17
  | issue   = 5
  | pages   = 400–01
  | date    = May 2002
  | pmid    = 12150593
  | doi     = 10.1177/088307380201700520
}}{{dead link|date=February 2019|bot=medic}}{{cbignore|bot=medic}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal
  | title   = Generalized seizures following topical lidocaine administration during circumcision: establishing causation.
  | last    = Rezvani
  | first   = Massoud
  | last2   = Finkelstein
  | first2  = Yaron
  | journal = Paediatr Drugs
  | volume  = 9
  | issue   = 2
  | pages   = 125–27
  | date    = 2007
  | pmid    = 17407368
  | doi     = 10.2165/00148581-200709020-00006
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Kvatter===
The title of ''[[wikt:קוואַטער|kvater]]'' among [[Ashkenazi Jews]] is for the person who carries the baby from the mother to the father, who in turn carries him to the ''[[mohel]].'' This honor is usually given to a couple without children, as a merit or ''[[Segula (Kabbalah)|segula]]'' (efficacious remedy) that they should have children of their own. The origin of the term is [[Middle High German]] ''gevater(e)'' (&quot;godfather&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Beider|first=Alexander|title=Origins of Yiddish Dialects|year=2015|publisher=Oxford University Press|page=153}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Seudat mitzvah===
After the ceremony, a [[Seudat mitzvah|celebratory meal]] takes place. At the ''[[birkat hamazon]]'', additional introductory lines, known as ''Nodeh Leshimcha'', are added. These lines praise God and request the permission of God, the [[Torah]], [[Kohen|Kohanim]] and distinguished people present to proceed with the grace. When the four main blessings are concluded, special ''ha-Rachaman'' prayers are recited. They request various blessings by God that include:
# the parents of the baby, to help them raise him wisely;
# the ''[[sandek]]'' (companion of child);
# the baby boy to have strength and grow up to trust in God and perceive Him [[Three pilgrim festivals|three times a year]];
# the ''mohel'' for unhesitatingly performing the ritual;
# to send the [[Messiah in Judaism]] speedily in the merit of this ''[[mitzvah]]'';
# to send [[Elijah (prophet)|Elijah]] the prophet, known as &quot;The Righteous Kohen&quot;, so that God's covenant can be fulfilled with the re-establishment of the throne of King [[David]].

==Ritual components==

===Uncovering, ''priah''===
[[File:Britmila2.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Infant after brit]]
At the neonatal stage, the inner preputial [[epithelium]] is still linked with the surface of the [[glans]].&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal
 |url         = http://www.cirp.org/library/general/oster/
 |title       = Further Fate of the Foreskin
 |accessdate  = 2010-11-14
 |last        = Øster
 |first       = Jakob
 |date        = April 1968
 |publisher   = Archives of Disease in Childhood
 |volume      = 43
 |pages       = 200–02
 |url-status     = live
 |archiveurl  = https://web.archive.org/web/20100629054954/http://www.cirp.org/library/general/oster/
 |archivedate = 2010-06-29
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
The ''mitzvah'' is executed only when this epithelium is either removed, or permanently peeled back to uncover the glans.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
  | title = Mishnah Shabbat 19:6
  | quote = circumcised but did not perform priah, it is as if he did not circumcise.
| title-link = Mishnah
}}
The [[Jerusalem Talmud]] there adds: &quot;and is punished [[kareth]]!&quot;
&lt;/ref&gt;
On medical circumcisions performed by surgeons, the epithelium is removed along with the foreskin,&lt;ref&gt;[http://pediatrics.aappublications.org/cgi/reprint/pediatrics;103/3/686.pdf Circumcision Policy Statement] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090320161602/http://pediatrics.aappublications.org/cgi/reprint/pediatrics;103/3/686.pdf |date=2009-03-20 }} of The [[American Academy of Pediatrics]] notes that &quot;there are three methods of circumcision that are commonly used in the newborn male,&quot; and that all three include &quot;bluntly freeing the inner preputial epithelium from the epithelium of the glans,&quot; to be later amputated with the foreskin.&lt;/ref&gt; to prevent post operative penile adhesion and its complications.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal
 |url         = http://www.cirp.org/library/complications/gracely1/
 |title       = Further Fate of the Foreskin
 |accessdate  = 2010-11-14
 |last        = Gracely-Kilgore
 |first       = Katharine A.
 |date        = May 1984
 |publisher   = Nurse Practitioner
 |volume      = 5
 |issue       = 2
 |pages       = 4–22
 |url-status     = live
 |archiveurl  = https://web.archive.org/web/20100628100443/http://www.cirp.org/library/complications/gracely1/
 |archivedate = 2010-06-28
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
However, on ritual circumcisions performed by a mohel, the epithelium is most commonly peeled off only after the foreskin has been amputated. This procedure is called ''priah'' ({{lang-he|פריעה}}), which means: 'uncovering'. The main goal of &quot;priah&quot; (also known as &quot;bris periah&quot;), is to remove as much of the inner layer of the foreskin as possible and prevent the movement of the shaft skin, what creates the look and function of what is known as a &quot;low and tight&quot; circumcision.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | author     = Circlist Editor
  | url     = http://www.circlist.com/styles/page3.html
  | title     = Styles – Judaism and Islam
  | publisher     = Circlist
  | date     = 2014-03-07
  | accessdate     = 2014-06-11
  | url-status     = dead
  | archiveurl     = https://web.archive.org/web/20140515075416/http://www.circlist.com/styles/page3.html
  | archivedate     = 2014-05-15
  }}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Rabbinic interpretation of traditional Jewish sources,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book
  | url     = https://books.google.com/?id=SF6fbjNe0yYC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=when+did+metzitzah+start#v=onepage&amp;q=milah&amp;f=false
  | title   = Marked in Your Flesh: Circumcision from Ancient Judea to Modern America
  | isbn    = 978-0195176742
  | last1 = Glick
  | first1  = Leonard B.
  | date    = 2005-06-30
}}&lt;/ref&gt; the 'priah' has been performed as part of the Jewish circumcision since the [[Israelites]] first inhabited the [[Land of Israel]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Talmud Bavli]] Tractate Yebamoth 71b: Rabbah b. Isaac stated in the name of Rab: The commandment of uncovering the corona at circumcision was not given to Abraham; for it is said, At that time the Lord said unto Joshua: 'Make thee knives of flint etc.' But is it not possible [that this applied to] those who were not previously circumcised; for it is written, For all the people that came out were circumcised, but all the people that were born etc.? — If so, why the expression. 'Again!' Consequently it must apply to the uncovering of the corona.&lt;/ref&gt;
However, the ''Oxford Dictionary of the Jewish Religion'', states that many Hellenistic Jews attempted to restore their foreskins, and that similar action was taken during the Hadrianic persecution, a period in which a prohibition against circumcision was issued. Thus, the writers of the dictionary hypothesize that the more severe method practiced today was probably begun in order to prevent the possibility of restoring the foreskin after circumcision, and therefore the rabbis added the requirement of cutting the foreskin in periah.&lt;ref&gt;Werblowsky, R.J. Zwi &amp; Wigoder, Geoffrey (1997) The Oxford Dictionary of the Jewish Religion. Oxford: Oxford University Press&lt;/ref&gt; The [[frenulum]] may also be cut away at the same time, in a procedure called [[frenectomy]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |url         = http://www.phimosis-circumcision.com/welcome.html
 |title       = Male initiation and the phimosis taboos
 |accessdate  = 2007-10-05
 |last        = Stuart
 |first       = Robin
 |date        = July 2007
 |publisher   = Applied Research on Circumcision
 |url-status     = dead
 |archiveurl  = https://web.archive.org/web/20110721185129/http://www.phimosis-circumcision.com/welcome.html
 |archivedate = 2011-07-21
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
According to Shaye J. D. Cohen, in Why Aren't Jewish Women Circumcised?: Gender and Covenant in Judaism, pg 25, the Torah only commands circumcision (milah.)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book
  | url     = https://books.google.com/?id=PmL-LogqJ-YC&amp;pg=PA283&amp;lpg=PA283&amp;dq=kohler+kaufmann+circumcision#v=snippet&amp;q=milah&amp;f=false
  | title   = Why Aren't Jewish Women Circumcised?: Gender and Covenant in Judaism
  | isbn    = 9780-520212503
  | last1 = Cohen
  | first1  = Shaye J.D
  | date    = 2005-09-06
}}&lt;/ref&gt; David Gollaher has written that the rabbis added the procedure of priah to discourage men from trying to restore their foreskins: ‘Once established, priah was deemed essential to circumcision; if the mohel failed to cut away enough tissue, the operation was deemed insufficient to comply with God's covenant’ and ‘Depending on the strictness of individual rabbis, boys (or men thought to have been inadequately cut) were subjected to additional operations.’&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book
  | title     = Circumcision: A History of The World's Most Controversial Surgery
  | author    = David Gollaher
  | publisher = Basic Books 2000
  | page      = 17
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{clear}}

===''{{transl|he|Metzitzah}}''===
In the Metzitzah ({{lang-he|מְצִיצָה}}), the guard is slid over the foreskin as close to the [[glans]] as possible to allow for maximum removal of the former without any injury to the latter.  A [[scalpel]] is used to detach the foreskin.  A tube is used for ''metzitzah''
In addition to ''{{transl|he|milah}}'' (the actual circumcision) and ''{{transl|he|p'riah}}'', mentioned above, the [[Talmud]] ([[Mishnah]] Shabbat 19:2) mentions a third step, ''{{transl|he|metzitzah}}'', translated as suction, as one of the steps involved in the circumcision rite. The Talmud writes that a &quot;[[Mohel]] (Circumciser) who does not suck creates a danger, and should be dismissed from practice&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Tractate Shabbos 133b&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Rambam – Maimonides in his &quot;book of laws&quot; Laws of Milah Chapter 2, paragraph 2: &quot;...and afterwards he sucks the circumcision until blood comes out from far places, in order not to come to danger, and anyone who does not suck, we remove him from practice.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; [[Rashi]] on that Talmudic passage explains that this step is in order to draw some blood from deep inside the wound to prevent danger to the baby.&lt;ref&gt;Rashi and others on Tractate Shabbos 173a and 173b&lt;/ref&gt;
There are other modern antiseptic and antibiotic techniques—all used as part of the ''brit milah'' today—which many say accomplish the intended purpose of ''metzitzah'', however, since ''metzitzah'' is one of the four steps to fulfill Mitzvah, it continues to be practiced by a minority of Orthodox and Hassidic Jews.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
 |url         = https://www.nytimes.com/2012/09/13/nyregion/regulation-of-circumcision-method-divides-some-jews-in-new-york.html?pagewanted=all&amp;_r=0
 |title       = Denouncing City's Move to Regulate Circumcision
 |accessdate  = 2013-03-01
 |date        = September 12, 2012
 |publisher   = [[www.nytimes.com]]
 |url-status     = live
 |archiveurl  = https://web.archive.org/web/20130127041303/http://www.nytimes.com/2012/09/13/nyregion/regulation-of-circumcision-method-divides-some-jews-in-new-york.html?pagewanted=all&amp;_r=0
 |archivedate = January 27, 2013
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

==== {{anchor|Oral suction}}''{{transl|he|Metzitzah B'Peh}}'' (oral suction) ====
The ancient method of performing ''metzitzah b'peh'' ({{lang-he|מְצִיצָה בְּפֶה}}), or oral suction&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | url         = http://www.thejewishweek.com/news/newscontent.php3?artid=11539
  | archiveurl  = https://web.archive.org/web/20070522001308/http://www.thejewishweek.com/news/newscontent.php3?artid=11539
  | archivedate = 2007-05-22
  | title       = City Risking Babies' Lives With Brit Policy: Health Experts
  | last        = Nussbaum Cohen
  | first       = Debra
  | date        = October 14, 2005
  | publisher   = [[The Jewish Week]]
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | archiveurl  = https://web.archive.org/web/20061120073253/http://www.thejewishweek.com/news/newscontent.php3?artid=11833
  | archivedate = 2006-11-20
  | url         = http://www.thejewishweek.com/news/newscontent.php3?artid=11833&amp;print=yes
  | title       = City Challenged On Ritual Practice
  | accessdate  = 2007-04-19
  | last        = Nussbaum Cohen
  | first       = Debra
  | author2     = Larry Cohler-Esses
  | date        = December 23, 2005
  | publisher   = [[The Jewish Week]]
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;—has become controversial. The process has the ''[[mohel]]'' place his mouth directly on the circumcision wound to draw blood away from the cut. The majority of Jewish circumcision ceremonies do not use metzitzah b'peh,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
 |url         = http://www.jta.org/2014/02/02/news-opinion/united-states/n-y-newborn-contracts-herpes-from-controversial-circumcision-rite
 |title       = N.Y. newborn contracts herpes from controversial circumcision rite
 |publisher   = Jewish Telegraphic Agency
 |date        = February 2, 2014
 |url-status     = live
 |archiveurl  = https://web.archive.org/web/20140219113240/http://www.jta.org/2014/02/02/news-opinion/united-states/n-y-newborn-contracts-herpes-from-controversial-circumcision-rite
 |archivedate = February 19, 2014
}}&lt;/ref&gt; but some Haredi Jews use it.&lt;ref name=haaretz&gt;{{cite news
 |url         = http://www.haaretz.com/opinion/.premium-1.549545
 |title       = Controversial circumcisions
 |author      = Eliyahu Fink and Eliyahu Federman
 |newspaper   = Haaretz
 |date        = Sep 29, 2013
 |url-status     = live
 |archiveurl  = https://web.archive.org/web/20140210090831/http://www.haaretz.com/opinion/.premium-1.549545
 |archivedate = 2014-02-10
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;RCAMetzitzah&quot;&gt;{{cite web
 |url         = http://www.rabbis.org/news/article.cfm?id=100605
 |title       = Metzitza Be'Peh – Halachic Clarification
 |accessdate  = 2007-04-06
 |date        = June 7, 2005
 |publisher   = [[Rabbinical Council of America]]
 |quote       = The poskim consulted by the RCA agree that the normative halacha permits using a glass tube, and that it is proper for mohalim to do so given the health issues involved.
 |url-status     = dead
 |archiveurl  = https://web.archive.org/web/20070415221929/http://www.rabbis.org/news/article.cfm?id=100605
 |archivedate = April 15, 2007
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hartog&quot;&gt;{{cite news
 |first       = Kelly
 |last        = Hartog
 |url         = http://www.jewishjournal.com/home/preview.php?id=13676
 |title       = Death Spotlights Old Circumcision Rite
 |newspaper   = [[The Jewish Journal of Greater Los Angeles]]
 |date        = February 18, 2005
 |accessdate  = 2006-11-22
 |quote       = Metzizah b’peh — loosely translated as oral suction — is the part of the circumcision ceremony where the mohel removes the blood from the baby’s member; these days the removal of the blood is usually done using a sterilized glass tube, instead of with the mouth, as the Talmud suggests.
 |url-status     = live
 |archiveurl  = https://web.archive.org/web/20061213112130/http://www.jewishjournal.com/home/preview.php?id=13676
 |archivedate = December 13, 2006
}}&lt;/ref&gt; It has been documented that the practice poses a serious risk of spreading [[herpes]] to the infant.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gesundheit&quot;&gt;{{cite journal
 |last            = Gesundheit
 |first           = B.
 |date            = August 2004
 |title           = Neonatal Genital Herpes Simplex Virus Type 1 Infection After Jewish Ritual Circumcision: Modern Medicine and Religious Tradition
 |journal         = Pediatrics
 |volume          = 114
 |issue           = 2
 |pages           = e259–63
 |url             = http://pediatrics.aappublications.org/cgi/reprint/114/2/e259.pdf
 |doi             = 10.1542/peds.114.2.e259
 |accessdate      = 2006-06-28
 |pmid            = 15286266
 |issn            = 1098-4275
 |display-authors = etal
 |url-status         = live
 |archiveurl      = https://web.archive.org/web/20060723081226/http://pediatrics.aappublications.org/cgi/reprint/114/2/e259.pdf
 |archivedate     = 2006-07-23
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nydailynews.com/new-york/jewish-baby-contracted-herpes-bris-article-1.2055911|title=Another Jewish baby has contracted herpes through bris|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20151208042913/http://www.nydailynews.com/new-york/jewish-baby-contracted-herpes-bris-article-1.2055911|archivedate=2015-12-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Staff (8 June 2012) [https://news.yahoo.com/extreme-orthodox-jewish-circumcision-illegal-093500919.html Should extreme Orthodox Jewish circumcision be illegal?] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160305082226/http://news.yahoo.com/extreme-orthodox-jewish-circumcision-illegal-093500919.html |date=2016-03-05 }} The Week, Retrieved 30 June 2012&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.usatoday.com/story/news/2015/02/21/nyc-orthodox-jews-in-talks-over-ritual-after-herpes-cases/23798751/|title=NYC, Orthodox Jews in talks over ritual after herpes cases|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160710134721/http://www.usatoday.com/story/news/2015/02/21/nyc-orthodox-jews-in-talks-over-ritual-after-herpes-cases/23798751/|archivedate=2016-07-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; Proponents maintain that there is no conclusive evidence that links herpes to ''Metzitza'',&lt;ref name=&quot;matziv.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.matziv.com/pictures/drbermanarticlemetzitzah |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2012-07-09 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120617162008/http://www.matziv.com/pictures/drbermanarticlemetzitzah |archivedate=2012-06-17 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and that attempts to limit this practice infringe on religious freedom.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |url         = http://collive.com/show_news.rtx?id=22284&amp;hl=metzitza
 |title       = Lawsuit Unites Jewish Groups
 |accessdate  = 2013-01-01
 |date        = Oct 24, 2012
 |publisher   = collive.com
 |url-status     = live
 |archiveurl  = http://archive.wikiwix.com/cache/20130102162036/http://collive.com/show_news.rtx?id=22284&amp;hl=metzitza
 |archivedate = 2013-01-02
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
 |url         = https://www.nytimes.com/2012/06/13/nyregion/new-york-proposes-consent-waiver-for-circumcision-ritual-associated-with-herpes.html?_r=0
 |title       = City Urges Requiring Consent for Jewish Rite
 |accessdate  = 2013-02-01
 |date        = June 12, 2012
 |newspaper   = [[nytimes.com]]
 |url-status     = live
 |archiveurl  = https://web.archive.org/web/20170625012551/http://www.nytimes.com/2012/06/13/nyregion/new-york-proposes-consent-waiver-for-circumcision-ritual-associated-with-herpes.html?_r=0
 |archivedate = June 25, 2017
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
 |title       = Assault on Bris Milah Unites Jewish Communities
 |url         = http://crownheights.info/jewish-news/47779/assault-on-bris-milah-unites-jewish-communities/
 |publisher   = CrownHeights.info
 |date        = October 25, 2012
 |url-status     = live
 |archiveurl  = http://archive.wikiwix.com/cache/20140930002154/http://crownheights.info/jewish-news/47779/assault-on-bris-milah-unites-jewish-communities/
 |archivedate = September 30, 2014
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The practice has become a controversy in both secular and [[Jewish medical ethics]]. The ritual of ''metzitzah'' is found in [[Mishnah]] Shabbat 19:2, which lists it as one of the four steps involved in the circumcision rite. Rabbi [[Moses Sofer]] (1762–1839) observed that the Talmud states that the rationale for this part of the ritual was hygienic — i.e., to protect the health of the child.  The Chasam Sofer issued a leniency (Heter) that some consider to have been conditional to perform ''metzitzah'' with a sponge to be used instead of oral suction in a letter to his student, Rabbi [[Lazar Horowitz]] of Vienna. This letter was never published among Rabbi Sofer's responsa but rather in the secular journal ''Kochvei Yitzchok.''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | url         = http://www.thejewishweek.com/top/editletcontent.php3?artid=4591
  | title       = Editorial &amp; Opinion
  | publisher   = The Jewish Week
  | accessdate  = 2012-04-25
  | url-status     = dead
  | archiveurl  = https://web.archive.org/web/20061120073118/http://www.thejewishweek.com/top/editletcontent.php3?artid=4591| archivedate=November 20, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; along with letters from Dr. Wertheimer, the chief doctor of the Viennese General Hospital. It relates the story that a mohel (who was suspected of transmitting herpes via metzizah to infants) was checked several times and never found to have signs of the disease and that a ban was requested because of the &quot;possibility of future infections&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
  | url   = https://books.google.com/books?id=-vbWAAAAMAAJ&amp;q=divine+law+in+human+hands
  | title = Divine Law in Human Hands
| isbn = 978-9652239808
| last1 = Katz
| first1 = Jacob
| year = 1998
}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Moshe Schick]] (1807–1879), a student of Moses Sofer, states in his book of Responsa, ''She’eilos u’teshuvos Maharam Schick'' (Orach Chaim 152,) that Moses Sofer gave the ruling in that specific instance only because the mohel refused to step down and had secular Government connections that prevented his removal in favor of another mohel and the Heter may not be applied elsewhere. He also states (''Yoreh Deah'' 244) that the practice is possibly a Sinaitic tradition, i.e., [[Halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai]]. Other sources contradict this claim, with copies of Moses Sofer's responsa making no mention of the legal case or of his ruling applying in only one situation. Rather, that responsa makes quite clear that &quot;metzizah&quot; was a health measure and should never be employed where there is a health risk to the infant.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://onthemainline.blogspot.com/2012/04/chasam-sofers-ruling-on-metzitzah-be.html |website=onthemainline.blogspot.com |title=The Chasam Sofer's ruling on Metzitzah Be-peh |date=April 16, 2012 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150402175402/http://onthemainline.blogspot.com/2012/04/chasam-sofers-ruling-on-metzitzah-be.html |archivedate=April 2, 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Chaim Hezekiah Medini]], after corresponding with the greatest Jewish sages of the generation, concluded the practice to be [[Halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai]] and elaborates on what prompted Moses Sofer to give the above ruling.&lt;ref&gt;Sdei Chemed vol. 8 p. 238&lt;/ref&gt; He tells the story that a student of Moses Sofer, [[Lazar Horowitz]], [[Chief Rabbi of Vienna]] at the time and author of the responsa ''Yad Elazer'', needed the ruling because of a governmental attempt to ban circumcision completely if it included ''metztitzah b'peh.'' He therefore asked Sofer to give him permission to do ''brit milah'' without ''metzitzah b’peh.'' When he presented the defense in secular court, his testimony was erroneously recorded to mean that Sofer stated it as a general ruling.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |url        = http://dhengah.org/metzitzah4dummies/metzitzah4dummies.htm
 |archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20070927001229/http://dhengah.org/metzitzah4dummies/metzitzah4dummies.htm
 |url-status   = dead
 |archive-date = 2007-09-27
 |title      = Kuntres Hamiliuim
 |publisher  = Dhengah.org
 |accessdate = 2012-04-25
}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Rabbinical Council of America]], (RCA) which claims to be the largest American organization of Orthodox rabbis, published an article by mohel Dr Yehudi Pesach Shields in its summer 1972 issue of Tradition magazine, calling for the abandonment of Metzitzah b'peh.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |url         = http://traditionarchive.org/news/article.cfm?id=103933
 |title       = The Making of Metzitzah
 |publisher   = Tradition
 |accessdate  = 2014-05-02
 |url-status  = dead
 |archiveurl  = https://web.archive.org/web/20140502221419/http://traditionarchive.org/news/article.cfm?id=103933
 |archivedate = 2014-05-02
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since then the RCA has issued an opinion that advocates methods that do not involve contact between the mohel's mouth and the open wound, such as the use of a sterile syringe, thereby eliminating the risk of infection.&lt;ref name=haaretz/&gt; According to the [[Chief Rabbinate of Israel]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://cbci16.b1.cdn.co.il/imagebank/orig/orig_041F747012AB47F9A57A42BD87D1E8C4.JPG |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2013-04-26 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140222013130/http://cbci16.b1.cdn.co.il/imagebank/orig/orig_041F747012AB47F9A57A42BD87D1E8C4.JPG |archivedate=2014-02-22 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Edah HaChareidis]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://cbci16.b2.cdn.co.il/imagebank/orig/orig_C65A7314BA5E41F0B7EF10BFC75E4195.JPG |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2013-04-26 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140222013129/http://cbci16.b2.cdn.co.il/imagebank/orig/orig_C65A7314BA5E41F0B7EF10BFC75E4195.JPG |archivedate=2014-02-22 }}&lt;/ref&gt; ''metzitzah b'peh'' should still be performed.

The practice of ''metzitzah b'peh'' was alleged to pose a serious risk in the transfer of [[Herpes simplex virus|herpes]] from [[mohel]]im to eight Israeli infants, one of whom suffered brain damage.&lt;ref name = &quot;Gesundheit&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | url         = http://my.webmd.com/content/article/91/101352.htm?lastselectedguid=%7B5FE84E90-BC77-4056-A91C-9531713CA348%7D
  | title       = Rare Circumcision Ritual Carries Herpes Risk
  | publisher   = My.webmd.com
  | accessdate  = 2012-04-25
  | url-status     = dead
  | archiveurl  = https://web.archive.org/web/20050920215004/http://my.webmd.com/content/article/91/101352.htm?lastselectedguid=%7B5FE84E90-BC77-4056-A91C-9531713CA348%7D| archivedate=September 20, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; When three New York City infants contracted herpes after ''metzizah b'peh'' by one ''mohel'' and one of them died, New York authorities took out a restraining order against the ''mohel'' requiring use of a sterile glass tube, or pipette.&lt;ref name = &quot;Hartog&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NewmanNYT&quot;&gt;{{cite news
 |first       = Andy
 |last        = Newman
 |title       = City Questions Circumcision Ritual After Baby Dies
 |url         = https://www.nytimes.com/2005/08/26/nyregion/26circumcise.html?ex=1164344400&amp;en=31f8462c34a55f16&amp;ei=5070
 |newspaper   = The New York Times
 |date        = August 26, 2005
 |accessdate  = 2006-11-23
 |url-status     = live
 |archiveurl  = https://web.archive.org/web/20130515144532/http://www.nytimes.com/2005/08/26/nyregion/26circumcise.html?ex=1164344400&amp;en=31f8462c34a55f16&amp;ei=5070
 |archivedate = May 15, 2013
}}&lt;/ref&gt; The mohel's attorney argued that the New York Department of Health had not supplied conclusive medical evidence linking his client with the disease.&lt;ref name = &quot;NewmanNYT&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Lohud&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  | url       = http://www.lohud.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20060621/NEWS03/606210352/1197/
  | title       = State offers new guidelines on oral-suction circumcision
  | accessdate       = 2006-06-28
  | last       = Clarke
  | first       = Suzan
  | date       = June 21, 2006
  | publisher       = [[The Journal News]]
  | archiveurl       = https://web.archive.org/web/20060706171003/http://www.lohud.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=%2F20060621%2FNEWS03%2F606210352%2F1197%2FRSS01
  | archivedate       = 2006-07-06
  | url-status       = dead
  }}
&lt;/ref&gt; In September 2005, the city withdrew the restraining order and turned the matter over to a rabbinical court.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |url=http://www.thejewishweek.com/news/newscontent.php3?artid=11412
 |title=City: Brit Case To Bet Din
 |accessdate=2006-11-23
 |last=Nussbaum Cohen
 |first=Debra
 |date=September 23, 2005
 |publisher=[[The Jewish Week]]
 |url-status=dead
 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20061120073353/http://www.thejewishweek.com/news/newscontent.php3?artid=11412
 |archivedate=2006-11-20
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; Dr. Thomas Frieden, the Health Commissioner of New York City, wrote, &quot;There exists no reasonable doubt that ‘metzitzah b'peh’ can and has caused neonatal herpes infection....The Health Department recommends that infants being circumcised not undergo metzitzah b'peh.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
 |first       = Debra
 |last        = Nussbaum Cohen
 |title       = Controversy rages in New York over circumcision practice
 |url         = http://www.jewishledger.com/articles/2006/02/23/news/news02.txt
 |publisher   = The Jewish Ledger
 |date        = February 23, 2006
 |accessdate  = 2006-11-23
 |url-status     = dead
 |archiveurl  = https://web.archive.org/web/20060429154742/http://www.jewishledger.com/articles/2006/02/23/news/news02.txt
 |archivedate = April 29, 2006
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; In May 2006, the Department of Health for New York State issued a protocol for the performance of metzitzah b'peh.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.health.state.ny.us/diseases/communicable/herpes/newborns/circumcision_protocol.htm |title=Circumcision Protocol Regarding the Prevention of Neonatal Herpes Transmission |accessdate=2006-11-23 |date=November 2006 |publisher=Department of Health, New York State |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070205033348/http://www.health.state.ny.us/diseases/communicable/herpes/newborns/circumcision_protocol.htm |archivedate=February 5, 2007 |quote= &quot;The person performing metzizah b'peh must do the following: Wipe around the outside of the mouth thoroughly, including the labial folds at the corners, with a sterile alcohol wipe, and then discard in a safe place. Wash hands with soap and hot water for 2-6 minutes. Within 5 minutes before metzizah b'peh, rinse mouth thoroughly with a mouthwash containing greater than 25% alcohol (for example, Listerine) and hold the rinse in mouth for 30 seconds or more before discarding it.&quot; }}
&lt;/ref&gt; Dr. [[Antonia Novello|Antonia C. Novello]], Commissioner of Health for New York State, together with a board of rabbis and doctors, worked, she said,  to &quot;allow the practice of metzizah b'peh to continue while still meeting the Department of Health's responsibility to protect the public health.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.health.state.ny.us/diseases/communicable/herpes/newborns/2006-05-08_letter_to_rabbis.htm |title=Dear Rabbi Letter |accessdate=2006-11-23 |last=Novello |first=Antonia C. |date=May 8, 2006 |publisher=Department of Health, New York State |quote=The meetings have been extremely helpful to me in understanding the importance of metzizah b'peh to the continuity of Jewish ritual practice, how the procedure is performed, and how we might allow the practice of metzizah b'peh to continue while still meeting the Department of Health's responsibility to protect the public health. I want to reiterate that the welfare of the children of your community is our common goal and that it is not our intent to prohibit metzizah b'peh after circumcision, rather our intent is to suggest measures that would reduce the risk of harm, if there is any, for future circumcisions where metzizah b'peh is the customary procedure and the possibility of an infected mohel may not be ruled out. I know that successful solutions can and will be based on our mutual trust and cooperation. |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070218224659/http://www.health.state.ny.us/diseases/communicable/herpes/newborns/2006-05-08_letter_to_rabbis.htm |archivedate=February 18, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Later in New York City in 2012 a 2-week-old baby died of herpes because of metzitzah b'peh.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://abcnews.go.com/Health/baby-dies-herpes-virus-ritual-circumcision-nyc-orthodox/story?id=15888618 |title=Baby Dies of Herpes in Ritual Circumcision By Orthodox Jews |author=Susan Donaldson James |date=March 12, 2012 |website=abcnews.go.com |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170419065328/http://abcnews.go.com/Health/baby-dies-herpes-virus-ritual-circumcision-nyc-orthodox/story?id=15888618 |archivedate=April 19, 2017 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In three medical papers done in Israel, Canada, and the US, oral suction following circumcision was suggested as a cause in 11 cases of neonatal herpes.&lt;ref name = &quot;Gesundheit&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Rubin LG, Lanzkowsky P. Cutaneous neonatal herpes simplex infection associated with ritual circumcision. Pediatric Infectious Diseases Journal. 2000. 19(3) 266–67.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Distel R, Hofer V, Bogger-Goren S, Shalit I, Garty BZ. Primary genital herpes simplex infection associated with Jewish ritual circumcision. Israel Medical Association Journal. [http://www.ima.org.il/imaj/ar03dec-14.pdf 2003 Dec;5(12):893-4] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121021093342/http://www.ima.org.il/imaj/ar03dec-14.pdf |date=October 21, 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Researchers noted that prior to 1997, neonatal herpes reports in Israel were rare, and that the late incidences were correlated with the mothers carrying the virus themselves.&lt;ref name = &quot;Gesundheit&quot; /&gt; Rabbi Doctor [[Mordechai Halperin]] implicates the &quot;better hygiene and living conditions that prevail among the younger generation&quot;, which lowered to 60% the rate of young Israeli Chareidi mothers who carry the virus. He explains that an &quot;absence of antibodies in the mothers’ blood means that their newborn sons received no such antibodies through the placenta, and therefore are vulnerable to infection by HSV-1.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Halperin&quot;&gt;{{cite journal 
| first = Mordechai
| last = Halperin
| authorlink = Mordechai Halperin
| translator-first = Yocheved
| translator-last = Lavon
| title = Metzitzah B'peh Controversy: The View from Israel
| url = http://www.ou.org/jewish_action/article/8987
| journal = [[Jewish Action]]
| volume = 67
| issue = 2
| pages = 25, 33–39
| date = Winter 2006
| accessdate = February 15, 2007
| archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20120306221308/http://www.ou.org/jewish_action/article/8987
| archivedate = March 6, 2012
| quote = The mohel brings the baby’s organ into his mouth immediately after the excision of the foreskin and sucks blood from it vigorously. This action lowers the internal pressure in the tissues of the organ, in the blood vessels of the head of the organ and in the exposed ends of the arterioles that have just been cut. Thus, the difference between the pressure in the blood vessels in the base of the organ and the pressure in the blood vessels at its tip is increased. This requirement has deep religious significance as well as medical benefits....Immediately after incising or injuring an artery, the arterial walls contract and obstruct, or at least reduce, the flow of blood. Since the arterioles of the orlah, or the foreskin, branch off from the dorsal arteries (the arteries of the upper side of the organ), cutting away the foreskin can result in a temporary obstruction in these dorsal arteries. This temporary obstruction, caused by arterial muscle contraction, continues to develop into a more enduring blockage as the stationary blood begins to clot. The tragic result can be severe hypoxia (deprivation of the supply of blood and oxygen) of the glans penis.28 If the arterial obstruction becomes more permanent, gangrene follows; the baby may lose his glans, and it may even become a life-threatening situation. Such cases have been known to occur. Only by immediately clearing the blockage can one prevent such clotting from happening. Performing metzitzah immediately after circumcision lowers the internal pressure within the tissues and blood vessels of the glans, thus raising the pressure gradient between the blood vessels at the base of the organ and the blood vessels at its distal end—the glans as well as the excised arterioles of the foreskin, which branch off of the dorsal arteries. This increase in pressure gradient (by a factor of four to six!) can resolve an acute temporary blockage and restore blood flow to the glans, thus significantly reducing both the danger of immediate, acute hypoxia and the danger of developing a permanent obstruction by means of coagulation. How do we know when a temporary blockage has successfully been averted? When the “blood in the further reaches [i.e., the proximal dorsal artery] is extracted,” as Rambam has stated.}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

====Barriers====
Because of the risk of infection, some rabbinical authorities have ruled that the traditional practice of direct contact should be replaced by using a sterile tube between the wound and the [[mohel]]'s mouth, so there is no direct oral contact. The [[Rabbinical Council of America]], the largest group of [[Modern Orthodox]] rabbis, endorses this method.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |url         = http://www.rabbis.org/news/article.cfm?id=100605
 |title       = Metzitza Be'Peh – Halachic Clarification Regarding Metzitza Be'Peh, RCA Clarifies Halachic Background to Statement of March 1, 2005
 |publisher   = Rabbis.org
 |accessdate  = 2012-04-25
 |url-status     = dead
 |archiveurl  = https://web.archive.org/web/20120117161842/http://www.rabbis.org/news/article.cfm?id=100605
 |archivedate = January 17, 2012
}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The RCA paper states: ''&quot;Rabbi Schachter even reports that Rav Yosef Dov Soloveitchik reports that his father, Rav Moshe Soloveitchik, would not permit a mohel to perform metzitza be’peh with direct oral contact, and that his grandfather, Rav Chaim Soloveitchik, instructed mohelim in Brisk not to do metzitza be’peh with direct oral contact. However, although Rav Yosef Dov Soloveitchik also generally prohibited metzitza be’peh with direct oral contact, he did not ban it by those who insisted upon it,...&quot;. '' The sefer Mitzvas Hametzitzah&lt;ref&gt;The book was originally published in German, ''Die Ausübung der Mezizo'', Frankfurt a.M. 1906; It was subsequently translated into Hebrew, reprinted in Jerusalem in 1966 under the title &quot;''Mitzvas Hametzitzah''&quot; and appended to the back of Dvar Sinai, a book written by the author's grandson, Sinai Adler.&lt;/ref&gt; by Rabbi Sinai Schiffer of Baden, Germany, states that he is in possession of letters from 36 major Russian (Lithuanian) rabbis that categorically prohibit Metzitzah with a sponge and require it to be done orally. Among them is Rabbi Chaim Halevi Soloveitchik of Brisk.

In September 2012, the [[New York Department of Health]] unanimously ruled that the practice of metztizah b'peh should require informed consent from the parent or guardian of the child undergoing the ritual.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vosizneias.com/113562/2012/09/13/new-york-ny-city-approves-metzitzah-bpeh-consent-form/ New York City Approves Metzitzah B’Peh Consent Form (full video NYC DOH debate)] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20151231212114/http://www.vosizneias.com/113562/2012/09/13/new-york-ny-city-approves-metzitzah-bpeh-consent-form/ |date=2015-12-31 }}, Vosizneias.com, Published September 13, 2012&lt;/ref&gt; Prior to the ruling, several hundred rabbis, including Rabbi David Neiderman, the executive director of the United Jewish Organization of Williamsburg, signed a declaration stating that they would not inform parents of the potential dangers that came with metzitzah b'peh, even if informed consent became law.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vosizneias.com/112847/2012/09/02/new-york-rabbis-say-theyll-defy-state-law-on-metzitzah-bpeh New York – Rabbis Say They’ll Defy Law On Metzitzah B’peh] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160306062427/http://www.vosizneias.com/112847/2012/09/02/new-york-rabbis-say-theyll-defy-state-law-on-metzitzah-bpeh/ |date=2016-03-06 }}, Vosizneias.com, Published September 2, 2012&lt;/ref&gt;

In a motion for preliminary injunction with intent to sue, filed against New York City Department of Health &amp; Mental Hygiene, affidavits by [[Awi Federgruen]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://protectmilah.org/wp-content/uploads/2012/11/MBP-Federgruen-Affidavit.pdf |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2013-04-17 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130515030405/http://protectmilah.org/wp-content/uploads/2012/11/MBP-Federgruen-Affidavit.pdf |archivedate=2013-05-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.courtlistener.com/docket/4351278/central-rabbinical-congress-of-the-usa-canada-v-new-york-city-department/#entry-18|title=Docket for Central Rabbinical Congress of the USA &amp; Canada v. New York City Department of Health &amp; Mental..., 1:12-cv-07590 |website=CourtListener|accessdate=8 May 2018|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20180508014112/https://www.courtlistener.com/docket/4351278/central-rabbinical-congress-of-the-usa-canada-v-new-york-city-department/#entry-18|archivedate=8 May 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; Brenda Breuer,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://protectmilah.org/wp-content/uploads/2012/11/MBP-Breuer-Affidavit2.pdf |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2013-04-17 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130515000708/http://protectmilah.org/wp-content/uploads/2012/11/MBP-Breuer-Affidavit2.pdf |archivedate=2013-05-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.courtlistener.com/docket/4351278/central-rabbinical-congress-of-the-usa-canada-v-new-york-city-department/#entry-19|title=Docket for Central Rabbinical Congress of the USA &amp; Canada v. New York City Department of Health &amp; Mental..., 1:12-cv-07590 |website=CourtListener|accessdate=8 May 2018|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20180508014112/https://www.courtlistener.com/docket/4351278/central-rabbinical-congress-of-the-usa-canada-v-new-york-city-department/#entry-19|archivedate=8 May 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Daniel S. Berman,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://protectmilah.org/wp-content/uploads/2012/11/MBP-Berman-Affidavit.pdf |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2013-04-17 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130515015938/http://protectmilah.org/wp-content/uploads/2012/11/MBP-Berman-Affidavit.pdf |archivedate=2013-05-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.courtlistener.com/docket/4351278/central-rabbinical-congress-of-the-usa-canada-v-new-york-city-department/#entry-13|title=Docket for Central Rabbinical Congress of the USA &amp; Canada v. New York City Department of Health &amp; Mental..., 1:12-cv-07590 |website=CourtListener|accessdate=8 May 2018|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20180508014112/https://www.courtlistener.com/docket/4351278/central-rabbinical-congress-of-the-usa-canada-v-new-york-city-department/#entry-13|archivedate=8 May 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; argued that the study on which the department passed its conclusions is flawed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://forward.com/opinion/letters/194118/no-conclusive-evidence-on-circumcision-rite-and-he/|title=No Conclusive Evidence on Circumcision Rite and Herpes|website=forward.com|accessdate=8 May 2018|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20151020085846/http://forward.com/opinion/letters/194118/no-conclusive-evidence-on-circumcision-rite-and-he/|archivedate=20 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://yated.com/bris-milah-lawsuit-court-to-rule-on-temporary-injuction-against-anti-mbp-law/|title=Bris Milah Lawsuit: Court To Rule On Temporary Injuction Against Anti-MBP Law |first=Debbie|last=Maimon|date=26 December 2012|website=yated.com|accessdate=8 May 2018|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20180508014112/https://yated.com/bris-milah-lawsuit-court-to-rule-on-temporary-injuction-against-anti-mbp-law/|archivedate=8 May 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://hamodia.com/2013/01/10/judge-rejects-injunction-in-landmark-milah-suit/|title=Judge Rejects Injunction in Landmark Milah Suit |publisher= Jewish News – Israel News – Israel Politics|date=10 January 2013|website=hamodia.com|accessdate=8 May 2018|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20171026020216/http://hamodia.com/2013/01/10/judge-rejects-injunction-in-landmark-milah-suit/|archivedate=26 October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jewishpress.com/indepth/opinions/consent-forms-for-metzitzah-bpeh-empowering-parents-or-interfering-in-religious-practice/2013/10/25/2/|title=Consent Forms For ''Metzitzah B'Peh'' – Empowering Parents Or Interfering In Religious Practice?|first=Dr. Daniel Berman and Prof. Brenda Breuer and Prof. Awi|last=Federgruen|website=jewishpress.com|accessdate=8 May 2018|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20171122005218/http://www.jewishpress.com/indepth/opinions/consent-forms-for-metzitzah-bpeh-empowering-parents-or-interfering-in-religious-practice/2013/10/25/2/|archivedate=22 November 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The &quot;informed consent&quot; regulation was challenged in court. In January 2013 the U.S. District court ruled that the law did not specifically target religion and therefore must not pass [[strict scrutiny]]. The ruling was appealed to the Court of Appeals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.becketlaw.org/case/central-rabbinical-congress-v-new-york-city-department-health-mental-hygiene/|title=Central Rabbinical Congress v. New York City Department of Health &amp; Mental Hygiene |website=becketlaw.org|accessdate=8 May 2018|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20180318183002/https://www.becketlaw.org/case/central-rabbinical-congress-v-new-york-city-department-health-mental-hygiene/|archivedate=18 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On August 15, 2014 the Second Circuit Court of Appeals reversed the decision by the lower court, and ruled that the regulation does have to be reviewed under [[strict scrutiny]] to determine whether it infringes on Orthodox Jews' freedom of religion.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.reuters.com/article/2014/08/15/us-usa-newyork-circumcision-idUSKBN0GF1LZ20140815 |title=U.S. Court revives challenge to New York City circumcision law |accessdate=2017-06-30 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150930150149/http://www.reuters.com/article/2014/08/15/us-usa-newyork-circumcision-idUSKBN0GF1LZ20140815 |archivedate=2015-09-30 |newspaper=Reuters |date=2014-08-15 }}
&lt;/ref&gt;

On September 9, 2015 after coming to an agreement with the community The New York City Board of Health voted to repeal the informed consent regulation.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2015/09/10/nyregion/new-york-city-health-board-repeals-rule-on-consent-forms-for-circumcision-ritual.html|title=New York City Health Board Repeals Rule on Consent Forms for Circumcision Ritual|first=Michael M.|last=Grynbaum|date=9 September 2015|via=NYTimes.com|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170716195928/https://www.nytimes.com/2015/09/10/nyregion/new-york-city-health-board-repeals-rule-on-consent-forms-for-circumcision-ritual.html|archivedate=16 July 2017|newspaper=The New York Times}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Hatafat dam brit===
A brit milah is more than circumcision, it is a sacred ritual in Judaism, as distinguished from its non-ritual requirement in [[Islam]]. One ramification is that the brit is not considered complete unless a drop of blood is actually drawn. The standard medical methods of [[circumcision]] through constriction do not meet the requirements of the [[halakhah]] for brit milah, because they cause [[hemostasis]], ''i.e.'', they stop the flow of blood. Moreover, circumcision alone, in the absence of the brit milah ceremony, does not fulfill the requirements of the mitzvah. Therefore, in cases where a Jew who was circumcised outside of a brit milah, an already-circumcised convert, or an [[Aposthia|aposthetic]] (born without a foreskin) individual, the mohel draws a symbolic drop of blood ({{lang-he|הטפת דם}}, {{transl|he|''hatafat-dam''}}) from the penis at the point where the foreskin would have been or was attached.&lt;ref&gt;[[Shulchan Aruch]], [[Yoreh De'ah]], 263:4&lt;/ref&gt;

==''Milah l'shem giur''==
[[File:Göttingen-Beschneidungswerkzeuge.02.JPG|thumb|right|Set of brit milah implements, [[Göttingen]] city museum]]
A ''Milah L'shem giur'' is a &quot;Circumcision for the purpose of conversion&quot;. In [[Orthodox Judaism]], this procedure is usually done by adoptive parents for adopted boys who are being converted as part of the adoption or by families with young children converting together. It is also required for adult converts who were not previously circumcised, e.g. those born in countries where circumcision at birth is not common. The conversion of a minor is valid in both [[Orthodox Judaism|Orthodox]] and [[Conservative Judaism]] until a child reaches the age of majority (13 for a boy, 12 for a girl); at that time the child has the option of renouncing his conversion and Judaism, and the conversion will then be considered retroactively invalid. He must be informed of his right to renounce his conversion if he wishes. If he does not make such a statement, it is accepted that the boy is halakhically Jewish. [[Orthodox Judaism|Orthodox]] rabbis will generally not convert a non-Jewish child raised by a mother who has not converted to Judaism.&lt;ref&gt;Rabbi Paysach J. Krohn, ''Bris Milah'' [[Artscroll|Mesorah Publications Ltd]], 1985, pp.103-105&lt;/ref&gt;

The laws of conversion and conversion-related circumcision in [[Orthodox Judaism]] have numerous complications, and authorities recommend that a rabbi be consulted well in advance.

In [[Conservative Judaism]], the Milah l'Shem giur procedure is also performed for a boy whose mother has not converted, but with the intention that the child be raised Jewish.  This conversion of a child to Judaism without the conversion of the mother is allowed by [[Conservative Judaism|Conservative]] interpretations of [[halakha]]. Conservative Rabbis will authorize it only under the condition that the child be raised as a Jew in a single-faith household. Should the mother convert, and if the boy has not yet reached his third birthday, the child may be immersed in the [[mikveh]] with the mother, after the mother has already immersed, to become Jewish.  If the mother does not convert, the child may be immersed in a mikveh, or body of natural waters, to complete the child's conversion to Judaism. This can be done before the child is even one year old. If the child did not immerse in the [[mikveh]], or the boy was too old, then the child may choose of their own accord to become Jewish at age 13 as a [[Bar Mitzvah]], and complete the conversion then.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rabbinicalassembly.org/teshuvot/docs/19861990/reisner_conversion.pdf Rabbi Avram Israel Reisner, On the conversion of adoptive and patrilineal children] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20101127135422/http://www.rabbinicalassembly.org/teshuvot/docs/19861990/reisner_conversion.pdf |date=2010-11-27 }}, Rabbinical Assembly [[Committee on Jewish Law and Standards]], 1988&lt;/ref&gt;
* The ceremony, when performed l'Shem giur, does not have to be performed on a particular day, and does not override [[Shabbat]] and [[Jewish Holidays]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |url         = http://www.askmoses.com/en/article/212,657813/Can-a-brit-take-place-on-Yom-Kippur.html
 |title       = Can a brit take place on Yom Kippur? – holidays general information holiday information life cycle circumcision the brit
 |publisher   = Askmoses.com
 |accessdate  = 2012-04-25
 |url-status     = live
 |archiveurl  = https://web.archive.org/web/20120221222357/http://www.askmoses.com/en/article/212,657813/Can-a-brit-take-place-on-Yom-Kippur.html
 |archivedate = 2012-02-21
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |url         = http://www.ahavat-israel.com/torat/britmila.php
 |title       = The Mitzvah of Brit Milah (Bris)
 |publisher   = Ahavat Israel
 |accessdate  = 2012-04-25
 |url-status     = live
 |archiveurl  = https://web.archive.org/web/20120204162505/http://www.ahavat-israel.com/torat/britmila.php
 |archivedate = 2012-02-04
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In Orthodox Judaism, there is a split of authorities on whether the child receives a [[Hebrew name]] at the Brit ceremony or upon immersion in the [[Mikvah]]. According to ''Zichron Brit LeRishonim'', naming occurs at the Brit with a different formula than the standard Brit Milah. The more common practice among [[Ashkenazic]] Jews follows Rabbi [[Moshe Feinstein]], with naming occurring at immersion.

Where the procedure was performed but not followed by immersion or other requirements of the conversion procedure (e.g., in [[Conservative Judaism]], where the mother has not converted), if the boy chooses to complete the conversion at [[Bar Mitzvah]], a ''Milah l'shem giur'' performed when the boy was an infant removes the obligation to undergo either a full brit milah or ''hatafat dam brit''.

==Reasons for circumcision==
In ''Of the Special Laws, Book 1'', the Jewish philosopher [[Philo]] (20 BCE – CE 50) gives six reasons for the practice of circumcision.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book
  | author1    = Philo of Alexandria
  | last2      = Colson
  | first2     = F.H. (trans.)
  | title      = Of the special laws, Book I (i and ii), in Works of Philo
  | publisher  = Harvard University Press
  | location   = Loeb Classical Library
  | year       = 1937
  | pages      = 103–05
  | volume     = Vol. VII
  | isbn       = 978-0674992504
  | postscript = &lt;!--None--&gt;
| author1-link = Philo of Alexandria
 }}
&lt;/ref&gt;  He attributes four of the reasons to &quot;men of divine spirit and wisdom.&quot;  These include the idea that circumcision:
# Protects against disease,
# Secures cleanliness &quot;in a way that is suited to the people consecrated to God,&quot;
# Causes the circumcised portion of the penis to resemble a heart, thereby representing a physical connection between the &quot;breath contained within the heart [that] is generative of thoughts, and the generative organ itself [that] is productive of living beings,&quot; and
# Promotes prolificness by removing impediments to the flow of semen.

To these, Philo added two of his own reasons, including the idea that circumcision
# &lt;li value=&quot;5&quot;&gt;&quot;Signified figuratively the excision of all superfluous and excessive pleasure,&quot; and&lt;/li&gt;
# &quot;Is a symbol of a man's knowing himself.&quot;

[[Saadia Gaon|Rabbi Saadia Gaon]] considers something to be &quot;complete,&quot; if it lacks nothing, but also has nothing that is unneeded. He regards the foreskin an unneeded organ that God created in man, and so by amputating it, the man is completed.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book
  | first1     = Saadia
  | last1      = Gaon
  | authorlink = Saadia Gaon
  | last2      = Rosenblatt
  | first2     = Samuel (trans.)
  | title      = the Book of Beliefs and Opinions
  | publisher  = Yale Judaica
  | year       = 1958
  | chapter    = article III chapter 10
  | isbn       = 978-0300044904
  | postscript = &lt;!--None--&gt;
| title-link      = Emunoth ve-Deoth
  }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Maimonides]] (Moses ben Maimon &quot;Rambam&quot;, CE 1135–1204), who apart from being a great Torah scholar was also a physician and philosopher, argued that circumcision serves as a common bodily sign to members of the same faith. He also asserted that the main purpose of the act is to repress sexual pleasure, with the strongest reason being that it is difficult for a woman to separate from an uncircumcised man with whom she has had sex:&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal
 |first       = Moses
 |last        = Maimonides
 |last2       = Pines
 |first2      = Schlomo (trans.)
 |title       = Guide to the Perplexed. Part III. Chapter XLIX
 |publisher   = The University of Chicago Press
 |year        = 1963
 |url         = http://www.sacred-texts.com/jud/gfp/gfp185.htm
 |url-status     = live
 |archiveurl  = https://web.archive.org/web/20070929155622/http://www.sacred-texts.com/jud/gfp/gfp185.htm
 |archivedate = 2007-09-29
}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{quote|It has been thought that circumcision perfects what is defective congenitally. This gave the possibility to everyone to raise an objection and to say: How can natural things be defective so that they need to be perfected from outside, all the more because we know how useful the foreskin is for that member? In fact this commandment has not been prescribed with a view to perfecting what is defective congenitally, but to perfecting what is defective morally. The bodily pain caused to that member is the real purpose of circumcision. None of the activities necessary for the preservation of the individual is harmed thereby, nor is procreation rendered impossible, but violent concupiscence and lust that goes beyond what is needed are diminished. The fact that circumcision weakens the faculty of sexual excitement and sometimes perhaps diminishes the pleasure is indubitable. For if at birth this member has been made to bleed and has had its covering taken away from it, it must indubitably be weakened. The Sages, may their memory be blessed, have explicitly stated: It is hard for a woman with whom an uncircumcised man has had sexual intercourse to separate from him. In my opinion this is the strongest of the reasons for circumcision.
| author = [[Maimonides]]
| source = [[The Guide to the Perplexed|''The Guide to the Perplexed'' (1190)]]
}}

The author of [[Sefer ha-Chinuch]]&lt;ref&gt;2nd commandment&lt;/ref&gt; provides three reasons for the practice of circumcision:
# To complete the form of man, by removing what he claims to be a redundant organ;
# To mark the chosen people, so that their bodies will be different as their souls are. The organ chosen for the mark is the one responsible for the sustenance of the species.
# The completion effected by circumcision is not congenital, but left to the man. This implies that as he completes the form of his body, so can he complete the form of his soul.

Talmud professor [[Daniel Boyarin]] offered two explanations for circumcision. One is that it is a literal inscription on the Jewish body of the name of God in the form of the letter &quot;[[yodh|yud]]&quot; (from &quot;yesod&quot;). The second is that the act of bleeding represents a feminization of Jewish men, significant in the sense that the covenant represents a marriage between Jews and (a symbolically male) God.&lt;ref&gt;Boyarin, Daniel. {{&quot;'}}This We Know to Be the Carnal Israel': Circumcision and the Erotic Life of God and Israel&quot;, Critical Inquiry. (Spring, 1992), 474-506.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Reform Judaism==
The Reform societies established in Frankfurt and Berlin regarded circumcision as barbaric and wished to abolish it. However, while prominent rabbis such as [[Abraham Geiger]] believed the ritual to be barbaric and outdated, they refrained from instituting any change in this matter. In 1843, when a father in Frankfurt refused to circumcise his son, rabbis of all shades in Germany stated it was mandated by Jewish law; even [[Samuel Holdheim]] affirmed this.&lt;ref name=&quot;A&quot;&gt;Judith Bleich, &quot;The Circumcision Controversy in Classical Reform in Historical Context&quot;, KTAV Publishing House, 2007. pp. 1–28.&lt;/ref&gt; By 1871, Reform rabbinic leadership in Germany reasserted &quot;the supreme importance of circumcision in Judaism&quot;, while affirming the traditional viewpoint that non-circumcised are Jews nonetheless. Although the issue of circumcision of converts continues to be debated, the necessity of Brit Milah for Jewish infant boys has been stressed in every subsequent Reform rabbis manual or guide.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |url         = http://data.ccarnet.org/cgi-bin/respdisp.pl?file=54&amp;year=arr
 |title       = Circumcision of Infants
 |accessdate  = 2010-09-12
 |year        = 1982
 |publisher   = Central Conference of American Rabbis
 |url-status     = dead
 |archiveurl  = https://web.archive.org/web/20120315231116/http://data.ccarnet.org/cgi-bin/respdisp.pl?file=54&amp;year=arr
 |archivedate = 2012-03-15
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; Since 1984 [[Reform Judaism]] has trained and certified over 300 of their own practicing ''[[mohel|mohalim]]'' in this ritual.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
 |url        = https://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E6DC1639F93BA15755C0A9679C8B63
 |archive-url = https://archive.today/20130130104343/http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E6DC1639F93BA15755C0A9679C8B63
 |url-status   = dead
 |archive-date = January 30, 2013
 |title      = Reform Rabbis' Vote Reflects Expanding Interest in Rituals
 |accessdate = 2007-10-03
 |last       = Niebuhr
 |first      = Gustav
 |date       = June 28, 2001
 |newspaper  = The New York Times
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |url         = http://beritmila.org/
 |title       = Berit Mila Program of Reform Judaism
 |accessdate  = 2010-01-23
 |year        = 2010
 |publisher   = National Association of American Mohalim
 |url-status     = live
 |archiveurl  = https://web.archive.org/web/20131007073323/http://beritmila.org/
 |archivedate = 2013-10-07
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

==The anti-circumcision movement and ''Brit Shalom''==
{{main|Circumcision controversies|Brit shalom (naming ceremony)|Religious male circumcision#Criticism and opposition to circumcision|Violence against men}}

A growing number&lt;ref name=&quot;chernikoff&quot;&gt;{{Cite news
 |url         = https://www.reuters.com/article/domesticNews/idUSN22970720071003?pageNumber=1
 |title       = Jewish &quot;intactivists&quot; in U.S. stop circumcising
 |accessdate  = 2019-04-03
 |last        = Chernikoff
 |first       = Helen
 |date        = October 3, 2007
 |newspaper   = [[Reuters]]
 |url-status     = live
 |archiveurl  = https://web.archive.org/web/20081227025338/http://www.reuters.com/article/domesticNews/idUSN22970720071003?pageNumber=1
 |archivedate = December 27, 2008
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Schonfeld&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.circinfo.org/Jews_against_circumcision.html|title=Jewish voices against circumcision getting stronger|accessdate=2018-11-04|last=Schonfeld|first=Victor|date=2014|website=Circinfo.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;kasher&quot;&gt;{{cite news
 |last        = Kasher
 |first       = Rani
 |title       = It's 2017. Time to Talk About Circumcision
 |newspaper   = [[Haaretz]]
 |location    = [[Tel Aviv]]
 |language    = English
 |date        = 23 August 2017
 |url         = http://www.haaretz.com/opinion/.premium-1.808557
 |access-date = 4 September 2017
 |url-status     = live
 |archiveurl  = https://web.archive.org/web/20170904032317/http://www.haaretz.com/opinion/.premium-1.808557
 |archivedate = 4 September 2017
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Jewish News&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Oryszczuk |first=Stephen |date=28 February 2018 |title=The Jewish parents cutting out the bris |url=https://jewishnews.timesofisrael.com/the-jewish-parents-cutting-out-the-bris/ |work=[[The Times of Israel]] |location=[[Jerusalem]] |access-date=4 August 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; of contemporary Jews and [[Intactivist]] Jewish groups in the [[United States]], [[United Kingdom]], and [[Israel]], both religious and secular, choose not to circumcise their sons.&lt;ref name=&quot;chernikoff&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Schonfeld&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;kasher&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Jewish News&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Goldman 1997&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://jewishcircumcision.org/spectator.htm|title=Circumcision: A Source of Jewish Pain|access-date=26 December 2019|last=Goldman|first=Ronald|date=1997|website=Jewish Circumcision Resource Center|publisher=Jewish Spectator}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kimmel&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Kimmel|first=Michael S.|author-link=Michael Kimmel|title=The Kindest Un-Cut: Feminism, Judaism, and My Son's Foreskin|journal=[[Tikkun (magazine)|Tikkun]]|volume=16|issue=3|pages=43–48|date=May–June 2001|access-date=26 December 2019|url=http://www.cirp.org/pages/cultural/kimmel1/}}&lt;/ref&gt; Among the reasons for their choice are the claims that circumcision is a form of [[child abuse]] that involves [[genital mutilation]] [[Forced circumcision|forced on men]] and [[violence]] against helpless infants,&lt;ref name=&quot;Goldman 1997&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kimmel&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Goodman 1999&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.cirp.org/library/cultural/goodman1999/|title=Jewish circumcision: an alternative perspective|last=Goodman|first=Jason|date=January 1999|journal=[[BJU International]]|volume=83|issue=1: Supplement|pages=22–27|doi=10.1046/j.1464-410x.1999.0830s1022.x|pmid=10349411|access-date=26 December 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; a violation of [[children's rights]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Goldman 1997&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kimmel&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Schonfeld&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Goodman 1999&quot; /&gt; and their opinion that circumcision is a dangerous,&lt;ref name=&quot;Goldman 1997&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Goodman 1999&quot; /&gt; unnecessary,&lt;ref name=&quot;Goldman 1997&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kimmel&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Goodman 1999&quot; /&gt; painful,&lt;ref name=&quot;Goldman 1997&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kimmel&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Goodman 1999&quot; /&gt; [[Psychological trauma|traumatic]] and [[Psychological stress|stressful]] event for the child,&lt;ref name=&quot;Goldman 1997&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kimmel&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Goodman 1999&quot; /&gt; which can cause even further psychophysical complications down the road, including serious [[disability]] and even death.&lt;ref name=&quot;Goodman 1999&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Boyle |first1=Gregory J. |last2=Svoboda |first2=J. Steven |last3=Price |first3=Christopher P. |last4=Turner |first4=J. Neville |date=2000 |title=Circumcision of Healthy Boys: Criminal Assault? |url=http://www.cirp.org/library/legal/boyle1/ |journal=Journal of Law and Medicine |volume=7 |issue= |pages=301–310 |doi= |access-date=22 November 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; They are assisted by a small number of [[Reform Judaism|Reform]], [[Liberal Judaism (United Kingdom)|Liberal]], and [[Reconstructionist Judaism|Reconstructionist]] rabbis, and have developed a welcoming ceremony that they call the ''[[Brit shalom (naming ceremony)|Brit shalom]]'' (&quot;Covenant [of] Peace&quot;) for such children,&lt;ref name=&quot;Kimmel&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Schonfeld&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Jewish News&quot; /&gt; also accepted by [[Humanistic Judaism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | url      = http://www.circumstitions.com/Jewish-shalom.html
  | title      = Celebrants of Brit Shalom
  | accessdate      = 2007-10-03
  | last      = Reiss, MD
  | first      = Dr. Mark
  | year      = 2006
  | publisher      = Brit Shalom
  | url-status      = dead
  | archiveurl      = https://web.archive.org/web/20141213065752/http://www.circumstitions.com/Jewish-shalom.html
  | archivedate      = 2014-12-13
  }}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | url      = http://www.jewsagainstcircumcision.org/brisshalom.htm
  | title      = Providers of Brit Shalom
  | accessdate      = 2007-10-03
  | last      = Goldman, PhD
  | first      = Ron
  | year      = 2006
  | publisher      = [[Jews Against Circumcision]]
  | url-status      = dead
  | archiveurl      = https://web.archive.org/web/20070929080506/http://www.jewsagainstcircumcision.org/brisshalom.htm
  | archivedate      = 2007-09-29
  }}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:הפגנת פעילים נגד ברית-מילה.jpg|thumb|right|230px|Secular [[Israeli Jews]] (''[[Hiloni]]m'') protest against ritual circumcision (brit milah) in [[Tel Aviv]]]]

The ceremony of ''Brit shalom'' is not officially approved of by the Reform or Reconstructionist rabbinical organizations, who make the recommendation that male infants should be circumcised, though the issue of converts remains controversial&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | url      = http://urj.org/Articles/index.cfm?id=8320&amp;pge_prg_id=29839&amp;pge_id=3450
  | title      = B'rit Milah: A Jewish Answer to Modernity
  | accessdate      = 2007-11-03
  | last      = Glickman
  | first      = Mark
  | date      = November 12, 2005
  | publisher      = [[Union for Reform Judaism]]
  | url-status      = dead
  | archiveurl      = https://web.archive.org/web/20071015161234/http://urj.org/Articles/index.cfm?id=8320&amp;pge_prg_id=29839&amp;pge_id=3450
  | archivedate      = October 15, 2007
  }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www4.jrf.org/showdt&amp;rid=322&amp;pid=15 |title=Bo: Defining Boundaries |accessdate=2007-11-03 |last=Cohen |first=Rabbi Howard |date=May 20, 2002 |publisher=Jewish Reconstructionist Federation |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071113210451/http://www4.jrf.org/showdt%26rid%3D322%26pid%3D15 |archivedate=November 13, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and circumcision of converts is not mandatory in either movement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jewishcalgary.org/page.html?ArticleID=63645 |title=The Conversion Process |accessdate=2007-11-03 |last=Epstein |first=Lawrence |year=2007 |publisher=Calgary Jewish Community Council |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20081227065531/http://www.jewishcalgary.org/page.aspx?id=63645 |archivedate=December 27, 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The connection of the Reform movement to an anti-circumcision, pro-symbolic stance is a historical one.&lt;ref name=&quot;Yivo&quot;&gt;{{quote|In the first half of the nineteenth century, various European governments considered regulating, if not banning, ''berit milah'' on the grounds that it posed potential medical dangers. In the 1840s, radical Jewish reformers in [[Frankfurt]] asserted that circumcision should no longer be compulsory. This controversy reached [[Russian Empire|Russia]] in the 1880s. Russian Jewish physicians expressed concern over two central issues: the competence of those carrying out the procedure and the method used for ''metsitsah''. Many Jewish physicians supported the idea of procedural and hygienic reforms in the practice, and they debated the question of physician supervision during the ceremony. Most significantly, many advocated carrying out ''metsitsah'' by pipette, not by mouth. In 1889, a committee on circumcision convened by the Russian Society for the Protection of Health, which included leading Jewish figures, recommended educating the Jewish public about the concerns connected with circumcision, in particular, the possible transmission of diseases such as [[tuberculosis]] and [[syphilis]] through the custom of ''metsitsah'' by mouth.

Veniamin Portugalov, who—alone among Russian Jewish physicians—called for the abolition of circumcision, set off these discussions. Portugalov not only denied all medical claims regarding the sanitary advantages of circumcision but disparaged the practice as barbaric, likening it to pagan ritual mutilation. Ritual circumcision, he claimed, stood as a self-imposed obstacle to the Jews’ [[Jewish emancipation|attainment of true equality with the other peoples of Europe]].|author=Epstein, Lisa|source=[http://www.yivoencyclopedia.org/article.aspx/Circumcision &quot;Circumcision&quot;], ''[[The YIVO Encyclopedia of Jews in Eastern Europe]]'', [[Yale University Press]].}}&lt;/ref&gt; From the early days of the movement in [[Germany]] and [[Eastern Europe]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Yivo&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Gollaher|first=David|author-link=David Gollaher|title=Circumcision: A History Of The World's Most Controversial Surgery |chapter=1, ''The Jewish Tradition'' |pages=1–30 |date=February 2001 |publisher=Basic Books|location=New York City|isbn=978-0465026531 |chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=usEzSffvPBMC}}&lt;/ref&gt; some classical Reformers hoped to replace ritual circumcision &quot;with a symbolic act, as has been done for other bloody practices, such as the sacrifices&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Katz, Jacob (1998), ''Divine Law in Human Hands: Case Studies in Halakhic Flexibility''. [[Jerusalem]]: [[Hebrew University of Jerusalem|Hebrew University]], {{ISBN|978-9652239808}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the US, an official Reform resolution in 1893 announced converts are no longer mandated to undergo the ritual,&lt;ref&gt;Meyer, Michael. &quot;''Berit Mila'' within the History of the Reform Movement&quot; in Barth, Lewis (1990), ''Berit Mila in the Reform Context''. New York: Berit Milah Board of reform Judaism.&lt;/ref&gt; and this ambivalence towards the practice has carried over to classical-minded Reform Jews today. In Elyse Wechterman's essay ''A Plea for Inclusion'', she argues that, even in the absence of circumcision, committed Jews should never be turned away, especially by a movement &quot;where no other ritual observance is mandated&quot;. She goes on to advocate an alternate covenant ceremony, ''brit atifah'', for both boys and girls as a welcoming ritual into Judaism.&lt;ref&gt;Mark, Elizabeth Wyner (2003) ''The Covenant of Circumcision''. Lebanon, New Hampshire: Brandeis {{ISBN|1584653078}}&lt;/ref&gt; With a continuing negativity towards circumcision still present within a minority of modern-day Reform, Judaic scholar Jon Levenson has warned that if they &quot;continue to judge ''brit milah'' to be not only medically unnecessary but also brutalizing and mutilating ... the abhorrence of it expressed by some early Reform leaders will return with a vengeance&quot;, proclaiming that circumcision will be &quot;the latest front in the battle over the Jewish future in America&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Levenson, Jon (March 2000). &quot;The New Enemies of Circumcision&quot;, ''Commentary''&lt;/ref&gt;

Many European Jewish fathers during the nineteenth century chose not to circumcise their sons, including [[Theodor Herzl]].&lt;ref&gt;Stewart, Desmond (1974), ''Theodor Herzl''. New York: Doubleday, {{ISBN|978-0385088961}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Goldman 1997&quot; /&gt; However, unlike many other forms of religious observance, it remained one of the last rituals Jewish communities could enforce. In most of Europe, both the government and the unlearned Jewish masses believed circumcision to be a rite akin to baptism, and the law allowed communities not to register uncircumcised children as Jewish. This legal maneuver spurred several debates addressing the advisibility of its use, since many parents later chose to convert to Christianity. In early 20th-century Russia, [[Chaim Soloveitchik]] advised his colleagues to reject this measure, stating that uncircumcised Jewish males are no less Jewish than Jews who violate other commandments.&lt;ref name=&quot;A&quot;/&gt;

== Similarities with Islam ==

Islamic male circumcision is analogous but not identical to Jewish circumcision. Jewish circumcision is tightly bound by ritual timing and tradition; however, in Islam, there is no fixed age for circumcision.{{Citation needed|date=December 2019}} According to some traditions, Muhammad was circumcised by his grandfather Abd-al-Muttalib when he was seven days old.{{Citation needed|date=December 2019}}

== See also ==
* [[Circumcision of Jesus]]
* [[Khitan (circumcision)]]
* [[History of male circumcision]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.chabad.org/library/article_cdo/aid/144122/jewish/brit-milah-circumcision.htm/ Chabad.org's Brit Milah: The Covenant of Circumcision]
* [http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/articles/4391-circumcision/ Jewish Encyclopedia's entry for Circumcision]
* [https://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/circumcision-brit-milah/ Jewish Virtual Library's Circumcision – Brit Milah]
* [http://circcentral.bobmeyer99.com/ CircCentral, an online museum of Brit Milah instruments]
 
{{Circumcision series}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Brit Milah}}
[[Category:Circumcision]]
[[Category:Jewish life cycle]]
[[Category:Jewish medical ethics]]
[[Category:Judaism and children]]
[[Category:Judaism-related controversies]]
[[Category:Lech-Lecha]]
[[Category:Positive Mitzvoth]]
[[Category:Rites of passage]]</text>
      <sha1>5v3tkhimwkhaibf0xsieoz3l4kugvqp</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
