  <page>
    <title>Baralong incidents</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4794</id>
    <revision>
      <id>915352369</id>
      <parentid>909380416</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-09-12T18:49:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Rich Farmbrough</username>
        <id>82835</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>clean up</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{DISPLAYTITLE:''Baralong'' incidents}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}
{{more footnotes|date=February 2014}}
{{Infobox military conflict
 |conflict    = ''Baralong'' incidents
 |partof      = {{nowr|the [[Atlantic U-boat campaign of World War I]]}}
 |image       = 
 |date        = 19 August and 24 September 1915
 |place       = [[Irish Sea]], [[Atlantic Ocean]]
 |result      = British victory
 |combatant1  = {{flagcountry|United Kingdom}}
 |combatant2  = {{flagcountry|German Empire}}
 |commander1  = {{ubl|[[Godfrey Herbert]]|A. Wilmot-Smith}}
 |commander2  = {{ubl|Bernd Wegener{{KIA}}|Klaus Hansen{{KIA}}}}
 |strength1   = {{ubl|1 decoy vessel|2 steamers}}
 |strength2   = 2 submarines
 |casualties1 = 2 steamers damaged
 |casualties2 = 2 submarines sunk
 |campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Atlantic 1914–1918}}
}}

The '''''Baralong''''' '''incidents''' were naval engagements of the [[World War I|First World War]] in August and September 1915, involving the [[Royal Navy]] decoy vessel {{HMS|Baralong}} and two German [[U-boat]]s.

''Baralong'' sank {{SMU|U-27|Germany|2}}, which had been preparing to sink a nearby merchant ship, the ''Nicosian''. About a dozen of the crewmen managed to escape from the sinking submarine, and Lieutenant [[Godfrey Herbert]], commanding officer of ''Baralong'', ordered the surviving sailors to be summarily executed after they boarded the ''Nicosian''. All the survivors of ''U-27''{{'}}s sinking, including several who had reached the ''Nicosian'', were shot by ''Baralong''{{'}}s crew. Later, ''Baralong'' sank {{SMU|U-41|Germany|2}} in an incident which has been described as a [[war crime]].&lt;ref&gt;Coles 1986 {{Page needed|date=May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bridgland 1999, pp. 20–55.&lt;/ref&gt;

==First incident==

===Action of 19 August 1915===
After the sinking of {{RMS|Lusitania}} by a German submarine in May 1915, Lieutenant-Commander [[Godfrey Herbert]], commanding officer of ''Baralong'', was visited by two officers of the [[Admiralty]]'s Secret Service branch at the naval base at [[Cobh|Queenstown, Ireland]]. He was told, &quot;This ''Lusitania'' business is shocking. Unofficially, we are telling you... take no prisoners from U-boats.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Bridgland 1999, p. 21.&lt;/ref&gt;

Interviews with his subordinate officers have established Herbert's undisciplined manner of commanding his ship. Herbert allowed his men to engage in drunken binges during shore leave. During one such incident, at [[Dartmouth, Devon|Dartmouth]], several members of ''Baralong''{{'}}s crew were arrested after destroying a local saloon. Herbert paid their bail, then left port with the indicted crewmen aboard. Beginning in April 1915, Herbert ordered his subordinates to cease calling him &quot;Sir&quot;, and to address him only by the [[pseudonym]] &quot;Captain William McBride&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Messimer 2002, p. 23.&lt;/ref&gt;

Throughout the summer of 1915, ''Baralong'' continued routine patrol duties in the [[Irish Sea]] without encountering the enemy.

On 19 August 1915, {{SMU|U-24||2}} sank the [[White Star Line]]r {{SS|Arabic|1902|6}} with the loss of 44 lives – this included three Americans and led to a diplomatic incident between Germany and the United States. HMS ''Baralong'' had been about {{convert|20|mi|abbr=on}} from the scene, and had received a distress call from the ship.&lt;ref name=oneill9/&gt; ''Baralong''{{'}}s crew was infuriated by the attack and by their inability to locate survivors.&lt;ref name=messimer4647/&gt;

Meanwhile, about {{convert|70|nmi|lk=on}} south of Queenstown, {{SMU|U-27|Germany|2}}, commanded by ''[[Kapitänleutnant]]'' Bernd Wegener, stopped the British steamer ''Nicosian'' in accordance with the rules laid down by the [[London Declaration concerning the Laws of Naval War|London Declaration]]. A boarding party of six men from ''U-27'' discovered that ''Nicosian'' was carrying munitions and 250 American mules earmarked for the [[British Army]] in France. The Germans allowed the freighter's crew and passengers to board lifeboats, and prepared to sink the freighter with the U-boat's deck gun.

''U-27'' was lying off ''Nicosian''{{'}}s port quarter and firing into it when ''Baralong'' appeared on the scene, flying the ensign of the United States as a [[false flag]]. When she was half a mile away, ''Baralong'' ran up a signal flag indicating that she was going to rescue ''Nicosian''{{'}}s crew. Wegener acknowledged the signal, then ordered his men to cease firing, and took ''U-27'' along the port side of ''Nicosian'' to intercept ''Baralong''. As the submarine disappeared behind the steamship, Herbert steered ''Baralong'' on a parallel course along ''Nicosian''{{'}}s starboard side.&lt;ref name=messimer4647&gt;Messimer 2002, pp. 46–47.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:HMS Baralong vs SM U-27.jpg|thumb|The action of 19 August 1915]]

Before ''U-27'' came round ''Nicosian''{{'}}s bow, ''Baralong'' hauled down the American flag, hoisted the Royal Navy's [[White Ensign]], and unmasked her guns. As ''U-27'' came into view from behind ''Nicosian'', ''Baralong'' opened fire with her three [[QF 12 pounder 12 cwt naval gun|12-pounder guns]] at a range of {{convert|600|yd|abbr=on}}, firing 34 rounds for only a single shot from the submarine. ''U-27'' rolled over and began to sink.&lt;ref name=oneill9&gt;O'Neill 2006, p. 9.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=messimer4647/&gt;

According to Tony Bridgland; &lt;blockquote&gt;Herbert screamed, &quot;Cease fire!&quot; But his men's blood was up. They were avenging the ''Arabic'' and the ''Lusitania''. For them this was no time to cease firing, even as the survivors of the crew appeared on the outer casing, struggling out of their clothes to swim away from her. There was a mighty hiss of compressed air from her tanks and the ''U-27'' vanished from sight in a vortex of giant rumbling bubbles, leaving a pall of smoke over the spot where she had been. It had taken only a few minutes to fire the thirty-four shells into her.&lt;ref&gt;Messimer 2002, pp. 29–30.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Meanwhile, ''Nicosian''{{'}}s crew were cheering wildly from the lifeboats. Captain Manning was heard to yell, &quot;If any of those bastard [[List of terms used for Germans#Hun|Huns]] come up, lads, hit 'em with an oar!&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Messimer 2002, p. 30.&lt;/ref&gt;

Twelve men survived the sinking of the submarine: the crews of her two deck guns and those who had been on the conning tower. They swam to ''Nicosian'' and attempted to join the six-man boarding party by climbing up her hanging lifeboat falls and pilot ladder. Herbert, worried that they might try to scuttle the steamer, ordered his men to open fire with small arms, killing all in the water.&lt;ref name=oneill9/&gt;&lt;ref name=GibPren53&gt;Gibson &amp; Prendergast, p. 53.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=grant&gt;Grant 2002, p. 27.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=halpern&gt;Halpern 1994, p. 301.&lt;/ref&gt; Wegener is described by some accounts as being shot while trying to swim to the ''Baralong''.&lt;ref name=grant/&gt;

Herbert sent ''Baralong''{{'}}s 12 [[Royal Marines]], under the command of a Corporal Collins, to find the surviving German sailors aboard ''Nicosian''. As they departed, Herbert told Collins, &quot;Take no prisoners.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Messimer 2002, p. 42.&lt;/ref&gt; The Germans were discovered in the engine room and shot on sight. According to Sub-Lieutenant [[Gordon Charles Steele]]: &quot;Wegener ran to a cabin on the upper deck – I later found out it was Manning's bathroom. The marines broke down the door with the butts of their rifles, but Wegener squeezes through a scuttle and dropped into the sea. He still had his life-jacket on and put up his arms in surrender. Corporal Collins, however, took aim and shot him through the head.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bridgland43&quot;&gt;Bridgland 1999, p. 43.&lt;/ref&gt; Corporal Collins later recalled that, after Wegener's death, Herbert threw a revolver in the German captain's face and screamed, &quot;What about the ''Lusitania'', you bastard!&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bridgland43&quot;/&gt; An alternative account says that the Germans who boarded ''Nicosian'' were killed by the freighter's engine room staff; this report apparently came from the officer in command of the muleteers.&lt;ref name=oneill9/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;McGill &amp; Norris 2007, pp. 320–321.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Aftermath===
In Herbert's report to the Admiralty, he stated he feared the survivors from the U-boat's crew would board the freighter and scuttle her, so he ordered the Royal Marines on his ship to shoot the survivors. If they had scuttled the freighter, it could have been counted as negligence on the part of Herbert. Moments before ''Baralong'' began her attack, the submarine was firing on the freighter. It is not known if the escaping sailors actually intended to scuttle the freighter.

The Admiralty, upon receiving Herbert's report, immediately ordered its suppression, but the strict censorship imposed on the event failed when Americans who had witnessed the incident from ''Nicosian''{{'}}s lifeboats spoke to newspaper reporters after their return to the United States.&lt;ref name=&quot;halpern&quot;/&gt;

===German memorandum===
The German government delivered a memorandum on the incident via the American ambassador in Berlin, who received it on 6 December 1915. In it, they cited six US citizens as witnesses, stating they had made sworn depositions regarding the incident before [[Notary public|notaries public]] in the US.

The statements said that five survivors from ''U-27'' managed to board ''Nicosian'', while the rest were shot and killed on Herbert's orders while clinging to the merchant vessel's lifeboat falls. It was further stated that when Herbert ordered his Marines to board ''Nicosian'', he gave the order &quot;take no prisoners&quot;. Four German sailors were found in ''Nicosian''{{'}}s engine room and propeller shaft tunnel, and were killed. According to the witness statements, ''U-27''{{'}}s commander was shot while swimming towards ''Baralong''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Memorandum of the German Government... and reply of His Majesty's Government thereto|work= |publisher=WWW Virtual Library |date= |url=http://www.vlib.us/wwi/resources/archives/texts/t050925/Baralong.html |accessdate=8 December 2012}}[note: the British reply is not included]&lt;/ref&gt;

The memorandum demanded that the captain and crew of ''Baralong'' be tried for the murder of unarmed German sailors, threatening to &quot;take the serious decision of retribution for an unpunished crime&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Baralong Case|url=http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article15635604|accessdate=28 July 2013|newspaper=Sydney Morning Herald|date=6 January 1916|page=7}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Edward Grey, 1st Viscount Grey of Fallodon|Sir Edward Grey]] replied through the American ambassador that the incident could be grouped together with the Germans' sinking of SS ''Arabic'', their attack on a stranded British submarine on the neutral Dutch coast, and their attack on the steamship ''Ruel'', and suggested that they be placed before a tribunal composed of US Navy officers.&lt;ref name=reg&gt;Hesperides 2007, pp. 58–59.&lt;/ref&gt;

===German reaction===
A debate took place in the [[Reichstag building|''Reichstag'']] on 15 January 1916, where the incident was described as a &quot;cowardly murder&quot; and Grey's note as being &quot;full of insolence and arrogance&quot;.{{citequote|date=January 2016}} It was announced that reprisals had been decided, but not what form they would take.&lt;ref name=reg/&gt;

Meanwhile, the Military Bureau for the Investigation of Violations of the Laws of War ({{lang-de|Militäruntersuchungstelle für Verletzungen des Kriegsrechts}}) added ''Baralong''{{'}}s commander, whose name was known only as &quot;Captain William McBride&quot;, to the Prussian Ministry of War's &quot;Black List of Englishmen who are Guilty of Violations of the Laws of War vis-à-vis Members of the German Armed Forces&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Alfred M. de Zayas, ''The Wehrmacht War Crimes Bureau 1939–1945'', p 8.&lt;/ref&gt;

HMS ''Baralong''{{'}}s actions led the ''[[Kaiserliche Marine]]'' to cease adhering to the [[Prize Rules]] and to practise [[unrestricted submarine warfare]].{{citation needed|date=January 2016}} During the Second World War, it was cited{{by whom|date=January 2016}} as a reason for the ''[[Kriegsmarine]]'' to do the same.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}} A German medal was issued commemorating the event.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://collections.nmm.ac.uk/collections/objects/39815.html |title=Medal commemorating the sinking of 'U.27' by Q-ship 'Baralong', 1915 |work=The Collection |publisher=National Maritime Museum |accessdate=10 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As a precaution to protect the ships against any reprisals against their crews, HMS ''Wyandra''{{clarify|Renamed when|date=December 2011}} was transferred to the Mediterranean, and took the name of sister ship ''Manica'', while ''Baralong''{{'}}s name was deleted from [[Lloyd's Register]]. ''Nicosian'' was renamed ''Nevisian'', and the crew was issued new Discharge Books, with the voyage omitted.&lt;ref&gt;O'Neill 2006, p. 10.&lt;/ref&gt;

''Baralong''{{'}}s crew were later awarded [[Pound sterling|£]]185 prize bounty for sinking ''U-27''.&lt;ref name=chatterton&gt;Chatterton 1980, p. 26.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Second incident==

===Action of 24 September 1915===
On 24 September 1915, ''Baralong'' sank the U-boat {{SMU|U-41|Germany|2}}, for which her commanding officer at the time, Lieutenant-Commander A. Wilmot-Smith, was later awarded £170 prize bounty.&lt;ref name=chatterton/&gt;

''U-41'' was in the process of sinking SS ''Urbino'' with gunfire when ''Baralong'' arrived on the scene, flying an American flag. When ''U-41'' surfaced near ''Baralong'', the latter opened fire while continuing to fly the American flag, and sank the U-boat.

===Aftermath of the second incident===
Unlike the neutral Americans in the first incident, the only witnesses to the second attack were the German and British sailors present. ''[[Oberleutnant zur See]]'' Iwan Crompton, after returning to Germany from a prisoner-of-war camp, reported that ''Baralong'' had run down the lifeboat he was in; he leapt clear and was shortly after taken aboard ''Baralong''. The British crew denied that they had run down the lifeboat.&lt;ref&gt;Messimer 2002, pp. 61–62.&lt;/ref&gt; Crompton later published an account of ''U-41''{{'}}s exploits in 1917, ''U-41: der zweite Baralong-Fall'', which called the sinking of ''U-41'' a &quot;second Baralong case&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Hadley 1995, p. 36.&lt;/ref&gt;

The event was also commemorated in a propaganda medal designed by the German engraver Karl Goetz. This was one of many medals that were popular in Germany from around 1910 to 1940.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The sinking of 'U.41' by Q-ship 'Baralong', 1915|url=http://collections.rmg.co.uk/collections/objects/39816.html|website=Royal Museums, Greenwich|publisher=National Maritime Museum|accessdate=20 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Unrestricted submarine warfare]]
* [[Merchant raiders]]
* [[Commerce raiding]]
* [[Tonnage war]]

==Citations==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==References==
{{Refbegin}}
* {{cite book |last=Bridgland |first=Tony |title=Sea Killers in Disguise: Q Ships and Decoy Raiders |publisher=Leo Cooper |year=1999 |isbn=9780850526752 |chapter=The ''Baralong'': Germany is Outraged}}
* {{cite book |last=Chatterton |first=E. Keble |title=Q-Ships and Their Story |publisher=Ayer Publishing |year=1980 |location= |isbn=0405130341}}
* {{cite book |last=Coles |first=Alan |title=Slaughter at Sea: The Truth Behind a Naval War Crime |publisher=R. Hale |location= London |year=1986}}
* {{cite book |last=Gibson |first=R.H. |author2=Prendergast, Maurice |title=The German Submarine War 1914–1918 |publisher= Periscope Publishing Ltd |year=2002 |location= |isbn=1904381081}}
* {{cite book |last=Grant |first=Robert M. |title=U-boats Destroyed: The Effect of Anti-submarine Warfare 1914–1918 |publisher= Periscope Publishing Ltd |year=2002 |location= |isbn=1904381006}}
* {{cite book |last=Hadley |first=Michael L. |title=Count Not the Dead: The Popular Image of the German Submarine |publisher=McGill-Queen's Press - MQUP |year=1995 |location= |isbn=0773512829}}
* {{cite book |last=Halpern |first=Paul G. |title=A Naval History of World War I |publisher=Routledge |year=1994 |location= |isbn=1857284984}}
* {{cite book |last=Hesperides |first= |title=The Annual Register Review of Public Events at Home and Abroad for the Year 1916 |publisher=Read Books |year=2007 |location= |isbn=1406751987}}
* {{cite book |last=Massie |first=Robert K. |title=Castles of Steel: Britain, Germany, and the Winning of the Great War at Sea |year=2003 |publisher=Random House |location=New York |isbn=}}
* {{cite book |last=McGill |first=Harold W. |author2=Norris, Majorie Barron |title=Medicine and Duty: The World War I Memoir of Captain Harold W. McGill, Medical Officer, 31st Battalion, C.E.F. |publisher=University of Calgary Press |year=2007 |location=Calgary |isbn=1552381935}}
* {{cite book |last=Messimer |first=Dwight R. |title=Verschollen: World War I U-boat Losses |publisher=Naval Institute Press |year= 2002 |location= |isbn=155750475X}}
* {{Cite journal|last=O'Neill |first=Gerry |title=Scandal of The Baralong Incident Was Hidden in Veil of Secrecy |journal=Journal of the Sea |publisher=The Maritime Institute of Ireland |volume=1 |issue=4 |pages=8–10 |date=Spring 2006 |url=http://www.mii.connect.ie/journal/2006.pdf |accessdate=10 December 2011 |url-status = dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071119155246/http://mii.connect.ie/journal/2006.pdf |archivedate=19 November 2007 |df=dmy }}
{{Refend}}

[[Category:World War I massacres]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1915]]
[[Category:1915 crimes]]
[[Category:Atlantic operations of World War I]]
[[Category:Massacres committed by the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Extrajudicial killings]]
[[Category:Deaths by firearm in international waters]]
[[Category:World War I crimes by the British Empire and Commonwealth]]</text>
      <sha1>8s61vkvqq70v2t8ppkrz16g2nfnod63</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
