  <page>
    <title>André Gide</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1058</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941849615</id>
      <parentid>937332942</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-21T01:37:27Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bluelink 1 book for [[Wikipedia:Verifiability|verifiability]]. [goog]) #IABot (v2.0) ([[User:GreenC bot|GreenC bot]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=December 2013}}
{{Infobox writer &lt;!-- for more information see [[:Template:Infobox writer/doc]] --&gt;
| name = André Gide
| awards = {{awd|[[Nobel Prize in Literature]]|1947}}
| image = André Gide.jpg
| caption =
|birth_name=André Paul Guillaume Gide
| birth_date = {{birth date|df=yes|1869|11|22}}
| birth_place = [[Paris]], [[Second French Empire|French Empire]]
| death_date = {{death date and age|df=yes|1951|2|19|1869|11|22}}
| death_place = Paris, [[French Fourth Republic|France]]
| resting_place = Cimetière de Cuverville, [[Cuverville, Seine-Maritime]]
| occupation = Novelist, essayist, dramatist
| genre =
| movement =
| notableworks = ''[[The Immoralist|L'immoraliste]]'' (''The Immoralist'')&lt;br /&gt; ''[[Strait Is the Gate|La porte étroite]]'' (''Strait Is the Gate'')&lt;br /&gt;  ''Les caves du Vatican'' (''The Vatican Cellars''; sometimes published in English under the title ''Lafcadio's Adventures'')&lt;br /&gt; ''[[La Symphonie Pastorale]]'' (''The Pastoral Symphony'')&lt;br /&gt; ''[[The Counterfeiters (novel)|Les faux-monnayeurs]]'' (''The Counterfeiters'')
| spouse                    = Madeleine Rondeaux Gide
| children =  Catherine Gide

| signature = André Gide signature.svg
| website ={{URL|andregide.org}}
| education     = [[Lycée Henri-IV]]
}}

{{French literature sidebar}}
'''André Paul Guillaume Gide''' ({{IPA-fr|ɑ̃dʁe pɔl ɡijom ʒid|lang}}; 22 November 1869 – 19 February 1951) was a French author and winner of the [[Nobel Prize in Literature]] (in 1947). Gide's career ranged from its beginnings in the [[Symbolism (arts)|symbolist]] movement, to the advent of [[Anti-imperialism|anticolonialism]] between the two World Wars. The author of more than fifty books, at the time of his death his obituary in ''[[The New York Times]]'' described him as &quot;France's greatest contemporary man of letters&quot; and &quot;judged the greatest French writer of this century by the literary cognoscenti.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.andregide.org/remembrance/nytgide.html|title=new york time obituary|website=www.andregide.org|accessdate=20 March 2018|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110806050538/http://www.andregide.org/remembrance/nytgide.html|archive-date=6 August 2011|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Known for his fiction as well as his autobiographical works, Gide exposes to public view the conflict and eventual reconciliation of the two sides of his personality (characterized by a Protestant austerity and a transgressive sexual adventurousness, respectively), which a strict and moralistic education had helped set at odds. Gide's work can be seen as an investigation of freedom and empowerment in the face of moralistic and [[puritan]]ical constraints, and centers on his continuous effort to achieve intellectual honesty. His self-exploratory texts reflect his search of how to be fully oneself, including owning one's sexual nature, without at the same time betraying one's values. His political activity is shaped by the same ethos, as indicated by his repudiation of [[communism]] after his 1936 voyage to the [[Soviet Union|USSR]].

==Early life==
[[File:Gide 1893.jpg|thumb|left|150px|Gide in 1893]]
Gide was born in Paris on 22 November 1869, into a middle-class [[Protestant]] family. His father was a [[University of Paris|Paris University]] professor of law who died in 1880, Jean Paul Guillaume Gide, and his mother was Juliette Maria Rondeaux. His uncle was the political economist [[Charles Gide]]. His paternal family traced its roots back to [[Italy]], with his ancestors, the Guidos, moving to France and other western and northern European countries after converting to Protestantism during the 16th century, due to persecution.&lt;ref&gt;[[Wallace Fowlie]], ''André Gide: His Life and Art'', Macmillan (1965), p. 11&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Pierre de Boisdeffre, ''Vie d'André Gide, 1869-1951: André Gide avant la fondation de la Nouvelle revue française (1869-1909)'', Hachette (1970), p. 29&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Jean Delay]], ''La jeunesse d'André Gide'', Gallimard (1956), p. 55&lt;/ref&gt;

Gide was brought up in isolated conditions in [[Normandy]] and became a prolific writer at an early age, publishing his first novel, ''The Notebooks of André Walter'' (French: ''Les Cahiers d'André Walter''), in 1891, at the age of twenty-one.

In 1893 and 1894, Gide traveled in Northern Africa, and it was there that he came to accept his attraction to boys.&lt;ref&gt;''If It Die: Autobiographical Memoir'' by André Gide (first edition 1920) (Vintage Books, 1935, translated by Dorothy Bussy: &quot;but when Ali – that was my little guide's name – led me up among the sandhills, in spite of the fatigue of walking in the sand, I followed him; we soon reached a kind of funnel or crater, the rim of which was just high enough to command the surrounding country...As soon as we got there, Ali flung the coat and rug down on the sloping sand; he flung himself down too, and stretched on his back...I was not such a simpleton as to misunderstand his invitation&quot;...&quot;I seized the hand he held out to me and tumbled him on to the ground.&quot; [p. 251]&lt;/ref&gt;

He befriended [[Oscar Wilde]] in Paris, and in 1895 Gide and Wilde met in [[Algiers]]. Wilde had the impression that he had introduced Gide to [[homosexuality]], but, in fact, Gide had already discovered this on his own.&lt;ref&gt;Out of the past, Gay and Lesbian History from 1869 to the present (Miller 1995:87)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''If It Die: Autobiographical Memoir'' by André Gide (first edition 1920) (Vintage Books, 1935, translated by Dorothy Bussy: &quot;I should say that if Wilde had begun to discover the secrets of his life to me, he knew nothing as yet of mine; I had taken care to give him no hint of them, either by deed or word....No doubt, since my adventure at Sousse, there was not much left for the Adversary to do to complete his victory over me; but Wilde did not know this, nor that I was vanquished beforehand or, if you will...that I had already triumphed in my imagination and my thoughts over all my scruples.&quot; [p. 286])&lt;/ref&gt;

==The middle years==
{{more citations needed|section|date=November 2017}}&lt;!--5 paragraphs have no citations--&gt;
[[File:Gide 1920 cropped.jpg|thumb|Gide photographed by [[Ottoline Morrell]] in 1924.]]
[[Image:Gide by Laurens.jpg|thumb|André Gide by [[Paul Albert Laurens]] (1924)]]
In 1895, after his mother's death, he married his cousin Madeleine Rondeaux,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.museeprotestant.org/en/notice/andre-gide1869-1951/|title=André Gide (1869-1951) - Musée virtuel du Protestantisme|author=|date=|website=www.museeprotestant.org|accessdate=20 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; but the marriage remained unconsummated. In 1896, he became mayor of [[La Roque-Baignard]], a [[Communes of France|commune]] in Normandy.

In 1901, Gide rented the property [[Maderia]] in [[St. Brélade's Bay]] and lived there while residing in [[Jersey]]. This period, 1901–07, is commonly seen as a time of apathy and turmoil for him.

In 1908, Gide helped found the literary magazine ''[[Nouvelle Revue Française]]'' (''The New French Review'').&lt;ref&gt;[http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/literature/laureates/1947/gide-bio.html André Gide Biography]. nobelprize.org&lt;/ref&gt; In 1916, [[Marc Allégret]], only 15 years old, became his lover. Marc was the son &amp;ndash; one of five children &amp;ndash; of Élie Allégret, who years before had been hired by Gide's mother to tutor her son in light of his weak grades in school, after which he and Gide became fast friends; Élie Allégret was best man at Gide's wedding. Gide and Marc fled to London, in retribution for which his wife burned all his correspondence – &quot;the best part of myself,&quot; he later commented. In 1918, he met [[Dorothy Bussy]], who was his friend for over thirty years and translated many of his works into English.

In the 1920s, Gide became an inspiration for writers such as [[Albert Camus]] and [[Jean-Paul Sartre]]. In 1923, he published a book on [[Fyodor Dostoyevsky]]; however, when he defended homosexuality in the public edition of ''[[Corydon (book)|Corydon]]'' (1924) he received widespread condemnation. He later considered this his most important work.

In 1923, he sired a daughter, Catherine, by Elisabeth van Rysselberghe, a woman who was much younger than he. He had known her for a long time, as she was the daughter of his closest female friend, Maria Monnom, the wife of his friend the Belgian neo-impressionist painter [[Théo van Rysselberghe]]. This caused the only crisis in the long-standing relationship between Allégret and Gide and damaged the relation with van Rysselberghe. This was possibly Gide's only sexual liaison with a woman,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lrb.co.uk/v20/n24/edmund-white/on-the-chance-that-a-shepherd-boy-|title=On the chance that a shepherd boy …|first=Edmund|last=White|date=10 December 1998|publisher=|pages=3–6|accessdate=20 March 2018|via=London Review of Books}}&lt;/ref&gt; and it was brief in the extreme. Catherine became his only descendant by blood. He liked to call Elisabeth &quot;La Dame Blanche&quot; (&quot;The White Lady&quot;). Elisabeth eventually left her husband to move to Paris and manage the practical aspects of Gide's life (they had adjoining apartments built for each on the rue Vavin). She worshiped him, but evidently they no longer had a sexual relationship.{{Citation needed|reason=Elisabeth's mother Maria was called La Petite Dame. Never heard about La Dame blanche as a name for Elisabeth. Also not sure that Elisabeth was married during the affair.|date=April 2019}}

Gide's legal wife, Madeleine, died in 1938. Later he explored their unconsummated marriage in his memoir of Madeleine, ''Et nunc manet in te''.

In 1924, he published an [[autobiography]], ''If it Die...'' (French: ''[[Si le grain ne meurt]]'').

In the same year, he produced the first French language editions of [[Joseph Conrad]]'s ''[[Heart of Darkness]]'' and ''[[Lord Jim]]''.

After 1925, he began to campaign for more humane conditions for convicted criminals.

==Africa==
From July 1926 to May 1927, he traveled through the [[French Equatorial Africa]] colony with his lover [[Marc Allégret]]. Gide went successively to [[Middle Congo]] (now the [[Republic of the Congo]]), [[Ubangi-Shari]] (now the [[Central African Republic]]), briefly to [[Chad]] and then to [[Cameroon]] before returning to France. He related his peregrinations in a journal called ''[[Travels in the Congo (book)|Travels in the Congo]]'' (French: ''Voyage au Congo'') and ''[[Return from Chad]]'' (French: ''Retour du Tchad''). In this published journal, he criticized the behavior of French business interests in the Congo and inspired reform.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/literature/laureates/1947/gide-bio.html|title=André Gide - Biographical|author=|date=|website=www.nobelprize.org|accessdate=20 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; In particular, he strongly criticized the ''Large Concessions'' regime (French: ''Régime des Grandes Concessions''), ''i.e.,'' a regime according to which part of the colony was conceded to French companies and where these companies could exploit all of the area's [[natural resource]]s, in particular rubber. He related, for instance, how natives were forced to leave their village for several weeks to collect rubber in the forest, and went as far as comparing their [[exploitation of labour|exploitation]] to [[slavery]]. The book had important influence on [[anti-colonialism]] movements in France and helped re-evaluate the [[Impact of Western European colonialism and colonisation|impact of colonialism]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lire.fr/critique.asp/idC=31184/idR=219/idTC=3/idG=2 Voyage au Congo suivi du Retour du Tchad]  {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070316041458/http://www.lire.fr/critique.asp/idC%3D31184/idR%3D219/idTC%3D3/idG%3D2 |date=16 March 2007 }}, in ''[[Lire (magazine)|Lire]]'', July–August 1995 {{in lang|fr}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Russia==
During the 1930s, he briefly became a communist, or more precisely, a [[Fellow traveller|fellow traveler]] (he never formally joined any communist party). As a distinguished writer sympathizing with the cause of communism, he was invited to speak at [[Maxim Gorky]]'s funeral and to tour the [[Soviet Union]] as a guest of the Soviet Union of Writers. He encountered censorship of his speeches and was particularly disillusioned with the state of culture under Soviet communism, breaking with his socialist friends {{Who|date=August 2018}}  in ''Retour de L'U.R.S.S.'' in 1936.

{{quote|Then would it not be better to, instead of playing on words, simply to acknowledge that the revolutionary spirit (or even simply the critical spirit) is no longer the correct thing, that it is not wanted any more? What is wanted now is compliance, conformism. What is desired and demanded is approval of all that is done in the U. S. S. R.; and an attempt is being made to obtain an approval that is not mere resignation, but a sincere, an enthusiastic approval. What is most astounding is that this attempt is successful. On the other hand the smallest protest, the least criticism, is liable to the severest penalties, and in fact is immediately stifled. And I doubt whether in any other  country in the world, even Hitler's Germany, thought to be less free, more bowed down, more fearful (terrorized), more vassalized.|André Gide ''Return from the U. S. S. R.''&lt;ref&gt;''Return from the U. S. S. R.'' translated D. Bussy (Alfred Knopf, 1937), pp. 41-42&lt;/ref&gt;}}

In the 1949 anthology ''[[The God that Failed|The God That Failed]]'' Gide describes his early enthusiasm:

{{quote|My faith in communism is like my faith in religion: it is a promise of salvation for mankind. If I have to lay my life down that it may succeed, I would do so without hesitation.|André Gide, ''The God That Failed''{{page needed|date=August 2018}}}}

&lt;!-- This quote needs a source and context --&gt;
{{quote|It is impermissible under any circumstances for morals to sink as low as communism has done. No one can begin to imagine the tragedy of humanity, of morality, of religion and of freedoms in the land of communism, where man has been debased beyond belief.|André Gide, as quoted in [[Tarek Heggy]]'s book ''Culture, Civilization, and Humanity''&lt;ref&gt;André Gide as [http://www.heggy.org/books/imperative/chapter_8.htm quoted by Tarek Heggy {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080407205033/http://www.heggy.org/books/imperative/chapter_8.htm |date=7 April 2008 }} in his book ''Culture, Civilization, and Humanity'' (2003). {{ISBN|0-7146-5554-6}}]&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==1930s and 1940s==

In 1930 Gide published a book about the [[Blanche Monnier]] case called ''La Séquestrée de Poitiers'', changing little but the names of the protagonists. Monnier was a young woman who was kept captive by her own mother for more than 25 years.&lt;ref name=Pujolas&gt;Pujolas, Marie. ''En tournage, un documentaire sur l'incroyable affaire de &quot;La séquestrée de Poitiers&quot;''. France TV info. Feb 27, 2015 [http://culturebox.francetvinfo.fr/cinema/documentaire/un-documentaire-sur-lincroyable-affaire-de-la-sequestree-de-poitiers-212899]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Levy&gt;Levy, Audrey. ''Destins de femmes: Ces Poitevines plus ou moins célèbres auront marqué l'Histoire''.  Le Point. Apr 21, 2015. [http://www.lepoint.fr/villes/destins-de-femmes-21-04-2015-1923072_27.php]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1939, Gide became the first living author to be published in the prestigious ''[[Bibliothèque de la Pléiade]]''.

He left France for Africa in 1942 and lived in [[Tunis]] until the end of World War II. In 1947, he received the [[Nobel Prize in Literature]] &quot;for his comprehensive and artistically significant writings, in which human problems and conditions have been presented with a fearless love of truth and keen psychological insight&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/literature/laureates/1947/|title=The Nobel Prize in Literature 1947|author=|date=|website=www.nobelprize.org|accessdate=20 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; He devoted much of his last years to publishing his Journal.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|title= André Gide (1869–1951)
|publisher=Musée virtuel du Protestantisme français
|url= http://www.museeprotestant.org/Pages/Notices.php?scatid=148&amp;noticeid=811&amp;lev=1&amp;Lget=FR
|accessdate=6 September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Gide died in Paris on 19 February 1951. The Roman Catholic Church placed his works on the ''[[Index Librorum Prohibitorum|Index of Forbidden Books]]'' in 1952.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.leninimports.com/andre_gide.html André Gide Biography (1869–1951)]. eninimports.com&lt;/ref&gt;

==Gide's life as a writer==

Gide's biographer Alan Sheridan summed up Gide's life as a writer and an intellectual:

{{quote|Gide was, by general consent, one of the dozen most important writers of the 20th century. Moreover, no writer of such stature had led such an interesting life, a life accessibly interesting to us as readers of his autobiographical writings, his journal, his voluminous correspondence and the testimony of others. It was the life of a man engaging not only in the business of artistic creation, but reflecting on that process in his journal, reading that work to his friends and discussing it with them; a man who knew and corresponded with all the major literary figures of his own country and with many in Germany and England; who found daily nourishment in the Latin, French, English and German classics, and, for much of his life, in the Bible; [who enjoyed playing Chopin and other classic works on the piano;] and who engaged in commenting on the moral, political and sexual questions of the day.&lt;ref&gt;''André Gide: A Life in the Present'' by Alan Sheridan. Harvard University Press, 1999, pages p. xvi.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

&quot;Gide's fame rested ultimately, of course, on his literary works. But, unlike many writers, he was no recluse: he had a need of friendship and a genius for sustaining it.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Alan Sheridan, p. xii.&lt;/ref&gt; But his &quot;capacity for love was not confined to his friends: it spilled over into a concern for others less fortunate than himself.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Alan Sheridan, p. 624.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Writings===

André Gide's writings spanned many genres – &quot;As a master of prose narrative, occasional dramatist and translator, literary critic, letter writer, essayist, and diarist, André Gide provided twentieth-century French literature with one of its most intriguing examples of the man of letters.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Article on ''André Gide'' in ''Contemporary Authors Online''' 2003. Retrieved with library card October 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

But as Gide's biographer Alan Sheridan points out, &quot;It is the fiction that lies at the summit of Gide's work.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Information in this paragraph is extracted from ''André Gide: A Life in the Present'' by Alan Sheridan, pp. 629-33.&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;Here, as in the ''oeuvre'' as a whole, what strikes one first is the variety. Here, too, we see Gide's curiosity, his youthfulness, at work: a refusal to mine only one seam, to repeat successful formulas...The fiction spans the early years of Symbolism, to the &quot;comic, more inventive, even fantastic&quot; pieces, to the later &quot;serious, heavily autobiographical, first-person narratives&quot;...In France Gide was considered a great stylist in the classical sense, &quot;with his clear, succinct, spare, deliberately, subtly phrased sentences.&quot;

Gide's surviving letters run into the thousands. But it is the ''Journal'' that Sheridan calls &quot;the pre-eminently Gidean mode of expression.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Information in this paragraph is extracted from ''André Gide: A Life in the Present'' by Alan Sheridan, pages 628.&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;His first novel emerged from Gide's own journal, and many of the first-person narratives read more or less like journals. In ''[[The Counterfeiters (novel)|Les faux-monnayeurs]]'', Edouard's journal provides an alternative voice to the narrator's.&quot; &quot;In 1946, when Pierre Herbert asked Gide which of his books he would choose if only one were to survive,&quot; Gide replied, 'I think it would be my ''Journal.'''&quot;  Beginning at the age of eighteen or nineteen, Gide kept a journal all of his life and when these were first made available to the public, they ran to thirteen hundred pages.&lt;ref&gt;''Journals: 1889-1913'' by André Gide, trans. by Justin O'Brien, p. xii.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Struggle for values===

&quot;Each volume that Gide wrote was intended to challenge itself, what had preceded it, and what could conceivably follow it. This characteristic, according to Daniel Moutote in his ''Cahiers de André Gide'' essay, is what makes Gide's work 'essentially modern': the 'perpetual renewal of the values by which one lives.'&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Quote taken from the article on ''André Gide'' in ''Contemporary Authors Online,'' 2003. Retrieved with library card October 2014.&lt;/ref&gt; Gide wrote in his ''Journal'' in 1930: &quot;The only drama that really interests me and that I should always be willing to depict anew, is the debate of the individual with whatever keeps him from being authentic, with whatever is opposed to his integrity, to his integration. Most often the obstacle is within him. And all the rest is merely accidental.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Journals: 1889-1913'' by André Gide, trans. by Justin O'Brien, p. xvii.&lt;/ref&gt;

As a whole, &quot;The works of André Gide reveal his passionate revolt against the restraints and conventions inherited from 19th-century France. He sought to uncover the authentic self beneath its contradictory masks.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Quote taken from the article on André Gide in the ''Encyclopedia of World Biography'', Dec. 12, 1998, Gale Pub. Retrieved with library card October 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Sexuality==
In his journal, Gide distinguishes between adult-attracted &quot;sodomites&quot; and boy-loving &quot;pederasts&quot;, categorizing himself as the latter.
{{quote|I call a pederast the man who, as the word indicates, falls in love with young boys. I call a sodomite (&quot;The word is sodomite, sir,&quot; said Verlaine to the judge who asked him if it were true that he was a sodomist) the man whose desire is addressed to mature men. […]
The pederasts, of whom I am one (why cannot I say this quite simply, without your immediately claiming to see a brag in my confession?), are much rarer, and the sodomites much more numerous, than I first thought. […] That such loves can spring up, that such relationships can be formed, it is not enough for me to say that this is natural; I maintain that it is good; each of the two finds exaltation, protection, a challenge in them; and I wonder whether it is for the youth or the elder man that they are more profitable.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Journals Of André Gide, Vol II 1914-1927.&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Gide|first1=Andre|title=The Journals Of André Gide, Vol II 1914-1927.|date=1948|publisher=Alfred A. Knopf|isbn=978-0252069307|pages=[https://archive.org/details/journalsofandreg031199mbp/page/n255 246]–247|url=https://archive.org/details/journalsofandreg031199mbp|accessdate=27 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

In the company of [[Oscar Wilde]], he had several sexual encounters with young boys abroad. {{quote|Wilde took a key out of his pocket and showed me into a tiny apartment of two rooms… The youths followed him, each of them wrapped in a burnous that hid his face. Then the guide left us and Wilde sent me into the further room with little Mohammed and shut himself up in the other with the [other boy]. Every time since then that I have sought after pleasure, it is the memory of that night I have pursued. […] My joy was unbounded, and I cannot imagine it greater, even if love had been added. 
How should there have been any question of love? How should I have allowed desire to dispose of my heart? No scruple clouded my pleasure and no remorse followed it. But what name then am I to give the rapture I felt as I clasped in my naked arms that perfect little body, so wild, so ardent, so sombrely lascivious? For a long time after Mohammed had left me, I remained in a state of passionate jubilation, and though I had already achieved pleasure five times with him, I renewed my ecstasy again and again, and when I got back to my room in the hotel, I prolonged its echoes until morning.&lt;ref name=&quot;If It Die: An Autobiography&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Gide|first1=Andre|title=If It Die: An Autobiography|date=1935|publisher=Random House|isbn=978-0375726064|pages=288|edition=New|url=https://books.google.com/?id=e0-TBQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT3&amp;lpg=PT3&amp;dq=Gide+A.+(1935).+If+It+Die:+An+Autobiography.+New+York:+Random+House.#v=onepage&amp;q=Gide%20A.%20(1935).%20If%20It%20Die%3A%20An%20Autobiography.%20New%20York%3A%20Random%20House.&amp;f=false|accessdate=27 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Gide's novel ''[[Corydon (book)|Corydon]]'', which he considered his most important work, erects a defense of [[pederasty]].  Depending on [[age of consent]] laws this practice is of course usually prohibited as [[child sexual abuse]] or [[statutory rape]].

==Bibliography==
{{main|Bibliography of André Gide}}

== See also ==
* [[Colonialism]]
* [[LGBT culture in Paris]]
* ''[[Mise en abyme]]''

==References==
'''Notes'''
{{Reflist}}

'''Sources'''
* [[Alan Sheridan]], ''André Gide: A Life in the Present.'' Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 1999.

==Further reading==
* Noel I. Garde [Edgar H. Leoni], ''Jonathan to Gide: The Homosexual in History''. New York:Vangard, 1964. '''OCLC''' [https://www.worldcat.org/title/jonathan-to-gide-the-homosexual-in-history/oclc/3149115 3149115]
* For a chronology of Gide's life, see pages 13–15 in Thomas Cordle, ''André Gide'' (The Griffin Authors Series). Twayne Publishers, Inc., 1969.
* For a detailed bibliography of Gide's writings and works about Gide, see pages 655-678 in Alan Sheridan, ''André Gide: A Life in the Present.'' Harvard, 1999.

==External links==
{{wikisource author}}
{{Commons category|André Gide}}
{{Wikiquote}}
* Website of the [http://www.fondation-catherine-gide.org/ ''Catherine Gide Foundation''], held by Catherine Gide, his daughter.
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20171016085651/http://www.andregide.org/ Center for Gidian Studies]
* {{Gutenberg author | id=2184 | name=André Gide}}
* {{FadedPage|id=Gide, André|name=André Gide|author=yes}}
* {{Internet Archive author |sname=André Gide |sopt=t}}
* {{Librivox author |id=11460}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20090913094434/http://www.gidiana.net/ Amis d'André Gide] ''in French''
* [http://www.gidiana.net/GA.htm Period newspaper articles on Gide] ''interface in French''
* [http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/literature/laureates/1947/ André  Gide, 1947 Nobel Laureate for Literature]
* [http://www.ljhammond.com/classics/cl3.htm#gide André Gide: A Brief Introduction]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20071006001903/http://www.societe-jersiaise.org/whitsco/mader1.htm Gide at Maderia in Jersey, 1901–7]
{{Bibliowiki}}
* {{PM20|FID=pe/006083}}

{{André Gide}}
{{Nobel Prize in Literature Laureates 1926-1950}}
{{Portal bar|Biography|France|Novels|LGBT}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Gide, Andre}}
[[Category:1869 births]]
[[Category:1951 deaths]]
[[Category:Writers from Paris]]
[[Category:French essayists]]
[[Category:French novelists]]
[[Category:French Protestants]]
[[Category:French travel writers]]
[[Category:French anti-communists]]
[[Category:French communists]]
[[Category:LGBT rights activists from France]]
[[Category:LGBT writers from France]]
[[Category:LGBT Nobel laureates]]
[[Category:Nobel laureates in Literature]]
[[Category:French Nobel laureates]]
[[Category:Western writers about Soviet Russia]]
[[Category:Modern pederasty]]
[[Category:Modernist writers]]
[[Category:Fyodor Dostoyevsky scholars]]
[[Category:Lycée Henri-IV alumni]]
[[Category:LGBT novelists]]
[[Category:Male essayists]]
[[Category:French male novelists]]
[[Category:French people of Italian descent]]
[[Category:French-language LGBT writers]]
[[Category:Anti-Stalinist left]]</text>
      <sha1>27n2zinnh1j354k8xuo4wxz4ak3pl09</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
