  <page>
    <title>Hercule Poirot</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1000</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942796918</id>
      <parentid>942364134</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-26T22:07:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Sheila1988</username>
        <id>30585864</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{redirect|Poirot|the television series|Agatha Christie's Poirot|the surname|Poirot (surname)}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2019}}
{{Infobox character
| name        = Hercule Poirot
| image       = DavidSuchet - Poirot.png
| caption     = [[David Suchet]] as Hercule Poirot in ''[[Agatha Christie's Poirot]]''
| creator     = [[Agatha Christie]]
| first       = ''[[The Mysterious Affair at Styles]]'' (1921)
| last        = ''[[Curtain (novel)|Curtain]]'' (1975)
| portrayer   = {{collapsible list| title = {{nbsp}} |[[Charles Laughton]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Francis L. Sullivan]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Austin Trevor]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Orson Welles]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Harold Huber]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Richard Bebb|Richard Williams]]&lt;br /&gt;[[John Malkovich]]&lt;br /&gt;[[José Ferrer]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Martin Gabel]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Tony Randall]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Albert Finney]]&lt;br /&gt;Dudley Jones&lt;br /&gt;[[Peter Ustinov]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Ian Holm]]&lt;br /&gt;[[David Suchet]]&lt;br /&gt;[[John Moffatt (actor)|John Moffatt]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Maurice Denham]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Peter Sallis]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Konstantin Raikin]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Alfred Molina]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Robert Powell]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Jason Durr]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Kenneth Branagh]]&lt;br /&gt;Shirō Itō (Takashi Akafuji)&lt;br /&gt;[[Mansai Nomura]] (Takeru Suguro)&lt;br /&gt;[[Tom Conti]]}}
| voice       = [[Kōtarō Satomi]]
| gender      = Male
| nationality = Belgian
| occupation  = [[Private investigator]]&lt;br&gt;[[Police officer]] (former occupation)
| family      = Jules-Louis Poirot (father)&lt;br&gt;Godelieve Poirot (mother)
| religion    = [[Catholic Church|Catholic]]
| lbl21       = Birth date and place
| data21      = c. 1854–1873&lt;ref&gt;Based on his subscription in the [[Belgian Police]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;[[Spa, Belgium|Spa]], [[Wallonia]], Belgium
}}

'''Hercule Poirot''' ({{IPAc-en|UK|ˈ|ɛər|k|juː|l|_|ˈ|p|w|ɑːr|oʊ}}, {{IPAc-en|US|h|ɜːr|ˈ|k|juː|l|_|p|w|ɑː|ˈ|r|oʊ}};&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.oxfordlearnersdictionaries.com/definition/english/hercule-poirot |title=Definition |publisher=Oxfordlearnersdictionaries.com |date= |accessdate=5 January 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; {{IPA-fr|ɛʁkyl pwaʁo|lang}}) is a fictional [[Belgians|Belgian]] detective created by [[Agatha Christie]]. Poirot is one of Christie's most famous and long-running characters, appearing in 33 novels, 2 plays (''[[Black Coffee (play)|Black Coffee]]'' and ''[[Alibi (play)|Alibi]]'' ), and more than 50 short stories published between 1920 and 1975.

Poirot has been portrayed on radio, in film and on television by various actors, including [[Austin Trevor]], [[John Moffatt (actor)|John Moffatt]], [[Albert Finney]], [[Peter Ustinov]], [[Ian Holm]], [[Tony Randall]], [[Alfred Molina]], [[Orson Welles]], [[David Suchet]], [[Kenneth Branagh]] and [[John Malkovich]].
{{toclimit}}

== Overview ==

=== Influences ===

Poirot's name was derived from two other fictional detectives of the time: [[Marie Belloc Lowndes]]' Hercule Popeau and Frank Howel Evans' Monsieur Poiret, a retired Belgian police officer living in London.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.litencyc.com/php/speople.php?rec=true&amp;UID=5054 |title=Agatha Christie (1890–1976) |accessdate=6 September 2006 |first=Chris|last= Willis|location=London Metropolitan University}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A more obvious influence on the early Poirot stories is that of [[Arthur Conan Doyle]]. In ''An Autobiography'', Christie states, &quot;I was still writing in the [[Sherlock Holmes]] tradition – eccentric detective, stooge assistant, with a [[Inspector Lestrade|Lestrade]]-type Scotland Yard detective, Inspector Japp&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Reproduced as the &quot;Introduction&quot; to {{harvnb|Christie|2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; For his part, Conan Doyle acknowledged basing his detective stories on the model of [[Edgar Allan Poe]]'s [[C. Auguste Dupin]] and his anonymous narrator, and basing his character Sherlock Holmes on [[Joseph Bell]], who in his use of &quot;[[wikt:ratiocination|ratiocination]]&quot; prefigured Poirot's reliance on his &quot;little grey cells&quot;.

Poirot also bears a striking resemblance to [[A. E. W. Mason]]'s fictional detective [[Inspector Hanaud]] of the French [[Sûreté]], who first appeared in the 1910 novel ''[[At the Villa Rose (novel)|At the Villa Rose]]'' and predates the first Poirot novel by ten years.

Unlike the models mentioned above, Christie's Poirot was clearly the result of her early development of the detective in her first book, written in 1916 and published in 1920. His Belgian nationality was interesting because of Belgium's occupation by Germany, which also provided a plausible explanation of why such a skilled detective would be out of work and available to solve mysteries at an [[English country house]].{{sfn|Christie|1939}} At the time of Christie's writing, it was considered patriotic to express sympathy towards the Belgians,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Horace Cornelius Peterson|title=Propaganda for War. The Campaign Against American Neutrality, 1914–1917|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=PkJbnQEACAAJ|year=1968|publisher=Kennikat}}&lt;/ref&gt; since the invasion of their country had constituted Britain's ''[[casus belli]]'' for entering World War I, and British wartime propaganda emphasised the &quot;[[Rape of Belgium]]&quot;.

=== Popularity ===

Poirot first appeared in ''[[The Mysterious Affair at Styles]]'' (published in 1920) and exited in ''[[Curtain (novel)|Curtain]]'' (published in 1975). Following the latter, Poirot was the only fictional character to receive an obituary on the front page of ''[[The New York Times]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://uk.agathachristie.com/story-explorer/characters/poirot/ |title=Poirot |publisher=Official Agatha Christie website |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100412131601/http://uk.agathachristie.com/story-explorer/characters/poirot/ |archivedate=12 April 2010 |accessdate=10 June 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Hercule Poirot is Dead; Famed Belgian Detective; Hercule Poirot, the Detective, Dies |first=Thomas |last=Lask |date=6 August 1975 |page=1 |work=[[The New York Times]] |url=https://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=FB0E10F63A5E157493C4A91783D85F418785F9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

By 1930 Agatha Christie found Poirot &quot;insufferable&quot;, and by 1960 she felt that he was a &quot;detestable, bombastic, tiresome, ego-centric little creep&quot;. Yet the public loved him and Christie refused to kill him off, claiming that it was her duty to produce what the public liked.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.litencyc.com/php/speople.php?rec=true&amp;UID=5054 |title=Agatha Christie (1890–1976) |date=16 July 2001 |accessdate=10 June 2013 |first=Chris |last=Willis |work=The Literary Encyclopedia |publisher=The Literary Dictionary Company |issn=1747-678X}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Appearance and proclivities ===

[[Captain Arthur Hastings]]'s first description of Poirot:

{{quote|He was hardly more than five feet four inches but carried himself with great dignity. His head was exactly the shape of an egg, and he always perched it a little on one side. His moustache was very stiff and military. Even if everything on his face was covered, the tips of moustache and the pink-tipped nose would be visible.

The neatness of his attire was almost incredible; I believe a speck of dust would have caused him more pain than a bullet wound. Yet this quaint dandified little man who, I was sorry to see, now limped badly, had been in his time one of the most celebrated members of the Belgian police.{{sfn|Christie|1939}}}}

Agatha Christie's initial description of Poirot in ''The Murder on the Orient Express'':

{{quote|By the step leading up into the sleeping-car stood a young French lieutenant, resplendent in uniform, conversing with a small man [Hercule Poirot] muffled up to the ears of whom nothing was visible but a pink-tipped nose and the two points of an upward-curled moustache.{{sfn|Christie|2011}}}}

In the later books, his limp is not mentioned, suggesting it may have been a temporary wartime injury. (In ''[[Curtain: Poirot's Last Case|Curtain]]'', Poirot admits he was wounded when he first came to England.) Poirot has green eyes that are repeatedly described as shining &quot;like a cat's&quot; when he is struck by a clever idea,&lt;ref&gt;E.g. &quot;For about ten minutes [Poirot] sat in dead silence... and all the time his eyes grew steadily greener&quot; {{harvnb|Christie|1939|loc=Chapter 5}}&lt;/ref&gt; and dark hair, which he dyes later in life. In ''Curtain'', he admits to Hastings that he wears a wig and a false moustache.&lt;ref&gt;as Hastings discovers in {{harvnb|Christie|1991|loc=Chapter 1}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, in many of his screen incarnations, he is bald or balding.

Frequent mention is made of his [[patent leather]] shoes, damage to which is frequently a source of misery for him, but comical for the reader.&lt;ref&gt;E.g. &quot;Hercule Poirot looked down at the tips of his patent-leather shoes and sighed.&quot; {{harvnb|Christie|1947a}}&lt;/ref&gt; Poirot's appearance, regarded as fastidious during his early career, later falls hopelessly out of fashion.&lt;ref&gt;E.g. &quot;And now here was the man himself. Really a most impossible person – the wrong clothes – button boots! an incredible moustache! Not his – Meredith Blake's kind of fellow at all.&quot; {{harvnb|Christie|2011|loc=Chapter 7}}&lt;/ref&gt; He employs [[pince-nez]] reading glasses.

Among Poirot's most significant personal attributes is the sensitivity of his stomach:

{{quote|The plane dropped slightly. ''&quot;Mon estomac,&quot;'' thought Hercule Poirot, and closed his eyes determinedly.{{sfn|Christie|2010|loc=Chapter 1}}}}

He suffers from [[sea sickness]],&lt;ref&gt;&quot;My stomach, it is not happy on the sea&quot;{{harvnb|Christie|1980|loc=Chapter 8, iv}}&lt;/ref&gt; and, in ''Death in the Clouds'', he states that his air sickness prevents him from being more alert at the time of the murder. Later in his life, we are told:

{{quote|Always a man who had taken his stomach seriously, he was reaping his reward in old age. Eating was not only a physical pleasure, it was also an intellectual research.{{sfn|Christie|2010|loc=Chapter 1}}}}

Poirot is extremely punctual and carries a [[pocket watch]] almost to the end of his career.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;he walked up the steps to the front door and pressed the bell, glancing as he did so at the neat wrist-watch which had at last replaced an old favourite – the large turnip-faced watch of early days. Yes, it was exactly nine-thirty. As ever, Hercule Poirot was exact to the minute.&quot; {{harvnb|Christie|2011b}}&lt;/ref&gt; He is also particular about his personal finances, preferring to keep a bank balance of 444&amp;nbsp;pounds, 4 shillings, and 4 pence.{{sfn|Christie|2013a}} Actor [[David Suchet]], who portrayed Poirot on television, said &quot;there's no question he's [[obsessive-compulsive]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/culture/2009/may/19/david-suchet-poirot-agatha-christie|title=Laura Barton meets David Suchet, star of Agatha Christie's Poirot|last=Barton|first=Laura|date=18 May 2009|work=The Guardian|access-date=25 November 2017|language=en-GB|issn=0261-3077}}&lt;/ref&gt; Film portrayer [[Kenneth Branagh]] said that he &quot;enjoyed finding the sort of obsessive-compulsive&quot; in Poirot.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.npr.org/2017/11/10/563378736/kenneth-branagh-on-his-meticulous-master-detective-role-in-murder-on-the-orient-|title=Kenneth Branagh On His Meticulous Master Detective Role In 'Murder On The Orient Express'|publisher=NPR |access-date=26 November 2017|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As mentioned in ''[[Curtain (novel)|Curtain]]'' and ''[[The Clocks]]'', he is fond of classical music, particularly [[Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart|Mozart]] and [[Johann Sebastian Bach|Bach]].

=== Methods ===

In ''The Mysterious Affair at Styles'', Poirot operates as a fairly conventional, clue-based and logical detective; reflected in his vocabulary by two common phrases: his use of &quot;[[Grey matter|the little grey cells]]&quot; and &quot;order and method&quot;. Hastings is irritated by the fact that Poirot sometimes conceals important details of his plans, as in ''The Big Four''.{{sfn|Christie|2004b}} In this novel, Hastings is kept in the dark throughout the climax. This aspect of Poirot is less evident in the later novels, partly because there is rarely a narrator to mislead.

In ''Murder on the Links,'' still largely dependent on clues himself, Poirot mocks a rival &quot;bloodhound&quot; detective who focuses on the traditional trail of clues established in detective fiction (e.g., Sherlock Holmes depending on [[footprints]], [[fingerprint]]s, and cigar ash). From this point on, Poirot establishes his psychological bona fides. Rather than painstakingly examining crime scenes, he enquires into the nature of the victim or the psychology of the murderer. He predicates his actions in the later novels on his underlying assumption that particular crimes are committed by particular types of people.

Poirot focuses on getting people to talk. In the early novels, he casts himself in the role of &quot;Papa Poirot&quot;, a benign confessor, especially to young women. In later works, Christie made a point of having Poirot supply false or misleading information about himself or his background to assist him in obtaining information.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;It has been said of Hercule Poirot by some of his friends and associates, at moments when he has maddened them most, that he prefers lies to truth and will go out of his way to gain his ends by elaborate false statements, rather than trust to the simple truth.&quot; {{harvnb|Christie|2011b|loc= Book One, Chapter 9}}&lt;/ref&gt; In ''The Murder of Roger Ackroyd'', Poirot speaks of a non-existent mentally disabled nephew&lt;ref&gt;E.g. &quot;After a careful study of the goods displayed in the window, Poirot entered and represented himself as desirous of purchasing a rucksack for a hypothetical nephew.&quot; ''Hickory Dickory Dock'', Chapter 13&lt;/ref&gt; to uncover information about homes for the mentally unfit. In ''Dumb Witness'', Poirot invents an elderly invalid mother as a pretence to investigate local nurses. In ''The Big Four'', Poirot pretends to have (and poses as) an identical twin brother named Achille: however, this brother was mentioned again in ''The Labours of Hercules''.{{sfn|Christie|2004b}}

&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;If I remember rightly – though my memory isn't what it was – you also had a brother called Achille, did you not?” Poirot's mind raced back over the details of Achille Poirot's career. Had all that really happened? &quot;Only for a short space of time,&quot; he replied.{{sfn|Christie|1947|p=}}&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Poirot is also willing to appear more foreign or vain in an effort to make people underestimate him. He admits as much:

&lt;blockquote&gt;It is true that I can speak the exact, the idiomatic English. But, my friend, to speak the broken English is an enormous asset. It leads people to despise you. They say – a foreigner – he can't even speak English properly. ... Also I boast! An Englishman he says often, &quot;A fellow who thinks as much of himself as that cannot be worth much.&quot; ... And so, you see, I put people off their guard.{{sfn|Christie|2006b|loc=final chapter}}&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In later novels, Christie often uses the word ''mountebank'' when characters describe Poirot, showing that he has successfully passed himself off as a [[charlatan]] or fraud.

Poirot's investigating techniques assist him solving cases; &quot;For in the long run, either through a lie, or through truth, people were bound to give themselves away...&quot;{{sfn|Christie|2005|loc=Chapter 18}} At the end, Poirot usually reveals his description of the sequence of events and his deductions to a room of suspects, often leading to the culprit's apprehension.

== Life ==
[[File:2011-07-26 Belgique - Ellezelles - Hercule Poirot 002.jpg|thumb|230px|Statuette of Poirot in [[Ellezelles]], [[Belgium]]]]

===Origins===
Christie was purposely vague about Poirot's origins, as he is thought to be an elderly man even in the early novels. In ''An Autobiography,'' she admitted that she already imagined him to be an old man in 1920. At the time, however, she had no idea she would write works featuring him for decades to come.

A brief passage in ''The Big Four'' provides original information about Poirot's birth or at least childhood in or near the town of [[Spa, Belgium]]: &quot;But we did not go into Spa itself. We left the main road and wound into the leafy fastnesses of the hills, till we reached a little hamlet and an isolated white villa high on the hillside.&quot;{{sfn|Christie|2004b|loc=Chapter 16}} Christie strongly implies that this &quot;quiet retreat in the [[Ardennes]]&quot;{{sfn|Christie|2004b|loc=Chapter 17}} near Spa is the location of the Poirot family home.
 
An alternative tradition holds that Poirot was born in the village of [[Ellezelles]] (province of Hainaut, Belgium).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://magazine.bellesdemeures.com/en/luxury/lifestyle/province-hainaut-village-ellezelles-adopts-detective-hercule-poirot-article-27759.html|title=In the province of Hainaut, the village of Ellezelles adopts detective Hercule Poirot|website=Belles Demeures|language=en-gb|access-date=17 December 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; A few memorials dedicated to Hercule Poirot can be seen in the centre of this village. There appears to be no reference to this in Christie's writings, but the town of Ellezelles cherishes a copy of Poirot's birth certificate in a local memorial 'attesting' Poirot's birth, naming his father and mother as Jules-Louis Poirot and Godelieve Poirot.

Christie wrote that Poirot is a Catholic by birth,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Hercule Poirot was a Catholic by birth.&quot; {{harvnb|Christie|1947a}}&lt;/ref&gt; but not much is described about his later religious convictions, except sporadic references to his &quot;going to church&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;In ''[[Taken at the Flood]]'', Book II, Chapter 6 Poirot goes into church to pray and happens across a suspect with whom he briefly discusses ideas of sin and confession. {{harvnb|Christie|1948}}&lt;/ref&gt; Christie provides little information regarding Poirot's childhood, only mentioning in ''Three Act Tragedy'' that he comes from a large family with little wealth, and has at least one younger sister. Apart from French and English, Poirot is also fluent in German.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Christie|2011|loc=Chapter 12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Policeman ===

&lt;blockquote&gt;Gustave ... was not a policeman. I have dealt with policemen all my life and I ''know''. He could pass as a detective to an outsider but not to a man who was a policeman himself.

: — Hercule Poirot {{harvnb|Christie|1947c}}&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Hercule Poirot was active in the [[Brussels]] police force by 1893.{{sfn|Christie|2009b|loc=Chapter 15}} Very little mention is made about this part of his life, but in &quot;[[The Labours of Hercules#The Nemean Lion|The Nemean Lion]]&quot; (1939) Poirot refers to a Belgian case of his in which &quot;a wealthy soap manufacturer ... poisoned his wife in order to be free to marry his secretary&quot;. As Poirot was often misleading about his past to gain information, the truthfulness of that statement is unknown; it does however scare off a would be killer of his wife.

In the short story [[Poirot's Early Cases#The Chocolate Box|&quot;The Chocolate Box&quot;]] (1923), Poirot reveals to [[Captain Arthur Hastings]] an account of what he considers to be his only failure. Poirot admits that he has failed to solve a crime &quot;innumerable&quot; times:

&lt;blockquote&gt;I have been called in too late. Very often another, working towards the same goal, has arrived there first. Twice I have been struck down with illness just as I was on the point of success.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Nevertheless, he regards the 1893 case in &quot;The Chocolate Box&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;The date is given in {{harvnb|Christie|2009b|loc=Chapter 15}}&lt;/ref&gt; as his only actual failure of detection. Again, Poirot is not reliable as a narrator of his personal history and there is no evidence that Christie sketched it out in any depth. During his police career Poirot shot a man who was firing from a roof into the public below.{{sfn|Christie|1975|loc=Postscript}} In ''[[Lord Edgware Dies]]'', Poirot reveals that he learned to read writing upside down during his police career. Around that time he met Xavier Bouc, director of the [[Compagnie Internationale des Wagons-Lits]]. Poirot also became a uniformed director, working on trains.

Inspector Japp offers some insight into Poirot's career with the Belgian police when introducing him to a colleague:

&lt;blockquote&gt;You've heard me speak of Mr Poirot? It was in 1904 he and I worked together – the Abercrombie forgery case – you remember he was run down in Brussels. Ah, those were the days Moosier. Then, do you remember &quot;Baron&quot; Altara? There was a pretty rogue for you! He eluded the clutches of half the police in Europe. But we nailed him in Antwerp – thanks to Mr. Poirot here.{{sfn|Christie|1939|loc=Chapter 7}}&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In ''The Double Clue,'' Poirot mentions that he was Chief of Police of Brussels, until &quot;the Great War&quot; (World War I) forced him to leave for England. (In ''[[The Mysterious  Affair at Styles]]'' Poirot had retired at age 55 in 1905)

=== Private detective ===

&lt;blockquote&gt;I had called in at my friend Poirot's rooms to find him sadly overworked. So much had he become the rage that every rich woman who had mislaid a bracelet or lost a pet kitten rushed to secure the services of the great Hercule Poirot.{{sfn|Christie|2013b}}&lt;/blockquote&gt;

During World War I, Poirot left Belgium for England as a [[refugee]], although he returned a few times. On 16 July 1916 he again met his lifelong friend, Captain Arthur Hastings, and solved the first of his cases to be published, ''The Mysterious Affair at Styles''. It is clear that Hastings and Poirot are already friends when they meet in Chapter 2 of the novel, as Hastings tells Cynthia that he has not seen him for &quot;some years&quot;. Particulars such as the date of 1916 for the case and that Hastings had met Poirot in Belgium, are given in ''Curtain: Poirot's Last Case'', Chapter 1.  After that case, Poirot apparently came to the attention of the British secret service and undertook cases for the British government, including foiling the attempted abduction of the [[Prime Minister of Britain|Prime Minister]].&lt;ref&gt;Recounted in {{harvnb|Christie|2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Readers were told that the British authorities had learned of Poirot's keen investigative ability from certain members of [[Belgian Royal Family|Belgium's royal family]].

{{multiple image
&lt;!-- Layout --&gt;
 | align             = right
 | direction         = &lt;!-- horizontal (default), vertical --&gt;
 | background color  = &lt;!-- box background --&gt;
 | total_width       = &lt;!-- total width of all the displayed images in pixels (an integer, omit &quot;px&quot; suffix) --&gt;
 | caption_align     = &lt;!-- left (default), center, right --&gt;

 | image1            = Florin Court (2).jpg
 | width1            = 200
 | height1           = 200
 | alt1              = 
 | link1             = 
 | caption1          =

 | image2            = Florin Court-13909277428.jpg
 | width2            = 200
 | height2           = 200
 | alt2              = 
 | link2             = 
 | caption2          =

 | footer_background = 
 | footer_align      = 
 | footer            = [[Florin Court]] became the fictional residence of Agatha Christie's Poirot, known as &quot;Whitehaven Mansions&quot;
}}
After the war Poirot became a private detective and began undertaking civilian cases. He moved into what became both his home and work address, Flat 203 at 56B Whitehaven Mansions. Hastings first visits the flat when he returns to England in June 1935 from Argentina in ''[[The A.B.C. Murders]]'', Chapter 1. The TV programmes place this in [[Florin Court]], Charterhouse Square, in the wrong part of London.  According to Hastings, it was chosen by Poirot &quot;entirely on account of its strict geometrical appearance and proportion&quot; and described as the &quot;newest type of service flat&quot;. (The Florin Court building was actually built in 1936, decades after Poirot fictionally moved in.) His first case in this period was &quot;The Affair at the Victory Ball&quot;, which allowed Poirot to enter high society and begin his career as a private detective.

Between the world wars, Poirot travelled all over Europe, Africa, Asia, and half of South America investigating crimes and solving murders. Most of his cases occurred during this time and he was at the height of his powers at this point in his life. In ''The Murder on the Links'', the Belgian pits his grey cells against a French murderer. In the Middle East, he solved the cases ''Death on the Nile'' and ''Murder in Mesopotamia'' with ease and even survived ''An Appointment with Death''. As he passed through Eastern Europe on his return trip, he solved ''The Murder on the Orient Express''. However he did not travel to North America, the West Indies, the Caribbean or Oceania, probably to avoid sea sickness.

&lt;blockquote&gt;It is this villainous sea that troubles me! The ''mal de mer'' – it is horrible suffering!&lt;ref&gt;Poirot, in {{harvnb|Christie|2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

It was during this time he met the Countess Vera Rossakoff, a glamorous jewel thief. The history of the Countess is, like Poirot's, steeped in mystery. She claims to have been a member of the Russian aristocracy before the Russian Revolution and suffered greatly as a result, but how much of that story is true is an open question. Even Poirot acknowledges that Rossakoff offered wildly varying accounts of her early life. Poirot later became smitten with the woman and allowed her to escape justice.&lt;ref&gt;Cassatis, John (1979). ''The Diaries of A. Christie''. London.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;It is the misfortune of small, precise men always to hanker after large and flamboyant women. Poirot had never been able to rid himself of the fatal fascination that the Countess held for him.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The Capture of Cerebus&quot; (1947). The first sentence quoted is also a close paraphrase of something said to Poirot by Hastings in Chapter 18 of ''The Big Four''{{harvnb|Christie|2004b}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Although letting the Countess escape was morally questionable, it was not uncommon. In ''The Nemean Lion'', Poirot sided with the criminal, Miss Amy Carnaby, allowing her to evade prosecution by blackmailing his client Sir Joseph Hoggins, who, Poirot discovered, had plans to commit murder. Poirot even sent Miss Carnaby two hundred pounds as a final payoff prior to the conclusion of her dog kidnapping campaign. In ''The Murder of Roger Ackroyd'', Poirot allowed the murderer to escape justice through suicide and then withheld the truth to spare the feelings of the murderer's relatives. In ''The Augean Stables'', he helped the government to cover up vast corruption. In ''Murder on the Orient Express'', Poirot allowed the murderers to go free after discovering that twelve different people participated in the murder, each one stabbing the victim in a darkened carriage after drugging him into unconsciousness so that there is no way for anyone to definitively determine which of them actually delivered the killing blow. The victim had been committed a disgusting crime which had led to the deaths of at least five people. There was no question of his guilt, but he had been acquitted in America in a miscarriage of justice. Considering it poetic justice that twelve jurors had acquitted him and twelve people had stabbed him, Poirot produced an alternative sequence of events to explain the death involving an unknown additional passenger on the train, with the medical examiner agreeing to doctor his own report to support this theory.

After his cases in the Middle East, Poirot returned to Britain. Apart from some of the so-called &quot;Labours of Hercules&quot; (see next section) he very rarely went abroad during his later career. He moved into Styles Court towards the end of his life.

While Poirot was usually paid handsomely by clients, he was also known to take on cases that piqued his curiosity, although they did not pay well.

Poirot shows a love of steam trains, which Christie contrasts with Hastings' love of autos: this is shown in ''[[Poirot's Early Cases|The Plymouth Express]]'', ''[[The Mystery of the Blue Train]]'', ''Murder on the Orient Express'', and ''The ABC Murders'' (in the TV series, steam trains are seen in nearly all of the episodes).

=== Retirement ===

&lt;blockquote&gt;That’s the way of it. Just a case or two, just one case more – the Prima Donna’s farewell performance won’t be in it with yours, Poirot.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Christie|2006a}} Dr. Burton in the Preface&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Confusion surrounds Poirot's retirement. Most of the cases covered by Poirot's private detective agency take place before his retirement to grow [[Squash (plant)|marrows]], at which time he solves ''The Murder of Roger Ackroyd''. It has been said that the twelve cases related in ''The Labours of Hercules'' (1947) must refer to a different retirement, but the fact that Poirot specifically says that he intends to grow marrows indicates that these stories also take place before ''Roger Ackroyd'', and presumably Poirot closed his agency once he had completed them. There is specific mention in &quot;The Capture of Cerberus&quot; of the twenty-year gap between Poirot's previous meeting with Countess Rossakoff and this one. If the ''Labours'' precede the events in ''Roger Ackroyd'', then the Ackroyd case must have taken place around twenty years ''later'' than it was published, and so must any of the cases that refer to it. One alternative would be that having failed to grow marrows once, Poirot is determined to have another go, but this is specifically denied by Poirot himself.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Christie|2004a|loc=Chapter 13}} in response to the suggestion that he might take up gardening in his retirement, Poirot answers &quot;Once the vegetable marrows, yes – but never again&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; Also, in &quot;The Erymanthian Boar&quot;, a character is said to have been turned out of Austria by the [[Nazism|Nazis]], implying that the events of ''[[The Labours of Hercules]]'' took place after 1937. Another alternative would be to suggest that the Preface to the ''Labours'' takes place at one date but that the labours are completed over a matter of twenty years. None of the explanations is especially attractive.

In terms of a rudimentary chronology, Poirot speaks of retiring to grow marrows in Chapter 18 of ''The Big Four''{{sfn|Christie|2004b|loc=Chapter 18}} (1927) which places that novel out of published order before ''Roger Ackroyd''. He declines to solve a case for the Home Secretary because he is retired in Chapter One of ''Peril at End House'' (1932). He is certainly retired at the time of ''Three Act Tragedy'' (1935) but he does not enjoy his retirement and repeatedly takes cases thereafter when his curiosity is engaged. He continues to employ his secretary, Miss Lemon, at the time of the cases retold in ''Hickory Dickory Dock'' and ''Dead Man's Folly'', which take place in the mid-1950s. It is therefore better to assume that Christie provided no authoritative chronology for Poirot's retirement, but assumed that he could either be an active detective, a consulting detective, or a retired detective as the needs of the immediate case required.

One consistent element about Poirot's retirement is that his fame declines during it, so that in the later novels he is often disappointed when characters (especially younger characters) recognise neither him nor his name:

&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;I should, perhaps, Madame, tell you a little more about myself. I am ''Hercule Poirot''.&quot;&lt;br/&gt;

The revelation left Mrs Summerhayes unmoved.&lt;br/&gt;

&quot;What a lovely name,&quot; she said kindly. &quot;Greek, isn't it?&quot;{{sfn|Christie|1952|loc=Chapter 4}}&lt;/blockquote&gt;

=== Post–World War II ===
{{Quote | He, I knew, was not likely to be far from his headquarters. The time when cases had drawn him from one end of England to the other was past. |  Hastings{{Sfn |Christie|2004b|loc = Chapter 1}}{{Page needed | date = August 2014}}}}

Poirot is less active during the cases that take place at the end of his career. Beginning with ''Three Act Tragedy'' (1934), Christie had perfected during the inter-war years a subgenre of Poirot novel in which the detective himself spent much of the first third of the novel on the periphery of events. In novels such as ''Taken at the Flood'', ''[[After the Funeral]]'', and ''Hickory Dickory Dock'', he is even less in evidence, frequently passing the duties of main interviewing detective to a subsidiary character. In ''Cat Among the Pigeons'', Poirot's entrance is so late as to be almost an afterthought. Whether this was a reflection of his age or of Christie's distaste for him, is impossible to assess. ''[[Crooked House]]'' (1949) and ''[[Ordeal by Innocence]]'' (1957), which could easily have been Poirot novels, represent a logical endpoint of the general diminution of his presence in such works.

Towards the end of his career, it becomes clear that Poirot's retirement is no longer a convenient fiction.  He assumes a genuinely inactive lifestyle during which he concerns himself with studying famous unsolved cases of the past and reading detective novels. He even writes a book about mystery fiction in which he deals sternly with [[Edgar Allan Poe]] and [[Wilkie Collins]].{{sfn|Christie | 2011c |loc =Chapter 1}}{{Page needed | date = August 2014}}  In the absence of a more appropriate puzzle, he solves such inconsequential domestic riddles as the presence of three pieces of orange peel in his umbrella stand.{{sfn|Christie | 2006a |loc=Chapter 14}} {{Page needed | date = August 2014}}

Poirot (and, it is reasonable to suppose, his creator){{efn | In ''The Pale Horse'', Chapter 1, the novel's narrator, Mark Easterbrook, disapprovingly describes a typical &quot;Chelsea girl&quot;{{Sfn | Christie |1961}}{{Page needed | date = August 2014}} in much the same terms that Poirot uses in Chapter 1 of ''Third Girl'', suggesting that the condemnation of fashion is authorial.{{Sfn | Christie | 2011c}}{{Page needed | date = August 2014}}}} becomes increasingly bemused by the vulgarism of the up-and-coming generation's young people. In ''Hickory Dickory Dock'', he investigates the strange goings on in a student hostel, while in ''Third Girl'' (1966) he is forced into contact with the smart set of Chelsea youths. In the growing drug and pop culture of the sixties, he proves himself once again, but has become heavily reliant on other investigators (especially the [[private investigator]], Mr. Goby) who provide him with the clues that he can no longer gather for himself.
{{Quote | ''You're too old''.  Nobody told me you were so old. I really don't want to be rude but – there it is. ''You're too old''. I'm really very sorry. | Norma Restarick to Poirot in ''Third Girl'', Chapter 1{{Sfn |Christie | 2011c|loc=Chapter 1}}{{Page needed | date = August 2014}}}}

Notably, during this time his physical characteristics also change dramatically, and by the time Arthur Hastings meets Poirot again in ''Curtain'', he looks very different from his previous appearances, having become thin with age and with obviously dyed hair.

=== Death ===

On the ITV television series, Poirot died in October 1949&lt;ref&gt;The extensive letter addressed to Hastings where he explains how he solved the case is dated from October 1949 (&quot;Curtain&quot;, 2013)&lt;/ref&gt; from complications of a heart condition at the end of ''[[Curtain (novel)|Curtain: Poirot's Last Case]]''. This took place at Styles Court, scene of his first English case in 1916. In Christie's novels, he lived into the late 1960s, perhaps even until 1975 when ''Curtain'' was published. In both the novel and the television adaptation, he had moved his [[amyl nitrite]] pills out of his own reach, possibly because of guilt. He thereby became the murderer in ''Curtain'', although it was for the benefit of others. Poirot himself noted that he wanted to kill his victim shortly before his own death so that he could avoid succumbing to the arrogance of the murderer, concerned that he might come to view himself as entitled to kill those whom he deemed necessary to eliminate.

The &quot;murderer&quot; that he was hunting had never actually killed anyone, but he had manipulated others to kill for him, subtly and psychologically manipulating the moments where others desire to commit murder so that they carry out the crime when they might otherwise dismiss their thoughts as nothing more than a momentary passion. Poirot thus was forced to kill the man himself, as otherwise he would have continued his actions and never been officially convicted, as he did not legally do anything wrong. It is revealed at the end of ''Curtain'' that he fakes his need for a wheelchair to fool people into believing that he is suffering from [[arthritis]], to give the impression that he is more infirm than he is. His last recorded words are &quot;''Cher ami!''&quot;, spoken to Hastings as the Captain left his room. (The TV adaptation adds that as Poirot is dying alone, he whispers out his final prayer to God in these words: &quot;Forgive me... forgive...&quot;)&lt;ref name=&quot;Suchet&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/tvshowbiz/article-2506890/Poirot-finale-My-agony-Poirot-drew-breath-David-Suchet.html |title='My agony as Poirot drew out his last breath', by DAVID SUCHET: Shock as the little Belgian sensationally turns out to be the killer in his own final case (SPOILER) |last=Suchet |first=David |authorlink=David Suchet |newspaper=[[Daily Mail]] |date=13 November 2013 |accessdate=30 September 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Poirot was buried at Styles, and his funeral was arranged by his best friend Hastings and Hastings' daughter Judith. Hastings reasoned, &quot;Here was the spot where he had lived when he first came to this country. He was to lie here at the last.&quot;

Poirot's actual death and funeral occurred in ''Curtain'', years after his retirement from active investigation, but it was not the first time that Hastings attended the funeral of his best friend. In ''The Big Four'' (1927), Poirot feigned his death and subsequent funeral to launch a surprise attack on the Big Four.

== Recurring characters ==

=== Captain Arthur Hastings ===
{{Main|Arthur Hastings}}

Hastings, a former British Army officer, first meets Poirot during Poirot's years as a police officer in Belgium and almost immediately after they both arrive in England. He becomes Poirot's lifelong friend and appears in many cases. Poirot regards Hastings as a poor private detective, not particularly intelligent, yet helpful in his way of being fooled by the criminal or seeing things the way the average man would see them and for his tendency to unknowingly &quot;stumble&quot; onto the truth.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |year=2000 |first=Bunson |last=Matthew |title=Hastings, Captain Arthur, O.B.E. |encyclopedia=The Complete Christie: An Agatha Christie Encyclopedia |publisher=Pocket Books |location=New York}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hastings marries and has four children – two sons and two daughters. As a loyal, albeit somewhat naïve companion, Hastings is to Poirot what Watson is to Sherlock Holmes.

Hastings is capable of great bravery and courage, facing death unflinchingly when confronted by ''The Big Four'' and displaying unwavering loyalty towards Poirot. However, when forced to choose between Poirot and his wife in that novel, he initially chooses to betray Poirot to protect his wife. Later, though, he tells Poirot to draw back and escape the trap.

The two are an airtight team until Hastings meets and marries Dulcie Duveen, a beautiful music hall performer half his age, after investigating the ''Murder on the Links''. They later emigrate to Argentina, leaving Poirot behind as a &quot;very unhappy old man&quot;. However, Poirot and Hastings reunite during the novels ''The Big Four'', ''Peril at End House'', ''The ABC Murders'', ''Lord Edgware Dies'', and ''Dumb Witness,'' when Hastings arrives in England for business, with Poirot noting in ''ABC Murders'' that he enjoys having Hastings over because he feels that he always has his most interesting cases with Hastings. The two collaborate for the final time in ''Curtain: Poirot's Last Case'', when the seemingly-crippled Poirot asks Hastings to assist him in his final case. When the killer they are tracking nearly manipulates Hastings into committing murder, Poirot describes this in his final farewell letter to Hastings as the catalyst that prompted him to eliminate the man himself, as Poirot ''knew'' that his friend was not a murderer and refused to let a man capable of manipulating Hastings in such a manner go on.

=== Mrs Ariadne Oliver ===
{{Main|Ariadne Oliver}}
Detective novelist Ariadne Oliver is Agatha Christie's humorous self-caricature. Like Christie, she is not overly fond of the detective whom she is most famous for creating–in Ariadne's case, Finnish sleuth [[Sven Hjerson]]. We never learn anything about her husband, but we do know that she hates alcohol and public appearances and has a great fondness for apples until she is put off them by the events of ''[[Hallowe'en Party]]''. She also has a habit of constantly changing her hairstyle, and in every appearance by her much is made of her clothes and hats. Her maid Maria prevents the public adoration from becoming too much of a burden on her employer, but does nothing to prevent her from becoming too much of a burden on others.

She has authored more than 56 novels and greatly dislikes people modifying her characters. She is the only one in Poirot's universe to have noted that &quot;It’s not natural for five or six people to be on the spot when B is murdered and all have a motive for killing B.&quot; She first met Poirot in the story ''Cards on the Table'' and has bothered him ever since.

=== Miss Felicity Lemon ===
Poirot's secretary, Miss Felicity Lemon, has few human weaknesses. The only mistakes she makes within the series are a typing error during the events of ''Hickory Dickory Dock'' and the mis-mailing of an electricity bill, although she was worried about strange events surrounding her sister at the time. Poirot described her as being &quot;Unbelievably ugly and incredibly efficient. Anything that she mentioned as worth consideration usually was worth consideration.&quot; She is an expert on nearly everything and plans to create the perfect filing system. She also worked for the government statistician-turned-philanthropist [[Parker Pyne]]. Whether this was during one of Poirot's numerous retirements or before she entered his employ is unknown.{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}} In ''The Agatha Christie Hour'', she was portrayed by British actress Angela Easterling, while in ''[[Agatha Christie's Poirot]]'' she was portrayed by [[Pauline Moran]]. On a number of occasions, she joins Poirot in his inquiries or seeks out answers alone at his request.

=== Chief Inspector James Harold Japp ===
{{Main|Inspector Japp}}

Japp is a [[Scotland Yard]] Inspector and appears in many of the stories trying to solve cases that Poirot is working on. Japp is outgoing, loud, and sometimes inconsiderate by nature, and his relationship with the refined Belgian is one of the stranger aspects of Poirot's world. He first met Poirot in Belgium in 1904, during the Abercrombie Forgery. Later that year they joined forces again to hunt down a criminal known as Baron Altara. They also meet in England where Poirot often helps Japp and lets him take credit in return for special favours. These favours usually entail Poirot being supplied with other interesting cases.&lt;ref&gt;Captain Arthur Hastings {{harvnb|Christie|2004b|loc=Chapter 9}}&lt;/ref&gt; In ''[[Agatha Christie's Poirot]]'', Japp was portrayed by [[Philip Jackson (actor)|Philip Jackson]]. In the film, ''[[Thirteen at Dinner (film)|Thirteen at Dinner]]'' (1985), adapted from ''Lord Edgware Dies'', the role of Japp was taken by the actor [[David Suchet]], who would later star as Poirot in the ITV adaptations.

== Major novels ==
{{Main|Hercule Poirot in literature}}
The Poirot books take readers through the whole of his life in England, from the first book (''The Mysterious Affair at Styles''), where he is a refugee staying at Styles, to the last Poirot book (''Curtain''), where he visits Styles before his death. In between, Poirot solves cases outside England as well, including his most famous case, ''Murder on the Orient Express'' (1934).

Hercule Poirot became famous in 1926 with the publication of ''[[The Murder of Roger Ackroyd]]'', whose surprising solution proved controversial. The novel is still among the most famous of all detective novels: [[Edmund Wilson]] alludes to it in the title of his well-known attack on detective fiction, &quot;Who Cares Who Killed Roger Ackroyd?&quot; Aside from ''Roger Ackroyd'', the most critically acclaimed Poirot novels appeared from 1932 to 1942, including ''[[Murder on the Orient Express]]'' (1934); ''[[The A.B.C. Murders|The ABC Murders]]'' (1935)''; [[Cards on the Table]]'' (1936); and ''[[Death on the Nile]]'' (1937), a tale of multiple homicide upon a Nile steamer. ''Death on the Nile'' was judged by detective novelist [[John Dickson Carr]] to be among the ten greatest mystery novels of all time&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books/about/Omnibus_IV.html?id=4dY0hHqQ4lgC|title=Omnibus IV: The Ancient World|last=Veith|first=Gene Edward|last2=Wilson|first2=Douglas|last3=Fischer|first3=G. Tyler|publisher=Veritas Press|year=2009|isbn=9781932168860|location=|pages=460}}&lt;/ref&gt;.

The 1942 novel ''[[Five Little Pigs]]'' (a.k.a. ''Murder in Retrospect''), in which Poirot investigates a murder committed sixteen years before, by analysing various accounts of the tragedy, is a ''[[Rashomon (movie)|Rashomon]]''-like performance. In his analysis of this book, critic and mystery novelist [[Robert Barnard]] referred to it as &quot;the best Christie of all&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Barnard (1980), p. 85&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2014, the Poirot canon was added to by [[Sophie Hannah]], the first author to be commissioned by the Christie estate to write an original story. The novel was called ''[[The Monogram Murders]]'', and was set in the late 1920s, placing it chronologically between ''[[The Mystery of the Blue Train]]'' and ''[[Peril at End House]]''. A second Hannah-penned Poirot came out in 2016, called ''[[Closed Casket (novel)|Closed Casket]]'', and a third, ''[[The Mystery of Three Quarters]]'', in 2018.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://link.galegroup.com/apps/doc/A461530204/ITOF?u=mlin_c_worpoly&amp;sid=ITOF&amp;xid=42ac4a2a.|title=Hannah, Sophie. Closed Casket: The New Hercule Poirot Mystery|website=link.galegroup.com|language=en|access-date=24 May 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Portrayals ==
{{in popular culture|date=December 2016}}{{more citations needed|date=December 2016}}

=== Stage ===

The first actor to portray Hercule Poirot was [[Charles Laughton]]. He appeared on the West End in 1928 in the play ''[[Alibi (play)|Alibi]]'' which had been adapted by [[Michael Morton (dramatist)|Michael Morton]] from the novel ''The Murder of Roger Ackroyd''. 
In 1932 the play was performed as ''The Fatal Alibi'' on Broadway.

=== Film ===

==== Austin Trevor ====

[[Austin Trevor]] debuted the role of Poirot on screen in the 1931 British film ''[[Alibi (1931 film)|Alibi]]''. The film was based on the stage play. Trevor reprised the role of Poirot twice, in ''[[Black Coffee (1931 film)|Black Coffee]]'' and ''[[Lord Edgware Dies (1934 film)|Lord Edgware Dies]]''. Trevor said once that he was probably cast as Poirot simply because he could do a French accent.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.poirot.us/ptvfilm.html At the Hercule Poirot Central website] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080430024329/http://www.poirot.us/ptvfilm.html |date=30 April 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Notably, Trevor's Poirot did not have a moustache. [[Leslie S. Hiscott]] directed the first two films, and [[Henry Edwards (actor)|Henry Edwards]] took over for the third.

==== Tony Randall ====

[[Tony Randall]] portrayed Poirot in ''[[The Alphabet Murders]]'', a 1965 film also known as ''The ABC Murders''. This was more a satire of Poirot than a straightforward adaptation, and was greatly changed from the original. Much of the story, set in modern times, was played for comedy, with Poirot investigating the murders while evading the attempts by Hastings ([[Robert Morley]]) and the police to get him out of England and back to Belgium.

==== Albert Finney ====
[[File:Albert Finney plays Poirot.jpg|thumb|[[Albert Finney]] playing Poirot in the 1974 film, ''[[Murder on the Orient Express (1974 film)|Murder on the Orient Express]]'']]

[[Albert Finney]] played Poirot in 1974 in the cinematic version of ''[[Murder on the Orient Express (1974 film)|Murder on the Orient Express]]''. As of today, Finney is the only actor to receive an [[Academy Awards|Academy Award]] nomination for playing Poirot, though he did not win.
{{clear}}

==== Peter Ustinov ====
[[File:Ustinov is Poirot.jpg|thumb|[[Peter Ustinov]] as Poirot in a [[Evil Under the Sun (1982 film)|1982 adaptation]] of the novel ''[[Evil Under the Sun]]'']]

[[Peter Ustinov]] played Poirot six times, starting with ''[[Death on the Nile (1978 film)|Death on the Nile]]'' (1978). He reprised the role in ''[[Evil Under the Sun (1982 film)|Evil Under the Sun]]'' (1982) and ''[[Appointment with Death (film)|Appointment with Death]]'' (1988).

Christie's daughter [[Rosalind Hicks]] observed Ustinov during a rehearsal and said, &quot;''That's'' not Poirot! He isn't at all like that!&quot; Ustinov overheard and remarked &quot;He is ''now!''&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|url=http://www.mapdig.com/?title=Hercule_Poirot |title=Hercule Poirot |publisher=Map dig |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140517152810/http://www.mapdig.com/?title=Hercule_Poirot |archivedate=17 May 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

He appeared again as Poirot in three [[made-for-television]] movies: ''[[Thirteen at Dinner (film)|Thirteen at Dinner]]'' (1985), ''[[Dead Man's Folly (film)|Dead Man's Folly]]'' (1986), and ''[[Murder in Three Acts]]'' (1986). Earlier adaptations were set during the time in which the novels were written, but these TV movies were set in the contemporary era. The first of these was based on ''[[Lord Edgware Dies]]'' and was made by [[Warner Bros.]]  It also starred [[Faye Dunaway]], with David Suchet as Inspector Japp, just before Suchet began to play Poirot. David Suchet considers his performance as Japp to be &quot;possibly the worst performance of [his] career&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | url = http://www.strandmag.com/suchet.htm | title = Interview | first = David | last = Suchet | newspaper = Strand mag | access-date = 5 December 2006 | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20150530010249/http://www.strandmag.com/suchet.htm | archive-date = 30 May 2015 | url-status = dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Kenneth Branagh ====

In 2017, Kenneth Branagh directed and starred in [[Murder on the Orient Express (2017 film)|a 2017 film adaptation of ''Murder on the Orient Express'']]. Branagh has been confirmed to return for a new film version of ''[[Death on the Nile (2020 film)|Death on the Nile]]'', set for a 2020 release.

==== Other ====

* [[Anatoly Ravikovich]], ''Zagadka Endkhauza'' (''End House Mystery'') (1989; based on &quot;Peril at End House&quot;)

=== Television ===

==== David Suchet ====

[[David Suchet]] starred as Poirot in the [[ITV (TV network)|ITV]] series ''[[Agatha Christie's Poirot]]'' from 1989 until June 2013, when he announced that he was bidding farewell to the role. &quot;No one could've guessed then that the series would span a quarter-century or that the classically trained Suchet would complete the entire catalogue of whodunits featuring the eccentric Belgian investigator, including 33 novels and dozens of short stories.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Henry Chu |url=http://articles.latimes.com/2013/jul/19/entertainment/la-et-st-poirot-20130721 |title=David Suchet bids farewell to Agatha Christie's Poirot – Los Angeles Times |publisher=Articles.latimes.com |date=19 July 2013 |accessdate=17 November 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; His final appearance was in an adaptation of ''Curtain: Poirot's Last Case'', aired on 13 November 2013. During the time that it was filmed, Suchet expressed his sadness at his final farewell to the Poirot character whom he had loved:

&lt;blockquote&gt;Poirot's death was the end of a long journey for me. I had only ever wanted to play Dame Agatha's true Poirot [...] He was as real to me as he had been to her: a great detective, a remarkable man, if, perhaps, just now and then, a little irritating.

I think back to Poirot’s last words in the scene before he dies. That second ‘Cher ami’ was for someone other than Hastings. It was for my dear, dear friend Poirot. I was saying goodbye to him as well — and I felt it with all my heart.&lt;ref name=&quot;Suchet&quot;/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The writers of the &quot;Binge!&quot; article of ''[[Entertainment Weekly]]'' Issue #1343–44 (26 December 2014 – 3 January 2015) picked Suchet as &quot;Best Poirot&quot; in the &quot;Hercule Poirot &amp; Miss Marple&quot; timeline.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=Binge! Agatha Christie: Hercule Poirot &amp; Miss Marple |magazine=[[Entertainment Weekly]] |issue=1343–44 |date=26 December 2014|pages=32–33}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The episodes were shot in various locations in the UK, and foreign scenes were shot in [[Twickenham Studios|Twickenham studios]].&lt;ref name=&quot;chimni&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Homes Used In Poirot Episodes|url=http://www.chimni.com/wiki/Homes_Used_In_Poirot_Episodes|website=www.chimni.com|publisher=Chimni – the architectural wiki|accessdate=15 September 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Other ====

* Heini Göbel, (1955; an adaptation of ''Murder on the Orient Express'' for the West German television series ''Die Galerie der großen Detektive'')
* [[José Ferrer]], ''Hercule Poirot'' (1961; Unaired TV Pilot, MGM; adaptation of &quot;The Disappearance of Mr. Davenheim&quot;)
* [[Martin Gabel]], ''General Electric Theater'' (4/1/1962; adaptation of &quot;The Disappearance of Mr. Davenheim&quot;)
* Horst Bollmann, ''Black Coffee'' 1973
* [[Ian Holm]], ''Murder by the Book'', 1986
* [[Alfred Molina]], ''[[Murder on the Orient Express (2001 film)|Murder on the Orient Express]]'', 2001
* [[Konstantin Raikin]], ''Neudacha Puaro'' (''Poirot's Failure'') (2002; based on &quot;The Murder of Roger Ackroyd&quot;)
* [[Shirō Itō]] (Takashi Akafuji), ''Meitantei Akafuji Takashi'' (''The Detective Takashi Akafuji''), 2005
* [[Mansai Nomura]] (Takeru Suguro), ''Orient Kyūkō Satsujin Jiken'' (''Murder on the Orient Express''), 2015; ''Kuroido Goroshi'' (''The Murder of Kuroido''), (2018; based on &quot;The Murder of Roger Ackroyd&quot;)
* [[John Malkovich]] was cast as Poirot in [[The ABC Murders (TV series)|the 2018 BBC adaptation]] of ''[[The A.B.C. Murders|The ABC Murders]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.agathachristie.com/news/2018/all-star-cast-announced-for-the-abc-murders-bbc-adaptation |title=Casting announced for The ABC Murders BBC adaptation |publisher=Agatha Christie |date= |accessdate=5 January 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

=== Anime ===

In 2004, [[NHK]] (Japanese public TV network) produced a 39 episode anime series titled ''[[Agatha Christie's Great Detectives Poirot and Marple]]'', as well as a [[manga]] series under the same title released in 2005. The series, adapting several of the best-known Poirot and Marple stories, ran from 4 July 2004 through 15 May 2005, and in repeated reruns on [[NHK]] and other networks in Japan. Poirot was voiced by [[Kōtarō Satomi]] and Miss Marple was voiced by [[Kaoru Yachigusa]].

=== Radio ===
Radio adaptations of the Poirot stories also appeared,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.radioechoes.com/?page=series&amp;genre=Detective&amp;series=Hercule%20Poirot&lt;/ref&gt; most recently twenty-seven of them on [[BBC Radio 4]] (and regularly repeated on [[BBC 7]], later [[BBC Radio 4 Extra]]), starring [[John Moffatt (actor)|John Moffatt]]; [[Maurice Denham]] and [[Peter Sallis]] have also played Poirot on [[BBC Radio 4]] in ''[[The Mystery of the Blue Train]]'' and in ''[[Hercule Poirot's Christmas]]'', respectively (see &quot;BBC Radio 4 Poirot radio dramas&quot; below).

In 1939, [[Orson Welles]] and the [[Mercury Theatre|Mercury Players]] dramatised ''Roger Ackroyd'' on CBS's ''[[The Campbell Playhouse (radio series)|Campbell Playhouse]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cox, Jim 2002, p. 18&quot;&gt;Cox, Jim, ''Radio Crime Fighters'', 2002, p. 18, McFarland, Jefferson, NC, {{ISBN|978-0-7864-1390-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://orsonwelles.indiana.edu/items/show/2002 |title=The Murder of Roger Ackroyd |website=Orson Welles on the Air, 1938–1946 |publisher=Indiana University Bloomington |access-date=29 July 2018 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

On October 6, 1942, the [[Mutual Broadcasting System|Mutual]] radio series ''Murder Clinic'' broadcast &quot;The Tragedy at Marsden Manor&quot; starring [[Maurice Tarplin]] as Poirot.&lt;ref&gt;https://archive.org/details/Murder_Clinic/Murder_Clinic-42-10-06_012_Tragedy_At_Marsden_Manor.mp3&lt;/ref&gt;

A 1945 radio series of at least 13 original half-hour episodes (none of which apparently adapt any Christie stories) transferred Poirot from London to New York and starred character actor [[Harold Huber]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.otrsite.com/logs/logh1033.htm |title=A list of episodes of the half-hour 1945 radio program |publisher=Otrsite.com |date= |accessdate=27 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; perhaps better known for his appearances as a police officer in various [[Charlie Chan]] films. On 22 February 1945, &quot;speaking from London, [[Agatha Christie]] introduced the initial broadcast of the Poirot series via shortwave&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cox, Jim 2002, p. 18&quot;/&gt;

An adaptation of ''Murder in the Mews'' was broadcast on the [[BBC Light Programme]] in March 1955 starring [[Richard Bebb Williams|Richard Williams]] as Poirot; this program was thought lost, but was discovered in the BBC archives in 2015.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b06ss65l|title=Murder in the Mews, Poirot – BBC Radio 4 Extra|website=BBC}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== BBC Radio 4 Poirot radio dramas ===

Recorded and released ([[John Moffatt (actor)|John Moffatt]] stars as Poirot unless otherwise indicated):&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b03js5pl/episodes/guide|title=BBC Radio 4 Extra – Poirot – Episode guide|work=BBC}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{columns-list|colwidth=24em|
* The Mystery of the Blue Train (1985 w/[[Maurice Denham]] as Poirot – 6 parts)
* Hercule Poirot’s Christmas (1986 w/[[Peter Sallis]] as Poirot)
* The Murder of Roger Ackroyd (1987)
* Murder on the Links (1990)
* Lord Edgware Dies (a.k.a. Thirteen at Dinner) (1992 – 5 episodes)
* Sad Cypress (1992 – 5 episodes)
* Hallowe’en Party (1992)
* Murder on the Orient Express (1992 – 5 episodes)
* Five Little Pigs (1994)
* Murder in Mesopotamia (1994 – 5 episodes)
* Death on the Nile (1997 – 5 episodes)
* Evil Under the Sun (1998 – 5 episodes)
* After the Funeral (1999)
* The ABC Murders (2000)
* Peril at End House (2000 – 5 episodes)
* Appointment With Death (2001)
* Cards on the Table (2002)
* Three Act Tragedy (2002 – 5 episodes)
* Death in the Clouds (2003)
* Taken at the Flood (2003 – 5 episodes)
* One, Two Buckle My Shoe (2004 – 5 episodes)
* The Adventure of the Christmas Pudding (2004)
* Elephants Can Remember (2005)
* The Mysterious Affair at Styles (2005 – 5 episodes)
* Mrs. McGinty’s Dead (2006 – 5 episodes)
* Dumb Witness (2006 – 5 episodes)
* Dead Man’s Folly (2007 – 5 episodes)

}}

=== Other audio ===

In 2017, [[Audible (store)|Audible]] released an original audio adaptation of ''Murder on the Orient Express'' starring [[Tom Conti]] as Poirot.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.agathachristie.com/news/2017/audible-original-dramatisation-of-christies-classic-story |title=Audible Original dramatisation of Christie's classic story |publisher=Agatha Christie |date= |accessdate=5 January 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The cast included [[Jane Asher]] as Mrs. Hubbard, [[Jay Benedict]] as Monsieur Bouc, [[Ruta Gedmintas]] as Countess Andrenyi, [[Sophie Okonedo]] as Mary Debenham, [[Eddie Marsan]] as Ratchett, [[Walles Hamonde]] as Hector MacQueen, [[Paterson Joseph]] as Colonel Arbuthnot, [[Rula Lenska]] as Princess Dragimiroff and [[Art Malik]] as the Narrator.  According to the Publisher's Summary on Audible.com, &quot;sound effects [were] recorded on the Orient Express itself.&quot;

=== Parodies and references ===
{{sources|section|date=January 2019}}

In ''[[Revenge of the Pink Panther]]'', Poirot makes a cameo appearance in a mental asylum, portrayed by [[Andrew Sachs]] and claiming to be &quot;the greatest detective in all of France, the greatest in all the world&quot;.

In Neil Simon's ''[[Murder by Death]]'', American actor [[James Coco]] plays &quot;Milo Perrier&quot;, a parody of Poirot. The film also features parodies of [[Charlie Chan]], [[Sam Spade]], [[Nick and Nora Charles]], [[Hildegarde Withers]], and [[Miss Marple]].

In season 7 episode 2 of ''The Benny Hill Show'', a sketch entitled &quot;Murder on the Oregon Express&quot; had [[Benny Hill]] parodying Poirot (also [[McCloud (TV series)|Deputy Sam McCloud]], [[Cannon (TV series)|Frank Cannon]], [[Kojak|Theo Kojak]] and [[Ironside (1967 TV series)|Robert Ironside]]). Hill played Poirot as French, not Belgian.{{cn|date=January 2019}}

Dudley Jones played Poirot in the film ''[[The Strange Case of the End of Civilization as We Know It]]'' (1977).

In the film ''[[Spice World (film)|Spice World]]'', [[Hugh Laurie]] plays Poirot. 

In ''[[Sherlock Holmes: The Awakened]]'', Poirot appears as a young boy on the train transporting Holmes and Watson. Holmes helps the boy in opening a puzzle-box, with Watson giving the boy advice about using his &quot;little grey cells&quot;, giving the impression that Poirot first heard about grey cells and their uses from Dr. Watson.

The Belgian brewery Brasserie Ellezelloise makes a stout called ''Hercule'' with a moustachioed caricature of Hercule Poirot on the label.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.brasserie-ellezelloise.be/bieres-uk.shtml#L%27Hercule |title=The Brasserie Ellezelloise's Hercule |publisher=Brasserie-ellezelloise.be |accessdate=27 June 2010 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100602134946/http://www.brasserie-ellezelloise.be/bieres-uk.shtml#L%27Hercule |archivedate=2 June 2010  }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In season 2, episode 4 of [[The Viral Fever|TVFPlay]]'s Indian web series ''Permanent Roommates'', one of the characters refers to Hercule Poirot as her inspiration while she attempts to solve the mystery of the cheating spouse. Throughout the episode, she is mocked as Hercule Poirot and Agatha Christie by the suspects.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://tvfplay.com/episode/1/3/68/783|title=Watch TVF's Permanent Roommates S02E04 – The Dinner on TVF Play|website=TVFPlay}}&lt;/ref&gt; TVFPlay also telecasted a spoof of Indian TV suspense drama [[CID (Indian TV series)|''CID'']] as &quot;''Qissa Missing Dimaag Ka: C.I.D Qtiyapa''&quot;. In the first episode, when Ujjwal is shown to browse for the best detectives of the world, [[David Suchet]] appears as Poirot in his search.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://tvfplay.com/category/2/series/73|title=Qissa Missing Dimaag Ka (Part 1/2)|website=TVFPlay}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{portal|Novels}}
*''[[Poirot Investigates]]''
*[[Tropes in Agatha Christie's novels]]

== Footnotes ==
{{Notelist}}

== References ==
{{Reflist|30em}}

== Literature ==
=== Works ===
* {{cite book|first=Agatha |last=Christie|title=The Mysterious Affair at Styles|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=GFu5EVQWkHoC|year=1939|publisher=Penguin|isbn=978-1-61298-214-4 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|first=Agatha |last=Christie|title=Hercule Poirot: The Complete Short Stories: A Hercule Poirot Collection with Foreword by Charles Todd|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=NdydxJIUrD4C|year=2013|publisher=HarperCollins|isbn=978-0-06-225165-7 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|first=Agatha |last=Christie|title=Murder on the Orient Express: A Hercule Poirot Mystery|url=https://archive.org/details/isbn_9780062073501|url-access=registration |date=29 March 2011|publisher=HarperCollins|isbn=978-0-06-207350-1 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|first=Agatha |last=Christie|title=The A.B.C. murders: &amp;#91;a Hercule Poirot mystery&amp;#93;|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=2xJhQgAACAAJ|year=1991|publisher=Berkley Publishing Group|isbn=978-0-425-13024-7 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|first=Agatha |last=Christie|title=The Apples of the Hesperides|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=0_fGXwAACAAJ|year=1947a|publisher=Collins |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|first=Agatha |last=Christie|title=Five Little Pigs: A Hercule Poirot Mystery|url=https://archive.org/details/fivelittlepigs0000chri|url-access=registration |date=1 February 2011|publisher=HarperCollins|isbn=978-0-06-207357-0 |ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|first=Agatha |last=Christie|title=Death in the Clouds|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=50HvHBYcvTEC|date=10 February 2010|publisher=HarperCollins|isbn=978-0-06-174311-5 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|first=Agatha |last=Christie|title=Evil Under the Sun: Death Comes as the End; The Sittaford Mystery|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=3ParPQAACAAJ|year=1980|publisher=Lansdowne Press|isbn=978-0-7018-1458-8 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|first=Agatha |last=Christie|title=The Dream: A Hercule Poirot Short Story|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=37KgywOXgCQC|date=1 September 2011|publisher=HarperCollins Publishers|isbn=978-0-00-745198-2 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|first=Agatha |last=Christie|title=The Lost Mine: A Hercule Poirot Story|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=SelokMldIX0C|date=9 July 2013|publisher=HarperCollins|isbn=978-0-06-229818-8 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|first=Agatha |last=Christie|title=The Clocks|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=1F4GAl314HQC|date=28 September 2004 |publisher=HarperCollins|isbn=978-0-06-174050-3 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|first=Agatha |last=Christie|title=The Labours of Hercules: Hercule Poirot Investigates|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=c3X6K58mm2UC|date=3 October 2006 |publisher=HarperCollins|isbn=978-0-06-174638-3 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|first=Agatha |last=Christie|title=The Big Four|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=MQRAVaVQGYIC|date=6 January 2004 |publisher=HarperCollins|isbn=978-0-06-173909-5 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|first=Agatha |last=Christie |title=Mrs. McGinty's Dead|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=SkpwPQAACAAJ|year=1952 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |first=Agatha |last=Christie|title=The Stymphalean Birds|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=0BNTywAACAAJ|year=1947b|publisher=Collins |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |first=Agatha |last=Christie|title=Three Act Tragedy|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=CvsCA2ZNTHEC|date=3 October 2006 |publisher=HarperCollins|isbn=978-0-06-175403-6 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |first=Agatha |last=Christie|title=After the Funeral: Hercule Poirot Investigates|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=6Hw1_-iGGksC|date=25 January 2005|publisher=HarperCollins|isbn=978-0-06-173991-0 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |first=Agatha |last=Christie|title=Third Girl: A Hercule Poirot Mystery|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=XRu3nf6TRWEC|date=14 June 2011|publisher=HarperCollins|isbn=978-0-06-207376-1 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |first=Agatha |last=Christie|title=The Pale Horse by A.Christie|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=aTPGOQAACAAJ|year=1961|publisher=Collins |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|first=Agatha |last=Christie|title=The Murder of Roger Ackroyd|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=jLUPkkcWpjQC|date=17 March 2009|publisher=HarperCollins|isbn=978-0-06-176340-3 |ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|first=Agatha |last=Christie |title=Taken at the Flood|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=GrCcOwAACAAJ|year=1948 |ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|first=Agatha |last=Christie|title=The Erymanthian Boar|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=P-0PywAACAAJ|year=1947c|publisher=Collins |ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|first=Agatha |last=Christie|title=Peril at End House|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=OJqxNpp1qB8C|date=17 March 2009|publisher=HarperCollins|isbn=978-0-06-174927-8 |ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|first=Agatha|last=Christie|title=Curtain: Poirot's Last Case|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=dpzN2pDv-N0C|year=1975|publisher=HarperCollins|isbn=978-0-00-712112-0 |ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|first=Agatha|last=Christie|title=Double Sin: A Hercule Poirot Story|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=l6qCPA-gdW0C|date=23 July 2013|publisher=HarperCollins|isbn=978-0-06-229845-4 |ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|first=Agatha|last=Christie|title=The Kidnapped Prime Minister: A Hercule Poirot Short Story|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=MWMFWy_KrH0C|date=12 April 2012|publisher=HarperCollins Publishers|isbn=978-0-00-748658-8 |ref=harv}}
*{{cite book |first=Agatha |last=Christie|title=Prologue|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=0BNTywAACAAJ|year=1947|publisher=Collins |ref=harv|isbn=|location=|pages=}}

=== Reviews ===
* {{Citation|last= Barnard |first= Robert |year= 1980
|title= A Talent to Deceive
|publisher= Fontana/Collins|location= London
|isbn= }}
* Goddard, John (2018), ''Agatha Christie’s Golden Age: An Analysis of Poirot’s Golden Age Puzzles'', Stylish Eye Press, {{ISBN|978-1-999-61200-9}}
* {{Citation|last= Hart|first= Anne |year= 2004
|title= Agatha Christie's Poirot: The Life and Times of Hercule Poirot
|publisher= Harper and Collins|location= London
|isbn= }}
*{{Citation|editor1-last=Kretzschmar|editor1-first=Judith|editor2-last=Stoppe|editor2-first=Sebastian|editor3-last=Vollberg|editor3-first=Susanne|title=Hercule Poirot trifft Miss Marple. Agatha Christie intermedial|location=Darmstadt|publisher =Büchner|year=2016|isbn= 978-3-941310-48-3}}.
* {{Citation|last= Osborne|first= Charles |authorlink=Charles Osborne (music writer)|year= 1982
|title= The Life and Crimes of Agatha Christie
|publisher= Collins|location= London
|isbn= }}

== External links ==
{{commons category|Hercule Poirot}}
* [https://www.agathachristie.com/characters/hercule-poirot Official Agatha Christie website]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20170710163846/http://www.imdb.com/character/ch0013286/ Hercule Poirot] on [[IMDb]]
* {{gutenberg|no=863|name=The Mysterious Affair at Styles}}
* [https://archive.org/details/TheMurderOfRogerAckroyd Listen to Orson Welles in &quot;The Murder of Roger Ackroyd&quot;]
* [https://archive.org/details/otr_herculepoirot-us Listen to the 1945 Hercule Poirot radio program]
* [[Wiktionary]] definition of [[Edgar Allan Poe]]'s &quot;[[wikt:ratiocination|ratiocination]]&quot;

{{Hercule Poirot}}
{{Agatha Christie}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Poirot, Hercule}}
[[Category:Hercule Poirot| ]]
[[Category:Characters in British novels of the 20th century]]
[[Category:Fictional Belgian people]]
[[Category:Literary characters introduced in 1920]]
[[Category:Fictional criminologists]]
[[Category:Fictional Belgian police officers]]
[[Category:Fictional private investigators]]
[[Category:Male characters in literature]]
[[Category:Hercule Poirot characters]]
[[Category:Series of books]]
[[Category:British novels adapted into films|Hercule Poirot]]
[[Category:British novels adapted into plays|Hercule Poirot]]
[[Category:Novels adapted into radio programs|Hercule Poirot]]
[[Category:Novels adapted into television programs|Hercule Poirot]]
[[Category:Novels adapted into video games|Hercule Poirot]]
[[Category:Fictional contract bridge players]]
[[Category:Fictional gentleman detectives]]</text>
      <sha1>dgsf47t4uymfulmo3ljvadtwgjc3oy0</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
