  <page>
    <title>Miss Marple</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1002</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941806499</id>
      <parentid>941773121</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-20T20:14:45Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>81.108.165.3</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Angela Lansbury */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Fictional character appearing in Agatha Christie's crime novels}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=December 2012}}
{{Infobox character
| color              = #FF5F5F
| name               = Miss Jane Marple
| image              = File:Miss Marple First Image.jpg
| caption            = Illustration by Gilbert Wilkinson of Miss Marple (December 1927 issue of ''The Royal Magazine'')
| first              = &quot;[[The Thirteen Problems#The Tuesday Night Club|The Tuesday Night Club]]&quot;
| last               = ''[[Sleeping Murder]]''
| creator            = [[Agatha Christie]]
| portrayer          = [[Gracie Fields]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Margaret Rutherford]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Angela Lansbury]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Dulcie Gray]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Helen Hayes]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Ita Ever]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Joan Hickson]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Geraldine McEwan]]&lt;br/&gt;[[June Whitfield]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Julia McKenzie]]&lt;br/&gt; Isabella Parriss (playing young Miss Marple)&lt;br/&gt;[[Julie Cox]] (playing Miss Marple as a young woman.)&lt;br/&gt;[[Keiko Kishi]] (Junko Mabuchi)
| voice              = [[Kaoru Yachigusa]]
| occupation         = Amateur detective
| gender             = Female
| title              = Miss
| family             = [[Raymond West (character)|Raymond West]] (nephew)&lt;br&gt;David West (great-nephew)&lt;br&gt;Lionel West (great-nephew)
| relatives          = Joan West (niece-in-law)&lt;br&gt;Mabel Denham (niece)&lt;br&gt;Henry (uncle)&lt;br&gt;Antony (cousin)&lt;br&gt;Gordon (cousin)&lt;br&gt;Fanny Godfrey (cousin)&lt;ref&gt;''[[At Bertram's Hotel]]'' – page 141&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;Lady Ethel Merridew (cousin)&lt;ref&gt;''[[At Bertram's Hotel]]'' – page 138&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;Thomas (uncle)&lt;br&gt;Helen (aunt)&lt;br&gt;Diane &quot;Bunch&quot; Harmon (goddaughter)
| religion           = [[Church of England]] (Christian)
| nationality        = British
}}
'''Miss Marple''' is a [[fictional character]] in [[Agatha Christie]]'s crime novels and short stories. '''Jane Marple''' is an elderly [[spinster]] who lives in the village of [[St. Mary Mead]] and acts as an amateur consulting [[detective]]. She is one of the best known of Christie's characters and has been portrayed numerous times on screen. Her first appearance was in a short story published in ''[[The Royal Magazine]]'' in December 1927, &quot;[[The Tuesday Night Club]]&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=John|last=Curran|title=Agatha Christie: Murder in the Making|location=New York|publisher=Harper|year=2011|isbn=978-0-06-206542-1|page=[https://archive.org/details/agathachristiemu0000curr/page/140 140]|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/agathachristiemu0000curr/page/140}}&lt;/ref&gt; which later became the first chapter of ''[[The Thirteen Problems]]'' (1932). Her first appearance in a full-length novel was in ''[[The Murder at the Vicarage]]'' in 1930 and her last appearance was in ''[[Sleeping Murder]]'' in 1976.

==Origins==
The character of Miss Marple is based on friends of Christie's step grandmother/aunt (Margaret Miller, née West).&lt;ref&gt;Margaret West was the sister of Mary Ann Boehmer, Agatha Christie's maternal grandmother. Margaret married Christie's paternal grandfather, Nathaniel Frary Miller, in 1863 in Westbourne, West Sussex. He died in 1869 and she dedicated a stained glass window to his memory in St.John's Church, Main Road, Southbourne, West Sussex. Margaret's stepson, Frederick Miller, went on to marry her niece Clara, and Agatha was the result. {{cite news|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/2957794/Agatha-Christie-used-her-grandmother-as-a-model-for-Miss-Marple-new-tapes-reveal.html|title=Agatha Christie used her step grandmother as a model for Miss Marple, new tapes reveal|first=Stephen|last=Adams|newspaper=[[The Daily Telegraph]]|date=2008-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; Christie attributed the inspiration for the character of Miss Marple to a number of sources, stating that Miss Marple was &quot;the sort of old lady who would have been rather like some of my step grandmother's Ealing cronies – old ladies whom I have met in so many villages where I have gone to stay as a girl&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Christie|first=Agatha|title=An Autobiography|year=2001|publisher=HarperCollins|isbn=978-0-00-635328-7|page=449}}&lt;/ref&gt; Christie also used material from her fictional creation, spinster Caroline Sheppard, who appeared in ''[[The Murder of Roger Ackroyd]]''. When [[Michael Morton (dramatist)|Michael Morton]] adapted the novel for the stage, he replaced the character of Caroline with a young girl. This change saddened Christie and she determined to give old maids a voice: Miss Marple was born.&lt;ref name=&quot;agathachristie.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://agathachristie.com/christies-work/detectives-and-sidekicks/miss-marple/|title=Characters – Miss Marple|work=Agatha Christie|accessdate=2012-10-09|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20121010144904/http://agathachristie.com/christies-work/detectives-and-sidekicks/miss-marple/|archivedate=10 October 2012|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Christie may have taken the name from [[Marple railway station]], through which she passed, or from Marple Hall, near her sister Madge's home at [[Abney Hall]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Cheshire Life&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=https://www.cheshirelife.co.uk/out-about/was-miss-marple-born-in-cheshire-1-1631050 | title=Was Miss Marple Born in Cheshire? | date=15 September 2010 | publisher=Cheshire Life | accessdate=1 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.poirot.us/mprofile.php &quot;Marple's Profile&quot;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20101126123518/http://poirot.us/mprofile.php |date=26 November 2010 }}, Hercule Poirot Central, ''accessed 30 March 2009''.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Character==
The character of Jane Marple in the first Miss Marple book, ''[[The Murder at the Vicarage]]'', is markedly different from how she appears in later books. This early version of Miss Marple is a gleeful gossip and not an especially nice woman. The citizens of St. Mary Mead like her but are often tired by her nosy nature and how she seems to expect the worst of everyone. In later books, she becomes more modern and a kinder person.

Miss Marple solves difficult crimes because of her shrewd intelligence, and St. Mary Mead, over her lifetime, has given her seemingly infinite examples of the negative side of human nature. Crimes always remind her of a parallel incident, although acquaintances may be bored by analogies that often lead her to a deeper realization about the true nature of a crime. She also has a remarkable ability to latch onto a casual comment and connect it to the case at hand. In several stories, she is able to rely on her acquaintance with [[Sir Henry Clithering]], a retired commissioner of the [[Metropolitan Police]], for official information when required.

Miss Marple never married and has no close living relatives. Her nephew, the &quot;well-known author&quot; Raymond West, appears in some stories, including ''[[The Thirteen Problems]]'', ''Sleeping Murder'' and ''Ingots of Gold'' (which also feature his wife, Joyce Lemprière). Raymond overestimates himself and underestimates his aunt's mental acuity. Miss Marple employs young women (including Clara, Emily, Alice, Esther, Gwenda, and Amy) from a nearby orphanage, whom she trains for service as general housemaids after the retirement of her long-time maid-housekeeper, faithful Florence. She was briefly looked after by her irritating companion, Miss Knight. In her later years, companion Cherry Baker, first introduced in ''The Mirror Crack'd From Side to Side'', lives in.

Miss Marple has never worked for her living and is of independent means, although she benefits in her old age from the financial support of Raymond West, her nephew (''[[A Caribbean Mystery]]'', 1964). She is not herself from the aristocracy or landed gentry, but is quite at home among them and would probably have been happy to describe herself as &quot;genteel&quot;; indeed, a ''[[gentlewoman]]''. Miss Marple may thus be considered a female version of that staple of British detective fiction, the [[gentleman detective]]. She demonstrates a remarkably thorough education, including some art courses that involved study of human anatomy through the study of human cadavers. In ''[[They Do It with Mirrors]]'' (1952), it is revealed that Miss Marple grew up in a [[cathedral close]], and that she studied at an Italian finishing school with Americans Ruth Van Rydock and Caroline &quot;Carrie&quot; Louise Serrocold.

While Miss Marple is described as &quot;an old lady&quot; in many of the stories, her age is mentioned in &quot;At Bertram's Hotel&quot;, where it is said she visited the hotel when she was fourteen and almost sixty years have passed since then. Excluding ''Sleeping Murder'', forty-one years passed between the first and last-written novels, and many characters grow and age. An example would be the Vicar's nephew: in ''The Murder at the Vicarage'', the Reverend Clement's nephew Dennis is a teenager; in ''The Mirror Crack'd from Side to Side'', it is mentioned that the nephew is now grown and successful and has a career. The effects of ageing are seen on Miss Marple, such as needing a holiday after illness in ''[[A Caribbean Mystery]]'' but she is if anything more agile in ''[[Nemesis (Christie novel)|Nemesis]]'', set only sixteen months later.

Miss Marple's background is described in some detail, albeit in glimpses across the novels and short stories in which she appears. She has a very large family, including a sister, the mother of [[Raymond West (character)|Raymond]] and Mabel Denham, a young woman who was accused of poisoning her husband Geoffrey (''[[The Thirteen Problems#The Thumb Mark of St. Peter|The Thumb Mark of St. Peter]]'').

==Bibliography==
===Miss Marple Series===
# ''[[The Murder at the Vicarage]]'' (1930, Novel)
#''[[The Thirteen Problems]]'' (1932, Collection)
#''[[The Regatta Mystery and Other Stories]]'' (1939, Collection)
# ''[[The Body in the Library]]'' (1942, Novel)
# ''[[The Moving Finger]]'' (1943, Novel)
# ''[[A Murder Is Announced]]'' (1950, Novel)
# ''[[Three Blind Mice and Other Stories]]'' (1950, Collection)
# ''[[They Do It with Mirrors]]'' (1952, Novel)
# ''[[A Pocket Full of Rye]]'' (1953, Novel)
# ''[[4.50 from Paddington]]'' (1957, Novel)
# ''[[The Adventure of the Christmas Pudding]]'' (1960, Collection)
# ''[[Double Sin and Other Stories]]'' (1961, Collection)
# ''[[The Mirror Crack'd from Side to Side]] (''1962, Novel)
# ''[[A Caribbean Mystery]]'' (1964, Novel)
# ''[[At Bertram's Hotel]]'' (1965, Novel)
# ''[[Nemesis (Agatha Christie novel)|Nemesis]]'' (1971, Novel)
# ''[[Sleeping Murder]]'' (1976, Novel)
# ''[[Miss Marple's Final Cases and Two Other Stories|Miss Marple's Final Cases]]'' (1979, Collection)

===Miss Marple short story collections===
* ''[[The Thirteen Problems]]'' (1932 short story collection featuring Miss Marple, also published as ''The Tuesday Club Murders'')
* ''[[Miss Marple's Final Cases and Two Other Stories]]'' (short stories collected posthumously, also published as ''Miss Marple's Final Cases'', but only six of the eight stories actually feature Miss Marple) (written between 1939 and 1954, published 1979)
* ''Miss Marple: The Complete Short Stories'', published 1985, includes 20 from 4 sets: ''[[The Tuesday Club Murders]]'', ''[[The Regatta Mystery]]'', ''[[Three Blind Mice and Other Stories]]'', and ''[[Double Sin and Other Stories]]''.

Miss Marple also appears in &quot;Greenshaw's Folly&quot;, a short story included as part of the Poirot collection ''[[The Adventure of the Christmas Pudding]]'' (1960). Four stories in the ''[[Three Blind Mice and Other Stories|Three Blind Mice]]'' collection (1950) feature Miss Marple: &quot;Strange Jest&quot;, &quot;Tape-Measure Murder&quot;, &quot;The Case of the Caretaker&quot;, and &quot;The Case of the Perfect Maid&quot;.

The Autograph edition of ''Miss Marple's Final Cases'' includes the eight in the original plus &quot;Greenshaw's Folly&quot;.

===Books about Miss Marple===
* ''The Life and Times of Miss Jane Marple'' – a [[biography]] by [[Anne Hart (Canadian author)|Anne Hart]]

==Stage==
A stage adaptation of ''Murder at the Vicarage'', by Moie Charles and Barbara Toy, was first seen at Northampton on 17 October 1949;&lt;ref&gt;'Chit Chat', ''The Stage'', 29 September 1949&lt;/ref&gt; it was directed by [[Reginald Tate]], starred the 35-year-old [[Barbara Mullen]] as Miss Marple, and after touring, reached the [[Playhouse Theatre]] in London's [[West End theatre|West End]] on 14 December. Having run till late March 1950, it then went on tour again.&lt;ref&gt;Frances Stephens (ed), ''Theatre World Annual (London)'' number 1, Rockliff Publishing Corporation 1950&lt;/ref&gt;

In July 1974, Mullen (by then 60) returned to the role in another national tour of the same play, culminating 12 months later when the show opened at London's [[Savoy Theatre]] on 28 July 1975.&lt;ref&gt;''Murder at the Vicarage'' programme: Theatre Print vol 5 # 9 [October 1975], Martin Tickner (ed)&lt;/ref&gt; At the end of March 1976 the Miss Marple role was taken over by [[Avril Angers]], after which the production transferred to the [[Fortune Theatre]] on 5 July. The role then passed to [[Muriel Pavlow]] in June 1977&lt;ref&gt;''Murder at the Vicarage'' programme: Theatre Print # 27 [December 1977], Martin Tickner (ed)&lt;/ref&gt; and to [[Gabrielle Hamilton (actress)|Gabrielle Hamilton]] late the following year; the production finally closed in October 1979.&lt;ref&gt;'On Next Week', ''The Stage'', 18 October 1979&lt;/ref&gt;

On 21 September 1977, while ''Murder at the Vicarage'' was still running at the Fortune, a stage adaptation by Leslie Darbon of ''A Murder Is Announced'' opened at the [[Vaudeville Theatre]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.pbs.org/wgbh/mystery/announced/notes.html |title=Mystery! &amp;#124; A murder is announced &amp;#124; Production notes |publisher=Pbs.org |date= |accessdate=20 March 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; with [[Dulcie Gray]] as Miss Marple.&lt;ref&gt;Vaudeville Theatre programme, No.29 February 1978&lt;/ref&gt; The show ran to the end of September 1978 and then went on tour.&lt;ref&gt;'On the Way', ''The Stage'', 10 August 1978&lt;/ref&gt;

==Films==

===Margaret Rutherford===
Jane Marple had to wait thirty-two years after her first appearance in 1930 for her first big-screen appearance, the first in a sequence of films starring [[Margaret Rutherford]]. These were successful light comedies, but were disappointing to Christie herself.&lt;ref&gt;Matthew Bunson, ''The Complete Christie: An Agatha Christie Encyclopedia''. NY: Simon and Schuster, 2000. 386-87.
{{ISBN|9780671028312}} 
books.google.com/books?id=R3syC8weGO8C&amp;pg=PA386&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, Agatha Christie dedicated the novel ''[[The Mirror Crack'd from Side to Side]]'' to Rutherford.

Rutherford presented the character as a bold and eccentric old lady, different from the prim and birdlike character Christie created in her novels. As penned by Christie, Miss Marple has never worked for a living, but the character as portrayed by Margaret Rutherford briefly works as a cook-housekeeper, a stage actress, a sailor and criminal reformer, and is offered the chance to run a riding establishment-cum-hotel. Her education and genteel background are hinted at when she mentions her awards at marksmanship, fencing, and equestrianism (although these hints are played for comedic value).

''[[Murder, She Said]]'' (1961, directed by [[George Pollock (director)|George Pollock]]) was the first of four British MGM productions starring Rutherford. This film was based on the 1957 novel ''4:50 from Paddington'' (U.S. title, ''What Mrs. McGillicuddy Saw!''), and the changes made in the plot were typical of the series. In the film, Mrs. McGillicuddy is cut from the plot. Miss Marple herself sees an apparent murder committed on a train running alongside hers. Likewise, it is Miss Marple herself who poses as a maid to find out the facts of the case, not a young friend of hers who has made a business of it. Actress [[Joan Hickson]], who played Marple in the 1984-1992 television adaptations, has a role as a housekeeper in ''[[Murder, She Said]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;celebration140&quot;/&gt;

The other Rutherford films, all directed by Pollock, were ''[[Murder at the Gallop]]'' (1963), based on the 1953 [[Hercule Poirot]] novel ''[[After the Funeral]]'' (in this film, she is identified as Miss JTV Marple, though there was no indication as to what the extra initials might stand for); ''[[Murder Most Foul]]'' (1964), based on the 1952 Poirot novel ''[[Mrs McGinty's Dead]]''; and ''[[Murder Ahoy!]]'' (1964). The last film is not based on any Christie work but displays a few plot elements from ''They Do It With Mirrors'' (viz., the ship is used as a reform school for wayward boys and one of the teachers uses them as a crime force), and there is a kind of salute to [[The Mousetrap|''The Mousetrap''.]] Rutherford also appeared briefly as Miss Marple in the parodic Hercule Poirot adventure ''[[The Alphabet Murders]]'' (1965).

The music to all four films was composed and conducted by [[Ron Goodwin]]. The same theme is used on all four films with slight variations in each. The main theme has a distinct 1960s feel to it and is known to be a highly complex piece of music due to the quick playing of the [[violin]]. The score was written within a couple of weeks by Goodwin who was approached by Pollock after Pollock had heard about him from [[Stanley Black]]. Black had worked with Pollock on &quot;Stranger in Town&quot; in 1957 and had previously used Goodwin as his orchestrator.

Rutherford, who was 68 years old when the first film was shot in February 1961, insisted that she wear her own clothes during the filming of the movie, as well as having her real-life husband, [[Stringer Davis]], appear alongside her as the character 'Mr Stringer'. The Rutherford films are frequently repeated on television in Germany, and in that country Miss Marple is generally identified with Rutherford's quirky portrayal.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20060721192731/https://www.pbs.org/wgbh/mystery/marple2/shoes.html|title=Filling Miss Marple's Shoes|first=Phil|last=Clymer|accessdate=2012-03-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Angela Lansbury===
In 1980, [[Angela Lansbury]] played Miss Marple in ''[[The Mirror Crack'd]]'' (EMI, directed by [[Guy Hamilton]]), based on Christie's 1962 novel. The film featured an all-star cast that included [[Elizabeth Taylor]], [[Rock Hudson]], [[Geraldine Chaplin]], [[Tony Curtis]], and [[Kim Novak]]. [[Edward Fox (actor)|Edward Fox]] appeared as Inspector Craddock, who did Miss Marple's legwork. Lansbury's Marple was a crisp, intelligent woman who moved stiffly and spoke in clipped tones. Unlike most incarnations of Miss Marple, this one smoked cigarettes. Lansbury would find later fame in a similar role as [[Jessica Fletcher]].

===Ita Ever===
In 1983, [[Estonians|Estonian]] stage and film actress [[Ita Ever]] starred in the [[Russian language]] [[Mosfilm]] adaptation of Agatha Christie's novel ''[[A Pocket Full of Rye]]'' (using the Russian edition's translated title, ''The Secret of the Blackbirds'') as the character of Miss Marple.&lt;ref name=&quot;PBS Mystery. Miss Marple&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.pbs.org/wgbh/mystery/marple/links.html |title=PBS Mystery. Miss Marple |publisher=Pbs.org |date= |accessdate=9 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.agathachristie.com/stories/a-pocket-full-of-rye|title=A Pocket Full of Rye|publisher=agathachristie.com|accessdate=3 January 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ever has also portrayed the character of Miss Marple in the [[Eesti Televisioon]] (ETV) series ''Miss Marple Stories'' in 1990, and onstage at the [[Tallinn City Theatre]] in a production of ''[[The Mirror Crack'd from Side to Side]]'' in 2005.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.ohtuleht.ee/181131/palju-onne-miss-marple|title=Palju õnne, miss Marple!|last=Tael|first=Triin|newspaper=[[Õhtuleht]]|date=14 September 2005|accessdate=3 January 2018|language=Estonian}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Television==
American TV was the setting for the first screen portrayal of Miss Marple with [[Gracie Fields]], the British actress and singer, playing her in a 1956 episode of ''Goodyear TV Playhouse'' based on ''A Murder Is Announced'', the 1950 Christie novel.

In 1970, the character of Miss Marple was portrayed by [[Inge Langen]] in a West German television adaptation of ''The Murder at the Vicarage '' (''Mord im Pfarrhaus'').&lt;ref name=&quot;PBS Mystery. Miss Marple&quot;/&gt;

In 2015, CBS planned a &quot;much younger&quot; version of the character, a granddaughter who takes over a California bookstore.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://decoy.tvpassport.com/q_a/q-it-true-theyre-making-new-miss-marple-tv-series-whos-going-play-her?subid=national-00001|title=Q &amp; A|publisher=TV Media|accessdate=19 November 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2018, Miss Marple was portrayed by [[Yunjin Kim]] in the South Korean television series ''[[Ms. Ma, Nemesis]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://english.yonhapnews.co.kr/kwave/2018/09/17/3001000000AEN20180917009200315.html|title=Yunjin Kim hopes 'Ms. Ma, Goddess of Revenge' becomes her best Korean TV series|publisher=Yonhap News|date=17 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Helen Hayes===
American stage and screen actress Helen Hayes portrayed Miss Marple in two American made-for-TV movies near the end of her decades long acting career, both for [[CBS]]: ''[[A Caribbean Mystery (film)|A Caribbean Mystery]]'' (1983) and ''[[Murder with Mirrors]]'' (1985). [[Sue Grafton]] contributed to the screenplay of the former. Hayes's Marple was benign and chirpy. She had earlier appeared in a TV movie adaptation of the non-Marple Christie story ''Murder Is Easy'', playing an elderly lady somewhat similar to Miss Marple.

===Joan Hickson===
{{Main article|Miss Marple (TV series)}}

From 1984 to 1992, the [[BBC]] adapted all of the original Miss Marple novels as a series titled ''Miss Marple''. [[Joan Hickson]] played the lead role. In the 1940s she had appeared on stage in an Agatha Christie play, ''[[Appointment with Death]]'', which was seen by Christie who wrote in a note to her, &quot;I hope one day you will play my dear Miss Marple&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;celebration140&quot;&gt;{{cite book| last = Haining| first = Peter| title = Agatha Christie: Murder in four acts : a centenary celebration of 'The Queen of Crime' on stage, films, radio &amp; TV| year = 1990| publisher = Carol Pub Group| isbn = 978-1-85227-273-9| page = 140 }}&lt;/ref&gt; She portrayed a maid in the 1937 film, ''[[Love from a Stranger (1937 film)|Love from a Stranger]]'', which starred Ann Harding and Basil Rathbone, another Agatha Christie play adaptation. As well as portraying Miss Marple on television, Hickson also narrated a number of Miss Marple stories on audio books. In the &quot;Binge!&quot; article of ''[[Entertainment Weekly]]'' Issue #1343–1344 (26 December 2014 – 3 January 2015), the writers picked Hickson as &quot;Best Marple&quot; in the &quot;Hercule Poirot &amp; Miss Marple&quot; timeline.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=Binge! Agatha Christie: Hercule Poirot &amp; Miss Marple |journal=[[Entertainment Weekly]] |issue=1343–44 |date=26 December 2014|pages=32–33}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Listing of the TV series featuring Joan Hickson:
* ''[[The Body in the Library]]'' (1984)
* ''[[A Murder Is Announced]]'' (1985)
* ''[[A Pocket Full of Rye]]'' (1985)
* ''[[The Moving Finger]]'' (1985)
* ''[[The Murder at the Vicarage]]'' (1986) – BAFTA nomination
* ''[[Sleeping Murder]]'' (1987)
* ''[[At Bertram's Hotel]]'' (1987)
* ''[[Nemesis (Christie novel)|Nemesis]]'' (1987) – BAFTA nomination
* ''[[4.50 from Paddington]]'' (1987)
* ''[[A Caribbean Mystery]]'' (1989)
* ''[[They Do It with Mirrors|They Do It With Mirrors]]'' (1991)
* ''[[The Mirror Crack'd from Side to Side]]'' (1992)

===Geraldine McEwan (2004–2008)/Julia McKenzie (2009–2013)===
{{Main article|Agatha Christie's Marple}}
Beginning in 2004, [[ITV (TV network)|ITV]] broadcast a series of adaptations of Agatha Christie's books under the title ''Agatha Christie's Marple'', usually referred to as ''Marple.'' [[Geraldine McEwan]] starred in the first three series. [[Julia McKenzie]] took over the role in the fourth season.

The adaptations change the plots and characters of the original books (e.g. incorporating lesbian affairs, changing the identities of some killers, renaming or removing significant characters, and even using stories from other books in which Miss Marple did not originally feature). In the Geraldine McEwan series it is revealed that when she was young (portrayed by [[Julie Cox]] in a flashback), Miss Marple had an affair with a married soldier, Captain Ainsworth, who was killed in action in World War I, in December 1915. It is also said (in ''[[A Murder Is Announced]]'') that she served as an ambulance driver during World War I.

Listing of the TV series featuring Geraldine McEwan and Julia McKenzie:
* ''[[The Body in the Library]]'' (2004)
* ''[[The Murder at the Vicarage]]'' (2004)
* ''[[4.50 from Paddington]]'' (2004)
* ''[[A Murder Is Announced]]'' (2005)
* ''[[Sleeping Murder]]'' (2005)
* ''[[The Moving Finger]]'' (2006)
* ''[[By the Pricking of My Thumbs]]'' (2006)
* ''[[The Sittaford Mystery]]'' (2006)
* ''[[At Bertram's Hotel]]'' (2007)
* ''[[Ordeal by Innocence]]'' (2007)
* ''[[Towards Zero]]'' (2008)
* ''[[Nemesis (Agatha Christie novel)|Nemesis]]'' (2008)
* ''[[A Pocket Full of Rye]]'' (2009)
* ''[[Murder Is Easy]]'' (2009)
* ''[[They Do It with Mirrors]]'' (2010)
* ''[[Why Didn't They Ask Evans?]]'' (2011)
* ''[[The Pale Horse (novel)|The Pale Horse]]'' (2010)
* ''[[The Secret of Chimneys]]'' (2010)
* ''[[The Thirteen Problems#The Blue Geranium|The Blue Geranium]]'' (2010)
* ''[[The Mirror Crack'd from Side to Side]]'' (2011)
* ''[[A Caribbean Mystery]]'' (2013)
* ''[[The Adventure of the Christmas Pudding#Greenshaw.27s Folly|Greenshaw's Folly]]'' (2013)
* ''[[Endless Night (novel)|Endless Night]]'' (2013)

===Anime===
{{Main article|Agatha Christie's Great Detectives Poirot and Marple}}
From 2004 to 2005, Japanese TV network [[NHK]] produced a 39 episode [[anime]] series titled ''Agatha Christie's Great Detectives Poirot and Marple'', which features both Miss Marple and [[Hercule Poirot]]. Miss Marple's voice is provided by [[Kaoru Yachigusa]]. Episodes adapted both short stories and novels.

The anime series dramatised the following Miss Marple stories:
* ''[[Three Blind Mice and Other Stories#List of stories|Strange Jest]]'' (EP 3)
* ''[[Three Blind Mice and Other Stories#List of stories|The Case of the Perfect Maid]]'' (EP 4)
* ''[[Three Blind Mice and Other Stories#List of stories|The Tape-Measure Murder]]'' (EP 13)
* ''[[The Thirteen Problems#Ingots of Gold|Ingots of Gold]]'' (EP 14)
* ''[[The Thirteen Problems#The Blue Geranium|The Blue Geranium]]'' (EP 15)
* ''[[4.50 from Paddington]]'' (EP 21–24)
* ''[[The Thirteen Problems#Motive v. Opportunity|Motive versus Opportunity]]'' (EP 27)
* ''[[Sleeping Murder]]'' (EP 30–33)

==Radio==
[[BBC Radio 4]] dramatised all of the novels from 1993 to 2001 with [[June Whitfield]] as Miss Marple.&lt;ref name=&quot;EpiList&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Miss Marple on BBC Radio, June Whitfield| url=http://www.geocities.com/gregorym101/marple.html|accessdate=21 July 2009|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090808154228/http://geocities.com/gregorym101/marple.html |archivedate=8 August 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;  style=&quot;width:100%; margin-right:0;&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;width:25%;&quot;| Title
! style=&quot;width:25%;&quot;| Show
! style=&quot;width:10%;&quot;| Episodes
! style=&quot;width:15%;&quot;| Episode Frequency
! style=&quot;width:25%;&quot;| Original airdate
|-
|Murder At the Vicarage
|
|align=center|5
|align=center|Daily
|26–30 December 1993
|-
|A Pocket Full of Rye
|The Saturday Playhouse
|align=center|1
|
|11 February 1995
|-
|At Bertram's Hotel
|
|align=center|5
|align=center|Daily
|25–29 December 1995
|-
|The 4:50 From Paddington
|The Saturday Playhouse
|align=center|1
|
|29 March 1997
|-
|A Caribbean Mystery
|
|align=center|5
|align=center|Weekly
|30 October – 27 November 1997
|-
|The Mirror Crack'd From Side to Side
|Agatha Christie Special
|align=center|1
|
|29 August 1998
|-
|Nemesis
|
|align=center|5
|align=center|Weekly
|9 November – 7 December 1998
|-
|The Body In the Library
|The Saturday Play
|align=center|1
|
|22 May 1999
|-
|A Murder Is Announced
|
|align=center|5
|align=center|Weekly
|9 August – 6 September 1999
|-
|The Moving Finger
|The Saturday Play
|align=center|1
|
|5 May 2001
|-
|They Do It With Mirrors
|
|align=center|5
|align=center|Weekly
|23 July 2001 – 20 August 2001
|-
|Sleeping Murder
|The Saturday Play
|align=center|1
|
|8 December 2001
|}
Three short stories with Whitfield (&quot;Tape-Measure Murder&quot;, &quot;The Case of the Perfect Maid&quot; and &quot;Sanctuary&quot;) were also broadcast under the collective title ''Miss Marple's Final Cases'' weekly 16 – 30 September 2015.

==Other appearances==
[[File:Jane Marple in Case Closed.jpg|thumb|Marple, as she appeared in volume 20 of ''[[Case Closed (manga)|Case Closed]]'']]

Marple was highlighted in volume 20 of the ''[[Case Closed (manga)|Case Closed]]'' manga's edition of &quot;Gosho Aoyama's Mystery Library&quot;, a section of the graphic novels (usually the last page) where the author introduces a different detective (or occasionally, a villain) from mystery literature, television, or other media.

In the 1976 [[Neil Simon]] [[spoof film|spoof]] ''[[Murder by Death]]'', Miss Marple is parodied as &quot;Miss Marbles&quot; by [[Elsa Lanchester]].

==See also==
{{portal|Novels}}
* [[List of female detective characters]]
{{Clear}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20110608002907/http://uk.agathachristie.com/christies-work/detectives-and-sidekicks/miss-marple/ Miss Marple] at the official Agatha Christie website
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20170511131724/http://www.imdb.com/character/ch0026660/ Miss Marple] on [[IMDb]]
* {{cite book| last1 = Shaw| first1 = Marion| last2 = Vanackere| first2 = Sabine| title = Reflecting on Miss Marple| url = https://books.google.com/books?id=j9AOAAAAQAAJ&amp;pg=PA35| year = 1991| publisher = Taylor &amp; Francis| isbn = 978-0-415-01794-7| page = 35 }}
* {{cite book| author = Mary Jean Demarr| title = In the beginning: first novels in mystery series| url = https://books.google.com/books?id=Kaf44WMWsA0C&amp;pg=PA36| year = 1995| publisher = Popular Press| isbn = 978-0-87972-674-4| page = 36 }}

{{Miss Marple}}
{{Agatha Christie}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Marple, Miss}}
[[Category:Book series introduced in 1930]]
[[Category:Miss Marple| ]]
[[Category:British novels adapted into films]]
[[Category:British novels adapted into plays]]
[[Category:Characters in British novels of the 20th century]]
[[Category:Detective television series]]
[[Category:Female characters in literature]]
[[Category:Fictional amateur detectives]]
[[Category:Fictional British people]]
[[Category:Literary characters introduced in 1927]]
[[Category:Fictional English people]]
[[Category:Fictional female detectives]]
[[Category:Novel series]]
[[Category:Novels adapted into radio programs]]
[[Category:Novels adapted into television programs]]</text>
      <sha1>kfvm1qq2qls9ajglxdvfyv6x6wd1yw9</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
