  <page>
    <title>All Souls' Day</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1055</id>
    <revision>
      <id>940313325</id>
      <parentid>938949717</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-11T20:06:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Gonzo fan2007</username>
        <id>1347436</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Per [[MOS:BOLDAVOID]]: Links should not be placed in the boldface reiteration of the title in the opening sentence of a lead</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{about|the Christian holiday|the 1998 novel|All Souls' Day (novel)|the 2005 film|All Souls Day (film)}}
{{redirect|Holy Souls}}
{{redirect|Faithful Departed|the Cranberries album|To the Faithful Departed}}
{{pp-move-vandalism|small = yes}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2020}}
{{Infobox holiday
|holiday_name = All Souls' Day
|type = Christian
|image = William-Adolphe Bouguereau (1825-1905) - The Day of the Dead (1859).jpg
|caption = ''All Souls' Day'' by [[William-Adolphe Bouguereau]]
|nickname = Feast of All Souls; Defuncts' Day; Day of Remembrance; Commemoration of all the faithful departed
|observedby = [[Catholicism]]&lt;br&gt;[[Eastern Orthodoxy]]&lt;br&gt;[[Lutheranism]]&lt;br&gt;[[Anglicanism]]&lt;br&gt;[[Methodism]]&lt;br&gt;Other [[Protestantism|Protestant denominations]]
|litcolor = Violet/purple or, where customary, black&lt;ref&gt;''General Instruction of the Roman Missal'', 346&lt;/ref&gt;
|begins =
|ends =
|significance = For the souls of all good who have passed away
|date = (West) 2 (or 3) November&lt;br /&gt;(East) Several times during the year
|celebrations =
|duration = 1 day
|frequency = annual
|observances = Prayer for the departed, visits to cemeteries, special meals
|relatedto = [[Saturday of Souls]], [[Thursday of the Dead]], [[Day of the Dead]], [[Halloween]], [[All Saints' Day]], [[Samhain]], [[Totensonntag]], [[Blue Christmas (holiday)|Blue Christmas]]
}}

'''All Souls' Day''', also known as the '''Commemoration of All the Faithful Departed''' and the '''Day of the Dead''', is a day of prayer and remembrance for the [[soul]]s of those who have died, which is observed by some [[Christian denominations]]. All Souls' Day is often, although not exclusively, celebrated in [[Western Christianity]]; [[Saturday of Souls]] is a related tradition more frequently observed in [[Eastern Christianity]]. Practitioners of All Souls' Day traditions often remember deceased loved ones in various ways on the day.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Cross |first1=Frank Leslie |last2=Livingstone |first2=Elizabeth A. |title=The Oxford Dictionary of the Christian Church |year=2005 |publisher=[[Oxford University Press]] |isbn=9780192802903 |page=42 |quote=All Souls' Day. The commemoration of the souls of the faithful departed on 2 Nov., the day following All Saints' Day.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Ball |first=Ann |title=Encyclopedia of Catholic Devotions and Practices |year=2003 |publisher=Our Sunday Visitor Publishing |isbn=9780879739102 |page=33 |quote=All Souls' Day: The annual commemoration of all the faithful departed, 2 November.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Beliefs and practices associated with All Souls' Day vary widely among Christian churches and denominations.

In contemporary [[Western Christianity]] the annual celebration is held on 2 November, and is part of the season of [[Allhallowtide]] that includes [[All Saints' Day]] (1 November) and its eve, [[Halloween]] (31 October).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Bannatyne |first=Lesley Pratt |title=Halloween: An American Holiday, an American History |url=https://books.google.com/?id=rNAXt9jLXWwC&amp;pg=PA12&amp;dq=Hallowmas+three+All+Souls+All+Saints#v=onepage&amp;q=Hallowmas%20three%20All%20Souls%20All%20Saints&amp;f=false |accessdate=1 November 2012 |date=1 August 1998 |publisher=Pelican Publishing |isbn=1565543467 |page=12 |quote=The Church brought its saints' celebrations to every new land it conquered. The celebrations on the eve of All Saints, All Saints' Day and All Souls' Day (the three were referred to as Hallowmas) spread throughout Europe. From the British Isles to France to Poland and Italy, the religious remembrance of the ancestral dead became an annual celebration of major importance.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Prior to the standardization of Catholic observance on 2 November by St. Odlio of Cluny during the 10th century, many Catholic congregations celebrated All Souls Day on various dates during the Easter season as it is still observed in some [[Eastern Orthodox Church]] and [[Eastern Catholic Churches]].

==Combined celebrations of All Saints and All Souls==
In some countries, All Saints' Day is a public holiday, but All Souls' Day is not. Consequently, people visit graves and conduct other All Souls' Day practices on All Saints Day instead. Countries where All Souls' Day traditions are observed on All Saints' Day in this fashion include Belgium,&lt;ref name=&quot;army.mil-toussaint&quot;&gt;[https://www.army.mil/article/196239/all_saints_day_honors_the_deceased &quot;All Saints' Day honors the deceased&quot;, USAG Benelux Public Affairs, November 1, 2017]&lt;/ref&gt; Bosnia and Herzegovina, Croatia, the Czech Republic, France,&lt;ref name=&quot;couleur-toussaint&quot;&gt;[https://www.couleurnature.com/blogs/news/the-flower-of-death &quot;The Flower of Death&quot;, Couleur Nature, Paris, 25 July 2011]&lt;/ref&gt; Finland, Germany, Guatemala,&lt;ref name=&quot;revuemag-guatemala&quot;&gt;[http://www.revuemag.com/2012/11/all-saints-day-in-guatemala-a-photographic-essay/ Mijangos, Nelo. &quot;All Saints Day in Guatemala&quot;, ''Revue'', 2 November 2012]&lt;/ref&gt; Hungary, Italy, Lithuania, Macedonia, Moldova, the Philippines,&lt;ref name=&quot;guardian-world-saints&quot;&gt;[https://www.theguardian.com/world/gallery/2010/nov/01/all-saints-day &quot;All Saints Day around the world&quot;, ''Guardian Weekly'', 1 November 2010]&lt;/ref&gt; Poland, Portugal,&lt;ref name=&quot;portugese-american-saints&quot;&gt;[http://portuguese-american-journal.com/national-holiday-november-1st-is-all-saints-day-%E2%80%93-portugal/ &quot;National holiday: November 1st is All Saints Day – Portugal&quot;, ''Portuguese American Journal'', 1 November 2011]&lt;/ref&gt; Romania, Slovakia, Slovenia, Serbia, and Sweden.
{{Main|All Saints' Day}}

== Popular customs ==
Many All Souls' Day traditions reflect popular notions associated with [[purgatory]]. For example, ringing bells for the dead was believed to comfort them in their cleansing, while the sharing of [[soul cakes]] with the poor helped to buy the dead a bit of respite from the suffering of purgatory. In the same way, lighting candles was meant to kindle a light for the dead souls languishing in the darkness. Out of this grew the traditions of &quot;going souling&quot; and the baking of special types of bread or cakes.&lt;ref&gt;Medieval Histories 2012: 11:1 http://medievalhistories.com/wp-content/uploads/medievalhistories-november1.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;{{Verify source|date=November 2019}}

===Europe===
In [[Tyrol (state)|Tirol]], cakes are left for them on the table and the room kept warm for their comfort. In [[Brittany]], people flock to the cemeteries at nightfall to kneel, bareheaded, at the graves of their loved ones, and to anoint the hollow of the [[tomb stone|tombstone]] with [[holy water]] or to pour libations of milk on it. At bedtime, the supper is left on the table for the souls.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chisholm1911&quot;/&gt;

In [[Malta]], a traditional All Souls' supper includes roasted pig, based on a custom of letting a pig loose on the streets with a bell around its neck, to be fed by the entire neighborhood and cooked on that day to feed the poor.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://timesofmalta.com/articles/view/maltese-traditions-to-mark-all-souls-day-at-the-inquisitors-palace.629197|title=Maltese traditions to mark All Souls Day at the Inquisitor's Palace|website=Times of Malta}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Linz]], funereal musical pieces known as [[aequale]]s were played from tower tops on All Souls' Day and the evening before.&lt;ref name=triton&gt;From sleevenotes, Triton Trombone Quartet: &quot;German Trombone Music&quot;; BIS-CD-644&lt;/ref&gt;

===Philippines===
{{Main|All Saints' Day#Philippines}}
In the Philippines, Hallow mas is variously called &quot;''Undás''&quot;, &quot;''Todos los Santos''&quot; (Spanish, &quot;All Saints&quot;), and sometimes &quot;''Araw ng mga Patay / Yumao''&quot; ([[Tagalog language|Tagalog]], &quot;Day of the dead / those who have passed away&quot;), which incorporates All Saints' Day and All Souls' Day. Filipinos traditionally observe this day by visiting the family dead to clean and repair their tombs. Offerings of prayers, flowers, candles,&lt;ref name=&quot;guardian-world-saints&quot;/&gt; and food. [[Chinese Filipinos]] additionally burn [[joss stick|incense]] and ''[[joss paper|kim]]''. Many also spend the day and ensuing night holding reunions at the cemetery with feasts and merriment.

== Religious observance by denomination ==
===Byzantine (Greek) Catholic and the Eastern Orthodoxy===
{{Main|Saturday of Souls}}

[[File:Soul Saturday Kollyva offerings.jpg|right|thumb|Kollyva offerings of boiled wheat blessed liturgically on Soul Saturday (''Psychosabbaton'').]]
'''Saturday of Souls''' (or Soul Saturday) is a day set aside for the commemoration of the dead within the [[liturgical year]] of the [[Eastern Orthodox]] and Byzantine Catholic Churches. Saturday is a traditional day of prayer for the dead, because Christ lay dead in the [[Holy Sepulchre|Tomb]] on Saturday.

These days are devoted to prayer for departed relatives and others among the faithful who would not be commemorated specifically as saints. The [[Divine Services]] on these days have special hymns added to them to commemorate the departed. There is oftena [[Panikhida]] (Memorial Service) either after the [[Divine Liturgy]] on Saturday morning or after [[Vespers]] on Friday evening, for which [[Koliva]] (a dish made of boiled wheatberries or rice and honey) is prepared and placed on the Panikhida table. After the Service, the priest blesses the Koliva. It is then eaten as a memorial by all present.

====Radonitsa====
{{Main|Radonitsa}}
Another Memorial Day in the East, Radonitsa, does not fall on a Saturday, but on either Monday or Tuesday of the second week after Pascha (Easter). Radonitsa does not have special hymns for the dead at the Divine Services. Instead a Panikhida will follow the Divine Liturgy, and then all will bring paschal foods to the cemeteries to greet the departed with the joy of the Resurrection.

===East Syriac tradition===
East Syriac churches including the [[Syro Malabar Church]] and [[Chaldean Catholic Church]] commemorates the feast of departed faithful on the last Friday of [[Epiphany season]] (which means Friday just before start of [[Great Lent]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nasranifoundation.org/calendar/dr/reflection_9fri_denha.html |title=Commemoration of the Departed Faithful |work=Nasrani Foundation}}&lt;/ref&gt; The season of Epiphany remembers the revelation of Christ to the world. Each Friday of Epiphany season, the church remembers important evangelistic figures.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.syromalabarchurch.in/pdf/Panchangam%20English2016.pdf |title=Syro Malabar Liturgical Calendar 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In East Syriac liturgy, the church remembers departed souls including saints on every Fridays throughout the year since the Christ was crucified and died on Friday.

====Syro Malabar Church====
In the [[Syro Malabar Church]], the Friday before the parish festival is also celebrated as feast of departed faithful when the parish remembers the activities of forebearers who worked for the parish and faithful. They also request the intercession of all departed souls for the faithful celebration of parish festival.

===Western Catholicism===
[[File:Jakub Schikaneder - All Souls' Day.jpg|thumbnail|''All Souls' Day'', painting by [[Jakub Schikaneder]], 1888]]

====Background====
In the [[Catholic Church]], [[Faithful (baptized Catholic)|&quot;the faithful&quot;]] refers specifically to baptized Catholics; &quot;all souls&quot; commemorates the [[church penitent]] of souls in [[Purgatory]], whereas &quot;all saints&quot; commemorates the [[church triumphant]] of [[saint]]s in Heaven. In the [[liturgical]] books of the western [[Catholic Church]] (the [[Latin Church]]) it is called the Commemoration of All the Faithful Departed ({{lang-la|links=yes|Commemoratio omnium fidelium defunctorum}}), and is celebrated annually on 2 November. In the ordinary form of the Roman Rite, as well as in the [[Personal Ordinariates]] established by [[Benedict XVI]] for former Anglicans, it remains on 2 November if this date falls on a Sunday;&lt;ref&gt;''Roman Missal'', &quot;The Commemoration of All the Faithful Departed&quot;, and &quot;Universal Norms on the Liturgical Year and the Calendar&quot;, 59&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Divine Worship: The Missal'', &quot;Commemoration of All the Faithful Departed (All Souls)&quot;, p.871&lt;/ref&gt; in the 1962–1969 form of the [[Roman Rite]], use of which is still authorized, it is transferred to Monday, 3 November.&lt;ref&gt;''Missale Romanum'' 1962, ''Rubricæ generales'', &quot;De dierum liturgicorum occurentia accidentali eorumque translatione&quot;, 96b&lt;/ref&gt; On this day in particular, Catholics [[pray for the dead]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Bregman |first=Lucy |title=Religion, Death, and Dying |year=2010 |publisher=ABC-CLIO |isbn=9780313351808 |page=45 |quote=The church also determined to observe 2 November as All Souls' Day, when Catholics pray for the souls of all who had died.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Catholic Church teaches that the purification of the souls in Purgatory can be hastened by the actions of the faithful on earth. Its teaching is based also on the practice of prayer for the dead mentioned as far back as 2 Maccabees 12:42–46.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/__P2N.HTM |title=Catechism of the Catholic Church – IntraText |publisher=vatican.va}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the West there is ample evidence of the custom of praying for the dead in the inscriptions of the [[catacomb]]s, with their constant prayers for the peace of the souls of the departed and in the early liturgies, which commonly contain commemorations of the dead. Tertullian, Cyprian and other early Western Fathers witness to the regular practice of praying for the dead among the early Christians.&lt;ref name=&quot;ODCC&quot;&gt;''Oxford Dictionary of the Christian Church'' (Oxford University Press 2005 {{ISBN|978-0-19-280290-3}}), article &quot;dead, prayer for the&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; The theological basis for the feast is the doctrine that the souls which, on departing from the body, are not perfectly cleansed from venial sins, or have not fully atoned for past transgressions, are debarred from the Beatific Vision, and that the faithful on earth can help them by prayers, alms deeds and especially by the sacrifice of the Mass.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mershman&quot;&gt;{{catholic |wstitle=All Souls' Day |inline=1 |volume=1 |year=1907 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Because [[Purgatory]] is outside of time and space, it is not necessarily accurate to speak of a location or duration in Purgatory.

====History====
In the sixth century, it was customary in Benedictine monasteries to hold a commemoration of the deceased members at Whitsuntide. In the time of [[St. Isidore of Seville]] (d. 636) who lived in what is today Spain, the Monday after Pentecost was designated to remember the deceased. At the beginning of the ninth century, Abbot [[Eigil of Fulda]] set 17 December as commemoration of all deceased in part of what is today Germany.&lt;ref name=&quot;new-catholic-2nd-all-souls&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=New Catholic Encyclopedia |date=2003 |isbn=0-7876-4004-2 |pages=290–291 |edition=Second}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to [[Widukind of Corvey]] (c. 975), there also existed a ceremony praying to the dead on 1 October in Saxony.&lt;ref name=Mershman/&gt; But it was the day after [[All Saints' Day]] that Saint [[Odilo of Cluny]] chose when in the 11th century he instituted for all the monasteries dependent on the [[Abbey of Cluny]] an annual commemoration of all the faithful departed, to be observed with alms, prayers, and sacrifices for the relief of the suffering souls in purgatory.&lt;ref name=Butler&gt;{{cite web |url=http://catholicsaints.info/butlers-lives-of-the-saints-saint-odilo-or-olon-sixth-abbot-of-cluni/ |title=Butler's Lives of the Saints – Saint Odilo, or Olon, Sixth Abbot of Cluni |date=20 January 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Odilo decreed that those requesting a Mass be offered for the departed should make an offering for the poor, thus linking almsgiving with fasting and prayer for the dead.

The 2 November date and customs spread from the Cluniac monasteries to other Benedictine monasteries and thence to the Western Church in general.&lt;ref name=ZENIT&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.zenit.org/en/articles/all-souls-commemoration |title=Edward McNamara, &quot;All Souls' Commemoration&quot; |work=ZENIT – The World Seen From Rome |accessdate=30 October 2014 |date=3 December 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Roman Catholic Diocese of Liège|Diocese of Liège]] was the first diocese to adopt the practice under [[Notker of Liège|Bishop Notger]] (d. 1008).&lt;ref name=Mershman/&gt; 2 November was adopted in Italy and Rome in the thirteenth century.&lt;ref name=&quot;new-catholic-2nd-all-souls&quot; /&gt;

In the 15th century the [[Dominican Order|Dominican]]s instituted a custom of each priest offering three Masses on the Feast of All Souls. During World War I, given the great number of war dead and the many destroyed churches where mass could no longer be said, [[Pope Benedict XV]], granted all priests the privilege of offering three Masses on All Souls Day,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.catholiceducation.org/en/culture/catholic-contributions/all-saints-and-all-souls.html|title=All Saints and All Souls|first=Super|last=User|website=www.catholiceducation.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; a permission that still stands.

====Liturgical practice====
In the Roman Rite as revised in 1969, if 2 November falls on a Sunday, the Mass is of All Souls, but the [[Liturgy of the Hours]] is that of the Sunday. However, public celebration of Lauds and Vespers of the Dead with the people participating is permitted. While celebration of a Sunday, a solemnity or a feast of the Lord replacing a Sunday begins on the previous evening with Vespers and perhaps evening Mass, the general norms do not allow for anticipation on Saturday evening of the liturgy of All Souls' Day falling on a Sunday, and so they suggest that the formula of the Mass on that Saturday evening is that of the solemnity of All Saints, which outranks the Sunday of Ordinary Time whose Mass would be celebrated on that evening.&lt;ref name=ZENIT/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Universal Norms on the Liturgical Year and the Calendar, &quot;Table of Liturgical Days&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; However, in 2014, the United States Conference of Catholic Bishops decided that for that year the Saturday evening (Sunday vigil) Mass in that country was to be that of All Souls; in countries such as Italy the situation was less clear.&lt;ref name=ZENIT14&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.zenit.org/en/articles/all-souls-day-and-the-vigil-mass|title=Edward McNamara, &quot;All Souls' Day and the Vigil Mass&quot;|date=29 October 2014 |work=ZENIT – The World Seen From Rome|accessdate=30 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In countries where All Saints' Day is not a [[holy day of obligation]] attendance at an evening Mass of All Saints on Saturday 1 November satisfies the Sunday obligation.&lt;ref name=ZENIT/&gt; In England and Wales, where holy days of obligation that fall on a Saturday are transferred to the following day, if 2 November is a Sunday, the solemnity of All Saints is transferred to that date, and All Souls Day is transferred to 3 November.&lt;ref name=ZENIT14/&gt; In pre-1970 forms of the Roman Rite, still observed by some, if All Souls Day falls on a Sunday, it is always transferred to 3 November.

In [[Divine Worship: The Missal]] the minor propers (Introit, Gradual, Tract, Sequence, Offertory, and Communion) are those used for Renaissance and Classical musical [[requiem]] settings, including the [[Dies Irae]].  This permits the performance of traditional requiem settings in the context of the Divine Worship Form of the Roman Rite on All Souls Day as well as at funerals, votive celebrations of all faithful departed, and anniversaries of deaths.&lt;ref&gt;''Divine Worship: The Missal'', pp.871–875 &amp; pp.1024–1032&lt;/ref&gt;

====All Souls' indulgence====
According to The Enchiridion of Indulgences, 
An indulgence, applicable only to the souls in purgatory, is granted to the faithful, who devoutly visit a cemetery and pray for the departed. The indulgence is plenary, under the usual conditions, each day from the first to the eighth of November; a partial indulgence is granted on any other days of the year.&lt;ref name=&quot;auto&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.catholic.org/prayers/indulgw.php|title=The Enchiridion of Indulgences – Prayers|first=Catholic|last=Online|website=Catholic Online}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&quot;Visit to a Church or Oratory on All Souls Day. PLENARY INDULGENCE. A plenary indulgence, applicable ONLY to the souls in purgatory, may be obtained by those who, on All Souls Day, piously visit a church, public oratory, or -for those entitled to use it, a semi public oratory.  It may be acquired either on the day designated as All Souls Day or, with the consent of the bishop, on the preceding or following Sunday or the feast of All Saints. On visiting the church or oratory it is required that one Our Father and the Creed be recited.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/tribunals/apost_penit/documents/rc_trib_appen_doc_20020826_enchiridion-indulgentiarum_lt.html |publisher=Libreria Editrice Vaticana |year=1999 |edition=16 iulii 1999 – Quarta editio |title=Enchiridion Indulgentiarum |language=Latin |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100114232116/http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/tribunals/apost_penit/documents/rc_trib_appen_doc_20020826_enchiridion-indulgentiarum_lt.html |archivedate=14 January 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|N.15}}&lt;ref name=&quot;auto&quot;/&gt;

===Lutheran Churches===
[[File:Alla helgons dag vid Röke kyrka-1.jpg|A [[churchyard|graveyard]] outside a [[Lutheranism|Lutheran]] church in the Swedish city of [[Röke]] during Allhallowtide|250px|thumb|right]]
Among continental [[Protestantism|Protestants]] its tradition has been more tenaciously maintained. During [[Martin Luther (religious leader)|Luther's]] lifetime, All Souls' Day was widely observed in [[Saxony]] although the Roman Catholic meaning of the day was discarded;&lt;ref name=&quot;Chisholm1911&quot;&gt;{{EB1911|inline=1|wstitle=All Souls' Day}}&lt;/ref&gt; ecclesiastically in the [[Lutheran Church]], the day was merged with, and is often seen as an extension of All Saints' Day,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=St. Paul's Lutheran Church of Wurtemburg |last=Isaacs |first=Linda A. |date=6 November 2011 |publisher=[[Evangelical Lutheran Conference &amp; Ministerium of North America]] |quote=In fact, the Lutheran tradition lumps &quot;All Saints Day&quot; and &quot;All Souls Day&quot; together because we believe that we are all saints through our faith! }}&lt;/ref&gt; with many Lutherans still visiting and decorating graves on all the days of Allhallowtide, including All Souls' Day.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Venbrux |first1=Eric |last2=Quartier |first2=Thomas |last3=Venhorst|first3=Claudia|first4=Brenda |last4=Mathijssen|title=Changing European Death Ways |date=12 January 2013 |publisher=LIT Verlag Münster |isbn=9783643900678 |page=183 |quote=The way in which graveyards in Denmark are looked after suggests that they are deemed important. ... they are in the hands of the Lutheran church ... Furthermore, special attention to the graves is paid by decorating them in the month of Christmas, at Easter and on All Souls' day. Aagedal (2010) writes that folk-church religiosity in Norway is best understood by looking at the burning of candles on graves.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Just as it is the custom of [[French people]], of all ranks and creeds, to decorate the graves of their dead on the ''jour des morts'', so [[German people|German]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Chisholm1911&quot;/&gt; [[Poles|Polish]] and [[Hungarians|Hungarian]] people stream to the graveyards once a year with offerings of flowers and special grave lights. Among [[Czech people]] the custom of visiting and tidying graves of relatives on the day is quite common. In 1816, [[Prussia]] introduced a new date for the remembrance of the Dead among its Lutheran citizens: [[Totensonntag]], the last Sunday before [[Advent]]. This custom was later also adopted by the non-Prussian Lutherans in Germany, but it has not spread much beyond the Protestant areas of Germany.

===Anglican Communion===
[[File:Leichhardt All Souls Anglican Church.JPG|right|thumb|[[All Souls Anglican Church, Leichhardt|All Souls Anglican Church]] in the [[Anglican Diocese of Sydney|Diocese of Sydney]], a parish dedicated to All Souls]]

In the [[Church of England]] it is called The Commemoration of the Faithful Departed and is an optional celebration; Anglicans view All Souls' Day as an extension of the observance of All Saints' Day and it serves to &quot;remember those who have died&quot;, in connection with the theological doctrines of the [[Resurrection of the dead|resurrection of the body]] and the [[Communion of Saints]].&lt;ref name=&quot;BaysHancock2012&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=Third&gt;{{cite book|last1=Armentrout|first1=Donald S. |last2=Slocum |first2=Robert Boak|title=An Episcopal Dictionary of the Church|url=https://books.google.com/?id=y_RpbmWNfHcC&amp;pg=PA7&amp;dq=All+Hallows'+Eve#v=onepage&amp;q=All%20Hallows'%20Eve&amp;f=false|accessdate=1 November 2012 |year=1999|publisher=Church Publishing, Inc.|isbn=0898692113|page=7|quote='''All Faithful Departed, Commemoration of.''' This optional observance is an extension of All Saints' Day. While All Saints' is to remember all the saints, popular piety felt the need to distinguish between outstanding saints and those who are unknown in the wider fellowship of the church, especially family members and friends. It is also known as All Souls' Day. Many churches now commemorate all the faithful departed in the context of the All Saints' Day celebration.&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[Anglican Communion]], All Souls' Day is known liturgically as the Commemoration of All Faithful Departed, and is an optional observance seen as &quot;an extension of All Saints' Day&quot;, the latter of which marks the second day of [[Allhallowtide]].&lt;ref name=Third/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://baptistnews.com/opinion/commentaries/item/29405-recovering-allhallowtide|title=Recovering Allhallowtide|last=Dickison|first=Scott|date=22 October 2014|publisher=[[Baptist News Global]]|accessdate=20 September 2015|quote=Within the greater tradition of the church, All Hallows' Eve and All Hallows'/Saints' Day are actually the first two days of &quot;Allhallowtide&quot;, with &quot;All Souls' Day&quot; being the final holiday of this three-day &quot;season&quot;.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Historically and at present, several Anglican churches are dedicated to All Souls. During the [[English Reformation]], the observance of All Souls' Day lapsed, although a new Anglican theological understanding of the day has &quot;led to a widespread acceptance of this commemoration among Anglicans&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Michno|first=Dennis G.|title=A Priest's Handbook: The Ceremonies of the Church, Third Edition|date=1 July 1998|publisher=Church Publishing, Inc.|isbn=9780819225047|page=160|quote=Though the observance of this day was abolished at the Reformation because of abuses connected with Masses for the dead, a renewed understanding of its meaning has led to a widespread acceptance of this commemoration among Anglicans, and to its inclusion as an optional observance in the calendar of the Episcopal Church.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Patricia Bays, with regard to the Anglican view of All Souls' Day, wrote that:&lt;ref name=&quot;BaysHancock2012&quot;/&gt;
{{quote|All Souls Day (November 2) is a time when we particularly remember those who have died. The prayers appointed for that day remind us that we are joined with the [[Communion of Saints]], that great group of Christians who have finished their earthly life and with who we share the hope of [[Resurrection of the dead|resurrection from the dead]].&lt;ref name=&quot;BaysHancock2012&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Bays|first1=Patricia|last2=Hancock|first2=Carol L.|title=This Anglican Church of Ours|year=2012|publisher=Wood Lake Publishing Inc.|isbn=9781770644397|page=128}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
As such, Anglican parishes &quot;now commemorate all the faithful departed in the context of the All Saints' Day celebration&quot;, in keeping with this fresh perspective.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Armentrout|first=Don S.|title=An Episcopal Dictionary of the Church|date=1 January 2000|publisher=Church Publishing, Inc.|isbn=9780898697018|page=7|quote=Many churches now commemorate all the faithful departed in the context of the All Saints' Day celebration.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Contributing to the revival was the need &quot;to help Anglicans mourn the deaths of millions of soldiers in [[World War I]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=English|first=June|title=Anglican Young People's Dictionary|year=2004|publisher=Church Publishing, Inc.|isbn=9780819219855|page=4}}&lt;/ref&gt; Members of the [[Guild of All Souls]], an [[Anglican devotional society]] founded in 1873, &quot;are encouraged to pray for the dying and the dead, to participate in a requiem of All Souls' Day and say a Litany of the Faithful Departed at least once a month&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Armentrout |first1=Donald S. |last2=Slocum |first2=Robert Boak |title=An Episcopal Dictionary of the Church|date=1 January 2000 |publisher=Church Publishing, Inc. |isbn=9780898692112 |page=232}}&lt;/ref&gt;

At the [[Protestant Reformation|Reformation]] the celebration of All Souls' Day was fused with [[All Saints' Day]] in the [[Church of England]]&lt;ref name=Episcopal&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.episcopalchurch.org/files/bi102812half_0.pdf |title=The Episcopal Church, &quot;All Saints' Day/All Faithful Departed&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt; or, in the judgement of some, it was &quot;deservedly abrogated&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://books.google.com/?id=xUhVAAAAcAAJ&amp;pg=PR59&amp;dq=%22all+souls%22+%22deservedly+abrogated%22#v=onepage&amp;q=%22all+souls%22+%22deservedly+abrogated%22&amp;f=false |title=The Book of Common Prayer ... With Notes ... by the Right Rev. Richard Mant ... Sixth Edition |date=5 July 1850 |publisher=Francis &amp; John Rivington}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was reinstated in certain parishes in connection with the [[Oxford Movement]] of the 19th century&lt;ref name=Episcopal/&gt; and is acknowledged in United States Anglicanism in the ''Holy Women, Holy Men'' calendar&lt;ref name=Episcopal/&gt; and in the Church of England with the 1980 ''[[Alternative Service Book]]''. It features in ''[[Common Worship]]'' as a [[Lesser Festival]] called &quot;Commemoration of the Faithful Departed (All Souls' Day)&quot;.

===Methodist Churches===
In the [[Methodist Church]], [[Saints in Methodism|saints]] refer to all [[Christians]] and therefore, on [[All Saint's Day]], the [[Church Universal]], as well as the deceased members of a [[local congregation]] are honoured and remembered.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Laura Huff Hileman|title=What is All Saint's Day?|url=http://upperroom.org/askjulian/default.asp?act=answer&amp;itemid=276387|quote=Saints are just people who are trying to listen to God's word and live God's call. This is &quot;the communion of saints&quot; that we speak of in the Apostle's Creed – that fellowship of believers that reaches beyond time and place, even beyond death. Remembering the saints who have helped extend and enliven God's kingdom is what All Saints Day is about.|publisher=[[The Upper Room (United Methodist Church)]]|year=2003|accessdate=31 October 2011|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120126142637/http://upperroom.org/askjulian/default.asp?act=answer&amp;itemid=276387 |archive-date=26 January 2012 |url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=The Rev. J. Richard Peck |title=Do United Methodists believe in saints? |url=http://www.umc.org/site/apps/nlnet/content3.aspx?c=lwL4KnN1LtH&amp;b=4746355&amp;ct=3166373 |quote=We also recognize and celebrate All Saints' Day (1 Nov.) and &quot;all the saints who from their labors rest&quot;. United Methodists call people &quot;saints&quot; because they exemplified the Christian life. In this sense, every Christian can be considered a saint. |publisher=[[The United Methodist Church]] |year=2011 |accessdate=31 October 2011 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120718063201/http://www.umc.org/site/apps/nlnet/content3.aspx?c=lwL4KnN1LtH&amp;b=4746355&amp;ct=3166373 |archivedate=18 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Methodist congregations that celebrate the liturgy on All Souls Day, the observance, as with Anglicanism and Lutheranism, is viewed as an extension of All Saints' Day and as such, Methodists &quot;remember our loved ones who had died&quot; in their observance of this feast.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.sheringhammethodist.org.uk/allsoulsdayservice.htm |title=All Souls Day Service |last=Sherwood |first=Colin |work=St Andrew`s Methodist Church |publisher=[[Methodist Church of Great Britain]] |accessdate=21 September 2015 |quote=During our All Souls Day Service on 2nd. November, as we remembered our loved ones who had died, some recently and other longer ago, candles were lit in memory of them and placed on a cairn built in front of the pulpit.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Christianity}} 
* [[Day of the Dead]]
* [[Festival of the Dead]]
* [[International Day of Prayer for the Persecuted Church]]
* [[Office of the Dead]]
* [[Prayer for the dead]]
* [[Thursday of the Dead]]
* [[Zaduszki]]
* [[Flowering Sunday]]
* [[Decoration Day (Appalachia and Liberia)]]
* [[Cemetery Sunday]]

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==Further reading==
* [https://www.catholicireland.net/the-liturgy-of-all-souls-day/ Tracey OSM, Liam. &quot;The liturgy of All Souls Day&quot;, ''Catholic Ireland'', 30 November 1999]

==External links==
{{Wikiquote}}
* {{cite web |url=http://www.transfigcathedral.org/faith/Bulgakov/0606.pdf |title=Saturday before Pentecost |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070630225412/http://www.transfigcathedral.org/faith/Bulgakov/0606.pdf |archivedate=30 June 2007}}&amp;nbsp;{{small|(17.1&amp;nbsp;KB)}} Notes on Russian Orthodox observance by N. Bulgakov
* {{cite web |url=http://www.transfigcathedral.org/faith/Bulgakov/0492.pdf |title=Saturday of Meatfare Week |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071129060838/http://www.transfigcathedral.org/faith/Bulgakov/0492.pdf |archivedate=29 November 2007}}&amp;nbsp;{{small|(13.9&amp;nbsp;KB)}} N. Bulgakov
* [http://en.radiovaticana.va/news/2016/11/02/pope_offers_mass_for_faithful_departed_on_all_souls_day/1269610 &quot;Pope offers Mass for faithful departed on All Souls' Day&quot;, Vatican radio, 2 November 2016]

{{Hallowtide}}
{{Liturgical year of the Catholic Church}}
{{Halloween}}
{{Authority control}}

[[Category:November observances]]
[[Category:Allhallowtide]]
[[Category:Eastern Orthodox liturgical days]]
[[Category:Christianity and death]]
[[Category:Observances honoring the dead]]
[[Category:Holidays based on the date of Easter]]&lt;!--Eastern Orthodox churches have movable days for this--&gt;</text>
      <sha1>ap8ddqpfpqle1c8hzaxih9euwtkk2co</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
