  <page>
    <title>Foreign relations of Armenia</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1098</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942965672</id>
      <parentid>942707741</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-28T00:09:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bsherr</username>
        <id>4386431</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>dating template message</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2015}}
{{Politics of Armenia}}
[[Armenia]] has maintained a policy of complementarism by trying to have positive and friendly relations with Iran, Russia, and the West, including the United States and the [[European Union]] since its independence.&lt;ref&gt;[http://times.am/2010/03/29/armenian-foreign-policy-between-russia-iran-and-u-s/ – &quot;Armenian Foreign Policy Between Russia, Iran And U.S.&quot; – 29 March 2010] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110724192109/http://times.am/2010/03/29/armenian-foreign-policy-between-russia-iran-and-u-s/ |date=24 July 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; It has full membership status in a number of international organizations and observer status, etc. in some others. However, the dispute over the [[Armenian Genocide]] of 1915 and the recent war over [[Nagorno–Karabakh]] have created tense relations with two of its immediate neighbors, Azerbaijan and Turkey.

==Foreign relations==
Armenia is a member of more than 50 different international organizations, including the following:
 
* [[Asian Development Bank]]	
* [[Commonwealth of Independent States]] and the [[Collective Security Treaty Organization]]
* [[Council of Europe]] 
* The [[EU]]'s [[Eastern Partnership]] and the [[Euronest Parliamentary Assembly]] 
* The UN's [[Eastern European Group]]
* [[Eurocontrol]]
* [[European Bank for Reconstruction and Development]]
* [[Eurasian Union]]	
* [[Eurasian Development Bank]] and the [[Eurasian Customs Union]]	
* [[Federation of Euro-Asian Stock Exchanges]]	
* [[International Bank for Reconstruction and Development]]
* [[International Monetary Fund]]
* [[Interpol]]
* [[La Francophonie]]	
* [[NATO]]'s [[Partnership for Peace]], [[Individual Partnership Action Plan]] and the [[Euro-Atlantic Partnership Council]]
* [[Organization for Security and Cooperation in Europe]]
* [[Organization of the Black Sea Economic Cooperation]]	
* [[United Nations]]		
* [[TRACECA]]
* [[World Trade Organization]], the [[World Bank]] and the [[World Customs Organization]]	

Armenia is also an observer member of the [[Community of Democratic Choice]], the [[Non-Aligned Movement]], the [[Organization of American States]], the [[Pacific Alliance]],&lt;ref&gt;https://armenpress.am/eng/news/981310.html&lt;/ref&gt; the [[Arab League]], the [[Community of Democracies]],&lt;ref&gt;https://community-democracies.org/?p=7783&lt;/ref&gt; a dialogue partner in the [[Shanghai Cooperation Organisation]], and a prospective member of the [[Asian Infrastructure Investment Bank]]. [[Zohrab Mnatsakanian]] serves as [[Minister of Foreign Affairs (Armenia)|Minister of Foreign Affairs of Armenia]].

==Armenian Genocide recognition==
{{see also|Armenian Genocide recognition}}
[[File:Nations recognising the Armenian Genocide.svg|left|thumb|200px|
{{legend|green|Countries that officially recognize the events as genocide.}}
{{legend|#96C8A2|Countries where certain political parties, provinces or municipalities have recognized the events as genocide, independently from the government as a whole.}}]]
As of 2020, 32 states have officially recognized the historical events as genocide. Parliaments of countries that recognize the Armenian Genocide include Argentina, Armenia, Austria, Belgium, Bolivia, Brazil, Bulgaria, Canada, Chile, Cyprus, Czech Republic, France, Germany, Greece, Italy, Lebanon, Libya, Lithuania, Luxembourg, the Netherlands, Paraguay, Poland, Portugal, Russia, Slovakia, Sweden, Switzerland, Syria, United States, Uruguay, Vatican City and Venezuela.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.armenian-genocide.org/current_category.7/affirmation_list.html|title=Resolutions, Laws, and Declarations|website=www.armenian-genocide.org|access-date=2016-06-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, some regional governments of countries recognize the Armenian genocide too, such as [[New South Wales]] and [[South Australia]] in Australia&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://armenianweekly.com/2009/03/25/south-australia-passes-armenian-genocide-motion/|title=South Australia Passes Armenian Genocide Motion|last=Hairenik|date=25 March 2009|website=Armenian Weekly|access-date=2016-06-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.parliament.nsw.gov.au/prod/parlment/hansart.nsf/V3Key/LA19970417004 |title=Armenian Genocide Commemoration - 17/04/1997 - NSW Parliament |date=19 January 2012 |access-date=6 June 2016 |url-status=unfit |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120119075550/http://www.parliament.nsw.gov.au/prod/parlment/hansart.nsf/V3Key/LA19970417004 |archivedate=19 January 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as Scotland, Northern Ireland and Wales in the United Kingdom.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.am/eng/news/12175.html|title=Scotland, North Ireland and Wales recognize Armenian Genocide|website=news.am|access-date=2016-06-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.am/eng/news/155362.html|title=Parliament of Scotland passes motion on Armenian Genocide|website=news.am|access-date=2016-06-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[US House Resolution 106]] was introduced on 30 January 2007, and later referred to the House Committee on Foreign Affairs. The bill has 225 co-sponsors.&lt;ref&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20070927173509/http://www3.capwiz.com/y/issues/bills/?billnum=H.RES.106&amp;congress=110 ]&lt;/ref&gt; The bill called for former President [[George W. Bush]] to recognize and use the word genocide in his annual 24 April speech which he never used. His successor President [[Barack Obama]] expressed his desire to recognize the Armenian Genocide during the electoral campaigns,&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|last=hyebiz|title=Sen. Barack Obama Discusses Armenian Genocide ...|date=2008-01-30|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JwR83GZjwdo|access-date=6 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; but after being elected, has not used the word &quot;genocide&quot; to describe the events that occurred in 1915.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.politifact.com/truth-o-meter/promises/obameter/promise/511/recognize-armenian-genocide/|title=Recognize the Armenian genocide|website=PolitiFact|access-date=6 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The US [[United States House of Representatives|House of Representatives]] formally recognized the Armenian Genocide with House Resolution 296 on 29 October 2019.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bbc.com/news/world-europe-50229787?ocid=socialflow_twitter|title=US House votes to recognize Armenian genocide|website=BBC|date=30 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; As of 2020, 49 out of 50 US states have also recognized the events as genocide.

==Disputes==

=== Nagorno-Karabakh and independent republic ===
{{see also|Nagorno-Karabakh conflict}}
Armenia provides political, material and military support to the [[Republic of Artsakh]] in the longstanding [[Nagorno-Karabakh conflict]] against the Azerbaijani government.

The current conflict over Nagorno-Karabakh began in 1988 when Armenian demonstrations against Azerbaijani rule broke out in Nagorno–Karabakh and later in Armenia and the Nagorno-Karabakh [[Supreme Soviet]] voted to secede from Azerbaijan and join Armenia. Soon, violence broke out against Armenians in Azerbaijan and Azeris in Armenia. In 1990, after violent episodes in Nagorno–Karabakh and Azerbaijani cities like [[Baku]], [[Sumgait]] and [[Kirovabad]], Moscow declared a state of emergency in Karabakh, sending troops to the region, and [[Black January|forcibly occupied Baku]], killing over a hundred civilians. In April 1991, Azerbaijani militia and Soviet forces targeted Armenian populations in Karabakh, known as [[Operation Ring]]. Moscow also deployed troops to [[Yerevan]]. Following the collapse of the [[Soviet Union]], conflict escalated into a full-scale war between the Nagorno-Karabakh Republic, supported by Armenia and Azerbaijan. Military action was influenced by the Russian military, which inspired and manipulated the rivalry between the two neighbouring sides in order to keep both under control.{{Citation needed|date=June 2015}}

More than 30,000 people were killed in the fighting during the period of 1988 to 1994. In May 1992, Armenian forces seized [[Shusha]] and [[Lachin]] (thereby linking Nagorno-Karabakh to Armenia). By October 1993, Armenian forces succeeded in taking almost all of former NKAO, Lachin and large areas in southwestern Azerbaijan. In 1993, the [[UN Security Council]] adopted [[List of United Nations Security Council resolutions on the Nagorno-Karabakh War|four resolutions]] calling for the cessation of hostilities, unimpeded access for international humanitarian relief efforts, and the eventual deployment of a peacekeeping force in the region. Fighting continued, however, until May 1994 at which time Russia brokered a cease-fire between the three sides.

Negotiations to resolve the conflict peacefully have been ongoing since 1992 under the aegis of the Minsk Group of the [[Organization for Security and Co-operation in Europe]]. The Minsk Group is co-chaired by Russia, France, and the United States and has representation from Turkey, the U.S., several European nations, Armenia and Azerbaijan. Despite the 1994 cease-fire, sporadic violations, [[sniper]]-fire and [[land mine|landmine]] incidents continue to claim over 100 lives each year.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/?id=XMF3DAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA32&amp;lpg=PA32&amp;dq=Negotiations+to+resolve+the+conflict+peacefully+have+been+ongoing+since+1992+under+the+aegis+of+the+Minsk+Group+of+the+Organization+for+Security+and+Co-operation+in+Europe.+The+Minsk+Group+is+co-chaired+by+Russia,+France,+and+the+United+States+and+has+representation+from+Turkey,+the+U.S.,+several+European+nations,+Armenia+and+Azerbaijan.+Despite+the+1994+cease-fire,+sporadic+violations,+sniper-fire+and+landmine+incidents+continue+to+claim+over+100+lives+each+year.%5B#v=onepage&amp;q=Negotiations%20to%20resolve%20the%20conflict%20peacefully%20have%20been%20ongoing%20since%201992%20under%20the%20aegis%20of%20the%20Minsk%20Group%20of%20the%20Organization%20for%20Security%20and%20Co-operation%20in%20Europe.%20The%20Minsk%20Group%20is%20co-chaired%20by%20Russia,%20France,%20and%20the%20United%20States%20and%20has%20representation%20from%20Turkey,%20the%20U.S.,%20several%20European%20nations,%20Armenia%20and%20Azerbaijan.%20Despite%20the%201994%20cease-fire,%20sporadic%20violations,%20sniper-fire%20and%20landmine%20incidents%20continue%20to%20claim%20over%20100%20lives%20each%20year.%5B&amp;f=false|title=Azerbaijan Business and Investment Opportunities Yearbook Volume 1 Strategic, Practical Information and Opportunities|last=Inc|first=IBP|date=2016-04-14|publisher=Lulu.com|isbn=9781438776194|language=en}}{{self-published source|date=February 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{self-published inline|date=February 2020}}

Since 1997, the Minsk Group co-chairs have presented three proposals to serve as a framework for resolving the conflict. Each proposal was rejected. Beginning in 1999, the presidents of Azerbaijan and Armenia initiated a direct dialogue through a series of face-to-face meetings, often facilitated by the Minsk Group Co-Chairs. The OSCE sponsored a round of negotiations between the presidents in [[Key West]], Florida. U.S. Secretary of State [[Colin Powell]] launched the talks 3 April 2001, and the negotiations continued with mediation by the U.S., Russia and France until 6 April 2001. The Co-Chairs are still continuing to work with the two presidents in the hope of finding a lasting peace.

The two countries are still at war. Citizens of Armenia, as well as citizens of any other country who are of [[Armenian diaspora|Armenian descent]], are forbidden entry to the Republic of Azerbaijan. If a person's passport shows evidence of travel to Nagorno–Karabakh, they are forbidden entry to the Republic of Azerbaijan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ncsj.org/Azerbaijan.shtml |title=Azerbaijan Country Page of the ''NCSJ'' (advocates on behalf of Jews in Russia, Ukraine, the Baltic States &amp; Eurasia) accessed 23 May 2010 |accessdate=2010-05-26 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090308021931/http://www.ncsj.org/Azerbaijan.shtml |archivedate=8 March 2009 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;panarmenian.net&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.panarmenian.net/eng/world/news/25889/|title=Azerbaijan doesn't allow Armenians in the country|work=PanARMENIAN.Net|access-date=19 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2008, in what became known as the [[2008 Mardakert Skirmishes]], Armenia forces and Azerbaijan clashed over Nagorno-Karabakh. The fighting between the sides was brief, with few casualties on either side.&lt;ref name=&quot;regnum.ru&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.regnum.ru/english/943595.html |title=Azerbaijani president: Armenians are guests in Yerevan |publisher=[[REGNUM News Agency]] |date=17 January 2008 |access-date=21 April 2010 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090612043901/http://www.regnum.ru/english/943595.html |archivedate=12 June 2009 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Clear}}

==Countries with no diplomatic relations==
Armenia does not have diplomatic relations with the following countries (organized by continent):

=== Africa ===
* [[Botswana]], [[Lesotho]], [[São Tomé and Príncipe]], [[South Sudan]]

=== Asia ===
* [[Azerbaijan]], [[Pakistan]] (Pakistan does not recognize Armenia), [[Saudi Arabia]], [[Turkey]], [[Yemen]]

=== Europe ===
* [[Hungary]] (suspended by Armenia since 31 August 2012 due to [[Ramil Safarov]]'s extradition to Azerbaijan)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rferl.org/content/azerbaijani-officer-who-killed-armenian-officer-pardoned/24694081.html|title=Row Erupts After Azerbaijan Pardons Armenian Officer's Repatriated Killer|work=RadioFreeEurope/RadioLiberty|access-date=19 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://arka.am/en/news/politics/hungary_wants_to_restore_diplomatic_relations_with_armenia/|title=Hungary wants to restore diplomatic relations with Armenia|publisher=|access-date=19 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== North America ===
* [[Barbados]], [[Trinidad and Tobago]]

=== Oceania ===
* [[Marshall Islands]], [[Papua New Guinea]], [[Samoa]], [[Solomon Islands]], [[Tonga]]

Armenia also has no diplomatic relations with [[List of states with limited recognition|states with limited recognition]].

==Countries with diplomatic relations==
[[File:Armenia Diplomatic Relations.svg|thumb|center  |upright=3.2|Foreign relations of Armenia:{{legend|#008000|Diplomatic relations established}}{{legend|#ACACAC|No diplomatic relations established}}{{legend|#ff0000|Diplomatic relations suspended by Armenia}}]]

Armenia has diplomatic relations with 172 separate entities (including the African Union, Arab League, European Union, the [[Sovereign Military Order of Malta|Order of Malta]], and Vatican City).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/|title=Bilateral Relations|author=Helix Consulting LLC|access-date=19 February 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150222045118/http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/|archive-date=22 February 2015|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; These include: Afghanistan, Albania, Algeria, Andorra, Angola, Antigua and Barbuda, Argentina, Australia, Austria, Bahamas, Bahrain, Bangladesh, Belarus, Belgium, Belize, Benin, Bhutan,&lt;ref name=&quot;Bhutan&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/bt/|title=Armenia Establishes Diplomatic Relations with Bhutan&lt;!--8 October 2012--&gt;|date=12 February 2015|access-date=8 March 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110815191938/http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/bt/|archive-date=15 August 2011|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bolivia, Brazil, Brunei Darussalam, Bulgaria, Burkina Faso, Burundi, Cambodia, Cameroon, Canada, Cape Verde, Central African Republic, Chad, Chile, the People's Republic of China, Colombia, Comoros, Costa Rica, Côte d'Ivoire, Croatia, Cuba, Cyprus, Czech Republic, Denmark, Djibouti, Dominica, Dominican Republic, DR Congo,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://panorama.am/en/politics/2012/06/22/kongo-armenia/|title=Armenia to establish diplomatic relations with Congo|author=Helix Consulting LLC|publisher=|access-date=19 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; East Timor, Ecuador, Egypt, El Salvador, Equatorial Guinea, Eritrea, Estonia, Eswatini,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.armradio.am/en/2013/05/04/armenia-swaziland-establish-diplomatic-relations/|title=Armenia, Swaziland establish diplomatic relations|work=Public Radio of Armenia|access-date=19 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ethiopia, Fiji, Finland, France, Gabon, The Gambia,&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://armenpress.am/eng/news/950509.html|title=Diplomatic relations established between Armenia and The Gambia|last=|first=|date=October 10, 2018|website=armenpress.am|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Georgia, Germany, Ghana, Greece, Grenada,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://times.am/?l=en&amp;p=6368|title=Times.am – Armenia and Grenada established diplomatic relations|author=Sargssyan Studio|publisher=|access-date=19 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Guatemala, Guinea, Guinea-Bissau, Haiti, Holy See (Vatican City), Honduras, Iceland, India, Indonesia, Iran, Iraq, Ireland, Israel, Italy, Jamaica, Japan, Jordan, Kazakhstan, Kenya, Kiribati, North Korea, South Korea, Kuwait, Kyrgyzstan, Laos, Latvia, Lebanon, Liberia, Libya, Liechtenstein, Lithuania, Luxembourg, Madagascar, Malawi, Malaysia, Maldives, Mali, Malta, Mauritania, Mexico, Micronesia, Moldova, Monaco, Mongolia, Montenegro, Morocco, Mozambique, Myanmar,&lt;ref name=&quot;Myanmar&quot;&gt;[http://www.shanghaidaily.com/article/article_xinhua.asp?id=124459 Myanmar establishes diplomatic ties with Armenia]&lt;!-- 2013-2-8 --&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; Namibia, Nauru, Nepal, Netherlands, New Zealand, Nicaragua, Niger, Nigeria, North Macedonia,&lt;ref name=&quot;North Macedonia&quot;&gt;[http://www.macedonianembassy.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=50%3Abilateral-relations&amp;catid=50%3Abilateral-relations&amp;Itemid=81&amp;lang=en Established Full Diplomatic Relations of the Republic of Macedonia]&lt;!-- &quot;Armenia - 27 April 1993&quot; --&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.panarmenian.net/eng/news/103141/|title=Consul of Macedonia: good partner in Balkans beneficial to Armenia|work=PanARMENIAN.Net|access-date=19 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Norway, Oman, Palau, Panama, Paraguay, Peru, Philippines, Poland, Portugal, Qatar, Romania, Russia, Rwanda, Saint Kitts and Nevis, Saint Lucia, Saint Vincent and the Grenadines, San Marino, Senegal, Serbia, Seychelles, Sierra Leone, Singapore, Slovakia, Slovenia, Somalia, South Africa, Spain, Sri Lanka, Sudan, Suriname, Sweden, Switzerland, Syria, Tajikistan, Tanzania, Thailand, Togo, Tunisia, Turkmenistan, Tuvalu,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://asbarez.com/102114/turks-and-azeris-alarmed-that-tuvalu-may-recognize-artsakh/|title=Turks and Azeris Alarmed that Tuvalu May Recognize Artsakh|work=Asbarez News|accessdate=19 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Uganda, Ukraine, the United Arab Emirates, the United Kingdom, the United States of America, Uruguay, Vanuatu, Venezuela, Vietnam, Zambia and Zimbabwe.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.aaainc.org/info/armForel.php |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20061011114705/http://www.aaainc.org/info/armForel.php |url-status=dead |archive-date=11 October 2006 |title=U.S. – Armenia Relations |publisher=aaainc.org |access-date=12 November 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.armeniaforeignministry.com/ministry/embassiesList.html |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20040530095847/http://www.armeniaforeignministry.com/ministry/embassiesList.html |url-status=dead |archive-date=30 May 2004 |title=Armenian Embassies, Consulates And Representations |publisher=Armeniaforeignministry.com |access-date=12 November 2011 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://english.people.com.cn/english/200007/21/eng20000721_46059.html |title=Armenia to Establish Diplomatic Relations With Iraq |work=People's Daily |date=21 July 2000 |access-date=12 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dfat.gov.au/geo/armenia/armenia_brief.html |title=Armenia country brief |publisher=Dfat.gov.au |accessdate=12 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.qatar-conferences.org/new-democracy/viewlastnews.php?id=30 |title=Welcome in Sixth Doha Forum oN Dmocracy and Free Trade |publisher=Qatar-conferences.org |date=11 April 2006 |accessdate=12 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.panarmenian.net/news/eng/?nid=4365 |title=Armenia To Establish Embassy in Japan |publisher=Panarmenian.Net |date=8 January 2002 |access-date=12 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.armeniaforeignministry.com/pr_05/main.html |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20060507142540/http://www.armeniaforeignministry.com/pr_05/main.html |url-status=dead |archive-date=7 May 2006 |title=Ministry of Foreign Affairs of The Republic of Armenia Official Site |publisher=Armeniaforeignministry.com |accessdate=12 November 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.panarmenian.net/news/eng/?nid=20528 |title=Armenia and Chad Established Diplomatic Relations |publisher=Panarmenian.Net |date=27 December 2006 |access-date=12 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.panarmenian.net/news/eng/?nid=24708 |title=Armenia establishes diplomatic relations with Mauritania |publisher=Panarmenian.Net |date=31 January 2008 |accessdate=12 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.armenews.com/article.php3?id_article=41042 |title=Nouvelles d'Arménie en Ligne |publisher=Armenews.com |accessdate=12 November 2011 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20111004141313/http://www.armenews.com/article.php3?id_article=41042 |archive-date=4 October 2011 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.panarmenian.net/news/eng/?nid=26699 |title=Armenia, DPRK going to develop cooperation |publisher=Panarmenian.Net |date=23 July 2008 |accessdate=12 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.defacto.am/index.php?OP=71338881 |title=Де-Факто &amp;#124; Информационно-аналитическое агентство |publisher=Defacto.am |accessdate=12 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.orderofmalta.int/diplomatic-relations/862/sovereign-order-of-malta-bilateral-relations/?lang=en |title=Bilateral relations |author=Ordine di Malta |accessdate=19 February 2015 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20151203180316/http://www.orderofmalta.int/diplomatic-relations/862/sovereign-order-of-malta-bilateral-relations/?lang=en |archivedate=3 December 2015 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.panarmenian.net/news/eng/?nid=27488 |title=Armenia, Nigeria develop bilateral cooperation |publisher=Panarmenian.Net |date=28 October 2008 |accessdate=12 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=AZG Daily |url=http://www.azg.am/EN/2008122404 |title=Armenia Planning To Open Diplomatic Representations in Brazil, Lithuania, Finland And Japan |publisher=Azg.am |accessdate=12 November 2011 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110717045956/http://www.azg.am/EN/2008122404 |archive-date=17 July 2011 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/bd/ |publisher=Ministry of Foreign Affairs of Republic of Armneia |date=2 February 2015 |accessdate=28 August 2015 |title=Archived copy |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150927092111/http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/bd/ |archive-date=27 September 2015 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Notes on some of these relations follow:

===African Union===
* Armenia established diplomatic relations with the [[African Union]] on 25 October 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://panarmenian.net/eng/news/55764|title=Armenia, African Union to develop relations|author=|date=|work=PanArmenian.net|access-date=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
* The [[African Union Commission]] hailed the Armenian government's intention to have a representative in the AU, and expressed willingness to develop relations with Armenia. 
* The Representative of Armenia to the African Union is located in [[Cairo]], Egypt.

===Africa===
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin:auto;&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;width:15%;&quot;| Country
! style=&quot;width:12%;&quot;| Formal Relations Began
!Notes
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Algeria}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|30 December 1992}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 30 December 1992.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/dz/|title=Algeria - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|work=MFA.am|access-date=23 April 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170228075445/http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/dz/|archive-date=28 February 2017|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Angola}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|3 October 1994}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 3 October 1994.&lt;ref name=&quot;auto1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/bo/|title=Bolivia - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|work=MFA.am|access-date=23 April 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171227233258/http://mfa.am/en/country-by-country/bo/|archive-date=27 December 2017|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Benin}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|2 August 2007}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 2 August 2007.&lt;ref name=&quot;auto1&quot;/&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Burkina Faso}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|16 November 1992}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 16 November 1992.&lt;ref name=&quot;auto1&quot;/&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Burundi}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|28 May 1992}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 28 May 1992.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/bi/|title=Burundi - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|work=mfa.am|accessdate=23 April 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110815184218/http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/bi/|archive-date=15 August 2011|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Cameroon}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|28 May 2007}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 28 May 2007.&lt;ref name=&quot;auto1&quot;/&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Cape Verde}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|26 February 2007}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 26 February 2007.&lt;ref name=&quot;auto1&quot;/&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Central African Republic}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|September 2017}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 21 September 2017.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.panorama.am/en/news/2017/09/22/Armenia-diplomatic-relations/1838703}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Chad}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|26 December 2006}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 26 December 2006.&lt;ref name=&quot;auto1&quot;/&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Comoros}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|3 July 2008}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 3 July 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://armenpress.am/eng/news/524557/www.idealsystem.am|title=DIPLOMATIC RELATIONS ESTABLISHED BETWEEN REPUBLIC OF ARMENIA AND UNION OF COMOROS|author=|date=|work=armenpress.am|accessdate=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Congo}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|15 March 2007}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 15 March 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/cg/|title=Congo - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|date=|work=mfa.am|accessdate=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Cote D'Ivoire}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|13 May 1998}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 13 May 1998.&lt;ref name=&quot;auto1&quot;/&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Democratic Republic of Congo}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|10 November 2015}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 10 November 2015.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/press-releases/item/2015/10/11/min_congo/|title=Meeting of Foreign Ministers of Armenia and Democratic Republic of Congo - Press Releases - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|date=|work=mfa.am|accessdate=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Djibouti}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|22 May 2019}}
|
In October 2015, both countries Foreign Ministers met to discuss establishing diplomatic relations and possible ways of developing bilateral ties.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://news.am/eng/news/290227.html|title=Armenia and Djibouti plan to develop relations|author=|date=|work=news.am|accessdate=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Both countries officially established diplomatic relations on 22 May 2019 at the United Nations.&lt;ref&gt;[https://armenpress.am/eng/news/975886.html]&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Egypt}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|March 1992}}
| See [[Armenia–Egypt relations]]
* Egypt has an embassy in [[Yerevan]].
* Armenia has an embassy in [[Cairo]].
* Roughly 6,000 Armenians live in Egypt. See also [[Armenians in Egypt]]
|-
|{{Flag|Eswatini}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|3 May 2013}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 3 May 2013.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/sz/|title=Swaziland - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|last=LLC|first=Helix Consulting|work=mfa.am|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170113062025/http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/sz/|archive-date=13 January 2017|url-status=dead|accessdate=23 April 2017|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Ethiopia }}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|2 December 1993}}
|
* Both countries established diplomatic relations on 2 December 1993.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/et/|title=Ethiopia - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|work=mfa.am|accessdate=23 April 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170227193121/http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/et|archive-date=27 February 2017|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Armenia is represented in Ethiopia through its embassy in [[Cairo]], [[Egypt]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;/&gt;
* Ethiopia is represented in Armenia through its embassy in [[Moscow]], [[Russia]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;/&gt;
* In May 2016, it was decided that Armenia would open an embassy in Ethiopia's capital, Addis Ababa.
* There is a small community of Armenians in Ethiopia's capital [[Addis Ababa]]. See also [[Armenians in Ethiopia]]
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Eritrea}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|16 October 1994}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 16 October 1994.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/er/|title=Eritrea - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|date=|work=mfa.am|accessdate=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Equatorial Guinea}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|19 May 1992}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 19 May 1992.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/gq/|title=Equatorial Guinea - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|date=|work=mfa.am|accessdate=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Gabon}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|9 March 1994}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 9 March 1994.&lt;ref name=&quot;auto1&quot;/&gt;
|-
|{{Flag|Gambia}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|9 October 2018}}
|Both countries established diplomatic relations on 9 October 2018.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Ghana}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|29 May 1992}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 29 May 1992.&lt;ref name=&quot;auto1&quot;/&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Guinea}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|1992}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations in 1992.&lt;ref name=&quot;auto1&quot;/&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Guinea-Bissau}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|3 September 1992}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 3 September 1992.&lt;ref name=&quot;auto1&quot;/&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Kenya}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|13 July 1993}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 13 July 1993.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/ke/|title=Kenya - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|date=|work=mfa.am|accessdate=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Liberia}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|21 September 2017}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 21 September 2017.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://gnnliberia.com/2017/09/24/armenia-liberia-establish-diplomatic-relations/}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Libya}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|2000}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations in the year 2000.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/ly/|title=Libya - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|date=|work=mfa.am|accessdate=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Madagascar}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|25 June 1993}}
|
Diplomatic relations between Armenia and Madagascar were established on 25 June 1993.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/mg/|title=Madagascar - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|date=|work=mfa.am|accessdate=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Malawi}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|20 January 2012}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 20 January 2012.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/mw/|title=Malawi - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|work=mfa.am|accessdate=23 April 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170228075239/http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/mw/|archive-date=28 February 2017|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Mali}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|21 February 1994}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 21 February 1994.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/ml/|title=Mali - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|date=|work=MFA.am|access-date=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Mauritania}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|30 January 2008}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 30 January 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://armenpress.am/eng/news/520783/armenia-and-mauritania-establish--------------------------------diplomatic-relations.html|title=ARMENIA AND MAURITANIA ESTABLISH DIPLOMATIC RELATIONS|author=|date=|work=ArmenPress.am|access-date=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Mauritius}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|28 June 2013}}
|
Diplomatic relations between Armenia and Mauritius were established on 28 June 2013.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/mu/|title=Mauritius - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|date=|work=mfa.am|accessdate=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Morocco}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|June 1992}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations in June 1992.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/ma/|title=Morocco - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|date=|work=MFA.am|access-date=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Morocco has an honorary consulate in Yerevan
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Mozambique}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|13 September 1995}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 13 September 1995.&lt;ref name=&quot;auto1&quot;/&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Namibia}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|2 October 2006}}
|
Diplomatic relations between Armenia and Namibia were established on 2 October 2006.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/na/ | title=Bilateral Relations - Namibia | publisher=Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia | date=18 February 2015 | access-date=8 March 2017 | archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110815192139/http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/na/ | archive-date=15 August 2011 | url-status=dead | df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Niger}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|26 November 2016}}
|
Diplomatic relations between Armenia and Niger were established on 26 November 2016.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/press-releases/item/2016/11/26/min_oif_niger/| access-date=8 March 2017 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Nigeria}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|4 February 1993}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 4 February 1993.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/ng/|title=Nigeria - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|date=|work=mfa.am|accessdate=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Rwanda}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|2004}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations in 2004.&lt;ref name=&quot;auto1&quot;/&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Senegal}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|8 April 2004}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 8 April 2004.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/sn/|title=Senegal - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|date=|work=mfa.am|accessdate=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Armenia is represented by Senegal through its embassy in Moscow.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Seychelles}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|19 April 2006}}
|
Diplomatic relations between the two countries were established on 19 April 2006.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/sc/|title=Seychelles - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|work=mfa.am|accessdate=23 April 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170702135715/http://mfa.am/en/country-by-country/sc/|archive-date=2 July 2017|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Sierra Leone}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|22 March 2004}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 22 March 2004.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.armeniandiaspora.com/showthread.php?704-Armenia-Sierra-Leone-establish-diplomatic-relations|title=Armenia, Sierra Leone establish diplomatic relations|author=|date=|work=armeniandiaspora.com|accessdate=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Somalia}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|2001}}
|
Diplomatic relations between Armenia and Somalia were established on 28 June 2001.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.mfa.am/en/bilateral-relations/so]&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|South Africa}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|1993}}
|
Diplomatic relations between Armenia and South Africa were established on 23 June 1993.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/za/|title=South Africa - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|date=|work=mfa.am|accessdate=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Armenia is represented in South Africa through its embassy in [[Cairo]], [[Egypt]].&lt;ref name=&quot;dirco.gov.za&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dirco.gov.za/foreign/bilateral/armenia.html|title=Armenia (Republic of)|author=|date=|work=dirco.gov.za|accessdate=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* South Africa is represented in Armenia through its embassy in [[Kiev]], Ukraine.&lt;ref name=&quot;dirco.gov.za&quot;/&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|South Sudan}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt;
|
Armenia and South Sudan have not yet established diplomatic relations, however the Foreign Minister of Armenia stated that Armenia recognizes the Republic of South Sudan as an independent state on July 9, 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/ss/|title=SouthSudan - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|date=|work=mfa.am|accessdate=24 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Sudan}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|8 December 1992}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 8 December 1992.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/sd/|title=Sudan - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|work=mfa.am|accessdate=23 April 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110815175210/http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/tn/|archive-date=15 August 2011|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*  There is a small Armenian community in Sudan, most are concentrated in the Sudanese capital [[Khartoum]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Tanzania}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|1992}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations in 1992.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/tz/|title=Tanzania United Republic of - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|date=|work=mfa.am|accessdate=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Togo}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|14 November 2013}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 14 November 2013.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.mfa.am/en/bilateral-relations/tg|title=Armenia, Togo bilateral relations|author=|date=|work=News.am|access-date=9 April 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Tunisia}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|15 July 2002}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 15 July 2002.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/tn/|title=Tunisia - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|date=|work=MFA.am|access-date=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Uganda}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|28 June 2013}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 28 June 2013.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/ug/|title=Uganda - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|date=|work=mfa.am|accessdate=23 April 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170330084415/http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/ug/|archive-date=30 March 2017|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Zambia}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|1993}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations in 1993.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/zm/|title=Zambia - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|date=|work=MFA.am|access-date=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Zimbabwe}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|1992}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations in 1992.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/zw/|title=Zimbabwe - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|work=MFA.am|access-date=23 April 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170226212914/http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/zw/|archive-date=26 February 2017|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|}

===Americas===
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin:auto;&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;width:15%;&quot;| Country
! style=&quot;width:12%;&quot;| Formal Relations Began
!Notes
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Antigua and Barbuda}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|14 May 1993}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 14 May 1993.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/ag/|title=Antigua and Barbuda - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|date=|work=MFA.am|access-date=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Argentina}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|17 January 1992}}
| See [[Argentina–Armenia relations]]
* Argentina is represented in Armenia through its embassy in Yerevan.
* Armenia has an embassy in [[Buenos Aires]].
* Argentine parliament has recognized the [[Armenian Genocide]].
* Around 135,000 ethnic Armenians live in the country.
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20120219175135/http://www.mrecic.gov.ar/portal/seree/ditra/am.html List of Treaties ruling the relations Argentina and Armenia (Argentine Foreign Ministry, in Spanish)]
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Bahamas}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|21 September 2017}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 21 September 2017.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bahamas.gov.bs/wps/portal/public/gov/government/news/the%20bahamas%20establishes%20diplomatic%20relations%20with%20armenia/!ut/p/b1/vZTZbqMwFIafpQ-QYna4NCE47DE73ESQUAqEpUASwtMPlSqNZqR2bqb1kS8s_cefzmfJREJERNKmt7JIp7Jr08v7OeGONEAmhIxgCgoHgerTCs3qkEaYXAPxGgCfLAj-7EdeAIBKAui4JAY2TRIhEe1jwMujWex27g1fD25RevF4Gk93iiulc9KoNFvW0SLWsrewdV1V5-WSXcxhOU2TL-9eMnby7iJGTgLIOBRwUb8yo1sEjR8phQmZNztx0AHiAgcPONvqIdPuwU63gVltph6wY1Z2Od6RcanjYxbBEnPJcsO0C9irMNtBNOBzRnFnp6HDmFyuQBzkLuMtc-YbNT888ghIgm7pKX56-vDxxcD_8BkSydfKqI_AF8qtfdfkRLzG-M_uEXie8IgIMEe3evTqUi9OteDFW_z76EkaWQXm6HmB5TcPz7JJU9ZJSVL7NzdFSZP2qd-izdDYZddBOU_DHK6j_wW0KU9cgVuS030WuIj-biBibWGVyXsHyFKrCO6ngex3AZFt4u27Uk96V0rv95AzaHtH_jTw_7-hRiRl1jzfT80zeGYZkmVFkhI5iqd4kieCNmZ4uVBnef0bmDK-NKIDRGkuOn-fD0quXVQhQLxxajvIQF3jOlHpkus8GgAFlRAnJH19YXq1jXhrzgGrVLYVBpt1W7itabRR3sJSvHXOVRySq_KgKfFEGwVH4dp6dS_bbkvDaheW_hYFfrqVYhNJCDqGovm-phkS8qqwcm5HW57iEugmumtp7xjusc0psIXnt5jpBx88ZHHZl8iZmjE4Izk-x1MztEd-U8_HFsD6wGZF_UT0jX8zOEewXn6XuUr6BYZV4Nk!/dl4/d5/L2dBISEvZ0FBIS9nQSEh/}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Belize}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|12 February 1999}}||
Both countries established diplomatic relation on 12 February 1999.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/bz/|title=Belize - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|date=|work=MFA.am|access-date=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Bolivia}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|27 July 1992}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 27 July 1992.&lt;ref name=&quot;auto1&quot;/&gt;
* In 2014, Bolivia recognized the Armenian Genocide.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Brazil}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|17 February 1992}}
| See [[Armenia–Brazil relations]]
* Armenia has an embassy in [[Brasília]].
* Brazil has an embassy in Yerevan.
* In 2015, Brazil recognized the Armenian Genocide.
* There are between 80,000- 100,000 people of [[Armenian diaspora|Armenian descent]] living in Brazil.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Canada}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|31 January 1992}}
| See also [[Armenia–Canada relations]], [[Embassy of Armenia in Ottawa]], [[Armenian Canadian]]
* Armenia has an embassy in [[Ottawa]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://canada.mfa.am/en/|title=Embassy of the Republic of Armenia to Canada|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|date=|work=mfa.am|accessdate=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Canada is accredited to Armenia from its embassy in Moscow, Russia and an honorary consulate in Yerevan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.canadainternational.gc.ca/russia-russie/index.aspx?lang=eng|title=Embassy of Canada to Russia|first=Foreign Affairs Trade and Development Canada|last=Government of Canada|date=|work=canadainternational.gc.ca|accessdate=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In 2004, the parliament of Canada recognized the Armenian Genocide.
* There are approximately 65,000 Armenians in Canada
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20080526064932/http://geo.international.gc.ca/cip-pic/geo/armenia-en.aspx Canadian Ministry of Foreign Affairs and International Trade about relations with Armenian]
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Chile}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|15 April 1993}}
| See [[Armenia–Chile relations]]
* Armenia is accredited to Chile from its embassy in Buenos Aires, Argentina and maintains an honorary consulate in [[Santiago]].
* Chile is accredited to Armenia from its embassy in Moscow, Russia and maintains an honorary consulate in Yerevan.
* In 2007, Chile recognized the Armenian Genocide.
* There are around 1,600 people of [[Armenian diaspora|Armenian descent]] living in Chile.{{citation needed|date=June 2016}}
Chile [[Recognition of the Armenian Genocide|recognized]] the [[Armenian Genocide]] on 14 September 2007.&lt;ref name=&quot;consejo&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title=El Consejo Nacional Armenio del Uruguay fue recibido en la Embajada de Chile | date=21 May 2007 | publisher= [[International Armenian Network]] | url=http://www.ian.cc/notas/noticias_ian.php?id=1003 }}. Fuente [[Diario Armenia]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.hairenik.com/armenianweekly/col06160701p.htm | title = Chile Proves Genocide Recognition is Based on Truth, Not Lobbying | publisher = Armenian Weekly | first = Harut | last = Sassounian | volume = 73 | number = 24 | date = 16 June 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.senado.cl/prontus_senado/antialone.html?page=http://www.senado.cl/prontus_senado/site/artic/20070914/pags/20070914115407.html&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Colombia}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|22 December 1994}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 22 December 1994.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/co/|title=Colombia - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|work=mfa.am|accessdate=23 April 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170702160759/http://mfa.am/en/country-by-country/co/|archive-date=2 July 2017|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The city of [[Armenia, Colombia]] was renamed after Armenia in memory of the victims of the Armenian Genocide.
* There are mainly 250 people of Armenian descent.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.soyarmenio.com.ar/2014/01/el-nombre-armenia-en-colombia-por.html Jan 29, 2014&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Costa Rica}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|8 April 1997}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 8 April 1997.&lt;ref name=&quot;auto1&quot;/&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Cuba}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|27 March 1992}}
|
* Both countries established diplomatic relations on 27 March 1992.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/cu/|title=Cuba - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|work=mfa.am|accessdate=23 April 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170702183505/http://mfa.am/en/country-by-country/cu/|archive-date=2 July 2017|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Armenia is represented in Cuba through its embassy in Mexico City, [[Mexico]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;
* Cuba is represented in Armenia through its embassy in [[Moscow]], [[Russia]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Dominica}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|8 April 2019}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 8 April 2019.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.armradio.am/en/10242|title=Armenia, Commonwealth of Dominica establish diplomatic relations|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|date=|work=armradio.am|accessdate=9 April 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.caribbeanwidenews.com/2019/04/12/dominica-establishes-diplomatic-relations-with-armenia/]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.dominicavibes.dm/news-257584/]&lt;/ref&gt;
.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.mfa.am/en/bilateral-relations/dm]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.mfa.am/en/press-releases/2019/04/05/us/9357]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;dominicanewsonline.com&quot;&gt;[https://dominicanewsonline.com/news/homepage/news/dominica-establishes-diplomatic-relations-with-armenia/]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;dominicanewsonline.com&quot;/&gt; 
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Dominican Republic}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|9 October 2007}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 9 October 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/do/|title=Dominican Republic - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|date=|work=mfa.am|accessdate=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Ecuador}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|20 May 1997}}
|
* Both countries established diplomatic relations on 20 May 1997.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/ec/|title=Ecuador - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|date=|work=mfa.am|accessdate=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Ecuador is a member of the [[Andean Parliament]] which recognized the Armenian Genocide in September 2016.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|El Salvador}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|22 March 1999}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 22 March 1999.&lt;ref name=&quot;auto1&quot;/&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Guatemala}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|29 June 1998}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 29 June 1998.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/gt/|title=Guatemala - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|date=|work=mfa.am|accessdate=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Guyana}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|24 October 2003}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 24 October 2003.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/gy/|title=Guyana - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|work=mfa.am|accessdate=23 April 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170420003722/http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/gy|archive-date=20 April 2017|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Greenland}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|14 January 1992}}
|
Armenia maintains relations with Greenland via [[Denmark]], established on 14 January 1992.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/dk/|title=Denmark - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|work=mfa.am|accessdate=23 April 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110815165225/http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/dk/|archive-date=15 August 2011|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Grenada}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt;{{dts|3 April 2012}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 3 April. 2012.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/gd/|title=Grenada - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|date=|work=mfa.am|accessdate=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Haiti}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|21 January 1999}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 21 January 1999.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/ht/|title=Haiti - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|date=|work=mfa.am|accessdate=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Honduras}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|16 September 2011}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 16 September 2011.&lt;ref name=&quot;auto1&quot;/&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Jamaica}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|1 December 1995}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 1 December 1995.&lt;ref name=&quot;auto1&quot;/&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Mexico}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|14 January 1992}}&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/mx/|title=Mexico – Bilateral Relations – Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|author=Helix Consulting LLC|work=MFA.am|access-date=19 February 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150219163904/http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/mx/|archive-date=19 February 2015|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| See [[Armenia–Mexico relations]]
* Armenia has an embassy in [[Mexico City]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/by-countries2/mx/|title=Mexico - By country - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|work=MFA.am|access-date=23 April 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160819220255/http://mfa.am/en/by-countries2/mx/|archive-date=19 August 2016|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Mexico is accredited to Armenia from its embassy in Moscow, Russia and an Honorary Consulate in Yerevan&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://embamex.sre.gob.mx/rusia/|title=Inicio|author=|date=|work=SRE.gob.mx|access-date=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://armenpress.am/eng/news/978527.html]&lt;/ref&gt;
* There are approximately 400 Armenians living in Mexico and several thousand Mexicans of Armenian descent.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.armeniadiaspora.com/population.html |title=ArmeniaDiaspora.com – News from Armenia, Events in Armenia, Travel and Entertainment – Armenian Population in the World |author=Hayk |work=ArmeniaDiaspora.com – News from Armenia, Events in Armenia, Travel and Entertainment |access-date=19 February 2015 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130511084353/http://www.armeniadiaspora.com/population.html |archivedate=11 May 2013 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''See also:'' [[Armenians in Mexico]]
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Nicaragua}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|6 July 1994}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 6 July 1994.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/ni/|title=Nicaragua - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|date=|work=mfa.am|accessdate=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Panama}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|7 August 1998}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 7 August 1998.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.mire.gob.pa/sites/default/files/documentos/Trasnsparencia/gestion-anual-2011-2012.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Paraguay}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|2 July 1992}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 2 July. 1992.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/py/|title=Paraguay - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|date=|work=mfa.am|accessdate=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In 2015, Paraguay recognized the Armenian Genocide.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Peru}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|20 April 1992}}&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;/&gt;
| 
* Peru recognized Armenia on 26 December 1991.
* Peru is represented in Armenia through its embassy in Moscow, Russia.
* There are around 50 people of [[Armenian diaspora|Armenian descent]] living in Peru.
* Peru is a member of the [[Andean Parliament]] which recognized the Armenian Genocide in September 2016.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Saint Lucia}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|17 October 2000}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 17 October 2000.&lt;ref name=&quot;auto1&quot;/&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Saint Kitts and Nevis}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|21 September 2017}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 21 September 2017.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.foreign.govt.kn/st-kitts-and-nevis-establishes-diplomatic-relations-with-armenia/}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Saint Vincent and the Grenadines}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|17 December 2004}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 17 December 2004.&lt;ref name=&quot;auto1&quot;/&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Suriname}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|24 July 1999}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 24 July 1999.&lt;ref name=&quot;auto1&quot;/&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|United States}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt;1920 &amp; 1991
| See [[Armenia–United States relations]]

The dissolution of the [[Soviet Union]] in December 1991 brought an end to the [[Cold War]] and created the opportunity for [[bilateral relations]] with the New Independent States (NIS) as they began a political and economic transformation. The U.S. recognized the independence of Armenia on 25 December 1991, and opened an embassy in Yerevan in February 1992.
* Armenia has an embassy in [[Washington, D.C.]], a consulate-general in [[Los Angeles]], and honorary consulates in [[Chicago]], [[Fresno]], and [[Las Vegas]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.usa.mfa.am/en/|title=Embassy of Armenia to the United States of America|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|date=|work=MFA.am|access-date=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The United States has an [[Embassy of the United States, Yerevan|embassy]] in Yerevan, which is the second-largest American embassy in the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://armenia.usembassy.gov|title=Home - Yerevan, Armenia - Embassy of the United States|work=USEmbassy.gov|access-date=23 April 2017|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170207002030/https://armenia.usembassy.gov/|archivedate=7 February 2017|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* As of 2019, 49 out of 50 US States have fully [[Armenian Genocide recognition#Position of the United States|recognized the Armenian Genocide]].
* The US House of Representatives recognized the Armenian Genocide on 29 October 2019.
* There are approximately 1,500,000 million Armenian-Americans.
* ''See also:'' [[Armenian American]]
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Uruguay}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|27 May 1992}}
| See [[Armenia–Uruguay relations]]
* Armenia is represented in Uruguay through its embassy in [[Buenos Aires]] (Argentina) and an honorary consulate in [[Montevideo]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mrree.gub.uy/protocolo/Misiones/GuiaMisionesA.htm#Armenia Uruguayan Ministry of Foreign Relations: directions of the representation of Armenia in Uruguay] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090721093446/http://www.mrree.gub.uy/protocolo/Misiones/GuiaMisionesA.htm#Armenia |date=21 July 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Uruguay is represented in Armenia through its embassy in Moscow (Russia) and through a consulate in Yerevan.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mrree.gub.uy/mrree/Embajadas_y_Consulados/Misiones/Scripts_Misiones/por_pais.idc Uruguayan Ministry of Foreign Relations: directions of the representation of Uruguay in Armenia]{{dead link|date=November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* There are around 20,000 people of [[Armenian diaspora|Armenian descent]] living in Uruguay.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt;
* Uruguay was the first country to [[Recognition of the Armenian Genocide|recognize]] the [[Armenian Genocide]] on 20 April 1965.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Venezuela}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|30 October 1993}}&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;/&gt;
| 
* Armenia has an honorary consulate in Caracas
* Venezuela is represented in Armenia through its embassy in Moscow, Russia.
* There are around 4000 people of [[Armenian diaspora|Armenian descent]] living in Venezuela.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt;
* Venezuelan parliament has recognized the [[Armenian Genocide]].
|}

===Arab League===
Armenia was granted Observer Status in the [[Arab League]] in 2004 after a Syrian invitation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://azad-hye.blogspot.ca/2005/01/observer-status-for-armenia-in-arab.html|title=Observer status for Armenia in the Arab League|author=|date=|work=azad-hye.Blogspot.ca|access-date=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Armenia maintains positive relations with most Arab states, with the exception of Saudi Arabia.
* A memorandum on mutual understanding and cooperation between Armenia and the Arab League was signed in January 2005.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.armeniandiaspora.com/showthread.php?16766-Armenia-Arab-League-sign-memo-on-mutual-understanding|title=Armenia, Arab League sign memo on mutual understanding|author=|date=|work=ArmenianDiaspora.com|access-date=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; The agreement promotes intensifying cooperation and the opening of Armenian diplomatic missions in Arab states.
* The Representative of Armenia to the Arab League is located in Cairo, Egypt.

===Asia===
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin:auto;&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;width:15%;&quot;| Country
! style=&quot;width:12%;&quot;| Formal relations began
!Notes
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Afghanistan}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|5 September 1996}}
||
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 5 September 1996.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/af/|title=Afghanistan - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|date=|work=MFA.am|access-date=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Artsakh}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|}}
||See [[Foreign relations of Artsakh]]
* The disputed region of Artsakh has very close relations with Armenia.
* A Representative Office of Artsakh was established in Yerevan.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Azerbaijan}}
|No diplomatic relations
|See [[Armenia–Azerbaijan relations]], [[Nagorno-Karabakh War]], [[Sumgait pogrom]], [[Baku pogrom]], [[Maraga massacre]], [[Khachkar destruction in Nakhichevan]]
The two nations have fought two wars in [[Armenian–Azerbaijani War|1918–20 (Armenian–Azerbaijani War)]] and in [[Nagorno-Karabakh War|1988–94 (Nagorno-Karabakh War)]], in the past century, with last one ended with provisional cease fire agreement signed in Bishkek. There are no formal diplomatic relations between the two countries, because of the ongoing Nagorno-Karabakh conflict and dispute.

During the Soviet period, many Armenians and Azeris lived in relative peace under the Soviet iron fist. However, when Mikhail Gorbachev introduced the policies of Glasnost and Perestroika, the majority of Armenians from the [[Nagorno-Karabakh Autonomous Oblast|Nagorno-Karabakh Autonomous Oblast (NKAO)]] of the [[Azerbaijan Soviet Socialist Republic|Azerbaijan SSR]] began a movement to unify with the [[Armenian Soviet Socialist Republic|Armenian SSR]]. In 1988, the Armenians of Karabakh voted to secede and join [[Armenia]]. This, along with sporadic massacres in Azerbaijan against Armenians resulted in the conflict that became known as the [[Nagorno-Karabakh War]]. The violence resulted in ''de facto'' Armenian control of former NKAO and seven surrounding Azerbaijani regions which was effectively halted when the three sides agreed to observe a cease-fire which has been in effect since May 1994, and in late 1995 the sides also agreed to mediation of the OSCE Minsk Group. The Minsk Group is co-chaired by the [[United States|U.S.]], [[France]] and [[Russia]], and comprises [[Armenia]], [[Azerbaijan]], [[Turkey]] and several [[Western europe during the cold war|Western European nations]]. Despite the cease fire, up to 40 clashes are reported along the Nagorno-Karabakh conflict lines of control each year.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}}

The sides are still technically at war. Citizens of Armenia, as well as citizens of any other country who are of Armenian descent, are forbidden entry to the Republic of Azerbaijan.&lt;sup&gt;[5]&lt;/sup&gt; If a person's passport shows any evidence of travel to [[Nagorno-Karabakh]], they are forbidden to enter the Republic of Azerbaijan.&lt;sup&gt;[54]&lt;/sup&gt;

In 2008, in what became known as the [[2008 Mardakert skirmishes|2008 Mardakert Skirmishes]], Armenia and Azerbaijan clashed over [[Nagorno-Karabakh Republic|Nagorno-Karabakh.]] The fighting between the three sides was brief, with few casualties on either side.&lt;sup&gt;[6]&lt;/sup&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Bahrain}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|October 1996}}
||
Both countries established diplomatic relations in October 1996.&lt;ref name=&quot;auto&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/kh/|title=Cambodia - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|work=MFA.am|access-date=23 April 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160325182747/http://mfa.am/en/country-by-country/kh/|archive-date=25 March 2016|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Bangladesh}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|11 November 1992}}
||
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 11 November 1992.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/bd/|title=Bangladesh - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|date=|work=MFA.am|access-date=23 April 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150927092111/http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/bd/|archive-date=27 September 2015|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* There is a small community of Armenians in the capital [[Dhaka]], the neighborhood of [[Armanitola]] was named after the Armenian Community. See also [[Armenians in Bangladesh]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Bhutan}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|27 September 2012}}
||
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 27 September 2012.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Brunei Darussalam}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|15 April 2012}}
||
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 15 April 2012.&lt;ref name=&quot;auto&quot;/&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Cambodia}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|14 May 1992}}
||
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 14 May 1992.&lt;ref name=&quot;auto&quot;/&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|China}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|6 April 1992}}
|| See [[Armenia–China relations]]
* China recognized Armenia on 21 December 1991.
* Armenia has an embassy in [[Beijing]].
* China has an embassy in Yerevan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://am.chineseembassy.org/ |title=Chinese embassy in Yerevan (in Chinese and Russian only) |publisher=Am.ChineseEmbassy.org |access-date=12 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Since the establishment of diplomatic relations, cultural exchange has been a major component of bilateral relations, as both nations recognize the importance of creating a strong foundation based upon their ancient and rich histories.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fmprc.gov.cn/eng/wjb/zzjg/dozys/gjlb/3130/ |title=Chinese Ministry of Foreign Affairs about relations with Armenia |publisher=Fmprc.gov.cn |access-date=12 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|East Timor}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|23 December 2003}}
||
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 23 December 2003.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.panarmenian.net/eng/world/news/8480/|title=ARMENIA ESTABLISHED DIPLOMATIC RELATIONS WITH TIMOR-LESTE REPUBLIC|author=|date=|work=PanArmenian.net|access-date=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flagicon image|Flag of the Eurasian Economic Union.svg}} [[Eurasian Economic Union]] (Organization)||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|2015}}
|| See [[Member states of the Eurasian Economic Union]] and [[Enlargement of the Eurasian Economic Union]]
* Armenia joined the [[Eurasian Union]] on January 2, 2015.
* Armenia is a member of the [[Eurasian Customs Union]] Free-trade area.
* Other members include Belarus, Kazakhstan, Kyrgyzstan, Russia and Observer member Moldova.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Georgia}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|17 July 1992}}
|| See [[Armenia–Georgia relations]]

Armenians and Georgians have a lot in common. Both are ancient Christian civilizations with their own distinct alphabets. Both use the terms &quot;Apostolic&quot; and &quot;Orthodox&quot; in the full titles of their respective churches. They also use the term &quot;Catholicos&quot; to refer to their church patriarchs. Despite all this, however, Armenians and Georgians have tended to have a tenuous relationship (at times, sharing close bonds while at other times regarding each other as rivals).

Today, relations with Georgia are of particular importance for Armenia because, under the economic blockade imposed by Turkey and Azerbaijan due to the ongoing [[Nagorno-Karabakh War|Karabakh conflict]], Georgia offers Armenia its only land connection with Europe and access to its [[Black Sea]] ports. However, because of Armenia's reliance on Russia and Georgia, both of whom fought the [[Russo-Georgian War|2008 South Ossetia wa]]&lt;nowiki/&gt;r and severed diplomatic and economic relations as a result; and as 70% of Armenia's imports entered via Georgia especially from Russia which has imposed an economic blockade on Georgia, Armenia also has been indirectly affected from this blockade as well. The development of close relations between Turkey and Georgia (such as the [[Baku–Tbilisi–Ceyhan pipeline|Baku-Tbilisi-Ceyhan oil pipeline]] and [[South Caucasus Pipeline|South Caucasus natural gas pipeline]]) have also weighed on the mutual relations. For example, on 20 March 2006, Georgian Ambassador to Armenia Revaz Gachechiladze stated, &quot;We sympathize with the sister nation but taking decisions of the kind we should take into account the international situation. When the time comes Georgia will do everything within the limits of the possible for the recognition of the Armenian Genocide by the international community including Georgia.&quot;&lt;sup&gt;[59]&lt;/sup&gt; However, Armenian-Georgian relations have begun to improve. On 10 May 2006, Armenia and Georgia agreed on the greater part of the lines of the state border between the two countries.&lt;sup&gt;[60]&lt;/sup&gt; The [[Javakheti-Armenian Uplands|Javakheti]] region in southern Georgia contains a large Armenian population and although there have been local civic organizations (such as United [[Javakheti|Javakhk]]) pushing for autonomy, there has been no violence between Armenians and Georgians in the area.
* Armenia has an embassy in [[Tbilisi]] and general consulate in [[Batumi]].
* Georgia has an embassy in Yerevan.
* There are roughly 170,000 Armenians in Georgia today.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|India}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|31 August 1992}}
|| See [[Armenia–India relations]]
* Since 1999, Armenia has an embassy in New Delhi and two honorary consulates [[Mumbai]], and [[Chennai]].
* India has an embassy in Yerevan.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.indianembassy.am/eng/main.html Indian embassy in Yerevan] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100227100947/http://www.indianembassy.am/eng/main.html |date=27 February 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Indian government]] is funding the renovation of schools in Lori region.
* Around 700 Medical students are studying in Armenian universities.
* Armenia recognizes [[Kashmir]] to be part of India and not of Pakistan.
* Armenia supports India's bid for permanent seat in the [[UNSC]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.indianembassy.am/relation.html |title=Armenia – India Bilateral Relations |publisher=Indianembassy.am |accessdate=12 November 2011 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20111028080319/http://www.indianembassy.am/relation.html |archivedate=28 October 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Indonesia}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|22 September 1992}}
||
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 22 September 1992.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/id/|title=Indonesia - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|work=MFA.am|access-date=23 April 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170702140639/http://mfa.am/en/country-by-country/id/|archive-date=2 July 2017|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Armenia has an embassy in [[Jakarta]]
* Indonesia has an honorary consulate in Yerevan
* Armenia's Representative to the [[Association of Southeast Asian Nations]] is also located in Jakarta.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.mfa.am/en/in-international-organizations/175]&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Iran}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|9 February 1992}}
||See [[Armenia–Iran relations]]

Despite religious and ideological differences, relations between Armenia and the Islamic Republic of Iran remain cordial and Armenia and Iran are strategic partners in the region. Armenia and Iran enjoy cultural and historical ties that go back thousands of years. There are no border disputes between the two countries and the Christian Armenian minority in Iran enjoys official recognition. Of special importance is the cooperation in the field of [[energy security]] which lowers Armenia's dependence on Russia and can in the future also supply Iranian gas to Europe through Georgia and the Black Sea.
* Armenia has an embassy in [[Tehran]].
* Iran has an embassy in Yerevan.
* An estimated 200,000 Armenians live in Iran. ''See also'' [[Iranian Armenians]]
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Iraq}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|2000}}
||
Both countries established diplomatic relations in the year 2000&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/iq/|title=Iraq - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|date=|work=MFA.am|access-date=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Armenia has an embassy in [[Baghdad]]
* Iraq has an embassy in Yerevan
* In 2015, Armenia announced it would establish a consulate general in [[Erbil]], the capital of [[Kurdistan Region]].
* Today it is estimated that there are around 15,000 Armenians in Iraq.
* Armenian is an official minority language in Iraq.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Israel}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|4 April 1992}}
||See [[Armenia–Israel relations]]

Since independence, Armenia has received support from Israel and today remains one of its major trade partners. While both countries have diplomatic relations, neither maintains an embassy in the other country. Instead, Ehude Moshe Eytam, the Israeli ambassador to Armenia is based in Tbilisi, Georgia, and visits Yerevan twice a month. Israel has recognized 24 Armenians as [[Righteous Among the Nations]] for risking their lives to save Jews during [[the Holocaust]].
* Israel has an honorary consulate in Yerevan.
* Armenia has an honorary consulate in [[Jerusalem]].
* Between 3,000 and 10,000 Armenians live in Israel. See [[Armenians in Israel]].
* One of the four quarters of the [[Old City (Jerusalem)]] is known as the [[Armenian Quarter]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Japan}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|7 September 1992}}
|See [[Armenia–Japan relations]]
* Armenia has an embassy in [[Tokyo]].
* Japan has an embassy in Yerevan.
* [http://www.mofa.go.jp/region/europe/armenia/index.html Japanese Ministry of Foreign Affairs about relations with Armenia]
* [http://japanarmenia.com/ Japanese and Armenian relations]
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Jordan}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|18 June 1996}}
||
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 18 June 1996.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/jo/|title=Jordan - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|work=MFA.am|access-date=23 April 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110815192737/http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/jo/|archive-date=15 August 2011|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Armenia is represented by a consulate in the capital [[Amman]].
* There are an estimated 3,000-5,000 Armenians living in the country today.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Kazakhstan}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|27 August 1992}}
|See [[Armenia–Kazakhstan relations]]
* Since 1992 Armenia first had its embassy in [[Almaty]] and later moved it to [[Astana]] (Nur-Sultan)).
* Kazakhstan has an embassy in Yerevan.
* Both countries are members of the [[Eurasian Union]].
* There are 25,000 people of Armenian descent living in Kazakhstan.
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20120419065538/http://portal.mfa.kz/portal/page/portal/mfa/en/content/policy/cooperation/CIS/07 Kazakh Ministry of Foreign Affairs about relations with Armenia]
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Kuwait}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|1994}}
|| 
* Armenia has an embassy in [[Kuwait city]].
* Kuwait has an embassy in Yerevan.
* There are around 6,000 people of [[Armenians|Armenian descent]] living in Kuwait.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Kyrgyzstan}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; 1993
|
* Both countries established diplomatic relations in January 1993 by protocol.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/kg/|title=Kyrgyzstan - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|date=|work=MFA.am|access-date=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Armenia is represented in Kyrgyzstan through its embassy in [[Nur-Sultan]], [[Kazakhstan]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/by-countries/kg/|title=Kyrgyzstan - Embassies - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|date=|work=MFA.am|access-date=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;  and an honorary consulate in [[Bishkek]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/consulates/kg/|title=Kyrgyzstan - Consulates - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|work=MFA.am|access-date=23 April 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170422045547/http://www.mfa.am/en/consulates/kg|archive-date=22 April 2017|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Kyrgyzstan is represented in Armenia through its embassy in [[Moscow]], [[Russia]] and an honorary consulate in Yerevan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/representations-by-countries2/kg/|title=Kyrgyzstan - By country - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|date=|work=MFA.am|access-date=23 April 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170623082101/http://mfa.am/en/representations-by-countries2/kg/|archive-date=23 June 2017|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Both countries are members of the [[Commonwealth of Independent States]], [[Collective Security Treaty Organization]] and [[Commonwealth of Independent States Free Trade Area]].
* Around 1,000 Armenians live in the country.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Laos}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; 1998
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 21 April 1998.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/la/|title=Lao People's Democratic Republic - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|work=MFA.am|access-date=23 April 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170702140719/http://mfa.am/en/country-by-country/la/|archive-date=2 July 2017|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Lebanon}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|4 March 1992}}
||See [[Armenia–Lebanon relations]]

Diplomatic relations between Armenia and Lebanon were established on 4 March 1992.

Armenian-Lebanese relations are very friendly. Lebanon is host to the eighth largest Armenian population in the world with around 160,000 Armenians in the country. Lebanon is the only member of the [[Arab League]], much less of the Middle East and the [[Islamic World]] that recognizes the [[Armenian Genocide]]. During the [[2006 Lebanon War]], Armenia announced that it would send humanitarian aid to Lebanon. According to the Armenian government, an unspecified amount of medicines, tents and fire-fighting equipment was allocated to Lebanese authorities on 27 July 2006.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.armenialiberty.org/armeniareport/report/en/2006/07/EB9E5465-7B17-4A96-B513-03AA0567FAB0.ASP Armenia To Provide Relief To Lebanon], Armenialiberty.org.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.panarmenian.net/news/eng/?nid=18992&amp;page=1 Armenia Sent Humanitarian Assistance To Lebanon], PanArmenian.Net&lt;/ref&gt;

In September 2009 Mr. Ashot Kocharian was appointed the Ambassador of Armenia in Lebanon. On 18 April 2013, the newly appointed Ambassador of Lebanon to Armenia Mr. Jean Makaron presented his credentials to the President of Armenia.

On 4 March 2016, Mr. Samvel Mkrtchyan was appointed the Ambassador Extraordinary and Plenipotentiary of the Republic of Armenia to the Lebanese Republic.

* Armenian is a recognized minority language in Lebanon.
* Armenia has an embassy in [[Beirut]].
* Lebanon has an embassy in Yerevan.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Malaysia}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|11 March 1993}}
|
* Armenia is represented in Malaysia through embassy in Jakarta (Indonesia).
* Malaysia is represented in Armenia through embassy in Moscow (Russia).
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Maldives}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; 1995
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 10 January 1995.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.foreign.gov.mv/v2/en/foreign-relations/bilateral-relations/ |title=Bilateral Relations : Ministry of Foreign Affairs |accessdate=2017-12-14 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150912081607/http://www.foreign.gov.mv/v2/en/foreign-relations/bilateral-relations/ |archivedate=12 September 2015 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Mongolia}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; 1992
|
* Both countries established diplomatic relations on 11 February 1992.&lt;ref name=&quot;mfa.am&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/mn/|title=Mongolia - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|work=MFA.am|access-date=23 April 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171227233929/http://mfa.am/en/country-by-country/mn/|archive-date=27 December 2017|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Armenia is represented in Mongolia through its embassy in [[Beijing]], [[China]].&lt;ref name=&quot;mfa.am&quot;/&gt;

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Myanmar}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|31 January 2013}}
||
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 31 January 2013.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/mm/|title=Myanmar - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|date=|work=MFA.am|access-date=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Nepal}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|26 March 1993}}
||
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 26 March 1993.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/np/|title=Nepal - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|date=|work=MFA.am|access-date=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|North Korea}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt;13 February 1992&lt;ref name=&quot;search.naver.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://search.naver.com/search.naver?sm=tab_hty.top&amp;where=nexearch&amp;ie=utf8&amp;query=%EB%B6%81%ED%95%9C%20%EC%95%84%EB%A5%B4%EB%A9%94%EB%8B%88%EC%95%84%20%EC%88%98%EA%B5%90|title=북한 아르메니아 수교 : 네이버 통합검색|trans-title=|language=|author=|date=|work=Naver.com|access-date=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|| 
* The establishment of diplomatic relations between the Republic of Armenia and the Democratic People's Republic of Korea (North Korea) started on 13 February 1992.&lt;ref name=&quot;search.naver.com&quot;/&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Oman}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|July 1992}}
||
Both countries established diplomatic relations in July 1992.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/om/|title=Oman - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|work=MFA.am|access-date=23 April 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110815183315/http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/om/|archive-date=15 August 2011|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Oman has an honorary consulate in Yerevan.

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Pakistan}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt;
|See [[Armenia–Pakistan relations]]
Armenia-Pakistan relations are poor owing to disagreements between the two countries. The main issue is the [[Nagorno-Karabakh conflict]]. Pakistan is a major supporter of Azerbaijan during and after the [[Nagorno-Karabakh War]]. Pakistan also does not recognize Armenia despite Armenia recognizing Pakistan.  Pakistan does not recognize the [[Armenian Genocide]] and maintains that during the war large number of [[Armenian people|Armenians]] and Muslims were killed.  Armenia also has friendly relations with India, which Pakistan heavily opposes.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Philippines}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|20 May 1992}}
|See [[Armenia–Philippines relations]]
* The Philippines has a consulate in Yerevan.
* Armenia has a consulate in [[Manila]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Qatar}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|5 November 1997}}
||
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 5 November 1997.&lt;ref name=&quot;auto&quot;/&gt;
* Approximately 5,500 Armenians live in Qatar, mostly in the capital [[Doha]]. See also [[Armenians in Qatar]].
* Armenia maintains an embassy in Doha.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Saudi Arabia}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt;
|| 
There are no diplomatic relations between Armenia and Saudi Arabia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/sa/ |title=Saudi Arabia – Bilateral Relations – Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia |publisher=MFA.am |access-date=12 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Singapore}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|1 July 1992}}
||
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 1 July 1992.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/sg/|title=Singapore - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|work=MFA.am|access-date=23 April 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150417172441/http://mfa.am/en/country-by-country/sg/|archive-date=17 April 2015|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|South Korea}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt;21 February 1992&lt;ref name=&quot;mofa.go.kr&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mofa.go.kr/ENG/countries/europe/countries/20070803/1_24643.jsp?menu=m_30_40|archive-url=https://archive.today/20151010192406/http://www.mofa.go.kr/ENG/countries/europe/countries/20070803/1_24643.jsp?menu=m_30_40|url-status=dead|archive-date=10 October 2015|title=Countries and Regions &gt; Europe &gt; List of the Countries|first=Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Republic of|last=Korea|work=MOFA.go.kr|access-date=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
||See [http://www.mofa.go.kr/eng/nation/m_4902/view.do?seq=76 Armenia–South Korea relations]
The establishment of diplomatic relations between the Republic of Armenia and the Republic of Korea began on 21 February 1992.
* The Republic of Korea and the Republic of Armenia Policy Consultation will deal with ways to vitalize high-level exchanges promote substantive cooperation and work together on regional and global issues.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mofa.go.kr/ENG/press/pressreleases/index.jsp?menu=m_10_20&amp;sp=/webmodule/htsboard/template/read/engreadboard.jsp?typeID=12&amp;boardid=302&amp;seqno=310308|title=Press &gt; Press Releases|first=Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Republic of|last=Korea|date=|work=MOFA.go.kr|access-date=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Armenia has an honorary consulate in [[Seoul]].
* The Republic of Korea has an honorary consulate in [[Yerevan]].
* Bilateral trade in 2014:
** Exports : $15&amp;nbsp;million (textile, automobile)
** Imports : $3&amp;nbsp;million (animal feed, rubber)
* The number of the South Korean citizens living in the Republic of Armenia in 2019 was about 373.
* [[Foreign relations of South Korea#Europe Foreign relations of South Korea Foreign relations of the Republic of Korea]].&lt;ref name=&quot;mofa.go.kr&quot;/&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Sri Lanka}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|12 February 1992}}
|| 
* Armenia is represented in Sri Lanka through the Embassy of Armenia in [[New Delhi]].
* Sri Lanka is represented in Armenia through its embassy in Moscow (Russia) and an honorary consulate in Yerevan.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Syria}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|1992}}
|| See [[Armenia–Syria relations]]
* Armenia has an embassy in [[Damascus]] and a consulate general in [[Aleppo]] and honorary consulate in Der ez-Zor .&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.armeniaforeignministry.com/ministry/embassiesList.html#Damascus |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20040530095847/http://www.armeniaforeignministry.com/ministry/embassiesList.html#Damascus |url-status=dead |archive-date=30 May 2004 |title=Armenian Ministry of Foreign Affairs: direction of the Armenian embassy in Damascus |publisher=ArmeniaForeignMinistry.com |access-date=12 November 2011 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Since 1997, Syria has an embassy in Yerevan.
* There are around 150,000 people of [[Armenian diaspora|Armenian descent]] living in the Syria.{{Citation needed|date=February 2009}} During the [[Armenian Genocide]], the main killing fields of Armenians were located in the Syrian desert of [[Deir ez-Zor]]. In 2015, the government of Syria recognized the Armenian Genocide.
* Armenian Ministry of Foreign Affairs: direction of the Syrian embassy in Yerevan&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.armeniaforeignministry.com/ministry/mid_2007.pdf|title=Armenian Ministry of Foreign Affairs: direction of the Syrian embassy in Yerevan|work=Archive.org|access-date=23 April 2017|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080828192535/http://www.armeniaforeignministry.com/ministry/mid_2007.pdf|archivedate=28 August 2008|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Tajikistan}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; 1992
|
* Both countries established diplomatic relations on 21 October 1992 by protocol.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/tj/|title=Tajikistan - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|work=mfa.am|access-date=23 April 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170702190332/http://mfa.am/en/country-by-country/tj/|archive-date=2 July 2017|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Armenia is represented in Tajikistan through its embassy in [[Ashgabat]], [[Turkmenistan]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/by-countries/tj/|title=Tajikistan - Embassies - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|work=MFA.am|access-date=23 April 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160408170334/http://www.mfa.am/en/by-countries/tj/|archive-date=8 April 2016|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;  and an honorary consulate in [[Dushanbe]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/consulates/tj/|title=Tajikistan - Consulates - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|date=|work=MFA.am|access-date=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Tajikistan is represented in Armenia through its embassy in [[Moscow]], [[Russia]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/representations-by-countries2/tj/|title=Tajikistan - By country - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|date=|work=MFA.am|access-date=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Both countries are members of the [[Commonwealth of Independent States]], [[Collective Security Treaty Organization]] and [[Commonwealth of Independent States Free Trade Area]].
* There are roughly 3,000 Armenians living in Tajikistan.

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Thailand}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; 1992
|
* Both countries established diplomatic relations on 7 July 1992 by protocol.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/th/|title=Thailand - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|work=mfa.am|access-date=23 April 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170702144543/http://mfa.am/en/country-by-country/th/|archive-date=2 July 2017|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Armenia has an honorary consulate in [[Bangkok]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/consulates/th/|title=Thailand - Consulates - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|date=|work=mfa.am|access-date=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Thailand is represented in Armenia through its embassy in [[Moscow]], [[Russia]] and an honorary consulate in Yerevan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/representations-by-countries2/th/|title=Thailand - By country - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|work=mfa.am|access-date=23 April 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170623115651/http://mfa.am/en/representations-by-countries2/th/|archive-date=23 June 2017|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Turkey}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; No formal diplomatic relations
|See [[Armenia–Turkey relations]]

Turkey was one of the first countries to recognize Armenia's independence in 1991. Despite this, for most of the 20th century and early 21st century, relations remain tense and there are no formal diplomatic relations between the two countries for numerous reasons. Some bones of contention include the unresolved Karabakh conflict between Armenia and Azerbaijan (which has resulted in Turkey imposing a blockade on Armenia that is still in effect today), the treatment of Armenians in Turkey, the Baku-Tbilisi-Ceyhan oil pipeline, and the Armenian claim of Turkey's holding of historic Armenian lands{{Citation needed|date=June 2015}}{{dubious|date=June 2015}} (ceded to them in the [[Treaty of Kars]], a treaty which Armenia refuses to recognize to this day since it was signed between the Soviet Union and Turkey, and not between Armenia and Turkey proper). At the forefront of all disputes, however, is the issue surrounding the Armenian Genocide. The killing and deportation of between one and one-and-a-half million Armenians from the [[Ottoman Empire]] orchestrated by the [[Young Turks]] is a taboo subject in Turkey itself as the Turkish government refuses to acknowledge that a genocide ever happened. However, since Turkey has become a candidate to join the European Union, limited discussion of the event is now taking place in Turkey. Some in the European Parliament have even suggested that one of the provisions for Turkey to join the E.U. should be the full recognition of the event as genocide.

On 5 June 2005, Armenian President Robert Kocharian announced that he was ready to &quot;continue dialogue with Azerbaijan for the settlement of the Nagorno-Karabakh conflict and with Turkey on establishing relations without any preconditions.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.panarmenian.net/news/eng/?nid=18307 |title=Yerevan Ready to Continue Dialogue with Baku for Karabakh Settlement |publisher=PanArmenian.net |date=5 June 2006 |access-date=12 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Armenia has also stated that as a legal successor to the [[Armenian SSR]], it is loyal to the Treaty of Kars and all agreements inherited by the former Soviet Armenian government.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
  | title = In Vartan Oskanian's Words, Turkey Casts Doubt on the Treaty of Kars With Its Actions
  | publisher = All Armenian Mass Media Association
  | date = 13 December 2006
  | url = http://www.mediaforum.am/armtoday.php?year=2006&amp;month=12&amp;day=13&amp;LangID=1
  | access-date = 13 December 2006
  | url-status = dead
  | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20071009175655/http://www.mediaforum.am/armtoday.php?year=2006&amp;month=12&amp;day=13&amp;LangID=1
  | archivedate = 9 October 2007
  | df = dmy-all
  }}&lt;/ref&gt; Yet Turkey continues to lay preconditions on relations, insisting that Armenia abandon its efforts to have the Genocide recognized, which official [[Yerevan]] is not willing to do.

In the wake of the [[2008 South Ossetia war]] between Russia and Georgia, Armenia and Turkey have shown signs of an inclination to reconsider their relationship. According to ''[[The Economist]]'' magazine, 70% of Armenia's imports enter via Georgia. Because of the apparently belligerent posture of the Russian state, economic ties with Turkey appear especially attractive.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Turkey and Armenia; Friends and Neighbors, rising hopes of better relations between two historic enemies&quot;, ''The Economist'', 27 September 2008, p. 67.&lt;/ref&gt;

It is estimated that around 70,000 Armenians live in Turkey today, down from nearly 2 million before the start of the Armenian Genocide in 1914. See [[Armenians in Turkey]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Turkmenistan}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|1992}}
|| 
* Armenia has an embassy in [[Ashgabat]].
* Turkmenistan has an embassy in Yerevan.
* Both countries are full members of the [[Organization for Security and Co-operation in Europe]].
* There are between 20,000 and 32,000 people of [[Armenians|Armenian descent]] living in Turkmenistan.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.haias.net/news/_armenian-population.html|title=ARMENIAN POPULATION IN THE WORLD|website=www.haias.net|access-date=5 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|United Arab Emirates}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|25 June 1998}}
|| 
* Diplomatic relations between Armenia and the UAE were established on June 25, 1998.
* Armenia has an embassy in [[Abu Dhabi]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.armeniaforeignministry.com/ministry/embassiesList.html#Abu%20Dhabi |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20040530095847/http://www.armeniaforeignministry.com/ministry/embassiesList.html#Abu%20Dhabi |url-status=dead |archive-date=30 May 2004 |title=Armenian Ministry of Foreign Affairs: direction of the Armenian embassy in Abu Dhabi |publisher=ArmeniaForeignMinistry.com |access-date=12 November 2011 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The United Arab Emirates has an embassy in Yerevan.
* There are around 3,500 people of [[Armenian diaspora|Armenian descent]] living in the United Arab Emirates.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.armeniadiaspora.com/followup/population.html ArmenianDiaspora website] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090204150034/http://www.armeniadiaspora.com/followup/population.html |date=4 February 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Armenian Ministry of Foreign Affairs: presentation of the Emirati ambassador's credentials to the Armenian Foreign Minister&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.armeniaforeignministry.com/PR/PR201.html|title=Ambassador of United Arab Emirates Presents Credentials|date=27 September 2004|work=Archive.org|access-date=23 April 2017|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20040927130450/http://www.armeniaforeignministry.com/PR/PR201.html|archivedate=27 September 2004|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Uzbekistan}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|25 June 1995}}
||
* Both countries established diplomatic relations on 27 October 1995 by protocol.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.uz/en/cooperation/country/?sphrase_id=2004455|title=Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Uzbekistan — States with which the Republic of Uzbekistan established diplomatic relations|author=|date=|work=MFA.uz|access-date=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/uz/|title=Uzbekistan - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|work=MFA.am|access-date=23 April 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170202065539/http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/uz/|archive-date=2 February 2017|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Uzbekistan is represented in Armenia through its embassy in [[Moscow]], [[Russia]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/representations-by-countries2/uz/|title=Uzbekistan - By country - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|work=MFA.am|access-date=23 April 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170202065420/http://www.mfa.am/en/representations-by-countries2/uz/|archive-date=2 February 2017|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Both countries are members of the [[Commonwealth of Independent States]] and [[Commonwealth of Independent States Free Trade Area]].
* Around 70,000 Armenians live in Uzbekistan.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Vietnam}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|14 July 1992}}
||
* Diplomatic relations between Armenia and Vietnam were established on 14 July 1992.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mofa.gov.vn/en/cn_vakv/euro/nr040819105821/ns070924160837 Ministry of Foreign Affairs of Vietnam]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Armenia has an embassy in [[Hanoi]].
* Vietnam is represented in Armenia through its embassy in Moscow, Russia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/vn/|title=Vietnam - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|work=MFA.am|access-date=23 April 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170702131920/http://mfa.am/en/country-by-country/vn/|archive-date=2 July 2017|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|}

===Europe===
{{further|Armenia–European Union relations}}
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin:auto;&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;width:15%;&quot;| Country
! style=&quot;width:12%;&quot;| Formal relations began
!Notes
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Albania}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|18 February 1993}}
||
* Armenia is represented in Albania through its embassy in [[Athens]], (Greece).
* Albania is represented in Armenia through its embassy in Athens, (Greece).
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Andorra}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|18 November 2003}}
||
* Armenia is represented in Andorra through its embassy in Paris, (France).
* Andorra is represented in Armenia through its embassy in Paris, (France).
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Austria}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|24 January 1992}}
||
* Armenia has an embassy in [[Vienna]].
* Austria has an honorary consulate in [[Yerevan]].
* Approximately 6,000 Armenians live in Austria. See [[Armenians in Austria]].
* In 2015, Austria recognized the Armenian Genocide.
* Armenia's permanent representative to the [[Organization for Security and Co-operation in Europe]] is located in Vienna.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Belarus}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|12 June 1993}}
||
* Armenia has an embassy in [[Minsk]].
* Belarus has an embassy in Yerevan and honorary consulate in [[Gyumri]].
* Both countries are full members of the [[Eurasian Union]].
* Approximately 30,000 Armenians live in Belarus, mainly in [[Minsk]]. See also [[Armenians in Belarus]].
* Armenia's permanent representative to the [[Commonwealth of Independent States]] is located in Minsk, Belarus.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Belgium}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|10 March 1992}}
||
* Armenia has an embassy in [[Brussels]].
* Belgium is represented in Armenia through its embassy in Moscow.
* Around 8,000 Armenians live in Belgium.
* Belgium recognized the Armenian Genocide in 1998.
* Armenia's permanent representative to [[NATO]] is located in Brussels. 
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Bosnia and Herzegovina}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|29 July 1997}}
||
* Bosnia is represented in Armenia through its embassy in Moscow.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Bulgaria}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|18 January 1992}}
|| See [[Armenia–Bulgaria relations]]
* Armenia has an embassy in [[Sofia]] and honorary consulates in [[Plovdiv]] and [[Varna]].
* Since 19 December 1999, Bulgaria has an embassy in [[Yerevan]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mfa.bg/yerevan/ Bulgarian embassy in Yerevan] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071219122252/http://www.mfa.bg/yerevan/ |date=19 December 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Both countries are full members of the [[Organization of the Black Sea Economic Cooperation]].
* There are around 50,000 people of [[Armenian diaspora|Armenian descent]] living in Bulgaria.
* In 2015, Bulgaria recognized the Armenian Genocide.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Croatia}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|8 July 1994}}
||See [[Armenia–Croatia relations]]
* Armenia is represented in Croatia through its embassy in Rome (Italy) and honorary consulate in [[Zagreb]].
* Croatia is represented in Armenia through its embassy in [[Athens]] (Greece) and honorary consulate in [[Yerevan]].
|-
|{{Flag|Cyprus}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|18 March 1992}}
||See [[Armenia–Cyprus relations]]
* Cyprus was the second country to recognise the [[Armenian Genocide]], on 24 April 1975.
* Armenia is represented in Cyprus through its embassy in [[Athens]] (Greece).
* Cyprus is represented in Armenia through its embassy in [[Moscow]] (Russia), and through an honorary consulate in [[Yerevan]].
* There are over 3.500 people of [[Armenian diaspora|Armenian descent]] living in Cyprus.&lt;sup&gt;[57]&lt;/sup&gt;
* Armenian is an official minority language in Cyprus.
* Vahan Ovanesyan of the [[Armenian Revolutionary Federation]] visited Cyprus on 24 January 2001 to take part in celebrations of the 110th anniversary of the federation.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Czech Republic}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|30 March 1992}}
|| 
* Armenia is represented in Czech Republic through its embassy in [[Prague]].
* The Czech Republic is represented in Armenia through its embassy in [[Yerevan]].
* The Czech Republic has recognized the Armenian Genocide.
* There are around 12,000 people of [[Armenian diaspora|Armenian descent]] living in the Czech Republic.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Denmark}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|14 January 1992}}
||See [[Armenia–Denmark relations]]
* Armenia is represented in Denmank through its embassy in [[Kopenhagen]], Denmark.
* Denmark is represented in Armenia through its embassy in [[Kiev]], Ukraine and honorary consulate in [[Yerevan]].
* On January 26, 2017, the Parliament of Denmark approved a resolution condemning Turkish violence and massacres against Armenians during the Armenian Genocide. 
* There are approximately 3,000 Armenians in Denmark.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Estonia}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt;{{dts|23 August 1992}}
|
* Armenia is represented in Estonia through its embassy in [[Vilnius]] (Lithuania) and an honorary consulate in [[Tallinn]].
* Estonia is represented in Armenia through its embassy in [[Athens]] (Greece) and through an honorary consulate in [[Yerevan]].
* There are approximately 3,000 Armenians in Estonia.
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20071012012830/http://www.vm.ee/eng/kat_176/978.html Estonian Ministry of Foreign Affairs about relations with Armenia]
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|European Union}} (Organization)||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt;{{dts|1991}}
| See [[Armenia–European Union relations]] and [[Future enlargement of the European Union]]
* Formal relations began in 1991 when Armenia gained independence from the [[Soviet Union]].
* In 2002, the [[European Parliament]] announced that Armenia could potentially join the EU in the future.
* A Comprehensive and Enhanced Partnership Agreement between the EU and Armenia was finalized in 2017.
* Armenia is a member of the [[Euronest Parliamentary Assembly]], the [[Council of Europe]], the EU's [[Eastern Partnership]] and [[Energy Community]].
* The Delegation of the European Union to Armenia Office is located in [[Yerevan]]. The Armenian Mission to the EU Office is in [[Brussels]].
* Since 2013, EU citizens enjoy visa-free travel to Armenia.
* In 2017, Armenia began talks on visa-liberalization for Armenian citizens traveling into the EU's [[Schengen Area]].
* Both the European Parliament and the Council of Europe have recognized the Armenian Genocide.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Finland}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|25 March 1992}}
|
* Before 1918, both countries were part of the Russian Empire. Finland recognised Armenia on 30 December 1991. Armenia is represented in Finland by a non-resident ambassador (based in Stockholm, Sweden). Finland is represented in Armenia by a non-resident ambassador (based in Helsinki at the Ministry of Foreign Affairs) and an honorary consulate in Yerevan. Around 1,000 people of Armenian descent live in Finland.
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20170801044422/http://formin.finland.fi/public/default.aspx?nodeid=17200&amp;culture=en-US&amp;contentlan=2 Finnish Ministry of Foreign Affairs about relations with Armenia]
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|France}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|24 February 1992}}
||See [[Armenia–France relations]]

Franco-Armenian relations have existed since the French and the Armenians established contact in the [[Armenian Kingdom of Cilicia]] and are close to this day. 2006 was proclaimed the Year of Armenia in France.
* Armenia has an embassy in [[Paris]] and honorary consulates in [[Lyon]] and [[Marseille]].
* France has an embassy in [[Yerevan]].
* There are around 750,000 Armenians in France. See also [[Armenians in France]].
* France recognized the Armenian Genocide in 1998.
* Armenia's permanent representative to the [[Council of Europe]] is located in [[Strasbourg]], France.
* Armenia's permanent representative to the [[Organisation internationale de la Francophonie]] is located in Paris, France.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Germany}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|January 1992}}
| See [[Armenia–Germany relations]]
* Armenia has an embassy in [[Berlin]] and honorary consulate in [[Karlsruhe]].
* Germany has an embassy in [[Yerevan]].
* Between 90,000-110,000 Armenians live in Germany today. See also [[Armenians in Germany]].
* Germany recognized the Armenian Genocide in 2005.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Greece}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|20 January 1992}}
||See [[Armenia–Greece relations]]

Greece was one of the first countries to recognize Armenia's independence on 21 September 1991, and one of those that have officially recognized the Armenian Genocide. Since the independence of Armenia the two countries have been partners within the framework of international organizations (United Nations, OSCE, Council of Europe, BSEC), whilst Greece firmly supports the community programs aimed at further developing relations between the EU and Armenia.

Continuous visits of the highest level have shown that both countries want to continue to improve the levels of friendship and cooperation (Visit by the President of Armenia Levon Ter-Petrossian to Greece in 1996, visit by the President of the Hellenic Republic Costis Stephanopoulos in 1999, visit by the President of Armenia Robert Kocharyan to Greece in 2000 and 2005 and visit by Greek president [[Karolos Papoulias]] to Armenia in June 2007).

Greece is, after Russia, the major military partner of Armenia. Armenian officers are trained in Greek military academies, and various technical assistance is supplied by Greece. Since 2003, an Armenian platoon has been deployed in Kosovo as part of [[Kosovo Force|KFOR]], where they operate as a part of the Greek battalion of KFOR. It is estimated that around 80,000 Armenians live in Greece.
* Armenia has an embassy in Athens.
* Greece has an embassy in Yerevan.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Holy See}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|23 May 1992}}
||
* Armenia maintains an embassy in the Vatican.
* In 2000, the Vatican recognized the Armenian Genocide.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Hungary}}||align=right| {{dts|26 February 1992}}&lt;br /&gt;—&lt;br /&gt;31 Aug 2012
|
See [[Armenia–Hungary relations]]
* Armenia was represented in Hungary through its embassy in [[Vienna]] (Austria).
* Hungary was represented in Armenia through its embassy in Tbilisi(Georgia) and an honorary consulate in [[Yerevan]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.kulugyminiszterium.hu/kum/en/bal/missions/missions_abroad/honorary_consulates/europe.htm |title=Hungarian Ministry of Foreign Affairs: direction of the Hungarian honorary consulate in Yerevan |publisher=Kulugyminiszterium.hu |accessdate=12 November 2011 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20111001140534/http://www.kulugyminiszterium.hu/kum/en/bal/missions/missions_abroad/honorary_consulates/europe.htm |archivedate=1 October 2011 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* There are around 30,000 people of [[Armenian diaspora|Armenian descent]] living in Hungary.
* Armenian is an official minority language in Hungary.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Iceland}}||&lt;!--start date --&gt;{{dts|1995}}
| 
* Iceland is represented in Armenia through its embassy in Moscow, Russia.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Ireland}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|13 June 1996}}
| 
* Ireland recognized Armenia's independence in December 1991.
* Armenia is represented in Ireland through its embassy in London and through an honorary consulate in [[Dublin]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.armenianembassy.org.uk/Ireland-armenia-bilateral.htm |title=Armenian embassy in London (also accredited to Ireland) |publisher=Armenianembassy.org.uk |accessdate=12 November 2011 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20101021223430/http://www.armenianembassy.org.uk/Ireland-armenia-bilateral.htm |archivedate=21 October 2010 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Ireland is represented in Armenia through its embassy in [[Sofia]] (Bulgaria) and through an honorary consulate in Yerevan.
* Both countries are full members of the [[Council of Europe]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.embassyofireland.bg/home/index.aspx?id=35062 |title=Irish embassy in Sofia (also accredited to Armenia) |publisher=Embassyofireland.bg |date=15 June 2011 |accessdate=12 November 2011 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110706142821/http://www.embassyofireland.bg/home/index.aspx?id=35062 |archivedate=6 July 2011 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* There is a small Armenian community in Ireland, mostly in Dublin.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Italy}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|12 May 1993}}
| See [[Armenia–Italy relations]]
* Armenia has an embassy in [[Rome]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://xoomer.alice.it/gbaghdas/Index.html |title=Armenian embassy in Rome |publisher=Xoomer.alice.it |accessdate=12 November 2011 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20081213153932/http://xoomer.alice.it/gbaghdas/Index.html |archivedate=13 December 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and honorary consulate in [[Milano]].
* Italy has an embassy in Yerevan and an honorary consulate in [[Gyumri]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ambjerevan.esteri.it/Ambasciata_Jerevan |title=Italian embassy in Yerevan |publisher=Ambjerevan.esteri.it |accessdate=12 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Italy has [[Recognition of the Armenian Genocide|recognized]] the [[Armenian Genocide]] in 2000.
* There are around 4,000 people of [[Armenian diaspora|Armenian descent]] living in Italy.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Kosovo}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt;
||See [[Armenia–Kosovo relations]]
* Armenia has not established diplomatic relations with Kosovo.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Latvia}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|22 August 1992}}
| 
* Armenia is represented in Latvia through its embassy in [[Vilnius]] (Lithuania).
* Latvia is represented in Armenia through a non-resident ambassador based in [[Riga]] (at the Ministry of Foreign Affairs) and through an honorary consulate in [[Yerevan]].
* There are around 5,000 people of [[Armenian diaspora|Armenian descent]] living in Latvia.
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20080621120238/http://www.am.gov.lv/en/policy/bilateral-relations/4542/Armenia/ Latvian Ministry of Foreign Affairs about relations with Armenia]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20110605110037/http://www.am.gov.lv/en/ministry/mission/?lv=1&amp;org=ARM Latvian Ministry of Foreign Affairs: direction if the Latvian representation in Armenia]
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Liechtenstein}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|7 May 2008}}
| 
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 7 May 2008.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Lithuania}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|21 November 1991}}
| 
* Armenia has an embassy in [[Vilnius]].
* Lithuania has an embassy in [[Yerevan]].
* There are around 2,500 people of [[Armenian diaspora|Armenian descent]] living in Lithuania.
* Lithuania recognized the Armenian Genocide in 2005.
* [http://www.urm.lt/index.php?-1458231391 Lithuanian Ministry of Foreign affairs: list of bilateral treaties with Armenia (in Lithuanian only)]
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Luxembourg}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|11 June 1992}}
| 
* Armenia is represented in Luxembourg through its embassy in [[Brussels]], (Belgium), and an honorary consulate in [[Luxembourg (city)|Luxembourg]].
* Luxembourg maintains a consulate in Yerevan.
* Luxembourg recognized the Armenian Genocide in 2015.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Malta}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|27 May 1993}}
| 
* Armenia is represented in Malta through its embassy in [[Rome]].
* Malta is represented in Armenia through its embassy in [[Warsaw]] and honorary consulate in Yerevan.
* Around 500 Armenians live in Malta.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Moldova}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|May 1992}}
|| 
* Armenia has an embassy in [[Chișinău]].
* Moldova is accredited to Armenia from its embassy in Kiev, Ukraine.
* There are around 8000 people of [[Armenian diaspora|Armenian descent]] living in Moldova.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Monaco}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|Oct 2008}}
| 
* Armenia is accredited to Monaco from its embassy in Paris, France.
* Monaco does not have an accreditation to Armenia.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Montenegro}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt;{{dts|7 November 2006}}
| 
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 7 November 2006.
* Montenegro has an honorary consulate in Yerevan.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Netherlands}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|30 January 1992}}
||See [[Armenia–Netherlands relations]]
* Armenia has an embassy in [[The Hague]] and honorary consulate in [[Hilversum]].
* The Netherlands is represented in Armenia through its embassy in [[Tbilisi]], Georgia. It made plans to open an embassy in Yerevan.{{Citation needed|date=March 2013}}
* There are between 12,000-20,000 people of [[Armenian diaspora|Armenian descent]] living in the Netherlands.
* The Netherlands recognized the Armenian Genocide in 2004.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=National |first=Global |url=http://www.canada.com/globaltv/national/story.html?id=a5f2efe0-1811-4d1c-a6a9-55198d792e40 |title=Harper affirms Canadian position on Armenian Genocide |publisher=Canada.com |date=19 April 2006 |accessdate=12 November 2011 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120225113011/http://www.canada.com/globaltv/national/story.html?id=a5f2efe0-1811-4d1c-a6a9-55198d792e40 |archivedate=25 February 2012 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Both countries are full members of the [[Council of Europe]].
* Both countries have the worlds{{Clarify|date=March 2013}} third largest trade of diamonds and second largest trade in between the countries.{{Citation needed|date=March 2013}} Both the Netherlands and Armenia have the worlds{{Clarify|date=March 2013}} top share in the diamond industry.{{Citation needed|date=March 2013}}
* [http://www.minbuza.nl/binaries/pdf/reizen-en-landen/betrekkingen-met-nederland/armenie.pdf{{dead link|date=September 2017 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }} Dutch Ministry of Foreign Affairs about relations with Armenia (in Dutch only)]{{dead link|date=March 2013}}
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|North Macedonia}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|27 April 1993}}&lt;ref name=&quot;North Macedonia&quot;/&gt;
| 
Both countries established relations on 27 April 1993.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Norway}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|5 June 1992}}
|| 
* Armenia is represented in Norway through its embassy in [[Kopenhagen]] (Denmark).
* Norway has an honorary consulate in Yerevan.
* Approximately 2,000 Armenians live in Norway.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Poland}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|26 February 1992}}
|| See [[Armenia–Poland relations]]
* Armenia has an embassy in [[Warsaw]].
* Poland has an embassy in Yerevan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.erewan.polemb.net/ |title=Polish embassy in Yerevan (in Armenian and Polish only) |publisher=Erewan.polemb.net |accessdate=12 November 2011 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100626025753/http://www.erewan.polemb.net/ |archivedate=26 June 2010 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* There are around 50,000 Armenians in Poland.
* See also [[Armenians in Poland]]
* Armenian is an official minority language in Poland.
* Poland recognized the Armenian Genocide in 2005.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Portugal}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|25 May 1992}}
||See [[Armenia–Portugal relations]]
* Armenia is represented in Portugal through its embassy in Rome (Italy) and honorary consulates in [[Lisbon]] and [[Porto]].
* Portugal is represented in Armenia through its embassy in Moscow (Russia) and an honorary consulate in Yerevan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.armeniaforeignministry.com/ministry/embassiesList.html |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20040530095847/http://www.armeniaforeignministry.com/ministry/embassiesList.html |url-status=dead |archive-date=30 May 2004 |title=Armenians embassies around the world |accessdate=10 May 2009 |publisher=Armenian Ministry of Foreign Affairs |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Portugal recognized the Armenian Genocide in 2019.

One of the most notable Armenians who resided in Portugal was [[Calouste Gulbenkian]]. He was a wealthy Armenian businessman and philanthropist, who made [[Lisbon]] the headquarters for his businesses. He established the international charity, the [[Calouste Gulbenkian Foundation]] in Lisbon. He also founded the [[Museu Calouste Gulbenkian]] in Lisbon.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author2= |title=Calouste Gulbenkian Dies at 86. One of the Richest Men in the World. Oil Financier, Art Collector Lived in Obscurity, Drove in Rented Automobile. |url=https://www.nytimes.com/1955/07/21/archives/calouste-gulbenkian-dies-at-86-one-of-richest-men-in-the-world-oit.html |quote= |work=New York Times |date=21 July 1955 |accessdate=7 May 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author2= |title=Solid Gold Scrooge |url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,810402,00.html |quote= |work=[[Time (magazine)|Time]] |date=23 July 1958 |accessdate=7 May 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Romania}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|17 November 1991}}
||See [[Armenia–Romania relations]]
* Armenia has an embassy in [[Bucharest]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mae.ro/index.php?unde=doc&amp;id=5841&amp;idlnk=4&amp;cat=6 |title=Romanian Ministry of Foreign Affairs: direction of the Armenian embassy in Bucharest |publisher=Mae.ro |accessdate=12 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Romania has an embassy in Yerevan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mae.ro/index.php?unde=doc&amp;id=6207&amp;idlnk=4&amp;cat=6 |title=Romanian Ministry of Foreign Affairs: direction of the Romania embassy in Yerevan |publisher=Mae.ro |accessdate=12 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Around 10,000 Armenians live in Romania.
* Armenian is an official minority language in Romania.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Russia}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|3 April 1992}}
||See [[Armenia–Russia relations]]

Armenia's most notable recent foreign policy success came with 29 August treaty with Russia on friendship, cooperation and mutual assistance, in which Moscow committed itself to the defense of Armenia should it be attacked by a third party. Russia is the key regional security player, and has proved a valuable historical ally for Armenia. Although it appeared as a response to Aliyev's US trip, the treaty had probably long been under development. However, it is clear from the wider context of Armenian foreign policy that—while Yerevan welcomes the Russian security guarantee—the country does not want to rely exclusively on Moscow, nor to become part of a confrontation between Russian and US-led alliances in the Transcaucasus.
* Armenia has an embassy in [[Moscow]] and general consulates [[Dony Rostov]] and [[Sankt Peterburg]] and honorary consulates in [[Kaliningrad]] and [[Sochi]].
* Russia has an embassy in Yerevan and general consulate in [[Gyumri]].
* Armenia's permanent representative to the [[Collective Security Treaty Organization]] is located in Moscow.
* Russia has recognized the Armenian Genocide in 1995.
* Armenia joined the Russian-led [[Eurasian Union]] in 2015.
* It is estimated that there are between 2,500,000 and 2,900,000 million Armenians in Russia.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|San Marino}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|21 March 2006}}
| 
* Armenia is represented in San Marino through its embassy in Rome (Italy).
* San Marino has an honorary consulte in Yerevan.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Serbia}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|14 January 1993}}
|| See [[Armenia–Serbia relations]]
* Armenia is represented in Serbia through its embassy in Athens (Greece) and honorary consulate in [[Belgrad]].
* Serbia is also represented in Armenia through its embassy in Athens and honorary consulate in Yerevan. Serbia will open embassy in Yerevan 2020.
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20120305042244/http://www.mfa.gov.rs/Policy/Bilaterala/armenia/index_e.html Serbian Ministry of Foreign Affairs about relations with Armenia]
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Slovakia}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt;{{dts|14 January 1993}}
| 
* Armenia is represented in Slovakia through its embassy in [[Prague]] (Czech Republic).
* Slovakia has an embassy in Yerevan. 
* Both countries are full members of the [[Organization for Security and Co-operation in Europe]] and of the [[Council of Europe]].
* Between 24–28 February 2008, [[Foreign relations of Slovakia|Slovak Foreign Minister]] [[Ján Kubiš]] made an official visit to Armenia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.mzv.sk/servlet/content?MT=/App/WCM/main.nsf/vw_ByID/ID_60BFE0A6939BE901C12570840032B081_EN&amp;OpenDocument=Y&amp;LANG=EN&amp;OB=113&amp;DS=Y&amp;TG=BlankMaster&amp;URL=http://www.mzv.sk/App/WCM/Aktualit.nsf/vw_ByID/ID_6CE17E4E26E0DBACC12573F9006714C4 |title=Slovak Ministry of Foreign Affairs about Ján Kubiš's visit to Armenia |publisher=Mzv.sk |accessdate=12 November 2011 }}{{dead link|date=July 2017 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Slovakia recognized the Armenian Genocide in 2004.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Slovenia}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|27 June 1994}}
| 
* Armenia has an honorary consulate in [[Ljubljana]].
* Slovenia has an honorary consulate in Yerevan.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Sovereign Military Order of Malta}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|29 May 1998}}
|
* Diplomatic relations were established on 29 May 1998.
* The Sovereign Military Order of Malta maintains an embassy in Yerevan.
* The Order of Malta has recognized the Armenian Genocide.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Spain}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|27 January 1992}}
|| See [[Armenia–Spain relations]]
* Armenia has an embassy in [[Madrid]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.am/eng/news/32428.html |title=Armenia opens embassy in Spain &amp;#124; Armenia News |publisher=NEWS.am |date=13 June 2009 |accessdate=12 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and there are two honorary consulates in [[Valencia]] and [[Barcelona]].
* Spain is represented in Armenia through its embassy in Moscow (Russia) and an honorary consulate in Yerevan. 
* Five regional parliaments in Spain including the [[Balearic Islands]], [[Aragon]], [[Navarre]], [[Basque Country (autonomous community)|Basque Country]] and [[Catalonia]] as well as 29 municipalities have recognized the Armenian Genocide.
* Around 80,000 Armenians live in Spain.
* Spanish Ministry of Foreign Affairs and Cooperations about the relation with Armenia&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.maec.es/SiteCollectionDocuments/Monografias/Armenia.pdf|title=Spanish Ministry of Foreign Affairs and Cooperations about the relation with Armenia (in Spanish only)|work=MAEC.es|access-date=23 April 2017|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120312024911/https://www.maec.es/SiteCollectionDocuments/Monografias/Armenia.pdf|archivedate=12 March 2012|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Sweden}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|10 July 1992}}
|| 
* Sweden recognized the Armenian Genocide in 2010.
* Armenia has an embassy in [[Stockholm]].
* Sweden has an embassy in Yerevan in 2014.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.swedenabroad.com/en-GB/Embassies/Tblisi/About-us/About-the-Embassy/ |title=ABOUT US |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120920123331/http://www.swedenabroad.com/en-GB/Embassies/Tblisi/About-us/About-the-Embassy/ |archivedate=20 September 2012 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Swedish Ministry of Foreign Affairs: information about the Swedish ambassador to Armenia&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.regeringen.se/404/|title=Sidan kan inte hittas|first=Regeringen och|last=Regeringskansliet|date=1 May 2015|work=Regeringen.se|access-date=23 April 2017}}{{dead link|date=July 2017 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Around 5,000–8,000 Armenians live in Sweden.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Switzerland}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|23 December 1991}}
|| See [[Armenia–Switzerland relations]]
* The Armenian ambassador to Switzerland and the Swiss ambassador to Armenia (based in Yerevan, Armenia) were both accredited in 2011.
* The Armenian ambassador to Switzerland is based in [[Geneva]], in the Armenian representation to the United Nations.
* Switzerland maintains an embassy in Yerevan.
* There are roughly 5,000 Armenians in Switzerland.
* In 2003, Switzerland recognized the Armenian Genocide.
* Armenia's representative to the [[World Trade Organization]] is also located in Geneva.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.mfa.am/en/in-international-organizations/148]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Swiss Federal Department of Foreign Affairs about relations with Armenia&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.eda.admin.ch/eda/en/home/reps/eur/varm/afoarm.html|title=Swiss representation in Armenia|author=|date=|work=Admin.ch|access-date=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Ukraine}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|25 December 1992}}
||
Armenian–Ukrainian relations have lasted for centuries and today are cordial. Relations between Armenia and Ukraine have deflated since Armenia recognized the disputed referendum in Crimea and its subsequent annexation by Russia, and Ukraine has withdrawn its ambassador to Armenia for consultations. The Ukrainian government has asserted that this is temporary and that diplomatic relations between the two states shall indeed continue.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rferl.org/content/armenia-crimea-russia-ukraine/25310243.html|title=Armenian Consul Denies Labeling Crimea 'Reunification'|work=RadioFreeEurope/RadioLiberty|access-date=19 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Armenia has an embassy in [[Kiev]] and consulates in [[Odessa]] and [[Yalta]].
* Ukraine has an embassy in Yerevan and honorary consulate in [[Gyumri]].
* Armenian is an official minority language in Ukraine.
* An estimated 250,000 Armenians live in Ukraine.
* [[Crimea]] recognized the Armenian Genocide in 2005.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|United Kingdom}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|20 January 1992}}
|| See [[Armenia–United Kingdom relations]]
* The United Kingdom recognised Armenia on 31 December 1991.
* The first embassy of the Republic of Armenia in Europe was established in London in October 1992.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.armenianembassyuk.com/ |title=Armenian embassy in London |publisher=Armenianembassyuk.com |accessdate=12 November 2011 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20111003154252/http://www.armenianembassyuk.com/ |archivedate=3 October 2011 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Since 1995, the United Kingdom has had an embassy in [[Yerevan]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.britishembassy.gov.uk/servlet/Front?pagename=OpenMarket/Xcelerate/ShowPage&amp;c=Page&amp;cid=1053447059775 British embassy in Yerevan]  {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080618101301/http://www.britishembassy.gov.uk/servlet/Front?pagename=OpenMarket%2FXcelerate%2FShowPage&amp;c=Page&amp;cid=1053447059775 |date=18 June 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The two countries maintain collaborative and friendly relations, however the United Kingdom does not recognize the [[Armenian Genocide]], as it considers that the evidence is not clear enough to respectively consider &quot;the terrible events that afflicted the Ottoman Armenian population at the beginning of the last century&quot; genocide under the 1948 UN convention. The British government states the &quot;massacres were an appalling tragedy&quot; and states that this was the view of the government during that period.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.number10.gov.uk/Page13999 |title=armeniangenocide – epetition response |date=6 December 2007 |publisher=number10.gov.uk |accessdate=8 November 2009 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120402040200/http://www.number10.gov.uk/Page13999 |archivedate=2 April 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Wales]], [[Scotland]] and [[Northern Ireland]] consider it to be a genocide, and there is a memorial in Cardiff, Wales.
* There are approximately 20,000 Armenians in the UK, mostly in [[Greater London]] and [[Manchester]].
* [http://www.fco.gov.uk/servlet/Front?pagename=OpenMarket/Xcelerate/ShowPage&amp;c=Page&amp;cid=1007029394365&amp;a=KCountryProfile&amp;aid=1019233781786 British Foreign and Commonwealth Office about relations with Armenia]
|}

===Oceania===
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin:auto;&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;width:15%;&quot;| Country
! style=&quot;width:12%;&quot;| Formal Relations Began
!Notes
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Australia}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|15 January 1992}}
| 
* The first Armenians migrated to Australia in the 1850s, during the gold rush.
* The majority came to Australia in the 1960s, starting with the Armenians of Egypt after Nasser came to power then, in the early 1970s, from Cyprus after the Turkish occupation of the island and from 1975 until 1992, a period of civil unrest in Lebanon.
* Person-to-person governmental links are increasing although they are still modest. In September 2003, The Hon Mr Philip Ruddock MP visited Armenia in his former capacity as Australian Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs. In October 2005, the Armenian Foreign Minister, H.E. Mr [[Vardan Oskanyan]], visited Australia. In November 2005, The Hon Mr Joe Hockey MP, Minister for Human Services, visited Armenia.
* The Parliament of the Commonwealth of Australia refuses to recognise the mass murder of Armenians in 1915 as Genocide, although the State of [[New South Wales]] and [[South Australia]] passed a law recognising the Armenian Genocide. The Australian Government elections of 2007 created an atmosphere in which the Opposition Labor party declared it will push for the Recognition of the Armenian Genocide in Australian Parliament if Labor wins the Elections.
* There are around 60,000 Armenians in Australia.
* Australia maintains a consulate in Yerevan.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Fiji}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|7 June 2010}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 7 June 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/fj/|title=Fiji - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|date=|work=MFA.am|access-date=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Kiribati}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|26 September 2018}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 26 September 2018.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.panarmenian.net/eng/news/260533/Armenia_established_diplomatic_relations_with_Kiribati|title=Armenia, Kiribati establish diplomatic ties|author=|date=|work=PanArmenian.net|access-date=27 September 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Micronesia}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|21 September 2017}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 21 September 2017.&lt;ref name=&quot;armenpress.am&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://armenpress.am/eng/news/906184/armenia-establishes-diplomatic-ties-with-palau-and-micronesia.html |title=Armenia establishes diplomatic ties with Palau and Micronesia |publisher=Armenpress|date=22 September 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Nauru}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|22 September 2017}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 22 September 2017.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/press-releases/item/2017/09/23/fm_nauru/}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|New Zealand}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|6 June 1992}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 6 June 1992.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/nz/|title=New Zealand - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|work=mfa.am|accessdate=23 April 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170702175322/http://mfa.am/en/country-by-country/nz/|archive-date=2 July 2017|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Armenia is represented by New Zealand through its embassy in Moscow.
* There is a small Armenian community in New Zealand, mostly in [[Auckland]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Palau}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|21 September 2017}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 21 September 2017.&lt;ref name=&quot;armenpress.am&quot;/&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Tuvalu}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|16 March 2012}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 16 March 2012.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.panarmenian.net/eng/news/99280/|title=Armenia, Tuvalu establish diplomatic ties|author=|date=|work=PanArmenian.net|access-date=23 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Vanuatu}}||align=right|&lt;!--start date --&gt; {{dts|26 September 2013}}
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 26 September 2013.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/vu/|title=Vanuatu - Bilateral Relations - Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Armenia|first=Helix Consulting|last=LLC|work=MFA.am|access-date=23 April 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170202053017/http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/vu/|archive-date=2 February 2017|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|}

==Other international organizations==
Armenia is additionally a full member, unless otherwise noted, in the following international organizations, programs and treaties:
{{columns-list|colwidth=22em|
* [http://ancientcivilizationsforum.org// Ancient Civilizations Forum]
* [[Assembly of European Regions]]
* [[Black Sea Trade and Development Bank]]
* [[Bologna Process]]
* [[British Council]]
* [[Commonwealth of Independent States Free Trade Area]]
* [[Energy Charter Treaty]]
* [[European Athletic Association]]
* [[European Atomic Energy Community]] (Cooperation agreement)
* [[European Aviation Safety Agency]] (Pan-European Partner)
* [[European Broadcasting Union]]
* [[European Civil Aviation Conference]]
* [[European Charter for Regional or Minority Languages]]
* [[European Committee for Standardization]] (Affiliate member)
* [[European Common Aviation Area]] (Negotiating candidate)
* [[European Court of Human Rights]] and the [[European Convention on Human Rights]]
* [[European Cultural Convention]]
* [[European Higher Education Area]]
* [[European Neighbourhood Policy]]
* [[European Olympic Committees]]
* [[European Organization for Nuclear Research]] (Cooperation agreement)&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | url =https://home.cern/about/who-we-are/our-governance/member-states| title = Our Member States|  date = 2020-01-07}}.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[FIFA]] and [[UEFA]]
* [[Food and Agriculture Organization]]
* [[Framework Convention for the Protection of National Minorities]]
* [[Horizon 2020]]
* [[ICRANet]]
* [[International Atomic Energy Agency]]
* [[International Civil Aviation Organization]]
* [[International Committee of the Red Cross]]
* [[International Chamber of Commerce]]
* [[International Criminal Court]] (Signatory)
* [[International Development Association]]
* [[International Finance Corporation]]
* [[International Labour Organization]]
* [[International Olympic Committee]]
* [[International Organization for Migration]]
* [[International Organization for Standardization]]
* [[International Road Transport Union]] and the [[TIR Convention]]
* [[International Telecommunications Satellite Organization]]
* [[International Telecommunication Union]]
* [[Interparliamentary Assembly on Orthodoxy]]
* [[Inter-Parliamentary Union]]
* [[Multilateral Investment Guarantee Agency]]
* [[Open Government Partnership]]
* [[Organisation for the Prohibition of Chemical Weapons]]
* [[Parliamentary Assembly of the Council of Europe]]
* [[PostEurop]]
* [[Swiss Agency for Development and Cooperation]]
* [[UNESCO]]
* [[United Nations Conference on Trade and Development]]
* [[United Nations Economic Commission for Europe]]
* [[United Nations Industrial Development Organization]]
* [[Universal Postal Union]]
* [[Treaty on Conventional Armed Forces in Europe]]
* [[Treaty on the Non-Proliferation of Nuclear Weapons]]
* [[Venice Commission]]
* [[Warsaw Declaration]]
* [[World Health Organization]]
* [[World Intellectual Property Organization]]
* [[World Meteorological Organization]]
* [[World Peace Council]]
* [[World Tourism Organization]]
}}

==See also==
* [[Armenian diaspora]]
* [[Armenia and the United Nations]]
* [[Euronest Parliamentary Assembly]]
* [[Largest Armenian diaspora communities]]
* [[List of ambassadors of Armenia]]
* [[List of diplomatic missions in Armenia]]
* [[List of diplomatic missions of Armenia]]
* [[Foreign relations of Artsakh]]
* [[Politics of Europe]]
* [[Visa requirements for Armenian citizens]]
* [[Visa policy of Armenia]]
{{clear}}
{{Portal bar|Politics}}
{{Foreign relations of Europe}}

==Footnotes==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==References==
* {{CIA World Factbook}}
* {{StateDept}}

==External links==
{{External links|date=April 2017}}
; Argentina
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20120219175135/http://www.mrecic.gov.ar/portal/seree/ditra/am.html List of Treaties ruling the relations Argentina and Armenia (Argentine Foreign Ministry, in Spanish)]
; Canada
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20110609075158/http://www.armembassycanada.ca/ Armenian embassy in Ottawa]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20080526064932/http://geo.international.gc.ca/cip-pic/geo/armenia-en.aspx Canadian Ministry of Foreign Affairs and International Trade about relations with Armenian]
;Chile
* {{cite news | url = http://www.hairenik.com/armenianweekly/col06160701p.htm | title = Chile Proves Genocide Recognition is Based on Truth, Not Lobbying | publisher = Armenian Weekly | first = Harut | last = Sassounian | volume = 73 | number = 24 | date = 16 June 2007}}
* [http://www.senado.cl/prontus_senado/antialone.html?page=http://www.senado.cl/prontus_senado/site/artic/20070914/pags/20070914115407.html Chilean Senate: recognition of the Armenian Genocide (in Spanish only)]
; Czech
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20111003154252/http://www.armenianembassyuk.com/ Armenian embassy in London]
* [http://www.fco.gov.uk/servlet/Front?pagename=OpenMarket/Xcelerate/ShowPage&amp;c=Page&amp;cid=1007029394365&amp;a=KCountryProfile&amp;aid=1019233781786 British Foreign and Commonwealth Office about relations with Armenia] *[https://web.archive.org/web/20080618101301/http://www.britishembassy.gov.uk/servlet/Front?pagename=OpenMarket%2FXcelerate%2FShowPage&amp;c=Page&amp;cid=1053447059775 British embassy in Yerevan]
;Denmark
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20081204061720/http://www.um.dk/en/menu/DevelopmentPolicy/DanishDevelopmentPolicyCountries/TheNeighbourhoodProgramme/Countries/Armenia/Armenia.htm Danish Foreign Ministry: development program with Armenia]
;NATO
* Iskandaryan, Alexander:&quot;NATO and Armenia: A Long Game of Complementarism&quot; in the [http://www.laender-analysen.de/cad/pdf/CaucasusAnalyticalDigest05.pdf Caucasus Analytical Digest No. 5]
;International
* Khachatrian, Haroutiun: &quot;Foreign Investments in Armenia: Influence of the Crisis and Other Peculiarities&quot; in the [http://www.laender-analysen.de/cad/pdf/CaucasusAnalyticalDigest28.pdf Caucasus Analytical Digest No. 28]
{{Foreign relations of Armenia}}
{{Armenia topics}}
{{Armenia ties}}
{{Foreign relations of Asia}}
{{Foreign relations of Europe}}

[[Category:Foreign relations of Armenia| ]]</text>
      <sha1>7rbipvd3569g119cetwxja86hcsxz10</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
