  <page>
    <title>Bela Lugosi</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5034</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942489366</id>
      <parentid>942489301</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-25T00:11:07Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Baeleigh</username>
        <id>21586036</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Death */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Hungarian actor}}
{{eastern name order|Blaskó Béla Ferenc Dezső}}
{{Infobox person
| name          = Bela Lugosi
| image         = Lugosi Béla fortepan 14652.jpg
| image_size    = 
| caption       = Bela Lugosi, ca. 1912
| birth_name    = Béla Ferenc Dezső Blaskó
| birth_date    = {{birth date|1882|10|20|df=yes}}
| birth_place   = [[Lugoj|Lugos]], [[Austria-Hungary]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(now [[Lugoj]], [[Romania]])&lt;/small&gt;
| death_date    = {{death date and age|1956|08|16|1882|10|20|df=yes}}
| death_place   = [[Los Angeles, California]], U.S.
| resting place = [[Holy Cross Cemetery, Culver City|Holy Cross Cemetery]]
| occupation    = Actor
| height_ft     = 6
| height_in     = 1
| years_active  = 1901/02–1956
| other_names   = Arisztid Olt
| website       = {{url|http://belalugosi.com}}
| spouse        = {{marriage|Ilona Szmick|1917|1920|reason=divorced}}&lt;br /&gt;{{marriage|Ilona von Montagh|1921|1924|end=divorced}}&lt;br /&gt;{{marriage|Beatrice Weeks|1929|1929|end=divorced}}&lt;br /&gt;{{marriage|Lillian Arch|1933|1953|end=divorced}}&lt;br /&gt;{{marriage|Hope Lininger&lt;br&gt;|1955}}
| children      = [[Bela G. Lugosi|Bela George Lugosi]]
| signature     = Bela Lugosi signature.svg
}}

'''Béla Ferenc Dezső Blaskó''' ({{IPA-hu|ˈbeːlɒ ˈfɛrɛnt͡s ˈdɛʒøː ˈblɒʃkoː|lang}}; 20 October 1882 – 16 August 1956), known professionally as '''Bela Lugosi''' ({{IPAc-en|l|ə|ˈ|g|oʊ|s|i|}}; {{IPA-hu|ˈluɡoʃi|lang}}), was a [[Hungarian-American]] actor best remembered for portraying [[Count Dracula]] in the [[Dracula (1931 English-language film)|1931 film]] and for his roles in other [[horror films]].&lt;ref name=obit/&gt;

After playing small parts on the stage in his native Hungary, Lugosi gained his first role in a film in 1917. He had to leave the country after [[Hungarian Soviet Republic|the failed Hungarian Communist Revolution of 1919]] because of his socialist activism. He acted in several films in [[Weimar Germany]] before arriving in the United States as a seaman on a merchant ship.

In 1927, he appeared as Count Dracula in a Broadway adaptation of [[Bram Stoker]]'s [[Dracula|novel]]. He later appeared in the 1931 film ''Dracula'' directed by [[Tod Browning]] and produced by [[Universal Studios|Universal Pictures]]. Through the 1930s, he occupied an important niche in horror films, with their East European setting, but his Hungarian accent limited his potential casting, and he unsuccessfully tried to avoid typecasting.

Meanwhile, he was often paired with [[Boris Karloff]], who was able to demand top billing. To his frustration, Lugosi, a charter member of the American [[Screen Actors Guild]], was increasingly restricted to minor parts, kept employed by the studio principally so that they could put his name on the posters. Among his pairings with Karloff, he performed major roles only in ''[[The Black Cat (1934 film)|The Black Cat]]'' (1934), ''[[The Raven (1935 film)|The Raven]]'' (1935), and ''[[Son of Frankenstein]]'' (1939); even in ''The Raven'', Karloff received top billing despite Lugosi performing the lead role. By this time, Lugosi had been receiving regular medication for [[sciatica|sciatic neuritis]], and he became addicted to [[morphine]] and [[methadone]]. This drug dependence was known to producers, and the offers eventually dwindled to a few parts in [[Ed Wood]]'s low-budget films—including a brief appearance in ''[[Plan 9 from Outer Space]]'' (1959). Lugosi was married five times and had one son, [[Bela G. Lugosi|Bela George]]. He died of a heart attack on August 16, 1956.

==Early life==
[[File:Bela Lugosi 18.jpg|left|thumb|upright|Lugosi at age 18]]
Lugosi, the youngest of four children,&lt;ref name=monsters-universal-studios&gt;{{cite book |author1=Osborn, Jennifer (editor) |author2=Milano, Roy (photo captions) |year=2006 |title=Monsters: A Celebration of the Classics from Universal Studios |publisher=Del Ray Books, imprint of Random House, Inc. |location=New York, NY |page=38 |isbn=0-345-48685-4}} Referenced information is from an essay in the book written by his son Bela G. Lugosi.&lt;/ref&gt; was born Béla Ferenc Dezső Blaskó in Lugos, [[Kingdom of Hungary]] (now [[Lugoj]], [[Romania]]) to [[Hungarian people|Hungarian]] father István Blaskó, a banker, and [[Serbian people|Serbian]]-born mother Paula de Vojnich.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;United States Census, 1930,&quot; database with images, FamilySearch (https://familysearch.org/ark:/61903/1:1:XCJB-Z61 : accessed 20 May 2018), Bela Lugosi, Los Angeles (Districts 0001-0250), Los Angeles, California, United States; citing enumeration district (ED) ED 47, sheet 9A, line 4, family 193, NARA microfilm publication T626 (Washington D.C.: National Archives and Records Administration, 2002), roll 133; FHL microfilm 2,339,868.&lt;/ref&gt; He later based his last name on his hometown.&lt;ref name=monsters-universal-studios/&gt; He and his sister Vilma were raised in a [[Roman Catholic]] family.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Rhodes |first=Gary |title=Lugosi: His Life in Films, on Stage, and in the Hearts of Horror Lovers |year=1997 |url=https://books.google.com/books?visbn=0-7864-0257-1&amp;id=Aueo3mOrIKIC&amp;pg=PA38&amp;lpg=PA38 |isbn=0-7864-0257-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

At the age of 12, Lugosi dropped out of school.&lt;ref name=monsters-universal-studios/&gt; He began his acting career in 1901 or 1902. His earliest known performances are from provincial theatres in the 1903–04 season, playing small roles in several plays and [[operetta]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Arthur Lennig, ''The Immortal Count'', University Press of Kentucky, 2003, p. 21; {{ISBN|978-0-8131-2273-1}}.&lt;/ref&gt; He went on to perform in [[William Shakespeare|Shakespeare]]'s plays. After moving to [[Budapest]] in 1911, he played dozens of roles with the National Theatre of Hungary between 1913–19. Although Lugosi would later claim that he &quot;became the leading actor of Hungary's Royal National Theatre&quot;, almost all his roles there were small or supporting parts.&lt;ref&gt;Arthur Lennig, ''The Immortal Count'', University Press of Kentucky, 2003, pp. 25–26, 28–29; {{ISBN|978-0-8131-2273-1}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

During [[World War I]], he served as an infantryman in the [[Austro-Hungarian Army]] from 1914–16, rising to the rank of [[Rank insignia of the Austro-Hungarian armed forces#Officers and officials|Lieutenant]]. He was awarded the [[Wound Medal (Austria-Hungary)|Wound Medal]] for wounds he suffered while serving on the [[Eastern Front (World War I)|Russian front]].&lt;ref name=monsters-universal-studios/&gt;

Due to his activism in the actors' union in Hungary during the [[Revolutions and interventions in Hungary (1918–1920)|revolution of 1919]], he was forced to flee his homeland.&lt;ref name=monsters-universal-studios/&gt; He went first to [[Vienna]] before settling in [[Berlin]] (in the Langestrasse), where he continued acting.&lt;ref name=monsters-universal-studios/&gt; He took the name &quot;Lugosi&quot; in 1903 to honor his birthplace,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/dr-franklin-ruehl-phd/halloween-facts-history-_b_1074357.html |title=15 Intriguing Halloween-Related Factoids! |date=3 November 2011 |work=Huffington Post}}&lt;/ref&gt; and eventually travelled to [[New Orleans, Louisiana]] as a crewman aboard a [[Merchant vessel|merchant ship]].&lt;ref name=monsters-universal-studios/&gt;

==Career==

===Early films===
Lugosi's first film appearance was in the movie ''[[The Colonel (1917 film)|Az ezredes]]'' (''The Colonel'', 1917). When appearing in [[Cinema of Hungary|Hungarian]] [[silent film]]s, he used the stage name '''Arisztid Olt'''.&lt;ref name=&quot;mank&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://www.worldcat.org/oclc/607553826 |title=Bela Lugosi and Boris Karloff : the expanded story of a haunting collaboration, with a complete filmography of their films together |last=Mank |first=Gregory W. |publisher=McFarland &amp; Co., Publishers |year=2009 |isbn=9780786434800 |location=Jefferson, N.C. |pages=22–23 |oclc=607553826}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lugosi made 12 films in Hungary between 1917 and 1918 before leaving for Germany. Following the collapse of [[Béla Kun]]'s [[Hungarian Soviet Republic]] in 1919, [[political left|leftists]] and [[trade union]]ists became vulnerable. Lugosi was proscribed from acting due to his participation in the formation of an actors' [[labor union|union]]. Exiled in [[Weimar Republic|Weimar]]-era Germany, he began appearing in a small number of well-received films, among them adaptations of the [[Karl May]] novels ''[[On the Brink of Paradise]]'' (''Auf den Trümmern des Paradieses'', 1920) and ''[[Caravan of Death (film)|Caravan of Death]]'' (''Die Todeskarawane'', also 1920) with [[Dora Gerson]] (Gerson, who was Jewish, died in [[Auschwitz concentration camp|Auschwitz]]).

Lugosi left Germany in October 1920, intending to emigrate to the United States, and entered the country at [[New Orleans]] in December 1920. He made his way to [[New York City|New York]] and was inspected by immigration officers at [[Ellis Island]] in March 1921.&lt;ref&gt;Passenger list of the S.S. ''Graf Tisza Istvan'', port of New Orleans, 4 December 1920, with later notation.&lt;/ref&gt; He declared his intention to become a [[Citizenship of the United States|US citizen]] in 1928; on June 26, 1931, he was [[naturalization|naturalized]].&lt;ref&gt;Ancestry.com. ''Selected U.S. Naturalization Records — Original Documents, 1790–1974 (World Archives Project)'' [database on-line]. Provo, Utah, US: The Generations Network, Inc., 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

On his arrival in America, the {{convert|6|ft|1|in|m|adj=on}},&lt;ref name=&quot;mank&quot;/&gt; {{convert|180|lb|kg|adj=on}} Lugosi worked for some time as a laborer, and then entered the theater in New York City's Hungarian immigrant colony. With fellow expatriate Hungarian actors he formed a small [[repertory|stock company]] that toured Eastern cities, playing for immigrant audiences. Lugosi acted in several Hungarian plays before breaking out into his first English [[Broadway theatre|Broadway]] play, ''The Red Poppy'', in 1922.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=Hollywood Gothic |last=Skal |first=David |publisher=Faber and Faber Inc |year=2004 |isbn=9780571211586 |location=New York City |pages=124}}&lt;/ref&gt; Three more parts came in 1925–26, including a five-month run in the comedy-fantasy ''The Devil in the Cheese''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ibdb.com/person.php?id=50322 Bela Lugosi profile], ibdb.com; accessed 1 November 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1925, he appeared as an Arab Sheik in ''Arabesque'' which premiered in [[Buffalo, New York]] at the Teck Theatre before moving to Broadway.&lt;ref&gt;[http://beladraculalugosi.wordpress.com/bela-lugosi-on-the-on-stage/ Bela Lugosi premieres in Buffalo, New York]&lt;/ref&gt; His first American film role was in the melodrama ''[[The Silent Command]]'' (1923). Several more silent roles followed, [[villain]]s and continental types, all in productions made in the New York area.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://belalugosi.com/|title=Bela Lugosi – The Official Site|language=en-US|access-date=2020-02-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===''Dracula''===
{{Main|Dracula (1931 English-language film)}}
[[File:Bela Lugosi as Dracula-2.jpg|thumb|Lugosi in ''[[Dracula (1931 English-language film)|Dracula]]'', the role for which he became most widely known.]]
&lt;!--[[File:Bela Lugosi as Dracula, anonymous photograph from 1931, Universal Studios.jpg|left|thumb|upright|Lugosi as [[Dracula]]]]--&gt;
Lugosi was approached in the summer of 1927 to star in a [[Broadway theatre]] production of ''[[Dracula (1924 play)|Dracula]]'', which had been adapted by [[Hamilton Deane]] and [[John L. Balderston]] from [[Bram Stoker]]'s 1897 [[Dracula (novel)|novel]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last1=Rhodes |first1=Gary Don |title=Lugosi: his life in films, on stage, and in the hearts of horror lovers |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Aueo3mOrIKIC&amp;pg=PA169 |format=[[Google Books]] |accessdate=18 February 2009 |year=1997 |page=169 |chapter=Stage Appearances}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Horace Liveright]] production was successful, running for 261 performances before touring the United States to much fanfare and critical acclaim throughout 1928 and 1929. In 1928, Lugosi decided to stay in California when the play ended its West Coast run. His performance had piqued the interest of [[Fox Film]], and he was cast in the studio's silent film ''[[The Veiled Woman]]'' (1929). He also appeared in the film ''[[Prisoners (1929) film|Prisoners]]'' (also 1929), believed [[Lost film|lost]], which was released in both silent and [[Sound film|talkie]] versions.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book
  | last1=        Lennig
  | first1=       Arthur
  | title=         The Immortal Count: The Life and Films of Bela Lugosil
  | date=         2010
  | publisher= University Press of Kentucky
  | location=    Lexington
  | isbn=          9780813126616
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
  | title=            Prisoners (1929)
  | url=              https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0020291/ 
  | website=      IMDb 
  | publisher=   IMDb.com, Inc.
  | accessdate= 7 December 2015
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1929, with no other film roles in sight, he returned to the stage as Dracula for a short West Coast tour of the play. Lugosi remained in California where he resumed his film work under contract with Fox, appearing in early talkies often as a [[Villain|heavy]] or an &quot;exotic [[Sheikh|sheik]]&quot;. He also continued to lobby for his prized role in the film version of ''[[Dracula (1931 English-language film)|Dracula]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0402729/ |title=Biography (TV Series):  Bela Lugosi: Hollywood's Dark Prince |website=IMDb |publisher=IMDb.com, Inc. |accessdate=7 December 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite his critically acclaimed performance on stage, Lugosi was not [[Universal Studios|Universal Pictures]]' first choice for the role of Dracula when the company optioned the rights to the Deane play and began production in 1930.{{Efn|group=notes|name=rumour|A persistent rumor asserts that director [[Tod Browning]]'s long-time collaborator [[Lon Chaney, Sr.|Lon Chaney]] was Universal's first choice for the role, and that Lugosi was chosen only due to Chaney's death shortly before production. This is questionable because Chaney had been under long-term contract to [[Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer]] since 1925, and had negotiated a lucrative new contract just before his death.{{citation needed|date=December 2015}} Chaney and Browning had worked together on several projects (including four of Chaney's final five releases), but Browning was only a last-minute choice to direct the movie version of ''Dracula'' after the death of director [[Paul Leni]], who had originally been slated to direct.}} Different prominent actors were considered before Browning cast Lugosi for the role, but the film was a hit.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://mentalfloss.com/article/84310/12-surprising-facts-about-bela-lugosi |title=12 Surprising Facts About Bela Lugosi |date=2016-08-16 |access-date=2017-08-04 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Typecasting===
[[File:Irene Ware and Bela Lugosi in The Raven.jpg|thumb|left|[[Irene Ware]] and Lugosi in ''[[The Raven (1935 film)|The Raven]]'' (1935)]]

Through his association with ''[[Dracula]]'' (in which he appeared with minimal makeup, using his natural, heavily accented voice), Lugosi found himself [[Typecasting (acting)|typecast]] as a [[horror film|horror]] villain in films such as ''[[Murders in the Rue Morgue (1932 film)|Murders in the Rue Morgue]]'' (1932), ''[[The Raven (1935 film)|The Raven]]'' (1935), and ''[[Son of Frankenstein]]'' (1939) for Universal, and the independent ''[[White Zombie (film)|White Zombie]]'' (1932). His accent, while a part of his image, limited the roles he could play.

Lugosi did attempt to break type by auditioning for other roles. He lost out to [[Lionel Barrymore]] for the role of [[Grigori Rasputin]] in ''[[Rasputin and the Empress]]'' (also 1932); [[C. Henry Gordon]] for the role of Surat Khan in ''[[The Charge of the Light Brigade (1936 film)|Charge of the Light Brigade]]'' (1936), and [[Basil Rathbone]] for the role of Commissar Dimitri Gorotchenko in ''[[Tovarich (film)|Tovarich]]'' (1937) a role Lugosi had played on stage).&lt;ref name=&quot;Bela Lugosi In Person&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last1=Kaffenberger |first1=Bill |last2=Rhodes |first2=Gary |title=Bela Lugosi In Person |date=2015 |publisher=BearManor Media |isbn=1593938055 |url=https://www.amazon.com/Bela-Lugosi-Person-William-Kaffenberger/dp/1593938055/}}&lt;/ref&gt; He played the elegant, somewhat hot-tempered General Nicholas Strenovsky-Petronovich in ''[[International House (1933 film)|International House]]'' (1933).

Regardless of controversy, five films at Universal — ''[[The Black Cat (1934 film)|The Black Cat]]'' (1934), ''[[The Raven (1935 film)|The Raven]]'' (1935), ''[[The Invisible Ray (1936 film)|The Invisible Ray]]'' (1936), ''[[Son of Frankenstein]]'' (1939), ''[[Black Friday (1940 film)|Black Friday]]'' (1940), plus minor cameo performances in ''[[Gift of Gab (1934 film)|Gift of Gab]]'' (1934) and two at [[RKO Pictures]], ''[[You'll Find Out]]'' (1940) and ''[[The Body Snatcher (film)|The Body Snatcher]]'' (1945) — paired Lugosi with [[Boris Karloff]]. Despite the relative size of their roles, Lugosi inevitably received second billing, below Karloff. There are contradictory reports of Lugosi's attitude toward Karloff, some claiming that he was openly resentful of Karloff's long-term success and ability to gain good roles beyond the horror arena, while others suggested the two actors were — for a time, at least — good friends. Karloff himself in interviews suggested that Lugosi was initially mistrustful of him when they acted together, believing that the Englishman would attempt to upstage him. When this proved not to be the case, according to Karloff, Lugosi settled down and they worked together amicably (though some have further commented that the English Karloff's on-set demand to break from filming for mid-afternoon tea annoyed Lugosi).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Mank |first1=Gregory William |title=Bela Lugosi and Boris Karloff : the expanded story of a haunting collaboration, with a complete filmography of their films together |date=2009 |publisher=McFarland &amp; Co., Publishers |location=Jefferson, N.C. |isbn=0786434805 |pages=237–238}}&lt;/ref&gt; Karloff also insinuated that his rival could not act, claiming Lugosi had &quot;never learned his trade&quot;. A small percentage of critics cited his &quot;dull and slow performance&quot; in ''Dracula'' as a great example of minimal dialogue with no real acting prowess needed. Lugosi did get a few heroic leads, as in Universal's ''[[The Black Cat (1934 film)|The Black Cat]]'' after Karloff had been accorded the more colorful role of the villain, ''[[The Invisible Ray (1936 film)|The Invisible Ray]]'', and a romantic role in producer [[Sol Lesser]]'s adventure serial ''[[The Return of Chandu]]'' (1934), but his typecasting problem appears to have been too entrenched to be alleviated by those films.
[[File:Béla Lugosi-Angelo Rossitto in Scared to Death.jpg|thumb|With [[Angelo Rossitto]] in ''[[Scared to Death]]'' (1947)]]
Lugosi addressed his plea to be cast in non-horror roles directly to casting directors through his listing in the 1937 ''Players Directory'', published by the [[Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences]], in which he (or his agent) calls the idea that he is only fit for horror films &quot;an error.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Michael Mallory. [https://books.google.com/books/about/Universal_Studios_Monsters.html?id=ZHhOPgAACAAJ ''Universal Studios Monsters: A Legacy of Horror''], 2009, Universe, p. 63. {{ISBN|978-0-7893-1896-1}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Career decline===
[[File:LugosiDevilBat1.jpg|thumb|right|Lugosi in ''[[The Devil Bat]]'' (1940)]]
A number of factors began to work against Lugosi's career in the mid-1930s. Universal changed management in 1936, and because of a British ban on horror films, dropped them from their production schedule; Lugosi found himself consigned to Universal's non-horror [[B-movie|B-film]] unit, at times in small roles where he was obviously used for &quot;name value&quot; only. Throughout the 1930s, Lugosi, experiencing a severe career decline despite popularity with audiences (Universal executives always preferred his rival Karloff), accepted many leading roles from independent producers like [[Nat Levine]], [[Sol Lesser]], and [[Sam Katzman]]. These low-budget thrillers indicate that Lugosi was less discriminating than Karloff in selecting screen vehicles, but the exposure helped Lugosi financially if not artistically. Lugosi tried to keep busy with stage work, but had to borrow money from the [[Actors Fund of America]] to pay hospital bills when his only child, Bela George Lugosi, was born in 1938.

Historian John McElwee reports, in his 2013 book ''Showmen, Sell It Hot!'', that Bela Lugosi's popularity received a much-needed boost in August 1938, when California theater owner Emil Umann revived ''Dracula'' and ''Frankenstein'' as a special double feature. The combination was so successful that Umann scheduled extra shows to accommodate the capacity crowds, and invited Lugosi to appear in person, which thrilled new audiences that had never seen Lugosi's classic performance. &quot;I owe it all to that little man at the Regina Theatre,&quot; said Lugosi of exhibitor Umann. &quot;I was dead, and he brought me back to life.&quot; Universal took notice of the tremendous business and launched its own national re-release of the same two horror favorites. The studio then rehired Lugosi to star in new films.

The first was Universal's ''[[Son of Frankenstein]]'' (1939), when he played the character role of Ygor, a mad blacksmith with a broken neck, in heavy makeup and beard. The same year saw Lugosi making a rare appearance in an A-list motion picture: he was a stern commissar in [[Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer]]'s romantic comedy ''[[Ninotchka]]'', starring [[Greta Garbo]] and directed by [[Ernst Lubitsch]]. Lugosi was effective in this small but prestigious character role, and it could have been a turning point for the actor, but within the year, he was back on Hollywood's Poverty Row, playing leads for Sam Katzman. These horror, comedy and [[Mystery fiction|mystery]] B-films were released by [[Monogram Pictures]]. At Universal, he often received star billing for what amounted to a supporting part. ''[[The Gorilla (1939 film)|The Gorilla]]'' (1939) had him playing straight man to [[Patsy Kelly]] and the [[Ritz Brothers]].
[[File:Invisible Ghost (1941) 1.jpg|thumb|left|Lugosi (center) with [[Polly Ann Young]] and [[Clarence Muse]] in ''[[The Invisible Ghost]]'' (1941)]]

Ostensibly due to injuries received during military service, Lugosi developed severe, chronic [[sciatica]]. Though at first he was treated with pain remedies such as [[asparagus]] juice, doctors increased the medication to [[opiate]]s. The growth of his dependence on [[analgesic]] drugs, particularly [[morphine]] and, after 1947 when it became available in America, [[methadone]], was directly proportional to the dwindling of screen offers. He was finally cast in the role of [[Frankenstein's monster]] for Universal's ''[[Frankenstein Meets the Wolf Man]]'' (1943), but Lugosi had no dialogue. Lugosi's voice had been dubbed over that of [[Lon Chaney Jr.]], from line readings at the end of ''[[The Ghost of Frankenstein]]'' (1942).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.britannica.com/biography/Bela-Lugosi |title=Bela Lugosi {{!}} Hungarian-American actor|work=Encyclopedia Britannica|access-date=2017-08-04|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lugosi played Dracula for a second and last time on film in ''[[Abbott and Costello Meet Frankenstein]]'' (1948).

''Abbott and Costello Meet Frankenstein'' was Bela Lugosi's last &quot;A&quot; movie. For the remainder of his life he appeared — less and less frequently — in obscure, low-budget features. From 1947 to 1950, he performed in [[summer stock]], often in productions of ''Dracula'' or ''[[Arsenic and Old Lace (play)|Arsenic and Old Lace]]'', and during the other parts of the year made personal appearances in a touring &quot;spook show&quot;, and on early commercial television.

In September 1949 [[Milton Berle]] invited Lugosi to appear in a sketch on ''[[Texaco Star Theatre]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tv.com/9-27-1949/episode/670241/summary.htmlTexaco Star Theater Episode Guide], tv.com; accessed 1 November 2015.&lt;/ref&gt; Lugosi memorized the script for the skit, but became confused on the air when Berle began to ad lib.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Weaver |first=Tom |title=Science Fiction and Fantasy Film Flashbacks: Conversations with 24 Actors, Writers, Producers and Directors from the Golden Age |publisher=McFarland |year=2004 |page=160 |isbn=0-7864-2070-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; His only television dramatic role was on the anthology series ''[[Suspense (U.S. TV series)|Suspense]]'' on October 11, 1949, in an adaptation of [[Edgar Allan Poe]]'s ''[[The Cask of Amontillado]]''.&lt;ref&gt;''The Complete Actors' Television Credits, 1948–1988, James Robert Parrish and Vincent Terrace''&lt;!--publishing info, ISSN/ISBN, year needed--&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1951, while in [[England]] to play a six-month tour of ''Dracula'', Lugosi co-starred in a [[Low culture|lowbrow]] film comedy, ''[[Mother Riley Meets the Vampire]]'' (also known as ''Vampire over London'' and ''My Son, the Vampire''), released the following year. Following his return to the United States, he was interviewed for television, and reflected wistfully on his typecasting in horror parts: &quot;Now I am the [[Bogeyman|boogie man]]&quot;. In the same interview he expressed a desire to play more comedy, as he had in the ''Mother Riley'' [[farce]]. Independent producer Jack Broder took Lugosi at his word, casting him in a jungle-themed comedy, ''[[Bela Lugosi Meets a Brooklyn Gorilla]]'' (1952), co-starring nightclub comedians [[Duke Mitchell]] and [[Sammy Petrillo]], whose act closely resembled that of [[Dean Martin]] and [[Jerry Lewis]].

===Stage and personal appearances===
Lugosi enjoyed a lively career on stage. with plenty of personal appearances. As film offers declined, he became more and more dependent on live venues to support his family. Bela took over the role of Jonathan Brewster from Boris Karloff for ''[[Arsenic and Old Lace (play)|Arsenic and Old Lace]]''. Bela had also expressed interest in playing Elwood P. Dowd in ''[[Harvey (play)|Harvey]]'' to help himself professionally. He also made plenty of personal appearances to promote his horror image and/or an accompanying film.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bela Lugosi In Person&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Kaffenberger |first1=Bill |last2=Rhodes |first2=Gary |title=No Traveler Returns: The Lost Years of Bela Lugosi |date=2012 |publisher=BearManor Media |isbn=1593932855 |url=https://www.amazon.com/No-Traveler-Returns-Years-Lugosi/dp/1593932855/}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ed Wood and final projects===
[[File:PlanNine 08.jpg|thumb|Lugosi in Ed Wood's ''[[Plan 9 from Outer Space]]'' (1959)]]
Late in his life, Bela Lugosi again received star billing in films when the ambitious but financially limited filmmaker [[Ed Wood]], a fan of Lugosi, found him living in obscurity and near-poverty and offered him roles in his films, such as an anonymous narrator in ''[[Glen or Glenda]]'' (1953) and a [[Victor Frankenstein|Dr. Frankenstein]]-like [[mad scientist]] in ''[[Bride of the Monster]]'' (1955). During [[post-production]] of the latter, Lugosi decided to seek treatment for his [[drug addiction]], and the premiere of the film was said to be intended to help pay for his hospital expenses. According to [[Kitty Kelley]]'s biography of [[Frank Sinatra]], when the entertainer heard of Lugosi's problems, he helped with expenses and visited Lugosi at the hospital. Sinatra would recall Lugosi's amazement at his visit, since the two men had never met before.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Kelley |first=Kitty |title=His Way: The Unauthorized Biography of Frank Sinatra |publisher=Bantam Books |year=1987 |page=[https://archive.org/details/hiswayunauthoriz00kell_0/page/248 248] |isbn=0-553-26515-6 |url-access=registration |url=https://archive.org/details/hiswayunauthoriz00kell_0/page/248 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

During an impromptu interview upon his exit from the treatment center in 1955, Lugosi stated that he was about to go to work on a new Ed Wood film, ''The Ghoul Goes West''. This was one of several projects proposed by Wood, including ''The Phantom Ghoul'' and ''Dr. Acula''. With Lugosi in his Dracula cape, Wood shot impromptu test footage, with no storyline in mind, in front of [[Tor Johnson]]'s home, a suburban graveyard, and in front of Lugosi's apartment building on Carlton Way. This footage ended up in ''[[Plan 9 from Outer Space]]'' (1959), which was mostly filmed after Lugosi died. Wood hired [[Tom Mason]], his wife's [[chiropractor]], to double for Lugosi in additional shots.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.lostmag.com/issue18/lugosi.php |title=Bela Lugosi's Legacy |last=Nuzum |first=Eric |work=Lost |accessdate=2008-10-08 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080917071843/http://www.lostmag.com/issue18/lugosi.php |archivedate=17 September 2008 |url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; Mason was noticeably taller and thinner than Lugosi, and had the lower half of his face covered with his cape in every shot, as Lugosi sometimes did in ''[[Abbott and Costello Meet Frankenstein]]''.

Following his treatment, Lugosi made one final film, in late 1955, ''[[The Black Sleep]]'', for Bel-Air Pictures, which was released in the summer of 1956 through [[United Artists]] with a promotional campaign that included several personal appearances. To Lugosi's disappointment, however, his role in this film was that of a [[Muteness|mute]], with no dialogue.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bela Lugosi: Dreams and Nightmares&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last1=Rhodes |first1=Gary |last2=Sheffield |first2=Richard |title=Bela Lugosi: Dreams and Nightmares |date=2007 |publisher=Collectables Press |isbn=0977379817 |url=https://www.amazon.com/Bela-Lugosi-Rhodes-Richard-Sheffield/dp/0977379817}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Personal life==
[[File:Lugosi Béla színművész és első felesége, Szmik Ilona. Fortepan 8777.jpg|thumb|With his first wife, Ilona Szmik, in 1917]]
In 1917, Lugosi married Ilona Szmik (1898-1991). The couple divorced in 1920, reputedly over political differences with her parents. In 1921, he married Ilona von Montagh, and divorced in 1924. In 1929, Lugosi took his place in Hollywood society and scandal when he married wealthy [[San Francisco]] resident Beatrice Weeks (1897-1931), widow of [[Weeks and Day|architect Charles Peter Weeks]]. She filed for divorce four months later, citing actress [[Clara Bow]] as the &quot;other woman&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Arthur Lennig, ''The Immortal Count'', University Press of Kentucky, 2003, p. 68; {{ISBN|978-0-8131-2273-1}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 26 June 1931, Lugosi became a naturalized United States citizen. In 1933, he married 22-year-old Lillian Arch (1911-1981), the daughter of Hungarian immigrants. They had a child, [[Bela G. Lugosi]], in 1938.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Friedemann O'Brien Goldberg &amp; Zarian Names Bela G. Lugosi Of Counsel |url=http://www.metnews.com/articles/bela021402.htm |quote=Bela G. Lugosi, a well-known Los Angeles trial and entertainment lawyer and son of the actor famed for his portrayals of Count Dracula, has become of counsel to the downtown office of Friedemann O'Brien Goldberg &amp; Zarian. |work=Metropolitan News-Enterprise |accessdate=2008-04-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bela had four grandchildren and six great-grandchildren.

Lillian and Bela, as well as his mother, vacationed on their lake property in [[Lake Elsinore, California]] (then called Elsinore), on two lots between 1944 and 1953. Bela Lugosi Jr. attended the Elsinore Naval &amp; Military School in Lake Elsinore. Lillian and Béla divorced in 1953,&lt;ref name=arch&gt;{{cite news |title=Divorced |url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,936129,00.html |quote=Bela Lugosi, 68, veteran Hollywood cinemonster (Dracula); by his third wife, Lillian Arch Lugosi, 41, on the ground that his 'unfounded jealousy' constituted mental cruelty; after 20 years of marriage, one son; in [[Los Angeles]]. |work=[[Time (magazine)|Time]] |date=27 July 1953 |accessdate=21 March 2008 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080330000614/http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0%2C9171%2C936129%2C00.html |archivedate=30 March 2008 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt; at least partially because of Béla's jealousy over Lillian taking a full-time job as an assistant to [[Brian Donlevy]] on the sets and studios for Donlevy's radio and television series ''[[Dangerous Assignment]]''&lt;ref&gt;Arthur Lennig, ''The Immortal Count'', University Press of Kentucky, 2003, p. 393; {{ISBN|978-0-8131-2273-1}}.&lt;/ref&gt; – Lillian eventually did marry [[Brian Donlevy]], in 1966. Lugosi married Hope Lininger, his fifth wife, in 1955; they remained married until his death. She had been a fan, writing letters to him when he was in the hospital, recovering from addiction to [[Demerol]]. She would sign her letters &quot;A dash of Hope&quot;. She died in 1997 at age 78.

==Death==
[[File:Bela Lugosi's grave.JPG|thumb|right|Lugosi's grave at [[Holy Cross Cemetery, Culver City]], California]]
Lugosi died of a [[heart attack]] on August 16, 1956, while lying on a bed in his [[Los Angeles]] apartment. He was 73.&lt;ref name=obit&gt;{{cite news |title=From the Archives: Actor Bela Lugosi, Dracula of Screen, Succumbs After Heart Attack at 73 |url=http://www.latimes.com/local/obituaries/la-me-bela-lugosi-19560817-story.html |work=[[Los Angeles Times]] |date=August 17, 1956 |accessdate=December 31, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The rumor that Lugosi was clutching the script for ''[[Final Curtain (film)|The Final Curtain]]'', a planned Ed Wood project, at the time of his death is not true.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Rhodes |first=Gary Don |title=Lugosi: His Life in Films, on Stage, and in the Hearts of Horror Lovers |publisher=McFarland |year=1997 |page=36 |isbn=0-7864-0257-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Lugosi was buried wearing one of the &quot;Dracula&quot; cape costumes in the [[Holy Cross Cemetery, Culver City|Holy Cross Cemetery]] in [[Culver City, California]]. Contrary to popular belief, Lugosi never requested to be buried in his cloak; [[Bela G. Lugosi]] confirmed on numerous occasions that he and his mother, Lillian, actually made the decision but believed that it is what his father would have wanted.&lt;ref&gt;[[Bela G. Lugosi]] states this in &quot;The Road to Dracula&quot;, a documentary supplement in the DVD &quot;Dracula -(1931)&quot; [Universal Studios Classic Monster Collection, Universal DVD #903 249 9.11]&lt;/ref&gt;

==California Supreme Court decision on personality rights==
{{Main|Lugosi v. Universal Pictures}}

In 1979, the ''[[Lugosi v. Universal Pictures]]'' decision by the [[California Supreme Court]] held that Lugosi's [[personality rights]] could not pass to his heirs, as a [[copyright]] would have. The court ruled that under California law any rights of publicity, including the right to his image, terminated with Lugosi's death.{{Efn|group=notes|name=ruling|California's descendibility statute for rights of publicity, Civil Code Section 990, was enacted in 1988, and Lugosi's estate now licenses the commercial use of his name and image. The right of publicity in some states endures for 50, 70, 75 or 100 years past the death of the celebrity.&lt;ref name=findlaw&gt;{{cite web |url=http://library.findlaw.com/1998/Feb/1/130405.html |title=Lugosi v. Universal Pictures, 603 P.2d 425 (Cal. 1979) |accessdate=14 February 2007 |quote=In this decision preceding (and precipitating) the Legislature's enactment of Section 990, the California Supreme Court held that rights of publicity were not descendible in California. Bela Lugosi's heirs, Hope Lininger Lugosi and Bela George Lugosi, sued to enjoin and recover profits from Universal Pictures for licensing Lugosi's name and image on merchandise reprising Lugosi's title role in the 1931 film ''Dracula''. The [[California Supreme Court]] faced the question whether Bela Lugosi's film contracts with Universal included a grant of merchandising rights in his portrayal of Count Dracula, and the descendibility of any such rights. Adopting the opinion of Justice Roth for the Court of Appeal, Second Appellate District, the court held that the right to exploit one's name and likeness is personal to the artist and must be exercised, if at all, by him during his lifetime. Lugosi, 603 P.2d at 431. |publisher=[[FindLaw]] |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070309000423/http://library.findlaw.com/1998/Feb/1/130405.html |archivedate=9 March 2007 |url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
[[File:Budapest Vajdahunyad 07.jpg|right|thumb|upright|Statue of Lugosi on the [[Vajdahunyad Castle]] in [[Budapest]], Hungary]]

==Legacy==
In [[Tim Burton]]'s ''[[Ed Wood (film)|Ed Wood]]'', Lugosi is portrayed by [[Martin Landau]], who received the 1994 [[Academy Award for Best Supporting Actor]] for the performance. According to [[Bela G. Lugosi]] (his son), [[Forrest Ackerman]], [[Dolores Fuller]] and Richard Sheffield, the film's portrayal of Lugosi is inaccurate: In real life, he never used profanity, owned small dogs, or slept in coffins. And contrary to this film, Bela did not struggle performing on ''[[The Red Skelton Show]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bela Lugosi: Dreams and Nightmares&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Rhodes |first1=Gary |last2=Weaver |first2=Tom |title=Ed Wood's Bride of the Monster |date=2015 |publisher=BearManor Media |isbn=1593938578 |url=https://www.amazon.com/Woods-Bride-Monster-Gary-Rhodes/dp/1593938578/}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Three Lugosi projects were featured on the television show ''[[Mystery Science Theater 3000]]''. The 1942 film ''[[The Corpse Vanishes]]'' appeared in episode 105; the serial ''[[The Phantom Creeps]]'' appeared throughout season two, and the Ed Wood production ''[[Bride of the Monster]]'' in episode 423.
An episode of ''[[Sledge Hammer!]]'' titled &quot;Last of the Red Hot Vampires&quot; was an homage to Bela Lugosi; at the end of the episode, it was dedicated to &quot;Mr. Blasko&quot;.

In 2001, [[BBC Radio 4]] broadcast ''There Are Such Things'' by [[Steven McNicoll]] and Mark McDonnell. Focusing on Lugosi and his well-documented struggle to escape from the role that had typecast him, the play went on to receive the Hamilton Dean Award for best dramatic presentation from the Dracula Society in 2002.

A statue of Lugosi was erected on one of the corners of the [[Vajdahunyad Castle]] in [[Budapest]].

The Ellis Island Immigration Museum in [[New York City]] features a live 30-minute play that focuses on Lugosi's illegal entry into the country and then his arrival at Ellis Island to enter the country legally.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ellisisland.org/genealogy/ellis_island_visiting.asp |title=Visiting the Ellis Island Immigration Museum |publisher=ellisisland.org |accessdate=1 November 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Bela Lugosi star on HWF.JPG|thumb|left|Lugosi's star on the [[Hollywood Walk of Fame]]]]
The cape Lugosi wore in ''[[Dracula (1931 English-language film)|Dracula]]'' (1931) was in the possession of his family until it was put up for auction in 2011. It was expected to sell for up to $2 million,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.npr.org/2011/11/01/141895733/last-word|title=Bela Lugosi's 'Dracula' Cape To Be Auctioned Off|website=NPR|language=en|access-date=2019-05-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; but has since been listed again by Bonhams in 2018.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.bonhams.com/auctions/24838/lot/191/|title=Bonhams : Bela Lugosi's Count Dracula cape from Abbott and Costello Meet Frankenstein|website=www.bonhams.com|access-date=2019-11-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2019 the [[Academy Museum of Motion Pictures]] announced acquisition of the cape via partial donation from the Lugosi family&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.oscars.org/news/academy-museum-motion-pictures-announces-acquisition-bela-lugosis-iconic-cape-dracula|title=ACADEMY MUSEUM OF MOTION PICTURES ANNOUNCES ACQUISITION OF BELA LUGOSI’S ICONIC CAPE FROM DRACULA|date=2019-10-18|website=Oscars.org {{!}} Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences|language=en|access-date=2019-11-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; and that the cape will be on display in 2020.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://bloody-disgusting.com/news/3590104/bela-lugosis-screen-worn-dracula-cape-will-display-academy-museum-motion-pictures/|title=Bela Lugosi’s Screen-Worn ‘Dracula’ Cape Will Be on Display at the Academy Museum of Motion Pictures|last=Squires|first=John|date=2019-10-21|website=Bloody Disgusting!|language=en-US|access-date=2019-11-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The theatrical play ''Lugosi - the Shadow of the Vampire'' ({{Lang-hu|Lugosi - a vámpír árnyéka}}) is based on Lugosi's life, telling the story of his life as he became typecast as Dracula and as his drug addiction worsened. He was played by one of Hungary's most renowned actors, [[Ivan Darvas]].

[[Andy Warhol]]'s 1963 silkscreen ''The Kiss'' depicts Lugosi from ''[[Dracula (1931 English-language film)|Dracula]]'' about to bite into the neck of co-star [[Helen Chandler]], who played [[Mina Harker]]. A copy sold for $798,000 at [[Christie's]] in May 2000.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.christies.com/LotFinder/lot_details.aspx?intObjectID=1787949 Andy Warhol (1928–1987): The Kiss (Bela Lugosi)], christies.com; accessed 1 November 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;

Lugosi was also the subject of &quot;[[Bela Lugosi's Dead]]&quot;, the first single by the English band [[Bauhaus (band)|Bauhaus]]. Released in August 1979, it is often considered to be the first [[gothic rock]] record.

Lugosi's star on the [[Hollywood Walk of Fame]] is mentioned in &quot;[[Celluloid Heroes]]&quot;, a song performed by [[The Kinks]] and written by their lead vocalist and principal songwriter, [[Ray Davies]]. It appeared on their 1972 album ''[[Everybody's in Show-Biz]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Palmer |first1=Bob |title=Everybody's in Showbiz |url=https://www.rollingstone.com/music/music-album-reviews/everybodys-in-showbiz-202212/ |website=Rolling Stone |publisher=Wordpress.com VIP |accessdate=21 February 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A fan of the occult, Lugosi's haunted mirror is on display at [[Zak Bagans]]' haunted museum in Las Vegas, Nevada.

==Filmography==
{{Main|Bela Lugosi filmography}}

==Notes==
{{notelist|group=notes}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
* ''Ed Wood's Bride of the Monster'' by Gary D. Rhodes and Tom Weaver (2015) BearManor Media, {{ISBN|1593938578}}
* ''Tod Browning's Dracula'' by Gary D. Rhodes (2015) Tomahawk Press, {{ISBN|0956683452}}
* ''Bela Lugosi In Person'' by Bill Kaffenberger and Gary D. Rhodes (2015) BearManor Media, {{ISBN|1593938055}}
* ''No Traveler Returns: The Lost Years of Bela Lugosi'' by Bill Kaffenberger and Gary D. Rhodes (2012) BearManor Media, {{ISBN|1593932855}}
* ''Bela Lugosi: Dreams and Nightmares'' by Gary D. Rhodes, with Richard Sheffield, (2007) Collectables/Alpha Video Publishers, {{ISBN|0-9773798-1-7}} (hardcover)
* ''Lugosi: His Life on Film, Stage, and in the Hearts of Horror Lovers'' by Gary D. Rhodes (2006) McFarland &amp; Company, {{ISBN|978-0786427659}} 
* ''The Immortal Count: The Life and Films of Bela Lugosi'' by Arthur Lennig (2003), {{ISBN|0-8131-2273-2}} (hardcover)
* ''Bela Lugosi (Midnight Marquee Actors Series)'' by Gary Svehla and Susan Svehla (1995) {{ISBN|1-887664-01-7}} (paperback)
* ''Bela Lugosi: Master of the Macabre'' by Larry Edwards (1997), {{ISBN|1-881117-09-X}} (paperback)
* ''Films of Bela Lugosi'' by Richard Bojarski (1980) {{ISBN|0-8065-0716-0}} (hardcover)
* ''Sinister Serials of Boris Karloff, Bela Lugosi and Lon Chaney, Jr.'' by Leonard J. Kohl (2000) {{ISBN|1-887664-31-9}} (paperback)
* ''Vampire over London: Bela Lugosi in Britain'' by Frank J. Dello Stritto and Andi Brooks  (2000) {{ISBN|0-9704269-0-9}} (hardcover)
* ''Lugosi: The Man Behind the Cape'' by Robert Cremer (1976) {{ISBN|0-8092-8137-6}} (hardcover)
* ''Bela Lugosi: Biografia di una metamorfosi'' by Edgardo Franzosini (1998) {{ISBN|88-459-1370-8}}

==External links==
{{Portal|Biography}}
{{Commons category|Bela Lugosi}}
{{wikiquote}}
* {{Official website}}
* {{IMDb name}}
* {{PORT.hu person}}
* {{AllMovie name}}
* {{IBDB name}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20160304061735/http://www.cinemascream.com/bela-lugosi-biography-10-facts/ Video Biography] at CinemaScream.com

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Lugosi, Bela}}
[[Category:1882 births]]
[[Category:1956 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Lugoj]]
[[Category:19th-century Hungarian people]]
[[Category:20th-century Hungarian male actors]]
[[Category:20th-century American male actors]]
[[Category:19th-century Roman Catholics]]
[[Category:20th-century Roman Catholics]]
[[Category:20th-century sailors]]
[[Category:American male film actors]]
[[Category:American anti-fascists]]
[[Category:American Roman Catholics]]
[[Category:American people of Serbian descent]]
[[Category:American socialists]]
[[Category:American trade unionists]]
[[Category:Austro-Hungarian military personnel of World War I]]
[[Category:Broadway theatre people]]
[[Category:Burials at Holy Cross Cemetery, Culver City]]
[[Category:Disease-related deaths in California]]
[[Category:Hungarian emigrants to the United States]]
[[Category:Hungarian expatriates in Austria]]
[[Category:Hungarian expatriates in Germany]]
[[Category:Hungarian male film actors]]
[[Category:Hungarian male silent film actors]]
[[Category:Hungarian male stage actors]]
[[Category:Hungarian Roman Catholics]]
[[Category:Hungarian people of Serbian descent]]
[[Category:Hungarian sailors]]
[[Category:Hungarian trade unionists]]
[[Category:Hungarian socialists]]
[[Category:Male Shakespearean actors]]
[[Category:People with acquired American citizenship]]</text>
      <sha1>4etc9je6wu6uratb76z1acf1c3oqgoh</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
