  <page>
    <title>Brigham Young</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5048</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942478174</id>
      <parentid>942378918</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-24T22:38:54Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>2604:2000:E010:1100:DC1B:15D8:6C3:E7F9</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* See also */ add</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|19th-century Latter Day Saint religious leader}}
{{Other uses}}
{{POV check|date=November 2018}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=December 2019}}
{{ Infobox Latter Day Saint biography
 | name                = Brigham Young
 | image               = Brigham Young by Charles William Carter.jpg
 | caption             = Brigham Young [[Circa|c.]] 1870
 | birth_date          = {{birth date|mf = yes|1801|06|01}}
 | birth_place         = [[Whitingham, Vermont]], U.S.
 | death_date          = {{death date and age|mf = yes|1877|08|29|1801|06|01}}
 | death_place         = [[Salt Lake City]], [[Utah Territory]], U.S.
 | death_cause         = Ruptured appendix
 | resting_place       = [[Brigham Young Cemetery]]
 | resting_place_coordinates = {{Coord|40.7703|-111.8856|type:landmark|display=inline|name=Brigham Young Cemetery}}
 | boards              =
 | spouse              = See [[List of Brigham Young's wives]]&lt;!-- Since number of spouses is disputed, leave this blank --&gt;
 | children            = 56&lt;ref name=byubio&gt;{{citation |url= http://yfacts.byu.edu/Article?id=214 |title= Brigham Young Biography: Facts of Faith |work= Y Facts |publisher= BYU |access-date= September 19, 2013 |archive-url= https://archive.today/20130920194808/http://yfacts.byu.edu/Article?id=214 |archive-date= September 20, 2013 |url-status= dead |df= mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
 | parents             = John and Abigail Young
 | awards              =
 | signature           = Brigham Young Signature.svg
 | signature_alt       = Signature of Brigham Young
 | website             = [http://www.brighamyoung.org/ brighamyoung.org]
 | portals             = LDS
 | footnotes           =
 | position_or_quorum1 = 2nd [[President of the Church (LDS Church)|President]] of [[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]]
 | predecessor1        = [[Joseph Smith]]
 | successor1          = [[John Taylor (Mormon)|John Taylor]]
 | start_date1         = {{start date|mf = yes|1847|12|27}}
 | end_date1           = {{end date|mf = yes|1877|08|29}}
 | position_or_quorum2 = [[President of the Quorum of the Twelve Apostles (LDS Church)|President of the Quorum of the Twelve Apostles]]
 | start_date2         = {{start date|1840|04|14}}
 | end_date2           = {{end date|mf = yes|1847|12|27}}
 | predecessor2        = [[Thomas B. Marsh]]
 | successor2          = [[Orson Hyde]]
 | end_reason2         = Became President of the Church
 | position_or_quorum3 = [[Quorum of the Twelve Apostles (LDS Church)|Quorum of the Twelve Apostles]]
 | called_by3          = [[Three Witnesses]]
 | start_date3         = {{start date|mf = yes|1835|02|14}}
 | end_date3           = {{end date|mf = yes|1847|12|27}}
 | end_reason3         = Became President of the Church
 | position_or_quorum4 = [[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints|LDS Church]] [[Apostle (Latter Day Saints)|Apostle]]
 | called_by4          = Three Witnesses
 | start_date4         = {{start date|mf = yes|1835|02|14}}
 | ordination_reason4  = Initial organization of Quorum of the Twelve
 | end_date4           = {{end date|mf = yes|1877|08|29}}
 | reorganization4     = No apostles immediately ordained&lt;ref&gt;A year after Young's death, [[Orson Hyde]] died and [[Moses Thatcher]] was ordained an apostle. The [[First Presidency (LDS Church)|First Presidency]] was not reorganized until October 10, 1880, after which [[Francis M. Lyman]] and [[John Henry Smith]] were ordained. [[Orson Pratt]] died in 1881, and the Quorum of the Twelve did not have twelve members again until October 16, 1882, when [[George Teasdale]] and [[Heber J. Grant]] were ordained.&lt;/ref&gt;
 | political_office1   = 1st [[List of Governors of Utah|Governor of Utah Territory]]
 | term_start1         = February 3, 1851
 | term_end1           = April 12, 1858&lt;!--
 | appointer1          = [[Millard Filmore]] --&gt;
 | office_predecessor1 = None
 | office_successor1   = [[Alfred Cumming (governor)|Alfred Cumming]]
 | list_notes          = Succeeded Smith as leader of the LDS Church.  Was also [[List of Governors of Utah|Governor of Utah Territory]] from February 3, 1851 to April 12, 1858.
 | poly_date           = April 5, 1841&lt;ref name=&quot;Nauvoo Roots&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Smith|1994|p=16}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 | poly_wives          = 55
 | poly_notes          = Is probably the most famous Latter Day Saint polygamist with 55 wives.
}}
'''Brigham Young''' ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|b|r|ɪ|ɡ|əm}}; June 1, 1801{{snd}}August 29, 1877)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://ancestors.familysearch.org/en/KWJH-9QN/brigham-young-1801-1877|title=Brigham Young (1801–1877) {{!}} FamilySearch|website=ancestors.familysearch.org|access-date=October 5, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; was an American [[religious leader]], politician, and [[settler]]. He was the second [[President of the Church (LDS Church)|president]] of [[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]] (LDS Church) from 1847 until his death in 1877. He founded [[Salt Lake City]] and he served as the first governor of the [[Utah Territory]]. Young also led the foundings of the precursors to the [[University of Utah]] and [[Brigham Young University]].

Young had many nicknames, among the most popular being &quot;American [[Moses]]&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |url=https://newsroom.churchofjesuschrist.org/article/brigham-young |title=Topics and Background: Topic {{ndash}} Brigham Young |work=Newsroom (MormonNewsroom.org) |publisher=LDS Church }}&lt;/ref&gt; (alternatively, the &quot;Modern Moses&quot; or &quot;Mormon Moses&quot;),&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |first=Francis M. |last=Gibbons |authorlink=Francis M. Gibbons |title=Brigham Young: Modern Moses, Prophet of God |place=Salt Lake City, Utah |publisher=Deseret Book |year=1981 |isbn=978-0877478584 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |authorlink=Jason Lee Steorts| first=Jason Lee |last=Steorts |url=https://www.nationalreview.com/nrd/articles/330077/mormon-moses |title=The Mormon Moses |journal=[[National Review]] |date=October 29, 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt; because, like the [[Bible|biblical]] figure, Young led his followers, the [[Mormon pioneers]], in an [[Emigration|exodus]] through a desert, to what they saw as a promised land.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |first=Russell M. |last=Nelson |authorlink=Russell M. Nelson |url=https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/ensign/1999/07/the-exodus-repeated |title=The Exodus Repeated |journal=[[Ensign (LDS magazine)|Ensign]] |date=July 1999 |quote=Many instructive parallels exist between the exodus from Egypt of the Israelites under Moses and the exodus from the United States of the Latter-day Saint pioneers under Brigham Young. We can learn much from these stalwarts of ancient and modern Israel.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Young was dubbed by his followers the &quot;Lion of the Lord&quot; for his bold personality and commonly was called &quot;Brother Brigham&quot; by [[Latter-day Saint]]s. A [[Polygamy and the Latter Day Saint movement|polygamist]], Young had 55 wives. He [[Black people and Mormon priesthood|instituted a church ban]] against conferring the [[Black people and early Mormonism|priesthood on men of black African descent]], and also led the church during the [[Utah War]] against the [[United States Armed Forces|United States]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Roberts |first1=David |title=The Brink of War |url=https://www.smithsonianmag.com/history/the-brink-of-war-48447228/ |website=Smithsonian Magazine |publisher=Smithsonian Institution}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early life==
[[File:Brigham Young and his brothers.jpg|225px|thumb|left|The five sons of John and Nabby Young&lt;br&gt;From left to right: Lorenzo Dow, Brigham, [[Phineas Young|Phineas H.]], [[Joseph Young|Joseph]], and John.]]

Young was born the eighth child of John Young and Abigail &quot;Nabby&quot; Howe&lt;ref&gt;Thomas G. Alexander. ''Brigham Young and the Expansion of Mormonsim'', University of Oklahoma Press]&lt;/ref&gt;, a farming family in [[Whitingham, Vermont]]. When he was three his family moved to upstate New York settling in [[Sherburne, New York]].&lt;ref&gt;Alexander, ''Brigham Young''&lt;/ref&gt; At age 12 he moved with his parents to [[Aurelius, New York]] close to Cayuga Lake. When he was 14 his mother died of Tuberculosis. After that he moved with his father to [[Tyrone, New York]]. 

At age 16, Young's father made him leave home. He first worked odd jobs and then became an apprentice to a John C. Jeffries in [[Auburn, New York]]. He worked as a carpenter, joined, glazer and painter.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |last=Sheret |first=John G. |url=http://crookedlakereview.com/articles/136_167/141fall2006winter2007/141sheret.html |title=Brigham Young: Carpenter and Cabinet Maker |work=The Crooked Lake Review |issue=141 |date=Fall 2006 – Winter 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt; One home Young helped paint in Auburn was that of [[Elijah Miller]], which later became the residence of [[William Seward]]. It is now a local museum (see [[William Seward House]]). It is also claimed by locals that the fireplace mantle of this house was created by Young.&lt;ref&gt;Alexander, ''Brigham Young''&lt;/ref&gt; With the onset of the depression of 1819 Jeffries dismissed Young from his apprenticeship and Young moved to [[Port Byron, New York]].&lt;ref&gt;Alexander, ''Brigham Young''&lt;/ref&gt;

Young had converted to the Reformed Methodist Church in 1824. This was after a period of deep reading of the Bible. He insisted when joining the Methodists on being baptized by immersion instead of their normal practice of sprinkling.&lt;ref&gt;Aldexander, ''Brigham Young''&lt;/ref&gt;

Young was first married in 1824 to Miriam Angeline Works, whom he had met in Port Byron. They first lived in a small unpainted house adjacent to the pail factory which was at the time Young's main place of employment. Also in Port Byron, Young joined a debating society. Shortly after the birth of their first daughter the family moved to [[Oswego, New York]] on the shores of Lake Ontario. Later on in 1828 they moved to [[Mendon, New York]]. Most of Young's siblings had already moved to Mendon, or did so shortly after he moved there. It was here he first became friends with [[Heber C. Kimball]]. Here he worked as a carpenter and joined and built a saw mill that he operated.&lt;ref&gt;Alexander, ''Brigham Young''&lt;/ref&gt; In 1832, Mariam died and Young and his two young daughters moved into the household of Kimball and his wife, Vilate.

By this point Young had for all intents and purposes left the Reformed Methodist, becoming a Christian seeker, unconvinced that he had found a church with the true authority of Jesus Christ. As early as 1830, Young was introduced to the [[Book of Mormon]] by way of a copy his brother, Phineas H., had obtained from [[Samuel H. Smith (Latter Day Saints)|Samuel H. Smith]]. In 1831, five missionaries of the [[Latter Day Saint movement]] (Eleazer Miller, Elial Strong, Alpheus Gifford, Enos Curtis, and Daniel Bowen) came from the branch of the church in [[Columbia, Pennsylvania]] to preach in Mendon. A key attraction of the teachings of this group to Young was their practicing of spiritual gifts. This was partly experienced when Young traveled with his wife and Kimball to visit the branch of the church in Columbia, Pennsylvania.&lt;ref&gt;Alexander, ''Brigham Young''&lt;/ref&gt;

Young was drawn to the new church after reading the Book of Mormon. He officially joined the [[Church of Christ (Latter Day Saints)|Church of Christ]] on April 14, 1832, being baptized by Eleazer Miller. A branch of the church was organized in Mendon, and Young was one of the regular preachers to the branch. He quickly expanded his area of sharing the gospel of Jesus Christ, traveling southwest to [[Warsaw, New York]] and southeast to various towns along Lake Canandaigua.&lt;ref&gt;Alexander, ''Brigham Young''&lt;/ref&gt; Shortly after this, Young saw Alpheus Gifford speak in tongues and in response Young also spoke in an unknown language. In November 1832, Young travelled with Kimball to [[Kirtland, Ohio]] and visited [[Joseph Smith]]. During this trip Young spoke in a tongue that was identified by Smith as the &quot;Adamic language&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Alexander, ''Brigham Young''&lt;/ref&gt;

In December 1832, Young left his daughters with the Kimballs and set out on a mission with his brother, [[Joseph Young|Joseph]], to [[Upper Canada]], primarily to what is now [[Kingston, Ontario]]. Later they extended their preaching to various towns along the north shore of Lake Erie. In February 1833, they returned to Mendon. A few months later Young again set out on a mission with his brother, Joseph, this time traveling into the north of New York and then on into modern Ontario.

In the summer of 1833, Young moved to [[Kirtland, Ohio]]. Here he met Mary Ann Angell and they were married on February 18, 1834. In Kirtland, Young continued to preach the gospel, in fact Mary Ann first encountered him through hearing him preach. Young also resumed work on building houses. In May 1834, Young became a member of [[Zion's Camp]]. He traveled to Missouri and was part of it until it disbanded on July 3, 1834. After his return to Kirtland, Young focused his carpentry work on the [[Kirtland Temple]] and also prepared for the birth of his third child, his first son, [[Joseph A. Young]]. Mary Ann had largely provided for Young's two daughters on her own while pregnant with her first child while Young was away with Zion's Camp.&lt;ref&gt;Alexander, ''Brigham Young''&lt;/ref&gt; In Kirtland, Young was involved in adult education including studying in a Hebrew language class under Joshua Sexias.

==Church service==
Young was ordained a member of the original [[Quorum of the Twelve|Quorum of the Twelve Apostles]] in May 1835. Later that month, Young left with the other members of the Quorum of the Twelve on a proselytizing mission to New York state and New England. In August 1835, Young and the rest of the Quorum of the Twelve issued a testimony in support of the divine origin of the [[Doctrine and Covenants]]. He was then involved in the dedication of the Kirtland Temple in 1836. Shortly after this Young went on another mission with his brother, Joseph, to New York and New England. On this mission he visited the family of his aunt, Rhoda Howe Richards. They converted to the church, including his cousin [[Willard Richards]]. He then returned to Kirtland where he remained until events related to anger over the failure of the [[Kirtland Safety Society]] forced him to flee the community in December 1837. He then stayed for a short time in [[Dublin, Indiana]] with his brother, Lorenzo, and then moved on to [[Caldwell County, Missouri]].&lt;ref&gt;Alexander, ''Brigham Young''&lt;/ref&gt;

Young became the [[President of the Quorum of the Twelve Apostles|quorum president]] in March 1839. Under his direction, the quorum served a mission to the United Kingdom and organized the exodus of Latter Day Saints from Missouri in 1838.

In 1844, while in jail awaiting trial for treason charges, the church's president, Joseph Smith was [[Death of Joseph Smith|killed by an armed mob]]. Several claimants to the role of church president emerged during [[Succession crisis (Latter Day Saints)|the succession crisis]] that ensued. Before a large meeting convened to discuss the succession in [[Nauvoo, Illinois]], [[Sidney Rigdon]], the senior surviving member of the church's [[First Presidency]], argued there could be no successor to the deceased prophet and that he should be made the &quot;Protector&quot; of the church.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |editor-link=B. H. Roberts |editor-last=Roberts |editor-first=B. H. |title=History of the Church |volume=7 |chapter=XVIII|title-link=History of the Church (Joseph Smith) }}&lt;/ref&gt; Young opposed this reasoning and motion. Smith had earlier recorded a [[revelation (Latter Day Saints)|revelation]] which stated the Quorum of the Twelve was &quot;equal in authority and power&quot; to the First Presidency,&lt;ref&gt;{{lds|Doctrine and Covenants|dc|107|23|24}}&lt;/ref&gt; so Young claimed that the leadership of the church fell to the Twelve Apostles.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |editor-link=B. H. Roberts |editor-last=Roberts |editor-first=B. H. |title=History of the Church |volume=7 |chapter=XIX|title-link=History of the Church (Joseph Smith) }}&lt;/ref&gt; The majority in attendance were persuaded that the Quorum of the Twelve was to lead the church, with Young as the quorum's president. Many of Young's followers would later reminisce that while Young spoke to the congregation, he looked or sounded exactly like Smith, which they attributed to the power of God.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=The Mormon Hierarchy: Origins of Power|last=Quinn|first=D. Michael|publisher=Signature Books|year=1994|isbn=1-56085-056-6|page=166|authorlink=D. Michael Quinn}}; {{Harvnb|Harper|1996}}; {{citation|last=Jorgensen|first=Lynne Watkins|title=Opening the Heavens: Accounts of Divine Manifestations, 1820–1844|year=2005|pages=374–480|contribution=The Mantle of the Prophet Joseph Smith Passes to Brother Brigham: One Hundred Twenty-one Testimonies of a Collective Spiritual Witness|place=Provo, Utah|publisher=[[BYU Press]]|editor-last=Welch|editor-first=John W.|editor-link=John W. Welch}}; {{citation|last=England|first=Eugene|title=George Laub's Nauvoo Journal|date=Winter 1978|quote=Now when President Young arose to address the congregation his voice was the voice of Bro[ther] Joseph and his face appeared as Joseph's face &amp; should I have not seen his face but heard his voice I should have declared that it was Joseph. [spelling and punctuation normalized]|journal=[[BYU Studies]]|volume=18|page=16}}; {{citation|last=Burton|first=William|title=William Burton Diary, May 1845|quote=But their [Joseph Smith and Hyrum Smith's] places were filed by others much better than I once supposed they could have been, the spirit of Joseph appeared to rest upon Brigham&quot;|location=LDS Church Archives}}; {{citation|last=Johnson|first=Benjamin F.|title=My Life's Review|year=1928|quote=But as soon as he spoke I jumped upon my feet, for in every possible degree it was Joseph's voice, and his person, in look, attitude, dress and appearance; [it] was Joseph himself, personified and I knew in a moment the spirit and mantle of Joseph was upon him&quot;|pages=103–104|location=Independence}}; {{citation|title=Life Story of Mosiah Hancock|quote=Although only a boy, I saw the mantle of the Prophet Joseph rest upon Brigham Young; and he arose lion-like to the occasion and led the people forth|page=23|location=BYU Library}}; {{citation|last=Woodruff|first=Wilford|title=none|date=March 15, 1892|quote=If I had not seen him with my own eyes, there is no one that could have convinced me that it was not Joseph Smith|authorlink=Wilford Woodruff|newspaper=Deseret News}}; {{citation|last=Cannon|first=George Q.|title=none|date=October 29, 1870|quote=When Brigham Young spoke it was with the voice of Joseph himself; and not only was it the voice of Joseph which was heard, but it seemed in the eyes of the people as though it was the every person of Joseph which stood before them|authorlink=George Q. Cannon|journal=[[Juvenile Instructor]]|volume=5|issue=22|pages=174–175}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt; However, historians have come to different conclusions on whether the occurrence of such events is supported by contemporary records. Van Wagoner observed of contemporary accounts that &quot;none of these references an explicit transfiguration, a physical metamorphosis of Brigham Young into the form and voice of Joseph Smith,&quot; and &quot;[w]hen 8 August 1844 is stripped of emotional overlay, there is not a shred of irrefutable contemporary evidence to support the occurrence of a mystical event either in the morning or afternoon gatherings of that day.&quot;: {{cite journal |last=Van Wagoner |first=Richard S. |date=Winter 1995 |title=The Making of a Mormon Myth: The 1844 Transfiguration of Brigham Young |journal=Dialogue: A Journal of Mormon Thought |volume=28 |issue=4 |pages=1–24 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Jorgenson |first=Lynne W. |year=1996–97 |title=The Mantle of the Prophet Joseph Passes to Brother Brigham: A Collective Spiritual Witness |journal=BYU Studies |volume=36 |issue=4 |pages=125–204 |ref=harv }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Arrington |first=Leonard J. |title=Brigham Young: American Moses |publisher=University of Illinois Press |pages=[https://archive.org/details/brighamyoungamer00arri/page/114 114–115] |year=1986 |isbn=0-252-01296-8 |url-access=registration |url=https://archive.org/details/brighamyoungamer00arri/page/114 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Young was ordained President of the Church in December 1847, three and a half years after Smith's death. Rigdon became the president of [[Rigdonite|a separate church organization]] based in [[Pittsburgh]], Pennsylvania, and other potential successors emerged to lead what became other denominations of the movement.

==Migration west==
{{See also|Mormon pioneers}}
Repeated conflict led Young to relocate his group of Latter-day Saints to the [[Salt Lake Valley]], which was then part of Mexico. Young organized the journey that would take the [[Mormon pioneers]] to [[Winter Quarters, Nebraska]], in 1846, then to the Salt Lake Valley. By the time Young arrived at the final destination, it had come under American control as a result of [[Mexican–American War|war with Mexico]], although U.S. sovereignty would not be confirmed [[Treaty of Guadalupe Hidalgo|until 1848]]. Young arrived in the Salt Lake Valley on July 24, 1847, a date now recognized as [[Pioneer Day (Utah)|Pioneer Day]] in Utah. Young's expedition was one of the largest and one of the best organized westward treks.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web
|url=http://historytogo.utah.gov/people/brighamyoung.html|title=Brigham Young|website=historytogo.utah.gov|access-date=February 29, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; On August 22, 29 days after arriving in the Salt Lake Valley, Young organized the [[Mormon Tabernacle Choir]].&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |url=http://mormontabernaclechoir.org/faq |title=Frequently Asked Questions {{ndash}} When was the Mormon Tabernacle Choir formed?|work=Mormontabernaclechoir.org |publisher=[[Mormon Tabernacle Choir]] |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130329063236/http://www.mormontabernaclechoir.org/faq |archivedate=March 29, 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

After three years of leading the church as the [[President of the Quorum of the Twelve Apostles (LDS Church)|President of the Quorum of the Twelve Apostles]], Young reorganized a new [[First Presidency (LDS Church)|First Presidency]] and was [[Common consent|sustained]] as the second president of the church on December 27, 1847.

==Governor of Utah Territory==
[[File:1853 Brigham Young Daguerreotype.jpg|thumb|upright|left|A beardless Brigham Young in 1853.]]
As colonizer and founder of [[Salt Lake City]], Young was appointed the territory's first governor and superintendent of [[Indigenous peoples of the Americas|American Indian]] affairs by [[Millard Fillmore|President Millard Fillmore]] on February 3, 1851.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://udn.lib.utah.edu/cdm4/document.php?CISOROOT=/tgm14&amp;CISOSHOW=102598&amp;CISOPTR=102457 | title=Utah's new capitol grows from humble beginning; first political sessions were held in council house; fight for statehood | newspaper=Salt Lake Telegram | date=October 22, 1916 | accessdate=May 14, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; During his time as prophet, Young directed the establishment of settlements throughout present-day Utah, Idaho, Arizona, Nevada, California and parts of southern Colorado and northern Mexico. Under his direction, the Mormons built roads and bridges, forts, irrigation projects; established public welfare; organized a militia; [[Battle at Fort Utah|issued an extermination order against the Timpanogos]] and after a series of wars eventually made peace with the Native Americans. Young was also one of the first to subscribe to [[Union Pacific Railroad|Union Pacific]] stock, for the construction of the [[First Transcontinental Railroad]]. Young organized the first legislature and established [[Fillmore, Utah|Fillmore]] as the territory's first capital.

Young organized a board of regents to establish a university in the Salt Lake Valley.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |url=http://utahhistory.sdlhost.com/#/item/000000011019614/view/33 |title=The Beginnings of the University of Utah |first=Yvette D. |last=Ison |date=January 1995 |journal=History Blazer |publisher=Utah State Historical Society }}. [http://historytogo.utah.gov/utah_chapters/pioneers_and_cowboys/thebeginningsoftheuniversityofutah.html Online reprint], with permission, at HistoryToGo.utah.gov by the Utah Division of State History, Utah Department of Heritage and Arts, State of Utah.&lt;/ref&gt; It was established on February 28, 1850, as the University of Deseret; its name was eventually changed to the [[University of Utah]].

[[File:Brigham Young by Charles Roscoe Savage, 1855.jpg|thumb|upright|150px|right|Brigham Young photographed by Charles Roscoe Savage, 1855]]
In 1851, Young and several federal officials, including territorial Secretary [[Broughton Harris]], became unable to work cooperatively. Harris and the others departed Utah without replacements being named, and these individuals later became known as the [[Runaway Officials of 1851]].&lt;ref&gt;Randal S. Chase, [https://books.google.com/books?id=OvnSO8VKD0EC&amp;pg=PA85&amp;dq=broughton+harris+brigham+young+brandenbury&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=CLiwUpi_EIzgsASW2YKQDg&amp;ved=0CDUQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=broughton%20harris%20brigham%20young%20brandenbury&amp;f=false Church History Study Guide], Part 3, 2012, p. 85.&lt;/ref&gt;

Young supported slavery and [[History of slavery in Utah|its expansion into Utah]], and led the efforts to legalize and regulate slavery in the 1852 [[Act in Relation to Service]], based on [[Mormonism and slavery|his beliefs on slavery]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Journals of the Legislative Assembly of the Territory of Utah, of the ... Annual Session, for the Years ..., Volume 1|author=Utah Legislative Assembly|year=1852|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=PH1DAQAAMAAJ|pages=108–110}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Young Collier&quot;&gt;{{citation |title=The Teachings of President Brigham Young: Vol. 3 1852–1854 |editor-first=Fred C. |editor-last=Collier |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=LkRZGQ8oO8IC|year=1987 |first=Brigham |last=Young |location=Salt Lake City, Utah |publisher=Colliers Publishing Company |isbn=0934964017 |oclc=18192348 |pages=26–28|quote=Inasmuch as we believe in the ordinances of God, in the Priesthood and order and decrees of God, we must believe in slavery}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mit.irr.org/brigham-young-we-must-believe-in-slavery-23-january-1852|title=Brigham Young: We Must Believe in Slavery (23 January 1852)|website=mit.irr.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1856, Young organized an efficient mail service. In 1858, following the events of the [[Utah War]], he stepped down to his successor, [[Alfred Cumming (governor)|Alfred Cumming]].&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |url=http://archives.utah.gov/research/guides/governor-young.htm |title=Brigham Young |publisher=Utah State Archives }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==LDS Church president==
Young was the longest-serving president of the LDS Church in history, having served for 29 years.

===Educational endeavors===
On October 16, 1875, Young deeded buildings and land in [[Provo, Utah]] to a board of trustees for establishing an institution of learning, ostensibly as part of the University of Deseret.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Sloan|first=Robert W.|title=Utah Gazatteer and Directory of Logan, Ogden, Provo and Salt Lake Cities, for 1884|year=1884|page=278|url=https://books.google.com/?id=-tABAAAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA17}}&lt;/ref&gt; Young said, &quot;I hope to see an Academy established in Provo ... at which the children of the Latter-day Saints can receive a good education unmixed with the pernicious atheistic influences that are found in so many of the higher schools of the country.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;dusenberry&quot;/&gt; The school broke off from the University of Deseret and became [[Brigham Young Academy]],&lt;ref name=&quot;dusenberry&quot;&gt;{{cite news |first=Sarah |last=Bills |url=http://newsnet.byu.edu/story.cfm/43900 |title=Warren Dusenberry (1875–1876) |newspaper=[[The Universe (BYU)|The Universe]] |publisher=BYU NewsNet |date=April 16, 2003 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120207182134/http://newsnet.byu.edu/story.cfm/43900 |archivedate=February 7, 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt; the precursor to [[Brigham Young University]].

Within the church, Young reorganized the [[Relief Society]] for women in 1867, and he created organizations for [[Young Women (organization)|young women]] in 1869 and [[Young Men (organization)|young men]] in 1875.

===Temple building===
Young was involved in [[Temple (LDS Church)|temple]] building throughout his membership in the LDS Church, making it a priority of his church presidency. Under Smith's leadership, Young participated in the building of the [[Kirtland Temple|Kirtland]] and [[Nauvoo Temple|Nauvoo]] temples. Just four days after arriving in the Salt Lake Valley, Young designated the location for the [[Salt Lake Temple]]; he presided over its groundbreaking on April 6, 1853.&lt;ref name=&quot;EoM&quot;&gt;{{citation |last=Hanks |first=Marion Duff |authorlink=Marion D. Hanks |contribution=Salt Lake Temple |url=http://contentdm.lib.byu.edu/cdm/ref/collection/EoM/id/4155 |pages=1252–1254 |editor1-last=Ludlow |editor1-first=Daniel H |editor1-link=Daniel H. Ludlow |title=Encyclopedia of Mormonism |location=New York |publisher=[[Macmillan Publishing]] |year=1992 |isbn=0-02-879602-0 |oclc=24502140 }}&lt;/ref&gt; During his tenure, Young oversaw construction of the [[Salt Lake Tabernacle]] and he announced plans to build the [[St. George Utah Temple|St. George]] (1871), [[Manti Utah Temple|Manti]] (1875), and [[Logan Utah Temple|Logan]] (1877) temples. He also provisioned the building of the [[Endowment House]], a &quot;temporary temple&quot; which began to be used in 1855 to provide temple [[ordinance (Latter Day Saints)|ordinances]] to church members while the Salt Lake Temple was under construction.

===Teachings===
The majority of Young's teachings are contained in the 19 volumes of transcribed and edited sermons in the [[Journal of Discourses]].  The LDS Church's [[Doctrine and Covenants]] contains one section from Young that has been canonized as scripture, adding the section in 1876.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/scriptures/dc-testament/dc/136?lang=eng The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]&lt;/ref&gt;

{{LDSpolygamy}}Though [[plural marriage|polygamy]] was practiced by Young's predecessor [[Joseph Smith]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/topics/plural-marriage-in-kirtland-and-nauvoo?lang=eng|title=Plural Marriage in Kirtland and Nauvoo|website=ChurchofJesusChrist.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; the practice is often associated with Young. Some Latter Day Saint denominations, such as the [[Community of Christ]], consider Young the &quot;Father of Mormon Polygamy&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |author=Richard and Pamela Price |title=Joseph Smith Fought Polygamy: How Men Nearest the Prophet Attached Polygamy to His Name in Order to Justify Their Own Polygamous Crimes |place=Independence, Missouri |publisher=Price Publishing Company |year=2000 |chapter-url=http://restorationbookstore.org/articles/nopoligamy/jsfp-vol1/chp4.htm |chapter=Vol.1, Ch.4: Brigham Young: The Father of Mormon Polygamy |isbn=1891353063 |oclc=42027453 |lccn=99041763 |type=[[self-published]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1853, Young made the church's first official statement on the subject since the church had arrived in Utah. Young acknowledged the suffering the doctrine created for women, but stated its necessity for creating large families, proclaiming: &quot;But the first wife will say, 'It is hard, for I have lived with my husband twenty years, or thirty, and have raised a family of children for him, and it is a great trial to me for him to have more women;' then I say it is time that you gave him up to other women who will bear children.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;http://jod.mrm.org/4/51. Vol.4 p.56&lt;/ref&gt;

One of the more controversial teachings of Young was the [[Adam–God doctrine]]. According to Young, he was taught by Smith that [[Adam]] is &quot;our Father and our God, and the only God with whom we have to do&quot;. According to the doctrine, Adam was once a mortal man who became resurrected and [[exaltation (Latter Day Saints)|exalted]]. From another planet, Adam brought [[Eve]], one of his wives, with him to the earth, where they became mortal by eating the fruit of the [[Garden of Eden]]. After bearing mortal children and establishing the human race, Adam and Eve returned to their heavenly thrones where Adam acts as the god of this world. Later, as Young is generally understood to have taught, Adam returned to the earth to become the biological father of Jesus.&lt;ref&gt;Widmer, Kurt (2000), ''Mormonism and the Nature of God: A Theological Evolution, 1830–1915'', Jefferson, N.C.: McFarland, p. 131.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Gary James Bergera, [http://content.lib.utah.edu/u?/dialogue,2878 &quot;The Orson Pratt–Brigham Young Controversies: Conflict Within the Quorums, 1853 to 1868&quot;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110614014538/http://content.lib.utah.edu/u/?%2Fdialogue%2C2878 |date=June 14, 2011 }}, [[Dialogue: A Journal of Mormon Thought]] '''13'''(2):7–49 (1980) at p. 41.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Boyd Kirkland, [https://www.sunstonemagazine.com/wp-content/uploads/sbi/articles/044-36-44.pdf &quot;Jehovah as the Father: The Development of the Mormon Jehovah Doctrine&quot;], ''[[Sunstone (magazine)|Sunstone]]'' '''44''':36–44 (1984) at p. 39 (Adam &quot;later begot Jesus, his firstborn spirit son, in the flesh&quot;).&lt;/ref&gt; The LDS Church has since repudiated the Adam–God doctrine.&lt;ref&gt;Spencer W. Kimball, [https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/ensign/1976/11/our-own-liahona?lang=eng &quot;Our Own Liahona,&quot;] ''[[Ensign (LDS magazine)|Ensign]]'', November 1976, p. 77 (&quot;We denounce that theory and hope that everyone will be cautioned against this and other kinds of false doctrine.&quot;).&lt;/ref&gt;

Young is generally considered to have instituted [[Black people and Mormonism|a church ban]] against conferring the priesthood on men of black African descent, who had been treated equally in this respect under Smith's presidency.&lt;ref name=Bush&gt;{{cite book |last=Bush |first=Lester E., Jr. |first2=Armand L. |last2=Mauss |author2-link=Armand Mauss |title=Neither White nor Black: Mormon Scholars Confront the Race Issue in a Universal Church |publisher=Signature Books |year=1984 |location=Midvale, Utah |pages =54–65, 70 |chapter=Chapter 3: Mormonism's Negro Doctrine: An Historical Overview |chapter-url=http://signaturebookslibrary.org/?p=445 |isbn=978-0-941214-22-3 }}&lt;/ref&gt; After settling in Utah in 1848, Young announced the ban,&lt;ref name=Bush/&gt; which also forbade blacks from participating in Mormon temple rites such as the [[Endowment (Latter Day Saints)|endowment]] or [[sealing (Latter Day Saints)|sealings]]. On many occasions, Young taught that blacks were denied the priesthood because they were &quot;the seed of Cain&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |url=https://www.dialoguejournal.com/2012/mormonisms-negro-doctrine-an-historical-overview/|title=Mormonism's Negro Doctrine: An Historical Overview |publisher=Dialogue |date=Spring 1973 |author=Bush, Lester E. |pages=54–97 |accessdate=December 17, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; but also stated that they would eventually receive the priesthood after &quot;all the other children of Adam have the privilege of receiving the Priesthood, and of coming into the kingdom of God, and of being redeemed from the four-quarters of the earth, and have received their resurrection from the dead, then it will be time enough to remove the curse from Cain and his posterity.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |title=Journal of Discourses |volume=2 |page=[http://contentdm.lib.byu.edu/cdm/compoundobject/collection/JournalOfDiscourses3/id/9600/rec/2 142]|title-link=Journal of Discourses }}&lt;/ref&gt; These racial restrictions remained in place until 1978, when the policy was rescinded by LDS Church president [[Spencer W. Kimball]],&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |chapter-url=https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/scriptures/dc-testament/od/2?lang=eng |contribution=Official Declaration 2 |title=Doctrine and Covenants|title-link=Doctrine and Covenants }}&lt;/ref&gt; and the LDS Church subsequently &quot;disavow[ed] theories advanced in the past&quot; to explain this ban,&lt;ref name=&quot;Gospel Topics-Race and the Priesthood&quot;&gt;{{citation |url=https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/topics/race-and-the-priesthood |title=Gospel Topics {{ndash}} Race and the Priesthood |publisher=LDS Church }}&lt;/ref&gt; thereby &quot;plac[ing] the origins of black priesthood denial blame squarely on Brigham Young.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=The Mormon Church Disavows Its Racist Past But Still Offers No Apology|work=[[HuffPost]]|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/darron-t-smith-phd/the-mormon-church-disavow_b_4440244.html|accessdate=December 17, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

In 1863, Young stated: &quot;Shall I tell you the law of God in regard to the African race? If the white man who belongs to the chosen seed mixes his blood with the seed of Cain, the penalty, under the law of God, is death on the spot. This will always be so.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |title=Journal of Discourses |volume=10 |page=[http://contentdm.lib.byu.edu/cdm/ref/collection/JournalOfDiscourses3/id/4266 110]|title-link=Journal of Discourses }}. See also: [[miscegenation]].&lt;/ref&gt; 

Young was a vocal opponent of theories of human polygenesis, being a firm voice for stating that all humans were the product of one creation.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.patheos.com/blogs/danpeterson/2015/08/brigham-young-against-a-then-fashionable-scientific-form-of-racism.html Daniel Peterson quoting statements from Paul Reeve in ''Religion of a Different Color'']&lt;/ref&gt;

===Conflicts===
Shortly after the arrival of Young's pioneers, the new Mormon colonies were incorporated into the United States through the [[Mexican Cession]]. Young petitioned the [[U.S. Congress]] to create the [[State of Deseret]]. The [[Compromise of 1850]] instead carved out [[Utah Territory]] and Young was installed as governor. As governor and church president, Young directed both religious and economic matters. He encouraged independence and self-sufficiency. Many cities and towns in Utah, and some in neighboring states, were founded under Young's direction. Young's leadership style has been viewed as autocratic.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |url=http://encarta.msn.com/encyclopedia_761555412/Brigham_Young.html |title=Brigham Young |work=[[Encarta]] |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20091030200308/http://encarta.msn.com/encyclopedia_761555412/Brigham_Young.html |url-status=dead |archivedate=October 30, 2009 |access-date=October 31, 2009  }}.{{unreliable source?|date=September 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; When federal officials received reports of widespread and systematic obstruction of federal officials in Utah (most notably judges), U.S. President [[James Buchanan]] decided to install a non-Mormon governor. Buchanan accepted the reports of the judges without any further investigation, and the new non-sectarian governor was accompanied by troops sent to garrison forts in the new territory. When Young received word that federal troops were headed to Utah with his replacement, he called out his militia to ambush the federal force. During the defense of Utah, now called the [[Utah War]], Young held the [[U.S. Army]] at bay for a winter by taking their cattle and burning supply wagons. The Mormon forces were largely successful thanks to [[Lot Smith]]. Young eventually relented and agreed to step down as governor. He later received a [[pardon]] from Buchanan. Relations between Young and future governors and U.S. Presidents were mixed.

[[File:Brigham Young and company 1870.PNG|thumb|left|500px|Brigham Young (seated near the middle, wearing a tall [[beaver hat]]) and an exploring party camped at the [[Colorado River]] in 1870]]

The degree of Young's involvement in the [[Mountain Meadows massacre]], which took place in [[Washington County, Utah|Washington County]] in 1857, is disputed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Emily |last=Eakin |title=Reopening a Mormon Murder Mystery; New Accusations That Brigham Young Himself Ordered an 1857 Massacre of Pioneers |url=http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F10E17F6395E0C718DDDA90994DA404482&amp;showabstract=1 |work=[[The New York Times]] |date=October 12, 2002 |edition=Late Edition-Final |page=Section B, Page 9, Column 2}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Leonard J. Arrington]] reports that Young received a rider at his office on the day of the massacre, and that when he learned of the contemplated attack by the members of the LDS Church in Parowan and Cedar City, he sent back a letter directing that the [[Fancher party]] be allowed to pass through the territory unmolested.&lt;ref&gt;Brigham Young to Isaac C. Haight, September 10, 1857, Letterpress Copybook 3:827–28, Brigham Young Office Files, LDS Church Archives&lt;/ref&gt; Young's letter reportedly arrived on September 13, 1857, two days after the massacre. As governor, Young had promised the federal government he would protect immigrants passing through Utah Territory, but over 120 men, women and children were killed in this incident. There is no debate concerning the involvement of individual Mormons from the surrounding communities by scholars. Only children under the age of seven, who were cared for by local Mormon families, survived, and the murdered members of the wagon train were left unburied. The remains of about 40 people were later found and buried, and [[Union Army]] officer [[James Henry Carleton]] had a large cross made from local trees, the transverse beam bearing the engraving, &quot;Vengeance Is Mine, Saith The Lord: I Will Repay&quot; and erected a [[cairn]] of rocks at the site. A large slab of granite was put up on which he had the following words engraved: &quot;Here 120 men, women and children were massacred in cold blood early in September, 1857. They were from Arkansas.&quot; For two years, the monument stood as a memorial to those travelling the [[Old Spanish Trail (trade route)|Spanish Trail]] through Mountain Meadow. Some claim that, in 1861, Young brought an entourage to Mountain Meadows and had the cairn and cross destroyed, while exclaiming, &quot;Vengeance is mine and I have taken a little&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Sally Denton (2003). ''American Massacre: The Tragedy at Mountain Meadows, September 1857'' (New York: [[Vintage Books]], {{ISBN|0-375-72636-5}}) p. 210.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Death===
[[File:BrighamYoungGrave.jpg|right|thumb|Young is buried on the grounds of the [[Mormon Pioneer Memorial Monument]] in [[Salt Lake City]].]]

Before his death in Salt Lake City on August 29, 1877,&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.nytimes.com/1877/08/30/archives/death-of-brigham-young-the-mormon-prophets-history-birth-and-early.html &quot;Death of Brigham Young&quot;], ''[[The New York Times]]'', August 30, 1877.&lt;/ref&gt; Young was suffering from cholera morbus and inflammation of the bowels.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.nytimes.com/1877/08/29/archives/brigham-youngs-health.html &quot;Brigham Young's Health&quot;], ''[[The New York Times]]'', August 29, 1877.&lt;/ref&gt; It is believed that he died of [[peritonitis]] from a ruptured [[Vermiform appendix|appendix]].&lt;ref name=byubio /&gt; His last words were &quot;Joseph! Joseph! Joseph!&quot;, invoking the name of the late Joseph Smith, founder of the Mormon faith.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation |url=https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/ensign/1977/08/brigham-young-man-of-the-spirit |title=Brigham Young: Man of the Spirit |first=D. Michael |last=Quinn |authorlink=D. Michael Quinn |date=August 1977 |journal=[[Ensign (LDS magazine)|Ensign]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; On September 2, 1877, Young's funeral was held in the [[Salt Lake Tabernacle|Tabernacle]] with an estimated 12,000 to 15,000 people in attendance.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.nytimes.com/1877/09/03/archives/brigham-youngs-funeral-a-great-concourse-present-no-intimation-as.html &quot;Brigham Young's Funeral&quot;], ''[[The New York Times]]'', September 3, 1877.&lt;/ref&gt; He is buried on the grounds of the [[Mormon Pioneer Memorial Monument]] in the heart of Salt Lake City. A bronze marker was placed at the grave site June 10, 1938, by members of the [[Young Men (organization)|Young Men]] and [[Young Women (organization)|Young Women]] organizations, which he founded.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://history.utah.gov/apps/markers/detailed_results.php?markerid=2182 |archive-url=https://archive.today/20120717112905/http://history.utah.gov/apps/markers/detailed_results.php?markerid=2182 |archive-date=July 17, 2012 |title=Grave of Brigham Young |publisher=[[State of Utah]] |accessdate=October 17, 2011 |url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy==

===Impact===
A century after his death, one writer stated that&lt;ref name=&quot;paul197412&quot;&gt;{{citation |url=http://calteches.library.caltech.edu/357/1/mormons.pdf |title=The Mormons of Yesterday and Today |publisher=[[California Institute of Technology]] &amp; Alumni Association |journal=Engineering and Science |volume=38 |issue=2 |date= December 1974 – January 1975 |author=Paul, Rodman W. |pages=12–27 |accessdate=September 19, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|[Joseph Smith] was succeeded by one of the outstanding organizers of the 19th century, Brigham Young. If the circumstances of his life had worked out differently [he] might have become a [[captain of industry]]—an [[Andrew Carnegie]] or [[John D. Rockefeller]] or a railroad builder. Instead, this able, energetic, earthy man became the absolute ruler and the revered, genuinely loved father figure of all Mormons everywhere.}}

He credited Young's leadership with helping to settle much of the American West:{{r|paul197412}}

{{quote|During the 30 years between the Mormons' arrival in Utah in 1847 and [his death in] 1877, Young directed the founding of 350 towns in the Southwest. Thereby the Mormons became the most important single agency in colonizing that [[Intermountain West|vast arid West between the Rockies and the Sierra Nevada]].}}

Memorials to Young include a bronze statue in front of the Abraham O. Smoot Administration Building, [[Brigham Young University]]; a [[Brigham Young (Mahonri Young statue)|marble statue]] in the [[National Statuary Hall Collection]] at the [[United States Capitol]], donated by the [[State of Utah]] in 1950;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |url=http://www.aoc.gov/capitol-hill/national-statuary-hall-collection/brigham-young |title=Art: Sculpture {{ndash}} Statues: Brigham Young |work=Explore Capitol Hill |publisher=[[Architect of the Capitol]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; and a statue atop the ''[[This is the Place Monument]]'' in [[Salt Lake City]].
{{multiple image
 | align = right | direction = horizontal | width =
 | header = Memorials to Brigham Young | header_align = center | header_background =
 | footer = | footer_align = left/right/center | footer_background =
 | image1 =| width1 = 145 | caption1 = Statue on campus of [[Brigham Young University]]
 | image2 = Young.jpg | width2 = 121 | caption2 = Statue in [[National Statuary Hall Collection|Statuary Hall]] of the [[United States Capitol]]
 | image3 = This Is The Place Heritage Park.jpg | width3 = 131 | caption3 = ''[[This Is the Place Monument]]'', [[Salt Lake City]]
 | image4 = Brigham Young Monument.jpg | width4 = 144 | caption4 = ''[[Brigham Young Monument]]'', [[Salt Lake City]]
}}

Young's [[Teachings of Presidents of the Church|teachings]] were the 1998–99 course of study in the LDS Church's Sunday [[Relief Society]] and [[Melchizedek priesthood (Latter Day Saints)|Melchizedek priesthood]] classes.

===Family and descendants===
{{See also|List of Brigham Young's wives}}
[[File:In memoriam brigham young 2.jpg|thumb|right|Caricature of Young's wives, after his death]]
Young was a [[plural marriage|polygamist]], marrying a total of 55 wives, 54 of them after he converted to Mormonism.&lt;ref name =&quot;joj&quot;&gt;{{citation |first=Jeffrey Odgen |last=Johnson |url=http://content.lib.utah.edu/u?/dialogue,17879 |title=Determining and Defining 'Wife'&amp;nbsp;— The Brigham Young Households |journal=[[Dialogue: A Journal of Mormon Thought]] |volume=20 |issue=3 |date=Fall 1987 |pages=57–70}}&lt;/ref&gt; The policy was difficult for many in the church. Young stated that upon being taught about plural marriage, &quot;It was the first time in my life that I desired the grave.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |url=https://www.pbs.org/mormons/peopleevents/e_polygamy.html |title=People &amp; Events {{ndash}} Polygamy and the Church: A History |work=[[The Mormons (miniseries)|The Mormons]] |date=April 30, 2007 |publisher=[[PBS]] |accessdate=September 19, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; By the time of his death, Young had 56 children by 16 of his wives; 46 of his children reached adulthood.&lt;ref name=byubio/&gt;

Sources have varied on the number of Young's wives, due to differences in what scholars have considered to be a &quot;wife&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;joj&quot; /&gt; There were 55 women who Young was [[Sealing (Latter Day Saints)|sealed]] to during his lifetime. While the majority of the sealings were [[Celestial marriage|&quot;for eternity&quot;]], some were &quot;for time only&quot;. Researchers believe that not all of the 55 marriages were [[Marriage#Rights and obligations|conjugal]].&lt;ref name=&quot;joj&quot; /&gt; Young did not live with a number of his wives or publicly hold them out as wives, which has led to confusion on the number and their identities.&lt;ref name=&quot;joj&quot; /&gt; This is in part due to the complexity of how wives were identified in the Mormon society at the time.

Of Young's 55 wives, 21 had never been married before; 16 were widows; six were divorced; six had living husbands and the marital status of six others is unknown.&lt;ref name=&quot;joj&quot; /&gt; In 1856, Young built the [[Lion House (Salt Lake City)|Lion House]] to accommodate his sizable family. This building remains a Salt Lake City landmark, together with the [[Beehive House]], another Young family home. A contemporary of Young wrote: &quot;It was amusing to walk by Brigham Young's big house, a long rambling building with innumerable doors. Each wife has an establishment of her own, consisting of parlor, bedroom, and a front door, the key of which she keeps in her pocket.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=DeHegermann-Lindencrone |first=Lillie |title=The Sunny Side of Diplomatic Life, 1875–1912 |url=http://www.gutenberg.org/files/13955/13955-h/13955-h.htm |publisher=Project Gutenberg |accessdate=July 18, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the time of Young's death, 19 of his wives had predeceased him; he was divorced from ten, and 23 survived him. The status of four was unknown.&lt;ref name=&quot;joj&quot; /&gt; One of his wives, Zina Huntington Young, served as the third president of the Relief Society.  In his [[will (law)|will]], Young shared his estate with the 16 surviving wives who had lived with him; the six surviving non-conjugal wives were not mentioned in the will.&lt;ref name=&quot;joj&quot;/&gt;

====Notable descendants====
{{Main|Descendants of Brigham Young}}
In 1902, 25 years after his death, ''The New York Times'' established that Young's direct descendants numbered more than 1,000.&lt;ref&gt;[https://timesmachine.nytimes.com/timesmachine/1902/06/22/101218688.pdf &quot;Descendants of Brigham Young to Hold Annual Mass Meetings&quot;], ''[[The New York Times]]'', June 22, 1902.&lt;/ref&gt; Some of Young's descendants have become leaders in the LDS Church.

==Cultural references==

===In comics===
Brigham Young appeared at the end of [[Le Fil qui chante]] album, the last [[Lucky Luke]] album written by [[Goscinny]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Homer |first1=Michael |title=From Sherlock Holmes to Godzilla: The Mormon Image in Comics |journal=Sunstone |date=September 2010 |page=73 |url=https://www.sunstonemagazine.com/wp-content/uploads/sbi/articles/160-68-73.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===In literature===
The Scottish poet [[John Lyon (poet)|John Lyon]], who was an intimate friend of Young, wrote ''Brigham the Bold'' in tribute to him after his death.&lt;ref&gt;Lyon, T. Edgar (1989). John Lyon : the life of a pioneer poet. Provo, Utah: Religious Studies Center, Brigham Young University. {{ISBN|0-88494-708-4}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://rsc.byu.edu/archived/john-lyon-life-pioneer-poet/fair-home-my-choice-1853-1889|title=&quot;Fair Home of My Choice&quot; (1853–1889) {{!}} Religious Studies Center|website=rsc.byu.edu|access-date=January 24, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Florence Claxton]]'s graphic novel, ''The Adventures of a Woman in Search of Her Rights'' (1872), satirizes a would-be emancipated woman whose failure to establish an independent career results in her marriage to Young before she wakes to discover she's been dreaming.

[[Arthur Conan Doyle]] based his first [[Sherlock Holmes]] novel, ''[[A Study in Scarlet]]'', on Mormon history, mentioning Young by name. When asked to comment on the story, which had, &quot;provoked the animosity of the Mormon faithful&quot;, Doyle noted, &quot;all I said about the [[Danite Band]] and the murders is historical so I cannot withdraw that though it is likely that in a work of fiction it is stated more luridly than in a work of history.&quot; Doyle's daughter stated: &quot;You know father would be the first to admit that his first Sherlock Holmes novel was full of errors about the Mormons.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |first=Harold |last=Schindler |authorlink=Harold Schindler |date=April 10, 1994 |title=The Case of the Repentant Writer: Sherlock Homes' Creator Raises The Wrath Of Mormons |newspaper=[[The Salt Lake Tribune]] |page=D1 |id=Archive Article ID: 101185DCD718AD35 ([[NewsBank]])}}. [http://historytogo.utah.gov/salt_lake_tribune/in_another_time/041094.html Online reprint] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20060923063139/http://historytogo.utah.gov/salt_lake_tribune/in_another_time/041094.html |date=September 23, 2006}}, with permission, at HistoryToGo.utah.gov by the Utah Division of State History, Utah Department of Heritage and Arts, State of Utah.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Mark Twain]] devoted a chapter and much of an appendix to Young in ''[[Roughing It]]''.

[[Oliver Wendell Holmes Sr.]], talking about his fondness of trees, joked in his ''[[The Autocrat of the Breakfast-Table]]'': &quot;I call all trees mine that I have put my wedding-ring on, and I have as many tree-wives as Brigham Young has human ones.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Autocrat of the Breakfast Table|last=Holmes |first=Oliver Wendell|publisher=J.M. Dent &amp; Sons Ltd|year=1952|isbn=1406813176|location=London|pages=222}}&lt;/ref&gt;
===In movies===
Brigham Young was played by [[Dean Jagger]] in the 1940 film ''[[Brigham Young (film)|Brigham Young]]''.

===In television===
{{more citations needed|section|date=November 2017}}
[[Byron Morrow]] played Young in a cameo appearance in the ''[[Death Valley Days]]'' 1966 episode, &quot;An Organ for Brother Brigham&quot;. In the story line, the organ built and guided west to Salt Lake City by Joseph Harris Ridges (1827–1914) of Australia becomes mired in the [[sand]]. Wagonmaster Luke Winner ([[Morgan Woodward]]) feels compelled to leave the instrument behind until Ridges finds solid rock under the sand.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0556554/|title=An Organ for Brother Brigham on ''Death Valley Days''|publisher=Internet Movie Data Base|accessdate=October 5, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In another ''Death Valley Days'' episode in 1969, &quot;Biscuits and Billy, the Kid&quot;, Michael Hinn (1913–1988) of the former ''[[Boots and Saddles (TV series)|Boots and Saddles]]'' western series was cast as Young. In the story line, the Tugwell family, Jason ([[Ben Cooper]]), Ellie (Emily Banks), and Mary ([[Erin Moran]]), are abandoned by their guide while on a wagon train from Utah to California.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0556562/?ref_=ttep_ep19|title=Biscuits and Billy, the Kid|publisher=Internet Movie Data Base|accessdate=July 20, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Gregg Henry]] depicts Young in the fourth (2014) and fifth (2015) seasons of the TV series [[Hell on Wheels (TV series)|''Hell on Wheels'']], a fictional story about the construction of the [[First Transcontinental Railroad]]. As the competing rail lines approach Utah from the east and west coasts, Young supplies Mormon laborers to both railroad companies and negotiates with the railways to have them make Salt Lake City their meeting point. In the Season 5 mid-season finale, &quot;False Prophets&quot;, Young's son, Phineas, attempts to murder his father. Persuaded by The Swede, Phineas believed he was the chosen one to go forward to lead the Mormons, instead of his father.

==Literary works==
Since Young's death, a number of works have published collections of his discourses and sayings.
*{{cite book
  | title     = Teachings of President Brigham Young: Salvation for the Dead, the Spirit World, and Kindred Subjects
  | year      = 1922
  | publisher = Seagull Press
 }}
*{{cite book
  | author    = Brigham Young
  | title     = Discourses of Brigham Young
  | year      = 1925
  | publisher = Deseret Book
  | others    = selected by [[John A. Widtsoe]]
  | url       = https://archive.org/details/discoursesofbrig028407mbp
 }}
*{{cite book
  | author    = Young, Brigham
  | title     = The Best from Brigham Young: Statements from His Sermons on Religion, Education, and Community Building
  | year      = 1952
  | publisher = Deseret Book Company
  | others    = selected by Alice K. Chase
 }}
*{{cite book
  | title     = Manuscript History of Brigham Young, 1801–1844
  | year      = 1969
  | publisher = Eldon J. Watson
 }}
*{{cite book
  | title     = Manuscript History of Brigham Young, 1846–1847
  | year      = 1971
  | publisher = Eldon J. Watson
 }}
*{{cite book
  | title     = Letters of Brigham Young to His Sons
  | year      = 1974
  | publisher = Deseret Book Company
  | editor    = [[Dean C. Jessee]]
 }}
*{{cite book
  | title     = Diary of Brigham Young, 1857
  | year      = 1980
  | publisher = Tanner Trust Fund, University of Utah Library
  | editor    = Everett L. Cooley
  | url       = http://content.lib.utah.edu/u?/tanner,2124
 }}
*{{cite book
  | title     = The Essential Brigham Young
  | year      = 1992
  | publisher = Signature Books
  | isbn      = 1-56085-010-8
  | url       = http://signaturebookslibrary.org/?p=11139
 }}
*{{cite book
  | title     = Teachings of Presidents of the Church: Brigham Young
  | year      = 1997
  | publisher = The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints
 | title-link = Teachings of Presidents of the Church: Brigham Young
 }} LDS Church [https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/item/manual/teachings-brigham-young publication number 35554]
*{{Cite book
  | last       = Young
  | first      = Brigham
  | editor     = [[Richard Van Wagoner]]
  | title      = The Complete Discourses of Brigham Young
  | year       = 2009
  | publisher  = Smith-Pettit Foundation
  | isbn       = 978-1-56085-206-3
  | volume     = 5
  | ref        = harv
 }}

==See also==
{{Wikipedia books
 |1=LDS Church presidents
}}
{{Portal|Latter Day Saint movement}}
* [[Brigham Young (1940 film)|''Brigham Young'' (1940 film)]]
* [[Brigham Young Winter Home and Office]]
* [[This Is The Place Heritage Park]]
* [[Ann Eliza Young]]&lt;!-- alphabetized by surname--&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;
*[[List of people pardoned or granted clemency by the president of the United States]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==References==
{{refbegin|2}}
* [[Leonard J. Arrington|Arrington, Leonard J.]], ''[[Brigham Young: American Moses]]''; [[University of Illinois Press]]; {{ISBN|0-252-01296-8}}, (1985; Paperback, 1986).
* {{Cite book
 | last = Nibley
 | first = Hugh W.
 | author-link = Hugh Nibley
 | title = Brother Brigham Challenges the Saints (The Collected Works of Hugh Nibley, vol. 13)
 | year = 1994
 | location = [[Salt Lake City]], Utah
 | publisher = Shadow Mountain Pub.
 | isbn = 0-87579-818-7
}}, republished online at {{Cite book
 | title=Brother Brigham Challenges the Saints by Hugh W. Nibley
 | url = http://publications.maxwellinstitute.byu.edu/book/brother-brigham-challenges-the-saints/
 | publisher = [[Foundation for Ancient Research and Mormon Studies|FARMS]]
 | accessdate =April 28, 2009
 }}.
* Bergera, Gary James, [https://web.archive.org/web/20040205091243/http://www.signaturebooks.com/excerpts/conflict.html ''Conflict in the Quorum: Orson Pratt, Brigham Young, Joseph Smith'']
* {{Cite book
 | last1 = Cannon
 | first1 = Frank J.
 | author-link = Frank J. Cannon
 | last2 = Knapp
 | first2 = George L.
 | title = Brigham Young and His Mormon Empire
 | year = 1913
 | place = New York
 | publisher = Fleming H. Revell Co.
 | url = https://archive.org/details/brighamyoungandh003273mbp
}}
* {{Cite book
 | last = Tullidge
 | first = Edward W.
 | author-link = Edward Tullidge
 | title = Life of Brigham Young: Or, Utah and Her Founders
 | year = 1877
 | place = New York
 | publisher = Tullidge &amp; Crandall
 | url = https://books.google.com/?id=mEcOAAAAIAAJ
 }}
* Turner, John G. ''Brigham Young: Pioneer Prophet.'' Cambridge, MA: Belknap, 2012.
* {{Cite book
 | last = Waite
 | first = C.V. (Catherine Van Valkenburg)
 | title = The Mormon prophet and his harem: or, An authentic history of Brigham Young, his numerous wives and children
 | year = 1868
 | place = Chicago
 | publisher = J.S. Goodman &amp; Co.
 | url = https://archive.org/details/mormonprophetand00waitiala
 }}. See also: ''[[The Mormon Prophet and His Harem]]''.
* {{Cite book
 | last = Young
 | first = Brigham
 | contribution = Self-Government&amp;nbsp;— Mysteries&amp;nbsp;— Recreation and Amusements, not in Themselves Sinful&amp;nbsp;— Tithing&amp;nbsp;— Adam, Our Father and Our God
 | date = April 9, 1852
 | title = Journal of Discourses by Brigham Young, President of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-Day Saints, His Two Counsellors, the Twelve Apostles, and Others
 | editor-last = Watt
 | editor-first = G.D.
 | volume = 1
 | place = Liverpool
 | publisher = F.D. &amp; S.W. Richards
 | publication-date = 1854
 | url = https://archive.org/stream/JoDV01/JoD_v01#page/n53/mode/2up
 | pages = 46–53
 }}
* {{Cite book
 | last = Young
 | first = Brigham
 | contribution = The Necessity of the Saints Living up to the Light Which Has Been Given Them
 | date = March 2, 1856
 | title = Journal of Discourses Delivered by President Brigham Young, His Two Counsellors, and the Twelve Apostles, and Others
 | editor1-last = Watt
 | editor1-first = G.D.
 | editor1-link = George D. Watt
 | volume = 3
 | place = Liverpool
 | publisher = [[Daniel H. Wells]]
 | publication-date = 1856
 | pages = 221–226
 | contribution-url = http://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Journal_of_Discourses/Volume3/The_Necessity_of_the_Saints_Living_up_to_the_Light_which_has_been_Given_Them?oldid=400881
 | title-link = Journal of Discourses
 }}
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Wikiquote}}
{{wikisource author}}
{{commons}}
{{EB1911 poster|Mormons}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20120104215904/http://josephsmithpapers.org/person?name=Brigham+Young Brigham Young] biography at ''[[The Joseph Smith Papers|Joseph Smith Papers Project]]''
* [https://findingaid.lib.byu.edu/viewItem/MSS%20SC%20890 Brigham Young Letters, MSS SC 890] at [https://sites.lib.byu.edu/sc/ L. Tom Perry Special Collections], [[Brigham Young University]]

{{S-start}}
{{s-off|}}
{{S-bef| before = None}}
{{s-ttl| title  = [[List of governors of Utah|Governor of Utah Territory]] | years = 1850–1858}}
{{s-aft| after  = [[Alfred Cumming (governor)|Alfred Cumming]]}}
{{s-rel| mo}}
{{S-bef| before = [[Joseph Smith]]}}
{{s-ttl| title  = [[President of the Church (LDS Church)|President of the Church]] | years = December 27, 1847{{snd}}August 29, 1877}}
{{s-aft| after  = [[John Taylor (Latter Day Saint)|John Taylor]]}}

{{S-bef| before = [[Thomas B. Marsh]]}}
{{s-ttl| title  = [[President of the Quorum of the Twelve Apostles (LDS Church)|President of the Quorum of the Twelve Apostles]] | years = March 17, 1839{{snd}}December 27, 1847}}
{{s-aft| after  = [[Orson Hyde]]}}

{{S-bef| before = [[David W. Patten]]}}
{{s-ttl| title  = [[Quorum of the Twelve|Quorum of the Twelve Apostles]] | years = February 14, 1835{{snd}}December 27, 1847}}
{{s-aft| after  = [[Heber C. Kimball]]}}
{{S-end}}
{{Latter-day Saints|show}}
{{LDSApostles}}
{{LDScouncil50}}
{{LDSfirstpresidency|counselors=no}}
{{LDSpresq12}}
{{Governors of Utah}}
{{American frontier}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Young, Brigham}}
[[Category:Brigham Young| ]]
[[Category:1801 births]]
[[Category:1877 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Whitingham, Vermont]]
[[Category:People from Mendon, New York]]
[[Category:American general authorities (LDS Church)]]
[[Category:American carpenters]]
[[Category:American Mormon missionaries in the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Converts to Mormonism from Methodism]]
[[Category:Governors of Utah Territory]]
[[Category:American Mormon missionaries in Canada]]
[[Category:Mormon pioneers]]
[[Category:Mormon Tabernacle Choir]]
[[Category:Mountain Meadows massacre]]
[[Category:Politicians from Salt Lake City]]
[[Category:Recipients of American presidential pardons]]
[[Category:Richards–Young family]]
[[Category:American city founders]]
[[Category:19th-century Mormon missionaries]]
[[Category:Presidents of the Church (LDS Church)]]
[[Category:Members of the Council of Fifty]]
[[Category:Apostles (LDS Church)]]
[[Category:Presidents of the Quorum of the Twelve Apostles (LDS Church)]]
[[Category:Apostles of the Church of Christ (Latter Day Saints)]]
[[Category:People of the Utah War]]
[[Category:Doctrine and Covenants people]]
[[Category:Deaths from peritonitis]]
[[Category:Burials at the Mormon Pioneer Memorial Monument]]
[[Category:Religious leaders from Vermont]]
[[Category:Latter Day Saints from Utah]]
[[Category:Latter Day Saints from Vermont]]
[[Category:Latter Day Saints from Ohio]]
[[Category:Latter Day Saints from Illinois]]
[[Category:Latter Day Saints from New York (state)]]</text>
      <sha1>sz9x6maep4jzwvss96fdlqy0krswzbm</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
