  <page>
    <title>Bride of the Monster</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5035</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942329005</id>
      <parentid>942296497</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-24T01:12:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Nikkimaria</username>
        <id>372290</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>rm non-[[WP:RS|RS]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|1955 American science fiction horror film by Ed Wood}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=April 2016}}
{{Infobox film
| name = Bride of the Monster
| image = Bride of the Monster (1956 movie poster).jpg
| alt = 
| caption = Original theatrical poster
| director = [[Ed Wood]]
| producer = Ed Wood
| writer = {{Plainlist|
* [[Alex Gordon (writer-producer)|Alex Gordon]]
* Ed Wood
}}
| starring = {{Plainlist|
* [[Bela Lugosi]]
* [[Tor Johnson]]
* Tony McCoy
* [[Loretta King Hadler|Loretta King]]
}}
| music = [[Frank Worth]]
| cinematography = {{Plainlist|
* [[Ted Allan]]
* [[William C. Thompson (cinematographer)|William C. Thompson]]
}}
| editing = Warren Adams
| studio = Rolling M. Productions
| distributor = Banner Pictures
| released = {{Film date|1955|05|11}}
| runtime = 75 minutes
| country = United States
| language = English
| budget = $70,000
}}
'''''Bride of the Monster''''' is a 1955 American [[Science fiction film|science fiction]] [[horror film]] directed, written and produced by [[Ed Wood|Edward D. Wood Jr.]], and starring [[Bela Lugosi]] and [[Tor Johnson]] with a supporting cast featuring Tony McCoy and [[Loretta King Hadler|Loretta King]].

The film is considered to have Wood's biggest budget ($70,000). Production commenced in 1953 but, due to further financial problems, was not completed until 1955. It was released in May 1955, initially on a double bill with ''Macumba''.&lt;ref&gt;Weldon, Michael (1983). &quot;The Psychotronic Encyclopedia of Film&quot;. Ballantine Books. {{ISBN|0-345-34345-X}}. Page 89&lt;/ref&gt;


A [[sequel]], entitled ''[[Night of the Ghouls]]'', was finished in 1959, but due to last-minute financial problems, was not released until 1984.&lt;ref name=&quot;imdb-ghouls-trivia&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0156843/trivia | title = Night of the Ghouls – Trivia | work = [[Internet Movie Database]] | accessdate = 2007-04-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Plot==
[[File:Bride of the Monster (1955).webm|thumb|thumbtime=44|upright=1.5|left|''Bride of the Monster'' (full film)]]
In a stretch of woods, two hunters are caught in a &quot;raging thunderstorm&quot;. They decide to seek refuge in Willows House, which is supposedly abandoned and [[Haunted house|haunted]]. When they reach Willows House, they find it to be occupied and the current owner repeatedly denies them hospitality. One of the hunters attempts to force his entry into the house, but a giant octopus is released from its tank and sent after the intruders.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ed Wood's Bride of the Monster&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Rhodes|first1=Gary|last2=Weaver|first2=Tom|title=Ed Wood's Bride of the Monster|date=2015|publisher=BearManor Media|isbn=1593938578}}&lt;/ref&gt; One of the fleeing hunters is killed by the octopus, while the other is captured by the giant. The owner is a scientist, Dr. Eric Vornoff, and the giant is his mute assistant, Lobo. Vornoff explains that he will perform an experiment on the unwilling hunter, who dies on the operating table.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ed Wood's Bride of the Monster&quot;/&gt;

In a police station, Officer Tom Robbins sees Lieutenant Dick Craig. There are now 12 missing victims, and the police still do not know what happened to them. The reporter behind the newspaper reports is Janet Lawton, Craig's [[Engagement|fiancée]]. Janet forces her way into the office and argues with Robbins, and vows to go to Lake Marsh to investigate. At the police station, Robbins and Craig have a meeting with an intellectual from Europe, Professor Vladimir Strowski, who agrees to assist the police in investigating the Marsh, but not at night. As night falls and another storm begins, Janet drives alone to Lake Marsh, but visibility is poor and she drives off the road and into a ravine. Lobo rescues her.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ed Wood's Bride of the Monster&quot;/&gt;

Janet awakens to find herself a prisoner of Vornoff, who uses [[hypnosis]] to put her back to sleep. The following day, Craig and his partner drive to the area around Lake Marsh, a swamp. The partners also discuss the strange weather and mention that the newspapers could be right about &quot;the atom bomb explosions distorting the atmosphere&quot;. The duo eventually discover Janet's abandoned car and realize she is the 13th missing victim. They leave the swamp while Strowski drives a rented car to the swamp.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ed Wood's Bride of the Monster&quot;/&gt;

Janet awakens at Willows House. Vornoff assures her that Lobo is harmless, but the giant seems fascinated with the female captive and approaches her with questionable intent. Vornoff explains the giant is human and that Vornoff found him in the &quot;wilderness of [[Tibet]]&quot;. Vornoff then hypnotically places Janet back to sleep. He orders Lobo to transport the captive to Vornoff's private quarters. Meanwhile, Strowski silently approaches Willows House and enters through the unlocked front door. While Strowski searches the house, Vornoff arrives to greet him. Their country of origin is interested in Vornoff's groundbreaking experiments with [[atomic energy]] and wants to recruit him. Vornoff narrates that two decades prior, Vornoff had suggested using experiments with [[nuclear power]] which could create [[superhuman]]s of great strength and size. In response, he was branded a [[Mad scientist|madman]] and exiled by his country. Strowski reveals that he has dreams of conquest in the name of their country, while Vornoff dreams of his creations conquering in his own name. By late evening, Craig and his partner return to the swamp and discover Strowski's abandoned car. The partners split up to search the area, Craig heading towards Willows House. Back in the secret laboratory, Vornoff uses a wave of his hand to summon Janet to his current location. She arrives dressed as a bride, summoned through [[telepathy]]. He has decided to use her as the next subject of his experiments. Lobo is reluctant to take part in this experiment, and Vornoff uses a whip to re-assert his control over his slave and assistant. Meanwhile, Craig has entered the house and accidentally discovers the secret passage. He is himself captured by Vornoff and Lobo.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ed Wood's Bride of the Monster&quot;/&gt;

As the experiment is about to begin, Lobo is visibly distressed. Making his decision, Lobo rebels and attacks Vornoff. After a fight, Lobo knocks Vornoff out, releases Janet, and transports the unconscious Vornoff to the operating table. The scientist becomes the subject of his own human experiment. This time the experiment works and Vornoff is transformed into an atomic-powered superhuman being. He and Lobo physically struggle with each other, and their fight destroys the laboratory and starts a fire. Vornoff grabs Janet and escapes from the flames. Robbins and other officers arrive to help Craig. The police pursue Vornoff through the woods. There is another thunderstorm, and a lightning strike further destroys Willows House. With his home and equipment destroyed, a distressed Vornoff abandons Janet and merely attempts to escape. Craig rolls a rock at him and lands him in the water with the octopus. They struggle until a nuclear explosion obliterate both combatants, apparently the end result of the chain reaction started at the destroyed laboratory. Robbins comments that Vornoff &quot;[[Playing God (ethics)|tampered in God's domain]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ed Wood's Bride of the Monster&quot;/&gt;

==Cast==
{{div col}}
* [[Bela Lugosi]] as Dr. Eric Vornoff
* [[Tor Johnson]] as Lobo
* Tony McCoy as Lt. Dick Craig
* [[Loretta King Hadler|Loretta King]] as Janet Lawton
* [[Harvey B. Dunn]] as Captain Robbins
* George Becwar as Professor Strowski
* [[Paul Marco]] as Officer Kelton
* Don Nagle as Martin
* [[Bud Osborne]] as Mac
* John Warren as Jake
* Ann Wilner as Tillie
* [[Dolores Fuller]] as Margie
* [[William &quot;Billy&quot; Benedict]] as Newsboy
* Ben Frommer as Drunk
{{div col end}}

==Production and release==
The first incarnation of the film was a 1953 script by [[Alex Gordon (writer-producer)|Alex Gordon]] titled ''The Atomic Monster'', but a lack of financing prevented any production.&lt;ref name=&quot;rhodes&quot;/&gt; Later Ed Wood revived the project as ''The Monster of the Marshes''. Actual shooting began in October 1954 at the Ted Allan Studios, but further money problems quickly halted the production.&lt;ref name=&quot;rhodes&quot;/&gt; The required funds were supplied by a rancher named Donald McCoy, who became the film's producer. He also provided his son to star as the film's hero.&lt;ref name=&quot;rhodes&quot;/&gt; According to screenwriter Dennis Rodriguez, casting the younger McCoy as a protagonist was one of two terms Donald imposed on Wood. The other term was to include an atomic explosion in the finale.&lt;ref name=&quot;Craig2&quot;&gt;Craig (2009), p. 293-294&lt;/ref&gt; Production resumed in 1955 at Centaur Studios.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rhodes2&quot;&gt;Rhodes (2006), p. 142-143&lt;/ref&gt;

The film premiered at Hollywood's [[El Capitan Theatre|Paramount theater]] in May 1955, under the title ''Bride of the Atom''.&lt;ref name=&quot;rhodes&quot;&gt;
{{cite book| last = Rhodes| first = Gary D.| authorlink =| title = ''Lugosi: his life in films, on stage, and in the hearts of horror lovers''| year = 1997| publisher = McFarland| location =| isbn = 0-7864-0257-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; The film was reportedly completed and released through a deal with [[Samuel Z. Arkoff]]. Arkoff profited from the film more than Wood, and his earnings contributed to the funding of [[American International Pictures]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Craig&quot;&gt;Craig (2009), p. 83–103&lt;/ref&gt; The ending credits identify the copyright holder of the film as &quot;Filmakers Releasing Organization&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Craig2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Reid&quot;&gt;Reid (2007), p. 26–27&lt;/ref&gt; Distribution rights were held by Banner Films in the United States, and by Exclusive in the United Kingdom.&lt;ref name=&quot;Reid&quot;/&gt;

==Analysis==

===Genre and background===
The film combines elements of [[science fiction]] and [[horror fiction]], genres which were frequently combined in films of the 1950s. Like many of these contemporaries, ''Bride'' serves in part as a [[Cold War]] [[propaganda film]]. Once again, an external threat from &quot;[[Old Europe (politics)|Old Europe]]&quot; serves as the enemy of the righteous United States. In Cold War [[Thriller (genre)|thrillers]], foreign nations served as a vilified and [[Demonization|demonized]] [[Other (philosophy)|Other]] for American audiences.&lt;ref name=&quot;Craig&quot;/&gt; The country of origin for Vornoff and Strowski is left unnamed. The only clues is that it is European and has its own dreams of conquest. By implication, the country which exiled Vornoff in the 1930s could be [[Nazi Germany]] or the [[Soviet Union]]. Their role as villains for the American cinema had already been solidified by the 1950s, and Wood could be alluding to both of them. Strowski uses the term [[master race]], which is a key concept in [[Nazism]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Craig&quot;/&gt;

Both the working title ''Bride of the Atom'' and the final title ''Bride of the Monster'' allude to the earlier film ''[[Bride of Frankenstein]]'' (1935).&lt;ref name=&quot;Craig&quot;/&gt; The film otherwise follows the template of the [[Poverty Row]] horror films of the 1940s. The [[Atomic Age]] influences the film in its ominous implications concerning [[nuclear weapon]]s and the threat they posed towards human civilization.&lt;ref name=&quot;Craig&quot;/&gt; Rob Craig makes an argument for including the film in a subgenre of Cold War-themed thrillers along with ''[[Kiss Me Deadly]]'' (1955), ''[[The World, the Flesh and the Devil (1959 film)|The World, the Flesh and the Devil]]'' (1959), ''[[On the Beach (1959 film)|On the Beach]]'' (1959), ''[[The Manchurian Candidate (1962 film)|The Manchurian Candidate]]'' (1962), ''[[Dr. Strangelove]]'' (1964), ''[[Seven Days in May]]'' (1964) and ''[[Fail Safe (1964 film)|Fail-Safe]]'' (1964).&lt;ref name=&quot;Craig2&quot;/&gt;

===Content===
This was [[Bela Lugosi]]'s last speaking role in a feature film.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rhodes2&quot;/&gt; Lugosi subsequently played a silent part in ''[[The Black Sleep]]'' (1956). ''[[Plan 9 from Outer Space]]'' (1959) uses silent archive footage of Lugosi, but he died prior to the creation of its script. The footage was from an unfinished Ed Wood film that was to be called ''The Vampire's Tomb''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rhodes3&quot;&gt;Rhodes (2006), p. 143–145&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Lock Up Your Daughters (1959 film)|Lock Up Your Daughters]]'' (1959) recycled footage from Lugosi's earlier films, possibly mixed with some new material.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rhodes3&quot;/&gt; According to Rob Craig, in ''Bride'' Lugosi for the last time plays  &quot;a charismatic [[villain]] whose [[megalomania]] leads to downfall and destruction&quot;. Craig considers this to be one of Lugosi's finest roles, citing the surprisingly energetic performance of the aging actor.&lt;ref name=&quot;Craig&quot;/&gt; The scenes involving hypnosis contain [[close-up]]s of Lugosi's eyes. Wood was probably trying to recreate similar scenes from an older film of Lugosi, ''[[White Zombie (film)|White Zombie]]'' (1932).&lt;ref name=&quot;Craig&quot;/&gt; Lugosi did not actually play Vornoff in the scenes demanding physicality. The film made use of [[body double]]s for Lugosi: [[Eddie Parker (actor)|Eddie Parker]] and Red Reagan.&lt;ref name=&quot;Craig&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Reid&quot;/&gt; Parker was also the body-double of Lugosi in ''[[Frankenstein Meets the Wolf Man]]'' (1943).&lt;ref name=&quot;Rhodes2&quot;/&gt; Lugosi's fee for the film is estimated to have been 1000 [[dollar]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rhodes2&quot;/&gt;

The story is similar to an earlier Bela Lugosi movie, &quot;The Corpse Vanishes&quot;. &lt;ref&gt; {{cite web | url = http://publicdomainmovie.net/movie/the-corpse-vanishes | title = The Corpse Vanishes | accessdate = 2020-02-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; In both movies, each bride at her wedding was given an orchid, which she sniffed before passing out. In &quot;The Corpse Vanishes&quot;, Lugosi played a doctor who captured the brides and took some kind of liquid from each bride's body and injected it into his wife to make her temporarily young again. Characters included his wife, an old woman, the old woman's grown son, and a dwarf. In &quot;Bride of the Monster&quot;, Lugosi again plays a doctor doing experiments, but his only housemate/assistant is Lobo, and when his experiment fails to turn someone into an &quot;atomic-powered superman&quot;, he throws the dead subject to an octopus or an alligator, similar to Lugosi throwing a body into a river in &quot;Murders in the Rue Morgue&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = https://immortalephemera.com/55426/murders-in-the-rue-morgue-1932/ | title = Murders in the Rue Morgue | accessdate = 2020-02-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The hunters of the opening scenes are unnamed in the actual scenes, but identified later in the film as Jake Long and Blake &quot;Mac&quot; McCreigh.&lt;ref name=&quot;Craig&quot;/&gt; According to the credits, Jake was played by John Warren and Mac by [[Bud Osborne]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Reid&quot;/&gt; The police station scenes feature cameos by a drunk and a newspaper seller. The former is played by Ben Frommer (known for playing Count Bloodcount in ''[[Transylvania 6-5000 (1963 film)|Transylvania 6-5000]]''), the latter is played by [[William Benedict]] (known as one of [[The Bowery Boys]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;Reid&quot;/&gt; Janet Lawton briefly speaks with a co-worker called Margie. Margie is played by [[Dolores Fuller]]. Dick Craig's partner, Martin, is played by Don Nagel. Both Fuller and Nagel had worked with Wood in ''[[Jail Bait (1954 film)|Jail Bait]]'' (1954).&lt;ref name=&quot;Craig&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Reid&quot;/&gt;

The film uses both stock footage of both a real octopus and a fake, rubber octopus in scenes where &quot;the monster&quot; interacts with the actors. It is widely believed this was a prop from the John Wayne film ''[[Wake of the Red Witch]]'' (1948). Contradictory accounts claim that Wood either stole or legally rented the prop from [[Republic Pictures]], which produced the earlier film.&lt;ref name=&quot;Craig2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Rhodes2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Craig&quot;/&gt; The struggle between Vornoff and the octopus was filmed at [[Griffith Park]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Rhodes2&quot;/&gt;

Craig comments that there is a stark contrast between the characters of Dick Craig and Janet Lawton. Dick speaks in a [[deadpan]] unemotional way and seems to be a rather lethargic character. Janet is a &quot;brassy girl reporter&quot;, a dynamic character with a sense of autonomy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Craig&quot;/&gt; The role was reportedly intended for [[Dolores Fuller]]. According to Fuller's recollections, [[Loretta King Hadler|Loretta King]] bribed Wood into casting her as Janet, with promises of securing further funding for the film. Fuller was thus reduced to a cameo role.&lt;ref name=&quot;Craig2&quot;/&gt; King vehemently denies bribing Wood in any way, so the story lacks confirmation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Craig2&quot;/&gt;

In a subplot of the film, there are storms every night for three months and strange weather patterns. The characters attribute the phenomenon to the effects the [[nuclear explosion]]s have on the atmosphere. This probably reflects actual anxiety of the 1950s about potential [[climate change]]. Until the [[Partial Nuclear Test Ban Treaty]] (1963), atmospheric [[nuclear weapons testing]] was used widely and recklessly.&lt;ref name=&quot;Craig&quot;/&gt; Rob Craig suggests that the months of constant storms could be inspired by the [[Genesis flood narrative]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Craig&quot;/&gt; In the context of the film, the strange weather is implied to be a side-effect of the experiments of Vornoff which apparently release radioactivity into the atmosphere.&lt;ref name=&quot;Craig&quot;/&gt;

The dialogue of the film includes well-known lines such as &quot;''Home? I have no home!&quot;'', &quot;''One is always considered mad, when one discovers something which others cannot grasp&quot;'', and the closing &quot;''He tampered in God's domain&quot;''.&lt;ref&gt;Rhodes, Gary; Weaver, Tom (2015). Ed Wood's Bride of the Monster. BearManor Media. {{ISBN|1593938578}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The phrases could well apply to the fates of [[avant-garde]] artists and thinkers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Craig&quot;/&gt; The title &quot;''Bride of the Atom&quot;'', which Vornoff uses for Janet in the bridal dress, is inexplicable unless the scientist is actually attempting to use Janet to replace his long-lost wife. One of his reassuring lines to Janet concerning the experiment, &quot;''It hurts, just for a moment, but then you will emerge a woman...&quot;'', sounds as if preparing her for the loss of her virginity.&lt;ref name=&quot;Craig&quot;/&gt; The scene of a young woman, in a bridal gown, restrained by leather shackles seems to be [[Sadomasochism|sadomasochistic]] in nature.&lt;ref name=&quot;Craig&quot;/&gt;

Throughout the film, the mute Lobo is implied to have an unspecified [[intellectual disability]] and to be of sub-human intelligence. Yet he successfully operates complex machinery as if trained to do so. Craig views this scene as implying that supposedly &quot;dumb&quot; servants, can have a capacity of learning the secrets of their masters .&lt;ref name=&quot;Craig&quot;/&gt;

The final scenes, with the [[mushroom cloud]] of the nuclear explosion, use stock footage from the blast of a [[thermonuclear weapon]] (&quot;hydrogen bomb&quot;).&lt;ref name=&quot;Craig&quot;/&gt;

===Film series===
The apparent fetish of Lobo with [[angora wool]] is a reflection of Wood's own fetish for the material. This also serves as the film's connection to ''[[Glen or Glenda]]'' (1953), where the fetish plays a more prominent role.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hayes&quot;&gt;Hayes (2006), p. 137&lt;/ref&gt;

The character of Lobo also appeared again in Wood's ''[[Night of the Ghouls]]''. This film served as a sequel of sorts to ''Bride''. Vornoff is absent from the later film, but there are references to the activities of &quot;the mad doctor&quot;.
&lt;ref name=&quot;Rhodes2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;imdb-ghouls&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url = https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0156843/| title = ''Night of the Ghouls''| work = [[Internet Movie Database]]| accessdate = 2006-05-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Tor Johnson]] also plays a character called Lobo in ''[[The Unearthly]]'' (1957) by Boris Petroff. This character also serves the main villain.&lt;ref name=&quot;Craig3&quot;&gt;Craig (2013), p. 135–137&lt;/ref&gt;

This film is part of what Wood aficionados refer to as &quot;The Kelton Trilogy&quot;, a trio of films featuring [[Paul Marco]] as Officer Kelton, a whining, reluctant policeman. The other two films are ''[[Plan 9 from Outer Space]]'' and ''[[Night of the Ghouls]]''. Kelton is the only character to appear in all three films.&lt;ref name=&quot;Times&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url=https://www.nytimes.com/movies/movie/35298/Night-of-the-Ghouls/overview |title=''Night of the Ghouls (1959)'' |year=2010 |accessdate=November 10, 2013 |author= Bruce Eder  |newspaper=[[The New York Times]] }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy==
In 1986, the film was featured in the syndicated series, the ''[[Canned Film Festival]]'' and was later featured on the comedy series, ''[[Mystery Science Theater 3000]]''.

The late 1990s dream trance track &quot;Alright&quot;, by DJ Taucher, sampled a monologue from Bela Lugosi during the interlude of the song.

In 2005, [[The Devil's Rejects]] Footage of the movie was played in the movie.

In 2008, a [[Film colorization|colorized]] version was released by [[Legend Films]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.amazon.com/dp/B001BSBBKI |title=ASIN: B001BSBBKI |accessdate=2009-01-30 |last= |first= |work= |publisher=[[Amazon.com]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; This version is also available from [[Amazon Video on Demand]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.amazon.com/dp/B001LNV63U/ |title=ASIN: B001LNV63U |accessdate=2009-01-30 |publisher=[[Amazon.com]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2010, a retrospective on the movie entitled ''Citizen Wood: Making ‘The Bride’, Unmaking the Legend'' was included in the ''Mystery Science Theater 3000'' Volume 19 DVD set as a bonus feature for said episode featuring the movie.&lt;ref name=&quot;Film Threat&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=https://filmthreat.com/reviews/27760/|title=Film Threat – Mystery Science Theater 3000: Volume Xix (dvd)|author=Brad Cook|date=12 November 2010|work=|publisher=[[Film Threat]]|accessdate=15 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Horror host]] [[Mr. Lobo]] is among the interviewees of the 27 minute documentary.&lt;ref name=&quot;Film Threat&quot;/&gt;

==Controversies==
In 1980, the book ''[[The Golden Turkey Awards]]'' claims that Lugosi's character declares his manservant Lobo ([[Tor Johnson]]) &quot;as harmless as kitchen&quot; {{sic}}. This allegedly misspoken line is cited as evidence of either Lugosi's failing health/mental faculties, or as further evidence of Wood's incompetence as a director.&lt;ref name=&quot;medved&quot;&gt;{{cite book| last = Medved| first = Harry|author2=[[Michael Medved]] | title = [[The Golden Turkey Awards|The Golden Turkey Awards: Nominees and Winners, the Worst Achievements in Hollywood History]]| year = 1980| publisher = Putnam| location = New York| isbn = 0-399-50463-X| page = 178}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, a viewing of the film itself reveals that Lugosi said this line correctly, the exact words being, &quot;''Don't be afraid of Lobo; he's as gentle as a kitten.''&quot; The easier explanation would be that authors [[Michael Medved]] and Harry Medved saw the film in a theater setting with inferior sound quality. A single viewing in such conditions could result in mishearing some lines of dialogue. Unfortunately the inaccurate claim managed to achieve [[urban legend]] status, and it keeps circulating.&lt;ref name=&quot;Craig2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Rhodes2&quot;/&gt;

In 1994, the biopic ''[[Ed Wood (film)|Ed Wood]]'', directed by [[Tim Burton]], alleged that Wood and the filmmakers stole the mechanical [[octopus]] (previously used in the film ''[[Wake of the Red Witch]]'') from the [[Republic Pictures|Republic Studios]] backlot, while failing to steal the motor which enabled the prop to move realistically, although, by the director's admission, the film preferred narrative interest over historical accuracy. These events are also alleged in the 2004 documentary, ''The 50 Worst Movies Ever Made.'' However, other stories circulated insist Wood legitimately rented the octopus, along with some cars.&lt;ref&gt;Lennig, Arthur (2010). &quot;The Immortal Count: The Life and Films of Bela Lugosi&quot;. University Press of Kentucky. {{ISBN|0813126614}}. Page 519&lt;/ref&gt; To remedy the lack of movement from the octopus prop, whenever someone was killed by the monster in the film, they simply flailed around in the shallow water while holding the tentacles to imitate movement. The filming of these scenes, as well as the production of the film in general, were played to comic effect in ''Ed Wood''.

Rudolph Grey's book ''Nightmare of Ecstasy: The Life and Art of Edward D. Wood Jr.'' contains anecdotes regarding the making of this film.&lt;ref name=&quot;grey&quot;&gt;
{{cite book| last = Grey| first = Rudolph| authorlink = Rudolph Grey| title = ''Nightmare of Ecstasy: The Life and Art of Edward D. Wood Jr.''| year = 1992| publisher = Feral House| location = Los Angeles| isbn = 0-922915-04-0| url-access = registration| url = https://archive.org/details/nightmareofecsta00rudo}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Grey notes that participants in the original events sometimes contradict one another, but he relates each person's information for posterity. He also includes Ed Wood's claim that one of his films made a profit and surmises that it was most likely ''Bride of the Monster'', but that Wood had oversold the film and could not reimburse the backers.

==See also==
* [[List of American films of 1955]]
* [[List of killer octopus films]]
* [[Ed Wood filmography]]

==Further reading==
* ''Ed Wood's Bride of the Monster'' by Gary D. Rhodes and Tom Weaver (2015) BearManor Media, {{ISBN|1593938578}}
* ''Bela Lugosi: Dreams and Nightmares'' by Gary D. Rhodes, with Richard Sheffield, (2007) Collectables/Alpha Video Publishers, {{ISBN|0-9773798-1-7}} (hardcover)
* {{citation | last1=Craig | first1=Rob| title=''Ed Wood, Mad Genius: A Critical Study of the Films'' | chapter=Bride of the Monster (1956)|year=2009| publisher=[[McFarland &amp; Company]]| isbn= 978-0-7864-5423-5 | url =https://books.google.com/books?id=XrjzCGsiyWEC&amp;pg=PA83 }}
* {{citation | last1=Craig | first1=Rob| title=''Ed Wood, Mad Genius: A Critical Study of the Films'' | chapter=Notes|year=2009| publisher=[[McFarland &amp; Company]]| isbn= 978-0-7864-5423-5 | url =https://books.google.com/books?id=XrjzCGsiyWEC&amp;pg=PA294 }}
* {{citation | last1=Craig | first1=Rob| title=''It Came from 1957'' | chapter= The Unearthly| year=2013 | publisher=[[McFarland &amp; Company]]| isbn=978-0786477777| url =https://books.google.com/books?id=DZDqAAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA137 }}
* [[Rudolph Grey]], ''Nightmare of Ecstasy: The Life and Art of Edward D. Wood, Jr.'' (1992) {{ISBN|978-0-922915-24-8}}
* {{citation | last1=Hayes | first1=David C.| title=''Muddled Mind: The Complete Works of Edward D. Wood, Jr.'' | chapter=On Identifying Wood-work|year=2006| publisher=[[Lulu (company)|Lulu]]| isbn= 978-1-6054-3053-9| url =https://books.google.com/books?id=WWLna_OuIokC&amp;pg=PA27 }}
* {{citation | last1=Reid | first1=John Howard| title=''Science Fiction &amp; Fantasy Cinema: Classic Films of Horror, Sci-Fi &amp; and the Supernatural'' | chapter=Bride of the Monster|year=2007| publisher=[[Lulu (company)|Lulu]]| isbn= 978-1-4303-0113-4| url =https://books.google.com/books?id=WWLna_OuIokC&amp;pg=PA27 }}
* {{citation | last1=Rhodes | first1=Gary Don| title=''Lugosi: His Life in Films, on Stage, and in the Hearts of Horror Lovers'' | chapter=Feature-Length Films – United States and United Kingdom|year=2006| publisher=[[McFarland &amp; Company]]| isbn= 978-0-7864-2765-9 | url =https://books.google.com/books?id=E4hflza6Jo4C&amp;pg=PA143 }}
* {{cite journal| last = Sloan| first = Will|date=April 2005| title = Can Your Heart Stand the Shocking Facts About Kelton the Cop A/K/A Paul Marco?| journal = Filmfax| volume =| issue = 106| pages = 88–89}}
* ''The Haunted World of Edward D. Wood, Jr.'' (1996), documentary film directed by Brett Thompson

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{Wikiquote}}

==External links==
{{commons category|Bride of the Monster}}
* {{IMDb title|0047898|Bride of the Monster}}
* {{Amg title|7096|Bride of the Monster}}
* {{Internet Archive film|id=brideofthemonsteredwood}}

{{Ed Wood}}

[[Category:1955 films]]
[[Category:1950s monster movies]]
[[Category:1950s science fiction horror films]]
[[Category:American black-and-white films]]
[[Category:American science fiction horror films]]
[[Category:American monster movies]]
[[Category:American films]]
[[Category:Films about journalists]]
[[Category:Films featuring hypnosis]]
[[Category:Films directed by Ed Wood]]
[[Category:Films produced by Ed Wood]]
[[Category:Films set in the United States]]
[[Category:Films shot in Los Angeles]]
[[Category:Mad scientist films]]
[[Category:Films with screenplays by Ed Wood]]
[[Category:Articles containing video clips]]
[[Category:1955 horror films]]
[[Category:American exploitation films]]
[[Category:Films featured on Mystery Science Theater 3000]]</text>
      <sha1>d83rdeake825gwixdikjhmdtoiewc8p</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
