  <page>
    <title>Battle of Adwa</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5013</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943377599</id>
      <parentid>943369814</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-03-01T15:26:01Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>174.192.206.188</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>The clothing worn by Ras Alula is not just of Arab origin. The similar climate in the tigrayans dry lands were similar to that of the Arabian gulf. The clothing worn are winter clothing also worn by tigrayans. The culture similarity may stem from Tigrays close ancestory to yemen</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{ghjFor|the earlier battle|Battle of Adwa (1871)}}
{{short description|Battle between the Ethiopian Empire and the Kingdom of Italy near the town of Adwa}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2019}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| image       = COLLECTIE TROPENMUSEUM De slag bij Adua TMnr 5956-2.jpg
| image_size  = 300
| caption     = Ethiopian forces, assisted by St George (top), win the battle. Painted 1965–75.
| campaign    = 
| conflict    = Battle of Adwa
| partof      = the [[First Italo-Ethiopian War]]
| date        = 1 March 1896
| place       = {{Coord|14|1|8|N|38|58|24|E|display=title|name=Battle of Adwa}}[[Adwa]], [[Ethiopian Empire|Ethiopia]]
| result      = Ethiopian victory
| territory   = Ethiopian territorial sovereignty confirmed&lt;br /&gt;
----[[Menelik II of Ethiopia|Menelik II]] personally ratifies [[French Somaliland]] (''[[Djibouti]]'').&lt;ref name=FTTo&gt;{{cite book|title=Ethiopia at Bay |first=John H. |last=Spencer |year=2006 |page=31|place=Tsehai Puiblishers}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| combatant1  = {{flagcountry|Ethiopian Empire|old}}&lt;br /&gt;'''Supported by:'''&lt;br /&gt;{{flagcountry|Russian Empire}}&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sworld.com.ua/index.php/ru/history/world-history-and-the-history-of-ukraine/768-vinogradova-kv The activities of the officer the Kuban Cossack army N. S. Leontjev in the Italian-Ethiopic war in 1895–1896] {{in lang|ru}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.linkethiopia.org/guide/pankhurst/medicine/medicine_6.html |title=Ethiopia's Historic Quest for Medicine, 6 |publisher=The Pankhurst History Library |first=Pankhurst |last=Richard |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20111003141829/http://www.linkethiopia.org/guide/pankhurst/medicine/medicine_6.html |archivedate=2011-10-03 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;{{flagcountry|French Third Republic}} &lt;ref&gt;[https://libcom.org/library/soviet-appeasement-collective-security-italo-ethiopian-war-1935-1936 Soviet Appeasement, Collective Security, and the Italo-Ethiopian war of 1935 and 1936]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Thomas Wilson|first= Edward|date= 1974|title= Russia and Black Africa Before World War II|location= New York|publisher= |page=57-58 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
| combatant2  = {{flagcountry|Kingdom of Italy}}
* {{flagicon|Kingdom of Italy}} [[Italian Eritrea]]
| commander1  = {{flagicon|Ethiopian Empire|old}} '''[[Menelik II of Ethiopia|Menelik II]]'''&lt;br /&gt;[[Ras Alula]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Taytu Betul]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Tekle Haymanot of Gojjam|Tekle Haymanot]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Ras Makonnen]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Mikael of Wollo|Ras Mikael]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Ras Mengesha Yohannes|Ras Mengesha]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Fit'awrari Gebeyehu]]{{KIA}}&lt;br /&gt;[[Fitawrari]] [[Habte Giyorgis]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Fitawrari Damtew]]{{KIA}}&lt;br /&gt;[[Dejazmach]] [[Balcha Safo]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Russian Empire}} [[Nikolay Leontiev]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://dic.academic.ru/dic.nsf/enc_biography/71087/%D0%9B%D0%B5%D0%BE%D0%BD%D1%82%D1%8C%D0%B5%D0%B2  Nikolay Stepanovich Leontiev]&lt;/ref&gt;
| commander2  = {{flagicon|Kingdom of Italy}} '''[[Oreste Baratieri]]'''&lt;br /&gt;[[Vittorio Dabormida]]{{KIA}}&lt;br /&gt;[[Giuseppe Arimondi]]{{KIA}}&lt;br /&gt;[[Matteo Albertone]]{{POW}}&lt;br /&gt;[[Giuseppe Ellena]]
| strength1   = 80,000 armed with rifles&lt;ref name=FTTt&gt;{{cite book|title=Armies of the Adowa Campaign 1896 |first=Sean |last=McLachlan |year=2011 |page= 37|place=Osprey Publishing}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{#tag:ref|According to [[Richard K. P. Pankhurst|Pankhurst]], the Ethiopians were armed with approximately 100,000 rifles of which about half were &quot;fast firing.&quot;.&lt;ref name=p190&gt;[[Richard K. P. Pankhurst|Pankhurst]], ''The Ethiopians'', p. 190&lt;/ref&gt;|group=nb}}&lt;br /&gt;20,000 armed with spears and swords&lt;ref name=FTTt/&gt;&lt;br /&gt;8,600 horses&lt;ref name=FTTt /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;42 artillery pieces&lt;ref name=RRT&gt;{{cite book|title=Ethiopia: the Land, Its People, History and Culture |first=Yohannes |last=Mekonnen |year=2013 |pages= 76–80|place=New Africa Press}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| strength2   = 17,700 including 7,104 Eritrean askaris&lt;ref name=PWS&gt;{{cite book|title=Adwa Victory Centenary Conference, 26 February – 2 March 1996 |last=Abdussamad H. Ahmad and Richard Pankhurst |year=1998 |pages=158–62 |place=Addis Ababa University}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CasualtiesAscari&quot;/&gt;&lt;br /&gt;56 artillery pieces&lt;ref name=PWS/&gt; rifles and artillery – all antiquated&lt;ref name=RRT /&gt;
| casualties1 = 3,867 killed&lt;ref name=PTZ&gt;{{cite book|title=The Battle of Adwa |last=Paulos Milkias and Getachew Metaferia |year=2005 |page= 128 |place=Algora Publishing}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;~8,000 wounded&lt;ref name=&quot;Casualties&quot; /&gt;
| casualties2 = 6,394 killed&lt;ref name=PWS/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CasualtiesAscari&quot;&gt;Uhlig, Siegbert, ed. ''[[Encyclopaedia Aethiopica]]: A–C'' (Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz Verlag, 2003), p. 372.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;1,428 wounded&lt;ref name=PWS /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;~3,000 captured&lt;ref name=&quot;Casualties&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;(^ including wounded)&lt;ref name=RRT /&gt;
}}
{{Campaignbox First Italo-Ethiopian War}}

[[File:Alula Engida.jpg|thumb|right|upright|''[[General]]'' [[Ras Alula|Ras Alula (Abba Nega)]] of [[Tembien Province|Tembien]], [[Tigray region|Tigray]]]]
The '''Battle of Adwa''' ({{lang-ti|ዓድዋ}}; [[Amharic]]: አድዋ; [[Italian language|Italian]] ''Adua'') was the climactic battle of the [[First Italo-Ethiopian War]]. Led by [[Emperor of Ethiopia|Emperor]] [[Menelik II]], Ethiopian forces defeated an invading Italian force on Sunday 1 March 1896, near the town of [[Adwa]] in [[Tigray Region|Tigray]]. The decisive victory thwarted the [[Kingdom of Italy]]'s campaign to expand its colonial empire in the [[Horn of Africa]] and secured the [[Ethiopian Empire]]'s sovereignty for [[Second Italo-Ethiopian War|another forty years]]. Though not the first African nation to resist European conquest during the [[scramble for Africa]], Ethiopia became a pre-eminent symbol of the [[Pan-Africanism|pan-African movement]] and international opposition to [[colonialism]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Abraham&quot;/&gt;

By the end of the 19th century, European powers had carved up almost all of Africa after the [[Berlin Conference]]. Only Ethiopia, then still commonly known as Abyssinia and the [[Liberia|Republic of Liberia]] still maintained their independence (Liberia being a settler nation supported by the United States). The newly unified [[Kingdom of Italy]] was a relative newcomer to the imperialist [[scramble for Africa]]. Two of its recently obtained African territories, [[Italian Eritrea]] and [[Italian Somaliland]], bordered Ethiopia on the [[Horn of Africa]]. Italy sought to improve its position in Africa by conquering Ethiopia and joining it with its two territories. Menelik II successfully pitted Italy against its European rivals while stockpiling advanced weapons to defend his empire against the Italians and British.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

==Background==
In 1889, the Italians signed the [[Treaty of Wuchale]] with then ''[[Negus]]''{{#tag:ref|Roughly equivalent to [[King]].|group=nb}} [[Menelik II|Menelik]] of [[Shewa]]. The treaty ceded territories previously part of Ethiopia, namely the provinces of [[Bogos]], [[Hamasien]], [[Akele Guzai]], [[Serae]], and parts of [[Tigray Province|Tigray]]. In return, Italy promised Menelik II continued rule, financial assistance and military supplies. A dispute later arose over the interpretation of the two versions of the document. The Italian-language version of the disputed Article 17 of the treaty stated that the Emperor of Ethiopia was obliged to conduct all foreign affairs through Italian authorities. This would in effect make Ethiopia a [[protectorate]] of the Kingdom of Italy. The [[Amharic]] version of the article however, stated that the Emperor could use the good offices of the Kingdom of Italy in his relations with foreign nations if he wished. However, the Italian diplomats claimed that the original Amharic text included the clause and that Menelik II knowingly signed a modified copy of the Treaty.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author=Piero Pastoretto | title=Battaglia di Adua | url=http://www.arsmilitaris.org/pubblicazioni/ADUA/adua.htm | accessdate=2006-06-04 |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20060531223251/http://www.arsmilitaris.org/pubblicazioni/ADUA/adua.htm |archivedate=31 May 2006 |language=it}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Italian government decided on a military solution to force Ethiopia to abide by the Italian version of the treaty. As a result, Italy and Ethiopia came into confrontation, in what was later to be known as the [[First Italo-Ethiopian War]]. In December 1894, [[Bahta Hagos]] led a rebellion against the Italians in Akele Guzai, in what was then Italian controlled [[Eritrea]]. Units of General [[Oreste Baratieri]]'s army under Major {{Interlanguage link multi|Pietro Toselli|it}} crushed the rebellion and killed Bahta. The Italian army then occupied the [[Tigray Province|Tigrayan]] capital, [[Adwa]]. In January 1895, Baratieri's army went on to defeat [[Ethiopian aristocratic and court titles#Men's honorifics|Ras]] [[Mengesha Yohannes]] in the [[Battle of Coatit]], forcing Mengesha to retreat further south.

By late 1895, Italian forces had advanced deep into Ethiopian territory. On 7 December 1895, ''Ras'' [[Makonnen Wolde Mikael]], ''Ras'' [[Welle Betul]] and ''Ras'' [[Mengesha Yohannes]] commanding a larger Ethiopian group of Menelik's vanguard annihilated a small Italian unit at the [[Battle of Amba Alagi (1895)|Battle of Amba Alagi]]. The Italians were then forced to withdraw to more defensible positions in [[Tigray Province]], where the two main armies faced each other. By late February 1896, supplies on both sides were running low. General [[Oreste Baratieri]], commander of the Italian forces, knew the Ethiopian forces had been living off the land, and once the supplies of the local peasants were exhausted, Emperor Menelik II's army would begin to melt away. However, the Italian government insisted that General Baratieri act.

[[File:ET Tigray asv2018-01 img46 Adwa.jpg|thumb|upright=1.1|The landscape of Adwa]]
On the evening of 29 February, Baratieri, about to be replaced by a new governor, General Baldissera, met with his [[brigadier general]]s [[Matteo Albertone]], [[Giuseppe Arimondi]], [[Vittorio Dabormida]], and [[Giuseppe Ellena]], concerning their next steps. He opened the meeting on a negative note, revealing to his brigadiers that provisions would be exhausted in less than five days, and suggested retreating, perhaps as far back as [[Asmara]]. His subordinates argued forcefully for an attack, insisting that to retreat at this point would only worsen the poor morale.&lt;ref&gt;Harold G. Marcus, ''The Life and Times of Menelik II: Ethiopia 1844–1913'', 1975 (Lawrenceville: Red Sea Press, 1995), p. 170&lt;/ref&gt; Dabormida exclaiming, &quot;Italy would prefer the loss of two or three thousand men to a dishonorable retreat.&quot; Baratieri delayed making a decision for a few more hours, claiming that he needed to wait for some last-minute intelligence, but in the end announced that the attack would start the next morning at 9:00am.&lt;ref&gt;David Levering Lewis, ''The Race for Fashoda'' (New York: Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson, 1987), p. 116. {{ISBN|1-55584-058-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; His troops began their march to their starting positions shortly after midnight.

==Forces assembled==
The Italian army consisted of four [[brigade]]s, totaling 17,978 troops with fifty-six artillery pieces.&lt;ref&gt;Lewis, ''Fashoda'', pp. 116f. He breaks down their numbers into 10,596 Italian officers and soldiers and 7,104 Eritrean askaris.&lt;/ref&gt; However, it is likely that fewer fought in the actual battle on the Italian side: Harold Marcus notes that &quot;several thousand&quot; soldiers were needed in support roles and to guard the lines of communication to the rear. He accordingly estimates that the Italian force at Adwa consisted of 14,923 effective combat troops.&lt;ref&gt;Marcus, ''Menelik II'', p. 173&lt;/ref&gt; One brigade under General Albertone was made up of [[Eritrean Ascari]] led by Italian officers.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas Pakenham, p. 481 ''The Scramble for Africa'', {{ISBN|0-349-10449-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; The remaining three brigades were Italian units under Brigadiers Dabormida, Ellena and Arimondi. While these included elite [[Bersaglieri]] and [[Alpini]] units, a large proportion of the troops were inexperienced conscripts recently drafted from metropolitan regiments in Italy into newly formed &quot;d'Africa&quot; [[battalion]]s for service in Africa. Additionally, a limited number of troops were drafted from the [[Cacciatori d'Africa]] units of local Italian settlers.&lt;ref name = &quot;Berkley 1901&quot;&gt;George Fitz-Hardinge Berkley ''The Campaign of Adowa and the rise of Menelik'', London: Constable 1901.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Raffaele Ruggeri, p. 82 ''Le Guerre Coloniali Italiane 1885/1900'', Editrice Militare Italiana 1988&lt;/ref&gt;

As Chris Prouty describes:

{{quote|They [the Italians] had inadequate maps, old-model guns, poor communication equipment and inferior footgear for the rocky ground. (The newer [[Carcano]] Model 91 rifles were not issued because Baratieri, under constraints to be economical, wanted to use up the old cartridges.) Morale was low as the veterans were homesick and the newcomers were too inexperienced to have any ''esprit de corps''. There was a shortage of mules and saddles.&lt;ref name=CPr&gt;{{cite book|title=Empress Taytu and Menilek II |first=Chris |last=Prouty |year=1986 |page= 155|place=Trenton: The Red Sea Press |ISBN=0-932415-11-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==Order of battle==
[[File:Adwa map.jpg|thumb|upright=1.3|An 1890s Italian map of Adwa. A small arrow indicates that north is to the right.]]

===Ethiopian forces===
{{Further|Ethiopian aristocratic and court titles}}
* [[Shewa]] forces; ''Negus Negasti'' [[Menelik II]]: 25,000 rifles / 3,000 horses / 32 guns&lt;ref name=FTTt/&gt;
* [[Semien Province|Semien]] forces; ''Itaghiè'' [[Taytu Betul|Taytu]]: 3,000 rifles / 600 horses / 4 guns&lt;ref name=FTTt/&gt;
* [[Gojjam]] forces; ''Negus'' [[Tekle Haymanot of Gojjam|Tekle Haymanot]]: 5,000 rifles&lt;ref name=FTTt/&gt;
* [[Harar]] forces; ''Ras'' [[Makonnen Wolde Mikael|Makonnen]]: 15,000 rifles&lt;ref name=FTTt/&gt;
* [[Tigray Province|Tigray and Hamasen]] forces; ''Ras'' [[Ras Mengesha Yohannes|Mengesha Yohannes]] and ''Ras'' [[Ras Alula|Alula (Abba Nega)]]: 12,000 rifles / 6 guns&lt;ref name=FTTt/&gt;
* [[Wollo Province|Wollo]] forces; ''Ras'' [[Mikael of Wollo|Mikael]]: 6,000 rifles / 5,000 horses&lt;ref name=FTTt/&gt;
* Forces of the [[Ras Mengesha Yohannes]] Atikim: 6,000 rifles&lt;ref name=FTTt/&gt;
* Forces of ''Ras'' Oliè and others: 8,000 rifles&lt;ref name=FTTt/&gt;
* In addition there were ~20,000 spearmen and swordsmen as well as an unknown number of armed peasants.&lt;ref name=FTTt/&gt;

Estimates for the Ethiopian forces under Menelik range from a low of 73,000 to a high of over 120,000, outnumbering the Italians by an estimated five or six times.&lt;ref&gt;[[Richard K. P. Pankhurst|Pankhurst]] has published one collection of these estimates, ''Economic History of Ethiopia'' (Addis Ababa: Haile Selassie University, 1968), pp. 555–57. ''See also ''Uhlig, Siegbert, ed. ''[[Encyclopaedia Aethiopica]]: A–C''. Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz Verlag, 2003, p. 108.&lt;/ref&gt; The forces were divided among Emperor Menelik, Empress [[Taytu Betul]], ''[[Ethiopian aristocratic and court titles|Ras]]'' [[Wale Betul]], ''Ras'' [[Mengesha Atikem]], ''Ras'' [[Ras Mengesha Yohannes|Mengesha Yohannes]], ''Ras'' [[Ras Alula|Alula Engida (Abba Nega)]], ''Ras'' [[Mikael of Wollo]], ''Ras'' [[Ras Makonnen|Makonnen Wolde Mikael]], ''[[Fitawrari]]''{{#tag:ref|Roughly equivalent to Commander of the [[Vanguard (military tactics)|Vanguard]].|group=nb}} [[Gebeyyehu]], and ''[[Ethiopian aristocratic and religious titles|Negus]]''{{#tag:ref|Roughly equivalent to [[Monarch|King]].|group=nb}} [[Tekle Haymanot of Gojjam|Tekle Haymanot Tessemma]].&lt;ref&gt;Pétridès (as well as [[Richard K. P. Pankhurst|Pankhurst]], with slight variations) break the troop numbers down (over 100,000 by their estimates) as follows: 35,000 infantry (25,000 riflemen and 10,000 spearmen) and 8,000 cavalry under Emperor Menelik; 5,000 infantry under Empress Taytu; 8,000 infantry (6,000 riflemen and 2,000 spearmen) under Ras Wale; 8,000 infantry (5,000 riflemen and 3,000 spearmen) under Ras Mengesha Atikem, 5,000 riflemen, 5,000 spearmen, and 3,000 cavalry under Ras Mengesha Yohannes and Ras Alula Engida; 6,000 riflemen, 5,000 spearmen, and 5,000 [[Oromo people|Oromo]] cavalry under Ras Mikael of Wollo; 25,000 riflemen under Ras Makonnen; 8,000 infantry under ''Fitawrari'' Gebeyyehu; 5,000 riflemen, 5,000 spearmen, and 3,000 cavalry under ''Negus'' Tekle Haymanot of Gojjam, von Uhlig, ''Encyclopedia'', p. 109.&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, the armies were followed by a similar number of [[camp follower]]s who supplied the army, as had been done for centuries.&lt;ref name=&quot;Casualties&quot;&gt;Uhlig, Siegbert, ed. ''[[Encyclopaedia Aethiopica]]: A–C'' (Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz Verlag, 2003), p. 108.&lt;/ref&gt; Most of the army consisted of riflemen, a significant percentage of which were in Menelik's reserve; however, there were also a significant number of cavalry and infantry only armed with [[lance]] (people with lances were referred to as &quot;lancer servant
s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Casualties&quot;/&gt; The [[Kuban Cossacks|Kuban Cossack]] army officer [[Nikolay Leontiev|N. S. Leontiev]] who visited Ethiopia in 1895,&lt;ref name=&quot;RUSSIAN MISSION TO ABYSSINIA&quot;&gt;[http://hansard.millbanksystems.com/commons/1895/feb/28/russian-mission-to-abyssinia Russian Mission to Abyssina].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Who Was Count Abai&quot;&gt;[http://www.300.years.spb.ru/eng/3_spb_3.html?id=64 Who Was Count Abai?] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110716112407/http://www.300.years.spb.ru/eng/3_spb_3.html?id=64 |date=16 July 2011 }}.&lt;/ref&gt; according to some sources, led a small team of Russian advisers and volunteers.&lt;ref name=&quot;vostlit.info&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.vostlit.info/Texts/Dokumenty/Aethiopien/Artamonov/framepred.htm|title=ДОКУМЕНТЫ-&gt;ЭФИОПИЯ-&gt;Л. К. АРТАМОНОВ-&gt;ЧЕРЕЗ ЭФИОПИЮ К БЕРЕГАМ БЕЛОГО НИЛА-&gt;ПРЕДИСЛОВИЕ|website=www.vostlit.info|accessdate=3 March 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;sworld.com.ua&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.sworld.com.ua/index.php/ru/history/world-history-and-the-history-of-ukraine/768-vinogradova-kv|title=Виноградова К.В. - Научная Конференция, Симпозиум, Конгресс на Проекте SWorld - Апробация, Сборник научных трудов и Монография - Россия, Украина, Казахстан, СНГ - 1. Всемирная история и история Украины|website=www.sworld.com.ua|accessdate=3 March 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.samizdat.com/armies.html |title=– With the Armies of Menelik II by Alexander K. Bulatovich |access-date=13 August 2011 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140414223626/http://www.samizdat.com/armies.html |archive-date=14 April 2014 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Other sources assert that Leontiev did not in fact participate in the battle, rather he visited Ethiopia first unofficially in January 1895, and then officially as a representative of Russia in August 1895, but then left later that year, only to return after the Battle of Adwa.&lt;ref&gt;Raymond Jonas, &quot;The Battle of Adwa&quot; (Harvard University Press, 2011), pp. 310–14.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Italian forces===
The Italian operational corps in Eritrea was under the command of General [[Oreste Baratieri]]. The chief of staff was Lieutenant Colonel Giacchino Valenzano.

*'''Right column''': (3,800 rifles / 18 cannons)&lt;ref name=&quot;PWS&quot; /&gt; 2nd Infantry Brigade (Gen. [[Vittorio Dabormida]]);
** 3rd Africa Infantry Regiment,&lt;ref&gt;Italian national units, formed for service in the colonies with personnel drawn from the regular infantry regiments of the Army.&lt;/ref&gt; (Col. Ragni)
*** 5th Africa Infantry Battalion (Maj. Giordano)
*** 6th Africa Infantry Battalion (Maj. Prato)
*** 10th Africa Infantry Battalion (Maj. De Fonseca)
** 6th Africa Infantry Regiment (Col. [[:it:Cesare Airaghi|Airaghi]])
*** 3rd Africa Infantry Battalion (Maj. Branchi)
*** 13th Africa Infantry Battalion (Maj. Rayneri)
*** 14th Africa Infantry Battalion (Maj. Solaro)
** Native Mobile Militia Battalion (Maj. De Vito)
** Native Company from the [[Asmara]] ''Chitet''&lt;ref&gt;Native feudal levy.&lt;/ref&gt; (Cpt. Sermasi)
** 2nd Artillery Brigade (Maj. Zola)
*** 5th Mountain Artillery Battery&lt;ref name=&quot;75B&quot;&gt;Six light 75mm bronze rifled breach-loading mountain howitzers [[:it:7 BR Ret. Mont|Mod.75B]]&lt;/ref&gt; (Cpt. Mottino)
*** 6th Mountain Artillery Battery&lt;ref name=&quot;75B&quot; /&gt; (Cpt. Regazzi)
*** 7th Mountain Artillery Battery&lt;ref name=&quot;75B&quot; /&gt; (Cpt. Gisla)
*'''Central column''': (2,493 rifles / 12 cannons)&lt;ref name=&quot;PWS&quot; /&gt; 1st Infantry Brigade (Gen. [[:it:Giuseppe Arimondi|Giuseppe Arimondi]]);
** 1st Africa [[Bersaglieri]] Regiment&lt;ref&gt;Italian national units, formed for service in the colonies with personnel drawn from the regular [[Bersaglieri]] regiments of the Army.&lt;/ref&gt; (Col. Stevani)
*** 1st Africa Bersaglieri Battalion (Maj. De Stefano)
*** 2nd Africa Bersaglieri Battalion (Maj. Compiano)
** 1st Africa Infantry Regiment (Col. [[:it:Ugo Brusati|Brusati]])
*** 2nd Africa Infantry Battalion (Maj. Viancini)
*** 4th Africa Infantry Battalion (Maj. De Amicis)
*** 9th Africa Infantry Battalion (Maj. Baudoin)
** 1st Company of the 5th Native Battalion (Cpt. Pavesi)
** 8th Mountain Artillery Battery&lt;ref name=&quot;75B&quot; /&gt; (Cpt. Loffredo)
** 11th Mountain Artillery Battery&lt;ref name=&quot;75B&quot; /&gt; (Cpt. Franzini)
*'''Left column''': (4,076 rifles / 14 cannons)&lt;ref name=&quot;PWS&quot; /&gt; Native Brigade (Gen. [[:it:Matteo Albertone|Matteo Albertone]]);
** 1st Native Battalion (Maj. Turitto)
** 6th Native Battalion (Maj. Cossu)
** 5th Native Battalion (Maj. Valli)
** 8th Native Battalion (Maj. Gamerra)
** &quot;Okulè Kusai&quot; Native [[Bands (Italian Army irregulars)|Irregular Company]] (Lt. Sapelli)
** 1st Artillery Brigade (Maj. De Rosa)
*** 1st Native Mountain Artillery Battery&lt;ref name=&quot;75B2&quot;&gt;Six light 75mm bronze rifled breach-loading mountain howitzers [[:it:7 BR Ret. Mont|Mod.75B]].&lt;/ref&gt; (Cpt. Henry)
*** 2nd Section of the 2nd Native Mountain Artillery Battery&lt;ref&gt;Two light 75mm bronze rifled breach-loading mountain howitzers [[:it:7 BR Ret. Mont|Mod.75B]]&lt;/ref&gt; (Lt. Vibi)
*** 3rd Mountain Artillery Battery&lt;ref name=&quot;75B2&quot; /&gt; (Cpt. Bianchini)
*** 4th Mountain Artillery Battery&lt;ref name=&quot;75B2&quot; /&gt; (Cpt. Masotto)
*'''Reserve column''': (4,150 rifles /12 cannons)&lt;ref name=&quot;PWS&quot; /&gt; 3rd Infantry Brigade (Gen. [[:it:Giuseppe Ellena|Giuseppe Ellena]]);
** 4th Africa Infantry Regiment (Col. Romero)
*** 7th Africa Infantry Battalion (Maj. Montecchi)
*** 8th Africa Infantry Battalion (Maj. Violante)
*** 11th Africa Infantry Battalion (Maj. Manfredi)
** 5th Africa Infantry Regiment (Col. [[:it: Luigi Nava|Nava]])
*** 15th Africa Infantry Battalion (Maj. Ferraro)
*** 16th Africa Infantry Battalion (Maj. Vandiol)
*** 1st Africa [[Alpini]] Battalion (Lt. Col. Menini)
** 3rd Native Battalion (Lt. Col. [[:it: Giuseppe Galliano|Galliano]])
** 1st Quick Fire Artillery Battery (Cpt. Aragno)
** 2nd Quick Fire Artillery Battery (Cpt. Mangia)
**[[Sappers]] company

Budget restrictions and supply shortages meant that many of the rifles and artillery pieces issued to the Italian reinforcements sent to Africa were obsolete models, while clothing and other equipment was often substandard.  In terms of logistics and training, the recently arrived conscript contingents from Italy were inferior to the experienced colonial troops based in Eritrea.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Sean|last=Mclachlan|pages=40–41|title=Armies of the Adowa Campaign 1896|ISBN=978-1-84908-457-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Battle==
[[File:ItaloAbyssinianWarpainting.JPG|thumb|upright=1.3|Ethiopian painting depicting the Battle of Adwa]]
On the night of 29 February and the early morning of 1 March,  three Italian brigades advanced separately towards Adwa over narrow mountain tracks, while a fourth remained camped.&lt;ref name=&quot;Uhlig-109&quot;&gt;Uhlig, ''Encyclopedia'', p. 109.&lt;/ref&gt; [[David Levering Lewis]] states that the Italian battle plan:{{quote|called for three columns to march in parallel formation to the crests of three mountains – Dabormida commanding on the right, Albertone on the left, and Arimondi in the center – with a reserve under Ellena following behind Arimondi. The supporting crossfire each column could give the others made the 'soldiers as deadly as razored shears'. Albertone's brigade was to set the pace for the others. He was to position himself on the summit known as [[Kidane Mehret]], which would give the Italians the high ground from which to meet the Ethiopians.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lewis-117&quot;/&gt;}} However, the three leading Italian brigades had become separated during their overnight march and by dawn were spread across several miles of very difficult terrain. Their sketchy maps caused Albertone to mistake one mountain for Kidane Meret, and when a scout pointed out his mistake, Albertone advanced directly into [[Ras Alula]]'s position.

[[File:Tekle Haymanot of Gojjam.png|thumb|left|upright|''[[Negus]]'' [[Tekle Haymanot of Gojjam]]]]
Unbeknownst to General Baratieri, Emperor Menelik knew his troops had exhausted the ability of the local peasants to support them and had planned to break camp the next day (2 March). The Emperor had risen early to begin prayers for divine guidance when spies from [[Ras Alula|Ras Alula (Abba Nega)]], his chief military advisor, brought him news that the Italians were advancing. The Emperor summoned the separate armies of his nobles and with the Empress Taytu beside him, ordered his forces forward. Negus Tekle Haymanot commanded the right wing with his troops from Gojjam, [[Ras Alula]] the left with his troops from Tigray, Ras Makonnen and [[Ras Mengesha Yohannes]] the center, and [[Mikael of Wollo|Ras Mikael]] at the north side leading the [[Wollo]] Oromo cavalry;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.sahistory.org.za/sites/default/files/file%20uploads%20/sean_mclachlan_armies_of_the_adowa_campaign_1896book4you.pdf |title=Sean McLachlan,page 15 &quot;Armies of the Adowa Campaign 1896: The Italian Disaster in Ethiopia&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Emperor and his consort remained with the reserve.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lewis-117&quot;&gt;Lewis, ''Fashoda'', p. 117.&lt;/ref&gt; The Ethiopian forces positioned themselves on the hills overlooking the Adwa valley, in perfect position to receive the Italians, who were exposed and vulnerable to crossfire.&lt;ref name=&quot;Casualties&quot; /&gt;

Albertone's Ascari Brigade was the first to encounter the onrush of Ethiopians at 06:00, near Kidane Meret,&lt;ref&gt;In the attached map, this is labelled &quot;Chidane Meret&quot;, which is immediately above (west) of the hill &quot;Rajò&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; where the Ethiopians had managed to set up their mountain artillery. Accounts of the Ethiopian artillery deployed at Adwa differ; Russian advisor [[Leonid Artamonov]] wrote that it comprised forty-two Russian mountain guns supported by a team of fifteen advisers,&lt;ref name=&quot;vostlit.info&quot;/&gt; but British writers suggest that the Ethiopian guns were Hotchkiss and Maxim pieces captured from the Egyptians or purchased from French and other European suppliers.&lt;ref&gt;Sean McLachlan, p. 37 &quot;Armies of the Adowa Campaign 1896&quot;, {{ISBN|978-1-84908-457-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; Albertone's heavily outnumbered Ascaris held their position for two hours until Albertone's capture, and under Ethiopian pressure the survivors sought refuge with Arimondi's brigade. Arimondi's brigade beat back the Ethiopians who repeatedly charged the Italian position for three hours with gradually fading strength until Menelik released his reserve of 25,000 [[Shewa]]ns and swamped the Italian defenders. Two [[Company (military unit)|companies]] of Bersaglieri who arrived at the same moment could not help and were cut down.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Sean|last=Mclachlan|page=20|title=Armies of the Adowa Campaign 1896|ISBN=978-1-84908-457-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Adoua 1.jpg|thumb|upright=1.3|British illustration of &quot;''Dabormida's last rally''&quot;]]
Dabormida's Italian Brigade had moved to support Albertone but was unable to reach him in time. Cut off from the remainder of the Italian Army, Dabormida began a fighting retreat towards friendly positions. However, he inadvertently marched his command into a narrow valley where the Wollo Oromo cavalry under Ras Mikael slaughtered his brigade, while shouting ''Ebalgume! Ebalgume!'' (&quot;Reap! Reap!&quot;). Dabormida's remains were never found, although his brother learned from an old woman living in the area that she had given water to a mortally wounded Italian officer, &quot;a chief, a great man with spectacles and a watch, and golden stars&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;George Fitz-Hardinge Berkeley, ''Campaign of Adowa'' (1902), quoted in Lewis, ''Fashoda'', p. 118.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Avanti i mei alpini Adua.jpg|thumb|upright=1|Italian illustration of ''[[Alpini]]'' soldiers at Adwa]]
The remaining two brigades under Baratieri himself were outflanked and destroyed piecemeal on the slopes of [[Mount Belah]]. Menelik watched as [[Gojjam]] forces under the command of [[Tekle Haymanot of Gojjam|Tekle Haymonot]] made quick work of the last intact Italian brigade. By noon, the survivors of the Italian army were in full retreat and the main battle was over. The Ethiopian pursuit continued for nine miles until the late afternoon, while local peasants alerted by signal fires, killed Italian and Ascari stragglers throughout the night.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Sean|last=Mclachlan|page=22|title=Armies of the Adowa Campaign 1896|ISBN=978-1-84908-457-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Immediate aftermath==
[[File:Two Italian soldiers survivors Battle of Adua.jpg|thumb|upright|220px|Two [[Italian diaspora|Italian]] soldiers captured and held captive after the Battle of Adwa]]
[[File:Tomb Dabormida Adwa.jpg|thumb|upright=1.0|Tomb of general Dabormida at Ado Scium Cohena, after the Battle of Adwa]]
[[File:Alula Engida2.JPG|right|thumb|''[[General]]'' [[Ras Alula|Ras Alula (Abba Nega)]] of [[Tigray region|Tigray]], in his final days.]]
The Italians suffered about 6,000 killed and 1,500 wounded in the battle and subsequent retreat back into Eritrea, with 3,000 taken prisoner. Brigadiers Dabormida and Arimondi were amongst the dead. Ethiopian losses have been estimated at around 4,000–5,000 killed and 8,000 wounded.&lt;ref name=&quot;Uhlig-109&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Pankhurst-1998&quot;&gt;[[Richard K. P. Pankhurst|Pankhurst]]. ''The Ethiopians'', pp. 191–92.&lt;/ref&gt; In their flight to [[Eritrea]], the Italians left behind all of their artillery and 11,000 rifles, as well as most of their transport.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pankhurst-1998&quot;/&gt; As Paul B. Henze notes, &quot;Baratieri's army had been completely annihilated while Menelik's was intact as a fighting force and gained thousands of rifles and a great deal of equipment from the fleeing Italians.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Henze, ''Layers of Layers of Time: A History of Ethiopia'' (New York: Palgrave, 2000), p. 170.&lt;/ref&gt; The 3,000 Italian prisoners, who included Brigadier Albertone, appear to have been treated as well as could be expected under difficult circumstances, though about 200 died of their wounds in captivity.&lt;ref&gt;Chris Prouty notes that Albertone was given into the care of Azaj Zamanel, commander of Empress Taytu's personal army, and &quot;had a tent to himself, a horse and servants&quot;. ''Empress Taytu'', pp. 169ff.&lt;/ref&gt;

However, 800 captured [[Eritrean Ascari]], regarded as traitors by the Ethiopians, had their right hands and left feet amputated.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://journals.openedition.org/etudesafricaines/docannexe/image/14887/img-12.jpg|title=Photo of some of the Eritrean Ascari mutilated|publisher=|accessdate=3 March 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Sean|last=McLachlan|page=23|title=Armies of the Adowa Campaign 1896|ISBN=978-1-84908-457-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; Augustus Wylde records when he visited the battlefield months after the battle, the pile of severed hands and feet was still visible, &quot;a rotting heap of ghastly remnants.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Augustus B. Wylde, ''Modern Abyssinia'' (London: Methuen, 1901), p. 213&lt;/ref&gt; Further, many Ascari had not survived their punishment, Wylde writing how the neighborhood of Adwa &quot;was full of their freshly dead bodies; they had generally crawled to the banks of the streams to quench their thirst, where many of them lingered unattended and exposed to the elements until death put an end to their sufferings.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Wylde, ''Modern Abyssinia'', p. 214&lt;/ref&gt; There does not appear to be any foundation for reports that some Italians were castrated and these may reflect confusion with the atrocious treatment of the Ascari prisoners.&lt;ref&gt;

Prouty has collected the few documented experiences of these Italian POWs, none of whom claim to have been treated inhumanely (''Empress Taytu'', pp. 170–83). She repeats the opinion of the Italian historian [[Angelo del Boca]], that &quot;the paucity of the record is attributable to the glacial welcome received in Italy by the returning prisoners for having lost a war, and the fact that they were subjected to long interrogations when they debarked, were defrauded of their back pay, had their mementoes confiscated and were ordered not to talk to journalists&quot; (p. 170).&lt;/ref&gt;

Baratieri was relieved of his command and later charged with preparing an &quot;inexcusable&quot; plan of attack and for abandoning his troops in the field. He was acquitted on these charges but was described by the court martial judges as being &quot;entirely unfit&quot; for his command.

Public opinion in Italy was outraged.&lt;ref&gt;Giuseppe Maria Finaldi, ''Italian National Identity in the Scramble for Africa: Italy's African Wars in the Era of Nation-Building, 1870–1900'' (2010)&lt;/ref&gt; Chris Prouty offers a panoramic overview of the response in Italy to the news:
{{quote|When news of the calamity reached Italy there were street demonstrations in most major cities. In Rome, to prevent these violent protests, the universities and theatres were closed. Police were called out to disperse rock-throwers in front of Prime Minister Crispi's residence. Crispi resigned on 9 March. Troops were called out to quell demonstrations in Naples. In Pavia, crowds built barricades on the railroad tracks to prevent a troop train from leaving the station. The Association of Women of Rome, Turin, Milan and Pavia called for the return of all military forces in Africa. Funeral masses were intoned for the known and unknown dead. Families began sending to the newspapers letters they had received before Adwa in which their menfolk described their poor living conditions and their fears at the size of the army they were going to face. King Umberto declared his birthday (14 March) a day of mourning. Italian communities in [[St. Petersburg]], [[London]], [[New York City|New York]], [[Chicago]], [[Buenos Aires]] and [[Jerusalem]] collected money for the families of the dead and for the Italian Red Cross.&lt;ref&gt;Prouty, ''Empress Taytu'', pp. 159f.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

The Russian support for Ethiopia led to the advent of a Russian Red Cross mission. The Russian mission was a military mission conceived as a medical support for the Ethiopian troops. It arrived in Addis Ababa some three months after Menelik's Adwa victory.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.linkethiopia.org/guide/pankhurst/medicine/medicine_6.html The Russian Red Cross Mission] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20111003141829/http://www.linkethiopia.org/guide/pankhurst/medicine/medicine_6.html |date=3 October 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
In 1895 Emperor Menelik II invited Leontiev to return to Ethiopia with a Russian military mission. Leontiev organized a delivery of Russian weapons for Ethiopia: 30,000 rifles, 5,000,000 cartridges, 5000 sabres, and a few cannons.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.proza.ru/2011/06/29/667|title=Проза.ру|website=www.proza.ru|accessdate=3 March 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://dic.academic.ru/dic.nsf/enc_biography/71087/%D0%9B%D0%B5%D0%BE%D0%BD%D1%82%D1%8C%D0%B5%D0%B2 Nikolay Stepanovich Leontiev]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Follow-up to Ethiopian victory ==
[[File:Oreste Baratieri.jpg|thumb|middle|220px|General [[Oreste Baratieri]]]]
Emperor Menelik decided not to follow up on his victory by attempting to drive the routed Italians out of their colony. The victorious Emperor limited his demands to little more than the abrogation of the [[Treaty of Wuchale]].{{citation needed|date=February 2013}} In the context of the prevailing balance of power, the emperor's crucial goal was to preserve Ethiopian independence. In addition, Ethiopia had just begun to emerge from a long and brutal [[Famines in Ethiopia|famine]]; Harold Marcus reminds us that the army was restive over its long service in the field, short of rations, and the short rains which would bring all travel to a crawl would soon start to fall.&lt;ref&gt;Marcus, ''Menelik II'', p. 176.&lt;/ref&gt; At the time, Menelik claimed a shortage of cavalry horses with which to harry the fleeing soldiers. Chris Prouty observes that &quot;a failure of nerve on the part of Menelik has been alleged by both Italian and Ethiopian sources.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Prouty, ''Empress T'aytu'', p. 161.&lt;/ref&gt; Lewis believes that it &quot;was his farsighted certainty that total annihilation of Baratieri and a sweep into Eritrea would force the Italian people to turn a bungled colonial war into a national crusade&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Lewis, ''Fashoda'', p. 120.&lt;/ref&gt; that stayed his hand.

As a direct result of the battle, Italy signed the [[Treaty of Addis Ababa]], recognizing Ethiopia as an independent state. Almost forty years later, on 3 October 1935, after the [[League of Nations]]'s weak response to the [[Abyssinia Crisis]], the Italians launched a new military campaign endorsed by [[Benito Mussolini]], the [[Second Italo-Ethiopian War]]. This time the Italians employed vastly superior military technology such as tanks and aircraft, as well as [[chemical warfare]], and the Ethiopian forces were defeated by May 1936. Following the war, Italy occupied Ethiopia for five years (1936–41), before eventually being driven out during World War II by [[British Empire]] and Ethiopian ''Arbegnoch'' (patriot)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=A.D.|last=Roberts|page=740|title=The Cambridge History of Africa Vol 7|ISBN=0-521-22505-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; forces.

==Significance==
[[File:Minilk.jpg|thumb|[[Emperor of Ethiopia|Emperor]] [[Menelik II]]]]
&quot;The confrontation between Italy and Ethiopia at Adwa was a fundamental turning point in Ethiopian history,&quot; writes Henze.&lt;ref&gt;Henze, ''Layers of Layers of Time'', p.180.&lt;/ref&gt; On a similar note, the Ethiopian historian [[Bahru Zewde]] observed that &quot;few events in the modern period have brought Ethiopia to the attention of the world as has the victory at Adwa&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Bahru Zewde, ''A History of Modern Ethiopia'' (London: James Currey, 1991), p. 81.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Russian Empire]] had sold many artillery pieces to the Ethiopian forces and paid enthusiastic compliments to the Ethiopian success. One of the documents of that time stated &quot;The Victory immediately gained the general sympathy of Russian society and it continued to grow.&quot; The unique outlook which polyethnic Russia exhibited to Ethiopia disturbed many supporters of European nationalism during the twentieth century.&lt;ref name=&quot;RUSSIAN MISSION TO ABYSSINIA&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Who Was Count Abai&quot;/&gt; The Russian [[Cossacks|Cossack]] captain [[Nikolay Leontiev]] with a small escort was present at the battle as an observer.&lt;ref name=&quot;sworld.com.ua&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.tvoros.ru/proza/kazaki-u-imperatora-menelika-vtorogo.html |title=Cossacks of the emperor Menelik II |access-date=10 February 2012 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150716233744/http://www.tvoros.ru/proza/kazaki-u-imperatora-menelika-vtorogo.html |archive-date=16 July 2015 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

This defeat of a colonial power and the ensuing recognition of African sovereignty became rallying points for later African nationalists during their struggle for decolonization, as well as activists and leaders of the [[Pan-African]] movement.&lt;ref name=&quot;Abraham&quot;&gt;Professor [[Kinfe Abraham]], &quot;The Impact of the Adowa Victory on The Pan-African and Pan-Black Anti-Colonial Struggle,&quot; Address delivered to The [[Institute of Ethiopian Studies]], Addis Ababa University, 8 February 2006&lt;/ref&gt; As the [[Afrocentric]] scholar Molefe Asante explains,
{{quote|After the victory over Italy in 1896, Ethiopia acquired a special importance in the eyes of Africans as the only surviving African State. After Adowa, Ethiopia became emblematic of African valor and resistance, the bastion of prestige and hope to thousands of Africans who were experiencing the full shock of European conquest and were beginning to search for an answer to the myth of African inferiority.&lt;ref&gt;Molefe Asante, quoted in Rodney Worrell, ''Pan-africanism in Barbados'', (New Academia Publishing: 2005) p. 16&lt;/ref&gt;}}

On the other hand, many writers have pointed out how this battle was a humiliation for the Italian military. Italian historian Tripodi pinpointed that some of the roots of the rise of [[Fascism]] in Italy went back to this defeat and to the need to &quot;avenge&quot; the defeat that started to be present in the military and nationalistic groups of the Kingdom of Italy. The same [[Mussolini]] declared when Italian troops occupied [[Addis Ababa]] in May 1936: ''Adua e' vendicata'' (Adwa has been avenged).

Indeed, one student of Ethiopia's History, Donald N. Levine, points out that for the Italians Adwa &quot;became a [[national trauma]] which demagogic leaders strove to avenge. It also played no little part in motivating Italy's revanchist adventure in 1935&quot;. Levine also noted that the victory &quot;gave encouragement to isolationist and conservative strains that were deeply rooted in Ethiopian culture, strengthening the hand of those who would strive to keep Ethiopia from adopting techniques imported from the modern West – resistances with which both Menelik and Ras Teferi/[[Haile Selassie]] would have to contend&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;[http://www.ethiopianreview.com/content/2009/03/the-battle-of-adwa-as-a-historic-event/ &quot;The Battle of Adwa as a 'Historic' Event&quot;], ''[[Ethiopian Review]]'', 3 March 2009 (Retrieved 9 March 2009)&lt;/ref&gt;

== Contemporary celebrations of Adwa ==
===Public holiday===
The Victory of Adwa is a public holiday in all regional states and [[charter cities]] across Ethiopia. All schools, banks, post offices and government offices are closed, with the exceptions of health facilities. Some taxi services and public transports choose not to operate on this day. Shops are normally open but most close earlier than usual.&lt;ref name=&quot;aglobalworld.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://aglobalworld.com/holidays-around-the-world/ethiopia-victory-adowa/|title=Ethiopia Celebrates Victory of Adowa|publisher=|accessdate=3 March 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Public celebrations===
The Victory of Adwa, being a [[public holiday]], is commemorated in public spaces. In [[Addis Ababa]], the Victory of Adwa is celebrated at [[Menelik Square]] with the presence of government officials, patriots, foreign diplomats and the general public. Ethiopian Police Orchestra play various patriotic songs as they walk around Menelik Square.&lt;ref name=&quot;borkena.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://borkena.com/2018/03/02/adwa-victory-colorfully-celebrated-addis-ababa/|title=Adwa victory 122 anniversary colorfully celebrated in Addis Ababa|publisher=|accessdate=3 March 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The public dress up in traditional Ethiopian patriotic attire. Men often wear [[Jodhpurs]] pants, various types of vest tops, and carry the Ethiopian flag, various patriotic banners and placards, and traditional Ethiopian shields and swords called [[Shotel]]. Women dress up in different patterns of handcrafted traditional [[Ethiopian clothing]], known in [[Amharic]] as [[Habesha kemis]]. Some wear black gowns on top, while others put royal crowns on their head. Women's dressing style, like their male counterparts, imitate the traditional style of Ethiopian patriotic women. Of particular note is the dominant presence of Empress [[Taytu Betul]] during these celebrations.&lt;ref name=&quot;aglobalworld.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;borkena.com&quot;/&gt;

Empress [[Taytu Betul]] is the beloved and influential wife of Emperor [[Menelik II]], who played a significant role during the Battle of Adwa. Although often overlooked, thousands of women fought during the Battle of Adwa alongside men. Some were trained as nurses to attend to the wounded, while others mainly cooked and supplied food and water to the soldiers and comforted the wounded.&lt;ref name=&quot;borkena.com&quot;/&gt;

In addition to [[Addis Ababa]], other major cities in Ethiopia, including [[Bahir Dar]], [[Debre Markos]] and the town of [[Adwa]] itself, where the Battle of Adwa took place, celebrate the Victory of Adwa in public ceremonies.&lt;ref name=&quot;aglobalworld.com&quot;/&gt;

===Symbols===
Several images and symbols are used during the commemoration of the Victory of Adwa, including the tri-coloured Green, Gold and Red Ethiopian flag, images of [[Emperor]] [[Menelik II]] and [[Empress]] [[Taytu Betul]], as well as other prominent kings and war generals of the time including [[King]] [[Tekle Haymanot of Gojjam]], [[Michael of Wollo|King Michael]] of [[Wollo]], [[Dejazmach]] [[Balcha Safo]], [[Fitawrari]] [[Habte Giyorgis Dinagde]], and [[Fitawrari]] [[Gebeyehu]], among others. Surviving members of the Ethiopian patriotic battalions wear the various medals that they collected for their participation during different battle fields. Young people often wear T-shirts adorned by Emepror [[Menelik II]], Empress [[Taytu]], Emperor [[Haile Selassie]] and other notable members of the Ethiopian monarchy. Popular and patriotic songs are often played on amplifiers. Of particular note are [[Ejigayehu Shibabaw]]’s [[ballad]] dedicated to the Battle of Adwa and [[Teddy Afro]]’s popular song &quot;Tikur Sew&quot;, which literally translates to &quot;black man or black person&quot; – a poetic reference to Emperor [[Menelik II]]’s decisive African victory over Europeans, as well as the Emperor's darker skin complexion.

==Film==
* [[Adwa (film)|''Adwa'']] – 1999 documentary film directed by [[Haile Gerima]]

==See also==
* [[Battle of Annual]]
* [[First Boer War]]
* [[Battle of Isandlwana]]
* [[Battle of the Little Bighorn]]
* [[Russo-Japanese War]]
* [[Massacre of Elphinstone's Army]]
* [[St. Clair's Defeat]]

==Notes==
===Footnotes===
{{Reflist|2|group=nb}}

===Citations===
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==References==
{{Refbegin}}
* Berkeley, G.F.-H. (1902) ''The Campaign of Adowa and the Rise of Menelik'', Westminister: A. Constable, 403 pp., {{OCLC|11834888}}
* Brown, P.S. and Yirgu, F. (1996) ''The Battle of Adwa 1896'', Chicago: Nyala Publishing, 160 pp., {{ISBN|978-0-9642068-1-6}}
* Bulatovich, A.K. (nd) ''With the Armies of Menelik II: Journal of an Expedition from Ethiopia to Lake Rudolf'', translated by Richard Seltzer, {{OCLC|454102384}}
* Bulatovich, A.K. (2000) ''Ethiopia Through Russian Eyes: Country in Transition, 1896–1898'', translated by Richard Seltzer, Lawrenceville, N.J. : Red Sea Press, {{ISBN|978-1-5690211-7-0}}
* Henze, P.B. (2004) ''Layers of Time: A History of Ethiopia'', London: Hurst &amp; Co., {{ISBN|1-85065-522-7}}
* Jonas, R.A. (2011) ''The Battle of Adwa: African Victory in the Age of Empire'', Bellknap Press of Harvard University Press, {{ISBN|978-0-6740-5274-1}}
* Lewis, D.L. (1988) ''The Race to Fashoda: European Colonialism and African Resistance in the Scramble for Africa'', 1st ed., London: Bloomsbury, {{ISBN|0-7475-0113-0}}
* Marcus, H.G. (1995) ''The Life and Times of Menelik II: Ethiopia, 1844–1913'', Lawrenceville, N.J.: Red Sea Press, {{ISBN|1-56902-010-8}}
* [[Richard K. P. Pankhurst|Pankhurst, K.P.]] (1968) ''Economic History of Ethiopia, 1800–1935'', Addis Ababa: Haile Sellassie I University Press, 772 pp., {{OCLC|65618}}
* [[Richard K. P. Pankhurst|Pankhurst, K.P.]] (1998) ''The Ethiopians: A History'', The Peoples of Africa Series, Oxford: Blackwell Publishers, {{ISBN|0-631-22493-9}}
* Rosenfeld, C.P. (1986) ''Empress Taytu and Menelik II: Ethiopia 1883–1910'', London: Ravens Educational &amp; Development Services, {{ISBN|0-947895-01-9}}
* Uhlig, S. (ed.) (2003) ''[[Encyclopaedia Aethiopica]]'', '''1''' ''(A–C)'', Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz, {{ISBN|3-447-04746-1}}
* Worrell, R. (2005) ''Pan-Africanism in Barbados: An Analysis of the Activities of the Major 20th-Century Pan-African Formations in Barbados'', Washington, DC: New Academia Publishing, {{ISBN|0-9744934-6-5}}
* Zewde, Bahru (1991) ''A History of Modern Ethiopia, 1855–1974'', Eastern African Studies series, London: Currey, {{ISBN|0-85255-066-9}}
* With the Armies of Menelik II, emperor of Ethiopia at www.samizdat.com
{{Refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Battle of Adua}}
* [http://www.historynet.com/first-italo-abyssinian-war-battle-of-adowa.htm Historynet: Ethiopia's Decisive Victory at Adowa]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20110716112407/http://www.300.years.spb.ru/eng/3_spb_3.html?id=64 Who Was Count Abai?]
* [http://www.wdl.org/en/item/2549 ''The Colony of Eritrea from its Origins until March 1, 1899''] from 1899 which details the Battle of Adwa from the [[World Digital Library]]
* [http://collections.nmnh.si.edu/search/anth/?irn=8378154 Painting depicting the Battle of Adwa], Catalogue No. E261845, Department of Anthropology, NMNH, Smithsonian Institution


{{authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Adwa}}
[[Category:Conflicts in 1896]]
[[Category:Battles of the First Italo-Ethiopian War]]
[[Category:1896 in the Italian Empire|Battle of Adwa]]
[[Category:1896 in Ethiopia|Battle of Adwa]]
[[Category:Battles involving Italy]]
[[Category:Battles involving Ethiopia]]
[[Category:Battles involving Eritrea]]
[[Category:History of Eritrea]]
[[Category:History of Ethiopia]]
[[Category:March 1896 events]]</text>
      <sha1>epjandb6lgcczfgdvijix490bcf8mkd</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
