  <page>
    <title>Unit of alcohol</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1946</id>
    <revision>
      <id>930772744</id>
      <parentid>930644757</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-12-14T20:55:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>FrankP</username>
        <id>120987</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* See also */ removed link to &quot;Alcohol equivalence&quot; as this is now a redirect to &quot;Standard drink&quot;</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[File:Red Wine Glass.jpg|thumb|upright|A ''large'' (250&amp;nbsp;ml) glass of 12%&amp;nbsp;ABV red wine has about three units of alcohol. A ''medium'' (175&amp;nbsp;ml) glass has about two units.&lt;ref group=Note&gt;Even though the sizes of wine glasses are defined in UK law, the terms ''large'', ''medium'', ''standard'', etc. are not defined in law.&lt;/ref&gt;]]

'''Units of alcohol''' are used in the United Kingdom (UK) as a measure to quantify the actual alcoholic content within a given volume of an [[alcoholic beverage]], in order to provide guidance on total alcohol consumption.

A number of other countries (including Australia, Canada, New Zealand, and the US) use the concept of a ''[[standard drink]]'', the definition of which varies from country to country, for the same purpose.  ''Standard drinks'' were referred to in the first UK guidelines (1984) that published &quot;safe limits&quot; for drinking, but these were replaced by references to &quot;alcohol units&quot; in the 1987 guidelines and the latter term has been used in all subsequent UK guidance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Alcohol guidelines, Eleventh Report of Session 2010–12|url=https://publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201012/cmselect/cmsctech/1536/1536.pdf|website=UK Parliament|publisher=House of Commons, Science and Technology Committee|accessdate=13 February 2015|page=7|format=PDF|date=7 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

One '''unit of alcohol''' (UK) is defined as 10 [[litre|millilitres]] (8 [[grams]]) of pure [[ethanol|alcohol]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Drinkaware-Unit&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Drinkaware - What is an alcohol unit?|url=http://www.drinkaware.co.uk/check-the-facts/what-is-alcohol/what-is-an-alcohol-unit/}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NHS-HowLong&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=How long does alcohol stay in your blood?|url=http://www.nhs.uk/chq/Pages/853.aspx?CategoryID=87|website=NHS Choices|accessdate=11 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Typical drinks (i.e., typical quantities or servings of common alcoholic beverages) may contain 1–3 units of alcohol.&lt;ref name=&quot;NHS-HowLong&quot; /&gt;

Containers of alcoholic beverages sold directly to UK consumers are normally labelled to indicate the number of units of alcohol in a typical serving of the beverage (optional) and in the full container (can or bottle), as well as information about responsible drinking.&lt;ref name=&quot;Labelling&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Alcohol Labelling|url=http://www.portmangroup.org.uk/codes/alcohol-marketing/alcohol-labelling|accessdate=11 February 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150211183841/http://www.portmangroup.org.uk/codes/alcohol-marketing/alcohol-labelling|archive-date=11 February 2015|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As an approximate guideline, a typical healthy adult can metabolise (break down) about one unit of alcohol per hour,&lt;ref name=&quot;NHS-HowLong&quot; /&gt; although this may vary depending on sex, age, weight, health and many other factors.

== Formula ==
The number of UK units of alcohol in a drink can be determined by multiplying &lt;var&gt;the volume of the drink (in millilitres)&lt;/var&gt; by its &lt;var&gt;percentage [[Alcohol by volume|ABV]]&lt;/var&gt;, and dividing by 1000.

For example, one [[Imperial units|imperial]] [[pint]] (568 ml) of beer at 4% [[alcohol by volume]] (ABV) contains:

:&lt;math&gt;\begin{align}
  568\mbox{ ml} \times 4\% \times \frac{1\mbox{ unit}}{10\mbox{ ml}} &amp;&amp; = &amp;&amp; 568\mbox{ ml} \times \frac{4}{100} \times \frac{1\mbox{ unit}}{10\mbox{ ml}} &amp;&amp; = &amp;&amp; 568\mbox{ ml} \times \frac{4\mbox{ units}}{1000\mbox{ ml}} &amp;= 2.3\mbox{ units}
\end{align}&lt;/math&gt;

The formula uses {{math|&lt;var&gt;ml ÷ 1000&lt;/var&gt;}}. This results in exactly one unit per percentage point per litre, of any alcoholic beverage.

The formula can be simplified for everyday use by expressing the serving size in [[centilitre]]s and the alcohol content literally as a [[percentage]]:

:&lt;math&gt;\begin{align}
  75\mbox{ cl} \times 12\% \times \frac{1\mbox{ unit}}{1\mbox{ cl}} &amp;&amp; = &amp;&amp; 75\mbox{ cl} \times \frac{12}{100} \times \frac{1\mbox{ unit}}{1\mbox{ cl}} &amp;&amp; = &amp;&amp; 75 \times \frac{12}{100}\mbox{ units} &amp;= 9\mbox{ units}
\end{align}&lt;/math&gt;

Thus, a 750&amp;nbsp;ml bottle of wine at 12% ABV contains 75&amp;nbsp;cl × 12% = 9 units. Alternatively, the serving size in litres multiplied by the alcohol content as a number, the above example giving 0.75 × 12 = 9 units:

:&lt;math&gt;\begin{align}
  0.75\mbox{ l} \times 12\% \times \frac{100\mbox{ units}}{1\mbox{ l}} &amp;&amp; = &amp;&amp; 0.75\mbox{ l} \times \frac{12}{100} \times \frac{100\mbox{ units}}{1\mbox{ l}} &amp;&amp; = &amp;&amp; 0.75 \times 12\mbox{ units} &amp;= 9\mbox{ units}
\end{align}&lt;/math&gt;

Both pieces of input data are usually mentioned in this form on the bottle, so is easy to retrieve.

==Labelling==
[[File:Example_UK_Wine_Label.jpg|thumb|right|Example of Wine Bottle label in accordance with UK voluntary health labelling scheme]]

UK alcohol companies pledged in March 2011 to implement an innovative health labelling scheme to provide more information about responsible drinking on alcohol labels and containers. This voluntary scheme is the first of its kind in Europe and has been developed in conjunction with the UK Department of Health. The pledge stated:&lt;ref name=&quot;DoH Pledge&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Alcohol Labelling pledge|url=https://responsibilitydeal.dh.gov.uk/pledges/pledge/?pl=1|website=Dept of Health (UK)|accessdate=13 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

: ''&quot;We will ensure that over 80% of products on shelf (by December 2013) will have labels with clear unit content, NHS guidelines and a warning about drinking when pregnant.&quot;''

At the end of 2014, 101 companies had committed to the pledge labelling scheme.&lt;ref name=&quot;DoH Pledge&quot; /&gt;

There are five elements included within the overall labelling scheme, the first three being mandatory, and the last two optional:
# Unit alcohol content per container ''(mandatory)'', and per serving ''(optional)''
# Chief Medical Officers' daily guidelines for lower-risk consumption
# Pregnancy warning (in text or as a graphic)
# Mention of &quot;drinkaware.co.uk&quot; ''(optional)''
# Responsibility statement (e.g., &quot;please drink responsibly&quot;) ''(optional)''
: ''Further detailed specifications about the labelling scheme are available from the &quot;Alcohol labelling tool kit&quot;.''&lt;ref name=&quot;Health Labelling&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=UK Alcohol Health Labelling|url=http://www.portmangroup.org.uk/codes/alcohol-marketing/alcohol-labelling|website=Portman Group|publisher=Portman Group|accessdate=13 February 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150211183841/http://www.portmangroup.org.uk/codes/alcohol-marketing/alcohol-labelling|archive-date=11 February 2015|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Drinks companies had pledged to display the three mandatory items on 80% of drinks containers on shelves in the UK off-trade by the end of December 2013.&lt;ref name=&quot;Health Labelling&quot; /&gt;  A report published in Nov 2014, confirmed that UK drinks producers had delivered on that pledge with a 79.3% compliance with the pledge elements as measured by products on shelf. Compared with labels from 2008 on a like-for-like basis, information on Unit alcohol content had increased by 46%; 91% of products displayed alcohol and pregnancy warnings (18% in 2008); and 75% showed the Chief Medical Officers’ lower risk daily guidelines (6% in 2008).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Drinks companies achieve voluntary alcohol labelling target|url=http://portmangroup.org.uk/media/news-details/2014/11/06/drinks-companies-achieve-voluntary-alcohol-labelling-target|website=Portman Group|publisher=Portman Group|accessdate=13 February 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150213184249/http://portmangroup.org.uk/media/news-details/2014/11/06/drinks-companies-achieve-voluntary-alcohol-labelling-target|archive-date=13 February 2015|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Quantities ==
[[File:Units of alcohol chart.svg|250px|thumb|Chart showing alcohol unit count for drink size and ABV]]
It is sometimes misleadingly stated that there is one unit per half-pint of beer, or small glass of wine, or single measure of spirits. However, such statements do not take into account the various strengths and volumes supplied in practice.&lt;ref name=&quot;bmj.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://dtb.bmj.com/content/39/12/95.extract|title=Getting tight on units of alcohol|publisher=|accessdate=9 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;alcoholandyouni.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.alcoholandyouni.com/alcohol-and-you-home/check-the-facts/understanding-units/|title=What is a unit of alcohol?|accessdate=9 January 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160106165354/http://www.alcoholandyouni.com/alcohol-and-you-home/check-the-facts/understanding-units/|archive-date=6 January 2016|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;apas.org.uk&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.apas.org.uk/index.php/worried-about-alcohol/alcohol-units/|title=What is a Unit of Alcohol Anyway? -apas : Alcohol, Gambling, Solutions|publisher=|accessdate=9 January 2016}}{{Dead link|date=August 2019 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc.co.uk&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/magazine/8721029.stm|title=BBC News - Do you know how much you drink?|publisher=|accessdate=9 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

For example, the ABV of beer typically varies from 3.5% to 5.5%. A typical &quot;medium&quot; glass of wine with 175 ml at 12% ABV has 2.1 units. And spirits, although typically 35–40% ABV, have single measures of 25&amp;nbsp;ml or 35&amp;nbsp;ml (so 1 or 1.4 units) depending on location.&lt;ref name=&quot;bmj.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;alcoholandyouni.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;apas.org.uk&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc.co.uk&quot;/&gt;

The misleading nature of &quot;one unit per half-pint of beer, or small glass of wine, or single measure of spirits&quot; can lead to people underestimating their alcohol intake.&lt;ref name=&quot;bmj.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;alcoholandyouni.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;apas.org.uk&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc.co.uk&quot;/&gt;

=== Beers ===
* Half an [[imperial pint]] (284 ml) of [[beer]] with 3.5% ABV contains almost exactly one unit; however, most beers are stronger. In pubs in the United Kingdom, beers generally range from 3.5–5.5% ABV, and continental lagers start at around 4% ABV. An imperial pint of such lager (e.g., 568 ml at 5.2%) contains almost 3 units of alcohol&lt;ref&gt;The volume of the drink in litres multiplied by its percentage strength in ABV give the number of units. In this case, {{nowrap|0.568 × 5.2 gives 2.95}}; i.e., almost 3 units.&lt;/ref&gt; rather than the oft-quoted 2 units.
* Stronger beer (6–12%) may contain 2 units or more per half pint (imperial).
* A half litre (500&amp;nbsp;ml) of standard [[lager]] or [[ale]] (5%) contains 2.5 units.
* One litre (1000&amp;nbsp;ml) of typical [[Oktoberfest]] beer (5.5–6%) contains 5.5–6 units of alcohol.

=== Wines ===
* A medium glass (175&amp;nbsp;ml) of 12% ABV [[wine]] contains around two units of alcohol. However, British pubs and restaurants often supply larger quantities (large glass ≈ 250&amp;nbsp;ml), which contain 3 units. Red wines often have a higher alcohol content (on average 12.5%, sometimes up to 16%).
* Wine sold by the glass is often served in nearly full glasses. Wine served at home, or when bought by the bottle in, say, a restaurant, is usually served in glasses less than half filled; the capacity of a wine glass is not the only criterion for judging quantity.
* A 750&amp;nbsp;ml bottle of 12% ABV wine contains 9 units; 16% ABV wine contains 12 units; a [[fortified wine]] such as [[Port wine|port]] at 20% ABV contains 15 units.

=== Fortified wines ===
* A small glass (50&amp;nbsp;ml) of [[sherry]], [[fortified wine]], or cream liqueur (≈20% ABV) contains about one unit.

=== Spirits ===
Most [[Distilled beverage|spirits]] sold in the [[United Kingdom]] have 40% ABV or slightly less. In England, a single pub measure (25&amp;nbsp;ml) of a spirit contains one unit. However, a larger 35&amp;nbsp;ml measure is increasingly used (and in particular is standard in [[Northern Ireland]] &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.alcoholandyouni.com/alcohol-and-you-home/check-the-facts/what-is-a-unit-of-alcohol/|title=What is a unit of alcohol {{!}} Alcohol and You Northern Ireland|website=www.alcoholandyouni.com|language=en-US|access-date=2017-01-24}}{{Dead link|date=April 2019 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;), which contains 1.4 units of alcohol at 40% ABV. Sellers of spirits by the glass must state the capacity of their standard measure in ml.

=== Alcopops ===
* According to Alcohol and You Northern Ireland resource website, &quot;Most [[alcopops]] contain 1.1–1.5 units per bottle. For example, a normal 275&amp;nbsp;ml bottle of [[WKD Original Vodka|WKD]] contains 1.1 units, whereas [[Bacardi Breezer]] and [[Smirnoff Ice]] both contain 1.5 units of alcohol.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;% volume of wkd&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.qfak.com/livelihood/food_drink/?id=b158893#.UXvAYaKG2So | title=Question:- &quot;How much alcohol is there in WKD vodka blue?&quot; | accessdate=27 April 2013 | archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140112043845/http://www.qfak.com/livelihood/food_drink/?id=b158893#.UXvAYaKG2So | archive-date=12 January 2014 | url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Time to metabolise==
On average, it takes about one hour for the body to [[Metabolism|metabolise]] (break down) one unit of alcohol. However, this will vary with body weight, sex, age, personal metabolic rate, recent food intake, the type and strength of the alcohol, and medications taken. Alcohol may be metabolised more slowly if [[liver]] function is impaired.&lt;ref name=howlong&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nhs.uk/chq/Pages/853.aspx?CategoryID=87|title=How long does alcohol stay in your blood?|publisher=|accessdate=9 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Recommended maximum==
{{Main|Recommended maximum intake of alcoholic beverages}}

From 1992 to 1995, the UK government advised that men should drink no more than 21 units per week, and women no more than 14.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.drinkaware.co.uk/facts/factsheets/health-fact-sample-2 |title=Health Effects of Alcohol |publisher=Drinkaware.co.uk |accessdate=27 May 2013 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090421194737/http://www.drinkaware.co.uk/facts/factsheets/health-fact-sample-2 |archivedate=21 April 2009 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; (The difference between the sexes was due to the typically lower weight and water-to-body-mass ratio of women).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Sex differences in alcohol metabolism|publisher=Women's Health Research Institute: Northwestern University|url=https://www.womenshealth.northwestern.edu/blog/sex-differences-alcohol-metabolism}}&lt;/ref&gt;  ''[[The Times]]'' reported in October 2007 that these limits had been &quot;plucked out of the air&quot; and had no scientific basis.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/life_and_style/food_and_drink/article2697975.ece Drink limits ‘useless’], ''The Times'', 20 October 2007&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2009/jan/26/alcohol-drinking-guidelines-studies The great alcohol myth], ''The Guardian'', 26 January 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

This was changed after a government study showed that many people were in effect &quot;saving up&quot; their units and using them at the end of the week, a phenomenon referred to as [[binge drinking]].{{Citation needed|date= October 2007}} Since 1995 the advice was that regular consumption of 3–4 units a day for men, or 2–3 units a day for women, would not pose significant health risks, but that consistently drinking four or more units a day (men), or three or more units a day (women), is not advisable.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://www.nidirect.gov.uk/sensible-drinking 
 | title = Sensible drinking
 | year = 2013
 | accessdate = 27 May 2013
 | publisher = NIdirect Government Services
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

An international study&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Kanis JA |title=Alcohol intake as a risk factor for fracture |journal=Osteoporosis International |volume=16 |issue=7 |pages=737–42 |date=July 2005 |pmid=15455194 |doi=10.1007/s00198-004-1734-y |url= |name-list-format=vanc|author2=Johansson H |author3=Johnell O |display-authors=3 |last4=Oden |first4=Anders |last5=Laet |first5=Chris |last6=Eisman |first6=John A. |last7=Pols |first7=Huibert |last8=Tenenhouse |first8=Alan}}&lt;/ref&gt; of about 6,000 men and 11,000 women for a total of 75,000 person-years found that people who reported that they drank more than a threshold value of 2 units of alcohol a day had a higher risk of fractures than non-drinkers. For example, those who drank over 3 units a day had nearly twice the risk of a hip fracture.

==See also==
{{portal|Liquor|Drink}}
* [[Standard drink]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|group=Note}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=February 2011}}

==External links==
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20180423142255/http://www.iard.org/policy-tables/drinking-guidelines-general-population/ IARD: Drinking Guidelines General Population by country]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20150211183841/http://www.portmangroup.org.uk/codes/alcohol-marketing/alcohol-labelling Alcohol Labelling, with downloadable &quot;Alcohol labelling tool kit&quot; including labelling specifications]
*[http://www.cleavebooks.co.uk/scol/ccalcoh1.htm Online converter between different countries' standard drinks and units]
*[http://www.drinkaware.co.uk Drinkaware]
*[http://www.nhs.uk/Livewell/alcohol/Pages/Alcoholhome.aspx NHS Choices: Drinking and alcohol]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20150221102901/http://www.nhs.uk/Tools/Pages/Alcohol-unit-calculator.aspx NHS Choices: Alcohol unit calculator]
*[http://www.abbeycarefoundation.com/alcohol-demotivator/ Online alcohol demotivator calculator]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Unit Of Alcohol}}
[[Category:Units of measurement]]
[[Category:Alcohol measurement]]

[[de:Alkoholeinheit]]</text>
      <sha1>6v925sfdfmd0qvqnpiug2hr2zggnyad</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
