  <page>
    <title>Alexander Fleming</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1937</id>
    <revision>
      <id>939731117</id>
      <parentid>938564949</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-08T10:05:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Gb89.2</username>
        <id>37938212</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{About|the biologist|other people named Alexander Fleming|Alexander Fleming (disambiguation)}}
{{pp|small=yes}}
{{short description|Scottish biologist, pharmacologist and botanist}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2019}}
{{Use British English|date=June 2018}}
{{Infobox scientist
| honorific_prefix  =
| name              = Sir Alexander Fleming
| honorific_suffix  = {{postnominals|country=GBR|FRS|FRSE|FRCS|size=100%}}
| image             = Synthetic Production of Penicillin TR1468.jpg
| caption           =
| birth_date        =  {{birth date|df=y|1881|08|06}}
| birth_place       = [[Darvel]], [[East Ayrshire]], Scotland
| death_date        = {{Death date and age|df=y|1955|03|11|1881|08|6}}
| death_place       = London, England
| resting_place     = [[St. Paul's Cathedral]]
| citizenship       = British
| field             = [[Bacteriology]], [[immunology]]
| alma_mater        = {{hlist|[[University of Westminster|Royal Polytechnic Institution]]|[[St Mary's Hospital Medical School]]|[[Imperial College London]]}}
| doctoral_advisor  =
| doctoral_students =
| known_for         = [[Discovery of penicillin]] and &lt;br&gt;[[Lysozyme]]
| influences        =
| influenced        =
| prizes            = {{Plainlist|
* [[Fellow of the Royal Society|FRS]] (1943)&lt;ref name=&quot;frs&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal | last1 = Colebrook | first1 = L. | authorlink1 = Leonard Colebrook| doi = 10.1098/rsbm.1956.0008 | title = Alexander Fleming 1881-1955 | journal = [[Biographical Memoirs of Fellows of the Royal Society]] | volume = 2 | pages = 117–126 | year = 1956 | jstor = 769479}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine|Nobel Prize]] (1945)&lt;ref name=&quot;NobelPrizeBio&quot; /&gt;
* [[Fellow of the Royal Society of Edinburgh|FRSE]]
* [[Fellow of the Royal College of Surgeons of England|FRCS(Eng)]]
* [[Knight Bachelor]] (1944)}}
| signature         = Alexander Fleming signature.svg
}}
'''Sir Alexander Fleming''' {{postnominals|country=GBR|FRS|FRSE|FRCS}}&lt;ref name=&quot;frs&quot;/&gt; (6 August 1881 – 11 March 1955) was a Scottish [[biologist]], [[physician]], [[microbiologist]], and [[pharmacologist]]. His best-known discoveries are the [[enzyme]] [[lysozyme]] in 1923 and the world's first [[antibiotic]] substance [[benzylpenicillin]] (Penicillin G) from the mould ''[[Penicillium notatum]]'' in 1928, for which he shared the [[Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine]] in 1945 with [[Howard Florey]] and [[Ernst Boris Chain]].&lt;ref name=&quot;lesprixnobel&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Alexander Fleming Biography|url=http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/medicine/laureates/1945/fleming.html|work=Les Prix Nobel| publisher=The Nobel Foundation|year=1945|accessdate=27 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last= Hugh |first=TB | title = Howard Florey, Alexander Fleming and the fairy tale of penicillin | journal = The Medical Journal of Australia | volume = 177 | issue = 1 | pages = 52–53; author 53 53 | year = 2002 | pmid = 12436980 |doi=10.5694/j.1326-5377.2002.tb04643.x }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;natureobit&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | first= Robert |last=Cruickshank | title = Sir Alexander Fleming, F.R.S | journal = Nature | volume = 175 | issue = 4459 | pages = 663 | year = 1955 | doi = 10.1038/175663a0 | bibcode =1955Natur.175..663C }}&lt;/ref&gt; He wrote many articles on bacteriology, immunology, and chemotherapy.

Fleming was [[Orders, decorations, and medals of the United Kingdom|knighted]] for his scientific achievements in 1944.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last= McIntyre |first=N | title = Sir Alexander Fleming | journal = Journal of Medical Biography | volume = 15 | issue = 4 | pages = 234 | year = 2007 | pmid = 18615899 | doi=10.1258/j.jmb.2007.05-72}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1999, he was named in ''[[Time (magazine)|Time]]'' magazine's list of the [[Time 100: The Most Important People of the Century|100 Most Important People of the 20th century]]. In 2002, he was chosen in the BBC's television poll for determining the [[100 Greatest Britons]], and in 2009, he was also voted third &quot;greatest Scot&quot; in an opinion poll conducted by [[STV (TV channel)|STV]], behind only [[Robert Burns]] and [[William Wallace]].

==Early life and education==
Born on 6 August 1881 at Lochfield farm near [[Darvel]], in [[Ayrshire]], Scotland, Alexander was the third of four children of farmer Hugh Fleming (1816–1888) from his second marriage to Grace Stirling Morton (1848–1928), the daughter of a neighbouring farmer. Hugh Fleming had four surviving children from his first marriage. He was 59 at the time of his second marriage, and died when Alexander was seven.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fleming bio&quot;/&gt;

Fleming went to [[Loudoun]] Moor School and Darvel School, and earned a two-year scholarship to [[Kilmarnock Academy]] before moving to London, where he attended the [[University of Westminster|Royal Polytechnic Institution]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Penicillin man&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Brown|first1=Kevin|title=Penicillin man : Alexander Fleming and the antibiotic revolution|date=2004|publisher=Sutton|location=Stroud|isbn=978-0750931526|url=https://books.google.com/?id=PP06AwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT27&amp;dq=Alexander+Fleming++Loudoun+Moor#v=onepage&amp;q=Loudoun%20Moor&amp;f=false|accessdate=11 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; After working in a shipping office for four years, the twenty-year-old Alexander Fleming inherited some money from an uncle, John Fleming. His elder brother, Tom, was already a physician and suggested to him that he should follow the same career, and so in 1903, the younger Alexander enrolled at [[St Mary's Hospital Medical School]] in [[Paddington]]; he qualified with an [[Bachelor of Medicine, Bachelor of Surgery|MBBS]] degree from the school with distinction in 1906.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fleming bio&quot;/&gt;

Fleming, who was a [[private (rank)|private]] in the [[London Scottish Regiment]] of the [[Volunteer Force (Great Britain)|Volunteer Force]] from 1900&lt;ref name=&quot;lesprixnobel&quot; /&gt; to 1914,&lt;ref name=Kelly&gt;{{cite book|title=Kelly's Handbook to the Titled, Landed and Official Clases, 1955|publisher=Kelly's|page=802}}&lt;/ref&gt; had been a member of the rifle club at the medical school. The captain of the club, wishing to retain Fleming in the team, suggested that he join the research department at St Mary's, where he became assistant bacteriologist to Sir [[Almroth Wright]], a pioneer in [[vaccine]] therapy and immunology. In 1908, he gained a [[Bachelor of Science|BSc]] degree with Gold Medal in [[Bacteriology]], and became a lecturer at St Mary's until 1914.
Commissioned lieutenant in 1914 and promoted captain in 1917,&lt;ref name=Kelly/&gt; Fleming served throughout [[World War I]] in the [[Royal Army Medical Corps]], and was [[Mentioned in Dispatches]]. He and many of his colleagues worked in battlefield hospitals at the [[Western Front (World War I)|Western Front]] in France. In 1918 he returned to [[St Mary's Hospital, London|St Mary's Hospital]], where he was elected Professor of Bacteriology of the [[University of London]] in 1928. In 1951 he was elected the Rector of the [[University of Edinburgh]] for a term of three years.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fleming bio&quot;/&gt;

==Research==

===Work before penicillin===
During World War I, Fleming witnessed the death of many soldiers from [[sepsis]] resulting from infected [[wound]]s. [[Antiseptic]]s, which were used at the time to treat infected wounds, often worsened the injuries.&lt;ref name=&quot;SingMedJ&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Tan |first1=SY |last2=Tatsumura |first2=Y |title=Alexander Fleming (1881–1955): Discoverer of penicillin |journal=Singapore Medical Journal |date=July 2015 |volume=56 |issue=7 |pages=366–367 |doi=10.11622/smedj.2015105 |pmc=4520913 |pmid=26243971}}&lt;/ref&gt; In an article he submitted for the medical journal ''[[The Lancet]]'' during World War I, Fleming described an ingenious experiment, which he was able to conduct as a result of his own glass blowing skills, in which he explained why antiseptics were killing more soldiers than infection itself during World War I. Antiseptics worked well on the surface, but deep wounds tended to shelter anaerobic bacteria from the antiseptic agent, and antiseptics seemed to remove beneficial agents produced that protected the patients in these cases at least as well as they removed bacteria, and did nothing to remove the bacteria that were out of reach.&lt;ref name=&quot;Flavine&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last1=FLEMING |first1=ALEXANDER |title=The Physiological and Antiseptic Action of Flavine (With Some Observations on the Testing of Antiseptics) |journal=The Lancet |date=September 1917 |volume=190 |issue=4905 |pages=341–345 |doi=10.1016/S0140-6736(01)52126-1 |url=https://zenodo.org/record/2098298 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Sir [[Almroth Wright]] strongly supported Fleming's findings, but despite this, most army physicians over the course of the war continued to use antiseptics even in cases where this worsened the condition of the patients.{{anchor|accidental discovery}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Fleming bio&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | last= Mazumdar |first=PM | title = Fleming as Bacteriologist: Alexander Fleming | journal = Science | volume = 225 | issue = 4667 | pages = 1140–1141 | year = 1984 | pmid = 17782415 | doi = 10.1126/science.225.4667.1140 | bibcode = 1984Sci...225.1140C }}&lt;/ref&gt;

At St Mary's Hospital Fleming continued his investigations into antibacterial substances. Testing the nasal secretions from a patient with a heavy cold, he found that nasal mucus had an inhibitory effect on bacterial growth.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Fleming |first=A |year=1922 |title=On a remarkable bacteriolytic element found in tissues and secretions |journal=Proceedings of the Royal Society B |volume=93 |issue=653 |pages=306–317 |doi=10.1098/rspb.1922.0023}}&lt;/ref&gt; This was the first recorded discovery of [[lysozyme]], an enzyme present in many secretions including tears, saliva, skin, hair and nails as well as mucus.  Although he was able to obtain larger amounts of lysozyme from egg whites, the enzyme was only effective against small counts of harmless bacteria, and therefore had little therapeutic potential.&lt;ref name=&quot;SingMedJ&quot; /&gt;

==Accidental discovery==
{{Main|History of penicillin}}
[[File:PenicillinPSAedit.jpg|thumb|An advertisement advertising penicillin's &quot;miracle cure&quot;.]]
{{quote| One sometimes finds, what one is not looking for. When I woke up just after dawn on September 28, 1928, I certainly didn't plan to revolutionize all medicine by discovering the world's first antibiotic, or bacteria killer. But I suppose that was exactly what I did.|Alexander Fleming&lt;ref name=&quot;isbn1-56308-159-8&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Haven|first =Kendall F.|title=Marvels of Science : 50 Fascinating 5-Minute Reads|publisher=Libraries Unlimited|location=Littleton, Colo|year=1994|page= 182|isbn=1-56308-159-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;|source=}}

By 1927, Fleming had been investigating the properties of [[staphylococcus|staphylococci]]. He was already well known from his earlier work, and had developed a reputation as a brilliant researcher, but his laboratory was often untidy. On 3 September 1928, Fleming returned to his laboratory having spent August on holiday with his family. Before leaving for his holiday, he had stacked all his cultures of staphylococci on a bench in a corner of his laboratory. On returning, Fleming noticed that one culture was contaminated with a fungus, and that the colonies of staphylococci immediately surrounding the fungus had been destroyed, whereas other staphylococci colonies farther away were normal, famously remarking &quot;That's funny&quot;.&lt;ref name=Brown&gt;Brown, K. (2004). ''Penicillin Man: Alexander Fleming and the Antibiotic Revolution''. 320 pp. Sutton Publishing. {{ISBN|0-7509-3152-3}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Fleming showed the contaminated culture to his former assistant Merlin Pryce, who reminded him, &quot;That's how you discovered [[lysozyme]].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Hare, R. ''The Birth of Penicillin'', Allen &amp; Unwin, London, 1970&lt;/ref&gt; Fleming grew the mould in a pure culture and found that it produced a substance that killed a number of disease-causing bacteria. He identified the mould as being from the genus ''[[Penicillium]]'', and, after some months of calling it &quot;mould juice&quot;, named the substance it released ''[[penicillin]]'' on 7 March 1929.&lt;ref&gt;Diggins, F. ''The true history of the discovery of penicillin by Alexander Fleming'' Biomedical Scientist, March 2003, Institute of Biomedical Sciences, London. (Originally published in the Imperial College School of Medicine Gazette)&lt;/ref&gt; The laboratory in which Fleming discovered and tested penicillin is preserved as the [[Alexander Fleming Laboratory Museum]] in St. Mary's Hospital, [[Paddington]].

He investigated its positive anti-bacterial effect on many organisms, and noticed that it affected bacteria such as staphylococci and many other [[Gram-positive]] pathogens that cause [[scarlet fever]], [[pneumonia]], [[meningitis]] and [[diphtheria]], but not [[typhoid fever]] or [[paratyphoid fever]], which are caused by [[Gram-negative]] bacteria, for which he was seeking a cure at the time. It also affected ''[[Neisseria gonorrhoeae]],'' which causes [[gonorrhoea]], although this bacterium is Gram-negative.

Fleming published his discovery in 1929, in the ''British Journal of Experimental Pathology,''&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid6994200&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | last= Fleming |first=A | title = On the antibacterial action of cultures of a penicillium, with special reference to their use in the isolation of B. influenzae. (Reprinted from the British Journal of Experimental Pathology 10:226–236, 1929) | journal = Clin Infect Dis | volume = 2 | issue = 1 | pages = 129–39 | year = 1980 | pmid = 6994200 |pmc=2041430 | doi = 10.1093/clinids/2.1.129 }}; Reprint of {{cite journal |pmc=2048009 | pages=226–236 | volume=10 | issue=3 | journal=Br J Exp Pathol | title=On the Antibacterial Action of Cultures of a Penicillium, with Special Reference to their Use in the Isolation of B. influenzæ | year=929 | last1=Fleming | first1=A. }}&lt;/ref&gt; but little attention was paid to his article. Fleming continued his investigations, but found that cultivating ''Penicillium'' was quite difficult, and that after having grown the mould, it was even more difficult to isolate the antibiotic agent. Fleming's impression was that because of the problem of producing it in quantity, and because its action appeared to be rather slow, penicillin would not be important in treating infection. Fleming also became convinced that penicillin would not last long enough in the human body (''in vivo'') to kill bacteria effectively. Many clinical tests were inconclusive, probably because it had been used as a surface antiseptic. In the 1930s, Fleming's trials occasionally showed more promise,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Rossiter|first=Peter|title=Keith Bernard Rogers|journal=BMJ|date=10 September 2010|quote=Keith was probably the first patient to be treated clinically with the mould juice.|pmc=1200632|page=579|volume=331|issue=7516|doi=10.1136/bmj.331.7516.579-c }}&lt;/ref&gt; but Fleming largely abandoned penicillin work, leaving [[Howard Florey]] and [[Ernst Boris Chain]] at the [[Radcliffe Infirmary]] in Oxford to take up research to mass-produce it, with funds from the U.S. and British governments.&lt;ref&gt;Bickel, L. ''Florey: The Man Who Made Penicillin'', Sun Books, Melbourne, 1972. https://trove.nla.gov.au/work/21266280&lt;/ref&gt; They started mass production after the bombing of [[Pearl Harbor]]. By [[Normandy landings|D-Day]] in 1944, enough penicillin had been produced to treat all the wounded in the [[Allies of World War II|Allied forces]].

===Purification and stabilisation===
{{refimprove section|date=September 2017}}&lt;!--middle 2 paragraphs need citations--&gt;
[[File:Penicillin-G 3D.png|thumb|left|3D-model of benzylpenicillin]]
In Oxford, [[Ernst Boris Chain]] and [[Edward Abraham]] were studying the molecular structure of the antibiotic. Abraham was the first to propose the correct structure of penicillin.&lt;ref&gt;in October 1943 Abraham proposed a molecular structure which included a cyclic formation containing three carbon atoms and one nitrogen atom, the β-lactam ring, not then known in natural products. This structure was not immediately published due to the restrictions of wartime secrecy, and was initially strongly disputed, by Sir Robert Robinson among others, but it was finally confirmed in 1945 by Dorothy Crowfoot Hodgkin using X-ray analysis.&quot; Oxford Dictionary of National Biography; &quot;Abraham, Sir Edward Penley&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.independent.co.uk/arts-entertainment/obituary-sir-edward-abraham-1093226.html|location=London|work=The Independent |first=Gordon|last=Lowe|title=Obituary: Sir Edward Abraham|date=13 May 1999}}&lt;/ref&gt; Shortly after the team published its first results in 1940, Fleming telephoned [[Howard Florey]], Chain's head of department, to say that he would be visiting within the next few days. When Chain heard that Fleming was coming, he remarked &quot;Good God! I thought he was dead.&quot;

[[Norman Heatley]] suggested transferring the active ingredient of penicillin back into water by changing its acidity. This produced enough of the drug to begin testing on animals. There were many more people involved in the Oxford team, and at one point the entire Dunn School was involved in its production.

After the team had developed a method of purifying penicillin to an effective first stable form in 1940, several clinical trials ensued, and their amazing success inspired the team to develop methods for mass production and mass distribution in 1945.

Fleming was modest about his part in the development of penicillin, describing his fame as the &quot;Fleming Myth&quot; and he praised Florey and Chain for transforming the laboratory curiosity into a practical drug. Fleming was the first to discover the properties of the active substance, giving him the privilege of naming it: penicillin. He also kept, grew, and distributed the original mould for twelve years, and continued until 1940 to try to get help from any chemist who had enough skill to make penicillin. But Sir [[Henry Harris (scientist)|Henry Harris]] said in 1998: &quot;Without Fleming, no Chain; without Chain, no Florey; without Florey, no Heatley; without Heatley, no penicillin.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Henry Harris, ''Howard Florey and the development of penicillin'', a lecture given on 29 September 1998, at the Florey Centenary, 1898–1998, Sir William Dunn School of Pathology, Oxford University (sound recording) [http://catalogue.nla.gov.au/Record/1610017]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Antibiotics===
[[File:Staphylococcus aureus (AB Test).jpg|right|thumb|Modern antibiotics are tested using a method similar to Fleming's discovery.]]
Fleming's accidental discovery and isolation of penicillin in September 1928 marks the start of modern [[antibiotics]]. Before that, several scientists had published or pointed out that mould or ''Penicillium sp.'' were able to inhibit bacterial growth, and even to cure bacterial infections in animals. [[Ernest Duchesne]] in 1897 in his thesis &quot;Contribution to the study of vital competition in micro-organisms: antagonism between moulds and microbes&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;Duchesne 1897&quot;&gt;[https://www.amazon.com/dp/B00DZVXPIK Duchesne 1897], Antagonism between molds and bacteria. An English translation by Michael Witty. Fort Myers, 2013. ASIN B00E0KRZ0E and B00DZVXPIK.&lt;/ref&gt; or also [[Clodomiro Picado Twight]] whose work at the [[Pasteur Institute|Institut Pasteur]] in 1923 on the inhibiting action of fungi of the ''Penicillin sp.'' genre in the growth of staphylococci drew little interest from the directors of the Institut at the time. Fleming was the first to push these studies further by isolating the penicillin, and by being motivated enough to promote his discovery at a larger scale.&lt;ref name=&quot;shea&quot;&gt;Infection Control And Hospital Epidemiology. (April 2012). Policy Statement on Antimicrobial Stewardship by the Society for Healthcare Epidemiology of America (SHEA), the Infectious Diseases Society of America (IDSA), and the Pediatric Infectious Diseases Society (PIDS). Retrieved from https://www.cambridge.org/core/services/aop-cambridge-core/content/view/48207C6BE27AB8C26F17672EF25F5808/S0195941700041175a.pdf/div-class-title-policy-statement-on-antimicrobial-stewardship-by-the-society-for-healthcare-epidemiology-of-america-shea-the-infectious-diseases-society-of-america-idsa-and-the-pediatric-infectious-diseases-society-pids-div.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

Fleming also discovered very early that bacteria developed [[antibiotic resistance]] whenever too little penicillin was used or when it was used for too short a period. [[Almroth Wright]] had predicted antibiotic resistance even before it was noticed during experiments. Fleming cautioned about the use of penicillin in his many speeches around the world. On 26 June 1945, he made the following cautionary statements: &quot;the microbes are educated to resist penicillin and a host of penicillin-fast organisms is bred out&amp;nbsp;... In such cases the thoughtless person playing with penicillin is morally responsible for the death of the man who finally succumbs to infection with the penicillin-resistant organism. I hope this evil can be averted.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;shea&quot;/&gt; He cautioned not to use penicillin unless there was a properly diagnosed reason for it to be used, and that if it were used, never to use too little, or for too short a period, since these are the circumstances under which bacterial resistance to antibiotics develops.

==Myths==
The popular story&lt;ref&gt;e.g., ''The Philadelphia Inquirer'', 17 July 1945: Brown, ''Penicillin Man'', note 43 to Chapter 2&lt;/ref&gt; of [[Lord Randolph Churchill|Winston Churchill's father]] paying for Fleming's education after Fleming's father saved young [[Winston Churchill|Winston]] from death is false. According to the biography, ''Penicillin Man: Alexander Fleming and the Antibiotic Revolution'' by [[Kevin Brown (historian of medicine)|Kevin Brown]], Alexander Fleming, in a letter&lt;ref&gt;14 November 1945; British Library Additional Manuscripts 56115: Brown, ''Penicillin Man'', note 44 to Chapter 2&lt;/ref&gt; to his friend and colleague Andre Gratia,&lt;ref&gt;see Wikipedia [[Discovery of penicillin]] article entry for 1920&lt;/ref&gt; described this as &quot;A wondrous fable.&quot; Nor did he save Winston Churchill himself during [[World War II]]. Churchill was saved by [[Charles Wilson, 1st Baron Moran|Lord Moran]], using [[Sulfonamide (medicine)|sulphonamides]], since he had no experience with penicillin, when Churchill fell ill in [[Carthage]] in Tunisia in 1943. ''[[The Daily Telegraph]]'' and ''[[The Morning Post]]'' on 21 December 1943 wrote that he had been saved by penicillin. He was saved by the new sulphonamide drug [[sulfapyridine|Sulphapyridine]], known at the time under the research code M&amp;B 693, discovered and produced by [[May &amp; Baker]] Ltd, [[Dagenham]], Essex – a subsidiary of the French group [[Rhône-Poulenc]]. In a subsequent radio broadcast, Churchill referred to the new drug as &quot;This admirable M&amp;B&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;A History of May &amp; Baker 1834–1984, Alden Press 1984.&lt;/ref&gt; It is highly probable that the correct information about the [[Sulfonamide (medicine)|sulphonamide]] did not reach the newspapers because, since the original sulphonamide antibacterial, [[Prontosil]], had been a discovery by the German laboratory [[Bayer]], and as Britain was at war with [[Nazi Germany|Germany]] at the time, it was thought better to raise British morale by associating Churchill's cure with a British discovery, penicillin.

==Awards and honours==
[[File:Flemingawardsnationalmuseumofscotland.jpg|thumb|right|Display of Fleming's awards, including his Nobel Prize. Also shows a sample of penicillin and an example of an early apparatus for preparing it.]]
[[File:Nobelpristagare Fleming Midi.jpg|thumb|Fleming (centre) receiving the Nobel prize from King [[Gustaf V of Sweden]] (right) in 1945]]
[[File:Faroe stamp 079 europe (fleming).jpg|thumb|right|[[Faroe Islands]] postage stamp commemorating Fleming]]
[[File:Barcelona a Sir Alexander Fleming.JPG|thumb|''Barcelona to Sir Alexander Fleming'' (1956), by [[Catalans|Catalan]] sculptor [[:es:Josep Manuel Benedicto|Josep Manuel Benedicto]]. [[Barcelona]]: jardins del Doctor Fleming.]]
Fleming's discovery of penicillin changed the world of modern medicine by introducing the age of useful [[antibiotic]]s; penicillin has saved, and is still saving, millions of people around the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Roberts|first=Michael|title=Biology|year=2001|publisher=Nelson Thornes|isbn=0-7487-6238-8|pages=105|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=juiDySqWVYkC&amp;pg=PT120|edition=2, illustrated|first2=Neil |last2=Ingram|accessdate=4 March 2012|quote=Penicillin is just one of a very large number of drugs which today are used by doctors to treat people with diseases.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The laboratory at St Mary's Hospital where Fleming discovered penicillin is home to the [[St Mary's Hospital, London#Fleming Museum|Fleming Museum]], a popular London attraction. His alma mater, [[St Mary's Hospital Medical School]], merged with [[Imperial College London]] in 1988. The ''Sir Alexander Fleming Building'' on the [[South Kensington]] campus was opened in 1998, where his son Robert and his great granddaughter Claire were presented to the Queen; it is now one of the main preclinical teaching sites of the [[Imperial College School of Medicine]].

His other alma mater, the Royal Polytechnic Institution (now the [[University of Westminster]]) has named one of its student halls of residence ''Alexander Fleming House'', which is near to [[Old Street]].

{{unordered list
| Fleming, Florey and Chain jointly received the [[Nobel Prize in Medicine]] in 1945. According to the rules of the Nobel committee a maximum of three people may share the prize. Fleming's Nobel Prize medal was acquired by the [[National Museums of Scotland]] in 1989 and is on display after the museum re-opened in 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=100,000 visitors in 6 days |url=http://www.nms.ac.uk/about_us/about_us/press_office/press_releases/2011/100,000_visitors_in_6_days.aspx |publisher=National Museums Scotland |date=3 August 2011 |accessdate=4 March 2012 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120223192704/http://www.nms.ac.uk/about_us/about_us/press_office/press_releases/2011/100%2C000_visitors_in_6_days.aspx |archivedate=23 February 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
| Fleming was a member of the [[Pontifical Academy of Sciences]].&lt;ref name=&quot;lesprixnobel&quot;/&gt;
| Fleming was elected a [[List of Fellows of the Royal Society elected in 1943|Fellow of the Royal Society (FRS) in 1943]].&lt;ref name=&quot;frs&quot;/&gt;
| Fleming was awarded the Hunterian Professorship by the [[Royal College of Surgeons of England]].
| Fleming was [[Orders, decorations, and medals of the United Kingdom|knighted]], as a [[Knight Bachelor]], by king [[George VI]] in 1944.&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=36544|date=2 June 1944 |page=2566 |supp=y}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;People of the century&quot;. P. 78. CBS News. Simon &amp; Schuster, 1999&lt;/ref&gt;
| Fleming was awarded the [[Medal for Merit]] by the President of the United States.&lt;ref name=Kelly/&gt;
! Fleming was made a Grand Cross of the [[Legion of Honour]] by the French Republic.&lt;ref name=Kelly/&gt;
| Fleming was made a Grand Cross of the [[Order of the Phoenix (Greece)|Order of the Phoenix]] of Greece.&lt;ref name=Kelly/&gt;
| He was made a Knight Grand Cross of the [[Civil Order of Alfonso X, the Wise|Order of Alfonso X the Wise]] in 1948.
| In 1999, ''[[Time (magazine)|Time]]'' magazine named Fleming one of the [[Time 100: The Most Important People of the Century|100 Most Important People of the 20th century]], stating:
{{quote|It was a discovery that would change the course of history. The active ingredient in that mould, which Fleming named penicillin, turned out to be an infection-fighting agent of enormous potency. When it was finally recognized for what it was, the most efficacious life-saving drug in the world, penicillin would alter forever the treatment of bacterial infections. By the middle of the century, Fleming's discovery had spawned a huge [[pharmaceutical industry]], churning out synthetic penicillins that would conquer some of mankind's most ancient scourges, including [[syphilis]], [[gangrene]] and [[tuberculosis]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Time 100&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Alexander Fleming – Time 100 People of the Century|url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,990612,00.html|work=[[Time (magazine)|Time]]|date=29 March 1999}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
| The importance of his work was recognized by the placement of an [[International Historic Chemical Landmark]] plaque at the Alexander Fleming Laboratory Museum in London on 19 November 1999.&lt;ref name=&quot;Landmark&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Discovery and Development of Penicillin |url=https://www.acs.org/content/acs/en/education/whatischemistry/landmarks/flemingpenicillin.html |publisher = American Chemical Society |work = International Historic Chemical Landmarks |accessdate = 21 August 2018 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
| When 2000 was approaching, at least three large Swedish magazines ranked penicillin as the most important discovery of the millennium.
| In 2002, Fleming was named in the [[BBC]]'s list of the [[100 Greatest Britons]] following a nationwide vote.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/history/programmes/greatbritons/list.shtml/|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20021204214727/http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/programmes/greatbritons/list.shtml/|archivedate=4 December 2002|title=BBC – Great Britons – Top 100|work=[[Internet Archive]]|accessdate=19 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| A statue of Alexander Fleming stands outside the main bullring in [[Madrid]], Plaza de Toros de [[Las Ventas]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Lewine&quot;&gt;Edward Lewine (2007). &quot;Death and the Sun: A Matador's Season in the Heart of Spain&quot;. p. 123. Houghton Mifflin Harcourt, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; It was erected by subscription from grateful [[matador]]s, as penicillin greatly reduced the number of deaths in the bullring.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lewine&quot;/&gt;
| Flemingovo náměstí is a square named after Fleming in the university area of the [[Dejvice]] community in [[Prague]].
| A secondary school is named after him in [[Sofia, Bulgaria|Sofia]], Bulgaria.
| In [[Athens, Greece|Athens]], a small square in the downtown district of Votanikos is named after Fleming and bears his bust. There are also a number of Streets in greater Athens and other towns in Greece named after either Fleming or his Greek second wife Amalia.
| In mid-2009, Fleming was commemorated on a new series of [[banknotes of the pound sterling|banknotes]] issued by the [[Clydesdale Bank]]; his image appears on the new issue of £5 notes.&lt;ref name=&quot;banknotes&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/scotland/7828554.stm|title= Banknote designs mark Homecoming|date=14 January 2008|work=BBC News|accessdate=20 January 2009| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20090125014009/http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/scotland/7828554.stm| archivedate= 25 January 2009 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| In 2009, Fleming was voted third greatest Scot in an opinion poll conducted by [[STV (TV channel)|STV]], behind only Scotland's [[national poet]] [[Robert Burns]] and national hero [[William Wallace]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://stv.tv/news/scotland/141018-robert-burns-voted-greatest-scot/ |title=Robert Burns voted Greatest Scot|work=[[STV Group (Scotland)|STV Group]]|date=30 November 2009|accessdate=7 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| [[91006 Fleming]], an asteroid in the Asteroid Belt, is named after Fleming.
| [[Fleming station]], on the [[Thessaloniki Metro]] system, takes its name from Fleming Street on which it is located.
| [[Sir Alexander Fleming College]], a British school in [[Trujillo, Peru|Trujillo]], northern [[Perú]]
}}

==Personal life==
[[File:St-Pauls-Cathedral London Plaque-for-Sir-Alexander-Fleming-01.jpg|thumb|Grave of Alexander Fleming in the crypt of [[St Paul's Cathedral, London]].]]
On 24 December 1915, Fleming married a trained nurse, Sarah Marion McElroy of [[Killala]], County Mayo, Ireland. Their only child, Robert Fleming (1924–2015), became a [[General practitioner|general medical practitioner]]. After his first wife's death in 1949, Fleming married Dr. [[Amalia Fleming|Amalia Koutsouri-Vourekas]], a [[Greek people|Greek]] colleague at St. Mary's, on 9 April 1953; she died in 1986.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Biographical Index of Former Fellows of the Royal Society of Edinburgh 1783–2002|date=July 2006|publisher=The Royal Society of Edinburgh|isbn=0-902-198-84-X|url=https://www.royalsoced.org.uk/cms/files/fellows/biographical_index/fells_indexp1.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fleming was a [[Roman Catholic]].

From 1921 until his death in 1955, Fleming owned a country home in [[Barton Mills]], Suffolk.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bartonmills.net/local-history/ BartonMills.net local history]. Retrieved 17 October 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Death==
On 11 March 1955, Fleming died at his home in London of a heart attack. His ashes are buried in [[St Paul's Cathedral]].&lt;ref name=&quot;NobelPrizeBio&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/medicine/laureates/1945/fleming-bio.html |title=Sir Alexander Fleming – Biography |publisher=Nobel Foundation |accessdate=25 October 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[List of people on banknotes#Scotland|People on Scottish banknotes]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
* [https://archive.org/stream/lifeofsiralexand000085mbp#page/n7/mode/2up ''The Life Of Sir Alexander Fleming'', Jonathan Cape, 1959. Maurois, André.]
* ''Nobel Lectures, the Physiology or Medicine 1942–1962'', Elsevier Publishing Company, Amsterdam, 1964
* ''An Outline History of Medicine''. London: Butterworths, 1985. Rhodes, Philip.
* ''The Cambridge Illustrated History of Medicine''. Cambridge, England: Cambridge University Press, 1996. Porter, Roy, ed.
* ''Penicillin Man: Alexander Fleming and the Antibiotic Revolution'', Stroud, Sutton, 2004. Brown, Kevin.
* ''Alexander Fleming: The Man and the Myth'', Oxford University Press, Oxford, 1984. [[Robert Gwyn Macfarlane|Macfarlane, Gwyn]]
* ''Fleming, Discoverer of Penicillin'', Ludovici, Laurence J., 1952
* ''The Penicillin Man: the Story of Sir Alexander Fleming'', Lutterworth Press, 1957, Rowland, John.

==External links==
{{Wikiquote}}
{{commons category-inline|Alexander Fleming}}
* [https://www.theguardian.com/theguardian/2013/mar/12/penicillin-fleming-alexander-bacteriology Alexander Fleming Obituary]
* [http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/medicine/laureates/1945/fleming-bio.html Alexander Fleming Biography]
* [http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,990612,00.html ''Time'', 29 March 1999, Bacteriologist Alexander Fleming]
* [http://himetop.wikidot.com/alexander-fleming Some places and memories related to Alexander Fleming]
* {{PM20|FID=pe/005299}}

{{s-start}}
{{s-aca}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Alastair Sim]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[Rector of the University of Edinburgh]]|years=1951–1954}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Sydney Smith (forensic expert)|Sydney Smith]]}}
{{s-end}}

{{Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine Laureates 1926-1950}}
{{FRS 1943}}{{Infectious disease}}{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Fleming, Alexander}}
[[Category:1881 births]]
[[Category:1955 deaths]]
[[Category:People from East Ayrshire]]
[[Category:People educated at Kilmarnock Academy]]
[[Category:20th-century biologists]]
[[Category:British Army personnel of World War I]]
[[Category:Alumni of Imperial College London]]
[[Category:Alumni of the University of Westminster]]
[[Category:Academics of Imperial College London]]
[[Category:Academics of the University of London]]
[[Category:Burials at St Paul's Cathedral]]
[[Category:Honorary Fellows of the Royal Society of Edinburgh]]
[[Category:Fellows of the Royal Society]]
[[Category:Fellows of the Royal College of Physicians of Edinburgh]]
[[Category:Fellows of the Royal College of Physicians]]
[[Category:Fellows of the Royal College of Surgeons]]
[[Category:Members of the Pontifical Academy of Sciences]]
[[Category:Knights Bachelor]]
[[Category:Nobel laureates in Physiology or Medicine]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Civil Order of Alfonso X, the Wise]]
[[Category:Rectors of the University of Edinburgh]]
[[Category:Royal Army Medical Corps officers]]
[[Category:Scottish bacteriologists]]
[[Category:Scottish biologists]]
[[Category:Scottish inventors]]
[[Category:Scottish knights]]
[[Category:20th-century Scottish medical doctors]]
[[Category:Scottish Freemasons]]
[[Category:Scottish microbiologists]]
[[Category:Scottish Nobel laureates]]
[[Category:Scottish pharmacologists]]
[[Category:Scottish soldiers]]
[[Category:Scottish surgeons]]
[[Category:Alumni of St Mary's Hospital Medical School]]
[[Category:People from Forest Heath (district)]]
[[Category:Physicians of Guy's Hospital]]
[[Category:Physicians of St Mary's Hospital, London]]</text>
      <sha1>sknmly0dz53301oihj7coit4w1e8azf</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
