  <page>
    <title>Allele</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1911</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942137153</id>
      <parentid>939523543</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-22T20:53:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>The Eloquent Peasant</username>
        <id>18054835</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Importing Wikidata [[Wikipedia:Short description|short description]]: &quot;One of alternative forms of the same gene&quot; ([[Wikipedia:Shortdesc helper|Shortdesc helper]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|One of alternative forms of the same gene}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2015}}

An '''allele''' ({{IPAc-en|UK|ˈ|æ|l|iː|l}}, {{IPAc-en||ə|ˈ|l|iː|l}}; {{IPAc-en|US|ə|ˈ|l|iː|l}}; from German ''Allel'' and Greek ἄλλος ''állos'', &quot;other&quot;)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.lexico.com/definition/allele|title=Allele {{!}} Meaning of Allele by Lexico|website=Lexico Dictionaries {{!}} English|language=en|access-date=2020-01-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopedia|url=https://www.oxfordlearnersdictionaries.com/definition/english/allele|title=allele noun - Definition, pictures, pronunciation and usage notes|encyclopedia=Oxford Advanced Learner's Dictionary|accessdate=29 October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://dictionary.cambridge.org/dictionary/english/allele|title=allele Meaning in the Cambridge English Dictionary|website=Dictionary.cambridge.org|accessdate=29 October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; is a variant form of a given [[gene]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.1016/0307-4412(95)90659-2|title=The encyclopedia of molecular biology|journal=Biochemical Education|volume=23|issue=2|pages=1165|year=1995|last1=Wood|first1=E.J.}}&lt;/ref&gt; meaning it is one of two or more versions of a known [[mutation]] at the [[Locus (genetics)|same place]] on a [[chromosome]]. It can also refer to different sequence variations for a several-hundred base-pair or more region of the genome that codes for a protein. Alleles can come in different extremes of size. At the lowest possible end one can be the single base choice of a [[Single-nucleotide polymorphism|single nucleotide polymorphism]] (SNP).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Smigielski|first=Elizabeth M.|last2=Sirotkin|first2=Karl|last3=Ward|first3=Minghong|last4=Sherry|first4=Stephen T.|date=2000-01-01|title=dbSNP: a database of single nucleotide polymorphisms|journal=Nucleic Acids Research|volume=28|issue=1|pages=352–355|issn=0305-1048|pmid=10592272|pmc=102496|doi=10.1093/nar/28.1.352}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the higher end, it can be the sequence variations for the regions of the genome that code for the same protein which can be up to several thousand [[Base pair|base-pairs]] long.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Elston|first=Robert|last2=Satagopan|first2=Jaya|last3=Sun|first3=Shuying|date=2012|chapter=Genetic Terminology|series=Methods in Molecular Biology (Clifton, N.J.)|volume=850|pages=1–9|doi=10.1007/978-1-61779-555-8_1|issn=1064-3745|pmc=4450815|pmid=22307690|title=Statistical Human Genetics|isbn=978-1-61779-554-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.ebi.ac.uk/training/online/course/human-genetic-variation-i-introduction-2019/what-genetic-variation/what-effect-do-variants|title=What effect do variants in coding regions have?|date=2019-05-02|website=EMBL-EBI Train online|language=en|access-date=2019-11-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Sometimes, different alleles can result in different observable [[phenotypic trait]]s, such as different [[pigmentation]]. A notable example of this trait of color variation is [[Gregor Mendel|Gregor Mendel's]] discovery that the white and purple flower colors in [[pea]] plants were the result of &quot;pure line&quot; traits which could be used as a control for future experiments. However, most alleles result in little or no observable phenotypic variation.

Most [[multicellular organism]]s have two sets of [[chromosome]]s; that is, they are [[diploid]]. In this case, the chromosomes can be paired: each pair is made up of two [[homologous chromosome]]s. If both alleles of a gene at the [[Locus (genetics)|locus]] on the homologous chromosomes are the same, they and the organism are [[homozygous]] with respect to that gene. If the alleles are different, they and the organism are [[heterozygous]] with respect to that gene.

==Etymology==
The word &quot;allele&quot; is a short form of '''allelomorph''' (&quot;other form&quot;, a word coined by British geneticists [[William Bateson]] and [[Edith Rebecca Saunders]]),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last = Craft | first = Jude | title = Genes and genetics: the language of scientific discovery | work = Genes and genetics | publisher = [[Oxford English Dictionary]] | date = 2013 | url = http://public.oed.com/aspects-of-english/shapers-of-english/genes-and-genetics-the-language-of-scientific-discovery/ | accessdate = 2016-01-14 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bateson, W. and Saunders, E. R. (1902) &quot;The facts of heredity in the light of Mendel’s discovery.&quot; Reports to the Evolution Committee of the Royal Society, '''I.''' pp 125-160&lt;/ref&gt; which was used in the early days of [[genetics]] to describe variant forms of a [[gene]] detected as different [[phenotypes]]. It derives from the [[Greek language|Greek]] prefix ἀλληλο-, ''allelo-'', meaning &quot;mutual&quot;, &quot;reciprocal&quot;, or &quot;each other&quot;, which itself is related to the Greek adjective ἄλλος, ''allos'' (cognate with [[Latin]] ''alius''), meaning &quot;other&quot;.

==Alleles that lead to dominant or recessive phenotypes==
{{main|Dominance (genetics)}}
In many cases, genotypic interactions between the two alleles at a locus can be described as [[Dominance (genetics)|dominant]] or [[recessive]], according to which of the two homozygous phenotypes the [[heterozygote]] most resembles. Where the heterozygote is indistinguishable from one of the homozygotes, the allele expressed is the one that leads to the &quot;dominant&quot; phenotype,&lt;ref name=&quot;Essential genetics: A genomics perspective&quot;/&gt; and the other allele is said to be &quot;recessive&quot;. The degree and pattern of dominance varies among loci. This type of interaction was first formally described by [[Gregor Mendel]]. However, many traits defy this simple categorization and the phenotypes are modeled by [[co-dominance]] and [[Quantitative trait locus|polygenic inheritance]].

The term &quot;[[wild type]]&quot; allele is sometimes used to describe an allele that is thought to contribute to the typical phenotypic character as seen in &quot;wild&quot; populations of organisms, such as fruit flies (''[[Drosophila melanogaster]]''). Such a &quot;wild type&quot; allele was historically regarded as leading to a dominant (overpowering - always expressed), common, and normal phenotype, in contrast to &quot;[[mutant]]&quot; alleles that lead to recessive, rare, and frequently deleterious phenotypes. It was formerly thought that most individuals were homozygous for the &quot;wild type&quot; allele at most gene loci, and that any alternative &quot;mutant&quot; allele was found in homozygous form in a small minority of &quot;affected&quot; individuals, often as [[genetic diseases]], and more frequently in heterozygous form in &quot;[[Genetic carrier|carriers]]&quot; for the mutant allele. It is now appreciated that most or all gene loci are highly polymorphic, with multiple alleles, whose frequencies vary from population to population, and that a great deal of genetic variation is hidden in the form of alleles that do not produce obvious phenotypic differences.

==Multiple alleles==
{{multiple image
| footer    = [[Eye color]] is an inherited trait influenced by [[Polygene|more than one gene]], including ''[[OCA2]]'' and ''[[HERC2]]''. The interaction of multiple genes—and the variation in these genes (&quot;alleles&quot;) between individuals—help to determine a person's eye color [[phenotype]]. Eye color is influenced by [[pigment]]ation of the [[Iris (anatomy)|iris]] and the frequency-dependence of the light [[scattering]] by the [[Turbidity|turbid]] medium within the [[Stroma of iris|stroma]] of the iris.
| width     = 140
| direction = horizontal
| image1    = Deep Blue eye.jpg
| image2   = Beautiful green eye.jpg
| image3    = Hazel eye1.png
| image4    = Lens5.jpg
}}
[[File:ABO blood type.svg|thumb|right|300px|In the [[ABO blood group system]], a person with Type A blood displays A-antigens and may have a genotype I&lt;sup&gt;A&lt;/sup&gt;I&lt;sup&gt;A&lt;/sup&gt; or I&lt;sup&gt;A&lt;/sup&gt;i. A person with Type B blood displays B-antigens and may have the genotype I&lt;sup&gt;B&lt;/sup&gt;I&lt;sup&gt;B&lt;/sup&gt; or I&lt;sup&gt;B&lt;/sup&gt;i. A person with Type AB blood displays both A- and B-antigens and has the genotype I&lt;sup&gt;A&lt;/sup&gt;I&lt;sup&gt;B&lt;/sup&gt; and a person with Type O blood, displaying neither antigen, has the genotype ii.]]

A population or [[species]] of organisms typically includes multiple alleles at each locus among various individuals. Allelic variation at a locus is measurable as the number of alleles ([[Genetic polymorphism|polymorphism]]) present, or the proportion of heterozygotes in the population. A [[null allele]] is a gene variant that lacks the gene's normal function because it either is not expressed, or the expressed protein is inactive.

For example, at the gene locus for the [[ABO]] [[blood type]] [[carbohydrate]] [[antigen]]s in humans,&lt;ref name=&quot;OnlineMendelianInheritanceinMan&quot;/&gt; classical genetics recognizes three alleles, I&lt;sup&gt;A&lt;/sup&gt;, I&lt;sup&gt;B&lt;/sup&gt;, and i, which determine compatibility of [[blood transfusion]]s. Any individual has one of six possible [[genotype]]s (I&lt;sup&gt;A&lt;/sup&gt;I&lt;sup&gt;A&lt;/sup&gt;, I&lt;sup&gt;A&lt;/sup&gt;i, I&lt;sup&gt;B&lt;/sup&gt;I&lt;sup&gt;B&lt;/sup&gt;, I&lt;sup&gt;B&lt;/sup&gt;i, I&lt;sup&gt;A&lt;/sup&gt;I&lt;sup&gt;B&lt;/sup&gt;, and ii) which produce one of four possible [[phenotype]]s: &quot;Type A&quot; (produced by I&lt;sup&gt;A&lt;/sup&gt;I&lt;sup&gt;A&lt;/sup&gt; homozygous and I&lt;sup&gt;A&lt;/sup&gt;i heterozygous genotypes), &quot;Type B&quot; (produced by I&lt;sup&gt;B&lt;/sup&gt;I&lt;sup&gt;B&lt;/sup&gt; homozygous and I&lt;sup&gt;B&lt;/sup&gt;i heterozygous genotypes), &quot;Type AB&quot; produced by I&lt;sup&gt;A&lt;/sup&gt;I&lt;sup&gt;B&lt;/sup&gt; heterozygous genotype, and &quot;Type O&quot; produced by ii homozygous genotype. (It is now known that each of the A, B, and O alleles is actually a class of multiple alleles with different DNA sequences that produce proteins with identical properties: more than 70 alleles are known at the ABO locus.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sequence variation at the human ABO locus&quot;/&gt; Hence an individual with &quot;Type A&quot; blood may be an AO heterozygote, an AA homozygote, or an AA heterozygote with two different &quot;A&quot; alleles.)

==Genotype frequencies==
{{main|Allele frequency}}
The frequency of alleles in a diploid population can be used to predict the frequencies of the corresponding genotypes (see [[Hardy-Weinberg principle]]). For a simple model, with two alleles;

: &lt;math&gt;p + q=1 \, &lt;/math&gt;

: &lt;math&gt;p^2 + 2pq + q^2=1 \,&lt;/math&gt;

where ''p'' is the frequency of one allele and ''q'' is the frequency of the alternative allele, which necessarily sum to unity. Then, ''p''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; is the fraction of the population homozygous for the first allele, 2''pq'' is the fraction of heterozygotes, and ''q''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; is the fraction homozygous for the alternative allele. If the first allele is dominant to the second then the fraction of the population that will show the dominant phenotype is ''p''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; + 2''pq'', and the fraction with the recessive phenotype is ''q''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;.

With three alleles:

: &lt;math&gt;p + q + r = 1 \, &lt;/math&gt; and

: &lt;math&gt;p^2 + q^2 + r^2 + 2pq + 2pr + 2qr = 1. \,&lt;/math&gt;

In the case of multiple alleles at a diploid locus, the number of possible genotypes (G) with a number of alleles (a) is given by the expression:

: &lt;math&gt;G= \frac{a(a+1)}{2}. &lt;/math&gt;

==Allelic dominance in genetic disorders==
A number of [[genetic disorders]] are caused when an individual inherits two recessive alleles for a single-gene trait. Recessive genetic disorders include [[albinism]], [[cystic fibrosis]], [[galactosemia]], [[phenylketonuria]] (PKU), and [[Tay–Sachs disease]]. Other disorders are also due to recessive alleles, but because the gene locus is located on the X chromosome, so that males have only one copy (that is, they are [[hemizygosity|hemizygous]]), they are more frequent in males than in females. Examples include red-green [[color blindness]] and [[fragile X syndrome]].

Other disorders, such as [[Huntington's disease]], occur when an individual inherits only one dominant allele.

==Epialleles==
While [[heredity|heritable traits]] are typically studied in terms of genetic alleles, [[epigenetic]] marks such as [[DNA methylation]] can be inherited at specific genomic regions in certain species, a process termed [[transgenerational epigenetic inheritance]]. The term ''epiallele'' is used to distinguish these heritable marks from traditional alleles, which are defined by [[nucleotide sequence]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Daxinger|first1=Lucia|last2=Whitelaw|first2=Emma|title=Understanding transgenerational epigenetic inheritance via the gametes in mammals|journal=Nature Reviews Genetics|date=31 January 2012|volume=13|issue=3|pages=153–62|doi=10.1038/nrg3188|pmid=22290458}}&lt;/ref&gt; A specific class of epiallele, the [[metastable epiallele]]s, has been discovered in mice and in humans which is characterized by stochastic (probabilistic) establishment of epigenetic state that can be mitotically inherited.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Rakyan|first1=Vardhman K|last2=Blewitt|first2=Marnie E|last3=Druker|first3=Riki|last4=Preis|first4=Jost I|last5=Whitelaw|first5=Emma|title=Metastable epialleles in mammals|journal=Trends in Genetics|date=July 2002|volume=18|issue=7|pages=348–351|doi=10.1016/S0168-9525(02)02709-9|pmid=12127774}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Waterland|first1=RA|last2=Dolinoy|first2=DC|last3=Lin|first3=JR|last4=Smith|first4=CA|last5=Shi|first5=X|last6=Tahiliani|first6=KG|title=Maternal methyl supplements increase offspring DNA methylation at Axin Fused.|journal=Genesis|date=September 2006|volume=44|issue=9|pages=401–6|pmid=16868943|doi=10.1002/dvg.20230}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Evolutionary biology}}
{{Columns-list|colwidth=22em|
* [[Allozyme]]
* [[Evolution]]
* [[Genealogical DNA test]]
* [[Haploinsufficiency]]
* [[Meiosis]]
* [[Mendelian error]]
* [[Mendelian inheritance]]
* [[Mitosis]]
* [[Penetrance]]
* [[Polymorphism (biology)|Polymorphism]]
* [[Punnett square]]
* [[Single-nucleotide polymorphism]]
}}

==References and notes==
{{reflist|refs=&lt;ref name=&quot;OnlineMendelianInheritanceinMan&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/dispomim.cgi?id=110300 |title=ABO Glycosyltransferase; ABO |author1=Victor A. McKusick |author2=Cassandra L. Kniffin |author3=Paul J. Converse |author4=Ada Hamosh |date=10 November 2009 |work=Online Mendelian Inheritance in Man |publisher=National Library of Medicine |accessdate=24 March 2010 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080924220935/http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/dispomim.cgi?id=110300 |archivedate=24 September 2008 |url-status=live |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Essential genetics: A genomics perspective&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Essential genetics: A genomics perspective |edition=4th |last=Hartl |first=Daniel L. |authorlink= |author2=Elizabeth W. Jones |year=2005 |publisher=Jones &amp; Bartlett Publishers |location= |isbn=978-0-7637-3527-2 |oclc=  |page=600 |url= }}&lt;!--|accessdate=5 October 2009--&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Sequence variation at the human ABO locus&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author=Yip SP |title=Sequence variation at the human ABO locus |journal=Annals of Human Genetics |volume=66 |issue=1 |pages=1–27 |date=January 2002 |pmid=12014997 |doi=10.1017/S0003480001008995}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

==External links==
{{Wiktionary|allele}}
* [http://alfred.med.yale.edu/alfred/index.asp ALFRED: The ALlele FREquency Database]

[[Category:Classical genetics]]
[[Category:Genetic genealogy]]</text>
      <sha1>8qycxna4dd4f89dfep9asmkoayz8qmm</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
