  <page>
    <title>Ally McBeal</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1948</id>
    <revision>
      <id>938749056</id>
      <parentid>933992891</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-02T03:52:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>JJMC89 bot III</username>
        <id>35936988</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Moving [[:Category:Fox network shows]] to [[:Category:Fox Broadcasting Company original programming]] per [[Wikipedia:Categories for discussion/Log/2020 January 22#American television series by network]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{For|the character|Ally McBeal (character)}}
{{short description|American legal comedy-drama television series}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=June 2013}}
{{Infobox television
| show_name = Ally McBeal
| image = Ally McBeal S1 Opening.jpg
| caption = Series title card
| genre = [[Surrealism|Surreal]] [[dramedy]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Legal drama]]
| creator = [[David E. Kelley]]
| starring = [[Calista Flockhart]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Courtney Thorne-Smith]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Greg Germann]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Lisa Nicole Carson]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Jane Krakowski]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Vonda Shepard]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Portia de Rossi]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Lucy Liu]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Peter MacNicol]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Gil Bellows]]
| theme_music_composer = [[Vonda Shepard]]
| opentheme = &quot;Searchin' My Soul&quot; 
| composer = [[Danny Lux]]&lt;br/&gt;Vonda Shepard
| country = United States
| language = English
| num_seasons = 5
| num_episodes = 112
| list_episodes = List of Ally McBeal episodes
| executive_producer = David E. Kelley&lt;br/&gt;[[Bill D'Elia]]
| producer = Kayla Alpert (2000–01)&lt;br/&gt;Kim Hamberg (1998–2002)&lt;br/&gt;[[Mike Listo]] (1997–2000)&lt;br/&gt;Jack Philbrick (2000–02)&lt;br/&gt;[[Steve Robin]] (1997–2002)&lt;br/&gt;Pamela J. Wisne (1997–2002)
| cinematography = Thomas F. Denove&lt;br/&gt;[[Billy Dickson]]&lt;br/&gt;David A. Harp&lt;br/&gt;[[Tim Suhrstedt]]
| camera = [[Single-camera setup|Single-camera]]
| runtime = 45–48 minutes
| company = [[20th Century Fox Television]]&lt;br/&gt;David E. Kelley Productions
| distributor = [[20th Television]]
| channel = [[Fox Broadcasting Company|Fox]]
| picture_format = [[4:3]] &lt;small&gt;(seasons 1-2)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br/&gt;[[16:9]] &lt;small&gt;(season 3-5)&lt;/small&gt;
| audio_format =[[Dolby Surround]]
| first_aired = {{Start date|1997|9|8}}
| last_aired = {{End date|2002|5|20}}
| related    = ''[[The Practice]]''
}}

'''''Ally McBeal''''' is&lt;!-- DO NOT change the tense please! Read WP:MOSTV#Lead_paragraphs--&gt; an American [[legal drama|legal]] [[comedy-drama]] [[television series]], originally aired on [[Fox Broadcasting Company|Fox]] from September 8, 1997, to May 20, 2002. Created by [[David E. Kelley]], the series stars [[Calista Flockhart]] in the [[Ally McBeal (character)|title role]] as a lawyer working in the fictional [[Boston]] [[List of fictional law firms|law firm]] Cage and Fish, with other lawyers whose lives and loves were eccentric, humorous, and dramatic. The series received critical acclaim in its early seasons, winning the [[Golden Globe Award for Best Television Series&amp;nbsp;– Musical or Comedy]] in 1997 and 1998, and also winning the [[Primetime Emmy Award for Outstanding Comedy Series|Emmy Award for Outstanding Comedy Series]] in 1999.

==Overview==
The series, set in the fictional [[Boston]] [[List of fictional law firms|law firm]] Cage and Fish, begins with main character [[Ally McBeal (character)|Allison Marie &quot;Ally&quot; McBeal]] joining the firm co-owned by her law school classmate Richard Fish ([[Greg Germann]]) after leaving her previous job due to sexual harassment. On her first day, Ally is horrified to find that she will be working alongside her ex-boyfriend Billy Thomas ([[Gil Bellows]])&amp;mdash;whom she has never gotten over. To make things worse, Billy is now married to fellow lawyer Georgia ([[Courtney Thorne-Smith]]), who later joins Cage and Fish. The triangle among the three forms the basis for the main plot for the show's first three seasons.

Although ostensibly a legal drama, the main focus of the series was the romantic and personal lives of the main characters, often using legal proceedings as [[plot device]]s to contrast or reinforce a character's drama. For example, bitter divorce litigation of a client might provide a backdrop for Ally's decision to break up with a boyfriend. Legal arguments were also frequently used to explore multiple sides of various social issues.

Cage and Fish (which becomes Cage/Fish &amp; McBeal or Cage, Fish, &amp; Associates towards the end of the series), the fictional law firm where most of the characters work, is depicted as a highly sexualized environment symbolized by its unisex restroom. Lawyers and secretaries in the firm routinely date, flirt with, or have a romantic history with each other and frequently run into former or potential romantic interests in the courtroom or on the street outside.

The series had many offbeat and frequently surreal running gags and themes, such as Ally's tendency to immediately fall over whenever she met somebody she found attractive, Richard Fish's [[Wattle (anatomy)|wattle]] fetish and humorous mottos (&quot;Fishisms&quot; &amp; &quot;Bygones&quot;), John's gymnastic dismounts out of the office's unisex bathroom stalls, or the dancing twins (played by Eric &amp; Steve Cohen) at the bar, that ran through the series. The show also used vivid, dramatic [[fantasy]] sequences for Ally's and other characters' wishful thinking; of particular note is the early internet sensation the [[dancing baby]].

The series also featured regular visits to a local bar where singer [[Vonda Shepard]] regularly performed (though occasionally handing over the microphone to the characters). Star contemporary singers also performed in the bar at the end of the shows, including acts such as [[Mariah Carey]], [[Barry White]] and [[Anastacia]]. The series also took place in the same [[Continuity (fiction)|continuity]] as David E. Kelley's legal drama ''[[The Practice]]'' (which aired on [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]]), as the two shows crossed over with one another on occasion, a very rare occurrence for two shows that aired on different networks.

Ultimately, in the last installment of the fifth and final season, &quot;Bygones&quot;, Ally decided to resign from Cage &amp; Fish, leave Boston, and return to New York City.

==Cancellation==
Fox canceled ''Ally McBeal'' after five seasons. In addition to being the lowest-rated season of ''Ally McBeal'' and the grounds for the show's cancellation, the fifth season was also the only season of the show that failed to win any Emmy or Golden Globe awards.

==Main cast==
[[File:Ally mcbeal season 4 cast.jpg|thumb|Cast of season 4 (''from left''): (''top'') Liu, Downey, Krakowski, Germann, MacNicol; ''(middle)'' Carson, de Rossi, Flockhart; ''(bottom)'' Shepard, LeGros]]
[[File:14 Beacon Street (Fish, Cage, &amp; McBeal) (7183315650).jpg|thumb|14 Beacon Street in Boston, the exterior of which was used as the location for the law firm &quot;Cage &amp; Fish&quot; (later &quot;Cage, Fish, &amp; McBeal&quot;), which was located on the 7th floor of this building]]
{| class=&quot;wikitable plainrowheaders&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;
! rowspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;width:10%;&quot; | Actor
! rowspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;width:10%;&quot; | Character
! colspan=&quot;5&quot; | Seasons
|-
! style=&quot;width:3%;&quot;|[[Ally McBeal (season 1)|1]]
! style=&quot;width:3%;&quot;|[[Ally McBeal (season 2)|2]]
! style=&quot;width:3%;&quot;|[[Ally McBeal (season 3)|3]]
! style=&quot;width:3%;&quot;|[[Ally McBeal (season 4)|4]]
! style=&quot;width:3%;&quot;|[[Ally McBeal (season 5)|5]]
|-
| [[Calista Flockhart]]
| [[Ally McBeal (character)|Ally McBeal]]
| colspan=&quot;5&quot; {{cMain}}
|-
| [[Courtney Thorne-Smith]]
| Georgia Thomas
| colspan=&quot;3&quot; {{cMain}}
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; {{CGuest}}
|-
| [[Greg Germann]]
| Richard Fish
| colspan=&quot;5&quot; {{cMain}}
|-
|-
| [[Lisa Nicole Carson]]
| Renée Raddick
| colspan=&quot;4&quot; {{cMain}}
| {{CGuest}}
|-
| [[Jane Krakowski]]
| Elaine Vassal
| colspan=&quot;5&quot; {{cMain}}
|-
| [[Peter MacNicol]]
| [[John Cage (character)|John Cage]]
| colspan=&quot;4&quot; {{cMain}}
| {{cRecurring}}
|-
| [[Gil Bellows]]
| Billy Allen Thomas
| colspan=&quot;3&quot; {{cMain}}
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; {{CGuest}}
|-
|-
| [[Vonda Shepard]]
| Herself
| {{cRecurring}}
| colspan=&quot;4&quot; {{cMain}}
|-
| [[Portia de Rossi]]
| [[Nelle Porter]]
| {{N/A|}}
| colspan=&quot;4&quot; {{cMain}}
|-
| [[Lucy Liu]]
| [[Ling Woo]]
| {{N/A|}}
| colspan=&quot;3&quot; {{cMain}}
| {{cRecurring}}
|-
| [[James LeGros]]
| [[Mark Albert]]
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; {{N/A|}}
| {{cRecurring}}
| {{cMain}}
| {{N/A|}}
|-
| [[Robert Downey Jr.]]
| Larry Paul
| colspan=&quot;3&quot; {{N/A|}}
| {{cMain}}
| {{CGuest}}
|-
| [[Regina Hall]]
| Coretta Lipp
| colspan=&quot;3&quot; {{N/A|}}
| {{cRecurring}}
| {{cMain}}
|-
| [[Julianne Nicholson]]
| Jenny Shaw
| colspan=&quot;4&quot; {{N/A|}}
| {{cMain}}
|-
| [[James Marsden]]
| Glenn Foy
| colspan=&quot;4&quot; {{N/A|}}
| {{cMain}}
|-
| [[Josh Hopkins]]
| Raymond Millbury
| colspan=&quot;4&quot; {{N/A|}}
| {{cMain}}
|-
| [[Hayden Panettiere]]
| Maddie Harrington
| colspan=&quot;4&quot; {{N/A|}}
| {{cMain}}
|}

==Episodes==
{{Main|List of Ally McBeal episodes}}
{{:List of Ally McBeal episodes}}

In Australia, ''Ally McBeal'' was aired by the [[Seven Network]] from 1997 to 2002. In 2010, it was aired repeatedly by [[Network 10]].

===Crossovers with ''The Practice''===
{{See also|The Practice#Crossovers}}
Seymore Walsh, a stern judge often exasperated by the eccentricities of the Cage &amp; Fish lawyers and played by actor Albert Hall, was also a recurring character on ''The Practice''. In addition, Judge Jennifer (Whipper) Cone appears on ''The Practice'' episode &quot;Line of Duty&quot; (S02 E15), while Judge Roberta Kittelson, a recurring character on ''The Practice'', has a featured guest role in the ''Ally McBeal'' episode &quot;Do you Wanna Dance?&quot;

Most of the primary ''Practice'' cast members guest starred in the ''Ally McBeal'' episode &quot;The Inmates&quot; (S01 E20), in a storyline that concluded with the ''Practice'' episode &quot;Axe Murderer&quot; (S02 E26), featuring Calista Flockhart and Gil Bellows reprising their ''Ally'' characters. What is unusual about this continuing storyline is that ''Ally McBeal'' and ''The Practice'' aired on different networks. Bobby Donnell, the main character of ''The Practice'' played by [[Dylan McDermott]], was featured heavily in both this crossover and another ''Ally McBeal'' episode, &quot;These are the Days&quot;.

Regular ''Practice'' cast members [[Lara Flynn Boyle]] and [[Michael Badalucco]] each had a cameo in ''Ally McBeal'' (Boyle as a woman who trades insults with Ally in the episode &quot;Making Spirits Bright&quot; and Badalucco as one of Ally's dates in the episode &quot;I Know him by Heart&quot;) but it is unclear whether they were playing the same characters they play on ''The Practice''.

==Reception==

Upon premiering in 1997, the show was an instant hit, averaging around 11 million viewers per episode. The show's second season saw an increase in ratings and soon became a top 20 show, averaging around 13 million viewers per episode. The show's ratings began to decline in the third season, but stabilized in the fourth season after [[Robert Downey Jr.]] joined the regular cast as Ally's boyfriend Larry Paul, and a fresher aesthetic was created by new art director Matthew DeCoste. However, Downey's character was written out after the end of the season due to the actor's troubles with drug addiction.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://spinoff.comicbookresources.com/2014/03/05/tv-legends-revealed-robert-downey-jr-was-written-out-of-own-tv-wedding/|title=TV Legends Revealed – Robert Downey Jr. Was Written Out of Own TV Wedding|last=Cronin|first=Brian|date=2014-03-05|website=Comic Book Resources|archive-url=https://archive.today/20180224014412/https://www.cbr.com/tv-legends-revealed-robert-downey-jr-was-written-out-of-own-tv-wedding/|archive-date=February 24, 2018|url-status=live|access-date=2018-02-24|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The first two seasons, as well as the fourth, remain the most critically acclaimed and saw the most awards success at the Emmys, SAG Awards and the Golden Globes. In 2007, ''Ally McBeal'' placed #48 on ''[[Entertainment Weekly]]''{{'s}} 2007 &quot;New TV Classics&quot; list.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20207339,00.html|title=The New Classics: TV|date=June 18, 2007|work=[[Entertainment Weekly]]|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180115162745/http://ew.com/article/2007/06/18/new-classics-tv/|archive-date=2018-01-15|url-status=live|accessdate=February 5, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Ratings==
{|class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!colspan=&quot;2&quot;|Season   !!U.S. ratings   !!Network   !!Rank
|-
| 1 || 1997–98 ||11.4 million ||Fox ||#59&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,283382,00.html|title=The Final Countdown|date=May 29, 1998|publisher=ew.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 2 || 1998–99 ||13.8 million ||Fox ||#20&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Final ratings for the 1998–1999 TV season |url=http://www.geocities.com/Hollywood/4616/ew0604.html |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20091020115727/http://geocities.com/Hollywood/4616/ew0604.html |archivedate=October 20, 2009 |url-status=dead |df=mdy }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 3 || 1999–2000 ||12.4 million ||Fox ||#35&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://fbibler.chez.com/tvstats/by_5_yr_period/1999-00.html|title=TV Ratings 1999–2000|publisher=fbibler.chez.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 4 || 2000–01 ||12.0 million ||Fox ||#40&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,256435,00.html|title=The Bitter End|date=June 1, 2001|publisher=ew.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 5 || 2001–02 ||9.4 million ||Fox ||#65&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.usatoday.com/life/television/2002/2002-05-28-year-end-chart.htm|title=How Did Your Favorite Show Rate?|date=May 28, 2002|publisher=usatoday.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|}

==Feminist criticism==
''Ally McBeal'' received some criticism from TV critics and feminists who found the title character annoying and demeaning to women (specifically regarding professional women&lt;ref&gt;Michelle L. Hammers, &quot;Cautionary Tales of Liberation and Female Professionalism: The Case Against ''Ally McBeal''&quot; ''Western Journal of Communication'' '''69''' 2, April (2005): 168. &quot;The ease with which ''McBeal''{{'s}} depictions of women are reincorporated into dominant masculinist discourses ... is particularly problematic for professional women. The increased danger that co-optation poses for professional women is due to the complex ways in which the discursive sedimentation that surrounds the female body, particularly as it has been traditionally sexualized and linked to emotionality, operates as a barrier to women's full and effective participation in professional spheres. Thus, ''McBeal'' operates as a cautionary tale about the dangers presented by the co-optation of postfeminist and third-wave feminist discourses as they relate to current professional discourses surrounding the female body.&lt;/ref&gt;) because of her perceived flightiness, lack of demonstrated legal knowledge, short skirts,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine|url=http://content.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,988616,00.html|title=Is Feminism Dead? (Chat Transcript – Phyllis Chesler)|magazine=Time Magazine|date=June 29, 1998}}&lt;/ref&gt; and emotional instability. Perhaps the most notorious example of the debate sparked by the show was the June 29, 1998, cover story of ''Time'' magazine, which juxtaposed McBeal with three pioneering feminists ([[Susan B. Anthony]], [[Betty Friedan]], [[Gloria Steinem]]) and asked &quot;Is Feminism Dead?&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://content.time.com/time/covers/0,16641,19980629,00.html|title=TIME Magazine Cover: Is Feminism Dead? - June 29, 1998|website=TIME.com|language=en-us|access-date=2018-02-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; In episode 12 of the second season of the show, Ally talks to her co-worker John Cage about a dream she had, saying &quot;You know, I had a dream that they put my face on the cover of ''Time'' magazine as 'the face of feminism'.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TdHSOF6gVwo|title=Ally McBeal, episode 12, season 2|publisher=20th Century Fox|date=August 22, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Music==
{{more citations needed section|date=January 2012}}

''Ally McBeal'' was a heavily music-oriented show. [[Vonda Shepard]], a virtually unknown musician at the time, was featured continually on the show. Her song &quot;Searchin' My Soul&quot; became the show's theme song. Many of the songs Shepard performed were established hits with lyrics that paralleled the events of the episode, including &quot;[[Both Sides Now (song)|Both Sides Now]]&quot;, &quot;[[Hooked on a Feeling]]&quot; and &quot;[[Tell Him (Bert Berns song)|Tell Him]]&quot;. Besides recording background music for the show, Shepard frequently appeared at the ends of episodes as a musician performing at a local [[piano bar]] frequented by the main characters. On rare occasions, her character would have conventional dialogue. A portion of &quot;Searchin' My Soul&quot; was played at the beginning of each episode, but the song was never played in its entirety.

Several of the characters had a musical [[leitmotif]] that played when they appeared. John Cage's was &quot;[[You're the First, the Last, My Everything]]&quot;, Ling Woo's was the [[Wicked Witch of the West]] theme from ''[[The Wizard of Oz (1939 film)|The Wizard of Oz]]'', and Ally McBeal herself picked &quot;[[Tell Him (Bert Berns song)|Tell Him]]&quot;, when told by a psychiatrist that she needed a theme.

Due to the popularity of the show and Shepard's music, a soundtrack titled ''[[Songs from Ally McBeal]]'' was released in 1998, as well as a successor soundtrack titled ''[[Heart and Soul: New Songs from Ally McBeal]]'' in 1999. Two compilation albums from the show featuring Shepard were also released in 2000 and 2001. A Christmas album was also released under the title ''Ally McBeal: A Very Ally Christmas''.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.amazon.com/The-Man-With-Bag/dp/B00138A8P0 ''Ally McBeal: A Very Ally Christmas'' (2000) Sony Music]&lt;/ref&gt; The album received positive reviews, and Shephard's version of [[Kay Starr]]'s Christmas song &quot;[[(Everybody's Waitin' For) The Man with the Bag]]&quot;, received considerable airplay during the holiday season.&lt;ref&gt;Atkinson, Terry (December 3, 2000) &quot;TV Shows Breed Christmas Albums&quot; ''The Post-Tribune'' (Gary, Indiana) (Entertainment News Service), page D-5.[https://search.proquest.com/docview/343646798]{{dead link|date=July 2017|bot=InternetArchiveBot|fix-attempted=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other artists featured on the show include [[Michael Jackson]], [[Barry White]], [[Al Green]], [[Tina Turner]], [[Macy Gray]], [[Gloria Gaynor]], [[Chayanne]], [[Barry Manilow]], [[Anastacia]], [[Elton John]], [[Sting (musician)|Sting]] and [[Mariah Carey]]. [[Josh Groban]] played the role of Malcolm Wyatt in the May 2001 season finale, performing &quot;You're Still You&quot;. The series creator, David E. Kelley, was impressed with Groban's performance at The Family Celebration event and based on the audience reaction to Groban's singing, Kelley created a character for him in that finale. The background score for the show was composed by [[Danny Lux]].

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!Soundtrack name
!Tk#
! Release date
|-
| ''Songs from Ally McBeal''
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|14
| May 5, 1998
|-
| ''Heart and Soul: New Songs from Ally McBeal''
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|14
| November 9, 1999
|-
| ''Ally McBeal: A Very Ally Christmas''
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|14
| November 7, 2000
|-
| ''Ally McBeal: For Once in My Life''
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|14
| April 24, 2001
|-
| ''The Best of Ally McBeal''
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|12
| October 6, 2009
|}

==Home media==
Due to [[music licensing]] issues, none of the seasons of ''Ally McBeal'' were available on [[DVD-Video|DVD]] in the United States (only 6 random episodes could be found on the R1 edition) until 2009, though the show had been available in Italy, Belgium, the Netherlands, Japan, Hong Kong, Portugal, Spain, France, Germany, the United Kingdom, Mexico, Taiwan, Australia, Brazil, and the Czech Republic with all the show's music intact since 2005. In the UK, Ireland, and Spain all seasons are available in a complete box set.

[[20th Century Fox Home Entertainment|20th Century Fox]] released the complete first season on DVD in Region 1 on October 6, 2009. They also released a special complete series edition on the same day.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://tvshowsondvd.com/news/Ally-McBeal-Season-1-Complete-Series-Dates/12247|title=Amazon Posts Date for Season 1 &amp; Complete Series|publisher=TVShowsonDVD|date=July 3, 2009|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090707220213/http://www.tvshowsondvd.com/news/Ally-McBeal-Season-1-Complete-Series-Dates/12247|archivedate=July 7, 2009|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; Season 1 does not contain any special features, but the complete series set contains several bonus features, including featurettes, an all-new retrospective, the [[List of The Practice episodes#Season 2|episode]] of ''[[The Practice]]'' in which Calista Flockhart guest-starred, and a bonus disc entitled &quot;The Best of Ally McBeal Soundtrack.&quot; In addition, both releases contain all of the original music.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://tvshowsondvd.com/news/Ally-McBeal-Press-Release/12444|title=Fox's Press Release for The Complete Series Confirms ALL ORIGINAL MUSIC!|publisher=TVShowsonDVD|date=August 7, 2009|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090811040941/http://www.tvshowsondvd.com/news/Ally-McBeal-Press-Release/12444|archivedate=August 11, 2009|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; Season 2 was released on April 6, 2010. Seasons 3, 4, and 5 were all released on October 5, 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tvshowsondvd.com/news/Ally-McBeal-Seasons-3-4-5/14076|title=Ally McBeal DVD news: Release Date and More for Individual Sets of Seasons 3, 4 and 5|publisher=TVShowsOnDVD.com|accessdate=July 14, 2010|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100717095917/http://www.tvshowsondvd.com/news/Ally-McBeal-Seasons-3-4-5/14076|archivedate=July 17, 2010|url-status=dead|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!DVD name
!Ep#
! Region 1
! Region 2
! Region 4
|-
| The Complete First Season
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|23
| October 6, 2009
| February 21, 2005
| April 26, 2006
|-
| The Complete Second Season
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|23
| April 6, 2010
| February 21, 2005
| April 26, 2006
|-
| The Complete Third Season
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|21
| October 5, 2010
| February 21, 2005
| April 26, 2006
|-
| The Complete Fourth Season
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|23
| October 5, 2010
| May 9, 2005
| April 26, 2006
|-
| The Complete Fifth and Final Season
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|22
| October 5, 2010
| May 9, 2005
| April 26, 2006
|-
| The Complete Series
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|112
| October 6, 2009
| October 30, 2006
| April 18, 2012&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ezydvd.com.au/DVD/ally-mcbeal-season-1-5/dp/6110150|archive-url=https://archive.today/20121231001143/http://www.ezydvd.com.au/DVD/ally-mcbeal-season-1-5/dp/6110150|url-status=dead|archive-date=December 31, 2012|title=Ally McBeal: Season 1-5|publisher=[[EzyDVD]]|accessdate=January 28, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|}

==''Ally'' (1999)==
In 1999, at the height of the show's popularity, a half-hour version entitled ''Ally''&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0210403/ &quot;Ally&quot; (1999) at IMDB]&lt;/ref&gt; began airing in parallel with the main program. This version, designed in a sitcom format, used re-edited scenes from the main program, along with previously unseen footage. The intention was to further develop the plots in the comedy-drama in a sitcom style. It also focused only on Ally's personal life, cutting all the courtroom plots. The repackaged show was cancelled partway through its initial run. While 13 episodes of ''Ally'' were produced, only ten aired.

==In popular culture==
McBeal and 1990s [[yuppie|young affluent professional]] women were parodied in the song ''Ally McBeal'' (tune of &quot;[[Like a Rolling Stone]]&quot; by [[Bob Dylan]]) by [[a cappella]] group [[Da Vinci's Notebook]] on their album ''The Life and Times of Mike Fanning'', released in 2000.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Ally McBeal|url=http://www.elyrics.net/read/d/da-vinci_s-notebook-lyrics/ally-mcbeal-lyrics.html|publisher=elyrics.net|accessdate=April 8, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Rogovoy|first=Seth|title=Da Vinci's Notebook fills doctor's prescription|url=http://rogovoy.com/archive/378.shtml|date=February 18, 2003|publisher=Berkshire Eagle|accessdate=April 8, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In episode 2, season 3 of the British comedy ''[[The Adam and Joe Show]]'', the show was parodied as &quot;Ally McSqueal&quot; using soft toys.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gLjdlq21c5M The Adam and Joe Show]. YouTube. Retrieved on 2012-04-23. {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160617125211/https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gLjdlq21c5M&amp;feature=sh_e_se&amp;list=SL|date=June 17, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Episode 2, season 2 of the show ''[[Futurama]]'', &quot;[[When Aliens Attack]]&quot;, centers on an invasion of Earth by the Omicronians precipitated by a signal loss during the climax of an episode of ''Single Female Lawyer'', whose main character is Jenny McNeal.

==Awards and nominations==
{{Main|List of awards and nominations received by Ally McBeal}}

==See also==
* Other American legal dramedy TV series set in Boston
** ''[[The Practice]]'' {{small|(1997–2004)}}
** ''[[Boston Legal]]'' {{small|(2004–08)}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Wikiquote}}
* {{Dmoz|Arts/Television/Programs/Dramas/Dramedies/Ally_McBeal/}}
* {{IMDb title|0118254}}
* {{tv.com show|ally-mcbeal|Ally McBeal}}
* {{IMDb title|0210403|Ally (1999–2000)}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20051220134133/http://www.salon.com/ent/tv/1997/10/20ally.html Ally McBeal: Woman of the '90s or Retro Airhead]
* [http://www.paramountcomedy.co.uk/shows/show.aspx?id=37 Ally McBeal on Paramount Comedy]

{{AllyMcBeal}}
{{Navboxes
|title = [[List of awards and nominations received by Ally McBeal|Awards for ''Ally McBeal'']]
|list =
{{EmmyAward ComedySeries 1976–2000}}
{{GoldenGlobeTVComedy 1990–2009}}
{{ScreenActorsGuildAwards EnsembleTVComedy 1994–1999}}
{{TCA Award for Outstanding New Program}}
}}
{{David E. Kelley}}

{{Portal bar|Television|United States|Comedy|1990s}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Ally Mcbeal}}
[[Category:Ally McBeal| ]]
[[Category:1997 American television series debuts]]
[[Category:2002 American television series endings]]
[[Category:1990s American comedy-drama television series]]
[[Category:1990s American legal television series]]
[[Category:1990s American romantic comedy television series]]
[[Category:1990s American workplace comedy television series]]
[[Category:1990s American workplace drama television series]]
[[Category:1990s romantic drama television series]]
[[Category:2000s American comedy-drama television series]]
[[Category:2000s American legal television series]]
[[Category:2000s American romantic comedy television series]]
[[Category:2000s American workplace comedy television series]]
[[Category:2000s American workplace drama television series]]
[[Category:2000s romantic drama television series]]
[[Category:American romantic drama television series]]
[[Category:Best Musical or Comedy Series Golden Globe winners]]
[[Category:English-language television programs]]
[[Category:Fox Broadcasting Company original programming]]
[[Category:Outstanding Performance by an Ensemble in a Comedy Series Screen Actors Guild Award winners]]
[[Category:Peabody Award-winning television programs]]
[[Category:Primetime Emmy Award for Outstanding Comedy Series winners]]
[[Category:Primetime Emmy Award-winning television series]]
[[Category:Television series by 20th Century Fox Television]]
[[Category:Television series created by David E. Kelley]]
[[Category:Television shows set in Boston]]
[[Category:The Practice]]</text>
      <sha1>enobmhqkkjnxfnmvlcr9q68grktmho8</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
