  <page>
    <title>Aeon</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1941</id>
    <revision>
      <id>921582073</id>
      <parentid>921581917</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-10-16T15:56:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>El C</username>
        <id>92203</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contribs/2A02:587:3C0E:5F00:5155:F2B9:AD16:9700|2A02:587:3C0E:5F00:5155:F2B9:AD16:9700]] ([[User talk:2A02:587:3C0E:5F00:5155:F2B9:AD16:9700|talk]]) to last version by Monkbot</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{about||the geologic time|Geologic time scale|other uses}}
{{Use British (Oxford) English|date=August 2016}}{{More citations needed|date=June 2009}}

{{wiktionary|eon}}

The word '''aeon''' {{IPAc-en|ˈ|iː|ɒ|n}}, also spelled '''eon''' ([[American English|in American English]]), originally meant &quot;life&quot;, &quot;vital force&quot; or &quot;being&quot;, &quot;generation&quot; or &quot;a period of time&quot;, though it tended to be translated as &quot;age&quot; in the sense of  &quot;ages&quot;, &quot;forever&quot;, &quot;timeless&quot; or &quot;for [[eternity]]&quot;. It is a [[Latin]] transliteration from the [[koine Greek]] word {{lang|grc|ὁ [[wikt:αἰών|αἰών]]}} (''ho aion''), from the archaic {{lang|grc|αἰϝών}}  (''aiwon''). In [[Homer]] it typically refers to life or lifespan. Its latest meaning is more or less similar to the [[Sanskrit]] word ''[[Kalpa (aeon)|kalpa]]'' and [[Hebrew language|Hebrew]] word ''[[olam (disambiguation)|olam]]''. A [[cognate]] [[Latin language|Latin]]  word ''aevum'' or ''aeuum'' (cf. {{lang|grc|αἰϝών}}) for &quot;age&quot; is present in words such as ''longevity'' and ''mediaeval''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pballew.net/arithm16.html|title=Math words page 16|access-date=2006-09-15|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100618055137/http://pballew.net/arithm16.html|archive-date=2010-06-18|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although the term aeon may be used in reference to a period of a billion years (especially in [[geology]], [[cosmology]] or [[astronomy]]), its more common usage is for any long, indefinite period.  Aeon can also refer to the four aeons on the [[Geologic Time Scale]] that make up the Earth's history, the [[Hadean]], [[Archean]], [[Proterozoic]], and the current aeon [[Phanerozoic]].

==Astronomy and cosmology==
In astronomy an aeon is defined as a billion years (10&lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt; years, abbreviated AE).&lt;ref name=Keel&gt;{{cite book |title=Astrophysical Concepts |edition=2nd |author=Martin Harweit |isbn=3-540-96683-8 |year=1991 |publisher=Springer-Verlag}} p. 4.&lt;/ref&gt;
 
[[Roger Penrose]] uses the word ''aeon'' to describe the period between successive and cyclic [[Big Bang]]s within the context of [[conformal cyclic cosmology]].

==Eternity or age==
{{further|In saecula saeculorum}}
The [[Bible]] translation is a treatment of the [[Hebrew language|Hebrew]] word ''olam'' and the [[Greek language|Greek]] word ''aion''.  These words have similar meaning, and [[Young's Literal Translation]] renders them and their derivatives as &quot;age&quot; or &quot;age-during&quot;. Other [[English language|English]] versions most often translate them to indicate eternity, being translated as eternal, everlasting, forever, etc. However, there are notable exceptions to this in all major translations, such as {{bibleref2|Matthew|28:20}}: &quot;...I am with you always, to the end of the age&quot; (NRSV), the word &quot;age&quot; being a translation of ''aion''. Rendering ''aion'' to indicate eternality in this verse would result in the contradictory phrase &quot;end of eternity&quot;, so the question arises whether it should ever be so.&lt;ref&gt;Canon F. W. Farrar &quot;Mercy and Judgment&quot; 1904 pages 378-382 {{cite web |url=http://www.tentmaker.org/books/mercyandjudgment/mercy_and_judgment_ch1.html |title=? |author= |date= |work= |publisher= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Proponents of [[universal reconciliation]] point out that this has significant implications for the [[problem of hell]].&lt;ref&gt;Thomas Talbott ''Three Pictures of God in Western Theology'' 1995 pages 13–15 {{cite web|url=http://www.willamette.edu/~ttalbott/PICTURES.pdf |title=? |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080413172335/http://www.willamette.edu/~ttalbott/PICTURES.pdf |archivedate=2008-04-13 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Contrast {{bibleref2|Matthew|25:46}} in well-known English translations with its rendering in Young's Literal Translation:

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;poem&gt;And these shall go away to punishment age-during, but the righteous to life age-during. ([[Young's Literal Translation|YLT]])&lt;ref&gt;Matthew 25:46 Young's Literal Translation&lt;/ref&gt;

Then they will go away to eternal punishment, but the righteous to eternal life. ([[New International Version|NIV]])&lt;ref&gt;Matthew 25:46 New International Version&lt;/ref&gt;

These will go away into eternal punishment, but the righteous into eternal life. ([[New American Standard Bible|NASB]])&lt;ref&gt;Matthew 25:46 New American Standard Bible&lt;/ref&gt;

And these shall go away into everlasting punishment, but the righteous into eternal life. ([[King James Version|KJV]])&lt;ref&gt;Matthew 25:46 King James Version&lt;/ref&gt;

And these will depart into everlasting cutting-off, but the righteous ones into everlasting life. ([[New World Translation|NWT]])&lt;ref&gt;Matthew 25:46 New World Translation&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/poem&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Philosophy and mysticism==
[[Plato]] used the word ''aeon'' to denote the eternal world of ideas, which he conceived was &quot;behind&quot; the perceived world, as demonstrated in his famous [[allegory of the cave]].

[[Christianity]]'s idea of &quot;[[Eternal life (Christianity)|eternal life]]&quot; comes from the word for life, ''zoe'', and a form of ''aeon'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://biblehub.com/kjvs/genesis/1.htm|title=Genesis Chapter 1 (KJV)|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; which could mean life in the next aeon, the [[Kingdom of God]], or [[Heaven]], just as much as immortality, as in {{bibleref2|John|3:16}}.

According to the Christian doctrine of [[universal reconciliation]], the [[Novum Testamentum Graece|Greek New Testament]] scriptures use the word &quot;aeon&quot; to mean a long period (perhaps 1000 years) and the word &quot;aeonian&quot; to mean &quot;during a long period&quot;; Thus there was a time before the aeons, and the aeonian period is finite. After each man's mortal life ends, he is judged worthy of aeonian life or aeonian punishment. That is, after the period of the aeons, all punishment will cease and death is overcome and then God becomes the all in each one ({{bibleref2|1Cor|15:28|NKJV}}).  This contrasts with the conventional Christian belief in eternal life and eternal punishment.

[[Occult]]ists of the [[Thelema]] and [[Ordo Templi Orientis|O.T.O.]] traditions sometimes speak of a &quot;[[Aeon (Thelema)|magical Aeon]]&quot; that may last for far less time, perhaps as little as 2,000 years.{{Citation needed|date=December 2011}}

[[Order of Nine Angles|The Order of Nine Angles]], a UK-based [[Left-hand path and right-hand path|Left Hand Path]]/[[Satanism|Satanic]] organisation propose the concept of Aeons are central to the esoteric philosophy developed by the pseudonymous Anton Long, who wrote that &quot;an aeon is the term used [by the O9A] to describe a stage or a type of evolution. Evolution itself is taken to result from a certain specific process – and this process can be described, or explained [or 're-presented' ] via a bifurcation of time. That is, evolution is an expression of how the cosmos changes over or through or because of,'time' – this 'time' having two components. These two components are the causal and the acausal ...

&quot;An aeon is a manifestation, in the causal, of a particular type of acausal energy. This energy re-orders, or changes, the causal. These changes have certain limits – in both causal space and causal time. That is, they have a specific beginning and a specific end. A civilization (or rather, a higher or aeonic-civilization) is how this energy becomes ordered or manifests itself in the causal: how this energy is revealed. A civilization represents the practical changes which this energy causes in the causal -in terms of the effect such energy has on individuals and this planet. A civilization is tied to, is born from, a particular aeon. By the nature of this energy, a civilization is an evolution of life – a move toward a more complex, and thus more conscious existence ...&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.scribd.com/document/321516646/Aeonic-Theory-Of-The-Order-Of-Nine-Angles|title=Aeonic Theory Of The Order Of Nine Angles {{!}} Causality {{!}} Civilization|website=Scribd|language=en|access-date=2017-05-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Aeon may also be an archaic name for omnipotent beings, such as gods.

===Gnosticism===
{{main|Aeon (Gnosticism)}}

In many [[Gnosticism|Gnostic]] systems, the various [[emanationism|emanations]] of [[God]], who is also known by such names as the One, the [[Monad (Gnosticism)|Monad]], ''Aion teleos'' ({{lang|grc|αἰών τέλεος}} &quot;The Broadest Aeon&quot;), [[Bythos]] (&quot;depth or profundity&quot;, Greek {{lang|grc|βυθός}}), ''Proarkhe'' (&quot;before the beginning&quot;, Greek {{lang|grc|προαρχή}}), the ''Arkhe'' (&quot;the beginning&quot;, Greek {{lang|grc|ἀρχή}}), &quot;Sophia&quot; (wisdom), Christos (the Anointed One) are called ''Aeons''. In the different systems these emanations are differently named, classified, and described, but the emanation theory itself is common to all forms of Gnosticism.

In the [[Basilidian]] Gnosis they are called sonships (υἱότητες ''huiotetes''; sing.: {{lang|grc|υἱότης}} ''huiotes''); according to [[Marcosians|Marcus]], they are numbers and sounds; in [[Valentinianism]] they form male/female pairs called &quot;syzygies&quot; (Greek {{lang|grc|συζυγίαι}}, from σύζυγοι ''syzygoi'').

Similarly, in the Greek Magical Papyri, the term &quot;Aion&quot; is often used to denote the All, or the supreme aspect of God.&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=K0hCj5u3HNQC&amp;pg=PR47&amp;dq=%22the+All+%28Aion%29%22&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=nEK4T4bvNqSm6gGk3pnFCg&amp;ved=0CDUQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22the%20All%20%28Aion%29%22&amp;f=false] H. D. Betz, The Greek Magical Papyri in Translation, Including the Demotic Spells&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Aion (deity)]]
*[[Kalpa (aeon)]]
*[[Plato]]
*[[Saeculum]], comparable Latin concept

==References==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:New Testament Greek words and phrases]]
[[Category:Units of time]]
[[Category:Latin words and phrases]]</text>
      <sha1>1ydnbxzirqacgz4wfx00jzw7yixa3dm</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
