  <page>
    <title>Antimicrobial resistance</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1914</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941456178</id>
      <parentid>941453459</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-18T18:07:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>GermanJoe</username>
        <id>12935443</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 941453459 by [[Special:Contributions/Raphael Hans|Raphael Hans]] ([[User talk:Raphael Hans|talk]]) spam, not a [[WP:MEDRS]] source</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|ability of a microbe to resist the effects of medication}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2020}}
[[File:Antibiotic sensitvity and resistance.JPG|thumb|upright=1.4|Antibiotic resistance tests: Bacteria are streaked on dishes with white disks, each impregnated with a different antibiotic. Clear rings, such as those on the left, show that bacteria have not grown—indicating that these bacteria are not resistant. The bacteria on the right are fully susceptible to only three of the seven antibiotics tested.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.microbelibrary.org/component/resource/laboratory-test/3189-kirby-bauer-disk-diffusion-susceptibility-test-protocol Kirby-Bauer Disk Diffusion Susceptibility Test Protocol] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110626190940/http://www.microbelibrary.org/component/resource/laboratory-test/3189-kirby-bauer-disk-diffusion-susceptibility-test-protocol |date=26 June 2011 }}, Jan Hudzicki, ASM&lt;/ref&gt;|alt=Two petri dishes with antibiotic resistance tests]]

&lt;!-- Definition &amp; symptoms and mechanism--&gt;
'''Antimicrobial resistance''' ('''AMR''' or '''AR''') is the ability of a microbe to resist the effects of medication that once could successfully treat the microbe.&lt;ref name=ARM&gt;{{cite web|title=Review on Antimicrobial Resistance|url=http://amr-review.org/|website=amr-review.org|access-date=20 May 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150925061349/http://amr-review.org/|archive-date=25 September 2015|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=WHO2014&gt;{{cite web|title=Antimicrobial resistance Fact sheet N°194|url=http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs194/en/|website=who.int|access-date=7 March 2015|date=April 2014|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150310081111/http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs194/en/|archive-date=10 March 2015|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.cdc.gov/drugresistance/about.html|title=About Antimicrobial Resistance – Antibiotic/Antimicrobial Resistance – CDC|date=19 September 2017|website=www.cdc.gov|access-date=8 September 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171001044758/https://www.cdc.gov/drugresistance/about.html|archive-date=1 October 2017|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; The term '''antibiotic resistance''' ('''AR''' or '''ABR''') is a subset of AMR, as it applies only to [[bacteria]] becoming resistant to [[antibiotic]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;WHO2014&quot;/&gt; Resistant microbes are more difficult to treat, requiring alternative medications or higher doses of antimicrobials. These approaches may be more expensive, [[adverse effect|more toxic]] or both. Microbes resistant to multiple antimicrobials are called [[multiple drug resistance|multidrug resistant]] (MDR). Those considered extensively drug resistant (XDR) or totally drug-resistant (TDR) are sometimes called &quot;superbugs&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;cdcgetsmart&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Antibiotic Resistance Questions &amp; Answers|url=https://www.cdc.gov/getsmart/antibiotic-use/antibiotic-resistance-faqs.html#e|work=Get Smart: Know When Antibiotics Work|publisher=Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, USA|access-date=20 March 2013|date=30 June 2009|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130329183317/http://www.cdc.gov/getsmart/antibiotic-use/antibiotic-resistance-faqs.html#e|archive-date=29 March 2013|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Resistance arises through one of three mechanisms: natural resistance in certain types of bacteria, genetic [[mutation]], or by one species acquiring resistance from another.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.tufts.edu/med/apua/about_issue/about_antibioticres.shtml|title=General Background: About Antibiotic Resistance|website=www.tufts.edu|access-date=30 October 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20151023035356/http://www.tufts.edu/med/apua/about_issue/about_antibioticres.shtml|archive-date=23 October 2015|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; All classes of microbes can develop resistance. Fungi develop [[antifungal]] resistance. [[Virus]]es develop [[antiviral]] resistance. [[Protozoa]] develop [[antiprotozoal]] resistance, and [[bacteria]] develop [[antibiotic]] resistance. Resistance can appear spontaneously because of random mutations. However, extended use of antimicrobials appears to encourage selection for mutations which can render antimicrobials ineffective.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

&lt;!-- Prevention --&gt;
Preventive measures include only using antibiotics when needed, thereby stopping [[antibiotic misuse|misuse of antibiotics or antimicrobials]].&lt;ref name=&quot;About Antimicrobial Resistance&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.cdc.gov/drugresistance/about.html|title=About Antimicrobial Resistance|website=www.cdc.gov|access-date=30 October 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171001044758/https://www.cdc.gov/drugresistance/about.html|archive-date=1 October 2017|url-status=live|date=10 September 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Swedish&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title = Swedish work on containment of antibiotic resistance – Tools, methods and experiences|publisher = Public Health Agency of Sweden|year = 2014|isbn = 978-91-7603-011-0|url = http://www.folkhalsomyndigheten.se/pagefiles/17351/Swedish-work-on-containment-of-antibiotic-resistance.pdf|location = Stockholm|pages = 16–17, 121–128|access-date = 23 July 2015|archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20150723081110/http://www.folkhalsomyndigheten.se/pagefiles/17351/Swedish-work-on-containment-of-antibiotic-resistance.pdf|archive-date = 23 July 2015|url-status = live|df = dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; Narrow-spectrum antibiotics are preferred over broad-spectrum antibiotics when possible, as effectively and accurately targeting specific organisms is less likely to cause resistance, as well as side effects.&lt;ref name=&quot;NPS2013&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title = Duration of antibiotic therapy and resistance|url = http://www.nps.org.au/publications/health-professional/health-news-evidence/2013/duration-of-antibiotic-therapy|website = NPS Medicinewise|publisher = National Prescribing Service Limited trading, Australia|access-date = 22 July 2015|date = 13 June 2013|archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20150723074759/http://www.nps.org.au/publications/health-professional/health-news-evidence/2013/duration-of-antibiotic-therapy|archive-date = 23 July 2015|url-status = dead|df = dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Gerber JS, Ross RK, Bryan M, Localio AR, Szymczak JE, Wasserman R, Barkman D, Odeniyi F, Conaboy K, Bell L, Zaoutis TE, Fiks AG | title = Association of Broad- vs Narrow-Spectrum Antibiotics With Treatment Failure, Adverse Events, and Quality of Life in Children With Acute Respiratory Tract Infections | journal = JAMA | volume = 318 | issue = 23 | pages = 2325–2336 | date = December 2017 | pmid = 29260224 | pmc = 5820700 | doi = 10.1001/jama.2017.18715 }}&lt;/ref&gt; For people who take these medications at home, education about proper use is essential. Health care providers can minimize spread of resistant infections by use of proper [[sanitation]] and [[hygiene]], including [[handwashing]] and disinfecting between patients, and should encourage the same of the patient, visitors, and family members.&lt;ref name=&quot;CDC Mission&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.cdc.gov/Features/AntibioticResistance/index.html|title=CDC Features – Mission Critical: Preventing Antibiotic Resistance|website=www.cdc.gov|access-date=22 July 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171108202412/https://www.cdc.gov/features/antibioticresistance/index.html|archive-date=8 November 2017|url-status=live|date=4 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- Treatment and Epidemiology --&gt;
Rising drug resistance is caused mainly by use of antimicrobials in humans and other animals, and spread of resistant strains between the two.&lt;ref name=&quot;About Antimicrobial Resistance&quot;/&gt; Growing resistance has also been linked to dumping of inadequately treated effluents from the pharmaceutical industry, especially in countries where bulk drugs are manufactured.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Changing Markets|title=IMPACTS OF PHARMACEUTICAL POLLUTION ON COMMUNITIES AND ENVIRONMENT IN INDIA|url=https://www.nordea.com/Images/35-107206/impacts%201-20.pdf|website=Nordea|publisher=Nordea|accessdate=1 May 2018|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170520031434/https://www.nordea.com/Images/35-107206/impacts%201-20.pdf|archive-date=20 May 2017|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; Antibiotics increase [[selective pressure]] in bacterial populations, causing vulnerable bacteria to die; this increases the percentage of resistant bacteria which continue growing. Even at very low levels of antibiotic, resistant bacteria can have a growth advantage and grow faster than vulnerable bacteria.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Gullberg E, Cao S, Berg OG, Ilbäck C, Sandegren L, Hughes D, Andersson DI | title = Selection of resistant bacteria at very low antibiotic concentrations | journal = PLoS Pathogens | volume = 7 | issue = 7 | pages = e1002158 | date = July 2011 | pmid = 21811410 | pmc = 3141051 | doi = 10.1371/journal.ppat.1002158 }}&lt;/ref&gt; With resistance to antibiotics becoming more common there is greater need for alternative treatments. Calls for new antibiotic therapies have been issued, but new drug development is becoming rarer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Cassir N, Rolain JM, Brouqui P | title = A new strategy to fight antimicrobial resistance: the revival of old antibiotics | journal = Frontiers in Microbiology | volume = 5 | pages = 551 | date = 2014 | pmid = 25368610 | pmc = 4202707 | doi = 10.3389/fmicb.2014.00551 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Antimicrobial resistance is increasing globally because of greater access to antibiotic drugs in [[developing countries]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite newspaper|url=https://www.theguardian.com/science/2018/mar/26/calls-to-rein-in-antibiotic-use-after-study-shows-65-increase-worldwide|title=Calls to rein in antibiotic use after study shows 65% increase worldwide|last=Sample|first=Ian|name-list-format=vanc|date=26 March 2018|journal=The Guardian|access-date=28 March 2018|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180408063812/https://www.theguardian.com/science/2018/mar/26/calls-to-rein-in-antibiotic-use-after-study-shows-65-increase-worldwide|archive-date=8 April 2018|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; Estimates are that 700,000 to several million deaths result per year.&lt;ref name=&quot;WHO 2014&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.who.int/drugresistance/documents/surveillancereport/en/|title=Antimicrobial resistance: global report on surveillance 2014|author=WHO|date=April 2014|work=WHO|publisher=WHO|access-date=9 May 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150515101620/http://www.who.int/drugresistance/documents/surveillancereport/en/|archive-date=15 May 2015|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AMR2016&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://amr-review.org/sites/default/files/160525_Final%20paper_with%20cover.pdf|title=TACKLING DRUG-RESISTANT INFECTIONS GLOBALLY: FINAL REPORT AND RECOMMENDATIONS|last=O'neill|first=Jim|name-list-format=vanc|date=May 2016|website=amr-review.org/|access-date=10 November 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171114170946/https://amr-review.org/sites/default/files/160525_Final%20paper_with%20cover.pdf|archive-date=14 November 2017|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; Each year in the United States, at least 2.8 million people become infected with bacteria that are resistant to antibiotics and at least 35,000 people die as a result.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=The biggest antibiotic-resistant threats in the U.S. |url=https://www.cdc.gov/drugresistance/biggest-threats.html |website=Centers for Disease Control and Prevention |accessdate=15 November 2019 |language=en-us |date=6 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; There are public calls for global collective action to address the threat that include proposals for [[international treaty|international treaties]] on antimicrobial resistance.&lt;ref name=Hoffman /&gt; Worldwide antibiotic resistance is not completely identified, but poorer countries with weaker healthcare systems are more affected.&lt;ref name=&quot;Swedish&quot;/&gt;
{{TOC limit|3}}

==Definition==
[[File:WhatIsDrugResistance.gif|thumb|300x300px|Diagram showing the difference between non-resistant bacteria and drug resistant bacteria. Non-resistant bacteria multiply, and upon drug treatment, the bacteria die. Drug resistant bacteria multiply as well, but upon drug treatment, the bacteria continue to spread.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = What is Drug Resistance?|url = https://www.niaid.nih.gov/topics/antimicrobialResistance/Understanding/Pages/drugResistanceDefinition.aspx|website = www.niaid.nih.gov|access-date = 26 July 2015|archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20150727153042/http://www.niaid.nih.gov/topics/antimicrobialResistance/Understanding/Pages/drugResistanceDefinition.aspx|archive-date = 27 July 2015|url-status = live|df = dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;|alt=Diagram showing difference between non-resistance bacteria and drug resistant bacteria]]
The WHO defines antimicrobial resistance as a microorganism's resistance to an antimicrobial drug that was once able to treat an infection by that microorganism.&lt;ref name=WHO2014/&gt;
A person cannot become resistant to antibiotics. Resistance is a property of the microbe, not a person or other organism infected by a microbe.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.cdc.gov/getsmart/antibiotic-use/antibiotic-resistance-faqs.html#antibiotic-resistance-concerns|title=CDC: Get Smart: Know When Antibiotics Work|publisher=Cdc.gov|access-date=12 June 2013|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150429180658/http://www.cdc.gov/getsmart/antibiotic-use/antibiotic-resistance-faqs.html#antibiotic-resistance-concerns|archive-date=29 April 2015|url-status=live|date=29 May 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Antibiotic resistance is a subset of antimicrobial resistance.&amp;nbsp; This more specified resistance is linked to pathogenic bacteria and thus broken down into two further subsets, microbiological and clinical. Resistance linked microbiologically is the most common and occurs from genes, mutated or inherited, that allow the bacteria to resist the mechanism associated with certain antibiotics.&amp;nbsp; Clinical resistance is shown through the failure of many therapeutic techniques where the bacteria that are normally susceptible to a treatment become resistant after surviving the outcome of the treatment. In both cases of acquired resistance, the bacteria can pass the genetic catalyst for resistance through conjugation, transduction, or transformation.&amp;nbsp; This allows the resistance to spread across the same pathogen or even similar bacterial pathogens.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Macnaughton|first=Emily|last2=MacGowan|first2=Alasdair|date=1 October 2017|title=Antibiotic resistance|url=https://www.medicinejournal.co.uk/article/S1357-3039(17)30188-3/abstract|journal=Medicine|language=English|volume=45|issue=10|pages=622–628|doi=10.1016/j.mpmed.2017.07.006|issn=1357-3039}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Overview ==
A [[World Health Organization]] (WHO) report released April 2014 stated, &quot;this serious threat is no longer a prediction for the future, it is happening right now in every region of the world and has the potential to affect anyone, of any age, in any country. Antibiotic resistance—when bacteria change so antibiotics no longer work in people who need them to treat infections—is now a major threat to public health.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;who.int&quot;&gt;[http://www.who.int/mediacentre/news/releases/2014/amr-report/en/ &quot;WHO's first global report on antibiotic resistance reveals serious, worldwide threat to public health&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140502044726/http://www.who.int/mediacentre/news/releases/2014/amr-report/en/ |date=2 May 2014 }} Retrieved 2 May 2014&lt;/ref&gt; The [[European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control]] calculated that in 2015 there were 671,689 infections in the EU and European Economic Area caused by antibiotic-resistant bacteria, resulting in 33,110 deaths.  Most were acquired in healthcare settings.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Antibiotic-resistant bacteria responsible for over 33,000 deaths in Europe in 2015, study finds |url=https://www.pharmaceutical-journal.com/20205705.article |accessdate=16 December 2018 |publisher=Pharmaceutical Journal |date=7 November 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Causes==
[[File:CDCinfographicANTIBIORESISTANCE.png|thumb|How antibiotic resistance evolves and spreads|390x390px|alt=Infographic on how antibiotic resistance evolves and spreads]]
Bacteria with resistance to antibiotics predate medical use of antibiotics by humans.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = D'Costa VM, King CE, Kalan L, Morar M, Sung WW, Schwarz C, Froese D, Zazula G, Calmels F, Debruyne R, Golding GB, Poinar HN, Wright GD | title = Antibiotic resistance is ancient | journal = Nature | volume = 477 | issue = 7365 | pages = 457–61 | date = August 2011 | pmid = 21881561 | doi = 10.1038/nature10388 | bibcode = 2011Natur.477..457D }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Caldwell|Lindberg|2011}} However, widespread antibiotic use has made more bacteria resistant through the process of [[evolutionary pressure]].{{sfn|Hawkey|Jones|2009|pp=i3-i10}}&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Goossens H, Ferech M, Vander Stichele R, Elseviers M | title = Outpatient antibiotic use in Europe and association with resistance: a cross-national database study | journal = Lancet | volume = 365 | issue = 9459 | pages = 579–87 | year = 2005 | pmid = 15708101 | doi = 10.1016/S0140-6736(05)17907-0 }}{{subscription required}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Reasons for the widespread use of antibiotics in human medicine include:
* increasing global availability over time since the 1950s
* uncontrolled sale in many low or middle income countries, where they can be obtained over the counter without a prescription, potentially resulting in antibiotics being used when not indicated.&lt;ref name=lid13&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Laxminarayan R, Duse A, Wattal C, Zaidi AK, Wertheim HF, Sumpradit N, Vlieghe E, Hara GL, Gould IM, Goossens H, Greko C, So AD, Bigdeli M, Tomson G, Woodhouse W, Ombaka E, Peralta AQ, Qamar FN, Mir F, Kariuki S, Bhutta ZA, Coates A, Bergstrom R, Wright GD, Brown ED, Cars O | title = Antibiotic resistance-the need for global solutions | journal = The Lancet. Infectious Diseases | volume = 13 | issue = 12 | pages = 1057–98 | date = December 2013 | pmid = 24252483 | doi = 10.1016/S1473-3099(13)70318-9 | hdl = 10161/8996 | url = https://dukespace.lib.duke.edu/dspace/bitstream/10161/8996/1/CarsEtAl_AntibioticResistance-TheNeedforGlobalSolutions_LancetInfectiousDiseases_2013%5b1%5d.pdf }} As [http://www.princeton.edu/pei/news/S1473309913703189-main.pdf PDF] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150924124909/http://www.princeton.edu/pei/news/S1473309913703189-main.pdf |date=24 September 2015 }}.&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|1060}} This may result in emergence of resistance in any remaining bacteria.

Other causes include:
* [[Antibiotic use in livestock]] feed at low doses for growth promotion is an accepted practice in many industrialized countries and is known to lead to increased levels of resistance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Ferber D | title = Antibiotic resistance. Livestock feed ban preserves drugs' power | journal = Science | volume = 295 | issue = 5552 | pages = 27–8 | date = January 2002 | pmid = 11778017 | doi = 10.1126/science.295.5552.27a | ref = harv }}{{subscription required}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;mathew&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Mathew AG, Cissell R, Liamthong S | title = Antibiotic resistance in bacteria associated with food animals: a United States perspective of livestock production | journal = Foodborne Pathogens and Disease | volume = 4 | issue = 2 | pages = 115–33 | year = 2007 | pmid = 17600481 | doi = 10.1089/fpd.2006.0066 | ref = harv | url = https://semanticscholar.org/paper/3117944806150f47ae8acd12b99538f1d69bc1b2 }}&lt;/ref&gt; 
* Releasing large quantities of antibiotics into the environment during pharmaceutical manufacturing through inadequate [[wastewater treatment]] increases the risk that antibiotic-resistant strains will develop and spread.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Pharmaceuticals Sold in Sweden Cause Serious Environmental Harm in India, Research Shows|url=https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2009/02/090205083522.htm|access-date=29 January 2015|work=ScienceDaily|publisher=ScienceDaily, LLC|date=7 February 2009|quote=We estimated that the[water] treatment plant released 45 kilograms of the antibiotic ciprofloxacin in one day, which is equivalent to five times the daily consumption of Sweden&quot;,|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150204053640/http://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2009/02/090205083522.htm|archive-date=4 February 2015|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Joakim Larsson DG, Fick J | title = Transparency throughout the production chain—a way to reduce pollution from the manufacturing of pharmaceuticals? | journal = Regulatory Toxicology and Pharmacology | volume = 53 | issue = 3 | pages = 161–3 | date = April 2009 | pmid = 19545507 | doi = 10.1016/j.yrtph.2009.01.008 | ref = harv }}{{subscription required}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
* It is uncertain whether antibacterials in soaps and other products contribute to antibiotic resistance, but [[antibacterial soap]]s are discouraged for other reasons.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=CDC |url=https://www.cdc.gov/getsmart/antibiotic-use/antibiotic-resistance-faqs.html#antibacterial-products |trans-title=Are antibacterial-containing products (soaps, household cleaners, etc.) better for preventing the spread of infection? Does their use add to the problem of resistance? |title=Antibiotic Resistance Questions and Answers |publisher=Centers for Disease Control and Prevention |location=Atlanta, Georgia, USA. |access-date=25 February 2015 |ref=harv |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150429180658/http://www.cdc.gov/getsmart/antibiotic-use/antibiotic-resistance-faqs.html#antibacterial-products |archive-date=29 April 2015 |url-status=live  |date=29 May 2018 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Aiello AE, Larson EL, Levy SB | title = Consumer antibacterial soaps: effective or just risky? | journal = Clinical Infectious Diseases | volume = 45 Suppl 2 | issue = Supplement 2 | pages = S137–47 | date = September 2007 | pmid = 17683018 | doi = 10.1086/519255 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Antiseptics create AMR to antibiotics and other antiseptics:

Antiseptics appear to activate tolerance mechanisms in bacteria, which offer them protection against a range of antiseptics as well as antibiotics. Antiseptics are used for cleaning in hospitals and in many wound care dressings. These findings may explain the increase in treatment-resistant hospital infections.

Exposure to low doses of the antiseptic octenidine allowed several different strains of ''Pseudomonas aeruginosa'' to develop cross-tolerance to other antiseptics and to several different antibiotics.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Shepherd MJ, Moore G, Wand ME, Sutton JM, Bock LJ | title = Pseudomonas aeruginosa adapts to octenidine in the laboratory and a simulated clinical setting, leading to increased tolerance to chlorhexidine and other biocides | journal = The Journal of Hospital Infection | volume = 100 | issue = 3 | pages = e23–e29 | date = November 2018 | pmid = 29614247 | doi = 10.1016/j.jhin.2018.03.037 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The level of tolerance was substantial, i.e. in several cases a 32-fold increase in concentrations of the antiseptic was required to obtain the same antimicrobial effect. Also, this increased resistance was permanent. The same group also reported&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Wand ME, Bock LJ, Bonney LC, Sutton JM | title = Mechanisms of Increased Resistance to Chlorhexidine and Cross-Resistance to Colistin following Exposure of Klebsiella pneumoniae Clinical Isolates to Chlorhexidine | journal = Antimicrobial Agents and Chemotherapy | volume = 61 | issue = 1 | date = January 2017 | pmid = 27799211 | pmc = 5192135 | doi = 10.1128/AAC.01162-16 }}&lt;/ref&gt; that ''Klebsiella pneumoniae'' was able to develop tolerance to chlorhexidine and that 5 out of 6 strains showed cross-resistance to the last-resort antibiotic, colistin.

=== Clinical significance ===
[[File:AntimcrresUKreview2.jpg|thumb|Deaths per year (estimated for 2050) attributable to antimicrobial resistance compared to other major causes of death.&lt;ref name=AMR2016/&gt;|300x300px|alt=Infographic showing deaths attributable to antimicrobial resistance]]
Increasing bacterial resistance is linked with the volume of antibiotic prescribed, as well as missing doses when taking antibiotics.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pechère JC 2001 S170–3&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Pechère JC | title = Patients' interviews and misuse of antibiotics | journal = Clinical Infectious Diseases | volume = 33 Suppl 3 | pages = S170–3 | date = September 2001 | pmid = 11524715 | doi = 10.1086/321844 | quote = Noncompliance may have an impact on antibiotic resistance ... Type A consists in shorter than prescribed courses. By reducing the antibiotic pressure, provided that the daily doses are otherwise respected, one may see a theoretical advantage ... Type B noncompliance reduces the number of daily doses ... indicate that such underdosing may promote the selection of resistance | citeseerx = 10.1.1.560.8090 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Inappropriate prescribing of antibiotics has been attributed to a number of causes, such as patients insisting on antibiotics and physicians prescribing them as they do not have time to explain why they are not necessary. Another cause can be physicians not knowing when to prescribe antibiotics or being overly cautious for medical or legal reasons.&lt;ref name=Arn2005&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Arnold SR, Straus SE | title = Interventions to improve antibiotic prescribing practices in ambulatory care | journal = The Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews | issue = 4 | pages = CD003539 | date = October 2005 | pmid = 16235325 | doi = 10.1002/14651858.CD003539.pub2 | ref = harv | editor1-first = Sandra R | editor1-last = Arnold }}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, 70 to 80 percent of [[diarrhea]] is caused by viral pathogens, for which antibiotics are not effective. But nevertheless, around 40 percent of these cases are attempted to be treated with antibiotics.&lt;ref name=&quot;Araya&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://amr-review.org/sites/default/files/LSE%20AMR%20Capstone.pdf|title=The Impact of Water and Sanitation on Diarrhoeal Disease Burden and Over-Consumption of Anitbiotics.|last=Araya|first=Pablo|date=May 2016|access-date=12 November 2017|name-list-format=vanc|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171001195326/https://amr-review.org/sites/default/files/LSE%20AMR%20Capstone.pdf|archive-date=1 October 2017|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; In some areas even over 80 percent of such cases are attempted to be treated with antibiotics.&lt;ref name=&quot;Araya&quot; /&gt; Also, hospitals are often unable to identify the causative organism(s) in time to treat patients presenting with rapidly progressing sepsis or other severe infections, resulting in the overuse of broad-spectrum antibiotics.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Frieri|first=Marianne|last2=Kumar|first2=Krishan|last3=Boutin|first3=Anthony|date=1 July 2017|title=Antibiotic resistance|journal=Journal of Infection and Public Health|volume=10|issue=4|pages=369–378|doi=10.1016/j.jiph.2016.08.007|pmid=27616769|issn=1876-0341}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Lower antibiotic concentration contributes to the increase of AMR by introducing more mutations that support bacterial growth in higher antibiotic concentration. For example, sub-inhibitory concentration have induced genetic mutation in bacteria such as ''Pseudomonas aeruginosa'' and ''Bacteroides fragilis''.&lt;ref&gt;Ventola, C. Lee. &quot;The antibiotic resistance crisis: part 1: causes and threats.&quot; Pharmacy and Therapeutics 40.4 (2015): 277.&lt;/ref&gt;

Up to half of antibiotics used in humans are unnecessary and inappropriate.&lt;ref name=&quot;About Antimicrobial Resistance&quot;/&gt; For example, a third of people believe that antibiotics are effective for the [[common cold]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = McNulty CA, Boyle P, Nichols T, Clappison P, Davey P | title = The public's attitudes to and compliance with antibiotics | journal = The Journal of Antimicrobial Chemotherapy | volume = 60 Suppl 1 | pages = i63–8 | date = August 2007 | pmid = 17656386 | doi = 10.1093/jac/dkm161 | ref = harv }}{{subscription required}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the common cold is the most common reason antibiotics are prescribed even though antibiotics are useless against viruses.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | editor-first1 = Ronald | editor-last1 = Eccles | editor-first2 = Olaf | editor-last2 = Weber | name-list-format = vanc | title = Common cold | year = 2009 | publisher = Birkhäuser | location = Basel | isbn = 978-3-7643-9894-1 | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=rRIdiGE42IEC | edition = Online | page = 234}}&lt;/ref&gt; A single regimen of antibiotics even in compliant individuals leads to a greater risk of resistant organisms to that antibiotic in the person for a month to possibly a year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Costelloe C, Metcalfe C, Lovering A, Mant D, Hay AD | title = Effect of antibiotic prescribing in primary care on antimicrobial resistance in individual patients: systematic review and meta-analysis | journal = BMJ | volume = 340 | pages = c2096 | date = May 2010 | pmid = 20483949 | doi = 10.1136/bmj.c2096 }}{{subscription required}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Antimicrobial Resistance: Tackling a Crises for the Health and Welfare of Nations: 2014|date=11 December 2014|location=London|url=https://amr-review.org/sites/default/files/AMR%20Review%20Paper%20-%20Tackling%20a%20crisis%20for%20the%20health%20and%20wealth%20of%20nations_1.pdf|access-date=24 April 2018|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180503063119/https://amr-review.org/sites/default/files/AMR%20Review%20Paper%20-%20Tackling%20a%20crisis%20for%20the%20health%20and%20wealth%20of%20nations_1.pdf|archive-date=3 May 2018|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Antibiotic resistance increases with duration of treatment. Therefore, as long as an effective minimum is kept, shorter courses of antibiotics are likely to decrease rates of resistance, reduce cost, and have better outcomes with fewer complications.&lt;ref name=NPS2013/&gt; Short course regimens exist for [[community-acquired pneumonia]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Li JZ, Winston LG, Moore DH, Bent S | title = Efficacy of short-course antibiotic regimens for community-acquired pneumonia: a meta-analysis | journal = The American Journal of Medicine | volume = 120 | issue = 9 | pages = 783–90 | date = September 2007 | pmid = 17765048 | doi = 10.1016/j.amjmed.2007.04.023 | ref = harv }}{{subscription required}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[spontaneous bacterial peritonitis]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Runyon BA, McHutchison JG, Antillon MR, Akriviadis EA, Montano AA | title = Short-course versus long-course antibiotic treatment of spontaneous bacterial peritonitis. A randomized controlled study of 100 patients | journal = Gastroenterology | volume = 100 | issue = 6 | pages = 1737–42 | date = June 1991 | pmid = 2019378 | doi = 10.1016/0016-5085(91)90677-D }}{{subscription required}}&lt;/ref&gt; suspected lung infections in intense care wards,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Singh N, Rogers P, Atwood CW, Wagener MM, Yu VL | title = Short-course empiric antibiotic therapy for patients with pulmonary infiltrates in the intensive care unit. A proposed solution for indiscriminate antibiotic prescription | journal = American Journal of Respiratory and Critical Care Medicine | volume = 162 | issue = 2 Pt 1 | pages = 505–11 | date = August 2000 | pmid = 10934078 | doi = 10.1164/ajrccm.162.2.9909095 | url = https://semanticscholar.org/paper/ec4c9cfcec69ca594340ea44ef3bc48df42d7dbf }}{{subscription required}}&lt;/ref&gt; so-called [[acute abdomen]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Gleisner AL, Argenta R, Pimentel M, Simon TK, Jungblut CF, Petteffi L, de Souza RM, Sauerssig M, Kruel CD, Machado AR | title = Infective complications according to duration of antibiotic treatment in acute abdomen | journal = International Journal of Infectious Diseases | volume = 8 | issue = 3 | pages = 155–62 | date = May 2004 | pmid = 15109590 | doi = 10.1016/j.ijid.2003.06.003 }}{{subscription required}}&lt;/ref&gt; middle ear infections, sinusitis and throat infections,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Pichichero ME, Cohen R | title = Shortened course of antibiotic therapy for acute otitis media, sinusitis and tonsillopharyngitis | journal = The Pediatric Infectious Disease Journal | volume = 16 | issue = 7 | pages = 680–95 | date = July 1997 | pmid = 9239773 | doi = 10.1097/00006454-199707000-00011 }}{{subscription required}}&lt;/ref&gt; and penetrating gut injuries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Dellinger EP, Wertz MJ, Lennard ES, Oreskovich MR | title = Efficacy of short-course antibiotic prophylaxis after penetrating intestinal injury. A prospective randomized trial | journal = Archives of Surgery | volume = 121 | issue = 1 | pages = 23–30 | date = January 1986 | pmid = 3942496 | doi = 10.1001/archsurg.1986.01400010029002 }}{{subscription required}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Perez-Gorricho B, Ripoll M | title = Does short-course antibiotic therapy better meet patient expectations? | journal = International Journal of Antimicrobial Agents | volume = 21 | issue = 3 | pages = 222–8 | date = March 2003 | pmid = 12636982 | doi = 10.1016/S0924-8579(02)00360-6 }}{{subscription required}}&lt;/ref&gt; In some situations a short course may not cure the infection as well as a long course.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Keren R, Chan E | title = A meta-analysis of randomized, controlled trials comparing short- and long-course antibiotic therapy for urinary tract infections in children | journal = Pediatrics | volume = 109 | issue = 5 | pages = E70–0 | date = May 2002 | pmid = 11986476 | doi = 10.1542/peds.109.5.e70 }}{{subscription required}}&lt;/ref&gt; A [[BMJ]] editorial recommended that antibiotics can often be safely stopped 72&amp;nbsp;hours after symptoms resolve.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = McCormack J, Allan GM | title = A prescription for improving antibiotic prescribing in primary care | journal = BMJ | volume = 344 | pages = d7955 | date = February 2012 | pmid = 22302779 | doi = 10.1136/bmj.d7955 }}{{subscription required}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Because individuals may feel better before the infection is eradicated, doctors must provide instructions to them so they know when it is safe to stop taking a prescription. Some researchers advocate doctors' using a very short course of antibiotics, reevaluating the patient after a few days, and stopping treatment if there are no clinical signs of infection.&lt;ref&gt;Marc Bonten, MD; Eijkman-Winkler Institute for Medical Microbiology, Utrecht, the Netherland | [http://hicsigwiki.asid.net.au/images/4/41/Should_you_stop_an_antibiotic_course_early_if_you_feel_better_R._Everts.pdf Infectious Diseases, and Inflammation] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130517042502/http://hicsigwiki.asid.net.au/images/4/41/Should_you_stop_an_antibiotic_course_early_if_you_feel_better_R._Everts.pdf |date=17 May 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Certain [[antibiotic classes]] result in resistance more than others. Increased rates of MRSA infections are seen when using [[Glycopeptide antibiotic|glycopeptides]], [[cephalosporin]]s, and [[quinolone antibiotic]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Tacconelli E, De Angelis G, Cataldo MA, Pozzi E, Cauda R | title = Does antibiotic exposure increase the risk of methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus (MRSA) isolation? A systematic review and meta-analysis | journal = The Journal of Antimicrobial Chemotherapy | volume = 61 | issue = 1 | pages = 26–38 | date = January 2008 | pmid = 17986491 | doi = 10.1093/jac/dkm416 | ref = harv }}{{subscription required}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Muto CA, Jernigan JA, Ostrowsky BE, Richet HM, Jarvis WR, Boyce JM, Farr BM | title = SHEA guideline for preventing nosocomial transmission of multidrug-resistant strains of Staphylococcus aureus and enterococcus | journal = Infection Control and Hospital Epidemiology | volume = 24 | issue = 5 | pages = 362–86 | date = May 2003 | pmid = 12785411 | doi = 10.1086/502213 | url = http://www.shea-online.org/Assets/files/position_papers/SHEA_MRSA_VRE.pdf | ref = harv | access-date = 24 October 2017 | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20160418051055/http://www.shea-online.org/Assets/files/position_papers/SHEA_MRSA_VRE.pdf | archive-date = 18 April 2016 | url-status = dead | df = dmy-all | citeseerx = 10.1.1.575.8929 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Cephalosporins, and particularly quinolones and [[clindamycin]], are more likely to produce colonisation with [[Clostridium difficile (bacteria)|''Clostridium difficile'']].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |first= Ralf-Peter |last=Vonberg | name-list-format = vanc |title=Clostridium difficile: a challenge for hospitals |url=http://www.ihe-online.com/feature-articles/clostridium-difficile-a-challenge-for-hospitals/trackback/1/index.html |work=European Center for Disease Prevention and Control |publisher=IHE |location=Institute for Medical Microbiology and Hospital Epidemiology |access-date=27 July 2009 |ref=harv |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090611151535/http://www.ihe-online.com/feature-articles/clostridium-difficile-a-challenge-for-hospitals/trackback/1/index.html |archive-date=11 June 2009 |url-status=dead  }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Kuijper EJ, van Dissel JT, Wilcox MH | title = Clostridium difficile: changing epidemiology and new treatment options | journal = Current Opinion in Infectious Diseases | volume = 20 | issue = 4 | pages = 376–83 | date = August 2007 | pmid = 17609596 | doi = 10.1097/QCO.0b013e32818be71d | ref = harv }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Factors within the intensive care unit setting such as mechanical ventilation and multiple underlying diseases also appear to contribute to bacterial resistance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Thomas JK, Forrest A, Bhavnani SM, Hyatt JM, Cheng A, Ballow CH, Schentag JJ | title = Pharmacodynamic evaluation of factors associated with the development of bacterial resistance in acutely ill patients during therapy | journal = Antimicrobial Agents and Chemotherapy | volume = 42 | issue = 3 | pages = 521–7 | date = March 1998 | pmid = 9517926 | pmc = 105492 | ref = harv | doi = 10.1128/AAC.42.3.521 }}{{subscription required}}&lt;/ref&gt; Poor hand [[hygiene]] by hospital staff has been associated with the spread of resistant organisms.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Girou E, Legrand P, Soing-Altrach S, Lemire A, Poulain C, Allaire A, Tkoub-Scheirlinck L, Chai SH, Dupeyron C, Loche CM | title = Association between hand hygiene compliance and methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus prevalence in a French rehabilitation hospital | journal = Infection Control and Hospital Epidemiology | volume = 27 | issue = 10 | pages = 1128–30 | date = October 2006 | pmid = 17006822 | doi = 10.1086/507967 | ref = harv }}{{subscription required}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Counterfeit medications]] may contain sub-therapeutic concentrations of antibiotics, designed to reduce the chance of detection, and this by definition, increases antimicrobial resistance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Fake drugs: the global industry putting your life at risk |url=https://mosaicscience.com/story/fake-drugs-global-antibiotics-amr-counterfeit-meds/ |accessdate=13 December 2018 |publisher=Mosaic |date=30 October 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Veterinary medicine===
{{main|Antibiotic use in livestock}}
[[File:Ar-infographic-950px.jpg|thumb|300px|All animals carry bacteria in their intestines. Antibiotics are given to animals. Antibiotics kill most bacteria. But resistant bacteria survive and multiply.|alt=Infographics showing antibiotic resistance from the farm to the table]]
The [[World Health Organization]] concluded that inappropriate use of antibiotics in animal husbandry is an underlying contributor to the emergence and spread of antibiotic-resistant germs, and that the use of antibiotics as growth promoters in animal feeds should be restricted.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/antibiotic-resistance/en/|title=Antibiotic resistance|website=World Health Organization|access-date=21 April 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160420213223/http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/antibiotic-resistance/en/|archive-date=20 April 2016|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[World Organisation for Animal Health]] has added to the Terrestrial Animal Health Code a series of guidelines with recommendations to its members for the creation and harmonization of national antimicrobial resistance surveillance and monitoring programs,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Access online: OIE – World Organisation for Animal Health|chapter-url = http://www.oie.int/index.php?id=169&amp;L=0&amp;htmfile=chapitre_1.6.7.htm|chapter = 1.6.7|website = www.oie.int|access-date = 14 November 2015|archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20131203002321/http://www.oie.int/index.php?id=169&amp;L=0&amp;htmfile=chapitre_1.6.7.htm|archive-date = 3 December 2013|url-status = live|df = dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; monitoring of the quantities of antibiotics used in animal husbandry,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Access online: OIE – World Organisation for Animal Health|chapter-url = http://www.oie.int/index.php?id=169&amp;L=0&amp;htmfile=chapitre_1.6.8.htm|chapter = 1.6.8|website = www.oie.int|access-date = 14 November 2015|archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20131203002040/http://www.oie.int/index.php?id=169&amp;L=0&amp;htmfile=chapitre_1.6.8.htm|archive-date = 3 December 2013|url-status = live|df = dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; and recommendations to ensure the proper and prudent use of antibiotic substances. Another guideline is to implement methodologies that help to establish associated risk factors and assess the risk of antibiotic resistance.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Access online: OIE – World Organisation for Animal Health|chapter-url = http://www.oie.int/index.php?id=169&amp;L=0&amp;htmfile=chapitre_1.6.9.htm|chapter = 1.6.9|website = www.oie.int|access-date = 14 November 2015|archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20131203001913/http://www.oie.int/index.php?id=169&amp;L=0&amp;htmfile=chapitre_1.6.9.htm|archive-date = 3 December 2013|url-status = live|df = dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Natural occurrence===

Naturally occurring antibiotic resistance is common.&lt;ref name=Wright10&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Wright GD | title = Antibiotic resistance in the environment: a link to the clinic? | journal = Current Opinion in Microbiology | volume = 13 | issue = 5 | pages = 589–94 | date = October 2010 | pmid = 20850375 | doi = 10.1016/j.mib.2010.08.005 }}{{subscription required}}&lt;/ref&gt; Genes for resistance to antibiotics, like antibiotics themselves, are ancient.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = D'Costa VM, King CE, Kalan L, Morar M, Sung WW, Schwarz C, Froese D, Zazula G, Calmels F, Debruyne R, Golding GB, Poinar HN, Wright GD | title = Antibiotic resistance is ancient | journal = Nature | volume = 477 | issue = 7365 | pages = 457–61 | date = August 2011 | pmid = 21881561 | doi = 10.1038/nature10388 | ref = harv | bibcode = 2011Natur.477..457D }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Pawlowski AC, Wang W, Koteva K, Barton HA, McArthur AG, Wright GD | title = A diverse intrinsic antibiotic resistome from a cave bacterium | journal = Nature Communications | volume = 7 | pages = 13803 | date = December 2016 | pmid = 27929110 | pmc = 5155152 | doi = 10.1038/ncomms13803 | bibcode = 2016NatCo...713803P }}&lt;/ref&gt; The genes that confer resistance are known as the environmental [[resistome]].&lt;ref name=Wright10/&gt; These genes may be transferred from non-disease-causing bacteria to those that do cause disease, leading to clinically significant antibiotic resistance.&lt;ref name=Wright10/&gt;

In 1952 it was shown that penicillin-resistant bacteria existed before penicillin treatment;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://evolution.berkeley.edu/evolibrary/article/mutations_07|title=Mutations are random|publisher=University of California|access-date=14 August 2011|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120208025322/http://evolution.berkeley.edu/evolibrary/article/mutations_07|archive-date=8 February 2012|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; and also preexistent bacterial resistance to [[streptomycin]].&lt;ref&gt;Richard William Nelson. ''Darwin, Then and Now: The Most Amazing Story in the History of Science'', i Universe, 2009, p. 294&lt;/ref&gt; In 1962, the presence of [[penicillinase]] was detected in dormant [[endospore]]s of ''[[Bacillus licheniformis]]'', revived from dried soil on the roots of plants, preserved since 1689 in the [[British Museum]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |vauthors=Kiser JS, Gale GO, Kemp GA |chapter=3.2 Resistance to Antimicrobial Agents: Evolution of Drug Resistance |title=Advances in Applied Microbiology |chapterurl=https://books.google.com/books?id=cPKJd9hC3pMC&amp;pg=PA80 |date=1970 |publisher=Academic Press |isbn=978-0-08-056425-8 |volume=11 |pages=[https://archive.org/details/advancesinapplie0000unse_z3t0/page/80 80] |url-access=registration |url=https://archive.org/details/advancesinapplie0000unse_z3t0/page/80 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid4963324&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Pollock MR | title = Origin and function of penicillinase: a problem in biochemical evolution | journal = British Medical Journal | volume = 4 | issue = 5571 | pages = 71–7 | date = October 1967 | pmid = 4963324 | pmc = 1748446 | doi = 10.1136/bmj.4.5571.71 }}{{subscription required}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;penicillinase&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |title=Some bacteria choose to live in a pool of penicillin |journal=New Scientist |volume=54 |issue=799 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=F5Sf5nImY88C&amp;pg=PA546 |date=8 June 1972 |pages=546 |last1=Information |first1=Reed Business }}&lt;/ref&gt; Six [[Strain (biology)|strains]] of ''[[Clostridium]]'', found in the bowels of William Braine and John Hartnell (members of the [[Franklin Expedition]]) showed resistance to [[cefoxitin]] and [[clindamycin]].&lt;ref name=&quot;NS&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Siddal R | title = Ancient bacteria resitent to some antibiotics |journal=New Scientist |volume=121 |issue=1651 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=fA9tecLhj9wC&amp;pg=PA34 |date=11 February 1989 |page=34|bibcode=1989NewSc.121...34H }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Penicillinase may have emerged as a defense mechanism for bacteria in their [[habitat]]s, such as the case of penicillinase-rich ''[[Staphylococcus aureus]]'', living with penicillin-producing ''[[Trichophyton]]''; however, this may be circumstantial.&lt;ref name=&quot;penicillinase&quot; /&gt; Search for a penicillinase ancestor has focused on the class of [[protein]]s that must be ''a priori'' capable of specific combination with [[penicillin]].&lt;ref&gt;Pollock, p. 77&lt;/ref&gt; The resistance to cefoxitin and clindamycin in turn was attributed to Braine's and Hartnell's contact with microorganisms that naturally produce them or [[random mutation]] in the [[chromosome]]s of ''Clostridium'' strains.&lt;ref name=&quot;NS&quot; /&gt;

There is evidence that [[heavy metals]] and other pollutants may select for antibiotic-resistant bacteria, generating a constant source of them in small numbers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Seiler C, Berendonk TU | title = Heavy metal driven co-selection of antibiotic resistance in soil and water bodies impacted by agriculture and aquaculture | journal = Frontiers in Microbiology | volume = 3 | pages = 399 | date = 14 December 2012 | pmid = 23248620 | pmc = 3522115 | doi = 10.3389/fmicb.2012.00399 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Water pollution===
Antibiotic resistance is a growing problem among humans and wildlife in terrestrial or aquatic environments. In this respect, the spread of antibiotic resistance and contamination of the environment, especially through [[water pollution]] &quot;hot spots&quot; such as hospital [[wastewater]], untreated urban wastewater and also urban [[wastewater treatment plant]] effluent itself, is a growing and serious public health problem.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rizzo resistance&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Rizzo |first1=Luigi |title=Urban wastewater treatment plants as hotspots for antibiotic resistant bacteria and genes spread into the environment: A review |journal=Science of the Total Environment |date=March 2014 |volume=447 |pages=345–60 |doi=10.1016/j.scitotenv.2013.01.032 |pmid=23396083 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Novo Resistance&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Novo |first1=Ana |title=Antibiotic resistance, antimicrobial residues and bacterial community composition in urban wastewater |journal=Water Research |date=April 2013 |volume=47 |issue=5 |pages=1875–1887 |doi=10.1016/j.watres.2013.01.010 |pmid=23375783 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Levy SB | title = The 2000 Garrod lecture. Factors impacting on the problem of antibiotic resistance | journal = The Journal of Antimicrobial Chemotherapy | volume = 49 | issue = 1 | pages = 25–30 | date = January 2002 | pmid = 11751763 | doi = 10.1093/jac/49.1.25 | url = http://jac.oxfordjournals.org/content/49/1/25 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Marti E, Variatza E, Balcazar JL | title = The role of aquatic ecosystems as reservoirs of antibiotic resistance | journal = Trends in Microbiology | volume = 22 | issue = 1 | pages = 36–41 | date = January 2014 | pmid = 24289955 | doi = 10.1016/j.tim.2013.11.001 | df = dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Antibiotics have been polluting the environment since their introduction through [[human waste]] (medication, farming), animals, and the pharmaceutical industry.&lt;ref name=&quot;Martinez, J. L. 2012 pp. 151- 171&quot;&gt;Martinez, J. L., &amp; Olivares, J. (2012). 
Environmental Pollution By Antibiotic Resistance Genes. In P. L. Keen, &amp; M. H. Montforts, Antimicrobial Resistance in the Environment (pp. 151- 171). Hoboken, N.J.: John Wiley &amp; Sons.&lt;/ref&gt; The contribution of the pharmaceutical industry is so significant that parallels can be drawn between countries with highest rate of increasing antibiotic resistance and countries with largest footprint of pharmaceutical industry.{{original research inline|date=June 2019}} China, which contributes to nearly 40 percent of the world's active pharmaceutical ingredient (API) manufacturing,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.ft.com/content/38991820-8fc7-11e8-b639-7680cedcc421|title=Subscribe to read|website=Financial Times|language=en-GB|access-date=7 August 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; has seen a 22 per cent increase in rate of antimicrobial resistance in six years, compared to a 6 per cent increase in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Yezli S, Li H | title = Antibiotic resistance amongst healthcare-associated pathogens in China | journal = International Journal of Antimicrobial Agents | volume = 40 | issue = 5 | pages = 389–97 | date = November 2012 | pmid = 22999767 | doi = 10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2012.07.009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Along with antibiotic waste, resistant bacteria follow, thus introducing antibiotic-resistant bacteria into the environment. Already in 2011, mapping of sewage and water supply samples in [[New Delhi]] showed widespread and uncontrolled infection as indicated by the presence of NDM-1-positive enteric bacteria ([[New Delhi metallo-beta-lactamase 1]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;Walsh_2011&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Walsh TR, Weeks J, Livermore DM, Toleman MA | title = Dissemination of NDM-1 positive bacteria in the New Delhi environment and its implications for human health: an environmental point prevalence study | journal = The Lancet. Infectious Diseases | volume = 11 | issue = 5 | pages = 355–62 | date = May 2011 | pmid = 21478057 | doi = 10.1016/S1473-3099(11)70059-7 | url = https://zenodo.org/record/3423672 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

As bacteria replicate quickly, the resistant bacteria that enter water bodies through wastewater replicate their resistance genes as they continue to divide. In addition, bacteria carrying resistance genes have the ability to spread those genes to other species via [[horizontal gene transfer]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Lerminiaux NA, Cameron AD | title = Horizontal transfer of antibiotic resistance genes in clinical environments | journal = Canadian Journal of Microbiology | volume = 65 | issue = 1 | pages = 34–44 | date = January 2019 | pmid = 30248271 | doi = 10.1139/cjm-2018-0275 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | vauthors = Barlow M | chapter = What antimicrobial resistance has taught us about horizontal gene transfer | volume = 532 | pages = 397–411 | date = 2009 | pmid = 19271198 | doi = 10.1007/978-1-60327-853-9_23 | isbn = 978-1-60327-852-2 | series = Methods in Molecular Biology | title = Horizontal Gene Transfer }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Cairns J, Ruokolainen L, Hultman J, Tamminen M, Virta M, Hiltunen T | title = Ecology determines how low antibiotic concentration impacts community composition and horizontal transfer of resistance genes | journal = Communications Biology | volume = 1 | issue = 1 | pages = 35 | date = 19 April 2018 | pmid = 30271921 | doi = 10.1038/s42003-018-0041-7 | pmc = 6123812 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Therefore, even if the specific antibiotic is no longer introduced into the environment, antibiotic-resistance genes will persist through the bacteria that have since replicated without continuous exposure.&lt;ref name=&quot;Martinez, J. L. 2012 pp. 151- 171&quot; /&gt; Antibiotic resistance is widespread in marine vertebrates, and they may be important reservoirs of antibiotic-resistant bacteria in the [[Marine ecosystem|marine environment]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Rose JM, Gast RJ, Bogomolni A, Ellis JC, Lentell BJ, Touhey K, Moore M | title = Occurrence and patterns of antibiotic resistance in vertebrates off the Northeastern United States coast | journal = FEMS Microbiology Ecology | volume = 67 | issue = 3 | pages = 421–31 | date = March 2009 | pmid = 19187217 | pmc = 5444207 | doi = 10.1111/j.1574-6941.2009.00648.x }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Prevention==
[[File:Antibioticresistance diagram.png|thumb|350px|Mission Critical: Preventing Antibiotic Resistance (CDC report, 2014)|alt=Infographic from CDC report on preventing antibiotic resistance]]

There have been increasing public calls for global collective action to address the threat, including a proposal for international treaty on antimicrobial resistance. Further detail and attention is still needed in order to recognize and measure trends in resistance on the international level; the idea of a global tracking system has been suggested but implementation has yet to occur. A system of this nature would provide insight to areas of high resistance as well as information necessary for evaluation of programs and other changes made to fight or reverse antibiotic resistance.

===Duration of antibiotics===
Antibiotic treatment duration should be based on the infection and other health problems a person may have.&lt;ref name=NPS2013/&gt;&lt;!-- &quot;When optimising therapy for an infection consider the person’s immune status, the infecting agent and the focus of infection.&quot; --&gt; For many infections once a person has improved there is little evidence that stopping treatment causes more resistance.&lt;ref name=NPS2013/&gt;&lt;!--  &quot;There does not appear to be strong evidence to support the notion that stopping antibiotics before the end of the recommended treatment contributes to increasing resistance&quot; --&gt; Some therefore feel that stopping early may be reasonable in some cases.&lt;ref name=NPS2013/&gt;&lt;!--  &quot;Therefore, in selected cases, it may be appropriate to stop antibiotic therapy early.&quot; --&gt; Other infections, however, do require long courses regardless of whether a person feels better.&lt;ref name=NPS2013/&gt;&lt;!-- &quot;For some infections, such as Staphylococcus aureus bacteraemia, enterococcal endocarditis or tuberculosis, clear evidence favours prolonged treatment to prevent relapse&quot; --&gt;

===Monitoring and mapping===
There are multiple national and international monitoring programs for drug-resistant threats, including [[methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus|methicillin-resistant ''Staphylococcus aureus'']] (MRSA), [[Vancomycin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus|vancomycin-resistant ''S. aureus'']] (VRSA), [[Beta-lactamase|extended spectrum beta-lactamase]] (ESBL), [[Vancomycin-resistant Enterococcus|vancomycin-resistant ''Enterococcus'']] (VRE), [[Acinetobacter baumannii|multidrug-resistant ''A. baumannii'']] (MRAB).&lt;ref name=&quot;CDC2013&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.cdc.gov/drugresistance/biggest_threats.html|title=Biggest Threats – Antibiotic/Antimicrobial Resistance – CDC|website=www.cdc.gov|access-date=5 May 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170912115220/https://www.cdc.gov/drugresistance/biggest_threats.html|archive-date=12 September 2017|url-status=live|date=10 September 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

ResistanceOpen is an online global map of antimicrobial resistance developed by [[HealthMap]] which displays aggregated data on antimicrobial resistance from publicly available and user submitted data.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.healthmap.org/en/index.php|title=HealthMap Resistance|publisher=HealthMap.org Boston Children’s Hospital|access-date=15 November 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171115063743/http://www.healthmap.org/en/index.php|archive-date=15 November 2017|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Scales|first1=David|name-list-format=vanc|title=Mapping Antibiotic Resistance: Know The Germs in Your Neighborhood|url=http://commonhealth.wbur.org/2015/12/antibiotic-resistance-data|website=WBUR|publisher=National Public Radio|access-date=8 December 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20151208101609/http://commonhealth.wbur.org/2015/12/antibiotic-resistance-data|archive-date=8 December 2015|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; The website can display data for a 25-mile radius from a location. Users may submit data from [[antibiogram]]s for individual hospitals or laboratories. European data is from the EARS-Net (European Antimicrobial Resistance Surveillance Network), part of the [[European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control|ECDC]].

ResistanceMap is a website by the [[Center for Disease Dynamics, Economics &amp; Policy]] and provides data on antimicrobial resistance on a global level.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://resistancemap.cddep.org/About.php|title=ResistanceMap|publisher=Center for Disease Dynamics, Economics &amp; Policy|access-date=14 November 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171114202902/https://resistancemap.cddep.org/About.php|archive-date=14 November 2017|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Limiting antibiotic use ===
{{Further|Antibiotic misuse}}
{{Further|Antimicrobial spectrum}}

[[Antibiotic stewardship programme]]s appear useful in reducing rates of antibiotic resistance.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid28629876&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Baur D, Gladstone BP, Burkert F, Carrara E, Foschi F, Döbele S, Tacconelli E | title = Effect of antibiotic stewardship on the incidence of infection and colonisation with antibiotic-resistant bacteria and Clostridium difficile infection: a systematic review and meta-analysis | journal = The Lancet. Infectious Diseases | volume = 17 | issue = 9 | pages = 990–1001 | date = September 2017 | pmid = 28629876 | doi = 10.1016/S1473-3099(17)30325-0 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The antibiotic stewardship program will also provide pharmacists with the knowledge to educate patients that antibiotics will not work for a virus.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Gallagher|first=Jason C.|last2=Justo|first2=Julie Ann|last3=Chahine|first3=Elias B.|last4=Bookstaver|first4=P. Brandon|last5=Scheetz|first5=Marc|last6=Suda|first6=Katie J.|last7=Fehrenbacher|first7=Lynne|last8=Klinker|first8=Kenneth P|last9=MacDougall|first9=Conan|date=29 November 2017|title=Preventing the Post-Antibiotic Era: Training Future Pharmacists as Antimicrobial Stewards|journal=American Journal of Pharmaceutical Education|volume=82|issue=6|language=en|pages=ajpe6770|doi=10.5688/ajpe6770|pmid=30181677|issn=0002-9459|pmc=6116871}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Excessive antibiotic use has become one of the top contributors to the development of antibiotic resistance. Since the beginning of the antibiotic era, antibiotics have been used to treat a wide range of disease.&lt;ref name=Andersson2011&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Andersson DI, Hughes D | title = Persistence of antibiotic resistance in bacterial populations | journal = FEMS Microbiology Reviews | volume = 35 | issue = 5 | pages = 901–11 | date = September 2011 | pmid = 21707669 | doi = 10.1111/j.1574-6976.2011.00289.x }}&lt;/ref&gt; Overuse of antibiotics has become the primary cause of rising levels of antibiotic resistance. The main problem is that doctors are willing to prescribe antibiotics to ill-informed individuals who believe that antibiotics can cure nearly all illnesses, including viral infections like the common cold. In an analysis of drug prescriptions, 36% of individuals with a cold or an upper respiratory infection (both viral in origin) were given prescriptions for antibiotics.&lt;ref name=Gilberg2003&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Gilberg K, Laouri M, Wade S, Isonaka S | title = Analysis of medication use patterns:apparent overuse of antibiotics and underuse of prescription drugs for asthma, depression, and CHF | journal = Journal of Managed Care Pharmacy | volume = 9 | issue = 3 | pages = 232–7 | year = 2003 | pmid = 14613466 | doi = 10.18553/jmcp.2003.9.3.232 | url = https://semanticscholar.org/paper/0c1c17fdc75990c2cdfc0cf06e8515640a83437d }}&lt;/ref&gt; These prescriptions accomplished nothing other than increasing the risk of further evolution of antibiotic resistant bacteria.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Llor|first=Carl|last2=Bjerrum|first2=Lars|date=December 2014|title=Antimicrobial resistance: risk associated with antibiotic overuse and initiatives to reduce the problem|url=https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4232501/|journal=Therapeutic Advances in Drug Safety|volume=5|issue=6|pages=229–241|doi=10.1177/2042098614554919|issn=2042-0986|pmc=4232501|pmid=25436105}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== At the hospital level ====
[[Antimicrobial stewardship]] teams in hospitals are encouraging optimal use of antimicrobials.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Doron S, Davidson LE | title = Antimicrobial stewardship | journal = Mayo Clinic Proceedings | volume = 86 | issue = 11 | pages = 1113–23 | date = November 2011 | pmid = 22033257 | pmc = 3203003 | doi = 10.4065/mcp.2011.0358 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The goals of antimicrobial stewardship are to help practitioners pick the right drug at the right dose and duration of therapy while preventing misuse and minimizing the development of resistance. Stewardship may reduce the length of stay by an average of slightly over 1 day while not increasing the risk of death.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Davey P, Marwick CA, Scott CL, Charani E, McNeil K, Brown E, Gould IM, Ramsay CR, Michie S | title = Interventions to improve antibiotic prescribing practices for hospital inpatients | journal = The Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews | volume = 2 | pages = CD003543 | date = February 2017 | pmid = 28178770 | pmc = 6464541 | doi = 10.1002/14651858.cd003543.pub4 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== At the farming level ====
It is established that the use of antibiotics in animal husbandry can give rise to AMR resistances in bacteria found in food animals to the antibiotics being administered (through injections or medicated feeds).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Agga GE, Schmidt JW, Arthur TM | title = Effects of In-Feed Chlortetracycline Prophylaxis in Beef Cattle on Animal Health and Antimicrobial-Resistant Escherichia coli | journal = Applied and Environmental Microbiology | volume = 82 | issue = 24 | pages = 7197–7204 | date = December 2016 | pmid = 27736789 | pmc = 5118930 | doi = 10.1128/AEM.01928-16 }}&lt;/ref&gt; For this reason antimicrobials that are deemed &quot;not-clinically relevant&quot; are used in these practices.

Recent studies have shown that the prophylactic use of &quot;non-priority&quot; or &quot;non-clinically relevant&quot; antimicrobials in feeds can potentially, under certain conditions, lead to co-selection of environmental AMR bacteria with resistance to medically important antibiotics.&lt;ref name=&quot;Brown EE 2019&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Brown EE, Cooper A, Carrillo C, Blais B | title = Selection of Multidrug-Resistant Bacteria in Medicated Animal Feeds | language = English | journal = Frontiers in Microbiology | volume = 10 | pages = 456 | date = 2019 | pmid = 30894847 | pmc = 6414793 | doi = 10.3389/fmicb.2019.00456 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The possibility for co-selection of AMR resistances in the food chain pipeline may have far-reaching implications for human health.&lt;ref name=&quot;Brown EE 2019&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Marshall BM, Levy SB | title = Food animals and antimicrobials: impacts on human health | journal = Clinical Microbiology Reviews | volume = 24 | issue = 4 | pages = 718–33 | date = October 2011 | pmid = 21976606 | pmc = 3194830 | doi = 10.1128/CMR.00002-11 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== At the level of GP ====
Given the volume of care provided in primary care (General Practice), recent strategies have focused on reducing unnecessary antibiotic prescribing in this setting. Simple interventions, such as written information explaining the futility of antibiotics for common infections such as upper respiratory tract infections, have been shown to reduce antibiotic prescribing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = O'Sullivan JW, Harvey RT, Glasziou PP, McCullough A | title = Written information for patients (or parents of child patients) to reduce the use of antibiotics for acute upper respiratory tract infections in primary care | journal = The Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews | volume = 11 | pages = CD011360 | date = November 2016 | pmid = 27886368 | pmc = 6464519 | doi = 10.1002/14651858.CD011360.pub2 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The prescriber should closely adhere to the five rights of drug administration: the right patient, the right drug, the right dose, the right route, and the right time.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.ihi.org/resources/pages/improvementstories/fiverightsofmedicationadministration.aspx|title=The Five Rights of Medication Administration|website=www.ihi.org|access-date=30 October 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20151024101457/http://www.ihi.org/resources/pages/improvementstories/fiverightsofmedicationadministration.aspx|archive-date=24 October 2015|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Cultures should be taken before treatment when indicated and treatment potentially changed based on the susceptibility report.&lt;ref name=&quot;CDC Mission&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Leekha S, Terrell CL, Edson RS | title = General principles of antimicrobial therapy | journal = Mayo Clinic Proceedings | volume = 86 | issue = 2 | pages = 156–67 | date = February 2011 | pmid = 21282489 | pmc = 3031442 | doi = 10.4065/mcp.2010.0639 | url = http://www.mayoclinicproceedings.org/article/S0025-6196(11)60140-7/pdf }}&lt;/ref&gt;

About a third of antibiotic prescriptions written in [[Patient#Outpatients and inpatients|outpatient settings]] in the United States were not appropriate in 2010 and 2011. Doctors in the U.S. wrote 506 annual antibiotic scripts for every 1,000 people, with 353 being medically necessary.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Fleming-Dutra KE, Hersh AL, Shapiro DJ, Bartoces M, Enns EA, File TM, Finkelstein JA, Gerber JS, Hyun DY, Linder JA, Lynfield R, Margolis DJ, May LS, Merenstein D, Metlay JP, Newland JG, Piccirillo JF, Roberts RM, Sanchez GV, Suda KJ, Thomas A, Woo TM, Zetts RM, Hicks LA | title = Prevalence of Inappropriate Antibiotic Prescriptions Among US Ambulatory Care Visits, 2010–2011 | journal = JAMA | volume = 315 | issue = 17 | pages = 1864–73 | date = May 2016 | pmid = 27139059 | doi = 10.1001/jama.2016.4151 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Health workers and pharmacists can help tackle resistance by: enhancing infection prevention and control; only prescribing and dispensing antibiotics when they are truly needed; prescribing and dispensing the right antibiotic(s) to treat the illness.&lt;ref name=&quot;who.int&quot; /&gt;

==== At the individual level ====
People can help tackle resistance by using antibiotics only when prescribed by a doctor; completing the full prescription, even if they feel better; never sharing antibiotics with others or using leftover prescriptions.&lt;ref name=&quot;who.int&quot; /&gt;

====Country examples====
* The [[Netherlands]] has the lowest rate of antibiotic prescribing in the [[OECD]], at a rate of 11.4 defined daily doses (DDD) per 1,000 people per day in 2011. 
* [[Germany]] and [[Sweden]] also have lower prescribing rates, with Sweden's rate having been declining since 2007. 
* [[Greece]], [[France]] and [[Belgium]] have high prescribing rates of more than 28 DDD.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.qualitywatch.org.uk/indicator/antibiotic-prescribing#vis-ref_585|title=Indicator: Antibiotic prescribing|website=QualityWatch|publisher=Nuffield Trust &amp; Health Foundation|access-date=16 July 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150114213112/http://www.qualitywatch.org.uk/indicator/antibiotic-prescribing#vis-ref_585|archive-date=14 January 2015|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Water, sanitation, hygiene ===
Infectious disease control through improved [[WASH|water, sanitation and hygiene (WASH)]] infrastructure needs to be included in the antimicrobial resistance (AMR) agenda. The &quot;Interagency Coordination Group on Antimicrobial Resistance&quot; stated in 2018 that &quot;the spread of pathogens through unsafe water results in a high burden of gastrointestinal disease, increasing even further the need for antibiotic treatment.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;:4&quot;&gt;IACG (2018) [http://www.who.int/antimicrobial-resistance/interagency-coordination-group/IACG_Optimize_use_of_antimicrobials_120718.pdf?ua=1 Reduce unintentional exposure and the need for antimicrobials, and optimize their use IACG Discussion Paper], Interagency Coordination Group on Antimicrobial Resistance, [http://www.who.int/antimicrobial-resistance/interagency-coordination-group/public-consultation-discussion-papers/en/ public consultation process] at WHO, Geneva, Switzerland&lt;/ref&gt; This is particularly a problem in [[developing countries]] where the spread of infectious diseases caused by inadequate WASH standards is a major driver of antibiotic demand.&lt;ref name=&quot;Araya&quot; /&gt; Growing usage of antibiotics together with persistent infectious disease levels have led to a dangerous cycle in which reliance on antimicrobials increases while the efficacy of drugs diminishes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Araya&quot; /&gt; The proper use of infrastructure for water, sanitation and hygiene (WASH) can result in a 47–72 percent decrease of diarrhea cases treated with antibiotics depending on the type of intervention and its effectiveness.&lt;ref name=&quot;Araya&quot; /&gt; A reduction of the diarrhea disease burden through improved infrastructure would result in large decreases in the number of diarrhea cases treated with antibiotics. This was estimated as ranging from 5 million in Brazil to up to 590 million in India by the year 2030.&lt;ref name=&quot;Araya&quot; /&gt; The strong link between increased consumption and resistance indicates that this will directly mitigate the accelerating spread of AMR.&lt;ref name=&quot;Araya&quot; /&gt; Sanitation and water for all by 2030 is [[Sustainable Development Goal 6|Goal Number 6]] of the [[Sustainable Development Goals]].

An increase in [[hand washing]] compliance by hospital staff results in decreased rates of resistant organisms.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Swoboda SM, Earsing K, Strauss K, Lane S, Lipsett PA | title = Electronic monitoring and voice prompts improve hand hygiene and decrease nosocomial infections in an intermediate care unit | journal = Critical Care Medicine | volume = 32 | issue = 2 | pages = 358–63 | date = February 2004 | pmid = 14758148 | doi = 10.1097/01.CCM.0000108866.48795.0F | ref = harv }}{{subscription required}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Water supply and sanitation infrastructure in health facilities offer significant co-benefits for combatting AMR, and investment should be increased.&lt;ref name=&quot;:4&quot; /&gt; There is much room for improvement: WHO and UNICEF estimated in 2015 that globally 38% of health facilities did not have a source of water, nearly 19% had no toilets and 35% had no water and soap or alcohol-based hand rub for handwashing.&lt;ref&gt;WHO, UNICEF (2015). [https://www.susana.org/en/knowledge-hub/resources-and-publications/library/details/2374 Water, sanitation and hygiene in health care facilities – Status in low and middle income countries and way forward] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180912092005/https://www.susana.org/en/knowledge-hub/resources-and-publications/library/details/2374 |date=12 September 2018 }}. World Health Organization (WHO), Geneva, Switzerland, {{ISBN|978 92 4 150847 6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Industrial wastewater treatment ===
Manufacturers of antimicrobials need to improve the treatment of their wastewater (by using [[industrial wastewater treatment]] processes) to reduce the release of residues into the environment.&lt;ref name=&quot;:4&quot; /&gt;

=== Management in animal use ===
{{Main|Antibiotic use in livestock#Antibiotic resistance}}

====Europe====
In 1997, European Union health ministers voted to ban [[avoparcin]] and four additional antibiotics used to promote animal growth in 1999.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Casewell M, Friis C, Marco E, McMullin P, Phillips I | title = The European ban on growth-promoting antibiotics and emerging consequences for human and animal health | journal = The Journal of Antimicrobial Chemotherapy | volume = 52 | issue = 2 | pages = 159–61 | date = August 2003 | pmid = 12837737 | doi = 10.1093/jac/dkg313 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2006 a ban on the use of antibiotics in European feed, with the exception of two antibiotics in poultry feeds, became effective.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Castanon JI | title = History of the use of antibiotic as growth promoters in European poultry feeds | journal = Poultry Science | volume = 86 | issue = 11 | pages = 2466–71 | date = November 2007 | pmid = 17954599 | doi = 10.3382/ps.2007-00249 | ref = harv }}{{subscription required}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Scandinavia, there is evidence that the ban has led to a lower [[prevalence]] of antibiotic resistance in (nonhazardous) animal bacterial populations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Bengtsson B, Wierup M | title = Antimicrobial resistance in Scandinavia after ban of antimicrobial growth promoters | journal = Animal Biotechnology | volume = 17 | issue = 2 | pages = 147–56 | year = 2006 | pmid = 17127526 | doi = 10.1080/10495390600956920 | ref = harv }}{{subscription required}}&lt;/ref&gt; As of 2004, several European countries established a decline of antimicrobial resistance in humans through limiting the usage antimicrobials in agriculture and food industries without jeopardizing animal health or economic cost.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Angulo FJ, Baker NL, Olsen SJ, Anderson A, Barrett TJ | title = Antimicrobial use in agriculture: controlling the transfer of antimicrobial resistance to humans | journal = Seminars in Pediatric Infectious Diseases | volume = 15 | issue = 2 | pages = 78–85 | date = April 2004 | pmid = 15185190 | doi = 10.1053/j.spid.2004.01.010 | df = dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

====United States====
The [[United States Department of Agriculture]] (USDA) and the [[Food and Drug Administration]] (FDA) collect data on antibiotic use in humans and in a more limited fashion in animals.&lt;ref name=&quot;gao&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gao.gov/assets/330/323097.html|title=GAO-11-801, Antibiotic Resistance: Agencies Have Made Limited Progress Addressing Antibiotic Use in Animals|publisher=gao.gov|access-date=25 January 2014|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131105120254/http://www.gao.gov/assets/330/323097.html|archive-date=5 November 2013|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The FDA first determined in 1977 that there is evidence of emergence of antibiotic-resistant bacterial strains in livestock. The long-established practice of permitting OTC sales of antibiotics (including penicillin and other drugs) to lay animal owners for administration to their own animals nonetheless continued in all states.
In 2000, the FDA announced their intention to revoke approval of [[fluoroquinolone]] use in poultry production because of substantial evidence linking it to the emergence of fluoroquinolone-resistant ''[[Campylobacter]]'' infections in humans. Legal challenges from the food animal and pharmaceutical industries delayed the final decision to do so until 2006.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nelson-2007&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Nelson JM, Chiller TM, Powers JH, Angulo FJ | title = Fluoroquinolone-resistant Campylobacter species and the withdrawal of fluoroquinolones from use in poultry: a public health success story | journal = Clinical Infectious Diseases | volume = 44 | issue = 7 | pages = 977–80 | date = April 2007 | pmid = 17342653 | doi = 10.1086/512369 | ref = harv }}&lt;/ref&gt; Fluroquinolones have been banned from extra-label use in food animals in the USA since 2007. However, they remain widely used in companion and exotic animals.

===Global action plans and awareness===

The increasing interconnectedness of the world and the fact that new classes of antibiotics have not been developed and approved for more than 25 years highlight the extent to which antimicrobial resistance is a global health challenge.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.rand.org/randeurope/research/health/focus-on-antimicrobial-resistance.html|title=RAND Europe Focus on Antimicrobial Resistance (AMR)|website=www.rand.org|access-date=23 April 2018|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180421004546/https://www.rand.org/randeurope/research/health/focus-on-antimicrobial-resistance.html|archive-date=21 April 2018|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; A global action plan to tackle the growing problem of resistance to antibiotics and other antimicrobial medicines was endorsed at the Sixty-eighth World Health Assembly in May 2015.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.wpro.who.int/entity/drug_resistance/resources/global_action_plan_eng.pdf|title=GLOBAL ACTION PLAN ON ANTIMICROBIAL RESISTANCE|last=WHO|access-date=14 November 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171031170522/http://www.wpro.who.int/entity/drug_resistance/resources/global_action_plan_eng.pdf|archive-date=31 October 2017|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; One of the key objectives of the plan is to improve awareness and understanding of antimicrobial resistance through effective communication, education and training. This global action plan developed by the World Health Organization was created to combat the issue of antimicrobial resistance and was guided by the advice of countries and key stakeholders. The WHO's global action plan is composed of five key objectives that can be targeted through different means, and represents countries coming together to solve a major problem that can have future health consequences.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt; These objectives are as follows:

* improve awareness and understanding of antimicrobial resistance through effective communication, education and training.
* strengthen the knowledge and evidence base through surveillance and research.
* reduce the incidence of infection through effective sanitation, hygiene and infection prevention measures.
* optimize the use of antimicrobial medicines in human and animal health.
* develop the economic case for sustainable investment that takes account of the needs of all countries and to increase investment in new medicines, diagnostic tools, vaccines and other interventions.

'''Steps towards progress'''

* React based in Sweden has produced informative material on AMR for the general public.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.reactgroup.org/antibiotic-resistance/the-threat/|title=React|access-date=16 November 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171116185129/https://www.reactgroup.org/antibiotic-resistance/the-threat/|archive-date=16 November 2017|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Videos are being produced for the general public to generate interest and awareness.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LX6XHvFdzeY|title=Antibiotic Resistance: the silent tsunami (youtube video)|date=6 March 2017|website=ReActTube|access-date=17 November 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?time_continue=1&amp;v=xZbcwi7SfZE|title=The Antibiotic Apocalypse Explained |date=16 March 2016|website=Kurzgesagt – In a Nutshell|access-date=17 November 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*The Irish Department of Health published a National Action Plan on Antimicrobial Resistance in October 2017.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Health (DoH)|first=Department of|date=October 2017|title=Ireland's National Action Plan on Antimicrobial Resistance 2017 – 2020|url=https://www.lenus.ie/handle/10147/622661|via=Lenus (Irish Health Repository)}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Strategy for the Control of Antimicrobial Resistance in Ireland (SARI), Iaunched in 2001 developed Guidelines for Antimicrobial Stewardship in Hospitals in Ireland&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://www.lenus.ie/handle/10147/303394|title=Guidelines for antimicrobial stewardship in hospitals in Ireland|last=Group|first=SARI Hospital Antimicrobial Stewardship Working|publisher=HSE Health Protection Surveillance Centre (HPSC)|year=2009|isbn=9780955123672|location=Dublin}}&lt;/ref&gt; in conjunction with the Health Protection Surveillance Centre, these were published in 2009. Following their publication a public information campaign 'Action on Antibiotics&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.hse.ie/eng/health/hl/hcaiamr/antibiotics/antibiotics.html|title=Taking antibiotics for colds and flu? There's no point|website=HSE.ie|access-date=11 January 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;' was launched to highlight the need for a change in antibiotic prescribing. Despite this, antibiotic prescribing remains high with variance in adherence to guidelines.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Murphy M, Bradley CP, Byrne S | title = Antibiotic prescribing in primary care, adherence to guidelines and unnecessary prescribing—an Irish perspective | journal = BMC Family Practice | volume = 13 | pages = 43 | date = May 2012 | pmid = 22640399 | pmc = 3430589 | doi = 10.1186/1471-2296-13-43 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Antibiotic Awareness Week ====
The World Health Organization has promoted the first World Antibiotic Awareness Week running from 16–22 November 2015. The aim of the week is to increase global awareness of antibiotic resistance. It also wants to promote the correct usage of antibiotics across all fields in order to prevent further instances of antibiotic resistance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.who.int/mediacentre/events/2015/world-antibiotic-awareness-week/event/en/|title=World Antibiotic Awareness Week|website=World Health Organization|access-date=20 November 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20151120222039/http://www.who.int/mediacentre/events/2015/world-antibiotic-awareness-week/event/en/|archive-date=20 November 2015|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

World Antibiotic Awareness Week has been held every November since 2015. For 2017, the Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations (FAO), the World Health Organization (WHO) and the World Organisation for Animal Health (OIE) are together calling for responsible use of antibiotics in humans and animals to reduce the emergence of antibiotic resistance.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.who.int/campaigns/world-antibiotic-awareness-week/2017/launch-event/en/|title=World Antibiotic Awareness Week|website=WHO|access-date=14 November 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171113074006/http://www.who.int/campaigns/world-antibiotic-awareness-week/2017/launch-event/en/|archive-date=13 November 2017|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''United Nations'''

In 2016 the Secretary-General of the United Nations convened the Interagency Coordination Group (IACG) on Antimicrobial Resistance.&lt;ref name=&quot;:5&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.who.int/antimicrobial-resistance/interagency-coordination-group/en/|title=WHO {{!}} UN Interagency Coordination Group (IACG) on Antimicrobial Resistance|website=WHO|access-date=7 August 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; The IACG worked with international organizations and experts in human, animal, and plant health to create a plan to fight antimicrobial resistance.&lt;ref name=&quot;:5&quot; /&gt; Their report released in April 2019 highlights the seriousness of antimicrobial resistance and the threat is poses to world health. It suggests five recommendations for member states to follow in order to tackle this increasing threat. The IACG recommendations are as follows:

* Accelerate progress in countries
* Innovate to secure the future
* Collaborate for more effective action
* Invest for a sustainable response
* Strengthen accountability and global governance

==Mechanisms and organisms==

===Bacteria===
{{Further|List of antibiotic resistant bacteria}}[[File:mecA Resistance.svg|thumb|Diagram depicting antibiotic resistance through alteration of the antibiotic's target site, modeled after MRSA's resistance to penicillin. Beta-lactam antibiotics permanently inactivate [[Penicillin-binding protein|PBP enzymes]], which are essential for bacterial life, by permanently binding to their active sites. [[Methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus|MRSA]], however, expresses a PBP that does not allow the antibiotic into its active site.|alt=Diagram depicting antibiotic resistance through alteration of the antibiotic's target site]]

The four main mechanisms by which bacteria exhibit resistance to antibiotics are:
# Drug inactivation or modification: for example, enzymatic deactivation of [[Penicillin|''penicillin'' G]] in some penicillin-resistant bacteria through the production of [[Beta-lactamases|β-lactamases]]. Most commonly, the protective enzymes produced by the bacterial cell will add an acetyl or phosphate group to a specific site on the antibiotic, which will reduce its ability to bind to the bacterial ribosomes and disrupt protein synthesis.&lt;ref name=&quot;Criswell, Daniel 2004&quot;&gt;[Criswell, Daniel. &quot;The &quot;Evolution&quot; of Antibiotic Resistance.&quot; Institute for Creation Research. N.p., 2004. Web. 28 October 2014.]&lt;/ref&gt;
# Alteration of target- or binding site: for example, alteration of [[Penicillin binding protein|PBP]]—the binding target site of penicillins—in [[Methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus|MRSA]] and other penicillin-resistant bacteria. Another protective mechanism found among bacterial species is ribosomal protection proteins. These proteins protect the bacterial cell from antibiotics that target the cell's ribosomes to inhibit protein synthesis. The mechanism involves the binding of the ribosomal protection proteins to the ribosomes of the bacterial cell, which in turn changes its conformational shape. This allows the ribosomes to continue synthesizing proteins essential to the cell while preventing antibiotics from binding to the ribosome to inhibit protein synthesis.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Connell SR, Tracz DM, Nierhaus KH, Taylor DE | title = Ribosomal protection proteins and their mechanism of tetracycline resistance | journal = Antimicrobial Agents and Chemotherapy | volume = 47 | issue = 12 | pages = 3675–81 | date = December 2003 | pmid = 14638464 | pmc = 296194 | doi = 10.1128/AAC.47.12.3675-3681.2003 | df = dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
# Alteration of metabolic pathway: for example, some [[sulfa drugs|sulfonamide]]-resistant bacteria do not require [[para-aminobenzoic acid]] (PABA), an important precursor for the synthesis of [[folic acid]] and [[nucleic acid]]s in bacteria inhibited by sulfonamides, instead, like mammalian cells, they turn to using preformed folic acid.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Henry|first=Richard J.|date=December 1943|pmc=440870|journal=Bacteriological Reviews|volume=7|issue=4|pages=175–262|issn=0005-3678|pmid=16350088|title=The Mode of Action of Sulfonamides|doi=10.1128/MMBR.7.4.175-262.1943}}&lt;/ref&gt;
# Reduced drug accumulation: by decreasing drug [[Semipermeable membrane|permeability]] or increasing active [[efflux (microbiology)|efflux]] (pumping out) of the drugs across the cell surface&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Li XZ, Nikaido H | title = Efflux-mediated drug resistance in bacteria: an update | journal = Drugs | volume = 69 | issue = 12 | pages = 1555–623 | date = August 2009 | pmid = 19678712 | pmc = 2847397 | doi = 10.2165/11317030-000000000-00000 | ref = harv }}&lt;/ref&gt; These pumps within the cellular membrane of certain bacterial species are used to pump antibiotics out of the cell before they are able to do any damage. They are often activated by a specific substrate associated with an antibiotic.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Aminov RI, Mackie RI | year = 2007 | title = Evolution and ecology of antibiotic resistance genes | journal = FEMS Microbiology Letters | volume =  271| issue = 2| pages =  147–161| doi = 10.1111/j.1574-6968.2007.00757.x | pmid = 17490428 }}&lt;/ref&gt; as in [[fluoroquinolone]] resistance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Morita Y, Kodama K, Shiota S, Mine T, Kataoka A, Mizushima T, Tsuchiya T | title = NorM, a putative multidrug efflux protein, of Vibrio parahaemolyticus and its homolog in Escherichia coli | journal = Antimicrobial Agents and Chemotherapy | volume = 42 | issue = 7 | pages = 1778–82 | date = July 1998 | pmid = 9661020 | pmc = 105682 | ref = harv | doi = 10.1128/AAC.42.7.1778 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Antibiotic resistance mechanisms.jpg|thumb|300x300px|A number of mechanisms used by common antibiotics to deal with bacteria and ways by which bacteria become resistant to them.|alt=Infographic showing mechanisms for antibiotic resistance]]

In gram-negative bacteria, plasmid-mediated resistance genes produce proteins that can bind to [[DNA gyrase]], protecting it from the action of quinolones. Finally, mutations at key sites in DNA gyrase or [[topoisomerase IV]] can decrease their binding affinity to quinolones, decreasing the drug's effectiveness.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|vauthors=Robicsek A, Jacoby GA, Hooper DC|date=October 2006|title=The worldwide emergence of plasmid-mediated quinolone resistance|journal=The Lancet. Infectious Diseases|volume=6|issue=10|pages=629–40|doi=10.1016/S1473-3099(06)70599-0|pmid=17008172|ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some bacteria are naturally resistant to certain antibiotics; for example, gram-negative bacteria are resistant to most [[β-lactam antibiotic]]s due to the presence of [[Beta-lactamases|β-lactamase]]. Antibiotic resistance can also be acquired as a result of either genetic mutation or [[horizontal gene transfer]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|vauthors=Ochiai K, Yamanaka T, Kimura K, Sawada O, O|year=1959|title=Inheritance of drug resistance (and its transfer) between Shigella strains and Between Shigella and E.coli strains|journal=Hihon Iji Shimpor|language=Japanese|volume=34|page=1861|ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although mutations are rare, with spontaneous mutations in the [[pathogen]] [[genome]] occurring at a rate of about 1 in 10&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt; to 1 in 10&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt; per chromosomal replication,&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|last=Watford|first=Shelby|last2=Warrington|first2=Steven J. | name-list-format = vanc |title=Bacterial DNA Mutations|date=2018 |url=https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK459274/ |work=StatPearls |publisher=StatPearls Publishing |pmid=29083710 |access-date=21 January 2019 }}&lt;/ref&gt; the fact that bacteria reproduce at a high rate allows for the effect to be significant. Given that lifespans and production of new generations can be on a timescale of mere hours, a new (de novo) mutation in a parent cell can quickly become an [[heredity|inherited]] mutation of widespread prevalence, resulting in the [[microevolution]] of a fully resistant colony. However, chromosomal mutations also confer a cost of fitness. For example, a ribosomal mutation may protect a bacterial cell by changing the binding site of an antibiotic but will also slow protein synthesis.&lt;ref name=&quot;Criswell, Daniel 2004&quot; /&gt; manifesting, in slower growth rate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Levin BR, Perrot V, Walker N | title = Compensatory mutations, antibiotic resistance and the population genetics of adaptive evolution in bacteria | journal = Genetics | volume = 154 | issue = 3 | pages = 985–97 | date = March 2000 | pmid = 10757748 | pmc = 1460977 | url = http://www.genetics.org/cgi/pmidlookup?view=long&amp;pmid=10757748 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, some adaptive mutations can propagate not only through inheritance but also through [[horizontal gene transfer]]. The most common mechanism of horizontal gene transfer is the transferring of [[Plasmid-mediated resistance|plasmids]] carrying antibiotic resistance genes between bacteria of the same or different species via [[Bacterial conjugation|conjugation]]. However, bacteria can also acquire resistance through [[Transformation (genetics)|transformation]], as in ''Streptococcus pneumoniae'' uptaking of naked fragments of extracellular DNA that contain antibiotic resistance genes to streptomycin,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Hotchkiss RD | title = Transfer of penicillin resistance in pneumococci by the desoxyribonucleate derived from resistant cultures | journal = Cold Spring Harbor Symposia on Quantitative Biology | volume = 16 | pages = 457–61 | date = 1951 | pmid = 14942755 | doi = 10.1101/SQB.1951.016.01.032 }}&lt;/ref&gt; through [[Transduction (genetics)|transduction]], as in the bacteriophage-mediated transfer of tetracycline resistance genes between strains of ''S. pyogenes'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Ubukata K, Konno M, Fujii R | title = Transduction of drug resistance to tetracycline, chloramphenicol, macrolides, lincomycin and clindamycin with phages induced from Streptococcus pyogenes | journal = The Journal of Antibiotics | volume = 28 | issue = 9 | pages = 681–8 | date = September 1975 | pmid = 1102514 | doi = 10.7164/antibiotics.28.681 }}&lt;/ref&gt; or through [[gene transfer agent]]s, which are particles produced by the host cell that resemble bacteriophage structures and are capable of transferring DNA.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = von Wintersdorff CJ, Penders J, van Niekerk JM, Mills ND, Majumder S, van Alphen LB, Savelkoul PH, Wolffs PF | title = Dissemination of Antimicrobial Resistance in Microbial Ecosystems through Horizontal Gene Transfer | journal = Frontiers in Microbiology | volume = 7 | pages = 173 | date = 19 February 2016 | pmid = 26925045 | pmc = 4759269 | doi = 10.3389/fmicb.2016.00173 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Antibiotic resistance can be introduced artificially into a microorganism through laboratory protocols, sometimes used as a [[selectable marker]] to examine the mechanisms of gene transfer or to identify individuals that absorbed a piece of DNA that included the resistance gene and another gene of interest.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Chan CX, Beiko RG, Ragan MA | title = Lateral transfer of genes and gene fragments in Staphylococcus extends beyond mobile elements | journal = Journal of Bacteriology | volume = 193 | issue = 15 | pages = 3964–77 | date = August 2011 | pmid = 21622749 | pmc = 3147504 | doi = 10.1128/JB.01524-10 | ref = harv }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Recent findings show no necessity of large populations of bacteria for the appearance of antibiotic resistance. Small populations of ''E. coli'' in an antibiotic gradient can become resistant. Any heterogeneous environment with respect to nutrient and antibiotic gradients may facilitate antibiotic resistance in small bacterial populations. Researchers hypothesize that the mechanism of resistance development is based on four SNP mutations in the genome of ''E. coli'' produced by the gradient of antibiotic.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|vauthors=Johansen TB, Scheffer L, Jensen VK, Bohlin J, Feruglio SL|date=June 2018|title=Whole-genome sequencing and antimicrobial resistance in Brucella melitensis from a Norwegian perspective|journal=Scientific Reports|volume=8|issue=1|pages=8538|bibcode=2018NatSR...8.8538J|doi=10.1038/s41598-018-26906-3|pmc=5986768|pmid=29867163}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In recent years, the emergence and spread of [[Beta-lactamases|β-lactamases]] called [[carbapenemase]]s has become a major health crisis.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Diene SM, Rolain JM | title = Carbapenemase genes and genetic platforms in Gram-negative bacilli: Enterobacteriaceae, Pseudomonas and Acinetobacter species | journal = Clinical Microbiology and Infection | volume = 20 | issue = 9 | pages = 831–8 | date = September 2014 | pmid = 24766097 | doi = 10.1111/1469-0691.12655 }}&lt;/ref&gt; One such carbapenemase is [[New Delhi metallo-beta-lactamase 1]] (NDM-1),&lt;ref name=&quot;Kumarasamy&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Kumarasamy KK, Toleman MA, Walsh TR, Bagaria J, Butt F, Balakrishnan R, Chaudhary U, Doumith M, Giske CG, Irfan S, Krishnan P, Kumar AV, Maharjan S, Mushtaq S, Noorie T, Paterson DL, Pearson A, Perry C, Pike R, Rao B, Ray U, Sarma JB, Sharma M, Sheridan E, Thirunarayan MA, Turton J, Upadhyay S, Warner M, Welfare W, Livermore DM, Woodford N | title = Emergence of a new antibiotic resistance mechanism in India, Pakistan, and the UK: a molecular, biological, and epidemiological study | journal = The Lancet. Infectious Diseases | volume = 10 | issue = 9 | pages = 597–602 | date = September 2010 | pmid = 20705517 | pmc = 2933358 | doi = 10.1016/S1473-3099(10)70143-2 }}&lt;/ref&gt; an [[enzyme]] that makes [[bacteria]] [[Antibiotic resistance|resistant]] to a broad range of [[beta-lactam antibiotic]]s. The most common bacteria that make this enzyme are [[Gram-negative bacteria|gram-negative]] such as ''[[Escherichia coli]]'' and ''Klebsiella pneumoniae'', but the gene for NDM-1 can spread from one strain of bacteria to another by [[horizontal gene transfer]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Hudson CM, Bent ZW, Meagher RJ, Williams KP | title = Resistance determinants and mobile genetic elements of an NDM-1-encoding Klebsiella pneumoniae strain | journal = PLOS ONE | volume = 9 | issue = 6 | pages = e99209 | date = 7 June 2014 | pmid = 24905728 | pmc = 4048246 | doi = 10.1371/journal.pone.0099209 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{See also|AAC/AAD leader}}

===Viruses===
Specific [[antiviral drug]]s are used to treat some viral infections. These drugs prevent viruses from reproducing by inhibiting essential stages of the virus's replication cycle in infected cells. Antivirals are used to treat [[HIV]], [[hepatitis B]], [[hepatitis C]], [[influenza]], [[herpesviridae|herpes viruses]] including [[varicella zoster virus]], [[cytomegalovirus]] and [[Epstein-Barr virus]]. With each virus, some strains have become resistant to the administered drugs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Lou Z, Sun Y, Rao Z | title = Current progress in antiviral strategies | journal = Trends in Pharmacological Sciences | volume = 35 | issue = 2 | pages = 86–102 | date = February 2014 | pmid = 24439476 | doi = 10.1016/j.tips.2013.11.006 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Antiviral drugs typically target key components of viral reproduction; for example, [[oseltamivir]] targets influenza [[neuraminidase]], while guanosine analogs inhibit viral DNA polymerase. Resistance to antivirals is thus acquired through mutations in the genes that encode the protein targets of the drugs.

Resistance to HIV antivirals is problematic, and even multi-drug resistant strains have evolved.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Pennings PS | title = HIV Drug Resistance: Problems and Perspectives | journal = Infectious Disease Reports | volume = 5 | issue = Suppl 1 | pages = e5 | date = June 2013 | pmid = 24470969 | pmc = 3892620 | doi = 10.4081/idr.2013.s1.e5 }}&lt;/ref&gt; One source of resistance is that many current HIV drugs, including NRTIs and NNRTIs, target [[reverse transcriptase]]; however, HIV-1 reverse transcriptase is highly error prone and thus mutations conferring resistance arise rapidly.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Das K, Arnold E | title = HIV-1 reverse transcriptase and antiviral drug resistance. Part 1 | journal = Current Opinion in Virology | volume = 3 | issue = 2 | pages = 111–8 | date = April 2013 | pmid = 23602471 | pmc = 4097814 | doi = 10.1016/j.coviro.2013.03.012 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Resistant strains of the HIV virus emerge rapidly if only one antiviral drug is used.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Ton Q, Frenkel L | title = HIV drug resistance in mothers and infants following use of antiretrovirals to prevent mother-to-child transmission | journal = Current HIV Research | volume = 11 | issue = 2 | pages = 126–36 | date = March 2013 | pmid = 23432488 | doi = 10.2174/1570162x11311020005 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Using three or more drugs together, termed [[combination therapy]], has helped to control this problem, but new drugs are needed because of the continuing emergence of drug-resistant HIV strains.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Ebrahim O, Mazanderani AH | title = Recent developments in hiv treatment and their dissemination in poor countries | journal = Infectious Disease Reports | volume = 5 | issue = Suppl 1 | pages = e2 | date = June 2013 | pmid = 24470966 | pmc = 3892621 | doi = 10.4081/idr.2013.s1.e2 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Fungi===
Infections by fungi are a cause of high morbidity and mortality in [[Immunodeficiency|immunocompromised]] persons, such as those with HIV/AIDS, tuberculosis or receiving [[chemotherapy]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Xie JL, Polvi EJ, Shekhar-Guturja T, Cowen LE | title = Elucidating drug resistance in human fungal pathogens | journal = Future Microbiology | volume = 9 | issue = 4 | pages = 523–42 | year = 2014 | pmid = 24810351 | doi = 10.2217/fmb.14.18 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The fungi [[Candida (fungus)|candida]], ''[[Cryptococcus neoformans]]'' and ''[[Aspergillus fumigatus]]'' cause most of these infections and antifungal resistance occurs in all of them.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Srinivasan A, Lopez-Ribot JL, Ramasubramanian AK | title = Overcoming antifungal resistance | journal = Drug Discovery Today: Technologies | volume = 11 | pages = 65–71 | date = March 2014 | pmid = 24847655 | pmc = 4031462 | doi = 10.1016/j.ddtec.2014.02.005 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Multidrug resistance in fungi is increasing because of the widespread use of antifungal drugs to treat infections in immunocompromised individuals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Costa C, Dias PJ, Sá-Correia I, Teixeira MC | title = MFS multidrug transporters in pathogenic fungi: do they have real clinical impact? | journal = Frontiers in Physiology | volume = 5 | pages = 197 | date = 2014 | pmid = 24904431 | pmc = 4035561 | doi = 10.3389/fphys.2014.00197 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Of particular note, [[Fluconazole]]-resistant Candida species have been highlighted as a growing problem by the CDC.&lt;ref name=&quot;CDC2013&quot; /&gt; More than 20 species of Candida can cause [[Candidiasis]] infection, the most common of which is ''[[Candida albicans]]''. Candida yeasts normally inhabit the skin and mucous membranes without causing infection. However, overgrowth of Candida can lead to Candidiasis. Some Candida strains are becoming resistant to first-line and second-line [[Antifungal|antifungal agents]] such as [[Azole#Use as anti-fungal agents|azoles]] and [[echinocandin]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;CDC2013&quot; /&gt;

===Parasites===

The [[protozoa]]n parasites that cause the diseases [[malaria]], [[trypanosomiasis]], [[toxoplasmosis]], [[cryptosporidiosis]] and [[leishmaniasis]] are important human pathogens.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid25057459&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Andrews KT, Fisher G, Skinner-Adams TS | title = Drug repurposing and human parasitic protozoan diseases | journal = International Journal for Parasitology. Drugs and Drug Resistance | volume = 4 | issue = 2 | pages = 95–111 | date = August 2014 | pmid = 25057459 | pmc = 4095053 | doi = 10.1016/j.ijpddr.2014.02.002 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Malarial parasites that are resistant to the drugs that are currently available to infections are common and this has led to increased efforts to develop new drugs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Visser BJ, van Vugt M, Grobusch MP | title = Malaria: an update on current chemotherapy | journal = Expert Opinion on Pharmacotherapy | volume = 15 | issue = 15 | pages = 2219–54 | date = October 2014 | pmid = 25110058 | doi = 10.1517/14656566.2014.944499 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Resistance to recently developed drugs such as [[artemisinin]] has also been reported. The problem of drug resistance in malaria has driven efforts to develop vaccines.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Chia WN, Goh YS, Rénia L | title = Novel approaches to identify protective malaria vaccine candidates | journal = Frontiers in Microbiology | volume = 5 | pages = 586 | year = 2014 | pmid = 25452745 | pmc = 4233905 | doi = 10.3389/fmicb.2014.00586 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Trypanosoma|Trypanosomes]] are parasitic protozoa that cause [[African trypanosomiasis]] and [[Chagas disease]] (American trypanosomiasis).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Franco JR, Simarro PP, Diarra A, Jannin JG | title = Epidemiology of human African trypanosomiasis | journal = Clinical Epidemiology | volume = 6 | pages = 257–75 | year = 2014 | pmid = 25125985 | pmc = 4130665 | doi = 10.2147/CLEP.S39728 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Herrera L | title = Trypanosoma cruzi, the Causal Agent of Chagas Disease: Boundaries between Wild and Domestic Cycles in Venezuela | journal = Frontiers in Public Health | volume = 2 | pages = 259 | date = 2014 | pmid = 25506587 | pmc = 4246568 | doi = 10.3389/fpubh.2014.00259 }}&lt;/ref&gt; There are no vaccines to prevent these infections so drugs such as [[pentamidine]] and [[suramin]], [[benznidazole]] and [[nifurtimox]] are used to treat infections. These drugs are effective but infections caused by resistant parasites have been reported.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid25057459&quot; /&gt;

[[Leishmaniasis]] is caused by protozoa and is an important public health problem worldwide, especially in sub-tropical and tropical countries. Drug resistance has &quot;become a major concern&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Mansueto P, Seidita A, Vitale G, Cascio A | title = Leishmaniasis in travelers: a literature review | journal = Travel Medicine and Infectious Disease | volume = 12 | issue = 6 Pt A | pages = 563–81 | year = 2014 | pmid = 25287721 | doi = 10.1016/j.tmaid.2014.09.007 | url = https://iris.unipa.it/bitstream/10447/101959/4/Travel%20Medicine%20and%20Infectious%20Disease%202014%2012%20563-581.pdf | hdl = 10447/101959 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
The discovery of penicillin in 1928 and other antibiotics in the 20th century proved to be a significant medical achievement, saving millions of lives and significantly reducing the burden of infectious diseases.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Adedeji WA | journal = Annals of Ibadan Postgraduate Medicine | volume = 14 | issue = 2 | pages = 56–57 | date = December 2016 | pmid = 28337088 | pmc = 5354621 | title = The Treasure Called Antibiotics }}&lt;/ref&gt; The 1950s to 1970s represented the golden age of antibiotic discovery, where countless new classes of antibiotics were discovered to treat previously incurable diseases such as tuberculosis and syphilis.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Aminov RI | title = A brief history of the antibiotic era: lessons learned and challenges for the future | language = English | journal = Frontiers in Microbiology | volume = 1 | pages = 134 | date = 2010 | pmid = 21687759 | pmc = 3109405 | doi = 10.3389/fmicb.2010.00134 }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, since that time the discovery of new classes of antibiotics has been almost nonexistent, and represents a situation that is especially problematic considering the resiliency of bacteria&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal 
| last1 = Carvalho | first1 = Gabriel | last2 = Forestier | first2 = Christiane | last3 = Mathias | first3 = Jean-Denis
| title = Antibiotic resilience: a necessary concept to complement antibiotic resistance?
| volume = 286
| issue = 1916 | pages = 20192408 | journal = Proc. R. Soc. B
| doi = 10.1098/rspb.2019.2408| pmid = 31795866 | pmc = 6939251 | year = 2019 }}&lt;/ref&gt; shown over time and the continued misuse and overuse of antibiotics in treatment.&lt;ref name=&quot;worldcat.org&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title=Antimicrobial resistance : global report on surveillance|others=World Health Organization|isbn=9789241564748|location=Geneva, Switzerland|oclc=880847527|last1 = Organization|first1 = World Health|year=2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The phenomenon of antimicrobial resistance caused by overuse of antibiotics was predicted by [[Alexander Fleming]] who said &quot;The time may come when penicillin can be bought by anyone in the shops. Then there is the danger that the ignorant man may easily under-dose himself and by exposing his microbes to nonlethal quantities of the drug make them resistant.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Amábile-Cuevas CF, editor. Antimicrobial resistance in bacteria. Horizon Scientific Press; 2007&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/medicine/laureates/1945/fleming-lecture.pdf|title=Nobel Price Lecture|last=Fleming|first=Alexander|name-list-format=vanc|date=11 December 1945|website=nobelprize.org|access-date=1 March 2018|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180331001640/https://www.nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/medicine/laureates/1945/fleming-lecture.pdf|archive-date=31 March 2018|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; Without the creation of new and stronger antibiotics an era where common infections and minor injuries can kill, and where complex procedures such as surgery and chemotherapy become too risky, is a very real possibility.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.who.int/antimicrobial-resistance/publications/global-action-plan/en/|title=WHO {{!}} Global action plan on antimicrobial resistance|website=WHO|access-date=23 April 2018|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180418062254/http://www.who.int/antimicrobial-resistance/publications/global-action-plan/en/|archive-date=18 April 2018|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; Antimicrobial resistance threatens the world as we know it, and can lead to epidemics of enormous proportions if preventive actions are not taken. In this day and age current antimicrobial resistance leads to longer hospital stays, higher medical costs, and increased mortality.&lt;ref name=&quot;worldcat.org&quot;/&gt;

==Society and culture==
Since the mid-1980s pharmaceutical companies have invested in medications for cancer or chronic disease that have greater potential to make money and have &quot;de-emphasized or dropped development of antibiotics&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT_jan_21_2016&quot; /&gt; On 20 January 2016 at the [[World Economic Forum]] in [[Davos]], [[Switzerland]], more than &quot;80 pharmaceutical and diagnostic companies&quot; from around the world called for &quot;transformational commercial models&quot; at a global level to spur research and development on antibiotics and on the &quot;enhanced use of diagnostic tests that can rapidly identify the infecting organism&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT_jan_21_2016&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url=https://www.nytimes.com/2016/01/21/business/to-fight-superbugs-drug-makers-call-for-incentives-to-develop-antibiotics.html?smid=tw-share | title=To Fight 'Superbugs,' Drug Makers Call for Incentives to Develop Antibiotics | newspaper=New York Times | date=20 January 2016 | access-date=24 January 2016 | last=Pollack | first=Andrew | name-list-format=vanc | series=Davos 2016 Special Report | location=Davos, Switzerland | archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180424142407/https://www.nytimes.com/2016/01/21/business/to-fight-superbugs-drug-makers-call-for-incentives-to-develop-antibiotics.html?smid=tw-share | archive-date=24 April 2018 | url-status=live | df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Legal frameworks===
Some global health scholars have argued that a global, legal framework is needed to prevent and control antimicrobial resistance.&lt;ref name=&quot;A. Behdinan, S.J. Hoffman 2015&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Behdinan A, Hoffman SJ | year = 2015 | title = Some Global Strategies for Antibiotic Resistance Require Legally Binding and Enforceable Commitments | url = https://semanticscholar.org/paper/ea7a41338b1fb16394d1e981840c993a31b92e89| journal = Journal of Law, Medicine &amp; Ethics | volume = 43 | issue = 2| pages = 68–73 | doi = 10.1111/jlme.12277 | pmid = 26243246 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Hoffman SJ, Ottersen T | year = 2015 | title = What Will It take to Address the Global Threat of Antibiotic Resistance? | url = https://scholarship.law.bu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1007&amp;context=faculty_scholarship| journal = Journal of Law, Medicine &amp; Ethics | volume = 43 | issue = 2| pages = 363–368 | doi = 10.1111/jlme.12253 | pmid = 26242959 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hoffman&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Hoffman SJ, Outterson K, Røttingen JA, Cars O, Clift C, Rizvi Z, Rotberg F, Tomson G, Zorzet A | title = An international legal framework to address antimicrobial resistance | journal = Bulletin of the World Health Organization | volume = 93 | issue = 2 | pages = 66 | date = February 2015 | pmid = 25883395 | pmc = 4339972 | doi = 10.2471/BLT.15.152710 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Rizvi Z, Hoffman SJ | year = 2015 | title = Effective Global Action on Antibiotic Resistance Calls for Careful Consideration of the Convening Forum | url = https://semanticscholar.org/paper/435c7756bd150b33b6959910a133764116277bec| journal = Journal of Law, Medicine &amp; Ethics | volume = 43 | issue = 2| pages = 74–8 | doi = 10.1111/jlme.12278 | pmid = 26243247 }}&lt;/ref&gt; For instance, binding global policies could be used to create antimicrobial use standards, regulate antibiotic marketing, and strengthen global surveillance systems.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hoffman&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;A. Behdinan, S.J. Hoffman 2015&quot; /&gt; Ensuring compliance of involved parties is a challenge.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hoffman&quot; /&gt; Global antimicrobial resistance policies could take lessons from the environmental sector by adopting strategies that have made international environmental agreements successful in the past such as: sanctions for non-compliance, assistance for implementation, majority vote decision-making rules, an independent scientific panel, and specific commitments.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Andresen S, Hoffman SJ | year = 2015 | title = Much Can Be Learned about Addressing Antibiotic Resistance from Multilateral Environmental Agreements | journal = Journal of Law, Medicine &amp; Ethics | volume = 43 | issue = 2| pages = 46–52 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== United States ====
For the [[2016 United States federal budget|United States 2016 budget]], [[President of the United States|U.S. president]] [[Barack Obama]] proposed to nearly double the amount of federal funding to &quot;combat and prevent&quot; antibiotic resistance to more than $1.2 billion.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.whitehouse.gov/the-press-office/2015/01/27/fact-sheet-president-s-2016-budget-proposes-historic-investment-combat-a President’s 2016 Budget Proposes Historic Investment to Combat Antibiotic-Resistant Bacteria to Protect Public Health] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150311113659/https://www.whitehouse.gov/the-press-office/2015/01/27/fact-sheet-president-s-2016-budget-proposes-historic-investment-combat-a |date=11 March 2015 }} The White House, Office of the Press Secretary, 27 January 2015&lt;/ref&gt; Many international funding agencies like USAID, DFID, [[Swedish International Development Cooperation Agency|SIDA]] and [[Bill &amp; Melinda Gates Foundation]] have pledged money for developing strategies to counter antimicrobial resistance.

On 27 March 2015, the [[White House]] released a comprehensive plan to address the increasing need for agencies to combat the rise of antibiotic-resistant bacteria. The Task Force for Combating Antibiotic-Resistant Bacteria developed ''The National Action Plan for Combating Antibiotic-Resistant Bacteria'' with the intent of providing a roadmap to guide the US in the antibiotic resistance challenge and with hopes of saving many lives. This plan outlines steps taken by the Federal government over the next five years needed in order to prevent and contain outbreaks of antibiotic-resistant infections; maintain the efficacy of antibiotics already on the market; and to help to develop future diagnostics, antibiotics, and vaccines.&lt;ref name=&quot;whitehouse.gov&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.whitehouse.gov/the-press-office/2015/03/27/fact-sheet-obama-administration-releases-national-action-plan-combat-ant|title=FACT SHEET: Obama Administration Releases National Action Plan to Combat Antibiotic-Resistant Bacteria|website=whitehouse.gov|access-date=30 October 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20151122075741/https://www.whitehouse.gov/the-press-office/2015/03/27/fact-sheet-obama-administration-releases-national-action-plan-combat-ant|archive-date=22 November 2015|url-status=live|date=27 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Action Plan was developed around five goals with focuses on strengthening health care, public health veterinary medicine, agriculture, food safety and research, and manufacturing. These goals, as listed by the White House, are as follows:
* Slow the Emergence of Resistant Bacteria and Prevent the Spread of Resistant Infections
* Strengthen National One-Health Surveillance Efforts to Combat Resistance
* Advance Development and use of Rapid and Innovative Diagnostic Tests for Identification and Characterization of Resistant Bacteria
* Accelerate Basic and Applied Research and Development for New Antibiotics, Other Therapeutics, and Vaccines
* Improve International Collaboration and Capacities for Antibiotic Resistance Prevention, Surveillance, Control and Antibiotic Research and Development
The following are goals set to meet by 2020:&lt;ref name=&quot;whitehouse.gov&quot;/&gt;
* Establishment of antimicrobial programs within acute care hospital settings
* Reduction of inappropriate antibiotic prescription and use by at least 50% in outpatient settings and 20% inpatient settings
* Establishment of State Antibiotic Resistance (AR) Prevention Programs in all 50 states
* Elimination of the use of medically important antibiotics for growth promotion in food-producing animals.

==== United Kingdom  ====
[[Public Health England]] reported that the total number of antibiotic resistant infections in England rose by 9% from 55,812 in 2017 to 60,788 in 2018, but antibiotic consumption had fallen by 9% from 20.0 to 18.2 defined daily doses per 1,000 inhabitants per day between 2014 and 2018.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Patients contracted 165 antibiotic resistant infections each day in 2018, says PHE |url=https://www.pharmaceutical-journal.com/20207273.article |accessdate=11 December 2019 |publisher=Pharmaceutical Journal |date=31 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Policies ===
According to [[World Health Organization]], policymakers can help tackle resistance by strengthening resistance-tracking and laboratory capacity and by regulating and promoting the appropriate use of medicines.&lt;ref name=&quot;who.int&quot; /&gt; Policymakers and industry can help tackle resistance by: fostering innovation and research and development of new tools; and promoting cooperation and information sharing among all stakeholders.&lt;ref name=&quot;who.int&quot; /&gt;

== Further research ==
It is unclear if rapid viral testing affects antibiotic use in children.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Doan Q, Enarson P, Kissoon N, Klassen TP, Johnson DW | title = Rapid viral diagnosis for acute febrile respiratory illness in children in the Emergency Department | journal = The Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews | volume = 9 | issue = 9 | pages = CD006452 | date = September 2014 | pmid = 25222468 | doi = 10.1002/14651858.CD006452.pub4 | pmc = 6718218 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Vaccines===
Microorganisms do not develop resistance to [[vaccine]]s because a vaccine enhances the body's immune system, whereas an antibiotic operates separately from the body's normal defenses. Furthermore, if the use of vaccines increases, there is evidence that antibiotic resistant strains of pathogens will decrease; the need for antibiotics will naturally decrease as vaccines prevent infection before it occurs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Mishra RP, Oviedo-Orta E, Prachi P, Rappuoli R, Bagnoli F | title = Vaccines and antibiotic resistance | journal = Current Opinion in Microbiology | volume = 15 | issue = 5 | pages = 596–602 | date = October 2012 | pmid = 22981392 | doi = 10.1016/j.mib.2012.08.002 }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, new strains that escape immunity induced by vaccines may [[Evolution|evolve]]; for example, an updated [[influenza vaccine]] is needed each year.

While theoretically promising, antistaphylococcal vaccines have shown limited efficacy, because of immunological variation between ''Staphylococcus'' species, and the limited duration of effectiveness of the antibodies produced. Development and testing of more effective vaccines is underway.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.homesteadschools.com/nursing/courses/Immunity/Chapter05.html|title=Immunity, Infectious Diseases, and Pandemics—What You Can Do|publisher=HomesteadSchools.com|access-date=12 June 2013|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131203005320/http://www.homesteadschools.com/nursing/courses/Immunity/Chapter05.html|archive-date=3 December 2013|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Alternating therapy===
Alternating therapy is a proposed method in which two or three antibiotics are taken in a rotation versus taking just one antibiotic such that bacteria resistant to one antibiotic are killed when the next antibiotic is taken. Studies have found that this method reduces the rate at which antibiotic resistant bacteria emerge in vitro relative to a single drug for the entire duration.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Kim S, Lieberman TD, Kishony R | title = Alternating antibiotic treatments constrain evolutionary paths to multidrug resistance | journal = Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America | volume = 111 | issue = 40 | pages = 14494–9 | date = October 2014 | pmid = 25246554 | pmc = 4210010 | doi = 10.1073/pnas.1409800111 | bibcode = 2014PNAS..11114494K }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Studies have found that bacteria that evolve antibiotic resistance towards one group of antibiotic may become more sensitive to others.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Pál C, Papp B, Lázár V | title = Collateral sensitivity of antibiotic-resistant microbes | journal = Trends in Microbiology | volume = 23 | issue = 7 | pages = 401–7 | date = July 2015 | pmid = 25818802 | pmc = 5958998 | doi = 10.1016/j.tim.2015.02.009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; This phenomenon can be utilized to select against resistant bacteria using an approach termed collateral sensitivity cycling,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Imamovic L, Sommer MO | title = Use of collateral sensitivity networks to design drug cycling protocols that avoid resistance development | journal = Science Translational Medicine | volume = 5 | issue = 204 | pages = 204ra132 | date = September 2013 | pmid = 24068739 | doi = 10.1126/scitranslmed.3006609 | df = dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; which has recently been found to be relevant in developing treatment strategies for chronic infections caused by ''Pseudomonas aeruginosa''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Imamovic L, Ellabaan MM, Dantas Machado AM, Citterio L, Wulff T, Molin S, Krogh Johansen H, Sommer MO | title = Drug-Driven Phenotypic Convergence Supports Rational Treatment Strategies of Chronic Infections | journal = Cell | volume = 172 | issue = 1–2 | pages = 121–134.e14 | date = January 2018 | pmid = 29307490 | pmc = 5766827 | doi = 10.1016/j.cell.2017.12.012 | df = dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Development of new drugs===
Since the discovery of antibiotics, [[research and development]] (R&amp;D) efforts have provided new drugs in time to treat bacteria that became resistant to older antibiotics, but in the 2000s there has been concern that development has slowed enough that seriously ill people may run out of treatment options.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Liu J, Bedell TA, West JG, Sorensen EJ | title = Design and Synthesis of Molecular Scaffolds with Anti-infective Activity | journal = Tetrahedron | volume = 72 | issue = 25 | pages = 3579–3592 | date = June 2016 | pmid = 27284210 | pmc = 4894353 | doi = 10.1016/j.tet.2016.01.044 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= https://www.wp.dh.gov.uk/publications/files/2013/03/CMO-Annual-Report-Volume-2-20111.pdf |title=Annual Report of the Chief Medical Officer - Infections and the rise of antimicrobial resistance|date=2011|publisher=UK NHS|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131030190650/http://media.dh.gov.uk/network/357/files/2013/03/CMO-Annual-Report-Volume-2-20111.pdf|archive-date=30 October 2013|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another concern is that doctors may become reluctant to perform routine surgeries because of the increased risk of harmful infection.&lt;ref name=&quot;obama&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.npr.org/blogs/health/2013/06/04/188380562/obama-administration-seeks-to-loosen-antibiotic-approvals|title=Obama Administration Seeks To Ease Approvals For Antibiotics|date=4 June 2013|publisher=NPR|access-date=7 August 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150313042023/http://www.npr.org/blogs/health/2013/06/04/188380562/obama-administration-seeks-to-loosen-antibiotic-approvals|archive-date=13 March 2015|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; Backup treatments can have serious side-effects; for example, treatment of [[multi-drug-resistant tuberculosis]] can cause deafness or psychological disability.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.npr.org/2013/06/04/188566805/moldova-grapples-with-whether-to-isolate-tb-patients|title=Moldova Grapples With Whether To Isolate TB Patients|date=4 June 2013|publisher=NPR|access-date=7 August 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160803104507/http://www.npr.org/2013/06/04/188566805/moldova-grapples-with-whether-to-isolate-tb-patients|archive-date=3 August 2016|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; The potential crisis at hand is the result of a marked decrease in industry R&amp;D.&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/health-21737844|title=BBC News&amp;nbsp;— Antibiotics resistance 'as big a risk as terrorism' – medical chief|last=Walsh|first=Fergus|name-list-format=vanc|publisher=Bbc.co.uk|access-date=12 March 2013|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180808002730/https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/health-21737844|archive-date=8 August 2018|url-status=live|work=BBC News|date=11 March 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Poor financial investment in antibiotic research has exacerbated the situation.&lt;ref name=&quot;TheRealNews-2014-05-18&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://therealnews.com/t2/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=31&amp;Itemid=74&amp;jumival=11872 | title = Why Are Antibiotics Becoming Useless All Over the World? | first = Martin | last = Khor | name-list-format = vanc | author-link = Martin Khor | date = 18 May 2014 | publisher = [[The Real News]] | access-date = 18 May 2014 | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20140518173348/http://therealnews.com/t2/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=31&amp;Itemid=74&amp;jumival=11872 | archive-date = 18 May 2014 | url-status = live | df = dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc&quot;/&gt; The pharmaceutical industry has little incentive to invest in antibiotics because of the high risk and because the potential financial returns are less likely to cover the cost of [[drug development|development]] than for other pharmaceuticals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Antibiotic Resistance: Why Aren't Drug Companies Developing New Medicines to Stop Superbugs?|last = Nordrum | first =  Amy | name-list-format = vanc | website = International Business Times|year=2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2011, [[Pfizer]], one of the last major pharmaceutical companies developing new antibiotics, shut down its primary research effort, citing poor shareholder returns relative to drugs for chronic illnesses.&lt;ref name=&quot;medpage&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.medpagetoday.com/InfectiousDisease/GeneralInfectiousDisease/24708|title=Pfizer Moves May Dim Prospect for New Antibiotics|last=Gever|first=John|name-list-format=vanc|date=4 February 2011|publisher=MedPage Today|access-date=12 March 2013 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131214004508/http://www.medpagetoday.com/InfectiousDisease/GeneralInfectiousDisease/24708 |archive-date=14 December 2013|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, small and medium-sized pharmaceutical companies are still active in antibiotic drug research.

In the United States, drug companies and the administration of President [[Barack Obama]] had been proposing changing the standards by which the FDA approves antibiotics targeted at resistant organisms.&lt;ref name=&quot;obama&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Ledford H | title = FDA under pressure to relax drug rules | journal = Nature | volume = 492 | issue = 7427 | pages = 19 | date = December 2012 | pmid = 23222585 | doi = 10.1038/492019a | bibcode = 2012Natur.492...19L }}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 18 September 2014 Obama signed an executive order&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.whitehouse.gov/the-press-office/2014/09/18/executive-order-combating-antibiotic-resistant-bacteria|title=Executive Order – Combating Antibiotics-Resistant Bacteria|author=Office of the Press Secretary|date=18 September 2014|publisher=The White House|access-date=22 September 2014|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140922223714/http://www.whitehouse.gov/the-press-office/2014/09/18/executive-order-combating-antibiotic-resistant-bacteria|archive-date=22 September 2014|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; to implement the recommendations proposed in a report&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.whitehouse.gov/sites/default/files/microsites/ostp/PCAST/pcast_carb_report_sept2014.pdf|title=Report to the President on Combating Antibiotic Resistance|author=President's Council of Advisors on Science and Technology|date=September 2014|publisher=PCAST|access-date=22 September 2014|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140922223724/http://www.whitehouse.gov/sites/default/files/microsites/ostp/PCAST/pcast_carb_report_sept2014.pdf|archive-date=22 September 2014|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; by the [[President's Council of Advisors on Science and Technology]] (PCAST) which outlines strategies to stream-line clinical trials and speed up the R&amp;D of new antibiotics.  Among the proposals:
* Create a 'robust, standing national clinical trials network for antibiotic testing' which will promptly enroll patients once identified to be suffering from dangerous bacterial infections.  The network will allow testing multiple new agents from different companies simultaneously for their safety and efficacy.
* Establish a 'Special Medical Use (SMU)' pathway for FDA to approve new antimicrobial agents for use in limited patient populations, shorten the approval timeline for new drug so patients with severe infections could benefit as quickly as possible.
* Provide economic incentives, especially for development of new classes of antibiotics, to offset the steep R&amp;D costs which drive away the industry to develop antibiotics.

===Rediscovery of ancient treatments===
Similar to the situation in malaria therapy, where successful treatments based on ancient recipes have been found,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Medieval medical books could hold the recipe for new antibiotics
|date=18 April 2017 |first=Erin |last=Connelly |work=The Conversation |url=https://theconversation.com/medieval-medical-books-could-hold-the-recipe-for-new-antibiotics-74490 }}&lt;/ref&gt; there has already been some success in finding and testing ancient drugs and other treatments that are effective against AMR bacteria.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.nottingham.ac.uk/news/pressreleases/2015/march/ancientbiotics---a-medieval-remedy-for-modern-day-superbugs.aspx |title=AncientBiotics – a medieval remedy for modern day superbugs? |publisher=University of Nottingham |date=30 March 2015 |type=Press release }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Rapid diagnostics ===
Distinguishing infections requiring antibiotics from self-limiting ones is clinically challenging. In order to guide appropriate use of antibiotics and prevent the development and spread of antimicrobial resistance, diagnostic tests that provide clinicians with timely, actionable results are needed.

Acute febrile illness is a common reason for seeking medical care worldwide and a major cause of morbidity and mortality. In areas with decreasing malaria incidence, many febrile patients are inappropriately treated for malaria, and in the absence of a simple diagnostic test to identify alternative causes of fever, clinicians presume that a non-malarial febrile illness is most likely a bacterial infection, leading to inappropriate use of antibiotics. Multiple studies have shown that the use of malaria rapid diagnostic tests without reliable tools to distinguish other fever causes has resulted in increased antibiotic use.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Hopkins|first=Heidi|last2=Bruxvoort|first2=Katia J|last3=Cairns|first3=Matthew E|last4=Chandler|first4=Clare I R|last5=Leurent|first5=Baptiste|last6=Ansah|first6=Evelyn K|last7=Baiden|first7=Frank|last8=Baltzell|first8=Kimberly A|last9=Björkman|first9=Anders|last10=Burchett|first10=Helen E D|last11=Clarke|first11=Siân E|date=29 March 2017|title=Impact of introduction of rapid diagnostic tests for malaria on antibiotic prescribing: analysis of observational and randomised studies in public and private healthcare settings|journal=BMJ|volume=356|language=en|pages=j1054|doi=10.1136/bmj.j1054|issn=0959-8138|pmc=5370398|pmid=28356302}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Antibiotic sensitivity|Antimicrobial susceptibility testing]] (AST) can help practitioners avoid prescribing unnecessary antibiotics in the style of [[precision medicine]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.mddionline.com/diagnostics-are-helping-counter-antimicrobial-resistance-more-work-needed|title=Diagnostics Are Helping Counter Antimicrobial Resistance, But More Work Is Needed|date=20 November 2018|work=MDDI Online|access-date=2 December 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; and help them prescribe effective antibiotics, but with the traditional approach it could take 12 to 48 hours.&lt;ref name=&quot;:6&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = van Belkum A, Bachmann TT, Lüdke G, Lisby JG, Kahlmeter G, Mohess A, Becker K, Hays JP, Woodford N, Mitsakakis K, Moran-Gilad J, Vila J, Peter H, Rex JH, Dunne WM | title = Developmental roadmap for antimicrobial susceptibility testing systems | journal = Nature Reviews. Microbiology | volume = 17 | issue = 1 | pages = 51–62 | date = January 2019 | pmid = 30333569 | doi = 10.1038/s41579-018-0098-9 | url = http://repub.eur.nl/pub/111533 | hdl = 2445/132505 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Rapid testing, possible from [[molecular diagnostics]] innovations, is defined as &quot;being feasible within an 8-h working shift&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;:6&quot; /&gt; Progress has been slow due to a range of reasons including cost and regulation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors =  | title = Progress on antibiotic resistance | journal = Nature | volume = 562 | issue = 7727 | pages = 307 | date = October 2018 | pmid = 30333595 | doi = 10.1038/d41586-018-07031-7 | bibcode = 2018Natur.562Q.307. }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Phage therapy===
{{Main|Phage therapy}}

[[Phage therapy]] is the [[therapeutic]] use of [[bacteriophage]]s to treat [[pathogenic]] [[bacterial infection]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kohn&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2002/09/19/48hours/main522596.shtml|title=Silent Killers: Fantastic Phages?|access-date=14 November 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130210183045/http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2002/09/19/48hours/main522596.shtml|archive-date=10 February 2013|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; Phage therapy has many potential applications in human medicine as well as dentistry, veterinary science, and agriculture.&lt;ref name=&quot;McAuliffe&quot;&gt;{{cite book | chapter-url = http://www.highveld.com/pages2/phage.html | author = McAuliffe|display-authors=et al | chapter = The New Phage Biology: From Genomics to Applications&quot; (introduction) | veditors = McGrath S, van Sinderen D | title = Bacteriophage: Genetics and Molecular Biology | publisher = Caister Academic Press | isbn = 978-1-904455-14-1 | year = 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Phage therapy relies on the use of naturally-occurring bacteriophages to infect and lyse bacteria at the site of infection in a host. Due to current advances in genetics and biotechnology these bacteriophages can possibly be manufactured to treat specific infections.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Lin DM, Koskella B, Lin HC | title = Phage therapy: An alternative to antibiotics in the age of multi-drug resistance | journal = World Journal of Gastrointestinal Pharmacology and Therapeutics | volume = 8 | issue = 3 | pages = 162–173 | date = August 2017 | pmid = 28828194 | pmc = 5547374 | doi = 10.4292/wjgpt.v8.i3.162 | df = dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Phages can be bioengineered to target multidrug-resistant bacterial infections, and their use involves the added benefit of preventing the elimination of beneficial bacteria in the human body.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt; Phages destroy bacterial cell walls and membrane through the use of lytic proteins which kill bacteria by making many holes from the inside out.&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Salmond GP, Fineran PC | title = A century of the phage: past, present and future | journal = Nature Reviews. Microbiology | volume = 13 | issue = 12 | pages = 777–86 | date = December 2015 | pmid = 26548913 | doi = 10.1038/nrmicro3564 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Bacteriophages can even possess the ability to digest the biofilm that many bacteria develop that protect them from antibiotics in order to effectively infect and kill bacteria. Bioengineering can play a role in creating successful bacteriophages.&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot; /&gt;

Understanding the mutual interactions and evolutions of bacterial and phage populations in the environment of a human or animal body is essential for rational phage therapy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Letarov AV, Golomidova AK, Tarasyan KK | title = Ecological basis for rational phage therapy | journal = Acta Naturae | volume = 2 | issue = 1 | pages = 60–72 | date = April 2010 | pmid = 22649629 | pmc = 3347537 | doi = 10.32607/20758251-2010-2-1-60-71 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Bacteriophage|Bacteriophagic]]s are used against antibiotic resistant bacteria in [[Georgia (country)|Georgia]] ([[George Eliava Institute]]) and in one institute in [[Wrocław]], Poland.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Parfitt T | title = Georgia: an unlikely stronghold for bacteriophage therapy | journal = Lancet | volume = 365 | issue = 9478 | pages = 2166–7 | date = June 2005 | pmid = 15986542 | doi = 10.1016/S0140-6736(05)66759-1 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Golkar Z, Bagasra O, Pace DG | title = Bacteriophage therapy: a potential solution for the antibiotic resistance crisis | journal = Journal of Infection in Developing Countries | volume = 8 | issue = 2 | pages = 129–36 | date = February 2014 | pmid = 24518621 | doi = 10.3855/jidc.3573 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Bacteriophage cocktails are common drugs sold over the counter in pharmacies in eastern countries.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid23755967&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = McCallin S, Alam Sarker S, Barretto C, Sultana S, Berger B, Huq S, Krause L, Bibiloni R, Schmitt B, Reuteler G, Brüssow H | title = Safety analysis of a Russian phage cocktail: from metagenomic analysis to oral application in healthy human subjects | journal = Virology | volume = 443 | issue = 2 | pages = 187–96 | date = September 2013 | pmid = 23755967 | doi = 10.1016/j.virol.2013.05.022 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Abedon ST, Kuhl SJ, Blasdel BG, Kutter EM | title = Phage treatment of human infections | journal = Bacteriophage | volume = 1 | issue = 2 | pages = 66–85 | date = March 2011 | pmid = 22334863 | pmc = 3278644 | doi = 10.4161/bact.1.2.15845 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{collist|colwidth=30em|
* [[Alliance for the Prudent Use of Antibiotics]]
* [[Broad-spectrum antibiotic]]
* [[Colonisation resistance]]
* [[Drug of last resort]]
* [[Genetic engineering]]
* [[Beta-lactamase#KPC (K. pneumoniae carbapenemase) (Class A)|(KPC) antibacterial resistance gene]]
* [[Multidrug tolerance]]
* [[Multidrug-resistant Gram-negative bacteria]] 
* [[Resistance-nodulation-cell division superfamily]] (RND)
* [[Resistome]]
}}

== References ==
{{reflist}}

=== Books ===
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite web |url=http://evolution.berkeley.edu/evolibrary/article/mutations_07|trans-title = Mutations are random|title=Understanding Evolution|publisher =University of California Museum of Paleontology |editor-first=Roy |editor-last=Caldwell |editor2-first=David |editor2-last=Lindberg| name-list-format = vanc |year=2011|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|editor1=Reynolds LA|editor2=Tansey EM|title=Superbugs and superdrugs : a history of MRSA : the transcript of a Witness Seminar held by the Wellcome Trust Centre for the History of Medicine at UCL, London, on 11 July 2006|date=2008|publisher=Wellcome Trust Centre for the History of Medicine at UCL|location=London|isbn=978-0-85484-114-1}}
{{refend}}
* [[OECD]] (2018), ''Stemming the Superbug Tide: Just A Few Dollars More, OECD Health Policy Studies'', OECD Publishing, Paris, https://doi.org/10.1787/9789264307599-en.

=== Journals ===
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite journal |last=Anomaly |first=Jonathan | name-list-format = vanc |date=2017 |title=Antibiotics and Public Policy |publisher=Georgetown University Press  |url= https://philpapers.org/archive/ANOEAA.pdf}}
* {{cite journal | vauthors = Arias CA, Murray BE | title = Antibiotic-resistant bugs in the 21st century—a clinical super-challenge | journal = The New England Journal of Medicine | volume = 360 | issue = 5 | pages = 439–43 | date = January 2009 | pmid = 19179312 | doi = 10.1056/NEJMp0804651 | ref = harv | url = https://semanticscholar.org/paper/4ed3abd6bf8ac3aa11fd2a1e2b551515486a52ff }}
* {{cite journal | title = Special Issue: Ethics and Antimicrobial Resistance | journal = Bioethics | volume = 365 | issue = 33 | year = 2019 | url=https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/toc/14678519/2019/33/7 }}
* {{cite journal | vauthors = Goossens H, Ferech M, Vander Stichele R, Elseviers M | title = Outpatient antibiotic use in Europe and association with resistance: a cross-national database study | journal = Lancet | volume = 365 | issue = 9459 | pages = 579–87 | year = 2005 | pmid = 15708101 | doi = 10.1016/S0140-6736(05)17907-0 | ref = harv | series = Group Esac Project | others = Esac Project }}
* {{cite journal | vauthors = Hawkey PM, Jones AM | title = The changing epidemiology of resistance | journal = The Journal of Antimicrobial Chemotherapy | volume = 64 Suppl 1 | pages = i3–10 | date = September 2009 | pmid = 19675017 | doi = 10.1093/jac/dkp256 | url = https://academic.oup.com/jac/article-pdf/64/suppl_1/i3/2249203/dkp256.pdf | ref = harv }}
* {{cite journal | vauthors = Soulsby EJ | title = Resistance to antimicrobials in humans and animals | journal = BMJ | volume = 331 | issue = 7527 | pages = 1219–20 | date = November 2005 | pmid = 16308360 | pmc = 1289307 | doi = 10.1136/bmj.331.7527.1219 | ref = harv }}
* {{cite journal |url=http://www.csiro.au/solutions/Alternatives-to-antibodies.html |title=Alternatives to Antibiotics Reduce Animal Disease|journal= Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organization|date=9 January 2006|ref=harv}}
* {{cite AV media |last=Cooke |first=Paul |first2=Dominic |last2=Rees-Roberts | name-list-format = vanc |year=2017 |title=CATCH |url=http://www.catchshortfilm.com/ }} 16-minute film about a post-antibiotic world. Review: {{cite journal |first=Clare |last=Sansom | name-list-format = vanc |title=Media Watch: An intimate family story in a world without antibiotics |journal=Lancet Infect Dis |volume=17 |issue=3 |pages=274 |date=March 2017 |doi=10.1016/S1473-3099(17)30067-1 }}
{{refend}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Antibiotic resistance}}
{{offline|med}}
* {{Curlie|Health/Pharmacy/Drugs_and_Medications/Antibiotics/Resistance_Issues/}}
* [http://pharmaxchange.info/press/2011/02/animation-of-antimicrobial-resistance/ Animation of Antibiotic Resistance]
* [https://www.cdc.gov/ncidod/dhqp/pdf/ar/mdroGuideline2006.pdf CDC Guideline &quot;Management of Multidrug-Resistant Organisms in Healthcare Settings, 2006&quot;]
* [http://www.cidrap.umn.edu/asp Antimicrobial Stewardship Project], at the [[Center for Infectious Disease Research and Policy]] (CIDRAP), University of Minnesota
* [https://www.amrindustryalliance.org/ AMR Industry Alliance], &quot;members from large R&amp;D pharma, generic manufacturers, biotech, and diagnostic companies&quot;
{{Antibiotics social and layman issues}}
{{Pharmacology}}
{{Portal bar|Biology|Medicine}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Antibiotic Resistance}}
[[Category:Antibiotic resistance| ]]
[[Category:Evolutionary biology]]
[[Category:Health disasters]]
[[Category:Pharmaceuticals policy]]
[[Category:Veterinary medicine]]
[[Category:Global issues]]</text>
      <sha1>hogrgrmervt57bpwrzw99sfa312itlu</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
