  <page>
    <title>Abel Tasman</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1988</id>
    <revision>
      <id>937256087</id>
      <parentid>935082922</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-23T21:37:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Harmsma</username>
        <id>1681098</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Tasman Map */ Changed image of map to higher resolution alternative. Small text is now readable.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{other uses}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2018}}
{{Infobox person
| name        = Abel Tasman 
| image       = Abel Tasman - Cuyp (cropped).jpg
| caption     = Detail from portrait by [[Jacob Gerritsz. Cuyp]], c. 1637
| birth_date  = 1603
| birth_place = [[Lutjegast]], [[Dutch Republic]]
| death_date  = {{death date and age |1659|10|10|1603|df=y}}
| death_place = [[History of Jakarta|Batavia]], [[Dutch East Indies]]
| education   = 
| occupation  = [[Navigator]], [[explorer]] [[sea captain]]
| title       = 
| spouse      = {{plainlist|1=
*Claesgie Heyndrix
*Jannetje Tjaers = Joanna Tiercx}}
| parents     = 
| children    = Claesjen Tasman (daughter)
| nationality = [[Dutch Republic|Dutch]]
}}

'''Abel Janszoon Tasman''' ({{IPA-nl|ˈɑbəl ˈjɑnsoːn ˈtɑsmɑn|lang}}; 1603 – 10 October 1659) was a [[Dutch Republic|Dutch]] [[sea explorer|seafarer]], [[exploration|explorer]], and [[merchant]], best known for his voyages of 1642 and 1644 in the service of the [[Dutch East India Company]] (VOC). He was the first known European explorer to reach the islands of [[Van Diemen's Land]] (now [[Tasmania]]) and [[New Zealand]], and to sight the [[Fiji]] islands.

==Origins and early life==
[[File:Jacob Cuyp - Abel Tasman, his wife and daughter.jpg|thumb|Portrait of Abel Tasman, his wife and daughter. Attributed to [[Jacob Gerritsz Cuyp]], 1637 (not authenticated).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://nationaltreasures.nla.gov.au/index.html|archive-url=http://pandora.nla.gov.au/pan/63316/20060914-0000/nationaltreasures.nla.gov.au/index.html|url-status=dead|archive-date=2006-09-14|title=Treasures : Home|website=pandora.nla.gov.au}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://artsearch.nga.gov.au/Detail.cfm?IRN=169493|title=Portrait of Abel Tasman, his wife and daughter|first=Jacob|last=Cuyp|website=Item held by National Gallery of Australia}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
Tasman originated from [[Lutjegast]], a small village in the [[province of Groningen]], in the north of the Netherlands.  The oldest available source mentioning him is dated 27 December 1631 when, as a seafarer living in Amsterdam, the 28-year-old became engaged to marry 21-year-old Jannetje Tjaers, of Palmstraat in the [[Jordaan]] district of the city.&lt;ref name=&quot;amsterdam&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://archief.amsterdam/5716kK4HtSGg01/indexen/ondertrouwregisters_1565-1811/zoek/query.nl.pl?i1=1&amp;a1=Tasman&amp;x=20&amp;z=a#A24711000098 |title= Amsterdam City Archives |publisher=stadsarchief.amsterdam.nl|accessdate=8 August 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.genealogieonline.nl/stamboom-helmantel/I25050.php|title=Abel Janszoon Tasman (1603-1659) » Stamboom Helmantel » Genealogie Online|first=Klaas|last=Pera|website=Genealogie Online|accessdate=19 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Tasmanroutes.PNG|thumb|Routes taken by Tasman in the Australasian region, on his first and second voyages.]]

== Relocation to the Dutch East Indies ==

Employed by the [[Dutch East India Company]] (VOC), Tasman sailed from [[Texel]] to [[Batavia, Dutch East Indies|Batavia]] in 1633 taking the southern [[Brouwer Route]]. During this period, Tasman took part in a voyage to [[Seram Island]]; the locals had sold spices to other European nationalities than the Dutch. He had a narrow escape from death, when in an incautious landing several of his companions were killed by people of Seram.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://adb.anu.edu.au/biography/tasman-abel-janszoon-2716|title=Tasman, Abel Janszoon (1603–1659)|first=J. W.|last=Forsyth|publisher=National Centre of Biography, Australian National University|via=Australian Dictionary of Biography}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 1637, Tasman was back in Amsterdam, and the following year he signed on for another ten years and took his wife with him to Batavia. On 25 March 1638 he tried to sell his property in the Jordaan, but the purchase was cancelled.&lt;!--; in 1650, while living in the East Indies, it was sold to the same man.&lt;ref&gt;City Archives Amsterdam [http://stadsarchief.amsterdam.nl/archieven/archiefbank/indexen/transportakten_voor_1811/zoek/query.nl.pl?i1=1&amp;v1=Abel&amp;a1=Tas*&amp;i2=2&amp;p2=p&amp;y2=1620&amp;z2=1660&amp;x=14&amp;z=a]&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt;

He was second-in-command of a 1639 exploration expedition in the north Pacific under [[Matthijs Quast]]. The fleet included the ships ''Engel'' and ''Gracht'' and reached [[Fort Zeelandia (Taiwan)|Fort Zeelandia]] ([[Dutch Formosa]]) and [[Deshima]].

==First major voyage==

&lt;!--{{Quote box
| title = The Province of Beach
| quote = &lt;small&gt; {{main|Province of Beach}}
The non-existent landmass of ''Beach'' appeared on maps in the 15th and 16th centuries. It appears to have resulted from errors in some editions of ''[[The Travels of Marco Polo]]'', which mislocated and misnamed the old Thai kingdom of [[Lopburi|Lavo]].&lt;ref&gt;G. E. Gerini, ''Researches on Ptolemy's geography of Eastern Asia (further India and Indo-Malay archipelago),'' London, Royal Asiatic Society, Asiatic Society Monographs vol.1, 1909, p.180.&lt;/ref&gt;  In [[Cantonese]], Lavo was pronounced &quot;lo-huk&quot; (羅斛), from which Marco Polo took his rendition of the name, ''[[Locach]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Paul Pelliot, ''Notes on [[Marco Polo]],'' Paris, Imprimerie Nationale, 1963, Vol. II, pp.768–9, note 2.&lt;/ref&gt; According to Polo, this  was a kingdom where gold was &quot;so plentiful that no one who did not see it could believe it&quot;.  In Book III, Polo described his journey by sea from China to India by way of [[Champa]] (Southern Vietnam), Java (which he called ''[[Jave la Grande|Java Major]]''), Locach and Sumatra (called ''Java Minor''). When Polo's narrative described the route southward from Champa toward [[Sumatra]],&lt;ref&gt;''Milione: il Milione nelle redazioni toscana e franco–italiana, Le Divisament dou Monde,'' Gabriella Ponchi (ed.), Milano, Arnoldo Mondadori Editore, 1982, p.540: cap. clxiii, &quot;La grant isle de Java&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; the name &quot;Java&quot; was erroneously substituted for &quot;Champa&quot; as the point of departure, locating Sumatra 1,300 miles to the south of Java instead of Champa. Locach, located between Champa and Sumatra, was likewise misplaced far to the south of Java, by some geographers on or near an extension of the ''Terra Australis''.&lt;ref&gt;James R. McClymont, &quot;The Theory of an Antipodal Southern Continent during the Sixteenth Century&quot;, ''Report of the Fourth Meeting of the Australasian Association for the Advancement of Science,'' Hobart, January 1892, Hobart, the Association, 1893, pp. 442–462; Paul Pelliot, ''Notes on Marco Polo,'' Paris, Imprimerie Nationale, 1963, Vol. II, p.769.&lt;/ref&gt; The name ''Beach'' was a later mistranscription of ''Locach'' In the [[Kurrent|German cursive script]], ''Locach'' resembles &quot;Boeach&quot; and in the 1532 edition of Polo's ''Travels'', ''Boëach'' was substituted for Locach.&lt;ref&gt;Simon Grynaeus and Johann Huttich, ''Novus Orbis Regionum ac Insularum,'' Basel and Paris, 1532, Marco Polo cap.xi, &quot;De provincia Boëach&quot;; cited in Thomas Suarez, ''Early Mapping of Southeast Asia,'' Hong Kong, Periplus, 1999, p.160.&lt;/ref&gt; Sir [[Henry Yule]], the editor of modern English edition  (1921) of Marco Polo's ''Travels'' stated: &quot;Some geographers ... following the old editions which carried the travellers south-east of Java to the land of 'Boeach' (or Locac), introduced in their maps a continent in that situation&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Sir Henry Yule (ed.), ''The Book of Ser Marco Polo,'' London, Murray, 1921, Volume 2, pp. 276–280.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;
It seems to have first been drawn on a map of the world published in Florence in 1489 by [[Henricus Martellus]], in which ''provincia boëach'' appears as a southern neighbour of ''provincia ciamba'' (Champa). [[Gerard Mercator]], on his 1541 globe, placed ''Beach provincia aurifera'' (&quot;Beach the gold-bearing province&quot;) in the northernmost part of the hypothesized southern continent,''[[Terra Australis]]'' in accordance with the faulty text of Marco Polo's ''Travels''. Beach remained in this location in Mercator's world map of 1569, with the amplified description, quoting Marco Polo, ''Beach provincia aurifera quam pauci ex alienis regionibus adeunt propter gentis inhumanitatem'' (&quot;Beach the gold-bearing province, whither few go from other countries because of the inhumanity of its people&quot;) with ''Lucach regnum'' shown somewhat to its south west.&lt;ref&gt;Peter van der Krogt, ''Globi Neerlandici: The Production of Globes in the Low Countries,'' Utrecht, HES Publishers, 1993, p.64, plate 2.14.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Abraham Ortelius]] of 1570 and Mercator, following  Ortelius also showed ''BEACH'' and ''LVCACH'' in these locations on his world map of 1571. Likewise, Linschoten's very popular 1596 map of the East Indies showed ''BEACH'' projecting from the map's southern edge,  [[Jan Huygen van Linschoten]] of 1596, as the northernmost part of the ''Terra Australis'', along with ''Locach''.&lt;br&gt; The discovery that land existed, ironically, where maps showed ''Beach'' to be, occurred in 1616, following the accidental encounter of a crew led by [[Dirk Hartog]] with the Australian mainland, which Hartog named [[Eendrachtsland]] after his ship.&lt;/small&gt;
| width = 40%
| align = right
}}--&gt;

In August 1642, the Council of the Indies, consisting of [[Antonie van Diemen]], [[Cornelis van der Lijn]], [[Joan Maetsuycker]], Justus Schouten, [[Salomon Sweers]], Cornelis Witsen, and Pieter Boreel in Batavia despatched Tasman and Franchoijs Jacobszoon Visscher on a voyage of exploration to little-charted areas east of the [[Cape of Good Hope]], west of [[Isla de los Estados|Staten Land]] (near Cape Horn, South America) and south of the [[Solomon Islands]].&lt;ref&gt;Andrew Sharp, ''The Voyages of Abel Janszoon Tasman,'' Oxford, Clarendon Press, 1968, pp. 25.&lt;/ref&gt;

One of the objectives was to obtain knowledge of &quot;all the totally unknown&quot; [[Provinces of Beach]].&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot;&gt;J.E. Heeres, &quot;Abel Janszoon Tasman, His Life and Labours&quot;, ''Abel Tasman's Journal,'' Los Angeles, 1965, pp.137, 141–2; cited in Andrew Sharp, ''The Voyages of Abel Janszoon Tasman,'' Oxford, Clarendon Press, 1968, p.24.&lt;/ref&gt; This was a purported yet [[phantom island|non-existent landmass]] alleged to have plentiful gold, which had appeared on European maps since the 15th century, as a result of an error in some editions of [[Marco Polo]]'s works (see the box, right for more information).

The expedition was to use two small ships, ''Heemskerck'' and ''Zeehaen''.

===Mauritius===

In accordance with Visscher's directions, Tasman sailed from Batavia on 14 August 1642&lt;ref name=&quot;robinsonlibrary&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.robinsonlibrary.com/geography/geography/discoveries/tasman.htm |title= Abel Janszoon Tasman, the first known European explorer to reach Tasmania and New Zealand and to sight Fiji |publisher=robinsonlibrary.com|accessdate=31 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; and arrived at [[Mauritius]] on 5 September 1642, according to the captain's journal.&lt;ref name=&quot;abeltasman.org&quot;/&gt; The reason for this was the crew could be fed well on the island; there was plenty of fresh water and timber to repair the ships. Tasman got the assistance of the governor [[Adriaan van der Stel]].

Because of the prevailing winds Mauritius was chosen as a turning point. After a four-week stay on the island both ships left on 8 October using the [[Roaring Forties]] to sail east as fast as possible. (No-one had gone as far as [[Pieter Nuyts]] in 1626/27.) On 7 November snow and hail influenced the ship's council to alter course to a more north-eastern direction,&lt;ref name=&quot;gutenberg&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://gutenberg.net.au/ebooks06/0600611.txt|title=ebooks06/0600611|publisher=gutenberg.net.au|accessdate=31 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; expecting to arrive one day at the [[Solomon Islands]].

=== Tasmania ===
[[File:Coastal-cliffs Tasman-peninsula.jpg|thumb|Coastal cliffs of [[Tasman Peninsula]]]]

On 24 November 1642, Tasman reached and sighted the west coast of Tasmania, north of [[Macquarie Harbour]].&lt;ref name=&quot;nla&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://nla.gov.au/nla.map-ra265-s97 |title=Digital Collections - Maps - Monumenta cartographica &amp;#91;cartographic material&amp;#93; : reproductions of unique and rare maps, plans and views in the actual size of the originals : accompanied by cartographical monographs &amp;#124; Original map of Tasmania in December 1642 |publisher=nla.gov.au|accessdate=31 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; He named his discovery Van Diemen's Land, after [[Antonio van Diemen]], [[Governor-General of the Dutch East Indies]].

Proceeding south, Tasman skirted the southern end of Tasmania and turned north-east. He then tried to work his two ships into [[Adventure Bay, Tasmania|Adventure Bay]] on the east coast of [[South Bruny Island]] where he was blown out to sea by a storm. This area he named [[Storm Bay]]. Two days later, on December 1, Tasman anchored to the north of Cape Frederick Hendrick just north of the [[Forestier Peninsula]]. On December 2, two ship's boats under the command of the Pilot, Major Visscher, rowed through the Marion Narrows into Blackman Bay, and across the west to the outflow of Boomer Creek where they gathered some edible &quot;greens&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Burney, J (1813) ''A Chronological History of the Voyage and Discoveries in the South Sea of Pacific Ocean'' L Hansard &amp; Sons, London, p. 70, cited in Potts, B.M. et al (2006) ''Janet Sommerville's Botanical History of Tasmania'' University of Tasmania and TMAG&lt;/ref&gt;  Tasman named Frederick Hendrik Bay, which included the present North Bay, [[Marion Bay, Tasmania|Marion Bay]] and the inlet Blackman Bay (the name Frederick Henry Bay was mistakenly transferred to its present location by Marion Dufresne in 1772). The next day, an attempt was made to land in North Bay. However, because the sea was too rough, the carpenter swam through the surf and planted the Dutch flag. Tasman then claimed formal possession of the land, on 3 December 1642.{{sfn|Chisholm|1911}}

For two more days, he continued to follow the east coast northward to see how far it went. When the land veered to the north-west at [[Eddystone Point]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Schilder |first1=Günter |title=Australia unveiled : the share of the Dutch navigators in the discovery of Australia |date=1976 |publisher=Theatrum Orbis Terrarum Ltd. |location=Amsterdam |isbn=9022199975 |page=170}}&lt;/ref&gt; he tried to keep in with it but his ships were suddenly hit by the [[Roaring Forties]] howling through Bass Strait.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Valentyn |first1=Francois |title=Oud en nieuw Oost-Indien |date=1724–1726 |publisher=J. van Braam |location=Dordrecht |isbn=9789051942347 |page=vol.3, p.47}}&lt;/ref&gt; The impenetrable wind wall indicated that here was a strait, not a bay. Tasman was on a mission to find the Southern Continent, not more islands, so he abruptly turned away to the east and continued his continent-hunting.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Cameron-Ash |first1=M. |title=Lying for the Admiralty |date=2018 |publisher=Rosenberg |location=Sydney |isbn=9780648043966 |page=105}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== New Zealand ===
[[File:Gilsemans 1642.jpg|thumb|Murderers' Bay, drawing by [[Isaack Gilsemans]]&lt;ref name=&quot;govt&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.teara.govt.nz/en/history/2/1|title='A view of the Murderers' Bay' &amp;ndash; History &amp;ndash; Te Ara: The Encyclopedia of New Zealand|publisher=teara.govt.nz|accessdate=31 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
[[File:DanceMaori.jpg|thumb|Māori [[haka]]]]

After some exploration, Tasman had intended to proceed in a northerly direction but as the wind was unfavourable he steered east. The expedition endured an extremely rough voyage and in one of his diary entries Tasman credited his compass, claiming it was the only thing that had kept him alive.

On 13 December 1642 they sighted land on the north-west coast of the [[South Island]], New Zealand, becoming the first Europeans to sight New Zealand.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.teara.govt.nz/en/european-discovery-of-new-zealand/2 | title=European discovery of New Zealand | publisher=Encyclopedia of New Zealand | date=4 March 2009 | accessdate=9 December 2010| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20101110165647/http://www.teara.govt.nz/en/european-discovery-of-new-zealand/2| archivedate= 10 November 2010 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt; Tasman named it ''Staten Landt'' &quot;in honour of the [[States General of the Netherlands|States General]]&quot; (Dutch parliament).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://nzetc.victoria.ac.nz//tm/scholarly/tei-Stout44-t2-body-d1-d1.html|title= The Pamphlet Collection of Sir Robert Stout:Volume 44.   Chapter 1, Discovery and Settlement |author= John Bathgate|authorlink= |coauthors= |date= |year= |month= |work= |publisher=NZETC|pages= |language= |quote= He named the country Staaten Land, in honour of the States-General of Holland, in the belief that it was part of the great southern continent.|accessdate=17 August 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; He wrote, &quot;it is possible that this land joins to the Staten Landt but it is uncertain&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://gutenberg.net.au/ebooks06/0600611.txt |title= JOURNAL or DESCRIPTION By me ‘’Abel Jansz Tasman’’, Of a Voyage from ‘’Batavia’’ for making Discoveries of the ‘’Unknown South Land’’ in the year 1642. |accessdate= 26 March 2018|first= Abel |last = Tasman|date= |year= |month= |work= |publisher=Project Gutenberg Australia|pages= |language= |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt; referring to [[Isla de los Estados]], a landmass of the same name at the southern tip of South America, encountered by the Dutch navigator [[Jacob Le Maire]] in 1616.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopedia|first=John|last=Wilson|title=European discovery of New Zealand – Tasman's achievement|encyclopedia=[[Te Ara: The Encyclopedia of New Zealand]]|date=March 2009|url=http://www.teara.govt.nz/en/european-discovery-of-new-zealand/3|accessdate=24 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, in 1643 [[Hendrik Brouwer|Brouwer's]] [[Dutch expedition to Valdivia|expedition to Valdivia]] found out that Staaten Landt was separated by sea from any the hypothetical Southern Land.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Lane |first=Kris E. |title=Pillaging the Empire: Piracy in the Americas 1500–1750 |url=https://books.google.com/?id=bRgFqADzOLkC&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q=Brouwer&amp;f=false |accessdate= |year=1998 |edition= |publisher=M.E. Sharpe |location=Armonk, N.Y. |isbn=978-0-76560-256-5|page=88 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Kock&gt;{{cite web|first=Robbert|last=Kock|url=http://www.colonialvoyage.com/dutchchile.html|title=Dutch in Chile|publisher=Colonial Voyage.com|access-date=23 October 2014|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160229232448/http://www.colonialvoyage.com/dutch-chile/|archive-date=29 February 2016|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
 | last       = Barros Arana
 | first      = Diego
 | author-link1 = Diego Barros Arana 
 | title      = Historia General de Chile
 | volume     = IV
 | url        = http://www.memoriachilena.gob.cl/602/w3-article-7988.html
 | year       = 2000
 | origyear   = 1884
 | edition    = 2
 | publisher  = [[Editorial Universitaria]]
 | location   = Santiago, Chile
 | isbn       = 956-11-1535-2 
 | ref        = harv
 | language   = Spanish
 | page = 280
  }}&lt;/ref&gt; Tasman continued: &quot;We believe that this is the mainland coast of the unknown Southland.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Tasman |first1=Abel Jansz |title=The Huydecoper Journal, 1642-1643 |publisher=Mitchell Library, SLNSW |location=Sydney |page=43}}&lt;/ref&gt; Tasman thought he had found the western side of the long-imagined [[Terra Australis]] that stretched across the Pacific to near the southern tip of South America.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Cameron-Ash |first1=M. |title=Lying for the Admiralty |date=2018 |publisher=Rosenberg |location=Sydney |isbn=9780648043966 |pages=21–22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After sailing north, then east for five days, the expedition anchored about 7&amp;nbsp;km from the coast off what is now believed to have been [[Golden Bay]]. Tasman sent ship's boats to gather water, but one of his boats was attacked by [[Māori people|Māori]] in a double-hulled [[waka (canoe)|waka]] (canoe) and four of his men were killed with [[Mere (weapon)|mere]] (clubs). {{quote|In the evening about one hour after sunset we saw many lights on land and four vessels near the shore, two of which betook themselves towards us. When our two boats returned to the ships reporting that they had found not less than thirteen fathoms of water, and with the sinking of the sun (which sank behind the high land) they had been still about half a mile from the shore. After our people had been on board about one glass, people in the two canoes began to call out to us in gruff, hollow voices. We could not in the least understand any of it; however, when they called out again several times we called back to them as a token answer. But they did not come nearer than a stone's shot. They also blew many times on an instrument, which produced a sound like the moors' trumpets. We had one of our sailors (who could play somewhat on the trumpet) play some tunes to them in answer.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;abeltasman.org&quot;/&gt;}} As Tasman sailed out of the bay he observed 22 waka near the shore, of which &quot;eleven swarming with people came off towards us.&quot; The waka approached the ''Zeehaen'' which fired and hit a man in the largest waka holding a small white flag. [[Canister shot]] also hit the side of a waka.&lt;ref name=&quot;abeltasman.org&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Diary of Abel Tasman p. 21-22.Random House. 2008&lt;/ref&gt; Archaeological research has shown the Dutch had tried to land at a major agricultural area, which the Māori may have been trying to protect.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.nzherald.co.nz/nz/news/article.cfm?c_id=1&amp;objectid=10675488 |title=First contact violence linked to food |work=[[The New Zealand Herald]]  |date=23 September 2010 |accessdate=23 September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Tasman named the area &quot;Murderers' Bay&quot;.

The expedition then sailed north, sighting [[Cook Strait]], which it mistook for a [[bight (geography)|bight]] and named &quot;Zeehaen's Bight&quot;. Two names that the expedition gave to landmarks in the far north of New Zealand still endure: [[Cape Maria van Diemen]] and [[Three Kings Islands]].  (''Kaap Pieter Boreels'' was renamed [[Cape Egmont]] by Captain [[James Cook]] 125 years later.)

=== Return voyage ===
[[File:Tasman-dagboek-b.jpg|thumb|[[Tongatapu]], the main island of [[Tonga]]; drawing by [[Isaack Gilsemans]]]]
[[File:Tasman-dagboek-a.jpg|thumb|The bay of Tongatapu with the two ships; drawing by Isaack Gilsemans]]

En route back to Batavia, Tasman came across the [[Tonga]]n archipelago on 20 January 1643. While passing the [[Fiji|Fiji Islands]] Tasman's ships came close to being wrecked on the dangerous reefs of the north-eastern part of the Fiji group. He charted the eastern tip of [[Vanua Levu]] and Cikobia before making his way back into the open sea.

The expedition turned north-west towards [[New Guinea]] and arrived at Batavia on 15 June 1643.{{sfn|Chisholm|1911}}

== Second major voyage ==
Tasman left [[Batavia, Dutch East Indies|Batavia]] on 30 January 1644 on his second voyage with three ships (''Limmen'', ''Zeemeeuw'' and the tender ''Braek''). He followed the south coast of New Guinea eastwards in an attempt to find a passage to the eastern side of [[New Holland (Australia)|New Holland]]. However, he missed the [[Torres Strait]] between New Guinea and Australia, probably due to the numerous reefs and islands obscuring potential routes, and continued his voyage by following the shore of the [[Gulf of Carpentaria]] westwards along the north Australian coast. He mapped the north coast of Australia making observations on [[New Holland (Australia)|New Holland]], and its people.&lt;ref name=Quanchi&gt;Quanchi, ''Historical Dictionary of the Discovery and Exploration of the Pacific Islands'', page 237&lt;/ref&gt; He arrived back in [[Batavia, Dutch East Indies|Batavia]] in August 1644.

From the point of view of the [[Dutch East India Company]], Tasman's explorations were a disappointment: he had neither found a promising area for trade nor a useful new shipping route. Although received modestly, the company was upset to a degree that Tasman did not fully explore the lands he found, and decided that a more &quot;persistent explorer&quot; should be chosen for any future expeditions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Abel Tasman's great voyage|url=http://tpo.tepapa.govt.nz/ViewTopicExhibitDetail.asp?TopicFileID=0x000ae4f7|work=Abel Tasman's great voyage|publisher=Tai Awatea-Knowledge Net|accessdate=14 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; For over a century, until the era of James Cook, Tasmania and New Zealand were not visited by Europeans – mainland Australia was visited, but usually only by accident.

== Later life ==
On 2 November 1644 Abel Tasman was appointed a member of the Council of Justice at Batavia. He went to Sumatra in 1646, and in August 1647 to Siam (now [[Thailand]]) with letters from the company to the King. In May 1648 he was in charge of an expedition sent to [[Manila]] to try to intercept and loot the Spanish silver ships coming from America, but he had no success and returned to Batavia in January 1649. In November 1649 he was charged and found guilty of having in the previous year hanged one of his men without trial, was suspended from his office of commander, fined, and made to pay compensation to the relatives of the sailor. On 5 January 1651 he was formally reinstated in his rank and spent his remaining years at Batavia. He was in good circumstances, being one of the larger landowners in the town. He died at Batavia on 10 October 1659 and was survived by his second wife and a daughter by his first wife. His property was divided between his wife and his daughter by his first marriage. In his testimony (dating from 1657&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www1.nationaalarchief.nl/vitrine/wie_was_tasman.html|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080420083101/http://www.nationaalarchief.nl/vitrine/wie_was_tasman.html|url-status=dead|title=National Archives|archivedate=20 April 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;) he left 25 guilders to the poor of his village Lutjegast.&lt;ref name=&quot;history-nz&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.history-nz.org/discovery1.html |title=Abel Janszoon Tasman - New Zealand in History - Holland 1603 - 1659 |author=Robbie Whitmore|publisher=history-nz.org|accessdate=31 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although Tasman's pilot, Frans Visscher, published ''Memoir concerning the discovery of the South land'' in 1642, Tasman's detailed journal was not published until 1898; however, some of his charts and maps were in general circulation and used by subsequent explorers.&lt;ref name= Quanchi/&gt;

==Legacy==
Tasman's ten-month voyage in 1642–43 had significant consequences. By circumnavigating Australia (albeit at a distance) Tasman proved that the small fifth continent was not joined to any larger sixth continent, such as the long-imagined Southern Continent. Further, Tasman's suggestion that New Zealand was the western side of that Southern Continent was seized upon by many European cartographers who, for the next century, depicted New Zealand as the west coast of a Terra Australis rising gradually from the waters around Tierra del Fuego. This theory was eventually disproved when Captain Cook circumnavigated New Zealand in 1769.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Cameron-Ash |first1=M. |title=Lying for the Admiralty |date=2018 |publisher=Rosenberg |isbn=9780648043966 |pages=21–22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{more citations needed|section|date=November 2018}}&lt;!--need citations for things that are not obviously after him and those without articles--&gt;
[[File:AbelTasmanNP.jpg|thumb|[[Abel Tasman National Park]]]]

Multiple places have been named after Tasman, including:
*the Australian island and state of [[Tasmania]], renamed after him, formerly Van Diemen's land. It includes features such as:
**the [[Tasman Peninsula]]
**the [[Tasman Bridge]]
**the [[Tasman Highway]]
*the [[Tasman Sea]]
*in New Zealand:
**the [[Tasman Glacier]]
**[[Tasman Lake]]
**the [[Tasman River]]
**[[Mount Tasman]]
**the [[Abel Tasman National Park]]
**[[Tasman Bay]]
**the [[Tasman, New Zealand|Tasman District]]
&lt;!-- Probably not reasonable to list things indirectly named after him
Animal and plant species:
*Indirectly via Tasmania
** the [[Tasmanian Devil]]
** the [[Thylacine|Tasmanian Tiger]]
** [[Tasmannia]] (Tasmanian pepper and relatives)
** the [[Tasman flaxlily]]
*Indirectly via the Tasman Sea
** the [[Tasman Booby]]
** two species named [[Tasman Parakeet]]s
** the [[Tasman Starling]]
** the [[Tasman whale]]--&gt;

Also named after Tasman are:
*Abel Tasman Drive, in [[Takaka]].
*The former passenger/vehicle ferry ''[[Abel Tasman (ship)|Abel Tasman]]''
*The [[Able Tasmans]] – an [[indie band]] from Auckland, New Zealand.
*[[Tasman (layout engine)|Tasman]], a [[Browser engine|layout engine]] for [[Internet Explorer]]
* [[6594 Tasman]] (1987 MM1), a main-belt asteroid
* Tasman Drive in [[San Jose, California]] and its [[Tasman (VTA)|Tasman]] light rail station
* Tasman Road in [[Claremont, Cape Town|Claremont]], [[Cape Town]], South Africa
&lt;!-- More indirect naming: * [[Tasman Mill|Tasman Forestry Ltd.]] and via it the [[Tasman Accord]]
* The [[Tasman Rugby Union]] and [[Tasman rugby league team]]
* the [[Tasman Series]], a motor racing series between Australia and New Zealand --&gt;
* [[Hunter-class frigate|HMAS ''Tasman'']] is a [[Hunter-class frigate]] that is expected to enter service with the [[Royal Australian Navy]] in the late 2020s.

His portrait has been on 4 New Zealand postage stamp issues, on a 1992 5 [[NZD]] coin, and on 1963, 1966&lt;ref&gt;[https://stamporama.com/discboard/disc_main.php?action=20&amp;id=15080 Oceania/Australia : 1963 4/- &amp; 1966 40 cent Tasman and his ship the &quot;Heemskerk&quot;], Stamporama&lt;/ref&gt; and 1985 Australian postage stamps.&lt;ref name=&quot;australianstamp&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.australianstamp.com/images/large/0015370.jpg|title=Image: 0015370.jpg, (378 × 378 px)|publisher=australianstamp.com|accessdate=31 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the Netherlands many streets are named after him. In Lutjegast, the village he was born, there is a museum dedicated to his life and travels.

==Tasman Map==
[[Image:Tasmanmap1644.jpg|thumb|Abel Tasman map, circa 1644, also known as the Tasman 'Bonaparte' map]]
[[Image:State Library of New South Wales000.jpg|thumb|[[State Library of New South Wales]] vestibule, showing a mosaic of the Tasman map inlaid in the floor]]

Held within the collection of the [[State Library of New South Wales]] is the [http://library.sl.nsw.gov.au/record=b2058092~S2 Tasman Map], thought to have been drawn by Isaac Gilsemans, or completed under the supervision of Franz Jacobszoon Visscher.&lt;ref name=&quot;THE TASMAN MAP&quot;&gt;{{cite journal| title = The tasman map | work=Discover Collections | publisher = State Library of New South Wales | date = 2012 | url = http://www.sl.nsw.gov.au/stories/tasman-map}}&lt;/ref&gt; The map is also known as the Bonaparte map, as it was once owned by [[Roland Bonaparte|Prince Roland Bonaparte]], the great-nephew of [[Napoleon]].&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Hooker|first=Brian N.|date=November 2015|title=New Light on the Origin of the Tasman-Bonaparte Map|url=http://search.informit.com.au/documentSummary;dn=596240577706873;res=IELHSS|journal=The Globe |issue=78|doi=|pmid=|access-date=8 August 2016|via=Informit}}&lt;/ref&gt; The map was completed sometime after 1644 and is based on the original charts drawn during Tasman's first and second voyages.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title=Tasman's Legacy|last=Patton|first=Maggie|work=Mapping our world|publisher=National Library of Australia|year=2014|isbn=9780642278098|editor-last=Pool|editor-first=David|location=Canberra|pages=140–142|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt; As none of the journals or logs composed during Tasman's second voyage have survived, the Bonaparte map remains as an important contemporary artefact of Tasman's voyage to the northern coast of the Australian continent.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

The Tasman map largely reveals the extent of understanding the Dutch had of the Australian continent at the time.&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title=Historical Geography of New South Wales to 1901|last=Jeans|first=D.N.|publisher=Reed Education|year=1972|isbn=0589091174|location=|page=24|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The map includes the western and southern coasts of Australia, accidentally encountered by Dutch voyagers as they journeyed by way of the Cape of Good Hope to the [[Dutch East India Company|VOC]]  headquarters in [[Batavia, Dutch East Indies|Batavia]].&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt; In addition, the map shows the tracks of Tasman's two voyages.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt; Of his second voyage, the map shows the area of the [[Banda Islands]], the southern coast of [[New Guinea]] and much of the northern coast of Australia. However, the area of the Torres Strait is shown unexamined; this is despite having been given orders by VOC Council at Batavia to explore the possibility of a channel between New Guinea and the Australian continent.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot; /&gt;

There is debate as to the origin of the map.&lt;ref name=&quot;:4&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Merchant of the Zeehaen: Isaac Gilsemans and the voyages of Abel Tasman|last=Anderson|first=G|publisher=Te Papa Press|year=2001|isbn=0909010757|location=Wellington|pages=155–158|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is widely believed that the map was produced in Batavia; however, it has also been argued that the map was produced in Amsterdam.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:4&quot; /&gt; The authorship of the map has also been debated: while the map is commonly attributed to Tasman, it is now thought to have been the result of a collaboration, probably involving Franchoijs Visscher and [[Isaack Gilsemans]], who took part in both of Tasman's voyages.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:4&quot; /&gt; Whether the map was produced in 1644 is also subject to debate, as a VOC company report in December 1644 suggests that at that time no maps showing Tasman's voyages were yet complete.&lt;ref name=&quot;:4&quot; /&gt;

In 1943, a mosaic version of the map, composed of coloured marble and brass, was inlaid into the vestibule floor of the [[State Library of New South Wales|Mitchell Library]] in Sydney.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sl.nsw.gov.au/collection-items/tasman-map-mitchell-vestibule Tasman Map in the Mitchell Vestibule], State Library of NSW&lt;/ref&gt; The work was commissioned by the Principal&amp;nbsp;Librarian [[William Herbert Ifould|William Ifould]], and completed by the [http://adb.anu.edu.au/biography/melocco-galliano-13274 Melocco Brothers] of Annandale, who also worked on [[ANZAC War Memorial]] in Hyde Park and the crypt at [[St Mary's Cathedral, Sydney]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://adb.anu.edu.au/biography/melocco-galliano-13274/text23687|title=Melocco, Galliano (1897–1971)|last=Kevin|first=Catherine|date=2005|website=Australian Dictionary of Biography|publisher=National Centre of Biography, Australian National University|access-date=9 August 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;THE TASMAN MAP&quot;/&gt;

==See also==
* [[Dieppe maps]]
* [[Willem Janszoon]]
* [[Janszoon voyage of 1605–06]]
* [[Theory of Portuguese discovery of Australia]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em|refs=
&lt;ref name=&quot;abeltasman.org&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.abeltasman.org/journal-tasman.html |title=Tasman Journal |access-date=10 August 2016 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160829063757/http://www.abeltasman.org/journal-tasman.html |archive-date=29 August 2016 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

==Sources==
*{{Dictionary of Australian Biography|First=Abel|Last=Tasman|shortlink=0-dict-biogT-V.html#tasman1}}
*[[Edward Duyker]] (ed.) The Discovery of Tasmania: Journal Extracts from the Expeditions of Abel Janszoon Tasman and Marc-Joseph Marion Dufresne 1642 &amp; 1772, St David's Park Publishing/Tasmanian Government Printing Office, Hobart, 1992, pp.&amp;nbsp;106, {{ISBN|0-7246-2241-1}}.
*{{cite book | last = Quanchi | first = Max|authorlink=| year = 2005 | title = Historical Dictionary of the Discovery and Exploration of the Pacific Islands | publisher = The Scarecrow Press  | location =  | isbn = 0810853957}}
*{{cite EB1911|mode=cs2|wstitle=Tasman, Abel Janszoon|volume=26}}

==External links==
{{wikisource author}}
{{Commons category|Abel Tasman}}
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20021004115657/http://www.lexicon.net/world/tasman/bhouse.htm A transcript of a paper on the voyages of Tasman, read to the Royal Society of Tasmania in 1895]
*[http://gutenberg.net.au/pages/tasman.html The Tasman page at Project Gutenberg of Australia] This page has links to Tasman's journal and other important documents relating to Tasman
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20130211084454/http://www.sl.nsw.gov.au/discover_collections/history_nation/voyages/rich_lands/voya_huydecoper.html The Huydecoper journal – Abel Tasman – The State Library of NSW]
*[http://www.adb.online.anu.edu.au/biogs/A020463b.htm J. W. Forsyth, 'Tasman, Abel Janszoon (1603? – 1659)', [[Australian Dictionary of Biography]], Volume 2, [[Melbourne University Press]], 1967, pp 503–504.]
*{{cite web|url=http://www.gahetna.nl/collectie/archief/inventaris/gahetnascans/eadid/1.11.01.01/inventarisnr/121/level/file |title=The Journal of Abel Tasman in the Dutch National Archives, 194 scans |website=nationaal archief |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160304173856/http://www.gahetna.nl/collectie/archief/inventaris/gahetnascans/eadid/1.11.01.01/inventarisnr/121/level/file |archivedate=4 March 2016 |df=dmy }}
&lt;!-- | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20160304173856/http://www.gahetna.nl/collectie/archief/inventaris/gahetnascans/eadid/1.11.01.01/inventarisnr/121/level/file | archive-date = 4 March 2016 --&gt;

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Tasman, Abel}}
[[Category:1603 births]]
[[Category:1659 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Grootegast]]
[[Category:Dutch explorers of the Pacific]]
[[Category:17th-century Dutch explorers]]
[[Category:European exploration of Australia]]
[[Category:Explorers of Australia]]
[[Category:Explorers of New Zealand]]
[[Category:Tasman Sea]]
[[Category:Explorers of Tasmania]]
[[Category:Maritime exploration of Australia]]
[[Category:Sailors on ships of the Dutch East India Company]]
[[Category:Maritime history of the Dutch East India Company]]</text>
      <sha1>glpbhkkgbrhqhqpwhkvml6v5kye7yxp</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
