  <page>
    <title>Antisemitism in Christianity</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6728</id>
    <revision>
      <id>939920908</id>
      <parentid>939918615</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-09T14:36:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>50.49.129.236</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Antisemitism in Christianity}}
{{Antisemitism}}
'''Antisemitism in Christianity''' refers to the feeling of hostility that some [[Christian Church]]es, [[Christian denomination|Christian groups]], and ordinary [[Christians]] have towards the [[Judaism|Jewish religion]] and the [[Jews|Jewish people]].

Christian rhetoric and antipathy towards Jews developed in the [[Apostolic Age|early years of Christianity]] and it was reinforced by the belief that Jews had [[Jewish deicide|killed Christ]] and ever increasing anti-Jewish measures over the [[Early Christianity|ensuing centuries]]. The action taken by Christians against Jews included acts of [[ostracism]], [[humiliation]], [[violence]], and [[murder]], culminating in the [[Holocaust]].&lt;ref name=HarriesAfter/&gt;{{rp|21}}&lt;ref name=Kung/&gt;{{rp|169}}&lt;ref name=Dawidowicz/&gt;

Christian [[antisemitism]] has been attributed to numerous factors including [[Split of early Christianity and Judaism|theological differences]], competition between [[Church (building)|Church]] and [[Synagogue]], the Christian drive for converts,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Nancy Calvert Koyzis |title=Paul, monotheism and the people of God : the significance of Abraham traditions for early Judaism and Christianity
|year=2004 |publisher=Continuum International Publishing Group |isbn=0-567-08378-0
|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=FsDxt4E_4UMC&amp;pg=PA119&amp;lpg=PA119&amp;dq=judaism+proselytization}}&lt;/ref&gt; misunderstanding of Jewish beliefs and practices, and the perception that Judaism was hostile towards Christianity. For two millennia, these attitudes were reinforced in Christian preaching, art and popular teachings,, all of which expressed contempt for Jews&lt;ref name=JCPSHorst&gt;Jerusalem Center for Public Affairs. May 5, 2009. [http://jcpa.org/article/the-origins-of-christian-anti-semitism/ The Origins of Christian Anti-Semitism: Interview with Pieter van der Horst]&lt;/ref&gt; as well as statutes which were designed to humiliate and stigmatise Jews.

Modern antisemitism has primarily been described as [[Racial antisemitism|hatred against Jews as a race]] and its most recent expression is rooted in 18th-century [[Scientific racism|racial theories]], while [[anti-Judaism]] is rooted in hostility towards the [[Judaism|Jewish religion]], but in [[Western Christianity]], anti-Judaism effectively merged into [[antisemitism]] during the 12th century.&lt;ref name=HarriesAfter/&gt;{{rp|16}} Scholars have debated how Christian antisemitism played a role in the [[Nazism|Nazi]] [[Nazi Germany|Third Reich]], [[World War II]] and [[the Holocaust]]. The Holocaust has forced many Christians to reflect on the relationship between [[Christian theology]], Christian practices, and how they contributed to it.&lt;ref name=&quot;Susannah_Heschel_2008&quot;&gt;Heschel, Susannah, [https://books.google.com/books?id=fiCJeNJIhoAC&amp;dq The Aryan Jesus: Christian theologians and the Bible in Nazi Germany], p. 20, Princeton University Press, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early differences between Christianity and Judaism==
{{main article|Anti-Judaism in early Christianity}}
The legal status of Christianity and Judaism differed within the [[Roman Empire]]: Because the practice of Judaism was restricted to the [[Jews|Jewish people]] and Jewish [[proselyte]]s, its followers were generally exempt from following the obligations that were imposed on followers of other religions by the [[Imperial cult of ancient Rome|Roman imperial cult]] and since the reign of [[Julius Caesar]], it enjoyed the status of a &quot;licit religion&quot;, but occasional persecutions still occurred, for example in 19 [[Tiberius]] expelled the Jews from Rome,&lt;ref&gt;Suetonius, [[Lives of the Twelve Caesars]], Tiberius 36&lt;/ref&gt; as [[Claudius]] did again in 49.&lt;ref&gt;Suetonius, Lives of the Twelve Caesars, Claudius XXV.4, referenced in {{Bibleref2|Acts|18:2}}&lt;/ref&gt; Christianity however was not restricted to one people, and because Jewish Christians were excluded from the [[synagogue]] (see [[Council of Jamnia]]), they also lost the protected status that was granted to Judaism, even though the said ''protection'' still had its limits (see [[Titus Flavius Clemens (consul)]], [[Rabbi Akiva]], and [[Ten Martyrs]]).

From the reign of [[Nero]] onwards, who is said by [[Tacitus]] to have blamed the [[Great Fire of Rome]] on Christians, the practice of Christianity was criminalized and Christians were frequently [[Persecution of Christians#Persecution of early Christians in the Roman Empire|persecuted]], but the persecution differed from region to region. Comparably, Judaism suffered setbacks due to the [[Jewish–Roman wars|Jewish-Roman wars]], and these setbacks are remembered in the legacy of the [[Ten Martyrs]]. [[Robin Lane Fox]] traces the origin of much of the later hostility to this early period of persecution, when the Roman authorities commonly tested the faith of suspected Christians by forcing them to pay homage to the deified emperor. Jews were exempt from this requirement as long as they paid the [[Fiscus Judaicus]], and Christians (many or mostly of Jewish origin) would say that they were Jewish but refused to pay the tax. This had to be confirmed by the local Jewish authorities, who were likely to refuse to accept the Christians as fellow Jews, often leading to their execution.&lt;ref&gt;In [https://books.google.com/books?id=bBqOAAAAMAAJ&amp;q=%22Pagans+and+Christians%22+Robin+Lane+Fox&amp;dq=%22Pagans+and+Christians%22+Robin+Lane+Fox&amp;pgis=1 ''Pagans and Christians'']&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Birkat haMinim]] was often brought forward as support for this charge that the Jews were responsible for the [[Persecution of Christians in the Roman Empire]].{{citation needed|date=May 2013}} In the 3rd century systematic persecution of Christians began and lasted until [[Constantine I (emperor)|Constantine]]'s conversion to Christianity.{{citation needed|date=May 2013}} In 390 [[Theodosius I]] made Christianity the [[state church of the Roman Empire]]. While pagan cults and [[Manichaeism]] were suppressed, Judaism retained its legal status as a licit religion, though anti-Jewish violence still occurred. In the 5th century, some legal measures worsened the status of the [[Jews in the Roman Empire]] (now more properly called the [[Byzantine Empire]] since relocating to [[Constantinople]]).{{citation needed|date=May 2013}}

Another point of contention for Christians concerning Judaism, which according to the modern KJV of the Protestant Bible, is attributed more to a religious bias, rather than an issue of race or being a &quot;Semite&quot;. Paul (a Benjamite Hebrew&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=https://biblehub.com/greek/3004.htm |title = Strong's Greek: 3004. λέγω (Legó) -- to say}}&lt;/ref&gt;) clarifies this point in the letter to the Galatians where he makes plain his declaration ″28There is neither Jew nor Greek, there is neither bond nor free, there is neither male nor female: for ye are all one in Christ Jesus. 29And if ye be Christ's, then are ye Abraham's seed, and heirs according to the promise.″ Further Paul states: ″15Brethren, I speak after the manner of men; Though it be but a man's covenant, yet if it be confirmed, no man disannulleth, or addeth thereto. 16Now to Abraham and his seed were the promises made. He saith not, And to seeds, as of many; but as of one, And to thy seed, which is Christ.″ Many misled Christians read Matthew 23, John 8:44, Revelations 2:9, 3:9, and wrongly believe that the term &quot;Jew&quot; means a Hebrew or a Semite...it does not, rather, it refers to the religious belief in Judaism. &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=https://biblehub.com/kjv/galatians/3.htm |title = Galatians 3 KJV}}&lt;/ref&gt; A perfect real life example of this clarification is &quot;Brother Nathanael&quot; a Christian Hebrew. &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=http://brothernathanaelfoundation.org/ |title = The Brother Nathanael Foundation - the Brother Nathanael Foundation}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC82oaFM2O_rnT171XtKIPOg&lt;/ref&gt;

==Issues arising from the New Testament==
{{more citations needed|date=March 2017}}

===Jesus as the Messiah===
{{See also|Judaism's view of Jesus|Rejection of Jesus}}
Jesus is rejected in [[Judaism]] as a failed [[Jewish Messiah claimants|Jewish Messiah claimant]] and a [[False_prophet#Judaism|false prophet]].&lt;ref name=&quot;BergerDWyschogrodM&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Berger|first=David|title=Jews and &quot;Jewish Christianity&quot;|year=1978|publisher=KTAV Publ. House|location=[New York]|isbn=0-87068-675-5|page=|author2=Wyschogrod, Michael }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;SingerT&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Singer|first=Tovia|title=Let's Get Biblical|year=2010|publisher=RNBN Publishers; 2nd edition (2010)|location=|isbn=978-0615348391|page=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;KaplanA&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Kaplan|first=Aryeh|title=The real Messiah? a Jewish response to missionaries|year=1985|publisher=National Conference of Synagogue Youth|location=New York|isbn=978-1879016118|edition=New}} [http://www.simpletoremember.com/vitals/the_real_messiah.pdf The real Messiah (pdf)]&lt;/ref&gt; Belief in the divinity of any human being is incompatible with [[Judaism]]:&lt;ref name=&quot;SingerT-Monotheism&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Singer|first=Tovia|title=Monotheism|url=http://www.outreachjudaism.org/articles/monotheism.html|accessdate=19 August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;SpiroK&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Spiro|first=Ken (Rabbi, Masters Degree in History)|title=Seeds of Christianity|url=http://www.simpletoremember.com/articles/a/seeds_of_christianity/|work=Judaism online|publisher=Simpletoremember.com|accessdate=19 August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, since the traditional Jewish belief is that the [[Jewish messianism|messiah]] has not yet come and the [[Messianic Age]] is not yet present, the total [[rejection of Jesus]] as either messiah or [[deity]] has never been a central issue for Judaism.

===Criticism of the Pharisees===
{{Main article|Woes of the Pharisees}}
Many New Testament passages criticise the [[Pharisees]] and it has been argued that these passages have shaped the way that Christians viewed Jews. Like most Bible passages, however, they can be and have been interpreted in a variety of ways.

Mainstream [[Talmud]]ic [[Rabbinical Judaism]] today directly descends from the Pharisees whom Jesus often criticized.&lt;ref&gt;Universal Jewish Encyclopedia (1943); Jewish Encyclopedia (1905), Exhibit 264.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/articles/12087-pharisees|title=PHARISEES - JewishEncyclopedia.com|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; During Jesus' life and at the time of his execution, the Pharisees were only one of several Jewish groups such as the [[Sadducee]]s, [[Zealot]]s, and [[Essene]]s who mostly died out not long after the period;&lt;ref&gt;Jewish Encyclopedia (1905)&lt;/ref&gt; indeed, Jewish scholars such as [[Harvey Falk]] and [[Hyam Maccoby]] have suggested that Jesus was himself a Pharisee. Arguments by Jesus and his disciples against the Pharisees and what he saw as their hypocrisy were most likely examples of disputes among Jews and internal to Judaism that were common at the time, see for example [[Hillel and Shammai]].

===Recent studies on antisemitism in the New Testament===
{{Main article|Antisemitism and the New Testament}}

Professor Lillian C. Freudmann, author of ''Antisemitism in the New Testament'' ([[University Press of America]], 1994) has published a detailed study of the description of Jews in the New Testament, and the historical effects that such passages have had in the Christian community throughout history. Similar studies of such verses have been made by both Christian and Jewish scholars, including, Professors Clark Williamsom (Christian Theological Seminary), [[Hyam Maccoby]] (The Leo Baeck Institute), Norman A. Beck (Texas Lutheran College), and [[Michael Berenbaum]] (Georgetown University). Most rabbis feel that these verses are antisemitic, and many Christian scholars, in America and Europe, have reached the same conclusion. Another example is [[John Dominic Crossan]]'s 1995 ''book titled Who Killed Jesus? Exposing the Roots of Anti-Semitism in the Gospel Story of the Death of Jesus''.

Some biblical scholars have also been accused of holding antisemitic beliefs. [[Bruce J. Malina]], a founding member of [[The Context Group]], has come under criticism for going as far as to deny the Semitic ancestry of modern Israelis. He then ties this back to his work on first century cultural anthropology.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Myles|first=Robert|author2=James Crossley |title=Biblical Scholarship, Jews and Israel: On Bruce Malina, Conspiracy Theories and Ideological Contradictions|journal=The Bible and Interpretation|date=Dec 2012|url=http://www.bibleinterp.com/opeds/myl368013.shtml}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Church Fathers==
&lt;!--{{Main article|Antisemitism in patristics}}--&gt;
{{see|Adversus Judaeos|John Chrysostom}}
{{refimprove section|date=September 2014}}
After [[Saint Paul|Paul]]'s death, Christianity emerged as a separate religion, and [[Pauline Christianity]] emerged as the dominant form of Christianity, especially after Paul, James and the other apostles agreed on a compromise set of requirements.{{Bibleref2c|Acts|15}} Some Christians continued to adhere to aspects of Jewish law, but they were few in number and often considered [[Christian heresy|heretics]] by the Church. One example is the [[Ebionites]], who seem to have denied the [[Virgin Birth (Christian doctrine)|virgin birth]] of Jesus, the physical [[Resurrection of Jesus]], and most of the books that were later [[biblical canon|canonized]] as the [[New Testament]]. For example, the [[Ethiopian Orthodox]] still continue [[Old Testament]] practices such as the [[Shabbat|Sabbath]]. As late as the 4th century [[Church Father]] [[John Chrysostom]] [[John Chrysostom#Homilies on Jews and Judaizing Christians|complained]] that some Christians were still attending Jewish synagogues.

The [[Church Fathers]] identified Jews and Judaism with [[Heresy#Christianity|heresy]] and declared the people of Israel to be ''extra Deum'' (lat. &quot;outside of God&quot;). [[Saint Peter]] of Antioch referred to Christians that refused to worship [[iconoclast|religious images]] as having &quot;Jewish minds&quot;.&lt;ref name=RobertM1&gt;{{cite book|last1=Michael|first1=Robert|title=A history of Catholic antisemitism : the dark side of the church|date=2011|publisher=Palgrave Macmillan|location=New York|isbn=978-0230111318|pages=28–30|edition=1st Palgrave Macmillan pbk.|url=https://books.google.com/?id=8ZnFAAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA28&amp;lpg=PA28&amp;dq=anti-semitism+jews+jewish+heretics+heresy#v=onepage&amp;q=heretic&amp;f=false|accessdate=9 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the early second century AD, the heretic [[Marcion of Sinope]] ({{circa}} 85 – {{circa}} 160 AD) declared that the Jewish God was a different God, inferior to the Christian one,&lt;ref name=&quot;Nicholls1993&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last1=Nicholls |first1=William |title=Christian Antisemitism: A History of Hate |date=1993 |publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield Publishers, Inc. |location=Lanham, Maryland, Boulder, Colorado, New York City, New York, Toronto, Ontario, and Oxford, England |isbn=0-87668-398-7 |pages=178–187 |url=https://books.google.com/?id=cBAAitrH9vMC&amp;pg=PA179&amp;dq=marcion+and+anti+semitism#v=onepage&amp;q=Marcion&amp;f=false |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; and rejected the Jewish scriptures as the product of a lesser deity.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nicholls1993&quot;/&gt; Marcion's teachings, which were extremely popular, rejected Judaism not only as an incomplete revelation, but as a false one as well,&lt;ref name=&quot;Nicholls1993&quot;/&gt; but, at the same time, allowed less blame to be placed on the Jews personally for having not recognized Jesus,&lt;ref name=&quot;Nicholls1993&quot;/&gt; since, in Marcion's worldview, Jesus was not sent by the lesser Jewish God, but by the supreme Christian God, whom the Jews had no reason to recognize.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nicholls1993&quot;/&gt;

In combating Marcion, orthodox apologists conceded that Judaism was an incomplete and inferior religion to Christianity,&lt;ref name=&quot;Nicholls1993&quot;/&gt; while also defending the Jewish scriptures as canonical.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nicholls1993&quot;/&gt; The Church Father [[Tertullian]] ({{circa}} 155 – {{circa}} 240 AD) had a particularly intense personal dislike towards the Jews&lt;ref name=&quot;Nicholls1993&quot;/&gt; and argued that the Gentiles had been chosen by God to replace the Jews, because they were worthier and more honorable.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nicholls1993&quot;/&gt; [[Origen|Origen of Alexandria]] ({{circa}} 184 – {{circa}} 253) was more knowledgeable about Judaism than any of the other Church Fathers,&lt;ref name=&quot;OLeary2004&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=O'Leary|first=Joseph S.|date=2004|chapter=Judaism|title=The Westminster Handbook to Origen|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/?id=riEdrWEDFq0C&amp;pg=PA13&amp;dq=Origen+ordination#v=onepage&amp;q=Origen%20ordination&amp;f=false|location=Louisville, Kentucky|editor-last=McGuckin|editor-first=John Anthony|publisher=Westminster John Knox Press|isbn=0-664-22472-5|pages=135–138|ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; having studied [[Hebrew language|Hebrew]], met [[Hillel, son of Gamaliel III|Rabbi Hillel the Younger]], consulted and debated with Jewish scholars, and been influenced by the allegorical interpretations of [[Philo|Philo of Alexandria]].&lt;ref name=&quot;OLeary2004&quot;/&gt; Origen defended the canonicity of the Old Testament&lt;ref name=&quot;OLeary2004&quot;/&gt; and defended Jews of the past as having been chosen by God for their merits.&lt;ref name=&quot;OLeary2004&quot;/&gt; Nonetheless, he condemned contemporary Jews for not understanding their own Law, insisted that Christians were the &quot;true Israel&quot;, and blamed the Jews for the death of Christ.&lt;ref name=&quot;OLeary2004&quot;/&gt; He did, however, maintain that Jews would eventually attain salvation in the final ''[[apocatastasis]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;OLeary2004&quot;/&gt;

Patristic bishops of the patristic era such as [[Augustine of Hippo|Augustine]] argued that the Jews should be left alive and suffering as a perpetual reminder of their [[deicide|murder of Christ]]. Like his anti-Jewish teacher, [[Ambrose of Milan]], he defined Jews as a special subset of those damned to [[hell]]. As &quot;[[Witness People]]&quot;, he sanctified collective punishment for the [[Jewish deicide]] and enslavement of Jews to Catholics: &quot;Not by bodily death, shall the ungodly race of carnal Jews perish ... 'Scatter them abroad, take away their strength. And bring them down O [[God the Son|Lord]]{{' &quot;}}. Augustine claimed to &quot;love&quot; the Jews but as a means to [[Proselytization and counter-proselytization of Jews|convert]] them to Christianity. Sometimes he identified all Jews with the evil Judas and developed the doctrine (together with [[St. Cyprian]]) that there was &quot;no salvation outside the Church&quot;.&lt;ref name=RobertM11&gt;{{cite book|last1=Michael|first1=Robert|title=A history of Catholic antisemitism : the dark side of the church|date=2011|publisher=Palgrave Macmillan|location=New York|isbn=978-0230111318|pages=|edition=1st Palgrave Macmillan pbk.|url=https://books.google.com/?id=8ZnFAAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA28&amp;lpg=PA28&amp;dq=anti-semitism+jews+jewish+heretics+heresy#v=onepage&amp;q=heretic&amp;f=false|accessdate=9 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other Church Fathers, such as [[John Chrysostom]], went further in their condemnation. The Catholic editor Paul Harkins wrote that [[St. John Chrysostom]]'s anti-Jewish theology &quot;is no longer tenable (..) For these objectively unchristian acts he cannot be excused, even if he is the product of his times.&quot; John Chrysostom held, as most Church Fathers did, that the sins of all Jews were communal and endless, to him his Jewish neighbours were the collective representation of all alleged crimes of all preexisting Jews. All Church Fathers applied the passages of the New Testament concerning the alleged advocation of the crucifixion of Christ to all Jews of his day, the Jews were the ultimate evil. However, John Chrysostom went so far to say that because Jews rejected the [[God in Christianity|Christian God]] in human flesh, Christ, they therefore deserved to be killed: &quot;grew fit for slaughter.&quot; In citing the New Testament,{{Bibleref2c|Luke|19:27}} he claimed that Jesus was speaking about Jews when he said, &quot;as for these enemies of mine who did not want me to reign over them, bring them here and ''slay them'' before me.&quot;&lt;ref name=RobertM11/&gt;

[[St. Jerome]] identified Jews with [[Judas Iscariot]] and the immoral use of money (&quot;Judas is cursed, that in Judas the Jews may be accursed... their prayers turn into sins&quot;). Jerome's homiletical assaults, that may have served as the basis for the anti-Jewish [[Good Friday prayer for the Jews|Good Friday liturgy]], contrasts Jews with the evil, and that &quot;the ceremonies of the Jews are harmful and deadly to Christians&quot;, whoever keeps them was doomed to the [[devil]]: &quot;My enemies are the Jews; they have conspired in hatred against Me, crucified Me, heaped evils of all kinds upon Me, blasphemed Me.&quot;&lt;ref name=RobertM11/&gt;

[[Ephraim the Syrian]] wrote polemics against Jews in the 4th century, including the repeated accusation that Satan dwells among them as a partner. The writings were directed at Christians who were being proselytized by Jews. Ephraim feared that they were slipping back into Judaism; thus, he portrayed the Jews as enemies of Christianity, like Satan, to emphasize the contrast between the two religions, namely, that Christianity was Godly and true and Judaism was Satanic and false. Like John Chrysostom, his objective was to dissuade Christians from reverting to Judaism by emphasizing what he saw as the wickedness of the Jews and their religion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://syrcom.cua.edu/Hugoye/Vol1No2/HV1N2Palmer.html |title=Ephraim the Syrian and his polemics against Jews |publisher=Syrcom.cua.edu |date= |accessdate=2013-07-10 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120807105307/http://syrcom.cua.edu/Hugoye/Vol1No2/HV1N2Palmer.html |archive-date=2012-08-07 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://syrcom.cua.edu/Hugoye/Vol5No1/HV5N1Shepardson.html |title=Analysis of Ephraim's writings |publisher=Syrcom.cua.edu |date= |accessdate=2013-07-10 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120807105203/http://syrcom.cua.edu/Hugoye/Vol5No1/HV5N1Shepardson.html |archive-date=2012-08-07 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, there are also positive remarks from the Church Fathers on the issue, such as [[Eusebius of Caesarea]] (circa. 263-340 A.D) in his Ecclesiastical History, who said, &quot;The race of the Hebrews is not new, but is honoured among all men for its antiquity and is itself well known to all.&quot;

==Middle Ages==
{{Main article|Medieval antisemitism}}
[[File:1182 french expulsion of jews.jpg|thumb|A miniature from [[Grandes Chroniques de France]] depicting the expulsion of Jews from France in 1182.]]
[[Bernard of Clairvaux]] (1090-1153), a Doctor of the Catholic Church, said &quot;For us the Jews are Scripture's living words, because they remind us of what Our Lord suffered. They are not to be persecuted, killed, or even put to flight.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Catholic Book of Quotations, by Leo Knowles, Copyright 2004 by Our Sunday Visitor Publishing Division, Our Sunday Visitor, Inc. All rights reserved.&lt;/ref&gt;

Jews were subject to a wide range of legal [[Disabilities (Jewish)|disabilities]] and restrictions in Medieval Europe. Jews were excluded from many trades, the occupations varying with place and time, and determined by the influence of various non-Jewish competing interests. Often Jews were barred from all occupations but money-lending and peddling, with even these at times forbidden. Jews' association to money lending would carry on throughout history in the stereotype of Jews being greedy and perpetuating capitalism.

In the later medieval period, the number of Jews permitted to reside in certain places was limited; they were concentrated in [[ghetto]]s, and were not allowed to own land; they were subject to discriminatory taxes on entering cities or districts other than their own,{{citation needed|date=December 2012}}
The [[Oath More Judaico]], the form of oath required from Jewish witnesses, in some places developed bizarre or humiliating forms, e.g. in Swabian law of the 13th century,  the Jew would be required to stand on the hide of a sow or a bloody lamb.{{citation needed|date=September 2016}}

The [[Fourth Lateran Council]] in 1215 was the first to proclaim the requirement for Jews to wear something that distinguished them as Jews (and Muslims the same).
On many occasions, Jews were accused of a [[blood libel]], the supposed drinking of blood of Christian children in mockery of the Christian [[Eucharist]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Ritual murder in Russia, Eastern Europe, and beyond : new histories of an old accusation|last=|first=|publisher=|others=Avrutin, Eugene M.,, Dekel-Chen, Jonathan L.,, Weinberg, Robert|isbn=9780253026576|location=Bloomington, Indiana|pages=39–40|oclc=972200793|date = 2017-07-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===''Sicut Judaeis''===
''[[Sicut Judaeis]]'' (the &quot;Constitution for the Jews&quot;) was the official position of the papacy regarding Jews throughout the Middle Ages and later. The first [[Papal bull|bull]] was issued in about 1120 by [[Calixtus II]], intended to protect Jews who suffered during the [[First Crusade]], and was reaffirmed by many popes, even until the 15th century although they were not always strictly upheld.

The bull forbade, besides other things, Christians from coercing Jews to convert, or to harm them, or to take their property, or to disturb the celebration of their festivals, or to interfere with their cemeteries, on pain of excommunication.&lt;ref&gt;{{CathEncy|wstitle=History of Toleration}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Popular antisemitism===
[[File:Burning Jews.jpg|thumb|Jews burned alive for the alleged [[host desecration]] in [[Deggendorf]], Bavaria, in 1337]]
Antisemitism in popular European Christian culture escalated beginning in the 13th century. [[Blood libels]] and [[host desecration]] drew popular attention and led to many cases of persecution against Jews. Many believed Jews poisoned wells to cause plagues. In the case of blood libel it was widely believed that the Jews would kill a child before Easter and needed Christian blood to bake matzo. Throughout history if a Christian child was murdered accusations of blood libel would arise no matter how small the Jewish population. The Church often added to the fire by portraying the dead child as a martyr who had been tortured and child had powers like Jesus was believed to. Sometimes the children were even made into Saints.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Butcher's Tale&quot;&gt;The Butcher's Tale&lt;/ref&gt; Antisemitic imagery such as [[Judensau]] and [[Ecclesia et Synagoga]] recurred in Christian art and architecture.

In Iceland, one of the hymns repeated in the days leading up to Easter includes the lines,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jcpa.org/phas/phas-vilhjalmur-f04.htm |title=Iceland, the Jews, and Anti-Semitism, 1625-2004 - Vilhjálmur Örn Vilhjálmsson |publisher=Jcpa.org |date= |accessdate=2013-07-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;
:The righteous Law of Moses
:The Jews here misapplied,
:Which their deceit exposes,
:Their hatred and their pride.
:The judgement is the Lord's.
:When by falsification
:The foe makes accusation,
:It's His to make awards.

===Persecutions and expulsions===
[[File:Massaker von Lissabon.jpg|thumb|[[Lisbon Massacre]] in 1506]]
During the [[Middle Ages]] in [[Europe]] persecutions and formal expulsions of Jews were liable to occur at intervals, although it should be said that this was also the case for other minority communities, regardless of whether they were religious or ethnic. There were particular outbursts of riotous persecution during the [[Rhineland massacres]] of 1096 in Germany accompanying the lead-up to the [[First Crusade]], many involving the crusaders as they travelled to the East. There were many local expulsions from cities by local rulers and city councils.  In Germany the [[Holy Roman Emperor]] generally tried to restrain persecution, if only for economic reasons, but he was often unable to exert much influence.  In the [[Edict of Expulsion]], [[Edward I of England|King Edward I]] expelled all the Jews from England in 1290 (only after ransoming some 3,000 among the most wealthy of them), on the accusation of [[usury]] and undermining loyalty to the dynasty.  In 1306 there was a wave of persecution in France, and there were widespread [[Black Death Jewish persecutions]] as the Jews were blamed by many Christians for the plague, or spreading it.&lt;ref name=&quot;isbn0-7065-1327-4&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author= |authorlink= |editor= |others= |title=Anti-Semitism |edition= |language= |publisher=Keter Books |location=Jerusalem |year=1974 |origyear= |pages= |quote= |isbn=9780706513271 |oclc= |doi= |url= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Teacher's&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Map of Jewish expulsions and resettlement areas in Europe|url=http://fcit.usf.edu/HOLOCAUST/gallery/expuls.htm|work=Florida Center for Instructional Technology, College of Education, University of South Florida|publisher=A Teacher's Guide to the Holocaust|accessdate=24 December 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  As late as 1519, the Imperial city of [[Regensburg]] took advantage of the recent death of [[Emperor Maximilian I]] to expel its 500 Jews.&lt;ref&gt;Wood, Christopher S., ''Albrecht Altdorfer and the Origins of Landscape'', p. 251, 1993, Reaktion Books, London, {{ISBN|0948462469}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Expulsion of Jews from Spain====
{{Main article|Alhambra Decree}}
{{unreferenced section|date=September 2014}}
The largest expulsion of Jews followed the [[Reconquista]] or the reunification of Spain, and it preceded the [[Expulsion of the Moriscos|expulsion of the Muslims]] who would not convert, in spite of the protection of their religious rights promised by the [[Treaty of Granada (1491)]].  On 31 March 1492 [[Ferdinand II of Aragon]] and [[Isabella I of Castile]], the rulers of [[Spain]] who financed [[Christopher Columbus]]' voyage to the New World just a few months later in 1492, declared that all Jews in their territories should either convert to Christianity or leave the country. While some converted, many others left for [[Portugal]], [[France]], [[Italy]] (including the [[Papal States]]), [[Netherlands]], [[Poland]], the [[Ottoman Empire]], and [[North Africa]]. Many of those who had fled to Portugal were later expelled by [[Manuel I of Portugal|King Manuel]] in 1497 or left to avoid forced conversion and [[Marranos|persecution]].

==Renaissance to the 17th century==
{{unreferenced section|date=September 2014}}

===Cum Nimis Absurdum===
On 14 July 1555, [[Pope Paul IV]] issued [[papal bull]] [[Cum nimis absurdum]] which revoked all the rights of the Jewish community and placed religious and economic restrictions on [[Jews]] in the [[Papal States]], renewed anti-Jewish legislation and subjected Jews to various degradations and restrictions on their personal freedom.

The bull established the [[Roman Ghetto]] and required Jews of Rome, which had existed as a community since before Christian times and which numbered about 2,000 at the time, to live in it. The Ghetto was a walled quarter with three gates that were locked at night. Jews were also restricted to one [[synagogue]] per city.

Paul IV's successor, [[Pope Pius IV]], enforced the creation of other ghettos in most Italian towns, and his successor, [[Pope Pius V]], recommended them to other bordering states.

===Protestant Reformation===
[[File:1543 On the Jews and Their Lies by Martin Luther.jpg|thumb|Luther's 1543 pamphlet ''[[On the Jews and Their Lies (Martin Luther)|On the Jews and Their Lies]]'']]
{{See also|Luther and antisemitism}}

[[Martin Luther]] at first made overtures towards the Jews, believing that the &quot;evils&quot; of [[Catholic Church|Catholicism]] had prevented their conversion to Christianity. When his call to convert to his version of Christianity was unsuccessful, he became hostile to them.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.theologian.org.uk/churchhistory/lutherandthejews.html|title=Luther and the Jews|website=www.theologian.org.uk|access-date=2017-02-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{citation needed|date=February 2017}}

In his book ''[[On the Jews and Their Lies]]'', Luther excoriates them as &quot;venomous beasts, vipers, disgusting scum, canders, devils incarnate.&quot;  He provided detailed recommendations for a [[pogrom]] against them, calling for their permanent [[oppression]] and expulsion, writing &quot;Their private houses must be destroyed and devastated, they could be lodged in stables. Let the magistrates burn their synagogues and let whatever escapes be covered with sand and mud. Let them be forced to work, and if this avails nothing, we will be compelled to expel them like dogs in order not to expose ourselves to incurring divine wrath and eternal damnation from the Jews and their lies.&quot;  At one point he wrote: &quot;...we are at fault in not slaying them...&quot;  a passage that &quot;may be termed the first work of modern antisemitism, and a giant step forward on the road to [[the Holocaust]].&quot;&lt;ref name=Johnson&gt;[[Paul Johnson (writer)|Johnson, Paul]]. ''A History of the Jews'', HarperCollins Publishers, 1987, p.242. {{ISBN|5-551-76858-9}}. [[Paul Johnson (writer)|Paul Johnson]].&lt;/ref&gt;

Luther's harsh comments about the Jews are seen by many as a continuation of medieval Christian antisemitism. In his final sermon shortly before his death, however, Luther preached: &quot;We want to treat them with Christian love and to pray for them, so that they might become converted and would receive the Lord.&quot;&lt;ref name=Luther&gt;[[Martin Luther|Luther, Martin]]. ''D. Martin Luthers Werke: kritische Gesamtausgabe'', Weimar: Hermann Böhlaus Nachfolger, 1920, Vol. 51, p. 195.&lt;/ref&gt;

==18th century==
In accordance with the anti-Jewish precepts of the [[Russian Orthodox Church]],&lt;ref name=Beller&gt;Steven Beller (2007)  Antisemitism: A Very Short Introduction. Oxford University Press 2007. 
{{ISBN|978-0192892775}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|14}} Russia's discriminatory policies towards Jews intensified when the [[partition of Poland]] in the 18th century resulted, for the first time in Russian history, in the possession of land with a large Jewish population.&lt;ref name=Beller/&gt;{{rp|28}} This land was designated as the [[Pale of Settlement]] from which Jews were forbidden to migrate into the interior of Russia.&lt;ref name=Beller/&gt;{{rp|28}}  In 1772 [[Catherine the Great|Catherine II]], the empress of Russia, forced the Jews living in the Pale of Settlement to stay in their ''[[shtetls]]'' and forbade them from returning to the towns that they occupied before the partition of Poland.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/vjw/Poland.html |title=The Virtual Jewish History Tour By Rebecca Weiner |publisher=Jewishvirtuallibrary.org |date= |accessdate=2013-07-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==19th century==
{{See also|Christianity and Judaism|Relations between Catholicism and Judaism}}
{{unreferenced section|date=September 2014}}
Throughout the 19th century and into the 20th, the Roman Catholic Church still incorporated strong antisemitic elements, despite increasing attempts to separate anti-Judaism (opposition to the Jewish religion on religious grounds) and racial antisemitism. Brown University historian [[David Kertzer]], working from the Vatican archive, has argued in his book ''[[The Popes Against the Jews]]'' that in the 19th and early 20th centuries the Roman Catholic Church adhered to a distinction between &quot;good antisemitism&quot; and &quot;bad antisemitism&quot;. The &quot;bad&quot; kind promoted hatred of Jews because of their descent. This was considered un-Christian because the Christian message was intended for all of humanity regardless of ethnicity; anyone could become a Christian. The &quot;good&quot; kind criticized alleged [[Jewish conspiracy|Jewish conspiracies]] to control newspapers, banks, and other institutions, to care only about accumulation of wealth, etc. Many Catholic bishops wrote articles criticizing Jews on such grounds, and, when they were accused of promoting hatred of Jews, they would remind people that they condemned the &quot;bad&quot; kind of antisemitism. Kertzer's work is not without critics. Scholar of Jewish-Christian relations [[Rabbi David G. Dalin]], for example, criticized Kertzer in the ''[[Weekly Standard]]'' for using evidence selectively.

===Opposition to the French Revolution===

The [[counter-revolutionary]] Catholic royalist [[Louis de Bonald]] stands out among the earliest figures to explicitly call for the reversal of Jewish emancipation in the wake of the [[French Revolution]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Battini1&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title=Socialism of Fools: Capitalism and Modern Anti-Semitism|last=Battini|first=Michele|publisher=Columbia University Press|year=2016|isbn=|location=|pages=2–7 and 30–37}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Katz |first1=Jacob |title=From Prejudice to Destruction: Anti-Semitism, 1700-1933 |date=1980 |publisher=Harvard University Press |pages=112–115}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bonald's attacks on the Jews are likely to have influenced [[Napoléon Bonaparte|Napoleon]]'s decision to limit the civil rights of Alsatian Jews.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Socialism of Fools: Capitalism and Modern Anti-Semitism|last=Battini|first=Michele|publisher=Columbia University Press|year=2016|isbn=|location=|pages=164}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Garṭner |first1=Aryeh |last2=Gartner |first2=Lloyd P. |title=History of the Jews in Modern Times |date=2001 |publisher=Oxford University Press |page=116}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Joskowicz |first1=Ari |title=The Modernity of Others: Jewish Anti-Catholicism in Germany and France |date=2013 |publisher=Stanford University Press |page=99}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Michael |first1=Robert |last2=Rosen |first2=Philip |title=Dictionary of Antisemitism from the Earliest Times to the Present |date=2007 |publisher=Scarecrow Press |page=67}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bonald's article ''Sur les juifs'' (1806) was one of the most venomous screeds of its era and furnished a paradigm which combined anti-liberalism, a defense of a rural society, traditional Christian antisemitism, and the identification of Jews with bankers and finance capital, which would in turn influence many subsequent right-wing reactionaries such as [[Roger Gougenot des Mousseaux]], [[Charles Maurras]], and [[Édouard Drumont]], nationalists such as [[Maurice Barrès]] and [[Paolo Orano]], and antisemitic socialists such as [[Alphonse Toussenel]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Battini1&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Sanos |first1=Sandrine |title=The Aesthetics of Hate: Far-Right Intellectuals, Antisemitism, and Gender in 1930s France |date=2012 |publisher=Stanford University Press |page=47}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Laqueur |first1=Walter |last2=Baumel |first2=Judith Tydor |title=The Holocaust Encyclopedia |date=2001 |publisher=Yale University Press |page=20}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bonald furthermore declared that the Jews were an &quot;alien&quot; people, a &quot;state within a state&quot;, and should be forced to wear a distinctive mark to more easily identify and discriminate against them.&lt;ref name=&quot;Battini1&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Michael1&quot; /&gt;

In the 1840s, the popular counter-revolutionary Catholic journalist [[Louis Veuillot]] propagated Bonald's arguments against the Jewish &quot;financial aristocracy&quot; along with vicious attacks against the Talmud and the Jews as a &quot;deicidal people&quot; driven by hatred to &quot;enslave&quot; Christians.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Graetz |first1=Michael |title=The Jews in Nineteenth-century France: From the French Revolution to the Alliance Israélite Universelle |date=1996 |publisher=Stanford University Press |page=208}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Michael1&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last1=Michael |first1=Robert |title=A History of Catholic Antisemitism: The Dark Side of the Church |date=2008 |publisher=Springer |pages=128–129}}&lt;/ref&gt; Gougenot des Mousseaux's ''Le Juif, le judaïsme et la judaïsation des peuples chrétiens'' (1869) has been called a &quot;Bible of modern antisemitism&quot; and was translated into German by Nazi ideologue [[Alfred Rosenberg]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Michael1&quot; /&gt; Between 1882 and 1886 alone, French priests published twenty antisemitic books blaming France's ills on the Jews and urging the government to consign them back to the ghettos, expel them, or hang them from the gallows.&lt;ref name=&quot;Michael1&quot; /&gt; 

In Italy the Jesuit priest [[Antonio Bresciani (writer)|Antonio Bresciani]]'s highly popular novel 1850 novel ''L'Ebreo di Verona'' (''The Jew of Verona'') shaped religious anti-Semitism for decades, as did his work for ''[[La Civiltà Cattolica]]'', which he helped launch.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Brustein |first1=William |title=Roots of Hate: Anti-Semitism in Europe Before the Holocaust |date=2003 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |page=76}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Feinstein |first1=Wiley |title=The Civilization of the Holocaust in Italy: Poets, Artists, Saints, Anti-semites |date=2003 |publisher=Fairleigh Dickinson Univ Press |pages=151–152}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Pope Pius VII]] (1800–1823) had the walls of the Jewish [[ghetto]] in Rome rebuilt after the Jews were [[Jewish emancipation|emancipated]] by [[Napoleon and the Jews|Napoleon]], and Jews were restricted to the ghetto through the end of the [[Papal States]] in 1870. Official Catholic organizations, such as the [[Jesuits]], banned candidates &quot;who are descended from the Jewish race unless it is clear that their father, grandfather, and great-grandfather have belonged to the Catholic Church&quot; until 1946.

==20th century==
In Russia, under the Tsarist regime, antisemitism intensified in the early years of the 20th century and was given official favour when the secret police forged the notorious ''[[Protocols of the Elders of Zion]]'', a document purported to be a transcription of a plan by Jewish elders to achieve [[New World Order (conspiracy theory)|global domination]].&lt;ref&gt;Steven Beller (2007) ''Antisemitism: A Very Short Introduction'': p. 32&lt;/ref&gt; Violence against the Jews in the [[Kishinev pogrom]] in 1903 was continued after the 1905 revolution by the activities of the [[Black Hundreds]].&lt;ref&gt;Steven Beller (2007) ''Antisemitism: A Very Short Introduction'': p. 29&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Menahem Mendel Beilis|Beilis Trial]] of 1913 showed that it was possible to revive the blood libel accusation in Russia.

Catholic writers such as [[Ernest Jouin]], who published the ''Protocols'' in French, seamlessly blended racial and religious anti-Semitism, as in his statement that &quot;from the triple viewpoint of race, of nationality, and of religion, the Jew has become the enemy of humanity.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Michael&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last1=Michael |first1=R. |title=A History of Catholic Antisemitism: The Dark Side of the Church |date=2008 |publisher=Springer |page=171}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Pope Pius XI]] praised Jouin for &quot;combating our mortal [Jewish] enemy&quot; and appointed him to high papal office as a [[protonotary apostolic]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Marks&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last1=Marks |first1=Steven Gary |title=How Russia Shaped the Modern World: From Art to Anti-semitism, Ballet to Bolshevism |date=2003 |publisher=Princeton University Press |page=159}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Michael&quot; /&gt;

===WWI to the eve of WWII===
{{Main article|Pope Benedict XV and Judaism}}
In 1916, in the midst of the [[World War I|First World War]], [[American Jews]] petitioned Pope Benedict XV on behalf of the [[History of the Jews in Poland|Polish Jews]].

===Nazi antisemitism===
{{further|Pope Pius XI and Judaism}}
During a meeting with Roman Catholic Bishop {{Interlanguage link multi|Wilhelm Berning|de|3=Hermann Wilhelm Berning}} of Osnabrück On April 26, 1933, Hitler declared:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
“I have been attacked because of my handling of the Jewish question. The Catholic Church considered the Jews pestilent for fifteen hundred years, put them in ghettos, etc., because it recognized the Jews for what they were. In the epoch of liberalism the danger was no longer recognized. I am moving back toward the time in which a fifteen-hundred-year-long tradition was implemented. I do not set race over religion, but I recognize the representatives of this race as pestilent for the state and for the Church, and perhaps I am thereby doing Christianity a great service by pushing them out of schools and public functions.”
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The transcript of the discussion contains no response by Bishop Berning. [[Martin Rhonheimer]] does not consider that unusual since in his opinion, for a Catholic Bishop in 1933 there was nothing particularly objectionable &quot;in this historically correct reminder&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;firstthings.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=The Holocaust: What Was Not Said'' |first=Martin |last=Rhonheimer |publisher=First Things Magazine |date=November 2003 |accessdate=1 July 2009 |url=http://www.firstthings.com/article/2007/01/the-holocaust-what-was-not-said-10 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20091016114240/http://www.firstthings.com/article/2007/01/the-holocaust-what-was-not-said-10 |archivedate=16 October 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Nazis used [[Martin Luther]]'s book, ''[[On the Jews and Their Lies]]'' (1543), to [[Luther and antisemitism#Use by the Nazis|claim]] a moral righteousness for their ideology.  Luther even went so far as to advocate the murder of Jews who refused to convert to Christianity by writing that &quot;we are at fault in not slaying them&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Luther, Martin. ''On the Jews and Their'' ''Lies'', cited in Robert.Michael. &quot;Luther, Luther Scholars, and the Jews,&quot;''Encounter'' 46 (Autumn 1985) No.4.343–344&lt;/ref&gt;

Archbishop [[Robert Runcie]] has asserted that: &quot;Without centuries of Christian antisemitism, Hitler's passionate hatred would never have been so fervently echoed... because for centuries Christians have held Jews collectively responsible for the death of [[Jesus]]. On Good Friday Jews, have in times past, cowered behind locked doors with fear of a Christian mob seeking 'revenge' for deicide. Without the poisoning of Christian minds through the centuries, the Holocaust is unthinkable.&quot;&lt;ref name=HarriesAfter&gt;Richard Harries.  After the evil: Christianity and Judaism in the shadow of the Holocaust. Oxford University Press, 2003.  {{ISBN|978-0199263134}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|21}} The dissident Catholic priest [[Hans Küng]] has written that &quot;Nazi anti-Judaism was the work of godless, anti-Christian criminals. But it would not have been possible without the almost two thousand years' pre-history of 'Christian' anti-Judaism...&quot;&lt;ref name=Kung&gt;Hans Küng. On Being a Christian. Doubleday, Garden City NY, 1976 {{ISBN|978-0385027120}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|169}}

The document [[Dabru Emet]] was issued by over 220 [[rabbi]]s and [[intellectual]]s from all branches of [[Judaism]] in 2000 as a statement about Jewish-Christian relations. This document states,&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;[[Nazism]] was not a Christian phenomenon. Without the long history of Christian anti-Judaism and Christian violence against Jews, Nazi ideology could not have taken hold nor could it have been carried out. Too many Christians participated in, or were sympathetic to, Nazi atrocities against Jews. Other Christians did not protest sufficiently against these atrocities. But Nazism itself was not an inevitable outcome of Christianity.&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
According to American [[historian]] [[Lucy Dawidowicz]], antisemitism has a long history within Christianity. The line of &quot;antisemitic descent&quot; from Luther, the author of ''[[On the Jews and Their Lies]]'', to Hitler is &quot;easy to draw.&quot; In her ''[[The War Against the Jews]], 1933-1945'', she contends that Luther and Hitler were obsessed by the &quot;demonologized universe&quot; inhabited by Jews. Dawidowicz writes that the similarities between Luther's anti-Jewish writings and modern antisemitism are no coincidence, because they derived from a common history of ''Judenhass'', which can be traced to [[Haman (Bible)|Haman]]'s advice to [[Ahasuerus]]. Although modern German antisemitism also has its roots in German [[nationalism]] and the [[liberalism|liberal]] revolution of 1848, [[Christianity|Christian]] antisemitism she writes is a foundation that was laid by the [[Roman Catholic]] Church and &quot;upon which Luther built.&quot;&lt;ref name=Dawidowicz&gt;Lucy Dawidowicz ''The War Against the Jews, 1933-1945''. First published 1975; this Bantam edition 1986, p.23. {{ISBN|0-553-34532-X}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Collaborating Christians====
* [[German Christians]]
* ''[[Gleichschaltung]]''
* [[Hanns Kerrl]], Minister for Ecclesiastical Affairs
* [[Positive Christianity]] (the approved Nazi version of Christianity)
* [[Protestant Reich Church]]

====Opposition to the Holocaust====
The [[Confessing Church]] was, in 1934, the first Christian opposition group. The Catholic Church officially condemned the Nazi theory of racism in Germany in 1937 with the [[encyclical]] &quot;''[[Mit brennender Sorge]]''&quot;, signed by [[Pope Pius XI]], and Cardinal [[Michael von Faulhaber]] led the Catholic opposition, preaching against racism.

Many individual Christian clergy and laypeople of all denominations had to pay for their opposition with their life, including:
* Catholic priest, [[Maximilian Kolbe]].
* Lutheran pastor [[Dietrich Bonhoeffer]]
* the Catholic parson of Berlin Cathedral, [[Bernhard Lichtenberg]].
* the mostly Catholic members of the [[Munich]] resistance group [[White Rose]] around [[Hans Scholl|Hans]] and [[Sophie Scholl]].

By the 1940s fewer Christians were willing to oppose Nazi policy publicly, but many secretly helped save the lives of Jews. There are many sections of Israel's Holocaust Remembrance Museum, [[Yad Vashem]], dedicated to honoring these &quot;[[Righteous Among the Nations]]&quot;.

====Pope Pius XII====
{{further|Pope Pius XII and Judaism}}

Before becoming Pope, Cardinal Pacelli addressed the [[International Eucharistic Congress]] in [[Budapest]] on 25–30 May 1938 during which he made reference to the Jews &quot;whose lips curse [Christ] and whose hearts reject him even today&quot;; at this time antisemitic laws were in the process of being formulated in Hungary.&lt;ref&gt;Donald J. Dietrich.  Christian responses to the Holocaust: moral and ethical issues
Religion, theology, and the Holocaust. Syracuse University Press, 2003, {{ISBN|0-8156-3029-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|92}}

The 1937 encyclical ''[[Mit brennender Sorge]]'' was issued by [[Pope Pius XI]],&lt;ref&gt;Coppa, Frank J. (1999). ''Controversial Concordats.'' Catholic University of America Press. p. 132&lt;/ref&gt; but drafted by the future [[Pope Pius XII]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Pham45&quot;&gt;Pham, p. 45, quote: &quot;When Pius XI was complimented on the publication, in 1937, of his encyclical denouncing Nazism, ''Mit brennender Sorge'', his response was to point to his Secretary of State and say bluntly, 'The credit is his.'&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; and read from the pulpits of all German Catholic churches, it condemned Nazi ideology and has been characterized by scholars as the &quot;first great official public document to dare to confront and criticize [[Nazism]]&quot; and &quot;one of the greatest such condemnations ever issued by the Vatican.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Bokenkotter, pp. 389–392, quote &quot;And when Hitler showed increasing belligerence toward the Church, Pius met the challenge with a decisiveness that astonished the world. His encyclical ''Mit brennender Sorge'' was the 'first great official public document to dare to confront and criticize Nazism' and 'one of the greatest such condemnations ever issued by the Vatican.' Smuggled into Germany, it was read from all the Catholic pulpits on Palm Sunday in March 1937. It denounced the Nazi &quot;myth of blood and soil&quot; and decried its neopaganism. The Nazis retaliated by closing and sealing all the presses that had printed it and took numerous vindictive measures against the Church, including staging a long series of immorality trials of Catholic clergy.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

In the summer of 1942, Pius explained to his college of Cardinals the reasons for the great gulf that existed between Jews and Christians at the theological level: &quot;''Jerusalem has responded to His call and to His grace with the same rigid blindness and stubborn ingratitude that has led it along the path of guilt to the murder of God.&quot;'' Historian Guido Knopp describes these comments of Pius as being &quot;''incomprehensible''&quot; at a time when &quot;''Jerusalem was being murdered by the million''&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Knopp, Guido. ''Hitler's Holocaust'', Sutton,2000, p. 250, {{ISBN|0-7509-2700-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; This traditional adversarial relationship with Judaism would be reversed in ''[[Nostra aetate]]'' issued during the Second Vatican Council.&lt;ref&gt;Kessler, Edward, Neil Wenborn.'' A dictionary of Jewish-Christian relations''&quot;, p. 86, Cambridge University Press, 2005, {{ISBN|0-521-82692-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Prominent members of the Jewish community have contradicted the criticisms of Pius and spoke highly of his efforts to protect Jews.&lt;ref&gt;Bokenkotter, Thomas (2004). A Concise History of the Catholic Church. Doubleday. pp. 480–481, quote: &quot;A recent article by American rabbi, David G. Dalin, challenges this judgment. He calls making Pius XII a target of moral outrage a failure of historical understanding, and he thinks Jews should reject any 'attempt to usurp the Holocaust' for the partisan purposes at work in this debate. Dalin surmises that well-known Jews such as Albert Einstein, Golda Meir, Moshe Sharett, and Rabbi Isaac Herzog would likely have been shocked at these attacks on Pope Pius. ... Dalin points out that Rabbi Herzog, the chief rabbi of Israel, sent a message in February 1944 declaring 'the people of Israel will never forget what His Holiness ... (is) doing for our unfortunate brothers and sisters in the most tragic hour of our history.'&quot; Dalin cites these tributes as recognition of the work of the Holy See in saving hundreds of thousands of Jews.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; The Israeli historian [[Pinchas Lapide]] interviewed war survivors and concluded that Pius XII &quot;was instrumental in saving at least 700,000, but probably as many as 860,000&amp;nbsp;Jews from certain death at Nazi hands&quot;. Some historians dispute this estimate.&lt;ref&gt;Deák, István (2001). Essays on Hitler's Europe. University of Nebraska Press. p. 182.&lt;/ref&gt;

===&quot;White Power&quot; movement===
[[File:proper hands.jpg|thumb|right|In Proper Hands. The Protestant Christian dominated KKK hinting at violence against Jews and Catholics. Illustration by Rev. [[Branford Clarke]] from ''[[Heroes of the Fiery Cross]]'' (1928), by Bishop [[Alma White]] and published by the [[Pillar of Fire Church]] in [[Zarephath, New Jersey]].]]

The [[Christian Identity]] movement, the [[Ku Klux Klan]] and other [[White supremacy|White supremacist]] groups have expressed antisemitic views. They claim that their antisemitism is based on purported Jewish control of the media, international banks, radical [[left-wing politics]], and the Jews' promotion of [[multiculturalism]], anti-Christian groups, [[liberalism]] and perverse organizations. They rebuke charges of [[racism]] by claiming that Jews who share their ideology maintain membership in their organizations. A racial belief which is common among these groups, but not universal among them, is an [[Historical revisionism (political)|alternative history]] doctrine, which is sometimes called [[British Israelism]]. In some of its forms, this doctrine absolutely denies the view that modern Jews have any racial connection to the [[History of ancient Israel and Judah|Israel of the Bible]]. Instead, according to extreme forms of this doctrine, the true racial [[Israelites]] and the true humans are the members of the Adamic ([[white people|white]]) race. These groups are often rejected and not even considered Christian groups by mainstream [[Christian denomination]]s and the vast majority of [[Christians]] around the world.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Barkun for the Southern Poverty Law Center. [http://www.splcenter.org/get-informed/intelligence-files/ideology/christian-identity/the-christian-identity-movement The Christian Identity Movement] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140930190613/http://www.splcenter.org/get-informed/intelligence-files/ideology/christian-identity/the-christian-identity-movement |date=2014-09-30 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Southern Poverty Law Center. [http://www.splcenter.org/get-informed/intelligence-files/ideology/ku-klux-klan Ku Klux Klan]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Post World War II antisemitism===
Antisemitism remains a substantial problem in Europe and to a greater or lesser degree, it also exists in many other nations, including [[Eastern Europe]] and the [[Post-Soviet states|former Soviet Union]], and tensions between some [[Islam in Europe|Muslim]] immigrants and Jews have grown increasingly frequent across Europe.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Stone |first=Andrea |url=https://www.usatoday.com/news/world/2004-11-22-jews-france_x.htm |title=As attacks rise in France, Jews flock to Israel |publisher=Usatoday.com |date=2004-11-22 |accessdate=2013-07-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.haaretz.com/hasen/spages/841445.html Jews for Le Pen] by Daniel Ben-Simon. Haaretz. 25/03/07&lt;/ref&gt; The [[US State Department]] reports that antisemitism has increased dramatically in Europe and Eurasia since 2000.&lt;ref&gt;[https://2001-2009.state.gov/g/drl/rls/40258.htm State Department Report on Anti-Semitism: Europe and Eurasia: anti-Semitism in Europe increased in recent years] (2005 report)&lt;/ref&gt;

While in a decline since the 1940s, there is still a measurable amount of antisemitism in the United States of America as well, although acts of violence are rare. For example, the influential evangelical preacher [[Billy Graham]] and then-president [[Richard Nixon]] were captured on tape in the early 1970s discussing matters like how to address the [[Antisemitic canard#Accusations of controlling the media|Jews' control]] of the [[Media of the United States|American media]].&lt;ref name=&quot;bbcregret&quot;&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/americas/1850077.stm &quot;Graham regrets Jewish slur&quot;], [[BBC]], March 2, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;newsweek1&quot;&gt;{{cite magazine |title=Pilgrim's Progress, p. 5 |url=http://www.newsweek.com/id/46365/page/5 |magazine=Newsweek |date=August 14, 2006 |accessdate=September 20, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; This belief in Jewish conspiracies and domination of the media was similar to those of Graham's former mentors: [[William Bell Riley]] chose Graham to succeed him as the second president of Northwestern Bible and Missionary Training School and evangelist [[Mordecai Ham]] led the meetings where Graham first believed in Christ. Both held strongly antisemitic views.&lt;ref&gt;Himes, A (2011) The Sword of the Lord: The roots of fundamentalism in an American Family [http://www.worldcat.org/title/sword-of-the-lord-the-roots-of-fundamentalism-in-an-american-family/oclc/752306393]&lt;/ref&gt;  The 2001 survey by the [[Anti-Defamation League]] reported 1432 acts of antisemitism in the United States that year. The figure included 877 acts of harassment, including verbal intimidation, threats and physical assaults.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.adl.org/PresRele/ASUS_12/4057_12.asp ADL Audit: Anti-Semitic Incidents in U.S. Declined in 2001 Americans Reject Conspiracy Theories Blaming Jews for 9/11] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20030210065655/http://www.adl.org/PresRele/ASUS_12/4057_12.asp |date=2003-02-10 }} (2002 report)&lt;/ref&gt; A minority of American churches engage in anti-Israel activism, including support for the controversial BDS ([[Boycott, Divestment and Sanctions]]) movement. While not directly indicative of anti-semitism, this activism often conflates the Israeli government's treatment of Palestinians with that of Jesus, thereby promoting the anti-semitic doctrine of [[Jewish guilt]].&lt;ref&gt;http://ngo-monitor.org/data/images/File/NGOM_IPMN_June_2014.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; Many [[Christian Zionism|Christian Zionists]] are also accused of anti-semitism, such as [[John Hagee]], who argued that the Jews brought the Holocaust upon themselves by angering God.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://tabletmag.com/scroll/40563/my-hagee-problem%E2%80%94and-ours|title=My Hagee Problem—And Ours - Tablet Magazine – Jewish News and Politics, Jewish Arts and Culture, Jewish Life and Religion|publisher=|date=2010-07-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Relations between Jews and Christians have dramatically improved since the 20th century. According to a global poll which was conducted in 2014 by the [[Anti-Defamation League]], a Jewish group which is devoted to fighting antisemitism and other forms of [[racism]], data was collected from 102 countries with regard to their population's attitudes towards Jews and it revealed that only 24% of the world's Christians held views which were considered antisemitic according to the ADL's index, compared to 49%of the world's Muslims.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=ADL Poll of Over 100 Countries Finds More Than One-Quarter of Those Surveyed Infected With Anti-Semitic Attitudes |url=https://www.adl.org/news/press-releases/adl-global-100-poll |accessdate=November 20, 2019 |work=[[Anti-Defamation League]] |date=May 13, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Anti-Judaism==
{{Main article|Anti-Judaism}}
Many Christians do not consider [[anti-Judaism]] to be [[antisemitism]].{{according to whom|date=May 2013}} They regard anti-Judaism as a disagreement with the tenets of Judaism by religiously sincere people, while they regard antisemitism as an emotional bias or hatred which does not specifically target the religion of Judaism. Under this approach, anti-Judaism is not regarded as antisemitism because it only rejects the religious beliefs of Judaism and does not involve actual hostility towards the Jewish people.{{Citation needed|date=May 2010}}

Others believe that anti-Judaism is rejection of Judaism as a religion or opposition to Judaism's beliefs and practices ''essentially because'' of their source in [[Judaism]] or because a belief or practice is associated with the Jewish people. (But see [[supersessionism]])

The position that &quot;Christian theological anti-Judaism is a phenomenon distinct from modern antisemitism, which is rooted in economic and racial thought, so that Christian teachings should not be held responsible for antisemitism&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Susannah_Heschel_2008&quot;/&gt; has been articulated, among other people, by [[Pope John Paul II]] in 'We Remember: A Reflection on the [[Shoah]],' and the Jewish declaration on Christianity, [[Dabru Emet]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Susannah_Heschel_2008&quot;/&gt; Several scholars, including Susannah Heschel,&lt;ref name=&quot;Susannah_Heschel_2008&quot;/&gt; Gavin I Langmuir&lt;ref name=&quot;langmuir_1990&quot;&gt;Langmuir, AvGavin I., [https://archive.org/details/historyreligiona0000lang History, Religion, and Antisemitism], p. 40, University of California Press, 1990&lt;/ref&gt; and Uriel Tal&lt;ref name=&quot;Susannah_Heschel_2008&quot;/&gt; have challenged this position, arguing that anti-Judaism led directly to modern antisemitism.

Although some Christians did consider anti-Judaism to be contrary to Christian teaching in the past, this view was not widely expressed by leaders and lay people. In many cases, the practical tolerance towards the Jewish religion and Jews prevailed. Some Christian groups condemned verbal anti-Judaism, particularly in their early years.{{citation needed|date=November 2011}}

==Conversion of Jews==
{{See also|Hebrew Catholics|Messianic Judaism|Jews for Jesus}}
Some Jewish organizations have denounced evangelistic and missionary activities which are specifically directed at Jews  by labeling them [[antisemitic]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.culteducation.com/reference/jews_for_jesus/jews_for_jesus6.html Keeping Faith. Scottsdale Progress] by Kim Sue Lia Perkes (Religion Editor, The Arizona Republic) December, 1982&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bnaibrith.ca/publications/audit1998/audit1998-07.html 1998 Audit of Antisemitic Incidents: Missionaries and Messianic Churches] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20060719205927/http://www.bnaibrith.ca/publications/audit1998/audit1998-07.html |date=2006-07-19 }} (Bnai Brith Canada)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://torahatlanta.com/IntheNewsArticles/Portland.html Portland Jews Brace for Assault by 'Jews for Jesus'] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20060515145611/http://torahatlanta.com/IntheNewsArticles/Portland.html |date=2006-05-15 }} by Paul Haist (Jewish Review) May 15, 2002&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Southern Baptist Convention]] (SBC), the largest Protestant Christian denomination in the U.S., has explicitly rejected suggestions that it should back away from seeking to convert Jews, a position which critics have called antisemitic, but a position which [[Baptists]] believe is consistent with their view that salvation is solely found through faith in Christ. In 1996 the SBC approved a resolution calling for efforts to seek the conversion of Jews &quot;as well as the salvation of 'every kindred and tongue and people and nation.'&quot;

Most [[Evangelicalism|Evangelicals]] agree with the SBC's position, and some of them also support efforts which specifically seek the Jews' conversion. Additionally, these Evangelical groups are among the most pro-Israel groups. (''For more information, see [[Christian Zionism]]''.) One [[Messianic Judaism|controversial group]] which has received a considerable amount of support from some Evangelical churches is [[Jews for Jesus]], which claims that Jews can &quot;complete&quot; their Jewish faith by accepting Jesus as the Messiah.

The [[Presbyterian Church USA|Presbyterian Church (USA)]], the [[United Methodist Church]], and the [[United Church of Canada]] have ended their efforts to convert Jews. While [[Anglicans]] do not, as a rule, seek converts from other Christian denominations,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.anglicancommunion.org/acns/news.cfm/2003/5/20/ACNS3443 |title=Anglican Communion News Service: European Anglicans set common goals at Madrid consultation |publisher=Anglicancommunion.org |date= |accessdate=2013-07-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; the General Synod has affirmed that &quot;the good news of salvation in Jesus Christ is for all and must be shared with all including people from other faiths or of no faith and that to do anything else would be to institutionalize discrimination&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Owen |first=Peter |url=http://www.thinkinganglicans.org.uk/archives/003647.html |title=General Synod - Uniqueness of Christ in Multi-Faith Britain |publisher=Thinking Anglicans |date=2009-02-11 |accessdate=2013-07-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Catholic Church|Roman Catholic Church]] formerly operated religious congregations which specifically aimed to convert Jews. Some of these congregations were actually founded by Jewish converts, like the [[Congregation of Our Lady of Sion]], whose members were [[nun]]s and ordained [[priest]]s. Many Catholic saints were specifically noted for their missionary zeal to convert Jews, such as [[Vincent Ferrer]]. After the [[Second Vatican Council]], many missionary orders which aimed to convert Jews to Christianity no longer actively sought to missionize (or [[proselytism|proselytize]]) them. However, [[Traditionalist Catholic|Traditionalist Roman Catholic]] groups, congregations and clergymen continue to advocate the missionizing of Jews according to traditional patterns, sometimes with success (''e.g.'', the [[Society of St. Pius X]] which has notable Jewish converts among its faithful, many of whom have become traditionalist priests).

==Reconciliation between Judaism and Christian groups==
{{Main article|Christian–Jewish reconciliation}}
In recent years there has been much to note in the way of reconciliation between some Christian groups and the Jews.

==See also==
{{Portal|Judaism}}
{{Div col}}
* [[Anti-Jewish pogroms in the Russian Empire]]
* [[Anti-Jewish violence in Poland, 1944–1946]]
* [[Antisemitism and the New Testament]] 
* [[Antisemitism in Europe]]
* [[Antisemitism in Islam]]
* [[Antisemitism in the Soviet Union]]
* [[Antisemitism in the United States]]
* [[Antisemitism in Ukraine]]
* [[Christianity and Judaism]]
* [[Criticisms of Christianity]]
* [[Ecclesia et Synagoga]]
* [[Good Friday Prayer for the Jews]]
* [[History of antisemitism in the United States]]
* [[History of antisemitism]]
* [[History of the Jews in Poland]]
* [[History of the Jews in Ukraine]]
* [[History of the Jews and the Crusades]]
* [[History of the Jews in Germany]]
* [[History of the Jews in Hungary]]
* [[History of the Jews in Romania]]
* [[History of the Jews in Russia]]
* [[Jewish deicide]]
* [[Kishinev pogrom]]
* [[New antisemitism]]
* [[History of Christian thought on persecution and tolerance]]
* [[Persecution of Jews]]
* [[Pope John Paul II and Judaism]]
* [[Racial antisemitism]]
* [[Religious antisemitism]]
* [[Timeline of antisemitism]]
{{Div col end}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin|60em}}

* Beck, Norman A. ''Mature Christianity: The Recognition and Repudiation of the Anti-Jewish Polemic in the New Testament'' (Expanded Edition). Crossroad Pub Co 1994.  {{ISBN|978-0824513580}}
* [[Daniel Boyarin|Boyarin, Daniel]]. [http://nes.berkeley.edu/Web_Boyarin/BoyarinArticles/70%20Subversion%20of%20the%20Jews%20(1993).pdf ''The Subversion of the Jews: Moses's Veil and the Hermeneutics of Supersession'']  diacritics 23.2: 16–35 Summer 1993.
* Boys, Mary (Ed.). ''Seeing Judaism Anew: Christianity's Sacred Obligation''.  Sheed &amp; Ward March 31, 2005 {{ISBN|978-0742548824}}
* Carmichael, Joel. ''The Satanizing of the Jews: Origin and development of mystical anti-Semitism''. Fromm, 1993 {{ISBN|978-0880641326}}
* Eckhardt, A. Roy. ''Elder and Younger Brothers: The Encounter of Jews and Christians'', Schocken Books (1973)
* Eckhardt, A. Roy. ''Your People, My People: The Meeting of Christians &amp; Jews'', Crown Publishing Group (1974); {{ISBN|0-8129-0412-5}}
* [[John Gager|Gager, John C.]] ''The Origins of Anti-Semitism: Attitudes Toward Judaism in Pagan and Christian Antiquity''. Oxford Univ. Press, 1983 {{ISBN|978-0195036077}}
* Gould, Allan, (Ed.). ''What Did They Think of the Jews?'',  Jason Aronson Inc., 1991 {{ISBN|978-0876687512}}
* Hall III, Sidney G. ''Christian Anti-Semitism and Paul's Theology''. Fortress Press, 1993. {{ISBN|978-0800626549}}
* Johnson, Luke. [https://www.jstor.org/stable/3267112 ''The New Testament's Anti-Jewish Slander and Conventions of Ancient Polemic'']  Journal of Biblical Literature, Vol. 108, No. 3, Autumn, 1989 
* [[Pinchas Lapide|Lapide, Pinchas E]], ''Three Popes and the Jews''. Hawthorne Books, 1967 {{ISBN|978-0285501973}}
* Micklem, Nathaniel. [https://archive.org/details/nationalsocialis009929mbp ''National Socialism and the Roman Catholic Church: Being an Account of the Conflict between the National Socialist Government of Germany and the Roman Catholic Church, 1933-1938'']. London: Oxford University Press, 1939.
* Nicholls, William, ''Christian Antisemitism: A History of Hate''.  Jason Aronson Inc., 1993. {{ISBN|978-0876683989}}
* [[Rosemary Radford Ruether|Ruether, Rosemary Radford]] ''Faith and fratricide: the theological roots of anti-Semitism''. New York 1974, Seabury Press, {{ISBN|978-0-8164-2263-0}}.
* Synan, Edward A. ''The Popes and the Jews in the Middle Ages''. Macmillan, New York, 1965 {{ISBN|978-1597400947}}
* Tausch, Arno, ''The Effects of 'Nostra Aetate:' Comparative Analyses of Catholic Antisemitism More Than Five Decades after the Second Vatican Council'', 2018. Available at SSRN: https://ssrn.com/abstract=3098079
* Utz, Richard. &quot;Remembering Ritual Murder: The Anti-Semitic Blood Accusation Narrative in Medieval and Contemporary Cultural Memory&quot;. Pp.&amp;nbsp;145–62 in ''Genre and Ritual: The Cultural Heritage of Medieval Rituals''. Ed. Eyolf Østrem. Copenhagen: Museum Tusculanum Press/University of Copenhagen, 2005.  {{ISBN|978-8763502412}}
* Wilken, Robert L.  ''John Chrysostom and the Jews : Rhetoric and Reality in the Late 4th Century'', University of California Press, Berkeley, 1983 {{ISBN|978-0520047570}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
* [http://www.ushmm.org/ United States Holocaust Memorial Museum]
* [http://www.yadvashem.org Yad Vashem]

{{Antisemitism topics|state=collapsed}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Christianity And Antisemitism}}
[[Category:Christianity and antisemitism| ]]
[[Category:Early Christianity]]
[[Category:New Testament]]</text>
      <sha1>4aieldm47p0ah8imealw7oocdb6r3qv</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
