  <page>
    <title>Cheka</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6752</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943188503</id>
      <parentid>941537319</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-29T11:41:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>AlexTref871</username>
        <id>18994131</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Soviet national security agency (1917-1922)}}
{{Infobox Government agency
|agency_name   = All-Russian Extraordinary Commission
|nativename    = Vserossiyskaya chrezvychaynaya komissiya&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;({{lang-ru|Всероссийская чрезвычайная комиссия}})&lt;/small&gt;
|nativename_a  = | nativename_r  =
|logo          = GPU 5th anniversary emblem.png
|logo_width    = 80px
|logo_caption  = Badge commemorating 5 years of the VCK–GPU
|seal = | seal_width = | seal_caption  =
|formed        = December 5, 1917
|preceding1    = [[Ministry of the Interior of the Russian Empire]]
|preceding2    = [[Petrograd Military Revolutionary Committee|PVRK]]
|dissolved     = February 6, 1922
|superseding   = [[State Political Directorate|GPU &lt;small&gt;under NKVD RSFSR&lt;/small&gt;]]
|jurisdiction  = | headquarters  = 
*2 Gorokhovaya street, [[Petrograd]]
*[[Lubyanka (KGB)|Lubyanka Square]], [[Moscow]]
|latd= | longd= | region_code = | employees = | budget = | minister1_name =
|minister1_pfo  = | minister2_name = | minister2_pfo  =
|chief1_name = [[Felix Dzerzhinsky]]
|chief1_position = | chief2_name = | chief2_position =
|agency_type = [[State security]]
|parent_agency = [[File:Coat of arms of the Soviet Union (1923–1936).svg|30px]] [[Council of the People's Commissars |CPC]]
|child1_agency = | child2_agency = | keydocument1 = | website = | footnotes =
|chief3_name= |chief3_position= |chief4_name= |chief4_position= |chief5_name= |chief5_position= |chief6_name= |chief6_position= |chief7_name= |chief7_position= |chief8_name= |chief8_position= |chief9_name= |chief9_position= |parent_department= }}

The '''All-Russian Extraordinary Commission''' ({{lang-rus|Всероссийская Чрезвычайная Комиссия | translit = Vserossiyskaya chrezvychaynaya komissiya}}), abbreviated as '''VChK''' ({{lang-rus|ВЧК}}, ''Ve-Che-Ka'') and commonly known as '''Cheka'''  (from the initialism ChK - {{lang-ru| ЧК}}), was the first of a succession of [[Soviet Union|Soviet]] [[secret police | secret-police]] organizations. Established on December 5 ([[Julian calendar|Old Style]]) 1917 by the [[Council of People's Commissars|Sovnarkom]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title= Voices of Revolution, 1917|last= Steinberg|first= Mark D.|publisher= Yale University Press|year= 2001|isbn= 978-0-300-09016-1|location= London and New Haven|pages= 265–266}}&lt;/ref&gt; it came under the leadership of [[Felix Dzerzhinsky]], a [[Szlachta |Polish aristocrat]]-turned-[[communist]].&lt;ref name=Stalinsleadership&gt;{{cite book | title= The Impact of Stalin's Leadership in the USSR, 1924–1941 | authorlink= John Laver | year= 2008 | publisher= Nelson Thornes | isbn= 978-0-7487-8267-3 | page= 3}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite book
|url= https://g.co/kgs/eCdzrG
|title= The Russian Revolution
|last= Moorehead|first= Alan
|publisher= Harper &amp; Brothers
|year= 1958
|isbn= 978-0881843316
|location= New York|pages= 260
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
By late 1918 hundreds of Cheka committees had sprung up in the [[RSFSR]] at the [[oblast]], [[guberniya]], [[raion]], [[uyezd]], and [[volost]] levels.

== Name ==
The official designation was '''All-Russian Extraordinary''' (or '''Emergency''') '''Commission for Combating Counter-Revolution and Sabotage under the Council of People's Commissars of the RSFSR''' ({{lang-rus|Всероссийская Чрезвычайная Комиссия По Борьбе с Контрреволюцией и Саботажем при Совете Народных Комиссаров РСФСР}}, ''Vserossiyskaya chrezvychaynaya komissiya po borbe s kontrrevolyutsiyey i sabotazhem pri Sovete narodnykh komisarov RSFSR'').&lt;ref&gt;'''Tcheka''' – Official designation pertaining to [[State Archive of the Russian Federation]] «ф. 130, оп. 1, д. 1, л. 31 об.»&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1918 its name was changed, becoming '''All-Russian Extraordinary Commission for Combating Counter-Revolution, Profiteering and Corruption'''.

A member of Cheka was called a ''chekist''. Also, the term ''chekist'' often referred to Soviet [[secret police]] throughout the Soviet period, despite official name changes over time. In ''[[The Gulag Archipelago]]'', [[Alexander Solzhenitsyn]] recalls that ''[[White Sea-Baltic Canal#Commemoration|zeks]]'' in the [[Gulag|labor camps]] used ''old chekist'' as a mark of special esteem for particularly experienced camp administrators.&lt;ref name=&quot;Solzhenitsyn cite&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=The Gulag Archipelago |last=Solzhenitsyn |first=Alexander |authorlink=Alexander Solzhenitsyn |year=1974 |publisher=[[Harper Perennial]] |location=New York, NY |isbn=978-0-06-092103-3 |volume= II |pages= 537–38|quote=''An old Chekist''! Who has not heard these words, drawled with emphasis, as a mark of special esteem? If the zeks wish to distinguish a camp keeper from those who are inexperienced, inclined to fuss, and do not have a bulldog grip, they say: 'And the chief there is an o-o-old Chekist!' ... 'An old Chekist' – what that means at the least is that he was well-regarded under [[Genrikh Yagoda|Yagoda]], [[Nikolai Yezhov|Yezhov]] and [[Lavrenti Beria|Beria]]. He was useful to them all.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The term is still found in use in [[Russia]] today (for example, President [[Vladimir Putin]] has been referred to in the Russian [[News media|media]] as a ''chekist'' due to his career in the [[KGB]] and as head of the KGB's successor, [[Federal Security Service|FSB]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.themoscowtimes.com/opinion/article/a-stalin-slip-and-putin-trick/436470.html |title=A Stalin Slip and Putin Trick &amp;#124; Opinion |newspaper=The Moscow Times |date=2011-05-10 |accessdate=2011-07-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;).

The chekists commonly dressed in black leather, including long flowing coats, reportedly after being issued such distinctive coats early in their existence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/?id=UBbSGEaFZkIC&amp;pg=PA34&amp;dq=cheka%20head%20to%20toe%20black%20leather#v=onepage&amp;q=cheka%20head%20to%20toe%20black%20leather&amp;f=false|title=The Russian Civil War (1): The Red Army|first=Mikhail|last=Khvostov|date=1 July 1995|publisher=Bloomsbury USA|via=Google Books|isbn=9781855326088}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/?id=Yi3ow3TU8-4C&amp;pg=PA70&amp;lpg=PA70&amp;dq=cheka+leather+coats#v=onepage&amp;q=cheka%20leather%20coats&amp;f=false |title=Stalin and His Hangmen: The Tyrant ... – Google Books |date= 2007-12-18|accessdate=2011-07-27|isbn=9780307431837 |last1=Rayfield |first1=Donald }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Western [[communism|communists]] adopted this clothing fashion. The Chekists also often carried with them Greek-style [[worry beads]] made of amber, which had become &quot;fashionable among high officials during the time of the 'cleansing'&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Louis Rapoport, Stalin's war against the Jews: the doctors' plot and the Soviet solution, 1990, page 44&lt;/ref&gt;
{{clear}}

== History ==
{{Chronology of Soviet secret police agencies}}
In 1921, the ''[[Internal Troops|Troops for the Internal Defense of the Republic]]'' (a branch of the Cheka) numbered at least 200,000.&lt;ref name=&quot;History Learning Site: The Cheka&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.historylearningsite.co.uk/the_Cheka.htm|title= The Cheka|publisher= History Learning Site|date= January 2013|accessdate= 2013-12-11|archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20150516133305/http://www.historylearningsite.co.uk/the_Cheka.htm#|archive-date= 2015-05-16|url-status= dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; These troops policed [[labor camps]], ran the [[Gulag]] system, conducted [[Prodrazvyorstka|requisitions of food]], and subjected political opponents to secret arrest, detention, [[torture]] and [[summary execution]]. They also put down rebellions and riots by workers&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | title=Workers' Unrest and the Bolsheviks' Response in 1919 | publisher=Slavic Review | author=Vladimir Brovkin | year=1990 | pages=350-373}}&lt;/ref&gt; or peasants, and mutinies in the desertion-plagued [[Red Army]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Black&quot;&gt;Nicolas Werth, Karel Bartošek, Jean-Louis Panné, Jean-Louis Margolin, Andrzej Paczkowski, [[Stéphane Courtois]], ''The [[Black Book of Communism]]: Crimes, Terror, Repression'', [[Harvard University Press]], 1999, hardcover, 858 pages, {{ISBN|0-674-07608-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{qn|date=August 2017}}

After 1922 Cheka groups underwent the first of [[Chronology of Soviet secret police agencies|a series of reorganizations]]; however the theme of a government [[Chekism|dominated by &quot;the organs&quot;]] persisted indefinitely afterward, and Soviet citizens continued to refer to members of the various organs as [[Chekism|Chekists]].&lt;ref name=&quot;lcweb2.loc.gov&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url= http://lcweb2.loc.gov/frd/cs/soviet_union/su_glos.html#union |title= Library of Congress / Federal Research Division / Country Studies / Area Handbook Series/ Soviet Union / Glossary |publisher= Lcweb2.loc.gov |date= |accessdate= 2011-07-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Creation ===
[[File:Menzhinsky V 1921-2.jpg|thumb|Members of the [[presidium]] of VCheKa (left to right) [[Yakov Peters]], [[Józef Unszlicht]], [[Abram Belenky]] (standing), [[Felix Dzerzhinsky]], [[Vyacheslav Menzhinsky]], 1921]]

In the first month and half after the [[October Revolution]] (1917), the duty of &quot;extinguishing the resistance of exploiters&quot; was assigned to the [[Petrograd Military Revolutionary Committee]] (or PVRK). It represented a temporary body working under directives of the [[Council of People's Commissars]] (Sovnarkom) and [[Central Committee of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union|Central Committee]] of [[Russian Social Democratic Labour Party|RDSRP]]([[Bolshevik|b]]). The VRK created new bodies of government,{{Clarify|date=April 2011}} organized food delivery to cities and the Army, requisitioned products from ''[[bourgeoisie]]'', and sent its emissaries and agitators into provinces. One of its most important functions was the security of ''[[revolutionary]] order'', and the fight against ''[[counterrevolutionary]]'' activity (see: [[Anti-Soviet agitation]]).

On December 1, 1917, the [[All-Russian Central Executive Committee]] (VTsIK or TsIK)&lt;ref&gt;[[All-Russian Central Executive Committee]] (VTsIK or TsIK) is not to be confused with the [[Central Committee of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union|Central Committee]] of [[Russian Social Democratic Labour Party|RDSRP]]([[Bolshevik|b]])&lt;/ref&gt; reviewed a proposed reorganization of the VRK, and possible replacement of it. On December 5, the [[Petrograd]] VRK published an announcement of dissolution and transferred its functions to the department of TsIK for the fight against &quot;counterrevolutionaries&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mozokhin&quot;&gt;[http://mozohin.ru/article/a-4.html Mozokhin, O.B. ''out of history of activities of VChK, OGPU, NKVD, MGB'']. FSB archives.{{in lang|ru}}&lt;/ref&gt; On December 6, the Council of People's Commissars (Sovnarkom) strategized how to persuade government workers to strike across Russia. They decided that a special commission was needed to implement the &quot;most energetically revolutionary&quot; measures. [[Felix Dzerzhinsky]] (the Iron Felix) was appointed as Director and invited the participation of the following individuals: [[Vasiliy Averin|V. K. Averin]], [[Vasily Yakovlev|Vasili '''Vasilyevich Yakovlev''']], [[D. G. Yevseyev]], [[N. A. Zhydelev]], [[Ivan Ksenofontov|I. K. Ksenofontov]], [[Grigoriy Ordzhonikidze|G. K. Ordjonikidze]], [[Yakov Peters|Ya. Kh. Peters]], [[K. A. Peterson]], [[Valentin Trifonov|V. A. Trifonov]].

On December 7, 1917, all invited except Zhydelev and Vasilevsky gathered in the [[Smolny Institute]] to discuss the competence and structure of the commission to combat counterrevolution and sabotage. The obligations of the commission were: &quot;to liquidate to the root all of the counterrevolutionary and sabotage activities and all attempts to them in all of Russia, to hand over counter-revolutionaries and saboteurs to the [[revolutionary tribunal (Russia)|revolutionary tribunals]], develop measures to combat them and relentlessly apply them in real world applications. The commission should only conduct a preliminary investigation&quot;.{{clarify|date=November 2011}} The commission should also observe the press and counterrevolutionary parties, sabotaging officials and other criminals. 

[[File:Sankt Petersburg-Regierungssitz Smolny.jpg|thumb|left|[[Smolny Institute|Smolny]], the seat of the Soviet government, 1917]]

Three sections were created: informational, organizational, and a unit to combat counter-revolution and sabotage. Upon the end of the meeting, Dzerzhinsky reported to the [[Sovnarkom]] with the requested information. The commission was allowed to apply such measures of repression as 'confiscation, deprivation of ration cards, publication of lists of enemies of the people etc.'&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mozokhin&quot; /&gt; That day, Sovnarkom officially confirmed the creation of VCheKa. The commission was created not under the VTsIK as was previously anticipated, but rather under the Council of the People's Commissars.&lt;ref name=&quot;People's Commissars&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://memory.irk.ru/zp1.htm |title=Partial protocol of the 21st session of the Council of the People's Commissars |publisher=Memory.irk.ru |date=1998-12-26 |accessdate=2011-07-27 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170804181732/http://memory.irk.ru/zp1.htm |archive-date=2017-08-04 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

On December 8, 1917, some of the original members of the VCheka were replaced. Averin, Ordzhonikidze, and Trifonov were replaced by V. V. Fomin, S. E. Shchukin, Ilyin, and Chernov.&lt;ref name=&quot;People's Commissars&quot; /&gt; On the meeting of December 8, the presidium of VChK was elected of five members, and chaired by Dzerzhinsky. The issue of &quot;[[speculation]]&quot; {{ambiguous|date=November 2011}} was raised at the same meeting, which was assigned to Peters to address and report with results to one of the next meetings of the commission.  A circular, published on {{OldStyleDate|December 28|1917|December 15}}, gave the address of VCheka's first headquarters as &quot;Petrograd, Gorokhovaya 2, 4th floor&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;People's Commissars&quot; /&gt; On December 11, Fomin was ordered to organize a section to suppress &quot;speculation.&quot;  And in the same day, VCheKa offered Shchukin to conduct arrests of counterfeiters.

In January 1918, a subsection of the anti-counterrevolutionary effort was created to police bank officials.  The structure of VCheKa was changing repeatedly.  By March 1918, when the organization came to Moscow, it contained the following sections: against counterrevolution, speculation, non-residents, and information gathering. By the end of 1918–1919, some new units were created: secretly operative, investigatory, of transportation, military (special), operative, and instructional.  By 1921, it changed once again, forming the following sections: directory of affairs, administrative-organizational, secretly operative, economical, and foreign affairs.

=== First months ===
[[File:Vladimir Bonch-Bruyevich 1919.jpg|thumb|upright=0.70|Vladimir Bonch-Bruyevich]]

In the first months of its existence, VCheKa consisted of only 40 officials. It commanded a team of soldiers, the Sveaborgesky regiment, as well as a group of Red Guardsmen. On January 14, 1918, Sovnarkom ordered Dzerzhinsky to organize teams of &quot;energetic and ideological&quot; sailors to combat speculation. By the spring of 1918, the commission had several teams: in addition to the Sveaborge team, it had an intelligence team, a team of sailors, and a strike team. Through the winter of 1917–1918, all activities of VCheKa were centralized mainly in the city of Petrograd. It was one of several other commissions in the country which fought against counterrevolution, speculation, banditry, and other activities perceived as crimes. Other organizations included: the Bureau of Military Commissars, and an Army-Navy investigatory commission to attack the counterrevolutionary element in the [[Red Army]], plus the Central Requisite and Unloading Commission to fight speculation. The investigation of counterrevolutionary or major criminal offenses was conducted by the Investigatory Commission of Revtribunal. The functions of VCheKa were closely intertwined with the Commission of [[Vladimir Bonch-Bruyevich|V. D. Bonch-Bruyevich]], which beside the fight against wine [[pogrom]]s was engaged in the investigation of most major political offenses (see: [[Bonch-Bruyevich Commission]]).

[[File:Petrovskiy Grigoriy.jpg|thumb|upright=0.7|left|Grigory Petrovsky]]

All results of its activities, VCheKa had either to transfer to the Investigatory Commission of Revtribunal, or to dismiss. The control of the commission's activity was provided by the [[Ministry of Justice (Soviet Union)|People's Commissariat for Justice]] (Narkomjust, at that time headed by Isidor Steinberg) and Internal Affairs (NKVD, at that time headed by [[Grigory Petrovsky]]). Although the VCheKa was officially an independent organization from the [[NKVD]], its chief members such as Dzerzhinsky, [[Martin Latsis|Latsis]], [[Józef Unszlicht|Unszlicht]], and [[Moisei Uritsky|Uritsky]] (all main chekists), since November 1917 composed the collegiate of NKVD headed by Petrovsky. In November 1918, Petrovsky was appointed as head of the All-Ukrainian Central [[Military Revolutionary Committee]] during VCheKa's expansion to provinces and front-lines. At the time of political competition between Bolsheviks and SRs (January 1918), [[Left Socialist-Revolutionaries|Left SRs]] attempted to curb the rights of VCheKa and establish through the [[Ministry of Justice (Soviet Union)|Narkomiust]] their control over its work. Having failed in attempts to subordinate the VCheKa to Narkomiust, the Left SRs tried to gain control of the Extraordinary Commission in a different way: they requested that the Central Committee of the party was granted the right to directly enter their representatives into the VCheKa. [[Sovnarkom]] recognized the desirability of including five representatives of the Left Socialist-Revolutionary faction of VTsIK. Left SRs were granted the post of a companion (deputy) chairman of VCheKa. However, Sovnarkom, in which the majority belonged to the representatives of RSDLP(b) retained the right to approve members of the collegium of the VCheKa.

Originally, members of the Cheka were exclusively [[Bolshevik]]; however, in January 1918, [[Left Socialist-Revolutionaries|Left SRs]] also joined the organization&lt;ref&gt;Schapiro (1984).&lt;/ref&gt; The Left SRs were expelled or arrested later in 1918, following the attempted assassination of [[Lenin]] by an SR, [[Fanni Kaplan]].

=== Consolidation of VCheKa and National Establishment ===
By the end of January 1918, the Investigatory Commission of [[Petrograd Soviet]] (probably same as of Revtribunal) petitioned [[Sovnarkom]] to delineate the role of detection and judicial-investigatory organs. It offered to leave, for the VCheKa and the Commission of Bonch-Bruyevich, only the functions of detection and suppression, while investigative functions entirely transferred to it.  The Investigatory Commission prevailed.  On January 31, 1918, Sovnarkom ordered to relieve VCheKa of the investigative functions, leaving for the commission only the functions of detection, suppression, and prevention of anti revolutionary crimes.  At the meeting of the Council of People's Commissars on January 31, 1918, a merger of VCheKa and the Commission of Bonch-Bruyevich was proposed.  The existence of both commissions, VCheKa of Sovnarkom and the Commission of Bonch-Bruyevich of VTsIK, with almost the same functions and equal rights, became impractical.  A decision followed two weeks later.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Izvestiya]]''. February 28, 1918.&lt;/ref&gt;

On February 23, 1918, VCheKa sent a radio telegram to all Soviets with a petition to immediately organize emergency commissions to combat counter-revolution, sabotage and speculation, if such commissions had not been yet organized.  February 1918 saw the creation of local Extraordinary Commissions.  One of the first founded was the [[Moscow]] Cheka.  Sections and commissariats to combat counterrevolution were established in other cities.  The Extraordinary Commissions arose, usually in the areas during the moments of the greatest aggravation of political situation.  On February 25, 1918, as the counterrevolutionary organization ''Union of Front-liners'' was making advances, the executive committee of the [[Saratov]] Soviet formed a counter-revolutionary section.  On March 7, 1918, because of the move from [[Petrograd]] to Moscow, the Petrograd Cheka was created.  On March 9, a section for combating counterrevolution was created under the [[Omsk]] Soviet.  Extraordinary commissions were also created in [[Penza]], [[Perm]], [[Novgorod]], [[Cherepovets]], [[Rostov]], [[Taganrog]].  On March 18, VCheKa adopted a resolution, ''The Work of VCheKa on the All-Russian Scale'', foreseeing the formation everywhere of Extraordinary Commissions after the same model, and sent a letter that called for the widespread establishment of the Cheka in combating counterrevolution, speculation, and sabotage.  Establishment of provincial Extraordinary Commissions was largely completed by August 1918.  In the Soviet Republic, there were 38 [[guberniya|gubernatorial]] Chekas (Gubcheks) by this time.

On June 12, 1918, the All-Russian Conference of Cheka adopted the ''Basic Provisions on the Organization of Extraordinary Commissions''. They set out to form Extraordinary Commissions not only at [[Oblast]] and [[Guberniya]] levels, but also at the large [[Uyezd]] Soviets. In August 1918, in the Soviet Republic had accounted for some 75 Uyezd-level Extraordinary Commissions.  By the end of the year, 365 Uyezd-level Chekas were established.  In 1918, the All-Russia Extraordinary Commission and the Soviets managed to establish a local Cheka apparatus.  It included Oblast, Guberniya, [[Raion]], [[Uyezd]], and [[Volost]] Chekas, with Raion and Volost Extraordinary Commissioners. In addition, border security Chekas were included in the system of local Cheka bodies.

In the autumn of 1918, as consolidation of the political situation of the republic continued, a move toward elimination of Uyezd-, Raion-, and Volost-level Chekas, as well as the institution of Extraordinary Commissions was considered. On January 20, 1919, VTsIK adopted a resolution prepared by VCheKa, ''On the abolition of Uyezd Extraordinary Commissions''. On January 16 the presidium of VCheKa approved the draft on the establishment of the Politburo at Uyezd [[militsiya]]. This decision was approved by the Conference of the Extraordinary Commission IV, held in early February 1920.

=== Other types of Cheka ===
[[File:1988 CPA 6011.jpg|thumb|upright|Portrait of [[Martin Latsis]] on a Soviet [[postage stamp]].]]

On August 3, a VCheKa section for combating counterrevolution, speculation and sabotage on railways was created. On August 7, 1918, [[Sovnarkom]] adopted a decree on the organization of the railway section at VCheKa. Combating counterrevolution, speculation, and [[malfeasance]] on railroads was passed under the jurisdiction of the railway section of VCheKa and local Cheka. In August 1918, railway sections were formed under the Gubcheks. Formally, they were part of the non-resident sections, but in fact constituted a separate division, largely autonomous in their activities. The gubernatorial and oblast-type Chekas retained in relationship to the transportation sections only control and investigative functions.

The beginning of a systematic work of organs of VCheKa in [[RKKA]] refers to July 1918, the period of extreme tension of the [[Russian Civil War|civil war]] and class struggle in the country. On July 16, 1918, the Council of People's Commissars formed the Extraordinary Commission for combating counterrevolution at the Czechoslovak (Eastern) Front, led by [[Martin Latsis|M. I. Latsis]]. In the fall of 1918, Extraordinary Commissions to combat counterrevolution on the Southern (Ukraine) Front were formed. In late November, the Second All-Russian Conference of the Extraordinary Commissions accepted a decision after a report from [[I. N. Polukarov]] to establish at all frontlines, and army sections of the Cheka and granted them the right to appoint their commissioners in military units.  On December 9, 1918, the collegiate (or presidium) of VCheKa had decided to form a military section, headed by [[Mikhail Sergeevich Kedrov|M. S. Kedrov]], to combat counterrevolution in the Army.  In early 1919, the military control and the military section of VCheKa were merged into one body, the [[Special Section of the Republic]], with Kedrov as head.  On January 1, he issued an order to establish the Special Section. The order instructed agencies everywhere to unite the Military control and the military sections of Chekas and to form special sections of frontlines, armies, military districts, and [[guberniya]]s.

In November 1920 the [[Soviet of Labor and Defense]] created a Special Section of VCheKa for the security of the state border.  On February 6, 1922, after the Ninth All-Russian Soviet Congress, the Cheka was dissolved by VTsIK, &quot;with expressions of gratitude for heroic work.&quot;  It was replaced by the [[State Political Administration]] or OGPU, a section of the [[NKVD]] of the [[Russian Soviet Federative Socialist Republic]] (RSFSR).  Dzerzhinsky remained as chief of the new organization.
{{Clear}}

== Operations ==
=== Suppression of political opposition ===
{{See also|Red Terror}}

Initially formed to fight against counter-revolutionaries and saboteurs, as well as [[Speculation|financial speculators]], the Cheka had its own classifications. Those counter-revolutionaries fell under these categories:

# any civil or military servicemen suspected of working for Imperial Russia;
# families of officers-volunteers (including children);{{citation needed|date=February 2015}}
# all clergy;
# workers and peasants who were under suspicion of not supporting the Soviet government;{{citation needed|date=February 2015}}
# any other person whose private property was valued at over 10,000 rubles.{{citation needed|date=February 2015}}

As its name implied, the Extraordinary Commission had virtually unlimited powers and could interpret them in any way it wished.  No standard procedures were ever set up, except that the Commission was supposed to send the arrested to the Military-Revolutionary tribunals if outside of a war zone. This left an opportunity for a wide range of interpretations, as the whole country was in total chaos. At the direction of Lenin, the Cheka performed mass arrests, imprisonments, and executions of &quot;[[enemies of the people]]&quot;. In this, the Cheka said that they targeted &quot;class enemies&quot; such as the [[bourgeoisie]], and members of the [[clergy]]; the first organized mass repression began against the [[Libertarianism|libertarians]] and socialists of Petrograd in April 1918. Over the next few months, 800 were arrested and shot without trial.{{citation needed|date=March 2018}}

Within a month, the Cheka had extended its repression to all political opponents of the communist government, including [[Anarchism|anarchists]] and others on the left.  On April 11/12, 1918, some 26 anarchist political centres in Moscow were attacked. Forty anarchists were killed by Cheka forces, and about 500 were arrested and jailed after a pitched battle took place between the two groups.&lt;ref&gt;P. Avrich. G. Maximoff&lt;/ref&gt; In response to the anarchists' resistance, the Cheka orchestrated a massive retaliatory campaign of repression, executions, and arrests against all opponents of the Bolshevik government, in what came to be known as &quot;[[Red Terror]]&quot;.  The ''Red Terror'', implemented by Dzerzhinsky on September 5, 1918, was vividly described by the [[Red Army]] journal ''Krasnaya Gazeta'':

&lt;blockquote&gt;Without mercy, without sparing, we will kill our enemies in scores of hundreds. Let them be thousands, let them drown themselves in their own blood. For the blood of Lenin and [[Moisei Uritsky|Uritsky]] … let there be floods of blood of the [[bourgeoisie]] – more blood, as much as possible...&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Applebaum (2003), page 9.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

An early Bolshevik, [[Victor Serge]] described in his book ''Memoirs of a Revolutionary'':

{{quote|Since the first massacres of Red prisoners by the Whites, the murders of Volodarsky and Uritsky and the attempt against Lenin (in the summer of 1918), the custom of arresting and, often, executing hostages had become generalized and legal. Already the Cheka, which made mass arrests of suspects, was tending to settle their fate independently, under formal control of the Party, but in reality without anybody's knowledge. The Party endeavoured to head it with incorruptible men like the former convict Dzerzhinsky, a sincere idealist, ruthless but chivalrous, with the emaciated profile of an [[Inquisitor]]: tall forehead, bony nose, untidy goatee, and an expression of weariness and austerity. But the Party had few men of this stamp and many Chekas. I believe that the formation of the Chekas was one of the gravest and most impermissible errors that the Bolshevik leaders committed in 1918 when plots, blockades, and interventions made them lose their heads. All evidence indicates that [[revolutionary tribunal (Russia)|revolutionary tribunals]], functioning in the light of day and admitting the right of defense, would have attained the same efficiency with far less abuse and depravity. Was it necessary to revert to the procedures of the Inquisition?&quot;}}

The Cheka was also used against the armed anarchist [[Revolutionary Insurrectionary Army of Ukraine|Black Army]] of [[Nestor Makhno]] in the Ukraine.  After the Black Army had served its purpose in aiding the [[Red Army]] to stop the [[White Army|Whites]] under [[Anton Denikin|Denikin]], the Soviet communist government decided to eliminate the anarchist forces. In May 1919, two Cheka agents sent to assassinate Makhno were caught and executed.&lt;ref&gt;Avrich, Paul, &quot;Russian Anarchists and the Civil War&quot;, ''Russian Review'', Volume 27, Issue 3 (July 1968), pp. 296–306.&lt;/ref&gt;

Many victims of Cheka repression were &quot;bourgeois hostages&quot; rounded up and held in readiness for [[summary execution]] in reprisal for any alleged counter-revolutionary act. Wholesale, indiscriminate arrests became an integral part of the system.&lt;ref&gt;Figes (1996), page 643.&lt;/ref&gt; The Cheka used trucks disguised as delivery trucks, called &quot;Black Marias&quot;, for the secret arrest and transport of prisoners.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://gulaghistory.org/items/show/186|title=Prisoners Exiting a Black Maria|last=Unknown|date=17 December 2016|publisher=|via=Gulag: Many Days, Many Lives}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It was during the [[Red Terror]] that the Cheka, hoping to avoid the bloody aftermath of having half-dead victims writhing on the floor, developed a technique for execution known later by the German words &quot;''Nackenschuss''{{-&quot;}} or &quot;''Genickschuss''{{-&quot;}}, a shot to the [[nape]] of the neck, which caused minimal blood loss and instant death. The victim's head was bent forward, and the executioner fired slightly downward at point blank range. This had become the standard method used later by the [[NKVD]] to liquidate [[Joseph Stalin]]'s [[Great Purge|purge]] victims and others.&lt;ref&gt;Paul, Allen. ''Katyn: Stalin's Massacre and the Seeds of Polish Resurrection''. Naval Institute Press, 1996. {{ISBN|1-55750-670-1}}. pp. 111/112.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Persecution of deserters ===
It is believed that there were more than three million [[deserter]]s from the Red Army in 1919 and 1920. Approximately 500,000 deserters were arrested in 1919 and close to 800,000 in 1920, by troops of the 'Special Punitive Department' of the Cheka, created to punish desertions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Black&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Chamberlain, William Henry, ''The Russian Revolution: 1917–1921'', New York: Macmillan Co. (1957), p. 131&lt;/ref&gt; These troops were used to forcibly [[Repatriation|repatriate]] deserters, taking and shooting hostages to force compliance or to set an example. Throughout the course of the civil war, several thousand deserters were shot – a number comparable to that of belligerents during [[World War I]].

In September 1918, according to ''[[The Black Book of Communism]]'', in only twelve provinces of Russia, 48,735 deserters and 7,325 &quot;bandits&quot; were arrested, 1,826 were killed and 2,230 were executed.  The exact identity of these individuals is confused by the fact that the Soviet Bolshevik government used the term 'bandit' to cover ordinary criminals as well as armed and unarmed political opponents, such as the anarchists.

== Repression ==
{{Repression in the Soviet Union}}

=== Number of victims ===
Estimates on Cheka executions vary widely. The lowest figures (''disputed below'') are provided by Dzerzhinsky's lieutenant [[Martin Latsis|Martyn Latsis]], limited to RSFSR over the period 1918–1920:

*For the period 1918 – July 1919, covering only twenty provinces of central Russia:
::In 1918: 6,300; in 1919 (up to July): 2,089; Total: 8,389

*For the whole period 1918–19:
::In 1918: 6,185; in 1919: 3,456; Total: 9,641

*For the whole period 1918–20:
::In January–June 1918: 22; in July–December 1918: more than 6,000; in 1918–20: 12,733.

Experts generally agree these semi-official figures are vastly understated.&lt;ref&gt;pages 463–464, Leggett (1986).&lt;/ref&gt; Pioneering historian of the [[Red Terror]] [[Sergei Melgunov]] claims that this was done deliberately in an attempt to demonstrate the government's humanity. For example, he refutes the claim made by Latsis that only 22 executions were carried out in the first six months of the Cheka's existence by providing evidence that the true number was 884 executions.&lt;ref&gt;[[Sergei Melgunov]], [http://www.paulbogdanor.com/left/soviet/redterror.pdf &quot;The Record of the Red Terror&quot;], paulbogdanor.com.&lt;/ref&gt; W. H. Chamberlin claims, &quot;It is simply impossible to believe that the Cheka only put to death 12,733 people in all of Russia up to the end of the civil war.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Chamberlin&quot;&gt;pages 74–75, Chamberlin (1935).&lt;/ref&gt; [[Donald Rayfield]] concurs, noting that, &quot;Plausible evidence reveals that the actual numbers . . . vastly exceeded the official figures.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Donald Rayfield]]. ''[[Stalin and His Hangmen]]: The Tyrant and Those Who Killed for Him.'' [[Random House]], 2004. {{ISBN|0-375-50632-2}}, p.1926: [https://books.google.com/books?id=Yi3ow3TU8-4C&amp;lpg=PA1926&amp;pg=RA2-PA1915#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false GBYi].&lt;/ref&gt;  Chamberlin provides the &quot;reasonable and probably moderate&quot; estimate of 50,000,&lt;ref name=&quot;Chamberlin&quot; /&gt; while others provide estimates ranging up to 500,000.&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?vid=ISBN1560008873&amp;id=sK5CJFpb2DAC&amp;pg=PA39&amp;lpg=PA39&amp;ots=TubCNy7NoM&amp;dq=lethal+politics+cheka+executions+most+probably+about+500,000&amp;ie=ISO-8859-1&amp;sig=X7A0DHHZ6WCVlnpj5m9CTB-u_rg page 39], Rummel (1990).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/2273462.stm |title=Statue plan stirs Russian row (BBC) |work=BBC News |date=2002-09-21 |accessdate=2011-07-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; Several scholars put the number of executions at about 250,000.&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=9TWUAQ7Xof8C&amp;pg=PA28 page 28], Andrew and Mitrokhin, ''The Sword and the Shield'', paperback edition, Basic books, 1999.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;page 180, Overy, ''The Dictators: Hitler's Germany, Stalin's Russia,'' W. W. Norton &amp; Company; 1st American Ed edition, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; Some believe it is possible more people were murdered by the Cheka than died in battle.&lt;ref&gt;page 649, Figes (1996).&lt;/ref&gt; Historian James Ryan gives a modest estimate of 28,000 executions per year from December 1917 to February 1922.&lt;ref&gt;Ryan, James (2012). ''[https://www.routledge.com/Lenins-Terror-The-Ideological-Origins-of-Early-Soviet-State-Violence/Ryan/p/book/9781138815681 Lenin's Terror: The Ideological Origins of Early Soviet State Violence].'' London: [[Routledge]]. p. 2. {{ISBN|978-1-138-81568-1}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Lenin himself seemed unfazed by the killings. On 12 January 1920, while addressing trade union leaders, he said: &quot;We did not hesitate to shoot thousands of people, and we shall not hesitate, and we shall save the {{nowrap|country.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;pages 72 &amp; 73, Volkogonov (1998).&lt;/ref&gt;}}. On 14 May 1921, the [[Politburo]], chaired by Lenin, passed a motion &quot;broadening the rights of the [Cheka] in relation to the use of the [death penalty].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;page 238, Volkogonov (1994).&lt;/ref&gt;

== Atrocities ==
The Cheka engaged in the widespread practice of [[torture]]. Depending on Cheka committees in various cities, the methods included:&lt;ref name=&quot;Linc&quot;&gt;Lincoln (1999).&lt;/ref&gt; being skinned alive, scalped, &quot;crowned&quot; with barbed wire, impaled, crucified, hanged, stoned to death, tied to planks and pushed slowly into furnaces or tanks of boiling water, or rolled around naked in internally nail-studded barrels. Chekists reportedly poured water on naked prisoners in the winter-bound streets until they became living ice statues. Others reportedly beheaded their victims by twisting their necks until their heads could be torn off. The [[Chinese in Russian Revolution|Cheka detachments]] stationed in [[Kiev]] reportedly would attach an iron tube to the torso of a bound victim and insert a rat in the tube closed off with wire netting, while the tube was held over a flame until the rat began gnawing through the victim's guts in an effort to escape.&lt;ref name=Linc /&gt; [[Anton Denikin]]'s investigation discovered corpses whose lungs, throats, and mouths had been packed with earth.&lt;ref name=&quot;Linc&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;pages 177–179, Melg(o)unov (1925).&lt;/ref&gt;

Women and children were also victims of Cheka terror. Women would sometimes be tortured and raped before being shot. Children between the ages of 8 and 13 were imprisoned and occasionally executed.&lt;ref&gt;page 198, Leggett (1986).&lt;/ref&gt;

All of these atrocities were published on numerous occasions in ''[[Pravda]]'' and ''[[Izvestiya]]'': January 26, 1919 ''Izvestiya'' #18 article ''Is it really a medieval imprisonment?'' («Неужели средневековый застенок?»); February 22, 1919 ''Pravda'' #12 publishes details of the [[Vladimir, Russia|Vladimir]] Cheka's tortures, September 21, 1922 ''Socialist Herald'' publishes details of series of tortures conducted by the [[Stavropol]] Cheka (hot basement, cold basement, skull measuring etc.).

The Chekists were also supplemented by the militarized Units of Special Purpose (the Party's Spetsnaz or {{lang-ru|ЧОН}}).

Cheka was actively and openly utilizing kidnapping methods.&lt;ref&gt;[http://mozohin.ru/article/a-10.html History of governmental bodies of Cheka] {{in lang|ru}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;В. П. Данилов. «Советская деревня глазами ВЧК-ОГПУ-НКВД», 1918–1922, М., 1998. // РГВА (Российский Государственный Военно-исторический Архив), 33987/3/32.&lt;/ref&gt; With kidnapping methods Cheka was able to extinguish numerous cases of discontent especially among the rural population. Among the notorious ones was the [[Tambov rebellion]].

Villages were bombarded to complete annihilation like in the case of Tretyaki, Novokhopersk uyezd, [[Voronezh Governorate]]. {{citation needed|date=December 2010}}

As a result of this relentless violence more than a few Chekists ended up with psychopathic disorders, which [[Nikolai Bukharin]] said were &quot;an occupational hazard of the Chekist profession.&quot; Many hardened themselves to the executions by heavy drinking and drug use. Some developed a gangster-like slang for the verb to kill in an attempt to distance themselves from the killings, such as 'shooting partridges', of 'sealing' a victim, or giving him a ''natsokal'' (onomatopoeia of the trigger action).&lt;ref&gt;page 647, Figes (1996).&lt;/ref&gt;

On November 30, 1992, by the initiative of the [[President of the Russian Federation]] the Constitutional Court of the Russian Federation recognized the Red Terror as unlawful, which in turn led to suspension of the Communist Party of the RSFSR.

== Regional Chekas ==
{{Refimprove section|date=December 2010}}
Cheka departments were organized not only in big cities and [[guberniya]] seats, but also in each [[uyezd]], at any front-lines and military formations. Nothing is known on what resources they were created. Many who were hired to head those departments were so-called &quot;nestlings of [[Alexander Keren]]&quot;.
;Moscow Cheka (1918–1919)
* Chairman – [[Felix Dzerzhynsky]], Deputy – [[Yakov Peters]] (initially heading the Petrograd Department), other members – Shklovsky, Kneyfis, Tseystin, Razmirovich, Kronberg, Khaikina, Karlson, Shauman, Lentovich, Rivkin, Antonov, Delafabr, Tsytkin, G.Sverdlov, Bizensky, [[Yakov Blumkin]], Aleksandrovich, Fines, Zaks, [[Yakov Goldin]], Galpershtein, Kniggisen, [[Martin Latsis]] (later transfer (chief of jail), Fogel, Zakis, Shillenkus, Yanson).
;Petrograd Cheka (1918–1919)
* Chairman – Meinkman, [[Moisei Uritsky]] (reiller, Kozlovsky, Model, Rozmirovich, I.Diesporov, Iselevich, Krassikov, Bukhan, Merbis, Paykis, Anvelt.
;Kharkov Cheka
* Deych, Vikhman, Timofey, Vera (Dora) Grebenshchikova, Aleksandra (ag
* Ashykin.

== Popular culture ==
* The Cheka were popular staples in Soviet film and literature. This was partly due to a romanticization of the organisation in the post-Stalin period, and also because they provided a useful action/detection template. Films featuring the Cheka include [[Ostern]]'s ''[[Miles of Fire]]'', [[Nikita Mikhalkov]]'s  ''[[At Home among Strangers]]'', the miniseries ''[[The Adjutant of His Excellency]]'', and also ''[[Dead Season]]'' (starring [[Donatas Banionis]]), and the [[1992 in film|1992]] [[cinema of Russia|Russian]] [[Drama (film and television)|drama film]] ''[[The Chekist]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0103949/|title=Chekist|date=1 January 2000|publisher=|via=IMDb}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In [[Spain]], during the [[Spanish Civil War]], the detention and torture centers operated by the Communists were named &quot;''checas''&quot; after the Soviet organization.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.firmaspress.com/285.htm International justice begins at home] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140903094502/http://www.firmaspress.com/285.htm |date=September 3, 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Alfonso Laurencic]] was their promoter, ideologist and builder.&lt;ref&gt;[[Rafael Chacón]], &quot;''Por qué hice las checas de Barcelona. Laurencic ante el consejo de guerra''&quot;, ''Editorial Solidaridad nacional'', Barcelona, 1939.&lt;/ref&gt;
* Dzerzhinsky, who rarely drank, is said to have told Lenin – on an occasion in which he did so excessively – that secret police work could be done by &quot;only saints or scoundrels ... but now the saints are running away from me and I am left with the scoundrels&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nationalobserver.net/2001_winter_106.htm R.J. Stove. (2001). ''The Cheka, G.P.U. and O.G.P.U.: Bolshevism's Early Secret Police'']&lt;/ref&gt;&quot;.

== Legacy ==
[[Konstantin Preobrazhenskiy]] criticised the continuing celebration of the  professional holiday of the [[NKVD|old]] and the modern Russian security services on the anniversary of the creation of the Cheka, with the assent of the Presidents of [[Russia]]. (Vladimir Putin, former KGB officer, chose not to change the date to another): &quot;The [[Federal Security Service|successors]] of the [[KGB]] still haven't renounced anything; they even celebrate their professional [[holiday]] the same day, as during [[Political repression in the Soviet Union|repression]], on the 20th of December. It is  as if the present intelligence and counterespionage services of [[Germany]] celebrated [[Gestapo]] Day. I can imagine how indignant our press would be!&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Article of Konstantin Preobrazhenskiy: &quot;[http://justicefornorthcaucasus.info/?p=1115535600 People's Commissariat of Internal Affairs and Gestapo: cooperation of friends]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://translate.google.com/translate?sl=ru&amp;tl=en&amp;js=n&amp;prev=_t&amp;hl=ru&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;u=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.fsb.ru%2Ffsb%2Fhistory.htm History of creation of the FSB on the official website of FSB] (English translation).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://russiatrek.org/about-russian-holidays Russian holidays and celebrations info]: &quot;December 20 – The day of national security service workers (professional holiday)&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{div col|colwidth=30em}}
* [[Chekism]]
* [[Commanders of the border troops USSR and RF]]
* [[Central Case Examination Group]]
* [[Chronology of Soviet secret police agencies]]
* [[Great Purge]]
* [[Ministry for State Security (Soviet Union)]]
* [[Okhrana]]
* [[People's Commissariat for State Security (Soviet Union)]]
* [[Russian Revolution of 1917]]
{{div col end}}

== Notes ==
{{reflist|30em}}

== References and further reading ==
* [[Christopher Andrew (historian)|Andrew, Christopher M.]] and [[Vasili Mitrokhin]] (1999) ''The Sword and the Shield : The [[Mitrokhin Archive]] and the Secret History of the KGB.'' New York: [[Basic Books]]. {{ISBN|0-465-00312-5}}.
* [[E. H. Carr|Carr, E. H.]] (1958) ''The Origin and Status of the Cheka.'' [[Soviet Studies]], vol. 10, no. 1, pp.&amp;nbsp;1–11.
* Chamberlin, W. H. (1935) ''The Russian Revolution 1917–1921, '' 2 vols. London and New York. The Macmillan Company.
* Dziak, John. (1988) ''Chekisty: A History of the KGB.'' Lexington, Mass. Lexington Books.
* [[Orlando Figes|Figes, Orlando]] (1997) ''A People's Tragedy: The Russian Revolution 1891–1924.'' [[Penguin Books]]. {{ISBN|0-670-85916-8}}.
* Leggett, George (1986) ''The Cheka: Lenin's Political Police.'' [[Oxford University Press]], New York. {{ISBN|0-19-822862-7}}
* Lincoln, Bruce W. (1999) ''Red Victory: A History of the Russian Civil War.'' Da Capo Press. {{ISBN|0-306-80909-5}}
* [[Sergei Melgunov|Melgounov, Sergey Petrovich]] (1925) ''The Red Terror in Russia.'' London &amp; Toronto: J. M. Dent &amp; Sons Ltd.
* [[Richard Overy|Overy, Richard]] (2004) ''The Dictators: Hitler's Germany, Stalin's Russia.'' W. W. Norton &amp; Company; 1st American edition. {{ISBN|0-393-02030-4}}
* [[R. J. Rummel|Rummel, Rudolph Joseph]] (1990) ''Lethal Politics: Soviet Genocide and Mass Murder Since 1917.'' Transaction Publishers. {{ISBN|1-56000-887-3}}
*{{Cite book |last = Ryan | first = James | title = Lenin's Terror: The Ideological Origins of Early Soviet State Violence | publisher = [[Routledge]] | location = London | year = 2012 | isbn = 978-1-138-81568-1 | url= https://www.routledge.com/products/9781138815681 | ref=harv }}
* [[Leonard Schapiro|Schapiro, Leonard B.]] (1984) ''The Russian Revolutions of 1917 : The Origins of Modern Communism.'' New York: Basic Books. {{ISBN|0-465-07154-6}}
* [[Dmitri Volkogonov|Volkogonov, Dmitri]] (1994) ''Lenin: A New Biography.'' [[Free Press (publisher)|Free Press]]. {{ISBN|0-02-933435-7}}
* Volkogonov, Dmitri (1998) ''Autopsy of an Empire: The Seven Leaders Who Built the Soviet Regime'' [[Free Press (publisher)|Free Press]]. {{ISBN|0-684-87112-2}}

== External links ==
*[http://www.spartacus-educational.com/RUScheka.htm The Cheka] – Spartacus Schoolnet collection of primary source extracts relating to the Cheka
*[http://www.hrono.ru/organ/ukazatel/gulag.php Development of the Soviet system of punitive organs] {{in lang|ru}}

{{Secret police of Communist Europe}}
{{Russian Revolution 1917}}
{{Soviet Union topics}}
{{Authority control}}
[[Category:Cheka| ]]
[[Category:Defunct law enforcement agencies of Russia]]
[[Category:Russian intelligence agencies]]
[[Category:Defunct intelligence agencies]]
[[Category:Organizations of the Russian Revolution]]
[[Category:Law enforcement in communist states]]
[[Category:Paramilitary organizations based in Russia]]
[[Category:Political repression in Russia]]
[[Category:Secret police]]
[[Category:Soviet intelligence agencies]]
[[Category:State-sponsored terrorism]]
[[Category:1917 establishments in Russia]]
[[Category:1922 disestablishments in Russia]]
[[Category:Government agencies established in 1917]]
[[Category:Government agencies disestablished in 1922]]</text>
      <sha1>8he91qmcwa87vkfgutw9jlddbdbb1cf</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
