  <page>
    <title>Cereal</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6700</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943279158</id>
      <parentid>943276609</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-29T23:29:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Plantsurfer</username>
        <id>1750837</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/144.96.22.198|144.96.22.198]] ([[User talk:144.96.22.198|talk]]) to last revision by El C ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{About|cereal grasses and cereal grains in general|breakfast cereal|Breakfast cereal|food grains in general|Grain|other uses|}}
{{distinguish|Serial (disambiguation){{!}}serial}}
{{short description|Grass of which the fruits are used as grain, or said fruits}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=February 2015}}

[[File:Various grains.jpg|thumb|Various cereals and their products]]
A '''cereal''' is any [[Poaceae|grass]] cultivated (grown) for the edible components of its [[grain]] (botanically, a type of [[fruit]] called a [[caryopsis]]), composed of the [[endosperm]], [[cereal germ|germ]], and [[bran]]. The term may also refer to the resulting grain itself (specifically &quot;'''cereal grain'''&quot;). Cereal [[Food grain|grain crops]] are grown in greater quantities and provide more food energy worldwide than any other type of crop&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.idrc.ca/en|title=IDRC - International Development Research Centre|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160609075145/https://www.idrc.ca/en|archivedate=9 June 2016|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; and are therefore [[staple food|staple crops]]. Edible grains from other plant families, such as [[buckwheat]] ([[Polygonaceae]]), [[quinoa]] ([[Amaranthaceae]]) and [[Salvia hispanica|chia]] ([[Lamiaceae]]), are referred to as [[pseudocereal]]s.

In their natural, unprocessed, ''[[whole grain]]'' form, cereals are a rich source of [[vitamin]]s, [[Dietary mineral|minerals]], [[carbohydrate]]s, [[fat]]s, oils, and [[protein (nutrient)|protein]]. When processed by the removal of the bran, and germ, the remaining [[endosperm]] is mostly [[carbohydrate]]. In some [[Developing country|developing countries]], grain in the form of [[rice]], [[wheat]], [[millet]], or [[maize]] constitutes a majority of daily sustenance. In [[Developed country|developed countries]], cereal consumption is moderate and varied but still substantial.

The word ''cereal'' is derived from ''[[Ceres (Roman mythology)|Ceres]]'', the Roman goddess of harvest and agriculture.&lt;ref name=&quot;spaeth&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last1=Spaeth |first1=Barbette Stanley |title=The Roman goddess Ceres |date=1996 |publisher=University of Texas Press |isbn=0292776934 |edition=1st }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Ancient history==
{{Further|Neolithic Revolution}}
[[File:Trilla del trigo en el Antiguo Egipto.jpg|thumb|Threshing of grain in [[ancient Egypt]]]]
[[File:Roman harvester, Trier.jpg|thumb|Roman harvesting machine]]

[[Agriculture]] allowed for the support of an increased population, leading to larger societies and eventually the development of cities. It also created the need for greater organization of political power (and the creation of [[social stratification]]), as decisions had to be made regarding labor and harvest allocation and access rights to water and land. Agriculture bred immobility, as populations settled down for long periods of time, which led to the accumulation of material goods.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://anthro.ucsd.edu/~dkjordan/arch/neolithic/Neo3-LivRev.html|title=Living the Revolution|author=DK Jordan|date=24 November 2012|work=The Neolithic|publisher=University of California – San Diego|accessdate=22 April 2013|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131029191022/http://anthro.ucsd.edu/~dkjordan/arch/neolithic/Neo3-LivRev.html|archivedate=29 October 2013|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Early [[Neolithic]] villages show evidence of the development of processing grain. The [[Levant]] is the ancient home of the ancestors of [[wheat]], [[barley]] and [[pea]]s, in which many of these villages were based. There is evidence of the cultivation of cereals in Syria approximately 9,000 years ago. During the same period, farmers in China began to farm [[rice]] and [[millet]], using human-made floods and fires as part of their cultivation regimen.&lt;ref name=NatGeo&gt;{{cite magazine|url=https://genographic.nationalgeographic.com/development-of-agriculture/ |title=The Development of Agriculture |magazine=National Geographic |accessdate=22 April 2013 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160414142437/https://genographic.nationalgeographic.com/development-of-agriculture/ |archivedate=14 April 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Fiber crops were domesticated as early as food crops, with China domesticating [[hemp]], [[cotton]] being developed independently in Africa and South America, and [[Western Asia]] domesticating [[flax]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Plant evolution and the origin of crop species|page=119|author=Hancock, James F.|url=https://books.google.com/?id=j_O9ZnFRNngC&amp;pg=PA119&amp;lpg=PA119&amp;dq=domestication+of+fiber+crops#v=onepage&amp;q=domestication%20of%20fiber%20crops&amp;f=false|publisher=CABI|year=2012|isbn=978-1-84593-801-7|edition=3rd}}&lt;/ref&gt; The use of [[soil amendment]]s, including [[manure]], fish, [[compost]] and [[wood ash|ashes]], appears to have begun early, and developed independently in several areas of the world, including [[Mesopotamia]], the [[Nile Valley]] and Eastern Asia.&lt;ref name=FertMan&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/?id=qPkoOU4BvEsC&amp;pg=PA44&amp;dq=history+of+fertilizer#v=onepage&amp;q=history%20of%20fertilizer&amp;f=false|page=46|author=UN Industrial Development Organization, [[International Fertilizer Development Center]]|title=The Fertilizer Manual|publisher=Springer|year=1998|edition=3rd|isbn=978-0-7923-5032-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The first cereal grains were [[domesticated]] by early primitive humans.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url= https://books.google.com/?id=OgzSBQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA535&amp;dq=first+cereal+grain#v=onepage&amp;q=first%20cereal%20grain&amp;f=false|title= Cereal Grains: Properties, Processing, and Nutritional Attributes|last1= Serna-Saldivar|first1= Sergio|page= 535|date= 2010|accessdate= 22 June 2015|url-status= live|archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20150622063309/https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=OgzSBQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA535&amp;dq=first+cereal+grain&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=_1yHVbjCG4bB7gb5soLoAw&amp;ved=0CDgQ6AEwBA#v=onepage&amp;q=first%20cereal%20grain&amp;f=false|archivedate= 22 June 2015|df= dmy-all|isbn=978-1-4398-8209-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; About 8,000 years ago, they were domesticated by ancient farming communities in the [[Fertile Crescent]] region. [[Emmer|Emmer wheat]], [[einkorn wheat]], and [[barley]] were three of the so-called [[Neolithic founder crops]] in the development of agriculture. Around the same time, millets and rices were starting to become domesticated in East Asia. Sorghum and millets were also being domesticated in sub-Saharan West Africa.

==The Green Revolution==
{{main|Green Revolution}}
During the second half of the 20th century there was a significant increase in the production of high-yield cereal crops worldwide, especially  wheat and rice, due to an initiative known as the [[Green Revolution]].&lt;ref name=FAOGreenRevolution&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fao.org/docrep/003/w2612e/w2612e06a.htm|title=Lessons from the green revolution: towards a new green revolution|publisher=[[Food and Agriculture Organization|FAO]]|accessdate=5 June 2017|quote=The green revolution was a technology package comprising material components of improved high-yielding varieties (HYVs) of two staple cereals (rice or &quot;wheat&quot;), irrigation or controlled &quot;water&quot; supply and improved moisture utilization, fertilizers and pesticides and associated management skills.|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170518074944/http://www.fao.org/docrep/003/w2612e/w2612e06a.htm|archivedate=18 May 2017|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; The strategies developed by the Green Revolution focused on fending off starvation and increasing yield-per-plant, and were very successful in raising overall yields of cereal grains, but did not give sufficient relevance to nutritional quality.&lt;ref name=SandsMorris2009&gt;{{cite journal| vauthors=Sands DC, Morris CE, Dratz EA, Pilgeram A| title=Elevating optimal human nutrition to a central goal of plant breeding and production of plant-based foods. | journal=Plant Sci | year= 2009 | volume= 177 | issue= 5 | pages= 377–89 | pmid=20467463 | doi=10.1016/j.plantsci.2009.07.011 | pmc=2866137 | type=Review }}&lt;/ref&gt; These modern high yield-cereal crops tend have low [[Protein quality|quality proteins]], with [[essential amino acid]] deficiencies, are high in [[carbohydrate]]s, and lack balanced [[essential fatty acid]]s, [[vitamin]]s, [[mineral]]s and other quality factors.&lt;ref name=SandsMorris2009 /&gt; So-called ancient grains and heirloom varieties have seen an increase in popularity with the &quot;organic&quot; movements of the early 21st century, but there is a tradeoff in yield-per-plant, putting pressure on resource-poor areas as food crops are replaced with cash crops.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://recipes.howstuffworks.com/did-quinoa-get-too-popular-for-its-own-good.htm|title=Did Quinoa Get Too Popular for Its Own Good?|date=2018-11-05|website=HowStuffWorks|language=en|access-date=2019-08-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Farming==
[[File:040719 172 dorset marnhull.jpg|thumb|A wheat field in [[Dorset]], [[England]]]]
While each individual species has its own peculiarities, the cultivation of all cereal crops is similar. Most are [[annual plant]]s; consequently one planting yields one harvest. Wheat, rye, triticale, oats, barley, and spelt are the &quot;cool-season&quot; cereals.{{citation needed|date=January 2011}} These are hardy plants that grow well in moderate weather and cease to grow in hot weather (approximately {{convert|30|°C|disp=sqbr}}, but this varies by species and variety). The &quot;warm-season&quot; cereals are tender and prefer hot weather. Barley and rye are the hardiest cereals, able to overwinter in the [[subarctic]] and [[Siberia]]. Many cool-season cereals are grown in the tropics. However, some are only grown in cooler highlands, where it ' &quot;may&quot; ' be possible to grow multiple crops per year.

For the past few decades, there has also been increasing interest in [[perennial]] grain plants. This interest developed due to advantages in erosion control, reduced need for fertiliser, and potential lowered costs to the farmer. Though research is still in early stages, [[The Land Institute]] in Salina, Kansas has been able to create a few cultivars that produce a fairly good crop yield.&lt;ref&gt;Kunzig, Robert (April 2011) [http://ngm.nationalgeographic.com/2011/04/big-idea/perennial-grains-text The Big Idea: Perennial Grains] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20111005202205/http://ngm.nationalgeographic.com/2011/04/big-idea/perennial-grains-text |date=5 October 2011 }}. National Geographic.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Planting===
[[File:Dinrêyes.jpg|thumb|Cereal [[grain]] seeds from left to right, top to bottom: [[wheat]], [[spelt]], [[barley]], [[oat]].]]
The warm-season cereals are grown in tropical lowlands year-round and in temperate climates during the frost-free season. Rice is commonly grown in flooded fields, though some strains are grown on dry land. Other warm climate cereals, such as [[sorghum]], are adapted to arid conditions.

Cool-season cereals are well-adapted to temperate climates. Most varieties of a particular species are either '''winter''' or '''spring''' types. Winter varieties are sown in the autumn, germinate and grow vegetatively, then become [[dormancy|dormant]] during winter. They resume growing in the springtime and mature in late spring or early summer. This cultivation system makes optimal use of water and frees the land for another crop early in the growing season.

Winter varieties do not flower until springtime because they require [[vernalization]]: exposure to low temperatures for a genetically determined length of time. Where winters are too warm for vernalization or exceed the hardiness of the crop (which varies by species and variety), farmers grow spring varieties. Spring cereals are planted in early springtime and mature later that same summer, without vernalization. Spring cereals typically require more irrigation and yield less than winter cereals.

===Harvesting===
[[File:3-piantagione, Taccuino Sanitatis, Casanatense 4182.jpg|thumb|upright=0.8|Threshing; ''Tacuinum Sanitatis'', 14th century]]
Once the cereal plants have grown their seeds, they have completed their [[Biological life cycle|life cycle]]. The plants die, become brown, and dry. As soon as the parent plants and their seed kernels are reasonably dry, harvest can begin.

In developed countries, cereal crops are universally machine-harvested, typically using a [[combine harvester]], which cuts, [[threshing|threshes]], and [[winnowing|winnows]] the grain during a single pass across the field. In developing countries, a variety of harvesting methods are in use, depending on the cost of labor, from combines to hand tools such as the [[scythe]] or [[grain cradle]].

If a crop is harvested during humid weather, the grain may not dry adequately in the field to prevent spoilage during its storage. In this case, the grain is sent to a dehydrating facility, where artificial heat dries it.

In North America, farmers commonly deliver their newly harvested grain to a [[grain elevator]], a large storage facility that consolidates the crops of many farmers. The farmer may sell the grain at the time of delivery or maintain ownership of a share of grain in the pool for later sale. Storage facilities should be protected from small grain pests, rodents and birds.

==Production==
[[File:MaizeYield.png|thumb|right|Worldwide maize production]]
[[File:RiceYield.png|thumb|right|Worldwide rice production]]
[[File:WheatYield.png|thumb|right|A map of worldwide wheat production.]]
The following table shows the annual production of cereals in 1961,{{efn|1961 is the earliest year for which [[FAO]] statistics are available.}} 2010, 2011, 2012, and 2013 ranked by 2013 production.&lt;ref name=&quot;prodstat&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://faostat.fao.org/site/567/DesktopDefault.aspx | title=ProdSTAT | work=FAOSTAT | accessdate=26 December 2006 | url-status=live | archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120210214103/http://faostat.fao.org/site/567/DesktopDefault.aspx | archivedate=10 February 2012 | df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

{| valign=&quot;top&quot; | class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
! rowspan=2 | Grain
! colspan=5 nowrap | Worldwide production &lt;br /&gt; (millions of metric tons)
! rowspan=2 | Notes
|-
! 1961 !! 2010 !! 2011 !! 2012 !! 2013
|-
| [[Maize]] (corn)
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 205
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 851
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 888
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 872
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 1016
| A staple food of people in the Americas, Africa, and of [[livestock]] worldwide; often called corn in North America, Australia, and New Zealand. A large portion of maize crops are grown for purposes other than human consumption.
|-
| [[Rice]]{{efn|The weight given is for paddy rice}}
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 285
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 703
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 725
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 720
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 745
| The primary cereal of tropical and some temperate regions. [[Staple food]] in most of [[Brazil]] (both maize and manioc/[[cassava]] were once more important and their presence is still stronger in some areas), other parts of [[Latin America]] and some other Portuguese-descended cultures, parts of Africa (even more before the [[Columbian exchange]]), most of [[South Asia]] and the [[Far East]]. Largely overridden by [[breadfruit]] (a dicot tree) during the South Pacific's part of the [[Austronesian peoples|Austronesian]] expansion.
|-
| [[Wheat]]
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 222
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 650
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 699
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 671
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 713
| The primary cereal of temperate regions. It has a worldwide consumption but it is a staple food of North America, Europe, Australia, New Zealand, most of the [[Southern Cone]] and much of the [[Greater Middle East]]. [[Wheat gluten (food)|Wheat gluten]]-based meat substitutes are important in the Far East (albeit less than [[tofu]]) and said to resemble meat texture more than others.
|-
| [[Barley]]
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 72
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 124
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 133
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 133
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 144
| Grown for [[malt]]ing and [[livestock]] on land too poor or too cold for wheat.
|-
| [[Commercial sorghum|Sorghum]]
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 41
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 60
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 58
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 57
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 61
| Important staple food in Asia and Africa and popular worldwide for livestock.
|-
| [[Millet]]
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 26
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 33
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 27
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 30
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 30
| A group of similar but distinct cereals that form an important staple food in Asia and Africa.
|-
| [[Oat]]s
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 50
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 20
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 22
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 21
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 23
| Popular worldwide as a breakfast food and livestock feed. In human consumption, oats can be served as [[porridge]] as [[oatmeal]],&lt;ref name=&quot;whfoods&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.whfoods.com/genpage.php?tname=foodspice&amp;dbid=54 | title=Oats | publisher=The World's Healthiest Foods | accessdate=25 June 2015 | url-status=live | archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150629012417/http://www.whfoods.com/genpage.php?tname=foodspice&amp;dbid=54 | archivedate=29 June 2015 | df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; although oats could be eaten in various different forms other than [[rolled oats]], including unprocessed oats.&lt;ref name=&quot;whfoods&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://wholegrainscouncil.org/whole-grains-101/types-of-oats | title=Types of Oats | accessdate=25 June 2015 | url-status=live | archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150629041311/http://wholegrainscouncil.org/whole-grains-101/types-of-oats | archivedate=29 June 2015 | df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| [[Rye]]
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 12
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 12
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 13
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 15
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 16
| Important in cold climates.
|-
| [[Triticale]]
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 35
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 14
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 13
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 14
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 14.5
| [[Hybrid (biology)|Hybrid]] of wheat and rye, grown similarly to rye.
|-
| [[Fonio]]
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 0.18
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 0.57
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 0.59
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 0.59
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 0.6
| Several varieties are grown as food crops in Africa.
|}

Maize, wheat, and rice together accounted for 89% of all cereal production worldwide in 2012, and 43% of all food calories in 2009,&lt;ref name=&quot;prodstat&quot;/&gt; while the production of oats and triticale have drastically fallen from their 1960s levels.

Other cereals worthy of notice, but not included in [[FAO]] statistics, include:
* [[Teff]], an ancient grain that is a staple in [[Ethiopia]]. It is high in fiber and protein. Its flour is often used to make [[injera]]. It can also be eaten as a warm breakfast cereal similar to [[farina (food)|farina]] with a chocolate or nutty flavor. Its flour and whole grain products can usually be found in natural foods stores.
* [[Wild rice]], grown in small amounts in North America.

Several other species of wheat have also been domesticated, some very early in the history of agriculture:
* [[Spelt]], a close relative of common wheat.
* [[Einkorn]], a wheat species with a single grain.
* [[Emmer]], one of the first crops domesticated in the [[Fertile Crescent]].
* [[Durum]], the only [[tetraploid]] species of wheat currently cultivated, used to make [[semolina]].
* [[Kamut]], an ancient relative of durum with an unknown history.

In 2013 global cereal production reached a record 2,521 million tonnes. A slight dip to 2,498 million tonnes was forecasted for 2014 by the FAO in July 2014.

== Nutritional facts ==
Some grains are deficient in the [[essential amino acid]], [[lysine]]. That is why many vegetarian cultures, in order to get a balanced diet, combine their diet of grains with [[legume]]s. Many legumes, however, are deficient in the essential amino acid [[methionine]], which grains contain. Thus, a [[protein combining|combination]] of legumes with [[grain]]s forms a well-balanced diet for vegetarians. Common examples of such combinations are [[dal]] (lentils) with [[rice]] by [[South India]]ns and [[Bengali people|Bengalis]], dal with wheat in [[Pakistan]] and [[North India]], [[beans]] with corn tortillas, [[tofu]] with rice, and [[peanut butter]] with wheat bread (as sandwiches) in several other cultures, including the Americas.&lt;ref name=&quot;vogel301&quot;&gt;Vogel, Steven (2003). ''Prime Mover – A Natural History of Muscle''. W.W. Norton &amp; Company, p. 301. {{ISBN|0-393-32463-X}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The amount of [[crude protein]] measured in grains is expressed as grain crude protein concentration.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=Effects of Dietary Protein Concentration on Lactating Cows | journal =[[Journal of Dairy Science]] | volume = 63| issue = 2| page= 243| doi=10.3168/jds.S0022-0302(80)82920-1 |year=1980 |last1=Edwards |first1=J.S. |last2=Bartley |first2=E.E. |last3=Dayton |first3=A.D.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Cereals contain [[Exogeny|exogenous]] [[opioid]] [[peptide]]s called [[exorphin]]s and include [[opioid food peptides]] like [[Gluten exorphin]]. They mimic the actions of [[endorphine]]s because they bind to the same [[opioid receptor]]s in the brain.

==Standardization==
The [[International Organization of Standardization|ISO]] has published a series of standards regarding cereal products which are covered by ICS 67.060.&lt;ref name=cpdp&gt;{{cite web
 |last        = [[International Organization for Standardization]]
 |title       = 67.060: Cereals, pulses and derived products
 |url         = http://www.iso.org/iso/products/standards/catalogue_ics_browse.htm?ICS1=67&amp;ICS2=060&amp;
 |accessdate  = 23 April 2009
 |url-status     = live
 |archiveurl  = https://www.webcitation.org/685BF7hSA?url=http://www.iso.org/iso/products/standards/catalogue_ics_browse.htm?ICS1=67
 |archivedate = 31 May 2012
 |df          = dmy-all
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Food}}
{{Div col|colwidth=22em}}
* [[Breakfast cereal]]
* [[Chillcuring]], grain ventilating process
* [[Food price crisis]]
* [[Food quality]]
* [[Food safety]]
* [[Lists of foods]]
* [[Nutrition]]
* [[Post-harvest losses (grains)|Post-harvest losses]]
* [[Pseudocereal]]
* [[Pulse (legume)|Pulse]]
* [[Push–pull technology]]
* [[Zadoks scale]]
{{div col end}}

==Notes==
{{notelist}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
{{commonscat-inline|Cereals}}
{{wiktionary-inline|cereal}}
&lt;!--
 ! PLEASE READ THIS BEFORE ADDING A LINK HERE
 !
 ! The article is NOT about breakfast cereals! Please don't add links here for
 ! Web sites about them. If the link is otherwise appropriate (i.e. not spam)
 ! then you might consider adding it to [[breakfast cereal]] instead. Links
 ! about cereals will be REMOVED from this section.
 !--&gt;
{{Cereals}}
{{Agriculture country lists}}
{{Vegetarianism}}
{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Cereals| ]]
[[Category:Crops]]</text>
      <sha1>cpivw3m1o5ytqwdl0154yh8adua55uc</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
