  <page>
    <title>Constantius II</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6746</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942760870</id>
      <parentid>933983220</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-26T17:43:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Iridescent</username>
        <id>937705</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* War against Magnentius */Cleanup and [[WP:AWB/T|typo fixing]], [[WP:AWB/T|typo(s) fixed]]: ‘s → 's</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Roman emperor
| name            = Constantius II
| full name       = Flavius Julius Constantius
| regnal name     = *Flavius Julius Constantius Caesar (as Caesar)
*Imperator Caesar Flavius Julius Constantius Augustus (as Emperor)
| image=Constance II Colosseo Rome Italy.jpg
| caption         = Bust of Constantius II
| succession      = [[Roman Emperor|Emperor of the Roman Empire]]
| reign           = '''324''' (13 November) – '''337''' (22 May): [[Caesar (title)#Tetrarchy|Caesar]] under his father, [[Constantine I]]&lt;br&gt;
'''337 – 350''': co-[[Augustus (honorific)|Augustus]] (ruled Asian provinces &amp; [[History of Roman Egypt|Egypt]]) with [[Constantine II (emperor)|Constantine II]] and [[Constans]]
| predecessor     = [[Constantine I]]
| reg-type        = {{nowrap|Co-emperors}}
| regent          = Constantine II {{small|([[Western Roman Empire|Western Emperor]], 337–340)}}&lt;br&gt;Constans {{small|(Western Emperor, 337–350)}}
| reign1          = '''350''' – '''361''' (3 November): Sole Augustus of the Roman Empire
| successor1      = [[Julian (emperor)|Julian]]
| reg-type1       = {{no-wrap|Co-emperor}}
| regent1         = Julian {{small|(Western Emperor, 360–361)}}
| spouse 1        = [[Daughter of Julius Constantius]]
| spouse 2        = [[Eusebia (empress)|Eusebia]]
| spouse 3        = [[Faustina (empress)|Faustina]]
| issue           = [[Flavia Maxima Constantia]], born posthumously (later married [[Gratian]])
| dynasty         = [[Constantinian dynasty|Constantinian]]
| father          = [[Constantine I]]
| mother          = [[Fausta]]
| religion        = [[Arian Christianity]]
| birth_date      = 7 August 317
| birth_place     = [[Sirmium]], [[Pannonia Inferior]] ([[Sremska Mitrovica]], [[Serbia]])
| death_date      = {{death date and age|361|11|3|317|8|7|df=y}}
| death_place     = [[Mopsuestia]], [[Cilicia]]
| place of burial = [[Church of the Holy Apostles]]
| title           = [[Augustus (honorific)|Augustus]]}}

'''Constantius II''' ({{lang-la|Flavius Julius Constantius Augustus}};&lt;ref&gt;In [[Classical Latin]], Constantius' name would be inscribed as FLAVIVS IVLIVS CONSTANTIVS AVGVSTVS.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;CIL 06, 40776 = AE 1934, 00158 = AE 1950, 00174 = AE 1951, 00102 = AE 1982, 00011&lt;/ref&gt; {{lang-grc-gre|Κωνστάντιος}}; 7 August 317 – 3 November 361) was [[Roman Emperor]] from 337 to 361. His reign saw constant warfare on the borders against the [[Sasanian Empire]] and [[Germanic peoples]], while internally the [[Roman Empire]] went through repeated civil wars and usurpations. His religious policies inflamed domestic conflicts that would continue after his death.

The second son of [[Constantine I]] and [[Fausta]], Constantius was made ''[[Caesar (title)|Caesar]]'' by his father in 324. He led the [[Late Roman army|Roman army]] in [[Persian wars of Constantius II|war]] against the Sasanian Empire in 336. A year later, Constantine I died, and Constantius became ''[[Augustus (title)|Augustus]]'' with his brothers [[Constantine II (emperor)|Constantine II]] and [[Constans]]. He promptly oversaw the massacre of eight of his relatives, consolidating his hold on power. The brothers divided the empire among themselves, with Constantius receiving the eastern provinces. In 340, his brothers Constantine and Constans clashed over the western provinces of the empire. The resulting conflict left Constantine dead and Constans as ruler of the west. The war against the Sasanians continued, with Constantius losing a major [[Siege of Singara|battle]] at [[Singara]] in 344. Constans was overthrown and assassinated in 350 by the [[usurper]] [[Magnentius]]. 

Unwilling to accept Magnentius as co-ruler, Constantius waged a [[Roman civil war of 350–353|civil war]] against the usurper, defeating him at the battles of [[Battle of Mursa Major|Mursa Major]] in 351 and [[Battle of Mons Seleucus|Mons Seleucus]] in 353. Magnentius committed suicide after the latter battle, leaving Constantius as sole ruler of the empire. In 351, Constantius elevated his cousin [[Constantius Gallus]] to the subordinate rank of ''Caesar'' to rule in the east, but had him executed three years later after receiving scathing reports of his violent and corrupt nature. Shortly thereafter, in 355, Constantius promoted his last surviving cousin, Gallus' younger half-brother Julian, to the rank of ''Caesar''.

As emperor, Constantius promoted [[Arianism|Arian Christianity]], [[Anti-paganism policy of Constantius II|persecuted]] [[Paganism|pagan]]s by banning sacrifices and closing pagan temples and issued laws discriminating against [[Jews]]. His military campaigns against Germanic tribes were successful: he defeated the [[Alamanni]] in 354 and campaigned across the [[Danube]] against the [[Quadi]] and [[Sarmatians]] in 357. The war against the Sasanians, which had been in a lull since 350, erupted with renewed intensity in 359 and Constantius traveled to the east in 360 to restore stability after the loss of several border fortresses to the Sasanians. However, Julian claimed the rank of [[Augustus (honorific)|Augustus]] in 360, leading to war between the two after Constantius' attempts to convince Julian to back down failed. No battle was fought, as Constantius became ill and died of fever on 3 November 361 in [[Mopsuestia]], naming Julian as his rightful successor before his death.

==Early life==
{{stack|float=right| {{multiple image|direction=vertical
|image1=Roman Imperial Follis Caesar Constantius II 325.jpg
|caption1=Caesar Constantius II on an early [[follis]] of [[Heraclea Lucania|Heraclea]] 325
|image2=Bust of Prince Constantius II in blue glass, Romisch-Germanisches Museum, Cologne (8115676712).jpg
|caption2=Bust of Constantius II while he was a prince, [[Romano-Germanic Museum]], [[Cologne]]
|image3=Impero Romano da maggio a settembre 337.png
|caption3=Division of the Roman Empire among the Caesars appointed by [[Constantine I]]: from west to east, the territories of [[Constantine II (emperor)|Constantine II]], [[Constans I]], [[Dalmatius]] and Constantius II. After the death of Constantine I (May 337), this was the formal division of the Empire, until Dalmatius was killed and his territory divided between Constans and Constantius.
}}}}
Constantius was born in 317 at [[Sirmium]], [[Pannonia]]. He was the third son of [[Constantine the Great]], and second by his second wife [[Fausta]], the daughter of [[Maximian]]. Constantius was made [[Caesar (title)|Caesar]] by his father on 13 November 324.&lt;ref&gt;DiMaio Jr., M. &amp; Frakes, R. 'DIR-Constantius II' from De Imperatoribus Romanis [http://www.roman-emperors.org/constaii.htm]&lt;/ref&gt; 
In 336, religious unrest in [[Kingdom of Armenia (antiquity)|Armenia]] and tense relations between Constantine and king [[Shapur II]] caused war to break out between Rome and [[Sassanid Persia]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Dodgeon, M.H p152-153&quot;&gt;Dodgeon, M.H. and Lieu, N.C. ''The Roman Eastern Frontier and the Persian Wars, AD 226–363''. p152-153&lt;/ref&gt; Though he made initial preparations for the war, Constantine fell ill and sent Constantius east to take command of the eastern frontier.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dodgeon, M.H p152-153&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Julian, ''Orationes'' I, 13B&lt;/ref&gt; Before Constantius arrived, the Persian general Narses, who was possibly the king's brother, overran [[Mesopotamia (Roman province)|Mesopotamia]] and captured [[Diyarbakir|Amida]]. Constantius promptly attacked Narses, and after suffering minor setbacks defeated and killed Narses at the Battle of Narasara.&lt;ref&gt;Festus, ''breviarum'' 27, p. 67, 2–3&lt;/ref&gt; Constantius captured Amida and initiated a major refortification of the city, enhancing the city's circuit walls and constructing large towers. He also built a new stronghold in the hinterland nearby, naming it ''Antinopolis''.&lt;ref&gt;Ammianus Marcellinus XVIII, 9, 1&lt;/ref&gt;

==Augustus in the East==
{{multiple image|direction=vertical
|image4=Constantius II.jpg
|caption4=Bust of youthful Constantius II, [[Capitoline Museums]]
|image5=Constantius II - solidus - antioch RIC viii 025.jpg
|caption5=Gold [[Solidus (coin)|solidus]] of Constantius II, celebrating the 15th year of his reign
|image6=Double Centenionalis Magnentius-XR-s4017.jpg
|caption6=Bronze coin of [[Magnentius]]
|image7=Solidus-Constantius Gallus-thessalonica RIC 149.jpg
|caption7=Gold solidus of Constantius Gallus. A paternal cousin of Constantius, he was made [[Caesar (title)|Caesar]] by Constantius in 350 and was married to the Emperor's sister, [[Constantina]]. However, his mismanagement of the eastern provinces led to his downfall and death in 354.
}}
In early 337, Constantius hurried to [[Constantinople]] after receiving news that his father was near death.&lt;ref&gt;''Chronicon Paschale'' p.533, 5–17&lt;/ref&gt; After Constantine died, Constantius buried him  with lavish ceremony in the [[Church of the Holy Apostles]].&lt;ref&gt;Julian, ''or''. I, 18D-19A (14.16–22, pp. 31–2, Bidez)&lt;/ref&gt; Soon after his father's death Constantius supposedly ordered a massacre of his relatives descended from the second marriage of his paternal grandfather [[Constantius Chlorus]], though the details are unclear.&lt;ref&gt;X. Lucien-Brun, &quot;Constance II et le massacre des princes,&quot; ''Bulletin de l'[[Association Guillaume Budé]]'' ser. 4 (1973): 585–602; Joe W. Leedom, &quot;Constantius II: Three Revisions,&quot; ''Byzantion'' 48 (1978): 132–145, and Michael DiMaio and Duane Arnold, &quot;Per Vim, Per Caedem, Per Bellum: A Study of Murder and Ecclesiastical Politics in the Year 337 A.D,&quot; ''Byzantion'', 62(1992), 158ff. Cited in DiMaio and Frakes.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Zosimus]], ''New History'' II.57-8&lt;/ref&gt; [[Eutropius (historian)|Eutropius]], writing between 350 and 370, states that Constantius merely sanctioned “''the act, rather than commanding it''”.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;[[Eutropius (historian)|Eutropius]], ''Historiae Romanae Breviarium'' X.9&lt;/ref&gt; The massacre killed two of Constantius' uncles and six of his cousins,&lt;ref&gt;Julian, ''epistula ad Athenienses'' 270C (3.5–8, p. 215, Bidez)&lt;/ref&gt; including [[Hannibalianus]] and [[Dalmatius]], rulers of [[Diocese of Pontus|Pontus]] and [[Diocese of Moesia|Moesia]] respectively. The massacre left Constantius, his older brother [[Constantine II (emperor)|Constantine II]], his younger brother [[Constans]], and three cousins [[Constantius Gallus|Gallus]], [[Julian the Apostate|Julian]] and [[Nepotianus]] as the only surviving male relatives of Constantine the Great.

Soon after, Constantius met his brothers in [[Pannonia]] at [[Sirmium]] to formalize the partition of the empire.&lt;ref&gt;Odahl, C.M., ''Constantine and the Christian Empire'' (2004), p. 275&lt;/ref&gt; Constantius received the eastern provinces, including Constantinople, [[Roman Thrace|Thrace]], [[Asia Minor]], [[Roman Syria|Syria]], [[Roman Egypt|Egypt]], and [[Cyrenaica]]; Constantine received [[Roman Britain|Britannia]], [[Roman Gaul|Gaul]], [[Hispania]], and [[Mauretania Tingitana|Mauretania]]; and Constans, initially under the supervision of Constantine II, received [[Italia (Roman Empire)|Italy]], [[Africa Province|Africa]], [[Illyricum (Roman province)|Illyricum]], [[Pannonia]], [[Macedonia (Roman province)|Macedonia]], and [[Achaea (Roman province)|Achaea]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Zosimus]], ''New History'' II.57&lt;/ref&gt;

Constantius then hurried east to [[Antioch]] to resume the [[Persian wars of Constantius II|war with Persia]].&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;Theodoret, ''Historia Ecclesiastica'' II, 30, 1–14, GCS&lt;/ref&gt; While Constantius was away from the eastern frontier in early 337, King [[Shapur II]] assembled a large army, which included war elephants, and launched an attack on Roman territory, laying waste to Mesopotamia&lt;ref&gt;Jerome, ''Chronicon, s. a.'' 338 p. 234, 17–18&lt;/ref&gt; and putting the city of Nisibis under siege.&lt;ref&gt;Theodoret, ''Historia religiosa'' I, 11–12, edd. Canivet and Leroy-Molinghen, pp. 184–8&lt;/ref&gt; Despite initial success, Shapur lifted his siege after his army missed an opportunity to exploit a collapsed wall.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;/&gt; When Constantius learned of Shapur's withdrawal from Roman territory, he prepared his army for a counter-attack.

Constantius repeatedly defended the eastern border against invasions by the aggressive [[Sassanid Empire]] under Shapur. These conflicts were mainly limited to Sassanid sieges of the major fortresses of [[Roman Mesopotamia]], including [[Nisibis]] ([[Nusaybin]]), [[Singara]], and [[Diyarbakir|Amida]] ([[Diyarbakir]]). Although Shapur seems to have been victorious in most of these confrontations, the Sassanids were able to achieve little.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;&gt;[[Festus (historian)|Festus]], ''Brevarium'' XXVII&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Dignas, B. 2007 p. 89&quot;&gt;Dignas, B. &amp; Winter, E., ''Rome and Persia in Late Antiquity'' (2007), p. 89&lt;/ref&gt; However, the Romans won a decisive victory at the Battle of Narasara, killing Shapur's brother, Narses.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Theophanes the Confessor|Theophanes]], ''Chronicle'' A.M. 5815&lt;/ref&gt; Ultimately, Constantius was able to push back the invasion, and Shapur failed to make any significant gains.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dignas, B. 2007 p. 89&quot;/&gt;

Meanwhile, Constantine II desired to retain control of Constans' realm, leading the brothers into open conflict. Constantine was killed in 340 near [[Aquileia]] during an ambush.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; As a result, Constans took control of his deceased brother's realms and became sole ruler of the Western two-thirds of the empire. This division lasted until 350, when Constans was assassinated by forces loyal to the [[Roman usurper|usurper]] [[Magnentius]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Zosimus]] ''New History'' II.58-9&lt;/ref&gt;

===War against Magnentius===
{{main|Roman civil war of 350–353}}
As the only surviving son of Constantine the Great, Constantius felt that the position of [[Roman Emperor|emperor]] was his alone,&lt;ref name=&quot;Zosimus, New History II.60&quot;&gt;Zosimus, ''New History'' II.60&lt;/ref&gt; and he determined to march west to fight the usurper, [[Magnentius]]. However, feeling that the east still required some sort of imperial presence, he elevated his cousin [[Constantius Gallus]] to Caesar of the eastern provinces. As an extra measure to ensure the loyalty of his cousin, he married the elder of his two sisters, [[Constantina]], to him.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zosimus, New History II.60&quot;/&gt;

Before facing Magnentius, Constantius first came to terms with [[Vetranio]], a loyal general in [[Illyricum (Roman province)|Illyricum]] who had recently been acclaimed emperor by his soldiers. Vetranio immediately sent letters to Constantius pledging his loyalty, which Constantius may have accepted simply in order to stop Magnentius from gaining more support. These events may have been spurred by the action of Constantina, who had since traveled east to marry Gallus. Constantius subsequently sent Vetranio the imperial diadem and acknowledged the general's new position as ''[[Augustus (title)|Augustus]]''. However, when Constantius arrived, Vetranio willingly resigned his position and accepted Constantius’ offer of a comfortable retirement in [[Bithynia]].&lt;ref&gt;Zosimus, ''New History'' II.59&lt;/ref&gt;

In 351, Constantius clashed with Magnentius in [[Pannonia]] with a large army. The ensuing [[Battle of Mursa Major]] was one of the largest and bloodiest battles ever between two Roman armies.&lt;ref&gt;[[Joannes Zonaras|Zonaras]], ''Extracts of History'' XIII.8.5–13&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Julian the Apostate]], ''The Caesars'' XLII.9–10&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Zosimus]], ''New History'' II.46.2&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Eutropius (historian)|Eutropius]], ''Roman History'' X.12&lt;/ref&gt; The result was a victory for Constantius, but a costly one. Magnentius survived the battle and, determined to fight on, withdrew into northern Italy. Rather than pursuing his opponent, however, Constantius turned his attention to securing the Danubian border, where he spent the early months of 352 campaigning against the [[Sarmatians]] along the middle [[Danube]]. After achieving his aims, Constantius advanced on Magnentius in Italy. This action led the cities of Italy to switch their allegiance to him and eject the usurper's garrisons. Again, Magnentius withdrew, this time to southern [[Roman Gaul|Gaul]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Potter, D.S. 2004 p. 474&quot;&gt;Potter, D.S., ''The Roman Empire at Bay: AD 180–395'' (2004), p. 474&lt;/ref&gt;

In 353, Constantius and Magnentius met for the final time at the [[Battle of Mons Seleucus]] in southern Gaul, and again Constantius emerged the victor.&lt;ref name=&quot;Potter, D.S. 2004 p. 474&quot;/&gt; Magnentius, realizing the futility of continuing his position, committed suicide on 10 August 353.&lt;ref&gt;[[Eutropius (historian)|Eutropius]], ''Historiae Romanae Breviarium'' X.12&lt;/ref&gt;

==Sole ruler of the empire==
Constantius spent much of the rest of 353 and early 354 on campaign against the [[Alamanni]] on the Danube frontier. The campaign was successful and raiding by the Alamanni ceased temporarily. In the meantime, Constantius had been receiving disturbing reports regarding the actions of his cousin Gallus.&lt;ref&gt;[[Ammianus Marcellinus]], ''Res Gestae'' 14.1.10&lt;/ref&gt; Possibly as a result of these reports, Constantius concluded a peace with the Alamanni and traveled to [[Mediolanum]] ([[Milan]]).&lt;ref&gt;[[Ammianus Marcellinus]], ''Res Gestae'' XIV.10.16&lt;/ref&gt;

In Mediolanum, Constantius first summoned [[Ursicinus (Roman general)|Ursicinus]], Gallus’ ''magister equitum'', for reasons that remain unclear.&lt;ref&gt;[[Ammianus Marcellinus]], ''Res Gestae'' XIV.11.3–5&lt;/ref&gt; Constantius then summoned Gallus and Constantina.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceC&quot;&gt;[[Ammianus Marcellinus]], ''Res Gestae'' XIV.11.6&lt;/ref&gt; Although Gallus and Constantina complied with the order at first, when Constantina died in [[Bithynia]],&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceC&quot;/&gt; Gallus began to hesitate. However, after some convincing by one of Constantius’ agents,&lt;ref&gt;[[Ammianus Marcellinus]], ''Res Gestae'' XIV.11.11–12&lt;/ref&gt; Gallus continued his journey west, passing through [[Constantinople]] and [[Thracia (Roman province)|Thrace]] to [[Poetovio]] ([[Ptuj]]) in [[Pannonia]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Ammianus Marcellinus]], ''Res Gestae'' XIV.11.19&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;roman-emperors.org&quot;&gt;[http://www.roman-emperors.org/gallus.htm Banchich, T.M., 'DIR-Gallus' from De Imperatoribus Romanis]&lt;/ref&gt;

In Poetovio, Gallus was arrested by the soldiers of Constantius under the command of [[Barbatio]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Ammianus Marcellinus]], ''Res Gestae'' XIV.11.20&lt;/ref&gt; Gallus was then moved to [[Pula|Pola]] and interrogated. Gallus claimed that it was Constantina who was to blame for all the trouble while he was in charge of the eastern provinces.&lt;ref&gt;[[Ammianus Marcellinus]], ''Res Gestae'' XIV.11.22&lt;/ref&gt; This angered Constantius so greatly that he immediately ordered Gallus' execution.&lt;ref&gt;[[Ammianus Marcellinus]], ''Res Gestae'' XIV.11.23&lt;/ref&gt; He soon changed his mind, however, and recanted the order.&lt;ref&gt;[[Joannes Zonaras|Zonaras]], ''Extracts of History'' XIII.9.20&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Libanius]], ''Orations'' XVIII.152&lt;/ref&gt; Unfortunately for Gallus, this second order was delayed by [[Eusebius (praepositus sacri cubiculi)|Eusebius]], one of Constantius' eunuchs, and Gallus was executed.&lt;ref name=&quot;roman-emperors.org&quot;/&gt;

===Religious issues===
[[File:07 constantius2Chrono354.png|thumb|right|300px|Constantius II depicted in the [[Chronography of 354]] dispensing largesse (a [[Renaissance]] copy of a [[Carolingian art|Carolingian]] copy)]]

====Paganism====
{{See also|Anti-paganism policy of Constantius II}}
In spite of some of the edicts issued by Constantius, he never made any attempt to disband the various Roman priestly colleges or the [[Vestal Virgin]]s, he never acted against the various pagan schools, and, at times, he actually made some effort to protect paganism. In fact, he even ordered the election of a priest for Africa.&lt;ref name=&quot;Vasiliev, A.A 1958 p. 68&quot;&gt;Vasiliev, A.A, ''History of the Byzantine Empire 324–1453'' (1958), p. 68&lt;/ref&gt; Also, he remained [[pontifex maximus]] and was deified by the Roman Senate after his death. His relative moderation toward paganism is reflected by the fact that it was over twenty years after his death, during the reign of [[Gratian]], that any pagan senator protested his treatment of their religion.&lt;ref&gt;Salzman, M.R., ''The Making of a Christian Aristocracy: Social and Religious Change in the Western Roman Empire'' (2002), p. 182&lt;/ref&gt;

====Christianity====
Although often considered an [[Arianism|Arian]],&lt;ref&gt;Jones, A.H.M, ''The Later Roman Empire, 284–602: a Social, Economic and Administrative Survey'' (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University, 1986), p. 118&lt;/ref&gt; Constantius ultimately preferred a third, compromise version that lay somewhere in between [[Arianism]] and the [[Nicene Creed]], retrospectively called [[Semi-Arianism]].&lt;ref&gt;Pelikan, J.J., ''The Christian Tradition'' (1989), pp. 209–10&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Gaddis, M., ''There is No Crime for Those who Have Christ'' (2005), p. 92&lt;/ref&gt; During his reign he attempted to mold the Christian church to follow this compromise position, convening several Christian councils. The most notable of these were the [[Council of Rimini]] and its twin at [[Silifke|Seleucia]], which met in 359 and 360 respectively. &quot;Unfortunately for his memory the theologians whose advice he took were ultimately discredited and the malcontents whom he pressed to conform emerged victorious,&quot; writes the historian [[A.H.M. Jones]]. &quot;The great councils of 359–60 are therefore not reckoned [[Ecumenical council|ecumenical]] in the tradition of the church, and Constantius II is not remembered as a restorer of unity, but as a [[Arianism|heretic]] who arbitrarily imposed his will on the church.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones, A.H.M 1986 p. 118&quot;&gt;Jones, A.H.M, ''The Later Roman Empire, 284–602: a Social, Economic and Administrative Survey'' (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University, 1986), p. 118.&lt;/ref&gt;

Christian-related edicts issued by Constantius (by himself or with others) included:
* Exemption from compulsory public service for the clergy&lt;ref&gt;[[Codex Theodosianus]] 16.2.9&lt;/ref&gt;
* Exemption from compulsory public service for the sons of clergy&lt;ref&gt;[[Codex Theodosianus]] 16.2.11&lt;/ref&gt;
* Tax exemptions for clergy and their servants,&lt;ref&gt;[[Codex Theodosianus]] 16.2.8&lt;/ref&gt; and later for their family&lt;ref&gt;[[Codex Theodosianus]] 16.2.14&lt;/ref&gt;
* Clergy and the issue of private property&lt;ref&gt;[[Codex Theodosianus]] 16.2.15, 12.1.49 &amp; 8.4.7&lt;/ref&gt;
* Bishops exempted from being tried in secular courts&lt;ref&gt;[[Codex Theodosianus]] 16.2.12&lt;/ref&gt;
* Christian prostitutes only able to be bought by Christians&lt;ref&gt;[[Codex Theodosianus]] 15.8.1&lt;/ref&gt;

====Judaism====
[[File:Byzantine - Belt Section with Medallions of Constantius II and Faustina - Walters 57527 - Back.jpg|right|thumb|This section of a belt contains two gold medallions.  The larger coin depicts the triumphant emperor in his chariot.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |publisher= [[The Walters Art Museum]]
|url= http://art.thewalters.org/detail/# |title= Belt Section with Medallions of Constantius II and Faustina}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Walters Art Museum.]]
Judaism faced some severe restrictions under Constantius, who seems to have followed an anti-Jewish policy in line with that of his father.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schäfer, P. 2003 pp. 180-1&quot;&gt;Schäfer, P., ''The History of the Jews in the Greco-Roman World'' (2003), pp. 180–1&lt;/ref&gt; Early in his reign, Constantius issued a double edict in concert with his brothers limiting the ownership of slaves by Jewish people&lt;ref name=&quot;Codex Theodosianus 16.9.2&quot;&gt;[[Codex Theodosianus]] 16.9.2&lt;/ref&gt; and banning marriages between Jews and Christian women.&lt;ref name=&quot;Codex Theodosianus 16.9.2&quot;/&gt; A later edict issued by Constantius after becoming sole emperor decreed that a person who was proven to have converted from Christianity to Judaism would have all of his property confiscated by the state.&lt;ref name=&quot;Codex Theodosianus 16.8.7&quot;&gt;[[Codex Theodosianus]] 16.8.7&lt;/ref&gt; However, Constantius' actions in this regard may not have been so much to do with Jewish religion as with Jewish business—apparently, privately owned Jewish businesses were often in competition with state-owned businesses. As a result, Constantius may have sought to provide an advantage to state-owned businesses by limiting the skilled workers and slaves available to Jewish businesses.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schäfer, P. 2003 pp. 180-1&quot;/&gt;

Jew-related edicts issued by Constantius (by himself or with others) included:
* Weaving women who moved from working for the government to working for Jews must be restored to the government&lt;ref name=&quot;Codex Theodosianus 16.9.2&quot;/&gt;
* Jews may not marry Christian women&lt;ref name=&quot;Codex Theodosianus 16.9.2&quot;/&gt;
* Jews may not attempt to convert Christian women&lt;ref name=&quot;Codex Theodosianus 16.9.2&quot;/&gt;
* Any non-Jewish slave bought by a Jew will be confiscated by the state&lt;ref name=&quot;Codex Theodosianus 16.9.2&quot;/&gt;
* If a Jew attempts to circumcise a non-Jewish slave, the slave will be freed and the Jew shall face capital punishment&lt;ref name=&quot;Codex Theodosianus 16.9.2&quot;/&gt;
* Any Christian slaves owned by a Jew will be taken away and freed&lt;ref name=&quot;Codex Theodosianus 16.9.2&quot;/&gt;
* A person who is proven to have converted from Christianity to Judaism shall have their property confiscated by the state&lt;ref name=&quot;Codex Theodosianus 16.8.7&quot;/&gt;

===More usurpers and Julian===
[[File:Bust of Constantius II (Mary Harrsch).jpg|thumb|Bust of Constantius II in the [[University of Pennsylvania]]'s [[University of Pennsylvania Museum of Archaeology and Anthropology|Museum of Archaeology]]]]
On 11 August 355, the [[magister militum]] [[Claudius Silvanus]] revolted in Gaul. Silvanus had surrendered to Constantius after the [[Battle of Mursa Major]]. Constantius had made him magister militum in 353 with the purpose of blocking the German threats, a feat that Silvanus achieved by bribing the German tribes with the money he had collected. A plot organized by members of Constantius' court led the emperor to recall Silvanus. After Silvanus revolted, he received a letter from Constantius recalling him to Milan, but which made no reference to the revolt. [[Ursicinus (Roman general)|Ursicinus]], who was meant to replace Silvanus, bribed some troops, and Silvanus was killed.

Constantius realised that too many threats still faced the Empire, however, and he could not possibly handle all of them by himself. So on 6 November 355,&lt;ref&gt;[[Ammianus Marcellinus]], ''Res Gestae'' XV.8.17&lt;/ref&gt; he elevated his last remaining male relative, [[Julian the Apostate|Julian]], to the rank of [[Caesar (title)|Caesar]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Ammianus Marcellinus]], ''Res Gestae'' XV.8.5–16&lt;/ref&gt; A few days later, Julian was married to [[Helena, wife of Julian|Helena]], the last surviving sister of Constantius.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot;&gt;[[Ammianus Marcellinus]], ''Res Gestae'' XV.8.18&lt;/ref&gt; Constantius soon sent Julian off to Gaul.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot;/&gt;

Constantius spent the next few years overseeing affairs in the western part of the empire primarily from his base at Mediolanum. In 357 he visited [[Rome]] for the only time in his life. The same year, he forced [[Sarmatians|Sarmatian]] and [[Quadi]] invaders out of Pannonia and [[Moesia|Moesia Inferior]], then led a successful counter-attack across the Danube.&lt;ref&gt;[[Ammianus Marcellinus]], ''Res Gestae'' XVI.12&lt;/ref&gt;

In the winter of 357–58, Constantius received ambassadors from [[Shapur II]] who demanded that Rome restore the lands surrendered by [[Narseh]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Ammianus Marcellinus]], ''Res Gestae'' XVII.5.3–8&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Joannes Zonaras|Zonaras]], ''Extracts of History'' XII.9.25-7&lt;/ref&gt; Despite rejecting these terms,&lt;ref&gt;[[Ammianus Marcellinus]], ''Res Gestae'' XVII.5.9–14&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Joannes Zonaras|Zonaras]], ''Extracts of History'' XII.9.28-9&lt;/ref&gt; Constantius tried to avert war with the [[Sassanid Empire]] by sending two embassies to Shapur II.&lt;ref&gt;[[Libanius]], ''Epistle'' 331&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Ammianus Marcellinus]], ''Res Gestae'' XVII.14.1–3 &amp; XVIII.6.17-8&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Eunapius]], ''Lives of the Sophists'' VI. 5.1–10&lt;/ref&gt; Shapur II nevertheless launched another invasion of Roman Mesopotamia. In 360, when news reached Constantius that Shapur II had destroyed [[Singara]],&lt;ref&gt;[[Ammianus Marcellinus]], ''Res Gestae'' XX.6&lt;/ref&gt; and taken [[Hasankeyf|Kiphas]] ([[Hasankeyf]]), [[Diyarbakır|Amida]],&lt;ref&gt;[[Ammianus Marcellinus]], ''Res Gestae'' XIX&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Cizre|Ad Tigris]] ([[Cizre]]),&lt;ref&gt;[[Ammianus Marcellinus]], ''Res Gestae'' XX.7.1–16&lt;/ref&gt; he decided to travel east to face the re-emergent threat.

===Usurpation of Julian and crises in the east===
[[File:Missorium Kerch.jpg|thumb|300px|Missorium of Kerch depicting Constantius II on horseback with a spear. He is preceded by victory and accompanied by a guardsman.]]
In the meantime, Julian had won some victories against the [[Alamanni]], who had once again invaded [[Roman Gaul]]. However, when Constantius requested reinforcements from Julian's army for the eastern campaign, the Gallic legions revolted and proclaimed Julian ''Augustus''.&lt;ref&gt;[[Julian the Apostate]], ''Letter To The Senate And People of Athens'', X.12–17&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Libanius]], ''Orations'' XII.58 &amp; XVIII.90-1&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Eutropius (historian)|Eutropius]], ''Historiae Romanae Breviarium'' X.15.1&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Ammianus Marcellinus]], ''Res Gestae'' XX.4.1–2&lt;/ref&gt;

On account of the immediate Sassanid threat, Constantius was unable to directly respond to his cousin's usurpation, other than by sending missives in which he tried to convince Julian to resign the title of ''Augustus'' and be satisfied with that of ''Caesar''. By 361, Constantius saw no alternative but to face the usurper with force, and yet the threat of the [[Sassanid Empire|Sassanids]] remained. Constantius had already spent part of early 361 unsuccessfully attempting to re-take the fortress of Ad Tigris.&lt;ref&gt;[[Ammianus Marcellinus]], ''Res Gestae'' XX.11.6–25&lt;/ref&gt; After a time he had withdrawn to [[Antioch]] to regroup and prepare for a confrontation with [[Shapur II]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Ammianus Marcellinus]], ''Res Gestae'' XXI.7.7 &amp; 13.1–5&lt;/ref&gt; The campaigns of the previous year had inflicted heavy losses on the Sassanids, however, and they did not attempt another round of campaigns that year. This temporary respite in hostilities allowed Constantius to turn his full attention to facing Julian.&lt;ref name=&quot;Vagi, D.L. 2001 p. 508&quot;&gt;Vagi, D.L. &amp; Coquand, T., ''Coinage and History of the Roman Empire'' (2001), p. 508&lt;/ref&gt;

===Death===
Constantius immediately gathered his forces and set off west. However, by the time he reached [[Mopsuestia]] in Cilicia, it was clear that he was fatally ill and would not survive to face Julian. Apparently, realising his death was near, Constantius had himself baptised by [[Arianism|Euzoius]], the [[Semi-Arianism|Semi-Arian]] bishop of [[Antioch]], and then declared that Julian was his rightful successor.&lt;ref name=&quot;Vagi, D.L. 2001 p. 508&quot;/&gt; Constantius II died of fever on 3 November 361.&lt;ref&gt;The manuscript of Ammianus Marcellinus, ''Res Gestae'' 21.15.2 reads ''tertium nonarum Octobrium'', which is the equivalent of 5 October. The latest editor of the ''Res Gestae'' accepts Otto Seeck's emendation ''tertium nonarum Novembrium'' which is the equivalent of 3 November. T.D. Barnes (''Classical Philology'', 88 [1993], p. 64f) provides indirect evidence showing 3 November is a better fit.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Like Constantine the Great, he was buried in the [[Church of the Holy Apostles]], in a [[Porphyry (geology)#Imperial sarcophagi|porphyry sarcophagus]] that was described in the 10th century by [[Constantine VII|Constantine VII Porphyrogenitus]] in the ''[[De Ceremoniis]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=A. A. Vasiliev|title=Imperial Porphyry Sarcophagi in Constantinople|journal=Dumbarton Oaks Papers|volume=4|date=1848|pages=1+3-26|url=https://lucazavagno.files.wordpress.com/2012/12/vasiliev.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Marriages and children==
Constantius II was married three times:

First to a [[Daughter of Julius Constantius|daughter]] of his half-uncle [[Julius Constantius]], whose name is unknown. She was a full-sister of Gallus and a half-sister of Julian. She died c. 352/3.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.roman-emperors.org/gallus.htm |title=Gallus Caesar (15 March 351 - 354 A.D.) |last=Banchich |first=Thomas M. |website=De Imperatoribus Romanis |access-date=2018-09-07 |df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Second, to [[Eusebia (empress)|Eusebia]], a woman of [[Ancient Macedonians|Macedonian]] origin, originally from the city of [[Thessaloniki]], whom Constantius married before his defeat of Magnentius in 353. She died in 360.&lt;ref name=&quot;juneau&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | last = Juneau | first = J. | authorlink = | coauthors = | title = Piety and Politics: Eusebia and Constantius at Court | journal = The Classical Quarterly |series=New Series | volume = 49 | issue = 2 | pages = 641–644 | publisher = Cambridge University Press| location = | date= December 1999 | doi =10.1093/cq/49.2.641-a | id = | jstor=639898}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Third and lastly, in 360, to [[Faustina (empress)|Faustina]], who gave birth to Constantius' only child, a posthumous daughter named [[Flavia Maxima Constantia]], who later married Emperor [[Gratian]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |url=http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Ammian/21*.html |first=Ammianus |last=Marcellinus |author-link=Ammianus Marcellinus |title=The Roman History of Ammianus Marcellinus |volume=Vol. 2, Book 21, chapter 15 |year=1940 |translator-first=J. C. |translator-last=Rolfe |publisher=Harvard University Press |series=Loeb Classical Library |accessdate=2011-04-11 |df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Reputation==
[[File:Nummus of Constantius II (YORYM 2014 395 59) obverse.jpg|thumb|left|A ''[[nummus]]'' of Constantius II]]
Constantius II is a particularly difficult figure to judge properly due to the hostility of most sources toward him. A. H. M. Jones writes that Constantius &quot;appears in the pages of [[Ammianus Marcellinus|Ammianus]] as a conscientious emperor but a vain and stupid man, an easy prey to flatterers. He was timid and suspicious, and interested persons could easily play on his fears for their own advantage.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Jones, A. H. M., ''Later Roman Empire'', p. 116.&lt;/ref&gt; However, Kent and M. and A. Hirmer suggest that Constantius &quot;has suffered at the hands of unsympathetic authors, ecclesiastical and civil alike. To orthodox churchmen he was a bigoted supporter of the Arian heresy, to [[Julian (emperor)|Julian the Apostate]] and the many who have subsequently taken his part he was a murderer, a tyrant and inept as a ruler&quot;. They go on to add, &quot;Most contemporaries seem in fact to have held him in high esteem, and he certainly inspired loyalty in a way his brother could not&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Kent, J.P.C., Hirmer, M. &amp; Hirmer, A. ''Roman Coins'' (1978), p. 54&lt;/ref&gt;

==Ancestry==
{{Ahnentafel
|align=center|collapsed=no
|title=Ancestors of Constantius II
|boxstyle_1=background-color: #fcc;
|boxstyle_2=background-color: #fb9;
|boxstyle_3=background-color: #ffc;
|boxstyle_4=background-color: #bfc;
|boxstyle_5=background-color: #9fe;
|1= 1.'''Constantius II'''
|2= 2. [[Constantine the Great|Constantine I]]
|3= 3. [[Fausta]]
|4= 4. [[Constantius Chlorus]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Odahl|first1=Charles M.|title=Constantine and the Christian empire|date=2001|publisher=Routledge|location=London|isbn=978-0-415-17485-5|pages=40–41|url=https://books.google.com/?id=770uCgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA40&amp;dq=constantine+illyrian#v=onepage&amp;q=constantine%20illyrian&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|5= 5. [[Helena of Constantinople|Helena]]&lt;ref&gt;Drijvers, J.W. ''Helena Augusta: The Mother of Constantine the Great and the Legend of Her finding the True Cross'' (Leiden, 1991) 9, 15–17.&lt;/ref&gt;
|6= 6. [[Maximian]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Barnes&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Barnes |first=Timothy D. |title=The New Empire of Diocletian and Constantine |location=Cambridge, MA |publisher=Harvard University Press |year=1982 |isbn=0-7837-2221-4 |page=34}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|7= 7. [[Eutropia]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Barnes&quot;/&gt;
|8= 8. Eutropius&lt;ref&gt;''[[Historia Augusta]]'', ''Life of Claudius'' [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Historia_Augusta/Claudius*.html#13 13]&lt;/ref&gt;
|9= 9. Claudia (?)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Southern |first=Pat |title=The Roman Empire from Severus to Constantine |publisher=Routledge |year=2001 |page=172}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==See also==
{{portal|Byzantine Empire}}
*[[Persian wars of Constantius II]]
*[[Flavia (gens)]]
*[[Itineraries of the Roman emperors, 337–361]]
*[[List of Byzantine emperors]]

==References==

===Ancient sources===
{{refbegin|2}}
*Ammianus Marcellinus. ''Res Gestae''.
**Yonge, Charles Duke, trans. ''Roman History''. London: Bohn, 1862. Online at [http://www.tertullian.org/fathers/ammianus_00_eintro.htm Tertullian]. Accessed 15 August 2009.
**Rolfe, J.C., trans. ''History''. 3 vols. Loeb ed. London: Heinemann, 1939–52. Online at [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Ammian/home.html LacusCurtius]. Accessed 15 August 2009.
**Hamilton, Walter, trans. ''The Later Roman Empire (A.D. 354–378)''. Harmondsworth: Penguin, 1986. [Abridged edition]
*Athanasius of Alexandria.
**''Festal Index''.
:**Atkinson, M., and Archibald Robertson, trans. ''Festal Letters''. From ''Nicene and Post-Nicene Fathers'', Second Series, Vol. 4. Edited by Philip Schaff and Henry Wace. Buffalo, NY: Christian Literature Publishing Co., 1892. Revised and edited for New Advent by Kevin Knight. Online at [http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/npnf204.xxv.iii.iii.html Christian Classics Ethereal Library]. Accessed 15 August 2009.
**''Epistula encyclica'' (''Encyclical letter''). Summer 339.
:**Atkinson, M., and Archibald Robertson, trans. ''Encyclical letter''. From ''Nicene and Post-Nicene Fathers'', Second Series, Vol. 4. Edited by Philip Schaff and Henry Wace. Buffalo, NY: Christian Literature Publishing Co., 1892. Revised and edited for New Advent by Kevin Knight. Online at [http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/2807.htm New Advent] and [http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/npnf204.xii.ii.i.html Christian Classics Ethereal Library]. Accessed 15 August 2009.
**''Apologia Contra Arianos'' (''Defense against the Arians''). 349.
:**Atkinson, M., and Archibald Robertson, trans. ''Apologia Contra Arianos''. From ''Nicene and Post-Nicene Fathers'', Second Series, Vol. 4. Edited by Philip Schaff and Henry Wace. Buffalo, NY: Christian Literature Publishing Co., 1892. Revised and edited for New Advent by Kevin Knight. Online at [http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/2808.htm New Advent]. Accessed 14 August 2009.
**''Apologia ad Constantium'' (''Defense before Constantius''). 353.
:**Atkinson, M., and Archibald Robertson, trans. ''Apologia ad Constantium''. From ''Nicene and Post-Nicene Fathers'', Second Series, Vol. 4. Edited by Philip Schaff and Henry Wace. Buffalo, NY: Christian Literature Publishing Co., 1892. Revised and edited for New Advent by Kevin Knight. Online at [http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/2813.htm New Advent]. Accessed 14 August 2009.
**''Historia Arianorum'' (''History of the Arians''). 357.
:**Atkinson, M., and Archibald Robertson, trans. ''Historia Arianorum''. From ''Nicene and Post-Nicene Fathers'', Second Series, Vol. 4. Edited by Philip Schaff and Henry Wace. Buffalo, NY: Christian Literature Publishing Co., 1892. Revised and edited for New Advent by Kevin Knight. Online at [http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/2815.htm New Advent]. Accessed 14 August 2009.
**''De Synodis'' (''On the Councils of Arminium and Seleucia''). Autumn 359.
:**Newman, John Henry and Archibald Robertson, trans. ''De Synodis''. From ''Nicene and Post-Nicene Fathers'', Second Series, Vol. 4. Edited by Philip Schaff and Henry Wace. Buffalo, NY: Christian Literature Publishing Co., 1892. Revised and edited for New Advent by Kevin Knight. Online at [http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/2817.htm New Advent]. Accessed 15 August 2009.
**''Historia acephala''. 368&amp;nbsp;–&amp;nbsp;c. 420.
:**Robertson, Archibald, trans. ''Historia Acephala''. From ''Nicene and Post-Nicene Fathers'', Second Series, Vol. 4. Edited by Philip Schaff and Henry Wace. Buffalo, NY: Christian Literature Publishing Co., 1892. Revised and edited for New Advent by Kevin Knight. Online at [http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/2820.htm New Advent] and [http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/npnf204.xxv.ii.ii.html Christian Classics Ethereal Library]. Accessed 15 August 2009.
*''Chronica minora'' 1, 2.
**Mommsen, T., ed. ''Chronica Minora saec. IV, V, VI, VII'' 1, 2 (in Latin). ''Monumenta Germaniae Historia'', Auctores Antiquissimi 9, 11. Berlin, 1892, 1894. Online at {{cite web|url=http://bsbdmgh.bsb.lrz-muenchen.de/dmgh_new/ |title=Bayerische StaatsBibliothek |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://archive.is/20120708060352/http%3A%2F%2Fbsbdmgh.bsb.lrz-muenchen.de%2Fdmgh_new%2F |archivedate=2012-07-08 }}. Accessed 25 August 2009.
*''Codex Theodosianus''.
**Mommsen, T. and Paul M. Meyer, eds. ''Theodosiani libri XVI cum Constitutionibus Sirmondianis et Leges novellae ad Theodosianum pertinentes''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; (in Latin). Berlin: Weidmann, [1905] 1954. Complied by Nicholas Palmer, revised by [[Tony Honoré]] for Oxford Text Archive, 1984. Prepared for online use by R.W.B. Salway, 1999. Preface, books 1–8. Online at [https://web.archive.org/web/20090826174516/http://www.ucl.ac.uk/history2/volterra/texts/cthinfo.htm University College London] and the [http://web.upmf-grenoble.fr/Haiti/Cours/Ak/Constitutiones/codtheod.html University of Grenoble]. Accessed 25 August 2009.
**Unknown edition (in Latin). Online at [http://ancientrome.ru/ius/library/codex/theod/ AncientRome.ru]. Accessed 15 August 2009.
*''Codex Justinianus''.
**Scott, Samuel P., trans. ''The Code of Justinian'', in ''The Civil Law''. 17 vols. 1932. Online at the [http://www.constitution.org/sps/sps.htm Constitution Society]. Accessed 14 August 2009.
*Ephraem the Syrian. ''Carmina Nisibena'' (''Songs of Nisibis'').
**Stopford, J.T. Sarsfield, trans. ''The Nisibene Hymns''. From ''Nicene and Post-Nicene Fathers'', Second Series, Vol. 13. Edited by Philip Schaff and Henry Wace. Buffalo, NY: Christian Literature Publishing Co., 1890. Revised and edited for New Advent by Kevin Knight. Online at [http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/3702.htm New Advent]. Accessed 16 August 2009.
**Bickell, Gustav, trans. ''S. Ephraemi Syri Carmina Nisibena: additis prolegomenis et supplemento lexicorum Syriacorum'' (in Latin). Lipetsk: Brockhaus, 1866. Online at [https://books.google.com/books†id=FNECZJZEUVUC Google Books]. Accessed 15 August 2009.
*''Epitome de Caesaribus''.
**Banchich, Thomas M., trans. ''A Booklet About the Style of Life and the Manners of the Imperatores''. ''Canisius College Translated Texts'' 1. Buffalo, NY: Canisius College, 2009. Online at [http://www.roman-emperors.org/epitome.htm De Imperatoribus Romanis]. Accessed 15 August 2009.
*Eunapius. ''Lives of the Sophists''.
*Eusebius of Caesarea.
**''Oratio de Laudibus Constantini'' (''Oration in Praise of Constantine'', sometimes the ''Tricennial Oration'').
:**Richardson, Ernest Cushing, trans. ''Oration in Praise of Constantine''. From ''Nicene and Post-Nicene Fathers'', Second Series, Vol. 1. Edited by Philip Schaff and Henry Wace. Buffalo, NY: Christian Literature Publishing Co., 1890. Revised and edited for New Advent by Kevin Knight. Online at [http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/2504.htm New Advent]. Accessed 16 August 2009.
**''Vita Constantini'' (''Life of Constantine'').
:**Richardson, Ernest Cushing, trans. ''Life of Constantine''. From ''Nicene and Post-Nicene Fathers'', Second Series, Vol. 1. Edited by Philip Schaff and Henry Wace. Buffalo, NY: Christian Literature Publishing Co., 1890. Revised and edited for New Advent by Kevin Knight. Online at [http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/2502.htm New Advent]. Accessed 25 August 2009.
*[[Eutropius (historian)|Eutropius]]. ''Historiae Romanae Breviarium''.
**Watson, John Selby, trans. ''Abridgment of Roman History''. London: George Bell &amp; Sons, 1886. Revised and edited for Tertullian by Roger Pearse, 2003. Online at [http://www.tertullian.org/fathers/eutropius_breviarium_2_text.htm Tertullian]. Accessed 11 June 2010.
*Festus. ''Breviarium''.
**Banchich, Thomas M., and Jennifer A. Meka, trans. ''Breviarium of the Accomplishments of the Roman People''. ''Canisius College Translated Texts'' 2. Buffalo, NY: Canisius College, 2001. Online at [http://www.roman-emperors.org/festus.htm De Imperatoribus Romanis]. Accessed 15 August 2009.
*Firmicus Maternus. ''De errore profanarum religionum'' (''On the error of profane religions'').
**Baluzii and Rigaltii, eds. ''Divi Cæcilii Cypriani, Carthaginensis Episcopi, Opera Omnia; accessit J. Firmici Materni, Viri Clarissimi, De Errore Profanarum Religionum'' (in Latin). Paris: Gauthier Brothers and the Society of Booksellers, 1836. Online at [https://books.google.com/books†id=Zow7AAAAcAAJ Google Books]. Accessed 15 August 2009.
*Hilary of Poitiers. ''Ad Constantium'' (''To Constantius'').
**Feder, Alfred Leonhard, ed. ''S. Hilarii episcopi Pictaviensis Tractatus mysteriorum. Collectanea Antiariana Parisina (fragmenta historica) cum appendice (liber I Ad Constantium). Liber ad Constantium imperatorem (Liber II ad Constantium). Hymni. Fragmenta minora. Spuria'' (in Latin). In the ''Corpus Scriptorum Ecclesiasticorum Latinorum'', Vol. 65. Vienna: Tempsky, 1916.
*''Itinerarium Alexandri'' (''Itinerary of Alexander'').
**Mai, Angelo, ed. ''Itinerarium Alexandri ad Constantium Augustum, Constantini M. Filium'' (in Latin). Regiis Typis, 1818. Online at [https://books.google.com/books†id=LaB9JC1Fm6kC Google Books]. Accessed 15 August 2009.
**Davies, Iolo, trans. ''Itinerary of Alexander''. 2009. Online at [http://papyri.info/idp_static/current/ddb-citations-p+abinn.html DocStoc]{{dead link|date=March 2015}}. Accessed 15 August 2009.
*Jerome.
**''Chronicon'' (''Chronicle'').
:**Pearse, Roger, ''et al.'', trans. ''The Chronicle of St. Jerome'', in ''Early Church Fathers: Additional Texts''. Tertullian, 2005. Online at [http://www.tertullian.org/fathers/jerome_chronicle_00_eintro.htm Tertullian]. Accessed 14 August 2009.
**''de Viris Illustribus'' (''On Illustrious Men'').
:**Richardson, Ernest Cushing, trans. ''De Viris Illustribus (On Illustrious Men)''. From ''Nicene and Post-Nicene Fathers'', Second Series, Vol. 3. Edited by Philip Schaff and Henry Wace. Buffalo, NY: Christian Literature Publishing Co., 1892. Revised and edited for New Advent by Kevin Knight. Online at [http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/2708.htm New Advent]. Accessed 15 August 2009.
*Julian.
**[[Wilmer Cave Wright|Wright, Wilmer Cave]], trans. ''Works of the Emperor Julian''. 3 vols. Loeb ed. London: Heinemann, 1913. Online at the Internet Archive: [https://archive.org/details/workswithenglish01juliuoft Vol. 1], [https://archive.org/details/workswithenglish02juliuoft 2], [https://archive.org/details/workswithenglish03juliuoft 3].
*Libanius. ''Oratio'' 59 (''Oration'' 59).
**M.H. Dodgeon, trans. ''The Sons of Constantine: Libanius Or. LIX''. In ''From Constantine to Julian: Pagan and Byzantine Views, A Source History'', edited by S.N.C. Lieu and [[Dominic Montserrat]], 164–205. London: Routledge, 1996. {{ISBN|0-415-09336-8}}
*''Origo Constantini Imperatoris''.
**Rolfe, J.C., trans. ''Excerpta Valesiana'', in vol. 3 of Rolfe's translation of Ammianus Marcellinus' ''History''. Loeb ed. London: Heinemann, 1952. Online at [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Excerpta_Valesiana/1*.html LacusCurtius]. Accessed 16 August 2009.
*''Papyri Abinnaeus''.
**''The Abinnaeus Archive: Papers of a Roman Officer in the Reign of Constantius II'' (in Greek). Duke Data Bank of Documentary Papyri. Online at [http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/ptext?doc=Perseus:text:1999.05.0052&amp;query=document%3D%231 Perseus] and the [http://papyri.info/idp_static/current/ddb-citations-p+abinn.html Duke Data Bank]{{dead link|date=March 2015}}. Accessed 15 August 2009.
*''Papyri Laurentius''.
**''Dai Papiri della Biblioteca Medicea Laurenziana'' (in Greek). Duke Data Bank of Documentary Papyri. Online at [http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text;jsessionid=AC847D304432C05A3A6019E311003F54?doc=Perseus:text:1999.05.0147 Perseus] and the [http://papyri.info/idp_static/current/ddb-citations-p+laur.html Duke Data Bank]{{dead link|date=April 2017|bot=medic}}{{cbignore|bot=medic}}. Accessed 15 August 2009.
*Philostorgius. ''Historia Ecclesiastica''.
**Walford, Edward, trans. ''Epitome of the Ecclesiastical History of Philostorgius, Compiled by Photius, Patriarch of Constantinople''. London: Henry G. Bohn, 1855. Online at [http://www.tertullian.org/fathers/philostorgius.htm Tertullian]. Accessed 15 August 2009.
*Socrates. ''Historia Ecclesiastica'' (''History of the Church'').
**Zenos, A.C., trans. ''Ecclesiastical History''. From ''Nicene and Post-Nicene Fathers'', Second Series, Vol. 2. Edited by Philip Schaff and Henry Wace. Buffalo, NY: Christian Literature Publishing Co., 1890. Revised and edited for New Advent by Kevin Knight. Online at [http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/2601.htm New Advent]. Accessed 14 August 2009.
*Sozomen. ''Historia Ecclesiastica'' (''History of the Church'').
**Hartranft, Chester D. ''Ecclesiastical History''. From ''Nicene and Post-Nicene Fathers'', Second Series, Vol. 2. Edited by Philip Schaff and Henry Wace. Buffalo, NY: Christian Literature Publishing Co., 1890. Revised and edited for New Advent by Kevin Knight. Online at [http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/2602.htm New Advent]. Accessed 15 August 2009.
*Sulpicius Severus. ''Sacred History''.
**Roberts, Alexander, trans. ''Sacred History''. From ''Nicene and Post-Nicene Fathers'', Second Series, Vol. 11. Edited by Philip Schaff and Henry Wace. Buffalo, NY: Christian Literature Publishing Co., 1894. Revised and edited for New Advent by Kevin Knight. Online at [http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/3505.htm New Advent]. Accessed 14 August 2009.
*Theodoret. ''Historia Ecclesiastica'' (''History of the Church'').
**Jackson, Blomfield, trans. ''Ecclesiastical History''. From ''Nicene and Post-Nicene Fathers'', Second Series, Vol. 3. Edited by Philip Schaff and Henry Wace. Buffalo, NY: Christian Literature Publishing Co., 1892. Revised and edited for New Advent by Kevin Knight. Online at [http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/2702.htm New Advent]. Accessed 15 August 2009.
*Themistius. ''Orationes'' (''Orations'').
*[[Theophanes the Confessor|Theophanes]]. ''Chronicle''.
*[[Joannes Zonaras|Zonaras]]. ''Extracts of History''.
*Zosimus. ''Historia Nova'' (''New History'').
**Unknown trans. ''The History of Count Zosimus''. London: Green and Champlin, 1814. Online at [http://www.tertullian.org/fathers/zosimus00_intro.htm Tertullian]. Accessed 15 August 2009. [An unsatisfactory edition.]
**Unknown trans. ''Histoire Nouvelle'' and ''ΖΩΣΙΜΟΥ ΚΟΜΙΤΟΣ ΚΑΙ ΑΠΟΦΙΣΚΟΣΥΝΗΓΟΡΟΥ'' (in French and Greek). Online at the [http://pot-pourri.fltr.ucl.ac.be/files/aclassftp/TEXTES/Zosimus/ Catholic University of Louvain]. Accessed 16 November 2009.
{{refend}}

===Modern sources===
{{refbegin|2}}
* Banchich, T.M., 'DIR-Gallus' from ''De Imperatoribus Romanis'' [http://www.roman-emperors.org/gallus.htm]
* Dignas, B. &amp; Winter, E., ''Rome and Persia in Late Antiquity'' (Cambridge University Press, 2007)
* DiMaio, M., and Frakes, R., 'DIR-Constantius II' from ''De Imperatoribus Romanis'' [http://www.roman-emperors.org/constaii.htm &quot;Constantius II,&quot;].
* Gaddis, M., ''There is No Crime for Those who Have Christ'' (University of California Press, 2005).„
* Hunt, ''Constantius II in the Ecclesiastical Historians''orians, Ph.D. diss. (Fordham University, 2010), AAT 3431914.
* Jones, A.H.M, ''The Later Roman Empire, 284–602: a Social, Economic and Administrative Survey'' (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University, 1986)
* Kent, J.P.C., Hirmer, M. &amp; Hirmer, A. ''Roman Coins'' (Thames and Hudson, 1978)
* Moser, Muriel. 2018. Emperor and Senators in the Reign of Constantius II. Cambridge University Press.
* Odahl, C.M., ''Constantine and the Christian Empire'' (Routledge, 2004)
* Pelikan, J.J., ''The Christian Tradition'' (University of Chicago, 1989)
* Potter, D.S., ''The Roman Empire at Bay: AD 180–395'' (Routledge, 2004)
* Salzman, M.R., ''The Making of a Christian Aristocracy: Social and Religious Change in the Western Roman Empire'' (Harvard University Press, 2002)
* Schäfer, P., ''The History of the Jews in the Greco-Roman World'' (Routledge, 2003)
* Vagi, D.L. &amp; Coquand, T., ''Coinage and History of the Roman Empire'' (Taylor &amp; Francis, 2001)
* Vasiliev, A.A., ''History of the Byzantine Empire 324–1453'' (University of Wisconsin Press, 1958)
{{refend}}

==External links==
* This [https://web.archive.org/web/20081025063840/http://www.fourthcentury.com/index.php/imperial-laws-chart-364 list of Roman laws of the fourth century] shows laws passed by Constantius II relating to Christianity.

{{Commons|Constantius II}}
{{Wikiquote}}

{{s-start}}
{{s-hou|[[Constantinian dynasty]]|7 August|317|3 November|361}}
{{s-reg}}
{{s-bef| before=[[Constantine I]]}}
{{s-ttl| title=[[List of Roman Emperors|Roman Emperor]]
       | years=337–361
       | alongside=[[Constans]] and [[Constantine II (emperor)|Constantine II]]}}
{{s-aft| after=[[Julian the Apostate|Julian]]}}
{{s-off}}
{{s-bef | before= [[Sextus Anicius Faustus Paulinus (consul 325)|Sextus Anicius Faustus Paulinus]],&lt;br /&gt; [[Julius Julianus]]}}
{{s-ttl | title=[[List of Roman Consuls|Consul]] of the [[Roman Empire]] | years=326 |regent1= [[Constantine I]]}}
{{s-aft | after= [[Lucius Valerius Maximus Basilius (consul)|Lucius Valerius Maximus Basilius]],&lt;br /&gt; Flavius Constantius}}
{{s-bef | before= Ursus,&lt;br /&gt; Polemius}}
{{s-ttl | title=[[List of Roman Consuls|Consul]] of the [[Roman Empire]] | years=339 |regent1= [[Constans]]}}
{{s-aft | after= [[Septimius Acindynus]],&lt;br /&gt; [[Lucius Aradius Valerius Proculus]]}}
{{s-bef | before= [[Petronius Probinus (consul 341)|Petronius Probinus]],&lt;br /&gt; [[Antonius Marcellinus]]}}
{{s-ttl | title=[[List of Roman Consuls|Consul]] of the [[Roman Empire]] | years=342 |regent1= [[Constans]]}}
{{s-aft | after= [[Marcus Maecius Memmius Furius Baburius Caecilianus Placidus]],&lt;br /&gt; Flavius Romulus}}
{{s-bef | before= Amantius,&lt;br /&gt;[[Marcus Nummius Albinus]]}}
{{s-ttl | title=[[List of Roman Consuls|Consul]] of the [[Roman Empire]] | years=346 |regent1= [[Constans]]}}
{{s-aft | after= [[Vulcacius Rufinus]],&lt;br /&gt; [[Eusebius (consul 347)|Flavius Eusebius]]}}
{{s-bef | before= [[Magnentius]],&lt;br /&gt; [[Gaiso]]}}
{{s-ttl | title=[[List of Roman Consuls|Consul]] of the [[Roman Empire]] | years=352–354 |regent1= [[Constantius Gallus]],&lt;br /&gt;[[Decentius]],&lt;br /&gt;Paulus,&lt;br /&gt;[[Magnentius]]}}
{{s-aft | after= [[Arbitio]],&lt;br /&gt; [[Lollianus Mavortius]]}}
{{s-bef | before= [[Arbitio]],&lt;br /&gt; [[Lollianus Mavortius]]}}
{{s-ttl | title=[[List of Roman Consuls|Consul]] of the [[Roman Empire]] | years=356–357 |regent1= [[Julian (emperor)|Julian]]}}
{{s-aft | after= [[Neratius Cerealis]],&lt;br /&gt; [[Censorius Datianus]]}}
{{s-bef | before= [[Eusebius (consul 359)|Flavius Eusebius]],&lt;br /&gt; [[Hypatius (consul 359)|Flavius Hypatius]]}}
{{s-ttl | title=[[List of Roman Consuls|Consul]] of the [[Roman Empire]] | years=360 |regent1= [[Julian (emperor)|Julian]]}}
{{s-aft | after= [[Taurus (consul 361)|Taurus]],&lt;br /&gt; [[Florentius (consul 361)|Florentius]]}}
{{s-end}}

{{Roman Emperors}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Constantius 2}}
[[Category:317 births]]
[[Category:361 deaths]]
[[Category:Constantinian dynasty]]
[[Category:Flavii]]
[[Category:Julii|Constantius, Flavius]]
[[Category:4th-century Christians]]
[[Category:4th-century Roman emperors]]
[[Category:Imperial Roman consuls]]
[[Category:People from Sremska Mitrovica]]
[[Category:Deaths from infectious disease]]
[[Category:4th-century Byzantine emperors]]
[[Category:People of the Roman–Sasanian Wars]]
[[Category:Arian Christians]]
[[Category:Illyrian people]]</text>
      <sha1>ju6ziagwy4m2963yl69v4l0ivs569s3</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
