  <page>
    <title>Capybara</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6776</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943380921</id>
      <parentid>943139305</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-03-01T15:53:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Tastybaldeagle</username>
        <id>34698121</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Added information</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Species of giant rodent in the cavy family}}
{{About|the animal|the video game developer|Capybara Games|test automation software|Capybara (software)}}
{{Good article}}
{{speciesbox
| name = Capybara
| status = LC
| status_system = IUCN3.1
| status_ref = &lt;ref name=iucn/&gt;
| image = Capybara (Hydrochoerus hydrochaeris).JPG
| image_caption =
| genus = Hydrochoerus
| species = hydrochaeris
| authority = ([[Carl Linnaeus|Linnaeus]], 1766)
| range_map = Hydrochoerus hydrochaeris range.png
| range_map_caption = Native range
| synonyms = ''Sus hydrochaeris'' {{small|Linnaeus,&amp;nbsp;1766}}
}}

The '''capybara''' (''Hydrochoerus hydrochaeris'') is a mammal native to [[South America]]. It is the largest living [[rodent]] in the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | author= Basic Biology | date= 2015 | title= Rodents | url= https://basicbiology.net/animal/mammals/rodents}}&lt;/ref&gt; Also called '''Capivara''' (in Brazil), '''chigüire''', '''chigüiro''' (in Colombia and Venezuela) and '''carpincho''', it is a member of the genus ''[[Hydrochoerus]]'', of which the only other [[extant taxon|extant]] member is the [[lesser capybara]] (''Hydrochoerus isthmius'').  Its close relatives include [[guinea pig]]s and [[Rock cavy|rock cavies]], and it is more distantly related to the [[agouti]], the [[chinchilla]], and the [[coypu]]. The capybara inhabits [[savanna]]s and dense forests and lives near bodies of water. It is a highly social species and can be found in groups as large as 100 individuals, but usually lives in groups of 10–20 individuals. The capybara is not a threatened species but it is hunted for its meat and [[Hide (skin)|hide]] and also for grease from its thick fatty [[skin]], which is used in the pharmaceutical trade.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.arkive.org/capybara/hydrochoerus-hydrochaeris/ Capybara (''Hydrochoerus hydrochaeris'')] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120103075238/http://www.arkive.org/capybara/hydrochoerus-hydrochaeris/ |date=2012-01-03 }}. ARKive.org&lt;/ref&gt;

==Etymology==
Its [[common name]] is derived from [[Tupi language|Tupi]] ''{{lang|tpw|ka'apiûara}}'', a complex agglutination of ''{{lang|tpw|kaá}}'' (leaf) + ''{{lang|tpw|píi}}'' (slender) + ''{{lang|tpw|ú}}'' (eat) + ''{{lang|tpw|ara}}'' (a suffix for agent nouns), meaning &quot;one who eats slender leaves&quot;, or &quot;grass-eater&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Ferreira, A. B. H. (1986) ''[[Novo Dicionário da Língua Portuguesa]]'', 2nd ed., Rio de Janeiro: Nova Fronteira, p.344&lt;/ref&gt; Capybaras were called several times &quot;Cuartins&quot; in Colombia in 2018: in Eje Cafetero (Alcalà) and near Barranquilla where the meat was offered as &quot;Cuartin Asado&quot;.

The [[scientific name]], both ''hydrochoerus'' and ''hydrochaeris'', comes from [[Ancient Greek|Greek]] {{lang|grc|ὕδωρ}} (''{{lang|grc-Latn|hydor}}'' &quot;water&quot;) and {{lang|grc|χοῖρος}} (''{{lang|grc-Latn|choiros}}'' &quot;pig, hog&quot;).&lt;ref name=msw3&gt;{{MSW3 Woods|id=13400218|page=1556}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;inDarwin&quot;&gt;{{Cite book | last=Darwin | first=Charles R. | authorlink =Charles Darwin| year=1839 | title=Narrative of the surveying voyages of His Majesty's Ships Adventure and Beagle between the years 1826 and 1836, describing their examination of the southern shores of South America, and the Beagle's circumnavigation of the globe. Journal and remarks. 1832–1836. | titlelink =The Voyage of the Beagle| place =London | publisher =[[Henry Colburn]] | page=619}}
* In page 57, Darwin says &quot;The largest gnawing animal in the world, the ''Hydrochærus Capybara'' (the water-hog), is here also common.&quot;
* See it also in [http://darwin-online.org.uk/content/frameset?itemID=F10.3&amp;viewtype=side&amp;pageseq=1 The Complete Work of Charles Darwin Online]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Classification and phylogeny==
The capybara and the [[lesser capybara]] belong to the subfamily [[Hydrochoerinae]] along with the [[Kerodon|rock cavies]]. The living capybaras and their [[extinct]] relatives were previously classified in their own family Hydrochoeridae.&lt;ref name=r4/&gt; Since 2002, molecular phylogenetic studies have recognized a close relationship between ''Hydrochoerus'' and ''[[Kerodon]]'', the rock cavies,&lt;ref name=&quot;Rowe 2002&quot;/&gt; supporting placement of both genera in a subfamily of [[Caviidae]].&lt;ref name=msw3/&gt;

Paleontological classifications previously used Hydrochoeridae for all capybaras, while using Hydrochoerinae for the living genus and its closest fossil relatives, such as ''[[Neochoerus]]''&lt;ref name=&quot;Vucetich 2005&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Deschamp 2007&quot;/&gt;, but more recently have adopted the classification of Hydrochoerinae within Caviidae.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cerdeño 2019&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Cerdeño |first1=E. |last2=Pérez |first2=M.E. |last3=Deschamps |first3=C.M. |last4=Contreras |first4=V.H. |year=2019 |title=A new capybara from the late Miocene of San Juan Province, Argentina, and its phylogenetic implications |journal=Acta Palaeontologica Polonica |volume=64 |issue=1 |pages=199–212 |doi=10.4202/app.00544.2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The taxonomy of fossil hydrochoerines is also in a state of flux. In recent years, the diversity of fossil hydrochoerines has been substantially reduced.&lt;ref name=&quot;Vucetich 2005&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Deschamp 2007&quot;/&gt; This is largely due to the recognition that capybara [[Molar (tooth)|molar]] teeth show strong variation in shape over the life of an individual.&lt;ref name=&quot;Vucetich 2005&quot;/&gt; In one instance, material once referred to four genera and seven species on the basis of differences in molar shape is now thought to represent differently aged individuals of a single species, ''Cardiatherium paranense''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Vucetich 2005&quot;/&gt;
Among fossil species, the name &quot;capybara&quot; can refer to the many species of Hydrochoerinae that are more closely related to the modern ''Hydrochoerus'' than to the &quot;cardiomyine&quot; rodents like ''Cardiomys''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cerdeño 2019&quot;/&gt;  The fossil genera ''Cardiatherium'', ''Phugatherium'', ''Hydrochoeropsis'', and ''Neochoerus'' are all capybaras under that concept.

==Description==
[[file:Taxidermy specimen of Capybara (Hydrochoerus hydrochaeris).jpg|thumb|left|Taxidermy specimen of a Capybara]]
[[File:Capybara skeleton.jpg|thumb|Capybara skeleton]]
The capybara has a heavy, [[barrel]]-shaped body and short head, with reddish-brown fur on the upper part of its body that turns yellowish-brown underneath. Its sweat glands can be found in the surface of the hairy portions of its skin, an unusual trait among rodents.&lt;ref name=r4/&gt; The animal lacks [[Fur#DownHair|down hair]], and its [[Fur#GuardHair|guard hair]] differs little from over hair.{{citation needed|date= August 2017|reason = Make up of hair layers not referenced. Also, &quot;over hair&quot; is not used in the Fur article, or elsewhere. What is this?}}

Adult capybaras grow to {{convert|106|to|134|cm|ft|abbr=on}} in length, stand {{convert|50|to|62|cm|in|abbr=on}} tall at the [[withers]], and typically weigh {{convert|35|to|66|kg|lb|abbr=on}}, with an average in the Venezuelan [[Los Llanos, Venezuela|llanos]] of {{convert|48.9|kg|lb|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref name=Arkive&gt;[http://www.arkive.org/capybara/hydrochoerus-hydrochaeris/#text=Facts Capybara] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120103075238/http://www.arkive.org/capybara/hydrochoerus-hydrochaeris/#text=Facts#text=Facts |date=2012-01-03 }}, Arkive&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Smithsonian&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Palm Beach Zoo&quot;/&gt; Females are slightly heavier than males. The top recorded weights are {{convert|91|kg|lb|abbr=on}} for a wild female from Brazil and {{convert|73.5|kg|lb|abbr=on}} for a wild male from Uruguay.&lt;ref name=r4/&gt;&lt;ref name=r3/&gt; Also, an 81&amp;nbsp;kg individual was reported in São Paulo in 2001 or 2002.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.scielo.br/pdf/bn/v5n1/v5n1a19.pdf|title=Relationship Between Body Mass and Body Length in Capybaras (Hydrochoerus Hydrochaeris)|accessdate = June 29, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[dental formula]] is {{DentalFormula|upper=1.0.1.3|lower=1.0.1.3}}.&lt;ref name=r4/&gt; Capybaras have slightly [[Interdigital webbing|webbed]] feet and  [[Vestigiality|vestigial]] tails.&lt;ref name=r4/&gt; Their hind legs are slightly longer than their forelegs; they have three toes on their rear feet and four toes on their front feet.&lt;ref name=&quot;enchantedlearning.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.enchantedlearning.com/subjects/mammals/rodent/Capybaraprintout.shtml |title=Capybara Printout |publisher=Enchantedlearning.com |accessdate=2013-05-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; Their muzzles are blunt, with nostrils, and the eyes and ears are near the top of their heads.

Its [[karyotype]] has [[Diploid|2n]] = 66 and [[Fundamental number|FN]] = 102.&lt;ref name=msw3/&gt;&lt;ref name=r4/&gt;

==Ecology==
[[File:Yellow-headed caracara (Milvago chimachima) on capybara (Hydrochoeris hydrochaeris).JPG|thumb|[[Yellow-headed caracara]] on a capybara]]
[[File:Capybara swimming.jpg|thumb|A family of Capybara swimming]]
Capybaras are [[List of semiaquatic tetrapods|semiaquatic]] mammals&lt;ref name=&quot;Palm Beach Zoo&quot;/&gt; found throughout almost all countries of South America except [[Chile]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Bristol&quot;/&gt; They live in densely [[forest]]ed areas near bodies of water, such as lakes, rivers, [[swamp]]s, ponds, and [[marsh]]es,&lt;ref name=&quot;Smithsonian&quot;/&gt; as well as flooded [[savannah]] and along rivers in the [[tropical rainforest]]. They are superb swimmers and can hold their breath underwater for up to five minutes at a time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://animals.net/capybara/ |title=Capybara – Description, Habitat, Image, Diet, and Interesting Facts |publisher=Animals Network |accessdate=2019-01-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; Capybara have flourished in cattle ranches.&lt;ref name=r4/&gt; They roam in home [[range (biology)|range]]s averaging 10 hectares (25 acres) in high-density populations.&lt;ref name=r4/&gt;

Many escapees from captivity can also be found in similar watery habitats around the world. Sightings are fairly common in [[Florida]], although a breeding population has not yet been confirmed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://myfwc.com/wildlifehabitats/nonnatives/mammals/capybara/|title=Nonnatives – Capybara|website=myfwc.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2011, one specimen was spotted on the [[Central Coast (California)|Central Coast of California]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.latimes.com/news/local/la-me-0818-capybara-20110818,0,104462.story|title=A gnawing question answered: It's a capybara roaming Paso Robles|last=Mather|first=Kate|date=18 August 2011|work=[[Los Angeles Times]]|accessdate=10 January 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Diet and predation===
[[File:Cattle tyrant (Machetornis rixosa) on Capybara.jpg|thumb|left|[[Cattle tyrant]] on a capybara]]
Capybaras are [[herbivore]]s, grazing mainly on grasses and [[aquatic plants]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Smithsonian&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;RevBiolTrop&quot;/&gt; as well as [[fruit]] and tree bark.&lt;ref name=&quot;Palm Beach Zoo&quot;/&gt; They are very selective feeders&lt;ref name=&quot;Quintana 1998&quot;/&gt; and feed on the leaves of one species and disregard other species surrounding it. They eat a greater variety of plants during the dry season, as fewer plants are available. While they eat grass during the wet season, they have to switch to more abundant reeds during the dry season.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barreto 1998&quot;/&gt; Plants that capybaras eat during the summer lose their nutritional value in the winter, so are not consumed at that time.&lt;ref name=&quot;Quintana 1998&quot;/&gt; The capybara's jaw hinge is not perpendicular, so they chew food by grinding back-and-forth rather than side-to-side.&lt;ref name=&quot;SFZoo&quot;/&gt; Capybaras are auto[[coprophagous]], meaning they eat their own [[feces]] as a source of bacterial [[gut flora]], to help [[digestion|digest]] the [[cellulose]] in the grass that forms their normal diet, and to extract the maximum protein and vitamins from their food. They may also regurgitate food to masticate again, similar to cud-chewing by [[cattle]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Lord-Rexford 1994&quot;/&gt; As is the case with other rodents, the front teeth of capybaras grow continually to compensate for the constant wear from eating grasses;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bristol&quot;/&gt; their cheek teeth also grow continuously.&lt;ref name=&quot;SFZoo&quot;/&gt;

Like its relative the guinea pig, the capybara does not have the capacity to synthesize [[vitamin C]], and capybaras not supplemented with vitamin C in captivity have been reported to develop gum disease as a sign of [[scurvy]].&lt;ref name=r2/&gt;

They can have a [[life expectancy|lifespan]] of 8–10 years,&lt;ref name=r6/&gt; but live less than four years in the wild, because they are &quot;a favourite food of [[South American jaguar|jaguar]], [[South American cougar|puma]], [[ocelot]], [[eagle]], and [[caiman]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bristol&quot;/&gt; The capybara is also the preferred [[prey]] of the [[Eunectes murinus|anaconda]].&lt;ref name=&quot;SoundsandColours&quot;/&gt;

==Social organization==
[[File:Capybara (Hydrochoerus hydrochaeris) alpha male.JPG|thumb|right|Capybaras have a scent gland on their noses, called a morrillo]]

Capybaras are known to be [[gregarious]]. While they sometimes live solitarily, they are more commonly found in groups of around 10–20 individuals, with two to four adult males, four to seven adult females, and the remainder juveniles.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alho 1987&quot;/&gt; Capybara groups can consist of as many as 50 or 100 individuals during the dry season&lt;ref name=&quot;Lord-Rexford 1994&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Macdonald 1981&quot;/&gt; when the animals gather around available water sources. Males establish social bonds, dominance, or general group consensus.{{clarify|reason=This is a non-standard use of the word 'census', which means 'official periodic count of a population'; perhaps 'consensus', meaning 'general agreement of a group', is what is meant here.|date=January 2017}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Macdonald 1981&quot;/&gt; They can make dog-like barks&lt;ref name=&quot;Lord-Rexford 1994&quot;/&gt; when threatened or when females are herding young.&lt;ref name=&quot;Murphey 1985&quot;/&gt;

Capybaras have two types of scent glands; a morrillo, located on the snout, and anal glands.&lt;ref name=&quot;Macdonald 1984&quot;/&gt; Both sexes have these glands, but males have much larger morrillos and use their anal glands more frequently. The anal glands of males are also lined with detachable hairs. A crystalline form of scent secretion is coated on these hairs and is released when in contact with objects such as plants. These hairs have a longer-lasting scent mark and are tasted by other capybaras. Capybaras scent-mark by rubbing their morrillos on objects, or by walking over scrub and marking it with their anal glands. Capybaras can spread their scent further by urinating; however, females usually mark without urinating and scent-mark less frequently than males overall. Females mark more often during the wet season when they are in [[estrus]]. In addition to objects, males also scent-mark females.&lt;ref name=&quot;Macdonald 1984&quot;/&gt;

===Reproduction===
[[File:Young capybaras.jpg|thumb|right|Mother with typical litter of about four pups.]]

When in [[estrus]], the female's scent changes subtly and nearby males begin pursuit.&lt;ref name=&quot;Herrera 1993&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.1093/beheco/4.2.114|title= Aggression, dominance, and mating success among capybara males (''Hydrochaeris hypdrochaeris'')|year=1993|last1=Herrera|first1=Emilio A.|last2=MacDonald|first2=David W.|journal=[[Behavioral Ecology (journal)|Behavioral Ecology]]|volume=4|issue=2|page=114}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, a female alerts males she is in estrus by whistling through her nose.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lord-Rexford 1994&quot;/&gt; During mating, the female has the advantage and mating choice. Capybaras mate only in water, and if a female does not want to mate with a certain male, she either submerges or leaves the water.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lord-Rexford 1994&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Macdonald 1981&quot;/&gt; Dominant males are highly protective of the females, but they usually cannot prevent some of the subordinates from copulating.&lt;ref name=&quot;Herrera 1993&quot;/&gt; The larger the group, the harder it is for the male to watch all the females. Dominant males secure significantly more matings than each subordinate, but subordinate males, as a class, are responsible for more matings than each dominant male.&lt;ref name=&quot;Herrera 1993&quot;/&gt; The lifespan of the capybara's sperm is longer than that of other rodents.&lt;ref name=r1/&gt;
[[File:Capivara(Hydrochoerus hydrochaeris).jpg|thumb|left|Mother and three pups]]
Capybara [[gestation]] is 130–150 days, and produces a [[litter (animal)|litter]] of four capybaras young on average, but may produce between one and eight in a single litter.&lt;ref name=r4/&gt; Birth is on land and the female rejoins the group within a few hours of delivering the newborn capybaras, which join the group as soon as they are mobile. Within a week, the young can eat grass, but continue to suckle—from any female in the group—until weaned around 16 weeks. The young form a group within the main group.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bristol&quot;/&gt; [[Alloparenting]] has been observed in this species.&lt;ref name=&quot;Macdonald 1981&quot;/&gt; Breeding peaks between April and May in Venezuela and between October and November in [[Mato Grosso]], Brazil.&lt;ref name=r4/&gt;

===Activities===
Though quite [[Agility|agile]] on land, capybaras are equally at home in the water. They are excellent swimmers, and can remain completely submerged for up to five minutes,&lt;ref name=&quot;Smithsonian&quot;/&gt; an ability they use to evade [[predator]]s. Capybaras can sleep in water, keeping only their noses out of the water. As temperatures increase during the day, they [[Wallowing in animals|wallow]] in water and then graze during the late afternoon and early evening.&lt;ref name=r4/&gt; They also spend time wallowing in mud.&lt;ref name=&quot;enchantedlearning.com&quot;/&gt; They rest around [[midnight]] and then continue to graze before [[dawn]].

==Conservation and human interaction==
[[File:Capybara Ueno Zoo 2009.ogv|thumb|left|Captive capybaras resting]]
[[File:Capybara Izu Shaboten 001.jpg|thumb|right|Capybaras in a bath at Izu Shaboten Park in Japan]]

Capybaras are not considered a [[threatened species]];&lt;ref name=iucn&gt;{{cite iucn | author = Reid, F. | title = ''Hydrochoerus hydrochaeris'' | volume = 2016 | page = e.T10300A22190005 | year = 2016 | doi = 10.2305/IUCN.UK.2016-2.RLTS.T10300A22190005.en | accessdate = 1 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; their [[population]] is stable throughout most of their South American range, though in some areas hunting has reduced their numbers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smithsonian&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bristol&quot;/&gt;

Capybaras are hunted for their meat and [[Pelage|pelts]] in some areas,&lt;ref name=&quot;inRich&quot;/&gt; and otherwise killed by humans who see their grazing as competition for [[livestock]]. In some areas, they are [[farming|farmed]], which has the effect of ensuring the [[wetland]] [[habitats]] are protected. Their survival is aided by their ability to breed rapidly.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bristol&quot;/&gt;

Capybaras have adapted well to urbanization in South America. They can be found in many areas in [[zoo]]s and [[park]]s,&lt;ref name=&quot;SFZoo&quot;/&gt; and may live for 12 years in [[captivity (animal)|captivity]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Bristol&quot;/&gt; Capybaras are gentle and usually allow humans to pet and hand-feed them, but physical contact is normally discouraged, as their [[tick]]s can be [[vector (epidemiology)|vectors]] to [[Rocky Mountain spotted fever]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://drauziovarella.com.br/audios-videos/estacao-medicina/febre-maculosa/|title=Febre maculosa: &quot;Os médicos no Brasil não conhecem a doença|trans-title= Rocky Mountain spotted fever: Brazilian doctors unaware of the disease |language=Portuguese |publisher=drauziovarella.com.br |accessdate=2015-08-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[European Association of Zoos and Aquaria]] asked [[Drusillas Park]] in [[Alfriston]], [[Sussex]], [[England]] to keep the [[studbook]] for capybaras, to monitor captive populations in Europe. The studbook includes information about all births, deaths and movements of capybaras, as well as how they are related.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.drusillas.co.uk/conservation-1 |title=Conservation at Drusillas Park |publisher=Drusillas.co.uk |accessdate=2013-05-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Capybaras are farmed for meat and skins in South America.&lt;ref name=&quot;SDzoo&quot;/&gt; The meat is considered unsuitable to eat in some areas, while in other areas it is considered an important source of protein.&lt;ref name=r4/&gt; In parts of South America, especially in Venezuela, capybara meat is popular during [[Lent]] and [[Holy Week]] as the [[Catholic Church]] previously issued special dispensation to allow it to be eaten while [[Fasting and abstinence in the Catholic Church|other meats are generally forbidden]].&lt;ref name=&quot;NYSun&quot;/&gt; There is widespread perception in Venezuela that consumption of capybaras is exclusive to rural people.

Although it is illegal in some [[U.S. state|states]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://capybarafacts.com/Capybara-as-Pets/ | title=Capybaras as Pets| publisher=capybarafacts.com|accessdate=2014-10-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; capybaras are occasionally kept as pets in the United States.&lt;ref name=&quot;perez_snake&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Perez|first=Larry|title=Snake in the Grass: an Everglades Invasion|year=2012|publisher=[[Pineapple Press]]|location=Sarasota, Fla.|isbn=9781561645138|page=89|edition=1st}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The image of a capybara features on the [[Uruguayan peso|2-peso]] coin of Uruguay.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=2 Pesos Uruguayos de 2014|url=http://www.monedasuruguay.com/mon/2014/182.htm|publisher=Monedas Uruguay|accessdate=8 June 2016|language=Spanish}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Japan, following the lead of Izu Shaboten Park in 1982,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.tripadvisor.com/Attraction_Review-g298123-d1196864-Reviews-Izu_Shaboten_Animal_Park-Ito_Shizuoka_Prefecture_Chubu.html|title=Izu Shaboten Animal Park (Ito) – 2018 All You Need to Know Before You Go (with Photos) – TripAdvisor|website=www.tripadvisor.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; multiple establishments in Japan that raise capybaras have adopted the practice of having them relax in [[onsen]] during the winter.

==See also==
{{Portal|Animals|Latin America}}
*''[[Josephoartigasia monesi]]'', an extinct species identified as the largest rodent ever
*[[Kurloff cell]], a type of cell found in capybaras and guinea pigs

==References==
{{Reflist|30em|refs=
&lt;ref name=&quot;Bristol&quot;&gt;[http://www.bristolzoo.org.uk/learning/animals/mammals/capybara Bristol Zoo Gardens (UK) '&amp;#39;Capybara'&amp;#39;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070918183854/http://www.bristolzoo.org.uk/learning/animals/mammals/capybara |date=2007-09-18 }}. Bristolzoo.org.uk. Retrieved on 2011-12-07.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Barreto 1998&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |title=Foraging patterns of capybaras in a seasonally flooded savanna of Venezuela| jstor=2559868|doi=10.1017/S0266467498000078 |year=1998 |last1=Barreto |first1=Guillermo R. |last2=Herrera |first2=Emilio A. |journal=Journal of Tropical Ecology |volume=14 | issue=1| pages=87–98}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Quintana 1998&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|author1=Quintana, R.D. |author2=S. Monge |author3=A.I. Malvárez |year=1998|title=Feeding patterns of capybara ''Hydrochaeris hypdrochaeris'' (Rodentia, Hydrochaeridae) and cattle in the non-insular area of the Lower Delta of the Parana River, Argentina|journal=Mammalia |volume=62|issue=1|pages=37–52|doi=10.1515/mamm.1998.62.1.37}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=r6&gt;Burton M and Burton R. (2002) ''The International Wildlife Encyclopedia''. Marshall Cavendish, {{ISBN|0-7614-7269-X}}, p. 384&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;SoundsandColours&quot;&gt;[http://soundsandcolours.com/subjects/south-american-nature/capybara-the-master-of-the-grasses-pest-or-prey-3937/ Capybara, the master of the grasses: pest or prey]  Sounds and Colours. Retrieved on January 23, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;SFZoo&quot;&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20070614005832/http://www.sfzoo.org/cgi-bin/animals.py?ID=90 Capybara. ''Hydrochaeris hydrochaeris'']. San Francisco Zoo&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;SDzoo&quot;&gt;{{cite web  | date = October 2008  | publisher = San Diego Zoo  | title = Capybara, ''Hydrochoerus hydrochaeris''  | url = http://library.sandiegozoo.org/factsheets/capybara/capybara.htm  | accessdate = 22 June 2011  | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20110930051431/http://library.sandiegozoo.org/factsheets/capybara/capybara.htm  | archive-date = 30 September 2011  | url-status = dead  | df = dmy-all  }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Alho 1987&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author1=Alho C. J. R. |author2=Rondon N. L. | year = 1987 | title = Habitats, population densities, and social structure of capybaras (''Hydrochaeris hypdrochaeris'', Rodentia) in the Pantanal, Brazil | journal = Revista Brasileira de Zoologia | volume = 4 | issue = 2| pages = 139–149 | doi=10.1590/s0101-81751987000200006}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Lord-Rexford 1994&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|author=Lord-Rexford, D. |year=1994|title=A descriptive account of capybara behaviour|journal=Studies on Neotropical Fauna and Environment|volume=29|issue=1|pages=11–22|doi=10.1080/01650529409360912}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Macdonald 1981&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|author=Macdonald, D. W. |year=1981|title=Dwindling resources and the social behavior of Capybaras, (''Hydrochoerus hydrochaeris'') (Mammalia)|doi=10.1111/j.1469-7998.1981.tb04588.x| journal= [[Journal of Zoology]]|volume= 194|pages= 371–391|issue=3}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Murphey 1985&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.1016/0168-1591(85)90040-1 |title=Behavioral observations in a capybara colony (''Hydrochaeris hypdrochaeris'')|year=1985|last1=Murphey|first1=R|last2=Mariano|first2=J|last3=Mouraduarte|first3=F|journal=Applied Animal Behaviour Science|volume=14|page=89}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=r1&gt;{{cite journal|title=Seminiferous epithelium cycle and its duration in capybaras (''Hydrochaeris hypdrochaeris'') |pmid=10481304|doi=10.1054/tice.1999.0039|year=1999|last1=Paula|first1=T.A.R.|last2=Chiarini-Garcia|first2=H.|last3=França|first3=L.R.|journal=Tissue and Cell|volume=31|issue=3|pages=327–34}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=r2&gt;{{cite journal|pmid=10682750|year=2000|last1=Cueto|first1=GR|last2=Allekotte|first2=R|last3=Kravetz|first3=FO|title=Scurvy in capybaras bred in captivity in Argentine|volume=36|issue=1|pages=97–101|journal=Journal of Wildlife Diseases|doi=10.7589/0090-3558-36.1.97}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=r3&gt;[http://www.waza.org/virtualzoo/factsheet.php?id=110-020-001-001&amp;view=Rodents%20and%20Hares&amp;main=virtualzoo World Association of Zoos and Aquariums]. [[World Association of Zoos and Aquariums|WAZA]]. Retrieved on 2011-12-07.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=r4&gt;{{cite journal|journal=[[Mammalian Species]]| volume=264|issue=264| pages= 1–7|date=16 June 1986|last1=Mones|first1=Alvaro|authorlink1=Álvaro Mones|last2=Ojasti|first2=Juhani| title=Hydrochoerus hydrochaeris. Brisson, 1762| doi=10.2307/3503784|jstor=3503784}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Smithsonian&quot;&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20050930231549/http://nationalzoo.si.edu/Animals/Amazonia/Facts/capybarafacts.cfm Capybara Facts.] [[Smithsonian National Zoological Park]].  Retrieved on December 16, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Palm Beach Zoo&quot;&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20100620162726/http://palmbeachzoo.org/animals/capybara.html Capybara.] Palm Beach Zoo. Retrieved on December 17, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Macdonald 1984&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|author1=Macdonald, D. W. |author2=Krantz, K. |author3=Aplin, R. T. |title=Behavioral anatomical and chemical aspects of scent marking among Capybaras (''Hydrochaeris hypdrochaeris'') (Rodentia: Caviomorpha)|journal=Journal of Zoology|volume=202|issue=3|pages=341–360|doi=10.1111/j.1469-7998.1984.tb05087.x|year=1984}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;RevBiolTrop&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|vauthors=Forero-Montana J, Betancur J, Cavelier J |url=http://www.scielo.sa.cr/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S0034-77442003000200029&amp;lng=es&amp;nrm=iso |title=Dieta del capibara ''Hydrochaeris hydrochaeris'' (cavia: Hydrochaeridae) en Caño Limón, Arauca, Colombia|journal=Revista de Biología Tropical |year=2003|volume=51|issue=2|pages=571–578|pmid=15162749}} [https://web.archive.org/web/20090325001404/http://rbt.biologia.ucr.ac.cr/revistas/F51-2%20%5B2003%5D.pdf/29-Forero-Dieta.pdf PDF]&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;NYSun&quot;&gt;Ellsworth, Brian (March 24, 2005). [http://www.nysun.com/article/11063 &quot;In Days Before Easter, Venezuelans Tuck Into Rodent-Related Delicacy&quot;]. ''[[New York Sun]]''.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;inRich&quot;&gt;Thompson, Andy (January 18, 2008) [https://archive.is/20130204101346/http://www2.timesdispatch.com/lifestyles/2008/jan/18/-rtd_2008_01_18_0043-ar-147752/ Trip to South America gives new meaning to outdoors life]. Richmond Times.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Rowe 2002&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal
  | last = Rowe | first = D. L. |author2=Honeycutt, R. L.
  | title = Phylogenetic relationships, ecological correlates, and molecular evolution within the Cavioidea (Mammalia, Rodentia)  | journal = [[Molecular Biology and Evolution]]
  | volume = 19 | issue = 3 | pages = 263–277| year = 2002| pmid = 11861886 | doi=10.1093/oxfordjournals.molbev.a004080}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Vucetich 2005&quot;&gt;{{cite journal
 | last = Vucetich | first = M. G. |author2=Deschamps, C. M. |author3=Olivares, A. I. |author4=Dozo, M. T.
 | title = Capybaras, size, shape, and time: A model kit
 | journal = [[Acta Palaeontologica Polonica]] | volume = 50 | issue = 2 | pages = 259–272| year = 2005 | url = https://vanina-ue.academia.edu/ItatiOlivares/Papers/1301590/Capybaras_size_shape_and_time_A_model_kit | accessdate = 2012-05-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Deschamp 2007&quot;&gt;{{cite journal
 | last = Deschamps | first = C. M. |author2=Olivares, A. I. |author3=Vieytes, E. C. |author4=Vucetich, M. G.
 | title = Ontogeny and diversity of the oldest capybaras (Rodentia: Hydrochoeridae; late Miocene of Argentina)
 | journal = [[Journal of Vertebrate Paleontology]] | volume = 27 | issue = 3 | pages = 683–692| year = 2007 | jstor = 30126368 | doi=10.1671/0272-4634(2007)27[683:oadoto]2.0.co;2}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

==External links==
{{Commons cat|Hydrochoeris hydrochaeris|Hydrochoeris_hydrochaeris}}
{{EB1911 poster|Capybara}}
* {{cite web|title=Companionable Capybaras (18 Photos)|author=Alan Taylor|date=29 Nov 2018|website=The Atlantic|url=https://www.theatlantic.com/photo/2018/11/photos-companionable-capybaras/576991/}}
*{{Wikispecies-inline|Hydrochoerus hydrochaeris}}
*{{Wiktionary inline|capybara}}
* [http://animaldiversity.ummz.umich.edu/site/accounts/information/Hydrochoerus_hydrochaeris.html Animal Diversity Web ''Hydrochoerus hydrochaeris'']
* [http://www.capybarafacts.com Capybara information]

{{Caviidae nav}}
{{portalbar|Mammals|Animals|Biology|South America}}

{{Taxonbar|from=Q131538}}

[[Category:Mammals described in 1766]]
[[Category:Cavies]]
[[Category:Herbivorous mammals]]
[[Category:Mammals of Argentina]]
[[Category:Mammals of Bolivia]]
[[Category:Mammals of Brazil]]
[[Category:Mammals of Colombia]]
[[Category:Mammals of Ecuador]]
[[Category:Mammals of French Guiana]]
[[Category:Mammals of Guyana]]
[[Category:Mammals of Paraguay]]
[[Category:Mammals of Peru]]
[[Category:Mammals of Uruguay]]
[[Category:Mammals of Venezuela]]
[[Category:Articles containing video clips]]
[[Category:Semiaquatic mammals]]
[[Category:Rodents of South America]]</text>
      <sha1>fpta9dls0uucc51gqkpxkd63pwn6oh9</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
