  <page>
    <title>Consubstantiation</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6774</id>
    <revision>
      <id>916107221</id>
      <parentid>911462656</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-09-17T01:59:05Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Monkbot</username>
        <id>20483999</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* Use */[[User:Monkbot/task 16: remove replace deprecated dead-url params|Task 16]]: replaced (1×) / removed (0×) deprecated |dead-url= and |deadurl= with |url-status=;</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{distinguish|consubstantiality}}
{{Communion}}
'''Consubstantiation''' is a [[Christian theology|Christian theological doctrine]] that (like [[transubstantiation]]) describes the [[real presence]]  in the [[Eucharist]]. It holds that during the [[sacrament]], the [[Substance theory|substance]] of the body and blood of [[Christ]] are present ''alongside'' the substance of the bread and wine, which remain present. 
It was part of the doctrines of [[Lollardy]] and considered a [[heresy]] by the [[Roman Catholic Church]].

==Early examples==
In the early church it was common for the bread to be regarded as bread yet also as the Body of Christ, and the wine regarded as wine yet also as the Blood of Christ; indeed, some argued that to deny that both bread and wine, and Body and Blood, were present was to deny the Incarnation.

In about 150, [[Justin Martyr]], referring to the Eucharist, wrote: &quot;Not as common bread and common drink do we receive these; but in like manner as Jesus Christ our Savior, having been made flesh by the Word of God, had both flesh and blood for our salvation, so likewise have we been taught that the food which is blessed by the prayer of His word, and from which our blood and flesh by transmutation are nourished, is the flesh and blood of that Jesus who was made flesh.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.earlychristianwritings.com/text/justinmartyr-firstapology.html|title=Saint Justin Martyr: First Apology (Roberts-Donaldson)|website=www.earlychristianwritings.com |accessdate=2017-11-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Justin Martyr wrote, in the ''Dialogue with Trypho'', ch 70: &quot;Now it is evident, that in this prophecy [allusion is made] to the bread which our Christ gave us to eat, in remembrance of His being made flesh for the sake of His believers, for whom also He suffered; and to the cup which He gave us to drink, in remembrance of His own blood, with giving of thanks.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/anf01.viii.iv.lxx.html Justin Martyr, ''Dialogue with Trypho'', LXX]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Irenaeus of Lyons]] wrote, &quot;But what consistency is there in those who hold that the bread over which thanks have been given is the body of their Lord,  and the cup his blood,  if they do not acknowledge that He is the Son of the Creator… How can they say that the flesh which has been nourished by the Body of the Lord and by his blood gives way to corruption and does not partake of life? …For as the bread from the earth, receiving the invocation of God, is no longer common bread but the Eucharist, consisting of two elements, earthly and heavenly…”&lt;ref&gt;[https://actheologian.com/2016/05/20/church-fathers-on-the-real-presence/ Church Fathers on the Real Presence], Irenaeus, 140–202 AD, ''Against Heresies''&lt;/ref&gt;

==Use==
The doctrine of consubstantiation is often held in contrast to the doctrine of [[transubstantiation]]. While some Lutherans use the term &quot;consubstantiation&quot; to describe their doctrine, many reject it as not accurately reflecting the eucharistic doctrine of [[Martin Luther]], the [[sacramental union]].&lt;ref name=WELS/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;F.L. Cross, ed., ''The Oxford Dictionary of the Christian Church'', second edition, (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1974), 340 ''sub loco''.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Weimar Ausgabe'' 26, 442; ''Luther's Works'' 37, 299-300.&lt;/ref&gt; They reject the concept of consubstantiation because it replaces what they believe to be the biblical doctrine with a philosophical construct, denotes a mixing of substances (bread and wine with body and blood), and denotes a &quot;gross, Capernaitic, carnal&quot; presence of the body and blood of Christ.&lt;ref&gt;J.T. Mueller, &lt;cite&gt;''Christian Dogmatics: A Handbook of Doctrinal Theology''&lt;/cite&gt;, (St. Louis: CPH, 1934), 519.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Erwin L. Lueker, &lt;cite&gt;''Christian Cyclopedia''&lt;/cite&gt;, (St. Louis: CPH, 1975), &quot;[https://web.archive.org/web/20041109230057/http://www.lcms.org/ca/www/cyclopedia/02/display.asp?t1=C&amp;word=CONSUBSTANTIATION consubstantiation]&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Formula of Concord, Epitome, VII.42 and Solid Declaration VII.127 in F. Bente, ''Triglot Concordia'', (St Louis: CPH, 1921), 817, 1015.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=WELS&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.wels.net/cgi-bin/site.pl?1518&amp;cuTopic_topicID=58&amp;cuItem_itemID=11345 |archive-url=https://wayback.archive-it.org/all/20080102105710/https://www.wels.net/cgi-bin/site.pl?1518&amp;cuTopic_topicID=58&amp;cuItem_itemID=11345 |url-status=dead |archive-date=2 January 2008 |work=WELS Topical Q&amp;A |title=Real Presence Communion – Consubstantiation? |publisher=Wisconsin Evangelical Lutheran Synod |quote=Although some Lutherans have used the term 'consbstantiation' [sic] and it might possibly be understood correctly (e.g., the bread &amp; wine, body &amp; blood coexist with each other in the Lord's Supper),  most Lutherans reject the term because of the false connotation it contains...either that the body and blood, bread and wine come together to form one substance in the Lord’s Supper or that the body and blood are present in a natural manner like the bread and the wine. Lutherans believe that the bread and the wine are present in a natural manner in the Lord’s Supper and Christ’s true body and blood are present in an illocal, supernatural manner. |accessdate=26 Jan 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;America1888&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=Lectures on the Augsburg Confession|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=XWwrAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA350|accessdate=13 June 2014|year=1888|publisher=Lutheran Publication Society|quote=But in neither sense can that monstrous doctrine of Consubstantiation be attributed to our church, since Lutherans do not believe either in that local conjunction of two bodies, nor in any commingling of bread and of Christ's body, of wine and of his blood.|work=Theological Seminary of the United Lutheran Church in America|page=350}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[England]] in the late 14th century, there was a political and religious movement known as [[Lollardy]]. Among much broader goals, the Lollards affirmed a form of consubstantiation—that the Eucharist remained physically bread and wine, while becoming spiritually the body and blood of Christ. Lollardy survived up until the time of the [[English Reformation]].

Literary critic [[Kenneth Burke]]'s dramatism takes this concept and utilizes it in secular rhetorical theory to look at the [[dialectic]] of unity and difference within the context of [[logology (theology)|logology]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://bradley.bradley.edu/~ell/burke.html |title=Introduction to Kenneth Burke |first=Edward |last=Lamoureux |website=Bradley.edu}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Eucharistic theology]]
*[[Impanation]]
*[[Real Presence]]
*[[Transignification]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}

{{Authority control}}
[[Category:Lutheran Eucharistic theology]]
[[Category:Eucharist]]
[[Category:Christian terminology]]</text>
      <sha1>geeq9vxda4al75tkf5wmvgljhjrmcmc</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
