  <page>
    <title>Clitic</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6753</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942081847</id>
      <parentid>941900840</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-22T13:47:31Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Wolfdog</username>
        <id>1071745</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>rearranging lead</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">In [[Morphology (linguistics)|morphology]] and [[syntax]], a '''clitic''' ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|k|l|ɪ|t|ᵻ|k}}, backformed from [[Ancient Greek|Greek]] {{lang|grc|ἐγκλιτικός}} {{grc-transl|ἐγκλιτικός}} &quot;leaning&quot; or &quot;enclitic&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;crystal&quot;&gt;Crystal, David. ''A First Dictionary of Linguistics and Phonetics''. Boulder, CO: Westview, 1980. Print.&lt;/ref&gt;) is a [[morpheme]] that has syntactic characteristics of a word, but depends [[phonology|phonologically]] on another word or phrase. In this sense, it is syntactically independent but phonologically dependent—always attached to a host.&lt;ref name=&quot;sil-clitic&quot;&gt;SIL International (2003). SIL Glossary of Linguistic Terms: What is a clitic? &quot;This page is an extract from the LinguaLinks Library, Version 5.0 published on CD-ROM by SIL International, 2003.&quot; Retrieved from {{cite web |url=http://www.sil.org/linguistics/GlossaryOfLinguisticTerms/WhatIsACliticGrammar.htm |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2004-04-16 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20040510110313/http://www.sil.org/linguistics/GlossaryOfLinguisticTerms/WhatIsACliticGrammar.htm |archivedate=2004-05-10 }}.&lt;/ref&gt; A clitic is pronounced like an [[affix]], but plays a syntactic role at the [[phrase]] level.  In other words, clitics have the ''form'' of affixes, but the distribution of [[function word]]s. For example, the contracted forms of the auxiliary verbs in ''I'm'' and ''we've'' are clitics.

Clitics can belong to any grammatical category, although they are commonly [[pronoun]]s, [[determiner]]s, or [[adposition]]s. Note that [[orthography]] is not always a good guide for distinguishing clitics from affixes: clitics may be written as separate words, but sometimes they are joined to the word they depend on (like the Latin clitic ''-que'', meaning &quot;and&quot;), or separated by special characters such as [[hyphen]]s or [[apostrophe]]s (like the English clitic ''’s'' in &quot;it's&quot; for &quot;it has&quot; or &quot;it is&quot;).

==Classification==
{{confusing|section|reason=it is unclear which words or parts of words are clitics in the examples|date=July 2014}}

Clitics fall into various categories depending on their position in relation to the word they connect to.&lt;ref name=&quot;crystal&quot; /&gt;

=== Proclitic ===

A proclitic appears before its host.&lt;ref name=&quot;crystal&quot; /&gt; It is common in Romance languages. For example, in French, there is &quot;il '''s''''est réveillé&quot; (&quot;he woke up&quot;), or &quot;je '''t''''aime&quot; (&quot;I love you&quot;).

=== Enclitic ===

An enclitic appears after its host.&lt;ref name=&quot;crystal&quot; /&gt;
*[[Latin]]: [[SPQR|Senatus ''Populus'''''que''' Romanus]]
::&quot;Senate ''people''-'''and''' Roman&quot; = &quot;The Senate and people of Rome&quot;
*[[Ancient Greek]]: ''ánthrōpoí'' ('''te''') ''theoí'' '''te'''
:::&quot;''people'' ('''and''') ''gods'' '''and'''&quot; = &quot;(both) men and gods&quot;
*[[Sanskrit]]: ''naro gajaś'' '''ca'' 'नरो गजश्च' i.e. &quot;naraḥ gajaḥ ca&quot; &quot;नरः गजः च&quot; with [[sandhi]],:::&quot;''the man the elephant and''&quot; = &quot;the man and the elephant&quot;
*Sanskrit: [[Namaste|Namas'''te''']] &lt; ''namaḥ'' + ''te'', ([[Devanagari]]: नमः + ते = नमस्ते), with sandhi change ''namaḥ'' &gt; ''namas''.
::: &quot;''bowing to you''&quot;
*[[Czech language|Czech]]: ''Nevím, chtělo'''-li by se mi si to tam však''' také vyzkoušet''.
::&quot;'''However''' ('''''však'''''), I do not know (''nevím''), '''if''' ('''''-li''''') '''it''' '''would''' ('''''by''''') want (''chtělo '''se''''') to try (''vyzkoušet '''si''''') '''it''' ('''''to''''') '''to me''' ('''''mi''''') '''there''' ('''''tam''''') as well (''také'').&quot; (= However, I'm not sure if I would like to try it there as well.)
*[[Tamil language|Tamil]]: ''idhu en poo'' = இது என் பூ (This is my flower). With enclitic '''vē''', which indicates certainty, this sentence becomes
::idhu en poo'''vē''' = இது என் பூவே (This is ''certainly'' my flower)
*[[Telugu language|Telugu]]: ''idi nā puvvu'' = ఇది నా పువ్వు (This is my flower). With enclitic '''ē''', which indicates certainty, this sentence becomes
::Idi nā puvv'''ē''' = ఇది నా పువ్వే (This is ''certainly'' my flower)

=== Mesoclitic ===

A mesoclitic appears between the [[Word stem|stem]] of the host and other affixes. For example, in Portuguese, ''conquistar-'''se'''-á'' (&quot;it will be conquered&quot;), ''dá-'''lo'''-ei'' (&quot;I will give it&quot;), ''matá-'''la'''-ia'' (&quot;he/she/it would kill her&quot;). These are found much more often in writing than in speech. It is even possible to use two pronouns inside the verb, as in ''dar-'''no'''-'''lo'''-á'' (&quot;he/she/it will give it to us&quot;), or ''dar-'''ta'''-ei'' (''ta'' = ''te'' + ''a'', &quot;I will give it/her to you&quot;). As in other [[Western Romance language]]s, the Portuguese synthetic future tense comes from the merging of the infinitive and the corresponding finite forms of the verb ''haver'' (from Latin ''habēre''), which explains the possibility of separating it from the infinitive.

=== Endoclitic ===

The endoclitic splits apart the root and is inserted between the two pieces. Endoclitics defy the [[Lexical Integrity Hypothesis]] (or Lexicalist hypothesis) and so were long thought impossible. However, evidence from the [[Udi language]] suggests that they exist.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
 | last = Harris
 | first = Alice C.
 | year = 2002
 | title = Endoclitics and the Origins of Udi Morphosyntax
 | publisher = Oxford University Press
 | location = Oxford
 | isbn=0-19-924633-5
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; Endoclitics are also found in [[Pashto language|Pashto]]&lt;ref&gt;[[Craig Kopris|Craig A. Kopris]] &amp; Anthony R. Davis ([[Apptek|AppTek]], Inc. / StreamSage, Inc.), September 18, 2005.  Endoclitics in Pashto: Implications for Lexical Integrity ([https://web.archive.org/web/20060507073023/http://morbo.lingue.unibo.it/mmm/mm5-abstracts/kopris-davis.pdf abstract pdf])&lt;/ref&gt; and are reported to exist in [[Degema language|Degema]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
 | last = Kari
 | first = Ethelbert Emmanuel
 | year = 2003
 | title = Clitics in Degema: A Meeting Point of Phonology, Morphology, and Syntax
 | publisher = Research Institute for Languages and Cultures of Asia and Africa
 | location = Tokyo
 | isbn=4-87297-850-1
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

==Distinction==
One important distinction divides the broad term 'clitics' into two categories, simple clitics and special clitics.&lt;ref name=&quot;miller&quot;&gt;Miller, Philip H. &quot;Clitics and Phrasal Affixes.&quot; Clitics and Constituents in Phrase Structure Grammar. New York: Garland, 1992. N. pag. Print.&lt;/ref&gt; This distinction is, however, disputed.&lt;ref&gt;Bermúdez-Otero, Ricardo &amp; John Payne (2011). There are no special clitics. In Alexandra Galani, Glyn Hicks &amp; George Tsoulas (eds), ''Morphology and its interfaces'' (Linguistik Aktuell 178), 57–96. Amsterdam: John Benjamins.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Simple clitics ===

Simple clitics are free morphemes, meaning they can stand alone in a phrase or sentence.{{Example needed|date=December 2018}} They are unaccented and thus phonologically dependent upon a nearby word. They only derive meaning from this &quot;host&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;miller&quot; /&gt;

=== Special clitics ===

Special clitics are morphemes that are bound to the word they are dependent upon, meaning they exist as a part of their host.{{Example needed|date=December 2018}} This form, which is unaccented, represents a variant of a free form that does carry stress. While the two variants carry similar meaning and phonological makeup, the special clitic is bound to a host word and unaccented.&lt;ref name=&quot;miller&quot; /&gt;

==Properties==
Some clitics can be understood as elements undergoing a historical process of [[grammaticalization]]:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
 | last = Hopper
 | first = Paul J.
 |author2=Elizabeth Closs Traugott
 | year = 2003
 | edition = 2nd
 | title = Grammaticalization
 | publisher = Cambridge University Press
 | location = Cambridge
 | isbn=978-0-521-80421-9}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

{{in5}}lexical item → clitic → affix&lt;ref name=&quot;klavans&quot;&gt;[[Judith Klavans|Klavans, Judith L.]] On Clitics and Cliticization: The Interaction of Morphology, Phonology, and Syntax. New York: Garland Pub., 1995. Print.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to this model from [[Judith Klavans]], an autonomous lexical item in a particular context loses the properties of a fully independent word over time and acquires the properties of a morphological affix (prefix, suffix, infix, etc.). At any intermediate stage of this evolutionary process, the element in question can be described as a &quot;clitic&quot;. As a result, this term ends up being applied to a highly heterogeneous class of elements, presenting different combinations of word-like and affix-like properties.&lt;ref name=&quot;klavans&quot; /&gt;

===Prosody===
One characteristic shared by many clitics is a lack of [[Prosody (linguistics)|prosodic]] independence. A clitic attaches to an adjacent word, known as its ''host''. Orthographic conventions treat clitics in different ways: Some are written as separate words, some are written as one word with their hosts, and some are attached to their hosts, but set off by punctuation (a hyphen or an apostrophe, for example).{{citation needed|date=December 2012}}

===Comparison with affixes===
Although the term &quot;clitic&quot; can be used descriptively to refer to any element whose grammatical status is somewhere in between a typical word and a typical affix, linguists have proposed various definitions of &quot;clitic&quot; as a technical term. One common approach is to treat clitics as words that are prosodically deficient: they cannot appear without a host, and they can only form an accentual unit in combination with their host. The term &quot;'''postlexical clitic'''&quot; is used for this narrower sense of the term.&lt;ref&gt;Klavans, Judith L. On Clitics and Cliticization: The Interaction of Morphology, Phonology, and Syntax. New York: Garland Pub., 1995. Print.&lt;/ref&gt;

Given this basic definition, further criteria are needed to establish a dividing line between postlexical clitics and morphological affixes, since both are characterized by a lack of prosodic autonomy. There is no natural, clear-cut boundary between the two categories (since from a historical point of view, a given form can move gradually from one to the other by morphologization). However, by identifying clusters of observable properties that are associated with core examples of clitics on the one hand, and core examples of affixes on the other, one can pick out a battery of tests that provide an empirical foundation for a clitic/affix distinction.

An affix syntactically and [[phonology|phonologically]] attaches to a base [[morpheme]] of a limited [[part of speech]], such as a verb, to form a new word.  A clitic syntactically functions above the word level, on the [[phrase]] or [[clause]] level, and attaches only phonetically to the first, last, or only word in the phrase or clause, whichever part of speech the word belongs to.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
 | last = Zwicky
 | first = Arnold
 | authorlink = Arnold Zwicky
 | year = 1977
 | title = On Clitics
 | publisher = Indiana University Linguistics Club
 | location = Bloomington}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
The results of applying these criteria sometimes reveal that elements that have traditionally been called &quot;clitics&quot; actually have the status of affixes (e.g., the Romance pronominal clitics discussed [[#Romance languages|below]]).&lt;ref name=Spencer/&gt;

Zwicky and Pullum postulated five characteristics that distinguish clitics from affixes:&lt;ref name=Spencer/&gt;
# Clitics do not select their hosts.  That is, they are &quot;promiscuous&quot;, attaching to whichever word happens to be in the right place.  Affixes do select their host:  They only attach to the word they are connected to semantically, and generally attach to a particular part of speech.
# Clitics do not exhibit arbitrary gaps.  Affixes, on the other hand, are often lexicalized and may simply not occur with certain words.  (English plural -s, for example, does not occur with &quot;child&quot;.)
# Clitics do not exhibit morphophonological idiosyncrasies.  That is, they follow the morphophonological rules of the rest of the language.  Affixes may be irregular in this regard.
# Clitics do not exhibit semantic idiosyncrasies.  That is, the meaning of the phrase-plus-clitic is predictable from the meanings of the phrase and the clitic.  Affixes may have irregular meanings.
# Clitics can attach to material already containing clitics (and affixes).  Affixes can attach to other affixes, but not to material containing clitics.
An example of differing analyses by different linguists is the discussion of the possessive ('s) in English, some linguists treating it as an affix, while others treat it as a special clitic.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Clitics: An Introduction | first1=Andrew |last1=Spencer| first2=Ana R. |last2=Luis |isbn=9781139560313 |url= https://books.google.de/books?id=wLYgAwAAQBAJ |date= 2012 |publisher= Cambridge University Press |pages=292–293|quote=There are two alternatives that have been explored in recent literature.}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

===Comparison with words===
Similar to the discussion above, clitics must be distinguishable from words. Linguists have proposed a number of tests to differentiate between the two categories. Some tests, specifically, are based upon the understanding that when comparing the two, clitics resemble affixes, while words resemble syntactic phrases. Clitics and words resemble different categories, in the sense that they share certain properties. Six such tests are described below. These, of course, are not the only ways to differentiate between words and clitics.&lt;ref name=&quot;zwicky&quot;&gt;Zwicky, Arnold M. &quot;Clitics and Particles.&quot; Language 61.2 (1985): 283–305. Print.&lt;/ref&gt;

#If a morpheme is bound to a word and can never occur in complete isolation, then it is likely a clitic. In contrast, a word is not bound and can appear on its own.
#If the addition of a morpheme to a word prevents further affixation, then it is likely a clitic.
#If a morpheme combines with single words to convey a further degree of meaning, then it is likely a clitic. A word combines with a group of words or phrases to denote further meaning.{{Contradiction inline|reason=Further above it is said that clitics work on the phrase level. The English possessive, for example, attaches to a complete phrase.|date=October 2014}}
#If a morpheme must be in a certain order with respect to other morphemes within the construction, then it is likely a clitic. Independent words enjoy free ordering with respect to other words, within the confines of the word order of the language.
#If a morpheme’s allowable behavior is determined by one principle, it is likely a clitic. For example, &quot;a&quot; precedes indefinite nouns in English. Words can rarely be described with one such description.
#In general, words are more morphologically complex than clitics. Clitics are rarely composed of more than one morpheme.&lt;ref name=&quot;zwicky&quot; /&gt;

===Word order&lt;!--'Wackernagel's Law' and 'Wackernagel's law' redirect here--&gt;===
Clitics do not always appear next to the word or phrase that they are associated with grammatically. They may be subject to global word order constraints that act on the entire sentence. Many [[Indo-European languages]], for example, obey '''Wackernagel's law'''&lt;!--boldface per WP:R#PLA--&gt; (named after [[Jacob Wackernagel]]), which requires sentential clitics to appear in &quot;second position&quot;, after the first syntactic phrase or the first stressed word in a clause:&lt;ref name=&quot;klavans&quot; /&gt;
*[[Latin language|Latin]] had three enclitics that appeared in second or third position of a clause: ''enim'' 'indeed, for', ''autem'' 'but, moreover', ''vero'' 'however'.  For example, ''quis enim potest negare?'' (from [[Martial]]'s epigram LXIV, literally &quot;who indeed can deny [her riches]?&quot;). Spevak (2010) reports that in her corpus of [[Caesar]], [[Cicero]] and [[Sallust]], these three words appear in such position in 100% of the cases.&lt;ref&gt;Spevak, Olga (2010). ''The Constituent Order of Classical Latin Prose''. In series: ''Studies in language Amsterdam / Companion series'' (vol. 117). {{ISBN|9027205841}}. Page 14.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Indo-European languages==

===Germanic languages===

==== English ====
[[English language|English]] enclitics include the contracted versions of auxiliary verbs, as in ''I'm'' and ''we've''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last1=Huddleston |first1=Rodney |authorlink1=Rodney Huddleston
|last2= Pullum |first2= Geoffrey |authorlink2=Geoffrey Pullum
|title=The Cambridge Grammar of the English Language |year=2002 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |location=Cambridge; New York |isbn=0-521-43146-8|pages=1614–1616}}
&lt;/ref&gt; Some also regard the [[English possessive|possessive marker]], as in ''The Queen of England's crown'' as an enclitic, rather than a (phrasal) genitival inflection.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last1=Huddleston |first1=Rodney |authorlink1=Rodney Huddleston|last2= Pullum |first2= Geoffrey |authorlink2=Geoffrey Pullum|title=The Cambridge Grammar of the English Language |year=2002 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |location=Cambridge; New York |isbn=0-521-43146-8|pages=480–481}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some consider the [[Uses_of_English_verb_forms#To-infinitive|infinitive marker]] ''to'' and the [[English articles]] ''a, an, the'' to be proclitics.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://web.stanford.edu/~zwicky/what-is-a-clitic.pdf|title=What is a clitic?|author=|date=|website=stanford.edu|accessdate=30 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The negative marker ''n’t'' as in ''couldn’t'' etc. is typically considered a clitic that developed from the lexical item ''not''. Linguists [[Arnold Zwicky]] and [[Geoffrey Pullum]] argue, however, that the form has the properties of an affix rather than a syntactically independent clitic.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal
| last= Zwicky
| first= Arnold M.
| year= 1983
| title= Cliticization vs. inflection: the case of English ''n't''
| journal= Language
| volume= 59
| pages= 502–513
| doi= 10.2307/413900
| issue= 3
| author2= Pullum}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Other Germanic languages====
{{dubious|date=July 2013}}
*[[Old Norse]]: The definite article was the enclitic ''-inn'', ''-in'', ''-itt'' (masculine, feminine and neuter nominative singular), as in ''álfrinn'' &quot;the elf&quot;, ''gjǫfin'' &quot;the gift&quot;, and ''tréit'' &quot;the tree&quot;, an abbreviated form of the independent pronoun ''hinn'', [[cognate]] of the German pronoun ''jener''. It was fully declined for gender, case and number. Since both the noun and enclitic were declined, this led to &quot;double declension&quot;. The situation remains similar in modern [[Faroese language|Faroese]] and [[Icelandic language|Icelandic]], but in [[Danish language|Danish]], [[Norwegian language|Norwegian]] and [[Swedish language|Swedish]], the enclitics have become [[Suffix#Inflectional suffixes|endings]]. Old Norse had also some enclitics of personal pronouns that were attached to verbs. These were ''-sk'' (from ''sik''), ''-mk'' (from ''mik''), ''-k'' (from ''ek''), and ''-ðu'' / ''-du'' / ''-tu'' (from ''þú''). These could even be stacked up, e.g. &quot;fásktu&quot; (from Hávamál, stanza 116).
*[[Dutch language|Dutch]]: ''&amp;#39;t'' definite article of neuter nouns and third person singular neuter pronoun, ''&amp;#39;k'' first person pronoun, ''je'' second person singular pronoun, ''ie'' third person masculine singular pronoun, ''ze'' third person plural pronoun
* [[Plautdietsch]]: ''&quot;Deit'a't vondoag?&quot;'': &quot;Will he do it today?&quot;
*[[Gothic language|Gothic]]: Sentence clitics appear in second position in accordance with [[Wackernagel's Law]], including ''-u'' ([[yes-no question]]), ''-uh'' &quot;and&quot;, ''þan'' &quot;then&quot;, ''ƕa'' &quot;anything&quot;, for example ''ab-'''u''' þus silbin'' &quot;of thyself?&quot;. Multiple clitics can be stacked up, and split a [[preverb]] from the rest of the verb if the preverb comes at the beginning of the clause, e.g. ''diz-'''uh-þan'''-sat ijōs'' &quot;and then he seized them (fem.)&quot;, ''ga-'''u-ƕa'''-sēƕi'' &quot;whether he saw anything&quot;.

===Romance languages===
In [[Romance languages]], some feel the [[object (grammar)|object]] [[personal pronoun]] forms are clitics. Others consider them affixes, as they only attach to the verb they are the object of.&lt;ref name=Spencer&gt;Andrew Spencer and Ana Luís, &quot;The canonical clitic&quot;.  In Brown, Chumakina, &amp; Corbett, eds. ''Canonical Morphology and Syntax''.  Oxford University Press, pp. 123–150.&lt;/ref&gt; There is no general agreement on the issue.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.diplist.it/mmm8/handout/Gaglia_Schwarze.pdf |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2014-05-18 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140518102639/http://www.diplist.it/mmm8/handout/Gaglia_Schwarze.pdf |archivedate=2014-05-18 }}&lt;/ref&gt; For the [[Spanish object pronouns]], for example:

*'''''lo''' atamos'' {{IPA|['''lo'''aˈtamos]}} (&quot;'''it''' tied-&lt;small&gt;1PL&lt;/small&gt;&quot; = &quot;we tied it&quot; or &quot;we tied him&quot;; can only occur with the verb it is the object of)
*''dá'''melo''''' {{IPA|[ˈda'''melo''']}} (&quot;give '''me it'''&quot;)

Colloquial [[European Portuguese]] allows object suffixes before the conditional and future suffixes of the verbs:&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal 
 |last=Gadelii 
 |first=Karl Erland 
 |year=2002 
 |title=Pronominal Syntax in Maputo Portuguese (Mozambique) from a Comparative Creole and Bantu Perspective 
 |journal=Africa &amp; Asia 
 |volume=2 
 |pages=27–41 
 |issn=1650-2019 
 |url=http://www.african.gu.se/aa/pdfs/aa02027.pdf 
 |format=PDF 
 |accessdate=2006-09-20 
 |url-status=dead 
 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20060920015915/http://www.african.gu.se/aa/pdfs/aa02027.pdf 
 |archivedate=2006-09-20 
 }}
&lt;/ref&gt;

*''Ela levá-'''lo'''-ia'' (&quot;''She take-'''it'''-would''&quot; – &quot;She would take it&quot;).
*''Eles dar-'''no'''-'''lo'''-ão'' (&quot;''They give-'''us'''-'''it'''-will''&quot; – &quot;They will give it to us&quot;).

Colloquial [[Portuguese language|Portuguese]] of Brazil and Portugal and [[Spanish language|Spanish]] of the former [[Gran Colombia]] allow '''ser''' to be conjugated as a verbal clitic adverbial adjunct to emphasize the importance of the phrase compared to its context, or with the meaning of &quot;really&quot; or &quot;in truth&quot;:&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal
 |last        = Bartens
 |first       = Angela, and Niclas Sandström
 |year        = 2005
 |title       = Novas notas sobre a construção com ser focalizador
 |journal     = EStudos em homenagem ao Professor Doutor Mário Vilela
 |volume      = 1
 |pages       = 105–119
 |url         = http://ler.letras.up.pt/uploads/ficheiros/4523.pdf
 |format      = PDF
 |accessdate  = 2014-03-11
 |url-status     = live
 |archiveurl  = https://web.archive.org/web/20140312000606/http://ler.letras.up.pt/uploads/ficheiros/4523.pdf
 |archivedate = 2014-03-12
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

*''Ele estava '''era''' gordo'' (&quot;''He was '''was''' fat''&quot; – &quot;He was very fat&quot;).
*''Ele ligou '''é''' para Paula'' (&quot;''He phoned '''is''' Paula''&quot; – &quot;He phoned Paula (''with emphasis'')&quot;).

Note that this clitic form is only for the verb '''ser''' and is restricted to only third-person singular conjugations. It is not used as a verb in the grammar of the sentence but introduces prepositional phrases and adds emphasis. It does not need to concord with the tense of the main verb, as in the second example, and can be usually removed from the sentence without affecting the simple meaning.

===Proto-Indo-European===
In the [[Indo-European language]]s, some clitics can be traced back to [[Proto-Indo-European language|Proto-Indo-European]]: for example, *''{{PIE|-kʷe}}'' is the original form of [[Sanskrit]] ''[[wikt:च|च]]'' (''-ca''), [[Greek language|Greek]] ''[[wikt:τε|τε]]'' (''-te''), and [[Latin]] ''[[wikt:que#Latin|-que]]''.
*Latin: ''[[wikt:-que#Latin|-que]]'' &quot;and&quot;, ''[[wikt:-ve#Latin|-ve]]'' &quot;or&quot;, ''[[wikt:-ne#Latin|-ne]]'' ([[yes-no question]])
*Greek: ''[[wikt:τε|τε]]'' &quot;and&quot;, ''[[wikt:δέ|δέ]]'' &quot;but&quot;, ''[[wikt:γάρ|γάρ]]'' &quot;for&quot; (in a logical argument), ''[[wikt:οὖν|οὖν]]'' &quot;therefore&quot;

===Slavic languages===
*[[Russian language|Russian]]: [[wikt:ли|ли]] (yes-no question), [[wikt:же|же]] (emphasis), то (emphasis), [[wikt:не|не]] &quot;not&quot; (proclitic), [[wikt:бы|бы]] (subjunctive)
* [[Czech language|Czech]]: special clitics: weak personal and reflexive pronouns (''mu'', &quot;him&quot;), certain auxiliary verbs (''by'', &quot;would&quot;), and various short particles and adverbs (''tu'', &quot;here&quot;; ''ale'', &quot;though&quot;). &quot;''Nepodařilo '''by se mi mu to''' dát''&quot; &quot;I would not succeed in giving it to him&quot;. In addition there are various simple clitics including short prepositions.
* [[Polish language|Polish]]: ''[[wikt:by|-by]]'' (conditional mood particle), ''[[wikt:się|się]]'' (reflexive, also modifies meaning of certain verbs), ''[[wikt:no|no]]'' and ''[[wikt:że|-że]]'' (emphasis), ''-m, -ś, -śmy, -ście'' (personal auxiliary), ''mi, ci, cię, go, mu'' &amp;c. (unstressed personal pronouns in [[Oblique case|oblique cases]])
* [[Croatian language|Croatian]]: the [[reflexive pronoun]] forms ''si'' and ''se'', ''li'' (yes-no question), unstressed [[present]] and [[aorist]] tense forms of ''biti'' (&quot;to be&quot;; ''sam, si, je, smo, ste, su''; and ''bih, bi, bi, bismo, biste, bi'', for the respective tense), unstressed [[personal pronoun]]s in genitive (''me, te, ga, je, nas, vas, ih''), dative (''mi, ti, mu, joj, nam, vam, im'') and accusative (''me, te, ga (nj), je (ju), nas, vas, ih''), and unstressed present tense of ''htjeti'' (&quot;want/will&quot;; ''ću, ćeš, će, ćemo, ćete, će'')

In [[Croatian language|Croatian]] these clitics follow the first stressed word in the sentence or clause in most cases, which may have been inherited from [[Proto-Indo-European]] (see [[Wackernagel's Law]]), even though many of the modern clitics became cliticised much more recently in the language (e.g. auxiliary verbs or the accusative forms of pronouns). In subordinate clauses and questions, they follow the connector and/or the question word respectively. 

Examples (clitics – ''sam'' &quot;I am&quot;, ''biste'' &quot;you would (pl.)&quot;, ''mi'' &quot;to me&quot;, ''vam'' &quot;to you (pl.)&quot;, ''ih'' &quot;them&quot;): 

* ''Pokažite '''mi ih'''.'' &quot;Show (pl.) them to me.&quot; 
* ''Pokazao '''sam vam ih''' jučer.'' &quot;I showed them to you (pl.) yesterday.&quot; 
* ''Sve '''sam vam ih''' (jučer) pokazao. / Sve '''sam vam ih''' pokazao (jučer).'' &quot;I showed all of them to you (yesterday).&quot; (focus on &quot;all&quot;) 
* ''Jučer '''sam vam ih''' (sve) pokazao.'' &quot;I showed (all of) them to you yesterday.&quot; (focus on &quot;yesterday&quot;) 
* ''Znam da '''sam vam ih''' već pokazao.'' &quot;I know that I have already shown them to you.&quot; 
* ''Zašto '''sam vam ih''' jučer pokazao?'' &quot;Why did I show them to you yesterday?&quot; 
* ''Zar '''sam vam ih''' jučer pokazao?'' &quot;Did I (really) show them to you yesterday?&quot; 
* ''Kad '''biste mi ih''' sada dali...'' &quot;If you (pl.) gave them to me now...&quot; (lit. If you-would to-me them now give-PARTICIPLE...) 
* ''Što '''sam''' god vidio...'' &quot;Whatever I saw...&quot; (lit. What I-am ever see-PARTICIPLE...) 

In certain rural dialects this rule is (or was until recently) very strict, whereas elsewhere various exceptions occur. These include phrases containing conjunctions (e. g. ''Ivan i Ana'' &quot;Ivan and Ana&quot;), nouns with a genitival attribute (e. g. ''vrh brda'' &quot;the top of the hill&quot;), proper names and titles and the like (e. g. ''(gospođa) Ivana Marić'' &quot;(Mrs) Ivana Marić&quot;, ''grad Zagreb'' &quot;the city (of) Zagreb&quot;), and in many local varieties clitics are hardly ever inserted into any phrases (e. g. ''moj najbolji prijatelj'' &quot;my best friend&quot;, ''sutra ujutro'' &quot;tomorrow morning&quot;). In cases like these, clitics normally follow the initial phrase, although some Standard grammar handbooks recommend that they should be placed immediately after the verb (many native speakers find this unnatural). 

Examples: 
* ''Ja '''smo''' i on otišli u grad.'' &quot;He and I went to town.&quot; (lit. I are and him gone to town) – this is dialectal. 
* ''Ja i on '''smo''' otišli u grad.'' – commonly heard
* ''Ja i on otišli '''smo''' u grad.'' – prescribed by some Standard grammars 

* ''Moja '''mu je''' starija sestra to rekla.'' &quot;My elder sister told him that.&quot; (lit. my to-him is elder sister that say-PARTICIPLE) – standard and usual in many dialects 
* ''Moja starija sestra '''mu je''' to rekla.'' – common in many dialects 

Clitics are however never inserted after the negative particle ''ne'', which always precedes the verb in Croatian, or after prefixes (earlier preverbs), and the interrogative particle ''li'' always immediately follows the verb. Colloquial interrogative particles such as ''da li'', ''dal'', ''jel'' appear in sentence-initial position and are followed by clitics (if there are any). 

Examples: 
* ''Ne vidim '''te'''.'' &quot;I don't (or can't) see you.&quot; 
* ''Dovedite '''ih'''.'' &quot;Bring them (over here)!&quot; (a prefixed verb: ''do+vedite'') 
* ''Vidiš '''li me'''?'' &quot;Do/can you see me?&quot; 
* ''Vidiš '''li''' sestru?'' &quot;Do you see the sister?&quot; (It is impossible to say, e. g. **Sestru li vidiš?, although ''Sestru vidiš.'' &quot;It's the sister that you see.&quot; is natural) 
* ''Jel '''(me)''' vidiš?'' &quot;Do/Can you see (me)?&quot; (colloquial)

==Other languages==
*[[Arabic language|Arabic]]: Suffixes standing for direct object pronouns and/or indirect object pronouns (as found in Indo-European languages) are suffixed to verbs, possessive determiners are suffixed to nouns, and pronouns are suffixed to particles.
*[[Finnish language|Finnish]]: Finnish has seven clitics, which change according to the [[Vowel_harmony#Finnish|vowel harmony]]: ''-kO'' (''-ko ~ -kö''), ''-kA'' (''-ka ~ -kä''), ''-kin'', ''-kAAn'' (''-kaan ~ -kään''), ''-pA'' (''-pa'' ~ ''-pä''), ''-hAn'' (''-han ~ -hän'') and ''-s''. One word can have multiple clitics attached to it: ''on'''kohan'''?'' &quot;'''I wonder''' '''if''' it is?&quot;
**''-kO'' attached to a verb makes it a question: ''Katsot televisiota'' &quot;You are watching television&quot; → ''Katsot'''ko''' televisiota?'' &quot;Are you watching television?&quot;
**''-kA'' gives the host word a colloquial tone: ''miten'' ~ ''miten'''kä''''' (&quot;how&quot;). When attached to a [[Negative_verb#Finnish|negative verb]] it corresponds with &quot;and&quot;: ''En pidä mansikoista en'''kä''' mustikoista'' &quot;I don't like strawberries '''nor''' blueberries&quot;. It can also make a negative verb stronger: ''En'''kä''' tule!'' &quot;I '''definitely''' won't come!&quot;
**''-kin'' is a focus particle, often used instead of ''myös'' (&quot;also&quot; / &quot;as well&quot;): ''Minä'''kin''' olin siellä'' &quot;I was there '''too'''&quot;. Depending on the context when attached to a verb it can also express that something happened according to the plan or as a surprise and not according to the plan. It can also make exclamations stronger. It can be attached to several words in the same sentence, changing the focus of the host word, but can only appear once per sentence: ''Minä'''kin''' olin siellä'' (&quot;'''I''' was there '''too'''&quot;), ''Minä olin'''kin''' siellä'' (&quot;'''Surprisingly''' I '''was''' there&quot;), ''Minä olin siellä'''kin''''' (&quot;I was '''there''' '''too'''&quot;)
**''-kAAn'' is also a focus particle and it corresponds with ''-kin'' in negative sentences: ''Minä'''kään''' en ollut siellä'' &quot;I wasn't there '''either'''&quot;. Like ''-kin'' it can be attached to several host words in the same sentence. The only word it cannot be attached to is a negative verb. In questions it acts as a confirmation, like the word ''again'' in English: ''Missä sanoit'''kaan''' asuvasi?'' &quot;Where did you say you lived '''again'''?&quot;
**''-pA'' is a tone particle which can either add an arguing or patronising tone, or strengthen the host word:  ''Minä'''pä''' tiedän paremmin!'' &quot;Well I know better!&quot;, ''On'''pa''' kaunis kissa!'' &quot;'''Wow''' what a beautiful cat!&quot;
**''-hAn'' is also a tone particle. In interrogative sentences  it can make the question more polite and not as pressing: ''Onko'''han''' isäsi kotona?'' &quot;('''I wonder''') Is your dad home?&quot; In command phrases it makes the command softer: ''Tule'''han''' tänne'' &quot;Come here '''you'''&quot;. It can also make a sentence more explanatory, make a claim more self-evident, express that something happened according to one's expectations, or that something came as a surprise etc. ''Pekka tuntee minut, on'''han''' hän minun opettajani'' &quot;Pekka knows me, he is my teacher '''after all'''&quot;, ''Kaikki'''han''' niin tekevät'' &quot;Everyone do so '''after all'''&quot;, ''Maija'''han''' se siinä!'' &quot;Oh but it is Maija!&quot; ''Luulin, ettette osaisi, mutta te'''hän''' puhutte suomea hyvin'' &quot;I thought you wouldn't be able to, but you speak Finnish well&quot;
** ''-s'' is a tone particle as well. It can also be used as a mitigating or softening phrase like ''-hAn'': ''Anniko'''s''' se on?'' &quot;'''Oh but''' isn't it Anni?&quot;, ''Tule'''s''' tänne'' &quot;Come here '''you'''&quot;, ''Miksikä'''s''' ei?'' &quot;'''Well''' why not?&quot;, ''Paljonko'''s''' kello on?'' &quot;'''I wonder''' what time it is?&quot;
*[[Ganda language|Ganda]]: ''-nga'' attached to a verb to form the [[progressive aspect|progressive]]; ''-wo'' 'in' (also attached to a verb)
*[[Georgian language|Georgian]]: ''-o'' (2nd and 3rd person speakers) and ''-metki'' (1st person speakers) is added to the end of a sentence to show reported speech. Examples: ''K'atsma miutxra, xval gnaxe-o'' = The man told me that he would see you tomorrow (Literally, &quot;The man told me, tomorrow I see you [reported]&quot;) vs. ''K'atss vutxari, xval gnaxe-metki ='' I told the man that I would see you tomorrow (Literally, &quot;To man I told, tomorrow I see you [first person reported]).
*[[Hungarian language|Hungarian]]: the marker of indirect questions is ''-e:'' ''Nem tudja még, jön'''-e'''.'' &quot;He doesn't know yet '''if''' he'll come.&quot; This clitic can also mark direct questions with a falling intonation. ''Is'' (&quot;as well&quot;) and ''se'' (&quot;not... either&quot;) also function as clitics: although written separately, they are pronounced together with the preceding word, without stress: ''Ő is jön.'' &quot;He'll come too.&quot; ''Ő sem jön.'' &quot;He won't come, either.&quot;
*[[Japanese language|Japanese]]: all [[Japanese particles|particle]]s, such as the [[genitive case|genitive]] [[postposition]] [[wikt:の#Particle|の]] (''no'') and the [[topic (linguistics)|topic]] marker [[wikt:は#Particle|は]] (''wa'').
*[[Korean language|Korean]]: The copula [[wikt:이다|이다]] (''ida'') and the adjectival [[wikt:하다|하다]] (''hada''), as well as some nominal and verbal particles (e.g. [[wikt:는|는]], ''neun'').&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal
 |last        = Chae
 |first       = Hee-Rahk
 |year        = 1995
 |title       = Clitic Analyses of Korean &quot;Little Words&quot;
 |journal     = Language, Information and Computation Proceedings of the 10th Pacific Asia Conference
 |pages       = 97–102
 |url         = http://www.oasis.go.kr/ctrlu?cmd=resource-downview&amp;type=resource&amp;old_flag=N&amp;FN=maincc.hufs.ac.kr%2F_hrchae%2F6publi.htm&amp;resourceNo=95577
 |accessdate  = 2007-03-28
 |url-status     = dead
 |archiveurl  = https://web.archive.org/web/20120207234322/http://www.oasis.go.kr/ctrlu?cmd=resource-downview&amp;type=resource&amp;old_flag=N&amp;FN=maincc.hufs.ac.kr%2F_hrchae%2F6publi.htm&amp;resourceNo=95577
 |archivedate = 2012-02-07
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; However, alternative analysis suggests that the nominal particles do not function as clitics, but as phrasal affixes.&lt;ref name=uiuc_Korean_particles&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.linguistics.uiuc.edu/jyoon/Papers/Affix-order-final-single.pdf
| title = Non-morphological Determination of Nominal Particle Ordering in Korean
| author = James Hye Suk Yoon
| format = PDF
| url-status = dead
| archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20070927013419/http://www.linguistics.uiuc.edu/jyoon/Papers/Affix-order-final-single.pdf
| archivedate = 2007-09-27
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Somali language|Somali]]: pronominal clitics, either subject or object clitics, are required in Somali. These exist as simple clitics postponed to the noun they apply to. Lexical arguments can be omitted from sentences, but pronominal clitics cannot be.&lt;ref&gt;Mereu, Lunella. &quot;Agreement, Pronominalization, and Word Order in Pragmatically-Oriented Languages.&quot; Boundaries of Morphology and Syntax. Amsterdam: J. Benjamins, 1999. N. pag. Print.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Clitic climbing]]
*[[Clitic doubling]]
*[[Functional item]]
*[[Genitive case]]
*[[Grammatical particle]]
*[[Possessive case]]
*[[Separable affix]]
*[[Tmesis]]
*[[V2 word order]]
*[[Weak and strong forms in English]]
*[[Weak pronoun]]

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

[[Category:Syntax]]
[[Category:Morphophonology]]
[[Category:Units of linguistic morphology]]</text>
      <sha1>gv1k8hjzgqo6a9iccs1bpc79newdot1</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
