  <page>
    <title>Central Plaza (Hong Kong)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7017</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943150919</id>
      <parentid>943149986</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-29T04:31:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>North wiki</username>
        <id>4474448</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Ce</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use Hong Kong English|date=December 2018}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=December 2018}}
{{Infobox building
|name                = Central Plaza
|native_name         = 中環廣場
|image               = 中環廣場.JPG
|caption             = Central Plaza in April 2003
|location            = 18 Harbour Road &lt;br/&gt; [[Hong Kong]]
|coordinates         = {{coord|22|16|48|N|114|10|25|E|region:HK|display=inline,title}}
|status              = Complete
|start_date          = 1989
|completion_date     = 1992
|building_type       = Commercial offices
|architectural_style = [[Modern architecture|Postmodern]]
|architectural       = {{convert|373.9|m|ft|0|abbr=on}}
|roof                = {{convert|309|m|ft|0|abbr=on}}
|top_floor           = {{convert|299|m|ft|0|abbr=on}}
|floor_count         = 78 &lt;br/&gt;3 below ground
|elevator_count      = 39
|cost                =
|floor_area          = {{convert|172798|m2|sqft|0|abbr=on}}
|architect           = Dennis Lau &amp; Ng Chun Man Architects &amp; Engineers (HK) Ltd.
|structural_engineer = [[Arup Group Limited|Arup]]
|main_contractor     = Manloze Ltd
|developer           = Ryoden Development&lt;br&gt;Sino Land&lt;br&gt;Sun Hung Kai Properties
|owner               =
|management          =
|references          = &lt;ref&gt;{{ctbuh|277}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{emporis|120372}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{skyscraperpage|112}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{structurae|20004050}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
{{Chinese
|t=中環廣場
|s=中环广场
|showflag=y
|y=Jūngwàahn Gwóngchèuhng
|ci={{IPAc-yue|z|ung|1|.|w|aan|4|-|gw|ong|2|.|c|oeng|4}}
|j=Zung1waan4 Gwong2coeng4
|p=Zhōnghuán Guǎngchǎng
}}

'''Central Plaza''' is a 78-[[storey]], {{convert|374|m|abbr=on}} [[skyscraper]] completed in August 1992 at 18 Harbour Road, in [[Wan Chai]] on [[Hong Kong Island]] in [[Hong Kong]]. It is the third tallest tower in the city after [[International Finance Centre (Hong Kong)|2 International Finance Centre]] in [[Central, Hong Kong|Central]] and the [[International Commerce Centre|ICC]] in [[West Kowloon]]. It was the tallest building in Asia from 1992 to 1996, until the [[Shun Hing Square]] was built in [[Shenzhen]], a neighbouring city. Central Plaza surpassed the [[Bank of China Tower, Hong Kong|Bank of China Tower]] as the [[List of tallest buildings in Hong Kong|tallest building in Hong Kong]] until the completion of [[International Finance Centre (Hong Kong)|2 IFC]].

Central Plaza was also the tallest [[reinforced concrete]] building in the world, until it was surpassed by [[CITIC Plaza]], [[Guangzhou]]. The building uses a triangular [[floor plan]]. On the top of the tower is a four-bar neon clock that indicates the time by displaying different colours for 15-minute periods, blinking at the change of the quarter.

An [[anemometer]] is installed on the tip of the building's mast, at {{convert|378|m}} above sea level. The mast has a height of {{convert|102|m|abbr=on}}. It also houses the world's highest [[Church (building)|church]] inside a skyscraper, Sky City Church.

==History==
The land upon which Central Plaza sits was reclaimed from [[Victoria Harbour]] in the 1970s. The {{convert|77800|sqft|sqm}} site was auctioned off by the Hong Kong Government at [[Hong Kong City Hall|City Hall Theatre]] on 25 January 1989. It was sold for a record HK$3.35 billion to a joint venture called &quot;Cheer City Properties&quot;, owned 50 per cent by [[Sun Hung Kai Properties]] and 50 per cent by fellow real estate conglomerate [[Sino Land]] and their major shareholder the [[Ng Teng Fong]] family.&lt;ref name=&quot;record&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last1=Chan|first1=Chi-keung|title=Site sold for record $3.35 billion|work=South China Morning Post|date=26 January 1989|page=1}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;tocost&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last1=Chan|first1=Chi-keung|title=Wan Chai site development to cost $1.8b|work=South China Morning Post|date=27 January 1989|page=47}}&lt;/ref&gt; A third developer, Ryoden Development, joined the consortium afterward.&lt;ref name=&quot;arupjournal&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Ayres|first1=Peter|last2=MacArthur|first2=John|title=Central Plaza, Hong Kong|journal=Arup Journal|date=1993|volume=28|issue=4|pages=16–21}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ryoden Development disposed its 5% interest for 190,790 square feet of office space in New Kowloon Plaza from Sun Hung Kai in 1995.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Central Plaza sell-off boosts Ryoden |url=https://www.scmp.com/article/132204/central-plaza-sell-boosts-ryoden |accessdate=29 February 2020 |work=South China Morning Post |date=21 September 1995 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The first major tenant to sign a lease was the [[Provisional Airport Authority]], who on 2 August 1991 agreed to lease the 24th to 26th floors.&lt;ref name=&quot;PAA&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last1=Moreira|first1=Peter|title=Central Plaza draws airport authority|work=South China Morning Post|date=3 August 1991|page=21}}&lt;/ref&gt; A topping-out ceremony, presided over by Sir [[David Ford (civil servant)|David Ford]], was held on 9 April 1992.&lt;ref name=&quot;heady&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last1=Wigan|first1=David|title=New tower lures a heady mix|work=South China Morning Post|date=1 April 1992|page=29}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;newheights&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last1=Thompson|first1=Nick|title=Central Plaza reaches new heights|work=South China Morning Post|date=10 April 1992}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Design==
[[Image:HK Central Plaza 60407 1st.jpg|left|thumb|Main Lobby]]
Central Plaza is made up of two principal components: a free standing {{convert|368|m|ft|adj=mid|-high}} office tower and a {{convert|30.5|m|ft|adj=mid|-high}} podium block attached to it. The tower is made up of three sections: a {{convert|30.5|m|ft|adj=mid|-high}} tower base forming the main entrance and public circulation spaces; a {{convert|235.4|m|ft|adj=mid|-tall}} tower body containing 57 office floors, a [[sky lobby]] and five mechanical plant floors; and the tower top consist of six mechanical plant floors and a {{convert|102|m|ft|adj=mid|-tall}} tower mast.

The ground level public area along with the public sitting out area form an {{convert|8400|m²|abbr=on}} landscaped garden with fountain, trees and artificial stone paving. No commercial element is included in the podium. The first level is a public thoroughfare for three pedestrian bridges linking the Mass Transit Railway, the Convention and Exhibition Centre and the China Resource Building. By turning these space to public use, the building got 20% plot ratio more as bonus. The shape of the tower is not truly triangular but with its three corners cut off to provide better internal office spaces.

Central Plaza was designed by the Hong Kong architectural firm Ng Chun Man and Associates and engineered by [[Arup Group|Arup]]. The main contractor was a joint venture, comprising the contracting firms Sanfield (a subsidiary of Sun Hung Kai) and Tat Lee, called Manloze Ltd.&lt;ref name=&quot;arupjournal&quot;/&gt;

==Design constraints==

===Triangular shaped floor plan===
The building was designed to be triangular in shape because it would allow 20% more of the office area to enjoy the harbour view as compared with a square or rectangular shaped buildings. From an architectural point of view, this arrangement provides better floor area utilisation, offering an internal column-free office area with a clear depth of {{convert|9|to|13.4|m|ft|abbr=on}} and an overall usable floor area efficiency of 81%.
Nonetheless, the triangular building plan causes the air handling unit (AHU) room in the internal core to also assume a triangular configuration. With only limited space, this makes the adoption of a standard AHU not feasible. Furthermore, all air-conditioning ducting, electrical trunking and piping gathered inside the core area has to be squeezed into a very narrow and congested corridor ceiling void.

===Super high-rise building===
As the building is situated opposite to the [[Hong Kong Convention and Exhibition Centre]], the only way to get more sea view for the building and not be obstructed by the neighbouring high-rise buildings is to build it tall enough. However, a tall building brings a lot of difficulties to structural and building services design, for example, excessive system static pressure for water systems, high line voltage drop and long distance of vertical transportation. All these problems can increase the capital cost of the building systems and impair the safety operation of the building.

===Maximum clear ceiling height===
As a general practice, for achieving a clear height of {{convert|2.6|to|2.7|m|ft|abbr=on}}, a floor-to-floor height of {{convert|3.9|to|4.0|m|ft|abbr=on}} would be required. However, because of high windload in Hong Kong for such a super high-rise building, every increase in building height by a metre would increase the structural cost by more than HK$1 million (HK$304,800 per ft). Therefore, a comprehensive study was conducted and finally a floor height of {{convert|3.6|m|abbr=on}} was adopted. With this issue alone, an estimated construction cost saving for a total of 58 office floors, would be around HK$30 million. Yet at the same time, a maximum ceiling height of {{convert|2.6|m|abbr=on}} in office area could still be achieved with careful coordination and dedicated integration.

===Structural constraints===
[[Image:Sky City Church Lounge.jpg|thumb|Sky City Church lounge area in the Apex]]
*The site is a newly reclaimed area with a maximum water table rises to about {{convert|2|m|abbr=on}} below ground level. In the original brief, a 6-storey basement is required, therefore a diaphragm wall design came out.
*The keyword to this project is time. With a briefing in a limited detail, the structural engineer needed to start work The diaphragm wall design allowed for the basement to be constructed by the top-down method. It allows the superstructure to be constructed at the same time as the basement, thereby removing time-consuming basement construction period from the critical path.
*Wind loading is another major design criterion in Hong Kong as it is situated in an area influenced by typhoons. Not only must the structure be able to resist the loads generally and the cladding system and its fixings resist higher local loads, but the building must also perform dynamically in an acceptable manner such that predicted movements lie within acceptable standards of occupant comfort criteria. To ensure that all aspects of the building's performance in strong winds will be acceptable, a detailed wind tunnel study was carried out by Professor [[Alan Davenport]] at the Boundary Layer Wind Tunnel Laboratory at the [[University of Western Ontario]].

===Steel structure vs reinforced concrete===
Steel structure is more commonly adopted in high-rise building. In the original scheme, an externally cross-braced framed tube was applied with primary/secondary beams carrying metal decking with reinforced concrete slab. The core was also of steelwork, designed to carry vertical load only. Later after a financial review by the developer, they decided to reduce the height of the superstructure by increasing the size of the floor plate so as to reduce the complex architectural requirements of the tower base which means a highstrength concrete solution became possible.

In the final scheme, columns at {{convert|4.6|m|abbr=on}} centres and {{convert|1.1|m|ft|adj=mid|-deep}} floor edge beams were used to replace the large steel corner columns. As climbing form and table form construction method and efficient construction management are used in this project which make this reinforced concrete structure take no longer construction time than the steel structure. And the most attractive point is that the reinforced concrete scheme can save HK$230 million compared to that of steel structure. Hence the reinforced concrete structure was adopted and Central Plaza is now one of the tallest reinforced concrete buildings in the world.

In the reinforced concrete structure scheme, the core has a similar arrangement to the steel scheme and the wind shear is taken out from the core at the lowest basement level and transferred to the perimeter diaphragm walls. In order to reduce large shear reversals in the core walls in the basement, and at the top of the tower base level, the ground floor, basement levels 1 and 2 and the 5th and 6th floors, the floor slabs and beams are separated horizontally from the core walls.

Another advantage of using reinforced concrete structure is that it is more flexible to cope with changes in structural layout, sizes and height according to the site conditions by using table form system.

==Trivia==
[[Image:Central Plaza Sky Lobby.JPG|right|thumb|The ''Sky Lobby'' on the 46th floor was visited by American TV show ''[[The Amazing Race 2]]''.]]
This skyscraper was visited in the seventh leg of the reality TV show ''[[The Amazing Race 2]]'', which described Central Plaza as &quot;the tallest building in Hong Kong&quot;. Although contestants were told to reach the top floor,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Hidden in Plain Sight |url=http://www.cbs.com/primetime/amazing_race2/show/episode07/story2.shtml |website=CBS.com |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20020603144302/http://www.cbs.com/primetime/amazing_race2/show/episode07/story2.shtml |archivedate=3 June 2002}}&lt;/ref&gt; the actual task was performed on the 46th floor.

==See also==
{{Portal|Hong Kong|Architecture}}

* [[List of tallest buildings in Hong Kong]]
* [[List of buildings and structures in Hong Kong]]
* [[List of tallest freestanding structures in the world]]
{{clear}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
{{commons category|Central Plaza, Hong Kong}}
* {{official website|http://www.centralplaza.com.hk/}}
* [https://archive.is/20090601234410/http://courses.arch.hku.hk/IntgBuildTech/cases/centplaz/centplaz.htm Architectural study of the building]
* [http://www.skyscraperpage.com/diagrams/?c7 Hong Kong's skyscrapers in comparison]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20090304062222/http://www.hku.hk/bse/bbse2001/lift-example03.gif Central Plaza Elevator Layout]
{{Wan Chai District}}
{{Buildings in Hong Kong timeline}}
{{Hong Kong Skyscrapers}}
{{Supertall skyscrapers | current}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2011}}

[[Category:Office buildings completed in 1992]]
[[Category:Skyscraper office buildings in Hong Kong]]
[[Category:Sun Hung Kai Properties]]
[[Category:Wan Chai North]]</text>
      <sha1>8kdudu9z8gvhqyw0d5mhmfok955xrcb</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
