  <page>
    <title>Concubinage</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7016</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943320849</id>
      <parentid>942376897</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-03-01T05:48:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>172.58.43.63</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Vikings */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|Concubine}}
{{Short description|Sexual relationship in which the couple are not or cannot be married}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}
[[File:François-Joseph_Navez_-_Agar_et_Ismaël_dans_le_désert.jpg|thumb|''Hagar and Ishmael in the Desert'' by [[François-Joseph Navez]], 1820. [[Hagar]] was [[Abraham]]'s Egyptian concubine. [[Ishmael]] was their first-born son.]]
{{Close Relationships|types}}
'''Concubinage''' ({{IPAc-en|k|ɑː|n|ˈ|k|juː|b|aɪ|n|ᵻ|dʒ}}) is an [[interpersonal relationship|interpersonal]] and [[Intimate relationship|sexual relationship]] between a man and a woman in which the couple are not or cannot be married. The inability to marry may be due to multiple factors such as differences in social rank status, an existing marriage, religious or professional prohibitions (for example Roman soldiers), or a lack of recognition by appropriate authorities. The woman in such a relationship is referred to as a '''concubine''' ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|k|ɒ|ŋ|k|j|ᵿ|ˌ|b|aɪ|n}}). A concubine among [[Polygyny|polygynyous]] peoples is a secondary wife, usually of inferior rank.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.dictionary.com/browse/concubine|title=Dictionary.com - Concubine|last=|first=|date=|website=Dictionary|url-status=live|archive-url=|archive-date=|accessdate=14 February 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/concubine|title=Definition of CONCUBINE|website=www.merriam-webster.com|language=en|access-date=2020-02-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://dictionary.cambridge.org/us/dictionary/english/concubine|title=CONCUBINE {{!}} definition in the Cambridge English Dictionary|website=dictionary.cambridge.org|language=en-US|access-date=2020-02-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Judaism]], a concubine is a marital companion of inferior status to a wife.&lt;ref name=&quot;Concubine&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/concubine|title=Concubine|website=Jewish Virtual Library|accessdate=14 February 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The prevalence of concubinage and the status of rights and expectations of a concubine have varied among cultures, as have the rights of children of a concubine. Whatever the status and rights of the concubine, they were always inferior to those of the wife, and typically neither she nor her children had rights of inheritance. Historically, concubinage was usually voluntary (by the woman or her family), as it provided a measure of economic security for the woman.{{Citation needed|date=June 2019}} Involuntary or servile concubinage sometimes involved [[sexual slavery]] of one member of the relationship, usually the woman. Nevertheless, sexual relations outside marriage were{{when|date=January 2019}}{{where?|date=January 2019}} not uncommon, [[Courtesan|especially]] among royalty and nobility, and the woman in such relationships was commonly described as a [[Mistress (lover)|mistress]]. The children of such relationships were counted as [[illegitimate]] and in some societies were barred from inheriting the father's title or estates, even in the absence of legitimate heirs.

==In Asia==
Concubinage was highly popular before the early 20th century all over [[East Asia]]. The main function of concubinage was producing additional heirs, as well as bringing males pleasure. Children of concubines had lower rights in account to inheritance, which was regulated by the [[Dishu system]].

===China===
{{See also|Women in ancient and imperial China}}
[[File:Hua-Qing-Chi-Yang-Gui-Fei.jpg|alt=|thumb|289x289px|Statue of [[Yang Guifei]] (719-756), the favoured concubine of Emperor [[Tang Xuanzong]] of [[China]].]]
[[File:The Fourth Concubine of Hexing.jpg|thumb|upright|Portrait of a concubine, by Chinese painter [[Lam Qua]], 1864]]
In China, successful men often had concubines until the practice was outlawed when the [[Communist Party of China]] came to power in 1949. The standard Chinese term translated as &quot;concubine&quot; was ''qiè'' {{lang|zh|妾}}, a term that has been used since ancient times, which means &quot;concubine; I, your servant (deprecating self reference)&quot;. Concubinage resembled marriage in that concubines were recognized sexual partners of a man and were expected to bear children for him. Unofficial concubines ({{zh|t=婢妾|p=bì qiè}}) were of lower status, and their children were considered illegitimate. The English term concubine is also used for what the Chinese refer to as ''pínfēi'' ({{zh|t=嬪妃}}), or &quot;consorts of emperors&quot;, an official position often carrying a very high rank.&lt;ref&gt;Patricia Buckley Ebrey (2002): ''Women and the Family in Chinese History''. Oxford: Routledge, p. 39.&lt;/ref&gt;

In premodern China it was illegal and socially disreputable for a man to have more than one wife at a time, but it was acceptable to have concubines.&lt;ref&gt;Ebrey 2002:39.&lt;/ref&gt; In the earliest records a man could have as many concubines as he could afford. From the [[Han dynasty#Eastern Han|Eastern Han]] period (AD 25–220) onward, the number of concubines a man could have was limited by law. The higher rank and the more noble identity a man possessed, the more concubines he was permitted to have.&lt;ref&gt;Shi Fengyi 史凤仪 (1987): Zhongguo gudai hunyin yu jiating 中国古代婚姻与家庭 ''Marriage and Family in Ancient China''. Wuhan: Hubei Renmin Chubanshe, p. 74.&lt;/ref&gt;

A concubine's treatment and situation was variable and was influenced by the social status of the male to whom she was attached, as well as the attitude of his wife. In the ''[[Book of Rites]]'' chapter on &quot;The Pattern of the Family&quot; ({{zh|t=內則}}) it says, “If there were betrothal rites, she became a wife; and if she went without these, a concubine.”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://ctext.org/liji/nei-ze#n9964|title=Nei Ze|accessdate=11 December 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160304051012/http://ctext.org/liji/nei-ze#n9964|archive-date=4 March 2016|url-status=live|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; Wives brought a [[dowry]] to a relationship, but concubines did not. A concubinage relationship could be entered into without the ceremonies used in marriages, and neither remarriage nor a return to her natal home in widowhood were allowed to a concubine.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ebrey 2002: 60&quot;&gt;Ebrey 2002: 60.&lt;/ref&gt;

The position of the concubine was generally inferior to that of the wife. Although a concubine could produce heirs, her children would be inferior in social status to a wife's children, although they were of higher status than illegitimate children. The child of a concubine had to show filial duty to two women, their biological mother and their legal mother—the wife of their father.&lt;ref&gt;Ebrey 2002: 54.&lt;/ref&gt; After the death of a concubine, her sons would make an offering to her, but these offerings were not continued by the concubine's grandsons, who only made offerings to their grandfather's wife.&lt;ref&gt;Ebrey 2002: 42.&lt;/ref&gt;

There are early records of concubines allegedly being buried alive with their masters to &quot;keep them company in the afterlife&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Concubines of Ancient China&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Concubines of Ancient China|url=http://www.beijingmadeeasy.com/beijing-history/concubines-of-ancient-china|work=Beijing Made Easy|publisher=Beijing Made Easy|accessdate=13 June 2012|year=2012|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120608030129/http://www.beijingmadeeasy.com/beijing-history/concubines-of-ancient-china|archive-date=8 June 2012|url-status=live|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; Until the [[Song dynasty]] (960–1276), it was considered a serious breach of social ethics to promote a concubine to a wife.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ebrey 2002: 60&quot;/&gt;

During the [[Qing dynasty]] (1644–1911), the status of concubines improved. It became permissible to promote a concubine to wife, if the original wife had died and the concubine was the mother of the only surviving sons. Moreover, the prohibition against forcing a widow to remarry was extended to widowed concubines. During this period tablets for concubine-mothers seem to have been more commonly placed in family ancestral altars, and genealogies of some lineages listed concubine-mothers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ebrey 2002: 60&quot;/&gt;

Imperial concubines, kept by emperors in the [[Forbidden City]], had [[ranks of imperial consorts in China|different ranks]] and were traditionally guarded by [[eunuch]]s to ensure that they could not be impregnated by anyone but the emperor.&lt;ref name=&quot;Concubines of Ancient China&quot;/&gt; In [[Ming dynasty|Ming China]] (1368–1644) there was an official system to select concubines for the emperor. The age of the candidates ranged mainly from 14 to 16. Virtues, behavior, character, appearance and body condition were the selection criteria.&lt;ref&gt;Qiu Zhonglin(Chung-lin Ch'iu)邱仲麟:&quot;Mingdai linxuan Houfei jiqi guizhi&quot; 明代遴選後妃及其規制 (The Imperial Concubine Selection System during the Ming Dynasty). Mingdai Yanjiu 明代研究 (Ming Studies) 11.2008:58.&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite the limitations imposed on Chinese concubines, there are several examples in history and literature of concubines who achieved great power and influence. Lady Yehenara, otherwise known as [[Empress Dowager Cixi]], was arguably one of the most successful concubines in Chinese history. Cixi first entered the court as a concubine to [[Xianfeng Emperor]] and gave birth to his only surviving son, who later became [[Tongzhi Emperor]]. She eventually became the ''[[de facto]]'' ruler of Qing China for 47 years after her husband's death.&lt;ref name=EmpressChina&gt;{{cite book|author= Sterling Seagrave, Peggy Seagrave|title=Dragon lady: the life and legend of the last empress of China|year=1993|publisher=Vintage Books}}&lt;/ref&gt;

An examination of concubinage features in one of the [[Four Great Classical Novels]], ''[[Dream of the Red Chamber]]'' (believed to be a [[autobiographical novel|semi-autobiographical]] account of author [[Cao Xueqin]]'s family life).{{Citation needed|date=July 2018}} Three generations of the Jia family are supported by one notable concubine of the emperor, [[Jia Yuanchun]], the full elder sister of the male protagonist [[Jia Baoyu]]. In contrast, their younger half-siblings by concubine Zhao, [[Jia Tanchun]] and Jia Huan, develop distorted personalities because they are the children of a concubine.{{Citation needed|date=July 2018}}

Emperors' concubines and [[harems]] are emphasized in 21st-century romantic novels written for female readers and set in ancient times. As a plot element, the children of concubines are depicted with a status much inferior to that in actual history.{{citation needed|date=July 2018}} The '''zhai dou''' ({{zh|t=宅斗}}，residential intrigue) and '''gong dou'''({{zh|t=宫斗}}，harem intrigue) genres show concubines and wives, as well as their children, scheming secretly to gain power. [[Empresses in the Palace]], a ''gong dou'' type novel and TV drama, has had great success in 21st-century China.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://en.people.cn/102774/8067124.html|title=Top 10 Chinese entertainment events in 2012 (7) - People's Daily Online|website=en.people.cn|access-date=2020-02-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;
===Hong Kong and Macau===
Hong Kong officially abolished the [[Great Qing Legal Code]] in 1971, thereby making concubinage illegal. Casino magnate [[Stanley Ho]] of Macau took his &quot;second wife&quot; as his official concubine in 1957, while his &quot;third and fourth wives&quot; retain no official status.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aiweibang.com/yuedu/101925130.html|title=港台剧怀旧经典|website=www.aiweibang.com|access-date=5 September 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160923232525/http://www.aiweibang.com/yuedu/101925130.html|archive-date=23 September 2016|url-status=live|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Japan===
{{See also|Ōoku}}
[[File:Taikō gosai rakutō yūkan no zu.jpg|thumb|16th-century [[Samurai]] [[Toyotomi Hideyoshi]] with his wives and concubines.]]
Before [[monogamy]] was legally imposed in the [[Meiji period]], concubinage was common among the nobility.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://departments.kings.edu/womens_history/concubin.html|title=Concubinage in Asia|accessdate=11 December 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170326034744/http://departments.kings.edu/womens_history/concubin.html|archive-date=26 March 2017|url-status=live|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its purpose was to ensure male heirs. For example, the son of an [[Imperial House of Japan|Imperial]]  concubine often had a chance of becoming emperor. [[Yanagihara Naruko]], a high-ranking concubine of [[Emperor Meiji]], gave birth to [[Emperor Taishō]], who was later legally adopted by [[Empress Haruko]], Emperor Meiji's formal wife. Even among merchant families, concubinage was occasionally used to ensure heirs. [[Asako Hirooka]], an entrepreneur who was the daughter of a concubine, worked hard to help her husband's family survive after the [[Meiji Restoration]]. She lost her fertility giving birth to her only daughter, Kameko; so her husband—with whom she got along well—took Asako's maid-servant as a concubine and fathered three daughters and a son with her. Kameko, as the child of the formal wife, married a noble man and matrilineally carried on the family name.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sankei.com/west/news/150602/wst1506020001-n1.html|title=【九転十起の女（２７）】女盛りもとうに過ぎ…夫とお手伝いの間に子供|first=SANKEI DIGITAL|last=INC.|accessdate=11 December 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161019020813/http://www.sankei.com/west/news/150602/wst1506020001-n1.html|archive-date=19 October 2016|url-status=live|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Korea===
[[Joseon]] monarchs had a harem which contained concubines of different ranks. [[Empress Myeongseong]] managed to have sons, preventing sons of concubines getting power.

Children of concubines often had lower value in account of marriage. A daughter of concubine could not marry a wife-born son of the same class. For example, [[Jang Nok-su]] was a concubine-born daughter of a mayor, who was initially married to a slave-servant, and later became a high-ranking concubine of [[Yeonsangun]].

== Vikings ==
[[Polygyny]] was common among [[Vikings]], rich and powerful Viking men tended to have many wives and concubines. Viking men would often buy or [[Bride kidnapping|capture women]] and make them into their wives or concubines.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Karras|first=Ruth Mazo|date=1990|title=Concubinage and Slavery in the Viking Age|journal=Scandinavian Studies|volume=62|issue=2|pages=141–162|issn=0036-5637|jstor=40919117}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Poser|first=Charles M.|date=1994|title=The dissemination of multiple sclerosis: A Viking saga? A historical essay|journal=Annals of Neurology|language=en|volume=36|issue=S2|pages=S231–S243|doi=10.1002/ana.410360810|issn=1531-8249}}&lt;/ref&gt; Researchers have suggested that Vikings may have originally started sailing and raiding due to a need to seek out women from greater continental Europe.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.sciencealert.com/vikings-might-have-raided-because-there-was-a-shortage-of-single-women|title=Vikings Might Have Started Raiding Because There Was a Shortage of Single Women|last=Hrala|first=Josh|website=ScienceAlert|language=en-gb|url-status=live|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190530102637/https://www.sciencealert.com/vikings-might-have-raided-because-there-was-a-shortage-of-single-women|archive-date=30 May 2019|access-date=2019-07-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:12&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.livescience.com/56786-vikings-raided-to-find-love.html|title=The Real Reason for Viking Raids: Shortage of Eligible Women?|last=Choi|first=Charles Q.|last2=November 8|first2=Live Science Contributor {{!}}|website=Live Science|url-status=live|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190729113022/https://www.livescience.com/56786-vikings-raided-to-find-love.html|archive-date=29 July 2019|access-date=2019-07-21|last3=ET|first3=2016 09:07am}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://allthatsinteresting.com/iceland-founded-viking-slaves|title=Sex Slaves – The Dirty Secret Behind The Founding Of Iceland|date=2018-01-16|website=All That's Interesting|language=en-US|url-status=live|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190722043846/https://allthatsinteresting.com/iceland-founded-viking-slaves|archive-date=22 July 2019|access-date=2019-07-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.nationalgeographic.com/news/2015/12/151228-vikings-slaves-thralls-norse-scandinavia-archaeology/|title=Kinder, Gentler Vikings? Not According to Their Slaves|date=2015-12-28|website=National Geographic News|url-status=live|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190802035726/https://www.nationalgeographic.com/news/2015/12/151228-vikings-slaves-thralls-norse-scandinavia-archaeology/|archive-date=2 August 2019|access-date=2019-08-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; Polygynous relationships among Vikings may have led to a shortage of eligible women for the average Viking male. Polygynous marriage increases [[male-male competition]] in society because it creates a pool of unmarried men who are willing to engage in risky status-elevating and sex seeking behaviors.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Raffield|first=Ben|last2=Price|first2=Neil|last3=Collard|first3=Mark|date=2017-05-01|title=Male-biased operational sex ratios and the Viking phenomenon: an evolutionary anthropological perspective on Late Iron Age Scandinavian raiding|journal=Evolution and Human Behavior|volume=38|issue=3|pages=315–24|doi=10.1016/j.evolhumbehav.2016.10.013|issn=1090-5138}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.sciencemag.org/news/2016/04/vikings-may-have-first-taken-seas-find-women-slaves|title=Vikings may have first taken to seas to find women, slaves|last=LawlerApr. 15|first=rew|last2=2016|date=2016-04-13|website=Science {{!}} AAAS|language=en|url-status=live|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190727122934/https://www.sciencemag.org/news/2016/04/vikings-may-have-first-taken-seas-find-women-slaves|archive-date=27 July 2019|access-date=2019-07-19|last3=Am|first3=3:00}}&lt;/ref&gt; Due to this, the average Viking man could have been forced to perform riskier actions to gain wealth and power to be able to find suitable women.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.nbcnews.com/id/26755692/ns/technology_and_science-science/t/viking-age-triggered-shortage-wives/|title=Viking Age triggered by shortage of wives?|last=Viegas|first=Jennifer|date=2008-09-17|website=msnbc.com|language=en|url-status=live|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190723002325/http://www.nbcnews.com/id/26755692/ns/technology_and_science-science/t/viking-age-triggered-shortage-wives/|archive-date=23 July 2019|access-date=2019-07-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|last=Knapton|first=Sarah|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/2016/11/05/viking-raiders-were-only-trying-to-win-their-future-wives-hearts/|title=Viking raiders were only trying to win their future wives' hearts|date=2016-11-05|work=The Telegraph|access-date=2019-08-01|url-status=live|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190801070257/https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/2016/11/05/viking-raiders-were-only-trying-to-win-their-future-wives-hearts/|archive-date=1 August 2019|language=en-GB|issn=0307-1235}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.thevintagenews.com/2018/10/22/vikings-invasions/|title=New Viking Study Points to &quot;Love and Marriage&quot; as the Main Reason for their Raids|date=2018-10-22|website=The Vintage News|language=en|url-status=live|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190802035734/https://www.thevintagenews.com/2018/10/22/vikings-invasions/|archive-date=2 August 2019|access-date=2019-08-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; The concept was expressed in the 11th century by historian [[Dudo of Saint-Quentin]] in his semi imaginary ''History of The Normans''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyatt2009&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=David R. Wyatt|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=RWJGynaKSkkC&amp;pg=PA124|title=Slaves and Warriors in Medieval Britain and Ireland: 800–1200|publisher=Brill|year=2009|isbn=978-90-04-17533-4|page=124}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Annals of Ulster]] depicts [[raptio]] and states that in 821 the Vikings plundered an Irish village and &quot;carried off a great number of women into captivity&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;DolfiniCrellin2018&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author1=Andrea Dolfini|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=8e1lDwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA349|title=Prehistoric Warfare and Violence: Quantitative and Qualitative Approaches|author2=Rachel J. Crellin|author3=Christian Horn|author4=Marion Uckelmann|publisher=Springer|year=2018|isbn=978-3-319-78828-9|page=349}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Greco-Roman Antiquity==
===Ancient Greece===
In [[Ancient Greece]], the practice of keeping a slave concubine ({{lang-grc|παλλακίς}} ''pallakís'') was little recorded but appeared throughout Athenian history. The law prescribed that a man could kill another man caught attempting a relationship with his concubine for the production of free children, which suggests that a concubine's children were not granted citizenship.{{clarify|date=February 2019}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Davidson&quot;&gt;{{cite book | author = James Davidson | title = Courtesans and Fishcakes: The Consuming Passions of Classical Athens | url = https://archive.org/details/isbn_9780312185596 | url-access = registration |page = [https://archive.org/details/isbn_9780312185596/page/98 98] | isbn = 0-312-18559-6 | year = 1998 }}&lt;/ref&gt; While references to the sexual exploitation of maidservants appear in literature, it was considered disgraceful for a man to keep such women under the same roof as his wife.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = James Davidson | title = Courtesans and Fishcakes: The Consuming Passions of Classical Athens | url = https://archive.org/details/isbn_9780312185596 | url-access = registration | pages = [https://archive.org/details/isbn_9780312185596/page/98 98–99] | isbn = 0-312-18559-6 | year = 1998 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Some interpretations of ''[[Hetaira|hetaera]]'' have held they were concubines when they had a permanent relationship with a single man.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = James Davidson | title = Courtesans and Fishcakes: The Consuming Passions of Classical Athens | url = https://archive.org/details/isbn_9780312185596 | url-access = registration | page = [https://archive.org/details/isbn_9780312185596/page/101 101] | isbn = 0-312-18559-6 | year = 1998 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ancient Roman ''concubinae'' and ''concubini''===
{{Details|Marriage in ancient Rome#Concubinage}}
Concubinage was an institution practiced in [[ancient Rome]] that allowed a man to enter into an informal but recognized relationship with a woman (''concubina'', plural ''concubinae'') who was not his wife, most often a woman whose lower [[social class in ancient Rome|social status]] was an obstacle to marriage. Concubinage was &quot;tolerated to the degree that it did not threaten the religious and legal integrity of the family&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Grimal, Love in Ancient Rome (University of Oklahoma Press) 1986:111.&lt;/ref&gt; It was not considered derogatory to be called a ''concubina'', as the title was often inscribed on tombstones.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;Kiefer, Sexual Life in Ancient Rome (Kegan Paul International) 2000:50.&lt;/ref&gt;

==In Abrahamic traditions==
[[File:1-concubine-dore.jpg|thumb|left|upright|''The [[Israelites|Israelite]] discovers his concubine, dead on his doorstep'' – by [[Gustave Doré]]]]

=== In Judaism ===
{{see also|Pilegesh}}
Among the [[Israelites]], men commonly acknowledged their concubines, and such women enjoyed the same rights in the house as legitimate wives.&lt;ref name=&quot;JewEncPil&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=PILEGESH (Hebrew, ; comp. Greek, παλλακίς).|url=http://jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=313&amp;letter=P&amp;search=Pilegesh|encyclopedia=Jewish Encyclopedia|publisher=JewishEncyclopedia.com|accessdate=13 June 2012|author=Staff|year=2002–2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====In ancient Judaism====
The term concubine did not necessarily refer to women after the first wife. A man could have many wives and concubines. Legally, any children born to a concubine was considered to be the child of the wife to whom she was under. [[Sarah]] had to get [[Ishmael]] out of her house because legally Ishmael would always be the first born son even though [[Isaac]] was her natural child.
The concubine may not have commanded the exact amount of respect as the wife. In the [[Levitical]] rules on sexual relations, the Hebrew word that is commonly translated as &quot;wife&quot; is distinct from the Hebrew word that means &quot;concubine&quot;. However, on at least one other occasion the term is used to refer to a woman who is not a wife{{snd}} specifically, the handmaiden of Jacob's wife.&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Genesis|30:4|}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the Levitical code, sexual intercourse between a man and a wife of a different man was forbidden and punishable by death for both persons involved.&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Leviticus|20:10|}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Deuteronomy|22:22|}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since it was regarded as the highest blessing to have many children, wives often gave their maids to their husbands if they were barren, as in the cases of [[Sarah]] and [[Hagar (Bible)|Hagar]], and [[Rachel]] and [[Bilhah]]. The children of the concubine often had equal rights with those of the wife;&lt;ref name=&quot;JewEncPil&quot; /&gt; for example, King [[Abimelech (Judges)|Abimelech]] was the son of [[Gideon]] and his concubine.&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Judges|8:31|}}&lt;/ref&gt; Later biblical figures such as Gideon, and [[Solomon]] had concubines in addition to many childbearing wives. For example, the [[Books of Kings]] say that Solomon had 700 wives and 300 concubines.&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse|1|Kings|11:1–3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Fiddlerandtaborer.png|thumb|Illustration from the [[Morgan Bible]] of the [[Benjamite]]s taking women of [[Shiloh (biblical city)|Shiloh]] as concubines.]]
The account of the unnamed Levite in Judges 19–20&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Judges|19|NRVS}}, {{bibleverse||Judges|20|NRSV}}&lt;/ref&gt; shows that the taking of concubines was not the exclusive preserve of kings or patriarchs in Israel during the time of the Judges, and that the rape of a concubine was completely unacceptable to the Israelite nation and led to a [[civil war]]. In the story, the Levite appears to be an ordinary member of the tribe, whose concubine was a woman from Bethlehem in Judah. This woman was unfaithful, and eventually abandoned him to return to her paternal household. However, after four months, the Levite, referred to as her husband, decided to travel to her father's house to persuade his concubine to return. She is amenable to returning with him, and the father-in-law is very welcoming. The father-in-law convinces the Levite to remain several additional days, until the party leaves behind schedule in the late evening. The group pass up a nearby non-Israelite town to arrive very late in the city of Gibeah, which is in the land of the Benjaminites. The group sit around the town square, waiting for a local to invite them in for the evening, as was the custom for travelers. A local old man invites them to stay in his home, offering them [[guest right]] by washing their feet and offering them food. A band of wicked townsmen attack the house and demand the host send out the Levite man so they can have sex with him. The host offers to send out his virgin daughter as well as the Levite's concubine for them to rape, to avoid breaking guest right towards the Levite. Eventually, to ensure his own safety and that of his host, the Levite gives the men his concubine, who is raped and abused through the night, until she is left collapsed against the front door at dawn. In the morning, the Levite finds her when he tries to leave. When she fails to respond to her husband's order to get up, most likely because she is dead, the Levite places her on his donkey and continues home. Once home, he dismembers her body and distributes the 12 parts throughout the nation of Israel. The Israelites gather to learn why they were sent such grisly gifts, and are told of the sadistic rape of his concubine by the Levite. The crime is considered outrageous by the Israelite tribesmen, who then wreak total retribution on the men of Gibeah, as well as the surrounding tribe of Benjamin when they support the Gibeans, killing them without mercy and burning all their towns. The inhabitants of (the town of) Jabesh Gilead are then slaughtered as a punishment for not joining the eleven tribes in their war against the Benjaminites, and their four hundred unmarried daughters given in [[forced marriage]] to the six hundred Benjamite survivors. Finally, the two hundred Benjaminite survivors who still have no wives are granted a [[raptio|mass marriage by abduction]] by the other tribes.

====In modern Judaism====
In Judaism, concubines are referred to by the Hebrew term [[pilegesh]] ({{lang-he|פילגש}}). The term is a loanword from [[Ancient Greek]] {{lang|grc|παλλακίς}},&lt;ref&gt;Michael Lieb, Milton and the culture of violence, p.274, Cornell University Press, 1994&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Agendas for the study of Midrash in the twenty-first century, Marc Lee Raphael, p.136, Dept. of Religion, College of William and Mary, 1999&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Nicholas Clapp, Sheba: Through the Desert in Search of the Legendary Queen, p.297, Houghton Mifflin, 2002&lt;/ref&gt; meaning &quot;a mistress staying in house&quot;.

According to the [[Talmud|Babylonian Talmud]],&lt;ref name=&quot;JewEncPil&quot; /&gt; the difference between a concubine and a legitimate wife was that the latter received a [[ketubah]] and [[Jewish wedding|her marriage]] (''nissu'in'') was preceded by an [[erusin]] (&quot;formal betrothal&quot;), which was not the case for a concubine.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/articles/12148-pilegesh|title=PILEGESH (Hebrew, ; comp. Greek, παλλακίς).|last=|first=|date=|website=Jewish Virtual Library|url-status=live|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; One opinion in the [[Jerusalem Talmud]] argues that the concubine should also receive a ''marriage contract'', but without a clause specifying a divorce settlement.&lt;ref name=&quot;JewEncPil&quot; /&gt;   According to Rashi, &quot;wives with kiddushin and ketubbah, concubines with kiddushin but without ketubbah&quot;; this reading is from the Jerusalem Talmud,&lt;ref name=&quot;Concubine&quot;/&gt;

Certain Jewish thinkers, such as [[Maimonides]], believed that concubines were strictly reserved for Royal leadership, kings and queens, and thus that a commoner may not have a concubine. Indeed, such thinkers argued that commoners may not engage in any type of [[human sexuality|sexual relations]] outside of a marriage.

Maimonides was not the first Jewish thinker to criticise concubinage. For example, [[Leviticus Rabbah]] severely condemns the custom.&lt;ref&gt;''Leviticus Rabbah'', 25&lt;/ref&gt; Other Jewish thinkers, such as [[Nahmanides]], [[Samuel ben Uri Shraga Phoebus]], and [[Jacob Emden]], strongly objected to the idea that concubines should be forbidden.

In the [[Modern Hebrew|Hebrew]] of the contemporary [[Israel|State of Israel]], ''pilegesh'' is often used as the equivalent of the English word &quot;[[Mistress (lover)|mistress]]&quot;—i.e., the female partner in extramarital relations—regardless of legal recognition. Attempts have been initiated to popularise ''pilegesh'' as a form of premarital, non-marital or extramarital relationship (which, according to the perspective of the enacting person(s), is permitted by [[Halakha|Jewish law]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Kosher sex without marriage |url=http://www.jpost.com/Jewish-World/Jewish-Features/Kosher-sex-without-marriage |newspaper=The Jerusalem Post |date=16 March 2006 |author=Matthew Wagner |accessdate=13 June 2012 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140503230106/http://www.jpost.com/Jewish-World/Jewish-Features/Kosher-sex-without-marriage |archive-date=3 May 2014 |url-status=live |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Adam Dickter, &quot;ISO: Kosher Concubine&quot;, ''New York Jewish Week'', December 2006&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P2-4826676.html Suzanne Glass, &quot;The Concubine Connection&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://archive.li/20130103033314/http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P2-4826676.html |date=3 January 2013 }}, ''The Independent'', London 20 October 1996&lt;/ref&gt;

===In Islam and Arab world===
{{main|Ma malakat aymanukum}}
{{See also|Islamic views on slavery#Sexual intercourse}}
{{POV section|date=August 2014}}
[[File:V.M. Doroshevich-East and War-Harem enhaced.jpg|thumb|[[Harem]], by [[Vlas Doroshevich|Doroshevich]], c. 1905]]
[[File:Jules Laurens 14.jpg|thumb|''Women of the Harem'' by [[Jules Laurens]], circa 1847|alt=Painting of seated women, with man standing]]

Concubinage in [[Islamic sexual jurisprudence]] is permitted in Islam, though some muslim scholars vehemently object to this and reject Concubinage all along,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Message of the Quran|last=Asad|first=Mohammad|publisher=|year=|isbn=|location=|pages=Surah 4:25 [commentary]|quote=This passage lays down in an unequivocal manner that sexual relations with female slaves are permitted only on the basis of marriage, and that in this respect there is no difference between them and free women; consequently, concubinage is ruled out.“}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Quran, translated by Mustafa Islamoğlu|last=|first=|publisher=|year=|isbn=|location=|pages=Surah 23:6, Commentary}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Mohammad Asad: The Message of the Quran, Surah 23:6, [Commentary].|last=|first=|publisher=|year=|isbn=|location=|pages=|quote=Lit., &quot;or those whom their right hands possess&quot; (aw ma malakat aymanuhum). Most of the commentators assume unquestioningly that this relates to female slaves, and that the particle aw (&quot;or&quot;) denotes a permissible alternative. This conventional interpretation is, in my opinion inadmissible inasmuch as it is based on the assumption that sexual intercourse with one's female slave is permitted without marriage: an assumption which is contradicted by the Qur'an itself (see 4:3, {24}, {25} and 24:32, with the corresponding notes). Nor is this the only objection to the above-mentioned interpretation. Since the Qur'an applies the term &quot;believers&quot; to men and women alike, and since the term azwaj (&quot;spouses&quot;), too, denotes both the male and the female partners in marriage, there is no reason for attributing to the phrase aw ma malakat aymanuhum the meaning of &quot;their female slaves&quot;; and since, on the other hand, it is out of the question that female and male slaves could have been referred to here, it is obvious that this phrase does not relate to slaves at all, but has the same meaning as in 4:24- namely, &quot;those whom they rightfully possess through wedlock&quot; (see note [26] on 4:24) - with the significant difference that in the present context this expression relates to both husbands and wives, who &quot;rightfully possess&quot; one another by virtue of marriage. On the basis of this interpretation, the particle aw which precedes this clause does not denote an alternative (&quot;or&quot;) but is, rather, in the nature of an explanatory amplification, more or less analgous to the phrase &quot;in other words&quot; or &quot;that is&quot;, thus giving to the whole sentence the meaning, &quot;...save with their spouses - that is, those whom they rightfully possess [through wedlock]...&quot;, etc. (Cf. a similar construction 25:62 - &quot;for him who has the will to take thought - that is [lit., &quot;or&quot;], has the will to be grateful&quot;.)“}}&lt;/ref&gt; which was not considered prostitution, and was very common during the [[Arab slave trade]] throughout the Middle Ages and [[early modern period]], when women and girls from the [[Caucasus]], [[Africa]], [[Central Asia]] and [[Europe]] were captured and served as [[concubine]]s in the [[harem]]s of the [[Arab World]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/religions/islam/history/slavery_7.shtml|title=BBC – Religions – Islam: Slavery in Islam|accessdate=11 December 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090521234122/http://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/religions/islam/history/slavery_7.shtml|archive-date=21 May 2009|url-status=live|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Ibn Battuta]] tells us several times that he was given or purchased female slaves.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sfusd.k12.ca.us/schwww/sch618/Ibn_Battuta/Slavery.html Insights into the concept of Slavery] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20091122171200/http://www.sfusd.k12.ca.us/schwww/sch618/ibn_battuta/Slavery.html |date=2009-11-22 }}. San Francisco Unified School District.&lt;/ref&gt;

Concubinage is permitted and regulated in Islam. [[Al-Muminun]] 6 and [[Al-Maarij]] 30 both, in identical wording, draw a distinction between spouses and &quot;those whom one's right hands possess&quot; (concubines), saying &quot; أَزْوَاجِهِمْ أَوْ مَا مَلَكَتْ أَيْمَانُهُمْ&quot; (literally, &quot;their spouses or what their right hands possess&quot;), while clarifying that sexual intercourse with either is permissible.  However both these surahs literal wording&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://corpus.quran.com/wordbyword.jsp?chapter=70&amp;verse=30#(70:30:1)|title=Surah Marijj 30|last=|first=|date=|website=|url-status=live|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://corpus.quran.com/wordbyword.jsp?chapter=23&amp;verse=6|title=Surah Muminun 6|last=|first=|date=|website=|url-status=live|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; do not specifically use the term wife but instead the more general &amp; both-gender including term ''spouse'' in the grammatically masculine plural (azwajihim), thus Mohammad Asad in his commentary to both these Surahs rules out concubinage due to the fact that &quot;''since the term azwaj (&quot;spouses&quot;), too, denotes both the male and the female partners in marriage, there is no reason for attributing to the phrase aw ma malakat aymanuhum the meaning of &quot;their female slaves&quot;; and since, on the other hand, it is out of the question that female and male slaves could have been referred to here, it is obvious that this phrase does not relate to slaves at all, but has the same meaning as in 4:24 namely, &quot;those whom they rightfully possess through wedlock&quot; with the significant difference that in the present context this expression relates to both husbands and wives, who &quot;rightfully possess&quot; one another by virtue of marriage''.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Message of the Quran|last=Asad|first=Mohammad|publisher=|year=|isbn=|location=|pages=Surah Muminun, Ayah 6 (See note 3)}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Following this approach, Mohammad Asads translation of the mentioned verses denotes a different picture, which is as follows: &quot;with any but their spouses - that is, those whom they rightfully possess [through wedlock]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Ibid|last=Asad|first=Muhammad|publisher=|year=|isbn=|location=|pages=Surah Muminun ayah 6}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Sayyid [[Abul Ala Maududi]] explains that &quot;two categories of women have been excluded from the general command of guarding the private parts: (a) wives, (b) women who are legally in one's possession&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.translatedquran.com/meaning.asp?pagetitle=AL+-+MUMINOON&amp;sno=23&amp;tno=1324|archiveurl=https://archive.is/20070311085024/http://www.translatedquran.com/meaning.asp?pagetitle=AL+-+MUMINOON&amp;sno=23&amp;tno=1324|url-status=dead|title=Surah – AL – MUMINOON|date=11 March 2007|archivedate=11 March 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;Concubine&quot; (''surriyya'') refers to the female slave (''jāriya''), whether Muslim or non-Muslim, with whom her master engages in sexual intercourse. The word &quot;''surriyya''&quot; is not mentioned in the Qur'an. However, the expression &quot;[[Ma malakat aymanukum]]&quot; (that which your right hands own), which occurs fifteen times in the sacred book, refers to slaves and therefore, though not necessarily, to concubines. Concubinage was a pre-Islamic custom that was allowed to be practiced under Islam with Jews and non-Muslim people to marry concubine after teaching her and instructing her well and then giving them  freedom.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://quranx.com/Hadith/adab/In-Book/Book-9/Hadith-48/ | title=Al-Adab Al-Mufrad / Book-9 / Hadith-48 | publisher=quranx.com | accessdate=7 June 2015 | archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170217062833/http://quranx.com/Hadith/adab/In-Book/Book-9/Hadith-48/ | archive-date=17 February 2017 | url-status=live | df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Rationale given for recognition of concubinage in Islam is that &quot;it satisfied the sexual desire of the female slaves and thereby prevented the spread of immorality in the [[Ummah|Muslim community]].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Sikainga 1996 p22&quot;&gt;{{cite book | author=Sikainga, Ahmad A. | title=Slaves Into Workers: Emancipation and Labor in Colonial Sudan | publisher=University of Texas Press | year=1996 | isbn=0-292-77694-2 | url=https://archive.org/details/slavesintoworker0000sika }} p.22&lt;/ref&gt; Most schools restrict concubinage to a relationship where the female slave is required to be monogamous to her master&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author1=Bloom, Jonathan |author2=Blair, Sheila |title=Islam: A Thousand Years of Faith and Power |publisher=Yale University Press |year=2002 |isbn=0-300-09422-1 |url=https://archive.org/details/isbn_9780300094220 }} p.48&lt;/ref&gt;  (though the master's monogamy to her is not required), but according to Sikainga, &quot;in reality, however, female slaves in many Muslim societies were prey for [male] members of their owners' household, their [owner's male] neighbors, and their [owner's male] guests.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Sikainga 1996 p22&quot;/&gt; 
Concubines were common in [[pre-Islamic Arabia]] and when Islam arrived, it had a society with concubines. Islam introduced legal restrictions to the concubinage&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.islamicstudies.info/quran/maarif/maarif.php?sura=4&amp;verse=22 |title=Maarif ul Quran |access-date=19 November 2015 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20151119191859/http://www.islamicstudies.info/quran/maarif/maarif.php?sura=4&amp;verse=22 |archive-date=19 November 2015 |url-status=live |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; and encouraged manumission.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.islamicstudies.info/quran/maarif/maarif.php?sura=2&amp;verse=177|title=Surah Al-Baqara 2:177-177 – Maariful Quran – Maarif ul Quran – Quran Translation and Commentary|accessdate=11 December 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20151119195319/http://www.islamicstudies.info/quran/maarif/maarif.php?sura=2&amp;verse=177|archive-date=19 November 2015|url-status=live|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; Islam furthermore endorsed educating, freeing and marrying female slaves.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Sahih Bukhari Volume 3, Book 46, Number 724|last=|first=|publisher=|year=|isbn=|location=|pages=|quote=The Prophet said, &quot;He who has a slave-girl and teaches her good manners and improves her education and then manumits and marries her, will get a double reward.}}&lt;/ref&gt; In verse 23:6 in the Quran it is allowed to have sexual intercourse with concubines after marrying them, as Islam forbids sexual intercourse outside of marriage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.astudyofquran.org/web/index.php?id=93,0,0,1,0,0|title=A Study of the Quran – 3. Does the Qur'an permit sex outside marriage with female slaves?|accessdate=11 December 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160911222959/http://astudyofquran.org/web/index.php?id=93,0,0,1,0,0|archive-date=11 September 2016|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Children of former concubines were generally declared as legitimate with or without wedlock, and the mother of a free child was considered free upon the death of the male partner.

According to [[Shia]] Muslims, Muhammad sanctioned [[Nikah mut‘ah]] (fixed-term marriage, called muta'a in [[Iraq]] and [[sigheh]] in [[Iran]]) which has instead been used as a legitimizing cover for sex workers, in a culture where prostitution is otherwise forbidden.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | last = İlkkaracan | first = Pınar | title = Deconstructing sexuality in the Middle East: challenges and discourses | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=pnGwP9-FhxYC&amp;pg=PA36&amp;dq#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false | publisher =Ashgate Publishing, Ltd. | year = 2008 | page = 36  | isbn = 978-0-7546-7235-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some Western writers have argued that mut'ah approximates prostitution.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last = İlkkaracan |first = Pınar |title = Deconstructing sexuality in the Middle East: challenges and discourses |url = https://books.google.com/books?id=pnGwP9-FhxYC&amp;pg=PA36&amp;dq#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false |publisher   =Ashgate Publishing, Ltd. |year = 2008 |page = 36 |isbn= 978-0-7546-7235-7 |url-status = live |archiveurl  = https://web.archive.org/web/20151030194344/https://books.google.com/books?id=pnGwP9-FhxYC&amp;pg=PA36&amp;dq#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false |archivedate = 2015-10-30
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; Julie Parshall writes that mut'ah is legalised prostitution which has been sanctioned by the Twelver Shia authorities. She quotes the Oxford encyclopedia of modern Islamic world to differentiate between marriage (nikah) and Mut'ah, and states that while nikah is for procreation, mut'ah is just for sexual gratification.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title = Lifting the Veil: The World of Muslim Women|url = https://books.google.com/books?id=JKqkohMVPVsC|publisher = InterVarsity Press|date = 1 April 2003|isbn = 9780830856961|language = en|first = Philip L.|last = Parshall|first2 = Julie|last2 = Parshall}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to Zeyno Baran, this kind of temporary marriage provides Shi'ite men with a religiously sanctioned equivalent to prostitution.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title = Citizen Islam: The Future of Muslim Integration in the West|url = https://books.google.com/books?id=hfdGAQAAQBAJ|publisher = A&amp;C Black|date = 21 July 2011|isbn = 9781441112484|language = en|first = Zeyno|last = Baran}}&lt;/ref&gt;  According to Elena Andreeva's observation published in 2007, Russian travellers to Iran consider mut'ah to be &quot;legalized profligacy&quot; which is indistinguishable from prostitution.&lt;ref&gt;Andreeva, Elena (2007). Russia and Iran in the great game: travelogues and Orientalism. Routledge studies in Middle Eastern history. 8. Psychology Press. pp. 162–163. {{ISBN|0415771536}}. &quot;Most of the travelers describe the Shi'i institution of temporary marriage (sigheh) as 'legalized profligacy' and hardly distinguish between temporary marriage and prostitution.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Religious supporters of mut'ah argue that temporary marriage is different from prostitution for a couple of reasons, including the necessity of [[iddah]] in case the couple have sexual intercourse. It means that if a woman marries a man in this way and has sex, she has to wait for a number of months before marrying again and therefore, a woman cannot marry more than 3 or 4 times in a year.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.al-islam.org/shiite-encyclopedia-ahlul-bayt-dilp-team/temporary-marriage-islam-part-6-similarities-and Temporary Marriage in Islam Part 6: Similarities and Differences of Mut’a and Regular Marriage | A Shi'ite Encyclopedia | Books on Islam and Muslims | Al-Islam.org]..&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sistani.org/english/book/48/2350/|title=Marriage » Mut'ah (temporary marriage) – Islamic Laws – The Official Website of the Office of His Eminence Al-Sayyid Ali Al-Husseini Al-Sistani|website=www.sistani.org|access-date=16 February 2018|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180207195026/http://www.sistani.org/english/book/48/2350/|archive-date=7 February 2018|url-status=live|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.al-islam.org/a-summary-of-rulings-makarim-shirazi/rules-matrimony-and-marriage|title=The Rules in Matrimony and Marriage|website=Al-Islam.org|access-date=16 February 2018|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180614195353/https://www.al-islam.org/a-summary-of-rulings-makarim-shirazi/rules-matrimony-and-marriage|archive-date=14 June 2018|url-status=live|df=dmy-all|date=3 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://islam.stackexchange.com/questions/16461/how-is-mutah-different-from-prostitution-from-a-non-muslim-point-of-view|title=How is Mutah different from prostitution (from a non-Muslim point of view)?|website=islam.stackexchange.com|access-date=16 February 2018|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180615004448/https://islam.stackexchange.com/questions/16461/how-is-mutah-different-from-prostitution-from-a-non-muslim-point-of-view|archive-date=15 June 2018|url-status=live|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://english.bayynat.org.lb/QA/1a.htm|title=Marriage|website=english.bayynat.org.lb|access-date=16 February 2018|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180223065313/http://english.bayynat.org.lb/QA/1a.htm|archive-date=23 February 2018|url-status=live|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Pre-modern times====
[[File:A drunken prince assaults a Chinese maiden.Miniature from Gulistan Sa'di. Herat, 1427. Chester Beatty Library, Dublin. f.16r.jpg|thumb|upright|A drunken Persian prince assaults a Chinese maiden. Miniature from [[Gulistan of Sa'di]]. Herat, 1427]]

In ancient times, two sources for concubines were permitted under an Islamic regime. Primarily, non-Muslim women taken as prisoners of war were made concubines as happened after the [[banu Qurayza#Battle of the Trench|Battle of the Trench]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Majlisi, M. B. 1966&quot;&gt;Majlisi, M. B. (1966). Hayat-ul-Qaloob, Volume 2, Translated by Molvi Syed Basharat Hussain Sahib Kamil, Imamia Kutub Khana, Lahore, Pakistan&lt;/ref&gt; or in numerous later Caliphates.&lt;ref&gt;Murat Iyigun, “Lessons From the Ottoman Harem on Culture, Religion &amp; Wars”, University of Colorado, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;
It was encouraged to [[manumit]] slave women who rejected their initial faith and embraced Islam, or to bring them into [[Marriage in Islam|formal marriage]].

====Modern times====
According to the rules of Islamic [[Fiqh]], what is ''halal'' (permitted) by Allah in the Quran cannot be altered by any authority or individual. Therefore, although the ''concept'' of concubinage is ''halal'', concubines are mostly no longer available in this modern era nor allowed to be sold or purchased in accordance with the latest human rights standards.

It is further clarified that all domestic and organizational female employees are not concubines in this era and hence sex is forbidden with them unless Nikah,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nikah.com/marriage/definition_nikah.asp|title=Definition of Nikah (Islamic marriage)|work=nikah.com|accessdate=16 December 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20040806052730/http://www.nikah.com/marriage/definition_nikah.asp|archive-date=6 August 2004|url-status=live|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Nikah mut‘ah]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Mutahhari7&quot;&gt;Motahhari M. [http://www.al-islam.org/rightsofwomeninislam/7.htm &quot;The rights of woman in Islam, fixed-term marriage and the problem of the harem&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120928195343/http://www.al-islam.org/rightsofwomeninislam/7.htm |date=28 September 2012 }}. Al-islam.org website. Accessed 15 March 2014.&lt;/ref&gt; or [[Nikah Misyar]] is committed through the proper channels.

==In the United States==
[[File:Free Woman of Color with daughter NOLA Collage.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Free people of color|Free woman of color]] with [[quadroon]] daughter; late 18th century collage painting, [[New Orleans]].]]

When [[slavery]] became institutionalized in the North American colonies, white men, whether or not they were married, sometimes took enslaved women and men as concubines.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/?id=PQzmjgSObrEC&amp;pg=PA147&amp;dq=u.s.+slavery+concubine#v=onepage&amp;q=u.s.%20slavery%20concubine&amp;f=false|title=Race, Gender, and Work: A Multi-cultural Economic History of Women in the United States|last=Amott|first=Teresa L.|last2=Matthaei|first2=Julie A.|date=1996|publisher=South End Press|isbn=9780896085374|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; Marriage between the races was prohibited by law in the colonies and the later United States. Many colonies and states also had laws against [[miscegenation]], or any interracial relations. From 1662 the Colony of Virginia, followed by others, incorporated into law the principle that children took their mother's status, i.e., the principle of ''[[partus sequitur ventrem]]''. All children born to enslaved mothers were born into slavery, regardless of their father's status or ancestry.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kolchin17&quot;&gt;[[Peter Kolchin]], ''American Slavery, 1619–1877'', New York: Hill and Wang, 1993, p. 17&lt;/ref&gt; This led to generations of [[multiracial]] slaves, some of whom were otherwise considered legally white (one-eighth or less African, equivalent to a great-grandparent) before the [[American Civil War]].

In some cases, men had long-term relationships with enslaved women, giving them and their mixed-race children freedom and providing their children with apprenticeships, education and transfer of capital.  A [[Jefferson–Hemings controversy|relationship]] between [[Thomas Jefferson]] and [[Sally Hemings]] is an example of this.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hemings&quot;&gt;[http://www.monticello.org/plantation/hemingscontro/hemings-jefferson_contro.html &quot;Thomas Jefferson and Sally Hemings: A Brief Account&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100430175449/http://www.monticello.org/plantation/hemingscontro/hemings-jefferson_contro.html |date=30 April 2010 }}, Monticello Website, Thomas Jefferson Foundation. Retrieved 22 June 2011. Quote: &quot;Ten years later [referring to its 2000 report], TJF and most historians now believe that, years after his wife's death, Thomas Jefferson was the father of the six children of Sally Hemings mentioned in Jefferson's records, including Beverly, Harriet, Madison and Eston Hemings ... Since then, a committee commissioned by the Thomas Jefferson Heritage Society, after reviewing essentially the same material, reached different conclusions, namely that Sally Hemings was only a minor figure in Thomas Jefferson's life and that it is very unlikely he fathered any of her children. This committee also suggested in its report, issued in April 2001 and revised in 2011, that Jefferson's younger brother Randolph (1755–1815) was more likely the father of at least some of Sally Hemings's children.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;   Such arrangements were more prevalent in the [[Southern United States|Southern states]] during the antebellum years.

===Plaçage===

{{main|Plaçage}}
In [[Louisiana (New France)|Louisiana]] and former French territories, a formalized system of concubinage called ''plaçage'' developed. European men took enslaved or [[free people of color|free women of color]] as mistresses after making arrangements to give them a dowry, house or other transfer of property, and sometimes, if they were enslaved, offering freedom and education for their children.&lt;ref name=&quot;everyculture.com&quot;&gt;[http://www.everyculture.com/multi/Bu-Dr/Creoles.html Helen Bush Caver and Mary T. Williams, &quot;Creoles&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110813013942/http://www.everyculture.com/multi/Bu-Dr/Creoles.html |date=13 August 2011 }}, ''Multicultural America'', Countries and Their Cultures Website. Retrieved 3 Feb 2009&lt;/ref&gt; A third class of [[free people of color]] developed, especially in [[New Orleans]].&lt;ref name=&quot;everyculture.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Peter Kolchin, ''American Slavery, 1619–1865'', New York: Hill and Wang, 1993, pp. 82–83&lt;/ref&gt; Many became educated, artisans and property owners. French-speaking and practicing [[Catholicism]], these women combined French and African-American culture and created an elite between those of European descent and the slaves.&lt;ref name=&quot;everyculture.com&quot;/&gt; Today, descendants of the free people of color are generally called [[Louisiana Creole people]].&lt;ref name=&quot;everyculture.com&quot;/&gt;

==See also==
{{Div col|colwidth=25em}}
* [[Concubinage in Canada]]
* [[Cicisbeo]]
* [[Cohabitation]]
* [[Common-law marriage]]
* [[Courtesan]]
* [[Cullagium]]
* [[Cuckquean]]
* [[Free union]]
* [[Harem]]
* [[Monogamy in Christianity]]
* [[Morganatic marriage]]
* [[Extramarital sex|Paramour]]
* [[Polygamy]]
* [[Polyamory]]
* [[Polygyny]]
* [[Slavery in the United States]]
{{Div col end}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
{{Wiktionary|concubinage|concubine}}
* {{Wikisource-inline}}
* {{commonscatinline|Concubines}}
* [http://anti-slaverysociety.addr.com/concubinage.htm Servile Concubinage]

{{Types of marriages|state=autocollapse}}
{{Interpersonal relationships footer}}
{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Concubinage| ]]
[[Category:Heterosexuality]]
[[Category:Polygyny]]</text>
      <sha1>k5mk0h7cwlvt1nsistcuy9vkaix0e4n</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
