  <page>
    <title>History of the Cook Islands</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7068</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943038616</id>
      <parentid>917087432</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-28T13:02:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>58.96.113.112</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* added the arrival of the native people</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[Image:Patepou.jpg|thumb|Pa te Pou Ariki, Chief of the Takitumu tribe, [[Rarotonga]] (c. 1837)]]

The '''[[Cook Islands]]''' are named after [[James Cook|Captain James Cook]], who visited the islands in 1773 and 1777.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Cook : the Extraordinary voyages of Captain James Cook|date=2003|author=Nicholas Thomas|pages=310–311}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Cook Islands]] became a British [[protectorate]] in 1888.

By 1900, the islands were annexed as British territory. In 1901, the islands were included within the boundaries of the [[Colony of New Zealand]].

The Cook Islands contain 15 islands in the group spread over a vast area in the [[Oceania|South Pacific]]. The majority of islands are low coral atolls in the Northern Group, with [[Rarotonga]], a volcanic island in the Southern Group, as the main administration and government centre. The main Cook Islands language is [[Cook Islands Maori|Rarotongan Māori]]. There are some variations in dialect in the 'outer' islands.

==Early settlers of the Cooks ==
It is thought that the Cook Islands may have been settled between the years 900-1200 AD. Early settlements suggest that the settlers were generally great warriors{{peacock term|date=September 2019}} migrating from [[Tahiti]], to the northeast of the Cooks. The Cook Islands continue to hold important connections with Tahiti, and this is generally found in the two countries' culture, tradition and language. It is also thought that the early settlers were true Tahitians, who landed in [[Rarotonga]] ([[Tākitimu#Cook Islands Māori traditions|Takitumu]] city). There are notable historic epics of great warriors who travel between the two nations for a wide variety of reasons. The purpose of these missions is still unclear but recent research indicates that large to small groups often fled their island due to local wars being forced upon them. For each group to travel and to survive, they would normally rely on a warrior to lead them. Outstanding warriors are still mentioned in the countries' traditions and stories.

These arrivals are evidenced by an older road in Toi, the ''Ara Metua'', which runs around most of Rarotonga, and is believed to be at least 1200 years old. This 29&amp;nbsp;km long, paved road is a considerable achievement of ancient engineering, possibly unsurpassed elsewhere in Polynesia.&lt;ref name=&quot;wondermondo&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.wondermondo.com/Countries/Au/NZ/Cook/AraMetua.htm|title=Ara Metua - ancient Polynesian road|publisher=Wondermondo}}&lt;/ref&gt; The islands of [[Manihiki]] and [[Rakahanga]] trace their origins to the arrival of Toa, an outcast from Rarotonga, and Tupaeru, a high-ranking woman from the Puaikura tribe of Rarotonga. The remainder of the northern islands were probably settled by expeditions from [[Samoa]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ck/history.htm#pre|title=History of the Cook Islands: Pre-European|publisher=www.ck}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.lonelyplanet.com/rarotonga-and-the-cook-islands/history#269025 |title=History of Rarotonga &amp; the Cook Islands: Polynesian settlement|publisher=Lonely Planet}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early European contact==
[[Spain|Spanish]] ships visited the islands in the 16th century; the first written record of contact between Europeans and the native inhabitants of the Cook Islands came with the sighting of [[Pukapuka]] by Spanish sailor [[Álvaro de Mendaña]] in 1595, who called it ''San Bernardo'' (Saint Bernard). Portuguese-Spaniard [[Pedro Fernández de Quirós]] made the first recorded European landing in the islands when he set foot on [[Rakahanga]] in 1606, calling it ''Gente Hermosa'' (Beautiful People).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ck/rakahang.htm|title=Rakahanga - Island of Beautiful People|publisher=www.ck}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lonelyplanet.com/rarotonga-and-the-cook-islands/history#269027|title=History of Rarotonga &amp; the Cook Islands: European explorers|publisher=Lonely Planet}}&lt;/ref&gt;

British navigator Captain [[James Cook]] arrived in 1773 and 1777. Cook named the islands the '[[Augustus Hervey, 3rd Earl of Bristol|Hervey]] Islands' to honour a British Lord of the [[Board of Admiralty|Admiralty]]. Half a century later, the Russian [[Baltic Germans|Baltic German]] Admiral [[Adam Johann von Krusenstern]] published the ''Atlas de l'Ocean Pacifique'', in which he renamed the islands the Cook Islands to honour Cook. [[Captain Cook]] navigated and mapped much of the group. Surprisingly, Cook never sighted the largest island, [[Rarotonga]], and the only island that he personally set foot on was the tiny, uninhabited [[Palmerston Island|Palmerston Atoll]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Lonely Planet Guidebook : Rarotonga &amp; the Cook Islands|author=Errol Hunt &amp; Nancy J. Keller|pages=10–11|ISBN=1-74059-083-X}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The first recorded landing by Europeans was in 1814 by the ''[[HMS Cumberland (1807)|Cumberland]]''; trouble broke out between the sailors and the Islanders and many were killed on both sides.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author=Errol Hunt | date=2003 | title=Rarotonga &amp; the Cook Islands | page=63 |publisher=Lonely Planet | isbn=1-74059-083-X }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The islands saw no more Europeans until missionaries arrived from England in 1821. Christianity quickly took hold in the culture and remains the predominant religion today.

In 1823, [[Captain John Dibbs]] of the colonial barque ''Endeavour'' made the first official sighting of the island [[Rarotonga]]. The ''Endeavour'' was transporting Rev. [[John Williams (missionary)|John Williams]] on a missionary voyage to the islands.

Brutal [[Peruvian]] [[slave traders]], known as [[blackbirding|blackbirders]], took a terrible toll on the islands of the Northern Group in 1862 and 1863. At first, the traders may have genuinely operated as labour recruiters, but they quickly turned to subterfuge and outright kidnapping to round up their human cargo. The [[Cook Islands]] was not the only island group visited by the traders, but [[Penrhyn Island|Penrhyn Atoll]] was their first port of call and it has been estimated that three-quarters of the population was taken to [[Callao]], [[Peru]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Discoverers Of The Cook Islands And The Names They Gave|url=http://nzetc.victoria.ac.nz/tm/scholarly/tei-KloDisc-t1-body-d10.html|date=1976|author=Alphons M.J. Kloosterman|pages=34–35}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Rakahanga]] and [[Pukapuka]] also suffered tremendous losses.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Lonely Planet Guidebook : Rarotonga &amp; the Cook Islands|author=Errol Hunt &amp; Nancy J. Keller|pages=11–12|ISBN=1-74059-083-X}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==British protectorate==

The Cook Islands became a British [[protectorate]] in 1888, due largely to community fears that France might occupy the territory as it had Tahiti. On 6 September 1900, the leading islanders presented a petition asking that the islands (including [[Niue]] &quot;if possible&quot;) should be annexed as British territory.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kenneth Roberts-Wray 1966. P. 891&quot;&gt;''&quot;Commonwealth and Colonial Law&quot;'' by Kenneth Roberts-Wray, London, Stevens, 1966. p. 891&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;N.Z. Parliamentary Pp., A3 (1901)&lt;/ref&gt; On 8–9 October 1900, seven instruments of cession of Rarotonga and other islands were signed by their chiefs and people, and a British proclamation issued at the same time accepted the cessions, the islands being declared parts of Her Britannic Majesty's dominions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kenneth Roberts-Wray 1966. P. 891&quot;/&gt; These instruments did not include [[Aitutaki]]. It appears that, though the inhabitants regarded themselves as British subjects, the Crown's title was uncertain, and the island was formally annexed by Proclamation dated 9 October 1900.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;''Commonwealth and Colonial Law''&quot; by Kenneth Roberts-Wray, London, Stevens, 1966. p. 761&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;N.Z. Parliamentary Pp., A1 (1900)&lt;/ref&gt; The islands were included within the boundaries of the [[Colony of New Zealand]] in 1901 by Order in Council&lt;ref&gt;S.R.O. &amp; S.I. Rev. XVI, 862-863&lt;/ref&gt; under the Colonial Boundaries Act, 1895 of the United Kingdom.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kenneth Roberts-Wray 1966. P. 891&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;58 &amp; 59 V. c. 34.&lt;/ref&gt; The boundary change became effective on 11 June 1901, and the Cook Islands have had a formal relationship with New Zealand since that time.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kenneth Roberts-Wray 1966. P. 891&quot;/&gt;

==Recent history==

The islands remained a New Zealand dependent territory until 1965, at which point they became a [[self-government|self-governing]] territory in [[Associated state|free association]] with New Zealand. The first Prime Minister [[Albert Henry (politician)|Albert Henry]] led the country until 1978 when he was accused of [[vote-rigging]]. Since 1965, the Cook Islands have been essentially independent (self-governing in free association with New Zealand), but remained officially placed under New Zealand [[sovereignty]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfai.gov.ck/attachments/068_WELLINGTON-1129712-v1-CookIslands%20%20Constitutional%20Status%20and%20International%20Personality%20%20informationpaper.pdf |title= Cook Islands: Constitutional Status and International Personality |publisher=www.mfai.gov.ck |access-date=11 February 2015 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160304000423/http://www.mfai.gov.ck/attachments/068_WELLINGTON-1129712-v1-CookIslands%20%20Constitutional%20Status%20and%20International%20Personality%20%20informationpaper.pdf |archivedate=4 March 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt; New Zealand is tasked with overseeing the country's foreign relations and defense. The Cook Islands, [[Niue]], and New Zealand (with its territories: [[Tokelau]] and the [[Ross Dependency]]) make up the [[Realm of New Zealand]].

After achieving autonomy in 1965, the Cook Islands elected [[Albert Henry (politician)|Albert Henry]] of the [[Cook Islands Party]] as their first [[Prime Minister]]. He was succeeded in 1978 by [[Tom Davis (Cook Islands)|Tom Davis]] of the [[Democratic Party (Cook Islands)|Democratic Party]].

On 11 June 1980, the [[United States]] signed [[Cook Islands – United States Maritime Boundary Treaty|a treaty]] with the Cook Islands specifying the maritime [[border]] between the Cook Islands and [[American Samoa]] and also relinquishing the US claim to the islands of [[Penrhyn Island|Penrhyn]], [[Pukapuka]], [[Manihiki]], and [[Rakahanga]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.paclii.org/pits/en/treaty_database/1980/6.html|title=Treaty Between the United States of America and the Cook Islands on Friendship and Delimitation of the Maritime Boundary Between the United States of America and the Cook Islands (and Exchange of Notes)|work=Pacific Islands Treaty Series|publisher=University of the South Pacific School of Law|accessdate=2009-05-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1990, the Cook Islands signed [[Cook Islands – France Maritime Delimitation Agreement|a treaty]] with [[France]] which [[boundary delimitation|delimited]] the [[maritime boundary]] between the Cook Islands and [[French Polynesia]].

On June 13, 2008, a small majority of members of the [[House of Ariki]] attempted a coup, claiming to dissolve the elected government and to take control of the country's leadership. &quot;Basically we are dissolving the leadership, the prime minister and the deputy prime minister and the ministers,&quot; chief Makea Vakatini Joseph Ariki explained. The ''Cook Islands Herald'' suggested that the ''[[ariki]]'' were attempting thereby to regain some of their traditional prestige or ''[[mana]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;TVNZ_1845025&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://tvnz.co.nz/view/page/536641/1845025 |title=Cooks heading for internal strife |date=June 13, 2008 |work=[[Television New Zealand]] |accessdate=October 3, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.stuff.co.nz/4583560a12.html |title=NZ Maori stirs Cooks sovereignty stoush |date=June 13, 2008 |work=[[Stuff.co.nz]] |accessdate=October 3, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Prime Minister [[Jim Marurai]] described the take-over move as &quot;ill-founded and nonsensical&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.stuff.co.nz/stuff/4587067a12.html |title=NZ Maori behind strange Cook's 'coup' |date=June 17, 2008 |work=[[Stuff.co.nz]] |accessdate=October 3, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; By June 23, the situation appeared to have normalised, with members of the House of Ariki accepting to return to their regular duties.&lt;ref name=&quot;RNZI_40504&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.rnzi.com/pages/news.php?op=read&amp;id=40504 |title=Cook Islands chiefs drop take over claim, return to normal duties |date=June 23, 2008 |work=[[Radio New Zealand International]] |accessdate=October 3, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Gallery==
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Rarotonga Island Council 1923-1925.jpg|&lt;center&gt;Rarotonga Island Council (1923–1925)&lt;/center&gt;
File:Flag of Rarotonga 1888-1893.svg|&lt;center&gt;The Kingdom of Rarotonga flag (1888–1893)&lt;/center&gt; 
File:Rarotongan monarchs with Seddon 1900.jpg|&lt;center&gt;Ngamaru Rongotini Ariki, Mrs Seddon, [[Makea Takau Ariki]], [[Richard Seddon|Mr Seddon]] (1900)&lt;/center&gt;
File:Makeapalace.jpg|&lt;center&gt;Queen Makea's Palace &amp; Makea's Summer Cottage (1908)&lt;/center&gt;
File:Arikiraro.jpg|&lt;center&gt;[[Pa Maretu Ariki]], [[Makea Takau Ariki]], [[Charles H. Mills]], [[Tinomana Mereana Ariki]] (1903)&lt;/center&gt;
File:Ngamaru.jpg|&lt;center&gt;Prince Ngamaru the Ariki of Atiu (1885)&lt;/center&gt;
File:Makea Karika Tavaki with Ngati Karaka elders.jpg|&lt;center&gt;Makea Karika Tavake Ariki and elders of the Karika tribe, Rarotonga (1888–1910)&lt;/center&gt;
File:Makeapori.jpg|&lt;center&gt;[[Makea Pori Ariki]], Chief of Te-au-o-{{sic|hide=y|tonga}}, Rarotonga (1837)&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Timeline==

'''900 ''' - first People arrive to the islands 

'''1595''' — Spaniard [[Álvaro de Mendaña de Neira]] is the first European to sight the islands.

'''1606''' — Portuguese-Spaniard [[Pedro Fernández de Quirós]] makes the first recorded European landing in the islands when he sets foot on Rakahanga.

'''1773''' — [[Captain (Royal Navy)|Captain]] [[James Cook]] explores the islands and names them the Hervey Islands. Fifty years later they are renamed in his honour by Russian [[Admiral]] [[Adam Johann von Krusenstern]].

'''1821''' — English and Tahitian missionaries land in [[Aitutaki]], become the first non-Polynesian settlers.

'''1823''' — English missionary [[John Williams (missionary)|John Williams]] lands in Rarotonga, converting [[Makea Pori Ariki]] to Christianity.

'''1858''' — The Cook Islands become united as a state, the [[Kingdom of Rarotonga]].

'''1862''' — [[Peruvian]] [[slave traders]] take a terrible toll on the islands of [[Penrhyn Island|Penrhyn]], [[Rakahanga]] and [[Pukapuka]] in 1862 and 1863.

'''1888''' — Cook Islands are proclaimed a British protectorate and a single federal parliament is established.

'''1900''' — The Cook Islands are ceded to the United Kingdom as British territory, except for [[Aitutaki]] which was annexed by the United Kingdom at the same time.

'''1901''' — The boundaries of the [[Colony of New Zealand]] are extended by the United Kingdom to include the Cook Islands.

'''1924''' — The [[New Zealand national rugby union team|All Black]] ''Invincibles'' stop in Rarotonga on their way to the United Kingdom and play a friendly match against a scratch Rarotongan team.

'''1946''' — Legislative Council is established. For the first time since 1912, the territory has direct representation.

'''1957''' — Legislative Council is reorganized as the Legislative Assembly.

'''1965''' — The Cook Islands become a self-governing territory in free association with New Zealand. [[Albert Henry (politician)|Albert Henry]], leader of the [[Cook Islands Party]], is elected as the territory's first prime minister.

'''1974''' — Albert Henry is knighted by Queen Elizabeth II

'''1979''' — Sir [[Albert Henry (politician)|Albert Henry]] is found guilty of electoral fraud and stripped of his premiership and his knighthood. [[Tom Davis (Cook Islands)|Tom Davis]] becomes Premier.

'''1980''' — [[Cook Islands – United States Maritime Boundary Treaty]] establishes the Cook Islands – [[American Samoa]] boundary

'''1981''' — Constitution is amended. Legislative Assembly is renamed Parliament, which grows from 22 to 24 seats, and the parliamentary term is extended from four to five years. Tom Davis is knighted.

'''1984''' — The country's first coalition government, between Sir Thomas and Geoffrey Henry, is signed in the lead up to hosting regional Mini Games in 1985. Shifting coalitions saw ten years of political instability. At one stage, all but two MPs were in government.

'''1985''' — [[Rarotonga Treaty]] is opened for signing in the Cook Islands, creating a nuclear-free zone in the South Pacific.

'''1986''' — In January 1986, following the rift between New Zealand and the USA in respect of the ANZUS security arrangements Prime Minister Tom Davis declared the Cook Islands a neutral country, because he considered that New Zealand (which has control over the islands' defence and foreign policy) was no longer in a position to defend the islands. The proclamation of neutrality meant that the Cook Islands would not enter into a military relationship with any foreign power, and, in particular, would prohibit visits by US warships. Visits by US naval vessels were allowed to resume by Henry's Government.

'''1990''' — [[Cook Islands – France Maritime Delimitation Agreement]] establishes the Cook Islands–French Polynesia boundary

'''1991''' — The Cook Islands signed a treaty of friendship and co-operation with France, covering economic development, trade and surveillance of the islands' EEZ. The establishment of closer relations with France was widely regarded as an expression of the Cook Islands' Government's dissatisfaction with existing arrangements with New Zealand which was no longer in a position to defend the Cook Islands.

'''1995''' — The French Government resumed its programme of nuclear-weapons testing at [[Moruroa|Mururoa Atoll]] in September 1995 upsetting the Cook Islands. New Prime Minister [[Geoffrey Henry]] was fiercely critical of the decision and dispatched a ''vaka'' (traditional voyaging canoe) with a crew of Cook Islands' traditional warriors to protest near the test site. The tests were concluded in January 1996 and a moratorium was placed on future testing by the French government.

'''1997''' — Full diplomatic relations established with the People's Republic of China.

'''1997''' — In November, [[Cyclone Martin]] in Manihiki kills at least six people; 80% of buildings are damaged and the black pearl industry suffered severe losses.

'''1999''' — A second era of political instability begins, starting with five different coalitions in less than nine months, and at least as many since then.

'''2000''' — Full diplomatic relations concluded with France.

'''2002''' — Prime Minister [[Terepai Maoate]] is ousted from government following second vote of no-confidence in his leadership.

'''2004''' — Prime Minister [[Robert Woonton]] visits China; Chinese Premier [[Wen Jiabao]] grants $16 million in development aid.

'''2006''' — [[2006 Cook Islands general election|Parliamentary elections]] held. The Democratic Party keeps majority of seats in parliament, but is unable to command a majority for confidence, forcing a coalition with breakaway MPs who left, then rejoined the &quot;Demos&quot;.

'''2008''' — Pacific Island nations imposed a series of measures aimed at halting overfishing.

==See also==
{{commons category}}
*[[Cook Islands mythology]]
*[[Postage stamps and postal history of the Cook Islands]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

{{History of Oceania}}
{{Territories of the British Empire}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:History Of The Cook Islands}}
[[Category:History of the Cook Islands| ]]</text>
      <sha1>6w0mhrlc97nkm5fj8zoudk6mstinh4i</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
