  <page>
    <title>Jean-Baptiste-Siméon Chardin</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7019</id>
    <revision>
      <id>925759287</id>
      <parentid>925624114</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-11-12T03:54:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ewulp</username>
        <id>998182</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>egad, rv</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|18th-century French painter}}
{{Expand French|Jean Siméon Chardin|fa=yes|topic=cult|date=April 2015}}
[[Image:Chardin pastel selfportrait.jpg|thumb|185px|''Self-portrait'', 1771, [[pastel]], [[Musée du Louvre]], Paris]]

'''Jean-Baptiste-Siméon Chardin''' ({{IPA-fr|ʃaʁdɛ̃|lang}}; November 2, 1699&amp;nbsp;– December 6, 1779&lt;ref&gt;{{Britannica|106359}}&lt;/ref&gt;) was an 18th-century [[France|French]] [[List of painters|painter]]. He is considered a master of [[still life]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.artchive.com/artchive/C/chardin.html|title=Jean Baptiste Simeon Chardin|work=artchive.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; and is also noted for his [[genre works|genre]] paintings which depict kitchen maids, children, and domestic activities.  Carefully balanced composition, soft diffusion of light, and granular [[impasto]] characterize his work.

==Life==
Chardin was born in [[Paris]], the son of a cabinetmaker, and rarely left the city. He lived on the [[Left Bank]] near [[Église Saint-Sulpice, Paris|Saint-Sulpice]] until 1757, when [[Louis XV]] granted him a studio and living quarters in the [[Louvre]].&lt;ref name=&quot;metmuseum1&quot;/&gt;

Chardin entered into a marriage contract with Marguerite Saintard in 1723, whom he did not marry until 1731.&lt;ref name=rosenberg179&gt;Rosenberg p. 179.&lt;/ref&gt; He served apprenticeships with the history painters [[Pierre-Jacques Cazes]] and [[Noël-Nicolas Coypel]], and in 1724 became a master in the [[Académie de Saint-Luc]].

[[Image:Jean-Baptiste Siméon Chardin 007.jpg|thumb|left|''[[The Ray (painting)|The Ray]]'', 1728, [[Musée du Louvre]], Paris]]

According to one nineteenth-century writer, at a time when it was hard for unknown painters to come to the attention of the Royal Academy, he first found notice by displaying a painting at the &quot;small Corpus Christi&quot; (held eight days after the regular one) on the [[Place Dauphine]] (by the [[Pont Neuf]]). [[Jean-Baptiste van Loo|Van Loo]], passing by in 1720, bought it and later assisted the young painter.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://books.google.com/books?dq=intitle:Pont-neuf+inauthor&amp;q=Chardin&amp;pg=PA300&amp;id=w3jG6Xy1rHUC#v=snippet&amp;q=Chardin&amp;f=false|title=Histoire du Pont-Neuf|work=google.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Upon presentation of ''[[The Ray (painting)|The Ray]]'' in 1728, he was admitted to the Académie Royale de Peinture et de Sculpture. The following year he ceded his position in the Académie de Saint-Luc. He made a modest living by &quot;produc[ing] paintings in the various genres at whatever price his customers chose to pay him&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;Rosenberg56&quot;&gt;Rosenberg and Bruyant, p. 56.&lt;/ref&gt; and by such work as the restoration of the [[fresco]]es at the Galerie François I at [[Fontainebleau]] in 1731.&lt;ref&gt;Rosenberg and Bruyant, p. 20.&lt;/ref&gt;
In November 1731 his son Jean-Pierre was baptized, and a daughter, Marguerite-Agnès, was baptized in 1733. In 1735 his wife Marguerite died, and within two years Marguerite-Agnès had died as well.&lt;ref name=rosenberg179/&gt;

[[Image:Jean Siméon Chardin - Retrato de Auguste Gabriel Godefroy.jpg|thumb| ''[[Boy with a Spinning-Top]]'', c. 1735, oil on canvas, [[São Paulo Museum of Art]]]]

Beginning in 1737 Chardin exhibited regularly at the [[Salon (Paris)|Salon]]. He would prove to be a &quot;dedicated academician&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;metmuseum1&quot;&gt;http://www.metmuseum.org/special/Chardin/chardin_more.htm&lt;/ref&gt; regularly attending meetings for fifty years, and functioning successively as counsellor, treasurer, and secretary, overseeing in 1761 the installation of Salon exhibitions.&lt;ref&gt;Rosenberg and Bruyant, p. 23.&lt;/ref&gt;

Chardin's work gained popularity through reproductive engravings of his [[genre works|genre]] paintings (made by artists such as [[François-Bernard Lépicié]] and P.-L. Sugurue), which brought Chardin income in the form of &quot;what would now be called royalties&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Rosenberg and Bruyant, p. 32.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1744 he entered his second marriage, this time to Françoise-Marguerite Pouget. The union brought a substantial improvement in Chardin's financial circumstances. In 1745 a daughter, Angélique-Françoise, was born, but she died in 1746.

In 1752 Chardin was granted a pension of 500 [[livres]] by Louis XV. At the Salon of 1759 he exhibited nine paintings; it was the first Salon to be commented upon by [[Denis Diderot]], who would prove to be a great admirer and public champion of Chardin's work.&lt;ref&gt;Rosenberg, p.182.&lt;/ref&gt; Beginning in 1761, his responsibilities on behalf of the Salon, simultaneously arranging the exhibitions and acting as treasurer, resulted in a diminution of productivity in painting, and the showing of 'replicas' of previous works.&lt;ref name=&quot;rosenberg183&quot;&gt;Rosenberg, p.183.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1763 his services to the Académie were acknowledged with an extra 200 livres in pension. In 1765 he was unanimously elected associate member of the Académie des Sciences, Belles-Lettres et Arts of Rouen, but there is no evidence that he left Paris to accept the honor.&lt;ref name=&quot;rosenberg183&quot;/&gt; By 1770 Chardin was the 'Premier peintre du roi', and his pension of 1,400 livres was the highest in the Academy.&lt;ref name=&quot;rosenberg184&quot;&gt;Rosenberg, p.184.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1772 Chardin's son, also a painter, drowned in [[Venice]], a probable suicide.&lt;ref name=&quot;rosenberg184&quot;/&gt; The artist's last known oil painting was dated 1776; his final Salon participation was in 1779, and featured several pastel studies. Gravely ill by November of that year, he died in Paris on December 6, at the age of 80.

==Work==
[[Image:Jean-Baptiste Siméon Chardin 017.jpg|thumb|left|upright|''[[The Kitchen Maid (Chardin)|Woman Cleaning Turnips]]'', ca. 1738, [[Alte Pinakothek]]]]

Chardin worked very slowly and painted only slightly more than 200 pictures (about four a year) in total.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Morris, Roderick Conway|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2010/12/23/arts/23iht-chardin23.html|title=Chardin's Enchanting and Ageless Moments|date=December 22, 2010|work=The New York Times|accessdate=December 24, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Chardin's work had little in common with the [[Rococo painting]] that dominated French art in the 18th century. At a time when history painting was considered the supreme classification for public art, Chardin's subjects of choice were viewed as minor categories.&lt;ref name=&quot;metmuseum1&quot;/&gt; He favored simple yet beautifully textured still lifes, and sensitively handled domestic interiors and [[Genre works|genre paintings]].  Simple, even stark, paintings of common household items (''Still Life with a Smoker's Box'') and an uncanny ability to portray children's innocence in an unsentimental manner (''Boy with a Top'' [right]) nevertheless found an appreciative audience in his time, and account for his timeless appeal.
[[File:Jean-Siméon Chardin, Boy Building a House of Cards, 1735 at Waddesdon Manor.jpg|thumb|220x220px|Jean-Siméon Chardin, ''Le Faiseur de Châteaux de Cartes'' (Boy Building a House of Cards), 1735 at [[Waddesdon Manor]]]]
Largely self-taught, Chardin was greatly influenced by the realism and subject matter of the 17th-century [[Low Countries|Low Country]] masters. Despite his unconventional portrayal of the ascendant [[bourgeoisie]], early support came from patrons in the French [[aristocracy]], including Louis XV. Though his popularity rested initially on paintings of animals and fruit, by the 1730s he introduced kitchen utensils into his work (''The Copper Cistern'', ca. 1735, Louvre). Soon figures populated his scenes as well, supposedly in response to a portrait painter who challenged him to take up the genre.&lt;ref&gt;Rosenberg, p. 71.&lt;/ref&gt;  ''Woman Sealing a Letter'' (ca. 1733), which  may have been his first attempt,&lt;ref&gt;Rosenberg and Bruyant, p. 190.&lt;/ref&gt; was followed by half-length compositions of children saying grace, as in ''[[Le Bénédicité]]'', and kitchen maids in moments of reflection. These humble scenes deal with simple, everyday activities, yet they also have functioned as a source of documentary information about a level of French society not hitherto considered a worthy subject for painting.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.museothyssen.org/thyssen_ing/coleccion/obras_ficha_biografia_print207.html# Chardin at the Museo Thyssen-Bornemisza] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070927021648/http://www.museothyssen.org/thyssen_ing/coleccion/obras_ficha_biografia_print207.html |date=2007-09-27 }} Retrieved 15 July 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; The pictures are noteworthy for their formal structure and pictorial harmony.&lt;ref name=&quot;metmuseum1&quot; /&gt; Chardin said about painting, &quot;Who said one paints with colors? One ''employs'' colors, but one paints with ''feeling''.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Johnson, Paul. ''Art: A New History'', Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson, 2003, p. 414.&lt;/ref&gt;

A child playing was a favourite subject of Chardin. He depicted an adolescent building a house of cards on at least four occasions.  The version at [[Waddesdon Manor]] is the most elaborate.  Scenes such as these derived from 17th-century Netherlandish vanitas works, which bore messages about the transitory nature of human life and the worthlessness of material ambitions, but Chardin's also display a delight in the ephemeral phases of childhood for their own sake.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://waddesdon.org.uk/the-collection/search/?search=Chardin|title=Search Results|last=|first=|date=|website=collection.waddesdon.org.uk|language=en|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=2017-04-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Jean-Baptiste Siméon Chardin 029.jpg|thumb|left|upright|''Still Life with Glass Flask and Fruit'', c.1728 (note reflected light on glass/silver)]]

Chardin frequently painted replicas of his compositions—especially his genre paintings, nearly all of which exist in multiple versions which in many cases are virtually indistinguishable.&lt;ref&gt;Rosenberg and Bruyant, pp. 68–70.&lt;/ref&gt; Beginning with ''The Governess'' (1739, in the [[National Gallery of Canada]], [[Ottawa]]), Chardin shifted his attention from  working-class subjects to slightly more spacious scenes of bourgeois life.&lt;ref&gt;Rosenberg and Bruyant, pp. 187 and 242.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1756 Chardin returned to the subject of the still life. In the 1770s his eyesight weakened and he took to painting in [[pastels]], a medium in which he executed portraits of his wife and himself (see ''Self-portrait'' at top right). His works in pastels are now highly valued.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ibiblio.org/wm/paint/auth/chardin/|title=WebMuseum: Chardin, Jean-Baptiste-Siméon|work=ibiblio.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; Chardin's extant paintings, which number about 200,&lt;ref name=&quot;Rosenberg56&quot; /&gt; are in many major museums, including the [[Louvre]].

==Influence==
[[File:Souvenir MET DP169562.jpg | thumb|right | Enameled  box and other objects painted after the style of Chardin]]
Chardin's influence on the art of the modern era was wide-ranging, and has been well-documented.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Without realizing he was doing it, he rejected his own time and opened the door to modernity&quot;. Rosenberg, cited by Wilkin, Karen, ''[http://www.newcriterion.com/articles.cfm/chardin-wilkin-2351 The Splendid Chardin]'', New Criterion. Requires subscription. Retrieved 15 October 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Édouard Manet]]'s half-length ''Boy Blowing Bubbles'' and the still lifes of [[Paul Cézanne]] are equally indebted to their predecessor.&lt;ref name=&quot;wilkin1&quot;&gt;Wilkin.&lt;/ref&gt; He was one of [[Henri Matisse]]'s most admired painters; as an art student Matisse made copies of four Chardin paintings in the [[Louvre]].&lt;ref&gt;''The Unknown Matisse: A Life of Henri Matisse, the Early Years, 1869–1908'', Hilary Spurling, p.86. accessed online July 15, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; [[Chaim Soutine]]'s still lifes looked to Chardin for inspiration, as did the paintings of [[Georges Braque]], and later, [[Giorgio Morandi]].&lt;ref name=&quot;wilkin1&quot;/&gt; In 1999 [[Lucian Freud]] painted and etched several copies after ''The Young Schoolmistress'' ([[National Gallery, London]]).&lt;ref&gt;Smee, Sebastian, ''Lucian Freud 1996-2005'', illustrated. Alfred A. Knopf, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Marcel Proust]], in the chapter &quot;How to open your eyes?&quot; from ''[[In Search of Lost Time]]'' (''À la recherche du temps perdu''), describes a melancholic young man sitting at his simple breakfast table. The only comfort he finds is in the imaginary ideas of beauty depicted in the great masterpieces of the Louvre, materializing fancy palaces, rich princes, and the like. The author tells the young man to follow him to another section of the Louvre where the pictures of Jean-Baptiste Chardin are. There he would see the beauty in still life at home and in everyday activities like peeling turnips.
{{clear}}

==See also==
*''[[The Attributes of Civilian and Military Music]]''

==Notes==
{{reflist|30em}}

==References==
* [[ArtCyclopedia]]: [http://www.artcyclopedia.com/artists/chardin_jean-baptiste-simeon.html Jean-Baptiste Siméon Chardin].
* Rosenberg, Pierre (2000), ''Chardin''. Munich: Prestel. {{ISBN|9783791323398}}.
* Rosenberg, Pierre, and Florence Bruyant (2000), ''Chardin''. London: Royal Academy of Arts. {{ISBN|0-900946-83-0}}.

==External links==
{{commons category|Jean Siméon Chardin}}
*[http://www.metmuseum.org/special/se_event.asp?OccurrenceId={A238C1BD-B848-11D3-936D-00902786BF44} Chardin exhibition] at the [[Metropolitan Museum of Art]]
*[http://www.getty.edu/art/gettyguide/artMakerDetails?maker=539 Getty Museum: Chardin].
*[http://www.ibiblio.org/wm/paint/auth/chardin/ WebMuseum: Jean-Baptiste-Siméon Chardin].
*[http://www.jean-baptiste-simeon-chardin.org Jean-Baptiste-Simeon-Chardin.org] 124 works by Jean-Baptiste-Siméon Chardin.
*[http://www.artcyclopedia.com/artists/chardin_jean-baptiste-simeon.html Artcylopedia: Jean-Baptiste Siméon Chardin - identifies where Chardin's work is in galleries and museums around the world].
*[http://www.wga.hu/frames-e.html?/html/c/chardin/index.html Web Gallery of Art: Chardin].
*[http://www.pastellists.com Neil Jeffares, ''Dictionary of pastellists before 1800'', online edition]
*[https://waddesdon.org.uk/the-collection/item/?id=17590 Chardin, ''Boy Building a House of Cards'' at Waddesdon Manor]

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Chardin, Jean-Baptiste-Simeon}}
[[Category:18th-century French painters]]
[[Category:French male painters]]
[[Category:Rococo painters]]
[[Category:1699 births]]
[[Category:1779 deaths]]
[[Category:French still life painters]]
[[Category:Waddesdon Manor]]</text>
      <sha1>pbrtdge5sp47fcpm076jfilzwolgfq7</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
