  <page>
    <title>Christiaan Barnard</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7015</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942576459</id>
      <parentid>942532172</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-25T14:50:29Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Graham87</username>
        <id>194203</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contribs/105.255.216.239|105.255.216.239]] ([[User talk:105.255.216.239|talk]]) to last version by 41.246.28.168</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{redirect|Chris Barnard}}
{{Use South African English|date=May 2012}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2018}}
{{Infobox medical person
| image             = Christiaan Barnard 1969.jpg
| caption           = Christiaan Barnard in 1969
| birth_name        = Christiaan Neethling Barnard
| birth_date        = {{Birth date|1922|11|08|df=yes}}
| birth_place       = [[Beaufort West]], [[Cape Province]],  [[Union of South Africa]]
| death_date        = {{Death date and age|df=yes|2001|09|02|1922|11|08}}
| death_place       = [[Paphos]], Cyprus
| profession        = [[Surgeon]]
| specialism        = [[Cardiothoracic surgery]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Heart transplantation]]
| research_field    =
| known_for         = first successful human-to-human heart transplant
| years_active      = 1950–2001
| education         = [[University of Cape Town]]&lt;br /&gt;[[University of Minnesota Medical Center|University of Minnesota]]
| work_institutions = [[Groote Schuur Hospital]]&lt;br /&gt;University of Minnesota
| prizes            =
| relations         = [[Marius Barnard (surgeon)|Marius Barnard]]
}}

'''Christiaan Neethling Barnard''' (8 November 1922&amp;nbsp;– 2 September 2001) was a South African [[cardiothoracic surgery|cardiac surgeon]] who performed the world's first highly publicized heart transplant and the first one in which the patient regained consciousness.&lt;ref name=&quot;Organ Donation, GlobalViewpoints, Margaret Haerens editor, 2013&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;The operation that took medicine into the media age, BBC, 2017&quot;/&gt; On 3 December 1967, Barnard transplanted the heart of accident-victim [[Denise Darvall]] into the chest of 54-year-old [[Louis Washkansky]], with Washkansky regaining full consciousness and being able to easily talk with his wife, before dying 18 days later of pneumonia. The anti-rejection drugs that suppressed his immune system were a major contributing factor.&lt;ref name=&quot;S-Afr-Med-J-Barnard's-first-heart-transplant&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;mcrae2006&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=New-York-Times-2001-obituary-Christiaan-Barnard/&gt;&lt;ref name=Science-Museum-patient-Louis-Washkansky/&gt;  Barnard had told Mr. and Mrs. Washkansky that the operation had an 80% chance of success, a claim which has been criticised as misleading.&lt;ref name=&quot;Calculated-Risks-Gerd-Gigerenzer-2002&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Companion-To-Bioethics-Second-Edition-2012&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Barnard stating to Mr. and Mrs. Washkansky 80% of success, in Every Second Counts, by Donald McRae&quot;/&gt; Barnard's second transplant patient [[Philip Blaiberg]], whose operation was performed at the beginning of 1968, lived for a year and a half and was able to go home from the hospital.&lt;ref name=New-York-Times-2001-obituary-Christiaan-Barnard/&gt;&lt;ref name=Chicago-Tribune-Philip-Blaiberg-1968/&gt;

Born in [[Beaufort West]], [[Cape Province]], Barnard studied medicine and practised for several years in his native South Africa.&lt;ref name=New-York-Times-2001-obituary-Christiaan-Barnard/&gt;  As a young doctor experimenting on dogs, Barnard developed a remedy for the infant defect of [[intestinal atresia]].  His technique saved the lives of ten babies in Cape Town and was adopted by surgeons in Britain and the United States.&lt;ref name=&quot;Every Second Counts, pages 48-49, Barnard's work remedying intestinal atresia&quot;/&gt;  In 1955, he travelled to the United States and was initially assigned further gastrointestinal work by [[Owen Harding Wangensteen]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Every Second Counts, page 51&quot;/&gt;  He was introduced to the heart-lung machine, and Barnard was allowed to transfer to the service run by open heart surgery pioneer [[C. Walton Lillehei|Walt Lillehei]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Every Second Counts, page 53, Barnard meets Vince Gott&quot;/&gt; Upon returning to South Africa in 1958, Barnard was appointed head of the Department of Experimental Surgery at the Groote Schuur Hospital, Cape Town.&lt;ref name=BMJ-Raymond-Hoffenberg-December-2001/&gt;

He retired as Head of the Department of Cardiothoracic Surgery in Cape Town in 1983 after developing [[rheumatoid arthritis]] in his hands which ended his surgical career. He became interested in anti-aging research, and in 1986 his reputation suffered when he promoted ''[[Glycel]]'', an expensive &quot;anti-aging&quot; skin cream, whose approval was withdrawn by the United States [[Food and Drug Administration]] soon thereafter. During his remaining years, he established the [[Christiaan Barnard Foundation]], dedicated to helping underprivileged children throughout the world. He died in 2001 at the age of 78 after an asthma attack.

== Early life ==
Barnard grew up in [[Beaufort West]], [[Cape Province]], [[Union of South Africa]]. His father, Adam Barnard, was a minister in the [[Dutch Reformed Church in South Africa|Dutch Reformed Church]].&lt;ref name=&quot;mcrae2006&quot;/&gt; One of his four brothers, Abraham, was a &quot;blue baby&quot; who died of a heart problem at the age of three (Barnard would later guess that it was [[tetralogy of Fallot]]).  The family also experienced the loss of a daughter who was stillborn and who had been the fraternal twin of Barnard's older brother Johannes, who was twelve years older than Chris.&lt;ref&gt;''Every Second Counts'', McRae [https://books.google.com/books?id=2Fv9dRT9TC4C&amp;pg=PT44&amp;lpg=PT44&amp;dq=%22Chris+and+Marius+often+felt+that+she+was+grieving+over+the+loss+of+her+only+daughter%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=0sfG2pL-b5&amp;sig=AHk7xZK5s6ocBHV7gUmxq6fKvao&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwiJ-8GRvO_RAhUnw1QKHS1rDakQ6AEIGjAA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22Chris%20and%20Marius%20often%20felt%20that%20she%20was%20grieving%20over%20the%20loss%20of%20her%20only%20daughter%22&amp;f=false page 46].&lt;/ref&gt; Barnard matriculated from the Beaufort West High School in 1940, and went to study medicine at the [[University of Cape Town]] [[Medical School]], where he obtained his [[MBChB|MB ChB]] in 1945.

His father served as a missionary to mixed-race peoples.  His mother, the former Maria Elisabeth de Swart, instilled in the surviving brothers the belief that they could do anything they set their minds to.&lt;ref name=New-York-Times-2001-obituary-Christiaan-Barnard/&gt;

==Career==
Barnard did his [[internship (medicine)|internship]] and [[residency (medicine)|residency]] at the [[Groote Schuur Hospital]] in [[Cape Town]], after which he worked as a general practitioner in [[Ceres, Western Cape|Ceres]], a rural town in the Cape Province.&lt;ref name=&quot;mcrae2006&quot;&gt;''Every Second Counts: The Race to Transplant the First Human Heart'', [[Donald McRae (author)|Donald McRae]], New York: Penguin (Berkley/Putnam), 2006.  See esp. Ch. 10 &quot;The Wait&quot; and Ch. 11 &quot;Fame and Heartbreak,&quot; pages 173–214.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1951, he returned to Cape Town where he worked at the City Hospital as a Senior Resident Medical Officer, and in the Department of Medicine at the Groote Schuur Hospital as a registrar.&lt;ref name=&quot;mcrae2006&quot;/&gt; He completed his master's degree, receiving Master of Medicine in 1953 from the University of Cape Town. In the same year he obtained a doctorate in medicine (MD) from the same university for a dissertation titled &quot;The treatment of tuberculous meningitis&quot;.

Soon after qualifying as a doctor, Barnard performed experiments on dogs while investigating intestinal atresia, a birth defect which allows life-threatening gaps to develop in the intestines.  He followed a medical hunch that this was caused by inadequate blood flow to the fetus.  After nine months and forty-three attempts, Barnard was able to reproduce this condition in a fetus puppy by tying off some of the blood supply to a puppy's intestines and then placing the animal back in the womb, after which it was born some two weeks later, with the condition of intestinal atresia.  He was also able to cure the condition by removing the piece of intestine with inadequate blood supply.  The mistake of previous surgeons had been attempting to reconnect ends of intestine which themselves still had inadequate blood supply.  To be successful, it was typically necessary to remove between 15 and 20 centimeters of intestine (6 to 8 inches).  Jannie Louw used this innovation in a clinical setting, and Barnard's method saved the lives of ten babies in Cape Town.  This technique was also adapted by surgeons in Britain and the US.  In addition, Barnard analyzed 259 cases of tubercular meningitis.&lt;ref name=&quot;Every Second Counts, pages 48-49, Barnard's work remedying intestinal atresia&quot;&gt;''Every Second Counts'', McRae, [https://books.google.com/books?id=2Fv9dRT9TC4C&amp;pg=PT45&amp;lpg=PT45&amp;dq=%22Soon+after+qualifying+as+a+doctor,+Barnard+produced+a+staggering+piece+of+experimental+research%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=0sfG1rO1f1&amp;sig=nA43OxSj7yF1KpnylXq1K8yOp8Y&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwiIkrSVnu3RAhUJxmMKHXvEB_QQ6AEIGjAA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22Soon%20after%20qualifying%20as%20a%20doctor%2C%20Barnard%20produced%20a%20staggering%20piece%20of%20experimental%20research%22&amp;f=false pages 48–49].&lt;/ref&gt;

Owen Wangensteen in Minnesota had been impressed by the work of Alan Thal, a young South African doctor working in Minnesota.  He asked Groote Schuur Head of Medicine John Brock if he might recommend any similarly talented South Africans and Brock recommended Barnard.&lt;ref name=&quot;Every Second Counts, page 49, Barnard goes to Minnesota&quot;&gt;''Every Second Counts'', McRae, [https://books.google.com/books?id=2Fv9dRT9TC4C&amp;pg=PT47&amp;dq=%22In+December+1955,+Christiaan+Barnard+flew+to+the+city+of+snow%22&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwiK3vTLo5DSAhVDMGMKHalQCt4Q6AEIGjAA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22In%20December%201955%2C%20Christiaan%20Barnard%20flew%20to%20the%20city%20of%20snow%22&amp;f=false page 49].&lt;/ref&gt;  In December 1955, Barnard travelled to the [[University of Minnesota]], [[Minneapolis]], United States, to begin a two-year scholarship under Chief of Surgery Wangensteen, who assigned Barnard more work on the intestines, which Barnard accepted even though he wanted to move onto something new.&lt;ref name=&quot;Every Second Counts, page 51&quot;&gt;''Every Second Counts'', McRae, [https://books.google.com/books?id=2Fv9dRT9TC4C&amp;pg=PT48&amp;lpg=PT48&amp;dq=%22Wangensteen+considered+gastrointestinal+research+to+be+intellectually+delicious%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=0sfI2oM_g3&amp;sig=jPUPhhkvTYfmK5dlqON8uzv_nas&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwi67cj_tKnSAhVIwWMKHVSsAZIQ6AEIHDAA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22Wangensteen%20considered%20gastrointestinal%20research%20to%20be%20intellectually%20delicious%22&amp;f=false page 51].&lt;/ref&gt;  Simply by luck, whenever Barnard needed a break from this work, he could wander across the hall and talk with [[Vince Gott]] who ran the lab for open-heart surgery pioneer [[C. Walton Lillehei|Walt Lillehei]].  Gott had begun to develop a technique of running blood backwards through the veins of the heart so Lillehei could more easily operate on the aortic valve (McRae writes, &quot;It was the type of inspired thinking that entranced Barnard&quot;).  In March 1956, Gott asked Barnard to help him run the heart-lung machine for an operation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Every Second Counts, page 53, Barnard meets Vince Gott&quot;&gt;''Every Second Counts'', McRae, [https://books.google.com/books?id=2Fv9dRT9TC4C&amp;pg=PT50&amp;lpg=PT50&amp;dq=%22Whenever+he+needed+a+break+from+the+gullet,+Barnard+wandered+across+the+hall%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=0sfI2oPW86&amp;sig=_mVcwW7qo08i8kXim2ERnySlu9k&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwja28myvqnSAhVQ42MKHeTSBgsQ6AEIGjAA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22Whenever%20he%20needed%20a%20break%20from%20the%20gullet%2C%20Barnard%20wandered%20across%20the%20hall%22&amp;f=false page 53].&lt;/ref&gt;  Shortly thereafter, Wangensteen agreed to let Barnard switch to Lillehei's service.  It was during this time that Barnard first became acquainted with fellow future heart transplantation surgeon [[Norman Shumway]].&lt;ref name=Invest-Surg-2010&gt;{{cite journal | pmid = 20497008 | doi=10.3109/08941939.2010.484321 | volume=23 | issue=2 | title=Christiaan Barnard | year=2010 | author=Toledo-Pereyra LH | journal=J Invest Surg | pages=72–78| quote=  under pioneer surgeons C. Walton Lillehei and Richard L. Varco. Many future distinguished cardiac surgeons, such as Shumway, Cabrol, and many others, were his contemporaries at Minnesota.}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Barnard also became friendly with Gil Campbell who had demonstrated that a dog's lung could be used to oxygenate blood during open-heart surgery.  (The year before Barnard arrived, Lillehei and Campbell had used this procedure for twenty minutes during surgery on a 13-year-old boy with ventricular septal defect, and the boy had made a full recovery.)  Barnard and Campbell met regularly for early breakfast.&lt;ref&gt;''Every Second Counts'', McRae, [https://books.google.com/books?id=2Fv9dRT9TC4C&amp;pg=PT51&amp;lpg=PT51&amp;dq=%22the+South+African+relaxed+a+little+and+became+friendly+with+Gil+Campbell%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=0sfI2oS_9-&amp;sig=-StBQtHhsq9nLASuHfslCkY_HC4&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwiZqJ6Jy6nSAhVGHGMKHbCpC5kQ6AEIGjAA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22the%20South%20African%20relaxed%20a%20little%20and%20became%20friendly%20with%20Gil%20Campbell%22&amp;f=false page 54].&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1958, Barnard received a Master of Science in Surgery for a thesis titled &quot;The [[aortic valve]] – problems in the fabrication and testing of a prosthetic valve&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;mcrae2006&quot;/&gt; The same year he was awarded a Ph.D. for his dissertation titled &quot;The aetiology of congenital intestinal [[atresia]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;mcrae2006&quot;/&gt; Barnard described the two years he spent in the United States as &quot;the most fascinating time in my life.&quot;

Upon returning to South Africa in 1958, Barnard was appointed head of the Department of Experimental Surgery at Groote Schuur hospital, as well as holding a joint post at the University of Cape Town.&lt;ref name=BMJ-Raymond-Hoffenberg-December-2001&gt;{{cite journal| pmc=1121917 | pmid=11751363 | volume=323 | issue=7327 | title=Christiaan Barnard: his first transplants and their impact on concepts of death | author=Hoffenberg R | journal=BMJ | pages=1478–80 | year=2001 | doi=10.1136/bmj.323.7327.1478}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Dictionary-of-African-Biography-Volume-6-2012&gt;''Dictionary of African Biography, Volume 6'', Emmanuel Kwaku Akyeampong, Henry Louis Gates, Jr., editors-in-chief,  [https://books.google.com/books?id=39JMAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA386&amp;lpg=PA386&amp;dq=%22as+well+as+surgical+work+and+teaching,+he+did+advanced+work+in+research+laboratories%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=1zei2rxyZr&amp;sig=AGMrRsI4d9USWLfdubmfPnb0SNg&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwjj0ejP3e_SAhUX1GMKHSQXCYIQ6AEIGjAA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22as%20well%20as%20surgical%20work%20and%20teaching%2C%20he%20did%20advanced%20work%20in%20research%20laboratories%22&amp;f=false Barnard, Christiaan Neethling], Anne Digby, Oxford University Press, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;  He was promoted to full-time lecturer and Director of Surgical Research at the University of Cape Town. In 1960, he flew to Moscow in order to meet [[Vladimir Demikhov]], a top expert on [[Organ transplantation|organ transplants]]&lt;ref&gt;Bosco, Teresio (1968) ''{{interlanguage link|Uomini come noi|it}}'', Società Editrice Internazionale&lt;/ref&gt; (later he credited Demikhov's accomplishment saying that &quot;if there is a father of heart and lung transplantation then Demikhov certainly deserves this title.&quot;)&lt;ref&gt;Fricke, T. A.; Konstantinov, I. E. (2013) ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=pejGYnnkddwC&amp;pg=PA82&amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Dawn and Evolution of Cardiac Procedures]'', [[Springer (publisher)|Springer]]&lt;/ref&gt; In 1961 he was appointed Head of the Division of Cardiothoracic Surgery at the teaching hospitals of the University of Cape Town. He rose to the position of Associate Professor in the Department of Surgery at the University of Cape Town in 1962. Barnard's younger brother [[Marius Barnard (surgeon)|Marius]], who also studied medicine, eventually became Barnard's right-hand man at the department of Cardiac Surgery.&lt;ref name=&quot;mcrae2006&quot;/&gt; Over time, Barnard became known as a brilliant surgeon with many contributions to the treatment of cardiac diseases, such as the [[Tetralogy of Fallot]] and [[Ebstein's anomaly]]. He was promoted to Professor of Surgical Science in the Department of Surgery at the University of Cape Town in 1972. In 1981, Barnard became a founding member of the [[World Cultural Council]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = About Us | publisher = [[World Cultural Council]] | url = http://www.consejoculturalmundial.org/about-us/ | accessdate = 8 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Among the many awards he received over the years, he was named [[Emeritus|Professor Emeritus]] in 1984.

== Historical context ==

Following the first successful [[kidney transplantation|kidney transplant]] in 1953, in the United States, Barnard performed the second kidney transplant in South Africa in October 1967, the first being done in Johannesburg the previous year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Marius|last=Barnard|title=Defining Moments}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{page needed|date=July 2013}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|year=2008 |title=Flesh and Blood: Organ Transplantation and Blood Transfusion in Twentieth-Century America |url=https://books.google.com/?id=JaZn25Uv6XwC&amp;dq=flesh+and+blood |first=Susan E. |last=Lederer |publisher=Oxford University Press |page=174 |isbn=978-0-19-516150-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 23 January 1964, [[James Hardy (surgeon)|James Hardy]] at the [[University of Mississippi Medical Center]] in [[Jackson, Mississippi|Jackson]], [[Mississippi]], performed the world's first [[Heart transplantation|heart transplant]] and world's first cardiac [[Xenotransplantation|xenotransplant]] by transplanting the heart of a chimpanzee into a desperately ill and dying man.  This heart did beat in the patient's chest for approximately 60 to 90 minutes.  The patient, [[Boyd Rush]], died without ever regaining consciousness.&lt;ref name=JAMA-James-Hardy-June-29-1964&gt;[http://jamanetwork.com/journals/jama/article-abstract/1163619 Heart Transplantation in Man: Developmental Studies and Report of a Case], ''JAMA'' (''Journal of the American Medical Association''), James D. Hardy, MD; Carlos M. Chavez, MD; Fred D. Kurrus, MD; William A. Neely, MD; Sadan Eraslan, MD; M. Don Turner, PhD; Leonard W. Fabian, MD; Thaddeus D. Labecki, MD; 188(13): 1132–1140; 29 June 1964.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Brief-History-Cross-Species-Transplantation-David-Cooper-2012&gt;{{cite journal| pmc=3246856 | pmid=22275786 | volume=25 | issue=1 | title=A brief history of cross-species organ transplantation | author=Cooper DK | journal=Proc (Bayl Univ Med Cent) | pages=49–57 | year=2012| doi=10.1080/08998280.2012.11928783 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Telegraph-UK-obituary-James-Hardy-2003&gt;[https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/obituaries/1425080/James-Hardy.html James Hardy], Obituary, ''The Telegraph'' [UK], 20 March 2003.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Every Second Counts'', McRae, see Ch. 7 &quot;Mississippi Gambling&quot;, esp. [https://books.google.com/books?id=2Fv9dRT9TC4C&amp;pg=PT109&amp;dq=%22Rush+was+in+a+comatose+state+with+only+a+faint+pulse%22&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwjHmuLxhtDTAhUI3IMKHb3HBLgQ6AEIJjAA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22Rush%20was%20in%20a%20comatose%20state%20with%20only%20a%20faint%20pulse%22&amp;f=false pages bottom 122 through 127] which talk about the 23 January 1964, operation in which surgeon James Hardy transplanted a chimp's heart into patient Boyd Rush.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2003/02/21/us/james-d-hardy-84-dies-paved-way-for-transplants.html?pagewanted=1 |title=James D. Hardy, 84, Dies; Paved Way for Transplants – Obituary; Biography |newspaper=NYTimes.com |date=21 February 2003 |accessdate=24 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://archive.today/20160524183055/https://www.umc.edu/Education/Schools/Medicine/Clinical_Science/Surgery/Dr__James_D__Hardy.aspx Dr. James D. Hardy], University of Mississippi Medical Center (Bio Sketch).&lt;/ref&gt;

Barnard had experimentally transplanted forty-eight hearts into dogs, which was about a fifth the number that [[Adrian Kantrowitz]] had performed at Maimonides Medical Center in New York and about a sixth the number [[Norman Shumway]] had performed at Stanford University in California.  Barnard had no dogs which had survived longer than ten days, unlike Kantrowitz and Shumway who had had dogs survive for more than a year.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.theguardian.com/society/2006/jun/26/health.southafrica A new heart, a new era], ''The Guardian'', Donald McRae, 25 June 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Every Second Counts'', McRae, page 190.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Daily_I&quot;&gt;{{cite news|date=29 November 1987 |title=Memories of the Heart |work=Daily Intelligencer |location=Doylestown, Pennsylvania |page=A-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

With the availability of new breakthroughs introduced by several pioneers, also including [[Richard Lower (surgeon)|Richard Lower]] at the Medical College of Virginia, several surgical teams were in a position to prepare for a human heart transplant.&lt;ref name=&quot;mcrae2006&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Adrian-Kantrowitz-Papers&quot;&gt;[https://profiles.nlm.nih.gov/ps/retrieve/Narrative/GN/p-nid/315 The Adrian Kantrowitz Papers, Replacing Hearts: Left Ventricle Assist Devices and Transplants, 1960–1970], National Institutes of Health, U.S. National Library of Medicine.  &quot;  .  .  Two Stanford surgeons, Norman Shumway and Richard Lower, had started transplanting dog hearts while experimenting with hypothermia during the late 1950s.  .  &quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Barnard had a patient willing to undergo the procedure, but as with other surgeons, he needed a suitable donor.&lt;ref name=&quot;mcrae2006&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Daily_I&quot; /&gt;

During the [[Apartheid]] era in South Africa, non-white persons and citizens were not given equal opportunities in the medical professions.  At [[Groote Schuur Hospital]], [[Hamilton Naki]] was an informally taught surgeon.  He started out as a gardener and cleaner.  One day he was asked to help out with an experiment on a giraffe.  From this modest beginning, Naki became principal lab technician and taught hundreds&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT 2009&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2005/08/27/world/africa/accounts-of-south-africans-career-now-seen-as-overstated.html|title=Accounts of South African's Career Now Seen as Overstated|first=Michael|last=Wines|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; of surgeons, and assisted with Barnard's organ transplant program.  Barnard said, &quot;Hamilton Naki had better technical skills than I did.  He was a better craftsman than me, especially when it came to stitching, and had very good hands in the theatre&quot;.  A popular myth, propagated principally by a widely [[Hamilton Naki|discredited]] documentary film called ''Hidden Heart''&lt;ref&gt;McKay R. Heart movie skips a beat. Times Live (South Africa) 1 September 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Berger S. Inspiring tale dismissed as 'rubbish.' The National (Abu Dhabi) 4 June 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;October A. Dokkie 'verdraai' Barnard-verhaal.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sabcnews.co.za/SABCnews.com/Documents/SpecialAssignment/HEART-SCRIPT.pdf|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110723010408/http://www.sabcnews.co.za/SABCnews.com/Documents/SpecialAssignment/HEART-SCRIPT.pdf|url-status=dead|archive-date=23 July 2011|title=Wayback Machine|date=23 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and an erroneous [[The Guardian Newspaper|newspaper article]],&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT 2009&quot; /&gt; maintains incorrectly that [[Hamilton Naki|Naki]] was present during the Washkansky transplant.&lt;ref name=Guardian-David-Smith-May-2009&gt;[https://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/may/31/black-surgeon-first-heart-transplant Film on black surgeon in first heart transplant team rekindles controversy], ''The Guardian'' (UK), David Smith, 31 May 2009.  Refers to documentary film ''Hidden Heart'' about Hamilton Naki.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT 2009&quot; /&gt;

== First human-to-human heart transplant ==
Barnard performed the world's first human-to-human heart transplant operation in the early morning hours of Sunday 3 December 1967.&lt;ref name=&quot;S-Afr-Med-J-Barnard's-first-heart-transplant&quot;&gt;''S Afr Med J'', &quot;[http://www.grandroundsjournal.com/articles/gr049002/grhist-001-barnard.pdf A human cardiac transplant: an interim report of a successful operation performed at Groote Schuur Hospital, Cape Town]&quot;, Barnard CN, 1967 Dec 30; ''41''(48): 1271–74.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=New-York-Times-2001-obituary-Christiaan-Barnard/&gt;&lt;ref name=Los-Angeles-Times-Jill-Gottesman-March-1988&gt;[http://articles.latimes.com/1988-03-20/magazine/tm-1895_1_cardiac-care Milestones in Cardiac Care], ''Los Angeles Times'', Jill Gottesman, 20 March 1988.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Louis Washkansky]], a 54-year-old grocer who was suffering from [[Diabetes mellitus|diabetes]] and incurable [[Cardiovascular disease|heart disease]], was the patient.&lt;ref name=Science-Museum-patient-Louis-Washkansky&gt;[http://www.sciencemuseum.org.uk/broughttolife/people/louiswashkansky Louis Washkansky (1913–1967)], Science Museum.  Louis was born in Lithuania in 1913 and moved to South Africa in 1922.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;This Day in Jewish History&quot;&gt;[http://www.haaretz.com/jewish/this-day-in-jewish-history/.premium-1.561467 1967: First Heart Transplant Patient Goes Under the Knife], ''Haaretz'', This Day in Jewish History, David B. Green, 3 December 2013.  &quot;  .  .  When he was 9, his mother took him [Louis Washkansky] and his three siblings to Cape Town, to join their father, who had come ahead of the family  .  .  &quot;&lt;/ref&gt;  Barnard was assisted by his brother Marius Barnard, as well as a team of thirty staff members.  The operation lasted approximately five hours.&lt;ref name=&quot;Daily_I&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Every Second Counts'', McRae, 2006, pages 191–96.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;South African History Online&quot;&gt;[http://www.sahistory.org.za/people/christiaan-neethling-barnard Christiaan Neethling Barnard], South African History Online, updated 11 January 2017.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;This Day in Jewish History&quot;/&gt;

Barnard stated to Washkansky and his wife Ann Washkansky that the transplant had an 80% chance of success.&lt;ref name=&quot;Calculated-Risks-Gerd-Gigerenzer-2002&quot;&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=10yfCgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA27&amp;lpg=PA27&amp;dq=%22calculated+risks%22+Barnard+Washkansky&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=FYxKViDZ9W&amp;sig=Ot46od0J3PLFvTCq_rLo2XBqyrM&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwi52_2X6LzQAhUCilQKHUXRDkIQ6AEIGzAA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22calculated%20risks%22%20Barnard%20Washkansky&amp;f=false Calculated Risks: How to Know When Numbers Deceive You], Gerd Gigerenzer, Simon &amp; Schuster, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Barnard stating to Mr. and Mrs. Washkansky 80% of success, in Every Second Counts, by Donald McRae&quot;&gt;''Every Second Counts'', McRae, pages 176, 190.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ethics of Scientific Research, by Shrader-Frechette, 1994&quot;&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=PbgzAAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA38&amp;lpg=PA38&amp;dq=%22Barnard's+failure+to+tell+Washkansky's+wife+that+her+husband+was+dying%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=IQXk2sdVJ9&amp;sig=cffx8FCmKtYRwNc4cj29VxifqPg&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwjB9YqA2OrSAhUB52MKHaZ9CkIQ6AEIGjAA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22Barnard's%20failure%20to%20tell%20Washkansky's%20wife%20that%20her%20husband%20was%20dying%22&amp;f=false Ethics of Scientific Research], Kristin Shrader-Frechette, Rowman &amp; Littlefield, 1994, page 38.  Along a similar line, this author states, &quot;Barnard's failure to tell Washkansky's wife that her husband was dying,&quot; although it's not clear whether this was pre- or post-transplant.&lt;/ref&gt; This has been criticised by the ethicists [[Peter Singer]] and [[Helga Kuhse]] as making claims for chances of success to the patient and family which were &quot;unfounded&quot; and &quot;misleading&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Companion-To-Bioethics-Second-Edition-2012&quot;&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=_e03TWSl1OIC&amp;pg=PT542&amp;lpg=PT542&amp;dq=%22Barnard+gave+Washkansky+an+unfounded+and+misleading+assurance%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=WWHCNRbstw&amp;sig=ba0P1vuCZpPrOckqOSbmqLTlXmY&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwjL-bqw6KnUAhWJLmMKHZDpAbkQ6AEIIjAA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22Barnard%20gave%20Washkansky%20an%20unfounded%20and%20misleading%20assurance%22&amp;f=false A Companion to Bioethics, Second Edition], Helga Kuhse, Peter Singer, Wiley-Blackwell, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;
 
Barnard later wrote, &quot;For a dying man it is not a difficult decision because he knows he is at the end. If a lion chases you to the bank of a river filled with crocodiles, you will leap into the water, convinced you have a chance to swim to the other side.&quot; The donor heart came from a young woman, [[Denise Darvall]], who had been rendered brain dead in an accident on 2 December 1967, while crossing a street in Cape Town.&lt;ref name=&quot;mcrae2006&quot;/&gt; On examination at Groote Schuur hospital, Darvall had two serious fractures in her skull, with no electrical activity in her brain detected, and no sign of pain when ice water was poured into her ear.&lt;ref&gt;''Every Second Counts'', McRae, 2006, p. 188.&lt;/ref&gt;  Coert Venter and Bertie Bosman requested permission from Darvall's father for Denise's heart to be used in the transplant attempt.&lt;ref&gt;''Every Second Counts'', McRae, [https://books.google.com/books?id=nBYTCwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA189&amp;lpg=PA189&amp;dq=%22He+was+still+in+a+daze+when+Coert+Venter+knocked+gently%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=eK3RGGCxdA&amp;sig=igcAK_m1D47HUZCvy3t1qlsOPTE&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwj4mdywoejQAhXphlQKHTg4DccQ6AEIGjAA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22He%20was%20still%20in%20a%20daze%20when%20Coert%20Venter%20knocked%20gently%22&amp;f=false page 189], &quot;Coert Venter . . [and] Bertie Bosman . . withdrew, stressing that he should take as long as he needed to consider their request.  They would understand if he declined to give his consent.&quot;  Edward Darvall took four minutes to reach his decision, mainly thinking about his daughter, including how she tried to help others.  He then told the doctors, &quot;If you can't save my daughter, you must try and save this man.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; The afternoon before his first transplant, Barnard dozed at his home while listening to music.  When he awoke, he decided to modify Shumway and Lower's technique.  Instead of cutting straight across the back of the atrial chambers of the donor heart, he would avoid damage to the septum and instead cut two small holes for the venae cavae and pulmonary veins.&lt;ref&gt;''Every Second Counts'', McRae, 2006, [https://books.google.com/books?id=2Fv9dRT9TC4C&amp;pg=PT162&amp;lpg=PT162&amp;dq=%22Barnard+eventually+became+drowsy+and+he+drifted+in+and+out+of+sleep%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=0sfC-nP083&amp;sig=xGL_NszJxgKT5LeGYIbA5FZiREI&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwiIjOGE7vHQAhXmrVQKHdWDBkkQ6AEIGjAA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22Barnard%20eventually%20became%20drowsy%20and%20he%20drifted%20in%20and%20out%20of%20sleep%22&amp;f=false page 187].&lt;/ref&gt;  Prior to the transplant, rather than wait for Darvall's heart to stop beating, at his brother Marius Barnard's urging, Christiaan had injected potassium into her heart to paralyse it and render her technically dead by the whole-body standard.&lt;ref name=&quot;mcrae2006&quot;/&gt; Twenty years later, Marius Barnard recounted, &quot;Chris stood there for a few moments, watching, then stood back and said, 'It works.'&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;mcrae2006&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Daily_I&quot; /&gt;

Washkansky survived the operation and lived for 18 days, having succumbed to [[pneumonia]] as he was taking [[immunosuppressive drug]]s.

== Additional heart transplants ==

Barnard and his patient received worldwide publicity.&lt;ref name=&quot;Organ Donation, GlobalViewpoints, Margaret Haerens editor, 2013&quot;&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=8IRmDwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA18&amp;lpg=PA18&amp;dq=%22The+amount+of+publicity+generated+by+the+first+heart+transplant+was+extensive.++Critics+viewed%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=ntdCAcR0Vq&amp;sig=fI1iNvuxgBfS8FT71SL8bqu2tpw&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=2ahUKEwi_vbW4-prfAhURP6wKHS1QC-kQ6AEwAHoECAAQAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=%22The%20amount%20of%20publicity%20generated%20by%20the%20first%20heart%20transplant%20was%20extensive.%20%20Critics%20viewed%22&amp;f=false Organ Donation], GlobalViewpoints, Margaret Haerens editor, Detroit, New York, San Francisco, New Haven, Conn., Waterville, Maine, U.S.A; London, England, UK: Greenhaven Press, 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Every Second Counts, regarding international publicity of Barnard's first heart transplant, esp. pages 207 and 208&quot;&gt;''Every Second Counts'', McRae, see [https://books.google.com/books?id=nBYTCwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA207&amp;dq=%22On+Monday+morning,+as+international+news+teams+flocked+to+Cape+Town,+the+BBC+and+CBS+leading+the+first+requests+for+exclusive+interviews%22&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwjtkqTF36fgAhXHna0KHVuzCt4Q6AEIKDAA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22On%20Monday%20morning%2C%20as%20international%20news%20teams%20flocked%20to%20Cape%20Town%2C%20the%20BBC%20and%20CBS%20leading%20the%20first%20requests%20for%20exclusive%20interviews%22&amp;f=false page 207] and, regarding publicity in the Soviet Union, [https://books.google.com/books?id=2Fv9dRT9TC4C&amp;pg=PT180&amp;lpg=PT180&amp;dq=%22In+Moscow,+Pravda+gave+over+its+front+page+to+the+news+and+suggested+to+its+readers+that+in+spite+of+South+Africa's+backward+place%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=0tbKZpS09Z&amp;sig=ACfU3U1-5lot6u5MiFmEX-5A2lCXccjtqg&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=2ahUKEwiD1Ym14qfgAhVJba0KHc6cBNYQ6AEwAHoECAAQAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=%22In%20Moscow%2C%20Pravda%20gave%20over%20its%20front%20page%20to%20the%20news%20and%20suggested%20to%20its%20readers%20that%20in%20spite%20of%20South%20Africa's%20backward%20place%22&amp;f=false pages 208–09] in which ''Pravda'' states, &quot;in spite of South Africa's backward place in the community of nations, positive, creative forces seem to thrive there, as proven by the immense feat of Dr. Chris Barnard.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; As a 2017 BBC retrospective article describes, &quot;Journalists and film crews flooded into Cape Town's Groote Schuur Hospital, soon making Barnard and Washkansky household names.&quot;  Barnard himself was described as &quot;charismatic&quot; and &quot;photogenic.&quot;  And the operation was initially reported as &quot;successful&quot; even though Washkansky only lived a further 18 days.&lt;ref name=&quot;The operation that took medicine into the media age, BBC, 2017&quot;&gt;[https://www.bbc.com/news/health-42170023 The operation that took medicine into the media age], BBC, Dr Ayesha Nathoo (Centre for Medical History, University of Exeter), 3 December 2017.  The photo caption incorrectly states [[Louis Washkansky]] was the first heart transplant recipient, when in actuality he was second.  [[Boyd Rush]] with physician James D. Hardy was the first person to receive a heart transplant in 1964.&lt;/ref&gt;

Worldwide, approximately 100 transplants were performed by various doctors during 1968.&lt;ref&gt;[http://dspace.ucalgary.ca/bitstream/1880/48963/1/2009_HMD_Elzinga.pdf MAJOR MEDICAL MILESTONES LEADING UP TO THE FIRST HUMAN HEART TRANSPLANTATION], Kate Elzinga, from ''Proceedings of the 18th Annual History of Medicine Days Conference 2009: The University of Calgary Faculty of Medicine, Alberta, Canada'', Cambridge Scholars Publishing, 2011. &quot; . . following Barnard's landmark heart transplantation on December 3, 1967, 107 human heart transplants were performed by 64 surgical teams in 24 countries in 1968. . &quot;&lt;/ref&gt;  However, only a third of these patients lived longer than three months.  Many medical centers stopped performing transplants.  In fact, a U.S. [[National Institutes of Health]] publication states, &quot;Within several years, only Shumway's team at Stanford was attempting transplants.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Adrian-Kantrowitz-Papers&quot;/&gt;

Barnard's second transplant operation was conducted on 2 January 1968, and the patient, [[Philip Blaiberg]], survived for 19 months.&lt;ref name=New-York-Times-2001-obituary-Christiaan-Barnard/&gt;&lt;ref name=Chicago-Tribune-Philip-Blaiberg-1968&gt;[http://archives.chicagotribune.com/1969/10/12/page/254/article/philip-blaiberg-was-dying-this-time-for-certain Philip Blaiberg was dying—this time for certain], ''Chicago Tribune'', Mrs. Philip Blaiberg, 12 October 1969, page 68.&lt;/ref&gt; Blaiberg's heart was donated by Clive Haupt, a 24-year-old black man who suffered a stroke, inciting controversy (especially in the African-American press) during the time of South African apartheid.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Koretzky|first=Maya Overby|date=2016|title='A Change of Heart': Racial Politics, Scientific Metaphor and Coverage of 1968 Interracial Heart Transplants in the African American Press|journal=Social History of Medicine|volume=30|issue=2|pages=408–428|doi=10.1093/shm/hkw052|pmc=5914447|pmid=29713117}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Dirk van Zyl, who received a new heart in 1971, was the longest-lived recipient, surviving over 23 years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|date=7 July 1994 |title=Dirk van Zyl, 68; Had '71 Transplant |url=https://www.nytimes.com/1994/07/07/obituaries/dirk-van-zyl-68-had-71-transplant.html |work=New York Times |accessdate=28 March 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Between December 1967 and November 1974 at Groote Schuur Hospital in Cape Town, South Africa, ten heart transplants were performed, as well as a heart and lung transplant in 1971.  Of these ten patients, four lived longer than 18 months, with two of these four becoming long-term survivors.  One patient lived for over thirteen years and another for over twenty-four years.&lt;ref name=&quot;South-African-Medical-Journal-2012&quot;&gt;[http://www.samj.org.za/index.php/samj/article/view/5020/4123 Transplantation of the heart: An overview of 40 years' clinical and research experience at Groote Schuur Hospital and the University of Cape Town], ''South African Medical Journal'', &quot;Part I. Surgical experience and clinical studies.&quot; J Hassoulas, Vol. 102, No. 6 (2012).&lt;/ref&gt;

Full recovery of donor heart function often takes place over hours or days, during which time considerable damage can occur.  Other deaths to patients can occur from preexisting conditions.  For example, in pulmonary hypertension the patient's right ventricle has often adapted to the higher pressure over time and, although diseased and hypertrophied, is often capable of maintaining circulation to the lungs.  Barnard designed the idea of the heterotopic (or &quot;piggy back&quot; transplant) in which the patient's diseased heart is left in place while the donor heart is added, essentially forming a &quot;double heart&quot;.  Barnard performed the first such [[Heart transplantation#Heterotopic procedure|heterotopic]] heart transplant in 1974.&lt;ref name=&quot;South-African-Medical-Journal-2012&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Postgrad-Medical-Journal-2016&quot;&gt;[http://pmj.bmj.com/content/early/2016/07/27/postgradmedj-2016-134309.extract &quot;A tale of two hearts&quot;], ''Postgrad Medical Journal'', 27 July 2016.  &quot;...  HHT [Heterotopic Heart Transplantation] involves transplanting the donor heart without removing the recipient heart, effectively forming a 'double heart'.  It was widely used in the pre-cyclosporine era when the donor was not strong enough (eg, the recipient had a much larger body) or the recipient had pre-existing pulmonary hypertension.  Christiaan Barnard performed the first HHT ('piggy back' transplant) in 1974 ...&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

From November 1974 through December 1983, 49 consecutive heterotopic heart transplants on 43 patients were performed at Groote Schuur. The survival rate for patients at one year was over 60%, as compared to less than 40% with standard transplants, and the survival rate at five years was over 36% as compared to less than 20% with standard transplants.&lt;ref name=&quot;South-African-Medical-Journal-2012&quot;/&gt;

Many surgeons gave up cardiac transplantation due to poor results, often due to [[Transplant rejection|rejection of the transplanted heart]] by the patient's immune system. Barnard persisted until the advent of [[ciclosporin|cyclosporine]], an effective immunosuppressive drug, which helped revive the operation throughout the world. He also attempted [[xenotransplantation]] in a human patient, while attempting to save the life of a girl who was unable to leave artificial life support after her second aortic valve replacement.

== Public life ==
[[File:Christiaan Barnard 1968.jpg|thumb|Christiaan Barnard in Italy in 1968]]
Barnard was an outspoken opponent of South Africa's laws of apartheid, and was not afraid to criticise his nation's government, although he had to temper his remarks to some extent to travel abroad.{{Citation needed|date=September 2008}}  Rather than leaving his homeland, he used his fame to campaign for a change in the law. Christiaan's brother, [[Marius Barnard (surgeon)|Marius Barnard]], went into politics, and was elected to the [[Parliament of South Africa|legislature]] from [[Progressive Federal Party]]. Barnard later stated that the reason he never won the [[Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine]] was probably because he was a &quot;[[white South African]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hinduonnet.com/fline/fl1422/14220850.htm &quot;It's the quality of survival that's important&quot;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070711210948/http://www.hinduonnet.com/fline/fl1422/14220850.htm |date=11 July 2007 }}. Hinduonnet.com (31 October 1997). Retrieved on 30 June 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;

Shortly before his visit to Kenya in 1978, the following was written about his views regarding race relations in South Africa;
&quot;While he believes in the participation of Africans in the political process of South Africa, he is opposed to a one-man-one-vote system in South Africa&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Hilary|first=Ng'weno|date=5 May 1978|title=Dr. Christiaan Barnard Visit to Kenya|url=|journal=The Weekly Review|volume=|pages=13|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In answering a hypothetical question on how he would solve the race problem were he a &quot;benevolent dictator in South Africa&quot;, Barnard stated the following in a long interview at the Weekly Review:&lt;ref name=&quot;Hilary 16–17&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Hilary|first=Ng'weno|date=19 May 1978|title=I Would Split South Africa Into Two Parts – Equitably|url=|journal=The Weekly Review|volume=|pages=16–17|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* While &quot;I would abolish Social discrimination&quot;, political discrimination would continue.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hilary 16–17&quot;/&gt; 
* He favoured the total division of the country along racial lines. His words were; &quot;I somehow feel ... but we may have to divide South Africa into two equal divisions&quot;. In a follow-up question about where the coloured people would end up in that scenario, he replied that 'I would include them in the white South Africa&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hilary 16–17&quot;/&gt;
* That coloured people have &quot;always been accepted&quot; among whites.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hilary 16–17&quot;/&gt;
* That &quot;the black man will not accept this view&quot; of universal suffrage.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hilary 16–17&quot;/&gt;
* That &quot;we are still out of the Olympic games&quot; despite the fact that &quot;in the field of sports where we have virtually integrated completely.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hilary 16–17&quot;/&gt;
* Regarding the [[Soweto uprising]], he claimed &quot;there was ... a lot of external stirring up of turbulence&quot;. Regarding the anger from the black population when [[Steve Biko]] was murdered, he said that &quot;I think that something like $50,000 came in from outside to work up feelings at that funeral.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hilary 16–17&quot;/&gt;
* He stated that the National Party members were as upset about Biko's murder as were blacks; &quot;The white community was thoroughly upset, let me tell you. The nationalists themselves were very upset.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hilary 16–17&quot;/&gt;

The interview ended with the following summary from he himself;
&quot;I often say that, like [[King Lear]], South Africa is a country more sinned against than sinning.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hilary 16–17&quot;/&gt;

== Personal life ==
Barnard's first marriage was to Aletta Gertruida Louw, a nurse, whom he married in 1948 while practising medicine in Ceres. The couple had two children: Deirdre (born 1950) and Andre (1951–1984).&lt;ref name=&quot;mcrae2006&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[https://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/africa/christiaan-barnard-celebrated-pioneer-of-heart-transplant-surgery-dies-aged-78-667863.html Christiaan Barnard, celebrated pioneer of heart transplant surgery, dies aged 78]&quot;, ''The Independent'', 3 September 2001. Retrieved 18 September 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; International fame took a toll on his personal life, and in 1969, Barnard and his wife divorced. In 1970, he married heiress Barbara Zoellner when she was 19, the same age as his son, and they had two children: Frederick (born 1972) and Christiaan Jr. (born 1974).&lt;ref name=cbarnardbio&gt;{{cite web |title=Christiaan Barnard Biography |url=http://www.allsands.com/entertainment/people/christiaanbarna_aoi_gn.htm |accessdate=10 June 2009 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090523102543/http://www.allsands.com/entertainment/people/christiaanbarna_aoi_gn.htm |archive-date=23 May 2009 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; He divorced Zoellner in 1982.&lt;ref name=cbarnardbio/&gt; Barnard married for a third time in 1988 to Karin Setzkorn, a young model.&lt;ref name=cbarnardbio/&gt; They also had two children, Armin (born 1989) and Lara (born 1997), but this last marriage also ended in divorce in 2000.&lt;ref name=cbarnardbio/&gt;

Barnard described in his autobiography ''The Second Life'' a one-night extramarital affair with Italian film star [[Gina Lollobrigida]],&lt;ref name=&quot;mcrae2006&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Barnard|first=Chris |date=1994 |title= Druhý dech |trans-title=The Second Life|pages = 70–71|language= cs |location=Prague |publisher=Lidové noviny |isbn= 80-7106-096-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!-- Czech translation of The Second Life --&gt; that occurred in January 1968. During that visit to Rome he received an audience from [[Pope Paul VI]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title= Pope Tells Barnard Of 'Heart' Prayers|url= https://news.google.com/newspapers?nid=1144&amp;dat=19680130&amp;id=sLcpAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=o08EAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=5795,4863293&amp;hl=cs|date= 30 January 1968|access-date= 8 October 2016|location=Pittsburgh |newspaper=Pittsburgh Post-Gazette}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!-- article via Google news with image of Barnard and Lollobrigida --&gt;

In October 2016, U.S. Congresswoman [[Ann McLane Kuster]] (D-NH) stated that Barnard sexually assaulted her when she was 23 years old. According to Kuster, he attempted to grope her under her skirt, while seated at a business luncheon with  Rep. [[Pete McCloskey]] (R-CA), whom she worked for at the time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dailyherald.com/article/20161013/news/310139819/|title=Trump comments prompt congresswoman to share assault story|first=Associated|last=Press|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.nh1.com/news/rep-annie-kuster-tells-concord-monitor-famous-doctor-sexually-assaulted-her-decades-ago/ |title=Archived copy |access-date=13 October 2016 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161017230458/http://www.nh1.com/news/rep-annie-kuster-tells-concord-monitor-famous-doctor-sexually-assaulted-her-decades-ago/ |archive-date=17 October 2016 |url-status = dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;https://www.usnews.com/news/politics/articles/2016-10-13/trump-comments-prompt-congresswoman-to-share-assault-story&lt;/ref&gt;

== Retirement ==
Barnard retired as Head of the Department of Cardiothoracic Surgery in Cape Town in 1983 after developing [[rheumatoid arthritis]] in his hands which ended his surgical career. He had struggled with arthritis since 1956, when it was diagnosed during his postgraduate work in the United States.&lt;ref name=&quot;mcrae2006&quot;/&gt; After retirement, he spent two years as the Scientist-In-Residence at the Oklahoma Transplantation Institute in the United States and as an acting consultant for various institutions.{{citation needed|date=December 2017}}

He had by this time become very interested in anti-aging research, and his reputation suffered in 1986 when he promoted ''[[Glycel]]'', an expensive &quot;anti-aging&quot; skin cream, whose approval was withdrawn by the United States [[Food and Drug Administration]] soon thereafter.&lt;ref name=New-York-Times-2001-obituary-Christiaan-Barnard&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2001/09/03/world/christiaan-barnard-78-surgeon-for-first-heart-transplant-dies.html|title=Christiaan Barnard, 78, Surgeon For First Heart Transplant, Dies|last=Altman|first=Lawrence K.|date=3 September 2001|work=The New York Times|accessdate=30 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; He also spent time as a research advisor to the Clinique la Prairie, in [[Switzerland]], where the controversial &quot;rejuvenation therapy&quot; was practised.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/news/2001/sep/03/guardianobituaries.medicalscience|title=Obituary: Christiaan Barnard|last=Cooper|first=David K. C.|date=3 September 2001|work=The Guardian|accessdate=2 December 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Barnard divided the remainder of his years between [[Austria]], where he established the [[Christiaan Barnard Foundation]], dedicated to helping underprivileged children throughout the world, and his game farm in Beaufort West, South Africa.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://cbheartfoundation.com/the-foundation/|title=The Foundation – Christiaan Barnard Heart Foundation|work=Christiaan Barnard Heart Foundation|access-date=2018-11-26|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|chapter=Heart and Blood Vessel Surgery|date=2016-09-13|doi=10.1142/9789814699389_0007|pages=165–187|publisher=WORLD SCIENTIFIC|isbn=9789814699365|title=The First Transplant Surgeon}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Death ==
Christiaan Barnard died on 2 September 2001, while on holiday in [[Paphos]], Cyprus. Early reports stated that he had died of a heart attack, but an [[autopsy]] showed his death was caused by a severe [[asthma]] attack.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title=Autopsy confirms asthma killed Barnard | date= 5 September 2001 | url =http://www.cyprus-mail.com/news/main_old.php?id=4655&amp;archive=1 | work =[[Cyprus Mail]] | accessdate =15 March 2007 |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20070927202905/http://www.cyprus-mail.com/news/main_old.php?id=4655&amp;archive=1 &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 27 September 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Books==
Christiaan Barnard wrote two autobiographies. His first book, ''One Life'', was published in 1969 ({{ISBN|0245599525}}) and sold copies worldwide. Some of the proceeds were used to set up the Chris Barnard Fund for research into heart disease and heart transplants in Cape Town.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Brink JG, Hassoulas J |title=The first human heart transplant and further advances in cardiac transplantation at Groote Schuur Hospital and the University of Cape Town – with reference to : the operation. A human cardiac transplant : an interim report of a successful operation performed at Groote Schuur Hospital, Cape Town |journal=Cardiovasc J Afr |volume=20 |issue=1 |pages=31–5 |year=2009 |pmid=19287813 |pmc=4200566 |doi= |url=}}&lt;/ref&gt; His second autobiography, ''The Second Life'', was published in 1993, eight years before his death ({{ISBN|0947461388}}).

Apart from his autobiographies, Dr Barnard also wrote several other books including:&lt;ref&gt;{{Worldcat id|lccn-n79090011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*''The Donor''
*''Your Healthy Heart''
*''In The Night Season''
*''The Best Medicine''
*''Arthritis Handbook: How to Live With Arthritis''
*''Good Life Good Death: A Doctor's Case for Euthanasia and Suicide''
*''South Africa: Sharp Dissection''
*''50 Ways to a Healthy Heart''
*''Body Machine''

== See also ==
* [[René Favaloro]]
* [[Pierre Grondin]]
* [[Hamilton Naki]]
* [[Geoffrey Tovey]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

== External links ==
{{Wikiquote}}
{{Commons category}}
* [http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=1121917 Christiaan Barnard: his first transplants and their impact on concepts of death]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20111001054057/http://www.heart-transplant.co.uk/barnard.html To Transplant and Beyond : First Human Heart Transplant]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20061217194135/http://www.ctsnet.org/doc/6272 In Memoriam : Christiaan Neethling Barnard]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20120206092146/http://www.info.gov.za/speeches/2007/07113014151003.htm 40th anniversary of first human heart transplant]
* [http://www.heartofcapetown.co.za Official Heart Transplant Museum – Heart Of Cape Town]

{{Founding members of the World Cultural Council}}
{{Organ transplantation}}
{{Authority control}}
{{Portal bar|Medicine|Biography}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Barnard, Christiaan}}
[[Category:1922 births]]
[[Category:2001 deaths]]
[[Category:Deaths from pneumonia]]
[[Category:Infectious disease deaths in South Africa]]
[[Category:People from Beaufort West]]
[[Category:Afrikaner people]]
[[Category:White South African people]]
[[Category:South African cardiac surgeons]]
[[Category:South African transplant surgeons]]
[[Category:University of Cape Town academics]]
[[Category:University of Cape Town alumni]]
[[Category:University of Minnesota alumni]]
[[Category:Founding members of the World Cultural Council]]
[[Category:Deaths from asthma]]
[[Category:20th-century surgeons]]
[[Category:20th-century South African physicians]]</text>
      <sha1>nb3l7jmh1jfbv18posjxui7l9jalmpp</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
