  <page>
    <title>Cracking joints</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7042</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942957979</id>
      <parentid>941080810</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-27T22:57:01Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>216.16.54.134</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}
{{Multiple image
|direction = vertical
|width = 250
|image1 = Cracking knuckles.jpg
|caption1 = Cracking finger joints makes a distinct cracking or popping sound.
|image2 = Knuckle crack.ogg
}}
'''Cracking joints''' is manipulating one's joints to produce a distinct cracking or popping sound. It is sometimes performed by [[Physical therapy|physical therapist]]s, [[chiropractor]]s, [[osteopath]]s, and [[Massage#Turkish bath massage|masseurs in Turkish bath]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Richard Boggs, ''Hammaming in the Sham: A Journey Through the Turkish Baths of Damascus, Aleppo and Beyond'', 2012, {{isbn|1859643256}}, [https://books.google.com/books?id=uoMH_psyizoC&amp;pg=PT161 p. 161]&lt;/ref&gt;

The cracking of joints, especially knuckles, was long believed to lead to [[arthritis]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=2018-05-14|title=Knuckle cracking: Annoying &amp; harmful, or just annoying?|url=https://www.health.harvard.edu/blog/knuckle-cracking-annoying-and-harmful-or-just-annoying-2018051413797|first=Robert H.|last=Shmerling|department=How do we know that knuckle cracking is harmless?|website=health.harvard.edu|accessdate=2019-07-19|quote=One study published in 1990 found that among 74 people who regularly cracked their knuckles, their average grip strength was lower and there were more instances of hand swelling than among 226 people who did not crack their knuckles. However, the incidence of arthritis was the same in both groups.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Castellanos&quot;/&gt; and other joint problems. However, medical research has not demonstrated such a connection.

The cracking mechanism and the resulting sound is caused by carbon dioxide [[cavitation]] bubbles suddenly partially collapsing inside the joints. To be able to crack the same knuckle again requires waiting about 15 minutes for the bubbles to reform.&lt;ref name=&quot;dvorsky&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://gizmodo.com/now-we-know-why-knuckle-cracking-makes-that-awful-sound-1824154323|title=Simulation May Finally Explain Why Knuckle Cracking Makes That Awful Sound|last=Dvorsky|first=George|work=Gizmodo|access-date=2018-03-30|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Causes==
[[File:Real-Time-Visualization-of-Joint-Cavitation-pone.0119470.s002.ogv|thumb|[[Magnetic resonance imaging|MRI]] of a cracking finger joint, visualizing cavitation.]]

For many decades, the physical mechanism that causes the cracking sound as a result of bending, twisting, or compressing joints was uncertain. Suggested causes included:

* Formation of bubbles of [[pneumatosis|joint air]] as the joint is expanded.&lt;ref name=&quot;kawchuk&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|author1=Gregory N. Kawchuk|author2=Jerome Fryer|author3=Jacob L. Jaremko|author4=Hongbo Zeng|author5=Lindsay Rowe|author6=Richard Thompson|year=2015|title=Real-Time Visualization of Joint Cavitation|journal=PLoS ONE|volume=10|issue=6|pages=384–390|bibcode=2015PLoSO..1019470K|doi=10.1371/journal.pone.0119470|pmc=4398549|pmid=25875374}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Cavitation]] within the joint—small cavities of partial vacuum form in the [[synovial fluid]] and then rapidly collapse, producing a sharp sound.&lt;ref name=&quot;telegraph&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/science/science-news/11539913/Why-knuckle-cracking-makes-a-popping-sound-and-why-it-might-be-beneficial.html|title=Why knuckle cracking makes a popping sound, and why it might be beneficial|last1=Knapton|first1=Sarah|date=15 April 2015|work=[[The Daily Telegraph]]|accessdate=17 December 2016|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;guardian&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.theguardian.com/science/2015/apr/15/cracked-it-scientists-solve-puzzle-of-why-knuckles-crack-when-pulled|title=Cracked it! Scientists solve puzzle of why knuckles pop when pulled|first1=Ian|last1=Sample|first2=science|last2=editor|date=15 April 2015 |accessdate=20 September 2016|work=The Guardian |location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Rapid stretching of ligaments.&lt;ref name=&quot;Protopapas&quot; /&gt;
* Intra-articular (within-joint) [[Adhesion (medicine)|adhesions]] being broken.&lt;ref name=&quot;Protopapas&quot; /&gt;

There were several theories to explain the cracking of joints. Synovial fluid cavitation has some evidence to support it.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Brodeur R. |title=The audible release associated with joint manipulation |journal=J Manipulative Physiol Ther |volume=18 |issue=3 |pages=155–64 |year=1995 |pmid=7790795}}&lt;/ref&gt; When a [[spinal manipulation]] is performed, the applied force separates the articular surfaces of a fully encapsulated synovial joint, which in turn creates a reduction in pressure within the joint cavity. In this low-pressure environment, some of the [[gas]]es that are dissolved in the synovial fluid (which are naturally found in all bodily fluids) leave the solution, making a [[liquid bubble|bubble]], or [[Cavitation|cavity]], which rapidly collapses upon itself, resulting in a &quot;clicking&quot; sound.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Maigne|first1=Jean-Yves|last2=Vautravers|first2=Philippe|title=Mechanism of action of spinal manipulative therapy|journal=Joint Bone Spine|date=September 2003|volume=70|issue=5|pages=336–341|doi=10.1016/S1297-319X(03)00074-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; The contents of the resultant gas bubble are thought to be mainly [[carbon dioxide]], [[oxygen]] and [[nitrogen]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|vauthors=Unsworth A, Dowson D, Wright V|year=1971|title='Cracking joints'. A bioengineering study of cavitation in the metacarpophalangeal joint.|journal=Ann Rheum Dis|volume=30|issue=4|pages=348–58|doi=10.1136/ard.30.4.348|pmc=1005793|pmid=5557778}}[https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1005793/pdf/annrheumd00004-0008.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt;  The effects of this process will remain for a period of time known as the &quot;[[Refractory period (physiology)|refractory period]],&quot; during which the joint cannot be &quot;re-cracked,&quot; which lasts about twenty minutes, while the gases are slowly reabsorbed into the [[synovial fluid]]. There is some evidence that [[Ligamentous laxity|ligament laxity]] may be associated with an increased tendency to cavitate.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fryer&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author1=Fryer, Gary |author2= Jacob Mudge |author3=McLaughlin, Patrick |last-author-amp=yes |year=2002 |title=The Effect of Talocrural Joint Manipulation on Range of Motion at the Ankle |journal=[[Journal of Manipulative and Physiological Therapeutics]] |issue=6 |pages=384–390 |pmid=12183696 |doi=10.1067/mmt.2002.126129 |volume=25|url= http://vuir.vu.edu.au/504/1/Ankle_manipulation_-_revised.pdf }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2015, research showed that bubbles remained in the fluid after cracking, suggesting that the cracking sound was produced when the bubble within the joint was formed, not when it collapsed.&lt;ref name=&quot;kawchuk&quot; /&gt; In 2018, a team in France created a mathematical simulation of what happens in a joint just before it cracks. The team concluded that the sound is caused by bubbles' collapse, and bubbles observed in the fluid are the result of a partial collapse. Due to the theoretical basis and lack of physical experimentation, the scientific community is still not fully convinced of this conclusion.&lt;ref name=&quot;dvorsky&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://time.com/5220275/knuckles-crack-science-why-reason/|title=Why Does Cracking Your Knuckles Make So Much Noise? Science Finally Has an Answer|website=Time|language=en|access-date=2018-03-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Chandran Suja|first=V.|last2=Barakat|first2=A. I.|date=2018-03-29|title=A Mathematical Model for the Sounds Produced by Knuckle Cracking|journal=Scientific Reports|language=En|volume=8|issue=1|page=4600|doi=10.1038/s41598-018-22664-4|pmid=29599511|pmc=5876406|issn=2045-2322|bibcode=2018NatSR...8.4600C}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The snapping of tendons or scar tissue over a prominence (as in [[snapping hip syndrome]]) can also generate a loud snapping or popping sound.&lt;ref name=&quot;Protopapas&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Protopapas M, Cymet T, Protapapas M |title=Joint cracking and popping: understanding noises that accompany articular release. |journal=J Am Osteopath Assoc |volume=102 |issue=5 |pages=283–7 |date=1 May 2002 |pmid=12033758 |url=http://www.jaoa.org/cgi/reprint/102/5/283 |access-date=2 March 2007 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070927214025/http://www.jaoa.org/cgi/reprint/102/5/283 |archive-date=27 September 2007 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Effects==

The common claim that cracking one's knuckles causes [[arthritis]] is not supported by evidence.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Rizvi|first=Asad|last2=Loukas|first2=Marios|last3=Oskouian|first3=Rod J.|last4=Tubbs|first4=R. Shane|date=August 2018|title=Let's get a hand on this: Review of the clinical anatomy of &quot;knuckle cracking&quot;|journal=Clinical Anatomy|language=en|volume=31|issue=6|pages=942–945|doi=10.1002/ca.23243|pmid=30080300|issn=0897-3806}}&lt;/ref&gt;  A study published in 2011 examined the hand radiographs of 215 people (aged 50 to 89) and compared the joints of those who regularly cracked their knuckles to those who did not.&lt;ref name=&quot;Deweber&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Deweber K, Olszewski M, Ortolano R | title = Knuckle cracking and hand osteoarthritis | journal = J Am Board Fam Med | pages = 169–174 | year = 2011 | doi = 10.3122/jabfm.2011.02.100156| pmc = | volume = 24 | pmid=21383216 | issue = 2}}&lt;/ref&gt; The study concluded that knuckle-cracking did not cause hand osteoarthritis, no matter how many years or how often a person cracked their knuckles.&lt;ref name=&quot;Deweber&quot;/&gt; A 1990 study also concluded that there was no increased preponderance of arthritis of the hand of chronic knuckle-crackers but that habitual knuckle-crackers were more likely to have hand swelling and lowered grip strength.&lt;ref name=&quot;Castellanos&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Castellanos|first1=Jorge|last2=Axelrod| first2=David | title = Effect of habitual knuckle cracking on hand function | journal = Annals of the Rheumatic Diseases | pages = 308–9 | year = May 1990 | doi = 10.1136/ard.49.5.308 | pmc = 1004074 | volume = 49 | pmid=2344210 | issue = 5}}&lt;/ref&gt; It claimed further that habitual knuckle-cracking was associated with manual labour, [[Nail biting|biting of the nails]], [[smoking]], and [[drinking alcohol]] and suggested it resulted in functional hand impairment.&lt;ref name=&quot;Castellanos&quot;/&gt; This early study has been criticized for not taking into consideration the possibility of confounding factors, such as whether the ability to crack one's knuckles is associated with impaired hand functioning rather than being a cause of it. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Simkin|first=Peter|title=Habitual knuckle cracking and hand function.|journal=Annals of the Rheumatic Diseases|date=November 1990 |volume=49 |issue=11 |page=957 |doi=10.1136/ard.49.11.957-b|pmid=2256753|pmc=1004281}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Crepitus]]—sounds made by joints

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Cracking Joints}}
[[Category:Articles containing video clips]]
[[Category:Habits]]
[[Category:Joints]]</text>
      <sha1>jo5bxjnece6y9twz87v7e83fspippsa</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
