  <page>
    <title>Dennis Hopper</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8791</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942767452</id>
      <parentid>940954634</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-26T18:27:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rescuing 1 sources and tagging 0 as dead.) #IABot (v2.0</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|American actor and film director}}
{{Use American English|date=September 2019}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=September 2019}}
{{Infobox person
| name          = Dennis Hopper
| image         = Dennis Hopper Cannes 2008.jpg
| caption       = Hopper at the [[2008 Cannes Film Festival]]
| birth_date    = {{birth date|1936|5|17}}
| birth_place   = [[Dodge City, Kansas]], U.S.
| death_date    = {{death date and age|2010|5|29|1936|5|17}}
| death_place   = {{nowrap|[[Venice, Los Angeles]], [[California]], U.S.}}
| nationality   = American
| resting_place = Jesus Nazareno Cemetery, [[Ranchos de Taos, New Mexico]]
| education     = [[Helix High School]]
| alma_mater    = [[Actors Studio]]
| notable_works = [[Dennis Hopper filmography|Filmography]]
| occupation    = {{hlist|Actor|filmmaker|photographer|artist}}
| years_active  = 1954–2010
| party         = [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican]]
| spouse        = {{marriage|[[Brooke Hayward]]|1961|1969|end=divorced}}&lt;br&gt;{{marriage|[[Michelle Phillips]]|October 31, 1970|November 8, 1970|end=divorced}}&lt;br&gt;{{marriage|[[Daria Halprin]]|1972|1976|end=divorced}}&lt;br&gt;{{marriage|[[Katherine LaNasa]]|June 17, 1989|April 1992|end=divorced}}&lt;br&gt;{{marriage|Victoria Duffy|April 13, 1996|2010|end=[[Legal separation|{{abbr|sep.|separation}}]]}}
| children      = 4
| family        =
| awards        = See [[#Awards|awards]]
}}
'''Dennis Lee Hopper''' (May 17, 1936 – May 29, 2010) was an American actor, filmmaker, photographer, and artist. He attended the [[Actors Studio]], made his first television appearance in 1954, and soon after appeared alongside [[James Dean]] in ''[[Rebel Without a Cause]]'' (1955), and ''[[Giant (1956 film)|Giant]]'' (1956). In the next ten years he made a name in television, and by the end of the 1960s had appeared in several films, notably ''[[Cool Hand Luke]]'' (1967) and ''[[Hang 'Em High]]'' (1968). Hopper also began a prolific and acclaimed photography career in the 1960s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dennis Hopper&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/obituaries/culture-obituaries/film-obituaries/7786470/Dennis-Hopper.html | location=London | work=The Daily Telegraph | title=Dennis Hopper | date=May 30, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Hopper made his directorial film debut with ''[[Easy Rider]]'' (1969), which he and co-star [[Peter Fonda]] wrote with [[Terry Southern]]. The film earned Hopper a [[Cannes Film Festival]] Award for &quot;Best First Work&quot; and a nomination for the [[Academy Award for Best Original Screenplay]] (shared with Fonda and Southern). Journalist Ann Hornaday wrote: &quot;With its portrait of [[counterculture of the 1960s|counterculture]] heroes raising their middle fingers to the uptight middle-class hypocrisies, ''Easy Rider'' became the cinematic symbol of the 1960s, a celluloid anthem to freedom, macho bravado and anti-establishment rebellion&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Hornaday, Ann (May 29, 2010). [https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2010/05/29/AR2010052903020.html Dennis Hopper's influential career came full-circle]. ''washingtonpost.com''; The Washington Post. Retrieved 2010-05-30.&lt;/ref&gt; Film critic Matthew Hays wrote &quot;no other persona better signifies the lost idealism of the 1960s than that of Dennis Hopper&quot;.&lt;ref name=Hays&gt;Unterburger, Amy L. (editor) ''International Dictionary of Films and Filmmakers – vol 3 Actors and Actresses'', St. James Press (1997) p. 564&lt;/ref&gt;

Following the critical and commercial failure of his second film as director, ''[[The Last Movie]]'' (1971), he worked on various [[Independent film|independent]] and foreign projects - in which he was frequently [[typecast]] as mentally disturbed outsiders in such films as ''[[Mad Dog Morgan]]'' (1976) and ''[[The American Friend]]'' (1977) - until he found new fame for his role as an American photojournalist in ''[[Apocalypse Now]]'' (1979). He went on to helm his third directorial work ''[[Out of the Blue (1980 film)|Out of the Blue]]'' (1980), for which he was again honored at Cannes, and appeared in ''[[Rumble Fish]]'' (1983) and ''[[The Osterman Weekend (film)|The Osterman Weekend]]'' (1983). He saw a career resurgence in 1986 when he was widely acclaimed for his performances in ''[[Blue Velvet (film)|Blue Velvet]]'' and ''[[Hoosiers (film)|Hoosiers]]'', the latter of which saw him nominated for the [[Academy Award for Best Supporting Actor]]. His fourth directorial outing came about through ''[[Colors (film)|Colors]]'' (1988), followed by an [[Emmy]]-nominated lead performance in ''[[Paris Trout]]'' (1991). Hopper found greater fame for portraying the villains of the films ''[[Super Mario Bros. (film)|Super Mario Bros.]]'' (1993), ''[[Speed (1994 film)|Speed]]'' (1994) and ''[[Waterworld]]'' (1995).

Hopper's later work included a leading role in the short-lived television series ''[[Crash (2008 TV series)|Crash]]'' (2008–2009), inspired by the [[Crash (2004 film)|film of the same name]]. He appeared in three films released posthumously: ''[[Alpha and Omega (film)|Alpha and Omega]]'' (2010), ''[[The Last Film Festival]]'' (2016)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.indiewire.com/2016/06/dennis-hopper-the-last-film-festival-linda-yellen-1201691519/|title=Dennis Hopper's 'The Last Film Festival' Acquired by Monterey Media – IndieWire|first=Michael|last=Nordine|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the long-delayed ''[[The Other Side of the Wind]]'' (2018), which had been filmed in the early 1970s.&lt;ref name=&quot;swan song&quot;&gt;[http://www.indiewire.com/2017/03/netflix-the-other-side-of-the-wind-orson-welles-unfinished-1201793651/ Netflix Acquires 'The Other Side of the Wind,' Orson Welles' Unfinished Swan Song]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Early life ==
Hopper was born on May 17, 1936, in [[Dodge City, Kansas]], the son of Marjorie Mae (née Davis; July 12, 1917 – January 12, 2007)&lt;ref name=&quot;SSDI&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ssdi.rootsweb.ancestry.com |title=Social Security Death Index |publisher=Ssdi.rootsweb.ancestry.com |date= |accessdate=2010-06-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Staff (March 11, 2008). [http://www.contactmusic.com/news.nsf/story/republican-hopper-considers-a-vote-for-obama_1062239 Dennis Hopper – Republican Hopper considers a vote for Obama]. ContactMusic.com. Retrieved 2010-05-29.&lt;/ref&gt; and James Millard Hopper&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/culture/film/7783681/Dennis-Hopper-Born-to-be-wild.html|title=Dennis Hopper: Born to be wild|newspaper=[[The Daily Telegraph]]|author1=Philip Sherwell |author2=Robert Mendick | date=May 29, 2010| accessdate=2010-09-06| location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; (June 23, 1916 – August 7, 1982). He had Scottish ancestors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2009/feb/21/1 | location=London | work=The Guardian | first=Rosanna | last=Greenstreet | title=Q&amp;A | date=February 21, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hopper had two brothers, Marvin and David.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/northamerica/usa/7799095/Jack-Nicholson-pays-tribute-to-soul-mate-Dennis-Hopper.html|title=Jack Nicholson pays tribute to 'soul mate' Dennis Hopper | location=London | work=The Daily Telegraph|date=June 2, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After World War II, the family moved to Kansas City, Missouri, where the young Hopper attended Saturday art classes at the [[Kansas City Art Institute]]. When he was 13, Hopper and his family moved to San Diego, where his mother worked as a lifeguard instructor and his father was a post office manager, having previously served in the [[Office of Strategic Services]], the precursor to the [[Central Intelligence Agency]], in World War II.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://tv.zap2it.com/tveditorial/tve_main/1,1002,271%7C98259%7C1%7C,00.html |author=O'Hare, Cate |title=Hopper Evolves From Rebel to Republican |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070828103035/http://tv.zap2it.com/tveditorial/tve_main/1%2C1002%2C271%7C98259%7C1%7C%2C00.html |url-status=dead |archivedate=August 28, 2007 |publisher=Tribune Media Services |work=Zap2It.com |date=October 26, 2005 |accessdate=May 31, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hopper was voted most likely to succeed at [[Helix High School]], where he was active in the drama club, speech and choir.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Helix High's Hopper rebels without pause|date=February 4, 1990|newspaper=The San Diego Union-Tribune|page=E-1|first=Divina|last=Infusino}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was there that he developed an interest in acting, studying at the [[Old Globe Theatre]] in San Diego,&lt;!--&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.filmcatcher.com/interview_detail/141/620/ |title=Archived copy |accessdate=November 12, 2008 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20081207033043/http://www.filmcatcher.com/interview_detail/141/620/ |archivedate=December 7, 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt; rm horrible blog cite --&gt; and the [[Actors Studio]] in New York City (he studied with [[Lee Strasberg]] for five years). Hopper struck up a friendship with actor [[Vincent Price]], whose passion for art influenced Hopper's interest in art. He was especially fond of the plays of [[William Shakespeare]].

==Career==

===Film===
Hopper was reported to have an uncredited role in ''[[Johnny Guitar]]'' in 1954 but he has stated that he was not in Hollywood when this film was made.&lt;ref name=&quot;AVCRR&quot;&gt;Murray, Noel (December 2, 2008). [http://www.avclub.com/content/feature/random_roles_dennis_hopper Random Roles with Dennis Hopper] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20081203122236/http://www.avclub.com/content/feature/random_roles_dennis_hopper |date=December 3, 2008 }}. ''[[The A.V. Club]]'', Onion Inc. Retrieved 2010-05-29.&lt;/ref&gt; Hopper made his debut on film in two roles with [[James Dean]] (whom he admired immensely) in ''[[Rebel Without a Cause]]'' (1955) and ''[[Giant (1956 film)|Giant]]'' (1956). Dean's death in a 1955 car accident affected the young Hopper deeply and it was shortly afterwards that he got into a confrontation with veteran director [[Henry Hathaway]] on the film ''[[From Hell to Texas]]'' (1958). Hopper forced Hathaway to shoot more than 80 takes of a scene over several days before he acquiesced to Hathaway's direction. After filming was finally completed, Hathaway allegedly told Hopper that his career in Hollywood was finished.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Wyatt|first=Edward|title=Dennis Hopper, 74, Hollywood Rebel, Dies|  url=https://www.nytimes.com/2010/05/30/movies/30hopper.html|newspaper=New York Times| date=May 29, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In his book ''Last Train to Memphis'', American popular music historian [[Peter Guralnick]] says that in 1956, when [[Elvis Presley]] was making his first film in Hollywood, Hopper was roommates with fellow actor [[Nick Adams (actor, born 1931)|Nick Adams]] and the three became friends and socialized together. In 1959 Hopper moved to New York to study Method acting under Lee Strasberg at the Actors Studio.&lt;ref&gt;Noever, Peter. ''Dennis Hopper: a System of Moments'', Hatje Cantz Publishers (2001) p. 258&lt;/ref&gt; In 1961, Hopper played his first lead role in ''[[Night Tide]]'', an atmospheric supernatural thriller involving a mermaid in an amusement park.

In a December 1994 interview on the ''[[Charlie Rose Show]]'', Hopper credited [[John Wayne]] with saving his career, as Hopper acknowledged that because of his insolent behavior, he could not find work in Hollywood for seven years. Hopper stated that because he was the son-in-law of actress [[Margaret Sullavan]], a friend of John Wayne, Wayne hired Hopper for a role in ''[[The Sons of Katie Elder]]'' (1965), also directed by Hathaway, which enabled Hopper to restart his film career.&lt;ref&gt;Charlie Rose (December 21, 1994). [http://www.charlierose.com/view/interview/7142 Dennis Hopper Interview] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100608221033/http://www.charlierose.com/view/interview/7142 |date=June 8, 2010 }} (video). ''CharlieRose.com''; Charlie Rose LLC. Retrieved 2010-05-29.&lt;/ref&gt; Hopper acted in another John Wayne film, ''[[True Grit (1969 film)|True Grit]]'' (1969), and during its production he became well acquainted with Wayne. In both of the films with Wayne, Hopper's character is killed in the presence of Wayne's character, to whom he utters his dying words.

[[File:Hopper Rider.jpg|thumb|left|Hopper in ''Easy Rider'' wearing then radical long hair and mustache]]
Hopper had a supporting role as the bet-taker, &quot;Babalugats&quot;, in ''[[Cool Hand Luke]]'' (1967). In 1968, Hopper teamed with [[Peter Fonda]], [[Terry Southern]] and [[Jack Nicholson]] to make ''[[Easy Rider]]'', which premiered in July 1969. With the release of ''[[True Grit (1969 film)|True Grit]]'' a month earlier, Hopper had starring roles in two major box office films that summer. Hopper won wide acclaim as the director for his improvisational methods and innovative editing for ''Easy Rider''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Biskind2011&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Peter Biskind|title=Easy Riders Raging Bulls: How the Sex-Drugs-And Rock 'N Roll Generation Save|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=J3ucTdpeE9YC&amp;pg=PA74|accessdate=November 18, 2012|date=December 13, 2011|publisher=Simon and Schuster|isbn=978-1-4391-2661-5|pages=74–}}&lt;/ref&gt; The production was plagued by creative differences and personal acrimony between Fonda and Hopper, the dissolution of Hopper's marriage to Hayward, his unwillingness to leave the editor's desk and his accelerating abuse of drugs and alcohol.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Peter Biskind|title=Easy Riders Raging Bulls: How the Sex-Drugs-And Rock 'N Roll Generation Save|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=J3ucTdpeE9YC&amp;pg=PA71|accessdate=November 19, 2012|date=December 13, 2011|publisher=Simon and Schuster|isbn=978-1-4391-2661-5|pages=71–}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hopper said of ''Easy Rider'': &quot;The cocaine problem in the United States is really because of me. There was no cocaine before Easy Rider on the street. After Easy Rider, it was everywhere&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jahsonic.com/NewHollywood.html|title=New Hollywood (1967–1977)|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Besides showing drug use on film, it was one of the first films to portray the hippie lifestyle. Hopper became a stereotype for some male youths who rejected traditional jobs and traditional American culture, partly exemplified by Fonda's long sideburns and Hopper wearing shoulder-length hair and a long mustache. They were denied rooms in motels and proper service in restaurants as a result of their radical looks.&lt;ref name=Hillman&gt;Hillman, Betty Luther. ''Dressing for the Culture Wars: Style and the Politics of Self-Presentation in the 1960s and 1970s'', Univ. of Nebraska Press (2015) e-book&lt;/ref&gt; Their long hair became a point of contention in various scenes during the film.&lt;ref name=Hillman/&gt;

Hopper was unable to capitalize on his ''Easy Rider'' success for several years. In 1970 he filmed ''The Last Movie'', cowritten by Stewart Stern and photographed by Laszlo Kovacs in Peru, and completed production in 1971. It won the prestigious CIDALC Award at that year's Venice Film Festival, but Universal Studios leaders expected a blockbuster like ''Easy Rider'', and did not like the film or give it an enthusiastic release, while American film audiences found it confounding – as convoluted as an abstract painting. On viewing the first release print, fresh from the lab, in his screening room at Universal, MCA founder Jules Stein rose from his chair and said, &quot;I just don't understand this younger generation.&quot;  &lt;ref&gt;Rol Murrow, quoted in book ''&quot;HOPPER&quot;'' by Tom Folsom (2013)&lt;/ref&gt; During the tumultuous editing process, Hopper ensconced himself at the [[Mabel Dodge Luhan House]] in Taos, New Mexico, which he had purchased in 1970,&lt;ref name=&quot;Thompson&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nmmagazine.com/outings_mdlhouse_feb10.php|title=Outings: Mabel Dodge Luhan House|last=Thompson|first=Linda|work=[[New Mexico Magazine]]|accessdate=August 7, 2010|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100504093655/http://www.nmmagazine.com/outings_mdlhouse_feb10.php|archivedate=May 4, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; for almost an entire year. In between contesting Fonda's rights to the majority of the residual profits from ''Easy Rider'', he married singer [[Michelle Phillips]] of [[The Mamas and the Papas]]  on [[Halloween]] of 1970. The marriage lasted eight days.

Hopper was able to sustain his lifestyle and a measure of celebrity by acting in numerous [[low budget]] and European films throughout the 1970s as the archetypal &quot;tormented maniac&quot;, including ''[[Mad Dog Morgan]]'' (1976), ''[[Tracks (1976 film)|Tracks]]'' (1976), and ''[[The American Friend]]'' (1977). With [[Francis Ford Coppola]]'s blockbuster ''[[Apocalypse Now]]'' (1979), Hopper returned to prominence as a hyper-manic Vietnam-era photojournalist. Stepping in for an overwhelmed director, Hopper won praise in 1980 for his directing and acting in ''[[Out of the Blue (1980 film)|Out of the Blue]]''. Immediately thereafter, Hopper starred as an addled short-order cook &quot;Cracker&quot; in the [[Neil Young]]/[[Dean Stockwell]] low-budget collaboration ''[[Human Highway]]''. Production was reportedly often delayed by his unreliable behavior. [[Peter Biskind]] states in the [[New Hollywood]] history ''Easy Riders, Raging Bulls'' that Hopper's cocaine intake had reached three grams a day by this time, complemented by 30 beers, and some marijuana and [[Cuba libre]]s.

After staging a &quot;suicide attempt&quot; (really more of a daredevil act) in a coffin using 17 sticks of dynamite during an &quot;art happening&quot; at the Rice University Media Center (filmed by professor and documentary filmmaker Brian Huberman),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.brianhuberman.com/about/ |title=Brian Huberman About Brian Hubberman |publisher=Brianhuberman.com |date=January 5, 1995 |accessdate=2013-01-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; and later disappearing into the Mexican desert during a particularly extravagant bender, Hopper entered a [[drug rehabilitation]] program in 1983.

Though Hopper gave critically acclaimed performances in Coppola's ''[[Rumble Fish]]'' (1983) and [[Sam Peckinpah]]'s ''[[The Osterman Weekend (film)|The Osterman Weekend]]'' (1983), it was not until he portrayed the gas-huffing, obscenity-screaming iconic villain [[Frank Booth (Blue Velvet)|Frank Booth]] in [[David Lynch]]'s ''[[Blue Velvet (film)|Blue Velvet]]'' (1986) that his career truly revived. On reading the script Hopper said to Lynch: &quot;You have to let me play Frank Booth. Because I am Frank Booth!&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Egan, Barry (November 2, 2007). [http://www.independent.ie/entertainment/film-cinema/keeping-your-hair-on-1210900.html Keeping your hair on]. [[Irish Independent|The Independent]]. Retrieved 2010-05-29.&lt;/ref&gt; He won critical acclaim and several awards for this role, and in the same year received an Oscar nomination for Best Supporting Actor for his role as an alcoholic assistant basketball coach in ''[[Hoosiers (film)|Hoosiers]]''. Also in 1986, Hopper portrayed Lt. Enright in the [[comedy horror]] ''[[The Texas Chainsaw Massacre 2]]''. In 1988, he directed ''[[Colors (film)|Colors]]'', a critically acclaimed [[police procedural]] about gang violence in Los Angeles starring [[Sean Penn]] and [[Robert Duvall]].

He was nominated for an [[Emmy Award]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.emmys.com/celebrities/dennis-hopper |title=Dennis Hopper Emmy Nominated |publisher=Emmys.com |date= |accessdate=2013-01-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; for the 1991 HBO film ''Paris Trout''. Shortly thereafter, he played drug smuggler and [[Drug Enforcement Administration|DEA]] informant [[Barry Seal]] in the HBO film ''Doublecrossed''. He starred as [[Bowser (character)|King Koopa]] in ''[[Super Mario Bros. (film)|Super Mario Bros.]]'', a 1993 critical and commercial failure loosely based on the video game of the same name.&lt;ref name=&quot;AVCRR&quot;/&gt; In 1993, he played Clifford Worley in ''[[True Romance]]''. He co-starred in the 1994 blockbuster ''[[Speed (1994 film)|Speed]]'' with [[Keanu Reeves]] and [[Sandra Bullock]], and as magic-phobic [[H.P. Lovecraft]] in the TV movie ''[[Witch Hunt (1994 film)|Witch Hunt]]''.

In 1995, Hopper played a greedy TV self-help guru, Dr. Luther Waxling in ''[[Search and Destroy (1995 film)|Search and Destroy]]''. The same year, he starred as Deacon, the one-eyed nemesis of Kevin Costner in ''[[Waterworld]]''. And in 1996 he starred in the science fiction comedy ''[[Space Truckers]]'' directed by [[Stuart Gordon]]. In 1999, he starred in The Prophet's Game (a dark thriller), Directed by David Worth and also starring [[Stephanie Zimbalist]], Robert Yocum, [[Sondra Locke|Sandra Locke]], [[Joe Penny]] and [[Tracey Birdsall]]. In 2003, Hopper was in the running for the dual lead in the indie horror drama ''[[Firecracker (film)|Firecracker]]'', but was ousted at the last minute in favor of [[Mike Patton]]. In 2005, Hopper played Paul Kaufman in George A. Romero's ''[[Land of the Dead]]''. In 2008, Hopper starred in ''[[An American Carol]]''. In 2008 he also played The Death in [[Wim Wenders]]' ''[[Palermo Shooting]]''. His last major feature film appearance was in the 2008 film ''[[Elegy (film)|Elegy]]'' with [[Ben Kingsley]], [[Penélope Cruz]] and [[Debbie Harry]]. For his last performance, he was the voice of Tony, the alpha-male of the Eastern wolf pack inside the 2010 3D computer animated film ''[[Alpha and Omega (film)|Alpha and Omega]]''. He died before the movie was released. This brought the directors to dedicate the film to his memory at the beginning of the movie credits.

Hopper filmed scenes for ''[[The Other Side of the Wind]]'' in 1971, appearing as himself; after decades of legal, financial and technical delays, the film was finally released on [[Netflix]] in 2018.&lt;ref name=&quot;swan song&quot; /&gt;

===Television===
Hopper debuted in an episode of the Richard Boone television series ''[[Medic (TV series)|Medic]]'' in 1955, portraying a young [[epilepsy|epileptic]].

He appeared as an arrogant young gunfighter, the Utah Kid, in the 1956 episode &quot;Quicksand&quot; of the first hour-long [[western (genre)|western]] television series ''[[Cheyenne (TV series)|Cheyenne]]'', starring [[Clint Walker]]. In the story line, the Kid gave Cheyenne Bodie no choice but to kill him in a gunfight. In 1957 Hopper played thief Abe Larson in another ''[[Cheyenne (TV series)|Cheyenne]]'' episode titled &quot;The Iron Trail.&quot; In 1957, he played [[Billy the Kid]] on the episode &quot;Brannigan's Boots&quot; of ''[[Sugarfoot]]'' with [[Will Hutchins]].

He subsequently appeared in over 140 episodes of television shows such as ''[[Gunsmoke]]'', ''[[Bonanza]]'', ''[[Petticoat Junction]]'', ''[[The Twilight Zone (1959 TV series)|The Twilight Zone]]'', ''[[The Barbara Stanwyck Show]]'', ''[[The Defenders (1961 TV series)|The Defenders]]'', ''[[The Investigators (American TV series)|The Investigators]]'', ''[[The Legend of Jesse James (TV series)|The Legend of Jesse James]]'', ''[[Entourage (U.S. TV series)|Entourage]]'', ''[[The Big Valley]]'', ''[[The Time Tunnel]]'', ''[[The Rifleman]]'' in which he appeared in the premier episode as a sharpshooter&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.riflemanconnors.com/dennis_hopper.htm|title=Dennis Hopper|publisher=Riflemanconnors.com |date=May 17, 1936|accessdate=2009-11-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; and ''[[Combat!]]''.

Hopper teamed with Nike in the early 1990s to make a series of television commercials. He appeared as a &quot;crazed referee&quot; in those ads.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tailgatingideas.com/dennis-hopper-nike-football-commercials/|title=A Collection of the Dennis Hopper &quot;Crazy Ref&quot; Commercials – Tailgating Ideas|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; He portrayed villain [[Victor Drazen]] in the first season of the popular drama ''[[24 (TV series)|24]]''.

Hopper appeared on the final two episodes of the cult 1991 television show ''[[Fishing with John]]'' with host ''[[John Lurie]]''.

Hopper starred as a U.S. Army colonel in the 2005 television series ''[[E-Ring]]'', a drama set at [[The Pentagon]], but the series was cancelled after 14 episodes aired. Hopper appeared in all 22 episodes that were filmed. He also played the part of record producer Ben Cendars in the Starz television series ''[[Crash (2008 TV series)|Crash]]'', which lasted two seasons (26 episodes).

==Photography and art==
[[File:Dennis Hopper hat.jpg|thumb|Hopper in June 2008]]
Hopper had several artistic pursuits beyond film. He was a prolific photographer, painter, and sculptor.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hopper art show opens&quot;&gt;Staff (February 20, 2001) [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/entertainment/1180943.stm Hopper art show opens]. ''BBC.com'', [[BBC]]. Retrieved 2010-05-29.&lt;/ref&gt;

Hopper's fascination with art began with painting lessons at the [[Nelson-Atkins Museum]] while still a child in Kansas City, Missouri.&lt;ref name=&quot;articles.latimes.com&quot;&gt;Jessica Hundley (July 11, 2010), [http://articles.latimes.com/2010/jul/11/entertainment/la-ca-dennis-hopper-20100711 Dennis Hopper, easy-rider art enthusiast] ''[Los Angeles Times]''.&lt;/ref&gt; Early in his career, he painted and wrote poetry, though many of his works were destroyed in a 1961 fire that burned scores of homes, including his, on Stone Canyon Road&lt;ref name=&quot;Once Upon a Time in L.A&quot;&gt;Brooke Hayward (September 2001), [http://www.vanityfair.com/hollywood/classic/features/making-of-easy-rider-200109 Once Upon a Time in L.A.] ''[[Vanity Fair (magazine)|Vanity Fair]]''.&lt;/ref&gt; in [[Bel Air, Los Angeles|Bel Air]].&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimes.com&quot;&gt;Edward Wyatt (May 29, 2010), [https://www.nytimes.com/2010/05/30/movies/30hopper.html Dennis Hopper, 74, Hollywood Rebel, Dies] ''[[The New York Times]]''.&lt;/ref&gt; His painting style ranges from [[abstract impressionism]] to [[photorealism]] and often includes references to his cinematic work and to other artists.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dennis Hopper&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Dennis Hopper, Jan-Hein Sassen &amp; Rudi Fuchs, ''Dennis Hopper: Paintings, Photographs, Films'' (Amsterdam: NAi Publishers/Stedelijk Museum, 2001) {{ISBN|90-5662-195-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Ostracized by the Hollywood film studios due to his reputation for being a &quot;difficult&quot; actor, Hopper turned to photography in the 1960s with a camera bought for him by his first wife [[Brooke Hayward]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Once Upon a Time in L.A&quot;/&gt; During this period he created the cover art for the [[Ike &amp; Tina Turner]] single ''[[River Deep – Mountain High]]'' (released in 1966).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=The World's Greatest Heartbreaker|work=[[Rolling Stone]]|last=Fong-Torres|first=Ben|authorlink=Ben Fong-Torres|date=October 14, 1971|page=2|url=https://www.rollingstone.com/news/story/17617414/cover_story_the_worlds_greatest_heartbreaker| archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090525233209/http://www.rollingstone.com/news/story/17617414/cover_story_the_worlds_greatest_heartbreaker/print |archivedate=May 25, 2009| accessdate=2012-09-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; He would become a prolific photographer, and noted writer [[Terry Southern]] profiled Hopper in ''Better Homes and Gardens]'' as an up-and-coming photographer &quot;to watch&quot; in the mid-1960s. Hopper's early photography is known for portraits from the 1960s, and he began shooting portraits for ''Vogue'' and other magazines. His photographs of Martin Luther King, Jr.'s 1963 March on Washington and 1965 civil-rights march in Selma, Alabama, were published. His intimate and unguarded images of celebrities like Andy Warhol and [[Jane Fonda]] were the subject of gallery shows and were collected in a book, &quot;1712 North Crescent Heights&quot;. The book, whose title was his address in the [[Hollywood Hills]] in the 1960s, was edited by Marin Hopper.&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimes.com&quot;/&gt; In 1960–67, before the making of ''Easy Rider'', Hopper shot a selection of groundbreaking images that is seen as telling a remarkable history of art, artist, places and events of that time.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tonyshafrazigallery.com/index.php?mode=past&amp;object_id=90&amp;view=bio Edward Ruscha and Dennis Hopper: New Work, April 25 – May 22, 1992] [[Tony Shafrazi|Tony Shafrazy Gallery]], New York.&lt;/ref&gt; ''Dennis Hopper: Photographs 1961–1967'' was published in February 2011, by [[Taschen]].&lt;ref&gt;Walsh, John, [https://www.independent.co.uk/arts-entertainment/books/features/rebel-with-a-camera-dennis-hoppers-stunning-photographic-archive-is-revealed-2216480.html &quot;Rebel with a camera: Dennis Hopper's stunning photographic archive is revealed&quot;], ''The Independent'', February 19, 2011. Retrieved 2011-04-12.&lt;/ref&gt;

Hopper began working as a painter and a poet as well as a collector of art in the 1960s as well, particularly [[Pop Art]]. Over his lifetime he amassed a formidable array of 20th- and 21st-century art, including many of [[Julian Schnabel]]'s works (such as a shattered-plate portrait of Hopper); numerous works from his early cohorts, such as [[Ed Ruscha]], [[Edward Kienholz]], [[Roy Lichtenstein]] (''Sinking Sun'', 1964),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine | last=Hopper | first=Marin | date=June 6, 2012 | title=Marin Hopper's Malibu Memories | magazine=[[Harper's Bazaar]] | url=http://www.harpersbazaar.com/magazine/feature-articles/marin-hopper-malibu-childhood-0612 | archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131019220113/http://www.harpersbazaar.com/culture/features/marin-hopper-malibu-childhood-0612 | archive-date=October 19, 2013 | url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; and Warhol (''Double Mona Lisa'', 1963);&lt;ref name=&quot;Once Upon a Time in L.A&quot;/&gt; and pieces by contemporary artists such as [[Damien Hirst]] and [[Robin Rhode]]. He was involved in L.A.'s [[Virginia Dwan]] and [[Ferus]] galleries of the 1960s, and he was a longtime friend and supporter to New York dealer [[Tony Shafrazi]].&lt;ref name=&quot;articles.latimes.com&quot;/&gt; One of the first art works Hopper owned was an early print of [[Andy Warhol]]'s [[Campbell's Soup Cans]] bought for US$75. Hopper also once owned Warhol's ''Mao'', which he shot one evening in a fit of paranoia, the two bullet holes possibly adding to the print's value. The print sold at Christie's, New York, for US$302,500 in January 2011.&lt;ref name=christie&gt;[http://www.christies.com/lotfinder/prints-multiples/andy-warhol-in-collaboration-with-dennis-5399542-details.aspx Sale 2412 Lot 37: Andy Warhol (1928–1987) In Collaboration With Dennis Hopper (1936–2010)]. Christie's, New York. Accessed September 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; The proceeds of the two-day sale of some 300 pieces from Hopper's collection at Christie's went to his four children.&lt;ref&gt;Cynthia R. Fagen (January 12, 2011), [http://www.nypost.com/p/news/national/dennis_put_the_pop_in_pop_art_zzgXHKTJyJckcpDhc4pQHM#ixzz26r2vZxw7 Hopper's shot-up War-'hole' fetches 300G] ''[[New York Sun]]''.&lt;/ref&gt;

During his lifetime, Hopper's own work as well as his collection was shown in monographic and group exhibitions around the world including theCorcoran Gallery of Art, Washington D.C.; Walker Art Center, Minneapolis, Minnesota; the Stedelijk Museum, Amsterdam; the [[State Hermitage Museum]], St. Petersburg; MAK Vienna: Austrian Museum of Applied Arts/Contemporary Art, Vienna; the Whitney Museum of American Art, New York; and the Cinémathèque Française, Paris, and the Australian Centre for the Moving Image, Melbourne. In March 2010, it was announced that Hopper was on the &quot;short list&quot; for Jeffrey Deitch's inaugural show at the Museum of Contemporary Art, Los Angeles (MOCA).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://flavorwire.com/80848/dennis-hopper-said-to-be-shortlisted-for-deitch-debut-at-la-moca |title=Dennis Hopper to be Deitch's Debut at LA MOCA |author=Kelsey Keith |publisher=Flavorpill| work=Flavorwire.com| date=March 30, 2010| accessdate=2010-05-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; In April 2010, Deitch confirmed that Hopper's work, curated by Julian Schnabel, will indeed be the focus of his debut at MOCA.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://latimesblogs.latimes.com/culturemonster/2010/04/deitch-on-first-show-at-moca-dennis-hopper-art-curated-by-julian-schnabel-.html|title=Jeffrey Deitch's first show at MOCA: Dennis Hopper, curated by Julian Schnabel |author=Finkel, Jori| publisher=[[Los Angeles Times]]|work=Culture Monster| date=April 15, 2010|accessdate=2010-05-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; The title of the exhibition, ''Double Standard'', was taken from Hopper's iconic 1961 photograph of the two Standard Oil signs seen through an automobile windshield at the intersection of Santa Monica Boulevard, Melrose Avenue, and North Doheny Drive on historic [[U.S. Route 66|Route 66]] in Los Angeles. The image was reproduced on the invitation for [[Ed Ruscha]]'s second solo exhibition at Ferus Gallery in 1964.

In 2013, Harper Collins published ''Hopper: A Journey into the American Dream'', a biography on Hopper by American writer [[Tom Folsom]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Folsom |first=Tom |url=http://www.harpercollins.com/books/Hopper-Tom-Folsom/?isbn=9780062206947 |title=Hopper: A Journey into the American Dream |publisher=Harpercollins.com |date=March 24, 2010 |accessdate=2013-01-14 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130313170402/http://www.harpercollins.com/books/Hopper-Tom-Folsom?isbn=9780062206947 |archive-date=March 13, 2013 |url-status=dead |df=mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

On the [[Gorillaz]] album ''[[Demon Days]]'', Hopper narrates the song &quot;Fire Coming Out of the Monkey's Head&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://pitchfork.com/reviews/albums/3526-demon-days/|title=Gorillaz, Demon Days review| author=Mitchum, Rob| date=May 22, 2005 |publisher=Pitchfork Media Inc.| work=pitchfork.com| accessdate=2010-05-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the late 1980s, Hopper purchased a trio of nearly identical two-story, loft-style condominiums at 330 Indiana Avenue in Venice Beach, California – one made of concrete, one of plywood, and one of green roofing shingles – built by [[Frank Gehry]] and two artist friends of Hopper's, [[Chuck Arnoldi]] and Laddie John Dill, in 1981.&lt;ref&gt;[[Bob Colacello]] (August 2010), [http://www.vanityfair.com/culture/features/2010/08/dennis-hopper-201008 The City of Warring Angels] ''[[Vanity Fair (magazine)|Vanity Fair]]''.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1987, he commissioned an industrial-style main residence, with a corrugated metal exterior designed by Brian Murphy, as a place to display his artwork.&lt;ref&gt;Lauren Beale (August 4, 2012), [http://articles.latimes.com/2011/aug/04/home/la-hm-hotprop-dennis-hopper-20110804 Dennis Hopper's Venice property is back on the market] ''[Los Angeles Times]''.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Personal life==
[[File:DennisHopperJackNicholson.jpg|upright|thumb|right|alt=Dennis Hopper and Jack Nicholson wearing tuxedos and holding drinks |Hopper with [[Jack Nicholson]] at the [[62nd Academy Awards]] in 1990]]
According to ''Rolling Stone'' magazine, Hopper was &quot;one of Hollywood's most notorious drug addicts&quot; for 20 years. He spent much of the 1970s and early 1980s living as an &quot;outcast&quot; in [[Taos, New Mexico]] after the success of ''Easy Rider''. Hopper was also &quot;notorious for his troubled relationships with women&quot;, including [[Michelle Phillips]], who divorced him after eight days of marriage.&lt;ref name=&quot;RSObit&quot;&gt;{{cite web|
url=https://www.rollingstone.com/movies/news/hollywood-hellraiser-dennis-hopper-dies-at-74-20100529 |title=Hollywood Hellraiser Dennis Hopper Dies at 74| author=Matos, Michaelangelo| publisher=Rolling Stone| work=RollingStone.com| date=May 29, 2010| accessdate=March 11, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hopper was married five times:
* [[Brooke Hayward]], married 1961 – divorced 1969, 1 child, daughter Marin Hopper (b. 1962)
* [[Michelle Phillips]]; married October 31, 1970 – divorced November 8, 1970
* [[Daria Halprin]]; married 1972 – divorced 1976, 1 child, daughter [[Ruthanna Hopper]] (b. 1972)
* [[Katherine LaNasa]]; married June 17, 1989 – divorced April 1992, 1 child, son Henry Lee Hopper (b. 1990)
* Victoria Duffy; married April 13, 1996 – separated January 12, 2010, 1 child, daughter Galen Grier Hopper (b. 2003)

Hopper has been widely reported to be the godfather of actress [[Amber Tamblyn]];&lt;ref&gt;{{IMDb name|id=0848560|section=bio|name=Russ Tamblyn|accessdate=April 3, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; in a 2009 interview with ''Parade'', Tamblyn explained that &quot;godfather&quot; was &quot;just a loose term&quot; for Hopper, [[Dean Stockwell]] and [[Neil Young]], three famous friends of [[Russ Tamblyn|her father]]'s, who were always around the house when she was growing up, and who were big influences on her life.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Tamblyn|first=Amber|title=Amber Tamblyn: Confessions of a Child Star|url=http://www.parade.com/celebrity/2009/08/amber-tamblyn-confessions.html|work=Interview by Kevin Sessums, August 30, 2009|publisher=Parade Publications, Inc.|accessdate=April 3, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1994, [[Rip Torn]] filed a defamation lawsuit against Hopper over a story Hopper told on ''[[The Tonight Show with Jay Leno]]''. Hopper claimed that Torn pulled a knife on him during pre-production of the film ''[[Easy Rider]]''. According to Hopper, Torn was originally cast in the film but was replaced with [[Jack Nicholson]] after the incident. According to Torn's suit, it was actually Hopper who pulled the knife on him. A judge ruled in Torn's favor and Hopper was ordered to pay US$475,000 in damages. Hopper then appealed but the judge again ruled in Torn's favor and Hopper was required to pay another US$475,000 in punitive damages.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Court ruling doubles the 'Easy' score: Torn 2, Hopper zip| url=http://www.cnn.com/SHOWBIZ/News/9905/11/showbuzz/#story3| publisher=CNN| author=Staff| date=May 11, 1999|accessdate=2007-04-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Newsmeat, Hopper donated US$2,000 to the [[Republican National Committee]] in 2004 and an equal amount in 2005.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.newsmeat.com/celebrity_political_donations/Dennis_Hopper.php |title=NEWSMEAT ▷ Dennis Hopper's Federal Campaign Contribution Report |publisher=Newsmeat.com |date= |accessdate=2009-11-12 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20091231160308/http://newsmeat.com/celebrity_political_donations/Dennis_Hopper.php |archivedate=December 31, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Hopper was honored with the rank of commander of [[Ordre des Arts et des Lettres|France's National Order of Arts and Letters]], at a ceremony in Paris.&lt;ref&gt;Staff (October 15, 2008). [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/entertainment/7668813.stm French honour for Dennis Hopper]. [[BBC]] News. Retrieved 2010-05-29.&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite being a Republican, Hopper supported [[Barack Obama]] in the 2008 US [[United States presidential election|Presidential election]].&lt;ref&gt;AFP (October 13, 2008). [http://afp.google.com/article/ALeqM5j5EWRC22Nx_phjXpenOArhNeOUew Dennis Hopper praying for Obama victory] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20081015231035/http://afp.google.com/article/ALeqM5j5EWRC22Nx_phjXpenOArhNeOUew |date=October 15, 2008 }}. [[Agence France-Presse|AFP]]. Retrieved 2010-05-29.&lt;/ref&gt; Hopper confirmed this in an [[Election Day (politics)|election day]] appearance on the [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]] daytime show ''[[The View (U.S. TV series)|The View]]''. He said his reason for not voting Republican was the selection of [[Sarah Palin]] as the Republican [[vice presidential candidate]].&lt;ref&gt;Huffington Post (November 4, 2008). [http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2008/11/04/dennis-hopper-i-voted-for_n_140940.html Dennis Hopper: I Voted For Obama Because Of Palin] (video). ''The View''; [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]]. Via Huffington Post. Retrieved 2010-05-29.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Divorce from Victoria Duffy===
On January 14, 2010, Hopper filed for divorce from his fifth wife Victoria Duffy.&lt;ref&gt;Thomson, Katherine (January 15, 2010). [http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2010/01/15/dennis-hopper-divorce-sho_n_424589.html &quot;Dennis Hopper divorce shocker&quot;]. Huffington Post. Retrieved 2010-05-29.&lt;/ref&gt; After citing her &quot;outrageous conduct&quot; and stating she was &quot;insane&quot;, &quot;inhuman&quot; and &quot;volatile&quot;, Hopper was granted a restraining order against her on February 11, 2010, and as a result, she was forbidden to come within {{convert|10|ft|m|0}} of him or contact him.&lt;ref&gt;Sehgal, Samia (February 12, 2010). [http://www.themoneytimes.com/featured/20100212/dennis-hopper-gets-restraining-order-against-wife-id-10100264.html &quot;Dennis Hopper gets restraining order against wife&quot;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110721203650/http://www.themoneytimes.com/featured/20100212/dennis-hopper-gets-restraining-order-against-wife-id-10100264.html |date=July 21, 2011 }}. TheMoneyTimes.com. Retrieved 2010-05-29.&lt;/ref&gt; On March 9, 2010, Duffy refused to move out of the Hopper home, despite the court's order that she do so by March 15.&lt;ref&gt;Staff (March 10, 2010). [http://www.contactmusic.com/news.nsf/story/hoppers-wife-refuses-to-move-out_1134848 &quot;Hopper's Wife Refuses to Move Out&quot;]. ContactMusic.com. Retrieved 2010-05-29.&lt;/ref&gt;

On March 23, 2010, he filed papers in court alleging Duffy had absconded with US$1.5&amp;nbsp;million of his art, refused his requests to return it, and then had &quot;left town&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Staff (March 24, 2010). [http://www.nypost.com/p/pagesix/hopper_says_wife_stole_art_xDgwvsK5DFRqqUSb50Q1AN &quot;Dennis Hopper: Wife 'Stole' Valuable Art&quot;]. [[New York Post]]. Retrieved 2010-05-29.&lt;/ref&gt;

On April 5, 2010, a court ruled that Duffy could continue living on Hopper's property, and that he must pay US$12,000 per month spousal and child support for their daughter Galen. Hopper did not attend the hearing.&lt;ref&gt;Chubb, Tina (April 6, 2010). [http://www.inentertainment.co.uk/20100406/dennis-hopper-divorce-case-key-issues-settled-by-judge/ &quot;Dennis Hopper divorce case: key issues settled by judge&quot;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100409123310/http://www.inentertainment.co.uk/20100406/dennis-hopper-divorce-case-key-issues-settled-by-judge/ |date=April 9, 2010 }}. ''InEntertainment.co.uk''. Retrieved 2010-05-29.&lt;/ref&gt; On May 12, 2010, a hearing was held before Judge Amy Pellman in downtown Los Angeles Superior Court. Though Hopper died two weeks later, Duffy insisted at the hearing that he was well enough to be deposed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Finn&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.eonline.com/uberblog/b180743_dennis_hoppers_wife_wasnt_too_sick_pot.html |title=Dennis Hopper's Wife: He Wasn't Too sick for Pot Runs and Plane Rides| last=Finn| first=Natalie| date=May 12, 2010| work=[[E! Online|eonline.com]]|accessdate=August 18, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The hearing also dealt with whom to designate on Hopper's life insurance policy, which listed his wife as a beneficiary.&lt;ref&gt;Staff (April 6, 2010). [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/entertainment/arts_and_culture/8604410.stm &quot;Judge allows wife to live with Dennis Hopper&quot;]. ''news.BBC.co.uk''; BBC News. Retrieved 2010-05-29.&lt;/ref&gt; A very ill Hopper did not appear in court though his estranged wife did – case BD518046. Despite Duffy's bid to be named the sole beneficiary of Hopper's million-dollar policy, the judge ruled against her and limited her claim to one-quarter of the policy. The remaining US$750,000 was to go to his estate.&lt;ref&gt;James, Michael S. and Marikar, Sheila (May 29, 2010) [http://abcnews.go.com/Entertainment/Media/dennis-hopper-dies-age-74/story?id=10214007/ &quot;Dennis Hopper Dies at Age 74&quot;.] Retrieved 2010-08-10.&lt;/ref&gt;

On November 14, 2010, it was revealed that, despite Duffy's earlier assertion in her court papers of February 2010 that Hopper was mentally incompetent, and that his children had rewritten his estate plan in order to leave Duffy and her daughter, Hopper's youngest child Galen, destitute, Galen would in fact receive the proceeds of 40% of his estate.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nypost.com/nypost.com/p/pagesix/dennis_hopper_art_fetches_more_than_n2tfTMJ1eF845MT9g3MgFN &quot;Dennis Hopper Art Fetches More than $10 million at Auction&quot;]. NY Post. Retrieved 2010-11-18.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Illness and death==
[[File:DennisHopperSideMar10.jpg|thumb|Hopper at a ceremony to receive a star on the [[Hollywood Walk of Fame]] on March 26, 2010, two months before his death.]]
On September 28, 2009, Hopper, then 73, was reportedly brought by ambulance to an unidentified Manhattan hospital wearing an oxygen mask and &quot;with numerous tubes visible&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| author=Kate Stanhope|title=Dennis Hopper Hospitalized in New York| url=http://www.tvguide.com/News/Dennis-Hopper-Hospitalized-1010368.aspx| work=TVGuide.com|date=September 29, 2009| accessdate=2009-09-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; On October 2, he was discharged, after receiving treatment for dehydration.&lt;ref&gt;IANS (November 2, 2009). [http://story.heraldglobe.com/index.php/ct/9/cid/b8de8e630faf3631/id/549835/cs/1 Dennis Hopper released from hospital] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110711163434/http://story.heraldglobe.com/index.php/ct/9/cid/b8de8e630faf3631/id/549835/cs/1 |date=July 11, 2011 }}. Herald Globe. Retrieved 2010-05-29.&lt;/ref&gt;

On October 29, Hopper's manager Sam Maydew reported that he had been diagnosed with advanced [[prostate cancer]].&lt;ref&gt;AP (October 29, 2009). [http://www.today.com/id/33543972 Dennis Hopper's manager reports prostate cancer diagnosis]. [[Associated Press|AP]]. Retrieved 2010-05-29.&lt;/ref&gt; In January 2010, it was reported that Hopper's cancer had [[Metastasis|metastasized]] to his bones.&lt;ref&gt;Lee, Ken (January 15, 2010). [http://www.people.com/people/article/0,,20337245,00.html Dennis Hopper files for divorce]. People Magazine. Retrieved 2010-05-29.&lt;/ref&gt;

On March 18, 2010, he was honored with the 2,403rd star on the [[Hollywood Walk of Fame]] in front of [[Grauman's Egyptian Theatre]] on [[Hollywood Boulevard]].&lt;ref&gt;Staff (March 18, 2010). [http://www.pr-inside.com/hopper-to-be-honored-on-hollywood-r1783445.htm Hopper to be Honored on Hollywood Walk of Fame] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120531152952/http://www.pr-inside.com/hopper-to-be-honored-on-hollywood-r1783445.htm |date=May 31, 2012 }}. PR Inside.com. Retrieved 2010-05-29.&lt;/ref&gt; Surrounded by friends including [[Jack Nicholson]], [[Viggo Mortensen]], [[David Lynch]], [[Michael Madsen]], family and fans, he attended its addition to the sidewalk six days later.&lt;ref&gt;Duke, Alan (March 26, 2010). [http://www.cnn.com/2010/SHOWBIZ/Movies/03/26/dennis.hopper/index.html Dennis Hopper attends Hollywood Walk of Fame ceremony] ''CNN.com''; CNN. Retrieved 2010-05-29.&lt;/ref&gt;

By March 2010, Hopper reportedly weighed only {{convert|100|lb|kg}} and was unable to carry on long conversations.&lt;ref&gt;KTLA (March 26, 2010). [http://www.ktla.com/news/landing/ktla-dennis-hopper-star,0,1384617.story Ailing Actor Dennis Hopper Receives Star on Walk of Fame] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20101010013443/http://www.ktla.com/news/landing/ktla-dennis-hopper-star,0,1384617.story |date=October 10, 2010 }}. [[KTLA]] News. Retrieved 2010-05-29.&lt;/ref&gt; According to papers filed in his divorce court case, Hopper was [[terminal illness|terminally ill]] and was unable to undergo [[chemotherapy]] to treat his prostate cancer.&lt;ref&gt;BBC (March 25, 2010). [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/entertainment/8586552.stm Actor Dennis Hopper 'is terminally ill']. [[BBC]] News. Retrieved 2010-05-29.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;AP (March 25, 2010). {{YouTube|67Mc1UzBcOY|Actor Dennis Hopper Reportedly on His Death Bed}}; [[Associated Press]]. Retrieved 2010-05-29.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!-- This AP video is not copyvio, it's published by AP under their YouTube account. --&gt;

Hopper died at his home in the coastal [[Venice, Los Angeles|Venice]] district of Los Angeles on the morning of May 29, 2010, 12 days after his 74th birthday.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://news.yahoo.com/s/nm/20100529/en_nm/us_hopper/ |title=Hollywood hellraiser Dennis Hopper dead at 74 |author=Goodman, Dean; Reuters. |publisher=Yahoo! |date=May 29, 2010 |accessdate=2010-05-29 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100602031132/http://news.yahoo.com/s/nm/20100529/en_nm/us_hopper |archivedate=June 2, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; His funeral took place on June 3, 2010, at [[San Francisco de Asis Mission Church]] in [[Ranchos de Taos, New Mexico]]. His body was buried at the Jesus Nazareno Cemetery in Ranchos de Taos.

The film ''[[Alpha and Omega (film)|Alpha and Omega]]'', which was among his last film roles, was dedicated to him as was the 2011 film ''[[Restless (2011 film)|Restless]]'', which starred his son Henry Hopper.

==Archive==
The moving image collection of Dennis Hopper is held at the Academy Film Archive. The Dennis Hopper Trust Collection represents Hopper's directorial efforts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Dennis Hopper Trust Collection|url=http://www.oscars.org/film-archive/collections/dennis-hopper-collection|website=Academy Film Archive}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Awards==
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|-
! scope=&quot;col&quot;| Year
! scope=&quot;col&quot;| Award
! scope=&quot;col&quot;| Category
! scope=&quot;col&quot;| Work
! scope=&quot;col&quot;| Result
! scope=&quot;col&quot; class=&quot;unsortable&quot;| {{Abbr|Ref(s)|Reference(s)}}
|-
| rowspan=&quot;6&quot; | 1969
| [[Academy Awards]]
| [[Academy Award for Best Original Screenplay|Best Original Screenplay]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(shared with [[Peter Fonda]] and [[Terry Southern]])&lt;/small&gt;
| rowspan=&quot;6&quot; | ''[[Easy Rider]]''
| {{nom}}
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; |&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://awardsdatabase.oscars.org/ampas_awards/DisplayMain.jsp?curTime=1461541200273|title=Session Timeout – Academy Awards® Database – AMPAS|publisher=}}{{dead link|date=September 2017 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | [[Cannes Film Festival]]
| Best First Work
| {{won}}
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; |&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.festival-cannes.fr/en/archives/1969/awardCompetition.html|title=Awards 1969 : Competition|access-date=December 2, 2018|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160601051638/http://www.festival-cannes.fr/en/archives/1969/awardCompetition.html|archive-date=June 1, 2016|url-status=dead|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| [[Palme d'Or]]
| {{nom}}
|
|-
| [[Directors Guild of America Awards]]
| [[Directors Guild of America Award for Outstanding Directing - Feature Film|Outstanding Directing – Feature Film]]
| {{nom}}
|
|-
| [[National Society of Film Critics Awards]]
| Special Award&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(For his achievements as director, co-writer and co-star.)&lt;/small&gt;
| {{won}}
|
|-
| [[Writers Guild of America Awards]]
| [[Writers Guild of America Award for Best Original Screenplay|Best Drama Written Directly for the Screen]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(shared with [[Peter Fonda]] and [[Terry Southern]])&lt;/small&gt;
| {{nom}}
|
|-
| 1971
| Venice Film Festival
| CIDALC Award
| ''The Last Movie''
| {{Won}}
|
|-
| 1980
| [[Cannes Film Festival]]
| [[Palme d'Or]]
| ''[[Out of the Blue (1980 film)|Out of the Blue]]''
| {{nom}}
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; |&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.imdb.com/event/ev0000147/1980 |title=Cannes Film Festival – Awards for 1980 |website=IMDb}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| rowspan=&quot;8&quot; | 1986
| [[Boston Society of Film Critics]]
| [[Boston Society of Film Critics Award for Best Supporting Actor|Best Supporting Actor]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(tied with [[Ray Liotta]] for ''[[Something Wild (1986 film)|Something Wild]]'')&lt;/small&gt;
| rowspan=&quot;5&quot; | ''[[Blue Velvet (film)|Blue Velvet]]''
| rowspan=&quot;4&quot; {{won}}
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; |&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bostonfilmcritics.org/content/past-award-winners#1980s|title=Past Award Winners – Boston Society of Film Critics|access-date=April 25, 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141008041238/http://www.bostonfilmcritics.org/content/past-award-winners#1980s|archive-date=October 8, 2014|url-status=dead|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| [[Independent Spirit Awards]]
| [[Independent Spirit Award for Best Male Lead|Best Male Lead]]
|
|-
| [[Montreal World Film Festival]]
| Best Actor
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; |&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ffm-montreal.org/en/awards/31-awards-of-the-montreal-world-film-festival-1986.html|title=Awards of the Montreal World Film Festival – 1986 – World Film Festival|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| [[National Society of Film Critics Awards]]
| [[National Society of Film Critics Award for Best Supporting Actor|Best Supporting Actor]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; |&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://nationalsocietyoffilmcritics.com/about-2/|title=Past Awards|date=December 19, 2009|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| [[Golden Globe Awards]]
| [[Golden Globe Award for Best Supporting Actor - Motion Picture|Best Supporting Actor]]
| {{nom}}
|
|-
| [[Golden Globe Awards]]
| [[Golden Globe Award for Best Supporting Actor - Motion Picture|Best Supporting Actor]]
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | ''[[Hoosiers (film)|Hoosiers]]''
| {{nom}}
|
|-
| [[Academy Awards]]
| [[Academy Award for Best Supporting Actor|Best Supporting Actor]]
| {{nom}}
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; |&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://awardsdatabase.oscars.org/ampas_awards/DisplayMain.jsp?curTime=1461546130313|title=Session Timeout – Academy Awards® Database – AMPAS|publisher=}}{{dead link|date=September 2017 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| [[Los Angeles Film Critics Association]]
| [[Los Angeles Film Critics Association Award for Best Supporting Actor|Best Supporting Actor]]
| ''[[Hoosiers (film)|Hoosiers]]'' + ''[[Blue Velvet (film)|Blue Velvet]]''
| {{won}}
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; |&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lafca.net/years/1986.html|title=LAFCA|publisher=|access-date=April 25, 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160521041317/http://www.lafca.net/years/1986.html|archive-date=May 21, 2016|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| rowspan=&quot;3&quot; | 1991
| [[Primetime Emmy Awards|Emmy Awards]]
| [[Primetime Emmy Award for Outstanding Lead Actor in a Miniseries or a Movie|Outstanding Lead Actor – Miniseries or a Movie]]
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | ''[[Paris Trout]]''
| rowspan=&quot;3&quot; {{nom}}
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; |&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.emmys.com/bios/dennis-hopper|title=DENNIS HOPPER – Television Academy|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | [[CableACE Awards]]
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | Outstanding Lead Actor – Movie or Miniseries
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; |
|-
| ''Doublecrossed''
|-
| 1994
| [[MTV Movie Awards]]
| [[MTV Movie Award for Best Villain|Best Villain]]
| ''[[Speed (1994 film)|Speed]]''
| {{won}}
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; |&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mtv.com/ontv/movieawards/1995/|title=Movie Awards 1995 – MTV Movie Awards – MTV|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 1995
| [[Razzie Awards]]
| [[Razzie Award for Worst Supporting Actor|Worst Supporting Actor]]
| ''[[Waterworld]]''
| {{won}}
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; |&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.razzies.com/forum/1995-razzie-nominees-winners_topic345.html|title=404 – Page Not Found|access-date=September 4, 2012|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120831204732/http://www.razzies.com/forum/1995-razzie-nominees-winners_topic345.html|archive-date=August 31, 2012|url-status=dead|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|}

==Works==

===Books===
* Hopper, Dennis. ''Dennis Hopper: Out of the Sixties'', Twelvetrees Press (1986)

==Filmography==
{{main|Dennis Hopper filmography}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Bibliography==
* &quot;Dennis Hopper, Riding High&quot;, ''Playboy'' (Chicago), Dec. 1969
* Interview with G. O'Brien and M. Netter, in ''Inter/View'' (New York), Feb. 1972
* Interview in ''Cahiers du Cinema (Paris), July–August 1980
* &quot;How Far to the Last Movie?&quot;, ''Monthly Film Bulleting (London) Oct. 1982
* &quot;Citizen Hopper&quot;, interview with C. Hodenfield, in ''Film Comment'' (New York) Nov/Dec. 1986
* Interview with B. Kelly, in ''American Film'' (Los Angeles) March 1988
* Interview with David Denicolo, in ''Interview'' (New York), Feb. 1990
* &quot;Sean Penn&quot;, interview with Julian Schnabel and Dennis Hopper, ''Interview'' (New York) Sept. 1991
* &quot;Gary Oldman&quot;, in ''Interview'' (New York), Jan. 1992

==Further reading==
;Books
* [[Peter Biskind|Biskind, Peter]]. ''Easy Riders, Raging Bulls: How the Sex-Drugs-and-Rock 'N' Roll Generation Saved Hollywood'', Simon and Schuster (1999)
* [[J. Hoberman|Hoberman, J.]] ''Dennis Hopper: From Method to Madness'', Walker Art Center (1988)
* Krull, Craig. &quot;Photographing the LA Art Scene: 1955–1975&quot;, Craig Krull Gallery (1996)
* Rodriguez, Elean. ''Dennis Hopper: A Madness to his Method'', St. Martin's Press (1988)
* ''Dennis Hopper: Photographs 1961–1967'', Taschen (2011)
* Winkler, Peter L. &quot;Dennis Hopper: The Wild Ride of a Hollywood Rebel&quot;, Barricade Books (2011)
*[[Tom Folsom|Folsom, Tom]]. &quot;Hopper: A Journey into the American Dream,&quot; It Books/HarperCollins (2013)

;Articles
* Algar, N., &quot;Hopper at Birmingham&quot;, in ''Sight and Sound'' (London), Summer 1982
* Burke, Tom, &quot;Dennis Hopper Saves the Movies&quot;, in ''Esquire (New York), Dec. 1970
* Burns, Dan E., &quot;Dennis Hopper's ''The Last Movie'': Beginning of the End&quot;, in ''Literature/Film Quarterly, 1979
* Herring, H. D., &quot;Out of the Dream and into the Nightmare: Dennis Hopper's Apocalyptic Vision of America&quot;, in ''Journal of Popular Film'' (Washington, D.C.), Winter 1983
* {{cite news |last=Hopper |first=Marin |url=http://tmagazine.blogs.nytimes.com/2014/09/09/dennis-hopper-day-descends-on-taos-new-mexico/ |title=Dennis Hopper Day Descends on Taos, N.M. |work=The New York Times Style Magazine |date=September 9, 2014}}
* Macklin, F. A., &quot;Easy Rider: The Initiation of Dennis Hopper&quot;, in ''Film Heritage'' (Dayton, Ohio), Fall 1969
* Martin, A., &quot;Dennis Hopper: Out of the Blue and into the Black&quot;, in ''Cinema Papers (Melbourne), July 1987
* Scharres, B., &quot;From Out of the Blue: The Return of Dennis Hopper&quot; in ''Journal of the University Film and Video Assoc. (Carbondale, IL), Spring 1983
* Weber, Bruce, &quot;A Wild Man is Mellowing, Albeit Not on Screen&quot;, in ''New York Times, September 8, 1994

==External links==
{{Portal|Biography}}
* {{IMDb name|454}}
* {{Find a Grave|52979594}}
* {{Tcmdb name}}
* {{amg name|94825}}
* [http://www.artnet.com/Artists/ArtistHomePage.aspx?artist_id=8500&amp;page_tab=Bio_and_links Dennis Hopper Exhibition History]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20100601005915/http://www.life.com/image/first/in-gallery/34392/dennis-hopper-life--times Dennis Hopper: Life &amp; Times] – slideshow by ''[[Life magazine]]''
* {{Commons-inline}}

{{Dennis Hopper}}
{{Navboxes
|title = Awards for Dennis Hopper (see list above)
|list =
{{Boston Society of Film Critics Award for Best Supporting Actor}}
{{Los Angeles Film Critics Association Award for Best Supporting Actor}}
{{National Society of Film Critics Award for Best Supporting Actor}}
}}

{{Venice Film Festival jury presidents}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Hopper, Dennis}}
[[Category:American male film actors]]
[[Category:American male screenwriters]]
[[Category:American male television actors]]
[[Category:Film directors from California]]
[[Category:1936 births]]
[[Category:2010 deaths]]
[[Category:Film directors from Missouri]]
[[Category:Male actors from Greater Los Angeles]]
[[Category:Male actors from San Diego]]
[[Category:Photographers from California]]
[[Category:American people of Scottish descent]]
[[Category:American people of Welsh descent]]
[[Category:Kansas Republicans]]
[[Category:Deaths from cancer in California]]
[[Category:American male voice actors]]
[[Category:Deaths from prostate cancer]]
[[Category:Kansas City Art Institute alumni]]
[[Category:People from Dodge City, Kansas]]
[[Category:Male actors from Kansas City, Missouri]]
[[Category:People from Taos, New Mexico]]
[[Category:People from Topanga, California]]
[[Category:20th-century American male actors]]
[[Category:21st-century American male actors]]
[[Category:20th-century American writers]]
[[Category:Writers from Kansas City, Missouri]]
[[Category:Male actors from Kansas]]
[[Category:Film directors from New Mexico]]
[[Category:Film directors from Kansas]]
[[Category:Screenwriters from California]]
[[Category:Screenwriters from New Mexico]]
[[Category:California Republicans]]
[[Category:People from Bel Air, Los Angeles]]</text>
      <sha1>ct0o8mx7o8y59ueubs1tvro6ashoz1q</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
