  <page>
    <title>David Bowie</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8786</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943149942</id>
      <parentid>942337419</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-29T04:19:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Superspongebobbros</username>
        <id>31881866</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* 1968–1971: Space Oddity to Hunky Dory */ c</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Other uses}}
{{Pp-blp|small=yes|expiry=indefinite}}
{{short description|British musician, actor, record producer and arranger}}
{{EngvarB|date=January 2017}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=November 2019}}
{{Infobox person
| image              = David-Bowie Chicago 2002-08-08 photoby Adam-Bielawski-cropped.jpg
&lt;!-- NOTE: Do not replace David-Bowie Chicago 2002-08-08 photoby Adam-Bielawski-cropped.jpg unless it is with a photo under a public domain or free license (meaning NOT fair use). Any fair use photos (i.e. 'promotional photos') violate the Fair Use Policy and will be deleted. See [[Wikipedia:Fair]] use criteria --&gt;| alt                = Bowie smiling
| caption            = Bowie in [[Tinley Park, Illinois]], during the [[Heathen Tour]], 2002
| birth_name         = David Robert Jones
| birth_date         = {{Birth date|df=yes|1947|1|8}}
| birth_place        = [[Brixton]], [[London]], England
| death_date         = {{Death date and age|df=yes|2016|1|10|1947|1|8}}
| death_place        = [[New York City]], U.S.
| resting_place      = Ashes scattered in [[Bali]]&lt;ref name=ashes&gt;{{cite news|last=Woolf|first=Nicky|url=https://www.theguardian.com/music/2016/jan/29/david-bowie-will-details-millions-estate-wife-children-bali|title=David Bowie's Will Detailed, Ashes Scattered in Bali|work=[[The Guardian]]|accessdate=7 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| occupation         = {{hlist|Singer|songwriter|actor}}&lt;!--Please do not add to this list without first discussing your proposal on the talk page. --&gt;
| years_active       = {{hlist|1962–2016}}
| spouse             = {{unbulleted list|{{marriage|[[Angie Bowie|Angie Barnett]]|19 March 1970|8 February 1980|end=divorced}}|{{marriage|[[Iman (model)|Iman]]|24 April 1992|2016}}}}
| children           = 2, including [[Duncan Jones]]&lt;!-- do not name the other child, who is not notable and hence not reported in the infobox --&gt;
| module             = {{Infobox musical artist| embed= yes
| background          = solo_singer
| instrument          = {{hlist|Vocals|guitar|keyboards|saxophone|harmonica}}&lt;!-- If you think an instrument should be listed or removed, a discussion to reach consensus is needed first --&gt;
| genre               = {{hlist|[[Art rock]]|[[glam rock]]|[[pop music|pop]]|[[Electronic music|electronic]]|[[Experimental music|experimental]]}}
| associated_acts     = {{hlist|[[Tony Visconti]]|[[Carlos Alomar]]|[[the Riot Squad]]|[[Arnold Corns]]|[[Tin Machine]]|[[The Hype (David Bowie band)|the Hype]]|[[Queen (band)|Queen]]|[[Iggy Pop]]|[[Arcade Fire]]|[[Brian Eno]]|[[Ryuichi Sakamoto]]|[[Lou Reed]]|[[Adrian Belew]]|[[Mick Ronson]]|[[Reeves Gabrels]]||[[John Lennon]]|[[Nine Inch Nails]]|[[Mick Jagger]]|[[Tina Turner]]|[[Mott the Hoople]]}}&lt;!--Please do not add to this list without first discussing your proposal on the talk page. --&gt;
| label               = {{hlist|ISO|[[RCA Records|RCA]]|[[Virgin Records|Virgin]]|[[EMI Records|EMI]]|[[Columbia Records|Columbia]]|[[Deram Records|Deram]]|[[Mercury Records|Mercury]]|[[Bertelsmann Music Group|BMG]]|[[Pye Records|Pye]]|[[Vocalion Records|Vocalion]]|[[Parlophone]]|[[Rykodisc|Ryko]]}}
| website             = {{URL|https://www.davidbowie.com/}}
}}
}}
'''David Robert Jones''' (8 January 1947 – 10 January 2016), known professionally as '''David Bowie''' ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|b|oʊ|i}} {{respell|BOH|ee|}}),&lt;ref name=&quot;saybowe&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/blogs/magazinemonitor/2007/01/how_to_say_bowie.shtml|title=How to say: Bowie|accessdate=16 September 2010|publisher=BBC|date=8 January 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt; was an English singer-songwriter and actor. He was a leading figure in the music industry and is considered one of the most influential musicians of the 20th century, acclaimed by critics and musicians, particularly for his innovative work during the 1970s. His career was marked by reinvention and visual presentation, with his music and stagecraft having a significant impact on [[popular music]]. During his lifetime, his record sales, estimated at over 100 million records worldwide, made him one of the [[List of best-selling music artists|world's best-selling music artists]]. In the UK, he was awarded ten [[Music recording certification|platinum]] album certifications, eleven gold and eight silver, and released [[List of artists by number of UK Albums Chart number ones|eleven number-one albums]]. In the US, he received five platinum and nine gold certifications. He was inducted into the [[Rock and Roll Hall of Fame]] in 1996.

Born in [[Brixton]], [[South London]], Bowie developed an interest in music as a child, eventually studying art, music and design before embarking on a professional career as a musician in 1963. &quot;[[Space Oddity]]&quot; became his first top-five entry on the [[UK Singles Chart]] after its release in July 1969. After a period of experimentation, he re-emerged in 1972 during the [[glam rock]] era with his flamboyant and androgynous [[alter ego]] Ziggy Stardust. The character was spearheaded by the success of his single &quot;[[Starman (song)|Starman]]&quot; and album ''[[The Rise and Fall of Ziggy Stardust and the Spiders from Mars]]'', which won him widespread popularity. In 1975, Bowie's style shifted radically towards a sound he characterised as &quot;[[plastic soul]]&quot;, initially alienating many of his UK devotees but garnering him his first major US crossover success with the number-one single &quot;[[Fame (David Bowie song)|Fame]]&quot; and the album ''[[Young Americans]]''. In 1976, Bowie starred in the cult film ''[[The Man Who Fell to Earth]]'', directed by [[Nicolas Roeg]], and released ''[[Station to Station]]''. The following year, he further confounded musical expectations with the [[electronic music|electronic]]-inflected album ''[[Low (David Bowie album)|Low]]'' (1977), the first of three collaborations with [[Brian Eno]] that came to be known as the &quot;[[Berlin Trilogy]]&quot;. ''[[&quot;Heroes&quot; (David Bowie album)|&quot;Heroes&quot;]]'' (1977) and ''[[Lodger (album)|Lodger]]'' (1979) followed; each album reached the UK top five and received lasting critical praise.

After uneven commercial success in the late 1970s, Bowie had UK number ones with the 1980 single &quot;[[Ashes to Ashes (David Bowie song)|Ashes to Ashes]]&quot;, its parent album ''[[Scary Monsters (and Super Creeps)]]'', and &quot;[[Under Pressure]]&quot;, a 1981 collaboration with [[Queen (band)|Queen]]. He reached his commercial peak in 1983 with ''[[Let's Dance (David Bowie album)|Let's Dance]]''; the album's [[Let's Dance (David Bowie song)|title track]] topped both UK and US charts. Throughout the 1990s and 2000s, Bowie continued to experiment with musical styles, including [[industrial music|industrial]] and [[oldschool jungle|jungle]]. He also continued acting; his roles included Major Jack Celliers in ''[[Merry Christmas, Mr. Lawrence]]'' (1983), [[Jareth]] the Goblin King in ''[[Labyrinth (1986 film)|Labyrinth]]'' (1986), [[Pontius Pilate]] in ''[[The Last Temptation of Christ (film)|The Last Temptation of Christ]]'' (1988), and [[Nikola Tesla]] in ''[[The Prestige (film)|The Prestige]]'' (2006), among other film and television appearances and cameos. He stopped touring after 2004 and his last live performance was at a charity event in 2006. In 2013, Bowie returned from a decade-long recording hiatus with ''[[The Next Day]].'' He remained musically active until he [[Death of David Bowie|died of liver cancer]] at his home in [[New York City]], two days after his 69th birthday and the release of his final album, ''[[Blackstar (album)|Blackstar]]'' (2016).

==Early life==
Bowie was born David Robert Jones on 8 January 1947 in [[Brixton]], London. His mother, Margaret Mary &quot;Peggy&quot; (née Burns; 2 October 1913 – 2 April 2001),&lt;ref name=&quot;bowiewonderworld.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bowiewonderworld.com/faq.htm#p06|title=David Bowie FAQ – Frequently Asked Questions}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;news.bbc.co.uk&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/entertainment/1256864.stm|title=Bowie mourns mother's death|date=2 April 2001|work=BBC News}}&lt;/ref&gt; was born at [[Shorncliffe Army Camp]] near [[Cheriton, Kent|Cheriton]], [[Kent]].&lt;ref&gt;Gillman (1987) p.17 &quot;[Peggy] was born in the hospital at Shorncliffe Camp [near Folkestone, Kent] on October 2nd, 1913.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Her paternal grandparents were Irish immigrants who had settled in [[Manchester]].&lt;ref&gt;Gillman (1987) p.15 &quot;[Her father] Jimmy Burns's parents were poor Irish immigrants who had settled in Manchester&quot; p.16 &quot;[Jimmy] had known [her mother] in Manchester. Her name was Margaret Heaton&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; She worked as a waitress at a cinema in [[Royal Tunbridge Wells]].&lt;ref&gt;Gillman (1987) p. 44 &quot;At the end of the war, Peggy Burns was working as a waitress at the Ritz cinema in Tunbridge Wells&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; His father, Haywood Stenton &quot;John&quot; Jones (21 November 1912 – 5 August 1969),&lt;ref name=&quot;bowiewonderworld.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;news.bbc.co.uk&quot;/&gt; was from [[Doncaster]], [[Yorkshire]]&lt;ref&gt;Gillman (1987) p. 44 &quot;John Jones was born in the grimy Yorkshire town of Doncaster in 1912.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; and worked as a promotions officer for the children's charity [[Barnardo's]]. The family lived at 40 Stansfield Road, on the boundary between Brixton and [[Stockwell]] in the south London borough of [[Lambeth]]. Bowie attended [[Stockwell Primary School|Stockwell Infants School]] until he was six years old, acquiring a reputation as a gifted and single-minded child—and a defiant brawler.&lt;ref&gt;Sandford (1997): pp. 9–16&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1953, Bowie moved with his family to [[Bromley]]. Two years later, he started attending Burnt Ash Junior School. His voice was considered &quot;adequate&quot; by the school choir, and he demonstrated above-average abilities in playing the [[Recorder (musical instrument)|recorder]].&lt;ref name=&quot;sandford18-19&quot;&gt;Sandford (1997): pp. 18–19&lt;/ref&gt; At the age of nine, his dancing during the newly-introduced music and movement classes was strikingly imaginative: teachers called his interpretations &quot;vividly artistic&quot; and his poise &quot;astonishing&quot; for a child.&lt;ref name=&quot;sandford18-19&quot;/&gt; The same year, his interest in music was further stimulated when his father brought home a collection of American [[Gramophone record|45s]] by artists including [[the Teenagers]], [[the Platters]], [[Fats Domino]], [[Elvis Presley]], and [[Little Richard]].&lt;ref&gt;Buckley (2000): p. 21.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;sandford19-20&quot; /&gt; Upon listening to Little Richard's song &quot;[[Tutti Frutti (song)|Tutti Frutti]]&quot;, Bowie would later say that he had &quot;heard God&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Doggett|first=Peter|title=Teenage Wildlife|journal=Mojo Classic|issue=60 Years of Bowie|pages=8–9|date=January 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Bowie was first impressed with Presley when he saw his cousin dance to &quot;[[Hound Dog (song)|Hound Dog]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;sandford19-20&quot;&gt;Sandford (1997): pp. 19–20&lt;/ref&gt; By the end of the following year, Bowie had taken up the [[ukulele]] and [[tea-chest bass]], begun to participate in [[skiffle]] sessions with friends, and had started to play the piano; meanwhile, his stage presentation of numbers by both Presley and [[Chuck Berry]]—complete with gyrations in tribute to the original artists—to his local [[Cub Scout|Wolf Cub]] group was described as &quot;mesmerizing&amp;nbsp;... like someone from another planet&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;sandford19-20&quot; /&gt; After taking his [[eleven-plus]] exam at the conclusion of his Burnt Ash Junior education, Bowie went to [[Ravens Wood School|Bromley Technical High School]].&lt;ref name=&quot;bromleytech&quot;/&gt;

It was an unusual technical school, as biographer Christopher Sandford wrote:

{{quote|Despite its status it was, by the time David arrived in 1958, as rich in arcane ritual as any [English] [[Independent school (United Kingdom)|public school]]. There were [[House system|houses]] named after eighteenth-century statesmen like [[William Pitt, 1st Earl of Chatham|Pitt]] and [[William Wilberforce|Wilberforce]]. There was a uniform, and an elaborate system of rewards and punishments. There was also an accent on languages, science and particularly design, where a collegiate atmosphere flourished under the tutorship of [[Owen Frampton]]. In David's account, Frampton led through force of personality, not intellect; his colleagues at Bromley Tech were famous for neither, and yielded the school's most gifted pupils to the arts, a regime so liberal that Frampton actively encouraged his own son, [[Peter Frampton|Peter]], to pursue a musical career with David, a partnership briefly intact thirty years later.&lt;ref name=&quot;bromleytech&quot;&gt;Sandford (1997): pp. 21–22&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Bowie studied art, music, and design, including layout and typesetting. After his half-brother Terry Burns introduced him to modern jazz, his enthusiasm for players like [[Charles Mingus]] and [[John Coltrane]] led his mother to give him a [[Grafton saxophone]] in 1961. He was soon receiving lessons from [[baritone saxophone|baritone saxophonist]] [[Ronnie Ross]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.berklee.edu/commencement/past|title=Commencement 1999 - Berklee College of Music|website=www.berklee.edu|accessdate=10 February 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Sandford (1997): p. 25&lt;/ref&gt; He received a serious injury at school in 1962 when his friend [[George Underwood (artist)|George Underwood]] punched him in the left eye during a fight over a girl. After a series of operations during a four-month hospitalisation,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Mike|last=Evans|title=Rock 'n' Roll's Strangest Moments: Extraordinary Tales from Over Fifty Years|publisher=Anova Books|location=Chicago|year=2006|isbn=978-1-86105-923-9|page=57}}&lt;/ref&gt; his doctors determined that the damage could not be fully repaired and Bowie was left with faulty [[depth perception]] and a [[anisocoria|permanently dilated pupil]], which gave a false impression of a [[Heterochromia iridum|change in the iris's colour]]; the eye later became one of Bowie's most recognisable features.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|first=Tanya|last=Basu|url=https://www.thecut.com/2016/01/story-behind-david-bowies-unusual-eyes.html|title=The Story Behind David Bowie's Unusual Eyes|work=The Cut|date=12 January 2016|accessdate= 21 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite their altercation, Bowie remained on good terms with Underwood, who went on to create the artwork for Bowie's early albums.&lt;ref&gt;Buckley (2005): p.19&lt;/ref&gt;

==Music career==
{{Main|David Bowie discography}}

===1962–1967: Early career to debut album===
[[File:David Bowie (1967).png|thumb|upright|alt=Bowie looking to the camera|A trade ad photo of Bowie in 1967]]
In 1962, Bowie formed his first band at the age of 15, named the Konrads. Playing guitar-based [[rock and roll]] at local youth gatherings and weddings, the Konrads had a varying line-up of between four and eight members, Underwood among them.&lt;ref&gt;Sandford (1997): p. 28&lt;/ref&gt; When Bowie left the technical school the following year, he informed his parents of his intention to become a pop star. His mother arranged his employment as an electrician's mate. Frustrated by his bandmates' limited aspirations, Bowie left the Konrads and joined another band, the King Bees. He wrote to the newly successful washing-machine entrepreneur [[John Bloom (businessman)|John Bloom]] inviting him to &quot;do for us what [[Brian Epstein]] has done for [[the Beatles]]—and make another million.&quot; Bloom did not respond to the offer, but his referral to [[Dick James]]'s partner Leslie Conn led to Bowie's first personal management contract.&lt;ref name=&quot;sandford29-30&quot;&gt;Sandford (1997): pp. 29–30&lt;/ref&gt;

Conn quickly began to promote Bowie. The singer's debut single, &quot;[[Liza Jane (David Bowie song)|Liza Jane]]&quot;, credited to Davie Jones with the King Bees, was not commercially successful. Dissatisfied with the King Bees and their repertoire of [[Howlin' Wolf]] and [[Willie Dixon]] covers, Bowie quit the band less than a month later to join the Manish Boys, another blues outfit, who incorporated folk and soul—&quot;I used to dream of being their [[Mick Jagger]]&quot;, Bowie was to recall.&lt;ref name=&quot;sandford29-30&quot; /&gt; Their cover of [[Bobby Bland]]'s &quot;[[I Pity the Fool]]&quot; was no more successful than &quot;Liza Jane&quot;, and Bowie soon moved on again to join the Lower Third, a blues trio strongly influenced by [[The Who]]. &quot;[[You've Got a Habit of Leaving]]&quot; fared no better, signalling the end of Conn's contract. Declaring that he would exit the pop music world &quot;to study mime at [[Sadler's Wells Theatre|Sadler's Wells]]&quot;, Bowie nevertheless remained with the Lower Third. His new manager, Ralph Horton, later instrumental in his transition to solo artist, soon witnessed Bowie's move to yet another group, the Buzz, yielding the singer's fifth unsuccessful single release, &quot;[[Do Anything You Say]]&quot;. While with the Buzz, Bowie also joined the [[The Riot Squad|Riot Squad]]; their recordings, which included one of Bowie's original songs and material by [[The Velvet Underground]], went unreleased. [[Kenneth Pitt]], introduced by Horton, took over as Bowie's manager.&lt;ref&gt;Sandford (1997): pp. 35–39&lt;/ref&gt;

Dissatisfied with his stage name as Davy (and Davie) Jones, which in the mid-1960s invited confusion with [[Davy Jones (musician)|Davy Jones]] of [[The Monkees]], Bowie renamed himself after the 19th-century American pioneer [[James Bowie]] and [[Bowie knife|the knife he had popularised]].&lt;ref&gt;Buckley (2000): p. 33&lt;/ref&gt; His April 1967 solo single, &quot;[[The Laughing Gnome]]&quot;, using speeded-up thus high-pitched vocals, failed to chart. Released six weeks later, his album debut, ''[[David Bowie (1967 album)|David Bowie]]'', an amalgam of pop, [[psychedelic rock|psychedelia]], and [[music hall]], met the same fate. It was his last release for two years.&lt;ref name=&quot;albumdebut&quot; /&gt;

=== 1968–1971: ''Space Oddity'' to ''Hunky Dory'' ===
{{anchor|Hermione Farthingale}}

Bowie met dancer [[Lindsay Kemp]] in 1967 and enrolled in his dance class at the [[The Dance Centre|London Dance Centre]].&lt;ref name=Kemp&gt;{{cite book|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=UQ2UBwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA131|page=131|last=Thian|first=Helene Marie|chapter=Moss Garden|title=David Bowie: Critical Perspectives|editor=Eoin Devereux|publisher=Routledge|location=Abingdon, United Kingdom|date=24 March 2015|isbn=978-1-317-75449-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; He commented in 1972 that meeting Kemp was when his interest in image &quot;really blossomed&quot;.&lt;ref name=Kemp /&gt; &quot;He lived on his emotions, he was a wonderful influence. His day-to-day life was the most theatrical thing I had ever seen, ever. It was everything I thought Bohemia probably was. I joined the circus.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;buckley41-42&quot;&gt;Buckley (2005): pp. 41–42&lt;/ref&gt; Studying the dramatic arts under Kemp, from [[avant-garde]] theatre and [[mime artist|mime]] to [[commedia dell'arte]], Bowie became immersed in the creation of personae to present to the world. Satirising life in a British prison, meanwhile, the Bowie composition &quot;Over the Wall We Go&quot; became a 1967 single for [[Paul Nicholas|Oscar]]; another Bowie song, &quot;Silly Boy Blue&quot;, was released by [[Billy Fury]] the following year.&lt;ref&gt;Buckley (2005): p. 46&lt;/ref&gt; In January 1968, Kemp choreographed a dance scene for a [[BBC]] play, ''The Pistol Shot'', in the [[Theatre 625]] series, and used Bowie with a dancer, [[Hermione Farthingale]];&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Nicholas|last=Pegg|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=nnO_BgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT1937#v=onepage|title=The Complete David Bowie|publisher=Titan Books|location=London, England|date=2 December 2011|isbn=978-0-85768-719-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Christopher|last=Sandford|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=OomyGN_btTQC&amp;pg=PA46#v=onepage|page=46|title=Bowie: Loving The Alien|publisher=Da Capo Press|location=Cambridge, Massachusetts|date=5 August 2009|isbn=978-0-7867-5096-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; the pair began dating, and moved into a London flat together. Playing acoustic guitar, Farthingale formed a group with Bowie and guitarist John Hutchinson; between September 1968 and early 1969 the trio gave a small number of concerts combining folk, [[Beat music|Merseybeat]], poetry, and mime.&lt;ref&gt;Buckley (2005): pp. 49–52&lt;/ref&gt; Bowie and Farthingale broke up in early 1969 when she went to Norway to take part in a film, ''[[Song of Norway (film)|Song of Norway]]'';&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|first=Sophie|last=Heawood|url=https://www.independent.co.uk/voices/comment/david-bowie-has-gone-from-new-to-old--and-what-a-beautiful-thing-it-is-8443239.html|title=David Bowie has gone from new to old – and what a beautiful thing it is|work=[[The Independent]]|location=London, England|date=8 January 2013|accessdate=8 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; this affected him, and several songs, such as &quot;[[Letter to Hermione]]&quot; and &quot;[[Life on Mars (song)|Life on Mars?]]&quot; reference her,&lt;ref name=&quot;HeatleyHopkinson2014&quot;&gt;{{cite book|first1=Michael|last1=Heatley|first2=Frank|last2=Hopkinson|title=The Girl in the Song: The Real Stories Behind 50 Rock Classics|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=bsC_CAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT88|date=24 November 2014|publisher=Anova Books|location=Chicago|isbn=978-1-909396-88-3|page=88}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first=Paul|last=Trynka|url=http://www.trynka.net/archive/Hermione.html|title=A Letter from Hermione|website=trynka.net}}&lt;/ref&gt; and for the video accompanying &quot;[[Where Are We Now?]]&quot;, he wore a T-shirt with the words &quot;m/s Song of Norway&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |first=Jack |last=Seale |url= https://www.radiotimes.com/news/2013-01-08/david-bowie-rocks-music-world-with-where-are-we-now-video/ |title= David Bowie rocks music world with Where Are We Now? |work= [[Radio Times]] |location= London, England |date=8 January 2013 |accessdate= 8 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; They were last together in January 1969 for the filming of ''[[Love You till Tuesday (film)|Love You till Tuesday]]'', a 30-minute film that was not released until 1984: intended as a promotional vehicle, it featured performances from Bowie's repertoire, including &quot;[[Space Oddity]]&quot;, which had not been released when the film was made.&lt;ref name=&quot;sandford49-50&quot; /&gt;

After the break-up with Farthingale, Bowie moved in with Mary Finnigan as her lodger.&lt;ref name=&quot;sandford53&quot;&gt;Sandford (1997): p. 53&lt;/ref&gt; During this period he appeared in a [[Lyons Maid]] ice cream commercial, and was rejected for another by [[Kit Kat]].&lt;ref name=&quot;sandford49-50&quot;&gt;Sandford (1997): pp. 49–50&lt;/ref&gt; In February and March 1969, he undertook a short tour with [[Marc Bolan]]'s duo [[T. Rex (band)|Tyrannosaurus Rex]], as third on the bill, performing a mime act.&lt;ref name=&quot;Paytress2009&quot;&gt;{{cite book|first=Mark|last=Paytress|title=Bolan: The Rise and Fall of a 20th Century Superstar|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=-yk4U2LILeMC&amp;pg=PT199|publisher=Omnibus Press|location=London, England|date=5 November 2009|isbn=978-0-85712-023-6|page=199}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 11 July 1969, &quot;Space Oddity&quot; was released five days ahead of the [[Apollo 11]] launch, and reached the top five in the UK.&lt;ref name=&quot;sandford49-50&quot; /&gt; Continuing the divergence from rock and roll and blues begun by his work with Farthingale, Bowie joined forces with Finnigan, Christina Ostrom and Barrie Jackson to run a folk club on Sunday nights at the Three Tuns pub in [[Beckenham]] High Street.&lt;ref name=&quot;sandford53&quot; /&gt; The club was influenced by the [[Arts Lab]] movement, developing into the [[Beckenham Arts Lab]] and became extremely popular. The Arts Lab hosted a free festival in a local park, the subject of his song &quot;[[Memory of a Free Festival]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=George|last=McKay|title=Senseless Acts of Beauty: Cultures of Resistance|publisher=[[Verso]]|location=Miamisburg, Ohio|year=1996|isbn=978-1-85984-908-8|page=188}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Bowie's second album followed in November; originally issued in the UK as ''[[David Bowie (1969 album)|David Bowie]]'', it caused some confusion with its predecessor of the same name, and the early US release was instead titled ''Man of Words/Man of Music''; it was reissued internationally in 1972 by [[RCA Records]] as ''Space Oddity''. Featuring philosophical post-[[hippie]] lyrics on peace, love, and morality, its acoustic folk rock occasionally fortified by harder rock, the album was not a commercial success at the time of its release.&lt;ref&gt;Sandford (1997): p. 60&lt;/ref&gt;

Bowie met [[Angie Bowie|Angela Barnett]] in April 1969. They married within a year. Her impact on him was immediate, and her involvement in his career far-reaching, leaving manager Ken Pitt with limited influence which he found frustrating.&lt;ref name=&quot;sandford54-60&quot;&gt;Sandford (1997): pp. 54–60&lt;/ref&gt; Having established himself as a solo artist with &quot;Space Oddity&quot;, Bowie began to sense a lacking: &quot;a full-time band for gigs and recording—people he could relate to personally&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;sandford62-63&quot; /&gt; The shortcoming was underlined by his artistic rivalry with [[Marc Bolan]], who was at the time acting as his session guitarist.&lt;ref name=&quot;sandford62-63&quot;&gt;Sandford (1997): pp. 62–63&lt;/ref&gt; The band Bowie assembled comprised John Cambridge, a drummer Bowie met at the Arts Lab, [[Tony Visconti]] on bass and [[Mick Ronson]] on electric guitar. Known as [[Hype (David Bowie band)|Hype]], the bandmates created characters for themselves and wore elaborate costumes that prefigured the glam style of the Spiders from Mars. After a disastrous opening gig at the [[Roundhouse (venue)|London Roundhouse]], they reverted to a configuration presenting Bowie as a solo artist.&lt;ref name=&quot;sandford62-63&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Buckley (2000): pp. 89–90&lt;/ref&gt; Their initial studio work was marred by a heated disagreement between Bowie and Cambridge over the latter's drumming style. Matters came to a head when an enraged Bowie accused the drummer of the disturbance, exclaiming &quot;You're fucking up my album.&quot; Cambridge left and was replaced by [[Mick Woodmansey]].&lt;ref name=&quot;sandford67&quot;&gt;Sandford (1997): p. 67&lt;/ref&gt; Not long after, the singer fired his manager and replaced him with [[Tony Defries]]. This resulted in years of litigation that concluded with Bowie having to pay Pitt compensation.&lt;ref name=&quot;sandford67&quot; /&gt;

The studio sessions continued and resulted in Bowie's third album, ''[[The Man Who Sold the World (album)|The Man Who Sold the World]]'' (1970), which contained references to [[schizophrenia]], paranoia, and delusion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first=Karl|last=Smith|title=Random Ultra-Violence: Simon Critchley On David Bowie|url=https://thequietus.com/articles/16414-david-bowie-simon-critchley-biography-extract-2|work=The Quietus|location=London, England|date=6 October 2014|accessdate=14 December 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Characterised by the heavy rock sound of his new [[Backup band|backing band]], it was a marked departure from the acoustic guitar and folk rock style established by ''Space Oddity''. To promote it in the US, [[Mercury Records]] financed a coast-to-coast publicity tour across America in which Bowie, between January and February 1971, was interviewed by radio stations and the media. Exploiting his [[androgyny|androgynous]] appearance, the original cover of the UK version unveiled two months later depicted the singer wearing a dress: taking the garment with him, he wore it during interviews—to the approval of critics, including ''[[Rolling Stone]]''{{'}}s [[John Mendelsohn (musician)|John Mendelsohn]] who described him as &quot;ravishing, almost disconcertingly reminiscent of [[Lauren Bacall]]&quot;&amp;nbsp;– and in the street, to mixed reaction including laughter and, in the case of one male pedestrian, producing a gun and telling Bowie to &quot;kiss my ass&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;sandford73-74&quot;&gt;Sandford (1997): pp. 73–74&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Pegg (2000): pp. 260–65&lt;/ref&gt;

During the tour, Bowie's observation of two seminal American [[proto-punk]] artists led him to develop a concept that eventually found form in the Ziggy Stardust character: a melding of the persona of [[Iggy Pop]] with the music of [[Lou Reed]], producing &quot;the ultimate pop idol&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;sandford73-74&quot; /&gt; A girlfriend recalled his &quot;scrawling notes on a cocktail napkin about a crazy rock star named Iggy or Ziggy&quot;, and on his return to England he declared his intention to create a character &quot;who looks like he's landed from Mars&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;sandford73-74&quot; /&gt; The &quot;Stardust&quot; surname was a tribute to the &quot;[[Legendary Stardust Cowboy]]&quot;, whose record he was given during the tour. Bowie would later cover &quot;I Took a Trip on a Gemini Space Ship&quot; on 2002's ''[[Heathen (David Bowie album)|Heathen]]''.{{sfn|Spitz|2009|p=177}}

''[[Hunky Dory]]'' (1971) found Visconti, Bowie's producer and bassist, supplanted in both roles by [[Ken Scott]] and [[Trevor Bolder]] respectively. The album saw the partial return of the fey pop singer of &quot;Space Oddity&quot;, with light fare such as &quot;[[Kooks (song)|Kooks]]&quot;, a song written for his son, [[Duncan Jones|Duncan Zowie Haywood Jones]], born on 30 May.&lt;ref name=&quot;buckley95-99&quot;&gt;Buckley (2005): pp. 95–99&lt;/ref&gt; (His parents chose &quot;his kooky name&quot;—he was known as Zowie for the next 12 years—after the Greek word ''zoe'', life.)&lt;ref name=&quot;sandford80&quot;&gt;Sandford (1997): p. 80&lt;/ref&gt; Elsewhere, the album explored more serious subjects, and found Bowie paying unusually direct homage to his influences with &quot;[[Song for Bob Dylan]]&quot;, &quot;[[Andy Warhol (song)|Andy Warhol]]&quot;, and &quot;[[Queen Bitch]]&quot;, the latter a [[The Velvet Underground|Velvet Underground]] pastiche. It was not a significant commercial success at the time.&lt;ref&gt;Sandford (1997): pp. 85–86&lt;/ref&gt;

===1972–1974: ''Ziggy Stardust''{{anchor|Ziggy Stardust}}===
[[File:David-Bowie Early.jpg|thumb|upright|Bowie during the [[Ziggy Stardust Tour]], 1972–1973]]
Dressed in a striking costume, his hair dyed reddish-brown, Bowie launched his Ziggy Stardust stage show with [[the Spiders from Mars]]—Ronson, Bolder, and Woodmansey—at the Toby Jug pub in [[Tolworth]] in [[Kingston upon Thames]] on 10 February 1972.&lt;ref name=&quot;buckley135-6&quot; /&gt; The show was hugely popular, catapulting him to stardom as he toured the UK over the next six months and creating, as described by Buckley, a &quot;cult of Bowie&quot; that was &quot;unique—its influence lasted longer and has been more creative than perhaps almost any other force within pop fandom.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;buckley135-6&quot;&gt;Buckley (2005): pp. 135–36&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[The Rise and Fall of Ziggy Stardust and the Spiders from Mars]]'' (1972), combining the hard rock elements of ''The Man Who Sold the World'' with the lighter experimental rock and pop of ''Hunky Dory'', was released in June. &quot;[[Starman (song)|Starman]]&quot;, issued as an April single ahead of the album, was to cement Bowie's UK breakthrough: both single and album charted rapidly following his July ''[[Top of the Pops]]'' performance of the song. The album, which remained in the chart for two years, was soon joined there by the 6-month-old ''Hunky Dory''. At the same time the non-album single &quot;[[John, I'm Only Dancing]]&quot;, and &quot;[[All the Young Dudes]]&quot;, a song he wrote and produced for [[Mott the Hoople]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Why David Bowie gave away All the Young Dudes to Mott the Hoople |url=https://www.walesonline.co.uk/whats-on/music-nightlife-news/david-bowie-gave-away-young-10749662 |website=Wales Online |accessdate=12 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; were successful in the UK. The [[Ziggy Stardust Tour]] continued to the United States.&lt;ref&gt;Sandford (1997): pp. 93–95&lt;/ref&gt;

Bowie contributed backing vocals, keyboards, and guitar to Reed's 1972 solo breakthrough ''[[Transformer (Lou Reed album)|Transformer]]'', co-producing the album with Mick Ronson.&lt;ref&gt;Buckley (2000): p. 156&lt;/ref&gt; The following year, Bowie co-produced and [[Audio mixing (recorded music)|mixed]] [[The Stooges]] album ''[[Raw Power]]'' alongside Iggy Pop.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Berman|first1=Stuart|title=Iggy and the Stooges Raw Power [Legacy Edition] / Raw Power [Deluxe Edition] Album Review|url=https://pitchfork.com/reviews/albums/14125-raw-power-legacy-edition-raw-power-deluxe-edition/|website=[[Pitchfork (website)|Pitchfork]]|accessdate=30 November 2017|date=14 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; His own ''[[Aladdin Sane]]'' (1973) topped the UK chart, his first number-one album. Described by Bowie as &quot;Ziggy goes to America&quot;, it contained songs he wrote while travelling to and across the US during the earlier part of the Ziggy tour, which now continued to Japan to promote the new album. ''Aladdin Sane'' spawned the UK top five singles &quot;[[The Jean Genie]]&quot; and &quot;[[Drive-In Saturday]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Pegg (2004): pp. 281–83&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Sandford (1997): p. 108&lt;/ref&gt;

Bowie's love of acting led his total immersion in the characters he created for his music. &quot;Offstage I'm a robot. Onstage I achieve emotion. It's probably why I prefer dressing up as Ziggy to being David.&quot; With satisfaction came severe personal difficulties: acting the same role over an extended period, it became impossible for him to separate Ziggy Stardust—and later, the Thin White Duke—from his own character offstage. Ziggy, Bowie said, &quot;wouldn't leave me alone for years. That was when it all started to go sour&amp;nbsp;... My whole personality was affected. It became very dangerous. I really did have doubts about my sanity.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Sandford (1997): pp. 106–07&lt;/ref&gt; His later Ziggy shows, which included songs from both ''Ziggy Stardust'' and ''Aladdin Sane'', were ultra-theatrical affairs filled with shocking stage moments, such as Bowie stripping down to a [[sumo]] wrestling loincloth or simulating [[oral sex]] with Ronson's guitar.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowie: An Illustrated Record p.7&quot;&gt;Carr &amp; Murray (1981): p. 7&lt;/ref&gt; Bowie toured and gave press conferences as Ziggy before a dramatic and abrupt on-stage &quot;retirement&quot; at London's [[Hammersmith Odeon]] on 3 July 1973. Footage from the final show was released the same year for the film ''[[Ziggy Stardust and the Spiders from Mars (film)|Ziggy Stardust and the Spiders from Mars]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Carr &amp; Murray (1981): p. 116&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Listen|filename=David Bowie - Ziggy Stardust.ogg|title=&quot;Ziggy Stardust&quot;|description=Sample of &quot;[[Ziggy Stardust (song)|Ziggy Stardust]]&quot; (1972). A pioneer of [[glam rock]], Bowie performed as the character Ziggy Stardust, backed by [[the Spiders from Mars]].}}
After breaking up the Spiders from Mars, Bowie attempted to move on from his Ziggy persona. His back catalogue was now highly sought after: ''The Man Who Sold the World'' had been re-released in 1972 along with ''Space Oddity''. &quot;[[Life on Mars?]]&quot;, from ''Hunky Dory'', was released in June 1973 and peaked at No. 3 on the [[UK Singles Chart]]. Entering the same chart in September, Bowie's novelty record from 1967, &quot;[[The Laughing Gnome]]&quot;, reached No. 6.&lt;ref&gt;Buckley (2005): p. 163&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Pin Ups]]'', a collection of covers of his 1960s favourites, followed in October, producing a UK No. 3 hit in his version of [[the McCoys]]'s &quot;[[Sorrow (The McCoys song)|Sorrow]]&quot; and itself peaking at number one, making David Bowie the best-selling act of 1973 in the UK. It brought the total number of Bowie albums concurrently on the UK chart to six.&lt;ref&gt;Sandford (1997): p. 115&lt;/ref&gt;

===1974–1976: &quot;Plastic soul&quot; and the Thin White Duke===
[[File:David Bowie - TopPop 1974 08.png|thumb|185px|Bowie filming a video for &quot;[[Rebel Rebel]]&quot; in 1974|left]]
Bowie moved to the US in 1974, initially staying in New York City before settling in Los Angeles.&lt;ref&gt;Buckley (2005): p. 3&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Diamond Dogs]]'' (1974), parts of which found him heading towards [[Soul music|soul]] and [[funk]], was the product of two distinct ideas: a musical based on a wild future in a post-[[apocalypse|apocalyptic]] city, and setting [[George Orwell]]'s ''[[Nineteen Eighty-Four|1984]]'' to music.&lt;ref&gt;Buckley (2005): pp. 180–83&lt;/ref&gt; The album went to number one in the UK, spawning the hits &quot;[[Rebel Rebel]]&quot; and &quot;[[Diamond Dogs (song)|Diamond Dogs]]&quot;, and No. 5 in the US. To promote it, Bowie launched the [[Diamond Dogs Tour]], visiting cities in North America between June and December 1974. Choreographed by [[Toni Basil]], and lavishly produced with theatrical special effects, the high-budget stage production was filmed by [[Alan Yentob]]. The resulting documentary, ''[[Cracked Actor]]'', featured a pasty and emaciated Bowie: the tour coincided with the singer's slide from heavy [[cocaine]] use into addiction, producing severe physical debilitation, [[paranoia]], and emotional problems.&lt;ref name=&quot;buckley 204-5&quot;&gt;Buckley (2005): pp. 204–5&lt;/ref&gt; He later commented that the accompanying live album, ''[[David Live]]'', ought to have been titled &quot;David Bowie Is Alive and Well and Living Only in Theory&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Jones |first1=Allan |title=Goodbye to Ziggy and All That... |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ByCzBwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA65&amp;lpg=PA65&amp;dq=%22god,+that+album!+i%27ve+never+played+it%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=dgghrX-Xy_&amp;sig=GzZoLpuBXtCGRCvQRslcTC4xz1Y&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwiPwbn8nKLKAhXBbT4KHSRPDQ4Q6AEIHTAA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22god%2C%20that%20album!%20i've%20never%20played%20it%22&amp;f=false |website=Melody Maker |accessdate=12 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''David Live'' nevertheless solidified Bowie's status as a superstar, charting at No. 2 in the UK and No. 8 in the US. It also spawned a UK No. 10 hit in Bowie's cover of [[Eddie Floyd]]'s &quot;[[Knock on Wood (song)|Knock on Wood]]&quot;. After a break in [[Philadelphia]], where Bowie recorded new material, the tour resumed with a new emphasis on soul.&lt;ref&gt;Sandford (1997): p. 128&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Bowie-DD-1974-3.jpg|thumb|upright|right|Bowie performing during [[Diamond Dogs Tour]], 1974]]
The fruit of the Philadelphia recording sessions was ''[[Young Americans (album)|Young Americans]]'' (1975). Biographer Christopher Sandford writes, &quot;Over the years, most British rockers had tried, one way or another, to become black-by-extension. Few had succeeded as Bowie did now.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Sandford (1997): p. 138&lt;/ref&gt; The album's sound, which the singer identified as &quot;[[plastic soul]]&quot;, constituted a radical shift in style that initially alienated many of his UK devotees.&lt;ref&gt;Carr &amp; Murray (1981): pp. 68–74&lt;/ref&gt; ''Young Americans'' yielded Bowie's first US number one, &quot;[[Fame (David Bowie song)|Fame]]&quot;, co-written with [[John Lennon]], who contributed backing vocals, and [[Carlos Alomar]]. Lennon called Bowie's work &quot;great, but it's just rock'n'roll with lipstick on&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|editor-last=Buckley|editor-first=Peter|year=2003|title=The Rough Guide to Rock|page=130|publisher=Rough Guides|isbn=978-1-84353-105-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; Earning the distinction of being one of the first white artists to appear on the US variety show ''[[Soul Train]]'', Bowie mimed &quot;Fame&quot;, as well as &quot;[[Golden Years (song)|Golden Years]]&quot;, his November single,&lt;ref name=&quot;sandfordoctobersingle&quot;&gt;Sandford (1997): p. 146&lt;/ref&gt; which was originally offered to [[Elvis Presley]], who declined it.&lt;ref name=&quot;sandfordoctobersingle&quot;/&gt; ''Young Americans'' was a commercial success in both the US and the UK, and a re-issue of the 1969 single &quot;Space Oddity&quot; became Bowie's first number-one hit in the UK a few months after &quot;Fame&quot; achieved the same in the US.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Roberts|first=David (ed.)|year=2001|publisher=Guinness World Records Ltd|title=Guinness World Records: British Hit Singles|isbn=978-0-85156-156-1|page=120}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite his by now well established superstardom, Bowie, in the words of Sandford, &quot;for all his record sales (over a million copies of ''Ziggy Stardust'' alone), existed essentially on loose change.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;firesDefries&quot;&gt;Sandford (1997): pp. 135–36&lt;/ref&gt; In 1975, in a move echoing Ken Pitt's acrimonious dismissal five years earlier, Bowie fired his manager. At the culmination of the ensuing months-long legal dispute, he watched, as described by Sandford, &quot;millions of dollars of his future earnings being surrendered&quot; in what were &quot;uniquely generous terms for Defries&quot;, then &quot;shut himself up in West 20th Street, where for a week his howls could be heard through the locked attic door.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;firesDefries&quot; /&gt; Michael Lippman, Bowie's lawyer during the negotiations, became his new manager; Lippman in turn was awarded substantial compensation when Bowie fired him the following year.&lt;ref&gt;Sandford (1997): pp. 137, 153&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:David Bowie and Cher 1975.JPG|thumb|left|Bowie performing with [[Cher]] on the variety show ''[[Cher (TV series)|Cher]]'', 1975]]

''[[Station to Station]]'' (1976), produced by Bowie and Harry Maslin,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=How David Bowie Brought Thin White Duke to Life on ‘Station to Station’ |url=https://www.rollingstone.com/music/music-features/how-david-bowie-brought-thin-white-duke-to-life-on-station-to-station-125797/ |accessdate=23 December 2019 |work=Rolling Stone}}&lt;/ref&gt; introduced a new Bowie persona, &quot;[[The Thin White Duke]]&quot; of its title-track. Visually, the character was an extension of Thomas Jerome Newton, the extraterrestrial being he portrayed in the film ''[[The Man Who Fell to Earth]]'' the same year.&lt;ref&gt;Buckley (2005): p. 238&lt;/ref&gt; Developing the funk and soul of ''Young Americans'', ''Station to Station'''s synthesizer-heavy arrangements prefigured the [[krautrock]]-influenced music of his next releases. The extent to which drug addiction was now affecting Bowie was made public when [[Russell Harty]] interviewed the singer for his [[London Weekend Television]] talk show in anticipation of the album's supporting tour. Shortly before the satellite-linked interview was scheduled to commence, the death of the Spanish dictator [[Francisco Franco]] was announced. Bowie was asked to relinquish the satellite booking, to allow the Spanish Government to put out a live newsfeed. This he refused to do, and his interview went ahead. In the ensuing lengthy conversation with Harty, Bowie was incoherent and looked &quot;disconnected&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Buckley (2005): p. 244&lt;/ref&gt; His sanity—by his own later admission—had become twisted from cocaine; he overdosed several times during the year, and was withering physically to an alarming degree.&lt;ref name=&quot;buckley 204-5&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;sandford158&quot; /&gt;

''Station to Station''{{'}}s January 1976 release was followed in February by a 3{{sfrac|1|2}}-month-long concert tour of Europe and North America. Featuring a starkly lit set, the [[Isolar – 1976 Tour]] with its iconic colour newsprint [[Isolar]] concert program, highlighted songs from the album, including the dramatic and lengthy [[Station to Station (song)|title track]], the ballads &quot;[[Wild Is the Wind (song)|Wild Is the Wind]]&quot; and &quot;[[Word on a Wing]]&quot;, and the funkier &quot;[[TVC 15]]&quot; and &quot;[[Stay (David Bowie song)|Stay]]&quot;. The core band that coalesced to record this album and tour—rhythm guitarist [[Carlos Alomar]], bassist [[George Murray (musician)|George Murray]], and drummer [[Dennis Davis]]—continued as a stable unit for the remainder of the 1970s. The tour was highly successful but mired in political controversy. Bowie was quoted in [[Stockholm]] as saying that &quot;Britain could benefit from a Fascist leader&quot;, and was detained by customs on the Russian/Polish border for possessing [[Nazism|Nazi]] paraphernalia.&lt;ref name=&quot;Buckley pp.289–91&quot;&gt;Buckley (2000): pp. 289–91.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:David Bowie 1976.jpg|thumb|Bowie as the Thin White Duke at [[Maple Leaf Gardens]], Toronto, 1976]]
Matters came to a head in London in May in what became known as the &quot;[[London Victoria station|Victoria Station]] incident&quot;. Arriving in an open-top [[Mercedes-Benz|Mercedes]] [[convertible]], Bowie waved to the crowd in a gesture that some alleged was a [[Nazi salute]], which was captured on camera and published in ''[[NME]]''. Bowie said the photographer caught him in mid-wave.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Paytress|first=Mark|title=The Controversial Homecoming|journal=Mojo Classic|date=January 2007|issue=60 Years of Bowie|page=64}}&lt;/ref&gt; He later blamed his pro-fascism comments and his behaviour during the period on his addictions and the character of the Thin White Duke.&lt;ref&gt;Carr &amp; Murray (1981): p. 11&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;I was out of my mind, totally crazed. The main thing I was functioning on was mythology&amp;nbsp;... that whole thing about Hitler and Rightism&amp;nbsp;... I'd discovered [[King Arthur]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;sandford158&quot;&gt;Sandford (1997): p. 158&lt;/ref&gt; According to playwright Alan Franks, writing later in ''[[The Times]]'', &quot;he was indeed 'deranged'. He had some very bad experiences with hard drugs.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Buckley (2005): p. 252&lt;/ref&gt; Bowie's cocaine addiction, which had motivated these controversies, had much to do with his time living in Los Angeles, a city which alienated him. Discussing his flirtations with fascism in a 1980 interview with ''NME'', Bowie explained that Los Angeles was &quot;where it had all happened. The fucking place should be wiped off the face of the Earth. To be anything to do with rock and roll and go and live in Los Angeles is, I think, just heading for disaster. It really is.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|first=Angus|last=MacKinnon|title=The future isn't what it used to be David Bowie talks about loneliness, insecurity, and myth, And the dangers of messing with Major Tom|url=http://www.bowiegoldenyears.com/articles/800913-nme.html|work=[[NME]]|location=London, England|date=13 September 1980|accessdate=30 January 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170106013020/http://www.bowiegoldenyears.com/articles/800913-nme.html|archive-date=6 January 2017|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After recovering from addiction, Bowie apologised for these statements, and throughout the 1980s and '90s criticised racism in European politics and the American music industry.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|first=Stereo|last=Williams|url=https://www.thedailybeast.com/on-race-david-bowie-delved-deep-into-the-darkness-and-came-back-human|title=On Race, David Bowie Delved Deep into the Darkness and Came Back Human|work=[[Daily Beast]]|publisher=IAC/InteractiveCorp|location=New York City|date=12 January 2016|accessdate=8 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, Bowie's comments on fascism, as well as [[Eric Clapton]]'s alcohol-fuelled denunciations of Pakistani immigrants in 1976, led to the establishment of [[Rock Against Racism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first=Andy|last=Greene|title=Flashback: The Clash Rock Against Racism in 1978|url=https://www.rollingstone.com/music/videos/flashback-the-clash-rock-against-racism-in-1978-20140513|work=[[Rolling Stone]]|location=New York City|date=13 May 2014|accessdate=21 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===1976–1979: Berlin era===
{{main|Berlin Trilogy}}
Bowie moved to Switzerland in 1976, purchasing a chalet in the hills to the north of [[Lake Geneva]]. In the new environment, his cocaine use decreased and he found time for other pursuits outside his musical career.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|first=Malcolm|last=Curtis|url=https://www.thelocal.ch/20160111/bowies-discreet-time-in-switzerland-remembered|title=Bowie's discreet time in Switzerland recalled|work=[[The Local]]|location=Stockholm, Sweden|date=11 January 2016|accessdate=22 September 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; He devoted more time to his painting, and produced a number of [[post-modernist]] pieces. When on tour, he took to sketching in a notebook, and photographing scenes for later reference. Visiting galleries in [[Geneva]] and the [[Brücke Museum]] in Berlin, Bowie became, in the words of biographer Christopher Sandford, &quot;a prolific producer and collector of contemporary art.&amp;nbsp;... Not only did he become a well-known patron of [[expressionist art]]: locked in Clos des Mésanges he began an intensive self-improvement course in classical music and literature, and started work on an autobiography.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Sandford (1997): pp. 154–55&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Hauptstraße 155 Berlin-Schöneberg.jpg|thumb|Apartment building at 155, Hauptstraße, [[Schöneberg]], Berlin, where Bowie lived from 1976 to 1978]]
Before the end of 1976, Bowie's interest in the burgeoning German music scene, as well as his drug addiction, prompted him to move to [[West Berlin]] to clean up and revitalise his career. There he was often seen riding a bicycle between his apartment on Hauptstraße in [[Schöneberg]] and [[Hansa Tonstudio]], the recording studio he used, located on Köthener Straße in [[Kreuzberg]], near the [[Berlin Wall]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Ruether 82–85&quot;&gt;{{cite web|first=Tobias|last=Ruether|url=https://032c.com/the-man-who-came-from-hell/|title=The Man Who Came from Hell|work=[[032c]]|pages=82–85|date=Winter 2006–2007|accessdate=21 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; While working with [[Brian Eno]] and sharing an apartment with Iggy Pop, he began to focus on minimalist, ambient music for the first of three albums, co-produced with [[Tony Visconti]], that became known as his [[Berlin Trilogy]].&lt;ref&gt;Sandford (1997): p. 149&lt;/ref&gt; During the same period, Iggy Pop, with Bowie as a co-writer and musician, completed his solo album debut ''[[The Idiot (album)|The Idiot]]'' and its follow-up ''[[Lust for Life (Iggy Pop album)|Lust for Life]]'', touring the UK, Europe, and the US in March and April 1977.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Kris |last=Needs |title= The Passenger |work= [[Mojo (magazine)|Mojo Classic]] |location= London, England |issue= &quot;60 Years of Bowie&quot; |page=65 |date= January 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:David bowie 05061978 01 150.jpg|thumb|left|upright|Bowie performing in [[Oslo]], Norway, 1978]]
The album ''[[Low (David Bowie album)|Low]]'' (1977), partly influenced by the [[Krautrock]] sound of [[Kraftwerk]] and [[Neu!]], evinced a move away from narration in Bowie's songwriting to a more abstract musical form in which lyrics were sporadic and optional. Although he completed the album in November 1976, it took his unsettled record company another three months to release it.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ruether 82–85&quot;/&gt; It received considerable negative criticism upon its release—a release which RCA, anxious to maintain the established commercial momentum, did not welcome, and which Bowie's former manager, Tony Defries, who still maintained a significant financial interest in the singer's affairs, tried to prevent. Despite these forebodings, ''Low'' yielded the UK No. 3 single &quot;[[Sound and Vision]]&quot;, and its own performance surpassed that of ''Station to Station'' in the UK chart, where it reached No. 2. Leading contemporary composer [[Philip Glass]] described ''Low'' as &quot;a work of genius&quot; in 1992, when he used it as the basis for his ''[[Symphony No. 1 (Glass)|Symphony No. 1 &quot;Low&quot;]]''; subsequently, Glass used Bowie's next album as the basis for his 1996 ''[[Symphony No. 4 (Glass)|Symphony No. 4 &quot;Heroes&quot;]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;low&quot;&gt;Sandford (1997): pp. 166–68&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Perone (2007): p. 175&lt;/ref&gt; Glass has praised Bowie's gift for creating &quot;fairly complex pieces of music, masquerading as simple pieces&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Thomson (1993): p. xiii&lt;/ref&gt; Also in 1977, [[London Records|London]] released ''Starting Point'', a ten-song LP containing releases from Bowie's [[Deram Records|Deram]] period (1966—67).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first=Alex|last=Henderson|title=Starting Point – David Bowie|url=https://www.allmusic.com/album/starting-point-mw0000312210|website=AllMusic|accessdate=9 January 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Listen|filename=David Bowie - Heroes.ogg|title=&quot;Heroes&quot;|description=Sample of &quot;[[&quot;Heroes&quot; (David Bowie song)|Heroes]]&quot; (1977). One of the ambient rock songs to emerge from Bowie's [[Berlin Trilogy]] era, &quot;Heroes&quot; gained lasting popularity.}}
Echoing ''Low''{{'}}s minimalist, instrumental approach, the second of the trilogy, ''[[&quot;Heroes&quot; (David Bowie album)|&quot;Heroes&quot;]]'' (1977), incorporated pop and rock to a greater extent, seeing Bowie joined by guitarist [[Robert Fripp]]. Like ''Low'', ''&quot;Heroes&quot;'' evinced the [[zeitgeist]] of the [[Cold War]], symbolised by the divided city of Berlin.&lt;ref&gt;Pegg (2000): pp. 90–92&lt;/ref&gt; Incorporating ambient sounds from a variety of sources including white noise generators, synthesisers and [[Koto (instrument)|koto]], the album was another hit, reaching No. 3 in the UK. Its [[&quot;Heroes&quot; (song)|title-track]], though only reaching No. 24 in the UK singles chart, gained lasting popularity, and within months had been released in both German and French.&lt;ref name=&quot;heroes&quot;&gt;Sandford (1997): pp. 181–82&lt;/ref&gt; Towards the end of the year, Bowie performed the song for Marc Bolan's television show ''[[Marc (TV series)|Marc]]'', and again two days later for [[Bing Crosby]]'s final [[CBS]] television Christmas special, when he joined Crosby in &quot;[[Peace on Earth/Little Drummer Boy]]&quot;, a version of &quot;[[The Little Drummer Boy]]&quot; with a new, [[Counterpoint|contrapuntal]] verse. Five years later, the duet proved a worldwide seasonal hit, charting in the UK at No. 3 on Christmas Day, 1982.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Bronson|first=Fred|title=The Billboard Book of Number 1 Hits|year=1990|publisher=Billboard Books|isbn=978-0-8230-7677-2|page=572}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After completing ''Low'' and ''&quot;Heroes&quot;'', Bowie spent much of 1978 on the [[Isolar II – The 1978 World Tour|Isolar II world tour]], bringing the music of the first two Berlin Trilogy albums to almost a million people during 70 concerts in 12 countries. By now he had broken his drug addiction; biographer David Buckley writes that Isolar II was &quot;Bowie's first tour for five years in which he had probably not anaesthetised himself with copious quantities of cocaine before taking the stage.&amp;nbsp;... Without the oblivion that drugs had brought, he was now in a healthy enough mental condition to want to make friends.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Buckley (2005): p. 293&lt;/ref&gt; Recordings from the tour made up the live album ''[[Stage (David Bowie album)|Stage]]'', released the same year.&lt;ref&gt;Sandford (1997): p. 189&lt;/ref&gt; Bowie also recorded narration for an adaptation of [[Sergei Prokofiev]]'s classical composition ''[[Peter and the Wolf]]'', which was released as an [[David Bowie Narrates Prokofiev's Peter and the Wolf|album]] in May 1978.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=David Bowie Narrates Prokofiev's Peter and the Wolf |url=https://www.allmusic.com/album/david-bowie-narrates-prokofievs-peter-and-the-wolf-mw0001375571 |website=Allmusic |accessdate=16 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The final piece in what Bowie called his &quot;[[triptych]]&quot;, ''[[Lodger (album)|Lodger]]'' (1979), eschewed the minimalist, ambient nature of the other two, making a partial return to the drum- and guitar-based rock and pop of his pre-Berlin era. The result was a complex mixture of [[New wave music|new wave]] and [[world music]], in places incorporating [[Phrygian dominant scale|Hijaz]] [[Musical scale#Non-Western scales|non-Western scales]]. Some tracks were composed using Eno and [[Peter Schmidt (artist)|Peter Schmidt]]'s [[Oblique Strategies]] cards: &quot;Boys Keep Swinging&quot; entailed band members swapping instruments, &quot;Move On&quot; used the chords from Bowie's early composition &quot;All the Young Dudes&quot; played backwards, and &quot;Red Money&quot; took backing tracks from &quot;Sister Midnight&quot;, a piece previously composed with Iggy Pop.&lt;ref&gt;Carr &amp; Murray (1981): pp. 102–07&lt;/ref&gt; The album was recorded in Switzerland. Ahead of its release, RCA's Mel Ilberman stated, &quot;It would be fair to call it Bowie's ''[[Sgt. Pepper's Lonely Hearts Club Band|Sergeant Pepper]]''&amp;nbsp;... a concept album that portrays the Lodger as a homeless wanderer, shunned and victimized by life's pressures and technology.&quot; As described by biographer Christopher Sandford, &quot;The record dashed such high hopes with dubious choices, and production that spelt the end—for fifteen years—of Bowie's partnership with Eno.&quot; ''Lodger'' reached No. 4 in the UK and No. 20 in the US, and yielded the UK hit singles &quot;[[Boys Keep Swinging]]&quot; and &quot;[[DJ (David Bowie song)|DJ]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Buckley (2005): p. 281&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;lodger&quot;&gt;Sandford (1997): pp. 191–92&lt;/ref&gt; Towards the end of the year, Bowie and Angie initiated divorce proceedings, and after months of court battles the marriage was ended in early 1980.&lt;ref&gt;Sandford (1997): p. 197&lt;/ref&gt;

===1980–1988: New Romantic and pop era===
[[File:Bowie 1983 serious moonlight.jpg|thumb|150px|upright|left|[[Serious Moonlight Tour]], 1983]]
''[[Scary Monsters and Super Creeps]]'' (1980) produced the number-one hit &quot;[[Ashes to Ashes (David Bowie song)|Ashes to Ashes]]&quot;, featuring the textural work of guitar-synthesist [[Chuck Hammer]] and revisiting the character of Major Tom from &quot;Space Oddity&quot;. The song gave international exposure to the underground [[New Romantic]] movement when Bowie visited the London club &quot;Blitz&quot;—the main New Romantic hangout—to recruit several of the regulars (including [[Steve Strange]] of the band [[Visage (band)|Visage]]) to act in the accompanying video, renowned as one of the most innovative of all time.&lt;ref&gt;Pegg (2000): p. 29&lt;/ref&gt; While ''Scary Monsters'' used principles established by the Berlin albums, it was considered by critics to be far more direct musically and lyrically. The album's hard rock edge included conspicuous guitar contributions from [[Robert Fripp]], [[Chuck Hammer]], and [[Pete Townshend]].&lt;ref&gt;Carr &amp; Murray (1981): pp. 108–14&lt;/ref&gt; As &quot;Ashes to Ashes&quot; hit number one on the UK charts, Bowie opened a three-month run on Broadway on 24 September, starring as [[Joseph Merrick|John Merrick]] in ''[[The Elephant Man (play)|The Elephant Man]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;elephantman&quot;&gt;Sandford (1997): pp. 205–07&lt;/ref&gt;

Bowie paired with [[Queen (band)|Queen]] in 1981 for a one-off single release, &quot;[[Under Pressure]]&quot;. The duet was a hit, becoming Bowie's third UK number-one single. Bowie was given the lead role in the BBC's 1982 televised adaptation of [[Bertolt Brecht]]'s play ''[[Baal (play)|Baal]]''. Coinciding with its transmission, a five-track [[Extended play|EP]] of songs from the play, recorded earlier in Berlin, was released as ''[[Baal (EP)|David Bowie in Bertolt Brecht's Baal]]''. In March 1982, the month before [[Paul Schrader]]'s film ''[[Cat People (1982 film)|Cat People]]'' came out, Bowie's title song, &quot;[[Cat People (Putting Out Fire)]]&quot;, was released as a single, becoming a minor US hit and entering the UK Top 30.&lt;ref&gt;Sandford (1997): pp. 208, 211–12&lt;/ref&gt;

Bowie reached his peak of popularity and commercial success in 1983 with ''[[Let's Dance (David Bowie album)|Let's Dance]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | first=Mick | last=Brown| url= https://www.telegraph.co.uk/music/artists/david-bowie-interview-from-1996-i-have-done-just-about-everythin/ | title= David Bowie interview from 1996: 'I have done just about everything that it's possible to do' | work=[[The Daily Telegraph]]|location=London, England | date=11 January 2016 | accessdate=14 March 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Co-produced by [[Chic (band)|Chic]]'s [[Nile Rodgers]], the album went platinum in both the UK and the US. Its three singles became Top 20 hits in both countries, where its [[Let's Dance (David Bowie song)|title track]] reached number one. &quot;[[Modern Love (song)|Modern Love]]&quot; and &quot;[[China Girl (song)|China Girl]]&quot; each made No. 2 in the UK, accompanied by a pair of &quot;absorbing&quot; promotional videos that biographer David Buckley said &quot;activated key archetypes in the pop world. 'Let's Dance', with its little narrative surrounding the young [[Aboriginal Australians|Aborigine]] couple, targeted 'youth', and 'China Girl', with its bare-bummed (and later partially censored) beach lovemaking scene (a homage to the film ''[[From Here to Eternity]]''), was sufficiently sexually provocative to guarantee heavy rotation on MTV&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Buckley (2000): p. 344.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Stevie Ray Vaughan]] was guest guitarist playing solo on &quot;Let's Dance&quot;, although the video depicts Bowie miming this part.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Timothy|last=White |title=David Bowie Interview |work=Musician|date=May 1983|volume=55 |pages=52–66, 122}}&lt;/ref&gt; By 1983, Bowie had emerged as one of the most important video artists of the day. ''Let's Dance'' was followed by the [[Serious Moonlight Tour]], during which Bowie was accompanied by guitarist [[Earl Slick]] and backing vocalists [[The Simms Brothers Band|Frank and George Simms]]. The world tour lasted six months and was extremely popular.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Buckley (2005): pp. 335–55&lt;/ref&gt; At the [[1984 MTV Video Music Awards]] Bowie received two awards including the inaugural [[Michael Jackson Video Vanguard Award|Video Vanguard Award]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mtv.com/ontv/vma/1984/|title=1984 Video Music Awards|website=MTV|accessdate=17 August 2016|at=Select &quot;Winners&quot;, and then &quot;View all nominees&quot; under the relevant category}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:David Bowie (1987).jpg|thumb|upright|Bowie performing during the [[Glass Spider Tour]], 1987]]
''[[Tonight (David Bowie album)|Tonight]]'' (1984), another dance-oriented album, found Bowie collaborating with [[Tina Turner]] and, once again, Iggy Pop. It included a number of cover songs, among them the 1966 [[The Beach Boys|Beach Boys]] hit &quot;[[God Only Knows]]&quot;. The album bore the transatlantic Top 10 hit &quot;[[Blue Jean (song)|Blue Jean]]&quot;, itself the inspiration for a short film that won Bowie a [[Grammy Award for Best Music Video|Grammy Award for Best Short Form Music Video]], ''[[Jazzin' for Blue Jean]]''. Bowie performed at [[Wembley Stadium (1923)|Wembley Stadium]] in 1985 for [[Live Aid]], a multi-venue benefit concert for Ethiopian famine relief.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url= https://www.rollingstone.com/music/videos/flashback-david-bowie-triumphs-at-live-aid-in-1985-20160126 | title= Flashback: David Bowie Triumphs at Live Aid in 1985 | work=Rolling Stone | first=Andy | last=Greene | date=26 January 2016 | accessdate=5 May 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the event, the video for a fundraising single was premiered, Bowie's duet with [[Mick Jagger]]. &quot;[[Dancing in the Street]]&quot; quickly went to number one on release. The same year, Bowie worked with the [[Pat Metheny Group]] to record &quot;[[This Is Not America]]&quot; for the soundtrack of ''[[The Falcon and the Snowman]]''. Released as a single, the song became a Top 40 hit in the UK and US.&lt;ref&gt;Buckley (2005): pp. 165–66&lt;/ref&gt;

Bowie was given a role in the 1986 film ''[[Absolute Beginners (film)|Absolute Beginners]]''. It was poorly received by critics, but Bowie's [[Theme music|theme song]], also named &quot;[[Absolute Beginners (David Bowie song)|Absolute Beginners]]&quot;, rose to No. 2 in the UK charts. He also appeared as [[Jareth]], the Goblin King, in the 1986 [[Jim Henson]] film ''[[Labyrinth (1986 film)|Labyrinth]]'', for which he worked with composer [[Trevor Jones (composer)|Trevor Jones]] and wrote five original songs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=All hail the Goblin King: David Bowie's 'Labyrinth' soundtrack being reissued |url=http://abcnewsradioonline.com/music-news/2017/4/27/all-hail-the-goblin-king-david-bowies-labyrinth-soundtrack-b.html |website=ABC Newsradio Online |accessdate=12 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; His final solo album of the decade was 1987's ''[[Never Let Me Down]]'', where he ditched the light sound of his previous two albums, instead offering harder rock with an [[Industrial music|industrial]]/[[techno]] dance edge. Peaking at No. 6 in the UK, the album yielded the hits &quot;[[Day-In Day-Out|Day-In, Day-Out]]&quot; (his 60th single), &quot;[[Time Will Crawl]]&quot;, and &quot;[[Never Let Me Down (David Bowie song)|Never Let Me Down]]&quot;. Bowie later described it as his &quot;nadir&quot;, calling it &quot;an awful album&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite work|first=James|last=McNair|title=Tumble &amp; Twirl|work=Mojo Classic|location=London, England|date=January 2007|issue=60 Years of Bowie|page=101}}&lt;/ref&gt; Supporting ''Never Let Me Down'', and preceded by nine promotional press shows, the 86-concert [[Glass Spider Tour]] commenced on 30 May. Bowie's backing band included [[Peter Frampton]] on lead guitar. Contemporary critics maligned the tour as overproduced, saying it pandered to the current [[arena rock|stadium rock]] trends in its special effects and dancing,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|first=Andy|last=Fyfe|title=Too Dizzy|work=Mojo Classic|location=London, England|date=January 2007|issue=60 Years of Bowie|pages=88–91}}&lt;/ref&gt; although years after the tour's conclusion, critics acknowledged that the tour influenced how other artists performed concerts, including [[Britney Spears]], [[Madonna (entertainer)|Madonna]], and [[U2]].&lt;ref name=BBC09&gt;{{cite news|first=Ian|last=Youngs| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/entertainment/8188140.stm |work=BBC News| title=Stadium rock, from Beatles to Bono | date=13 August 2009 | accessdate=25 June 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |first=Charles | last=Platiau| url=http://theconversation.com/bowies-greatest-gift-even-his-failures-will-echo-through-the-ages-53003 | title=Bowie's greatest gift? Even his 'failures' will echo through the ages |work=[[The Conversation (website)|The Conversation]]|location=Melbourne, Australia|date=12 January 2016 | accessdate=25 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===1989–1991: Tin Machine===
{{Main|Tin Machine}}
Bowie shelved his solo career in 1989, retreating to the relative anonymity of band membership for the first time since the early 1970s. A hard-rocking quartet, [[Tin Machine]] came into being after Bowie began to work experimentally with guitarist [[Reeves Gabrels]]. The line-up was completed by [[Tony Fox Sales|Tony]] and [[Hunt Sales]], whom Bowie had known since the late 1970s for their contribution, on bass and drums respectively, to Iggy Pop's 1977 album ''Lust for Life''.&lt;ref&gt;Buckley (2005): p. 387&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:David Bowie Chile.jpg|thumb|upright|Bowie in Chile during the [[Sound+Vision Tour]], 1990]]
Although he intended Tin Machine to operate as a democracy, Bowie dominated, both in songwriting and in decision-making.&lt;ref&gt;Sandford (1997): p. 274&lt;/ref&gt; The band's album debut, ''[[Tin Machine (album)|Tin Machine]]'' (1989), was initially popular, though its politicised lyrics did not find universal approval: Bowie described one song as &quot;a simplistic, naive, radical, laying-it-down about the emergence of [[Neo-Nazism|Neo-Nazis]]&quot;; in the view of biographer Christopher Sandford, &quot;It took nerve to denounce drugs, fascism and TV&amp;nbsp;... in terms that reached the literary level of a comic book.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;tinmachine1&quot;&gt;Sandford (1997): p. 275&lt;/ref&gt; EMI complained of &quot;lyrics that preach&quot; as well as &quot;repetitive tunes&quot; and &quot;minimalist or no production&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Sandford (1997): p. 273&lt;/ref&gt; The album nevertheless reached No. 3 and went gold in the UK.&lt;ref name=&quot;tinmachine1&quot;/&gt;

Tin Machine's first world tour was a commercial success, but there was growing reluctance—among fans and critics alike—to accept Bowie's presentation as merely a band member.&lt;ref&gt;Buckley (2005): p. 394&lt;/ref&gt; A series of Tin Machine singles failed to chart, and Bowie, after a disagreement with EMI, left the label.&lt;ref&gt;Sandford (1997): pp. 278–79&lt;/ref&gt; Like his audience and his critics, Bowie himself became increasingly disaffected with his role as just one member of a band.&lt;ref&gt;Sandford (1997): p. 278&lt;/ref&gt; Tin Machine began work on a second album, but Bowie put the venture on hold and made a return to solo work. Performing his early hits during the seven-month [[Sound+Vision Tour]], he found commercial success and acclaim once again.&lt;ref&gt;Sandford (1997): pp. 280–86&lt;/ref&gt;

In October 1990, a decade after his divorce from Angie, Bowie and [[Somalis|Somali]]-born supermodel [[Iman (model)|Iman]] were introduced by a mutual friend. Bowie recalled, &quot;I was naming the children the night we met&amp;nbsp;... it was absolutely immediate.&quot; They married in 1992.&lt;ref&gt;Sandford (1997): p. 289&lt;/ref&gt; Tin Machine resumed work the same month, but their audience and critics, ultimately left disappointed by the first album, showed little interest in a second. ''[[Tin Machine II]]''{{'}}s arrival was marked by a widely publicised and ill-timed conflict over the cover art: after production had begun, the new record label, [[Victory Records|Victory]], deemed the depiction of four ancient nude [[Kouros|Kouroi]] statues, judged by Bowie to be &quot;in exquisite taste&quot;, to be &quot;a show of wrong, obscene images&quot;, requiring air-brushing and patching to render the figures sexless.&lt;ref&gt;Sandford (1997): p. 292&lt;/ref&gt; Tin Machine toured again, but after the live album ''[[Tin Machine Live: Oy Vey, Baby]]'' failed commercially, the band drifted apart, and Bowie, though he continued to collaborate with Gabrels, resumed his solo career.&lt;ref&gt;Sandford (1997): pp. 294–95&lt;/ref&gt;

===1992–1998: Electronic period===
On 20 April 1992, Bowie appeared at [[The Freddie Mercury Tribute Concert]], following the Queen singer's death the previous year. As well as performing &quot;Heroes&quot; and &quot;All the Young Dudes&quot;, he was joined on &quot;Under Pressure&quot; by [[Annie Lennox]], who took Mercury's vocal part; during his appearance, Bowie knelt and recited the [[Lord's Prayer]] at [[Wembley Stadium (1923)|Wembley Stadium]].&lt;ref&gt;Sandford (1997): pp. 298–99&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;LA Times Mercury&quot;&gt;{{cite news|first=Jeff|last=Kaye|url=https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-1992-04-22-ca-497-story.html|title=(Safe) Sex, (No) Drugs and Rock 'n' Roll : A Star-Filled Send-Off to Freddie Mercury|work=[[Los Angeles Times]]|date=22 April 1992|accessdate=11 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Four days later, Bowie and Iman were married in Switzerland. Intending to move to Los Angeles, they flew in to search for a suitable property, but found themselves confined to their hotel, under curfew: the [[1992 Los Angeles riots]] began the day they arrived. They settled in New York instead.&lt;ref&gt;Buckley (2005): pp. 413–14&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:David Bowie 1997.jpg|thumb|left|upright|Bowie performing in [[Turku]], Finland, 1997]]
In 1993, Bowie released his first solo offering since his Tin Machine departure, the soul, jazz, and [[hip hop music|hip-hop]] influenced ''[[Black Tie White Noise]]''. Making prominent use of electronic instruments, the album, which reunited Bowie with ''Let's Dance'' producer [[Nile Rodgers]], confirmed Bowie's return to popularity, hitting the number-one spot on the UK charts and spawning three Top 40 hits, including the Top 10 single &quot;[[Jump They Say]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Sandford (1997): pp. 301–08&lt;/ref&gt; Bowie explored new directions on ''[[The Buddha of Suburbia (soundtrack)|The Buddha of Suburbia]]'' (1993), ostensibly a soundtrack album of his music composed for the BBC television adaptation of [[The Buddha of Suburbia (novel)|Hanif Kureishi's novel]]. Only the title track had been used in the television adaptation, although some of his [[Subject (music)|themes]] for it were also present on the album.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.popmatters.com/david-bowie-the-buddha-of-suburbia-2496207891.html |last=Keefe |first=Michael |title=David Bowie The Buddha of Suburbia |work=PopMatters |date=16 October 2007 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20190327123037/https://www.popmatters.com/david-bowie-the-buddha-of-suburbia-2496207891.html |archivedate=27 March 2019 |url-status=live |accessdate=6 January 2017 }}&lt;/ref&gt; It contained some of the new elements introduced in ''Black Tie White Noise'', and also signalled a move towards [[alternative rock]]. The album was a critical success but received a low-key release and only made No. 87 in the UK charts.&lt;ref&gt;Buckley (2000): pp. 494–95, 623&lt;/ref&gt;

Reuniting Bowie with Eno, the quasi-[[industrial music|industrial]] ''[[Outside (David Bowie album)|Outside]]'' (1995) was originally conceived as the first volume in a non-linear narrative of art and murder. Featuring characters from a short story written by Bowie, the album achieved UK and US chart success, and yielded three Top 40 UK singles.&lt;ref&gt;Buckley (2000): pp. 623–24&lt;/ref&gt; In a move that provoked mixed reaction from both fans and critics, Bowie chose [[Nine Inch Nails]] as his tour partner for the [[Outside Tour]]. Visiting cities in Europe and North America between September 1995 and February 1996, the tour saw the return of Gabrels as Bowie's guitarist.&lt;ref&gt;Buckley (2000): pp. 512–13&lt;/ref&gt; On 7 January 1997, Bowie celebrated his half century with a [[Earthling (album)#Live performances|50th birthday concert]] at [[Madison Square Garden]], New York, at which he was joined in playing his songs and those of his guests, Lou Reed, [[Dave Grohl]] and the [[Foo Fighters]], [[Robert Smith (musician)|Robert Smith]] of [[the Cure]], [[Billy Corgan]] of [[the Smashing Pumpkins]], [[Black Francis]] of the [[Pixies (band)|Pixies]], and [[Sonic Youth]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=David Bowie Birthday Celebration Live Album an Unauthorized Bootleg|url=https://www.pastemagazine.com/articles/2011/03/david-bowie-to-release-live-album-featuring-foo-fi.html|work=Paste Magazine|date=21 March 2011|first=Nathan|last=Spicer}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Bowie was inducted into the [[Rock and Roll Hall of Fame]] on 17 January 1996.&lt;ref name=&quot;rockhall&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=David Bowie: Rock and Roll Hall of Fame Induction|website=Rock and Roll Hall of Fame|url=https://www.rockhall.com/inductees/david-bowie|accessdate=16 September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Incorporating experiments in British jungle and [[drum and bass|drum 'n' bass]], ''[[Earthling (album)|Earthling]]'' (1997) was a critical and commercial success in the UK and the US, and two singles from the album – &quot;[[Little Wonder (song)|Little Wonder]]&quot; and &quot;[[Dead Man Walking (song)|Dead Man Walking]]&quot; – became UK Top 40 hits. Bowie's song &quot;[[I'm Afraid of Americans]]&quot; from the [[Paul Verhoeven]] film ''[[Showgirls]]'' was re-recorded for the album, and remixed by [[Trent Reznor]] for a single release. The heavy rotation of the accompanying video, also featuring [[Trent Reznor]], contributed to the song's 16-week stay in the US [[Billboard Hot 100|''Billboard'' Hot 100]]. Reznor also executive produced the ''[[Lost Highway (soundtrack)|Lost Highway]]'' soundtrack (1997) which begins and ends with different mixes of Bowie's ''Outside'' song &quot;[[I'm Deranged]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Lost Highway [Original Motion Picture Soundtrack] |url=https://www.allmusic.com/album/lost-highway-original-motion-picture-soundtrack-mw0000082314 |website=Allmusic}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bowie received a star on the [[Hollywood Walk of Fame]] on 12 February 1997.&lt;ref name=DB97x&gt;{{citation | url=https://www.davidbowie.com/1997/1997/01/30/david-bowie-launches-new-album-earthling-with-network-television-appearances-a-pay-per-view-concert-a-national-radio-broadcast-and-star-on-hollywood-blvds-walk-of-fame | title=David Bowie Launches New Album 'earthling' With Network Television Appearances, A Pay-per-view Concert, A National Radio Broadcast, And Star On Hollywood Blvd's Walk Of Fame | date=30 January 1997 | accessdate=5 July 2013 | url-status=live | archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20200113001444/https://www.davidbowie.com/1997/1997/01/30/david-bowie-launches-new-album-earthling-with-network-television-appearances-a-pay-per-view-concert-a-national-radio-broadcast-and-star-on-hollywood-blvds-walk-of-fame | archivedate=13 January 2020 | df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Earthling Tour]] took in Europe and North America between June and November 1997.&lt;ref name=&quot;Buckley pp. 533–34&quot;&gt;Buckley (2000): pp. 533–34&lt;/ref&gt; In November 1997, Bowie performed on the BBC's [[Children in Need]] charity single &quot;[[Perfect Day 97|Perfect Day]]&quot;, which reached number one in the UK.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.independent.co.uk/arts-entertainment/oh-its-such-a-perfect-song-1293130.html|title=Oh, it's such a perfect song|newspaper=The Independent|date=9 November 1997|accessdate=13 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bowie reunited with Visconti in 1998 to record &quot;(Safe in This) Sky Life&quot; for ''[[The Rugrats Movie]]''. Although the track was edited out of the final cut, it was later re-recorded and released as &quot;Safe&quot; on the B-side of Bowie's 2002 single &quot;[[Everyone Says 'Hi']]{{-&quot;}}.&lt;ref&gt;Thompson (2006): p. 203&lt;/ref&gt; The reunion led to other collaborations including a limited-edition single release version of [[Placebo (band)|Placebo's]] track &quot;[[Without You I'm Nothing (song)|Without You I'm Nothing]]&quot;, co-produced by Visconti, with Bowie's harmonised vocal added to the original recording.&lt;ref&gt;Thompson (2006): pp. 203, 212&lt;/ref&gt;

===1999–2012: Neoclassicist era===
[[File:Heathen Tour Bowie and Sterling Campbell.jpg|thumb|Bowie on stage with [[Sterling Campbell]] during the [[Heathen Tour]], 2002]]
Bowie, with Reeves Gabrels, created the soundtrack for ''[[Omikron: The Nomad Soul]]'', a 1999 computer game in which he and Iman also voiced characters based on their likenesses. Released the same year and containing re-recorded tracks from ''Omikron'', his album ''[[Hours (David Bowie album)|Hours]]'' featured a song with lyrics by the winner of his &quot;Cyber Song Contest&quot; Internet competition, Alex Grant.&lt;ref&gt;Buckley (2005): p. 466&lt;/ref&gt; Making extensive use of live instruments, the album was Bowie's exit from heavy electronica.&lt;ref&gt;Perone (2007): p. 125&lt;/ref&gt; Sessions for the planned album ''[[Toy (David Bowie album)|Toy]]'', intended to feature new versions of some of Bowie's earliest pieces as well as three new songs, commenced in 2000, but the album was never released. Bowie and Visconti continued their collaboration, producing a new album of completely original songs instead: the result of the sessions was the 2002 album ''[[Heathen (David Bowie album)|Heathen]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Buckley (2005): pp. 488–89&lt;/ref&gt;

On 25 June 2000, Bowie made his second appearance at the [[Glastonbury Festival]] in England, playing 30 years after his first.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/entertainment/805739.stm |title=Bowie ends 'best-ever' Glastonbury |date=26 June 2000 |publisher=BBC |accessdate=13 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The performance was released as a posthumous [[Glastonbury 2000|live album]] in November 2018.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=David Bowie's Glastonbury 2000 Set Getting Full Release |url=https://www.rollingstone.com/music/music-news/davie-bowie-glastonbury-2000-set-concert-film-album-release-732202/ |website=Rolling Stone |accessdate=16 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 27 June, Bowie performed a concert at [[Broadcasting House|BBC Radio Theatre]] in London, which was released in the compilation album ''[[Bowie at the Beeb]]'', which also featured BBC recording sessions from 1968 to 1972.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=Dave |last=Thompson |year=2006 |title=Hallo Spaceboy: The Rebirth of David Bowie |page=357 |publisher=ECW Press}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bowie and Iman's daughter was born on 15 August.&lt;ref&gt;Buckley (2005): p. 485&lt;/ref&gt; His interest in [[Buddhism]] led him to support the [[Tibetan Buddhism|Tibetan]] cause by performing at the February 2001 and February 2003 concerts to support [[Tibet House US]] at [[Carnegie Hall]] in New York.&lt;ref name=&quot;lifetimeinterest&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Bowie, Moby, Matthews Spark Tibet House Benefit |url=https://www.billboard.com/articles/news/80520/bowie-moby-matthews-spark-tibet-house-benefit |accessdate=24 September 2019 |publisher=Billboard |date=27 February 2001}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Andrew Dansby |title=Bowie Back in Tibet House |url=https://www.rollingstone.com/music/music-news/bowie-back-in-tibet-house-179077/ |accessdate=24 September 2019 |publisher=Rolling Stone |date=9 January 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In October 2001, Bowie opened [[the Concert for New York City]], a charity event to benefit the victims of the [[September 11 attacks]], with a minimalist performance of [[Simon &amp; Garfunkel]]'s &quot;[[America (Simon &amp; Garfunkel song)|America]]&quot;, followed by a full band performance of &quot;Heroes&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Buckley (2005): p. 491&lt;/ref&gt; 2002 saw the release of ''Heathen'', and, during the second half of the year, the [[Heathen Tour]]. Taking place in Europe and North America, the tour opened at London's annual ''[[Meltdown (festival)|Meltdown]]'' festival, for which Bowie was that year appointed artistic director. Among the acts he selected for the festival were [[Philip Glass]], [[Television (band)|Television]], and [[the Dandy Warhols]]. As well as songs from the new album, the tour featured material from Bowie's ''[[Low (David Bowie album)|Low]]'' era.&lt;ref&gt;Buckley (2005): pp. 493–95&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Reality (David Bowie album)|Reality]]'' (2003) followed, and its accompanying world tour, the [[A Reality Tour]], with an estimated attendance of 722,000, grossed more than any other in 2004. Onstage in [[Oslo]], Norway, on 18 June, Bowie was hit in the eye with a lollipop thrown by a fan; a week later he suffered chest pain while performing at the [[Hurricane Festival]] in [[Scheeßel]], Germany. Originally thought to be a pinched nerve in his shoulder, the pain was later diagnosed as an acutely blocked [[Coronary circulation|coronary artery]], requiring an emergency [[angioplasty]] in Hamburg. The remaining 14 dates of the tour were cancelled.&lt;ref&gt;Buckley (2005): pp. 504–05&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Duncan Jones and David Bowie at the premiere of Moon.jpg|thumb|Bowie with his son [[Duncan Jones]] at the premiere of Jones's directorial debut ''[[Moon (film)|Moon]]'', 2009]]
In the years following his recuperation from the heart attack, Bowie reduced his musical output, making only one-off appearances on stage and in the studio. He sang in a duet of his 1971 song &quot;[[Changes (David Bowie song)|Changes]]&quot; with [[Butterfly Boucher]] for the 2004 animated film ''[[Shrek 2]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Buckley (2004): p. 16&lt;/ref&gt;

During a relatively quiet 2005, he recorded the vocals for the song &quot;(She Can) Do That&quot;, co-written with [[BT (musician)|Brian Transeau]], for the film ''[[Stealth (film)|Stealth]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Perone (2007): p. 142&lt;/ref&gt; He returned to the stage on 8 September 2005, appearing with [[Arcade Fire]] for the US nationally televised event Fashion Rocks, and performed with the Canadian band for the second time a week later during the [[CMJ]] Music Marathon.&lt;ref&gt;Thompson (2006): pp. 291–92&lt;/ref&gt; He contributed backing vocals on [[TV on the Radio]]'s song &quot;Province&quot; for their album ''[[Return to Cookie Mountain]]'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine|date=June 2006|title=Space Is the Place: Innovative Brooklyn rockers blast off to the future|magazine=[[Spin (magazine)|Spin]]|page=1}}&lt;/ref&gt; made a commercial with [[Snoop Dogg]] for [[XM Satellite Radio]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Marketing|last1=Lamb|first=Charles W.|last2=Hair|first2=Joseph F.|last3=McDaniel|first3=Carl|publisher=South-Western College Pub|year=2007|isbn=978-0-324-36208-4|page=472}}&lt;/ref&gt; and joined with Lou Reed on Danish alt-rockers [[Kashmir (band)|Kashmir's]] 2005 album ''[[No Balance Palace]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Stone|first=Andrew|title=Denmark|year=2008|publisher=Lonely Planet|isbn=978-1-74104-669-4|page=[https://archive.org/details/lonelyplanetdenm00andr/page/46 46]|url=https://archive.org/details/lonelyplanetdenm00andr/page/46}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Bowie was awarded the [[Grammy Lifetime Achievement Award]] on 8 February 2006.&lt;ref&gt;Thompson (2006): p. 293&lt;/ref&gt; In April, he announced, &quot;I'm taking a year off—no touring, no albums.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Yuan|first=Jada|url=http://nymag.com/news/intelligencer/16865|title=David Bowie Takes Time Off, Sneaks into Movies|work=New York|date=1 May 2006|accessdate=16 September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; He made a surprise guest appearance at [[David Gilmour]]'s 29 May concert at the [[Royal Albert Hall]] in London. The event was recorded, and a selection of songs on which he had contributed joint vocals were subsequently released.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Guitar Gods: The 25 Players Who Made Rock History|last=Gulla|first=Bob|year=2008|publisher=Greenwood|isbn=978-0-313-35806-7|page=95}}&lt;/ref&gt; He performed again in November, alongside [[Alicia Keys]], at the Black Ball, a benefit event for [[Keep a Child Alive]] at the [[Hammerstein Ballroom]] in New York.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|date=November 2009|title=The Elements of Style|first=Gail|last=Mitchell|journal=Billboard|page=22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Jones|first1=Dylan|title=David Bowie: A Life|date=2017|publisher=Preface Publishing|isbn=9781848094956|url=https://books.google.com/?id=pnXcDQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT438&amp;lpg=PT438&amp;dq=david+bowie+final+performance+hammerstein+ballroom#v=onepage&amp;q=david%20bowie%20final%20performance%20hammerstein%20ballroom|accessdate=22 December 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; The performance marked the last time Bowie performed his music on stage.&lt;ref name=RS1149&gt;{{cite magazine|last=Gilmore|first=Mikal|title=How Ziggy Stardust Fell to Earth|magazine=[[Rolling Stone]]|issue=1149|date=2 February 2012|pages=36–43, 68}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Bowie was chosen to curate the 2007 High Line Festival, selecting musicians and artists for the [[Manhattan]] event, including electronic pop duo [[AIR (French band)|AIR]], surrealist photographer [[Claude Cahun]], and English comedian [[Ricky Gervais]].&lt;ref&gt;Schinder &amp; Schwartz (2007): p. 500&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Ten Days on a High|url=http://nymag.com/nightlife/features/highline-festival/|work=[[New York (magazine)|New York magazine]]|date=16 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bowie performed on [[Scarlett Johansson]]'s 2008 album of [[Tom Waits]] covers, ''[[Anywhere I Lay My Head]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine|date=May 2008|title=The Inquisition: Scarlett Johansson|first=David|last=Marchese|magazine=Spin|page=40}}&lt;/ref&gt; In June of 2008 a [[Live Santa Monica '72|live album]] was released of a Ziggy Stardust-era concert from 1972.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Live Santa Monica '72 |url=https://www.allmusic.com/album/r1391051 |website=Allmusic |accessdate=17 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; On the 40th anniversary of the [[Apollo program|July 1969 moon landing]]—and Bowie's accompanying commercial breakthrough with &quot;Space Oddity&quot;—EMI released the individual tracks from the original eight-track studio recording of the song, in a 2009 contest inviting members of the public to create a remix.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nme.com/news/music/david-bowie-339-1317705|work=NME News|title=David Bowie to release &quot;Space Oddity&quot; multi-tracks to celebrate moon landing|date=6 July 2009|accessdate=2 September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[A Reality Tour (album)|A Reality Tour]]'', a double album of live material from the 2003 concert tour, was released in January 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/music/reviews/5gwx|title=David Bowie A Reality Tour Review|first=Mike|last=Diver|date=5 February 2010|accessdate=2 September 2010|publisher=BBC}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In late March 2011, ''[[Toy (David Bowie album)|Toy]]'', Bowie's previously unreleased album from 2001, was leaked onto the internet, containing material used for ''Heathen'' and most of its single B-sides, as well as unheard new versions of his early back catalogue.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Perpetua|first=Matthew|title=Unreleased David Bowie LP 'Toy' Leaks Online|newspaper=[[Rolling Stone]]|date=22 March 2011|url=https://www.rollingstone.com/music/news/unreleased-david-bowie-lp-toy-leaks-online-20110322|accessdate=25 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Michaels|first=Sean|title=David Bowie's unreleased album Toy leaks online|newspaper=[[The Guardian]]|location=UK|date=23 March 2011|url=https://www.theguardian.com/music/2011/mar/23/david-bowie-toy-album-leak|accessdate=25 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===2013–2016: Final years===
On 8 January 2013, his 66th birthday, his website announced a new album, to be titled ''[[The Next Day]]'' and scheduled for release 8 March for Australia, 12 March for the United States, and 11 March for the rest of the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=David Bowie To Release New Album and Posts New Music Video|url=http://nymn.com/david-bowie-video-and-new-album/|publisher=New York Music News|date=8 January 2013|accessdate=8 January 2013|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131230112954/http://nymn.com/david-bowie-video-and-new-album/|archive-date=30 December 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bowie's first studio album in a decade, ''The Next Day'' contains 14 songs plus 3 bonus tracks.&lt;ref name=&quot;birthday boy&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=New Website, Album, Single And Video for the Birthday Boy|url=http://www.davidbowie.com/news/new-website-album-single-and-video-birthday-boy-47841|date=8 January 2013|publisher=davidbowie.com|accessdate=8 January 2013|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130111171526/http://www.davidbowie.com/news/new-website-album-single-and-video-birthday-boy-47841|archivedate=11 January 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=spin&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.spin.com/2013/01/david-bowie-returns-hiatus-new-album-single-where-are-we-now/|title=David Bowie Returns From Decade-Long Hiatus With New Album, Single|work=Spin|accessdate=22 September 2014|date=8 January 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; His website acknowledged the length of his hiatus.&lt;ref name=&quot;nmenextday&quot;/&gt; Record producer [[Tony Visconti]] said 29 tracks were recorded for the album, some of which could appear on Bowie's next record, which he might start work on later in 2013. The announcement was accompanied by the immediate release of a single, &quot;[[Where Are We Now?]]&quot;, written and recorded by Bowie in New York and produced by longtime collaborator Visconti.&lt;ref name=&quot;nmenextday&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=David Bowie announces first album in 10 years and releases new single |url=https://www.nme.com/news/music/david-bowie-300-1265209|work=NME|accessdate=8 January 2013|date=8 January 2013|first=Nick|last=Levine}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A music video for &quot;Where Are We Now?&quot; was released onto [[Vimeo]] the same day, directed by New York artist [[Tony Oursler]].&lt;ref name=&quot;nmenextday&quot;/&gt; The single topped the UK [[iTunes]] Chart within hours of its release,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=David Bowie's comeback single rockets to Number One on iTunes|url=https://www.nme.com/news/music/david-bowie-299-1265015|work=NME|accessdate=8 January 2013|date=8 January 2013|first=Nick|last=Levine}}&lt;/ref&gt; and debuted in the [[UK Singles Chart]] at No. 6,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=David Bowie secures first Top 10 single in two decades|url=https://www.officialcharts.com/chart-news/david-bowie-secures-first-top-10-single-in-two-decades__2716/|website=[[Official Chart Company]]|accessdate=13 January 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; his first single to enter the Top 10 for two decades (since &quot;[[Jump They Say]]&quot; in 1993). &lt;!--Please do not edit text to reflect news article's claim that it was Bowie's first single since &quot;Absolute Beginners&quot;, second source proves this to be incorrect.--&gt; A second video, &quot;The Stars (Are Out Tonight)&quot;, was released 25 February. Directed by [[Floria Sigismondi]], it stars Bowie and [[Tilda Swinton]] as a married couple.&lt;ref name=charthistory&gt;{{cite web|title=David Bowie chart history |url=http://www.officialcharts.com/artist/_/david%20bowie/ |publisher=Official Chart Company |accessdate=23 January 2013 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131103181930/http://www.officialcharts.com/artist/_/david%20bowie/ |archivedate=3 November 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 1 March, the album was made available to stream for free through [[iTunes]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Phillips|first=Amy|title=Listen to the New David Bowie Album|url=https://pitchfork.com/news/49744-listen-to-the-new-david-bowie-album/|accessdate=1 March 2013|newspaper=PitchforkMedia|date=28 February 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''The Next Day'' debuted at No. 1 on the [[UK Albums Chart]], was his first album to achieve that position since ''Black Tie White Noise'' (1993), and was the fastest-selling album of 2013 at the time.&lt;ref name=nextdayukchart&gt;{{cite web|title=David Bowie scores first Number 1 album in 20 years|url=https://www.officialcharts.com/chart-news/david-bowie-scores-first-number-1-album-in-20-years__2877/|website=[[Official Chart Company]]|accessdate=17 March 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The music video for the song &quot;[[The Next Day (song)|The Next Day]]&quot; created some controversy, initially being removed from YouTube for [[Terms of service|terms-of-service]] violation, then restored with a warning recommending viewing only by those 18 or over.&lt;ref name=&quot;CBS_video_controversy&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Savage|first=Lesley|url=https://www.cbsnews.com/news/david-bowies-new-religious-themed-video-causing-controversy/|title=David Bowie's new religious-themed video causing controversy|website=[[CBS News]]|date=9 May 2013|accessdate=10 May 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to ''[[The Times]]'', Bowie ruled out ever giving an interview again.&lt;ref name=&quot;Times&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=Tony Visconti spills the beans on cocaine, AA and sushi with David Bowie |work=The Times |location=London, UK |date=12 January 2013 |last=Teeman |first=Tim |url=https://www.thetimes.co.uk/article/tony-visconti-spills-the-beans-on-cocaine-aa-and-sushi-with-david-bowie-cc93v5cjfqh |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20190626214402/https://www.thetimes.co.uk/article/tony-visconti-spills-the-beans-on-cocaine-aa-and-sushi-with-david-bowie-cc93v5cjfqh |archivedate=26 June 2019 |url-status=live |url-access=subscription |access-date=13 January 2020 }}&lt;/ref&gt; An exhibition of Bowie artefacts, called ''[[David Bowie Is]]'', was organised by the [[Victoria and Albert Museum]] in London, and shown there in 2013.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=David Bowie Is|url=https://www.vam.ac.uk/collections/david-bowie|website=Victoria and Albert Museum|accessdate=8 September 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The London exhibit was visited by 311,956 people, making it one of the most successful exhibitions ever staged at the museum.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |title=Alexander McQueen: Savage Beauty Is Most Popular Show in V&amp;A's History |url=https://www.theguardian.com/fashion/2015/aug/03/alexander-mcqueen-show-savage-beauty-most-popular-victoria-and-albert-history |newspaper=[[The Guardian]] |location=London |agency=[[Press Association]] |date=3 August 2015 |access-date=27 January 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Later that year the exhibition began a world tour which started in [[Art Gallery of Ontario|Toronto]] and included stops in [[Museum of Contemporary Art, Chicago|Chicago]], [[Paris]], [[Melbourne]], [[Groningen]] and [[Brooklyn]], New York where the exhibit ended on 15 July at the [[Brooklyn Museum]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Touring Exhibition: David Bowie is|url=http://www.vam.ac.uk/content/articles/t/touring-exhibition-david-bowie-is|publisher=Victoria and Albert Museum|accessdate=24 September 2014|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140925041217/http://www.vam.ac.uk/content/articles/t/touring-exhibition-david-bowie-is/|archive-date=25 September 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bowie was featured in a cameo vocal in the [[Arcade Fire]] song [[Reflektor (song)|&quot;Reflektor&quot;]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/music/2013/oct/24/arcade-fire-reflektor-voodoo-dance-david-bowie|title=Arcade Fire: Voodoo rhythms, dance music and David Bowie|first=Laura|last=Barton|work=The Guardian|location=London|accessdate=22 September 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; A poll carried out by BBC History Magazine, in October 2013, named Bowie as the best-dressed Briton in history.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/music/2013/oct/16/david-bowie-best-dressed-briton-bbc-history-magazine|title=David Bowie voted the best-dressed person in British history|first=Sean|last=Michaels|work=The Guardian|location=London|accessdate=22 September 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

At the [[2014 Brit Awards]] on 19 February, Bowie became the oldest recipient of a [[Brit Awards|Brit Award]] in the ceremony's history when he won the award for [[Brit Award for British Male Solo Artist|British Male Solo Artist]], which was collected on his behalf by [[Kate Moss]]. His speech read: &quot;I'm completely delighted to have a Brit for being the best male – but I am, aren't I Kate? Yes. I think it's a great way to end the day. Thank you very, very much and Scotland stay with us.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/entertainment-arts-26230608|title=Brit Awards 2014: David Bowie wins best British male award|newspaper=BBC News|accessdate=22 September 2014|date=20 February 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bowie's reference to the forthcoming September 2014 [[2014 Scottish independence referendum|Scottish independence referendum]] garnered a significant reaction throughout the UK on [[social media]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-scotland-scotland-politics-26267726|title=Oldest Brit winner David Bowie enters independence debate|work=BBC News|date=20 February 2014|accessdate=21 February 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.independent.co.uk/arts-entertainment/music/news/david-bowie-on-scottish-independence-reactions-on-twitter-9140683.html|title=David Bowie on Scottish independence: Reactions on Twitter|work=The Independent|location=London, UK|date=20 February 2014|accessdate=21 February 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 18 July, Bowie indicated that future music would be forthcoming, though he was vague about details.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.independent.co.uk/arts-entertainment/music/news/david-bowie-has-promised-new-music-soon-9610274.html|title=David Bowie new album: Singer promises new music 'soon'|work=The Independent|location=London, UK|accessdate=22 September 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

New information was released in September 2014 regarding his next compilation album, ''[[Nothing Has Changed]]'', which was released in November. The album featured rare tracks and old material from his catalogue in addition to a new song titled &quot;[[Sue (Or in a Season of Crime)]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.independent.ie/entertainment/music/music-news/david-bowie-to-release-retrospective-album-nothing-has-changed-with-single-sue-or-in-a-season-of-crime-in-november-30573204.html|title=David Bowie to release retrospective album 'Nothing has Changed' with single 'Sue (Or in a Season of Crime)' in November|work=Irish Independent|location=Dublin|accessdate=22 September 2014|first=Anthony|last=Barnes|date=9 September 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; In May 2015, &quot;Let's Dance&quot; was announced to be reissued as a yellow vinyl single on 16 July 2015 in conjunction with the ''David Bowie Is'' exhibition at the [[Australian Centre for the Moving Image]] in [[Melbourne]], Australia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=David Bowie's 'Let's Dance' to get limited vinyl reissue|url=http://www.neverenoughnotes.co.uk/2015/05/david-bowies-lets-dance-to-get-limited-vinyl-reissue|website=Never Enough Notes|accessdate=19 May 2015|ref=David Bowie's 'Let's Dance' to get limited vinyl reissue|date=19 May 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160114134809/http://www.neverenoughnotes.co.uk/2015/05/david-bowies-lets-dance-to-get-limited-vinyl-reissue|archive-date=14 January 2016|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 2015, it was announced that Bowie was writing songs for a Broadway musical based on the ''[[SpongeBob SquarePants]]'' cartoon series.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.rollingstone.com/music/news/david-bowie-aerosmith-flaming-lips-pen-songs-for-spongebob-musical-20150831|title=David Bowie, Aerosmith, Flaming Lips Pen Songs for 'SpongeBob Musical'|work=Rolling Stone|date=31 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bowie wrote and recorded the opening title song to the television series ''[[The Last Panthers]]'', which aired in November 2015.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Kreps|first1=Daniel|title=David Bowie Records Theme Song for 'Last Panthers' Series|url=https://www.rollingstone.com/music/news/david-bowie-records-theme-song-for-last-panthers-series-20150922|website=[[Rolling Stone]]|accessdate=23 September 2015|date=22 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The theme that was used for ''The Last Panthers'' was also the title track for his January 2016 release ''[[Blackstar (album)|Blackstar]]'' which is said to take cues from his earlier krautrock influenced work.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Carley|first=Brennan|url=https://www.spin.com/2015/10/david-bowie-blackstar-new-album-january-2016-the-times/|title=David Bowie Will Reportedly Release New Album, 'Blackstar,' in January|work=Spin|date=24 October 2015|accessdate=11 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to ''The Times'': &quot;''Blackstar'' may be the oddest work yet from Bowie&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine|last=Young|first=Alex|url=https://consequenceofsound.net/2015/10/david-bowie-to-release-oddest-album-yet-blackstar-in-january/|title=David Bowie to release &quot;oddest&quot; album yet, Blackstar, in January|magazine=Consequence of Sound|date=24 October 2015|accessdate=11 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 7 December 2015, Bowie's musical ''[[Lazarus (musical)|Lazarus]]'' debuted in New York. His last public appearance was at opening night of the production.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Last Pictures of David Bowie: Icon Looked in Good Spirits at Final Public Appearance a Month Ago|url=https://people.com/celebrity/david-bowies-final-public-appearance-before-death/|work=People|date=23 February 2016|first=Char|last=Adams}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''Blackstar'' was released on 8 January 2016, Bowie's 69th birthday, and was met with critical acclaim.&lt;ref name=&quot;MCblackstar&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.metacritic.com/music/blackstar/david-bowie |title=Reviews for Blackstar by David Bowie |work=[[Metacritic]] |accessdate=27 December 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Following his death on 10 January, producer Tony Visconti revealed that Bowie had planned the album to be his [[swan song]], and a &quot;parting gift&quot; for his fans before his death.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/celebritynews/12092542/Bowies-last-album-was-parting-gift-for-fans-in-carefully-planned-finale.html|title=David Bowie's last release, Lazarus, was 'parting gift' for fans in carefully planned finale|date=11 January 2016|work=The Daily Telegraph|last1=Furness|first1=Hannah}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/music/musicblog/2016/jan/11/was-david-bowie-saying-goodbye-on-blackstar?|title=Was David Bowie saying goodbye on Blackstar?|first=Tim|last=Jonze|newspaper=The Guardian|date=11 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.nme.com/blogs/nme-blogs/how-david-bowie-told-us-he-was-dying-in-the-lazarus-video-12143|title=How David Bowie told us he was dying in the 'Lazarus' video|work=NME|date=11 January 2016|first=Leonie|last=Cooper}}&lt;/ref&gt; Several reporters and critics subsequently noted that most of the lyrics on the album seem to revolve around his impending death,&lt;ref name=CNNdeath&gt;{{cite news|last1=Griggs|first1=Brandon|title='Blackstar': Haunting final album hints at David Bowie's death|url=https://www.cnn.com/2016/01/11/entertainment/david-bowie-blackstar-lazarus-death-meaning-feat/|website=CNN|accessdate=12 January 2020|date=13 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Billboarddeath&gt;{{cite web|last1=Payne|first1=Chris|title=David Bowie's Final Album 'Blackstar' &amp; 'Lazarus' Video Were Goodbye Notes|url=https://www.billboard.com/articles/columns/rock/6836563/david-bowie-blackstar-goodbye-note-death-lazarus-2016|website=Billboard|accessdate=12 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; with [[CNN]] noting that the album &quot;reveals a man who appears to be grappling with his own mortality&quot;.&lt;ref name=CNNdeath/&gt; Visconti later said that Bowie had been planning a post-''Blackstar'' album, and had written and recorded demo versions of five songs in his final weeks, suggesting that Bowie believed he had a few months left.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.rollingstone.com/music/news/david-bowie-planned-post-blackstar-album-thought-he-had-few-more-months-20160113|title=David Bowie Planned Post-'Blackstar' Album, 'Thought He Had Few More Months'|work=[[Rolling Stone]]|last=Hiatt|first=Brian|date=13 January 2016|accessdate=14 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The day following his death, online viewing of Bowie's music skyrocketed, breaking the record for [[Vevo]]'s [[Vevo#Record holders|most viewed artist in a single day]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.techtimes.com/articles/124452/20160114/david-bowie-breaks-vevo-record-51-million-video-views-one.htm|quote=Bowie's catalog generated 51 million video views on Vevo on Monday, Jan. 11, the day after he died, making him the most viewed artist in a single day in the video-streaming platform's history, the company reported Thursday morning via a press release.|first=Mark|last=Lelinwalla|title=David Bowie Breaks Vevo Record with 51 Million Video Views in One Day|work=Tech Times|date=14 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 15 January, ''Blackstar'' debuted at number one on the UK Albums Chart; nineteen of his albums were in the UK Top 100 Albums Chart, and thirteen singles were in the UK Top 100 Singles Chart.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.officialcharts.com/chart-news/david-bowie-is-the-starman-of-this-weeks-official-chart-as-the-nation-pays-tribute-to-a-music-icon__13562/|title=David Bowie is the Starman of this week's Official Chart as the nation pays tribute to a music icon|date=15 January 2016|website=[[Official Charts Company]]|first=Rob|last=Copsey}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/music/2016/jan/15/david-bowie-dominates-uk-album-charts-blackstar-adele|title=David Bowie dominates UK album charts as latest album hits No 1 |newspaper=The Guardian|author=Harriet Gibsone|date=15 January 2016|access-date=15 January 2016|quote=Elsewhere, 19 Bowie albums and 13 singles have entered the top 100}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Blackstar'' also debuted at number one on album charts around the world, including Australia, France, Germany, Italy, New Zealand, and the US ''Billboard'' 200.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=David Bowie's final album Blackstar rockets to top of charts|url=https://www.abc.net.au/news/2016-01-16/bowie-last-album-rockets-to-top-of-british-charts/7092934|website=[[Australian Broadcasting Corporation|ABC]]|date=17 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|first=Keith|last=Caulfield|title=David Bowie's 'Blackstar' Album Debuts at No. 1 on Billboard 200 Chart|url=https://www.billboard.com/articles/columns/chart-beat/6844036/david-bowie-blackstar-album-debuts-no-1-on-billboard-200-charts|work=[[Billboard (magazine)|Billboard]]|date=17 January 2016|accessdate=17 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===2016-present: Posthumous releases===

{{as of|2016|January|11}}, more than 1.3&amp;nbsp;million people had visited the ''[[David Bowie Is]]'' exhibit, making it the most successful exhibition ever staged by the Victoria and Albert Museum in terms of worldwide attendance.&lt;ref name=&quot;brown11jan2016&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/music/2016/jan/11/david-bowie-is-exhibition-300-items-13m-visitors-but-no-bakelite-saxophone|title=David Bowie exhibition opens as fans can't wait to say 'I love you' till Tuesday |work=The Guardian|author=Mark Brown|date=11 January 2016|access-date=27 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |title=V&amp;A's David Bowie Is Exhibition Receives Its Millionth Visitor |url=http://www.vam.ac.uk/__data/assets/pdf_file/0005/254534/V-and-A-David-Bowie-1mil-visitor_RELEASE.pdf |location= |publisher=Victoria and Albert Museum |date=May 2015 |access-date=27 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The museum stated that the exhibition would continue to tour, with confirmed travel to Japan in 2017.&lt;ref name=&quot;brown11jan2016&quot; /&gt; In September 2016 a [[Who Can I Be Now? (1974–1976)|box set]] was released covering Bowie's mid-70s soul period, including ''The Gouster'', a previously unreleased 1974 album.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Slate |first1=Jeff |title=The Making of David Bowie's Lost Soul Album |url=https://www.esquire.com/entertainment/music/a48869/the-making-of-david-bowies-lost-soul-album/ |website=Esquire |accessdate=9 January 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

An EP, ''[[No Plan (EP)|No Plan]]'', was released on 8 January 2017, which would have been Bowie's 70th birthday.&lt;ref name=&quot;noplan&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last1=Young|first1=Alex|title=Final David Bowie songs collected on new EP released for his 70th birthday|url=https://consequenceofsound.net/2017/01/final-david-bowie-songs-collected-on-new-ep-released-for-his-70th-birthday/|website=Consequence of Sound|accessdate=8 January 2017|date=8 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Apart from &quot;Lazarus&quot;, the EP includes three songs that Bowie had recorded during the ''Blackstar'' sessions, but were left off the album and subsequently appeared on the [[Lazarus (soundtrack)|soundtrack album]] for the ''Lazarus'' musical in October 2016.&lt;ref name=&quot;noplan2&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last1=Kreps|first1=Daniel|title=Watch David Bowie's Mysterious 'No Plan' Video|url=https://www.rollingstone.com/music/news/watch-david-bowies-mysterious-no-plan-video-w459603|website=Rolling Stone|accessdate=8 January 2017|date=8 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; A music video for the title track was also released.&lt;ref name=&quot;noplan2&quot;/&gt; 2017 and 2018 also saw the release of a series of posthumous live albums, covering the [[Cracked Actor (Live Los Angeles '74)|Diamond Dogs tour of 1974]], the [[Live Nassau Coliseum '76|Isolar tour of 1976]] and the [[Welcome to the Blackout (Live London '78)|Isolar II tour of 1978]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Randle |first1=Chris |title=Cracked Actor (Live Los Angeles '74) |url=https://pitchfork.com/reviews/albums/david-bowie-cracked-actor-live-los-angeles-74/ |website=Pitchfork |accessdate=17 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Live Nassau Coliseum '76 |url=https://www.allmusic.com/album/release/live-nassau-coliseum-76-mr0004667560 |website=Allmusic |accessdate=17 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Welcome to the Blackout (Live London '78) |url=https://www.allmusic.com/album/welcome-to-the-blackout-live-london-78-mw0003173016 |website=Allmusic |accessdate=17 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the two years following his death, Bowie had sold 5 million records in the United Kingdom alone.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.independent.co.uk/arts-entertainment/music/news/david-bowie-forever-record-sales-blackstar-hunky-dory-life-on-mars-best-songs-albums-tributes-a8151181.html|title=Two years since his death, Bowie is still selling millions of records|date=10 January 2018|work=The Independent|access-date=27 January 2018|language=en-GB}}&lt;/ref&gt;

At the [[59th Annual Grammy Awards]] on 12 February 2017, Bowie won all five nominated awards: [[Grammy Award for Best Rock Performance|Best Rock Performance]]; [[Grammy Award for Best Alternative Music Album|Best Alternative Music Album]]; [[Grammy Award for Best Engineered Album, Non-Classical|Best Engineered Album, Non-Classical]]; [[Grammy Award for Best Recording Package|Best Recording Package]]; and [[Grammy Award for Best Rock Song|Best Rock Song]]. The wins marked Bowie's first ever in musical categories.&lt;ref name=59thGA&gt;{{cite news|last=Kelley|first=Seth|url=https://variety.com/2017/music/news/grammys-david-bowie-wins-early-1201986057/|title=David Bowie’s ‘Blackstar’ Wins All Five Nominated Categories at 2017 Grammys|work=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|date=12 February 2017|accessdate=12 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 8 January 2020, on what would have been Bowie's 73rd birthday, a previously unreleased version of the song &quot;The Man Who Sold the World&quot; was released, and two new releases were announced: a streaming-only EP entitled ''Is It Any Wonder?'' and a 9 track album entitled ''CHANGESNOWBOWIE'', set to be released on [[Record Store Day]] 2020.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Prisco |first1=Jacopo |title=Rare and unreleased music by David Bowie is coming this year |url=https://www.cnn.com/style/article/david-bowie-posthumous-albums-2020/index.html |website=CNN |accessdate=9 January 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Acting career==
{{Main|David Bowie filmography}}

While always primarily a musician, Bowie took acting roles throughout his career, appearing in over 30 movies, television shows and theatrical productions. Bowie's acting career was &quot;productively selective,&quot; largely eschewing starring roles for cameos and supporting parts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Kenny |first1=Glenn |title=David Bowie in Movies: The Definition of Screen Presence |url=https://www.vanityfair.com/hollywood/2016/01/david-bowie-acting |website=Vanity Fair |accessdate=10 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Whitington |first1=Paul |title=Sound and vision: the best and the worst of David Bowie's acting career |url=https://www.independent.ie/entertainment/music/sound-and-vision-the-best-and-the-worst-of-david-bowies-acting-career-37700388.html |website=Independent.IE |accessdate=10 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many critics have observed that, had Bowie not chosen to pursue music, he could have found great success as an actor.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=David Bowie - The man who could have been a movie star |url=https://www.charlotteobserver.com/entertainment/ent-columns-blogs/state-of-the-art/article54172320.html |website=Charlotte Observer |accessdate=10 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=10 Brilliant Stories From David Bowie's Film Career |url=https://uk.movies.yahoo.com/david-bowies-10-best-behind-the-scenes-movie-101127838.html?guccounter=1&amp;guce_referrer=aHR0cHM6Ly93d3cuZ29vZ2xlLmNvbS91cmw_c2E9dCZyY3Q9aiZxPSZlc3JjPXMmc291cmNlPXdlYiZjZD00NyZjYWQ9cmphJnVhY3Q9OCZ2ZWQ9MmFoVUtFd2p5NElUSjhOX2xBaFV3aE9BS0hWVGdDYzQ0S0JBV01BWjZCQWdIRUFFJnVybD1odHRwcyUzQSUyRiUyRnVrLm1vdmllcy55YWhvby5jb20lMkZkYXZpZC1ib3dpZXMtMTAtYmVzdC1iZWhpbmQtdGhlLXNjZW5lcy1tb3ZpZS0xMDExMjc4MzguaHRtbCZ1c2c9QU92VmF3MnFqSk9NRms4djluN0tVcUM5Zm5ZUw&amp;guce_referrer_sig=AQAAAAMHvS5QVa3QYKT3zbPPwFDu5kY-sizaQcjOh7i49G-WhK1jncaHQBpQfM5fbPMCptq3egZJuNVGVeu2mgeZuqi82Hi368Ua4MUFaR0cbAdty0jsY36dCVGVBifz-rCE_OH3_1uCnqOgiFtdLDDhcbTiM5s2gqR5c-A5rI6enLXk |website=Yahoo! Movies |accessdate=10 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other critics have noted that, while his screen presence was singular, his best contributions to film were the use of his songs in movies like ''[[Lost Highway (film)|Lost Highway]]'', ''[[A Knight's Tale]]'', ''[[The Life Aquatic with Steve Zissou]]'' and ''[[Inglourious Basterds]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Lane |first1=Anthony |title=David Bowie in the Movies |url=https://www.newyorker.com/culture/cultural-comment/david-bowie-in-the-movies |website=The New Yorker |accessdate=10 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=VanDerWerff |first1=Emily Todd |title=9 times David Bowie songs transformed movies and television |url=https://www.vox.com/2016/1/12/10751794/david-bowie-songs-movies-television |website=Vox |accessdate=10 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====1960s and 1970s====
The beginnings of Bowie's acting career predate his commercial breakthrough as a musician. Studying [[avant-garde]] theatre and [[mime artist|mime]] under [[Lindsay Kemp]], he was given the role of Cloud in Kemp's 1967 theatrical production ''Pierrot in Turquoise'' (later made into the 1970 television film ''The Looking Glass Murders'').&lt;ref&gt;Sandford (1997): p. 43&lt;/ref&gt; Bowie filmed a walk-on role for the [[BBC]] drama series ''[[Theater 625]]'' that aired in May 1968.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Trynka |first1=Paul |title=David Bowie: Starman |date=2011 |publisher=Little, Brown |isbn=9780316134248 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=51THbRlGpUQC&amp;pg=PT92}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the black-and-white [[short film|short]] ''[[The Image (short film)|The Image]]'' (1969), he played a ghostly boy who emerges from a troubled artist's painting to haunt him.&lt;ref name=&quot;Buckley 2005: p. 49&quot;&gt;Buckley (2005): p. 49&lt;/ref&gt; The same year, the film of [[Leslie Thomas]]'s 1966 comic novel ''[[The Virgin Soldiers]]'' saw Bowie make a brief appearance as an extra.&lt;ref name=&quot;Buckley 2005: p. 49&quot; /&gt;

In 1976 Bowie earned acclaim for his first major film role, portraying Thomas Jerome Newton, an alien from a dying planet, in ''[[The Man Who Fell to Earth]]'', directed by [[Nicolas Roeg]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=The Man Who Fell Into Movie Acting |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2013/08/04/movies/the-man-who-fell-into-movie-acting.html |website=The New York Times |accessdate=5 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; He later admitted that his severe cocaine use during the film's production left him in such a fragile state of mind that he barely understood the movie.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=McManus |first1=Brian |title=Remembering David Bowie's Movie Career |url=https://www.vice.com/en_us/article/wd7yqb/david-bowie-actor |website=Vice |accessdate=10 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Just a Gigolo (1978 film)|Just a Gigolo]]'' (1979), an Anglo-German co-production directed by [[David Hemmings]], saw Bowie in the lead role as Prussian officer Paul von Przygodski, who, returning from World War I, is discovered by a Baroness ([[Marlene Dietrich]]) and put into her gigolo stable.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Hendrikse|first1=Wim|title=David Bowie – The Man Who Changed the World|date=2013|publisher=New Generation Publishing}}&lt;/ref&gt; The movie was a critical and commercial bomb, and Bowie later expressed embarrassment at his role in it.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Beautiful images from David Bowie's least favorite film role: 1978's Just a Gigolo |url=https://dangerousminds.net/comments/beautiful_images_from_david_bowies_least_favorite_film_role_1978s_just_a_gi |website=Dangerous Minds |accessdate=10 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====1980s====

[[File:EMP 2015-06 Labrynth.jpg|thumb|upright|Bowie's costume from ''[[Labyrinth (1986 film)|Labyrinth]]'' at the [[Museum of Pop Culture]], Seattle]]
Bowie played [[Joseph Merrick]] in the Broadway theatre production ''[[The Elephant Man (play)|The Elephant Man]]'', which he undertook wearing no stage make-up, and which earned high praise for his expressive performance. He played the part 157 times between 1980 and 1981.&lt;ref name=&quot;elephantman&quot;/&gt; ''[[Christiane F. – We Children from Bahnhof Zoo]]'', a 1981 biographical film focusing on a young girl's drug addiction in [[West Berlin]], featured Bowie in a cameo appearance as himself at a concert in Germany. Its soundtrack album, ''[[Christiane F. (album)|Christiane F.]]'' (1981), featured much material from his Berlin Trilogy albums.&lt;ref&gt;Sandford (1997); p. 208&lt;/ref&gt; In 1982 he starred in the titular role in a [[BBC]] adaptation of the [[Bertolt Brecht]] play ''[[Baal (play)|Baal]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=David Bowie in Baal, Alan Clarke's 1982 Bertolt Brecht adaptation – video |url=https://www.theguardian.com/film/video/2016/jun/09/david-bowie-baal-alan-clarke-bertolt-brecht-bbc-video |website=The Guardian}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bowie portrayed a [[vampire]] in [[Tony Scott]]'s erotic horror film ''[[The Hunger (1983 film)|The Hunger]]'' (1983), with [[Catherine Deneuve]] and [[Susan Sarandon]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=VAMPIRES AND CHIC |url=https://www.nytimes.com/1983/04/29/movies/vampires-and-chic.html |website=The New York Times |accessdate=20 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Nagisa Oshima]]'s film the same year, ''[[Merry Christmas, Mr. Lawrence]]'', based on [[Laurens van der Post]]'s novel ''[[The Seed and the Sower]]'', Bowie played Major Jack Celliers, a prisoner of war in a Japanese internment camp.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=DAVID BOWIE IN 'MERRY CHRISTMAS' |url=https://www.nytimes.com/1983/08/26/movies/david-bowie-in-merry-christmas.html |website=The New York Times |accessdate=5 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bowie had a cameo in ''[[Yellowbeard]]'', a 1983 pirate comedy created by [[Monty Python]] members and directed by [[Mel Damski]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=David Bowie, Actor: A Complete Look Back at His Film and TV Roles |url=https://ultimateclassicrock.com/david-bowie-acting-career/ |website=Ultimate Classic Rock |accessdate=5 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

To promote the single &quot;[[Blue Jean]]&quot; Bowie filmed the 21 minute short film ''[[Jazzin' for Blue Jean]]'' (1984) with director [[Julien Temple]], and played the dual roles of romantic protagonist Vic and arrogant rock star Screaming Lord Byron.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Elder |first1=Sean |title=David Bowie: The Man Who Showed the World |url=https://www.newsweek.com/2014/11/21/david-bowie-man-who-showed-world-283172.html |website=Newsweek |accessdate=16 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; The short won Bowie his only non-posthumous Grammy award.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=David Bowie Swept The 2017 Grammys |url=https://www.vulture.com/2017/02/david-bowie-wins-first-ever-grammy-for-his-music.html |website=Vulture |accessdate=25 December 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bowie had a supporting role as [[Contract killing|hitman]] Colin in the 1985 [[John Landis]] film ''[[Into the Night (film)|Into the Night]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=FILM: JOHN LANDIS'S INTO THE NIGHT |url=https://www.nytimes.com/1985/02/22/movies/film-john-landis-s-into-the-night.html |website=The New York Times}}&lt;/ref&gt; He declined to play the villain [[Max Zorin]] in the [[James Bond]] film ''[[A View to a Kill]]'' (1985).&lt;ref&gt;Pegg (2004), p. 561&lt;/ref&gt; Bowie reteamed with Temple for ''[[Absolute Beginners (film)|Absolute Beginners]]'' (1986), a [[rock musical]] film [[Film adaptation|adapted]] from [[Colin MacInnes]]'s [[Absolute Beginners (novel)|book of the same name]] about life in late 1950s London, in a supporting role as ad man Vendice Partners.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=How we made Absolute Beginners |url=https://www.theguardian.com/culture/2015/sep/21/how-we-made-absolute-beginners-julien-temple-patsy-kensit |website=The Guardian |accessdate=5 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; The same year, [[Jim Henson]]'s dark musical fantasy ''[[Labyrinth (1986 film)|Labyrinth]]'' cast him as [[Jareth]], the villainous [[Goblin]] King.&lt;ref&gt;Sandford (1997): pp. 252–53&lt;/ref&gt; Despite initial poor box office the movie grew in popularity, becoming a [[cult film]] and arguably Bowie's most iconic movie role.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Behind-the-scenes secrets from Bowie’s cult classic ‘Labyrinth’ |url=https://nypost.com/2018/04/26/behind-the-scenes-secrets-from-bowies-cult-classic-labyrinth/ |website=New York Post |accessdate=21 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Labyrinth is now 30 years old. Here’s how this gloriously weird movie became a cult classic. |url=https://www.vox.com/2016/1/12/10755050/labyrinth-david-bowie |website=Vox |accessdate=21 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Two years later, he played [[Pontius Pilate]] in [[Martin Scorsese]]'s critically acclaimed biblical epic ''[[The Last Temptation of Christ (film)|The Last Temptation of Christ]]'' (1988).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Martin Scorsese pays tribute to the late David Bowie |url=https://www.independent.co.uk/arts-entertainment/films/news/martin-scorsese-pays-tribute-to-the-late-david-bowie-a6809986.html |website=Independent UK |accessdate=5 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====1990s====
In 1991 Bowie reteamed with director John Landis for an episode of the [[HBO]] sitcom ''[[Dream On (TV Series)|Dream On]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Director John Landis on David Bowie: &quot;A Gentleman&quot; |url=https://www.hollywoodreporter.com/news/director-john-landis-david-bowie-855480 |website=Hollywood Reporter |accessdate=1 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; and played a disgruntled restaurant employee opposite [[Rosanna Arquette]] in ''[[The Linguini Incident]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=The Linguini Incident: a Bowie re-release nobody needs to see |url=https://www.theguardian.com/film/2016/feb/06/the-linguine-incident-david-bowie |website=The Guardian |accessdate=5 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bowie portrayed the mysterious [[Federal Bureau of Investigation|FBI]] agent [[Phillip Jeffries]] in [[David Lynch]]'s ''[[Twin Peaks: Fire Walk with Me]]'' (1992). The [[prequel]] to the [[Twin Peaks|television series]] was poorly received at the time of its release, but has since been critically reevaluated.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Fire Walk With Me: how David Lynch's film went from laughing stock to the key to Twin Peaks |url=https://www.theguardian.com/film/filmblog/2017/sep/02/twin-peaks-fire-walk-with-me-david-lynch |website=The Guardian |accessdate=5 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; He took a small but pivotal role as his friend [[Andy Warhol]] in ''[[Basquiat (film)|Basquiat]]'', artist/director [[Julian Schnabel]]'s 1996 biopic of [[Jean-Michel Basquiat]], another artist he considered a friend and colleague.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Remembering David Bowie As Neo-Expressionist Painter, Avid Art Collector, Friend of Warhol, Basquiat |url=https://www.forbes.com/sites/natashagural/2019/01/10/remembering-david-bowie-as-neo-expressionist-painter-avid-art-collector-friend-of-warhol-basquiat/ |website=Forbes |accessdate=5 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bowie co-starred in [[Giovanni Veronesi]]'s [[Spaghetti Western]] ''Il Mio West'' (1998, released as ''[[Gunslinger's Revenge]]'' in the US in 2005) as the most feared gunfighter in the region.&lt;ref&gt;Thompson (2006): p. 195&lt;/ref&gt; He played the aging gangster Bernie in Andrew Goth's ''[[Everybody Loves Sunshine]]'' (1999, released in the U.S. as ''B.U.S.T.E.D.''),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=That time David Bowie and Goldie starred in a gangster film |url=https://www.dazeddigital.com/music/article/38053/1/that-time-david-bowie-and-goldie-starred-in-a-gangster-film |website=Dazed Digital |accessdate=12 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; and appeared as the host in the second season of the television horror anthology series ''[[The Hunger (TV series)|The Hunger]]''. Despite having several episodes which focus on vampires and Bowie's involvement, the show had no plot connection to the 1983 film of the same name.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Bowie sates 'Hunger' |url=https://variety.com/1998/tv/news/bowie-sates-hunger-1117488581/ |website=Variety |accessdate=20 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1999 Bowie voiced two characters in the [[Sega Dreamcast]] game ''[[Omikron: The Nomad Soul]]'', his only appearance in a [[video game]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=David Bowie dead: Singer and actor appeared in bizarre Dreamcast video game 'Omikron: The Nomad Soul' |url=https://www.independent.co.uk/life-style/gadgets-and-tech/gaming/david-bowie-dead-singer-and-actor-appeared-in-bizarre-dreamcast-video-game-omikron-the-nomad-soul-a6806071.html |website=Independent UK |accessdate=29 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====2000s and posthumous notes====
In ''[[Mr. Rice's Secret]]'' (2000), Bowie played the title role as the neighbour of a terminally ill 12-year-old.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=David Bowie With a Secret and a Power |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2000/12/22/movies/david-bowie-with-a-secret-and-a-power.html |website=The New York Times |accessdate=5 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bowie appeared as himself in the 2001 [[Ben Stiller]] comedy ''[[Zoolander]]'', judging a &quot;walk-off&quot; between rival male models,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Ben Stiller live-tweets Zoolander: I can’t believe David Bowie actually did this |url=https://www.standard.co.uk/showbiz/celebrity-news/ben-stiller-livetweets-zoolander-i-can-t-believe-david-bowie-actually-did-this-a3170296.html |website=Evening Standard |accessdate=21 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; and in [[Eric Idle]]'s 2002 [[mockumentary]] ''[[The Rutles 2: Can't Buy Me Lunch]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=The Rutles 2: Can't Buy Me Lunch |url=https://variety.com/2005/digital/features/the-rutles-2-can-t-buy-me-lunch-1200527441/ |website=Variety |accessdate=29 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bowie portrayed a fictionalized version of physicist and inventor [[Nikola Tesla]] in [[Christopher Nolan]]'s film ''[[The Prestige (film)|The Prestige]]'' (2006), which was about the bitter rivalry between two magicians in the late 19th century. Nolan later claimed that Bowie was his only preference to play Tesla, and that he personally appealed to Bowie to take the role after he initially passed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Why Christopher Nolan Begged David Bowie to Star in The Prestige |url=https://www.cinemablend.com/new/Why-Christopher-Nolan-Begged-David-Bowie-Star-Prestige-106927.html |access-date=4 October 2019|website=Cinema Blend}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the same year, he voice-acted in [[Luc Besson]]'s animated film ''[[Arthur and the Invisibles]]'' as the powerful villain Maltazard,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=The kingdom isn't magic in 'Arthur and the Invisibles' |url=http://archive.boston.com/ae/movies/articles/2007/01/12/the_kingdom_isnt_magic_in_arthur_and_the_invisibles/ |access-date=4 October 2019|website=Boston.com|first=Ty|last=Burr|department=Movie Review}}&lt;/ref&gt; and appeared as himself in an episode of the [[Ricky Gervais]] television series ''[[Extras (TV series)|Extras]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=David Bowie pokes fun at Ricky Gervais on 'Extras' |url=https://www.rollingstone.com/music/music-news/flashback-david-bowie-pokes-fun-at-ricky-gervais-on-extras-226777/ |access-date=4 October 2019|website=Rolling Stone}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2007, he lent his voice to the character Lord Royal Highness in the ''[[SpongeBob's Atlantis SquarePantis]]'' television film.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Grammy Winner David Bowie Lends His Voice to SpongeBob |url=https://www.tvguide.com/news/atlantis-squarepantis-bowie-40418/ |access-date=4 October 2019|website=TV Guide}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the 2008 film ''[[August (2008 film)|August]]'', directed by [[Austin Chick]], he played a supporting role as Ogilvie, a &quot;ruthless venture capitalist.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=August review: A Web of Cynicism |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2008/07/11/movies/11augu.html |website=The New York Times |accessdate=5 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bowie's final film appearance was a cameo as himself in the 2009 teen comedy ''[[Bandslam]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title='Bandslam': Vanessa Hudgens miscast as outcast, but cool high school movie still rocks |url=https://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/tv-movies/bandslam-vanessa-hudgens-miscast-outcast-cool-high-school-movie-rocks-article-1.395454 |website=New York Daily News |accessdate=14 October 2019 |date=13 August 2009 |first=Elizabeth |last=Weitzman}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a 2017 interview with ''[[Consequence of Sound]]'', director [[Denis Villeneuve]] revealed his intention to cast Bowie in ''[[Blade Runner 2049]]'' as the lead villain, Niander Wallace, but when news broke of Bowie's death in January of the same year, Villeneuve was forced to look for talent with similar &quot;rock star&quot; qualities. He eventually cast actor and lead singer of [[Thirty Seconds to Mars]], [[Jared Leto]]. Talking about the casting process, Villeneuve said: &quot;Our first thought [for the character] had been David Bowie, who had influenced ''[[Blade Runner]]'' in many ways. When we learned the sad news, we looked around for someone like that. He [Bowie] embodied the Blade Runner spirit.&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine|url=https://consequenceofsound.net/2017/11/denis-villeneuve-on-wanting-to-cast-david-bowie-he-embodied-the-blade-runner-spirit/|title=Denis Villeneuve on wanting to cast David Bowie: &quot;He embodied the Blade Runner spirit&quot;|date=16 November 2017|magazine=Consequence of Sound|accessdate=2 May 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; David Lynch also hoped to have Bowie reprise his ''Fire Walk With Me'' character for ''[[Twin Peaks (season 3)|Twin Peaks: The Return]]'' but Bowie's illness prevented this. His character was portrayed via archival footage. At Bowie's request, Lynch overdubbed Bowie's original dialogue with a different actor's voice, as Bowie was unhappy with his [[Cajun]] accent in the original movie.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=How David Lynch and Twin Peaks Honored One Final David Bowie Request |url=https://www.vanityfair.com/hollywood/2017/09/twin-peaks-david-bowie-david-lynch-voice-over-request |website=Vanity Fair |accessdate=5 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy and influence==
[[File:David Bowie holywood.jpg|thumb|right|Bowie's star on the [[Hollywood Walk of Fame]]]]
[[File:Berliner Gedenktafel Hauptstr 155 (Schön) David Bowie.jpg|thumb|right|[[:de:Berliner Gedenktafel|Berlin Memorial Plaque]], Hauptstraße 155, in [[Schöneberg]], Germany]]
Bowie's songs and stagecraft brought a new dimension to popular music in the early 1970s, strongly influencing both its immediate forms and its subsequent development. Bowie was a pioneer of glam rock, according to music historians Schinder and Schwartz, who credited [[Marc Bolan]] and Bowie with creating the genre.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schinder &amp; Schwartz 2007: p. 482&quot;&gt;Schinder &amp; Schwartz (2007): p. 482&lt;/ref&gt; At the same time, he inspired the innovators of the [[punk rock]] music movement.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Popular Music in America:The Beat Goes On|last = Campbell|first = Michael|publisher = Schirmer|year = 2011|isbn = 978-0840029768|location = United States|page = 345}}&lt;/ref&gt; When punk musicians were &quot;noisily reclaiming the three-minute pop song in a show of public defiance&quot;, biographer David Buckley wrote that &quot;Bowie almost completely abandoned traditional rock instrumentation.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Campbell (2008) p. 304&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Buckley (2004): p. 45&lt;/ref&gt; Bowie's record company promoted his unique status in popular music with the slogan, &quot;There's old wave, there's new wave, and there's David Bowie&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Thomson (1993): p. 217&lt;/ref&gt;

Musicologist James Perone credited Bowie with having &quot;brought sophistication to rock music&quot;, and critical reviews frequently acknowledged the intellectual depth of his work and influence.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schinder &amp; Schwartz 2007: p. 482&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Perone (2007): p. 183&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Mark|last=Paytress|title=Bolan: The Rise and Fall of a 20th Century Superstar|year=2003|publisher=Omnibus Press|isbn=978-0-7119-9293-1|page=218}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[The Human League]] founder [[Martyn Ware]] remarked that he had lived his life &quot;as though he were an art installation.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;20K Tweets a Minute&quot;&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.bbc.com/news/magazine-38418802 |title=2016 deaths: The great, the good and the lesser known |date=30 December 2016|newspaper=BBC News }}&lt;/ref&gt; The BBC's arts editor [[Will Gompertz]] likened Bowie to [[Pablo Picasso]], writing that he was &quot;an innovative, visionary, restless artist who synthesised complex avant garde concepts into beautifully coherent works that touched the hearts and minds of millions&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/entertainment-arts-35284134|title=David Bowie: The Picasso of pop|first=Will|last=Gompertz|work=BBC News|date=11 January 2016|accessdate=19 March 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[U2]] lead singer [[Bono]] commented, &quot;I like Bowie when he’s evenly pulled in the direction of being a pop star and Picasso, where he's right down the middle. That’s usually my favorite, when the songwriting is disciplined but the recording is not. I love when he's pulled equally in the directions of art and populism.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.rollingstone.com/culture/culture-news/bono-remembers-david-bowie-he-is-my-idea-of-a-rock-star-225955/|title=Bono Remembers David Bowie: 'He Is My Idea of a Rock Star'|work=Rolling Stone|date=27 January 2016|accessdate=18 March 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Broadcaster [[John Peel]] contrasted Bowie with his [[progressive rock]] contemporaries, arguing that Bowie was &quot;an interesting kind of fringe figure... on the outskirts of things&quot;. Peel said he &quot;liked the idea of him reinventing himself... the one distinguishing feature about early-70s progressive rock was that it didn't progress. Before Bowie came along, people didn't want too much change&quot;. Buckley called the era &quot;bloated, self-important, leather-clad, self-satisfied&quot;; then Bowie &quot;subverted the whole notion of what it was to be a rock star&quot;.&lt;!-- See ref &quot;buckley_legacy&quot; to follow. --&gt;

{{quote|After Bowie there has been no other pop icon of his stature, because the pop world that produces these rock gods doesn't exist any more.&amp;nbsp;... The fierce partisanship of the cult of Bowie was also unique—its influence lasted longer and has been more creative than perhaps almost any other force within pop fandom.}}&lt;!-- See ref &quot;buckley_legacy&quot; to follow. --&gt;

Buckley called Bowie &quot;both star and icon. The vast body of work he has produced&amp;nbsp;... has created perhaps the biggest cult in popular culture.&amp;nbsp;... His influence has been unique in popular culture—he has permeated and altered more lives than any comparable figure.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;buckley_legacy&quot;&gt;Buckley (2005): pp. 516–17, 524, 529&lt;/ref&gt;

Through continual reinvention, his influence broadened and extended.&lt;ref name=&quot;Filicky&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Filicky|first=Brad|title=Reviews; David Bowie: Heathen|journal=CMJ New Music Report|volume=71|issue=766|date=10 June 2002|page=13}}&lt;/ref&gt; Biographer Thomas Forget added, &quot;Because he has succeeded in so many different styles of music, it is almost impossible to find a popular artist today that has not been influenced by David Bowie.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Forget|first=Thomas|year=2002|title=David Bowie (Rock &amp; Roll Hall of Famers)|publisher=Rosen Publishing Group|isbn=978-0-8239-3523-9|page=7}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2000, Bowie was voted by other music stars as the &quot;most influential artist of all time&quot; in a poll by ''[[NME]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Bowie Voted Most Influential Artist by Today's Pop Stars|url=http://www.nyrock.com/worldbeat/11_2000/112900.asp|work=NY Rock|date=29 November 2000|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20161208010944/http://www.nyrock.com/worldbeat/11_2000/112900.asp|archivedate=8 December 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=NME poll places Bowie as most influential artist of all-time|url=https://www.nme.com/news/music/david-bowie-343-1306703|work=NME|date=27 November 2000}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Alexis Petridis]] of ''[[The Guardian]]'' wrote that Bowie was confirmed by 1980 to be &quot;the most important and influential artist since [[the Beatles]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url= https://www.theguardian.com/music/2016/jan/11/david-bowie-man-who-thrilled-the-world-appreciation | title= David Bowie: the man who thrilled the world | work=The Guardian | location=London | first=Alexis | last=Petridis | date=11 January 2016 | accessdate=7 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Neil McCormick]] of ''[[The Daily Telegraph]]'' stated that Bowie had &quot;one of the supreme careers in popular music, art and culture of the 20th century&quot; and &quot;he was too inventive, too mercurial, too strange for all but his most devoted fans to keep up with&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url= https://www.telegraph.co.uk/music/artists/david-bowie-music-tribute/ | title= A one-man melting pot of ideas: why we will never solve the mystery of David Bowie's music | work=The Daily Telegraph | location=London | first=Neil | last=McCormick | date=11 January 2016 | accessdate=12 March 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The BBC's [[Mark Easton]] argued that Bowie provided fuel for &quot;the creative powerhouse that Britain has become&quot; by challenging future generations &quot;to aim high, to be ambitious and provocative, to take risks&quot;. Easton concluded that Bowie had &quot;changed the way the world sees Britain. And the way Britain sees itself&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;easton&quot;/&gt; Annie Zaleski of ''[[Alternative Press (music magazine)|Alternative Press]]'' wrote, &quot;Every band or solo artist who's decided to rip up their playbook and start again owes a debt to Bowie&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Zaleski|first=Annie|url=https://www.altpress.com/features/how_david_bowie_influenced_our_scene/|title=How David Bowie influenced our scene|work=[[Alternative Press (music magazine)|Alternative Press]]|date=12 January 2016|accessdate=14 August 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2016, he was dubbed &quot;The Greatest Rock Star Ever&quot; by ''[[Rolling Stone]]'' magazine.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.rollingstone.com/music/news/thanks-starman-why-david-bowie-was-the-greatest-rock-star-ever-20160111|title=Why David Bowie Was the Greatest Rock Star Ever|work=Rolling Stone|access-date=13 February 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Numerous figures from the music industry whose careers Bowie had influenced paid tribute to him following his death; [[panegyric]]s on Twitter (tweets about him peaked at 20,000 a minute an hour after the announcement of his death)&lt;ref name=&quot;20K Tweets a Minute&quot;/&gt; also came from outside the entertainment industry and [[Popular culture|pop culture]], such as those from the [[Holy See|Vatican]], namely Cardinal [[Gianfranco Ravasi]], who quoted &quot;Space Oddity&quot;, and the [[Federal Foreign Office]], which thanked Bowie for his part in the [[fall of the Berlin Wall]] and referenced &quot;Heroes&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=David Bowie death triggers tributes from Iggy Pop, Madonna—even the Vatican and the German government|url=https://www.marketwatch.com/story/death-of-david-bowie-sparks-howls-of-anguish-across-social-media-2016-01-11|website=MarketWatch|date=11 January 2016|first=Barbara|last=Kollmeyer}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://catholicherald.co.uk/news/2016/01/11/vatican-culture-official-pays-tribute-to-david-bowie/ |title=Vatican culture official pays tribute to David Bowie |date=11 January 2016 |website=Catholic Herald |access-date=14 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 7 January 2017 the BBC broadcast the 90-minute documentary ''David Bowie: The Last Five Years'', taking a detailed look at Bowie's last albums, ''The Next Day'' and ''Blackstar'', and his play ''Lazarus''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b088ktm6 |title=David Bowie: The Last Five Years |publisher=BBC |date=7 January 2017 |accessdate=8 January 2017 }}&lt;/ref&gt; On 8 January 2017, which would have been Bowie's 70th birthday, a charity concert in his birthplace of Brixton was hosted by the actor [[Gary Oldman]], a close friend.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Celebrating David Bowie's 70th birthday in Brixton, gig review: Touching tributes from those who knew him|url=https://www.independent.co.uk/arts-entertainment/music/reviews/david-bowie-70th-birthday-brixton-academy-review-year-anniversary-a7517586.html|work=The Independent|date=10 January 2017|accessdate=11 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; A David Bowie walking tour through Brixton was also launched, and other events marking his birthday weekend included concerts in New York, Los Angeles, Sydney, and Tokyo.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=David Bowie fans gather for birthday concert|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/entertainment-arts-38553380|publisher=BBC|date=10 January 2017|accessdate=11 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 6 February 2018 the [[Falcon Heavy Test Flight|maiden flight]] of the [[SpaceX]] [[Falcon Heavy]] rocket carried [[Elon Musk]]'s personal [[Elon Musk's Tesla Roadster|Tesla Roadster]] and a mannequin affectionately named [[Starman (song)|Starman]] into space. &quot;[[Space Oddity]]&quot; and &quot;[[Life on Mars?]]&quot; were looping on the car's sound system during the launch.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title=SpaceX Successfully Launches the Falcon Heavy—And Elon Musk's Roadster|url=https://www.wired.com/story/spacex-successfully-launches-the-falcon-heavyand-elon-musks-roadster/|journal=Wired|accessdate=7 February 2018|date=6 February 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== ''Stardust'' biopic ===
It was announced on 31 January 2019 that musician and actor [[Johnny Flynn (musician)|Johnny Flynn]] would be playing Bowie in an upcoming [[biopic]] titled ''Stardust'' which will be set around Bowie's first trip to the United States in 1971. Christopher Bell is writing the script and [[Gabriel Range]] will direct. Actress [[Jena Malone]] has signed on to play Bowie's wife Angie while actor [[Marc Maron]] will play Bowie's record company publicist.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title=Johnny Flynn to Play David Bowie in 'Stardust,' Marc Maron Also Attached|url=https://www.msn.com/en-us/movies/news/johnny-flynn-to-play-david-bowie-in-stardust-marc-maron-also-attached/ar-BBT0Tue?OCID=ansmsnnews11|journal=Variety|accessdate=1 February 2019|date=31 January 2019|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190202042218/https://www.msn.com/en-us/movies/news/johnny-flynn-to-play-david-bowie-in-stardust-marc-maron-also-attached/ar-BBT0Tue?OCID=ansmsnnews11|archive-date=2 February 2019|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 1 February 2019, Bowie's son Duncan Jones spoke out against the film saying that he knew nothing about the movie and was informed about it by a fan on [[Twitter]]. Jones also said that the film would not have permission to use any of Bowie's music. &quot;Pretty certain nobody has been granted music rights for ANY biopic... I would know. I'm not saying this movie is not happening. I honestly wouldn't know. I'm saying that as it stands, this movie won't have any of dads music in it, &amp; I can't imagine that changing.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title=David Bowie's son Duncan Jones slams plans for planned biopic about his dad|url=https://www.yahoo.com/entertainment/david-bowies-son-duncan-jones-slams-plans-planned-biopic-dad-104411494.html?bcmt=1|journal=Yahoo|accessdate=1 February 2019|date=1 February 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Musicianship==
[[File:David Bowie's Vox Mark VI guitar, HRC Warsaw.jpg|thumb|right|Bowie's [[Vox (musical equipment)|Vox]] [[Vox Mark III|Mark VI guitar]] in the [[Hard Rock Cafe]], [[Warsaw]], Poland]]
From the time of his earliest recordings in the 1960s, Bowie employed a wide variety of musical styles. His early compositions and performances were strongly influenced by rock and rollers like [[Little Richard]] and [[Elvis Presley]], and also the wider world of show business. He particularly strove to emulate the British musical theatre singer-songwriter and actor [[Anthony Newley]], whose vocal style he frequently adopted, and made prominent use of for his 1967 debut release, ''[[David Bowie (1967 album)|David Bowie]]'' (to the disgust of Newley himself, who destroyed the copy he received from Bowie's publisher).&lt;ref name=&quot;albumdebut&quot;&gt;Sandford (1997): pp. 41–42&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Perone (2007): p. 4&lt;/ref&gt; Bowie's [[music hall]] fascination continued to surface sporadically alongside such diverse styles as hard rock and heavy metal, soul, psychedelic folk, and pop.&lt;ref&gt;Perone (2007): pp. 22, 36–37&lt;/ref&gt;

Musicologist James Perone observes Bowie's use of octave switches for different repetitions of the same melody, exemplified in his commercial breakthrough single, &quot;[[Space Oddity]]&quot;, and later in the song &quot;[[&quot;Heroes&quot; (song)|Heroes]]&quot;, to dramatic effect; Perone notes that &quot;in the lowest part of his vocal register&amp;nbsp;... his voice has an almost crooner-like richness.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Perone (2007) p. 12&lt;/ref&gt;

Voice instructor Jo Thompson describes Bowie's vocal vibrato technique as &quot;particularly deliberate and distinctive&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Find Your Voice: A Self-Help Manual for Singers|first=Jo|last=Thompson|publisher=Artemis Editions|year=2004|isbn=978-0-634-07435-6|page=76}}&lt;/ref&gt; Schinder and Schwartz call him &quot;a vocalist of extraordinary technical ability, able to pitch his singing to particular effect.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Schinder &amp; Schwartz (2007): p. 483&lt;/ref&gt; Here, too, as in his stagecraft and songwriting, the singer's role playing is evident: historiographer Michael Campbell says that Bowie's lyrics &quot;arrest our ear, without question. But Bowie continually shifts from person to person as he delivers them&amp;nbsp;... His voice changes dramatically from section to section.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Campbell (2008): p. 254&lt;/ref&gt; In a 2014 analysis of 77 &quot;top&quot; singers' vocal ranges, Bowie was 8th, just behind [[Christina Aguilera]] and just ahead of [[Paul McCartney]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.huffingtonpost.com.au/2014/05/20/top-artists-vocal-range_n_5357698.html|title=Comparing The Top Artists, Past And Present, By Vocal Range|date=20 May 2014|accessdate=22 May 2014|first=Ryan|last=Kristobak|journal=The Huffington Post|location=Australia}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to the guitar, Bowie also played a variety of keyboards, including piano, Mellotron, Chamberlin, and synthesizers; harmonica; alto and baritone saxophones; [[stylophone]]; [[viola]]; cello; [[Koto (instrument)|koto]] (in the ''Heroes'' track &quot;Moss Garden&quot;); [[Mbira|thumb piano]]; drums (on the ''Heathen'' track &quot;Cactus&quot;), and various percussion instruments.&lt;ref&gt;Thompson (2006): p. 346&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Bowie|first=Jerry|last=Hopkins|publisher=MacMillan|year=1985|isbn=978-0-02-553730-9|page=[https://archive.org/details/bowie00hopk/page/239 239]|url=https://archive.org/details/bowie00hopk/page/239}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Perone (2007): pp. 17–44, 152–60&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Buckley (2004): p. 48&lt;/ref&gt;

==Other works==

===Painter and art collector===
{{Main|David Bowie's art collection}}
Bowie was also a painter and artist. One of his paintings sold at auction in late 1990 for $500,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine | magazine=[[Newsweek]] | title=Random notes | date=10 December 1990 | page=94}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the cover for his 1995 album ''[[Outside (David Bowie album)|Outside]]'' is a close-up of a self-portrait (from a series of five) he painted that same year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://bowieart.com/ |title=Bowieart.com / David Bowie / Printmaking |accessdate=13 January 2016 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160113161231/http://www.bowieart.com/ |archivedate=13 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; His first solo show was at The Gallery, [[Cork Street]] in 1995, entitled 'New Afro/Pagan and Work: 1975–1995'.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2016/01/15/arts/design/painting-offered-a-different-palette-for-david-bowies-talents.html|title=Painting Offered a Different Palette for David Bowie's Talents|author=Roslyn Sulcas|date=14 January 2016|accessdate=15 June 2017|newspaper=New York Times}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://rockarteditions.com/david-bowie-is-paris/|title=David Bowie is – la Philharmonie de Paris: fine exhibition, superlative venue|date=7 April 2015|accessdate=15 June 2015|work=Rock Art Editions|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150523175456/http://rockarteditions.com/david-bowie-is-paris/|archive-date=23 May 2015|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; He was invited to join the editorial board of the journal ''[[Modern Painters (magazine)|Modern Painters]]'' in 1998,&lt;ref name=&quot;TGS&quot;&gt;{{Cite news | url=https://www.theguardian.com/music/2016/jul/14/david-bowies-private-art-collection-unveiled-first-time-sothebys | title=David Bowie's private art collection to be unveiled for the first time | date=14 July 2016 | accessdate=14 July 2016 | first=Maev | last=Kennedy | journal=[[The Guardian]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; and participated in the [[Nat Tate: An American Artist 1928–1960|Nat Tate]] art hoax later that year.&lt;ref name=NW98&gt;{{Cite magazine | last=Plagens | first=Peter | title=The Late Great Tate | magazine=[[Newsweek]] | date=20 April 1998 | page=62}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1998 during an interview with [[Michael Kimmelman]] for ''[[The New York Times]]'' he said &quot;Art was, seriously, the only thing I'd ever wanted to own.&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Kimmelman |first=Michael |author-link=Michael Kimmelman |date=14 June 1998 |title=David Bowie on His Favorite Artists |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2016/01/15/arts/design/david-bowie-on-his-favorite-artists.html |newspaper=The New York Times |access-date=5 December 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; subsequently in 1999, in an interview for the BBC, he said &quot;The only thing I buy obsessively and addictively is art&quot;.&lt;ref name=ibt&gt;{{Cite journal | url=https://www.ibtimes.com/david-bowies-art-collection-beautiful-you-imagined-photos-2391686 | title=David Bowie's Art Collection Is As Beautiful As You Imagined | work=International Business Times| date=14 July 2016 | accessdate=15 July 2016 | first=Cristina | last=Silva}}&lt;/ref&gt; His art collection, which included works by [[Damien Hirst]], [[Derek Boshier]], [[Frank Auerbach]], [[Henry Moore]], and [[Jean-Michel Basquiat]] among others, was valued at over £10m in mid-2016.&lt;ref name=&quot;TGS&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.vice.com/en_us/article/evg7zn/david-bowie-and-the-clash-were-fans-of-derek-boshiers-art-and-you-should-be-too|title=David Bowie and The Clash Were Fans of Derek Boshier’s Art, and You Should Be Too|last=Bain|first=Katie|date=2017-05-25|website=Vice|language=en|access-date=2019-12-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After his death his family decided to sell most of the collection because they &quot;didn't have the space&quot; to store it.&lt;ref name=&quot;TGS&quot; /&gt; On 10 and 11 November three auctions were held at [[Sotheby's]] in London, first with 47 lots and second with 208 paintings, drawings, and sculptures, third with 100 design lots.&lt;ref name=sh&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.sothebys.com/en/slideshows/david-bowies-art-captivates-collectors|title=David Bowie's Art Captivates Collectors|website=Sotheby's|accessdate=30 December 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The items on sale represented about 65 percent of the collection.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.dw.com/en/after-two-days-david-bowie-art-auction-raises-41-million/a-36366994|title=After two days, David Bowie art auction raises $41&amp;nbsp;million |date=11 December 2016|website=Deutsche Welle|accessdate=30 December 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Exhibition of the works in the auction attracted 51,470 visitors, the auction itself was attended by 1,750 bidders, with over 1,000 more bidding online. The auctions has overall sale total £32.9&amp;nbsp;million (app. $41.5&amp;nbsp;million), while the highest-selling item, [[Jean-Michel Basquiat]]'s graffiti-inspired painting ''Air Power'', sold for £7.09&amp;nbsp;million.&lt;ref name=sh/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.yahoo.com/news/david-bowie-art-collection-worth-over-41mn-auction-142214379.html|title=David Bowie art collection worth over $41 mn at auction|accessdate=30 December 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Bowie Bonds===
{{Main|Celebrity bond}}
&quot;Bowie Bonds&quot;, an early example of [[celebrity bond]]s, were [[Asset-backed security|asset-backed securities]] of current and future revenues of the 25 albums (287 songs) that Bowie recorded before 1990.&lt;ref name=&quot;Investment&quot;&gt;{{Cite news | at = Sec. Business, p. 28 | newspaper=[[New York Daily News]] | publication-date = 26 October 1998 | title = Investment Banker Hopes to Issue More Rock 'n' Roll Bonds | first = Phyllis| last = Furman | accessdate = 18 January 2013 | url =http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-53133655.html| archive-url =https://web.archive.org/web/20160223125210/https://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-53133655.html| url-status=dead| archive-date =23 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Issued in 1997, the bonds were bought for US$55 million by the [[Prudential Financial|Prudential Insurance Company of America]].&lt;ref name=BowieBond3&gt;{{cite news|last=Venkataraghavan|first=Srinivasan|title=David Bowie Bonds &amp; IP Securitization|url=http://www.commodityonline.com/news/david-bowie-bonds--ip-securitization-1896-3-1897.html|work=CommodityOnline|accessdate=19 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=AP97&gt;{{cite news | agency = Associated Press| title = Bowie Rocks Wall Street| newspaper = Eastside Journal| publication-place = Bellevue, WA| date = 15 February 1997 | pages = B1, B4}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Royalty payment|Royalties]] from the 25 albums generated the cash flow that secured the bonds' interest payments.&lt;ref&gt;
[http://www.pullmanco.com/dbb.htm &quot;The Pullman Group – David Bowie Bonds&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120731112349/http://www.pullmanco.com/dbb.htm |date=31 July 2012 }}, fetched 15 March 2009.
&lt;/ref&gt; By forfeiting ten years worth of royalties, Bowie received a payment of US$55&amp;nbsp;million up front. Bowie used this income to buy songs owned by his former manager, [[Tony Defries]].&lt;ref name=upennalumni&gt;[http://www.upenn.edu/gazette/0497/0497pro2.html &quot;The Pennsylvania Gazette: David Pullman&quot;], fetched 16 March 2009,&lt;/ref&gt; The bonds liquidated in 2007 and the rights to the income from the songs reverted to Bowie.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://ftalphaville.ft.com/2016/01/11/2149761/a-short-history-of-the-bowie-bond/ |title=A Short History of the Bowie Bond |date=11 January 2016 |publisher=[[FT Alphaville]] |url-access=registration }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===BowieNet===
In September 1998, Bowie launched an [[Internet service provider]], BowieNet, developed in conjunction with Robert Goodale and Ron Roy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stuart&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2016/jan/11/david-bowie-bowienet-isp-internet|title=BowieNet: how David Bowie's ISP foresaw the future of the internet|last=Stuart|first=Keith|work=[[The Guardian]]|date=11 January 2016|accessdate=13 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hogan&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.billboard.com/articles/business/6842796/bowienet-david-bowie-pioneering-online-fan-club-isp|title=Behind David Bowie's Pioneering Internet Service BowieNet, Where the 'Sailor' Was Known to Roam|last=Hogan|first=Marc|work=[[Billboard (magazine)|Billboard]]|accessdate=13 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Subscribers to the [[Dial-up Internet access|dial-up]] service were offered exclusive content, as well as a BowieNet email address and Internet access.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stuart&quot; /&gt; The service was closed by 2006.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stuart&quot; /&gt;

==Personal life==

===Family===
[[File:Iman and David Bowie at the premiere of Moon.jpg|thumb|right|Bowie and wife [[Iman (model)|Iman]], 2009]]
Bowie married his first wife, [[Angela Bowie|Mary Angela Barnett]] on 19 March 1970 at Bromley Register Office in [[Bromley]], London. They had an [[open marriage]]. Angela described their union as a marriage of convenience. &quot;We got married so that I could work [to get a permit]. I didn't think it would last and David said, before we got married, 'I'm not really in love with you' and I thought that's probably a good thing,&quot; she said. Bowie said about Angela that &quot;living with her is like living with a blow torch.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.standard.co.uk/showbiz/why-i-gave-up-my-son-zowie-7279091.html|title=Angie Bowie: 'Why I gave up my son Zowie'|last=Saner|first=Emine|date=17 March 2006|website=Evening Standard|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Their son [[Duncan Jones|Duncan]], born on 30 May 1971, was at first known as Zowie.&lt;ref&gt;Doggett (2011): p. 114&lt;/ref&gt; Bowie and Angela divorced on 8 February 1980 in Switzerland.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Sandford|first1=Christopher|title=Bowie: Loving The Alien|date=5 August 2009|publisher=Da Capo Press|page=197}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bowie received custody of their son. After the gag order that was part of their divorce agreement ended, Angela wrote, ''Backstage Passes: Life on the Wild Side with David Bowie'', a memoir of their turbulent marriage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=David Bowie's first wife Angie on her fiery marriage to 'one in a million' music genius |url=https://www.mirror.co.uk/3am/celebrity-news/david-bowies-first-wife-angie-7155221 |website=Mirror UK |accessdate=5 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 24 April 1992, Bowie married [[Somali people|Somali]]-American model [[Iman (model)|Iman]] in a private ceremony in [[Lausanne]]. The wedding was later solemnised on 6 June in [[Florence]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Pegg&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Pegg|first=Nicholas|title=The Complete David Bowie|year=2006|publisher=Reynolds &amp; Hearn|isbn=978-1-905287-15-4|page=238}}&lt;/ref&gt; They had one daughter, Alexandria &quot;Lexi&quot; Zahra Jones, born in August 2000.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fltnib&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.eonline.com/news/40304/first-look-the-news-in-brief-august-15-2000|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120930185211/http://www.eonline.com/news/40304/first-look-the-news-in-brief-august-15-2000|archivedate=30 September 2012|title=FIRST LOOK: The News in Brief, 15 August 2000|date=15 August 2000|work=E!|accessdate=22 September 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Fmdiman&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fashionmodeldirectory.com/news/Model+News/still-ties-shoes-for-iman-reveals-how-david-bowie-makes-her-feel-special.htm|title=Iman|publisher=The FMD – FashionModelDirectory.com|accessdate=22 September 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; The couple resided primarily in New York City and London, as well as owning an apartment in Sydney's [[Elizabeth Bay, New South Wales|Elizabeth Bay]]&lt;ref name=Dumas&gt;{{cite news|last1=Dumas|first1=Daisy|title=Bowie Down Under: star hooked on Sydney|url=http://www.smh.com.au/entertainment/bowie-down-under-star-hooked-on-sydney-20160115-gm6f3v.html|accessdate=16 January 2016|work=The Sydney Morning Herald|date=16 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dailytelegraph.com.au/newslocal/city-east/who-knew-pop-superstar-david-bowie-was-once-a-secret-resident-of-sydneys-elizabeth-bay/story-fngr8h22-1226908685763|title=Who knew? Pop superstar David Bowie was once a secret resident of Sydney's Elizabeth Bay|work=[[The Daily Telegraph (Sydney)]]|date=7 May 2014|accessdate=11 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Britannia Bay House on the island of [[Mustique]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.architecturaldigest.com/gallery/david-bowie-iman-house-mustique-island-grenadines-slideshow/all|title=David Bowie's House on the Island of Mustique|date=31 August 1992|work=Architectural Digest|first=Christopher|last=Buckley}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sexuality===
Bowie declared himself &lt;!-- See comment to follow. --&gt;gay&lt;!-- EDITORS: Bowie makes different declarations in different interviews. Please treat each on its own as it comprises the narrative. --&gt; in an interview with Michael Watts for a 1972 issue of ''[[Melody Maker]]'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Watts|first=Michael|title=On the cusp of fame, Bowie tells Melody Maker he's gay – and changes pop for ever|url=https://www.theguardian.com/music/2006/jan/22/popandrock.davidbowie|accessdate=11 August 2012|newspaper=The Observer|date=22 January 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; coinciding with his campaign for stardom as Ziggy Stardust.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowie: An Illustrated Record p.7&quot;/&gt; According to Buckley, &quot;If Ziggy confused both his creator and his audience, a big part of that confusion centred on the topic of sexuality.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Buckley (2005): p. 140&lt;/ref&gt; In a September 1976 interview with ''[[Playboy]]'', Bowie said, &quot;It's true—I am a [[Bisexuality|bisexual]]. But I can't deny that I've used that fact very well. I suppose it's the best thing that ever happened to me.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;playboy&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.playboy.com/articles/david-bowie-interview/index.html?page=2|title=Interview: David Bowie|date=September 1976|work=Playboy|accessdate=14 September 2010|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100801045250/http://www.playboy.com/articles/david-bowie-interview/index.html?page=2|archivedate=1 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; His first wife, Angie, supports his claim of bisexuality and alleges that Bowie had a relationship with [[Mick Jagger]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Andersen|first=Christopher|date=July 2012|title=Mick: the Wild Life and Mad Genius of Jagger|publisher=Robson Press|isbn=978-1-84954-382-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/gossip/new-book-takes-mick-jagger-affair-david-bowie-article-1.1109887 |title=Mick Jagger's affair with David Bowie revealed in new book: They 'were really sexually obsessed with each other' |work=Daily News |location=New York |accessdate=11 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a 1983 interview with ''Rolling Stone'', Bowie said his public declaration of bisexuality was &quot;the biggest mistake I ever made&quot; and &quot;I was always a closet heterosexual.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=David Bowie Calls Himself 'A Closet Heterosexual'|work=Orlando Sentinel|date=30 May 1993|accessdate=13 May 2012|url=http://articles.orlandosentinel.com/1993-05-30/news/9305300344_1_david-bowie-mick-jagger-ziggy}}&lt;/ref&gt; On other occasions, he said his interest in homosexual and bisexual culture had been more a product of the times and the situation in which he found himself than of his own feelings.&lt;ref&gt;Buckley (2005): p. 106&lt;/ref&gt;{{efn|In 1993, Bowie recalled having read ''[[City of Night]]'' in the 1960s, and it connected with his loneliness. &quot;And that led me a merry dance in the early Seventies, when gay clubs really became my lifestyle and all my friends were gay&quot;.&lt;ref name=Arena1993&gt;{{cite journal|last=Parsons|first=Tony|url=https://exploringdavidbowie.wordpress.com/2013/02/14/bowie-what-is-he-like/|title=Bowie, what is he like?|periodical=[[Arena (magazine)|Arena]]|volume=Spring/Summer 1993|via=Exploring David Bowie|accessdate=31 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

''[[Blender (magazine)|Blender]]'' asked Bowie in 2002 whether he still believed his public declaration was his biggest mistake. After a long pause, he said, &quot;I don't think it was a mistake in Europe, but it was a lot tougher in America. I had no problem with people knowing I was bisexual. But I had no inclination to hold any banners nor be a representative of any group of people.&quot; Bowie said he wanted to be a songwriter and performer rather than a headline for his bisexuality, and in &quot;[[Puritans|puritanical]]&quot; America, &quot;I think it stood in the way of so much I wanted to do.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Collis |first=Clark |title=Dear Superstar: David Bowie |work=[[Blender (magazine)|Blender]] |date=August 2002 |accessdate=16 September 2010 |url=http://www.blender.com/guide/articles.aspx?id=366 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080510103103/http://www.blender.com/guide/articles.aspx?id=366 |archivedate=10 May 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Buckley wrote that Bowie &quot;mined sexual intrigue for its ability to shock&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;Buckley (2005): p. 141&lt;/ref&gt; and was probably &quot;never gay, nor even consistently actively bisexual&quot;, instead experimenting &quot;out of a sense of curiosity and a genuine allegiance with the 'transgressional'.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Buckley (2005): p. 147&lt;/ref&gt; Biographer Christopher Sandford said, according to Mary Finnigan—with whom Bowie had an affair in 1969—the singer and his first wife Angie &quot;created their bisexual fantasy&quot;.&lt;ref name=sandford48&gt;Sandford (1997): p. 48&lt;/ref&gt; Sandford wrote that Bowie &quot;made a positive fetish of repeating the quip that he and his wife had met while 'fucking the same bloke'&amp;nbsp;... Gay sex was always an anecdotal and laughing matter. That Bowie's actual tastes swung the other way is clear from even a partial tally of his affairs with women.&quot;&lt;ref name=sandford48/&gt; The BBC's [[Mark Easton]] wrote in 2016 that Britain was &quot;far more tolerant of difference&quot; and that gay rights, such as same-sex marriage, and gender equality would not have &quot;enjoyed the broad support they do today without Bowie's androgynous challenge all those years ago&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;easton&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url= https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-35290677|title= Bowie: the creative force who changed Britain|first=Mark|last=Easton|work=BBC News|date=12 January 2016|accessdate=14 March 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Spirituality and religion===
Over the years, Bowie made numerous references to religions and to his evolving spirituality. Beginning in 1967, he became interested in [[Buddhism]] and considered becoming a Buddhist monk.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Thurston Moore Reflects on David Bowie |url=https://pitchfork.com/news/62878-thurston-moore-reflects-on-david-bowie/ |accessdate=24 September 2019 |publisher=Pitchfork |date=12 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; After a few months' study at Tibet House in London, he was told by a [[Lama]], &quot;You don't want to be Buddhist.{{nbsp}}... You should follow music.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;newsday.com&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.newsday.com/entertainment/music/stardust-memories-without-tibet-house-david-bowie-never-may-have-gotten-ziggy-with-it-now-the-pop-star-returns-the-favor-by-performing-at-the-annual-benefit-concert-1.396658|title=Stardust Memories – Without Tibet House, David Bowie never may have gotten Ziggy with it. Now the pop star returns the favor&amp;nbsp;...|work=[[Newsday]]|accessdate=11 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; By 1975, Bowie admitted, &quot;I felt totally, absolutely alone. And I probably was alone because I pretty much had abandoned God.&quot;&lt;ref name=Arena1993/&gt; In his will, Bowie stipulated that he be [[Cremation|cremated]] and his ashes scattered in [[Bali]] &quot;in accordance with the Buddhist rituals&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;lifetimeinterest&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last1=Sawer |first1=Patrick |last2=McNulty |first2=Bernadette |title=David Bowie's lifetime interest in Buddhism to culminate in Bali scattering of his ashes |url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/culture/music/rockandpopmusic/12131199/Bowie-wanted-ashes-scattered-in-Bali.html |accessdate=24 September 2019 |publisher=The Telegraph |date=30 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After Bowie married Iman in a private ceremony in 1992, he said they knew that their &quot;real marriage, sanctified by God, had to happen in a church in Florence&quot;.&lt;ref name=PJ&gt;{{cite web |last=Johnson|first=Bridget|url=https://pjmedia.com/faith/2016/1/14/why-david-bowie-knelt-and-said-the-lords-prayer-at-wembley-stadium/|title=Why David Bowie Knelt and Said the Lord's Prayer at Wembley Stadium|work=[[PJ Media]]|date=13 January 2016|accessdate=18 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Earlier that year, he knelt on stage at [[The Freddie Mercury Tribute Concert]] and recited the [[Lord's Prayer]] before a television audience.&lt;ref name=&quot;LA Times Mercury&quot;/&gt;&lt;!-- Per source: &quot;with the potential to reach 1 billion viewers&quot;. --&gt;{{efn|Asked why he knelt and prayed, Bowie said he had a friend who was dying of AIDS. &quot;He was just dropping into a coma that day. And just before I went on stage something just told me to say the Lord's Prayer. The great irony is that he died two days after the show&quot;.&lt;ref name=Arena1993/&gt;}} In 1993, Bowie said he had an &quot;undying&quot; belief in the &quot;unquestionable&quot; existence of God.&lt;ref name=Arena1993/&gt; In a separate 1993 interview, while describing the genesis of the music for his album ''[[Black Tie White Noise]]'', he said &quot; … it was important for me to find something [musically] that also had no sort of representation of institutionalized and organized religion, of which I'm not a believer, I must make that clear.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Simon Bates]] radio interviews, [[BBC Radio 1]], 29–31 March 1993&lt;/ref&gt; Interviewed in 2005, Bowie said whether God exists &quot;is not a question that can be answered.{{nbsp}}... I'm not quite an atheist and it worries me. There's that little bit that holds on: 'Well, I'm ''almost'' an atheist. Give me a couple of months.{{nbsp}}... I've nearly got it right.{{'&quot;}}&lt;ref name=&quot;DeCurtis2005&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=DeCurtis|first=Anthony|title=In Other Words: Artists Talk About Life And Work|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=8Rr53q4VxuoC&amp;pg=PA262|accessdate=14 May 2012|date=5 May 2005|publisher=Hal Leonard Corporation|isbn=978-0-634-06655-9|pages=262–263}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&quot;Questioning [his] spiritual life [was] always&amp;nbsp;... germane&quot; to Bowie's songwriting.&lt;ref name=&quot;DeCurtis2005&quot;/&gt; The song &quot;[[Station to Station (song)|Station to Station]]&quot; is &quot;very much concerned with the [[Stations of the Cross]]&quot;; the song also specifically references [[Christian Kabbalah|Kabbalah]]. Bowie called the album &quot;extremely dark{{nbsp}}... the nearest album to a [[Magick (Thelema)|magick]] treatise that I've written&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Cavanagh|first=David|title=ChangesFiftyBowie|journal=[[Q (magazine)|Q]]|date=February 1997|pages=52–59}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!-- Cites previous 2 sentences. --&gt;{{efn|He later said he was influenced by his cocaine addiction and the &quot;psychological terror&quot; from making ''The Man Who Fell To Earth'', marking &quot;the first time I'd really seriously thought about Christ and God&amp;nbsp;... I very nearly got suckered into that narrow [view of] finding the Cross as the salvation of mankind&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Egan|first=Sean|title=Bowie on Bowie: Interviews and Encounters|publisher=Souvenir Press Ltd|year=2015|isbn=978-1569769775|page=116}}&lt;/ref&gt; }} ''[[Earthling (album)|Earthling]]'' showed &quot;the abiding need in me to vacillate between [[atheism]] or a kind of [[gnosticism]]{{nbsp}}... What I need is to find a balance, spiritually, with the way I live and my demise.&quot;&lt;ref name=Q97X&gt;{{Citation | last=Cavanagh | first=David | title=ChangesFiftyBowie | journal=[[Q (magazine)|Q magazine]] |date=February 1997 | pages=52–59}}&lt;/ref&gt; Released shortly before his death, &quot;[[Lazarus (David Bowie song)|Lazarus]]&quot;—from his final album, ''[[Blackstar (album)|Blackstar]]''—began with the words, &quot;Look up here, I'm in Heaven&quot; while the rest of the album deals with other matters of mysticism and mortality.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Clement|first=Olivia|url=http://www.playbill.com/news/article/look-up-here-im-in-heaven-poignant-lyrics-to-bowies-lazarus-signal-his-farewell-378793|title='Look Up Here, I'm in Heaven' – Poignant Lyrics to Bowie's 'Lazarus' Signal His Farewell|website=[[Playbill]]|date=11 January 2016|accessdate=18 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Politics===
In 1976, speaking as [[The Thin White Duke]], Bowie's persona at the time, and &quot;at least partially tongue-in-cheek&quot;, he made statements that expressed support for fascism and perceived admiration for [[Adolf Hitler]] in interviews with ''[[Playboy]]'', ''NME'', and a Swedish publication. Bowie was quoted as saying: &quot;Britain is ready for a fascist leader... I think Britain could benefit from a fascist leader. After all, fascism is really nationalism... I believe very strongly in fascism, people have always responded with greater efficiency under a regimental leadership.&quot; He was also quoted as saying: &quot;Adolf Hitler was one of the first rock stars&quot; and &quot;You've got to have an [[Far-right politics|extreme right]] front come up and sweep everything off its feet and tidy everything up.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.rollingstone.com/music/videos/flashback-the-clash-rock-against-racism-in-1978-20140513|title=Flashback: The Clash Rock Against Racism in 1978|work=Rolling Stone|accessdate=15 January 2015|date=13 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/music/2008/apr/20/popandrock.race|title=1978, the year rock found the power to unite|last=Manzoor|first=Sarfraz|newspaper=The Guardian|accessdate=15 January 2015|date=20 April 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bowie later retracted these comments in an interview with ''[[Melody Maker]]'' in October 1977, blaming them on mental instability caused by his drug problems at the time, saying: &quot;I was out of my mind, totally, completely crazed.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Gilmore|first=Mikal|url=https://www.rollingstone.com/music/news/cover-story-excerpt-david-bowie-20120118|title=Cover Story Excerpt: David Bowie|work=Rolling Stone|date=18 January 2012|accessdate=11 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 1980s and 1990s, Bowie's public statements shifted sharply towards [[anti-racism]] and [[anti-fascism]]. In an interview with [[MTV]] in 1983, Bowie criticised the channel for not providing enough coverage of black musicians,&lt;ref name=&quot;MTV video&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XZGiVzIr8Qg|title=David Bowie Criticizes MTV for Not Playing Videos by Black Artists|via=YouTube|year=1983|publisher=MTV News|access-date=13 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Jet Black artists&quot;&gt;{{cite magazine|title=Why It Took So Long For MTV To Play Black Videos|first=Margena A|last=Christian|magazine=Jet|date=9 October 2006|page=17}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the music videos for &quot;China Girl&quot; and &quot;Let's Dance&quot; were described by Bowie as a &quot;very simple, very direct&quot; statement against racism.&lt;ref name=RS83&gt;{{cite magazine | last=Loder | first=Kurt | author-link=Kurt Loder | title=Straight Time | magazine=[[Rolling Stone]] | issue=395 | date=12 May 1983 | pages=22–28, 81}}&lt;/ref&gt; The album ''Tin Machine'' took a more direct stance against fascism and Neo-Nazism, and was criticised for being too preachy.&lt;ref name=&quot;tinmachine1&quot;/&gt;

In 2016, filmmaker and activist [[Michael Moore]] said he had wanted to use &quot;[[Panic in Detroit]]&quot; for his 1998 documentary ''[[The Big One (film)|The Big One]]''; denied at first, he was given the rights after calling Bowie personally. &quot;I've read stuff since his death saying that he wasn't that political and he stayed away from politics. But that wasn't the conversation that I had with him.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Greene|first=Andy|url=https://www.rollingstone.com/music/news/michael-moore-bob-dylan-loved-fahrenheit-9-11-20160202|title=Michael Moore: Bob Dylan Loved ''Fahrenheit 9/11''|work=[[Rolling Stone]]|date=2 February 2016|accessdate=13 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Death==
{{Main|Death of David Bowie}}
[[File:David Bowie Death New York Apartment Memorial 2016 7.JPG|thumb|A woman places flowers outside Bowie's apartment in New York on [[Lafayette Street]] the day after his death was announced.]]
On 10 January 2016, two days after his 69th birthday and the release of the album ''[[Blackstar (album)|Blackstar]]'', Bowie died from [[liver cancer]] in his New York City apartment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.independent.co.uk/news/people/news/david-bowie-died-from-liver-cancer-he-kept-secret-from-all-but-handful-of-people-friend-says-a6806596.html|title=David Bowie died from liver cancer he kept secret from all but handful of people, friend says|last=Gallagher|first=Paul|date=11 January 2016|work=The Independent}}&lt;/ref&gt; He had been diagnosed 18 months earlier but had not made the news of his illness public.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Sandle|first1=Paul|last2=Faulconbridge|first2=Guy|title=David Bowie dies after 18-month battle with cancer|url=https://www.reuters.com/article/us-people-bowie-death-idUSKCN0UP0KD20160111|agency=[[Reuters]]|date=11 January 2016|accessdate=11 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Belgian theatre director [[Ivo van Hove]], who had worked with the singer on his [[Off-Broadway]] musical ''[[Lazarus (musical)|Lazarus]]'', explained that Bowie was unable to attend rehearsals due to the progression of the disease. He noted that Bowie had kept working during the illness.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Shock and condolences as the Netherlands reacts to David Bowie's death|url=http://www.dutchnews.nl/news/archives/2016/01/shock-and-condolences-as-netherlands-reacts-to-david-bowies-death/|accessdate=11 January 2016|publisher=DutchNews.nl|date=11 January 2016|language=en-GB}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Bowie's producer Tony Visconti wrote:

{{quote|He always did what he wanted to do. And he wanted to do it his way and he wanted to do it the best way. His death was no different from his life – a work of art. He made ''Blackstar'' for us, his parting gift. I knew for a year this was the way it would be. I wasn't, however, prepared for it. He was an extraordinary man, full of love and life. He will always be with us. For now, it is appropriate to cry.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/entertainment-arts-35279642|title=David Bowie: Friends and stars pay tribute|newspaper=BBC News|date=11 January 2016|accessdate=11 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=David Bowie's Death a 'Work of Art,' Says Tony Visconti|url=https://www.rollingstone.com/music/news/david-bowies-death-a-work-of-art-says-tony-visconti-20160111|website=[[Rolling Stone]]|accessdate=11 January 2016|date=11 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Following Bowie's death, fans gathered at impromptu street shrines.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Bowie 'died from liver cancer'|url=http://m.nzherald.co.nz/entertainment/news/article.cfm?c_id=1501119&amp;objectid=11572921|newspaper=The New Zealand Herald|date=14 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the mural of Bowie in his birthplace of Brixton, south London, which shows him in his ''[[Aladdin Sane]]'' character, fans laid flowers and sang his songs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=David Bowie fans create makeshift London shrines|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/entertainment-arts-35283801|work=BBC News|date=14 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other memorial sites included Berlin, Los Angeles, and outside his apartment in New York.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=David Bowie: Brit Awards tribute for 'visionary' musician|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/entertainment-arts-35289998|work=BBC News|date=14 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; After news of his death, sales of his albums and singles soared.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/music/2016/jan/13/global-streams-of-david-bowies-songs-on-spotify-soar-2822-after-his-death|title=Global streams of David Bowie's songs on Spotify soar 2,822% after his death|author=Elle Hunt|work=The Guardian}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bowie had insisted that he did not want a funeral, and according to his death certificate he was cremated in New Jersey on 12 January.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Barron|first=James|title=David Bowie's Will Splits Estate Said to Be Worth $100 Million|work=The New York Times|date=29 January 2016|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2016/01/30/nyregion/david-bowies-will-splits-estate-said-to-be-worth-100-million.html|accessdate=30 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; As he wished in his will, his ashes were scattered in a Buddhist ceremony in [[Bali]], Indonesia.&lt;ref name=ashes/&gt;

==Awards and recognition==
{{Main|List of awards and nominations received by David Bowie}}
[[File:David Bowie's Outfits - Rock and Roll Hall of Fame (2014-12-30 13.09.55 by Sam Howzit).jpg|thumb|right|Variety of Bowie's outfits on display at the [[Rock and Roll Hall of Fame]]]]
Bowie's 1969 commercial breakthrough, the song &quot;Space Oddity&quot;, won him an [[Ivor Novello Awards|Ivor Novello]] Special Award For Originality.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bucksmusicgroup.com/about/Ivor_Novello_Awards.html|title=Ivor Novello Awards|publisher=Bucks Music Group|accessdate=16 September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; For his performance in the 1976 science fiction film ''[[The Man Who Fell to Earth]]'', he won a [[Saturn Award for Best Actor]]. In the ensuing decades he was honoured with numerous awards for his music and its accompanying videos, receiving, among others, six [[Grammy Award]]s&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.grammy.com/nominees/search?artist=%22David+Bowie%22&amp;field_nominee_work_value=&amp;year=All&amp;genre=All|title=Grammy Award Winners|publisher=National Academy of Recording Arts and Sciences|accessdate=16 September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.grammy.com/Recording_Academy/Awards/Lifetime_Awards/ |title=Lifetime Achievement Award: Past Recipients |publisher=National Academy of Recording Arts and Sciences |accessdate=16 September 2010 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100826002047/http://www2.grammy.com/Recording_Academy/Awards/Lifetime_Awards |archivedate=26 August 2010 |url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=59thGA/&gt; and four [[Brit Awards]]—winning Best British Male Artist twice; the award for Outstanding Contribution to Music in 1996; and the Brits Icon award for his &quot;lasting impact on British culture&quot;, given posthumously in 2016.&lt;ref name=&quot;Icon 2016&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Brit Awards 2016: Adele dominates with four awards|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/entertainment-arts-35656227|agency=BBC|date=25 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Brit Awards 2014: David Bowie wins Best Male and wades into Scottish independence debate via Kate 'Ziggy' Moss|url=https://www.independent.co.uk/arts-entertainment/music/news/brit-awards-2014-david-bowie-wins-best-male-and-kate-ziggy-moss-collects-it-for-him-9139637.html|newspaper=The Independent|date=11 January 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Read Annie Lennox And Gary Oldman's David Bowie Tribute Speeches at the Brit Awards 2016|url=http://www.nme.com/blogs/nme-blogs/read-annie-lennox-and-gary-oldmans-david-bowie-tribute-speeches-at-the-brit-awards-2016|newspaper=NME|date=4 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1999, Bowie was made a Commander of the [[Ordre des Arts et des Lettres]] by the French government.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/europe/the-big-question-how-does-the-french-honours-system-work-and-why-has-kylie-been-decorated-822752.html|title=The Big Question: How does the French honours system work, and why has Kylie been decorated?|last=Lichfield|first=John|date=8 May 2009|work=The Independent|location=UK|accessdate=17 September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; He received an honorary doctorate from [[Berklee College of Music]] the same year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.berklee.edu/news/1999/grad99.html|title=ChChChChanges|publisher=[[Berklee College of Music]]|accessdate=17 September 2010|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120326155914/http://www.berklee.edu/news/1999/grad99.html|archive-date=26 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; He declined the royal honour of [[Order of the British Empire|Commander of the Order of the British Empire]] (CBE) in 2000, and turned down a [[knight]]hood in 2003.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Thompson|first=Jody|title=Sixty things about David Bowie|publisher=(No. 35): BBC News|date=8 January 2007|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/entertainment/6230201.stm|accessdate=17 September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bowie later stated &quot;I would never have any intention of accepting anything like that. I seriously don't know what it's for. It's not what I spent my life working for.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |date=18 April 2015 |url=http://www.music-news.com/news/UK/88765/Read |title=David Bowie turns down knighthood |publisher=music-news.com |accessdate=11 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Statue of David Bowie (geograph 5942789).jpg|thumb|left|upright|[[Statue of David Bowie|Statue of Bowie]] in different guises in [[Aylesbury]], Buckinghamshire, the town where he debuted Ziggy Stardust in 1972]]
Bowie has sold over 100 million records worldwide.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.belfasttelegraph.co.uk/life/rebel-rebel-we-profile-singing-legend-david-bowie-34329294.html|title=Rebel, rebel: We profile singing legend David Bowie|first=Andy|last=Gill|work=[[The Belfast Telegraph]]|date=January 2, 2016|accessdate=January 11, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{efn|Additional sources place this figure somewhere between 100 million and 150 million.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.belfasttelegraph.co.uk/life/rebel-rebel-we-profile-singing-legend-david-bowie-34329294.html|title=Rebel, rebel: We profile singing legend David Bowie|first=Andy|last=Gill|work=[[Belfast Telegraph]]|date=2 January 2016|accessdate=28 April 2017}}{{indent|3}}{{cite news|last=Wilkinson|first=Peter|url=http://www.cnn.com/2013/03/22/showbiz/uk-david-bowie-exhibition/|title=Bowie exhibition charts life of pop's ultimate Starman|publisher=CNN|date=22 March 2013|accessdate=29 April 2017}}{{indent|3}}{{cite news|last=Anderson|first=Kyle|url=http://ew.com/article/2016/01/21/david-bowie-ew-cover-story/|title=David Bowie EW cover story: How the singer, style icon, and eternal chameleon, ch-ch-ch-changed pop culture forever|work=[[Entertainment Weekly]]|date=21 January 2016|accessdate=29 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;}} In the United Kingdom, he was awarded 9 platinum, 11 gold, and 8 silver albums, and in the United States, 5 platinum and 9 gold.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.riaa.com/gold-platinum/?tab_active=default-award&amp;se=David+bowie#search_section|title=RIAA Searchable Database: search for David Bowie|publisher=[[Recording Industry Association of America]]|accessdate=11 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2003, five of Bowie's albums appeared on ''[[Rolling Stone]]''{{'}}s list of the [[Rolling Stone's 500 Greatest Albums of All Time|500 Greatest Albums of All Time]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| editor-last=Levy| editor-first=Joe| editor2-last=Van Zandt| editor2-first=Steven| editor2-link=Steven Van Zandt|title=Rolling Stone 500 Greatest Albums of All Time|origyear=2005|edition=3rd|year=2006|publisher=Turnaround|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2004, four of Bowie's songs appeared on the ''Rolling Stone'' list of the [[500 Greatest Songs of All Time]]. Additionally, four of his songs are included in [[The Rock and Roll Hall of Fame's 500 Songs that Shaped Rock and Roll]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://rockhall.com/exhibits/500-songs-that-shaped-rock-and/ |title=The Songs That Shaped Rock and Roll |accessdate=12 January 2008 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100317150057/http://rockhall.com/exhibits/500-songs-that-shaped-rock-and/ |archivedate=17 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to [[Acclaimed Music]], he is the fourth most celebrated artist in popular music history.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.acclaimedmusic.net/artist/David%20Bowie.htm |title=David Bowie ranked 4th most celebrated artist|work=Acclaimed Music|access-date=15 July 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the BBC's 2002 poll of the [[100 Greatest Britons]], he was ranked 29.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=100 great British heroes|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/entertainment/2208671.stm|publisher=BBC|accessdate=11 January 2015|date=21 August 2002}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2004, ''Rolling Stone'' magazine ranked him 39th on their list of the 100 Greatest Rock Artists of All Time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=100 Greatest Artists: 39 David Bowie|url=https://www.rollingstone.com/music/lists/100-greatest-artists-of-all-time-19691231/david-bowie-20110420|work=Rolling Stone|date=11 January 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bowie was inducted into the [[Rock and Roll Hall of Fame]] in 1996.&lt;ref name=&quot;rockhall&quot; /&gt; He was inducted into the [[Science Fiction and Fantasy Hall of Fame]] in 2013.&lt;ref name=sffhof2013&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.empmuseum.org/about-emp/emp-news/emp-newsflash/science-fiction-and-fantasy-hall-of-fame-emp-welcomes-five-major-players.aspx |title=Science Fiction and Fantasy Hall of Fame: EMP welcomes five major players |date=June 2013 |publisher=EMP Museum |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130818180527/http://empmuseum.org/about-emp/emp-news/emp-newsflash/science-fiction-and-fantasy-hall-of-fame-emp-welcomes-five-major-players.aspx |archivedate=18 August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.empmuseum.org/at-the-museum/museum-features/science-fiction-and-fantasy-hall-of-fame/members/david-bowie.aspx |title=David Bowie: Shape-shifting musician and movie star |publisher=EMP Museum |accessdate=11 September 2013 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130925235627/http://www.empmuseum.org/at-the-museum/museum-features/science-fiction-and-fantasy-hall-of-fame/members/david-bowie.aspx |archivedate=25 September 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2016, ''Rolling Stone'' proclaimed Bowie &quot;the greatest rock star ever&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Sheffield|first=Rob|url=https://www.rollingstone.com/music/news/thanks-starman-why-david-bowie-was-the-greatest-rock-star-ever-20160111|title=Thanks, Starman: Why David Bowie Was the Greatest Rock Star Ever|work=[[Rolling Stone]]|date=11 January 2016|accessdate=10 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2008, the spider ''[[Heteropoda davidbowie]]'' was named in Bowie's honour.&lt;ref name=&quot;ARKive&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.arkive.org/david-bowie-spider/heteropoda-davidbowie/|title=David Bowie spider videos, photos and facts – Heteropoda davidbowie|work=[[ARKive]]|accessdate=11 January 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160113215125/http://www.arkive.org/david-bowie-spider/heteropoda-davidbowie/|archive-date=13 January 2016|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 5 January 2015, a main-belt [[asteroid]] was named [[342843 Davidbowie]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://denver.cbslocal.com/2016/01/11/its-no-space-oddity-mile-wide-david-bowie-asteroid-to-forever-float-in-outer-space/|title=It's no 'Space Oddity': Mile-Wide David Bowie Asteroid to Forever Float in Outer Space|publisher=denver.cbslocal.com|accessdate=19 January 2016|date=11 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 13 January 2016, Belgian amateur astronomers at MIRA Public Observatory created a &quot;Bowie [[Asterism (astronomy)|asterism]]&quot; of seven stars which had been in the vicinity of Mars at the time of Bowie's death; the &quot;constellation&quot; forms the lightning bolt on Bowie's face from the cover of his ''[[Aladdin Sane]]'' album.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Kreps|first1=Daniel|title=Belgian Astronomers Pay Tribute to David Bowie With New Constellation|url=https://www.rollingstone.com/music/news/belgian-astronomers-pay-tribute-to-david-bowie-with-new-constellation-20160116|work=Rolling Stone|date=16 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 25 March 2018 a [[Statue of David Bowie|statue of Bowie]] was unveiled in [[Aylesbury]], Buckinghamshire, the town where he debuted Ziggy Stardust.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.billboard.com/articles/news/8262345/david-bowie-statue-unveiled-england-ziggy-stardust|title=David Bowie Statue Unveiled in English Town Where Ziggy Stardust Debuted|work=Billboard|access-date=27 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; The statue features a likeness of Bowie in 2002 accompanied with various characters and looks from over his career, with Ziggy at the front.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Musical David Bowie statue unveiled in Aylesbury|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-beds-bucks-herts-43513296|agency=BBC|date=26 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Biography|Arts|Film|Music|LGBT}}
* ''[[Nat Tate: An American Artist 1928–1960]]''
* [[Celebrity bond]]
* [[List of ambient music artists]]
* [[List of artists by number of UK Albums Chart number ones]]
* [[List of artists who reached number one in the United States]]
* [[List of artists who reached number one on the US Dance Club Songs chart]]
* [[List of best-selling music artists]]
* [[List of Billboard number-one Dance Club songs]]
* [[List of Billboard number-one singles]]

==Notes==
{{notelist}}

==References==
{{Reflist|25em}}

'''Sources'''
{{refbegin|30em}}
* {{cite book|last=Buckley|first=David|year=2000|origyear=First published 1999|title=Strange Fascination&amp;nbsp;– David Bowie: The Definitive Story|location=London|publisher=Virgin|isbn=978-0-7535-0457-4 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Buckley|first=David|year=2004|title=David Bowie: The Complete Guide To His Music|publisher=Omnibus Press|isbn=978-1-84449-423-1 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Buckley|first=David|year=2005|origyear=First published 1999|title=Strange Fascination&amp;nbsp;– David Bowie: The Definitive Story|location=London|publisher=Virgin|isbn=978-0-7535-1002-5 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Campbell|first=Michael|year=2008|title=Popular Music in America: And The Beat Goes On|publisher=Schirmer|isbn=978-0-495-50530-3 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Carr|first=Roy|authorlink=Roy Carr|author2=Murray, Charles Shaar|authorlink2=Charles Shaar Murray|year=1981|title=Bowie: An Illustrated Record|location=New York|publisher=Avon|isbn=978-0-380-77966-6 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Cole|first=Shaun|year=2000|title='Don we now our gay apparel': gay men's dress in the twentieth century|location=London|publisher=Berg|isbn=978-1-85973-415-5 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Ditmore|first=Melissa Hope|year=2006|title=Encyclopedia of Prostitution and Sex Work|volume=2|publisher=Greenwood Publishing Group|isbn=978-0-313-32970-8 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Doggett|first=Peter|year=2011|title=The Man Who Sold the World: David Bowie and the 1970s|publisher=The Bodley Head|isbn=978-1-84792-145-1 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last1=Gillman|first=Peter|author1-link=Peter Gillman|last2=Gillman|first2=Leni|year=1987|origyear=1986|title=Alias David Bowie|publisher=New English Library|isbn=978-0-450-41346-9 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Pegg|first=Nicholas|authorlink=Nicholas Pegg|year=2004|origyear=First published 2000|title=The Complete David Bowie|location=London|publisher=Reynolds &amp; Hearn|isbn=978-1-903111-73-4 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Perone|first=James E.|year=2007|title=The Words and Music of David Bowie|publisher=Praeger|isbn=978-0-275-99245-3 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Sandford|first=Christopher|title=Bowie: Loving the Alien|publisher=Time Warner|year=1997|origyear=First published 1996|isbn=978-0-306-80854-8|ref=harv|url=https://archive.org/details/bowielovingalien00sand}}
* {{cite book|last1=Schinder|first1=Scott|year=2007|last2=Schwartz|first2=Andy|title=Icons of Rock: An Encyclopedia of the Legends Who Changed Music Forever|publisher=Greenwood Press|location=Westport, Connecticut|isbn=978-0-313-33845-8 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Spitz |first=Marc |author-link1=Marc Spitz |title=Bowie: A Biography |publisher=Crown Publishers |year=2009 |ref=harv |isbn=978-0-307-71699-6|title-link=Bowie: A Biography }}
* {{cite book|last=Thomson|first=Elizabeth|title=The Bowie Companion|publisher=Macmillan|year=1993|isbn=978-0-283-06262-9|ref=harv|url=https://archive.org/details/bowiecompanion0000thom}}
* {{cite book|last=Thompson|first=Dave|title=Hallo Spaceboy: The Rebirth of David Bowie|publisher=Ecw Press|year=2006|isbn=978-1-55022-733-8 |ref=harv}}
{{refend}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin|30em}}
* {{cite book|first=Philippe|last=Auliac|title=Passenger – David Bowie Photobook|publisher=Sound &amp; Vision|location=Venezia|year=2004|isbn=|page=200}}
* {{cite book|last=Cann|first=David|title=Any Day Now: David Bowie the London Years 1947–1974|publisher=Kenneth Pitt in Books|year=2011|isbn=|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|author1=Duffy, Chris|author2=Cann, Kevin|title=Duffy/Bowie Five Sessions|date=2014|publisher=ACC Editions|isbn=978-1-85149-765-2|page=170|edition=1st UK|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Egan|first=Sean|title=Bowie on Bowie|publisher=Chicago Review Press|year=2015|ref=harv|isbn=978-1-56976-977-5|pages=}}
* {{cite book|last=Greco|first=Nicholas P.|title=David Bowie in Darkness: A Study of'' 1. Outside ''and the Late Career|publisher=McFarland &amp; Co.|year=2015|isbn=978-0-7864-9410-1|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Hendrikse|first=Wim|title=Never Get Old. Man of Ch-Ch-Changes Part 1 and Part 2|publisher=Gopher Publishers|year=2004|isbn=|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Hendrikse|first=Wim|title=David Bowie: The Man Who Changed the World|publisher=Authors Online|year=2013|isbn=|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Jacke|first=Andreas|title=David Bowie – Station To Station|publisher=Psychosozial- Verlag|year=2011|isbn=|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Seabrook|first=Thomas Jerome|title=Bowie in Berlin: A New Career in a New Town|publisher=Jawbone Press|year=2008|isbn=|ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book|title=On Bowie|last=Sheffield|first=Rob|publisher=Dey Street Books|year=2016|isbn=9780062562708|pages=}}
* {{cite book|last=Tremlett|first=George|title=David Bowie: Living on the Brink|url=https://archive.org/details/davidbowieliving00trem|url-access=registration|publisher=Carroll and Graf|year=1997|isbn=|ref=harv}}
* Waldrep, Shelton, &quot;Phenomenology of Performance&quot;, ''The Aesthetics of Self-Invention: Oscar Wilde to David Bowie'', University of Minnesota Press, 2004.'
* {{cite book|author-link=Chris Welch|last=Welch|first=Chris|title=David Bowie: We Could Be Heroes: The Stories Behind Every David Bowie Song|publisher=Da Capo Press|year=1999|isbn=|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Wilcken|first=Hugo|title=33⅓: David Bowie's Low|publisher=Continuum|year=2005|isbn=|ref=harv}}
* [[Jeffrey St. Clair|St. Clair, Jeffrey]] (6 May 2016). [http://www.counterpunch.org/2016/05/06/david-bowies-100-favorite-books-the-counterpunch-connection/ David Bowie’s 100 Favorite Books]
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{wikimedia|d=Q5383|wikt=no|c=Category:David Bowie|s=no|v=no|b=no|voy=no|m=no|mw=no|species=no|n=no}}
{{Library resources box|by=no|onlinebooks=no|about=yes|wikititle=David Bowie}}
* {{official website}}
* {{Britannica|76182}}
* [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jlmuuQBM4Gs David Bowie – Sound and Vision] BBC Documentary (YouTube), 2003, 1:26 h,
* {{IMDb name|0000309}}
* {{tcmdb name|id=20269|name=David Bowie}}
* {{IBDB name}}
* {{Curlie|Arts/People/B/Bowie%2C_David/}}
* {{Rockhall}}
* {{Worldcat id|lccn-n81-112099}}
* [https://www.npg.org.uk/collections/search/portrait-list.php?search=ap&amp;firstRun=true&amp;title=David+Bowie&amp;npgno=&amp;eDate=&amp;lDate=&amp;medium=&amp;subj=&amp;set=&amp;portraitplace=&amp;searchCatalogue=&amp;ow=restrict&amp;submitSearchTerm.x=46&amp;submitSearchTerm.y=10&amp;submitSearchTerm=Search+Now David Bowie National Portrait Gallery]

{{David Bowie|state=uncollapsed}}
{{David Bowie singles}}
{{Major Tom}}
{{Navboxes
|title = Awards for David Bowie
|list =
{{1996 Rock and Roll Hall of Fame}}
{{Brit British Male}}
{{Grammy Lifetime Achievement Award}}
{{Michael Jackson Video Vanguard Award}}
{{Saturn Award for Best Actor}}
}}
{{Authority control}}
{{featured article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Bowie, David}}
[[Category:David Bowie| ]]
[[Category:1947 births]]
[[Category:2016 deaths]]
[[Category:21st-century art collectors]]
[[Category:20th-century English male actors]]
[[Category:20th-century English singers]]
[[Category:Art pop musicians]]
[[Category:Art rock musicians]]
[[Category:Bisexual men]]
[[Category:Bisexual musicians]]
[[Category:Brit Award winners]]
[[Category:British male guitarists]]
[[Category:British mimes]]
[[Category:Columbia Records artists]]
[[Category:Commandeurs of the Ordre des Arts et des Lettres]]
[[Category:Deaths from cancer in New York (state)]]
[[Category:Deaths from liver cancer]]
[[Category:Decca Records artists]]
[[Category:EMI Records artists]]
[[Category:English art collectors]]
[[Category:English baritones]]
[[Category:English electronic musicians]]
[[Category:English expatriates in Germany]]
[[Category:English expatriates in Switzerland]]
[[Category:English expatriates in the United States]]
[[Category:English experimental musicians]]
[[Category:English guitarists]]
[[Category:English male guitarists]]
[[Category:English male film actors]]
[[Category:English male singer-songwriters]]
[[Category:English multi-instrumentalists]]
[[Category:English people of Irish descent]]
[[Category:English people of Welsh descent]]
[[Category:English pop singers]]
[[Category:English record producers]]
[[Category:English rock saxophonists]]
[[Category:British male saxophonists]]
[[Category:English rock singers]]
[[Category:English soul singers]]
[[Category:Experimental pop musicians]]
[[Category:Glam rock musicians]]
[[Category:Grammy Lifetime Achievement Award winners]]
[[Category:Ivor Novello Award winners]]
[[Category:LGBT musicians from England]]
[[Category:LGBT singers]]
[[Category:LGBT songwriters]]
[[Category:Male actors from London]]
[[Category:Mercury Records artists]]
[[Category:Parlophone artists]]
[[Category:People from Brixton]]
[[Category:Deram Records artists]]
[[Category:Philips Records artists]]
[[Category:Protopunk musicians]]
[[Category:Pye Records artists]]
[[Category:RCA Records artists]]
[[Category:Rykodisc artists]]
[[Category:Science Fiction Hall of Fame inductees]]
[[Category:Singers from London]]
[[Category:Synthpop singers]]
[[Category:The Hype (band) members]]
[[Category:The Spiders from Mars members]]
[[Category:Tin Machine members]]
[[Category:Virgin Records artists]]
[[Category:Science fiction fans]]
[[Category:Hansa Records artists]]</text>
      <sha1>ac9l2dzd7qlfnrk949m59yfnc2isxoe</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
