  <page>
    <title>Volkssturm</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8730</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942153513</id>
      <parentid>940413396</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-22T23:00:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Visviva</username>
        <id>123395</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>dab precinct</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Nazi German militia of WW2.}}
{{Italic title}}
{{Infobox military unit
| unit_name = ''Volkssturm''
| image = Bundesarchiv Bild 146-1971-033-15, Vorbeimarsch des Volkssturms an Goebbels, Berlin.jpg | image_size = 260px
| caption = ''Volkssturm'' marching, November 1944
| type = [[Militia]]
| country = {{flag|Nazi Germany}}
| allegiance = [[Nazi Party]]
| start_date = 18 October 1944
| disbanded =  8 May 1945
| ceremonial_chief = [[Joseph Goebbels]]
}}

The '''''Volkssturm''''' ({{IPA-de|ˈfɔlks.ʃtʊɐ̯m}}, &quot;people's storm&quot;){{sfn|Fritz|2004|p=ix}}{{sfn|Kershaw|2011|pp=86–88}} was a national [[militia]] established by [[Nazi Germany]] during the last months of [[World War II]]. It was not set up by the [[German Army (1935–1945)|German Army]], the ground component of the combined German ''[[Wehrmacht]]'' armed forces, but by the [[Nazi Party]] on the orders of [[Adolf Hitler]], and its existence was only officially announced on 16 October 1944.{{sfn|Burleigh|2000|p=786}} It was staffed by conscripting males between the ages of [[child soldier|16]] and 60 years who were not already serving in some military unit. The ''Volkssturm'' comprised one of the final components of the [[Total war#Germany|total war]] promulgated by Propaganda Minister [[Joseph Goebbels]], part of a Nazi endeavor to overcome their enemies' military strength through force of will.{{sfn|Kershaw|2001|pp=713–714}}

==Origins and organization==
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 146-1979-107-10, Angetretene Volkssturmmänner.jpg|right|thumb|21 October 1944. An SS Propaganda Company photograph of ''Volkssturm''; only the men on the far left and far right end of the line appear to be uniformed members.]]
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-H29033, Ratibor, Volkssturmmänner mit Panzerfäusten.jpg|thumb|Bundesarchiv Bild 183-H29033, Ratibor, Volkssturmmänner mit Panzerfäusten| This photo depicts the disparity in age between the members, on the left a man of 50 or more with a boy of about 15 or 16.]]
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-J28787, Volkssturmbataillon an der Oder.jpg|right|thumb|''Volkssturm'' defending the Oder River, February 1945]]
[[File:The British Army in North-west Europe 1944-45 BU2810.jpg|right|thumb|Two members of the ''Volkssturm'' surrender to British troops near [[Bocholt, Germany|Bocholt]], 28 March 1945.]]

The new ''Volkssturm'' drew inspiration from the old [[Kingdom of Prussia|Prussian]] ''[[Landsturm]]'' of 1813–1815, that fought in the liberation wars against [[Napoleon]], mainly as guerrilla forces.{{sfn|Herzstein|1986|p=246}} Plans to form a ''Landsturm'' national militia in eastern Germany as a last resort to boost fighting strength were first proposed in 1944 by General [[Heinz Guderian]], chief  of the General Staff.{{sfn|Guderian|2001|p=362}} The Army did not have enough men  to resist the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Soviet onslaught]]. So, additional categories of men were called into service, including those in non-essential jobs, those previously deemed unfit, over-age, or under-age, and those recovering from wounds.{{sfn|Moorhouse|2012|p=351}} The ''Volkssturm'' had existed, on paper, since around 1925, but it was only after Hitler ordered [[Martin Bormann]] to recruit six million men for this militia that the group became a physical reality. The intended strength of &quot;six million&quot; was never attained.{{sfn|Read|2005|p=855}}

[[Joseph Goebbels]] and other propagandists depicted the ''Volkssturm'' as an outburst of enthusiasm and the will to resist.{{sfn|Herzstein|1986|pp=251–252}} While it had some marginal effect on morale, it was undermined by the recruits' visible lack of uniforms and weaponry.{{sfn|Herzstein|1986|p=248}} Nazi themes of death, transcendence, and commemoration were given full play to encourage the fight.{{sfn|Herzstein|1986|p=252}} Many German civilians realized that this was a desperate attempt to turn the course of the war. Sardonic old men would remark, &quot;We old monkeys are the Führer’s newest weapon&quot; (in German this [[rhyme]]s: &quot;Wir alten Affen sind des Führers neue Waffen&quot;). A popular joke about the ''Volkssturm'' went &quot;Why is the Volkssturm Germany's most precious resource? Because its members have silver in their hair, gold in their mouths, and lead in their bones.&quot;{{sfn|Fritz|2004|p=36}}

For these militia units to be effective, they needed not only strength in numbers, but also [[fanaticism]].{{sfn|Benz|2007|p=254}} During the early stages of ''Volkssturm'' planning, it became apparent that units lacking morale would lack combat effectiveness. To generate fanaticism, ''Volkssturm'' units were placed under direct command of the local Nazi party officials, the ''[[Gauleiter]]'' and ''[[Kreisleiter]]''. The new ''Volkssturm'' was also to become a nationwide organization, with [[Heinrich Himmler]], as [[Replacement Army]] commander, responsible for armament and training. Though nominally under party control, ''Volkssturm'' units were placed under ''[[Wehrmacht]]'' command when engaged in action. Aware that a &quot;people's army&quot; would not be able to withstand the onslaught of the modern army wielded by the Allies, Hitler issued the following order towards the end of 1944: 
::Experience in the East has shown that ''Volkssturm'', emergency and reserve units have little fighting value when left to themselves, and can be quickly destroyed. The fighting value of these units, which are for the most part strong in numbers, but weak in the armaments required for modern battle, is immeasurably higher when they go into action with troops of the regular army in the field.

::I, therefore, order: where ''Volkssturm'', emergency, and reserve units are available, together with regular units, in any battle sector, mixed battle-groups (brigades) will be formed under unified command, so as to give the ''Volkssturm'', emergency, and reserve units stiffening and support.{{sfn|Trevor-Roper|1964|p=204}}

With the Nazi Party in charge of organizing the ''Volkssturm'', each ''Gauleiter'', or Nazi Party District Leader, was charged with the leadership, enrollment, and organization of the ''Volkssturm'' in their district. The largest ''Volkssturm'' unit seems to have corresponded to the next smaller territorial subdivision of the Nazi Party organization—the ''Kreis''. The basic unit was a [[battalion]] of 642 men. Units were mostly composed of members of the [[Hitler Youth]], invalids, the elderly, or men who had previously been considered unfit for military service.{{sfn|Zentner|Bedürftig|1991|pp=1004–1005}}  {{efn|[[Hans Jürgen Massaquoi]], of Liberian and German parents, had been rejected by the ''[[Jungvolk]]'' and the ''Wehrmacht'' on racial grounds, but was called by the ''Volkssturm''. See: Hans J. Massaquoi, ''[[Destined to Witness]], 1990.}} On 12 February 1945, the Nazis conscripted German women and girls into the auxiliaries of the ''Volkssturm''.{{sfn|Hildebrand|1984|p=82}} Correspondingly, girls as young as 14 years were trained in the use of small arms, [[panzerfaust]], [[MG42| machine guns]], and hand grenades from December 1944 through May 1945.{{sfn|Kater|2004|p=238}} 

Municipal organization:

* A ''Bataillon&lt;!--German--&gt;'' ([[battalion]]) in every ''[[Districts of Germany|Kreis]]'' (roughly equivalent to a [[County (United States)|U.S. county]]; there were 920 ''Kreise'' in Greater Germany)
* A ''Kompanie'' ([[Company (military unit)|company]]) in every ''Ortsgruppe'' (the &quot;local chapter&quot; of the Nazi Party).		
* A ''Zug'' ([[platoon]]) in every ''Zelle'' (literally a &quot;cell&quot; of Party members; roughly equivalent to a U.S. [[electoral precinct|precinct]]) 	   	
* A ''Gruppe'' ([[squad]]) in every ''Block'' (city block) 		

Each ''Gauleiter'' and ''Kreisleiter'' had a ''Volkssturm'' Chief of Staff.

From the militia's inception until the spring of 1945, Himmler and Bormann engaged in a power-struggle over the jurisdictional control over the ''Volkssturm'' regarding security and police powers in Germany and the occupied territories; a contest which Himmler and his SS more or less won on one level (police and security), but lost to Bormann on another (mobilizing reserve forces).{{sfn|Yelton|2003|pp=167–177}} Historian David Yelton described the situation as two ranking officers at the helm of a sinking ship fighting over command.{{sfn|Yelton|2003|p=176}}

==Uniforms and insignia==&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Comparative military ranks]] --&gt;
[[Image:Volkssturm armband.svg|thumb|200px|''Volkssturm'' armband.]]
The ''Volkssturm'' &quot;uniform&quot; was only a black armband with the German words ''Deutscher Volkssturm Wehrmacht''. Some variants of the above-mentioned armband worn by Volkssturm members were simply red or yellow cloth-bands with &quot;Deutscher Volkssturm Wehrmacht&quot; printed in black on them. On top of the identification armbands, there were black rank-patches, either with or without silver pips, worn on the collar of the Volkssturm members' uniform. These were characteristically derived from the [[Nazi party paramilitary ranks|rank insignia]] of the various paramilitary organizations of the [[Nazi Party]], which had control over them, and not of the regular ''Wehrmacht''.{{Citation needed|date=December 2018}}

The German government tried to issue as many of its members as possible with military uniforms of all sorts, ranging from field-gray to camouflage types. Most members of the ''Volkssturm'', especially elderly members, had no uniform and were not supplied, so they generally wore either work-attire (including railway workers, policemen and firemen) or their civilian clothing and usually carried with them their own personal rucksacks, blankets and cooking-equipment, etc.{{sfn|Evans|2010|pp=675–676}} 
==Ranks==
The simple paramilitary insignia of the ''Volkssturm'' were as follows:
{| style=&quot;border:1px solid #8888aa; background-color:#f7f8ff; padding:5px; font-size:95%; margin: 0px 12px 12px 0px;&quot;
|-align=&quot;center&quot;
! Volkssturm Rank
! Translation
! Comparative military rank
! Insignia
|-align=&quot;center&quot;
|  ''[[Bataillonsführer]]''
|  Battalion leader
|  [[Major]]
|  [[File:NSKK-Sturmbannführer.svg|50px]]
|-align=&quot;center&quot;
|  ''Bataillonsarzt''
|  Battalion Physician
|  [[Captain (OF-2)#History|Captain]]
|  [[File:NSKK-Sturmführer.svg|50px]]&lt;br&gt;{{small|with [[Rod of Asclepius]]}}
|-align=&quot;center&quot;
|  ''[[Kompanieführer]]''
|  Company leader
|  [[Captain (OF-2)#History|Captain]]
|  [[File:NSKK-Sturmführer.svg|50px]]
|-align=&quot;center&quot;
|  ''[[Zugführer]]''
|  [[Platoon leader]]
|  [[Lieutenant]]
|  [[File:NSKK-Truppführer.svg|50px]]
|-align=&quot;center&quot;
| ''Sanitätsdienstgrad''
| [Platoon]&lt;br&gt;Medical Orderly 
| [[Corporal]]
| [[File:NSKK-Scharführer.svg|50px]]
|- align=&quot;center&quot;
| ''[[Gruppenführer]]''
|  [[Squad]] leader
|  [[Corporal]]
|  [[File:NSKK-Scharführer.svg|50px]]
|-align=&quot;center&quot;
|  ''[[Volkssturmmann]]''
|  People's Storm Trooper
|  [[Private (rank)|Private]]
|  [[File:NSKK-Mann.svg|50px]]
|}

==Training and impact==
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-J31391, Berlin, Volkssturm, Ausbildung.jpg|thumb|February or March 1945: ''Volkssturm'' members being trained to use the ''[[Panzerfaust]]'' anti-tank weapon.]]
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 146-1973-001-30, Volkssturm, Frau mit Panzerfaust.jpg|thumb|March 1945: ''Volkssturm'' trooper explaining the handling of a ''[[Panzerfaust]]'' to a female civilian.]]

Typically, members of the ''Volkssturm'' received only very basic military training. It included a brief indoctrination and training on the use of basic weapons such as the [[Karabiner 98k]] [[rifle]] and ''[[Panzerfaust]]''. Because of continuous fighting and weapon shortages, weapon training was often minimal. There was also a lack of instructors, meaning that weapons training was sometimes done by World War I veterans drafted into service themselves. Often ''Volkssturm'' members were only able to familiarize themselves with their weapons when in actual combat.

There was no standardization of any kind and units were issued only what equipment was available. This was true of every form of equipment—''Volkssturm'' members were required to bring their own uniforms and culinary equipment etc. This resulted in the units looking very ragged and, instead of boosting civilian morale, it often reminded people of Germany's desperate state.{{sfn|Herzstein|1986|p=248}} Armament was equally haphazard: though some [[Karabiner 98k]]s were on hand, members were also issued older [[Gewehr 98]]s and 19th-century [[Mauser Model 1871|Gewehr 71s]] and [[Steyr-Mannlicher M1888]]s, as well as [[Dreyse M1907]] pistols. In addition there was a plethora of Soviet, British, Belgian, French, Italian, and other weapons that had been captured by German forces during the war. The Germans had also developed cheap but reasonably effective ''Volkssturm'' weapons, such as [[MP 3008]] machine pistols and [[Volkssturmgewehr]] rifles. These were completely stamped and machine-pressed constructions (in the 1940s, industrial processes were much cruder than today, so a firearm needed great amounts of semi-artisanal work to be actually reliable). The ''Volkssturm'' troops were nominally supplied when and where possible by both the ''Wehrmacht'' and the SS.{{sfn|Duffy|2002|p=383}}

When units had completed their training and received armament, members took a customary [[Hitler oath|oath to Hitler]] and were then dispatched into combat. Unlike most English-speaking countries, Germany had universal military service for all young men for several generations, so many of the older members would have had at least basic military training from when they served in the [[Imperial German army|German Army]] and many would have been veterans of the [[First World War]]. ''Volkssturm'' units were supposed to be used only in their own districts, but many were sent directly to the front lines. Ultimately, it was their charge to confront the overwhelming power of the British, Canadian, Soviet, American, and French armies alongside ''Wehrmacht'' forces to either turn the tide of the war or set a shining example for future generations of Germans and expunge the defeat of 1918 by fighting to the last, dying before surrendering.{{sfn|Bessel|2010|p=17}}{{efn|Also see: Berd Wegner, &quot;Zweite Weltkrieg und die Choreographie des Untergangs&quot;, ''Geschichte und Gesellschaft'', vol. xxvi (2000), no. 3, pp. 492–518.}} It was an apocalyptic goal which some of those assigned to the ''Volkssturm'' took to heart. Unremittingly fanatical members of the ''Volkssturm'' refused to abandon the Nazi ethos unto the dying days of Nazi Germany, and in a number of instances took brutal police &quot;actions&quot; against German civilians deemed defeatists or cowards.{{sfn|Kershaw|2011|p=87}}

On some occasions, members of the ''Volkssturm'' showed tremendous courage and a determined will to resist, more so even than soldiers in the ''Wehrmacht''. The ''Volkssturm'' battalion 25/235 for instance, started out with 400 men but fought on until there were only 10 men remaining. Fighting at [[Küstrin]] between 30 January to 29 March 1945, militia units made up mostly of the ''Volkssturm'' resisted for nearly two months. Losses were upwards of 60 percent for the ''Volkssturm'' at [[Kolberg]], roughly 1900 of them died at [[Breslau]], and during the [[Battle of Königsberg]] ([[Kaliningrad]]), another 2400 members of the ''Volkssturm'' were killed.{{sfn|Sorge|1986|pp=49–50}} At other times along the western front particularly, ''Volkssturm'' troops would cast their arms aside and disappear into the chaos.{{sfn|Burleigh|2000|p=786}} Youthful ardor and fanaticism among Hitler Youth members fighting with the ''Volkssturm'' or an insatiable sense of duty from old men proved tragic sometimes. An example shared by historian Stephen Fritz is instructive in this case:
::In one representative village just north of [[Bad Windsheim]], the Herbolzheim ''Volkssturm'' unit, with its customary composition of elderly men and young boys under the influence of a few regular army soldiers, foolishly declared the town a fortress and laid mines in the streets. As American troops approached in midmorning on April 12, shots from the village rang out. Angered, the Americans commenced a two-hour artillery barrage complemented by aerial attacks that gutted the town with incendiary and high-explosive bombs. With their village engulfed in flames, the civilian inhabitants, mostly the elderly, women, and children, fled in search of shelter to the surrounding fields, all the while under American fire.{{sfn|Fritz|2004|p=121}}

Not every ''Volkssturm'' unit was suicidal or apocalyptic in outlook as the war drew closer to its end. Many of them lost their enthusiasm for the fight when it became clear that the Allies had won, prompting them to lay down their weapons and surrender – they also feared being captured by Allied forces and tortured or executed as partisans.{{sfn|Moorhouse|2012|p=352}} Duty to their communities and sparing them from horrors like at Bad Windsheim also played a part in their capitulation, as did self-preservation.{{sfn|Bessel|2010|p=22}}

Their most extensive use was during the [[Battle of Berlin]], where ''Volkssturm'' units fought in many parts of the city. This battle was particularly devastating to its formations, however; many members fought to the death out of fear of being captured by the Soviets, holding out to the very end, which was in keeping with their covenant.{{sfn|Kissel|1962|p=32}} Nonetheless, a force of over 2.5 million Soviet troops, equipped with 6,250 tanks and over 40,000 artillery pieces were assigned to capture the city, and the diminished remnants of the ''Wehrmacht'' were no match for them. Meanwhile, Hitler denounced every perceived &quot;betrayal&quot; to the inhabitants of the ''[[Führerbunker]]''.{{sfn|Bessel|2010|pp=104–109}} Not eager to die what was thought to be a pointless death, many older members of the ''Volkssturm'' looked for places to hide from the approaching Soviet Army.{{sfn|Kershaw|2001|p=811}} Juxtaposed against the tragic image of Berlin holding out against all odds was the frequent exodus and capitulation of ''Wehrmacht'' soldiers and members of the ''Volkssturm'' in southern and western Germany.{{sfn|Bessel|2010|pp=135–137}}

==Battle for Berlin==
In the [[Battle in Berlin|Battle for Berlin]], members of the ''Volkssturm'' (mainly young boys from the ages of 13-18 and old men) were used by the German high command as a last-ditch attempt to defend Berlin. The ''Volkssturm'' had a strength of about 60,000 in the Berlin area formed into 92 battalions, of which about 30 battalions of ''Volkssturm I'' (those with some weapons) were sent to forward positions, while those of ''Volkssturm II'' (those without weapons){{sfn|Beevor|2002|p=178}} remained in the inner city. One of the few substantive fighting units left to defend Berlin was the [[LVI Panzer Corps]], which occupied the southeastern sector of the town, whereas the remaining parts of the city were being defended by what remained of the SS, the ''Volkssturm'', and the Hitler Youth formations.{{sfn|Ziemke|1968|p=481}}

One notable and unusual ''Volkssturm'' unit in the Battle for Berlin was the 3/115 [[Siemensstadt]] Battalion. It comprised 770 men, mainly First World War veterans in their 50s who were reasonably fit factory workers, with experienced officers. Unlike most ''Volkssturm'' units it was quite well equipped and trained. It was formed into three rifle companies, a support company (with two [[infantry support gun]]s, four infantry mortars and heavy machine guns), and a heavy weapons company (with four Soviet [[152 mm howitzer-gun M1937 (ML-20)|M-20 howitzers]] and a French De Bange 220&amp;nbsp;mm mortar). The battalion first engaged Soviet troops at [[Friedrichsfelde]] on 21 April and saw the heaviest fighting over the following two days. It held out until 2 May, by which time it was down to just 50 rifles and two light machine guns. The survivors fell back to join other ''Volkssturm'' units. 26 men from the battalion were awarded the [[Iron Cross]].{{sfn|Le Tissier|2008|p=212}} Allied bombing had reduced Berlin to rubble; meanwhile the final stand in Berlin dwindled to fighting between highly trained, battle-hardened Soviet troops on the brink of final victory, who viewed resistance fighters like the ''Volkssturm'' as terrorists in much the same way the Wehrmacht once had potential partisans during [[Operation Barbarossa]].{{sfn|Beevor|2002|p=299–301}} [[Red Army]] soldiers called the Hitler Youth formations and members of the ''Volkssturm'' still fighting to the end in Berlin &quot;totals&quot; for being part of Germany's total mobilization effort.{{sfn|Beevor|2002|p=316}}

==Final phase==
While [[Iron Cross]]es were being handed out in places like Berlin, other cities and towns like [[Parchim]] and [[Mecklenburg]] witnessed old elites, acting as military commandants over the Hitler Youth and ''Volkssturm'', asserting themselves and demanding that the defensive fighting stop so as to spare lives and property.{{sfn|Bessel|2010|pp=139–140}} Despite their efforts, the last four months of the war were an exercise in futility for the ''Volkssturm'', and the Nazi leadership's insistence to continue the fight to the bitter end contributed to an additional 1.23 million (approximated) deaths, half of them German military personnel and the other half from the ''Volkssturm''.{{sfn|Fritz|2004|p=191}} The figure historian Stephen Fritz puts forward does not match the observations of [[Richard J. Evans]], who reported 175,000 ''Volkssturm'' members killed fighting the professional armies of the western Allies and Soviet Union.{{sfn|Evans|2010|p=676}} Evans' figures are based on the card-indexed members listed, who were officially reported as killed, but Martin Sorge points out that this figure does not include the 30,000 listed as presumed missing or dead from a 1963 report.{{sfn|Sorge|1986|p=50}}

Interrogated members of the ''Volkssturm''—when questioned as to where the regular forces had gone—revealed that German soldiers surrendered to the Americans instead of the Red Army for fear of reprisals related to the atrocities they had committed in the Soviet Union.{{sfn|Beevor|2002|p=308}}

==Notable members==
*[[Ernst Tiburzy]], received the [[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross]].{{sfn|Fellgiebel|2000|pp=423, 506}}
*[[Martin Heidegger]], German philosopher{{sfn|Safranski|1999|pp=332–333}}
*[[Otto Dix]], German painter

==In fiction==
* [[Gregor Dorfmeister]], under the pseudonym of [[Manfred Gregor]], published in 1958 the novel ''[[Die Brücke (novel)|Die Brücke]]'' based on his experiences in a ''Volkssturm'' unit. The novel has been adapted to film in [[Die Brücke (film)|1959]] and a made-for-television movie in [[Die Brücke (film)#Remake|2008]].

* ''Volkssturm'' units composed of teenagers are depicted in battle scenes in the 2004 film, ''[[Downfall (2004 film)|Downfall]]''.{{efn|See ''Downfall'' (2004) on IMDB.com: https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0363163/?___441}}

==See also==
*[[Einstossflammenwerfer 46]]
*[[Landwehr]]
*[[MP 3008]]
*[[Volksgrenadier]]
*[[Volkspistole]]
*[[Volkssturmgewehr]]
*[[Wachdienst]]
*[[Werwolf Guerrillas]]

'''Other nations:'''
*[[Black Brigades|Black Brigades (Italy)]]
*[[Home Guard (United Kingdom)]]
*[[Volunteer Fighting Corps|Volunteer Fighting Corps (Japan)]]

== Notes ==
{{Notelist}}

== References ==
=== Citations ===
{{Reflist|20em}}

=== Bibliography ===
{{refbegin|30em|indent=yes}}
* {{cite book | last = Beevor | first = Antony | authorlink = Antony Beevor | title = The Fall of Berlin, 1945 | year = 2002 | publisher = Viking | location = New York; London | isbn = 0-670-03041-4 | ref = harv }}
* {{cite book | last=Benz | first= Wolfgang | year=2007 | title= A Concise History of the Third Reich | location= Berkeley and Los Angeles | publisher= University of California Press | isbn= 978-0-52025-383-4 | ref = harv }}
* {{cite book | last = Bessel | first = Richard | year = 2010 | title = Germany 1945: From War to Peace | location = New York | publisher = Harper Perennial | isbn = 978-0-06054-037-1| ref= harv }}
* {{cite book | last=Burleigh | first=Michael | year=2000 | title=The Third Reich: A New History | location=New York | publisher=Hill and Wang | isbn=978-0-80909-325-0 | ref=harv | url=https://archive.org/details/thirdreichnewhis00burl }}
* {{cite book | last=Duffy | first=Christopher | year=2002 | title= Red Storm on the Reich: The Soviet March on Germany, 1945| location= Edison, NJ | publisher= Castle Books | isbn=0-7858-1624-0 | ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | last=Evans | first=Richard | year=2010 | title=The Third Reich at War | location=New York | publisher=Penguin | isbn=978-0-14311-671-4 | ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | last=Fritz | first=Stephen G. | year=2004 | title=Endkampf: Soldiers, Civilians, and the Death of the Third Reich | location= Lexington | publisher= The University Press of Kentucky | isbn=978-0-81312-325-7 | ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | last=Guderian | first=Heinz | year=2001 | title=Panzer Leader | location=New York and Boston | publisher=Da Capo Press | asin=B008CMU05I | ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | last=Herzstein | first=Robert E.| year=1986 | title=The War That Hitler Won: Goebbels and the Nazi Media Campaign | location=St Paul, MN | publisher=Paragon House | isbn=978-0913729472 | ref= harv}}
* {{cite book | last=Hildebrand | first=Klaus | year=1984 | title=The Third Reich | location=London and New York | publisher=Routledge | isbn=0-0494-3033-5 | ref=harv | url=https://archive.org/details/thirdreich0000hild }}
* {{cite book | last=Fellgiebel | first=Walther-Peer | year=2000 | title=Die Träger des Ritterkreuzes des Eisernen Kreuzes 1939–1945 | language=German | location=Friedberg | publisher=Podzun-Pallas | isbn=978-3-7909-0284-6 | ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | last=Kater | first=Michael H. | year=2004 | title=Hitler Youth | location=Cambridge, MA | publisher=Harvard University Press | isbn=0-674-01496-0 | ref=harv | url=https://archive.org/details/hitleryouth00kate }}
* {{cite book | last=Kershaw | first=Ian | year=2001 | title= Hitler: 1936–1945, Nemesis | location= New York | publisher= W. W. Norton &amp; Company | isbn=978-0-39332-252-1| ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | last=Kershaw | first=Ian | year=2011 | title= The End: The Defiance and Destruction of Hitler’s Germany, 1944–1945 | url=https://archive.org/details/enddefiancedestr00kers_0 | url-access=registration | location= New York | publisher= Penguin Books | isbn=978-0-14312-213-5| ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | last=Kissel | first=Hans | year=1962 | title=Der Deutsche Volkssturm 1944/45: Eine territoriale Miliz im Rahmen der Landesverteidung | language=German | location=Frankfurt am Main | publisher=Verlag E. S. Mittler und Sohn | asin=B00DSDZEGQ | ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | last=Le Tissier | first=Tony | year=2008 | title=Berlin Battlefield Guide: Third Reich &amp; Cold War | location=South Yorkshire | publisher=Pen &amp; Sword Military | isbn=1-84415-766-0 | ref=harv}}
* Massaquoi, Hans J. (1990). ''Destined to Witness: Growing Up Black in Nazi Germany''. Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press.
* {{cite book | last=Moorhouse | first=Roger | year=2012 | title=Berlin at War | location=New York | publisher=Basic Books | isbn=978-0-46502-855-9| ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | last = Read | first = Anthony | title = The Devil's Disciples: Hitler's Inner Circle | place = New York | publisher = Norton | year = 2005 | isbn = 978-039332-697-0 | ref = harv}}
* {{cite book | last=Safranski | first=Rüdiger | title=Martin Heidegger: Between Good and Evil | place=Cambridge, MA | publisher=Harvard University Press | year=1999 | isbn=978-0-67438-710-2 | ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | last=Sorge | first=Martin K. | title=The Other Price of Hitler's War: German Military and Civilian Losses Resulting from World War II | year=1986 | place=New York | publisher=Greenwood Press | isbn=978-0-31325-293-8 | ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | last=Trevor-Roper | first=Hugh | title=Blitzkrieg to Defeat: Hitler's War Directives, 1939–1945 | year=1964 | place=New York | publisher=Holt, Rinehart and Winston | isbn=978-0-03085-494-1 | ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | last=Yelton | first=David K. | chapter=The SS, NSDAP, and the Question of Volkssturm Expansion | title=The Impact of Nazism: New Perspectives on the Third Reich and Its Legacy | editor1=Alan E. Steinweis | editor2=Daniel Rogers| year=2003 | location=Lincoln, NE | publisher=University of Nebraska Press | isbn=978-0-80324-299-9 | ref = harv}}
* {{cite book | last1=Zentner | first1=Christian | last2=Bedürftig | first2=Friedemann | year=1991 | title=The Encyclopedia of the Third Reich (2 vols.) | location= New York | publisher=MacMillan Publishing | isbn=0-02-897500-6 |ref=harv }}
*{{cite book | last=Ziemke | first=Earl F | year=1968 | title= Stalingrad to Berlin: The German Defeat in the East | url=https://archive.org/details/stalingradtoberl00ziem | url-access=registration | location= Washington D.C. | publisher= Office of the Chief of Military History – U.S. Army | asin= B002E5VBSE |ref = harv }}
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{commonscat}}
*[http://www.lonesentry.com/articles/volkssturm/index.html U.S. Wartime Intelligence Report on German Volkssturm]

{{Uniforms, insignia and ranks of Nazi Germany}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Groups of World War II]]
[[Category:Home front during World War II]]
[[Category:Paramilitary organisations based in Germany]]
[[Category:Civil defense]]
[[Category:Military units and formations established in 1944]]
[[Category:Military units and formations of Germany in World War II]]
[[Category:German words and phrases]]</text>
      <sha1>h2ao9y73bd1yk7lu23hyjp4sxgmgysu</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
