  <page>
    <title>Dorothy Parker</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8781</id>
    <revision>
      <id>936223329</id>
      <parentid>935942311</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-17T13:26:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Sysilverstein</username>
        <id>9710013</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Added title of compilation, added 2nd edition of compilation</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use mdy dates|date=August 2019}}
{{Infobox writer &lt;!-- for more information see [[:Template:Infobox writer/doc]] --&gt;
| name = Dorothy Parker
| image = File:Young Dorothy Parker.jpg
|birth_name=Dorothy Rothschild
| birth_date = {{birth date|1893|8|22|mf=y}}
| birth_place = [[Long Branch, New Jersey]], U.S.
|nationality = American
| death_date = {{death date and age|mf=yes|1967|6|7|1893|8|22}}
| death_place = [[New York City]], U.S.
| occupation = Author, poet, [[critic]], [[screenwriter]]
| genre = Poetry, satire, short stories
| movement = [[American modernism]]
| notableworks = Enough Rope, Sunset Gun, Star Light, Star Bright--, [[A Star Is Born (1937 film)|A Star Is Born]]
|spouses = {{marriage|Edwin Pond Parker II&lt;br /&gt;|1917|1928|end=divorced}}&lt;br /&gt;{{marriage|[[Alan Campbell (screenwriter)|Alan Campbell]]&lt;br /&gt;|1934|1947|end=divorced}}&lt;br /&gt;{{marriage||1950|1963|end=died}}
&lt;!-- | influences = [[Franklin Pierce Adams]], [[Robert Benchley]], [[Colette]], [[Ring Lardner]], [[William Makepeace Thackeray]], [[Elinor Wylie]]
| influenced = [[Candace Bushnell]], [[Maureen Dowd]], [[Nora Ephron]], [[Fran Lebowitz]], [[Amy Sedaris]], [[David Sedaris]], [[Amy Sherman-Palladino]] --&gt;
| awards = {{awd|[[O. Henry Award]]|1929}}
| website = {{URL|http://www.dorothyparker.com}}
}}
'''Dorothy Parker''' (née '''Rothschild'''; August 22, 1893 – June 7, 1967) was an American poet, writer, critic, and [[satire|satirist]] based in New York; she was best known for her [[wit]], wisecracks, and eye for 20th-century urban foibles.

From a conflicted and unhappy childhood, Parker rose to acclaim, both for her literary works published in such magazines as ''[[The New Yorker]]'' and as a founding member of the [[Algonquin Round Table]]. Following the breakup of the circle, Parker traveled to Hollywood to pursue [[screenwriting]]. Her successes there, including two [[Academy Awards|Academy Award]] nominations, were curtailed when her involvement in [[left-wing politics]] resulted in her being placed on the [[Hollywood blacklist]].

Dismissive of her own talents, she deplored her reputation as a &quot;wisecracker&quot;. Nevertheless, both her literary output and reputation for sharp wit have endured.

== Early life and education ==
Also known as Dot or Dottie, {{cn|date=August 2019}} Parker was born Dorothy Rothschild in 1893 to Jacob Henry Rothschild and his wife Eliza Annie (née Marston)&lt;ref&gt;Meade 6&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Meade |first=Marion |title=Dorothy Parker: What Fresh Hell Is This? |publisher=Penguin Books |year=1987 |location=New York |page=5 |isbn=0-14-011616-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; (1851–1913) at 732 Ocean Avenue in [[Long Branch, New Jersey|Long Branch]], [[New Jersey]].&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT obit&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://dorothyparker.com/gallery/new-york-times-obituary |title=Dorothy Parker, 73, Literary Wit, Dies |newspaper=The New York Times |date=June 8, 1967 |first=Alden |last=Whitman}}&lt;/ref&gt; Her parents had a summer beach cottage there. Parker's mother was of Scottish descent, and her father was of German Jewish descent, son of Sampson Jacob Rothschild (1818–1899), a merchant who immigrated to the USA around 1846 settling in Monroe, AL, and Mary Greissman (b. 1824), both Prussian-born Jewish immigrants. Her father was one of five known siblings: Simon (1854–1908), Samuel (b. 1857), Hannah (1860–1911, later Mrs William Henry Theobald), and the youngest, Martin Rothschild, born in Manhattan, New York on December 12, 1865, who perished in the sinking of the [[Titanic]].&lt;ref&gt;https://www.encyclopedia-titanica.org/titanic-victim/martin-rothschild.html&lt;/ref&gt; Parker wrote in her essay &quot;My Hometown&quot; that her parents returned to their [[Manhattan]] apartment shortly after Labor Day so that she could be called a true New Yorker. Her mother died in West End in July 1898, a month before Parker's fifth birthday.&lt;ref&gt;Meade 12&lt;/ref&gt;

Her father remarried in 1900 to Eleanor Frances Lewis (1851–1903).&lt;ref&gt;Meade 13&lt;/ref&gt; Parker hated her father, whom she accused of physical abuse; and despised her stepmother, whom she refused to call &quot;mother&quot;, &quot;stepmother&quot;, or &quot;Eleanor&quot;, instead referring to her as &quot;the housekeeper&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Herrmann |first=Dorothy |title=With Malice Toward All: The Quips, Lives and Loves of Some Celebrated 20th-Century American Wits |publisher=G. P. Putnam's Sons |year=1982 |location=New York |page=78 |isbn=0-399-12710-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; – though her biographer [[Marion Meade]] refers to this account as &quot;largely false&quot;, stating that the atmosphere in which Parker was growing up was indulgent, affectionate, supportive and generous&lt;ref&gt;Meade, M. (1987). Dorothy Parker: what fresh hell is this? New York: Villard Books.&lt;/ref&gt;. Parker grew up on the [[Upper West Side]] and attended a [[Roman Catholic]] elementary school at the Convent of the Blessed Sacrament on West [[79th Street (Manhattan)|79th Street]] with her sister, Helen, although their father was [[Jewish]] and her stepmother was [[Protestant]].&lt;ref&gt;Meade 14&lt;/ref&gt; ([[Mercedes de Acosta]] was a classmate.) Parker once joked that she was asked to leave following her characterization of the [[Immaculate Conception]] as &quot;[[spontaneous combustion]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Chambers |first=Dianne |contribution=Parker, Dorothy |year=1995 |title=The Oxford Companion to Women's Writing in the United States | editor-last = Wagner-Martin | editor-first = Linda |publisher=Oxford University Press | contribution-url = http://www.oxfordreference.com/views/ENTRY.html?subview=Main&amp;entry=t196.e0604}}&lt;/ref&gt; Her stepmother died in 1903, when Parker was nine.&lt;ref&gt;Meade 16&lt;/ref&gt; Parker later attended [[Miss Dana's School for Young Ladies|Miss Dana's School]], a [[finishing school]] in [[Morristown, New Jersey]].&lt;ref&gt;Meade 27&lt;/ref&gt; She graduated from Miss Dana's School in 1911, at the age of 18, according to Authur,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Kinney |first=Authur F. |title=Dorothy Parker |url=https://archive.org/details/dorothyparker0000kinn |url-access=registration |publisher=Twayne Publishers |year=1978 |location=Boston |pages=[https://archive.org/details/dorothyparker0000kinn/page/26 26–27]}}&lt;/ref&gt; though other authors (e.g. Rhonda Pettit,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.english.illinois.edu/MAPS/poets/m_r/parker/bio.htm&lt;/ref&gt; Marion Meade) state she never graduated from either school. Following her father's death in 1913, she played piano at a dancing school to earn a living&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Silverstein |first=Stuart Y. |title=Not Much Fun: The Lost Poems of Dorothy Parker |publisher=Scribner |year=1996 |location=New York |page=13 |isbn=0-7432-1148-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; while she worked on her poetry.

She sold her first poem to ''[[Vanity Fair (magazine)|Vanity Fair]]'' magazine in 1914 and some months later was hired as an editorial assistant for ''[[Vogue (magazine)|Vogue]]'', another [[Condé Nast Publications|Condé Nast]] magazine. She moved to ''Vanity Fair'' as a staff writer after two years at ''Vogue''.&lt;ref&gt;Silverstein 13&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1917, she met and married a [[Wall Street]] [[stockbroker]], Edwin Pond Parker II&lt;ref&gt;Herrmann 78&lt;/ref&gt;
(1893–1933&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Edwin P. Parker 2d |newspaper=The New York Times |agency=Associated Press |date=January 8, 1933 |url=https://www.nytimes.com/1933/01/08/archives/edwin-p-parker-2d.html |accessdate=2013-02-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;) and they married before he left to serve in [[World War I]] with the [[U.S. Army]] 4th Division. Dorothy Parker filed for divorce in 1928. He later remarried, to Anne E. O’Brien, formerly probation officer of the Juvenile Court and died at 39, from an overdose of a sleeping powder for pain following a dental procedure.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.newspapers.com/image/?clipping_id=20026728&amp;fcfToken=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJmcmVlLXZpZXctaWQiOjM3MDEwNTU0MCwiaWF0IjoxNTY2NTExOTc2LCJleHAiOjE1NjY1OTgzNzZ9.R_3bqYKimqgQP75_q2aQPrq1Shm5bPzVl5zkbx9w1rA Hartford] Courant, Hartford, Connecticut, January 8, 1933, Sun. Page 6&lt;/ref&gt; Dorothy Parker retained her married name, though she remarried the screenwriter and former actor [[Alan Campbell (screenwriter)|Alan Campbell]], and moved to Hollywood.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.english.illinois.edu/MAPS/poets/m_r/parker/bio.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

== Algonquin Round Table years ==
[[File:Algonquin Round Table.gif|thumb|Parker, with Algonquin Round Table members and guests (l–r) Art Samuels (editor of ''Harper's'' and, briefly, ''The New Yorker''), Charles MacArthur, Harpo Marx, and Alexander Woollcott, circa 1919]]

Parker's career took off in 1918 while she was writing theater criticism for ''Vanity Fair'', filling in for the vacationing [[P. G. Wodehouse]].&lt;ref&gt;Silverstein 18&lt;/ref&gt; At the magazine, she met [[Robert Benchley]], who became a close friend, and [[Robert E. Sherwood]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Altman |first=Billy |title=Laughter's Gentle Soul: The Life of Robert Benchley |publisher=W. W. Norton &amp; Company |year=1997 |location=New York |page=[https://archive.org/details/laughtersgentles00altm/page/146 146] |isbn=0-393-03833-5 |url=https://archive.org/details/laughtersgentles00altm/page/146}}&lt;/ref&gt; The trio began lunching at the [[Algonquin Hotel]] on a near-daily basis and became founding members of what became known as the [[Algonquin Round Table]]. The Round Table numbered among its members the newspaper columnists [[Franklin Pierce Adams]] and [[Alexander Woollcott]]. Through their publication of Parker's lunchtime remarks and short verses, particularly in Adams' column &quot;The Conning Tower&quot;, Dorothy began developing a national reputation as a wit. When the group was informed that famously taciturn former president [[Calvin Coolidge]] had died, Parker remarked, &quot;How could they tell?&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=Calvin Coolidge |date=2006 |first=David |last=Greenberg |series=The American Presidents Series |publisher=Times Books |isbn=978-0-8050-6957-0 |page=[https://archive.org/details/calvincoolidge00gree/page/9 9] |url=https://archive.org/details/calvincoolidge00gree/page/9|access-date=March 19, 2015|url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Parker's caustic wit as a critic initially proved popular, but she was eventually dismissed by ''Vanity Fair'' in 1920 after her criticisms too often offended powerful producers. In solidarity, both Benchley and Sherwood resigned in protest.&lt;ref&gt;Altman 156–8&lt;/ref&gt; She soon started working for ''[[Ainslee's Magazine]]'', which had a higher circulation. She also published pieces in ''Vanity Fair'', which was happier to publish her than employ her, ''The Smart Set'', and ''The American Mercury'', but also in the popular ''Ladies’ Home Journal'', ''Saturday Evening Post'', and ''Life''.&lt;ref name=&quot;gottlieb&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last1=Gottlieb |first1=Robert |title=Brilliant, Troubled Dorothy Parker |url=https://www.nybooks.com/articles/2016/04/07/brilliant-troubled-dorothy-parker/ |accessdate=August 23, 2018 |work=New York Review of Books |date=April 7, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

When [[Harold Ross]] founded ''[[The New Yorker]]'' in 1925, Parker and Benchley were part of a board of editors established by Ross to allay concerns of his investors. Parker's first piece for the magazine was published in its second issue.&lt;ref&gt;Silverstein 32&lt;/ref&gt; Parker became famous for her short, viciously humorous poems, many highlighting ludicrous aspects of her many (largely unsuccessful) romantic affairs and others wistfully considering the appeal of suicide.

The next 15 years were Parker's greatest period of productivity and success. In the 1920s alone she published some 300 poems and free verses in ''Vanity Fair'', ''Vogue'', &quot;The Conning Tower&quot; and ''The New Yorker'' as well as ''[[Life (magazine)|Life]]'', ''[[McCall's]]'' and ''[[The New Republic]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Silverstein 62–3&lt;/ref&gt;  Her poem, &quot;Song in a Minor Key&quot; was published during a candid interview with New York [[Newspaper Enterprise Association|N.E.A.]] writer, [[Josephine Van de Grift]]. &lt;ref&gt; Van de Grift, Josephine. (November 5, 1922). ''Dorothy Parker says it's not all fun to be funny.'' The Salina Daily Union.  p.&amp;nbsp;18. &lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Enough Rope by Dorothy Parker.jpg|thumb|left|Cover of the first edition of ''Enough Rope'']]
Parker published her first volume of poetry, ''Enough Rope'', in 1926. The collection sold 47,000 copies&lt;ref name=&quot;canlqr&quot;&gt;Silverstein 35&lt;/ref&gt; and garnered impressive reviews. ''[[The Nation]]'' described her verse as &quot;caked with a salty humor, rough with splinters of disillusion, and tarred with a bright black authenticity&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Meade 177&lt;/ref&gt; Although some critics, notably ''[[The New York Times]]'' reviewer, dismissed her work as &quot;[[flapper]] verse&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;Meade 178&lt;/ref&gt; the volume helped affirm Parker's reputation for sparkling wit.&lt;ref name=&quot;canlqr&quot; /&gt; Parker released two more volumes of verse, ''Sunset Gun'' (1928) and ''Death and Taxes'' (1931), along with the short story collections ''Laments for the Living'' (1930) and ''After Such Pleasures'' (1933). ''Not So Deep as a Well'' (1936) collected much of the material previously published in ''Rope'', ''Gun'', and ''Death'' and she re-released her fiction with a few new pieces in 1939 under the title ''Here Lies''.

She collaborated with playwright [[Elmer Rice]] to create ''Close Harmony'', which ran on Broadway in December 1924. The play was well received in out-of-town previews and was favorably reviewed in New York but it closed after a run of just 24 performances. It did become a successful touring production under the title ''The Lady Next Door''.&lt;ref&gt;Meade 138&lt;/ref&gt;

Some of Parker's most popular work was published in ''The New Yorker'' in the form of acerbic book reviews under the byline &quot;Constant Reader&quot;. Her response to the whimsy of [[A. A. Milne]]'s ''[[The House at Pooh Corner]]'' was &quot;Tonstant Weader fwowed up&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Parker |first=Dorothy |title=Far From Well, collected in The Portable Dorothy Parker Revised and Enlarged Edition |publisher=Penguin Books |year=1976 |location=New York |page=518 |isbn=0-14-015074-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; Her reviews appeared semi-regularly from 1927 to 1933,&lt;ref&gt;Silverstein 38&lt;/ref&gt; were widely read, and were later published in a collection under the name ''Constant Reader'' in 1970.

Her best-known short story, &quot;Big Blonde&quot;, published in ''[[The Bookman (New York)|The Bookman]]'' magazine, was awarded the [[O. Henry Award]] as the best short story of 1929.&lt;ref&gt;Herrmann 74&lt;/ref&gt; Her short stories, though often witty, were also spare and incisive, and more bittersweet than comic; her style is often described as sardonic.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://archive.org/details/columbiacompanio00blan |title=The Columbia companion to the twentieth-century American short story |date=2000 |publisher=Columbia University Press |others=Gelfant, Blanche H., 1922– |isbn=978-0-231-11098-3 |location=New York |oclc=51443994}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Parker eventually separated from her husband, divorcing in 1928. She had a number of affairs, her lovers including reporter-turned-playwright [[Charles MacArthur]] and the publisher [[Seward Collins]]. Her relationship with MacArthur resulted in a pregnancy. Parker is alleged to have said, &quot;how like me, to put all my eggs into one bastard&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Meade 105&lt;/ref&gt; She had an abortion, and fell into a depression that culminated in her first attempt at suicide.&lt;ref&gt;Silverstein 29&lt;/ref&gt;

Toward the end of this period, Parker began to become more politically aware and active. What would become a lifelong commitment to activism began in 1927 when she became concerned about the pending executions of [[Sacco and Vanzetti]]. Parker traveled to [[Boston]] to protest the proceedings. She and fellow Round Tabler [[Ruth Hale (feminist)|Ruth Hale]] were arrested, and Parker eventually pleaded guilty to a charge of &quot;loitering and sauntering&quot;, paying a $5 fine.&lt;ref&gt;Silverstein 44&lt;/ref&gt;

== Hollywood ==
In 1932 Parker met [[Alan Campbell (screenwriter)|Alan Campbell]],&lt;ref&gt;Meade 238&lt;/ref&gt; an actor with aspirations to become a screenwriter. They married two years later in Raton, New Mexico. Campbell's mixed parentage was the reverse of Parker's: he had a German-Jewish mother and a Scottish father. She learned that he was [[bisexual]] and later proclaimed in public that he was &quot;[[queer]] as a billy goat&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wallace2012&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Wallace |first=David |title=Capital of the World: A Portrait of New York City in the Roaring Twenties |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ivN7BAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA184 |date=September 4, 2012 |publisher=Lyons Press |isbn=978-0-7627-6819-6 |pages=184–}}&lt;/ref&gt; The pair moved to Hollywood and signed ten-week contracts with [[Paramount Pictures]], with Campbell (who was also expected to act) earning $250 per week and Parker earning $1,000 per week. They would eventually earn $2,000 and in some instances upwards of $5,000 per week as freelancers for various studios.&lt;ref&gt;Silverstein 40&lt;/ref&gt; She and Campbell worked on more than 15 films.&lt;ref&gt;{{IMDb name|0662213|Dorothy Parker}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1936, Parker contributed lyrics for the song &quot;[[I Wished on the Moon]]&quot;, with music by [[Ralph Rainger]]. The song was introduced in ''[[The Big Broadcast of 1936]]'' by [[Bing Crosby]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=The great Hollywood musical pictures |last1=Parish |first1=J.R. |last2=Pitts |first2=M.R. |isbn=978-0-8108-2529-1 |url=https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=bnFZAAAAMAAJ |date=1992 |publisher=[[Scarecrow Press]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

With Campbell and [[Robert Carson (writer)|Robert Carson]], she wrote the script for the 1937 film ''[[A Star Is Born (1937 film)|A Star Is Born]]'', for which they were nominated for an [[Academy Awards|Academy Award]] for Best Writing—Screenplay. She wrote additional dialogue for ''[[The Little Foxes (film)|The Little Foxes]]'' in 1941. Together with Frank Cavett, she received a nomination for an Oscar for the screenplay of ''[[Smash-Up, the Story of a Woman]]'' (1947), starring [[Susan Hayward]].

After the United States entered the Second World War, Parker and [[Alexander Woollcott]] collaborated to produce an anthology of her work as part of a series published by [[Viking Press]] for servicemen stationed overseas. With an introduction by [[W. Somerset Maugham]],&lt;ref&gt;Meade 318&lt;/ref&gt; the volume compiled over two dozen of Parker's short stories, along with selected poems from ''Enough Rope'', ''Sunset Gun'', and ''Death and Taxes''. It was published in the United States in 1944 under the title ''The Portable Dorothy Parker''. Hers is one of three ''Portable'' series, including volumes devoted to [[William Shakespeare]] and The Bible, that have remained in continuous print.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Publisher's Note |title=The Portable Dorothy Parker Revised and Enlarged Edition |publisher=Penguin |year=1976 |location=New York |isbn=0-14-015074-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the 1930s and 1940s, Parker became an increasingly vocal advocate of civil liberties and civil rights, and a frequent critic of authority figures. During the [[Great Depression]], she was among numerous American intellectuals and artists who became involved in related social movements. She reported in 1937 on the [[Republican faction (Spanish Civil War)|Loyalist cause in Spain]] for the Communist magazine, ''[[The New Masses]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Meade 285&lt;/ref&gt; At the behest of [[Otto Katz]], a covert Soviet Comintern agent and operative of German Communist Party agent [[Willi Münzenberg]], Parker helped to found the [[Hollywood Anti-Nazi League]] in 1936, which the FBI suspected of being a Communist Party front.&lt;ref&gt;Koch, Stephen, ''Double Lives: Stalin, Willi Munzenberg and the Seduction of the Intellectuals'', New York: Enigma Books (2004), Revised Edition, {{ISBN|1-929631-20-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Hollywood Anti-Nazi League's membership eventually grew to some 4,000 strong. According to [[David Caute]], its often wealthy members were &quot;able to contribute as much to [Communist] Party funds as the whole American working class&quot;, although they may not have been intending to support the Party cause.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;Caute, David, ''The Fellow Travellers: Intellectual Friends of Communism'', New Haven: Yale University Press (1988), {{ISBN|0-300-04195-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.heretical.com/miscella/munzen.html |title=Michael Newland: Willi Münzenberg's 'Innocents' Clubs' |publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Parker also served as chair of the [[Joint Anti-Fascist Refugee Committee]]'s fundraising arm, &quot;Spanish Refugee Appeal&quot;. She organized Project Rescue Ship to transport Loyalist veterans to Mexico, headed Spanish Children's Relief, and lent her name to many other left-wing causes and organizations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Buhle |first=Paul |author2=Dave Wagner |title=Radical Hollywood: The Untold Story Behind America's Favorite Movies |publisher=The New Press |year=2002 |location=New York |page=89 |isbn=1-56584-718-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; Her former Round Table friends saw less and less of her, and her relationship with Robert Benchley became particularly strained (although they would reconcile).&lt;ref&gt;Altman 314&lt;/ref&gt; Parker met [[S. J. Perelman]] at a party in 1932 and, despite a rocky start (Perelman called it &quot;a scarifying ordeal&quot;),&lt;ref&gt;Perelman 171&lt;/ref&gt; they remained friends for the next 35 years. They became neighbors when the Perelmans helped Parker and Campbell buy a run-down farm in [[Bucks County, Pennsylvania]], near [[New Hope, Pennsylvania|New Hope]], a popular summer destination among many writers and artists from New York.

Parker was listed as a [[Communist]] by the publication ''[[Red Channels]]'' in 1950.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Dorothy ParkerR Writer, Versifier |work=Red Channels: The Report of Communist Influence in Radio and Television |publisher=Counterattack |url=http://www.authentichistory.com/1950s/redchannels/redch115.html |accessdate=2007-09-24 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070807192003/http://www.authentichistory.com/1950s/redchannels/redch115.html |archivedate=2007-08-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[FBI]] compiled a 1,000-page dossier on her because of her suspected involvement in Communism during the era when Senator [[Joseph McCarthy]] was raising alarms about communists in government and Hollywood.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Kunkel |first=Thomas |title=Genius in Disguise: Harold Ross of The New Yorker |publisher=Carrol &amp; Graf |year=1996 |page=[https://archive.org/details/geniusindisguise00kunk/page/405 405] |isbn=0-7867-0323-7 |url=https://archive.org/details/geniusindisguise00kunk/page/405}}&lt;/ref&gt; As a result, movie studio bosses placed her on the [[Hollywood blacklist]]. Her final screenplay was ''[[The Fan (1949 film)|The Fan]]'', a 1949 adaptation of [[Oscar Wilde]]'s ''[[Lady Windermere's Fan]]'', directed by [[Otto Preminger]].

Her marriage to Campbell was tempestuous, with tensions exacerbated by Parker's increasing alcohol consumption and Campbell's long-term affair with a married woman in Europe during [[World War II]].&lt;ref&gt;Meade 327&lt;/ref&gt; They divorced in 1947,&lt;ref&gt;Meade 329&lt;/ref&gt; remarried in 1950,&lt;ref&gt;Meade 339&lt;/ref&gt; then separated in 1952 when Parker moved back to New York.&lt;ref name=&quot;google2&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Mqz2cxXtwEQC&amp;pg=PA41#v=onepage&amp;q=%22East%2074th%22 |author=James Malanowski |title=Dead &amp; Famous; Where the Grim Reaper has Walked in New York |publisher=Spy |date=July 17, 1959 |accessdate=2013-04-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; From 1957 to 1962, she lived at the Volney Residential Hotel on Manhattan's Upper East Side and wrote book reviews for ''[[Esquire magazine]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |last=Itzkovitz |first=Daniel |title=Dorothy Rothschild Parker (1893–1967) |encyclopedia=Jewish Virtual Library |date=May 28, 1998 |url=http://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/biography/parker.html |accessdate=2005-09-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; Her writing became increasingly erratic due to her continued abuse of alcohol. She returned to Hollywood in 1961, reconciled with Campbell, and collaborated with him on a number of unproduced projects until Campbell died from a drug overdose in 1963.&lt;ref&gt;Meade 392–3&lt;/ref&gt;

== Later life and death ==
Following Campbell's death, Parker returned to New York City and the Volney Residential hotel. In her later years, she denigrated the Algonquin Round Table, although it had brought her such early notoriety:
{{Quote | These were no giants. Think who was writing in those days—[[Ring Lardner|Lardner]], [[F. Scott Fitzgerald|Fitzgerald]], [[William Faulkner|Faulkner]] and [[Ernest Hemingway|Hemingway]]. Those were the real giants. The Round Table was just a lot of people telling jokes and telling each other how good they were. Just a bunch of loudmouths showing off, saving their gags for days, waiting for a chance to spring them... There was no truth in anything they said. It was the terrible day of the wisecrack, so there didn't have to be any truth...&lt;ref&gt;Herrmann p. 85.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Parker occasionally participated in radio programs, including ''[[Information Please]]'' (as a guest) and ''Author, Author'' (as a regular panelist). She wrote for the ''[[Columbia Workshop]]'', and both [[Ilka Chase]] and [[Tallulah Bankhead]] used her material for radio monologues.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Dunning |first=John |title=On The Air: The Encyclopedia of Old-Time Radio |publisher=Oxford University Press |year=1998 |isbn=0-19-507678-8 |url=https://archive.org/details/onairencyclop00dunn}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Parker died on June 7, 1967, of a [[myocardial infarction|heart attack]]&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT obit&quot; /&gt; at the age of 73. In her will, she bequeathed her estate to [[Martin Luther King Jr.]] Following King's death, her estate was bequeathed by his family to the [[NAACP]].&lt;ref&gt;Silverstein 59.&lt;/ref&gt; Her [[executor]], [[Lillian Hellman]], bitterly but unsuccessfully contested this disposition.&lt;ref&gt;Meade 413.&lt;/ref&gt; Her ashes remained unclaimed in various places, including her attorney [[Paul O'Dwyer]]'s filing cabinet, for approximately 17 years.&lt;ref&gt;Meade 412.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Posthumous honors ==
In 1988, the NAACP claimed Parker's remains and designed a memorial garden for them outside its Baltimore headquarters.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson, Scott. ''Resting Places: The Burial Sites of More Than 14,000 Famous Persons'', 3d ed.: 2 (Kindle Location 36205). McFarland &amp; Company, Inc., Publishers. Kindle Edition.&lt;/ref&gt; The plaque reads,

{{quote|Here lie the ashes of Dorothy Parker (1893–1967) humorist, writer, critic. Defender of human and civil rights. For her epitaph she suggested, 'Excuse my dust'. This memorial garden is dedicated to her noble spirit which celebrated the oneness of humankind and to the bonds of everlasting friendship between black and Jewish people. Dedicated by the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People. October 28, 1988.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Hitchens |first=Christopher |title=Unacknowledged Legislation: Writers in the Public Sphere |publisher=Verso |year=2000 |location=New York |page=293 |isbn=1-85984-786-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
[[File:Dorothyparkerlandmark.jpg|thumb|Plaque at Parker's birthplace]]
On August 22, 1992, the 99th anniversary of Parker's birth, the [[United States Postal Service]] issued a 29¢ U.S. commemorative [[postage stamp]] in the Literary Arts series. The Algonquin Round Table, as well as the number of other literary and theatrical greats who lodged at the hotel, contributed to the Algonquin Hotel being designated in 1987 as a New York City Historic Landmark.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |last=Heller Anderson |first=Susan |title=City Makes It Official: Algonquin is Landmark |newspaper=The New York Times |date=September 20, 1987 |url=https://www.nytimes.com/1987/09/20/nyregion/city-makes-it-official-algonquin-is-landmark.html |accessdate=2007-10-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1996, the hotel was designated as a National Literary Landmark by the [[Friends of Libraries]] USA, based on the contributions of Parker and other members of the Round Table. The organization's bronze plaque is attached to the front of the hotel.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Friends of Libraries USA |title=1996 dedications |url=http://www.folusa.org/outreach/landmarks-year/1996.php |accessdate=2007-09-13 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080506140823/http://www.folusa.org/outreach/landmarks-year/1996.php |archivedate=May 6, 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Parker's birthplace at the Jersey Shore was also designated a National Literary Landmark by Friends of Libraries USA in 2005&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |work=[[New Jersey Monthly]] |title=The Write Stuff |date=February 7, 2008 |first=Christopher |last=Hann |url=http://njmonthly.com/articles/lifestyle/people/the-write-stuff.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; and a bronze plaque marks the former site of her family house.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Plaque Unveiled at Parker Teenage Home |url=http://dorothyparker.com/2009/08/plaque-unveiled-at-parker-teenage-home.html |website=Dorothyparker.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2014, Parker was elected to the [[New Jersey Hall of Fame]].

== In popular culture ==
Parker inspired a number of fictional characters in several plays of her day. These included &quot;Lily Malone&quot; in [[Philip Barry]]'s ''Hotel Universe'' (1932), &quot;Mary Hilliard&quot; (played by [[Ruth Gordon]]) in George Oppenheimer's ''Here Today'' (1932), &quot;Paula Wharton&quot; in Gordon's 1944 play ''[[Over 21 (play)|Over Twenty-one]]'' (directed by [[George S. Kaufman]]), and &quot;Julia Glenn&quot; in the Kaufman-[[Moss Hart]] collaboration ''[[Merrily We Roll Along (play)|Merrily We Roll Along]]'' (1934). Kaufman's representation of her in ''Merrily We Roll Along'' led Parker, once his Round Table compatriot, to despise him.&lt;ref&gt;Meade 241&lt;/ref&gt; She also was portrayed as &quot;Daisy Lester&quot; in [[Charles Brackett]]'s 1934 novel ''Entirely Surrounded''.&lt;ref&gt;Silverstein 10–11&lt;/ref&gt; She is mentioned in the original introductory lyrics in [[Cole Porter]]'s song &quot;[[Just One of Those Things (song)|Just One of Those Things]]&quot; from the 1935 [[Broadway theatre|Broadway]] musical [[Jubilee (musical)|''Jubilee'']], which have been retained in the standard interpretation of the song as part of the [[Great American Songbook]].

Parker is featured as a character in the novel ''The Dorothy Parker Murder Case'' by [[George Baxt]] (1984), in a series of ''Algonquin Round Table Mysteries'' by J.J. Murphy (2011– ), and in Ellen Meister's novel ''Farewell, Dorothy Parker'' (2013).&lt;ref&gt;Meister, Ellen (2013) ''Farewell, Dorothy Parker''. Putnam Adult.  {{ISBN|039915907X}}&lt;/ref&gt; She is the main character in &quot;Love For Miss Dottie&quot;, a short story by Larry N Mayer, which was selected by writer [[Mary Gaitskill]] for the collection ''Best New American Voices 2009'' (Harcourt).

She has been portrayed on film and television by [[Dolores Sutton]] in ''F. Scott Fitzgerald in Hollywood'' (1976), [[Rosemary Murphy]] in ''[[Julia (1977 film)|Julia]]'' (1977),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine |url=http://www.playbill.com/article/tony-nominee-and-emmy-winner-rosemary-murphy-dies-at-89-com-324377 |title=Tony Nominee and Emmy Winner Rosemary Murphy Dies at 89 |magazine=Playbill |date=July 9, 2014 |author=Simonson, Robert |authorlink1=Robert Simonson}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Bebe Neuwirth]] in ''[[Dash and Lilly]]'' (1999), and [[Jennifer Jason Leigh]] in ''[[Mrs. Parker and the Vicious Circle]]'' (1994). Neuwirth was nominated for an [[Emmy Award]] for her performance, and Leigh received a number of awards and nominations, including a [[Golden Globe]] nomination.

&lt;!-- In the absence of reliable sources that a particular song is in reference to this Dorothy Parker please do not add it. The Prince song is definitely NOT about this Dorothy Parker, as noted on the talk page, and so should not be re-added. --&gt;
Television creator [[Amy Sherman-Palladino]] named her production company '[[Dorothy Parker Drank Here Productions]]' in tribute to Parker.&lt;ref name=Crusie2007&gt;{{cite book |editor=Crusie, Jennifer |year=2007 |title=Coffee at Luke's: An Unauthorized Gilmore Girls Gabfest |chapter=Palladino on naming her company |chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ZWW72Cwfj14C&amp;pg=PA185&amp;lpg=PA185 |page=185 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ZWW72Cwfj14C&amp;printsec=frontcover |place=Dallas |publisher=BenBella Books |isbn=1-933771-17-8 |accessdate=2012-08-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Tucson actress Lesley Abrams wrote and performed the one-woman show ''Dorothy Parker's Last Call'' in 2009 in Tucson, Arizona at the Winding Road Theater Ensemble.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tucsonweekly.com/tucson/shaken-not-stirred/Content?oid=1473209 &quot;Shaken Not Stirred&quot;] Retrieved July 12, 2014.&lt;/ref&gt; She reprised the role at the Live Theatre Workshop in Tucson in 2014.&lt;ref&gt;[http://tucson.com/entertainment/blogs/caliente-tuned-in/last-call-an-energetic-reflection-of-dorothy-parker-s-life/article_bcad569e-fa8e-11e3-ad5f-0019bb2963f4.html &quot;'Last Call' an energetic reflection of Dorothy Parker's life] Retrieved July 12, 2014.&lt;/ref&gt; The play was selected to be part of the Capital Fringe Festival in DC in 2010.&lt;ref&gt;[http://dctheatrescene.com/2010/07/11/dorothy-parkers-last-call &quot;Dorothy Parker's Last Call&quot;] Retrieved July 12, 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2014, lyrics taken from her book of poetry ''Not So Deep as a Well'' were, with the authorization of the [[NAACP]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://tunes.mamabirdrecordingco.com/album/not-so-deep-as-a-well &quot;The composer wishes to thank the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People for authorizing the use of Dorothy Parker's works&quot;.] Retrieved May 21, 2015.&lt;/ref&gt; used by Canadian singer [[Myriam Gendron]] to create a [[Contemporary folk music|folk]] album of the same name.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/montreal/myriam-gendron-inspired-by-dorothy-parker-poems-1.2964068 &quot;Myriam Gendron inspired by Dorothy Parker poems&quot;] Retrieved May 21, 2015.&lt;/ref&gt; Also in 2014, [[Chicago]] [[jazz]] bassist/singer/composer [[Katie Ernst]] issued her album ''Little Words'', consisting of her authorized settings of seven of Parker's poems.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.chicagoreader.com/chicago/katie-ernst-jazz-bass-singer-twin-talk/Content?oid=21877053 |newspaper=[[Chicago Reader]] |author=Margasak, Peter |date=April 26, 2016 |title=Jazz bassist and vocalist Katie Ernst rises like the tide |accessdate=September 4, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite
 |url=https://katieernst.bandcamp.com/album/little-words
 |publisher=Ernst, Katie
 |author=Ernst, Katie
 |date=2014
 |title=Little Words
 |accessdate=September 4, 2017
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2018, American drag queen [[Miz Cracker]] played Parker in the celebrity-impersonation game show episode of the [[RuPaul's Drag Race (season 10)|Season 10]] of ''[[Rupaul's Drag Race]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Duarte |first1=Amanda |title=‘RuPaul’s Drag Race’ Season 10, Episode 7: Citizens Divided |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2018/05/03/arts/television/rupauls-drag-race-season-10-episode-7-recap.html |website=The New York Times |accessdate=May 5, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Bibliography ==

=== Essays and reporting ===

1970 ''Constant Reader''

*{{cite journal |author=Parker, Dorothy |authorlink= |authormask= |date=February 28, 1925 |title=A certain lady |department= |journal=The New Yorker |volume=1 |issue=2 |pages=15–16 |url=|&lt;!--accessdate=--&gt;}}
*{{cite book |last1=Fitzpatrick |first1=Kevin |title=Complete Broadway, 1918–1923 |date=2014 |publisher=iUniverse |isbn=978-1-4917-2267-1 |pages=}} (compilation of reviews, edited by Fitzpatrick; most of these reviews have never been reprinted)&lt;ref name=&quot;gottlieb&quot; /&gt;

=== Collections of short stories ===
1930: ''Laments for the Living''
(includes 13 short stories)

1933: ''After Such Pleasures''
(includes 11 short stories)

1939: ''Here Lies: The Collected Stories of Dorothy Parker''
(reprints of the stories from both previous collections, plus 3 new stories)

1942: ''Collected Stories''

1944: ''The Portable Dorothy Parker'' (reprints of the stories from the previous collections, plus 5 new stories and verse from 3 poetry books)

&lt;ref name=&quot;Academy of American Poets&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Academy of American Poets |url=https://www.poets.org/poetsorg/poet/dorothy-parker |publisher=Academy of American Poets}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Collections of poetry ===
1926: ''Enough Rope''

1928: ''Sunset Gun''

1931: ''Death and Taxes''

1936: ''Collected Poems: Not So Deep as a Well''

1944: ''Collected Poetry''

1996: ''Not Much Fun: The Lost Poems of Dorothy Parker'' (UK title: ''The Uncollected Dorothy Parker'')

2009: ''Not Much Fun: The Lost Poems of Dorothy Parker'' (2nd ed., with additional poems)

&lt;ref name=&quot;Academy of American Poets&quot; /&gt;

=== Plays ===
1929: ''Close Harmony''

1953: ''Ladies of the Corridor''

=== Screenplays ===
1949: [[The Fan (1949 film)|The Fan]]

1942: [[Saboteur (film)|Saboteur]]

1937: [[A Star Is Born (1937 film)|A Star is Born]]

1936: [[Suzy (film)|Suzy]]

1938: [[Sweethearts (1938 film)|Sweethearts]]

1938: [[Trade Winds (film)|Trade Winds]]

1941: [[Week-End for Three]]

1947: [[Smash-Up, the Story of a Woman]]

== See also ==
{{Portal|Poetry}}
* ''[[Dorothy Parker – Complete Stories]]''

== References ==
{{Reflist|30em}}

== Further reading ==
*Randall Calhoun, ''Dorothy Parker: A Bio-Bibliography''. Westport, Connecticut: Greenwood Press, 1993. {{ISBN|0-313-26507-0}}
* [[Kevin C. Fitzpatrick]], [https://books.google.com/books?id=aTyGc_sC4iUC&amp;printsec=frontcover ''A Journey into Dorothy Parker's New York'']. Berkeley, CA: Roaring Forties Press, 2005. {{ISBN|0-9766706-0-7}}
* [[John Keats (writer)|John Keats]], ''You Might As Well Live: The Life and Times of Dorothy Parker''. New York: Simon &amp; Schuster, 1970.
* [[Marion Meade]], ''Dorothy Parker: What Fresh Hell is This?''. New York: Villard, 1988.
* [[S. J. Perelman]], &quot;Dorothy Parker&quot;. In ''The Last Laugh''. New York: Simon &amp; Schuster, 1981.

== External links ==
{{Wikiquote|Dorothy Parker}}
{{Commons|Dorothy Parker}}
{{Library resources box
 |onlinebooks=no
 |by=yes
 |viaf=7395211
 |label=Dorothy Parker}}
* {{cite journal |url=http://www.theparisreview.org/interviews/4933/the-art-of-fiction-no-13-dorothy-parker |work=The Paris Review |title=Dorothy Parker, The Art of Fiction No. 13 |author=Marion Capron |date=Summer 1956}}
* [http://www.dorothyparker.com/ Dorothy Parker Society]
* {{IMDb name|id=0662213}}
* {{IBDB name}}
* {{iobdb name|30790}}
* [http://www.algonquinroundtable.org/ Algonquin Round Table]
* [https://www.poeticous.com/dorothy-parker Dorothy Parker] on Poeticous
* [http://rpo.library.utoronto.ca/poets/parker-dorothy Selected Poems by Dorothy Parker]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20060822081009/http://www.citypaper.com/bob/story.asp?id=10576 Parker's resting place]
* [http://emdashes.com/mt/mt-search.cgi?tag=Dorothy%20Parker Emdashes coverage] of Dorothy Parker
* [http://www.gettyimages.com/photos/dorothy-parker?family=editorial&amp;license=rf&amp;phrase=dorothy%20parker&amp;sort=best&amp;excludenudity=true#license Dorothy Parker photo gallery; GettyImages]

=== Online editions ===
* {{Gutenberg author |id=Parker,+Dorothy | name=Dorothy Parker}}
* {{FadedPage|id=Parker, Dorothy|name=Dorothy Parker|author=yes}}
* {{Internet Archive author |sname=Dorothy Parker |sopt=t}}
* {{Librivox author |id=8152}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20040603194709/http://www.cs.rice.edu/~ssiyer/minstrels/index_poet_P.html Minstrels Archive] section on Parker's works

{{good article}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Parker, Dorothy}}
[[Category:1893 births]]
[[Category:1967 deaths]]
[[Category:20th-century American non-fiction writers]]
[[Category:20th-century American poets]]
[[Category:20th-century American short story writers]]
[[Category:20th-century American women writers]]
[[Category:American anti-fascists]]
[[Category:American humorists]]
[[Category:American people of German-Jewish descent]]
[[Category:American people of Scottish descent]]
[[Category:American satirists]]
[[Category:American socialists]]
[[Category:American women non-fiction writers]]
[[Category:American women poets]]
[[Category:American women screenwriters]]
[[Category:American women short story writers]]
[[Category:Hollywood blacklist]]
[[Category:Journalists from New York City]]
[[Category:O. Henry Award winners]]
[[Category:People from Long Branch, New Jersey]]
[[Category:People from the Upper West Side]]
[[Category:Poets from New Jersey]]
[[Category:Screenwriters from New Jersey]]
[[Category:Screenwriters from New York (state)]]
[[Category:The New Yorker people]]
[[Category:Women satirists]]
[[Category:Writers from New York City]]</text>
      <sha1>phixzjabehmh3v88jowfllv961wrg0u</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
