  <page>
    <title>Fern Hill</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8785</id>
    <revision>
      <id>854571460</id>
      <parentid>845935061</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-08-12T09:06:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Briggstyne</username>
        <id>11932139</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>update</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">'''Fern Hill''' (1945) is a [[poetry|poem]] by [[Dylan Thomas]], first published in the October, 1945, Horizon magazine, with its first book publication as the last poem in ''[[Deaths and Entrances]]''.

The house Fernhill is just outside [[Llangain]] in Carmarthenshire. Thomas had extended stays here in the 1920s with his aunt Annie and her husband, Jim Jones, and wrote about the house in his short story, ''The Peaches''. His holidays here have been recalled in interviews with his schoolboy friends, and both the house and the Thomas family network in the area are detailed in the same book.&lt;ref&gt;''Dylan Remembered 1914-34,'' vol 1, by D N Thomas, Seren 2003&lt;/ref&gt; A further account describes both Thomas’ childhood and later years on the family farms between Llangain and [[Llansteffan]], as well as questioning whether the poem Fern Hill was inspired by the house Fernhill.&lt;ref&gt;''A True Childhood: Dylan’s Peninsularity'' by D. N. Thomas in ''Dylan Thomas: A Centenary Celebration'' ed. H. Ellis, Bloomsbury, 2014&lt;/ref&gt; 

==Linguistic considerations==

The poem starts as a straightforward evocation of his childhood visits to his Aunt Annie's farm:
:Now as I was young and easy under the apple boughs
:About the lilting house and happy as the grass was green,
:The night above the dingle starry,

In the middle section, the idyllic scene is expanded upon, reinforced by the lilting rhythm of the poem, the dreamlike, [[pastoral]] metaphors and allusion to [[Garden of Eden|Eden]].  
:All the sun long it was running, it was lovely, the hay
:Fields high as the house, the tunes from the chimneys, it was air...
:With the dew, come back, the cock on his shoulder: it was all
:Shining, it was Adam and maiden,

By the end, the poet's older voice has taken over, mourning his lost youth with echoes of the opening:
:Oh as I was young and easy in the mercy of his means,
:Time held me green and dying
:Though I sang in my chains like the sea.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/wales/arts/sites/themes/books/dylan_thomas.shtml Dylan Thomas] on BBC Wales Arts page&lt;/ref&gt;

The poem uses [[Internal rhyme|internal]] [[half rhyme]] and [[full rhyme]] as well as [[end rhyme]]. Thomas was very conscious of the effect of spoken or intoned verse and explored the potentialities of sound and rhythm, in a manner reminiscent of [[Gerard Manley Hopkins]]. He always denied having conscious knowledge of [[Welsh language|Welsh]], but &quot;his lines chime with internal consonantal correspondence, or ''[[cynghanedd]]'', a prescribed feature of Welsh versification&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Seymour H [https://books.google.com/books?id=kuUKoVypTcIC&amp;pg=PA255&amp;vq=Fern+Hill&amp;source=gbs_search_r&amp;cad=0_1#PPA255,M1 Sound and Form in Modern Poetry] page 255&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy==
''Fern Hill'' has been set to music by the American composer [[John Corigliano]], for [[SATB]] chorus with orchestral accompaniment.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.providencesingers.org/Concerts06/Season06-07/Mar07Corigliano.php Providence Singers] Musical background notes&lt;/ref&gt;

Samples of the ''Fern Hill'' poem read by Dylan Thomas himself are used in the track ''Apple Towns''&lt;ref&gt;[https://reflectionnebula.bandcamp.com/track/apple-towns Apple Towns]&lt;/ref&gt; by the one-man act ''Reflection Nebula''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.chimeshall.com/ Reflection Nebula]&lt;/ref&gt;

''[[Happy as the Grass Was Green]]'' became the title of a 1973 [[Drama (film and television)|drama film]].

==References==
&lt;references /&gt;

==External links==
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20080129234808/http://www.undermilkwood.net/index.html The Life and Work of Dylan Thomas (archive)]

{{Dylan Thomas}}

[[Category:Anglo-Welsh literature]]
[[Category:Welsh poems]]
[[Category:Works by Dylan Thomas]]</text>
      <sha1>fdeuwznfnx4lf78ekj28kuj3dpdh2nq</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
