  <page>
    <title>Darwin Awards</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8703</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943293843</id>
      <parentid>943293798</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-03-01T01:42:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>2406:E003:1002:5901:8F1:142C:BDF3:3CFD</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Corrected spelling mistakes and grammatical errors.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{About||the Royal Society award|Darwin Medal|the 2006 film|The Darwin Awards (film)}}
{{Infobox website
| name             = Darwin Awards
| logo             = Darwinaward.png
| screenshot       = 
| caption          = 
| url              = {{url|http://www.darwinawards.com/}}
| commercial       = Yes
| type             = [[Humor]]
| language         = [[English language|English]]
| owner            = Wendy Northcutt
| launch_date      = 1993
| alexa            = {{DecreasePositive}} 168,456 {{small|{{nowrap|(Global, {{as of|2018|05|01|alt=May 2018}})}}}}&lt;ref name=&quot;alexa_ranking&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Statistics Summary for darwinawards.com |url=http://www.alexa.com/siteinfo/darwinawards.com|publisher=[[Alexa Internet]]|accessdate=May 2, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| footnotes      = 
}}
The '''Darwin Awards''' are a [[tongue-in-cheek]] honour, originating in [[Usenet]] newsgroup discussions around 1985. They recognise individuals who have supposedly contributed to human [[evolution]] by [[natural selection|selecting]] themselves out of the [[gene pool]] via [[death]] or [[Sterilization (medicine)|sterilisation]] by their own actions.

The project became more formalized with the creation of a [[website]] in 1993, and followed up by a series of [[book]]s starting in 2000, authored by Wendy Northcutt. The criterion for the awards states, &quot;In the spirit of [[Charles Darwin]], the Darwin Awards commemorate individuals who protect our gene pool by making the ultimate sacrifice of their own lives. Darwin Award winners [[list of unusual deaths|eliminate themselves in an extraordinarily idiotic manner]], thereby improving our species' chances of long-term survival.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;history_and_rules&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Northcutt|first=Wendy|title=History &amp; Rules|url=http://www.darwinawards.com/rules/rules1.html|publisher=www.darwinawards.com|accessdate=August 14, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Accidental self-sterilisation also qualifies; however, the site notes: &quot;Of necessity, the award is usually bestowed posthumously.&quot; The candidate is disqualified, though, if &quot;innocent bystanders&quot;, who might have contributed positively to the gene pool, are killed in the process. The logical problem presented by award winners who may have already reproduced is not addressed in the selection process due to the difficulty of ascertaining if a person has or does not have children; the Darwin Award rules state that the presence of offspring does not disqualify a nominee&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://darwinawards.com/rules/rules.children.html|title=Darwin Awards: History and Rules|website=darwinawards.com|access-date=2020-02-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;.

People who have somehow miraculously survived their suicidal idiocy can be given an &quot;Honourable Mention&quot; if their attempted act of self removal is deemed worthy (and humorous), i.e. they tried their best.

The Darwin Awards books state that an attempt is made to disallow known [[urban legend]]s from the awards, but some older &quot;winners&quot; have been &quot;[[Grandfather clause|grandfathered]]&quot; to keep their awards. The Darwin Awards site does try to verify all submitted stories, but many similar sites, and the vast number of circulating &quot;Darwin awards&quot; emails, are largely fictional.

== History ==
[[File:Wendy Northcutt.jpg|thumb|right|Wendy Northcutt, author of the Darwin Awards website and books]]
The origin of the Darwin Awards can be traced back to posts on [[Usenet]] group discussions as early as 1985. An early post, on August 7, 1985, describes the awards as being, &quot;given posthumously to people who have made the supreme sacrifice to keep their genes out of our [[gene pool|pool]]. Style counts, not everyone who dies from their own stupidity can win.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Freeman_Andy&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Freeman|first=Andy|title=Darwin Awards.|url=https://groups.google.com/forum/?fromgroups#!msg/net.bizarre/V5o__gcmIf0/fZ5sv2BvzAsJ%5B1-25%5D|accessdate=August 14, 2012|newspaper=[[Google groups]] archive of net.bizarre.|date=August 7, 1985}}&lt;/ref&gt; This early post cites an example of a person who pulled a [[vending machine]] over his head and was crushed to death trying to break into it.&lt;ref name=&quot;Freeman_Andy&quot; /&gt; Another widely distributed early story mentioning the Darwin Awards is the [[JATO Rocket Car]], which describes a man who strapped a [[JATO|jet-assisted take-off]] unit to his [[Chevrolet Impala]] in the [[Arizona]] desert and who died on the side of a cliff as his car achieved speeds of {{convert|250|to|300|mph}}. This story was later confirmed to be an urban legend by the Arizona Department of Public Safety.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mikkelson_Barbara&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Mikkelson|first=Barbara|title=Carmageddon.|url=http://www.snopes.com/autos/dream/jato.asp|accessdate=August 14, 2012|newspaper=[[Snopes]]|date=November 12, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; The official Darwin Awards website run by Northcutt does its best to confirm all stories submitted, listing them as, &quot;confirmed true by Darwin.&quot; Many of the [[viral email]]s circulating the [[Internet]], however, are hoaxes and urban legends.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mikkelson_Barbara_2&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Mikkelson|first=Barbara|title=2004 Darwin Awards.|url=http://www.snopes.com/horrors/freakish/darwin04.asp|accessdate=August 14, 2012|newspaper=[[Snopes]]|date=July 3, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The website and collection of books were started in 1993 by Wendy Northcutt, who at the time was a graduate in [[molecular biology]] from the [[University of California, Berkeley]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Rice_Stanley&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Rice|first=Stanley A.|title=Encyclopedia of Evolution|chapter=Darwin Awards|year=2007|publisher=Facts on File|location=New York|isbn=978-0-8160-5515-9|page=[https://archive.org/details/encyclopediaofev0000rice/page/108 108]|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=YRcAVvmE6eMC&amp;pg=PA108|url=https://archive.org/details/encyclopediaofev0000rice/page/108}}&lt;/ref&gt; She went on to study [[neurobiology]] at [[Stanford University]], doing research on [[cancer]] and [[telomerase]]. In her spare time, she organised [[chain letter]]s from family members into the original Darwin Awards website hosted in her personal account space at  Stanford. She eventually left the bench in 1998 and devoted herself full-time to her website and books in September 1999.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hawkins_John&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Hawkins |first=John |title=A Conversation with Darwin (Webmaster of the Darwin Awards). |url=http://www.rightwingnews.com/interviews/darwin.php |accessdate=August 14, 2012 |newspaper=Right Wing News |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120622054043/http://www.rightwingnews.com/interviews/darwin.php |archivedate=June 22, 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt; By 2002, the website received 7 million page hits per month.&lt;ref name=&quot;Clark_Doug&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Clark |first=Doug |title=Let's hear it for natural selection. |url=http://www.spokesmanreview.com/news-story.asp?date=111402&amp;ID=s1253392 |accessdate=September 18, 2012 |newspaper=[[The Spokesman-Review]] |date=November 14, 2002 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131203052123/http://www.spokesmanreview.com/news-story.asp?date=111402&amp;ID=s1253392 |archivedate=December 3, 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

She encountered some difficulty in publishing the first book, since most publishers would only offer her a deal if she agreed to remove the stories from the internet. Northcutt refused to do so, saying, &quot;It was a community! I could not do that. Even though it might have cost me a lot of money, I kept saying no.&quot; She eventually found a publisher who agreed to print a book containing only 10% of the material gathered for the website. The first book turned out to be a success, and was listed on ''[[The New York Times]]'' best-seller list for six months.&lt;ref name=&quot;John_123reg&quot;&gt;{{cite news|author=John|title=Pet porn, rocket cars and hand grenades.|url=http://www.123-reg.co.uk/blog/interviews/darwin-awards-pet-porn-and-hand-grenades/|accessdate=August 31, 2012|newspaper=123-reg|date=April 14, 2008|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120831004041/http://www.123-reg.co.uk/blog/interviews/darwin-awards-pet-porn-and-hand-grenades/|archive-date=August 31, 2012|url-status=dead|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Not all of the feedback from the stories Northcutt published was positive, and she occasionally received email from people who knew the deceased. One such person wrote, &quot;This is horrible. It has shocked our community to the core. You should remove this.&quot; But Northcutt said &quot;I can't. It's just too stupid.&quot; Northcutt kept the stories on the website and in her books, citing them as a &quot;funny-but-true safety guide&quot;, and mentioning that children who read the book are going to be much more careful around explosives.&lt;ref name=&quot;CNN_interview&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title='Darwin Awards' author dedicated to documenting macabre mishaps. |url=http://articles.cnn.com/2001-01-03/entertainment/darwin.awards_1_deaths-darwin-award-wendy-northcutt |archive-url=https://archive.is/20130119105342/http://articles.cnn.com/2001-01-03/entertainment/darwin.awards_1_deaths-darwin-award-wendy-northcutt |url-status=dead |archive-date=January 19, 2013 |accessdate=September 18, 2012 |newspaper=[[CNN]] |date=January 3, 2001 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The website also recognises, with Honourable Mentions, individuals who survive their misadventures with their reproductive capacity intact. One example of this is [[Larry Walters|Lawnchair Larry]], who attached [[helium]]-filled [[weather balloon]]s to a lawn chair and floated far above [[Long Beach, California]], in July 1982. He reached an altitude of {{convert|16000|ft|m}} but survived, to be later fined for crossing [[controlled airspace]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Greany_Walker_Hecht&quot;&gt;{{cite news |authors=Greany, Ed; Walker, Douglas; Hecht, Walter |title=Lawn Chair Larry |url=http://darwinawards.com/stupid/stupid1998-11.html |accessdate=August 14, 2012 |newspaper=www.darwinawards.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another notable honourable mention was given to the two men who attempted to burgle the home of footballer [[Duncan Ferguson]] (who had four convictions for assault and had served six months in Glasgow's [[Barlinnie Prison]]) in 2001, with one burglar requiring three days' hospitalisation after being confronted by the player.&lt;ref name=&quot;McSean_Nash&quot;&gt;{{cite news |authors=McSean, Tony; Nash, Pete |title=Ferguson 2, Thieves 0 |url=http://darwinawards.com/stupid/stupid2001-04.html |accessdate=August 14, 2012 |publisher=www.darwinawards.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Lendrem et al.-2014-Figure 1-The Darwin Awards sex differences in idiotic behavior.jpg|thumb|right|alt=Figure charting sex differences between Darwin Award winners, 1995–2014 |&quot;Male and female Darwin Award winners. Line H&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt; indicates expected percentages under the null hypothesis that males and females are equally idiotic.&quot; &lt;ref name=Lendrem /&gt;]]
A 2014 study published in the [[British Medical Journal]] found that between 1995 and 2014 males represented 88.7% of Darwin Award winners (see figure).&lt;ref name=Lendrem&gt;{{Cite journal| doi=10.1136/bmj.g7094 |volume=349 |pages=g7094 |last1=Lendrem |first1=Ben Alexander Daniel |last2=Lendrem |first2=Dennis William |last3=Gray |first3=Andy |last4=Isaacs |first4=John Dudley |title=The Darwin Awards: sex differences in idiotic behaviour |journal=BMJ |date=December 11, 2014 |url=http://www.bmj.com/content/349/bmj.g7094 |pmid=25500113 |accessdate=August 12, 2016 |pmc=4263959}}{{open access}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2006 [[comedy film]], ''[[The Darwin Awards (film)|The Darwin Awards]]'', written and directed by [[Finn Taylor]], was based on the website and many of the Darwin Awards stories.

== Rules ==
Northcutt has stated five requirements for a Darwin Award:&lt;ref name=&quot;history_and_rules&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hansen_Suzy&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Hansen |first=Suzy |title=The Darwin Awards |url=http://www.salon.com/2000/11/10/northcutt/ |accessdate=September 18, 2012 |newspaper=[[Salon (website)|Salon]] |date=November 10, 2000}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Inability to reproduce ===
;Nominee must be dead or rendered sterile
This may be subject to dispute. Potential awardees may be out of the gene pool because of age; others have already reproduced before their deaths. To avoid debates about the possibility of [[in-vitro fertilization]], [[artificial insemination]], or [[human cloning|cloning]], the original Darwin Awards book applied the following &quot;deserted island&quot; test to potential winners: If the person were unable to reproduce when stranded on a deserted island with a fertile member of the opposite sex, he or she would be considered sterile.&lt;ref name=&quot;book_one&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Northcutt |first=Wendy |title=The Darwin Awards: Evolution in Action |year=2000 |publisher=PLUME (The Penguin Group) |location=[[New York City]] |isbn=978-0-525-94572-7 |pages=2–6 |url=https://books.google.com/?id=Cowke97r_IkC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=darwin+awards#v=onepage&amp;q=darwin%20awards&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt; Winners of the award, in general, either are dead or have become unable to use their [[sexual organs]].

=== Excellence ===
;Astoundingly stupid judgement
The candidate's foolishness must be unique and sensational, likely because the award is intended to be funny. A number of foolish but common activities, such as smoking in bed, are excluded from consideration. In contrast, [[self-immolation]] caused by smoking after being administered a flammable ointment in a hospital and specifically told not to smoke is grounds for nomination.&lt;ref name=&quot;stubbed_out&quot;&gt;{{cite web |author1=C.J. |author2=Malcolm, Andrew |author3=Sims, Iain |author4=Beeston, Richard. |title=Stubbed Out |url=http://darwinawards.com/darwin/darwin2006-06.html |publisher=www.darwinawards.com |accessdate=August 15, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; One &quot;Honourable Mention&quot; (a man who attempted suicide by swallowing [[Glyceryl trinitrate (pharmacology)|nitroglycerine pills]], and then tried to detonate them by running into a wall) is noted to be in this category, despite being intentional and self-inflicted (i.e. attempted [[suicide]]), which would normally disqualify the inductee.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cawcutt_Tom&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last=Cawcutt |first=Tom |title=Phenomenal Failure |url=http://darwinawards.com/stupid/stupid2001-24.html |publisher=www.darwinawards.com |accessdate=August 15, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Self-selection ===
;Cause of one's own demise
Killing a friend with a [[hand grenade]] would not be eligible, but killing oneself while manufacturing a home made [[chimney]]-cleaning device from a grenade would be eligible.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Northcutt, Wendy |title=Chimney-Cleaning Grenade |url=http://darwinawards.com/darwin/darwin2005-09.html |publisher=www.darwinawards.com |year=2005 |accessdate=August 15, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; To earn a Darwin Award, one must have killed oneself, or rendered oneself sterile; merely causing death to a third party is insufficient.

=== Maturity ===
;Capable of sound judgement
The nominee must be at least past the legal driving age and free of [[intellectual disability|mental defect]] (Northcutt considers injury or death caused by mental defect to be tragic, rather than amusing, and routinely disqualifies such entries). After much discussion, a small category regarding deaths below this age limit also exists. Entry into this category requires that the peers of the candidate be of the opinion that the actions of the person in question were above and beyond the limits of reason.

However, in 2011, the awards targeted a 16-year-old boy in Leeds who died stealing copper wiring (the standard minimum driving age in Great Britain being 17). In 2012, Northcutt made similar light of a 14-year-old girl in Brazil who was killed while leaning out of a school bus window; however, she was &quot;disqualified&quot; for the award itself because of the likely public objection due to the girl's age, which Northcutt asserts is based on &quot;[[magical thinking]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://homoeconomicusnet.wordpress.com/2012/12/10/darwin-awards-2012-too-young-to-include/|title=Darwin Awards 2012 – too young to include?|date=10 December 2012|publisher=|accessdate=4 June 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Veracity ===
;Event must be verified
The story must be documented by reliable sources: e.g., reputable newspaper articles, confirmed television reports, or responsible eyewitnesses. If a story is found to be untrue, it is disqualified, but particularly amusing ones are placed in the [[urban legend]] section of the archives. Despite this requirement, many of the stories are fictional{{Citation needed|reason=Darwin Awards is not Wikipedia|date=December 2018}}, often appearing as &quot;original submissions&quot; and presenting no further sources than unverified (and unreliable{{Citation needed|reason=Wikipedia is not Darwin Awards (yes really)|date=December 2018}}) &quot;eyewitnesses&quot;. Most such stories on Northcutt's Darwin Awards site are filed in the Personal Accounts section.

=== Rules under development ===
In addition, later revisions to the qualification criteria add several requirements that have not been made into formalised ‘rules’:
* Innocent bystanders cannot be endangered.
* The qualifying event ''must'' be caused without deliberate intent to end the nominee's own life (or fertility). (To discourage notoriety-seekers from injuring themselves purposely, to win a Darwin, despite the evident benefit of such individuals exiting the gene pool.)

== Books ==
* {{cite book |last = Northcutt |first = Wendy |title = The Darwin Awards: Evolution in Action |year =  2000 |publisher = Plume |location = New York City |isbn = 978-0-525-94572-7}}
* {{cite book |last = Northcutt |first = Wendy |title = The Darwin Awards II: Unnatural Selection |year =  2001 |publisher = Plume  |location = New York City |isbn = 978-1-101-21896-9}}
* {{cite book |last = Northcutt |first = Wendy |title = The Darwin Awards 3: Survival of the Fittest |year = 2003 |publisher = Plume |location = New York City |isbn = 978-0-525-94773-8 |url-access = registration |url = https://archive.org/details/darwinawards3sur00nort }}
* {{cite book |last = Northcutt |first = Wendy |title = The Darwin Awards: The Descent of Man |year =  2005 |publisher = Running Press Miniature Editions |isbn = 978-0-7624-2561-7}}
* {{cite book |last = Northcutt |first = Wendy |title = The Darwin Awards: Felonious Failures |year =  2005 |publisher = Running Press Miniature Editions |isbn = 978-0-7624-2562-4}}
* {{cite book |last = Northcutt |first = Wendy |title = The Darwin Awards 4: Intelligent Design |url = https://archive.org/details/isbn_9780525949602 |url-access = registration |year =  2006 |publisher = Dutton |location = New York City |isbn = 978-1-101-21892-1}}
* {{cite book |last = Northcutt |first = Wendy |title = The Darwin Awards V: Next Evolution |year =  2008 |publisher = Dutton  |location = New York City |isbn = 978-0-14-301033-3}}
* {{cite book |last = Northcutt |first = Wendy |title = The Darwin Awards Next Evolution: Chlorinating the Gene Pool |url = https://archive.org/details/darwinawardsnext00nort |url-access = registration |year =  2008 |publisher = Dutton  |location = New York City |isbn = 978-1-4406-3677-6}}
* {{cite book |last = Northcutt |first = Wendy |title = The Darwin Awards: Countdown to Extinction |url = https://archive.org/details/darwinawardscoun00nort |url-access = registration |year =  2010 |publisher = Dutton  |location = New York City |isbn = 978-1-101-44465-8}}

== See also ==
* [[Accident-proneness]]
* [[List of inventors killed by their own inventions]]
* [[List of preventable causes of death]]
* [[List of selfie-related injuries and deaths]]
* [[List of unusual deaths]]
* [[Just-world hypothesis]]
* [[Schadenfreude]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
{{Wikinews|2007 Darwin Award winners announced}}
* {{Official website|http://www.darwinawards.com/}}

{{Darwin|state=collapsed}}

[[Category:American comedy websites]]
[[Category:Ironic and humorous awards]]
[[Category:Incompetence]]
[[Category:Black comedy]]
[[Category:Internet properties established in 1993]]
[[Category:Awards established in 1993]]
[[Category:1993 establishments in the United States]]
[[Category:Evolution]]</text>
      <sha1>5616rvusn3kz6oky1619455vdstq0d1</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
