  <page>
    <title>Daniel Ortega</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8778</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943303749</id>
      <parentid>942613965</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-03-01T03:10:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>KolbertBot</username>
        <id>31691822</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[User:KolbertBot#Tasks|Task #2]] : Remove link referral data</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|President of Nicaragua}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=June 2018}}
{{Spanish name|Ortega|Saavedra}}
{{Format footnotes|date=October 2018}}
{{Infobox officeholder
| name = Daniel Ortega
| office = President of Nicaragua
| order = 58th and 62nd
| bodyclass = 
| mainwidth = 
| native_name = 
| image = Ortega Lula - ABr 28.07.20102225 (cropped).JPG
| caption = Daniel Ortega in 2010
| predecessor = [[Enrique Bolaños]]
| successor = 
| vicepresident = [[Jaime Morales Carazo]] (2007–12)&lt;br /&gt;[[Moises Omar Halleslevens Acevedo|Moisés Omar Halleslevens]] (2012–17)&lt;br /&gt;[[Rosario Murillo]] (2017–present)
| office2 = Coordinator of the [[Junta of National Reconstruction|Junta of National Reconstruction of Nicaragua]]
| predecessor2 = [[Francisco Urcuyo]] {{small|(Acting President)}}
| party = [[Sandinista National Liberation Front|FSLN]]
| predecessor1 = [[Anastasio Somoza Debayle]]
| successor1 = [[Violeta Chamorro]]
| vicepresident1 = [[Sergio Ramírez|Sergio Ramírez Mercado]] (1985–90)
| successor2 = Himself {{small|(President)}}
| birth_name = José Daniel Ortega Saavedra
| birth_date = {{birth date and age|1945|11|11}}
| birth_place = [[La Libertad, Chontales|La Libertad]], [[Nicaragua]]
| spouse = {{marriage|[[Rosario Murillo]]|2005}}
| children = 15
| term_start = January 10, 2007
| term_end = 
| term_start1 = June 16, 1979
| term_end1 = April 25, 1990
| term_start2 = July 18, 1979
| term_end2 = January 10, 1985
}}
'''José Daniel Ortega Saavedra''' ({{IPA-es|daˈnjel oɾˈteɣa}}; born November 11, 1945) is a Nicaraguan politician serving as [[President of Nicaragua]] since 2007; previously he was leader of Nicaragua from 1979 to 1990, first as Coordinator of the [[Junta of National Reconstruction]] (1979–1985) and then as President (1985–1990). A leader in the [[Sandinista National Liberation Front]] ({{lang-es|Frente Sandinista de Liberación Nacional}}, ''FSLN''), his policies in government have seen the implementation of leftist reforms across Nicaragua.

Born into a working-class family, from an early age Ortega opposed ruling President [[Anastasio Somoza Debayle]], widely recognized as a [[dictator]], and became involved in the underground movement against his regime. Joining the Sandinistas as a student in 1963, Ortega's urban resistance activities led to his arrest in 1967.&lt;ref name=&quot;:112&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title=Ortega Saavedra, Daniel|last=|first=|work=The Hutchinson Unabridged Encyclopedia with Atlas and Weather Guide|publisher=Helicon|year=2016|isbn=|editor-last=Helicon|location=Abington|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt; After his release in 1974, he also travelled to Cuba to receive training in [[guerrilla warfare]] from [[Fidel Castro]]'s [[Marxism-Leninism|Marxist–Leninist]] government. He played a crucial role in forming the Insurrectionist faction, which united the FSLN and sparked the mass uprisings of 1978-1979.&lt;ref name=&quot;:72&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title=Ortega, Daniel|last=|first=|work=Encyclopedia of Nationalism: Leaders, Movements, and Concepts|publisher=Elsevier Science &amp; Technology|year=2000|isbn=|editor-last=Motyl|editor-first=Alexander|location=Oxford|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt; After the [[Nicaraguan Revolution]] resulted in the overthrow and exile of Somoza's government, Ortega became leader of the ruling multipartisan [[Junta of National Reconstruction]]. In 1984, Ortega, the FSLN candidate, won Nicaragua's free presidential election with over 60 percent of the vote.&lt;ref name=&quot;:112&quot;/&gt; A Marxist–Leninist, his first period in office was characterized by a controversial program of nationalization, [[land reform]], [[wealth redistribution]] and [[Nicaraguan Literacy Campaign|literacy programs]].

Ortega's relationship with the United States was never very cordial, due to U.S. support for Somoza prior to the revolution.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=McClintock|first=Michael|title=The American Connection|year=1987}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Chomsky&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Chomsky|first=Noam|title=Turning the Tide|url=https://archive.org/details/turningtideusint00chom|url-access=registration|year=1985|publisher=South End Press|location=Boston, Massachusetts}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although the U.S. supplied post-revolution Nicaragua with tens of millions of dollars in economic aid,&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.nytimes.com/1981/04/02/world/us-halts-economic-aid-to-nicaragua.html &quot;U.S. halts economic aid to Nicaragua&quot;], ''The New York Times'', April 2, 1981.&lt;/ref&gt; relations broke down when the Sandinistas supplied weapons to leftist Salvadoran rebels (something which Ortega later admitted occurred).&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.nytimes.com/1988/11/24/world/salvador-rebels-where-do-they-get-the-arms.html &quot;Salvador Rebels: Where Do They Get the Arms&quot;], ''The New York Times'', November 24, 1988,&lt;/ref&gt; His government was opposed by the [[Contras]] in a vicious civil war; the Contras were funded by the [[Reagan administration]] of the United States. A joint peace proposal by the Democratic Speaker of the House [[Jim Wright]] and Ronald Reagan helped precipitate a peace agreement at a meeting of five Central American chiefs of state in July 1987, which won Costa Rican President [[Óscar Arias]] the Nobel Peace Prize. This led to free elections in which Ortega was defeated by [[Violeta Chamorro]] in the [[1990 Nicaraguan general election|1990 presidential election]], but he remained an important figure in Nicaraguan opposition politics, gradually moderating in his political position from Marxism–Leninism to [[democratic socialism]]. He also restored relations with the [[Catholic Church]], with the adoption of [[anti-abortion]] policies by his government.

Ortega was an unsuccessful candidate for president in 1996 and 2001, before winning the [[2006 Nicaraguan general election|2006 presidential election]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/americas/6117704.stm &quot;Ortega wins Nicaraguan election&quot;], BBC News, November 8, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; In office, he made alliances with fellow Latin American socialists, such as Venezuelan President [[Hugo Chávez]], and under his leadership, Nicaragua joined the [[Bolivarian Alliance for the Americas]].

As of June 2018, [[Amnesty International]] and the [[Inter-American Commission on Human Rights|IACHR]] of the [[Organization of American States]] have reported that Ortega has engaged in a violent oppression campaign against protesters in response to [[2018–2019 Nicaraguan protests|anti-Ortega protests since April 2018]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Amnesty&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.amnesty.org/en/documents/amr43/8470/2018/en/|title=Shoot to kill: Nicaragua's strategy to repress protest|last=|first=|date=29 May 2018|publisher=[[Amnesty International]] |access-date=2018-06-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite press release|title=IACHR Condemns Increased Violence in Nicaragua|date=June 13, 2018|location=Washington, D.C.|url=http://www.oas.org/en/iachr/media_center/PReleases/2018/128.asp|last1=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt;|agency=Organization of American States|access-date=2018-06-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; while government officials and government-owned media have denied such actions.

==Early life==
Ortega was born in [[La Libertad, Chontales|La Libertad]], department of [[Chontales Department|Chontales]], [[Nicaragua]]. His parents, Daniel Ortega Cerda and Lidia Saavedra, were opposed  to the regime of [[Anastasio Somoza Debayle]]. His mother was imprisoned by Somoza's National Guard for being in possession of &quot;love letters&quot; which the police stated were coded political missives. Ortega and his two brothers, [[Humberto Ortega]], former [[general]], military leader, and published writer, and Camilo Ortega, grew to become revolutionaries. He had a sister named Germania who is deceased.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://diario.lajornadanet.com/archivo/2005/mayo/05_05_05.html|title=La Jornada – Jueves, 5 de Mayo de 2005|work=lajornadanet.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;PANAM16&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Meet Daniel Ortega, Nicaragua's Rising Dictator|url=https://panampost.com/editor/2016/08/16/meet-daniel-ortega-nicaraguas-rising-dictator/|accessdate=November 4, 2017|work=[[PanAm Post]]|date=August 16, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The search for stable employment took the family from [[La Libertad, Chontales|La Libertad]] to the provincial capital of [[Juigalpa, Chontales|Juigalpa]], and then on to a working-class neighborhood in Managua.{{sfn|Kinzer|1991|p=186}} Daniel Ortega Cedra detested U.S. military intervention in Nicaragua and Washington's support for the [[Somoza family|Somoza]] dictatorship, and he imparted the anti-American sentiment to his sons.{{sfn|Kinzer|1991|p=186}}

Ortega was arrested for political activities at the age of 15,&lt;ref name=&quot;RT&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|title=Five facts about Nicaragua's Daniel Ortega |url=http://www.alertnet.org/thenews/newsdesk/N01359367.htm |work=Reuters|accessdate=2008-01-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; and quickly joined the then-underground [[Sandinista National Liberation Front]] (FSLN).&lt;ref name=&quot;LP&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|title=Daniel Ortega Saavedra, candidato presidencial del FSLN |date=2007-05-10 |url=http://www-ni.laprensa.com.ni/archivo/2006/septiembre/15/elecciones/candidatos/143891.shtml |work=La Prensa |accessdate=2007-05-11 |language=Spanish |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070520180905/http://www-ni.laprensa.com.ni/archivo/2006/septiembre/15/elecciones/candidatos/143891.shtml |archivedate=2007-05-20 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1964, Ortega travelled to [[Guatemala]], where the police arrested him and turned him over to the [[Nicaraguan National Guard]].{{sfn|Kinzer|1991|p=187}} After his release from detainment, Ortega arranged the assassination of his torturer, Guardsman Gonzalo Lacayo, in August 1967.{{sfn|Kinzer|1991|p=187}} He was imprisoned in 1967 for taking part in [[bank robbery|robbing]] a branch of the [[Bank of America]] while brandishing a machine gun, telling collaborators that they should be killed if they did not partake in the robbery.&lt;ref name=&quot;PANAM16&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;LO&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.commondreams.org/views01/0902-05.htm|title=Nicaragua's Daniel Ortega; In the Lions' Den Again|last=Vulliamy|first=Ed|date=September 2, 2001|work=The Observer|accessdate=2008-01-15|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071223093439/http://www.commondreams.org/views01/0902-05.htm|archivedate=2007-12-23|url-status=dead|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ortega was released in late 1974 along with other Sandinista prisoners in exchange for [[Somocista]] hostages. While he was imprisoned at the El Modelo jail, just outside [[Managua]], he wrote poems, one of which he titled ''&quot;I Never Saw Managua When Miniskirts Were in Fashion&quot;''.&lt;ref name=&quot;LO&quot;/&gt; During his imprisonment, Ortega was severely tortured.&lt;ref&gt;[[Bernard Diederich]], ''Somoza and the Legacy of U.S. Involvement in Central America'', p. 85.&lt;/ref&gt; While at El Modelo, his mother helped stage protests and hunger strikes for political prisoners, which improved the treatment of incarcerated Sandinistas.{{sfn|Kinzer|1991|p=188}} After his release, Ortega was exiled to [[Cuba]], where he received several months of [[guerrilla]] training. He later returned to Nicaragua secretly.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|first= |last= |title=Hispanic Heritage in the Americas: Ortega, Daniel |date= |publisher= |url=http://www.britannica.com/hispanic_heritage/article-9057473 |work=Encyclopædia Britannica |pages= |accessdate=2007-05-11 |language=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the late 1970s, divisions over the FSLN's campaign against Somoza led Daniel and [[Humberto Ortega]] to form the Insurrectionist, or Tercerista (Third Way) faction.&lt;ref name=&quot;:72&quot;/&gt; The Terceristas sought to combine the distinct guerrilla war strategies of the two other factions, [[Tomás Borge|Tomas Borge's]] Guerra Prolongada Popular (GPP or Prolonged People's War), and [[Jaime Wheelock|Jaime Wheelock's]] Proletarians.&lt;ref name=&quot;FSLNPostCollapse&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Perez|first=Andres|date=1992|title=The FSLN after the Debacle: The Struggle for the Definition of Sandinismo|jstor=40925837|journal=Journal of Interamerican Studies and World Affairs|volume=34|issue=4|pages=111–139}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Ortega brothers forged alliances with a wide array of anti-Somoza forces, including Catholic and Protestant activists and other non-Marxist civil society groups.{{sfn|DeFronzo|2011|p=258}} The Terceristas became the most effective faction in wielding political and military strength, and their push for FSLN solidarity received the support of revolutionary leaders like [[Fidel Castro]].&lt;ref name=&quot;FSLNPostCollapse&quot;/&gt;

Ortega married [[Rosario Murillo]] in 1979 in a secret ceremony.&lt;ref name=&quot;RT&quot; /&gt; and moved to [[Costa Rica]] with her three children from a previous marriage.&lt;ref name=&quot;LO&quot; /&gt; Ortega remarried Murillo in 2005 to have the marriage recognized by the [[Roman Catholic Church]]. The couple has eight children,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |title=Cardenal Obando caso a Daniel Ortega y poetisa Rosario Murillo |date=2005-09-28 |url=http://www.cardinalrating.com/cardinal_68__article_2094.htm |work=Cardinal Rating |accessdate=2007-05-11 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070328203222/http://www.cardinalrating.com/cardinal_68__article_2094.htm |archive-date=March 28, 2007 |url-status=dead |df=mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; three of them together.&lt;ref name=&quot;RT&quot;/&gt; She is currently the government's spokeswoman and a government minister, among other positions.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|first= |last= |title=Iran and Nicaragua in barter deal |publisher= |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/americas/6931807.stm |work=BBC News |pages= |accessdate=2007-10-05 |language= |date=August 5, 2007 |location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |title=Nicaragua-Venezuela Talk Cooperation |url=http://www.plenglish.com/article.asp?ID=%7B9FB2EF41-A435-459E-8111-4B04A12681DA%7D)&amp;language=EN |work=Prensa Latina |accessdate=2008-01-15 |quote=&quot;... Government minister and first lady, Rosario Murillo.&quot; |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080117220408/http://plenglish.com/article.asp?ID=%7B9FB2EF41-A435-459E-8111-4B04A12681DA%7D%29&amp;language=EN |archivedate=2008-01-17 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Ortega adopted stepdaughter Zoilamérica Narváez in 1986, through a court case.&lt;ref name=envio1567&gt;''Envio'', March 2002, No 248 [http://www.envio.org.ni/articulo/1567 Case 12,230: Zoilamérica Narváez vs. the Nicaraguan State]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Sandinista revolution (1979–1990)==
{{For|more details on Ortega's past presidency|Sandinista National Liberation Front|Iran–Contra affair}}
When Somoza was overthrown by the FSLN in July 1979, Ortega became a member of the five-person [[Junta of National Reconstruction]], which also included Sandinista militant [[Moisés Hassan]], novelist [[Sergio Ramírez]], businessman [[Alfonso Robelo]], and [[Violeta Barrios de Chamorro]], the widow of a murdered journalist. In September 1979, United States President [[Jimmy Carter|Carter]] hosted Ortega at the White House, and warned him against arming other Central American leftist guerrilla movements.{{sfn|Kinzer|1991|p=80}} At the time, Ortega spoke truthfully by denying Sandinista involvement in neighboring countries.{{sfn|Kinzer|1991|p=80}} When Ortega questioned the Americans about C.I.A. support for anti-Sandinista groups, Carter and Deputy Secretary of State [[Warren Christopher]] called the reports false.{{sfn|Kinzer|1991|p=80}} After the meeting, Carter asked Congress for $75 million in aid to Nicaragua, contingent on the Sandinista government's promise not to aid other guerrillas.{{sfn|Kinzer|1991|p=81}}

The FSLN came to dominate the junta, Robelo and Chamorro resigned, and in 1981 Ortega became the coordinator of the Junta.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|contribution=Daniel Ortega|title=Encyclopædia Britannica|year=1993|edition=15th}}&lt;/ref&gt; As the only member of the FSLN National Directorate in the Junta, he was the effective leader of the country. The FSLN embarked upon an ambitious programme of social reform upon attaining power. 5 million acres of land were redistributed to about 100,000 families, a literacy drive was launched, and health improvements were carried out which got rid of polio and reduced other diseases.&lt;ref&gt;Mastering Modern World History by Norman Lowe, second edition&lt;/ref&gt; The Sandinista nationalization efforts mostly affected banks and industries owned by the Somoza family.{{sfn|DeFronzo|2011|p=263}} More than half of all farms, businesses, and industries remained in private hands, as the revolutionary government still wanted to preserve a mixed economy and support private sector investment.{{sfn|DeFronzo|2011|p=263}} The Superior Council of Private Enterprise (COSEP) opposed the Sandinistas’ economic reform.{{sfn|DeFronzo|2011|p=264}} The main organization of Nicaraguan big business was composed of prosperous families from the Pacific coast cities, who dominated commerce and banking.&lt;ref&gt;Baumeister,&amp;nbsp;Eduardo.  &quot;The politics of land reform&quot; in {{harvnb|Close|Marti i Puig|McConnell|2012}}, p.&amp;nbsp;250.&lt;/ref&gt; Ortega took a very hard line against opposition to his policies: On February 21, 1981, the Sandinista army killed 7 Miskito Indians and wounded 17.&lt;ref name=&quot;OAS&quot;&gt;{{Cite ebook|title=Report on the Situation of Human Rights of a Segment of the Nicaraguan Population of Miskito Origin|last=|first=|publisher=Organization of American States: Inter-American Commission on Human Rights|year=1983|isbn=|location=|pages=|url=http://www.cidh.org/countryrep/Miskitoeng/toc.htm|chapter=Part I: Origin and Development of the Controversy|chapter-url=http://www.cidh.org/countryrep/Miskitoeng/part1.htm|access-date=October 14, 2014|id=OEA/Ser.L./V.II.62 doc.&amp;nbsp;10 rev.&amp;nbsp;3}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Forced displacement has also been documented to have occurred with the native population: 10,000 individuals had been moved by 1982.&lt;ref name=&quot;OAS&quot; /&gt; Thousands of Indians took refuge in Honduras and 14,000 were imprisoned in Nicaragua. [[Anthropologist]] Gilles Bataillon termed this &quot;politics of ethnocide&quot; in Nicaragua.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.persee.fr/web/revues/home/prescript/article/jsa_0037-9174_1983_num_69_1_3063 &quot;3 – Le Nicaragua (French)&quot;], Gilles Bataillon. Retrieved October 14, 2014.&lt;/ref&gt; The Indians formed two rebel groups – the Misura and Misurasata. They were joined in the north by Nicaraguan Democratic Force (FDN) and in the south by former Sandinistas and peasantry who under the leadership of [[Edén Pastora]] were resisting forced collectivization.&lt;ref name=&quot;OAS&quot; /&gt;

In 1980 the Sandinista government launched the massive [[Nicaraguan Literacy Campaign]], and claimed the illiteracy rate fell from 50% to 13% in the span of five months; these figures are disputed, as many &quot;unteachable&quot; illiterates were omitted from the statistics, and because many people declared literate turned out to be unable to read or write a simple sentence. The UNESCO rewarded Nicaragua the Nadezhda K. Krupskaya prize in recognition of its efforts.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite report|url=https://unesdoc.unesco.org/ark:/48223/pf0000146007|title=Nicaragua’s literacy campaign|last=Hanemann|first=Ulrike|date=March 2005|publisher=UNESCO|issue=|doi=|volume=|pmid=|id=2006/ED/EFA/MRT/PI/43|access-date=9 March 2019}}  Paper commissioned for the ''EFA Global Monitoring Report 2006, Literacy for Life''.&lt;/ref&gt;{{Unreliable source?|reason=Specifically states &quot;The views and opinions expressed in this paper are those of the author(s) and should not be attributed to the EFA Global Monitoring Report or to UNESCO&quot;|date=September 2016}} The FSLN also focused on improving the Nicaraguan health system, particularly through vaccination campaigns and the construction of public hospitals, and halved child mortality&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1987/03/23/world/casualties-in-nicaragua-schools-and-health-care.html?pagewanted=all|title=Casualties in Nicaragua: Schools and Health Care|last=Kinzer|first=Stephen|date=1987-03-23|newspaper=The New York Times|access-date=|publisher=The New York Times Corporation}}&lt;/ref&gt; to 40 deaths per thousand.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.lecourrier.ch/141179/la_sante_c_est_d_abord_un_choix_politique_et_gouvernemental | title=La santé c'est d'abord un choix politique et gouvernemental| date=2016-07-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; By 1982, the [[World Health Organization]] deemed Nicaragua a model for primary health care.{{sfn|DeFronzo|2011|p=264}}

In 1981, United States President [[Ronald Reagan]] accused the FSLN of joining with [[Soviet Union|Soviet]]-backed [[Cuba]] in supporting [[Marxism|Marxist]] revolutionary movements in other [[Latin America]]n countries such as [[El Salvador]]. People within the [[Reagan administration]] authorized the [[Central Intelligence Agency]] to begin financing, arming and training rebels, some of whom were former officers from Somoza's National Guard, as anti-Sandinista guerrillas. These were known collectively as the [[Contra (guerrillas)|Contras]]. This also led to one of the largest political scandals in US history, (the [[Iran–Contra affair]]), when [[Oliver North]] and several members of the Reagan administration defied the [[Boland Amendment]], selling arms to [[Iran]] and then using the proceeds to fund the [[Contras]]. The Contra war would claim 30,000 lives.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas Walker, ''Nicaragua: Living in the Shadow of the Eagle'', 4th Ed. (Westview Press, 2003)&lt;/ref&gt; The tactics used by the Sandinista government to fight the Contras have been widely condemned for their suppression of civil rights. On March 15, 1982, the Junta declared a state of siege, which allowed it to close independent radio stations, suspend the right of association and limit the freedom of trade unions. Nicaragua's Permanent Commission on Human Rights condemned Sandinista human rights violations, accusing them of killing and disappearing thousands in the first few years of the war.&lt;ref&gt;John Norton Moore, The Secret  War in Central America (University  Publications  of  America, 1987), p. 143&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Roger Miranda and William Ratliff, The Civil War in Nicaragua (Transaction, 1993), p.193.&lt;/ref&gt;

At the [[1984 Nicaraguan general election|1984 general election]] Ortega won the presidency with 67% of the vote and took office on January 10, 1985. In the early phases of the campaign, Ortega enjoyed many institutional advantages, and used the full power of the press, police, and [[Supreme Electoral Council (Nicaragua)|Supreme Electoral Council]] against the fractured opposition.{{sfn|Kinzer|1991|p=242}}  In the weeks before the November election, Ortega gave a U.N. speech denouncing talks held in Rio de Janeiro on electoral reform.{{sfn|Kinzer|1991|p=244}} But by October 22, the Sandinistas signed an accord with opposition parties to reform electoral and campaign laws, making the process more fair and transparent.&lt;ref&gt;McConnell,&amp;nbsp;Shelley&amp;nbsp;A.  &quot;The uncertain evolution of the electoral system,&quot; in {{harvnb|Close|Marti i Puig|McConnell|2012}}, p.&amp;nbsp;127.&lt;/ref&gt; While campaigning, Ortega promoted the Sandinistas’ achievements, and at a rally claimed that “Democracy is literacy, democracy is land reform, democracy is education and public health.”{{sfn|Kinzer|1991|p=246}} International observers judged the election to be the first free election held in the country in more than half a century.  A report by an [[Irish government]]ary delegation stated: &quot;The electoral process was carried out with total integrity. The seven parties participating in the elections represented a broad spectrum of political ideologies.&quot; The general counsel of New York's [[Human Rights Commission]] described the election as &quot;free, fair and hotly contested.&quot; A study by the US [[Latin American Studies Association]] (LASA) concluded that the FSLN (Sandinista Front) &quot;did little more to take advantage of its incumbency than incumbent parties everywhere (including the U.S.) routinely do.&quot; However some people described the election as &quot;rigged&quot;. According to a detailed study, since the 1984 election was for posts subordinate to the Sandinista Directorate, the elections were no more subject to approval by vote than the Central Committee of the Communist Party is in countries of the East Bloc.&lt;ref&gt;Martin Kriele, “Power and Human Rights in Nicaragua,” German Comments, April 1986, pp. 56–7, 63–7, a chapter excerpted from his Nicaragua: Das blutende Herz Amerikas (Piper, 1986). See also Robert S. Leiken, &quot;The Nicaraguan Tangle&quot;, ''The New York Review of Books'', December 5, 1985 and &quot;The Nicaraguan Tangle: Another Exchange&quot;, ''The New York Review of Books'', June 26, 1986; Alfred G. Cuzan, Letter, Commentary, December 1985 and &quot;The Latin American Studies Association vs. the United States&quot;, ''Academic Questions'', Summer 1994.&lt;/ref&gt;

Thirty-three percent of the Nicaraguan voters cast ballots for one of six opposition parties—three to the right of the Sandinistas, three to the left—which had campaigned with the aid of government funds and free TV and radio time. Two conservative parties captured a combined 23 percent of the vote. They held rallies across the country (a few of which were disrupted by FSLN supporters) and blasted the Sandinistas in harsh terms. Most foreign and independent observers noted this pluralism in debunking the Reagan administration charge—ubiquitous in the [[US media]]—that it was a &quot;Soviet-style sham&quot; election.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fair.org/index.php?page=2479 'The Sandinistas won't submit to free elections'] Article from &quot;Fairness and Accuracy in Reporting&quot;. November 1987&lt;/ref&gt; Some opposition parties [[boycott]]ed the election, allegedly under pressure from US embassy officials, and so it was denounced as being unfair by the Reagan administration.&lt;ref&gt;Ronald Reagan. [http://www.reagan.utexas.edu/search/speeches/speech_srch.html Remarks Following Discussions With President Jose Napoleon Duarte of El Salvador]. May 16, 1984&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=sanctions&gt;{{cite news|last1=Neikirk|first1=Bill|last2=Coffey|first2=Raymond|title=Reagan Puts Embargo On Nicaragua To `Mend Their Ways`|url=http://articles.chicagotribune.com/1985-05-02/news/8501260877_1_nicaraguan-economy-church-mediated-dialogue-trade-embargo|accessdate=August 31, 2015|newspaper=Chicago Tribune|date=May 2, 1985|location=Chicago, Illinois}}&lt;/ref&gt; Reagan thus maintained that he was justified to continue supporting what he referred to as the Contras' &quot;democratic resistance&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=Aid to the Nicaraguan Democratic Resistance |date=October 1987 |url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m1079/is_n2127_v87/ai_6101573 |archive-url=http://arquivo.pt/wayback/20090628114702/http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m1079/is_n2127_v87/ai_6101573 |url-status=dead |archive-date=2009-06-28 |work=U.S. Department of State Bulletin |accessdate=2006-12-14 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==In opposition (1990–2007)==
In the 1990 presidential election, Ortega lost his reelection bid to [[Violeta Barrios de Chamorro]], his former colleague in the junta. Chamorro was supported by the US and a 14-party anti-Sandinista alliance known as the [[National Opposition Union]] (Unión Nacional Oppositora, UNO), an alliance that ranged from conservatives and liberals to communists. She ran an effective campaign, presenting herself as the peace candidate and promising to end the US-funded Contra War if she won.&lt;ref&gt;Anderson, Leslie E. and Lawrence C. Dodd, Learning Democracy:  Citizen Engagement and Electoral Choice in Nicaragua, 1990-2001, Chicago, University of Chicago Press, 2005, esp Chapter 3.&lt;/ref&gt;  Ortega campaigned on the slogan, &quot;Everything Will Be Better,&quot; and promised that, with the Contra war over, he could focus on the nation's recovery.{{sfn|Kinzer|1991|p=389}}  Contrary to what most observers expected,&lt;ref&gt;Alma Guillermoprieto, The Heart That Bleeds: Latin America Now, pp. 23–25&lt;/ref&gt; Chamorro shocked Ortega and won the election. Chamorro's UNO coalition garnered 54 percent of the vote, and won 51 of the 92 seats in the [[National Assembly (Nicaragua)|National Assembly]].&lt;ref&gt;Marti&amp;nbsp;i&amp;nbsp;Puig,&amp;nbsp;Salvador.  &quot;The FSLN and Sandinismo,&quot; in {{harvnb|Close|Marti i Puig|McConnell|2012}}, p.&amp;nbsp;30.&lt;/ref&gt; Immediately after the loss, the Sandinistas tried to maintain unity around their revolutionary posture. In Ortega's concession speech the following day he vowed to keep &quot;ruling from below&quot; a reference to the power that the FSLN still wielded in various sectors. He also stressed his belief that the Sandinistas had the goal of bringing &quot;dignity&quot; to Latin America, and not necessarily to hold on to government posts. In 1991, Ortega claimed elections were “an instrument to reaffirm” the FSLN's “political and ideological positions,” and also “confront capitalism.”{{sfn|Baltodano|2012|p=70}} However, the electoral loss led to pronounced divisions in the FSLN. Some members adopted more pragmatic positions, and sought to transform the FSLN into a modern social democratic party engaged in national reconciliation and class cooperation. Ortega and other party insiders found common ground with the radicals, who still promoted anti-imperialism and class conflict to achieve social change.&lt;ref name=&quot;FSLNPostCollapse&quot; /&gt;

Possible explanations for his loss include that the Nicaraguan people were disenchanted with the Ortega government as well as the fact that already in November 1989, the White House had announced that the economic embargo against Nicaragua would continue unless [[Violeta Chamorro]] won.&lt;ref&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20130117074255/http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P2-1222025.html &quot;Bush Vows to End Embargo if Chamorro Wins&quot;], ''The Washington Post,'' November 9, 1989&lt;/ref&gt; Also, there had been reports of intimidation from the side of the contras,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite report|publisher=Human Rights Watch|title=Human Rights Watch World Report 1989|chapter=Nicaragua|url=https://www.hrw.org/legacy/reports/1989/WR89/index.htm|date=1990|access-date=9 March 2016|chapter-url=https://www.hrw.org/legacy/reports/1989/WR89/Nicaragu.htm|quote=The policy of keeping the contras alive &amp;hellip; also has placed in jeopardy the holding of elections by encouraging contra attacks on the electoral process. Thus, while the Bush administration proclaims its support for human rights and free and fair elections in Nicaragua, it persists in sabotaging both.}}&lt;/ref&gt; with a Canadian observer mission claiming that 42 people were killed by the contras in &quot;election violence&quot; in October 1989.&lt;ref&gt;[https://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/thestar/access/471113751.html?FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:FT&amp;type=current&amp;date=Oct+27%2C+1989&amp;author=%28CP%29&amp;pub=Toronto+Star&amp;desc=U.S.+trying+to+disrupt+election+in+Nicaragua%2C+Canadians+report&amp;pqatl=google &quot;U.S. trying to disrupt election in Nicaragua, Canadians report&quot;] ''[[The Toronto Star]]'', October 27, 1989&lt;/ref&gt; This led many commentators to assume that Nicaraguans voted against the Sandinistas out of fear of a continuation of the contra war and economic deprivation.{{citation needed|date=April 2018}}

From July 19–21, 1991, the FSLN held a National Congress to mend the rifts between members and form a new overarching political program. The effort failed to unite the party, and intense debates over the internal governance of the FSLN continued. The pragmatists, led by the former vice president [[Sergio Ramírez|Sergio Ramirez]], formed the basis of a &quot;renovating&quot; faction, and supported collaboration with other political forces to preserve the rule of law in Nicaragua. Under the leadership of Ortega and [[Tomás Borge|Tomas Borge]], the radicals regrouped into the &quot;principled&quot; faction, and branded themselves the Izquierda Democratica (ID), or Democratic Left (DL).&lt;ref name=&quot;FSLNAdaptation&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Marti i Puig|first=Salvador|last2=Wright|first2=Claire|date=2010|title=The Adaptation of the FSLN: Daniel Ortega's Leadership and Democracy in Nicaragua|jstor=40925837|journal=Latin American Politics and Society|volume=52|issue=4|pages=79–106}}&lt;/ref&gt; The DL fought the [[Violeta Chamorro|Chamorro]] government with disruptive labor strikes and demonstrations, and renewed calls for the revolutionary reconstruction of Nicaraguan society.{{sfn|DeFronzo|2011|p=276}} During the May 20–23, 1994, extraordinary congress, Ortega ran against a fellow National Directorate member, [[Henry Ruiz]], for the position of party secretary-general. Ortega was elected with 287 to Ruiz's 147 votes, and the DL secured the most dominant role in the FSLN.&lt;ref name=&quot;MiP35&quot;&gt;Marti&amp;nbsp;i&amp;nbsp;Puig,&amp;nbsp;Salvador.  &quot;The FSLN and Sandinismo,&quot; in {{harvnb|Close|Marti i Puig|McConnell|2012}}, p.&amp;nbsp;35.&lt;/ref&gt;

On September 9, 1994, Ortega gained more power after taking over Sergio Ramirez's seat in the Asamblea Sandinista (Sandinista Assembly).&lt;ref name=&quot;FSLNAdaptation&quot;/&gt; Ramirez had served as chief of the FSLN's parliamentary caucus since 1990, but Ortega came to oppose his actions in the [[National Assembly (Nicaragua)|National Assembly]], setting the stage for Ramirez's removal. Historic leaders, such as [[Ernesto Cardenal]], a former minister of culture in the Sandinista government, rejected Ortega's consolidation of power: “My resignation from the FSLN has been caused by the kidnapping of the party carried out by Daniel Ortega and the group he heads.”&lt;ref name=&quot;MiP35&quot;/&gt; The party formally split on January 8, 1995, when Ramirez and a number of prominent Sandinista officials quit.&lt;ref name=&quot;FSLNAdaptation&quot;/&gt;

Ortega ran for election again, in October 1996 and November 2001, but lost on both occasions to [[Arnoldo Alemán]] and [[Enrique Bolaños]], respectively. In these elections, a key issue was the allegation of corruption. In Ortega's last days as president, through a series of legislative acts known as &quot;The [[Piñata]]&quot;, estates that had been seized by the Sandinista government (some valued at millions and even billions of US dollars) became the private property of various FSLN officials, including Ortega himself.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|author=Shirley Christian |url=https://www.nytimes.com/1991/06/08/world/managua-journal-victor-s-lament-to-the-losers-belong-the-spoils.html |title=Managua Journal; Victor's Lament: To the Losers Belong the Spoils – New York Times |location=Nicaragua |publisher=Nytimes.com |date= 1991-06-08|accessdate=2014-08-18|newspaper=The New York Times }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 1996 campaign, Ortega faced the Liberal Alliance (Alianza Liberal), headed by [[Arnoldo Alemán|Arnoldo Aleman Lacayo]], a former mayor of Managua. The Sandinistas softened their anti-imperialist rhetoric, with Ortega calling the U.S. “our great neighbor,” and vowing to cooperate “within a framework of respect, equality, and justice.” The image change failed, as Aleman's Liberal Alliance came first with 51.03 percent of the vote, while Ortega's FSLN secured 37.75 percent.{{sfn|Baltodano|2012|pp=72-3}}

Ortega's policies became more moderate during his time in opposition, and he gradually changed much of his former [[Marxist]] stance in favor of an agenda of [[democratic socialism]]. His [[Roman Catholic]] faith has become more public in recent years as well, leading Ortega to embrace a variety of [[socially conservative]] policies; in 2006 the FSLN endorsed a strict law banning all [[abortion]]s in Nicaragua.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2006/11/20/world/americas/20nicaragua.html|title=Nicaragua Eliminates Last Exception to Strict Anti-Abortion Law|date=November 20, 2006|newspaper=The New York Times|accessdate=August 5, 2016|last1=Jr|first1=James C. Mckinley}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the run-up to the 2006 elections, Ortega displayed his ties to the Catholic Church by renewing his marriage vows before Cardinal [[Miguel Obando y Bravo|Miguel Obanda y Bravo]].{{sfn|Baltodano|2012|p=81}}

Ortega was instrumental in creating the controversial strategic pact between the FSLN and the [[Constitutional Liberal Party]] (Partido Liberal Constitucionalista, PLC). The controversial alliance of Nicaragua's two major parties is aimed at distributing power between the PLC and FSLN, and preventing other parties from rising. After sealing the agreement in January 2000, the two parties controlled the three key institutions of the state: the Comptroller General of the Republic, the [[Supreme Court of Justice (Nicaragua)|Supreme Court]], and the Supreme Electoral Council.&lt;ref name=&quot;FSLNAdaptation&quot;/&gt; ''&quot;El Pacto,&quot;'' as it is known in Nicaragua, is said to have personally benefited former presidents Ortega and Alemán greatly, while constraining then-president Bolaños. One of the key accords of the pact was to lower the percentage necessary to win a presidential election in the first round from 45% to 35%, a change in electoral law that would become decisive in Ortega's favor in the 2006 elections{{Citation needed|date=August 2010}}.

At the Fourth Ordinary Congress of the FSLN, held March 17–18, 2002, Ortega eliminated the National Directorate (DN). Once the main collective leadership body of the party, with nine members, the DN no longer met routinely, and only three historic members remained. Instead, the body just supported decisions already made by the secretary-general. Ortega sidelined party officials and other members while empowering his own informal circle, known as the ring of iron.&lt;ref name=&quot;FSLNAdaptation&quot;/&gt;

=== 2001 presidential election ===
{{Main|2001 Nicaraguan general election}}
Under Ortega's direction, the FSLN formed the broad National Convergence (Convergencia Nacional) coalition to defeat the PLC in the 2001 elections. Ortega abandoned the revolutionary tone of the past, and infused his campaign with religious imagery. In speeches, he gave thanks to “God and the Revolution” for the post-1990 democracy, and claimed a Sandinista victory would enable the Nicaraguan people to “pass through the sea and reach the Promised Land.”{{sfn|Baltodano|2012|pp=76-7}}  The U.S. opposed Ortega's candidacy from the beginning. The U.S. ambassador even made an appearance with the PLC's [[Enrique Bolaños|Enrique Bolanos]] while distributing food aid.&lt;ref&gt;McConnell,&amp;nbsp;Shelley&amp;nbsp;A.  &quot;The uncertain evolution of the electoral system,&quot; in {{harvnb|Close|Marti i Puig|McConnell|2012}}, p.&amp;nbsp;142.&lt;/ref&gt; The September 11, 2001 terrorist attacks doomed Ortega's chances, as the threat of a U.S. invasion became an issue. Bolanos convinced many Nicaraguans that the renewed U.S. hostility towards terrorism would endanger their country if the openly anti-U.S. Ortega prevailed.{{sfn|DeFronzo|2011|p=280}} Bolanos ended up with 56.3 percent of the vote, and Ortega won 42.3 percent.&lt;ref&gt;McConnell,&amp;nbsp;Shelley&amp;nbsp;A.  &quot;The uncertain evolution of the electoral system,&quot; in {{harvnb|Close|Marti i Puig|McConnell|2012}}, p.&amp;nbsp;143.&lt;/ref&gt;

===2006 presidential election===
{{Main|2006 Nicaraguan general election}}
In 2006, Daniel Ortega was elected president with 38% of the vote. This occurred despite the fact that the breakaway [[Sandinista Renovation Movement]] continued to oppose the FSLN, running former Mayor of Managua  [[Herty Lewites]] as its candidate for president. Ortega personally attacked [[Herty Lewites|Lewites]]’ Jewish background, compared him to Judas, and warned he “could end up hanged.”{{sfn|Baltodano|2012|p=83}} However, Lewites died several months before the elections.

Ortega emphasized peace and reconciliation in his campaign, and selected a former Contra leader, [[Jaime Morales Carazo|Jaime Morales Corazo]], as his running mate.{{sfn|DeFronzo|2011|p=281}} The FSLN also won 38 seats in the congressional elections, becoming the party with the largest representation in parliament. The split in the Constitutionalist Liberal Party helped allow the FSLN to become the largest party in Congress; however, the Sandinista vote had a minuscule split between the FSLN and MRS, and that the liberal party combined is larger than the Frente Faction. In 2010, several liberal congressmen raised accusations about the FSLN presumably attempting to buy votes to pass constitutional reforms that would allow Ortega to run for office for the 6th time since 1984.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.laprensa.com.ni/2010/06/15/politica/27852|title=Ofertas de &quot;cañonazos&quot; en US$500 mil|last=Uriarte|first=María José|date=15 June 2010|work=La Prensa|access-date=|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131019083239/http://www.laprensa.com.ni/2010/06/15/politica/27852|archive-date=19 October 2013|language=Spanish|trans-title=Offers of canonization for US$500 million}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Second presidency (2007–present)==
{{Main|2011 Nicaraguan general election||Nicaraguan general election, 2016}}
{{Infobox President styles
| image    = [[File:Coat of arms of Nicaragua.svg|75px]]
| name     = Daniel Ortega
| dipstyle = ''Daniel Ortega, Presidente de la República de Nicaragua'' Daniel Ortega, President of the Republic of Nicaragua
| offstyle = ''Presidente Ortega'' President Ortega
| altstyle = ''Señor Presidente'' Mister President
}}
Soon after his inauguration, Ortega paid an official visit to Iran and met [[Iranian President]] [[Mahmoud Ahmadinejad]]. Ortega told the press that the &quot;revolutions of Iran and Nicaragua are almost twin revolutions...since both revolutions are about justice, liberty, self-determination, and the struggle against [[imperialism]].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/hi/spanish/latin_america/newsid_6741000/6741829.stm|title=Nicaragua e Irán, 'unión invencible'|last=Hauser|first=Karim|date=2007-06-11|work=BBC World Service|access-date=2019-03-09|archive-url=https://archive.today/20120711234659/http://news.bbc.co.uk/hi/spanish/latin_america/newsid_6741000/6741829.stm|archive-date=11 July 2012|url-status=live|language=Spanish|trans-title=Nicaragua and Iran: &quot;Together Invincible&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since the start of his second presidency, various measures have been introduced to combat hunger and to improve access to healthcare, education,&lt;ref name=&quot;wilsoncenter.org&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.wilsoncenter.org/index.cfm?topic_id=1425&amp;fuseaction=topics.event_summary&amp;event_id=481319 |title= Latin American Program |publisher= Wilson Center |date= 2011-03-31|accessdate= 2014-08-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; credit,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= https://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/nov/03/daniel-ortega-nicaragua-election | location= London | work= The Guardian |first= Eva |last= Carroll |title= Daniel Ortega set for Nicaragua election victory but heroic sheen wearing off | date= November 3, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and social security.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite report|url=http://tortillaconsal.com/may_briefing_eng.html|title=Nicaragua in 2010 compared to Nicaragua in 2006: the concrete achievements of Daniel Ortega's government|last=|first=|date=8 May 2011|issue=|doi=|volume=|pmid=|access-date=2014-08-18|agency=Nicaragua Triunfa|translator-last=Jacobs|translator-first=Karla}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, other reforms have been carried out, including an enhancement of labour rights,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite blog|url=http://www.latinamericaconference.org.uk/2011/01/labour-rights-improve-under-ortega-government/|title=Labour rights improve under Ortega government|website=Latin America Conference|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130522055014/http://www.latinamericaconference.org.uk/2011/01/labour-rights-improve-under-ortega-government/|archive-date=22 May 2013|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; the introduction of low-interest loans and training for female micro-entrepreneurs in rural areas,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author= Richard Feinberg |url= http://www.foreignaffairs.com/features/letters-from/daniel-ortega-and-nicaraguas-soft-authoritarianism |title= Daniel Ortega and Nicaragua's Soft Authoritarianism |journal= Foreign Affairs |date= 2011-11-02 |accessdate= 2014-08-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the distribution of transport subsidies, scholarships, medicine, land titles, and housing materials throughout the population.&lt;ref name=&quot;wilsoncenter.org&quot;/&gt; Altogether, these policies have helped to reduce high levels of poverty and inequality in Nicaragua.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url= http://www.coha.org/nicaragua-under-daniel-ortega%E2%80%99s-second-presidency-daniel-style-politics-as-usual/ |title= Nicaragua Under Daniel Ortega's Second Presidency: Daniel-Style Politics as Usual? |publisher= Coha.org |date= 2011-04-15 |accessdate= 2014-08-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.ticotimes.net/Region/Nicaragua/Is-Nicaragua-Winning-War-on-Poverty-_Friday-September-03-2010/|title=Is Nicaragua Winning War on Poverty?|last=Rogers|first=Tim|date=3 September 2010|work=Tico Times|access-date=|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130529232319/http://www.ticotimes.net/Region/Nicaragua/Is-Nicaragua-Winning-War-on-Poverty-_Friday-September-03-2010/|archive-date=29 May 2013|location=San José, Costa Rica}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ipsnews.net/news.asp?idnews=52737|title=Inter Press Service - News and Views from the Global South|accessdate=August 5, 2016|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100907183416/http://ipsnews.net/news.asp?idnews=52737|archivedate=September 7, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url= https://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/jan/11/nicaragua-world-ortega | location= London | work= The Guardian | first= Rory | last= Carroll | title= Second Coming of the Sandinistas turns sour | date= January 11, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last= Amplifier |first= Scoop |url= http://www.scoop.co.nz/stories/HL1104/S00029/nicaragua-fsln-victory-in-november-will-permit-change.htm |title= Nicaragua: FSLN victory in November will permit change &amp;#124; Scoop News |publisher= Scoop.co.nz |date= 2011-04-05 |accessdate= 2014-08-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://en.mercopress.com/2011/11/08/re-election-for-daniel-ortega-in-nicaragua-continent-s-poorest-nation |title= Re-election for Daniel Ortega in Nicaragua, continent's poorest nation — MercoPress |publisher= En.mercopress.com |date= 2011-11-08 |accessdate= 2014-08-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.redpepper.org.uk/central-america-21st-century-sandinismo-or-losing-the-revolution/ |title= Nicaragua: 21st century Sandinismo – or losing the revolution? |publisher= Red Pepper |date= |accessdate= 2014-08-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ortega placed the first lady, Rosario Murillo, in charge of the Citizens’ Power Councils (CPCs), designed to implement his anti-poverty social policies.&lt;ref name=&quot;FSLNAdaptation&quot;/&gt; The CPCs also undermined municipal autonomy, as they effectively functioned as local governments by determining the distribution of public goods and services.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thaler2017&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Thaler|first1=Kai M.|title=Nicaragua: A Return to Caudillismo|journal=Journal of Democracy|volume=28|issue=2|year=2017|pages=157–169|issn=1086-3214|doi=10.1353/jod.2017.0032|url=https://muse.jhu.edu/article/653384|via=Project MUSE}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 2008 the [[Nicaraguan Supreme Court]] disqualified the MRS and the Conservative Party from participation in municipal elections.{{Citation needed|date=August 2010}}&lt;ref name=counterpunch27feb09&gt;Robert Burbach, ''CounterPunch'', February 27, 2009, [http://www.counterpunch.org/burbach02272009.html Et Tu, Daniel? The Betrayal of the Sandinista Revolution] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090304121907/http://www.counterpunch.org/burbach02272009.html |date=2009-03-04 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In November 2008, the Supreme Electoral Council received national and international criticism following irregularities in municipal elections, but agreed to review results for Managua only, while the opposition demanded a nationwide review.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url= http://www.cnn.com/2008/WORLD/americas/11/12/nicaragua.elections/|title= Review follows election fraud allegations in Nicaragua |publisher= CNN |date = 2008-11-12 | accessdate = 2008-11-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; For the first time since 1990, the Council decided not to allow national or international observers to witness the election.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url= http://www.economist.com/displaystory.cfm?story_id=12607338 |newspaper= The Economist|date= 2008-11-13 |title= How to steal an election | accessdate = 2008-11-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Conozca como Daniel Ortega preparo el fraude electoral | url = http://central-america-forum.com/forum-topic/daniel-ortega-y-el-fraude-electoral-nicaragua | accessdate = 2009-03-03 | archive-url = https://archive.today/20120714052706/http://central-america-forum.com/forum-topic/daniel-ortega-y-el-fraude-electoral-nicaragua | archive-date = July 14, 2012 | url-status = dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; Instances of intimidation, violence, and harassment of opposition political party members and NGO representatives have been recorded.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title= Irregularities in Nicaraguan Municipal Elections |url= https://2001-2009.state.gov/r/pa/prs/ps/2008/nov/111736.htm |last= Wood |first= Robert |publisher= US Department of State |accessdate= 2008-11-14 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Official results show Sandinista candidates winning 94 of the 146 municipal mayoralties, compared to 46 for the main opposition Liberal Constitutional Party (PLC).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url = http://www.miamiherald.com/news/americas/story/766863.html |title= Nicaraguan opposition demands election review| newspaper= Miami Herald |first= Filadelfo |last= Aleman}}&lt;/ref&gt; The opposition claimed that marked ballots were dumped and destroyed, that party members were refused access to some of the vote counts and that tallies from many polling places were altered.&lt;ref&gt;''LA Times'', November 20, 2008, [http://www.latimes.com/news/opinion/editorials/la-ed-nicaragua20-2008nov20,0,56506.story Voter fraud allegations directed at Nicaragua's Sandinistas]&lt;/ref&gt; As a result of the fraud allegations, the [[European Union]] suspended $70m of aid, and the US $64m.&lt;ref&gt;''Daily Times (Pakistan)'', February 20, 2009, [http://www.dailytimes.com.pk/default.asp?page=2009\story_20-2-2009_pg3_3 COMMENT: The Mugabe of Latin America &amp;nbsp;—Carlos R Chamorro] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120112122855/http://www.dailytimes.com.pk/default.asp?page=2009 |date=January 12, 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

With the [[late-2000s recession]], Ortega in 2011 characterised [[capitalism]] as in its &quot;death throes&quot; and portrayed the [[Bolivarian Alternative for the People of Our America]] (ALBA) is the most advanced, most Christian and fairest project.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://insidecostarica.com/dailynews/2008/october/11/reg01.htm | date = 2008-01-11|title= Ortega Says Capitalism In Its Death Throes|publisher= |accessdate= April 25, 2015 | quote = Nicaraguan President Daniel Ortega stated that the capitalism is in its death throes and the Bolivarian Alternative for the Peoples of Our America (ALBA) as the most advanced, Christian and fairest project.}}&lt;/ref&gt; He also said God was punishing the United States with the [[financial crisis]] for trying to impose its economic principles on poor countries. &quot;It's incredible that in the most powerful country in the world, which spends billions of dollars on brutal wars ... people do not have enough money to stay in their homes.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url= http://uk.reuters.com/article/oddlyEnoughNews/idUKTRE4997KH20081010 |work=Reuters |title= Nicaragua's Ortega says crisis is God punishing U.S | date= October 10, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Before the National Sandinista Council held in September 2009, Lenin Cerna, the secretary of the party organization, called for diversifying its political strategies. He declared the FSLN's future depended on implementing new plans, “so that the party can advance via new routes and in new ways, always under Ortega’s leadership.” Ortega gained power over the selection of candidates, allowing him to personally choose all candidates for public office.&lt;ref name=&quot;FSLNAdaptation&quot; /&gt;

During an interview with [[David Frost]] for the [[Al Jazeera English]] programme ''[[Frost Over The World]]'' in March 2009, Ortega suggested that he would like to change the constitution to allow him to run again for president.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://english.aljazeera.net/programmes/frostovertheworld/2009/03/2009378501399631.html|title=Daniel Ortega|last=|first=|date=|website=Al Jazeera|publisher=|accessdate=April 25, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Judicial Decision 504, issued on October 19, 2009, the Supreme Court of Justice of Nicaragua declared portions of Articles 147 and 178 of the Constitution of Nicaragua inapplicable; these provisions concerned the eligibility of candidates for president, vice-president, mayor, and vice-mayor—a decision that had the effect of allowing Ortega to run for reelection in 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://content.glin.gov/summary/224071|archive-url=https://archive.today/20120708011111/http://content.glin.gov/summary/224071|url-status=dead|archive-date=July 8, 2012|title=Global Legal Information Network&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;|accessdate=August 5, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

For this decision, the Sandinista magistrates formed the required quorum by excluding the opposition magistrates and replacing them with Sandinista substitutes, violating the Nicaraguan constitution.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last = PH |first = Editor |title = Presidente de la CSJ de Nicaragua tilda de &quot;ilegal&quot; reelección de Ortega |url= http://informe21.com/presidente/presidente-del-supremo-tilda-ilegal-fallo-permite-reeleccion-ortega |accessdate = October 30, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Opposing parties, the church and human rights groups in Nicaragua denounced the decision.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last = Jarquin | first = Leyla | title = Oposición toca a rebato |url = http://www.elnuevodiario.com.ni/nacionales/59762 | accessdate = October 30, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=San Martin |first=Nieves |title=NICARAGUA: LA IGLESIA, CONTRA LA REELECCIÓN &quot;ILEGAL&quot; DE ORTEGA |url=http://www.zenit.org/article-38051?l=spanish |accessdate=October 30, 2011 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110221101839/http://www.zenit.org/article-38051?l=spanish |archivedate=February 21, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last = EFE | first = International | title = Núñez: &quot;Reelección ilegal de Ortega aumenta persecución contra sociedad civil&quot; | url= http://www.laprensa.com.ni/2011/03/25/nacionales/55923#.Tq2Vqd6a9tM | accessdate = October 30, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Throughout 2010, court rulings gave Ortega greater power over judicial and civil service appointments.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thaler2017&quot;/&gt;

While supporting [[abortion rights]] during his presidency during the 1980s, Ortega has since embraced the [[Catholic Church]]'s position of strong opposition.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/americas/6161396.stm Nicaragua brings in abortion ban: Nicaraguan President [[Enrique Bolaños]] has signed into law a ban on all abortions, even in cases when a woman's life is judged to be at risk] November 18, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; While non-emergency abortions have long been illegal in Nicaragua, recently even abortions &quot;in the case where the pregnancy endangers the mother's life&quot;, otherwise known as [[therapeutic abortions]] have been made illegal in the days before the 2006 election, with a six-year prison term in such cases, too—a move supported by Ortega.&lt;ref&gt;[http://upsidedownworld.org/main/content/view/472/1/ Abortion Outlawed in Nicaragua Ten Days Before Controversial Elections] October 27, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Comandante Daniel Ortega celebrando su triunfo Presidencial.jpg|Ortega and his supporters celebrating his victory in the 2011 elections.|thumb]]

Ortega was re-elected president with a vote on November 6 and confirmation on November 16, 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://aljazeera.com/news/americas/2011/11/2011111641224404319.html |title= Nicaragua electoral body confirms Ortega win – Americas |publisher= Al Jazeera English |date= |accessdate= 2014-08-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the election, the Supreme Electoral Council (CSE) blocked both domestic and international poll observers from multiple polling stations.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thaler2017&quot;/&gt; According to the Supreme Electoral Council, Ortega defeated [[Fabio Gadea Mantilla|Fabio Gadea]], with 63 percent of the vote.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thaler2017&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Daniel Ortega (cropped).jpg|thumb|Daniel Ortega in 2013.]]
In January 2014 the National Assembly, dominated by the FSLN, approved constitutional amendments that abolished term limits for the presidency and allowed a president to run for an unlimited number of five-year terms.  Although billed{{by whom|date=May 2016}} as a measure to ensure stability, critics{{Which|date=May 2016}} charged that the amendments threatened Nicaraguan democracy.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url= https://www.bbc.com/news/world-latin-america-25937292|title= Nicaragua: Ortega allowed to run for third successive term|newspaper= BBC News|accessdate= April 25, 2015|date= 2014-01-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; The constitutional reforms also gave Ortega the sole power to appoint military and police commanders.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thaler2017&quot;/&gt;

As of 2016, Ortega's family owns three of the nine free-to-air television channels in Nicaragua, and controls a fourth (the public Channel 6). Four of the remaining five are controlled by Mexican mogul [[Remigio Ángel González|Ángel González]], and are generally considered to be aligned with Ortega's ruling FSLN party. There are no government restrictions on Internet use; the Ortega administration attempted to gain complete control over online media in 2015, but failed due to opposition from civil society, political parties, and private organizations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Nicaragua Country report/Freedom of the Press/2016|url=https://freedomhouse.org/report/freedom-press/2016/nicaragua|website=freedomhouse.org|accessdate=August 4, 2016|date=2016-04-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 2016, the Nicaraguan supreme court ruled to oust [[Eduardo Montealegre]], the leader of the main opposition party, leaving the main opposition coalition with no means of contesting the November 2016 national elections.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Lakhani|first1=Nina|title=Nicaragua suppresses opposition to ensure one-party election, critics say|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/jun/26/nicaragua-opposition-daniel-ortega-presidential-election|accessdate=August 4, 2016|work=The Guardian|date=June 26, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; In August 2016, Ortega chose his wife, [[Rosario Murillo]], as his vice-presidential running-mate for re-election.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Nicaragua's President Picks Wife as Running Mate|url=https://www.nbcnews.com/news/world/nicaragua-s-daniel-ortega-picks-wife-running-mate-pledges-joint-n622201|accessdate=August 4, 2016|work=[[NBC News]]|date=August 3, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the ''Washington Post'', figures announced on November 7, 2016 put Daniel Ortega in line for his third consecutive term as President, also being his fourth term overall. The Supreme Electoral Council (CSE) reported Ortega and Murillo won 72.4 percent of the vote, with 68 percent turnout.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thaler2017&quot;/&gt; The opposition coalition had called the election a &quot;farce&quot; and had called for the boycott of the election. International observers were not allowed to observe the vote. Nevertheless, according to the BBC, Ortega was the most popular candidate by far, possibly due to Nicaragua's stable economic growth and lack of violence compared to its neighbours El Salvador and Honduras in recent years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Nicaragua's Ortega re-elected president|url=https://www.bbc.com/news/world-latin-america-37892477|accessdate=November 29, 2017|work=BBC News|date=November 7, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In April 2018, student protests over a nature reserve fire expanded to cover an unpopular social security decree. The protesters were violently set upon by the state sponsored Sandinista Youth.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Peaceful Protests against Nicaraguan Social Security Reforms Violently Repressed|url=https://www.havanatimes.org/?p=132219|date=April 19, 2018|work=the Havana Times}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite attempts by Ortega's government to hide the incident through censorship of all private-owned news outlets, photos and videos of the violence made their way to social media where they sparked outrage and urged more Nicaraguans to join in on the protests.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Nicaragua Roiled by Protests Over Social Security Benefits |url= https://www.nytimes.com/2018/04/20/world/americas/nicaragua-protests-ortega.html |work= The New York Times |date= April 20, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite blog |url= https://ijnet.org/en/blog/facing-censorship-nicaraguan-journalists-and-citizens-turn-social-media|title=Facing censorship, Nicaraguan journalists and citizens turn to social media|work=ijnet|date=May 3, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite blog|title=Amidst unrest, Nicaraguan journalists use digital innovation to share information|url=https://ijnet.org/en/blog/amidst-unrest-nicaraguan-journalists-use-digital-innovation-share-information|work=ijnet|date=July 24, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; Tensions escalated quickly, as police began using tear gas canisters and rubber bullets, and eventually live ammunition on unarmed protesters.&lt;ref name=&quot;the Miami Herald&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=In Nicaragua, the political battle is moving from the streets to the negotiating table|url=https://www.miamiherald.com/latest-news/article210129639.html|work=the Miami Herald|date=May 2, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; Authorities were also seen arming Sandinista Youth members with weapons to serve as paramilitary forces.&lt;ref name=&quot;the Miami Herald&quot;/&gt; Dozens of student protesters were subsequently killed. Despite the withdrawal of the unpopular decree, the [[2018 Nicaraguan protests|protests continue]], with most protesters demanding Ortega's and his cabinet's resignations. As the protests continue, support for the Ortega-Murillo regime dwindles.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=As Nicaragua Death Toll Grows, Support for Ortega Slips|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2018/05/04/world/americas/nicaragua-protests-ortega.html|accessdate=May 7, 2018|work=The New York Times|date=May 4, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On May 30, Nicaragua's Mother's Day, a march attended by over 300,000 people took place. It was held to honor the mothers of students killed in the recent protests. The demonstration was peaceful, attended by children, mothers and retirees. Yet Ortega's regime ordered sharpshooters, perched at the National Stadium to shoot indiscriminately at the marchers, resulting in the deaths of 15 civilians, one of them in the hands of his own mother. This event has been dubbed by Nicaraguans as the &quot;Mother's Day Massacre&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;The New York Times&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Nicaragua Protests Grow Increasingly Violent, 100 Killed Since April|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2018/05/31/world/americas/nicaragua-protests-killings.html|accessdate=May 31, 2018|work=The New York Times|date=May 31, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Protests on Nicaragua's Mother's Day turn deadly|url=https://edition.cnn.com/2018/05/31/americas/nicaragua-mothers-day-deadly-violence/index.html|accessdate=May 31, 2018|work=CNN|date=June 1, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Nicaragua: Violent attack on mass Mother's Day march in Managua|url=https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/news/2018/05/nicaragua-violento-ataque-a-multitudinaria-marcha-de-las-madres-en-managua/|accessdate=May 30, 2018|work=CNN|date=May 30, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Estados Unidos condena masacre del Día de las Madres y pide una investigación inmediata|url=https://www.laprensa.com.ni/2018/05/31/politica/2428258-estados-unidos-condena-masacre/|accessdate=June 23, 2018|work=La Prensa|date=May 31, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Foreign policy===
[[File:Dmitry Medvedev 18 December 2008-6.jpg|thumb|Ortega with [[Russian Prime Minister]] [[Dmitry Medvedev]] in [[Russia]] on December 18, 2008.]]
On March 6, 2008, following the [[2008 Andean diplomatic crisis]], Ortega announced that Nicaragua was breaking diplomatic ties with [[Colombia]] &quot;in solidarity with the [[Ecuador]]ian people&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://edition.cnn.com/2008/WORLD/americas/03/06/nic.colombia/index.html &quot;Nicaragua breaks diplomatic relations with Colombia&quot;] March 6, 2008 ''[[CNN]]''&lt;/ref&gt; Ortega also stated, &quot;We are not breaking relations with the Colombian people. We are breaking relations with the terrorist policy practiced by [[Álvaro Uribe]]'s government&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|first= Xuequan |last= Mu |title= Nicaragua breaks off relations with Colombian gov't |url= http://news.xinhuanet.com/english/2008-03/07/content_7734634.htm |work= Xinhua News |accessdate= 2008-03-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; The relations were restored with the resolution at a [[Rio Group]] summit held in [[Santo Domingo]], [[Dominican Republic]], on March 7, 2008. At the summit Colombia's Álvaro Uribe, Ecuador's [[Rafael Correa]], Venezuela's [[Hugo Chávez]] and Ortega publicly shook hands in a show of good-will. The handshakes, broadcast live throughout Latin America, appeared to signal that a week of military buildups and diplomatic repercussions was over. After the handshakes, Ortega said he would re-establish diplomatic ties with Colombia. Uribe then quipped that he would send him the bill for his ambassador's plane fare.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url= http://voanews.com/english/2008-03-07-voa73.cfm |title= Colombia, Ecuador, Venezuela Agree to End Border Crisis |publisher= [[VOA]] |date= 2008-03-07 |accessdate= 2008-03-08 |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20080309093506/http://www.voanews.com/english/2008-03-07-voa73.cfm &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2008-03-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news|url= http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/americas/7284597.stm |title= Leaders say Colombia crisis over |work= BBC News |date= 2008-03-08 |accessdate= 2008-03-08 | location= London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On May 25, 2008, Ortega, upon learning of the death of [[FARC]] guerrilla leader [[Manuel Marulanda]] in Colombia, expressed condolences to the family of Marulanda and solidarity with the FARC and called Marulanda an extraordinary fighter who battled against profound inequalities in Colombia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url= http://www.miamiherald.com/519/story/546814.html |title= Colombian rebels' loss of leader ends an era |first= Tyler |last= Bridges |newspaper= Miami Herald |date= 2008-05-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://espanol.news.yahoo.com/s/reuters/080525/latinoamerica/latinoamerica_farc_marulanda_ortega_sol |work=Reuters |date=2008-05-25 |language=Spanish |title=Ortega expresa condolencias a FARC por muerte líder |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080527052757/http://espanol.news.yahoo.com/s/reuters/080525/latinoamerica/latinoamerica_farc_marulanda_ortega_sol |archivedate=2008-05-27 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The declarations were protested by the [[Colombian government]] and criticized in the major Colombian media outlets.

[[File:Ortega Lula - ABr 28.07.20102225.JPG|thumb|Ortega with [[President of Brazil|Brazilian President]] [[Luiz Inácio Lula da Silva]] at [[Itamaraty Palace]] in [[Brasília]], July 28, 2010.]]
On September 2, 2008, during ceremonies for the 29th anniversary of the founding of the [[Sandinista Popular Army|Nicaraguan army]], Ortega announced that &quot;Nicaragua recognizes the independence of [[South Ossetia]] and [[Abkhazia]] and fully supports the [[Russian government]]'s position&quot;. Ortega's decision made Nicaragua the second country (after [[Russia]]) to recognize the independence of Abkhazia and South Ossetia from [[Georgia (country)|Georgia]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://en.rian.ru/world/20080904/116538071.html|title= Nicaragua recognizes South Ossetia and Abkhazia|work= rian.ru}}&lt;/ref&gt; A day after [[Venezuela]] recognised the two Republics, Nicaragua established diplomatic relations with Abkhazia, and followed this by establishing diplomatic links with South Ossetia. Embassies have been mooted, but as of 2013 these had not opened.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://en.rian.ru/world/20100603/159280095.html|title= Abkhazia, S. Ossetia may soon open embassies in Nicaragua|work= rian.ru}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:01.10 總統與尼加拉瓜總統奧德嘉(José Daniel Ortega Saavedra)雙邊會晤 (32074399712).jpg|thumb|Ortega with [[Taiwan]]'s president [[Tsai Ing-wen]], January 10, 2017]]
When seeking office, Ortega threatened to cut ties with the [[Republic of China]] ([[Taiwan]]) in order to restore relations with the [[People's Republic of China]] (as in the period from 1985 to 1990). But he did not do so. In 2007 Ortega stated that Nicaragua did not accept the [[One China Policy]] of the PRC government and that Nicaragua reserved the right to maintain official diplomatic relations with Taiwan. He reassured President Chen Shui Bian in 2007 that Nicaragua would not break diplomatic relations with Taiwan. He explained that during the Reagan administration the United States imposed sanctions on Nicaragua. But cutting ties with Taiwan was a sad and painful decision because of the friendship between Nicaragua and Taiwan's people and government. Ortega met with Taiwan's President [[Ma Ying-jeou]] in 2009 and both agreed to improve the diplomatic ties between both countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chinapost.com.tw/commentary/the-china-post/joe-hung/2009/06/09/211402/Ma-Ying-jeou.htm|title=Ma Ying-jeou shouldn't meet Daniel Ortega|publisher=|accessdate=August 5, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, with a trade show from China in Managua in 2010, he is attempting a two-track policy to get benefits from both sides. In 2016 Nicaragua and Taiwan signed an air services agreement and Ortega stated that Nicaragua's  free trade deal with Taiwan had benefited both nations. Taiwan increased its investment in Nicaragua. In 2017 Ortega reaffirmed Nicaragua's diplomatic relations with Taiwan.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|url=http://solpropertygroup.wordpress.com/2011/01/17/nicaragua-seeks-economic-relations-with-china-the-nica-times-the-nica-times-costa-rica-newspaper-the-tico-times/ |title=Nicaragua seeks economic relations with China |author=Tim Rogers |date=January 14, 2011 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110721183306/http://solpropertygroup.wordpress.com/2011/01/17/nicaragua-seeks-economic-relations-with-china-the-nica-times-the-nica-times-costa-rica-newspaper-the-tico-times/ |archivedate=2011-07-21 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In September 2010, after a US report listed Nicaragua as a &quot;major&quot; drug-trafficking centre, with Costa Rica and Honduras, Ortega urged the US Congress and [[Obama administration]] to allocate more resources to assist the fight against drug trafficking.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.miamiherald.com/2010/09/21/1834482/us-adds-three-nations-to-drug.html|title=U.S. adds three nations to drug-traffic-hub list – Americas – MiamiHerald.com&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;transshipment point for cocaine destined for the US and transshipment point for arms-for-drugs dealing&quot; {{citation|url= https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/fields/2086.html|title= Field Listing :: Illicit drugs|publisher= CIA|accessdate= 2011-04-21|archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20101229044611/https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/fields/2086.html|archive-date= December 29, 2010|url-status= dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the [[2011 Libyan Civil War|Libyan Civil War]], Ortega was among the [[International reactions to the 2011 Libyan civil war|very few leaders]] who spoke out in clear defense of the embattled [[Muammar Gaddafi]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://blogs.aljazeera.net/africa/2011/02/22/live-blog-libya-feb-22|title= Live Blog – Libya Feb 22|work= Al Jazeera Blogs}}&lt;/ref&gt; During a telephone conversation between the two, Ortega told  Gaddafi that he was &quot;waging a great battle to defend his nation&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Al Jazeera (February 24, 2011). {{YouTube|u-HvdqjsqXM|''Latin America divided over Gaddafi''}}.&lt;/ref&gt; and stated that &quot;it's at difficult times that loyalty and resolve are put to the test.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=|title=Gaddafi vows to fight until 'the end'|last=Raghavan|first=Sudarsan|date=23 February 2011|work=The Washington Post|access-date=|at=A1|via=Factiva}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Ortega has said that Assad's victory in the [[2014 Syrian presidential election|2014 election]] is an important step to &quot;attain peace in Syria and a clear cut evidence that the Syrian people trust their president as a national leader and support his policies which aim at maintaining Syria's sovereignty and unity&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://syriatimes.sy/index.php/presidential-elections/13206-nicaragua-s-ortega-congratulates-president-al-assad-on-winning-elections|title=syriatimes.sy - Nicaragua's Ortega Congratulates President Al-Assad on Winning Elections|work=syriatimes.sy}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Ortega attended the swearing-in ceremony of [[Nicolás Maduro]] for his second term on 10 January 2019.{{citation needed|date=April 2019}}

In an interview with [[Max Blumenthal]] in August 2019, Ortega stated that he was open to the idea of [[Bernie Sanders]] (who had visited him in 1985) winning the [[President of the United States|U.S. Presidency]] [[2020 United States presidential election|in 2020]] and that Bernie's message &quot;goes in the right direction for the U.S. to become a pole of peace, development, and cooperation.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Daniel Ortega dice que le gustaría que Bernie Sanders ganara las elecciones presidenciales de 2020 |url=https://www.univision.com/local/miami-wltv/daniel-ortega-dice-que-le-gustaria-que-bernie-sanders-ganara-las-elecciones-presidenciales-de-2020-video |publisher=Univision}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Environmental policy===
In 2016, Daniel Ortega did not sign the [[Paris Agreement]] because he felt the deal did not do enough to protect the climate, although he later changed his mind. Moreover, [[Nicaragua]] rejected projects of mining of the Canadian group B2 Gold which could represent a threat to the environment.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.lemonde.fr/planete/article/2017/04/28/en-premiere-mondiale-le-salvador-interdit-les-mines-de-metaux_5118997_3244.html|title=Le Salvador devient le premier pays au monde à interdire les mines de métaux|newspaper=Le Monde.fr|date=2017-04-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to government estimates, Nicaragua has passed from 25 percent renewable electricity to 52 percent between 2007 and 2016.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://time.com/4799844/nicaragua-paris-climate-agreement-countries/|title=Nicaragua Didn't Sign the Paris Agreement Because It Didn't Go Far Enough|website=Time}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Electoral history of Daniel Ortega==

;[[1984 Nicaraguan general election|1984 elections]]
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!Candidate
!Party/Alliance
!Votes
!%
|-
|José Daniel Ortega Saavedra
|[[Sandinista National Liberation Front]] (FSLN)
|align=right|735,967
|align=right|66.97%
|-
|[[Clemente Guido Chavez]]
|[[Democratic Conservative Party|Democratic Conservative Party of Nicaragua]] (PCDN)
|align=right|154,327
|align=right|14.04%
|-
|[[Virgilio Godoy Reyes]]
|[[Independent Liberal Party (Nicaragua)|Independent Liberal Party]] (PLI)
|align=right|105,560
|align=right|9.60%
|-
|[[Mauricio Díaz Dávila]]
|[[Popular Social Christian Party]] (PPSC)
|align=right|61,199
|align=right|5.56%
|-
|[[Allan Zambrana Salmerón]]
|[[Communist Party of Nicaragua]] (PC de N)
|align=right|16,034
|align=right|1.45%
|-
|[[Domingo Sánchez Salgado]]
|[[Nicaraguan Socialist Party]] (PSN)
|align=right|14,494
|align=right|1.31%
|-
|[[Isidro Téllez Toruño]]
|[[Marxist-Leninist Popular Action Movement]] (MAP ML)
|align=right|11,352
|align=right|1.03%
|-
|colspan=2|Total valid votes
|align=right|'''1,098,933'''
|align=right|'''100%'''
|-
|colspan=2|Spoilt and invalid votes
|align=right|71,209
|align=right|6.09%
|-
|colspan=2|Total votes/Turnout
|align=right|1,170,142
|align=right|75.42%
|-
|colspan=2|Registered voters
|align=right|1,551,597
|align=right|–
|-
|colspan=2|Population
|align=right|3,165,000
|align=right|–
|}

;[[1990 Nicaraguan general election|1990 elections]]
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!Candidate
!Party/Alliance
!%
!Votes
|-
|[[Violeta Barrios de Chamorro]]
|[[National Opposition Union]] (UNO) = [[National Conservative Party (Nicaragua)|National Conservative Party]] (PNC) / [[Popular Conservative Alliance]] (APC) / [[National Conservative Action]] (ACN) / [[Democratic Party of National Confidence]] (PDCN) / [[Independent Liberal Party (Nicaragua)|Independent Liberal Party]] (PLI) / [[Neoliberal Party]] (PALI) / [[Constitutionalist Liberal Party]] (PLC) / [[National Action Party (Nicaragua)|National Action Party]] (PAN) / [[Nicaraguan Socialist Party]] (PSN) / [[Communist Party of Nicaragua]] (PC de N) / [[Popular Social Christian Party]] (PPSC) / [[Nicaraguan Democratic Movement]] (MDN) / [[Social Democratic Party (Nicaragua)|Social Democratic Party]] (PSD) / [[Central American Integrationist Party]] (PIAC)
|align=right|54.74%
|align=right|777,552
|-
|José Daniel Ortega Saavedra
|[[Sandinista National Liberation Front]] (FSLN)
|align=right|40.82%
|align=right|579,886
|-
|[[Erick Ramírez Beneventes]]
|[[Social Christian Party (Nicaragua)|Social Christian Party]] (PCS)
|align=right|1.18%
|align=right|16,751
|-
|[[Moisés Hassán]]
|[[Revolutionary Unity Movement]] (MUR)
|align=right|0.78%
|align=right|11,136
|-
|[[Bonifacio Miranda Bengoechea]]
|[[Workers' Revolutionary Party (Nicaragua)|Workers' Revolutionary Party]] (PRT)
|align=right|0.60%
|align=right|8,590
|-
|[[Isidro Téllez Toruño]]
|[[Marxist-Leninist Popular Action Movement]] (MAP ML)
|align=right|0.57%
|align=right|8,115
|-
|[[Fernando Agüero Rocha]]
|[[Social Conservative Party]] (PSC)
|align=right|0.41%
|align=right|5,798
|-
|[[Blanca Rojas Echaverry]]
|[[Central American Unionist Party]] (PUCA)
|align=right|0.36%
|align=right|5,065
|-
|[[Eduardo Molina Palacios]]
|[[Democratic Conservative Party|Democratic Conservative Party of Nicaragua]] (PCDN)
|align=right|0.32%
|align=right|4,500
|-
|[[Rodolfo Robelo Herrera]]
|[[Independent Liberal Party for National Unity]] (PLIUN)
|align=right|0.22%
|align=right|3,151
|-
|colspan=2|'''Total valid votes'''
|align=right|'''100%'''
|align=right|'''1,420,544'''
|-
|colspan=2|Spoilt and invalid votes
|align=right|5.97%
|align=right|90,249
|-
|colspan=2|Total votes/Turnout
|align=right|86.23%
|align=right|1,510,838
|-
|colspan=2|Registered voters
|align=right|–
|align=right|1,752,088
|-
|colspan=2|Population
|align=right|–
|align=right|3,800,000
|}

;[[1996 Nicaraguan general election|1996 elections]]
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!Candidate
!Party/Alliance
!Votes
!%
|-
|[[José Arnoldo Alemán Lacayo]]
|''[[Liberal Alliance (Nicaragua)|Liberal Alliance]] (AL)'' = [[Constitutionalist Liberal Party]] (PLC) / [[Independent Liberal Party for National Unity]] (PLIUN) / [[Nationalist Liberal Party]] (PLN) / [[Neoliberal Party]] (PALI)
|align=right|896,207
|align=right|50.99%
|-
|José Daniel Ortega Saavedra
|[[Sandinista National Liberation Front]] (FSLN)
|align=right|664,909
|align=right|37.83%
|-
|[[Guillermo Osorno]]
|[[Nicaraguan Party of the Christian Path]] (PCCN)
|align=right|71,908
|align=right|4.09%
|-
|[[Noel Vidaurre]]
|[[Conservative Party of Nicaragua]] (PCN)
|align=right|39,983
|align=right|2.27%
|-
|[[Benjamin Ramón Lanzas Selva]]
|[[National Project]] (PRONAL)
|align=right|9,265
|align=right|0.53%
|-
|[[Sergio Ramírez Mercado]]
|[[Sandinista Renovation Movement]] (MRS)
|align=right|7,665
|align=right|0.44%
|-
|[[Francisco José Mayorga Balladares]]
|''[[Bread and Strength Alliance (Nicaragua)|Bread and Strength Alliance]] (Pan y Fuerza)'' = [[National Action Party (Nicaragua)|National Action Party]] (PAN) / [[Republican Strength 96 Alliance]] (ASR)
|align=right|7,102
|align=right|0.40%
|-
|[[Francisco José Duarte Tapia]]
|[[National Conservative Action]] (ACN)
|align=right|6,178
|align=right|0.35%
|-
|[[Edgar Enrique Quiñónez Tuckler]]
|[[Nicaraguan Resistance Party]] (PRN)
|align=right|5,813
|align=right|0.33%
|-
|[[Andrés Abelino Robles Pérez]]
|[[Nicaraguan Workers, Peasants and Professionals Unity Party]] (PUNOCP)
|align=right|5,789
|align=right|0.33%
|-
|[[Virgilio Godoy]]
|[[Independent Liberal Party (Nicaragua)|Independent Liberal Party]] (PLI)
|align=right|5,692
|align=right|0.32%
|-
|[[Jorge Alberto Díaz Cruz]]
|[[National Justice Party (Nicaragua)|National Justice Party]] (PJN)
|align=right|5,582
|align=right|0.32%
|-
|[[Alejandro Serrano Caldera]]
|''[[Unity Alliance]] (AU)'' = [[Social Christian Party (Nicaragua)|Social Christian Party]] (PCS) / [[Revolutionary Unity Movement]] (MUR) / [[Social Democratic Party (Nicaragua)|Social Democratic Party]] (PSD)
|align=right|4,873
|align=right|0.28%
|-
|[[Elí Altamirano Pérez]]
|[[Communist Party of Nicaragua]] (PC de N)
|align=right|4,802
|align=right|0.27%
|-
|[[Miriam Auxiliadora Argüello Morales]]
|[[Popular Conservative Alliance]] (APC)
|align=right|4,632
|align=right|0.26%
|-
|[[Ausberto Narváez Argüello]]
|[[Liberal Unity Party (Nicaragua)|Liberal Unity Party]] (PUL)
|align=right|3,887
|align=right|0.22%
|-
|[[Alfredo César Aguirre]]
|''[[UNO-96 Alliance|National Opposition Union 96]](UNO 96)'' = [[National Democratic Party (Nicaragua)|National Democratic Party]] (PND) / Conservative Action Movement (MAC) / [[Nicaraguan Democratic Movement]] (MDN)
|align=right|3,664
|align=right|0.21%
|-
|[[Allan Antonio Tefel Alba]]
|[[National Renovation Movement (Nicaragua)|National Renovation Movement]] (MORENA)
|align=right|2,641
|align=right|0.15%
|-
|[[James Odnith Webster Pitts]]
|[[Democratic Action Party (Nicaragua)|Democratic Action Party]] (PAD)
|align=right|1,895
|align=right|0.11%
|-
|[[Sergio Abilio Mendieta Castillo]]
|[[Central American Integrationist Party]] (PIAC)
|align=right|1,653
|align=right|0.09%
|-
|[[Moises Hassán Morales]]
|[[Renovating Action Movement (Nicaragua)|Renovating Action Movement]] (MAR)
|align=right|1,393
|align=right|0.08%
|-
|[[Gustavo Ernesto Tablada Zelaya]]
|[[Nicaraguan Socialist Party]] (PSN)
|align=right|1,352
|align=right|0.08%
|-
|[[Roberto Urcuyo Muñoz]]
|[[Nicaraguan Democratic Party]] (PADENIC)
|align=right|890
|align=right|0.05%
|-
|colspan=2|'''Total valid votes'''
|align=right|'''1,757,775'''
|align=right|'''100%'''
|-
|colspan=2|Spoilt and invalid votes
|align=right|91,587
|align=right|4.95%
|-
|colspan=2|Total votes/Turnout
|align=right|1,849,362
|align=right|76.39%
|-
|colspan=2|Registered voters
|align=right|2,421,067
|align=right|–
|-
|colspan=2|Population
|align=right|4,706,000
|align=right|–
|}

;[[2001 Nicaraguan general election|2001 elections]]
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!Candidate
!Party/Alliance
!Votes
!%
|-
|[[Enrique Bolaños Geyer]]
|[[Constitutionalist Liberal Party]] (PLC)
|align=right|1,228,412
|align=right|56.31%
|-
|José Daniel Ortega Saavedra
|[[Sandinista National Liberation Front]] (FSLN)
|align=right|922,436
|align=right|42.28%
|-
|[[Alberto Saborío]]
|[[Conservative Party of Nicaragua]] (PC)
|align=right|30,670
|align=right|1.41%
|-
|colspan=2|'''Total valid votes'''
|align=right|'''2,181,518'''
|align=right|'''100%'''
|}

; 2006 elections
{{Nicaraguan presidential election, 2006}}

; 2011 elections
{{Nicaraguan presidential election, 2011}}

;[[2016 Nicaraguan general election|2016 elections]]
{| class=wikitable style=text-align:right
!Candidate
!Party
!Votes
!%
|-
|align=left|José Daniel Ortega Saavedra||align=left|[[Sandinista National Liberation Front]]||1,806,651||72.44
|-
|align=left|[[Maximino Rodríguez Martínez]]||align=left|[[Constitutionalist Liberal Party]]||374,898||15.03
|-
|align=left|[[José del Carmen Alvarado]]||align=left|[[Independent Liberal Party (Nicaragua)|Independent Liberal Party]]||112,562||4.51
|-
|align=left|[[Saturnino Mirando Cerrato Hogdson]]||align=left|[[Nicaraguan Liberal Alliance]]||107,392||4.31
|-
|align=left|[[Erick Antonio Cabezas Granados]]||align=left|[[Conservative Party (Nicaragua)|Conservative Party]]||57,437||2.30
|-
|align=left|[[Carlos José Canales]]||align=left|[[Alliance for the Republic (Nicaragua)|Alliance for the Republic]]||35,002||1.40
|-
|align=left colspan=2|Invalid/blank votes||–||–
|-
|align=left colspan=2|'''Total'''||'''2,493,942'''||'''100'''
|-
|align=left colspan=2|Registered voters/turnout||– ||–
|-
|align=left colspan=4|Source: [https://web.archive.org/web/20161114025014/http://www.cse.gob.ni/fri3/respres1.php CSE]

|}

==Controversy==
In Nicaragua, reviews of Ortega's presidency have not always been glowing, with many considering him a dictator{{citation needed|date=May 2019}}. Many Nicaraguans, including prominent former Sandinista leaders, such as Daniel Ortega's own brother [[Humberto Ortega]], have accused him of forgetting where he came from and catering to his own capitalist interests, calling his government monopolistic and authoritarian and denouncing him as a &quot;Bloody Dictator&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.miamiherald.com/news/local/news-columns-blogs/andres-oppenheimer/article210536964.html|title=Ortega’s repressive regime cannot survive — even his younger brother, a former Sandinista leader, says so|date=May 5, 2018|first=Associated|last=Press|website=the Miami Herald}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[2018 Nicaraguan protests|2018 protests]] are symbolic of these tensions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Amnesty&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/apr/23/nicaragua-withdraws-social-security-changes-after-people-killed-in-riots|title=Nicaragua abandons social security changes after dozens killed in riots|first=Associated|last=Press|date=April 23, 2018|newspaper=The Guardian|agency=Associated Press}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sexual abuse allegations===
In 1998, Daniel Ortega's adopted stepdaughter [[Zoilamerica Ortega Murillo|Zoilamérica Narváez]] released a 48-page report&lt;ref&gt;{{in lang|es}} [http://www.jornada.unam.mx/2002/01/07/arts_41/41_zoilamerica.htm Zoilamerica Narvaez 48-page testimony about sexual abuse] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141026130910/http://www.jornada.unam.mx/2002/01/07/arts_41/41_zoilamerica.htm |date=2014-10-26 }}; [http://www.therealnicaragua.com/Files/testimony_of_Zoilamerica_vs_Ortega.pdf Zoilamerica Narvaez 48-page testimony about sexual abuse (in English)]&lt;/ref&gt; describing how, she alleged, Ortega had systematically [[sexually abused]] her from 1979, when she was 12, until 1990.&lt;ref name=&quot;GUARD16&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last1=Watts|first1=Jonathan|title=As Nicaragua's first couple consolidates power, a daughter fears for her country|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/nov/04/nicaraguas-first-couple-daniel-ortega-tighten-grip-power-election-win|accessdate=November 4, 2017|work=[[The Guardian]]|date=November 4, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=time230398&gt;''[[Time (magazine)|Time]]'',  March 23, 1998, [http://www.time.com/time/magazine/1998/int/980323/latin_america.an_ugly_fa3.html An Ugly Family Affair: Charges of sexual abuse leveled against Sandinista leader Daniel Ortega swirl atop a power struggle]&lt;/ref&gt; Ortega, his wife Murillo and their other children denied the allegations, as did many Sandinistas who believe it is politically motivated.&lt;ref name=&quot;CommandantCaudillo&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2006/nov/07/thecomandantewhobecameaca|title=From comandante to caudillo|last=Anthony|first=Andrew|date=2006-11-07|work=The Guardian|access-date=2019-03-10|language=en-GB|issn=0261-3077}}&lt;/ref&gt; The case could not proceed in Nicaraguan courts, which have been consistently allied with Ortega,&lt;ref name=&quot;DB13&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last1=Margolis|first1=Mac|title=Nicaragua’s President Accused of Sex Abuse by His Stepdaughter|url=https://www.thedailybeast.com/nicaraguas-president-accused-of-sex-abuse-by-his-stepdaughter|accessdate=November 4, 2017|work=[[The Daily Beast]]|date=May 20, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; because Ortega had immunity from prosecution as a member of parliament,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.independent.co.uk/news/ortega-faces-sex-abuse-case-from-his-stepdaughter-1156496.html|title=Ortega faces sex abuse case from his stepdaughter|work=The Independent|access-date=2018-08-30|language=en-GB}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the five-year statute of limitations for sexual abuse and rape charges was judged to have been exceeded.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.aljazeera.com/indepth/opinion/2011/11/2011112415754381234.html|title=Ignoring sexual violence in Nicaragua|last=Picq|first=Manuela|website=www.aljazeera.com|access-date=2018-08-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; Narváez took a complaint to the [[Inter American Human Rights Commission]], which was ruled [[Admissible evidence|admissible]] on October 15, 2001.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cidh.org/annualrep/2001eng/nicaragua12230.htm|title=Nicaragua 12.230 - Admissible|publisher=|accessdate=August 5, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; On March 4, 2002 the Nicaraguan government accepted the Commission's recommendation of a friendly settlement.&lt;ref name=&quot;envio1567&quot;/&gt; 
Ortega continued to deny the allegations and Narváez withdrew the accusations in 2008, though she later renewed her complaints shortly after.&lt;ref name=&quot;CommandantCaudillo&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;DB13&quot;/&gt; Following the 2016 election, Narváez continued to make the accusations saying that she had become an outcast of her family.&lt;ref name=&quot;GUARD16&quot;/&gt;&lt;!--In 2005, Nicaraguan Elvia Junieth Flores and her family stated that she had been sexually abused by Ortega since she was 15 years-old. Flores said that she was under travel restrictions, that she is under constant surveillance and that her family has been blackmailed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Los motivos de la minga: “Somos distintos porque queremos la vida”|url=https://www.prensarural.org/spip/spip.php?article24210|accessdate=November 4, 2017|work=Prensa rural.|date=November 2, 2017|language=es-LA}}&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt;

==References==
=== Specific citations ===
{{Reflist|30em}}

=== General references ===
{{refbegin}}
* {{Cite book|title=Revolutions and Revolutionary Movements|last=DeFronzo|first=James|publisher=Westview Press|year=2011|isbn=9780813344805|edition=4th|location=Boulder|ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book|last1=Kinzer|first1=Stephen|title=[[Blood of Brothers: Life and War in Nicaragua]]|publisher=G. P. Putnam's Sons|year=1991|isbn=9780399135941|location=New York|ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book|url=http://search.ebscohost.com/login.aspx?direct=true&amp;db=e000xna&amp;AN=709336|title=The Sandinistas &amp; Nicaragua Since 1979|publisher=Lynne Rienner Publishers|year=2012|isbn=978-1-58826-798-6|editor-last=Close|editor-first=David|location=Boulder|editor-last2=Marti i Puig|editor-first2=Salvador|editor-last3=McConnell|editor-first3=Shelley|via=EBSCOHost|ref=harv}}, especially:
** {{wikicite|reference=Baltodano, Andrés Péréz, &quot;Political Culture&quot;, pp.&amp;nbsp;65-90.  [[#{{sfnref|Close|Marti i Puig|McConnell|2012}}|''loc. cit.'']]|ref={{harvid|Baltodano|2012}}}} 
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons category}}
{{Wikiquote}}
{{Wikinews|Nicaragua's Ortega visits Imam Khamenei in Iran}}
*[http://www.presidencia.gob.ni Office of the President]
*[http://www.cidob.org/biografias_lideres_politicos/america_central_y_caribe/nicaragua/daniel_ortega_saavedra Biography by CIDOB] {{in lang|es}}

{{s-start}}
{{s-off}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Francisco Urcuyo]]|as=Acting President of Nicaragua}}
{{s-ttl|title=Coordinator of the [[Junta of National Reconstruction|Junta of National Reconstruction of Nicaragua]]|years=1979–1985}}
{{s-aft|after=Himself|as=President of Nicaragua}}
|-
{{s-bef|before=Himself|as=Coordinator of the Junta of National Reconstruction of Nicaragua}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[President of Nicaragua]]|years=1985–1990}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Violeta Chamorro]]}}
|-
{{s-bef|before=[[Enrique Bolaños]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[President of Nicaragua]]|years=2007–present}}
{{s-inc}}
{{s-end}}

{{Presidents and heads of state of Nicaragua}}
{{Heads of State in Central America}}
{{Current ALBA leaders}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Ortega, Daniel}}
[[Category:1945 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Nicaraguan socialists]]
[[Category:Nicaraguan communists]]
[[Category:Nicaraguan Christian socialists]]
[[Category:Nicaraguan Marxists]]
[[Category:Nicaraguan prisoners and detainees]]
[[Category:Nicaraguan revolutionaries]]
[[Category:Nicaraguan Roman Catholics]]
[[Category:Nicaraguan torture victims]]
[[Category:Nicaraguan male writers]]
[[Category:People from Chontales Department]]
[[Category:People of the Nicaraguan Revolution]]
[[Category:Presidents of Nicaragua]]
[[Category:Socialist rulers]]
[[Category:Sandinista National Liberation Front politicians]]
[[Category:Catholic socialists]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of Friendship]]</text>
      <sha1>039wxm4giv8pybzsh4pdgz3xvkdamy6</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
