  <page>
    <title>Darwin's Dangerous Idea</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8757</id>
    <revision>
      <id>940381050</id>
      <parentid>940380838</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-12T06:03:00Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>207.161.86.162</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{about||the [[PBS]] documentary|Evolution (TV series)|the [[BBC]] documentary|BBC Darwin Season}}

{{Infobox book &lt;!-- null edit --&gt;
| name          = Darwin's Dangerous Idea
| image         = File:Darwin's Dangerous Idea (first edition).jpg
| caption       = Cover of the first edition
| author        = [[Daniel Dennett|Daniel C. Dennett]]
| cover_artist  = 
| country       = United States
| language      = English
| series        = 
| subjects      = {{hlist | [[Evolution]] | [[ethics]]}}
| published     = 1995 ([[Simon &amp; Schuster]])
| media_type    = Print ([[hardcover]]{{·}}[[paperback]])
| pages         = 586
| isbn          = 978-0-684-80290-9
| isbn_note     = (hardcover)&lt;br/&gt;{{ISBN|978-0-684-82471-0|plainlink=yes}} (paperback)
}}

'''''Darwin's Dangerous Idea: Evolution and the Meanings of Life''''' is a 1995 book by [[Daniel Dennett]], in which the author looks at some of the repercussions of [[Darwinian]] theory. The crux of the argument is that, whether or not Darwin's theories are overturned, there is no going back from the dangerous idea that design (purpose or what something is for) might not need a designer. Dennett makes this case on the basis that [[natural selection]] is a blind process, which is nevertheless sufficiently powerful to explain the [[evolution]] of [[life]]. Darwin's discovery was that the generation of life worked algorithmically, that processes behind it work in such a way that given these processes the results that they tend toward must be so.

Dennett says, for example, that by claiming that minds cannot be [[reductionism|reduced]] to purely algorithmic processes, many of his eminent contemporaries are claiming that [[miracles]] can occur. These assertions have generated a great deal of debate and discussion in the general public. The book was a finalist for the 1995 [[National Book Award]] in non-fiction&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.nationalbook.org/awards-prizes/national-book-awards-1995 The National Book Foundation]&lt;/ref&gt; and the 1996 [[Pulitzer Prize for General Non-Fiction]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pulitzer.org/finalists/1996 The Pulitzer Prizes - 1996 Finalists]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Background==

Dennett's previous book was ''[[Consciousness Explained]]'' (1991). Dennett noted discomfort with [[Darwinism]] among not only lay people but also even academics and decided it was time to write a book dealing with the subject.&lt;ref&gt;Material in this section is largely drawn from ''Darwin's Dangerous Idea'', preface.&lt;/ref&gt; ''Darwin's Dangerous Idea'' is not meant to be a work of [[science]], but rather an [[interdisciplinary]] book; Dennett admits that he does not understand all of the scientific details himself. He goes into a moderate level of detail, but leaves it for the reader to go into greater depth if desired, providing references to this end.

In writing the book, Dennett wanted to &quot;get thinkers in other disciplines to take evolutionary theory seriously, to show them how they have been underestimating it, and to show them why they have been listening to the wrong sirens&quot;. To do this he tells a story; one that is mainly original but includes some material from his previous work.

Dennett taught an undergraduate seminar at [[Tufts University]] on Darwin and philosophy, which included most of the ideas in the book. He also had the help of fellow staff and other academics, some of whom read drafts of the book.&lt;ref&gt;These include [[Richard Dawkins]], [[David Haig (biologist)|David Haig]], [[Douglas Hofstadter]], [[Nick Humphrey]], [[Ray Jackendoff]], [[Philip Kitcher]], [[Justin Leiber]], [[Ernst Mayr]], [[Steve Pinker]] and [[Kim Sterelny]].&lt;/ref&gt; It is dedicated to [[Willard Van Orman Quine|W. V. O. Quine]], &quot;teacher and friend&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;''Darwin's Dangerous Idea'', p. 5&lt;/ref&gt;

==Synopsis==

===Part I: Starting in the Middle===
&quot;Starting in the Middle&quot;, Part I of ''Darwin's Dangerous Idea'', gets its name from a quote by [[Willard Van Orman Quine]]: &quot;Analyze theory-building how we will, we all must start in the middle. Our conceptual firsts are middle-sized, middle-distance objects, and our introduction to them and to everything comes midway in the cultural evolution of the race.&quot;

The first chapter &quot;Tell Me Why&quot; is named after a song.

{{quote|text=
Tell me why the stars do shine,&lt;br&gt;
Tell me why the ivy twines, &lt;br&gt;
Tell me why the sky's so blue.&lt;br&gt;
Then I will tell you just why I love you.&lt;br&gt;

Because God made the stars to shine,&lt;br&gt;
Because God made the ivy twine,&lt;br&gt;
Because God made the sky so blue.&lt;br&gt;
Because God made you, that's why I love you.}}

Before [[Charles Darwin]], and still today, a majority of people see [[God]] as the [[ultimate cause]] of all design, or the ultimate answer to 'why&lt;!-- this should have an article too... --&gt;?' questions. [[John Locke]] argued for the primacy of [[mind]] before [[matter]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=[[An Essay Concerning Human Understanding]] |last=Locke |first=John |authorlink=John Locke |year=1690 |publisher= |location=London |isbn= |pages= |url= }}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[David Hume]], while exposing problems with Locke's view,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=[[Dialogues Concerning Natural Religion]] |last=Hume |first=David |authorlink=David Hume |year=1779 |publisher= |location=London |isbn= |pages= |url= }}&lt;/ref&gt; could not see any alternative.

[[Image:Cranes from Encyclopédie.jpg|thumb|''Darwin's Dangerous Idea'' makes extensive use of [[crane (machine)|crane]]s as an analogy.]]
Darwin provided just such an alternative: [[evolution]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=[[On the Origin of Species]] |last=Darwin |first=Charles |authorlink=Charles Darwin |year=1859 |publisher=John Murray |location=London |isbn= |pages= |url= }}&lt;/ref&gt; Besides providing [[evidence of common descent]], he introduced a [[mechanism (philosophy)|mechanism]] to explain it: [[natural selection]]. According to Dennett, natural selection is a mindless, mechanical and [[algorithm]]ic process&amp;mdash;Darwin's dangerous idea. The third chapter introduces the concept of &quot;skyhooks&quot; and &quot;cranes&quot; (see below). He suggests that resistance to [[Darwinism]] is based on a desire for skyhooks, which do not really exist. According to Dennett, good [[reductionism|reductionists]] explain apparent [[design]] without skyhooks; [[greedy reductionism|greedy reductionists]] try to explain it without cranes.

Chapter 4 looks at the [[Tree of life (science)|tree of life]], such as how it can be visualized and some crucial events in [[evolutionary history of life|life's history]]. The next chapter concerns the possible&lt;!--  we should have an article on this, no? --&gt; and the actual, using the 'Library of [[Gregor Mendel|Mendel]]' (the space of all [[logical possibility|logically possible]] [[genome]]s) as a conceptual aid.

In the last chapter of part I, Dennett treats human [[social artifact|artifacts]] and [[culture]] as a branch of a unified Design Space. [[Common descent|Descent]] or [[homology (anthropology)|homology]] can be detected by shared design features that would be unlikely to appear independently. However, there are also &quot;Forced Moves&quot; or &quot;Good Tricks&quot; that will be discovered repeatedly, either by natural selection (see [[convergent evolution]]) or human investigation.

===Part II: Darwinian Thinking in Biology===
[[Image:Origin of Species illustration cropped.png|thumb|left|Tree diagram in ''[[On the Origin of Species|Origin]]'']]
The first chapter of part II, &quot;Darwinian Thinking in Biology&quot;, asserts that [[origin of life|life originated]] without any skyhooks, and the orderly world we know is the result of a blind and undirected shuffle through chaos.

The eighth chapter's message is conveyed by its title, &quot;Biology is Engineering&quot;; [[biology]] is the study of design, [[function (biology)|function]], construction and operation. However, there are some important differences between biology and [[engineering]]. Related to the engineering concept of optimization, the next chapter deals with [[adaptationism]], which Dennett endorses, calling [[Stephen Jay Gould|Gould]] and [[Richard Lewontin|Lewontin]]'s &quot;refutation&quot; of it&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Gould |first=Stephen Jay |authorlink=Stephen Jay Gould |author2=[[Richard Lewontin]] |year=1979 |title=The Spandrels of San Marco and the Panglossian Paradigm: A Critique of the Adaptationist Programme |journal=[[Proceedings of the Royal Society|Proceedings of the Royal Society of London B]] |volume=205 |issue=1161 |pages=581–598 |url=http://www.aaas.org/spp/dser/03_Areas/evolution/perspectives/Gould_Lewontin_1979.shtml |doi=10.1098/rspb.1979.0086 |pmid=42062 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090426061028/http://www.aaas.org/spp/dser/03_Areas/evolution/perspectives/Gould_Lewontin_1979.shtml |archive-date=2009-04-26 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; an illusion. Dennett thinks adaptationism is, in fact, the best way of uncovering constraints&lt;!-- pretty sure we should have an article on constraints too --&gt;.

The tenth chapter, entitled &quot;[[Bully for Brontosaurus]]&quot;, is an extended [[critique]] of [[Stephen Jay Gould]], who Dennett feels has created a distorted view of evolution with his [[popular science|popular]] writings; his &quot;self-styled revolutions&quot; against adaptationism, [[gradualism]] and other orthodox Darwinism all being false alarms. The final chapter of part II dismisses [[directed mutation]], the [[inheritance of acquired traits]] and [[Pierre Teilhard de Chardin|Teilhard]]'s &quot;[[Omega Point]]&quot;, and insists that other controversies and hypotheses  (like the [[unit of selection]] and [[Panspermia]]) have no dire consequences for orthodox Darwinism.

===Part III: Mind, Meaning, Mathematics and Morality===
[[Image:Leviathan.jpg|thumb|The frontispiece to Thomas Hobbes' ''[[Leviathan (Hobbes book)|Leviathan]]'', which appears at the beginning of chapter 16 &quot;On the Origin of Morality&quot;.]]
&quot;Mind, Meaning, Mathematics and Morality&quot; is the name of Part III, which begins with a quote from Nietzsche.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=[[Daybreak: Thoughts on the Prejudices of Morality]] |last=Nietzsche |first=Friedrich |authorlink=Friedrich Nietzsche |year=1881 |publisher= |location= |isbn= |pages= |url= }} Translated by R. J. Hollingdale. [Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1982].&lt;/ref&gt; Chapter 12, &quot;The Cranes of Culture&quot;, discusses [[cultural evolution]]. It asserts that the [[meme]] has a role to play in our understanding of culture, and that it allows [[human]]s, alone among [[animal]]s, to &quot;transcend&quot; our [[gene-centered view of evolution|selfish genes]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=[[The Selfish Gene]] |last=Dawkins |first=Richard |authorlink=Richard Dawkins |year=1976 |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=Oxford |isbn= |pages= |url= }}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;Losing Our Minds to Darwin&quot; follows, a chapter about the evolution of brains, minds and [[language]]. Dennett criticizes [[Noam Chomsky]]'s perceived resistance to the [[evolution of language]], its modeling by [[artificial intelligence]], and [[reverse engineering]].

The evolution of meaning&lt;!-- to what can I link? maybe [[Meaning (philosophy of language)]]? --&gt; is then discussed, and Dennett uses a series of [[thought experiment]]s to persuade the reader that meaning is the product of meaningless, algorithmic processes.

[[Image:Racknitz - The Turk 3.jpg|thumb|left|[[Wolfgang von Kempelen|Von Kempelen]]'s chess automaton, discussed in chapter 15.]]
Chapter 15 asserts that [[Gödel's incompleteness theorems|Gödel's Theorem]] does not make certain sorts of [[artificial intelligence]] impossible. Dennett extends his criticism to [[Roger Penrose]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=[[The Emperor's New Mind]] |last=Penrose |first=Roger |authorlink=Roger Penrose |year=1989 |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=Oxford |isbn= |pages= |url= }}&lt;/ref&gt; The subject then moves on to the [[evolution of morality|origin and evolution of morality]], beginning with [[Thomas Hobbes]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=[[Leviathan (Hobbes book)|Leviathan]] |last=Hobbes |first=Thomas |authorlink=Thomas Hobbes |year=1651 |publisher=Crooke |location=London |isbn= |pages= |url= }}&lt;/ref&gt; (who Dennett calls &quot;the first [[sociobiology|sociobiologist]]&quot;) and [[Friedrich Nietzsche]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=[[On the Genealogy of Morals]] |last=Nietzsche |first=Friedrich |authorlink=Friedrich Nietzsche |year=1887 |publisher= |location= |isbn= |pages= |url= }} Translated by [[Walter Kaufmann (philosopher)|Walter Kaufmann]] [New York: Vintage, 1967].&lt;/ref&gt; He concludes that only an evolutionary analysis of [[ethics]] makes sense, though he cautions against some varieties of 'greedy ethical reductionism'. Before moving to the next chapter, he discusses some [[sociobiology]] controversies.

The penultimate chapter, entitled &quot;Redesigning Morality&quot;, begins by asking if ethics can be 'naturalized'. Dennett does not believe there is much hope of discovering an algorithm for doing the right thing, but expresses optimism in our ability to design and redesign our approach to moral problems. In &quot;The Future of an Idea&quot;, the book's last chapter, Dennett praises [[biodiversity]], including [[cultural diversity]]. In closing, he uses ''[[Beauty and the Beast]]'' as an analogy; although Darwin's idea may seem dangerous, it is actually quite beautiful.

== Central concepts ==

=== Design Space ===
Dennett believes there is little or no principled difference between the naturally generated products of evolution and the man-made artifacts of human creativity and culture. For this reason he indicates deliberately that the complex fruits of the tree of life are in a very meaningful sense &quot;designed&quot;&amp;mdash;even though he does not believe evolution was guided by a higher intelligence.

Dennett supports using the notion of memes to better understand [[cultural evolution]]. He also believes even human creativity might operate by the Darwinian mechanism.&lt;ref&gt;[http://ase.tufts.edu/cogstud/papers/valencia.htm Could there be a Darwinian Account of Human Creativity?]&lt;/ref&gt; This leads him to propose that the &quot;space&quot; describing biological &quot;design&quot; is connected with the space describing human culture and technology.

A precise mathematical definition of Design Space is not given in ''Darwin's Dangerous Idea''. Dennett acknowledges this and admits he is offering a philosophical idea rather than a scientific formulation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://ase.tufts.edu/cogstud/papers/philbook.htm Reply to Gregory Mulhauser]&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Natural selection as an algorithm ===
Dennett describes [[natural selection]] as a substrate-neutral, mindless [[algorithm]] for moving through Design Space.

=== Universal acid ===
Dennett writes about the fantasy of a [[alkahest|&quot;universal acid&quot;]] as a liquid that is so corrosive that it would eat through anything that it came into contact with, even a potential container.  Such a powerful substance would transform everything it was applied to; leaving something very different in its wake.  This is where Dennett draws parallels from the “universal acid” to Darwin's idea: 
&lt;blockquote&gt;
“it eats through just about every traditional concept, and leaves in its wake a revolutionized world-view, with most of the old landmarks still recognizable, but transformed in fundamental ways.”
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
While there are people who would like to see Darwin's idea contained within the field of biology, Dennett asserts that this dangerous idea inevitably “leaks” out to transform other fields as well.

===Skyhooks and cranes===
Dennett uses the term &quot;skyhook&quot; to describe a source of design [[complexity]] that does not build on lower, simpler layers&amp;mdash;in simple terms, a [[miracle]].

In philosophical arguments concerning the [[reduction (philosophy)|reducibility]] (or [[irreducible (philosophy)|otherwise]]) of the human mind, Dennett's concept pokes fun at the idea of [[intelligent design]] emanating from on high, either originating from one or more [[god]]s, or providing its own grounds in an absurd, [[Baron Munchausen|Munchausen]]-like [[bootstrapping]] manner.

Dennett also accuses various competing [[neo-Darwinism|neo-Darwinian]] ideas of making use of such supposedly unscientific skyhooks in explaining [[evolution]], coming down particularly hard on the ideas of [[Stephen Jay Gould]].

Dennett contrasts theories of complexity that require such miracles with those based on &quot;[[crane (machine)|crane]]s&quot;, structures that permit the construction of entities of greater complexity but are themselves founded solidly &quot;on the ground&quot; of physical science.

== Reception ==
In ''[[The New York Review of Books]]'', [[John Maynard Smith]] praised ''Darwin's Dangerous Idea'':

&lt;blockquote&gt;
It is therefore a pleasure to meet a philosopher who understands what Darwinism is about, and approves of it.
Dennett goes well beyond biology. He sees Darwinism as a corrosive acid, capable of dissolving our earlier belief and forcing a reconsideration of much of sociology and philosophy. Although modestly written, this is not a modest book. Dennett argues that, if we understand ''Darwin's dangerous idea'', we are forced to reject or modify much of our current intellectual baggage...&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nybooks.com/articles/1703 New York Review of Books: John Maynard Smith &quot;Genes, Memes, &amp; Minds&quot;, 1995]&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Writing in the same publication, [[Stephen Jay Gould]] criticised ''Darwin's Dangerous Idea'' for being an &quot;influential but misguided ultra-Darwinian manifesto&quot;:

&lt;blockquote&gt;Daniel Dennett devotes the longest chapter in ''Darwin's Dangerous Idea'' to an excoriating caricature of my ideas, all in order to bolster his defense of Darwinian fundamentalism. If an argued case can be discerned at all amid the slurs and sneers, it would have to be described as an effort to claim that I have, thanks to some literary skill, tried to raise a few piddling, insignificant, and basically conventional ideas to &quot;revolutionary&quot; status, challenging what he takes to be the true Darwinian scripture. Since Dennett shows so little understanding of evolutionary theory beyond natural selection, his critique of my work amounts to little more than sniping at false targets of his own construction. He never deals with my ideas as such, but proceeds by hint, innuendo, false attribution, and error.&lt;ref name=&quot;gould&quot;&gt;[http://cogweb.ucla.edu/Debate/Gould.html Evolution: The Pleasures of Pluralism&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Gould was also a harsh critic of Dennett's idea of the &quot;universal [[acid]]&quot; of natural selection and of his subscription to the idea of [[memetics]]; Dennett responded, and the exchange between Dennett, Gould, and [[Robert Wright (journalist)|Robert Wright]] was printed in the ''New York Review of Books''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.nybooks.com/articles/1096 |author= Stephen Jay Gould, Daniel Dennett | title= 'Darwinian Fundamentalism': An Exchange |year= 1997}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Biologist [[H. Allen Orr]] wrote a critical review emphasizing similar points in the ''[[Boston Review]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= https://bostonreview.net/archives/BR21.3/Orr.html | author = H. Allen Orr | title = Dennett's Strange Idea| journal = Boston Review | year = 1996 | number = 3}} &lt;/ref&gt;

The book has also provoked a negative reaction from creationists; [[Frederick Crews]] writes that ''Darwin's Dangerous Idea'' &quot;rivals [[Richard Dawkins]]'s ''[[The Blind Watchmaker]]'' as the creationists' most cordially hated text.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Crews, Frederick. ''Follies of the Wise: Dissenting Essays''. Shoemaker Hoard, 2006, p. 267.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Bayes' theorem]]
*[[Jerry Fodor]]
*[[John Searle]]
*[[Universal Darwinism]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Darwin's Dangerous Idea}}

*[http://cogweb.ucla.edu/Debate/Gould.html Gould's response] to Dennett's &quot;neo-Darwinian orthodoxy&quot; from the New York Review of Books, June 26, 1997.
*[http://dannyreviews.com/h/Darwins_Dangerous_Idea.html Danny Yee's Book Review of &quot;Darwin's Dangerous Idea&quot;]
*{{cite web|url= http://www.nybooks.com/articles/1096 |author= Stephen Jay Gould, Daniel Dennett | title= 'Darwinian Fundamentalism': An Exchange |year= 1997}}
*[http://serendip.brynmawr.edu/sci_cult/evolit/s04/web2/rrich.html Where do Morals Come From?] Rebekah Rich, Bryn Mawr College, Spring 2004

{{Dennett}}

[[Category:1995 non-fiction books]]
[[Category:Analytic philosophy literature]]
[[Category:Books about evolution]]
[[Category:Books by Daniel Dennett]]
[[Category:Cognitive science literature]]
[[Category:English-language books]]
[[Category:Simon &amp; Schuster books]]
[[Category:Books about meaning of life]]</text>
      <sha1>mh03i53rf9gthgdn40s36bn8h4835og</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
