  <page>
    <title>Dublin Core</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8742</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942242994</id>
      <parentid>942107508</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-23T14:24:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Hooman Mallahzadeh</username>
        <id>37666339</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Dot is incorrect in the middle of sentence, a comma should be placed here.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[file:DCMI-logo.svg|thumb|220px|Logo image of DCMI, which formulates Dublin Core]]
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}
The '''Dublin Core Schema''' is a small set of [[Controlled vocabulary|vocabulary terms]] that can be used to describe digital resources (video, images, web pages, etc.), as well as physical resources such as books or CDs, and objects like artworks.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.dublincore.org/documents/dcmi-type-vocabulary/ |title=DCMI Type Vocabulary |website=dublincore.org |accessdate=11 November 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; The full set of Dublin Core [[metadata]] terms can be found on the [http://dublincore.org/documents/dcmi-terms/ Dublin Core Metadata Initiative (DCMI) website].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://dublincore.org/documents/dcmi-terms/ |title=DCMI Metadata Terms |website=dublincore.org |accessdate=11 November 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; The original set of 15 classic&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://dublincore.org/specifications/ |title=DCMI Specifications |website=dublincore.org |date=14 December 2009 |accessdate=11 November 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; metadata terms, known as the Dublin Core Metadata Element Set (DCMES),&lt;ref name=&quot;DCMES&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://dublincore.org/documents/dces/ |title=Dublin Core Metadata Element Set, Version 1.1 |website=dublincore.org |accessdate=11 November 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; is endorsed in the following standards documents:

* IETF RFC 5013&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc5013.txt The Dublin Core Metadata Element Set], Dublin Core Metadata Initiative, August 2007&lt;/ref&gt;
* ISO Standard 15836-1:2017&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.iso.org/iso/iso_catalogue/catalogue_ics/catalogue_detail_ics.htm?csnumber=71339 |title=ISO 15836-1:2017 - Information and documentation - The Dublin Core metadata element set - Part 1: Core elements |publisher=Iso.org |date= May 2017 |accessdate=2 October 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* NISO Standard Z39.85&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.niso.org/kst/reports/standards?step=2&amp;gid=None&amp;project_key=9b7bffcd2daeca6198b4ee5a848f9beec2f600e5 |title=NISO Standards - National Information Standards Organization |publisher=Niso.org |date=22 May 2007 |accessdate=5 April 2013 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20111116005843/http://www.niso.org/kst/reports/standards?step=2&amp;gid=None&amp;project_key=9b7bffcd2daeca6198b4ee5a848f9beec2f600e5 |archive-date=16 November 2011 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Dublin Core metadata may be used for multiple purposes, from simple resource description to combining metadata vocabularies of different [[Metadata#Standards|metadata standards]], to providing interoperability for metadata vocabularies in the [[linked data]] cloud and [[Semantic Web]] implementations.

==Background==
&quot;Dublin&quot; refers to [[Dublin, Ohio]], USA where the schema originated during the 1995 invitational OCLC/NCSA Metadata Workshop,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dublincore.org/news/1995/03-01-the-oclcncsa-metadata-workshop-the-essential-elements-of-network-object-description/ |title=DCMI: The OCLC/NCSA Metadata Workshop: The Essential Elements of Network Object Description|author=|date=|website=www.dublincore.org|accessdate=13 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; hosted by the [[OCLC]] (Online Computer Library Center), a library consortium based in Dublin, and the [[National Center for Supercomputing Applications]] (NCSA). &quot;Core&quot; refers to the metadata terms as &quot;broad and generic being usable for describing a wide range of resources&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;DCMES&quot;/&gt; The semantics of Dublin Core were established and are maintained by an international, cross-disciplinary group of professionals from [[librarianship]], [[computer science]], [[text encoding]], [[museum]]s, and other related fields of scholarship and practice.

Starting in 2000, the Dublin Core community focused on &quot;[[application profile]]s&quot; &amp;ndash; the idea that metadata records would use Dublin Core together with other specialized vocabularies to meet particular implementation requirements. During that time, the World Wide Web Consortium's work on a generic [[data model]] for metadata, the [[Resource Description Framework]] (RDF), was maturing. As part of an extended set of DCMI metadata terms, Dublin Core became one of the most popular vocabularies for use with RDF, more recently in the context of the [[linked data]] movement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://dublincore.org/metadata-basics/|title=Metadata Basics|publisher=DCMI|accessdate=19 February 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The '''Dublin Core Metadata Initiative''' (DCMI)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://dublincore.org/ |title=DCMI Home: Dublin Core® Metadata Initiative (DCMI) |publisher=Dublincore.org |date= |accessdate=2015-12-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; provides an open forum for the development of interoperable online [[metadata standards]] for a broad range of purposes and of business models. DCMI's activities include consensus-driven working groups, global conferences and workshops, standards liaison, and educational efforts to promote widespread acceptance of metadata standards and practices. In 2008, DCMI separated from OCLC and incorporated as an independent entity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=OCLC Research and the Dublin Core Metadata Initiative | url=http://www.oclc.org/research/activities/past/orprojects/dublincore/default.htm | accessdate=21 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Currently, any and all changes that are made to the Dublin Core standard, are reviewed by a DCMI Usage Board within the context of a DCMI Namespace Policy (DCMI-NAMESPACE). This policy describes how terms are assigned and also sets limits on the amount of editorial changes allowed to the labels, definitions, and usage comments.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://dublincore.org/documents/dces/ |title=Dublin Core Metadata Element Set, Version 1.1 |publisher=Dublincore.org |date= |accessdate=2015-12-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Levels of the standard==
The Dublin Core standard originally included two levels: Simple and Qualified. '''Simple Dublin Core''' comprised 15 elements; '''Qualified Dublin Core''' included three additional elements (Audience, Provenance and RightsHolder), as well as a group of element refinements (also called qualifiers) that could refine the semantics of the elements in ways that may be useful in resource discovery.

Since 2012, the two have been incorporated into the '''DCMI Metadata Terms''' as a single set of terms using the [[Resource Description Framework|RDF]] data model.&lt;ref name=&quot;dublincore1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://dublincore.org/documents/dcmi-terms/ |title=DCMI Metadata Terms |publisher=Dublincore.org |date= |accessdate=2015-12-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; The full set of elements is found under the namespace http://purl.org/dc/terms/. Because the definition of the terms often contains domains and ranges, which may not be compatible with the pre-RDF definitions used for the original 15 Dublin Core elements, there is a separate namespace for the original 15 elements as previously defined: http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://dublincore.org/documents/dces/|title=DCMI: Dublin Core Metadata Element Set, Version 1.1: Reference Description|author=|date=|website=dublincore.org|accessdate=3 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Dublin Core Metadata Element Set===
The original '''DCMES''' Version 1.1 consists of 15 metadata elements, defined this way in the original specification:&lt;ref name=&quot;DCMES&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dublincore.org/specifications/dublin-core/dcmi-terms/#section-3 Section 3: Properties] of DCMI Metadata Terms at dublincore.org&lt;/ref&gt;
# Contributor – “An entity responsible for making contributions to the resource.”
# Coverage – “The spatial or temporal topic of the resource, the spatial applicability of the resource, or the jurisdiction under which the resource is relevant.”
# Creator – “An entity primarily responsible for making the resource.”
# Date – “A point or period of time associated with an event in the lifecycle of the resource.”
# Description – “An account of the resource.”
# Format – “The file format, physical medium, or dimensions of the resource.”
# Identifier – “An unambiguous reference to the resource within a given context.”
# Language – “A language of the resource.”
# Publisher – “An entity responsible for making the resource available.”
# Relation – “A related resource.”
# Rights – “Information about rights held in and over the resource.”
# Source – “A related resource from which the described resource is derived.”
# Subject – “The topic of the resource.”
# Title – “A name given to the resource.”
# Type – “The nature or genre of the resource.”

Each Dublin Core element is optional and may be repeated. The DCMI has established standard ways to refine elements and encourage the use of encoding and vocabulary schemes. There is no prescribed order in Dublin Core for presenting or using the elements. The Dublin Core became a NISO standards, Z39.85, and IETF RFC 5013 in 2007,  ISO 15836 standard in 2009 and is used as a base-level data element set for the description of learning resources in the [[ISO/IEC 19788]]-2 Metadata for learning resources (MLR) &amp;ndash; Part 2: Dublin Core elements, prepared by the [[ISO/IEC JTC1/SC36|ISO/IEC JTC1 SC36]].

Full information on element definitions and term relationships can be found in the Dublin Core Metadata Registry.&lt;ref name=&quot;registry&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://dcmi.kc.tsukuba.ac.jp/dcregistry/ |title=Dublin Core Metadata Registry |access-date=18 March 2008 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170507045948/http://dcmi.kc.tsukuba.ac.jp/dcregistry/ |archive-date=7 May 2017 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Encoding examples====
: {{code|2=html5|1=&lt;meta name=&quot;DC.Format&quot; content=&quot;video/mpeg; 10 minutes&quot; /&gt;}}
: {{code|2=html5|1=&lt;meta name=&quot;DC.Language&quot; content=&quot;en&quot; /&gt;}}
: {{code|2=html5|1=&lt;meta name=&quot;DC.Publisher&quot; content=&quot;publisher-name&quot; /&gt;}}
: {{code|2=html5|1=&lt;meta name=&quot;DC.Title&quot; content=&quot;HYP&quot; /&gt;}}

====Example of use [and mention] by WebCite====
On the &quot;archive form&quot; web page for [[WebCite]] it says,&lt;ref name=&quot;WebCite form&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://webcitation.org/archive |title= WebCite archive form |website=[[WebCite]] |quote=These are Dublin Core elements. Entering these will help you to correctly cite the URL. [...]}}{{cbignore}}&lt;/ref&gt; in part: &quot;Metadata (optional): These are Dublin Core elements. [...]&quot;.

===Qualified Dublin Core===
(Superseded in 2008 by the DCMI Metadata Terms.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://dublincore.org/documents/2000/07/11/dcmes-qualifiers/ |title=Dublin Core Qualifiers |publisher=Dublincore.org |date= |accessdate=2017-05-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;) Subsequent to the specification of the original 15 elements, an ongoing process to develop exemplary terms extending or refining the DCMES was begun. The additional terms were identified, generally in working groups of the DCMI, and judged by the DCMI Usage Board to be in conformance with principles of good practice for the qualification of Dublin Core metadata elements.

Element refinements make the meaning of an element narrower or more specific. A refined element shares the meaning of the unqualified element, but with a more restricted scope. The guiding principle for the qualification of Dublin Core elements, colloquially known as the ''Dumb-Down Principle'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dublincore.org/usage/documents/principles/|title=DCMI: DCMI Grammatical Principles|author=|date=|website=www.dublincore.org|accessdate=3 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; states that an application that does not understand a specific element refinement term should be able to ignore the qualifier and treat the metadata value as if it were an unqualified (broader) element. While this may result in some loss of specificity, the remaining element value (without the qualifier) should continue to be generally correct and useful for discovery.

In addition to element refinements, Qualified Dublin Core includes a set of recommended encoding schemes, designed to aid in the interpretation of an element value. These schemes include [[Controlled vocabulary|controlled vocabularies]] and formal notations or parsing rules. A value expressed using an encoding scheme may thus be a token selected from a controlled vocabulary (for example, a term from a classification system or set of subject headings) or a string formatted in accordance with a formal notation, for example, &quot;2000-12-31&quot; as the ISO standard expression of a date. If an encoding scheme is not understood by an application, the value may still be useful to a '''human reader'''.

'''Audience, Provenance''' and '''RightsHolder''' are elements, but not part of the Simple Dublin Core 15 elements. Use Audience, Provenance and RightsHolder only when using Qualified Dublin Core. DCMI also maintains a small, general vocabulary recommended for use within the element Type. This vocabulary currently consists of 12 terms.&lt;ref name=&quot;registry&quot;/&gt;

===DCMI Metadata Terms===
The DCMI Metadata Terms lists the current set of the Dublin Core vocabulary.&lt;ref name=&quot;dublincore1&quot;/&gt; This set includes the fifteen terms of the DCMES (in ''italic''), as well as the qualified terms. Each term has a unique URI in the namespace http://purl.org/dc/terms, and all are defined as [[Resource Description Framework|RDF]] properties.

{{columns-list|colwidth=18em|
*abstract
*accessRights
*accrualMethod
*accrualPeriodicity
*accrualPolicy
*alternative
*audience
*available
*bibliographicCitation
*conformsTo
*''contributor''
*''coverage''
*created
*''creator''
*''date''
*dateAccepted
*dateCopyrighted
*dateSubmitted
*''description''
*educationLevel
*extent
*''format''
*hasFormat
*hasPart
*hasVersion
*''identifier''
*instructionalMethod
*isFormatOf
*isPartOf
*isReferencedBy
*isReplacedBy
*isRequiredBy
*issued
*isVersionOf
*''language''
*license
*mediator
*medium
*modified
*provenance
*''publisher''
*references
*''relation''
*replaces
*requires
*''rights''
*rightsHolder
*''source''
*spatial
*''subject''
*tableOfContents
*temporal
*''title''
*''type''
*valid
}}

==Syntax==
Syntax choices for metadata expressed with the Dublin Core elements depend on context. Dublin Core concepts and semantics are designed to be syntax independent{{clarify|date=May 2019}} and apply to a variety of contexts, as long as the metadata is in a form suitable for interpretation by both machines and people.

The '''Dublin Core Abstract Model'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://dublincore.org/documents/abstract-model/|title=DCMI: DCMI Abstract Model|author=|date=|website=dublincore.org|accessdate=3 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; provides a reference model against which particular Dublin Core encoding guidelines can be compared, independent of any particular encoding syntax. Such a reference model helps implementers get a better understanding of the kinds of descriptions they are trying to encode and facilitates the development of better mappings and translations between different syntaxes.

==Notable applications==
One [[Document Type Definition]] based on Dublin Core is the Open Source Metadata Framework (OMF) specification.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ibiblio.org/osrt/omf/|title=m e t a l a b open source metadata framework|author=|date=|website=www.ibiblio.org|accessdate=3 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; OMF is in turn used by [[Rarian]] (superseding [[ScrollKeeper]]), which is used by the [[GNOME]] desktop and [[KDE]] help browsers and the ScrollServer documentation server.

[[PBCore]] is also based on Dublin Core.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://pbcore.org/schema/|title=PBCore Schema – PBCore|last=|first=|date=|website=pbcore.org|language=en-US|access-date=2018-01-19|quote=PBCore is built on the foundation of the Dublin Core (ISO 15836), an international standard for resource discovery.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Zope]] [[Zope Content Management Framework|CMF's]] Metadata products, used by the [[Plone (software)|Plone]], [[ERP5]], the Nuxeo CPS [[Content management system]]s, [[SimpleDL]], and [[Fedora Commons]] also implement Dublin Core. The [[EPUB]] [[e-book]] format uses Dublin Core metadata in the [[OPF (file format)|OPF file]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.idpf.org/epub/20/spec/OPF_2.0_latest.htm#Section2.2 |title=Open Packaging Format (OPF) § Publication Metadata |website=[[International Digital Publishing Forum]] |accessdate=11 November 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Australian Government Locator Service]] (AGLS) metadata standard is an application profile of Dublin Core.&lt;ref name = &quot;AGLS Reference&quot;&gt;{{Cite web
| title = AGLS Metadata Standard Part 1 – Reference Description
| publisher = National Archives of Australia
| date = 30 June 2010
| url = http://www.agls.gov.au/pdf/AGLS%20Metadata%20Standard%20Part%201%20Reference%20Description.PDF
| accessdate = 28 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|5}}

==See also==
* [[Metadata registry]]
* [[Metadata Object Description Schema]]
* [[Ontology (information science)]]
* [[Open Archives Initiative]] (OAI)
* [[Controlled vocabulary]]
* [[Interoperability]]
* [[Asset Description Metadata Schema]] ([https://www.w3.org/TR/vocab-adms/ ADMS]), a metadata standard maintained by the [[World Wide Web Consortium|W3C]] for describing semantic standards. Implemented on [[Joinup collaboration platform|Joinup]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://joinup.ec.europa.eu/release/adms-ap-joinup-version/20 |title=ADMS-AP for Joinup version 2.0 |website=[[Joinup collaboration platform|Joinup]] |date=December 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
* [[Metadata Encoding and Transmission Standard]] (METS), maintained by the [[Library of Congress]] for the [[Digital Library Federation]]
* [[Preservation Metadata: Implementation Strategies]] (PREMIS)

===Related software===
* [[Fedora Commons|Fedora]], a [[digital asset management]] (DAM) architecture capable of implementing [[OAI-PMH]] (thus, also Dublin Core).
* [[Omeka]], a free and open source [[content management system]] using an unqualified Dublin Core metadata standard.

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite book |title=Organising Knowledge in a Global Society |last=Harvey |first=Ross |last2=Hider |first2=Philip |year=2004 |publisher=[[Charles Sturt University]] |location=Wagga Wagga NSW |isbn=1-876938-66-8}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20110426155937/https://www.inf.unibz.it/courses/images/stories/2005_2006/Digital_Libraries/dini-less-5-6.ppt Dublin Core presentation], by Luca Dini, lecturer at the [[Free University of Bozen-Bolzano]]

==External links==
{{Wikiversity|Digital Libraries/Metadata}}
* {{Official website}}
* [http://xml.coverpages.org/ni2005-03-21-a.html Dublin Core Metadata Initiative Publishes DCMI Abstract Model] (''Cover Pages'', March 2005)
* [https://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-userguide-3-0.html Metadata Object Description Schema (MODS)]

{{Semantic Web}}
{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Archival science]]
[[Category:Bibliography file formats]]
[[Category:Information management]]
[[Category:Interoperability]]
[[Category:ISO standards]]
[[Category:Knowledge representation]]
[[Category:Library cataloging and classification]]
[[Category:Metadata standards]]
[[Category:Museology]]
[[Category:Records management]]
[[Category:Reference models]]
[[Category:Semantic Web]]</text>
      <sha1>dgnrzk1g53zfxijsasa1eqb8sh8yvdv</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
