  <page>
    <title>DKW</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8707</id>
    <revision>
      <id>932022091</id>
      <parentid>930562479</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-12-22T22:41:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Cyberfan195</username>
        <id>36384742</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* External links */ fixed.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|German car and motorcycle marque, now Audi}}
{{more citations needed|date=July 2019}}
{{Infobox company
|name         = DKW
|logo         = Dkw-symbol-vorn.jpg
|logo_size    = 200px
|logo_caption = The logotype of DKW Auto Union
|foundation   = 1916
|defunct      = 1966
|fate         = merged into [[Auto Union]] in 1932, marque defunct 1969
|successor    = Auto Union AG (1932-1969)&lt;br&gt;Audi NSU Auto Union AG (1969-1985)&lt;br&gt;Audi AG (1985-present)
|location     = [[Zschopau]], Germany (1906-1932)&lt;br&gt;[[Chemnitz]] (1932-1949)&lt;br&gt;[[Ingolstadt]] (1949-1969)
|industry     = [[Automotive]]
|key_people   = [[Jørgen Skafte Rasmussen|Dr Jørgen Skafte Rasmussen]], founder of DKW&lt;ref name=&quot;MC&quot;&gt;[[The Motor Cycle|Motor Cycle]] 27 August 1964 ''DKW man dies
''. Added 2014-06-16&lt;/ref&gt;
|products     = [[Automobiles]], [[motorcycle]]s
|parent       = 
}}

'''DKW''' ('''''Dampf-Kraft-Wagen''''', {{lang-en|&quot;steam-powered car&quot;}}, also '''''Deutsche Kinder-Wagen''''' {{lang-en| &quot;German kids' car&quot;}}. '''''Das-Kleine-Wunder''''', {{lang-en|&quot;the little wonder&quot; }} or '''''Des-Knaben-Wunsch''''', {{lang-en|&quot;the boy's wish&quot;- from when the company built toy [[two-stroke engine]]s}}) is a German [[automobile|car]] and [[motorcycle]] [[marque]].  DKW was one of the four companies that formed [[Auto Union]] in 1932 and is hence an ancestor of the modern day [[Audi]] company.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.seriouswheels.com/art-four-rings-1.htm|title=History of the Four Rings--Part 1--Audi Auto Union|website=www.seriouswheels.com|accessdate=8 May 2018|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20161210010605/http://www.seriouswheels.com/art-four-rings-1.htm|archivedate=10 December 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1916, Danish [[engineer]] [[Jørgen Skafte Rasmussen]] founded a factory in [[Zschopau]], [[Saxony]], Germany, to produce steam fittings. That year he attempted to produce a steam-driven car, called the DKW.&lt;ref name=Odin&gt;Odin, L.C. ''World in Motion 1939 - The whole of the year's automobile production''. Belvedere Publishing, 2015. ASIN: B00ZLN91ZG.&lt;/ref&gt; Although unsuccessful, he made a two-stroke toy engine in 1919, called ''Des Knaben Wunsch'' &amp;ndash; &quot;the boy's wish&quot;. He put a slightly modified version of this engine into a motorcycle and called it ''Das Kleine Wunder''&lt;ref name= Odin /&gt; &amp;ndash; &quot;the little wonder&quot; the initials from this becoming the '''DKW''' brand: by the late 1920s, DKW was the world's largest motorcycle manufacturer.

In September 1924, DKW bought {{ill|Slaby-Beringer|de|vertical-align=sup}}, saving them from Germany's [[hyperinflation]] [[Hyperinflation in the Weimar Republic|economic crisis]]. Rudolf Slaby became chief-engineer at DKW.&lt;ref&gt;
 {{
  cite web
| title='Unfortunately the fledgling company was adversely hit &lt;!--
  --&gt; by the German economic crisis and by 1924 was plunged &lt;!--
  --&gt; into insolvency. Rasmussen saw an opportunity in Slaby-Beringer's &lt;!--
  --&gt; crisis and offered to buy out the company. Both Slaby and Beringer &lt;!--
  --&gt; took shares in the Rasmussen Group of companies and Slaby &lt;!--
  --&gt; became the chief engineer at DKW's newly formed automobile division. &lt;!--
  --&gt; By the time the company closed its doors in &lt;!--
  --&gt; September 1924 2005 Elecrowagens had been built. &lt;!--
  --&gt; The last 266 cars were powered by a DKW motorcycle &lt;!--
  --&gt; engine mounted at the rear.' &lt;!--
  --&gt; &lt;br&gt;in&lt;br&gt; &lt;!--
  --&gt; dkwautounionproject.blogspot.com/2017/06/1919-slaby-beringer-elektrowagen.html &lt;!--
  --&gt; &lt;br&gt; from google (dkw slaby-beringer september1924) result 4 &lt;!--
  --&gt; &lt;br&gt; from 'Aber auch dies half wenig und im Juni 1924 musste &lt;!--
  --&gt; die SB-Automobil-Gesellschaft Konkurs anmelden. Insgesamt &lt;!--
  --&gt; sind 2005 SB-Wagen gebaut worden, davon 266 mit DKW-Motor. &lt;!--
  --&gt; Am 1. September 1924 wurde die Produktionsstätte in Berlin stillgelegt.' &lt;!--
  --&gt; &lt;br&gt;in&lt;br&gt;de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slaby-Beringer &lt;!--
  --&gt; &lt;br&gt;with translation-help from translate.google.com/#de/en
| url=http://heinkelscooter.blogspot.com/2017/04/1919-slaby-beringer-elektrowagen.html
  }}
&lt;/ref&gt;
In 1932, DKW merged with [[Audi]], [[Horch]] and [[Wanderer (car)|Wanderer]] to form Auto Union.&lt;ref name= Odin /&gt; After [[World War II]], DKW moved to [[West Germany]]. The original factory became [[MZ Motorrad- und Zweiradwerk|MZ]].&lt;ref name=&quot;MC&quot;/&gt; Auto Union came under [[Daimler-Benz]] ownership in 1957 and was purchased by the [[Volkswagen Group]] in 1964. The last German-built DKW car was the [[DKW F102|F102]], which ceased production in 1966. Its successor, the [[four-stroke]] [[Audi F103|F103]], was marketed under the Audi brand, another Auto Union marque.

DKW-badged cars continued to be built under license in Brazil and Argentina until 1967 and 1969 respectively.  The DKW trademark is currently owned by Auto Union GmbH, a wholly owned subsidiary of Audi AG which also owns the rights to other historical trademarks and intellectual property of the Auto Union combine.

==Automobiles made between 1928 and 1942==
[[File:MHV DKW F1 1931 01.jpg|thumb|1931 DKW F1]]
DKW cars were made from 1928 until 1966, apart from the interruption caused by the Second World War. DKWs always used two-stroke engines, reflecting the company's position by the end of the 1920s as the world's largest producer of motorcycles. The first DKW car, the small and rather crude [[DKW Typ P|Typ P]], emerged on 7 May 1928&lt;ref name=&quot;Oswald, p 86&quot;&gt;[[#Oswald|Oswald]], p 86&lt;/ref&gt; and the model continued to be built at the company's [[Spandau]] (Berlin) plant, first as a roadster and later as a stylish if basic sports car, until 1931.

More significant was a series of inexpensive cars built 300&amp;nbsp;km (185 miles) to the south in Zwickau in the plant acquired by [[Jørgen Skafte Rasmussen|the company's owner]] in 1928 when he had become the majority owner in [[Audi|Audi Werke AG]].&lt;ref&gt;[[#Oswald|Oswald]], p 85&lt;/ref&gt; Models [[DKW F1|F1]] to [[DKW F8|F8]] (F for Front) were built between 1931 and 1942, with successor models reappearing after the end of the [[Second World War|war]] in 1945. They were the first volume production cars in Europe with [[front wheel drive]], and were powered by [[transversely mounted engine|transversely mounted]] two-cylinder two-stroke engines. Displacement was 584 or 692&amp;nbsp;cc: claimed maximum power was initially 15 PS, and from 1931 a choice between 18 or {{convert|20|hp|abbr=on}}. These models had a generator that doubled as a starter, mounted directly on the [[crankshaft]], known as a [[Dynastart]].&lt;ref&gt;[[#Oswald|Oswald]], p 94 - 103&lt;/ref&gt; DKWs from Zwickau notched up approximately 218,000 units between 1931 and 1942.&lt;ref name=&quot;Oswald, p 86&quot;/&gt; Most cars were sold on the home market and over 85% of DKWs produced in the 1930s were the little F series cars: DKW reached second place in German sales by 1934 and stayed there, accounting for 189,369 of the cars sold between 1931 and 1938, more than 16% of the market.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Oswald|Oswald]], p 531&lt;/ref&gt;

Between 1929 and 1940, DKW produced a less well remembered but technically intriguing series of rear-wheel drive cars called (among other names) [[DKW Typ 4=8|''Schwebeklasse'' and ''Sonderklasse'']] with two-stroke [[V4 engine|V4]] engines.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Oswald|Oswald]], p 87&lt;/ref&gt; [[Engine displacement]] was 1,000&amp;nbsp;cc, later 1,100&amp;nbsp;cc. The engines had two extra cylinders for [[forced induction]], so they appeared like [[V6 engine]]s but without [[spark plug]]s on the front cylinder pair.

In 1939, DKW made a [[prototype]] with the first [[straight-three engine|three-cylinder engine]], with a displacement of 900&amp;nbsp;cc and producing {{convert|30|hp|kW|abbr=on}}. With a streamlined body, the car could run at {{convert|115|km/h|mph|abbr=on}}. It was put into production after [[World War II]], first as an [[Industrieverband Fahrzeugbau]] (IFA) F9 (later [[Wartburg (car)|Wartburg]]) in [[Zwickau]], [[East Germany]], and shortly afterwards in DKW-form from Düsseldorf as the 3=6 or F91.

DKW engines were used by [[Saab Automobile|Saab]] as a model for the [[Saab two-stroke]] in its [[Saab 92]] car manufacturing venture, in 1947.

==Automobiles made after 1945==
[[File:Osmo Kalpala - 1956 Rally Finland.jpeg|thumb|Osmo Kalpala servicing his DKW during the 1956 [[Rally Finland]].]]

As Auto Union was based in Saxony in what became the [[German Democratic Republic]], it took some time for it to regroup after the war. The company was registered in West Germany as Auto Union GmbH in 1949, first as a spare-part provider, but soon to take up production of the RT 125 motorcycle and a new [[delivery van]], called a ''[[DKW Schnellaster|Schnellaster]]'' F800. Their first line of production took place in [[Düsseldorf]]. This van used the same engine as the last F8 made before the war.

Their first car was the F89 using the body from the prototype F9 made before the war and the two-cylinder [[two-stroke engine]] from the last F8. Production went on until it was replaced by the successful three-cylinder engine that came with the F91. The F91 was in production 1953–1955, and was replaced by the larger F93 in 1956. The F91 and F93 had 900&amp;nbsp;cc three-cylinder two-stroke engines, the first ones delivering {{convert|34|hp|kW|abbr=on}}, the last {{convert|38|hp|kW|abbr=on}}. The ignition system comprised three independent sets of [[Circuit breaker|points]] and [[Ignition coil|coils]], one for each cylinder, with the points mounted in a cluster around a single [[wikt:lobe|lobed]] [[cam]] at the front end of the crankshaft. The cooling system was of the [[convection|free convection]] type assisted by a fan driven from a pulley mounted at the front end of the crankshaft.

The F93 was produced until 1959, and was replaced by the Auto-Union 1000. These models where produced with a 1,000&amp;nbsp;cc two-stroke engine, with a choice between {{convert|44|hp|kW|abbr=on}} or {{convert|50|hp|kW|abbr=on}} S versions until 1963. During this transition, production was moved from Düsseldorf to [[Ingolstadt]], where Audi still has its production. From 1957, the cars could be fitted with a [[saxomat]], an automatic clutch, the only small car then offering this feature. The last versions of the Auto-Union 1000S had [[disc brakes]] as option, an early development for this technology. A sporting 2+2 seater version was available as the Auto-Union 1000 SP from 1957 to 1964, the first years only as a [[coupé]] and from 1962 also as a [[Convertible (car)|convertible]].

In 1956, the very rare [[DKW Monza]] was put into small-scale production on a private initiative, with a sporting two-seater body of [[glassfiber]] on a standard F93 frame. It was first called Solitude, but got its final name from the long-distance speed records it made on the [[Autodromo Nazionale Monza]] in Italy in November 1956. Running in [[Fédération Internationale de l'Automobile]] (FIA) class G, it set records including 48 hours at an average speed of {{convert|140.961|km/h|mph|abbr=on}}, 10,000&amp;nbsp;km at {{convert|139.453|km/h|mph|abbr=on}} and 72 hours at {{convert|139.459|km/h|mph|abbr=on}}. The car was first produced by {{ill|Dannenhauer &amp; Strauss|de|vertical-align=sup}}  in [[Stuttgart]], then by Massholder in [[Heidelberg]] and lastly by Robert Schenk in Stuttgart. The number produced is said to be around 230 and production finished by the end of 1958.
[[File:DKW Junior DeLuxe 1962.JPG|thumb|right|DKW Junior (1962)]]

A more successful range of cars was sold from 1959, the Junior/F12 series based on a modern concept from the late 1950s. The range consists of Junior (basic model) made from 1959 to 1961, Junior de Luxe (a little enhanced) from 1961 to 1963, F11 (a little larger) and F12 (larger and bigger engine) from 1963 to 1965, and F12 Roadster from 1964 to 1965. The Junior/F12 series became quite popular, and many cars were produced. An assembly plant was licensed in Ballincollig, co.cork, Ireland between 1952 and c.1964 and roughly 4,000 vehicles were assembled, ranging from saloons, vans and motorbikes to commercial [[combine harvester]]s. This was the only DKW factory outside Germany in Europe and for many years after its closure its large DKW sign could be visible on the wall of the factory.  The building was demolished in the late 2000s and was redeveloped into the German Aldi store and a McDonald's drive-thru.

All the three-cylinder two-stroke post-war cars had some sporting potential and formed the basis for many [[rallying|rally]] victories in the 1950s and early 1960s. This made DKW the most winning car brand in the European rally league for several years during the fifties.

In 1960, DKW developed a [[V6 engine]] by combining two three-cylinder two-stroke engines, with a capacity of 1,000&amp;nbsp;cc. The capacity was increased and the final V6 in 1966 had a capacity of 1,300&amp;nbsp;cc, which developed {{convert|83|hp|kW|abbr=on}} at 5,000&amp;nbsp;rpm using the standard configuration with two [[carburettor]]s. A four-carburettor version produced {{convert|100|hp|kW|abbr=on}}, a six-carburettor one {{convert|130|hp|kW|abbr=on}}. It weighed only {{convert|84|kg|lb|abbr=on}}. The V6 was planned to be used in the [[DKW Munga]] and the F102. About 100 engines were built for testing purposes and 13 DKW F102 and some Mungas were fitted with the V6 engine in the 1960s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.dyna.co.za/cars/specs.htm |title=DKW Specifications |publisher=Dyna.co.za |date=2008-11-13 |accessdate=2010-10-02 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100605035112/http://www.dyna.co.za/cars/specs.htm |archivedate=2010-06-05 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The last DKW was the F102, coming into production in 1964 as a replacement for the old-looking AU1000. However, the F102 sold poorly, largely due to its two-stroke engine technology which was at the limit of its development. Auto Union's parent, Daimler-Benz, decided to offload the company to Volkswagen. The car was re-engineered with a four-stroke engine and relaunched as the Audi F103. This marked the end of the DKW marque for cars, and the rebirth of the Audi name.

From 1956 to 1961, Dutch importer [[Hart, Nibbrig &amp; Greve]] assembled cars in an abandoned asphalt factory in [[Sassenheim]], where they employed about 120 workers, two transporter, that collected SKD kits from Duesseldorf and build about 13.500 cars. When the DKW plant moved the import of SKD kits stopped, as it became too expensive.&lt;ref&gt;Autokampioen 25/26 2007 &quot;Made in Holland&quot; by Yop Segers&lt;/ref&gt;

==DKW in South America==
From 1956 to 1967, DKW cars were made in Brazil by the local company Vemag (''Veículos e Máquinas Agrícolas S.A.'', &quot;Vehicles and Agricultural Machinery Inc.&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|year=1973|journal=Automobile Quarterly|publisher=Automobile Quarterly|volume=11|issue=4|title=Vemag|quote=the Vemag company that had been manufacturing two-stroke DKW models under license in Brazil.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Vemag was assembling [[Scania-Vabis]] trucks, but Scania Vabis became an independent company in July 1960.&lt;ref name=shapiro&gt;{{cite journal | title = Determinants of Firm Entry into the Brazilian Automobile Manufacturing Industry, 1956-1968 | ref = HShap | first = Helen | last = Shapiro | volume = 65 | journal = The Business History Review | number = 4, The Automobile Industry |date=Winter 1991 | page = 897 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The original plans were to build the Candango off-roader (Munga), a utility vehicle and a four-door sedan, called Vemaguet and Belcar respectively. The first model built was the 900&amp;nbsp;cc F91 Universal but the Belcar and Vemaguet names were applied later.
[[File:1967 DKW-Vemag Belcar.jpg|thumb|A second series 1967 DKW-Vemag Belcar in front of a first series 1964 DKW-Vemag Belcar]]

In 1958, the F94 four-door sedan and station wagon were launched, in the early 1960s renamed Belcar and Vemaguet. The company also produced a luxury coupe (the DKW Fissore) and the off-road [[DKW Munga|Munga]] (locally called Candango). In 1960 Vemag cars received the larger one-litre, {{convert|50|PS|kW|0|abbr=on}} engine from the [[Auto Union 1000]].&lt;ref name=VoGo&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.team.net/www/ktud/saspeci/dkwbr.html |title=DKWs in Brazil |last1=Vogel |first1=Jason |last2=Gomes |first2=Flavio |publisher=KTUD Online Automotive Archive |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130515084413/http://www.team.net/www/ktud/saspeci/dkwbr.html |archivedate=2013-05-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Vemag had a successful official racing team, with the coupe GT Malzoni, with fiberglass body. This project was the foundation of the long-lasting Brazilian sports car brand [[Puma (car manufacturer)|Puma]]. The Brazilian F94 line has been improved with several cosmetic changes and became more and more different from the German and Argentine models. Vemag had no capital to invest in new products and came under governmental pressure to merge. In 1964-1965 Volkswagen gradually took over [[Auto Union]], a minority holder in Vemag, and in 1967 Volkswagen bought the remainder of the stock.&lt;ref&gt;[[#HShap|Shapiro]], p. 935&lt;/ref&gt; VW quickly began phasing out DKW-Vemag production and introduced the [[Volkswagen Type 3#Coffin|Volkswagen 1600]] sedan to the old Vemag plant, after a total of 109,343 DKW-Vemag cars had been built.&lt;ref name=VoGo/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Maravilha&quot;&gt;{{citation | title = DKW - A grande história da Pequena Maravilha |trans-title=DKW: The great history of the little wonder | language = Portuguese | first1 = Paulo César | last1 = Sandler | first2 = Rogério | last2 = de Simone | publisher = Editora Alaúde | isbn = 978-85-7881-037-5 | location = São Paulo, Brazil }}&lt;/ref&gt;

DKW vehicles were made in [[Argentina]] from 1960 to 1969 by IASF S.A. (Industria Automotriz Santa Fe Sociedad Anónima) in [[Sauce Viejo, Argentina|Sauce Viejo]], [[Santa Fe Province|Santa Fe]]. The most beautiful were the Cupé Fissore, which had many famous owners (Julio Sosa, César Luis Menotti, and others). Other models are the Auto Union 1000 S Sedán (21,797 made until 1969) and the Auto Union 1000 Universal S (6,396 made until 1969).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.cocheargentino.com.ar/a/auto_union.htm |title=Auto Union |publisher=Coche Argentino |date=2009-05-18 |accessdate=2011-10-30 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20111105181653/http://www.cocheargentino.com.ar/a/auto_union.htm |archivedate=2011-11-05 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and the Auto Union [[DKW Schnellaster|Combi/Pick-up]].
The last version of the Auto Union Combi/Pick-up ([[DKW F1000 L]]), launched in 1969, survived a few months and was bought out by [[Industrias Aeronáuticas y Mecánicas del Estado|IME]], which continued production until 1979.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.cocheargentino.com.ar/a/auto_union.htm#frontal69 |title=Auto Union |publisher=Coche Argentino |date=2009-05-18 |accessdate=2011-10-30 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20111105181653/http://www.cocheargentino.com.ar/a/auto_union.htm#frontal69 |archivedate=2011-11-05 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

{|
|[[File:DKW-Vemag Fissore.jpg|thumb|200px|1967 DKW-Vemag Fissore]]
|[[File:GT Malzoni 1966.jpg|thumb|200px|DKW GT Malzoni]]
|}

==Vans and utility vehicles==
[[File:DKW F 91-4.jpg|thumb|DKW Munga]]
The [[DKW Munga]] was built by Auto Union in Ingolstadt. Production began in October 1956 and ended in December 1968, with 46,750 cars built.

From 1949 to 1962, DKW produced the ''[[DKW Schnellaster|Schnellaster]]'' with a trailing-arm [[rear suspension]] system with [[Spring (device)|springs]] in the cross bar assembly. Spanish subsidiary IMOSA produced a modern successor introduced in 1963, the DKW F 1000&amp;nbsp;L. This van started with the three-cylinder 1,000&amp;nbsp;cc engine, but later received a [[Mercedes-Benz]] [[Diesel engine]] and was renamed a Mercedes-Benz in 1975.
{{Clear}}

==Motorcycles==

[[File:DKW 192X.jpg|thumb|DKW]]

During the late 1920s and until WWII broke out, DKW was the world's largest motorcycle manufacturer&lt;ref&gt;http://bikelinks.com/directory/Classic_Motorcycles/A_to_Z/D/DKW/http://www.audi.com/corporate/en/company/history/models/{{dead link|date=May 2018 |bot=SheriffIsInTown |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt; and the pioneer of front wheel drive automobiles with their [[DKW F1|DKW Front]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.audi.com/corporate/en/company/history/models/dkw-front-f-1-roadster-1931.html|title=DKW Front F 1 roadster, 1931|website=audi.com|accessdate=8 May 2018|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20180115184732/http://www.audi.com/corporate/en/company/history/models/dkw-front-f-1-roadster-1931.html|archivedate=15 January 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; along with the [[Citroen Traction Avant]]. In 1931, Arnold Zoller started building [[split-single]]s and this concept made DKW the dominant racing motorcycle in the Lightweight and Junior classes between the wars.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.odd-bike.com/2014/02/dkw-supercharged-two-strokes-force-fed.html|title=DKW Supercharged Two-Strokes - Force-Fed Deeks|website=www.odd-bike.com|accessdate=8 May 2018|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20171004030738/http://www.odd-bike.com/2014/02/dkw-supercharged-two-strokes-force-fed.html|archivedate=4 October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; This included off-road events like the [[International Six Days Enduro|International Six Days Trial]] where the marque scored some considerable inter-war year successes alongside [[BMW|Bavarian Motor Works]] At the same time, the company also had some success with [[forced induction|super-charged]] racing motorcycles which because of their light weight were particularly successful in the ISDT&lt;ref&gt;[http://speedtracktales.com/folks-n-motors/silver-vase-winning-dkw-246-isdt-1935/ ISDT award winning DKW 246cc 1935] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140205062347/http://speedtracktales.com/folks-n-motors/silver-vase-winning-dkw-246-isdt-1935/ |date=2014-02-05 }}.&lt;/ref&gt;

The motorcycle branch produced famous models such as the [[DKW RT 125|RT 125]] pre- and post-[[World War II]], and after the war with production at the original factory in [[GDR]] becoming [[MZ Motorrad- und Zweiradwerk|MZ]]&lt;ref name=&quot;MC&quot;/&gt; it made 175, 250 and 350 (cc) models. As war reparations, the design drawings of the RT125 were given to [[Harley-Davidson]] in the US and [[Birmingham Small Arms Company|BSA]] in the UK. The Harley-Davidson version was known loosely as the [[Harley-Davidson Hummer|Hummer]] (Hummer is really just a few specific years, but generally people call the Harley lightweights Hummers), while BSA used them for the [[BSA Bantam|Bantam]]. IFA and later [[MZ Motorrad- und Zweiradwerk|MZ]] models continued in production until the 1990s, when economics brought production of the two stroke to an end. Other manufacturers copied the DKW design, officially or otherwise. This can be seen in the similarity of many small two-stroke motorcycles from the 1950s, including from [[Yamaha Motor Company|Yamaha]], [[Voskhod motorcycle|Voskhod]], [[Maserati (motorcycle)|Maserati]], and Polish [[PZL|WSK]].
{{Clear}}

==Cars==
===Pre-war production===
[[File:DKW F8 Meisterklasse.JPG|thumb|DKW F8 Meisterklasse (1939–1942)]]
* [[DKW Typ P]] (1928–1931)
* [[DKW Typ 4=8]] (1929–1940)
* [[DKW F1]] (1931–1932)
* [[DKW F2]] (1932–1935)
* [[DKW F4]] (1934–1935)
* [[DKW F5]] (1935–1937)
* [[DKW F7]] (1937–1938)
* [[DKW F8]] (1939–1942)
* [[DKW F9]] prototype (1939)

===Post-war===
[[File:DKW-F12-Baujahr1965.jpg|thumb|DKW F12 Saloon (1963-1965)]]
* [[DKW Schnellaster]] van (1949–1962)
* [[DKW F10]] (1950)
* [[DKW F89]] (1950–1954)
* [[DKW 3=6]] (F91/F93/F94) (1953–1959)
* [[DKW Monza]] (1956–1958)
* [[DKW Munga]] off-road (1956–1968)
* [[DKW Junior]] (F11/F12) (1959–1965)&lt;ref name=Sedgwick&gt;Michael Sedgwick &amp; Mark Gillies, A-Z of Cars 1945-1970, page 54&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[DKW F102]] (1963–1966)

==Motorcycles and scooters==
[[File:DKW Super Sport 500.jpg|thumb|DKW Super Sport 500]]
[[File: DKW SS 250 - Seite.jpg|thumb|DKW SS 250 from 1938/39]]
[[File: DKW RM 350, Bj. 1953 - re. Seite (museum mobile 2013-09-03).jpg|thumb|DKW RM 350 from 1953]]
{|
|-
|
* DKW ARE 175
* DKW Golem (''Sesselmotorrad'')
* DKW Hobby-Roller
* DKW Hummel
* DKW KM 200
* DKW KS 200
* DKW NZ 250
* DKW NZ 350
* DKW NZ 500
* DKW ORE 250
|
* DKW RT 100
* [[RT 125|DKW RT 125]]
* DKW RT 175
* DKW RT 200
* DKW RT 200H
* DKW RT 250/2
* DKW RT 250 H
* DKW RT 350 S
* DKW SB 200
* DKW SB 350
|
* DKW SB 500
* DKW Sport 250
* DKW SS 500 (water-cooled)
* DKW SS 600 (water-cooled)
* DKW ZS 500
* DKW ZSW 500 (water-cooled)
* DKW [[Hercules (motorcycle)|Hercules]] ([[Wankel engine|Wankel]])
|}

&lt;gallery perrow=&quot;5&quot;&gt;
File:DKW E 206, Bj. 1927 (museum mobile 2013-09-03).JPG|DKW E 206, 1927
File:DKW 97ccm 1939.JPG|DKW (1939)
File:DKW 198ccm 1940.jpg|DKW (1940)
File:DKW 1950-1.jpg|[[RT 125|DKW RT 125 W]] (1950)
File:DKW RT200 9,2PS 1952.jpg|DKW RT 200 (1952)
File:DKW RT 350 S, Bj. 1956 (links) im museum mobile.JPG|RT 350 S, 1956
File:DKW RT175-1 174ccm 1955.JPG|DKW RT 175 S (1955)
File:DKW Hummel.JPG|DKW Hummel
File:Express T.Sport DKW.JPG|Express T. Sport (DKW-Motor)
File:ZweiRadMuseumNSU DKW Hobby.JPG|DKW Motorroller ''Hobby'' of 1954 in the ''Deutsches Zweirad- und NSU-Museum''
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==See also==
* [[Eucort]]
* [[List of automobile manufacturers of Germany]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==References==
{{refbegin}}
*{{cite book | ref = Oswald | last = Oswald | first = Werner | title = Deutsche Autos 1920-1945, Band (vol) 2 | publisher = Motorbuch Verlag | language = German | year = 2001 | isbn = 3-613-02170-6 }}
*{{cite book|last=Uhlmann|first=Claus|authorlink=|title=RT 125 Das Kleine Wunder Aus Zschopau| publisher=Verlagsgesellschaft Bergstraße mbH|year=2005|isbn=}}
* Siegfried Rauch Hrsg. von Frank Rönicke: ''DKW – Geschichte einer Weltmarke''. Motorbuch-Verlag, Stuttgart 2007, {{ISBN|978-3-613-02815-9}}.
* Thomas Erdmann: ''Vom Dampfkraftwagen zur Meisterklasse – Die Geschichte der DKW Automobile 1907–1945''. autovision, Hamburg 2003, {{ISBN|3-9805832-7-9}}.
* [[Peter Kurze]]: ''DKW Meisterklasse – Ein Wagen für die ganze Welt''. Delius Klasing, Bielefeld 2005, {{ISBN|3-7688-1646-X}}.
* {{citation|surname1=Steffen Ottinger|title=DKW Motorradsport 1920–1939 : Von den ersten Siegen des Zschopauer Zweitakters bei Bahnrennen bis zu den Europameisterschafts-Erfolgen|edition=1.|publisher=HB-Werbung und Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KG|publicationplace=[[Chemnitz]]|year=2009|isbn=978-3-00-028611-7|language=German}}
* {{citation|surname1=Woldemar Lange|surname2= Jörg Buschmann|title=Die große Zeit des DKW-Motorradrennsports : 1920–1941 (Zschopau)|edition=1.|publisher=Bildverlag Böttger GbR|publicationplace=[[Witzschdorf]]|year=2009|isbn=978-3-937496-29-0|language=German}}
* {{citation|surname1=Woldemar Lange|surname2= Jörg Buschmann|title=DKW Zschopau und der Motorradgeländesport : 1920–1941|edition=1.|publisher=Bildverlag Böttger GbR|publicationplace=[[Witzschdorf]]|year=2012|isbn=978-3-937496-50-4|language=German}}
* Harald Linz, Halwart Schrader: ''Die Internationale Automobil-Enzyklopädie''. United Soft Media Verlag, München 2008, {{ISBN|978-3-8032-9876-8}}.
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{commons category|DKW}}
* [http://www.ifaclub.co.uk/home UK-based official Wartburg, Trabant and IFA owners' club]{{dead link|date=July 2016 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}
* [http://www.autounion1939.com AUTO UNION Sales Brochures 1939]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20080224002726/http://www.dkw-club.de/ DKW Owners' Club]
* [http://www.Dkw-Motorrad-Club.de/ DKW Motorcycle Club]
* [http://www.meisterdinger.de/dkw/index.htm ''Die Meisterdinger von Nürnberg'' – DKW webpages]
* [http://www.dyna.co.za/cars/history.htm ''DKW &amp; Auto Union History'']
* [https://archive.is/20121209074653/http://motocrossactionmag.com/Main/News/THE-LONG-HISTORY-OF-REVERSECYLINDER-ENGINE-DESIGNS-7056.aspx The Long History of Reverse-Cylinder Engine Designs] - motocrossactionmag.com

{{Major German motorcycle manufacturers}}
{{Volkswagen Group brands}}

[[Category:Dampf-Kraft-Wagen| ]]
[[Category:Audi]]
[[Category:Auto Union]]
[[Category:Vehicle manufacturing companies established in 1916]]
[[Category:Defunct motor vehicle manufacturers of Germany]]
[[Category:Motorcycle manufacturers of Germany]]
[[Category:Vehicle manufacturing companies disestablished in 1966]]
[[Category:Volkswagen Group]]</text>
      <sha1>sjwwv4d0iwcrqdvh8juo4q6aejqj40u</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
