  <page>
    <title>A Doll's House</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3144</id>
    <revision>
      <id>939171322</id>
      <parentid>939169748</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-04T20:20:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dramadrama34</username>
        <id>38470569</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|Dr. Rank|the Austrian psychoanalyst|Otto Rank|other uses|A Doll's House (disambiguation)}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2020}}
{{Infobox play
| name       = A Doll's House
| image      = A Doll's House.jpeg
| caption    = Original manuscript cover page, 1879
| writer     = [[Henrik Ibsen]]
| characters = {{plainlist|
* Nora
* Torvald Helmer
* Krogstad
* Mrs. Linde
* Dr. Rank
* Children
* Anne-Marie
* Helene
}}
| setting    = The home of the Helmer family in an unspecified Norwegian town or city, circa 1879.
| premiere   = {{Start date|df=y|1879|12|21}}
| place      = [[Royal Danish Theatre|Royal Theatre]]&lt;br /&gt;in [[Copenhagen]], Denmark
| orig_lang  = [[Norwegian language|Norwegian]],  [[Danish language|Danish]]
| subject    = The awakening of a middle-class wife and mother.
| genre      = [[Naturalism (theatre)|Naturalistic]] / [[Realism (theatre)|realistic]] [[problem play]]&lt;br /&gt;Modern [[tragedy]]
}}
&lt;!-- Please DO NOT alter the title to A Doll House; Wikipedia guidelines state that most-common title should be used. --&gt;
'''''A Doll's House''''' ([[Danish language|Danish]] and {{lang-nb|Et dukkehjem}}; also translated as ''A Doll House'') is a three-act play written by [[Norway]]'s [[Henrik Ibsen]]. It premiered at the [[Royal Danish Theatre|Royal Theatre]] in Copenhagen, [[Denmark]], on 21 December 1879, having been published earlier that month.&lt;ref&gt;Meyer (1967, 477).&lt;/ref&gt; The play is set in a Norwegian town circa 1879.

The play is significant for the way it deals with the fate of a married woman, who at the time [[Feminism in Norway|in Norway]] lacked reasonable opportunities for self-fulfillment in a male-dominated world, despite the fact that Ibsen denies it was his intent to write a feminist play. It aroused a great sensation at the time,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://www.worldcat.org/oclc/176284|title=&quot;Modernism&quot; in Modern Drama, A Definition and an Estimate|last=Krutch|first=Joseph Wood|date=1953|publisher=[[Cornell University Press]]|location=Ithaca|page=9|language=en|oclc=176284}}&lt;/ref&gt; and caused a &quot;storm of outraged controversy&quot; that went beyond the theatre to the world newspapers and society.&lt;ref name=&quot;four-major-plays&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://www.worldcat.org/oclc/39674082|title=Four Major Plays|last=Walter|first=McFarlane, James|last2=Jens|first2=Arup|date=1998|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=0192833871|oclc=39674082}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2006, the centennial of Ibsen's death, ''A Doll's House'' held the distinction of being the world's most performed play that year.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.pravdareport.com/news/world/22-05-2006/80777-ibsen-0/|title=Henrik Ibsen's psychodramas still grip the world 100 years after his death|work=Pravda Report|date=22 May 2006|access-date=30 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[UNESCO]] has inscribed Ibsen's autographed manuscripts of ''A Doll's House'' on the [[Memory of the World Register]] in 2001, in recognition of their historical value.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.unesco.org/new/en/henrik-ibsen-a-dolls-house/|title=Henrik Ibsen: A Doll's House|publisher=[[UNESCO]]|access-date=30 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The title of the play is most commonly translated as ''A Doll's House'', though some scholars use ''A Doll House''. [[John Simon (critic)|John Simon]] says that ''A Doll's House'' is &quot;the British term for what [Americans] call a 'dollhouse'&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=VukCAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA54|title=Bapuage=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Egil Törnqvist]] says of the alternative title: &quot;Rather than being superior to the traditional rendering, it simply sounds more idiomatic to Americans.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://www.worldcat.org/oclc/635006762|title=Ibsen: A Doll's House|last=Törnqvist|first=Egil|date=1995|publisher=[[Capilano University Press]]|isbn=9780521478663|oclc=635006762|page=54}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==List of characters==
*'''Nora Helmer''' – wife of Torvald, mother of three, is living out the ideal of the 19th-century wife, but leaves her family at the end of the play.
*'''Torvald Helmer''' – Nora's husband, a newly promoted bank manager, professes to be enamoured of his wife but their marriage stifles her.
*'''Dr Rank''' – a rich family friend. He is terminally ill, and it is implied that his &quot;tuberculosis of the spine&quot; originates from a [[venereal disease]] contracted by his father.
*'''Kristine Linde''' – Nora's old school friend, widowed, is seeking employment (sometimes spelled '''Christine''' in English translations). She was in a relationship with Krogstad prior to the play's setting.
*'''Nils Krogstad''' – an employee at Torvald's bank, single father, he is pushed to desperation. A supposed scoundrel, he is revealed to be a long-lost lover of Kristine.
*'''The Children''' – Nora and Torvald's children: Ivar, Bobby and Emmy (in order of age).
*'''Anne Marie''' – Nora's former nanny, who gave up her own daughter to &quot;strangers&quot; when she became, as she says, the only mother Nora knew.  She now cares for Nora's children.&lt;ref name=&quot;blaming-nora&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/stage/2009/may/02/ibsen-a-dolls-house|title=Blaming Nora|last=Byatt|first=A. S.|date=1 May 2009|work=The Guardian|access-date=30 May 2017|issn=0261-3077}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''Helen''' – the Helmers' maid
*'''The Porter''' – delivers a Christmas tree to the Helmer household at the beginning of the play.

==Synopsis==

===Act One===

The play opens at Christmas time as Nora Helmer enters her home carrying many packages. Nora's husband Torvald is working in his study when she arrives. He playfully rebukes her for spending so much money on Christmas gifts, calling her his &quot;little squirrel.&quot; He teases her about how the previous year she had spent weeks making gifts and ornaments by hand because money was scarce. This year Torvald is due a promotion at the bank where he works, so Nora feels that they can let themselves go a little. The maid announces two visitors: Mrs. Kristine Linde, an old friend of Nora's, who has come seeking employment; and Dr. Rank, a close friend of the family, who is let into the study. Kristine has had a difficult few years, ever since her husband died leaving her with no money or children. Nora says that things have not been easy for them either: Torvald became sick, and they had to travel to Italy so he could recover. Kristine explains that when her mother was ill she had to take care of her brothers, but now that they are grown she feels her life is &quot;unspeakably empty.&quot; Nora promises to talk to Torvald about finding her a job. Kristine gently tells Nora that she is like a child. Nora is offended, so she teases the idea that she got money from &quot;some admirer,&quot; so they could travel to Italy to improve Torvald's health.  She told Torvald that her father gave her the money, but in fact she managed to illegally borrow it without his knowledge because women couldn't do anything economical like signing checks without their husband. Over the years, she has been secretly working and saving up to pay it off.

Krogstad, a lower-level employee at Torvald's bank, arrives and goes into the study. Nora is clearly uneasy when she sees him. Dr. Rank leaves the study and mentions that he feels wretched, though like everyone he wants to go on living. In contrast to his physical illness, he says that the man in the study, Krogstad, is &quot;morally diseased.&quot;

After the meeting with Krogstad, Torvald comes out of the study. Nora asks him if he can give Kristine a position at the bank and Torvald is very positive, saying that this is a fortunate moment, as a position has just become available. Torvald, Kristine, and Dr. Rank leave the house, leaving Nora alone. The nanny returns with the children and Nora plays with them for a while until Krogstad creeps through the ajar door, into the living room, and surprises her. Krogstad tells Nora that Torvald intends to fire him at the bank and asks her to intercede with Torvald to allow him to keep his job. She refuses, and Krogstad threatens to blackmail her about the loan she took out for the trip to Italy; he knows that she obtained this loan by forging her father's signature after his death. Krogstad leaves and when Torvald returns, Nora tries to convince him not to fire Krogstad. Torvald refuses to hear her pleas, explaining that Krogstad is a liar and a hypocrite and that he committed a terrible crime: he forged someone's name. Torvald feels physically ill in the presence of a man &quot;poisoning his own children with lies and dissimulation.&quot;

===Act Two===
Kristine arrives to help Nora repair a dress for a costume function that she and Torvald plan to attend the next day. Torvald returns from the bank, and Nora pleads with him to reinstate Krogstad, claiming she is worried Krogstad will publish libelous articles about Torvald and ruin his career. Torvald dismisses her fears and explains that, although Krogstad is a good worker and seems to have turned his life around, he must be fired because he is too familial around Torvald in front of other bank personnel. Torvald then retires to his study to work.

Dr. Rank, the family friend, arrives. Nora asks him for a favor, but Rank responds by revealing that he has entered the terminal stage of [[tuberculosis]] of the spine and that he has always been secretly in love with her. Nora tries to deny the first revelation and make light of it but is more disturbed by his declaration of love. She then clumsily attempts to tell him that she is not in love with him, but that she loves him dearly as a friend.

Desperate after being fired by Torvald, Krogstad arrives at the house. Nora convinces Dr. Rank to go into Torvald's study so he will not see Krogstad. When Krogstad confronts Nora, he declares that he no longer cares about the remaining balance of Nora's loan, but that he will instead preserve the associated [[Bond (finance)|bond]] to blackmail Torvald into not only keeping him employed but also promoting him. Nora explains that she has done her best to persuade her husband, but he refuses to change his mind. Krogstad informs Nora that he has written a letter detailing her crime (forging her father's signature of [[surety]] on the bond) and put it in Torvald's mailbox, which is locked.

Nora tells Kristine of her difficult situation. She gives her Krogstad's card with his address, and asks her to try to convince him to relent.

Torvald enters and tries to retrieve his mail, but Nora distracts him by begging him to help her with the dance she has been rehearsing for the costume party, feigning anxiety about performing. She dances so badly and acts so childishly that Torvald agrees to spend the whole evening coaching her. When the others go to dinner, Nora stays behind for a few minutes and contemplates killing herself to save her husband from the shame of the revelation of her crime and to preempt any gallant gesture on his part to save her reputation.

===Act Three===
Kristine tells Krogstad that she only married her husband because she had no other means to support her sick mother and young siblings and that she has returned to offer him her love again. She believes that he would not have stooped to unethical behavior if he had not been devastated by her abandonment and been in dire financial straits. Krogstad changes his mind and offers to take back his letter from Torvald. However, Kristine decides that Torvald should know the truth for the sake of his and Nora's marriage.

After literally dragging Nora home from the party, Torvald goes to check his mail but is interrupted by Dr. Rank, who has followed them. Dr. Rank chats for a while, conveying obliquely to Nora that this is a final goodbye, as he has determined that his death is near. Dr. Rank leaves, and Torvald retrieves his letters. As he reads them, Nora steels herself to take her life. Torvald confronts her with Krogstad's letter. Enraged, he declares that he is now completely in Krogstad's power; he must yield to Krogstad's demands and keep quiet about the whole affair. He berates Nora, calling her a dishonest and immoral woman and telling her that she is unfit to raise their children. He says that from now on their marriage will be only a matter of appearances.

A maid enters, delivering a letter to Nora. The letter is from Krogstad, yet Torvald demands to read the letter and takes it from Nora. Torvald exults that he is saved, as Krogstad has returned the incriminating bond, which Torvald immediately burns along with Krogstad's letters. He takes back his harsh words to his wife and tells her that he forgives her. Nora realizes that her husband is not the strong and gallant man she thought he was, and that he truly loves himself more than he does Nora.

Torvald explains that when a man has forgiven his wife, it makes him love her all the more since it reminds him that she is totally dependent on him, like a child. He dismisses the fact that Nora had to make the agonizing choice between her conscience and his health, and ignores her years of secret efforts to free them from the ensuing obligations and the danger of loss of reputation. He preserves his peace of mind by thinking of the incident as a mere mistake that she made owing to her foolishness, one of her most endearing feminine traits.
{{Quotebox
|style = width:32em; max-width:32%;
|bgcolor = #c6dbf7
|quote = '''''We must come to a final settlement, Torvald. During eight whole years. . . we have never exchanged one serious word about serious things.'''''
|source = Nora, in [[Henrik Ibsen|Ibsen's]] ''A Doll's House'' (1879)
|salign = right
}}
Nora tells Torvald that she is leaving him, and in a confrontational scene expresses her sense of betrayal and disillusionment. She says he has never loved her, they have become strangers to each other. She feels betrayed by his response to the scandal involving Krogstad, and she says she must get away to understand herself. She has lost her religion. She says that she has been treated like a doll to play with for her whole life, first by her father and then by him. Concerned for the family reputation, Torvald insists that she fulfill her duty as a wife and mother, but Nora says that she has duties to herself that are just as important, and that she cannot be a good mother or wife without learning to be more than a plaything. She reveals that she had expected that he would want to sacrifice his reputation for hers and that she had planned to kill herself to prevent him from doing so. She now realizes that Torvald is not at all the kind of person she had believed him to be and that their marriage has been based on mutual fantasies and misunderstandings.

Torvald is unable to comprehend Nora's point of view, since it contradicts all that he has been taught about the female mind throughout his life. Furthermore, he is so narcissistic that it is impossible for him to understand how he appears to her, as selfish, hypocritical, and more concerned with public reputation than with actual morality. Nora leaves her keys and wedding ring; Torvald breaks down and begins to cry, baffled by what has happened. After Nora leaves the room, Torvald suddenly senses hope, as the door downstairs is heard closing.

===Alternative ending===
Ibsen's German agent felt that the original ending would not play well in German theatres. In addition, copyright laws of the time would not preserve Ibsen's original work. Therefore, for it to be considered acceptable, and prevent the translator from altering his work, Ibsen was forced to write an alternative ending for the German premiere. In this ending, Nora is led to her children after having argued with Torvald. Seeing them, she collapses, and as the curtain is brought down, it is implied that she stays. Ibsen later called the ending a disgrace to the original play and referred to it as a &quot;barbaric outrage&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://ibsen.nb.no/id/11111794.0|title=The alternative ending of A Doll's House|publisher=[[National Library of Norway]]|date=30 May 2005|access-date=30 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Virtually all productions today use the original ending, as do nearly all of the film versions of the play.

==Composition and publication==

===Real-life inspiration===
''A Doll's House'' was based on the life of [[Laura Kieler]] (maiden name Laura Smith Petersen), a good friend of Ibsen. Much that happened between Nora and Torvald happened to Laura and her husband, Victor. Similar to the events in the play, Laura signed an illegal loan to save her husband. She wanted the money to find a cure for her husband's tuberculosis.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Guardian - 2 May 2009 - Blaming Nora&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/stage/2009/may/02/ibsen-a-dolls-house|title=Blaming Nora|last=[[A. S. Byatt]]|date=2 May 2009|work=[[The Guardian]]|publisher=[[Guardian News and Media]]|accessdate=20 June 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; She wrote to Ibsen, asking for his recommendation of her work to his publisher, thinking that the sales of her book would repay her debt. At his refusal, she forged a check for the money. At this point she was found out. In real life, when Victor discovered about Laura's secret loan, he divorced her and had her committed to an asylum. Two years later, she returned to her husband and children at his urging, and she went on to become a well-known Danish author, living to the age of 83.

Ibsen wrote ''A Doll's House'' at the point when Laura Kieler had been committed to the asylum, and the fate of this friend of the family shook him deeply, perhaps also because Laura had asked him to intervene at a crucial point in the scandal, which he did not feel able or willing to do. Instead, he turned this life situation into an aesthetically shaped, successful drama. In the play, Nora leaves Torvald with head held high, though facing an uncertain future given the limitations single women faced in the society of the time.

Kieler eventually rebounded from the shame of the scandal and had her own successful writing career while remaining discontented with sole recognition as &quot;Ibsen's Nora&quot; years afterwards.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://www.worldcat.org/oclc/635006762|title=Ibsen: A Doll's House|last=Törnqvist|first=Egil|date=1995|publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]]|isbn=9780521478663|oclc=635006762|page=2}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://www.worldcat.org/oclc/610205542|title=The Wadsworth anthology of drama|last=Worthen|first=William B |date=2011|publisher=Wadsworth|isbn=9781428288157|oclc=610205542|page=667}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Composition===
Ibsen started thinking about the play around May 1878, although he did not begin its first draft until a year later, having reflected on the themes and characters in the intervening period (he visualised its [[protagonist]], Nora, for instance, as having approached him one day wearing &quot;a blue woolen dress&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;Meyer (1967, 463–467, 472).&lt;/ref&gt; He outlined his conception of the play as a &quot;modern [[tragedy]]&quot; in a note written in Rome on 19 October 1878.&lt;ref&gt;Meyer (1967, 466).&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;A woman cannot be herself in modern society,&quot; he argues, since it is &quot;an exclusively male society, with laws made by men and with prosecutors and judges who assess feminine conduct from a masculine standpoint!&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ibsen 1967&quot;/&gt;

===Publication===
Ibsen sent a [[Foul papers|fair copy]] of the completed play to his publisher on 15 September 1879.&lt;ref&gt;Meyer (1967, 474).&lt;/ref&gt; It was first published in Copenhagen on 4 December 1879, in an edition of 8,000 copies that sold out within a month; a second edition of 3,000 copies followed on 4 January 1880, and a third edition of 2,500 was issued on 8 March.&lt;ref&gt;Meyer (1967, 475).&lt;/ref&gt;

==Production history==
''A Doll's House'' received its world premiere on 21 December 1879 at the [[Royal Danish Theatre|Royal Theatre]] in Copenhagen, with [[Betty Hennings]] as Nora, Emil Poulsen as Torvald, and [[Peter Jerndorff]] as Dr. Rank.&lt;ref&gt;Meyer (1967, 477) and Moi (2006, 227, 230).&lt;/ref&gt; Writing for the Norwegian newspaper ''Folkets Avis'', the critic [[Erik Bøgh]] admired Ibsen's originality and technical mastery: &quot;Not a single declamatory phrase, no high dramatics, no drop of blood, not even a tear.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Quoted by Meyer (1967, 477).&lt;/ref&gt; Every performance of its run was sold out.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyer 1967, 480&quot;&gt;Meyer (1967, 480).&lt;/ref&gt; Another production opened at the [[Royal Dramatic Theatre|Royal Theatre]] in Stockholm, on 8 January 1880, while productions in [[Oslo|Christiania]] (with Johanne Juell as Nora and Arnoldus Reimers as Torvald) and [[Bergen]] followed shortly after.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyer 1967, 479&quot;&gt;Meyer (1967, 479).&lt;/ref&gt;

In Germany, the actress [[Hedwig Raabe|Hedwig Niemann-Raabe]] refused to perform the play as written, declaring, &quot;''I'' would never leave ''my'' children!&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyer 1967, 480&quot;/&gt; Since the playwright's wishes were not protected by copyright, Ibsen decided to avoid the danger of being rewritten by a lesser dramatist by committing what he called a &quot;barbaric outrage&quot; on his play himself and giving it an alternative ending in which Nora did not leave.&lt;ref name=&quot;Shapiro&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Meyer (1967, 480–481).&lt;/ref&gt; A production of this version opened in [[Flensburg]] in February 1880.&lt;ref name=m481&gt;Meyer (1967, 481).&lt;/ref&gt; This version was also played in [[Hamburg]], [[Dresden]], [[Hanover]], and [[Berlin]], although, in the wake of protests and a lack of success, Niemann-Raabe eventually restored the original ending.&lt;ref name=m481/&gt; Another production of the original version, some rehearsals of which Ibsen attended, opened on 3 March 1880 at the [[Residenz Theatre]] in Munich.&lt;ref name=m481/&gt;

In Great Britain, the only way in which the play was initially allowed to be given in London was in an adaptation by [[Henry Arthur Jones]] and [[Henry Herman]] called ''Breaking a Butterfly''.&lt;ref&gt;[https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=inu.32000006471181;view=1up;seq=1 text] Jones, Henry Arthur. Herman, Henry.  ''Breaking a butterfly : a play in three acts.''  Printed for private use only: not published. 76 pages.&lt;/ref&gt; This adaptation was produced at the Princess Theatre, 3 March 1884. Writing in 1896 in his book ''The Foundations of a National Drama'', Jones says: &quot;A rough translation from the German version of A Doll's House was put into my hands, and I was told that if it could be turned into a sympathetic play, a ready opening would be found for it on the London boards. I knew nothing of Ibsen, but I knew a great deal of Robertson and H. J. Byron. From these circumstances came the adaptation called ''Breaking a Butterfly''.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Jones, Henry Arthur. ''The Foundations of a National Drama: a collection of lectures, essays and speeches, delivered and written in the years 1896–1912''.  (1 January 1913). 1 January 1913. Reprinted: Wentworth Press (26 Aug 2016) {{ISBN|978-1362548942}}. Page 208.&lt;/ref&gt; [[H. L. Mencken]] writes that it was ''A Doll's House'' &quot;denaturized and [[dephlogisticated]]. … Toward the middle of the action Ibsen was thrown to the fishes, and Nora was saved from suicide, rebellion, flight and immortality by making a faithful old clerk steal her fateful promissory note from Krogstad's desk. … The curtain fell upon a happy home.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Mencken, H. L. ''The Collected Drama of H. L. Mencken: Plays and Criticism''. Scarecrow Press, 2012. {{ISBN|9780810883703}}. page 185.&lt;/ref&gt;

Before 1899 there were two private productions of the play in London (in its original form as Ibsen wrote it)  — one featured [[George Bernard Shaw]] in the role of Krogstad.&lt;ref name=&quot;blaming-nora&quot;/&gt; The first public British production of the play in its regular form opened on 7 June 1889 at the Novelty Theatre, starring [[Janet Achurch]] as Nora and Charles Charrington as Torvald.&lt;ref name=&quot;Archer&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Ibsen|first=Henrik|others=[[William Archer (critic)|William C. Archer]] translator|title=A Doll's House [Illustrated with photographs]|publisher=T Fisher Unwin|location=London|year=1889|oclc=29743002}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=ea&gt;{{Cite Americana |last=Moses |first=Montrose J. |wstitle=Doll's House, A}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite NIE|wstitle=Herman, Henry|year=1905}}&lt;/ref&gt; Achurch played Nora again for a 7-day run in 1897. Soon after its London premiere, Achurch brought the play to Australia in 1889.&lt;ref&gt;Brockett and Hildy (2003, 353).&lt;/ref&gt;

The play was first seen in America in 1883 in [[Louisville, Kentucky]]; [[Helena Modjeska]] acted Nora.&lt;ref name=ea/&gt; The play made its [[Broadway theatre|Broadway]] premiere at the [[Wallack's_Theatre#30th_Street_and_Broadway|Palmer's Theatre]] on 21 December 1889, starring [[Beatrice Cameron]] as Nora Helmer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Opening Night Production Credits: A Doll's House (1889) | url=http://www.ibdb.com/production.php?id=5582 | work=The Internet Broadway Database| year=2008 | accessdate=18 September 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was first performed in France in 1894.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyer 1967, 479&quot;/&gt;
Other productions in the United States include one in 1902 starring [[Mrs. Fiske|Minnie Maddern Fiske]], a 1937 adaptation with acting script by [[Thornton Wilder]] and starring [[Ruth Gordon]], and a 1971 production starring [[Claire Bloom]].

A new translation by [[Zinnie Harris]] at the [[Donmar Warehouse]], starring [[Gillian Anderson]], [[Toby Stephens]], [[Anton Lesser]], [[Tara FitzGerald]] and [[Christopher Eccleston]] opened in May 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal
   |author=Kate Bassett  |date=24 May 2009
   |title=The Donmar's new Ibsen isn't so much a clever interpretation as a bit of questionable rewriting|journal=[[The Independent]]
   |location=London|url=https://www.independent.co.uk/arts-entertainment/theatre-dance/reviews/a-dolls-house-donmar-londonbrthe-observer-nt-cottesloe-londonbrgrasses-of-a-thousand-colours-royal-court-upstairs-london-1689909.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The play was performed by [[24/6: A Jewish Theater Company]] in March 2011, one of their early performances following their December 2010 lower Manhattan launch.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite newspaper  |newspaper=[[The Forward]]  
   |title=For New Theater Company, Shabbat Takes Center Stage
   |date=16 December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 2013, Young Vic,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youngvic.org/|title=Homepage|website=Young Vic website}}&lt;/ref&gt; London, Great Britain, produced a new adaptation&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youngvic.org/whats-on/a-dolls-house-west-end ]{{dead link|date=July 2017 |bot=TheDragonFire |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt; of ''A Doll's House'' directed by Carrie Cracknell&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2014/02/09/theater/carrie-cracknell-adds-a-21st-century-flavor-to-ibsen.html|title=Carrie Cracknell Adds a 21st-Century Flavor to Ibsen|first=Alexis|last=Soloski|date=6 February 2014|work=The New York Times}}&lt;/ref&gt; based on the English language version by Simon Stephens.
In September 2014, in partnership with [[Brisbane Festival]], [[La Boite Theatre Company|La Boite]] located in Brisbane, Australia, hosted an adaptation of ''A Doll's House'' written by [[Lally Katz]] and directed by Stephen Mitchell Wright.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=A Doll's House by Henrik Ibsen in a new version by Lally Katz | url=http://www.laboite.com.au/cms/page.asp?ID=136 | publisher=La Boite Theatre Company | year=2014 | accessdate=2 November 2014 | url-status=dead | archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20141102035856/http://www.laboite.com.au/cms/page.asp?ID=136 | archivedate=2 November 2014 | df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
In June 2015, Space Arts Centre in London staged an adaptation of ''A Doll's House'' featuring the discarded alternate ending.&lt;ref name=&quot;A Doll's House at The Space&quot;&gt;.{{cite web | title=A Doll's House at The Space | url=https://space.org.uk/2015/03/25/a-dolls-house-2/ | access-date=1 April 2015 | archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150402132006/https://space.org.uk/2015/03/25/a-dolls-house-2/ | archive-date=2 April 2015 | url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;
'Manaveli' Toronto staged a Tamil version of ''A Doll's House'' (ஒரு பொம்மையின் வீடு)on 30 June 2018,Translated and Directed by Mr P Wikneswaran. The drama was very well received by the Tamil Community in Toronto and was staged again in few months later. The same stage play was filmed at the beginning of 2019 and screened in Toronto on 4 May 2019. The film was received with very good reviews and the artists were hailed for their performance. Now, arrangements are being made to screen the film, ஒரு பொம்மையின் வீடு, in London, at Safari Cinema Harrow, on 7 July 2019;&lt;ref name=&quot;A Doll's House at The Space&quot;/&gt;

==Analysis and criticism==
''A Doll's House'' questions the traditional roles of men and women in 19th-century marriage.&lt;ref name=&quot;Shapiro&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://www.worldcat.org/oclc/50638821|title=Women in literature: reading through the lens of gender|last=Fisher|first= Jerilyn|editor-last=Fisher|editor-first=Jerilyn|editor2-last=Silber|editor2-first=Ellen S|date=2003|publisher=Greenwood Press|isbn=9780313313462|oclc=50638821|pages=99–101|chapter=The slammed door that still reverberates}}&lt;/ref&gt; To many 19th-century Europeans, this was scandalous. The covenant of marriage was considered holy, and to portray it as Ibsen did was controversial.&lt;ref name=&quot;JMcF&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://www.worldcat.org/oclc/869601716|title=Cambridge Companion to Ibsen|last=James|first=McFarlane|date=1994|publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]]|isbn=9780521423212|oclc=869601716|page=167}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the Irish playwright [[George Bernard Shaw]] found Ibsen's willingness to examine society without prejudice exhilarating.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://www.worldcat.org/oclc/528524661|title=Superior Brains: Political Thought of Bernard Shaw|last=Griffith|first=Gareth|date=21 December 1995|publisher=Routledge|isbn=9780415124737|oclc=528524661|pages=164–165}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Swedish playwright [[August Strindberg]] criticised the play in his volume of essays and short stories ''[[Getting Married (Strindberg)|Getting Married]]'' (1884).&lt;ref&gt;Meyer (1967, 476).&lt;/ref&gt; Strindberg questioned Nora's walking out and leaving her children behind with a man that she herself disapproved of so much that she would not remain with him. Strindberg also considers that Nora's involvement with an illegal financial fraud that involved Nora forging a signature, all done behind her husband's back, and then Nora's lying to her husband regarding Krogstad's blackmail, are serious crimes that should raise questions at the end of the play, when Nora is moralistically judging her husband. And Strindberg points out that Nora's complaint that she and Torvald &quot;have never exchanged one serious word about serious things,&quot; is contradicted by the discussions that occur in act one and two.&lt;ref&gt;Sandbach, Mary, trans. Strindberg, August, author. 1972. ''Getting Married Parts I and II.''  London: Victor Gollancz. (1972) {{ISBN|0-575-00629-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The reasons Nora leaves her husband are complex, and various details are hinted at throughout the play.  In the last scene, she tells her husband she has been &quot;greatly wronged&quot; by his disparaging and condescending treatment of her, and his attitude towards her in their marriage – as though she were his &quot;doll wife&quot; — and the children in turn have become her &quot;dolls,&quot; leading her to doubt her own qualifications to raise her children. She is troubled by her husband's behavior in regard to the scandal of the loaned money. She does not love her husband, she feels they are strangers, she feels completely confused, and suggests that her issues are shared by many women. George Bernard Shaw suggests that she left to begin &quot;a journey in search of self-respect and apprenticeship to life,&quot; and that her revolt is &quot;the end of a chapter of human history.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;blaming-nora&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Shaw, Bernard. &quot;A Doll's House Again&quot;. ''Dramatic Opinions and Essays. Volume II.'' Brentanos (1916) p. 258&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;four-major-plays&quot;/&gt;

Ibsen was inspired by the belief that &quot;a woman cannot be herself in modern society,&quot; since it is &quot;an exclusively male society, with laws made by men and with prosecutors and judges who assess feminine conduct from a masculine standpoint.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ibsen 1967&quot;&gt;Ibsen, &quot;Notes for a Modern Tragedy&quot;; quoted by Meyer (1967, 466); see also Innes (2000, 79–81).&lt;/ref&gt; Its ideas can also be seen as having a wider application: [[Michael Meyer (translator)|Michael Meyer]] argued that the play's theme is not [[women's rights]], but rather &quot;the need of every individual to find out the kind of person he or she really is and to strive to become that person.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Meyer (1967, 478).&lt;/ref&gt; In a speech given to the [[Norwegian Association for Women's Rights]] in 1898, Ibsen insisted that he &quot;must disclaim the honor of having consciously worked for the women's rights movement,&quot; since he wrote &quot;without any conscious thought of making propaganda,&quot; his task having been &quot;the ''description of humanity''.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Ibsen, &quot;Speech at the Festival of the Norwegian Women's Rights League, Christiana&quot;, 26 May 1898; in Dukore (1974, 563); see also Moi (2006, 229–230).&lt;/ref&gt;

Because of the departure from traditional behavior and theatrical convention involved in Nora's leaving home, her act of slamming the door as she leaves has come to represent the play itself.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=Script into performance: a structuralist approach |first=Richard |last=Hornby |page=157 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=dsNX6DTt7w8C&amp;pg=PA157 |year=1995 |publisher=Hal Leonard Corporation |isbn=978-1-55783-237-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://www.worldcat.org/oclc/635006762|title=Ibsen: A Doll's House|last=Törnqvist|first=Egil|date=1995|publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]]|isbn=9780521478663|oclc=635006762|page=150}}&lt;/ref&gt; In ''Iconoclasts'' (1905), [[James Huneker]] noted &quot;That slammed door reverberated across the roof of the world.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Cunningham|first=Lawrence S.|title=Culture &amp; Values, Volume II: A Survey of the Humanities with Readings|year=2009|publisher=Cengage Learning|page=492|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=KiW8xOi0FvYC&amp;pg=PA492|first2=John J.|last2=Reich|isbn=978-0-495-56926-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Adaptations==
{{in popular culture|date=December 2016}}{{more citations needed|date=December 2016}}

===Film===
''A Doll's House'' has been adapted for the cinema on many occasions, including:
* A 1922 [[Lost film|lost]] [[silent film]] ''[[A Doll's House (1922 film)|A Doll's House]]'' starring [[Alla Nazimova]] as Nora.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.silentera.com/PSFL/data/D/DollsHouse1922.html Progressive Silent Film List: ''A Doll's House''] at silentera.com&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://lcweb2.loc.gov/diglib/ihas/loc.mbrs.sfdb.4847/default.html The Library of Congress American Silent Feature Film Survival Catalog: ''A Doll's House'']&lt;/ref&gt;
* A 1923 German silent film ''[[Nora (1923 film)|Nora]]'' was directed by [[Berthold Viertel]]. Nora was played by [[Olga Chekhova]], who was born Olga Knipper, and was the niece and namesake of [[Anton Chekhov]]’s wife.  She was also [[Michael Chekhov|Mikhail Chekhov]]'s wife.&lt;ref&gt;Holledge, Julie. Bollen, Jonathan.  Helland, Frode.  Tompkins, Joanne. ''A Global Doll's House: Ibsen and Distant Visions''. Springer, 2016. {{ISBN|9781137438997}}. Page 217.&lt;/ref&gt;
*A 1943 [[A Doll's House (1943 film)|Argentine film]], ''Casa de muñecas'', starring [[Delia Garcés]], which modernizes the story and uses the alternative ending.&lt;ref&gt;Plazaolapage, Luis Trelles. ''South American Cinema/ Cine De America Del Sur: Dictionary of Film Makers/ Diccionario De Los Productores De Peliculas''. Publisher: La Editorial, UPR (1989). {{ISBN|9780847720118}}. Page 10.&lt;/ref&gt;
* Two film versions were released in 1973: [[A Doll's House (1973 Losey film)|one was directed]] by [[Joseph Losey]], starring [[Jane Fonda]], [[David Warner (actor)|David Warner]] and [[Trevor Howard]];&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://variety.com/1972/film/reviews/a-doll-s-house-2-1200423089/|title= Review: A Doll’s House|website= Variety|date=31 December 1972}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[A Doll's House (1973 Garland film)|the other]] by [[Patrick Garland]] with [[Claire Bloom]], [[Anthony Hopkins]], and [[Ralph Richardson]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/movie/review?res=9A0DE3DE123DE63ABC4B51DFB3668388669EDE|last= Canby|first= Vincent|title= Claire Bloom's 'Doll's House on Film: The Cast|work= [[The New York Times]]|date=23 May 1973}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Dariush Mehrjui]]'s film ''[[Sara (1992 film)|Sara]]'' (1993) is based on ''A Doll's House'', with the plot transferred to [[Iran]]. ''Sara'', played by [[Niki Karimi]], is the ''Nora'' of Ibsen's play.&lt;ref&gt;Sloan, Jane. ''Reel Women: An International Directory of Contemporary Feature Films about Women''. Scarecrow Press, 2007. {{ISBN|9781461670827}}. Page 125.&lt;/ref&gt;
* In 2012 the [[Young Vic]] theatre in London released a short film called ''Nora'' with [[Hattie Morahan]] portraying what a modern-day Nora might look like.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Nora: a short film responding to Ibsen's A Doll's House|url=https://www.theguardian.com/film/video/2012/oct/18/nora-ibsen-dolls-house-video|accessdate=12 January 2017|newspaper=The Guardian|date=18 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* A scheduled 2018 film adaptation is set against the backdrop of the current economic crisis and stars [[Ben Kingsley]] as Doctor Rank and Michele Martin as Nora.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Wharton|first1=David|title=Ben Kingsley, Julian Sands, And Jena Malone Sign On for a Doll's House|url=http://www.cinemablend.com/new/Ben-Kingsley-Julian-Sands-Jena-Malone-Sign-Doll-House-27680.html|website=Cinema Blend|accessdate=12 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Mottram|first1=James|title=Sir Ben Kingsley interview|url=https://www.independent.co.uk/arts-entertainment/films/features/sir-ben-kingsley-interview-learning-to-drive-actor-gandhi-house-of-sand-and-fog-film-a7072516.html|accessdate=12 January 2017|newspaper=Independent|date=9 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Television===
* A live version for American TV [[A Doll's House (1959 TV drama)|was broadcast in 1959]] which was directed by [[George Schaefer (director)|George Schaefer]]. This version featured [[Julie Harris (American actress)|Julie Harris]], [[Christopher Plummer]], [[Hume Cronyn]], [[Eileen Heckart]] and [[Jason Robards]].
* In 1973 Norwegian TV produced an adaptation of A Doll's House (Et dukkehjem) directed by Arild Brinchmann and with Lise Fjeldstad as Nora Helmer. 
* A 1974 [[West Germany|West German]] television adaptation, titled ''{{Interlanguage link multi|Nora Helmer (film)|fr|3=Nora Helmer|lt=Nora Helmer}}'' was directed by [[Rainer Werner Fassbinder]] and starred [[Margit Carstensen]] in the title role.
* In 1992, [[David Thacker]] directed a British television adaptation with [[Juliet Stevenson]], [[Trevor Eve]] and [[David Calder (actor)|David Calder]].

===Radio===
* A 6 June 1938 ''[[Lux Radio Theatre]]'' production starred [[Joan Crawford]] as Nora and [[Basil Rathbone]] as Torvald.
* A later version by the ''[[The United States Steel Hour|Theatre Guild on the Air]]'' on 19 January 1947, featured Rathbone again as Torvald with [[Dorothy McGuire]] as Nora.
* In 2012, [[BBC Radio 3]] broadcast an adaptation by [[Tanika Gupta]] transposing the setting to India in 1879 where 'Nora', now Niru, is an Indian woman married to 'Torvald', now Tom, an English man working for the British Colonial Administration in Calcutta; this production starred [[Indira Varma]] as Niru and [[Toby Stephens]] as Tom.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b01n6r1w|title=BBC Radio 3 – Drama on 3, A Doll's House|publisher=BBC}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Re-staging===
* In 1989, film and stage director [[Ingmar Bergman]] staged and published a shortened reworking of the play, now entitled ''Nora'', which entirely omitted the characters of the servants and the children, focusing more on the power struggle between Nora and Torvald. It was widely viewed as downplaying the feminist themes of Ibsen's original.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ingmarbergman.se/en/production/dolls-house |title=A Doll's House |author=&lt;!--Not stated--&gt; |website=Ingmar Bergman |access-date=3 April 2017 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The first staging of it in New York was reviewed by the ''Times'' as heightening the play's melodramatic aspects.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1988/02/24/theater/stage-bergman-version-of-ibsen-s-doll-s-house.html|title=Stage: Bergman Version Of Ibsen's 'Doll's House'|last=Goodman|first=Walter|date=24 February 1988|work=The New York Times|access-date=3 April 2017|issn=0362-4331}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Los Angeles Times'' stated that &quot;''Nora'' shores up ''A Doll's House'' in some areas but weakens it in others.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://articles.latimes.com/1998/may/26/entertainment/ca-53435|title=Bergman Adaptation Restructures 'A Doll's House'|last=Shirley|first=Don|date=26 May 1998|work=Los Angeles Times|access-date=3 April 2017|issn=0458-3035}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Lucas Hnath]] wrote ''[[A Doll's House, Part 2]]'' as a follow-up about Nora 15 years later.
* The [[Citizens' Theatre]] in Glasgow have performed ''Nora: A Doll's House'' by Stef Smith, a radical re-working of the play, with three actors playing Nora, simultaneously taking place in 1918, 1968 and 2018.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.scotsman.com/lifestyle/culture/theatre/stef-smith-on-reimagining-a-doll-s-house-i-couldn-t-just-wrench-the-play-out-of-ibsen-s-hands-1-4887877|title=Stef Smith on reimagining A Doll's House: &quot;I couldn’t just wrench the play out of Ibsen’s hands&quot;|last=McMillan|first=Joyce|date=12 March 2019|work=[[The Scotsman]]|access-date=31 March 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; The production later transferred to the [[Young Vic]] in London.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Anna Russell-Martin on starring in Stef Smith’s Nora - A Doll’s House: “I still cry, whenever I read it” |first=Joyce |last=McMillan |work=The Scotsman |date=7 January 2020 |access-date=10 January 2020 |url= https://www.scotsman.com/arts-and-culture/theatre/anna-russell-martin-on-starring-in-stef-smith-s-nora-a-doll-s-house-i-still-cry-whenever-i-read-it-1-5071468 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Dottok-e-Log (Doll's House), adapted and directed by [[Kashif Hussain]], was performed in the [[Balochi language]] at the [[National Academy of Performing Arts]] on 30 and 31 March 2019.{{Importance inline|reason=No secondary sources offered to indicate notability of this adaptation|date=January 2020}}

=== Novels ===

* In 2019, memoirist, journalist and professor Wendy Swallow published ''Searching for Nora: After the Doll's House''. Swallow's historical novel tells the story of Nora Helmer's life from the moment in December 1879 that Nora walks out on her husband and young children at the close of A Doll's House. Swallow draws from her research into Ibsen's play and iconic protagonist, the realities of the time, and the 19th-century Norwegian emigration to America, following Nora as she first struggles to survive in Kristiania (today's Oslo) and then travels by boat, train and wagon to a new home in the western prairie of Minnesota.

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Sources==
* {{Cite book|url=https://www.worldcat.org/oclc/228061773|title=History of the theatre.|last=Brockett|first=Oscra G|last2=Hildy|first2=Franklin J|date=2002|publisher=Allyn &amp; Bacon|location=Boston|isbn=9780205410507|oclc=228061773}}
* Dukore, Bernard F., ed. 1974. ''Dramatic Theory and Criticism: Greeks to Grotowski''. Florence, KY: Heinle &amp; Heinle. {{ISBN|978-0-03-091152-1}}.
* {{Cite book|url=https://www.worldcat.org/title/sourcebook-of-naturalist-theatre/oclc/896687433|title=A sourcebook of naturalist theatre|last=Innes|first=Christopher|date=2000|publisher=Routledge|isbn=0415152291|oclc=896687433|location=London|language=English}}
* {{Cite book|url=https://www.worldcat.org/oclc/223316018|title=Ibsen: a biography|last=Meyer|first=Michael|date=1974|publisher=Penguin|isbn=9780140217728|oclc=223316018}}
* {{Cite book|url=https://archive.org/details/henrikibsenbirth0000moit|title=Henrik Ibsen and the Birth of Modernism: Art, Theater, Philosophy|last=Moi|first=Toril|date=2006|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]|isbn=0199295875|location=Oxford|language=English|url-access=registration}}

==Further reading==
* Ibsen, Henrick (trans McLeish). [https://www.amazon.co.uk/dp/185459236X ''A Doll's House''], [[Nick Hern Books]], London, 1994
* Unwin, Stephen. [https://www.amazon.co.uk/dp/1854598724 Ibsen's ''A Doll's House'' (Page to Stage Study Guide)] [[Nick Hern Books]], London, 1997
* William L. Urban. &quot;Parallels in ''A Doll's House''.&quot; Festschrift in Honor of Charles Speel. Ed. by Thomas J. Sienkewicz and James E. Betts. Monmouth College, Monmouth, Illinois, 1997.
*Merriam, Eve. After Nora Slammed the Door: From Doll's House to Paper Doll Lives? Merriam looks at the &quot;Women's Revolution&quot; in America. World Publishing Company, Cleveland, 1964.

==External links==
{{Wikisource|A Doll's House}}
{{Wikisourcelang|no|Et dukkehjem}}
{{Commons category|A Doll's House}}
* [http://ibsen.nb.no/id/512.0 Texts and other resources] at the [[National Library of Norway]]
* {{IBDB show|1085}}
* {{iobdb title|3817}}
* [https://www.imdb.com/find?s=tt&amp;q=a+doll%27s+house A Doll's House] at the Internet Movie Database
* [http://plays.about.com/od/plays/a/dolls_summary.htm ''A Doll’s House'': A Study Guide]
* {{Gutenberg|no=2542|name=A Doll's House}}
* {{Gutenberg|no=15492|name=A Doll's House}} (alternate edition)
* {{Librivox book|title=A Doll's House|author=Henrik Ibsen}}
* ''[[The Social Significance of the Modern Drama]]'', a book by [[Emma Goldman]], contains [http://sunsite.berkeley.edu/Goldman/Writings/Drama/doll.html a chapter on ''A Doll's House''].
* [https://archive.org/download/TheaterGuildontheAir/Tgoa_47-01-19_ep059-A_Dolls_House.mp3 1946 ''Theatre Guild on the Air'' radio adaptation] at [[Internet Archive]]
* [http://www.bestoftheatre.co.uk/blog/post/a-dolls-house-review ''A Doll's House'' review] for the London production of the play by [[Simon Stephens]].

{{Henrik Ibsen}}
{{A Doll's House|state=expanded}}
{{New Woman (late 19th century)}}
{{Navboxes
| title = Awards for ''A Doll's House''
| list = 
{{DramaDesk PlayRevival 1976–2000}}
{{TonyAward PlayRevival 1994–2000}}
}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Dolls House, A}}
[[Category:1879 plays]]
[[Category:Plays by Henrik Ibsen]]
[[Category:Plays about families]]
[[Category:Memory of the World Register]]
[[Category:Norwegian plays adapted into films]]
[[Category:West End plays]]
[[Category:Broadway plays]]
[[Category:Off-Broadway plays]]
[[Category:Drama Desk Award-winning plays]]
[[Category:Tony Award-winning plays]]
[[Category:Tragedy plays]]</text>
      <sha1>ocl8pms422bu0gebeizgms1h45lhn72</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
