  <page>
    <title>AIM-7 Sparrow</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3146</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941170137</id>
      <parentid>941169874</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-17T00:41:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>73.32.85.67</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Forgot the other variants</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect2|AIM7|Sparrow missile|the AIM7 benchmark|AIM Multiuser Benchmark|the Israeli target missile|Sparrow (target missile)}}
{{More citations needed|date=April 2011}}
{{Infobox weapon
| is_missile = yes
| name = AIM-7 Sparrow
| image = AIM 7 HAFB Museum.jpg
| image_size = 300
| caption = AIM-7 Sparrow at [[Hill Air Force Base]] Museum.
| origin = United States
| type = Medium-range, semi-active radar homing air-to-air missile
| used_by = Australia, Canada, Egypt, Greece, Iran, Iraq, Israel, Italy, Japan, Jordan, Kuwait, Malaysia, Saudi Arabia, Singapore, South Korea, Spain, Taiwan, Turkey, United Kingdom, United States
| manufacturer = [[Raytheon]]
| unit_cost = $125,000
| propellant =
| production_date = AIM-7D: 1959&lt;br/&gt;AIM-7F: 1976&lt;br/&gt;AIM-7M: 1982
| service =1958–present
| variants = Sparrow I: AIM-7A&lt;br/&gt;Sparrow II: AIM-7B&lt;br/&gt;Sparrow III: AIM-7C, AIM-7D, AIM-7E, AIM-7E2/[[Skyflash]]/[[Aspide]], AIM-7F, AIM-7M, AIM-7P, RIM-7M
| engine = AIM-7A/B/C – Aerojet 1.8KS7800 solid rocket &lt;br/&gt;AIM-7D/E – Rocketdyne MK 38/MK 52 solid rocket &lt;br/&gt;AIM-7F/M/P – Hercules MK-58 solid-propellant rocket motor&lt;ref name=&quot;designation-systems.net&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.designation-systems.net/dusrm/m-7.html|title=Raytheon AIM/RIM-7 Sparrow|website=www.designation-systems.net|access-date=6 December 2006|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160303202152/http://www.designation-systems.net/dusrm/m-7.html|archive-date=3 March 2016|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| weight = {{convert|510|lb|abbr=on}}
| length = {{convert|12|ft|abbr=on}}
| height =
| diameter = {{convert|8|in|abbr=on}}
| wingspan = {{convert|2|ft|8|in|abbr=on}} (AIM-7A/B)
| speed = AIM-7A/B: [[Mach number|Mach]] 2.5 &lt;br&gt;AIM-7C/E/F: Mach 4&lt;ref name=Designation_Systems&gt;[http://www.designation-systems.net/dusrm/m-7.html Directory of U.S. Military Rockets and Missiles: Raytheon AIM-7/RIM-7 Sparrow] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160303202152/http://www.designation-systems.net/dusrm/m-7.html |date=3 March 2016 }}. Designation Systems.&lt;/ref&gt;
| vehicle_range = AIM-7C: {{convert|22|km|mi}} &lt;br/&gt;AIM-7D: {{convert|39|km|mi}} &lt;br/&gt;AIM-7E/E2: {{convert|43|km|mi}} &lt;br/&gt;AIM-7F/M/P: {{convert|85|km|mi}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=AIM-7F Sparrow III - Standard Misssile Characteristics |url=http://www.alternatewars.com/SAC/AIM-7F_Sparrow_III_SMC_-_January_1977.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;designation-systems.net&quot;/&gt;
| ceiling =
| altitude =
| filling = [[High explosive]] [[blast-fragmentation]]&lt;br/&gt;AIM-7F/M: {{convert|88|lb}}
| guidance = semi-active radar
| detonation =
| launch_platform = '''Aircraft:'''
* [[McDonnell Douglas F-4 Phantom II]]
* [[McDonnell Douglas F-15 Eagle]]
* [[General Dynamics F-16 Fighting Falcon]]
* [[Grumman F-14 Tomcat]]
* [[F/A-18 Hornet]]
* [[JA-37 Viggen]]
* [[F-104 Starfighter|F-104S Starfighter]]
* [[Panavia Tornado|Tornado F.3 ADV]]
* [[F/A-18E/F Super Hornet]]
* [[Mitsubishi F-2]]
| number=70,000+&lt;ref name=&quot;forecastinternational.com&quot;&gt;https://www.forecastinternational.com/archive/disp_pdf.cfm%3FDACH_RECNO%3D600&amp;ved=0ahUKEwj2yc238Z3VAhVD2IMKHYcLAc4QFghuMA0&amp;usg=AFQjCNHdDZLNFbTdlUnFpCI9Od6teCVbrg {{dead link|date=November 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

The '''AIM-7 Sparrow''' is an American, medium-range [[semi-active radar homing]] [[air-to-air missile]] operated by the [[United States Air Force]], [[United States Navy]], and [[United States Marine Corps]], as well as other various air forces and navies. Sparrow and its derivatives were the West's principal beyond visual range (BVR) air-to-air missile from the late 1950s until the 1990s. It remains in service, although it is being phased out in aviation applications in favor of the more advanced [[AIM-120 AMRAAM]].

The early Sparrow was intended primarily for use against larger targets and especially bombers, and had numerous operational limitations in other uses. Against smaller targets, the need to receive a strong reflected radar signal made achieving [[Radar lock-on|lock-on]] at the missile's effective range difficult. As the launching aircraft's own radar needed to be pointed at the target throughout the engagement, this meant that in fighter-vs-fighter combat the enemy fighter would often approach within the range of shorter-range [[infrared homing]] missiles while the launching aircraft had to continue flying towards its target. Additionally, early models were only effective against targets at roughly the same or higher altitudes, below which reflections from the ground became a problem.

A number of upgraded Sparrow designs were developed to address these issues. In the early 1970s, the [[RAF]] developed a version with an [[inverse monopulse seeker]] and improved motor known as [[Skyflash]], while the [[Italian Air Force]] introduced the similar [[Aspide]]. Both had the ability to be fired at targets below the launching fighter (&quot;look-down, shoot down&quot;), were more resistant to countermeasures, and much more accurate in the terminal phases. This basic concept was then made part of the US Sparrows in the M model (for monopulse) and some of these were later updated as the P model, the last to be produced in the US. Aspides sold to [[China]] resulted in the locally produced [[LY-60 / FD-60 / PL10|PL10]]. The [[Japan Self-Defense Forces]] also employ the Sparrow missile, though it is being phased out and replaced by the [[Mitsubishi AAM-4]].

The Sparrow was also used as the basis for a [[surface-to-air missile]], the [[RIM-7 Sea Sparrow]], which is used by a number of navies for air defense of their ships. Fired at low altitude and flying directly at its target through the lower atmosphere, the range of the missile in this role is greatly reduced. With the retirement of the Sparrow in the air-to-air role, a new version of the Sea Sparrow was produced to address this concern, producing the much larger and more capable [[RIM-162 ESSM]].

NATO pilots use the [[brevity code]] ''[[Fox (code word)|Fox One]]'' in radio communication to signal launch of a Semi-Active Radar Homing Missile such as the Sparrow.&lt;ref name=&quot;DTIC1&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|date=25 April 1997 |title=Multi-service Air-Air, Air-Surface, Surface-Air brevity codes |publisher=[[Defense Technical Information Center]] (DTIC) |page=14 |url=http://www.dtic.mil/doctrine/jel/service_pubs/lbrevity.pdf |accessdate=12 April 2012 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120209014757/http://www.dtic.mil/doctrine/jel/service_pubs/lbrevity.pdf |archivedate=9 February 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Development==
===Sparrow I===
[[File:XF3D-1 AAM-N-2 NAN7-54.jpg|thumb|left|Sparrow I's during tests on a [[F3D Skyknight]] in the early 1950s]]

{{nowrap|The Sparrow emerged}} from a late-1940s [[United States Navy]] program to develop a guided rocket weapon for air-to-air use. In 1947 the Navy contracted [[Sperry Corporation|Sperry]] to build a [[beam riding]] version of a standard {{convert|5|in|mm|adj=on|sigfig=3}} [[HVAR]], the standard unguided aerial rocket, under  '''Project Hotshot'''. The weapon was initially dubbed '''KAS-1''', then '''AAM-2''', and, from 1948 on, '''AAM-N-2'''. The airframe was developed by [[Douglas Aircraft Company]]. The diameter of the HVAR proved to be inadequate for the electronics, leading Douglas to expand the missile's airframe to {{convert|8|in|mm|adj=on|sigfig=3}} diameter. The prototype weapon began unpowered flight-tests in 1947, and made its first aerial interception in 1952.&lt;ref name=Designation_Systems/&gt;

After a protracted development cycle the initial '''AAM-N-2 ''Sparrow''''' entered limited operational service in 1954 with specially modified [[Skyknight]]s all weather carrier night fighters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Hearst Magazines|title=Guided Missiles Ride Navy Jet|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=sdwDAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA116|date=November 1954|publisher=Hearst Magazines|page=116}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1956, they were joined by the [[F3H Demon|F3H-2M Demon]] and [[F7U Cutlass]] [[fighter aircraft]]. Compared to the modern versions, the Sparrow I was more [[Streamliner|streamlined]] and featured a bullet-shaped airframe with a long pointed nose.

Sparrow I was a limited and rather primitive weapon. The limitations of beam-riding guidance (which was slaved to an optical sight on single seater fighters and a radar with night fighters) restricted the missile to attacks against targets flying a straight course and made it essentially useless against a maneuvering target. Only about 2,000 rounds were produced to this standard.

===Sparrow II===
[[File:Sparrow 2 Missile.jpg|thumb|Sparrow 2 Missile]]
As early as 1950 Douglas examined equipping the Sparrow with an active radar seeker, initially known as '''XAAM-N-2a ''Sparrow II''''', the original retroactively becoming '''''Sparrow I'''''. In 1952 it was given the new code '''AAM-N-3'''. The active radar made the Sparrow II a &quot;fire and forget&quot; weapon, allowing several to be fired at separate targets at the same time.

By 1955 Douglas proposed going ahead with development, intending it to be the primary weapon for the [[F5D Skylancer]] [[interceptor aircraft|interceptor]]. It was later selected, with some controversy, to be the primary weapon for the Canadian [[Avro Arrow]] supersonic interceptor, along with the new Astra fire-control system. For Canadian use and as a second source for US missiles, [[Canadair]] was selected to build the missiles in [[Quebec]].

The small size of the missile forebody and the K-band AN/APQ-64-radar limited performance, and it was never able to work in testing. After considerable development and test firings in the U.S. and Canada, Douglas abandoned development in 1956. Canadair continued development until the Arrow was cancelled in 1959.

===Sparrow X===
A subvariant of the Sparrow I armed with the same nuclear warhead as the [[AIR-2 Genie|MB-1 Genie]] was proposed in 1958, but was cancelled shortly thereafter.

===Sparrow III===
[[File:Sparrow III launch F3H-2M NAN2-59.jpg|thumb|upright|[[F3H Demon]] launching a Sparrow III in 1958]]

Concurrently with the development of the Sparrow I, in 1951, [[Raytheon]] began work on the [[semi-active radar homing]] version of Sparrow family of missiles, the '''AAM-N-6 ''Sparrow III'''''. The first of these weapons entered [[United States Navy]] service in 1958.

The '''AAM-N-6a''' was similar to the -6, but used a new [[Thiokol]] liquid-fuel rocket engine for improved performance. It also included changes to the guidance electronics to make it effective at higher closing speeds. The -6a was also selected to arm the Air Force's ''F-110A Spectre'' ([[F-4 Phantom]]) fighters in 1962, known to them as the '''AIM-101'''. It entered production in 1959, with 7500 being built.

Another upgrade reverted to a Rocketdyne solid-fuel motor for the '''AAM-N-6b''', which started production in 1963. The new motor significantly increased maximum range to {{convert|35|km|mi}} for head-on attacks.

During this year the Air Force and Navy agreed on standardized naming conventions for their missiles. The Sparrows became the AIM-7 series. The original Sparrow I and aborted Sparrow II became the '''AIM-7A''' and '''AIM-7B''', despite both being out of service. The -6, -6a, and -6B became the '''AIM-7C''', '''AIM-7D''', and '''AIM-7E''' respectively.

25,000 AIM-7Es were produced, and saw extensive use during the [[Vietnam War]], where its performance was generally considered disappointing. The mixed results were a combination of reliability problems (exacerbated by the tropical climate), limited pilot training in fighter-to-fighter combat, and restrictive rules of engagement that generally prohibited BVR (beyond visual range) engagements. The P&lt;sub&gt;k&lt;/sub&gt; (kill probability) of the AIM-7E was less than 10%; US fighter pilots shot down 59&lt;ref group=Note&gt;Figure includes probables and bi-planes, which some sources sometime exclude&lt;/ref&gt; aircraft out of the 612 Sparrows fired.&lt;ref&gt;Michel III p. 286, 287&lt;/ref&gt; Of the 612 AIM-7D/E/E-2 missiles fired, 97 (or 15.8%) hit their targets, resulting in 56 (or 9.2%) kills. Two kills were obtained beyond visual range.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.dtic.mil/ndia/2006psa_winter_roundtable/watts.pdf# |title=Barry D. Watts: ''Six Decades of Guided Munitions'', Precision Strike Association, 25 January 2006, p. 5 |access-date=26 April 2014 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130720010705/http://www.dtic.mil/ndia/2006psa_winter_roundtable/watts.pdf# |archive-date=20 July 2013 |url-status=dead  }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1969 an improved version, the E-2, was introduced with clipped wings and various changes to the fuzing. Considered a &quot;dogfight Sparrow&quot;, the AIM-7E-2 was intended to be used at shorter ranges where the missile was still travelling at high speeds, and in the head-on aspect, making it much more useful in the visual limitations imposed on the engagements. Even so, its kill rate was only 13% in combat, leading to a practice of ripple-firing all four at once in hopes of increasing kill probability. Its worst tendency was that of detonating prematurely, approximately a thousand feet in front of the launching aircraft, but it also had many motor failures, erratic flights, and fuzing problems. An E-3 version included additional changes to the fuzing, and an E-4 featured a modified seeker for use with the [[F-14 Tomcat]].

===Vietnam War (1965–1973) records===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|+[[United States Air Force]] AIM-7 aerial combat kills&lt;ref name=&quot;McCarthy Jr., p. 148-157&quot;/&gt;
! scope=&quot;col&quot; width=&quot;140pt&quot; |Missile firing aircraft
! Model
! scope=&quot;col&quot; width=&quot;140pt&quot; |Aircraft shot down
! scope=&quot;col&quot; width=&quot;300pt&quot; |Comments
|-
| F-4C Phantom II
| AIM-7D
| 1 MiG-17
| [[555th Tactical Fighter Squadron]] (TFS)
|-
| F-4C
| AIM-7E
| 3 MiG-17s, 10 MiG-21s
| [[389th TFS]], [[433rd TFS]], [[480th TFS]], [[555th TFS]]
|-
| F-4D
| AIM-7E
| 4 MiG-17s, 2 MiG-21s
| [[433rd TFS]], [[435th TFS]], [[555th TFS]]
|-
| F-4D
| AIM-7E-2
| 18 MiG-21s, 3 [[MiG-19]]s
| [[4th TFS]], [[13th TFS]], [[34th TFS]], [[523rd TFS]], [[555th TFS]]
|-
| F-4E
| AIM-7E-2
| 8 MiG-21s, 1 MiG-19
| [[4th TFS]], [[35th TFS]], [[58th TFS]], [[366th TFS]], [[555th TFS]]
|}

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|+[[United States Navy]] AIM-7 aerial combat kills&lt;ref name=&quot;McCarthy Jr., p. 148-157&quot;&gt;McCarthy Jr., p. 148-157&lt;/ref&gt;
! scope=&quot;col&quot; width=&quot;140pt&quot; |Missile firing aircraft
! Model
! scope=&quot;col&quot; width=&quot;140pt&quot; |Aircraft shot down
! scope=&quot;col&quot; width=&quot;300pt&quot; |Comments
|-
| F-4B [[McDonnell Douglas F-4 Phantom II|Phantom II]]
| AIM-7D
| 4 [[MiG-17]]s (includes 2 probables)
| US fighters launched from [[USS Ranger (CV-61)|USS ''Ranger'']] CV-61, [[USS Midway (CV-41)|USS ''Midway'']] CV-41, [[USS Coral Sea (CV-43)|USS ''Coral Sea'']] CV-43
|-
| F-4B
| AIM-7E
| 2 [[An-2]] (Antonov [[Biplane]]s), 2 [[MiG-21]]s, 1 MiG-17
| US fighters launched from [[USS Constellation (CV-64)|USS ''Constellation'']] CV-64 and [[USS Enterprise (CVN-65)|USS ''Enterprise'']] CVN-65
|-
| F-4J
| AIM-7E-2
| 1 MiG-21
| US fighters launched from [[USS Saratoga (CV-60)|USS ''Saratoga'']] CV-60
|}

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|+ Kill count summary
! Category
! USAF
! USN
! Combined
|-
| An-2s
| {{N/A}}
| 2
| 2
|-
| MiG-17s
| 8
| 5
| 13
|-
| MiG-19s
| 4
| {{N/A}}
| 4
|-
| MiG-21s
| 38
| 3
| 41
|-
| Total
| 50
| 10
| 60
|}

Improved versions of the AIM-7 were developed in the 1970s in an attempt to address the weapon's limitations. The '''AIM-7F''', which entered service in 1976, had a dual-stage rocket motor for longer range, [[solid-state electronics]] for greatly improved reliability, and a larger warhead. Even this version had room for improvement, leading [[British Aerospace]] and the Italian firm [[Alenia Aeronautica|Alenia]] to develop advanced versions of Sparrow with better performance and improved electronics as the [[Skyflash|BAe Skyflash]] and [[Alenia Aspide]], respectively.

The most common version of the Sparrow today, the '''AIM-7M''', entered service in 1982 and featured a new inverse monopulse seeker (matching the capabilities of Skyflash), active radar [[proximity fuse]], digital controls, improved [[electronic countermeasures|ECM]] resistance, and better low-altitude performance. It was used to good advantage in the 1991 [[Gulf War]], where it scored many USAF air-to-air kills. Of 44 missiles fired, 30 (68.2%) hit their intended targets resulting in 24/26 (54.5%/59.1%) kills. 19 kills were obtained beyond visual range.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.dtic.mil/ndia/2006psa_winter_roundtable/watts.pdf# |title=Barry D. Watts: ''Six Decades of Guided Munitions'', Precision Strike Association, 25 January 2006, p. 7 |access-date=26 April 2014 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130720010705/http://www.dtic.mil/ndia/2006psa_winter_roundtable/watts.pdf# |archive-date=20 July 2013 |url-status=dead  }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The '''AIM-7P''' is similar in most ways to the M versions, and was primarily an upgrade program for existing M-series missiles. The main changes were to the software, improving low-level performance. A follow-on Block II upgrade added a new rear receiver allowing the missile to receive mid-course correction from the launching aircraft. Plans initially called for all M versions to be upgraded, but currently P's are being issued as required to replace M's lost or removed from the inventory.

The final version of the missile was to have been the '''AIM-7R''', which added an [[infrared homing]] seeker to an otherwise unchanged AIM-7P Block II. A general wind-down of the budget led to it being cancelled in 1997.

Sparrow is now being phased out with the availability of the active-radar [[AIM-120 AMRAAM]], but is likely to remain in service for several years.

====AIM-7 variants table====
&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.designation-systems.net/dusrm/m-7.html|title=Raytheon AIM/RIM-7 Sparrow|website=www.designation-systems.net|access-date=2016-08-23|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160303202152/http://www.designation-systems.net/dusrm/m-7.html|archive-date=3 March 2016|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|
|'''AAM-N-2''' ('''AIM-7A''')
|'''AAM-N-3''' ('''AIM-7B''')
|'''AIM-7C'''
|'''AIM-7E'''
|'''AIM-7F'''
|'''AIM-7M/P'''
|'''RIM-7M/P'''
|-
|Length
|3.74 m (147.3&amp;nbsp;in)
|3.85 m (151.7&amp;nbsp;in)
| colspan=&quot;5&quot; |3.66 m (144&amp;nbsp;in)
|-
|Wingspan
|0.94 m (37&amp;nbsp;in)
| colspan=&quot;6&quot; |1.02 m (40&amp;nbsp;in)
|-
|Finspan
|0.88 m (34.8&amp;nbsp;in)
|?
| colspan=&quot;4&quot; |0.81 m (32&amp;nbsp;in)
|0.62 m (24.3&amp;nbsp;in)
|-
|Diameter
| colspan=&quot;7&quot; |0.203 m (8&amp;nbsp;in)
|-
|Weight
|143&amp;nbsp;kg (315&amp;nbsp;lb)
|176&amp;nbsp;kg (389&amp;nbsp;lb)
|172&amp;nbsp;kg (380&amp;nbsp;lb)
|197&amp;nbsp;kg (435&amp;nbsp;lb)
| colspan=&quot;3&quot; |231&amp;nbsp;kg (510&amp;nbsp;lb)
|-
|Speed
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; |Mach 2.5
| colspan=&quot;5&quot; |Mach 4
|-
|Range
|10&amp;nbsp;km (5.4&amp;nbsp;nm)
|7&amp;nbsp;km (4&amp;nbsp;nm)
|11&amp;nbsp;km (6&amp;nbsp;nm)
|30&amp;nbsp;km (16&amp;nbsp;nm)
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; |70&amp;nbsp;km (38&amp;nbsp;nm)
|26&amp;nbsp;km (14&amp;nbsp;nm)
|-
|Propulsion
| colspan=&quot;3&quot; |Aerojet [[1.8KS7800]] solid rocket
|Rocketdyne MK 38/MK 52
solid rocket
| colspan=&quot;3&quot; |Hercules MK 58 dual-thrust solid rocket
|-
|Warhead
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; |20&amp;nbsp;kg (45&amp;nbsp;lb)
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; |30&amp;nbsp;kg (65&amp;nbsp;lb) MK 38 continuous rod
|39&amp;nbsp;kg (86&amp;nbsp;lb) MK 71
continuous rod
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; |40&amp;nbsp;kg (88&amp;nbsp;lb) WDU-27/B
blast-fragmentation
|}

&lt;gallery mode=&quot;packed&quot;&gt;
File:Australian F-18A Hornet launches Sparrow missile c1990.jpg|An Australian F-18A Hornet fires an AIM-7 Sparrow missile.
File:F-4C 154 FIS AIM-7E AIM-9P 1980.JPEG|AIM-7Es being loaded on a Hawaii ANG F-4C in 1980
File:F-4G 37FW AIM-7F AGM-65A AGM-88 1988.JPEG|AIM-7Fs on a 37th TFW F-4G in 1988
File:AIM-7 wing install.jpg|Wings being installed on an AIM-7
File:Loading AIM-7.jpg|An AIM-7M being loaded
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Foreign versions==
===Canada===
[[File:Canadair Sparrow missile.jpg|thumb|A Sparrow II is tested at a Canadair facility. Note the RCAF roundels painted on the fins.]]

As part of the [[Avro Canada CF-105 Arrow]] program, Canadair (now [[Bombardier Inc.|Bombardier]]) partnered with [[Douglas Aircraft Company]] in the development of the Sparrow II (AAM-N-3/AIM-7B).  After Douglas dropped out of this program, [[Canadair]] continued on with it until the termination of the Arrow project.

The AAM-N-3 Sparrow II was unique in that it had a fully [[active radar guidance]] system.&lt;ref name=&quot;forecastinternational.com&quot;/&gt; This combined both a radar transmitter and receiver in the missile, making it unnecessary for the pilot to keep the aircraft aimed at the target after firing the missile,&lt;ref name=&quot;Canadair1959&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://sites.google.com/site/canadair50otherproducts/1959missiles|title=1959missiles – canadair50otherproducts|website=sites.google.com|access-date=22 July 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160527151453/https://sites.google.com/site/canadair50otherproducts/1959missiles|archive-date=27 May 2016|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; unlike [[Semi-active radar homing]] (SARH) missiles which require continuous radar-assisted guidance throughout flight. This allowed the aircraft that fired the AAM-N-3 to turn away, prosecute other targets, and/or escape from potential retaliatory missiles fired by the enemy aircraft during the time it takes for the Sparrow to reach its target. Despite the significant advantages of this design over SARH guidance, all subsequent models of the Sparrow use [[semi-active radar homing]].

To accommodate the active radar guidance system, the AAM-N-3 Sparrow II had a much greater volume than its predecessor. Its size would subsequently set the precedent for all future Sparrow variants.&lt;ref name=&quot;forecastinternational.com&quot;/&gt;

In 1959, Canadair had completed five missiles based on airframes from Douglas, and built two models from scratch, when the program was cancelled with the cancellation of the Arrow.&lt;ref name=&quot;Canadair1959&quot;/&gt;

===Greece===
{{Main|Skyguard I}}
Skyguard I is an anti-aircraft system, utilizing ground-based AIM-7 Sparrow launchers.{{citation needed|date=December 2018}}

===Italy===
{{Main|Alenia Aspide}}
The Italian company Finmeccanica (now [[Leonardo S.p.A.]]), Alenia Difesa licensed the AIM-7E Sparrow technology from the US, and produced its own improved version called '''Aspide'''.

===People's Republic of China===
{{Main|PL-10}}
The LY-60/FD-60/PL-10 is a family of PRC missiles developed by the Shanghai Academy of Science and Technology, largely based on the Italian Aspide missile – a version of the Sparrow.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= https://fas.org/man/dod-101/sys/missile/row/ly-60.htm |title= LY-60 / PL-10 |website= FAS.org |accessdate= 15 November 2014 |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20150409025528/https://fas.org/man/dod-101/sys/missile/row/ly-60.htm |archive-date= 9 April 2015 |url-status= live }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/chinese-aam-aspirations-may-build-on-alenia-aspide-10158/ |title= Chinese AAM aspirations may build on Alenia Aspide |first= Douglas |last= Barrie |website= FlightGlobal |date= 27 November 1996 |access-date= 15 November 2014 |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20141129034417/http://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/chinese-aam-aspirations-may-build-on-alenia-aspide-10158/ |archive-date= 29 November 2014 |url-status= live }}&lt;/ref&gt; There are four versions of the basic design, three of which are surface-to-air and one air-to-air.

===Soviet Union===
The Soviet Union acquired an AIM-7 in 1968 and a [[Vympel PTO|Vympel]] team started copying it as the '''K-25'''. The missile did not enter production as the [[R-23 (missile)|R-23]] was thought to have better versatility, range, signal processing logic, and immunity from interference. K-25 work ended in 1971, but analysis of the Sparrow was later used to inform the design of the [[R-27 (air-to-air missile)|Vympel R-27]], particularly the servomechanisms and movable wings.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=AA-7 APEX|website=FAS|url=https://fas.org/man/dod-101/sys/missile/row/aa-7.htm|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160828044210/http://fas.org/man/dod-101/sys/missile/row/aa-7.htm|url-status=dead|archive-date=28 August 2016|date=21 March 1999|accessdate=28 August 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===UK===
{{Main|Skyflash}}
[[File:EAP Leaving Loughborough 7.jpg|thumb|The Skyflash looked identical to the Sparrow from the outside, but housed a greatly improved seeker and upgraded motor.]]

[[British Aerospace]] (BAe) licensed the AIM-7E2 technology in the 1970s, producing the '''Skyflash''' missile. Skyflash used a Marconi XJ521 monopulse Semi-Active seeker together with improvements to the electronics. It was powered by the Aerojet Mk52 mod 2 rocket engine (later by the Rocketdyne Mk38 mod 4). Skyflash entered service with the [[Royal Air Force]] (RAF) on their [[F-4 Phantom II|Phantom FG.1/FGR.2]] in 1978, and later on the [[Panavia Tornado ADV|Tornado F3]]. Skyflash was also exported to Sweden for use on their [[Saab 37 Viggen|Viggen]] fighters.

An upgraded version with active radar seeker, called '''Active Sky Flash''' was proposed by BAe and [[Thomson-CSF]], but did not receive funding because the RAF opted for other missiles.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Skyflash |url=https://fas.org/man/dod-101/sys/missile/row/skyflash.htm |website=FAS |accessdate=4 November 2018 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070313033117/https://fas.org/man/dod-101/sys/missile/row/skyflash.htm |archivedate=13 March 2007 |date=21 March 1999}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Design==
The Sparrow has four major sections: guidance section, [[warhead]], control, and rocket motor (currently the Hercules MK-58 solid-propellant rocket motor). It has a cylindrical body with four wings at mid-body and four tail fins. Although the external dimensions of the Sparrow remained relatively unchanged from model to model, the internal components of newer missiles represent major improvements, with vastly increased capabilities. The warhead is of the [[continuous-rod warhead|continuous-rod]] type.

As with other semi-active radar guided missiles, the missile does not generate radar signals, but instead homes in on reflected continuous-wave signals from the launch platform's radar. The receiver also senses the guidance radar to enable comparisons that enhance the missile's resistance to passive jamming.

==Principle of guidance ==
The launching aircraft will illuminate the target with its radar. In radars of the 1950s these were single target tracking devices using a [[Nutation|nutating]] horn as part of the antenna. This caused the beam to be swept in a small cone. Signal processing would be applied to determine the direction of maximum illumination and so develop a signal to steer the antenna toward the target. The missile detects the reflected signal from the target with a high gain antenna in a similar fashion and steers the entire missile toward closure with the target. The missile guidance also samples a portion of the illuminating signal via rearward pointing [[waveguide]]s. The comparison of these two signals enabled logic circuits to determine the true target reflection signal, even if the target were to eject radar-reflecting [[chaff (radar countermeasure)|chaff]].

==Operators==
[[File:AIM-7 operators.png|thumb|400px|Map with AIM-7 operators in blue]]
{{Div col|colwidth=30em}}
*{{flag|Australia}}
*{{flag|Canada}}
*{{flag|Egypt}}
*{{flag|Greece}}
*{{flag|Iraq}}
*{{flag|Iran}}
*{{flag|Israel}}
*{{flag|Italy}}
*{{flag|Japan}}
*{{flag|Jordan}}
*{{flag|Kuwait}}
*{{flag|Malaysia}}
*{{flag|Saudi Arabia}}
*{{flag|Singapore}}
*{{flag|Pakistan}}
*{{flag|South Korea}}
*{{flag|Spain}}
*{{flag|Taiwan}}
*{{flag|Turkey}}
*{{flag|United Kingdom}}
*{{flag|United States}}
{{div col end}}

==See also==
{{Portal|War}}

* [[AIM-9 Sidewinder]]
* [[AIM-54 Phoenix]]
* [[Brazo]]
* [[List of missiles]]
* [[R-27 (air-to-air missile)]]
* [[Sparoair]]
* [[Super 530]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|group=Note}}

==References==
;Footnotes
{{Reflist}}
;Bibliography
{{Refbegin}}
* {{Cite book|last=Bonds |first= Ray and David Miller |title= Illustrated Directory of Modern American Weapons |chapter-url= https://books.google.com/books?id=cfpBbuIlfV0C|chapter= AIM-7 Sparrow |publisher=Zenith Imprint|isbn=978-0-7603-1346-6|date= 2002}}
* McCarthy Jr., Donald J. ''MiG Killers, A Chronology of U.S. Air Victories in Vietnam 1965-1973.'' 2009; Specialty Press, USA.  {{ISBN|978-1-58007-136-9}}.
* {{cite book| author = Michel (III), Marshall L.| title = Clashes: Air Combat Over North Vietnam, 1965–1972| year = 1997| publisher = US Naval Institute Press| isbn = 978-1-55750-585-9 }}
{{Refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons|AIM-7 Sparrow}}
{{Commons|RIM-7 Sea Sparrow}}
* [http://www.avroarrow.org/Cancellation.htm Aero Arrow Recovery Canada]
* [http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/systems/munitions/aim-7.htm GlobalSecurity.org]
* [http://www.designation-systems.net/dusrm/m-7.html Designation-Systems.Net]

{{USN early SAMs}}
{{USN missiles}}
{{USAF missiles}}
{{US missiles}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2019}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Aim-7 Sparrow}}
[[Category:Cold War air-to-air missiles of the United States|AIM-7]]</text>
      <sha1>jls170oqe6rxj8ixe5p1y7y70207dzu</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
