  <page>
    <title>AIM-120 AMRAAM</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3147</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942512177</id>
      <parentid>941194086</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-25T03:19:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Kitplane01</username>
        <id>109625</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Unit cost</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|American air-to-air missile}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=July 2014}}
{{Infobox weapon
|is_missile      = yes
|name            = AIM-120 AMRAAM
| image           = AIM-120 AMRAAM.jpg
| image_size      = 300
|caption         = An AIM-120 AMRAAM mounted on the wingtip launcher of an [[F-16 Fighting Falcon]]
|origin          = United States
|type            = Medium-range, [[active radar homing]] [[air-to-air missile]]
|used_by         = [[#Operators|See ''operators'']]
|wars            = [[Operation Deny Flight]]&lt;br&gt;[[Operation Allied Force]]
|manufacturer    = • [[Hughes Aircraft|Hughes]]: 1991–97 &lt;br /&gt;• [[Raytheon]]: 1997–present
|unit_cost       = • $300,000–$400,000 for 120C variants &lt;br /&gt;• $1,786,000&lt;small&gt;(FY2014)&lt;/small&gt; for 120D&lt;ref name=&quot;FY15budget&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://comptroller.defense.gov/Portals/45/documents/defbudget/fy2015/fy2015_Weapons.pdf#page=53 | page=53 | format=pdf | title=United States Department Of Defense Fiscal Year 2015 Budget Request Program Acquisition Cost By Weapon System | publisher=Office Of The Under Secretary Of Defense (Comptroller)/ Chief Financial Officer | date=March 2014 | access-date=September 6, 2014 | archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140918222053/http://comptroller.defense.gov/Portals/45/Documents/defbudget/fy2015/fy2015_Weapons.pdf#page=53 | archive-date=September 18, 2014 | url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;{{US$|1,090,000}}&lt;ref name=theDrive&gt;{{cite web | url=https://www.thedrive.com/the-war-zone/32277/here-is-what-each-of-the-pentagons-air-launched-missiles-and-bombs-actually-cost | accessdate=15 Feb 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt; (AIM-120D FY 2019)
|propellant      =
|production_date =
|service         = {{start date|1991|09}}–present
|variants        = AIM-120A, AIM-120B, AIM-120C, AIM-120C-4/5/6/7, AIM-120D
|engine          = [[Solid-fuel rocket]] motor
|weight          = {{convert |335|lb|kg|abbr=on}}
|length          = {{convert |12|ft|m|abbr=on}}
|height          =
|diameter        = {{convert |7|in|mm|abbr=on}}
|wingspan        = {{convert |20.7|in|mm|abbr=on}} AIM-120A/B
|speed           = {{convert|4|Mach|km/h mph}}{{citation needed|date=February 2019}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Archived copy&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.deagel.com/Defensive-Weapons/AIM-120D-AMRAAM_a001164006.aspx |title=Archived copy |access-date=February 28, 2019 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190301021543/http://www.deagel.com/Defensive-Weapons/AIM-120D-AMRAAM_a001164006.aspx |archive-date=March 1, 2019 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://forums.eagle.ru/showthread.php?t=157310 |title=Archived copy |access-date=February 28, 2019 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190301074455/https://forums.eagle.ru/showthread.php?t=157310 |archive-date=March 1, 2019 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|vehicle_range   = • AIM-120A/B: {{nowrap|55–75 km}} ({{nowrap|30–40 [[Nautical mile|nmi]]}})&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |publisher= Designation Systems |url= http://www.designation-systems.net/dusrm/m-120.html |title= M-120 |access-date= January 8, 2005 |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20050130092522/http://www.designation-systems.net/dusrm/m-120.html |archive-date= January 30, 2005 |url-status= live }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | first = Doug | last = Richardson | language = German | title =Stealth – Unsichtbare Flugzeuge| publisher = Stocker-Schmid | place = Dietkion-Zürich | year =2002| isbn= 978-3-7276-7096-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
• AIM-120C-5: {{nowrap|&gt;105 km}} ({{nowrap|&gt;57 [[Nautical mile|nmi]]}})&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | publisher = Designation Systems | url = http://www.designation-systems.net/dusrm/m-120.html | title = Aim-120c-5 | access-date = January 8, 2005 | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20050130092522/http://www.designation-systems.net/dusrm/m-120.html | archive-date = January 30, 2005 | url-status = live }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
• AIM-120D (C-8): {{nowrap|&gt;160 km}} ({{nowrap|&gt;86 [[Nautical mile|nmi]]}})&lt;ref name=&quot;flightglobal.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/new-long-range-missile-project-emerges-in-us-budget-442816/|title=New long-range missile project emerges in US budget|date=November 2, 2017|access-date=November 25, 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171126120146/https://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/new-long-range-missile-project-emerges-in-us-budget-442816/|archive-date=November 26, 2017|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|ceiling         =
|altitude        =
|filling         = [[High explosive]] [[blast-fragmentation]]&lt;br /&gt;
• AIM-120A/B: WDU-33/B, {{Convert |50|lb|lk =on|1}}&lt;br /&gt;
• AIM-120C-5: WDU-41/B, {{Convert |40|lb|1}}
|guidance        = [[inertial guidance]], terminal [[active radar homing]]
|detonation      = Active RADAR Target Detection Device (TDD)&lt;br /&gt;
Quadrant Target Detection Device (QTDD) in AIM-120C-6 – lots 13+.&lt;ref name=&quot;DTIC1&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|date=2003–2004 |title=Updated Weapons File |publisher=[[Defense Technical Information Center]] (DTIC) |url=http://www.dtic.mil/dticasd/sbir/sbir041/srch/af276.pdf |format=PDF |accessdate=April 12, 2012 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120119111003/http://www.dtic.mil/dticasd/sbir/sbir041/srch/af276.pdf |archivedate=January 19, 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|launch_platform = '''Aircraft:'''
*[[Boeing F/A-18E/F Super Hornet]]
*[[British Aerospace Hawk 200]]
*[[Eurofighter Typhoon]]
*[[General Dynamics F-16 Fighting Falcon]]
*[[KAI T-50 Golden Eagle|KAI FA-50 Golden Eagle]]
*[[Lockheed Martin F-22 Raptor]]
*[[Lockheed Martin F-35 Lightning II]]
*[[McDonnell Douglas AV-8B Harrier II|McDonnell Douglas AV-8B+ Harrier II]]
*[[McDonnell Douglas F-15 Eagle]]
*[[McDonnell Douglas F-15E Strike Eagle]]
*[[McDonnell Douglas F/A-18 Hornet]]
*[[Northrop F-5]]S/T
*[[Panavia Tornado ADV]]
*[[Sea Harrier FA2]]
*[[Saab JAS 39 Gripen]]
'''Surface-launched:'''
*[[NASAMS]] and others
}}

The '''AIM-120 Advanced Medium-Range Air-to-Air Missile''', or '''AMRAAM''' (pronounced {{respell|AM|ram}}), is an American [[Beyond-visual-range missile|beyond-visual-range]] [[air-to-air missile]] (BVRAAM) capable of all-weather day-and-night operations. Designed with a 7-inch (180mm) diameter form-and-fit factor, and employing active transmit-receive radar guidance instead of semi-active receive-only radar guidance, it has the advantage of being a [[fire-and-forget]] weapon when compared to the previous generation [[AIM-7 Sparrow|Sparrow]] missiles. When an AMRAAM missile is launched, [[NATO]] pilots use the [[Multiservice tactical brevity code|brevity code]] [[Fox (code word)|Fox Three]].&lt;ref name=&quot;DTIC2&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|date=April 25, 1997 |title=Multi-service Air-Air, Air-Surface, Surface-Air brevity codes |publisher=DTIC |page=14 |url=http://www.dtic.mil/doctrine/jel/service_pubs/lbrevity.pdf |format=PDF |accessdate=April 12, 2012 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120209014757/http://www.dtic.mil/doctrine/jel/service_pubs/lbrevity.pdf |archivedate=February 9, 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The AMRAAM is the world's most popular beyond-visual-range missile, and more than 14,000 have been produced for the [[United States Air Force]], the [[United States Navy]], and 33 international customers.&lt;ref name=&quot;DTIC7&quot;&gt;{{cite web |date=10 June 2008 |title=Precision Strike: Enabler for Force Domination |publisher=Air Armament Center, via DTIC |page=10 |url=http://www.dtic.mil/ndia/2008psa_peo/eidsaune.pdf |format=PDF |accessdate=Aug 12, 2018 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150513083704/http://www.dtic.mil/ndia/2008psa_peo/eidsaune.pdf |archivedate=May 13, 2015 |df=mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; The AMRAAM has been used in several engagements and is credited with ten air-to-air kills.&lt;ref name=&quot;ausairpower.net&quot;/&gt; Now over 30 years old in design, the AMRAAM is due to be replaced by the new [[AIM-260 JATM]], which will offer better long-range performance and ability to defeat electronic warfare jamming.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.thedrive.com/the-war-zone/28636/meet-the-aim-260-the-air-force-and-navys-future-long-range-air-to-air-missile&lt;/ref&gt;

==Origins==
===AIM-7 Sparrow MRM===
The [[AIM-7 Sparrow]] medium range missile (MRM) was purchased by the US Navy from original developer [[Hughes Aircraft]] in the 1950s as its first operational air-to-air missile with &quot;[[beyond visual range]]&quot; (BVR) capability. With an effective range of about {{convert|12|mi|km}}, it was introduced as a radar [[beam riding|beam-riding]] missile and then it was improved to a [[semi-active radar homing|semi-active radar guided]] missile which would home in on reflections from a target illuminated by the radar of the launching aircraft. It was effective at visual to beyond visual range. The early beam riding versions of the Sparrow missiles were integrated onto the [[F3H Demon]] and [[F7U Cutlass]], but the definitive AIM-7 Sparrow was the primary weapon for the all-weather [[F-4 Phantom II]] fighter/interceptor, which lacked an internal gun in its [[U.S. Navy]], [[U.S. Marine Corps]], and early [[U.S. Air Force]] versions. The F-4 carried up to four AIM-7s in built-in recesses under its belly.

Although designed for use against non-maneuvering targets such as bombers, because of poor performance against fighters over North Vietnam, these missiles were progressively improved until they proved highly effective in dogfights. Together with the short-range, infrared-guided [[AIM-9 Sidewinder]], they replaced the [[AIM-4 Falcon]] IR and radar guided series for use in air combat by the USAF as well. A disadvantage to semi-active homing was that only one target could be illuminated by the launching [[fighter plane]] at a time. Also, the launching aircraft had to remain pointed in the direction of the target (within the azimuth and elevation of its own radar set) which could be difficult or dangerous in [[air-to-air combat]].

An active-radar variant called the Sparrow II was developed to address these drawbacks, but the U.S. Navy pulled out of the project in 1956.  The [[Royal Canadian Air Force]], which took over development in the hopes of using the missile to arm their prospective [[CF-105 Arrow]] interceptor, soon followed in 1958.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.designation-systems.net/dusrm/m-7.html|title=Raytheon AIM/RIM-7 Sparrow|work=designation-systems.net|accessdate=April 12, 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160303202152/http://www.designation-systems.net/dusrm/m-7.html|archive-date=March 3, 2016|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The electronics of the time simply could not be miniaturized enough to make Sparrow II a viable working weapon.  It would take decades, and a new generation of digital electronics, to produce an effective active-radar air-to-air missile as compact as the Sparrow.

===AIM-54 Phoenix LRM===
The US Navy later developed the [[AIM-54 Phoenix]] long-range missile (LRM) for the fleet air defense mission. It was a large {{convert|1000|lb|kg|-2|abbr=on}}, Mach 5 missile designed to counter [[cruise missile]]s and the bombers that launched them. Originally intended for the straight-wing [[Douglas F6D Missileer]] and then the navalized version of the [[F-111B#F-111B|F-111B]], it finally saw service with the [[Grumman F-14 Tomcat]], the only fighter capable of carrying such a heavy missile. Phoenix was the first US [[fire-and-forget]], multiple-launch, radar-guided missile: one which used its own active guidance system to guide itself without help from the launch aircraft when it closed on its target. This, in theory, gave a Tomcat with a six-Phoenix load the unprecedented capability of tracking and destroying up to six targets beyond visual range, as far as {{convert|100|mi|km|-1}} away—the only US fighter with such capability.

A full load of six Phoenix missiles and its {{convert |2000|lb|kg}} dedicated launcher exceeded a typical Vietnam-era bomb load. Its service in the US Navy was primarily as a deterrent, as its use was hampered by restrictive [[rules of engagement]] in conflicts such as Operations [[Desert Storm]], [[Southern Watch]], and [[Iraqi Freedom]]. The US Navy retired the Phoenix in 2004&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | title = Navy Retires AIM-54 Phoenix Missile | url = http://www.navy.mil/search/display.asp?story_id=15422 | place = United States | publisher = Navy | access-date = November 26, 2011 | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20110305105351/http://www.navy.mil/search/display.asp?story_id=15422 | archive-date = March 5, 2011 | url-status = live }}&lt;/ref&gt; in light of availability of the AIM-120 AMRAAM on the [[F/A-18 Hornet]] and the pending retirement of the F-14 Tomcat from active service in late 2006.

===ACEVAL/AIMVAL===
The [[United States Department of Defense|Department of Defense]] conducted an extensive evaluation of air combat tactics and missile technology from 1974 to 1978 at [[Nellis AFB]] using the F-14 Tomcat and F-15 Eagle equipped with Sparrow and Sidewinder missiles as the blue force and aggressor F-5E aircraft equipped with [[AIM-9L]] [[all-aspect]] Sidewinders as the red force. This [[joint test and evaluation]] (JT&amp;E) was designated Air Combat Evaluation/Air Intercept Missile Evaluation ([[ACEVAL/AIMVAL]]).{{citation needed| date= July 2010| reason= Dead link removed}} A principal finding was that the necessity to produce illumination for the Sparrow until impact resulted in the red force's being able to launch their all-aspect Sidewinders before impact, resulting in mutual kills. What was needed was Phoenix-type multiple-launch and terminal active capability in a Sparrow-size airframe. This led to a [[memorandum of agreement]] (MOA) with European allies (principally the UK and Germany for development) for the US to develop an advanced, medium-range, air-to-air missile with the USAF as lead service. The MOA also assigned responsibility for development of an advanced, short-range, air-to-air missile to the European team; this would become the British [[ASRAAM]].

===Requirements===
[[File:CATM 120C AMRAAM p1230119.jpg|thumb|Surface-to-air mounting (shown: CATM-120C captive training variant)]]

By the 1990s, the reliability of the Sparrow had improved so much from the dismal days of Vietnam that it accounted for the largest number of aerial targets destroyed in [[Gulf War|Desert Storm]]. But while the USAF had passed on the Phoenix and their own similar [[AIM-47]]/[[YF-12]] to optimize dogfight performance, they still needed a multiple-launch fire-and-forget capability for the F-15 and F-16. AMRAAM would need to be fitted on fighters as small as the F-16, and fit in the same spaces that were designed to fit the Sparrow on the F-4 Phantom. The European partners needed AMRAAM to be integrated on aircraft as small as the Sea Harrier. The US Navy needed AMRAAM to be carried on the F/A-18 Hornet and wanted capability for two to be carried on a launcher that normally carried one Sparrow to allow for more air-to-ground weapons.

The AMRAAM became one of the primary air-to-air weapons of the new [[F-22 Raptor]] fighter, which needed to place all of its weapons into internal weapons bays in order to help achieve an extremely low [[radar cross-section]].

==Development==
[[File:AIM-120 first kill.jpg|thumb|right|First successful test at the White Sands Missile Range, New Mexico 1982]]

AMRAAM was developed as the result of an agreement (the [[Family of Weapons]] MOA, no longer in effect by 1990), among the United States and several other [[NATO]] nations to develop air-to-air missiles and to share production technology. Under this agreement the U.S. was to develop the next generation medium range missile (AMRAAM) and Europe would develop the next generation short range missile ([[ASRAAM]]). Although Europe initially adopted the AMRAAM, an effort to develop the [[Meteor (missile)|Meteor]], a competitor to AMRAAM, was begun in Great Britain. Eventually the ASRAAM was developed solely by the British, but using another source for its infrared seeker. After protracted development, the deployment of AMRAAM (AIM-120A) began in September 1991 in US Air Force [[F-15 Eagle]] fighter [[Squadron (aviation)|squadron]]s. The US Navy soon followed (in 1993) in its [[F/A-18 Hornet]] squadrons.

The eastern counterpart of AMRAAM is the somewhat similar [[Russian Air Force]] [[R-77|AA-12 &quot;Adder&quot;]], sometimes referred to in the West as the &quot;AMRAAMski.&quot; Likewise, France began its own air-to-air missile development with the [[MICA (missile)|MICA]] concept that used a common airframe for separate radar-guided and infrared-guided versions.

==Operational features summary==
AMRAAM has an all-weather, beyond-visual-range (BVR) capability. It improves the aerial combat capabilities of US and allied aircraft to meet the threat of enemy air-to-air weapons as they existed in 1991. AMRAAM serves as a follow-on to the AIM-7 Sparrow missile series. The new missile is faster, smaller, and lighter, and has improved capabilities against low-altitude targets. It also incorporates a datalink to guide the missile to a point where its active radar turns on and makes terminal intercept of the target. An inertial reference unit and micro-computer system makes the missile less dependent upon the fire-control system of the aircraft.

Once the missile closes in on the target, its [[active radar]] guides it to intercept. This feature, known as &quot;fire-and-forget&quot;, frees the aircrew from the need to further provide guidance, enabling the aircrew to aim and fire several missiles simultaneously at multiple targets and break a radar lock after the missile seeker goes active and guide themselves to the targets.

The missile also features the ability to &quot;Home on Jamming,&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.fas.org/man/dod-101/sys/missile/aim-120.htm | title = Military Analysis Network: AIM-120 AMRAAM Slammer | date = April 14, 2000 | publisher = FAS | accessdate = April 12, 2012 | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20110316035752/http://www.fas.org/man/dod-101/sys/missile/aim-120.htm | archive-date = March 16, 2011 | url-status = live }}&lt;/ref&gt; giving it the ability to switch over from active radar homing to passive homing – homing on jamming signals from the target aircraft. Software on board the missile allows it to detect if it is being jammed, and guide on its target using the proper guidance system.

==Guidance system overview==
 {{Unreferenced section|date=January 2020}}
===Interception course stage===
[[File:F-14 carrying AMRAAM.jpg|thumb|[[Grumman F-14 Tomcat]] carrying an AMRAAM during a 1982 test]]

AMRAAM uses two-stage [[missile guidance|guidance]] when fired at long range. The aircraft passes data to the missile just before launch, giving it information about the location of the target aircraft from the launch point and its direction and speed. The missile uses this information to fly on an interception course to the target using its built-in [[inertial navigation system]] (INS). This information is generally obtained using the launching aircraft's radar, although it could come from an [[infra-red search and track]] system, from a [[Joint Tactical Information Distribution System|data link]] from another fighter aircraft, or from an [[Airborne Early Warning and Control|AWACS]] aircraft.

After launch, if the firing aircraft or surrogate continues to track the target, periodic updates—such as changes in the target's direction and speed—are sent from the launch aircraft to the missile, allowing the missile to adjust its course, via actuation of the rear fins, so that it is able to close to a self-homing distance where it will be close enough to &quot;catch&quot; the target aircraft in the ''basket'' (the missile's radar field of view in which it will be able to lock onto the target aircraft, unassisted by the launch aircraft).

Not all armed services using the AMRAAM have elected to purchase the mid-course update option, which limits AMRAAM's effectiveness in some scenarios. The [[Royal Air Force|RAF]] initially opted not to use mid-course update for its [[Panavia Tornado ADV|Tornado F3]] force, only to discover that without it, testing proved the AMRAAM was less effective in beyond visual range (BVR) engagements than the older [[semi-active radar homing]] [[Skyflash|BAE Skyflash]] weapon—the AIM-120's own radar is necessarily of limited range and power compared to that of the launch aircraft.

===Terminal stage and impact===
Once the missile closes to self-homing distance, it turns on its active radar seeker and searches for the target aircraft. If the target is in or near the expected location, the missile will find it and guide itself to the target from this point. If the missile is fired at short range, within visual range (WVR) or the near BVR, it can use its active seeker just after launch, making the missile truly &quot;fire and forget&quot;. {{citation needed|date=September 2014}}

===Boresight Visual mode===
Apart from the radar-slaved mode, there is a free guidance mode, called &quot;Visual&quot;. This mode is radar guidance-free—the missile just fires and locks onto the first thing it sees. This mode can be used for defensive shots, i.e. when the enemy has numerical superiority. {{citation needed|date=January 2020}}

==Kill probability and tactics==
{{More citations needed|date=October 2010}}

===General considerations===
The [[probability of kill|kill probability]] (P&lt;sub&gt;k&lt;/sub&gt;) is determined by several factors, including aspect (head-on interception, side-on or tail-chase), altitude, the speed of the missile and the target, and how hard the target can turn. Typically, if the missile has sufficient energy during the terminal phase, which comes from being launched at close range to the target from an aircraft with an altitude and speed advantage, it will have a good chance of success. This chance drops as the missile is fired at longer ranges as it runs out of overtake speed at long ranges, and if the target can force the missile to turn it might bleed off enough speed that it can no longer chase the target. Operationally, the missile, which was designed for [[Beyond-visual-range missile|beyond visual range]] combat, has a P&lt;sub&gt;k&lt;/sub&gt; of 63.15% (19 missiles for 12 kills, including the Syrian Su-22 downed by a US Navy F/A-18E).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ausairpower.net/APA-NOTAM-070109-1.html|title=Coffin Corners for the Joint Strike Fighter|work=ausairpower.net|accessdate=April 12, 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160322111910/http://www.ausairpower.net/APA-NOTAM-070109-1.html|archive-date=March 22, 2016|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; The targets included six [[Mikoyan MiG-29|MiG-29s]], a [[Mikoyan-Gurevich MiG-25|MiG-25]], a [[Mikoyan-Gurevich MiG-23|MiG-23]], two [[Sukhoi Su-17|Su-22s]], a [[Soko G-4 Super Galeb|Galeb]] and a US Army [[Sikorsky UH-60 Black Hawk|Blackhawk]] that was targeted by mistake.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ausairpower.net/APA-Rus-BVR-AAM.html|title=The Russian Philosophy of Beyond Visual Range Air Combat|pages=1|author=Dr C Kopp|work=ausairpower.net|accessdate=April 12, 2016|date=2008-03-15|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160402114905/http://ausairpower.net/APA-Rus-BVR-AAM.html|archive-date=April 2, 2016|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;auto&quot;&gt;[https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-40322666 &quot;US coalition downs first Syria government jet.&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180930211844/https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-40322666 |date=September 30, 2018 }} Retrieved 19 June 2017.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Variants and upgrades==
[[File:Aim 120 amraam missile 20040710 145603 1.4.jpg|thumb|An AIM-120 AMRAAM missile on display at the U.S. National Air and Space Museum]]
[[File:F-22 GBU39B AIM-120 m02006120800117.jpg|thumb|right|AIM-120 AMRAAM (right) fitted in a weapons bay of a [[F-22 Raptor]]]]

===Air-to-air missile versions===
There are currently four main variants of AMRAAM, all in service with the [[United States Air Force]], [[United States Navy]], and the United States Marine Corps. The '''AIM-120A''' is no longer in production and shares the enlarged wings and fins with the successor {{anchor|AIM-120B|B}}'''AIM-120B'''. The AIM-120C has smaller &quot;clipped&quot; aerosurfaces to enable internal carriage on the USAF [[F-22 Raptor]]. AIM-120B deliveries began in 1994.

The {{anchor|AIM-120C|C}}'''AIM-120C''' deliveries began in 1996. The C-variant has been steadily upgraded since it was introduced. The AIM-120C-6 contained an improved fuse (Target Detection Device) compared to its predecessor. The AIM-120C-7 development began in 1998 and included improvements in homing and greater range (actual amount of improvement unspecified). It was successfully tested in 2003 and is currently being produced for both domestic and foreign customers. It helped the [[United States Navy|U.S. Navy]] replace the [[F-14 Tomcat]]s with [[F/A-18E/F Super Hornet]]s&amp;nbsp;– the loss of the F-14's long-range [[AIM-54 Phoenix]] missiles (already retired) is offset with a longer-range AMRAAM-D. The lighter weight of the advanced AMRAAM enables an F/A-18E/F pilot greater bring-back weight upon carrier landings.

The {{anchor|AIM-120D|D}}'''AIM-120D''' is an upgraded version of the AMRAAM with improvements in almost all areas, including 50% greater range (than the already-extended range AIM-120C-7) and better guidance over its entire flight envelope yielding an improved kill probability ([[Probability of kill|P&lt;sub&gt;k&lt;/sub&gt;]]). Raytheon began testing the D model on August 5, 2008, the company reported that an AIM-120D launched from an [[F/A-18F Super Hornet]] passed within lethal distance of a QF-4 target drone at the [[White Sands Missile Range]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.prnewswire.com/cgi-bin/micro_stories.pl?ACCT=149999&amp;TICK=RTN&amp;STORY=/www/story/08-05-2008/0004861926&amp;EDATE=Aug+5,+2008 Raytheon Press Release, 5 August 2008] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20081102095547/http://www.prnewswire.com/cgi-bin/micro_stories.pl?ACCT=149999&amp;TICK=RTN&amp;STORY=%2Fwww%2Fstory%2F08-05-2008%2F0004861926&amp;EDATE=Aug+5%2C+2008 |date=November 2, 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The range of the AIM-120D is classified, but is thought to extend to about {{convert|100|miles|km}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;flightglobal.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/new-long-range-missile-project-emerges-in-us-budget-442816/|title=New long-range missile project emerges in US budget|date=November 2, 2017|access-date=November 25, 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171126120146/https://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/new-long-range-missile-project-emerges-in-us-budget-442816/|archive-date=November 26, 2017|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The AIM-120D (P3I Phase 4, formerly known as AIM-120C-8) is a development of the AIM-120C with a two-way data link, more accurate navigation using a GPS-enhanced IMU, an expanded no-escape envelope, and improved HOBS (high off-boresight) capability. The AIM-120D max speed is Mach 4&lt;ref name=&quot;Archived copy&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.deagel.com/Defensive-Weapons/AIM-120D-AMRAAM_a001164006.aspx |title=Archived copy |access-date=February 28, 2019 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190301021543/http://www.deagel.com/Defensive-Weapons/AIM-120D-AMRAAM_a001164006.aspx |archive-date=March 1, 2019 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt; and AIM-120D is a joint USAF/USN project, and is currently in the testing phase. The USN was scheduled to field it from 2014, and AIM-120D will be carried by all Pacific carrier groups by 2020, although the [[Budget sequestration in 2013|2013 sequestration cuts]] could push back this later date to 2022.&lt;ref name=Greenert20130918 &gt;{{cite web | url=http://docs.house.gov/meetings/AS/AS00/20130918/101291/HHRG-113-AS00-Wstate-GreenertUSNJ-20130918.pdf | format=PDF | first=Admiral Jonathan | last=Greenert | authorlink=Jonathan Greenert | title=Statement Before The House Armed Services Committee on Planning For Sequestration in FY 2014 And Perspectives of the Military Services on the Strategic Choices And Management Review | date=September 18, 2013 | publisher=US House of Representatives | accessdate=September 21, 2013 | archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130923100518/http://docs.house.gov/meetings/AS/AS00/20130918/101291/HHRG-113-AS00-Wstate-GreenertUSNJ-20130918.pdf | archive-date=September 23, 2013 | url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Royal Australian Air Force]] requested 450 AIM-120D missiles, which would make it the first foreign operator of the missile. The procurement, approved by the US Government in April 2016, will cost $1.1 billion and will be integrated for use on the F/A-18F Super Hornet, EA-18G Growler and the F-35 Lightning II aircraft.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/australia-seeks-dods-newest-air-to-air-missile-the-424574/|title=Australia seeks DOD's newest air-to-air missile, the AIM-120D|last=Drew|first=James|date=25 April 2016|website=FlightGlobal|access-date=26 April 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160426174657/https://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/australia-seeks-dods-newest-air-to-air-missile-the-424574/|archive-date=April 26, 2016|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There were also plans for [[Raytheon]] to develop a [[ramjet]]-powered derivative of the AMRAAM, the {{anchor|FMRAAM}}Future Medium Range Air-Air Missile ([[FMRAAM]]). The FMRAAM was not produced since the target market, the British Ministry of Defence, chose the [[MBDA Meteor|Meteor missile]] over the FMRAAM for a [[BVR]] missile for the [[Eurofighter Typhoon]] aircraft.

Raytheon is also working with the [[Missile Defense Agency]] to develop the [[Network Centric Airborne Defense Element]] (NCADE), an anti-ballistic missile derived from the AIM-120. This weapon will be equipped with a [[ramjet]] engine and an [[infrared homing]] seeker derived from the [[AIM-9 Sidewinder|Sidewinder]] missile. In place of a proximity-fused warhead, the NCADE will use a [[kinetic energy]] [[hit-to-kill]] vehicle based on the one used in the Navy's [[RIM-161 Standard Missile 3]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.defenseindustrydaily.com/ncade-an-abm-amraam-03305/ |title=Defense Industry Daily report, 20 November 2008 |publisher=Defenseindustrydaily.com |date=November 20, 2008 |accessdate=April 12, 2012 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120302084506/http://www.defenseindustrydaily.com/ncade-an-abm-amraam-03305/ |archive-date=March 2, 2012 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The -120A and -120B models are currently nearing the end of their service life while the -120D variant has just entered full production. AMRAAM was due to be replaced by the [[USAF]], the [[U.S. Navy]], and the [[U.S. Marine Corps]] after 2020 by the Joint Dual Role Air Dominance Missile ([[Next Generation Missile]]), but it was terminated in the 2013 budget plan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/usaf-cancels-amraam-replacement-368249/ |title=USAF cancels AMRAAM replacement |work=Flight International |date=February 14, 2012 |accessdate=April 12, 2012 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120508220712/http://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/usaf-cancels-amraam-replacement-368249/ |archive-date=May 8, 2012 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt; Exploratory work was started in 2017 on a replacement called [[Long-Range Engagement Weapon]].

In 2017, work on the '''[[AIM-260 Joint Advanced Tactical Missile]]''' ('''JATM''') began to create a longer-ranged replacement for the AMRAAM to contend with foreign weapons like the [[PL-15]]. Flight tests are planned to begin in 2021 and initial operational capability is slated for 2022, facilitating the end of AMRAAM production by 2026.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.airforcemag.com/Features/Pages/2019/June%202019/Air-Force-Developing-AMRAAM-Replacement-to-Counter-China.aspx Air Force Developing AMRAAM Replacement to Counter China] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190622194327/http://www.airforcemag.com/Features/Pages/2019/June%25202019/Air-Force-Developing-AMRAAM-Replacement-to-Counter-China.aspx |date=June 22, 2019 }}. ''Air Force Magazine''. 20 June 2019.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ground-launched systems===
{{main|SLAMRAAM}}
[[File:AIM-120 AMRAAM P6230147.JPG|thumb|Battery of four SL-AMRAAM on HMMWV]]
[[File:AMRAAM-ER.jpg|thumb|AMRAAM-ER]]

[[Raytheon]] successfully tested launching AMRAAM missiles from a five-missile carrier on a M1097 [[Humvee]]. This system will be known as the '''SLAMRAAM''' (Surface Launched (SL) and AMRAAM). They receive their initial guidance information from a radar not mounted on the vehicle. Since the missile is launched without the benefit of an aircraft's speed or high altitude, its range is considerably shorter. Raytheon is currently marketing an SL-AMRAAM EX, purported to be an extended range AMRAAM and bearing a resemblance to the [[RIM-162 ESSM]].

The [[NASAMS|Norwegian Advanced Surface-to-Air Missile System]] (NASAMS), developed by [[Kongsberg Defence &amp; Aerospace]], consists of a number of vehicle-pulled launch batteries (containing six AMRAAMs each) along with separate radar trucks and control station vehicles. A more recent version of the program is the ''High Mobility Launcher'', made in cooperation with [[Raytheon]] (Kongsberg Defence &amp; Aerospace was already a subcontractor on the SLAMRAAM system), where the launch-vehicle is a [[Humvee]] (M1152A1 HMMWV), containing four AMRAAMs each.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.kongsberg.com/en/kog/news/2013/june/ny-kapasitet-i-nasams-luftvernsystem/ |title=New capability in the NASAMS air defence system |publisher=Kongsberg.com |date=June 21, 2013 |accessdate=January 31, 2016 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160303000603/http://www.kongsberg.com/en/kog/news/2013/june/ny-kapasitet-i-nasams-luftvernsystem/ |archive-date=March 3, 2016 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;

While still under evaluation for replacement of current US Army assets, the SL-AMRAAM has been deployed in several nations' military forces. The United Arab Emirates (UAE) has requested the purchasing of SL-AMRAAM as part of a larger $7 billion foreign military sales package. The sale would include 288 AMRAAM C-7 missiles.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine |url=http://www.aviationweek.com/aw/generic/story_channel.jsp?channel=defense&amp;id=news/DSCA091108.xml&amp;headline=DSCA%20Announces%20Billions%20In%20Military%20Sales |title=DSCA Announces Billions in Military Sales |magazine=Aviation Week |date=September 11, 2008 |accessdate=April 12, 2012 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120307150630/http://www.aviationweek.com/aw/generic/story_channel.jsp?channel=defense&amp;id=news%2FDSCA091108.xml&amp;headline=DSCA%20Announces%20Billions%20In%20Military%20Sales |archivedate=March 7, 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The US Army has test fired the SL-AMRAAM from a [[HIMARS]] artillery rocket launcher as a common launcher, as part of a move to switch to a larger and more survivable launch platform.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lockheedmartin.com/news/press_releases/2009/MFC_032509_LockheedMartinsHIMARSLauncher.html HIMARS Launcher Successfully Fires Air Defense Missile] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110813225039/http://www.lockheedmartin.com/news/press_releases/2009/MFC_032509_LockheedMartinsHIMARSLauncher.html |date=August 13, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.upi.com/Business_News/Security-Industry/2010/09/10/Raytheon-Army-test-new-SLAMRAAM-platform/UPI-16391284134034/ |title=Raytheon, Army test new SLAMRAAM platform |publisher=Upi.com |date=September 10, 2010 |accessdate=April 12, 2012 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121022004916/http://www.upi.com/Business_News/Security-Industry/2010/09/10/Raytheon-Army-test-new-SLAMRAAM-platform/UPI-16391284134034/ |archive-date=October 22, 2012 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;

On January 6, 2011, Secretary of Defense [[Robert Gates]] announced that the U.S. Army has decided to terminate acquisition of the SLAMRAAM as part of a budget-cutting effort.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://richmedia.onset.freedom.com/nwfdn/lemv4s-7jsfgatestranscripts.pdf|title=Statement on Department Budget and Efficiencies|work=U.S. Department of Defense|date=January 6, 2011|format=PDF|accessdate=July 13, 2011|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110711025437/http://richmedia.onset.freedom.com/nwfdn/lemv4s-7jsfgatestranscripts.pdf|archivedate=July 11, 2011|url-status=dead|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The National Guard Association of the United States has sent a letter asking for the U.S. Senate to stop the Army's plan to drop the SLAMRAAM program because without it there would be no path to modernize the Guard's [[AN/TWQ-1 Avenger]] Battalions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.defensenews.com/story.php?i=4847002&amp;c=AME&amp;s=LAN |title=U.S. Army Recommends SLAMRAAM Termination |publisher=Defensenews.com |accessdate=April 12, 2012 }}{{Dead link|date=July 2018 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 22 February 2015, Raytheon announced an Extended Range upgrade to NASAMS-launched AMRAAM, calling it [[NASAMS#AMRAAM-ER|AMRAAM-ER]]. This combines the AMRAAM seeker with the ESSM rocket motor.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.defensenews.com/articles/raytheons-extended-range-amraam-missile-destroys-target-in-first-flight-test |title=Raytheon’s Extended Range AMRAAM Missile Destroys Target in First Flight Test |last1=Judson |first1=Jen |date=4 October 2016 |website=www.defensenews.com |publisher=Sightline Media Group |accessdate=4 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Operational history==
The AMRAAM was used for the first time on December 27, 1992, when a USAF [[F-16 Fighting Falcon|F-16D]] shot down an Iraqi [[MiG-25]] that violated the southern no-fly-zone.&lt;ref&gt;Bjorkman, Eileen, &quot;Small, fast and in your face&quot;, ''Air &amp; Space'', February/March 2014, p. 35.&lt;/ref&gt; This missile had been returned from the flight line as defective a day earlier. AMRAAM gained a second victory in January 1993 when an Iraqi [[MiG-23]] was shot down by a USAF [[F-16 Fighting Falcon|F-16C]].

The third combat use of the AMRAAM was in 1994, when a [[Republika Srpska Air Force]] [[Soko J-21 Jastreb|J-21 Jastreb]] aircraft was shot down by a USAF [[F-16]]C that was patrolling the UN-imposed no-fly zone over [[Bosnia]]. In that engagement, at least three other Serbian aircraft were shot down by USAF F-16C fighters using [[AIM-9]] missiles (see [[Banja Luka incident]] for more details). At that point, three launches in combat had resulted in three kills, resulting in the AMRAAM's being informally named &quot;slammer&quot; in the second half of the 1990s.{{Citation needed|date=January 2020}}

In 1998 and 1999 AMRAAMs were again fired by USAF [[McDonnell Douglas F-15 Eagle|F-15]] fighters at Iraqi aircraft violating the No-Fly-Zone, but this time they failed to hit their targets. During spring 1999, AMRAAMs saw their main combat action during [[Operation Allied Force]], the Kosovo [[1999 NATO bombing of the Federal Republic of Yugoslavia|bombing campaign]]. Six Serbian MiG-29 were shot down by NATO (four USAF F-15Cs, one USAF F-16C, and one Dutch F-16A MLU), all of them using AIM-120 missiles (the supposed kill by the F-16C may have actually been friendly fire, an [[SA-7]] MANPADS fired by Serbian infantry).&lt;ref name=&quot;ausairpower.net&quot;&gt;{{cite web |author=Air Power Australia |url=http://www.ausairpower.net/APA-Rus-BVR-AAM.html |title=Air Power Australia: Technical Report APA-TR-2008-0301 |pages=1 |publisher=Ausairpower.net |accessdate=April 12, 2012 |date=2008-03-15 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120430182655/http://www.ausairpower.net/APA-Rus-BVR-AAM.html |archive-date=April 30, 2012 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 18 June 2017, a US [[Boeing F/A-18E/F Super Hornet|F/A-18E Super Hornet]] engaged and [[Ja'Din shootdown incident|shot down]] a [[Sukhoi Su-22]] of the [[Syrian Air Force]] over northern Syria,&lt;ref name=&quot;auto&quot;/&gt; using an AIM-120. The Su-22 had previously avoided an [[AIM-9 Sidewinder#AIM-9X|AIM-9X Sidewinder]]; it was initially though this was done by using flares,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.popularmechanics.com/military/aviation/news/a27094/su-22-dodge-aim-9x-sidewinder/ |title=How Did a 30-Year-Old Jet Dodge the Pentagon's Latest Missile? |last=Mizokami |first=Kyle |date=June 27, 2017 |website=[[Popular Mechanics]] |access-date=December 7, 2017 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171207192704/http://www.popularmechanics.com/military/aviation/news/a27094/su-22-dodge-aim-9x-sidewinder/ |archive-date=December 7, 2017 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Browne |first=Ryan |date=June 22, 2017 |title=New details on US shoot down of Syrian jet |url=http://www.cnn.com/2017/06/21/politics/us-syria-russia-dogfight/index.html |work=[[CNN]] |access-date=December 7, 2017 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171204191838/http://www.cnn.com/2017/06/21/politics/us-syria-russia-dogfight/index.html |archive-date=December 4, 2017 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/checkpoint/wp/2017/06/18/a-u-s-aircraft-has-shot-down-a-syrian-government-jet-over-northern-syria-pentagon-says/ &quot;A U.S. aircraft has shot down a Syrian government jet over northern Syria, Pentagon says&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170620153944/https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/checkpoint/wp/2017/06/18/a-u-s-aircraft-has-shot-down-a-syrian-government-jet-over-northern-syria-pentagon-says/ |date=June 20, 2017 }}. Retrieved 18 June 2017.&lt;/ref&gt; although first-hand account by the F/A-18E pilot, Lt. Cmdr. Michael Tremel, was that the AIM-9X malfunctioned and failed to acquire the target, with no use of flares by the Su-22.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Rogoway |first=Tyler |title=Here's The Definitive Account Of The Syrian Su-22 Shoot Down From The Pilots Themselves |url=https://www.thedrive.com/the-war-zone/14344/heres-the-definitive-account-of-the-syrian-su-22-shoot-down-from-the-pilots-themselves |website=[[www.thedrive.com/the-war-zone/]] |access-date=November 14, 2019 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;

As of 2017, the AIM-120 AMRAAM has shot down eleven aircraft (six [[MiG-29]]s, one [[MiG-25]], one [[MiG-23]], one [[Sukhoi Su-17|Su-22]], one [[Soko J-21 Jastreb]], and one [[UH-60 Black Hawk]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;ausairpower.net&quot;/&gt; The latter was a friendly fire incident in 1994 when [[McDonnell Douglas F-15 Eagle|F-15]] fighters patrolling Iraq's Northern No-Fly Zone [[1994 Black Hawk shootdown incident|inadvertently shot down]] a pair of [[U.S. Army]] [[UH-60 Black Hawk|Black Hawk]] helicopters, one by an AIM-9 Sidewinder.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.nytimes.com/1994/04/15/world/us-jets-over-iraq-attack-own-helicopters-in-error-all-26-on-board-are-killed.html |title=U.S. Jets Over Iraq Attack Own Helicopters in Error; All 26 on Board Are Killed |last=R. Gordon |first=Michael |date=April 15, 1994 |work=The New York Times |accessdate=March 18, 2010 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130520123816/http://www.nytimes.com/1994/04/15/world/us-jets-over-iraq-attack-own-helicopters-in-error-all-26-on-board-are-killed.html |archive-date=May 20, 2013 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 7 August 2018, a Spanish Air Force [[Eurofighter Typhoon]] accidentally launched a missile in Estonia.&lt;ref name=&quot;abc-2018&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://abcnews.go.com/International/wireStory/spanish-fighter-jet-accidentally-fires-missile-estonia-57091457 |title=Spanish fighter jet accidentally fires missile In Estonia |access-date=August 8, 2018 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180808100555/https://abcnews.go.com/International/wireStory/spanish-fighter-jet-accidentally-fires-missile-estonia-57091457 |archive-date=August 8, 2018 |url-status=dead |df=mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; There were no human casualties, but a ten-day search operation for missile remains was unsuccessful.&lt;ref name=&quot;abc-2018&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;elpais-2018&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://elpais.com/politica/2018/09/27/actualidad/1538068366_828355.html |title=Sanción mínima para el piloto al que se le escapó un misil en Estonia |access-date=October 2, 2018 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20181002214925/https://elpais.com/politica/2018/09/27/actualidad/1538068366_828355.html |archive-date=October 2, 2018 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 27 February 2019, Pakistan Air Force downed an Indian Air Force MiG-21 Bison with its F-16s; Indian officials displayed fragments of the alleged AIM-120C-5 missile.&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimes-201903-03&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2019/03/03/world/asia/india-military-united-states-china.html |title=After India Loses Dogfight to Pakistan, Questions Arise About Its ‘Vintage’ Military |access-date=29 April 2019 |work=New York Times|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190304125040/https://www.nytimes.com/2019/03/03/world/asia/india-military-united-states-china.html |archive-date=4 March 2019 |url-status=live|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; Pakistan denies the use of F-16 in this aerial engagement.

==Foreign sales==
Canadair, now [[Bombardier Aerospace|Bombardier]], had largely helped with the development of the [[AIM-7 Sparrow]] and Sparrow II, and assisted to a lesser extent in the AIM-120 development. Canada had placed an order for 256 AIM-120's, but cancelled half of them after engine ignition problems due to cold weather conditions. The AIM-9X &amp; AIM-7 were ordered as replacements.

In early 1995 South Korea ordered 88 AIM-120A missiles for its KF-16 fleet. In 1997 South Korea ordered 737 additional AIM-120B missiles.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://newslibrary.naver.com/viewer/index.nhn?articleId=1995081400329102011&amp;editNo=40&amp;printCount=1&amp;publishDate=1995-08-14&amp;officeId=00032&amp;pageNo=2&amp;printNo=15510&amp;publishType=00010|title=네이버  뉴스 라이브러리|work=naver.com|accessdate=April 12, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.deagel.com/equipment/Air-to-Air-Missiles/AIM-120-AMRAAM.htm|title=AIM-120 AMRAAM Report Between 1995 and 2014|work=deagel.com|accessdate=April 12, 2016|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160406064649/http://www.deagel.com/equipment/Air-to-Air-Missiles/AIM-120-AMRAAM.htm|archivedate=April 6, 2016|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2006 Poland received AIM-120C-5 missiles to arm its new [[F-16|F-16C/D Block 52+]] fighters.&lt;ref name=&quot;deagel&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.deagel.com/equipment/Air-to-Air-Missiles-AIM-120-AMRAAM-a001164.aspx |title=Air-to-Air Missiles &gt;&gt; AIM-120 AMRAAM |website=www.deagel.com |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110918175628/http://www.deagel.com/equipment/Air-to-Air-Missiles-AIM-120-AMRAAM-a001164.aspx |archive-date=September 18, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In early 2006, the [[Pakistan Air Force]] (PAF) ordered 500 AIM-120C-5 AMRAAM missiles as part of a $650 million F-16 ammunition deal to equip its [[F-16|F-16C/D Block 50/52+]] and [[F-16|F-16A/B Block 15 MLU]] fighters. The PAF got the first three F-16C/D Block 50/52+ aircraft on July 3, 2010 and first batch of AMRAAMs on July 26, 2010.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.prnewswire.com/cgi-bin/micro_stories.pl?ACCT=149999&amp;TICK=RTN&amp;STORY=/www/story/01-15-2007/0004505958&amp;EDATE=Jan+15,+2007 Raytheon Press Release, 15 January 2007] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080129160020/http://www.prnewswire.com/cgi-bin/micro_stories.pl?ACCT=149999&amp;TICK=RTN&amp;STORY=%2Fwww%2Fstory%2F01-15-2007%2F0004505958&amp;EDATE=Jan+15%2C+2007 |date=January 29, 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2007, the United States government agreed to sell 218 AIM-120C-7 missiles to Taiwan as part of a large arms sales package that also included 235 AGM-65G-2 Maverick missiles. Total value of the package, including launchers, maintenance, spare parts, support and training rounds, was estimated at around US$421 million. This supplemented an earlier Taiwanese purchase of 120 AIM-120C-5 missiles a few years ago.&lt;ref name=&quot;deagel&quot;/&gt;

2008 has brought announcements of new or additional sales to Singapore, Finland, Morocco and South Korea; in December 2010 the Swiss government requested 150 AIM-120C-7 missiles.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.defpro.com/news/details/20859/|accessdate=December 27, 2010|title=defence.professionals|publisher=defpro.com|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20101228081149/http://www.defpro.com/news/details/20859/|archive-date=December 28, 2010|url-status=dead|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sales to Finland have stalled, because the manufacturer has not been able to fix a mysterious bug that causes the rocket motors of the missile to fail in cold tests.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hs.fi/kotimaa/Outo+vika+pys%C3%A4ytti+ohjuskaupan/a1346553626705|title=Outo vika pysäytti ohjuskaupan|work=HS.fi|accessdate=April 12, 2016|date=2012-09-03|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140221215901/http://www.hs.fi/kotimaa/Outo+vika+pys%C3%A4ytti+ohjuskaupan/a1346553626705|archive-date=February 21, 2014|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; In May 5, 2015, the State Department has made a determination approving a possible Foreign Military Sale to [[Royal Malaysian Air Force]] for AIM-120C7 AMRAAM missiles and associated equipment, parts and logistical support for an estimated cost of $21 million.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dsca.mil/major-arms-sales/malaysia-aim-120c7-amraam-missiles|title=Malaysia-AIM-120C7 AMRAAM|work=Defense Security Cooperation Agency|accessdate=February 12, 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170212164227/http://www.dsca.mil/major-arms-sales/malaysia-aim-120c7-amraam-missiles|archive-date=February 12, 2017|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.airforce-technology.com/news/newsus-approves-sale-of-aim-120c7-amraam-missiles-to-malaysia-4571072|title=US approves sale of AIM-120C7 AMRAAM missiles to Malaysia|work=airforce-technology.com|accessdate=February 12, 2017|date=2015-05-06|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170212165230/http://www.airforce-technology.com/news/newsus-approves-sale-of-aim-120c7-amraam-missiles-to-malaysia-4571072|archive-date=February 12, 2017|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In March 2016, the US government approved the sales of AIM-120C-7 missiles to the [[Indonesian Air Force]] to equip their fleet of F-16 C/D Block 32+.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dsca.mil/major-arms-sales/indonesia-aim-120c-7-advanced-medium-range-air-air-missiles-amraams|title=Indonesia - AIM-120C-7 Advanced Medium-Range Air-to-Air Missiles (AMRAAMs)|work=Defense Security Cooperation Agency|accessdate=April 12, 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171230182901/http://www.dsca.mil/major-arms-sales/indonesia-aim-120c-7-advanced-medium-range-air-air-missiles-amraams|archive-date=December 30, 2017|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://thediplomat.com/2016/03/us-clears-sale-of-advanced-missiles-to-indonesia/|title=US Clears Sale of Advanced Missiles to Indonesia|author=Franz-Stefan Gady|work=The Diplomat|accessdate=April 12, 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160424201737/http://thediplomat.com/2016/03/us-clears-sale-of-advanced-missiles-to-indonesia/|archive-date=April 24, 2016|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In March 2019, the US Department of State and Defense Security Cooperation Agency have formally signed-off on a US$240.5 million foreign military sale to support [[Australia]]’s introduction of the [[NASAMS]] and LAND 19 Phase 7B program. As part of the deal, the Australian government requested up to 108 Raytheon AIM-120C-7 AMRAAM, six AIM-120C-7 AMRAAM Air Vehicles Instrumented; and six spare AIM-120C-7 AMRAAM guidance sections.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.defenceconnect.com.au/key-enablers/3723-us-approves-foreign-military-sale-for-australian-air-defence-capability|title=US approves foreign military sale for Australian Air Defence Capability|last=Kuper|first=Stephen|last2=Kuper|first2=Stephen|date=2019-03-14|website=www.defenceconnect.com.au|language=en|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Operators==
[[File:AIM-120 operators.png|thumb|300px|Map with AIM-120 operators in blue]]

===Current operators===
;{{Flagu|Australia}}
*[[Royal Australian Air Force]]
;{{Flagu|Belgium}}
*[[Belgian Air Component]]
;{{Flagu|Bahrain}}
*[[Royal Bahraini Air Force]]
;{{Flagu|Canada}}&lt;ref name=&quot;2018b&quot;&gt;{{cite journal| author=International Institute for Strategic Studies (IISS)| authorlink=International Institute for Strategic Studies| title=The Military Balance 2018| journal=The Military Balance| volume=118| issue=| pages=| date=14 February 2018| language=english| doi= }}&lt;/ref&gt; 
*[[Royal Canadian Air Force]]
;{{Flagu|Chile}}
*[[Chilean Air Force]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.insightcrime.org/news-briefs/chile-air-force-peru-hackers-cyber-threat|title=Infiltration of Chile Air Force Emails Highlights LatAm Cyber Threats|first=Kyra|last=Gurney|date=15 August 2014|website=InSightCrime|access-date=August 19, 2014|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140821012214/http://www.insightcrime.org/news-briefs/chile-air-force-peru-hackers-cyber-threat|archive-date=August 21, 2014|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;
;{{Flagu|Czech Republic}}
*[[Czech Air Force]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.radio.cz/en/news/65161#2 |title=Czech Air force has bought 24 AMRAAMs |publisher=Radio.cz |accessdate=April 12, 2012 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120329033806/http://www.radio.cz/en/section/news/news-2005-04-06 |archivedate=March 29, 2012 |df=mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
;{{Flagu|Denmark}}
*[[Royal Danish Air Force]]
;{{Flagu|Finland}}
*[[Finnish Air Force]]
;{{Flagu|Germany}}
*[[German Air Force]]
;{{Flagu|Greece}}
*[[Hellenic Air Force]]
;{{Flagu|Hungary}}
*[[Hungarian Air Force]]
;{{Flagu|Indonesia}}
*[[Indonesian Air Force]]
;{{Flagu|Israel}}
*[[Israeli Air Force]]
;{{Flagu|Italy}}
*[[Italian Air Force]]
*[[Italian Navy]]
;{{Flagu|Japan}}
*[[Japan Air Self-Defense Force]] (Test uses)
;{{Flagu|Jordan}}
*[[Royal Jordanian Air Force]]
;{{Flagu|Kuwait}}
*[[Kuwait Air Force]]
;{{Flagu|Morocco}}
*[[Royal Moroccan Air Force]]
;{{Flagu|Malaysia}}
*[[Royal Malaysian Air Force]]
;{{Flagu|Netherlands}}
*[[Royal Netherlands Air Force]]
;{{Flagu|Norway}}
*[[Royal Norwegian Air Force]]
;{{Flagu|Oman}}
*[[Royal Air Force of Oman]] (RAFO)
;{{Flagu|Pakistan}}
*[[Pakistani Air Force]]
;{{Flagu|Poland}}
*[[Polish Air Force]]
;{{Flagu|Portugal}}
*[[Portuguese Air Force]]
;{{Flagu|Qatar}}
*[[Qatar Air Force]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://defpost.com/raytheon-receives-19m-contract-modification-for-amraam-missile-production-program/ |title=Raytheon Receives $19M Contract Modification for AMRAAM Missile Production Program |publisher=Defpost.com |accessdate=April 17, 2019 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190418060707/https://defpost.com/raytheon-receives-19m-contract-modification-for-amraam-missile-production-program/ |archive-date=April 18, 2019 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;
;{{Flagu|Romania}}
*[[Romanian Air Force]]
;{{Flagu|Saudi Arabia}}
*[[Royal Saudi Air Force]]
;{{Flagu|Singapore}}
*[[Republic of Singapore Air Force]]
;{{Flagu|South Korea}}
*[[Republic of Korea Air Force]]
;{{Flagu|Switzerland}}
*[[Swiss Air Force]]
;{{Flagu|Spain}}
*[[Spanish Air Force]]
*[[Spanish Army]]
*[[Spanish Navy]]
;{{Flagu|Sweden}}
*[[Swedish Air Force]]
;{{Flagu|Republic of China}}
*[[Republic of China Air Force]]
;{{Flagu|Thailand}}
*[[Royal Thai Air Force]]
;{{Flagu|Turkey}}
*[[Turkish Air Force]]
;{{Flagu|United Arab Emirates}}
*[[United Arab Emirates Air Force]]
;{{Flagu|United Kingdom}}
*[[Royal Air Force]]
;{{Flagu|United States}}
*[[United States Air Force]]&lt;ref name=&quot;2018b&quot;/&gt;
*[[United States Navy]]
*[[United States Marine Corps]]&lt;ref name=&quot;2018b&quot;/&gt;

==See also==
*[[BVRAAM]]
*[[FMRAAM]]
*[[List of missiles]]

===Similar weapons===
*[[AIM-7 Sparrow]]
*[[AAM-4]]
*[[Astra (missile)|Astra]]
*[[Rafael Derby|Derby]]
*[[R-27 (air-to-air missile)|R-27EA]]
*[[R-77]]
*[[MICA (missile)|MICA]]
*[[Meteor (missile)|Meteor]]&lt;!--Do not change this to &quot;MBDA Meteor&quot; as that name has been deprecated and redirects to &quot;Meteor (missile)&quot;--&gt;
*[[Sky Sword II]]
*[[PL-12]]
*[[PL-15]]

==References==
;Notes
{{Reflist|30em}}

;Bibliography
{{Refbegin}}
* {{Cite book|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=cfpBbuIlfV0C | title= Illustrated Directory of Modern American Weapons| last2 = Miller| first2 = David |publisher= Zenith | year = 2002 |isbn=978-0-7603-1346-6|chapter=AIM-120 AMRAAM|ref= | last1 =Bonds|first1 =Ray }}
*{{Cite book|title=Fighter Wing|last=Clancy|first=Tom| publisher = Harper Collins | year = 1995|isbn=978-0-00-255527-2|location= London |chapter=Ordnance: How Bombs Got 'Smart'|ref= }}
{{Refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|AIM-120 AMRAAM}}
* {{official website|http://www.raytheon.com/capabilities/products/amraam/}}{{Dead{{Dead link|date=September 2019 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }} link|date=August 2019 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}
* [http://www.designation-systems.net/dusrm/m-120.html AIM-120 at Designation-Systems].
* {{cite news |url= https://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/analysis-raytheon-hits-milestone-for-missile-that-c-433620/ |title= ANALYSIS: Raytheon hits milestone for missile that changed air warfare |date= 6 February 2017 |work= Flight Global |author= Stephen Trimble |location= Washington, D.C.}}

{{Raytheon}}
{{US missiles}}
{{USAF equipment}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Aim-120 Amraam}}
[[Category:Post–Cold War air-to-air missiles of the United States|AIM-120]]
[[Category:Surface-to-air missiles of the United States|AIM120]]
[[Category:Raytheon products]]</text>
      <sha1>leq7ga54nohtskrcw8zudpzjou0en3f</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
