  <page>
    <title>Alien and Sedition Acts</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3173</id>
    <revision>
      <id>940640569</id>
      <parentid>940633336</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-13T19:28:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>North Shoreman</username>
        <id>1664557</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contribs/2600:1012:B12E:5452:9C4E:2956:7FA:F317|2600:1012:B12E:5452:9C4E:2956:7FA:F317]] ([[User talk:2600:1012:B12E:5452:9C4E:2956:7FA:F317|talk]]) to last version by JavaHurricane</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">The '''Alien and Sedition Acts''' were four laws passed by the [[Federalist Party|Federalist]]-dominated [[5th United States Congress]] and signed into law by President [[John Adams]] in 1798.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://www.crf-usa.org/america-responds-to-terrorism/the-alien-and-sedition-acts.html|title = The Alien and Sedition Acts: Defining American Freedom|date = 2003|accessdate = 14 October 2015|website = Constitutional Rights Foundation|last = |first = }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;An [[alien (law)|alien]] in this sense is a person who is not a national of the United States.&lt;/ref&gt; They made it harder for an immigrant to become a citizen ([[Naturalization Act of 1798|Naturalization Act]]), allowed the president to imprison and deport non-citizens who were deemed dangerous (&quot;An Act Concerning Aliens&quot;, also known as the Alien Friends Act of 1798)&lt;ref&gt;[https://memory.loc.gov/cgi-bin/ampage?collId=llsl&amp;fileName=001/llsl001.db&amp;recNum=693 &quot;An Act Concerning Aliens&quot;], Sess II, Chap. 58; 5th Congress; 25 June 1798&lt;/ref&gt; or who were from a hostile nation (Alien Enemy Act of 1798),&lt;ref&gt;[http://library.uwb.edu/static/USimmigration/1%20stat%20577.pdf library.uwb.edu: &quot;An Act respecting Alien Enemies&quot;], Sess II, Chap. 58; 1 Stat. 577 5th Congress; ch. 66 25 June 1798&lt;/ref&gt; and criminalized making false statements that were critical of the federal government (Sedition Act of 1798).&lt;ref&gt;[https://memory.loc.gov/cgi-bin/ampage?collId=llsl&amp;fileName=001/llsl001.db&amp;recNum=719 'An Act in addition the act, entitled, &quot;An Act for the punishment of certain crimes against the United States&quot;'], Sess II, Chap. 74; 5th Congress; 14 July 1798&lt;/ref&gt;  The Alien Friends Act expired two years after its passage, and the Sedition Act expired on 3 March 1801, while the Naturalization Act and Alien Enemies Act had no expiration clause.

The Federalists argued that the bills strengthened national security during the [[Quasi-War]], an undeclared naval war with France from 1798 to 1800. Critics argued that they were primarily an attempt to suppress voters who disagreed with the Federalist party and its teachings, and violated the right of freedom of speech in the [[First Amendment to the United States Constitution|First Amendment]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Watkins|first=William J., Jr.|title=Reclaiming the American Revolution|page=28|isbn=978-0-230-60257-1|date=2008-02-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Naturalization Act increased the residency requirement for [[Citizenship in the United States|American citizenship]] from five to fourteen years. At the time, the majority of immigrants supported [[Thomas Jefferson]] and the [[Democratic-Republican Party|Democratic-Republicans]], the political opponents of the Federalists.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://www.crf-usa.org/america-responds-to-terrorism/the-alien-and-sedition-acts.html|title = The Alien and Sedition Acts: Defining American Freedom|date = 2003|accessdate = 14 October 2015|website = Constitutional Rights Foundation|last = |first = }}&lt;/ref&gt; The Alien Friends Act allowed the president to imprison or deport aliens considered &quot;dangerous to the peace and safety of the United States&quot; at any time, while the Alien Enemies Act authorized the president to do the same to any male citizen of a hostile nation above the age of fourteen during times of war. Lastly, the controversial Sedition Act restricted speech that was critical of the federal government. Under the Sedition Act, the Federalists allowed people who were accused of violating the sedition laws to use truth as a defense.&lt;ref name=&quot;acons&quot;&gt;{{cite book|first1=Howard |last1=Gillman |first2=Mark A. |last2=Graber |first3=Keith E. |last3=Whittington|title=American Constitutionalism|date=2012|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=New York|isbn=978-0-19-975135-8|page=174}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Sedition Act resulted in the prosecution and conviction of many Jeffersonian newspaper owners who disagreed with the government.&lt;ref name=&quot;acons&quot;/&gt;

The acts were denounced by Democratic-Republicans and ultimately helped them to victory in the [[1800 United States presidential election|1800 election]], when [[Thomas Jefferson]] defeated the incumbent, President Adams. The Sedition Act and the Alien Friends Act were allowed to expire in 1800 and 1801, respectively.  The Alien Enemies Act, however, remains in effect as Chapter 3; Sections 21–24 of [[Title 50 of the United States Code]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/text/50/chapter-3|title=Alien Enemies|publisher=Cornell University Law School|accessdate=October 17, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was used by the government to identify and imprison dangerous enemy aliens from Germany, Japan, and Italy in World War II. (This was separate from the [[Internment of Japanese Americans|Japanese internment camps]] used to remove people of Japanese descent from the West Coast.) After the war they were deported to their home countries. In 1948 the Supreme Court determined that presidential powers under the acts continued after cessation of hostilities until there was a peace treaty with the hostile nation. The revised Alien Enemies Act remains in effect today.&lt;ref name=&quot;AEAPP&quot; /&gt;

==History==
The Federalists' fear of the opposing Democratic-Republican Party reached new heights with the Democratic-Republicans' support of France in the midst of the [[French Revolution]]. Some appeared to desire a similar revolution in the United States to overthrow the government and social structure.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Thomas Jefferson: Establishing a Federal Republic|url=https://www.loc.gov/exhibits/jefferson/jefffed.html|website=Library of Congress}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Newspapers sympathizing with each side exacerbated the tensions by accusing the other side's leaders of corruption, incompetence, and treason&lt;ref name=&quot;Weisberger&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Weisberger|first1=Bernard A.|title=America Afire: Jefferson, Adams, and the Revolutionary Election of 1800|date=2000|publisher=William Morrow|page=201}}&lt;/ref&gt;  As the unrest sweeping Europe threatened to spread to the United States, calls for secession started to rise, and the fledgling nation seemed ready to tear itself apart.&lt;ref name=&quot;Knott p48&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Knott|first1=Stephen F.|title=Alexander Hamilton and the Persistence of Myth|date=2005|publisher=University Press of Kansas|location=Lawrence|isbn=978-0-7006-1419-6|page=48}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some of this agitation was seen by Federalists as having been caused by French and French-sympathizing immigrants.&lt;ref name=&quot;Knott p48&quot;/&gt;  The Alien Act and the Sedition Act were meant to guard against this perceived threat of anarchy.

The Acts were highly controversial at the time, especially the Sedition Act.  The Sedition Act was hotly debated in the Federalist-controlled Congress and passed only after multiple amendments softening its terms, such as enabling defendants to argue in their defense that their statements had been true.  Still, it passed the House only after three votes and another amendment causing it to automatically expire in March 1801&lt;ref name=&quot;Weisberger&quot;/&gt;.  They continued to be loudly protested and were a major political issue in the election of 1800.  Opposition to them resulted in the also-controversial [[Virginia and Kentucky Resolutions]], authored by [[James Madison]] and [[Thomas Jefferson]].

Prominent prosecutions under the Sedition Act include:

* [[James Thomson Callender]], a British subject, had been expelled from Great Britain for his political writings. Living first in Philadelphia, then seeking refuge close by in Virginia, he wrote a book titled ''The Prospect Before Us'' (read and approved by Vice President Jefferson before publication) in which he called the Adams administration a &quot;continual tempest of malignant passions&quot; and the President a &quot;repulsive pedant, a gross hypocrite and an unprincipled oppressor.&quot; Callender, already residing in Virginia and writing for the ''Richmond Examiner'', was indicted in mid-1800 under the Sedition Act and convicted, fined $200, and sentenced to nine months in jail.&lt;ref name=&quot;miller&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Miller |first=John C. |title=Crisis in Freedom: The Alien and Sedition Acts |url=https://archive.org/details/crisisinfreedoma0000mill |url-access=registration |location=New York |publisher=Little Brown and Company |date=1951}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|211–20}}
* [[Matthew Lyon]] was a Democratic-Republican congressman from Vermont. He was the first individual to be placed on trial under the Alien and Sedition Acts.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt; He was indicted in 1800 for an essay he had written in the ''Vermont Journal'' accusing the administration of &quot;ridiculous pomp, foolish adulation, and selfish avarice.&quot; While awaiting trial, Lyon commenced publication of ''Lyon's Republican Magazine'', subtitled &quot;The Scourge of Aristocracy&quot;. At trial, he was fined $1,000 and sentenced to four months in jail. After his release, he returned to Congress.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Foner |first=Eric|title=Give Me Liberty!|pages=282–83|year=2008|publisher=W.W. Norton and Company|isbn=978-0-393-93257-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{r|miller|page1=102–08}}
* [[Benjamin Franklin Bache (Journalist)|Benjamin Franklin Bache]] was editor of the ''[[Philadelphia Aurora]]'', a Democratic-Republican newspaper. Bache had accused [[George Washington]] of incompetence and financial irregularities, and &quot;the blind, bald, crippled, toothless, querulous Adams&quot; of nepotism and monarchical ambition. He was arrested in 1798 under the Sedition Act, but he died of yellow fever before trial.{{r|miller|page1=27–29, 65, 96}}
* [[Anthony Haswell (printer)|Anthony Haswell]] was an English immigrant and a printer of the Jeffersonian ''[[Vermont Gazette]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Tyler|first1=Resch|title=Anthony Haswell|url=http://www.benningtonmuseum.org/anthony-haswell.html|website=Bennington Museum|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160402201213/http://www.benningtonmuseum.org/anthony-haswell.html|archivedate=April 2, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Haswell had reprinted from the ''Aurora'' Bache's claim that the federal government employed [[Tories]], also publishing an advertisement from Lyon's sons for a lottery to raise money for his fine that decried Lyon's oppression by jailers exercising &quot;usurped powers&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=Francis |last=Wharton |title=State Trials of the United States during the administrations of Washington and Adams |url=https://archive.org/details/statetrialsunit00whargoog |location=Philadelphia |publisher=Carey and Hart |date=1849 |pages=684–87}}&lt;/ref&gt; Haswell was found guilty of seditious libel by judge [[William Paterson (judge)|William Paterson]], and sentenced to a two-month imprisonment and a $200 fine.&lt;ref name=&quot;Perilous&quot;/&gt;
* Luther Baldwin was indicted, convicted, and fined $100 for a drunken incident that occurred during a visit by President Adams to Newark, New Jersey. Upon hearing a gun report during a parade, he yelled &quot;I hope it hit Adams in the arse.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|last=Smith |first=James Morton|title=Freedom's Fetters: The Alien and Sedition Laws and American Civil Liberties |date=1956|publisher=Cornell University Press|location=Ithaca, NY |pages=270–74}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{r|miller|page1=112–14}}
* In November 1798, [[David Brown (Massachusetts)|David Brown]] led a group in [[Dedham, Massachusetts]], including [[Benjamin Fairbanks]], in setting up a [[liberty pole]] with the words, &quot;No [[Stamp Act 1765|Stamp Act]], No Sedition Act, No Alien Bills, No Land Tax, downfall to the Tyrants of America; peace and retirement to the President; Long Live the Vice President.&quot;&lt;ref name = Perilous&gt;{{cite book | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=S7ScI3Ia25sC&amp;pg=PA63 | pages = 63–64 | title = Perilous Times: Free Speech in Wartime from the Sedition Act of 1798 to the War on Terrorism | first = Geoffrey R. | last = Stone | publisher = W. W. Norton &amp; Company | year = 2004 | isbn=978-0-393-05880-2 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;American&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=_VOeQqUhTAsC&amp;pg=PA88 | page = 88 | title = Free speech, &quot;the people's darling privilege&quot;: struggles for freedom of expression in American history | first = Michael Kent | last = Curtis | publisher = Duke University Press | year = 2000 | isbn=978-0-8223-2529-1 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Brown was arrested in Andover, Massachusetts, but because he could not afford the $4,000 bail, he was taken to Salem for trial.&lt;ref name = American&gt;{{cite book | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=T1F1H2KUj80C&amp;pg=PA421 | pages = 420–21 | title = The American Counterrevolution: a Retreat from Liberty, 1783–1800 | first = Larry E. | last = Tise | publisher = Stackpole Books | year = 1998 | isbn=978-0-8117-0100-6 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Brown was tried in June 1799.&lt;ref name = Perilous/&gt;  Brown pleaded guilty, but Justice [[Samuel Chase]] asked him to name others who had assisted him.&lt;ref name = Perilous/&gt;  Brown refused, was fined $480,&lt;ref name = American/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=hfiPFq5PEH8C&amp;pg=RA1-PA55 | page = 55 | title = What Kind of Nation: Thomas Jefferson, John Marshall, and the Epic Struggle to Create a United States | first = James F. | last = Simon | publisher = Simon and Schuster | year = 2003 | isbn=978-0-684-84871-6 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and sentenced to eighteen months in prison, the most severe sentence ever imposed under the Sedition Act.&lt;ref name = Perilous/&gt;&lt;ref name = American/&gt;

==Contemporaneous reaction==
After the passage of the highly unpopular [[Alien and Sedition Acts]], protests occurred across the country,&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.google.com/books/edition/The_Alien_and_Sedition_Acts_of_1798/dX3_CwAAQBAJ?hl=en&amp;gbpv=1&amp;pg=PT104 The Alien and Sedition Acts of 1798]&lt;/ref&gt; with some of the largest being seen in Kentucky, where the crowds were so large they filled the streets and the entire town square.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.google.com/books/edition/The_Citizenship_Revolution/IbqTcM4rrR8C?hl=en&amp;gbpv=1&amp;pg=PA168 The Citizenship Revolution - Politics and the Creation of the American Union, 1774-1804]&lt;/ref&gt;  Noting the outrage among the populace, the Democratic-Republicans made the Alien and Sedition Acts an important issue in the [[1800 United States presidential election|1800 election]] campaign. Upon assuming the Presidency, Thomas Jefferson pardoned those still serving sentences under the Sedition Act,{{r|miller|page1=231}} and Congress soon repaid their fines.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.law.cornell.edu/supct/html/historics/USSC_CR_0376_0254_ZO.html Full opinion, ''New York Times v. Sullivan'']&lt;/ref&gt; It has been said that the Alien Acts were aimed at [[Albert Gallatin]], and the Sedition Act aimed at Benjamin Bache's ''Aurora''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://archive.lewrockwell.com/woods/woods33.html |title=What States Rights Really Mean |first=Thomas E. |last=Woods, Jr. |publisher=LewRockwell.com|date=2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; {{Better source|date=October 2018}} While government authorities prepared lists of aliens for deportation, many aliens fled the country during the debate over the Alien and Sedition Acts, and Adams never signed a deportation order.{{r|miller|page1=187–93}}

The Virginia and Kentucky state legislatures also passed the [[Kentucky and Virginia Resolutions]] denouncing the federal legislation, secretly authored by [[Thomas Jefferson]] and [[James Madison]].  &lt;ref&gt;[[s:Portal:Kentucky and Virginia Resolutions|Portal:Kentucky and Virginia Resolutions]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Wikisource:Virginia Resolutions of 1798]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,994570-2,00.html
|title=Thomas Jefferson: The Patriot Act of the 18th Century
|date=Jul 5, 2004
| work=Time
|first=Ishmael
|last=Reed
}}&lt;/ref&gt; While the eventual resolutions followed Madison in advocating &quot;[[interposition]]&quot;, Jefferson's initial draft would have [[Nullification (U.S. Constitution)|nullified]] the Acts and even threatened [[Secession in the United States|secession]].&lt;ref&gt;Jefferson's draft said: &quot;where powers are assumed [by the federal government] which have not been delegated, a nullification of the act is the rightful remedy: that every State has a natural right in cases not within the compact, (casus non fœderis) to nullify of their own authority all assumptions of power by others within their limits.&quot; See [http://www.constitution.org/cons/kent1798.htm Jefferson's draft of the Kentucky Resolutions of 1798].&lt;/ref&gt; Jefferson's biographer [[Dumas Malone]] argued that this might have gotten Jefferson impeached for treason, had his actions become known at the time.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chernow&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Chernow|first1=Ron|authorlink1=Ron Chernow|title=Alexander Hamilton|date=2004|publisher=Penguin Press|location=New York|isbn=9781594200090|pages=[https://archive.org/details/alexanderhamilto00cher/page/586 586–87]|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/alexanderhamilto00cher/page/586}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In writing the Kentucky Resolutions, Jefferson warned that, &quot;unless arrested at the threshold&quot;, the Alien and Sedition Acts would &quot;necessarily drive these states into revolution and blood&quot;.

The Alien and Sedition Acts were never appealed to the [[Supreme Court of the United States|Supreme Court]], whose power of [[Judicial review (law)|judicial review]] was not clearly established until ''[[Marbury v. Madison]]'' in 1803. Subsequent mentions in Supreme Court opinions beginning in the mid-20th century have assumed that the Sedition Act would today be found unconstitutional.&lt;ref&gt;In the seminal free speech case of ''[[New York Times Co. v. Sullivan]]'', the Court declared, &quot;Although the Sedition Act was never tested in this Court, the attack upon its validity has carried the day in the court of history.&quot; 376 U.S. 254, 276 (1964). In a [[concurring opinion]] in ''Watts v. United States'', which involved an alleged threat against President [[Lyndon Johnson]], [[William O. Douglas]] noted, &quot;The Alien and Sedition Laws constituted one of our sorriest chapters; and I had thought we had done with them forever… Suppression of speech as an effective police measure is an old, old device, outlawed by our Constitution.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=Watts v. United States, 394 U.S. 705|url=http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/scripts/getcase.pl?court=us&amp;vol=394&amp;invol=705}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== The Alien Enemies Act in the 20th and 21st centuries ==
{{refimprove section|date=July 2018}}
The Alien Enemies Acts remained in effect at the outset of [[World War I]] and remains U.S. law today.&lt;ref name=AEAPP/&gt; It was recodified to be part of the US war and national defense statutes (50 USC 21–24).&lt;ref name=AEAPP&gt;{{cite web|title=Alien Enemies Act and Related World War II Presidential Proclamations|url=http://gaic.info/history/related-laws/|website=German American Internee Coalition}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On December 7, 1941, responding to the [[bombing of Pearl Harbor]], [[President Franklin Delano Roosevelt]] used the authority of the revised Alien Enemies Act to issue [[presidential proclamation]]s 2525 (Alien Enemies – Japanese), 2526 (Alien Enemies – German), and 2527 (Alien Enemies – Italian), to apprehend, restrain, secure and remove Japanese, German, and Italian non-citizens.&lt;ref name=&quot;AEAPP&quot;/&gt; On February 19, 1942, citing authority of the wartime powers of the president and commander in chief, Roosevelt made [[Executive Order 9066]], authorizing the Secretary of War to prescribe military areas and giving him authority that superseded the authority of other executives under Proclamations 2525-7. EO 9066 led to the [[internment of Japanese Americans]], whereby over 110,000 people of Japanese ancestry living on the Pacific coast were forcibly relocated and forced to live in camps in the interior of the country, 62% of whom were [[United States citizen]]s, not aliens.&lt;ref&gt;''Semiannual Report of the War Relocation Authority, for the period January 1 to June 30, 1946'', not dated. Papers of [[Dillon S. Myer]]. [http://www.trumanlibrary.org/whistlestop/study_collections/japanese_internment/documents/index.php?pagenumber=4&amp;documentid=62&amp;documentdate=1946-00-00&amp;collectionid=JI&amp;nav=ok Scanned image at] trumanlibrary.org. Retrieved September 18, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=trumanlib_1948&gt;&quot;The War Relocation Authority and The Incarceration of Japanese Americans During World War II: 1948 Chronology&quot;, [http://www.trumanlibrary.org/whistlestop/study_collections/japanese_internment/1948.htm Web page] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20151105103017/http://www.trumanlibrary.org/whistlestop/study_collections/japanese_internment/1948.htm |date=2015-11-05 }} at www.trumanlibrary.org. Retrieved September 11, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

Hostilities with Germany and Italy ended in May 1945, and with Japan in August. Alien enemies, and U.S. citizens, continued to be interned. On July 14, 1945, President [[Harry S. Truman]] issued Presidential Proclamation 2655, titled &quot;Removal of Alien Enemies&quot;. The proclamation gave the [[United States Attorney General|Attorney General]] authority regarding aliens enemies within the [[continental United States]], to decide whether they are &quot;dangerous to the public peace and safety of the United States&quot;, to order them removed, and to create regulations governing their removal. The proclamation cited the revised Alien Enemies Act (50 U.S.C. 21–24) as to powers of the President to make public proclamation regarding &quot;subjects of the hostile nation&quot; more than fourteen years old and living inside the United States but not naturalized, to remove them as alien enemies, and to determine the means of removal.

On September 8, 1945, Truman issued Presidential Proclamation 2662, titled &quot;Removal of Alien Enemies&quot;. The revised Alien Enemies Act (50 U.S.C. 21–24) was cited as to removal of alien enemies in the interest of the public safety. The United States had agreed, at a conference in Rio de Janeiro in 1942, to assume responsibility for the restraint and repatriation of dangerous alien enemies to be sent to the United States from Latin American republics. In another inter-American conference in Mexico City on March 8, 1945, North and South American governments resolved to recommended adoption of measures to prevent aliens of hostile nations who were deemed to be security threats or threats to welfare from remaining in North or South America. Truman gave authority to the Secretary of State to determine if alien enemies in the United States who were sent to the United States from Latin America, or who were in the United States illegally, endangered the welfare or security of the country. The Secretary of State was given power to remove them &quot;to destinations outside the limits of the Western Hemisphere&quot;, to the former enemy territory of the governments to whose &quot;principles of which (the alien enemies) have adhered&quot;. The Department of Justice was directed to assist the Secretary of State in their prompt removal.

On April 10, 1946, Truman issued Presidential Proclamation 2685, titled &quot;Removal of Alien Enemies&quot;, citing the revised Alien Enemies Act (50 U.S.C. 21–24) as to its provision for the &quot;removal from the United States of alien enemies in the interest of the public safety&quot;. Truman proclaimed regulations that were in addition to and supplemented other &quot;regulations affecting the restraint and removal of alien enemies&quot;. As to alien enemies who had been brought into the [[continental United States]] from Latin America after December 1941, the proclamation gave the Secretary of State authority to decide if their presence was &quot;prejudicial to the future security or welfare of the Americas&quot;, and to make regulations for their removal. 30 days was set as the reasonable time for them to &quot;effect the recovery, disposal, and removal of (their) goods and effects, and for (their) departure&quot;.

In 1947 New York's [[Ellis Island]] continued to incarcerate hundreds of ethnic Germans. Fort Lincoln was a large internment camp still holding internees in [[North Dakota]]. North Dakota was represented by controversial Senator [[William Langer|William &quot;Wild Bill&quot; Langer]]. Langer introduced a bill (S. 1749) &quot;for the relief of all persons detained as enemy aliens&quot;, and directing the US Attorney General to cancel &quot;outstanding warrants of arrest, removal, or deportation&quot; for many German aliens still interned, listing many by name, and all of those detained by the [[Immigration and Naturalization Service]] (INS), which was under the Department of Justice (DOJ). It directed the INS not to issue any more warrants or orders, if their only basis was the original warrants of arrest. The bill never passed. The Attorney General gave up [[plenary power|plenary]] jurisdiction over the last internee on Ellis Island late in 1948.

In Ludecke v. Watkins (1948), the Supreme Court interpreted the time of release under the Alien Enemies Act. German alien Kurt G. W. Ludecke was detained in 1941, under Proclamation 2526. and continued to be held after cessation of hostilities. In 1947, Ludecke petitioned for a [[writ of habeas corpus]] to order his release, after the Attorney General ordered him deported. The court ruled 5–4 to release Ludecke, but also found that the Alien Enemies Act allowed for detainment beyond the time hostilities ceased, until an actual treaty was signed with the hostile nation or government.

In 1988, President Reagan and the 100th Congress introduced the Civil Liberties Act of 1988, whose purpose amongst others was to acknowledge and apologize for actions of the US against individuals of Japanese ancestry during World War II.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.gpo.gov/fdsys/pkg/STATUTE-102/pdf/STATUTE-102-Pg903.pdf Civil Liberties Act of 1988, GPO Public Law 100-383, 1988]&lt;/ref&gt; The statement from Congress agreed with the Commission on Wartime Relocation and Internment of Civilians, that &quot;a grave injustice was done to both citizens and permanent resident aliens of Japanese ... without adequate security reasons and without any acts of espionage or sabotage documented by the Commission, and were motivated largely by racial prejudice, wartime hysteria, and a failure of political leadership&quot;.

In 2015, presidential candidate [[Donald Trump]] made a proposal to ban foreign [[Muslims]] from entering the United States (as part of the [[War on Terror]]); Roosevelt's application of the Alien Enemies Act was cited as a possible justification. The proposal created international controversy, drawing criticism from foreign heads of state that have historically remained uninvolved in United States presidential elections.&lt;ref name=DCCDT&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-politics-35037553|title=David Cameron criticises Donald Trump 'Muslim ban' call|work=BBC News}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=PRMRT&gt;{{cite news |title=Priebus, Ryan and McConnell Rip Trump Anti-Muslim Proposal |first1=Deirdre |last1=Walsh |first2=Jeremy |last2=Diamond |first3=Ted |last3=Barrett |work=CNN |date=December 8, 2015 |url=http://www.cnn.com/2015/12/08/politics/paul-ryan-trump-comments-not-who-we-are-as-a-party/}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/world/the-world-reacts-to-trumps-proposed-ban-on-muslims-entering-us/2015/12/08/50eea1dc-9d4a-11e5-9ad2-568d814bbf3b_story.html|title=The world reacts to Trump's proposed ban on Muslims entering the U.S.|author=Annie Gowen|date=December 8, 2015|work=Washington Post}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Trump calls for 'shutdown' of Muslims entering US |first=Ben |last=Kamisar |work=The Hill |date=December 7, 2015 |url=http://thehill.com/blogs/ballot-box/presidential-races/262348-trump-calls-for-shutdown-of-muslims-entering-us}}&lt;/ref&gt; A former [[Reagan Administration]] aide noted that, despite criticism of Trump's proposal to invoke the law, &quot;the Alien Enemies Act ... is still on the books ... (and people) in Congress for many decades (haven't) repealed the law ... (nor has) [[Barack Obama]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Reagan Aide: Trump's Critics Are the Real Xenophobes |first=Andrew |last=Kirell |work=The Daily Beast |date=December 8, 2015 |url=http://www.thedailybeast.com/videos/2015/12/08/trump-backer-critics-the-real-racists.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other critics claimed that the proposal violated founding principles, and was unconstitutional for singling out a religion, and not a hostile nation. They included the [[United States Department of Defense|Pentagon]] and others, who argued that the proposal (and its citation of the Alien Enemies proclamations as authority) played into the [[ISIL]] narrative that the United States was at war with the entire Muslim religion (not just with ISIL and other [[terrorist]] entities).&lt;ref name=BBC8Dec&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.bbc.com/news/world-us-canada-35047105|title=Trump's Muslim ban call 'endangers US security'|date=December 8, 2015|accessdate=December 8, 2015|work=BBC}}&lt;/ref&gt; On June 26, 2018, in the 5–4 decision ''[[Trump v. Hawaii]]'', the U.S. Supreme Court upheld [[Executive_Order_13780#Presidential_Proclamation_9645|Presidential Proclamation 9645]], the third version of President Trump's [[Trump travel ban|travel ban]], with the majority opinion being written by Chief Justice John Roberts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Trump's Travel Ban Is Upheld by Supreme Court|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2018/06/26/us/politics/supreme-court-trump-travel-ban.html|publisher=nytimes.com|work=Adam Liptak and Michael D. Shear|date=26 June 2018|accessdate=26 June 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Alien Act of 1705]] in Great Britain
* [[Seditious Meetings Act 1795]] in Great Britain
* [[Civil Liberties Act of 1988]]
* [[Espionage Act of 1917]]
* [[Logan Act]] of 1799
* [[Nullification Crisis]]
* [[Sedition Act of 1918]]
* [[Smith Act|Alien Registration Act]] of 1940
* [[USA PATRIOT Act]] of 2001
* [[Violent Radicalization and Homegrown Terrorism Prevention Act of 2007]]
* [[State Secrecy Law]] of 2013 in Japan

== Notes ==
{{Reflist|group=&quot;nb&quot;}}
== Footnotes ==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
* Berkin, Carol. ''A Sovereign People: The Crises of the 1790s and the Birth of American Nationalism'' (2017) pp 201–44.
* {{cite journal|last1=Berns|first1=Walter|title=Freedom of the Press and the Alien and Sedition Laws: A Reappraisal|journal=Supreme Court Review|volume=1970|date=1970|pages=109–159|jstor=3108724|doi=10.1086/scr.1970.3108724}}
* Bird, Wendell (2016). ''Press and Speech Under Assault: The Early Supreme Court Justices, the Sedition Act of 1798, and the Campaign Against Dissent.'' New York: Oxford University Press.
* {{cite book|last1=Elkins |first1=Stanley M. |first2=Eric |last2=McKitrick |title=The Age of Federalism|date=1995}}
* {{cite journal|last=Jenkins |first=David |title=The Sedition Act of 1798 and the Incorporation of Seditious Libel into First Amendment Jurisprudence |journal=The American Journal of Legal History |volume=45 |issue=2 |date=April 2001| pages=154–213|jstor=3185366|doi=10.2307/3185366 }}
* {{cite journal|last=Martin |first=James P. |title=When Repression Is Democratic and Constitutional: The Federalist Theory of Representation and the Sedition Act of 1798 |journal=University of Chicago Law Review |volume=66 |issue=1 |date=Winter 1999 |pages=117–182|jstor=1600387|doi=10.2307/1600387 |url=https://chicagounbound.uchicago.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4992&amp;context=uclrev }}
* {{cite book |last=Miller |first=John Chester |title=Crisis in Freedom: The Alien and Sedition Acts |url=https://archive.org/details/crisisinfreedoma0000mill |url-access=registration |location=New York |publisher=Little Brown and Company |date=1951}}
* {{cite book |last=Rehnquist |first=William H. |title=Grand Inquests: The Historic Impeachments of Justice Samuel Chase and President Andrew Johnson |date=1994}} Chase was impeached and acquitted for his conduct of a trial under the Sedition act.
* {{cite book|last=Rosenfeld |first=Richard N. |title=American Aurora: A Democratic-Republican Returns: The Suppressed History of Our Nation's Beginnings and the Heroic Newspaper That Tried to Report It |url=https://archive.org/details/americanaurorade00rose |url-access=registration |location=New York |publisher=St. Martin's Press |date=1997}}
* {{cite book |last=Smith |first=James Morton |title=Freedom's Fetters: The Alien and Sedition Laws and American Civil Liberties |url=https://archive.org/details/freedomsfettersa00smit |url-access=registration |date=1956|publisher=Cornell University Press|location=Ithaca NY}}
* {{cite book|last=Stone |first=Geoffrey R. |title=Perilous Times: Free Speech in Wartime from The Sedition Act of 1798 to the War on Terrorism |url=https://archive.org/details/periloustimesfre00ston |url-access=registration |date=2004}}
* {{cite book|first=Alan |last=Taylor |chapter=The Alien and Sedition Acts |editor-first=Julian E. |editor-last=Zelizer |title=The American Congress |chapter-url=https://archive.org/details/americancongress00juli |chapter-url-access=registration |date=2004 |pages=[https://archive.org/details/americancongress00juli/page/63 63–76]}}
* {{cite journal|last=Wright |first=Barry |title=Migration, Radicalism, and State Security: Legislative Initiatives in the Canada and the United States c. 1794–1804 |journal=Studies in American Political Development |volume=16 |issue=1 |date=April 2002 |pages=48–60|doi=10.1017/S0898588X02000032}}

===Primary sources===
* Randolph, J.W. ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=zuc9AAAAIAAJ The Virginia Report of 1799–1800, Touching the Alien and Sedition Laws]; together with the Virginia Resolutions of December 21, 1798, the Debate and Proceedings thereon in the House of Delegates of Virginia, and several other documents illustrative of the report and resolutions''

==External links==
{{Wikisource}}
* [[s:Alien and Sedition Acts|Full Text of Alien and Sedition Acts]]
* [https://www.loc.gov/rr/program/bib/ourdocs/Alien.html Alien and Sedition Acts and Related Resources from the Library of Congress]
* [http://web.csulb.edu/~jlawler/Course%20DW/NaturalizationAct_1798.htm Naturalization Act, 1798]
* [http://www.ourdocuments.gov/doc.php?flash=true&amp;doc=16&amp;page=transcript#no-1 Alien Friends Act, Alien Enemies Act, Sedition Act, 1798]
* [https://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/text/50/21 50 U.S. Code § 21 – Restraint, regulation, 1918]
* [http://www.foitimes.com/internment/Proc2525.html Presidential Proclamation 2525, Alien Enemies—Japanese, December 07, 1941]
* [http://www.foitimes.com/internment/Proc2526.html Presidential Proclamation 2526, Alien Enemies—German, December 07, 1941]
* [http://www.foitimes.com/internment/Proc2527.html Presidential Proclamation 2527, Alien Enemies—Italians, December 07, 1941]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20151222163513/http://www.gaic.info/ShowPage.php?section=History&amp;page=Ex_Order_9066 Executive Order 9066 Authorizing the Secretary of War to Prescribe Military Areas, February 19, 1942]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20151222101732/http://www.gaic.info/ShowPage.php?section=History&amp;page=Proc_2655 Presidential Proclamation 2655—Removal of Alien Enemies, July 14, 1945]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20151222163101/http://www.gaic.info/ShowPage.php?section=History&amp;page=Proc_2662 Presidential Proclamation 2662—Removal of Alien Enemies, September 8, 1945]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20151222155625/http://www.gaic.info/ShowPage.php?section=History&amp;page=Proc_2685 Presidential Proclamation 2685—Removal of Alien Enemies, April 10, 1946]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20160316190605/http://gaic.info/converted/LangerS1749.html Langer Bill, S. 1749, 1947]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20160316190543/http://gaic.info/docs/Ludecke%20v.%20Watkins.htm Ludecke v. Watkins, 335 U.S. 160 (1948)]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20160101173339/https://www.donaldjtrump.com/press-releases/donald-j.-trump-statement-on-preventing-muslim-immigration Press Release—&quot;Donald J. Trump Statement on Preventing Muslim Immigration&quot;, December 07, 2015]

{{US history}}
{{John Adams}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Alien And Sedition Acts}}
[[Category:Alien and Sedition Acts| ]]
[[Category:1798 in American law]]
[[Category:5th United States Congress]]
[[Category:History of the United States (1789–1849)]]
[[Category:Internment of Japanese Americans]]
[[Category:Political repression in the United States]]
[[Category:Presidency of John Adams]]
[[Category:Sedition|Alien and Sedition Acts of 1798]]
[[Category:United States federal immigration and nationality legislation]]</text>
      <sha1>ootj9ohwl5jhkku1y739wwgnummw29y</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
