  <page>
    <title>E. E. Cummings</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9591</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943055436</id>
      <parentid>943055358</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-28T15:19:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>TheFrog001</username>
        <id>17952751</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contributions/99.203.37.188|99.203.37.188]] ([[User talk:99.203.37.188|talk]]) ([[WP:HG|HG]]) (3.4.9)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{distinguish|Elijah Cummings}}
{{short description|American poet, painter, essayist, author, and playwright}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=June 2018}}
{{Infobox person
| name             = E.&amp;nbsp;E. Cummings
| image            = E. E. Cummings NYWTS.jpg
| alt              = A black-and-white photo of Cummings standing in profile
| caption          = Cummings in 1953
| birth_name       = Edward Estlin Cummings
| birth_date       = {{Birth date|mf=yes|1894|10|14}}
| birth_place      = [[Cambridge, Massachusetts]], U.S.
| death_date       = {{Death date and age|mf=yes|1962|9|3|1894|10|14}}
| death_place      = [[Madison, New Hampshire]], U.S.
| alma_mater       = [[Harvard University]]
| occupation       = Author
| signature        = EE Cummings signature.svg
}}
'''Edward Estlin''' &quot;'''E.&amp;nbsp;E.'''&quot; '''Cummings''' (October 14, 1894&amp;nbsp;– September 3, 1962), often styled as '''e&amp;nbsp;e&amp;nbsp;cummings''', as he is attributed in many of his published works,&lt;ref name=&quot;chicago84&quot;/&gt; was an American poet, painter, essayist, author, and playwright. He wrote approximately 2,900 poems, two autobiographical novels, four plays, and several essays. He is often regarded as one of the most important American poets of the 20th century.
Cummings is associated with [[Modernist literature|modernist]] [[free verse|free-form poetry]]. Much of his work has idiosyncratic syntax and uses lower case spellings for poetic expression. His use of lower case extended to rendering even the personal pronoun ''I'' as ''i'', as in the phrase &quot;i shall go.”

==Life==

===Early years===
Edward Estlin Cummings was born on October 14, 1894 in [[Cambridge, Massachusetts]] to Edward Cummings and the former Rebecca Haswell Clarke, a well-known [[Unitarianism|Unitarian]] couple in the city. His father was a professor at Harvard University who later became nationally known as the minister of South Congregational Church (Unitarian) in Boston, Massachusetts.&lt;ref&gt;Collins, Leo W. ''This is Our Church''. Boston, Massachusetts: Society of the First Church in Boston, 2005: 104.&lt;/ref&gt; His mother, who loved to spend time with her children, played games with Cummings and his sister, Elizabeth. From an early age, Cummings' parents supported his creative gifts.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.english.illinois.edu/maps/poets/a_f/cummings/cummings_life.htm|title=E. E. Cummings' Life|website=english.illinois.edu|access-date=27 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cummings wrote poems and drew as a child, and he often played outdoors with the many other children who lived in his neighborhood. He grew up in the company of such family friends as the philosophers [[William James]] and [[Josiah Royce]]. Many of Cummings' summers were spent on [[Silver Lake (Madison, New Hampshire)|Silver Lake]] in [[Madison, New Hampshire]], where his father had built two houses along the eastern shore. The family ultimately purchased the nearby [[Joy Farm]] where Cummings had his primary summer residence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=wpkDRPueLiMC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=gbs_atb#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|title=E.E. Cummings: A Biography|first=Christopher|last=Sawyer-Lauçanno|date=January 1, 2004|publisher=Sourcebooks, Inc.|via=Google Books}}&lt;/ref&gt;

He expressed [[transcendentalism|transcendental]] leanings his entire life. As he matured, Cummings moved to an [[I and Thou|&quot;I, Thou&quot;]] relationship with God. His journals are replete with references to ''&quot;le bon Dieu&quot;'', as well as prayers for inspiration in his poetry and artwork (such as &quot;Bon Dieu! may i some day do something truly great. amen.&quot;). Cummings &quot;also prayed for strength to be his essential self ('may I be I is the only prayer—not may I be great or good or beautiful or wise or strong'), and for relief of spirit in times of depression ('almighty God! I thank thee for my soul; &amp; may I never die spiritually into a mere mind through disease of loneliness').&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.harvardsquarelibrary.org/unitarians/cummings.html |title=E. E. Cummings: Poet And Painter |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20060902151619/http://www.harvardsquarelibrary.org/unitarians/cummings.html |archivedate=September 2, 2006 |df=mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Cummings wanted to be a poet from childhood and wrote poetry daily from age 8 to 22, exploring assorted forms. He graduated from [[Harvard University]] with a [[Bachelor of Arts]] degree ''[[magna cum laude]]'' and [[Phi Beta Kappa]] in 1915 and received a [[Master of Arts]] degree from the university in 1916.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.notablebiographies.com/Co-Da/Cummings-E-E.html |title=E. E. Cummings Biography – life, family, children, story, death, wife, mother, book, old, information, born |publisher=Notablebiographies.com |date=September 3, 1962 |accessdate=24 December 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; In his studies at Harvard, he developed an interest in modern poetry, which ignored conventional grammar and syntax, while aiming for a dynamic use of language. Upon graduating, he worked for a book dealer.&lt;ref Name=&quot;PoetryF&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.poetryfoundation.org/bio/e-e-cummings|title=E. E. Cummings|date=November 21, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Harvard Monthly vol 56.jpg|thumb|right|Masthead from volume 56 of ''[[The Harvard Monthly]]''; Cummings was an editor and contributor to this literary journal while at Harvard]]

===War years===
In 1917, with the First World War ongoing in Europe, Cummings enlisted in the [[AFS Intercultural Programs#WWI|Norton-Harjes Ambulance Corps]]. On the boat to France, he met [[William Slater Brown]] and they would become friends. Due to an administrative error, Cummings and Brown did not receive an assignment five weeks, a period they spent exploring Paris. Cummings fell in love with the city, to which he would return throughout his life.&lt;ref name=utexas&gt;{{cite web|url=http://research.hrc.utexas.edu:8080/hrcxtf/view?docId=ead/00030.xml|title=E. E. Cummings: An Inventory of His Collection at the Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center|publisher=Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center |accessdate=May 9, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During their service in the ambulance corps, the two young writers sent letters home that drew the attention of the military censors. They were known to prefer the company of French soldiers over fellow ambulance drivers. The two openly expressed anti-war views; Cummings spoke of his lack of hatred for the Germans.&lt;ref&gt;Friedman, Norman &quot;Cummings, E[dward] E[stlin]&quot;, in Steven Serafin, ''The Continuum Encyclopedia of American Literature'', 2003, Continuum, p. 244.&lt;/ref&gt; On September 21, 1917, five months after starting his belated assignment, Cummings and William Slater Brown were arrested by the French military on suspicion of espionage and undesirable activities. They were held for three and a half months in a military detention camp at the ''[[La Ferté-Macé|Dépôt de Triage]]'', in [[La Ferté-Macé]], Orne, Normandy.&lt;ref name=utexas/&gt;

They were imprisoned with other detainees in a large room. Cummings' father failed to obtain his son's release through diplomatic channels, and in December 1917 he wrote a letter to President [[Woodrow Wilson]]. Cummings was released on December 19, 1917, and Brown was released two months later. Cummings used his prison experience as the basis for his novel, ''[[The Enormous Room]]'' (1922), about which [[F. Scott Fitzgerald]] said, &quot;Of all the work by young men who have sprung up since 1920 one book survives—''The Enormous Room'' by e e cummings... Those few who cause books to live have not been able to endure the thought of its mortality.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Bloom, p. 1814.&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;!-- Did F Scott Fitzgerald use upper- or lower-case for Cummings' name?  In a direct quote, it matters. --&gt;

Cummings returned to the United States on New Year's Day 1918. Later in 1918 he was drafted into the army. He served in the [[12th Division (United States)|12th Division]] at [[Camp Devens|Camp Devens, Massachusetts]], until November 1918.&lt;ref&gt;Kennedy, p. 186.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://freepages.military.rootsweb.ancestry.com/~worldwarone/WWI/divisions.html#Twelfth|title=Data on U.S. Army Divisions during World War I, WWI, The Great War}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Quote box |width=300px |align=right ||salign=right
 |quote  =&lt;poem&gt;
Buffalo Bill's
defunct
        who used to
        ride a watersmooth-silver
                                  stallion
and break onetwothreefourfive pigeonsjustlikethat
                                                  Jesus

he was a handsome man
                      and what i want to know is
how do you like your blueeyed boy
Mister Death
&lt;/poem&gt;
 |source =&quot;Buffalo Bill's&quot; (1920)}}

===Post-war years===
Cummings returned to Paris in 1921 and lived there for two years before returning to New York. His collection ''Tulips and Chimneys'' was published in 1923 and his inventive use of grammar and syntax is evident. The book was heavily cut by his editor. ''XLI Poems'' was published in 1925. With these collections, Cummings made his reputation as an avant garde poet.&lt;ref Name=&quot;PoetryF&quot;/&gt;

During the rest of the 1920s and 1930s, Cummings returned to Paris a number of times, and traveled throughout Europe, meeting, among others, artist [[Pablo Picasso]]. In 1931 Cummings traveled to the [[Soviet Union]], recounting his experiences in ''[[Eimi (book)|Eimi]]'', published two years later. During these years Cummings also traveled to Northern Africa and [[Mexico]]. He worked as an essayist and portrait artist for ''[[Vanity Fair (magazine)|Vanity Fair]]'' magazine (1924–1927).

In 1926, Cummings' parents were in a car crash; only his mother survived, although she was severely injured. Cummings later described the crash in the following passage from his ''i: six nonlectures'' series given at Harvard (as part of the [[Charles Eliot Norton Lectures]]) in 1952 and 1953:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
A locomotive cut the car in half, killing my father instantly. When two brakemen jumped from the halted train, they saw a woman standing – dazed but erect – beside a mangled machine; with blood spouting (as the older said to me) out of her head. One of her hands (the younger added) kept feeling her dress, as if trying to discover why it was wet. These men took my sixty-six-year old mother by the arms and tried to lead her toward a nearby farmhouse; but she threw them off, strode straight to my father's body, and directed a group of scared spectators to cover him. When this had been done (and only then) she let them lead her away.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

His father's death had a profound effect on Cummings, who entered a new period in his artistic life. He began to focus on more important aspects of life in his poetry. He started this new period by paying homage to his father in the poem &quot;my father moved through dooms of love&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.cs.berkeley.edu/~richie/poetry/html/aupoem114.html |title=My father moved through dooms of love |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20050315070117/http://www.cs.berkeley.edu/~richie/poetry/html/aupoem114.html |archivedate=March 15, 2005 |df=mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | first = Gary | last = Lane | authorlink =  | year = 1976 | title = I Am: A Study of E. E. Cummings' Poems | url = https://archive.org/details/iamstudyofeecumm0000lane | url-access = registration | location = [[Lawrence, Kansas]] | publisher=University Press of Kansas | isbn = 0-7006-0144-9 | pages = [https://archive.org/details/iamstudyofeecumm0000lane/page/41 41–43]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 1930s Samuel Aiwaz Jacobs was Cummings' publisher; he had started the Golden Eagle Press after working as a typographer and publisher.

===Final years===
[[File:EECummingsGrave.jpg|thumb|right|Grave of E. E. Cummings]]

In 1952, his alma mater, [[Harvard University]], awarded Cummings an honorary seat as a guest professor. The [[Charles Eliot Norton Lectures]] he gave in 1952 and 1955 were later collected as ''i: six nonlectures''.
{{Quote box |width=300px |align=left ||salign=right
 |quote  =&lt;poem&gt;
i thank You God for most this amazing
day:for the leaping greenly spirits of trees
and a blue true dream of sky; and for everything
which is natural which is infinite which is yes 
&lt;/poem&gt;
 |source =From &quot;i thank You God for most this amazing&quot; (1950)}}

Cummings spent the last decade of his life traveling, fulfilling speaking engagements, and spending time at his summer home, [[Joy Farm]], in [[Silver Lake, New Hampshire]]. He died of a stroke on September 3, 1962, at the age of 67 at Memorial Hospital in [[North Conway, New Hampshire]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1962/09/04/archives/ee-cummings-dies-of-stroke-poet-stood-for-stylistic-liberty-unusual.html|url-access=subscription|title=E.&amp;nbsp;E. Cummings Dies of Stroke. Poet Stood for Stylistic Liberty|date=September 4, 1962|work=The New York Times}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cummings was buried at Forest Hills Cemetery in Boston, Massachusetts. At the time of his death, Cummings was recognized as the second most read poet in the United States, behind [[Robert Frost]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.poets.org/poetsorg/poet/e-e-cummings|title=E. E. Cummings|last=Cummings|first=E. E.|date=February 4, 2014|website=E. E. Cummings|access-date=25 May 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Cummings' papers are held at the [[Houghton Library]] at [[Harvard University]] and the [[Harry Ransom Center]] at the [[University of Texas at Austin]].&lt;ref name=utexas/&gt;

==Personal life==

===Marriages===
[[File:EECummings pd4.jpg|thumb|upright|Sketched self-portrait circa 1920]]
Cummings was married briefly twice, first to Elaine Orr, then to Anne Minnerly Barton. His longest relationship lasted more than three decades, a [[common-law marriage]] to Marion Morehouse.

Cummings' first marriage, to Elaine Orr, began as a love affair in 1918 while she was still married to [[Scofield Thayer]], one of Cummings' friends from Harvard. During this time he wrote a good deal of his erotic poetry.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kennedy&quot;&gt;''Selected Poems,'' Ed. Richard S. Kennedy, Liveright, 1994.&lt;/ref&gt; After divorcing Thayer, Orr married Cummings on March 19, 1924. The couple had a daughter together out of wedlock. However, the couple separated after two months of marriage and divorced less than nine months later.

Cummings married his second wife Anne Minnerly Barton on May 1, 1929, and they separated three years later in 1932. That same year, Minnerly obtained a [[Mexican divorce]]; it was not officially recognized in the United States until August 1934. Anne died in 1970 aged 72.

In 1934, after his separation from his second wife, Cummings met Marion Morehouse, a fashion model and photographer. Although it is not clear whether the two were ever formally married, Morehouse lived with Cummings in a common-law marriage until his death in 1962. She died on May 18, 1969,&lt;ref&gt;''Marion Morehouse Cummings, Poet's Widow, Top Model, Dies'', ''[[The New York Times]]'', May 19, 1969.&lt;/ref&gt; while living at 4 [[Patchin Place]], [[Greenwich Village]], New York City, where Cummings had resided since September 1924.&lt;ref&gt;Sawyer-Lauçanno, p. 255.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Political views===
According to his testimony in ''[[Eimi (book)|EIMI]]'', Cummings had little interest in politics until his trip to the Soviet Union in 1931.&lt;ref name=Blumenkranz&gt;Carla Blumenkranz, [http://www.poetryfoundation.org/article/180437 &quot;The Enormous Poem: When E.E. Cummings Repunctuated Stalinism.&quot;] Poetry Foundation. www.poetryfoundation.org/&lt;/ref&gt; He subsequently shifted rightward on many political and social issues.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://college.cengage.com/english/lauter/heath/4e/students/author_pages/modern/cummings_ee.html|title=Heath Anthology of American Literature E.E. cummings – Author Page}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite his radical and [[Bohemianism|bohemian]] public image, he was a [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican]], and later, an ardent supporter of [[Joseph McCarthy]].&lt;ref&gt;Wetzsteon, Ross. 'Republic of Dreams: Greenwich Village: The American Bohemia, 1910–1960', pp. 449 [https://books.google.com/books?id=o2DB77ccf9sC&amp;pg=PA449 Google Books]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Work==

===Poetry===
Despite Cummings' familiarity with [[avant-garde]] styles (likely affected by the ''[[Calligrammes]]'' of French poet [[Apollinaire]], according to a contemporary observation&lt;ref&gt;Taupin, Rene, ''The Influence of French Symbolism on Modern American Poetry 1927'' (Trans. William Pratt), AMS Inc, New York 1985  {{ISBN|0404615791}}&lt;/ref&gt;), much of his work is quite traditional. Many of his poems are [[sonnet]]s, albeit often with a modern twist. He occasionally used the [[blues#Lyrics|blues]] form and [[acrostics]]. Cummings' poetry often deals with themes of love and nature, as well as the relationship of the individual to the masses and to the world. His poems are also often rife with satire.

While his poetic forms and themes share an affinity with the [[Romanticism|Romantic tradition]], Cummings' work universally shows a particular idiosyncrasy of [[syntax]], or way of arranging individual words into larger phrases and sentences. Many of his most striking poems do not involve any typographical or punctuation innovations at all, but purely syntactic ones.

&lt;!---NB **The typography is Cummings' original setting**---&gt;
{{Quote box |width=350px |align=right ||salign=right
 |quote  =&lt;poem&gt;
i carry your heart with me(i carry it in
my heart)i am never without it(anywhere
i go you go,my dear;and whatever is done
by only me is your doing,my darling)
                                            i fear
no fate(for you are my fate,my sweet)i want
no world(for beautiful you are my world,my true)
and it's you are whatever a moon has always meant
and whatever a sun will always sing is you

here is the deepest secret nobody knows
(here is the root of the root and the bud of the bud
and the sky of the sky of a tree called life;which grows
higher than soul can hope or mind can hide)
and this is the wonder that's keeping the stars apart

i carry your heart(i carry it in my heart)
&lt;/poem&gt;
 |source =From &quot;i carry your heart with me(i carry it in&quot; (1952)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.poetryfoundation.org/poem/179622 &quot;i carry your heart with me(i carry it in&quot;] at the Poetry Foundation.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

As well as being influenced by notable [[Modernist literature|modernists]], including [[Gertrude Stein]] and [[Ezra Pound]], Cummings in his early work drew upon the [[Imagism|imagist]] experiments of [[Amy Lowell]]. Later, his visits to Paris exposed him to [[Dada]] and [[Surrealism]], which he reflected in his work. He began to rely on symbolism and allegory, where he once had used simile and metaphor. In his later work, he rarely used comparisons that required objects that were not previously mentioned in the poem, choosing to use a symbol instead. Due to this, his later poetry is &quot;frequently more lucid, more moving, and more profound than his earlier.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Friedman, Norman. ''E. E. Cummings the Art of His Poetry.'' Baltimore: Johns Hopkins, 1967. p. 89.&lt;/ref&gt; Cummings also liked to incorporate imagery of nature and death into much of his poetry.

While some of his poetry is [[free verse]] (with no concern for [[rhyme]] or [[meter (poetry)|meter]]), many have a recognizable sonnet structure of 14 lines, with an intricate rhyme scheme. A number of his poems feature a typographically exuberant style, with words, parts of words, or punctuation symbols scattered across the page, often making little sense until read aloud, at which point the meaning and emotion become clear. Cummings, who was also a painter, understood the importance of presentation, and used typography to &quot;paint a picture&quot; with some of his poems.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | first = Iain | last = Landles | authorlink = Iain Landles | year = 2001 | title = An Analysis of Two Poems by E. E. Cummings | journal=SPRING, the Journal of the E. E. Cummings Society | volume = 10 | pages = 31–43 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The seeds of Cummings' unconventional style appear well established even in his earliest work. At age six, he wrote to his father:

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;small&gt;FATHER DEAR. BE, YOUR FATHER-GOOD AND GOOD,&lt;br&gt;
HE IS GOOD NOW, IT IS NOT GOOD TO SEE IT RAIN,&lt;br&gt;
FATHER DEAR IS, IT, DEAR, NO FATHER DEAR,&lt;br&gt;
LOVE, YOU DEAR,&lt;br&gt;
ESTLIN.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Selected letters of E. E. Cummings'', (1972) Edward Estlin Cummings, Frederick Wilcox Dupee, George Stade. University of Michigan p. 3 {{ISBN|978-0-233-95637-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Following his autobiographical novel, ''[[The Enormous Room]]'', Cummings' first published work was a collection of poems titled ''[[Tulips and Chimneys]]'' (1923). This work was the public's first encounter with his characteristic eccentric use of grammar and punctuation.

Some of Cummings' most famous poems do not involve much, if any, odd typography or punctuation, but still carry his unmistakable style, particularly in unusual and impressionistic word order.

{{Quote box |width=300px |align=right ||salign=right
 |quote  =&lt;poem&gt;
anyone lived in a pretty how town
(with up so floating many bells down)
spring summer autumn winter
he sang his didn't he danced his did

Women and men (both little and small)
cared for anyone not at all
they sowed their isn't they reaped their same
sun moon stars rain
&lt;/poem&gt;
 |source =From &quot;[[anyone lived in a pretty how town]]&quot; (1940)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.poetryfoundation.org/poetrymagazine/poem/11856 &quot;anyone lived in a pretty how town&quot; at the Poetry Foundation]&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Cummings' work often does not proceed in accordance with the conventional combinatorial rules that generate typical English sentences (for example, &quot;they sowed their isn't&quot;). In addition, a number of Cummings' poems feature, in part or in whole, intentional misspellings, and several incorporate phonetic spellings intended to represent particular dialects. Cummings also made use of inventive formations of compound words, as in &quot;in Just&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/images/modeng/public/Cum2Dia/CumDi580.jpg |title=in Just}}&lt;/ref&gt; which features words such as &quot;mud-luscious&quot;, &quot;puddle-wonderful&quot;, and &quot;eddieandbill.&quot; This poem is part of a sequence of poems titled ''Chansons Innocentes'';&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.poets.org/viewmedia.php/prmMID/15398 |title=''Chansons Innocentes'' |access-date=October 10, 2010 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20051227115128/http://www.poets.org/viewmedia.php/prmMID/15398 |archive-date=December 27, 2005 |url-status=dead |df=mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; it has many references comparing the &quot;balloonman&quot; to [[Pan (mythology)|Pan]], the mythical creature that is half-goat and half-man. Literary critic [[R.P. Blackmur]] has commented that this use of language is &quot;frequently unintelligible because [Cummings] disregards the historical accumulation of meaning in words in favour of merely private and personal associations.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Friedman, Norman. ''E. E. Cummings the Art of His Poetry''. Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 1967. pp. 61–62.&lt;/ref&gt;

Fellow poet [[Edna St. Vincent Millay]], in her equivocal letter recommending Cummings for the [[Guggenheim Fellowship]] he was awarded in 1934, expressed her frustration at his opaque symbolism. &quot;[I]f he prints and offers for sale poetry which he is quite content should be, after hours of sweating concentration, inexplicable from any point of view to a person as intelligent as myself, then he does so with a motive which is frivolous from the point of view of art, and should not be helped or encouraged by any serious person or group of persons... there is fine writing and powerful writing (as well as some of the most pompous nonsense I ever let slip to the floor with a wide yawn)... What I propose, then, is this: that you give Mr. Cummings enough rope. He may hang himself; or he may lasso a unicorn.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Millay to Mr. Moe of the Guggenheim Foundation, March 1934. Quoted in Milford, Nancy (2001) ''Savage Beauty: The Life of Edna St. Vincent Millay'', Doubleday: New York, NY. p370.&lt;/ref&gt;

Many of Cummings' poems are satirical and address social issues&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.poets.org/viewmedia.php/prmMID/15404 |title=&quot;why must itself up every of a park&quot; |access-date=October 10, 2010 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100813233241/http://poets.org/viewmedia.php/prmMID/15404 |archive-date=August 13, 2010 |url-status=dead |df=mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; but have an equal or even stronger bias toward romanticism: time and again his poems celebrate love, sex, and the season of rebirth.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.poets.org/viewmedia.php/prmMID/15403 |title=&quot;anyone lived in a pretty how town&quot; |access-date=October 10, 2010 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100726121247/http://www.poets.org/viewmedia.php/prmMID/15403 |archive-date=July 26, 2010 |url-status=dead |df=mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Cummings also wrote children's books and novels. A notable example of his versatility is an introduction he wrote for a collection of the comic strip ''[[Krazy Kat]]''.

===Controversy===
Cummings is known for controversial subject matter, as he wrote numerous erotic poems. He also sometimes included ethnic slurs in his writing. For instance, in his 1950 collection ''Xaipe: Seventy-One Poems'', Cummings published two poems containing words that caused outrage in some quarters.&lt;ref&gt;Friedman, Norman, and Harry Thornton Moore. ''E. E. Cummings the Growth of a Writer''. Carbondale: Southern Illinois UP, 1964. pp. 153–54.&lt;/ref&gt;

:&lt;poem&gt;
:one day a nigger
:caught in his hand
:a little star no bigger
:than not to understand

:i'll never let you go
:until you've made me white&quot;
:so she did and now
:stars shine at night.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cummings, 1950&quot;&gt;Cummings, ''Xaipe, Seventy-one Poems''. New York: Oxford UP, 1950.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/poem&gt;

and

&lt;poem&gt;
:a kike is the most dangerous
:machine as yet invented
:by even  yankee ingenu
:ity(out of a jew a few
:dead dollars and some twisted laws)
:it comes both prigged and canted&lt;ref name=&quot;Cummings, 1950&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/poem&gt;

Cummings biographer Catherine Reef notes of the controversy:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Friends begged Cummings to reconsider publishing these poems, and the book's editor pleaded with him to withdraw them, but he insisted that they stay. All the fuss perplexed him. The poems were commenting on prejudice, he pointed out, and not condoning it. He intended to show how derogatory words cause people to see others in terms of stereotypes rather than as individuals. &quot;America (which turns Hungarian into 'hunky' &amp; Irishman into 'mick' and Norwegian into 'square- head') is to blame for 'kike,'&quot; he said.&lt;ref Name=&quot;Reef&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

[[William Carlos Williams]] spoke out in his defense.&lt;ref Name=&quot;Reef&quot;&gt;''E. Cummings'' (2006) by Catherine Reef, Houghton Mifflin Harcourt p. 115 {{ISBN|978-0-618-56849-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Clarify|reason=|date=April 2018}}

===Plays===
During his lifetime, Cummings published four plays. ''HIM'', a three-act play, was first produced in 1928 by the [[Provincetown Players]] in New York City. The production was directed by James Light. The play's main characters are &quot;Him&quot;, a playwright, portrayed by [[William Johnstone (actor)|William Johnstone]], and &quot;Me&quot;, his girlfriend, portrayed by [[Erin O'Brien-Moore]].

Cummings said of the unorthodox play:
&lt;blockquote&gt;Relax and give the play a chance to strut its stuff—relax, stop wondering what it is all 'about'—like many strange and familiar things, Life included, this play isn't 'about,' it simply is. . . . Don't try to enjoy it, let it try to enjoy you. &lt;small&gt;DON'T TRY TO UNDERSTAND IT, LET IT TRY TO UNDERSTAND YOU.&lt;/small&gt;&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Kennedy, p. 295.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

''Anthropos, or the Future of Art'' is a short, one-act play that Cummings contributed to the anthology ''Whither, Whither or After Sex, What? A Symposium to End Symposium''. The play consists of dialogue between Man, the main character, and three &quot;infrahumans&quot;, or inferior beings. The word ''[[Greek language|anthropos]]'' is the [[Greek language|Greek]] word for &quot;man&quot;, in the sense of &quot;mankind&quot;.

''Tom, A Ballet'' is a ballet based on ''[[Uncle Tom's Cabin]]''. The ballet is detailed in a &quot;synopsis&quot; as well as descriptions of four &quot;episodes&quot;, which were published by Cummings in 1935. It has never been performed.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gvsu.edu/english/cummings/Tom.html GVSU.edu The E. E. Cummings Society] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20050423191607/http://www.gvsu.edu/english/cummings/Tom.html |date=April 23, 2005 }}.&lt;/ref&gt;

''[[Santa Claus: A Morality]]'' was probably Cummings' most successful play. It is an allegorical Christmas fantasy presented in one act of five scenes. The play was inspired by his daughter Nancy, with whom he was reunited in 1946. It was first published in the Harvard College magazine, ''Wake''. The play's main characters are Santa Claus, his family (Woman and Child), Death, and Mob. At the outset of the play, Santa Claus' family has disintegrated due to their lust for knowledge (Science). After a series of events, however, Santa Claus' faith in love and his rejection of the materialism and disappointment he associates with Science are reaffirmed, and he is reunited with Woman and Child.

===Name and capitalization===
Cummings' publishers and others have often echoed the unconventional [[orthography]] in his poetry by writing his name in lowercase and without periods ([[full stop]]s), but normal orthography for his name (uppercase and periods) is supported by scholarship and preferred by publishers today.&lt;ref name=&quot;friedman92&quot; /&gt; Cummings himself used both the lowercase and capitalized versions, though he most often signed his name with capitals.&lt;ref name=&quot;friedman92&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | last = Friedman | first =  Norman | year = 1992 | title = Not &quot;e. e. cummings&quot; | journal=Spring | volume = 1 | pages = 114–21 | url = http://faculty.gvsu.edu/websterm/cummings/caps.htm | accessdate = December 13, 2005 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The use of lowercase for his initials was popularized in part by the title of some books, particularly in the 1960s, printing his name in lower case on the cover and spine. In the preface to ''E. E. Cummings: The Growth of a Writer'' by Norman Friedman, critic Harry T. Moore notes Cummings &quot;had his name put legally into lower case, and in his later books the titles and his name were always in lower case.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Friedman | first = Norman | title = E. E. Cummings: The Growth of a Writer | location = Carbondale | publisher=Southern Illinois University Press | year = 1964 | isbn = 0-8093-0978-5 }}&lt;/ref&gt; According to Cummings' widow, however, this is incorrect.&lt;ref name=&quot;friedman92&quot; /&gt; She wrote to Friedman: &quot;You should not have allowed H. Moore to make such a stupid &amp; childish statement about Cummings &amp; his signature.&quot; On February 27, 1951, Cummings wrote to his French translator D. Jon Grossman that he preferred the use of upper case for the particular edition they were working on.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last = Friedman | first = Norman | year = 1995 | title = Not &quot;e. e. cummings&quot; Revisited | journal=Spring | volume = 5 | pages = 41–43 | url = http://faculty.gvsu.edu/websterm/cummings/caps2.html | accessdate = May 12, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt; One Cummings scholar believes that on the rare occasions that Cummings signed his name in all lowercase, he may have intended it as a gesture of humility, not as an indication that it was the preferred orthography for others to use.&lt;ref name=&quot;friedman92&quot; /&gt; Additionally, the ''Chicago Manual of Style'', which prescribes favoring non-standard capitalization of names in accordance with the bearer's strongly stated preference, notes &quot;E. E. Cummings can be safely capitalized; it was one of his publishers, not he himself, who lowercased his name.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;chicago84&quot;&gt;{{cite book |publisher=Chicago University Press|year=2010|title=Chicago Manual of Style|edition=16|section=Capitalization of Personal Names|page=388}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Adaptations==
In 1943, modern dancer and choreographer [[Jean Erdman]] presented &quot;The Transformations of Medusa, Forever and Sunsmell&quot; with a commissioned score by [[John Cage]] and a spoken text from the title poem by E. E. Cummings, sponsored by the [[Arts Club of Chicago]]. Erdman also choreographed &quot;Twenty Poems&quot; (1960), a cycle of E. E. Cummings' poems for eight dancers and one actor, with a commissioned score by [[Teiji Ito]]. It was performed in the round at the [[Circle in the Square Theatre]] in Greenwich Village.

Numerous composers have set Cummings' poems to music:
* In 1961, [[Pierre Boulez]] composed &quot;Cummings ist der dichter&quot; from poems by E. E. Cummings.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://brahms.ircam.fr/works/work/6957/|title=cummings ist der dichter, Pierre Boulez}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Aribert Reimann]] set Cummings to music in &quot;Impression IV&quot; (1961) for soprano and piano.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://catalogue.nla.gov.au/Record/2743128|title=Impression IV : nach einem Gedicht von E.E. Cummings : four Singstimme und Klavier (1961) / Aribert Reimann. music|first1=Aribert|last1=Reimann|first2=E. E. (Edward Estlin)|last2=Cummings|via=National Library of Australia}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Morton Feldman]] (1926-1987) in 1951 composed &quot;4 Songs to e.e. cummings&quot; for soprano, piano and cello, using material from Cummings' &quot;50 poems&quot; of 1940: &quot;!Blac&quot;, &quot;Air&quot;, &quot;(Sitting In A Tree-)&quot; and &quot;(Moan)&quot;.
* The Icelandic singer [[Björk]] used lines from Cummings's poem &quot;I Will Wade Out&quot; for the lyrics of &quot;Sun in My Mouth&quot; on her 2001 album ''[[Vespertine]].'' On her next album, ''[[Medúlla]]'' (2004), Björk used his poem &quot;It May Not Always Be So&quot; as the lyrics for the song &quot;Sonnets/Unrealities XI.&quot;
* The American composer [[Eric Whitacre]] wrote a [[Eric Whitacre#SATB choral|cycle of works]] for choir titled ''The City and the Sea'', which consists of five poems by Cummings set to music.
* Others who have composed settings for his poems include [[Dominic Argento]], [[William Bergsma]], [[Leonard Bernstein]], [[Marc Blitzstein]], [[John Cage]], [[Romeo Cascarino]], [[Aaron Copland]], [[Serge de Gastyne]], [[David Diamond (composer)|David Diamond]], [[John Woods Duke|John Duke]], [[Margaret Garwood]], [[Daron Hagen]], [[Michael Hedges]], [[Richard Hundley]], [[Barbara Kolb]], [[Leonard Lehrman]], [[Robert Manno]], [[Salvatore Martirano]], [[William Mayer (composer)|William Mayer]], [[John Musto]], [[Paul Nordoff]], [[Tobias Picker]], [[Vincent Persichetti]], [[Ned Rorem]], [[Peter Schickele]], [[Elie Siegmeister]], [[Aki Takase]], [[Hugo Weisgall]], [[Dan Welcher]], and [[James Yannatos]], among many others.&lt;ref name=&quot;lieder&quot;&gt;{{citation |title = Author: E. E. (Edward Estlin) Cummings (1894 - 1962) |date = April 25, 2019 |website = The LiederNet Archive |url = http://www.lieder.net/lieder/get_author_texts.html?AuthorId=621 |access-date = June 10, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Awards==
During his lifetime, Cummings received numerous awards in recognition of his work, including:
* [[The Dial#The Dial Award|Dial Award]] (1925)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.poetryfoundation.org/poets/e-e-cummings|title=E. E. Cummings|date=April 19, 2018|publisher=Poetry Foundation|others=Poetry Foundation|access-date=20 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Guggenheim Fellowship]] (1933)&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.gf.org/fellows/all-fellows/e-e-cummings/|title=John Simon Guggenheim Foundation {{!}} E. E. Cummings|website=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Shelley Memorial Award]] for Poetry (1945)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.poetrysociety.org/psa/awards/frost_and_shelley/shelley_winners/|title=Shelley Winners – Poetry Society of America |website=poetrysociety.org |access-date=20 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Harriet Monroe Prize from ''Poetry'' magazine (1950)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1950/06/11/archives/poetry-award-is-made-ee-cummings-wins-the-1950-harriet-monroe-prize.html|title=POETRY AWARD IS MADE; E.E. Cummings Wins the 1950 Harriet Monroe Prize|date=June 11, 1950|work=The New York Times|access-date=20 April 2018|issn=0362-4331|url-access=subscription}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Fellowship of [[American Academy of Poets]] (1950)&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.poets.org/poetsorg/poet/e-e-cummings|title=E. E. Cummings|last=Cummings|first=E. E.|date=February 4, 2014|website=E. E. Cummings|access-date=20 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Guggenheim Fellowship (1951)&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;
* [[Charles Eliot Norton]] Professorship at Harvard (1952–1953)&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt;
* Special citation from the [[National Book Award]] Committee for his ''Poems, 1923–1954'' (1957)
* [[Bollingen Prize]] in Poetry (1958)&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt;
* Boston Arts Festival Award (1957)
* Two-year [[Ford Foundation]] grant of $15,000 (1959)&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt;

==Books==
[[File:EecummingsLeidenWallPoem.jpg|{{largethumb}}|''the hours rise up'' on a [[Wall poems in Leiden|wall in Leiden]] ]]
* ''[[The Enormous Room]]'' (1922)
* ''[[Tulips and Chimneys]]'' (1923)
* ''&amp;'' (1925) (self-published)
* ''XLI Poems'' (1925)
* ''[[is 5]]'' (1926)
* ''HIM'' (1927) (a play)
* ''ViVa'' (1931)
* ''[[CIOPW]]'' (1931) (art works)
* ''[[Eimi (book)|EIMI]]'' (1933) (Soviet travelogue)
* ''[[No Thanks (collection)|No Thanks]]'' (1935)
* ''Collected Poems'' (1938)
* ''50 Poems'' (1940)
* ''[[1 × 1]]'' (1944)
* ''[[Santa Claus: A Morality]]'' (1946)
* ''XAIPE: Seventy-One Poems'' (1950)
*''i—six nonlectures'' (1953) [[Harvard University Press]]
* ''Poems, 1923–1954'' (1954)
* ''95 Poems'' (1958)
* ''73 Poems'' (1963) (posthumous)
* ''[[Fairy Tales (Cummings)|Fairy Tales]]'' (1965)
* ''Etcetera: The Unpublished Poems'' (1983)
* ''Complete Poems, 1904–1962'', edited by George James Firmage, Liveright 2008

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==References==
* Bloom, Harold, ''Twentieth-century American Literature'', New York : Chelsea House Publishers, 1985–1988. {{ISBN|978-0-87754-802-7}}.
* {{cite book| title=Poet and Painter: The Aesthetics of E. E. Cummings' Early Work| author=Cohen, Milton A.| publisher=Wayne State University Press| year=1987| isbn=978-0-8143-1845-4 }}
* Friedman, Norman (editor), ''E. E. Cummings: A Collection of Critical Essays''. {{ISBN|978-0-9829733-0-1}}
* Friedman, Norman, ''E. E. Cummings: The Art of his Poetry''.
* Galgano, Andrea, ''La furiosa ricerca di Edward E. Cummings'', in ''Mosaico'', Roma, Aracne, 2013, pp.&amp;nbsp;441–44 {{ISBN|978-88-548-6705-5}}
* Heusser, Martin. ''I Am My Writing: The Poetry of E.E. Cummings.'' Tübingen: Stauffenburg, 1997.
* Hutchinson, Hazel. ''The War That Used Up Words: American Writers and the First World War.'' New Haven, CT: Yale University Press, 2015.
* James, George, ''E. E. Cummings: A Bibliography''.
* {{Cite book |last=Kennedy |first=Richard S. |title=Dreams in the Mirror |edition=2nd |date=October 17, 1994 |origyear=1980 |publisher=Liveright |location=New York |isbn=0-87140-155-X |url=https://archive.org/details/dreamsinmirrorbi0000kenn }}
* McBride, Katharine, ''A Concordance to the Complete Poems of E.E.Cummings''.
* [[Christopher Mott|Mott, Christopher]]. &quot;[https://web.archive.org/web/20090224122955/http://gvsu.edu/english/cummings/Mott4.htm The Cummings Line on Race&quot;], ''Spring: The Journal of the E. E. Cummings Society,'' vol. 4, pp.&amp;nbsp;71–75, Fall 1995.
* [[Norman, Charles]], ''E. E. Cummings: The Magic-Maker'', Boston, Little Brown, 1972.
* Sawyer-Lauçanno, Christopher, ''E. E. Cummings: A Biography'', Sourcebooks, Inc. (2004) {{ISBN|978-1-57071-775-8}}.

==External links==
{{sisterlinks|d=Q298703|n=no|b=no|v=no|voy=no|s=Author:Edward Estlin Cummings|wikt=no|m=no|mw=no|species=no}}
{{Bibliowiki|E. E. Cummings|E. E. Cummings}}
* {{Gutenberg author |id=Cummings,+E.+E.+(Edward+Estlin) | name=E. E. Cummings}}
* {{Internet Archive author |sname=Edward Estlin Cummings}}
* {{Librivox author |id=2655}}
* [http://www.harvardsquarelibrary.org/biographies/e-e-cummings-3 E. E. Cummings, Lifelong Unitarian] Biography of Cummings and his relationship with Unitarianism
* [http://www.librarything.com/profile/e.e.cummingslibrary E.E. Cummings Personal Library] at [[LibraryThing]]
* [http://nrs.harvard.edu/urn-3:FHCL.Hough:hou00946 Papers of E. E. Cummings] at the [[Houghton Library]] at [[Harvard University]]
* [http://research.hrc.utexas.edu:8080/hrcxtf/view?docId=ead/00191.xml&amp;query=cummings&amp;query-join=and E. E. Cummings Collection] at the [[Harry Ransom Center]] at the [[University of Texas at Austin]]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20061003230902/http://www.poetryfoundation.org/archive/poet.html?id=81323 Poems by E. E. Cummings at PoetryFoundation.org]
* [https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/articles/A34132-2004Oct14.html Jonathan Yardley, ''E. E. Cummings: A Biography'', Sunday, October 17, 2004, Page BW02, ''The Washington Post Book Review'']
* [http://faculty.gvsu.edu/websterm/cummings/ ''SPRING'':The Journal of the E. E. Cummings Society]
* [http://www.english.illinois.edu/MAPS/poets/a_f/cummings/cummings.htm Modern American Poetry]
* [http://lccn.loc.gov/n79038464 E. E. Cummings] at [[Library of Congress]] Authorities&amp;nbsp;– with 202 catalog records
* [http://www.poets.org/poetsorg/poet/e-e-cummings Biography and poems of E. E. Cummings at Poets.org]

{{E. E. Cummings|state=uncollapsed}}
{{Portal bar|Biography|Poetry|United States}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Cummings, E. E.}}
[[Category:E. E. Cummings| ]]
[[Category:1894 births]]
[[Category:1962 deaths]]
[[Category:American male poets]]
[[Category:American Unitarians]]
[[Category:Formalist poets]]
[[Category:Guggenheim Fellows]]
[[Category:Harvard University alumni]]
[[Category:Massachusetts culture]]
[[Category:Massachusetts Republicans]]
[[Category:American modernist poets]]
[[Category:Modernist writers]]
[[Category:Writers from Cambridge, Massachusetts]]
[[Category:People from Carroll County, New Hampshire]]
[[Category:People from Greenwich Village]]
[[Category:Military personnel from Massachusetts]]
[[Category:Sonneteers]]
[[Category:Poets from Massachusetts]]
[[Category:Analysands of Fritz Wittels]]
[[Category:Self-published authors]]
[[Category:Bollingen Prize recipients]]
[[Category:Burials at Forest Hills Cemetery (Boston)]]
[[Category:20th-century American poets]]
[[Category:American anti-communists]]
[[Category:Harvard Advocate alumni]]
[[Category:Republicans (United States)]]</text>
      <sha1>9dnsw4ku97imhut36hgbgvbu4qwxm97</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
