  <page>
    <title>Empedocles</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9553</id>
    <revision>
      <id>939195405</id>
      <parentid>939124120</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-04T23:17:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Diannaa</username>
        <id>10728040</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>add attribution for public domain material</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Ancient Greek philosopher}}
{{other uses}}
{{Infobox philosopher
|region   = [[Western philosophy]]
|era      = [[Pre-Socratic philosophy]]
|image    = Empedocles in Thomas Stanley History of Philosophy.jpg
|caption  = Empedocles, 17th-century engraving
|name     = Empedocles
|birth_date  = {{circa|494 BC}}&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=A History of Greek Philosophy from the Earliest Period to the Time of Socrates|last=Zeller|first=Eduard|publisher=Longmans, Green, and Co.|year=1881|isbn=|volume=II|location=London|pages=118|translator-last=Alleyne|translator-first=S. F.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Wright |first1=M. R. |title=Empedocles: The Extant Fragments |date=1981 |publisher=Yale University Press |page=6}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|birth_place = 
|death_date  = {{circa|434 BC|lk=no}}&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=A History of Greek Philosophy from the Earliest Period to the Time of Socrates|last=Zeller|first=Eduard|publisher=Longmans, Green, and Co.|year=1881|isbn=|volume=II|location=London|pages=118|translator-last=Alleyne|translator-first=S. F.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Wright |first1=M. R. |title=Empedocles: The Extant Fragments |date=1981 |publisher=Yale University Press |page=6}}&lt;/ref&gt; (aged around 60)
|death_place = &quot;Empedokles did not die in Sicily, but in the Peloponnese, or, perhaps, at Thourioi.&quot;{{sfn|Burnet|1930|pp=202–203}}
|school_tradition = [[Pluralist school]]
|main_interests = [[Cosmogenesis]], [[ontology]], [[epistemology]]
|influences = [[Parmenides]],{{sfn|Burnet|1930|pp=202–203}} [[Pythagoreanism]], [[Alcmaeon of Croton]]{{sfn|Burnet|1930|pp=202–203}}
|influenced = [[Gorgias]], [[Socrates]]{{sfn|Burnet|1930|pp=202–203}} [[Critias]],{{sfn|Burnet|1930|pp=202–203}} [[Aristotle]], [[Lucretius]], [[Friedrich Nietzsche]]
|notable_ideas = All [[matter]] is made up of four elements: [[water (classical element)|water]], [[earth (classical element)|earth]], [[air (classical element)|air]] and [[fire (classical element)|fire]]&lt;br&gt;The [[Arche|cosmic principles]] of&lt;br&gt;[[Philotes (mythology)|Philotes]] (&quot;Love&quot;) and [[Neikea|Neikos]] (&quot;Repulsion&quot;)&lt;ref&gt;Frank Reynolds, David Tracy (eds.), [https://books.google.com/books?id=XdHPgPmSgYEC&amp;dq= ''Myth and Philosophy''], SUNY Press, 1990, p. 99.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;Theories about [[Cellular respiration|respiration]]&lt;ref name=&quot;frag100&quot;/&gt;
}}

'''Empedocles''' ({{IPAc-en|ɛ|m|ˈ|p|ɛ|d|ə|k|l|iː|z|}}; {{lang-grc-gre|Ἐμπεδοκλῆς}} {{IPA-grc|empedoklɛ̂ːs|}}, ''Empedoklēs''; {{circa|494|434&amp;nbsp;BC|lk=on}}&lt;ref name=&quot;:4&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title=A History of Greek Philosophy from the Earliest Period to the Time of Socrates|last=Zeller|first=Eduard|publisher=Longmans, Green, and Co.|year=1881|isbn=|volume=II|location=London|pages=117-118|translator-last=Alleyne|translator-first=S. F.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Empedocles: The Extant Fragments|last1=Wright|first1=M. R.|date=1981|publisher=Yale University Press|page=6}}&lt;/ref&gt;, fl. 444-443 BC{{sfn|Burnet|1930|p=198}}) was a [[Ancient Greece|Greek]] [[pre-Socratic philosopher]] and a native citizen of [[Akragas]],&lt;ref name=&quot;:4&quot; /&gt;{{sfn|Burnet|1930|p=197}} a Greek city in [[Sicily]]. Empedocles' philosophy is best known for originating the [[cosmogonic]] theory of the four [[classical elements]]. He also proposed forces he called Love and Strife which would mix and separate the elements, respectively.

Influenced by [[Pythagoras]] (died c. 495 BC) and the [[Pythagoreans]], Empedocles challenged the practice of animal sacrifice and killing animals for food. He developed a distinctive doctrine of [[reincarnation]]. He is generally considered the last Greek philosopher to have recorded his ideas in verse. Some of his work survives, more than is the case for any other pre-Socratic philosopher. Empedocles' death was mythologized by ancient writers, and has been the subject of a number of literary treatments.

==Life==
[[File:Temple of Hera - Agrigento - Italy 2015.JPG|left|thumb|The temple of [[Hera]] at [[Akragas]], built when Empedocles was a young man, {{circa|470 BC}}.]]
Empedocles (Empedokles) was a native citizen of [[Akragas]] in [[Sicily]].&lt;ref name=&quot;:4&quot; /&gt;{{sfn|Burnet|1930|p=197}} &quot;He came from a rich and noble family.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;:4&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Pre-Socratic Philosophers|last=Freeman|first=Kathleen|publisher=Basil Blackwell|year=1946|isbn=|location=Oxford|pages=172-173}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Diogenes Laërtius, viii. 51&lt;/ref&gt; Very little is known about his life. &quot;His grandfather, also called Empedokles, had won a victory in the horse-race at Olympia in [the 71st Olympiad] OL. LXXI (496-95 BC).&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;:4&quot; /&gt;{{sfn|Burnet|1930|p=197}}&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot; /&gt; &quot;His father’s name, according to the best accounts, was Meton.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;:4&quot; /&gt;{{sfn|Burnet|1930|p=197}}&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot; /&gt;

&quot;All, therefore, we can be said to know [about the dates of Empedocles] is, that his grandfather was still alive in 496 BC.; that he himself was active at Akragas after 472 BC, the date of Theron’s death; and that he died later than 444 BC.&quot;{{sfn|Burnet|1930|p=198}}

Empedocles &quot;broke up the assembly of the Thousand. perhaps some oligarchical association or club.&quot;{{sfn|Burnet|1930|p=199}} He is said to have been magnanimous in his support of the poor;&lt;ref&gt;Diogenes Laërtius, viii. 73&lt;/ref&gt; severe in persecuting the overbearing conduct of the [[oligarchy|oligarchs]];&lt;ref&gt;Timaeus, ap. Diogenes Laërtius, viii. 64, comp. 65, 66&lt;/ref&gt; and he even declined the sovereignty of the city when it was offered to him.&lt;ref&gt;Aristotle ap. Diogenes Laërtius, viii. 63; compare, however, Timaeus, ap. Diogenes Laërtius, 66, 76&lt;/ref&gt;

&quot;But there is another side to his public character...He claimed to be a god, and to receive the homage of his fellow-citizens in that capacity. The truth is, Empedokles was not a mere statesman; he had a good deal of the 'medicine-man' about him. According to Satyros, Gorgias affirmed that he had been present when his master was performing sorceries. We can see what this means from the fragments of the ''Purifications''. Empedokles was a preacher of the new religion which sought to secure release from the 'wheel of birth' by purity and abstinence. Orphicism seems to have been strong at Akragas in the days of Theron, and there are even some verbal coincidences between the poems of Empedokles and the Orphicsing Odes which Pindar addressed to that prince. On the other hand, there is no reason to doubt the statement of Ammonios that fr. 134 refers to Apollo; and, if that is so, it points to his having been an adherent of the Ionic form of the mystic doctrine, as we have seen Pythagoras was. 

[fr. 134. For he is not furnished with a human head on his body, two branches do not sprout from his shoulders, he has no feet, no swift knees, nor hairy parts; but he is only a sacred and unutterable mind flashing through the whole world with rapid thoughts.]

Further, Timaios already knew the story that Empedokles had been expelled from the Pythagorean Order for 'stealing discourses’ and it is probable on the whole that fr. 129 refers to Pythagoras.

[fr. 129. And there was among them a man of rare knowledge, most skilled in all manner of wise works, a man who had won the utmost wealth of wisdom; for whensoever he strained with all his mind, he easily saw everything of all the things that are, in ten, yea, twenty lifetimes of men.]&quot;{{sfn|Burnet|1930|p=199}}

His brilliant oratory,&lt;ref&gt;Satyrus, ap. Diogenes Laërtius, viii. 78; Timaeus, ap. Diogenes Laërtius, 67&lt;/ref&gt; his penetrating knowledge of nature, and the reputation of his marvellous powers, including the curing of diseases, and averting epidemics,&lt;ref&gt;Diogenes Laërtius, viii. 60, 70, 69; Plutarch, ''de Curios. Princ.'', ''adv. Colotes''; Pliny, ''H. N.'' xxxvi. 27, and others&lt;/ref&gt; produced many myths and stories surrounding his name. In his poem ''Purifications'' he claimed miraculous powers, including the destruction of evil, the curing of old age, and the controlling of wind and rain.

Empedocles was acquainted or connected by friendship with the physicians [[Pausanias of Sicily|Pausanias]]&lt;ref&gt;Diogenes Laërtius, viii. 60, 61, 65, 69&lt;/ref&gt; (his [[eromenos]]&lt;ref&gt;Diogenes Laërtius, viii. 60: &quot;Pausanias, according to [[Aristippus]] and [[Satyrus the Peripatetic|Satyrus]], was his eromenos&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;) and [[Acron]];&lt;ref&gt;Pliny, ''Natural History'', xxix.1.4–5; cf. Suda, ''Akron''&lt;/ref&gt; with various [[Pythagoras|Pythagoreans]]; and even, it is said, with [[Parmenides]] and [[Anaxagoras]].&lt;ref&gt;Suda, ''Empedocles''; Diogenes Laërtius, viii. 55, 56, etc.&lt;/ref&gt; The only pupil of Empedocles who is mentioned is the [[sophist]] and [[rhetorician]] [[Gorgias]].&lt;ref&gt;Diogenes Laërtius, viii. 58&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Timaeus (historian)|Timaeus]] and [[Dicaearchus]] spoke of the journey of Empedocles to the [[Peloponnese]], and of the admiration, which was paid to him there;&lt;ref&gt;Diogenes Laërtius, viii. 71, 67; Athenaeus, xiv.&lt;/ref&gt; others mentioned his stay at [[Athens]], and in the newly founded colony of [[Thurii]], 446 BC;&lt;ref&gt;Suda, ''Akron''; Diogenes Laërtius, viii. 52&lt;/ref&gt; there are also fanciful reports of him travelling far to the east to the lands of the [[Magi]].&lt;ref&gt;Pliny, ''H. N.'' xxx. 1, etc.&lt;/ref&gt;

The contemporary ''Life of Empedocles'' by [[Xanthus (historian)|Xanthus]] has been lost.

== Death ==
According to [[Aristotle]], he died at the age of sixty ({{circa|430&amp;nbsp;BC|lk=no}}), even though other writers have him living up to the age of one hundred and nine.&lt;ref&gt;Apollonius, ap. Diogenes Laërtius, viii. 52, comp. 74, 73&lt;/ref&gt; Likewise, there are myths concerning his death: a tradition, which is traced to [[Heraclides Ponticus]], represented him as having been removed from the Earth; whereas others had him perishing in the flames of Mount Etna. &lt;ref&gt;Diogenes Laërtius, viii. 67, 69, 70, 71; Horace, ''ad Pison.'' 464, etc. Refer to {{harvp|Arnold|1852|loc=Empedocles on Etna}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

&quot;We are told that Empedokles leapt into the crater of Etna that he might be deemed a god. This appears to be a malicious version of a tale set on foot by his adherents that he had been snatched up to heaven in the night. Both stories would easily get accepted; for there was no local tradition. Empedokles did not die in Sicily, but in the Peloponnese, or, perhaps, at Thourioi. It is not at all unlikely that he visited Athens.&quot;{{sfn|Burnet|1930|pp=202–203}}

&quot;Timaios refuted the common stories [about Empedokles] at some length. (Diog. viii. 71 sqq.; Ritter and. Preller [162].). He was quite positive that Empedokles never returned to Sicily after he went to Olympia to have his poem recited to the Hellenes. The plan for the colonisation of Thourioi would, of course,, be discussed at Olympia, and we know that Greeks from the Peloponnese and elsewhere joined it. He may very well have gone to Athens in connexion with this.&quot;{{sfn|Burnet|1930|pp=202–203}}

==Works==
[[File:Empedokles fragment Physika I 262–300.jpg|thumb|right|A piece of the Strasbourg Empedocles papyrus in the [[Bibliothèque nationale et universitaire]], Strasbourg]]
Empedocles is considered the last Greek philosopher to write in verse. There is a debate&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Inwood |first1=Brad |title=The poem of Empedocles : a text and translation with an introduction |date=2001 |publisher=University of Toronto Press |location=Toronto |isbn=0-8020-8353-6 |pages=8-21 |edition=Rev.}}&lt;/ref&gt; about whether the surviving fragments of his teaching should be attributed to two separate poems, ''Purifications'' and ''On Nature'', with different subject matter, or whether they may all derive from one poem with two titles&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Osborne |first1=Catherine |title=Rethinking early Greek philosophy : Hippolytus of Rome and the Presocratics |date=1987 |publisher=Duckworth |location=London |isbn=0-7156-1975-6 |pages=24-31, 108}}&lt;/ref&gt;, or whether one title refers to part of the whole poem. Some scholars argue that  the title ''Purifications'' refers to the first part of a larger work called (as a whole) ''On Nature''.&lt;ref&gt;Simon Trépanier, (2004), ''Empedocles: An Interpretation'', Routledge.&lt;/ref&gt; There is also a debate about which fragments should be attributed to each of the poems, if there are two poems, or if part of it is called &quot;Purifications&quot;; because ancient writers rarely mentioned which poem they were quoting. 
Empedocles was undoubtedly acquainted with the didactic poems of [[Xenophanes]] and [[Parmenides]]&lt;ref&gt;Hermippus and Theophrastus, ap. Diogenes Laërtius, viii. 55, 56&lt;/ref&gt;—allusions to the latter can be found in the fragments—but he seems to have surpassed them in the animation and richness of his style, and in the clearness of his descriptions and diction. [[Aristotle]] called him the father of [[rhetoric]],&lt;ref name=EB1911&gt;{{Cite EB1911 |wstitle=Empedocles |volume=9 |pages=344–345 |first=William |last=Wallace}}&lt;/ref&gt; and, although he acknowledged only the [[Meter (poetry)|meter]] as a point of comparison between the poems of Empedocles and the epics of [[Homer]], he described Empedocles as Homeric and powerful in his diction.&lt;ref&gt;Aristotle, ''Poetics'', 1, ap. Diogenes Laërtius, viii. 57.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Lucretius]] speaks of him with enthusiasm, and evidently viewed him as his model.&lt;ref&gt;See especially Lucretius, i. 716, etc. Refer to {{harvp|Sedley|1998}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The two poems together comprised 5000 lines.&lt;ref&gt;Diogenes Laërtius, viii. 77&lt;/ref&gt; About 550 lines of his poetry survive.  

===''Purifications''===
In the old editions of Empedocles, only about 100 lines were typically ascribed to his ''Purifications'', which was taken to be a poem about ritual purification, or the poem that contained all his religious and ethical thought. Early editors supposed that it was a poem that offered a mythical account of the world which may, nevertheless, have been part of Empedocles' philosophical system. According to [[Diogenes Laërtius]] it began with the following verses:
&lt;poem&gt;
Friends who inhabit the mighty town by tawny Acragas
which crowns the citadel, caring for good deeds,
greetings; I, an immortal God, no longer mortal,
wander among you, honoured by all,
adorned with holy diadems and blooming garlands.
To whatever illustrious towns I go,
I am praised by men and women, and accompanied
by thousands, who thirst for deliverance,
some ask for prophecies, and some entreat,
for remedies against all kinds of disease.&lt;ref&gt;[[Diels–Kranz numbering system|DK]] frag. B112 (Diogenes Laërtius, viii. 61)&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/poem&gt;
In the older editions, it is to this work that editors attributed the story about [[soul]]s,&lt;ref&gt;Frag. B115 (Plutarch, ''On Exile'', 607 C–E; Hippolytus, vii. 29)&lt;/ref&gt; where we are told that there were once spirits who lived in a state of bliss, but having committed a crime (the nature of which is unknown) they were punished by being forced to become mortal beings, [[reincarnate]]d from body to body. Humans, animals, and even plants are such spirits. The moral conduct recommended in the poem may allow us to become like [[Pantheon (gods)|gods]] again. If, as is now widely held, this title &quot;Purifications&quot; refers to the poem ''On Nature'', or to a part of that poem, this story will have been at the beginning of the main work on nature and the cosmic cycle. The relevant verses are also sometimes attributed to the proem of ''On Nature'', even by those who think that there was a separate poem called &quot;Purifications&quot;.

===''On Nature''===
There are about 450 lines of his poem ''On Nature'' extant,&lt;ref name=EB1911/&gt; including 70 lines which have been reconstructed from some papyrus scraps known as the ''Strasbourg Papyrus''. The poem originally consisted of 2000 lines of [[hexameter]] verse,&lt;ref&gt;Suda, ''Empedocles''&lt;/ref&gt; and was addressed to [[Pausanias of Sicily|Pausanias]].&lt;ref&gt;Diogenes Laërtius, viii. 60&lt;/ref&gt; It was this poem which outlined his philosophical system. In it, Empedocles explains not only the nature and history of the universe, including his theory of the four [[classical element]]s, but he describes theories on causation, perception, and thought, as well as explanations of terrestrial phenomena and biological processes.

==Philosophy==
[[File:Empedocles-2-sized.jpg|right|thumb|Empedocles as portrayed in the [[Nuremberg Chronicle]]]]
Although acquainted with the theories of the [[Eleatics]] and the [[Pythagoreans]], Empedocles did not belong to any one definite school.&lt;ref name=EB1911/&gt; An [[Eclecticism|eclectic]] in his thinking, he combined much that had been suggested by [[Parmenides]], [[Pythagoras]] and the [[Ionian school (philosophy)|Ionian school]]s.&lt;ref name=EB1911/&gt; He was a firm believer in [[Orphism (religion)|Orphic mysteries]], as well as a scientific thinker and a precursor of [[physics]]. Aristotle mentions Empedocles among the Ionic philosophers, and he places him in very close relation to the [[atomism|atomist]] philosophers and to [[Anaxagoras]].&lt;ref&gt;Aristotle, ''Metaphysics'', i. 3, 4, 7, ''Phys.'' i. 4, ''de General, et Corr.'' i. 8, ''de Caelo'', iii. 7.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to House (1956)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=House |first=Humphry |url=https://archive.org/details/aristotlespoetic032945mbp |page=32 |title=Aristotles Poetics |year=1956}}&lt;/ref&gt;
:Another of the fragments of the dialogue ''On the Poets'' ([[Aristotle]]) treats more fully what is said in Poetics ch. i about ''Empedocles'', for though clearly implying that he was not a poet, Aristotle there says he is [[Homeric]], and an artist in language, skilled in metaphor and in the other devices of poetry.

Empedocles, like the Ionian philosophers and the atomists, continued the tradition of tragic thought which tried to find the basis of the relationship of the one and many. Each of the various philosophers, following Parmenides, derived from the Eleatics, the conviction that an existence could not pass into non-existence, and vice versa. Yet, each one had his peculiar way of describing this relation of Divine and mortal thought and thus of the relation of the One and the Many. In order to account for change in the world, in accordance with the ontological requirements of the Eleatics, they viewed changes as the result of mixture and separation of unalterable fundamental realities. Empedocles held that the four elements (Water, Air, Earth, and Fire) were those unchangeable fundamental realities, which were themselves transfigured into successive worlds by the powers of Love and Strife ([[Heraclitus]] had explicated the Logos or the &quot;unity of opposites&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;James Luchte, Early Greek Thought: Before the Dawn, Bloomsbury, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

===The four elements===
Empedocles established four ultimate [[classical elements|elements]] which make all the structures in the world—[[Fire (classical element)|fire]], [[Air (classical element)|air]], [[Water (classical element)|water]], [[Earth (classical element)|earth]]&lt;ref name=EB1911/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Frag. B17 (Simplicius, ''Physics'', 157–159)&lt;/ref&gt;. Empedocles called these four elements &quot;roots&quot;, which he also identified with the mythical names of [[Zeus]], [[Hera]], [[Persephone|Nestis]], and [[Aidoneus]]&lt;ref&gt;Frag. B6 (Sextus Empiricus, ''Against the Mathematicians'', x, 315)&lt;/ref&gt; (e.g., &quot;Now hear the fourfold roots of everything: enlivening Hera, Hades, shining Zeus. And Nestis, moistening mortal springs with tears.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Peter Kingsley (scholar)|Peter Kingsley]], in ''Ancient Philosophy, Mystery, and Magic: Empedocles and Pythagorean Tradition'' (Oxford University Press, 1995).&lt;/ref&gt;) Empedocles never used the term &quot;element&quot; ({{lang|grc|στοιχεῖον}}, ''stoicheion''), which seems to have been first used by [[Plato]].&lt;ref&gt;Plato, ''Timaeus'', 48b–c&lt;/ref&gt; According to the different proportions in which these four indestructible and unchangeable elements are combined with each other the difference of the structure is produced.&lt;ref name=EB1911/&gt; It is in the aggregation and segregation of elements thus arising, that Empedocles, like the atomists, found the real process which corresponds to what is popularly termed growth, increase or decrease. Nothing new comes or can come into being; the only change that can occur is a change in the juxtaposition of element with element.&lt;ref name=EB1911/&gt; This theory of the four elements became the standard [[dogma]] for the next two thousand years.

===Love and Strife===
{{distinguish|text=the Greek deities [[Aphrodite|of love]] and [[Eris (mythology)|strife]]}}
[[File:Empedocles cosmic cycle concept map.svg|300px|right|thumb|Empedocles cosmic cycle is based on the conflict between love and strife]]
The four elements, however, are simple, eternal, and unalterable, and as change is the consequence of their mixture and separation, it was also necessary to suppose the existence of moving powers that bring about mixture and separation. The four elements are both eternally brought into union and parted from one another by two divine powers, [[Love]] and [[Wikt:strife|Strife]] or Hatred.&lt;ref name=EB1911/&gt; Love ({{lang|grc|φιλότης}}) is responsible for the attraction of different forms of matter, and Strife ({{lang|grc|νεῖκος}}) is the cause of their separation.&lt;ref&gt;Frag. B35, B26 (Simplicius, ''Physics'', 31–34)&lt;/ref&gt; If the four elements make up the universe, then Love and Strife explain their variation and harmony. Love and Strife are attractive and repulsive forces, respectively, which are plainly observable in human behavior, but also pervade the universe. The two forces wax and wane in their dominance, but neither force ever wholly escapes the imposition of the other.

&quot;Empedokles sometimes gave an efficient power to Love and Strife, and sometimes put them on a level with the other four. The fragments leave no room for doubt that they were thought of as spatial and corporeal. All the six are called “ equal&quot;. Love is said to be “ equal in length and breadth ” to the others, and Strife is described as equal to each of them in weight (fr. 17). These physical speculations were part of a history of the universe which also dealt with the origin and development of life.&quot;&lt;{{sfn|Burnet|1930|p=232}}

===The sphere of Empedocles===
As the best and original state, there was a time when the pure elements and the two powers co-existed in a condition of rest and inertness in the form of a sphere.&lt;ref name=EB1911/&gt; The elements existed together in their purity, without mixture and separation, and the uniting power of Love predominated in the sphere: the separating power of Strife guarded the extreme edges of the sphere.&lt;ref&gt;Frag. B35 (Simplicius, ''Physics'', 31–34; ''On the Heavens'', 528–530)&lt;/ref&gt; Since that time, strife gained more sway&lt;ref name=EB1911/&gt; and the bond which kept the pure elementary substances together in the sphere was dissolved. The elements became the world of phenomena we see today, full of contrasts and oppositions, operated on by both Love and Strife.&lt;ref name=EB1911/&gt; The sphere being the embodiment of pure existence is the embodiment or representative of [[God]]. Empedocles assumed a cyclical universe whereby the elements return and prepare the formation of the sphere for the next period of the universe.

===Cosmogony===
Empedocles attempted to explain the separation of elements, the formation of earth and sea, of Sun and Moon, of atmosphere.&lt;ref name=EB1911/&gt; He also dealt with the first origin of plants and animals, and with the [[physiology]] of humans.&lt;ref name=EB1911/&gt; As the elements entered into combinations, there appeared strange results—heads without necks, arms without shoulders.&lt;ref name=EB1911/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Frag. B57 (Simplicius, ''On the Heavens'', 586)&lt;/ref&gt; Then as these fragmentary structures met, there were seen horned heads on human bodies, bodies of oxen with human heads, and figures of [[intersexuality|double sex]].&lt;ref name=EB1911/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Frag. B61 (Aelian, ''On Animals'', xvi 29)&lt;/ref&gt; But most of these products of natural forces disappeared as suddenly as they arose; only in those rare cases where the parts were found to be adapted to each other did the complex structures last.&lt;ref name=EB1911/&gt; Thus the organic universe sprang from spontaneous aggregations that suited each other as if this had been intended.&lt;ref name=EB1911/&gt; Soon various influences reduced creatures of double sex to a male and a female, and the world was replenished with organic life.&lt;ref name=EB1911/&gt; It is possible to see this theory as an anticipation of [[Charles Darwin]]'s theory of [[natural selection]], although Empedocles was not trying to explain [[evolution]].&lt;ref&gt;Ted Everson (2007), ''The gene: a historical perspective'' page 5. Greenwood&lt;/ref&gt;

===Perception and knowledge===
Empedocles is credited with the first comprehensive theory of light and vision. He put forward the idea that we see objects because light streams out of our eyes and touches them. While flawed, this became the fundamental basis on which later Greek philosophers and mathematicians like [[Euclid]] would construct some of the most important theories of light, vision, and optics.&lt;ref name = Ep1&gt;''[[Let There be Light]]'' 7 August 2006 01:50 BBC Four&lt;/ref&gt;

Knowledge is explained by the principle that elements in the things outside us are perceived by the corresponding elements in ourselves.&lt;ref&gt;Frag. B109 (Aristotle, ''On the Soul'', 404b11–15)&lt;/ref&gt; Like is known by like. The whole body is full of [[Sweat pore|pores]] and hence [[Cellular respiration|respiration]] takes place over the whole frame. In the organs of sense these pores are specially adapted to receive the effluences which are continually rising from bodies around us; thus  [[perception]] occurs.&lt;ref name=&quot;frag100&quot;&gt;[http://www.mycrandall.ca/courses/grphil/EmpedoclesText.htm Frag. B100] (Aristotle, ''On Respiration'', 473b1–474a6)&lt;/ref&gt; In vision, certain particles go forth from the eye to meet similar particles given forth from the object, and the resultant contact constitutes vision.&lt;ref&gt;Frag. B84 (Aristotle, ''On the Senses and their Objects'', 437b23–438a5)&lt;/ref&gt; Perception is not merely a passive reflection of external objects.&lt;ref name=EB1911/&gt;

Empedocles noted the limitation and narrowness of human perceptions. We see only a part but fancy that we have grasped the whole. But the senses cannot lead to truth; thought and reflection must look at the thing from every side. It is the business of a philosopher, while laying bare the fundamental difference of elements, to show the identity that exists between what seem unconnected parts of the universe.&lt;ref name=EB1911/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Frag. B2 (Sextus Empiricus, ''Against the Mathematicians'', vii. 123–125)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Respiration===
In a famous fragment,&lt;ref name=&quot;frag100&quot;/&gt; Empedocles attempted to explain the phenomena of [[Respiration (physiology)|respiration]] by means of an elaborate analogy with the [[Water thief|clepsydra]], an ancient device for conveying liquids from one vessel to another.&lt;ref name=&quot;barnes313&quot;&gt;[[Jonathan Barnes]] (2002), ''The Presocratic Philosophers'', page 313. Routledge&lt;/ref&gt; This fragment has sometimes been connected to a passage in [[Aristotle]]'s ''[[Physics (Aristotle)|Physics]]'' where Aristotle refers to people who twisted wineskins and captured air in clepsydras to demonstrate that [[Vacuum|void]] does not exist.&lt;ref&gt;Aristotle, ''Physics'', 213a24–7&lt;/ref&gt; There is however, no evidence that Empedocles performed any experiment with clepsydras.&lt;ref name=&quot;barnes313&quot;/&gt; The fragment certainly implies that Empedocles knew about the [[Matter|corporeality]] of air, but he says nothing whatever about the void.&lt;ref name=&quot;barnes313&quot;/&gt; The clepsydra was a common utensil and everyone who used it must have known, in some sense, that the invisible air could resist liquid.&lt;ref name=&quot;guthrie224&quot;&gt;[[W. K. C. Guthrie]], (1980), ''A history of Greek philosophy II: The Presocratic tradition from Parmenides to Democritus'', page 224. Cambridge University Press&lt;/ref&gt;

===Reincarnation===
Like [[Pythagoras]], Empedocles believed in the [[transmigration of the soul]]/[[metempsychosis]], that souls can be reincarnated between humans, animals and even plants.&lt;ref&gt;Frag. B127 (Aelian, ''On Animals'', xii. 7); Frag. B117 (Hippolytus, i. 3.2)&lt;/ref&gt; For Empedocles, all living things were on the same spiritual plane; plants and animals are links in a chain where humans are a link too.&lt;ref name=EB1911/&gt; Empedocles was a [[vegetarianism|vegetarian]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last= Heath |first= John |title= The Talking Greeks: Speech, Animals, and the Other in Homer, Aeschylus, and Plato |date= 2005-05-12 |publisher= [[Cambridge University Press]] |isbn= 9781139443913 |page= 322 |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=QwkEVV0j8fgC&amp;pg=PA322&amp;dq=%22An+excellent+study+of+Empedocles'+vegetarianism+and+the+various+meanings+of+sacrifice+in+its+cultural+context+is+that+of+Rundin+(1998).%22&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwjn6t3vltbOAhVD7GMKHVe8Cz4Q6AEIHjAA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22An%20excellent%20study%20of%20Empedocles'%20vegetarianism%20and%20the%20various%20meanings%20of%20sacrifice%20in%20its%20cultural%20context%20is%20that%20of%20Rundin%20(1998).%22&amp;f=false |quote= An excellent study of Empedocles' vegetarianism and the various meanings of sacrifice in its cultural context is that of Rundin (1998).}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author= Plato |authorlink= Plato |title= Meno |editor-last= Bluck |editor-first= Richard Stanley Harold |publisher= [[Cambridge University Press]] |year= 1961 |orig-year = c. 360 BC |isbn= 9780521172288 |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=-u0XnKDTw1kC&amp;pg=PA72&amp;dq=%22This+suggests+that+e.g.+Empedocles'+vegetarianism+was+partly+at+least+due+to+the+idea+that+the+spilling+of+blood+brings+pollution.%22&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwjA07HTl9bOAhUEKWMKHeY1BPMQ6AEIIDAB#v=onepage&amp;q=%22This%20suggests%20that%20e.g.%20Empedocles'%20vegetarianism%20was%20partly%20at%20least%20due%20to%20the%20idea%20that%20the%20spilling%20of%20blood%20brings%20pollution.%22&amp;f=false |quote= This suggests that e.g. Empedocles' vegetarianism was partly at least due to the idea that the spilling of blood brings pollution.}}&lt;/ref&gt; and advocated vegetarianism, since the bodies of animals are the dwelling places of punished souls.&lt;ref&gt;Sextus Empiricus, ''Against the Mathematicians'', ix. 127; Hippolytus, vii. 21&lt;/ref&gt; Wise people, who have learned the secret of life, are next to the [[divinity|divine]],&lt;ref name=EB1911/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Clement of Alexandria, ''Miscellanies'', iv. 23.150&lt;/ref&gt; and their souls, free from the cycle of reincarnations, are able to rest in happiness for eternity.&lt;ref&gt;Clement of Alexandria, ''Miscellanies'', v. 14.122&lt;/ref&gt;

==Death and literary treatments==
[[File:The Death of Empedocles by Salvator Rosa.jpg|right|thumb|The Death of Empedocles by [[Salvator Rosa]] (1615 – 1673), depicting the legendary alleged suicide of Empedocles jumping into [[Mount Etna]] in [[Sicily]]]]
[[Diogenes Laërtius]] records the legend that Empedocles died by throwing himself into [[Mount Etna]] in Sicily, so that the people would believe his body had vanished and he had turned into an immortal god;&lt;ref&gt;Diogenes Laërtius, viii. 69&lt;/ref&gt; the volcano, however, threw back one of his bronze sandals, revealing the deceit. Another legend maintains that he threw himself into the volcano to prove to his disciples that he was immortal; he believed he would come back as a god after being consumed by the fire. [[Horace]] also refers to the death of Empedocles in his work ''[[Ars Poetica (Horace)|Ars Poetica]]'' and admits poets the [[right to die|right to destroy themselves]].&lt;ref&gt;Horace, ''[[Ars Poetica (Horace)|Ars Poetica]]'', [http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.02.0065%3Acard%3D453 465–466]&lt;/ref&gt;

In ''Icaro-Menippus'', a comedic dialogue written by the second century satirist [[Lucian of Samosata]], Empedocles’ final fate is re-evaluated. Rather than being incinerated in the fires of Mount Etna, he was carried up into the heavens by a volcanic eruption. Although a bit singed by the ordeal, Empedocles survives and continues his life on the Moon, surviving by feeding on dew.

Empedocles' death has inspired two major modern literary treatments. Empedocles' death is the subject of [[Friedrich Hölderlin]]'s play ''Tod des Empedokles'' (''[[The Death of Empedocles]]''), two versions of which were written between the years 1798 and 1800. A third version was made public in 1826. In [[Matthew Arnold]]'s poem ''Empedocles on Etna'', a narrative of the philosopher's last hours before he jumps to his death in the crater first published in 1852, Empedocles predicts:
&lt;poem&gt;
To the elements it came from
Everything will return.
Our bodies to earth,
Our blood to water,
Heat to fire,
Breath to air.
&lt;/poem&gt;

In his ''[[A History of Western Philosophy|History of Western Philosophy]]'', [[Bertrand Russell]] humorously quotes an unnamed poet on the subject&amp;nbsp;– &quot;Great Empedocles, that ardent soul, Leapt into Etna, and was roasted whole.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Bertrand Russell, ''A History of Western Philosophy'', 1946, [https://books.google.com/books?id=Ey94E3sOMA0C&amp;pg=PA60&amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false p. 60]&lt;/ref&gt;

In ''[[J R]]'' by [[William Gaddis]], Karl Marx's famous dictum (&quot;From each according to his abilities, to each according to his needs&quot;) is misattributed to Empedocles.&lt;ref&gt;JR by William Gaddis, Dalkey Archive, 2012&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2006, a massive underwater volcano off the coast of Sicily was named [[Empedocles (volcano)|Empedocles]].&lt;ref&gt;BBC News, [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/5108360.stm ''Underwater volcano found by Italy''], 23 June 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2016, Scottish musician [[Momus (musician)|Momus]] wrote and sang the song &quot;The Death of Empedokles&quot; for his album ''[[Scobberlotchers]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Freeman 2016&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Freeman|first=Zachary|title=Albums|url=http://nowthenmagazine.com/manchester/issue-35/albums/|work=Now Then|date=September 2016|accessdate=24 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[List of vegetarians]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==References==
*{{cite book|last1=Arnold|first1=Matthew|title=Empedocles on Etna, and Other Poems|url=https://archive.org/details/empedoclesonetna00arno|date=1852|publisher=B. Fellows|location=London|ref=harv}}
*{{Cite book|last=Burnet|first=John |authorlink=John Burnet (classicist) |title=Early Greek Philosophy|year=1930 |origyear=1892|publisher=A. &amp; C. Black, Ltd.|location= London | ref=harv}} {{PD-notice}}
*{{cite LotEP |chapter=Empedocles}}
*{{cite book|last1=Sedley|first1=David|title=Lucretius and the Transformation of Greek Wisdom|date=1998|publisher=Cambridge University Press|location=Cambridge|ref=harv}}

==Further reading==
*{{cite book |last=Bakalis |first=Nikolaos |title=Handbook of Greek Philosophy: From Thales to the Stoics |year=2005 |publisher=Trafford |location=Victoria, B.C. |isbn=1-4120-4843-5}}
*{{cite book |last=Burnet |first=John |title=Early Greek Philosophy |year=2003 |origyear=1892 |publisher=Kessinger |location=Whitefish, Mont. |isbn=0-7661-2826-1}}
*{{cite book |last=Gottlieb |first=Anthony |title=The Dream of Reason: A History of Western Philosophy from the Greeks to the Renaissance |year=2000 |publisher=Allen Lane |location=London |isbn=0-7139-9143-7}}
*{{cite book |last=Guthrie |first=W. K. C. |authorlink=W. K. C. Guthrie |title=The Presocratic Tradition from Parmenides to Democritus |editor=A History of Greek Philosophy, vol. 2 |year=1978 |origyear=1965 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |location=Cambridge |isbn=0-521-29421-5}}
*{{cite book |last=Hoffman |first=Eric |authorlink=Eric Hoffman (writer) |title=Presence of Life |year=2018 |publisher=Dos Madres Press |location=Loveland, Ohio |isbn=978-1-948017-16-9}}
*{{cite book |last=Inwood |first=Brad |title=The Poem of Empedocles |year=2001 |edition=rev. |publisher=University of Toronto Press |location=Toronto, ON |isbn=0-8020-4820-X}}
*{{cite book |last=Kingsley |first=Peter |authorlink=Peter Kingsley_%28scholar%29 |title=Ancient Philosophy, Mystery, and Magic: Empedocles and Pythagorean Tradition |year=1995 |publisher=Clarendon Press |location=Oxford |isbn=0-19-814988-3}}
**[http://ccat.sas.upenn.edu/bmcr/1997/97.10.19.html Review by John Bussanich]
**[https://web.archive.org/web/20061007041300/http://www.cs.utk.edu/~mclennan/BA/Kingsley-rev.html Review by John Opsopaus]
**[https://sites.google.com/site/empedoclesacragas/ancient-philosophy-mystery-and-magic Review by J.-C Picot]
*{{cite book |last=Kirk |first=G. S. |authorlink=Geoffrey Kirk |last2=Raven |first2=J.E. |author2-link=John Raven |last3=Schofield |first3=M. |title=The Presocratic Philosophers: A Critical History |year=1983 |edition=2nd |publisher=Cambridge University Press |location=Cambridge |isbn=0-521-25444-2}}
*{{cite book |last=Lambridis |first=Helle |title=Empedocles : a philosophical investigation |year=1976 |publisher=University of Alabama Press |location=Tuscaloosa, AL |isbn=0-8173-6615-6 |url-access=registration |url=https://archive.org/details/empedocles00hell }}
*{{cite book |last=Long |first=A. A. |title=The Cambridge Companion to Early Greek Philosophy |year=1999 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |location=Cambridge |isbn=0-521-44122-6}}
*{{cite book |last=Luchte |first=James |title=Early Greek Thought: Before the Dawn |year=2011 |publisher=Bloomsbury Publishing |location=London |ISBN=978-0567353313}} 
*{{cite book |last=Millerd |first=Clara Elizabeth |title=On the interpretation of Empedocles |year=1908 |publisher=University of Chicago Press |location=Chicago}}
*{{cite book |last=O'Brien |first=D. |title=Empedocles' cosmic cycle: a reconstruction from the fragments and secondary sources |year=1969 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |location=London |isbn=0-521-05855-4}}
*{{cite book |last=Russell |first=Bertrand |authorlink=Bertrand Russell |title=[[A History of Western Philosophy |A History of Western Philosophy, and Its Connection with Political and Social Circumstances from the Earliest Times to the Present Day]] |year=1945 |publisher=Simon and Schuster |location=New York |isbn=0-415-07854-7}}
*{{cite book |last=Wright |first=M. R. |title=Empedocles: The Extant Fragments |year=1995 |edition=new |publisher=Bristol Classical Press |location=London |isbn=1-85399-482-0}}

==External links==
{{Commons category}}
{{Wikiquote}}
{{Wikisource author}}
{{Library resources box |by=yes |onlinebooks=yes |others=yes |about=yes |label=Empedocles
  |viaf= |lccn= |lcheading= |wikititle= }}
*{{cite SEP |url-id=empedocles |title=Empedocles |last=Parry |first=Richard}}
*{{cite IEP |url-id=empedocl |title=Empedocles |last=Campbell |first=Gordon}}
*[http://history.hanover.edu/texts/presoc/emp.html#book1 Empedocles Fragments], translated by Arthur Fairbanks, 1898.
*[https://sites.google.com/site/empedoclesacragas/Home Empedocles] by Jean-Claude Picot with an extended and updated bibliography
*[http://demonax.info/doku.php?id=text:empedocles_fragments Empedocles Fragments] at [http://demonax.info/ demonax.info]
*{{MacTutor Biography|id=Empedocles}}
*{{Internet Archive author |sname=Empedocles}}
*{{Librivox author |id=8591}}

{{Presocratics}}
{{Ancient Greece topics}}
{{Vegetarianism}}
{{Authority control}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2011}}

[[Category:Deaths from fire]]
[[Category:5th-century BC Greek people]]
[[Category:5th-century BC philosophers]]
[[Category:5th-century BC poets]]
[[Category:Ancient Acragantines]]
[[Category:Ancient Greek shamans]]
[[Category:Pluralist philosophers]]
[[Category:Ancient Greek physicists]]
[[Category:Philosophers of Magna Graecia]]
[[Category:Natural philosophers]]
[[Category:Philosophers of science]]
[[Category:Presocratic philosophers]]
[[Category:Philosophers of love]]
[[Category:Sicilian Greeks]]
[[Category:490s BC births]]
[[Category:430s BC deaths]]</text>
      <sha1>elxrafvhc3es3wsyspsiivwjy9vd6to</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
