  <page>
    <title>Ellipsis</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9596</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943372419</id>
      <parentid>943360601</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-03-01T14:41:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Peter M. Brown</username>
        <id>12680084</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 943360601 by [[Special:Contributions/Materialscientist|Materialscientist]] ([[User talk:Materialscientist|talk]]) NOT test or vandalism.  Where the other entries in this row show U+2026 and &amp;amp;hellip; the &quot;Character&quot; entry should not be three periods (U+002E</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{about|the punctuation mark| the syntactic omission of words|Ellipsis (linguistics)|other uses}}
{{distinguish|Ellipse}}
{{short description|Series of dots that indicates omission}}
{{Infobox punctuation mark|mark=…&lt;!-- U+2026 is the most proper way of representing ellipsis, not three periods (they only imitate a proper typographical ligature, which should be used here as a completely accurate reference); see Talk:Ellipsis#The_huge_symbol_in_the_table --&gt;
|name=Ellipsis
|other_names=
|unicode={{unichar|2026|HORIZONTAL ELLIPSIS|html=}}
|variant1=...|caption1=AP format&lt;!--
--&gt;|variant2=.&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;.|caption2=Chicago format&lt;!--
--&gt;|variant3=⋯|caption3=Mid-line ellipsis}}
An '''ellipsis''' (plural '''ellipses'''; from the {{lang-grc|ἔλλειψις}}, {{lang|grc-Latn|élleipsis}}, 'omission' or '[[wikt:ellipsis|falling short]]') is a series of dots (typically three, such as &quot;…&quot;) that usually indicates an intentional omission of a word, sentence, or whole section from a text without altering its original meaning.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title=ellipsis|url=http://www.thefreedictionary.com/ellipsis|journal=The Free Dictionary|access-date=2013-01-25|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121114115735/http://www.thefreedictionary.com/ellipsis|archive-date=2012-11-14|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Opinions differ as to how to render ellipses in printed material. According to the ''[[The Chicago Manual of Style|Chicago Manual of Style]]'', each dot should be separated from its neighbor by a [[non-breaking space]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopedia|title=Ellipses defined |url=https://www.chicagomanualofstyle.org/book/ed17/part2/ch13/psec050.html|encyclopedia=The Chicago Manual of Style Online|year=2010|edition=16th}}&lt;/ref&gt; Such spaces should be omitted, however, according to the [[Associated Press]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bkacontent.com/ap-style-how-to-use-ellipses/|last=Fung|first=Henry|year=2016|title=AP Style: How to Use Ellipses|access-date=2018-12-10|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20181211010236/https://www.bkacontent.com/ap-style-how-to-use-ellipses/|archive-date=2018-12-11|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; A third option, illustrated in the opening sentence of this article, is to use the precomposed [[Unicode]] character with [[Unicode#Architecture and terminology|code point]] U+2026, in which the gaps are not as wide as standard spaces,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://practicaltypography.com/ellipses.html|last=Butterick|first=Matthew|title=Butterick's Practical Typography|edition=2nd|access-date=2018-12-11|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20181214070726/https://practicaltypography.com/ellipses.html|archive-date=2018-12-14|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; though not every font in practice obeys this dictate. It is also not uncommon to see the three dots set extremely tight.

==Background==
{{More citations needed section|date=December 2017}}
The ellipsis is also called a '''suspension point''', '''points of ellipsis''', '''periods of ellipsis''', or ([[colloquialism|colloquially]]) &quot;'''dot-dot-dot'''&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Toner&quot;&gt;{{cite book |first=Anne |last=Toner |title=Ellipsis in English Literature: Signs of Omission |location=Cambridge, England |publisher=Cambridge University Press |date=2015 |page=151}} According to Toner it is difficult to establish when the &quot;dot-dot-dot&quot; phrase was first used. There is an early instance, which is perhaps the first in a piece of fiction, in Virginia Woolf's short story &quot;An Unwritten Novel&quot; (1920).&lt;/ref&gt;

Depending on their context and placement in a sentence, ellipses can indicate an unfinished thought, a leading statement, a slight [[Pausa|pause]], an echoing voice, or a nervous or awkward silence. [[Aposiopesis]] is the use of an ellipsis to trail off into silence—for example: &quot;But I thought he was …&quot; When placed at the beginning or end of a sentence, the ellipsis can also inspire a feeling of melancholy or longing.

The most common form of an ellipsis is a row of three periods or full points&lt;!--Not full stop; the full stop is the role played by the full point in terminating a sentence.--&gt; (...) or a precomposed triple-dot glyph (...). The usage of the [[em dash]] (—) can overlap the usage of the ellipsis, especially in dialogue. Style guides often have their own rules governing the use of ellipses. For example, ''[[The Chicago Manual of Style]]'' (''Chicago'' style) recommends that an ellipsis be formed by typing three periods, each with a space on both sides (&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;), while the ''[[Associated Press Stylebook]]'' (''AP'' style) puts the dots together, but retains a space before and after the group.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Em Dashes and Ellipses: Closed or Spaced Out? |first=Karen |last=Yin |work=AP vs Chicago: Edit or Die |publisher=Quiet Press |date=2011 |url=https://apvschicago.com/2011/05/em-dashes-and-ellipses-closed-or-spaced.html |access-date=27 July 2018 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180727212304/https://apvschicago.com/2011/05/em-dashes-and-ellipses-closed-or-spaced.html |archive-date=27 July 2018 |url-status=live |df=dmy-all }} {{better source|date=July 2018|reason=Just some blog; better to get this from official AP materials, but this will do for now.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Whether an ellipsis at the end of a sentence needs a fourth dot to finish the sentence is a matter of debate; ''Chicago'' advises it,&lt;ref&gt;''The Chicago Manual of Style'', 17th edition (2017), §&amp;thinsp;13.51–52.&lt;/ref&gt; as does the ''[[Publication Manual of the American Psychological Association]]'' (APA style),&lt;ref&gt;Summarized here: {{cite web |first=Paige |last=Jackson |title=Ellipses–When and How? |date=22 April 2011 |work=Blog.APAStyle.org |publisher=[[American Psychological Association]] |url= http://blog.apastyle.org/apastyle/2011/04/ellipses-when-and-how.html |url-status=live |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20171210122450/http://blog.apastyle.org/apastyle/2011/04/ellipses-when-and-how.html |archive-date=10 December 2017 |access-date=27 July 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; while some other style guides do not;{{citation needed|date=July 2018|reason=Should be easy to source, but we need to actually do it.}} the ''[[Merriam-Webster]] Dictionary'' and related works treat this style as optional, saying that it &quot;may&quot; be used.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Usage Notes: All About Ellipses – It's time to stop calling them 'dot dot dot' |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |date=2017 |work=Merriam-Webster.com |publisher=[[Merriam-Webster]] |url= https://www.merriam-webster.com/words-at-play/ellipses-definition-uses |url-status=live |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20170531171513/https://www.merriam-webster.com/words-at-play/ellipses-definition-uses |archive-date=31 May 2017 |access-date=27 July 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; More commonly, a normal full stop (period) terminates the sentence, then a {{em|separate}} three-dot ellipsis is used to indicate one or more subsequent elided sentences before continuing a longer quotation. ''[[Business Insider]]'' magazine suggests this style,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Here's how to use the four-dot ellipsis like a pro |first=Melia |last=Robinson |date=30 April 2016 |work=BusinessInsider.com |publisher=[[Insider Inc.]] / [[Axel Springer SE]] |url= https://www.businessinsider.com/when-to-use-the-four-dot-ellipsis-2016-4 |url-status=live |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20171224064651/https://www.businessinsider.com/when-to-use-the-four-dot-ellipsis-2016-4 |archive-date=24 December 2017 |access-date=27 July 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; and it is also used in many [[academic journal]]s. Even the ''[[Associated Press Stylebook]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Using AP Style Ellipses Correctly |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |date=5 December 2017 |work=WordAgents.com |location=Lindenhurst, New York |publisher=Word Agents |url=http://wordagents.com/ap-style-ellipses/ |access-date=27 July 2018 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180727212231/http://wordagents.com/ap-style-ellipses/ |archive-date=27 July 2018 |url-status=live |df=dmy-all }} {{better source|date=July 2018|reason=Just some blog; better to get this from official AP materials, but this will do for now.}}&lt;/ref&gt; – notably hostile to punctuation that journalists may consider optional and removable to save newsprint column width – favors this approach. It is consistent in intent if not exact form with the agreement among those in favor of a fused four-dot ellipsis that the first of them is a full stop terminating the sentence and the other three are the ellipsis.

==In writing==
In her book on the ellipsis, ''Ellipsis in English Literature: Signs of Omission'' (Cambridge University Press, 2015), Anne Toner suggests that the first use of the punctuation in the English language dates to a 1588 translation of [[Terence]]'s ''[[Andria (comedy)|Andria]]'', by [[Maurice Kyffin]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Toner&quot; /&gt; In this case, however, the ellipsis consists not of dots but of short dashes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.cam.ac.uk/research/features/dot-dot-dot-how-the-ellipsis-made-its-mark |first=Alex |last=Buxton |title=… dot, dot, dot: How the ellipsis made its mark |work= Research |date=21 October 2015 |location=Cambridge, England |publisher=[[Cambridge University]] |url-status=live |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20180104063312/https://www.cam.ac.uk/research/features/dot-dot-dot-how-the-ellipsis-made-its-mark |archive-date=4 January 2018 |access-date=27 July 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;Subpuncting&quot; of [[medieval]] manuscripts also denotes omitted meaning and may be related.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=McNabb |first=Cameron Hunt |title=The Mysterious History of the Ellipsis, From Medieval Subpuncting to Irrational Numbers |url=http://www.slate.com/blogs/lexicon_valley/2016/08/17/the_ellipsis_in_medieval_manuscripts_how_subpuncting_in_the_middle_ages.html |access-date=18 August 2016 |work=[[Slate (magazine)|Slate]] |date=17 August 2016 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160818080323/http://www.slate.com/blogs/lexicon_valley/2016/08/17/the_ellipsis_in_medieval_manuscripts_how_subpuncting_in_the_middle_ages.html |archive-date=18 August 2016 |url-status=live |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 19th and early 20th centuries, an ellipsis was often used when a writer intentionally omitted a specific proper noun, such as a location: &quot;Jan was born on .&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;Street in Warsaw.&quot;{{Citation needed|date=January 2018}}

As commonly used, this juxtaposition of characters is referred to as &quot;dots of ellipsis&quot; in the English language.&lt;ref name=&quot;HumezHumez2008&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Humez|first1=Alexander|last2=Humez|first2=Nicholas|title=On the Dot: The Speck that Changed the World|date=2 October 2008|isbn=9780190295943|chapter-url=https://www.amazon.com/gp/search?index=books&amp;linkCode=qs&amp;keywords=9780190295943|accessdate=11 August 2016|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160811003951/https://www.amazon.com/gp/search?index=books&amp;linkCode=qs&amp;keywords=9780190295943|archivedate=11 August 2016|chapter=Chapter 7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Occasionally, it would be used in pulp fiction and other works of early 20th-century fiction to denote expletives that would otherwise have been censored.&lt;ref&gt;Raymond Chandler, Frank MacShane. ''Raymond Chandler: Stories and Early Novels''. First Edition. [[New York City|New York]]: [[Library of America]]. 1995. ''Note on the Texts''.&lt;/ref&gt;

An ellipsis may also imply an unstated alternative indicated by context. For example, when Sue says &quot;I never drink wine&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;&quot;, the implication is that she does drink something else{{mdash}}such as vodka.

In reported speech, the ellipsis can be used to represent an intentional silence.

In poetry, an ellipsis is used as a thought-pause or [[Line break (poetry)|line break]] at the [[caesura]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://classroom.synonym.com/ellipses-poem-3994.html|title=What Are Ellipses in a Poem?|accessdate=12 January 2018|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160305173518/http://classroom.synonym.com/ellipses-poem-3994.html|archive-date=5 March 2016|url-status=live|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; or this is used to highlight sarcasm or make the reader think about the last points in the poem.

In news reporting, often associated with [[brackets]], it is used to indicate that a quotation has been condensed for space, brevity or relevance.

[[Herb Caen]], Pulitzer-prize-winning columnist for the ''San Francisco Chronicle'', became famous for his &quot;three-dot journalism&quot;.&lt;ref name=Caen&gt;[http://www.deseretnews.com/article/492296/HERB-CAEN-WAY----HONORS-SF-COLUMNIST.html `HERB CAEN WAY . . .' HONORS S.F. COLUMNIST] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170905231945/http://www.deseretnews.com/article/492296/HERB-CAEN-WAY----HONORS-SF-COLUMNIST.html |date=2017-09-05 }}, in the ''[[Deseret News]]''; published May 29, 1996; retrieved September 5, 2017&lt;/ref&gt;

==In different languages==
{{anchor|In English|reason=Ellipsis in English redirects here.}}

===In American English===
''[[The Chicago Manual of Style]]'' suggests the use of an ellipsis for any omitted word, phrase, line, or paragraph from within but not at the end of a quoted passage. There are two commonly used methods of using ellipses: one uses three dots for any omission, while the second one makes a distinction between omissions within a sentence (using three dots:&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;.) and omissions between sentences (using a period and a space followed by three dots:&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;...).

The [[Modern Language Association]] (MLA) used to indicate that an ellipsis must include spaces before and after each dot in all uses. If an ellipsis is meant to represent an omission, [[square bracket]]s must surround the ellipsis to make it clear that there was no pause in the original quote: [&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;]. Currently, the MLA has removed the requirement of brackets in its style handbooks. However, some maintain that the use of brackets is still correct because it clears confusion.&lt;ref&gt;Fowler, H. Ramsey, Jane E. Aaron, Murray McArthur. ''The Little, Brown Handbook''. Fourth Canadian Edition. [[Toronto]]: [[Longman|Pearson Longman]]. 2005. p. 440.&lt;/ref&gt;

The MLA now indicates that a three-dot, spaced ellipsis (&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;) should be used for removing material from within one sentence within a quote. When crossing sentences (when the omitted text contains a period, so that omitting the end of a sentence counts), a four-dot, spaced (except for before the first dot) ellipsis (.&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;) should be used. When ellipsis points are used in the original text, ellipsis points that are not in the original text should be distinguished by enclosing them in square brackets (e.g. &quot;text […] text&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.uhv.edu/student-success-center/resources/e-p/ellipsis-use-in-mla-style/|last=Jones|first=Karalyn|title=Using Ellipsis in MLA Style|institution=[[University of Houston–Victoria]]|year=2009|access-date=2018-06-08|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180612140911/https://www.uhv.edu/student-success-center/resources/e-p/ellipsis-use-in-mla-style/|archive-date=2018-06-12|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://naropa.edu/documents/programs/jks/naropa-writing-center/citation-comparison.pdf |title=Archived copy |access-date=2016-06-05 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160804045039/http://naropa.edu/documents/programs/jks/naropa-writing-center/citation-comparison.pdf |archive-date=2016-08-04 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the Associated Press, the ellipsis should be used to condense quotations. It is less commonly used to indicate a pause in speech or an unfinished thought or to separate items in material such as show business gossip. The stylebook indicates that if the shortened sentence before the mark can stand as a sentence, it should do so, with an ellipsis placed after the period or other ending punctuation. When material is omitted at the end of a paragraph and also immediately following it, an ellipsis goes both at the end of that paragraph and at the beginning of the next, according to this style.&lt;ref&gt;Goldstein, Norm, editor. &quot;Associated Press Stylebook and Briefing on Media Law&quot;. 2005. pp.328–329.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Robert Bringhurst's ''[[Elements of Typographic Style]]'', the details of typesetting ellipses depend on the character and size of the font being set and the typographer's preference. Bringhurst writes that a full space between each dot is &quot;another Victorian eccentricity. In most contexts, the Chicago ellipsis is much too wide&quot;—he recommends using flush dots, or [[thin space|''thin''-spaced]] dots (up to one-fifth of an [[em (typography)|em]]), or the prefabricated ellipsis character ({{unichar|2026|HORIZONTAL ELLIPSIS|html=}}. Bringhurst suggests that normally an ellipsis should be spaced fore-and-aft to separate it from the text, but when it combines with other punctuation, the leading space disappears and the other punctuation follows. This is the usual practice in typesetting. He provides the following examples:

{| summary=&quot;six examples of setting ellipsis&quot; style=&quot;margin-left:3em;&quot;
|-
| style=&quot;width:5em;&quot; | i&amp;nbsp;... j
| style=&quot;width:5em;&quot; | k....
| style=&quot;width:5em;&quot; | l..., l
| style=&quot;width:5em;&quot; | l,&amp;nbsp;... l
| style=&quot;width:5em;&quot; | m...?
| style=&quot;width:5em;&quot; | n...!
|}

In legal writing in the United States, Rule 5.3 in the ''[[Bluebook]]'' citation guide governs the use of ellipses and requires a space before the first dot and between the two subsequent dots. If an ellipsis ends the sentence, then there are three dots, each separated by a space, followed by the final punctuation (e.g. Hah . . . ?). In some legal writing, an ellipsis is written as three [[asterisk]]s (*** or *&amp;nbsp;*&amp;nbsp;*) to make it obvious that text has been omitted.
(...) is also used for awkward silence.

===In British English===

''The [[Hart's Rules|Oxford Style Guide]]'' recommends setting the ellipsis as a single character (…) or as a series of three (narrow) spaced dots (.&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;.), and surrounding it by spaces. If there is an ellipsis at the end of an incomplete sentence, the final full stop is omitted. However, it is retained if the following ellipsis represents an omission between two complete sentences.&lt;ref&gt;''New Hart's Rules: The Oxford Style Guide''. 2nd ed. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

: ''The … fox jumps …''
: ''The quick brown fox jumps over the lazy dog. … And if they have not died, they are still alive today.''

Contrary to ''The Oxford Style Guide'', the ''University of Oxford Style Guide'' demands an ellipsis not to be surrounded by spaces, except when it stands for a pause; then, a space has to be set after the ellipsis (but not before). An ellipsis is never preceded or followed by a full stop.&lt;ref&gt;''[https://www.ox.ac.uk/sites/files/oxford/University%20of%20Oxford%20Style%20Guide%20%28updated%20Hilary%20term%202016%29.pdf University of Oxford Style Guide: Hilary term 2016] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170202030344/https://www.ox.ac.uk/sites/files/oxford/University%20of%20Oxford%20Style%20Guide%20%28updated%20Hilary%20term%202016%29.pdf |date=2017-02-02 }}'' (PDF). Oxford: University of Oxford, 2016. p. 15. Retrieved 18 May 2017.&lt;/ref&gt;

: ''The…fox jumps…''
: ''The quick brown fox jumps over the lazy dog…And if they have not died, they are still alive today.''
: ''It is not cold… it is freezing cold.''

===In Polish===
When applied in [[Polish language]] syntax, the ellipsis is called {{lang|pl|wielokropek}}, which means &quot;multidot&quot;. The word ''wielokropek'' distinguishes the ellipsis of Polish syntax from that of [[mathematical notation]], in which it is known as an {{lang|pl|elipsa}}.

When an ellipsis replaces a fragment omitted from a quotation, the ellipsis is enclosed in parentheses or square brackets. An unbracketed ellipsis indicates an interruption or pause in speech.

The syntactical rules for ellipses are standardized by the 1983 Polska Norma document [[PN-83/P-55366]], {{lang|pl|Zasady składania tekstów w języku polskim}} (&quot;Rules for setting texts in the Polish Language&quot;).

===In Russian===
The combination &quot;ellipsis+period&quot; is replaced by the ellipsis. The combinations &quot;ellipsis+exclamation mark&quot; and &quot;ellipsis+question mark&quot; are written in this way: !.. ?..

===In Japanese===
The most common character corresponding to an ellipsis is called ''3''-ten rīdā (&quot;''3''-dot leaders&quot;, {{lang|ja|…}}). 2-ten rīdā exists as a character, but it is used less commonly. In writing, the ellipsis consists usually of six dots (two ''3''-ten rīdā characters, {{lang|ja|……}}). Three dots (one ''3''-ten rīdā character) may be used where space is limited, such as in a header. However, variations in the number of dots exist. In horizontally written text the dots are commonly vertically centered within the text height (between the [[Baseline (typography)|baseline]] and the ascent line), as in the standard Japanese [[Microsoft Windows|Windows]] fonts; in vertically written text the dots are always centered horizontally. As the Japanese word for dot is pronounced &quot;{{lang|ja-Latn|ten}}&quot;, the dots are colloquially called &quot;{{lang|ja-Latn|ten-ten-ten}}&quot; ({{lang|ja|てんてんてん}}, akin to the English &quot;dot dot dot&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.sanspo.com/geino/news/20170605/geo17060514190023-n1.html |title=秋元順子、古希に得意のダジャレ　「あまり&quot;コキ&quot;使わないでください」 |date=2017-06-05 |website=SANSPO.COM |publisher=SANKEI DIGITAL Inc. |access-date=2018-01-10 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190309024932/https://www.sanspo.com/geino/news/20170605/geo17060514190023-n1.html |archive-date=2019-03-09 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In text in Japanese media, such as in [[manga]] or video games, ellipses are much more frequent than in English, and are often changed to another punctuation sign in translation. The ellipsis by itself represents speechlessness, or a &quot;[[pregnant pause]]&quot;. Depending on the context, this could be anything from an admission of guilt to an expression of being dumbfounded at another person's words or actions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Mandelin |first1=Clyde |title=Legends of Localization: How Japanese Ellipsis Usage Compares with English |url=https://legendsoflocalization.com/qa-japanese-ellipsis-usage-and-english-translation/ |website=Legends of Localization |accessdate=14 December 2018 |language=en |date=8 September 2013 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20181214164227/https://legendsoflocalization.com/qa-japanese-ellipsis-usage-and-english-translation/ |archive-date=14 December 2018 |url-status=live |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; As a device, the ''ten-ten-ten'' is intended to focus the reader on a character while allowing the character to not speak any dialogue. This conveys to the reader a focus of the narrative &quot;camera&quot; on the silent subject, implying an expectation of some motion or action. It is not unheard of to see inanimate objects &quot;speaking&quot; the ellipsis.

===In Chinese===
In [[Chinese language|Chinese]], the ellipsis is six dots (in two groups of three dots, occupying the same horizontal or vertical space as two characters) (i.e. &lt;span lang=&quot;zh&quot;&gt;......&lt;/span&gt;).&lt;ref&gt;[[:zh-tw:省略号|省略号]]&lt;/ref&gt;

===In Spanish===
In [[Spanish language|Spanish]], ellipsis is commonly used as a substitute of ''[[et cetera]]'' at the end of unfinished lists. So it means &quot;and so forth&quot; or &quot;and other things&quot;.

Other use is the suspension of a part of a text, or a paragraph, or a phrase or a part of a word because it is obvious, or unnecessary, or implied. For instance, sometimes the ellipsis is used to avoid the complete use of expletives.

When the ellipsis is placed alone into a [[Bracket|parenthesis]] (...) or—less often—between [[bracket]]s [...], which is what happens usually within a text [[Transcription (linguistics)|transcription]], it means the original text had more contents on the same position but are not useful to our target in the transcription. When the suppressed text is at the beginning or at the end of a text, the ellipsis does not need to be placed in a parenthesis.

The number of dots is three and only three.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Puntos suspensivos |url=http://lema.rae.es/dpd?id=c5GublcDAD6kWvCUUy |website=RAE |access-date=2019-01-21 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190122094659/http://lema.rae.es/dpd/?id=c5GublcDAD6kWvCUUy |archive-date=2019-01-22 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===In French===
In [[French language|French]], the ellipsis is commonly used at the end of lists to represent ''et cetera''. In French typography, the ellipsis is written close up to the preceding word but has a space after it, for example: ''comme ça… pas comme ceci''. If, exceptionally, it begins a sentence, there is a space before and after, for example: ''Lui ? … vaut rien, je crois… ''.

However, any omitted word, phrase or line at the end of a quoted passage would be indicated like this: [...] (space before and after the square brackets but not inside), for example: '' … à Paris, Nice, Nantes, Toulouse […] ''.

===In German===
In [[German language|German]], the ellipsis in general is surrounded by spaces, if it stands for one or more omitted words. On the other side there is no space between a letter or (part of) a word and an ellipsis, if it stands for one or more omitted letters, that should stick to the written letter or letters.

Example for both cases, using German style: ''The first el…is stands for omitted letters, the second … for an omitted word.''

If the ellipsis is at the end of a sentence, the final full stop is omitted.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.rechtschreibrat.com/DOX/rfdr_regeln_inkl_Nachtraegen.pdf |title=Deutsche Rechtschreibung. Regeln und Wörterverzeichnis |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |date=2010 |publisher=Rat für deutsche Rechtschreibung |access-date=2015-10-18 |quote=$ 100: Stehen die Auslassungspunkte am Ende eines Ganzsatzes, so setzt man keinen Satzschlusspunkt. |page=100 |language=German |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170426151612/http://www.rechtschreibrat.com/DOX/rfdr_regeln_inkl_Nachtraegen.pdf |archive-date=2017-04-26 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Example: ''I think that …''

==Usage in menus==
[[Image:Menu (computing) example.PNG|thumb|A [[drop-down menu]] of [[file operation]]s]]
In computer [[Menu (computing)|menu functions]] or [[button]]s, an ellipsis means that upon selection more options (sometimes in the form of a [[dialog box]]) will be displayed, where the user can or must make a choice.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://developer.apple.com/macos/human-interface-guidelines/menus/menu-anatomy/ |title=developer.apple.com: Menu and Menu Item Titles |access-date=2018-01-31 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180131140912/https://developer.apple.com/macos/human-interface-guidelines/menus/menu-anatomy/ |archive-date=2018-01-31 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt; If the ellipsis is missing, the function is immediately executed upon selection.

E.g., the menu item &quot;Save&quot; indicates that the file will be overwritten without further input, whereas &quot;Save as…&quot; indicates that a dialog follows where the user can, for example, select another location, file name, or format.

Ellipsis are also used as a separate button (particularly considering the limited screen area of [[mobile app]]s) to represent partially or completely hidden options. This usage may alternatively be described as a &quot;More button&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://medium.com/@jsaito/the-mighty-ellipsis-6c2c00ddc864 |title=The Mighty Ellipsis - How 3 little dots can say so much|access-date=2019-11-06 |url-status=live |date=2016-09-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; (see also [[hamburger button]] signifying completely hidden options).

In mobile, web, and general application design, the vertical ellipses ⋮ is sometimes used as an interface element, where it is sometimes called a kebab icon. The element typically indicates that a navigation menu can be accessed when the element is activated.

==In mathematical notation==
An ellipsis is also often used in [[mathematics]] to mean &quot;and so forth&quot;. In a list, between commas, or following a comma, a normal ellipsis is used, as in:

: &lt;math&gt;1,2,3,\ldots,100&lt;/math&gt;

or to mean an infinite list, as:

: &lt;math&gt;1,2,3,\ldots&lt;/math&gt;

To indicate the omission of values in a repeated operation, an ellipsis raised to the center of the line is used between two operation symbols or following the last operation symbol, as in:

: &lt;math&gt;1+2+3+\cdots+100&lt;/math&gt;

Sometimes, e.g. in Russian mathematical texts, normal, non-raised, ellipses are used even in repeated summations.&lt;ref&gt;Мильчин А. Э. [http://slovari.yandex.ru/~книги/Издательский%20словарь/Многоточие%20в%20математических%20формулах/ Издательский словарь-справочник] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150326175211/https://slovari.yandex.ru/~%D0%BA%D0%BD%D0%B8%D0%B3%D0%B8/%D0%98%D0%B7%D0%B4%D0%B0%D1%82%D0%B5%D0%BB%D1%8C%D1%81%D0%BA%D0%B8%D0%B9%20%D1%81%D0%BB%D0%BE%D0%B2%D0%B0%D1%80%D1%8C/%D0%9C%D0%BD%D0%BE%D0%B3%D0%BE%D1%82%D0%BE%D1%87%D0%B8%D0%B5%20%D0%B2%20%D0%BC%D0%B0%D1%82%D0%B5%D0%BC%D0%B0%D1%82%D0%B8%D1%87%D0%B5%D1%81%D0%BA%D0%B8%D1%85%20%D1%84%D0%BE%D1%80%D0%BC%D1%83%D0%BB%D0%B0%D1%85/ |date=2015-03-26 }}.— Изд. 3-е, испр. и доп., Электронное — М.: ОЛМА-Пресс, 2006. (in Russian)&lt;/ref&gt;

The latter formula means the sum of all [[natural number]]s from 1 to 100. However, it is not a formally defined [[mathematical symbol]]. Repeated summations or products may similarly be denoted using [[Capital sigma notation|capital sigma]] and [[capital pi notation]], respectively:

: &lt;math&gt;1+2+3+\cdots+100\ = \sum_{n=1}^{100} n = 100?&lt;/math&gt; (see [[termial]])
: &lt;math&gt;1 \times 2 \times 3 \times \cdots \times 100\ = \prod_{n=1}^{100} n = 100!&lt;/math&gt; (see [[factorial]])

Normally dots should be used only where the pattern to be followed is clear, the exception being to show the indefinite continuation of an [[irrational number]] such as:

: &lt;math&gt;\pi=3.14159265\ldots&lt;/math&gt;

Sometimes, it is useful to display a formula compactly, for example:

: &lt;math&gt;1+4+9+\cdots+n^2+\cdots+400&lt;/math&gt;

Another example is the set of positive [[Root of a function|zeros]] of the [[cosine]] [[Function (mathematics)|function]]:

: &lt;math&gt;\left\{\frac{\pi}{2}, \frac{3\pi}{2}, \frac{5\pi}{2}, \ldots \right\}&lt;/math&gt;

There are many related uses of the ellipsis in [[set notation]].

The diagonal and vertical forms of the ellipsis are particularly useful for showing missing terms in [[Matrix (mathematics)|matrices]], such as the size-''n'' [[identity matrix]]:

: &lt;math&gt;I_n = \begin{bmatrix}1 &amp; 0 &amp; \cdots &amp; 0 \\0 &amp; 1 &amp; \cdots &amp; 0 \\\vdots &amp; \vdots &amp; \ddots &amp; \vdots \\0 &amp; 0 &amp; \cdots &amp; 1 \end{bmatrix}&lt;/math&gt;

==Computer science==
===Programming languages===
A two- or three-dot ellipsis is used as an [[operator (programming)|operator]] in some [[programming language]]s. The precise meaning varies by language, but it generally involves something dealing with multiple items. One of its most common uses is in defining ranges or sequences. This is used in many languages, including Pascal, Modula, Oberon, Ada, Haskell, Perl, Python, Ruby, Bash shell and F#. It is also used to indicate so called [[variadic function]]s in the C, C++ and Java languages. ''See [[Ellipsis (programming operator)]]''.

===HTML and CSS===
The CSS &lt;code&gt;text-overflow&lt;/code&gt; property can be set to &lt;code&gt;ellipsis&lt;/code&gt;, which cuts off text with an ellipsis when it overflows the content area.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/CSS/text-overflow|title=text-overflow|website=Mozilla Developer Network|accessdate=12 January 2018|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180111172018/https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/CSS/text-overflow|archive-date=11 January 2018|url-status=live|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://drafts.csswg.org/css-ui-3/#text-overflow|title=CSS Basic User Interface Module Level 3 (CSS3 UI)|website=drafts.csswg.org|accessdate=12 January 2018|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180111171232/https://drafts.csswg.org/css-ui-3/#text-overflow|archive-date=11 January 2018|url-status=live|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==On the Internet and in text messaging==
The ellipsis is a non-verbal cue that is often used in computer-mediated interactions, in particular in synchronous genres, such as chat. The reason behind its popularity is the fact that it allows people to indicate in writing several functions:
* The sign of ellipsis can function as a floor holding device, and signal that more is to come, for instance when people break up longer turns in chat.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Simpson|first=J|title=Meaning-making online: Discourse and CMC in a Language learning community|journal=Recent Research Developments in Learning Technologies|year=2005|citeseerx = 10.1.1.108.463}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Dot-dot-dot can be used systematically to enact linguistic politeness, for instance indicating topic change or hesitation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Erika|first=Darics|title=Relational work in synchronous text-based CMC of virtual teams|journal=Handbook of Research on Discourse Behavior and Digital Communication: Language Structures and Social Interaction|year=2010|url=http://eprints.port.ac.uk/3682/|access-date=2012-07-09|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140405090849/http://eprints.port.ac.uk/3682/|archive-date=2014-04-05|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Suspension dots can be [[turn construction unit]]s to signal silence, for example when indicating disagreement, disapproval or confusion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Ong|first=Kenneth Keng Wee|title=Disagreement, Confusion, Disapproval, Turn Elicitation and Floor Holding: Actions accomplished by Ellipsis Marks-Only Turns and Blank Turns in Quasisynchronous Chat|journal=Discourse Studies|year=2011|volume=13|issue=2|pages=211–234|doi=10.1177/1461445610392138}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although an ellipsis is technically complete with three periods (...), its rise in popularity as a &quot;trailing-off&quot; or &quot;silence&quot; indicator, particularly in mid-20th-century comic strip and comic book prose writing, has led to expanded uses online. Today, extended ellipsis anywhere from two to dozens of periods have become common constructions in Internet chat rooms and text messages.&lt;ref name=dots&gt;{{cite conference|url=http://ucblibraries.colorado.edu/facultyprofiles/files/publications/ADmanessj/Maness--The%20Power%20of%20Dots%28personal%29.pdf|title=The Power of Dots: Using Nonverbal Compensators in Chat Reference|first=Jack M.|last=Maness|year=2007|conference=Annual Meeting of ASIS&amp;T|conferenceurl=http://www.asis.org/Conferences/AM07/|booktitle=Proceedings of the 2007 Annual Meeting of ASIS&amp;T|publisher=University Libraries − [[University of Colorado at Boulder]]|accessdate=24 October 2011|doi=10.1002/meet.1450440341|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121203091642/http://ucblibraries.colorado.edu/facultyprofiles/files/publications/ADmanessj/Maness--The%20Power%20of%20Dots%28personal%29.pdf|archive-date=3 December 2012|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; The extent of repetition in itself might serve as an additional contextualization or paralinguistic cue, to &quot;extend the lexical meaning of the words, add character to the sentences, and allow fine-tuning and personalisation of the message&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Kalman |first=Yoram M |last2=Gergle |first2=Darren |title=CMC cues enrich lean online communication: the case of letter and punctuation mark repetitions |url=http://www.kalmans.com/MCIS2010Cues.pdf |accessdate=9 July 2012 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131208021439/http://www.kalmans.com/MCIS2010Cues.pdf |archive-date=8 December 2013 |url-status=live |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Computer representations==
In [[computing]], several ellipsis [[character (computing)|characters]] have been codified, depending on the system used.

In the [[Unicode]] standard, there are the following characters:
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Name !! Character !! Unicode !! UTF-8 !! [[HTML entity]] name or&lt;br/&gt;[[Numeric character reference]] !! Use
|-
| Horizontal ellipsis || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| &amp;hellip; || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| U+2026 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 0xE2 0x80 0xA6 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| &lt;code&gt;&amp;amp;hellip;&lt;/code&gt; || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| General
|-
| [[Lao language|Laotian]] ellipsis || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| ຯ || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| U+0EAF || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 0xE0 0xBA 0xAF || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| &lt;code&gt;&amp;amp;#x0EAF;&lt;/code&gt; || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| General
|-
| [[Mongolian language|Mongolian]] ellipsis || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| ᠁ || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| U+1801 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 0xE1 0xA0 0x81 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| &lt;code&gt;&amp;amp;#x1801;&lt;/code&gt; || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| General
|-
| [[Thai language|Thai]] ellipsis || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| ฯ || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| U+0E2F || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 0xE0 0xB8 0xAF || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| &lt;code&gt;&amp;amp;#x0E2F;&lt;/code&gt; || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| General
|-
| Vertical ellipsis || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| ⋮ || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| U+22EE || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 0xE2 0x8B 0xAE || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| &lt;code&gt;&amp;amp;vellip;&lt;/code&gt; || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| Mathematics
|-
| Midline horizontal ellipsis || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| ⋯ || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| U+22EF || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 0xE2 0x8B 0xAF || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| &lt;code&gt;&amp;amp;#x22EF;&lt;/code&gt; || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| Mathematics
|-
| Up-right diagonal ellipsis || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| ⋰ || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| U+22F0 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 0xE2 0x8B 0xB0 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| &lt;code&gt;&amp;amp;#x22F0;&lt;/code&gt; || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| Mathematics
|-
| Down-right diagonal ellipsis || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| ⋱ || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| U+22F1 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 0xE2 0x8B 0xB1 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| &lt;code&gt;&amp;amp;#x22F1;&lt;/code&gt; || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| Mathematics
|-
| Presentation form for vertical horizontal ellipsis || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| ︙ || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| U+FE19 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 0xEF 0xB8 0x99 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| &lt;code&gt;&amp;amp;#xFE19;&lt;/code&gt; || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| Vertical form
|}

In Windows, the horizontal ellipsis can be inserted with {{key press|Alt|0}}{{key press|1}}{{key press|3}}{{key press|3}}, using the numeric keypad.

In macOS, it can be inserted with {{key press|Opt|;}} (on an English language keyboard).

In some Linux distributions, it can be inserted with {{key press|AltGr|.}}, or alternatively {{key press|[[Compose key|Compose]]}} {{key press|.}} {{key press|.}} sequence can be used.

In [[Chinese language|Chinese]] and sometimes in [[Japanese language|Japanese]], ellipsis characters are made by entering two consecutive ''horizontal ellipses'', each with [[Unicode]] code point U+2026. In vertical texts, the application should rotate the symbol accordingly.

Unicode recognizes a series of three [[full stop|period]] characters (U+002E) as [[Unicode equivalence|compatibility equivalent (though not canonical)]] to the horizontal ellipsis character.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.unicode.org/Public/UNIDATA/UnicodeData.txt UnicodeData.txt] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180322180511/http://www.unicode.org/Public/UNIDATA/UnicodeData.txt |date=2018-03-22 }}: &lt;code&gt;2026;HORIZONTAL ELLIPSIS;Po;0;ON;&amp;lt;compat&amp;gt; 002E 002E 002E;;;;N;;;;;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[HTML]], the horizontal ellipsis character may be represented by the entity reference &lt;code&gt;&amp;amp;hellip;&lt;/code&gt; (since HTML 4.0), and the vertical ellipsis character by the entity reference &lt;code&gt;&amp;amp;vellip;&lt;/code&gt; (since HTML 5.0).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.w3.org/TR/2011/WD-html5-20110113/named-character-references.html#entity-vellip |title=W3C Working Draft: HTML5: 8.5 Named character references |year=2011 |accessdate=2012-11-08 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121123052235/http://www.w3.org/TR/2011/WD-html5-20110113/named-character-references.html#entity-vellip |archive-date=2012-11-23 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt; Alternatively, in HTML, [[XML]], and [[SGML]], a [[numeric character reference]] such as &lt;code&gt;&amp;amp;#x2026;&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;&amp;amp;#8230;&lt;/code&gt; can be used.

In the [[TeX]] typesetting system, the following types of ellipsis are available:
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
! Name !! Glyph !! TeX markup
|-
| Lower ellipsis
| style=&quot;text-align:center; vertical-align:bottom;&quot;| &lt;math&gt;\ldots&lt;/math&gt;
| &lt;code&gt;\ldots&lt;/code&gt;
|-
| Centred ellipsis
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| &lt;math&gt;\cdots&lt;/math&gt;
| &lt;code&gt;\cdots&lt;/code&gt;
|-
| Diagonal ellipsis
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| &lt;math&gt;\ddots&lt;/math&gt;
| &lt;code&gt;\ddots&lt;/code&gt;
|-
| Vertical ellipsis
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| &lt;math&gt;\vdots&lt;/math&gt;
| &lt;code&gt;\vdots&lt;/code&gt;
|}

In [[LaTeX]], note that the reverse orientation of &lt;code&gt;\ddots&lt;/code&gt; can be achieved with &lt;code&gt;\reflectbox&lt;/code&gt; provided by the &lt;code&gt;graphicx&lt;/code&gt; package: &lt;code&gt;\reflectbox{\ddots}&lt;/code&gt; yields [[File:Iddots black.svg|18px]].

With the &lt;code&gt;amsmath&lt;/code&gt; package from [[AMS-Latex|AMS-LaTeX]], more specific ellipses are provided for math mode.&lt;ref&gt;[ftp://ftp.ams.org/pub/tex/doc/amsmath/amsldoc.pdf#page=16 ''User's Guide for the &lt;code&gt;amsmath&lt;/code&gt; Package'']. American Mathematical Society, 1999, p. 12.&lt;/ref&gt;
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Markup !! Usage || Example || Output
|-
| &lt;code&gt;\dotsc&lt;/code&gt; || dots with commas || &lt;code&gt;1, 2, \dotsc , 9&lt;/code&gt; || &lt;math&gt;1, 2, \dotsc , 9&lt;/math&gt;
|-
| &lt;code&gt;\dotsb&lt;/code&gt; || dots with binary operators/relations || &lt;code&gt;1 + 2 + \dotsb + 9&lt;/code&gt; || &lt;math&gt;1 + 2 + \dotsb + 9&lt;/math&gt;
|-
| &lt;code&gt;\dotsm&lt;/code&gt; || dots with multiplication || &lt;code&gt;A_1 A_2 \dotsm A_9&lt;/code&gt; || &lt;math&gt;A_1 A_2 \dotsm A_9&lt;/math&gt;
|-
| &lt;code&gt;\dotsi&lt;/code&gt; || dots with integrals || &lt;source lang=&quot;tex&quot; inline&gt;\int_{A_1}\int_{A_2}\dotsi\int_{A_9}&lt;/source&gt; || &lt;math&gt;\int_{A_1}\int_{A_2}\dotsi\int_{A_9}&lt;/math&gt;
|-
| &lt;code&gt;\dotso&lt;/code&gt; || other dots || &lt;code&gt;123 \dotso 9&lt;/code&gt; || &lt;math&gt;123 \dotso 9&lt;/math&gt;
|}

The horizontal ellipsis character also appears in the following older character maps:
* in [[Windows code page|Windows-1250—Windows-1258]] and in IBM/MS-DOS [[Code page 874]], at [[code point|code]] 85 (hexadecimal)
* in [[Mac-Roman encoding|Mac-Roman]], [[Macintosh Central European encoding|Mac-CentEuro]] and several other Macintosh encodings&lt;!-- surely, in MacCyrillic, but I am not willing to check how many Mac CPs have … at this code point --Incnis Mrsi --&gt;, at code C9 (hexadecimal)
* in [[Ventura International encoding]] at code C1 (hexadecimal)

Note that [[ISO/IEC 8859]] encoding series provides no code point for ellipsis.

As with all characters, especially those outside the [[ASCII]] range, the author, sender and receiver of an encoded ellipsis must be in agreement upon what bytes are being used to represent the character. Naive text processing software may improperly assume that a particular encoding is being used, resulting in [[mojibake]].

The [[The Chicago Manual of Style|Chicago Style]] Q&amp;A recommends to avoid the use of '''...'''&amp;nbsp;(U+2026) character in manuscripts and to place three periods plus two nonbreaking spaces (.&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;.) instead, so that an editor, publisher, or designer can replace them later.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.chicagomanualofstyle.org/CMS_FAQ/SpecialCharacters/SpecialCharacters09.html |title=Chicago Style Q&amp;A: How do I insert an ellipsis in my manuscript? |year=2010 |work=[[The Chicago Manual of Style]], edition 16 |publisher=[[University of Chicago Press]] |accessdate=2011-02-10 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20101010042223/http://www.chicagomanualofstyle.org/CMS_FAQ/SpecialCharacters/SpecialCharacters09.html |archive-date=2010-10-10 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Abstract Syntax Notation One]] (ASN.1), the ellipsis is used as an extension marker to indicate the possibility of type extensions in future revisions of a protocol specification. In a type constraint expression like &lt;code&gt;A ::= INTEGER (0..127, ..., 256..511)&lt;/code&gt; an ellipsis is used to separate the extension root from extension additions. The definition of type A in version 1 system of the form &lt;code&gt;A ::= INTEGER (0..127, ...)&lt;/code&gt; and the definition of type A in version 2 system of the form &lt;code&gt;A ::= INTEGER (0..127, ..., 256..511)&lt;/code&gt; constitute an extension series of the same type A in different versions of the same specification. The ellipsis can also be used in compound type definitions to separate the set of fields belonging to the extension root from the set of fields constituting extension additions. Here is an example: &lt;code&gt;B ::= SEQUENCE { {{not a typo|a}} INTEGER, b INTEGER, ..., c INTEGER }&lt;/code&gt; &lt;!-- Is the s.n. ellipsis defined as a &quot;...&quot; trigraph or something else? This paragraph is a matter of syntax, not text *representation*, and therefore is misplaced. --Incnis Mrsi --&gt;

==See also==
* [[Caesura]]
* [[Cohesion (linguistics)]]
* [[Elision]] – Omission or deletion of a sound or syllable
* [[Leader (typography)]] – A row of characters (usually dots or dashes) to connect items across a page (as in a table of contents)
* [[Leiden Conventions]]
* [[Line break (poetry)]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
{{Wiktionary}}
{{Commons category|Ellipses (punctuation)}}
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book |title=The Elements of Typographic Style |last=Bringhurst |first=Robert |authorlink=Robert Bringhurst |edition=Version 2.5 |year=2002 |publisher=Hartley &amp; Marks |location=[[Point Roberts, Washington]] |isbn=978-0-88179-132-7 |oclc=50848361 |pages=[https://archive.org/details/isbn_9780881791327/page/82 82–83] |title-link=The Elements of Typographic Style }}
* Halliday, M.A.K, and Ruqayia, H. (1976), ''Cohesion in English'', London: Longman.
* {{cite book |title= The Houghton Mifflin Canadian Dictionary of the English Language|last= Morris|first= William|year= 1980|publisher= [[Houghton Mifflin]] Canada|location= [[Markham, Ontario]]|isbn= 978-0-395-29654-7|oclc= 8063090|page= 424 (spacing of dots: . . .)}}
{{refend}}
{{Navbox punctuation}}
[[Category:Mathematical notation]]
[[Category:Punctuation]]
[[Category:Typographical symbols]]</text>
      <sha1>cgps87evxvl2lzu7zgqznb4nsuf0lad</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
