  <page>
    <title>Claudius Aelianus</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7213</id>
    <revision>
      <id>925928134</id>
      <parentid>925927975</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-11-13T05:20:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>175.140.217.234</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Varia Historia */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{distinguish|Aelianus Tacticus}}

'''Claudius Aelianus''' ({{lang-grc-gre|Κλαύδιος Αιλιανός}} ''Klávdios Elianós'';&lt;ref&gt;&lt;!--confirmation of Greek name--&gt;Η φυσιογνωμία ενός λαού θεμελιών. Μύθοι για την Ελιά. Retrieved June 5, 2011, from http://www.etwinning.gr/projects/elia/muthoi.htm&lt;/ref&gt; c. 175{{snd}}c. 235 AD), commonly '''Aelian''' ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|iː|l|i|ən}}), born at [[Praeneste]], was a Roman author and teacher of [[rhetoric]] who flourished under [[Septimius Severus]] and probably outlived [[Elagabalus]], who died in 222. He spoke [[Ancient Greek|Greek]] so fluently that he was called &quot;honey-tongued&quot; (μελίγλωσσος ''meliglossos''); Roman-born, he preferred Greek authors, and wrote in a slightly archaizing Greek himself.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;&gt;{{EB1911|wstitle=Aelian (Claudius Aelinaus) |display=Aelian |volume=1|page=256}} This cites:
* ''Editio princeps'' of complete works by Gesner, 1556; [[Rudolf Hercher|Hercher]], 1864-1866.
* English translation of the ''Various History'' only by Fleming, 1576, and Stanley, 1665
* Translation of the ''Letters'' by [[Pierre Quillard|Quillard]] (French), 1895&lt;/ref&gt;

His two chief works are valuable for the numerous quotations from the works of earlier authors, which are otherwise lost, and for the surprising lore, which offers unexpected glimpses into the Greco-Roman world-view.

==''De Natura Animalium''==
''On the Nature of Animals'' (&quot;On the Characteristics of Animals&quot; is an alternative title; Greek: Περί ζώων ιδιότητος ''Perí zóon idiótitos''; usually cited, though, by its [[Latin]] title: ''De Natura Animalium'') is a curious collection,&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt; in seventeen books, of brief stories of natural history, sometimes selected with an eye to conveying allegorical moral lessons, sometimes because they are just so astonishing:
:&quot;The Beaver is an amphibious creature: by day it lives hidden in rivers, but at night it roams the land, feeding itself with anything that it can find. Now it understands the reason why hunters come after it with such eagerness and impetuosity, and it puts down its head and with its teeth cuts off its testicles and throws them in their path, as a prudent man who, falling into the hands of robbers, sacrifices all that he is carrying, to save his life, and forfeits his possessions by way of ransom. If however it has already saved its life by self-castration and is again pursued, then it stands up and reveals that it offers no ground for their eager pursuit, and releases the hunters from all further exertions, for they esteem its flesh less. Often however Beavers with testicles intact, after escaping as far away as possible, have drawn in the coveted part, and with great skill and ingenuity tricked their pursuers, pretending that they no longer possessed what they were keeping in concealment.&quot;

The [[Loeb Classical Library]] introduction characterizes the book as
:&quot;an appealing collection of facts and fables about the animal kingdom that invites the reader to ponder contrasts between human and animal behavior.&quot;

Aelian's anecdotes on animals rarely depend on direct observation: they are almost entirely taken from written sources, often [[Pliny the Elder]], but also other authors and works now lost, to whom he is thus a valuable witness.&lt;ref&gt;The third volume of the Loeb Classical Library translation gives a gazetteer of authors cited by Aelian.&lt;/ref&gt; He is more attentive to marine life than might be expected,{{According to whom|date=February 2016}} though, and this seems to reflect first-hand personal interest; he often quotes &quot;fishermen&quot;. At times he strikes the modern reader as thoroughly credulous, but at others he specifically states that he is merely reporting what is told by others, and even that he does not believe them. Aelian's work is one of the sources of medieval natural history and of the [[Bestiary|bestiaries]] of the Middle Ages.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cohen2008&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Cohen |first=Simona |title=Animals as Disguised Symbols in Renaissance Art |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=FOZVPjSTznwC&amp;pg=PA39 |year=2008 |publisher=Brill |isbn=90-04-17101-0 |pages=38–39}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The portions of the text that are still extant are badly mangled and garbled and replete with later interpolations.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Aelian's text, riddled as it is with corrupt passages and packed with interpretations,provides ample scope for reckless emendation&quot;, D. E. Eichholz observed, reviewing Sholfield's Loeb Library translation in ''The Classical Review'' 1960:219, and praising the translator for restraint in this direction.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Conrad Gessner]] (or Gesner), the Swiss scientist and natural historian of the Renaissance, made a Latin translation of Aelian's work, to give it a wider European audience. An English translation by A. F. Scholfield has been published in the [[Loeb Classical Library]], 3 vols. (1958-59).

==''Varia Historia''==
[[File:Claudius Aelianus Varia Historia 1668 Title page.jpg|upright|thumb|Title page of ''Varia Historia'', from the 1668 edition by [[Tanaquil Faber]]]]
''Various History'' (Ποικίλη Ιστορία ''Pikíli Istoría'') &amp;mdash; for the most part preserved only in an abridged form&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt; &amp;mdash; is Aelian's other well-known work, a miscellany of anecdotes and biographical sketches, lists, pithy maxims, and descriptions of natural wonders and strange local customs, in 14&amp;nbsp;books, with many surprises for the cultural historian and the [[mythographer]], anecdotes about the famous Greek philosophers, poets, historians, and playwrights and myths instructively retold. The emphasis is on ''various'' moralizing tales about heroes and rulers, athletes and wise men; reports about food and drink, different styles in dress or lovers, local habits in giving gifts or entertainments, or in religious beliefs and death customs; and comments on Greek painting. Aelian gives an account of [[fly fishing]], using [[Artificial fly|lures]] of red wool and feathers, of lacquerwork, [[Serpent (symbolism)|serpent]] worship &amp;mdash; Essentially the ''Various History'' is a Classical &quot;[[magazine]]&quot; in the original senses of that word. He is not perfectly trustworthy in details, and his agenda was heavily influenced by [[Stoicism|Stoic]] opinions,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Zeyl |first=Donald |year=2013 |title=Encyclopedia of Classical Philosophy |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=yUGzAQAAQBAJ&amp;lpg=PA6&amp;dq=aelian%20varia%20historia%20correct%20stoic&amp;pg=PA6#v=onepage&amp;q=aelian%20varia%20historia%20correct%20stoic&amp;f=false |location= |publisher=Routledge |isbn=9781134270781 |accessdate=30 November 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt; perhaps so that his readers will not feel guilty, but [[Jane Ellen Harrison]] found survivals of archaic rites mentioned by Aelian very illuminating in her ''Prolegomena to the Study of Greek Religion'' (1903, 1922).

The first printing was in 1545. The standard modern text is Mervin R. Dilts's, of 1974.

Two English translations of the ''Various History,''  by Fleming (1576) and Stanley (1665) made Aelian's miscellany available to English readers, but after 1665 no English translation appeared, until three English translations appeared almost simultaneously: James G. DeVoto, ''Claudius Aelianus: Ποικίλη Ιστορία (&quot;Varia Historia&quot;)'' Chicago, 1995; Diane Ostrom Johnson, ''An English Translation of Claudius Aelianus' &quot;Varia Historia&quot;'', 1997; and N. G. Wilson, ''Aelian: Historical Miscellany'' in the [[Loeb Classical Library]].

==Other works==
Considerable fragments of two other works, ''On Providence'' and ''Divine Manifestations'', are preserved in the early medieval encyclopedia, the ''[[Suda]].''  Twenty &quot;letters from a farmer&quot; after the manner of [[Alciphron]] are also attributed to him.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt; The letters are invented compositions to a fictitious correspondent, which are a device for vignettes of agricultural and rural life, set in Attica, though mellifluous Aelian once boasted that he had never been outside Italy, never been aboard a ship (which is at variance, though, with his own statement, ''de Natura Animalium'' XI.40, that he had seen the bull [[Serapis]] with his own eyes). Thus conclusions about actual agriculture in the ''Letters'' are as likely to evoke [[Latium]] as [[Attica]]. The fragments have been edited in 1998 by D. Domingo-Foraste, but are not available in English. The ''Letters'' are available in the Loeb Classical Library, translated by Allen Rogers Benner and Francis H. Fobes (1949).

==See also==
*[[Historiae animalium (Gesner)|''Historiae animalium'' by Gessner]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
*Aelian, ''On Animals''. 3 volumes. Translated by A. F. Scholfield. 1958-9. Loeb Classical Library. {{ISBN|978-0-674-99491-1}}, {{ISBN|978-0-674-99493-5}}, and {{ISBN|978-0-674-99494-2}}
*Aelian, ''Historical Miscellany''. Translated by Nigel G. Wilson. 1997. Loeb Classical Library. {{ISBN|978-0-674-99535-2}}
*Alciphron, Aelian, and Philostratus, ''The Letters''.  Translated by A. R. Benner, F. H. Fobes. 1949. Loeb Classical Library. {{ISBN|978-0-674-99421-8}}
*Aelian, ''On the Nature of Animals''. Translated by Gregory McNamee. 2011. Trinity University Press. {{ISBN|978-1-59534-075-7}}
*Ailianos, ''Vermischte Forschung''. Greek and German by [[Kai Brodersen]]. 2018. Sammlung Tusculum. De Gruyter Berlin &amp; Boston {{ISBN|978-3-11-057638-2}}
*Ailianos, ''Tierleben''. Greek and German by [[Kai Brodersen]]. 2018. Sammlung Tusculum. De Gruyter Berlin &amp; Boston 2018, ISBN {{ISBN|978-3-11-060932-5}}

==External links==
{{wikisource author}}
* {{Internet Archive author |search=( Aelian OR &quot;Claudius Aelianus&quot; )}}
* {{Librivox author |id=1110}}
* [http://www.hs-augsburg.de/~harsch/graeca/Chronologia/S_post03/Aelianus/ael_hi00.html Ποικίλη ἱστορία – bibliotheca Augustana]
* Raw Greek OCR of Hercher's 1864 Teubner edition of Aelian's works at the Lace repository of [[Mount Allison University]]: [http://heml.mta.ca/lace/runs/claudiiaelianid00hercgoog vol. I], [http://heml.mta.ca/lace/runs/deanimaliumantur02aeliuoft vol. 2] 
* [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/aelian/ Various History] at James Eason's site (excerpts in English translation)
* [http://www.attalus.org/translate/aelian_f1.html English translation of Aelian's fragments] at ''attalus.org''
* [http://www.wayward.com/animal.htm Some quotes from Aelian's natural history] (English)
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20050728121931/http://www.flyfishinghistory.com/aelian.htm Aelian from the fly-fisherman's point-of-view]
* [http://apaclassics.org/index.php/annual_meeting/143rd_annual_meeting_abstracts/57.3.smith/ The Evidence for Aelian's Katêgoria tou gunnidos] regarding Aelian's presumed invective against [[Elagabalus]]
===Aelian's ''Characteristics of Animals''===
====Greek with English translation====
*[https://archive.org/details/L446AelianCharacteristicsOfAnimalsI15 Aelian on the Characteristics of Animals, Books I-V (Greek with English translation by A.F. Scholfield, 1950)]
*[https://archive.org/details/L448AelianCharacteristicsOfAnimalsII611 Aelian on the Characteristics of Animals, Books VI-XI (Greek with English translation by A.F. Scholfield, 1950)]
*[https://archive.org/details/L449AelianCharacteristicsOfAnimalsIII1217 Aelian on the Characteristics of Animals, Books XII-XVII (Greek with English translation by A.F. Scholfield, 1950)]
*[http://www.attalus.org/info/aelian.html HTML version of Scholfield's English translation] at ''attalus.org''
====Latin translation====
* [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Aelian/home.html ''De natura animalium'' at LacusCurtius] (complete Latin translation)
====Greek====
* ''De natura animalium libri XVII, Varia historia, Epistolae fragmenta, ex recognitione Rudolphi Hercheri'', Lipsiae, in aedibus B. G. Teubneri, 1864: [https://archive.org/details/claudiiaelianid03hercgoog vol. 1], [https://archive.org/details/claudiiaelianid01hercgoog vol. 2].
 
{{Natural history}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Aelianus, Claudius}}
[[Category:175 births]]
[[Category:235 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Palestrina]]
[[Category:Claudii]]
[[Category:Ancient Roman rhetoricians]]
[[Category:Ancient Greek writers]]
[[Category:2nd-century Romans]]
[[Category:3rd-century Romans]]
[[Category:3rd-century writers]]
[[Category:2nd-century Greek people]]
[[Category:3rd-century Greek people]]</text>
      <sha1>a17ffg7f656wd19z03vbwax8171kajy</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
