  <page>
    <title>Caste</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7257</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942245810</id>
      <parentid>942245286</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-23T14:47:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Clean Copy</username>
        <id>700572</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Indonesia */ simplify, contrast two systems</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Other uses}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}
[[File:Basor Dalit caste.jpg|thumb|The ''[[Basor]]'' weaving bamboo baskets in a 1916 book. The ''Basor'' are a [[Scheduled Caste]] found in the state of [[Uttar Pradesh]] in India.]]
{{Political anthropology|expanded=Basic concepts}}
{{Discrimination sidebar|General}}
'''Caste''' is a form of [[social stratification]] characterized by [[endogamy]], hereditary transmission of a style of life which often includes an occupation, ritual status in a hierarchy, and customary social interaction and exclusion based on cultural notions of purity and pollution.&lt;ref name=caste-lead&gt;
*{{citation|editor=Lagasse, Paul|title=The Columbia Encyclopedia|chapter=Caste|url=http://www.encyclopedia.com/topic/caste.aspx#3|accessdate=24 September 2012|year=2007|publisher=Columbia University Press|location=New York, NY|isbn=978-0-231-14446-9}} Quote: &quot;'''caste''' [Port., casta=basket], ranked groups based on heredity within rigid systems of social stratification, especially those that constitute Hindu India. Some scholars, in fact, deny that true caste systems are found outside India. The caste is a closed group whose members are severely restricted in their choice of occupation and degree of social participation. Marriage outside the caste is prohibited. Social status is determined by the caste of one's birth and may only rarely be transcended.&quot;
*{{citation|last1=Madan|first1=T. N.|authorlink1=T. N. Madan|last2=Editors|fist2= |title=caste|publisher= Encyclopæida Britannica Online|url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/98395/caste|date=2012}} Quote: &quot;'''caste''', any of the ranked, hereditary, endogamous social groups, often linked with occupation, that together constitute traditional societies in South Asia, particularly among Hindus in India. Although sometimes used to designate similar groups in other societies, the “caste system” is uniquely developed in Hindu societies.&quot;
*{{citation|last=Gupta|first=Dipankar|chapter=Caste|editor-last=Schaefer|editor-first=Richard T.|title=Encyclopedia of Race, Ethnicity, and Society|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=YMUola6pDnkC&amp;pg=PA246|location=Thousand Oaks|accessdate=5 August 2012|year=2008|publisher=SAGE|isbn=978-1-4129-2694-2|pages=246–250}} Quote: &quot;'''Caste''': What makes Indian society unique is the phenomenon of caste. Economic, religious, and linguistic differentiations, even race-based discrimination, are known elsewhere, but nowhere else does one see caste but in India.&quot;
*{{citation|last=Béteille|first =André|editor-last=Barnard|editor-first=Alan|editor2-last=Spencer|editor2-first=Jonathan|chapter=Caste|title=Encyclopedia of Social and Cultural Anthropology|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=o1VpdrbH3BUC&amp;pg=PA136|year=2002|location=New York, NY; London, UK|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-0-415-28558-2|pages=136–137}} Quote: &quot;'''Caste''': Caste has been described as the fundamental social institution of India. Sometimes the term is used metaphorically to refer to rigid social distinctions or extreme social exclusiveness wherever found, and some authorities have used the term 'colour-caste system' to describe the stratification based on race in the United States and elsewhere. But it is among the Hindus in India that we find the system in its most fully developed form although analogous forms exist among Muslims, Christians. Sikhs and other religious groups in South Asia. It is an ancient institution, having existed for at least 2,000 years among the Hindus who developed not only elaborate caste practices hut also a complex theory to explain and justify those practices (Dumont 1970).  The theory has now lost much of its force although many of the practices continue.&quot;
*{{citation|last=Mitchell|first=Geoffrey Duncan|title=A New Dictionary of the Social Sciences|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=-a4vvdBrSVgC&amp;pg=PA194|accessdate=10 August 2012|date=2006|publisher=Aldine Transaction Publishers|isbn=978-0-202-30878-4|pages=194–195|chapter=Castes (part of SOCIAL STRATIFICATION)|location=New Brunswick, NJ}} Quote:&quot;'''Castes''' A pure caste system is rooted in the religious order and may be thought of as a hierarchy of hereditary, endogamous, occupational groups with positions fixed and mobility barred by ritual distances between each caste. Empirically, the classical Hindu system of India approximated most closely to pure caste. The system existed for some 3,000 years and continues today despite many attempts to get rid of some of its restrictions. It is essentially connected with Hinduism.&quot;
*{{citation|chapter=caste, n.|title  = Oxford English Dictionary, Second edition; online version June 2012|publisher = Oxford University Press|location=Oxford, UK|url=http://www.oed.com/view/Entry/28546|accessdate =5 August 2019|year = 1989}}) Quote: &quot;'''caste, n.''' 2a. spec. One of the several hereditary classes into which society in India has from time immemorial been divided; ... ''This is now the leading sense, which influences all others.''&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;{{Sfn|Scott|Marshall|2005|p=66}}{{Sfn|Winthrop|1991|pp=27–30}}   Its paradigmatic  ethnographic example is the division of India's [[Hinduism|Hindu]] society into rigid social groups, with roots in India's ancient history and persisting to the present time.&lt;ref name=caste-lead/&gt;{{Sfn|Béteille|2002|p=66}}  However, the economic significance of the [[caste system in India]] has been declining as a result of urbanization and affirmative action programs. A subject of much scholarship by sociologists and anthropologists, the Hindu caste system is sometimes used as an analogical basis for the study of caste-like social divisions existing outside Hinduism and India. The term &quot;caste&quot; is also applied to morphological groupings in female populations of ants and bees.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last= Wilson |first= E. O. |year= 1979 |title= The Evolution of Caste Systems in Social Insects |journal= Proceedings of the American Philosophical Society |volume= 123 |number=4 |pages= 204–210 |jstor= 986579}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Etymology==
The English word &quot;caste&quot; derives from the Spanish and Portuguese ''[[casta]]'', which, according to the [[John Minsheu]]'s Spanish dictionary (1569), means &quot;race, lineage, tribe or breed&quot;.&lt;ref name=oed-caste&gt;{{Cite OED|caste|id=28546}}&lt;/ref&gt;  When the Spanish colonized the [[New World]], they used the word to mean a &quot;clan or lineage&quot;. It was, however, the Portuguese who first employed ''casta'' in the primary modern sense of the English word 'caste' when they applied it to the thousands of endogamous, hereditary Indian social groups they encountered upon their arrival in India in 1498.&lt;ref name=oed-caste/&gt;&lt;ref name=pitt-rivers&gt;{{citation|last=Pitt-Rivers|first=Julian|editor=T O Beidelman|title=The translation of culture essays to E.E. Evans-Pritchard|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=f509AAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=231|year=1971|publisher=Tavistock|location=London, UK|pages=231–256|chapter=On the word 'caste'|id=GGKEY:EC3ZBGF5QC9}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The use of the spelling &quot;caste&quot;, with this latter meaning, is first attested in English in 1613.&lt;ref name=oed-caste/&gt;

== Caste system in India ==
{{Main|Caste system in India}}
Modern India's caste system is based on the artificial superimposition of a four-fold theoretical classification called the ''[[Varna (Hinduism)|Varna]]'' on the natural social groupings called the ''[[Jāti]]''. From 1901 onwards, for the purposes of the [[Census of India prior to independence|Decennial Census]], the British classified all Jātis into one or the other of the ''[[Varna (Hinduism)|Varna]]'' categories as described in ancient texts. Herbert Hope Risley, the Census Commissioner, noted that &quot;The principle suggested as a basis was that of classification by social precedence as recognized by native public opinion at the present day, and manifesting itself in the facts that particular castes are supposed to be the modern representatives of one or other of the castes of the theoretical Indian system.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Crooke, William. &quot;Social Types&quot;. Chapter II in Risley, Sir Herbert Hope. The People of India&lt;/ref&gt; The system of ''Varnas'' propounded in ancient Hindu texts envisages the society divided into four classes: [[Brahmin]]s (scholars and yajna priests), [[Kshatriya]]s (rulers and warriors), [[Vaishyas]] (farmers, merchants and artisans) and [[Shudras]] (workmen/service providers). The texts do not mention any separate, untouchable category in ''[[Varna (Hinduism)|Varna]]'' classification. Scholars believe that the ''Varnas'' system was never truly operational in society and there is no evidence of it ever being a reality in Indian history. The practical division of the society had always been in terms of ''Jātis'' (birth groups), which are not based on any specific principle, but could vary from ethnic origins to occupations to geographic areas. The ''Jātis'' have been endogamous groups without any fixed hierarchy but subject to vague notions of rank articulated over time based on lifestyle and social, political or economic status. Many of India's major empires and dynasties like the Mauryas,&lt;ref&gt;Roy, Kaushik (2012), Hinduism and the Ethics of Warfare in South Asia: From Antiquity to the Present, Cambridge University Press, {{ISBN|978-1-107-01736-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; Shalivahanas,&lt;ref&gt;Shalivahana was born in a potter's house, by grace of Adi-Sheshan. William Cooke Taylor (1838). Examination and Analysis of the Mackenzie Manuscripts Deposited in the Madras College Library. Asiatic Society. pp. 49–55&lt;/ref&gt; Chalukyas,&lt;ref&gt;Bilhana, in his Sanskrit work Vikramanakadevacharitam claims the Chalukyas were born from the feet of Brahma, implying they were Shudras, while some sources claim they were born in the arms of Brahma, and hence were Kshatriyas (Ramesh 1984, p. 15)&lt;/ref&gt; Kakatiyas&lt;ref&gt;Most of the Kakatiya records proudly describe them as Shudra.[Talbot, Austin Cynthia (2001), Pre-colonial India in Practice: Society, Region, and Identity in Medieval Andhra, Oxford University Press, {{ISBN|978-0-19803-123-9}}] Examples include the Bothpur and Vaddamanu inscriptions of Ganapati's general Malyala Gunda senani. The Kakatiyas also maintained marital relations with other Shudra families, such as the Kotas and the Natavadi chiefs. All these evidences indicate that the Kakatiyas were of Shudra origin.[Sastry, P. V. Parabhrama (1978). N. Ramesan, ed. The Kākatiyas of Warangal. Hyderabad: Government of Andhra Pradesh. OCLC 252341228 page 29]&lt;/ref&gt; among many others, were founded by people who would have been classified as Shudras, under the ''Varnas'' system. It is well established that by the 9th century, kings from all the four castes, including Brahmins and Vaishyas, had occupied the highest seat in the monarchical system in Hindu India, contrary to the Varna theory.&lt;ref&gt;Notes of Yuan Chwang, Altekar, Anant Sadashiv (1934). The Rashtrakutas And Their Times; being a political, administrative, religious, social, economic and literary history of the Deccan during C. 750 A.D. to C. 1000 A.D. Poona: Oriental Book Agency. OCLC 3793499, p 331&lt;/ref&gt; In many instances, as in Bengal, historically the kings and rulers had been called upon, when required, to mediate on the ranks of ''Jātis'', which might number in thousands all over the subcontinent and vary by region. In practice, the ''jātis'' may or may not fit into the ''Varna'' classes and many prominent ''Jatis'', for example the Jats and Yadavs, straddled two Varnas i.e. Kshatriyas and Vaishyas, and the ''Varna'' status of ''Jātis'' itself was subject to articulation over time.

Starting with the British colonial Census of 1901 led by [[Herbert Hope Risley]], all the ''jātis'' were grouped under the theoretical ''varnas'' categories.&lt;ref name=dirks&gt;{{cite book|url=http://press.princeton.edu/titles/7191.html|author=Nicholas B. Dirks|title=Castes of Mind: Colonialism and the Making of New India|year=2001|isbn=978-0-691-08895-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to political scientist [[Lloyd Rudolph]], Risley believed that ''varna'', however ancient, could be applied to all the modern castes found in India, and &quot;[he] meant to identify and place several hundred million Indians within it.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=3vnsnma5nW4C |title=The Modernity of Tradition: Political Development in India |first=Lloyd I. |last=Rudolph |authorlink=Lloyd I. Rudolph |others=[[Susanne Hoeber Rudolph|Rudolph, Susanne Hoeber]] |year=1984 |publisher=University of Chicago Press |pages=116–117 |isbn=978-0-226-73137-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; In an effort to arrange various castes in order of precedence functional grouping was based less on the occupation that prevailed in each case in the present day than on that which was traditional with it, or which gave rise to its differentiation from the rest of the community. &quot;This action virtually removed Indians from the progress of history and condemned them to an unchanging position and place in time. In one sense, it is rather ironic that the British, who continually accused the Indian people of having a static society, should then impose a construct that denied progress&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=https://www.britishempire.co.uk/article/castesystem.htm | title=The British Empire, Imperialism, Colonialism, Colonies}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The terms ''varna'' (conceptual classification based on occupation) and ''jāti'' (groups) are two distinct concepts: while ''varna'' is the idealised four-part division envisaged by the [[Dvija|Twice-Born]], ''jāti'' (community) refers to the thousands of actual endogamous groups prevalent across the subcontinent. The classical authors scarcely speak of anything other than the ''varnas'', as it provided a convenient shorthand; but a problem arises when even Indologists sometimes confuse the two.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chicago&quot;&gt;{{citation |author=Dumont, Louis |title=Homo hierarchicus: the caste system and its implications |publisher=University of Chicago Press |location=Chicago |year=1980 |pages=66–67 |isbn=978-0-226-16963-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thus, starting with the 1901 Census, Caste officially became India's essential institution, with an imprimatur from the British administrators, augmenting a discourse that had already dominated Indology. “Despite India's acquisition of formal political independence, it has still not regained the power to know its own past and present apart from that discourse”.&lt;ref&gt;Inden, R. (1986). Orientalist Constructions of India. Modern Asian Studies, 20(3), 401-446. doi:10.1017/S0026749X00007800&lt;/ref&gt;

Upon independence from Britain, the Indian Constitution listed 1,108 castes across the country as Scheduled Castes in 1950, for positive discrimination.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://lawmin.nic.in/ld/subord/rule3a.htm |title=The Constitution (Scheduled Castes) Order 1950 |publisher=Lawmin.nic.in |date= |access-date=2013-11-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Untouchable communities are sometimes called ''[[Scheduled Castes]]'', ''[[Dalit]]'' or ''[[Harijan]]'' in contemporary literature.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Scaling Caste Walls With Capitalism’s Ladders in India|newspaper=The New York Times|author=Lydia Polgreen|date=21 December 2011|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2011/12/22/world/asia/indias-boom-creates-openings-for-untouchables.html?pagewanted=all}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2001, Dalits were 16.2% of India's population.&lt;ref name=censtat01&gt;{{cite web|title=Scheduled castes and scheduled tribes population: Census 2001|year=2004|publisher=Government of India|url=http://censusindia.gov.in/Census_Data_2001/India_at_glance/scst.aspx}}&lt;/ref&gt; Most of the 15 million bonded child workers are from the lowest castes.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.unicef.org/pon95/chil0016.html Children pay high price for cheap labour]&quot;. [[UNICEF]].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | author=ZAMA COURSEN-NEFF | date=30 January 2003 | title=For 15 million in India, a childhood of slavery | url=https://www.nytimes.com/2003/01/30/opinion/30iht-edzama_ed3__0.html | work=[[The New York Times]] | access-date=22 March 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Independent India has witnessed [[Caste-related violence in India|caste-related violence]]. In 2005, government recorded approximately 110,000 cases of reported violent acts, including rape and murder, against Dalits.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[https://www.cbc.ca/news/world/un-report-slams-india-for-caste-discrimination-1.693195 UN report slams India for caste discrimination]&quot;. CBC News. 2 March 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; For 2012, the government recorded 651 murders, 3,855 injuries, 1,576 rapes, 490 kidnappings, and 214 cases of arson.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.bbc.com/news/world-asia-india-27774908 &quot;Viewpoint: India must stop denying caste and gender violence]&quot;. BBC News. 11 June 2014&lt;/ref&gt;

The socio-economic limitations of the caste system are reduced due to urbanization and [[affirmative action]]. Nevertheless, the caste system still exists in [[endogamy]] and [[Family patrimony|patrimony]], and thrives in the politics of democracy, where caste provides ready made constituencies to politicians. The globalization and economic opportunities from foreign businesses has influenced the growth of India's middle-class population. Some members of the Chhattisgarh Potter Caste Community (CPCC) are middle-class urban professionals and no longer potters unlike the remaining majority of traditional rural potter members. There is persistence of caste in Indian politics. Caste associations have evolved into caste-based political parties. Political parties and the state perceive caste as an important factor for mobilization of people and policy development.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Sen|first1=Ronojoy.|title=The persistence of caste in indian politics|journal=Pacific Affairs|date=2012|volume=85|issue=2|pages=363–369|doi=10.5509/2012852363}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Studies by Bhatt and Beteille have shown changes in status, openness, mobility in the social aspects of Indian society. As a result of the modern social pressures on the country, India is experiencing a change in their social sphere dynamic as well as economically in the caste system.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Gandhi|first1=Rag S.|title=FROM CASTE TO CLASS IN INDIAN SOCIETY|journal=Humboldt Journal of Social Relations|date=1980|volume=7|issue=2|pages=1–14}}&lt;/ref&gt; While arranged marriages are still the most common practice in India, the internet has provided a network for younger Indians to take control of their relationships through the use of dating apps. This remains isolated to informal terms, as marriage is not often achieved through the use of these apps.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine|last1=Gandhi|first1=Divya.|title= Running in the family|magazine=The Hindu|date=April 2, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hypergamy is still a common practice in India and Hindu culture. Men are expected to marry within their caste, or one below, with no social repercussions. If a woman marries into a higher caste, then her children will take the status of their father. If she marries down, her family is reduced to the social status of their son in law. In this case, the women are bearers of the egalitarian principle of the marriage. There would be no benefit in marrying a higher caste if the terms of the marriage did not imply equality.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | author=Kingsley Davis | date=13 June 2013 | title=Intermarriage in Caste Societies | journal=[[AnthroSource]] | volume=43 | issue=3 | pages=376–395 | doi=10.1525/aa.1941.43.3.02a00030 }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, men are systematically shielded from the negative implications of the agreement.

Geographical factors also determine adherence to the caste system. Many Northern villages are more likely to participate in exogamous marriage, due to a lack of eligible suitors within the same caste. Women in North India have been found to be less likely to leave or divorce their husbands since they are of a relatively lower caste system, and have higher restrictions on their freedoms. On the other hand, Pahari women, of the northern mountains, have much more freedom to leave their husbands without stigma. This often leads to better husbandry as his actions are not protected by social expectations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1= Berreman|first1=Gerald D.|title=Village Exogamy in Northernmost India|date=1962|volume=18|issue=1|pages=55–58}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Chiefly among the factors influencing the rise of exogamy is the rapid [[urbanisation in India]] experienced over the last century. It is well known that urban centers tend to be less reliant on tradition and are more progressive as a whole. As India’s cities boomed in population, the job market grew to keep pace. Prosperity and stability were now more easily attained by an individual, and the anxiety to marry quickly and effectively was reduced as traditional marriage was viewed as a means to attain these principles. Thus, younger, more progressive generations of urban Indians are less likely than ever to participate in the antiquated system of arranged endogamy.

India has also experimented with Affirmative Action, locally known as “reservation groups”. Quota system jobs, as well as placements in publicly funded colleges, hold spots for the 8% of India’s minority, and underprivileged groups. As a result, in states such as Tamil Nadu or those in the north-east, where underprivileged populations predominate, over 80% of government jobs are set aside in quotas. In education, colleges lower the marks necessary for the Dalits to enter.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | author=Delhi A.R | date=13 June 2013 | title=Indian Reservations | url=https://www.economist.com/banyan/2013/06/29/indian-reservations | journal=[[The Economist]] | access-date=4 December 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Seventy-two Specimens of Castes in India (62).jpg|thumb|A page from the manuscript ''Seventy-two Specimens of Castes in India'', which consists of 72 full-color hand-painted images of men and women of various religions, occupations and ethnic groups found in [[Madurai|Madura, India]] in 1837, which confirms the popular perception and nature of caste as Jati, before the British made it applicable only to Hindus grouped under the ''[[Varna (Hinduism)|varna]]'' categories from the 1901 census onwards.]]

==Caste systems in the rest of South Asia==
===Nepal===
{{Main|Caste system in Nepal}}
The [[Nepal]]ese caste system resembles in some respects the Indian ''jāti'' system, with numerous ''jāti'' divisions with a ''varna'' system superimposed. Inscriptions attest the beginnings of a caste system during the [[Licchavi (kingdom)|Licchavi]] period.  Jayasthiti Malla (1382–1395) categorized Newars into 64 castes (Gellner 2001). A similar exercise was made during the reign of Mahindra Malla (1506–1575). The Hindu social code was later set up in Gorkha by Ram Shah (1603–1636).

===Pakistan===
{{Main|Caste system among South Asian Muslims}}

McKim Marriott claims a social stratification that is hierarchical, closed, endogamous and hereditary is widely prevalent, particularly in western parts of Pakistan. Frederik Barth in his review of this system of social stratification in Pakistan suggested that these are castes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Ecologic Relationships of Ethnic Groups in Swat, North Pakistan|author=Fredrick Barth|journal=American Anthropologist|doi=10.1525/aa.1956.58.6.02a00080|volume=58|issue=6|pages=1079–1089|date=December 1956}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The New Wind: Changing Identities in South Asia (Editor: Kenneth David)|author=Zeyauddin Ahmed|pages=337–354|isbn=978-90-279-7959-9|publisher=Aldine Publishing Company|year=1977}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Caste ranking and community structure in five regions of India and Pakistan|author=McKim Marriott|year=1960|oclc=186146571}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sri Lanka===
{{Main|Caste system in Sri Lanka}}
The caste system in Sri Lanka is a division of society into strata,&lt;ref name=&quot;John Rogers 51–77&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|title=Caste as a social category and identity in colonial Lanka|author=John Rogers| doi=10.1177/001946460404100104| journal=Indian Economic and Social History Review| date= February 2004|volume=41|number=1|pages=51–77}}&lt;/ref&gt; influenced by the textbook ''varnas'' and ''jāti'' system found in India. Ancient Sri Lankan texts such as the Pujavaliya, Sadharmaratnavaliya and Yogaratnakaraya and inscriptional evidence show that the above hierarchy prevailed throughout the feudal period. The repetition of the same caste hierarchy even as recently as the 18th century, in the British/Kandyan period Kadayimpoth – Boundary books as well, indicates the continuation of the tradition right up to the end of Sri Lanka's monarchy.

==Caste-like stratification outside South Asia==
===Southeast Asia===
[[File:COLLECTIE TROPENMUSEUM Een soedra een man uit de laagste kaste van Bali. TMnr 60002169.jpg|thumb|upright|A Sudra caste man from [[Bali]]. Photo from 1870, courtesy of [[Tropenmuseum]], [[Netherlands]].]]

====Indonesia====
{{Main|Balinese caste system}}
[[Bali]]nese caste structure has been described as being based either on three categories--the noble triwangsa (thrice born), the middle class of ''dwijāti'' (twice born), and the lower class of ''ekajāti'' (once born)--or on four castes&lt;ref name=boon&gt;{{cite book|title=The Anthropological Romance of Bali 1597-1972: Dynamic Perspectives in Marriage and Caste, Politics and Religion|author=James Boon|year=1977|isbn=978-0-521-21398-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Brahmin]]as – [[priest]]
*Satrias – [[knight]]hood
*Wesias – commerce
*Sudras – servitude

The Brahmana caste was further subdivided by these Dutch ethnographers into two: Siwa and Buda. The Siwa caste was subdivided into five: Kemenuh, Keniten, Mas, Manuba and Petapan. This classification was to accommodate the observed marriage between higher-caste Brahmana men with lower-caste women. The other castes were similarly further sub-classified by these 19th-century and early-20th-century ethnographers based on numerous criteria ranging from profession, endogamy or exogamy or polygamy, and a host of other factors in a manner similar to ''castas'' in Spanish colonies such as Mexico, and caste system studies in British colonies such as India.&lt;ref name=boon/&gt;

====Philippines====
[[File:Naturales 3.png|thumb|A [[Tagalog people|Tagalog]] royal couple (''[[maginoo]]''), from the [[Boxer Codex]] (c. 1590)]]
In the Philippines, pre-colonial societies do not have a single social structure. The class structures can be roughly categorized into four types:&lt;ref name=&quot;Scott1979&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Scott |first1=William Henry |title=Class Structure in the Unhispanized Philippines |journal=Philippine Studies |date=1979 |volume=27 |issue=2, Special Issue in Memory of Frank Lynch |pages=137–159 |jstor=42632474 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Classless societies - egalitarian societies with no class structure. Examples include the [[Mangyan people|Mangyan]] and the [[Kalanguya people]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scott1979&quot;/&gt;
* Warrior societies - societies where a distinct warrior class exists, and whose membership depends on martial prowess. Examples include the [[Mandaya people|Mandaya]], [[Bagobo people|Bagobo]], [[Tagakaulo people|Tagakaulo]], and [[B'laan people]]s who had warriors called the ''bagani'' or ''magani''. Similarly, in the [[Cordillera Central (Luzon)|Cordillera highlands]] of [[Luzon]], the [[Isneg people|Isneg]] and [[Kalinga people]]s refer to their warriors as ''mengal'' or ''maingal''. This society is typical for [[head-hunting]] ethnic groups or ethnic groups which had seasonal raids (''[[mangayaw]]'') into enemy territory.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scott1979&quot;/&gt;
* Petty [[Plutocracy|plutocracies]] - societies which have a wealthy class based on property and the hosting of periodic prestige feasts. In some groups, it was an actual caste whose members had specialized leadership roles, married only within the same caste, and wore specialized clothing. These include the ''kadangyan'' of the [[Ifugao people|Ifugao]], [[Bontoc people|Bontoc]], and [[Kankanaey people|Kankanaey]] peoples, as well as the ''baknang'' of the [[Ibaloi people]]. In others, though wealth may give one prestige and leadership qualifications, it was not a caste per se.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scott1979&quot;/&gt;
*Principalities - societies with an actual ruling class and caste systems determined by birthright. Most of these societies are either [[Greater India|Indianized]] or [[Islamized]] to a degree. They include the larger coastal ethnic groups like the [[Tagalog people|Tagalog]], [[Kapampangan people|Kapampangan]], [[Visayan people|Visayan]], and [[Moro people|Moro]] societies. Most of them were usually divided into four to five caste systems with different names under different ethnic groups that roughly correspond to each other. The system was more or less [[feudalistic]], with the ''datu'' ultimately having control of all the lands of the community. The land is subdivided among the enfranchised classes, the ''sakop'' or ''sa-op'' ([[vassal]]s, lit. &quot;those under the power of another&quot;). The castes were hereditary, though they were not rigid. They were more accurately a reflection of the interpersonal political relationships, a person is always the follower of another. People can move up the caste system by marriage, by wealth, or by doing something extraordinary; and conversely they can be demoted, usually as criminal punishment or as a result of debt. Shamans are the exception, as they are either volunteers, chosen by the ranking shamans, or born into the role by innate propensity for it. They are enumerated below from the highest rank to the lowest:&lt;ref name=&quot;Scott1979&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;arcilla&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Arcilla, José S. |title =An Introduction to Philippine History|publisher =Ateneo de Manila University Press|year =1998|page=14&amp;ndash;16|isbn =9789715502610|url =https://books.google.com/?id=uxEYobbU-D8C&amp;lpg=PA15&amp;dq=timawa&amp;pg=PA14#v=onepage&amp;q=timawa&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;scott2&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Scott, William Henry |title =Barangay: sixteenth-century Philippine culture and society|publisher =Ateneo de Manila University Press|isbn=9789715501354|year =1994}}&lt;/ref&gt;
:* Royalty - ([[Visayan people|Visayan]]: ''[[kadatoan]]'') the ''[[datu]]'' and immediate descendants. They are often further categorized according to purity of lineage. The power of the ''datu'' is dependent on the willingness of their followers to render him respect and obedience. Most roles of the datu were judicial and military. In case of an unfit ''datu'', support may be withdrawn by his followers. ''Datu'' were almost always male, though in some ethnic groups like the [[Banwaon people]], the female shaman (''[[babaylan|babaiyon]]'') co-rules as the female counterpart of the ''datu''.
:* Nobility - (Visayan: ''[[tumao]]''; [[Tagalog people|Tagalog]]: ''[[maginoo]]''; [[Kapampangan people|Kapampangan]] ''ginu''; [[Tausug people|Tausug]]: ''bangsa mataas'') the ruling class, either inclusive of or exclusive of the royal family. Most are descendants of the royal line or gained their status through wealth or bravery in battle. They owned lands and subjects, from whom they collected taxes.
:* Shamans - (Visayan: ''[[babaylan]]''; Tagalog: ''[[katalonan]]'') the spirit mediums, usually female or feminized men. While they weren't technically a caste, they commanded the same respect and status as nobility.
:* Warriors - (Visayan: ''[[timawa]]''; Tagalog: ''[[maharlika]]'') the martial class. They could own land and subjects like the higher ranks, but were required to fight for the ''datu'' in times of war. In some Filipino ethnic groups, they were often tattooed extensively to record feats in battle and as protection against harm. They were sometimes further subdivided into different classes, depending on their relationship with the ''datu''. They traditionally went on seasonal raids on enemy settlements.
:* Commoners and slaves - (Visayan, [[Maguindanao people|Maguindanao]]: ''[[ulipon]]''; Tagalog: ''[[alipin]]''; Tausug: ''kiapangdilihan''; [[Maranao people|Maranao]]: ''kakatamokan'') - the lowest class composed of the rest of the community who were not part of the enfranchised classes. They were further subdivided into the commoner class who had their own houses, the servants who lived in the houses of others, and the slaves who were usually captives from raids, criminals, or debtors. Most members of this class were equivalent to the European [[serf]] class, who paid taxes and can be conscripted to communal tasks, but were more or less free to do as they please.

===East Asia===

====China and Mongolia====

During the period of [[Yuan Dynasty]], ruler [[Kublai Khan]] enforced a ''Four Class System'', which was a legal caste system. The order of four classes of people was maintained by the information of the descending order were:
* [[Mongols|Mongolian]]
* [[Semu]] people
* [[Han Chinese|Han]] people (in the northern areas of China)
* Southerners (people of the former Southern [[Song dynasty]])

Today, the [[Hukou system]] is considered by various sources as the current caste system of [[China]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Chinese Society: Change, Conflict and Resistance&quot;, by Elizabeth J. Perry, Mark Selden, page [https://books.google.com/books?id=JqZyQCZmrRAC&amp;pg=PA90 90]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;China's New Confucianism: Politics and Everyday Life in a Changing Society&quot;, p. 86, by Daniel A. Bell&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title =Trust and Distrust: Sociocultural Perspectives|page = 63|chapter-url = https://books.google.com/books?id=bvknDwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA63#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|editor1-first= Ivana |editor1-last= Marková|editor2-first= Alex|editor2-last= Gillespie|author = Li Liu|chapter = Filial Piety, ''Guanxi'', Loyalty, and Money |publisher = IAP|year = 2007|isbn = 9781607526322}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There is also significant controversy over the [[social classes of Tibet]], especially with regards to the [[serfdom in Tibet controversy]].

====Japan====
{{Main|Edo society}}

[[File:Edo social structure.svg|thumb|left|Social classes during the Edo period ([[Tokugawa shogunate]])]]

In Japan's history, social strata based on inherited position rather than personal merit, were rigid and highly formalized in a system called ''mibunsei'' (身分制). At the top were the Emperor and Court nobles ([[kuge]]), together with the Shōgun and daimyō. Below them, the population was divided into [[Four occupations|four classes]]: [[samurai]], peasants, craftsmen and merchants. Only samurai were allowed to bear arms. A samurai had a right to kill any peasants, craftsman or merchant who he felt were disrespectful. Merchants were the lowest caste because they did not produce any products. The castes were further sub-divided; for example, peasants were labelled as ''furiuri'', ''tanagari'', ''mizunomi-byakusho'' among others. As in Europe, the castes and sub-classes were of the same race, religion and culture.

Howell, in his review of [[Japan]]ese society notes that if a Western power had colonized Japan in the 19th century, they would have discovered and imposed a rigid four-caste hierarchy in Japan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Geographies of identity in nineteenth-century Japan|author=David L. Howell|publisher=University of California Press|isbn=978-0-520-24085-8|year=2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

De Vos and Wagatsuma observe that Japanese society had a systematic and extensive caste system. They discuss how alleged caste impurity and alleged racial inferiority, concepts often assumed to be different, are superficial terms, and are due to identical inner psychological processes, which expressed themselves in Japan and elsewhere.&lt;ref name=gdvhw&gt;{{cite book|title=Japan's invisible race: caste in culture and personality|url=https://archive.org/details/japansinvisibler00devorich|url-access=registration|author=George De Vos and Hiroshi Wagatsuma|publisher=University of California Press|year=1966|isbn=978-0-520-00306-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Endogamy was common because marriage across caste lines was socially unacceptable.&lt;ref name=gdvhw/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Japanese Fashion: A Cultural History|author=Toby Slade|publisher=Berg|isbn=978-1-84788-252-3|year=2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Japan]] had its own untouchable caste, shunned and ostracized, historically referred to by the insulting term ''Eta'', now called ''[[Burakumin]]''. While modern law has officially abolished the class hierarchy, there are reports of discrimination against the [[Buraku]] or [[Burakumin]] underclasses.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hrdc.net/sahrdc/hrfeatures/HRF39.htm |title=Class, Ethnicity and Nationality: Japan Finds Plenty of Space for Discrimination |publisher=Hrdc.net |date=2001-06-18 |accessdate=2013-11-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Burakumin are regarded as &quot;ostracised&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal
| author = William H. Newell
|date=December 1961
| title = The Comparative Study of Caste in India and Japan
| journal = Asian Survey
| volume = 1
| issue = 10
| pages = 3–10
| doi = 10.1525/as.1961.1.10.01p15082
| jstor=3023467
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; The burakumin are one of the main [[demographics of Japan|minority groups in Japan]], along with the [[Ainu people|Ainu]] of [[Hokkaidō]] and those of [[Zainichi Korean|residents of Korean]] and [[Chinese in Japan|Chinese]] descent.

====Korea====
{{Korean caste system}}
[[File:Korea-History-Goban Game in Seoul Korea 1904 (LOC).jpg|thumbnail|A typical Yangban family scene from 1904.  The Yoon family had an enduring presence in Korean politics from the 1800s until the 1970s.]]

The [[baekjeong]] (백정) were an &quot;untouchable&quot; outcaste of Korea. The meaning today is that of butcher. It originates in the [[Goryeo-Khitan Wars|Khitan invasion of Korea]] in the 11th century. The defeated [[Khitans]] who surrendered were settled in isolated communities throughout Goryeo to forestall rebellion.  They were valued for their skills in hunting, herding, butchering, and making of leather, common skill sets among nomads.  Over time, their ethnic origin was forgotten, and they formed the bottom layer of Korean society.

In 1392, with the foundation of the Confucian [[Joseon dynasty]], Korea systemised its own native class system. At the top were the two official classes, the [[Yangban]], which literally means &quot;two classes&quot;. It was composed of scholars (''munban'') and warriors (''muban''). Scholars had a significant social advantage over the warriors. Below were the ''jung-in'' (중인-中人: literally &quot;middle people&quot;. This was a small class of specialized professions such as medicine, accounting, translators, regional bureaucrats, etc. Below that were the ''sangmin'' (상민-常民: literally 'commoner'), farmers working their own fields. Korea also had a [[serf]] population known as the ''nobi''. The nobi population could fluctuate up to about one third of the population, but on average the nobi made up about 10% of the total population.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Rodriguez|first1=Junius P.|title=The Historical Encyclopedia of World Slavery|publisher=ABC-CLIO|isbn=9780874368857|page=392|url=https://books.google.com/?id=ATq5_6h2AT0C&amp;pg=RA1-PA392&amp;dq=%2210+percent+of+the+total+population+on+average,+but+it+could+rise+up+to+one-third+of+the+total%22#v=onepage&amp;q=%2210%20percent%20of%20the%20total%20population%20on%20average%2C%20but%20it%20could%20rise%20up%20to%20one-third%20of%20the%20total%22&amp;f=false|accessdate=14 February 2017|language=en|year=1997}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1801, the vast majority of government nobi were emancipated,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Kim|first1=Youngmin|last2=Pettid|first2=Michael J.|title=Women and Confucianism in Choson Korea: New Perspectives|publisher=SUNY Press|isbn=9781438437774|page=141|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=UwgUa6WWFBMC&amp;pg=PA141#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|accessdate=14 February 2017|language=en|date=2011-11-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; and by 1858 the nobi population stood at about 1.5% of the total population of Korea.&lt;ref name=&quot;nobi&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Campbell|first1=Gwyn|title=Structure of Slavery in Indian Ocean Africa and Asia|publisher=Routledge|isbn=9781135759179|page=163|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=J0iRAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA163#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|accessdate=14 February 2017|language=en|date=2004-11-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; The hereditary nobi system was officially abolished around 1886–87 and the rest of the nobi system was abolished with the [[Gabo Reform]] of 1894,&lt;ref name=&quot;nobi&quot; /&gt; but traces remained until 1930.

The opening of Korea to foreign Christian missionary activity in the late 19th century saw some improvement in the status of the ''baekjeong''. However, everyone was not equal under the Christian congregation, and even so protests erupted when missionaries tried to integrate ''baekjeong'' into worship, with non-''baekjeong'' finding this attempt insensitive to traditional notions of hierarchical advantage.{{Citation needed|date=September 2007}} Around the same time, the ''baekjeong'' began to resist open social discrimination.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|chapter=In Search of Human Rights: The Paekchŏng Movement in Colonial Korea|title=Colonial Modernity in Korea|first=Joong-Seop|last=Kim|editor=Gi-Wook Shin and Michael Robinson|year=1999|pages=326|isbn=978-0-674-00594-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; They focused on social and economic injustices affecting them, hoping to create an [[egalitarianism|egalitarian]] Korean society. Their efforts included attacking social discrimination by upper class, authorities, and &quot;commoners&quot;, and the use of degrading language against children in public schools.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Korean Paekjŏng under Japanese rule: the quest for equality and human rights|first=Joong-Seop|last=Kim|year=2003|pages=147}}&lt;/ref&gt;

With the [[Gabo reform]] of 1896, the class system of Korea was officially abolished. Following the collapse of the [[Enlightenment Party|Gabo government]], the new cabinet, which became the Gwangmu government after the establishment of the Korean Empire, introduced systematic measures for abolishing the traditional class system. One measure was the new household registration system, reflecting the goals of formal [[social equality]], which was implemented by the loyalists' cabinet. Whereas the old registration system signified household members according to their hierarchical social status, the new system called for an occupation.&lt;ref name=&quot;proper&quot;&gt;Hwang, Kyung Moon (2004), University of Southern California. ''Citizenship, Social Equality and Government Reform: Changes in the Household Registration System in Korea, 1894–1910''&lt;/ref&gt;

While most Koreans by then had surnames and even [[bongwan]], although still substantial number of [[cheonmin]], mostly consisted of [[serfs]] and slaves, and [[Untouchability|untouchables]] did not. According to the new system, they were then required to fill in the blanks for surname in order to be registered as constituting separate households. Instead of creating their own family name, some cheonmins appropriated their masters' surname, while others simply took the most common surname and its bongwan in the local area. Along with this example, activists within and outside the Korean government had based their visions of a new relationship between the government and people through the concept of citizenship, employing the term ''inmin'' (&quot;people&quot;) and later, ''kungmin'' (&quot;citizen&quot;).&lt;ref name=&quot;proper&quot;/&gt;

====North Korea====
{{Main|Songbun}}

The [[Committee for Human Rights in North Korea]] reported that &quot;Every North Korean citizen is assigned a heredity-based class and socio-political rank over which the individual exercises no control but which determines all aspects of his or her life.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=06 Jun 2012 |url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/asia/northkorea/9313174/North-Korea-caste-system-underpins-human-rights-abuses.html |title=North Korea caste system 'underpins human rights abuses' |publisher=Telegraph.co.uk |date=2012-06-06 |accessdate=2013-11-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; Called ''[[Songbun]]'', [[Barbara Demick]] describes this &quot;class structure&quot; as an updating of the hereditary &quot;caste system&quot;, a combination of [[Confucianism]] and [[Stalinism]].&lt;ref&gt;Barbara Demick, ''Nothing to Envy: Love, Life and Death in North Korea'', Fourth Estate, London, 2010, pp. 26–27.&lt;/ref&gt; She claims that a bad family background is called &quot;tainted blood&quot;, and that by law this &quot;tainted blood&quot; lasts three generations.&lt;ref&gt;Demick, pp. 28, 197, 202.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Tibet====
{{See also|Social classes of Tibet}}

{{ill|Heidi Fjeld|no|vertical-align=sup}} has put forth the argument that pre-1950s Tibetan society was functionally a caste system, in contrast to previous scholars who defined the Tibetan social class system as similar to European feudal serfdom, as well as non-scholarly western accounts which seek to romanticize a supposedly 'egalitarian' ancient Tibetan society.

===West Asia===
{{further|Yazidi}}

[[Yezidi]] society is hierarchical. The secular leader is a hereditary [[emir]] or prince, whereas a chief [[sheikh]] heads the religious hierarchy. The Yazidi are strictly [[Endogamy|endogamous]]; members of the three Yazidi castes, the [[murid]]s, sheikhs and [[Islam Pir|pir]]s, marry only within their group.

====Iran====

Pre-Islamic [[Sassanid]] society was immensely complex, with separate systems of social organization governing numerous different groups within the empire.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nicolle, p. 11&quot;&gt;Nicolle, p. 11&lt;/ref&gt; Historians believe society comprised four&lt;ref&gt;
These four are the three common &quot;Indo-Euoropean&quot; [[Trifunctional hypothesis|social tripartition]] common among ancient Iranian, Indian and Romans with one extra Iranian element (from Yashna xix/17). cf. Frye, p. 54.
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Persian Night: Iran under the Khomeinist Revolution|page=1982|author=Amir Taheri|publisher=Encounter books}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Why the Middle East Lagged Behind: The Case of Iran|page=72|author=Kāẓim ʻAlamdārī|publisher=University Press of America}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[social class]]es:

# priests ({{lang-fa|Asravan}})
# warriors ({{lang-fa|Arteshtaran}})
# secretaries ({{lang-fa|Dabiran}})
# commoners ({{lang-fa|Vastryoshan}})

====Yemen====
{{further|Al-Akhdam}}
In [[Yemen]] there exists a hereditary caste, the [[Africa]]n-descended [[Al-Akhdam]] who are kept as perennial manual workers. Estimates put their number at over 3.5 million residents who are discriminated, out of a total Yemeni population of around 22 million.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ireport.cnn.com/docs/DOC-999239|title=Yemen's Al-Akhdam face brutal oppression|website=CNN iReport|accessdate=22 October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Africa===
{{Main|Caste system in Africa}}

Various sociologists have reported caste systems in Africa.&lt;ref name=Obinna1&gt;{{cite journal|title=Contesting identity: the Osu caste system among Igbo of Nigeria|author=Elijah Obinna|pages=111–121|journal=African Identities|volume=10|issue=1|year=2012|doi=10.1080/14725843.2011.614412}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;James B. Watson 356–379&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|title=Caste as a Form of Acculturation|author=James B. Watson|journal=Southwestern Journal of Anthropology|volume=19|number= 4|date= Winter 1963|pages=356–379|doi=10.1086/soutjanth.19.4.3629284}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=tamari1/&gt; The specifics of the caste systems have varied in ethnically and culturally diverse Africa, however the following features are common – it has been a closed system of social stratification, the social status is inherited, the castes are hierarchical, certain castes are shunned while others are merely endogamous and exclusionary.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Caste discrimination in Africa|author=Leo Igwe|publisher=International Humanist and Ethical Union|date=21 August 2009|url=http://www.iheu.org/caste-discrimination-africa}}&lt;/ref&gt; In some cases, concepts of purity and impurity by birth have been prevalent in Africa. In other cases, such as the ''Nupe'' of Nigeria, the ''Beni Amer'' of East Africa, and the ''Tira'' of Sudan, the exclusionary principle has been driven by evolving social factors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Caste and government in primitive society|author=SF Nadel|journal=Journal of Anthropological Society|volume=8|pages=9–22|year=1954}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====West Africa====
[[File:GriotFête.jpg|thumb|upright|left|A [[Griot]], who have been described as an endogamous caste of West Africa who specialize in oral story telling and culture preservation. They have been also referred to as the bard caste.]]
Among the Igbo of [[Nigeria]] – especially [[Enugu State|Enugu]], [[Anambra State|Anambra]], [[Imo State|Imo]], [[Abia State|Abia]], [[Ebonyi State|Ebonyi]], [[Edo State|Edo]] and [[Delta state|Delta]] states of the country – Obinna finds Osu caste system has been and continues to be a major social issue. The Osu caste is determined by one's birth into a particular family irrespective of the religion practised by the individual. Once born into Osu caste, this Nigerian person is an outcast, shunned and ostracized, with limited opportunities or acceptance, regardless of his or her ability or merit. Obinna discusses how this caste system-related identity and power is deployed within government, Church and indigenous communities.&lt;ref name=Obinna1/&gt;

The ''osu'' class systems of eastern [[Nigeria]] and southern [[Cameroon]] are derived from indigenous religious beliefs and discriminate against the &quot;Osus&quot; people as &quot;owned by deities&quot; and outcasts.

The Songhai economy was based on a caste system. The most common were metalworkers, fishermen, and carpenters. Lower caste participants consisted of mostly non-farm working immigrants, who at times were provided special privileges and held high positions in society. At the top were noblemen and direct descendants of the original Songhai people, followed by freemen and traders.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.africankingdoms.com|title=Kingdoms of Ancient African History|website=www.africankingdoms.com|accessdate=22 October 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190519102901/http://africankingdoms.com/|archive-date=19 May 2019|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a review of social stratification systems in Africa, Richter reports that the term caste has been used by French and American scholars to many groups of West African artisans. These groups have been described as inferior, deprived of all political power, have a specific occupation, are hereditary and sometimes despised by others. Richter illustrates caste system in [[Ivory Coast]], with six sub-caste categories. Unlike other parts of the world, mobility is sometimes possible within sub-castes, but not across caste lines. Farmers and artisans have been, claims Richter, distinct castes. Certain sub-castes are shunned more than others. For example, exogamy is rare for women born into families of woodcarvers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Further considerations of caste in West Africa: The Senufo|author=Dolores Richter|journal=Africa|date= January 1980|volume=50|issue=1|pages=37–54|doi=10.2307/1158641|jstor=1158641}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Similarly, the [[Mandé peoples|Mandé]] societies in [[Gambia]], [[Ghana]], [[Guinea]], [[Ivory Coast]], [[Liberia]], [[Senegal]] and [[Sierra Leone]] have social stratification systems that divide society by ethnic ties. The Mande class system regards the ''jonow'' slaves as inferior. Similarly, the [[Wolof people|Wolof]] in Senegal is divided into three main groups, the ''geer'' (freeborn/nobles), ''jaam'' (slaves and slave descendants) and the underclass ''neeno''. In various parts of West Africa, [[Fula people|Fulani]] societies also have class divisions. Other castes include ''Griots'', ''Forgerons'', and ''Cordonniers''.

Tamari has described endogamous castes of over fifteen West African peoples, including the Tukulor, Songhay, Dogon, Senufo, Minianka, Moors, Manding, Soninke, Wolof, Serer, Fulani, and Tuareg. Castes appeared among the ''Malinke'' people no later than 14th century, and was present among the ''Wolof'' and ''Soninke'', as well as some ''Songhay'' and ''Fulani'' populations, no later than 16th century. Tamari claims that wars, such as the ''Sosso-Malinke'' war described in the ''Sunjata'' epic, led to the formation of blacksmith and bard castes among the people that ultimately became the Mali empire.

As West Africa evolved over time, sub-castes emerged that acquired secondary specializations or changed occupations. Endogamy was prevalent within a caste or among a limited number of castes, yet castes did not form demographic isolates according to Tamari. Social status according to caste was inherited by off-springs automatically; but this inheritance was paternal. That is, children of higher caste men and lower caste or slave concubines would have the caste status of the father.&lt;ref name=tamari1&gt;{{cite journal|journal=The Journal of African History|year=1991|volume=32|issue=2|pages=221–250|doi=10.1017/S0021853700025718|title=The Development of Caste Systems in West Africa|author=Tal Tamari}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Central Africa====
{{Expand section|date=February 2019}}

Ethel M. Albert in 1960 claimed that the societies in [[Central Africa]] were caste-like social stratification systems.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Socio-Political Organization and Receptivity to Change: Some Differences between Ruanda and Urundi|author=Ethel M. Albert|journal=Southwestern Journal of Anthropology|volume=16|number= 1|date= Spring 1960|pages=46–74|doi=10.1086/soutjanth.16.1.3629054}}&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, in 1961, Maquet notes that the society in [[Rwanda]] and [[Burundi]] can be best described as castes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Premise of Inequality in Ruanda: A Study of Political Relations in a Central African Kingdom|author= Jacques J. Maquet|year=1962|pages=135–171|publisher=Oxford University Press, London|isbn=978-0-19-823168-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Tutsi]], noted Maquet, considered themselves as superior, with the more numerous [[Hutu]] and the least numerous [[Twa]] regarded, by birth, as respectively, second and third in the hierarchy of Rwandese society. These groups were largely endogamous, exclusionary and with limited mobility.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Power in Ruanda|author=Helen Codere|journal=Anthropologica|volume=4|number=1|year=1962|pages=45–85|jstor=25604523|doi=10.2307/25604523}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Horn of Africa====
[[File:NSRW Africa Midgan.png|thumb|upright|The [[Madhiban]] (Midgan) specialize in leather occupation. Along with the Tumal and Yibir, they are collectively known as ''sab''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lewis&quot;/&gt;]]
In a review published in 1977, Todd reports that numerous scholars report a system of social stratification in different parts of Africa that resembles some or all aspects of caste system. Examples of such caste systems, he claims, are to be found in Ethiopia in communities such as the [[Gurage people|Gurage]] and [[Konso people|Konso]]. He then presents the Dime of Southwestern Ethiopia, amongst whom there operates a system which Todd claims can be unequivocally labelled as caste system. The Dime have seven castes whose size varies considerably. Each broad caste level is a hierarchical order that is based on notions of purity, non-purity and impurity. It uses the concepts of defilement to limit contacts between caste categories and to preserve the purity of the upper castes. These caste categories have been exclusionary, endogamous and the social identity inherited.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=La Caste en Afrique? (Caste in Africa?)|author=D. M. Todd|journal=Africa|date=October 1977|volume=47 |issue=4|pages= 398–412|url=http://journals.cambridge.org/action/displayAbstract?fromPage=online&amp;aid=7903506|doi=10.2307/1158345|jstor=1158345}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Alula Pankhurst]] has published a study of caste groups in SW Ethiopia.&lt;ref&gt;Pankhurst, Alula. 1999. {{&quot;'}}Caste' in Africa: the evidence from south-western Ethiopia reconsidered&quot;. ''Africa'' 69(4), pp. 485–509.&lt;/ref&gt;

Among the [[Kingdom of Kafa|Kafa]], there were also traditionally groups labeled as castes. &quot;Based on research done before the Derg regime, these studies generally presume the existence of a social hierarchy similar to the caste system. At the top of this hierarchy were the Kafa, followed by occupational groups including blacksmiths (Qemmo), weavers (Shammano), bards (Shatto), potters, and tanners (Manno). In this hierarchy, the Manjo were commonly referred to as hunters, given the lowest status equal only to slaves.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;p. 299. Sayuri Yoshida. &quot;Why did the Manjo convert to Protestant? Social Discrimination and Coexistence in Kafa, Southwest Ethiopia?&quot; ''Proceedings of the 16th International Conference of Ethiopian Studies'', ed. by Svein Ege, Harald
Aspen, Birhanu Teferra and Shiferaw Bekele, Trondheim 2009. pp. 299–309.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Borana Oromo]] of southern [[Ethiopia]] in the [[Horn of Africa]] also have a class system, wherein the Wata, an acculturated hunter-gatherer group, represent the lowest class. Though the Wata today speak the [[Oromo language]], they have traditions of having previously spoken another language before adopting Oromo.&lt;ref name=&quot;Westermann&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Diedrich Westermann|first=Edwin William Smith, Cyril Daryll Forde|title=Africa|year=1981|publisher=Oxford University Press|page=853}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The traditionally nomadic [[Somali people]] are divided into clans, wherein the [[Rahanweyn]] agro-pastoral clans and the occupational clans such as the [[Madhiban]] were traditionally sometimes treated as outcasts.&lt;ref&gt;I. M. Lewis, ''A pastoral democracy: a study of pastoralism and politics among the Northern Somali of the Horn of Africa'' (LIT Verlag Berlin-Hamburg-Münster: 1999), pp. 13–14&lt;/ref&gt; As Gabboye, the Madhiban along with the [[Yibir]] and Tumaal (collectively referred to as ''sab'') have since obtained political representation within [[Somalia]], and their general social status has improved with the expansion of urban centers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lewis&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Lewis|first=I.M.|title=Understanding Somalia and Somaliland: Culture, History, Society|year=2008|publisher=Columbia University Press|isbn=978-0231700849|pages=8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Europe===

==== France and Spain ====
{{Expand section|date=February 2019}}

For centuries, through the modern times, the majority regarded [[Cagot]]s who lived primarily in the Basque region of France and Spain as an inferior caste, the untouchables. While they had the same skin color and religion as the majority, in the churches they had to use segregated doors, drink from segregated fonts, and receive communion on the end of long wooden spoons. It was a closed social system. The socially isolated Cagots were endogamous, and chances of social mobility non-existent.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=The last untouchable in Europe|author=Sean Thomas|date=28 July 2008|publisher=The Independent, United Kingdom|url=https://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/europe/the-last-untouchable-in-europe-878705.html|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hansson1996&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Anders Hansson|title=Chinese Outcasts: Discrimination and Emancipation in Late Imperial China|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=4Ibp1RTW0AoC&amp;pg=PA15|year=1996|publisher=Brill|isbn=978-90-04-10596-6|pages=15–16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====United Kingdom====
In July 2013, the UK government announced its intention to amend the [[Equality Act 2010]], to &quot;introduce legislation on caste, including any necessary exceptions to the caste provisions, within the framework of domestic discrimination law&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Government Equalities Office, [https://www.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/225658/130726-Caste-Discrimination.pdf Caste legislation introduction – programme and timetable], accessed 2 June 2016&lt;/ref&gt; Section 9(5) of the Equality Act 2010 provides that &quot;a [[Minister (government)|Minister]] may by [[Statutory order|order]] amend the statutory definition of race to include caste and may provide for exceptions in the Act to apply or not to apply to caste&quot;.

From September 2013 to February 2014, [[Meena Dhanda]] led a project on &quot;Caste in Britain&quot; for the UK [[Equality and Human Rights Commission]] (EHRC).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.equalityhumanrights.com/en/publication-download/research-report-91-caste-britain-socio-legal-review|title=Research report 91: Caste in Britain: Socio-legal Review {{!}} Equality and Human Rights Commission|website=www.equalityhumanrights.com|access-date=2017-10-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===United States===
{{main|racial segregation in the United States}}
In [[W. Lloyd Warner]]'s view, the historic relationship between [[African Americans|Blacks]] and [[White Americans|Whites]] in the US showed many caste-like features such as residential segregation and marriage restrictions.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | doi=10.1086/217391|title = American Caste and Class| journal=American Journal of Sociology| volume=42| issue=2| pages=234–237|year = 1936|last1 = Warner|first1 = W. Lloyd}}&lt;/ref&gt; Discrimination based upon socio-economic factors are historically prevalent within the country.

According to Gerald D. Berreman, in the two systems, there are rigid rules of avoidance and certain types of contacts are defined as contaminating. In India, there are complex religious features which make up the system, whereas in the United States race and color are the basis for differentiation. The caste systems in India and the United States have higher groups which desire to retain their positions for themselves and thus perpetuate the two systems.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Berreman|first=Gerald|date=September 1960|title=Caste in India and the United States|journal=American Journal of Sociology|volume=66|issue=2|pages=120–127|jstor=2773155|doi=10.1086/222839}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The process of creating a homogenized society by social engineering in both India and the US has created other institutions that have made class distinctions among different groups evident. Anthropologist James C. Scott elaborates on how “global [[capitalism]] is perhaps the most powerful force for homogenization, whereas the state may be the defender of local difference and variety in some instances.”&lt;ref&gt;https://libcom.org/files/Seeing%20Like%20a%20State%20-%20James%20C.%20Scott.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; The caste system further emphasizes differences between the socio-economic classes that arise as a product of capitalism,  which makes social mobility more difficult. Parts of the United States are sometimes divided by race and class status despite the national narrative of integration.

As a result of increased immigration, many [[Indian Americans]] have brought their traditional caste values to the United States. A survey commissioned by Equality Labs finds that caste discrimination is also playing out in the United States. 2/3 of the members of the lowest caste, called Dalits, said that they have faced workplace discrimination due to their caste. 41% of the Dalits who were surveyed said that they have experienced discrimination in education because the caste system is now being practiced in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;Subramanian Shankar Feed Subramanian Shankar, and University of Hawaii.“Does America Have a Caste System?” CityLab, The Atlantic Monthly Group, 26 Jan. 2018, www.citylab.com/equity/2018/01/does-america-have-a-caste-system/551591/.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Estates of the realm]]
*[[Kamaiya]]
*[[Priestly caste]]
*[[Propiska in the Soviet Union|Propiska]]
*[[Social exclusion]]
*[[Warrior caste]]{{dn|date=November 2019}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Sources==
{{refbegin}}
*{{citation|last=Béteille
|first =André|editor-last=Barnard|editor-first=Alan|editor2-last=Spencer|editor2-first=Jonathan|chapter=Caste|title=Encyclopedia of Social and Cultural Anthropology|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=o1VpdrbH3BUC&amp;pg=PA136|year=2002|location=New York; London|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-0-415-28558-2|pages=136–137}}
*{{citation|editor-last=Doniger|editor-first=Wendy|title=Merriam-Webster's Encyclopedia of World Religions|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ZP_f9icf2roC&amp;pg=PA186|accessdate=24 September 2012|year=1999|publisher=Merriam-Webster|location=Springfield, MA|isbn=978-0-87779-044-0|page=[https://archive.org/details/isbn_9780877790440/page/186 186]|chapter=Caste|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/isbn_9780877790440/page/186}}
*{{citation|last=Gupta
|first=Dipankar|chapter=Caste|editor-last=Schaefer|editor-first=Richard T.|title=Encyclopedia of Race, Ethnicity, and Society|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=YMUola6pDnkC&amp;pg=PA246|location=Thousand Oaks|accessdate=5 August 2012|year=2008|publisher=Sage|isbn=978-1-4129-2694-2|pages=246–250}}
*{{citation|editor-last=Lagasse
|editor-first=Paul|title=The Columbia Encyclopedia|chapter=Caste|chapter-url=http://www.encyclopedia.com/topic/caste.aspx#3|accessdate=24 September 2012|year=2007|publisher=Columbia University Press|location=New York|isbn=978-0-231-14446-9}}
*{{citation|last1=Madan
|first1=T. N.|authorlink1=T. N. Madan|last2=Editors|title=caste|publisher= Encyclopæida Britannica Online|url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/98395/caste|date=2012}}
*{{citation|last=Mitchell
|first=Geoffrey Duncan|title=A New Dictionary of the Social Sciences|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=-a4vvdBrSVgC&amp;pg=PA194|accessdate=10 August 2012|date=2006|publisher=Aldine Transaction Publishers|isbn=978-0-202-30878-4|pages=194–195|chapter=Castes (part of Social Stratification)|location=New Brunswick, NJ}}
*{{citation|last=Morris
|first=Mike|title=Concise Dictionary of Social and Cultural Anthropology|chapter=caste|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=5lTQRZru1SQC&amp;pg=PA33|accessdate=10 August 2012|date= 2012|publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons|isbn=978-1-4443-3209-4|location=Malden, MA|page=33}}
*{{citation|last=Nagar
|first=Richa|authorlink=Richa Nagar|editor=Derek Gregory|others=Ron Johnston, Geraldine Pratt, Michael Watts, Sarah Whatmore|title=The Dictionary of Human Geography|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=5gCHckKszz0C&amp;pg=PA72|accessdate=10 August 2012|year=2011|publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons|isbn=978-1-4443-5995-4|page=72|chapter=caste}}
*''[[Oxford English Dictionary]]'' ({{citation|chapter=caste, n.|title  = Oxford English Dictionary, Second edition; online version June 2012|publisher = Oxford University Press|location=Oxford, UK|chapter-url=http://www.oed.com/view/Entry/28546|accessdate =5 August 2012|year = 1989}}) Quote: '''caste, n.''' 2a. spec. One of the several hereditary classes into which society in India has from time immemorial been divided; ... ''This is now the leading sense, which influences all others.''
*{{citation|last=Parry
|first = Jonathan| editor1-last=Kuper|editor1-first=Adam|editor2-last=Kuper|editor2-first=Jessica|chapter=Caste|title=Social Science Encyclopedia|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=IKXj9sQ3aqIC&amp;pg=PA131|year=2003|location=London and New York|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-0-415-28560-5|page=131}}
*{{citation|last=Pavri|first=Firooza|editor=Tim Forsyth|title=Encyclopedia of International Development|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=93OsjK8GjE0C&amp;pg=PA63|year=2004|publisher=Routledge|location=Abingdon, Oxon; New York|isbn=978-0-415-25342-0|pages=[https://archive.org/details/encyclopediaofin0000unse_u5w6/page/63 63–]|chapter=Caste|url=https://archive.org/details/encyclopediaofin0000unse_u5w6/page/63}}
*{{citation|last=Ramu
|first=G. N.|editor=William A. Darity|title=International Encyclopedia of the Social Sciences|chapter-url=http://www.encyclopedia.com/topic/caste.aspx#2|accessdate=24 September 2012|series=(Macmillan social science library)|year=2008|publisher=Macmillan Reference US|location=Detroit, MI|isbn=978-0-02-865967-1|chapter=Caste}}
*{{citation|last=Roberts
|first=Nathaniel P.|editor=William A. Darity|title=International Encyclopedia of the Social Sciences|chapter-url=http://www.encyclopedia.com/doc/1G2-3045300290.html|accessdate=24 September 2012|series=Macmillan social science library|year=2008|publisher=Macmillan Reference US|location=Detroit, MI|isbn=978-0-02-865967-1|chapter=Anthropology of Caste}}
*{{citation|last=Salamone
|first=Frank A.|editor-first=Junius P. |editor-last=Rodriguez|chapter=Caste|title=The Historical Encyclopedia of World Slavery, Volume 1|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ATq5_6h2AT0C&amp;pg=PA133|location=Santa Barbara, CA; Oxford, UK|accessdate=5 August 2012|year=1997|publisher=ABC-CLIO|isbn=978-0-87436-885-7|page=133}}
*{{citation|last1=Scott
|first1=John|last2=Marshall|first2=Gordon|title=A Dictionary of Sociology|chapter=caste|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=id8iAQAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA66|location=Oxford; New York|accessdate=10 August 2012|year=2005|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-860987-2|page=66}}
*{{citation|last=Sonnad
|first=Subhash R. |editor1-last=Christensen|editor1-first=Karen|editor2-last=Levinson|editor2-first=David|title=Encyclopedia of Community: From the Village to the Virtual World|chapter=Caste|pages=115&amp;ndash;121|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=t1geOjQ6R0MC&amp;pg=PA115|accessdate=5 August 2012|year=2003|publisher=Sage|location=Thousand Oaks, CA|isbn=978-0-7619-2598-9}}
*{{citation|last=Sooryamoorthi
|first=Radhamany|editor-last=Leonard|editor-first=Thomas M.|chapter=Caste Systems|title=Encyclopedia of the Developing World|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=3mE04D9PMpAC&amp;pg=PA252|accessdate=5 August 2012|year=2006|location=New York|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-0-415-97662-6|pages=252–}}
*{{citation|last=Winthrop
|first=Robert H.|title=Dictionary of Concepts in Cultural Anthropology|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=3xoB_3C5N5QC&amp;pg=PA27|accessdate=10 August 2012|year=1991|publisher=ABC-CLIO|isbn=978-0-313-24280-9|pages=27–30}}
{{refend}}

==Further reading==
* ''Spectres of Agrarian Territory'' by David Ludden 11 December 2001
* &quot;Early Evidence for Caste in South India&quot;, pp.&amp;nbsp;467–492 in ''Dimensions of Social Life: Essays in honor of David G. Mandelbaum'', Edited by Paul Hockings and Mouton de Gruyter, Berlin, New York, Amsterdam, 1987.

==External links==
{{commons category}}
{{Wiktionary|caste}}
* [http://socserv.mcmaster.ca/econ/ugcm/3ll3/comte/Philosophy3.pdf Auguste Comte on why and how castes developed across the world - in The Positive Philosophy, Volume 3 (see page 55 onwards)]
* [http://sciencepolicy.colorado.edu/students/envs_5110/merton_sociology_science.pdf Robert Merton on Caste and The Sociology of Science]
* [http://www.cambridge.org/gb/knowledge/isbn/item1168367/?site_locale=en_GB Caste, Society and Politics in India from the Eighteenth Century to the Modern Age - [[Susan Bayly]]]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20061105095243/http://www.countercurrents.org/hr-marguerite250404.htm Class In Yemen] by Marguerite Abadjian (Archive of the Baltimore Sun)
* [http://idsn.org/ International Dalit Solidarity Network: An international advocacy group for Dalits]

{{Segregation by type|state=collapsed}}
{{Discrimination}}
{{Social class}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Caste| ]]
[[Category:Social status]]</text>
      <sha1>5x7m9ch8ew4b4radyw6eik4bp2tc1r7</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
