  <page>
    <title>Conspiracy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7230</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942830276</id>
      <parentid>938595401</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-27T03:02:09Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>The Eloquent Peasant</username>
        <id>18054835</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Importing Wikidata [[Wikipedia:Short description|short description]]: &quot;Secret plan or agreement for an unlawful or harmful purpose, especially with political motivation&quot; ([[Wikipedia:Shortdesc helper|Shortdesc helper]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Secret plan or agreement for an unlawful or harmful purpose, especially with political motivation}}
{{For|a secret agreement between two or more parties to limit open competition|Collusion}}
{{other uses}}
[[File:The Gunpowder Plot Conspirators, 1605 from NPG.jpg|thumb|Illustration of the conspirators in the [[Gunpowder Plot]], a secret plan devised in 1605 to blow up the Parliament of the United Kingdom.]]

A '''conspiracy''', also known as a '''plot''', is a secret plan or agreement between persons (called '''conspirers''' or '''conspirators''') for an unlawful or harmful purpose, such as [[murder]] or [[treason]], especially with political motivation,&lt;ref&gt;''Collins Dictionary'': [https://www.collinsdictionary.com/pt/dictionary/english/conspiracy conspiracy]&lt;/ref&gt; while keeping their agreement [[secret]] from the public or from other people affected by it. In a political sense, conspiracy refers to a group of people united in the goal of usurping, altering or overthrowing an established [[political power]]. Depending on the circumstances, a conspiracy may also be a [[crime]], or a [[civil wrong]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/conspiracy |title=Conspiracy |publisher=merriam-webster.com |accessdate=December 27, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; The term generally implies wrongdoing or illegality on the part of the conspirators, as people would not need to conspire to engage in activities that were lawful and ethical, or to which no one would object.

There are some coordinated activities that people engage in with secrecy that are not generally thought of as conspiracies. For example, intelligence agencies such as the American [[Central Intelligence Agency|CIA]] and the British [[Secret Intelligence Service|MI6]] necessarily make plans in secret to spy on suspected enemies of their respective countries, but this kind of activity is generally not considered to be a conspiracy so long as their goal is to fulfill their official functions, and not something like improperly enriching themselves.&lt;ref name=&quot;Knight&quot;&gt;Peter Knight, ''Conspiracy Theories in American History: An Encyclopedia'' (2003), p. 15-16.&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, the coaches of competing sports teams routinely meet behind closed doors to plan game strategies and specific plays designed to defeat their opponents, but this activity is not considered a conspiracy because this is considered a legitimate part of the sport. Furthermore, a conspiracy must be engaged in knowingly. The continuation of social traditions that work to the advantage of certain groups and to the disadvantage of certain other groups, though possibly unethical, is not a conspiracy if participants in the practice are not carrying it forward for the purpose of perpetuating this advantage.&lt;ref name=&quot;Knight&quot;/&gt;

On the other hand, if the intent of carrying out a conspiracy exists, then there is a conspiracy even if the details are never agreed to aloud by the participants.&lt;ref name=&quot;Knight&quot;/&gt; CIA [[covert operation]]s, for instance, are by their very nature hard to prove definitively. But research into the agency's work, as well as revelations by former CIA employees, has suggested several cases where the agency tried to influence events.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.bbc.com/news/world-africa-36303327 Four more ways the CIA has meddled in Africa]. BBC, 17 May 2016.&lt;/ref&gt; Between 1947 and 1989, the United States tried to change other nations' governments 72 times. During the [[Cold War]], 26 of the United States' covert operations successfully brought a U.S.-backed government to power; the remaining 40 failed.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/monkey-cage/wp/2016/12/23/the-cia-says-russia-hacked-the-u-s-election-here-are-6-things-to-learn-from-cold-war-attempts-to-change-regimes/ The U.S. tried to change other countries' governments 72 times during the Cold War]. By Lindsey A. O'Rourke. ''[[The Washington Post]]'', December 23, 2016&lt;/ref&gt;

A &quot;[[conspiracy theory]]&quot; is a belief that a conspiracy has actually been decisive in producing a political event of which the theorists strongly disapprove.&lt;ref&gt;Joseph E. Uscinski and Joseph M. Parent, ''American Conspiracy Theories'' (2014) [https://www.amazon.com/dp/0199351813/ref=rdr_ext_tmb excerpt]&lt;/ref&gt; Political scientist [[Michael Barkun]] has described conspiracy theories as relying on the view that the universe is governed by design, and embody three principles: nothing happens by accident, nothing is as it seems, and everything is connected.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Barkun|first1=Michael|author-link1=Michael Barkun|title=A Culture of Conspiracy: Apocalyptic Visions in Contemporary America|date=2003|publisher=University of California Press|location=Berkeley|pages=3–4|ref=harv|title-link=A Culture of Conspiracy}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another common feature is that conspiracy theories evolve to incorporate whatever evidence exists against them, so that they become, as Barkun writes, a closed system that is [[Falsifiability|unfalsifiable]], and therefore &quot;a matter of faith rather than proof&quot;.{{sfn|Barkun|2003|p=7}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Barkun|first1=Michael|author-link1=Michael Barkun|title=Chasing Phantoms: Reality, Imagination, and Homeland Security Since 9/11|date=2011|publisher=University of North Carolina Press|location=Chapel Hill|page=10|ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://foreignpolicy.com/2013/08/20/mapped-the-7-governments-the-u-s-has-overthrown/ Mapped: The 7 Governments the U.S. Has Overthrown]. Yes, we now have confirmation that the CIA was behind Iran's 1953 coup. But the agency hardly stopped there. By J. Dana Stuster. ''[[Foreign Policy]]'', August 20, 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Types of conspiracies==
* [[Conspiracy (civil)]], an agreement between people to deceive, mislead, or defraud others of their legal rights or to gain an unfair advantage.
* [[Conspiracy (criminal)]], an agreement between people to break the law in the future, in some cases having committed an act to further that agreement.
* [[List of political conspiracies|Conspiracy (political)]], an agreement between people with the goal of gaining political power or meeting a political objective.
* [[Hub-and-spoke conspiracy]], a conspiracy in which one or more principal conspirators (the &quot;hub&quot;) enter into several similar agreements with others (the &quot;spokes&quot;) who know concerted action is contemplated, usually where the success of the concerted action depends on the participation of the other spokes.

==See also==
* [[Conspiracy theory]]
* [[List of political conspiracies]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
{{wikiquote}}
{{commons category|Conspiracies}}

{{clear}}

[[Category:Conspiracy| ]]</text>
      <sha1>5knxkrpuyproi6powrb1e2x1vil7t4y</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
