  <page>
    <title>Cross-examination</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7203</id>
    <revision>
      <id>937963352</id>
      <parentid>929254709</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-28T08:46:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ghd256</username>
        <id>31583418</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Variations by jurisdiction */ Fixed a factual error.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{about|the court proceeding|the policy debate concept|Structure of policy debate|the research methodology|Triangulation (social science)}}
{{short description|The interrogation of a witness called by one's opponent}}
{{multiple issues|
{{more footnotes|date=August 2012}}
{{Globalize|article|USA|2name=the United States|date=October 2011|talk=Talk:Cross-examination#US}}
}}

{{Evidence law}}
In [[law]], '''cross-examination''' is the interrogation of a [[witness]] called by one's opponent. It is preceded by [[direct examination]] (in [[Republic of Ireland|Ireland]], the [[United Kingdom]], [[Australia]], [[Canada]], [[South Africa]], [[India]] and [[Pakistan]] known as examination-in-chief) and may be followed by a [[Redirect examination|redirect]] (re-examination in [[Republic of Ireland|Ireland]], [[England]], [[Scotland]], [[Australia]], [[Canada]], [[South Africa]], [[India]], [[Hong Kong]], and [[Pakistan]]). Redirect examination, performed by the attorney or pro se individual who performed the direct examination, clarifies the witness' testimony provided during cross-examination including any subject matter raised during cross-examination but not discussed during direct examination. Recross examination addresses the witness' testimony discussed in redirect by the opponent. Depending on the judge's discretion, opponents are allowed multiple opportunities to redirect and recross examine witnesses (may vary by jurisdiction).

== Variations by jurisdiction ==
In the [[Federal judiciary of the United States|United States federal Courts]], a cross-examining [[lawyer|attorney]] is typically not permitted to ask questions that do not pertain to the testimony offered during direct examination, but most [[State court (United States)|state courts]] do permit a lawyer to cross-examine a witness on matters not raised during direct examination. Similarly, courts in England, South Africa, Australia, and Canada allow a cross-examiner to exceed the scope of direct examination.

Since a witness called by the opposing party is presumed to be [[hostile witness|hostile]], cross-examination does permit [[leading question]]s. A witness called by a direct examiner, on the other hand, may only be treated as hostile by that examiner after being permitted to do so by the judge, at the request of that examiner and as a result of the witness being openly antagonistic and/or prejudiced against the party that called them.&lt;ref&gt;Ehrhardt, Charles W. and Stephanie J. Young, [http://www.law.fsu.edu/journals/lawreview/issues/232/ehrhardt.html &quot;Using Leading Questions During Direct Examination&quot;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20081103082145/http://www.law.fsu.edu/journals/lawreview/issues/232/ehrhardt.html |date=2008-11-03 }}, Florida State University Law Review, 1996. Accessed November 26, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Affecting the outcome of jury trials ==
Cross-examination is a key component in a trial and the topic is given substantial attention during courses on [[Trial Advocacy]].&lt;ref&gt;Lubet, Steven; ''Modern Trial Advocacy'', NITA, New York, NY 2004 pp. 83 et. seq. {{ISBN|1556818866}}&lt;/ref&gt; The opinions by a jury or judge are often changed during cross examination if doubt is cast on the witness. In other times a credible witness affirms the belief in their original statements or in some cases enhances the judge's or jury's belief. Though the closing argument is often considered the deciding moment of a trial, effective cross-examination wins trials.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| title=Relentless Criminal Cross-Examination| last=Mahoney| first=Kevin J| location=Costa Mesa, California| publisher=James Publishing| year=2008| isbn=158012125X}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Attorneys anticipate [[hostile witness]]' responses during pretrial planning, and often attempt to shape the witnesses' perception of the questions to draw out information helpful to the attorney's case.&lt;ref&gt;Dreier, A.S.; ''Strategy, Planning &amp; Litigating to Win''; Conatus, Boston, MA, 2012, pp. 79-85; {{ISBN|0615676952}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Typically during an attorney's [[closing argument]] he will repeat any admissions made by witnesses that favor their case. Indeed, in the United States, cross-examination is seen as a core part of the entire [[adversarial system]] of justice, in that it &quot;is the principal means by which the believability of a witness and the truth of his testimony are tested.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Davis v. Alaska'', {{ussc|415|308|1974}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Another key component affecting a trial outcome is the [[jury selection]], in which attorneys will attempt to include jurors from whom they feel they can get a favorable response or at the least unbiased fair decision. So while there are many factors affecting the outcome of a trial, the cross-examination of a witness will often influence an open-minded unbiased jury searching for the certainty of facts upon which to base their decision.

==See also==
* {{annotated link|Litigation strategy}}
* {{annotated link|Testimony}}
* {{annotated link|Trial advocacy}}
* {{annotated link|Witness impeachment}}

==References==
&lt;references /&gt;

== Further reading ==
{{Wiktionary|cross-examination}}
*{{cite book | title=Advocacy 2007/2008 (Blackstone Bar Manual) | author=[[City Law School]] | location=Oxford | publisher=[[Oxford University Press]] | year=2007 | isbn=0-19-921220-1 }}
*{{cite book | title=The Art of the Advocate | author=Du Cann, Richard | location=London | publisher=Penguin | year=1993 | isbn=0-14-017931-3 }}
*{{cite book | title=The Golden Rules of Advocacy | author=Evans, K. | year=1993 | location=London | publisher=[[Blackstone Press]] | isbn=1-85431-259-6 }}
*{{cite book | title=The Devil's Advocate | author=Morley, I | location=London | publisher=[[Sweet &amp; Maxwell]] | year=2005 | isbn=0-421-91480-7 }}
*{{cite book | title=Advocacy | author=Ross, D. | location=London | publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]] | year=2005 | isbn=0-521-61117-2 }}
*{{cite book | title=[[The Art of Cross-Examination]] | author=Wellman, F. | year=2007 | isbn=1-59462-647-2 | origyear=1903 | publisher=[[Standard Publications]] }}
*{{cite book | title=Relentless Criminal Cross-Examination | author=Mahoney, K. | year=2008 | publisher=[[James Publishing Company]] | isbn=978-1-58012-125-5}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Cross-Examination}}
[[Category:Criminal procedure]]
[[Category:Civil procedure]]
[[Category:Evidence law]]
[[Category:Testimony]]</text>
      <sha1>55teptexcyykjq46umat55k2zgs7v5o</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
