  <page>
    <title>Central nervous system</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7251</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943370680</id>
      <parentid>943369837</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-03-01T14:27:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>DemocraticLuntz</username>
        <id>7627388</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/2402:3A80:1052:EC5E:9B76:B41F:E15B:6E1A|2402:3A80:1052:EC5E:9B76:B41F:E15B:6E1A]] identified as test/vandalism using [[WP:STiki|STiki]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox anatomy
| Name        = Central nervous system
| Latin       = Systema nervosum centrale&lt;br /&gt;pars centralis systematis nervosi&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | title=Farlex Partner Medical Dictionary, Farlex 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| Image       = 1201 Overview of Nervous System.jpg
| Caption     = Schematic diagram showing the central nervous system in yellow, peripheral in orange
| Width       = 300
| Lymph       = 224
| Acronym     = CNS
}}

The '''central nervous system''' ('''CNS''') is the part of the [[nervous system]] consisting of the [[brain]] and [[spinal cord]]. The CNS is so named because it integrates the received information and coordinates and influences the activity of all parts of the bodies of [[bilaterian|bilaterally symmetric animals]]—i.e., all multicellular animals except [[sponge]]s and [[Radiata|radially symmetric animals]] such as [[jellyfish]]—and it contains the majority of the nervous system. Many consider the [[retina]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Purves 2000&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last1 = Purves | first1 = Dale | title = Neuroscience, Second Edition | year = 2000 | url = https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK10799/ | isbn = 9780878937424 | location = Sunderland, MA | publisher = Sinauer Associates | url-status = live | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20140311185033/http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK10799/ | archivedate = 11 March 2014 | df = dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[optic nerve]] ([[cranial nerve]] II),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Medical Subject Headings (MeSH): Optic Nerve|url=https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/mesh/68009900|publisher=National Library of Medicine|accessdate=28 September 2013|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131002063049/http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/mesh/68009900|archivedate=2 October 2013|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Fitzgerald&quot; /&gt; as well as the [[olfactory nerves]] (cranial nerve I) and [[olfactory epithelium]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Gizurarson S. 2012 566–582&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | author = Gizurarson S | title = Anatomical and histologica\ ]=\ factors affecting intranasal drug and vaccine delivery. | journal = Current Drug Delivery | volume = 9 | issue = 6 | pages = 566–582 | year = 2012 | pmid = 22788696 | pmc = 3480721 | doi = 10.2174/156720112803529828 }}&lt;/ref&gt; as parts of the CNS, synapsing directly on brain tissue without intermediate [[ganglion|ganglia]]. As such, the [[olfactory epithelium]] is the only central nervous tissue in direct contact with the environment, which opens up for [[therapeutic]] treatments.
&lt;ref name=&quot;Gizurarson S. 2012 566–582&quot;/&gt; The CNS is contained within the [[dorsal body cavity]], with the [[brain]] housed in the [[cranial cavity]] and the spinal cord in the [[spinal canal]]. In vertebrates, the brain is protected by the [[skull]], while the spinal cord is protected by the [[vertebrae]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Maton&quot; /&gt; The brain and spinal cord are both enclosed in the [[meninges]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Maton&quot;&gt;{{cite book| last = Maton| first = Anthea| author2 = Jean Hopkins| author3 = Charles William McLaughlin| author4 = Susan Johnson| author5 = Maryanna Quon Warner| author6 = David LaHart| author7 = Jill D. Wright| title = Human Biology and Health| publisher = Prentice Hall| year = 1993| location = Englewood Cliffs, New Jersey, USA| pages = [https://archive.org/details/humanbiologyheal00scho/page/132 132–144]| isbn = 0-13-981176-1| url-access = registration| url = https://archive.org/details/humanbiologyheal00scho/page/132}}&lt;/ref&gt; Within the CNS, the interneuronal space is filled with a large amount of supporting non-nervous cells called neuroglia or [[glia]] from the Greek for &quot;glue&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;KettenmannFaissner1996&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Kettenmann|first1=H.|last2=Faissner|first2=A.|last3=Trotter|first3=J.|title=Neuron-Glia Interactions in Homeostasis and Degeneration|year=1996|pages=533–543|doi=10.1007/978-3-642-60946-6_27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Structure==
{{main article|Neuroanatomy}}
The CNS consists of the two major structures: the [[brain]] and [[spinal cord]]. The brain is encased in the skull, and protected by the cranium.&lt;ref name=&quot;Moore's&quot; /&gt; The spinal cord is continuous with the brain and lies [[anatomical terminology|caudally]] to the brain.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kandel&quot; /&gt; It is protected by the [[vertebra]]e.&lt;ref name=&quot;Moore's&quot; /&gt; The spinal cord reaches from the base of the skull, continues through&lt;ref name=&quot;Moore's&quot; /&gt; or starting below&lt;ref name=&quot;Huijzen&quot; /&gt; the [[foramen magnum]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Moore's&quot; /&gt; and terminates roughly level with the first or second [[lumbar vertebra]],&lt;ref name=Kandel&gt;{{cite book|vauthors= Kandel ER, Schwartz JH |title=Principles of neural science|year=2012|publisher=McGraw Hill|location=Appleton &amp; Lange|isbn=978-0-07-139011-8|pages=338–343|edition=5.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Huijzen&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Huijzen|first=R. Nieuwenhuys, J. Voogd, C. van|title=The human central nervous system|year=2007|publisher=Springer|location=Berlin|isbn=978-3-540-34686-9|page=3|edition=4th}}&lt;/ref&gt; occupying the upper sections of the [[vertebral canal]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Fitzgerald&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Estomih Mtui|first=M.J. Turlough FitzGerald, Gregory Gruener|title=Clinical neuroanatomy and neuroscience|publisher=Saunders|location=Edinburgh|isbn=978-0-7020-3738-2|page=38|edition=6th}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===White and gray matter===
{{main article|Gray matter|White matter}}
[[Image:1202 White and Gray Matter.jpg|thumb|right|Dissection of a brain with labels showing the clear division between white and gray matter.]]
Microscopically, there are differences between the neurons and tissue of the CNS and the [[peripheral nervous system]] (PNS).{{citation needed|date=December 2013}} The CNS is composed of [[white matter|white]] and [[gray matter]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Kandel&quot; /&gt; This can also be seen macroscopically on brain tissue. The white matter consists of [[axon]]s and [[oligodendrocyte]]s, while the gray matter consists of [[neuron]]s and unmyelinated fibers. Both tissues include a number of [[glia]]l cells (although the white matter contains more), which are often referred to as supporting cells of the CNS. Different forms of glial cells have different functions, some acting almost as scaffolding for [[neuroblast]]s to climb during [[neurogenesis]] such as [[bergmann glia]], while others such as [[microglia]] are a specialized form of [[macrophage]], involved in the [[immune system]] of the brain as well as the clearance of various [[metabolite]]s from the [[brain tissue]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Fitzgerald&quot; /&gt; [[Astrocyte]]s may be involved with both clearance of metabolites as well as transport of fuel and various beneficial substances to neurons from the [[capillary|capillaries]] of the brain. Upon CNS injury astrocytes will proliferate, causing [[gliosis]], a form of neuronal scar tissue, lacking in functional neurons.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fitzgerald&quot; /&gt;

The brain ([[cerebrum]] as well as [[midbrain]] and [[hindbrain]]) consists of a [[Cerebral cortex|cortex]], composed of neuron-bodies constituting gray matter, while internally there is more white matter that form [[Nerve tract|tract]]s and [[commissural fiber|commissures]]. Apart from cortical gray matter there is also [[subcortical gray matter]] making up a large number of different [[Nucleus (neuroanatomy)|nuclei]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Kandel&quot; /&gt;

===Spinal cord===
{{main article|Spinal cord}}
[[File:Sobo 1909 615.png|thumb|right|Diagram of the columns and of the course of the fibers in the spinal cord. Sensory synapses occur in the dorsal spinal cord (above in this image), and motor nerves leave through the ventral (as well as lateral) horns of the spinal cord as seen below in the image.]]
[[Image:1508 Autonomic Control of Pupil Size.jpg|thumb|right|Different ways in which the CNS can be activated without engaging the cortex, and making us aware of the actions. The above example shows the process in which the pupil dilates during dim light, activating neurons in the spinal cord. The second example shows the constriction of the pupil as a result of the activation of the Eddinger-Westphal nucleus (a cerebral ganglion).]]

From and to the spinal cord are projections of the peripheral nervous system in the form of [[spinal nerve|spinal]] [[nerve]]s (sometimes segmental nerves&lt;ref name=&quot;Moore's&quot; /&gt;). The nerves connect the spinal cord to skin, joints, muscles etc. and allow for the transmission of [[Efferent nerve fiber|efferent]] motor as well as [[Afferent nerve fiber|afferent sensory signals]] and stimuli.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kandel&quot; /&gt; This allows for voluntary and involuntary motions of muscles, as well as the perception of senses.
All in all 31 spinal nerves project from the brain stem,&lt;ref name=&quot;Kandel&quot; /&gt; some forming plexa as they branch out, such as the [[brachial plexus|brachial plexa]], [[sacral plexus|sacral plexa]] etc.&lt;ref name=&quot;Moore's&quot; /&gt; Each spinal nerve will carry both sensory and motor signals, but the nerves synapse at different regions of the spinal cord, either from the periphery to sensory relay neurons that relay the information to the CNS or from the CNS to motor neurons, which relay the information out.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kandel&quot; /&gt;

The spinal cord relays information up to the brain through spinal tracts through the &quot;final common pathway&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kandel&quot; /&gt; to the [[thalamus]] and ultimately to the cortex.
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:1615 Locations Spinal Fiber Tracts.jpg|Schematic image showing the locations of a few tracts of the spinal cord.
File:1507 Short and Long Reflexes.jpg|Reflexes may also occur without engaging more than one neuron of the CNS as in the below example of a short reflex.
&lt;/gallery&gt;

====Cranial nerves====
Apart from the spinal cord, there are also peripheral nerves of the PNS that synapse through intermediaries or [[Ganglion|ganglia]] directly on the CNS. These 12 nerves exist in the head and neck region and are called [[cranial nerves]]. Cranial nerves bring information to the CNS to and from the face, as well as to certain muscles (such as the [[trapezius muscle]], which is innervated by [[accessory nerve]]s&lt;ref name=&quot;Moore's&quot; /&gt; as well as certain [[cervical spinal nerve]]s).&lt;ref name=&quot;Moore's&quot; /&gt;

Two pairs of cranial nerves; the [[olfactory nerve]]s and the [[optic nerve]]s&lt;ref name=&quot;Purves 2000&quot;/&gt; are often considered structures of the CNS. This is because they do not synapse first on peripheral ganglia, but directly on CNS neurons. The olfactory epithelium is significant in that it consists of CNS tissue expressed in direct contact to the environment, allowing for administration of certain pharmaceuticals and drugs.
&lt;ref name=&quot;Gizurarson S. 2012 566–582&quot;/&gt;

{{multiple image
| align       = left
| direction   = horizontal
| total_width = 640
| image1      = Periferal nerve myelination.jpg
| alt1        = Image showing the way Schwann cells myelinate periferal nerves.
| width1      = 822
| height1     = 232
| caption1    = 
| image2      = Neuron with oligodendrocyte and myelin sheath.svg
| alt2        = A neuron of the CNS, myelinated by an oligodendrocyte
| width2      = 410
| height2     = 485
| caption2    = 
| footer      = A peripheral nerve myelinated by [[Schwann cell]]s (left) and a CNS neuron myelinated by an [[oligodendrocyte]] (right)
}}{{clear left}}

===Brain===
{{main article|Brain}}
Rostrally to the spinal cord lies the brain.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kandel&quot; /&gt; The brain makes up the largest portion of the CNS. It is often the main structure referred to when speaking of the nervous system in general. The brain is the major functional unit of the CNS. While the spinal cord has certain processing ability such as that of [[spinal locomotion]] and can process [[reflex]]es, the brain is the major processing unit of the nervous system.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cancer.ca/en/cancer-information/cancer-type/brain-spinal/brain-and-spinal-tumours/the-brain-and-spinal-cord/?region=on|title=The brain and spinal cord - Canadian Cancer Society|website=www.cancer.ca|language=en|access-date=2019-03-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{citation needed|date=December 2013}}

====Brainstem====
{{main article|Brainstem}}
The brainstem consists of the [[medulla oblongata|medulla]], the [[pons]] and the [[midbrain]]. The medulla can be referred to as an extension of the spinal cord, which both have similar organization and functional properties.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kandel&quot; /&gt; The tracts passing from the spinal cord to the brain pass through here.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kandel&quot; /&gt;

Regulatory functions of the medulla nuclei include control of [[blood pressure]] and [[breathing]]. Other nuclei are involved in [[balance (ability)|balance]], [[taste]], [[hearing]], and control of muscles of the [[face]] and [[neck]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Kandel&quot; /&gt;

The next structure rostral to the medulla is the pons, which lies on the ventral anterior side of the brainstem. Nuclei in the pons include [[pontine nuclei]] which work with the [[cerebellum]] and transmit information between the cerebellum and the [[cerebral cortex]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Kandel&quot; /&gt;
In the dorsal posterior pons lie nuclei that are involved in the functions of breathing, sleep, and taste.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kandel&quot; /&gt;

The midbrain, or mesencephalon, is situated above and rostral to the pons. It includes nuclei linking distinct parts of the motor system, including the cerebellum, the [[basal ganglia]] and both [[cerebral hemisphere]]s, among others. Additionally, parts of the visual and auditory systems are located in the midbrain, including control of automatic eye movements.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kandel&quot; /&gt;

The brainstem at large provides entry and exit to the brain for a number of pathways for motor and autonomic control of the face and neck through cranial nerves,&lt;ref name=&quot;Kandel&quot; /&gt; Autonomic control of the organs is mediated by the [[vagus|tenth]] cranial nerve.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fitzgerald&quot; /&gt;&lt;!-- page 98-199 --&gt; A large portion of the brainstem is involved in such autonomic control of the body. Such functions may engage the [[heart]], [[blood vessels]], and [[pupil]]s, among others.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kandel&quot; /&gt;

The brainstem also holds the [[reticular formation]], a group of nuclei involved in both [[arousal]] and [[alertness]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Kandel&quot; /&gt;

====Cerebellum====
{{main article|Cerebellum}}
The cerebellum lies behind the pons. The cerebellum is composed of several dividing fissures and lobes. Its function includes the control of posture and the coordination of movements of parts of the body, including the eyes and head, as well as the limbs. Further, it is involved in motion that has been learned and perfected though practice, and it will adapt to new learned movements.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kandel&quot; /&gt;
Despite its previous classification as a motor structure, the cerebellum also displays connections to areas of the cerebral cortex involved in language and [[cognition]]. These connections have been shown by the use of [[medical imaging]] techniques, such as [[fMRI|functional MRI]] and [[Positron emission tomography]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Kandel&quot; /&gt;

The body of the cerebellum holds more neurons than any other structure of the brain, including that of the larger [[cerebrum]], but is also more extensively understood than other structures of the brain, as it includes fewer types of different neurons.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kandel&quot; /&gt; It handles and processes sensory stimuli, motor information, as well as balance information from the [[vestibular organ]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Kandel&quot; /&gt;

====Diencephalon====
{{main article|Diencephalon|Thalamus|Hypothalamus}}
The two structures of the diencephalon worth noting are the thalamus and the hypothalamus. The thalamus acts as a linkage between incoming pathways from the peripheral nervous system as well as the optical nerve (though it does not receive input from the olfactory nerve) to the cerebral hemispheres. Previously it was considered only a &quot;relay station&quot;, but it is engaged in the sorting of information that will reach cerebral hemispheres ([[neocortex]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;Kandel&quot; /&gt;

Apart from its function of sorting information from the periphery, the thalamus also connects the cerebellum and basal ganglia with the cerebrum. In common with the aforementioned reticular system the thalamus is involved in wakefullness and consciousness, such as though the [[Suprachiasmatic nucleus|SCN]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Kandel&quot; /&gt;

The hypothalamus engages in functions of a number of primitive emotions or feelings such as [[hunger]], [[thirst]] and [[maternal bond]]ing. This is regulated partly through control of secretion of [[hormone]]s from the [[pituitary gland]]. Additionally the hypothalamus plays a role in [[motivation]] and many other behaviors of the individual.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kandel&quot; /&gt;

====Cerebrum====
{{main article|Cerebrum|Cerebral cortex|Basal ganglia|Amygdala|Hippocampus}}
The cerebrum of cerebral hemispheres make up the largest visual portion of the human brain. Various structures combine to form the cerebral hemispheres, among others: the cortex, basal ganglia, amygdala and hippocampus. The hemispheres together control a large portion of the functions of the human brain such as emotion, memory, perception and motor functions. Apart from this the cerebral hemispheres stand for the cognitive capabilities of the brain.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kandel&quot; /&gt;

Connecting each of the hemispheres is the [[corpus callosum]] as well as several additional commissures.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kandel&quot; /&gt;
One of the most important parts of the cerebral hemispheres is the cortex, made up of gray matter covering the surface of the brain. Functionally, the cerebral cortex is involved in planning and carrying out of everyday tasks.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kandel&quot; /&gt;

The hippocampus is involved in storage of memories, the amygdala plays a role in perception and communication of emotion, while the basal ganglia play a major role in the coordination of voluntary movement.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kandel&quot; /&gt;

===Difference from the peripheral nervous system===
[[File:1205 Somatic Autonomic Enteric StructuresN.jpg|thumb|350px|right|A map over the different structures of the nervous systems in the body, showing the CNS, [[peripheral nervous system|PNS]], [[autonomic nervous system]], and [[enteric nervous system]].]]

This differentiates the CNS from the PNS, which consists of neurons, axons, and [[Schwann cells]]. Oligodendrocytes and Schwann cells have similar functions in the CNS and PNS, respectively. Both act to add [[myelin]] sheaths to the axons, which acts as a form of insulation allowing for better and faster proliferation of electrical signals along the nerves. Axons in the CNS are often very short, barely a few millimeters, and do not need the same degree of isolation as peripheral nerves. Some peripheral nerves can be over 1 meter in length, such as the nerves to the big toe. To ensure signals move at sufficient speed, myelination is needed.

The way in which the Schwann cells and oligodendrocytes myelinate nerves differ. A Schwann cell usually myelinates a single axon, completely surrounding it. Sometimes, they may myelinate many axons, especially when in areas of short axons.&lt;ref name=&quot;Moore's&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Arthur F. Dalley|first=Keith L. Moore, Anne M.R. Agur|title=Clinically oriented anatomy|year=2010|publisher=Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins, Wolters Kluwer|location=Philadelphia [etc.]|isbn=978-1-60547-652-0|pages=48–55,464,700,822,824,1075|edition=6th ed., [International ed.].}}&lt;/ref&gt; Oligodendrocytes usually myelinate several axons. They do this by sending out thin projections of their [[cell membrane]], which envelop and enclose the axon.

==Development==
{{multiple image
| align = right
| direction = vertical
| width     = 300
| image1    = Sobo 1909 621.png
| alt1      = CNS seen in a median section of a five week old embryo.
| width1    = 300
| image2    = Sobo 1909 622.png
| alt2      = CNS seen in a median section of a 3 month old embryo.
| width2    = 300
| footer            = Top image: CNS as seen in a median section of a 5 week old embryo. Bottom image: CNS seen in a median section of a 3 month old embryo.
| footer_align      = center 
}}

{{Main article|Neural development}}
During early development of the vertebrate embryo, a longitudinal [[neural groove|groove]] on the [[neural plate]] gradually deepens and the ridges on either side of the groove (the [[neural folds]]) become elevated, and ultimately meet, transforming the groove into a closed tube called the [[neural tube]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Gilbert|first1=Scott F.|last2=College|first2=Swarthmore|last3=Helsinki|first3=the University of|title=Developmental biology|date=2014|publisher=Sinauer|location=Sunderland, Mass.|isbn=978-0878939787|edition=Tenth}}&lt;/ref&gt; The formation of the neural tube is called [[neurulation]].  At this stage, the walls of the neural tube contain proliferating [[neural stem cells]] in a region called the [[ventricular zone]].  The neural stem cells, principally [[radial glial cell]]s, multiply and generate [[neuron]]s through the process of [[neurogenesis]], forming the rudiment of the CNS.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Rakic|first1=P|title=Evolution of the neocortex: a perspective from developmental biology.|journal=Nature Reviews. Neuroscience|date=October 2009|volume=10|issue=10|pages=724–35|pmid=19763105|doi=10.1038/nrn2719|pmc=2913577}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[neural tube]] gives rise to both [[brain]] and [[spinal cord]].  The anterior (or 'rostral') portion of the neural tube initially differentiates into three brain [[Vesicle (embryology)|vesicles]] (pockets): the [[prosencephalon]] at the front, the [[mesencephalon]], and, between the mesencephalon and the spinal cord, the [[rhombencephalon]]. (By six weeks in the human embryo) the prosencephalon then divides further into the [[telencephalon]] and [[diencephalon]]; and the rhombencephalon divides into the [[metencephalon]] and [[myelencephalon]].  The spinal cord is derived from the posterior or 'caudal' portion of the neural tube.

As a vertebrate grows, these vesicles differentiate further still. The telencephalon differentiates into, among other things, the [[striatum]], the [[hippocampus]] and the [[neocortex]], and its cavity becomes the [[lateral ventricles|first and second ventricles]]. Diencephalon elaborations include the [[subthalamus]], [[hypothalamus]], [[thalamus]] and [[epithalamus]], and its cavity forms the [[third ventricle]]. The [[tectum]], [[pretectum]], [[cerebral peduncle]] and other structures develop out of the mesencephalon, and its cavity grows into the [[mesencephalic duct]] (cerebral aqueduct). The metencephalon becomes, among other things, the [[pons]] and the [[cerebellum]], the myelencephalon forms the [[medulla oblongata]], and their cavities develop into the [[fourth ventricle]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Kandel&quot; /&gt;
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:EmbryonicBrain.svg|Diagram depicting the main subdivisions of the embryonic vertebrate brain, later forming [[forebrain]], [[midbrain]] and [[hindbrain]].
File:Development of the neural tube.png|Development of the neural tube
&lt;/gallery&gt;
{{clear}}
{|  style=&quot;margin:auto; width:75%;&quot; border=&quot;1&quot; cellpadding=&quot;1&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot;
|-
| rowspan=6| CNS
| rowspan=5|[[Brain]]||rowspan=2|[[Prosencephalon]]||[[Telencephalon]]||colspan=2|
[[Rhinencephalon]],
[[Amygdala]],
[[Hippocampus]],
[[Neocortex]],
[[Basal ganglia]],
[[Lateral ventricles]]
|-
|[[Diencephalon]]||colspan=2|
[[Epithalamus]],
[[Thalamus]],
[[Hypothalamus]],
[[Subthalamus]],
[[Pituitary gland]],
[[Pineal gland]],
[[Third ventricle]]
|-
| rowspan=3|[[Brain stem]]||[[Mesencephalon]]||colspan=2|
[[Tectum]],
[[Cerebral peduncle]],
[[Pretectum]],
[[Mesencephalic duct]]
|-
| rowspan=2|[[Rhombencephalon]]||[[Metencephalon]]||
[[Pons]],
[[Cerebellum]]
|-
|[[Myelencephalon]]||[[Medulla oblongata]]
|-
| colspan=&quot;5&quot; style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot;|[[Spinal cord]]
|}

===Evolution===
{{multiple image
| align = right
| direction = vertical
| width     = 200
| image1    = Branchiostoma lanceolatum.jpg
| alt1      = [[Lancelet]]s or ''amphioxus'' are regarded as similar to the archetypal vertebrate form, and possess to true brain.
| width1    = 200
| image2    = Haikouichthys cropped.jpg|The early vertebrate ''[[Haikouichthys]]''
| alt2      = A neuron of the CNS, myelinated by an oligodendrocyte
| width2    = 200
| image3    = Spindle diagram.jpg
| alt3      = Traditional spindle diagram of the evolution of the vertebrates at class level.
| width3    = 200
| footer            = Top: the [[lancelet]], regarded an archetypal vertebrate, lacking a true brain. Middle: an early [[vertebrate]]. Bottom: spindle diagram of the evolution of vertebrates.
| footer_align      = center 
}}
{{See also|Encephalization|Archicortex}}

====Planaria====
[[Planarians]], members of the phylum [[Platyhelminthes]] (flatworms), have the simplest, clearly defined delineation of a nervous system into a CNS and a [[peripheral nervous system|PNS]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
| last = Hickman, Jr.
| first = Cleveland P.
|author2=Larry S. Roberts|author3=Susan L. Keen|author4=Allan Larson|author5=Helen L'Anson|author6=David J. Eisenhour
| title = Integrated Princinples of Zoology: Fourteenth Edition
| publisher = McGraw-Hill Higher Education
| year = 2008
| location = New York, NY, USA
| page = 733
| isbn = 978-0-07-297004-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
| last = Campbell
| first = Neil A.
| authorlink =
|author2=Jane B. Reece|author3=Lisa A. Urry|author4=Michael L. Cain|author5=Steven A. Wasserman|author6=Peter V. Minorsky|author7=Robert B. Jackson
| title = Biology: Eighth Edition
| publisher = Pearson / Benjamin Cummings
| year = 2008
| location = San Francisco, CA, USA
| page = 1065
| isbn = 978-0-8053-6844-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Their primitive brains, consisting of two fused anterior ganglia, and longitudinal nerve cords form the CNS; the laterally projecting nerves form the PNS. A molecular study found that more than 95% of the 116 genes involved in the nervous system of planarians, which includes genes related to the CNS, also exist in humans.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Mineta K, Nakazawa M, Cebria F, Ikeo K, Agata K, Gojobori T | title = Origin and evolutionary process of the CNS elucidated by comparative genomics analysis of planarian ESTs | journal = PNAS | volume = 100 | issue = 13 | pages = 7666–7671 | year = 2003 | pmid = 12802012 | pmc = 164645 | doi = 10.1073/pnas.1332513100 | url = http://www.pnas.org/content/100/13/7666.full.pdf+html?sid=b2a914e7-5647-4ee2-835c-bc54c4927a98 | url-status = live | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20150924133841/http://www.pnas.org/content/100/13/7666.full.pdf+html?sid=b2a914e7-5647-4ee2-835c-bc54c4927a98 | archivedate = 24 September 2015 | df = dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Like planarians, vertebrates have a distinct CNS and PNS, though more complex than those of planarians.

====Arthropoda====
In [[arthropods]], the [[ventral nerve cord]], the [[subesophageal ganglia]] and the [[supraesophageal ganglia]] are usually seen as making up the CNS.
{{see also|Lateral horn of insect brain}}

====Chordata====
The CNS of [[chordate]]s differs from that of other animals in being placed dorsally in the body, above the gut and [[notochord]]/[[Vertebral column|spine]].&lt;ref name=Romer&gt;Romer, A.S. (1949): ''The Vertebrate Body.'' W.B. Saunders, Philadelphia. (2nd ed. 1955; 3rd ed. 1962; 4th ed. 1970)&lt;/ref&gt; The basic pattern of the CNS is highly conserved throughout the different species of [[vertebrate]]s and during evolution. The major trend that can be observed is towards a progressive telencephalisation: the [[telencephalon]] of reptiles is only an appendix to the large [[olfactory bulb]], while in mammals it makes up most of the volume of the CNS. In the human brain, the telencephalon covers most of the [[diencephalon]] and the [[mesencephalon]]. Indeed, the [[allometry|allometric]] study of brain size among different species shows a striking continuity from rats to whales, and allows us to complete the knowledge about the evolution of the CNS obtained through [[cranial endocast]]s.

=====Mammals=====
[[Mammal]]s – which appear in the fossil record after the first fishes, amphibians, and reptiles – are the only vertebrates to possess the evolutionarily recent, outermost part of the [[cerebral cortex]] known as the [[neocortex]].&lt;ref name=MarkFBear&gt;{{cite book
| last = Bear
| first = Mark F.
|author2=Barry W. Connors|author3=Michael A. Paradiso
| title = Neuroscience: Exploring the Brain: Third Edition
| publisher = Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins
| year = 2007
| location = Philadelphia, PA, USA
| pages = 196–199
| url = https://books.google.com/?id=75NgwLzueikC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=neuroscience+exploring+the+brain
| isbn = 978-0-7817-6003-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The neocortex of [[monotremes]] (the duck-billed [[platypus]] and several species of [[echidna|spiny anteater]]s) and of [[marsupials]] (such as [[kangaroo]]s, [[koala]]s, [[opossum]]s, [[wombat]]s, and [[Tasmanian devil]]s) lack the convolutions – [[gyri]] and [[sulcus (neuroanatomy)|sulci]] – found in the neocortex of most [[placental mammals]] ([[eutherians]]).&lt;ref name=KentCarr&gt;{{cite book
| last = Kent
| first = George C.
|author2=Robert K. Carr
| title = Comparative Anatomy of the Vertebrates: Ninth Edition
| publisher = McGraw-Hill Higher Education
| year = 2001
| location = New York, NY, USA
| page = 409
| isbn = 0-07-303869-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Within placental mammals, the size and complexity of the neocortex increased over time. The area of the neocortex of mice is only about 1/100 that of monkeys, and that of monkeys is only about 1/10 that of humans.&lt;ref name=MarkFBear/&gt; In addition, rats lack convolutions in their neocortex (possibly also because rats are small mammals), whereas cats have a moderate degree of convolutions, and humans have quite extensive convolutions.&lt;ref name=MarkFBear/&gt; Extreme convolution of the neocortex is found in [[dolphin]]s, possibly related to their complex [[Animal echolocation|echolocation]].

==Clinical significance==
===Diseases===
{{main article|Central nervous system disease}}
There are many CNS diseases and conditions, including [[List of central nervous system infections|infections]] such as [[encephalitis]] and [[poliomyelitis]], early-onset [[neurological disorders]] including [[ADHD]] and [[autism]], late-onset [[Neurodegeneration|neurodegenerative diseases]] such as [[Alzheimer's disease]], [[Parkinson's disease]], and [[essential tremor]], [[Autoimmune disease|autoimmune]] and inflammatory diseases such as [[multiple sclerosis]] and [[acute disseminated encephalomyelitis]], genetic disorders such as [[Krabbe's disease]] and [[Huntington's disease]], as well as [[amyotrophic lateral sclerosis]] and [[adrenoleukodystrophy]]. Lastly, cancers of the central nervous system can cause severe illness and, when [[Malignant brain tumor|malignant]], can have very high mortality rates. Symptoms depend on the size, growth rate, location and malignancy of tumors and can include alterations in motor control, hearing loss, headaches and changes in cognitive ability and autonomic functioning.

[[Specialty (medicine)|Specialty]] professional organizations recommend that neurological imaging of the brain be done only to answer a specific clinical question and not as routine screening.&lt;ref name=&quot;ACRASNRcomtom&quot;&gt;{{cite web |author1=American College of Radiology |author2=American Society of Neuroradiology |year=2010 |title=ACR-ASNR practice guideline for the performance of computed tomography (CT) of the brain |publisher=[[American College of Radiology]] |work=[[Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality]] |publication-place=Reston, VA, USA |url=http://www.guidelines.gov/content.aspx?id=32518 |accessdate=9 September 2012|url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120915211424/http://www.guidelines.gov/content.aspx?id=32518 |archivedate=15 September 2012 |df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{commons|Central nervous system}}
* [http://nba.uth.tmc.edu/neuroscience/s2/chapter01.html Overview of the Central Nervous System], ''Neuroscience Online'' (electronic neuroscience textbook)
* [http://primate-brain.org High-Resolution Cytoarchitectural Primate Brain Atlases]
* [http://www.humannervoussystem.info Explaining the human nervous system].
* The [[v:Topic:Neuroscience|Department of Neuroscience]] at [[v:|Wikiversity]]
* [http://www.histology-world.com/photoalbum/thumbnails.php?album=16 Central nervous system histology]

{{Nervous system}}
{{Nervous tissue}}

{{Authority control}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=April 2017}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Central Nervous System}}
[[Category:Central nervous system| ]]
[[Category:Neuroscience]]</text>
      <sha1>jcisd8pmq94bo641r0zblawq6a21qnd</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
