  <page>
    <title>Colonialism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7299</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941800150</id>
      <parentid>941800145</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-20T19:32:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ClueBot NG</username>
        <id>13286072</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverting possible vandalism by [[Special:Contribs/69.63.163.56|69.63.163.56]] to version by CLCStudent. [[WP:CBFP|Report False Positive?]] Thanks, [[WP:CBNG|ClueBot NG]]. (3701565) (Bot)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description| Creation and maintenance of colonies by people from another territory}}
{{About| modern territorial expansion|the architectural style|American colonial architecture|examples of colonialism that do not refer to modern colonialism beginning in the 16th century|Colony|and|Colonisation}}

[[File:Musee-de-lArmee-IMG 0976.jpg|thumb|The [[pith helmet]], an icon of colonialism in tropical lands. This one was used during the [[French colonial empire#Second French colonial empire| Second French colonial empire]].]]
'''Colonialism''' is the policy of a country seeking to extend or retain its authority over other people or territories,&lt;ref name=&quot;Webster&quot; /&gt;{{qn|date=February 2020}} generally with the aim of economic dominance.&lt;ref&gt;Rodney, W. (1972). How Europe underdeveloped Africa. Black Classic Press.&lt;/ref&gt; In the process of colonisation, colonisers may impose their religion, economics, and other cultural practices on [[indigenous peoples]]. The foreign invaders/interlopers rule the territory in pursuit of their interests, seeking to benefit from the colonised region's people and resources.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title= Settler Colonialism: A Theoretical Overview |last= Veracini |first= Lorenzo |publisher= Palgrave Macmillan |year= 2010 |isbn= 978-0-230-22097-3 |location= New York |pages= 5}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Starting in the 15th century, some European states established their own empires during the [[History of colonialism |European colonial period]]. The [[Belgian colonial empire| Belgian]], [[British Empire|British]], [[Danish overseas colonies |Danish]], [[Dutch Empire |Dutch]], [[French colonial empire| French]], [[Ottoman Empire| Ottoman ]]{{R|Gallaher}}{{rp|116}} [[Portuguese Empire| Portuguese]], [[Russian Empire| Russian]], [[Spanish Empire| Spanish]] and [[Swedish overseas colonies| Swedish]] empires established colonies across large areas. [[Empire of Japan| Japan]], the [[American imperialism| United States]] and [[Chinese imperialism |China]] also followed this path, as did the [[German colonial empire| Germans]] and the [[Italian Empire| Italians]] in the late 19th century.

At first, European colonising countries followed policies of [[mercantilism]], aiming to strengthen the home-country economy, so agreements usually restricted the colonies to trading only with the [[metropole]] (mother country). By the mid-19th century, however, the [[British Empire]] gave up mercantilism and trade restrictions and adopted the principle of [[free trade]], with few restrictions or [[tariff]]s. [[Christian mission]]aries were active in practically all of the European-controlled colonies because the metropoles were Christian. Historian Philip Hoffman calculated that by 1800, before the [[Industrial Revolution]], Europeans already controlled at least 35% of the globe, and by 1914, they had gained control of 84% of the globe.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=73zeBgAAQBAJ |title= Why Did Europe Conquer the World? |last= Philip T. Hoffman |date= 2015 |publisher= Princeton University Press |isbn= 978-1-4008-6584-0 |pages= 2–3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[aftermath of World War II]] colonial powers were forced to retreat between 1945–1975, when nearly all colonies gained [[independence]], entering into changed colonial, so-called [[postcolonialism |postcolonial]] and [[neocolonialism |neocolonialist]] relations. Postcolonialism and neocolonialism has continued or shifted relations and ideologies of colonialism, attempting to justify its continuation with adjusted narratives like [[development aid| development]] and [[New Frontier |new frontiers]], as in exploring outer space [[Space colonization |for colonization]].&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite web |url= https://www.washingtonpost.com/outlook/2019/07/22/how-imperialism-shaped-race-moon/ |title= How imperialism shaped the race to the moon |last= Gabrielle Cornish |date= 22 July 2019 |website= [[Washington Post]] |language= en |access-date= 19 September 2019}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
{{TOC limit|3}}

==Definitions==
[[File:Fundacion de Santiago.jpg|thumb|1541: Spanish [[Conquistadors]] founding [[Santiago de Chile]]]]

''[[Collins English Dictionary]]'' defines colonialism as &quot;the policy and practice of a power in extending control over weaker peoples or areas&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.collinsdictionary.com/dictionary/english/colonialism |title=Colonialism |year=2011 |website=[[Collins English Dictionary]] |publisher=[[HarperCollins]] |access-date=8 January 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Webster's Encyclopedic Dictionary'' defines colonialism as &quot;the system or policy of a nation seeking to extend or retain its authority over other people or territories&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Webster&quot;&gt;''Webster's Encyclopedic Unabridged Dictionary of the English Language'', 1989, p. 291.&lt;/ref&gt; The ''[[Merriam-Webster]] Dictionary'' offers four definitions, including &quot;something characteristic of a colony&quot; and &quot;control by one power over a dependent area or people&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/colonialism |title=Colonialism |year=2010 |website=Merriam-Webster |publisher=[[Merriam-Webster]] |access-date=5 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Etymologically, the word &quot;[[wikt:colony|colony]]&quot; comes from the Latin ''[[wikt:colōnia|colōnia]]''—&quot;a place for agriculture&quot;.

The ''[[Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy]]'' uses the term &quot;to describe the process of European settlement and political control over the rest of the world, including the Americas, Australia, and parts of Africa and Asia&quot;. It discusses the distinction between colonialism, [[imperialism]] and [[conquest]] and states that &quot;[t]he difficulty of defining colonialism stems from the fact that the term is often used as a synonym for imperialism. Both colonialism and imperialism were forms of conquest that were expected to benefit Europe economically and strategically.&quot;, and continues &quot;given the difficulty of consistently distinguishing between the two terms, this entry will use ''colonialism'' broadly to refer to the project of European political domination from the sixteenth to the twentieth centuries that ended with the national liberation movements of the 1960s&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/colonialism/ |title=Colonialism |last=Margaret Kohn |date=29 August 2017 |website=[[Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy]] |publisher=[[Stanford University]] |access-date=5 May 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In his preface to [[Jürgen Osterhammel]]'s ''Colonialism: A Theoretical Overview'', Roger Tignor says &quot;For Osterhammel, the essence of colonialism is the existence of colonies, which are by definition governed differently from other territories such as protectorates or informal spheres of influence.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://books.google.com/?id=CMfksrnWaUkC&amp;pg=PR10#v=onepage |title=Preface to Colonialism: a theoretical overview |last=Tignor |first=Roger |publisher=Markus Weiner Publishers |year=2005 |isbn=978-1-55876-340-1 |page=x |access-date=5 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the book, Osterhammel asks, &quot;How can 'colonialism' be defined independently from 'colony?'&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://books.google.com/?id=CMfksrnWaUkC&amp;pg=PA15#v=onepage |title=Colonialism: a theoretical overview |last=Osterhammel |first=Jürgen |publisher=Markus Weiner Publishers |others=trans. Shelley Frisch |year=2005 |isbn=978-1-55876-340-1 |page=15 |author-link=Jürgen Osterhammel |access-date=5 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; He settles on a three-sentence definition:

{{quote|Colonialism is a relationship between an indigenous (or forcibly imported) majority and a minority of foreign invaders. The fundamental decisions affecting the lives of the colonised people are made and implemented by the colonial rulers in pursuit of interests that are often defined in a distant metropolis. Rejecting cultural compromises with the colonised population, the colonisers are convinced of their own superiority and their ordained mandate to rule.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://books.google.com/?id=CMfksrnWaUkC&amp;pg=PA16#v=onepage |title=Colonialism: A Theoretical Overview |last=Osterhammel |first=Jürgen |publisher=Markus Weiner Publishers |others=trans. Shelley Frisch |year=2005 |isbn=978-1-55876-340-1 |page=16 |author-link=Jürgen Osterhammel |access-date=5 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

==Types of colonialism==
[[File:COLLECTIE TROPENMUSEUM Rijsttafel TMnr 60053682.jpg|thumb|Dutch family in [[Java]], 1927]]
Historians often distinguish between various overlapping forms of colonialism, which are classified into four types: settler colonialism, exploitation colonialism, surrogate colonialism, and internal colonialism.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |title=The Shadow of Colonialism on Europe's Modern Past |last=Healy |first=Roisin |last2=Dal Lago |first2=Enrico |publisher=Palgrave Macmillan |year=2014 |isbn=978-1-137-45075-3 |location=New York |page=126}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Settler colonialism]] involves large-scale [[immigration]], often motivated by religious, political, or economic reasons. It pursues to replace the original population. Here, a large number of people emigrate to the colony for the purpose of staying and cultivating the land.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt; [[Australia]], [[Canada]], and the [[United States]] are all examples of settler colonial societies.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |jstor = 40388468|last1 = Barker|first1 = Adam J.|title = The Contemporary Reality of Canadian Imperialism: Settler Colonialism and the Hybrid Colonial State|journal = American Indian Quarterly|volume = 33|issue = 3|pages = 325–351|year = 2009|doi = 10.1353/aiq.0.0054}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Glenn |first=Evelyn Nakano |date=2015 |title=Settler Colonialism as Structure: A Framework for Comparative Studies of U.S. Race and Gender Formation |url=http://ieas.unideb.hu/admin/file_9708.pdf |journal=Sociology of Race and Ethnicity |volume=1 |pages=52–72 |doi=10.1177/2332649214560440 |number=1}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Veracini |first=Lorenzo |date=2007 |title=Historylessness: Australia as a settler colonial collective |journal=Postcolonial Studies |volume=10 |issue=3 |pages=271–285 |doi=10.1080/13688790701488155}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Exploitation colonialism]] involves fewer colonists and focuses on the exploitation of natural resources or population as labour, typically to the benefit of the [[metropole]]. This category includes [[trading posts]] as well as larger colonies where colonists would constitute much of the political and economic administration. Prior to the end of the [[slave trade]] and widespread [[Abolitionism|abolition]], when indigenous labour was unavailable, [[Slavery|slaves]] were often imported to the Americas, first by the Portuguese Empire, and later by the Spanish, Dutch, French and British.{{Citation needed|date=October 2019}}
* [[Surrogate Colonialism|Surrogate colonialism]] involves a settlement project supported by a colonial power, in which most of the settlers do not come from a same ethnic group as the ruling power.
* [[Internal colonialism]] is a notion of uneven structural power between areas of a [[State (polity)|state]]. The source of exploitation comes from within the state. This is demonstrated in the way control and exploitation passes from whites in the colonising country to white immigrant population within a newly independent country.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=Race, Ethnicity, Crime, and Justice: An International Dilemma |last=Gabbidon |first=Shaun |publisher=SAGE |year=2010 |isbn=978-1-4129-4988-0 |location=Los Angeles, CA |pages=8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Socio-cultural evolution==
As colonialism often played out in pre-populated areas, [[sociocultural evolution]] included the formation of various ethnically hybrid populations. Colonialism gave rise to culturally and ethnically mixed populations such as the [[mestizo]]s of the Americas, as well as racially divided populations such as those found in [[French Algeria]] or in [[Southern Rhodesia]]. In fact, everywhere where colonial powers established a consistent and continued presence, hybrid communities existed.

Notable examples in Asia include the [[Anglo-Burmese people|Anglo-Burmese]], [[Anglo-Indian]], [[Burgher people|Burgher]], [[Eurasian Singaporean]], [[Filipino mestizo]], [[Kristang people|Kristang]] and [[Macanese people]]s. In the [[Dutch East Indies]] (later [[Indonesia]]) the vast majority of &quot;Dutch&quot; settlers were in fact Eurasians known as [[Indo people|Indo-Europeans]], formally belonging to the European legal class in the colony (see also [[Indos in pre-colonial history]] and [[Indos in colonial history]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=47wCTCJX9X4C&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PA223 |title=Being &quot;Dutch&quot; in the Indies: A History of Creolisation and Empire, 1500–1920 |last=Bosma |first=U. |last2=Raben |first2=R. |date=2008 |publisher=NUS Press |isbn=978-9971-69-373-2 |location=Singapore |page=223}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=nN6G-lMk_DEC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PA163 |title=Dutch Culture Overseas: Colonial Practice in the Netherlands Indies 1900–1942 |last=Gouda |first=Frances |date=2008 |publisher=Equinox |isbn=978-979-3780-62-7 |page=163 |chapter=Gender, Race, and Sexuality}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
{{Main|History of colonialism|Chronology of Western colonialism}}
&lt;gallery widths=&quot;300&quot; heights=&quot;150&quot;&gt;
Colonial empires in 1800.svg|Map of colonial empires throughout the world in 1800 CE.
World 1914 empires colonies territory.PNG|Map of colonial empires throughout the world in 1914 CE.
World 1936 empires colonies territory.png|Map of colonial empires throughout the world in 1936 CE.
Colonization 1945.png|Map of colonial empires at the end of the Second World War, 1945 CE.
&lt;/gallery&gt;
{{quote box|width=25%|quote=&quot;Why do the Christian nations, which were so weak in the past compared with Muslim nations begin to dominate so many lands in modern times and even defeat the once victorious Ottoman armies?&quot;...&quot;Because they have laws and rules invented by reason.&quot;|source=[[Ibrahim Muteferrika]], ''Rational basis for the Politics of Nations'' (1731)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.ted.com/talks/niall_ferguson_the_6_killer_apps_of_prosperity.html |title=The 6 killer apps of prosperity |date=11 August 2017 |website=Ted.com |access-date=11 August 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

===Premodern===
Activity that could be called colonialism has a long history starting with the [[Ancient Egypt|Egyptians]], [[Phoenicia]]ns, [[Ancient Greece|Greeks]] and [[Ancient Rome|Romans]] who all built [[colonies in antiquity]]. [[Phoenicia]] was an enterprising maritime trading culture that spread across the Mediterranean from 1550 BC to 300 BC and later the Greeks and Persians continued on this line of setting up colonies. The [[Ancient Rome|Romans]] would soon follow, setting up colonies throughout the Mediterranean, Northern Africa, and Western Asia. Beginning in the 7th century, [[Arab Empire|Arabs]] colonized a substantial portion of the Middle East, Northern Africa, and parts of Asia and Europe. In the 9th century a new wave of [[Mediterranean]] colonisation had begun between competing states such as the [[Stato da Màr|Venetians]], [[Genoese colonies|Genovese]] and [[Duchy of Amalfi|Amalfians]], invading the wealthy previously [[Byzantine]] or [[Eastern Roman]] islands and lands. [[Republic of Venice|Venice]] began with the conquest of Dalmatia and reached its greatest nominal extent at the conclusion of the Fourth Crusade in 1204, with the declaration of the [[Partitio terrarum imperii Romaniae|acquisition of three octaves]] of the Byzantine Empire.&lt;ref&gt;Peter N. Stearns, ed., ''An Encyclopedia of World History'' (2001) pp 21–238&lt;/ref&gt;

===Modern===
[[File:Philip II's realms in 1598.png|upright=1.25|thumb|[[Iberian Union]] of Spain and Portugal between 1580 and 1640]]
Modern colonialism started with the Portuguese [[Prince Henry the Navigator]], initiating the [[Age of Exploration]]. Spain (initially the [[Crown of Castile]]) and soon later Portugal encountered the [[Americas]] through sea travel and built trading posts or conquered large extensions of land. For some people, it is this building of colonies across oceans that differentiates colonialism from other types of [[expansionism]]. These new lands were divided between the [[Spanish Empire]] and [[Portuguese Empire]] .&lt;ref&gt;Charles R. Boxer, ''The Portuguese Seaborne Empire, 1415–1825'' (1969)&lt;/ref&gt;

The 17th century saw the creation of the [[French colonial empire]] and the [[Dutch Empire]], as well as the [[English overseas possessions]], which later became the [[British Empire]]. It also saw the establishment of a [[Danish colonial empire]] and some [[Swedish overseas colonies]].&lt;ref&gt;Thomas Benjamin,  ed. ''Encyclopedia of Western Colonialism Since 1450'' (3 vol 2006)&lt;/ref&gt;

A first wave of independence was started by the [[American Revolutionary War]] (1775–1783), initiating a new phase for the British Empire.&lt;ref&gt;See [http://www.victorianweb.org/history/empire/Empire.html  David Cody, &quot;The British Empire&quot; ''The Victorians Web'' (1988)]&lt;/ref&gt; The Spanish Empire largely collapsed in the Americas with the [[Latin American wars of independence]]. However, many new colonies were established after this time, including the [[German colonial empire]] and [[Belgian colonial empire]]. In the late 19th century, many European powers were involved in the [[Scramble for Africa]].&lt;ref&gt;Melvin E. Page, ed., ''Colonialism: An International Social, Cultural, and Political Encyclopedia'' (2003).&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Russian Empire]], [[Ottoman Empire]] and [[Habsburg Monarchy|Austrian Empire]] existed at the same time as the above empires but did not expand over oceans. Rather, these empires expanded through the more traditional route of the conquest of neighbouring territories. There was, though, some [[Russian colonisation of the Americas]] across the Bering Strait. The [[Empire of Japan]] modelled itself on European colonial empires. [[Argentina]] and the [[Empire of Brazil]] fought for hegemony in South America. The United States of America gained overseas territories after the [[Spanish–American War]] for which the term &quot;[[American imperialism|American Empire]]&quot; was coined.&lt;ref&gt;Benjamin,  ed. ''Encyclopedia of Western Colonialism Since 1450'' (3 vol 2006)&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Arthur Mees Flags of A Free Empire 1910 Cornell CUL PJM 1167 01.jpg|thumb|upright=1.75|Map of the [[British Empire]] (as of 1910)]]

After the [[World War I|First World War]], the victorious [[Allies of World War I|allies]] divided up the German colonial empire and much of the Ottoman Empire between themselves as [[League of Nations mandate]]s. These territories were divided into three classes according to how quickly it was deemed that they would be ready for independence.  The empires of Russia and Austria also collapsed.&lt;ref&gt;G.M. Gathorne-Hardy, ''A Short History of International Affairs, 1920–1939'' (4th ed. 1950), [https://archive.org/details/in.ernet.dli.2015.260425/page/n1 online]&lt;/ref&gt;

After World War II [[decolonisation]] progressed rapidly. This was caused by a number of reasons. First, the Japanese victories in the Pacific War showed Indians and other subject peoples that the colonial powers were not invincible. Second, all the colonial powers were significantly weakened by World War II.&lt;ref&gt;Nicholas White, ''Decolonisation'' (2014).&lt;/ref&gt;

Dozens of independence movements and global political solidarity projects such as the [[Non-Aligned Movement]] were instrumental in the decolonisation efforts of former colonies. These included significant wars of independence fought in Indonesia, Vietnam, Algeria, and Kenya. Eventually, the European powers—pressured by the United States and Soviets—resigned themselves to decolonisation.

In 1962 the [[United Nations]] set up a [[Special Committee on Decolonisation]], often called the Committee of 24, to encourage this process.

===European empires in the 20th century===
The major European empires consisted of the following colonies at the start of [[World War I]] (former colonies of the Spanish Empire became independent before 1914 and are not listed; former colonies of other European empires that previously became independent, such as the former French colony Haiti, are not listed).
[[File:Seychelles Governor inspection 1972.jpg|thumb|upright|Colonial Governor of the [[Seychelles]] inspecting police guard of honour in 1972]]

The world's colonial population at the time of the First World War totalled about 560 million people, of whom 70% were in British domains, 10% in French, 9% in Dutch, 4% in Japanese, 2% in German, 2% in American, 2% in Portuguese, 1% in Belgian and 1/2 of 1% in Italian possessions. The home domains of the colonial powers had a total population of about 370 million people.&lt;ref&gt;The Russian Empire, Austria-Hungary, Ottoman Empire, Spain and Denmark are not included. U.S. Tariff Commission. ''Colonial tariff policies'' (1922), p. 5 [https://archive.org/details/colonialtariffpo00unit online]&lt;/ref&gt;

Asking whether colonies paid, economic historian Grover Clark argues an emphatic &quot;No!&quot; He reports that in every case the support cost, especially the military system necessary to support and defend the colonies outran the total trade they produced. Apart from the British Empire, they were not favoured destinations for the immigration of surplus populations.&lt;ref&gt;Raymond Leslie Buell, &quot;Do Colonies Pay?&quot; [http://www.unz.org/Pub/SaturdayRev-1936aug01-00006?View=PDF ''The Saturday Review'', August 1, 1936 p 6 ]&lt;/ref&gt; The question of whether colonies paid is, however, a complicated one when recognizing the multiplicity of interests involved. In some cases colonial powers were paying a lot in military costs, while the benefits could be pocketed by private investors. In other cases the colonial powers managed to move the burden of administrative costs to the colonies themselves by imposing taxes.&lt;ref&gt;Rönnbäck &amp; Broberg (2019) Capital and Colonialism. The Return on British Investments in Africa 1869–1969 (Palgrave Studies in Economic History)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Neocolonialism===
{{Main|Neocolonialism}}
The term [[neocolonialism]] has been used to refer to a variety of contexts since decolonisation that took place after [[World War II]]. Generally it does not refer to a type of direct colonisation, rather, colonialism by other means. Specifically, neocolonialism refers to the theory that former or existing economic relationships, such as the [[General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade]] and the [[Central American Free Trade Agreement]], or through companies (such as [[Royal Dutch Shell]] in [[Nigeria]] and [[Brunei]]) created by former colonial powers were or are used to maintain control of their former colonies and dependencies after the colonial independence movements of the post–World War II period.

The term was popular in ex-colonies in the late 20th century.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Uzoigw |first=Godfrey N. |year=2019 |title=Neocolonialism Is Dead: Long Live Neocolonialism |journal=Journal of Global South Studies |volume=36 |issue=1 |pages=59–87 |doi=10.1353/gss.2019.0004}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==List of colonies==
=== British colonies and protectorates ===
[[File:Hakewill, A Picturesque Tour of the Island of Jamaica, Plate 04.jpg|thumb|Harbour Street, [[Kingston, Jamaica]], c. 1820]]
[[File:Isandhlwana.jpg|thumb|The [[Battle of Isandlwana]] during the [[Anglo-Zulu War]] of 1879. After an initial defeat the British were able to conquer [[Zulu Kingdom|Zululand]].]]
* [[Aden Protectorate|Aden]]
* [[Anglo-Egyptian Sudan]]
* [[Ascension Island]]
* [[Australia]]
** [[New South Wales]]
** [[Victoria (Australia)|Victoria]]
** [[Tasmania]]
** [[Queensland]]
** [[South Australia]]
** [[Western Australia]]
* [[Bahamas]]
* [[Barbados]]
* [[Basutoland]]
* [[Bechuanaland]]
* [[British Borneo]]
** [[Brunei]]
** [[Crown Colony of Labuan|Labuan]]
** [[North Borneo]]
** [[Kingdom of Sarawak|Sarawak]]
* [[British East Africa]]
* [[British Guiana]]
* [[British Honduras]]
* [[British Hong Kong]]
* [[British Leeward Islands]]
** [[Anguilla]]
** [[Antigua]]
** [[Barbuda]]
** [[British Virgin Islands]]
** [[Dominica]]
** [[Montserrat]]
** [[Nevis]] [[File:Procession1877.jpg|thumb|The [[Delhi Durbar]] of 1877: the proclamation of [[Queen Victoria]] as [[Empress of India]]]]
** [[Saint Kitts]]
* [[British Malaya]] [[File:Battle of ferozeshah(H Martens).jpg|thumb|The [[First Anglo-Sikh War]], 1845–46]]
** [[Federated Malay States]]
** [[Straits Settlements]]
** [[Unfederated Malay States]]
* [[British Somaliland]]
* [[British Western Pacific Territories]]
** [[British Solomon Islands]]
** [[Fiji]]
** [[Gilbert and Ellice Islands]]
** [[Phoenix Islands]]
** [[Pitcairn Islands]]
** [[New Hebrides]] ([[condominium (international law)|condominium]] with France)
** [[Tonga]]
** [[Union Islands]]
* [[British Windward Islands]]
** [[Barbados]]
** [[Dominica]]
** [[Grenada]]
** [[Saint Lucia]]
** [[Saint Vincent and the Grenadines]]
* [[Myanmar]]
* [[Canada]]
* [[Ceylon]]
* [[Christmas Island]]
* [[Cocos (Keeling) Islands]]
* [[Cyprus]] (including [[Akrotiri and Dhekelia]])[[File:Resa del bacino del Brandewater.jpg|thumb|The end result of the [[Boer Wars]] was the annexation of the [[Boer Republics]] to the British Empire in 1902]]
* [[Egypt]]
* [[Falkland Islands]]
* [[Falkland Islands Dependencies]]
** [[Graham Land]]
** [[South Georgia Island|South Georgia]]
** [[South Orkney Islands]]
** [[South Shetland Islands]]
** [[South Sandwich Islands]]
** [[Victoria Land]]
* [[Gambia]]
* [[Gibraltar]]
* [[Gold Coast (British colony)|Gold Coast]]
* [[British India|India (including what is today Pakistan and Bangladesh)]] [[File:A view of shops with anti-British and pro-Independence signs, possibly on Kings Street, Valetta, Malta (5074435957).jpg|thumb|A view of shops with anti-British and pro-Independence signs, [[Malta]], c. 1960]]
* [[Heard Island and McDonald Islands]]
* [[Ireland]]
* [[Jamaica]]
* [[Kenya]]
* [[Maldives]]
* [[Malta Colony|Malta]]
* [[Mandatory Palestine]]
* [[British Mauritius|Mauritius]]
* [[Muscat and Oman]]
* [[Norfolk Island]]
* [[Nigeria]]
* [[Northern Rhodesia]]
* [[Nyasaland]] [[File:Gibraltar National Day 027 (9719742224) (2).jpg|thumb|[[Gibraltar National Day]] in British-controlled [[Gibraltar]]]]
* [[Seychelles]]
* [[Sierra Leone]]
* [[South Africa]]
** [[Cape Colony]]
** [[Colony of Natal|Natal]]
** [[Transvaal Colony]]
** [[Orange River Colony]]
* [[Southern Rhodesia]]
* [[St Helena]]
* [[Swaziland]]
* [[Trinidad and Tobago]]
* [[Tristan da Cunha]]
* [[Trucial States]]
* [[Uganda]]
* [[Tonga]]
[[File:Flag of New Hebrides.svg|thumb|1966 flag of the Anglo-French [[Condominium (international law)|Condominium]] of the [[New Hebrides]]]]
{{div col end}}

=== French colonies ===
{{Main|List of French possessions and colonies}}
* [[Acadia]]
* [[French Algeria|Algeria]]
* [[Canada (New France)|Canada]]
* [[Clipperton Island]]
* [[Comoros Islands]] (including [[Mayotte]])[[File:Expeditionconstantine.jpg|thumb|Siege of Constantine (1836) during the [[French conquest of Algeria]].]]
* [[French conquest of Corsica|Corsica]]
* [[French Guiana]]
* [[French Equatorial Africa]]
** [[Chad]]
** [[Oubangui-Chari]]
** [[French Congo]]
** [[Gabon]]
* [[French India]] ([[Puducherry|Pondichéry]], [[Chandernagor]], [[Karaikal|Karikal]], [[Mahé, India|Mahé]] and [[Yanam|Yanaon]])
* [[French Indochina]]
**[[Annam (French protectorate)|Annam]] [[File:Hocquard and Tonkinese.jpg|thumb|right|French officers and [[Tonkinese Rifles|Tonkinese riflemen]], 1884]]
** [[Tonkin (French protectorate)|Tonkin]]
** [[French Cochinchina|Cochinchina]]
** [[French Protectorate of Cambodia|Cambodia]]
** [[French Protectorate of Laos|Laos]]
* [[French Polynesia]]
* [[French Somaliland]]
* [[French Southern and Antarctic Lands]]
* [[French West Africa]]
** [[Ivory Coast]]
** [[French Dahomey|Dahomey]]
** [[Guinea]] [[File:LeCommandantMarchand.jpg|thumb|right|upright|Contemporary illustration of Major [[Jean-Baptiste Marchand|Marchand]]'s [[Fashoda incident|trek across Africa]] in 1898]]
** [[French Sudan]]
** [[Mauritania]]
** [[Niger]]
** [[Senegal]]
** [[French Upper Volta|Upper Volta]]
* [[Guadeloupe]]
** [[Saint Barthélemy]]
** [[Collectivity of Saint Martin|Saint Martin]]
* [[La Réunion]]
* [[Louisiana (New France)|Louisiana]]
* [[Madagascar]]
* [[Martinique]]
* [[French protectorate of Morocco|French Morocco]]
* [[Lebanon]]
* [[New Caledonia]]
* [[Saint-Pierre-et-Miquelon]]
* [[Shanghai French Concession]] (similar concessions in [[Guangzhouwan|Kouang-Tchéou-Wan]], [[Tianjin|Tientsin]], [[Hankou|Hankéou]])
* [[French protectorate of Tunisia|Tunisia]]
* [[New Hebrides]] (condominium with Britain)
* [[Wallis-et-Futuna]]

=== Russian colonies and protectorates ===
[[File:Russian Sloop-of-War Neva.jpg|thumb|The Russian settlement of St. Paul's Harbour (present-day [[Kodiak, Alaska]]), [[Russian America]], 1814]]
* European Russia
**[[Adygea]]
** [[Åland Islands]]
** [[Baltic provinces]]
*** [[Governorate of Courland]]
*** [[Governorate of Livland]]
*** [[Governorate of Estland]]
** [[Lithuania Governorate]]
** [[Grand Principality of Finland]]
** [[Ingermanland]]
** [[East Karelia]]
** [[Russian Poland]] ([[Russian Partition]])
** [[Little Russia]] — [[Dnieper Ukraine]]
** [[New Russia]] — [[South Ukraine]] ([[Ottoman Ukraine]], [[Zaporizhian Sich]])
** [[Sloboda Ukraine]] — [[East Ukraine]]
** [[Bessarabia]]
** [[Taurida Governorate]] — [[Crimea]]
** [[Kuban]]
** [[Adygea]] — [[Cherkessia]]
** [[Chechnya]]
** [[Dagestan]]
** [[Ingushetia]]
** [[Kabardino-Balkaria]]
** [[Kalmykia]]
** [[Karachay–Cherkessia]]
** [[North Ossetia-Alania|Ossetia]]
** [[Bashkortostan]]
** [[Chuvashia]]
** [[Komi Republic|Komi]] 
** [[Great Perm]]
[[File:CircassianCoastBattle.JPG|thumb|[[Adyghe people|Circassian]] strike on a Russian military fort in [[Caucasus]], 1840]]
** [[Mari El]]
** [[Mordovia]]
** [[Tatarstan]]
** [[Udmurtia]]
* Asiatic Russia
** [[Armenia]]
** [[Azerbaijan]]
** [[Georgia (country)|Georgia]]
** [[Emirate of Bukhara]]
** [[Khanate of Khiva]]
** [[Russian Turkestan]]
*** [[Kazakhstan]]
*** [[Kyrgyzstan]]
*** [[Tajikistan]]
*** [[Turkmenistan]]
**[[Siberia]]
** [[Khakassia]]
** [[Yamalia]]
**[[Altai Republic|Altai]]
** [[Buryatia]] 
[[File:PG - Semireche Cossack.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Semirechye Cossacks|Semirechye Cossack]], Semirechye (present-day [[Kyrgyzstan]] and [[Kazakhstan]]), 1911]]
** [[Outer Manchuria]]
** [[Tuva]] — [[Tannu Uriankhai]]
** [[Dauria]]
** [[Yakutia]]
** [[Sakhalin]] and [[Kuril Islands]]
** [[Chukotka Autonomous Okrug|Chukotka]]
** [[Koryak Autonomous Okrug|Koryak]]
* [[Kauai]] ([[Hawaii]])
* [[Russian America]] ([[Alaska]])
*[[Fort Ross, California|Fort Ross]] ([[California]])
*[[Sagallo]]

=== German colonies ===
[[File:Victoria (Cameroon).jpg|thumb|[[Kamerun]] (by [[Rudolf Hellgrewe|R. Hellgrewe]], 1908)]]
* [[Bismarck Archipelago]]
* [[Cameroon]]
* [[Caroline Islands]]
* [[German New Guinea]]
* [[German Solomon Islands]]
* [[German East Africa]]
* [[German South-West Africa]]
* [[Gilbert Islands]]
* [[Mariana Islands]]
* [[Marshall Islands]]
* [[Togo]]
* [[Concessions in Tianjin|Tianjin]]

=== Italian colonies and protectorates ===
[[File:Italian aircraft attacking Ottoman forces in Libya 1911 or 1912.jpg|thumb|upright|The [[Italian invasion of Libya]] during the [[Italo-Turkish War]], 1911]]
* [[Italian Aegean Islands]]
* [[Italian protectorate of Albania (1939–1943)|Italian protectorate of Albania]]
* [[Governorate of Dalmatia|Italian governorate of Dalmatia]]
* [[Italian governorate of Montenegro]]
* [[Italian Concession of Tientsin]]
* [[Italian East Africa]]
** [[Italian Eritrea]]
** [[Italian Ethiopia]]
** [[Italian Somaliland]]&lt;br&gt;   -''[[Italian Trans-Juba]]'' &lt;small&gt;(briefly; annexed)&lt;/small&gt;  
* [[Italian Libya]]

=== Dutch colonies ===
[[File:Nicolaas Pieneman - The Submission of Prince Dipo Negoro to General De Kock.jpg|thumb|The submission of [[Diponegoro]] to [[Hendrik Merkus de Kock|General De Kock]] at the end of the [[Java War]] in 1830]]
* [[Dutch Brazil]]
* [[Dutch Ceylon]]
* [[Dutch Formosa]]
* [[Dutch Cape Colony]]
* [[Aruba]]
* [[Bonaire]]
* [[Curaçao]]
* [[Saba]]
* [[Sint Eustatius]]
* [[Sint Maarten]]
* [[Suriname]]
* [[Dutch East Indies]]
* [[Dutch New Guinea]]

=== Portuguese colonies ===
[[File:1600gora.jpg|thumb|upright|Portuguese women in [[Goa]], India, 16th century]]
* Portuguese Africa
** [[Portuguese Congo|Cabinda]]
** [[Ceuta]]
** [[Madeira]]
** [[Portuguese Angola]]
** [[Portuguese Cape Verde]]
** [[Portuguese Guinea]]
** [[Portuguese Mozambique]]
** [[Portuguese São Tomé and Príncipe]]
** [[Fort of São João Baptista de Ajudá]]
* Portuguese Asia
** [[Portuguese India]]
*** [[Goa]]
*** [[Daman District, India|Daman]]
*** [[Diu, India|Diu]]
** [[Macau|Portuguese Macau]]
* Portuguese Oceania
** [[Flores]]
** [[Portuguese Timor]]
** [[Solor]]
* Portuguese South America
** [[Colonial Brazil]]
** [[Cisplatina]]
** [[Misiones]]
* Portuguese North America
** [[Azores]]
** [[Newfoundland and Labrador]]

=== Spanish colonies ===
[[File:Mestizo.jpg|thumb|An 18th-century [[casta]] painting from [[New Spain]] shows a Spanish man and his indigenous wife.]]
[[File:093 La batalla de Tetuan, de Marià Fortuny (detall).jpg|thumb|The [[Battle of Tétouan]], 1860, by [[Marià Fortuny]]]]
[[File:Entrada triunfal de Arsenio Martínez Campos en La Habana, 1878.jpg|thumb|Spanish General [[Arsenio Martínez Campos]] in Havana, [[Captaincy General of Cuba|Colonial Cuba]], 1878]]
* [[Canary Islands]]
* [[Cape Juby]]
* [[Captaincy General of Cuba]]
** [[Spanish Florida]]
** [[Spanish Louisiana]]
* [[Captaincy General of the Philippines]]
** [[Caroline Islands]]
** [[Mariana Islands]]
** [[Palau Islands]]
* [[Ifni]]
* [[Río de Oro]]
* [[Saguia el-Hamra]]
* [[Spanish Morocco]]
* [[Spanish Netherlands]]
* [[Spanish Sahara]]
* [[Aragonese conquest of Sardinia|Spanish Sardinia]]
* [[Spanish Sicily]]
* [[Viceroyalty of Peru]]
** [[Captaincy General of Chile]]
* [[Viceroyalty of the Río de la Plata]]
** [[Spanish Guinea]]
*** [[Annobón]]
*** [[Bioko|Fernando Po]]
*** [[Río Muni]]
* [[Viceroyalty of New Granada]]
** [[Captaincy General of Venezuela]]
* [[Viceroyalty of New Spain]]
** [[Captaincy General of Guatemala]]
** [[Captaincy General of Yucatán]]
** [[Captaincy General of Santo Domingo]]
** [[Captaincy General of Puerto Rico]]
** [[Spanish Formosa]]

=== Austro-Hungarian colonies ===
[[File:Sarajevo 1878..jpg|thumb|[[Bosniaks|Muslim Bosniak]] resistance during the battle of Sarajevo in 1878 against the [[Austro-Hungarian campaign in Bosnia and Herzegovina in 1878|Austro-Hungarian occupation]]]]
* [[Austro-Hungarian rule in Bosnia and Herzegovina|Bosnia and Herzegovina]]
* [[Tianjin]]
* [[Austrian Netherlands]]
* [[Austrian colonization of Nicobar Islands|Nicobar Islands]]
* [[North Borneo]]
* [[Austrian colonial policy|Austrian Colonial Policy]]

=== Danish colonies ===
{{Main|Danish colonial empire}}
[[File:EU OCT and OMR map en.png|thumb|upright=2.5|Map of the European Union in the world, with [[Special member state territories and the European Union#Overseas countries and territories|Overseas Countries and Territories]] and [[Special member state territories and the European Union#Outermost regions|Outermost Regions]].]]
* [[Danish India|Andaman and Nicobar Islands]]
* [[Danish West Indies]] (now [[United States Virgin Islands]])
* [[Danish Norway]]
* [[Faroe islands]]
* [[Greenland]]
* [[Iceland]]
* [[Serampore]]
* [[Danish Gold Coast]]
* [[Danish India]]
*[[Duchy of Estonia (1219–1346)]]

=== Belgian colonies ===
* [[Belgian Congo]]
* [[Ruanda-Urundi]]
* [[Tianjin]]

=== Swedish colonies ===
* [[Baltic states]]
* [[Guadeloupe]]
* [[New Sweden]]
* [[Saint Barthélemy]]
* [[Swedish Pomerania]]
* [[Swedish Gold Coast]]

=== Polish-Lituanian colonies and protectorates ===
* [[Duchy of Prussia]]
* [[Polish Inflanty]]
* [[New Courland]]
* [[Couronian colonization|Couronian Africa]]
* [[Feodosia|Polish Kaffa]]

=== Romanian colonies and occupied territories ===
* [[Romanian concession in Sarandë]]
* [[Transnistria Governorate]]

=== Norwegian Overseas Territories ===
*[[Svalbard]]
*[[Jan Mayen]]
*[[Bouvet Island]]
*[[Queen Maud Land]]
*[[Peter I Island]]

===Other non-European colonialist countries===

====Australian protectorate====
* [[Papua New Guinea]]
* [[Christmas Island]]
* [[Cocos Islands]]
* [[Coral Sea Islands]]
* [[Heard Island and McDonald Islands]]
* [[Norfolk Island]]
* [[Nauru]]
* [[Australian Antarctic Territory]]

====New Zealand dependencies====
[[File:Cook Islands Annexation Ceremony.jpg|thumb|Governor [[Lord Ranfurly]] reading the annexation proclamation to [[Makea Takau Ariki|Queen Makea]] on 7 October 1900.]]
* [[Cook Islands]]
* [[Niue]]
* [[Ross Dependency]]
** [[Balleny Islands]]
** [[Ross Island]]
** [[Scott Island]]
** [[Roosevelt Island, Antarctica|Roosevelt Island]]

====United States colonies and protectorates====
{{Main|List of U.S. colonial possessions}}
[[File:Taft Addressing First Philippine Assembly 1907.jpg|thumb|Governor General [[William Howard Taft]] addressing the audience at the [[Philippine Assembly]] in the [[Manila Grand Opera House]]]]
* [[American Samoa]]
* [[Cuba]] ([[Platt Amendment]] turned Cuba into a protectorate)
* [[Falkland Islands]] (1832)
* [[Guantánamo Bay]]
* [[Guam]]
* [[Haiti]]
* [[Liberia]]
* [[Midway Atoll|Midway]]
* [[Nicaragua]]
* [[Palmyra Atoll]]
* [[Panama]] ([[Hay–Bunau-Varilla Treaty]] turned Panama into a protectorate)
* [[Panama Canal Zone]]
* [[Philippines]]
* [[Puerto Rico]]
* [[Sultanate of Sulu]]
* [[Swan Islands, Honduras]]
* [[Wake Island]]

====Japanese colonies and protectorates====
{{Main|Japanese colonial empire|List of territories occupied by Imperial Japan}}
* [[Bonin Islands]] [[File:Martial law, Korea 1900s.jpg|thumb|Three [[Koreans]] shot for pulling up rails as a protest against seizure of land without payment by the Japanese]]
* [[Karafuto]]
* [[Korea under Japanese rule|Korea]]
* [[Kuril Islands]]
* [[Kwantung Leased Territory]]
* [[South Pacific Mandate|Nanyo]]
** [[Caroline Islands]]
** [[Marshall Islands]]
** [[Northern Mariana Islands]]
* [[Penghu Islands]]
* [[Ryukyu Domain]]
* [[Taiwan under Japanese rule|Taiwan]]
* [[Volcano Islands]]

====Chinese colonies and protectorates====
[[File:Pacification of the Dzungars.jpg|thumb|Camp of the Qing Military in [[Khalkha]] in 1688.]]
* [[Guangxi]] ([[Tusi]])
* [[Hainan]]
** [[Nansha Islands]]
** [[Xisha Islands]]
* [[Manchuria]]
* [[Inner Mongolia]]
* [[Outer Mongolia]] during the Qing dynasty
* [[Taiwan]]
* [[Tibet]] ([[Kashag]])
* [[Tuva]] during the Qing dynasty
* [[Yunnan]] (Tusi)
* [[Chinese domination of Vietnam|Vietnam]] during the Han, Sui, and Tang dynasties
* [[Ryukyu Kingdom|Ryukyu]] from the 15th to the 19th century

====Omani colonies====
[[Omani Empire]]
[[File:Empire of Oman.svg|thumb|170px|Following the expulsion of the Portuguese colonizers, [[Sultanate of Oman]] was the preeminent power in the western Indian Ocean during the 17th century.&lt;ref name=&quot;OQCP&quot;&gt;Oman Country Profile. [https://www.qdl.qa/en/country-profile-oman Oman Country Profile.] British Library Partnership. Qatar Digital Library. 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;]]
* [[Swahili coast]]
* [[Zanzibar]]
* [[Qatar]]
* [[Somalia|Bahrain]]
* [[Somalia]]
* [[Socotra]]

====Mexican colonies====
* [[The Californias]]
* [[Texas]]
* [[Central America]]
* [[Clipperton Island]]
* [[Revillagigedo Islands]]
* [[Chiapas]]

====Ecuatorian colonies====
* [[Galápagos Islands]]

====Colombian colonies====
* [[Panama]]
* [[Ecuador]]
* [[Venezuela]]
* [[Archipelago of San Andrés, Providencia and Santa Catalina]]

====Argentine colonies and protectorates====
[[File:Base Marambio y el Hercules.jpg|thumb|Argentine [[Lockheed C-130 Hercules|C-130]] and control tower, [[Marambio Airport]]]]
[[File:Mapa ARGENTINA 1881.png|thumb|170px|The [[Conquest of the Desert]] extended Argentine power into [[Patagonia]].]]
* [[Protectorate of Peru]] (1820–1822)
* [[Gobierno del Cerrito]] (1843–1851)
* [[Chile]] (1817–1818)
* [[Paraguay]] (1810–1811, 1873)
* [[Uruguay]] (1810–1813)
* [[Bolivia]] (1810–1822)
* [[Tierra del Fuego Province, Argentina|Tierra del Fuego]]
* [[Conquest of the Desert|Patagonia]]
* [[Falkland Islands]] and [[Falkland Islands Dependencies|Dependencies]]  (1829–1831, 1832–1833, 1982)
* [[Argentine Antarctica]]
* [[Misiones]]
* [[Formosa province|Formosa]]
* [[Puna de Atacama]] (1839– )
* [[Hippolyte Bouchard|invasion Argentina to California]] (1818)

====Chilean colonies====
* [[Arica]]
* [[Easter Island]]
* [[Patagonia]]
* [[Chilean Antarctica]]
* [[Puna de Atacama]] (1879– )

====Paraguayan colonies====
* [[Mato Grosso do Sul]]
* [[Formosa province|Formosa]]

====Bolivian colonies====
* [[Puna de Atacama]] (1825–1839 ceded to Argentina) (1825–1879 ceded to Chile)
* [[Acre (state)|Acre]]

====Ethiopian colonies====
* [[Eritrea]]

====Moroccan colonies====
* [[Western Sahara]]

====India colonies and protectorates====
* [[Sikkim]]
* [[Kashmir]]
* [[Bhutan]]
* [[Nepal]]
* [[Goa]]
* [[North Sentinel Island]]
* [[Gilgit Baltistan]]

====Thailand colonies (Siam)====
[[File:Siamese Army in Laos 1893.jpg|thumb|Siamese Army in [[Laos]] in 1893.]]
* [[Kingdom of Vientiane]] (1778–1828)
* [[Kingdom of Luang Prabang]] (1778–1893)
* [[Kingdom of Champasak]] (1778–1893)
* [[Kingdom of Cambodia]] (1771–1867)
* [[Siamese invasion of Kedah|Kedah]] (1821–1826)

====(Ancient) Egyptian colonies====
* [[Canaan]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://books.google.com/?id=N3RyAAAAMAAJ |title=The Nile Delta in Transition: 4th.-3rd. Millennium B.C. : Proceedings of the Seminar Held in Cairo, 21.-24. October 1990, at the Netherlands Institute of Archaeology and Arabic Studies |last=Naomi Porat |publisher=Van den Brink |year=1992 |isbn=978-965-221-015-9 |editor-last=Edwin C. M. van den Brink |pages=433–440 |chapter=An Egyptian Colony in Southern Palestine During the Late Predynastic to Early Dynastic |access-date=24 February 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Impact of colonialism and colonisation==
{{Main|Analysis of Western European colonialism and colonization#Colonial actions and their impacts}}
[[File:Nieuws uit Indonesië, het werk van de Nederlandse dienst voor Volksgezondheid Weeknummer 46-21 - Open Beelden - 16742.ogv|thumb|The Dutch Public Health Service provides medical care for the natives of the [[Dutch East Indies]], May 1946]]

The impacts of colonisation are immense and pervasive.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://content.time.com/time/world/article/0,8599,1713275,00.html |title=Come Back, Colonialism, All Is Forgiven |last=Perry |first=Alex |date=2008-02-14 |work=Time |access-date=2019-09-29 |language=en-US |issn=0040-781X}}&lt;/ref&gt; Various effects, both immediate and protracted, include the spread of virulent [[Pandemic|diseases]], [[oppression|unequal social relations]], [[detribalization]], [[Exploitation of natural resources|exploitation]], [[enslavement]], [[History of medicine#Modern medicine|medical advances]], the creation of new institutions, [[Slavery in Africa#Abolition|abolitionism]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Lovejoy, Paul E. 2012&quot;&gt;Lovejoy, Paul E. (2012). Transformations of Slavery: A History of Slavery in Africa. London: Cambridge University Press.&lt;/ref&gt; improved infrastructure,&lt;ref&gt;Ferguson, Niall (2003). Empire: How Britain Made the Modern World. London: Allen Lane.&lt;/ref&gt; and technological progress.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Thong |first=Tezenlo |date=2012 |title=Civilised Colonisers and Barbaric Colonised: Reclaiming Naga Identity by Demythologising Colonial Portraits |journal=History and Anthropology |volume=23 |pages=375–97 |doi=10.1080/02757206.2012.697060 |number=3}}&lt;/ref&gt; Colonial practices also spur the spread of colonist languages, literature and cultural institutions, while endangering or obliterating those of native peoples. The native cultures of the colonised peoples can also have a powerful influence on the imperial country.{{citation needed|date=March 2012}}

===Economy, trade and commerce===
Economic expansion, sometimes described as the [[colonial surplus]], has accompanied imperial expansion since ancient times.{{citation needed|date=November 2012}} Greek trade networks spread throughout the Mediterranean region while Roman trade expanded with the primary goal of directing tribute from the colonised areas towards the Roman metropole. According to [[Strabo]], by the time of emperor [[Augustus]], up to 120 Roman ships would set sail every year from [[Myos Hormos]] in [[Roman Egypt]] to India.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Strabo/2E1*.html Strabo's Geography Book II Chapter 5 ]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; With the development of trade routes under the [[Ottoman Empire]],

{{blockquote|[[Gujari]] Hindus, Syrian Muslims, Jews, Armenians, Christians from south and central Europe operated trading routes that supplied Persian and Arab horses to the armies of all three empires, Mocha coffee to [[Delhi]] and [[Belgrade]], Persian silk to India and [[Istanbul]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=Peoples and Empires |last=Pagden |first=Anthony |publisher=Modern Library |year=2003 |isbn=978-0-8129-6761-6 |location=New York |page=45}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
[[File:16th century Portuguese Spanish trade routes.png|thumb|upright=1.5|[[Portuguese discoveries|Portuguese trade routes]] (blue) and the rival [[Manila galleon|Manila-Acapulco galleons]] trade routes (white) established in 1568]]
[[Aztec civilisation]] developed into an extensive empire that, much like the Roman Empire, had the goal of exacting tribute from the conquered colonial areas. For the Aztecs, a significant tribute was the acquisition of sacrificial victims for their religious rituals.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=Peoples and Empires |last=Pagden |first=Anthony |publisher=Modern Library |year=2003 |isbn=978-0-8129-6761-6 |location=New York |page=5}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On the other hand, European colonial empires sometimes attempted to channel, restrict and impede trade involving their colonies, funneling activity through the metropole and taxing accordingly.

Despite the general trend of economic expansion, the economic performance of former European colonies varies significantly. In &quot;Institutions as a Fundamental Cause of Long-run Growth&quot;, economists [[Daron Acemoglu]], [[Simon Johnson (economist)|Simon Johnson]] and [[James A. Robinson (Harvard University)|James A. Robinson]] compare the economic influences of the European colonists on different colonies and study what could explain the huge discrepancies in previous European colonies, for example, between West African colonies like [[Sierra Leone]] and [[Hong Kong]] and [[Singapore]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Institutions&quot;&gt;{{Cite book | doi=10.1016/S1574-0684(05)01006-3 |chapter = Institutions as a Fundamental Cause of Long-Run Growth|volume = 1A|pages = 385–472|title = Handbook of Economic Growth|year = 2005|last1 = Acemoglu|first1 = Daron|last2 = Johnson|first2 = Simon|last3 = Robinson|first3 = James A.|isbn = 9780444520418|chapter-url=http://economics.mit.edu/files/4469}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the paper, economic institutions are the determinant of the colonial success because they determine their financial performance and order for the distribution of resources. At the same time, these institutions are also consequences of political institutions – especially how [[de facto]] and [[de jure]] political power is allocated. To explain the different colonial cases, we thus need to look first into the political institutions that shaped the economic institutions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Institutions&quot; /&gt;
[[File:A Castro, Lorenzo - A Dutch East-Indiaman off Hoorn - Google Art Project.jpg|thumb|[[Dutch East India Company]] was the first-ever [[multinational corporation]], financed by shares that established the [[Amsterdam Stock Exchange|first modern stock exchange]].]]
For example, one interesting observation is &quot;the Reversal of Fortune&quot; – the less developed civilisations in 1500, like North America, Australia, and New Zealand, are now much richer than those countries who used to be in the prosperous civilisations in 1500 before the colonists came, like the Mughals in India and the Incas in the Americas. One explanation offered by the paper focuses on the political institutions of the various colonies: it was less likely for European colonists to introduce economic institutions where they could benefit quickly from the extraction of resources in the area. Therefore, given a more developed civilisation and denser population, European colonists would rather keep the existing economic systems than introduce an entirely new system; while in places with little to extract, European colonists would rather establish new economic institutions to protect their interests. Political institutions thus gave rise to different types of economic systems, which determined the colonial economic performance.&lt;ref name=&quot;Institutions&quot; /&gt;

European colonisation and development also changed gendered systems of power already in place around the world. In many pre-colonialist areas, women maintained power, prestige, or authority through reproductive or agricultural control. For example, in certain parts of sub-Saharan Africa women maintained farmland in which they had usage rights. While men would make political and communal decisions for a community, the women would control the village's food supply or their individual family's land. This allowed women to achieve power and autonomy, even in patrilineal and patriarchal societies.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://archive.org/details/noturningbackhis00free/page/25 |title=No Turning Back: The History of Feminism and The Future of Women |last=Freedman |first=Estelle |publisher=Random House Publishing Group |year=2002 |isbn=978-0-345-45053-1 |pages=[https://archive.org/details/noturningbackhis00free/page/25 25–26]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Through the rise of European colonialism came a large push for development and industrialisation of most economic systems. However, when working to improve productivity, Europeans focused mostly on male workers. Foreign aid arrived in the form of loans, land, credit, and tools to speed up development, but were only allocated to men. In a more European fashion, women were expected to serve on a more domestic level. The result was a technologic, economic, and class-based gender gap that widened over time.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://archive.org/details/noturningbackhis00free/page/113 |title=No Turning Back: The History of Feminism and The Future of Women |last=Freedman |first=Estelle |publisher=Random House Publishing |year=2002 |isbn=978-0-345-45053-1 |pages=[https://archive.org/details/noturningbackhis00free/page/113 113]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Within a colony, the presence of extractive colonial institutions in a given area has been found have effects on the modern day economic development, institutions and infrastructure of these areas.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | doi=10.1093/restud/rdz017 | title=The Development Effects of the Extractive Colonial Economy: The Dutch Cultivation System in Java| journal=The Review of Economic Studies| volume=87| pages=164–203| year=2020| last1=Dell| first1=Melissa| last2=Olken| first2=Benjamin A.|url=https://scholar.harvard.edu/dell/publications/development-effects-extractive-colonial-economy-dutch-cultivation-system-java}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | doi=10.1177/0010414015600465 | title= Colonial Legacies and State Institutions in China: Evidence From a Natural Experiment| journal=Comparative Political Studies| volume=50| issue=4| pages=434–463| year=2017| last1=Mattingly| first1=Daniel C.|url=http://daniel-mattingly.com/s/Mattingly_CPS_Preprint.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Slavery and indentured servitude===
{{Further|Atlantic slave trade|Indentured servant|Coolie|Blackbirding}}
[[File:Slave memorial Zanzibar.jpg|thumb|Slave memorial in [[Zanzibar]]. The Sultan of Zanzibar complied with British demands that slavery be banned in Zanzibar and that all the slaves be freed.]]

European nations entered their imperial projects with the goal of enriching the European metropole. Exploitation of non-Europeans and other Europeans to support imperial goals was acceptable to the colonisers. Two outgrowths of this imperial agenda were slavery and indentured servitude. In the 17th century, nearly two-thirds of English settlers came to North America as indentured servants.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.montgomerycollege.edu/Departments/hpolscrv/whiteser.html White Servitude] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141009091039/http://www.montgomerycollege.edu/Departments/hpolscrv/whiteser.html |date=2014-10-09 }}&quot;, by Richard Hofstadter, Montgomery College&lt;/ref&gt;

European slave traders brought large numbers of African slaves to the Americas by sail. Spain and Portugal had [[Atlantic slave trade|brought African slaves]] to work at African colonies such as [[Cape Verde]] and the [[Azores]], and then Latin America, by the 16th century. The British, French and Dutch joined in the slave trade in subsequent centuries. Approximately, around 11 million Africans were taken to the Caribbean and North and South America as slaves by European colonisers.&lt;ref name=&quot;King 2010 24&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://archive.org/details/peopleonmoveatla0000unse/page/24 |title=People on the Move: An Atlas of Migration |last=King |first=Russell |publisher=University of California Press |year=2010 |isbn=978-0-520-26124-2 |location=Berkeley, Los Angeles |page=[https://archive.org/details/peopleonmoveatla0000unse/page/24 24]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Marchands d'esclaves de Gorée-Jacques Grasset de Saint-Sauveur mg 8526.jpg|thumb|upright|Slave traders in Gorée, [[Senegal]], 18th century]]

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! European empire !! Colonial destination !! Number of slaves imported&lt;ref name=&quot;King 2010 24&quot; /&gt;
|-
| Portuguese Empire|| Brazil || 3,646,800
|-
| British Empire || British Caribbean || 1,665,000
|-
| French Empire || French Caribbean || 1,600,200
|-
| Spanish Empire || Latin America || 1,552,100
|-
| Dutch Empire || Dutch Caribbean || 500,000
|-
| British Empire || British North America || 399,000
|}

[[abolitionism|Abolitionists]] in Europe and Americas protested the inhumane treatment of African slaves, which led to the elimination of the slave trade by the late 18th century. The labour shortage that resulted inspired European colonisers to develop a new source of labour, using a system of indentured servitude. [[Indentured servant]]s consented to a contract with the European colonisers. Under their contract, the servant would work for an employer for a term of at least a year, while the employer agreed to pay for the servant's voyage to the colony, possibly pay for the return to the country of origin, and pay the employee a wage as well. The employee was &quot;indentured&quot; to the employer because they owed a debt back to the employer for their travel expense to the colony, which they were expected to pay through their wages. In practice, indentured servants were exploited through terrible working conditions and burdensome debts created by the employers, with whom the servants had no means of negotiating the debt once they arrived in the colony.

India and China were the largest source of indentured servants during the colonial era. Indentured servants from India travelled to British colonies in Asia, Africa and the Caribbean, and also to French and Portuguese colonies, while Chinese servants travelled to British and Dutch colonies. Between 1830 and 1930, around 30 million indentured servants migrated from India, and 24 million returned to India. China sent more indentured servants to European colonies, and around the same proportion returned to China.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://archive.org/details/peopleonmoveatla0000unse/page/26 |title=People on the Move: An Atlas of Migration |last=King |first=Russell |publisher=University of California Press |year=2010 |isbn=978-0-520-26124-2 |location=Berkeley, Los Angeles |pages=[https://archive.org/details/peopleonmoveatla0000unse/page/26 26–27]}}&lt;/ref&gt;l

Following the [[Scramble for Africa]], an early but secondary focus for most colonial regimes was the suppression of slavery and the slave trade. By the end of the colonial period they were mostly successful in this aim, though slavery is still very active in Africa and the world at large with much the same practices of de facto servility despite legislative prohibition.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lovejoy, Paul E. 2012&quot; /&gt;

===Military innovation===
[[File:Aschanti Gefecht 11 july 1824 300dpi.jpg|thumb|upright=1.2|The [[First Anglo-Ashanti War]], 1823–31]]
Conquering forces have throughout history applied innovation in order to gain an advantage over the armies of the people they aim to conquer. Greeks developed the [[phalanx]] system, which enabled their military units to present themselves to their enemies as a wall, with foot soldiers using shields to cover one another during their advance on the battlefield. Under [[Philip II of Macedon]], they were able to organise thousands of soldiers into a formidable battle force, bringing together carefully trained infantry and cavalry regiments.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=Peoples and Empires |last=Pagden |first=Anthony |publisher=Modern Library |year=2003 |isbn=978-0-8129-6761-6 |location=New York |page=6}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Alexander the Great]] exploited this military foundation further during his conquests.

The Spanish Empire held a major advantage over [[Mesoamerican]] warriors through the use of weapons made of stronger metal, predominantly iron, which was able to shatter the blades of axes used by the [[Aztec civilisation]] and others. The use of [[gunpowder]] weapons cemented the European military advantage over the peoples they sought to subjugate in the Americas and elsewhere.

===The end of empire===
[[File:Lord Pethic-Lawrence and Gandhi.jpg|thumb|[[Mohandas Karamchand Gandhi|Gandhi]] with [[Frederick Pethick-Lawrence, 1st Baron Pethick-Lawrence|Lord Pethwick-Lawrence]], British Secretary of State for India, after a meeting on 18 April 1946]]
The populations of some colonial territories, such as Canada, enjoyed relative peace and prosperity as part of a European power, at least among the majority; however, minority populations such as [[First Nations]] peoples and French-Canadians experienced [[marginalisation]] and resented colonial practises. Francophone residents of [[Quebec]], for example, were vocal in opposing conscription into the armed services to fight on behalf of Britain during World War I, resulting in the [[Conscription crisis of 1917]]. Other European colonies had much more pronounced conflict between European settlers and the local population. Rebellions broke out in the later decades of the imperial era, such as India's [[Sepoy Rebellion]].

The territorial boundaries imposed by European colonisers, notably in central Africa and South Asia, defied the existing boundaries of native populations that had previously interacted little with one another. European colonisers disregarded native political and cultural animosities, imposing peace upon people under their military control. Native populations were often relocated at the will of the colonial administrators. Once independence from European control was achieved, civil war erupted in some former colonies, as native populations fought to capture territory for their own ethnic, cultural or political group.{{citation needed|date=June 2017}} The [[Partition of India]], a 1947 civil war that came in the aftermath of India's independence from Britain, became a conflict with 500,000 killed. Fighting erupted between Hindu, Sikh and Muslim communities as they fought for territorial dominance. Muslims fought for an independent country to be partitioned where they would not be a religious minority, resulting in the creation of [[Pakistan]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=The Great Big Book of Horrible Things |title-link=The Great Big Book of Horrible Things |last=White |first=Matthew |publisher=W.W. Norton &amp; Co. |year=2012 |isbn=978-0-393-08192-3 |pages=427–28 |author-link=Matthew White (historian)}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Post-independence population movement===
[[File:Notting Hill Carnival 2002 large.jpg|thumb|The annual [[Notting Hill Carnival]] in [[London]] is a celebration led by the [[Trinidadian and Tobagonian British]] community.]]

In a reversal of the migration patterns experienced during the modern colonial era, post-independence era migration followed a route back towards the imperial country. In some cases, this was a movement of settlers of European origin returning to the land of their birth, or to an ancestral birthplace. 900,000 French colonists (known as the ''[[Pied-Noir]]s'') resettled in France following Algeria's independence in 1962. A significant number of these migrants were also of Algerian descent. 800,000 people of [[Processo Revolucionário Em Curso#The retornados|Portuguese]] origin migrated to Portugal after the independence of former colonies in Africa between 1974 and 1979; 300,000 settlers of Dutch origin migrated to the Netherlands from the [[Dutch West Indies]] after Dutch military control of the colony ended.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://archive.org/details/peopleonmoveatla0000unse/page/35 |title=People on the Move: An Atlas of Migration |last=King |first=Russell |publisher=University of California Press |year=2010 |isbn=978-0-520-26124-2 |location=Berkeley, Los Angeles |page=[https://archive.org/details/peopleonmoveatla0000unse/page/35 35]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After WWII 300,000 Dutchmen from the [[Dutch East Indies]], of which the majority were people of Eurasian descent called [[Indo people|Indo Europeans]], repatriated to the Netherlands. A significant number later migrated to the US, Canada, Australia and New Zealand.&lt;ref&gt;Willems, Wim &quot;De uittocht uit Indie (1945–1995), De geschiedenis van Indische Nederlanders&quot; (Publisher: Bert Bakker, Amsterdam, 2001). {{ISBN|90-351-2361-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Crul, Lindo and Lin Pang. Culture, Structure and Beyond, Changing identities and social positions of immigrants and their children (Het Spinhuis Publishers, 1999). {{ISBN|90-5589-173-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Global travel and migration in general developed at an increasingly brisk pace throughout the era of European colonial expansion. Citizens of the former colonies of European countries may have a privileged status in some respects with regard to immigration rights when settling in the former European imperial nation. For example, rights to dual citizenship may be generous,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/1981/61 |title=British Nationality Act 1981 |publisher=The National Archives, United Kingdom |access-date=February 24, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; or larger immigrant quotas may be extended to former colonies.

In some cases, the former European imperial nations continue to foster close political and economic ties with former colonies. The [[Commonwealth of Nations]] is an organisation that promotes cooperation between and among Britain and its former colonies, the Commonwealth members. A similar organisation exists for former colonies of France, the [[Francophonie]]; the [[Community of Portuguese Language Countries]] plays a similar role for former Portuguese colonies, and the [[Dutch Language Union]] is the equivalent for former colonies of the Netherlands.

Migration from former colonies has proven to be problematic for European countries, where the majority population may express hostility to ethnic minorities who have immigrated from former colonies. Cultural and religious conflict have often erupted in France in recent decades, between immigrants from the [[Maghreb]] countries of north Africa and the majority population of France. Nonetheless, immigration has changed the ethnic composition of France; by the 1980s, 25% of the total population of &quot;inner Paris&quot; and 14% of the metropolitan region were of foreign origin, mainly Algerian.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |jstor = 45038321|title = Cultural Conflicts: North African Immigrants in France|journal = International Journal of Peace Studies|volume = 2|issue = 2|pages = 67–75|last1 = Seljuq|first1 = Affan|year = 1997|url=http://www.gmu.edu/programs/icar/ijps/vol2_2/seljuq.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Introduced diseases===
{{See also|Globalisation and disease|Columbian Exchange|Impact and evaluation of colonialism and colonization}}
[[File:Florentinoviruela.JPG|thumb|Aztecs dying of smallpox, (&quot;[[Florentine Codex|The Florentine Codex]]&quot; 1540–85)]]

Encounters between explorers and populations in the rest of the world often introduced new diseases, which sometimes caused local epidemics of extraordinary virulence.&lt;ref&gt;Kenneth F. Kiple, ed. ''The Cambridge Historical Dictionary of Disease'' (2003).&lt;/ref&gt; For example, smallpox, measles, malaria, yellow fever, and others were unknown in pre-Columbian America.&lt;ref&gt;Alfred W. Crosby, Jr., ''The Columbian Exchange: Biological and Cultural Consequences of 1492'' (1974)&lt;/ref&gt;

Disease killed the entire native ([[Guanches]]) population of the [[Canary Islands]] in the 16th century. Half the native population of [[Hispaniola]] in 1518 was killed by [[smallpox]]. Smallpox also ravaged [[Mexico]] in the 1520s, killing 150,000 in [[Tenochtitlan]] alone, including the emperor, and [[Peru]] in the 1530s, aiding the European conquerors. [[Measles]] killed a further two million Mexican natives in the 17th century. In 1618–1619, smallpox wiped out 90% of the [[Massachusetts Bay]] Native Americans.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ucpress.edu/books/pages/9968/9968.ch01.html ''Smallpox – The Fight to Eradicate a Global Scourge''] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080907093641/http://www.ucpress.edu/books/pages/9968/9968.ch01.html |date=2008-09-07 }}, David A. Koplow.&lt;/ref&gt; Smallpox epidemics in 1780–1782 and [[1837-38 smallpox epidemic|1837–1838]] brought devastation and drastic depopulation among the [[Plains Indians]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Houston |first=C.S. |last2=Houston |first2=S. |year=2000 |title=The first smallpox epidemic on the Canadian Plains: In the fur-traders' words |journal=The Canadian Journal of Infectious Diseases |volume=11 |issue=2 |pages=112–15 |doi=10.1155/2000/782978 |pmc=2094753 |pmid=18159275}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some believe that the death of up to 95% of the [[Population history of American indigenous peoples|Native American population]] of the [[New World]] was caused by [[Old World]] diseases.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.pbs.org/gunsgermssteel/variables/smallpox.html |title=Guns Germs &amp; Steel: Variables. Smallpox {{!}} PBS |website=www.pbs.org |access-date=2019-09-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; Over the centuries, the Europeans had developed high degrees of [[Immunity (medical)|immunity]] to these diseases, while the [[indigenous peoples]] had no time to build such immunity.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.millersville.edu/~columbus/papers/goodling.html Stacy Goodling, &quot;Effects of European Diseases on the Inhabitants of the New World&quot;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080510163413/http://www.millersville.edu/~columbus/papers/goodling.html |date=2008-05-10 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Smallpox decimated the native population of [[Australia]], killing around 50% of [[indigenous Australians]] in the early years of British colonisation.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://encarta.msn.com/media_701508643/Smallpox_Through_History.html |title=Smallpox Through History |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20091029184350/http://encarta.msn.com/media_701508643/Smallpox_Through_History.html |archive-date=2009-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; It also killed many [[New Zealand]] [[Māori people|Māori]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.canr.msu.edu/overseas/nzenvironsci/infopart2.htm New Zealand Historical Perspective] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100612021507/http://www.canr.msu.edu/overseas/nzenvironsci/infopart2.htm |date=June 12, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; As late as 1848–49, as many as 40,000 out of 150,000 [[Hawaii]]ans are estimated to have died of [[measles]], [[whooping cough]] and [[influenza]]. Introduced diseases, notably smallpox, nearly wiped out the native population of [[Easter Island]].&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.independent.co.uk/news/science/how-did-easter-islands-ancient-statues-lead-to-the-destruction-of-an-entire-ecosystem-455877.html How did Easter Island's ancient statues lead to the destruction of an entire ecosystem?], ''The Independent''.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1875, [[measles]] killed over 40,000 [[Fiji]]ans, approximately one-third of the population.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fsm.ac.fj/aboutfsm.html Fiji School of Medicine] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141020165015/http://www.fsm.ac.fj/aboutfsm.html |date=October 20, 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Ainu people|Ainu]] population decreased drastically in the 19th century, due in large part
to infectious diseases brought by Japanese settlers pouring into [[Hokkaido]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/asia/features/ontheroad/japan.sapporo.ainu.html Meeting the First Inhabitants] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110622085958/http://www.time.com/time/asia/features/ontheroad/japan.sapporo.ainu.html |date=June 22, 2011 }}, TIMEasia.com, 21 August 2000.&lt;/ref&gt;

Conversely, researchers have hypothesised that a precursor to [[syphilis]] may have been carried from the New World to Europe after [[Christopher Columbus|Columbus]]'s voyages. The findings suggested Europeans could have carried the nonvenereal tropical bacteria home, where the organisms may have mutated into a more deadly form in the different conditions of Europe.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.nytimes.com/2008/01/15/science/15syph.html Genetic Study Bolsters Columbus Link to Syphilis], ''New York Times'', January 15, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; The disease was more frequently fatal than it is today; syphilis was a major killer in Europe during the [[Renaissance]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |title=Columbus May Have Brought Syphilis to Europe |url=http://www.livescience.com/history/080114-syphilis-columbus.html |journal=LiveScience}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[first cholera pandemic]] began in [[Bengal]], then spread across India by 1820. Ten thousand British troops and countless Indians died during this [[pandemic]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cbc.ca/health/story/2008/05/09/f-cholera-outbreaks.html Cholera's seven pandemics]. CBC News. December 2, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Between 1736 and 1834 only some 10% of [[East India Company]]'s officers survived to take the final voyage home.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.asianreviewofbooks.com/new/?revID=610 |title=Sahib: The British Soldier in India, 1750–1914 by Richard Holmes [Asi… |date=2012-05-30 |website=archive.fo |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://archive.today/20120530044859/http://www.asianreviewofbooks.com/new/?revID=610 |archive-date=2012-05-30 |access-date=2019-09-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Waldemar Haffkine]], who mainly worked in India, who developed and used [[vaccine]]s against [[cholera]] and [[bubonic plague]] in the 1890s, is considered the first [[microbiologist]].

====Countering disease====
As early as 1803, the [[Enlightenment in Spain|Spanish]] Crown organised a mission (the [[Balmis expedition]]) to transport the smallpox vaccine to the [[Spanish Empire|Spanish colonies]], and establish mass vaccination programs there.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.doh.gov.ph/sphh/balmis.htm Dr. Francisco de Balmis and his Mission of Mercy, Society of Philippine Health History.] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20041223112019/http://www.doh.gov.ph/sphh/balmis.htm |date=2004-12-23 }}&lt;/ref&gt; By 1832, the federal government of the United States established a [[Smallpox vaccine|smallpox vaccination]] program for Native Americans.&lt;ref&gt;[http://muse.jhu.edu/login?uri=/journals/wicazo_sa_review/v018/18.2pearson01.html Lewis Cass and the Politics of Disease: The Indian Vaccination Act of 1832.]&lt;/ref&gt; Under the direction of [[Mountstuart Elphinstone]] a program was launched to propagate [[smallpox vaccination]] in India.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.smallpoxhistory.ucl.ac.uk/Other%20Asia/ongoingwork.htm Smallpox History – Other histories of smallpox in South Asia.] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120416015559/http://www.smallpoxhistory.ucl.ac.uk/Other%20Asia/ongoingwork.htm |date=2012-04-16 }}&lt;/ref&gt; From the beginning of the 20th century onwards, the elimination or control of disease in tropical countries became a driving force for all colonial powers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gresham.ac.uk/event.asp?PageId=45&amp;EventId=696 Conquest and Disease or Colonialism and Health?] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20081207015726/http://www.gresham.ac.uk/event.asp?PageId=45&amp;EventId=696 |date=2008-12-07 }}, Gresham College | Lectures and Events.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[African trypanosomiasis|sleeping sickness]] epidemic in Africa was arrested due to mobile teams systematically screening millions of people at risk.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=WHO Media centre |year=2001 |title=Fact sheet N°259: African trypanosomiasis or sleeping sickness. |url=http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs259/en/index.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the 20th century, the world saw the biggest increase in its population in [[human history]] due to lessening of the [[mortality rate]] in many countries due to [[History of medicine#Modern medicine|medical advances]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Iliffe |first=John |year=1989 |title=The Origins of African Population Growth |journal=The Journal of African History |volume=30 |issue=1 |pages=165–69 |doi=10.1017/s0021853700030942 |jstor=182701}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[world population]] has grown from 1.6 billion in 1900 to over seven billion today.

==Colonialism and the history of thought==
{{See also|Historiography of the British Empire}}

===Universalism===
The conquest of vast territories brings multitudes of diverse cultures under the central control of the imperial authorities. From the time of Ancient Greece and Ancient Rome, this fact has been addressed by empires adopting the concept of universalism, and applying it to their imperial policies towards their subjects far from the imperial capitol. The capitol, the metropole, was the source of ostensibly enlightened policies imposed throughout the distant colonies.

The empire that grew from Greek conquest, particularly by [[Alexander the Great]], spurred the spread of Greek language, religion, science and philosophy throughout the colonies. While most Greeks considered their own culture superior to all others (the word [[barbarian]] is derived from mutterings that sounded to Greek ears like &quot;bar-bar&quot;), Alexander was unique in promoting a campaign to win the [[Winning hearts and minds|hearts and minds]] of the Persians. He [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Plutarch/Lives/Alexander*/6-7.html adopted Persian customs of clothing] and otherwise encouraged his men to [[wikt:go native|go native]] by adopting local wives and learning their mannerisms. Of note is that he radically departed from earlier Greek attempts at colonisation, characterised by the [[History of the Peloponnesian War|murder and enslavement of the local inhabitants]] and the settling of Greek citizens from the polis.

Roman universalism was characterised by cultural and religious tolerance and a focus on civil efficiency and the rule of law. [[Roman law]] was imposed on both Roman citizens and colonial subjects. Although Imperial Rome had [[Education in ancient Rome|no public education]], [[Latin]] spread through its use in government and trade. Roman law prohibited local leaders to wage war between themselves, which was responsible for the 200 year long [[Pax Romana]], at the time the longest period of peace in history. The Roman Empire was tolerant of diverse cultures and religious practises, even allowing them on a few occasions to [[Hyrcanus II|threaten Roman authority]].

===Colonialism and geography===
[[File:The National Archives UK - CO 1069-99-01.jpg|thumb|[[British Togoland]] in 1953]]

Settlers acted as the link between indigenous populations and the imperial hegemony, thus bridging the geographical, ideological and commercial gap between the colonisers and colonised. While the extent in which geography as an academic study is implicated in colonialism is contentious, geographical tools such as [[cartography]], [[shipbuilding]], [[navigation]], mining and agricultural productivity were instrumental in European colonial expansion. Colonisers' awareness of the Earth's surface and abundance of practical skills provided colonisers with a knowledge that, in turn, created power.&lt;ref name=&quot;Painter&quot;&gt;&quot;Painter, J. &amp; Jeffrey, A., 2009. ''Political Geography'', 2nd ed., Sage. &quot;Imperialism&quot; p. 23 (GIC).&lt;/ref&gt;

Anne Godlewska and Neil Smith argue that &quot;empire was 'quintessentially a geographical project{{'&quot;}}.{{clarify|reason=What is the meaning of the quote within a quote?|date=March 2018}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Nayak&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |title=Geographical thought : an introduction to ideas in human geography |last=Nayak |first=Anoop |last2=Jeffrey |first2=Alex |date=2011 |publisher=Pearson Prentice Hall |isbn=978-0-13-222824-4 |location=Harlow, England |pages=4–5}}&lt;/ref&gt; Historical geographical theories such as [[environmental determinism]] legitimised colonialism by positing the view that some parts of the world were underdeveloped, which created notions of skewed evolution.&lt;ref name=&quot;Painter&quot; /&gt; Geographers such as [[Ellen Churchill Semple]] and [[Ellsworth Huntington]] put forward the notion that northern climates bred vigour and intelligence as opposed to those indigenous to tropical climates (See [[The Tropics]]) viz a viz a combination of [[environmental determinism]] and [[Social Darwinism]] in their approach.&lt;ref name=&quot;arnold&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Arnold |first=David |date=March 2000 |title=&quot;Illusory Riches&quot;: Representations of the Tropical World, 1840–1950 |journal=Singapore Journal of Tropical Geography |volume=21 |issue=1 |pages=6–18 |doi=10.1111/1467-9493.00060}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Political geographers also maintain that colonial behaviour was reinforced by the physical mapping of the world, therefore creating a visual separation between &quot;them&quot; and &quot;us&quot;. Geographers are primarily focused on the spaces of colonialism and imperialism; more specifically, the material and symbolic appropriation of space enabling colonialism.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gallaher&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=XpBJclVnVdQC&amp;pg=PA5 |title=Key Concepts in Political Geography |last=Gallaher |first=Carolyn |last2=Dahlman |first2=Carl T. |last3=Gilmartin |first3=Mary |last4=Mountz |first4=Alison |last5=Shirlow |first5=Peter |date=2009 |publisher=Sage |isbn=978-1-4129-4672-8 |location=London |pages=392 |author-link=Carolyn Gallaher |access-date=July 31, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|5}}
[[File:Scramble-for-Africa-1880-1913.png|thumb|upright=1.5|Comparison of Africa in the years 1880 and 1913]]
Maps played an extensive role in colonialism, as Bassett would put it &quot;by providing geographical information in a convenient and standardised format, cartographers helped open West Africa to European conquest, commerce, and colonisation&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |jstor = 215456|title = Cartography and Empire Building in Nineteenth-Century West Africa|journal = Geographical Review|volume = 84|issue = 3|pages=316–335|last1 = Bassett|first1 = Thomas J.|year = 1994|doi = 10.2307/215456|url = https://semanticscholar.org/paper/945f542c5e9719b0ff9b928cf7ba48d830af2d33}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, because the relationship between colonialism and geography was not scientifically objective, cartography was often manipulated during the colonial era. Social norms and values had an effect on the constructing of maps. During colonialism map-makers used rhetoric in their formation of boundaries and in their art. The rhetoric favoured the view of the conquering Europeans; this is evident in the fact that any map created by a non-European was instantly regarded as inaccurate. Furthermore, European cartographers were required to follow a set of rules which led to ethnocentrism; portraying one's own ethnicity in the centre of the map. As [[J.B. Harley]] put it, &quot;The steps in making a map – selection, omission, simplification, classification, the creation of hierarchies, and 'symbolisation' – are all inherently rhetorical.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Harley |first=J. B. |title=Deconstructing the Map |journal=Cartographica |volume=26 |issue=2 |pages=1–20 |date=1989 |doi=10.3138/E635-7827-1757-9T53}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A common practice by the European cartographers of the time was to map unexplored areas as &quot;blank spaces&quot;. This influenced the colonial powers as it sparked competition amongst them to explore and colonise these regions. Imperialists aggressively and passionately looked forward to filling these spaces for the glory of their respective countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |jstor = 215456|title = Cartography and Empire Building in Nineteenth-Century West Africa|journal = Geographical Review|volume = 84|issue = 3|pages=322, 324–25|last1 = Bassett|first1 = Thomas J.|year = 1994|doi = 10.2307/215456|url = https://semanticscholar.org/paper/945f542c5e9719b0ff9b928cf7ba48d830af2d33}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Dictionary of Human Geography'' notes that cartography was used to empty 'undiscovered' lands of their Indigenous meaning and bring them into spatial existence via the imposition of &quot;Western place-names and borders, [therefore] priming 'virgin' (putatively empty land, 'wilderness') for colonisation (thus sexualising colonial landscapes as domains of male penetration), reconfiguring alien space as absolute, quantifiable and separable (as property).&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;human geo&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |title=The dictionary of human geography |date=2009 |publisher=Wiley-Blackwell |isbn=978-1-4051-3288-6 |editor-last=Gregory |editor-first=Derek |edition=5th |location=Chichester (UK) |pages=96–97 |editor-last2=Johnston |editor-first2=Ron |editor-last3=Pratt |editor-first3=Geraldine |editor-last4=Watts |editor-first4=Michael |editor-last5=Whatmore |editor-first5=Sarah}}&lt;/ref&gt;

David Livingstone stresses &quot;that geography has meant different things at different times and in different places&quot; and that we should keep an open mind in regards to the relationship between geography and colonialism instead of identifying boundaries.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nayak&quot; /&gt; Geography as a discipline was not and is not an objective science, Painter and Jeffrey argue, rather it is based on assumptions about the physical world.&lt;ref name=&quot;Painter&quot; /&gt; Comparison of [[wikt:exogeography|exogeographical]] representations of ostensibly tropical environments in science fiction art support this conjecture, finding the notion of the tropics to be an artificial collection of ideas and beliefs that are independent of geography.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Menadue |first=Christopher Benjamin |date=2018-09-04 |title=Cities in Flight: A Descriptive Examination of the Tropical City Imagined in Twentieth Century Science Fiction Cover Art |journal=ETropic: Electronic Journal of Studies in the Tropics |language=en |volume=17 |issue=2 |doi=10.25120/etropic.17.2.2018.3658 |issn=1448-2940}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Colonialism and imperialism===
[[File:Félix Éboué and Charles DeGaulle.jpg|thumb|upright|Governor-General [[Félix Éboué]] welcomes [[Charles de Gaulle]] to [[French Chad|Chad]]]]

A colony is a part of an empire and so colonialism is closely related to [[imperialism]]. Assumptions are that colonialism and imperialism are interchangeable, however [[Robert J. C. Young]] suggests that imperialism is the concept while colonialism is the practice. Colonialism is based on an imperial outlook, thereby creating a consequential relationship. Through an empire, colonialism is established and capitalism is expanded, on the other hand a capitalist economy naturally enforces an empire. In the next section Marxists make a case for this mutually reinforcing relationship.

===Marxist view of colonialism===
Marxism views colonialism as a form of capitalism, enforcing exploitation and social change. Marx thought that working within the global capitalist system, colonialism is closely associated with uneven development. It is an &quot;instrument of wholesale destruction, dependency and systematic exploitation producing distorted economies, socio-psychological disorientation, massive poverty and neocolonial dependency&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite encyclopedia | entry-url=https://books.google.com/?id=jXl0DwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT174 |title = Encyclopedia of International Development|isbn = 9781136952913|editor-last1 = Forsyth|editor-first1 = Tim|date = 2005|publisher=Routledge|entry=colonialism, history of|last=Watts|first=Michael}}&lt;/ref&gt; Colonies are constructed into modes of production. The search for raw materials and the current search for new investment opportunities is a result of inter-capitalist rivalry for [[capital accumulation]]. Lenin regarded colonialism as the root cause of imperialism, as imperialism was distinguished by monopoly capitalism via colonialism and as [[Lyal S. Sunga]] explains: &quot;Vladimir Lenin advocated forcefully the principle of self-determination of peoples in his &quot;Theses on the Socialist Revolution and the Right of Nations to Self-Determination&quot; as an integral plank in the programme of socialist internationalism&quot; and he quotes Lenin who contended that &quot;The right of nations to self-determination implies exclusively the right to independence in the political sense, the right to free political separation from the oppressor nation. Specifically, this demand for political democracy implies complete freedom to agitate for secession and for a referendum on secession by the seceding nation.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Dbb8eQH-vbQC&amp;pg=PA90 | title=The Emerging System of International Criminal Law: Developments in Codification and Implementation| isbn=9789041104724| last1=Sunga| first1=Lyal S.| date=1997|pp=90ff|publisher=Martinus Nijhoff Publishers}} Sunga traces the origin of the international movement against colonialism, and relates it to the rise of the right to self-determination in international law.&lt;/ref&gt; Non Russian marxists within the RSFSR and later the USSR, like Sultan Galiev and Vasyl Shakhrai, meanwhile, between 1918 and 1923 and then after 1929, considered the Soviet Regime a renewed version of the Russian imperialism and colonialism.

In his critique of colonialism in Africa, the Guyanese historian and political activist [[Walter Rodney]] states:

:&quot;The decisiveness of the short period of colonialism and its negative consequences for Africa spring mainly from the fact that Africa lost power. Power is the ultimate determinant in human society, being basic to the relations within any group and between groups. It implies the ability to defend one's interests and if necessary to impose one's will by any means available&amp;nbsp;... When one society finds itself forced to relinquish power entirely to another society that in itself is a form of [[underdevelopment]]&amp;nbsp;... During the centuries of pre-colonial trade, some control over social political and economic life was retained in Africa, in spite of the disadvantageous commerce with Europeans. That little control over internal matters disappeared under colonialism. Colonialism went much further than trade. It meant a tendency towards direct appropriation by Europeans of the social institutions within Africa. Africans ceased to set indigenous cultural goals and standards, and lost full command of training young members of the society. Those were undoubtedly major steps backwards&amp;nbsp;... Colonialism was not merely a system of exploitation, but one whose essential purpose was to repatriate the profits to the so-called 'mother country'. From an African view-point, that amounted to consistent expatriation of surplus produced by African labour out of African resources. It meant the development of Europe as part of the same dialectical process in which Africa was underdeveloped.

:&quot;Colonial Africa fell within that part of the international capitalist economy from which surplus was drawn to feed the metropolitan sector. As seen earlier, exploitation of land and labour is essential for human social advance, but only on the assumption that the product is made available within the area where the exploitation takes place.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=CwSSkemSJLcC&amp;pg=PA224 |title=How Europe Underdeveloped Africa |last=Walter Rodney |publisher=East African Publishers |isbn=978-9966-25-113-8 |pages=149, 224|year=1972 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=eyiZafDHpqoC&amp;pg=PA271 |title=A Companion To Postcolonial Studies |last=Henry Schwarz |last2=Sangeeta Ray |publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons |year=2004 |isbn=978-0-470-99833-5 |page=271}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to [[Vladimir Lenin|Lenin]], the new imperialism emphasised the transition of capitalism from [[free trade]] to a stage of [[monopoly]] [[capitalism]] to finance [[Capital (economics)|capital]]. He states it is, &quot;connected with the intensification of the struggle for the partition of the world&quot;. As [[free trade]] thrives on [[exports]] of commodities, monopoly capitalism thrived on the export of capital amassed by profits from banks and industry. This, to Lenin, was the highest stage of capitalism. He goes on to state that this form of capitalism was doomed for war between the capitalists and the exploited nations with the former inevitably losing. War is stated to be the consequence of imperialism. As a continuation of this thought G.N. Uzoigwe states, &quot;But it is now clear from more serious investigations of African history in this period that imperialism was essentially economic in its fundamental impulses.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Boahen, A. Adu. ''Africa under Colonial Domination 1880–1935''. London: Heinemann, 1985. 11. Print.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Liberalism, capitalism and colonialism===
[[Classical liberals]] were generally in abstract opposition to colonialism and imperialism, including [[Adam Smith]], [[Frédéric Bastiat]], [[Richard Cobden]], John Bright, Henry Richard, [[Herbert Spencer]], H.R. Fox Bourne, Edward Morel, Josephine Butler, W.J. Fox and [[William Ewart Gladstone]].&lt;ref name=&quot;dk&quot;&gt;[http://www.setav.org/ups/dosya/24514.pdf Liberal Anti-Imperialism] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110922011211/http://www.setav.org/ups/dosya/24514.pdf |date=2011-09-22 }}, professor Daniel Klein, 1.7.2004&lt;/ref&gt; Their philosophies found the [[Imperialism|colonial enterprise]], particularly [[mercantilism]], in opposition to the principles of [[free trade]] and [[Political freedom|liberal policies]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite encyclopedia |year=2007 |title=Anticolonialism |encyclopedia=Encyclopedia of Western Colonialism since 1450 |publisher=Macmillan Reference USA |location=Detroit |url=https://www.academia.edu/9048629 |accessdate=May 22, 2015 |editor-last=Benjamin, Thomas |edition=Gale Virtual Reference Library |pages=57–65 |last=Hidalgo|first= Dennis}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Adam Smith]] wrote in ''[[The Wealth of Nations]]'' that Britain should grant independence to all of its colonies and also argued that it would be economically beneficial for British people in the average, although the merchants having mercantilist privileges would lose out.&lt;ref name=dk/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=The nature and causes of the wealth of nations (&quot;Of Colonies&quot;) |last=Smith, Adam |publisher=T. Cadell |year=1811 |location=London |pages=343–84}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Scientific thought in colonialism, race and gender===
During the colonial era, the global process of colonisation served to spread and synthesize the social and political belief systems of the &quot;mother-countries&quot; which often included a belief in a certain natural racial superiority of the race of the mother-country. Colonialism also acted to reinforce these same racial belief systems within the &quot;mother-countries&quot; themselves. Usually also included within the colonial belief systems was a certain belief in the inherent superiority of male over female, however this particular belief was often pre-existing amongst the pre-colonial societies, prior to their colonisation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stoler 1989&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Stoler |first=Ann L. |date=Nov 1989 |title=Making Empire Respectable: The Politics of Race and Sexual Morality in 20th-Century Colonical Cultures |url=https://deepblue.lib.umich.edu/bitstream/2027.42/136501/1/ae.1989.16.4.02a00030.pdf |journal=American Ethnologist |volume=16 |issue=4 |pages=634–60 |doi=10.1525/ae.1989.16.4.02a00030|hdl=2027.42/136501 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Fee&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal |pmid = 394780|year = 1979|last1 = Fee|first1 = E.|title = Nineteenth-century craniology: The study of the female skull|journal = Bulletin of the History of Medicine|volume = 53|issue = 3|pages = 415–33}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Fausto-Sterling 2001&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |chapter=Gender, Race, and Nation: The Comparative Anatomy of &quot;Hottentot&quot; women in Europe, 1815–1817 |last=Fausto-Sterling |first=Anne |title=The Gender and Science Reader |publisher=Routledge |year=2001 |editor-last=Muriel Lederman and Ingrid Bartsch|chapter-url=https://www.researchgate.net/publication/234102374}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Popular political practices of the time reinforced colonial rule by legitimising European (and/ or Japanese) male authority, and also legitimising female and non-mother-country race inferiority through studies of [[Craniology]], [[Comparative Anatomy]], and [[Phrenology]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Fee&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Fausto-Sterling 2001&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books/about/The_Racial_Economy_of_Science.html?id=CmJWBaANlsEC |title=The &quot;Racial&quot; Economy of Science |last=Stepan |first=Nancy |publisher=Indiana University press |year=1993 |isbn=978-0-253-20810-1 |editor-last=Sandra Harding |edition=3 |pages=359–76}}&lt;/ref&gt; Biologists, naturalists, anthropologists, and ethnologists of the 19th century were focused on the study of colonised indigenous women, as in the case of [[Georges Cuvier]]'s study of [[Saartjie Baartman|Sarah Baartman]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Fausto-Sterling 2001&quot; /&gt; Such cases embraced a natural superiority and inferiority relationship between the races based on the observations of naturalists' from the mother-countries. European studies along these lines gave rise to the perception that African women's anatomy, and especially genitalia, resembled those of mandrills, baboons, and monkeys, thus differentiating colonised Africans from what were viewed as the features of the evolutionarily superior, and thus rightfully authoritarian, European woman.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fausto-Sterling 2001&quot; /&gt;

In addition to what would now be viewed as pseudo-scientific studies of race, which tended to reinforce a belief in an inherent mother-country racial superiority, a new supposedly &quot;science-based&quot; ideology concerning gender roles also then emerged as an adjunct to the general body of beliefs of inherent superiority of the colonial era.&lt;ref name=Fee /&gt; Female inferiority across all cultures was emerging as an idea supposedly supported by [[craniology]] that led scientists to argue that the typical brain size of the female human was, on the average, slightly smaller than that of the male, thus inferring that therefore female humans must be less developed and less evolutionarily advanced than males.&lt;ref name=Fee /&gt; This finding of relative cranial size difference was later simply attributed to the general typical size difference of the human male body versus that of the typical human female body.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.theguardian.com/science/brain-flapping/2013/dec/04/male-female-brains-real-differences Male and female brains: the REAL differences] 10 February 2016, by Dean Burnett, The Guardian&lt;/ref&gt;

Within the former European colonies, non-Europeans and women sometimes faced invasive studies by the colonial powers in the interest of the then prevailing pro-colonial scientific ideology of the day.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fausto-Sterling 2001&quot; /&gt; Such seemingly flawed studies of race and gender coincided with the era of colonialism and the initial introduction of foreign cultures, appearances, and gender roles into the now gradually widening world-views of the scholars of the mother-countries.

===The Other===
[[File:The East offering its riches to Britannia - Roma Spiridone, 1778 - BL Foster 245.jpg|thumb|&quot;The East offering its riches to Britannia&quot;, painted by [[Spiridione Roma]] for the boardroom of the [[British East India Company]] ]]

&quot;The Other&quot;, or &quot;[[othering]]&quot; is the process of creating a separate entity to persons or groups who are labelled as different or non-normal due to the repetition of characteristics.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |title=The Other, Key Concepts in Human Geography |last=Mountz |first=Alison |pages=2}}&lt;/ref&gt; Othering is the creation of those who discriminate, to distinguish, label, categorise those who do not fit in the societal norm. Several scholars in recent decades developed the notion of the &quot;other&quot; as an epistemological concept in social theory.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt; For example, postcolonial scholars, believed that colonising powers explained an &quot;other&quot; who were there to dominate, civilise, and extract resources through colonisation of land.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

Political geographers explain how colonial/imperial powers (countries, groups of people etc.) &quot;othered&quot; places they wanted to dominate to legalise their exploitation of the land.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt; During and after the rise of colonialism the Western powers perceived the East as the &quot;other&quot;, being different and separate from their societal norm. This viewpoint and separation of culture had divided the Eastern and Western culture creating a dominant/subordinate dynamic, both being the &quot;other&quot; towards themselves.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

===Post-colonialism===
{{Main| Post-colonialism|Postcolonial literature}}
{{Further| Dutch Indies literature}}
[[File:HK Queen Victoria Street The Central Market.jpg|thumb| [[Queen Victoria Street, Hong Kong|Queen Victoria Street]] in the former British colony of [[Hong Kong]]]]
Post-colonialism (or post-colonial theory) can refer to a set of theories in philosophy and literature that grapple with the legacy of colonial rule. In this sense, one can regard post-colonial literature as a branch of [[postmodern literature]] concerned with the political and cultural independence of peoples formerly subjugated in colonial empires. Many practitioners take [[Edward Said|Edward Saïd]]'s book  [[Orientalism (book)|''Orientalism'']] (1978) as the theory's founding work (although French theorists such as [[Aimé Césaire]] (1913–2008) and [[Frantz Fanon]] (1925–1961) made similar claims decades before Saïd).

Saïd analyzed the works of [[Honoré de Balzac|Balzac]], [[Charles Baudelaire|Baudelaire]] and [[Lautréamont]], arguing that they helped to shape a societal fantasy of European racial superiority. Writers of post-colonial fiction interact with the traditional colonial [[discourse]], but modify or subvert it; for instance by retelling a familiar story from the perspective of an oppressed minor character in the story. [[Gayatri Chakravorty Spivak]]'s ''[[Subaltern (post-colonialism)|Can the Subaltern Speak?]]'' (1998) gave its name to [[Subaltern Studies]].

In ''A Critique of Postcolonial Reason'' (1999), Spivak argued that major works of European [[metaphysics]] (such as those of  [[Immanuel Kant|Kant]] and [[Hegel]]) not only tend to exclude the subaltern from their discussions, but actively prevent non-Europeans from occupying positions as fully human [[subject (philosophy)|subjects]]. Hegel's ''[[Phenomenology of Spirit]]'' (1807), famous for its explicit ethnocentrism, considers  [[Western culture|Western civilisation]] as the most accomplished of all, while Kant also had some traces of  [[Racism|racialism]] in his work.

=== Colonistics ===
The field of '''colonistics''' studies colonialism from such viewpoints as those of economics, sociology and psychology.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=gZCAAAAAQBAJ |title=The Sociology of the Colonies [Part 1]: An Introduction to the Study of Race Contact |last=Maunier |first=René |publisher=Routledge |year=1949 |isbn=978-1-136-24522-0 |series=International Library of Sociology |publication-date=2013 |page=137 |translator-last=Lorimer |translator-first=E.-O. |quote=There are thus three elements in Colonistics or colonial study: Colonial ''Economics'', Colonial ''Sociology'' and Colonial ''Psychology''. |access-date=7 December 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Effects of Colonialism on the Colonisers ===
[[File:The Prime Minister, Shri Narendra Modi and the Prime Minister of United Kingdom (UK), Mr. David Cameron interacting with the school children, at Wembley Stadium, in London on November 13, 2015.jpg|thumb|Since 1945, [[Modern immigration to the United Kingdom|immigration]] to the United Kingdom under [[British nationality law]] has been significant, in particular from the former [[British Empire]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=qj8GEjW91oEC |title=Citizenship and Immigration in Postwar Britain |last=Randall Hansen |publisher=Oxford University Press |year=2000 |isbn=9780191583018}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
In his 1955 essay, ''[[Discourse on Colonialism]]'' ([[French language|French]]: ''Discours sur le colonialisme''), French poet [[Aimé Césaire]] evaluates the effects of racist, sexist, and capitalist attitudes and motivations on the civilisations that attempted to colonise other civilisations. In explaining his position, he says &quot;I admit that it is a good thing to place different civilisations in contact with each other that it is an excellent thing to blend different worlds; that whatever its own particular genius may be, a civilisation that withdraws into itself atrophies; that for civilisations, exchange is oxygen.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |title=Discourse on colonialism |first=Aimé |last=Césaire &lt;!-- |date=1972 --&gt; |publisher=Monthly Review Press |year=1955 |location=New York and London |pages=2 |oclc=849914517}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, he contends that colonisation is a harmful and counterproductive means of interacting with and learning from neighbouring civilisations.

To illustrate his point, he explains that colonisation relies on racist and xenophobic frameworks that dehumanise the targets of colonisation and justify their extreme and brutal mistreatment. Every time an immoral act perpetrated by colonisers onto the colonised is justified by racist, sexist, otherwise xenophobic, or capitalist motivations to subjugate a group of people, the colonising civilisation &quot;acquires another dead weight, a universal regression takes place, a gangrene sets in, a centre of infection begins to spread.&quot; &lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt; Césaire argues the result of this process is that &quot;a poison [is] instilled into the veins of Europe and, slowly but surely, the continent proceeds toward ''savagery''.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=Discourse on colonialism. |first=Aimé |last=Césaire &lt;!-- |date=1972 --&gt; |publisher=Monthly Review Press |year=1955 |location=New York and London |pages=3 |oclc=849914517}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Césaire is indicating that the racist and xenophobic justifications for colonisation—motivated by capitalist desires—ultimately result in the moral and cultural degradation of the colonising nation. Thusly, colonisation is damaging to the civilisations that participate as perpetrators in a way that is internally harmful.

==British public opinion about the British Empire==
The 2014 [[YouGov]] survey found that British people are mostly proud of colonialism and the [[British Empire]]:&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2016/aug/24/colonial-nostalgia-horrors-of-empire-britain-olympic |title=Colonial nostalgia is back in fashion, blinding us to the horrors of empire |date=24 August 2016 |work=The Guardian}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|A new YouGov survey finds that most think the British Empire is more something to be proud of (59%) rather than ashamed of (19%). 23% don't know. Young people are least likely to feel pride over shame when it comes to the Empire, though about half (48%) of 18–24 year old's do. In comparison, about two-thirds (65%) of over 60's feel mostly proud. ... A third of British people (34%) also say they would like it if Britain still had an empire. Under half (45%) say they would not like the Empire to exist today. 20% don't know.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://yougov.co.uk/news/2014/07/26/britain-proud-its-empire/ |title=The British Empire is 'something to be proud of' |last=Dahlgreen |first=Will |date=26 July 2014 |publisher=YouGov}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==Colonial migrations==
{{Further|Settler colonialism|Greater Europe}}
[[File:European Ancestry Large.svg|thumb|upright=1.5|&quot;Areas of European settlement&quot;. &lt;small&gt;Censuses, articles quoted in description.&lt;/small&gt;.)]]
Nations and regions outside Europe with significant populations of [[European ethnic groups|European]] ancestry&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/fields/2075.html Ethnic groups by country.] Statistics (where available) from CIA Factbook.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Boerfamily1886.jpg|thumb|right|[[Boer]] family in South Africa, 1886]]
* '''[[Africa]]''' (see [[Europeans in Africa]])
** [[South Africa]] ([[European South African]]): 16.6% of the population&lt;ref&gt;{{CIA World Factbook link|sf|South Africa|access-date=21 June 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Namibia]] ([[European Namibians]]): 6.5% of the population, of which most are Afrikaans-speaking, in addition to a German-speaking minority.&lt;ref&gt;{{CIA World Factbook link|wa|Namibia|access-date=21 June 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Réunion]]: estimated to be approx. 25% of the population&lt;ref name=&quot;advan&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Tarnus |first=Evelyne |last2=Bourdon |first2=Emmanuel |year=2006 |title=Anthropometric evaluations of body composition of undergraduate students at the University of La Réunion |journal=Advances in Physiology Education |volume=30 |issue=4 |pages=248–53 |doi=10.1152/advan.00069.2005 |pmid=17108254|url=https://semanticscholar.org/paper/e1056231b85d3270de7064e7b9d88b4e36de3690 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Zimbabwe]] ([[Europeans in Zimbabwe]])
** [[Algeria]] ([[Pied-noir]])&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/programmes/from_our_own_correspondent/5224244.stm |title=Former settlers return to Algeria |last=Laurenson |first=John |date=July 29, 2006 |work=BBC News}}&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Botswana]]: 3% of the population&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/bc.html#People Botswana: People: Ethnic Groups.] World Factbook of CIA&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Kenya]] ([[Europeans in Kenya]])
** [[Mauritius]] ([[Franco-Mauritian]])
** Morocco ([[European Moroccans]])&lt;ref&gt;De Azevedo, Raimondo Cagiano (1994) ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=N8VHizsqaH0C&amp;pg=PA25 Migration and development co-operation.]''. Council of Europe. p. 25. {{ISBN|92-871-2611-9}}.&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Ivory Coast]] ([[French people]])&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://countrystudies.us/ivory-coast/41.htm Ivory Coast – The Economy]&quot;. [[Library of Congress Country Studies]].&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Senegal]]&lt;ref&gt;[https://2009-2017.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/2862.htm Senegal], About 50,000 Europeans (mostly French) and Lebanese reside in Senegal, mainly in the cities.&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Canary Islands]] ([[Spanish people|Spaniards]]), known as [[Canarian people|Canarians]].
** [[Seychelles]] ([[Franco-Seychellois]])
** [[Somalia]] ([[Italian Somalis]])
** [[Eritrea]] ([[Italian Eritreans]])
** [[Saint Helena]] (UK) including [[Tristan da Cunha]] (UK): predominantly European.
** [[Swaziland]]: 3% of the population&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/wz.html#People Swaziland: People: Ethnic Groups.] World Factbook of CIA&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Tunisia]] ([[European Tunisians]])&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.encyclopedia.com/doc/1G2-2586700129.html Tunisia], Worldmark Encyclopedia of the Nations. Thomson Gale. 2007. ''Encyclopedia.com''.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Prokudin-Gorskii Russians in Central Asia.jpg|thumb|Russian settlers in [[Russian Turkestan|Central Asia]], present-day Kazakhstan, 1911]]
* '''[[Asia]]'''
** [[Siberia]] ([[Russians]], [[Volga Germans|Germans]] and [[Ukrainians in Russia|Ukrainians]])&lt;ref&gt;Fiona Hill, [http://www.theglobalist.com/printStoryId.aspx?StoryId=3727 Russia — Coming In From the Cold?] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110715022142/http://www.theglobalist.com/printStoryId.aspx?StoryId=3727 |date=2011-07-15 }}, [[The Globalist]], 23 February 2004&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.everyculture.com/Russia-Eurasia-China/Siberian-Germans-Orientation.html Siberian Germans]&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Kazakhstan]] ([[Russians in Kazakhstan]], [[Germans of Kazakhstan]]): 30% of the population&lt;ref&gt;&quot;''[https://books.google.com/books?id=YLeAxHLmgR8C&amp;pg=PA15#v=onepage Migrant resettlement in the Russian federation: reconstructing 'homes' and 'homelands']''&quot;. Moya Flynn. (1994). p. 15.
{{ISBN|1-84331-117-8}}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;russians&quot; /&gt;
** [[Uzbekistan]] ([[Russian diaspora|Russians]] and other [[Slavic peoples|Slavs]]): 6% of the population&lt;ref name=&quot;russians&quot;&gt;Robert Greenall, [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/asia-pacific/4420922.stm &quot;Russians left behind in Central Asia&quot;], [[BBC News]], 23 November 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Kyrgyzstan]] (Russians and other Slavs): 14% of the population&lt;ref name=&quot;russians&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/kg.html#People Kyrgyzstan: People: Ethnic Groups.] World Factbook of CIA&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;''[https://books.google.com/books?id=XRXVbGwPgqIC&amp;pg=PA125#v=onepage The Kyrgyz – Children of Manas.]''&quot;. Petr Kokaisl, Pavla Kokaislova (2009). p. 125. {{ISBN|80-254-6365-6}}.&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Turkmenistan]] (Russians and other Slavs): 4% of the population&lt;ref name=&quot;russians&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/tx.html#People Turkmenistan: People: Ethnic Groups.] World Factbook of CIA&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Tajikistan]] (Russians and other Slavs)&lt;ref name=&quot;russians&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://countrystudies.us/tajikistan/23.htm Tajikistan – Ethnic Groups]. Source: ''U.S. Library of Congress''.&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Hong Kong]]&lt;ref&gt;HK Census. &quot;
[http://www.censtatd.gov.hk/hong_kong_statistics/statistical_tables/index.jsp?htmlTableID=139&amp;excelID=&amp;chartID=&amp;tableID=139&amp;ID=&amp;subjectID=1 HK Census]&quot;. ''Statistical Table''. Retrieved on 2007-03-08.&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Philippines]] (Spanish Ancestry): 3% of the population
** [[People's Republic of China]] ([[Russians in China]])
** [[Indian subcontinent]] ([[Anglo-Indians]])
* '''[[Latin America]]''' (see [[White Latin American]]) [[File:Italians Sao Paulo.jpg|thumb|right|Italian immigrants arriving in [[São Paulo]], Brazil, c. 1890]]
**[[Argentina]] ([[Ethnography of Argentina#Ethnic groups|European Immigration to Argentina]]): 97% of the population&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/ar.html#People Argentina: People: Ethnic Groups.] World Factbook of CIA&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Bolivia]]: 15% of the population&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/bl.html#People Bolivia: People: Ethnic Groups.] World Factbook of CIA&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Brazil]] ([[White Brazilian]]): 47% of the population&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/br.html#People Brazil: People: Ethnic Groups.] World Factbook of CIA&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Chile]] ([[White Latin American#Chile|White Chilean]]): 60–70% of the population.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://books.google.com/?id=LcabJ98-t1wC&amp;pg=PA93&amp;dq=chile+60%25+blancos+Esteva-Fabregat |title=Composición Étnica de las Tres Áreas Culturales del Continente Americano al Comienzo del Siglo XXI |last=Fernández, Francisco Lizcano |publisher=UAEM |year=2007 |isbn=978-970-757-052-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.infoamerica.org/primera/lb_2011.pdf Informe Latinobarómetro 2011], [[Latinobarómetro]] (p. 58).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Cruz-Coke |first=R. |last2=Moreno |first2=R. S. |year=1994 |title=Genetic epidemiology of single gene defects in Chile |journal=Journal of Medical Genetics |volume=31 |issue=9 |pages=702–706 |doi=10.1136/jmg.31.9.702 |pmc=1050080 |pmid=7815439}}&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Colombia]] ([[White Colombian]]): 20% of the population&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/co.html#People Colombia: People: Ethnic Groups.] World Factbook of CIA&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Costa Rica]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/cs.html#People |title=Costa Rica; People; Ethnic groups |website=CIA World Factbook |access-date=2007-11-21 |quote=white (including mestizo) 94%}} = 3.9 million whites and mestizos&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Cuba]] ([[White Cuban]]): 65% of the population&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.cubagob.cu/otras_info/censo/tablas_html/ii_3.htm |title=Tabla II.3 Población por color de la piel y grupos de edades, según zona de residencia y sexo |year=2002 |website=Censo de Población y Viviendas |publisher=Oficina Nacional de Estadísticas |language=Spanish |access-date=2008-10-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Dominican Republic]]: 16% of the population&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/dr.html#People Dominican Republic: People: Ethnic groups.] World Factbook of CIA&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Ecuador]]: 7% of the population&lt;ref name=&quot;EC&quot;&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/ec.html#People |title=Ecuador: People; Ethnic groups |work=CIA World Factbook |access-date=2007-11-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[El Salvador]]: 12% of the population&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/es.html#People El Salvador: People: Ethnic Groups.] World Factbook of CIA&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Mexico]] ([[White Mexican]]): 9% or ~17% of the population.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/mx.html#People |title=Mexico: People; Ethnic groups |website=CIA World Factbook |access-date=2010-01-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;MEG&quot;&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/379167/Mexico |title=Mexico: Ethnic Groups |encyclopedia=Encyclopædia Britannica}}&lt;/ref&gt; and 70–80% more as [[Mestizo]]s.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/mx.html#People Mexico: People: Ethnic Groups.] World Factbook of CIA&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/379167/Mexico Mexico – Britannica Online Encyclopedia&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Nicaragua]]: 17% of the population&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/nu.html#People |title=Nicaragua: People; Ethnic groups |work=CIA World Factbook |access-date=2007-11-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Panama]]: 10% of the population&lt;ref name=&quot;PA&quot;&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/pm.html#People |title=Panama; People; Ethnic groups |work=CIA World Factbook |access-date=2007-11-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Puerto Rico]]: approx. 80% of the population&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/pm.html#People Puerto Rico: People: Ethnic Groups] World Factbook of CIA&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Peru]] ([[European Peruvian]]): 15% of the population&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/pe.html#People Peru: People: Ethnic Groups.] World Factbook of CIA&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Paraguay]]: approx. 20% of the population&lt;ref&gt;[http://convergencia.uaemex.mx/rev38/38pdf/LIZCANO.pdf 8 LIZCANO&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130626010236/http://convergencia.uaemex.mx/rev38/38pdf/LIZCANO.pdf |date=June 26, 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Uruguay]]: 88% of the population&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/uy.html#People Uruguay: People: Ethnic Groups.] World Factbook of CIA&lt;/ref&gt;[[File:Menonite Children.JPG|thumb|[[Mennonites in Belize|Mennonites]] of German descent in [[Belize]] ]]
** [[Venezuela]] ([[White Venezuelan]]): 42% of the population&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ine.gov.ve/CENSO2011/documentos/pdf/ResultadosBasicosCenso2011.pdf Resultado Basico del XIV Censo Nacional de Población y Vivienda 2011] (p. 14).&lt;/ref&gt;
* Rest of the '''[[Americas]]'''
**[[Bahamas]]: 12% of the population&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/bf.html#People Bahamas: People: Ethnic Groups.] World Factbook of CIA&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Barbados]] ([[White Barbadian]]): 4% of the population&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/bb.html#People Barbados: People: Ethnic Groups.] World Factbook of CIA&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Bermuda]]: 34% of the population&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/bd.html#People Bermuda: People: Ethnic Groups.] World Factbook of CIA&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Canada]]: 80% of the population&lt;ref&gt;[http://www12.statcan.ca/census-recensement/2006/dp-pd/tbt/Rp-eng.cfm?LANG=E&amp;APATH=3&amp;DETAIL=0&amp;DIM=0&amp;FL=A&amp;FREE=0&amp;GC=0&amp;GID=837928&amp;GK=0&amp;GRP=1&amp;PID=92334&amp;PRID=0&amp;PTYPE=88971,97154&amp;S=0&amp;SHOWALL=0&amp;SUB=0&amp;Temporal=2006&amp;THEME=80&amp;VID=0&amp;VNAMEE=&amp;VNAMEF= Canadian Census 2006]&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Falkland Islands]]: mostly of British descent.
** [[French Guiana]]: 12% of the population&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.umsl.edu/services/govdocs/wofact2006/geos/fg.html#People French Guiana: People: Ethnic Groups.] World Factbook of CIA&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Greenland]]: 12% of the population&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stalvik.com/Engelska/laegreenland.htm Greenland]&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Martinique]]: 5% of the population&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.umsl.edu/services/govdocs/wofact2003/geos/mb.html#People Martinique: People: Ethnic Groups.] World Factbook of CIA&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Saint Barthélemy]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cieux.com/stbarth/stbfact.html Fact Sheet on St. Barthélemy]&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Trinidad and Tobago]]:&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hawaii.edu/satocenter/langnet/definitions/trinidad.html Trinidad French Creole]&lt;/ref&gt; 1% of the population[[File:Portuguese immigrant family in Hawaii during the 19th century.jpg|thumb|[[Portuguese American|Portuguese]] immigrant family in Hawaii during the 19th century]]
** [[United States]] ([[European American]]): 72% of the population, including [[White Hispanic and Latino Americans|Hispanic]] and [[Non-Hispanic Whites]].
* '''[[Oceania]]''' (see [[Europeans in Oceania]])
** [[Australia]]: 89% of the population
** [[New Zealand]] ([[New Zealand European]]): 78% of the population
** [[New Caledonia]] ([[Caldoche]]): 35% of the population
** [[French Polynesia]]: 10% of the population&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/fp.html#People French Polynesia: People: Ethnic Groups.] World Factbook of CIA&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Hawaii]]: 25% of the population&lt;ref&gt;[http://factfinder2.census.gov/faces/tableservices/jsf/pages/productview.xhtml?pid=DEC_10_DP_DPDP1&amp;prodType=table American FactFinder – Results&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140305164937/http://factfinder2.census.gov/faces/tableservices/jsf/pages/productview.xhtml?pid=DEC_10_DP_DPDP1&amp;prodType=table |date=March 5, 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Christmas Island]]: approx. 20% of the population.
** [[Guam]]: 7% of the population&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/gq.html#People Brazil: People: Ethnic Groups.] World Factbook of CIA&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Norfolk Island]]: 9→5% of the population

=== Numbers of European settlers in the colonies (1500–1914) ===
[[File:Emigrants Leave Ireland by Henry Doyle 1868.jpg|thumb|upright| [[Irish diaspora|Irish]] leaving Ireland, many in response to the [[Great Famine (Ireland)|Great Famine]] in the 1840s]]
{{Further|Settler colonialism}}
By 1914, Europeans had migrated to the colonies in the millions. Some intended to remain in the colonies as temporary settlers, mainly as military personnel or on business. Others went to the colonies as immigrants. British people were by far the most numerous population to migrate to the colonies: 2.5 million settled in Canada; 1.5 million in Australia; 750,000 in New Zealand; 450,000 in the Union of South Africa; and 200,000 in India. French citizens also migrated in large numbers, mainly to the colonies in the north African [[Maghreb]] region: 1.3 million settled in Algeria; 200,000 in Morocco; 100,000 in Tunisia; while only 20,000 migrated to French Indochina. Dutch and German colonies saw relatively scarce European migration, since Dutch and German colonial expansion focused on commercial goals rather than settlement. Portugal sent 150,000 settlers to Angola, 80,000 to Mozambique, and 20,000 to Goa. During the Spanish Empire, approximately 550,000 Spanish settlers migrated to [[Latin America]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://archive.org/details/peopleonmoveatla0000unse/page/34 |title=People on the Move: An Atlas of Migration |last=King |first=Russell |publisher=University of California Press |year=2010 |isbn=978-0-520-26151-8 |location=Berkeley, Los Angeles |pages=[https://archive.org/details/peopleonmoveatla0000unse/page/34 34–35]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|History}}
{{Div col|colwidth=20em|rules=yes|gap=2em}}
* [[African independence movements]]
* [[Age of Discovery]]
* [[American imperialism|American Empire]]
* [[Soviet Empire|Soviet Empire]]
* [[Anti-imperialism]]
* [[Chartered companies]]
* [[Chinese imperialism]]
* [[Christianity and colonialism]]
* [[Civilising mission]]
* [[Colonial Empire]]
* [[Colonialism and the Olympic Games]]
* [[Coloniality of power]]
* [[Colonial wars]]
* [[Colonies in antiquity]]
* [[Colonisation]]
* [[Colony]]
* [[Decoloniality]]
* [[Decolonisation]]
* [[Direct colonial rule]]
* [[Empire of Liberty]]
* [[European colonisation of the Americas]]
* [[German eastward expansion]]
* [[Global Empire]]
* [[Historiography of the British Empire]]
* [[Impact of Western European colonialism and colonisation]]
* [[Imperialism]]
* [[International relations of the Great Powers (1814–1919)]]
* [[Muslim conquests]]
* [[Orientalism]]
* [[Pluricontinental]]
* [[Postcolonialism]]
* [[Protectorate]]
* [[Settler colonialism]]
* [[Special Committee on Decolonisation]]
* [[Stranger King (Concept)]]
* [[Western imperialism in Asia]]\
* [[French law on colonialism]]
{{div col end}}

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
* Albertini, Rudolf von. ''European Colonial Rule, 1880–1940: The Impact of the West on India, Southeast Asia, and Africa'' (1982) 581 pp
* Benjamin, Thomas, ed. ''Encyclopedia of Western Colonialism Since 1450'' (2006)
* Cooper, Frederick. ''Colonialism in Question: Theory, Knowledge, History'' (2005)
* Cotterell, Arthur. ''Western Power in Asia: Its Slow Rise and Swift Fall, 1415 – 1999'' (2009) popular history; [https://www.amazon.com/Western-Power-Asia-Slow-Swift/dp/0470824891/  excerpt]
* Getz, Trevor R. and Heather Streets-Salter, eds.: ''Modern Imperialism and Colonialism: A Global Perspective'' (2010)
* LeCour Grandmaison, Olivier: ''Coloniser, Exterminer – Sur la guerre et l'Etat colonial'', Fayard, 2005, {{ISBN|2-213-62316-3}}
* Lindqvist, Sven: ''Exterminate All The Brutes'', 1992, New Press; Reprint edition (June 1997), {{ISBN|978-1-56584-359-2}}
* Ness, Immanuel and Zak Cope, eds. ''The Palgrave Encyclopedia of Imperialism and Anti-Imperialism'' (2 vol 2015), 1456 pp
* Nuzzo, Luigi: [http://nbn-resolving.de/urn:nbn:de:0159-2012041215 ''Colonial Law''], [[European History Online]], Mainz: [[Institute of European History]], 2010, retrieved: December 17, 2012.
* Osterhammel, Jürgen: ''Colonialism: A Theoretical Overview'', Princeton, NJ: M. Wiener, 1997.
* Page, Melvin E. et al. eds. ''Colonialism: An International Social, Cultural, and Political Encyclopedia'' (3 vol 2003)
* Petringa, Maria, ''Brazza, A Life for Africa'' (2006), {{ISBN|978-1-4259-1198-0}}.
* Rönnbäck, K. &amp; Broberg, O. (2019) Capital and Colonialism. The Return on British Investments in Africa 1869–1969 (Palgrave Studies in Economic History)
* Schill, Pierre : ''Réveiller l'archive d'une guerre coloniale. Photographies et écrits de Gaston Chérau, correspondant de guerre lors du conflit italo-turc pour la Libye (1911–1912)'', Créaphis, 480 p., 2018 ({{ISBN|978-2-35428-141-0}}). ''Awaken the archive of a colonial war. Photographs and writings of a French war correspondent during the Italo-Turkish war in Libya (1911–1912)''. With contributions from art historian Caroline Recher, critic Smaranda Olcèse, writer Mathieu Larnaudie and historian Quentin Deluermoz.
* Stuchtey, Benedikt: [http://nbn-resolving.de/urn:nbn:de:0159-20101025319 ''Colonialism and Imperialism, 1450–1950''], [[European History Online]], Mainz: [[Institute of European History]], 2011, retrieved: July 13, 2011.
* Townsend, Mary Evelyn. ''European colonial expansion since 1871'' (1941).
* U.S. Tariff Commission. ''Colonial tariff policies'' (1922), worldwide; 922pp [https://archive.org/details/colonialtariffpo00unit survey online]
* {{Cite journal | doi=10.1353/imp.2002.0070 | title=The Issue of Russian Colonialism in Ukrainian Thought. Dependency Identity and Development| journal=Ab Imperio| volume=2002| pages=323–367| year=2002| last1=Velychenko| first1=Stephen|issue=1}} [http://abimperio.net/cgi-bin/aishow.pl?state=showa&amp;idart=222&amp;idlang=1&amp;Code=]
* Wendt, Reinhard: [http://nbn-resolving.de/urn:nbn:de:0159-20100921437 ''European Overseas Rule'',] [[European History Online]], Mainz: [[Institute of European History]], 2011, retrieved: June 13, 2012.

===Primary sources===
* [[Joseph Conrad|Conrad, Joseph]], ''[[Heart of Darkness]]'', 1899
* [[Frantz Fanon|Fanon, Frantz]], ''[[The Wretched of the Earth]]'', Preface by [[Jean-Paul Sartre]]. Translated by Constance Farrington. London: Penguin Book, 2001
* [[Rudyard Kipling|Kipling, Rudyard]], ''[[The White Man's Burden]]'', 1899
* [[Bartolomé de las Casas|Las Casas, Bartolomé de]], ''[[A Short Account of the Destruction of the Indies]]'' (1542, published in 1552).

==External links==
{{Wikiquote-inline|colonialism}}
* {{cite SEP |url-id=colonialism |title=Colonialism |last=Kohn |first=Margaret}}

{{Indigenous rights footer}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Articles with inconsistent citation formats]]
[[Category:Cultural geography]]
[[Category:International relations theory]]
[[Category:Colonialism| ]]
[[Category:Articles containing video clips]]</text>
      <sha1>ju9ch5917wsledlphdom6pqos1p3j1x</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
