  <page>
    <title>Edmund Stoiber</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9480</id>
    <revision>
      <id>932828680</id>
      <parentid>932740504</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-12-28T12:35:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>46.80.95.56</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox officeholder
| name          = Edmund Stoiber
| image         = DrEdmundStoiber.jpg
| imagesize     =
| caption       = Stoiber in 2010
| office        = [[List of Ministers-President of Bavaria|Minister President of Bavaria]]
| term_start    = 28 May 1993
| term_end      = 30 September 2007
| predecessor   = [[Max Streibl]]
| successor     = [[Günther Beckstein]]
| office2       = Leader of the [[Christian Social Union in Bavaria|Christian Social Union]]
| term_start2   = 9 October 1999
| term_end2     = 18 September 2007
| predecessor2  = [[Theo Waigel]]
| successor2    = [[Erwin Huber]]
| birth_date    = {{birth date and age|1941|9|28|df=y}}
| birth_place   = [[Oberaudorf]], [[Bavaria]], [[Nazi Germany]]
| nationality   = [[Germany|German]]
| death_date    = 
| death_place   = 
| party         = [[Christian Social Union in Bavaria|CSU]]
| relations     = 
| residence     = 
| alma_mater    = 
| occupation    = 
| spouse        = [[Karin Stoiber]]
| children      = Constanze &lt;br /&gt; Veronica &lt;br /&gt; Dominic
| religion      = [[Roman Catholicism]]
| signature     = 
| website       = 
}}
'''Edmund Rüdiger Stoiber''' (born 28 September 1941) is a [[Germany|German]] [[politics|politician]] who served as the 16th [[Minister President]] of the [[States of Germany|state]] of [[Bavaria]] between 1993 and 2007 and chairman of the [[Christian Social Union in Bavaria|Christian Social Union (CSU)]] between 1999 and 2007. In 2002 he ran for the office of [[Chancellor of Germany]] in the [[2002 German federal election|federal election]], but in one of the narrowest elections in German history lost against [[Gerhard Schröder]]. On 18 January 2007, he announced his decision to step down from the posts of minister-president and party chairman by 30 September, after having been under fire in his own party for weeks.&lt;ref name=&quot;resignation&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url= https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/01/18/AR2007011800636.html |title= Bavarian premier Stoiber says to step down early |author= Jens Hack |work= Reuters |date= January 18, 2007 |accessdate= 2007-09-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early life==
Edmund Stoiber was born in [[Oberaudorf]] in the district of [[Rosenheim (district)|Rosenheim]], [[Bavaria]].  Prior to entering politics in 1974 and serving in the Bavarian parliament, he was a [[lawyer]] and worked at the [[University of Regensburg]].

==Education and profession==
Stoiber attended the Ignaz-Günther-Gymnasium in [[Rosenheim]], where he received his [[Abitur]] (high school diploma) in 1961, although he had to repeat one year for failing in Latin.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wissen.de&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.wissen.de/wde/generator/wissen/ressorts/geschichte/zeitgeschehen/index,page=1309532.html |title=Edmund Stoiber Ein mittelmäßiger Schüler |last=Mayer |first=Christian |date=2000–2008 |publisher=wissen.de GmbH |pages=1 |language=German |accessdate=2008-08-15 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090821004004/http://www.wissen.de/wde/generator/wissen/ressorts/geschichte/zeitgeschehen/index%2Cpage%3D1309532.html |archivedate=2009-08-21 }}&lt;/ref&gt; His military service was with the [[1st Mountain Division (Bundeswehr)|1st Gebirgsdivision]] (mountain infantry division) in [[Mittenwald]] and [[Bad Reichenhall]] and was cut-short due to a knee injury. Then Stoiber studied at [[Ludwig Maximilians University of Munich]] [[political science]] and then, from fall 1962, [[law]]. In 1967, he passed the state law exam and then worked at the [[University of Regensburg]] in [[criminal law]] and [[Eastern Europe]]an law. He was awarded a [[doctorate]] of jurisprudence, and then in 1971 passed the second state examination with distinction.

In 1971, Stoiber joined the Bavarian State Ministry of Development and Environment.&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimes.com&quot;&gt;{{cite news |first=Steven |last=Erlanger |date=January 12, 2002 |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2002/01/12/world/german-right-backs-bavarian-to-run-against-schroder.html |title=German Right Backs Bavarian to Run Against Schröder |work=[[The New York Times]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Political career==
[[File:Bundesarchiv B 145 Bild-F061782-0032, Hamburg, CDU-Bundesparteitag, Blüm, Stoiber.jpg|thumb|left|[[Norbert Blüm]] and Edmund Stoiber in 1981]]

In 1978 Stoiber was elected secretary general of the CSU, a post he held until 1982/83. In this capacity, he served as campaign manager of [[Franz-Josef Strauss]], the first Bavarian leader to run for the chancellorship, in the [[1980 West German federal election|1980 national elections]].&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimes.com&quot;/&gt; From 1982 to 1986 he served as deputy to the Bavarian secretary of the state and then, in the position of State Minister, led the [[Bayerische Staatskanzlei|State Chancellery]] from 1982 to 1988. From 1988 to 1993 he served as [[Bavarian Ministry of the Interior|State Minister of the Interior]].

===Minister-President of Bavaria, 1993–2007===
In May 1993, the [[Landtag of Bavaria]], the state's parliament, elected Stoiber as Minister-President succeeding [[Max Streibl]]. He came to power amid a political crisis involving a sex scandal, surrounding a contender for the state premiership.&lt;ref&gt;Hugh Williamson (January 17, 2007), [http://www.ft.com/cms/s/0/8e4da0de-a5d1-11db-a4e0-0000779e2340.html Stoiber crisis threatens Merkel's coalition] ''[[Financial Times]]''.&lt;/ref&gt; Upon taking office, he nominated Strauss' daughter [[Monika Hohlmeier]] as State Minister for Education and Cultural Affairs.

In his capacity as Minister-President, Stoiber served as [[President of the German Bundesrat|President]] of the [[Bundesrat of Germany|Bundesrat]] in 1995/96. In 1998, he also succeeded [[Theo Waigel]] as chairman of the CSU.

During Stoiber's 14 years leading Bavaria, the state solidified its position as one of Germany's richest.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.spiegel.de/international/leadership-crisis-in-bavaria-edmund-stoiber-to-step-down-a-460704.html Leadership Crisis in Bavaria: Edmund Stoiber To Step Down] ''[[Spiegel Online]]'', January 18, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Already by 1998, under his leadership, the state had privatized more than $3 billion worth of state-owned businesses and used that money to invest in new infrastructure and provide venture capital for new companies.&lt;ref&gt;Edmund L. Andrews (September 14, 1998), [https://www.nytimes.com/1998/09/14/world/conservatives-win-decisive-victory-in-bavarian-election.html Conservatives Win Decisive Victory in Bavarian Election] ''[[The New York Times]]''.&lt;/ref&gt; He was widely regarded a central figure in building one of Europe's most powerful regional economies, attracting thousands of hi-tech, engineering and media companies and reducing unemployment to half the national average.&lt;ref&gt;Hugh Williamson (October 1, 2007), [http://www.ft.com/cms/s/0/b19f5756-6fd1-11dc-b66c-0000779fd2ac.html Stoiber steps aside and ends era in Germany] ''[[Financial Times]]''.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Candidate for Chancellor, 2002===
In 2002, Stoiber politically outmaneuvered [[Christian Democratic Union (Germany)|CDU]] chairwoman, [[Angela Merkel]], and was declared the CDU/CSU's candidate for the office of chancellor by practically the entire leadership of the CSU's sister party CDU, challenging [[Gerhard Schröder]]. At that time, Merkel had generally been seen as a transitional chair and was strongly opposed by the CDU's male leaders, often called the party's &quot;crown princes&quot;.

In the run up to the [[2002 German federal election|2002 national elections]], the CSU/CDU held a huge lead in the opinion polls and Stoiber famously remarked that &quot;...{{nbsp}}this election is like a [[association football|football]] match where it's the second half and my team is ahead by 2–0.&quot; However, on election day things had changed. The [[Social Democratic Party of Germany|SPD]] had mounted a huge comeback, and the CDU/CSU was narrowly defeated (though both the SPD and CDU/CSU had 38.5% of the vote, the SPD was ahead by a small 6,000 vote margin, winning 251 seats to the CDU/CSU's 248). The election was one of modern Germany's closest votes.&lt;ref&gt;Jess Smee (January 17, 2007), [https://www.theguardian.com/world/2007/jan/19/germany.mainsection Stoiber quits after snooping row] ''[[The Guardian]]''.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Gerhard Schröder]] was re-elected as chancellor by the parliament in a coalition with the [[Alliance '90/The Greens|Greens]], who had increased their vote share marginally. Many commentators faulted Stoiber's reaction to the [[2002 European floods|floods]] in eastern Germany, in the run-up to the election, as a contributory factor in his party's poor electoral result and defeat. In addition, Schröder distinguished himself from his opponent by taking an active stance against the upcoming United States-led [[2003 invasion of Iraq|Iraq War]]. His extensive campaigning on this stance was widely seen as swinging the election to the SPD in the weeks running up to the election.

===Later political career===
Stoiber subsequently led the CSU to an absolute majority in the [[2003 Bavarian state election]]s, for the third time in a row, winning this time 60.7% of the votes and a two-thirds majority in the Landtag. This was the widest margin ever achieved by a German party in any state.&lt;ref&gt;Mark Landler (September 23, 2002), [https://www.nytimes.com/2002/09/23/world/again-bavaria-s-favorite-is-germany-s-runner-up.html Again, Bavaria's Favorite Is Germany's Runner-Up] ''[[The New York Times]]''.&lt;/ref&gt;

Between 2003 and 2004, Stoiber served as co-chair (alongside [[Franz Müntefering]]) of the [[Federalism commission (Germany)|First Commission on the modernization of the federal state]] (''Föderalismuskommission I''), which had been established to reform the division of powers between federal and state authorities in Germany. In February 2004, he became a candidate of [[Jacques Chirac]] and [[Gerhard Schröder]] for the presidency of the [[European Commission]] but he decided not to run for this office.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ft.com/cms/s/0/c8549db8-ba7a-11d8-9a2f-00000e2511c8.html Overture over for staunch Stoiber] ''[[Financial Times]]'', June 10, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;

Stoiber had ambitions to run again for the chancellorship, but Merkel secured the nomination, and in November 2005 she won the general election. He was slated to join Merkel's first grand coalition cabinet as [[Federal Minister for Economics and Labour (Germany)|Economics minister]]. However, on 1 November 2005, he announced his decision to stay in Bavaria, due to personnel changes on the SPD side of the coalition ([[Franz Müntefering]] resigned as SPD chairman) and an unsatisfactory apportionment of competences between himself and designated Science minister [[Annette Schavan]]. Stoiber also resigned his seat in the 16th Bundestag, being a member from 18 October to 8 November.

Subsequently, criticism grew in the CSU, where other politicians had to scale back their ambitions after Stoiber's decision to stay in Bavaria. On 18 January 2007, he announced his decision to stand down from the posts of minister-president and party chairman by 30 September. [[Günther Beckstein]], then Bavarian state minister of the interior, succeeded him as minister-president and [[Erwin Huber]] as party chairman, defeating [[Horst Seehofer]] at a convention at 18 September 2007 with 58,1% of the votes. Both Beckstein and Huber resigned after the [[2008 Bavarian state election|2008 state elections]], in which the CSU vote dropped to 43,4% and the party had to form a coalition with another party for the first time since 1966.

==Life after politics==
Stoiber was first appointed in 2007 as a special adviser to then-[[European Commission President]] [[José Manuel Barroso]] to chair the &quot;High level group on administrative burdens,&quot; made up of national experts, NGOs, business and industry organizations. Quickly nicknamed the &quot;Stoiber Group,&quot; it produced a report in July 2014 with several proposals on streamlining the regulatory process.&lt;ref name=&quot;politico.eu&quot;&gt;Quentin Ariès (September 15, 2015), [http://www.politico.eu/article/eu-watchdog-to-probe-appointment-of-juncker-adviser-edmund-stoiber-timmermans-better-regulation/ EU watchdog to probe appointment of Juncker adviser] ''[[Politico Europe]]''.&lt;/ref&gt; Stoiber was re-appointed in December 2014 by [[Jean-Claude Juncker]] to the same role, from which he resigned after one year in late 2015.

Since his retirement from German politics in 2007, Stoiber has worked as a lawyer and held paid and unpaid positions, including:&lt;ref name=&quot;politico.eu&quot;/&gt;

* [[Bundesliga Foundation]], Member of the Board of Trustees
* [[Commerzbank]], Member of the Central Advisory Board
* [[Deloitte|Deloitte Germany]], Chairman of the Advisory Board&lt;ref&gt;[http://www2.deloitte.com/de/de/pages/about-deloitte/articles/deloitte-beirat.html Advisory Board] [[Deloitte]].&lt;/ref&gt; (since 2009)
* [[Donner &amp; Reuschel]], Member of the Advisory Board&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.donner-reuschel.de/unternehmen/ Advisory Board] [[Donner &amp; Reuschel]].&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[FC Bayern Munich]], Member of the Supervisory Board
* German-Russian Raw Materials Forum, Member of the Presidium
* [[Hanns Seidel Foundation]], Member&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.hss.de/fileadmin/user_upload/190701_HSS-Vorstand_und_Mitglieder.pdf Board and Members, 2019] [[Hanns Seidel Foundation]].&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Lindau Nobel Laureate Meetings]], Member of the Honorary Senate&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.lindau-nobel.org/about/ Honorary Senate] [[Lindau Nobel Laureate Meetings]].&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Ludwig Maximilians University of Munich]], Member of the Board of Trustees
* [[Munich Security Conference]], Member of the Advisory Council
* Nürnberger Beteiligungs-Aktiengesellschaft, Member of the Supervisory Board
* [[ProSiebenSat.1 Media]], Member of the Advisory Board (since 2011)

Stoiber was a CSU delegate to the [[Federal Convention (Germany)|Federal Convention]] for the purpose of electing the [[President of Germany]] in 2017.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.bayern.landtag.de/fileadmin/Internet_Dokumente/Sonstiges_P/20161122_Mitglieder_Bundesversammlung.pdf Mitglieder bzw. Ersatzmitglieder der 16. Bundesversammlung] [[Landtag of Bavaria]], press release of 22 November 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Political positions==

===Foreign policy===
[[File:Vladimir Putin with Edmund Stoiber-1.jpg|thumb|Stoiber and [[Vladimir Putin]]]]
In his capacity as Minister-President, Stoiber made 58 foreign trips, including to [[China]] (1995, 2003), [[Israel]] (2001), [[Egypt]] (2001), [[India]] (2004, 2007) and [[South Korea]] (2007).&lt;ref&gt;Wolfgang Wittl (February 3, 2016), [http://www.sueddeutsche.de/bayern/csu-seehofer-fehlt-die-lust-am-reisen-1.2847192 Seehofer fehlt die Lust am Reisen] ''[[Süddeutsche Zeitung]]''.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2002, Stoiber publicly expressed support for the United States in their policy toward [[Iraq]]. During his election campaign, he made clear his opposition to war, and his support for the introduction of weapons inspectors to Iraq without preconditions as a way of avoiding war, and he criticized Schröder for harming the German-American alliance by not calling [[President of the United States|President]] [[George W. Bush]] and discussing the issue privately.&lt;ref&gt;Steven Erlanger (September 9, 2002), [https://www.nytimes.com/2002/09/09/international/europe/09BERL.html Stance on Bush Policy Could Swing Election in Germany] ''[[The New York Times]]''.&lt;/ref&gt; He also attacked German Foreign Minister [[Joschka Fischer]] for his criticism of the U.S. position.&lt;ref&gt;William Boston (February 26, 2002), [https://www.wsj.com/articles/SB1014666184388287560 As Stoiber Looks Past Economy, His Campaign Hits Shaky Ground] ''[[Wall Street Journal]]''.&lt;/ref&gt;

Stoiber is known for backing [[Vladimir Putin]] and there have been comparisons to [[Gerhard Schröder]]. One author called Stoiber a &quot;Moscow's Trojan Horse&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jamestown.org/single/?no_cache=1&amp;tx_ttnews%5Btt_news%5D=32853 From Schröder to Stoiber?] Eurasia Daily Monitor Volume: 4 Issue: 132&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.axisglobe.com/article.asp?article=354 |title=Edmund Stoiber – Moscow's Trojan Horse in the Opposition Camp |access-date=2009-10-02 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070702043446/http://www.axisglobe.com/article.asp?article=354 |archive-date=2007-07-02 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thetrumpet.com/index.php?q=6122.4530.0.0 The German Election Campaign Has Commenced] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100114072046/http://thetrumpet.com/index.php?q=6122.4530.0.0 |date=2010-01-14 }}. The Trumpet. 2009&lt;/ref&gt; Putin is known to have given Stoiber &quot;extreme forms of flattery&quot; and privileges such as a private dinner at Putin's residence outside Moscow.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thetrumpet.com/index.php?q=5451.3777.0.0 Russia, Germany and Europe’s Future] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100117214428/http://thetrumpet.com/index.php?q=5451.3777.0.0 |date=2010-01-17 }}. Ron Fraser. The Trumpet. 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

===European integration===
Stoiber has been said to be skeptical of Germany's decision to adopt the [[euro]]. In 1997, he joined the ministers-president of two other German states, [[Kurt Biedenkopf]] and [[Gerhard Schröder]], in making the case for a five-year delay in Europe's currency union.&lt;ref&gt;John Schmid (July 28, 1997), [https://www.nytimes.com/1997/07/28/business/worldbusiness/IHT-another-german-premier-seeks-delay-on-the-euro.html Another German Premier Seeks Delay on the Euro] ''[[International Herald Tribune]]''.&lt;/ref&gt; When the [[European Commission]] recommended that [[Greece]] be allowed to join the [[eurozone]] in 1998, he demanded that the country be barred from adopting the common currency for several years instead.&lt;ref&gt;Edmund L. Andrews (May 8, 2000), [https://www.nytimes.com/2000/05/08/world/falling-euro-a-unity-currency-instead-bolsters-dollar-and-pound.html Falling Euro, a Unity Currency, Instead Bolsters Dollar and Pound] ''[[The New York Times]]''.&lt;/ref&gt; He is a staunch opponent of [[Turkey]]'s integration into the [[European Union]], claiming that its non-Christian culture would dilute the Union.
 
At the same time, Stoiber has repeatedly insisted he is a &quot;good European&quot; who is keen, for instance, on forging an EU-wide foreign policy, replete with a single European army.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.economist.com/node/28574 Edmund Stoiber, torch-bearer for Germany’s right] ''[[The Economist]]'', August 3, 2000.&lt;/ref&gt; Earlier, in 1993, he had told German newspapers: &quot;I want a simple confederation. That means the nation-states maintain their dominant role, at least as far as internal matters are concerned.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Craig R. Whitney (November 12, 1993), [https://www.nytimes.com/1993/11/12/world/kohl-defends-european-unity-to-doubters.html Kohl Defends European Unity to Doubters] ''[[The New York Times]]''.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Economic policy===
While the conservative wing of the German political spectrum, primarily formed of the [[Christian Democratic Union (Germany)|CDU]] and [[Christian Social Union in Bavaria|CSU]], enjoys considerable support, this support tends to be less extended to Stoiber. He enjoys considerably more support in his home state of Bavaria than in the rest of Germany, where CDU chairwoman [[Angela Merkel]] is more popular. This has its reasons: Merkel supports a kind of [[fiscal conservatism]], but a more [[Liberalism|liberal]] [[social policy]]. Stoiber, on the other hand, favors a more conservative approach to both fiscal and social matters, and while this ensures him the religious vote, strongest in Bavaria, it has weakened his support at the national level.

In 2005, Stoiber successfully lobbied [[Novartis]], the Swiss pharmaceuticals group, to move the headquarters of its [[Sandoz]] subsidiary to Munich, making it one of Europe's highest-profile corporate relocations that year as well as a significant boost to Stoiber's attempts to build up Bavaria as a pharmaceuticals and biotechnology center.&lt;ref&gt;Haig Simonian and Ralph Atkins (April 26, 2005), [http://www.ft.com/intl/cms/s/0/54458816-b5f0-11d9-be59-00000e2511c8.html Sandoz to move HQ to Munich] ''[[Financial Times]]''.&lt;/ref&gt;

During his time as Minister-President of Bavaria, Stoiber pushed for the construction of a roughly 40-kilometer high-speed [[Maglev|magnetic-levitation]] link from Munich's main station to its airport, to be built by [[Transrapid|Transrapid International]], a consortium including [[ThyssenKrupp]] and Munich-based [[Siemens]]. After he left office, the German federal government abandoned the plans in 2008 because of spiraling costs of as much as €3.4 billion.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.nytimes.com/2008/03/27/business/worldbusiness/27iht-27maglev.11473863.html Germany cancels magnetic-levitation train line] ''[[International Herald Tribune]]'', March 27, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Domestic policy===
Stoiber, as a minister in the state of Bavaria, was widely known for advocating a reduction in the number of [[asylum seekers]] Germany accepts, something that prompted critics to label him [[xenophobic]], anti-Turkish and anti-Islam. In the late 1990s he criticized the incoming Chancellor Schröder for saying that he would work hard in the interest of Germans ''and'' people living in Germany. Stoiber's remarks drew heavy criticism in the press.

When Germany's [[Federal Constitutional Court]] decided in 1995 that a Bavarian law requiring a [[crucifix]] to be hung in each of the state's 40,000 classrooms was unconstitutional, Stoiber said he would not order the removal of crucifixes &quot;for the time being,&quot; and asserted that he was under no obligation to remove them in schools where parents unanimously opposed such action.&lt;ref&gt;Stephen Kinzer (August 23, 1995), [https://www.nytimes.com/1995/08/23/world/crucifix-ruling-angers-bavarians.html Crucifix Ruling Angers Bavarians] ''[[The New York Times]]''.&lt;/ref&gt;

During his 2002 election campaign, Stoiber indicated he would not ban same-sex marriages – sanctioned by the Schröder government – a policy he had vehemently objected to when it was introduced.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/2045754.stm Edmund Stoiber: Bringing Bavaria to Berlin] ''[[BBC News]]'', June 17, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Media policy===
Stoiber has been a staunch advocate of changes in German law that would give more power to owners of private TV channels. In 1995, he publicly called for the abolition of Germany's public television service [[ARD (broadcaster)|ARD]] and a streamlining of its regional services, adding that he and Minister-President [[Kurt Biedenkopf]] of [[Saxony]] would break the contract ARD has with regional governments if reforms were not undertaken.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Kallenbach (April 3, 1995), [https://www.nytimes.com/1995/04/03/news/03iht-hh_0.html Public and Private Television at the Crossroads] ''[[International Herald Tribune]]''.&lt;/ref&gt; However, when [[European Commissioner for Competition]] [[Karel van Miert]] unveiled ideas for reforming the rules governing the financing of public service broadcasters in 1998, Stoiber led the way in rejecting moves to reform established practice.&lt;ref&gt;Peter Chapman (October 14, 1998), [http://www.politico.eu/article/poor-reception-for-tv-funding-policy/ Poor reception for TV funding policy] ''[[European Voice]]''.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Controversies==

===Comments on East Germany===
During the run-up to the German [[2005 German federal election|general election]] in 2005, which was held ahead of schedule, Stoiber created controversy through a campaign speech held in the beginning of August 2005 in the federal state of [[Baden-Württemberg]]. He  said, &quot;I do not accept that the East [of Germany] will again decide who will be Germany's chancellor. It cannot be allowed that the frustrated determine Germany's fate.&quot; People in the new federal states of Germany (the former [[German Democratic Republic]]) were offended by Stoiber's remarks. While the CSU attempted to portray them as &quot;misinterpreted&quot;, Stoiber created further controversy when he claimed that &quot;if it was like Bavaria everywhere, there wouldn't be any problems. Unfortunately, not everyone in Germany is as intelligent as in Bavaria.&quot; The tone of the comments was exacerbated by a perception by some within Germany of the state of Bavaria as &quot;arrogant&quot;.

Many, including members of the CDU, attribute Stoiber's comments and behavior as a contributing factor to the CDU's losses in the 2005 general election. He was accused by many in the CDU/CSU of offering &quot;half-hearted&quot; support to Angela Merkel, with some even accusing him of being reluctant to support a female candidate from the East. (This also contrasted unfavorably with Merkel's robust support for his candidacy in the [[2002 German federal election|2002 election]].) He has insinuated that votes were lost because of the choice of a female candidate. He came under heavy fire for these comments from press and politicians alike, especially since he himself lost almost 10% of the Bavarian vote – a dubious feat in itself as Bavarians tend to consistently vote conservatively. Nonetheless, a poll has suggested over 9% may have voted differently if the conservative candidate was a man from the West, although this does not clearly show if such a candidate would have gained or lost votes for the conservatives.

===BayernLB activities===
When the [[Croatian National Bank]] turned down [[BayernLB]]'s original bid to take over the local arm of [[Hypo Alpe-Adria-Bank International]], this drew strong criticism from Stoiber, who said the decision was &quot;unacceptable&quot; and a &quot;severe strain&quot; for Bavaria's relations with [[Croatia]]. Croatia was seeking to join the [[European Union]] at the time. The central bank's board later reviewed and accepted BayernLB's offer of 1.6 billion euros.&lt;ref&gt;Zoran Radosavljevic (September 12, 2007), [https://www.reuters.com/article/idUSL1281484820070912 BLB gets nod from Croatia to take over Hypo unit] ''[[Reuters]]''.&lt;/ref&gt; The investment in Hypo Group Alpe Adria was part of a series of ill-fated investments, which later forced BayernLB to take a 10 billion-euro bailout in the financial crisis.

===European Commission job===
In September 2015, [[Emily O'Reilly]], the [[European Ombudsman]], received a complaint from two NGOs, [[Corporate Europe Observatory]] and [[Friends of the Earth]], according to which Stoiber's appointment as special adviser on the Commission's better regulation agenda broke internal rules on appointments.&lt;ref&gt;Quentin Ariès (March 30, 2016), [http://www.politico.eu/article/commissioners-request-outside-help-from-big-hitters/ Commissioners request outside help from big hitters] ''[[Politico Europe]]''.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Personal life==
Stoiber is [[Roman Catholic]]. He is married to [[Karin Stoiber]]. They have three children: Constanze (1971), Veronica (1977), Dominic (1980) and five grandchildren: Johannes (1999), Benedikt (2001), Theresa Marie (2005), Ferdinand (2009) and another grandson (2011).

Stoiber is a keen [[association football|football]] fan and he serves as Co-Chairman on the Advisory Board of [[FC Bayern Munich]]. Before the 2002 election FC Bayern General Manager [[Uli Hoeneß]] expressed his support for Stoiber and the [[Christian Social Union in Bavaria|CSU]]. Football legend, former FC Bayern President and [[German Football Association|DFB]] Vice-President, [[Franz Beckenbauer]], on the other hand, showed his support for Stoiber by letting him join the [[German national football team]] on their flight home from [[Japan]] after the [[2002 FIFA World Cup]].

In his youth, he played for local football side [[BCF Wolfratshausen]].&lt;ref name=logo&gt;[http://www.bcf-wolfratshausen.de/Fussball/Entstehungsgeschichte.html Das Logo zeigt den Ursprung] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090102204305/http://www.bcf-wolfratshausen.de/Fussball/Entstehungsgeschichte.html |date=2009-01-02 }} {{in lang|de}} BCF website – Club history, accessed: 27 June 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

==Honours and awards==
[[File:Edmund Stoiber.jpg|thumb|Edmund Stoiber during the conferment Order against the deadly seriousness, March 2000]]
* 1984: [[Bavarian Order of Merit]]
* 1996: {{Interlanguage link multi|Karl-Valentin-Orden|de}}
* 1996: [[Grand Order of King Dmitar Zvonimir]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://narodne-novine.nn.hr/clanci/sluzbeni/1996_09_79_1382.html|title=Odluka o odlikovanju dr. Edmunda Stoibera Veleredom Dmitra Zvonimira s lentom i Danicom|website=narodne-novine.nn.hr|access-date=2019-08-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1999: [[Grand Cross]] of the [[Order of the Star of Romania]]
* 2000: {{Interlanguage link multi|Order against the deadly seriousness|de|3=Orden wider den tierischen Ernst}}
* 2002: Commander of the [[Legion of Honour]]
* 2003: Officer of the [[Ordre national du Québec]]
* 2004: Grand Cross of the [[Order of Merit of the Federal Republic of Germany]]
* 2005: [[Decoration of Honour for Services to the Republic of Austria|''Grand Decoration of Honour in Gold with Sash'' for Services to the Republic of Austria]] &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.parlament.gv.at/PAKT/VHG/XXIV/AB/AB_10542/imfname_251156.pdf | title = Reply to a parliamentary question about the Decoration of Honour | language = German | page=1366  |trans-title=| format = pdf | accessdate = November 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 2006: Grand Cross of [[Order of Merit of the Italian Republic]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.quirinale.it/onorificenze/insigniti/173900|title=Le onorificenze della Repubblica Italiana|website=www.quirinale.it|access-date=2019-08-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 2007: Large Gold Medal of the province of Upper Austria
* 2007: Honorary degree awarded by the [[Sogang University]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.abendblatt.de/politik/ausland/article458330/Edmund-Stoiber-ist-jetzt-Ehrendoktor-in-Suedkorea.html&lt;/ref&gt;
* 2008: [[Steiger Award]]
* 2009: [[Order of Merit of Baden-Württemberg]]

==Literature==
* Michael Stiller: ''Edmund Stoiber: der Kandidat.'' Econ, München 2002, {{ISBN|3-430-18786-9}}.
* Jürgen Roth, Peter Köhler: ''Edmund G. Stoiber: Weltstaatsmann und Freund des Volkes.'' Eichborn, Frankfurt 2002, {{ISBN|3-8218-3584-2}}. (satirische &quot;Biografie&quot;)
* Jule Philippi: Wer für alles offen ist, ist nicht ganz dicht. Weisheiten des Edmund Stoiber. Rowohlt, Reinbek bei Hamburg 2007, {{ISBN|978-3-499-62248-9}} . (Analyse Stoibers will- und unwillkürlicher Sprachproduktion)

==See also==
*[[List of Minister-Presidents of Bavaria]]

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

==External links==
{{Commons and category}}
{{Wikiquote|de:Edmund Stoiber}}
*{{Official website|www.stoiber.de}} {{in lang|de}}
*{{C-SPAN|Edmund Stoiber}}
*[http://www.gavagai.de/zitat/politik/HHC53.htm Stoiber quotes] (critic) {{in lang|de}}
*[http://www.dw-world.de/dw/article/0,1564,1676848,00.html Stoiber and the East] – Deutsche Welle
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20070927175703/http://www.parlazzo.com/index.php?id=580 Parlazzo Media Awards – Nomination 2007 – 10 Minutes – 10 Minuten] {{in lang|de}}

{{s-start}}
{{s-off}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Max Streibl]]}} 
{{s-ttl|title=[[List of Ministers-President of Bavaria|Minister president]] of [[Bavaria]]|years=1993–2007}} 
{{s-aft|after=[[Günther Beckstein]]}}
{{s-end}}

{{FC Bayern Munich board}}
{{Presidents of the German Federal Council}}
{{Ministers-President of Bavaria}}
{{BavariaIntMin}}
{{BavarianStaatskanzlei}}
{{CSUHeads}}
{{CSUGenSecs}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Stoiber, Edmund}}
[[Category:1941 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:People from Rosenheim (district)]]
[[Category:German Roman Catholics]]
[[Category:Christian Social Union in Bavaria politicians]]
[[Category:Ministers-President of Bavaria]]
[[Category:Ministers of the Bavaria State Government]]
[[Category:Members of the Landtag of Bavaria]]
[[Category:FC Bayern Munich board members]]
[[Category:Cartellverband members]]
[[Category:Ludwig Maximilian University of Munich alumni]]
[[Category:Leaders of political parties in Germany]]
&lt;!-- Honours ; Germany --&gt;
[[Category:Grand Crosses 1st class of the Order of Merit of the Federal Republic of Germany]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Bavarian Order of Merit]]
&lt;!-- Honours --&gt;
[[Category:Officers of the National Order of Quebec]]
[[Category:Grand Crosses of the Order of the Star of Romania]]
[[Category:Commandeurs of the Légion d'honneur]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Grand Decoration with Sash for Services to the Republic of Austria]]
[[Category:Knights Grand Cross of the Order of Merit of the Italian Republic]]
[[Category:21st-century German politicians]]</text>
      <sha1>2hgb2dy77i1uti98s8a8jdcd42vbi3s</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
