  <page>
    <title>Foreign relations of Ethiopia</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9406</id>
    <revision>
      <id>934469628</id>
      <parentid>926807373</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-06T18:23:46Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>GreenC bot</username>
        <id>27823944</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rescued 2 archive links; reformat 4 links. [[User:GreenC/WaybackMedic_2.5|Wayback Medic 2.5]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}
{{Politics of Ethiopia}}
Many historians trace modern [[Ethiopia]]'s foreign policy to the reign of Emperor [[Tewodros II of Ethiopia|Tewodros II]], whose primary concerns were the security of Ethiopia's traditional borders, obtaining technology from Europe (or modernization), and to a lesser degree Ethiopian rights to the monastery of Dar-es-Sultan in the city of [[Jerusalem]].&lt;ref&gt;The political history of the Ethiopian community, and their struggle for ownership of this small monastery, is retold in Chris Proutky, ''Empress Taytu and Menelik II'' (Trenton: The Red Sea Press, 1986), pp. 247-256&lt;/ref&gt; Tewodros' diplomatic efforts, however, ended disastrously with the [[1868 Expedition to Abyssinia|British expedition of 1868]] which concluded with his death. Despite the efforts of his successor Emperor [[Yohannes IV of Ethiopia|Yohannes IV]] to establish a relationship with the United Kingdom, Ethiopia was ignored by the world powers until the opening of the [[Suez Canal]], and more important, the [[Mahdist War]], drew outside attention to her once more.&lt;ref&gt;Although Bahru Zewde, ''A History of Modern Ethiopia'', second edition (Oxford: James Currey, 2001), believes that the Suez Canal brought strategic value to the Red Sea region (p. 73), Sven Rubenson, ''The Survival of Ethiopian Independence'' (Hollywood: Tsehai,1991) argues that only with the Mahdi War did the United Kingdom  interest themselves once again in Ethiopia (pp. 283ff).&lt;/ref&gt;

The same major interests that Tewodros had—the security of Ethiopia's traditional borders and modernization—were once again foremost, as demonstrated by the outcome of the [[First Italo–Ethiopian War]], Ethiopia's admission to the [[League of Nations]] (28 September 1923), and the 1935 [[Second Italo-Abyssinian War]]. Following the decisive Ethiopian victory at [[battle of Adwa|Adwa]], [[Menelik II of Ethiopia|Menelik II]] rapidly negotiated a series of treaties fixing Ethiopia's boundaries—with French Somaliland in March 1897, British Somaliland a few months later in June 1897, with Italian Eritrea in 1900, Anglo-Egyptian Sudan in 1902, British East Africa in 1907, and Italian Somaliland in 1908—which simplified this problem on one level. Although Emperor [[Haile Selassie of Ethiopia|Haile Selassie]] agreed to [[Anglo-Ethiopian Agreement|an agreement]] with the British government to help him restore order to Ethiopia, which benefited him in crushing the [[Woyane|Woyane Rebellion]], he worked to its eventual termination.

Following [[World War II]], Ethiopia played an active role in regional and global politics. Ethiopia was a [[charter member]] of the [[United Nations]] and took part in UN operations in [[Korea]] in 1951 and the [[Democratic Republic of the Congo|Congo]] in 1960. Former [[Emperor]] [[Haile Selassie I]] was also among the founders of the [[Organization of African Unity]] (OAU), and served as one of a series of rotating OAU chairmen. Although nominally a member of the [[Non-Aligned Movement]], after the 1974 revolution, Ethiopia also moved into a close relationship with the [[Soviet Union]] and its allies and supported their international policies and positions until a change of government in 1991.

Today, Ethiopia is a major economic partner of [[Djibouti]] and [[Sudan]], although border demarcation negotiations are still ongoing with the [[Omar Al-Bashir]] administration. Relations with [[Somalia]] have also gradually improved, particularly since the establishment of a new government in [[Mogadishu]]. Ethiopia's dealings with [[Eritrea]] are extremely tense due to an ongoing border dispute between the two countries.

The Ethiopian government's [[Ethiopia-United States relations|relations with the U.S.]] and the West in general have been centered on military and economic cooperation. In addition, Ethiopia maintains diplomatic links with [[China]], [[Israel]], [[Mexico]] and [[India]], among other countries. [[Addis Ababa]] also serves as the headquarters of the [[United Nations Economic Commission for Africa]] (UNECA) and the [[African Union]], as well as numerous other continental and international organizations.

==Africa==
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin:auto;&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;width:15%;&quot;| Country
! style=&quot;width:12%;&quot;| Formal Relations Began
!Notes
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Algeria  }}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;
|
* Algeria has an embassy in [[Addis Ababa]].
* Ethiopia has an embassy in [[Algiers]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Côte d'Ivoire}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;
|
* Côte d'Ivoire has an embassy in Addis Ababa.
* Ethiopia has an embassy in [[Abidjan]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Djibouti  }}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;
|
Diplomatic relations between Ethiopia and [[Djibouti]] were established in 1984.&lt;ref name=&quot;MFA-Dj&quot;&gt;[http://mfa.gov.et/Foreign_Policy_And_Relation/Bilateral.php &quot;Ethiopia - Djibouti relations&quot;] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120325095640/http://mfa.gov.et/Foreign_Policy_And_Relation/Bilateral.php |date=25 March 2012 }}, Ministry of Foreign Affairs website (Retrieved 9 October 2009)&lt;/ref&gt; The border between the two countries is based on the Franco-Ethiopian convention of 20 March 1897, which was later finalized in a protocol dated 16 January 1954 and rendered effective on 28 February of that year.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.law.fsu.edu/library/collection/LimitsinSeas/IBS154.pdf &quot;Djibouti – Ethiopia Boundary&quot;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131109115403/http://www.law.fsu.edu/library/collection/LimitsinSeas/IBS154.pdf |date=9 November 2013 }}, U.S. Department of State, International Boundary Study No. 154 – 20 February 1976&lt;/ref&gt; In October 1991, the Ethiopian and Djiboutian governments signed a Treaty of Friendship and Cooperation further solidifying relations. Since 1991, the two countries have signed over 39 protocol agreements.&lt;ref name=MFA-Dj/&gt;

Djibouti remains a major economic partner of Ethiopia. On 13 April 2002, the two countries signed an agreement concerning the use of the [[Port of Djibouti]] and the transit of cargo, which was later ratified by the Ethiopian [[Federal Parliamentary Assembly]] on 4 June of the same year.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ethiopar.net/type/English/hopre/bills/2004_2005/Proc%20No.%20284-%202002%20Ethio-Djibouti%20Utilization%20of%20Port%20of%20Dj.pdf &quot;Ethio-Djibouti Utilization of Port of Djibouti and Services to Cargo in Transit Agreement Ratification Proclamation No. 284/2002&quot;] (Retrieved 13 July 2010) {{dead link|date=June 2016|bot=medic}}{{cbignore|bot=medic}}&lt;/ref&gt; About 70% of the Port of Djibouti's activity consists of imports to and exports from neighboring Ethiopia, which depends on the harbour as its main maritime outlet. The port also serves as an international refueling center and transshipment hub.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cdpafoid&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Bansal|first=Ridhima|title=Current Development Projects and Future Opportunities in Djibouti|url=http://www.aaeafrica.org/start/current-development-projects-and-future-opportunities-in-djibouti/|publisher=Association of African Entrepreneurs|accessdate=26 February 2013|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130327074151/http://www.aaeafrica.org/start/current-development-projects-and-future-opportunities-in-djibouti/|archive-date=27 March 2013|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, both countries share ownership of the [[Ethio-Djibouti Railways|Addis Ababa-Djibouti Railroad]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Egypt  }}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||See [[Egypt–Ethiopia relations]]

As two of the oldest independent states in Africa, both countries have an ancient relationship in many forms. The [[Ethiopian Orthodox Tewahedo Church]] was under the administration of the [[Coptic Orthodox Church]] from ancient times until 1959. Ethiopian and Egyptian armies clashed in the early 19th century over control of territory in what is modern Sudan, and Ethiopia's access to the Red Sea. Both countries established formal diplomatic ties in 1927.&lt;ref name=&quot;SIS&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sis.gov.eg/En/Templates/Articles/tmpArticles.aspx?CatID=1193|title=Egyptian-Ethiopian relations|publisher=State Information Service}}&lt;/ref&gt; More recently, because both countries share a [[Special relationship (international relations)|special relationship]] over the Nile basin, both are members of the [[Nile Basin Initiative]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Eritrea  }}||9 July 2018||See [[Eritrea–Ethiopia relations]]
*The boundary between these two countries is based on three treaties between Ethiopia and [[Ethiopia-Italy relations|Italy]], in 1900, 1902, and 1908. However no part of the shared boundary was afterwards demarcated.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.un.org/NewLinks/eebcarbitration/ Findings of the UN Eritea-Ethiopia Boundary Commission] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110130110233/http://www.un.org/NewLinks/eebcarbitration/ |date=30 January 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* From 1950 until 1993, Eritrea was federated as part of Ethiopia. During much of this period, a number of Eritreans [[Eritrean War of Independence|fought for independence from Ethiopia]]. The federation was ended with an April 1993 [[United Nations Observer Mission to Verify the Referendum in Eritrea|plebiscite]] which approved Eritrea's full independence.
* Disputes over Eritrea's border alignment led to the [[Eritrean-Ethiopian War]] (1998–2000), which was resolved by an [[Algiers Agreement (2000)|independent boundary commission's]] [[boundary delimitation|delimitation]] decision in 2002. However, demarcation has been delayed, despite intense international intervention, by Ethiopian insistence that the decision ignored &quot;human geography,&quot; made technical errors in the delimitation, and determined that certain disputed areas, specifically [[Badme]], fall to Eritrea. Eritrea meanwhile insists on not deviating from the commission's decision. The [[United Nations Mission in Ethiopia and Eritrea|peacekeepers]] monitoring the disputed boundary were forced to withdraw in July 2008&lt;ref name=&quot;UN_SRES18272008&quot;&gt;{{UN document |docid=S-RES-1827(2008) |type=Resolution |body=Security Council |year=2008 |resolution_number=1827 |accessdate=17 August 2008|date=30 July 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; having considered their remaining options&lt;ref name=&quot;UN_S2008226&quot;&gt;{{UN document |docid=S-2008-226 |type=Document |body=Security Council |year=2008 |document_number=226 |accessdate=17 August 2008|title=Special report of the Secretary-General on the United Nations Mission in Ethiopia and Eritrea|date=7 April 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; after experiencing serious difficulties in supporting its troops.&lt;ref name=&quot;UN_S2008145&quot;&gt;{{UN document |docid=S-2008-145 |type=Document |body=Security Council |year=2008 |document_number=145 |accessdate=17 August 2008|title=Special report of the Secretary-General on the United Nations Mission in Ethiopia and Eritrea|date=3 March 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*In July 2018, leaders both countries [[2018 Eritrea–Ethiopia summit|signed]] a peace treaty to put a formal end to a state of war between both nations paving the way for greater economic cooperation and improved ties between them.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.reuters.com/article/us-ethiopia-eritrea-economy/ex-foes-ethiopia-eritrea-eye-peace-dividend-after-historic-deal-idUSKBN1JZ2KS&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Ghana}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;
|
* Ethiopia has an embassy in [[Accra]].
* Ghana has an embassy in Addis Ababa.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Kenya  }}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||See [[Ethiopia–Kenya relations]]

Relations between [[Kenya]] and [[Ethiopia]] date back to the 1954, when the Ethiopian authorities under [[Haile Selassie I]] established an honorary consulate general in the British [[Kenya Colony]]. In 1961, prior to Kenya's independence, Ethiopia appointed its first ambassador to Kenya, and six years later Kenya opened an embassy in [[Addis Ababa]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://mfa.gov.et/Foreign_Policy_And_Relation/Bilateral.php &quot;Ethiopia - Kenya relations&quot;] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120325095640/http://mfa.gov.et/Foreign_Policy_And_Relation/Bilateral.php |date=25 March 2012 }}, Ministry of Foreign Affairs website (accessed 9 October 2009)&lt;/ref&gt;

The border between the two countries is based on a treaty signed by Ethiopia and Kenya on 9 June 1970, which determines the present-day boundary, abrogating all previous boundary treaties. This border has been subjected to demarcation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.law.fsu.edu/library/collection/limitsinseas/IBS152.pdf &quot;Ethiopia – Kenya Boundary&quot;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090318063413/http://www.law.fsu.edu/library/collection/limitsinseas/IBS152.pdf |date=18 March 2009 }}, U.S. State Department International Boundary Study, No. 152 – 15 October 1975&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Morocco}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;
|
* Ethiopia has an embassy in [[Rabat]].
* Morocco has an embassy in Addis Ababa.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Namibia  }}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;
|
Ethiopia–Namibia relations refers to the [[bilateralism|current and historical relationship]] between Ethiopia and [[Namibia]]. Namibia maintains an embassy in Addis Ababa.

During the [[Namibia under South African occupation|South African occupation of Namibia]], Ethiopia was one of the country's leading proponents abroad; Ethiopia and [[Liberia]] were the first two states to bring the question of independence for then [[South West Africa]] to the [[United Nations]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| author = John Dugard| title = The South West Africa/Namibia Dispute: Documents and Scholarly Writings on the Controversy Between South Africa and the United Nations| url = https://books.google.com/?id=MA4mkNKXxqoC&amp;pg=PA220| year = 1973| publisher = University of California Press| isbn = 978-0-520-01886-0| page = 220 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Namibia gained independence in 1990 In 2007, the two governments signed an agreement which expanded air travel between the two states.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kilil5.com/news/12989_ethiopia-namibia-sign-air-transp Ethiopia, Namibia sign air transport agreement] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120119135029/http://www.kilil5.com/news/12989_ethiopia-namibia-sign-air-transp |date=19 January 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In December 2009, Namibia's Foreign Minister, [[Marko Hausiku]] met with Ethiopian Foreign Affairs Minister [[Seyoum Mesfin]] and noted the economic, science, technical and cultural agreements in place between the two countries and expressed a desire to improve the trade relations.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mfa.gov.et/Press_Section/publication.php?Main_Page_Number=4796 Ethiopia, Namibia working out to step up cooperation areas] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120328075854/http://www.mfa.gov.et/Press_Section/publication.php?Main_Page_Number=4796 |date=28 March 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Nigeria}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;
|
* Ethiopia has an embassy in [[Abuja]].
* Nigeria has an embassy in Addis Ababa.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Senegal}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;
|
* Ethiopia has an embassy in [[Dakar]].
* Senegal has an embassy in Addis Ababa.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Somalia }}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||See [[Ethiopia–Somalia relations]]

Relations between the peoples of Somalia and Ethiopia stretch back to antiquity, to a common origin. The Ethiopian region is one of the proposed homelands of the [[Horn of Africa]]'s various [[Afro-Asiatic languages|Afro-Asiatic]] communities.&lt;ref name=&quot;Levine&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Levine|first=Donald N.|title=Greater Ethiopia: The Evolution of a Multiethnic Society|year=2000|publisher=University of Chicago Press|isbn=0226475611|pages=27–28|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=TtmFQejWaaYC}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the Middle Ages, Somali [[Imam]] [[Ahmad ibn Ibrihim al-Ghazi]] (Ahmad Gurey or Gragn) led a [[Ethiopian-Adal War|Conquest of Abyssinia]] (''Futuh al-Habash''), which brought three-quarters of the Christian [[Ethiopian Empire]] under the power of the Muslim [[Adal Sultanate]].&lt;ref&gt;Saheed A. Adejumobi, ''The History of Ethiopia'', (Greenwood Press: 2006), p.178&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Encyclopædia Britannica, inc, Encyclopædia Britannica, Volume 1, (Encyclopædia Britannica: 2005), p.163&lt;/ref&gt; With an army mainly composed of [[Somali people|Somalis]],&lt;ref&gt;John L. Esposito, editor, ''The Oxford History of Islam'', (Oxford University Press: 2000), p. 501&lt;/ref&gt; Many historians trace the origins of tensions between Somalia and Ethiopia to this war.&lt;ref&gt;David D. Laitin and Said S. Samatar, ''Somalia: Nation in Search of a State'' (Boulder: Westview Press, 1987).&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 1960s and 1970s, a territorial dispute over the [[Ogaden]] region led to various armed confrontations between the Somalian and Ethiopian militaries. The tensions culminated in the [[Ogaden War]], which saw the Somali army capture most of the disputed territory by September 1977, before finally being expelled by a coalition of communist forces.

With changes in leadership in the early 1990s brought on by the start of the [[Somali Civil War]] and [[Ethiopian Civil War]], respectively, relations between the Somali and Ethiopian authorities entered a new phase of military cooperation against the [[Islamic Courts Union]] (ICU) rebel group and its more radical successor [[Al-Shabaab (militant group)|Al-Shabaab]]. In October 2011, a [[Operation Linda Nchi|coordinated multinational operation]] began against Al-Shabaab in southern Somalia; the Ethiopian military eventually joined the [[Transitional Federal Government]]-led mission the following month.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eatbsaois&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.businessweek.com/news/2011-11-25/ethiopia-agrees-to-back-somalia-army-operations-igad-says.html |title=Ethiopia Agrees to Back Somalia Military Operations, IGAD Says |work=Businessweek |date=1 December 2011 |accessdate=22 August 2012 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://archive.today/20120729154359/http://www.businessweek.com/news/2011-11-25/ethiopia-agrees-to-back-somalia-army-operations-igad-says.html |archivedate=29 July 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Federal Government of Somalia]] was later established on 20 August 2012,&lt;ref name=&quot;Fcacsunesinpshm&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Somalia: UN Envoy Says Inauguration of New Parliament in Somalia 'Historic Moment'|url=http://allafrica.com/stories/201208220474.html|accessdate=24 August 2012|newspaper=Forum on China-Africa Cooperation|date=21 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; representing the first permanent central government in the country since the start of the civil war.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fcacsunesinpshm&quot;/&gt; The following month, [[Hassan Sheikh Mohamud]] was elected as the new Somali government's first President, with the Ethiopian authorities welcoming his selection and newly appointed Prime Minister of Ethiopia [[Hailemariam Desalegn]] attending Mohamud's inauguration ceremony.&lt;ref name=&quot;Piuinefs&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Mohamed|first=Mahmoud|title=Presidential inauguration ushers in new era for Somalia|url=http://sabahionline.com/en_GB/articles/hoa/articles/features/2012/09/17/feature-01|accessdate=30 September 2012|newspaper=Sabahi|date=17 September 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|South Africa}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;
|
* Ethiopia has an embassy in [[Pretoria]].
* South Africa has an embassy in Addis Ababa.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Sudan  }}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;
|
[[Alodia]] and the [[Kingdom of Makuria]] had some relations with Ethiopia in Medieval times.

The [[Ethiopian Empire]] fought against [[Mahdist Sudan]] in the [[Mahdist War]].

Ethiopia and Sudan first established formal relations in 1956.&lt;ref&gt;[http://mfa.gov.et/Foreign_Policy_And_Relation/Bilateral.php &quot;Ethiopia - Sudan relations&quot;] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120325095640/http://mfa.gov.et/Foreign_Policy_And_Relation/Bilateral.php |date=25 March 2012 }}, Ministry of Foreign Affairs website (Retrieved 9 October 2009)&lt;/ref&gt; Relations between Ethiopia and Sudan were very good following the end of the [[Ethiopian Civil War]], due to the support that the Sudanese government had given to the [[Ethiopian People's Revolutionary Democratic Front]]. However, relations were strained for a time following the 26 June 1995 assassination attempt against Egyptian president [[Hosni Mubarak]] as he was leaving the OAU summit meeting in Addis Ababa. The subsequent investigation revealed that Sudan was involved in this act, forcing the Ethiopian government to take a series of steps against Sudan that September, which included closing the Sudanese consulate in [[Gambela, Ethiopia|Gambela]], reducing the number of Sudanese embassy staff, and terminating all [[Sudan Airways]] and [[Ethiopian Airlines]] flights between the two countries. However the start of the Eritrean-Ethiopian War led to Sudan and Ethiopia put this conflict between them and normalizing their relations by November 1999 when president [[Omar Hassan al-Bashir]] made a formal visit to Addis Ababa.&lt;ref&gt;David H. Shinn, [http://www.csis.org/media/csis/pubs/anotes_0202.pdf &quot;Ethiopia: Coping with Islamic Fundamentalism before and after September 11&quot;] (last accessed 10 December 2008)&lt;/ref&gt;

A protocol concerning Ethiopian access to [[Port Sudan]] was signed between the two countries 5 March 2000 in Khartoum, and this protocol and its subsequent amendment were ratified by the Ethiopian [[Federal Parliamentary Assembly]] on 3 July 2003.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ethiopar.net/type/English/hopre/bills/2004_2005/Proc%20No.%20352-2003%20protocol%20Agreement%20on%20Port%20Sudan%20Utilizat.pdf &quot;protocol Agreement on Port Sudan Utilization Ratification Proclamation No. 352/2003&quot;] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120304035135/http://www.ethiopar.net/type/English/hopre/bills/2004_2005/Proc%20No.%20352-2003%20protocol%20Agreement%20on%20Port%20Sudan%20Utilizat.pdf |date=4 March 2012 }}, [http://www.ethiopar.net/type/English/hopre/bills/2004_2005/Proc%20No.%20353-2003%20The%20Amendment%20to%20the%20protocol%20Agreement%20o.pdf &quot;Amendment to the Protocol Agreement, on Port Sudan Utilization, Ratification Proclamation No. 35312003&quot;] (Retrieved 13 July 2010) {{dead link|date=June 2016|bot=medic}}{{cbignore|bot=medic}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Efforts to demarcate the porous boundary with Sudan were delayed by the [[Second Sudanese Civil War]]. In May 2008, residents along the western Ethiopian border reportedly discovered that the government had agreed to demarcate this boundary when Sudanese soldiers forced them out of their homes. It was reported that as many as 2,000 people were displaced in the [[Gambela Region]], and the Sudanese army reportedly set fire to two dozen Ethiopian farms and imprisoned 34 people in the [[Amhara Region]]. However, Prime Minister Meles Zenawi publicly denied that any Ethiopians had been displaced by this agreement.&lt;ref&gt;Alisha Ryu, [http://www.voanews.com/english/archive/2008-06/2008-06-05-voa43.cfm?CFID=156867109&amp;CFTOKEN=60445804&amp;jsessionid=8830a70f00653c50c7a814604b23643f33fe &quot;Border Demarcation with Sudan Causes Anger in Ethiopia&quot;]{{dead link|date=April 2015}}, Voice of America website, 5 June 2008 (Retrieved 3 April 2009)&lt;/ref&gt; Negotiations over this boundary continues, with the twelfth meeting of the Boundary Commission announced 28 December 2009 at [[Mek'ele]], with Ethiopian representatives from the [[Tigray Region|Tigray]], [[Benishangul-Gumuz Region|Benishangul-Gumuz]], Amhara and Gambela Regions, and from the Sudanese side representatives of the [[Upper Nile State|Upper Nile]], [[Blue Nile State|Blue Nile]], [[Sennar]] and [[Al Qadarif (state)|Al Qadarif]] Administrations.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mfa.gov.et/Press_Section/publication.php?Main_Page_Number=4838 &quot;Ethio-Sudanese Border Commission Meeting To Open Monday (December 28, 2009)&quot;] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120220050517/http://www.mfa.gov.et/Press_Section/publication.php?Main_Page_Number=4838 |date=20 February 2012 }}, Ministry of Foreign Affairs website (Retrieved 28 December 2009)&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite these border tensions, Sudan remains a major economic partner of Ethiopia. According to the Ethiopian Petroleum Supplier Enterprise (EPSE), Ethiopia in April 2013 imported around $1.12 billion worth of oil from Sudan over the previous six months. In total, about 85% of Ethiopia's yearly oil consumption comes from Sudan via the Port of Djibouti. Ethiopia and Sudan are also in the process of linking their [[power grid]]s.&lt;ref name=Tekle&gt;{{cite news|last=Tekle|first=Tesfa-Alem|title=Sudan: Ethiopia Imports $U.S.1 Billion in Fuel From Sudan Via Djibouti|url=http://allafrica.com/stories/201304011187.html|accessdate=16 April 2013|newspaper=Sudan Tribune|date=30 March 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Tanzania }}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Ethiopia has an embassy in [[Dar-es-Salaam]].
* Tanzania has an embassy in Addis Ababa.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Uganda }}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Ethiopia has an embassy in [[Kampala]].
* Uganda has an embassy in Addis Ababa.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Zimbabwe}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;
|
* Ethiopia has an embassy in [[Harare]].
* Zimbabwe has an embassy in Addis Ababa.
|}

==Americas==
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin:auto;&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;width:15%;&quot;| Country
! style=&quot;width:12%;&quot;| Formal Relations Began
!Notes
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Argentina}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;
|
* Argentina has an embassy in Addis Ababa.
* Ethiopia does not have an accreditation to Argentina.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Brazil}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;
|
* Brazil has an embassy in Addis Ababa.
* Ethiopia has an embassy in [[Brasília]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Canada }}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;1956
|See [[Canada–Ethiopia relations]]
* Canada has an embassy in Addis Ababa.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.canadainternational.gc.ca/ethiopia-ethiopie/index.aspx?lang=eng Embassy of Canada in Addis Ababa (in English and French)]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Ethiopia has an embassy in Ottawa.&lt;ref&gt;[http://ethioembassycanada.org/ Embassy of Ethiopia in Ottawa]&lt;/ref&gt;
*''See also'': [[Ethiopian Canadian]]
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Chile}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;16 October 1945
|
* Chile has an embassy in Addis Ababa.
* Ethiopia does not have an accreditation to Chile
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Cuba}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;
|
* Cuba has an embassy in Addis Ababa.
* Ethiopia has an embassy in [[Havana]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Ecuador}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;
|
* Ecuador has an embassy in Addis Ababa.
* Ethiopia does not have an accreditation to Ecuador.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Guyana}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;1970
|
Both countries established diplomatic relations on 13 October 1970.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.minfor.gov.gy/docs/other/diplomatic_relations_list.pdf |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2016-07-16 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160307101008/http://www.minfor.gov.gy/docs/other/diplomatic_relations_list.pdf |archivedate=7 March 2016 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Mexico }}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;1949
|See [[Ethiopia–Mexico relations]]
* During the [[Second Italo-Ethiopian War]], Mexico was one of the member states of the [[League of Nations]] to condemn the occupation of Ethiopia and support the League's sanctions against Italy.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sre.gob.mx/images/stories/docnormateca/manexte/embajadas/moemetiopia12.pdf Bilateral relations between Mexico and Ethiopia (in Spanish)]&lt;/ref&gt; Since then, relations between the two nations have strengthened.
* In Addis Ababa, Ethiopia named a square in the capital &quot;Mexico Square.&quot; Mexico, in turn, named a metro station in Mexico City called [[Metro Etiopía]].
* Mexico has an embassy in Addis Ababa.&lt;ref&gt;[http://embamex.sre.gob.mx/etiopia/ Embassy of Mexico in Addis Ababa (in English and Spanish)]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Ethiopia is accredited to Mexico through its embassy in [[Washington, DC]], [[United States]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ethiopianembassy.org&quot;&gt;[http://www.ethiopianembassy.org/ Embassy of Ethiopia in Washington, DC]&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|United States }}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;1903
|See [[Ethiopia–United States relations]]
* Ethiopia is a strategic partner of the United States in the Global War on Terrorism.
* U.S. development assistance to Ethiopia is focused on reducing famine vulnerability, hunger, and poverty and emphasizes economic, governance, and social sector policy reforms.
* Ethiopia has an embassy in [[Washington, DC]] and a consulate-general in [[Los Angeles]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ethiopianembassy.org&quot;/&gt;
* United States has an embassy in Addis Ababa.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://ethiopia.usembassy.gov/ |title=US embassy in Addis Ababa |access-date=14 November 2014 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141127001057/http://ethiopia.usembassy.gov/ |archive-date=27 November 2014 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*''See also'': [[Ethiopian American]]
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Uruguay}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;
|
* Ethiopia does not have an accreditation to Uruguay.
* Uruguay has an embassy in Addis Ababa.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Venezuela}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;
|
* Ethiopia does not have an accreditation to Venezuela.
* Venezuela has an embassy in Addis Ababa.
|}

==Asia==
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin:auto;&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;width:15%;&quot;| Country
! style=&quot;width:12%;&quot;| Formal Relations Began
!Notes
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Armenia  }}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;1993
|
*Both countries established diplomatic relations on December 2, 1993.&lt;ref name=&quot;mfa.am&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/et/ |title=Archived copy |access-date=26 February 2017 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170227193121/http://www.mfa.am/en/country-by-country/et |archive-date=27 February 2017 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Armenia is represented in Ethiopia through its embassy in [[Cairo]], Egypt.&lt;ref name=&quot;mfa.am&quot;/&gt;
*Ethiopia is represented in Armenia through its embassy in [[Moscow]], Russia.&lt;ref name=&quot;mfa.am&quot;/&gt;
*Both nations have among the oldest christian communities
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|China}}||1970
| See [[China–Ethiopia relations]]

Ethiopia has an embassy in [[Beijing]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ethiopiaemb.org.cn/index.pl |title=Embassy of Ethiopia in P.R.China |publisher=Embassy of Ethiopia in P.R.China |accessdate=28 July 2009 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090601182926/http://www.ethiopiaemb.org.cn/index.pl |archivedate=1 June 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and the People's Republic of China has an embassy in Addis Ababa.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://et.china-embassy.org/eng/ |title=Embassy of the People's Republic of China in Ethiopia |publisher=People's Republic of China |accessdate=28 July 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; By 2009, direct Chinese investment in Ethiopia had reached US$900 million and bilateral trade had grown to $1.3 billion.&lt;ref name=&quot;ethiopol&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://ethiopolitics.com/news_1/20090715972.html |title=China’s direct investment to Ethiopia reaches (sic) $900mln |publisher=Ethiopolitics.com |date=15 July 2009 |accessdate=28 July 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|India}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;1948
|See [[India-Ethiopia relations|India–Ethiopia relations]]
* Ethiopia has an embassy in [[New Delhi]] and India in [[Addis Ababa]]
* India trains Ethiopian personnel under its [[Indian Technical and Economic Cooperation Programme|ITEC program]] and is Ethiopia's second largest source of [[Foreign Direct Investments]].
* The Second [[India-Africa Forum Summit]] was held in Addis Ababa in 2011 and India launched its [[Pan-African e-Network project|Pan-African e-Network Project]] in Ethiopia in 2007.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Israel}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;1992
|See [[Ethiopia–Israel relations]]
* Ethiopia has an embassy in [[Tel Aviv]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.ethioemb.org.il/ |title=Embassy of Ethiopia in Tel-Aviv |access-date=14 November 2014 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180116075623/http://www.ethioemb.org.il/ |archive-date=16 January 2018 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Israel has an embassy in Addis Ababa.&lt;ref&gt;[http://embassies.gov.il/addis_ababa/Pages/default.aspx Embassy of Israel in Addis Ababa]&lt;/ref&gt;
*''See also'': [[Ethiopian Jews in Israel]], [[Operation Moses]], [[Operation Solomon]], [[Beta Israel|History of the Jews in Ethiopia]]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20090621131646/http://www.mfa.gov.et/Foreign_Policy_And_Relation/Bilateral.php Ethiopian Ministry of Foreign Affairs about relations with Israel]
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Japan }}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;1930
|See [[Ethiopia-Japan relations]]
* Japan and Ethiopia explored diplomatic and economic relations in the 1930s in response to perceived common interests; however these contacts lapsed with the commencement of the [[Second Italo-Ethiopian War]]
* Relations were reestablished in 1955 and ambassadors exchanged in 1958.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mfa.gov.et/Foreign_Policy_And_Relation/Bilateral.php &quot;Bilateral relations&quot;] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120325095640/http://www.mfa.gov.et/Foreign_Policy_And_Relation/Bilateral.php |date=25 March 2012 }}, Ethiopian Ministry of Foreign Affairs website (Retrieved 28 December 2009)&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Malaysia }}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;
|See [[Ethiopia–Malaysia relations]]
* Ethiopia has a consulate-general in [[Kuala Lumpur]],&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.malaysia-ethiopia.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=62&amp;Itemid=74|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180504170819/http://www.malaysia-ethiopia.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=62&amp;Itemid=74|url-status=dead|archive-date=4 May 2018|title=Consulate General Office of Ethiopia, Kuala Lumpur|publisher=Ethiopia Consulat General Office|accessdate=27 January 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; while Malaysia doesn't have any embassy in Ethiopia.
* Malaysia is one of the major trade partner and also one of the largest investors in Ethiopia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://countries.bridgat.com/Ethiopia_Trade_Partners.html|title=Ethiopia Major Trade Partners|publisher=Bridgat|accessdate=27 January 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.freshplaza.com/article/44294/Ethiopia-Malaysian-company-to-set-up-285mln-birr-mushroom-farm-establishment|title=Ethiopia: Malaysian company to set up 285mln birr mushroom farm establishment|publisher=Fresh Plaza|work=Ethiopian Review|date=25 May 2009|accessdate=27 January 2014|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140201185121/http://www.freshplaza.com/article/44294/Ethiopia-Malaysian-company-to-set-up-285mln-birr-mushroom-farm-establishment|archive-date=1 February 2014|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mpocegypt.com/?p=1186|title=Malaysian edible oil producer to build a large refinery in Ethiopia|publisher=Malaysian Palm Oil Council|date=3 April 2013|accessdate=27 January 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|North Korea}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;1975 
|See [[foreign relations of North Korea]]
Both countries established diplomatic relations in 1975.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.voakorea.com/a/3849967.html&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Palestine}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;1989||
Palestine has an embassy in [[Addis Ababa]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Philippines}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;2013||
The Philippines and Ethiopia signed their first air agreement in 2014.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.rappler.com/business/industries/171-aviation-tourism/71532-philippines-ethiopia-air-agreement&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Qatar }}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;
|See [[Ethiopia-Qatar relations]]
* Ethiopia abruptly broke diplomatic ties with Qatar in April 2008, apparently due to statements made by the [[Al-Jazeera]] news channel which is based in Qatar.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|South Korea}}||23 December 1963||
Between The Federal Democratic Republic of Ethiopia and The Republic of Korea were established diplomatic relations on December 23, 1963.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.mofa.go.kr/ENG/countries/middleeast/countries/20070804/1_24478.jsp?menu=m_30_50{{Dead link|date=July 2018 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt; 
* Infantry men of 6,037 from Ethiopia have participated in the [[Korean War]] to help South Korea.
* The number of South Koreans living in Ethiopia in 2016 were about 460.
* The Republic of Korea`s official development assistance from 1991 to 2014 was about 88.61m USD. 
** The Federal Democratic Republic of Ethiopia has an embassy in [[Seoul]].&lt;ref&gt;https://search.naver.com/search.naver?where=nexearch&amp;query=%EC%A3%BC%ED%95%9C%EC%97%90%ED%8B%B0%EC%98%A4%ED%94%BC%EC%95%84%EB%8C%80%EC%82%AC%EA%B4%80&amp;ie=utf8&amp;sm=tab_she&amp;qdt=0&lt;/ref&gt;
** Since 1965 South Korea has an embassy in Addis Ababa.&lt;ref&gt;http://eth.mofa.go.kr/english/af/eth/main/index.jsp&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Turkey }}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||See [[Ethiopian–Turkish relations]]

* Ethiopia has an embassy in [[Ankara]].
* Turkey has an embassy in Addis Ababa since 1925.
* Contact between the two countries date back at least as far as [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman]] times.
* Turkey was the sixth country to open an embassy in Ethiopia.
* Today the relations between the two countries are described as excellent, both politically and economically.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.waltainfo.com/Interview/2008/Mar/mulatu.htm Ethiopian Ambassador to Turkey: Ethiopia does not need political reform] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110927140838/http://www.waltainfo.com/Interview/2008/Mar/mulatu.htm |date=27 September 2011 }}, [[Walta Information Center]]&lt;/ref&gt;
|}

==Europe==
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin:auto;&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;width:15%;&quot;| Country
! style=&quot;width:12%;&quot;| Formal Relations Began
!Notes
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Belarus }}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Belarus is accredited to Ethiopia from its embassy in Nairobi, Kenya.
* Ethiopia is accredited to Belarus from its embassy in Moscow, Russia.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Czech Republic }}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;
|
* Ethiopia is accredited to the Czech Republic from its embassy in Berlin, Germany.
* Czech Republic has an embassy in Addis Ababa.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mzv.cz/addisababa Czech embassy in Ethiopia]&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Denmark }}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;
|See [[Denmark–Ethiopia relations]]

* Denmark has an embassy in Addis Ababa.
* Ethiopia is accredited to Denmark from its embassy in Stockholm, Sweden.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Finland }}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;1959-07-17
|See [[Ethiopia–Finland relations]]
* Ethiopia is represented in Finland through its embassy in Stockholm, Sweden.
* Finland has an embassy in Addis Ababa.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://formin.finland.fi/public/default.aspx?nodeid=17210&amp;culture=en-US&amp;contentlan=2 |title=Ministry for Foreign Affairs of Finland about Ethiopia |access-date=13 June 2009 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110716073842/http://formin.finland.fi/public/default.aspx?nodeid=17210&amp;culture=en-US&amp;contentlan=2 |archive-date=16 July 2011 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|France }}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Ethiopia has an embassy in [[Paris]].
* France has an embassy in Addis Ababa.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Germany }}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;1905||
* Both countries signed a treaty of friendship in March 1905; a German Legation was opened in Addis Ababa in 1907, and an Ethiopian embassy in Berlin the same year.
* Germany supported Ethiopia in the [[Second Italo-Abyssinian War]].
* Ethiopia has an embassy in [[Berlin]].
* Germany has an embassy in Addis Ababa.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Greece }}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||See [[Ethiopia–Greece relations]]

* Ethiopia is accredited to Greece from its embassy in Rome, Italy.
* Greece has an embassy in Addis Ababa.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Ireland }}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;1994||See [[Ethiopia–Ireland relations]]
* Ethiopia has an embassy in [[Dublin]].
* Since 1994, Ireland has an embassy in Addis Ababa.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Italy}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;1889
|See [[Ethiopia–Italy relations]]
* Italy was one of the first European countries to open diplomatic relations with Ethiopia.
* Both countries have fought two wars against each other: the [[First Italo-Ethiopian War]] and the [[Second Italo-Ethiopian War]]
* Total trade volume between two countries reached 455,928,352.26 Birr in 2011.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mfa.gov.et/BilateralMore.php?pg=20 Ethiopian Ministry of Foreign Affairs about Italy] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140331065231/http://www.mfa.gov.et/BilateralMore.php?pg=20 |date=31 March 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Italy has an embassy in Addis Ababa.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ambaddisabeba.esteri.it/Ambasciata_AddisAbeba Embassy of Italy in Addis Ababa (in English and Italian)]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Ethiopia has an embassy in [[Rome]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ethiopianembassy.it/ Embassy of Ethiopia in Rome (in Italian)]&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Poland }}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Ethiopia is accredited to Poland from its embassy in Berlin, Germany.
* Poland has an embassy in Addis Ababa.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Romania }}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;
|
* Ethiopia is accredited to Romania from its Permanent Mission in [[Geneva]], Switzerland.
* Romania has an embassy in Addis Ababa.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mae.ro/index.php?unde=doc&amp;id=6257&amp;idlnk=4&amp;cat=6 Romanian Ministry of Foreign Affairs: direction of the Romenian embassy in Addis Ababa]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20110720153405/http://www.mfa.gov.et/Press_Section/publication.php?Pub_Page_Id=4217  Ethiopian Ministry of Foreign Affairs about bilateral relations with Romania]
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Russia }}||1943-4-21
| See [[Ethiopia–Russia relations]]
* Russia has an embassy in Addis Ababa.
* Ethiopia has an [[Embassy of Ethiopia in Moscow|embassy in Moscow]]. The Ethiopian ambassador to Russia is also accredited to Armenia, Azerbaijan, Belarus, Georgia, Kazakhstan, Kyrgyzstan, Moldova, Tajikistan, Turkmenistan, Ukraine, and Uzbekistan.
* The history of this relationship has its origins in the 19th century. Russia supplied the mountain guns the Ethiopian army used in the [[Battle of Adwa]].
* More recently, the [[Soviet Union]] was a major source of military and economic aid under the [[Derg]] and during the [[People's Democratic Republic of Ethiopia]].
* See also [[Alexander Bulatovich]]
* Relations are somewhat unsure owing to Russia's close ties with Ethiopia's neighboring rival, [[Sudan]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Serbia }}||1952
| See [[Ethiopia-Serbia relations]]
* Serbia has an embassy in Addis Ababa.
* Ethiopia is accredited Serbia from its embassy in Rome, Italy.
* Ethiopia is a strong advocate for Serbia on the issue of [[Kosovo]].
* The first vessel in the [[Ethiopian Navy]] was a gift from [[Yugoslavia]].
* The Serbian embassy is the former villa of Yugoslav President [[Josip Broz Tito]], which was given as a gift by [[Haile Selassie]]
* On 27 January 2012, after traveling to Addis Ababa in order to reaffirm Ethiopia's stance on Kosovo regarding Serbia, [[Vuk Jeremić]] and [[Haile Mariam]] signed a memorandum of understanding between the two nations' ministries of foreign affairs.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rtv.rs/sr_lat/politika/potpisan-memorandum-o-saradnji-srbije-i-etiopije_296993.html RTV - 27 January 2012 - Potpisan memorandum o saradnji Srbije i Etiopije (Serbian)]&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Spain }}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;
|
* Ethiopia is accredited to Spain from its embassy in Paris, France.
* Spain has an embassy in Addis Ababa.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Sweden }}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||See [[Ethiopia–Sweden relations]]

* Ethiopia has an embassy in [[Stockholm]].
* Sweden has an embassy in Addis Ababa.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Ukraine}}||1993-4-1||

* Ethiopia is accredited to Ukraine from its embassy in Berlin, Russia.
* Ukraine has an embassy in Addis Ababa.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|United Kingdom }}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||See 

* Ethiopia has an embassy in [[London]].
* United Kingdom has an embassy in Addis Ababa.
|}

==Oceania==
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin:auto;&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;width:15%;&quot;| Country
! style=&quot;width:12%;&quot;| Formal Relations Began
!Notes
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|Australia }}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Australia has an embassy in Addis Ababa.
* Ethiopia has an embassy in [[Canberra]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{Flag|New Zealand }}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Ethiopia is accredited to New Zealand from its embassy in Canberra, Australia.
* New Zealand has an embassy in Addis Ababa.
|}


==See also==
* [[:Category:Ethiopian diaspora]]
* [[Foreign aid to Ethiopia]]
* [[List of diplomatic missions in Ethiopia]]
* [[List of diplomatic missions of Ethiopia]]
* [[Ministry of Foreign Affairs (Ethiopia)|Ministry of Foreign Affairs]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20060207195509/http://www.mfa.gov.et/index.php Ministry of Foreign Affairs for Ethiopia's webpage]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20080731165125/http://ipsnews.net/news.asp?idnews=42906 A Tangled Political Landscape Raises Questions About African Ally of the U.S. by Michael Deibert, 12 June 2008]
* Abdul Mohammed, [https://web.archive.org/web/20090525223949/http://hornofafrica.ssrc.org/Abdul_Mohammed/ &quot;Ethiopia’s Strategic Dilemma in the Horn of Africa&quot;], Crisis in the Horn of Africa (Social Science Research Council website)
* [http://www.csmonitor.com/1989/0504/areg.html &quot;U.S. to Test Soviet 'New Thinking': Talks on Africa,&quot; ''The Christian Science Monitor'', 4 May 1989.]
* [http://www.unz.org/Pub/PolicyRev-1988q3-00074 &quot;Gorbachev's Holocaust: Soviet Complicity in Ethiopia's Famine&quot;], by Michael Johns, ''Policy Review'', Summer 1988.

==Further reading==
* Amare Tekle, [https://www.jstor.org/stable/161103 &quot;The Determinants of the Foreign Policy of Revolutionary Ethiopia&quot;, ''Journal of Modern African Studies''], Vol. 27, No. 3 (Sep., 1989), pp.&amp;nbsp;479–502
* Orobola Fasehun, [https://www.jstor.org/stable/40174065 &quot;Nigeria and the Ethiopia-Somalia Conflict: A Case Study of Continuity in Nigerian Foreign Policy&quot;, ''Africa Spectrum''], '''17''' (1982), pp.&amp;nbsp;183–193

{{CIA World Factbook}}

{{Foreign relations of Ethiopia}}
{{Ethiopia topics}}
{{Africa in topic|Foreign relations of}}

[[Category:Foreign relations of Ethiopia| ]]</text>
      <sha1>j8xjvqihcfu8xzlzgwgz9ddko60zd5t</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
