  <page>
    <title>Ernest Hemingway</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9428</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943133859</id>
      <parentid>940390225</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-29T01:43:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Deisenbe</username>
        <id>10077</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Nothing in article supports this removed [[Category:American expatriates in Canada]] using [[WP:HC|HotCat]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{redirect|Hemingway}}
{{for|the fictional character Ernest Hemmingway|A Very Peculiar Practice}}
{{pp-protected|small=yes}}
{{pp-move-indef}}
{{short description|American author and journalist}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=October 2015}}
{{Infobox Writer &lt;!-- for more information see [[:Template:Infobox Writer/doc]] --&gt; &lt;!-- Please do not modify the infobox!!! --&gt;
|name        = Ernest Hemingway
|image       = ErnestHemingway.jpg
|caption     = Hemingway working on his book ''[[For Whom the Bell Tolls]]'' at the Sun Valley Lodge, [[Idaho]], in December 1939
|alt         = Dark-haired man in light colored short-sleeved shirt working on a typewriter at a table on which sits an open book
|birth_date  = {{Birth date|1899|7|21}}
|birth_place = [[Oak Park, Illinois]], U.S.
|death_date  = {{Death date and age|1961|7|2|1899|7|21}}
|death_place = [[Ketchum, Idaho]], U.S.
|awards      = {{nowrap|[[Pulitzer Prize for Fiction]] (1953) &lt;br /&gt; [[Nobel Prize in Literature]] (1954)}}
}}
'''Ernest Miller Hemingway''' (July 21, 1899&amp;nbsp;– July 2, 1961) was an American journalist, novelist, short-story writer, and sportsman. His economical and understated style—which he termed the [[iceberg theory]]—had a strong influence on 20th-century fiction, while his adventurous lifestyle and his public image brought him admiration from later generations. Hemingway produced most of his work between the mid-1920s and the mid-1950s, and he won the Nobel Prize in Literature in 1954. He published seven novels, six short-story collections, and two nonfiction works. Three of his novels, four short-story collections, and three nonfiction works were published posthumously. Many of his works are considered classics of [[American literature]].

Hemingway was raised in [[Oak Park, Illinois]]. After high school, he was a reporter for a few months for ''[[The Kansas City Star]]'' before leaving for the [[Italian Front (World War I)|Italian Front]] to enlist as an ambulance driver in World War I. In 1918, he was seriously wounded and returned home. His wartime experiences formed the basis for his novel ''[[A Farewell to Arms]]'' (1929).

In 1921, Hemingway married [[Hadley Richardson]], the first of four wives. They moved to Paris where he worked as a foreign correspondent and fell under the influence of the modernist writers and artists of the 1920s' &quot;[[Lost Generation]]&quot; expatriate community. His debut novel ''[[The Sun Also Rises]]'' was published in 1926. He divorced Richardson in 1927 and married [[Pauline Pfeiffer]]; they divorced after he returned from the [[Spanish Civil War]], where he had been a journalist. He based ''[[For Whom the Bell Tolls]]'' (1940) on his experience there. [[Martha Gellhorn]] became his third wife in 1940; they separated after he met [[Mary Welsh Hemingway|Mary Welsh]] in London during [[World War II]]. He was present with the troops as a journalist at the [[Normandy landings]] and the [[liberation of Paris]].

Hemingway went on safari to Africa shortly after the publication of ''[[The Old Man and the Sea]]'' (1952), where he was involved in two successive near-fatal plane crashes that left him in pain and ill health for much of the rest of his life. In 1959, he bought a house in [[Ketchum, Idaho]], where he ended his own life in mid-1961.

== Life ==
=== Early life ===
&lt;!-- [[File:Ernest Hemingway Birthplace (7416212780).jpg|thumb|upright|left|Ernest Hemingway Birthplace in the Frank Lloyd Wright-Prairie School of Architecture Historic District in Oak Park, now a museum]]
 --&gt;
[[File:ErnestHemingwayBabyPicture.jpg|thumb|right|upright|Hemingway was the second child and first son born to Clarence and Grace Hemingway.|alt= photograph of an infant]]
Ernest Miller Hemingway was born on July 21, 1899, in [[Birthplace of Ernest Hemingway|his maternal grandfather's house]] in [[Oak Park, Illinois]], a suburb of Chicago.&lt;ref&gt;Oliver (1999), 140&lt;/ref&gt; His father, Clarence Edmonds Hemingway, was a physician, and his mother, [[Grace Hall Hemingway]], was a musician. Both were well-educated and well-respected in Oak Park,&lt;ref name=&quot;Reynolds pp 17-18&quot; /&gt; a conservative community about which resident  [[Frank Lloyd Wright]] said, &quot;So many churches for so many good people to go to.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Meyers (1985), 4&lt;/ref&gt; For a short period after their marriage,&lt;ref&gt;Oliver (1999), 134&lt;/ref&gt; Clarence and Grace Hemingway lived with Grace's father, Ernest Hall, Hemingway's namesake. Ernest was the second of six children; his sister Marcelline preceded him in 1898, followed by Ursula in 1902, Madelaine in 1904, Carol in 1911, and Leicester in 1915.&lt;ref&gt;See Reynolds (2000), 17–18&lt;/ref&gt; Later, Ernest Hemingway would say that he disliked his name, which he &quot;associated with the naive, even foolish hero of [[Oscar Wilde]]'s play ''[[The Importance of Being Earnest]]''&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers p8&quot;&gt;Meyers (1985), 8&lt;/ref&gt; The family eventually moved into a  seven-bedroom home in a respectable neighborhood with a music studio for Grace and a medical office for Clarence.&lt;ref name=&quot;Reynolds pp 17-18&quot;&gt;Reynolds (2000), 17–18&lt;/ref&gt;

Hemingway's mother frequently performed in concerts around the village. As an adult, Hemingway professed to hate his mother, although biographer Michael S. Reynolds points out that Hemingway mirrored her energy and enthusiasm.&lt;ref name=&quot;Reynolds 2000 19&quot;&gt;Reynolds (2000), 19&lt;/ref&gt; Her insistence that he learn to play the cello became a &quot;source of conflict&quot;, but he later admitted the music lessons were useful to his writing, as is evident in the &quot;[[Counterpoint|contrapuntal]] structure&quot; of ''[[For Whom the Bell Tolls]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Meyers (1985), 3&lt;/ref&gt; The family spent summers at [[Ernest Hemingway Cottage|Windemere]] on [[Walloon Lake]], near [[Petoskey, Michigan]]. Hemingway's father taught him to hunt, fish, and camp in the woods and lakes of [[Northern Michigan]] as a young boy. These early experiences in nature instilled a passion for outdoor adventure and living in remote or isolated areas.&lt;ref name=&quot;Beegel2000, p. 63-70&quot;&gt;Beegel (2000), 63–71&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Ernest Hemingway with Family, 1905.png|thumb|left|The Hemingway family in 1905 (from the left): Marcelline, Sunny, Clarence, Grace, Ursula, and Ernest]]

From 1913 until 1917, Hemingway attended [[Oak Park and River Forest High School]]. He took part in a number of sports such as boxing, track and field, water polo, and football. He excelled in English classes,&lt;ref&gt;Mellow (1992), 21&lt;/ref&gt; and with his sister Marcelline, performed in the school orchestra for two years.&lt;ref name=&quot;Reynolds 2000 19&quot; /&gt; During his junior year he had a journalism class, structured &quot;as though the classroom were a newspaper office,&quot; with better writers submitting pieces to the school newspaper, ''The Trapeze''. Hemingway and Marcelline both submitted pieces; Hemingway's first piece, published in January 1916, was about a local performance by the [[Chicago Symphony Orchestra]].&lt;ref&gt;Griffin (1985), 25&lt;/ref&gt; He edited the ''Trapeze'' and the ''Tabula'' (the yearbook), imitating the language of sportswriters, taking the pen name Ring Lardner, Jr.—a nod to [[Ring Lardner]] of the ''[[Chicago Tribune]]'' whose byline was &quot;Line O'Type.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers p19ff&quot; /&gt;

Like [[Mark Twain]], [[Stephen Crane]], [[Theodore Dreiser]], and [[Sinclair Lewis]], Hemingway was a journalist before becoming a novelist. After leaving high school he went to work for ''[[The Kansas City Star]]'' as a cub reporter.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers p19ff&quot;&gt;Meyers (1985), 19–23&lt;/ref&gt; Although he stayed there for only six months, he relied on the ''Star''{{'}}s [[style guide]] as a foundation for his writing: &quot;Use short sentences. Use short first paragraphs. Use vigorous English. Be positive, not negative.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20140408171529/http://www.kcstar.com/hemingway/ehstarstyle.shtml &quot;Star style and rules for writing&quot;]. ''[[The Kansas City Star]]''. KansasCity.com. Retrieved November 30, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== World War I ===
[[File:Ernest Hemingway in Milan 1918 retouched 3.jpg|thumb|upright|Hemingway in uniform in Milan, 1918. He drove ambulances for two months until he was wounded.|alt= photograph of a young man dressed in a military uniform]]
Early in 1918, after applying to serve with, and being turned down by the US Army, Navy, and Marines because of poor eyesight,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2014/08/hemingway-goes-to-war/373437/|title=Hemingway Goes to War|first=Marcelline Hemingway|last=Sanford|date=September 29, 2014|website=The Atlantic}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hemingway responded to a [[Red Cross]] recruitment effort in Kansas City and signed on to become an ambulance driver in Italy.&lt;ref&gt;Mellow (1992), 48–49&lt;/ref&gt; He left New York in May and arrived in Paris as the city was under bombardment from German artillery.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers p27ff&quot;&gt;Meyers (1985), 27–31&lt;/ref&gt; By June, he was at the [[Italian Front (World War I)|Italian Front]]. It was probably around this time that he first met [[John Dos Passos]], with whom he had a rocky relationship for decades.&lt;ref&gt;Pizer (1986)&lt;/ref&gt; On his first day in [[Milan]], he was sent to the scene of a munitions factory explosion, where rescuers retrieved the shredded remains of female workers. He described the incident in his non-fiction book ''[[Death in the Afternoon]]'': &quot;I remember that after we searched quite thoroughly for the complete dead we collected fragments.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Mellow57ff&quot;&gt;Mellow (1992), 57–60&lt;/ref&gt; A few days later, he was stationed at [[Fossalta di Piave]].
[[File:Ernest_Hemingway,_1918,_American_Red_Cross_Hospital.jpg|thumb|left|Hemingway in American Red Cross Hospital, July 1918]]
On July 8, he was seriously wounded by mortar fire, having just returned from the canteen bringing chocolate and cigarettes for the men at the front line.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mellow57ff&quot; /&gt; Despite his wounds, Hemingway assisted Italian soldiers to safety, for which he received the [[Silver Medal of Military Valor|Italian Silver Medal of Bravery]].&lt;ref&gt;Mellow (1992), 61&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group=&quot;note&quot;&gt;On awarding the medal, the Italians wrote of Hemingway: &quot;Gravely wounded by numerous pieces of shrapnel from an enemy shell, with an admirable spirit of brotherhood, before taking care of himself, he rendered generous assistance to the Italian soldiers more seriously wounded by the same explosion and did not allow himself to be carried elsewhere until after they had been evacuated.&quot; See Mellow (1992), p. 61&lt;/ref&gt; He was still only 18 at the time. Hemingway later said of the incident: &quot;When you go to war as a boy you have a great illusion of immortality. Other people get killed; not you&amp;nbsp;... Then when you are badly wounded the first time you lose that illusion and you know it can happen to you.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Putnam&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.archives.gov/publications/prologue/2006/spring/hemingway.html|title=Hemingway on War and Its Aftermath|date=August 15, 2016|website=archives.gov|accessdate=July 11, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; He sustained severe shrapnel wounds to both legs, underwent an immediate operation at a distribution center, and spent five days at a field hospital before he was transferred for recuperation to the Red Cross hospital in Milan.&lt;ref name=&quot;Desnoyers p3&quot;&gt;Desnoyers, 3&lt;/ref&gt; He spent six months at the hospital, where he met and formed a strong friendship with [[Eric Dorman-Smith|&quot;Chink&quot; Dorman-Smith]] that lasted for decades and shared a room with future American [[foreign service officer]], ambassador, and author [[Henry Serrano Villard]].&lt;ref&gt;Meyers (1985), 37–42, 34&lt;/ref&gt;

While recuperating, he fell in love for the first time with [[Agnes von Kurowsky]], a Red Cross nurse seven years his senior. By the time of his release and return to the United States in January 1919, Agnes and Hemingway had decided to marry within a few months in America. However, in March, she wrote that she had become engaged to an Italian officer. Biographer Jeffrey Meyers states in his book ''Hemingway: A Biography'' that Hemingway was devastated by Agnes's rejection, and in future relationships, he followed a pattern of abandoning a wife before she abandoned him.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers p37ff&quot;&gt;Meyers (1985), 37–42&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Toronto and Chicago ===
Hemingway returned home early in 1919 to a time of readjustment. Before the age of 20, he had gained from the war a maturity that was at odds with living at home without a job and with the need for recuperation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers45ff&quot;&gt;Meyers (1985), 45–53&lt;/ref&gt; As Reynolds explains, &quot;Hemingway could not really tell his parents what he thought when he saw his bloody knee.&quot; He was not able to tell them how scared he had been &quot;in another country with surgeons who could not tell him in English if his leg was coming off or not.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Reynolds (1998), 21&lt;/ref&gt;

In September, he took a fishing and camping trip with high school friends to the back-country of Michigan's [[Upper Peninsula of Michigan|Upper Peninsula]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Putnam&quot; /&gt; The trip became the inspiration for his short story &quot;[[Big Two-Hearted River]]&quot;, in which the [[Autobiographical novel|semi-autobiographical]] character [[Nick Adams (character)|Nick Adams]] takes to the country to find solitude after returning from war.&lt;ref&gt;Mellow (1992), 101&lt;/ref&gt; A family friend offered him a job in [[Toronto]], and with nothing else to do, he accepted. Late that year he began as a freelancer and staff writer for the ''Toronto Star Weekly''. He returned to Michigan the following June&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers45ff&quot; /&gt; and then moved to [[Chicago]] in September 1920 to live with friends, while still filing stories for the ''[[Toronto Star]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers pp56-59&quot; /&gt; In Chicago, he worked as an associate editor of the monthly journal ''Cooperative Commonwealth'', where he met novelist [[Sherwood Anderson]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers pp56-59&quot;&gt;Meyers (1985), 56–58&lt;/ref&gt;

When St. Louis native [[Hadley Richardson]] came to Chicago to visit the sister of Hemingway's roommate, Hemingway became infatuated. He later claimed, &quot;I knew she was the girl I was going to marry.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kert pp83-90&quot; /&gt; Hadley, red-haired, with a &quot;nurturing instinct,&quot; was eight years older than Hemingway.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kert pp83-90&quot; /&gt; Despite the age difference, Hadley, who had grown up with an overprotective mother, seemed less mature than usual for a young woman her age.&lt;ref name=&quot;Oliver p139&quot;&gt;Oliver (1999), 139&lt;/ref&gt; Bernice Kert, author of ''The Hemingway Women'', claims Hadley was &quot;evocative&quot; of Agnes, but that Hadley had a childishness that Agnes lacked. The two corresponded for a few months and then decided to marry and travel to Europe.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kert pp83-90&quot;&gt;Kert (1983), 83–90&lt;/ref&gt; They wanted to visit Rome, but Sherwood Anderson convinced them to visit Paris instead, writing letters of introduction for the young couple.&lt;ref name=&quot;Baker 1972 pp7&quot;&gt;Baker (1972), 7&lt;/ref&gt; They were married on September 3, 1921; two months later, Hemingway was hired as foreign correspondent for the ''Toronto Star'', and the couple left for Paris. Of Hemingway's marriage to Hadley, Meyers claims: &quot;With Hadley, Hemingway achieved everything he had hoped for with Agnes: the love of a beautiful woman, a comfortable income, a life in Europe.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers pp60–62&quot;&gt;Meyers (1985), 60–62&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Paris ===
[[File:Ernest Hemingway 1923 passport photo.TIF.jpg|thumb|upright|Hemingway's 1923 passport photo. At this time, he lived in Paris with his wife [[Hadley Richardson|Hadley]], and worked as a foreign correspondent for the ''Toronto Star Weekly''.|alt=Passport photograph]]
[[Carlos Baker]], Hemingway's first biographer, believes that while Anderson suggested Paris because &quot;the monetary exchange rate&quot; made it an inexpensive place to live, more importantly it was where &quot;the most interesting people in the world&quot; lived. In Paris, Hemingway met American writer and art collector [[Gertrude Stein]], Irish novelist [[James Joyce]], American poet [[Ezra Pound]] (who &quot;could help a young writer up the rungs of a career&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Baker 1972 pp7&quot; /&gt;) and other writers.

The Hemingway of the early Paris years was a &quot;tall, handsome, muscular, broad-shouldered, brown-eyed, rosy-cheeked, square-jawed, soft-voiced young man.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers pp70–74&quot; /&gt; He and Hadley lived in a small walk-up at 74 rue du Cardinal Lemoine &lt;!-- please do not change the spelling of the street name; should be lower case --&gt; in the [[Latin Quarter]], and he worked in a rented room in a nearby building.&lt;ref name=&quot;Baker 1972 pp7&quot; /&gt;  Stein, who was the bastion of [[modernism]] in Paris,&lt;ref&gt;Mellow (1991), 8&lt;/ref&gt; became Hemingway's mentor and godmother to his son Jack;&lt;ref&gt;Meyers (1985)&lt;/ref&gt; she introduced him to the expatriate artists and writers of the [[Montparnasse Quarter]], whom she referred to as the &quot;[[Lost Generation]]&quot;—a term Hemingway popularized with the publication of ''[[The Sun Also Rises]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mellow p308&quot;&gt;Mellow (1992), 308&lt;/ref&gt; A regular at Stein's [[Salon (gathering)|salon]], Hemingway met influential painters such as [[Pablo Picasso]], [[Joan Miró]], and [[Juan Gris]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Reynolds 2000 28&quot;&gt;Reynolds (2000), 28&lt;/ref&gt; He eventually withdrew from Stein's influence and their relationship deteriorated into a literary quarrel that spanned decades.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers pp77–81&quot;&gt;Meyers (1985), 77–81&lt;/ref&gt; Ezra Pound met Hemingway by chance at [[Sylvia Beach]]'s bookshop [[Shakespeare and Company (bookstore)|Shakespeare and Company]] in 1922. The two toured Italy in 1923 and lived on the same street in 1924.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers pp70–74&quot;&gt;Meyers (1985), 70–74&lt;/ref&gt; They forged a strong friendship, and in Hemingway, Pound recognized and fostered a young talent.&lt;ref name=&quot;Reynolds 2000 28&quot; /&gt; Pound introduced Hemingway to James Joyce, with whom Hemingway frequently embarked on &quot;alcoholic sprees&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers p82&quot;&gt;Meyers (1985), 82&lt;/ref&gt;

During his first 20 months in Paris, Hemingway filed 88 stories for the ''Toronto Star'' newspaper.&lt;ref&gt;Reynolds (2000), 24&lt;/ref&gt; He covered the [[Greco-Turkish War (1919–22)|Greco-Turkish War]], where he witnessed the burning of [[Smyrna]], and wrote travel pieces such as &quot;Tuna Fishing in Spain&quot; and &quot;Trout Fishing All Across Europe: Spain Has the Best, Then Germany&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Desnoyers p5&quot;&gt;Desnoyers, 5&lt;/ref&gt; He described also the retreat of the Greek army with civilians from [[East Thrace]].

Hemingway was devastated on learning that Hadley had lost a suitcase filled with his manuscripts at the [[Paris-Gare de Lyon|Gare de Lyon]] as she was traveling to [[Geneva]] to meet him in December 1922.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers pp69–70&quot;&gt;Meyers (1985), 69–70&lt;/ref&gt; The following September, the couple returned to Toronto, where their son [[Jack Hemingway|John Hadley Nicanor]] was born on October 10, 1923. During their absence, Hemingway's first book, ''[[Three Stories and Ten Poems]]'', was published. Two of the stories it contained were all that remained after the loss of the suitcase, and the third had been written early the previous year in Italy. Within months a second volume, ''in our time'' (without capitals), was published. The small volume included six [[Vignette (literature)|vignettes]] and a dozen stories Hemingway had written the previous summer during his first visit to Spain, where he discovered the thrill of the ''[[Bullfighting|corrida]]''. He missed Paris, considered Toronto boring, and wanted to return to the life of a writer, rather than live the life of a journalist.&lt;ref name=&quot;Baker 1972 15–18&quot;&gt;Baker (1972), 15–18&lt;/ref&gt;

Hemingway, Hadley and their son (nicknamed Bumby) returned to Paris in January 1924 and moved into a new apartment on the rue Notre-Dame des Champs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Baker 1972 15–18&quot; /&gt; Hemingway helped [[Ford Madox Ford]] edit ''[[The Transatlantic Review]]'', which published works by Pound, [[John Dos Passos]], Baroness [[Elsa von Freytag-Loringhoven]], and Stein, as well as some of Hemingway's own early stories such as &quot;[[Indian Camp]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers p126&quot;&gt;Meyers (1985), 126&lt;/ref&gt; When ''[[In Our Time (short story collection)|In Our Time]]'' was published in 1925, the dust jacket bore comments from Ford.&lt;ref&gt;Baker (1972), 34&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers p127&quot;&gt;Meyers (1985), 127&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;Indian Camp&quot; received considerable praise; Ford saw it as an important early story by a young writer,&lt;ref&gt;Mellow (1992), 236&lt;/ref&gt; and critics in the United States praised Hemingway for reinvigorating the short story genre with his crisp style and use of declarative sentences.&lt;ref&gt;Mellow (1992), 314&lt;/ref&gt; Six months earlier, Hemingway had met [[F. Scott Fitzgerald]], and the pair formed a friendship of &quot;admiration and hostility&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers pp159–160&quot;&gt;Meyers (1985), 159–160&lt;/ref&gt; Fitzgerald had published ''[[The Great Gatsby]]'' the same year: Hemingway read it, liked it, and decided his next work had to be a novel.&lt;ref name=&quot;Baker pp 30-34&quot;&gt;Baker (1972), 30–34&lt;/ref&gt;

{{multiple image
 | align     = left
 | direction = horizontal
 | header    =
 | header_align = left/right/center
 | header_background =
 | footer
 | footer_align = left/right/center
 | footer_background =
 | width     =
 | image1    = Ernest Hadley and Bumby Hemingway.jpg
 | width1    = 180
 | caption1  = Ernest, Hadley, and their son [[Jack Hemingway|Jack]] (&quot;Bumby&quot;) in [[Schruns]], Austria, 1926, just months before they separated|alt=photograph of woman, man, child
 | alt1      =
 | image2    = HemingwayLoeb.jpg
 | width2    = 195
 | caption2  = Ernest Hemingway with Lady Duff Twysden, Hadley, and friends, during the July 1925 trip to Spain that inspired ''[[The Sun Also Rises]]''
 | alt2      = photograph of three men and two women sitting at a sidewalk table
}}

With his wife [[Hadley Richardson|Hadley]], Hemingway first visited the Festival of [[San Fermín]] in [[Pamplona]], Spain, in 1923, where he became fascinated by [[bullfighting]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers pp117-119&quot;&gt;Meyers (1985), 117–119&lt;/ref&gt; It is at this time that he began to be referred to as &quot;Papa&quot;, even by much older friends. Hadley would much later recall that Hemingway had his own nicknames for everyone, and that he often did things for his friends; she suggested that he liked to be looked up to. She didn't remember precisely how the nickname came into being; however, it certainly stuck.&lt;ref name=&quot;MHPapa&quot;&gt;{{cite news |first=Mary |last=Harrington |title=They Call Him Papa |date=December 28, 1946 |newspaper=New York Post Week-End Magazine |page=3}} Reprinted in {{cite book |title=Conversations with Ernest Hemingway |series=Literary conversations series | issn=1555-7065 |editor-first=Matthew Joseph |editor-last=Bruccoli |publisher=Univ. Press of Mississippi |year=1986 |isbn=978-0-87805-273-8 |pages=42–45 |url=https://books.google.com/books?vid=AYQdKWlNE28C&amp;lpg=PA42&amp;pg=PA42#v=onepage |access-date=April 14, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;HRPapa&quot;&gt;{{cite interview |last=Richardson |first=Hadley |subject-link=Hadley Richardson |title=How Hemingway became Papa |date=n.d. |type=Audio segment (4&amp;nbsp;m 37s) from interview |interviewer=Alice Hunt Sokoloff |url=http://www.thehemingwayproject.com/wp-content/uploads/2010/06/hadley-how-hem-became-papa.mp3 |format=MP3 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160418212602/http://www.thehemingwayproject.com/wp-content/uploads/2010/06/hadley-how-hem-became-papa.mp3 |archivedate=2016-04-18 }} Published at {{cite web |url=http://www.thehemingwayproject.com/how-did-hemingway-become-papa/ |first=Allie |last=Baker |title=How did Hemingway become Papa? |work=The Hemingway Project |date=June 28, 2010 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160407105237/http://www.thehemingwayproject.com/how-did-hemingway-become-papa/ |archive-date=2016-04-07 |url-status=live |quote=In this clip, Alice Sokoloff asks Hadley if she remembers how the name 'Papa' began, which was sometime during their years in Paris. |access-date=April 14, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!-- PLS convert per citevar --&gt; The Hemingways returned to Pamplona in 1924 and a third time in June 1925; that year they brought with them a group of American and British expatriates: Hemingway's [[Michigan]] boyhood friend Bill Smith, Donald Ogden Stewart, [[Duff Twysden|Lady Duff Twysden]] (recently divorced), her lover Pat Guthrie, and [[Harold Loeb]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Nagel89ff&quot;&gt;Nagel (1996), 89&lt;/ref&gt; A few days after the fiesta ended, on his birthday (July 21), he began to write the draft of what would become ''[[The Sun Also Rises]]'', finishing eight weeks later.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers p189&quot;&gt;Meyers (1985), 189&lt;/ref&gt;  A few months later, in December 1925, the Hemingways left to spend the winter in [[Schruns]], Austria, where Hemingway began revising the manuscript extensively. [[Pauline Pfeiffer]] joined them in January and against Hadley's advice, urged Hemingway to sign a contract with [[Charles Scribner's Sons|Scribner's]]. He left Austria for a quick trip to New York to meet with the publishers, and on his return, during a stop in Paris, began an affair with Pfeiffer, before returning to Schruns to finish the revisions in March.&lt;ref&gt;Reynolds (1989), vi–vii&lt;/ref&gt;  The manuscript arrived in New York in April; he corrected the final proof in Paris in August 1926, and Scribner's published the novel in October.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers p189&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Mellow (1992), 328&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Baker p44&quot;&gt;Baker (1972), 44&lt;/ref&gt;

''The Sun Also Rises'' epitomized the post-war expatriate generation,&lt;ref name=&quot;Mellow p302&quot;&gt;Mellow (1992), 302&lt;/ref&gt; received good reviews, and is &quot;recognized as Hemingway's greatest work&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers p192&quot;&gt;Meyers (1985), 192&lt;/ref&gt; Hemingway himself later wrote to his editor [[Max Perkins]] that the &quot;point of the book&quot; was not so much about a generation being lost, but that &quot;the earth abideth forever&quot;; he believed the characters in ''The Sun Also Rises'' may have been &quot;battered&quot; but were not lost.&lt;ref name=&quot;Baker p82&quot;&gt;Baker (1972), 82&lt;/ref&gt;

Hemingway's marriage to Hadley deteriorated as he was working on ''The Sun Also Rises''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Baker p44&quot; /&gt; In early 1926, Hadley became aware of his affair with Pfeiffer, who came to Pamplona with them that July.&lt;ref name=&quot;Baker p43&quot;&gt;Baker (1972), 43&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Mellow (1992), 333&lt;/ref&gt; On their return to Paris, Hadley asked for a separation; in November she formally requested a divorce. They split their possessions while Hadley accepted Hemingway's offer of the proceeds from ''The Sun Also Rises''.&lt;ref&gt;Mellow (1992), 338–340&lt;/ref&gt; The couple were divorced in January 1927, and Hemingway married Pfeiffer in May.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers p172&quot;&gt;Meyers (1985), 172&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Ernest and Pauline Hemingway, Paris, 1927.jpg|thumb|Ernest and [[Pauline Pfeiffer|Pauline]] Hemingway in Paris, 1927]]

Pfeiffer, who was from a wealthy Catholic [[Arkansas]] family, had moved to  Paris to work for ''[[Vogue (magazine)|Vogue]]'' magazine. Before their marriage, Hemingway converted to Catholicism.&lt;ref&gt;Meyers (1985), 173, 184&lt;/ref&gt; They honeymooned in [[Le Grau-du-Roi]], where he contracted [[anthrax]], and he planned his next collection of short stories,&lt;ref&gt;Mellow (1992), 348–353&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Men Without Women (short story collection)|Men Without Women]]'', which was published in October 1927,&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers p195&quot;&gt;Meyers (1985), 195&lt;/ref&gt; and included his [[boxing]] story &quot;[[Fifty Grand]]&quot;. ''[[Cosmopolitan (magazine)|Cosmopolitan]]'' magazine editor-in-chief [[Ray Long]] praised &quot;Fifty Grand&quot;, calling it, &quot;one of the best short stories that ever came to my hands&amp;nbsp;... the best prize-fight story I ever read&amp;nbsp;... a remarkable piece of realism.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Long (1932), 2–3&lt;/ref&gt;

By the end of the year Pauline, who was pregnant, wanted to move back to America. John Dos Passos recommended [[Key West]], and they left Paris in March 1928. Hemingway suffered a severe injury in their Paris bathroom when he pulled a skylight down on his head thinking he was pulling on a toilet chain. This left him with a prominent forehead scar, which he carried for the rest of his life. When Hemingway was asked about the scar, he was reluctant to answer.&lt;ref&gt;Robinson (2005)&lt;/ref&gt; After his departure from Paris, Hemingway &quot;never again lived in a big city&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers p204&quot;&gt;Meyers (1985), 204&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Key West and the Caribbean ===
[[File:Hemingwayhouse.jpg|thumb|The [[Ernest Hemingway House|Hemingway House]] in Key West, Florida, where he lived between 1931 and 1939 and where he wrote ''[[To Have and Have Not]]''|alt=photograph of a house]]

Hemingway and Pauline traveled to Kansas City, where their son [[Patrick Hemingway|Patrick]] was born on June 28, 1928. Pauline had a difficult delivery; Hemingway fictionalized a version of the event as a part of ''[[A Farewell to Arms]]''. After Patrick's birth, Pauline and Hemingway traveled to Wyoming, Massachusetts, and New York.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers p208&quot;&gt;Meyers (1985), 208&lt;/ref&gt; In the winter, he was in New York with Bumby, about to board a train to Florida, when he received a cable telling him that his father had killed himself.&lt;ref group=note&gt;Clarence Hemingway used his father's Civil War pistol to shoot himself. See Meyers (1985), 2&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Mellow (1992), 367&lt;/ref&gt; Hemingway was devastated, having earlier written to his father telling him not to worry about financial difficulties; the letter arrived minutes after the suicide. He realized how Hadley must have felt after her own father's suicide in 1903, and he commented, &quot;I'll probably go the same way.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;qtd. in Meyers (1985), 210&lt;/ref&gt;

Upon his return to Key West in December, Hemingway worked on the draft of ''A Farewell to Arms'' before leaving for France in January. He had finished it in August but delayed the revision. The serialization in ''[[Scribner's Magazine]]'' was scheduled to begin in May, but as late as April, Hemingway was still working on the ending, which he may have rewritten as many as seventeen times. The completed novel was published on September 27.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers p215&quot;&gt;Meyers (1985), 215&lt;/ref&gt; Biographer James Mellow believes ''A Farewell to Arms'' established Hemingway's stature as a major American writer and displayed a level of complexity not apparent in ''The Sun Also Rises''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mellow p378&quot;&gt;Mellow (1992), 378&lt;/ref&gt; In Spain in mid-1929, Hemingway researched his next work, ''[[Death in the Afternoon]]''. He wanted to write a comprehensive [[treatise]] on bullfighting, explaining the ''toreros'' and ''corridas'' complete with glossaries and appendices, because he believed bullfighting was &quot;of great tragic interest, being literally of life and death.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Baker (1972), 144–145&lt;/ref&gt;

During the early 1930s, Hemingway spent his winters in Key West and summers in Wyoming, where he found &quot;the most beautiful country he had seen in the American West&quot; and hunted deer, elk, and grizzly bear.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers p222&quot;&gt;Meyers (1985), 222&lt;/ref&gt; He was joined there by Dos Passos and in November 1930, after bringing Dos Passos to the train station in [[Billings, Montana]], Hemingway broke his arm in a car accident. The surgeon tended the compound spiral fracture and bound the bone with kangaroo tendon. Hemingway was hospitalized for seven weeks, with Pauline tending to him; the nerves in his writing hand took as long as a year to heal, during which time he suffered intense pain.&lt;ref&gt;Reynolds (2000), 31&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Hemingway and Marlins.jpg|thumb|left|Ernest, Pauline, Bumby, Patrick, and Gregory Hemingway pose with [[marlin]]s after a fishing trip to [[Bimini]] in 1935|alt=photograph of a man, a woman, and three boys]]

His third son, [[Gregory Hemingway|Gregory Hancock Hemingway]], was born a year later on November 12, 1931, in Kansas City.&lt;ref name=&quot;Oliver144&quot;&gt;Oliver (1999), 144&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group=note&gt;Gregory Hemingway would undergo [[sex reassignment surgery]] in the mid-1990s and thereafter was known as Gloria Hemingway. See [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/entertainment/3160646.stm &quot;Hemingway legacy feud 'resolved'&quot;]. BBC News. October 3, 2003. Retrieved April 26, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Pauline's uncle bought the couple a [[Ernest Hemingway House|house]] in Key West with a carriage house, the second floor of which was converted into a writing studio.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers pp222-227&quot;&gt;Meyers (1985), 222–227&lt;/ref&gt; While in Key West, Hemingway frequented the local bar [[Sloppy Joe's (bar)|Sloppy Joe's]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Mellow p402&quot;&gt;Mellow (1992), 402&lt;/ref&gt; He invited friends—including [[Waldo Peirce]], Dos Passos, and [[Max Perkins]]&lt;ref&gt;Mellow (1992), 376–377&lt;/ref&gt;—to join him on fishing trips and on an all-male expedition to the [[Dry Tortugas]]. Meanwhile, he continued to travel to Europe and to Cuba, and—although in 1933 he wrote of Key West, &quot;We have a fine house here, and kids are all well&quot;—Mellow believes he &quot;was plainly restless&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mellow p424&quot;&gt;Mellow (1992), 424&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1933, Hemingway and Pauline went on safari to East Africa. The 10-week trip provided material for ''[[Green Hills of Africa]]'', as well as for the short stories &quot;[[The Snows of Kilimanjaro (short story)|The Snows of Kilimanjaro]]&quot; and &quot;[[The Short Happy Life of Francis Macomber]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Desnoyers p9&quot;&gt;Desnoyers, 9&lt;/ref&gt; The couple visited [[Mombasa]], [[Nairobi]], and [[Machakos]] in Kenya; then moved on to [[Tanganyika Territory]], where they hunted in the [[Serengeti]], around [[Lake Manyara]], and west and southeast of present-day [[Tarangire National Park]]. Their guide was the noted &quot;white hunter&quot; [[Philip Percival]] who had guided [[Theodore Roosevelt]] on his 1909 safari. During these travels, Hemingway contracted [[amoebic dysentery]] that caused a prolapsed intestine, and he was evacuated by plane to Nairobi, an experience reflected in &quot;The Snows of Kilimanjaro&quot;. On Hemingway's return to Key West in early 1934, he began work on ''Green Hills of Africa'', which he published in 1935 to mixed reviews.&lt;ref&gt;Mellow (1992), 337–340&lt;/ref&gt;

Hemingway bought a boat in 1934, named it the ''[[Pilar (Ernest Hemingway's boat)|Pilar]]'', and began sailing the [[Caribbean]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers p280&quot;&gt;Meyers (1985), 280&lt;/ref&gt; In 1935 he first arrived at [[Bimini]], where he spent a considerable amount of time.&lt;ref name=&quot;Desnoyers p9&quot; /&gt; During this period he also worked on ''[[To Have and Have Not]]'', published in 1937 while he was in Spain, the only novel he wrote during the 1930s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers p292&quot;&gt;Meyers (1985), 292&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Spanish Civil War ===
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-84600-0001, Ivens und Hemingway bei Ludwig Renn, Chef der XI. Internationalen Brigaden.jpg|thumb|Hemingway (center) with Dutch filmmaker [[Joris Ivens]] and German writer [[Ludwig Renn]] (serving as an International Brigades officer) in Spain during Spanish Civil War, 1937|alt=photograph of three men]]

In 1937, Hemingway agreed to report on the [[Spanish Civil War]] for the [[North American Newspaper Alliance]] (NANA),&lt;ref name=&quot;Mellow p488&quot;&gt;Mellow (1992), 488&lt;/ref&gt; arriving in Spain in March with Dutch filmmaker [[Joris Ivens]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Koch p87&quot;&gt;Koch (2005), 87&lt;/ref&gt; Ivens was filming ''[[The Spanish Earth]]'', a propaganda film in support of the [[Second Spanish Republic|Republican]] side. He wanted Hemingway to replace [[John Dos Passos]] as screenwriter, since Dos Passos had left the project when his friend [[José Robles]] was arrested and later executed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers p311&quot;&gt;Meyers (1985), 311&lt;/ref&gt; The incident changed Dos Passos' initially positive opinion of the leftist republicans, creating a rift between him and Hemingway, who later spread a rumor that Dos Passos left Spain out of cowardice.&lt;ref name=&quot;Koch p164&quot;&gt;Koch (2005), 164&lt;/ref&gt; He also rubbed shoulders with US volunteers fighting on the Republican side, including the ace fighter pilot [[Frank Glasgow Tinker|Frank G. Tinker]] and [[Robert Hale Merriman]], leader of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://theclaptonpress.com/some-still-live-by-f-g-tinker/|title= Some Still Live by F. G. Tinker, Funk &amp; Wagnalls Co, 1938, republished by The Clapton Press, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Journalist and writer [[Martha Gellhorn]], whom Hemingway had met in Key West the previous Christmas (1936), joined him in Spain. Like Hadley, Martha was a St. Louis native, and like Pauline, she had worked for ''Vogue'' in Paris. Of Martha, Kert explains, &quot;she never catered to him the way other women did&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kert pp287&quot;&gt;Kert (1983), 287–295&lt;/ref&gt; Late in 1937, while in Madrid with Martha, Hemingway wrote his only play, ''[[The Fifth Column and the First Forty-Nine Stories|The Fifth Column]]'', as [[Siege of Madrid|the city was being bombarded]] by Francoist forces.&lt;ref name=&quot;Koch p134&quot;&gt;Koch (2005), 134&lt;/ref&gt; He returned to Key West for a few months, then back to Spain twice in 1938, where he was present at the [[Battle of the Ebro]], the last republican stand, and he was among the British and American journalists who were some of the last to leave the battle as they crossed the river.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers p321&quot;&gt;Meyers (1985), 321&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Thomas p833&quot;&gt;Thomas (2001), 833&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Cuba ===
In early 1939, Hemingway crossed to Cuba in his boat to live in the [[Hotel Ambos Mundos]] in Havana. This was the separation phase of a slow and painful split from Pauline, which began when Hemingway met [[Martha Gellhorn]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers p326&quot;&gt;Meyers (1985), 326&lt;/ref&gt; Martha soon joined him in Cuba, and they rented &quot;[[Finca Vigía]]&quot; (&quot;Lookout Farm&quot;), a {{convert|15|acre|m2|adj=on}} property {{convert|15|mi|km}} from Havana. Pauline and the children left Hemingway that summer, after the family was reunited during a visit to Wyoming; when his divorce from Pauline was finalized, he and Martha were married on November 20, 1940 in [[Cheyenne, Wyoming]].&lt;ref&gt;Lynn (1987), 479&lt;/ref&gt;

{{multiple image
 | align     = right
 | direction = horizontal
 | header    =
 | header_align = left/right/center
 | header_background =
 | footer
 | footer_align = left/right/center
 | footer_background =
 | width     =
 | image1    = Gellhorn Hemingway 1941.jpg
 | width1    = 215
 | caption1  =Hemingway with his third wife [[Martha Gellhorn]], posing with General [[Yu Hanmou]], Chungking, China, 1941
 | alt1      =
 | image2    = Ernest Hemingway with sons Patrick and Gregory with kittens in Finca Vigia, Cuba.jpg
 | width2    = 175
 | caption2  = Hemingway and sons [[Patrick Hemingway|Patrick]] (left) and [[Gregory Hemingway|Gregory]], with three cats at ''[[Finca Vigía]]'' c. mid-1942
 | alt2      =
}}

Hemingway moved his primary summer residence to [[Ketchum, Idaho]], just outside the newly built resort of [[Sun Valley, Idaho|Sun Valley]], and moved his winter residence to Cuba.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers p342&quot;&gt;Meyers (1985), 342&lt;/ref&gt; He had been disgusted when a Parisian friend allowed his cats to eat from the table, but he became enamored of cats in Cuba and kept dozens of them on the property.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers p353&quot;&gt;Meyers (1985), 353&lt;/ref&gt;

Gellhorn inspired him to write his most famous novel ''[[For Whom the Bell Tolls]]'', which he started in March 1939 and finished in July 1940. It was published in October 1940.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers p334&quot;&gt;Meyers (1985), 334&lt;/ref&gt; His pattern was to move around while working on a manuscript, and he wrote ''For Whom the Bell Tolls'' in Cuba, Wyoming, and Sun Valley.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers p326&quot; /&gt; It became a Book-of-the-Month Club choice, sold half a million copies within months, was nominated for a Pulitzer Prize, and &quot;triumphantly re-established Hemingway's literary reputation&quot; in the words of Meyers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers pp334–339&quot;&gt;Meyers (1985), 334–338&lt;/ref&gt;

In January 1941, Martha was sent to China on assignment for ''[[Collier's]]'' magazine.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers pp=356–361&quot; /&gt; Hemingway went with her, sending in dispatches for the newspaper ''[[PM (newspaper)|PM]]'', but in general he disliked China.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers pp=356–361&quot;&gt;Meyers (1985), 356–361&lt;/ref&gt; A 2009 book suggests during that period he may have been recruited to work for Soviet intelligence agents under the name &quot;Agent Argo&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/books/2009/jul/09/hemingway-failed-kgb-spy|title=Hemingway revealed as failed KGB spy|first=John|last=Dugdale|date=July 9, 2009|publisher=|accessdate=July 11, 2017|newspaper=The Guardian}}&lt;/ref&gt; They returned to Cuba before the [[declaration of war by the United States]] that December, when he convinced the Cuban government to help him refit the ''Pilar'', which he intended to use to ambush German submarines off the coast of Cuba.&lt;ref name=&quot;Putnam&quot; /&gt;

=== World War II ===
[[File:Hemlatham-1.jpg|thumb|upright|Hemingway with [[Charles T. Lanham|Col. Charles 'Buck' Lanham]] in Germany, 1944, during the fighting in Hürtgenwald, after which he became ill with pneumonia.|alt=photograph of two men]]

Hemingway was in Europe from May 1944 to March 1945. When he arrived in London, he met ''[[Time (magazine)|Time]]'' magazine correspondent [[Mary Welsh Hemingway|Mary Welsh]], with whom he became infatuated. Martha had been forced to cross the Atlantic in a ship filled with explosives because Hemingway refused to help her get a press pass on a plane, and she arrived in London to find him hospitalized with a concussion from a car accident. She was unsympathetic to his plight; she accused him of being a bully and told him that she was &quot;through, absolutely finished&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kert pp393-398&quot;&gt;Kert (1983), 393–398&lt;/ref&gt; The last time that Hemingway saw Martha was in March 1945 as he was preparing to return to Cuba,&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers p416&quot;&gt;Meyers (1985), 416&lt;/ref&gt; and their divorce was finalized later that year.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kert pp393-398&quot; /&gt; Meanwhile, he had asked Mary Welsh to marry him on their third meeting.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kert pp393-398&quot; /&gt;

Hemingway accompanied the troops to the [[Normandy Landings]] wearing a large head bandage, according to Meyers, but he was considered &quot;precious cargo&quot; and not allowed ashore.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers pp400&quot;&gt;Meyers (1985), 400&lt;/ref&gt; The [[LCVP (United States)|landing craft]] came within sight of [[Omaha Beach]] before coming under enemy fire and turning back. Hemingway later wrote in ''[[Collier's]]'' that he could see &quot;the first, second, third, fourth and fifth waves of [landing troops] lay where they had fallen, looking like so many heavily laden bundles on the flat pebbly stretch between the sea and first cover&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Reynolds (1999), 96–98&lt;/ref&gt; Mellow explains that, on that first day, none of the correspondents were allowed to land and Hemingway was returned to the ''[[USS Dorothea L. Dix (AP-67)|Dorothea Dix]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Mellow (1992), 533&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!-- biographer Kenneth Lynn claims that Hemingway  fabricated accounts that he went ashore during the landings.&lt;ref&gt;Lynn (1987), 510&lt;/ref&gt; --&gt;

Late in July, he attached himself to &quot;the [[22nd Infantry Regiment (United States)|22nd Infantry Regiment]] commanded by Col. [[Charles T. Lanham|Charles 'Buck' Lanham]], as it drove toward Paris&quot;, and Hemingway became de facto leader to a small band of village militia in [[Rambouillet]] outside of Paris.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers pp398-405&quot;&gt;Meyers (1985), 398–405&lt;/ref&gt; [[Paul Fussell]] remarks: &quot;Hemingway got into considerable trouble playing infantry captain to a group of Resistance people that he gathered because a correspondent is not supposed to lead troops, even if he does it well.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Putnam&quot; /&gt; This was in fact in contravention of the [[Geneva Conventions|Geneva Convention]],  and Hemingway was brought up on formal charges; he said that he &quot;beat the rap&quot; by claiming that he only offered advice.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lynn 1987 518–519&quot;&gt;Lynn (1987), 518–519&lt;/ref&gt;

On August 25, he was present at the [[liberation of Paris]] as a journalist; contrary to the Hemingway legend, he was not the first into the city, nor did he liberate the [[Hôtel Ritz Paris|Ritz]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers p408ff&quot;&gt;Meyers (1985) 408–411&lt;/ref&gt; In Paris, he visited Sylvia Beach and Pablo Picasso with Mary Welsh, who joined him there; in a spirit of happiness, he forgave Gertrude Stein.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mellow p535ff&quot;&gt;Mellow (1992), 535–540&lt;/ref&gt; Later that year, he observed heavy fighting in the [[Battle of Hürtgen Forest]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers p408ff&quot; /&gt; On December 17, 1944, he had himself driven to Luxembourg in spite of illness to cover [[The Battle of the Bulge]]. As soon as he arrived, however, Lanham handed him to the doctors, who hospitalized him with pneumonia; he recovered a week later, but most of the fighting was over.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lynn 1987 518–519&quot; /&gt;

In 1947, Hemingway was awarded a [[Bronze Star]] for his bravery during World War II. He was recognized for having been &quot;under fire in combat areas in order to obtain an accurate picture of conditions&quot;, with the commendation that &quot;through his talent of expression, Mr. Hemingway enabled readers to obtain a vivid picture of the difficulties and triumphs of the front-line soldier and his organization in combat&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Putnam&quot; /&gt;

=== Cuba and the Nobel Prize ===
Hemingway said he &quot;was out of business as a writer&quot; from 1942 to 1945 during his residence in Cuba.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mellow p552&quot;&gt;qtd. in Mellow (1992), 552&lt;/ref&gt; In 1946 he married Mary, who had an [[ectopic pregnancy]] five months later. The Hemingway family suffered a series of accidents and health problems in the years following the war: in a 1945 car accident, he &quot;smashed his knee&quot; and sustained another &quot;deep wound on his forehead&quot;; Mary broke first her right ankle and then her left in successive skiing accidents. A 1947 car accident left Patrick with a head wound and severely ill.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers pp420–421&quot;&gt;Meyers (1985), 420–421&lt;/ref&gt; Hemingway sank into depression as his literary friends began to die: in 1939 [[William Butler Yeats]] and [[Ford Madox Ford]]; in 1940 Scott Fitzgerald; in 1941 Sherwood Anderson and James Joyce; in 1946 Gertrude Stein; and the following year in 1947, Max Perkins, Hemingway's long-time Scribner's editor and friend.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mellow pp548–550&quot;&gt;Mellow (1992) 548–550&lt;/ref&gt; During this period, he suffered from severe headaches, high blood pressure, weight problems, and eventually diabetes—much of which was the result of previous accidents and many years of heavy drinking.&lt;ref name=&quot;Desnoyers p12&quot;&gt;Desnoyers, 12&lt;/ref&gt; Nonetheless, in January 1946, he began work on ''[[The Garden of Eden (novel)|The Garden of Eden]]'', finishing 800 pages by June.&lt;ref&gt;Meyers (1985), 436&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group=note&gt;''The Garden of Eden'' was published posthumously in 1986. See Meyers (1985), 436&lt;/ref&gt; During the post-war years, he also began work on a trilogy tentatively titled &quot;The Land&quot;, &quot;The Sea&quot; and &quot;The Air&quot;, which he wanted to combine in one novel titled ''The Sea Book''.  However, both projects stalled, and Mellow says that Hemingway's inability to continue was &quot;a symptom of his troubles&quot; during these years.&lt;ref&gt;Mellow (1992), 552&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group=note&gt;The manuscript for ''The Sea Book'' was published posthumously as ''[[Islands in the Stream (novel)|Islands in the Stream]]'' in 1970. See Mellow (1992), 552&lt;/ref&gt;

{{multiple image
 | align     = right
 | direction = horizontal
 | header    =
 | header_align = left/right/center
 | header_background =
 | footer
 | footer_align = left/right/center
 | footer_background =
 | width     =
 | image1    = Ernest and Mary Hemingway on safari, 1953-54.jpg
 | width1    = 190
 | caption1  =Hemingway and Mary in Africa before the two plane accidents
 | alt1      =
 | image2    = Ernest Hemingway Kenya safari 1954.png
 | width2    = 200
 | caption2  = Hemingway at a fishing camp in 1954. His hand and arms are burned from a recent bushfire; his hair was burned in the recent plane crashes.
 | alt2      =
}}
&lt;!-- [File:Ernest and Mary Hemingway on safari, 1953-54.jpg|thumb|left|Hemingway and Mary in Africa before his plane accidents]] --&gt;
In 1948, Hemingway and Mary traveled to Europe, staying in [[Venice]] for several months. While there, Hemingway fell in love with the then 19-year-old [[Adriana Ivancich]]. The platonic love affair inspired the novel ''[[Across the River and into the Trees]]'', written in Cuba during a time of strife with Mary, and published in 1950 to negative reviews.&lt;ref&gt;Meyers (1985), 440–452&lt;/ref&gt; The following year, furious at the critical reception of ''Across the River and Into the Trees'', he wrote the draft of ''[[The Old Man and the Sea]]'' in eight weeks, saying that it was &quot;the best I can write ever for all of my life&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Desnoyers p12&quot; /&gt; ''The Old Man and the Sea'' became a book-of-the-month selection, made Hemingway an international celebrity, and won the [[Pulitzer Prize]] in May 1952, a month before he left for his second trip to Africa.&lt;ref name=&quot;Desnoyers p13&quot;&gt;Desnoyers, 13&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers p489&quot;&gt;Meyers (1985), 489&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- [[File:Ernest Hemingway Kenya safari 1954.png|thumb|Hemingway at a fishing camp in 1954. His hand and arms are burned from a recent bushfire; his hair was burned in the recent plane crashes.]] --&gt;
In 1954, while in Africa, Hemingway was almost fatally injured in two successive plane crashes. He chartered a sightseeing flight over the [[Belgian Congo]] as a Christmas present to Mary. On their way to photograph [[Murchison Falls]] from the air, the plane struck an abandoned utility pole and &quot;crash landed in heavy brush&quot;. Hemingway's injuries included a head wound, while Mary broke two ribs.&lt;ref&gt;Baker (1972), 331–333&lt;/ref&gt; The next day, attempting to reach medical care in [[Entebbe]], they boarded a second plane that exploded at take-off, with Hemingway suffering burns and another concussion, this one serious enough to cause leaking of [[cerebrospinal fluid|cerebral fluid]].&lt;ref&gt;Mellow (1992), 586&lt;/ref&gt; They eventually arrived in Entebbe to find reporters covering the story of Hemingway's death. He briefed the reporters and spent the next few weeks recuperating and reading his erroneous obituaries.&lt;ref&gt;Mellow (1992), 587&lt;/ref&gt; Despite his injuries, Hemingway accompanied Patrick and his wife on a planned fishing expedition in February, but pain caused him to be irascible and difficult to get along with.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mellow 1992 588&quot;&gt;Mellow (1992), 588&lt;/ref&gt; When a bushfire broke out, he was again injured, sustaining second degree burns on his legs, front torso, lips, left hand and right forearm.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers pp505-507&quot;&gt;Meyers (1985), 505–507&lt;/ref&gt; Months later in [[Venice]], Mary reported to friends the full extent of Hemingway's injuries: two cracked [[Intervertebral disc|discs]], a kidney and liver rupture, a [[dislocated shoulder]] and a broken skull.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mellow 1992 588&quot; /&gt; The accidents may have precipitated the physical deterioration that was to follow. After the plane crashes, Hemingway, who had been &quot;a thinly controlled alcoholic throughout much of his life, drank more heavily than usual to combat the pain of his injuries.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Beegel (1996), 273&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Ernest Hemingway 1950.jpg|thumb|left|Hemingway in the cabin of his boat ''Pilar'', off the coast of Cuba, c. 1950|alt=photograph of a man]]

In October 1954, Hemingway received the [[Nobel Prize in Literature]]. He modestly told the press that [[Carl Sandburg]], [[Isak Dinesen]] and [[Bernard Berenson]] deserved the prize,&lt;ref&gt;Lynn (1987), 574&lt;/ref&gt; but he gladly accepted the prize money.&lt;ref name=&quot;Baker p338&quot;&gt;Baker (1972), 38&lt;/ref&gt; Mellow says Hemingway &quot;had coveted the Nobel Prize&quot;, but when he won it, months after his plane accidents and the ensuing worldwide press coverage, &quot;there must have been a lingering suspicion in Hemingway's mind that his obituary notices had played a part in the academy's decision.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Mellow pp588–589&quot;&gt;Mellow (1992), 588–589&lt;/ref&gt; Because he was suffering pain from the African accidents, he decided against traveling to [[Stockholm]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers p509&quot;&gt;Meyers (1985), 509&lt;/ref&gt; Instead he sent a speech to be read, defining the writer's life: {{quote|Writing, at its best, is a lonely life. Organizations for writers palliate the writer's loneliness but I doubt if they improve his writing. He grows in public stature as he sheds his loneliness and often his work deteriorates. For he does his work alone and if he is a good enough writer he must face eternity, or the lack of it, each day.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/literature/laureates/1954/hemingway-speech.html |title = Ernest Hemingway The Nobel Prize in Literature 1954 Banquet Speech |publisher = The Nobel Foundation |accessdate = December 10, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group = note&gt;The full speech is available at [http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/literature/laureates/1954/hemingway-speech.html The Nobel Foundation]&lt;/ref&gt;}}

From the end of the year in 1955 to early 1956, Hemingway was bedridden.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers p512&quot;&gt;Meyers (1985), 512&lt;/ref&gt; He was told to stop drinking to mitigate liver damage, advice he initially followed but then disregarded.&lt;ref&gt;Reynolds (2000), 291–293&lt;/ref&gt; In October 1956, he returned to Europe and met [[Basque people|Basque]] writer [[Pio Baroja]], who was seriously ill and died weeks later. During the trip, Hemingway became sick again and was treated for &quot;high blood pressure, liver disease, and arteriosclerosis&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers p512&quot; /&gt;

{{Listen|filename=HemingwayNobelSpeechIntro.ogg|title= 1954 Nobel Acceptance Speech | pos = right| description=Opening statement of Nobel Prize acceptance speech, 1954 [recorded privately by Hemingway after the fact].|format=[[Ogg]]}}
In November 1956, while staying in Paris, he was reminded of trunks he had stored in the Ritz Hotel in 1928 and never retrieved. Upon re-claiming and opening the trunks, Hemingway discovered they were filled with notebooks and writing from his Paris years. Excited about the discovery, when he returned to Cuba in early 1957, he began to shape the recovered work into his memoir ''[[A Moveable Feast]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers p533&quot;&gt;Meyers (1985), 533&lt;/ref&gt; By 1959 he ended a period of intense activity: he finished ''A Moveable Feast'' (scheduled to be released the following year); brought ''True at First Light'' to 200,000 words; added chapters to ''The Garden of Eden''; and worked on ''Islands in the Stream''. The last three were stored in a safe deposit box in Havana, as he focused on the finishing touches for ''A Moveable Feast''. Author Michael Reynolds claims it was during this period that Hemingway slid into depression, from which he was unable to recover.&lt;ref&gt;Reynolds (1999), 321&lt;/ref&gt;

The Finca Vigia became crowded with guests and tourists, as Hemingway, beginning to become unhappy with life there, considered a permanent move to Idaho. In 1959 he bought a home overlooking the [[Big Wood River]], outside Ketchum, and left Cuba—although he apparently remained on easy terms with the [[Fidel Castro|Castro]] government, telling ''The New York Times'' he was &quot;delighted&quot; with Castro's overthrow of [[Fulgencio Batista|Batista]].&lt;ref&gt;Mellow (1992), 494–495&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers pp516–519&quot;&gt;Meyers (1985), 516–519&lt;/ref&gt; He was in Cuba in November 1959, between returning from Pamplona and traveling west to Idaho, and the following year for his 61st birthday; however, that year he and Mary decided to leave after hearing the news that Castro wanted to nationalize property owned by Americans and other foreign nationals.&lt;ref&gt;Reynolds (2000), 332, 344&lt;/ref&gt; On July 25, 1960, the Hemingways left Cuba for the last time, leaving art and manuscripts in a bank vault in Havana. After the 1961 [[Bay of Pigs Invasion]], the Finca Vigia was expropriated by the Cuban government, complete with Hemingway's collection of &quot;four to six thousand books&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mellow p599&quot;&gt;Mellow (1992), 599&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Idaho and suicide ===
Hemingway continued to rework the material that was published as ''A Moveable Feast'' through the 1950s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers p533&quot; /&gt; In mid-1959, he visited Spain to research a series of bullfighting articles commissioned by ''[[Life (magazine)|Life]]'' magazine.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers p520&quot;&gt;Meyers (1985), 520&lt;/ref&gt; ''Life'' wanted only 10,000&amp;nbsp;words, but the manuscript grew out of control.&lt;ref&gt;Baker (1969), 553&lt;/ref&gt; He was unable to organize his writing for the first time in his life, so he asked [[A. E. Hotchner]] to travel to Cuba to help him. Hotchner helped him trim the ''Life'' piece down to 40,000 words, and Scribner's agreed to a full-length book version (''[[The Dangerous Summer]]'') of almost 130,000 words.&lt;ref name=&quot;R544ff&quot;&gt;Reynolds (1999), 544–547&lt;/ref&gt; Hotchner found Hemingway to be &quot;unusually hesitant, disorganized, and confused&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;Mellow pp598–600&quot;&gt;qtd. in Mellow (1992), 598–600&lt;/ref&gt; and suffering badly from failing eyesight.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers p542-544&quot;&gt;Meyers (1985), 542–544&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Hemingway SunValley.jpg|thumb|Hemingway bird-hunting at [[Silver Creek (Idaho)|Silver Creek]], near [[Picabo, Idaho]], January 1959; with him are [[Gary Cooper]] and Bobbie Peterson|alt=photograph of two men and woman]]

Hemingway and Mary left Cuba for the last time on July 25, 1960. He set up a small office in his New York City apartment and attempted to work, but he left  soon after. He then traveled alone to Spain to be photographed for the front cover of ''Life'' magazine. A few days later, the news reported that he was seriously ill and on the verge of dying, which panicked Mary until she received a cable from him telling her, &quot;Reports false. Enroute Madrid. Love Papa.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;qtd. in Reynolds (1999), 546&lt;/ref&gt; He was, in fact, seriously ill, and believed himself to be on the verge of a breakdown.&lt;ref name=&quot;R544ff&quot; /&gt; Feeling lonely, he took to his bed for days, retreating into silence, despite having the first installments of ''The Dangerous Summer'' published in ''Life'' in September 1960 to good reviews.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mellow pp598-601&quot;&gt;Mellow (1992), 598–601&lt;/ref&gt; In October, he left Spain for New York, where he refused to leave Mary's apartment, presuming that he was being watched. She quickly took him to Idaho, where physician George Saviers met them at the train.&lt;ref name=&quot;R544ff&quot; /&gt;

At this time, Hemingway was constantly worried about money and his safety.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers p542-544&quot; /&gt; He worried about his taxes and that he would never return to Cuba to retrieve the manuscripts that he had left in a bank vault. He became paranoid, thinking that the FBI was actively monitoring his movements in Ketchum.&lt;ref name=&quot;R548&quot;&gt;Reynolds (1999), 548&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Meyers (1985), 543&lt;/ref&gt; The FBI had, in fact, opened a file on him during World War II, when he used the ''Pilar'' to patrol the waters off Cuba, and [[J. Edgar Hoover]] had an agent in Havana watch him during the 1950s.&lt;ref&gt;Mellow (1992), 597–598&lt;/ref&gt; By the end of November, Mary was at her wits' end, and Saviers suggested that Hemingway go to the [[Mayo Clinic]] in Minnesota; Hemingway might have believed that he was to be treated there for [[hypertension]].&lt;ref name=&quot;R548&quot; /&gt;  The FBI knew that Hemingway was at the Mayo Clinic, as an agent later documented in a letter written in January 1961.&lt;ref&gt;Meyers (1985), 543–544&lt;/ref&gt; He was checked in at the Mayo Clinic under Saviers's name in order to maintain anonymity.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mellow pp598-601&quot; /&gt; Meyers writes that &quot;an aura of secrecy surrounds Hemingway's treatment at the Mayo&quot; but confirms that he was treated with [[electroconvulsive therapy]] as many as 15 times in December 1960 and was &quot;released in ruins&quot; in January 1961.&lt;ref&gt;Meyers (1985), 547–550&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!--- THE FOLLOWING SENTENCE MAKES NO SENSE AND HAS BEEN HIDDEN. He went to the Mayo in the first place because of his paranoid depression; the meds did not cause it!---&gt;&lt;!--- Reynolds gained access to Hemingway's records at the Mayo, which indicated that the combination of medications given to him might have created the depressive state for which he was treated.&lt;ref&gt;Reynolds (2000), 350&lt;/ref&gt;---&gt;

Hemingway was [[Ernest and Mary Hemingway House|back in Ketchum]] in April 1961, three months after being released from the Mayo Clinic, when Mary &quot;found Hemingway holding a shotgun&quot; in the kitchen one morning. She called Saviers, who sedated him and admitted him to the Sun Valley Hospital; from there he was returned to the Mayo for more electroshock treatments.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers p551&quot;&gt;Meyers (1985), 551&lt;/ref&gt; He was released in late June and arrived home in Ketchum on June 30; he then &quot;quite deliberately&quot; shot himself with his favorite shotgun in the early morning hours of July 2, 1961.&lt;ref&gt;Reynolds (2000), 16&lt;/ref&gt; He had unlocked the basement storeroom where his guns were kept, gone upstairs to the front entrance foyer, and shot himself with the &quot;double-barreled shotgun that he had used so often it might have been a friend&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Mellow (1992), 604&lt;/ref&gt;

Mary called the Sun Valley Hospital, and a doctor quickly arrived at the house, determining that Hemingway &quot;had died of a self-inflicted wound to the head&quot;. Mary was sedated and taken to the hospital, returning home the next day where she cleaned the house and saw to the funeral and travel arrangements. Bernice Kert writes that it &quot;did not seem to her a conscious lie&quot; when she told the press that his death had been accidental.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kertp504&quot;&gt;Kert (1983), 504&lt;/ref&gt; In a press interview five years later, Mary confirmed that he had shot himself.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1966/08/23/archives/widow-believes-hemingway-committed-suicide-she-tells-of-his.html|title=Widow Believes Hemingway Committed Suicide; She Tells of His Depression and His 'Breakdown' Assails Hotchner Book|first=Harry|last=Gilroy|date=August 23, 1966|publisher=|accessdate=July 11, 2017|newspaper=The New York Times}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Hemingway Memorial Sun Valley.jpg|thumb|Hemingway Memorial, [[Sun Valley, Idaho]]]]

Family and friends flew to Ketchum for the funeral, officiated by the local Catholic priest, who believed that the death had been accidental.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kertp504&quot; /&gt; An altar boy fainted at the head of the casket during the funeral, and Hemingway's brother Leicester wrote: &quot;It seemed to me Ernest would have approved of it all.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Hemingway (1996), 14–18&lt;/ref&gt; He is buried in the Ketchum cemetery.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson, Scott. ''Resting Places: The Burial Sites of More Than 14,000 Famous Persons'', 3d ed.: 2 (Kindle Location 20869). McFarland &amp; Company, Inc., Publishers. Kindle Edition.&lt;/ref&gt;

Hemingway's behavior during his final years had been similar to that of his father before he killed himself;&lt;ref name=&quot;Burwell p234&quot;&gt;Burwell (1996), 234&lt;/ref&gt; his father may have had the genetic disease [[hemochromatosis]], whereby the inability to [[metabolize]] iron culminates in mental and physical deterioration.&lt;ref name=&quot;Burwell p14&quot;&gt;Burwell (1996), 14&lt;/ref&gt; Medical records made available in 1991 confirm that Hemingway had been diagnosed with hemochromatosis in early 1961.&lt;ref name=&quot;Burwell p189&quot;&gt;Burwell (1996), 189&lt;/ref&gt; His sister Ursula and his brother [[Leicester Hemingway|Leicester]] also killed themselves.&lt;ref&gt;Oliver (1999), 139–149&lt;/ref&gt; Hemingway's health was further compromised by being a heavy drinker for most of his life.&lt;ref name=&quot;Desnoyers p12&quot; /&gt;

A memorial to Hemingway just north of Sun Valley is inscribed on the base with a eulogy Hemingway had written for a friend several decades earlier:&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://articles.latimes.com/1987-07-12/travel/tr-3413_1_hemingway-memorial|title=Idaho Remembers the Times of Papa Hemingway : Idaho: Hemingway Is Well Remembered|first=Michael|last=Carlton|date=July 12, 1987|publisher=|accessdate=July 11, 2017|newspaper=Los Angeles Times}}&lt;/ref&gt;

:''Best of all he loved the fall
:''the leaves yellow on cottonwoods
:''leaves floating on trout streams
:''and above the hills
:''the high blue windless skies''
:...''Now he will be a part of them forever.''

== Writing style ==
''The New York Times'' wrote in 1926 of Hemingway's first novel,  &quot;No amount of analysis can convey the quality of ''The Sun Also Rises''. It is a truly gripping story, told in a lean, hard, athletic narrative prose that puts more literary English to shame.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT&quot;&gt;[https://www.nytimes.com/books/99/07/04/specials/hemingway-rises.html &quot;The Sun Also Rises&quot;]. (October 31, 1926). ''[[The New York Times]]''. Retrieved November 30, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; ''The Sun Also Rises'' is written in the spare, tight prose that made Hemingway famous, and, according to James Nagel, &quot;changed the nature of American writing.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Nagel 1996 87&quot;&gt;Nagel (1996), 87&lt;/ref&gt; In 1954, when Hemingway was awarded the Nobel Prize for Literature, it was for &quot;his mastery of the art of narrative, most recently demonstrated in ''The Old Man and the Sea'', and for the influence that he has exerted on contemporary style.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/literature/laureates/1954/index.html |title = The Nobel Prize in Literature 1954 |publisher = The Nobel Foundation |accessdate = March 7, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote box | width = 22em
| quote = If a writer of prose knows enough of what he is writing about he may omit things that he knows and the reader, if the writer is writing truly enough, will have a feeling of those things as strongly as though the writer had stated them. The dignity of movement of an ice-berg is due to only one-eighth of it being above water. A writer who omits things because he does not know them only makes hollow places in his writing.
| source = —Ernest Hemingway in ''[[Death in the Afternoon]]''&lt;ref&gt;qtd. in Oliver (1999), 322&lt;/ref&gt;
| style = padding:1.5em
| fontsize=85%
}}

[[Henry Louis Gates]] believes Hemingway's style was fundamentally shaped &quot;in reaction to [his] experience of world war&quot;. After World War&amp;nbsp;I, he and other modernists &quot;lost faith in the central institutions of Western civilization&quot; by reacting against the elaborate style of 19th-century writers and by creating a style &quot;in which meaning is established through dialogue, through action, and silences—a fiction in which nothing crucial—or at least very little—is stated explicitly.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Putnam&quot; /&gt;  

Because he began as a writer of short stories, Baker believes Hemingway learned to &quot;get the most from the least, how to prune language, how to multiply intensities and how to tell nothing but the truth in a way that allowed for telling more than the truth.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Baker p117&quot;&gt;Baker (1972),  117&lt;/ref&gt; Hemingway called his style the [[iceberg theory]]: the facts float above water; the supporting structure and symbolism operate out of sight.&lt;ref name=&quot;Baker p117&quot; /&gt; The concept of the iceberg theory is sometimes referred to as the &quot;theory of omission&quot;. Hemingway believed the writer could describe one thing (such as Nick Adams fishing in &quot;The Big Two-Hearted River&quot;) though an entirely different thing occurs below the surface (Nick Adams concentrating on fishing to the extent that he does not have to think about anything else).&lt;ref&gt;Oliver (1999), 321–322&lt;/ref&gt;  Paul Smith writes that Hemingway's first stories, collected as ''[[In Our Time (short story collection)|In Our Time]]'', showed he was still experimenting with his writing style.&lt;ref&gt;Smith (1996), 45&lt;/ref&gt; He avoided complicated syntax. About 70 percent of the sentences are [[simple sentence]]s—a childlike syntax without [[subordinate clause|subordination]].&lt;ref&gt;Wells (1975), 130–133&lt;/ref&gt;

Jackson Benson believes Hemingway used autobiographical details as framing devices about life in general—not only about his life. For example, Benson postulates that Hemingway used his experiences and drew them out with &quot;what if&quot; scenarios: &quot;what if I were wounded in such a way that I could not sleep at night? What if I were wounded and made crazy, what would happen if I were sent back to the front?&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Benson (1989), 351&lt;/ref&gt;  Writing in &quot;The Art of the Short Story&quot;, Hemingway explains: &quot;A few things I have found to be true. If you leave out important things or events that you know about, the story is strengthened. If you leave or skip something because you do not know it, the story will be worthless. The test of any story is how very good the stuff that you, not your editors, omit.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Hemingway (1975), 3&lt;/ref&gt;

The simplicity of the prose is deceptive. Zoe Trodd believes Hemingway crafted skeletal sentences in response to [[Henry James]]'s observation that World War&amp;nbsp;I had &quot;used up words&quot;. Hemingway offers a &quot;multi-focal&quot; photographic reality. His iceberg theory of omission is the foundation on which he builds. The syntax, which lacks [[grammatical conjunction|subordinating conjunctions]], creates static sentences. The photographic &quot;[[Snapshot (photography)|snapshot]]&quot; style creates a [[collage]] of images. Many types of internal punctuation (colons, semicolons, dashes, parentheses) are omitted in favor of short declarative sentences. The sentences build on each other, as events build to create a sense of the whole. Multiple strands exist in one story; an &quot;embedded text&quot; bridges to a different angle. He also uses other cinematic techniques of &quot;cutting&quot; quickly from one scene to the next; or of &quot;splicing&quot; a scene into another. Intentional omissions allow the reader to fill the gap, as though responding to instructions from the author, and create three-dimensional prose.&lt;ref&gt;Trodd (2007), 8&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote box | width = 22em
|quote = In the late summer that year we lived in a house in a village that looked across the river and the plain to the mountains. In the bed of the river there were pebbles and boulders, dry and white in the sun, and the water was clear and swiftly moving and blue in the channels. Troops went by the house and down the road and the dust they raised powdered the trees.
| source = —Opening passage of ''[[A Farewell to Arms]]'' showing Hemingway's use of the word ''and''&lt;ref&gt;qtd. in Mellow (1992), 379&lt;/ref&gt;
| style = padding:1.5em
| fontsize=85%
}}

Hemingway habitually used the word &quot;and&quot; in place of commas. This use of [[polysyndeton]] may serve to convey immediacy. Hemingway's polysyndetonic sentence—or in later works his use of subordinate clauses—uses conjunctions to juxtapose startling visions and images.  Benson compares them to [[haiku]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;McCormick p49&quot;&gt;McCormick, 49&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Benson 1989, 309&lt;/ref&gt; Many of Hemingway's followers misinterpreted his lead and frowned upon all expression of emotion; [[Saul Bellow]] satirized this style as &quot;Do you have emotions? Strangle them.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;qtd. in Hoberek (2005), 309&lt;/ref&gt; However, Hemingway's intent was not to eliminate emotion, but to portray it more scientifically. Hemingway thought it would be easy, and pointless, to describe emotions; he sculpted collages of images in order to grasp &quot;the real thing, the sequence of motion and fact which made the emotion and which would be as valid in a year or in ten years or, with luck and if you stated it purely enough, always&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Hemingway, Ernest. ''Death in the Afternoon''. New York: Simon and Schuster&lt;/ref&gt; This use of an image as an [[objective correlative]] is characteristic of Ezra Pound, T. S. Eliot, James Joyce, and [[Proust]].&lt;ref&gt;McCormick, 47&lt;/ref&gt; Hemingway's letters refer to Proust's ''[[In Search of Lost Time|Remembrance of Things Past]]'' several times over the years, and indicate he read the book at least twice.&lt;ref name=&quot;Burwell p187&quot;&gt;Burwell (1996), 187&lt;/ref&gt;
{{clear left}}

== Themes ==
The popularity of Hemingway's work depends on its themes of love, war, wilderness, and loss, all of which are strongly evident in the body of work.&lt;ref&gt;Svoboda (2000), 155&lt;/ref&gt; These are recurring themes in [[American literature]], and are quite clearly evident in Hemingway's work. Critic [[Leslie Fiedler]] sees the theme he defines as &quot;The Sacred Land&quot;—the [[American Old West|American West]]—extended in Hemingway's work to include mountains in Spain, Switzerland and Africa, and to the streams of Michigan. The American West is given a symbolic nod with the naming of the &quot;Hotel Montana&quot; in ''The Sun Also Rises'' and ''For Whom the Bell Tolls''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fiedler&quot; /&gt;  According to Stoltzfus and Fiedler, in Hemingway's work, nature is a place for rebirth and rest; and it is where the hunter or fisherman might experience a moment of transcendence at the moment they kill their prey.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stoltzfus&quot; /&gt; Nature is where men exist without women: men fish; men hunt; men find redemption in nature.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fiedler&quot; /&gt; Although Hemingway does write about sports, such as fishing, Carlos Baker notes the emphasis is more on the athlete than the sport.&lt;ref name=&quot;Baker1972 101–121&quot;&gt;Baker (1972), 101–121&lt;/ref&gt; At its core, much of Hemingway's work can be viewed in the light of American [[Naturalism (literature)|naturalism]], evident in detailed descriptions such as those in &quot;Big Two-Hearted River&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Beegel2000, p. 63-70&quot; /&gt;

Fiedler believes Hemingway inverts the American literary theme of the evil &quot;Dark Woman&quot; versus the good &quot;Light Woman&quot;. The dark woman—Brett Ashley of ''[[The Sun Also Rises]]''—is a goddess; the light woman—Margot Macomber of &quot;[[The Short Happy Life of Francis Macomber]]&quot;—is a murderess.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fiedler&quot;&gt;Fiedler (1975), 345–365&lt;/ref&gt; [[Robert Scholes]] admits that early Hemingway stories, such as &quot;[[A Very Short Story]]&quot;, present &quot;a male character favorably and a female unfavorably&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Scholes (1990),  42&lt;/ref&gt;  According to Rena Sanderson, early Hemingway critics lauded his male-centric world of masculine pursuits, and the fiction divided women into &quot;castrators or love-slaves&quot;. Feminist critics attacked Hemingway as &quot;public enemy number one&quot;, although more recent re-evaluations of his work &quot;have given new visibility to Hemingway's female characters (and their strengths) and have revealed his own sensitivity to gender issues, thus casting doubts on the old assumption that his writings were one-sidedly masculine.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Sanderson (1996), 171&lt;/ref&gt; Nina Baym believes that Brett Ashley and Margot Macomber &quot;are the two outstanding examples of Hemingway's 'bitch women.{{'&quot;}}&lt;ref&gt;Baym (1990), 112&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote box | width = 22em
|quote =The world breaks everyone and afterward many are strong in the broken places. But those that will not break it kills. It kills the very good and the very gentle and the very brave impartially. If you are none of these you can be sure it will kill you too but there will be no special hurry.
| source =—Ernest Hemingway in ''[[A Farewell to Arms]]''&lt;ref&gt;Hemingway, Ernest. (1929) ''A Farewell to Arms]''. New York: Scribner's&lt;/ref&gt;
| style = padding:1.5em
| fontsize=85%
}}

The theme of women and death is evident in stories as early as &quot;[[Indian Camp]]&quot;. The theme of death permeates Hemingway's work. Young believes the emphasis in &quot;Indian Camp&quot; was not so much on the woman who gives birth or the father who kills himself, but on Nick Adams who witnesses these events as a child, and becomes a &quot;badly scarred and nervous young man&quot;. Hemingway sets the events in &quot;Indian Camp&quot; that shape the Adams persona. Young believes &quot;Indian Camp&quot; holds the &quot;master key&quot; to &quot;what its author was up to for some thirty-five years of his writing career&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Young (1964), 6&lt;/ref&gt; Stoltzfus considers Hemingway's work to be more complex with a representation of the truth inherent in [[existentialism]]: if &quot;nothingness&quot; is embraced, then redemption is achieved at the moment of death. Those who face death with dignity and courage live an authentic life. Francis Macomber dies happy because the last hours of his life are authentic; the [[bullfighter]] in the [[Bullfighting|corrida]] represents the pinnacle of a life lived with authenticity.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stoltzfus&quot;&gt;Stoltzfus (2005), 215–218&lt;/ref&gt; In his paper ''The Uses of Authenticity: Hemingway and the Literary Field'', Timo Müller writes that Hemingway's fiction is successful because the characters live an &quot;authentic life&quot;, and the &quot;soldiers, fishers, boxers and backwoodsmen are among the archetypes of authenticity in modern literature&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Müller (2010), 31&lt;/ref&gt;

The theme of emasculation is prevalent in Hemingway's work, most notably in ''The Sun Also Rises''. Emasculation, according to Fiedler, is a result of a generation of wounded soldiers; and of a generation in which women such as Brett gained [[Women's suffrage|emancipation]]. This also applies to the minor character, Frances Clyne, Cohn's girlfriend in the beginning in the book. Her character supports the theme not only because the idea was presented early on in the novel but also the impact she had on Cohn in the start of the book while only appearing a small number of times.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fiedler&quot; /&gt; Baker believes Hemingway's work emphasizes the &quot;natural&quot; versus the &quot;unnatural&quot;. In &quot;Alpine Idyll&quot; the &quot;unnaturalness&quot; of skiing in the high country late spring snow is juxtaposed against the &quot;unnaturalness&quot; of the peasant who allowed his wife's dead body to linger too long in the shed during the winter. The skiers and peasant retreat to the valley to the &quot;natural&quot; spring for redemption.&lt;ref name=&quot;Baker1972 101–121&quot; /&gt;

Susan Beegel has written that some more recent critics—writing through the lens of a more modern social and cultural context several decades after Hemingway's death, and more than half a century after his novels were first published—have characterized the social era portrayed in his fiction as [[misogynistic]] and [[homophobic]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Beegel 1996 282&quot;&gt;Beegel (1996), 282&lt;/ref&gt; In her 1996 essay, &quot;Critical Reception&quot;, Beegel analyzed four decades of Hemingway criticism and found that &quot;critics interested in multiculturalism&quot;, particularly in the 1980s, simply ignored Hemingway, although some &quot;apologetics&quot; have been written.&lt;ref&gt;Beegel (1996)&lt;/ref&gt; Typical, according to Beegel, is an analysis of Hemingway's 1926 novel, ''The Sun Also Rises'', in which a critic contended: &quot;Hemingway never lets the reader forget that Cohn is a Jew, not an unattractive character who happens to be a Jew but a character who is unattractive because he is a Jew.&quot; Also during the 1980s, according to Beegel, criticism was published that focused on investigating the &quot;horror of [[homosexuality]]&quot; and the &quot;[[racism]]&quot; typical of the social era portrayed in Hemingway's fiction.&lt;ref name=&quot;Beegel 1996 282&quot; /&gt; In an overall assessment of Hemingway's work Beegel has written: &quot;Throughout his remarkable body of fiction, he tells the truth about human fear, guilt, betrayal, violence, cruelty, drunkenness, hunger, greed, apathy, ecstasy, tenderness, love and lust.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.kansascity.com/entertainment/arts-culture/article294978/Susan-Beegel-What-I-like-about-Hemingway.html|title=Susan Beegel: What I like about Hemingway|website=kansascity.com|accessdate=July 11, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Influence and legacy ==
[[File:Statue of Hemingway at Floridita.jpg|thumb|Life-sized statue of Hemingway by [[José Villa Soberón]], at [[El Floridita]] bar in [[Havana]]]]
Hemingway's legacy to American literature is his style: writers who came after him emulated it or avoided it.&lt;ref&gt;Oliver (1999), 140–141&lt;/ref&gt; After his reputation was established with the publication of ''The Sun Also Rises'', he became the spokesperson for the post-World War&amp;nbsp;I generation, having established a style to follow.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nagel 1996 87&quot; /&gt; His books were [[Nazi book burning|burned]] in Berlin in 1933, &quot;as being a monument of modern decadence&quot;, and disavowed by his parents as &quot;filth&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hallengren&quot;&gt;Hallengren, Anders. [http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/literature/laureates/1954/hemingway-article.html &quot;A Case of Identity: Ernest Hemingway&quot;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100803040752/http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/literature/laureates/1954/hemingway-article.html |date=August 3, 2010 }}. Nobelprize.org. Retrieved November 30, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Reynolds asserts the legacy is that &quot;[Hemingway] left stories and novels so starkly moving that some have become part of our cultural heritage.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Reynolds (2000), 15&lt;/ref&gt;

Benson believes the details of Hemingway's life have become a &quot;prime vehicle for exploitation&quot;, resulting in a Hemingway industry.&lt;ref&gt;Benson (1989), 347&lt;/ref&gt; Hemingway scholar Hallengren believes the &quot;hard boiled style&quot; and the machismo must be separated from the author himself.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hallengren&quot; /&gt; Benson agrees, describing him as introverted and private as [[J. D. Salinger]], although Hemingway masked his nature with braggadocio.&lt;ref&gt;Benson (1989), 349&lt;/ref&gt; During World War&amp;nbsp;II, Salinger met and corresponded with Hemingway, whom he acknowledged as an influence.  In a letter to Hemingway, Salinger claimed their talks &quot;had given him his only hopeful minutes of the entire war&quot; and jokingly &quot;named himself national chairman of the Hemingway Fan Clubs.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Baker (1969), 420&lt;/ref&gt;

The extent of Hemingway's influence is seen in the tributes and echoes of his fiction in popular culture. A [[minor planet]], discovered in 1978 by [[Soviet Union|Soviet]] astronomer [[Nikolai Chernykh]], was named for him ([[3656 Hemingway]]);&lt;ref&gt;Schmadel, Lutz D. (2003) ''Dictionary of Minor Planet Names''. New York: Springer Verlag. {{ISBN|3-540-00238-3}}, 307&lt;/ref&gt; [[Ray Bradbury]] wrote ''The Kilimanjaro Device'', with Hemingway transported to the top of [[Mount Kilimanjaro]];&lt;ref name=&quot;Oliver144&quot; /&gt; the 1993 motion picture ''[[Wrestling Ernest Hemingway]]'', about the friendship of two retired men, Irish and Cuban, in a seaside town in Florida, starred [[Robert Duvall]], [[Richard Harris]], [[Shirley MacLaine]], [[Sandra Bullock]], and [[Piper Laurie]].&lt;ref&gt;Oliver (1999), 360&lt;/ref&gt; The influence is evident with the many restaurants named &quot;Hemingway&quot;; and the proliferation of bars called &quot;Harry's&quot; (a nod to the bar in ''Across the River and Into the Trees'').&lt;ref&gt;Oliver (1999), 142&lt;/ref&gt; A line of Hemingway furniture, promoted by Hemingway's son Jack (Bumby), has pieces such as the &quot;Kilimanjaro&quot; bedside table, and a &quot;Catherine&quot; slip-covered sofa. [[Montblanc (company)|Montblanc]] offers a Hemingway fountain pen, and a line of Hemingway safari clothes has been created.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/library/books/061599lives-jackhemingway.html|title=A Line of Hemingway Furniture, With a Veneer of Taste|website=www.nytimes.com|accessdate=July 11, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[International Imitation Hemingway Competition]] was created in 1977 to publicly acknowledge his influence and the comically misplaced efforts of lesser authors to imitate his style. Entrants are encouraged to submit one &quot;really good page of really bad Hemingway&quot; and winners are flown to Italy to Harry's Bar.&lt;ref name=&quot;LA&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://articles.latimes.com/1993-03-15/news/vw-308_1_bad-hemingway|title=Wanted: One Really Good Page of Really Bad Hemingway|first=Jack|last=Smith|date=March 15, 1993|publisher=|accessdate=July 11, 2017|newspaper=Los Angeles Times}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1965, Mary Hemingway established the Hemingway Foundation and in the 1970s she donated her husband's papers to the John F. Kennedy Library. In 1980, a group of Hemingway scholars gathered to assess the donated papers, subsequently forming the Hemingway Society, &quot;committed to supporting and fostering Hemingway scholarship&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Miller (2006), 78–80&lt;/ref&gt;

Almost exactly 35 years after Hemingway's death, on July 1, 1996, his granddaughter [[Margaux Hemingway]] died in [[Santa Monica]], California.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://articles.latimes.com/1996-08-21/local/me-36349_1_margaux-hemingway |newspaper=[[The Los Angeles Times]] |title=Margaux Hemingway's Death Ruled a Suicide |last=Rainey |first=James| date=August 21, 1996 |access-date=April 1, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Margaux was a [[supermodel]] and actress, co-starring with her younger sister [[Mariel Hemingway|Mariel]] in the 1976 movie ''[[Lipstick (1976 film)|Lipstick]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.nytimes.com/1996/07/03/arts/margaux-hemingway-is-dead-model-and-actress-was-41.html &quot;Margaux Hemingway Is Dead; Model and Actress Was 41&quot;]. (July 3, 1996). ''The New York Times''. Retrieved May 14, 2010&lt;/ref&gt; Her death was later ruled a suicide, making her &quot;the fifth person in four generations of her family to commit suicide&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.nytimes.com/1996/08/21/us/coroner-says-death-of-actress-was-suicide.html &quot;Coroner Says Death of Actress Was Suicide&quot;]. (August 21, 1996). ''The New York Times''. Retrieved May 14, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

Three houses associated with Hemingway are listed on the U.S. National Register of Historic Places:  the [[Ernest Hemingway Cottage]] on Walloon Lake, Michigan, designated in 1968; the [[Ernest Hemingway House]] in Key West, designated in 1968; and the [[Ernest and Mary Hemingway House]] in Ketchum, designated in 2015. His boyhood home, in Oak Park, Illinois, is a museum and archive dedicated to Hemingway.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ehfop.org/foundation/index.html|title=The Ernest Hemingway Foundation of Oak Park|access-date=2017-10-08|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20081010205043/http://www.ehfop.org/foundation/index.html|archivedate=October 10, 2008|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2012, he was inducted into the Chicago Literary Hall of Fame.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://chicagoliteraryhof.org/inductees/profile/ernest-hemingway |title=Ernest Hemingway |date=2012 |website=Chicago Literary Hall of Fame |language=en |access-date=2017-10-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Several prizes have been established in his honour to recognise significant achievement in the arts and culture.  These include:
* [[Hemingway Foundation/PEN Award]]
* [[Premio Hemingway|Hemingway Award]]

== Selected list of works ==
{{Main|Ernest Hemingway bibliography}}
* (1926) ''[[The Torrents of Spring]]''
* (1926) ''[[The Sun Also Rises]]''
* (1929) ''[[A Farewell to Arms]]''
* (1937) ''[[To Have and Have Not]]''
* (1940) ''[[For Whom the Bell Tolls]]''
* (1950) ''[[Across the River and into the Trees]]''
* (1952) ''[[The Old Man and the Sea]]''

== Family tree ==
[[File:Ernest Hemingway family tree.svg|Family tree showing Ernest Hemingway's parents, siblings, wives, children and grandchildren]]

== Notes ==
{{Reflist|group=note|30em}}

== References ==
=== Citations ===
{{Reflist|20em}}

=== References cited ===
{{refbegin|30em}}
* Baker, Carlos. (1969). ''Ernest Hemingway: A Life Story''. New York: Charles Scribner's Sons. {{ISBN|978-0-02-001690-8}}
* Baker, Carlos. (1972). ''Hemingway: The Writer as Artist''. Princeton: Princeton UP. {{ISBN|978-0-691-01305-3}}
* Baker, Carlos. (1981). &quot;Introduction&quot; in ''Ernest Hemingway Selected Letters 1917–1961''. New York: Scribner's. {{ISBN|978-0-684-16765-7}}
* Banks, Russell. (2004). &quot;PEN/Hemingway Prize Speech&quot;. ''The Hemingway Review''. Volume 24, issue 1. 53–60
* Baym, Nina. (1990). &quot;Actually I Felt Sorry for the Lion&quot;. in Benson, Jackson J. (ed). ''New Critical Approaches to the Short Stories of Ernest Hemingway''. Durham: Duke UP. {{ISBN|978-0-8223-1067-9}}
* Beegel, Susan. (1996). &quot;Conclusion: The Critical Reputation&quot;. in Donaldson, Scott (ed). ''The Cambridge Companion to Ernest Hemingway''. New York: Cambridge UP. {{ISBN|978-0-521-45574-9}}
* Beegel, Susan (2000). &quot;Eye and Heart: Hemingway's Education as a Naturalist&quot;. in Wagner-Martin, Linda (ed). ''A Historical Guide to Ernest Hemingway''. New York: Oxford UP. {{ISBN|978-0-19-512152-0}}
* Benson, Jackson. (1989). &quot;Ernest Hemingway: The Life as Fiction and the Fiction as Life&quot;. ''American Literature''. Volume 61, issue 3. 354–358
* Benson, Jackson. (1975). ''The Short Stories of Ernest Hemingway: Critical Essays''. Durham: Duke UP. {{ISBN|978-0-8223-0320-6}}
* Burwell, Rose Marie. (1996). ''Hemingway: the Postwar Years and the Posthumous Novels''. New York: Cambridge UP. {{ISBN|978-0-521-48199-1}}
* Desnoyers, Megan Floyd. [http://www.jfklibrary.org/Research/The-Ernest-Hemingway-Collection/Online-Resources/Storytellers-Legacy.aspx?p=1 &quot;Ernest Hemingway: A Storyteller's Legacy&quot;]. John F. Kennedy Presidential Library Online Resources. [[John F. Kennedy Presidential Library and Museum]]. Retrieved November 30, 2011.
* Fiedler, Leslie. (1975). ''Love and Death in the American Novel''. New York: Stein and Day. {{ISBN|978-0-8128-1799-7}}
* Griffin, Peter. (1985). ''Along with Youth: Hemingway, the Early Years''. New York: Oxford UP. {{ISBN|978-0-19-503680-0}}
* Hemingway, Ernest. (1929). ''A Farewell to Arms''. New York: Scribner's. {{ISBN|978-1-4767-6452-8}}
* Hemingway, Ernest. (1975). &quot;The Art of the Short Story&quot; in Benson, Jackson (ed). ''New Critical Approaches to the Short Stories of Ernest Hemingway''. Durham: Duke UP. {{ISBN|978-0-8223-1067-9}}
* Hemingway, Leicester. (1996). ''My Brother, Ernest Hemingway''. New York: World Publishing Company. {{ISBN|978-1-56164-098-0}}
* Hoberek, Andrew. (2005). ''Twilight of the Middle Class: Post World War II fiction and White Collar Work''. New York: Cambridge UP. {{ISBN|978-0-691-12145-1}}
* Josephs, Allen. (1996). &quot;Hemingway’s Spanish Sensibility&quot;. in Donaldson, Scott (ed). ''The Cambridge Companion to Ernest Hemingway''. New York: Cambridge UP. {{ISBN|978-0-521-45574-9}}
* Kert, Bernice. (1983). ''The Hemingway Women''. New York: Norton. {{ISBN|978-0-393-31835-7}}
* Koch, Stephen. (2005). ''The Breaking Point: Hemingway, Dos Passos, and the Murder of Jose Robles''. New York: Counterpoint. {{ISBN|978-1-58243-280-9}}
* Long, Ray – editor. (1932). &quot;Why Editors Go Wrong: '[[Fifty Grand]]' by Ernest Hemingway&quot;, ''20 Best Stories in Ray Long's 20 Years as an Editor''. New York: Crown Publishers. 1–3
* Lynn, Kenneth. (1987). ''Hemingway''. Cambridge: Harvard UP. {{ISBN|978-0-674-38732-4}}
* McCormick, John (1971). ''American Literature 1919–1932''. London: Routledge. {{ISBN|978-0-7100-7052-4}}
* Mellow, James. (1992). ''Hemingway: A Life Without Consequences''. Boston: Houghton Mifflin. {{ISBN|978-0-395-37777-2}}
* Mellow, James. (1991). ''Charmed Circle: Gertrude Stein and Company''. Boston: Houghton Mifflin. {{ISBN|978-0-395-47982-7}}
* Meyers, Jeffrey. (1985). ''Hemingway: A Biography''. New York: Macmillan. {{ISBN|978-0-333-42126-0}}
* Miller, Linda Patterson. (2006). &quot;From the African Book to Under Kilimanjaro&quot;. ''The Hemingway Review'', Volume 25, issue 2. 78–81
* Müller, Timo. (2010). &quot;The Uses of Authenticity: Hemingway and the Literary Field, 1926–1936&quot;. ''Journal of Modern Literature''. Volume 33, issue 1. 28–42
* Nagel, James. (1996). &quot;Brett and the Other Women in ''The Sun Also Rises''&quot;. in Donaldson, Scott (ed). ''The Cambridge Companion to Ernest Hemingway''. New York: Cambridge UP. {{ISBN|978-0-521-45574-9}}
* Oliver, Charles. (1999). ''[https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=FuOvQgAACAAJ Ernest Hemingway A to Z: The Essential Reference to the Life and Work]''. New York: Checkmark Publishing. {{ISBN|978-0-8160-3467-3}}
* [[Donald Pizer|Pizer, Donald]]. (1986). &quot;The Hemingway: Dos Passos Relationship&quot;. ''Journal of Modern Literature''. Volume 13, issue 1. 111–128
* Reynolds, Michael (2000). &quot;Ernest Hemingway, 1899–1961: A Brief Biography&quot;. in Wagner-Martin, Linda (ed). ''A Historical Guide to Ernest Hemingway''. New York: Oxford UP. {{ISBN|978-0-19-512152-0}}
* Reynolds, Michael. (1999). ''Hemingway: The Final Years''. New York: Norton. {{ISBN|978-0-393-32047-3}}
* Reynolds, Michael. (1989). ''Hemingway: The Paris Years''. New York: Norton. {{ISBN|978-0-393-31879-1}}
* Reynolds, Michael. (1998). ''The Young Hemingway''. New York: Norton. {{ISBN|978-0-393-31776-3}}
* Robinson, Daniel. (2005). &quot;My True Occupation is That of a Writer:Hemingway's Passport Correspondence&quot;. ''The Hemingway Review''. 87–93 &lt;!-- issue &amp; volume? --&gt;
* Trogdon, Robert W. &quot;Forms of Combat: Hemingway, the Critics and Green Hills of Africa&quot;. ''The Hemingway Review''. Volume 15, issue 2. 1–14
* Sanderson, Rena. (1996). &quot;Hemingway and Gender History&quot;. in Donaldson, Scott (ed). ''The Cambridge Companion to Ernest Hemingway''. New York: Cambridge UP. {{ISBN|978-0-521-45574-9}}
* Scholes, Robert. (1990). &quot;New Critical Approaches to the Short Stories of Ernest Hemingway&quot;. in Benson, Jackson J. ''Decoding Papa: 'A Very Short Story' as Work and Text''. 33–47. Durham, NC: Duke University Press. {{ISBN|978-0-8223-1067-9}}
* Smith, Paul (1996). &quot;1924: Hemingway's Luggage and the Miraculous Year&quot;. in Donaldson, Scott (ed). ''The Cambridge Companion to Ernest Hemingway''. New York: Cambridge UP. {{ISBN|978-0-521-45574-9}}
* Stoltzfus, Ben. (2005). &quot;Sartre, &quot;Nada,&quot; and Hemingway's African Stories&quot;. ''Comparative Literature Studies''. Volume 42, issue 3. 205–228
* Svoboda, Frederic. (2000). &quot;The Great Themes in Hemingway&quot;. in Wagner-Martin, Linda (ed). ''A Historical Guide to Ernest Hemingway''. New York: Oxford UP. {{ISBN|978-0-19-512152-0}}
* Thomas, Hugh. (2001). ''The Spanish Civil War''. New York: Modern Library. {{ISBN|978-0-375-75515-6}}
* Trodd, Zoe. (2007). &quot;Hemingway's Camera Eye: The Problems of Language and an Interwar Politics of Form&quot;. ''The Hemingway Review''. Volume 26, issue 2. 7–21
* Wells, Elizabeth J. (1975). &quot;A Statistical Analysis of the Prose Style of Ernest Hemingway: ''Big Two-Hearted River''&quot;. in Benson, Jackson (ed).  ''The Short Stories of Ernest Hemingway: Critical Essays''. Durham NC: Duke UP. {{ISBN|978-0-8223-0320-6}}
* Young, Philip. (1964). ''Ernest Hemingway''. St. Paul, MN: University of Minnesota. {{ISBN|978-0-8166-0191-2}}
{{refend}}

== External links ==
{{Commons and category|Ernest Hemingway}}
{{Wikiquote|Ernest Hemingway}}
{{Wikisource author}}
{{Library resources box|onlinebooks=yes|by=yes}}
* [http://www.jfklibrary.org/Research/The-Ernest-Hemingway-Collection.aspx Hemingway Archives: John F. Kennedy Library]
* [http://www.lib.utexas.edu/taro/uthrc/00056/hrc-00056.html/ Ernest Hemingway's Collection] at [[The University of Texas at Austin]]
* [https://archives.library.sc.edu/repositories/5/resources/869 Maurice J. Speiser papers at the University of South Carolina Department of Rare Books and Special Collections]
* [http://www.historicjournalism.com/ernest-hemingway-1.html Ernest Hemingway's journalism at The Archive of American Journalism]
* [http://www.theparisreview.org/interviews/4825/the-art-of-fiction-no-21-ernest-hemingway &quot;The Art of Fiction No. 21]. ''The Paris Review''. Spring 1958.
* [http://vault.fbi.gov/ernest-miller-hemingway/ernest-hemingway-part-01-of-01/view FBI Records: The Vault, Subject: Ernest Hemingway]
* [http://www.nypl.org/sites/default/files/archivalcollections/pdf/mss18572_1.pdf Hemingway legal files collection, 1899–1971] Manuscripts and Archives, New York Public Library.

{{Ernest Hemingway |state=autocollapse}}
{{Nobel Prize in Literature Laureates 1951–1975}}
{{PulitzerPrize Fiction 1951–1975}}

{{Featured article}}

{{Authority control}}

&lt;!-- Note: Please do not alphabetize the categories — keeping them grouped makes it much easier to maintain and ensure completeness --&gt;

&lt;!-- top-level cats --&gt;


{{DEFAULTSORT:Hemingway, Ernest}}
[[Category:Ernest Hemingway| ]]
[[Category:Hemingway family]]
[[Category:1899 births]]
[[Category:1961 deaths]]

&lt;!-- novelist cats --&gt;
[[Category:20th-century American novelists]]
[[Category:American male novelists]]
[[Category:American war novelists]]

&lt;!-- misc writer cats --&gt;
[[Category:20th-century American short story writers]]
[[Category:American essayists]]
[[Category:American travel writers]]
[[Category:American memoirists]]
[[Category:Writers from Chicago]]
[[Category:American male writers who committed suicide]]
[[Category:Modernist writers]]

&lt;!-- journalist cats --&gt;
[[Category:American male journalists]]
[[Category:Toronto Star people]]
[[Category:American war correspondents]]
[[Category:Journalists from Illinois]]
[[Category:American war correspondents of World War II]]

&lt;!-- expatriates cats --&gt;
[[Category:American expatriates in Cuba]]
[[Category:American expatriates in France]]
[[Category:American expatriates in Italy]]
[[Category:American expatriates in Spain]]

&lt;!-- other jobs --&gt;
[[Category:American hunters]]
[[Category:American fishers]]

&lt;!-- war categories --&gt;
[[Category:American military personnel of World War I]]
[[Category:American people of the Spanish Civil War]]
[[Category:French Resistance members]]
[[Category:Operation Overlord people]]

&lt;!-- awards --&gt;
[[Category:American Nobel laureates]]
[[Category:Bancarella Prize winners]]
[[Category:Nobel laureates in Literature]]
[[Category:Pulitzer Prize for Fiction winners]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Silver Medal of Military Valor]]

&lt;!-- misc personal --&gt;
[[Category:American Roman Catholics]]
[[Category:Converts to Roman Catholicism]]
[[Category:History of Key West, Florida]]
[[Category:Writers from Oak Park, Illinois]]
[[Category:Suicides by firearm in Idaho]]
[[Category:Survivors of aviation accidents or incidents]]
[[Category:American anti-fascists]]
[[Category:American male essayists]]
[[Category:American male short story writers]]
[[Category:People from Ketchum, Idaho]]
[[Category:20th-century American journalists]]
[[Category:20th-century American male writers]]
[[Category:Journalists who committed suicide]]
[[Category:Male suicides]]
[[Category:Novelists from Illinois]]
[[Category:Catholics from Illinois]]
[[Category:Catholics from Idaho]]
[[Category:20th-century essayists]]</text>
      <sha1>dkq3el533o8ekdjh1t1x8tbl3wfdhuo</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
