  <page>
    <title>Election</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9457</id>
    <revision>
      <id>940777570</id>
      <parentid>939933089</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-14T15:36:42Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>2607:FEA8:A760:1041:CC6F:C55B:276A:553B</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Examples */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|Elect|other uses|-elect|and|Election (disambiguation)}}
{{Redirect|Free election|the &quot;free elections&quot; of Polish kings|Royal elections in Poland}}
{{short description|Process by which a population chooses the holder of a public office}}
{{more citations needed|date=October 2019}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}
[[File:Election MG 3455.JPG|thumb|right|A [[ballot box]] used in France]]
{{Elections}}
An '''election''' is a formal [[group decision-making]] process by which a population chooses an individual to hold [[Public administration|public office]].&lt;ref name = Brit&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/182308/election &quot;Election (political science),&quot;] Encyclopedia Britannica Online. Retrieved 18 August 2009&lt;/ref&gt; It is usually used in Democratic nations.

Elections have been the usual mechanism by which modern [[representative democracy]] has operated since the 17th century.&lt;ref name=&quot;Brit&quot; /&gt; Elections may fill offices in the [[legislature]], sometimes in the [[executive (government)|executive]] and [[judiciary]], and for [[local government|regional and local government]]. This process is also used in many other private and [[business]] organizations, from clubs to [[voluntary association]]s and [[corporation]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Robert's Rules of Order Newly Revised|last = Robert|first = Henry M.|publisher = Da Capo Press|year = 2011|isbn = 978-0-306-82020-5|location = Philadelphia, PA|pages = 438–446|edition = 11th|display-authors=etal|title-link = Robert's Rules of Order}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The universal use of elections as a tool for selecting representatives in modern representative democracies is in contrast with the practice in the democratic [[archetype]], ancient [[History of Athens|Athens]], where the Elections were not used were considered an [[oligarchy|oligarchic]] institution and most political offices were filled using [[sortition]], also known as allotment, by which officeholders were chosen by lot.&lt;ref&gt;Headlam, James Wycliffe (1891). Election by Lot at Athens. p. 12.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Electoral reform]] describes the process of introducing fair electoral systems where they are not in place, or improving the fairness or effectiveness of existing systems. [[Psephology]] is the study of results and other [[statistics]] relating to elections (especially with a view to predicting future results).

To ''elect'' means &quot;to select or make a decision&quot;, and so sometimes other forms of ballot such as [[referendum]]s are referred to as elections, especially in the United States.

==History==
{{see also|History of democracy}}
[[File:Roman Election.jpg|thumb|left|[[Roman coin]] depicting election]]
[[File:Cardiganshire Election ballot paper 1880.jpg|thumb|A British election campaign leaflet with an illustration of an example ballot paper, 1880]]
Elections were used as early in history as [[ancient Greece]] and [[ancient Rome]], and throughout the Medieval period to select rulers such as the [[Holy Roman Emperor]] (see [[imperial election]]) and the [[pope]] (see [[papal election]]).&lt;ref name = Brit/&gt;

In [[Vedic period]] of India, the ''[[Raja]]'' (chiefs) of a ''[[gana]]'' (a tribal organization) was apparently elected by the ''gana''. The ''Raja'' belonged to the noble [[Kshatriya]] [[varna in Hinduism|varna]] (warrior class), and was typically a son of the previous R''aja''. However, the ''gana'' members had the final say in his elections.&lt;ref name=&quot;Robinson1997&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author=Eric W. Robinson |title=The First Democracies: Early Popular Government Outside Athens |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=T1kfcobFRSMC&amp;pg=PA23 |year=1997 |publisher=Franz Steiner Verlag |isbn=978-3-515-06951-9 |pages=22–23 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Even during the Sangam Period people elected their representatives by casting their votes and the ballot boxes (Usually a pot) were tied by rope and sealed. After the election the votes were taken out and counted.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Agananooru|last=|first=|publisher=Saiva Siddantha Noor pathippu Kazhagam|year=1968|isbn=|location=Chennai|pages=183–186}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The [[Pala Empire|Pala]] King [[Gopala (Pala king)|Gopala]] (ruled c. 750s–770s CE) in early medieval [[Bengal]] was elected by a group of feudal chieftains. Such elections were quite common in contemporary societies of the region.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nitish2011&quot;&gt;{{cite book | author=Nitish K. Sengupta | title=Land of Two Rivers: A History of Bengal from the Mahabharata to Mujib | chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=kVSh_TyJ0YoC&amp;pg=PA40 | date=1 January 2011 | publisher=Penguin Books India | isbn=978-0-14-341678-4 | chapter = The Imperial Palas | pages=39–49 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author=Biplab Dasgupta | title=European Trade and Colonial Conquest | url=https://books.google.com/books?id=YRRnRK8lEYEC&amp;pg=PA341 | date=1 January 2005 | publisher=Anthem Press | isbn=978-1-84331-029-7 | pages=341–}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[Chola Empire]], around 920 CE, in [[Uthiramerur]] (in present-day [[Tamil Nadu]]), palm leaves were used for selecting the village committee members. The leaves, with candidate names written on them, were put inside a mud pot. To select the committee members, a young boy was asked to take out as many leaves as the number of positions available. This was known as the ''Kudavolai'' system.&lt;ref name=&quot;VKA_2010&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Indian History |editor=VK Agnihotri |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=MazdaWXQFuQC&amp;pg=SL2-PA62 |publisher=Allied |isbn=978-81-8424-568-4 |year=2010 |edition=26th |pages=B-62–B-65 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://tnsec.tn.nic.in/historical/Pre%20Independence.html|title=Pre-Independence Method of Election|publisher=Tamil Nadu State Election Commission, India|accessdate=3 November 2011|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20111029004115/http://tnsec.tn.nic.in/historical/Pre%20Independence.html|archive-date=29 October 2011|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The modern &quot;election&quot;, which consists of public elections of government officials, didn't emerge until the beginning of the 17th century when the idea of [[representative government]] took hold in North America and Europe.&lt;ref name = Brit/&gt;

Questions of [[suffrage]], especially suffrage for minority groups, have dominated the history of elections. Males, the dominant cultural group in North America and Europe, often dominated the [[:wikt:electorate|electorate]] and continue to do so in many countries.&lt;ref name = Brit/&gt; Early elections in countries such as the [[Elections in the United Kingdom|United Kingdom]] and [[Elections in the United States|the United States]] were dominated by [[landed gentry|landed]] or [[ruling class]] males.&lt;ref name = Brit/&gt; However, by 1920 all Western European and North American democracies had universal adult male suffrage (except Switzerland) and many countries began to consider [[women's suffrage]].&lt;ref name = Brit/&gt; Despite legally mandated universal suffrage for adult males, political barriers were sometimes erected to prevent fair access to elections (see [[civil rights movement]]).&lt;ref name = Brit/&gt;

==Characteristic==

===Suffrage===
The question of who may vote is a central issue in elections. The electorate does not generally include the entire population; for example, many countries prohibit those who are under the age of majority from voting, all jurisdictions require a minimum age for voting.

In Australia, Aboriginal people were not given the right to vote until 1962 (see [[Australian referendum, 1967 (Aboriginals)|1967 referendum entry]]) and in 2010 the federal government removed the rights of prisoners serving for 3 years or more to vote (a large proportion of which were Aboriginal Australians).

Suffrage is typically only for citizens of the country, though further limits may be imposed.

However, in the European Union, one can vote in municipal elections if one lives in the municipality and is an EU citizen; the nationality of the country of residence is not required. 
[[File:ElezioneMilano.jpg|thumb|right|Campaigners working on posters in [[Milan]], Italy, 2004]]
In some countries, voting is required by law; if an eligible voter does not cast a vote, he or she may be subject to punitive measures such as a fine. In Western Australia, the penalty for a first time offender failing to vote is a $20.00 fine, which increases to $50.00 if the offender refused to vote prior.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.elections.wa.gov.au/vote/failure-vote|title=Failure to Vote {{!}} Western Australian Electoral Commission|website=www.elections.wa.gov.au|language=en|access-date=2018-11-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Nomination of candidate===
A [[representative democracy]] requires a procedure to govern nomination for political office. In many cases, nomination for office is mediated through [[preselection]] processes in organized political parties.&lt;ref&gt;Reuven Hazan, 'Candidate Selection', in Lawrence LeDuc, Richard Niemi and Pippa Norris (eds), ''Comparing Democracies 2'', Sage Publications, London, 2002&lt;/ref&gt;

Non-partisan systems tend to be different from partisan systems as concerns nominations. In a [[direct democracy]], one type of [[non-partisan democracy]], any eligible person can be nominated. Although elections were used in ancient Athens, in Rome, and in the selection of popes and Holy Roman emperors, the origins of elections in the contemporary world lie in the gradual emergence of representative government in Europe and North America beginning in the 17th century. In some systems no nominations take place at all, with voters free to choose any person at the time of voting—with some possible exceptions such as through a minimum age requirement—in the jurisdiction. In such cases, it is not required (or even possible) that the members of the electorate be familiar with all of the eligible persons, though such systems may involve indirect elections at larger geographic levels to ensure that some first-hand familiarity among potential electees can exist at these levels (i.e., among the elected delegates).

As far as partisan systems, in some countries, only members of a particular party can be nominated (see [[one-party state]]).  Or, any eligible person can be nominated through a process; thus allowing him or her to be listed.

===Electoral systems===
Electoral systems are the detailed constitutional arrangements and [[voting system]]s that convert the vote into a political decision. The first step is to tally the votes, for which various [[vote counting systems]] and [[ballot]] types are used. Voting systems then determine the result on the basis of the tally. Most systems can be categorized as either [[Proportional representation|proportional]] or [[majoritarian]].  Among the former are [[party-list proportional representation]] and [[additional member system]].  Among the latter are [[First Past the Post electoral system]] (relative majority) and [[absolute majority]].  Many countries have growing electoral reform movements, which advocate systems such as [[approval voting]], [[single transferable vote]], [[Instant-runoff voting|instant runoff voting]] or a [[Condorcet method]]; these methods are also gaining popularity for lesser elections in some countries where more important elections still use more traditional counting methods.

While openness and [[accountability]] are usually considered cornerstones of a democratic system, the act of casting a vote and the content of a voter's ballot are usually an important exception.  The [[secret ballot]] is a relatively modern development, but it is now considered crucial in most free and fair elections, as it limits the effectiveness of intimidation.

===Scheduling===
The nature of democracy is that elected officials are accountable to the people, and they must return to the voters at prescribed intervals to seek their [[mandate (politics)|mandate]] to continue in office. For that reason most democratic constitutions provide that elections are held at fixed regular intervals. In the United States, elections for public offices are typically held between every two and six years in most states and at the federal level, with exceptions for elected judicial positions that may have longer terms of office. There is a variety of schedules, for example presidents: the [[President of Ireland]] is elected every seven years, the [[President of Russia]] and the [[President of Finland]] every six years, the [[President of France]] every five years, [[President of the United States]] every four years.

Pre-decided or fixed election dates have the advantage of fairness and predictability. However, they tend to greatly lengthen campaigns, and make [[dissolution of parliament|dissolving the legislature]] (parliamentary system) more problematic if the date should happen to fall at time when dissolution is inconvenient (e.g. when war breaks out). Other states (e.g., the [[United Kingdom]]) only set maximum time in office, and the executive decides exactly when within that limit it will actually go to the polls. In practice, this means the government remains in power for close to its full term, and choose an election date it calculates to be in its best interests (unless something special happens, such as a [[motion of no-confidence]]). This calculation depends on a number of variables, such as its performance in opinion polls and the size of its majority.

===Election campaigns===
{{main|Political campaign}}
When elections are called, politicians and their supporters attempt to influence policy by competing directly for the votes of constituents in what are called campaigns.  Supporters for a campaign can be either formally organized or loosely affiliated, and frequently utilize [[campaign advertising]]. It is common for political scientists to attempt to predict elections via [[Political Forecasting]] methods.

The most expensive election campaign included US$7 billion spent on the [[2012 United States presidential election]] and is followed by the US$5 billion spent on the [[2014 Indian general election]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web
| url = http://www.ndtv.com/elections/article/election-2014/india-s-spend-on-elections-could-challenge-us-record-report-493685
| title = India's spend on elections could challenge US record: report
| website = NDTV.com
| access-date = 2016-02-25
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Difficulties with elections===
[[File:The Presidential Election in Argentina, the Polling-Station at the Church of La Merced, Buenos Ayres.jpg|thumb|upright=1.35|[[Buenos Aires]] 1892 &quot;The rival voters were kept back by an armed force of police out of sight to others. Only batches of two or three were allowed to enter the polling-office at a time. Armed sentries guarded the gates and the doors.&quot; ([[Godefroy Durand]], ''[[The Graphic]]'', [[21 May]] [[1892]]).]]
{{main|Electoral fraud|Unfair election}}
{{see also|Electoral integrity|Foreign electoral intervention}}

In many of the countries with weak [[rule of law]], the most common reason why elections do not meet international standards of being &quot;free and fair&quot; is interference from the incumbent government. [[Dictator]]s may use the powers of the executive (police, martial law, censorship, physical implementation of the election mechanism, etc.) to remain in power despite popular opinion in favor of removal. Members of a particular faction in a legislature may use the power of the majority or supermajority (passing criminal laws, defining the electoral mechanisms including eligibility and district boundaries) to prevent the balance of power in the body from shifting to a rival faction due to an election.&lt;ref name=&quot;Brit&quot; /&gt;

Non-governmental entities can also interfere with elections, through physical force, verbal intimidation, or fraud, which can result in improper casting or counting of votes. Monitoring for and minimizing electoral fraud is also an ongoing task in countries with strong traditions of free and fair elections. Problems that prevent an election from being &quot;free and fair&quot; take various forms.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Free and Fair Elections|url=http://www.publicsphereproject.org/content/free-and-fair-elections|website=Public Sphere Project|accessdate=8 November 2015|date=2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Lack of open political debate or an informed electorate====
The electorate may be poorly informed about issues or candidates due to lack of [[freedom of the press]], lack of objectivity in the press due to state or corporate control, and/or lack of access to news and political media. [[Freedom of speech]] may be curtailed by the state, favoring certain viewpoints or state [[propaganda]].

====Unfair rules====

[[Gerrymandering]], exclusion of opposition candidates from eligibility for office, needlessly high restrictions on who may be a candidate, like [[ballot access]] rules, and manipulating thresholds for electoral success are some of the ways the structure of an election can be changed to favor a specific faction or candidate.

====Interference with campaigns====
{{see also|Foreign electoral intervention}}
Those in power may arrest or assassinate candidates, suppress or even criminalize campaigning, close campaign headquarters, harass or beat campaign workers, or intimidate voters with violence. [[Foreign electoral intervention]] can also occur, with the United States interfering between 1946 and 2000 in 81 elections and [[Russia]]/[[USSR]] in 36.&lt;ref name=&quot;LevinISQ2016&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Levin|first=Dov H.|url=http://isq.oxfordjournals.org/content/60/2/189|title=When the Great Power Gets a Vote: The Effects of Great Power Electoral Interventions on Election Results|journal=[[International Studies Quarterly]]|volume=60|issue=2|date=June 2016|pp=189–202|doi=10.1093/isq/sqv016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In 2018 the most intense interventions, by means of false information, were by [[China]] in [[Taiwan]] and by [[Russia]] in [[Latvia]]; the next highest levels were in Bahrain, Qatar and Hungary.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite report |url=https://www.v-dem.net/media/filer_public/99/de/99dedd73-f8bc-484c-8b91-44ba601b6e6b/v-dem_democracy_report_2019.pdf |title=Democracy Facing Global Challenges, V-DEM ANNUAL DEMOCRACY REPORT 2019, p.36 |date=2019-05-14 |access-date=2020-01-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:State audits.png|thumb|300px|Few US states check results]]

====Tampering with the election mechanism====
{{see also|Election audit|Certification of voting machines |Secret ballot|Voter impersonation |Voter ID laws|Voter suppression}}

This can include falsifying voter instructions,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.sanmateocourt.org/documents/grand_jury/2018/elections.pdf|title=Security of Election Announcements|last=2018-2019 San Mateo County Civil Grand Jury|date=July 24, 2019|publisher=Superior Court of California|access-date=August 20, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
violation of the [[secret ballot]], [[ballot stuffing]], tampering with voting machines,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2018/09/26/magazine/election-security-crisis-midterms.html|title=The Crisis of Election Security|last=Zetter|first=Kim|date=2018-09-26|work=The New York Times|access-date=2019-08-20|language=en-US|issn=0362-4331}}&lt;/ref&gt;
destruction of legitimately cast ballots,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/candidate-says-new-congressional-election-warranted-in-north-carolina/2019/02/21/acae4482-35e0-11e9-854a-7a14d7fec96a_story.html|title=N.C. board declares a new election in contested House race after the GOP candidate admitted he was mistaken in his testimony|last=Gardner|first=Amy|date=February 21, 2019|work=The Washington Post|access-date=August 20, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[voter suppression]], voter registration fraud, failure to validate voter residency, fraudulent tabulation of results, and use of physical force or verbal intimation at polling places. Other examples include persuading candidates not to run, such as through blackmailing, bribery, intimidation or physical violence.

== Show election ==
{{Anchor|Sham election}}
A '''sham election''', or '''show election''', is an election that is held purely for show; that is, without any significant political choice or real impact on results of election.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://definitions.uslegal.com/s/sham-election/|title=Sham Election Law and Legal Definition {{!}} USLegal, Inc.|last=Inc.|first=US Legal|website=definitions.uslegal.com|language=en-US|access-date=2018-07-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Show elections are a common event in [[Dictatorship|dictatorial regimes]] that feel the need to feign the appearance of public [[Legitimacy (political)|legitimacy]]. Published results usually show nearly 100% [[voter turnout]] and high support (typically at least 80%, and close to 100% in many cases) for the prescribed candidate(s) or for the [[referendum]] choice that favors the [[political party]] in power. Dictatorial regimes can also organize show elections with results simulating those that might be achieved in democratic countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=https://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/asia/kim-jong-un-wins-100-of-the-vote-in-north-korean-elections-9180814.html | title=Kim Jong-un wins 100% of the vote in his constituency| date=10 March 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Sometimes, only one government approved candidate is allowed to run in sham elections with no opposition candidates allowed, or opposition candidates are arrested on false charges (or even without any charges) before the election to prevent them from running.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.cnn.com/2012/02/21/world/meast/yemen-elections/index.html|title=Yemen holds presidential election with one candidate|first=Mohammed |last=Jamjoom|website=CNN}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/2018/01/29/egyptian-opposition-calls-boycott-elections-challengers-arrested/|title=Egyptian opposition calls for boycott of elections after challengers are arrested and attacked|first1=Raf|last1=Sanchez|first2=Magdy|last2=Samaan|date=29 January 2018|via=www.telegraph.co.uk}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;urlAlexei Navalny latest: Russian opposition leader arrested ahead of presidential election | The Independent&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/europe/alexei-navalny-latest-updates-russia-president-election-opposition-leader-putin-protests-a8222956.html |title=Alexei Navalny latest: Russian opposition leader arrested ahead of presidential election &amp;#124; The Independent |website= |accessdate=|date=22 February 2018 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Ballots may contain only one &quot;yes&quot; option, or in the case of a simple &quot;yes or no&quot; question, security forces often [[Persecution|persecute]] people who pick &quot;no&quot;, thus encouraging them to pick the &quot;yes&quot; option. In other cases, those who vote receive stamps in their passport for doing so, while those who did not vote (and thus do not receive stamps) are persecuted as [[Enemy of the people|enemies of the people]]. &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://content.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,764407,00.html|title=RUSSIA: Justice in The Baltic|date=1940-08-19|work=Time|access-date=2018-07-14|language=en-US|issn=0040-781X}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;urlYes, There Are Elections in North Korea and Heres How They Work - The Atlantic&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.theatlantic.com/international/archive/2014/03/north-korea-elections-guide/358875/ |title=Yes, There Are Elections in North Korea and Here's How They Work - The Atlantic |format= |website= |accessdate=|date=6 March 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In some cases, show elections can backfire against the party in power, especially if the regime believes they are popular enough to win without coercion or fraud. The most famous example of this was the [[1990 Myanmar general election]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.hrw.org/news/2010/05/26/burma-20-years-after-1990-elections-democracy-still-denied|title=Burma: 20 Years After 1990 Elections, Democracy Still Denied|date=2010-05-26|work=Human Rights Watch|access-date=2018-07-14|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Examples===
[[File:Wahlzettel-3.-Reich.jpg|thumb|right|A ballot from the [[1936 German parliamentary election and referendum|1936 elections in Nazi Germany]].]]

[[File:Stimmzettel-Anschluss.jpg|thumb|right|A ballot from the [[1938 German parliamentary election and referendum|1938 elections in Nazi Germany]] asking voters to approve the new [[Reichstag (Nazi Germany)|Reichstag]] and the [[Anschluss]]. The &quot;no&quot; box was made significantly smaller than the &quot;yes&quot; box.]]

Examples of sham elections are the [[1929 Italian general election|1929]] and [[1934 Italian general election|1934]] [[Elections in Italy|elections]] in [[Kingdom of Italy|Fascist Italy]], [[Elections in Nazi Germany|elections]] in [[Nazi Germany]], the [[Occupation of the Baltic States|1940 elections]] of the [[People's Parliament]]s in [[Estonian Soviet Socialist Republic|Estonia]], [[Latvian Soviet Socialist Republic|Latvia]] and [[Lithuanian Soviet Socialist Republic|Lithuania]], the [[1955 State of Vietnam referendum|1955 referendum in Vietnam]], the [[1958 Portuguese presidential election|1958 election]] in Portugal, post-[[Iranian Revolution|revolutionary]] Iran, the [[2014 Crimean status referendum|2014 Crimean referendum]], and in most [[Communist state|communist]] and [[socialist state|socalist]] states (e.g. [[Elections in East Germany|East Germany]], [[Elections in the Soviet Union|the Soviet Union]], [[Elections in China|China]], [[Elections in North Korea|North Korea]], [[Ba'athist Iraq]]).

A predetermined conclusion is always established by the regime through [[Political repression|suppression]] of the opposition, [[coercion]] of voters, [[Electoral fraud|vote rigging]], reporting a number of votes received greater than the number of voters, outright lying, or some combination of these.

In an extreme example, [[Charles D. B. King]] of [[Liberia]] was reported to have won by 234,000 votes in the [[1927 Liberian general election|1927 general election]], a &quot;majority&quot; that was over fifteen times larger than the number of eligible voters.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.liberiapastandpresent.org/1927ElectionsMF.htm|title=Liberia past and present 1927 elections|last=|first=|date=|website=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{div col|colwidth=22em}}
*[[Ballot access]]
*[[Concession (politics)]]
*[[Demarchy]]—&quot;Democracy without Elections&quot;
*[[Electoral calendar]]
*[[Electoral integrity]]
* [[Electoral system]]
*[[Election law]]
*[[Election litter]]
*[[Elections by country]]
*[[Electronic voting]]
*[[Fenno's paradox]]
*[[Full slate]]
*[[Garrat Elections]]
*[[Gerontocracy]]
*[[Issue voting]]
*[[Landslide election]]
*[[Meritocracy]]
*[[Multi-party system]]
*[[Nomination rules]]
*[[Party system]]
*[[Pluralism (political philosophy)]]
*[[Political science]]
*[[Polling station]]
*[[Reelection]]
*[[Slate (elections)|Slate]]
*[[Stunning elections]]
*[[Two-party system]]
*[[Voter turnout]]
*[[Voting system]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Bibliography==
{{div col|colwidth=30em}}
* [[Kenneth Arrow|Arrow, Kenneth J.]] 1963. ''Social Choice and Individual Values.'' 2nd ed. New Haven, CT: [[Yale University Press]].
* Benoit, Jean-Pierre and Lewis A. Kornhauser. 1994. &quot;Social Choice in a Representative Democracy.&quot; ''American Political Science Review'' 88.1: 185–192.
* Corrado Maria, Daclon. 2004. ''US elections and war on terrorism – Interview with professor Massimo Teodori'' Analisi Difesa, n. 50
* Farquharson, Robin. 1969. ''A Theory of Voting.'' New Haven, CT: Yale University Press.
* Mueller, Dennis C. 1996. ''Constitutional Democracy.'' Oxford: [[Oxford University Press]].
* Owen, Bernard, 2002. &quot;Le système électoral et son effet sur la représentation parlementaire des partis: le cas européen.&quot;, LGDJ;
* [[William H. Riker|Riker, William]]. 1980. ''Liberalism Against Populism: A Confrontation Between the Theory of Democracy and the Theory of Social Choice.'' Prospect Heights, IL: Waveland Press.
* Thompson, Dennis F. 2004. ''Just Elections: Creating a Fair Electoral Process in the U.S.'' Chicago: [[University of Chicago Press]]. {{ISBN|978-0226797649}}
* Ware, Alan. 1987. ''Citizens, Parties and the State.'' Princeton: [[Princeton University Press]].
{{div col end}}

==External links==
{{Wiktionary|election}}
{{Wikiquote}}
{{commons category|Elections}}
*[http://www.ipu.org/parline-e/parlinesearch.asp PARLINE database on national parliaments. Results for all parliamentary elections since 1966]
* [http://psephos.adam-carr.net/ &quot;Psephos,&quot; archive of recent electoral data from 182 countries]
*[http://www.electionguide.org ElectionGuide.org — Worldwide Coverage of National-level Elections]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20191012214801/http://parties-and-elections.de/ parties-and-elections.de: Database for all European elections since 1945]
*[http://www.aceproject.org ACE Electoral Knowledge Network] — electoral encyclopedia and related resources from a consortium of electoral agencies and organizations.
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20060108113500/http://www.angus-reid.com/tracker/ Angus Reid Global Monitor: Election Tracker]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20051228015533/http://www.idea.int/esd/world.cfm IDEA's Table of Electoral Systems Worldwide]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20070427195545/http://www.eurela.org/ European Election Law Association (Eurela)]
*[http://www.killercampaigning.com/local-elections-list-political-campaign-candidate-offices/ List of Local Elected Offices in the United States]
* [http://www.vote.caltech.edu/ Caltech/ MIT Voting Technology Project]

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Elections| ]]
[[Category:Politics]]</text>
      <sha1>c9umhk3sm19kapswzvb3c5mlblxzvjy</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
