  <page>
    <title>Etruscan language</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9455</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942383821</id>
      <parentid>942224144</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-24T09:48:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Salpynx</username>
        <id>18924881</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* Alphabet */ Main article has been split out to its own page</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Extinct language of ancient Italy}}
{{Infobox language
|name     = Etruscan
|image    = [[File:Perugia, Museo archeologico Nazionale dell'Umbria, cippo di Perugia.jpg|267px]]
|imagecaption=The [[Cippus Perusinus]], a stone tablet bearing 46 lines of incised Etruscan text, one of the longest extant Etruscan inscriptions. 3rd or 2nd century BC.
|states   = Ancient [[Etruria]]
|region   = [[Italian Peninsula]]
|era      = attested 700 BC to 20 AD&lt;ref name=PFreeman&gt;Freeman, Philip (1999). [https://scholarworks.umass.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1033&amp;context=etruscan_studies &quot;The Survival of the Etruscan Language&quot;]. ''Etruscan Studies'' 6.1 (1999): 75–84.&lt;/ref&gt;
|familycolor=grey
|fam1     = [[Tyrsenian languages|Tyrsenian]]? 
|iso3     = ett
|glotto   = etru1241
|glottorefname=Etruscan
|notice   = IPA
|map      = Idioma etrusco.png
|extinct  = &gt;20 AD&lt;ref name=PFreeman/&gt;|script = [[Old Italic script]]
}}
The '''Etruscan language''' ({{IPAc-en|ᵻ|ˈ|t|r|ʌ|s|k|ən}})&lt;ref&gt;Bauer, Laurie (2007). ''The Linguistics Student's Handbook''. Edinburgh.&lt;/ref&gt; was the [[spoken language|spoken]] and [[written language]] of the [[Etruscan civilization]], in [[Italy]], in the ancient region of [[Etruria]] (modern [[Tuscany]] plus western [[Umbria]] and northern [[Lazio|Latium]]) and in parts of [[Corsica]], [[Emilia-Romagna]], [[Veneto]], [[Lombardy]] and [[Campania]]. Etruscan influenced [[Latin]], but eventually was completely superseded by it. The Etruscans left around 13,000 [[epigraphy|inscriptions]] which have been found so far, only a small minority of which are of significant length; some bilingual inscriptions with texts also in Latin, [[Ancient Greek|Greek]], or [[Phoenician language|Phoenician]]; and a few dozen [[loanword]]s, such as the name [[Rome|Roma]], but Etruscan's influence was significant. Attested from 700 BC to AD 50, the relation of Etruscan to other languages has been a source of long-running speculation and study, with its being referred to at times as an [[language isolate|isolate]], one of the [[Tyrsenian languages]], and a number of other less well-known theories.

The consensus among linguists and etruscologists is that Etruscan is a [[Pre–Indo-European languages|pre–Indo-European language]],&lt;ref&gt;[[Massimo Pallottino]], ''La langue étrusque Problèmes et perspectives'', 1978.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Mauro Cristofani, ''Introduction to the study of the Etruscan'', Leo S. Olschki, 1991.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Romolo A. Staccioli, ''The &quot;mystery&quot; of the Etruscan language'', Newton &amp; Compton publishers, Rome, 1977.&lt;/ref&gt; and is closely related to the [[Raetic language]] spoken in the Alps, and to the [[Lemnian|language]] attested in a few inscriptions on [[Lemnos]].&lt;ref name=Schumacher1994&gt;Schumacher, Stefan (1994) Studi Etruschi in Neufunde ‘raetischer’ Inschriften Vol. 59 pp. 307–320 (German)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Schumacher1994b&gt;Schumacher, Stefan (1994) Neue ‘raetische’ Inschriften aus dem Vinschgau in Der Schlern Vol. 68 pp. 295-298 (German)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Schumacher1999&gt;Schumacher, Stefan (1999) Die Raetischen Inschriften: Gegenwärtiger Forschungsstand, spezifische Probleme und Zukunfstaussichten in I Reti / Die Räter, Atti del simposio 23–25 settembre 1993, Castello di Stenico, Trento, Archeologia delle Alpi, a cura di G. Ciurletti – F. Marzatico Archaoalp pp. 334–369 (German)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Schumacher2004&gt;Schumacher, Stefan (2004) Die Raetischen Inschriften. Geschichte und heutiger Stand der Forschung Archaeolingua. Innsbrucker Beiträge zur Kulturwissenschaft. (German)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Oettinger&gt;Norbert Oettinger, ''Seevölker und Etrusker'', 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=desimone2009&gt;de Simone Carlo (2009) ''La nuova iscrizione tirsenica di Efestia in Aglaia Archontidou'', Carlo de Simone, Emanuele Greco (Eds.), Gli scavi di Efestia e la nuova iscrizione ‘tirsenica’, Tripodes 11, 2009, pp. 3–58.  (Italian)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=marchesini2013&gt;Carlo de Simone, Simona Marchesini (Eds), ''La lamina di Demlfeld'' [= Mediterranea. Quaderni annuali dell'Istituto di Studi sulle Civiltà italiche e del Mediterraneo antico del Consiglio Nazionale delle Ricerche. Supplemento 8], Pisa – Roma: 2013. (Italian)&lt;/ref&gt;

Grammatically, the language is [[agglutinating]], with [[noun]]s and [[verb]]s showing [[suffix]]ed [[inflection]]al endings and [[ablaut]] in some cases. Nouns show four [[grammatical case|cases]], singular and [[grammatical number|plural numbers]], with a [[noun class|gender]] distinction between ''masculine'' and ''feminine'' in [[pronouns]].

Etruscan appears to have had a cross-linguistically common [[phonology|phonological]] system, with four [[phonemes|phonemic]] [[vowels]] and an apparent contrast between [[Aspirated consonant|aspirated and unaspirated]] [[Stop consonant|stops]]. The records of the language suggest that [[sound change|phonetic change]] took place over time, with the loss and then re-establishment of word-internal vowels, possibly due to the effect of Etruscan's word-initial [[stress (linguistics)|stress]].

[[Etruscan religion]] influenced [[Religion in ancient Rome|that of the Romans]], and many of the few surviving Etruscan language artifacts are of [[votive]] or religious significance. Etruscan was written in [[Etruscan alphabet|an alphabet]] derived from the [[Greek alphabet]]; this alphabet was the source of the [[Latin alphabet]]. The Etruscan language is also believed to be the source of certain important cultural words of [[Western Europe]] such as 'military' and 'person', which do not have obvious Indo-European roots.

==History of Etruscan literacy==
[[File:Haruspex.png|thumb|right|250px|Drawing of the inscriptions on the [[Liver of Piacenza]]; see ''[[haruspex]]'']]

Etruscan literacy was widespread over the [[Mediterranean Sea|Mediterranean]] shores, as evidenced by about 13,000 [[epigraphy|inscriptions]] (dedications, [[epitaph]]s, etc.), most fairly short, but some of considerable length.&lt;ref name=bonfante12&gt;Bonfante (1990), p. 12.&lt;/ref&gt; They date from about 700 BC.&lt;ref&gt;Bonfante (1990), p. 10.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Etruscans had a rich literature, as noted by Latin authors. [[Livy]] and [[Cicero]] were both aware that highly specialized Etruscan religious rites were codified in several sets of books written in Etruscan under the generic Latin title ''Etrusca Disciplina''. The ''Libri Haruspicini'' dealt with [[divination]] from the entrails of the sacrificed animal, while the ''Libri Fulgurales'' expounded the art of divination by observing [[lightning]]. A third set, the ''Libri Rituales'', might have provided a key to Etruscan civilization: its wider scope embraced Etruscan standards of social and political life, as well as ritual practices. According to the 4th century Latin writer [[Maurus Servius Honoratus]], a fourth set of Etruscan books existed; dealing with animal gods, but it is unlikely that any scholar living in that era could have read Etruscan. However, only one book (as opposed to inscription), the ''[[Liber Linteus]]'', survived, and only because the linen on which it was written was used as [[mummy]] wrappings.&lt;ref&gt;Van der Meer, L. Bouke, ed. ''Liber Linteus Zagrabiensis'' (= ''Monographs on antiquity'', vol. 4). Peeters, 2007,  {{ISSN|1781-9458}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 30 BC, [[Livy]] notes that Etruscan was once widely taught to Roman boys, but had since become replaced by the teaching of only Greek, while [[Varro]] notes that works of theatre had once been composed in Etruscan.&lt;ref&gt;Freeman, Philip. [https://scholarworks.umass.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1033&amp;context=etruscan_studies The Survival of Etruscan]. pp. 75–76.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Demise===
The date of extinction for Etruscan is held by scholarship to have been either in the late first century BC, or the early first century AD. Freeman's analysis of inscriptional evidence would appear to imply that Etruscan was still flourishing in the 2nd century BC, still alive in the first century BC, and surviving in at least one location in the beginning of the first century AD;&lt;ref name=Freeman82&gt;Freeman, Philip. [https://scholarworks.umass.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1033&amp;context=etruscan_studies The Survival of Etruscan]. p. 82&lt;/ref&gt;  however, the replacement of Etruscan by Latin likely occurred earlier in southern regions closer to Rome.&lt;ref name=Freeman79to80&gt;Freeman. [https://scholarworks.umass.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1033&amp;context=etruscan_studies The Survival of Etruscan]. pp. 79–80&lt;/ref&gt;

In Southern Etruria, the first Etruscan site to be Latinized was [[Veii]], when it was destroyed and repopulated by Romans in 396 BC.&lt;ref name=Freeman79to80/&gt; Caere (Cerveteri), another southerly Etruscan town on the coast 45 kilometers from Rome, appears to have shifted to Latin in the late 2nd century BC.&lt;ref name=Freeman79to80/&gt; In [[Tarquinia]] and [[Vulci]], Latin inscriptions coexisted with Etruscan inscriptions in wall paintings and grave markers for centuries, from the 3rd century BC until the early 1st century BC, after which Etruscan is replaced by exclusive use of Latin.&lt;ref name=Freeman79to80/&gt;

In Northern Etruria, Etruscan inscriptions continue after they disappear in Southern Etruria. At [[Clusium]] ([[Chiusi]]), tomb markings show mixed Latin and Etruscan in the first half of the 1st century BC, with cases where two subsequent generations are inscribed in Latin and then the third, youngest generation, surprisingly, is transcribed in Etruscan.&lt;ref name=Freeman79to80/&gt; At [[Perugia]], monolingual monumental inscriptions in Etruscan are still seen in the first half of the 1st century BC, while the period of bilingual inscriptions appears to have stretched from the 3rd century to the late 1st century BC.&lt;ref name=Freeman79to80/&gt; The isolated last bilinguals are found at three Northern sites. Inscriptions in [[Arezzo]] include one dated to 40 followed by two with slightly later dates, while in [[Volterra]] there is one dated to just after 40 BC and a final one dated to 10–20 AD; coins with written Etruscan near [[Saena]] have also been dated to 15 BC.&lt;ref&gt;Freeman, Philip. [https://scholarworks.umass.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1033&amp;context=etruscan_studies The Survival of Etruscan]. p. 81&lt;/ref&gt; Freeman notes that in rural areas the language may have survived a bit longer, and that a survival into the late 1st century AD and beyond &quot;cannot wholly be dismissed&quot;, especially given the revelation of Oscan writing in Pompeii's walls.&lt;ref&gt;Freeman, Philip. Survival of Etruscan. p. 82: &quot;How much longer may have Etruscan survived in isolated rural locations? The answer is impossible to say, given that we can only argue from evidence, not conjecture. But languages are notoriously tenacious, and the possibility of an Etruscan survival into the late 1st century A.D. and beyond cannot be wholly dismissed. Oscan graffiti on the walls of Pompeii show that non-Latin languages well into the 1st century A.D., making rural survival of Etruscan more credible. But this is only speculation...&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite the apparent extinction of Etruscan, it appears that Etruscan religious rites continued much later, continuing to use the Etruscan names of deities and possibly with some liturgical usage of the language. In late Republican and early Augustan times, various Latin sources including [[Cicero]] noted the esteemed reputation of Etruscan [[Divination|soothsayers]].&lt;ref&gt;Freeman, Philip. [https://scholarworks.umass.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1033&amp;context=etruscan_studies The Survival of Etruscan]. p. 77&lt;/ref&gt; An episode where lightning struck an inscription with the name Caesar, turning it into Aesar, was interpreted to have been a premonition of the deification of Caesar because of the resemblance to Etruscan ''aisar'', meaning &quot;gods&quot;, although this indicates knowledge of a single word and not the language. Centuries later and long after Etruscan is thought to have died out, [[Ammianus Marcellinus]] reports that [[Julian the Apostate]], the last pagan Emperor, apparently had Etruscan soothsayers accompany him on his military campaigns with books on war, lightning and celestial events, but the language these books were written in is unknown. According to [[Zosimus]], when Rome was faced with destruction by [[Alaric I|Alaric]] in 408 AD, the protection of nearby Etruscan towns was attributed to Etruscan pagan priests who claimed to have summoned a raging thunderstorm, and they offered their services &quot;in the ancestral manner&quot; to Rome as well, but the devout Christians of Rome refused the author, preferring death to help by pagans. Freeman notes that these events may indicate that a limited theological knowledge of Etruscan may have survived among the priestly caste much longer.&lt;ref&gt;Freeman, Philip. [https://scholarworks.umass.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1033&amp;context=etruscan_studies The Survival of Etruscan]. pp. 77–78&lt;/ref&gt; One 19th-century writer argued in 1892 that Etruscan deities retained an influence on early modern Tuscan folklore.&lt;ref&gt;Leland (1892). ''Etruscan Roman Remains in Popular Tradition''.&lt;/ref&gt;

Around 180, the Latin author [[Aulus Gellius]] mentions Etruscan alongside the [[Gaulish language]] in an anecdote.&lt;ref&gt;Aulus Gellius, ''Noctes Atticae''. Extract: ‘ueluti Romae nobis praesentibus uetus celebratusque homo in causis, sed repentina et quasi tumultuaria doctrina praeditus, cum apud praefectum urbi uerba faceret et dicere uellet inopi quendam miseroque uictu uiuere et furfureum panem esitare uinumque eructum et feditum potare. &quot;hic&quot;, inquit, &quot;eques Romanus apludam edit et flocces bibit&quot;. aspexerunt omnes qui aderant alius alium, primo tristiores turbato et requirente uoltu quidnam illud utriusque uerbi foret: post deinde, quasi nescio quid Tusce aut Gallice dixisset, uniuersi riserunt.’ English translation: ‘For instance in Rome in our presence, a man experienced and celebrated as a pleader, but furnished with a sudden and, as it were, hasty education, was speaking to the Prefect of the City, and wished to say that a certain man with a poor and wretched way of life ate bread from bran and drank bad and spoiled wine. &quot;This Roman knight&quot;, he said, &quot;eats apluda and drinks flocces.&quot; All who were present looked at each other, first seriously and with an inquiring expression, wondering what the two words meant; thereupon, as if he might have said something in, I don’t know, Gaulish or Etruscan, all of them burst out laughing.’ (based on Blom 2007: 183.)&lt;/ref&gt; Freeman notes that although Gaulish was clearly still alive during Gellius' time, his testimony may not indicate that Etruscan was still alive because the phrase could indicate a meaning of the sort of &quot;it's all Greek (incomprehensible) to me&quot;.&lt;ref name=Freeman78&gt;Freeman. Survival of Etruscan. p. 78&lt;/ref&gt;

At the time of its extinction, only a few educated Romans with antiquarian interests, such as [[Marcus Terentius Varro]], could read Etruscan. The Roman emperor [[Claudius]] (10&amp;nbsp;BC – AD&amp;nbsp;54), is considered to have possibly been able to read Etruscan, and authored a treatise on Etruscan history; a separate dedication made by Claudius implies a knowledge from &quot;diverse Etruscan sources&quot;, but it is unclear if any were fluent speakers of Etruscan.&lt;ref&gt;Freeman, Philip. [https://scholarworks.umass.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1033&amp;context=etruscan_studies The Survival of Etruscan]. p. 78&lt;/ref&gt; [[Plautia Urgulanilla]], the emperor's first wife, was Etruscan.&lt;ref&gt;For Urgulanilla, see [[Suetonius]], ''Life of Claudius'', section 26.1; for the 20 books, same work, section 42.2.&lt;/ref&gt;

Etruscan had some influence on Latin, as a few dozen Etruscan words and names were borrowed by the Romans, some of which remain in modern languages, among which are possibly ''columna'' &quot;column&quot;, ''voltur'' &quot;vulture&quot;, ''tuba'' &quot;trumpet&quot;, ''vagina'' &quot;sheath&quot;, ''populus'' &quot;people&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Ostler, Nicholas (2009). ''Ad Infinitum: A Biography of Latin and the World It Created.'' London: HarperPress, 2009, pp. 323 ff.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Etruscan civilization map.png|thumb|300px|Maximum extent of Etruscan civilization and the twelve Etruscan League cities.]]

==Geographic distribution==
Inscriptions have been found in north-west and west-central Italy, in the region that even now bears the name of the [[Etruscan civilization]], [[Tuscany]] (from Latin ''tuscī'' &quot;Etruscans&quot;), as well as in modern [[Latium]] north of Rome, in today's [[Umbria]] west of the [[Tiber]], in [[Campania]] and in the [[Po Valley]] to the north of Etruria. This range may indicate a maximum Italian homeland where the language was at one time spoken.

Outside mainland Italy, inscriptions have been found in [[Corsica]], [[Elba]], [[Gallia Narbonensis]], [[Greece]], the [[Balkans]], the [[Black Sea]].&lt;ref&gt;A summary of the locations of the inscriptions published in the EDP project, given below under ''External links'', is stated in its Guide.&lt;/ref&gt; But by far, the greatest concentration is in Italy.

==Classification==
The [[phonology]] of Etruscan is known through the alternation of Greek and Etruscan letters in some inscriptions (for example, the [[Iguvine Tablets]]), and many individual words are known through loans into or from Greek and Latin, as well as explanations of Etruscan words by ancient authors. A few concepts of word formation have been formulated (see below). Modern knowledge of the language is incomplete.

===Tyrsenian family hypothesis===
{{Main|Tyrsenian languages}}
[[File:Common Tyrrhenic model.svg|thumb|Tyrrhenian language family tree as proposed by de Simone and Marchesini (2013)&lt;ref name=marchesini2013/&gt;]]
In 1998, [[Helmut Rix]] put forward the view that Etruscan is related to other members of what he called the &quot;[[Tyrsenian language family]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Rix, Helmut (1998). ''Rätisch und Etruskisch''. Institut für Sprachwissenschaft der Universität Innsbruck: Innsbruck.&lt;/ref&gt; Rix's Tyrsenian family of languages—composed of [[Rhaetian language|Raetic]], anciently spoken in the [[eastern Alps]], and [[Lemnian language|Lemnian]], together with Etruscan—has gained acceptance among scholars.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Baldi|first=Philip Baldi|author-link=Philip Baldi|title=The Foundations of Latin|publisher=Walter de Gruyter|year=2002|pages=111–112|isbn=978-3-11-080711-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Comrie|first=Bernard|title=Languages of the world, in &quot;The handbook of linguistics&quot;|editor=Mark Aronoff, Janie Rees-Miller|publisher=Blackwell/Wiley|location=Oxford|date=15 April 2008|page=25}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Beekes, Robert S. P. (2003). ''The Origin of the Etruscans''. Koninklijke Nederlandse Akademie van Wetenschappen: Amsterdam.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Van der Meer, L. Bouke (2004). ''Etruscan origins: Language and Archaeology'', in: ''Bulletin antieke beschaving'', vol. 79.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;cambridge&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Woodard|first=Roger D.|title=The Ancient Languages of Europe|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=aPEENAEp938C|year=2008|publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=978-1-139-46932-6|page=142}}&lt;/ref&gt; Rix's Tyrsenian family has been confirmed by Stefan Schumacher,&lt;ref name=Schumacher1994/&gt;&lt;ref name=Schumacher1994b/&gt;&lt;ref name=Schumacher1999/&gt;&lt;ref name=Schumacher2004/&gt; Norbert Oettinger,&lt;ref name=Oettinger/&gt; [[Carlo De Simone (linguist)|Carlo De Simone]],&lt;ref name=desimone2009/&gt; and Simona Marchesini.&lt;ref name=marchesini2013/&gt; Common features between Etruscan, Raetic, and Lemnian have been found in [[Morphology (linguistics)|morphology]], [[phonology]], and [[syntax]]. On the other hand, few lexical correspondences are documented, at least partly due to the scant number of Raetic and Lemnian texts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://mnamon.sns.it/index.php?page=Lingua&amp;id=41&amp;lang=en |title=Raetic (languages) |author=Simona Marchesini (translation by Melanie Rockenhaus) |date= 2013|website=Mnamon – Ancient Writing Systems in the Mediterranean|publisher=Scuola Normale Superiore|access-date=26 July 2018 |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.univie.ac.at/raetica/wiki/Raetica |title=Raetica |author=Kluge Sindy, Salomon Corinna, Schumacher Stefan|date= 2013–2018|website=Thesaurus Inscriptionum Raeticarum|publisher= Department of Linguistics, University of Vienna|access-date=26 July 2018 |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Tyrsenian family, or Common Tyrrhenic, in this case is often considered to be [[Paleo-European language|Paleo-European]] and to [[pre-Indo-European languages|predate the arrival of Indo-European languages]] in southern Europe.&lt;ref name=&quot;auto&quot;&gt;Mellaart, James (1975),  &quot;The Neolithic of the Near East&quot; (Thames and Hudson)&lt;/ref&gt; Several scholars believe that the [[Lemnian language]] could have arrived in the [[Aegean Sea]] during the Late [[Bronze Age]], when Mycenaean rulers recruited groups of mercenaries from [[Sicily]], [[Sardinia]] and various parts of the Italian peninsula.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=de Ligt|first1=Luuk|title=An 'Eteocretan' inscription from Prasos and the homeland of the Sea Peoples|journal=Talanta|date=2008–2009|volume=XL–XLI|pages=151–172|url=http://www.talanta.nl/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/TAL-40-412008-2009-pag-151-172-DeLigt.pdf|accessdate=13 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Scholars such as Norbert Oettinger, Michel Gras and Carlo De Simone think that Lemnian is the testimony of an Etruscan piratesque or commercial settlement on the island that took place before 700 BC, not related to the Sea Peoples.&lt;ref&gt;Carlo de Simone, La nuova Iscrizione ‘Tirsenica’ di Lemnos (Efestia, teatro): considerazioni generali, in Rasenna: Journal of the Center for Etruscan Studies, pp. 1–34.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Robert Drews]], ''The End of the Bronze Age: Changes in Warfare and the Catastrophe of ca. 1200 B.C'', Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 1995, p. 59, {{ISBN|978-0-691-04811-6}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Some scholars think that the [[Camunic language]], an extinct language spoken in the [[Central Alps]] of [[Northern Italy]], may be also related to Etruscan and to [[Raetic language|Raetic]].&lt;ref name=Schumacher2000&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.blackwellreference.com/public/tocnode?id=g9780631220398_chunk_g97806312203989_ss1-3 |title=Camunic : Encyclopedia of the Languages of Europe : Blackwell Reference Online |publisher=Blackwellreference.com |date= |accessdate=2018-05-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;M. G. Tibiletti Bruno. 1978. ''Camuno, retico e pararetico'', in ''Lingue e dialetti dell'Italia antica'' ('Popoli e civiltà dell'Italia antica', 6), a cura di A. L. Prosdocimi, Roma, pp.&amp;nbsp;209–255. (Italian)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Isolate hypothesis===
Etruscan was traditionally considered to be a [[language isolate]]. In the first century BC, the Greek historian [[Dionysius of Halicarnassus]] stated that the Etruscan language was unlike any other.&lt;ref&gt;''Rhōmaikē archaiologia'', 1.30.2.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Giuliano Bonfante]], a leading scholar in the field, argued in 1990 that &quot;it resembles no other language in Europe or elsewhere&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;bonfante12&quot; /&gt;

===Other hypotheses===
Over the centuries many hypotheses on the Etruscan language have been developed, many of which have not been accepted or have been considered highly speculative. The interest in Etruscan antiquities and the Etruscan language found its modern origin in a book by a Renaissance Dominican friar, [[Annio da Viterbo]], a [[Kabbalah|cabalist]] and [[oriental studies|orientalist]] now remembered mainly for literary forgeries. In 1498, Annio published his antiquarian miscellany titled ''Antiquitatum variarum'' (in 17 volumes) where he put together a theory in which both the [[Hebrew]] and Etruscan languages were said to originate from a single source, the &quot;Aramaic&quot; spoken by [[Noah]] and his descendants, founders of the Etruscan city, [[Viterbo]]. Annio also started to excavate Etruscan tombs, unearthing sarcophagi and inscriptions, and made a bold attempt at deciphering the Etruscan language.{{Citation needed|date=June 2016}}

The 19th century saw numerous attempts to reclassify Etruscan. Ideas of [[Semitic languages|Semitic]] origins found supporters until this time. In 1858, the last attempt was made by [[Johann Gustav Stickel]], [[Jena University]] in his ''Das Etruskische […] als semitische Sprache erwiesen''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Das Etruskische durch Erklärung von Inschriften und Namen als semitische Sprache erwiesen|last=Stickel|first=Johann Gustav|publisher=Wilhelm Engelmann|place=Leipzig|year=1858}}&lt;/ref&gt; A reviewer&lt;ref&gt;Gildemeister, Johannes. In: ''ZDMG'' '''13''' (1859), pp. 289–304.&lt;/ref&gt; concluded that Stickel brought forward every possible argument which would speak for that hypothesis, but he proved the opposite of what he had attempted to do. In 1861, Robert Ellis proposed that Etruscan was related to [[Armenian language|Armenian]], which is nowadays acknowledged as an [[Indo-European languages|Indo-European]] language.&lt;ref&gt;Ellis, Robert (1861). ''The Armenian origin of the Etruscans''. London: Parker, Son, &amp; Bourn.&lt;/ref&gt; Exactly 100 years later, a relationship with [[Albanian language|Albanian]] was to be advanced by [[Zecharia Mayani]], but Albanian is also known to be an Indo-European language.&lt;ref&gt;Mayani, Zacharie (1961). ''The Etruscans Begin to Speak''. Translation by Patrick Evans. London: Souvenir Press.&lt;/ref&gt;

Several theories from the late 19th and early 20th centuries connected Etruscan to [[Uralic languages|Uralic]] or even [[Altaic languages]]. In 1874, the British scholar [[Isaac Taylor (priest)|Isaac Taylor]] brought up the idea of a genetic relationship between Etruscan and [[Hungarian Language|Hungarian]], of which also [[Jules Martha]] would approve in his exhaustive study ''La langue étrusque'' (1913).&lt;ref name=&quot;szabir.com&quot; /&gt; In 1911, the French orientalist Baron Carra de Vaux suggested a connection between Etruscan and the [[Altaic languages]].&lt;ref name=&quot;szabir.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.szabir.com/blog/etruscans-huns-and-hungarians/ |title=Etruscans, Huns and Hungarians|last=Tóth |first=Alfréd |accessdate=June 17, 2010 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100302115355/http://www.szabir.com/blog/etruscans-huns-and-hungarians/ |archivedate=March 2, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The Hungarian connection was recently revived by [[Mario Alinei]], Emeritus Professor of Italian Languages at the [[University of Utrecht]].&lt;ref&gt;Alinei, Mario (2003). [http://www.uu.nl/faculty/humanities/NL/Onderzoek/hoogleraren/Pages/emeritushoogleraren.aspx ''Etrusco: una forma arcaica di ungherese'']. Il Mulino: Bologna.&lt;/ref&gt; Alinei's proposal has been rejected by Etruscan experts such as Giulio M. Facchetti,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.uninsubria.eu/research/compscicomm/CV_CompSciComm/Facchetti.pdf |title=Archived copy |access-date=2010-10-15 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110720173303/http://www.uninsubria.eu/research/compscicomm/CV_CompSciComm/Facchetti.pdf |archive-date=2011-07-20 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Facchetti, Giulio M. [http://didattica.iulm.it/scritture_dimenticate/JIES.pdf &quot;The Interpretation of Etruscan Texts and its Limits&quot; (PDF)]{{Dead link|date=July 2018 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}. In: ''Journal of Indo-European Studies'' '''33''', 3/4, 2005, 359–388. Quote from p.&amp;nbsp;371: ‘[…] suffice it to say that Alinei clears away all the combinatory work done on Etruscan (for grammar specially) to try to make Uralic inflections fit without ripping the seams. He completely ignores the aforesaid recent findings in phonology (and phoneme/grapheme relationships), returning to the obsolete but convenient theory that the handwriting changed and orthography was not consolidated'.&lt;/ref&gt; Finno-Ugric experts such as Angela Marcantonio,&lt;ref&gt;Marcantonio, Angela (2004). &quot;Un caso di 'fantalinguistica'. A proposito di Mario Alinei: 'Etrusco: una forma arcaica di ungherese'.&quot; In: ''Studi e Saggi Linguistici'' '''XLII''', 173–200, where Marcantonio states that &quot;La tesi dell’Alinei è da rigettare senza alcuna riserva&quot; (&quot;Alinei's thesis must be rejected without any reservation&quot;), criticizes his methodology and the fact that he ignored the comparison with Latin and Greek words in pnomastic and institutional vocabulary. Large quotes can be read at Melinda Tamás-Tarr &quot;[http://www.osservatorioletterario.net/enigmaetrusco3.pdf Sulla scrittura degli Etruschi: «Ma è veramente una scrittura etrusca»? Cosa sappiamo degli Etruschi III]&quot;. In: ''Osservatorio letterario. Ferrara e l’Altrove'' ''X/XI'', Nos. 53/54 (November–December/January–February 2006/2007), 67–73. Marcantonio is Associated Professor of Historical Linguistics and Finno-Ugric Studies at the University of Rome &quot;La Sapienza&quot; ([http://sites.google.com/site/angelamarcantonio/ personal website]).&lt;/ref&gt; and by Hungarian historical linguists such as Bela Brogyanyi.&lt;ref&gt;Brogyanyi, Bela. &quot;[http://redaktion.gesus-info.de/S&amp;S-online/S&amp;S_38-2008.pdf Die ungarische alternative Sprachforschung und ihr ideologischer Hintergrund – Versuch einer Diagnose]&quot;. In: ''Sprache &amp; Sprachen'' '''38''' (2008), 3–15, who claims that Alinei shows a complete ignorance on Etruscan and Hungarian [&quot;glänzt er aber durch völlige Unkenntnis des Ungarischen und Etruskischen (vgl. Alinei 2003)&quot;] and that the thesis of a relation between Hungarian and Etruscan languages deserves no attention.&lt;/ref&gt;

The idea of a relation between the language of the [[Minoan civilization|Minoan]] Linear A scripts was taken into consideration as the main hypothesis by [[Michael Ventris]] before he discovered that, in fact, the language behind the later [[Linear B]] script was [[Mycenean Greek|Mycenean]], a [[Ancient Greek dialects|Greek dialect]]. It has been proposed to possibly be part of a wider Paleo-European &quot;Aegean&quot; language family, which would also include [[Minoan language|Minoan]], [[Eteocretan language|Eteocretan]] (possibly descended from Minoan) and [[Eteocypriot language|Eteocypriot]]. This has been proposed by Giulio Mauro Facchetti, a researcher who has dealt with both Etruscan and Minoan, and supported by S. Yatsemirsky, referring to some similarities between Etruscan and Lemnian on one hand, and [[Linear A|Minoan]] and Eteocretan on the other.{{Sfn | Facchetti | 2001}}{{Sfn | Facchetti | 2002 | p = 136}} It has also been proposed that this language family is related to the pre-Indo-European languages of Anatolia, based upon place name analysis.&lt;ref name=&quot;auto&quot;/&gt;

Others have suggested that Tyrsenian languages may yet be distantly related to early [[Indo-European languages]], such as those of the [[Anatolian languages|Anatolian branch]].&lt;ref&gt;For example, Steinbauer (1999).&lt;/ref&gt; More recently, [[Robert S. P. Beekes]] argued in 2002 that the people later known as the Lydians and Etruscans had originally lived in northwest [[Anatolia]], with a coastline to the [[Sea of Marmara]], whence they were driven by the [[Phrygians]] ''circa'' 1200 BC, leaving a remnant known in antiquity as the Tyrsenoi. A segment of this people moved south-west to [[Lydia]], becoming known as the [[Lydian language|Lydians]], while others sailed away to take refuge in Italy, where they became known as Etruscans.&lt;ref&gt;Beekes, Robert S. P.[http://www.knaw.nl/Content/Internet_KNAW/publicaties/pdf/20021051.pdf &quot;The Origin of the Etruscans&quot;]{{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120117190941/http://www.knaw.nl/Content/Internet_KNAW/publicaties/pdf/20021051.pdf |date=2012-01-17 }}. In: ''Biblioteca Orientalis'' '''59''' (2002), 206–242.&lt;/ref&gt;  This account draws on the well-known story by [[Herodotus]] (I, 94) of the Lydian origin of the Etruscans or Tyrrhenians, famously rejected by [[Dionysius of Halicarnassus]] (book I), partly on the authority of Xanthus, a Lydian historian, who had no knowledge of the story, and partly on what he judged to be the different languages, laws, and religions of the two peoples.

In 2006, Frederik Woudhuizen went further on Herodotus' traces, suggesting that Etruscan belongs to the [[Anatolian languages|Anatolian]] branch of the Indo-European family, specifically to [[Luwian]].&lt;ref name=&quot;luwianseapeoples&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Woudhuizen|first=Frederik Christiaan|title=The Ethnicity of the Sea Peoples|year=2006|publisher=Erasmus Universiteit|location=Rotterdam|page=139|url=http://repub.eur.nl/res/pub/7686/Woudhuizen%20bw.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; Woudhuizen revived a [[Etruscan civilization#Lydian immigration hypothesis|conjecture]] to the effect that the Tyrsenians came from [[Anatolia]], including [[Lydia]], whence they were driven by the [[Cimmerians]] in the early Iron Age, 750–675 BC, leaving some colonists on [[Lemnos]]. He makes a number of comparisons of Etruscan to [[Luwian]] and asserts that Etruscan is modified Luwian. He accounts for the non-Luwian features as a [[Mysia]]n influence: &quot;deviations from Luwian [...] may plausibly be ascribed to the dialect of the indigenous population of Mysia.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Woudhuizen 2006 p. 86&lt;/ref&gt; According to Woudhuizen, the Etruscans were initially colonizing the Latins, bringing the alphabet from Anatolia.

Another proposal, pursued mainly by a few linguists from the former Soviet Union, suggested a relationship with [[Northeast Caucasian]] (or Daghestanian) languages.&lt;ref name=&quot;robertson&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|first=Ed |last=Robertson |title=Etruscan's genealogical linguistic relationship with Nakh–Daghestanian: a preliminary evaluation |year=2006 |url=http://www.nostratic.ru/books/(329)EGRWND.pdf |format=PDF |accessdate=2009-07-13 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110810021157/http://www.nostratic.ru/books/(329)EGRWND.pdf |archivedate=10 August 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;starostin&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |last=Starostin | first=Sergei | author1-link=Sergei Starostin | last2=Orel | first2=Vladimir | year=1989 | contribution=Etruscan and North Caucasian| title=Explorations in Language Macrofamilies | editor-last =Shevoroshkin | editor-first=Vitaliy | series=Bochum Publications in Evolutionary Cultural Semiotics | issue=23 | publisher=Bochum |postscript=.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Writing system==
===Alphabet===
[[File:L'Arringatore.jpg|thumb|250px|''[[The Orator]]'', c. 100 BC, an [[Etruscan art|Etrusco]]-[[Roman sculpture|Roman]] [[bronze sculpture]] depicting Aule Metele (Latin: ''Aulus Metellus''), an [[Etruscan civilization|Etruscan]] man of Roman senatorial rank, engaging in [[rhetoric]]. The statue features an inscription in the Etruscan alphabet]]
{{Main|Etruscan alphabet}}

The [[Latin script]] owes its existence to the Etruscan alphabet, which was adapted for Latin in the form of the [[Old Italic script]]. The Etruscan alphabet&lt;ref&gt;The alphabet can also be found with alternative forms of the letters at [http://www.omniglot.com/writing/etruscan.htm Omniglot].&lt;/ref&gt; employs a [[Euboea]]n variant&lt;ref name=bonfantech2&gt;Bonfante (1990) chapter 2.&lt;/ref&gt; of the [[Greek alphabet]] using the letter [[digamma]] and was in all probability transmitted through [[Ischia|Pithecusae]] and [[Cumae]], two Euboean settlements in southern Italy. This system is ultimately derived from [[history of the alphabet|West Semitic scripts]].

The Etruscans recognized a 26-letter alphabet, which makes an early appearance incised for decoration on a small [[bucchero]] terracotta lidded vase in the shape of a cockerel at the Metropolitan Museum of Art, ca 650–600 BC.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.khanacademy.org/humanities/ancient-art-civilizations/etruscan/a/bucchero|title=Bucchero|website=Khan Academy|accessdate=15 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; The full complement of 26 has been termed the model alphabet.&lt;ref&gt;Bonfantes (2002) page 55.&lt;/ref&gt; The Etruscans did not use four letters of it, mainly because Etruscan did not have the voiced stops ''b'', ''d'' and ''g''; and also no ''o''. They innovated one letter for ''f''.&lt;ref name=&quot;bonfantech2&quot; /&gt;

===Text===
Writing was from right to left except in archaic inscriptions, which occasionally used [[boustrophedon]]. An example found at [[Cerveteri]] used left to right. In the earliest inscriptions, the words are continuous. From the sixth century BC, they are separated by a dot or a colon, which symbol might also be used to separate syllables. Writing was phonetic; the letters represented the sounds and not conventional spellings. On the other hand, many inscriptions are highly abbreviated and often casually formed, so the identification of individual letters is sometimes difficult. Spelling might vary from city to city, probably reflecting differences of pronunciation.&lt;ref&gt;The Bonfantes (2002) p. 56.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Complex consonant clusters===
Speech featured a heavy stress on the first syllable of a word, causing [[Syncope (phonetics)|syncopation]] by weakening of the remaining vowels, which then were not represented in writing: ''Alcsntre'' for ''Alexandros'', ''Rasna'' for ''Rasena''.&lt;ref name=&quot;bonfantech2&quot; /&gt; This speech habit is one explanation of the Etruscan &quot;impossible consonant clusters&quot;. The [[Sonorant|resonants]], however, may have been syllabic, accounting for some of the clusters (see below under [[#Consonants|Consonants]]). In other cases, the scribe sometimes inserted a vowel: Greek ''Hēraklēs'' became ''Hercle'' by syncopation and then was expanded to ''Herecele''. Pallottino&lt;ref&gt;Page 261&lt;/ref&gt; regarded this variation in vowels as &quot;instability in the quality of vowels&quot; and accounted for the second phase (e.g. ''Herecele'') as &quot;[[vowel harmony]], i.e., of the assimilation of vowels in neighboring syllables ....&quot;

===Phases===
The writing system had two historical phases: the archaic from the seventh to fifth centuries BC, which used the early Greek alphabet, and the later from the fourth to first centuries BC, which modified some of the letters. In the later period, syncopation increased.

The alphabet went on in modified form after the language disappeared. In addition to being the source of the Roman alphabet, it has been suggested that it passed northward into [[Veneto]] and from there through [[Raetia]] into the [[Germanic languages|Germanic]] lands, where it became the [[Elder Futhark]] alphabet, the oldest form of the [[runes]].&lt;ref&gt;The Bonfantes (2002), pp. 117 ff.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Corpus==
The Etruscan corpus is edited in the ''[[Corpus Inscriptionum Etruscarum]]'' (CIE) and ''[[Thesaurus Linguae Etruscae]]'' (TLE).&lt;ref&gt;
Massimo Pallottino, Maristella Pandolfini Angeletti,   ''Thesaurus linguae Etruscae'', Volume 1 (1978); review by A. J.  Pfiffig in ''Gnomon'' 52.6 (1980), 561–563.
Supplements in 1984, 1991 and 1998. A 2nd revised edition by Enrico Benelli appeared in 2009; review by G. van Heems, [http://bmcr.brynmawr.edu/2010/2010-01-05.html Bryn Mawr Classical Review 2010.01.05].
&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:EtruscanLanguage2.JPG|thumb|The Pyrgi Tablets laminated sheets of gold with a treatise both in Etruscan and [[Phoenician language]]s in the [[National Etruscan Museum|Etruscan Museum in Rome]]]]

===Bilingual text===
The [[Pyrgi Tablets]] are a bilingual text in Etruscan and [[Phoenician language|Phoenician]] engraved on three gold leaves, one for the Phoenician and two for the Etruscan. The Etruscan language portion has 16 lines and 37 words. The date is roughly 500 BC.&lt;ref name=B2002F58&gt;The Bonfantes (2002) p. 58.&lt;/ref&gt;

The tablets were found in 1964 by Massimo Pallottino during an excavation at the ancient Etruscan port of [[Pyrgi]], now [[Santa Severa]]. The only new Etruscan word that could be extracted from close analysis of the tablets was the word for &quot;three&quot;, ''ci''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Robinson|first1=Andrew|title=Lost languages : the enigma of the world's undeciphered scripts|date=2002|publisher=McGraw-Hill|location=New York|isbn=0071357432|page=[https://archive.org/details/isbn_9780071357432/page/170 170]|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/isbn_9780071357432/page/170}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Longer texts===
According to Rix and his collaborators, only two unified (though fragmentary) texts are available in Etruscan:
* The ''[[Liber Linteus Zagrabiensis]]'', which was later used for mummy wrappings in [[Egypt]]. Roughly 1,200&amp;nbsp;words of readable text, mainly repetitious prayers, yielded about 50&amp;nbsp;lexical items.&lt;ref name=&quot;B2002F58&quot; /&gt;
* The ''[[Tabula Capuana]]'' (the inscribed tile from [[Capua]]) has about 300&amp;nbsp;readable words in 62&amp;nbsp;lines, dating to the fifth century BC.

Some additional longer texts are:
* The lead foils of Punta della Vipera have about 40&amp;nbsp;legible words having to do with ritual formulae. It is dated to about 500&amp;nbsp;BC.&lt;ref&gt;Brief description and picture at [http://www.comune.santamarinella.rm.it/museo/html/inglese/a151.html ''The principle discoveries with Etruscan inscriptions''] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070703093518/http://www.comune.santamarinella.rm.it/museo/html/inglese/a151.html |date=2007-07-03 }}, article published by the Borough of [[Santa Marinella]] and the Archaeological Department of Southern Etruria of the Italian government.&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[Cippus Perusinus]], a stone slab (cippus) found at [[Perugia]], contains 46 lines and 130&amp;nbsp;words.
* The [[Piacenza Liver]], a bronze model of a sheep's liver representing the sky, has the engraved names of the gods ruling different sections.
* The [[Tabula Cortonensis]], a bronze tablet from [[Cortona]], is believed to record a legal contract, with about 200&amp;nbsp;words. Discovered in 1992, this new tablet contributed the word for &quot;lake&quot;, ''tisś'', but not much else.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Robinson |first1=Andrew |title=Lost Languages: The enigma of the world's undeciphered scripts |year=2002 |publisher=McGraw-Hill |location=New York |isbn=0071357432 |page=[https://archive.org/details/isbn_9780071357432/page/181 181] |url-access=registration |url=https://archive.org/details/isbn_9780071357432/page/181 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* A [[stele]], from a [[Sanctuary at Poggio Colla]], believed to be connected with the cult of the goddess [[Uni (mythology)|Uni]], with about 70&amp;nbsp;letters. Only discovered in 2016, it is still in the process of being deciphered.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://blog.smu.edu/research/2016/08/24/one-of-the-most-significant-etruscan-discoveries-in-decades-names-female-goddess-uni/ |title=One of the most significant Etruscan discoveries in decades names female goddess Uni |department=SMU Research |website=blog.smu.edu |accessdate=15 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Inscriptions on monuments===
[[File:Cerveteri,_necropoli_della_banditaccia,_via_sepolcrale_principale,_01.jpg|thumb|right|Tumulus on a street at Banditaccia, the main necropolis of [[Caere]]]]

The main material repository of [[Etruscan civilization]], from the modern perspective, is its tombs, all other public and private buildings having been dismantled and the stone reused centuries ago. The tombs are the main source of Etruscan portables, provenance unknown, in collections throughout the world. Their incalculable value has created a brisk black market in Etruscan ''objets d'art'' – and equally brisk law enforcement effort, as it is illegal to remove any objects from Etruscan tombs without authorization from the Italian government.

The magnitude of the task involved in cataloguing them means that the total number of tombs is unknown. They are of many types. Especially plentiful are the [[hypogeum|hypogeal]] or &quot;underground&quot; chambers or system of chambers cut into [[tuff]] and covered by a [[tumulus]]. The interior of these tombs represents a habitation of the living stocked with furniture and favorite objects. The walls may display painted [[mural]]s, the predecessor of wallpaper. Tombs identified as Etruscan date from the [[Villanovan]] period to about 100 BC, when presumably the cemeteries were abandoned in favor of Roman ones.&lt;ref&gt;Some Internet articles on the tombs in general are:&lt;br&gt;
''[http://www.mysteriousetruscans.com/tombs.html Etruscan Tombs]'' at mysteriousetruscans.com.&lt;br&gt;
''[http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,936863,00.html Scientific Tomb-Robbing]'', article in ''Time'', Monday, Feb. 25, 1957, displayed at time.com.&lt;br&gt;
''[http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,907013,00.html Hot from the Tomb: The Antiquities Racket]'', article in ''Time'', Monday, Mar. 26, 1973, displayed at time.com.&lt;/ref&gt; Some of the major cemeteries are as follows:
*[[Caere]] or [[Cerveteri]], a [[UNESCO]] site.&lt;ref name=cervtarq&gt;Refer to [https://whc.unesco.org/en/list/1158 Etruscan Necropoleis of Cerveteri and Tarquinia], a World Heritage site.&lt;/ref&gt; Three complete [[necropoleis]] with streets and squares. Many [[hypogeum|hypogea]] are concealed beneath [[tumulus|tumuli]] retained by walls; others are cut into cliffs. The Banditaccia necropolis contains more than 1,000 tumuli. Access is through a door.&lt;ref&gt;Some popular Internet sites giving photographs and details of the necropolis are:
[http://www.mysteriousetruscans.com/caisra.html Cisra (Roman Caere / Modern Cerveteri)] at mysteriousetruscans.com.&lt;br&gt;
[http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Gazetteer/Places/Europe/Italy/_Periods/Roman/Archaic/Etruscan/_Texts/DENETR*/33.html Chapter XXXIII CERVETRI.a – AGYLLA or CAERE.], George Dennis at Bill Thayer's Website.&lt;br&gt;
[http://www.mapsack.com/item/9002 Aerial photo and map] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070929221039/http://www.mapsack.com/item/9002 |date=2007-09-29 }} at mapsack.com.&lt;/ref&gt;

*[[Tarquinia]], Tarquinii or Corneto, a [[UNESCO]] site:&lt;ref name=&quot;cervtarq&quot; /&gt; Approximately 6,000 graves dating from the [[Villanovan]] (ninth and eighth centuries BC) distributed in ''[[necropoleis]]'', the main one being the Monterozzi [[hypogeum|hypogea]] of the sixth–fourth centuries BC. About 200 painted tombs display murals of various scenes with call-outs and descriptions in Etruscan. Elaborately carved sarcophagi of marble, [[alabaster]], and [[nenfro]] include identificatory and achievemental inscriptions. The [[Tomb of Orcus]] at the Scatolini necropolis depicts scenes of the [[Spurinna]] family with call-outs.&lt;ref&gt;A history of the tombs at Tarquinia and links to descriptions of the most famous ones is given at [http://www.mysteriousetruscans.com/tarchna.html] on mysteriousetruscans.com.&lt;/ref&gt;
* Inner walls and doors of tombs and sarcophagi
* Engraved steles (tombstones)
* [[Ossuary|ossuaries]]

===Inscriptions on portable objects===

====Votives====
''See'' [[votive offering|Votive gifts]].

====Specula====
A speculum is a circular or oval hand-mirror used predominantly by Etruscan women. ''Speculum'' is Latin; the Etruscan word is ''malena'' or ''malstria''. Specula were cast in bronze as one piece or with a tang into which a wooden, bone, or ivory handle fitted. The reflecting surface was created by polishing the flat side. A higher percentage of tin in the mirror improved its ability to reflect. The other side was convex and featured [[Intaglio (jewellery)|intaglio]] or [[cameo (carving)|cameo]] scenes from mythology. The piece was generally ornate.&lt;ref&gt;For pictures and a description refer to the ''[http://www.mysteriousetruscans.com/art/mirrors.html Etruscan Mirrors]'' article at mysteriousetruscans.com.&lt;/ref&gt;

About 2,300 specula are known from collections all over the world. As they were popular plunderables, the provenance of only a minority is known. An estimated time window is 530–100 BC.&lt;ref&gt;For the dates, more pictures and descriptions, see the ''[http://www.oberlin.edu/amam/Etruscan.htm Hand Mirror with the Judgment of Paris]'' article published online by the Allen Memorial Art Museum of [[Oberlin College]].&lt;/ref&gt; Most probably came from tombs.

Many bear inscriptions naming the persons depicted in the scenes, so they are often called picture bilinguals. In 1979, [[Massimo Pallottino]], then president of the ''Istituto di Studi Etruschi ed Italici'' initiated the Committee of the ''Corpus Speculorum Etruscanorum'', which resolved to publish all the specula and set editorial standards for doing so.

Since then, the committee has grown, acquiring local committees and representatives from most institutions owning Etruscan mirror collections. Each collection is published in its own fascicle by diverse Etruscan scholars.&lt;ref&gt;Representative examples can be found in the U.S. Epigraphy Project site of [[Brown University]]: [http://usepigraphy.brown.edu/view.php?textID=OH.Tol.TMA.L.1980.1340] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070512185430/http://usepigraphy.brown.edu/view.php?textID=OH.Tol.TMA.L.1980.1340 |date=2007-05-12 }}, [http://usepigraphy.brown.edu/view.php?textID=NY.NY.MMA.L.96.18.16] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20060904033701/http://usepigraphy.brown.edu/view.php?textID=NY.NY.MMA.L.96.18.16 |date=2006-09-04 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Cistae====
A cista is a bronze container of circular, ovoid, or more rarely rectangular shape used by women for the storage of sundries. They are ornate, often with feet and lids to which figurines may be attached. The internal and external surfaces bear carefully crafted scenes usually from mythology, usually intaglio, or rarely part intaglio, part [[cameo (carving)|cameo]].

Cistae date from the [[Roman Republic]] of the fourth and third centuries BC in Etruscan contexts. They may bear various short inscriptions concerning the manufacturer or owner or subject matter. The writing may be Latin, Etruscan, or both. Excavations at [[Palestrina|Praeneste]], an Etruscan city which became Roman, turned up about 118 cistae, one of which has been termed &quot;the Praeneste cista&quot; or &quot;the Ficoroni cista&quot; by art analysts, with special reference to the one manufactured by Novios Plutius and given by Dindia Macolnia to her daughter, as the archaic Latin inscription says. All of them are more accurately termed &quot;the Praenestine cistae&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Paggi, Maddalena. &quot;The Praenestine Cistae&quot; (October 2004), New York: The [[Metropolitan Museum of Art]], in [http://www.metmuseum.org/toah/hd/prae/hd_prae.htm Timeline of Art History].&lt;/ref&gt;

====Rings and ringstones====
Among the most plunderable portables from the Etruscan tombs of [[Etruria]] are the finely engraved gemstones set in patterned gold to form circular or ovoid pieces intended to go on finger rings. Of the magnitude of one centimeter, they are dated to the Etruscan [[floruit]] from the second half of the sixth to the first centuries BC. The two main theories of manufacture are native Etruscan&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite EB1911 |wstitle=Gem#Etruscan_Gems |display=Gem § ''Etruscan Gems'' |volume=11 |page=566 |first1=Alexander Stuart |last1=Murray |first2=Arthur Hamilton |last2=Smith}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Greek.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cvaonline.org/Gems/Styles/Etruscan2/Script/MythFrameset.htm Beazley Archive].&lt;/ref&gt; The materials are mainly dark red [[carnelian]], with [[agate]] and [[sard]] entering usage from the third to the first centuries BC, along with purely gold finger rings with a hollow engraved [[bezel setting]]. The engravings, mainly cameo, but sometimes intaglio, depict [[Dung beetle|scarabs]] at first and then scenes from Greek mythology, often with heroic personages called out in Etruscan. The gold setting of the bezel bears a border design, such as cabling.

====Coins====
Etruscan-minted coins can be dated between 5th and 3rd centuries BC. Use of the 'Chalcidian' standard, based on the silver unit of 5.8&amp;nbsp;grams, indicates that this custom, like the alphabet, came from Greece. Roman coinage later supplanted Etruscan, but the basic Roman coin, the ''[[sesterce]]'', is believed to have been based on the 2.5-denomination Etruscan coin.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.snible.org/coins/hn/etruria.html Ancient Coins of Etruria].&lt;/ref&gt; Etruscan coins have turned up in caches or individually in tombs and in excavations seemingly at random, and concentrated, of course, in [[Etruria]].

Etruscan coins were in gold, silver, and bronze, the gold and silver usually having been struck on one side only. The coins often bore a denomination, sometimes a minting authority name, and a cameo motif. Gold denominations were in units of silver; silver, in units of bronze. Full or abbreviated names are mainly Pupluna ([[Populonia]]), Vatl or Veltuna ([[Vetulonia]]), Velathri ([[Volaterrae]]), Velzu or Velznani (Volsinii) and Cha for Chamars ([[Camars]]). Insignia are mainly heads of mythological characters or depictions of mythological beasts arranged in a symbolic motif: [[Apollo]], [[Zeus]], [[Culsans]], [[Athena]], [[Hermes]], [[griffin]], [[gorgon]], male [[sphinx]], [[hippocamp]], bull, snake, eagle, or other creatures which had symbolic significance.

==Phonology==
In the tables below, conventional letters used for transliterating Etruscan are accompanied by likely pronunciation in [[help:IPA|IPA]] symbols within the square brackets, followed by examples of the early [[Etruscan alphabet]] which would have corresponded to these sounds:{{citation needed|date=December 2015}}

===Vowels===
The Etruscan [[vowel|vowel system]] consisted of four distinct vowels. Vowels &quot;o&quot; and &quot;u&quot; appear to have not been phonetically distinguished based on the nature of the writing system, as only one symbol is used to cover both in loans from Greek (e.g. Greek {{lang|grc|κώθων}} ''kōthōn'' &gt; Etruscan ''qutun'' &quot;pitcher&quot;).

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!
! [[Front vowel|Front]]

! [[Back vowel|Back]]
|- align=center
! [[Close vowel|Close]]
| i&lt;br&gt;{{IPA|[i]}}&lt;br&gt;[[File:EtruscanI-01.svg|14px|I]]

| u&lt;br&gt;{{IPA|[u]}}&lt;br&gt;[[File:EtruscanO-01.svg|14px|U]]
|- align=center
! [[Mid vowel|Mid]]
| e&lt;br&gt;{{IPA|[e]}}&lt;br&gt;[[File:EtruscanE-01.svg|14px|E]]
|
|- align=center
! [[Open vowel|Open]]
|
| a&lt;br&gt;{{IPA|[ɑ]}}&lt;br&gt;[[File:EtruscanA-01.svg|14px|A]]
|}

===Consonants===

====Table of consonants====
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!
! colspan=&quot;2&quot; | [[Bilabial]]
! colspan=&quot;2&quot; | [[Dental consonant|Dental]]
! [[Palatal consonant|Palatal]]
! colspan=&quot;2&quot; | [[Velar consonant|Velar]]
!| [[glottal consonant|Glottal]]
|- align=center
![[Nasal stop|Nasal]]
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; |m&lt;br&gt;{{IPA|[m]}}&lt;br&gt;[[File:EtruscanM-01.svg|14px|M]]
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; |n&lt;br&gt;{{IPA|[n̪]}}&lt;br&gt;[[File:EtruscanN-01.svg|14px|N]]
||
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; |
||
|- align=center
![[Plosive consonant|Plosive]]
|p&lt;br&gt;{{IPA|[p]}}&lt;br&gt;[[File:EtruscanP-01.svg|14px|P]]
|φ&lt;br&gt;{{IPA|[pʰ]}}&lt;br&gt;[[File:EtruscanPH-01.svg|14px|Φ]]
|t, d&lt;br&gt;{{IPA|[t̪]}}&lt;br&gt;[[File:EtruscanT-01.svg|14px|T]] [[File:EtruscanD-01.svg|14px|D]]
|θ&lt;br&gt;{{IPA|[t̪ʰ]}}&lt;br&gt;[[File:EtruscanTH-03.svg|14px|Θ]]
|
|c, k, q&lt;br&gt;{{IPA|[k]}}&lt;br&gt;[[File:EtruscanC-01.svg|14px|C]] [[File:EtruscanK-01.svg|14px|K]] [[File:EtruscanQ-01.svg|14px|Q]]
|χ&lt;br&gt;{{IPA|[kʰ]}}&lt;br&gt;[[File:EtruscanX-01.svg|14px|Χ]]
|
|- align=center
![[Affricate consonant|Affricate]]
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; |
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; | z&lt;br&gt;{{IPA|[t̪͡s̪]}}&lt;br&gt;[[File:EtruscanZ-01.svg|14px|Z]]
|
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; |
|
|- align=center
![[Fricative consonant|Fricative]]
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; | f&lt;br&gt;{{IPA|[ɸ]}}&lt;br&gt;[[File:EtruscanF-02.svg|14px|F]]
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; |s&lt;br&gt;{{IPA|[s̪]}}&lt;br&gt;[[File:EtruscanS-01.svg|14px|S]]
|ś&lt;br&gt;{{IPA|[ʃ]}}&lt;br&gt;[[File:Greek alphabet san2.png|14px]] [[File:Alfabeto camuno-ts.svg|14px|Ś]]
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; |
|h&lt;br&gt;{{IPA|[h]}}&lt;br&gt;[[File:EtruscanH-01.svg|14px|H]]
|- align=center
![[Approximant consonant|Approximant]]
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; |
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; |l&lt;br&gt;{{IPA|[l̪]}}&lt;br&gt;[[File:EtruscanL-01.svg|14px|L]]
|i&lt;br&gt;{{IPA|[j]}}&lt;br&gt;[[File:EtruscanI-01.svg|14px|I]]
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; |v&lt;br&gt;{{IPA|[w]}}&lt;br&gt;[[File:EtruscanF-01.svg|14px|V]]
|
|- align=center
![[Rhotic consonant|Rhotic]]
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; |
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; |r&lt;br&gt;{{IPA|[r̪]}}&lt;br&gt;[[File:EtruscanR-01.svg|14px|R]]
|
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; |
||
|}

====Voiced stops missing====
The Etruscan consonant system primarily distinguished between aspirated and non-aspirated stops. There were no voiced stops and loanwords with them were typically devoiced, e.g. Greek ''thriambos'' was borrowed by Etruscan, becoming ''triumpus'' and ''triumphus'' in Latin.&lt;ref&gt;J.H. Adams pp. 163–164.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Syllabic theory====
Based on standard spellings by Etruscan scribes of words without vowels or with unlikely consonant clusters (e.g. ''cl'' 'of this (gen.)' and ''lautn'' 'freeman'), it is likely that {{IPA|/m n l r/}} were sometimes syllabic [[sonorant]]s (cf. English &quot;litt'''le'''&quot;, &quot;butto'''n'''&quot;). Thus ''cl'' {{IPA|/kl̩/}} and ''lautn'' {{IPA|/ˈlɑwtn̩/}}.

Rix postulates several syllabic consonants, namely {{IPA|/l, r, m, n/}} and palatal {{IPA|/lʲ, rʲ, nʲ/}} as well as a labiovelar spirant {{IPA|/xʷ/}} and some scholars such as [[Mauro Cristofani]] also view the aspirates as palatal rather than aspirated but these views are not shared by most Etruscologists. Rix supports his theories by means of variant spellings such as amφare/amφiare, larθal/larθial, aranθ/aranθiia.

==Morphology==
Etruscan was [[Inflected language|inflected]], varying the endings of nouns, pronouns and verbs. It also had adjectives, adverbs, and conjunctions, which were uninflected.

===Nouns===
Etruscan substantives had five cases, and a singular and a plural. Not all five cases are attested for every word. Nouns merge the nominative and accusative; pronouns do not generally merge these. Gender appears in personal names (masculine and feminine) and in pronouns (animate and inanimate); otherwise, it is not marked.&lt;ref name = &quot;hwiaof&quot;&gt;Bonfante (1990), p. 20.&lt;/ref&gt;

Unlike the [[Indo-European languages]], Etruscan noun endings were more [[agglutinative]], with some nouns bearing two or three agglutinated suffixes. For example, where Latin would have distinct nominative plural and dative plural endings, Etruscan would suffix the case ending to a plural marker: Latin nominative singular ''fili-us'', &quot;son&quot;, plural ''fili-i'', dative plural ''fili-is'', but Etruscan ''clan, clen-ar'' and ''clen-ar-aśi''.&lt;ref&gt;Bonfante (1990) p. 19.&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;!--Need a different set of example as this one shows similar way of adding suffix in both Latin and Etruscan language 's' added to 'i' and 'aśi' added to 'ar'--&gt; Moreover, Etruscan nouns could bear multiple suffixes from the case paradigm alone: that is, Etruscan exhibited ''[[Suffixaufnahme]]''. Pallottino calls this phenomenon &quot;morphological redetermination&quot;, which he defines as &quot;the typical tendency ... to redetermine the syntactical function of the form by the superposition of suffixes.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Page 263.&lt;/ref&gt; His example is'' Uni-al-θi'', &quot;in the sanctuary of Juno&quot;, where'' -al'' is a genitive ending and ''-θi'' a locative.

Steinbauer says of Etruscan, &quot;there can be more than one marker ... to design a case, and ... the same marker can occur for more than one case.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.etruskisch.de/pgs/gr.htm Etruscan Grammar: Summary]'' at Steinbauer's website.&lt;/ref&gt;

; [[Nominative case|Nominative]]/[[accusative case]] : No distinction is made between nominative and accusative of nouns. Common nouns use the unmarked root. Names of males may end in ''-e'': ''Hercle'' (Hercules), ''Achle'' (Achilles), ''Tite'' (Titus); of females, in -i, -a, or -u: ''Uni'' (Juno), ''Menrva'' (Minerva), or ''Zipu''. Names of gods may end in -s: ''Fufluns, Tins''; or they may be the unmarked stem ending in a vowel or consonant: ''Aplu'' (Apollo), ''Paχa'' (Bacchus), or ''Turan''.
; [[Genitive case]] : Pallottino defines two declensions based on whether the genitive ends in -s/-ś or -l.&lt;ref&gt;Page 264.&lt;/ref&gt; In the -s group are most noun stems ending in a vowel or a consonant: ''fler/fler-ś, ramtha/ramtha-ś''. In the second are names of females ending in i and names of males that end s, th or n: ''ati/ati-al, Laris/Laris-al, Arnθ/Arnθ-al''. After l or r -us instead of -s appears: ''Vel/Vel-us''. Otherwise, a vowel might be placed before the ending: ''Arnθ-al'' instead of ''Arnθ-l''.
: There is a [[patronymic]] ending: -sa or -isa, &quot;son of&quot;, but the ordinary genitive might serve that purpose. In the genitive case, morphological redetermination becomes elaborate. Given two male names, ''Vel'' and ''Avle'', ''Vel Avleś'' means &quot;Vel son of Avle.&quot; This expression in the genitive become ''Vel-uś Avles-la''. Pallottino's example of a three-suffix form is ''Arnθ-al-iśa-la''.
; [[Dative case]] : The dative ending is -si: ''Tita/Tita-si''.&lt;ref name = &quot;hwiaof&quot;/&gt;
; [[Locative case]] : The locative ending is -θi: ''Tarχna/Tarχna-l-θi''.&lt;ref&gt;Pallottino page 114, Bonfante (1990) p. 41.&lt;/ref&gt;
; [[Plural number]] : In one case, a plural is given for ''clan'', &quot;son&quot;, as ''clenar'', &quot;sons&quot;. This shows both [[I-mutation|umlaut]] and an ending ''-ar''. Plurals for cases other than nominative are made by agglutinating the case ending on ''clenar''.

===Pronouns===
Personal pronouns refer to persons; demonstrative pronouns point out: English this, that, there.&lt;ref&gt;The summary in this section is taken from the tables of the Bonfantes (2002) pp. 91–94, which go into considerably more detail, citing examples.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Personal====
The first-person personal pronoun has a nominative ''mi'' (&quot;I&quot;) and an accusative ''mini'' (&quot;me&quot;).  The third person has a personal form ''an'' (&quot;he&quot; or &quot;she&quot;) and an inanimate ''in'' (&quot;it&quot;). The second person is uncertain, but some, like the Bonfantes, have claimed a dative singular ''une'' (&quot;to thee&quot;) and an accusative singular ''un'' (&quot;thee&quot;).

====Demonstrative====
The demonstratives, ''ca'' and ''ta'', are used without distinction. The nominative–accusative singular forms are: ''ica, eca, ca, ita, ta''; the plural: ''cei, tei''. There is a genitive singular: ''cla, tla, cal'' and plural ''clal''. The accusative singular: ''can, cen, cn, ecn, etan, tn''; plural ''cnl''. Locative singular: ''calti, ceiθi, clθ(i), eclθi''; plural ''caiti, ceiθi''.

===Adjectives===
Though uninflected, adjectives fall into a number of types formed from nouns with a suffix:
* quality, -u, -iu or -c:'' ais/ais-iu'', &quot;god/divine&quot;; ''zamaθi/zamθi-c'', &quot;gold/golden&quot;
* possession or reference, -na, -ne, -ni: ''paχa/paχa-na'', &quot;Bacchus, Bacchic&quot;; ''laut/laut-ni'', &quot;family/familiar&quot; (in the sense of servant)
* collective, -cva, -chva, -cve, -χve, -ia: ''sren/sren-cva'': &quot;figure/figured&quot;; ''etera/etera-ia'', &quot;slave/servile&quot;

===Adverbs===
Adverbs are unmarked: ''etnam'', &quot;again&quot;; ''θui'', &quot;now&quot;; ''θuni'', &quot;at first.&quot; Most [[Indo-European languages|Indo-European]] adverbs are formed from the oblique cases, which become unproductive and descend to fixed forms. Cases such as the [[ablative]] are therefore called &quot;adverbial&quot;. If there is any such system in Etruscan, it is not obvious from the relatively few surviving adverbs.

===Verbs===
Verbs had an [[indicative mood]] and an [[imperative mood]]. Tenses were [[Present tense|present]] and [[Past tense|past]]. The past tense had an [[active voice]] and a [[grammatical voice|passive voice]].

====Present active====
Etruscan used a verbal root with a zero suffix or -a without distinction to number or person: ''ar, ar-a'', &quot;he, she, we, you, they make&quot;.

====Past or preterite active====
Adding the suffix ''-(a)ce'' to the verb root produces a third-person singular active, which has been called variously a &quot;past&quot;, a &quot;preterite&quot;, a &quot;perfect&quot; or an &quot;aorist&quot;. In contrast to Indo-European, this form is not marked for [[Grammatical person|person]]. Examples: ''tur/tur-ce'', &quot;gives/gave&quot;; ''sval/sval-ce'', &quot;lives/lived.&quot;

====Past passive====
The third-person past passive is formed with -che: ''mena/mena-ce/mena-che'', &quot;offers/offered/was offered&quot;.

==Vocabulary==
===Borrowings from Etruscan===
Only a few hundred words of the Etruscan vocabulary are understood with some certainty. The exact count depends on whether the different forms and the expressions are included. Below is a table of some of the words grouped by topic.&lt;ref&gt;The words in this table come from the Glossaries of Bonfante (1990) and Pallottino. The latter also gives a grouping by topic on pages 275 following, the last chapter of the book.&lt;/ref&gt;

Some words with corresponding Latin or other Indo-European forms are likely [[loanword]]s to or from Etruscan. For example, ''neftś'' &quot;nephew&quot;, is probably from Latin (Latin ''nepōs, nepōtis''; this is a cognate of German ''Neffe'', Old Norse ''nefi''). A number of [[wikt:Category:Latin terms derived from Etruscan|words and names]] for which Etruscan origin has been proposed survive in Latin.

At least one Etruscan word has an apparent Semitic/Aramaic origin: ''talitha'' &quot;girl&quot;, that could have been transmitted by Phoenicians or by the Greeks (Greek: ταλιθα). The word ''pera'' &quot;house&quot; is a [[false cognate]] to the [[Coptic language|Coptic]] ''per'' &quot;house&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://sites.davidson.edu/csa/the-etruscan-language/ |title=Archived copy |access-date=2014-09-26 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150602084951/http://sites.davidson.edu/csa/the-etruscan-language/ |archive-date=2015-06-02 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition to words believed to have been borrowed into Etruscan from Indo-European or elsewhere, there is a corpus of words such as ''familia'' which seem to have been borrowed into Latin from the older Etruscan civilization as a [[linguistic superstratum|superstrate]] influence.&lt;ref&gt;Theo Vennemann, ''Germania Semitica, p. 123, Walter de Gruyter, Berlin 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; Some of these words still have widespread currency in English and Latin-influenced languages. Other words believed to have a possible Etruscan origin include:
{{main|List of English words of Etruscan origin}}

; [[arena]] : from ''arēna'' &quot;arena&quot; &lt; ''harēna'', &quot;arena, sand&quot; &lt; archaic ''hasēna'' &lt; Sabine ''fasēna'', unknown Etruscan word as the basis for ''fas-'' with Etruscan ending ''-ēna''.&lt;ref&gt;Breyer (1993) p. 259.&lt;/ref&gt;
; [[belt (clothing)|belt]] : from ''balteus'', &quot;sword belt&quot;; the sole connection between this word and Etruscan is a statement by [[Marcus Terentius Varro]] that it was of Etruscan origin. All else is speculation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Varronianus: A Critical and Historical Introduction to the Ethnography of Ancient Italy and to the Philological Study of the Latin Language|url=https://archive.org/details/cu31924021611466|first=John William|last= Donaldson|page=154|edition=2|publisher=J. W. Parker &amp; Son|year=1852|location=London, Cambridge}} Breyer (1993) pp. 428–429 reports on an attempt to bring in Hittite and Gothic connecting it with a totally speculative root *-lst-.&lt;/ref&gt;
; [[Market (economics)|market]] : from Latin ''mercātus'', of obscure origin, perhaps Etruscan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?term=market|title=market - Origin and meaning of market by Online Etymology Dictionary|website=www.etymonline.com|accessdate=15 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
; [[military]] : from Latin ''milēs'' &quot;soldier&quot;; either from Etruscan or related to Greek ''homilos'', &quot;assembled crowd&quot; (compare ''homily'').&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?term=military&amp;allowed_in_frame=0|title=military – Origin and meaning of military by Online Etymology Dictionary|website=www.etymonline.com|accessdate=15 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
; [[person]] : from Middle English ''persone'', from Old French ''persone'', from Latin ''persona'', &quot;mask&quot;, probably from Etruscan ''phersu'', &quot;mask&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;American Heritage Dictionary, New College Edition, p. 978&lt;/ref&gt;
; [[satellite (disambiguation)|satellite]] : from Latin ''satelles'', meaning &quot;bodyguard, attendant&quot;, perhaps from Etruscan ''satnal''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?term=satellite&amp;allowed_in_frame=0|title=satellite - Origin and meaning of satellite by Online Etymology Dictionary|website=www.etymonline.com|accessdate=15 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Etruscan vocabulary ===

====Numerals====
{{main|Etruscan numerals}}
Much debate has been carried out about a possible [[Proto-Indo-European numerals|Indo-European]] origin of the Etruscan cardinals. In the words of Larissa Bonfante (1990), &quot;What these numerals show, beyond any shadow of a doubt, is the non-Indo-European nature of the Etruscan language&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Bonfante, L.,''Etruscan'', University of California Press (Berkeley and Los Angeles, 1990), p. 22.&lt;/ref&gt; Conversely, other scholars, including [[Francisco Rodríguez Adrados|Francisco R. Adrados]], Albert Carnoy, Marcello Durante, Vladimir Georgiev, Alessandro Morandi and Massimo Pittau, have proposed a close phonetic proximity of the first ten Etruscan numerals to the corresponding numerals in other Indo-European languages.&lt;ref&gt;Carnoy, A., &quot;La langue étrusque et ses origines&quot;, ''L'Antiquité Classique'', 21 (1952), p. 326. {{JSTOR|41643730}}. ([http://www.persee.fr/web/revues/home/prescript/article/antiq_0770-2817_1952_num_21_2_3451])&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Morandi, A., ''Nuovi lineamenti di lingua etrusca'', Erre Emme (Roma, 1991), chapter IV.&lt;/ref&gt; Italian linguist Massimo Pittau has argued that &quot;all the first ten Etruscan numerals have a congruent phonetic matching in as many Indo-European languages&quot; and &quot;perfectly fit within the Indo-European series&quot;, supporting the idea that the Etruscan language was of Indo-European origins.&lt;ref&gt;Pittau, M., &quot;I numerali Etruschi&quot;, ''Atti del Sodalizio Glottologico Milanese'', vol. XXXV–XXXVI, 1994/1995 (1996), pp.&amp;nbsp;95–105. ([http://www.pittau.it/Etrusco/Studi/dadi.html])&lt;/ref&gt;

The Etruscan numbers are (G. Bonfante 2002:96):

#''θu''
#''zal''
#''ci''
#''śa / huθ''
#''maχ''
#''huθ / śa''
#''semφ''
#''cezp''
#''nurφ''
#''śar''

It is unclear which of ''śa'' and ''huθ'' meant &quot;four&quot; and &quot;six&quot; respectively.

====Core vocabulary====

{{col-begin}}
{{col-2}}
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Etruscan
! English
|-
!colspan=2|Family
|-
| ''apa''
| father (Latin: ''pater'')
|-
| ''apana''
| paternal
|-
| ''papa, papacs''
| grandfather
|-
| ''ati, ativu''
| mother
|-
| ''teta, ati nacna''
| grandmother
|-
| ''pui, puia''
| wife
|-
| ''tusurθir''
| married couple
|-
| ''clan''
| son
|-
| ''papals''
| grandson
|-
| ''sec, sech''
| daughter
|-
| ''ruva''
| brother
|-
| ''neftś, nefś, nefiś''
| nephew (Latin: ''nepos'')
|-
| ''prumaθ, prumaθś, prumats, prumts''
| great-nephew or great-grandson
|-
| ''nene''
| wetnurse
|-
| ''snenaθ''
| maid, companion
|-
| ''hus''
| youth
|-
| ''husiur''
| children
|-
| ''pava''
| boy
|-
| ''taliθa''
| girl (Greek: ταλιθα, Aramaic: ''talitha'')
|-
| ''lautun, lautn''
| gens, people (IE ''*h₁lewdʰ-'', 'people')
|-
| ''lautni''
| freedman (IE ''*h₁léwdʰ-eros'', 'free', 'pertaining to the people')
|-
| ''lautniθa, lautnita''
| freedwoman
|-
| ''etera, eteri''
| foreigner, slave, client (Greek ἕτερος)
|-
!colspan=2|Society
|-
|''aesar''&lt;ref&gt;Cassius Dio Roman History 56,29,4&lt;/ref&gt;
| god
|-
|''Rasenna'', ''Rasna''
| Etruscans
|-
|''meχl Rasnal''
| Etruria
|-
| ''pes''
| land
|-
| ''tul''
| stone
|-
| ''tular, tularu''
| boundaries
|-
| ''tular rasnal''
| public boundaries
|-
| ''tular spural''
| city boundaries
|-
| ''vaχr''
| contract
|-
| ''tudthi, tuθiu, tuθi, tuti''
| state
|-
|''tuθin, tuθina''
| public
|-
| ''mech''
| people
|-
| ''meχl, meθlum''
| nation, league, district
|-
| ''spur, śpur''
| ''civitas'', ''populus''
|-
| ''spureni, spurana''
| civic
|-
| ''θruna''
| sovereignty
|-
| ''lucair''
| to rule
|-
| ''lauχum''
| king, prince
|-
| ''lauχumna''
| regal, palace
|-
| ''tenve, tenine,&lt;br&gt;tenu, tenθas''
| hold office
|-
| ''zil, zilac, zilc,&lt;br&gt;zilaχ, zilath''
| praetor
|-
| ''camthi''
| rowspan=7 |unknown magistrates&lt;br&gt;or magistracies
|-
| ''ceχase''
|-
| ''parniχ''
|-
| ''macstreve''
|-
| ''maru, marunu, marniu,&lt;br&gt;marunuχ, maruχva''
|-
| ''purθ, purθne''
|-
| ''tamera''
|}
{{col-2}}
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Etruscan
! English
|-
!colspan=2|Time
|-
| ''tin-''
| day
|-
| ''θesan''
| morning, day
|-
| ''uslane''
| at noon
|-
| ''tiur, tivr, tiu''
| month, moon
|-
| ''avil''
| year
|-
| ''ril''
| at the age of
|-
| ''Velcitna''
| March
|-
| ''Capr-''
| April
|-
| ''Ampile''
| May
|-
| ''Acale''
| June
|-
| ''Hermi''
| August or summer?
|-
| ''Celi''
| September
|-
| ''Chosfer''
| October
|-
| ''Masan, Masn''
| unknown month
|-
!colspan=2|Nature
|-
| ''anθa''
| northwind, eagle (Latin: ''aquila'')
|-
| ''arac''
| sparrow-hawk, falcon (possibly Greek ἱέραξ)
|-
| ''arim''
| monkey
|-
| ''capu''
| falcon
|-
| ''falatu''
| sky
|-
| ''hiuls''
| screech-owl
|-
| ''leu''
| lion (Latin: ''leo'')
|-
| ''neri''
| water
|-
| ''pulumχva''
| stars
|-
| ''thamna''
| horse
|-
| ''thevru''
| bull (Latin: ''taurus'')
|-
| ''tisś''
| lake
|-
| ''tiu''
| moon
|-
| ''θi''
| water
|-
| ''usil''
| sun (Latin: ''sol'')
|-
| ''vers-''
| fire
|-
!colspan=2|Vessels
|-
| ''aska''
| Greek [[Typology of Greek Vase Shapes|ἄσκος]] ''áskos'' &quot;wineskin&quot;
|-
| ''aska eleivana''
| olive oil flask
|-
| ''cape, capi''
| container (perhaps Latin ''capio'' &quot;take&quot; or ''capis'' &quot;one-handled bowl&quot;)
|-
| ''capra''
| urn
|-
| ''cletram''
| Umbrian ''kletra'', a basin or basket
|-
| ''culiχna''
| [[Kylix (drinking cup)|κύλιξ]], a large wine-cup
|-
| ''cupe''
| κύπη or Latin ''cūpa'', English cup
|-
| ''leχtum''
| [[Lekythos|λήκυθος]], a small bottle
|-
| ''leχtumuza''
| a small lechtum
|-
| ''patna''
| πατάνη, a bowl
|-
| ''pruχ, pruχum''
| πρόχоυς, a ewer
|-
| ''qutun, qutum''
| [[Typology of Greek Vase Shapes|κώθων]], a vessel of [[Laconia]]
|-
| ''qutumuza''
| small qutum
|-
| ''θafna''
| chalice
|-
| ''θina, tina''
| derived from ''θi'' &quot;water&quot;
|-
!colspan=2|Common verbs
|-
| ''am-''
| to be
|-
| ''cer-''
| to make
|-
| ''tur-''
| to give
|-
| ''ziχ-''
| to write
|}
{{col-end}}
&lt;!--
==Sample texts==
To be supplied.
--&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Combinatorial method (linguistics)]]
* [[Corpus Inscriptionum Etruscarum]]
* [[Old Italic alphabet#Etruscan alphabet|Etruscan alphabet]]
* [[Etruscan civilization]]
* Etruscan documents
** ''[[Liber Linteus]]'' – An Etruscan linen book that ended as mummy wraps in Egypt.
** ''[[Tabula Cortonensis]]'' – An Etruscan inscription.
** ''[[Cippus perusinus]]'' – An Etruscan inscription.
** ''[[Pyrgi Tablets]]'' – Bilingual Etruscan-[[Phoenician language|Phoenician]] golden leaves.
* [[Etruscan mythology]]
* [[Etruscan numerals]]
* [[Lemnian language]]
* [[List of English words of Etruscan origin]]
* [[List of Spanish words of Etruscan origin]]
* [[Raetic language]]
* [[Helmut Rix]]
* [[Tyrsenian languages]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Bibliography==
* {{cite book| author=Adams, J. N. | title=Bilingualism and the Latin Language | year=2003 | publisher=Cambridge University Press | isbn=0-521-81771-4}} Available for preview on Google Books.
* Agostiniani, Luciano (2013). &quot;The Etruscan Language.&quot; ''The Etruscan World'', ed. [[Jean MacIntosh Turfa]], 457–77. Abingdon: Routledge. 
* Bellelli Vincenzo, Benelli Enrico (2018), ''Gli Etruschi. La scrittura, la lingua, la società'', Carrocci Editore, Roma 2018 (Italian).
* {{cite book| authorlink = Giuliano Bonfante| last = Bonfante | first =  Giuliano|author2=Bonfante, Larissa |authorlink2=Larissa Bonfante | title = The Etruscan Language: an Introduction| location = Manchester| publisher = University of Manchester Press| year = 2002| isbn = 0-7190-5540-7| url=https://books.google.co.uk/books?redir_esc=y&amp;id=VWGN6e5Rzf8C}} Preview available on Google Books.
* {{cite book| author=Bonfante, Larissa| authorlink=Larissa Bonfante| title=Etruscan| year=1990| location=Berkeley and Los Angeles| publisher=University of California Press| isbn= 0-520-07118-2}} Preview available at Google Books.
* {{cite book| authorlink = Mauro Cristofani| last = Cristofani | first = Mauro| title = Gli Etruschi: una nuova immagine
| publisher = Firenze, Giunti Martello| year = 1984|display-authors=etal}}
* {{cite book| authorlink = Mauro Cristofani| last = Cristofani | first = Mauro| title = The Etruscans: A New Investigation (Echoes of the ancient world)| publisher = Orbis Pub| year = 1979| isbn = 0-85613-259-4}}
* {{cite book| author=Facchetti, Giulio M.| title=L'enigma svelato della lingua etrusca| year=2000| location=Roma| publisher=Newton &amp; Compton| isbn=978-88-8289-458-0}}
* {{cite book| author=Facchetti, Giulio M.| title=Appunti di morfologia etrusca. Con un'appendice sulle questioni delle affinità genetiche dell'etrusco| year=2002| location=Roma| publisher=Olshcki| isbn=978-88-222-5138-1}}
* Maras, Daniele (2013). &quot;Numbers and reckoning: A whole civilization founded upon divisions.&quot; ''The Etruscan World,'' ed. Jean MacIntosh Turfa, 478–91. Abingdon: Routledge. 
* {{cite book| authorlink=Massimo Pallottino| last=Pallottino| first=Massimo| title=The Etruscans| url=https://archive.org/details/etruscans00pall| url-access=registration| publisher=Penguin Books| year=1955}} Translated from the Italian by J. Cremona.
*  Penney, John H. (2009), ''The Etruscan language and its Italic context'', pp.&amp;nbsp;88–93, in ''Etruscan by Definition'', eds. Judith Swaddling, Philip Perkins, British Museum, London.
* {{cite book| authorlink = Helmut Rix| last = Rix | first = Helmut| title = Etruskische Texte| publisher = G. Narr| year = 1991| isbn = 3-8233-4240-1}} 2 vols.
* Rix, Helmut (1998), ''Rätisch und Etruskisch'', Innsbruck, Inst. für Sprachwiss., {{ISBN|3-85124-670-5}}
* {{cite book| authorlink = Dieter H. Steinbauer| last = Steinbauer | first = Dieter H.| title = Neues Handbuch des Etruskischen| publisher = Scripta Mercaturae| year = 1999| isbn = 3-89590-080-X}}
* {{cite book| authorlink = Rex E. Wallace| last = Wallace | first = Rex E.| title = Zikh Rasna: A Manual of the Etruscan Language and Inscriptions| publisher = Beech Stave Press| year = 2008| isbn = 978-0-9747927-4-3}}
* Wallace, Rex E. (2016), ''Language, Alphabet, and Linguistic Affiliation'', in ''A Companion to the Etruscans'' a cura di Sinclair Bell, Alexandra A. Carpino, Wiley-Blackwell, Chichester.

==External links==
{{Library resources box |by=no |onlinebooks=yes |others=yes |about=yes |label=Etruscan language
  |viaf= |lccn= |lcheading= |wikititle= }}
{{Incubator|ett|wiktionary}}

===General===
* [http://www.umass.edu/etruscannews Etruscan News Online], the Newsletter of the American Section of the Institute for Etruscan and Italic Studies.
*[http://ancientstudies.as.nyu.edu/page/publications#content Etruscan News back issues], Center for Ancient Studies at New York University.
*[http://www.etruskisch.de/imp/imp-e.htm Etruscology at Its Best], the website of Dr. Dieter H. Steinbauer, in English. Covers origins, vocabulary, grammar and place names.
* {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20021207170759/http://www.netaxs.com/~salvucci/VTLhome.html |date=December 7, 2002 |title=Viteliu: The Languages of Ancient Italy }}.
* [http://linguistlist.org/forms/langs/LLDescription.cfm?code=ett The Etruscan Language], the linguistlist.org site. Links to many other Etruscan language sites.

===Inscriptions===
* [http://www.trismegistos.org/tm/list_etruscan.php TM Texts Etruscan] A list of all texts in Trismegistos.
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20050330053810/http://etp.classics.umass.edu/ ETP: Etruscan Texts Project] A searchable database of Etruscan texts.
* ''[http://www.umass.edu/etruscannews/articles/WallaceENews5.pdf Etruscan Inscriptions in the Royal Ontario Museum]'', article by Rex Wallace displayed at the umass.edu site.

===Lexical items===
* [http://etruskisch.de/pgs/vc.htm Etruscan Vocabulary], a vocabulary organized by topic by Dieter H. Steinbauer, in English.
* {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20021213221136/http://www.netaxs.com/~salvucci/VTLetrvocab.html |date=December 13, 2002 |title=An Etruscan Vocabulary }}. A short, one-page glossary with numerals as well.
*{{cite web|url=http://www.iolairweb.co.uk/etrusdict.htm |title=Etruscan–English Dictionary |accessdate=May 1, 2007 |url-status=unfit |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070927045655/http://www.iolairweb.co.uk/etrusdict.htm |archivedate=September 27, 2007 }} . An extensive lexicon compiled from other lexicon sites. Links to the major Etruscan glossaries on the Internet are included.
* [http://paleoglot.blogspot.com/2007/01/lingua-files.html#etruscan Paleoglot: Online Etruscan-English dictionary; summary of Etruscan grammar]. A searchable Etruscan-to-English dictionary applet and a summary of Etruscan grammar.

===Font===
* [http://www.fontspace.com/dave-bastian/etruscan Etruscan font download site] with unicode information
* [https://jamesfpatterson.wordpress.com/etruscan-and-early-italic-fonts/ Etruscan and Early Italic Fonts by James F. Patterson]

{{Etruscans}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Etruscan language| ]]
[[Category:Languages of ancient Italy]]
[[Category:Pre-Indo-Europeans]]
[[Category:Tyrsenian languages]]
[[Category:Languages attested from the 7th century BC]]
[[Category:Languages extinct in the 1st century BC]]
[[Category:Language isolates of Europe]]</text>
      <sha1>ns23qmbs13ly9purs6z2hhr1pfgug49</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
