  <page>
    <title>Ericsson</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9424</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943212077</id>
      <parentid>943211518</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-29T15:24:32Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Thinehaunt</username>
        <id>38650415</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Foundation */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{other uses}}
{{short description|Swedish provider of communications technology and services}}
{{EngvarB|date=July 2016}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=April 2016}}
{{Infobox company
| name = Telefonaktiebolaget LM Ericsson
| logo = Ericsson (2018).svg
| logo_size = 150px
| image = Isafjord 1 October 2015 01.jpg
| image_size = 250px
| image_caption = Ericsson's headquarters in [[Kista]], Stockholm
| type = [[Public company|Publicly traded]] [[aktiebolag]]
| traded_as = {{OMX|SSE100|ERIC-A}}, {{OMXb|SSE101|ERIC-B}}&lt;br /&gt;{{NASDAQ|ERIC}}
| industry = {{nowrap|[[Telecommunications equipment]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Networking equipment]]}}
| foundation = Stockholm, Sweden&lt;br /&gt; ({{start date and age|df=yes|1876}})
| founder = [[Lars Magnus Ericsson]]
| location = [[Kista]], Stockholm, Sweden
| area_served = Worldwide
| key_people = [[Ronnie Leten]]&lt;br /&gt; &lt;small&gt;([[Chairman]])&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt; [[Börje Ekholm]]&lt;br /&gt; &lt;small&gt;([[CEO|President and CEO (Chief Executive Officer)]])&lt;/small&gt;
| products = [[Cellular network|Mobile]] and [[Broadband networks|fixed broadband networks]], [[Consultant|consultancy]] and [[managed services]], [[Tv|TV]] and [[multimedia]] technology
| revenue = [[Swedish krona|SEK]]210.8&amp;nbsp;billion (2018)&lt;ref name=&quot;AR2017&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.ericsson.com/assets/local/investors/documents/financial-reports-and-filings/interim-reports-archive/2018/12month18-en.pdf |title=Fourth quarter and full-year report 2018 |website=ericsson.com |date= |accessdate=2019-02-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| operating_income = SEK1.2&amp;nbsp;billion (2018)&lt;ref name=&quot;AR2017&quot; /&gt;
| net_income = −SEK6.3&amp;nbsp;billion (2018)&lt;ref name=&quot;AR2017&quot; /&gt;
| assets = SEK268.7&amp;nbsp;billion (2018)&lt;ref name=&quot;AR2017&quot; /&gt;
| equity = SEK86.97&amp;nbsp;billion (2018)&lt;ref name=&quot;AR2017&quot; /&gt;
| num_employees = 95,359 (2018)&lt;ref name=&quot;auto&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Company facts|url=https://www.ericsson.com/about-us/company-facts|website=Ericsson.com|publisher=Ericsson AB|accessdate=2018-07-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| owners = {{Unbulleted list
  | [[Investor AB]] (7.20%; 22.53% votes)&lt;ref name=&quot;shareholders&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.ericsson.com/49616f/assets/local/investors/documents/shareholder-information/ericsson-ar-18-shareholders.pdf |title=Ericsson Annual Report 2018 - Share information |publisher=Telefonaktiebolaget LM Ericsson |format=PDF |access-date=5 September 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
  | AB Industrivärden sphere (with SHB Pensionsstiftelse) (3.31%; 19.26% votes)&lt;ref name=&quot;shareholders&quot; /&gt;
  }}
| subsid = [[Red Bee Media]]
| homepage = {{URL|ericsson.com/}}
}}

'''Telefonaktiebolaget LM Ericsson''', [[Trade name|doing business as]] '''Ericsson''', is a [[Sweden|Swedish]] multinational networking and telecommunications company headquartered in [[Stockholm]]. The company offers services, software and infrastructure in information and communications technology for telecommunications operators, traditional telecommunications and [[Internet Protocol]] (IP) networking equipment, mobile and fixed broadband, operations and business support services, cable television, [[IPTV]], video systems, and an extensive services operation.

Ericsson had a 27% market share in the 2G/3G/4G mobile network infrastructure market in 2018.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Telecomlead|url=https://www.telecomlead.com/telecom-equipment/huawei-retains-lead-in-mobile-network-market-in-2018-89772|website=www.telecomlead.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The company was founded in 1876 by [[Lars Magnus Ericsson]];&lt;ref name=&quot;BizHistory&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ericssonhistory.com/ |title=Start |publisher=Ericsson History |date= |accessdate=2016-11-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; {{as of|2016|alt=as of 2016}} it is headquartered in [[Stockholm]], Sweden. The company employs around 95,000 people and operates in around 180 countries.&lt;ref name=&quot;auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=About us|url=https://www.ericsson.com/about-us|website=Ericsson.com|publisher=Ericsson AB|accessdate=5 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ericsson holds over 49,000 granted patents as of September 2019, including many in wireless communications.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Patents and licensing|url=https://www.ericsson.com/en/tags/category/patents-licensing/?locs=68304|website=Ericsson.com|publisher=Ericsson AB|accessdate= 20 September 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
===Foundation===
{{More citations needed section|date=January 2016}}
[[File:Swedish inventor Lars Magnus Ericsson.jpg|thumb|upright|Lars Magnus Ericsson]]

[[Lars Magnus Ericsson]] began his association with telephones in his youth as an instrument maker. He worked for a firm that made [[telegraph]] equipment for the Swedish government agency [[Televerket (Sweden)|Telegrafverket]]. In 1876, at the age of 30, he started a telegraph repair shop with help from his friend [[Carl Johan Andersson]] in central [[Stockholm]] and repaired foreign-made telephones. In 1878 Ericsson began making and selling his own telephone equipment. His telephones were not technically innovative. In 1878 he made an agreement to supply telephones and switchboards to Sweden's first telecommunications operating company, Stockholms Allmänna Telefonaktiebolag.&lt;ref name=&quot;BizHistory&quot; /&gt;

Also in 1878, local telephone importer Numa Peterson hired Ericsson to adjust some telephones from the [[Bell Telephone Company]]. He bought a number of [[Siemens]] telephones and analyzed the technology; Ericsson had a scholarship at Siemens a few years earlier. He was familiar with Bell and Siemens Halske telephones through his firm's repair work for [[Televerket (Sweden)|Telegrafverket]] and [[Swedish State Railways]]. He improved these designs to produce a higher-quality instrument to be used by new telephone companies such as [[Rikstelefon]] to provide cheaper service than the Bell Group. Ericsson had no patent or [[Royalties|royalty]] problems because Bell had not patented their inventions in Scandinavia. His training as an instrument maker was reflected in the standard of finish and the ornate design of Ericsson telephones of this period. At the end of the year, he started to manufacture telephones much like those of Siemens; the first product was finished in 1879.{{Citation needed|date=April 2012}}

Ericsson became a major supplier of telephone equipment to [[Scandinavia]]. Its factory could not keep up with demand; joinery and metal-plating were contracted out. Much of its raw materials were imported; in the following decades Ericsson bought into a number of firms to ensure supplies of [[brass]], [[wire]], [[ebonite]], and [[magnet]] steel. Much of the [[walnut]] wood used for cabinets was imported from the United States.

Stockholm's telephone network expanded that year and the company reformed into a telephone manufacturer. When Bell bought the biggest telephone network in Stockholm, it only allowed its own telephones to be used with it. Ericsson's equipment was sold mainly to free telephone associations in the Swedish countryside and in other [[Nordic countries]].{{Citation needed|date=April 2012}}

The prices of Bell equipment and services led Henrik Tore Cedergren to form an independent telephone company called ''Stockholms Allmänna Telefonaktiebolag'' in 1883. As Bell would not deliver equipment to competitors, he formed a pact with Ericsson to supply the equipment for his new telephone network. In 1918 the companies were merged into ''Allmänna Telefonaktiebolaget LM Ericsson''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Beckman|first=Bengt|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=KPgrBgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA10&amp;dq=Allm%C3%A4nna+Telefonaktiebolaget+LM+Ericsson&amp;hl=en&amp;newbks=1&amp;newbks_redir=0&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=2ahUKEwihoZWciPfnAhWqknIEHf30DYwQ6AEwAHoECAYQAg#v=onepage&amp;q=Allm%C3%A4nna%20Telefonaktiebolaget%20LM%20Ericsson&amp;f=false|title=Swedish Signal Intelligence 1900-1945|last2=McKay|first2=C. G.|date=2013-01-11|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-1-136-34148-9|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1884, a multiple-[[Telephone switchboard|switchboard]] manual [[telephone exchange]] was mostly copied from a design by C.&amp;nbsp;E. Scribner at [[Western Electric]]. This was legal because the device was not patented in Sweden, although in the United States it had held [[patent]] 529421 since 1879. A single switchboard could handle up to 10,000 lines. The following year, LM Ericsson and Cedergren toured the United States, visiting several telephone exchange stations to gather &quot;inspiration&quot;.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}} They found U.S. switchboard designs were more advanced but Ericsson telephones were equal to others.{{Citation needed|date=April 2012}}

In 1884, a technician named Anton Avén at ''Stockholms Allmänna Telefonaktiebolag'' combined the earpiece and the mouthpiece of a standard telephone into a handset. It was used by operators in the exchanges where operators needed to have one hand free when talking to customers. Ericsson picked up this invention and incorporated it into Ericsson products, beginning with a telephone named ''The [[Telephone magneto|Dachshund]]''.

===International expansion===
[[File:Thinktank Birmingham - object 1961S01536.00001(1).jpg|thumb|upright|An early, wooden, Ericsson telephone, made by the Ericsson Telephone Co. Ltd., of [[Nottingham]], England, it is now in the collection of [[Thinktank, Birmingham Science Museum]].]]

As production grew in the late 1890s, and the Swedish market seemed to be reaching saturation, Ericsson expanded into foreign markets through a number of agents. The UK ([[Ericsson Telephones Ltd.]]) and Russia were early markets, where factories were later established improve the chances of gaining local contracts and to augment the output of the Swedish factory. In the UK, the [[National Telephone Company]] was a major customer; by 1897 sold 28% of its output in the UK. The Nordic countries were also Ericsson customers; they were encouraged by the growth of telephone services in Sweden.&lt;ref name=&quot;BizHistory&quot; /&gt;

Other countries and colonies were exposed to Ericsson products through the influence of their parent countries. These included Australia and New Zealand, which by the late 1890s were Ericsson's largest non-European markets. [[Mass production]] techniques now firmly established; telephones were losing some of their ornate finish and decoration.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.telephonecollecting.org/Bobs%20phones/Pages/SwedEricsson/EricssonCradles.htm |title=Ericsson Cradles |website=Bobs Phones Page |accessdate=1 September 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite their successes elsewhere, Ericsson did not make significant sales into the United States. The Bell Group, [[KBR (company)|Kellogg]] and [[Automatic Electric]] dominated the market. Ericsson eventually sold its U.S. assets. Sales in Mexico led to inroads into South American countries. South Africa and China were also generating significant sales. With his company now multinational, Lars Ericsson stepped down from the company in 1901.

===Automatic equipment===
[[File:Ericsson telefonplan 20050902 001.jpg|thumb|LM Ericsson's former headquarters at [[Telefonplan]] in Stockholm, see LM Ericsson building]]

Ericsson ignored the growth of [[automatic telephony]] in the United States and concentrated on manual exchange designs. Their first dial telephone was produced in 1921, although sales of the early automatic switching systems were slow until the equipment had proven itself on the world's markets. Telephones of this period had a simpler design and finish, and many of the early automatic desk telephones in Ericsson's catalogues were magneto styles with a dial on the front and appropriate changes to the electronics. Elaborate decals decorated the cases.&lt;ref name=&quot;BizHistory&quot; /&gt; [[World War I]], the subsequent [[Great Depression]], and the loss of its Russian assets after the [[Russian Revolution (1917)|Revolution]] slowed the company's development while sales to other countries fell by about half.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.ericsson.com/en/about-us/history/company/the-consequences-of-expansion/ericsson-and-the-great-depression|title=1931|date=2016-08-30|website=Ericsson.com|language=en|access-date=2019-01-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Shareholding changes===
The acquisition of other telecommunications companies put pressure on Ericsson's finances; in 1925, Karl Fredric Wincrantz took control of the company by acquiring most of the shares. Wincrantz was partly funded by [[Ivar Kreuger]], an international financier. The company was renamed ''Telefon AB LM Ericsson''. Kreuger started showing interest in the company, being a major owner of Wincrantz holding companies.&lt;ref name=&quot;BizHistory&quot; /&gt;

In 1928, Ericsson began issuing &quot;A&quot; and &quot;B&quot; shares; an &quot;A&quot; share had 1000 votes against a &quot;B&quot; share.  Wincrantz controlled the company by having only a few &quot;A&quot; shares, not a majority of the shares. The company raised more money by issuing a lot of &quot;B&quot; shares while maintaining the ''status quo'' of power distribution.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}} In 1930, the second issue of &quot;B&quot;-shares took place, and Kreuger gained majority control of the company with a mixture of &quot;A&quot; and &quot;B&quot; shares he bought with money lent by LM Ericsson, with [[collateral (finance)|security]] given in German state [[Bond (finance)|bonds]].  He then took a loan for his own company [[Kreuger &amp; Toll]] from [[ITT Corporation]] (administered by [[Sosthenes Behn]]), giving parts of LM Ericsson as security, and used its assets and name in a series of international financial dealings.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}}

Ericsson was now regarded by ITT as a takeover target as its main international competitor. In 1931, ITT acquired enough shares from Kreuger to have a majority interest in Ericsson. This news was not made public for some time because of a government-imposed limit on foreign shareholdings in Swedish companies, so the shares were still listed in Kreuger's name.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}} Kreuger in return gained shares in ITT; he stood to make a profit of $11&amp;nbsp;million{{clarify|reason=which currency?|date=January 2016}} on the deal.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}}  When ITT's Behn wanted to cancel this deal in 1932, he discovered there was no money left in the company, just a large claim on the same Kreuger &amp; Toll that Kreuger had himself lent money to. Kreuger had effectively bought LM Ericsson with its own money.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}}

Kreuger had been using the company as security for loans; despite his profits he was unable to repay them. Ericsson found they had invested in some doubtful share deals, whose losses were deemed significant. ITT examined the deal and found it had been misled about Ericsson's value.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}} ITT asked Kreuger to go to New York City for a conference, but he did not attend. As word of Kreuger's financial position spread, the banking institutions pressured him to provide security for his loans.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}} ITT cancelled the deal to buy Ericsson shares. Kreuger could not repay the $11&amp;nbsp;million, and committed suicide in Paris in 1932.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}} ITT owned one-third of Ericsson, but was forbidden to exercise this ownership because of a paragraph in the company's articles of association stating that no foreign investor was allowed to control more than 20% of the votes.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}}

===Wallenberg era begins===
Ericsson was saved from bankruptcy and closure with the help of banks including [[Stockholms Enskilda Bank]] (now [[Skandinaviska Enskilda Banken]]) and other Swedish investment banks controlled by the [[Wallenberg family]], and some Swedish government backing. Marcus Wallenberg Jr. negotiated a deal with several Swedish banks to rebuild Ericsson financially. The banks gradually increased their possession of LM Ericsson &quot;A&quot; shares, while ITT was still the largest shareholder. In 1960, the Wallenberg family arranged with ITT to buy its shares in Ericsson, and has since controlled the company.&lt;ref name=&quot;BizHistory&quot; /&gt;

===Market development===
[[File:Ericsson bakelittelefon 1931 sv.jpg|thumb|The Ericsson DBH1001 (1931) was the first combined telephone set with a housing and handset made from Bakelite. The design is attributed to Jean Heiberg.]]
[[File:Ericsson 1950s bakelite telephone.jpg|thumb|The Ericsson DBH15 telephone, a successor of the DBH 1001 and redesigned in 1947 by Gerard Kiljan]]

In the 1920s and 1930s, the world telephone markets were being organized and stabilized by many governments. The fragmented town-by-town systems serviced by small, private companies that had evolved were integrated and offered for lease to a single company. Ericsson obtained some leases, which represented further sales of equipment to the growing networks. Ericsson got almost one-third of its sales under the control of its telephone operating companies.&lt;ref name=&quot;BizHistory&quot; /&gt;

Negotiations between the major telephone companies aimed at dividing up the world between them.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}} The size of ITT made it hard to compete with. Ericsson reduced its involvement in telephone operating companies and went back to manufacturing telephones and [[switchgear]]. The [[Beeston, Nottinghamshire|Beeston]] factory in the UK had been a joint venture between Ericsson and the National Telephone Company.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}} The factory built automatic switching equipment for the GPO under license from Strowger, and exported products to former UK colonies.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}} The UK government divided its equipment contracts between competing manufacturers, but Ericsson's presence and manufacturing facilities in the UK allowed it to get most of the contracts.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}}

Sales drives resumed after the [[Great Depression]], but the company never achieved the market penetration that it had at the turn of the century. It still produced a range of telephones and switching equipment; the latter was becoming a more important part of its range. The distinctive Ericsson styles became subdued by the increasing use of bakelite telephones starting in the 1930s.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}}

===Further development===
Ericsson introduced the world's first fully automatic mobile telephone system, [[MTD (mobile network)#MTA|MTA]], in 1956.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cellular-news.com/story/19883.php |title=Ericsson Celebrates 50 Years of Mobile Telephony |website=Cellular-news.com |date=17 October 2006 |accessdate=9 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; It released one of the world's first hands-free speaker telephones in the 1960s. In 1954, it released the [[Ericofon]]. Ericsson [[crossbar switching]] equipment was used in telephone administrations in many countries.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Economist 1964 p. 1028&quot;&gt;{{cite book | title=The Economist | publisher=Economist Newspaper Limited | issue=v. 211, no. 2 | year=1964 | url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Kte7AAAAIAAJ | access-date=4 May 2019 | page=1028 |quote=... that are visible in Ericsson telephones have also been applied to the continuing improvement of high speed switching ... Ericsson crossbar systems are now standard equipment in many countries.}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1983 the company introduced the [[ERIPAX]] suite of network products and services.

===1995–2003: emergence of the Internet===
In the 1990s, during the emergence of the Internet, Ericsson was regarded as slow to realize its potential and falling behind in the area of IP technology.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Internet and the New World|url=http://www.ericssonhistory.com/changing-the-world/Big-bang/The-internet-and-the-new-world-/|website=History of Ericsson}}&lt;/ref&gt; But the company had established an Internet project in 1995 called Infocom Systems to exploit opportunities leading from fixed-line telecom and IT. CEO Lars Ramqvist wrote in the 1996 annual report that in all three of its business areas – Mobile Telephones and Terminals, Mobile Systems, and Infocom Systems – &quot;we will expand our operations as they relate to customer service and Internet Protocol (IP) access (Internet and intranet access)&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;ericsson.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Annual Report 1996|website=Ericsson|url=https://www.ericsson.com/assets/local/investors/documents/financial-reports-and-filings/annual-reports/annualreport1996_en.pdf|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Ericsson mobil.jpg|thumb|left|200px|An [[Ericsson GH337]] (1995) and [[Ericsson T28]] (1999) mobile phones]]
The growth of [[GSM]], which became a ''de facto'' world standard, combined with Ericsson's other mobile standards, such as [[D-AMPS]] and [[Personal Digital Cellular|PDC]], meant that by the start of 1997, Ericsson had an estimated 40% share of the world's mobile market, with around 54 million subscribers. There were also around 188&amp;nbsp;million [[AXE telephone exchange|AXE]] lines in place or on order in 117 countries.&lt;ref name=&quot;ericsson.com&quot; /&gt; Telecom and chip companies worked in the 1990s to provide Internet access over mobile telephones. Early versions such as [[Wireless Application Protocol]] (WAP) used packet data over the existing GSM network, in a form known as [[GPRS]] (General Packet Radio Service), but these services, known as 2.5G, were fairly rudimentary and did not achieve much mass-market success.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}}

The [[International Telecommunication Union]] (ITU) had prepared the specifications for a [[3G]] mobile service that included several technologies. Ericsson pushed hard for the [[WCDMA]] (wideband [[Code division multiple access|CDMA]]) form based on the GSM standard, and began testing it in 1996. Japanese operator [[NTT DoCoMo]] signed deals to partner with Ericsson and Nokia, who came together in 1997 to support WCDMA over rival standards. DoCoMo was the first operator with a live 3G network, using its own version of WCDMA called [[FOMA]]. Ericsson was a significant developer of the WCDMA version of GSM, while US-based chip developer [[Qualcomm]] promoted the alternative system [[CDMA2000]], building on the popularity of CDMA in the US market. This resulted in a patent infringement lawsuit that was resolved in March 1999&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Ericsson/Qualcomm bitter feud ends|date=29 March 1999|first=Nancy|last=Gohring|url=http://connectedplanetonline.com/mag/telecom_ericssonqualcomm_bitter_feud/|website=Connected Planet|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140109040128/http://connectedplanetonline.com/mag/telecom_ericssonqualcomm_bitter_feud|archivedate=9 January 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; when the two companies agreed to pay each other royalties for the use of their respective technologies and Ericsson purchased Qualcomm's wireless infrastructure business and some R&amp;D resources.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Short Take: Qualcomm, Ericsson finalize CDMA agreement |url=http://news.cnet.com/Short-Take-Qualcomm,-Ericsson-finalize-CDMA-agreement/2110-1033_3-226260.html |archive-url=https://wayback.archive-it.org/all/20171018160816/https://www.cnet.com/news/ |url-status=dead |archive-date=2017-10-18 |work=[[CNET]] }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Once the Qualcomm conflict was settled, Ericsson continued to be involved in mobile Internet. It announced a partnership with Microsoft to combine its web browser and server software with Ericsson's mobile Internet technologies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Microsoft, Ericsson announce strategic partnership to drive mobile Internet market|url=http://www.mobic.com/oldnews/9912/microsoft.htm|website=Mobic.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; The subsequent joint venture was dissolved in 2001 in the aftermath of the Internet and telecom crashes.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}}

Ericsson got caught up in the [[Dot-com bubble]] of the late 1990s. The company's market value increased; its share price peaked at [[Swedish krona|SEK]] 825 in March 2000, from a low of SEK 20 at the start of the 1990s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Shareholder Information {{ndash}} Share Graphs and Figures|url=http://www.ericsson.com/thecompany/investors/shareholder-information/share-graphs|website=Ericsson|access-date=7 July 2014|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140714202419/http://www.ericsson.com/thecompany/investors/shareholder-information/share-graphs|archive-date=14 July 2014|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Lars Ramqvist]] resigned as CEO in January 1998, and later became chairperson of the board. [[Sven-Christer Nilsson]] took over as CEO in early 1998, and led the company in a clearer IP direction. Under his leadership, the company's acquisitions including a share in US router company Juniper.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Ericsson Stake in Juniper|date=18 March 1999|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1999/03/18/business/ericsson-stake-in-juniper.html|work=The New York Times}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Ericsson had become a leading player in networks and the production of mobile telephones, sharing top place with [[Nokia]] and [[Motorola]] during 1997.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Problems with Mobile Phones|url=http://www.ericssonhistory.com/changing-the-world/Big-bang/Problems-with-mobile-phones-/|website=History of Ericsson}}&lt;/ref&gt; Services were becoming increasingly important; Ericsson had offered network rollout services for many years, and had operated networks, but at the end of the 1990s the service operations were amalgamated into a services unit.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}}

In June 1999, Kurt Hellström, the head of Ericsson's mobile division, replaced Nilsson as CEO.  Worldwide hype around the potential of the internet – and for Ericsson, in particular, the mobile internet – had inflated industry expectations.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}} Operators in many Westernized countries used much of their capital bidding for 3G licenses, and could not afford the new networks required to use the spectrum they had acquired.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}} The order intake that Ericsson and other telecom vendors had expected, and invested in preparing for, was disappointing, causing job losses and consolidations across the industry.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}}

Ericsson issued a profit warning in March 2001. Over the coming year, sales to operators halved.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Crisis|url=http://www.ericssonhistory.com/changing-the-world/Big-bang/Crisis/|website=History of Ericsson}}&lt;/ref&gt; Mobile telephones became a burden; the company's telephones unit made a loss of SEK 24 million in 2000. A fire in a Philips chip factory in New Mexico in March 2000 caused severe disruption to Ericsson's phone production,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Fire That Changed an Industry: A Case Study on Thriving in a Networked World|date=1 October 2008|first=Amit S.|last=Mukherjee|url=http://www.ftpress.com/articles/article.aspx?p=1244469|website=FT Press}}&lt;/ref&gt; dealing a ''coup de grâce'' to Ericsson's mobile phone hopes. Mobile phones would be spun off into a joint venture with Sony, Sony Ericsson Mobile Communications, in October 2001.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.cision.com/ericsson/r/sony-ericsson-mobile-communications-established-today,c48602 |title=Sony Ericsson Mobile Communications established today - Ericsson |website=News.cision.com |date=2001-10-01 |accessdate=2016-11-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Ericsson launched several rounds of restructuring, refinancing and job-cutting; during 2001, staff numbers fell from 107,000 to 85,000.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author1=Svenolof Karlsson |author2=Anders Lugn |url=http://www.ericssonhistory.com/changing-the-world/Big-bang/The-first-cutbacks/ |title=The first cutbacks |publisher=Ericsson History |date= |accessdate=2016-11-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; A further 20,000 went the next year,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author1=Svenolof Karlsson |author2=Anders Lugn  |url=http://www.ericssonhistory.com/changing-the-world/Big-bang/Second-round-of-cuts-/ |title=Second round of cuts |publisher=Ericsson History |date= |accessdate=2016-11-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; and 11,000 more in 2003.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author1=Svenolof Karlsson |author2=Anders Lugn  |url=http://www.ericssonhistory.com/changing-the-world/Big-bang/A-new-chairman-of-the-board/ |title=A new chairman of the board |publisher=Ericsson History |date= |accessdate=2016-11-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; A new rights issue raised SEK 30&amp;nbsp;billion to keep the company afloat. The company had survived as mobile Internet started growing. With record profits, it was in better shape than many of its competitors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author1=Svenolof Karlsson |author2=Anders Lugn |url=http://www.ericssonhistory.com/changing-the-world/Everyone-on-board/Record-profits/ |title=Record profits |publisher=Ericsson History |date= |accessdate=2016-11-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===2003–2018: rebuilding and growing===
The emergence of full mobile Internet began a period of growth for the global telecom industry, including Ericsson. After the launch of 3G services during 2003,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Pike |first=Rebecca |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/business/2856127.stm |title=Business &amp;#124; Italians pick up first 3G mobile phones |work=BBC News |date=2003-03-17 |accessdate=2016-11-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/technology/2808761.stm |title=Technology &amp;#124; 3G goes live in the UK |work=BBC News |date=2003-03-03 |accessdate=2016-11-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; people started to access the Internet using their telephones.

Ericsson's position as a supplier of [[GSM]] equipment to many major operators, and its pioneering role in the emerging 3G standards and associated technology, placed it at the forefront of many of the changes to come. The cutbacks that followed 10 consecutive quarters of losses meant the company could return to profit in Q3 2003, and begin to grow again.  After announcing in 2003 that it had returned to growth, new CEO Carl-Henric Svanberg said the company was to concentrate on operational excellence, a wide-ranging push for efficiency and better return on investment that dominated Ericsson's corporate culture for several years.{{citation needed|date=July 2014}}

During the cutbacks, Ericsson had reduced its CDMA organization. This standard, used largely in North America, Japan and mainland Asia, was a rival to GSM, and Ericsson had a global market share of 25%, but the overall volumes were too low so Ericsson wound down its CDMA commitment, ending it completely by 2006.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}} Ericsson started a series of acquisitions to strengthen its position in key technologies and market segments.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}} The first of these was Marconi, a company dating back to the dawn of radio whose assets included a strong portfolio in transmission, fiber optic and fixed network services.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.ericsson.com/en/about-us/history/changing-the-world/the-future-is-now/acquisition-of-marconi |title=Acquisition of Marconi|publisher=Ericsson |date=2006-05-09 |accessdate=2017-09-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Further acquisitions included Redback Networks (carrier edge-routers), Entrisphere (fiber) and [[LHS Telekommunikation]] (customer care services) in 2007, and Tandberg Television in 2008.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}} Ericsson sold its enterprise PBX division to [[Aastra Technologies]] the same year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release|title=Aastra Technologies to acquire Ericsson's Enterprise Communication Business |publisher=Aastra |date=18 February 2008 |url=http://www.aastra.com/news-room-2008_1554.htm |accessdate=18 February 2008 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140704233336/http://www.aastra.com/news-room-2008_1554.htm |archivedate=4 July 2014 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release |title=Ericsson to divest its enterprise PBX solutions to Aastra Technologies |publisher=Ericsson |date=18 February 2008 |url=http://www.ericsson.com/ericsson/press/releases/20080218-1192670.shtml |accessdate=7 November 2008 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20081220194126/http://www.ericsson.com/ericsson/press/releases/20080218-1192670.shtml |archivedate=20 December 2008 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt; Ericsson re-entered the CDMA market after acquiring North American vendor Nortel's CDMA operations and assets in 2009.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}} The acquisitions followed Ericsson's general strategy of expanding into next-generation network technologies and multimedia, a combined offering that became more important as video became the dominant form of data traffic on mobile broadband networks.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}}40% of the world's mobile traffic is carried over Ericsson networks.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.ericsson.com/about-us|title=About Ericsson - Corporate Information|website=Ericsson.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ericsson created a division to develop its multimedia business in early 2007.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}}

Ericsson was working on ways to improve [[WCDMA]] as operators were buying and rolling it out; it was the first generation of 3G access. New advances included IMS (IP Multimedia Subsystem) and the next evolution of WCDMA, called [[High-Speed Packet Access]] (HSPA). It was initially deployed in the download version called [[HSDPA]]; the technology spread from the first test calls in the US in late 2005&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.phonescoop.com/articles/article.php?a=1050 |title=Cingular HSDPA Test Successful |publisher=Phone Scoop |date=2005-01-04 |accessdate=2016-11-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; to 59 commercial networks in September 2006.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ericsson.com/ericsson/corpinfo/publications/review/2006_03/06.shtml |title=HSDPA performance and evolution |publisher=Ericsson |date= |accessdate=2016-11-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; HSPA would provide the world's first mobile broadband.

In July 2016, Hans Vestberg stepped down as Ericsson's CEO after heading the company for six years. Jan Frykhammar, who has been working for the company since 1991 will be stepping in as interim CEO as Ericsson searches for a full-time replacement.&lt;ref&gt;Brian Heater, TechCrunch. &quot;[https://techcrunch.com/2016/07/25/ericsson-ceo/ Ericsson's CEO steps down as the company begins search for a replacement].&quot; 25 July 2016. 25 July 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 16 January 2017, following Ericsson's announcement on 26 October 2016, new CEO Börje Ekholm started and interim CEO Jan Frykhammar stepped down the following day.&lt;ref&gt;Ericsson AB. &quot;[https://www.ericsson.com/news/2051527 Ericsson's Board names Börje Ekholm new President and CEO].&quot; 26 October 2016. 26 October 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 2018, Ericsson, Inc. and Ericsson AB have agreed to pay $145,893 to settle potential civil liability for an apparent violation of the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (IEEPA) and the Sudanese Sanctions Regulations, 31 C.F.R. part 538 (SSR).1&lt;ref&gt;Treasury Civil Penalty information &quot;https://www.treasury.gov/resource-center/sanctions/CivPen/Documents/20180606_ericsson.pdf&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

===Acquisitions, expansion, consolidation and cooperation===
Around 2000, companies and governments began to push for standards for mobile Internet. In May 2000, the [[European Commission]] created the [[Wireless Strategic Initiative]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=ftp://ftp.cordis.europa.eu/pub/ist/docs/ka4/mob_wsi.pdf|archive-url=https://wayback.archive-it.org/all/20171020163404/ftp://ftp.cordis.europa.eu/pub/ist/docs/ka4/mob_wsi.pdf|url-status=dead|archive-date=20 October 2017|title=WSI (Wireless Strategic Initiative)|publisher=Ericsson.se|date=1 May 2000}}&lt;/ref&gt; a consortium of four telecommunications suppliers in Europe – Ericsson, Nokia, [[Alcatel-Lucent|Alcatel]] (France), and [[Siemens AG]] (Germany) – to develop and test new prototypes for advanced wireless communications systems. Later that year, the consortium partners invited other companies to join them in a Wireless World Research Forum in 2001.&lt;ref name=&quot;InfoWorld p. 77-IA1&quot;&gt;{{cite book | title=InfoWorld | publisher=InfoWorld Media Group, Inc. | url=https://books.google.com/books?id=rzgEAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA77-IA1 | access-date=2018-12-17 | page=77-IA1}}&lt;/ref&gt; In December 1999, Microsoft and Ericsson announced a [[strategic partnership]] to combine the former's web browser and server software with the latter's mobile-internet technologies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.microsoft.com/en-us/news/features/1999/12-08ericsson.aspx|archive-url= http://webarchive.loc.gov/all/20120802225854/http://www.microsoft.com/en-us/news/features/1999/12-08ericsson.aspx|url-status=dead|archive-date= 2 August 2012|title= Microsoft, Ericsson Team Up to Bring Information Anytime Anywhere, to Carriers and Consumers|publisher= Microsoft.com|date= 8 December 1999|accessdate= 20 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2000, the Dot-com bubble burst with marked [[Economy of Sweden|economic implications for Sweden]]. Ericsson, the world's largest producer of mobile telecommunications equipment, shed thousands of jobs, as did the country's Internet consulting firms and [[dot-com start-up]]s. In the same year, [[Intel]], the world's largest semiconductor chip manufacturer, signed a $1.5&amp;nbsp;billion deal to supply [[flash memory]] to Ericsson over the next three years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.cnet.com/Intel-scores-flash-memory-deal-with-Ericsson/2100-1001_3-236518.html|title=Intel scores flash memory deal with Ericsson |publisher=cnet.com|date=4 February 2000 |accessdate=20 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The short-lived joint venture called [[Ericsson Microsoft Mobile Venture AB]], owned 70/30 percent by Ericsson and Microsoft, respectively, ended in October 2001 when Ericsson announced it would absorb the former joint venture and adopt a licensing agreement with Microsoft instead.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.itworld.com/IDG011005MicrosoftMobileJV|title= Microsoft pulls out of mobile JV with Ericsson|publisher=Itworld.com|date= 5 October 2001|accessdate=20 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The same month, Ericsson announced the launch of [[Sony Mobile Communications|Sony Ericsson]], a joint venture mobile telephone business, together with [[Sony]] Corporation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ericsson.com/press/20011001-1121.html |publisher=Ericsson.com |title=Ericsson – press release Sony Ericsson Mobile Communications established today |date=1 October 2001 |accessdate=20 June 2012 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20020209200043/http://www.ericsson.com/press/20011001-1121.html |archivedate=9 February 2002 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Sony Ericsson remained in operation until February 2012, when Sony bought out Ericsson's share; Ericsson said it wanted to focus on the global wireless market as a whole.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ericsson.com/news/1558488| title= Sony to acquire Ericsson's share of Sony Ericsson– Press release|publisher= Ericsson.com|date= 27 Oct 2011|accessdate=20 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.sonymobile.com/cws/corporate/press/pressreleases/pressreleasedetails/sonycompletesfullacquisitionofsonyericsson-20120216 |title=Sony Completes Full Acquisition of Sony Ericsson – Press release |publisher=Sonymobile.com |date=16 February 2012 |accessdate=20 July 2012 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://archive.today/20120911075353/http://www.sonymobile.com/cws/corporate/press/pressreleases/pressreleasedetails/sonycompletesfullacquisitionofsonyericsson-20120216 |archivedate=11 September 2012 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Lower stock prices and job losses affected many telecommunications companies in 2001. The major equipment manufacturers – [[Motorola]] (U.S.), [[Lucent Technologies]] (U.S.), [[Cisco Systems]] (U.S.), [[telent plc|Marconi]] (UK), [[Siemens AG]] (Germany), Nokia (Finland), as well as Ericsson – all announced job cuts in their home countries and in subsidiaries around the world. Ericsson's workforce worldwide fell during 2001 from 107,000 to 85,000.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://ericssonhistory.com/templates/Ericsson/EricssonBook/Article.aspx?id=3926&amp;epslanguage=EN| title= Changing the World, P202, Svenolof Karlsson and Anders Lugn, Centre for Business History |publisher=Ericssonhistory.com|accessdate=21 June 2012}}{{dead link|date=October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In September 2001, Ericsson purchased the remaining shares in [[EHPT]] from [[Hewlett Packard]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://news.cision.com/ericsson/r/ericsson-acquires-hewlett-packard-s-remaining-interest-in-ehpt,c46907|title=Ericsson acquires Hewlett-Packard's remaining interest in EHPT|website=News Powered by Cision|access-date=2017-02-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; Founded in 1993, Ericsson Hewlett Packard Telecom (EHPT) was a joint venture made up of 60% Ericsson interests and 40% Hewlett-Packard interests.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bidault 2012 p. 64&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last=Bidault | first=F. | title=Managing Joint Innovation: How to Balance Trust and Control in Strategic Alliances | publisher=Palgrave Macmillan | year=2012 | isbn=978-0-230-27997-1 | url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ktZIr8CjSOgC&amp;pg=PA64 | access-date=2018-12-17 | page=64}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2002, ICT investor losses topped $2&amp;nbsp;trillion and share prices fell by 95% until August that year. More than half a million people lost their jobs in the global telecom industry over the two years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.businessweek.com/magazine/content/02_31/b3794001.htm|title=Inside the Telecom Game - How a small group of insiders made billions as the industry collapsed|publisher=Businessweek.com|date=5 August 2002|accessdate=21 June 2012|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110822060147/http://www.businessweek.com/magazine/content/02_31/b3794001.htm|archivedate=22 August 2011|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; The collapse of U.S. carrier [[WorldCom]], with more than $107&amp;nbsp;billion in assets, was the biggest in U.S. history.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url= http://money.cnn.com/2002/07/19/news/worldcom_bankruptcy/| title= WorldCom files largest bankruptcy ever |publisher= Money.cnn.com|date= 22 July 2002|accessdate=21 June 2012|first1=Luisa|last1=Beltran}}&lt;/ref&gt; The sector's problems caused bankruptcies and job losses, and led to changes in the leadership of a number of major companies. Ericsson made 20,000 more staff redundant and raised about $3&amp;nbsp;billion from its shareholders.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url= https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2002/apr/22/mobilephones.marktran| title= Ericsson axes 17,000 jobs|work= Guardian.co.uk|date= 22 April 2002|accessdate=21 June 2012|location=London|first=Mark|last=Tran}}&lt;/ref&gt; In June 2002, [[Infineon Technologies AG]] (then the sixth-largest semiconductor supplier and a subsidiary of [[Siemens]]) bought Ericsson's [[microelectronics]] unit for $400&amp;nbsp;million.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.lightreading.com/document.asp?doc_id=17308| title= Infineon Buys Ericsson Microelectronics |publisher= Lightreading.com|date= 12 June 2002|accessdate=21 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Co-operation with Hewlett-Packard did not end with [[EHPT]]; in 2003 Ericsson outsourced its IT to HP, which included Managed Services, Help Desk Support, Data Center Operations, and HP Utility Data Center. The contract was extended in 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url=https://ssl.www8.hp.com/us/en/hp-news/press-release.html?id=172163 |title=HP News - HP Signs Contract with Ericsson for Global IT Outsourcing Services |website=Ssl.www8.hp.com |date= |accessdate=2016-11-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; There have also been a number of joint Ericsson/HP Telecoms outsourcing deals with telecoms operators including H3G and Vodafone.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}} In October 2005, Ericsson acquired the bulk of the troubled UK telecommunications manufacturer [[Marconi Company]], including its brand name that dates back to the creation of the original [[Marconi Company]] by the &quot;father of radio&quot; [[Guglielmo Marconi]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.infoworld.com/t/networking/ericsson-buy-most-marconi-21b-799| title= Ericsson to buy most of Marconi for $2.1B|publisher= InfoWorld.com|date= 25 October 2005|accessdate=21 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In September 2006, Ericsson sold the greater part of its [[defense contractor|defense]] business [[Ericsson Microwave Systems]], which mainly produced sensor and radar systems, to [[Saab AB]], which renamed the company to [[Saab Microwave Systems]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.defenseindustrydaily.com/saab-acquires-ericsson-microwave-systems-02354/| title= Saab Acquires Ericsson Microwave Systems|publisher= Defense Industry Daily|date= 13 Jun 2006|accessdate=21 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The sale meant [[Saab Ericsson Space]], previously a joint venture, was now fully owned by Saab. Not included in the sale to Saab was the National Security &amp; Public Safety division, which was transferred to Ericsson with the sale.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}}

In 2007, Ericsson acquired carrier edge-router maker [[Redback Networks]], and then Entrisphere, a US-based company providing fiber-access technology.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.networkworld.com/news/2006/122006-ericsson-to-buy-redback-for.html|title= Ericsson to buy Redback for $2.1&amp;nbsp;billion|publisher= Networkworld.com|date= 20 December 2006|accessdate= 21 June 2012|url-status=dead|archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20130501044239/http://www.networkworld.com/news/2006/122006-ericsson-to-buy-redback-for.html|archivedate= 1 May 2013|df= dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; In September 2007, Ericsson acquired an 84% interest in German customer-care and billing software firm [[LHS Telekommunikation|LHS]], a stake later raised to 100%.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.ericsson.com/news/1387484 | title= All shares in LHS acquired – Press release|publisher= Ericsson.com|date= 20 Feb 2010|accessdate=21 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2008, Ericsson sold its enterprise PBX division&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ericsson.com/news/1192670 |title=Ericsson to divest its enterprise PBX solutions to Aastra Technologies – Press Release |publisher=Ericsson.com |date=18 February 2008 |accessdate=22 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; to [[Aastra Technologies]], and acquired [[Tandberg Television]], the television technology division&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.ericsson.com/news/1107685 | title= Ericsson announces cash offer to acquire Tandberg Television– Press release|publisher= Ericsson.com|date= 26 Feb 2007|accessdate=21 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; of Norwegian company [[Tandberg]].

In 2009, Ericsson bought the [[CDMA2000]] and [[3GPP Long Term Evolution|LTE]] business of [[Nortel]]’s carrier networks division for US$1.18&amp;nbsp;billion;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ericsson.com/thecompany/press/releases/2009/07/1330882| title= Ericsson to acquire majority of Nortel's North American wireless business – Press release|publisher= Ericsson.com|date= 25 July 2009|accessdate=21 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bizitek, a Turkish business support systems integrator; the Estonian manufacturing operations of electronic manufacturing company [[Elcoteq]]; and completed its acquisition of LHS.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ericsson.com/news/1323236| title= Ericsson to acquire Elcoteq's operations in Tallinn to secure manufacturing capacity in Estonia – Press release|publisher= Ericsson.com|date= 17 Jun 2009|accessdate=21 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Acquisitions in 2010 included assets from the Strategy and Technology Group of inCode, a North American business and consulting-services company;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ericsson.com/news/1443012| title= Ericsson Expands Strategy and technology consulting capabilities – Press release|publisher= Ericsson.com|date= 7 Sep 2010|accessdate=20 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nortel's majority shareholding (50% plus one share) in LG-Nortel, a joint venture between [[LG Electronics]] and Nortel Networks providing sales, R&amp;D and industrial capacity in South Korea, now known as [[LG-Ericsson|Ericsson]]-LG; further Nortel carrier-division assets, relating from Nortel's GSM business in the United States and Canada; Optimi Corporation, a U.S.–Spanish telecommunications vendor specializing in network optimization and management;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://technews.tmcnet.com/telecommunications/topics/telecommunications/articles/129027-ericsson-takes-ownership-optimi-corporation.htm| title= Ericsson Takes Ownership of Optimi Corporation|publisher= Technews.com|date= 22 December 2010|accessdate=20 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Pride, a consulting and systems-integration company operating in Italy.

In 2011, Ericsson acquired manufacturing and research facilities, and staff from the [[Guangdong Nortel Telecommunication Equipment Company]] (GDNT)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ericsson.com/news/1515119| title= Ericsson closes the Acquisition of GDNT, China – Press release|publisher= Ericsson.com|date= 12 May 2011|accessdate=20 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as Nortel's Multiservice Switch business.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.cellular-news.com/story/45584.php| title= Ericsson Buys Nortel's Multi Service Switch Businesses|publisher= Cellular-news.com|date= 25 September 2010|accessdate=20 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; It also formed a strategic alliance with [[Akamai Technologies]] to develop and market mobile cloud acceleration services.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}} Ericsson acquired U.S. company [[Telcordia Technologies]] in January 2012,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ericsson.com/news/1576841| title= Ericsson closes Telcordia acquisition– Press release|publisher= Ericsson.com|date= 12 January 2012|accessdate=20 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; an operations and business support systems (OSS/BSS) company.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Rahn |first=Cornelius |url=https://www.bloomberg.com/news/2011-06-14/ericsson-agrees-to-acquire-telcordia-for-1-15-billion-in-an-all-cash-deal.html |title=Ericsson to Buy Telcordia for $1.2 Billion to Add Services |publisher=Bloomberg |date=14 June 2011 |accessdate=9 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In March, Ericsson announced it was buying the broadcast-services division of [[Technicolor SA|Technicolor]], a media broadcast technology company.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.ericsson.com/en/press-releases/2012/7/ericsson-closes-acquisition-of-technicolors-broadcast-services-division|title=Ericsson closes acquisition of Technicolor's broadcast services division|date=2012-07-03|website=Ericsson.com|language=en|access-date=2020-02-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; In April 2012 Ericsson completed the acquisition of BelAir Networks a strong Wi-Fi network technology company.&lt;ref&gt;BroadBandTechReport. &quot;[http://www.broadbandtechreport.com/articles/2012/04/ericsson-completes-belair-buy.html Ericsson Completes BelAir Buy].&quot; 2 April 2016. Retrieved 17 August 2017.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 3 May 2013, Ericsson announced it would divest its power cable operations to Danish company [[NKT Holding]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ericsson.com/news/1699030 |title=divests its power cable operation to NKT Cables |publisher=Ericsson |date=2013-05-03 |accessdate=2016-11-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 1 July 2013, Ericsson announced it would acquire the media management company [[Ericsson Broadcast and Media Services|Red Bee Media]], subject to regulatory approval.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release|url=http://www.ericsson.com/news/1713075 |title=Ericsson to acquire leading media services company Red Bee Media |publisher=Ericsson |date=1 July 2013 |accessdate=1 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The acquisition was completed on 9 May 2014.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release|url=http://www.ericsson.com/thecompany/press/releases/2014/05/1784304 |title=Ericsson completes acquisition of Red Bee Media |publisher=Ericsson |date=12 May 2014 |accessdate=15 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; In September 2013, Ericsson completed its acquisition of Microsoft's Mediaroom business and televisions services, originally announced in April the same year. The acquisition makes Ericsson the largest provider of IPTV and multi-screen services in the world, by market share; it was renamed [[Ericsson Mediaroom]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release|url=http://www.ericsson.com/news/1727445 |title=Ericsson closes acquisition of Microsoft Mediaroom |publisher=Ericsson |date=5 September 2013 |accessdate=3 October 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In September 2014, Ericsson acquired majority stake in [[Apcera]] for cloud policy compliance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release|url=http://www.pcworld.com/article/2686932/ericsson-acquires-majority-stake-in-apcera-for-cloud-policy-compliance.html|title=Ericsson acquires majority stake in Apcera for cloud policy compliance|publisher=PCWorld|date=22 September 2014 |accessdate=22 September 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In October 2015, Ericsson completed the acquisition of [[Envivio]], a software encoding company.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.ericsson.com/en/press-releases/2015/10/ericsson-completes-acquisition-of-envivio|title=Ericsson completes acquisition of Envivio|date=2015-10-27|website=Ericsson.com|language=en|access-date=2019-04-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In April 2016, Ericsson acquired Polish and Ukrainian operations of software development company [[Ericpol]], a long-time supplier to Ericsson.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.ericsson.com/en/news/2016/4/ericsson-completes-acquisition-of-software-developer-ericpol|title=Ericsson completes acquisition of software developer Ericpol|date=2016-04-20|website=Ericsson.com|language=en|access-date=2019-07-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; Approximately 2,300 Ericpol employees joined Ericsson, bringing software development competence in radio, cloud, and IP.

On 20 June 2017, Bloomberg disclosed that Ericsson hired Morgan Stanley to explore the sale of its media businesses.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2017-06-20/ericsson-said-to-hire-banks-to-explore-sale-of-media-businesses|title=Ericsson Hires Banks to Explore Sale of Media Businesses|date=20 June 2017|publisher=|via=www.bloomberg.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Red Bee Media business was kept in-house as an independent subsidiary company, as no suitable buyer was found, but a 51% stake of the remainder of the Media Solution division was sold to private equity firm One Equity Partners, the new company being named MediaKind. The transaction was completed on 31 January 2019.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.ericsson.com/en/press-releases/2019/2/ericsson-completes-divestment-of-majority-stake-in-mediakind|title=Ericsson completes divestment of majority stake in MediaKind|date=2019-02-01|website=Ericsson.com|language=en|access-date=2019-04-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In February 2018, Ericsson acquired the location-based mobile [[data management platform]] Placecast. Ericsson has since integrated Placecast's platform and capabilities with its programmatic mobile ad subsidiary, [[Emodo]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.mobilemarketer.com/news/ericsson-buys-placecast-for-ad-geotargeting/517164/|title=Ericsson buys Placecast for ad geotargeting|website=Mobile Marketer|language=en-US|access-date=2018-12-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In May 2018, SoftBank partnered with Ericsson to trial new radio technology.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://internetofbusiness.com/softbank-machine-learning-network-design-ericsson/|title=SoftBank, Ericsson bring machine learning to mobile network design {{!}} Internet of Business|last=Murison|first=Malek|date=2018-05-17|work=Internet of Business|access-date=2018-05-23|language=en-GB}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Corporate governance==
{{As of|2016}}, members of the board of directors of LM Ericsson were: [[Leif Johansson (businessman)|Leif Johansson]], [[Jacob Wallenberg]], Kristin S. Rinne, Helena Stjernholm, Sukhinder Singh Cassidy, Börje Ekholm, Ulf J. Johansson, Mikael Lännqvist, Zlatko Hadzic, Kjell-Åke Soting, Nora Denzel, Kristin Skogen Lund, Pehr Claesson, Karin Åberg and Roger Svensson.&lt;ref name=&quot;boardofdir&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.ericsson.com/thecompany/corporate_governance/board_of_directors/members_of_the_board|title=Board of Directors |publisher=Ericsson |date= |accessdate=1 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

With 25 locations in India that have approximately 10,000 employees, Ericsson was creating a large amount of plastic waste – 25,000 bottles a month on average. Knowing the impact of plastics on the environment, both on land and in the oceans (and specifically the [[Great Pacific garbage patch]]) Ericsson team in India was keen to find a new approach to providing clean drinking water to their staff. They reviewed the volumes, counted the cost, considered the environmental impact, and then identified a solution – a simple and straightforward water filtration process called reverse osmosis (RO).
The company identified a total of 21 suitable locations (the remaining four were too small to be cost efficient) and in February they installed 150 free-standing RO free systems, thereby removing approximately 25,000 plastic bottles a month from circulation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Ashworth |first1=Tony |title=Reducing plastic waste in India |url=https://www.ericsson.com/thecompany/sustainability_corporateresponsibility/technology-for-good-blog/2018/05/15/reducing-plastic-waste-in-india/ |website=Ericsson.com |accessdate=29 August 2018 |ref=https://www.ericsson.com/thecompany/sustainability_corporateresponsibility/technology-for-good-blog/author/tony-ashworth/}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Research and development==
Ericsson has structured its R&amp;D in three levels depending on when products or technologies will be introduced to customers and users.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ericsson.com/thinkingahead/technology_insights |title=Technology and Research Insights |accessdate=2016-02-05 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160101000410/http://www.ericsson.com/thinkingahead/technology_insights |archivedate=1 January 2016 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{better source|date=July 2019}} Its research and development organization is part of 'Group Function Technology' and addresses several facets of network architecture: wireless access networks; radio access technologies; broadband technologies; packet technologies; multimedia technologies; services software; EMF safety and sustainability; security; and global services.&lt;ref name=&quot;research&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ericsson.com/thecompany/company_facts/research |title=Our Research Areas |publisher=Ericsson |date= |accessdate=2016-11-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; The head of research since 2012 is [[Sara Mazur]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ericsson.com/news/1652330 New Head of Ericsson Research appointed]. Ericsson press release, 25 Oct 2012&lt;/ref&gt;

Group Function Technology holds research co-operations with several major universities and research institutes including: [[Lund University]] in Sweden, [[Eötvös Loránd University]] in Hungary and [[Beijing Institute of Technology]] in China.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url=http://www.lunduniversity.lu.se/research-and-innovation/business-and-innovation |title=Business and innovation |publisher=Lund University |date= |accessdate=2016-11-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ericsson also holds research co-operations within several European research programs such as [[GigaWam]] and [[OASE]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ericsson.com/careers/student/rd_program |title=Early Career Program &amp;#124; Students &amp; Young Professionals &amp;#124; Ericsson Careers |publisher=Ericsson |date= |accessdate=2016-11-11 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150428113002/http://www.ericsson.com/careers/student/rd_program |archive-date=28 April 2015 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Ericsson holds 33,000 granted patents, and is the number-one holder of GSM/GPRS/EDGE, WCDMA/HSPA, and LTE essential patents.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ericsson.com/thecompany/company_facts/patents |title=Patents |publisher=Ericsson |date=2016-11-05 |accessdate=2016-11-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Ericsson hosts a developer program called Ericsson Developer Connection designed to encourage development of applications and services.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ericsson.com/developer/sub/about/index.html |title=About our developer program |publisher=Ericsson |date= |accessdate=9 October 2011 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100310212801/http://www.ericsson.com/developer/sub/about/index.html |archivedate=10 March 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Ericsson also has an open innovation initiative for beta applications and beta API's &amp; tools called Ericsson Labs.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.fastcompany.com/3004745/boost-internal-innovation-ericsson-thinks-inside-boxes|title=To Boost Internal Innovation, Ericsson Thinks Inside The Boxes|date=2013-04-16|work=Fast Company|access-date=2018-09-18|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt; The company hosts several internal innovation competitions among its employees.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.fastcompany.com/3004745/boost-internal-innovation-ericsson-thinks-inside-boxes|title=To Boost Internal Innovation, Ericsson Thinks Inside The Boxes|date=2013-04-16|work=Fast Company|access-date=2018-01-16|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Products and services==
Ericsson's business includes technology research, development, network and software development, and running and evolving operations.&lt;ref name=&quot;research&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Self Organizing Networks|website=[[YouTube]]|date=4 October 2012|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XqJsGt9jU4E}}&lt;/ref&gt; and software&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=How Ericsson is a resource for app developers|date=12 March 2012|first=Roger|last=Cheng|url=http://news.cnet.com/8301-1035_3-57394284-94/how-ericsson-is-a-resource-for-app-developers/|work=[[CNET]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Ericsson's role in Sprint Spark should not be underestimated|date=6 November 2013|first=Martha|last=Degrasse|url=http://www.rcrwireless.com/article/20131106/networks/ericssons-role-in-sprint-spark-should-not-be-underestimated/|work=RCR Wireless News}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ericsson offers end-to-end services for all major mobile communication standards,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Company Facts|url=http://www.ericsson.com/thecompany/company_facts|website=Ericsson}}&lt;/ref&gt; and has four main business units.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ericsson.com/thecompany/company_facts/businesses|title=Our Businesses|work=Ericsson.com|accessdate=19 October 2014|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20141022115054/http://www.ericsson.com/thecompany/company_facts/businesses|archivedate=22 October 2014|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Business Area Networks (earlier Business Unit Networks)===
[[Business Unit Networks]] has been headed by Johan Wibergh since 2008. It develops network infrastructure for communication needs over mobile and [[Fixed line|fixed connections]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot; /&gt; As of 1 July 2014, BNET has been divided into Business Unit Radio and Business Unit Cloud &amp; IP.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ericsson.com/news/1779546|title=New business unit structure to support networks growth|work=Ericsson.com|accessdate=19 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its products include radio base stations, [[Radio Network Controller|radio network controllers]], [[mobile switching center]]s and [[Multi-service access node|service application nodes]]. Operators use Ericsson products to migrate from 2G to 3G and, most recently, to 4G networks.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ericsson.com/ourportfolio/products/lte-radio-access-network |title=LTE Radio Access Network |publisher=Ericsson |date=2016-11-05 |accessdate=2016-11-11 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140714142543/http://www.ericsson.com/ourportfolio/products/lte-radio-access-network |archive-date=14 July 2014 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The company's network division has been described as a driver in the development of 2G, 3G, 4G/LTE technology, future 5G and the evolution towards all-IP,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.q2s.ntnu.no/eurongi2007/slides/Sabella_keynote_ngi2007.pdf |format=PDF |title=Network Architecture Evolution: towards all-IP |author=Roberto Sabella |website=Q2s.ntnu.no |accessdate=2016-11-11 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150924083438/http://www.q2s.ntnu.no/eurongi2007/slides/Sabella_keynote_ngi2007.pdf |archivedate=24 September 2015 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; and it develops and deploys advanced LTE systems,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ericsson.com/thecompany/press/mediakits/lte |title=LTE Radio Access Network |publisher=Ericsson |date=2016-11-05 |accessdate=2016-11-11 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150428123122/http://www.ericsson.com/thecompany/press/mediakits/lte |archive-date=28 April 2015 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; but it is still developing the older [[GSM]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.ericsson.com/en/portfolio/networks/ericsson-radio-system/radio-system-software/gsm-radio-access-network |title=GSM Radio Access Network |publisher=Ericsson |date=2016-10-24 |accessdate=2016-11-11 }}{{Dead link|date=September 2019 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ericsson.com/news/110701_gsm_1991_244188810_c?tagsFilter=GSM |title=GSM still making a difference |publisher=Ericsson |date= |accessdate=2016-11-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[WCDMA]], and [[CDMA]] technologies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ericsson.com/res/docs/whitepapers/wp-wcdma.pdf |title=The future of WCDMA/HSPA |accessdate=2014-07-07 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130804212405/http://www.ericsson.com/res/docs/whitepapers/wp-wcdma.pdf |archivedate=4 August 2013 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt; The company's networks portfolio also includes [[core network]]s, microwave transport, Internet Protocol (IP) networks, fixed-access services for copper and fiber, and mobile broadband modules, several levels of fixed broadband access,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ericsson.com/ourportfolio/telecom-operators/fixed-broadband-and-convergence |title=Fixed Broadband and Convergence |accessdate=2014-07-07 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140626072239/http://www.ericsson.com/ourportfolio/telecom-operators/fixed-broadband-and-convergence |archivedate=26 June 2014 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.facweb.iitkgp.ernet.in/~pallab/mob_com/Ericsson_Intro_to_IMS.pdf |title=Ericsson white paper Introduction to IMS |website=Facweb.iitkgp.ernet.in |format=PDF |date= |accessdate=2016-11-11 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171020163844/http://www.facweb.iitkgp.ernet.in/~pallab/mob_com/Ericsson_Intro_to_IMS.pdf |archive-date=20 October 2017 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; radio access networks from small [[pico cell]]s to high-capacity macro cells, controllers for radio base stations, and core network nodes that interconnect radio access networks with other parts of the network.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}} Ericsson Power Modules supplies direct current (DC)/DC converters and DC/DC regulators, mainly to the communications industry, for advanced applications, such as multiplexors, switches, routers and radio base stations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.ericsson.com/en/press-releases/2017/6/ericsson-to-divest-its-power-modules-business-to-flex |title=Power Modules |publisher=Ericsson |date=2016-09-20 |accessdate=2016-11-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; Manufacturing is in China.

===Business Unit Global Services===
Since 2010, [[Magnus Mandersson]] has been head of Business Unit Global Services.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ericsson.com/thecompany/corporate_governance/company_management |title=Management |publisher=Ericsson |date= |accessdate=2016-11-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; It provides telecoms-related managed services, including taking responsibility for running an operator's network and the related business support systems.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}} The unit is active in 180 countries; it supplies managed services,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.ericsson.com/en/portfolio/managed-services |title=Managed Services |publisher=Ericsson |date=2016-09-12 |accessdate=2016-11-11 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140626072154/http://www.ericsson.com/ourportfolio/services/managed-services-1 |archive-date=26 June 2014 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; systems integration, consulting, network rollout, design and optimization, broadcast services, learning services and support.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceC&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ericsson.com/res/thecompany/docs/press/backgrounders/prs_backgrounder.pdf |title=Product Related Services: deploy, support, optimize |accessdate=2014-07-07 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140714161953/http://www.ericsson.com/res/thecompany/docs/press/backgrounders/prs_backgrounder.pdf |archivedate=14 July 2014 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ericsson.com/ourportfolio/ericsson-academy |title=Academy - training and consulting for the telecom and ICT industry |publisher=Ericsson |date= |accessdate=2016-11-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.ericsson.com/en/portfolio/digital-services/transform-business/learning-services |title=Learning Services |publisher=Ericsson |date=2016-08-11 |accessdate=2016-11-11 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190409215401/https://www.ericsson.com/en/portfolio/digital-services/transform-business/learning-services |archive-date=9 April 2019 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.ericsson.com/en/portfolio/networks/network-services/support-services |title=Support |publisher=Ericsson |date= |accessdate=2016-11-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The company also works with television and media, public safety, and utilities. Ericsson claims to manage networks that serve more than 1&amp;nbsp;billion subscribers worldwide,&lt;ref name=&quot;ericsson2&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ericsson.com/res/thecompany/docs/press/backgrounders/global_services_press_backgrounder.pdf |title=Global Services – strengthening operator competitiveness |accessdate=2014-07-07 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140714140217/http://www.ericsson.com/res/thecompany/docs/press/backgrounders/global_services_press_backgrounder.pdf |archivedate=14 July 2014 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt; and to support customer networks that serve more than 2.5&amp;nbsp;billion subscribers.

===Business Unit Support Solutions===
[[Per Borgklint]] has headed Business Unit Support Solutions since 2011.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot; /&gt; Initially established in 2007, as Business Unit Multimedia, Ericsson announced a new strategy for its multimedia business in February 2012.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ericsson.com/news/1587729?idx=10 |title=outlines strategy for its multimedia business |publisher=Ericsson |date= |accessdate=2016-11-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its Business Unit Support Solutions now develops software for operations and business support systems ([[Operations support system|OSS]] and [[Business support system|BSS]]), real-time, multi-screen and on-demand television and media, and for the emerging [[m-commerce]] eco-system. Ericsson claims a leading position in charging and billing, serving 1.6&amp;nbsp;billion people.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=https://www.bloomberg.com/news/2012-02-21/ericsson-forms-support-business-unit-around-billing-systems.html | work=Bloomberg | first=Diana | last=Ben-Aaron | title=Ericsson Forms Support Business Unit Around Billing Systems | date=21 February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''OSS and BSS''' expanded after the integration of Telcordia,&lt;ref name=&quot;Ericsson Boards Its Own BUSS&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.lightreading.com/document.asp?doc_id=217704&amp;f_src=lightreading_gnews|title=Ericsson Boards Its Own BUSS|work=Light Reading|accessdate=6 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; and it focuses on [[Customer experience]] management including fulfilment, assurance, network optimization and real-time charging.
* '''TV and media''' offers products that enable operators and content owners to sell [[multi-screen video|multi-screen TV]] services.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.iptv-news.com/iptv_news/february_2012_3/ericsson_outlines_new_strategic_focus |title=Ericsson Outlines New Strategic Focus |work=ipTVnews |accessdate=6 March 2012 }}{{dead link|date=June 2016|bot=medic}}{{cbignore|bot=medic}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''M-Commerce''' sells mobile e-commerce products,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.lightreading.com/document.asp?doc_id=218000|title=Ericsson Teams With Western Union|work=Light Reading|accessdate=6 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; for [https://www.behance.net/gallery/35815981/Telecom-Distributor-in-Dubai mobile operators] and financial institutions offer mobile wallet services to consumers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.telecomstechnews.com/news/2012/feb/21/ericsson-announces-new-m-commerce-portfolio/|title=Ericsson Announces New M-Commerce Portfolio|work=TelecomsTech |accessdate=6 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ericsson has announced m-commerce deals with Western Union&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url= https://www.bloomberg.com/news/2012-02-27/ericsson-ceo-turns-to-mobile-wallet-amid-short-term-uncertainty.html|title=Ericsson Turns To Mobile Wallet Amid Short-Term Uncertainty|work=Bloomberg |accessdate=6 March 2012|first=Marie|last=Mawad|date=28 February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; and African wireless carrier MTN.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mobileeurope.co.uk/news/news-analysis/9168-ericsson-announces-mcommerce-deals-picocell-and-in-building-products |title=Ericsson Announces MCommerce Deals, Picocell And In-Building Products |work=Mobile Europe |accessdate=6 March 2012 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120229172741/http://www.mobileeurope.co.uk/news/news-analysis/9168-ericsson-announces-mcommerce-deals-picocell-and-in-building-products |archivedate=29 February 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Systems integration====
Ericsson's [[systems integration]] offering currently{{when|date=July 2015}} consists of seven service offerings:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ericsson.com/res/thecompany/docs/press/backgrounders/csi_press_backgrounder.pdf |title=CONSULTING AND SYSTEMS INTEGRATION – MAKING SENSE OF A NEW WORLD |accessdate=2014-07-07 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140714225334/http://www.ericsson.com/res/thecompany/docs/press/backgrounders/csi_press_backgrounder.pdf |archivedate=14 July 2014 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Operations Support Systems
* Business Support Systems
* IP Networks and Architecture
* TV, Applications and Service Delivery Platforms
* Solution and Life-Cycle Management
* Data Migration
* Multi-Vendor Verification

====Network services====
Ericsson's network rollout services employ in-house capabilities, subcontractors and central resources to make changes to live networks.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ericsson.com/ourportfolio/services/network-roll-out |title=Network Roll-Out |publisher=Ericsson |date=2016-10-13 |accessdate=2016-11-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; Services such as technology deployment, network transformation, support services and network optimization are also provided.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceC&quot; /&gt;

====Broadcast services====
Ericsson's Broadcast Services deal with the [[playout]] of live and pre-recorded, commercial and public service television programmes, including [[continuity (broadcasting)|presentation]] (continuity announcements), [[Trailer (promotion)#TV show trailers|trailers]], and ancillary access services such as closed-caption [[subtitle (captioning)|subtitles]], [[audio description]] and in-vision [[sign language]] interpreters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ericsson.com/res/thecompany/docs/press/backgrounders/broadcast_services_press_backgrounder.pdf |title=BROADCAST &amp; Media SERVICES – MANAGING THE TRANSFORMATION OF TV |accessdate=2015-08-27 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150713012926/http://www.ericsson.com/res/thecompany/docs/press/backgrounders/broadcast_services_press_backgrounder.pdf |archivedate=13 July 2015 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt; Its media management services consist of Managed Media Preparation and Managed Media Internet Delivery.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ericsson.com/news/130909-ericsson-launches-new-media-management-services_244129227_c |title=Ericsson |publisher=Ericsson |date=2013-09-09 |accessdate=2016-11-11 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140714130425/http://www.ericsson.com/news/130909-ericsson-launches-new-media-management-services_244129227_c |archive-date=14 July 2014 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Business Unit Modems===
As of 7 May 2014, [[Robert Puskaric]] assumed the role as vice president and head of [[Business Unit Modems]], succeeding Mats Norin who had the position since August 2013.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ericsson.com/thecompany/press/releases/2014/05/1782930|title=Ericsson|work=Ericsson.com|accessdate=19 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; This unit designs and sells LTE multimode thin modems, including 2G, 3G and 4G interoperability.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ericsson.com/news/130815-head-of-bu-modems_244129227_c?query=Business+Unit+Modems |title=Ericsson |publisher=Ericsson |date= |accessdate=2016-11-11 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150713020225/http://www.ericsson.com/news/130815-head-of-bu-modems_244129227_c?query=Business+Unit+Modems |archive-date=13 July 2015 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; This activity was transferred to Ericsson from ST-Ericsson when the new Modems organization was put in place.&lt;ref&gt;[http://internal.ericsson.com/news/6380/day-1-new-modems-organization?unit=GFCO]{{dead link|date=November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The unit has developed products including the Ericsson M7000 series multimode modems which support LTE (FDD /TDD), HSPA+, HSPA, TD-SCDMA and EDGE. In September 2014, Ericsson announced it would stop developing modems, shutting a loss-making unit it took on after joint venture partner STMicroelectronics pulled out.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url= https://www.reuters.com/article/us-ericsson-modems/ericsson-to-shut-modem-business-1000-jobs-to-go-idUSKBN0HD0MM20140918| title= Ericsson to shut modem business, 1,000 jobs to go|work= Reuters|date= 18 September 2006|accessdate=18 September 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Divested businesses==
[[Sony Ericsson]] Mobile Communications AB (Sony Ericsson) was a joint venture with [[Sony]] that merged the previous mobile telephone operations of both companies. It manufactured mobile telephones, accessories and personal computer (PC) cards. Sony Ericsson was responsible for product design and development, marketing, sales, distribution and customer services. On 16 February 2012, Sony announced it had completed the full acquisition of Sony Ericsson.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.sony.net/SonyInfo/News/Press/201202/12-025E/ |title=Sony Completes Full Acquisition of Sony Ericsson Sony to Rename the Company Sony Mobile Communications and Accelerate Business Integration |publisher= |via=sony.net |access-date=23 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Further|List of Sony Ericsson products}}

===Mobile (cell) telephones===
As a joint venture with Sony, Ericsson's mobile telephone production was moved into the company Sony Ericsson in 2001. The following is a list of mobile phones marketed under the brand name Ericsson.
[[File:Ericsson-gf-768.jpg|thumb|GF 768]]
* Ericsson GS88 – Cancelled mobile telephone where Ericsson invented the &quot;Smartphone&quot; name for
* Ericsson GA628 – Known for its [[Z80]] CPU
* Ericsson SH888 – First mobile telephone to have wireless modem capabilities
* Ericsson A1018 – Dualband cellphone, notably easy to hack
* Ericsson A2618  &amp; Ericsson A2628 – Dualband cellphones. Use graphical LCD display based on PCF8548 I²C controller.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.module.ro/ericsson_lcd.html |title=Ericsson_lcd |publisher=Module.ro |date= |accessdate=9 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Ericsson PF768
* Ericsson GF768
* Ericsson GH388
* Ericsson T10 – Colourful Cellphone
* Ericsson T18 – Business model of the T10, with active flip
* [[Ericsson T28]] – Very slim telephone. Uses [[Lithium-ion polymer battery|lithium polymer]] batteries. [http://www.lokety.com/t28faq.html ''Ericsson T28'' FAQ] use graphical LCD display based on PCF8558 I²C controller.
* Ericsson T20s
* Ericsson T29s – Similar to the T28s, but with WAP support
* Ericsson T29m – pre-alpha prototype for the T39m
* Ericsson T36m – Prototype for the T39m. Announced in yellow and blue. Never hit the market due to release T39m
* [[Ericsson T39]] – Similar to the T28, but with a GPRS modem, Bluetooth and triband capabilities
* Ericsson T65
* [[Ericsson T66]]
* Ericsson T68m – The first Ericsson handset to have a color display, later branded as [[Sony Ericsson T68i]]
* Ericsson R250s Pro – Fully dust and water resistant telephone
* [[Ericsson R310s]]
* Ericsson R320s
* Ericsson R320s Titan – Limited Edition with titanium front
* Ericsson R320s GPRS – Prototype for testing GPRS networks
* Ericsson R360m – Pre-alpha prototype for the R520m
* [[Ericsson R380]] – First cellphone to use the [[Symbian OS]]
* Ericsson R520m – Similar to the T39, but in a candy bar form factor{{clarify|date=July 2014}} and with added features such as a built-in [[speakerphone]] and an optical proximity sensor
* Ericsson R520m UMTS – Prototype to test UMTS networks
* Ericsson R520m SyncML – Prototype to test the SyncML implementation
* Ericsson R580m – Announced in several press releases. Supposed to be a successor of the R380s without external antenna and with color display
* Ericsson R600

===Telephones===
* [[Ericsson Dialog]]
* [[Ericofon]]

===Ericsson Mobile Platforms===
[[Ericsson Mobile Platforms]] was a supplier of technology platforms for GSM/EDGE and WCDMA/HSPA platforms used in devices, such as mobile handsets and PC cards.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}} Through Ericsson Mobile Platforms, Ericsson licensed open-standard, end-to-end interoperability-tested GSM/EDGE and WCDMA technology platforms.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}} The product offering included reference designs, platform software, application-specific integrated circuit (ASIC) designs and development boards, development and test tools, training, support and documentation. Ericsson Mobile Platforms had operations at nine global locations, with main operations in Sweden.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}}

The company existed for eight years; on 12 February 2009, Ericsson announced it would be merged with the mobile platform company of [[STMicroelectronics]], ST-NXP Wireless, to create a 50/50 joint venture owned by Ericsson and STMicroelectronics.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.ericsson.com/en/press-releases/2009/2/st-ericsson-born-as-wireless-semiconductor-industry-leader|title=ST-Ericsson born as wireless-semiconductor industry leader |publisher=Ericsson |date=2009-02-12 |accessdate=2016-11-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;
This joint venture was divested in 2013 and remaining activities can be found in [[Ericsson Modems]] and [[STMicroelectronics]]. Ericsson Mobile Platform ceased being a legal entity early 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.bloomberg.com/research/stocks/private/snapshot.asp?privcapId=8377976|title=Bloomberg - Ericsson Mobile Platforms AB|last=|first=|date=|website=www.bloomberg.com|access-date=2018-12-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ericsson Enterprise===
Starting in 1983 Ericsson Enterprise provided communications systems and services for businesses, public entities and educational institutions. It produced products for [[voice over Internet protocol]] (VoIP)-based [[private branch exchange]]s (PBX), [[wireless local area network]]s (WLAN), and mobile [[intranet]]s.
Ericsson Enterprise operated mainly from Sweden but also operated through regional units and other partners/distributors. In 2008 it was sold to [[Aastra]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aastra.com/news-room-2008_1554.htm |title=Aastra Technologies to acquire Ericsson’s Enterprise Communication Business |date=2008-02-18 |accessdate=2008-02-18 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140704233336/http://www.aastra.com/news-room-2008_1554.htm |archivedate=4 July 2014 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ericsson.com/thecompany/press/releases/2008/02/1192670 |title=to divest its enterprise PBX solutions to Aastra Technologies |publisher=Ericsson |date=2008-02-18 |accessdate=2016-11-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==.mobi and mobile Internet==
Ericsson was an official backer in the launch of the [[.mobi]] top level domain created specifically for the [[mobile internet]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://mtld.mobi/company/about/investors dotMobi Investors | dotMobi] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070820165736/http://mtld.mobi/company/about/investors |date=20 August 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Since the launch of .mobi in September 2006, Ericsson has launched SonyEricsson.mobi, the mobile portal of Sony Ericsson.

==Controversies==
On 7 December 2019, Ericsson agreed to pay more than $1.2 billion (€1.09 billion) to settle US criminal and civil investigations into foreign corruption. US authorities accused the company of conducting a campaign of corruption between 2000 and 2016 across China, Indonesia, Vietnam, Kuwait and Djibouti. Ericsson admitted to paying bribes, falsifying books and records and failing to implement reasonable internal accounting controls in an attempt to strengthen its position in the telecommunications industry.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.reuters.com/article/us-usa-ericsson/ericsson-to-pay-over-1-billion-to-resolve-us-corruption-probes-idUSKBN1YA2HU |title=Ericsson to pay over $1 billion to resolve U.S. corruption probes |publisher=Reuters |date=7 December 2019 |accessdate=9 December 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.ft.com/content/d026b9c0-1876-11ea-8d73-6303645ac406 |title=Ericsson to pay US more than $1bn over foreign bribery |publisher=Financial Times |date=7 December 2019 |accessdate=9 December 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.dw.com/en/ericsson-fined-1-billion-for-widespread-corruption/a-51566829 |title=Ericsson fined $1 billion for widespread corruption |publisher=Deutsche Welle |date=7 December 2019 |accessdate=9 December 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Companies}}
* [[Cedergren]]
* [[Damovo]]
* [[Ericsson Nikola Tesla]]
* [[Erlang (programming language)]]
* [[Investor AB]]
* [[List of networking hardware vendors]]
* [[List of Sony Ericsson products]]
* [[Red Jade]]
* [[Tandberg Television]]

{{reflist|group=Blog}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
* John Meurling &amp; Richard Jeans (1994) ''A switch in time: AXE – creating a foundation for the information age''. London: Communications Week International. {{ISBN|0-9524031-1-0}}.
* John Meurling &amp; Richard Jeans (1997). ''The ugly duckling''. Stockholm: Ericsson Mobile Communications. {{ISBN|91-630-5452-3}}.
* John Meurling &amp; Richard Jeans (2000). ''The Ericsson Chronicle: 125 years in telecommunications''. Stockholm: Informationsförlaget. {{ISBN|91-7736-464-3}}.
* ''The Mobile Phone Book: The Invention of the Mobile Telephone Industry''. {{ISBN|0-9524031-0-2}}
* Mobile media and applications – from concept to cash: successful service creation and launch. {{ISBN|0-470-01747-3}}
* Anders Pehrsson (1996). ''International Strategies in Telecommunications''. London: Routledge Research. {{ISBN|0-415-14829-4}}

==External links==
* {{official website|http://www.ericsson.com/}}
* General reference to all chapters on the Ericsson history: {{cite web |URL=http://www.ericssonhistory.com/ |title= The History of Ericsson |publisher=Center for Business History, Stockholm, and Telefonaktiebolaget LM Ericsson}}

{{OMX Stockholm 30 companies}}
{{Major networking hardware companies}}
{{Queens Park Rangers F.C. shirt sponsors}}

[[Category:1876 establishments in Sweden]]
[[Category:Companies based in Stockholm]]
[[Category:Companies established in 1876]]
[[Category:Companies formerly listed on the London Stock Exchange]]
[[Category:Companies listed on NASDAQ]]
[[Category:Companies listed on the Stockholm Stock Exchange]]
[[Category:Companies related to the Wallenberg family]]
[[Category:Electronics companies of Sweden]]
[[Category:Ericsson| ]]
[[Category:Mobile phone manufacturers]]
[[Category:Multinational companies headquartered in Sweden]]
[[Category:Networking hardware companies]]
[[Category:Swedish brands]]
[[Category:Telecommunications equipment vendors]]
[[Category:Video equipment manufacturers]]</text>
      <sha1>6grdx4ituppv7yozenehhgm377tedar</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
