  <page>
    <title>Alp Arslan</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>868</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942168123</id>
      <parentid>939672106</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-23T01:02:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Display name 99</username>
        <id>15103255</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{for|the ruler of Aleppo in 1113–14|Alp Arslān al-Akhras}}
{{short description|Sultan of the Seljuq Empire}}
{{Infobox royalty
| name        = Alp Arslan&lt;br&gt;{{lang|fa|آلپ ارسلان}}
| title       = 
| image       = File:Alp Arslan on throne Majma al-Tawarikh by Hafiz Abru.png
| image_size  =
| caption     = Miniature from the [[Mojmal al-tawarikh]]. Depicts accession to the throne by Alp Arslan
| succession  = [[List of sultans of the Seljuq Empire|Sultan]] of the [[Seljuk Empire]]
| reign       = 4 September 1063 – 15 December 1072
| predecessor = [[Tughril]]
| successor   = [[Malik-Shah I]]
| queen       = [[Aka, daughter of Yusuf Qadir-Khan|Aka Khatun]]{{-}}Safariyya Khatun
| issue       = [[Malik-Shah I|Muizz ad-Din Malik-Shah I]]{{-}}[[Tutush I|Taj ad-Dawlah Tutush I]]{{-}}[[Arslan-Argun|Izz ad-Din Arslan-Argun]]{{-}}[[Bori-Bars]]{{-}}Toghrul{{-}}Ayaz{{-}}[[Toghan-Shah ibn Alp Arslan|Toghan-Shah]]{{-}}[[Arslan-Shah ibn Alp Arslan|Arslan-Shah]]{{-}}Tekish{{-}}Aisha Khatun{{-}}Zuleikha Khatun
| royal house = [[Seljuq dynasty|House of Seljuk]]
| father      = [[Çağrı Bey]]
| mother      =
| birth_date  = 20 January 1030
| birth_place =
| death_date  = {{death date and age|1072|12|15|1030|01|20|df=y}}
| death_place =
| religion    = [[Sunni Islam]]
}}
'''Alp Arslan''' (honorific in [[Turkish language|Turkish]] meaning &quot;Heroic Lion&quot;; in {{lang-fa|آلپ ارسلان}}; full name: ''Diyā ad-Dunyā wa ad-Dīn Adud ad-Dawlah Abu Shujā’ Muhammad Ālp Ārslan ibn Dawūd'' {{lang|fa|ضياء الدنيا و الدين عضد الدولة ابو شجاع محمد آلپ ارسلان ابن داود}};{{ltr}} 20 January 1029 – 15 December 1072), real name '''Muhammad bin Dawud Chaghri''', was the second [[Sultan]] of the [[Seljuk Empire]] and great-grandson of [[Seljuk (warlord)|Seljuk]], the [[eponym]]ous founder of the dynasty. As Sultan, Alp Arslan greatly expanded Seljuk territory and consolidated power, defeating rivals to his south and northwest. His victory over the [[Byzantine Greeks|Byzantines]] at the [[Battle of Manzikert]] in 1071 ushered in the Turkish settlement of [[Anatolia]]. For his military prowess and fighting skills he obtained the name ''Alp Arslan'', which means &quot;Heroic Lion&quot;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Alp Arslan.&quot; Encyclopedia of World Biography. 2004. Encyclopedia.com. (September 5, 2011). http://www.encyclopedia.com/doc/1G2-3404700163.html&lt;/ref&gt; in Turkish.

==Family==

Alp Arslan was the son of [[Chaghri Beg|Chaghri]] and nephew of [[Tughril]], the founding sultans of the [[Seljuk Empire|Seljuk empire]].  His grandfather was [[Mikail of Kınık tribe|Mikail]], who in turn was the son of the warlord [[Seljuk (warlord)|Seljuk]].  He was the father of numerous children, including [[Malik-Shah I]] and [[Tutush I]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.iranicaonline.org/articles/alp-arslan-saljuq-sultan|title=ALP ARSLAN|last=K. A. Luther, Encyclopaedia Iranica, Volume I, Fascicle 8, pgs. 895-898|first=|date=|website=|url-status=live|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;  It is unclear who the mother or mothers of his children were. Arslan was known to be married at least twice.  His wives included the widow of his uncle Tughril, a [[Kara-Khanid Khanate|Kara-Khanid]] princess known as Aka Khatun, and the daughter or niece of [[Bagrat IV of Georgia]] (who would later marry his vizier [[Nizam al-Mulk]])&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.iranicaonline.org/articles/ahmad-b-nezam|title=AḤMAD B. NEẒĀM-AL-MOLK|last=Bosworth, C. E., Encyclopaedia Iranica, Vol. I, Fasc. 6, pp. 642–643.|first=|date=|website=|url-status=live|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;.  One of Seljuk's other son's was the Turkic chieftain [[Arslan Isra'il|Arslan Isma'il]], whose son [[Qutalmish|Kutalmish]] contested his nephew's succession to the sultanate.  Alp Arslan's younger brothers Suleiman ibn Chaghri and [[Qavurt]] were his rivals for the sultanate.  [[Suleiman ibn Qutulmish|Suleiman ibn Kutalmish]] would later become [[Sultanate of Rum#Dynasty|Seljuk sultan of Rûm]].  The son of Suleiman was his successor [[Kilij Arslan I|Kilij Arslan]], a major opponent of the Franks during the [[First Crusade]] and the [[Crusade of 1101]].&lt;ref&gt;Peacock, A.C,S., ''Great Seljuk Empire'', Edinburgh University Press, 2015, pgs. 179, 183&lt;/ref&gt;

== Early career ==
Alp Arslan accompanied his uncle Tughril on campaigns in the south against the [[Fatimid Caliphate|Fatimids]] while his father [[Çağrı Bey|Chaghri]] remained in [[Greater Khorasan|Khorasan]]. Upon Alp Arslan's return to Khorasan, he began his work in administration at his father's suggestion. While there, his father introduced him to [[Nizam al-Mulk]], one of the most eminent statesmen in early Muslim history and Alp Arslan's future vizier.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Dictionary of World Biography: The Middle Ages, Volume 2|last = Magill|first = Frank Northen|publisher = Routledge|year = 1998|isbn = 978-1-57958-041-4|location = |pages = 67}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Alp-arslan.jpg|thumb|Monument to Alp Arslan, [[Ashgabat]], [[Turkmenistan]]]]
After the death of his father, Alp Arslan succeeded him as governor of Khorasan in 1059. His uncle Tughril died in 1063 and had designated his successor as  Suleiman, Arslan's infant brother. Arslan and his uncle [[Kutalmish]] both contested this succession which was resolved at the [[Battle of Damghan (1063)|battle of Damghan]] in 1063.  Arslan defeated Kutalmish for the throne and succeeded on 27 April 1064 as sultan of the [[Seljuk Empire]], thus becoming sole monarch of [[Iran|Persia]] from the river [[Oxus]] to the [[Tigris]].

In consolidating his empire and subduing contending factions, Arslan was ably assisted by Nizam al-Mulk, and the two are credited with helping to stabilize the empire after the death of Tughril. With peace and security established in his dominions, Arslan convoked an assembly of the states and in 1066, he declared his son [[Malik Shah I]] his heir and successor.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Dictionary of World Biography: The Middle Ages, Volume 2|last = Magill|first = Frank Northen|publisher = Routledge|year = 1998|isbn = 978-1-57958-041-4|location = |pages = 68}}&lt;/ref&gt;  With the hope of capturing [[Caesarea Mazaca]], the capital of [[Cappadocia]], he placed himself at the head of the Turkish cavalry, crossed the [[Euphrates]], and entered and invaded the city. Along with Nizam al-Mulk, he then marched into [[Kingdom of Armenia (Middle Ages)|Armenia]] and [[Kingdom of Georgia|Georgia]], which he conquered in 1064.{{sfn|Bosworth|1968|p=62-65}} After a siege of 25 days, the Seljuks captured [[Ani]], the capital city of Armenia.&lt;ref name=eb9&gt;{{citation |contribution=[[s:Encyclopædia Britannica, Ninth Edition/Anni|Anni]] |title=''[[s:Encyclopædia Britannica, Ninth Edition|''Encyclopædia Britannica'', 9th ed.]], [[s:Encyclopædia Britannica, Ninth Edition/Volume II|Vol.&amp;nbsp;II]]'' |editor-last=Baynes |editor-first=Thomas Spencer |display-editors=0 |publisher=Charles Scribner's Sons |location=New York |date=1878 |ref={{harvid|EB|1878}} |p=72 }}.&lt;/ref&gt; An account of the sack and massacres in Ani is given by the historian [[Sibt ibn al-Jawzi]], who quotes an eyewitness saying:

{{quotation|Putting the Persian sword to work, they spared no one... One could see there the grief and calamity of every age of human kind. For children were ravished from the embraces of their mothers and mercilessly hurled against rocks, while the mothers drenched them with tears and blood... The city became filled from one end to the other with bodies of the slain and [the bodies of the slain] became a road. [...] The army entered the city, massacred its inhabitants, pillaged and burned it, leaving it in ruins and taking prisoner all those who remained alive...The dead bodies were so many that they blocked the streets; one could not go anywhere without stepping over them. And the number of prisoners was not less than 50,000 souls. I was determined to enter city and see the destruction with my own eyes. I tried to find a street in which I would not have to walk over the corpses; but that was impossible.&lt;ref&gt;Quoted in {{cite book|last=Norwich|first=John Julius|authorlink=John Julius Norwich|title=Byzantium: The Apogee|publisher=Viking|location=New York|year = 1991|pages= 342–343|isbn = 978-0-394-53779-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

== Byzantine struggle ==
[[File:Manzikert.jpg|250px|left|thumb|Aftermath of the Battle of Manzikert, a diorama at the Istanbul Military Museum]]

En route to fight the Fatimids in Syria in 1068, Alp Arslan invaded the [[Byzantine Empire]]. The [[Byzantine Emperors|Emperor]] [[Romanos IV]] Diogenes, assuming command in person, met the invaders in [[Cilicia]]. In three arduous campaigns, the Turks were defeated in detail and driven across the Euphrates in 1070. The first two campaigns were conducted by the emperor himself, while the third was directed by Manuel Comnenos, great-uncle of Emperor [[Manuel Comnenus|Manuel Comnenos]]. During this time, Arslan gained the allegiance of [[Rashid al-Dawla Mahmud]], the Mirdasid emir of Aleppo.

In 1071 Romanos again took the field and advanced into Armenia with possibly 30,000 men, including a contingent of [[Cuman]] Turks as well as contingents of [[Franks]] and [[Normans]], under [[Roussel de Bailleul|Ursel de Baieul]]. Alp Arslan, who had moved his troops south to fight the Fatimids, quickly reversed to meet the Byzantines. At [[Manzikert]], on the [[Murat River]], north of [[Lake Van]], the two forces waged the [[Battle of Manzikert]]. The [[Cuman]] mercenaries among the Byzantine forces immediately defected to the Turkish side. Seeing this, &quot;the Western mercenaries rode off and took no part in the battle.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The First Crusade|first= Steve|last= Runciman|publisher= Cambridge University Press|year=1992}}&lt;/ref&gt; To be exact, Romanos was betrayed by general [[Andronikos Doukas (cousin of Michael VII)|Andronikos Doukas]], son of the Caesar (Romanos's stepson), who pronounced him dead and rode off with a large part of the Byzantine forces at a critical moment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| last = Norwich| first = John Julius| title = Byzantium The Apogee| year = 1993| publisher = Penguin| isbn = 0-14-011448-3 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The Byzantines were totally routed.

[[File:Byzantium vs Seljuk c 1071 cropped.png|thumb|[[Byzantine Empire|Byzantine territory]] (purple), Byzantine campaigns (red) and Seljuk campaigns (green)]]
Emperor Romanos IV was himself taken prisoner and conducted into the presence of Alp Arslan. After a ritual humiliation, Arslan treated him with generosity. After peace terms were agreed to, Arslan dismissed the Emperor, loaded with presents and respectfully attended by a military guard. The following conversation is said to have taken place after Romanos was brought as a prisoner before the Sultan:&lt;ref name=&quot;kings&quot;&gt;{{cite book| author = R. Scott Peoples| title = Crusade of Kings| year = 2007| publisher = Wildside Press LLC| isbn = 978-0-8095-7221-2| page = 13 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:BnF Fr232 fol323 Alp Arslan Romanus.jpg|thumb|right|220px|Alp Arslan humiliating Emperor [[Romanos IV]] after the [[Battle of Manzikert]]. From a 15th-century illustrated French translation of [[Boccaccio]]'s ''[[De Casibus Virorum Illustrium]].]]

{{quote|&lt;poem&gt;''Alp Arslan'': &quot;What would you do if I was brought before you as a prisoner?&quot;
''Romanos'': &quot;Perhaps I'd kill you, or exhibit you in the streets of Constantinople.&quot;
''Alp Arslan'': &quot;My punishment is far heavier.  I forgive you, and set you free.&quot;&lt;/poem&gt;}}

Alp Arslan's victories changed the balance in near Asia completely in favour of the [[Seljuq Turks]] and [[Sunnite|Sunni]] Muslims. While the Byzantine Empire was to continue for nearly four more centuries, and the Crusades would contest the issue for some time, the victory at Manzikert signalled the beginning of Turkish ascendancy in Anatolia. Most historians, including [[Edward Gibbon]], date the defeat at Manzikert as the beginning of the end of the Eastern Roman Empire.

== State organization ==

Alp Arslan's strength lay in the military realm.  Domestic affairs were handled by his able vizier, [[Nizam al-Mulk]], the founder of the administrative organization that characterized and strengthened the sultanate during the reigns of Alp Arslan and his son, Malik Shah. Military [[fiefdom|fiefs]], governed by Seljuq princes, were established to provide support for the soldiery and to accommodate the nomadic Turks to the established Anatolian agricultural scene.  This type of military fiefdom enabled the nomadic Turks to draw on the resources of the sedentary Persians, Turks, and other established cultures within the Seljuq realm, and allowed Alp Arslan to field a huge standing army without depending on tribute from conquest to pay his soldiers.  He not only had enough food from his subjects to maintain his military, but the taxes collected from traders and merchants added to his coffers sufficiently to fund his continuous wars.

According to the poet [[Saadi Shirazi]]:{{full citation needed|date=June 2017}}
{{quote|
Arslan possessed a fort, which raised at the height of Alwand, from all were those within its walls, for its roads were a labyrinth, like the curls of a bride. From a learned traveler Arslan once inquired: &quot;Didst thou ever, in thy wanderings, see a fort as strong as this?&quot; &quot;Splendid it is,&quot; was the traveler's reply, &quot;but methinks not it confers much strength. Before thee, did not other kings possess it for a while, then pass away? After thee, will not other kings assume control, and eat the fruits of the tree of thy hope?&quot;

In the estimation of the wise, the world is a false gem that passes each moment from one hand to another. (The fort was sacked by the Mongols led by [[Hulagu]].)
}}

[[Suleyman I of Rûm|Suleiman ibn Kutalmish]] was the son of the contender for Arslan's throne; he was appointed governor of the north-western provinces and assigned to completing the invasion of Anatolia. An explanation for this choice can only be conjectured from [[Ibn al-Athir]]'s account of the battle between Alp-Arslan and [[Kutalmish]], in which he writes that Alp-Arslan wept for the latter's death and greatly mourned the loss of his kinsman.

== Death ==

After Manzikert, the dominion of Alp Arslan extended over much of western [[Asia]]. He soon prepared to march for the conquest of [[Turkestan]], the original seat of his ancestors. With a powerful army he advanced to the banks of the Oxus. Before he could pass the river with safety, however, it was necessary to subdue certain fortresses, one of which was for several days vigorously defended by the governor, [[Yussuf al-Kharezmi]], a [[Khwarezmid Empire|Khwarezmian]]. He was obliged to surrender, however, and was carried as a prisoner before the sultan, who condemned him to death. Yussuf, in desperation, drew his dagger and rushed upon the sultan. Alp Arslan, who took great pride in his reputation as an archer, motioned to his guards not to interfere. He drew his bow, but his foot slipped, the arrow glanced aside, and he received the assassin's dagger in his chest. Alp Arslan died from this wound four days later, on 25 November 1072, in his 42nd year, and he was taken to [[Merv]] to be buried next to his father, [[Chaghri Beg]].

== Legacy ==

Alp Arslan is widely regarded as having begun [[Anatolianism]], although unintentionally. His victory at Manzikert is often cited as the beginning of the end of Byzantine power in Anatolia, and the beginning of Turkish identity there.

Alp Arslan's conquest of Anatolia from the Byzantines is also seen as one of the pivotal precursors to the launch of the [[crusade]]s.

From 2002 to July 2008 under [[Renaming of Turkmen months and days of week, 2002|Turkmen calendar reform]], the month of August was named after Alp Arslan.

== References ==
{{reflist|2}}

== Sources ==
*{{cite book|last=Minorsky|first=Vladimir| authorlink = Vladimir Minorsky|title=A History of Sharvān and Darband in the 10th–11th Centuries|location=|publisher=University of Michigan|year=1958|pages =1–219|isbn=978-1-84511-645-3|url=https://books.google.dk/books?id=GPMHVEt_wVUC}}
* {{cite book | title = The Cambridge History of Iran, Volume 4:  From the Arab Invasion to the Saljuqs | year = 1975 | publisher = Cambridge University Press | location = Cambridge | editor-last = Frye | editor-first = R. N. | last = Bosworth | first = C. E. | authorlink = C. E. Bosworth | chapter =  The early Ghaznavids | pages = 162–198 | isbn = 0-521-20093-8 | chapterurl = https://books.google.dk/books?id=hvx9jq_2L3EC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PA162#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | title = The Cambridge History of Iran, Volume 5: The Saljuq and Mongol periods | year = 1968 | publisher = Cambridge University Press | location = Cambridge | editor-last = Frye | editor-first = R. N. | last = Bosworth | first = C. E. | authorlink = C. E. Bosworth | chapter = The Political and Dynastic History of the Iranian World (A.D. 1000–1217) | pages = 1–202 | isbn = 0-521-06936-X | chapterurl = https://books.google.com/books?id=16yHq5v3QZAC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PA1#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | title = The Cambridge History of Iran, Volume 4:  From the Arab Invasion to the Saljuqs | year = 1975 | publisher = Cambridge University Press | location = Cambridge | editor-last = Frye | editor-first = R. N. | last = Bosworth | first = C. E. | authorlink = C. E. Bosworth | chapter = Iran under the Buyids | pages = 250–305 | isbn = 0-521-20093-8 | chapterurl = https://books.google.dk/books?id=hvx9jq_2L3EC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PA250#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | title = The Cambridge History of Iran, Volume 4: From the Arab Invasion to the Saljuqs | year = 1975 | publisher = Cambridge University Press | location = Cambridge | editor-last = Frye | editor-first = R. N. | last = Madelung | first = W. | authorlink = Wilferd Madelung | chapter = The Minor Dynasties of Northern Iran | pages = 198–249 | isbn = 978-0-521-20093-6 | chapterurl = https://books.google.com/books?id=hvx9jq_2L3EC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PA198#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|ref=harv}}

{{s-start}}
{{s-hou|[[Seljuq Dynasty|House of Seljuq]]||20 January 1029||15 December 1072}}
{{s-reg}}
{{s-bef
| before = [[Toghrul I|Toghrul-Beg]]
}}
{{s-ttl
| title = [[List of sultans of the Seljuq Empire|Sultan of the Seljuq Empire]]
| years = 4 September 1063– 15 December 1072
}}
{{s-aft
| after = [[Malik-Shah I]]
}}
{{s-end}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=February 2011}}

{{Authority control}}

{{Seljuk dynasty}}{{Wikiquote}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Arslan, Alp}}
[[Category:1029 births]]
[[Category:1072 deaths]]
[[Category:Seljuk rulers]]
[[Category:Monarchs of Persia]]
[[Category:Byzantine–Seljuq Wars]]
[[Category:11th-century murdered monarchs]]
[[Category:11th-century Turkic people]]
[[Category:Deaths by stabbing]]</text>
      <sha1>pho0zwe358jt6fxw9ski5v6gqf4gcix</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
