  <page>
    <title>Akira Kurosawa</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>872</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942757496</id>
      <parentid>939658805</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-26T17:17:44Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>DePiep</username>
        <id>199625</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>FA candidate, so check for typos and MOS</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{redirect|Kurosawa}}
{{short description|Japanese film director and screenwriter}}
{{good article}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=May 2016}}
{{Infobox person
| name          = Akira Kurosawa
| native_name   = {{lang|ja|黒澤 明}}
| image         = Akirakurosawa-onthesetof7samurai-1953-page88.jpg
| caption       = Akira Kurosawa on the set of ''[[Seven Samurai]]'' in December 1953
| birth_date    = {{Birth date|1910|3|23}}
| birth_place   = [[Shinagawa]], [[Tokyo]], [[Empire of Japan|Japan]]
| death_date    = {{Death date and age|1998|9|6|1910|3|23}}
| death_place   = [[Setagaya]], Tokyo, Japan
| resting_place = [[An'yō-in (Kamakura)|An'yō-in]], [[Kamakura]], [[Kanagawa Prefecture|Kanagawa]], Japan
| occupation    = {{hlist|Film director|screenwriter|producer|editor}}
| years_active  = 1936–1993
| spouse        = {{marriage|[[Yōko Yaguchi]]|1945|1985|end=her death}}
| children      = Hisao (b. 1945–) and [[Kazuko Kurosawa|Kazuko]] (b. 1954–)
| module        = {{Infobox Chinese/Japanese |child = yes
| romaji            = Kurosawa Akira
| hiragana          = くろさわ あきら
| katakana          = クロサワ アキラ
| kyujitai	    = 黑澤 明
| shinjitai	    = 黒沢 明
}}
}}

'''Akira Kurosawa''' ({{lang-ja|黒澤明}} or {{lang|ja|黒沢明}} or {{lang|ja|黑澤明}} ''Kurosawa Akira''; March 23, 1910 – September 6, 1998) was a Japanese film director and screenwriter, who directed 30 films in a career spanning 57 years. He is regarded as one of the most important and influential filmmakers in the history of cinema.

Kurosawa entered the [[Japanese film]] industry in 1936, following a brief stint as a painter. After years of working on numerous films as an [[assistant director]] and scriptwriter, he made his debut as a director during World War II with the popular [[action film]] ''[[Sanshiro Sugata]]'' (a.k.a. ''Judo Saga''). After the war, the critically acclaimed ''[[Drunken Angel]]'' (1948), in which Kurosawa cast then-unknown actor [[Toshiro Mifune]] in a starring role, cemented the director's reputation as one of the most important young filmmakers in Japan. The two men would go on to collaborate on another 15 films.

''[[Rashomon]]'', which premiered in Tokyo, became the surprise winner of the [[Golden Lion]] at the 1951 [[Venice Film Festival]]. The commercial and critical success of that film opened up Western film markets for the first time to the products of the Japanese film industry, which in turn led to international recognition for other Japanese filmmakers. Kurosawa directed approximately one film per year throughout the 1950s and early 1960s, including a number of highly regarded (and often adapted) films, such as ''[[Ikiru]]'' (1952), ''[[Seven Samurai]]'' (1954) and ''[[Yojimbo (film)|Yojimbo]]'' (1961). After the 1960s he became much less prolific; even so, his later work—including his final two epics, ''[[Kagemusha]]'' (1980) and ''[[Ran (film)|Ran]]'' (1985)—continued to win awards, though more often abroad than in Japan.

In 1990, he accepted the [[Academy Awards|Academy Award]] for [[Academy Honorary Award|Lifetime Achievement]]. Posthumously, he was named &quot;[[Asian of the Century]]&quot; in the &quot;Arts, Literature, and Culture&quot; category by ''[[AsianWeek]]'' magazine and [[CNN]], cited there as being among the five people who most prominently contributed to the improvement of Asia in the 20th century. His career has been honored by many retrospectives, critical studies and biographies in both print and video, and by releases in many consumer media formats.

== Biography ==
=== Childhood to war years (1910–45) ===
==== Childhood and youth (1910–35) ====
Kurosawa was born on March 23, 1910,&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|San Juan|2018|p=xi}}&lt;/ref&gt; in [[Ōimachi Station|Ōimachi]] in the [[Ōmori]] district of Tokyo. His father Isamu (1864–1948), a member of a [[samurai]] family from [[Akita Prefecture]], worked as the director of the Army's Physical Education Institute's [[Secondary education in Japan#Middle school|lower secondary school]], while his mother Shima (1870–1952) came from a merchant's family living in [[Osaka]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=14–15&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=14–15}}&lt;/ref&gt; Akira was the eighth and youngest child of the moderately wealthy family, with two of his siblings already grown up at the time of his birth and one deceased, leaving Kurosawa to grow up with three sisters and a brother.&lt;ref name=&quot;Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=14–15&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kurosawa 1983 17&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Kurosawa|1983|p=17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition to promoting physical exercise, Isamu Kurosawa was open to [[Western world|Western traditions]] and considered theater and motion pictures to have educational merit. He encouraged his children to watch films; young Akira viewed his first movies at the age of six.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Kurosawa|1983|pp=5–7}}&lt;/ref&gt; An important formative influence was his [[Elementary schools in Japan|elementary school]] teacher Mr. Tachikawa, whose progressive educational practices ignited in his young pupil first a love of drawing and then an interest in education in general.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Kurosawa|1983|pp=12–13}}&lt;/ref&gt; During this time, the boy also studied [[calligraphy]] and [[Kendo]] swordsmanship.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|p=16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another major childhood influence was Heigo Kurosawa, Akira's older brother by four years. In the aftermath of the [[1923 Great Kantō earthquake|Great Kantō earthquake]] of 1923, which devastated Tokyo, Heigo took the 13-year-old Akira to view the devastation. When the younger brother wanted to look away from the human corpses and animal carcasses scattered everywhere, Heigo forbade him to do so, encouraging Akira instead to face his fears by confronting them directly. Some commentators have suggested that this incident would influence Kurosawa's later artistic career, as the director was seldom hesitant to confront unpleasant truths in his work.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Kurosawa|1983|pp=51–52}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Prince|p=302}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Heigo was academically gifted, but soon after failing to secure a place in Tokyo's foremost [[Secondary education in Japan#Upper secondary school|high school]], he began to detach himself from the rest of the family, preferring to concentrate on his interest in foreign literature.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kurosawa 1983 17&quot; /&gt; In the late 1920s, Heigo became a [[benshi]] (silent film narrator) for Tokyo theaters showing foreign films and quickly made a name for himself. Akira, who at this point planned to become a painter,&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Kurosawa|1983|pp=70–71}}&lt;/ref&gt; moved in with him, and the two brothers became inseparable.&lt;ref name=&quot;Galbraith IV 2002 19&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|p=19}}&lt;/ref&gt; With Heigo's guidance, Akira devoured not only films but also theater and circus performances,&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Kurosawa|1983|pp=72–74, 82}}&lt;/ref&gt; while exhibiting his paintings and working for the left-wing Proletarian Artists' League. However, he was never able to make a living with his art, and, as he began to perceive most of the proletarian movement as &quot;putting unfulfilled political ideals directly onto the canvas&quot;, he lost his enthusiasm for painting.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Kurosawa|1983|p=77}}&lt;/ref&gt;

With the increasing production of [[Sound film|talking pictures]] in the early 1930s, film narrators like Heigo began to lose work, and Akira moved back in with his parents. In July 1933, Heigo committed suicide. Kurosawa has commented on the lasting sense of loss he felt at his brother's death&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Richie|1999|p=11}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the chapter of his autobiography (''[[Something Like an Autobiography]]'') that describes it—written nearly half a century after the event—is titled, &quot;A Story I Don't Want to Tell&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;story&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Kurosawa|1983|p=84}}&lt;/ref&gt; Only four months later, Kurosawa's eldest brother also died, leaving Akira, at age 23, the only one of the Kurosawa brothers still living, together with his three surviving sisters.&lt;ref name=&quot;Galbraith IV 2002 19&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;story&quot; /&gt;

==== Director in training (1935–41) ====
[[File:Kajiro Yamamoto.jpg|thumb|[[Kajirō Yamamoto]] was Kurosawa's mentor. Kurosawa was the assistant director for over a dozen of Yamamoto's films.]]
In 1935, the new film studio Photo Chemical Laboratories, known as P.C.L. (which later became the major studio, [[Toho]]), advertised for assistant directors. Although he had demonstrated no previous interest in film as a profession, Kurosawa submitted the required essay, which asked applicants to discuss the fundamental deficiencies of Japanese films and find ways to overcome them. His half-mocking view was that if the deficiencies were fundamental, there was no way to correct them. Kurosawa's essay earned him a call to take the follow-up exams, and director [[Kajirō Yamamoto]], who was among the examiners, took a liking to Kurosawa and insisted that the studio hire him. The 25-year-old Kurosawa joined P.C.L. in February 1936.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Kurosawa|1983|pp=89–93}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|p=25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During his five years as an assistant director, Kurosawa worked under numerous directors, but by far the most important figure in his development was Yamamoto. Of his 24 films as A.D., he worked on 17 under Yamamoto, many of them comedies featuring the popular actor [[Ken'ichi Enomoto]], known as &quot;Enoken&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=652–658 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Yamamoto nurtured Kurosawa's talent, promoting him directly from third assistant director to chief assistant director after a year.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=29–30}}&lt;/ref&gt; Kurosawa's responsibilities increased, and he worked at tasks ranging from stage construction and film development to location scouting, script polishing, rehearsals, lighting, dubbing, editing, and second-unit directing.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Goodwin|1994|p=40}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the last of Kurosawa's films as an assistant director for Yamamoto, [[Horse (Uma, 1941)|''Horse'' (''Uma'', 1941)]], Kurosawa took over most of the production, as his mentor was occupied with the shooting of another film.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|p=35}}&lt;/ref&gt;

One important piece of advice Yamamoto gave Kurosawa was that a good director needed to master screenwriting.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Kurosawa|1983|p=103}}&lt;/ref&gt; Kurosawa soon realized that the potential earnings from his scripts were much higher than what he was paid as an assistant director.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Goodwin|1994|p=42}}&lt;/ref&gt; Kurosawa would later write or co-write all of his own films. He also frequently wrote screenplays for other directors such as for the film director [[Satsuo Yamamoto]]'s film, ''[[Tsubasa no gaika|A Triumph of Wings]]'' (''Tsubasa no gaika'', 1942). This outside scriptwriting would serve Kurosawa as a lucrative sideline lasting well into the 1960s, long after he became world-famous.&lt;ref name=&quot;Akira Kurosawa&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=658–707}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Wartime films and marriage (1942–45) ====
In the two years following the release of ''Horse'' in 1941, Kurosawa searched for a story he could use to launch his directing career. Towards the end of 1942, about a year after the [[Attack on Pearl Harbor|Japanese attack on Pearl Harbor]], novelist Tsuneo Tomita published his [[Musashi (novel)|Musashi Miyamoto]]-inspired judo novel, ''Sanshiro Sugata'', the advertisements for which intrigued Kurosawa. He bought the book on its publication day, devoured it in one sitting, and immediately asked Toho to secure the film rights. Kurosawa's initial instinct proved correct as, within a few days, three other major Japanese studios also offered to buy the rights. Toho prevailed, and Kurosawa began pre-production on his debut work as director.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|p=39}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Kurosawa|1983|pp=121–123}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Yukiko Todoroki.1937.2.2.jpg|left|thumb|[[Yukiko Todoroki]] played the female lead in ''Sanshiro Sugata'' who would win the heart of Sanshiro in Kurosawa's early film. Contemporaneous photograph from 1937.]]
Shooting of ''[[Sanshiro Sugata]]'' began on location in Yokohama in December 1942. Production proceeded smoothly, but getting the completed film past the censors was an entirely different matter. The censorship office considered the work to be objectionably &quot;British-American&quot; by the standards of wartime Japan, and it was only through the intervention of director [[Yasujirō Ozu]], who championed the film, that ''Sanshiro Sugata'' was finally accepted for release on March 25, 1943. (Kurosawa had just turned 33.) The movie became both a critical and commercial success. Nevertheless, the censorship office would later decide to cut out some 18 minutes of footage, much of which is now considered lost.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=43, 45–46}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Kurosawa|1983|pp=124–128, 130–131}}&lt;/ref&gt;

He next turned to the subject of wartime female factory workers in ''[[The Most Beautiful]]'', a propaganda film which he shot in a semi-documentary style in early 1944. In order to coax realistic performances from his actresses, the director had them live in a real factory during the shoot, eat the factory food and call each other by their character names. He would use similar methods with his performers throughout his career.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Kurosawa|1983|pp=132–135 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=46–51 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

During production, the actress playing the leader of the factory workers, [[Yōko Yaguchi]], was chosen by her colleagues to present their demands to the director. She and Kurosawa were constantly at loggerheads, and it was through these arguments that the two, paradoxically, became close. They married on May 21, 1945, with Yaguchi two months pregnant (she never resumed her acting career), and the couple would remain together until her death in 1985.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Kurosawa|1983|pp=137–139}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=55–57}}&lt;/ref&gt; They had two children, both surviving Kurosawa {{as of|2018|lc=y}}: a son, Hisao, born December 20, 1945, who served as producer on some of his father's last projects, and [[Kazuko Kurosawa|Kazuko]], a daughter, born April 29, 1954, who became a costume designer.&lt;ref name=&quot;Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=64, 191&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=64, 191}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Shortly before his marriage, Kurosawa was pressured by the studio against his will to direct a sequel to his debut film. The often blatantly propagandistic ''[[Sanshiro Sugata Part II]]'', which premiered in May 1945, is generally considered one of his weakest pictures.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Kurosawa|1983|pp=135–137}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=51–55}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Richie|1999|pp=24–25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Kurosawa decided to write the script for a film that would be both censor-friendly and less expensive to produce. ''[[The Men Who Tread on the Tiger's Tail]]'', based on the Kabuki play ''[[Kanjinchō]]'' and starring the comedian Enoken, with whom Kurosawa had often worked during his assistant director days, was completed in September 1945. By this time, Japan had surrendered and the [[occupation of Japan]] had begun. The new American censors interpreted the values allegedly promoted in the picture as overly &quot;feudal&quot; and banned the work. (It was not released until 1952, the year another Kurosawa film, ''Ikiru'', was also released.) Ironically, while in production, the film had already been savaged by Japanese wartime censors as too Western and &quot;democratic&quot; (they particularly disliked the comic porter played by Enoken), so the movie most probably would not have seen the light of day even if the war had continued beyond its completion.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=660–661}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Richie|2001|p=106}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Early postwar years to ''Red Beard'' (1946–65) ===
==== First postwar works (1946–50) ====
After the war, Kurosawa, influenced by the democratic ideals of the Occupation, sought to make films that would establish a new respect towards the individual and the self. The first such film, ''[[No Regrets for Our Youth]]'' (1946), inspired by both the 1933 [[Takigawa incident]] and the [[Hotsumi Ozaki]] wartime spy case, criticized Japan's prewar regime for its political oppression.{{refn|group=note|In 1946, Kurosawa co-directed, with his mentor, Kajiro Yamamoto, and Hideo Sekigawa, the feature ''[[Those Who Make Tomorrow]]'' (''Asu o tsukuru hitobito''). Apparently, he was commanded to make this film against his will by [[Toho]] studios, to which he was under contract at the time. (He claimed that his part of the film was shot in only a week.) It was the only film he ever directed for which he did not receive sole credit as director, and the only one that has never been released on home video in any form. The movie was later repudiated by Kurosawa and is often not counted with the 30 other films he made, though it is listed in some filmographies of the director.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=65–67}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Akira Kurosawa&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.biography.com/people/akira-kurosawa-9370236|title=Akira Kurosawa |publisher=A&amp;E Television Networks |date=April 21, 2016 |accessdate=June 8, 2017 }}&lt;/ref&gt;}} Atypically for the director, the heroic central character is a woman, Yukie ([[Setsuko Hara]]), who, born into upper-middle-class privilege, comes to question her values in a time of political crisis. The original script had to be extensively rewritten and, because of its controversial theme (and because the protagonist was a woman), the completed work divided critics, but it nevertheless managed to win the approval of audiences, who turned variations on the film's title into a postwar [[catchphrase]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=70–79}}; {{Harvnb|Richie|1999|p=37}}; {{Harvnb|Kurosawa|1983|p=150}}; {{Harvnb|Yoshimoto|pp=114–134}}&lt;/ref&gt;

His next film, ''[[One Wonderful Sunday]]'' premiered in July 1947 to mixed reviews. It is a relatively uncomplicated and sentimental love story dealing with an impoverished postwar couple trying to enjoy, within the devastation of postwar Tokyo, their one weekly day off. The movie bears the influence of [[Frank Capra]], [[D. W. Griffith]] and [[F. W. Murnau]], each of whom was among Kurosawa's favorite directors.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Richie|1999|pp=43–46}}; {{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=87–91}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kurosawa Top 100&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.openculture.com/2015/01/akira-kurosawas-list-of-his-100-favorite-movies.html|title=Akira Kurosawa's Top 100 Films |publisher=Open Culture |last=Crow|first=Jonathan|date=January 9, 2015 |accessdate=August 8, 2017 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Another film released in 1947 with Kurosawa's involvement was the action-adventure thriller, ''[[Snow Trail]]'', directed by [[Senkichi Taniguchi]] from Kurosawa's screenplay. It marked the debut of the intense young actor Toshiro Mifune. It was Kurosawa who, with his mentor Yamamoto, had intervened to persuade Toho to sign Mifune, during an audition in which the young man greatly impressed Kurosawa, but managed to alienate most of the other judges.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Kurosawa|1983|pp=159–161}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Shimura Takashi.JPG|thumb|[[Takashi Shimura]] played the dedicated doctor helping the ailing Mifune who portrayed the critically ill gangster in ''[[Drunken Angel]]''. Shimura was also to star in Kurosawa's films ''Seven Samurai'', ''Ikiru'', and ''Rashomon''.|alt=Publicity still of Shimura cleanly shaven.]]
''[[Drunken Angel]]'' is often considered the director's first major work.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Morris|first1=Gary|title=Three Early Kurosawas: Drunken Angel, Scandal, I Live in Fear|url=http://brightlightsfilm.com/three-early-kurosawas-drunken-angel-scandal-live-fear/|website=Bright Lights Film Journal|date=October 1, 2000|accessdate=June 8, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although the script, like all of Kurosawa's occupation-era works, had to go through forced rewrites due to American censorship, Kurosawa felt that this was the first film in which he was able to express himself freely. A grittily realistic story of a doctor who tries to save a gangster ([[yakuza]]) with [[tuberculosis]], it was also the director's first film with Toshiro Mifune, who would proceed to play either the main or a major character in all but one (''Ikiru'') of the director's next 16 films. While Mifune was not cast as the protagonist in ''Drunken Angel'', his explosive performance as the gangster so dominates the drama that he shifted the focus from the title character, the alcoholic doctor played by [[Takashi Shimura]], who had already appeared in several Kurosawa movies. However, Kurosawa did not want to smother the young actor's immense vitality, and Mifune's rebellious character electrified audiences in much the way that [[Marlon Brando]]'s defiant stance would startle American film audiences a few years later.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Warren|first1=Richard|title=Brando and Eliot in shadows|url=https://richardawarren.wordpress.com/tag/toshiro-mifune/|publisher=Richard Warren Review|date=February 2, 2015|accessdate=August 8, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; The film premiered in Tokyo in April 1948 to rave reviews and was chosen by the prestigious [[Kinema Junpo]] critics poll as the best film of its year, the first of three Kurosawa movies to be so honored.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Kurosawa|1983|pp=161–164}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Bock|1978|p=169}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=94–97}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Richie|1999|pp=47–53}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Kurosawa, with producer Sōjirō Motoki and fellow directors and friends Kajiro Yamamoto, [[Mikio Naruse]] and [[Senkichi Taniguchi]], formed a new independent production unit called Film Art Association (Eiga Geijutsu Kyōkai). For this organization's debut work, and first film for [[Kadokawa Pictures|Daiei studios]], Kurosawa turned to a contemporary play by Kazuo Kikuta and, together with Taniguchi, adapted it for the screen. ''[[The Quiet Duel]]'' starred Toshiro Mifune as an idealistic young doctor struggling with [[syphilis]], a deliberate attempt by Kurosawa to break the actor away from being [[Typecasting (acting)|typecast]] as gangsters. Released in March 1949, it was a box office success, but is generally considered one of the director's lesser achievements.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Kurosawa|1983|pp=168–169}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Richie|1999|pp=54–57}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=100–104}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Yoshimoto|pp=140–146}}&lt;/ref&gt;

His second film of 1949, also produced by Film Art Association and released by [[Shintoho]], was ''[[Stray Dog (film)|Stray Dog]]''. It is a [[Mystery film|detective movie]] (perhaps the first important Japanese film in that genre)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Broe|first1=Dennis|title=Class, Crime and International Film Noir: Globalizing America's Dark Art|date=2014|publisher=Palgrave Macmillan|location=London|isbn=978-1-137-29013-7|pages=162–167|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=BbyuAwAAQBAJ|accessdate=June 9, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; that explores the mood of Japan during its painful postwar recovery through the story of a young detective, played by Mifune, and his fixation on the recovery of his handgun, which was stolen by a penniless war veteran who proceeds to use it to rob and murder. Adapted from an unpublished novel by Kurosawa in the style of a favorite writer of his, [[Georges Simenon]], it was the director's first collaboration with screenwriter Ryuzo Kikushima, who would later help to script eight other Kurosawa films. A famous, virtually wordless sequence, lasting over eight minutes, shows the detective, disguised as an impoverished veteran, wandering the streets in search of the gun thief; it employed actual documentary footage of war-ravaged Tokyo neighborhoods shot by Kurosawa's friend, [[Ishirō Honda]], the future director of ''[[Godzilla (1954 film)|Godzilla]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Kurosawa|1983|pp=172–177}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=108–115}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Richie|1999|pp=58–64}}&lt;/ref&gt; The film is considered a precursor to the contemporary [[police procedural]] and [[buddy cop film]] genres.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=FilmInt|journal=Film International|year=2006|volume=4|issue=1–6|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=y50qAQAAIAAJ|accessdate=June 9, 2017|page=163|quote=In addition to being a masterful precursor to the buddy cop movies and police procedurals popular today, Stray Dog is also a complex genre film that examines the plight of soldiers returning home to post-war Japan.|publisher=Kulturrådet|location=Sweden}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''[[Scandal (1950 film)|Scandal]]'', released by [[Shochiku]] in April 1950, was inspired by the director's personal experiences with, and anger towards, Japanese [[yellow journalism]]. The work is an ambitious mixture of courtroom drama and social problem film about free speech and personal responsibility, but even Kurosawa regarded the finished product as dramatically unfocused and unsatisfactory, and almost all critics agree.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Kurosawa|1983|pp=177–180}};
 {{Harvnb|Richie|1999|pp=65–69}}; {{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=118–126}}; {{Harvnb|Yoshimoto|pp=180–181}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, it would be Kurosawa's second film of 1950, ''[[Rashomon (film)|Rashomon]]'', that would ultimately win him, and Japanese cinema, a whole new international audience.

==== International recognition (1950–58) ====
After finishing ''Scandal'', Kurosawa was approached by [[Kadokawa Pictures|Daiei studios]], which asked the director to make another film for them. Kurosawa picked a script by an aspiring young screenwriter, [[Shinobu Hashimoto]], who would eventually work on nine of his films. Their first joint effort was based on [[Ryūnosuke Akutagawa]]'s experimental short story &quot;[[In a Grove]]&quot;, which recounts the murder of a samurai and the rape of his wife from various different and conflicting points-of-view. Kurosawa saw potential in the script, and with Hashimoto's help, polished and expanded it and then pitched it to Daiei, who were happy to accept the project due to its low budget.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=127–138}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The shooting of ''Rashomon'' began on July 7, 1950, and, after extensive location work in the primeval forest of [[Nara, Nara|Nara]], wrapped on August 17. Just one week was spent in hurried post-production, hampered by a studio fire, and the finished film premiered at Tokyo's Imperial Theatre on August 25, expanding nationwide the following day. The movie was met by lukewarm reviews, with many critics puzzled by its unique theme and treatment, but it was nevertheless a moderate financial success for Daiei.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Kurosawa|1983|pp=180–187}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Nogami|pp=82–99}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|p=132}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Vasily Perov - Портрет Ф.М.Достоевского - Google Art Project.jpg|thumb|upright|left|Kurosawa's favorite author was Dostoyevsky, who wrote ''The Idiot'', which Kurosawa adapted into a Japanese film version in 1951. [[Vasily Perov]] portrait from 19th century.]]
Kurosawa's next film, for Shochiku, was ''[[The Idiot (1951 film)|The Idiot]]'', an adaptation of the novel by the director's favorite writer, [[Fyodor Dostoyevsky]]. The filmmaker relocated the story from Russia to [[Hokkaido]], but it is otherwise very faithful to the original, a fact seen by many critics as detrimental to the work. A studio-mandated edit shortened it from Kurosawa's original cut of 265 minutes (nearly four-and-a-half hours) to just 166 minutes, making the resulting narrative exceedingly difficult to follow. The severely edited film version is widely considered today to be one of the director's least successful works and the original full length version no longer exists. Contemporary reviews of the much shortened edited version were very negative, but the film was a moderate success at the box office, largely because of the popularity of one of its stars, [[Setsuko Hara]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=144–147}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Prince|pp=135–142}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Yoshimoto|pp=190–193}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Richie|1999|pp=81–85}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Meanwhile, unbeknownst to Kurosawa, ''Rashomon'' had been entered in the prestigious [[Venice Film Festival]], due to the efforts of [[Giuliana Stramigioli]], a Japan-based representative of an Italian film company, who had seen and admired the movie and convinced Daiei to submit it. On September 10, 1951, ''Rashomon'' was awarded the festival's highest prize, the [[Golden Lion]], shocking not only Daiei but the international film world, which at the time was largely unaware of Japan's decades-old cinematic tradition.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|p=136}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After Daiei very briefly exhibited a subtitled print of the film in Los Angeles, [[RKO Pictures|RKO]] purchased distribution rights to ''Rashomon'' in the United States. The company was taking a considerable gamble. It had put out only one prior subtitled film in the American market, and the only previous Japanese talkie commercially released in New York had been [[Mikio Naruse]]'s comedy, ''Wife! Be Like a Rose'', in 1937: a critical and box-office flop. However, ''Rashomon''{{'}}s commercial run, greatly helped by strong reviews from critics and even the columnist [[Ed Sullivan]], was very successful. (It earned $35,000 in its first three weeks at a single New York theater, an almost unheard-of sum at the time.)

This success in turn led to a vogue in America and the West for Japanese movies throughout the 1950s, replacing the enthusiasm for [[Italian neorealism|Italian neorealist]] cinema.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=137–142}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, by the end of 1952 ''Rashomon'' was released in Japan, the United States, and most of Europe. Among the Japanese filmmakers whose work, as a result, began to win festival prizes and commercial release in the West were Kenji Mizoguchi (''[[The Life of Oharu]]'', ''[[Ugetsu]]'', ''[[Sansho the Bailiff]]'') and, somewhat later, Yasujirō Ozu (''[[Tokyo Story]]'', ''[[An Autumn Afternoon]]'')—artists highly respected in Japan but, prior to this period, almost totally unknown in the West.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Bock|1978|pp=35, 71}}&lt;/ref&gt; Kurosawa's growing reputation among Western audiences in the 1950s would make Western audiences more sympathetic to the reception of later generations of Japanese filmmakers ranging from [[Kon Ichikawa]], [[Masaki Kobayashi]], [[Nagisa Oshima]] and [[Shohei Imamura]] to [[Juzo Itami]], [[Takeshi Kitano]] and [[Takashi Miike]].

His career boosted by his sudden international fame, Kurosawa, now reunited with his original film studio, Toho (which would go on to produce his next 11 films), set to work on his next project, ''[[Ikiru]]''. The movie stars Takashi Shimura as a cancer-ridden Tokyo bureaucrat, Watanabe, on a final quest for meaning before his death. For the screenplay, Kurosawa brought in Hashimoto as well as writer Hideo Oguni, who would go on to co-write 12 Kurosawa films. Despite the work's grim subject matter, the screenwriters took a satirical approach, which some have compared to the work of [[Berthold Brecht|Brecht]], to both the bureaucratic world of its hero and the U.S. cultural colonization of Japan. (American pop songs figure prominently in the film.) Because of this strategy, the filmmakers are usually credited with saving the picture from the kind of sentimentality common to dramas about characters with terminal illnesses. ''Ikiru'' opened in October 1952 to rave reviews—it won Kurosawa his second Kinema Junpo &quot;Best Film&quot; award—and enormous box office success. It remains the most acclaimed of all the artist's films set in the modern era.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=155–167}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Richie|1999|pp=86–96}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Prince|pp=99–113}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In December 1952, Kurosawa took his ''Ikiru'' screenwriters, Shinobu Hashimoto and Hideo Oguni, for a forty-five-day secluded residence at an inn to create the screenplay for his next movie, ''[[Seven Samurai]]''. The [[ensemble cast|ensemble]] work was Kurosawa's first proper [[samurai cinema|samurai film]], the genre for which he would become most famous. The simple story, about a poor farming village in [[Sengoku period]] Japan that hires a group of samurai to defend it against an impending attack by bandits, was given a full epic treatment, with a huge cast (largely consisting of veterans of previous Kurosawa productions) and meticulously detailed action, stretching out to almost three-and-a-half hours of screen time.&lt;ref name=&quot;seven&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=170–171}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Three months were spent in pre-production and a month in rehearsals. Shooting took up 148 days spread over almost a year, interrupted by production and financing troubles and Kurosawa's health problems. The film finally opened in April 1954, half a year behind its original release date and about three times over budget, making it at the time the most expensive Japanese film ever made. (However, by Hollywood standards, it was a quite modestly budgeted production, even for that time). The film received positive critical reaction and became a big hit, quickly making back the money invested in it and providing the studio with a product that they could, and did, market internationally—though with extensive edits. Over time—and with the theatrical and home video releases of the uncut version—its reputation has steadily grown. It is now regarded by some commentators as the greatest Japanese film ever made, and in 1979, a poll of Japanese film critics also voted it the best Japanese film ever made.&lt;ref name=&quot;seven&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Mellen|2002|p=6}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Richie|1999|pp=97–108}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the most recent (2012) version of the widely respected [[British Film Institute]] (BFI) ''[[Sight &amp; Sound]]'' &quot;Greatest Films of All Time&quot; poll, ''Seven Samurai'' placed 17th among all films from all countries in both the critics' and the directors' polls, receiving a place in the Top Ten lists of 48 critics and 22 directors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Votes for Seven Samurai (1954)|url=http://www.bfi.org.uk/films-tv-people/4ce2b6b5b6382/sightandsoundpoll2012|website=BFI Film Forever|publisher=British Film Institute|accessdate=April 16, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1954, nuclear tests in the Pacific were causing radioactive rainstorms in Japan and one particular [[Daigo Fukuryū Maru|incident]] in March had exposed a Japanese fishing boat to [[nuclear fallout]], with disastrous results. It is in this anxious atmosphere that Kurosawa's next film, ''[[I Live in Fear|Record of a Living Being]]'', was conceived. The story concerned an elderly factory owner (Toshiro Mifune) so terrified of the prospect of a nuclear attack that he becomes determined to move his entire extended family (both legal and extra-marital) to what he imagines is the safety of a farm in Brazil. Production went much more smoothly than the director's previous film, but a few days before shooting ended, Kurosawa's composer, collaborator and close friend [[Fumio Hayasaka]] died (of tuberculosis) at the age of 41. The film's score was finished by Hayasaka's student, [[Masaru Sato]], who would go on to score all of Kurosawa's next eight films. ''Record of a Living Being'' opened in November 1955 to mixed reviews and muted audience reaction, becoming the first Kurosawa film to lose money during its original theatrical run. Today, it is considered by many to be among the finest films dealing with the psychological effects of the global nuclear stalemate.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=214–223}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Goodwin|1994|p=125}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Prince|pp=159–170}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Kurosawa's next project, ''[[Throne of Blood]]'', an adaptation of [[William Shakespeare]]'s ''[[Macbeth]]''—set, like ''Seven Samurai'', in the Sengoku Era—represented an ambitious transposition of the English work into a Japanese context. Kurosawa instructed his leading actress, [[Isuzu Yamada]], to regard the work as if it were a cinematic version of a ''Japanese'' rather than a European literary classic. Given Kurosawa's appreciation of traditional Japanese stage acting, the acting of the players, particularly Yamada, draws heavily on the stylized techniques of the [[Noh]] theater. It was filmed in 1956 and released in January 1957 to a slightly less negative domestic response than had been the case with the director's previous film. Abroad, ''Throne of Blood'', regardless of the liberties it takes with its source material, quickly earned a place among the most celebrated Shakespeare adaptations.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=230–239}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Richie|1999|pp=115–124}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Kurosawa (WNET)|loc=bonus materials: Isuzu Yamada interview}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Prince|pp=142–149}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another adaptation of a classic European theatrical work followed almost immediately, with production of ''[[The Lower Depths (1957 film)|The Lower Depths]]'', based on [[The Lower Depths|a play]] by [[Maxim Gorky]], taking place in May and June 1957. In contrast to the Shakespearean sweep of ''Throne of Blood'', ''The Lower Depths'' was shot on only two confined sets, in order to emphasize the restricted nature of the characters' lives. Though faithful to the play, this adaptation of Russian material to a completely Japanese setting—in this case, the late [[Edo period]]—unlike his earlier ''The Idiot'', was regarded as artistically successful. The film premiered in September 1957, receiving a mixed response similar to that of ''Throne of Blood''. However, some critics rank it among the director's most underrated works.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=239–246}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Prince|pp=149–154}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Bock|1978|pp=171, 185–186}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Richie|1999|pp=125–133}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Kurosawa's three consecutive movies after ''Seven Samurai'' had not managed to capture Japanese audiences in the way that that film had. The mood of the director's work had been growing increasingly pessimistic and dark, with the possibility of redemption through personal responsibility now very much questioned, particularly in ''Throne of Blood'' and ''The Lower Depths''. He recognized this, and deliberately aimed for a more light-hearted and entertaining film for his next production, while switching to the new [[widescreen]] format that had been gaining popularity in Japan. The resulting film, ''[[The Hidden Fortress]]'', is an action-adventure comedy-drama about a medieval princess, her loyal general and two peasants who all need to travel through enemy lines in order to reach their home region. Released in December 1958, ''The Hidden Fortress'' became an enormous box office success in Japan and was warmly received by critics both in Japan and abroad. Today, the film is considered one of Kurosawa's most lightweight efforts, though it remains popular, not least because it is one of several major influences on [[George Lucas]]'s 1977 [[space opera]], ''[[Star Wars (film)|Star Wars]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=253–264}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Richie|1999|pp=134–139}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Star Wars|loc=George Lucas commentary}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Birth of a company and ''Red Beard'' (1959–65) ====
Starting with ''Rashomon'', Kurosawa's productions had become increasingly large in scope and so had the director's budgets. Toho, concerned about this development, suggested that he might help finance his own works, therefore making the studio's potential losses smaller, while in turn allowing himself more artistic freedom as co-producer. Kurosawa agreed, and the Kurosawa Production Company was established in April 1959, with Toho as the majority shareholder.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|p=264}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite risking his own money, Kurosawa chose a story that was more directly critical of the Japanese business and political elites than any previous work. ''[[The Bad Sleep Well]]'', based on a script by Kurosawa's nephew Mike Inoue, is a revenge drama about a young man who is able to infiltrate the hierarchy of a corrupt Japanese company with the intention of exposing the men responsible for his father's death. Its theme proved topical: while the film was in production, mass demonstrations were held against the new [[Treaty of Mutual Cooperation and Security Between the United States and Japan|U.S.–Japan Security treaty]], which was seen by many Japanese, particularly the young, as threatening the country's democracy by giving too much power to corporations and politicians. The film opened in September 1960 to positive critical reaction and modest box office success. The 25-minute opening sequence depicting a corporate wedding reception is widely regarded as one of Kurosawa's most skillfully executed set pieces, but the remainder of the film is often perceived as disappointing by comparison. The movie has also been criticized for employing the conventional Kurosawan hero to combat a social evil that cannot be resolved through the actions of individuals, however courageous or cunning.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Richie|1999|pp=140–146}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Yoshimoto|p=274}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=286–293}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Prince|pp=175–188}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''[[Yojimbo (film)|Yojimbo]]'' (''The Bodyguard''), Kurosawa Production's second film, centers on a masterless samurai, Sanjuro, who strolls into a 19th-century town ruled by two opposing violent factions and provokes them into destroying each other. The director used this work to play with many genre conventions, particularly the [[Western (genre)|Western]], while at the same time offering an unprecedentedly (for the Japanese screen) graphic portrayal of violence. Some commentators have seen the Sanjuro character in this film as a fantasy figure who magically reverses the historical triumph of the corrupt merchant class over the samurai class. Featuring [[Tatsuya Nakadai]] in his first major role in a Kurosawa movie, and with innovative photography by [[Kazuo Miyagawa]] (who shot ''Rashomon'') and [[Takao Saito (cinematographer)|Takao Saito]], the film premiered in April 1961 and was a critically and commercially successful venture, earning more than any previous Kurosawa film. The movie and its [[Black comedy|blackly comic]] tone were also widely imitated abroad. [[Sergio Leone]]'s ''[[A Fistful of Dollars]]'' was a virtual (unauthorized) scene-by-scene remake with Toho filing a lawsuit on Kurosawa's behalf and prevailing.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=301–313}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Yoshimoto|pp=289–292}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Richie|1999|pp=147–155}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:EvanHunter.jpg|thumb|upright|right|Kurosawa based his 1963 crime film ''High and Low'' on the American author Ed McBain's novel ''King's Ransom''. Image of Ed McBain c. 2001.]]
Following the success of ''Yojimbo'', Kurosawa found himself under pressure from Toho to create a sequel. Kurosawa turned to a script he had written before ''Yojimbo'', reworking it to include the hero of his previous film. ''[[Sanjuro]]'' was the first of three Kurosawa films to be adapted from the work of the writer [[Shūgorō Yamamoto]] (the others would be ''Red Beard'' and ''Dodeskaden''). It is lighter in tone and closer to a conventional period film than ''Yojimbo'', though its story of a power struggle within a samurai clan is portrayed with strongly comic undertones. The film opened on January 1, 1962, quickly surpassing ''Yojimbo''{{'}}s box office success and garnering positive reviews.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=324–329}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Yoshimoto|pp=293–296}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Richie|1999|pp=156–162}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Kurosawa had meanwhile instructed Toho to purchase the film rights to ''King's Ransom'', a novel about a kidnapping written by American author and screenwriter [[Evan Hunter]], under his pseudonym of Ed McBain, as one of his [[87th Precinct]] series of crime books. The director intended to create a work condemning kidnapping, which he considered one of the very worst crimes. The suspense film, titled ''[[High and Low (1963 film)|High and Low]]'', was shot during the latter half of 1962 and released in March 1963. It broke Kurosawa's box office record (the third film in a row to do so), became the highest grossing Japanese film of the year, and won glowing reviews. However, his triumph was somewhat tarnished when, ironically, the film was blamed for a wave of kidnappings which occurred in Japan about this time (he himself received kidnapping threats directed at his young daughter, Kazuko). ''High and Low'' is considered by many commentators to be among the director's strongest works.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=341–361}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Richie|1999|pp=163–170}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Prince|pp=188–189}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Mellen|2002|p=28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Kurosawa quickly moved on to his next project, ''[[Red Beard]]''. Based on a short story collection by Shūgorō Yamamoto and incorporating elements from Dostoyevsky's novel ''[[Humiliated and Insulted|The Insulted and Injured]]'', it is a period film, set in a mid-nineteenth century clinic for the poor, in which Kurosawa's humanist themes receive perhaps their fullest statement. A conceited and materialistic, foreign-trained young doctor, Yasumoto, is forced to become an intern at the clinic under the stern tutelage of Doctor Niide, known as &quot;Akahige&quot; (&quot;Red Beard&quot;), played by Mifune. Although he resists Red Beard initially, Yasumoto comes to admire his wisdom and courage, and to perceive the patients at the clinic, whom he at first despised, as worthy of compassion and dignity.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=372–374}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Yūzō Kayama]], who plays Yasumoto, was an extremely popular film and music star at the time, particularly for his &quot;Young Guy&quot; (''Wakadaishō'') series of musical comedies, so signing him to appear in the film virtually guaranteed Kurosawa strong box-office. The shoot, the filmmaker's longest ever, lasted well over a year (after five months of pre-production), and wrapped in spring 1965, leaving the director, his crew and his actors exhausted. ''Red Beard'' premiered in April 1965, becoming the year's highest-grossing Japanese production and the third (and last) Kurosawa film to top the prestigious Kinema Jumpo yearly critics poll. It remains one of Kurosawa's best-known and most-loved works in his native country. Outside Japan, critics have been much more divided. Most commentators concede its technical merits and some praise it as among Kurosawa's best, while others insist that it lacks complexity and genuine narrative power, with still others claiming that it represents a retreat from the artist's previous commitment to social and political change.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=374–389}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Richie|1999|pp=171–183}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Yoshimoto|pp=332–333}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Prince|pp=235–249}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The film marked something of an end of an era for its creator. The director himself recognized this at the time of its release, telling critic [[Donald Richie]] that a cycle of some kind had just come to an end and that his future films and production methods would be different.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Richie|1999|p=183}}&lt;/ref&gt; His prediction proved quite accurate. Beginning in the late 1950s, television began increasingly to dominate the leisure time of the formerly large and loyal Japanese cinema audience. And as film company revenues dropped, so did their appetite for risk—particularly the risk represented by Kurosawa's costly production methods.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Prince|pp=4–5}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''Red Beard'' also marked the midway point, chronologically, in the artist's career. During his previous twenty-nine years in the film industry (which includes his five years as assistant director), he had directed twenty-three films, while during the remaining twenty-eight years, for many and complex reasons, he would complete only seven more. Also, for reasons never adequately explained, ''Red Beard'' would be his final film starring Toshiro Mifune. Yu Fujiki, an actor who worked on ''The Lower Depths'', observed, regarding the closeness of the two men on the set, &quot;Mr. Kurosawa's heart was in Mr. Mifune's body.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|p=242}}&lt;/ref&gt; Donald Richie has described the rapport between them as a unique &quot;symbiosis&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Kurosawa (WNET)|loc=Donald Richie interview}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Hollywood ambitions to last films (1966–98) ===
==== Hollywood detour (1966–68) ====
When Kurosawa's exclusive contract with Toho came to an end in 1966, the 56-year-old director was seriously contemplating change. Observing the troubled state of the domestic film industry, and having already received dozens of offers from abroad, the idea of working outside Japan appealed to him as never before.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=440–441}}&lt;/ref&gt;

For his first foreign project, Kurosawa chose a story based on a [[Life (magazine)|''Life'' magazine]] article. The [[Embassy Pictures]] action thriller, to be filmed in English and called simply ''Runaway Train'', would have been his first in color. But the language barrier proved a major problem, and the English version of the screenplay was not even finished by the time filming was to begin in autumn 1966. The shoot, which required snow, was moved to autumn 1967, then canceled in 1968. Almost two decades later, another foreign director working in Hollywood, [[Andrei Konchalovsky]], finally made ''[[Runaway Train (film)|Runaway Train]]'' (1985), though from a new script loosely based on Kurosawa's.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=440–448}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The director meanwhile had become involved in a much more ambitious Hollywood project. ''[[Tora! Tora! Tora!]]'', produced by [[20th Century Fox]] and Kurosawa Production, would be a portrayal of the Japanese [[attack on Pearl Harbor]] from both the American and the Japanese points-of-view, with Kurosawa helming the Japanese half and an English-speaking filmmaker directing the American half. He spent several months working on the script with Ryuzo Kikushima and Hideo Oguni, but very soon the project began to unravel. The director of the American sequences turned out not to be [[David Lean]], as originally planned, but American [[Richard Fleischer]]. The budget was also cut, and the screen time allocated for the Japanese segment would now be no longer than 90 minutes—a major problem, considering that Kurosawa's script ran over four hours. After numerous revisions with the direct involvement of [[Darryl Zanuck]], a more or less finalized cut screenplay was agreed upon in May 1968.

Shooting began in early December, but Kurosawa would last only a little over three weeks as director. He struggled to work with an unfamiliar crew and the requirements of a Hollywood production, while his working methods puzzled his American producers, who ultimately concluded that the director must be mentally ill. Kurosawa was examined at [[Kyoto University]] Hospital by a neuropsychologist, Dr. Murakami, whose diagnosis was forwarded to [[Darryl Zanuck]] and [[Richard Zanuck]] at Fox studios indicating a diagnosis of [[neurasthenia]] stating that, &quot;He is suffering from disturbance of sleep, agitated with feelings of anxiety and in manic excitement caused by the above mentioned illness. It is necessary for him to have rest and medical treatment for more than two months.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Hiroshi Tasogawa. ''All the Emperor's Men'', Hardcover: 337 pp Publisher: Applause; 1 edition (2012). {{ISBN|1-55783-850-X}}. p. 255.&lt;/ref&gt; On Christmas Eve 1968, the Americans announced that Kurosawa had left the production due to &quot;fatigue&quot;, effectively firing him. He was ultimately replaced, for the film's Japanese sequences, with two directors, [[Kinji Fukasaku]] and [[Toshio Masuda (director)|Toshio Masuda]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=448–468}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''Tora! Tora! Tora!'', finally released to unenthusiastic reviews in September 1970, was, as Donald Richie put it, an &quot;almost unmitigated tragedy&quot; in Kurosawa's career. He had spent years of his life on a logistically nightmarish project to which he ultimately did not contribute a foot of film shot by himself. (He had his name removed from the credits, though the script used for the Japanese half was still his and his co-writers'.) He became estranged from his longtime collaborator, writer Ryuzo Kikushima, and never worked with him again. The project had inadvertently exposed corruption in his own production company (a situation reminiscent of his own movie, ''The Bad Sleep Well''). His very sanity had been called into question. Worst of all, the Japanese film industry—and perhaps the man himself—began to suspect that he would never make another film.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Kurosawa: The Last Emperor|loc=Donald Richie interview}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=458–471}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== A difficult decade (1969–77) ====
Knowing that his reputation was at stake following the much publicised ''Tora! Tora! Tora!'' debacle, Kurosawa moved quickly to a new project to prove he was still viable. To his aid came friends and famed directors [[Keisuke Kinoshita]], Masaki Kobayashi and Kon Ichikawa, who together with Kurosawa established in July 1969 a production company called the Club of the Four Knights (Yonki no kai). Although the plan was for the four directors to create a film each, it has been suggested that the real motivation for the other three directors was to make it easier for Kurosawa to successfully complete a film, and therefore find his way back into the business.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=437–474}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Yojimbo|loc=DVD featurette: ''It Is Wonderful to Create'' – Crew Interview}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The first project proposed and worked on was a period film to be called ''[[Dora-heita]]'', but when this was deemed too expensive, attention shifted to ''[[Dodesukaden]]'', an adaptation of yet another Shūgorō Yamamoto work, again about the poor and destitute. The film was shot quickly (by Kurosawa's standards) in about nine weeks, with Kurosawa determined to show he was still capable of working quickly and efficiently within a limited budget. For his first work in color, the dynamic editing and complex compositions of his earlier pictures were set aside, with the artist focusing on the creation of a bold, almost surreal palette of primary colors, in order to reveal the toxic environment in which the characters live. It was released in Japan in October 1970, but though a minor critical success, it was greeted with audience indifference. The picture lost money and caused the Club of the Four Knights to dissolve. Initial reception abroad was somewhat more favorable, but ''Dodesukaden'' has since been typically considered an interesting experiment not comparable to the director's best work.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=474–486}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Unable to secure funding for further work and allegedly suffering from health problems, Kurosawa apparently reached the breaking point: on December 22, 1971, he slit his wrists and throat multiple times. The suicide attempt proved unsuccessful and the director's health recovered fairly quickly, with Kurosawa now taking refuge in domestic life, uncertain if he would ever direct another film.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=487–489, 522}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In early 1973, the Soviet studio [[Mosfilm]] approached the filmmaker to ask if he would be interested in working with them. Kurosawa proposed an adaptation of Russian explorer [[Vladimir Arsenyev]]'s autobiographical work ''[[Dersu Uzala]]''. The book, about a [[Nani people|Goldi]] hunter who lives in harmony with nature until destroyed by encroaching civilization, was one that he had wanted to make since the 1930s. In December 1973, the 63-year-old Kurosawa set off for the Soviet Union with four of his closest aides, beginning a year-and-a-half stay in the country. Shooting began in May 1974 in Siberia, with filming in exceedingly harsh natural conditions proving very difficult and demanding. The picture wrapped in April 1975, with a thoroughly exhausted and homesick Kurosawa returning to Japan and his family in June. ''[[Dersu Uzala (1975 film)|Dersu Uzala]]'' had its world premiere in Japan on August 2, 1975, and did well at the box office. While critical reception in Japan was muted, the film was better reviewed abroad, winning the Golden Prize at the [[9th Moscow International Film Festival]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Moscow1975&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://akirakurosawa.info/2015/07/23/40-years-ago-today-dersu-uzala-wins-at-the-moscow-international-film-festival/ |title=9th Moscow International Film Festival (1975) |publisher=Akira Kurosawa info |date=July 23, 2015 |accessdate=June 12, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as an [[Academy Award for Best Foreign Language Film]]. Today, critics remain divided over the film: some see it as an example of Kurosawa's alleged artistic decline, while others count it among his finest works.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Nogami|pp=127–155}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=518–522}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although proposals for television projects were submitted to him, he had no interest in working outside the film world. Nevertheless, the hard-drinking director did agree to appear in a series of television ads for [[Suntory]] whiskey, which aired in 1976. While fearing that he might never be able to make another film, the director nevertheless continued working on various projects, writing scripts and creating detailed illustrations, intending to leave behind a visual record of his plans in case he would never be able to film his stories.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=513–514, 522–523, 544–546}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Two epics (1978–86) ====
In 1977, American director George Lucas released ''[[Star Wars (film)|Star Wars]]'', a wildly successful science fiction film influenced by Kurosawa's ''The Hidden Fortress'', among other works. Lucas, like many other [[New Hollywood]] directors, revered Kurosawa and considered him a role model, and was shocked to discover that the Japanese filmmaker was unable to secure financing for any new work. The two met in San Francisco in July 1978 to discuss the project Kurosawa considered most financially viable: ''[[Kagemusha]]'', the epic story of a thief hired as the double of a medieval Japanese lord of a great clan. Lucas, enthralled by the screenplay and Kurosawa's illustrations, leveraged his influence over 20th Century Fox to coerce the studio that had fired Kurosawa just ten years earlier to produce ''Kagemusha'', then recruited fellow fan [[Francis Ford Coppola]] as co-producer.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lucas&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|p=547}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Production began the following April, with Kurosawa in high spirits. Shooting lasted from June 1979 through March 1980 and was plagued with problems, not the least of which was the firing of the original lead actor, [[Shintaro Katsu]]—creator of the very popular [[Zatoichi]] character—due to an incident in which the actor insisted, against the director's wishes, on videotaping his own performance. (He was replaced by Tatsuya Nakadai, in his first of two consecutive leading roles in a Kurosawa movie.) The film was completed only a few weeks behind schedule and opened in Tokyo in April 1980. It quickly became a massive hit in Japan. The film was also a critical and box office success abroad, winning the coveted [[Palme d'Or]] at the [[1980 Cannes Film Festival]] in May, though some critics, then and now, have faulted the film for its alleged coldness. Kurosawa spent much of the rest of the year in Europe and America promoting ''Kagemusha'', collecting awards and accolades, and exhibiting as art the drawings he had made to serve as storyboards for the film.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=547–558}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Richie|1999|pp=204–213}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:SidneyLumet07TIFF.jpg|thumb|left|[[Sidney Lumet]] successfully effected a nomination for Kurosawa as Best Director for his film ''Ran'' at the [[58th Academy Awards]] which was ultimately won by [[Sidney Pollack]] for ''[[Out of Africa (film)|Out of Africa]]''.]]
The international success of ''Kagemusha'' allowed Kurosawa to proceed with his next project, ''[[Ran (film)|Ran]]'', another epic in a similar vein. The script, partly based on [[William Shakespeare]]'s ''[[King Lear]]'', depicted a ruthless, bloodthirsty ''[[daimyō]]'' (warlord), played by Tatsuya Nakadai, who, after foolishly banishing his one loyal son, surrenders his kingdom to his other two sons, who then betray him, thus plunging the entire kingdom into war. As Japanese studios still felt wary about producing another film that would rank among the most expensive ever made in the country, international help was again needed. This time it came from French producer [[Serge Silberman]], who had produced [[Luis Buñuel]]'s final movies. Filming did not begin until December 1983 and lasted more than a year.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=569–576}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In January 1985, production of ''Ran'' was halted as Kurosawa's 64-year-old wife Yōko fell ill. She died on February 1. Kurosawa returned to finish his film and ''Ran'' premiered at the Tokyo Film Festival on 31 May, with a wide release the next day. The film was a moderate financial success in Japan, but a larger one abroad and, as he had done with ''Kagemusha'', Kurosawa embarked on a trip to Europe and America, where he attended the film's premieres in September and October.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=576–583}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''Ran'' won several awards in Japan, but was not quite as honored there as many of the director's best films of the 1950s and 1960s had been. The film world was surprised, however, when Japan passed over the selection of ''Ran'' in favor of another film as its official entry to compete for an Oscar nomination in the [[Academy Award for Best Foreign Language Film|Best Foreign Film]] category, which was ultimately rejected for competition at the [[58th Academy Awards]]. Both the producer and Kurosawa himself attributed the failure to even submit ''Ran'' for competition to a misunderstanding: because of the Academy's arcane rules, no one was sure whether ''Ran'' qualified as a ''Japanese'' film, a ''French'' film (due to its financing), or both, so it was not submitted at all. In response to what at least appeared to be a blatant snub by his own countrymen, the director [[Sidney Lumet]] led a successful campaign to have Kurosawa receive an Oscar nomination for [[Academy Award for Best Director|Best Director]] that year ([[Sydney Pollack]] ultimately won the award for directing ''[[Out of Africa (film)|Out of Africa]]''). ''Ran''{{'}}s costume designer, [[Emi Wada]], won the movie's only Oscar.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.allmovie.com/movie/ran-v40236/awards |title=Ran (1985) – Awards |work=AllMovie|accessdate=June 9, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=582–586}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''Kagemusha'' and ''Ran'', particularly the latter, are often considered to be among Kurosawa's finest works. After ''Ran''{{'}}s release, Kurosawa would point to it as his best film, a major change of attitude for the director who, when asked which of his works was his best, had always previously answered &quot;my next one&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=580–586}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Richie1999|p=214}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{clear}}

==== Final works and last years (1987–98) ====
For his next movie, Kurosawa chose a subject very different from any that he had ever filmed before. While some of his previous pictures (for example, ''Drunken Angel'' and ''Kagemusha'') had included brief dream sequences, ''[[Dreams (1990 film)|Dreams]]'' was to be entirely based upon the director's own dreams. Significantly, for the first time in over forty years, Kurosawa, for this deeply personal project, wrote the screenplay alone. Although its estimated budget was lower than the films immediately preceding it, Japanese studios were still unwilling to back one of his productions, so Kurosawa turned to another famous American fan, [[Steven Spielberg]], who convinced [[Warner Bros.]] to buy the international rights to the completed film. This made it easier for Kurosawa's son, Hisao, as co-producer and soon-to-be head of Kurosawa Production, to negotiate a loan in Japan that would cover the film's production costs. Shooting took more than eight months to complete, and ''Dreams'' premiered at Cannes in May 1990 to a polite but muted reception, similar to the reaction the picture would generate elsewhere in the world.&lt;ref name=&quot;Spielberg&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=604–608}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1990, he accepted the [[Academy Awards|Academy Award]] for [[Academy Honorary Award|Lifetime Achievement]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://aaspeechesdb.oscars.org/ics-wpd/exec/icswppro.dll?AC=qbe_query&amp;TN=AAtrans&amp;RF=WebReportPermaLink&amp;MF=oscarsmsg.ini&amp;NP=255&amp;BU=http://aaspeechesdb.oscars.org/index.htm&amp;QY=find+acceptorlink+%3D062-25 |title=Search Results |work=Academy Award Acceptance Speech Database |publisher=Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences|accessdate=June 12, 2017 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100217234929/http://aaspeechesdb.oscars.org/ics-wpd/exec/icswppro.dll?AC=qbe_query&amp;TN=AAtrans&amp;RF=WebReportPermaLink&amp;MF=oscarsmsg.ini&amp;NP=255&amp;BU=http%3A%2F%2Faaspeechesdb.oscars.org%2Findex.htm&amp;QY=find+acceptorlink+%3D062-25 |archivedate=February 17, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Steven Spielberg Masterclass Cinémathèque Française 2 cropped.jpg|thumb|right|Steven Spielberg was instrumental in the financing and production of several of Kurosawa's final films. Spielberg at his masterclass at the [[Cinémathèque Française]] in 2012.]]
Kurosawa now turned to a more conventional story with ''[[Rhapsody in August]]''—the director's first film fully produced in Japan since ''Dodeskaden'' over twenty years before—which explored the scars of the nuclear bombing which destroyed Nagasaki at the very end of World War II. It was adapted from a [[Kiyoko Murata]] novel, but the film's references to the Nagasaki bombing came from the director rather than from the book. This was his only movie to include a role for an American movie star: Richard Gere, who plays a small role as the nephew of the elderly heroine. Shooting took place in early 1991, with the film opening on 25 May that year to a largely negative critical reaction, especially in the United States, where the director was accused of promulgating naïvely anti-American sentiments,&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=612–618}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Gere&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1990/10/01/movies/kurosawa-still-finding-unfamiliar-seas-to-sail.html |last=Weisman|first=Steven R.|title=Kurosawa Still Finding Unfamiliar Seas to Sail |accessdate=June 9, 2017 | work=The New York Times | date=October 1, 1990}}&lt;/ref&gt; though Kurosawa rejected these accusations.

Kurosawa wasted no time moving onto his next project: ''[[Madadayo]]'', or ''Not Yet''. Based on autobiographical essays by [[Hyakken Uchida]], the film follows the life of a Japanese professor of German through the Second World War and beyond. The narrative centers on yearly birthday celebrations with his former students, during which the protagonist declares his unwillingness to die just yet—a theme that was becoming increasingly relevant for the film's 81-year-old creator. Filming began in February 1992 and wrapped by the end of September. Its release on April 17, 1993, was greeted by an even more disappointed reaction than had been the case with his two preceding works.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=622–627}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Kurosawa nevertheless continued to work. He wrote the original screenplays ''The Sea is Watching'' in 1993 and ''After the Rain'' in 1995. While putting finishing touches on the latter work in 1995, Kurosawa slipped and broke the base of his spine. Following the accident, he would use a wheelchair for the rest of his life, putting an end to any hopes of him directing another film.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=636–639}}&lt;/ref&gt; His longtime wish—to die on the set while shooting a movie&lt;ref name=&quot;Gere&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Kurosawa|1983|p=viii}}&lt;/ref&gt;—was never to be fulfilled.

After his accident, Kurosawa's health began to deteriorate. While his mind remained sharp and lively, his body was giving up, and for the last half-year of his life, the director was largely confined to bed, listening to music and watching television at home. On September 6, 1998, Kurosawa died of a stroke in [[Setagaya, Tokyo]], at the age of 88.&lt;ref name=&quot;indy&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last1=Adair |first1=Gilbert |title=Obituary: Akira Kurosawa |url=https://www.independent.co.uk/arts-entertainment/obituary-akira-kurosawa-1196526.html |accessdate=21 August 2019 |work=The Independent |agency= |issue= |publisher= |date=7 September 1998}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=639–640}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the time of his death, Kurosawa had two children, his son [[Dreams (1990 film)|Hisao Kurosawa]] who married [[Hiroko Hayashi (singer)|Hiroko Hayashi]] and his daughter [[Kazuko Kurosawa]] who married Harayuki Kato, along with several grandchildren.&lt;ref name=&quot;Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=64, 191&quot; /&gt; One of his grandchildren, the actor [[After the Rain (film)|Takayuki Kato]] and [[:ja:黒澤明#芸能界に関係する家族|grandson by Kazuko]], became a supporting actor in two films posthumously developed from screenplays written by Kurosawa which remained unproduced during his own lifetime, [[Takashi Koizumi]]'s ''[[After the Rain (film)|After the Rain]]'' (1999) and [[Kei Kumai]]'s ''The Sea is Watching'' (2002).&lt;ref name=&quot;Arnold&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.seattlepi.com/ae/movies/article/Sea-is-Watching-an-absorbing-slice-of-a-bygone-1119532.php |last=Arnold|first=William |title='Sea is Watching' an absorbing slice of a bygone Japan |accessdate=July 2, 2017 | work=Seattle Post-Intelligencer | date=July 17, 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Style and main themes ==
{{See also|Filmmaking technique of Akira Kurosawa}}
From the beginning, Kurosawa displayed a bold, dynamic style, strongly influenced by Western cinema yet quite distinct from it. Kurosawa was extensively involved with every aspect of [[filmmaking|film production]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Kurosawa|2008|loc=p. 131, reprinted from John Powers interview, ''[[L.A. Weekly]]'', 4 April 1986, pp. 45–47}}&lt;/ref&gt; He was also a gifted screenwriter, and would usually work in close collaboration with his co-writers from the beginning of the development of a film to ensure a high-quality script, which he insisted was the absolute foundation of a good film. He frequently served as editor of his own films and was regarded by his production team as &quot;the greatest editor in the world&quot;. Though it was common in the Japanese film industry of that time for established directors to assemble around them a team, or &quot;-gumi&quot;&lt;!-- it would be &quot;kumi&quot; without the hyphen --&gt;, with people drawn from the same pool of creative technicians, crew members and actors working from film to film (for example, the director [[Hiroshi Inagaki]], who worked at Toho during the same period as Kurosawa, had such a team), Kurosawa's team, known as the &quot;Kurosawa-gumi&quot; (Kurosawa group)—including, for example, the cinematographer [[Asakazu Nakai]], the production assistant Teruyo Nogami and the actor [[Takashi Shimura]]—was remarkable for its loyalty to the director and the consistent quality of its work.

Kurosawa's style is marked by a number of devices and techniques which Kurosawa introduced in his films over the decades. In his films of the 1940s and 1950s, Kurosawa frequently employs the &quot;[[axial cut]]&quot;, in which the camera moves closer to, or further away from, the subject, not through the use of [[tracking shot]]s or [[Dissolve (filmmaking)|dissolves]], but through a series of matched [[jump cut]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.davidbordwell.net/blog/2009/12/08/kurosawas-early-spring/ |title=Observations on Film Art: Kurosawa's Early Spring |type=Blog |date=December 8, 2009|accessdate=June 12, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another stylistic trait which scholars have pointed out is Kurosawa's tendency to &quot;cut on motion&quot;: that is, to edit a sequence of a character or characters in motion so that an action is depicted in two or more separate shots, rather than one uninterrupted shot.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mellentalk&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Seven Samurai|loc=DVD bonus featurette: ''Seven Samurai: Origins and Influences'', Joan Mellen commentary}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A form of cinematic punctuation very strongly identified with Kurosawa is the [[Wipe (transition)|wipe]]. This is an effect created through an [[optical printer]], in which, when a scene ends, a line or bar appears to move across the screen, &quot;wiping&quot; away the image while simultaneously revealing the first image of the subsequent scene. As a transitional device, it is used as a substitute for the straight cut or the [[Dissolve (filmmaking)|dissolve]] (though Kurosawa often used both of those devices as well). In his mature work, Kurosawa employed the wipe so frequently that it became a kind of signature. For example, one blogger has counted no fewer than 12 instances of the wipe in ''Drunken Angel''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://lewissaul.blogspot.com/2008/02/85-akira-kurosawa-yoidore-tenshi.html |title=85. Film Review #8a: Criterion Collection Spine #413: Akira Kurosawa: Yoidore Tenshi (Drunken Angel) (1948) (Part Two)|last=Saul|first=Lewis |type=Blog|date=February 18, 2008 |accessdate=June 9, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Kurosawa by all accounts always gave great attention to the soundtracks of his films, especially with an emphasis on sound-image counterpoint, in which the music or sound effects would ironically comment upon the image rather than merely reinforcing it. (Teruyo Nogami's memoir gives several such examples from ''Drunken Angel'' and ''Stray Dog''.) He was also involved with several of Japan's outstanding contemporary composers, including [[Fumio Hayasaka]] (who died in 1955) and the internationally famous [[Tōru Takemitsu]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Nogami|pp=183–209}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Kurosawa employed a number of recurring major themes in his films. These include: (a) the master-disciple relationship between a usually older mentor and one or more novices, which often involves spiritual as well as technical mastery and self-mastery; (b) the heroic champion, the exceptional individual who emerges from the mass of people to produce something or right some injustice; (c) the depiction of extremes of weather as both dramatic devices and symbols of human passion; and (d) the recurrence of cycles of inexorable savage violence within history. According to Stephen Prince, the latter theme began with ''Throne of Blood'' (1957), and recurred in Kurosawa films of the 1980s. Mr. Prince calls this theme &quot;the countertradition to the committed, heroic mode of Kurosawa's cinema&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Prince|p=149}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Legacy ==
=== Legacy of general criticism ===
{{See also|Criticism of Akira Kurosawa}}
Since the early to mid-1950s, a number of critics from the [[French New Wave]] championed the films of the older Japanese master, [[Kenji Mizoguchi]], at the expense of Kurosawa's work. New Wave critic-filmmaker [[Jacques Rivette]], said: &quot;You can compare only what is comparable and that which aims high enough&amp;nbsp;... [Mizoguchi] seems to be the only Japanese director who is completely Japanese and yet is also the only one that achieves a true universality, that of an individual.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.moviemaker.com/archives/moviemaking/directing/articles-directing/beauty-beneath-the-brutality-japanese-masters-mizoguchi-and-ozu-3225/|title=Beauty Beneath the Brutality: Japanese Masters Mizoguchi and Ozu|last=Thompson|first=Rustin|date=December 1, 1998|website=MovieMaker|accessdate=June 7, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to such French commentators, Mizoguchi seemed, of the two artists, the more authentically Japanese. But at least one film scholar has questioned the validity of this dichotomy between &quot;Japanese&quot; Mizoguchi and &quot;Western&quot; Kurosawa by pointing out that &quot;Mizo&quot; had been at least as much influenced by Western cinema and Western culture in general as Kurosawa had ever been, and that this awareness of foreign trends is reflected in his work.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Bock|1978|p=35}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Japan, there have been critics and other filmmakers who have accused Kurosawa's work of elitism, because of his focus on exceptional, heroic individuals and groups of men. In her DVD commentary on ''Seven Samurai'', Joan Mellen maintains that certain shots of the samurai characters Kambei and Kyuzo, which as far as she is concerned reveal Kurosawa &quot;privileging&quot; these samurai, &quot;support the argument voiced by several Japanese critics that Kurosawa was an elitist&amp;nbsp;... Kurosawa was hardly a progressive director, they argued, since his peasants could not discover among their own ranks leaders who might rescue the village ... Kurosawa defended himself against this charge in his interview with me. 'I wanted to say that after everything the peasants were the stronger, closely clinging to the earth&amp;nbsp;... It was the samurai who were weak because they were being blown by the winds of time.{{' &quot;}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Mellentalk&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Mellen|2002|p=65}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Owing to Kurosawa's popularity with European and American audiences from the early 1950s onward, he did not escape the charge of deliberately catering to the tastes of Westerners to achieve or maintain that popularity. Joan Mellen, recording the violently negative reaction (in the 1970s) of the left-wing director [[Nagisa Oshima]] to Kurosawa and his work, states: &quot;That Kurosawa had brought Japanese film to a Western audience meant [to Oshima] that he must be [[pandering (politics)|pandering]] to Western values and politics.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Mellen|2002|p=60}}&lt;/ref&gt; Kurosawa always strongly denied pandering to Western tastes: &quot;He has never catered to a foreign audience&quot; writes Audie Bock, &quot;and has condemned those who do&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Bock|1978|p=172}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Reputation among filmmakers ===
{{See also|Remakes of films by Akira Kurosawa}}
Many celebrated directors have been influenced by Kurosawa and have expressed admiration for his work. The filmmakers cited below can be presented according to four categories: (a) those who, like Kurosawa himself, established international critical reputations in the 1950s and early 1960s; (b) the so-called &quot;[[New Hollywood]]&quot; directors, that is, American moviemakers who, for the most part, established their reputations in the early to mid-1970s; (c) other Asian directors; and (d) modern-day directors.

[[File:Popiersie Ingmar Bergman ssj 20110627.jpg|thumb|left|upright=0.8|A bust of the Swedish director [[Ingmar Bergman]], located in Poland. Kurosawa was several years Bergman's senior and admired him as a fellow craftsman, writing him a commemorative letter at his 70th birthday.]]
The Swedish director [[Ingmar Bergman]] called his own film ''[[The Virgin Spring]]'' &quot;touristic, a lousy imitation of Kurosawa&quot;, and added, &quot;At that time my admiration for the Japanese cinema was at its height. I was almost a samurai myself!&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Sano|first=Frank|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=myqJ3XwjA1UC&amp;pg=PA241|title=The Passion of Ingmar Bergman |publisher=Duke University Press|year=1986|page=241 |accessdate=June 9, 2017|isbn=978-0-8223-0586-6}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Italy, [[Federico Fellini]] in an interview declared the director &quot;the greatest living example of all that an author of the cinema should be&quot;—despite admitting to having seen only one of his films, ''Seven Samurai''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Fellini|p=49}}&lt;/ref&gt; In France, [[Roman Polanski]] in 1965 cited Kurosawa as one of his three favorite filmmakers (with Fellini and [[Orson Welles]]), singling out ''Seven Samurai'', ''Throne of Blood'' and ''The Hidden Fortress'' for praise.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Morrison|p=160}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Italian director [[Bernardo Bertolucci]] considered the Japanese master's influence to be seminal: &quot;Kurosawa's movies and ''[[La Dolce Vita]]'' of Fellini are the things that pushed me, sucked me into being a film director.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Kurosawa: The Last Emperor|loc=Bernardo Bertolucci interview}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[German New Wave]] director [[Werner Herzog]] has cited Kurosawa as one of his greatest influences: &quot;Of the filmmakers with whom I feel some kinship, Griffith&amp;nbsp;... Buñuel, Kurosawa and Eisenstein's [[Ivan the Terrible (1944 film)|''Ivan the Terrible'']], all come to mind.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Werner Herzog&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Cronin|first1=Paul|title=Werner Herzog – A Guide for the Perplexed: Conversations with Paul Cronin|date=2014|publisher=Faber &amp; Faber|isbn=978-0-571-25977-9|edition=Revised}}&lt;!--|accessdate=May 22, 2016--&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; When asked to list his favorite directors, Russian director [[Andrei Tarkovsky]] cited Kurosawa as one of his favorites and named ''[[Seven Samurai]]''&lt;ref name=&quot;Andrei Tarkovsky&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last1=Lasica|first1=Tom|title=Tarkovsky's Choice|url=http://people.ucalgary.ca/~tstronds/nostalghia.com/TheTopics/Tarkovsky-TopTen.html|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170607011649/http://people.ucalgary.ca/~tstronds/nostalghia.com/TheTopics/Tarkovsky-TopTen.html|url-status=dead|archive-date=June 7, 2017|publisher=Nostalghia.com|accessdate=June 10, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; as one of his ten favorite films.

According to his personal assistant [[Anthony Frewin]], [[Stanley Kubrick]] &quot;thought Kurosawa was one of the great film directors and followed him closely. In fact I cannot think of any other director he spoke so consistently and admiringly about. So, if Kubrick was cast away on a desert island and could only take a few films, what would they be? My money would be on ''[[The Battle of Algiers]]'', ''[[Danton (1983 film)|Danton]]'', ''[[Rashomon]]'', ''[[Seven Samurai]]'' and ''[[Throne of Blood]]''.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last1=Wrigley | first1=Nick | title=Stanley Kubrick, cinephile | date=February 8, 2018 | publisher=BFI | accessdate=August 8, 2018 | url=https://www.bfi.org.uk/news-opinion/sight-sound-magazine/polls-surveys/stanley-kubrick-cinephile}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Kurosawa's New Hollywood admirers have included [[Robert Altman]], [[Francis Ford Coppola]], [[Steven Spielberg]],&lt;ref name=&quot;news.google.com&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=8ncVAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=t-sDAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=5882%2C1850102 |title=Filmmaker remembered as 'pictorial Shakespeare' |newspaper=Eugene Register-Guard|page=13A|agency=The Associated Press |date=September 7, 1998 |via=Google News Archive|accessdate=June 30, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Martin Scorsese]], [[George Lucas]],&lt;ref name=anaheim&gt;{{cite AV media|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ErelcWcNelQ |title=Akira Kurosawa Memorial Tribute |publisher=Anaheim University|date=June 13, 2013|via=YouTube|accessdate=July 1, 2018 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[John Milius]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite interview|last=Mulus|first=John|interviewer=Plume, Ken |url=http://www.ign.com/articles/2003/05/07/an-interview-with-john-milius?page=7 |title=An Interview with John Milius|publisher=IGN|date=May 7, 2003 |accessdate=June 30, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; In his early years while still a television director, Robert Altman stated that when he first saw ''Rashomon'' he was so impressed by its cinematographer's achievement of shooting several shots with the camera aimed directly at the sun—allegedly it was the first film in which this was done successfully—that he claims he was inspired the very next day to begin incorporating shots of the sun into his television work.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Rashomon|loc=Robert Altman Introductory Interview}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was Coppola who said of Kurosawa, &quot;One thing that distinguishes [him] is that he didn't make one masterpiece or two masterpieces. He made, you know, ''eight'' masterpieces.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Kurosawa: The Last Emperor|loc=Francis Ford Coppola interview}}&lt;/ref&gt; Both Spielberg and Scorsese have praised the older man's role as teacher and role model, and Scorsese called him his ''[[sensei]]'', using the Japanese term.&lt;ref name=Scorsese&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.architecturaldigest.com/story/kurosawa-article |title=Akira Kurosowa |work=Architectural Digest|last=Scorsese|first=Martin|date=October 31, 2008 |accessdate=August 9, 2017 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Spielberg has declared, &quot;I have learned more from him than from almost any other filmmaker on the face of the earth&quot;,&lt;ref name=anaheim /&gt; while Scorsese remarked, &quot;Let me say it simply: Akira Kurosawa was my master, and&amp;nbsp;... the master of so many other filmmakers over the years.&quot;&lt;ref name=anaheim /&gt; Several of these moviemakers were also instrumental in helping Kurosawa obtain financing for his late films: Lucas and Coppola served as co-producers on ''Kagemusha'',&lt;ref name=&quot;Lucas&quot; /&gt; while the Spielberg name, lent to the 1990 production, ''Dreams'', helped bring that picture to fruition.&lt;ref name=&quot;Spielberg&quot; /&gt;

As the first Asian filmmaker to achieve international prominence, Kurosawa has naturally served as an inspiration for other Asian ''[[Auteur theory|auteurs]]''. Of ''Rashomon'', the most famous director of India, [[Satyajit Ray]], said: &quot;The effect of the film on me [upon first seeing it in Calcutta in 1952] was electric. I saw it three times on consecutive days, and wondered each time if there was another film anywhere which gave such sustained and dazzling proof of a director's command over every aspect of film making.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Ray|p=180}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other Asian admirers include the Japanese actor and director [[Takeshi Kitano]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Tirard|p=167}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hong Kong filmmaker [[John Woo]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Kurosawa: The Last Emperor|loc=John Woo interview}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite interview|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/films/callingtheshots/john_woo.shtml |title=Getting Direct With Directors... No.10: John Woo|last=John|first=Woo|interviewer=Pierce, Nev |publisher=BBC |accessdate=June 9, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.thestar.com.my/lifestyle/entertainment/movies/news/2008/07/15/epic-homecoming/ |title=Epic homecoming |last=Koay|first=Allan |work=The Star |date=July 15, 2008 |accessdate=June 9, 2017 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Japanese [[anime]] director [[Hayao Miyazaki]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Hayao Miyazaki&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last1=Shinagawa|first1=Yuto|title=Miyazaki and Kurosawa Fireside Chat (Part One)|type=Interview|url=http://www.nausicaa.net/miyazaki/interviews/miyazaki_kurosawa_p1.html|website=The Hayao Miyazaki Web|accessdate=June 9, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Mainland China|mainland Chinese]] director [[Zhang Yimou]], who called Kurosawa &quot;the quintessential Asian director&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://content.time.com/time/world/article/0,8599,2054381,00.html |title=Akira Kurosawa |work=Time|last=Yimou|first=Zhang1 |date=August 23, 1999 |accessdate=June 10, 2017 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Even today, Kurosawa continues to inspire and influence contemporary filmmakers. [[Alexander Payne]] spent the early part of his career watching Kurosawa's films, most notably ''[[Seven Samurai]]'' and ''[[Ikiru]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alexander Payne&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Levinson|first1=Julie|title=Alexander Payne: Interviews|year=2014|publisher=University Press of Mississippi|location=Mississippi|isbn=978-1-62846-109-1|edition=1st}}&lt;!--|accessdate=May 22, 2016--&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; [[Guillermo del Toro]] referred to Kurosawa &quot;one of the essential masters&quot;, citing ''[[Throne of Blood]]'', ''[[High and Low (1963 film)|High and Low]]'' and ''[[Ran (film)|Ran]]'' as among his favorite films.&lt;ref name=&quot;Guillermo Del Toro&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Guillermo Del Toro's Top 10s|url=https://www.criterion.com/current/top-10-lists/125-guillermo-del-toro-s-top-10|website=Criterion|date=December 7, 2010|accessdate=June 11, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Kathryn Bigelow]] praised Kurosawa as one of &quot;high-impact filmmakers&quot; who can create emotionally invested characters.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kathryn Bigelow&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Keough|first1=Peter|title=Kathryn Bigelow: Interviews|date=2013|publisher=University Press of Mississippi|location=Mississippi|isbn=978-1-61703-774-0|page=47}}&lt;!--|accessdate=May 22, 2016--&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; [[J.J. Abrams]] says he drew from Kurosawa while making [[Star Wars: The Force Awakens|''Star Wars: the Force Awakens'']].&lt;ref name=&quot;J.J. Abrams&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last1=Jagernauth|first1=Kevin|title=J.J. Abrams Cites Influence of Terrence Malick, John Ford, And Akira Kurosawa On 'Star Wars: The Force Awakens'|url=https://www.indiewire.com/2015/11/j-j-abrams-cites-influence-of-terrence-malick-john-ford-and-akira-kurosawa-on-star-wars-the-force-awakens-102870/|website=Indiewire|date=November 28, 2015|accessdate=June 10, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the age of 19, [[Alejandro González Iñárritu]] remembers being spellbound when he first saw ''[[Ikiru]]'' and praises Kurosawa as &quot;one of the first storytelling geniuses who began to change the narrative structure of films&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alejandro Gonzalez Inarritu&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last1=Feld|first1=Rob|title=Simple Beauty|url=http://www.dga.org/Craft/DGAQ/All-Articles/1003-Fall-2010/Screening-Room-Inarritu.aspx|work=DGA Quarterly|publisher=Directors Guild of America|date=Fall 2010|accessdate=June 10, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; When [[Spike Lee]] posted a list of 87 films every aspiring director should see, he included three Kurosawa movies: ''[[Rashomon]]'', ''[[Yojimbo (film)|Yojimbo]]'' and ''[[Ran (film)|Ran]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Spike Lee&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last1=Renninger|first1=Bryce J.|title=Spike Lee's List of Films All Aspiring Filmmakers Must See|url=https://www.indiewire.com/2013/07/spike-lees-list-of-films-all-aspiring-filmmakers-must-see-36304/|website=Indiewire|date=July 26, 2013|accessdate=June 10, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Posthumous screenplays ===
{{See also|List of creative works by Akira Kurosawa}}
Following Kurosawa's death, several posthumous works based on his unfilmed screenplays have been produced. ''[[After the Rain (film)|After the Rain]]'', directed by [[Takashi Koizumi]], was released in 1999,&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Galbraith|pp=641–645}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/after_the_rain_1999 |title=After the Rain (1999) |accessdate=July 2, 2018| work=Rotten Tomatoes}}&lt;/ref&gt; and ''[[The Sea Is Watching]]'', directed by [[Kei Kumai]], premiered in 2002.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/the_sea_is_watching/ |title=The Sea Is Watching (2002) |work=Rotten Tomatoes|accessdate=June 9, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; A script created by the Yonki no Kai (&quot;Club of the Four Knights&quot;) (Kurosawa, Keisuke Kinoshita, Masaki Kobayashi, and Kon Ichikawa), around the time that ''Dodeskaden'' was made, finally was filmed and released (in 2000) as ''[[Dora-heita]]'', by the only surviving founding member of the club, Kon Ichikawa.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.japantimes.co.jp/text/ff20000523a1.html |title=The samurai flick that got away |last1=Schilling |first1=Mark |accessdate=June 9, 2017 |archive-url=https://archive.today/20121010102056/http://www.japantimes.co.jp/text/ff20000523a1.html |archive-date=October 10, 2012 |url-status=dead |df=mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Huayi Brothers]] Media and CKF Pictures in China announced in 2017 plans to produce a film of Kurosawa's posthumous screenplay of ''[[The Masque of the Red Death|The Masque of the Black Death]]'' by [[Edgar Allan Poe]] for 2020.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://thefilmstage.com/news/unfilmed-akira-kurosawa-script-the-mask-of-the-black-death-will-be-produced-in-china/ |title=Unfilmed Akira Kurosawa script the mask of the black death will be produced in china |last1=Raup |first1=Jordan |publisher=The Film Stage|date=March 5, 2017|accessdate=June 9, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Patrick Frater writing for ''Variety'' magazine in May 2017 stated that another two unfinished films by Kurosawa were planned, with ''Silvering Spear'' to start filming in 2018.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://variety.com/2017/film/asia/china-japan-pair-to-complete-akira-kurosawas-unfinished-movies-1202432044/ |title=Chinese-Japanese Partnership to Complete Akira Kurosawa's Unfinished Movies |last1=Frater |work=Variety|first1=Patrick|date=May 18, 2018 |accessdate=June 9, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Kurosawa Production Company ===
In September 2011, it was reported that remake rights to most of Kurosawa's movies and unproduced screenplays were assigned by the Akira Kurosawa 100 Project to the L.A.-based company Splendent. Splendent's chief Sakiko Yamada, stated that he aimed to &quot;help contemporary film-makers introduce a new generation of moviegoers to these unforgettable stories&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Patterson2011&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/film/2011/sep/01/akira-kurosawa-remakes |title=Why Hollywood can't get enough Akira Kurosawa remakes|newspaper=The Guardian|last=Patterson|first=John|date=September 1, 2011|accessdate=July 2, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Kurosawa Production Co., established in 1959, continues to oversee many of the aspects of Kurosawa's legacy. The director's son, Hisao Kurosawa, is the current head of the company. Its American subsidiary, Kurosawa Enterprises, is located in Los Angeles. Rights to Kurosawa's works were then held by Kurosawa Production and the film studios under which he worked, most notably [[Toho]]. These rights were then assigned to the Akira Kurosawa 100 Project before being reassigned in 2011 to the L.A. based company Splendent.&lt;ref name=&quot;Patterson2011&quot; /&gt; Kurosawa Production works closely with the Akira Kurosawa Foundation, established in December 2003 and also run by Hisao Kurosawa. The foundation organizes an annual [[Akira Kurosawa Memorial Short Film Competition|short film competition]] and spearheads Kurosawa-related projects, including a recently shelved one to build a memorial museum for the director.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Plans for Akira Kurosawa museum officially abandoned |url=http://akirakurosawa.info/2010/06/05/plans-for-akira-kurosawa-museum-officially-abandoned/ |publisher=Akira Kurosawa info|last=Maunula|first=Vili |date=June 5, 2010 |accessdate=June 7, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Film studios and awards ===
{{Main|List of awards and honors given to Akira Kurosawa}}
In 1981, the [[Kurosawa Film Studio]] was opened in Yokohama; two additional locations have since been launched in Japan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.kurosawafilmstudio.com/info.html |title=Kurosawa Film Studio |publisher=Kurosawa Film Studio Co. Ltd. |language=ja |accessdate=June 10, 2017 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20091105004851/http://www.kurosawafilmstudio.com/info.html |archivedate=November 5, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; A large collection of archive material, including scanned screenplays, photos and news articles, has been made available through the Akira Kurosawa Digital Archive, a Japanese proprietary website maintained by [[Ryukoku University]] Digital Archives Research Center in collaboration with Kurosawa Production.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.afc.ryukoku.ac.jp/Komon/kurosawa/index.html|title=bluesky |publisher=SGI Japan Ltd. | language=ja |accessdate=July 2, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Anaheim University]]'s Akira Kurosawa School of Film was launched in spring 2009 with the backing of Kurosawa Production. It offers online programs in digital film making, with headquarters in Anaheim and a learning center in Tokyo.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.anaheim.edu/schools-and-institutes/carland-entrepreneurship-institute/418-master-degrees/1800-akira-kurosawa-school-of-film-overview-2.html |title=Online MBA, Online Green MBA and Online TESOL programs – Online MFA in Digital Filmmaking |publisher=Anaheim University |accessdate=June 9, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Two film awards have also been named in Kurosawa's honor. The Akira Kurosawa Award for Lifetime Achievement in Film Directing is awarded during the [[San Francisco International Film Festival]], while the Akira Kurosawa Award is given during the [[Tokyo International Film Festival]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://history.sffs.org/awards_tributes/search.php?search_by=1&amp;searchfield=Akira+Kurosawa+Award&amp;x=16&amp;y=10 |title=Awards &amp; Tributes|publisher=San Francisco Film Society |accessdate=June 9, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://variety.com/2008/film/features/mikhalkov-given-kurosawa-award-1117994692/ |last=Schilling|first=Mark |title=Mikhalkov given Kurosawa Award|work=Variety |accessdate=June 9, 2017 | date=October 26, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1999 he was named &quot;[[Asian of the Century]]&quot; in the &quot;Arts, Literature, and Culture&quot; category by ''[[AsianWeek]]'' magazine and [[CNN]], cited as &quot;one of the [five] people who contributed most to the betterment of Asia in the past 100 years&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://edition.cnn.com/ASIANOW/asiaweek/features/aoc/aoc.kurosawa.html|title=ASIANOW&amp;nbsp;– Asiaweek&amp;nbsp;– Asian of the Century&amp;nbsp;– Kurosawa Akira&amp;nbsp;– 12/10/99 |accessdate=June 8, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; In commemoration of the 100th anniversary of Kurosawa's birth in 2010, a project called AK100 was launched in 2008. The AK100 Project aims to &quot;expose young people who are the representatives of the next generation, and all people everywhere, to the light and spirit of Akira Kurosawa and the wonderful world he created&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://akirakurosawa.info/2008/09/21/ak100-world-tour-website/ |title=AK100 World Tour website |publisher=Akira Kurosawa info|date=September 21, 2008|last=Maunula|first=Vili |accessdate=June 9, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Anaheim University in cooperation with the Kurosawa Family established the Anaheim University Akira Kurosawa School of Film&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Anaheim University Akira Kurosawa School of Film – Online MFA in Digital Filmmaking|publisher=Anaheim University|url=http://www.anaheim.edu/schools-and-institutes/akira-kurosawa-school-of-film|accessdate=September 22, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; to offer online and blended learning programs on Akira Kurosawa and filmmaking. The animated [[Wes Anderson]] film, ''[[Isle of Dogs (film)|Isle of Dogs]],'' is partially inspired by Kurosawa's filming techniques.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = https://www.yahoo.com/entertainment/wes-anderson-isle-dogs-inspired-173402638.html | title = Wes Anderson's 'Isle of Dogs' is Inspired By Akira Kurosawa and Christmas Television Specials | first=  Zach | last=  Sharf | date = March 13, 2017 | accessdate = March 28, 2017 | work = [[Indie Wire]]|via=Yahoo! }}&lt;/ref&gt; At the 64th Sydney Film Festival, there was a retrospective of Akira Kurosawa where films of his were screened to remember the great legacy he has created from his work.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = https://ourculturemag.com/2017/04/24/sydney-film-festival-announces-kurosawa-retrospective/ | title =  Sydney Film Festival announces Kurosawa retrospective | first=  Modestas | last=  Mankus | date = April 24, 2017 | accessdate = May 8, 2017 | work = Our Culture }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Documentaries ==
A significant number of full-length and short documentaries concerning the life and films of Kurosawa were made during his lifetime and after his death. ''[[A.K. (film)|AK]]'' was filmed in 1985 and is a French documentary film directed by [[Chris Marker]]. Though it was filmed while Kurosawa was working on ''[[Ran (film)|Ran]]'', the film focuses more on Kurosawa's remote but polite personality than on the making of the film. The documentary is sometimes seen as being reflective of Marker's fascination with [[Japanese culture]], which he also drew on for one of his best-known films, ''[[Sans Soleil]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kehr&quot; /&gt; The film was screened in the [[Un Certain Regard]] section at the [[1985 Cannes Film Festival]].&lt;ref name=&quot;festival-cannes.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.festival-cannes.com/en/films/a-k |title=A.K. |accessdate=2009-06-28|work=festival-cannes.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kehr&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.chicagoreader.com/chicago/ak/Film?oid=1054410|publisher=Chicgo Reader|last=Kehr|first=Dave|title=A.K.|accessdate=June 24, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other documentaries concerning Kurosawa's life and works produced posthumously include:
* ''Kurosawa: The Last Emperor'' (Alex Cox, 1999)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite interview|last=Kurosawa|first=Kasuko|url=http://www.alexcox.com/dir_lastemperor.htm|title=Kurosawa – The Last Emperor|accessdate=June 24, 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071113154911/http://www.alexcox.com/dir_lastemperor.htm|archive-date=November 13, 2007|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''A Message from Akira Kurosawa: For Beautiful Movies'' (Hisao Kurosawa, 2000)&lt;ref name=&quot;akirakurosawa.info documentaries&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://akirakurosawa.info/documentaries-on-akira-kurosawa/|publisher=Akira Kurosawa info|title=Documentaries on Akira Kurosawa|date=November 16, 2015|last=Maunula|first=Vili|accessdate=June 30, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''Kurosawa'' (Adam Low, 2001)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine|url=https://www.timeout.com/london/film/kurosawa|magazine=Time Out|location=London|title=Kurosawa|author=WH|accessdate=June 24, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''Akira Kurosawa: It Is Wonderful to Create'' (Toho Masterworks, 2002)&lt;ref name=&quot;akirakurosawa.info documentaries&quot; /&gt;
* ''Akira Kurosawa: The Epic and the Intimate'' (2010)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oldies.com/product-view/6130FD.html|publisher=Oldies.com|title=Ran (Blu-ray)|accessdate=June 24, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''[[Kurosawa's Way]]'' (Catherine Cadou, 2011)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.criterion.com/films/28700-akira-kurosawa-s-dreams|publisher=[[Criterion Collection]]|title=Akira Kurosawa's Dreams|accessdate=June 21, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{Portal|Japan|Film}}
* [[List of creative works by Akira Kurosawa]]

== Notes ==
{{reflist|group=note}}

== References ==
{{reflist}}

=== Sources ===
{{refbegin|2}}
* {{audie-bock-directors}}
* {{cite book|last=Desser|first=David|title=Eros Plus Massacre|url=https://archive.org/details/erosplusmassacre00davi|url-access=registration|year=1988|publisher=[[Indiana University Press]] |isbn=978-0-253-20469-1|ref=CITEREFDesser}}
* {{cite video|title=Dodes'ka-den (Criterion Collection Spine #465)|publisher=Criterion|type=DVD|ref=CITEREFDodeskaden}}
* {{cite video|title=Drunken Angel|publisher=Criterion|type=DVD|ref=CITEREFDrunken Angel}}
* {{cite book|last=Fellini|first=Federico|title=Federico Fellini: Interviews |url=https://archive.org/details/federicofellini00fede|url-access=registration|editor=Bert Cardullo |year=2006|publisher=[[University Press of Mississippi]]|isbn=978-1-57806-885-2 |ref=CITEREFFellini}}
* {{cite book|last=Galbraith|first=Stuart, IV|title=The Emperor and the Wolf: The Lives and Films of Akira Kurosawa and Toshiro Mifune|year=2002|publisher=[[Faber and Faber, Inc.]]|isbn=978-0-571-19982-2|ref=CITEREFGalbraith|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/emperorwolf00galb}}
* {{cite book|last=Godard|first=Jean-Luc|editor=Tom Milne|title=Godard on Godard|year=1972|publisher=[[Da Capo Press]]|isbn=978-0-306-80259-1|ref=CITEREFGodard}}
* {{cite book| last=Goodwin|first=James|title=Akira Kurosawa and Intertextual Cinema|year=1993|publisher=[[The Johns Hopkins University Press]]|isbn=978-0-8018-4661-8|ref=CITEREFGoodwin1993}}
* {{cite book| last=Goodwin|first=James|title=Perspectives on Akira Kurosawa|year=1994|publisher=G. K. Hall &amp; Co.|isbn=978-0-8161-1993-6|ref=CITEREFGoodwin1994}}
* {{cite book|last=High|first=Peter B.|title=The Imperial Screen: Japanese Film Culture in the Fifteen Years' War, 1931–45|year=2003|publisher=[[The University of Wisconsin Press]]|isbn=978-0-299-18134-5|ref=CITEREFHigh}}
* {{cite book|last=Kurosawa|first=Akira|others=Translated by [[Audie E. Bock]]|title=Something Like an Autobiography|year=1983|publisher=Vintage Books|isbn=978-0-394-71439-4|ref=CITEREFKurosawa1983}}
* {{cite book|last=Kurosawa|first=Akira|title=Yume wa tensai de aru (A Dream Is a Genius)|year=1999|publisher=Bungei Shunjū|isbn=978-4-16-355570-6|ref=CITEREFKurosawa1999}}
* {{cite book|last=Kurosawa|first=Akira|editor=Bert Cardullo|title=Akira Kurosawa: Interviews|year=2008|publisher=University Press of Mississippi |isbn=978-1-57806-996-5 |ref=CITEREFKurosawa2008}}
* {{cite video|title=Kurosawa: The Last Emperor |publisher=Channel Four (UK)/Exterminating Angel Productions|date=1999|type=[[DVD-R]]|ref=CITEREFKurosawa: The Last Emperor}}
* {{cite video|title=Kurosawa|date=2000|publisher=[[WNET]], [[BBC]] and [[NHK]]|type=DVD|ref=CITEREFKurosawa (WNET)}}
* {{cite book|last=Martinez|first=Delores P.|title=Remaking Kurosawa: Translations and Permutations in Global Cinema|year=2009 |publisher=[[Palgrave Macmillan]]|isbn=978-0-312-29358-1 |ref=CITEREFMartinez}}
* {{cite book|last=Mellen|first=Joan|title=Voices from the Japanese Cinema|year=1975|publisher=Liveright Publishing Corporation|isbn=978-0-87140-604-0|ref=CITEREFMellen1975}}
* {{cite book|last=Mellen|first=Joan|title=The Waves at Genji's Door|year=1976|publisher=Pantheon Books|isbn=978-0-394-49799-0|ref=CITEREFMellen1976|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/wavesatgenjisdoo0000mell}}
* {{cite book|last=Mellen|first=Joan|title=Seven Samurai (BFI Classics)|year=2002|publisher=British Film Institute|isbn=978-0-85170-915-4|ref=CITEREFMellen2002}}
* {{cite book|last=Morrison|first=James|title=Roman Polanski (Contemporary Film Directors)|year=2007|publisher=University of Illinois Press|isbn=978-0-252-07446-2|ref=CITEREFMorrison}}
* {{cite book|last=Nogami|first=Teruyo|title=Waiting on the Weather|year=2006|publisher=[[Stone Bridge Press]]|isbn=978-1-933330-09-9|ref=CITEREFNogami}}
* {{cite book|last=Peckinpah|first=Sam|title=Sam Peckinpah: Interviews |editor=Kevin J. Hayes |year=2008|publisher=[[University Press of Mississippi]] |isbn=978-1-934110-64-5 |ref=CITEREFPeckinpah}}
* {{cite book|last=Prince|first=Stephen|title=The Warrior's Camera: The Cinema of Akira Kurosawa|edition=2nd, revised |year=1999|publisher=[[Princeton University Press]]|isbn= 978-0-691-01046-5 |ref=CITEREFPrince}}
* {{cite video|title=Rashomon|date=2002|publisher=Criterion|type=DVD|ref=CITEREFRashomon}}
* {{cite book|last=Ray|first=Satyajit|title=Our Films Their Films|year=2007|publisher=[[Orient Blackswan]]|isbn=978-81-250-1565-9|ref=CITEREFRay}}
* {{cite book|last=Richie|first=Donald|authorlink=Donald Richie|title=The Films of Akira Kurosawa |edition=Third, Expanded and Updated|year=1999|publisher=[[University of California Press]]|isbn=978-0-520-22037-9|ref=CITEREFRichie1999}}
* {{cite book|last=Richie|first=Donald|title=A Hundred Years of Japanese Film|year=2001|publisher=[[Kodansha International]] |isbn=978-4-7700-2682-8|ref=CITEREFRichie2001}}
* {{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=SVVyDwAAQBAJ|title=Akira Kurosawa: A Viewer's Guide|last=San Juan|first=Eric|date=2018|publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield|isbn=9781538110904|pages=|language=en|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Sato|first=Tadao|title=Currents in Japanese Cinema|year=1987|publisher=Kodansha International Ltd.|isbn=978-0-87011-815-9|ref=CITEREFSato}}
* {{cite video|title=Star Wars Episode IV: A New Hope |date=2006|publisher=[[20th Century Fox Home Entertainment]] |type=DVD|ref=CITEREFStar Wars}}
* {{cite video|title=Seven Samurai: 3-disc Remastered Edition (Criterion Collection Spine #2)|publisher=Criterion|type=DVD|ref=CITEREFSeven Samurai}}
* {{cite book|last=Tirard|first=Laurent|title=Moviemakers' Master Class: Private Lessons from the World's Foremost Directors|year=2002|publisher=Faber and Faber Ltd.|isbn=978-0-571-21102-9|ref=CITEREFTirard}}
* {{cite video|title=Yojimbo: Remastered Edition (Criterion Collection Spine #52)|publisher=[[The Criterion Collection|Criterion]]|type=DVD|ref=CITEREFYojimbo}}
* {{cite book|last=Yoshimoto|first=Mitsuhiro|title=Kurosawa: Film Studies and Japanese Cinema|year=2000|publisher=[[Duke University Press]]|isbn=978-0-8223-2519-2|ref=CITEREFYoshimoto}}
{{refend}}

== Further reading ==
* Buchanan, Judith (2005). ''Shakespeare on Film''. Pearson Longman. {{ISBN|0-582-43716-4}}.
* Burch, Nöel (1979). ''[https://quod.lib.umich.edu/c/cjfs/aaq5060.0001.001 To the Distant Observer: Form and Meaning in the Japanese Cinema]''. University of California Press. {{ISBN|0-520-03605-0}}.
* Cowie, Peter (2010). ''Akira Kurosawa: Master of Cinema''. Rizzoli Publications. {{ISBN|0-8478-3319-4}}.
* Davies, Anthony (1990). ''Filming Shakespeare's Plays: The Adaptions of Laurence Olivier, Orson Welles, Peter Brook and Akira Kurosawa''. Cambridge University Press. {{ISBN|0-521-39913-0}}.
* Desser, David (1983). ''The Samurai Films of Akira Kurosawa (Studies in Cinema No. 23)''. UMI Research Press. {{ISBN|0-8357-1924-3}}.
* {{cite book|last=Kurosawa|first=Akira|year=1999|title=Kurosawa Akira zengashū|language=Japanese|publisher= Shogakukan|isbn=978-4-09-699611-9|trans-title=The complete artworks of Akira Kurosawa}}
* Leonard, Kendra Preston (2009). ''Shakespeare, Madness, and Music: Scoring Insanity in Cinematic Adaptations''. Plymouth: The Scarecrow Press. {{ISBN|0-8108-6946-2}}.
* Sorensen, Lars-Martin (2009). ''Censorship of Japanese Films During the U.S. Occupation of Japan: The Cases of Yasujiro Ozu and Akira Kurosawa''. Edwin Mellen Press. {{ISBN|0-7734-4673-7}}.
* Wild, Peter. (2014) ''Akira Kurosawa'' Reaktion Books {{ISBN|978-1-78023-343-7}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Akira Kurosawa}}
{{Wikiquote}}
* {{IMDb name|41}}
* {{Tcmdb name}}
* [https://www.criterion.com/shop/collection/3-akira-kurosawa Akira Kurosawa] at the [[Criterion Collection]]
* [http://akirakurosawa.info/ Akira Kurosawa: News, Information and Discussion]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20100704194325/http://archive.sensesofcinema.com/contents/directors/02/kurosawa.html Senses of Cinema: Great Directors Critical Database]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20081024014317/http://www.horror-house.jp/cat2/19101998.html Akira Kurosawa at Japanese celebrity's grave guide] {{in lang|ja}}
* {{jmdb name|0121190}}
* [https://sites.google.com/site/illustratedjapanesevocabulary/film/kurosawa Several trailers]
* [http://www.anaheim.edu/schools-and-institutes/akira-kurosawa-school-of-film Anaheim University Akira Kurosawa School of Film]
* {{Rotten Tomatoes person|akira_kurosawa}}

{{Akira Kurosawa}}
{{Yojimbo}}
{{Navboxes
|title = [[List of awards and honors given to Akira Kurosawa|Awards for Akira Kurosawa]]
|list =
{{Asian of the Century}}
{{Academy Award Best Foreign Language Film}}
{{Academy Honorary Award}}
{{BAFTA Award for Best Direction 1968–1984}}
{{British Film Institute Fellowship}}
{{DirectorsGuildofAmericaAwardLifetimeFilm}}
{{London Film Critics Circle Award for Director of the Year}}
{{National Board of Review Award for Best Director}}
{{Ramon Magsaysay Award Winners}}
{{Silver Bear for Best Director}}
}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Kurosawa, Akira}}
[[Category:1910 births]]
[[Category:1998 deaths]]
[[Category:20th-century Japanese writers]]
[[Category:20th-century male writers]]
[[Category:Academy Honorary Award recipients]]
[[Category:Akira Kurosawa| ]]
[[Category:Akira Kurosawa Award winners]]
[[Category:Best Director BAFTA Award winners]]
[[Category:César Award winners]]
[[Category:David di Donatello winners]]
[[Category:Deaths from cerebrovascular disease]]
[[Category:Directors Guild of America Award winners]]
[[Category:Directors of Best Foreign Language Film Academy Award winners]]
[[Category:Directors of Palme d'Or winners]]
[[Category:Disease-related deaths in Japan]]
[[Category:Fellows of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences]]
[[Category:Fukuoka Asian Culture Prize winners]]
[[Category:Japanese film directors]]
[[Category:Japanese film editors]]
[[Category:Japanese film producers]]
[[Category:Japanese male writers]]
[[Category:Japanese screenwriters]]
[[Category:Kyoto laureates in Arts and Philosophy]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Legion of Honour]]
[[Category:Male screenwriters]]
[[Category:People from Shinagawa]]
[[Category:People of the Empire of Japan]]
[[Category:People's Honour Award winners]]
[[Category:Propaganda film directors]]
[[Category:Ramon Magsaysay Award winners]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of Culture]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of Friendship of Peoples]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Praemium Imperiale]]
[[Category:Samurai film directors]]
[[Category:Silver Bear for Best Director recipients]]
[[Category:Writers from Tokyo]]
[[Category:Yakuza film directors]]</text>
      <sha1>iodnb9oidat8onqgiqv1p0g4frubs9u</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
