  <page>
    <title>A. E. van Vogt</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>888</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941711096</id>
      <parentid>941711062</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-20T05:15:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mennowiki</username>
        <id>30012582</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Early life */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use mdy dates|date=July 2014}}
{{Infobox writer
| name        = A. E. van Vogt
| image       = VanVogt1963.jpg
| imagesize   = 200px
| caption     = Van Vogt about 1963
| pseudonym   =
| birth_name  = Alfred Vogt
| birth_date  = {{birth date|1912|4|26|mf=y}}
| birth_place = Edenburg, near [[Gretna, Manitoba]], Canada
| death_date  = {{death date and age|2000|1|26|1912|4|26|mf=y}}
| death_place = Los Angeles, California, US
| occupation  = Writer
| nationality = Canadian
| period      = 1939–1986 (science fiction)
| genre       = Science fiction
| subject     = &lt;!--nonfiction--&gt;
| movement    = [[Golden Age of Science Fiction]]
| spouse      = {{plainlist|
* [[Edna Mayne Hull]] (1939–1975)
* Lydia Bereginsky (1979–2000) (his death)
}}
| signature   = A.E. van Vogt (signature).svg
| website     =
}}
'''Alfred Elton van Vogt'''  ({{IPAc-en|v|æ|n|_|v|oʊ|t}}; April 26, 1912&amp;nbsp;– January 26, 2000) was a Canadian-born [[science fiction author]]. His fragmented, bizarre narrative style influenced later science fiction writers, notably [[Philip K. Dick]]. He is one of the most popular and influential practitioners of science fiction in the mid-twentieth century, the genre's so-called [[Golden Age of Science Fiction|Golden Age]], and one of the most complex.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Although [van Vogt] catered for the pulps, he intensified the emotional impact and complexity of the stories they would bear&quot;. {{cite book | editor= Clute, John | editor-link= John Clute | editor2= Nicholls, Peter | editor2-link= Peter Nicholls (writer) |title= The Encyclopedia of Science Fiction |date= 1995 |publisher= [[St. Martin's Press]] |location= New York |page= 1268 |isbn= 978-0-312-13486-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early life==
Alfred Vogt (both &quot;Elton&quot; and &quot;van&quot; were added much later) was born on April 26, 1912 on his grandparents' farm in Edenburg, Manitoba, a tiny (and now defunct) [[Russian Mennonite]] community east of [[Gretna, Manitoba]], Canada in the Mennonite [[West Reserve]].  He was the third of six children born to Heinrich &quot;Henry&quot; Vogt and Aganetha &quot;Agnes&quot; Vogt (née Buhr), both of whom were themselves born in Manitoba, but who grew up in heavily immigrant communities.  Until age four, van Vogt and his family spoke only [[Plautdietsch]], a dialect of [[Dutch language|Dutch]] at home.&lt;ref name=panshin&gt;Panshin, Alexei [http://www.panshin.com/articles/vanvogt/vanvogt1.html &quot;Man Beyond Man. The Early Stories of A. E. van Vogt&quot; (page 1)]. Retrieved August 29, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

For the first dozen or so years of his life, van Vogt's father, Henry Vogt, a lawyer, moved his family several times within western Canada, alighting successively in [[Neville, Saskatchewan]]; [[Morden, Manitoba]]; and finally [[Winnipeg]], Manitoba.  Alfred Vogt found these moves difficult, later remarking:

{{quote|Childhood was a terrible period for me. I was like a ship without anchor being swept along through darkness in a storm. Again and again I sought shelter, only to be forced out of it by something new.&lt;ref name=panshin/&gt;}}

By the 1920s, living in Winnipeg, father Henry worked as an agent for a steamship company, but the stock market crash of 1929 proved financially disastrous, and the family could not afford to send Alfred to college.  During his teen years, Alfred worked as a farmhand and a truck driver, and by the age of 19, he was working in [[Ottawa]] for the Canadian census bureau.  He began his writing career with stories in the [[True Confessions (magazine)|true confession]] style of [[pulp magazines]] such as ''[[True Story (magazine)|True Story]]''.  Most of these stories were published anonymously, with the first-person narratives allegedly being written by people (often women) in extraordinary, emotional, and life-changing circumstances.

After a year in Ottawa, he moved back to Winnipeg, where he sold newspaper advertising space and continued to write.  While continuing to pen melodramatic &quot;true confessions&quot; stories through 1937, he also began writing short radio dramas for local radio station CKY, as well as conducting interviews published in trade magazines.  He added the middle name &quot;Elton&quot; at some point in the mid-1930s, and at least one confessional story (1937's &quot;To Be His Keeper&quot;) was sold to the ''[[Toronto Star]]'', who misspelled his name &quot;Alfred Alton Bogt&quot; in the byline.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.icshi.net/sevagram/stories/keeper.php#top|title=To Be His Keeper by A. E. van Vogt – Sevagram|website=www.icshi.net}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Shortly thereafter, he added the &quot;van&quot; to his surname, and from that point forward he used the name &quot;A. E. van Vogt&quot; both personally and professionally.

==Career==
By 1938, van Vogt decided to switch to writing science fiction, a genre he enjoyed reading.&lt;ref&gt;Elliot, Jeffery: &quot;An Interview with A. E. Van Vogt&quot;, ''Science Fiction Review'' #23, 1977. Available online http://www.angelfire.com/art/megathink/vanvogt/vanvogt_interview.html Retrieved on August 29, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;  He was inspired by the August 1938 issue of ''[[Astounding Science Fiction]],'' which he picked up at a newsstand. [[John W. Campbell]]'s novelette &quot;[[Who Goes There?]]&quot; (later adapted into ''[[The Thing from Another World]]'' and ''[[The Thing (1982)|The Thing]]'') inspired van Vogt to write &quot;[[Vault of the Beast]]&quot;, which he submitted to that same magazine. Campbell, who edited ''Astounding'' (and had written the story under a pseudonym), sent van Vogt a rejection letter, but one which encouraged van Vogt to try again. Van Vogt sent another story, entitled &quot;[[Black Destroyer]]&quot;, which was accepted. A revised version of &quot;Vault of the Beast&quot; would be published in 1940.
[[File:Fantasy book 1947 v1 n2.jpg|thumb|right|Van Vogt's &quot;Ship of Darkness&quot; was the cover story in the second issue of ''Fantasy Book'' in 1948.]]

Van Vogt's first SF publication was inspired by ''[[The Voyage of the Beagle]]'' by [[Charles Darwin]].&lt;ref&gt;Drake, H. L., ''A. E. van Vogt: Science Fantasy's Icon'', Booklocker.com Inc., 2001, page 36.&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;The Black Destroyer&quot; was published in July 1939 by [[John W. Campbell]] in ''[[Astounding Science Fiction]]'', the centennial year of Darwin's journal. It featured a fierce, carnivorous [[Extraterrestrial life|alien]], the [[coeurl]], stalking the crew of an exploration spaceship, and served as the inspiration for multiple science fiction movies, including ''[[Alien (movie)|Alien]]'' (1979).{{efn|name=movies}}

Also in 1939, still living in Winnipeg, van Vogt married [[Edna Mayne Hull]], a fellow Manitoban.  Hull, who had previously worked as a private secretary, would act as van Vogt's typist, and be credited with writing several SF stories of her own throughout the early 1940s.

The outbreak of [[World War II]] in September 1939 caused a change in van Vogt's circumstances.  Ineligible for military service due to his poor eyesight, he accepted a clerking job with the Canadian Department of National Defence.  This necessitated a move back to [[Ottawa]], where he and his wife would stay for the next year and a half.

Meanwhile, his writing career continued.  &quot;Discord in Scarlet&quot; was van Vogt's second story to be published, also appearing as the cover story.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.icshi.net/worlds/voyageof.htm &quot;The Voyage of the Space Beagle&quot;] (cover images for numerous editions and adaptations of &quot;The Black Destroyer&quot; and its series). ''The Weird Worlds of A. E. van Vogt''. Magnus Axelsson (pre-2000 to 2009). Now hosted by ''icshi.net''. Retrieved April 4, 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; It was accompanied by interior illustrations created by [[Frank Kramer (artist)|Frank Kramer]]{{efn |name=kramer |According to ISFDB, writer van Vogt&lt;ref name=isfdb/&gt; and illustrator Kramer both made their debuts, at least in speculative fiction, with &quot;The Black Destroyer&quot;.&lt;br&gt; [http://www.isfdb.org/cgi-bin/ea.cgi?116623 &quot;Frank Kramer – Summary Bibliography&quot;]. ISFDB. Retrieved 2013-04-04.}} and Paul Orban.&lt;ref name=isfdb/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&lt;!-- not [ref name=panshin] --&gt; Panshin, Alexei (1994). [http://www.icshi.net/worlds/intoslan.htm &quot;Introduction to Slan&quot;]. Connecticut: The Easton Press.&lt;!-- Easton is copyright holder. What is the publication? --&gt;&lt;br&gt; Quote: &quot;His first published SF story was &quot;Black Destroyer&quot; in the July 1939 ''Astounding''. Not only was &quot;Black Destroyer&quot; pictured on the cover of the magazine, but it would be recognized as one of the most significant stories published in ''Astounding'' that year&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; (Van Vogt and Kramer{{efn|name=kramer}} thus debuted in the issue of ''Astounding'' that is sometimes identified as the start of the [[Golden Age of Science Fiction]].&lt;ref name=&quot;earlyyears79_82&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://archive.org/stream/earlyasimovorele00asim#page/78/mode/2up |title=The early Asimov; or, Eleven years of trying |last=Asimov |first=Isaac |date=1972 |publisher=Doubleday |location=Garden City NY |pages=79–82}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;For example, Peter Nicholls ({{cite book | editor= Clute, John | editor-link= John Clute | editor2= Nicholls, Peter | editor2-link= Peter Nicholls (writer)| title= The Encyclopedia of Science Fiction| date= 1993| publisher= [[St. Martin's Press|St. Martin's Press, Inc.]]| location= New York| page= 199|isbn= 978-0-312-09618-2 |url={{google books |plainurl=y |id=duySQgAACAAJ|page=199}}}}) says &quot;The beginning of Campbell's particular Golden Age of SF can be pinpointed as the summer of 1939&quot; and goes on to begin the discussion with the July 1939 issue. Lester del Rey ({{cite book | first=Lester | last=del Rey | authorlink=Lester del Rey | title=The World of Science Fiction and Fantasy: The History of a Subculture | publisher=Ballantine Books | location=New York | date=1979 | page=[https://archive.org/details/worldofsciencefi00delr/page/94 94] | isbn=978-0-345-25452-8 | url=https://archive.org/details/worldofsciencefi00delr/page/94 }}) comments that &quot;July was the turning point&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt;)

Van Vogt's first completed novel, and one of his most famous, is ''[[Slan]]'' (Arkham House, 1946), which Campbell serialized in ''Astounding'' September to December 1940.&lt;ref name=isfdb/&gt; Using what became one of van Vogt's recurring themes, it told the story of a nine-year-old superman living in a world in which his kind are slain by ''[[Homo sapiens]]''.

Others saw van Vogt's talent from his first story,{{r|earlyyears79_82}} and in May 1941, van Vogt decided to become a full-time writer, quitting his job at the [[Department of National Defence (Canada)|Canadian Department of National Defence]]. Freed from the necessity of living in Ottawa, he and his wife lived for a time in the [[Gatineau]] region of [[Quebec]] before moving to [[Toronto]] in the fall of 1941.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://nationalpost.com/opinion/scott-van-wynsberghe-on-a-e-van-vogt-a-home-grown-science-fiction-king|title=A.E. van Vogt: A home-grown science-fiction king - National Post|first=Full|last=Comment|date=September 11, 2012|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.icshi.net/sevagram/interviews/weinberg.php#top|title=A.E. van Vogt Interviewed by Robert Weinberg (1980) - Sevagram|website=www.icshi.net}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Prolific throughout this period, van Vogt wrote many of his more famous short stories and novels in the years from 1941 through 1944. The novels ''[[The Book of Ptath]]'' and ''[[The Weapon Makers]]'' both appeared in magazines in serial form during this era; they were later published in book form after World War II.  As well, several (though not all) of the stories that were compiled to make up the novels ''[[The Weapon Shops of Isher]]'', ''[[The Mixed Men]]'' and ''[[The War Against the Rull]]'' were also published during this time.

===California and post-war writing (1944–1950)===
In November 1944, van Vogt and Hull moved to [[Hollywood]]; van Vogt would spend the rest of his life in California.  He had been using the name &quot;A. E. van Vogt&quot; in his public life for several years, and as part of the process of obtaining American citizenship in 1945 he finally and formally changed his legal name from Alfred Vogt to Alfred Elton van Vogt.  To his friends in the California science fiction community, he was known as &quot;Van&quot;.

==Method and themes==
Van Vogt systematized his writing method, using scenes of 800 words or so where a new complication was added or something resolved. Several of his stories hinge on temporal [[Riddle|conundra]], a favorite theme. He stated that he acquired many of his writing techniques from three books: ''Narrative Technique'' by Thomas Uzzell, ''The Only Two Ways to Write a Story'' by [[John Gallishaw]], and ''Twenty Problems of the Fiction Writer'' by Gallishaw.&lt;ref name=panshin/&gt;  He also claimed many of his ideas came from dreams; throughout his writing life he arranged to be awakened every 90&amp;nbsp;minutes during his sleep period so he could write down his dreams.&lt;ref name=platt&gt;[[Charles Platt (science-fiction author)|Platt, Charles]], [http://www.icshi.net/worlds/Plattprofile.htm &quot;A. E. van Vogt – A Profile&quot;]. From ''Who Writes Science Fiction?'' (London: Savoy Books, 1980); ''Dream Makers: The Uncommon People Who Write Science Fiction'' (Berkeley Books, 1980).&lt;/ref&gt;

Van Vogt was also always interested in the idea of all-encompassing systems of knowledge (akin to modern [[meta-systems]])—the characters in his very first story used a system called &quot;Nexialism&quot; to analyze the alien's behavior. Around this time, he became particularly interested in the [[general semantics]] of [[Alfred Korzybski]].

He subsequently wrote a novel merging these overarching themes, ''[[The World of Ā]]'', originally serialized in ''Astounding'' in 1945. Ā (often rendered as ''Null-A''), or [[non-Aristotelian logic]], refers to the capacity for, and practice of, using [[Intuition (knowledge)|intuitive]], [[inductive reasoning]] (compare [[fuzzy logic]]), rather than reflexive, or conditioned, [[deductive reasoning]].  The novel recounts the adventures of an individual living in an apparent [[Utopia]], where those with superior brainpower make up the ruling class... though all is not as it seems.  A sequel, ''The Players of Ā'' (later re-titled ''[[The Pawns of Null-A]]'') was serialized in 1948–49.

At the same time, in his fiction, van Vogt was consistently sympathetic to [[absolute monarchy]] as a form of government.&lt;ref name=&quot;DK&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Knight|first=Damon|authorlink=Damon Knight|date=1967|title=In Search of Wonder|location=Chicago|publisher=Advent}}&lt;/ref&gt; This was the case, for instance, in the ''[[The Weapon Shops of Isher|Weapon Shop]]'' series, the ''[[The Mixed Men|Mixed Men]]'' series, and in single stories such as &quot;Heir Apparent&quot; (1945), whose protagonist was described as a &quot;[[benevolent dictator]]&quot;.  These sympathies were the subject of much critical discussion during van Vogt's career, and afterwards.

Van Vogt published &quot;Enchanted Village&quot; in the July 1950 issue of ''Other Worlds Science Stories''. It was reprinted in over 20 collections or anthologies, and appeared many times in translation.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.isfdb.org/cgi-bin/title.cgi?56655 Retrieved 10 March 2017&lt;/ref&gt;

===Dianetics and fix-ups (1950–1961)===
In 1950, van Vogt was briefly appointed as head of [[L. Ron Hubbard]]'s [[Dianetics]] operation in California.  Van Vogt had first met Hubbard in 1945, and became interested in his [[Dianetics]] theories, which were published shortly thereafter.  Dianetics was the secular precursor to Hubbard's Church of [[Scientology]]; van Vogt would have no association with Scientology, as he did not approve of its mysticism.

The California Dianetics operation went broke nine months later, but never went bankrupt, due to van Vogt's arrangements with creditors. Very shortly after that, van Vogt and his wife opened their own Dianetics center, partly financed by his writings, until he &quot;signed off&quot; around 1961.  In practical terms, what this meant was that from 1951 through 1961, van Vogt's focus was on Dianetics, and no new story ideas flowed from his typewriter.

===Fix-ups===
However, during the 1950s, van Vogt retrospectively patched together many of his previously published stories into novels, sometimes creating new interstitial material to help bridge gaps in the narrative.  Van Vogt referred to the resulting books as &quot;[[fix-up]]s&quot;, a term that entered the vocabulary of science-fiction criticism. When the original stories were closely related this was often successful — although some van Vogt fix-ups featured disparate stories thrown together that bore little relation to each other, generally making for a less coherent plot.  One of his best-known (and well-regarded) novels, ''[[The Voyage of the Space Beagle]]'' (1950) was a fix-up of four short stories including &quot;Discord in Scarlet&quot;; it was published in at least five European languages by 1955.&lt;ref name=isfdb/&gt;

Although Van Vogt averaged a new book title every ten months from 1951 to 1961, none of them were new stories. All of van Vogt's books from 1951 to 1961 were fix-ups, or collections of previously published stories, or expansions of previously published short stories to novel length, or republications of his books under new titles.  All were based on story material written and originally published between 1939 and 1950.  As well, one non-fiction work, ''The Hypnotism Handbook'', appeared in 1956, though it had apparently been written much earlier.

Some of van Vogt's more well-known work was still produced using the fix-up method. In 1951, he published the fix-up ''[[The Weapon Shops of Isher]].'' In the same decade, van Vogt also produced collections and  [[fixup]]s such as ''[[The Mixed Men]]'' (1952), ''[[The War Against the Rull]]'' (1959), and the two &quot;Clane&quot; novels, ''[[Empire of the Atom]]'' (1957) and ''[[The Wizard of Linn]]'' (1962), which were inspired (like [[Isaac Asimov|Asimov]]'s [[Foundation series]]) by [[Roman Empire|Roman imperial history]], specifically the reign of [[Claudius]].

After more than a decade of running their Dianetics center, Hull and van Vogt closed it in 1961.  Nevertheless, van Vogt maintained his association with the overall organization and was still president of the Californian Association of Dianetic Auditors into the 1980s.&lt;ref name=platt/&gt;

==Return to writing and later career (1962–1986)==
Though the constant re-packaging of his older work meant that he had never really been away from the book publishing world, van Vogt had not published any wholly new fiction for almost 12 years when he decided to return to writing in 1962.  He did not return immediately to science fiction, however, but instead wrote the only mainstream, non-sf novel of his career.
 
Van Vogt was profoundly affected by revelations of [[totalitarian]] [[police state]]s that emerged after [[World War II]]. Accordingly, he wrote a mainstream novel that he set in [[Communist China (modern)|Communist China]], ''The Violent Man'' (1962); he said that to research this book he had read 100 books about China. Into this book he incorporated his view of &quot;the violent male type&quot;, which he described as a &quot;man who had to be right&quot;, a man who &quot;instantly attracts women&quot; and who he said were the men who &quot;run the world&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;HLDrake&quot; /&gt;  Contemporary reviews were lukewarm at best,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.kirkusreviews.com/book-reviews/aa-van-vogt/the-violent-man/|title=THE VIOLENT MAN by A.A. Van Vogt|publisher=|via=www.kirkusreviews.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; and van Vogt thereafter returned to science fiction.

From 1963 through the mid-1980s, van Vogt once again published new material on a regular basis, though fix-ups and reworked material also appeared relatively often.  His later novels included fix-ups such as ''The Beast'' (also known as ''Moonbeast'') (1963), ''[[Rogue Ship]]'' (1965), ''[[Quest for the Future]]'' (1970) and ''[[Supermind (novel)|Supermind]]'' (1977).  He also wrote novels by expanding previously published short stories; works of this type include ''The Darkness on Diamondia'' (1972) and ''Future Glitter'' (also known as ''Tyranopolis''; 1973).

Novels that were written simply as novels, and not serialized magazine pieces or fix-ups, were very rare in van Vogt's oeuvre, but began to appear regularly beginning in the 1970s.  Van Vogt's original novels included ''[[Children of Tomorrow]]'' (1970), ''The Battle of Forever'' (1971) and ''The Anarchistic Colossus'' (1977).  Over the years, many sequels to his classic works were promised, but only one appeared:  ''[[Null-A Three]]'' (1984; originally published in French). Several later books were originally published in Europe, and at least one novel only ever appeared in foreign language editions and was never published in its original English.

==Final years==
When the 1979 film ''[[Alien (film)|Alien]]'' appeared, it was noted that the plot closely matched the plot of van Vogt's ''[[Voyage of the Space Beagle]]''.  Van Vogt sued the production company for [[plagiarism]], and eventually collected an out-of-court settlement of $50,000 from [[20th Century Fox]].{{sfn|Ketterer|1992|p=47}}{{sfn|Decker|2016|p=31}}

In increasingly frail health, van Vogt published his final short story in 1986.

==Death==
On January 26, 2000, A. E. van Vogt died in [[Los Angeles]] from [[Alzheimer's disease]].  He was survived by his second wife, the former Lydia Bereginsky.

==Personal life==
Van Vogt's first wife, Edna Mayne Hull, died in 1975.  Van Vogt married Lydia Bereginsky in 1979; they remained together until his death.

==Critical reception==
Critical opinion about the quality of van Vogt's work is sharply divided. An early and articulate critic was [[Damon Knight]]. In a 1945&lt;ref&gt;Van Vogt, A E (1970).  Introduction to ''The World Of Null-A'' (London: Sphere Science Fiction, 1976), p. viii&lt;/ref&gt; chapter-long essay reprinted in ''[[In Search of Wonder]],''&lt;ref name=DK/&gt; entitled &quot;Cosmic Jerrybuilder: A. E. van Vogt&quot;, Knight described van Vogt as &quot;no giant; he is a pygmy who has learned to operate an overgrown typewriter&quot;. Knight described ''The World of Null-A'' as &quot;one of the worst allegedly adult science fiction stories ever published&quot;. Concerning van Vogt's writing, Knight said:

{{quote|In general van Vogt seems to me to fail consistently as a writer in these elementary ways: 1. His plots do not bear examination. 2. His choice of words and his sentence-structure are fumbling and insensitive. 3. He is unable either to visualize a scene or to make a character seem real.}}

About ''[[Empire of the Atom]]'' Knight wrote:

{{quote|If you can only throw your reasoning powers out of gear—something many van Vogt fans find easy to do—you'll enjoy this one.}}

Knight also expressed misgivings about van Vogt's politics. He noted that van Vogt's stories almost invariably present [[absolute monarchy]] in a favorable light. In 1974, Knight retracted some of his criticism after finding out about Vogt's writing down his dreams as a part of his working methods:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.depauw.edu/sfs/backissues/3/notes3.htm|title=Notes, Reports, and Correspondence: Spring 1974|publisher=|accessdate=March 15, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|This explains a good deal about the stories, and suggests that it is really useless to attack them by conventional standards. If the stories have a dream consistency which affects readers powerfully, it is probably irrelevant that they lack ordinary consistency.}}

Knight's criticism greatly damaged van Vogt's reputation.&lt;ref name=&quot;latham2009&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |title=The Routledge Companion to Science Fiction |last=Latham |first=Rob |publisher=Routledge |year=2009 |isbn=9781135228361 |editor-last=Bould |editor-first=Mark |pages=80–89 |chapter=Fiction, 1950-1963 |editor-last2=Butler |editor-first2=Andrew M. |editor-last3=Roberts |editor-first3=Adam |editor-last4=Vint |editor-first4=Sherryl |chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=y7CNAgAAQBAJ&amp;lpg=PA82&amp;ots=QpsnWwPrOs&amp;pg=PA80#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=true}}&lt;/ref&gt; On the other hand, when science fiction author Philip K. Dick was asked &lt;ref name=vertex&gt;
[http://www.philipkdick.com/media_vertex.html &quot;Vertex Interviews Philip K. Dick&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20101012062459/http://www.philipkdick.com/media_vertex.html |date=October 12, 2010 }} . ''[[Science fiction magazine#Defunct magazines|Vertex]]'', Vol. 1, No. 6, February 1974.
&lt;/ref&gt; which science fiction writers had influenced his work the most, he replied:

{{quote|I started reading sf when I was about twelve and I read all I could, so any author who was writing about that time, I read. But there's no doubt who got me off originally and that was A. E. van Vogt. There was in van Vogt's writing a mysterious quality, and this was especially true in ''[[The World of Null-A]]''. All the parts of that book did not add up; all the ingredients did not make a coherency. Now some people are put off by that. They think that's sloppy and wrong, but the thing that fascinated me so much was that this resembled reality more than anybody else's writing inside or outside science fiction.}}

Dick also defended van Vogt against Damon Knight's criticisms:

{{quote|Damon feels that it's bad artistry when you build those funky universes where people fall through the floor. It's like he's viewing a story the way a building inspector would when he's building your house. But reality really is a mess, and yet it's exciting. The basic thing is, how frightened are you of chaos? And how happy are you with order? Van Vogt influenced me so much because he made me appreciate a mysterious chaotic quality in the universe which is not to be feared.}}

In a review of ''Transfinite: The Essential A. E. van Vogt'', science fiction writer [[Paul Di Filippo]] said:

{{quote|Van Vogt knew precisely what he was doing in all areas of his fiction writing. There's hardly a wasted word in his stories. ... His plots are marvels of interlocking pieces, often ending in real surprises and shocks, genuine paradigm shifts, which are among the hardest conceptions to depict. And the intellectual material of his fictions, the conceits and tossed-off observations on culture and human and alien behavior, reflect a probing mind. ... Each tale contains a new angle, a unique slant, that makes it stand out.&lt;ref&gt;DiFilippo, Paul: [http://www.scifi.com/sfw/issue326/books2.html &quot;Off The Shelf&quot;]. Retrieved January 19, 2003.  {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20050403090307/http://www.scifi.com/sfw/issue326/books2.html |date=April 3, 2005 }}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

In ''The John W. Campbell Letters'', Campbell says, &quot;The son-of-a-gun gets hold of you in the first paragraph, ties a knot around you, and keeps it tied in every paragraph thereafter—including the ultimate last one&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;HLDrake&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Drake| first = Harold L. | title = The Null-A Worlds of A. E. van Vogt | publisher = C. Drumm Books | date = 1989 | isbn = 093605543X}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Campbell | first = John W.| authorlink = John W. Campbell | title = The John W. Campbell Letters With Isaac Asimov and A. E. van Vogt | volume = 2 | publisher = A.C.Projects | date = 1991| isbn = 978-0-931150-19-7 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Harlan Ellison]] (who had begun reading van Vogt as a teenager)&lt;ref name=&quot;harlan&quot;&gt;Ellison, Harlan (June 1999), [http://www.sfrevu.com/ISSUES/2000/ARTICLES/20000128-03.htm &quot;Van is Here, But Van is Gone&quot;]. Introduction to ''Futures Past: The Best Short Fiction of A. E. van Vogt'' (Kilimanjaro Corp., 1999). Reprinted in &quot;A. E. van Vogt, 1912–2000&quot; (''SFRevu'' 2001-01-28). Retrieved 2001-08-31.&lt;br&gt; Quote: &quot;Van is still with us, as I write this, in June of 1999, slightly less than fifty years since I first encountered van Vogt prose in a January 1950 issue of ''Startling Stories''{{nbsp}}...&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; wrote, &quot;Van was the first writer to shine light on the restricted ways in which I had been taught to view the universe and the human condition&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;HLDrake&quot; /&gt;

Writing in 1984, [[David Hartwell]] said:&lt;ref name=&quot;Hartwell1984&quot;&gt;{{cite book|first=David G. |last=Hartwell|title=Age of Wonders: Exploring the World of Science|url={{google books |plainurl=y |id=5GpIPgAACAAJ|page=131}}|date=1 June 1984|publisher=Washington Ave Books Incorporated|isbn=978-0-89366-163-2|pp=131–32}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|No one has taken van Vogt seriously as a writer for a long time. Yet he has been read and ''still'' is. What no one seems to have noticed is that van Vogt, more than any other single SF writer, is the conduit through which the energy of [[Gernsback]]ian, primitive wonder stories have been transmitted through the [[John W. Campbell|Campbellian]] age, when earlier styles of SF were otherwise rejected, and on into SF of the present.}}

The literary critic [[Leslie A. Fiedler]] said something similar:&lt;ref name=&quot;SlusserRabkin1983&quot;&gt;{{cite book|first=Leslie A. |last=Fiedler|editor-first1=George Edgar |editor-last1=Slusser|editor-first2=Eric S.|editor-last2= Rabkin|editor-first3=Robert E. |editor-last3=Scholes|title=Coordinates: placing science fiction and fantasy|url={{google books |plainurl=y |id=fX9ZAAAAMAAJ|page=10}}|date=1 August 1983|publisher=Southern Illinois University Press|isbn=978-0-8093-1105-7|pp=10–11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|Van Vogt is a test case ... since an apology for or analysis of science fiction which fails to come to terms with his appeal and major importance, defends or defines the genre by falsifying it.}}

American literary critic [[Fredric Jameson]] says of van Vogt:

{{quote|that van Vogt's work clearly prepares the way for that of the greatest of all Science Fiction writers, Philip K. Dick, whose extraordinary novels and stories are inconceivable without the opening onto that play of unconscious materials and fantasy dynamics released by van Vogt, and very different from the more hard-science aesthetic ideologies of his contemporaries (from Campbell to Heinlein).&lt;ref&gt;Jameson, Fredric. &quot;The Space of Science Fiction: Narrative in Van Vogt&quot;, ''Archaeologies of the Future. The Desire Called Utopia and Other Science Fictions'' (New York: Verso, 2005).&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|315}}}}

Van Vogt still has his critics. For example, [[Darrell Schweitzer]] writing to ''The New York Review of Science Fiction'' in 1999&lt;ref&gt;Schweitzer, Darrell (1999), &quot;Letters of Comment&quot;, ''The New York Review of Science Fiction'', May 1999, Number 129, Vol. 11, No. 9.&lt;/ref&gt; quoted a passage from the original van Vogt novelette &quot;The Mixed Men&quot;, which he was then reading, and remarked:

{{quote|This is the realism, and logic, of a small boy playing with toy soldiers in a sandbox. I'm tougher than you. I've got a ''billion'' spaceships! They're brand-new. They only took 800 years to develop.
And this is a story in which most of the cast either have two brains or are really robots ... and even the emotions of the human characters are programmed or deprogrammed as part of plots within counter plots. Next to this, Doc Smith was an icy realist. There is ''no'' intersection with adult reality at any point, for all van Vogt was able to write was that small boy's sandbox game with an adult level of intensity. This is, I think, the secret of van Vogt's bizarre fascination, as awful as his actual writing might be, and why he appealed so strongly to Philip K. Dick, who managed to put more adult characters and emotions into equally crazy situations. It's ultimately very strange to find this sort of writing so prominently sponsored by supposedly rational and scientifically minded John W. Campbell, when it seems to contravene everything the Golden Age stood for.}}

==Recognition==
The [[Science Fiction Writers of America]] named him its 14th [[SFWA Grand Master|Grand Master]] in 1995 (presented 1996).&lt;ref name=SFWA/&gt;  Also in 1996, van Vogt received a Special Award from the [[World Science Fiction Convention]] &quot;for six decades of golden age science fiction&quot;.&lt;ref name=SFAwards/&gt; That same year, he was inducted as an inaugural member of the [[EMP Museum#Science Fiction Hall of Fame|Science Fiction and Fantasy Hall of Fame]].&lt;ref name=sfhof-old/&gt;

In 1946, van Vogt and his first wife, [[Edna Mayne Hull]], were Guests of Honor at the fourth [[World Science Fiction Convention]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Beetz1996&quot;&gt;{{cite book|first=Kirk H. |last=Beetz|title=Encyclopedia of popular fiction|url={{google books |plainurl=y |id=Mn4YAAAAIAAJ}}|year=1996|publisher=Beacham Pub.|isbn=978-0-933833-38-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1980, van Vogt received a &quot;Casper Award&quot; (precursor to the Canadian [[Prix Aurora Awards]]) for Lifetime Achievement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last=Mullin | first=Dennis | date=October 27, 2007 | url=http://www.sentex.net/~dmullin/aurora/hist_dat.html | title=Prix AURORA Awards | publisher=Canadian Science Fiction and Fantasy Association | accessdate=May 2, 2008 | archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080509122152/http://www.sentex.net/~dmullin/aurora/hist_dat.html | archivedate=May 9, 2008 | url-status=dead | df=mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=SFAwards/&gt;

The [[Science Fiction Writers of America]] named him its 14th [[SFWA Grand Master|Grand Master]] in 1995 (presented 1996).&lt;ref name=SFWA/&gt; Great controversy within SFWA accompanied its long wait in bestowing its highest honor (limited to living writers, no more than one annually&lt;ref name=SFWA/&gt;). Writing an obituary of van Vogt, [[Robert J. Sawyer]], a fellow Canadian writer of science fiction, remarked:

{{quote|There was no doubt that van Vogt should have received this honor much earlier—the injustice of him being overlooked, at least in part because of damnable SFWA politics, had so incensed [[Harlan Ellison]], a man with an impeccable moral compass, that he'd lobbied hard on the [[Sci Fi Channel (United States)|Sci-Fi Channel]] and elsewhere on van Vogt's behalf.&lt;ref&gt;[[Robert J. Sawyer|Sawyer, Robert J.]] [http://www.sfwriter.com/vanvogt.htm &quot;Remembering A. E. van Vogt&quot;]. Retrieved August 31, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

It is generally held that the &quot;damnable SFWA politics&quot; concerns Damon Knight, the founder of the SFWA, who abhorred van Vogt's style and politics and thoroughly demolished his literary reputation in the 1950s.&lt;ref&gt;[[David Hartwell|Hartwell, David]]: &quot;The Way We Were: A. E. van Vogt, 1912-2000&quot;, ''[[The New York Review of Science Fiction]]'', March 2000, Number 139, Vol. 12, No. 7, page 24.&lt;/ref&gt;

Harlan Ellison was more explicit in 1999 introduction to ''Futures Past: The Best Short Fiction of A. E. van Vogt'':&lt;ref name=&quot;harlan&quot;/&gt;

{{quote|[A]t least I was able to make enough noise to get Van the Science Fiction Writers of America Grand Master Award, which was presented to him in full ceremony during one of the last moments when he was cogent and clearheaded enough to understand that finally, at last, dragged kicking and screaming to honor him, the generation that learned from what he did and what he had created had, at last, 'fessed up to his importance.

... were the same ones who assured me that Van would never get the Grand Master until Damon Knight had gotten it first, because Damon had loathed Van's work and had, in fact written the essay that ridiculed Van and held him up to opprobrium for decades thereafter, and Damon having founded SFWA it would be an affront to him if Van got it first. Well, I don't know if that's true or not, though it was common coin in the field for years; but Damon got the Grand Master award in 1994. And Van got it in 1995.{{efn|The award was presented to Knight and van Vogt in 1995 and 1996 respectively, the years following selection. It is restricted to living authors, no more than one annually. It was renamed the Damon Knight Memorial Grand Master (Award) after Knight's death in 2002.&lt;ref name=SFWA/&gt;}} As they say during sweeps week on television: coincidence or conspiracy?}}

In 1996, van Vogt received a Special Award from the [[World Science Fiction Convention]] &quot;for six decades of golden age science fiction&quot;.&lt;ref name=SFAwards/&gt; That same year, the [[EMP Museum#Science Fiction Hall of Fame|Science Fiction and Fantasy Hall of Fame]] inducted him in its inaugural class of two deceased and two living persons, along with writer [[Jack Williamson]] (also living) and editors [[Hugo Gernsback]] and [[John W. Campbell]].&lt;ref name=sfhof-old/&gt;

The works of van Vogt were translated into [[French language|French]] by the surrealist [[Boris Vian]] (''The World of Null-A'' as ''Le Monde des Å'' in 1958), and van Vogt's works were &quot;viewed as great literature of the [[Surrealism|surrealist school]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[Ian Watson (author)|Watson, Ian]] (1999), &quot;Science Fiction, Surrealism, and Shamanism&quot;, ''The New York Review of Science Fiction'', June 1999, Number 130, Vol. 11, No. 10, page 9.&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, ''Slan'' was published in French, translated by Jean Rosenthal, under the title ''À la poursuite des Slans'', as part of the paperback series 'Editions J'ai Lu: Romans-Texte Integral' in 1973, this edition also listing the following works by van Vogt as having been published in French as part of this series: ''Le Monde des Å'', ''La faune de l'espace'', ''Les joueurs du Å'', ''L'empire de l'atome'', ''Le sorcier de Linn'', ''Les armureries d'Isher'', ''Les fabricants d'armes'', and ''Le livre de Ptath''.&lt;ref&gt;''À la poursuite des Slans'', A. E. Van Vogt, Editions J'ai Lu, 31, rue de Tournon, Paris-VIe, 1973&lt;/ref&gt;

==Works==
&lt;!-- is this intended to be complete at least for books? if not use &quot;Selected works&quot; --&gt;

===Novels===

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|+ The following table can be sorted to show van Vogt's novels in chronological order,&lt;br /&gt;or arranged alphabetically by title, or by series.  Primary dates list first publication in book form.&lt;br /&gt;
! Year !! Title !! Series !! Notes !! Alternate titles
|-
|1946
|''[[Slan]]''
|
|Originally serialized in ''[[Astounding Science Fiction]]'', September – December 1940.
|
|-
|1947
|''[[The Weapon Makers]]''
| Isher
|Significantly revised version of a novel originally serialized in ''[[Astounding Science Fiction]]'', February – April 1943.&lt;br&gt;Revised again in 1952.
|''One Against Eternity'' (1964)
|-
|1947
|''[[The Book of Ptath]]''
|
|Originally appeared (complete) in ''[[Unknown (magazine)|Unknown]]'', October 1943.&lt;br&gt;
|''Two Hundred Million A.D.'' (1964)&lt;br&gt; ''Ptath'' (1976)
|-
|1948
|''[[The World of Ā]]'' 
| Null-A
|Revised and shortened version of a novel originally serialized in ''[[Astounding (magazine)|Astounding Science Fiction]]'', August – October 1945.&lt;br&gt;Revised again in 1970.
|''The World of Null-A'' (all editions from 1953 forward)
|-
|1950
|''[[The House That Stood Still]]'' 
| 
|
|''The Mating Cry'' (1960, revised)&lt;br&gt; ''The Undercover Aliens'' (1976)
|-
|1950
|''[[The Voyage of the Space Beagle]]'' 
| 
|Fix-up of four short stories, originally published 1939 – 1950.
|''Mission: Interplanetary'' (1952)
|-
|1951
|''[[The Weapon Shops of Isher]]''
| Isher
|Fix-up of three short stories, originally published 1941 – 1949.
|
|-
|1952
|''[[The Mixed Men]]''
|
|Fix-up of three short stories, originally published 1943 – 1945.
|''Mission to the Stars'' (1955)
|-
|1953
|''[[The Universe Maker]]''
|
|Extensively rewritten and expanded version of the short story &quot;The Shadow Men&quot; (1950).
|
|-
|1954
|''[[The Pawns of Null-A]]''
|Null-A
|Originally serialized (as ''The Players of Ā'') in ''[[Astounding Science Fiction]]'', October 1948 – January 1949.
|''The Players of Null-A'' (1966)
|-
|1957
|''[[The Mind Cage]]''
|
|Extensively rewritten and expanded version of the short story &quot;The Great Judge&quot; (1948].
|
|-
|1957
|''[[Empire of the Atom]]''
|Gods
|Fix-up of five short stories, originally published 1946 – 1947.
|
|-
|1959
|''Siege of the Unseen''
|
|Originally serialized (as ''The Chronicler'') in ''[[Astounding Science Fiction]]'', October – November 1946.
|''The Three Eyes of Evil'' (1973)
|-
|1959
|''[[The War Against the Rull]]''
|
|Fix-up of six short stories, originally published 1940 – 1950.
|
|-
|1960
|''Earth's Last Fortress''
|
|Novella, originally appeared (complete, as &quot;Recruiting Station&quot;) in ''[[Astounding Science Fiction]]'', March 1942.   
|Anthologized as &quot;Masters Of Time&quot; in the van Vogt collection ''Masters Of Time'' (1950). 
|-
|1962
|''[[The Wizard of Linn]]''
|Gods
|Originally serialized in ''[[Astounding Science Fiction]]'', April – June 1950.   
|
|-
|1962
|''The Violent Man''
|
|Non-sf; a political thriller. 
|
|-
|1963
|''The Beast''
|
|Substantially revised fix-up of three short stories, originally published 1943 – 1944. 
|''Moonbeast'' (1969)
|-
|1965
|''[[Rogue Ship]]''
|
|Fix-up of three short stories, originally published 1947 – 1963. 
|
|-
|1966
|''The Winged Man'' (with [[E. Mayne Hull]])
|
|Originally serialized (and credited solely to E. Mayne Hull) in ''[[Astounding Science Fiction]]'', May – June 1944. Greatly expanded (from 35,000 to 60,000 words) by van Vogt for book publication.
|
|-
|1967
|''The Changeling''
|
|Novella, originally appeared (complete) in ''[[Astounding Science Fiction]]'', April 1944. &lt;br&gt;Previously anthologized in the van Vogt collection ''Masters Of Time'' (1950). 
|
|-
|1969
|''[[The Silkie (novel)|The Silkie]]''
|
|Fix-up of three short stories, originally published 1964 – 1967.
|
|-
|1970
|''[[Children of Tomorrow]]''
|
|
|
|-
|1970
|''[[Quest for the Future]]''
|
|Fix-up of three short stories, originally published 1943 – 1946.
|
|-
|1971
|''The Battle of Forever''
|
|
|
|-
|1972
|''The Darkness on Diamondia''
|
|
|
|-
|1973
|''Future Glitter''
|
|
|''Tyranopolis'' (1977)
|-
|1974
|''[[The Man with a Thousand Names]]''
|
|
|
|-
|1974
|''The Secret Galactics''
|
|
|''Earth Factor X'' (1976)
|-
|1977
|''[[Supermind (novel)|Supermind]]''
|
|Fix-up of three short stories, originally published 1942 – 1968.  The 1965 story &quot;Research Alpha&quot;, minimally revised to form chapters 23-36 of this novel, was credited on original publication to van Vogt and [[James H. Schmitz]].
|
|-
|1977
|''The Anarchistic Colossus''
|
|
|
|-
|1979
|''Renaissance''
|
|
|
|-
|1979
|''Cosmic Encounter''
|
|
|
|-
|1983
|''Computerworld''
|
|
|''Computer Eye'' (1985)
|-
|1984
|''[[Null-A Three]]''
|Null-A
|
|
|-
|1985
|''To Conquer Kiber''
|
|Unpublished in English.  Published in French as ''A la conquête de Kiber'' and in Romanian as ''Cucerirea Kiberului''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| last1=Dubé| first1=Denis| title=Plot Summary: To Conquer Kiber by A.E. van Vogt| url= http://www.icshi.net/sevagram/summaries/kiber.php| website=Sevagram| accessdate=12 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|
|}

'''Also:'''
* ''Planets For Sale'' by E. Mayne Hull (1954) - A fix-up of five stories by Hull, originally published 1942 – 1946.  Some later editions (from 1965) credit both van Vogt and Hull as authors. 
* ''The Enchanted Village'' (1979) - A 25-page [[chapbook]] of a van Vogt short story originally published in 1950.
* ''Slan Hunter'' by [[Kevin J. Anderson]] (2007) - A sequel to ''Slan'', utilizing an unfinished draft by van Vogt.
* ''Null-A Continuum'' by [[John C. Wright (author)|John C. Wright]] (2008) - An authorized continuation of the Null-A series.  It ignored the events of ''[[Null-A Three]]''.

===Collections===
* ''[[Out of the Unknown (collection)|Out of the Unknown]]'' (1948), with [[Edna Mayne Hull]]
* ''[[Masters of Time]]'' (1950) (a.k.a. Recruiting Station) [also includes ''The Changeling'', both works were later published separately]
* ''Triad'' (1951) omnibus of ''The World of Null A'', ''The Voyage of the Space Beagle'', ''Slan''.
* ''Away and Beyond'' (1952) (abridged in paperback in 1959; abridged (differently) in paperback in 1963)
* ''[[Destination: Universe!]]'' (1952)
* ''[[The Twisted Men]]'' (1964)
* ''[[Monsters (collection)|Monsters]]'' (1965) (later as ''SF Monsters'' (1967)) abridged as ''The Blal'' (1976)
* ''A Van Vogt Omnibus'' (1967), omnibus of ''Planets for Sale'' (with [[Edna Mayne Hull]]), ''The Beast'', ''The Book of Ptath''
* ''The Far Out Worlds of Van Vogt'' (1968)
* ''The Sea Thing and Other Stories'' (1970) (expanded from ''[[Out of the Unknown (collection)|Out of the Unknown]]'' by adding an original story by Hull; later abridged in paperback as ''Out of the Unknown'' by removing 2 of the stories)
* ''[[M33 in Andromeda]]'' (1971)
* ''[[More Than Superhuman]]'' (1971)
* ''The Proxy Intelligence and Other Mind Benders'', ), with [[Edna Mayne Hull]] (1971), revised as ''The Gryb'' (1976)
* ''Van Vogt Omnibus 2'' (1971), omnibus of ''The Mind Cage'', ''The Winged Man'' (with [[Edna Mayne Hull]]), ''Slan''.
* ''The Book of Van Vogt'' (1972), also published as ''Lost: Fifty Suns'' (1979)
* ''The Three Eyes of Evil Including Earth's Last Fortress'' (1973)
* ''The Best of A. E. van Vogt'' (1974) later split into 2 volumes
* ''The Worlds of A. E. van Vogt (1974) (expanded from ''The Far Out Worlds of Van Vogt'' by adding 3 stories)
* ''The Best of A. E. van Vogt'' (1976) [differs to 1974 edition]
* ''Away and Beyond'' (1977)
* ''Pendulum'' (1978) (almost all original stories and articles)
* ''Futures Past: The Best Short Fiction of A.E. Van Vogt'' (1999)
* ''Transfinite: The Essential A.E. van Vogt'' (2002)
* ''Transgalactic'' (2006)

===Nonfiction===
* ''The Hypnotism Handbook'' (1956, Griffin Publishing Company, with [[Charles Edward Cooke]])
* ''The Money Personality'' (1972, Parker Publishing Company Inc., West Nyack, NY, {{ISBN|978-0-13-600676-3}})
* ''Reflections of A. E. Van Vogt: The Autobiography of a Science Fiction Giant'' (1979, Fictioneer Books Ltd., Lakemont, GA)
* ''A Report on the Violent Male'' (1992, Paupers' Press, UK, {{ISBN|978-0-946650-40-8}})

==See also==
{{Portal bar |Science fiction }} &lt;!-- delete &quot;bar&quot; if/when there are enough ordinary See also --&gt;

==Notes==
{{notelist |notes=
{{efn|name=movies |1=
{{quote|This [The voyage of the Space Beagle] is the classic 'bug-eyed monster' novel, the unacknowledged inspiration for the film ''Alien'' and scores of similar
|David Pringle|(1990) &quot;The Ultimate Guide to Science Fiction&quot;, Grafton Books, page 346.}}

{{quote|The stories collected in The Voyage of the Space Beagle were perhaps the first to chronicle the adventures of the crew of a large, military-style starship exploring the universe, and doubtless influenced [[Gene Roddenberry]] strongly when he created ''Star Trek''. ... One of the Space Beagle stories purportedly inspired the movie ''Alien'' - the resemblance was great enough that van Vogt brought a lawsuit against the filmmakers, which reportedly settled for a $50,000 payment.|Aaron Hughes|[http://fantasticreviews.com/weapon_shops_of_isher.htm &quot;Neglected Masters Book Review&quot;] retrieved 2010-09-09}}

{{quote|... The Voyage Of The Space Beagle (1950), later inspired the original ''Star Trek'' series and the movie ''Alien''.|Trent Walters|[http://www.zone-sf.com/vanvogtmethod.html &quot;Oh, the Humanity of A.E. van Vogt's Monsters: Reorienting Critics and Readers to the van Vogt Method&quot;] retrieved 2010-09-09}}.

{{quote|'Black Destroyer' has been cited as the inspiration for the movie ''Alien'' and its many sequels and imitations|Gerald Jonas|(2000) &quot;A. E. van Vogt, 87, Forceful Science-Fiction Voice&quot;, New York Times obituary, 2000-02-04}}

{{quote|''Alien'' is thus virtually a film version or translation of &quot;Black Destroyer&quot;. (Van Vogt is not credited, and as it turns out he sued the film-makers for plagiarism; the latter settling out of court.|Fredric Jameson|''Archaeologies of the Future. The Desire Called Utopia and Other Science Fictions'' (New York: Verso, 2005, pp. 325)}}
}}
}}

==References==
{{Reflist |refs=
&lt;ref name=isfdb&gt;
{{isfdb name |58}} ('''ISFDB'''). Retrieved April 4, 2013. Select a title to see its linked publication history and general information. Select a particular edition (title) for more data at that level, such as a front cover image or linked contents.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- some awards refs --&gt;
&lt;ref name=SFAwards&gt;
[http://www.locusmag.com/SFAwards/Db/NomLit140.html#5341 &quot;van Vogt, A. E.&quot;] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121016201749/http://www.locusmag.com/SFAwards/Db/NomLit140.html#5341 |date=October 16, 2012 }}. ''The Locus Index to SF Awards: Index to Literary Nominees''. [[Locus Publications]]. Retrieved March 25, 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=SFWA&gt;
[http://www.sfwa.org/nebula-awards/nebula-weekend/events-program/grandmaster/ &quot;Damon Knight Memorial Grand Master&quot;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110701114233/http://www.sfwa.org/nebula-awards/nebula-weekend/events-program/grandmaster/ |date=July 1, 2011 }}. Science Fiction and Fantasy Writers of America (SFWA). Retrieved March 25, 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=sfhof-old&gt;
[http://www.midamericon.org/halloffame/ &quot;Science Fiction and Fantasy Hall of Fame&quot;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130521070009/http://www.midamericon.org/halloffame/ |date=May 21, 2013 }}. Mid American Science Fiction and Fantasy Conventions, Inc. Retrieved March 25, 2013. This was the official website of the hall of fame to 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;

}}

==External links==
{{wikiquote}} 
* {{sfhof |959 | A. E. van Vogt}}
* [http://www.icshi.net/sevagram/ Sevagram], the A.E. van Vogt information site
* [http://www.locusmag.com/2000/News/News01e.html Obituary] at ''LocusOnline'' ([[Locus Publications]])
* [http://scifan.com/writers/vv/VanVogt.asp &quot;Writers: A. E. van Vogt (1912–2000, Canada)&quot;] – bibliography at SciFan
* [http://hdl.handle.net/10407/6587030761 A. E. van Vogt Papers] (MS 322) at the [https://spencer.lib.ku.edu Kenneth Spencer Research Library], University of Kansas
* {{isfdb name|58}}
* {{IBList|type=author|id=649|name=A. E. van Vogt}}
* [http://freesfonline.de/authors/A.%20E._van%20Vogt.html A. E. van Vogt's fiction] at Free Speculative Fiction Online
* {{OL author}}
* {{LCAuth|n79123985|A. E. van Vogt|21|}}

{{A. E. van Vogt}}{{Damon Knight Memorial Grand Master Awards}}{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Van Vogt, A. E.}}
[[Category:1912 births]]
[[Category:2000 deaths]]
[[Category:20th-century American novelists]]
[[Category:American male novelists]]
[[Category:American science fiction writers]]
[[Category:Canadian male novelists]]
[[Category:Canadian science fiction writers]]
[[Category:Canadian male short story writers]]
[[Category:Canadian expatriate writers in the United States]]
[[Category:Deaths from Alzheimer's disease]]
[[Category:Prometheus Award winners]]
[[Category:SFWA Grand Masters]]
[[Category:Science Fiction Hall of Fame inductees]]
[[Category:Writers from Manitoba]]
[[Category:Mennonite writers]]
[[Category:Canadian Mennonites]]
[[Category:American male short story writers]]
[[Category:20th-century Canadian short story writers]]
[[Category:20th-century American short story writers]]
[[Category:20th-century Canadian male writers]]
[[Category:Weird fiction writers]]
[[Category:Pulp fiction writers]]</text>
      <sha1>mdr096uud375ejna39i6j7iaxz5gf20</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
