  <page>
    <title>Aircraft</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>849</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943000696</id>
      <parentid>942998815</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-28T06:10:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dawnseeker2000</username>
        <id>1544984</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/77.97.119.151|77.97.119.151]] ([[User talk:77.97.119.151|talk]]) to last revision by Dawnseeker2000 ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2019}}
[[File:Mi-8 (RA-24477) Helicopter in SPB.jpg|thumb|upright=1.35|The [[Mil Mi-8]] is the [[List of most-produced aircraft|most-produced]] [[helicopter]] in history.]]
[[File:Cessna172-CatalinaTakeOff.JPG|thumb|upright=1.35|The [[Cessna 172]] ''Skyhawk'' is the [[List of most-produced aircraft|most produced aircraft]] in history.]]

An '''aircraft''' is a [[vehicle]] that is able to [[flight|fly]] by gaining support from the [[Atmosphere of Earth|air]].&lt;!-- English word &quot;aircraft&quot; is singular and plural with no &quot;s&quot;. See also the link to Wiktionary below. --&gt; It counters the force of gravity by using either [[Buoyancy|static lift]] or by using the [[Lift (force)|dynamic lift]] of an [[airfoil]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/aircraft|title=Aircraft&amp;nbsp;— Define Aircraft at Dictionary.com|work=Dictionary.com|access-date=1 April 2015|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150328141634/http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/aircraft|archivedate=28 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; or in a few cases the [[Powered lift|downward thrust]] from [[jet engine]]s. Common examples of aircraft include [[airplane]]s, [[helicopter]]s, [[airship]]s (including [[blimp]]s), [[Glider (aircraft)|gliders]], [[Powered paragliding|paramotors]] and [[hot air balloon]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;wingsoverkansas&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|title=Different Kinds &amp; Types of Aircraft|url=http://www.wingsoverkansas.com/features/a1037/|website=www.wingsoverkansas.com|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20161121165354/http://www.wingsoverkansas.com/features/a1037/|archivedate=21 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The human activity that surrounds aircraft is called ''[[aviation]]''. The science of aviation, including designing and building aircraft, is called ''[[aeronautics]].'' [[Aircrew|Crewed]] aircraft are flown by an onboard [[Aircraft pilot|pilot]], but [[unmanned aerial vehicle]]s may be remotely controlled or self-controlled by onboard [[computers]]. Aircraft may be classified by different criteria, such as lift type, [[Powered aircraft#Methods of propulsion|aircraft propulsion]], usage and others.

== History ==
{{Main|History of aviation}}
{{See also|Timeline of aviation}}
Flying model craft and stories of manned [[flight]] go back many centuries; however, the first manned ascent&amp;nbsp;— and safe descent&amp;nbsp;— in modern times took place by larger hot-air balloons developed in the 18th century. Each of the two [[World Wars]] led to great technical advances. Consequently, the history of aircraft can be divided into five eras:
* [[Early flying machines|Pioneers of flight]], from the earliest experiments to 1914.
* [[Aviation in World War I|First World War]], 1914 to 1918.
* [[Aviation between the World Wars]], 1918 to 1939.
* [[Air warfare of World War II|Second World War]], 1939 to 1945.
* [[Post-war|Postwar era]], also called the [[Jet Age]], 1945 to the present day.

== Methods of lift ==
=== Lighter than air – aerostats{{Anchor|Lighter than air}} ===
{{Main|Aerostat}}
[[File:Colorado Springs Hot Air Balloon Competition.jpg|thumb|left|Hot air [[Balloon (aeronautics)|balloons]]]]
[[Aerostat]]s use [[buoyancy]] to float in the air in much the same way that ships float on the water. They are characterized by one or more large cells or canopies, filled with a relatively low-density gas such as [[helium]], [[hydrogen]], or [[hot air balloon|hot air]], which is less dense than the surrounding air. When the weight of this is added to the weight of the aircraft structure, it adds up to the same weight as the air that the craft displaces.

Small hot-air balloons, called [[sky lantern]]s, were first invented in ancient China prior to the 3rd century BC and used primarily in cultural celebrations, and were only the second type of aircraft to fly, the first being [[kite]]s, which were first invented in ancient China over two thousand years ago. (See [[History of science and technology in China#Han Dynasty|Han Dynasty]])

[[File:USS Akron (ZRS-4) in flight over Manhattan, circa 1931-1933.jpg|thumb|Airship [[USS Akron|USS ''Akron'']] over Manhattan in the 1930s]]
A [[Balloon (aeronautics)|balloon]] was originally any aerostat, while the term [[airship]] was used for large, powered aircraft designs&amp;nbsp;— usually fixed-wing.&lt;ref&gt;[http://texashistory.unt.edu/ark:/67531/metapth172915/ US patent 467069] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140223070653/http://texashistory.unt.edu/ark%3A/67531/metapth172915/ |date=23 February 2014}} &quot;Air-ship&quot; referring to a compound aerostat/rotorcraft.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Ezekiel Airship]] (1902) [http://www.wright-brothers.org/History_Wing/History_of_the_Airplane/History_of_the_Airplane_Intro/History_of_the_Airplane_Intro.htm wright-brothers.org] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131203131729/http://www.wright-brothers.org/History_Wing/History_of_the_Airplane/History_of_the_Airplane_Intro/History_of_the_Airplane_Intro.htm |date=3 December 2013}}[http://altereddimensions.net/2012/burrell-cannon-flies-first-airplane altereddimensions.net] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140222065900/http://altereddimensions.net/2012/burrell-cannon-flies-first-airplane |date=22 February 2014}} &quot;airship,&quot; – referring to an HTA aeroplane.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://gustavewhitehead.org/news_journalism/1901_-_flying.html The Bridgeport Herald, August 18, 1901] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130803021718/http://gustavewhitehead.org/news_journalism/1901_-_flying.html |date=3 August 2013}} – &quot;air ship&quot; referring to Whitehead's aeroplane.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Cooley Airship of 1910, also called the Cooley monoplane.{{Cite web |url=http://www.wright-brothers.org/History_Wing/Aviations_Attic/UFOs/UFOs.htm |title=Unbelievable Flying Objects |access-date=2014-02-10 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131102031147/http://www.wright-brothers.org/History_Wing/Aviations_Attic/UFOs/UFOs.htm |archivedate=2 November 2013 }}{{Cite web |url=http://celticowboy.com/Round%20Aircraft%20Designs.htm |title=Archived copy |access-date=2011-09-07 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120402075442/http://celticowboy.com/Round%20Aircraft%20Designs.htm |archivedate=2 April 2012 }} – a heavier-than-air monoplane.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Frater, A.; ''The Balloon Factory'', Picador (2009), p. 163. Wright brothers' &quot;airship.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.technovelgy.com/ct/content.asp?Bnum=879 George Griffith, ''The angel of the Revolution'', 1893] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140222154830/http://www.technovelgy.com/ct/content.asp?Bnum=879 |date=22 February 2014}}&amp;nbsp;— &quot;air-ship,&quot; &quot;vessel&quot; referring to a VTOL compound rotorcraft (not clear from the reference if it might be an aerostat hybrid.)&lt;/ref&gt; In 1919 [[Frederick Handley Page]] was reported as referring to &quot;ships of the air,&quot; with smaller passenger types as &quot;Air yachts.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://paperspast.natlib.govt.nz/cgi-bin/paperspast?a=d&amp;d=AS19190224.2.104 Auckland Star, 24 February 1919] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140324163806/http://paperspast.natlib.govt.nz/cgi-bin/paperspast?a=d&amp;d=AS19190224.2.104 |date=24 March 2014}} &quot;Ships of the air,&quot; &quot;Air yachts&quot; – passenger landplanes large and small&lt;/ref&gt; In the 1930s, large intercontinental flying boats were also sometimes referred to as &quot;ships of the air&quot; or &quot;flying-ships&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article17455790 The Sydney Morning Herald, Monday 11 April 1938] – &quot;ship of the airs,&quot; &quot;flying-ship,&quot; referring to a large flying-boat.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://airandspace.si.edu/exhibitions/america-by-air/online/innovation/innovation16.cfm Smithsonian, America by air] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140118135217/http://airandspace.si.edu/exhibitions/america-by-air/online/innovation/innovation16.cfm |date=18 January 2014}} &quot;Ships of the Air&quot; referring to Pan Am's Boeing Clipper flying-boat fleet.&lt;/ref&gt;&amp;nbsp;— though none had yet been built. The advent of powered balloons, called dirigible balloons, and later of rigid hulls allowing a great increase in size, began to change the way these words were used. Huge powered aerostats, characterized by a [[rigid airship|rigid]] outer framework and separate aerodynamic skin surrounding the gas bags, were produced, the [[Zeppelin]]s being the largest and most famous. There were still no fixed-wing aircraft or non-rigid balloons large enough to be called airships, so &quot;airship&quot; came to be synonymous with these aircraft. Then several accidents, such as the [[Hindenburg disaster]] in 1937, led to the demise of these airships. Nowadays a &quot;balloon&quot; is an unpowered aerostat and an &quot;airship&quot; is a powered one.

A powered, steerable aerostat is called a ''[[Airship|dirigible]]''. Sometimes this term is applied only to non-rigid balloons, and sometimes ''dirigible balloon'' is regarded as the definition of an airship (which may then be rigid or non-rigid). Non-rigid dirigibles are characterized by a moderately aerodynamic gasbag with stabilizing fins at the back. These soon became known as ''[[blimp]]s''. During [[World War II]], this shape was widely adopted for [[Barrage balloon|tethered balloons]]; in windy weather, this both reduces the strain on the tether and stabilizes the balloon. The nickname ''blimp'' was adopted along with the shape. In modern times, any small dirigible or airship is called a blimp, though a blimp may be unpowered as well as powered.

=== Heavier-than-air – aerodynes{{Anchor|Heavier than air}} ===
&lt;!-- Note: there are links to this section from other articles --&gt;
Heavier-than-air aircraft, such as [[airplane]]s, must find some way to push air or gas downwards, so that a reaction occurs (by Newton's laws of motion) to push the aircraft upwards. This dynamic movement through the air is the origin of the term ''aerodyne''. There are two ways to produce dynamic upthrust&amp;nbsp;— [[aerodynamics|aerodynamic lift]], and [[powered lift]] in the form of engine thrust.

Aerodynamic lift involving [[wing]]s is the most common, with [[fixed-wing aircraft]] being kept in the air by the forward movement of wings, and [[rotorcraft]] by spinning wing-shaped rotors sometimes called rotary wings. A wing is a flat, horizontal surface, usually shaped in cross-section as an [[airfoil|aerofoil]]. To fly, air must flow over the wing and generate [[Lift (force)|lift]]. A ''flexible wing'' is a wing made of fabric or thin sheet material, often stretched over a rigid frame. A ''[[kite]]'' is tethered to the ground and relies on the speed of the wind over its wings, which may be flexible or rigid, fixed, or rotary.

With powered lift, the aircraft directs its engine thrust [[Vertical and horizontal|vertically]] downward. [[V/STOL]] aircraft, such as the [[Harrier Jump Jet]] and [[Lockheed Martin F-35 Lightning II#F-35B|Lockheed Martin F-35B]] take off and land vertically using powered lift and transfer to aerodynamic lift in steady flight.

A pure [[rocket]] is not usually regarded as an aerodyne, because it does not depend on the air for its lift (and can even fly into space); however, many aerodynamic lift vehicles have been powered or assisted by rocket motors. Rocket-powered missiles that obtain aerodynamic lift at very high speed due to airflow over their bodies are a marginal case.

==== Fixed-wing ====
{{Main|fixed-wing aircraft}}
[[File:Emirates Airbus A380-861 A6-EER MUC 2015 04.jpg|thumb|An [[Airbus A380]], the world's largest passenger [[airliner]]]]
The forerunner of the fixed-wing aircraft is the [[kite]]. Whereas a fixed-wing aircraft relies on its forward speed to create airflow over the wings, a kite is tethered to the ground and relies on the [[wind]] blowing over its wings to provide lift. Kites were the first kind of aircraft to fly, and [[History of science and technology in China|were invented in China]] around 500 BC. Much aerodynamic research was done with kites before test aircraft, [[wind tunnel]]s, and computer modelling programs became available.

The first heavier-than-air craft capable of controlled free-flight were [[glider (aircraft)|gliders]]. A glider designed by [[George Cayley]] carried out the first true manned, controlled flight in 1853.

The practical, powered, fixed-wing aircraft (the [[airplane]] or aeroplane) was invented by [[Wright brothers|Wilbur and Orville Wright]]. Besides the method of [[#Propulsion|propulsion]], fixed-wing aircraft are in general characterized by their [[wing configuration]]. The most important wing characteristics are:
* Number of wings&amp;nbsp;— [[monoplane]], [[biplane]], etc.
* Wing support&amp;nbsp;— Braced or cantilever, rigid, or flexible.
* Wing planform&amp;nbsp;— including [[aspect ratio]], angle of [[Swept wing|sweep]], and any variations along the span (including the important class of [[delta wing]]s).
* Location of the horizontal stabilizer, if any.
* [[Dihedral (aeronautics)|Dihedral angle]]&amp;nbsp;— positive, zero, or negative (anhedral).

A [[Wing configuration#Variable geometry|variable geometry]] aircraft can change its wing configuration during flight.

A ''[[flying wing]]'' has no fuselage, though it may have small blisters or pods. The opposite of this is a ''[[lifting body]]'', which has no wings, though it may have small stabilizing and control surfaces.

[[Ground-effect vehicle|Wing-in-ground-effect]] vehicles are not considered aircraft. They &quot;fly&quot; efficiently close to the surface of the ground or water, like conventional aircraft during takeoff. An example is the Russian ekranoplan (nicknamed the &quot;Caspian Sea Monster&quot;). [[History of human-powered aircraft|Man-powered aircraft]] also rely on [[Ground effect (aerodynamics)|ground effect]] to remain airborne with a minimal pilot power, but this is only because they are so underpowered—in fact, the airframe is capable of flying higher.
[[File:Flightline at Kabul International Airport.jpeg|thumb| Aircraft parked on the ground in Afghanistan]]

==== Rotorcraft ====
{{Main|Rotorcraft}}
[[File:20100627 Xenon2 Krakow 1328.jpg|thumb|An [[autogyro]]]]
Rotorcraft, or rotary-wing aircraft, use a spinning rotor with aerofoil section blades (a ''rotary wing'') to provide lift. Types include [[helicopter]]s, [[autogyro]]s, and various hybrids such as [[gyrodyne]]s and compound rotorcraft.

''[[Helicopter]]s'' have a rotor turned by an engine-driven shaft. The rotor pushes air downward to create lift. By tilting the rotor forward, the downward flow is tilted backward, producing thrust for forward flight. Some helicopters have more than one rotor and a few have rotors turned by gas jets at the tips.

''[[Autogyro]]s'' have unpowered rotors, with a separate power plant to provide thrust. The rotor is tilted backward. As the autogyro moves forward, air blows upward across the rotor, making it spin. This spinning increases the speed of airflow over the rotor, to provide lift. [[Rotor kite]]s are unpowered autogyros, which are towed to give them forward speed or tethered to a static anchor in high-wind for kited flight.

''[[Cyclogyro]]s'' rotate their wings about a horizontal axis.

''Compound rotorcraft'' have wings that provide some or all of the lift in forward flight. They are nowadays classified as ''[[powered lift]]'' types and not as rotorcraft. ''[[Tiltrotor]]'' aircraft (such as the [[Bell Boeing V-22 Osprey]]), [[tiltwing]], [[tail-sitter]], and [[coleopter]] aircraft have their rotors/[[Propeller (aeronautics)|propellers]] horizontal for vertical flight and vertical for forward flight.

==== Other methods of lift ====
[[File:X-24B on Lakebed - GPN-2000-000209.jpg|thumb|X-24B lifting body.]]
* A ''[[lifting body]]'' is an aircraft body shaped to produce lift. If there are any wings, they are too small to provide significant lift and are used only for stability and control. Lifting bodies are not efficient: they suffer from high drag, and must also travel at high speed to generate enough lift to fly. Many of the research prototypes, such as the [[Martin Marietta X-24]], which led up to the [[Space Shuttle]], were lifting bodies, though the Space Shuttle is not, and some [[Supersonic speed|supersonic]] [[missile]]s obtain lift from the airflow over a tubular body.
* ''[[Powered lift]]'' types rely on engine-derived lift for vertical takeoff and landing ([[VTOL]]). Most types transition to fixed-wing lift for horizontal flight. Classes of powered lift types include [[VTOL]] jet aircraft (such as the [[Harrier Jump Jet]]) and [[tiltrotor]]s, such as the [[Bell Boeing V-22 Osprey]], among others. A few experimental designs rely entirely on engine thrust to provide lift throughout the whole flight, including personal fan-lift hover platforms and jetpacks. [[VTOL]] research designs include the [[Rolls-Royce Thrust Measuring Rig]].
* The ''[[Flettner airplane]]'' uses a rotating cylinder in place of a fixed wing, obtaining lift from the [[Magnus effect]].
* The ''[[ornithopter]]'' obtains thrust by flapping its wings.

== Scale, sizes and speeds ==
=== Sizes ===
The '''smallest aircraft''' are toys/recreational items, and even smaller, [[nano-aircraft]].

The '''largest aircraft by dimensions and volume''' (as of 2016) is the 302-foot-long (about 95 meters) British [[Airlander 10]], a hybrid blimp, with helicopter and fixed-wing features, and reportedly capable of speeds up to 90&amp;nbsp;mph (about 150&amp;nbsp;km/h), and an airborne endurance of two weeks with a payload of up to 22,050 pounds (11 tons).&lt;ref name=&quot;airlander_2016_08_18_telegraph_co_uk&quot;&gt;[https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/2016/08/17/worlds-largest-aircraft-the-airlander-takes-first-flight/ &quot;World's largest aircraft the Airlander makes maiden flight in UK,&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161122224818/http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/2016/08/17/worlds-largest-aircraft-the-airlander-takes-first-flight/ |date=22 November 2016}} 16 August 2016, London 'Daily Telegraph' via Telegraph.co.uk, retrieved 22 November 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;airlander_2016_08_19_cbs_news&quot;&gt;[&quot;Airlander 10, the world's largest aircraft, takes off for the first time,&quot;] 19 August 2016, CBS News(TV) retrieved 22 November 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;airlander_crash_2016_08_24_cnn&quot;&gt;Kottasova, Ivana [http://money.cnn.com/2016/08/24/technology/worlds-largest-aircraft-crash-airlander-10/ &quot;The world's largest aircraft crashes after 2nd test flight&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161122224325/http://money.cnn.com/2016/08/24/technology/worlds-largest-aircraft-crash-airlander-10/ |date=22 November 2016}}, 24 August 2016, ''CNN Tech'' on [[CNN]], the Cable News Network, retrieved 22 November 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;

The '''largest aircraft by weight''' and '''largest regular fixed-wing aircraft''' ever built, {{as of|2016|lc=y}}, is the [[Antonov An-225 Mriya|Antonov An-225 ''Mriya'']]. That Ukrainian-built six-engine Russian transport of the 1980s is 84 meters (276 feet) long, with an 88-meter (289 foot) wingspan. It holds the world payload record, after transporting 428,834 pounds (200 tons) of goods, and has recently flown 100-ton loads commercially. Weighing in at somewhere between 1.1 and 1.4 million pounds (550–700 tons) maximum loaded weight, it is also the heaviest aircraft to be built, to date. It can cruise at 500&amp;nbsp;mph.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last1=July|first1=Dyre|title=Fly Drive Aanbiedingen |url=https://www.flydrivereizen.nl/aanbiedingen/|website=www.flydrivereizen.nl|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20161104014121/https://www.flydrivereizen.nl/aanbiedingen/|archivedate=4 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;watch_worlds_biggest_2016_05_16_foxnews&quot;&gt;[http://www.foxnews.com/tech/2016/05/16/watch-worlds-biggest-plane-land-in-australia.html &quot;Watch the world's biggest plane land in Australia,&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161122072300/http://www.foxnews.com/tech/2016/05/16/watch-worlds-biggest-plane-land-in-australia.html |date=22 November 2016}} 16 May 2016, Fox News, retrieved 22 November 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;worlds_biggest_airplane_2016_11_18_chron_com&quot;&gt;Rumbaugh, Andrea, [http://www.chron.com/business/article/World-s-largest-airplane-lands-at-Bush-airport-10622046.php#item-38488 &quot;World's biggest airplane lands at Bush airport,&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161123052928/http://www.chron.com/business/article/World-s-largest-airplane-lands-at-Bush-airport-10622046.php |date=23 November 2016}} Updated 18 November 2016, ''Houston Chonicle'' / Chron.com, retrieved 22 November 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;worlds_largest_might_lose_smithsonian_2015&quot;&gt;Lewis, Danny, [http://www.smithsonianmag.com/smart-news/worlds-largest-aircraft-might-lose-its-title-blimp-180956677/ &quot;The World's Largest Aircraft Might Lose its Title to a Blimp,&quot;], 18 September 2015, ''Smart News'', Smithsonian.com, [[Smithsonian Institution]], Washington, D.C., retrieved 22 November 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;largest_plane_aerospaceweb_org&quot;&gt;[http://www.aerospaceweb.org/question/design/q0188.shtml &quot;Ask Us – Largest Plane in the World,&quot;] Aerospaceweb.org, retrieved 22 November 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;

The '''largest military airplanes''' are the Ukrainian/Russian [[Antonov An-124 Ruslan|Antonov An-124 ''Ruslan'']] (world's second-largest airplane, also used as a civilian transport),&lt;ref name=&quot;worlds_2nd_largest_aircraft_nasa&quot;&gt;[https://www.nasa.gov/centers/glenn/multimedia/imagegallery/image_feature_028_Antonov.html &quot;World's Second Largest Aircraft,&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161122222701/https://www.nasa.gov/centers/glenn/multimedia/imagegallery/image_feature_028_Antonov.html |date=22 November 2016}} 28 July 2013, [[NASA]], retrieved 22 November 2016.&lt;/ref&gt; and American [[Lockheed C-5 Galaxy]] transport, weighing, loaded, over 765,000 pounds (over 380 tons).&lt;ref name=&quot;largest_plane_aerospaceweb_org&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;wide_body_transports_loftin_nasa&quot;&gt;Loftin, Laurence K., Jr., [https://history.nasa.gov/SP-468/ch13-5.htm &quot;Wide-Body Transports&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130607034616/http://history.nasa.gov/SP-468/ch13-5.htm |date=7 June 2013}}, in Chapter 13, &quot;Jet Transports,&quot; in Part II, &quot;The Jet Age,&quot; in ''Quest for Performance: The Evolution of Modern Aircraft'', NASA SP-468, 1985, Scientific and Technical Information Branch, [[NASA]], Washington, D.C., Updated: 6 August 2004, retrieved 22 November 2016.&lt;/ref&gt; The 8-engine, piston/propeller [[Hughes H-4 Hercules|Hughes H-4 ''Hercules'']] &quot;Spruce Goose&quot;&amp;nbsp;— an American [[World War II]] wooden flying boat transport with a greater wingspan (94 meters / 260 feet) than any current aircraft and a tail height equal to the tallest (Airbus A380-800 at 24.1 meters / 78 feet)&amp;nbsp;— flew only one short hop in the late 1940s and never flew out of [[Ground effect (aerodynamics)|ground effect]].&lt;ref name=&quot;largest_plane_aerospaceweb_org&quot; /&gt;

The '''largest civilian airplanes,''' apart from the above-noted An-225 and An-124, are the [[Airbus Beluga]] cargo transport derivative of the [[Airbus A300]] jet airliner, the [[Boeing Dreamlifter]] cargo transport derivative of the [[Boeing 747]] jet airliner/transport (the 747-200B was, at its creation in the 1960s, the heaviest aircraft ever built, with a maximum weight of 836,000 pounds (over 400 tons)),&lt;ref name=&quot;wide_body_transports_loftin_nasa&quot; /&gt; and the double-decker [[Airbus A380]] &quot;super-jumbo&quot; jet airliner (the world's '''largest passenger airliner''').&lt;ref name=&quot;largest_plane_aerospaceweb_org&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;airbus_reviews_2008_04_29_ny_times&quot;&gt;[https://www.nytimes.com/2008/04/29/business/worldbusiness/29iht-airbus.4.12438349.html &quot;Airbus reviews A380 schedule,&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170202002211/http://www.nytimes.com/2008/04/29/business/worldbusiness/29iht-airbus.4.12438349.html |date=2 February 2017}} 29 April 2008, ''[[The New York Times]]'', retrieved 22 November 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Main|List of large aircraft}}

=== Speeds ===
The '''fastest recorded powered aircraft flight''' and '''fastest recorded aircraft flight of an air-breathing powered aircraft''' was of the [[NASA X-43]]A ''Pegasus'', a [[scramjet]]-powered, [[Hypersonic speed|hypersonic]], [[lifting body]] experimental research aircraft, at '''[[Mach number|Mach]] 9.6 (nearly 7,000&amp;nbsp;mph).''' The X-43A set that new mark, and broke its own world record of Mach 6.3, nearly 5,000&amp;nbsp;mph, set in March 2004, on its third and final flight on 16 November 2004.&lt;ref name=&quot;x43_nasa&quot;&gt;[https://www.nasa.gov/missions/research/x43-main.html &quot;Hypersonic X-43A Takes Flight.htm,&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161102015325/http://www.nasa.gov/missions/research/x43-main.html |date=2 November 2016}} [[NASA]] retrieved November 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;fastest_air_breathing_2016_12_guinness&quot;&gt;[http://www.guinnessworldrecords.com/world-records/fastest-aircraft-air-breathing-engine &quot;Fastest aircraft, air-breathing engine,&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161220091658/http://www.guinnessworldrecords.com/world-records/fastest-aircraft-air-breathing-engine |date=20 December 2016}} Guinness World Records, retrieved 2 December 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;

Prior to the X-43A, the '''fastest recorded powered airplane flight''' (and still the record for the '''fastest manned, powered airplane''' / '''fastest manned, non-spacecraft aircraft''') was of the [[North American X-15|North American X-15A-2]], '''rocket-powered airplane''' at 4,520&amp;nbsp;mph (7,274&amp;nbsp;km/h), Mach 6.72, on 3 October 1967. On one flight it reached an altitude of 354,300 feet.&lt;ref name=&quot;aircraft_speed_records_aerospaceweb_org&quot;&gt;Jackson, Doug, [http://www.aerospaceweb.org/question/performance/q0023.shtml &quot;Ask Us – Aircraft Speed Records,&quot;] 22 April 2001, Aerospaceweb.org, retrieved 22 November 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;fastest_manned_non_spacecraft_2016_12_guinness&quot;&gt;[http://www.guinnessworldrecords.com/world-records/fastest-speed-in-a-non-spacecraft-aircraft &quot;Fastest speed in a non-spacecraft aircraft,&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161220054424/http://www.guinnessworldrecords.com/world-records/fastest-speed-in-a-non-spacecraft-aircraft |date=20 December 2016}} Guinness World Records, retrieved 2 December 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;fastest_airplanes_2014_09_17_flying_magz&quot;&gt;Bergqvist, Pia, [http://www.flyingmag.com/aircraft/fastest-aircraft-top-performers-their-class &quot;Fastest Airplanes: Top Performers in Their Class,&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170903072940/http://www.flyingmag.com/aircraft/fastest-aircraft-top-performers-their-class |date=3 September 2017}} 17 September 2014, ''[[Flying (magazine)|Flying]]'', retrieved 3 December 2016&lt;/ref&gt;

The '''fastest known, production aircraft''' (other than rockets and missiles) currently or formerly operational (as of 2016) are:
* The fastest '''fixed-wing aircraft,''' and '''fastest glider,''' is the [[Space Shuttle]], a rocket-glider hybrid, which has re-entered the atmosphere as a fixed-wing glider at more than Mach 25&amp;nbsp;— ver 25 times the speed of sound, about 17,000&amp;nbsp;mph at re-entry to Earth's atmosphere.&lt;ref name=&quot;aircraft_speed_records_aerospaceweb_org&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;speed_regimes_nasa&quot;&gt;Benson, Tom, ed., [https://www.grc.nasa.gov/WWW/BGH/hihyper.html &quot;Speed Regimes: Hypersonic Re-Entry,&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161123052843/https://www.grc.nasa.gov/WWW/BGH/hihyper.html |date=23 November 2016}} Glenn Research Center, [[NASA]], retrieved 22 November 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;
* The fastest '''military airplane''' ever built: [[Lockheed SR-71 Blackbird]], a U.S. [[reconnaissance]] jet fixed-wing aircraft, known to fly beyond Mach 3.3 (about 2,200&amp;nbsp;mph at cruising altitude). On 28 July 1976, an SR-71 set the record for the '''fastest and highest-flying operational aircraft''' with an '''absolute speed record of 2,193&amp;nbsp;mph''' and an '''absolute altitude record of 85,068 feet.''' At its retirement in the January 1990, it was the '''fastest air-breathing aircraft''' / '''fastest jet aircraft''' in the world, a record still standing {{as of|August 2016|lc=y}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;aircraft_speed_records_aerospaceweb_org&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.nasa.gov/centers/armstrong/news/FactSheets/FS-030-DFRC.html &quot;NASA Armstrong Fact Sheet: SR-71 Blackbird&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161123054447/https://www.nasa.gov/centers/armstrong/news/FactSheets/FS-030-DFRC.html |date=23 November 2016}} NASA. Retrieved 22 November 2016&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;lockheed_2015_05_29_usaf_museum&quot;&gt;
[http://www.nationalmuseum.af.mil/Visit/MuseumExhibits/FactSheets/Display/tabid/509/Article/198054/lockheed-sr-71a.aspx &quot;Lockheed SR-71A,&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161220161807/http://www.nationalmuseum.af.mil/Visit/MuseumExhibits/FactSheets/Display/tabid/509/Article/198054/lockheed-sr-71a.aspx |date=20 December 2016}} display notes, 29 May 2015, [[National Museum of the United States Air Force]] retrieved 2 December 2016&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;sr71_gone_2016_12_02_usaf&quot;&gt;Trujillo, Staff Sgt. Robert M.,[http://www.beale.af.mil/News/ArticleDisplay/tabid/6961/Article/667024/sr-71-blackbird-gone-but-not-forgotten.aspx &quot;SR-71 Blackbird: Gone but not forgotten,&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161220030831/http://www.beale.af.mil/News/ArticleDisplay/tabid/6961/Article/667024/sr-71-blackbird-gone-but-not-forgotten.aspx |date=20 December 2016}} 26 January 2016, 9th Reconnaissance Wing Public Affairs, U.S. Air Force, retrieved 2 December 2016&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;absolute_speed_record_2016_07_27_ga_news&quot;&gt;&quot;Absolute speed record still stands 40 years later,&quot; 27 July 2016 ''General Aviation News'', retrieved 22 November 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;sr71_pilots_2016_08_06_usaf&quot;&gt;Woolen, Angela, [http://www.af.mil/News/ArticleDisplay/tabid/223/Article/909026/sr-71-pilots-crew-relive-absolute-speed-record.aspx &quot;SR-71 pilots, crew relive absolute speed record,&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161220031451/http://www.af.mil/News/ArticleDisplay/tabid/223/Article/909026/sr-71-pilots-crew-relive-absolute-speed-record.aspx |date=20 December 2016}} 9 August 2016, 78th Air Base Wing Public Affairs, United States Air Force, retrieved 2 December 2016&lt;/ref&gt;
:Note: Some sources refer to the above-mentioned X-15 as the &quot;fastest military airplane&quot; because it was partly a project of the U.S. Navy and Air Force; however, the X-15 was not used in non-experimental actual military operations.&lt;ref name=&quot;fastest_airplanes_2014_09_17_flying_magz&quot; /&gt;
* The '''fastest current military aircraft''' are the Soviet/Russian [[Mikoyan-Gurevich MiG-25]]&amp;nbsp;— capable of Mach 3.2 (2,170&amp;nbsp;mph), at the expense of engine damage, or Mach 2.83 (1,920&amp;nbsp;mph) normally&amp;nbsp;— and the Russian [[Mikoyan MiG-31]]E (also capable of Mach 2.83 normally). Both are fighter-interceptor jet airplanes, in active operations as of 2016.&lt;ref name=&quot;9_fastest_planes_2015_09_18_business_insider&quot;&gt;
Bender, Jeremy and Amanda Macias, [http://www.businessinsider.com/the-9-fastest-piloted-planes-in-the-world-2015-9/#mikoyan-gurevich-mig-25-foxbat-7 &quot;The 9 fastest piloted planes in the world,&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161220032130/http://www.businessinsider.com/the-9-fastest-piloted-planes-in-the-world-2015-9/ |date=20 December 2016}} 18 September 2015, ''Business Insider'', retrieved 3 December 2016&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;fast_and_furious_2016_business_insider&quot;&gt;[http://www.airforce-technology.com/features/featurefast-and-furious---the-worlds-fastest-military-aircraft-4214937/ &quot;Fast and furious&amp;nbsp;— the world's fastest military aircraft,&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161220031242/http://www.airforce-technology.com/features/featurefast-and-furious---the-worlds-fastest-military-aircraft-4214937/ |date=20 December 2016}} ''Airforce Technology'', retrieved 3 December 2016&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;five_fastest_military_2016_bloomberg&quot;&gt;[https://www.bloomberg.com/news/videos/b/b8c1600e-38db-4bca-aed1-ccb4539f91dc The Five Fastest Military Jets Ever Made&quot;,&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160806085553/http://www.bloomberg.com/news/videos/b/b8c1600e-38db-4bca-aed1-ccb4539f91dc |date=6 August 2016}} 2016, Bloomberg, retrieved 3 December 2016&lt;/ref&gt;
* The fastest '''civilian airplane''' ever built, and '''fastest passenger airliner''' ever built: the briefly operated [[Tupolev Tu-144]] supersonic jet airliner (Mach 2.35, 1,600&amp;nbsp;mph, 2,587&amp;nbsp;km/h), which was believed to cruise at about Mach 2.2. The Tu-144 (officially operated from 1968 to 1978, ending after two crashes of the small fleet) was outlived by its rival, the ''[[Concorde]]'' (Mach 2.23), a French/British supersonic airliner, known to cruise at Mach 2.02 (1.450&amp;nbsp;mph, 2,333 kmh at cruising altitude), operating from 1976 until the small Concorde fleet was grounded permanently in 2003, following the crash of one in the early 2000s.&lt;ref name=&quot;aircraft_speed_records_aerospaceweb_org&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;fastest_airplanes_2014_09_17_flying_magz&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;fastest_airliner_aerospaceweb_org&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;fastest_airliner_2016_12_guinness&quot;&gt;[http://www.guinnessworldrecords.com/world-records/fastest-aircraft-airliner &quot;Fastest aircraft, airliner,&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161220164223/http://www.guinnessworldrecords.com/world-records/fastest-aircraft-airliner |date=20 December 2016}} Guinness World Records, retrieved 2 December. 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;
* The fastest '''civilian airplane currently flying''': the [[Cessna Citation X]], an American business jet, capable of Mach 0.935 (over 600&amp;nbsp;mph at cruising altitude). Its rival, the American [[Gulfstream G650]] business jet, can reach Mach 0.925&lt;ref name=&quot;aircraft_speed_records_aerospaceweb_org&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;fastest_airplanes_2014_09_17_flying_magz&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Whitfield, Bethany, [http://www.flyingmag.com/aircraft/jets/cessna-citation-ten-chases-mach-0935-top-speed &quot;Cessna Citation Ten Chases Mach 0.935 Top Speed: Jet would retake speed prize from G650,&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160720144729/http://www.flyingmag.com/aircraft/jets/cessna-citation-ten-chases-mach-0935-top-speed |date=20 July 2016}} 28 August 2012, ''[[Flying (magazine)|Flying]]'', retrieved 22 November 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;cessna_rolls_out_2016_04_15_wbj&quot;&gt;[http://www.bizjournals.com/wichita/news/2013/04/15/cessna-rolls-out-first-production-unit.html &quot;Cessna rolls out first production unit of new Citation X,&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161122221443/http://www.bizjournals.com/wichita/news/2013/04/15/cessna-rolls-out-first-production-unit.html |date=22 November 2016}} 15 April 2013, ''Wichita Business Journal'', retrieved 22 November 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;
* The fastest '''airliner currently flying''' is the [[Boeing 747]], quoted as being capable of cruising over Mach 0.885 (over 550&amp;nbsp;mph). Previously, the fastest were the troubled, short-lived Russian (Soviet Union) [[Tupolev Tu-144]] SST (Mach 2.35) and the French/British ''Concorde'' (Mach 2.23, normally cruising at Mach 2) .&lt;ref name=&quot;aircraft_speed_records_aerospaceweb_org&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;fastest_airliner_aerospaceweb_org&quot;&gt;[http://www.aerospaceweb.org/question/design/q0188.shtml &quot;Ask Us – Fastest Airliner and Area Rule,&quot;] Aerospaceweb.org, retrieved 22 November 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;fastest_airliner_2016_12_guinness&quot; /&gt; Before them, the [[Convair 990 Coronado]] jet airliner of the 1960s flew at over 600&amp;nbsp;mph.
{{Main|Flight airspeed record}}

== Propulsion ==
=== Unpowered aircraft ===
{{Main|Unpowered aircraft}}
[[Glider (aircraft)|Gliders]] are heavier-than-air aircraft that do not employ propulsion once airborne. Take-off may be by launching forward and downward from a high location, or by pulling into the air on a tow-line, either by a ground-based winch or vehicle, or by a powered &quot;tug&quot; aircraft. For a glider to maintain its forward air speed and lift, it must descend in relation to the air (but not necessarily in relation to the ground). Many gliders can &quot;soar&quot;, ''i.e.'', gain height from updrafts such as thermal currents. The first practical, controllable example was designed and built by the British scientist and pioneer [[George Cayley]], whom many recognise as the first aeronautical engineer. Common examples of gliders are [[Glider (sailplane)|sailplanes]], [[Hang gliding|hang gliders]] and [[Paragliding|paragliders]].

[[Balloon (aeronautics)|Balloons]] drift with the wind, though normally the pilot can control the altitude, either by heating the air or by releasing ballast, giving some directional control (since the wind direction changes with altitude). A wing-shaped hybrid balloon can glide directionally when rising or falling; but a spherically shaped balloon does not have such directional control.

[[Kite]]s are aircraft&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.grc.nasa.gov/WWW/K-12/airplane/guided.htm|title=Guided Tours of the BGA|work=nasa.gov|access-date=1 April 2015|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150325054529/http://www.grc.nasa.gov/WWW/K-12/airplane/guided.htm|archivedate=25 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; that are tethered to the ground or other object (fixed or mobile) that maintains tension in the tether or [[kite line]]; they rely on virtual or real wind blowing over and under them to generate lift and drag. [[Kytoon]]s are balloon-kite hybrids that are shaped and tethered to obtain kiting deflections, and can be lighter-than-air, neutrally buoyant, or heavier-than-air.

=== Powered aircraft ===
{{Main|Powered aircraft}}
Powered aircraft have one or more onboard sources of mechanical power, typically [[aircraft engine]]s although rubber and manpower have also been used. Most aircraft engines are either lightweight [[reciprocating engine]]s or [[gas turbine]]s. Engine fuel is stored in tanks, usually in the wings but larger aircraft also have additional [[fuel tank]]s in the [[fuselage]].

==== Propeller aircraft ====
{{Main|Powered aircraft#Propeller aircraft}}
[[File:WestCoastAirFloatplane.jpg|thumb|A [[turboprop]]-engined [[De Havilland Canada DHC-6 Twin Otter|DeHavilland Twin Otter]] adapted as a [[Seaplane|floatplane]]]]

[[Powered aircraft#Propeller aircraft|Propeller aircraft]] use one or more [[Propeller (aeronautics)|propellers]] (airscrews) to create thrust in a forward direction. The propeller is usually mounted in front of the power source in ''[[tractor configuration]]'' but can be mounted behind in ''[[pusher configuration]]''. Variations of propeller layout include ''[[contra-rotating propellers]]'' and ''[[ducted fan]]s''.

Many kinds of power plant have been used to drive propellers. Early airships used man power or [[Steam aircraft|steam engines]]. The more practical [[Internal combustion engine|internal combustion piston engine]] was used for virtually all fixed-wing aircraft until [[World War II]] and is still used in many smaller aircraft. Some types use turbine engines to drive a propeller in the form of a [[turboprop]] or [[propfan]]. [[History of human-powered aircraft|Human-powered flight]] has been achieved, but has not become a practical means of transport. Unmanned aircraft and models have also used power sources such as [[Electric aircraft|electric motors]] and rubber bands.

==== Jet aircraft ====
{{Main|Jet aircraft}}
[[File:Lockheed Martin F-22A Raptor JSOH.jpg|thumb| [[Lockheed Martin F-22 Raptor|Lockheed Martin F-22A Raptor]]]]

[[Jet aircraft]] use [[airbreathing jet engine]]s, which take in air, burn fuel with it in a [[combustion chamber]], and accelerate the exhaust rearwards to provide thrust.

[[Turbojet]] and [[turbofan]] engines use a spinning turbine to drive one or more fans, which provide additional thrust. An [[afterburner]] may be used to inject extra fuel into the hot exhaust, especially on military &quot;fast jets&quot;. Use of a turbine is not absolutely necessary: other designs include the [[pulsejet]] and [[ramjet]]. These mechanically simple designs cannot work when stationary, so the aircraft must be launched to flying speed by some other method. Other variants have also been used, including the [[motorjet]] and hybrids such as the [[Pratt &amp; Whitney J58]], which can convert between turbojet and ramjet operation.

Compared to propellers, jet engines can provide much higher thrust, higher speeds and, above about {{Convert|40000|ft|m|abbr=on}}, greater efficiency.&lt;ref name=hist8&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.hq.nasa.gov/pao/History/SP-468/ch10-3.htm|title=ch10-3|publisher=Hq.nasa.gov|access-date=26 March 2010|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100914184628/http://www.hq.nasa.gov/pao/History/SP-468/ch10-3.htm|archivedate=14 September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; They are also much more fuel-efficient than [[rocket]]s. As a consequence nearly all large, high-speed or high-altitude aircraft use jet engines.

==== Rotorcraft ====
{{Main|Rotorcraft}}
Some rotorcraft, such as [[helicopter]]s, have a powered rotary wing or ''rotor'', where the rotor disc can be angled slightly forward so that a proportion of its lift is directed forwards. The rotor may, like a propeller, be powered by a variety of methods such as a piston engine or turbine. Experiments have also used [[Tip jet|jet nozzles at the rotor blade tips]].

==== Other types of powered aircraft ====
* ''[[Rocket-powered aircraft]]'' have occasionally been experimented with, and the [[Messerschmitt Me 163 Komet|Messerschmitt Me 163 ''Komet'']] fighter even saw action in the Second World War. Since then, they have been restricted to research aircraft, such as the [[North American X-15]], which traveled up into space where air-breathing engines cannot work (rockets carry their own oxidant). Rockets have more often been used as a supplement to the main power plant, typically for the [[JATO|rocket-assisted take off]] of heavily loaded aircraft, but also to provide high-speed dash capability in some hybrid designs such as the [[Saunders-Roe SR.53]].
* The ''[[ornithopter]]'' obtains thrust by flapping its wings. It has found practical use in a [[Ornithopter#Applications for unmanned ornithopters|model hawk]] used to freeze prey animals into stillness so that they can be captured, and in toy birds.

== Design and construction ==
Aircraft are [[aircraft design process|designed]] according to many factors such as customer and manufacturer demand, [[Aviation safety|safety]] protocols and physical and economic constraints. For many types of aircraft the design process is regulated by national airworthiness authorities.

The key parts of an aircraft are generally divided into three categories:
* The ''structure'' comprises the main load-bearing elements and associated equipment.
* The ''propulsion system'' (if it is powered) comprises the power source and associated equipment, as described above.
* The ''avionics'' comprise the control, navigation and communication systems, usually electrical in nature.

=== Structure ===
The approach to structural design varies widely between different types of aircraft. Some, such as paragliders, comprise only flexible materials that act in tension and rely on aerodynamic pressure to hold their shape. A [[Balloon (aeronautics)|balloon]] similarly relies on internal gas pressure, but may have a rigid basket or gondola slung below it to carry its payload. Early aircraft, including [[airship]]s, often employed flexible [[Aircraft dope|doped]] [[aircraft fabric covering]] to give a reasonably smooth aeroshell stretched over a rigid frame. Later aircraft employed semi-[[monocoque]] techniques, where the skin of the aircraft is stiff enough to share much of the flight loads. In a true monocoque design there is no internal structure left.

The key structural parts of an aircraft depend on what type it is.

==== Aerostats ====
{{Main|Aerostat}}
Lighter-than-air types are characterised by one or more gasbags, typically with a supporting structure of flexible cables or a rigid framework called its hull. Other elements such as engines or a gondola may also be attached to the supporting structure.

==== Aerodynes ====
[[File:Merlin Airframe Material.jpg|thumb|Airframe diagram for an [[AgustaWestland AW101]] [[helicopter]]]]
Heavier-than-air types are characterised by one or more wings and a central [[fuselage]]. The fuselage typically also carries a tail or [[empennage]] for stability and control, and an undercarriage for takeoff and landing. Engines may be located on the fuselage or wings. On a [[fixed-wing aircraft]] the wings are rigidly attached to the fuselage, while on a [[rotorcraft]] the wings are attached to a rotating vertical shaft. Smaller designs sometimes use flexible materials for part or all of the structure, held in place either by a rigid frame or by air pressure. The fixed parts of the structure comprise the [[airframe]].

=== Avionics ===
{{Main|Avionics}}
The avionics comprise the [[aircraft flight control system]]s and related equipment, including the [[cockpit]] instrumentation, navigation, [[radar]], monitoring, and [[communications system]]s.

== Flight characteristics ==
=== Flight envelope ===
{{Main|Flight envelope}}
The flight envelope of an aircraft refers to its approved design capabilities in terms of [[airspeed]], [[Load factor (aeronautics)|load factor]] and altitude.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://ecfr.gpoaccess.gov/cgi/t/text/text-idx?type=simple;c=ecfr;cc=ecfr;sid=a8f38006e777ba46ba8000f7c2fe6641;region=DIV1;q1=23.335;rgn=div8;view=text;idno=14;node=14%3A1.0.1.3.10.3.70.8|title=eCFR&amp;nbsp;— Code of Federal Regulations|work=gpoaccess.gov|access-date=1 April 2015|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120402202400/http://ecfr.gpoaccess.gov/cgi/t/text/text-idx?type=simple%3Bc%3Decfr%3Bcc%3Decfr%3Bsid%3Da8f38006e777ba46ba8000f7c2fe6641%3Bregion%3DDIV1%3Bq1%3D23.335%3Brgn%3Ddiv8%3Bview%3Dtext%3Bidno%3D14%3Bnode%3D14%3A1.0.1.3.10.3.70.8|archivedate=2 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100601204507/http://www.access.gpo.gov/ecfr/graphics/pdfs/ec28se91.001.pdf|title=Wayback Machine|date=1 June 2010|website=web.archive.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; The term can also refer to other assessments of aircraft performance such as maneuverability. When an aircraft is abused, for instance by diving it at too-high a speed, it is said to be flown ''outside the envelope'', something considered foolhardy since it has been taken beyond the design limits which have been established by the manufacturer. Going beyond the envelope may have a known outcome such as [[Aeroelasticity#Flutter |flutter]] or entry to a non-recoverable spin (possible reasons for the boundary).

=== Range ===
[[File:Boeing 777-200LR banking over mountain.jpg|thumb|The [[Boeing 777#777-200LR|Boeing 777-200LR]] is one of the longest-range airliners, capable of flights of more than halfway around the world.]]
{{Main|Range (aeronautics)}}
The range is the distance an aircraft can fly between [[takeoff]] and [[landing]], as limited by the time it can remain airborne.

For a powered aircraft the time limit is determined by the fuel load and rate of consumption.

For an unpowered aircraft, the maximum flight time is limited by factors such as weather conditions and pilot endurance. Many aircraft types are restricted to daylight hours, while balloons are limited by their supply of lifting gas. The range can be seen as the average ground speed multiplied by the maximum time in the air.

The [[Airbus A350]] is now the longest range airliner.

=== Flight dynamics ===
{{Main|Flight dynamics (fixed-wing aircraft)}}
[[File:Flight dynamics with text.png|right|200px]]
'''Flight dynamics''' is the science of air vehicle orientation and control in three dimensions. The three critical flight dynamics parameters are the [[Angle of rotation|angles of rotation]] around [[Aircraft principal axes|three axes]] which pass through the vehicle's [[Center of mass#Center of gravity|center of gravity]], known as ''[[Aircraft principal axes#Pitch|pitch]]'', ''[[Aircraft principal axes#Roll|roll]],'' and ''[[Aircraft principal axes#Yaw|yaw]]''.
* Roll is a rotation about the longitudinal axis (equivalent to the rolling or [[Sailing#Heeling|heeling]] of a ship) giving an up-down movement of the wing tips measured by the roll or bank angle.
* Pitch is a rotation about the sideways horizontal axis giving an up-down movement of the aircraft nose measured by the [[angle of attack]].
* Yaw is a rotation about the vertical axis giving a side-to-side movement of the nose known as sideslip.

Flight dynamics is concerned with the stability and control of an aircraft's rotation about each of these axes.

==== Stability ====
[[File:Aircraft tail.JPG|thumb|The [[empennage]] of a [[Boeing 747|Boeing 747–200]]]]
An aircraft that is unstable tends to diverge from its intended flight path and so is difficult to fly. A very stable aircraft tends to stay on its flight path and is difficult to maneuver. Therefore, it is important for any design to achieve the desired degree of stability. Since the widespread use of digital computers, it is increasingly common for designs to be inherently unstable and rely on computerised control systems to provide artificial stability.

A fixed wing is typically unstable in  pitch, roll, and yaw. Pitch and yaw stabilities of conventional fixed wing designs require [[Stabilizer (aeronautics)|horizontal and vertical stabilisers]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Crane&quot;&gt;Crane, Dale: ''Dictionary of Aeronautical Terms, third edition'', p. 194. Aviation Supplies &amp; Academics, 1997. {{ISBN|1-56027-287-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;GroundUp&quot;&gt;Aviation Publishers Co. Limited, ''From the Ground Up'', p. 10 (27th revised edition) {{ISBN|0-9690054-9-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; which act similarly to the feathers on an arrow.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.airlines.org/ATAResources/Handbook/Pages/AirlineHandbookChapter5HowAircraftFly.aspx |title=Airline Handbook Chapter 5: How Aircraft Fly |work=Airline Handbook |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100620150339/http://airlines.org/ATAResources/Handbook/Pages/AirlineHandbookChapter5HowAircraftFly.aspx |archivedate=20 June 2010 |publisher=[[Airlines for America|Air Transport Association]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; These stabilizing surfaces allow equilibrium of aerodynamic forces and to stabilise the [[flight dynamics]] of pitch and yaw.&lt;ref name=&quot;Crane&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;GroundUp&quot; /&gt; They are usually mounted on the tail section ([[empennage]]), although in the [[Canard (aeronautics)|canard]] layout, the main aft wing replaces the canard foreplane as pitch stabilizer. [[Tandem wing]] and [[tailless aircraft]] rely on the same general rule to achieve stability, the aft surface being the stabilising one.

A rotary wing is typically unstable in yaw, requiring a vertical stabiliser.

A balloon is typically very stable in pitch and roll due to the way the payload is slung underneath the center of lift.

==== Control ====
[[Flight control surfaces]] enable the pilot to control an aircraft's [[Flight dynamics (fixed-wing aircraft)|flight attitude]] and are usually part of the wing or mounted on, or integral with, the associated stabilizing surface. Their development was a critical advance in the history of aircraft, which had until that point been uncontrollable in flight.

[[Aerospace engineering|Aerospace engineers]] develop [[control system]]s for a vehicle's orientation (attitude) about its [[center of mass]]. The control systems include actuators, which exert forces in various directions, and generate rotational forces or [[Moment (physics)|moments]] about the [[aerodynamic center]] of the aircraft, and thus rotate the aircraft in pitch, roll, or yaw. For example, a [[pitching moment]] is a vertical force applied at a distance forward or aft from the aerodynamic center of the aircraft, causing the aircraft to pitch up or down. Control systems are also sometimes used to increase or decrease drag, for example to slow the aircraft to a safe speed for landing.

The two main aerodynamic forces acting on any aircraft are lift supporting it in the air and [[Drag (physics)|drag]] opposing its motion. Control surfaces or other techniques may also be used to affect these forces directly, without inducing any rotation.

== Impacts of aircraft use ==
{{Main|Environmental impact of aviation}}
Aircraft permit long distance, high speed [[Air travel|travel]] and may be a more [[Energy efficiency in transport#Aircraft|fuel efficient]] mode of transportation in some circumstances. Aircraft have [[Environmental impact of aviation|environmental and climate impacts]] beyond fuel efficiency considerations, however. They are also relatively [[Aircraft noise pollution|noisy]] compared to other forms of travel and high altitude aircraft generate [[contrail]]s, which experimental evidence suggests may [[global dimming|alter weather patterns]].

== Uses for aircraft ==
Aircraft are produced in several different types optimized for various uses; [[military aircraft]], which includes not just combat types but many types of supporting aircraft, and [[civil aviation|civil aircraft]], which include all non-military types, experimental and model.

=== Military ===
[[File:Color Photographed B-17E in Flight.jpg|thumb|[[Boeing B-17 Flying Fortress|Boeing B-17E]] in flight]]
{{Main|Military aircraft}}
A military aircraft is any aircraft that is operated by a legal or insurrectionary armed service of any type.&lt;ref name=&quot;gunston&quot; /&gt; Military aircraft can be either combat or non-combat:
* Combat aircraft are aircraft designed to destroy enemy equipment using its own armament.&lt;ref name=&quot;gunston&quot; /&gt; Combat aircraft divide broadly into [[Fighter aircraft|fighters]] and [[bomber]]s, with several in-between types, such as [[fighter-bomber]]s and [[attack aircraft]], including [[attack helicopter]]s.
* Non-combat aircraft are not designed for combat as their primary function, but may carry weapons for self-defense. Non-combat roles include search and rescue, reconnaissance, observation, transport, training, and [[aerial refueling]]. These aircraft are often variants of civil aircraft.

Most military aircraft are powered heavier-than-air types. Other types, such as gliders and balloons, have also been used as military aircraft; for example, balloons were used for observation during the [[American Civil War]] and [[World War I]], and [[military glider]]s were used during [[World War II]] to land troops.

=== Civil ===
[[File:Pilatus Agusta A109 Flug.jpg|thumb|[[AgustaWestland AW109|Agusta A109]] helicopter of the [[Rega (air rescue)|Swiss air rescue service]]]]
{{Main|Civil aviation}}
Civil aircraft divide into ''commercial'' and ''general'' types, however there are some overlaps.

[[Commercial aviation|Commercial aircraft]] include types designed for scheduled and charter airline flights, carrying passengers, [[Airmail|mail]] and other [[cargo]]. The larger passenger-carrying types are the airliners, the largest of which are [[wide-body aircraft]]. Some of the smaller types are also used in [[general aviation]], and some of the larger types are used as [[Air transports of heads of state and government|VIP aircraft]].

[[General aviation]] is a catch-all covering other kinds of [[Private aviation|private]] (where the pilot is not paid for time or expenses) and commercial use, and involving a wide range of aircraft types such as [[Business jet|business jets (bizjets)]], [[Trainer aircraft|trainers]], [[Homebuilt aircraft|homebuilt]], [[glider (aircraft)|gliders]], [[warbird]]s and [[hot air balloon]]s to name a few. The vast majority of aircraft today are general aviation types.

=== Experimental ===
{{Main|Experimental aircraft}}
An experimental aircraft is one that has not been fully proven in flight, or that carries a [[Airworthiness certificate#Special Airworthiness Certificate|Special Airworthiness Certificate]], called an Experimental Certificate in United States parlance. This often implies that the aircraft is testing new aerospace technologies, though the term also refers to amateur-built and kit-built aircraft, many of which are based on proven designs.
[[File:MiniCeline ultralight aircraft.jpeg|thumb|A model aircraft, weighing six grams]]

=== Model ===
{{Main|Model aircraft}}
A model aircraft is a small unmanned type made to fly for fun, for static display, for aerodynamic research or for other purposes. A [[scale model]] is a replica of some larger design.

== See also ==

=== Lists ===
* [[Early flying machines]]
* [[Flight altitude record]]
* [[List of aircraft]]
* [[Flight altitude record]]
* [[wikt:Appendix:Glossary of aviation, aerospace, and aeronautics|List of aviation, aerospace and aeronautical terms]]
* [[List of civil aircraft]]
* [[List of fighter aircraft]]
* [[List of individual aircraft]]
* [[List of large aircraft]]

=== Topics ===
{|
| width=200px valign=top|
* [[Aircraft spotting]]
* [[Air traffic control]]
* [[Airport]]
* [[Flying car]]
* [[Personal air vehicle]]
* [[Powered parachute]]
| width=10px|&amp;nbsp;
| width=160px valign=top|
* [[Rocket]]
* [[Spacecraft]]
* [[Spaceplane]]
* [[Steam aircraft]]
|}

== References ==
{{Reflist|30em|refs=
&lt;ref name=&quot;gunston&quot;&gt;Gunston 1986, p. 274&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
* {{Cite book |last= Gunston |first= Bill |title=Jane's Aerospace Dictionary 1987 |year=1987 |publisher=Jane's Publishing Company Limited |location=London, England |isbn=978-0-7106-0365-4}}

== External links ==
{{Wiktionary|aircraft}}
{{Commons category|Aircraft}}

;History
* [http://www.hq.nasa.gov/office/pao/History/SP-468/contents.htm The Evolution of Modern Aircraft (NASA)]
* [http://invention.psychology.msstate.edu/Tale_of_Airplane/taleplane.html Virtual Museum]
* [http://www.nasm.si.edu/ Smithsonian Air and Space Museum]&amp;nbsp;— Online collection with a particular focus on history of aircraft and spacecraft
* [http://www.life.com/image/first/in-gallery/36582/amazing-early-flying-machines Amazing Early Flying Machines] slideshow by ''[[Life (magazine)|Life]]'' magazine

;Information
* [http://www.airliners.net/ Airliners.net]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20080624032037/http://www.aviationdictionary.org/ Aviation Dictionary] Free aviation terms, phrases and jargons
* [https://www.newscientist.com/topic/aviation ''New Scientist's'' Aviation page]

{{Aircraft types (by method of thrust and lift)}}
{{Lists of aircraft}}
{{Aircraft components}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Aircraft| ]]</text>
      <sha1>i04k1e2nqwmy8qpxcebi0d02fxes9vk</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
