  <page>
    <title>Alexander Graham Bell</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>852</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942440475</id>
      <parentid>942433592</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-24T18:11:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Sundayclose</username>
        <id>23483242</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Competitors */ I could not find these details in the source cited.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{pp-semi-indef}}
{{short description|scientist and inventor known for his work on the telephone}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=January 2019}}
{{Use British English Oxford spelling|date=September 2013}}
{{Infobox person
| name = Alexander Graham Bell
| image = Alexander Graham Bell.jpg
| caption = Portrait photo taken between 1914 and 1919
| birth_date = March 3, 1847
| birth_place = [[Edinburgh]], Scotland
| death_date = {{death date and age|1922|8|2|1847|3|3|mf=y}}
| death_place = [[Beinn Bhreagh]], [[Nova Scotia]], Canada
| occupation = {{hlist |Inventor |Scientist}} {{hlist |Engineer |Professor{{thinsp}}{{sup|a}}}} {{nowrap|Teacher of the deaf{{thinsp}}{{refn|''[Is the following a quote from the source referenced?:''] While Bell worked in many scientific, technical, professional and social capacities throughout his life he would remain fondest of his earliest vocation. To the end of his days, when discussing himself, Bell would always add with pride &quot;I am a teacher of the deaf&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Boileau |first=John |url=https://books.google.com/books/about/Fastest_in_the_World.html?id=lxq3yPsmF9AC |title=Fastest in the World: The Saga of Canada's Revolutionary Hydrofoils |location=Halifax, Nova Scotia |publisher=Formac Publishing |date=2004 |p=12 |isbn=978-0-88780-621-6 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; |group=&quot;N&quot;}}}}
| residence = {{ublist|class=nowrap &lt;!--(chronological:)--&gt;|United Kingdom |Canada |United States}}
| citizenship = United Kingdom (1847–1922)&lt;br /&gt;[[Canadian nationality law|British-subject in Canada]] (1870–1882)&lt;br /&gt;United States (1882–1922)
| alma_mater = {{ublist|class=nowrap |[[University of Edinburgh]] |[[University College London]]}}
| known_for = {{nowrap|&lt;!---The following is based on several reliable sources. Before changing, please discuss on the talk page:---&gt;[[Invention of the telephone]]{{thinsp}}{{sup|b}}}}
| awards = {{ublist|class=nowrap |{{smaller|1883}}&amp;nbsp; [[Member of the National Academy of Sciences|NAS Member]]|{{smaller|1902}}&amp;nbsp; [[Albert Medal (Royal Society of Arts)|Albert Medal]] |{{smaller|1907}}&amp;nbsp; [[John Fritz Medal]] |{{smaller|1912}}&amp;nbsp; [[Elliott Cresson Medal]]}}
| spouse = {{marriage|[[Mabel Hubbard]]|1877|1922}}
| parents = {{ublist|class=nowrap |[[Alexander Melville Bell]] |Eliza Grace Symonds Bell}}
| signature = Alexander Graham Bell (signature).svg
| children = Four{{thinsp}}{{sup|c}}
| relatives =
{{Unbulleted list |class=nowrap
| [[Gardiner Greene Hubbard|Gardiner G. Hubbard]]  {{small|(father-in-law)}}
| [[David Charles Bell (academic)|David C. Bell]]  {{small|(uncle)}}
| [[Gilbert Hovey Grosvenor|Gilbert H. Grosvenor]] {{small|(son-in-law)}}
| [[David Fairchild]]                              {{small|(son-in-law)}}
| [[Melville Bell Grosvenor]]                      {{small|(grandson)}}
| [[Mabel Harlakenden Grosvenor|Mabel Grosvenor]]  {{small|(granddaughter)}}
| [[Graham Fairchild|A. Graham Bell Fairchild]]    {{small|(grandson)}}
| [[Gilbert Melville Grosvenor|Gilbert Grosvenor]] {{small|(great-grandson)}}
| [[Edwin S. Grosvenor|Edwin Grosvenor]]           {{small|(great-grandson)}}
| [[Chichester Bell]]                              {{small|(cousin)}}
}}
| module = {{Listen |pos=center |embed=yes |filename=Alexander Graham Bell speaking.ogg |title={{big|Bell's voice}}{{thinsp}}&lt;ref name=&quot;voice&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=https://spectrum.ieee.org/tech-history/dawn-of-electronics/particle-physics-resurrects-alexander-graham-bells-voice|title=Particle Physics Resurrects Alexander Graham Bell's Voice|website=[[IEEE Spectrum]] |accessdate=May 10, 2018|date=April 30, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; |type=speech |description=[[Volta Laboratory and Bureau#Bell's voice|Re-identified in 2013]], Bell made this [[Phonograph cylinder#Early development|wax-disc]] recording of his voice in 1885.}}
| footnotes = {{ublist |{{sup|a}} [[Boston University]] (see [[#Continuing experimentation|below]]). |{{sup|b}} See [[#The telephone|below]]. |{{sup|c}} Two died soon after birth.}}
}}&lt;!--
***** EDITORS, PLEASE NOTE: *****

The question of nationality is a contentious one in that Alexander Graham Bell has been variously claimed as Scottish, British, American, and Canadian. Bell made a number of inventions as a formal British citizen after immigrating to Canada and then moving to the United States, including the telephone in 1876; however, he did not become an American citizen until 1882. Therefore, if nationality is to be described specifically ... Alexander Graham Bell, British inventor of the telephone, died as an American citizen in Canada. The wording in the lead paragraph was carefully crafted after input from many editors to accommodate the many diverse claims. It is recognized that in the last years of his life, Bell had American citizenship, although he lived primarily in Canada on his estate. His life's work and details on his nationality and citizenship are provided in later sections. Please discuss any potentially divisive submissions prior to editing the introductory section.
***** End editors' note *****
--&gt;
'''Alexander Graham Bell''' ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|ɡ|ɹ|eɪ|.|ə|m}}; March 3, 1847&amp;nbsp;– August 2, 1922)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bellhomestead.ca/history/Pages/TheBellFamily.aspx |title=The Bell Family |website=Bell Homestead National Historic Site |accessdate=September 27, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; was a &lt;!-- Read note above prior to modifying this introduction --&gt; [[Scottish people|Scottish]]-born{{refn|Bell was a [[British subject]] for most of his early life. When he moved to Canada in 1870, Canadian and British citizenship were functionally identical, with [[Canadian nationality law|Canadian citizenship]] only becoming a formal classification in 1910. He applied for American citizenship after 1877, gained it in 1882, and referred to himself as an American citizen from that point on. Quote from Bell speaking to his wife: &quot;you are a citizen because you can't help it – you were born one, but I chose to be one.&quot;{{sfn|Gray|2006|p=228}} Aside from Bell's own view of his citizenship, many, if not most Canadians considered him also as one of theirs as evidenced in an address by the Governor General of Canada. On October 24, 1917, in Brantford, Ontario, the Governor General spoke at the unveiling of the [[Bell Telephone Memorial]] to an audience numbering in the thousands, saying: &quot;Dr. Bell is to be congratulated upon being able to receive the recognition of his fellow citizens and fellow countrymen&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Reville |first=F. Douglas |url=http://brantford.library.on.ca/localhistory/pdfs/reville1.pdf |title=History of the County of Brant: Illustrated With Fifty Half-Tones Taken From Miniatures And Photographs |publisher=Brantford Historical Society &amp; Hurley Printing |location=Brantford, Ontario |date=1920 |p=319 |accessdate=May 4, 2012 |ref=harv |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120419162041/http://brantford.library.on.ca/localhistory/pdfs/reville1.pdf |archive-date=April 19, 2012 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; |group=N}} American inventor, scientist, and engineer who is credited with inventing and patenting the first practical [[telephone]]. He also co-founded the [[American Telephone and Telegraph Company]] (AT&amp;T) in 1885.&lt;ref&gt;Bruce 1990, p. 291.{{Full citation needed|date=February 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Pizer 2009, pp. 120–124. Bruce 1990, p. 291{{Full citation needed|date=February 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Bell's [[Alexander Melville Bell|father]], grandfather, and brother had all been associated with work on [[elocution]] and speech and both his mother and wife were deaf, profoundly influencing Bell's life's work.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Bruce |first=Robert V. |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ZmR0MOQAu0UC |title=Bell: Alexander Bell and the Conquest of Solitude |location=Ithaca, New York |publisher=Cornell University Press |date=1990 |p=419 |isbn=978-0-8014-9691-2 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; His research on hearing and speech further led him to experiment with hearing devices which eventually culminated in Bell being awarded the first [[United States patent law|U.S. patent]] for the telephone, on March 7, 1876.{{refn|From {{harvp|Black|1997|p=18}}: &quot;He thought he could harness the new [[Electronics|electronic technology]] by creating a machine with a transmitter and receiver that would send sounds telegraphically to help people hear.&quot;|group=N}} Bell considered his invention an intrusion on his real work as a scientist and refused to have a telephone in his study.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=MacLeod |first=Elizabeth |title=Alexander Graham Bell: An Inventive Life |location=Toronto, Ontario |publisher=Kids Can Press |date=1999 |p=19 |isbn=978-1-55074-456-9 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{refn|After Bell's death his wife Mabel wrote to [[John J. Carty]], an AT&amp;T vice-president, and commented on her husband's reluctance to have a phone in his study, saying &quot;[of the statements in the newspapers] ...publishing of Mr. Bell's dislike of the telephone. Of course, he never had one in his study. That was where he went when he wanted to be alone with his thoughts and his work. The telephone, of course, means intrusion by the outside world. And the little difficulties and delays often attending the establishment of conversation... did irritate him, so that as a rule he preferred having others send and receive messages. But all really important business over the telephone he transacted himself. There are few private houses more completely equipped with telephones than ours... and there was nothing that Mr. Bell was more particular about than our telephone service... We never could have come here [to Beinn Bhreagh] in the first place or continued here, but for the telephone which kept us in close touch with doctors and neighbors and the regular telegraph office... Mr. Bell did like to say in fun, &quot;Why did I ever invent the Telephone,&quot; but no one had a higher appreciation of its indispensableness or used it more freely when need was—either personally or by deputy —and he was really tremendously proud of it and all it was accomplishing.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Bell |first=Mabel |title=Dr. Bell's Appreciation of the Telephone Service |journal=Bell Telephone Quarterly |volume=1 |issue=3 |date=October 1922 |p=65 |url=https://archive.org/stream/belltelephonemag01amer#page/64/mode/2up |accessdate=September 18, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;|group=N}}

Many other inventions marked Bell's later life, including groundbreaking work in [[Free-space optical communication|optical telecommunications]], [[hydrofoil]]s, and [[aeronautics]]. Although Bell was not one of the 33 founders&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://newswatch.nationalgeographic.com/tag/national-geographic-founders/ |title=National Geographic founders |date= |accessdate=January 9, 2014 |quote= |publisher=National Geographic Society |location= }}&lt;/ref&gt; of the [[National Geographic Society]], he had a strong influence on the magazine while serving as the second president from January 7, 1898, until 1903.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://voices.nationalgeographic.com/2011/05/26/ngs-celebrates-23rd-founders-day |title=NGS Celebrates 23rd Founders Day |last=Howley |first=Andrew |date=May 26, 2011 |website=NGS |publisher=National Geographic Society |accessdate=January 18, 2016 |quote=Though he wasn't one of the original 33 founders, Bell had a major influence on the Society.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Beyond his scientific work, Bell was an advocate of [[compulsory sterilization]], and served as chairman or president of several [[eugenics]] organizations.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt; 

==Early life==
Alexander Bell was born in [[Edinburgh]], Scotland, on March 3, 1847.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Petrie |first=A. Roy |title=Alexander Graham Bell |location=Don Mills, Ontario |publisher=Fitzhenry &amp; Whiteside |date=1975 |p=[https://archive.org/details/alexandergrahamb0000petr_q2x0/page/4 4] |isbn=978-0-88902-209-6 |ref=harv |url=https://archive.org/details/alexandergrahamb0000petr_q2x0/page/4 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The family home was at South Charlotte Street, and has a stone inscription marking it as Alexander Graham Bell's birthplace. He had two brothers: Melville James Bell (1845–1870) and Edward Charles Bell (1848–1867), both of whom would die of [[tuberculosis]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://memory.loc.gov/ammem/bellhtml/belltime.html &quot;Time Line of Alexander Graham Bell.&quot;] ''memory.loc.goiv.'' Retrieved: July 28, 2010. {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20051024211905/http://memory.loc.gov/ammem/bellhtml/belltime.html |date=October 24, 2005 }}&lt;/ref&gt; His father was Professor [[Alexander Melville Bell]], a [[phonetics|phonetician]], and his mother was Eliza Grace (née Symonds).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Alexander M. Bell Dead. Father of Prof. A. G. Bell Developed Sign Language for Mutes |url=https://www.nytimes.com/1905/08/08/archives/alexander-m-bell-dead-father-of-prof-ag-bell-developed-sign.html |work=New York Times |date=August 8, 1905 |access-date=September 18, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Born as just &quot;Alexander Bell&quot;, at age 10, he made a plea to his father to have a middle name like his two brothers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://learn.fi.edu/learn/case-files/bell/agb.html|title = Call me Alexander Graham Bell|website = The Franklin Institute|access-date = February 24, 2015|date = January 14, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{refn| Bell typically signed his name in full on his correspondence.|group=N}} For his 11th birthday, his father acquiesced and allowed him to adopt the name &quot;Graham&quot;, chosen out of respect for Alexander Graham, a [[Canadians|Canadian]] being treated by his father who had become a family friend.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Groundwater |first=Jennifer |title=Alexander Graham Bell: The Spirit of Invention |location=Calgary, Alberta |publisher=Altitude Publishing |date=2005 |p=[https://archive.org/details/alexandergrahamb0000grou/page/23 23] |isbn=978-1-55439-006-9 |ref=harv |url=https://archive.org/details/alexandergrahamb0000grou/page/23 }}&lt;/ref&gt; To close relatives and friends he remained &quot;Aleck&quot;.{{sfn|Bruce|1990|pp=17–19}}

===First invention===
As a child, young Bell displayed a curiosity about his world; he in gathered botanical specimens and ran experiments at an early age. His best friend was Ben Herdman, a neighbour whose family operated a flour mill. At the age of 12, Bell built a homemade device that combined rotating paddles with sets of nail brushes, creating a simple dehusking machine that was put into operation at the mill and used steadily for a number of years.{{sfn|Bruce|1990|p=16}} In return, Ben's father John Herdman gave both boys the run of a small workshop in which to &quot;invent&quot;.{{sfn|Bruce|1990|p=16}}

From his early years, Bell showed a sensitive nature and a talent for art, poetry, and music that was encouraged by his mother. With no formal training, he mastered the piano and became the family's pianist.{{sfn|Gray|2006|p=8}} Despite being normally quiet and introspective, he revelled in mimicry and &quot;voice tricks&quot; akin to [[ventriloquism]] that continually entertained family guests during their occasional visits.{{sfn|Gray|2006|p=8}} Bell was also deeply affected by his mother's gradual deafness (she began to lose her hearing when he was 12), and learned a manual finger language so he could sit at her side and tap out silently the conversations swirling around the family parlour.{{sfn|Gray|2006|p=9}} He also developed a technique of speaking in clear, modulated tones directly into his mother's forehead wherein she would hear him with reasonable clarity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Mackay |first=James |title=Sounds Out of Silence: A life of Alexander Graham Bell |location=Edinburgh, UK |publisher=Mainstream Publishing |date=1997 |p=25 |isbn=978-1-85158-833-6 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bell's preoccupation with his mother's deafness led him to study [[acoustics]].

His family was long associated with the teaching of elocution: his grandfather, Alexander Bell, in London, his uncle in [[Dublin]], and his father, in Edinburgh, were all elocutionists. His father published a variety of works on the subject, several of which are still well known, especially his ''The Standard Elocutionist'' (1860),{{sfn|Gray|2006|p=8}} which appeared in Edinburgh in 1868. ''The Standard Elocutionist'' appeared in 168 British editions and sold over a quarter of a million copies in the United States alone. In this treatise, his father explains his methods of how to instruct [[deaf-mute]]s (as they were then known) to articulate words and read other people's lip movements to decipher meaning. Bell's father taught him and his brothers not only to write [[Visible Speech]] but to identify any symbol and its accompanying sound.{{sfn|Petrie|1975|p=7}} Bell became so proficient that he became a part of his father's public demonstrations and astounded audiences with his abilities. He could decipher Visible Speech representing virtually every language, including [[Latin]], [[Scottish Gaelic]], and even [[Sanskrit]], accurately reciting written tracts without any prior knowledge of their pronunciation.{{sfn|Petrie|1975|p=7}}

{{Commons category|Alexander_Graham_Bell#Earlier_photos_of_Bell.27s_ancestral_family|a young Bell with his parents}}

===Education===
As a young child, Bell, like his brothers, received his early schooling at home from his father. At an early age, he was enrolled at the [[Royal High School (Edinburgh)|Royal High School]], Edinburgh, Scotland, which he left at the age of 15, having completed only the first four forms.{{sfn|Mackay|1997|p=31}} His school record was undistinguished, marked by absenteeism and lacklustre grades. His main interest remained in the sciences, especially biology, while he treated other school subjects with indifference, to the dismay of his father.{{sfn|Gray|2006|p=11}} Upon leaving school, Bell travelled to London to live with his grandfather, Alexander Bell. During the year he spent with his grandfather, a love of learning was born, with long hours spent in serious discussion and study. The elder Bell took great efforts to have his young pupil learn to speak clearly and with conviction, the attributes that his pupil would need to become a teacher himself.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Town |first=Florida |title=Alexander Graham Bell |location=Toronto, Ontario |publisher=Grolier |date=1988 |p=7 |isbn=978-0-7172-1950-6 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the age of 16, Bell secured a position as a &quot;pupil-teacher&quot; of [[elocution]] and music, in Weston House Academy at [[Elgin, Moray]], Scotland. Although he was enrolled as a student in Latin and Greek, he instructed classes himself in return for board and £10 per session.{{sfn|Bruce|1990|p=37}} The following year, he attended the [[University of Edinburgh]]; joining his older brother Melville who had enrolled there the previous year. In 1868, not long before he departed for Canada with his family, Bell completed his matriculation exams and was accepted for admission to [[University College London]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Shulman |first=Seth |title=The Telephone Gambit: Chasing Alexander Bell's Secret |location=New York |publisher=Norton &amp; Company |date=2008 |p=[https://archive.org/details/telephonegambitc00shul/page/49 49] |isbn=978-0-393-06206-9 |ref=harv |url=https://archive.org/details/telephonegambitc00shul/page/49 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===First experiments with sound===
His father encouraged Bell's interest in speech and, in 1863, took his sons to see a unique [[automaton]] developed by Sir [[Charles Wheatstone]] based on the earlier work of [[Wolfgang von Kempelen|Baron Wolfgang von Kempelen]].{{sfn|Groundwater|2005|p=25}} The rudimentary &quot;mechanical man&quot; simulated a human voice. Bell was fascinated by the machine and after he obtained a copy of von Kempelen's book, published in German, and had laboriously translated it, he and his older brother Melville built their own automaton head. Their father, highly interested in their project, offered to pay for any supplies and spurred the boys on with the enticement of a &quot;big prize&quot; if they were successful.{{sfn|Groundwater|2005|p=25}} While his brother constructed the throat and [[larynx]], Bell tackled the more difficult task of recreating a realistic skull. His efforts resulted in a remarkably lifelike head that could &quot;speak&quot;, albeit only a few words.{{sfn|Groundwater|2005|p=25}} The boys would carefully adjust the &quot;lips&quot; and when a [[bellows]] forced air through the [[Vertebrate trachea|windpipe]], a very recognizable &quot;Mama&quot; ensued, to the delight of neighbours who came to see the Bell invention.{{sfn|Petrie|1975|pp=7–9}}

Intrigued by the results of the automaton, Bell continued to experiment with a live subject, the family's [[Skye Terrier]], &quot;Trouve&quot;.{{sfn|Petrie|1975|p=9}} After he taught it to growl continuously, Bell would reach into its mouth and manipulate the dog's lips and [[vocal cords]] to produce a crude-sounding &quot;Ow ah oo ga ma ma&quot;. With little convincing, visitors believed his dog could articulate &quot;How are you, grandma?&quot; Indicative of his playful nature, his experiments convinced onlookers that they saw a &quot;talking dog&quot;.{{sfn|Groundwater|2005|p=30}} These initial forays into experimentation with sound led Bell to undertake his first serious work on the transmission of sound, using [[tuning fork]]s to explore [[resonance]].

At age 19, Bell wrote a report on his work and sent it to philologist [[Alexander John Ellis|Alexander Ellis]], a colleague of his father (who would later be portrayed as Professor Henry Higgins in ''[[Pygmalion (play)|Pygmalion]]'').{{sfn|Groundwater|2005|p=30}} Ellis immediately wrote back indicating that the experiments were similar to existing work in Germany, and also lent Bell a copy of [[Hermann von Helmholtz]]'s work, ''The Sensations of Tone as a Physiological Basis for the Theory of Music''.{{sfn|Shulman|2008|p=46}}

Dismayed to find that groundbreaking work had already been undertaken by Helmholtz who had conveyed vowel sounds by means of a similar tuning fork &quot;contraption&quot;, Bell pored over the German scientist's book. Working from his own erroneous mistranslation of a French edition,&lt;ref name=&quot;DCB&quot; /&gt; Bell fortuitously then made a deduction that would be the underpinning of all his future work on transmitting sound, reporting: &quot;Without knowing much about the subject, it seemed to me that if vowel sounds could be produced by electrical means, so could consonants, so could articulate speech.&quot; He also later remarked: &quot;I thought that Helmholtz had done it&amp;nbsp;... and that my failure was due only to my ignorance of electricity. It was a valuable blunder&amp;nbsp;... If I had been able to read German in those days, I might never have commenced my experiments!&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=MacKenzie |first=Catherine |author-link=Catherine MacKenzie |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=iFOcw4lN_ZYC |title=Alexander Graham Bell |location=Boston, Massachusetts |publisher=Grosset and Dunlap |date=2003 |orig-year=1928 |p=41 |isbn=978-0-7661-4385-2 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Groundwater|2005|p=31}}{{sfn|Shulman|2008|pp=46–48}}{{refn| Helmholtz's ''The Sensations of Tone'' is credited with inspiring Bell, at the age of 23, to further his studies of electricity and electromagnetism.&lt;ref name=&quot;DCB&quot; /&gt;|group=N}}

===Family tragedy===
In 1865, when the Bell family moved to London,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Micklos |first=John Jr. |title=Alexander Graham Bell: Inventor of the Telephone |location=New York |publisher=[[HarperCollins]] |date=2006 |p=8 |isbn=978-0-06-057618-9 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bell returned to Weston House as an assistant master and, in his spare hours, continued experiments on sound using a minimum of laboratory equipment. Bell concentrated on experimenting with electricity to convey sound and later installed a [[telegraph]] wire from his room in Somerset College to that of a friend.{{sfn|Bruce|1990|p=45}} Throughout late 1867, his health faltered mainly through exhaustion. His younger brother, Edward &quot;Ted,&quot; was similarly bed-ridden, suffering from [[tuberculosis]]. While Bell recovered (by then referring to himself in correspondence as &quot;A. G. Bell&quot;) and served the next year as an instructor at Somerset College, [[Bath, Somerset|Bath]], England, his brother's condition deteriorated. Edward would never recover. Upon his brother's death, Bell returned home in 1867. His older brother Melville had married and moved out. With aspirations to obtain a degree at [[University College London]], Bell considered his next years as preparation for the degree examinations, devoting his spare time at his family's residence to studying.

Helping his father in Visible Speech demonstrations and lectures brought Bell to Susanna E. Hull's private school for the deaf in [[South Kensington]], London. His first two pupils were [[deaf-mute]] girls who made remarkable progress under his tutelage. While his older brother seemed to achieve success on many fronts including opening his own elocution school, applying for a patent on an invention, and starting a family, Bell continued as a teacher. However, in May 1870, Melville died from complications due to tuberculosis, causing a family crisis. His father had also suffered a debilitating illness earlier in life and had been restored to health by a convalescence in [[Newfoundland and Labrador|Newfoundland]]. Bell's parents embarked upon a long-planned move when they realized that their remaining son was also sickly. Acting decisively, Alexander Melville Bell asked Bell to arrange for the sale of all the family property,{{sfn|Bruce|1990|pp=67–28}}{{refn|The family pet was given to his brother's family.|group=N}} conclude all of his brother's affairs (Bell took over his last student, curing a pronounced lisp),{{sfn|Bruce|1990|p=68}} and join his father and mother in setting out for the &quot;[[New World]]&quot;. Reluctantly, Bell also had to conclude a relationship with Marie Eccleston, who, as he had surmised, was not prepared to leave England with him.{{sfn|Groundwater|2005|p=33}}

==Canada==
{{Main|Bell Homestead National Historic Site}}
[[File:The Bell Homestead National Historic Site, Brantford, Ontario, Canada, incl. Visitor Ctr, Henderson Home, Carriage House and Dreaming Place IMG 0039 09.JPG|thumb|[[Bell Homestead National Historic Site|Melville House]], the Bells' first home in North America, now a [[National Historic Sites of Canada|National Historic Site of Canada]]]]

In 1870, 23-year-old Bell travelled with his parents and his brother's widow, Caroline Margaret Ottaway,{{sfn|Mackay|1997|p=50}}  to [[Paris, Ontario]],{{sfn|Gray|2006|p=21}} to stay with the Reverend Thomas Henderson, a family friend. The Bell family soon purchased a farm of {{convert|10.5|acre|m2}} at Tutelo Heights (now called Tutela Heights), near [[Brantford]], Ontario. The property consisted of an orchard, large farmhouse, stable, pigsty, hen-house, and a [[carriage house]], which bordered the [[Grand River (Ontario)|Grand River]].{{sfn|Mackay|1997|p=61}}{{refn| The estate, dating from 1858, is in the present day located at 94 Tutela Heights Road, Brantford, and is now known as the &quot;Bell Homestead&quot;, and formally as the [[Bell Homestead National Historic Site|Bell Homestead National Historic Site of Canada]]. It received its historical designation from the Government of Canada on June 1, 1996.&lt;ref&gt;{{CRHP|12773|Bell Homestead National Historic Site of Canada|September 17, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;|group=N}}

At the homestead, Bell set up his own workshop in the converted carriage house near to what he called his &quot;dreaming place&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Wing |first=Chris |title=Alexander Graham Bell at Baddeck |location=Baddeck, Nova Scotia |publisher=Christopher King |date=1980 |p=10|ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; a large hollow nestled in trees at the back of the property above the river.{{sfn|Groundwater|2005|p=34}} Despite his frail condition upon arriving in Canada, Bell found the climate and environs to his liking, and rapidly improved.{{sfn|Mackay|1997|p=62}}{{refn| Bell would later write that he had come to Canada a &quot;dying man&quot;.|group=N}} He continued his interest in the study of the human voice and when he discovered the [[Six Nations 40, Ontario|Six Nations Reserve]] across the river at [[Onondaga (village)|Onondaga]], he learned the [[Mohawk language]] and translated its unwritten vocabulary into Visible Speech symbols. For his work, Bell was awarded the title of Honorary Chief and participated in a ceremony where he donned a [[Mohawk nation|Mohawk]] headdress and danced traditional dances.{{sfn|Groundwater|2005|p=35}}{{refn|Bell was thrilled at his recognition by the Six Nations Reserve and throughout his life would launch into a Mohawk war dance when he was excited.|group=N}}

After setting up his workshop, Bell continued experiments based on Helmholtz's work with electricity and sound.{{Sfn|Wing|1980|p=10}} He also modified a [[Pump organ|melodeon]] (a type of pump organ) so that it could transmit its music electrically over a distance.&lt;ref name=&quot;Waldi-undated&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Waldie |first=Jean H. |title=Historic Melodeon Is Given To Bell Museum |publisher=likely published either by the [[London Free Press]] or by the Brantford Expositor, date unknown}}&lt;/ref&gt; Once the family was settled in, both Bell and his father made plans to establish a teaching practice and in 1871, he accompanied his father to Montreal, where Melville was offered a position to teach his System of Visible Speech.

==Work with the deaf==
[[File:Bell at the Pemberton Avenue School for the Deaf, Boston, from the Library of Congress. 00837v.jpg|thumb|Bell, top right, providing [[Pedagogy|pedagogical instruction]] to teachers at the Boston School for Deaf Mutes, 1871. Throughout his life, he referred to himself as &quot;a teacher of the deaf&quot;.]]
{{Commons category|Alexander_Graham_Bell#Alexander_Graham_Bell_-General_photos_with_other_people_or_groups|the '''Scott Circle School for Deaf Children'''}}

Bell's father was invited by [[Sarah Fuller]], principal of the Boston School for Deaf Mutes (which continues today as the public [[Horace Mann School for the Deaf and Hard of Hearing|Horace Mann School for the Deaf]]),{{sfn|Bruce|1990|p=74}} in Boston, Massachusetts, United States, to introduce the Visible Speech System by providing training for Fuller's instructors, but he declined the post in favour of his son. Travelling to Boston in April 1871, Bell proved successful in training the school's instructors.{{sfn|Town|1988|p=12}} He was subsequently asked to repeat the programme at the [[American School for the Deaf|American Asylum for Deaf-mutes]] in [[Hartford, Connecticut]], and the [[Clarke School for the Deaf]] in [[Northampton, Massachusetts]].

Returning home to Brantford after six months abroad, Bell continued his experiments with his &quot;harmonic telegraph&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Alexander Graham Bell |type=(booklet) |location=Halifax, Nova Scotia |publisher=Maritime Telegraph &amp; Telephone Limited |date=1979 |p=8 |ref={{sfnRef|''Alexander Graham Bell''|1979}} }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{refn|In later years, Bell described the invention of the telephone and linked it to his &quot;dreaming place&quot;.|group=N}} The basic concept behind his device was that messages could be sent through a single wire if each message was transmitted at a different pitch, but work on both the transmitter and receiver was needed.{{sfn|Groundwater|2005|p=39}}

Unsure of his future, he first contemplated returning to London to complete his studies, but decided to return to Boston as a teacher.{{sfn|Petrie|1975|p=14}} His father helped him set up his private practice by contacting [[Gardiner Greene Hubbard]], the president of the Clarke School for the Deaf for a recommendation. Teaching his father's system, in October 1872, Alexander Bell opened his &quot;School of Vocal Physiology and Mechanics of Speech&quot; in Boston, which attracted a large number of deaf pupils, with his first class numbering 30 students.{{sfn|Petrie|1975|p=15}}{{sfn|Town|1988|pp=12–13}} While he was working as a private tutor, one of his pupils was [[Helen Keller]], who came to him as a young child unable to see, hear, or speak. She was later to say that Bell dedicated his life to the penetration of that &quot;inhuman silence which separates and estranges&quot;.{{sfn|Petrie|1975|p=17}} In 1893, Keller performed the sod-breaking ceremony for the construction of Bell's new [[Volta Bureau]], dedicated to &quot;the increase and diffusion of knowledge relating to the deaf&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schoenherr2005&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last=Schoenherr |first=Steven E. |url=http://www.aes.org/aeshc/docs/recording.technology.history/graphophone.html |website=Recording Technology History |title=Charles Sumner Tainter and the Graphophone |publisher=Audio Engineering Society |date=February 10, 2000 |access-date=September 19, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |title=Alexander Graham Bell |encyclopedia=Encyclopædia Britannica |first=David |last=Hochfelder |url=http://www.britannica.com/biography/Alexander-Graham-Bell |date=July 31, 2015 |access-date=September 18, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Several influential people of the time, including Bell, viewed deafness as something that should be eradicated, and also believed that with resources and effort, they could teach the deaf to speak and avoid the use of [[sign language]], thus enabling their integration within the wider society from which many were often being excluded.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Miller |first1=Don |first2=Jan |last2=Branson |url=https://archive.org/details/damnedfortheirdi00bran_0 |url-access=registration |title=Damned For Their Difference: The Cultural Construction Of Deaf People as Disabled: A Sociological History |location=Washington, D.C. |publisher=Gallaudet University Press |date=2002 |pp=[https://archive.org/details/damnedfortheirdi00bran_0/page/30 30]–31, 152–153 |isbn=978-1-56368-121-9 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; Owing to his efforts to suppress the teaching of sign language, Bell is often viewed negatively by those embracing [[Deaf culture]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |editor-last1=Ayers |editor-first1=William C. |editor-first2=Therese |editor-last2=Quinn |editor-first3=David |editor-last3=Stovall |title=The Handbook of Social Justice in Education |location=London |publisher=Routledge |date=2009 |pp=194–195 |isbn=978-0-80585-928-7 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Continuing experimentation==
&lt;!--Linked from infobox at start of article--&gt;
In 1872, Bell became professor of Vocal Physiology and Elocution at the [[Boston University]] School of Oratory. During this period, he alternated between Boston and Brantford, spending summers in his Canadian home. At Boston University, Bell was &quot;swept up&quot; by the excitement engendered by the many scientists and inventors residing in the city. He continued his research in sound and endeavored to find a way to transmit musical notes and articulate speech, but although absorbed by his experiments, he found it difficult to devote enough time to experimentation. While days and evenings were occupied by his teaching and private classes, Bell began to stay awake late into the night, running experiment after experiment in rented facilities at his boarding house. Keeping &quot;night owl&quot; hours, he worried that his work would be discovered and took great pains to lock up his notebooks and laboratory equipment. Bell had a specially made table where he could place his notes and equipment inside a locking cover.{{sfn|Town|1988|p=15}} Worse still, his health deteriorated as he suffered severe headaches.{{sfn|Groundwater|2005|p=39}} Returning to Boston in fall 1873, Bell made a fateful decision to concentrate on his experiments in sound.

Deciding to give up his lucrative private Boston practice, Bell retained only two students, six-year-old &quot;Georgie&quot; Sanders, deaf from birth, and 15-year-old [[Mabel Gardiner Hubbard|Mabel Hubbard]]. Each pupil would play an important role in the next developments. George's father, Thomas Sanders, a wealthy businessman, offered Bell a place to stay in nearby [[Salem, Massachusetts|Salem]] with Georgie's grandmother, complete with a room to &quot;experiment&quot;. Although the offer was made by George's mother and followed the year-long arrangement in 1872 where her son and his nurse had moved to quarters next to Bell's boarding house, it was clear that Mr. Sanders was backing the proposal. The arrangement was for teacher and student to continue their work together, with free room and board thrown in.{{sfn|Town|1988|p=16}} Mabel was a bright, attractive girl who was ten years Bell's junior but became the object of his affection. Having lost her hearing after a near-fatal bout of [[scarlet fever]] close to her fifth birthday,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Toward |first=Lilias M. |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=WXjSAAAACAAJ |title=Mabel Bell: Alexander's Silent Partner |location=Toronto, Ontario |publisher=Methuen |date=1984 |p=1 |isbn=978-0-458-98090-1 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author-link=Dorothy Harley Eber |last=Eber |first=Dorothy Harley |title=Genius at Work: Images of Alexander Graham Bell |location=Toronto, Ontario |publisher=[[McClelland and Stewart]] |date=1991 |orig-year=1982 |edition=reprint |p=43 |isbn=978-0-7710-3036-9 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{refn| {{harvp|Eber|1991|p=43}} claimed that Mabel suffered scarlet fever in New York &quot;''...shortly before her fifth birthday...''&quot;; however, {{harvp|Toward|1984}} provided a detailed chronology of the event claiming &quot;...&amp;nbsp;shortly after their arrival in New York [in January 1863]&quot; when Mabel would have been at least five years and five weeks of age. Mabel's exact age when she became deaf would later play a part in the debate on the effectiveness of [[Manualism and oralism|manual versus oral education for deaf children]], as children who are older at the onset of deafness retain greater vocalization skills and are thus more successful in oral education programs. Some of the debate centred on whether Mabel had to relearn oral speech from scratch, or whether she never lost it.|group=N}} she had learned to [[Lip reading|read lips]] but her father, [[Gardiner Greene Hubbard]], Bell's benefactor and personal friend, wanted her to work directly with her teacher.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Dunn |first=Andrew |title=Alexander Graham Bell |series=(Pioneers of Science) |location=East Sussex, UK |publisher=Wayland Publishers |date=1990 |p=20 |isbn=978-1-85210-958-5 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==The telephone==
&lt;!----Please note:
The question of authorship or claims to the invention of the telephone is discussed in the sub-article Invention of the Telephone. Although there remain disputes between various parties that were eventually resolved in litigation, this still remains a contentious issue. Before introducing any further controversial issues related to the invention of the telephone, please discuss on the talk page.
-----&gt;
&lt;!--Linked from infobox above--&gt;
{{external media | width = 210px | float = right | audio1 = [http://www.cbc.ca/archives/entry/alexander-graham-bell-and-thomas-watson Alexander Graham Bell and Thomas Watson], 26:58, [[Canadian Broadcasting Corporation|CBC Archives]]&lt;ref name=&quot;CBC archives&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title =Alexander Graham Bell and Thomas Watson | website = | publisher =[[Canadian Broadcasting Corporation|CBC]] | date = July 25, 1975 | url =http://www.cbc.ca/archives/entry/alexander-graham-bell-and-thomas-watson | accessdate =October 14, 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt; }}
{{Main|Invention of the telephone}}
By 1874, Bell's initial work on the harmonic telegraph had entered a formative stage, with progress made both at his new Boston &quot;laboratory&quot; (a rented facility) and at his family home in Canada a big success.{{refn| From {{harvp|''Alexander Graham Bell''|1979|p=8}}: &quot;Brantford is justified in calling herself 'The Telephone City' because the telephone originated there. It was invented in Brantford at Tutela Heights in the summer of 1874.&quot;|group=N}} While working that summer in Brantford, Bell experimented with a &quot;[[phonautograph]]&quot;, a pen-like machine that could draw shapes of sound waves on smoked glass by tracing their vibrations. Bell thought it might be possible to generate undulating electrical currents that corresponded to sound waves.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Matthews |first=Tom L. |title=Always Inventing: A Photobiography of Alexander Graham Bell |location=Washington, D.C. |publisher=National Geographic Society |date=1999 |pp=19–21 |isbn=978-0-7922-7391-2 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bell also thought that multiple metal reeds tuned to different frequencies like a harp would be able to convert the undulating currents back into sound. But he had no working model to demonstrate the feasibility of these ideas.{{sfn|Matthews|1999|p=21}}

In 1874, telegraph message traffic was rapidly expanding and in the words of [[Western Union]] President [[William Orton (businessman)|William Orton]], had become &quot;the nervous system of commerce&quot;. [[Antonio Meucci]] sent a telephone model and technical details to the Western Union telegraph company but failed to win a meeting with executives. When he asked for his materials to be returned, in 1874, he was told they had been lost. Two years later Bell, who shared a laboratory with Meucci, filed a patent for a telephone, became a celebrity and made a lucrative deal with Western Union. Meucci sued and was nearing victory—the supreme court agreed to hear the case and fraud charges were initiated against Bell—when the Florentine died in 1889. The legal action died with him.&lt;ref&gt;Carroll, Rory (June 17, 2002). [https://www.theguardian.com/world/2002/jun/17/humanities.internationaleducationnews &quot;Bell did not invent telephone, US rules&quot;]. ''the Guardian''. Retrieved on September 20, 2018.&lt;/ref&gt;  Orton had contracted with inventors [[Thomas Edison]] and [[Elisha Gray]] to find a way to send multiple telegraph messages on each telegraph line to avoid the great cost of constructing new lines.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|first1=Blaine |last1=McCormick |first2=Paul |last2=Israel |url=http://ieee.cincinnati.fuse.net/reiman/03_2005.htm |title=Underrated entrepreneur: Thomas Edison's overlooked business story |journal=IEEE Power &amp; Energy Magazine |volume=3 |issue=1 |pages=76–79 |date=January–February 2005 |ref={{sfnRef|McCormick|Israel|2005}} |doi=10.1109/MPAE.2005.1380243 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20091223075458/http://ieee.cincinnati.fuse.net/reiman/03_2005.htm |archivedate=December 23, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; When Bell mentioned to Gardiner Hubbard and Thomas Sanders that he was working on a method of sending multiple tones on a telegraph wire using a multi-reed device, the two wealthy patrons began to financially support Bell's experiments.{{sfn|Town|1988|p=17}} Patent matters would be handled by Hubbard's [[patent attorney]], [[Anthony Pollok]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Evenson |first=A. Edward |title=The Telephone Patent Conspiracy of 1876: The Elisha Gray&amp;nbsp;— Alexander Bell Controversy |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=KiJJ7Bp-xtcC |location=Jefferson, North Carolina |publisher=McFarland Publishing |date=2000 |pp=18–25 |isbn=978-0-7864-0883-2 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In March 1875, Bell and Pollok visited the scientist [[Joseph Henry]], who was then director of the [[Smithsonian Institution]], and asked Henry's advice on the electrical multi-reed apparatus that Bell hoped would transmit the human voice by telegraph. Henry replied that Bell had &quot;the germ of a great invention&quot;. When Bell said that he did not have the necessary knowledge, Henry replied, &quot;Get it!&quot; That declaration greatly encouraged Bell to keep trying, even though he did not have the equipment needed to continue his experiments, nor the ability to create a working model of his ideas. However, a chance meeting in 1874 between Bell and [[Thomas A. Watson]], an experienced electrical designer and mechanic at the electrical machine shop of Charles Williams, changed all that.

With financial support from Sanders and Hubbard, Bell hired Thomas Watson as his assistant,{{refn| Hubbard's financial support to the research efforts fell far short of the funds needed, necessitating Bell to continue teaching while conducting his experiments.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Fitzgerald |first=Brian |url=http://www.bu.edu/bridge/archive/2001/09-14/bell.html |title=Alexander Graham Bell: The BU Years |newspaper=B.U. Bridge |publisher=Boston University |volume=V |issue=5 |date=September 14, 2001 |access-date=March 28, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bell was so short of funds at times that he had to borrow money from his own employee, [[Thomas A. Watson|Thomas Watson]]. Bell also sought an additional CAD$150 from the former [[Premier (Canada)|Premier of Canada]], [[George Brown (Canadian politician)|George Brown]], in exchange for 50% of the patent rights in the British Empire (Brown later retracted his offer to patent the telephone in the U.K. for fear of being ridiculed). The [[Bell Telephone Company#Predecessor to the Bell Company|Bell Patent Association]], composed of Hubbard, Sanders and Bell and which would become the precursor of the Bell Telephone Company (and later, [[AT&amp;T Corporation|AT&amp;T]]), would later assign an approximate 10% interest of its shares to Watson,{{sfn|Bruce|1990|p=291}} in lieu of salary and for his earlier financial support to Bell while they worked together creating their first functional telephone.|group=N}} and the two of them experimented with [[acoustic telegraphy]]. On June 2, 1875, Watson accidentally plucked one of the reeds and Bell, at the receiving end of the wire, heard the overtones of the reed; overtones that would be necessary for transmitting speech. That demonstrated to Bell that only one reed or armature was necessary, not multiple reeds. This led to the &quot;gallows&quot; [[sound-powered telephone]], which could transmit indistinct, voice-like sounds, but not clear speech.

===The race to the patent office===
{{Main|Elisha Gray and Alexander Bell telephone controversy}}
In 1875, Bell developed an [[Acoustic Telegraph|acoustic telegraph]] and drew up a [[patent application]] for it. Since he had agreed to share U.S. profits with his investors Gardiner Hubbard and Thomas Sanders, Bell requested that an associate in Ontario, [[George Brown (Canadian politician)|George Brown]], attempt to patent it in Britain, instructing his lawyers to apply for a patent in the U.S. only after they received word from Britain (Britain would issue patents only for discoveries not previously patented elsewhere).{{sfn|Bruce|1990|pp=158–159}}

&lt;!--not in the right article- belongs in the Gray and Bell controversy---NPOV involved--[[File:Bell-gray-smoking-gun.png|thumb|Excerpts from Elisha Gray's patent caveat of February 14 and Alexander Graham Bell's lab notebook entry of March 8, note their similarity]]---&gt;
[[File:TelephonePatentDrawingBell.jpg|thumb|Alexander Graham Bell's telephone patent&lt;ref&gt;{{Patent|US|174465|Alexander Graham Bell: &quot;Improvement in Telegraphy&quot; filed on February 14, 1876, granted on March 7, 1876.}}&lt;/ref&gt; drawing, March 7, 1876]]

Meanwhile, [[Elisha Gray]] was also experimenting with acoustic telegraphy and thought of a way to transmit speech using a water transmitter. On February 14, 1876, Gray filed a [[Patent caveat|caveat]] with the U.S. Patent Office for a telephone design that used a water transmitter. That same morning, Bell's lawyer filed Bell's application with the patent office. There is considerable debate about who arrived first and Gray later challenged the primacy of Bell's patent. Bell was in Boston on February 14 and did not arrive in Washington until February 26.
[[File:USPTO Telephone Patent No. 174465.jpg|thumb|The master telephone patent, 174465, March 7, 1876]]
Bell's patent 174,465, was issued to Bell on March 7, 1876, by the [[United States Patent and Trademark Office|U.S. Patent Office]]. Bell's patent covered &quot;the method of, and apparatus for, transmitting vocal or other sounds telegraphically ... by causing electrical undulations, similar in form to the vibrations of the air accompanying the said vocal or other sound&quot;{{Sfn|MacLeod|1999|pp=12–13}}{{refn|A copy of a draft of the patent application is shown, described as &quot;probably the most valuable patent ever.&quot;|group=N}} Bell returned to Boston the same day and the next day resumed work, drawing in his notebook a diagram similar to that in Gray's patent caveat.

On March 10, 1876, three days after his patent was issued, Bell succeeded in getting his telephone to work, using a liquid transmitter similar to Gray's design. Vibration of the diaphragm caused a needle to vibrate in the water, varying the [[electrical resistance]] in the circuit. When Bell spoke the sentence &quot;Mr. Watson—Come here—I want to see you&quot; into the liquid transmitter,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://quotegrab.com/telephones/mr-watson-come-here |title=Alexander Graham Bell - Lab notebook pp. 40–41 (image 22) |website=Quotegrab |publisher=IAP Quotegrab |access-date=September 17, 2019|date=August 2, 2019 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Watson, listening at the receiving end in an adjoining room, heard the words clearly.{{Sfn|MacLeod|1999|p=12}}

Although Bell was, and still is, accused of stealing the telephone from Gray,{{sfn|Shulman|2008|p=211}} Bell used Gray's water transmitter design only after Bell's patent had been granted, and only as a [[proof of concept]] scientific experiment,{{sfn|Evenson|2000|p=99}} to prove to his own satisfaction that intelligible &quot;articulate speech&quot; (Bell's words) could be electrically transmitted.{{sfn|Evenson|2000|p=98}} After March 1876, Bell focused on improving the electromagnetic telephone and never used Gray's liquid transmitter in public demonstrations or commercial use.{{sfn|Evenson|2000|p=100}}

The question of priority for the variable resistance feature of the telephone was raised by the examiner before he approved Bell's patent application. He told Bell that his claim for the variable resistance feature was also described in Gray's caveat. Bell pointed to a variable resistance device in his previous application in which he described a cup of mercury, not water. He had filed the mercury application at the patent office a year earlier on February 25, 1875, long before Elisha Gray described the water device. In addition, Gray abandoned his caveat, and because he did not contest Bell's priority, the examiner approved Bell's patent on March 3, 1876. Gray had reinvented the variable resistance telephone, but Bell was the first to write down the idea and the first to test it in a telephone.{{sfn|Evenson|2000|pp=81–82}}

The [[Patent clerk|patent examiner]], Zenas Fisk Wilber, later stated in an [[affidavit]] that he was an alcoholic who was much in debt to Bell's lawyer, [[Marcellus Bailey]], with whom he had served in the Civil War. He claimed he showed Gray's patent caveat to Bailey. Wilber also claimed (after Bell arrived in Washington D.C. from Boston) that he showed Gray's caveat to Bell and that Bell paid him $100 ({{Inflation|US|100|1875|r=-2|fmt=eq}}). Bell claimed they discussed the patent only in general terms, although in a letter to Gray, Bell admitted that he learned some of the technical details. Bell denied in an affidavit that he ever gave Wilber any money.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | newspaper=The Washington Post |title=Mr. Wilbur &quot;confesses&quot;|date= May 22, 1886|page=1|url=http://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Mr._Wilber_Confesses}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Later developments===
[[File:Actor portraying Alexander Graham Bell in an AT&amp;T promotional film (1926).jpg|thumb|Actor portraying Alexander Graham Bell in a 1915 silent film. Shows Bell's first telephone transmitter ([[microphone]]), first displayed at the 1876 Centennial Exposition, Philadelphia.]] 
On March 10, 1876 Bell used &quot;the instrument&quot; in Boston to call Thomas Watson who was in another room but out of earshot. He said, &quot;Mr. Watson, come here – I want to see you&quot; and Watson soon appeared at his side.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Evenson |first=A Edward |date=November 10, 2000 |title=The Telephone Patent Conspiracy of 1876: The Elisha Gray-Alexander Bell Controversy and Its Many Players |url=https://books.google.com/?id=KiJJ7Bp-xtcC&amp;pg=PA99&amp;dq=Mr.+Watson+%E2%80%94+Come+here+%E2%80%94+I+want+to+see+you#v=onepage&amp;q=Mr.%20Watson%20%E2%80%94%20Come%20here%20%E2%80%94%20I%20want%20to%20see%20you&amp;f=false |location= |publisher=McFarland |page=99 |isbn=0786408839}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Continuing his experiments in Brantford, Bell brought home a working model of his telephone. On August 3, 1876, from the telegraph office in Brantford, Ontario, Bell sent a tentative telegram to the village of Mount Pleasant {{convert|4|mi|0|abbr=off|spell=on}} distant, indicating that he was ready. He made a telephone call via telegraph wires and faint voices were heard replying. The following night, he amazed guests as well as his family with a call between the Bell Homestead and the office of the Dominion Telegraph Company in Brantford along an improvised wire strung up along telegraph lines and fences, and laid through a tunnel. This time, guests at the household distinctly heard people in Brantford reading and singing. The third test on August 10, 1876, was made via the telegraph line between Brantford and Paris, Ontario, {{convert|8|mi|0|abbr=off|spell=on}} distant. This test was said by many sources to be the &quot;world's first long distance call&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.telecommunications.ca/alexander-graham-bell-invention-telephone.htm |title=Alexander Graham Bell 1847-1922 Inventor of the Bell System |publisher=Telecommunications Canada |access-date=January 14, 2020 |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.pc.gc.ca/apps/dfhd/page_nhs_eng.aspx?id=1187 |title=Invention of the Telephone National Historic Event |publisher=Parks Canada |access-date=January 14, 2020 |quote=Bell made public demonstrations of his now patented invention, culminating in the world's first long distance call, to Paris, 13 kilometres away, on 10 August}}&lt;/ref&gt; The final test certainly proved that the telephone could work over long distances, at least as a one-way call.
{{Sfn|MacLeod|1999|p=14}} 

The first two-way (reciprocal) conversation over a line occurred between Cambridge and Boston (roughly 2.5 miles) on October 9, 1876.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Popular Mechanics Aug 1912 |url=https://books.google.com/?id=8t0DAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA186&amp;lpg=PA186&amp;dq=The+first+reciprocal+conversation+over+a+line+occurred+in+Boston+on+October+9,+1876.#v=onepage&amp;q=The%20first%20reciprocal%20conversation%20over%20a%20line%20occurred%20in%20Boston%20on%20October%209%2C%201876.&amp;f=false |location=New York |publisher=Popular Mechanics |page=186}}&lt;/ref&gt; During that conversation, Bell was on Kilby Street in Boston and Watson was at the offices of the Walworth Manufacturing Company.&lt;ref&gt;[https://cambridgehistory.org/innovation/First%20Phone%20Call.html First Phone Call]&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[File:Alexander Graham Telephone in Newyork.jpg|thumb|Bell at the opening of the long-distance line from New York to Chicago in 1892]]

Bell and his partners, Hubbard and Sanders, offered to sell the patent outright to Western Union for $100,000. The president of Western Union balked, countering that the telephone was nothing but a toy. Two years later, he told colleagues that if he could get the patent for $25&amp;nbsp;million he would consider it a bargain. By then, the Bell company no longer wanted to sell the patent.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Fenster |first=Julie M. |title=Inventing the Telephone—And Triggering All-Out Patent War |website=American Heritage |url=http://www.americanheritage.com/events/articles/web/20060307-alexander-graham-bell-telephone-patent-telegraph-elisha-gray-thomas-watson-gardiner-hubbard-western-union-thomas-edison.shtml |date=March 7, 2006 |archive-date=March 11, 2006 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20060311000120/http://www.americanheritage.com/events/articles/web/20060307-alexander-graham-bell-telephone-patent-telegraph-elisha-gray-thomas-watson-gardiner-hubbard-western-union-thomas-edison.shtml |access-date=September 19, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bell's investors would become millionaires while he fared well from residuals and at one point had assets of nearly one million dollars.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Winfield |first=Richard |title=Never the Twain Shall Meet: Bell, Gallaudet, and the Communications Debate |location=Washington, D.C. |publisher=Gallaudet University Press |date=1987 |p=21 |isbn=978-0-913580-99-8 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Bell began a series of public demonstrations and lectures to introduce the new invention to the [[scientific community]] as well as the general public. A short time later, [[Bell Telephone Company#Early promotional success|his demonstration of an early telephone prototype]] at the 1876 [[Centennial Exposition]] in [[Philadelphia]] brought the telephone to international attention.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |editor-last=Webb |editor-first=Michael |title=Alexander Graham Bell: Inventor of the Telephone |location=Mississauga, Ontario |publisher=Copp Clark Pitman |date=1991 |p=[https://archive.org/details/alexandergrahamb0000webb/page/15 15] |isbn=978-0-7730-5049-5 |ref=harv |url=https://archive.org/details/alexandergrahamb0000webb/page/15 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Influential visitors to the exhibition included Emperor [[Pedro II of Brazil]]. One of the judges at the Exhibition, [[William Thomson, 1st Baron Kelvin|Sir William Thomson]] (later, Lord Kelvin), a renowned Scottish scientist, described the telephone as &quot;the greatest by far of all the marvels of the electric telegraph&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20170407132609/http://www.ingenious.org.uk/See/Scienceandtechnology/Telecommunications/?target=SeeMedium&amp;ObjectID={26E01AAD-9528-A037-3F8D-18F71C87E944}&amp;s=S1&amp;viewby=images&amp; |title=Bell's centennial telephone transmitter, 1876 |publisher=National Archives UK |access-date=January 14, 2020 |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

On January 14, 1878, at [[Osborne House]], on the [[Isle of Wight]], Bell demonstrated the device to [[Queen Victoria]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.islandecho.co.uk/140-years-since-first-telephone-call-queen-victoria-isle-wight/ |title=140 YEARS SINCE FIRST TELEPHONE CALL TO QUEEN VICTORIA ON THE ISLE OF WIGHT |date=January 14, 2018 |publisher=Island Echo |access-date=January 14, 2020 |quote=He made the UK’s first publicly-witnessed long distance calls, calling Cowes, Southampton and London. Queen Victoria liked the telephone so much she wanted to buy it.}}&lt;/ref&gt; placing calls to Cowes, Southampton and London. These were the first publicly-witnessed long distance telephone calls in the [[UK]]. The queen considered the process to be &quot;quite extraordinary&quot; although the sound was &quot;rather faint&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/technology/connecting-britain/alexander-graham-bell-unveils-telephone/ |title=Alexander Graham Bell demonstrates the newly invented telephone |date=January 13, 2017 |newspaper=The Telegraph |access-date=January 14, 2020 |quote=one of the Queen’s staff wrote to Professor Bell to inform him &quot;how much gratified and surprised the Queen was at the exhibition of the Telephone&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt; She later asked to buy the equipment that was used, but Bell offered to make &quot;a set of telephones&quot; specifically for her.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.loc.gov/item/magbell.30000106/ |title=pdf, Letter from Alexander Graham Bell to Sir Thomas Biddulph, February 1, 1878 |publisher=Library of Congress |access-date=January 14, 2020 |quote=&quot;The instruments at present in Osborne are merely those supplied for ordinary commercial purposes, and it will afford me much pleasure to be permitted to offer to the Queen a set of Telephones to be made expressly for her Majesty's use.&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Ross |first=Stewart |title=Alexander Graham Bell |series=(Scientists who Made History) |location=New York |publisher=Raintree Steck-Vaughn |date=2001 |pp=[https://archive.org/details/alexandergrahamb00ross/page/21 21–22] |isbn=978-0-7398-4415-1 |ref=harv |url=https://archive.org/details/alexandergrahamb00ross/page/21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Bell Telephone Company]] was created in 1877, and by 1886, more than 150,000 people in the U.S. owned telephones. Bell Company engineers made numerous other improvements to the telephone, which emerged as one of the most successful products ever. In 1879, the Bell company acquired Edison's patents for the [[carbon microphone]] from Western Union. This made the telephone practical for longer distances, and it was no longer necessary to shout to be heard at the receiving telephone.

Emperor [[Pedro II of Brazil]] was the first person to buy stock in Bell's company, the Bell Telephone Company. One of the first telephones in a private residence was installed in his palace in [[Petrópolis]], his summer retreat {{convert|40|mi|0|abbr=off|spell=on}} from [[Rio de Janeiro]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Dom Pedro II and America |website=The Library of Congress |url=https://memory.loc.gov/intldl/brhtml/br-1/br-1-5-2.html |access-date=March 7, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In January 1915, Bell made the first ceremonial transcontinental [[telephone call]]. Calling from the [[AT&amp;T Corporation|AT&amp;T]] head office at 15 Dey Street in New York City, Bell was heard by [[Thomas A. Watson|Thomas Watson]] at 333 Grant Avenue in San Francisco. The ''New York Times'' reported:
{{quote|On October 9, 1876, Alexander Graham Bell and Thomas A. Watson talked by telephone to each other over a two-mile wire stretched between Cambridge and Boston. It was the first wire conversation ever held. Yesterday afternoon [on January 25, 1915], the same two men talked by telephone to each other over a 3,400-mile wire between New York and San Francisco. Dr. Bell, the veteran inventor of the telephone, was in New York, and Mr. Watson, his former associate, was on the other side of the continent.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.nytimes.com/learning/general/onthisday/big/0125.html |title=Phone to Pacific From the Atlantic |work=The New York Times |date=January 26, 1915 |access-date=July 21, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

===Competitors===
As is sometimes common in scientific discoveries, simultaneous developments can occur, as evidenced by a number of inventors who were at work on the telephone.{{Sfn|MacLeod|1999|p=19}} Over a period of 18 years, the Bell Telephone Company faced 587 court challenges to its patents, including five that went to the [[Supreme Court of the United States|U.S. Supreme Court]],&lt;ref name=&quot;ATCS&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Who Really Invented The Telephone? |website=Australasian Telephone Collecting Society |url=http://www.telephonecollecting.org/invent.htm |location=Moorebank, NSW, Australia |access-date=April 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; but none was successful in establishing priority over the original Bell patent{{sfn|Groundwater|2005|p=95}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Black |first=Harry |title=Canadian Scientists and Inventors: Biographies of People who made a Difference |url=https://archive.org/details/canadianscientis0000blac |url-access=registration |location=Markham, Ontario |publisher=Pembroke |date=1997 |p=[https://archive.org/details/canadianscientis0000blac/page/19 19] |isbn=978-1-55138-081-0 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the Bell Telephone Company never lost a case that had proceeded to a final trial stage.{{sfn|Groundwater|2005|p=95}} Bell's laboratory notes and family letters were the key to establishing a long lineage to his experiments.{{sfn|Groundwater|2005|p=95}} The Bell company lawyers successfully fought off myriad lawsuits generated initially around the challenges by Elisha Gray and [[Amos Dolbear]]. In personal correspondence to Bell, both Gray and Dolbear had acknowledged his prior work, which considerably weakened their later claims.{{sfn|Mackay|1997|p=179}}

On January 13, 1887, the U.S. Government moved to annul the patent issued to Bell on the grounds of fraud and misrepresentation. After a series of decisions and reversals, the Bell company won a decision in the Supreme Court, though a couple of the original claims from the lower court cases were left undecided.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://caselaw.findlaw.com/us-supreme-court/167/224.html |title=US v. AMERICAN BELL TEL CO, (1897) |date=May 10, 1897 |website=Findlaw |access-date=July 28, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://supreme.justia.com/us/128/315/case.html |title=United States V. American Bell Telephone Co., 128 U.S. 315 (1888) |website=Jusrtia US Supreme Court |date=November 12, 1885 |access-date=July 28, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; By the time that the trial wound its way through nine years of legal battles, the U.S. prosecuting attorney had died and the two Bell patents (No. 174,465 dated March 7, 1876, and No. 186,787 dated January 30, 1877) were no longer in effect, although the presiding judges agreed to continue the proceedings due to the case's importance as a [[stare decisis|precedent]]. With a change in administration and charges of conflict of interest (on both sides) arising from the original trial, the [[United States Attorney General|US Attorney General]] dropped the lawsuit on November 30, 1897, leaving several issues undecided [[Merit (legal)|on the merits]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=The United States Government vs. Alexander Graham Bell. An important acknowledgment for Antonio Meucci |journal=[[Bulletin of Science, Technology &amp; Society]] |volume=22 |issue=6 |pages=426–442 |date=December 2002 |doi=10.1177/0270467602238886 |last1=Catania |first1=Basilio|url=https://semanticscholar.org/paper/f8b17817fe5ae69914d47093a9bf4105a0e99897 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

During a deposition filed for the 1887 trial, Italian inventor [[Antonio Meucci]] also claimed to have created the first working model of a telephone in Italy in 1834. In 1886, in the first of three cases in which he was involved,{{refn|Meucci was not involved in the final trial.{{clarify|date=June 2018|reason=What final trial is this talking about?}}|group=N}} Meucci took the stand as a witness in the hope of establishing his invention's priority. Meucci's testimony in this case was disputed due to a lack of material evidence for his inventions, as his working models were purportedly lost at the laboratory of [[ADT Security Services|American District Telegraph]] (ADT) of New York, which was later incorporated as a subsidiary of Western Union in 1901.&lt;ref name=&quot;Catania&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last=Catania |first=Basilio |url=http://www.chezbasilio.org/meucci_faq.htm#25 |title=Antonio Meucci – Questions and Answers: What did Meucci to bring his invention to the public? |website=Chezbasilio.org |date=November 6, 2009 |access-date=September 19, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ADT&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.adt.com/about-adt/history |title=Our History |website=ADT |access-date=September 18, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Meucci's work, like many other inventors of the period, was based on earlier acoustic principles and despite evidence of earlier experiments, the final case involving Meucci was eventually dropped upon Meucci's death.{{sfn|Bruce|1990|pp=271–272}} However, due to the efforts of Congressman [[Vito Fossella]], the [[U.S. House of Representatives]] on June 11, 2002, stated that Meucci's &quot;work in the invention of the telephone should be acknowledged&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;guardian.co.uk&quot;&gt;{{cite news |author=Rory Carroll |title=Bell did not invent telephone, US rules |url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2002/jun/17/humanities.internationaleducationnews |work=The Guardian|date=June 17, 2002|access-date=October 25, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://thomas.loc.gov/cgi-bin/query/z?c107 &quot;H.RES.269: Resolution 269.&quot;] ''thomas.loc.gov.'' Retrieved: July 28, 2010. {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150713175614/http://thomas.loc.gov/cgi-bin/query/z?c107 |date=July 13, 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.chezbasilio.it/us_congr_rec.htm |title=Congressional Record – Speech by Prof. Basillio |date=September 5, 2001 |archive-date=July 17, 2011 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110717032953/http://www.chezbasilio.it/us_congr_rec.htm |access-date=September 18, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; This did not put an end to the still-contentious issue.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Antonio Meucci (1808–1889) |website=Italian Historical Society of America |url=http://www.italianhistorical.org/page42.html |access-date=September 18, 2015 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20151015195124/http://www.italianhistorical.org/page42.html |archive-date=October 15, 2015 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; Some modern scholars do not agree with the claims that Bell's work on the telephone was influenced by Meucci's inventions.&lt;ref name=Bellis&gt;{{cite web |first=Mary |last=Bellis |url=http://inventors.about.com/library/inventors/bl_Antonio_Meucci.htm |title=The History of the Telephone – Antonio Meucci |website=About.com Inventors |access-date=December 29, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{refn|Tomas Farley also writes that &quot;Nearly every scholar agrees that Bell and Watson were the first to transmit intelligible speech by electrical means. Others transmitted a sound or a click or a buzz but our boys [Bell and Watson] were the first to transmit speech one could understand.&quot;&lt;ref name=Bellis/&gt;|group=N}}

The value of the Bell patent was acknowledged throughout the world, and patent applications were made in most major countries, but when Bell delayed the German patent application, the electrical firm of [[Siemens AG|Siemens &amp; Halske (S&amp;H)]] set up a rival manufacturer of Bell telephones under their own patent. The Siemens company produced near-identical copies of the Bell telephone without having to pay royalties.{{sfn|Mackay|1997|p=178}} The establishment of the [[International Bell Telephone Company]] in Brussels, Belgium in 1880, as well as a series of agreements in other countries eventually consolidated a global telephone operation. The strain put on Bell by his constant appearances in court, necessitated by the legal battles, eventually resulted in his resignation from the company.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Parker |first=Steve |title=Alexander Graham Bell and the Telephone |journal=Scientific American |volume=102 |issue=23 |series=(Science Discoveries) |date=1995 |p=[https://archive.org/details/alexandergrahamb00park/page/23 23] |isbn=978-0-7910-3004-2 |ref=harv |bibcode=1910SciAm.102..462. |doi=10.1038/scientificamerican06041910-462 |url=https://archive.org/details/alexandergrahamb00park/page/23 }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{refn| Many of the lawsuits became rancorous, with Elisha Gray becoming particularly bitter over Bell's ascendancy in the telephone debate, but Bell refused to launch a countersuit for libel.{{cn|date=February 2020}}|group=N}}

{{Further|The Telephone Cases}}

==Family life==
[[File:Alexander Graham Bell and family.jpg|thumb|alt=A distinguished bearded man, his young elegant wife next to him and their two young daughters poise for a formal portrait|Alexander Graham Bell, his wife [[Mabel Gardiner Hubbard]], and their daughters Elsie (left) and Marian ca. 1885]]
{{Commons|Alexander_Graham_Bell#General_photos_of_or_about_Alexander_Graham_Bell_and_his_family|Bell and his family members}}
[[File:Brodhead-Bell-Morton Mansion.jpg|thumb|alt=A three-story gray mansion, with a covered front entrance|The Brodhead–Bell mansion, the Bell family residence in Washington, D.C., from 1882 to 1889{{sfn|Bruce|1990|pp=297–299}}]]

On July 11, 1877, a few days after the [[Bell Telephone Company]] was established, Bell married [[Mabel Gardiner Hubbard|Mabel Hubbard]] (1857–1923) at the Hubbard estate in [[Cambridge, Massachusetts]]. His wedding present to his bride was to turn over 1,487 of his 1,497 shares in the newly formed Bell Telephone Company.{{sfn|Eber|1991|p=44}} Shortly thereafter, the newlyweds embarked on a year-long honeymoon in Europe. During that excursion, Bell took a handmade model of his telephone with him, making it a &quot;working holiday&quot;. The courtship had begun years earlier; however, Bell waited until he was more financially secure before marrying. Although the telephone appeared to be an &quot;instant&quot; success, it was not initially a profitable venture and Bell's main sources of income were from lectures until after 1897.{{sfn|Dunn|1990|p=28}} One unusual request exacted by his fiancée was that he use &quot;Alec&quot; rather than the family's earlier familiar name of &quot;Aleck&quot;. From 1876, he would sign his name &quot;Alec Bell&quot;.{{sfn|Mackay|1997|p=120}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Mrs. A.G. Bell Dies. Inspired Telephone. Deaf Girl's Romance With Distinguished Inventor Was Due to Her Affliction |work=The New York Times |date=January 4, 1923}}{{dead link|date=September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; They had four children:
* Elsie May Bell (1878–1964) who married [[Gilbert Hovey Grosvenor]] of [[National Geographic Society|National Geographic]] fame.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Dr. Gilbert H. Grosvenor Dies |work=The New York Times |agency=Canadian Press |url=https://www.nytimes.com/1966/02/05/archives/dr-gilbert-h-grosvenor-dies-head-of-national-geographic-90-editor.html |date=February 5, 1966 |access-date=September 18, 2015 |url-access=subscription  |quote=Dr. [[Gilbert H. Grosvenor]] ... died on the [[Cape Breton Island]] estate once owned by his father-in-law, the inventor Alexander Graham Bell.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Mrs. Gilbert Grosvenor Dead |work=The New York Times |url=https://www.nytimes.com/1964/12/27/mrs-gilbert-grosvenor-dead.html |date=December 27, 1964 |access-date=September 18, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Marian Hubbard Bell (1880–1962) who was referred to as &quot;Daisy&quot;. Married [[David Fairchild]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Grosvenor |first1=Edwin S. |first2=Morgan |last2=Wesson |title=Alexander Graham Bell: The Life and Times of the Man Who Invented the Telephone |location=New York |publisher=Harry N. Abrahms |date=1997 |p=[https://archive.org/details/alexandergrahamb00gros/page/104 104] |isbn=978-0-8109-4005-5 |ref=harv |url=https://archive.org/details/alexandergrahamb00gros/page/104 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Mrs. David Fairchild, 82, Dead; Daughter of Bell, Phone Inventor |work=The New York Times |url=https://www.nytimes.com/1962/09/25/archives/mrs-david-fairchild-82-dead-daughter-of-bell-phone-inventor.html |date=September 25, 1962 |agency=Canadian Press |url-access=subscription }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{refn|Marian was born only days after Bell and his assistant [[Charles Sumner Tainter|Sumner Tainter]] had successfully tested their new wireless telecommunication invention at their [[Volta Laboratory and Bureau|Volta Laboratory]], one which Bell would name as his greatest achievement. Bell was so ecstatic that he wanted to jointly name his new invention and his new daughter [[Photophone]] (Greek: &quot;''light–sound''&quot;),{{sfn|Grosvenor|Wesson|1997|p=104}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Carson |first=Mary Kay |date=2007 |chapter= |title=Alexander Graham Bell: Giving Voice To The World |url=https://archive.org/details/alexandergrahamb0000cars |url-access=registration |series=Sterling Biographies |location=New York |publisher=Sterling Publishing |p=[https://archive.org/details/alexandergrahamb0000cars/page/77 77] |isbn=978-1-4027-3230-0 |oclc=182527281 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bell wrote: &quot;Only think!—Two babies in one week! Mabel's baby was light enough at birth but mine was LIGHT ITSELF! Mabel's baby screamed inarticulately but mine spoke with distinct enunciation from the first.&quot; Bell's suggested scientific name for their new infant daughter did not go over well with Marian's mother, [[Mabel Gardiner Hubbard|Mabel Gardiner Hubbard Bell]].{{sfn|Grosvenor|Wesson|1997|p=104}}|group=N}}
* Two sons who died in infancy (Edward in 1881 and Robert in 1883).
The Bell family home was in Cambridge, Massachusetts, until 1880 when Bell's father-in-law bought a house in Washington, D.C.; in 1882 he bought a home in the same city for Bell's family, so they could be with him while he attended to the numerous court cases involving patent disputes.{{sfn|Gray|2006|pp=202–205}}

Bell was a [[British subject]] throughout his early life in Scotland and later in Canada until 1882 when he became a [[naturalized citizen]] of the United States. In 1915, he characterized his status as: &quot;I am not one of those hyphenated Americans who claim allegiance to two countries.&quot;{{sfn|Bruce|1990|p=90}} Despite this declaration, Bell has been proudly claimed as a &quot;native son&quot; by all three countries he resided in: the United States, Canada, and the United Kingdom&lt;!-- Bell also lived in London, so 'UK' is more appropriate than 'Scotland' --&gt;.{{sfn|Bruce|1990|pp=471–472}}

By 1885, a new summer retreat was contemplated. That summer, the Bells had a vacation on [[Cape Breton Island]] in Nova Scotia, spending time at the small village of [[Baddeck, Nova Scotia|Baddeck]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Bethune |first=Jocelyn |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=YmtoPgAACAAJ |title=Historic Baddeck |series=(Images of our Past) |location=Halifax, Nova Scotia |publisher=Nimbus Publishing |date=2009 |p=2 |isbn=978-1-55109-706-0 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; Returning in 1886, Bell started building an estate on a point across from Baddeck, overlooking [[Bras d'Or Lake]].{{sfn|Bethune|2009|p=92}} By 1889, a large house, christened ''The Lodge'' was completed and two years later, a larger complex of buildings, including a new laboratory,{{sfn|Bethune|2009|p=2}} were begun that the Bells would name [[Beinn Bhreagh]] ([[Scottish Gaelic|Gaelic]]: ''beautiful mountain'') after Bell's ancestral [[Scottish Highlands|Scottish highlands]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Tulloch |first=Judith |title=The Bell Family in Baddeck: Alexander Graham Bell and Mabel Bell in Cape Breton |location=Halifax, Nova Scotia |publisher=Formac Publishing |date=2006 |pp=25–27 |isbn=978-0-88780-713-8 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{refn|Under the direction of the Boston architects, [[Cabot, Everett &amp; Mead]], a Nova Scotia company, Rhodes, Curry &amp; Company, carried out the actual construction.|group=N}} Bell also built the [[Bell Boatyard]] on the estate, employing up to 40 people building experimental craft as well as wartime lifeboats and workboats for the [[Royal Canadian Navy]] and pleasure craft for the Bell family. He was an enthusiastic boater, and Bell and his family sailed or rowed a long series of vessels on [[Bras d'Or Lake]], ordering additional vessels from the [[H.W. Embree and Sons]] boatyard in [[Port Hawkesbury, Nova Scotia]]. In his final, and some of his most productive years, Bell split his residency between Washington, D.C., where he and his family initially resided for most of the year, and Beinn Bhreagh, where they spent increasing amounts of time.{{Sfn|MacLeod|1999|p=22}}

Until the end of his life, Bell and his family would alternate between the two homes, but ''Beinn Bhreagh'' would, over the next 30 years, become more than a summer home as Bell became so absorbed in his experiments that his annual stays lengthened. Both Mabel and Bell became immersed in the [[Baddeck]] community and were accepted by the villagers as &quot;their own&quot;.{{sfn|Bethune|2009|p=2}}{{refn| In one memorable incident, the newly arrived Bells were walking down one of Baddeck's central streets when Bell peered into a storefront window and saw a frustrated shopkeeper fiddling with his problematic telephone. Bell quickly disassembled it and effected a repair, to the owner's amazement. When asked how he was able to do so Bell only needed to introduce himself.|group=N}} The Bells were still in residence at ''Beinn Bhreagh'' when the [[Halifax Explosion]] occurred on December 6, 1917. Mabel and Bell mobilized the community to help victims in Halifax.{{Sfn|Tulloch|2006|p=42}}

{{Further|Beinn Bhreagh, Nova Scotia}}

==Later inventions==
[[File:AG Bell 1.jpg|thumb|Alexander Graham Bell in his later years]]
{{Commons category|Alexander_Graham_Bell#Inventions|Bell's many inventions}}

Although Alexander Graham Bell is most often associated with the invention of the telephone, his interests were extremely varied. According to one of his biographers, [[Charlotte Gray (author)|Charlotte Gray]], Bell's work ranged &quot;unfettered across the scientific landscape&quot; and he often went to bed voraciously reading the ''Encyclopædia Britannica'', scouring it for new areas of interest.{{sfn|Gray|2006|p=219}} The range of Bell's inventive genius is represented only in part by the 18 patents granted in his name alone and the 12 he shared with his collaborators. These included 14 for the telephone and telegraph, four for the [[photophone]], one for the [[phonograph]], five for aerial vehicles, four for &quot;hydroairplanes&quot;, and two for [[selenium]] cells. Bell's inventions spanned a wide range of interests and included a metal jacket to assist in breathing, the [[audiometer]] to detect minor hearing problems, a device to locate icebergs, investigations on how to separate salt from seawater, and work on finding [[alternative fuel]]s.

Bell worked extensively in [[medical research]] and invented techniques for teaching speech to the deaf. During his [[Volta Laboratory and Bureau|Volta Laboratory]] period, Bell and his associates considered impressing a [[magnetic field]] on a record as a means of reproducing sound. Although the trio briefly experimented with the concept, they could not develop a workable prototype. They abandoned the idea, never realizing they had glimpsed a basic principle which would one day find its application in the [[tape recorder]], the [[hard disc]] and [[floppy disc]] drive, and other [[magnetic medium|magnetic media]].

Bell's own home used a primitive form of air conditioning, in which fans blew currents of air across great blocks of ice. He also anticipated modern concerns with fuel shortages and industrial pollution. [[Methane]] gas, he reasoned, could be produced from the waste of farms and factories. At his Canadian estate in Nova Scotia, he experimented with [[composting toilet]]s and devices to capture water from the atmosphere. In a magazine interview published shortly before his death, he reflected on the possibility of using [[Photovoltaic module|solar panels]] to heat houses.

===Photophone===
{{Main|Photophone}}
[[File:Photophony1.jpg|thumb|Photophone receiver, one half of Bell's wireless [[optical communication]] system, ca. 1880]]

Bell and his assistant [[Charles Sumner Tainter]] jointly invented a wireless telephone, named a [[photophone]], which allowed for the transmission of both sounds and normal human conversations on a beam of [[light]].{{sfn|Bruce|1990|p=336}}&lt;ref name=&quot;SDU&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Jones |first=Newell |url=http://history.sandiego.edu/gen/recording/ar304.html |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20020219111153/http://history.sandiego.edu/gen/recording/ar304.html |url-status=dead |archive-date=February 19, 2002 |title=First 'Radio' Built by San Diego Resident Partner of Inventor of Telephone: Keeps Notebook of Experiences With Bell |location=San Diego, California |website=Evening Tribune |date=July 31, 1937 |access-date=November 26, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Both men later became full associates in the [[Volta Laboratory and Bureau#Laboratory projects|Volta Laboratory Association]].

On June 21, 1880, Bell's assistant transmitted a wireless voice telephone message a considerable distance, from the roof of the [[Franklin School (Washington, D.C.)|Franklin School]] in Washington, D.C., to Bell at the window of his laboratory, some {{convert|213|m|round=5|order=flip}} away, 19 years before the first voice radio transmissions.{{sfn|Carson|2007|pp=76–78}}{{sfn|Bruce|1990|p=338}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Groth |first=Mike |url=http://www.bluehaze.com.au/modlight/GrothArticle1.htm |title=Photophones Revisted |journal=Amateur Radio |date=April 1987 |pp=12–17 |access-date=September 19, 2015 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150802001855/http://www.bluehaze.com.au/modlight/GrothArticle1.htm |archivedate=August 2, 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Mims III |first=Forest M. |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=zoaSp1BJu50C |title=The First Century of Lightwave Communications |journal=Fiber Optics Weekly Update |date=February 10–26, 1982 |pp=11 of 6–23 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Bell believed the photophone's principles were his life's &quot;greatest achievement&quot;, telling a reporter shortly before his death that the photophone was &quot;the greatest invention [I have] ever made, greater than the telephone&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |last1=Phillipson |first1=Donald J.C. |first2=Laura |last2=Neilson |title=Alexander Graham Bell |encyclopedia=[[The Canadian Encyclopedia]] |publisher=[[Historica Canada]] |edition=online |date=March 4, 2015 |url=http://www.thecanadianencyclopedia.com/en/article/alexander-graham-bell/ |access-date=September 19, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The photophone was a precursor to the [[fiber-optic communication]] systems which achieved popular worldwide usage in the 1980s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite report|last=Morgan |first=Tim J. |title=The Fiber Optic Backbone |publisher=[[University of North Texas]] |date=2011 |url=https://classes.lt.unt.edu/Summer_10W_2011/LTEC_4550_020/tjm0146/Fiber%20Optic%20Backbone%20.docx |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150925132141/https://classes.lt.unt.edu/Summer_10W_2011/LTEC_4550_020/tjm0146/Fiber%20Optic%20Backbone%20.docx |url-status=dead |archive-date=September 25, 2015 |access-date=September 19, 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AmericanScientist-1984.V72.No1&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last=Miller |first=Stewart E. |jstor=i27852430 |title=Lightwaves and Telecommunication|journal=[[American Scientist]] |volume=72 |issue=1 |date=January–February 1984 |pp=66–71}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its master patent was issued in December 1880, many decades before the photophone's principles came into popular use.

===Metal detector===
[[File:Telephone Inventor’s Voice Heard in Restored Recording « Science World.theora.ogv|thumb|Bell's voice, from a [[Volta Laboratory and Bureau|Volta Laboratory]] recording in 1885. Restored by the Smithsonian in 2013.]]

Bell is also credited with developing one of the early versions of a [[metal detector]] through the use of an induction balance, after the [[Assassination of James A. Garfield|shooting]] of [[President of the United States|U.S. President]] [[James A. Garfield]] in 1881. According to some accounts, the metal detector worked flawlessly in tests but did not find [[Charles J. Guiteau|Guiteau]]'s bullet, partly because the metal bed frame on which the President was lying disturbed the instrument, resulting in static.{{sfn|Grosvenor|Wesson|1997|p=107}} Garfield's surgeons, led by self-appointed chief physician [[Doctor Willard Bliss]], were skeptical of the device, and ignored Bell's requests to move the President to a bed not fitted with metal springs.{{sfn|Grosvenor|Wesson|1997|p=107}} Alternatively, although Bell had detected a slight sound on his first test, the bullet may have been lodged too deeply to be detected by the crude apparatus.{{sfn|Grosvenor|Wesson|1997|p=107}}

Bell's own detailed account, presented to the [[American Association for the Advancement of Science]] in 1882, differs in several particulars from most of the many and varied versions now in circulation, by concluding that extraneous metal was not to blame for failure to locate the bullet. Perplexed by the peculiar results he had obtained during an examination of Garfield, Bell &quot;proceeded to the [[White House|Executive Mansion]] the next morning&amp;nbsp;... to ascertain from the surgeons whether they were perfectly sure that all metal had been removed from the neighborhood of the bed. It was then recollected that underneath the horse-hair mattress on which the President lay was another mattress composed of steel wires. Upon obtaining a duplicate, the mattress was found to consist of a sort of net of woven steel wires, with large meshes. The extent of the [area that produced a response from the detector] having been so small, as compared with the area of the bed, it seemed reasonable to conclude that the steel mattress had produced no detrimental effect.&quot; In a footnote, Bell adds, &quot;The death of President Garfield and the subsequent ''post-mortem'' examination, however, proved that the bullet was at too great a distance from the surface to have affected our apparatus.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Bell |first=Alexander Graham |date=1882 |title=Upon the electrical experiments to determine the location of the bullet in the body of the late President Garfield; and upon a successful form of induction balance for the painless detection of metallic masses in the human body |journal=American Journal of Science |volume=25 |issue=145 |pages=22–61 |url=https://archive.org/details/uponelectricalex00bell |access-date=April 29, 2013 |ref=harv|bibcode=1883AmJS...25...22B |doi=10.2475/ajs.s3-25.145.22 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Hydrofoils===
{{Main|HD-4}}
[[File:Bell HD-4.jpg|thumb|Bell [[HD-4]] on a test run ca. 1919]]

The March 1906 ''[[Scientific American]]'' article by American pioneer William E. Meacham explained the basic principle of [[hydrofoil]]s and [[Hydroplane (boat)|hydroplanes]]. Bell considered the invention of the hydroplane as a very significant achievement. Based on information gained from that article, he began to sketch concepts of what is now called a hydrofoil boat. Bell and assistant [[Frederick W. Baldwin|Frederick W. &quot;Casey&quot; Baldwin]] began hydrofoil experimentation in the summer of 1908 as a possible aid to airplane takeoff from water. Baldwin studied the work of the Italian inventor [[Enrico Forlanini]] and began testing models. This led him and Bell to the development of practical hydrofoil watercraft.

During his world tour of 1910–11, Bell and Baldwin met with Forlanini in France. They had rides in the Forlanini hydrofoil boat over [[Lake Maggiore]]. Baldwin described it as being as smooth as flying. On returning to Baddeck, a number of initial concepts were built as experimental models, including the ''Dhonnas Beag'' (Scottish Gaelic for ''little devil''), the first self-propelled Bell-Baldwin hydrofoil.{{sfn|Boileau|2004|p=18}} The experimental boats were essentially proof-of-concept prototypes that culminated in the more substantial [[HD-4]], powered by [[Renault]] engines. A top speed of {{convert|54|mph|km/h}} was achieved, with the hydrofoil exhibiting rapid acceleration, good stability, and steering, along with the ability to take waves without difficulty.{{sfn|Boileau|2004|pp=28–30}} In 1913, Dr. Bell hired Walter Pinaud, a Sydney yacht designer and builder as well as the proprietor of Pinaud's Yacht Yard in [[Westmount, Nova Scotia]], to work on the pontoons of the HD-4. Pinaud soon took over the boatyard at Bell Laboratories on Beinn Bhreagh, Bell's estate near [[Baddeck, Nova Scotia]]. Pinaud's experience in boat-building enabled him to make useful design changes to the HD-4. After the First World War, work began again on the HD-4. Bell's report to the [[United States Navy|U.S. Navy]] permitted him to obtain two {{convert|350|hp|kW|abbr=off}} engines in July 1919. On September 9, 1919, the HD-4 set a world marine speed record of {{convert|70.86|mph|km/h|abbr=off}},{{sfn|Boileau|2004|p=30}} a record which stood for ten years.

===Aeronautics===
{{Main|Aerial Experiment Association|AEA Silver Dart}}
[[File:AEA Silver Dart.jpg|thumb|AEA Silver Dart ca.&amp;nbsp;1909]]

In 1891, Bell had begun experiments to develop motor-powered heavier-than-air aircraft. The AEA was first formed as Bell shared the vision to fly with his wife, who advised him to seek &quot;young&quot; help as Bell was at the age of 60.

In 1898, Bell experimented with [[tetrahedral]] [[box kite]]s and wings constructed of multiple compound [[tetrahedral kite]]s covered in maroon silk.{{refn|Bell was inspired in part by Australian aeronautical engineer [[Lawrence Hargrave]]'s work with man-carrying box kites.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Technical Gazette |location=New South Wales, Australia |date=1924 |p=46}}{{Citation needed|date=September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hargrave declined to take patents on his inventions, similar to Bell's decision not to file patents on some of his inventions. Bell also chose maroon-colored silk as it would show up clearly against the light-colored sky in his photographic studies.|group=&quot;N&quot;}} The tetrahedral wings were named ''Cygnet'' I, II, and III, and were flown both unmanned and manned (''Cygnet I'' crashed during a flight carrying Selfridge) in the period from 1907–1912. Some of Bell's kites are on display at the [[Alexander Graham Bell honors and tributes|Alexander Graham Bell National Historic Site]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://ns1763.ca/victco/bellmusbbm.html &quot;Nova Scotia's Electric Scrapbook.&quot;] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090417080338/http://ns1763.ca/victco/bellmusbbm.html |date=April 17, 2009 }} ''ns1763.ca''. Retrieved: December 29, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

Bell was a supporter of [[aerospace engineering]] research through the [[Aerial Experiment Association]] (AEA), officially formed at Baddeck, Nova Scotia, in October 1907 at the suggestion of his wife [[Mabel Gardiner Hubbard|Mabel]] and with her financial support after the sale of some of her real estate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Gillis |first=Rannie |url=http://www.capebretonpost.com/Columnists/2008-09-29/article-781848/Mabel-Bell-was-a-focal-figure-in-the-first-flight-of-the-Silver-Dart/1 |title=Mabel Bell Was A Focal Figure In The First Flight of the Silver Dart |work=Cape Breton Post |location=Sydney, Nova Scotia |date=September 29, 2008 |access-date=June 12, 2010 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://archive.is/20160724050315/http://www.capebretonpost.com/Columnists/2008-09-29/article-781848/Mabel-Bell-was-a-focal-figure-in-the-first-flight-of-the-Silver-Dart/1 |archivedate=July 24, 2016  }}&lt;/ref&gt; The AEA was headed by Bell and the founding members were four young men: American [[Glenn H. Curtiss]], a motorcycle manufacturer at the time and who held the title &quot;world's fastest man&quot;, having ridden his self-constructed motor bicycle around in the shortest time, and who was later awarded the [[Scientific American|Scientific American Trophy]] for the first official one-kilometre flight in the [[Western hemisphere]], and who later became a world-renowned airplane manufacturer; Lieutenant [[Thomas Selfridge]], an official observer from the U.S. Federal government and one of the few people in the army who believed that aviation was the future; [[Frederick W. Baldwin]], the first Canadian and first British subject to pilot a public flight in [[Hammondsport, New York|Hammondsport]], New York; and [[J. A .D. McCurdy]]–Baldwin and McCurdy being new engineering graduates from the [[University of Toronto]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine |last1=|first1=|date=February 27, 1959|title=Canada's Golden Anniversary |magazine=[[Flight International|Flight]] |volume=75|issue=2614|page=280|url= http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1959/1959%20-%200579.html|accessdate=August 28, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The AEA's work progressed to heavier-than-air machines, applying their knowledge of kites to gliders. Moving to Hammondsport, the group then designed and built the ''[[AEA Red Wing|Red Wing]]'', framed in bamboo and covered in red silk and powered by a small [[Engine cooling|air-cooled]] engine.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Phillips |first=Allan |title=Into the 20th Century: 1900/1910 |series=(Canada's Illustrated Heritage) |location=Toronto, Ontario |publisher=Natural Science of Canada |date=1977 |p=95 |isbn=978-0-919644-22-9 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; On March 12, 1908, over [[Keuka Lake]], the biplane lifted off on the first public flight in North America.{{refn|&quot;Selfridge Aerodrome Sails Steadily for {{convert|319|ft|m}}.&quot; ''[[Washington Post]]'' May 13, 1908.|group=N}}{{refn| At 25 to 30 Miles an Hour. First Public Trip of Heavier-than-air Car in America. Professor Alexander Graham Bell's New Machine, Built After Plans by Lieutenant Selfridge, Shown to Be Practicable by Flight Over [[Keuka Lake]]. Portion of Tail Gives Way, Bringing the Test to an End. Views of an Expert. [[Hammondsport, New York|Hammondsport]], New York, March 12, 1908.|group=N}} The innovations that were incorporated into this design included a cockpit enclosure and [[Rudder|tail rudder]] (later variations on the original design would add ailerons as a means of control). One of the AEA's inventions, a practical wingtip form of the [[aileron]], was to become a standard component on all aircraft.{{refn|The aileron had been conceived of as early as 1868 by British inventor [[Matthew Piers Watt Boulton|M.P.W. Boulton]] and was also created independently by [[Robert Esnault-Pelterie]] and several others.|group=&quot;N&quot;}} The ''White Wing'' and ''June Bug'' were to follow and by the end of 1908, over 150 flights without mishap had been accomplished. However, the AEA had depleted its initial reserves and only a [[Mabel Gardiner Hubbard#Support to aeronautical research|$15,000 grant from Mrs. Bell]] allowed it to continue with experiments.{{sfn|Phillips|1977|p=96}} Lt. Selfridge had also become the first person killed in a powered heavier-than-air flight in a crash of the [[Wright Model A|Wright Flyer]] at [[Fort Myer]], [[Virginia]], on September 17, 1908.

Their final aircraft design, the ''[[AEA Silver Dart|Silver Dart]]'', embodied all of the advancements found in the earlier machines. On February 23, 1909, Bell was present as the ''Silver Dart'' flown by J. A. D. McCurdy from the frozen ice of Bras d'Or made the first aircraft flight in Canada.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine |last1=|first1=|date=October 19, 1956|title=Link with Canadian Pioneers |magazine=[[Flight International|Flight]] |volume=70|issue=2491|page=642|url= http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1956/1956%20-%201488.html|accessdate=August 28, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bell had worried that the flight was too dangerous and had arranged for a doctor to be on hand. With the successful flight, the AEA disbanded and the ''Silver Dart'' would revert to Baldwin and McCurdy, who began the Canadian Aerodrome Company and would later demonstrate the aircraft to the [[Canadian Army]].{{sfn|Phillips|1977|pp=96–97}}

==Eugenics==
&lt;!--Bell's work with Eugenics is still considered contentious. Any submissions to this section should be documented in the &quot;talk page&quot; associated with this article.--&gt;
Bell was connected with the [[eugenics]] movement in the United States. In his lecture ''Memoir upon the formation of a deaf variety of the human race'' presented to the [[National Academy of Sciences]] on November 13, 1883 (the year of his election as a [[Member of the National Academy of Sciences]]), he noted that congenitally deaf parents were more likely to produce deaf children and tentatively suggested that couples where both parties were deaf should not marry.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Bell |first=Alexander Graham |url=http://saveourdeafschools.org/race.pdf |title=Memoir: Upon the Formation of a Deaf Variety of the Human Race |publisher=National Academy of Sciences |date=1883 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, it was his hobby of livestock breeding which led to his appointment to biologist [[David Starr Jordan]]'s Committee on Eugenics, under the auspices of the [[American Breeders' Association]]. The committee unequivocally extended the principle to humans.{{sfn|Bruce|1990|pp=410–417}} From 1912 until 1918, he was the chairman of the board of scientific advisers to the [[Eugenics Record Office]] associated with [[Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory]] in New York, and regularly attended meetings. In 1921, he was the honorary president of the [[Second International Congress of Eugenics]] held under the auspices of the [[American Museum of Natural History]] in New York. Organizations such as these advocated passing laws (with success in some states) that established the [[compulsory sterilization]] of people deemed to be, as Bell called them, a &quot;defective variety of the human race&quot;. By the late 1930s, about half the states in the U.S. had eugenics laws, and [[Eugenics in California|California's compulsory sterilization law]] was used as a model for that of [[Nazi Germany]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author-link=Clarence Lusane |last=Lusane |first=Clarence |title=Hitler's Black Victims: The Historical Experiences of Afro-Germans, European Blacks, Africans, and African Americans in the Nazi Era |location=Hove, East Sussex, UK |publisher=Psychology Press |date=2003 |p=[https://archive.org/details/hitlersblackvict00clar/page/124 124] |isbn=978-0-415932-950 |ref=harv |url=https://archive.org/details/hitlersblackvict00clar/page/124 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy and honors==
{{Main|Volta Laboratory and Bureau|Alexander Graham Bell honors and tributes}}
[[File:Bell Statue in front of the Brantford Bell Telephone Building 0.98.jpg|thumb|Bell statue by [[Cleeve Horne|A.&amp;nbsp;E. Cleeve Horne]], similar in style to the [[Lincoln Memorial]], in the front portico of the Bell Telephone Building of Brantford, Ontario, ''[[The Telephone City]]''.{{refn|
The [[Charles Fleetford Sise]] Chapter of the [[Pioneers, a Volunteer Network|Telephone Pioneers of America]] commissioned and dedicated the large bronze statue of Bell in the front portico of [[Brantford]], Ontario's new Bell Telephone Building plant on June 17, 1949. Attending the formal ceremony were Bell's daughter, Mrs. Gillbert Grosvenor, [[Frederick Johnson (businessman)|Frederick Johnson]], President of the [[Bell Canada|Bell Telephone Company of Canada]], T.N. Lacy, President of the Telephone Pioneers, and Brantford Mayor Walter J. Dowden. To each side of the portico facing the monument are the engraved inscriptions &quot;In Grateful Recognition of the Inventor of the Telephone&quot;. Its dedication was broadcast live nationally by the [[Canadian Broadcasting Corporation]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Ireland |first=Carolyn |title=The Portrait Studio House |work=[[The Globe and Mail]] |date=February 27, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Daughter Unveils Inventor's Statue: Bronze Figure Is Dedicated By Phone Pioneers |work=[[Brantford Expositor]] |date=June 18, 1949}}&lt;/ref&gt;|group=&quot;N&quot;}} (Courtesy: Brantford Heritage Inventory, City of Brantford, Ontario, Canada)]]

Honors and tributes flowed to Bell in increasing numbers as his invention became ubiquitous and his personal fame grew. Bell received numerous honorary degrees from colleges and universities to the point that the requests almost became burdensome.&lt;ref name=&quot;AGB Family Papers&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=About this Collection |website=Alexander Graham Bell Family Papers |publisher=Library of Congress |url=https://www.loc.gov/collection/alexander-graham-bell-papers/about-this-collection/#overview |access-date=September 18, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; During his life, he also received dozens of major awards, medals, and other tributes. These included statuary monuments to both him and the new form of communication his telephone created, including the [[Bell Telephone Memorial]] erected in his honor in ''Alexander Graham Bell Gardens'' in [[Brantford]], Ontario, in 1917.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Osborne |first=Harold S. |title=Biographical Memoir of Alexander Graham Bell 1847–1922 |publisher=National Academy of Sciences |url=http://www.nasonline.org/publications/biographical-memoirs/memoir-pdfs/bell-alexander-graham.pdf |series=Biographical Memoirs |volume=Vol. XXIII  |p=18 |date=1943 |access-date=September 18, 2015 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Alexander Graham Bell Quote in stone.jpg|thumb|A quote by Alexander Graham Bell engraved in the stone wall within the Peace Chapel of the [[International Peace Garden]] (in Manitoba Canada and North Dakota, USA).]]
A large number of Bell's writings, personal correspondence, notebooks, papers, and other documents reside in both the United States [[Library of Congress|Library of Congress Manuscript Division]] (as the ''Alexander Graham Bell Family Papers''),&lt;ref name=&quot;AGB Family Papers&quot;/&gt; and at the Alexander Graham Bell Institute, [[Cape Breton University]], Nova Scotia; major portions of which are available for online viewing.

A number of historic sites and other marks commemorate Bell in North America and Europe, including the first telephone companies in the United States and Canada. Among the major sites are:
* The [[Alexander Graham Bell National Historic Site]], maintained by [[Parks Canada]], which incorporates the Alexander Graham Bell Museum, in [[Baddeck, Nova Scotia]], close to the Bell estate [[Beinn Bhreagh]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.pc.gc.ca/lhn-nhs/ns/grahambell/index_e.asp |title=Alexander Graham Bell National Historic Site |publisher=Parks Canada |date=August 7, 2015 |access-date=September 18, 2015 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071011122233/http://www.pc.gc.ca/lhn-nhs/ns/grahambell/index_e.asp |archivedate=October 11, 2007  }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[Bell Homestead National Historic Site]], includes the Bell family home, &quot;Melville House&quot;, and farm overlooking Brantford, Ontario and the [[Grand River (Ontario)|Grand River]]. It was their first home in North America;
* Canada's first telephone company building, the &quot;Henderson Home&quot; of the late 1870s, a predecessor of the [[Bell Canada|Bell Telephone Company of Canada]] (officially chartered in 1880). In 1969, the building was carefully moved to the historic Bell Homestead National Historic Site in [[Brantford]], Ontario, and was refurbished to become a telephone museum. The Bell Homestead, the Henderson Home telephone museum, and the National Historic Site's reception centre are all maintained by the Bell Homestead Society;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Pay Us a Call at Melville House! |url=http://www.bellhomestead.ca/Pages/default.aspx |website=Bell Homestead National Historic Site |access-date=September 18, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The Alexander Graham Bell Memorial Park, which features a broad neoclassical monument built in 1917 by public subscription. The monument depicts mankind's ability to span the globe through telecommunications;&lt;ref&gt;[https://maps.google.com/maps?f=q&amp;q=%22Alexander+Graham+Bell+%22,+Cambridge,+Ontario&amp;vps=34&amp;jsv=153e&amp;sll=40.657722,-74.098663&amp;sspn=0.674038,1.30188&amp;cd=1&amp;cid=43141094,-80268023,15275653568269528224&amp;li=lmd&amp;z=14&amp;t=m &quot;Alexander Graham Bell Memorial Park.&quot;] ''maps.google.com.'' Retrieved: February 14, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;
* The Alexander Graham Bell Museum (opened in 1956), part of the [[Alexander Graham Bell National Historic Site]] which was completed in 1978 in [[Baddeck, Nova Scotia]]. Many of the museum's artifacts were donated by Bell's daughters;&lt;br /&gt;[[File:Grahambellmuseumcorridoor.jpg|thumb|The [[Alexander Graham Bell National Historic Site|Bell Museum]], [[Cape Breton Island|Cape Breton]], part of the Alexander Graham Bell National Historic Site]]

In 1880, Bell received the [[Volta Prize]] with a purse of 50,000 [[French franc]]s (approximately US${{formatnum:{{Inflation|US|10000|1879|r=-4}}}} in today's dollars{{Inflation-fn|US}}) for the invention of the telephone from the French government.&lt;ref name=&quot;NYTimes&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.loc.gov/resource/magbell.21000309/?sp=1|title=Honors to Professor Bell Daily Evening Traveller|date=September 1, 1880|website=Alexander Graham Bell Family Papers|publisher=Library of Congress|access-date=September 18, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.loc.gov/resource/magbell.21000309/?sp=1|title=Volta Prize of the French Academy Awarded to Prof. Alexander Graham Bell|date=September 1, 1880|website=Alexander Graham Bell Family Papers|publisher=Library of Congress|access-date=September 18, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.loc.gov/resource/magbell.21000308/|title=Telegram from Grossman to Alexander Graham Bell|date=August 2, 1880|website=Alexander Graham Bell Family Papers|publisher=Library of Congress|access-date=September 18, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.loc.gov/resource/magbell.21000307/|title=Telegram from Alexander Graham Bell to Count du Moncel, undated|date=1880|website=Alexander Graham Bell Family Papers|publisher=Library of Congress|access-date=September 18, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.loc.gov/item/magbell.21000102/|title=Letter from Frederick T. Frelinghuysen to Alexander Graham Bell|date=January 7, 1882|website=Alexander Graham Bell Family Papers|publisher=Library of Congress|access-date=September 18, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Among the luminaries who judged were [[Victor Hugo]] and [[Alexandre Dumas, fils|Alexandre Dumas, ''fils''.]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite report|url=http://keionline.org/misc-docs/research_notes/kei_rn_2008_1.pdf|title=Selected Innovation Prizes and Reward Programs|date=2008|publisher=Knowledge Ecology International|access-date=September 18, 2015|chapter=The Volta Prize For Electricity|p=16}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Better source|date=August 2018}} The Volta Prize was conceived by [[Napoleon III]] in 1852, and named in honor of [[Alessandro Volta]], with Bell becoming the second recipient of the grand prize in its history.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/bpt6k97893365/f145.image|title=Les fondations de prix à l'Académie des sciences : les lauréats de l'Académie, 1714-1880|last=Maindron|first=Ernest|year=1881|isbn=|editor-last=Gauthier-Villars|volume=1|location=|pages=131–133|language=French}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Davis|first=John L.|date=July 1998|title=Artisans and savants: The Role of the Academy of Sciences in the Process of Electrical Innovation in France, 1850–1880|journal=Annals of Science|volume=55|issue=3|pages=291–314|doi=10.1080/00033799800200211}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since Bell was becoming increasingly affluent, he used his prize money to create endowment funds (the 'Volta Fund') and institutions in and around the United States capital of Washington, D.C.. These included the prestigious'' 'Volta Laboratory Association' ''(1880), also known as the'' [[Volta Laboratory and Bureau|Volta Laboratory]] ''and as the'' 'Alexander Graham Bell Laboratory', ''and which eventually led to the Volta Bureau (1887) as a center for studies on deafness which is still in operation in [[Georgetown, Washington, D.C.]] The Volta Laboratory became an experimental facility devoted to scientific discovery, and the very next year it improved Edison's phonograph by substituting wax for tinfoil as the recording medium and incising the recording rather than indenting it, key upgrades that Edison himself later adopted.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|title=Letter from Mabel Hubbard Bell |website=Alexander Graham Bell Family Papers |publisher=Library of Congress
|url=https://www.loc.gov/item/magbell.21000301/ |date=February 27, 1880 |access-date=September 18, 2015
|quote=The last line of the typed note refers to the future disposition of award funds: He intends putting the full amount into his Laboratory and Library.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The laboratory was also the site where he and his associate invented his &quot;proudest achievement&quot;, &quot;the [[photophone]]&quot;, the &quot;optical telephone&quot; which presaged [[Fiber-optic communication|fibre optical telecommunications]] while the Volta Bureau would later evolve into the [[Alexander Graham Bell Association for the Deaf and Hard of Hearing]] (the AG Bell), a leading center for the research and [[pedagogy]] of deafness.

In partnership with [[Gardiner Greene Hubbard]], Bell helped establish the publication ''[[Science (journal)|Science]]'' during the early 1880s. In 1898, Bell was elected as the second president of the [[National Geographic Society]], serving until 1903, and was primarily responsible for the extensive use of illustrations, including photography, in the magazine.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://press.nationalgeographic.com/about-national-geographic/milestones/ |title=National Geographic Milestones |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |date= June 20, 2012|website=National Geographic Milestones|publisher=National Geographic Society |access-date=January 18, 2016 |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt; He also served for many years as a Regent of the [[Smithsonian Institution]] (1898–1922).&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title = Volume IV of the Proceedings of the Board of Regents, Dec. 9, 1920 - Dec. 10, 1931 | publisher = Smithsonian Institution | location = Washington, D. C. | chapter = Proceedings of the Board of Regents of the Smithsonian Institution at the Annual Meeting held December 14, 1922 | date = December 14, 1922 | page = 547 | quote = RESOLVED:  That the Executive Committee be requested to prepare a memorial commemorative of the life and work of Dr. Alexander Graham Bell, Regent of the Smithsonian Institution from 1898 to 1922, said memorial to be presented at the next Annual Meeting of the Board. | chapter-url = https://transcription.si.edu/transcribe/11810/SIA-SIA_000001_BORMTG_1920-1931_098}}&lt;/ref&gt; The French government conferred on him the decoration of the [[Légion d'honneur]] (Legion of Honor); the [[Royal Society of Arts]] in London awarded him the [[Albert Medal (RSA)|Albert Medal]] in 1902; the [[University of Würzburg]], Bavaria, granted him a PhD, and he was awarded the [[Franklin Institute]]'s [[Elliott Cresson Medal]] in 1912. He was one of the founders of the [[American Institute of Electrical Engineers]] in 1884 and served as its president from 1891–92. Bell was later awarded the AIEE's [[Edison Medal]] in 1914 &quot;For meritorious achievement in the invention of the telephone&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Alexander Graham Bell |website=Engineering and Technology History Wiki |url=http://ethw.org/Alexander_Graham_Bell |access-date=September 18, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''bel'' (B) and the smaller ''[[decibel]]'' (dB) are [[units of measurement]] of [[Sound pressure|sound pressure level]] (SPL) invented by [[Bell Labs]] and named after him.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.sfu.ca/sonic-studio/handbook/Decibel.html &quot;Decibel.&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170809145931/http://www.sfu.ca/sonic-studio/handbook/Decibel.html |date=August 9, 2017 }} ''sfu.ca.'' Retrieved: July 28, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; {{refn|The decibel is defined as one tenth of a bel.|group=N}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |title=bel |encyclopedia=[[The American Heritage Dictionary of the English Language]] |url=http://www.thefreedictionary.com/bel |publisher=[[Houghton Mifflin Harcourt]] |edition=Fifth |date=2011 |access-date=September 18, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since 1976, the [[IEEE]]'s [[IEEE Alexander Graham Bell Medal|Alexander Graham Bell Medal]] has been awarded to honor outstanding contributions in the field of telecommunications.
[[File:Alexander Grahm Bell2 1940 Issue-10c.jpg|thumb|upright=0.8|left |A.G. Bell issue of 1940]]

In 1936, the [[United States Patent and Trademark Office|US Patent Office]] declared Bell first on its list of the country's greatest inventors,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Beauchamp |first=Christopher |url=http://muse.jhu.edu/journals/tech/summary/v051/51.4.beauchamp.html |title=Who Invented the Telephone?: Lawyers, Patents, and the Judgments of History |journal=[[Technology and Culture]] |volume=51 |issue=4 |date=October 2010 |pp=854–878 |doi=10.1353/tech.2010.0038 |ref={{sfnRef|Beauchamp|2010}} |doi-broken-date=2020-01-22 }}&lt;/ref&gt; leading to the [[United States Postal Service|US Post Office]] issuing a commemorative stamp honoring Bell in 1940 as part of its [[Postage stamps and postal history of the United States#Famous Americans Series of 1940|'Famous Americans Series']]. The First Day of Issue ceremony was held on October 28 in Boston, Massachusetts, the city where Bell spent considerable time on research and working with the deaf. The Bell stamp became very popular and sold out in little time. The stamp became, and remains to this day, the most valuable one of the series.&lt;ref&gt;''Scott's United States Stamp catalogue.''&lt;/ref&gt;

The 150th anniversary of Bell's birth in 1997 was marked by a special issue of [[The Royal Bank of Scotland £1 note|commemorative £1 banknotes]] from the [[Royal Bank of Scotland#Commemorative banknotes|Royal Bank of Scotland]]. The illustrations on the reverse of the note include Bell's face in profile, his signature, and objects from Bell's life and career: users of the telephone over the ages; an audio [[waveform|wave signal]]; a diagram of a telephone receiver; geometric shapes from engineering structures; representations of sign language and the phonetic alphabet; the geese which helped him to understand flight; and the sheep which he studied to understand genetics.&lt;ref name=&quot;commemorative&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.rampantscotland.com/SCM/royalcomm.htm |title=Royal Bank Commemorative Notes |website=Rampant Scotland |access-date=October 14, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, the Government of Canada honored Bell in 1997 with a [[Royal Canadian Mint numismatic coins (20th century)#100 Dollar Gold|C$100 gold coin]], in tribute also to the 150th anniversary of his birth, and with a silver dollar coin in 2009 in honor of the 100th anniversary of flight in Canada. That first flight was made by an airplane designed under Dr. Bell's tutelage, named the Silver Dart.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Proof Set - 100th Anniversary of Flight in Canada (2009) |website=Royal Canadian Mint |url=http://www.mint.ca/store/coin/proof-set-100th-anniversary-of-flight-in-canada-2009-prod530013 |access-date=September 18, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bell's image, and also those of his many inventions have graced paper money, coinage, and postal stamps in numerous countries worldwide for many dozens of years.

Alexander Graham Bell was ranked 57th among the [[100 Greatest Britons]] (2002) in an official BBC nationwide poll,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/entertainment/2208671.stm |title=100 great British heroes |work=BBC News World Edition |date=August 21, 2002 |access-date=April 5, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and among the [[The Greatest Canadian|Top Ten Greatest Canadians]] (2004), and [[The Greatest American|the 100 Greatest Americans]] (2005). In 2006, Bell was also named as one of the 10 greatest Scottish scientists in history after having been listed in the [[National Library of Scotland]]'s 'Scottish Science Hall of Fame'.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Alexander Graham Bell (1847–1922) |url=http://digital.nls.uk/scientists/biographies/alexander-graham-bell/index.html |website=Scottish Science Hall of Fame|year=2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Bell's name is still widely known and used as part of the names of dozens of educational institutes, corporate namesakes, street and place names around the world.

[[File:Bell receives honourary LL.D from University of Edinburgh.jpg|thumb|Bell, an alumnus of the [[University of Edinburgh]], Scotland, receiving an honorary Doctor of Laws degree (LL.D.) at the university in 1906]]

{{See also|Bell Telephone Memorial}}

===Honorary degrees===
{{Expand list|date=August 2016}}

Alexander Graham Bell, who could not complete the university program of his youth, received at least a dozen honorary degrees from academic institutions, including eight honorary [[Doctor of Laws|LL.D.s]] (Doctorate of Laws), two Ph.D.s, a D.Sc., and an M.D.:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |editor-last=MacDougall |editor-first=D. |title=Scots and Scots Descendant in America |chapter=Part V: Alexander Graham Bell |chapter-url={{google books|kX3XAAAAMAAJ|plainurl=yes|page=162}} |publisher=Caledonian |location=New York |date=1917 |p=162 |access-date=September 18, 2015 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Gallaudet College]] (then named National Deaf-Mute College) in Washington, D.C. (Ph.D.) in 1880{{sfn|MacDougall|1917|p=162}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://provost.gallaudet.edu/Academic_Affairs/Honorary_Degrees/Honorary_Degree_Recipients.html |title=Honorary Degree Recipients |website=Gallaudet University |location=Washington, DC |access-date=July 28, 2010 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100618060032/http://provost.gallaudet.edu/Academic_Affairs/Honorary_Degrees/Honorary_Degree_Recipients.html |archivedate=June 18, 2010  }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[University of Würzburg]] in Würzburg, Bavaria (Ph.D.) in 1882{{sfn|MacDougall|1917|p=162}}
* [[Heidelberg University]] in Heidelberg, Germany (M.D.) in 1886{{sfn|MacDougall|1917|p=162}}&lt;ref name=&quot;DCB&quot;&gt;{{cite DCB |first=Lawrence |last=Surtees |url=http://www.biographi.ca/en/bio/bell_alexander_graham_15E.html |title=BELL, ALEXANDER GRAHAM |volume=15 |access-date=March 6, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Harvard University]] in Cambridge, Massachusetts (LL.D.) in 1896{{sfn|MacDougall|1917|p=162}}
* [[Illinois College]], in Jacksonville, Illinois (LL.D.) in 1896, possibly 1881{{sfn|MacDougall|1917|p=162}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ic.edu/RelId/614303/ISvars/default/Honorary_Degrees_Conferred.htm |website=Illinois College |title=Honorary Degrees Conferred |access-date=September 18, 2015 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150924032410/http://www.ic.edu/RelId/614303/ISvars/default/Honorary_Degrees_Conferred.htm |archive-date=September 24, 2015 |url-status=dead  }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Amherst College]] in Amherst, Massachusetts (LL.D.) in 1901{{sfn|MacDougall|1917|p=162}}
* [[University of St Andrews|St. Andrew's University]] in St Andrews, Scotland (LL.D) in 1902{{sfn|MacDougall|1917|p=162}}
* [[University of Oxford]] in Oxford, England (D.Sc.) in 1906{{sfn|MacDougall|1917|p=162}}
* [[University of Edinburgh]] in Edinburgh, Scotland (LL.D.) in 1906{{sfn|MacDougall|1917|p=162}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Graduations |website=University of Edinburgh |url=http://www.scripts.sasg.ed.ac.uk/registry/Graduations/Honorary_Graduates.cfm |access-date=September 18, 2015 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150901034227/http://www.scripts.sasg.ed.ac.uk/registry/Graduations/Honorary_Graduates.cfm |archivedate=September 1, 2015  }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[George Washington University]] in Washington, D.C. (LL.D.) in 1913{{sfn|MacDougall|1917|p=162}}
* [[Queen's University at Kingston]] in Kingston, Ontario, Canada (LL.D.) in 1908{{sfn|MacDougall|1917|p=162}}
* [[Dartmouth College]] in Hanover, New Hampshire (LL.D.) in 1913,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://timesmachine.nytimes.com/timesmachine/1913/06/26/100569465.pdf |title=Dartmouth graduates 208: Alexander Graham Bell Among Those Receiving Honorary Degrees |newspaper=The New York Times |date=July 26, 1913 |access-date=July 30, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; possibly 1914{{sfn|MacDougall|1917|p=162}}

==Portrayal in film and television==
* The 1939 film ''[[The Story of Alexander Graham Bell]]'' was based on his life and works.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=THE SCREEN; The founding of the Wrong-Number Industry WellDramatized in Roxy's 'Alexander Graham Bell' At the 86th St. Garden Theatre At Three Theatres At the 86th Street Casino|url=https://www.nytimes.com/movie/review?res=9504E3D6133CE73ABC4953DFB2668382629EDE|newspaper=The New York Times|accessdate=February 2, 2017|date=April 1, 1939}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The 1992 film ''[[The Sound and the Silence]]'' was a TV film.
* ''[[Biography (TV series)|Biography]]'' aired an episode ''Alexander Graham Bell: Voice of Invention'' on August 6, 1996.
* ''Eyewitness No. 90 A Great Inventor Is Remembered'', a 1957 [[National Film Board of Canada|NFB]] short about Bell.

==Death==
Bell died of complications arising from [[diabetes]] on August 2, 1922, at his private estate in Cape Breton, Nova Scotia, at age 75.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Gray |first=Charlotte |title=Reluctant Genius: The Passionate Life and Inventive Mind of Alexander Graham Bell |url={{google books|ujlCgf1uSJIC|plainurl=yes|page=151}} |year=2006 |publisher=Arcade |location=New York |p=419 |isbn=978-1-55970-809-8 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bell had also been afflicted with [[pernicious anemia]].{{sfn|Gray|2006|p=418}} His last view of the land he had inhabited was by moonlight on his mountain estate at 2:00&amp;nbsp;a.m.{{refn|In the last years of his life, as his final projects wound down, Bell and his wife, their extended family and friends, lived exclusively at their beloved Beinn Bhreagh.{{sfn|Bethune|2009|p=95}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Duffy |first=Andrew |title=The Silver Dart sputtered into history |url=http://www2.canada.com/news/national/canada+flight/1319873/story.html?id=1319873 |work=[[Ottawa Citizen]] |date=February 23, 2009 |access-date=September 18, 2015 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150713175706/http://www2.canada.com/news/national/canada+flight/1319873/story.html?id=1319873 |archivedate=July 13, 2015  }}.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=N}}{{sfn|Bethune|2009|p=119}}{{refn|From {{harvp|Bethune|2009|p=119}}: &quot;[his end came] at 2:00&amp;nbsp;am... His wife, Mabel, daughter Daisy, and son-in-law David Fairchild had gathered around him. His last view was of the moon rising above the mountain he loved&quot;.|group=N}} While tending to him after his long illness, Mabel, his wife, whispered, &quot;Don't leave me.&quot; By way of reply, Bell signed &quot;no...&quot;, lost consciousness, and died shortly after.&lt;ref name=&quot;NYTimes&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=https://timesmachine.nytimes.com/timesmachine/1922/08/03/99050024.pdf |title=Dr. Bell, Inventor of Telephone, Dies |work=The New York Times |date=August 3, 1922 |access-date=March 3, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Bruce|1990|p=491}}

On learning of Bell's death, the [[Prime Minister of Canada|Canadian Prime Minister]], [[William Lyon Mackenzie King|Mackenzie King]], cabled Mrs. Bell, saying:&lt;ref name=&quot;NYTimes&quot;/&gt;
{{quote|My colleagues in the Government join with me in expressing to you our sense of the world's loss in the death of your distinguished husband. It will ever be a source of pride to our country that the great invention, with which his name is immortally associated, is a part of its history. On the behalf of the citizens of Canada, may I extend to you an expression of our combined gratitude and sympathy.}}

Bell's coffin was constructed of Beinn Bhreagh pine by his laboratory staff, lined with the same red silk fabric used in his tetrahedral kite experiments. To help celebrate his life, his wife asked guests not to wear black (the traditional funeral color) while attending his service, during which soloist Jean MacDonald sang a verse of [[Robert Louis Stevenson]]'s &quot;Requiem&quot;:{{sfn|Bethune|2009|pp=119–120}}
:Under a wide and starry sky,
:Dig the grave and let me lie.
:Glad did I live and gladly die
:And I laid me down with a will.

Upon the conclusion of Bell's funeral, &quot;every phone on the continent of North America was silenced in honor of the man who had given to mankind the means for direct communication at a distance&quot;.{{sfn|Bethune|2009|p=2}}{{sfn|Osborne|1943|pp=18–19}}

Dr. Alexander Graham Bell was buried atop Beinn Bhreagh mountain, on his estate where he had resided increasingly for the last 35 years of his life, overlooking Bras d'Or Lake.&lt;ref name=&quot;NYTimes&quot;/&gt; He was survived by his wife [[Mabel Gardiner Hubbard|Mabel]], his two daughters, Elsie May and Marian, and nine of his grandchildren&lt;!-- Note: grandson Alexander Graham Bell Grosvenor had died seven years prior, as seen here: http://memory.loc.gov/ammem/bellhtml/embgtree.html --&gt;.&lt;ref name=&quot;NYTimes&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.nytimes.com/learning/general/onthisday/bday/0303.html |title=Dr. Bell, Inventor of Telephone, Dies |work=The New York Times |date=August 3, 1922 |access-date=July 21, 2007 |quote=Dr. Alexander Graham Bell, inventor of the telephone, died at 2 o'clock this morning at Beinn Breagh, his estate near Baddeck}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Descendants of Alexander Melville Bell – Three Generations. ''Bell Telephone Company of Canada Historical Collection and Company Library'' (undated) |website=Brant Historical Society }}{{Citation needed|date=September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Div col|colwidth=35em}}

* [[Alexander Graham Bell Association for the Deaf and Hard of Hearing]]
* [[Alexander Graham Bell National Historic Site]]
* [[Bell Boatyard]]
* [[Bell Homestead National Historic Site]]
* [[Bell Telephone Memorial]]
* [[Emile Berliner|Berliner, Emile]]
* [[Charles Bourseul|Bourseul, Charles]]
* [[IEEE Alexander Graham Bell Medal]]
* [[John Peirce]], submitted telephone ideas to Bell
* [[Innocenzo Manzetti|Manzetti, Innocenzo]]
* [[Antonio Meucci|Meucci, Antonio]]
* [[Oriental Telephone Company]]
* [[List of people on banknotes#Scotland|People on Scottish banknotes]]
* [[Pioneers, a Volunteer Network]]
* [[Johann Philipp Reis|Reis, Philipp]]
* [[The Story of Alexander Graham Bell]], a 1939 movie of his life
* [[The Telephone Cases]]
* [[Volta Laboratory and Bureau]]
* [[William Francis Channing]], submitted telephone ideas to Bell
{{colend}}

==References==

===Notes===
{{reflist|30em|group=N}}

===Citations===
{{reflist|30em}}

===Bibliography===
{{Refbegin}}
* {{cite journal |last1=Bell |first1=Alexander Graham |date=October 1880 |title=On the Production and Reproduction of Sound by Light |url=https://www.histv.net/bell-production-of-sound-by-light |journal=[[American Journal of Science]] |type=Read before the American Association for the Advancement of Science, in Boston, August 27, 1880 |series=Third |volume=20 |issue=118 |pages=305–324 |doi=10.2475/ajs.s3-20.118.305|bibcode=1880AmJS...20..305B }}&lt;br /&gt;Also published as: {{cite journal |last=Bell |first=Alexander Graham |date=September 23, 1880 |title=Selenium and the Photophone |journal=[[Nature (journal)|Nature]] |volume=22 |issue= 569|pages=500–503 |doi=10.1038/022500a0 |bibcode=1880Natur..22..500. }}
* {{cite book |last=Bell |first=Alexander Graham |url=http://saveourdeafschools.org/question.pdf |title=The Question of Sign-Language and The Utility of Signs in the Instruction of the Deaf—Two papers |location=Washington, D.C. |publisher=Sanders Printing Office |date=1898}}
* {{cite magazine |last=Bell |first=Alexander Graham |date=February 1917 |title= Prizes for the Inventor: Some of the Problems Awaiting Solution|url=https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/National_Geographic_Magazine/Volume_31/Number_2/Prizes_for_the_Inventor|magazine=[[The National Geographic Magazine]] |volume=31 |issue=2 |pages=131–146 |publisher=[[National Geographic Society]]}}
{{Refend}}

===Further reading===
* Mullett, Mary B. [https://books.google.com/books?id=MaFXAAAAMAAJ&amp;pg=RA4-PA10 ''The Story of A Famous Inventor.''] New York: Rogers and Fowle, 1921.
* Walters, Eric. ''The Hydrofoil Mystery''. Toronto, Ontario, Canada: [[Penguin Books|Puffin Books]], 1999. {{ISBN|0-14-130220-8}}.
* Winzer, Margret A. [https://archive.org/details/historyofspecial00winz ''The History Of Special Education: From Isolation To Integration''.] Washington, D.C.: Gallaudet University Press, 1993. {{ISBN|978-1-56368-018-2}}.

==External links==
{{external links|date=December 2018}}
{{sisterlinks|d=Q34286|n=no|c=Category:Alexander Graham Bell|s=Author:Alexander Graham Bell|voy=no|m=no|mw=no|wikt=no|b=no|v=no}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20151208211550/http://bell.cbu.ca/agbi_about.asp Alexander Graham Bell Institute at Cape Breton University]
* [http://www.telephonetribute.com/pdf/bell_memorial_booklet.pdf Bell Telephone Memorial], [[Brantford]], Ontario
* [http://www.bellhomestead.ca/Pages/default.aspx Bell Homestead National Historic Site], Brantford, Ontario
* [http://www.pc.gc.ca/eng/lhn-nhs/ns/grahambell/index.aspx Alexander Graham Bell National Historic Site of Canada], Baddeck, Nova Scotia
* [https://www.loc.gov/collection/alexander-graham-bell-papers/about-this-collection/#overview Alexander Graham Bell Family Papers at the Library of Congress]
* {{Biographical Memoirs|bell-alexander-graham}}
* [http://www.biographi.ca/en/bio/bell_alexander_graham_15E.html Biography at the ''Dictionary of Canadian Biography Online'']
* [http://www.science.ca/scientists/scientistprofile.php?pID=120 Science.ca profile: Alexander Graham Bell]
* {{Gutenberg author|id=48508}}
* {{Find a Grave|2125|Alexander Graham Bell}}
* {{IMDb name|id=1745080|name=Alexander Graham Bell}}
* [https://archive.org/details/AlexanderGrahamBellsNotebooks Alexander Graham Bell's notebooks] at the [[Internet Archive]]
* [https://www.histv.net/graham-bell-contribution-indirecte  &quot;Téléphone et photophone : les contributions indirectes de Graham Bell à l'idée de la vision à distance par l'électricité&quot;] at the [https://www.histv.net Histoire de la télévision]
* {{PM20|FID=pe/001393}}

===Multimedia===
* [http://www.biography.com/people/alexander-graham-bell-9205497 Alexander Graham Bell] at [[The Biography Channel]]
* {{IMDb title|0031981|The Story of Alexander Graham Bell|(1939)}}
* {{cite AV media |people=Alexander Graham Bell portrayed by [[John Bach]]|year=1992 |title=[[The Sound and the Silence]]|medium=Television production |publisher=Atlantis Films |location=Canada, New Zealand, Ireland}}
* {{IMDb title|id=0956089|title=The Animated Hero Classics: Alexander Graham Bell|3= (1995)}}
* {{cite news|last=Gray|first=Charlotte|title=We Had No Idea What Alexander Graham Bell Sounded Like. Until Now|url=http://www.smithsonianmag.com/history-archaeology/We-Had-No-Idea-What-Alexander-Graham-Bell-Sounded-Like-Until-Now-204137471.html|newspaper=[[Smithsonian (magazine)|Smithsonian Magazine]]|date=May 2013}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20150922192029/https://www.historica-dominion.ca/content/heritage-minutes/shaping-future ''Shaping The Future''], from the ''[[Heritage Minutes]]'' and ''Radio Minutes'' collection at [[Historica Canada|HistoricaCanada.ca]] (1:31 audio drama, [[Adobe Flash]] required)

{{s-start}}
{{s-npo}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Gardiner Greene Hubbard]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=President of the [[National Geographic Society]]|years= 1897–1904}}
{{s-aft|after= [[William John McGee]]}}
{{s-end}}

{{Alexander Graham Bell|state=expanded}}
{{Hall of Fame for Great Americans}}
{{National Geographic}}
{{IEEE Edison Medal Laureates 1909-1925}}
{{John Fritz Medal}}
{{Scientists whose names are used as non SI units}}
{{Baddeck}}
{{Telecommunications}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Bell, Alexander Graham}}
[[Category:1847 births]]
[[Category:1922 deaths]]
[[Category:19th-century Scottish scientists]]
[[Category:Alexander Graham Bell| ]]
[[Category:Alumni of the University of Edinburgh]]
[[Category:Alumni of University College London]]
[[Category:American agnostics]]
[[Category:American educational theorists]]
[[Category:American eugenicists]]
[[Category:American physicists]]
[[Category:American Unitarians]]
[[Category:Aviation pioneers]]
[[Category:Canadian agnostics]]
[[Category:Canadian Aviation Hall of Fame inductees]]
[[Category:Canadian emigrants to the United States]]
[[Category:Canadian eugenicists]]
[[Category:Canadian inventors]]
[[Category:Canadian physicists]]
[[Category:Canadian Unitarians]]
[[Category:Deaths from diabetes]]
[[Category:Fellows of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences]]
[[Category:History of telecommunications]]
[[Category:IEEE Edison Medal recipients]]
[[Category:Language teachers]]
[[Category:Members of the American Philosophical Society]]
[[Category:Members of the American Antiquarian Society]]
[[Category:Members of the United States National Academy of Sciences]]
[[Category:National Aviation Hall of Fame inductees]]
[[Category:National Geographic Society]]
[[Category:Officiers of the Légion d'honneur]]
[[Category:People educated at the Royal High School, Edinburgh]]
[[Category:People from Baddeck, Nova Scotia]]
[[Category:Businesspeople from Boston]]
[[Category:People from Brantford]]
[[Category:People from Edinburgh]]
[[Category:People from Washington, D.C.]]
[[Category:Scottish agnostics]]
[[Category:Scottish businesspeople]]
[[Category:Scottish emigrants to Canada]]
[[Category:Scottish eugenicists]]
[[Category:Scottish inventors]]
[[Category:Scottish Unitarians]]
[[Category:Smithsonian Institution people]]
[[Category:Hall of Fame for Great Americans inductees]]
[[Category:George Washington University trustees]]
[[Category:Canadian activists]]
[[Category:Gardiner family]]
[[Category:Articles containing video clips]]
[[Category:Cosmos Club members]]
[[Category:19th-century inventors]]
[[Category:Scottish emigrants to the United States]]
[[Category:John Fritz Medal recipients]]
[[Category:20th-century American scientists]]
[[Category:20th-century American inventors]]
[[Category:Canadian educational theorists]]
[[Category:Scottish physicists]]
[[Category:19th-century Canadian scientists]]
[[Category:20th-century Scottish scientists]]
[[Category:20th-century Canadian scientists]]</text>
      <sha1>jtbl9wel31d12dtasvzaloce5u783vb</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
