  <page>
    <title>Arachnophobia</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1386</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941647302</id>
      <parentid>940971005</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-19T21:17:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jackchango</username>
        <id>34476637</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Added IPA.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{about|the specific phobia}}
{{Infobox medical condition (new)
| name            = Arachnophobia
| synonyms        = Arachnephobia&lt;ref&gt;Patricia Bowen (ed.), ''Internal Medicine Words'', Rayve Productions, 1997, p. 18.&lt;/ref&gt;
| image           = Little Miss Muffet 2 - WW Denslow - Project Gutenberg etext 18546.jpg
| alt             = 
| caption         = Though many arachnids are harmless, a person with arachnophobia may still panic or feel uneasy around one. Sometimes, even an object resembling a spider can trigger a panic attack in an arachnophobia individual. The above cartoon is a depiction of the nursery rhyme &quot;[[Little Miss Muffet]],&quot; in which the title character is &quot;frightened away&quot; by a spider.
| pronounce       = {{IPAc-en|ə|ˌ|r|æ|k|n|ə|ˈ|f|əʊ|b|i|ə}}
| synonym         = 
| field           = [[Psychiatry]]
| symptoms        = 
| complications   = 
| onset           = 
| duration        = 
| types           = 
| causes          = 
| risks           = 
| diagnosis       = 
| differential    = 
| prevention      = 
| treatment       = [[Exposure therapy]]&lt;ref name=Spe2015/&gt;
| medication      = 
| prognosis       = 
| frequency       = 
| deaths          = 
}}

'''Arachnophobia''' is an intense and unreasonable fear of [[spider]]s and other [[arachnid]]s such as [[scorpion]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Heather Hatfield. [http://www.webmd.com/anxiety-panic/guide/fear-factor-phobias &quot;The Fear Factor: Phobias&quot;]. Webmd.com&lt;/ref&gt;

Treatment is typically by [[exposure therapy]], where the person is presented with pictures of spiders or the spiders themselves.&lt;ref name=Spe2015&gt;{{cite book |last1=Sperry |first1=Len |title=Mental Health and Mental Disorders: An Encyclopedia of Conditions, Treatments, and Well-Being [3 volumes]: An Encyclopedia of Conditions, Treatments, and Well-Being |date=2015 |publisher=ABC-CLIO |isbn=9781440803833 |page=430 |url=https://books.google.ca/books?id=NzgVCwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA430 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Signs and symptoms==
People with arachnophobia tend to feel [[anxiety|uneasy]] in any area they believe could harbor spiders or that has visible signs of their presence, such as [[spider web|webs]]. If arachnophobes see a spider, they may not enter the general vicinity until they have overcome the [[panic attack]] that is often associated with their phobia. Some people run away, [[screaming|scream]], [[cry]], have emotional outbursts, experience trouble breathing, [[Perspiration|sweat]], have increased heart rates, or even faint when they come in contact with an area near spiders or their webs. In some extreme cases, even a [[picture]] or a realistic drawing of a spider can [[Trauma trigger|trigger]] intense [[fear]].

==Reasons==
Arachnophobia may be an exaggerated form of an [[instinct]]ive response that helped early humans to survive,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Friedenberg, J. |author2=Silverman, G. |title=Cognitive Science: An Introduction to the Study of Mind|publisher=SAGE |year=2005 |isbn=1-4129-2568-1 |pages=244–245|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=wGti6_4Qn_QC&amp;pg=PA244|accessdate=2008-10-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; or a cultural phenomenon that is most common in predominantly European societies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Davey, G.C.L.|title=The &quot;Disgusting&quot; Spider: The Role of Disease and Illness in the Perpetuation of Fear of Spiders|journal=Society and Animals |volume=2 |issue=1 |year=1994 |pages=17–25 |doi=10.1163/156853094X00045}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Evolutionary===
An evolutionary reason for the phobia remains unresolved. One view, especially held in [[evolutionary psychology]], is that the presence of [[Spider bite|venomous spiders]] led to the evolution of a fear of spiders, or made acquisition of a fear of spiders especially easy. Like all traits, there is variability in the intensity of fear of spiders, and those with more intense fears are classified as phobic. Being relatively small, spiders do not fit the usual criterion for a threat in the [[animal|animal kingdom]] where size is a factor, but they can have medically significant [[Venom (poison)|venom]].{{citation needed|date=August 2014}} However, a phobia is an irrational fear as opposed to a rational fear.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.webmd.com/anxiety-panic/features/fear-factor-phobias#1&lt;/ref&gt;

By ensuring that their surroundings were free from spiders, arachnophobes would have had a reduced risk of being bitten in ancestral environments, giving them a slight advantage over non-arachnophobes in terms of survival. However, having a disproportionate fear of spiders in comparison to other, potentially dangerous creatures&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://courses.washington.edu/evpsych/spiders%20are%20special%20-%20EHB%202009.pdf|year=2009|doi=10.1016/j.evolhumbehav.2008.08.005|title=Spiders are special: fear and disgust evoked by pictures of arthropods|last1=Gerdes|first1=Antje B.M.|last2=Uhl|first2=Gabriele|last3=Alpers|first3=Georg W.|journal=[[Evolution and Human Behavior]]|volume=30|pages=66–73}}&lt;/ref&gt; present during ''Homo sapiens''' [[Environment of evolutionary adaptedness|environment of evolutionary adaptiveness]] may have had drawbacks.{{citation needed|date=June 2018}}

A 2001 study found that people could detect images of spiders among images of flowers and mushrooms more quickly than they could detect images of flowers or mushrooms among images of spiders. The researchers suggested that this was because fast response to spiders was more relevant to human evolution.&lt;ref&gt;Öhman, A., Flykt, A., &amp; Esteves, F. (2001). &quot;Emotion drives attention: Detecting the snake in the grass&quot;. ''Journal of Experimental Psychology'': '''130''' (3), 466–478.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Cultural===
The alternative view is that the dangers, such as from spiders, are overrated and not sufficient to influence evolution.{{Attribution needed|date=June 2018}} Instead, inheriting phobias would have restrictive and debilitating effects upon survival, rather than being an aid. For some communities such as in [[Papua New Guinea]] and [[Cambodia]] spiders are included in traditional foods. This suggests arachnophobia may be a cultural, rather than genetic trait.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://webs.wichita.edu/depttools/depttoolsmemberfiles/psychology/publications/Wagener%20&amp;%20Zettle%20Paper.pdf |title=Targeting Fear of Spiders With Control-, Acceptance-, and Information-Based Approaches |author1=Wagener, Alexandra L. |author2=Zettle, Robert D. |year=2011 |journal=The Psychological Record |volume=61 |issue=1 |url-status = dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110614031029/http://webs.wichita.edu/depttools/depttoolsmemberfiles/psychology/publications/Wagener%20%26%20Zettle%20Paper.pdf |archivedate=2011-06-14 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Fears, Phobias, and Preparedness: Toward an Evolved Module of Fear and Fear Learning|url=http://instruct.uwo.ca/psychology/371g/Ohman2001.pdf|pmid=11488376|year=2001|last1=Ohman|first1=A|last2=Mineka|first2=S|volume=108|issue=3|pages=483–522|journal=Psychological Review|doi=10.1037/0033-295X.108.3.483}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Treatments==
The [[fear processing in the brain|fear]] of spiders can be treated by any of the general techniques suggested for [[specific phobia]]s. The first line of treatment is [[systematic desensitization]]&amp;nbsp;– also known as [[exposure therapy]].&lt;ref name=Spe2015/&gt; Before engaging in systematic desensitization, it is common to train the individual with arachnophobia in relaxation techniques, which will help keep the patient calm. Systematic desensitization can be done in vivo (with live spiders) or by getting the individual to imagine situations involving spiders, then modelling interaction with spiders for the person affected and eventually interacting with real spiders. This technique can be effective in just one session, although it generally takes more time.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal| last1 = Ost | first1 = L. G. | title = One-session treatment for specific phobias | journal = Behaviour Research and Therapy | volume = 27 | issue = 1 | pages = 1–7 | year = 1989 | pmid = 2914000 | doi=10.1016/0005-7967(89)90113-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Recent advances in technology have enabled the use of virtual or augmented reality spiders for use in therapy. These techniques have proven to be effective.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Bouchard|first1=S.|last2=Côté|first2=S.|last3=St-Jacques|first3=J.|last4=Robillard|first4=G.|last5=Renaud|first5=P.|year=2006|title=Effectiveness of virtual reality exposure in the treatment of arachnophobia using 3D games|journal=Technology and Healthcare|volume=14|issue=1|pages=19–27|url=http://iospress.metapress.com/content/d4cga4lnvyrcg5qu/?genre=article&amp;issn=0928-7329&amp;volume=14&amp;issue=1&amp;spage=19}}&lt;/ref&gt;  It has been suggested that exposure to short clips from the [[Spider-Man in film|''Spider-Man'' movies]] may help to reduce an individual's arachnophobia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.israelnationalnews.com/News/News.aspx/262298/|title=Israeli Researchers: &quot;Spider Man&quot; movies decrease Spider Phobia|author=Gabe Friedman|date=April 25, 2019|accessdate=April 25, 2019|work=Arutz Sheva}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Epidemiology==
Arachnophobia affects 3.5 to 6.1 percent of the global population.&lt;ref name=Sch2009&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Schmitt|first1=WJ|last2=Müri|first2=RM|year=2009|title=Neurobiologie der Spinnenphobie|journal=Schweizer Archiv für Neurologie|volume=160|issue=8|pages=352–355|url=http://cat.inist.fr/?aModele=afficheN&amp;cpsidt=22276624|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160823014205/http://cat.inist.fr/?aModele=afficheN&amp;cpsidt=22276624|archive-date=23 August 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Arachnophobia (film)|''Arachnophobia'' (film)]]
* [[Apiphobia]] (fear of bees)
* [[Entomophobia]] (fear of insects)
* [[Myrmecophobia]] (fear of ants)
* [[Zoophobia]] (fear of animals)

==References==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
{{Medical resources
|  DiseasesDB      = 
|  ICD10           = {{ICD10|F40.2}}
|  ICD9            = &lt;!--{{ICD9|xxx}}--&gt;
|  ICDO            = 
|  OMIM            = 
|  MedlinePlus     = 
|  MeSH            = 
|  GeneReviewsNBK  = 
|  GeneReviewsName = 
|  Orphanet        =
}}
*{{cite journal| last1 = Stiemerling | first1 = D. | year = 1973 | title = Analysis of a spider and monster phobia | url = | journal = Z Psychosom Med Psychoanal | volume =  19| issue = 4| pages = 327–45 |pmid=4129447 |language=de}}
*[http://news.nationalgeographic.com/news/2001/10/1004_snakefears.html National Geographic: &quot;Fear of Snakes, Spiders Rooted in Evolution, Study Finds&quot;]

{{Spider nav|state=collapsed}}

[[Category:Zoophobias]]
[[Category:Arachnids and humans]]</text>
      <sha1>62pz8w6a1s2lvys985rfxp1ocjr20am</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
