  <page>
    <title>AK-47</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1348</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943356601</id>
      <parentid>943356520</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-03-01T12:10:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Nyook</username>
        <id>37345946</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/2402:3A80:1051:1601:8821:242:2B2C:57FA|2402:3A80:1051:1601:8821:242:2B2C:57FA]] ([[User talk:2402:3A80:1051:1601:8821:242:2B2C:57FA|talk]]) to last revision by Brhee SangHyun ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=February 2020}}
{{about|the weapon}}
{{about|the AK-47|the AK family|Kalashnikov rifle}}
{{short description|1940s assault rifle of Soviet origin}}
{{Infobox weapon
| name            = AK-47&lt;ref group=N&gt;Table data covers the AK-47 with Type 3 receiver&lt;/ref&gt;
| image           = АК-47.jpg
| image_size      = 300
| caption         = AK-47 Type 2 with fixed bayonet.
| origin          = [[Soviet Union]] &lt;!-- Read WP:INFOBOXFLAG before you put a flag here --&gt;
| type            = [[Assault rifle]]
| is_ranged       = Yes
| service         = 1949–1974 (Soviet Union)&lt;br&gt;1949–present (other countries)
| used_by         = See ''[[#Users|Users]]''
| wars            = See ''[[#Conflicts|Conflicts]]''
| designer        = [[Mikhail Kalashnikov]]
| design_date     = 1946–1948&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Monetchikov|2005|loc=chpts. 6 and 7}}:&amp;nbsp;(if AK-46 and AK-47 are to be seen as separate designs).&lt;/ref&gt;
| manufacturer    = [[Kalashnikov Concern]] and various others including [[Norinco]]
| production_date = 1948–present&lt;ref name=&quot;Ezell, Edward Clinton 1986 112&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author=Ezell, Edward Clinton |authorlink=Edward Ezell |title=The AK47 Story, Evolution of the Kalashnikov Weapons |date=1986 |publisher=[[Stackpole Books]] |url=https://books.google.com/?id=FroVAQAACAAJ&amp;dq=The+AK47+Story,+Evolution+of+the+Kalashnikov+Weapons |isbn=978-0-811709163 |page=112}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Poyer, Joe |authorlink=Joe Poyer |title=The AK-47 and AK-74 Kalashnikov Rifles and Their Variations |date=2004 |publisher=[[North Cape Publications inc.]] |url=https://books.google.com/?id=EPArOwAACAAJ |isbn=1-882391-33-0 |page=8}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| number          = ≈ 75 million AK-47s, 100 million [[Kalashnikov rifle|Kalashnikov-family]] weapons.&lt;ref name=&quot;k3&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;foxnews&quot; /&gt;
| variants        = See ''[[#Variants|Variants]]''
| weight          = Without magazine:&lt;br /&gt;{{convert|3.47|kg|lb|abbr=on}}&lt;br /&gt;Magazine, empty:&lt;br /&gt;{{convert|0.43|kg|lb|abbr=on}} (early issue){{sfn|НСД. 7,62-мм автомат АК|1967|pp=161–162}}&lt;br /&gt;{{convert|0.33|kg|lb|abbr=on}} (steel){{sfn|НСД. 7,62-мм автомат АКМ (АКМС)|1983|pp=149–150}}&lt;br /&gt;{{convert|0.25|kg|lb|abbr=on}} (plastic)&lt;ref name=&quot;izhmash&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;{{convert|0.17|kg|lb|abbr=on}} (light alloy){{sfn|НСД. 7,62-мм автомат АКМ (АКМС)|1983|pp=149–150}}
| length          = Fixed wooden stock:&lt;br /&gt;{{convert|880|mm|abbr=on}}&lt;ref name=&quot;izhmash&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;{{convert|875|mm|abbr=on|1}} folding stock extended&lt;br /&gt;{{convert|645|mm|abbr=on|1}} stock folded{{sfn|НСД. 7,62-мм автомат АК|1967|pp=161–162}}
| part_length     = Overall length:&lt;br /&gt;{{convert|415|mm|abbr=on|1}}&lt;ref name=&quot;izhmash&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Rifled bore length:&lt;br /&gt;{{convert|369|mm|abbr=on|1}}&lt;ref name=&quot;izhmash&quot; /&gt;
| cartridge       = [[7.62×39mm]]
| action          = [[Gas-operated reloading|Gas-operated]], [[rotating bolt]]
| rate            = Cyclic rate of fire:&lt;br /&gt;600 rds/min&lt;ref name=&quot;izhmash&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Combat rate of fire:&lt;br /&gt;Semi-auto 40 rds/min&lt;ref name=&quot;izhmash&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Bursts 100 rds/min&lt;ref name=&quot;izhmash&quot; /&gt;
| velocity        = {{convert|715|m/s|abbr=on}}&lt;ref name=&quot;izhmash&quot; /&gt;
| range           = {{convert|350|m|yd|abbr=on}}&lt;ref name=&quot;izhmash&quot; /&gt;
| feed            = 30-round detachable box magazine&lt;ref name=&quot;izhmash&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;There are also 5- 10-, 20- and 40-round box and 75- and 100-round [[drum magazine|drum]] [[magazine (firearms)|magazines]] available
| sights          = 100–800&amp;nbsp;m adjustable [[iron sights]]&lt;br /&gt;Sight radius:&lt;br /&gt;{{convert|378|mm|abbr=on|1}}&lt;ref name=&quot;izhmash&quot; /&gt;
}}

The '''AK-47''', officially known as the '''Avtomat Kalashnikova''' ({{Lang-rus|Автома́т Кала́шникова|r=Avtomát Kaláshnikova|t=Kalashnikov’s automatic device}}; also known as the '''Kalashnikov''' and '''AK'''), is a [[gas operated|gas-operated]], [[7.62×39mm]] [[assault rifle]], developed in the [[Soviet Union]] by [[Mikhail Kalashnikov]]. It is the originating firearm of the [[Kalashnikov rifle]] (or &quot;AK&quot;) family. 47 refers to the year it was finished.

Design work on the AK-47 began in 1945. In 1946, the AK-47 was presented for official military trials, and in 1948, the fixed-stock version was introduced into active service with selected units of the [[Soviet Army]]. An early development of the design was the ''AKS'' (S—''Skladnoy'' or &quot;folding&quot;), which was equipped with an underfolding metal [[stock (firearms)|shoulder stock]]. In early 1949, the AK-47 was officially accepted by the [[Soviet Armed Forces]]{{sfnm|Monetchikov|2005|1p=67|Bolotin|1995|2p=129}} and used by the majority of the member states of the [[Warsaw Pact]].

Even after seven decades, the model and its variants remain the most popular and widely used assault rifles in the world because of its reliability under harsh conditions, low production costs compared to contemporary Western weapons, availability in virtually every geographic region, and ease of use. The AK-47 has been manufactured in many countries and has seen service with armed forces as well as [[irregular military|irregular forces]] and [[insurgencies]] worldwide, and was the basis for developing many other types of individual, crew-served and specialised firearms. {{as of|2004}}, &quot;Of the estimated 500 million firearms worldwide, approximately 100 million belong to the Kalashnikov family, three-quarters of which are AK-47s&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;k3&quot; /&gt;

== History ==
=== Origins ===
During [[World War II]], the [[StG 44|Sturmgewehr 44]] [[assault rifle]] used by [[Nazi Germany|German]] forces made a deep impression on their Soviet counterparts.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hallock&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Gun Book Review&quot; /&gt; The select-fire rifle was chambered for a new [[intermediate cartridge]], the [[7.92×33mm Kurz]], and combined the firepower of a submachine gun with the range and accuracy of a rifle.&lt;ref name=&quot;Machine Carbine Promoted&quot; /&gt;{{sfn|Rottman|2011|p=9}} On 15 July 1943, an earlier model of the Sturmgewehr was demonstrated before the [[People's Commissariat of Arms of the USSR]].&lt;ref name=&quot;english.pravda.ru&quot; /&gt; The Soviets were impressed with the weapon and immediately set about developing an intermediate caliber fully automatic rifle of their own,&lt;ref name=&quot;Hallock&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Gun Book Review&quot; /&gt; to replace the [[PPSh-41]] submachine guns and outdated [[Mosin–Nagant]] bolt-action rifles that armed most of the Soviet Army.&lt;ref name=&quot;Field &amp;amp; Stream&quot; /&gt;

The Soviets soon developed the [[7.62×39mm|7.62×39mm M43 cartridge]],&lt;ref name=&quot;english.pravda.ru&quot; /&gt; the semi-automatic [[SKS|SKS carbine]] and the [[RPD machine gun|RPD light machine gun]].&lt;ref name=&quot;virginia1774.org&quot; /&gt; Shortly after World War II, the Soviets developed the AK-47 assault rifle, which would quickly replace the SKS in Soviet service.&lt;ref name=&quot;nickpatonwalsh&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Rossiyskaya Gazeta&quot; /&gt; Introduced in 1959, the [[AKM]] is a lighter stamped steel version and the most ubiquitous variant of the entire AK series of firearms. In the 1960s, the Soviets introduced the [[RPK]] light machine gun, an AK type weapon with a stronger receiver, a longer heavy barrel, and a bipod, that would eventually replace the RPD light machine gun.&lt;ref name=&quot;virginia1774.org&quot; /&gt;

=== Concept ===
[[File:AK-47 type II Part DM-ST-89-01131.jpg|thumb|A Type 2A AK-47, the first machined receiver variation]]

[[Mikhail Kalashnikov]] began his career as a weapon designer in 1941, while recuperating from a shoulder wound which he received during the [[Battle of Bryansk]].&lt;ref name=&quot;foxnews&quot; /&gt;{{sfn|Bolotin|1995|pp=123–124}} Kalashnikov himself stated...&quot;I was in the hospital, and a soldier in the bed beside me asked: 'Why do our soldiers have only one rifle for two or three of our men, when the Germans have automatics?' So I designed one. I was a soldier, and I created a machine gun for a soldier. It was called an Avtomat Kalashnikova, the automatic weapon of Kalashnikov—AK—and it carried the year of its first manufacture, 1947.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;An interview with Mikhail Kalashnikov, Robert Fisk, The Independent (centrist), London, England. 22 April 2001. http://www.worldpress.org/cover5.htm {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161001104001/http://www.worldpress.org/cover5.htm |date=1 October 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The AK-47 is best described as a hybrid of previous rifle technology innovations. &quot;Kalashnikov decided to design an automatic rifle combining the best features of the American M1 and the German [[StG 44]].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;AP-Kalashnikov&quot; /&gt; Kalashnikov's team had access to these weapons and had no need to &quot;reinvent the wheel&quot;. Kalashnikov himself observed: &quot;A lot of Russian Army soldiers ask me how one can become a constructor, and how new weaponry is designed. These are very difficult questions. Each designer seems to have his own paths, his own successes and failures. But one thing is clear: before attempting to create something new, it is vital to have a good appreciation of everything that already exists in this field. I myself have had many experiences confirming this to be so.&quot;{{sfn|Bolotin|1995|pp=123–124}}

There are claims about Kalashnikov copying other designs, like [[TKB-415|Bulkin's TKB-415]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Popenker&quot; /&gt; or [[AVS-36|Simonov's AVS-31]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Kuptsov&quot; /&gt;

=== Early designs ===
Kalashnikov started work on a submachine gun design in 1942{{sfn|Bolotin|1995|p=123}} and with a light machine gun in 1943.{{sfn|Monetchikov|2005|p=38}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Bolotin p150&quot; /&gt; &quot;Early in 1944, Kalashnikov was given some 7.62×39mm M43 cartridges and informed that there were several designers working on weapons for this new Soviet small-arms cartridge. It was suggested to him that this new weapon might well lead to greater things, and he undertook work on the new rifle.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Power Custom&quot; /&gt; In 1944, he entered a design competition with this new 7.62×39mm, semi-automatic, gas-operated, long stroke piston, carbine, strongly influenced by the American [[M1 Garand]].&lt;ref name=&quot;The AR-15 2010&quot; /&gt; &quot;The rifle that Kalashnikov designed was in the same class as the familiar [[SKS-45]] Simonov with fixed magazine and gas tube above the barrel.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Power Custom&quot; /&gt; However, this new Kalashnikov design lost out to a Simonov design.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bolotin p115&quot; /&gt;

In 1946, a new design competition was initiated to develop a new assault rifle.{{sfn|Monetchikov|2005|p=36}} Kalashnikov submitted an entry. It was gas-operated rifle with a short-stroke gas piston above the barrel, a [[Breechblock|breech-block]] mechanism similar to his 1944 carbine, and a curved 30-round magazine.&lt;ref name=&quot;ak-akm-e&quot; /&gt; Kalashnikov's rifles AK-1 (with a milled [[receiver (firearms)|receiver]]) and AK-2 (with a stamped receiver) proved to be reliable weapons and were accepted to a second round of competition along with other designs.

These prototypes (also known as the AK-46) had a rotary bolt, a two-part receiver with separate trigger unit housing, dual controls (separate safety and fire selector switches) and a non-reciprocating charging handle located on the left side of the weapon.&lt;ref name=&quot;ak-akm-e&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Popenker-Williams&quot; /&gt; This design had many similarities to the StG 44.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.forgottenweapons.com/ak-and-stg-kissing-cousins/AK and StG – Kissing Cousins, 12 December 2012, by Ian McCollum&lt;/ref&gt; In late 1946, as the rifles were being tested, one of Kalashnikov's assistants, Aleksandr Zaitsev, suggested a major redesign to improve reliability. At first, Kalashnikov was reluctant, given that their rifle had already fared better than its competitors. Eventually, however, Zaitsev managed to persuade Kalashnikov.

[[File:AK 47.JPG|thumb|1955 AK-47 with a milled Type 3A receiver showing the milled lightening cut on the side above the magazine that for Type 3 receivers is slanted to the barrel axis]]

In November 1947, the new prototypes (AK-47s) were completed. It used a long-stroke gas piston above the barrel. The upper and lower receivers were combined into a single receiver. The selector and safety were combined into a single control-lever/dust-cover on the right side of the rifle. And, the bolt-handle was simply attached to the bolt-carrier. This simplified the design and production of the rifle. The first army trial series began in early 1948.{{sfn|Monetchikov|2005|p=64}} The new rifle proved to be reliable under a wide range of conditions with convenient handling characteristics. In 1949, it was adopted by the Soviet Army as &quot;7.62&amp;nbsp;mm Kalashnikov assault rifle (AK)&quot;.{{sfnm|Monetchikov|2005|1p=67|Bolotin|1995|2p=129}}

=== Further development ===
[[File:AKMS and AK-47 DD-ST-85-01270.jpg|thumb|AKMS with a stamped Type 4B receiver (top), and an AK-47 with a milled Type 2A receiver]]

There were many difficulties during the initial phase of production. The first production models had stamped sheet metal [[receiver (firearms)|receivers]] with a milled trunnion and butt stock insert, and a stamped body. Difficulties were encountered in welding the guide and ejector rails, causing high rejection rates.{{sfn|Poyer|2006|pp=8–11}} Instead of halting production, a heavy&lt;ref group=N&gt;2.6 lb milled from 6 lb stock. This was about 2.2 lb heavier than the stamped receiver.&lt;/ref&gt; machined receiver was substituted for the sheet metal receiver. Even though production of these milled rifles started in 1951, they were officially referred to as AK-49, based on the date their development started, but they are much widely known in the collectors' and current commercial market as &quot;Type 2 AK-47&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;e36&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ForgottenWeapons.com&quot; /&gt; This was a more costly process, but the use of machined receivers accelerated production as tooling and labor for the earlier [[Mosin–Nagant]] rifle's machined receiver were easily adapted.&lt;ref name=&quot;browningmgs.com&quot; /&gt; Partly because of these problems, the Soviets were not able to distribute large numbers of the new rifle to soldiers until 1956. During this time, production of the interim [[SKS]] rifle continued.{{sfn|Poyer|2006|pp=8–11}}

Once the manufacturing difficulties of non-milled receivers had been overcome, a redesigned version designated the [[AKM]] (M for &quot;modernized&quot; or &quot;upgraded&quot;; in Russian: ''Автомат Калашникова Модернизированный [Avtomat Kalashnikova Modernizirovanniy])'' was introduced in 1959.&lt;ref name=&quot;e36&quot; /&gt; This new model used a stamped sheet metal receiver and featured a slanted [[muzzle brake]] on the end of the [[gun barrel|barrel]] to compensate for [[muzzle rise]] under recoil. In addition, a hammer retarder was added to prevent the weapon from firing out of battery (without the bolt being fully closed), during rapid or fully automatic fire.{{sfn|Poyer|2006|pp=8–11}} This is also sometimes referred to as a &quot;cyclic rate reducer&quot;, or simply &quot;rate reducer&quot;, as it also has the effect of reducing the number of rounds fired per minute during fully automatic fire. It was also roughly one-third lighter than the previous model.&lt;ref name=&quot;e36&quot; /&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:left; margin:auto;&quot;
|-
! Receiver type
! Description&lt;ref name=&quot;browningmgs.com&quot; /&gt;
|-
! Type 1A/B
| The original [[Stamping (metalworking)|stamped]] receiver for the AK-47 first produced in 1948&lt;ref name=&quot;Ezell, Edward Clinton 1986 112&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author=Ezell, Edward Clinton |authorlink=Edward Ezell |title=The AK47 Story, Evolution of the Kalashnikov Weapons |date=1986 |publisher=[[Stackpole Books]] |url=https://books.google.com/?id=FroVAQAACAAJ&amp;dq=The+AK47+Story,+Evolution+of+the+Kalashnikov+Weapons |isbn=978-0-811709163 |page=112}}&lt;/ref&gt; adopted in 1949. The 1B was modified for an underfolding stock with a large hole present on each side to accommodate the hardware for the underfolding stock.
|-
! Type 2A/B
| The first [[Milling (machining)|milled]] receiver made from steel forging. It went into production in 1951 and production ended between 1953 and 1954. The Type 2A has a distinctive socketed metal &quot;boot&quot; connecting the butt stock to the receiver and the milled lightening cut on the sides runs parallel to the barrel.
|-
! Type 3A/B
| &quot;Final&quot; version of the AK milled receiver made from steel bar stock. It went into production between 1953 and 1954. The most ubiquitous example of the milled-receiver AK. The milled lightening cut on the sides is slanted to the barrel axis.
|-
! Type 4A/B
| [[AKM]] receiver stamped from a smooth {{convert|1.0|mm|abbr=on|2}} [[Sheet metal|sheet]] of [[steel]] supported extensively by pins and rivets. It went into production in 1959. Overall, the most-used design in the construction of the AK-series rifles.
|}

Both licensed and unlicensed production of the Kalashnikov weapons abroad were almost exclusively of the AKM variant, partially due to the much easier production of the stamped receiver. This model is the most commonly encountered, having been produced in much greater quantities. All rifles based on the Kalashnikov design are frequently referred to as AK-47s in the West, although this is only correct when applied to rifles based on the original three receiver types.{{sfn|Poyer|2006|p=2}} In most former Eastern Bloc countries, the weapon is known simply as the &quot;Kalashnikov&quot; or &quot;AK&quot;. The differences between the milled and stamped receivers includes the use of rivets rather than welds on the stamped receiver, as well as the placement of a small dimple above the magazine well for stabilization of the magazine.

=== Replacement ===
In 1974, the Soviets began replacing their AK-47 and AKM rifles with a newer design, the [[AK-74]], which uses [[5.45×39mm]] ammunition. This new rifle and cartridge had only started to be manufactured in Eastern European nations when the [[Collapse of the Soviet Union|Soviet Union collapsed]], drastically slowing production of the AK-74 and other weapons of the former Soviet bloc.

== Design ==
The AK-47 was designed to be a simple, reliable fully automatic rifle that could be manufactured quickly and cheaply, using mass production methods that were state of the art in the Soviet Union during the late 1940s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dunnigan&quot; /&gt; The AK-47 uses a [[Gas-operated reloading#Long-stroke piston|long stroke gas system]] that is generally associated with great reliability in adverse conditions.&lt;ref name=&quot;The AR-15 2010&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Tilstra&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Dockery&quot; /&gt; The large gas piston, generous clearances between moving parts, and tapered cartridge case design allow the gun to endure large amounts of foreign matter and fouling without failing to cycle.

=== Cartridge ===
{{Main|7.62×39mm}}
[[File:RussianWP.jpg|thumb|Wound Profiles of Russian small-arms ammunition compiled by Dr. [[Martin Fackler]] on behalf of the U.S. military]]

The AK fires the 7.62×39mm [[cartridge (weaponry)|cartridge]] with a muzzle velocity of {{convert|715|m/s|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;izhmash&quot; /&gt;
The cartridge weight is {{convert|16.3|g|oz|abbr=on|1}}, the projectile weight is {{convert|7.9|g|gr|abbr=on|0}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;ammoweight&quot; /&gt; The original Soviet M43 bullets are 123 grain [[boat-tail bullet]]s with a copper-plated steel jacket, a large steel core, and some lead between the core and the jacket. The AK has excellent penetration when shooting through heavy foliage, walls or a common vehicle's metal body and into an opponent attempting to use these things as cover. The 7.62×39mm M43 projectile does not generally fragment when striking an opponent and has an unusual tendency to remain intact even after making contact with bone. The 7.62×39mm round produces significant wounding in cases where the bullet tumbles (yaws) in tissue,&lt;ref name=&quot;Bellamy p146-155&quot; /&gt; but produces relatively minor wounds in cases where the bullet exits before beginning to yaw.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated7&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Roberts-2008&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Purdy&quot; /&gt; In the absence of yaw, the M43 round can pencil through tissue with relatively little injury.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated7&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bellamy p148&quot; /&gt;

Most, if not all, of the 7.62×39mm ammunition found today is of the upgraded M67 variety. This variety deleted the steel insert, shifting the center of gravity rearward, and allowing the projectile to destabilize (or yaw) at about {{convert|3.3|in|cm|abbr=on}}, nearly {{convert|6.7|in|cm|abbr=on}} earlier in tissue than the M43 round.&lt;ref name=&quot;uthr.org&quot; /&gt; This change also reduces penetration in ballistic gelatin to ~{{convert|25|in|cm|abbr=on}} for the newer M67 round versus ~{{convert|29|in|cm|abbr=on}} for the older M43 round.&lt;ref name=&quot;uthr.org&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Fackler&quot; /&gt; However, the wounding potential of M67 is mostly limited to the small permanent wound channel the bullet itself makes, especially when the bullet yaws.&lt;ref name=&quot;uthr.org&quot; /&gt;

=== Operating mechanism ===
[[File:Chinese type 56 AK47.jpg|thumb|The gas-operated mechanism of a [[Type 56 assault rifle|Norinco AK-47]]]]

To fire, the operator inserts a loaded [[Magazine (firearms)|magazine]], pulls back and releases the charging handle, and then pulls the [[Trigger (firearms)|trigger]]. In semi-automatic, the firearm fires only once, requiring the trigger to be released and depressed again for the next shot. In fully automatic, the rifle continues to fire automatically cycling fresh rounds into the chamber until the magazine is exhausted or pressure is released from the trigger. After ignition of the cartridge primer and propellant, rapidly expanding propellant gases are diverted into the gas cylinder above the barrel through a vent near the muzzle. The build-up of gases inside the gas cylinder drives the long-stroke piston and [[Bolt (firearm)|bolt]] carrier rearward and a cam guide machined into the underside of the bolt carrier, along with an ejector spur on the bolt carrier rail guide, rotates the bolt approximately 35° and unlocks it from the barrel extension via a camming pin on the bolt. The moving assembly has about {{convert|5.5|mm|abbr=on|1}} of free travel, which creates a delay between the initial recoil impulse of the piston and the bolt unlocking sequence, allowing gas pressures to drop to a safe level before the seal between the chamber and the bolt is broken. The AK-47 does not have a gas valve; excess gases are ventilated through a series of radial ports in the gas cylinder. The Kalashnikov operating system offers no [[primary extraction]] upon bolt rotation, but uses an extractor claw to eject the spent cartridge case.&lt;ref name=&quot;army&quot; /&gt;

=== Barrel ===
[[File:Ak-47-iraqis.jpg|thumb|AK-47 barrel and its distinctive gas block with a horizontal row of gas relief ports]]

The rifle received a barrel with a [[Chrome plating|chrome-lined]] bore and four right-hand grooves at a 240&amp;nbsp;mm (1 in 9.45 in) or 31.5 calibers [[Rifling#Twist rate|rifling twist rate]]. The gas block contains a gas channel that is installed at a slanted angle in relation to the bore axis. The muzzle is threaded for the installation of various muzzle devices such as a [[muzzle brake]] or a [[blank-firing adaptor]].

===Gas block===
The gas block of the AK-47 features a cleaning rod capture or sling loop. Gas relief ports that alleviate gas pressure are placed horizontally in a row on the gas cylinder.

=== Fire selector ===
[[File:Viet Cong soldier DD-ST-99-04298.jpg|thumb|left|upright|[[Việt Cộng]] soldier armed with an AK-47, standing beneath the flag of the [[National Liberation Front of South Vietnam]]]]

The fire selector is a large lever located on the right side of the rifle, it acts as a dust-cover and prevents the charging handle from being pulled fully to the rear when it is on safe.&lt;ref name=&quot;arsenalinc1&quot; /&gt; It is operated by the shooter's right fore-fingers and has 3 settings: safe (up), full-auto (center), and semi-auto (down).&lt;ref name=&quot;arsenalinc1&quot; /&gt; The reason for this is that under stress a soldier will push the selector lever down with considerable force bypassing the full-auto stage and setting the rifle to semi-auto.&lt;ref name=&quot;arsenalinc1&quot; /&gt; To set the AK-47 to full-auto requires the deliberate action of centering the selector lever.&lt;ref name=&quot;arsenalinc1&quot; /&gt; To operate the fire selector lever, right handed shooters have to briefly remove their right hand from the pistol grip, which is ergonomically sub-optimal. Some AK-type rifles also have a more traditional selector lever on the left side of the receiver just above the pistol grip.&lt;ref name=&quot;arsenalinc1&quot; /&gt; This lever is operated by the shooter's right thumb and has three settings: safe (forward), full-auto (center), and semi-auto (backward).&lt;ref name=&quot;arsenalinc1&quot; /&gt;

=== Sights ===
[[File:AK47-rear-sight.jpg|thumb|Rear sight of a Chinese Type 56, featuring {{convert|100|to|800|m|yd|0|abbr=on}} settings and omission of a battle zero setting]]

The AK-47 uses a notched rear tangent [[iron sight]] calibrated in {{convert|100|m|yd|0|abbr=on}} increments from {{convert|100|to|800|m|yd|0|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;scribd1&quot; /&gt; The front sight is a post adjustable for elevation in the field. Horizontal adjustment requires a special drift tool and is done by the armory before issue or if the need arises by an armorer after issue. The sight line elements are approximately {{convert|48.5|mm|in|1|abbr=on|lk=on}} over the bore axis. The &quot;[[point-blank range]]&quot; battle zero setting &quot;'''''П'''''&quot; standing for ''постоянная'' (constant) on the 7.62×39mm AK-47 rear tangent sight element corresponds to a {{convert|300|m|yd|0|abbr=on}} zero.&lt;ref name=&quot;scribd1&quot; /&gt;{{sfn|Rottman|2011|p=42}} These settings mirror the [[Mosin–Nagant]] and [[SKS]] rifles, which the AK-47 replaced. For the AK-47 combined with service cartridges, the 300 m battle zero setting limits the [[External ballistics#Bullet drop|apparent &quot;bullet rise&quot;]] within approximately {{convert|-5|to|+31|cm|in|1|abbr=on}} relative to the line of sight. Soldiers are instructed to fire at any target within this range by simply placing the sights on the center of mass (the belt buckle, according to Russian and former Soviet doctrine) of the enemy target. Any errors in range estimation are tactically irrelevant, as a well-aimed shot will hit the torso of the enemy soldier. Some AK-type rifles have a front sight with a flip-up luminous dot that is calibrated at {{convert|50|m|yd|0|abbr=on}}, for improved night fighting.&lt;ref name=&quot;scribd1&quot; /&gt;

=== Furniture ===
The AK-47 was originally equipped with a buttstock, handguard and an upper heat guard made from solid wood. With the introduction of the Type 3 receiver the buttstock, lower handguard and upper heatguard were manufactured from [[birch]] [[plywood]] [[laminates]].&lt;ref name=&quot;browningmgs.com&quot; /&gt; Such engineered woods are stronger and resist warping better than the conventional one-piece patterns, do not require lengthy maturing, and are cheaper. The wooden furniture was finished with the Russian amber shellac finishing process.{{citation needed|date=October 2015}} AKS and AKMS models featured a downward-folding metal butt-stock similar to that of the German [[MP40|MP40 submachine-gun]], for use in the restricted space in the [[BMP development|BMP infantry combat vehicle]], as well as by paratroops. All 100 series AKs use plastic furniture with side-folding stocks.

=== Magazines ===

[[File:Bakelite AK magazines.jpg|thumb|&quot;Bakelite&quot; rust-colored steel-reinforced 30-round plastic box 7.62×39mm AK magazines. Three magazines have an &quot;arrow in triangle&quot; [[Izhmash]] arsenal mark on the bottom right. The other magazine has a &quot;star&quot; [[Tula Arms Plant|Tula]] arsenal mark on the bottom right]]

The standard magazine capacity is 30 rounds. There are also 10, 20, and 40-round box magazines, as well as 75-round [[drum magazine|drum]] magazines.

The AK-47's standard 30-round magazines have a pronounced curve that allows them to smoothly feed ammunition into the chamber. Their heavy steel construction combined with &quot;feed-lips&quot; (the surfaces at the top of the magazine that control the angle at which the cartridge enters the chamber) machined from a single steel billet makes them highly resistant to damage. These magazines are so strong that &quot;Soldiers have been known to use their mags as hammers, and even bottle openers&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Small Arms Defense Journal&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;magazine video&quot; /&gt; This contributes to the AK-47 magazine being more reliable, but makes it heavier than U.S. and NATO magazines.

The early slab-sided steel AK-47 30-round detachable box magazines had {{convert|1|mm|in|abbr=on}} sheet-metal bodies and weighed {{convert|0.43|kg|lb|abbr=on}} empty.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dockery&quot; /&gt; The later steel AKM 30-round magazines had lighter sheet-metal bodies with prominent reinforcing ribs weighing {{convert|0.33|kg|lb|abbr=on}} empty.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dockery&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;scribd2&quot; /&gt; To further reduce weight, a lightweight magazine with an aluminum body with a prominent reinforcing waffle rib pattern weighing {{convert|0.19|kg|lb|abbr=on}} empty was developed for the AKM that proved to be too fragile and the small issued amount of these magazines was quickly withdrawn from service. As a replacement steel-reinforced 30-round plastic 7.62×39mm box magazines were introduced. These [[Rust (color)|rust-colored]] magazines weigh {{convert|0.24|kg|lb|abbr=on}} empty and are often mistakenly identified as being made of [[Bakelite]] (a [[phenolic resin]]), but were actually fabricated from two-parts of AG-S4 molding compound (a [[glass-filled polymer|glass-reinforced]] phenol-formaldehyde binder impregnated composite), assembled using an [[epoxy resin]] adhesive.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kokalis&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AG-S4&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kokalis_49&quot; /&gt; Noted for their durability, these magazines did however compromise the rifle's camouflage and lacked the small horizontal reinforcing ribs running down both sides of the magazine body near the front that were added on all later plastic magazine generations.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kokalis_49&quot; /&gt; A second generation steel-reinforced dark-brown (color shades vary from [[maroon]] to [[Plum (color)|plum]] to near [[black]]) 30-round 7.62×39mm magazine was introduced in the early 1980s, fabricated from [[Acrylonitrile butadiene styrene|ABS]] plastic. The third generation steel-reinforced 30-round 7.62×39mm magazine is similar to the second generation, but is darker colored and has a matte nonreflective surface finish. The current issue steel-reinforced matte true black nonreflective surface finished 7.62×39mm 30-round magazines, fabricated from ABS plastic weigh {{convert|0.25|kg|lb|abbr=on}} empty.&lt;ref name=&quot;izhmash&quot; /&gt;

Early steel AK-47 magazines are {{convert|9.75|in|mm|abbr=on}} long; the later ribbed steel AKM and newer plastic 7.62×39mm magazines are about {{convert|1|in|mm|abbr=on}} shorter.&lt;ref name=&quot;dtic.mil&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;tormented&quot; /&gt;

The transition from steel to mainly plastic magazines yields a significant weight reduction and allows a soldier to carry more ammunition for the same weight.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;background:#efefef;&quot; | Rifle
! style=&quot;background:#efefef;&quot; | Cartridge
! style=&quot;background:#efefef;&quot; | Cartridge weight
! style=&quot;background:#efefef;&quot; | Weight of empty magazine
! style=&quot;background:#efefef;&quot; | Weight of loaded magazine
! style=&quot;background:#efefef;&quot; | Max. {{convert|10.12|kg|lbs|abbr=on}} ammunition load*
|-
| AK-47 (1949)
| [[7.62×39mm]]
| {{convert|16.3|g|gr|abbr=on}}
| slab-sided steel&lt;br /&gt;{{convert|430|g|lb|abbr=on}}
| 30-rounds&lt;br /&gt;{{convert|916|g|lbs|abbr=on}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Dockery&quot; /&gt;
| 11 magazines for 330 rounds&lt;br /&gt;{{convert|10.08|kg|lbs|abbr=on}}
|-
| [[AKM]] (1959)
| 7.62×39mm
| {{convert|16.3|g|gr|abbr=on}}
| ribbed stamped-steel&lt;br /&gt;{{convert|330|g|lbs|abbr=on}}
| 30-rounds&lt;br /&gt;{{convert|819|g|lbs|abbr=on}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Dockery&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;scribd2&quot; /&gt;
| 12 magazines for 360 rounds&lt;br /&gt;{{convert|9.83|kg|lbs|abbr=on}}
|-
| [[AK-103]] (1994)
| 7.62×39mm
| {{convert|16.3|g|gr|abbr=on}}
| steel-reinforced plastic&lt;br /&gt;{{convert|250|g|lbs|abbr=on}}
| 30-rounds&lt;br /&gt;{{convert|739|g|lbs|abbr=on}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Dockery&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;scribd2&quot; /&gt;
| 13 magazines for 390 rounds&lt;br /&gt;{{convert|9.61|kg|lbs|abbr=on}}
|}

All 7.62×39mm AK magazines are backwards compatible with older AK variants.

10.12&amp;nbsp;kg (22.3&amp;nbsp;lb) is the maximum amount of ammo that the average soldier can comfortably carry. It also allows for best comparison of the three most common 7.62×39mm AK magazines.

Most Yugoslavian and some East German AK magazines were made with cartridge followers that hold the bolt open when empty; however, most AK magazine followers allow the bolt to close when the magazine is empty.

=== Accessories ===
[[File:AK-47 bayonet and scabbard.jpg|thumb|left|AK-47 6H2 bayonet and scabbard]]
[[File:AK103 GP 34.jpg|thumb|AK-103 with [[GP-25|GP-34]] Grenade Launcher]]
[[File:AK47Figure54.jpg|thumb|left|AK-47 with Kalashnikov grenade launcher mounted on the muzzle]]
Accessories supplied with the rifle include a {{convert|387|mm|in|abbr=on}} long 6H3 [[bayonet]] featuring a {{convert|200|mm|in|abbr=on}} long spear point blade. The AK-47 bayonet is installed by slipping the {{convert|17.7|mm|in|abbr=on}} diameter muzzle ring around the muzzle and latching the handle down on the bayonet lug under the front sight base.&lt;ref name=&quot;worldbayonets.com&quot; /&gt;

All current model AKM rifles can mount under-barrel 40&amp;nbsp;mm grenade launchers such as the [[GP-25]] and its variants, which can fire up to 20 rounds per minute and have an effective range of up to 400 metres.&lt;ref name=&quot;Izhmash gp-34&quot; /&gt; The main grenade is the VOG-25 (VOG-25M) fragmentation grenade which has a 6&amp;nbsp;m (9&amp;nbsp;m) (20&amp;nbsp;ft (30&amp;nbsp;ft)) lethality radius. The VOG-25P/VOG-25PM (&quot;jumping&quot;) variant explodes {{convert|0.5|–|1|m|ft}} above the ground.&lt;ref name=&quot;Russian Close Combat Weapon&quot; /&gt;

The AK-47 can also mount a (rarely used) [[Rifle grenade#Cup-type|cup-type grenade launcher]], the [[Kalashnikov grenade launcher]] that fires standard [[RGD-5]] Soviet hand-grenades. The maximum effective range is approximately 150 meters.&lt;ref name=&quot;ar15&quot; /&gt; This launcher can also be used to launch [[tear-gas]] and [[riot control]] grenades.

All current AKs (100 series) and some older models, have side rails for mounting a variety of scopes and sighting devices, such as the [[PSO-1|PSO-1 Optical Sniper Sight]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Izhmash ak103&quot; /&gt; The side rails allow for the removal and remounting of optical accessories without interfering with the zeroing of the optic. However, the 100 series side folding stocks cannot be folded with the optics mounted.

== Characteristics ==
=== Service life ===
The AK-47 and its variants have been and are made in dozens of countries, with &quot;quality ranging from finely engineered weapons to pieces of questionable workmanship.&quot;{{sfn|Rottman|2011|p=39}} As a result, the AK-47 has a service/system life of approximately 6,000,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.mouseguns.com/mak90web/mak90man.pdf | author=Norinco | title=Instruction Manual Model MAK-90 Semi-Automatic Rifle | publisher=mouseguns.com | accessdate=12 January 2016 | archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160304080152/http://www.mouseguns.com/mak90web/mak90man.pdf | archive-date=4 March 2016 | url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt; to 10,000,&lt;ref name=&quot;Forgotten Weapons&quot; /&gt; to 15,000&lt;ref name=&quot;AR-M1&quot; /&gt; rounds. The AK-47 was designed to be a cheap, simple, easy to manufacture assault rifle,&lt;ref name=&quot;VDH&quot; /&gt; perfectly matching Soviet military doctrine that treats equipment and weapons as disposable items.&lt;ref name=&quot;scribd.com&quot; /&gt; As units are often deployed without adequate logistical support and dependent on &quot;battlefield cannibalization&quot; for resupply, it is actually more cost-effective to replace rather than repair weapons.&lt;ref name=&quot;scribd.com&quot; /&gt;

The AK-47 has small parts and springs that need to be replaced every few thousand rounds. However, &quot;Every time it is disassembled beyond the field stripping stage, it will take some time for some parts to regain their fit, some parts may tend to shake loose and fall out when firing the weapon. Some parts of the AK-47 line are riveted together. Repairing these can be quite a hassle, since the end of the rivet has to be ground off and a new one set after the part is replaced.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;scribd1&quot; /&gt;

== Variants ==
[[File:AK-47 bullets from China, Pakistan and Russia.jpg|thumb|7.62×39mm cartridges from Russia, China and Pakistan]]

; Early variants (7.62×39mm)
* Issue of 1948/49: Type 1: The very earliest models, stamped sheet metal receiver, are now very rare.
* Issue of 1951: Type 2: Has a milled receiver. Barrel and chamber are chrome plated to resist corrosion.
* Issue of 1954/55: Type 3: Lightened, milled receiver variant. Rifle weight is {{convert|3.47|kg|lb|abbr=on}}.{{sfn|НСД. 7,62-мм автомат АК|1967|pp=161–162}}
* AKS (AKS-47): Type 1, 2, or 3 receiver: Featured a downward-folding metal stock similar to that of the [[MP 40]] produced in [[Nazi Germany]], for use in the restricted space in the [[BMP-1|BMP]] infantry combat vehicle, as well as by paratroops.
* AKN (AKSN): Night scope rail.{{sfn|Monetchikov|2005|p=76}}

; Modernized (7.62×39mm)
* [[AKM]]: A simplified, lighter version of the AK-47; Type 4 receiver is made from stamped and riveted sheet metal. A slanted muzzle device was added to counter climb in automatic fire. Rifle weight is {{convert|3.1|kg|lb|abbr=on}}&lt;ref name=&quot;izhmash&quot; /&gt; due to the lighter receiver. This is the most ubiquitous variant of the AK-47.
** AKMS: Under-folding stock version of the AKM intended for [[airborne forces|airborne]] troops.
** AKMN (AKMSN): Night scope rail.
** AKML (AKMSL): Slotted flash suppressor and night scope rail.&lt;ref name=&quot;AKML&quot; /&gt;
* [[RPK]]: Hand-held machine gun version with longer barrel and [[bipod]]. The variants—RPKS, RPKN (RPKSN), RPKL (RPKSL)—mirror AKM variants. The &quot;S&quot; variants have a side-folding wooden stock.

For the further developed AK models, see [[Kalashnikov rifle]]&lt;nowiki/&gt;s.

== Production ==
{{more citations needed|section|date=July 2018}}&lt;!--most of this table is not cited--&gt;
Manufacturing countries of AK-47 and its variants in alphabetical order.
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot;
|-
! Country !! Military variant(s)
|-
! Albania {{r|alb}}
| Automatiku Shqiptar 1978 model 56 (ASH-78 Tip-1) made at Poliçan Arsenal (copy of [[Type 56 assault rifle|Type 56]] based on [[AKM]] rifle); model 56 Tip-2, copy of [[RPK]]; model 56 Tip-3 hybrid for multi-purpose roles with secondary assault rifle and grenade launcher capability; 1982 model (ASH-82) copy of [[AKMS]]. Several other versions of the AKMS have been produced mainly with short barrels similar to Soviet [[AK-74|AKS-74U]] for special forces, tank &amp; armoured crew and for helicopter pilots and police. There have also been modified ASh-82 ([[AKMS]]) with [[SOPMOD]] accessories, mainly for Albania's special forces [[RENEA]] &amp; exports.&lt;ref name=alb&gt;[http://aftermathgunclub.com/2015/04/20/albanian-small-arms/ Albanian Small Arms] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171014034429/http://aftermathgunclub.com/2015/04/20/albanian-small-arms/ |date=14 October 2017 }} by Aftermath Gun Club.&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
! Armenia
| [[K-3 (rifle)|K-3]] (bullpup, [[5.45×39mm]])
|-
! Azerbaijan {{r|Azerbaijan}}
| Khazri (AK-74M){{r|Azerbaijan}}
|-
! Bangladesh
| Chinese [[Type 56 assault rifle|Type 56]]
|-
! Bulgaria
| AKK/AKKS (Type 3 AK-47/w. side-folding buttstock); AKKMS (AKMS), AKKN-47 (fittings for NPSU night sights); AK-47M1 (Type 3 with black polymer furniture); [[AR-M1|AK-47MA1/AR-M1]] (same as -M1, but in 5.56mm NATO); AKS-47M1 (AKMS in [[5.56×45mm NATO]]); AKS-47S (AK-47M1, short version, with East German folding stock, laser aiming device); AKS-47UF (short version of -M1, Russian folding stock), AR-SF (same as −47UF, but 5.56mm NATO); AKS-93SM6 (similar to −47M1, cannot use grenade launcher); and RKKS (RPK), AKT-47 (.22 rimfire training rifle)
|-
! Cambodia
| Chinese [[Type 56 assault rifle|Type 56]], Soviet AK-47, and [[AKM]]
|-
! China
| [[Type 56 assault rifle|Type 56]]
|-
! Colombia
| [[Galil ACE]]
|-
! Croatia
| [[APS-95]]
|-
! Cuba {{r|variants}}
| AKM {{r|variants}}
|-
! [[East Germany]] {{r|MPi-AK}}
| MPi-K/MPi-KS (AK-47/AKS); MPi-KM (AKM; wooden and plastic stock), MPi-KMS-72 (side-folding stock), MPi-KMS-K (carbine); MPi-AK-74N (AK-74), MPi-AKS-74N (side-folding stock), MPi-AKS-74NK (carbine); KK-MPi Mod.69 ([[.22 Long Rifle|.22 LR]] select-fire trainer) {{r|MPi-AK}}
|-
! Egypt
| AK-47, [[Misr assault rifle]] (AKMS), Maadi ARM (AKM)
|-
! Ethiopia {{r|Et-97/1}}
| AK-47, [[AK-103]] (manufactured locally at the State-run ''[[Gafat Armament Engineering Complex]]'' as the Et-97/1) {{r|Et-97/1}}
|-
! Finland
| [[Rk 62]], [[Valmet M76]] (other names Rk 62 76, M62/76), [[Valmet M78]] (light machine gun), [[Rk 95 Tp]]
|-
! Hungary {{r|Hungary}}
| AK-55 (domestic manufacture of the 2nd Model AK-47); AKM-63 (also known as AMD-63 in the US; modernized AK-55), [[AMD-65]]M (modernized AKM-63, shorter barrel and side-folding stock), [[AMP-69]] (rifle grenade launcher); [[AK-63]]F/D (other name AMM/AMMSz), AK-63MF (modernized); NGM-81 ([[5.56×45mm NATO]]; fixed and under-folding stock) {{r|Hungary}}
|-
! India {{r|India}}
| [[INSAS]] (fixed and side-folding stock), [[INSAS#Variant &amp; Developments|KALANTAK]] (carbine), [[INSAS#Variant &amp; Developments|INSAS light machine gun]] (fixed and side-folding stock), a local unlicensed version with carbon fibre furniture designated as AK-7;{{r|India}} and Trichy Assault Rifle 7.62&amp;nbsp;mm manufactured by [[Ordnance Factory Tiruchirappalli]] of [[Ordnance Factories Board]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Ordnance Factories Board&quot; /&gt;
|-
! Iran
| KLS/KLF (AK-47/AKS), KLT (AKMS)
|-
! Iraq
| [[Tabuk Sniper Rifle]], Tabuk Assault Rifle (with fixed or underfolding stock, outright clones of Yugoslavian M70 rifles series), Tabuk Short Assault Rifle (carbine)
|-
! Israel
| [[IMI Galil]]: AR (assault/battle rifle), ARM (assault rifle/light machine gun), SAR (carbine), MAR (compact carbine), Sniper (sniper rifle), SR-99 (sniper rifle); and [[Galil ACE]]
|-
! Italy {{r|Bernardelli}}
| Bernardelli VB-STD/VB-SR (Galil AR/SAR) {{r|Bernardelli}}
|-
! Nigeria {{r|DICON}}
| Produced by the Defence Industries Corporation of Nigeria as OBJ-006&lt;ref name=&quot;People's Daily Nigeria&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;DICON&quot; /&gt;
|-
! North Korea
| [[Type 58 assault rifle|Type 58]]A/B (Type 3 AK-47/w. stamped steel folding stock), Type 68A/B (AKM/AKMS), Type 88A/B-2 (AK-74/AKS-74/w. top folding stock)&lt;ref name=&quot;Weapon&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;North Korea&quot; /&gt;
|-
! Pakistan {{r|Pakistan}}
| [[Reverse Engineering|Reverse engineered]] by hand and machine in Pakistan's highland areas (see [[Khyber Pass Copy]]) near the border of Afghanistan; more recently the [[Pakistan Ordnance Factories]] started the manufacture of an AK-47/AKM clone called PK-10&lt;ref name=&quot;Pakistan&quot; /&gt;
|-
! Poland {{r|Poland}}
| PmK (kbk AK) / PmKS (kbk AKS), Kalashnikov SMG name change to Kbk AK, Kalashnikov Carbine in 1960s, (AK-47/AKS); [[kbkg wz. 1960]] (rifle grenade launcher), kbkg wz. 1960/72 (modernized); kbk AKM / kbk AKMS (AKM/AKMS); [[kbk wz. 1988 Tantal]] ([[5.45×39mm]]), [[skbk wz. 1989 Onyks]] (compact carbine); [[kbs wz. 1996 Beryl]] ([[5.56×45mm NATO|5.56×45mm]]), [[kbk wz. 1996 Mini-Beryl]] (compact carbine) {{r|Poland}}
|-
! Romania
| [[Pistol Mitralieră model 1963/1965|PM md. 63/65]] (AKM/AKMS), [[Pistol Mitralieră model 1963/1965#PM md. 80|PM md. 80]], [[Pistol Mitralieră model 1963/1965#PM md. 90|PM md. 90]], collectively exported under the umbrella name AIM or AIMS; [[PA md. 86]] (AK-74) exported as the AIMS-74; PM md. 90 short barrel, PA md. 86 short barrel exported as the AIMR; [[PSL (rifle)|PSL]] (designated marksman rifle; other names PSL-54C, Romak III, FPK and SSG-97)
|-
! South Africa
| [[R4 assault rifle]], [[Truvelo Raptor]], [[Vektor CR-21]] (bullpup)
|-
! Sudan {{r|MAZ}}
| MAZ (based on the [[Type 56 assault rifle|Type 56]]) {{r|MAZ}}
|-
! Ukraine {{r|Malyuk}}
| [[Vepr]] (bullpup, [[5.45×39mm]]), Malyuk (bullpup)&lt;ref name=&quot;Malyuk&quot; /&gt;
|-
! United States
| Century Arms: C39 (AK-47 var.), RAS47 (AKM var.), and C39v2 (AK-47 var.)), InterOrdnance: AKM247 (AKM var.) M214 (pistol), Palmetto State Armory: PSAK-47 (AKM var.), Arsenal Inc: SA M-7 (AK-47 var.), Destructive Devices Industries: DDI 47S (AKM var.) DDI 47M (AK-47 var), Rifle Dynamics: RD700 and other custom build AK / AKM guns
|-
! Vietnam
| AKM-1 (AKM), TUL-1 (RPK), Galil Ace 31/32
|-
! Venezuela {{r|Venezuela}}
| License granted, factory under construction&lt;ref name=&quot;Venezuela&quot; /&gt;
|-
! [[Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia|Yugoslavia]]/[[Serbia]]
| M64, [[Zastava M70|M70]], [[Zastava M72|M72]], [[Zastava M76|M76]], [[Zastava M77|M77]], [[Zastava M80|M80]], [[Zastava M82|M82]], [[Zastava M85|M85]], [[Zastava M90|M90]], [[Zastava M91|M91]], [[Zastava M92|M92]], [[Zastava M99|M99]], [[Zastava M21|M21]]
|}

A private company [[Kalashnikov Concern]] (formerly Izhmash) from Russia has repeatedly claimed that the majority of foreign manufacturers are producing AK-type rifles without proper [[license|licensing]].&lt;ref name=&quot;licensing-1&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;licensing-2&quot; /&gt;

==Accuracy potential==
===Western method===
The AK-47's accuracy has always been considered {{By whom|date=October 2017}} to be &quot;good enough&quot; to hit an adult male torso out to about {{convert|300|m|yd|0|abbr=on}},&lt;ref name=&quot;defenseindustrydaily1&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;alpharubicon2&quot; /&gt; though even experts firing from prone or bench rest positions at this range were observed to have difficulty placing ten consecutive rounds on target.&lt;ref name=&quot;chivers&quot; /&gt; Later designs did not significantly improve its accuracy.&lt;ref name=chivers/&gt; An AK can fire a 10-shot group of {{convert|5.9|in|cm|abbr=on}} at {{convert|100|m|yd|0|abbr=on}},&lt;ref name=&quot;krtraining1&quot; /&gt; and {{convert|17.5|in|cm|abbr=on}} at {{convert|300|m|yd|0|abbr=on}}&lt;ref name=&quot;chivers&quot; /&gt; The newer stamped-steel receiver [[AKM]] models, while more rugged and less prone to metal fatigue, are actually less accurate than the forged/milled receivers of their predecessors: the milled AK-47s are capable of shooting {{convert|3|to|5|in|cm|0|abbr=on}} groups at {{convert|100|yd|m|0|abbr=on}}, whereas the stamped AKMs are capable of shooting {{convert|4|to|6|in|cm|0|abbr=on}} groups at {{convert|100|yd|m|0|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;alpharubicon2&quot; /&gt;

The best shooters are able to hit a man-sized target at {{convert|800|m|yd|0|abbr=on}} within five shots (firing from prone or bench rest position) or ten shots (standing).&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|НСД. 7,62-мм автомат АКМ (АКМС)|1983|p=155}}:&amp;nbsp;(under the default conditions of no wind and sea level atmospheric pressure, {{convert|15|C|F|0}}).&lt;/ref&gt;

The single-shot hit-probability on the NATO E-type Silhouette Target (a human upper body half and head silhouette) of the AK-47 and the later developed AK-74, M16A1 and M16A2 assault rifles were measured by the US military under ideal proving ground conditions in the 1980s as follows:

[[File:NATO E-type Silhouette Target.PNG|thumb|75 px|NATO E-type Silhouette Target]]

{|class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;
|-valign=&quot;top&quot;
! colspan=11 |'''Single-shot hit-probability on Crouching Man (NATO E-type Silhouette) Target'''{{efn|name=note1}}&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.dtic.mil/dtic/tr/fulltext/u2/a228398.pdf|title=TECHNICAL REPORT NO. 461 SYSTEM ERROR BUDGETS, TARGET DISTRIBUTIONS AND HITTING PERFORMANCE ESTIMATES FOR GENERAL-PURPOSE RIFLES AND SNIPER RIFLES OF 7.62 X 51 MM AND LARGER CALIBERS JONATHAN M. WEAVER, JR. LTC, INFANTRY, U.S. ARMY (RETIRED) MAY 1990 U.S. ARMY MATERIEL SYSTEMS ANALYSIS ACTIVITY ABERDEEN PROVING GROUND, MARYLAND, Page 87|accessdate=28 March 2019|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20151123093816/http://www.dtic.mil/dtic/tr/fulltext/u2/a228398.pdf|archive-date=23 November 2015|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
! rowspan=2|Rifle
! rowspan=2|Chambering
! colspan=9|Hit-probability &lt;small&gt;(With no range estimation or aiming errors)&lt;/small&gt;
|-
! &lt;small&gt;50 meters&lt;/small&gt;
! &lt;small&gt;100 meters&lt;/small&gt;
! &lt;small&gt;200 meters&lt;/small&gt;
! &lt;small&gt;300 meters&lt;/small&gt;
! &lt;small&gt;400 meters&lt;/small&gt;
! &lt;small&gt;500 meters&lt;/small&gt;
! &lt;small&gt;600 meters&lt;/small&gt;
! &lt;small&gt;700 meters&lt;/small&gt;
! &lt;small&gt;800 meters&lt;/small&gt;
|-
|AK-47 &lt;small&gt;(1949)&lt;/small&gt;
|[[7.62×39mm]]
|100%
|100%
|99%
|94%
|82%
|67%
|54%
|42%
|31%
|-
|[[AK-74]] &lt;small&gt;(1974)&lt;/small&gt;
|[[5.45×39mm]]
|100%
|100%
|100%
|99%
|93%
|81%
|66%
|51%
|34%
|-
|[[M16 rifle#XM16E1 and M16A1 (Colt Model 603)|M16A1]] &lt;small&gt;(1967)&lt;/small&gt;
|[[5.56×45mm NATO]] M193
|100%
|100%
|100%
|100%
|96%
|87%
|73%
|56%
|39%
|-
|[[M16 rifle#M16A2|M16A2]] &lt;small&gt;(1982)&lt;/small&gt;
|[[5.56×45mm NATO]] SS109/M855
|100%
|100%
|100%
|100%
|98%
|90%
|79%
|63%
|43%
|}
{{notelist|refs=
&lt;ref name=note1&gt;Under worst field exercise circumstances, due to range estimation and aiming errors, the hit probabilities for the tested assault rifles were drastically reduced with differences without operational significance.&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

===Russian method===
The following table represents the Russian method for determining accuracy, which is far more complex than Western methods. In the West, one fires a group of shots into the target and then simply measures the overall diameter of the group. The Russians, on the other hand, fire a group of shots into the target. They then draw two circles on the target, one for the maximum vertical dispersion of hits and one for the maximum horizontal dispersion of hits. They then disregard the hits on the outer part of the target and only count half of the hits (50% or R&lt;sub&gt;50&lt;/sub&gt;) on the inner part of the circles. This dramatically reduces the overall diameter of the groups. They then use both the vertical and horizontal measurements of the reduced groups to measure accuracy. This [[circular error probable]] method used by the Russians and other European militaries cannot be converted and is not comparable to US military methods for determining rifle accuracy. When the R&lt;sub&gt;50&lt;/sub&gt; results are doubled the hit probability increases to 93.7%.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;
!colspan=&quot;7&quot;|AK-47 semi-automatic and short burst dispersion with 57-N-231 steel core service ammunition&lt;ref name=&quot;мануал&quot;&gt;Instruction on small business 7,62- mm Kalashnikov (AK). - Moscow: Military Publishing House of the Ministry of Defense of the USSR, 1967.&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
!Range||Vertical accuracy of fire (R&lt;sub&gt;50&lt;/sub&gt;) semi-automatic||Horizontal accuracy of fire (R&lt;sub&gt;50&lt;/sub&gt;) semi-automatic||Vertical accuracy of fire (R&lt;sub&gt;50&lt;/sub&gt;) short burst||Horizontal accuracy of fire (R&lt;sub&gt;50&lt;/sub&gt;) short burst||Remaining bullet energy||Remaining bullet velocity
|-
|{{convert|0|m|yd|0|abbr=on}}||{{convert|0|cm|in|1|abbr=on}}||{{convert|0|cm|in|1|abbr=on}}||{{convert|0|cm|in|1|abbr=on}}||{{convert|0|cm|in|1|abbr=on}}||{{convert|2036|J|ftlbf|abbr=on}}||{{convert|718|m/s|ft/s|0|abbr=on}}
|-
|{{convert|100|m|yd|0|abbr=on}}||{{convert|8|cm|in|1|abbr=on}}||{{convert|4|cm|in|1|abbr=on}}||{{convert|9|cm|in|1|abbr=on}}||{{convert|11|cm|in|1|abbr=on}}||{{convert|1540|J|ftlbf|abbr=on}}||{{convert|624|m/s|ft/s|0|abbr=on}}
|-
|{{convert|200|m|yd|0|abbr=on}}||{{convert|11|cm|in|1|abbr=on}}||{{convert|8|cm|in|1|abbr=on}}||{{convert|18|cm|in|1|abbr=on}}||{{convert|22|cm|in|1|abbr=on}}||{{convert|1147|J|ftlbf|abbr=on}}||{{convert|539|m/s|ft/s|0|abbr=on}}
|-
|{{convert|300|m|yd|0|abbr=on}}||{{convert|17|cm|in|1|abbr=on}}||{{convert|12|cm|in|1|abbr=on}}||{{convert|27|cm|in|1|abbr=on}}||{{convert|33|cm|in|1|abbr=on}}||{{convert|843|J|ftlbf|abbr=on}}||{{convert|462|m/s|ft/s|0|abbr=on}}
|-
|{{convert|400|m|yd|0|abbr=on}}||{{convert|23|cm|in|1|abbr=on}}||{{convert|16|cm|in|1|abbr=on}}||{{convert|31|cm|in|1|abbr=on}}||{{convert|44|cm|in|1|abbr=on}}||{{convert|618|J|ftlbf|abbr=on}}||{{convert|395|m/s|ft/s|0|abbr=on}}
|-
|{{convert|500|m|yd|0|abbr=on}}||{{convert|29|cm|in|1|abbr=on}}||{{convert|20|cm|in|1|abbr=on}}||{{convert|46|cm|in|1|abbr=on}}||{{convert|56|cm|in|1|abbr=on}}||{{convert|461|J|ftlbf|abbr=on}}||{{convert|342|m/s|ft/s|0|abbr=on}}
|-
|{{convert|600|m|yd|0|abbr=on}}||{{convert|35|cm|in|1|abbr=on}}||{{convert|24|cm|in|1|abbr=on}}||{{convert|56|cm|in|1|abbr=on}}||{{convert|67|cm|in|1|abbr=on}}||{{convert|363|J|ftlbf|abbr=on}}||{{convert|303|m/s|ft/s|0|abbr=on}}
|-
|{{convert|700|m|yd|0|abbr=on}}||{{convert|42|cm|in|1|abbr=on}}||{{convert|29|cm|in|1|abbr=on}}||{{convert|66|cm|in|1|abbr=on}}||{{convert|78|cm|in|1|abbr=on}}||{{convert|314|J|ftlbf|abbr=on}}||{{convert|282|m/s|ft/s|0|abbr=on}}
|-
|{{convert|800|m|yd|0|abbr=on}}||{{convert|49|cm|in|1|abbr=on}}||{{convert|34|cm|in|1|abbr=on}}||{{convert|76|cm|in|1|abbr=on}}||{{convert|89|cm|in|1|abbr=on}}||{{convert|284|J|ftlbf|abbr=on}}||{{convert|268|m/s|ft/s|0|abbr=on}}
|}
* &lt;small&gt;R&lt;sub&gt;50&lt;/sub&gt; means the closest 50 percent of the shot group will all be within a circle of the mentioned diameter.&lt;/small&gt;

The vertical and horizontal mean (R&lt;sub&gt;50&lt;/sub&gt;) deviations with service ammunition at {{convert|800|m|yd|0|abbr=on}} for AK platforms are.
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;
!colspan=&quot;4&quot;|SKS, AK-47, AKM, and AK-74 dispersion at {{convert|800|m|yd|0|abbr=on}}
|-
!Rifle||Firing mode||Vertical accuracy of fire (R&lt;sub&gt;50&lt;/sub&gt;)||Horizontal accuracy of fire (R&lt;sub&gt;50&lt;/sub&gt;)
|-
|[[SKS]] &lt;small&gt;(1945)&lt;/small&gt;||semi-automatic||{{convert|38|cm|in|1|abbr=on}}||{{convert|29|cm|in|1|abbr=on}}
|-
|AK-47 &lt;small&gt;(1949)&lt;/small&gt;||semi-automatic||{{convert|49|cm|in|1|abbr=on}}||{{convert|34|cm|in|1|abbr=on}}
|-
|AK-47 &lt;small&gt;(1949)&lt;/small&gt;||short burst||{{convert|76|cm|in|1|abbr=on}}||{{convert|89|cm|in|1|abbr=on}}
|-
|[[AKM]] &lt;small&gt;(1959)&lt;/small&gt;||short burst||{{convert|64|cm|in|1|abbr=on}}||{{convert|90|cm|in|1|abbr=on}}
|-
|[[AK-74]] &lt;small&gt;(1974)&lt;/small&gt;||short burst||{{convert|48|cm|in|1|abbr=on}}||{{convert|64|cm|in|1|abbr=on}}
|-
|}

== Users ==
&lt;!--READ FIRST: This section is for cited entries only. Please do not add entries into this list without a citation from a reliable source. All entries without a citation will be removed. Thank you.--&gt;

{{Div col|colwidth=18em}}
* {{Flagcountry|Afghanistan}}&lt;ref name=&quot;washingtonpost&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Albania}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Algeria}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Angola}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Armenia}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Azerbaijan}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Bangladesh}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Belarus}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Benin}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Bosnia and Herzegovina}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Botswana}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Bulgaria}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Burkina Faso}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Army Recognition Burkina Faso&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Africa Defense Journal&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;afrikitalia&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Burundi}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Burundi-flickr&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;SSR Monitor&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Cambodia}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Cape Verde}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Central African Republic}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Chad}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Chile}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Gander&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|China}}: [[Type 56 assault rifle|Type 56]] variant.&lt;ref name=&quot;Miller&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Comoros}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Congo}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Cuba}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Democratic Republic of the Congo}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Djibouti}}&lt;ref name=&quot;roberthuffstutter&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Army Recognition Djibouti&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Egypt}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Equatorial Guinea}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Eritrea}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Ethiopia}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Gabon}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Georgia}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Greece}}: [[Special Anti-Terrorist Unit (Greece)|EKAM]]: The counter-terrorist unit of the [[Hellenic Police]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Milosevic&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hellenic Police&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Guinea}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Guinea-Bissau}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Guyana}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Hungary}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|India}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Force One&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Indonesia}}&lt;ref&gt;https://www.shadowspear.com/2009/01/kopassus/&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Iran}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Iraq}}&lt;ref name=&quot;washingtonpost&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Israel}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot;/&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Kazakhstan}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Kyrgyzstan}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Laos}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Lebanon}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Lesotho}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Liberia}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Libya}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Madagascar}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Mali}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Moldova}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Mongolia}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Morocco}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Mozambique}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Nicaragua}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Carlos Caballero|last= Jurado|title=Central American Wars 1959-89|series= Men-at-Arms 221 |publisher=[[Osprey Publishing]]|place= London|year= 1990 |isbn=9780850459456|ref=harv|pages=20, 45}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|North Korea}}: [[Type 58 assault rifle|Type 58]] variant.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|North Macedonia}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Nikolovski&quot; /&gt;
*{{Flagcountry|Pakistan}} - Locally made as well as being in service with the Army&lt;ref&gt;http://www.aljazeera.com/amp/indepth/features/darra-adam-khel-pakistan-dying-gun-bazaar-190204090518478.html&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Peru}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Poland}}&lt;ref name=&quot;popenker&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Qatar}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Romania}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Russia}}: Replaced by the [[AKM]] in 1959 and the [[AK-74]] in 1974.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Rwanda}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Army Recognition Rwanda&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|São Tomé and Príncipe}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Saudi Arabia}}&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://syrianobserver.com/EN/news/47016/uae-saudi-arabia-dispatch-troops-to-syria.html|title=UAE, Saudi Arabia Dispatch Troops to Syria|date=22 November 2018|accessdate=28 March 2019|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20181122120242/https://syrianobserver.com/EN/news/47016/uae-saudi-arabia-dispatch-troops-to-syria.html|archive-date=22 November 2018|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Serbia}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Seychelles}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Sierra Leone}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Somalia}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Sudan}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Suriname}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Syria}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Tajikistan}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Tanzania}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Thailand}}&lt;ref&gt;https://www.marketwatch.com/story/the-russian-guns-are-coming-ak-47s-could-soon-be-american-made-2015-01-22&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Togo}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Turkey}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Turkmenistan}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Ukraine}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{flag|United States}}&lt;ref&gt;https://www.thefirearmblog.com/blog/2016/04/12/aks-among-u-s-police-departments/&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;https://nationalinterest.org/blog/buzz/why-us-commandos-loved-ak-47-rifle-44872&lt;/ref&gt;
**{{flagdeco|Alabama}} [[List of law enforcement agencies in Alabama|Marshal County Police]]
**{{flagdeco|Alaska}} [[List of law enforcement agencies in Alaska|North Slope Borough Police Department]]
**{{flagdeco|California}} [[Ventura County Sheriff's Office]]
**{{flagdeco|Montana}} [[List of law enforcement agencies in Montana|Glacier County Sheriff's Department]]
**{{flag|United States Navy}} (In use with special forces)
* {{Flagcountry|Uzbekistan}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Vietnam}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Miller&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Yemen}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Zambia}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Zimbabwe}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;

=== Former users ===
* {{Flagcountry|East Germany}}: MPi-K (AK-47) and MPi-KM (AKM).&lt;ref name=&quot;popenker&quot;&gt;[http://world.guns.ru/assault/as01-e.htm Modern Firearms – AK-47 AKM] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080306135325/http://world.guns.ru/assault/as01-e.htm |date=6 March 2008 }}. World.guns.ru (24 January 2011). Retrieved on 14 March 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Rhodesia}}&lt;ref name=&quot;PTW&quot; /&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Soviet Union}}: Replaced by the AKM and AK-74.&lt;ref name=&quot;miller2001&quot;&gt;{{cite book| author = D. M. O. Miller| title = Illustrated directory of twentieth century guns| url = https://books.google.com/?id=GgpRPgAACAAJ| date = 31 August 2001| isbn = 978-1-84065-245-1 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{Flagcountry|Yugoslavia}}: Zastava M64 (AK-47) and M70 (AKM).&lt;ref name=&quot;popenker&quot;/&gt;
{{div col end}}

=== Illicit trade ===
{{see also|Crime in Russia#Arms trafficking}}
[[File:Somalimerirosvojen rynnäkkökiväärejä Maneesi.JPG|thumb|AK-47 copies confiscated from Somali pirates by Finnish mine-layer {{ship|Finnish minelayer|Pohjanmaa||2}} during [[Operation Atalanta]], photographed in Manege Military Museum. The stocks are missing on the top three AKs]]

Throughout the world, the AK and its variants are commonly used by governments, revolutionaries, terrorists, criminals, and civilians alike. In some countries, such as Somalia, Rwanda, Mozambique, Congo and Tanzania, the prices for Black Market AKs are between $30 and $125 per weapon and prices have fallen in the last few decades due to mass counterfeiting.&lt;ref name=&quot;ControlArms&quot; /&gt; In Kenya, &quot;an AK-47 fetches five head of cattle (about 10,000 Kenya shillings or 100 U.S. dollars) when offered for barter, but costs almost half that price when cash is paid&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;van Schendel&quot; /&gt; There are places around the world where AK type weapons can be purchased on the [[black market]] &quot;for as little as $6, or traded for a chicken or a sack of grain&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;ECOSOCDEV&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;UNCHR&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kabbani&quot; /&gt;

The AK-47 has also spawned a cottage industry of sorts and has been copied and manufactured (one gun at a time) in small shops around the world (see [[Khyber Pass Copy]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;Santos&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;smallarmssurvey-1&quot; /&gt; The estimated numbers of AK-type weapons vary greatly. The Small Arms Survey suggest that &quot;between 70 and 100&amp;nbsp;million of these weapons have been produced since 1947&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;smallarmssurvey-2&quot; /&gt; The World Bank estimates that out of the 500&amp;nbsp;million total firearms available worldwide, 100&amp;nbsp;million are of the Kalashnikov family, and 75&amp;nbsp;million are AK-47s.&lt;ref name=&quot;k3&quot; /&gt; Because AK-type weapons have been made in many countries, often illicitly, it is impossible to know how many really exist.&lt;ref name=&quot;Graves-Brown&quot; /&gt;

== Conflicts ==
[[File:Burundi peacekeepers prepare for next rotation to Somalia, Bjumbura, Burundi 012210 (4324781393).jpg|thumb|Burundi peacekeepers prepare for next rotation to [[Somalia]], 2006]]
[[File:YPJ fighters shake hands with one another.jpg|thumb|Kurdish [[Women's Protection Units|YPJ]] fighters in Syria, 2014]]
The AK-47 has been used in the following conflicts:

=== 1950s ===
* [[Hungarian Revolution of 1956|Hungarian Revolution (1956)]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nybooks.com/articles/2011/02/10/most-influential-weapon-our-time/ {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170811010810/http://www.nybooks.com/articles/2011/02/10/most-influential-weapon-our-time/ |date=11 August 2017 }} The Most Influential Weapon of Our Time. The New York Review of Books. Max Hastings 10 FEBRUARY 2011 ISSUE. &quot;József Tibor Fejes, a young Hungarian identified by C. J. Chivers in The Gun as 'the first known insurgent to carry an AK-47.' According to Chivers, 'Fejes obtained his prize after Soviet soldiers dropped their rifles during their attack on revolutionaries in Budapest in 1956…. The Hungarian Revolution marked the AK-47's true battlefield debut.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Vietnam War|Vietnam War (1955–1975)]]
* [[Laotian Civil War|Laotian Civil War (1959–1975)]]

=== 1960s ===
* [[Congo Crisis|Congo Crisis (1960–1965)]]&lt;ref&gt;https://www.alamy.com/stock-photo-geographytravel-congo-events-simba-uprising-1964-1965-mercenary-with-58514865.html&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Portuguese Colonial War|Portuguese Colonial War (1961–1975)]]
* [[Rhodesian Bush War|Rhodesian Bush War (1964–1979)]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Zimbabwe&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=Modern African Wars (1): Rhodesia 1965–80|series=Men-at-Arms 183|first1=Peter|last1= Abbott|first2= Philip|last2= Botham |date=15 June 1986|isbn=9780850457285 |publisher = Osprey Publishing|page=10}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[The Troubles|The Troubles (Late 1960s–1998)]]
* [[South African Border War|South African Border War (1966–1990)]]
* [[Cambodian Civil War|Cambodian Civil War (1967–1975)]]
* [[Nigerian Civil War|Nigerian Civil War (1967–1970)]]&lt;ref name=&quot;auto&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Jowett|first=Philip|title=Modern African Wars (5): The Nigerian-Biafran War 1967-70|year=2016|publisher=[[Osprey Publishing]] Press|location=Oxford|isbn=978-1472816092|page=20|ref={{harvid|Jowett|2016}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== 1970s ===
* [[Yom Kippur War|Yom Kippur War (1973)]]
* [[Ethiopian Civil War|Ethiopian Civil War (1974–1991)]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine|title=Ethiopian military rifle cartridges: Part 2: from Mauser to Kalashnikov.|last=Scarlata|first=Paul|magazine=Shotgun News|date=1 March 2009|url=https://www.thefreelibrary.com/Ethiopian+military+rifle+cartridges%3A+Part+2%3A+from+Mauser+to...-a0195134991|access-date=24 November 2018|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20181124055029/https://www.thefreelibrary.com/Ethiopian+military+rifle+cartridges%3A+Part+2%3A+from+Mauser+to...-a0195134991|archive-date=24 November 2018|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Western Sahara War|Western Sahara War (1975–1991)]]
* [[Cambodian–Vietnamese War|Cambodian–Vietnamese War (1978–1989)]]
* [[Chadian–Libyan conflict|Chadian–Libyan conflict (1978–1987)]]
* [[Soviet–Afghan War|Soviet–Afghan War (1979–1989)]]

=== 1980s ===
* [[Iran–Iraq War|Iran–Iraq War (1980–1988)]]
* [[United States invasion of Grenada|United States invasion of Grenada (1983)]]&lt;ref&gt;https://nara.getarchive.net/media/soviet-made-ak-47-assault-rifles-seized-during-operation-urgent-fury-on-the-a52b7b&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Lord's Resistance Army insurgency|Lord's Resistance Army insurgency (1987–present)]]&lt;ref name ='SAS 2007 10'&gt;{{cite book|url=http://www.smallarmssurvey.org/publications/by-type/yearbook/small-arms-survey-2007.html|chapter-url=http://www.smallarmssurvey.org/fileadmin/docs/A-Yearbook/2007/en/full/Small-Arms-Survey-2007-Chapter-10-EN.pdf|chapter=Persistent Instability: Armed Violence and Insecurity in South Sudan|title=The Small Arms Survey 2007: Guns and the City|publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]]|year=2007|author=Small Arms Survey|page=325|isbn=978-0-521-88039-8|access-date=29 August 2018|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180827001033/http://www.smallarmssurvey.org/publications/by-type/yearbook/small-arms-survey-2007.html|archive-date=27 August 2018|url-status=live|author-link=Small Arms Survey}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== 1990s ===
* [[Tuareg rebellion (1990–1995)]]&lt;ref name ='SAS 2005'&gt;{{cite book|url=http://www.smallarmssurvey.org/publications/by-type/yearbook/small-arms-survey-2005.html|chapter-url=http://www.smallarmssurvey.org/fileadmin/docs/A-Yearbook/2005/en/Small-Arms-Survey-2005-Chapter-06-EN.pdf|chapter=Sourcing the Tools of War: Small Arms Supplies to Conflict Zones|title=Small Arms Survey 2005: Weapons at War|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]|year=2005|author=Small Arms Survey|page=166|isbn=978-0-19-928085-8|access-date=29 August 2018|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180830004838/http://www.smallarmssurvey.org/publications/by-type/yearbook/small-arms-survey-2005.html|archive-date=30 August 2018|url-status=live|author-link=Small Arms Survey}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Gulf War|Gulf War (1990–1991)]]
* [[Somali Civil War|Somali Civil War (1991–present)]]
* [[Yugoslav Wars|Yugoslav Wars (1991–2001)]]
* [[Burundian Civil War|Burundian Civil War (1993–2005)]]&lt;ref name ='SAS 2007 6'&gt;{{cite book|url=http://www.smallarmssurvey.org/publications/by-type/yearbook/small-arms-survey-2007.html|chapter-url=http://www.smallarmssurvey.org/fileadmin/docs/A-Yearbook/2007/en/full/Small-Arms-Survey-2007-Chapter-06-EN.pdf|chapter=Armed Violence in Burundi: Conflict and Post-Conflict Bujumbura|title=The Small Arms Survey 2007: Guns and the City|publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]]|year=2007|author=Small Arms Survey|page=204|isbn=978-0-521-88039-8|access-date=29 August 2018|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180827001033/http://www.smallarmssurvey.org/publications/by-type/yearbook/small-arms-survey-2007.html|archive-date=27 August 2018|url-status=live|author-link=Small Arms Survey}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Republic of the Congo Civil War (1997–99)|Congo Civil War (1997–1999)]]&lt;ref name ='SAS 2003 263'&gt;{{cite book|url=http://www.smallarmssurvey.org/publications/by-type/yearbook/small-arms-survey-2003.html|chapter-url=http://www.smallarmssurvey.org/fileadmin/docs/A-Yearbook/2003/en/Small-Arms-Survey-2003-Chapter-08-EN.pdf|chapter=Making the Difference?: Weapon Collection and Small Arms Availability in the Republic of Congo|title=Small Arms Survey 2003: Development Denied|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]|year=2003|author=Small Arms Survey|pages=268|isbn=0199251754|access-date=29 August 2018|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180829175229/http://www.smallarmssurvey.org/publications/by-type/yearbook/small-arms-survey-2003.html|archive-date=29 August 2018|url-status=live|author-link=Small Arms Survey}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== 2000s ===
* [[War in Afghanistan (2001–present)]]
* [[Iraq War|Iraq War (2003–2011)]]
* [[Mexican Drug War|Mexican Drug War (2006–present)]]

=== 2010s ===
* [[Libyan Civil War (2011)]]
* [[Syrian Civil War|Syrian Civil War (2011–present)]]
* [[Iraqi insurgency (2011–2013)]]
* [[Central African Republic Civil War (2012–present)]]&lt;ref name=&quot;CAR&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Centrafrique : le Soudan a-t-il armé les ex-Séléka ?|language=fr|work=[[Jeune Afrique]]|date=17 December 2013|url=https://www.jeuneafrique.com/166718/politique/centrafrique-le-soudan-a-t-il-arm-les-ex-s-l-ka/|first=Laurent|last=Touchard|access-date=29 January 2019|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190130111716/https://www.jeuneafrique.com/166718/politique/centrafrique-le-soudan-a-t-il-arm-les-ex-s-l-ka/|archive-date=30 January 2019|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Cultural influence and impact ==
{{Quote box
| quote = &quot;Basically, it's the anti-Western cachet of it&amp;nbsp;... And you know, one man's terrorist is another man's [[freedom fighter]], so we all sort of think, oh boy, we've got a little bit of [[Che Guevara]] in us. And this accounts for the popularity of the (AK 47) weapon. Plus I think that in the United States it's considered [[counterculture]], which is always something that citizens in this country kind of like&amp;nbsp;... It's kind of sticking a finger in the eye of [[the man]], if you will.&quot;
| source = — Larry Kahaner, author of ''AK-47: The Weapon That Changed the Face of War''&lt;ref name = &quot;NPRKahaner&quot; /&gt; | width = 25% | align = right
}}

During the [[Cold War]], the Soviet Union and the People's Republic of China, as well as United States and other NATO nations supplied arms and technical knowledge to numerous countries and rebel forces around the world. During this time the Western countries used relatively expensive automatic rifles, such as the [[FN FAL]], the [[Heckler &amp; Koch G3|HK G3]], the [[M14 rifle|M14]], and the [[M16 rifle|M16]]. In contrast, the Russians and Chinese used the AK-47; its low production cost and ease of manufacture allow them to make AKs in vast numbers.

In the pro-communist states, the AK-47 became a symbol of the [[Third World]] revolution. They were utilized in the [[Cambodian Civil War]] and the [[Cambodian–Vietnamese War]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones1981&quot;&gt;Christopher Jones (20 December 1981), [https://www.nytimes.com/1981/12/20/magazine/in-the-land-of-the-khmer-rouge.html &quot;IN THE LAND OF THE KHMER ROUGE.&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171211210646/http://www.nytimes.com/1981/12/20/magazine/in-the-land-of-the-khmer-rouge.html |date=11 December 2017 }} The New York Times.&lt;/ref&gt; During the 1980s, the Soviet Union became the principal arms dealer to countries embargoed by Western nations, including Middle Eastern nations such as Iran,{{citation needed|date=September 2018}} Libya, and Syria, which welcomed Soviet Union backing against Israel. After the [[History of the Soviet Union (1985–1991)|fall of the Soviet Union]], AK-47s were sold both openly{{by whom|date=December 2017}} and on the black market to any group with cash, including drug cartels and dictatorial states, and more recently they have been seen in the hands of Islamic groups such as [[Al-Qaeda]], [[Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant|ISIL]], and the [[Taliban]] in Afghanistan and Iraq, and [[FARC]], [[Ejército de Liberación Nacional]] guerrillas in Colombia.&lt;ref name=&quot;NPRKahaner&quot; /&gt;

[[File:Kalashnikov Vodka (5604438939).jpg|thumb|Kalashnikov Vodka]]

In Russia, the Kalashnikov is a tremendous source of national pride.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kalashnikov dies&quot; /&gt; &quot;The family of the inventor of the world's most famous assault rifle, Mikhail Kalashnikov, has authorized German engineering company MMI to use the well-known Kalashnikov name on a variety of not-so-deadly goods.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Moscow Times&quot; /&gt; In recent years, Kalashnikov Vodka has been marketed with souvenir bottles in the shape of the AK-47 Kalashnikov.&lt;ref name=&quot;russianvodka&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;vodka-wired&quot; /&gt; There are also Kalashnikov watches,&lt;ref name=&quot;watches&quot; /&gt; umbrellas,&lt;ref name=&quot;umbrellas&quot; /&gt; and knives.&lt;ref name=&quot;knives&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Boker&quot; /&gt;

The Kalashnikov Museum (also called the AK-47 museum) opened on 4 November 2004 in [[Izhevsk]], Udmurt Republic. This city is in the [[Ural Region]] of Russia. The museum chronicles the biography of General [[Mikhail Kalashnikov|Kalashnikov]] and documents the invention of the AK-47. The museum complex of Kalashnikov's small arms, a series of halls, and multimedia exhibitions are devoted to the evolution of the AK-47 assault rifle and attracts 10,000 monthly visitors.&lt;ref name=&quot;museum&quot; /&gt; Nadezhda Vechtomova, the museum director, stated in an interview that the purpose of the museum is to honor the ingenuity of the inventor and the hard work of the employees and to &quot;separate the weapon as a weapon of murder from the people who are producing it and to tell its history in our country&quot;. [https://www.google.com/maps/@56.8503169,53.2067659,3a,75y,355.95h,84.2t/data=!3m6!1e1!3m4!1sGs-piLd6jw2WuUmh3mhl-g!2e0!7i13312!8i6656?hl=en Google Earth view of the Kalashnikov Museum]

On 19 September 2017 a {{convert|9|m}} monument of Kalashnikov was unveiled in central Moscow. A protester, later detained by police, attempted to unfurl a banner reading &quot;a creator of weapons is a creator of death&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2017/sep/19/30ft-high-statue-of-mikhail-kalashnikov-unveiled-in-moscow|title=30ft-high statue of Mikhail Kalashnikov unveiled in Moscow|first=Marc|last=Bennetts|date=19 September 2017|accessdate=19 September 2017|via=www.theguardian.com|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170919111207/https://www.theguardian.com/world/2017/sep/19/30ft-high-statue-of-mikhail-kalashnikov-unveiled-in-moscow|archive-date=19 September 2017|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The proliferation of this weapon is reflected by more than just numbers. The AK-47 is included on the [[flag of Mozambique]] and its [[Emblem of Mozambique|emblem]], an acknowledgment that the country gained its independence in large part through the effective use of their AK-47s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gordon-1997&quot; /&gt; It is also found in the coats of arms of [[Coat of arms of East Timor|East Timor]] and the revolution era [[coat of arms of Burkina Faso|Burkina Faso]], as well as in the flags of [[flag of Hezbollah|Hezbollah]], [[Syrian Resistance]], [[FARC-EP]], the [[New People's Army]], [[Communist Party of Turkey/Marxist–Leninist|TKP/TIKKO]] and the [[International Revolutionary People's Guerrilla Forces]].

U.S. and Western Europe countries frequently associate the AK-47 with their enemies; both Cold War era and present-day. For example, Western works of fiction (movies, television, novels, video games) often portray criminals, gang members, insurgents, and terrorists using AK-47s as the weapon of choice. Conversely, throughout the [[developing world]], the AK-47 can be positively attributed with [[revolutionaries]] against foreign occupation, [[imperialism]], or [[colonialism]]. Numerous fictional depictions of the Soviet/Russian armed forces such as ''[[Call of Duty#Modern Warfare series|Call of Duty: Modern Warfare]]'' show them armed with 7.62x39mm AK variants (AK-47 or [[AKM]]) as their standard-issue assault rifles, a long-standing anachronism thanks to the AK-47's iconic status, despite the Soviets having actually replaced them with the 5.45x39mm [[AK-74]] in the 1970s. Movies and video games often pass off licensed clones like the Norinco [[Type 56 assault rifle]] as the AK-47.&lt;ref name=&quot;NPRKahaner&quot; /&gt;

The AK-47 made an appearance in U.S. popular culture as a recurring focus in the [[Nicolas Cage]] film ''[[Lord of War]]'' (2005). Numerous monologues in the movie focus on the weapon, and its effects on global conflict and the [[gun running]] market.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lord of War&quot; /&gt;

In Iraq and Afghanistan, [[Private military company]] contractors from the U.K. and other countries used the AK-47 and its variants along with western firearms such as the [[AR-15]].&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.g4s.com/en-ci/riskmanagement/g4s-iraq G4S Iraq]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2006, the Colombian musician and peace activist [[Cesar Lopez|César López]] devised the ''[[escopetarra]]'', an AK converted into a guitar. One sold for US$17,000 in a fundraiser held to benefit the victims of [[anti-personnel mine]]s, while another was exhibited at the United Nations' [[Conference on Disarmament]].&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC&quot; /&gt;

In Mexico, the AK-47 is known as &quot;Cuerno de Chivo&quot; (literally &quot;Goat's Horn&quot;) because of its curved magazine design. It is one of the weapons of choice of Mexican drug cartels. It is sometimes mentioned in Mexican folk music lyrics.&lt;ref name=&quot;AolNews&quot; /&gt;

==Gallery==
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:AK47map.svg|A map of current and former AK users
File:AK 1 and 2 model.jpg|An AK-47 Type 1 (top) and 2 (bottom) on display. The Type 1 features a stamped receiver while the Type 2 receiver is milled.
File:MP Inspects Captured AK-47 Vietnam.jpg|A [[United States Army|U.S. Army]] [[Military police|M.P]] inspects a Chinese AK-47 recovered in Vietnam, 1968
File:ASC Leiden - Coutinho Collection - G 24 - Life in Ziguinchor, Senegal - Carrying weapons to Hermangono, Guinea-Bissau - 1973.tif|AK-47s of the [[PAIGC]]-liberation movement, ready to be transported from Senegal to Guinea-Bissau, 1973
File:Evstafiev-spetsnaz-prepare-for-mission.jpg|A [[Soviet Union|Soviet]] [[Spetsnaz]] (special operations) group prepares for a mission in Afghanistan, 1988
File:Mortar attack on Shigal Tarna garrison, Kunar Province, 87.jpg|During the [[Soviet–Afghan War]] in the 1980s, several sources simultaneously armed both sides of the Afghan conflict, filling the country with AK-47s and their derivatives.&lt;ref name=&quot;most abundant&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/gallery&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Comparison of the AK-47 and M16]]
* [[AK-74]]
* [[RPK]]

== Notes ==
{{Reflist|group=N}}

== References ==
{{reflist|30em|refs=
&lt;ref name=&quot;Africa Defense Journal&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://africadefensejournal.wordpress.com/2011/05/24/burkina-nouveau-mouvement-de-colere-des-militaires-a-ouagadougou/ |title=Burkina : nouveau mouvement de colère des militaires à Ouagadougou |work=Africa Defense Journal |date=24 May 2011 |accessdate=29 December 2013 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131023042817/http://africadefensejournal.wordpress.com/2011/05/24/burkina-nouveau-mouvement-de-colere-des-militaires-a-ouagadougou/ |archive-date=23 October 2013 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;afrikitalia&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.afrikitalia.it/burkina-faso-ces-mesures-presidentielles-qui-font-plaisir-a-larmee/ |title=Burkina Faso: Ces Mesures Présidentielles Qui Font Plaisir à l'Armée |publisher=afrikitalia.it |accessdate=29 December 2013 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://archive.today/20131017212241/http://www.afrikitalia.it/burkina-faso-ces-mesures-presidentielles-qui-font-plaisir-a-larmee/ |archivedate=17 October 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;AG-S4&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.1007/BF00867112|title=Elastic characteristics of AG-4S glass-reinforced plastic under short-time and long-time loads|author=Grezin V. M. |journal= Polymer Mechanics|volume= 2|issue =2|pages= 188–190 |year= 1966 |bibcode=1966PoMec...2..188G}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;ak-akm-e&quot;&gt;[http://world.guns.ru/assault/rus/ak-akm-e.html Kalashnikov AK (AK-47) AKS, AKM and AKMS assault rifles (USSR)] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130120230537/http://world.guns.ru/assault/rus/ak-akm-e.html |date=20 January 2013 }}. World.guns.ru. Retrieved 25 November 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;AKML&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=AKML (AKMSL)|publisher=AK-INFO.RU|url=http://www.ak-info.ru/joomla/index.php/aaka/6-akm/54-akmsl|accessdate=8 February 2013|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130523004257/http://www.ak-info.ru/joomla/index.php/aaka/6-akm/54-akmsl|archive-date=23 May 2013|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;alpharubicon2&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.alpharubicon.com/leo/akseries.htm|title=Avtomat Kalashnikov|publisher=alpharubicon.com|access-date=10 June 2012|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120513012711/http://www.alpharubicon.com/leo/akseries.htm|archive-date=13 May 2012|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;ammoweight&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Land Forces Weapons: Export Catalogue |year=2003 |page=85 |publisher=[[Rosoboronexport]] |location=Moscow |url=https://www.scribd.com/doc/30301368/Rosoboronexport-Land-Forces-Weapons-Catalogue |oclc=61406322 |access-date=8 September 2017 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170614160811/https://www.scribd.com/doc/30301368/Rosoboronexport-Land-Forces-Weapons-Catalogue |archive-date=14 June 2017 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;AolNews&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=Muessig, Ben|title=Narcocorridos: The Songs of Mexico's Drug War|url=http://www.aolnews.com/2010/08/10/narcocorridos-the-songs-of-mexicos-drug-war/|publisher=AolNews|date=10 August 2010|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120814224007/http://www.aolnews.com/2010/08/10/narcocorridos-the-songs-of-mexicos-drug-war/|archivedate=14 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;AP-Kalashnikov&quot;&gt;[http://www.foxnews.com/story/2007/07/06/ak-47-inventor-doesnt-lose-sleep-over-havoc-wrought-with-his-invention/ AK-47 Inventor Doesn't Lose Sleep Over Havoc Wrought With His Invention. An interview with Mikhail Kalashnikov] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140114000457/http://www.foxnews.com/story/2007/07/06/ak-47-inventor-doesnt-lose-sleep-over-havoc-wrought-with-his-invention/ |date=14 January 2014 }}. Associated Press via Fox News Channel (6 July 2007). Retrieved 25 November 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;ar15&quot;&gt;[https://www.ar15.com/content/webPDF/AK47USArmyOperatorManual.pdf Operator's Manual for AK-47 Assault Rifle. Department of the Army] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140122215048/http://www.ar15.com/content/webPDF/AK47USArmyOperatorManual.pdf |date=22 January 2014 }}. (PDF). Retrieved 25 November 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;AR-M1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.arsenal-bg.com/defense_police/7,62ar-m1-m1f.htm |title=Arsenal 7.62mm &quot;Arsenal&quot; Assault Rifle AR-M1 and with Folding Butt AR-M1F |accessdate=2 October 2014 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20141006075455/http://www.arsenal-bg.com/defense_police/7%2C62ar-m1-m1f.htm |archivedate=6 October 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Army Recognition Burkina Faso&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.armyrecognition.com/burkina_faso_army_land_forces_ranks_combat_uniform/burkina_faso_army_defence_force_ranks_military_pattern_camouflage_combat_field_uniforms_dress_grades.html |title=Burkina Faso Army defence force ranks military pattern camouflage combat field uniforms dress grades – Army Recognition – Army Recognition |publisher=Armyrecognition.com |accessdate=29 December 2013 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131019063944/http://www.armyrecognition.com/burkina_faso_army_land_forces_ranks_combat_uniform/burkina_faso_army_defence_force_ranks_military_pattern_camouflage_combat_field_uniforms_dress_grades.html |archive-date=19 October 2013 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Army Recognition Djibouti&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.armyrecognition.com/djibouti_army_ranks_military_combat_uniforms/djibouti_army_ranks_land_ground_forces_combat_field_uniforms_military_grades_uniformes_de.html |title=Djibouti Army ranks land ground forces combat field uniforms military grades uniformes de – Army Recognition – Army Recognition |publisher=Armyrecognition.com |accessdate=29 December 2013 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131019065454/http://www.armyrecognition.com/djibouti_army_ranks_military_combat_uniforms/djibouti_army_ranks_land_ground_forces_combat_field_uniforms_military_grades_uniformes_de.html |archive-date=19 October 2013 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Army Recognition Rwanda&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.armyrecognition.com/rwanda_armee_rwandaise_grades_uniformes_combat/rwanda_rwandan_army_ranks_land_ground_forces_combat_uniforms_military_equipment_rwandais_grades_unif.html |title=Rwanda Rwandan Army ranks land ground forces combat uniforms military equipment rwandais grades unif – Army Recognition – Army Recognition |publisher=Armyrecognition.com |accessdate=29 December 2013 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150923225606/http://www.armyrecognition.com/rwanda_armee_rwandaise_grades_uniformes_combat/rwanda_rwandan_army_ranks_land_ground_forces_combat_uniforms_military_equipment_rwandais_grades_unif.html |archive-date=23 September 2015 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;army&quot;&gt;[[s:en:AK-47 Operator's Manual|Department of the Army. 203d Military Intelligence Battalion]]&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;arsenalinc1&quot;&gt;[http://www.arsenalinc.com/usa/imgs/articles/BulgarianAK.pdf Peter G. Kokalis, Kalashnikovs – 3 of the best. arsenalinc.com] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150923173907/http://www.arsenalinc.com/usa/imgs/articles/BulgarianAK.pdf |date=23 September 2015 }}. (PDF). Retrieved 25 November 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated7&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ciar.org/ttk/mbt/papers/misc/paper.x.small-arms.wounding-ballistics.patterns_of_military_rifle_bullets.fackler.unk.html |title=Patterns of Military Rifle Bullets |publisher=Ciar.org |accessdate=23 August 2012 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121120174401/http://www.ciar.org/ttk/mbt/papers/misc/paper.x.small-arms.wounding-ballistics.patterns_of_military_rifle_bullets.fackler.unk.html |archive-date=20 November 2012 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC&quot;&gt;{{cite news | title = Escopetarras: disparando música | author = Héctor Latorre| date = 24 January 2006 | accessdate =31 January 2007 | publisher = BBC World | url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/hi/spanish/misc/newsid_4644000/4644028.stm | archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20070222195808/http://news.bbc.co.uk/hi/spanish/misc/newsid_4644000/4644028.stm| archivedate= 22 February 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Bellamy p146-155&quot;&gt;Bellamy RF and Zajtchuk R. (1990) &quot;The physics and biophysics of wound ballistics&quot;. In: Zajtchuk R, ed. ''Textbook of Military Medicine, Part I: Warfare, Weaponry, and the Casualty'', Vol. 5, Conventional Warfare: Ballistic, Blast, and Burn Injuries. Washington, DC: Office of the Surgeon General, Department of the Army, United States of America. pp. 146–155&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Bellamy p148&quot;&gt;Bellamy RF and Zajtchuk R. (1990) &quot;The physics and biophysics of wound ballistics. In: Zajtchuk R, ed. ''Textbook of Military Medicine, Part I: Warfare, Weaponry, and the Casualty'', Vol. 5, Conventional Warfare: Ballistic, Blast, and Burn Injuries. Washington, DC: Office of the Surgeon General, Department of the Army, United States of America (1990) Fig. 4-38 p. 148&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Bernardelli&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Bernardelli company profile and history |work=V. Bernardelli S.r.l. |url=http://www.bernardelli.com/en/index.htm |accessdate=20 February 2013 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130210034642/http://www.bernardelli.com/en/index.htm |archivedate=10 February 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Boker&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bladehq.com/cat--Boker-Kalashnikov--249|title=Boker Kalashnikov Knives|publisher=bladehq.com|access-date=13 June 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150615030753/http://www.bladehq.com/cat--Boker-Kalashnikov--249|archive-date=15 June 2015|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Bolotin p115&quot;&gt;{{cite book|authors=Bolotin, David Naumovich [translation: Igor F. Naftul'eff ; edited by John Walter, Heikki Pohjolainen]|title=Soviet Small-arms and Ammunition|year=1995|publisher=Finnish Arms Museum Foundation (Suomen asemuseosäätiö)|location=Hyvinkää|isbn=9519718419|page=115}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Bolotin p150&quot;&gt;{{cite book|authors=Bolotin, David Naumovich [translation: Igor F. Naftul'eff ; edited by John Walter, Heikki Pohjolainen]|title=Soviet Small-arms and Ammunition|year=1995|publisher=Finnish Arms Museum Foundation (Suomen asemuseosäätiö)|location=Hyvinkää|isbn=9519718419|page=150}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;browningmgs.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://browningmgs.com/T2T3/Kalashnikov.htm|title=Type 2 &amp; Type 3 AK-47|publisher=browningmgs.com|access-date=19 June 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161026055254/http://browningmgs.com/T2T3/Kalashnikov.htm|archive-date=26 October 2016|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Burundi-flickr&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.flickr.com/photos/dvids/7591704762/ |title=Blending |publisher=Flickr |date=21 July 2012 |accessdate=29 December 2013 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131022212815/http://www.flickr.com/photos/dvids/7591704762/ |archive-date=22 October 2013 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;chivers&quot;&gt;C. J. Chivers (2011) ''The Gun''. Simon &amp; Schuster Publishing. {{ISBN|0743271734}}. pp. 206–207.  Taken from the Long-Range Dispersion Firing Test of the AK-47 Assault Rifle, U.S. Army Foreign Science and Technology Center. August 1969&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;ControlArms&quot;&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20140809180916/http://www.oxfam.de/files/20060623_theak47_200kb.pdf The AK-47: The World's Favourite Killing Machine]. ControlArms Briefing Note (26 June 2006)&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;defenseindustrydaily1&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.defenseindustrydaily.com/the-usas-m4-carbine-controversy-03289/ |title=The USA's M4 Carbine Controversy |publisher=Defenseindustrydaily.com |date=21 November 2011 |accessdate=10 January 2012 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070713081000/http://www.defenseindustrydaily.com/the-usas-m4-carbine-controversy-03289/ |archive-date=13 July 2007 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;DICON&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dicon.gov.ng/military1.html|title=DEFENCE INDUSTRY CORPORATION OF NIGERIA (DICON) OFFICIAL WEBSITE|accessdate=2 October 2014|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131227081924/http://www.dicon.gov.ng/military1.html|archivedate=27 December 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Dockery&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Dockery|first=Kevin|title=Future Weapons|year=2007|page=102|isbn=978-0-425-21750-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;dtic.mil&quot;&gt;[http://www.dtic.mil/cgi-bin/GetTRDoc?Location=U2&amp;doc=GetTRDoc.pdf&amp;AD=ADA046961 Rifle Evaluation Study, United States Army, Combat Development Command, ADA046961, 20 Dec 1962] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121201030728/http://www.dtic.mil/cgi-bin/GetTRDoc?Location=U2&amp;doc=GetTRDoc.pdf&amp;AD=ADA046961 |date=1 December 2012 }}. None. Retrieved 25 November 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Dunnigan&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.strategypage.com/dls/articles/20030423.asp |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070325171640/http://www.strategypage.com/dls/articles/20030423.asp |archivedate=25 March 2007 |title=An AK for Every Market by James Dunnigan April 23, 2003 |publisher=strategypage.com |accessdate=26 June 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;e36&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author=Ezell, Edward |authorlink=Edward Ezell |title=The AK47 story: evolution of the Kalashnikov weapons |date=1986 |publisher=[[Stackpole Books]] |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=LsYqAQAAMAAJ |isbn=978-0-8117-0916-3 |page=36}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;ECOSOCDEV&quot;&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20060105000803/http://www.un.org/ecosocdev/geninfo/afrec/vol15no4/154arms.htm Small arms in Africa: Counting the cost of gun violence]. Un.org (6 July 2000).&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;english.pravda.ru&quot;&gt;[http://english.pravda.ru/history/02-08-2003/3461-kalashnikov-0/ The History of Kalashnikov Gun. Pravda. 02.08.2003] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20151015195847/http://english.pravda.ru/history/02-08-2003/3461-kalashnikov-0/ |date=15 October 2015 }}. English.pravda.ru. Retrieved 25 November 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Et-97/1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ethiopiabook.com/galleryimg/l/print-advert-371.jpg |title=Advertisement flyer for manufacturing capabilities of the Gafat Armament Engineering Complex |accessdate=2014-01-23 |url-status=bot: unknown |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110710203214/http://ethiopiabook.com/galleryimg/l/print-advert-371.jpg |archivedate=10 July 2011 }} Retrieved on 8 October 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Fackler&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.frfrogspad.com/terminal2.htm |title= Military rifle bullet wound patterns comparison charts |author= Fackler, Martin L. |publisher= Frfrogspad.com |access-date= 29 June 2014 |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20140816033604/http://www.frfrogspad.com/terminal2.htm |archive-date= 16 August 2014 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Field &amp; Stream&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fieldandstream.com/articles/guns/2006/02/father-100-million-rifles|title=Mikhail Kalashnikov: The Father of 100 Million Rifles|work=Field &amp; Stream|date=February 2006|access-date=19 April 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160815145427/http://www.fieldandstream.com/articles/guns/2006/02/father-100-million-rifles|archive-date=15 August 2016|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Force One&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=Maha's elite counter terror unit Force One becomes operational |date=25 November 2009 |newspaper=[[Business Standard]] |publisher=Business Standard Ltd |location=New Delhi |url=http://www.business-standard.com/india/news/maha%5Cs-elite-counter-terror-unit-force-one-becomes-operational/377563/ |accessdate=5 July 2010 |oclc=496280002}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Forgotten Weapons&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.forgottenweapons.com/rifles/wz-88-tantal/|title=wz.88 Tantal|work=Forgotten Weapons|accessdate=2 October 2014|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141006141410/http://www.forgottenweapons.com/rifles/wz-88-tantal/|archive-date=6 October 2014|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;foxnews&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=AK-47 Inventor Doesn't Lose Sleep Over Havoc Wrought With His Invention |publisher=[[Fox News Channel]] |date=6 July 2007 |location=USA |url=http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,288456,00.html |accessdate=3 April 2010 |oclc=36334372 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100603232941/http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,288456,00.html |archive-date=3 June 2010 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Gander&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author=Gander, Terry J. |author2=Hogg, Ian V. |authorlink2=Ian V. Hogg |title=Jane's Infantry Weapons 1995–96 |date=1 May 1995 |edition=21 |publisher=[[Jane's Information Group]] |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=qSL8AAAACAAJ |isbn=978-0-7106-1241-0 |access-date=6 March 2016 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150318225343/http://books.google.com/books?id=qSL8AAAACAAJ |archive-date=18 March 2015 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Gordon-1997&quot;&gt;Gordon, Michael R. (13 March 1997) [https://www.nytimes.com/1997/03/13/world/burst-of-pride-for-a-staccato-executioner-ak-47.html &quot;Burst of Pride for a Staccato Executioner: AK-47&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170623171800/http://www.nytimes.com/1997/03/13/world/burst-of-pride-for-a-staccato-executioner-ak-47.html |date=23 June 2017 }}. ''The New York Times''.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Graves-Brown&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|author=Graves-Brown, P. |doi=10.1177/1359183507081896  |title=Avtomat Kalashnikova|journal=Journal of Material Culture|date= November 2007 |volume=12 |issue=3|pages= 285–307}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Gun Book Review&quot;&gt;[http://www.popularmechanics.com/technology/military/weapons/ak-47-questions-about-most-important-gun-ever History of AK-47 Gun – The Gun Book Review] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140803184020/http://www.popularmechanics.com/technology/military/weapons/ak-47-questions-about-most-important-gun-ever |date=3 August 2014 }}. ''Popular Mechanics'' (12 October 2010).&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Hallock&quot;&gt;Hallock, Richard R. (16 March 1970) [http://pogoarchives.org/labyrinth/09/02.pdf M16 Rifle Case Study. Prepared for the Presidents Blue Ribbon Defense Panel] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150906090843/http://pogoarchives.org/labyrinth/09/02.pdf |date=6 September 2015 }}. pogoarchives.org&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Hellenic Police&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Greece Ministry of Public Order Press Office: Special Anti-Terrorist Unit |date=July 2004 |publisher=[[Hellenic Police]] |url=http://www.astynomia.gr/images/stories/DOCS/Attachment11480_ENHMEROTIKO_EKAM_ENGL.pdf |accessdate=27 September 2009 |archiveurl=https://www.webcitation.org/5rOg1WIHo?url=http://www.astynomia.gr/images/stories/DOCS/Attachment11480_ENHMEROTIKO_EKAM_ENGL.pdf |archivedate=21 July 2010 |url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;India&quot;&gt;Unnithan, Sandeep (30 December 2013) [http://indiatoday.intoday.in/story/why-general-kalashnikov-couldnt-sell-the-ak-47-in-india/1/333532.html &quot;Why General Kalashnikov couldn't sell the AK in India&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150416002043/http://indiatoday.intoday.in/story/why-general-kalashnikov-couldnt-sell-the-ak-47-in-india/1/333532.html |date=16 April 2015 }}. ''India Today''.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!--unused&lt;ref name=&quot;inmoscowsshadows.wordpress.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://inmoscowsshadows.wordpress.com/2008/10/23/new-guns-for-russias-cops-so-what/|title=New guns for Russia's cops: so what?: In Moscow's Shadows|work=In Moscow's Shadows|date=23 October 2008|access-date=15 July 2014|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20111123065045/http://inmoscowsshadows.wordpress.com/2008/10/23/new-guns-for-russias-cops-so-what/|archive-date=23 November 2011|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Izhmash gp-34&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=40 mm underbarrel grenade launcher GP-34 |publisher=[[Izhmash]] |url=http://www.izhmash.ru/eng/product/gp-34.shtml |accessdate=20 October 2012 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120728115857/http://www.izhmash.ru/eng/product/gp-34.shtml |archivedate=28 July 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;izhmash&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=AKM (AK-47) Kalashnikov modernized assault rifle, caliber 7.62mm |publisher=[[Izhmash]] |url=http://www.izhmash.ru/eng/product/akm.shtml |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20141006092719/http://www.izhmash.ru/eng/product/akm.shtml |archivedate=6 October 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot;&gt;{{cite book |editor=Richard D. Jones |editor2=Leland S. Ness |title=Jane's Infantry Weapons 2009–2010 |date=27 January 2009 |edition=35 |publisher=[[Jane's Information Group]] |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=A5ngPgAACAAJ |isbn=978-0-7106-2869-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;k3&quot;&gt;{{cite web |author=Killicoat, Phillip |title=Weaponomics: The Global Market for Assault Rifles |work=World Bank Policy Research Working Paper 4202 (Post-Conflict Transitions Working Paper No. 10) |publisher=[[University of Oxford|Oxford University]] |date=April 2007 |url=http://www-wds.worldbank.org/servlet/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2007/04/13/000016406_20070413145045/Rendered/PDF/wps4202.pdf |accessdate=3 April 2010 |page=3 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120112121512/http://www-wds.worldbank.org/servlet/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2007/04/13/000016406_20070413145045/Rendered/PDF/wps4202.pdf |archive-date=12 January 2012 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Kabbani&quot;&gt;[http://www.keyforensic.co.uk/docs/2013_45_3_222_Kabbani.pdf AFTE Journal – Volume 45 Number 3 – Summer 2013] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160304064134/http://www.keyforensic.co.uk/docs/2013_45_3_222_Kabbani.pdf |date=4 March 2016 }}. (PDF). Retrieved 25 November 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Kalashnikov dies&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://uk.reuters.com/article/2013/12/24/uk-russia-kalashnikov-idUKBRE9BM0KP20131224|title=AK-47 rifle inventor Mikhail Kalashnikov dies at 94|agency=Reuters UK|date=24 December 2013|access-date=13 June 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150614183816/http://uk.reuters.com/article/2013/12/24/uk-russia-kalashnikov-idUKBRE9BM0KP20131224|archive-date=14 June 2015|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;knives&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thetruthaboutknives.com/2013/06/edc-for-ccw-boker-kalashnikov-anniversary-knife/|title=EDC for CCW: Boker Kalashnikov Anniversary Knife|work=The Truth About Knives|date=June 2013|access-date=13 June 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150615122911/http://www.thetruthaboutknives.com/2013/06/edc-for-ccw-boker-kalashnikov-anniversary-knife/|archive-date=15 June 2015|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Kokalis&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.arsenalinc.com/usa/imgs/articles/BulgarianAK.pdf|title=Kalashnikovs 3 of the best|journal=Shotgun News|volume=59|issue=12|date=May 2005|access-date=15 June 2012|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150923173907/http://www.arsenalinc.com/usa/imgs/articles/BulgarianAK.pdf|archive-date=23 September 2015|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Kokalis_49&quot;&gt;Kokalis, 49&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;krtraining1&quot;&gt;Kjellgren, G. L. M. [http://www.krtraining.com/KRTraining/Archive/PracticalRangeSmallArms.pdf The Practical Range of Small Arms] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150305142959/http://www.krtraining.com/KRTraining/Archive/PracticalRangeSmallArms.pdf |date=5 March 2015 }}. ''The American Rifleman''. pp. 40–44.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Lord of War&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Lord of War (2005) – memorable quotes|url=https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0399295/quotes?qt=qt0403308|publisher=Internet Movie Database|accessdate=29 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Machine Carbine Promoted&quot;&gt;[http://www.lonesentry.com/articles/ttt07/stg44-assault-rifle.html &quot;Machine Carbine Promoted&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120921233948/http://www.lonesentry.com/articles/ttt07/stg44-assault-rifle.html |date=21 September 2012 }}. ''Tactical and Technical Trends'', No. 57, April 1945.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;magazine video&quot;&gt;[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xjeiCbVUEyA The many uses of an AK-47 magazine video] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150517101258/https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xjeiCbVUEyA |date=17 May 2015 }}. YouTube.com (7 May 2014). Retrieved 25 November 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;MAZ&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mic.sd/images/products/wepons/en/MAZbn.html|title=MAZ|publisher=[[Military Industry Corporation]]|accessdate=8 February 2009| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20081227202939/http://www.mic.sd/images/products/wepons/en/MAZbn.html| archivedate= 27 December 2008 | url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Miller&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author=Miller, David M. O. |title=The Illustrated Directory of 20th Century Guns |date=1 May 2001 |series=Illustrated Directory Series |publisher=Salamander Books |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=GgpRPgAACAAJ |isbn=978-1-84065-245-1 |access-date=6 March 2016 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150319011022/http://books.google.com/books?id=GgpRPgAACAAJ |archive-date=19 March 2015 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Milosevic&quot;&gt;{{cite web |author=Milosevic, Milan |title=Trojanski Konj za Teroriste |language=Serbian |year=2005 |work=Kalibar |publisher=[[Novosti a.d.|Novosti]] |url=http://www.kalibar.rs/code/navigate.php?Id=74 |accessdate=4 April 2009 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120227190204/http://www.kalibar.rs/code/navigate.php?Id=74 |archive-date=27 February 2012 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Moscow Times&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P1-71989519.html|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140610172638/http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P1-71989519.html|url-status=dead|archive-date=2014-06-10|title=Care for a Kalashnikov Umbrella?, THE MOSCOW TIMES}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;most abundant&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url=https://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/how-did-the-ak47-become-the-most-abundant-weapon-on-earth-2124407.html | title=How did the AK-47 become the most abundant weapon on earth? | newspaper=The Independent | date=24 December 2013 | access-date=21 August 2017 | archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150925192633/http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/how-did-the-ak47-become-the-most-abundant-weapon-on-earth-2124407.html | archive-date=25 September 2015 | url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;museum&quot;&gt;Chivers, C.J. (18 February 2007) [http://travel.nytimes.com/2007/02/18/travel/18heads.html &quot;AK-47 Museum: Homage to the Gun That Won the East&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070622225359/http://travel.nytimes.com/2007/02/18/travel/18heads.html |date=22 June 2007 }}. ''The New York Times''&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;nickpatonwalsh&quot;&gt;{{cite news | last=Walsh | first=Nick Paton | date=10 October 2003 | url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2003/oct/10/russia.nickpatonwalsh | title=Mikhail Kalashnikov: 'I sleep soundly' | newspaper=The Guardian | accessdate=12 January 2016 | archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170510215042/https://www.theguardian.com/world/2003/oct/10/russia.nickpatonwalsh | archive-date=10 May 2017 | url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Nikolovski&quot;&gt;{{cite news |author=Nikolovski, Zoran |title=Macedonian military police, US National Guard conduct joint manoeuvres |date=12 October 2006 |newspaper=[[Southeast European Times]] |publisher=[[United States European Command]] |url=http://www.setimes.com/cocoon/setimes/xhtml/en_GB/features/setimes/features/2006/10/12/feature-03 |accessdate=14 March 2011 |oclc=731936128 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110125193606/http://setimes.com/cocoon/setimes/xhtml/en_GB/features/setimes/features/2006/10/12/feature-03 |archive-date=25 January 2011 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;North Korea&quot;&gt;US Department of Defense, North Korea Country Handbook 1997, Appendix A: Equipment Recognition, TYPE-68 (AKM) ASSAULT RIFLE, p. A-77.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;NPRKahaner&quot;&gt;Seabrook, Andrea (26 November 2006) [https://web.archive.org/web/20140730054103/http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=6539945 &quot;AK-47: The Weapon Changed the Face of War&quot;]. ''NPR Weekend Edition Sunday''.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Ordnance Factories Board&quot;&gt;[http://ofbindia.nic.in/products/data/weapons/wsc/21.htm &quot;Assault Rifle 7,62mm&quot;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20101027095921/http://ofbindia.nic.in/products/data/weapons/wsc/21.htm |date=27 October 2010 }}. Indian Ordnance Factory Board&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Pakistan&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.upiasia.com/Security/2009/11/16/russia_confronts_pakistan_china_over_copied_weapons/5776/ |title=Russia confronts Pakistan, China over copied weapons |publisher=upiasia.com |author=Chang, Andrei |date=16 November 2009 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110717170742/http://www.upiasia.com/Security/2009/11/16/russia_confronts_pakistan_china_over_copied_weapons/5776/ |archivedate=17 July 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;People's Daily Nigeria&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://english.peopledaily.com.cn/200610/02/eng20061002_308128.html|title=People's Daily Online – Nigeria to mass-produce Nigerian version of AK-47 rifles|accessdate=2 October 2014|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131019155159/http://english.peopledaily.com.cn/200610/02/eng20061002_308128.html|archive-date=19 October 2013|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Popenker&quot;&gt;{{cite web |author=Popenker, Maksim |title=Kalashnikov AK (AK-47) AKS, AKM and AKMS assault rifles (USSR) |work=World Guns. Modern Firearms &amp; Ammunition |date=5 February 2009 |url=http://world.guns.ru/assault/rus/ak-akm-e.html |accessdate=14 March 2011 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110311080339/http://world.guns.ru/assault/rus/ak-akm-e.html |archive-date=11 March 2011 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Popenker-Williams&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author=Popenker, Maxim |author2=Williams, Anthony G |title=Assault Rifle |year=2005 |publisher=Crowood Press |url=https://books.google.com/?id=TNwgAAAACAAJ |isbn=978-1-86126-700-9}}{{Page needed|date=February 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Power Custom&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.powercustom.com/AKPages/MikhailKalashnikov.htm |title=Mikhail Kalashnikov |author=Shilin, Val |author2=Cutshaw, Charlie |publisher=Power Custom |accessdate=19 October 2008 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20050402150638/http://www.powercustom.com/AKPages/MikhailKalashnikov.htm |archivedate=2 April 2005 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;PTW&quot;&gt;{{cite book | author = Wells, Rod | title = Part-Time War|edition= 2011|page= 155 | publisher = Fern House| isbn= 978-1-902702-25-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Purdy&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|title=Wounding effects of the AK-47 rifle used by Patrick Purdy in the Stockton, California, schoolyard shooting of January 17, 1989|date=September 1990|volume=11|issue=3|pages=185–9|journal=American Journal of Forensic Medicine and Pathology|pmid=2220700|first=ML |last=Fackler|last2=Malinowski|first2=JA |last3=Hoxie |first3=SW |last4=Jason |first4=A.|url=http://www.dtic.mil/docs/citations/ADA233190|doi=10.1097/00000433-199009000-00001}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!--unused&lt;ref name=&quot;ria23dec13&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://en.ria.ru/military_news/20131223/185857826/Kalashnikov-Plans-New-Rifle-More-Foreign-Models--Director-.html|title=Kalashnikov Plans New Rifle, More Export Models – Director|agency=RIA Novosti|accessdate=2 October 2014|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131225090747/http://en.ria.ru/military_news/20131223/185857826/Kalashnikov-Plans-New-Rifle-More-Foreign-Models--Director-.html|archive-date=25 December 2013|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;roberthuffstutter&quot;&gt;{{cite web |author=roberthuffstutter |url=https://www.flickr.com/photos/usarmyafrica/5505821033/ |title=Djiboutian Army Quick Reaction Regiment trains at Ali Oune, Djibouti, February 2011 &amp;#124; Flickr – Photo Sharing! |publisher=Flickr |date=22 December 2011 |accessdate=29 December 2013 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131022212803/http://www.flickr.com/photos/usarmyafrica/5505821033/ |archive-date=22 October 2013 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Roberts-2008&quot;&gt;Roberts, G.K. (21 May 2008) [http://www.dtic.mil/ndia/2008Intl/Roberts.pdf U.S. Military Small Arms Ammunition Failures and Solutions] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110628234759/http://www.dtic.mil/ndia/2008Intl/Roberts.pdf |date=28 June 2011 }}, NDIA Dallas, TX.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Rossiyskaya Gazeta&quot;&gt;[https://www.telegraph.co.uk/sponsored/rbth/6453703/Russia-celebrates-Mikhail-Kalashnikovs-90th-birthday-the-designer-who-armed-the-world.html Russia celebrates Mikhail Kalashnikov's 90th birthday – the designer who armed the world] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20151209005458/http://www.telegraph.co.uk/sponsored/rbth/6453703/Russia-celebrates-Mikhail-Kalashnikovs-90th-birthday-the-designer-who-armed-the-world.html |date=9 December 2015 }}. ''39;Rossiyskaya Gazeta'' via Telegraph.co.uk (28 October 2009). Retrieved 25 November 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Russian Close Combat Weapon&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Russian Close Combat Weapon |pages=482–489 |year=2010 |publisher=Association &quot;Defense Enterprises Assistance League&quot; |location=Moscow |isbn=978-5-904540-04-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;russianvodka&quot;&gt;[http://www.russianvodka.com.au/html/the_ak_47_vodka_bottle.html The AK 47 Kalashnikov Vodka Souvenir Bottle] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150227095919/http://russianvodka.com.au/html/the_ak_47_vodka_bottle.html |date=27 February 2015 }}. Russianvodka.com.au. Retrieved 25 November 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Santos&quot;&gt;Santos, Soliman M. Jr. (April 2010) [http://www.smallarmssurvey.org/fileadmin/docs/D-Book-series/book-12-Philippines/SAS-Armed-Groups-Human-Security-Efforts-Philippines.pdf ''Primed and purposeful armed groups and human security efforts in the Philippines. South–South Network for Non-State Armed Group Engagement and the Small Arms Survey''] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150924103021/http://www.smallarmssurvey.org/fileadmin/docs/D-Book-series/book-12-Philippines/SAS-Armed-Groups-Human-Security-Efforts-Philippines.pdf |date=24 September 2015 }}. Philippines/Switzerland. {{ISBN|978-2-940415-29-8}}.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;scribd.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.scribd.com/doc/50751945/Soviet-Weapon-System-Acquisition|title=Soviet Weapon-System Acquisition|author=Greenewald, John|access-date=8 September 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160307035554/https://www.scribd.com/doc/50751945/Soviet-Weapon-System-Acquisition|archive-date=7 March 2016|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;scribd1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.scribd.com/doc/35165946/Ak-47-Technical-Manual|title=Ak 47 Technical Manual|accessdate=2 October 2014|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141008112552/https://www.scribd.com/doc/35165946/Ak-47-Technical-Manual|archive-date=8 October 2014|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;scribd2&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.scribd.com/doc/38483061/Ak-47-Technical-Description-Manual |title=Ak 47 Technical Description – Manual |publisher=Scribd.com |date=30 September 2010 |accessdate=23 August 2012 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120328103151/http://www.scribd.com/doc/38483061/Ak-47-Technical-Description-Manual |archive-date=28 March 2012 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Small Arms Defense Journal&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sadefensejournal.com/wp/?p=419|title=Identifying &amp; Collecting the 7.62×39 AK-47/AKM Magazine|work=Small Arms Defense Journal|accessdate=2 October 2014|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141006074849/http://www.sadefensejournal.com/wp/?p=419|archive-date=6 October 2014|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;smallarmssurvey-1&quot;&gt;[http://www.smallarmssurvey.org/fileadmin/docs/H-Research_Notes/SAS-Research-Note-3.pdf &quot;Craft Production of Small Arms&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150924103100/http://www.smallarmssurvey.org/fileadmin/docs/H-Research_Notes/SAS-Research-Note-3.pdf |date=24 September 2015 }}. ''Small Arms Survey Research Notes'' • Number 3 • March 2011 pp. 1–2.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;smallarmssurvey-2&quot;&gt;[http://www.smallarmssurvey.org/fileadmin/docs/A-Yearbook/2004/en/Small-Arms-Survey-2004-Chapter-01-EN.pdf &quot;Continuity and Change: PRODUCTS AND PRODUCERS&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120514205138/http://www.smallarmssurvey.org/fileadmin/docs/A-Yearbook/2004/en/Small-Arms-Survey-2004-Chapter-01-EN.pdf |date=14 May 2012 }}. ''Small Arms Survey'' 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;SSR Monitor&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ssrresourcecentre.org/2010/10/22/latest-edition-of-the-ssr-monitor-burundi-focuses-on-armed-forces-reform/ |title=Latest edition of the SSR Monitor: Burundi focuses on armed forces reform |publisher=Security Sector Reform Resource Centre |date=20 December 2013 |accessdate=29 December 2013 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131018020437/http://www.ssrresourcecentre.org/2010/10/22/latest-edition-of-the-ssr-monitor-burundi-focuses-on-armed-forces-reform/ |archivedate=18 October 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;The AR-15 2010&quot;&gt;Patrick Sweeney (2010) ''The Gun Digest Book of The AR-15'', Vol. 3. Gun Digest Books. p. 20. {{ISBN|1440213763}}.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Tilstra&quot;&gt;''The Battle Rifle: Development and Use Since World War II'', By Russell C. Tilstra, (McFarland 2014) page 25-28&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;tormented&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thefreelibrary.com/Are+kalashnikov+magazines+as+robust+as+their+reputation%3F+He+tormented...-a0262692779|title=Are kalashnikov magazines as robust as their reputation? He tormented a selection of AR magazines last year, now he takes on the AK. The results you may find surprising.|accessdate=2 October 2014|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141006101126/http://www.thefreelibrary.com/Are+kalashnikov+magazines+as+robust+as+their+reputation%3F+He+tormented...-a0262692779|archive-date=6 October 2014|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;umbrellas&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/2772975.stm|title=Europe – Coming soon – the Kalashnikov brolly?|publisher=BBC|access-date=13 June 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150614173725/http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/2772975.stm|archive-date=14 June 2015|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;UNCHR&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.unhcr.org/refworld/publisher,HRW,,KEN,3cfe0db94,0.html|title=Refworld – Playing with Fire: Weapons Proliferation, Political Violence, and Human Rights in Kenya|author=United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees|work=Refworld|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20121120180843/http://www.unhcr.org/refworld/publisher%2CHRW%2C%2CKEN%2C3cfe0db94%2C0.html|archivedate=20 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;uthr.org&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uthr.org/SpecialReports/Military_rifle_bullet_wound_patterns.htm|title=Military rifle bullet wound patterns|accessdate=2 October 2014|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110910081057/http://www.uthr.org/SpecialReports/Military_rifle_bullet_wound_patterns.htm|archive-date=10 September 2011|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;van Schendel&quot;&gt;Illicit Flows and Criminal Things: States, Borders, and the Other Side of Globalization. By Willem van Schendel, Itty Abraham. Indiana University Press, 4 November 2005 – Political Science – page 217&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;variants&quot;&gt;{{cite web |author=Dimov, Roman |title=Kalashnikov Arms Versions |work=The AK Site |url=http://kalashnikov.guns.ru/models.html |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070929125610/http://kalashnikov.guns.ru/models.html |archivedate=29 September 2007 |url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;VDH&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.thenewatlantis.com/publications/the-worlds-most-popular-gun|title=The Most Popular Gun in the World|author=Hanson, Victor Davis|journal=The New Atlantis|volume=32|year=2011|pages=140–147|access-date=1 July 2014|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140912041010/http://www.thenewatlantis.com/publications/the-worlds-most-popular-gun|archive-date=12 September 2014|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Venezuela&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.upi.com/International_Security/Industry/Analysis/2007/08/15/defense_focus_venezuelas_kalashnikovs/1273/ |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080604095328/http://www.upi.com/International_Security/Industry/Analysis/2007/08/15/defense_focus_venezuelas_kalashnikovs/1273/ |archivedate=4 June 2008 |title=Defense Focus: Venezuela's Kalashnikovs |agency=United Press International |author=Sieff, Martin |date=15 August 2007 |accessdate=19 October 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;virginia1774.org&quot;&gt;Johnson, Harold E. (September 1973) [http://www.virginia1774.org/DIA-ST-HB-07-03-74.pdf Small Arms Identifiction and Operations Guide-Eurasain Communist Countries] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160304090738/http://www.virginia1774.org/DIA-ST-HB-07-03-74.pdf |date=4 March 2016 }}. U.S. Army Foreign Science and Technology Center of the U.S. Army Materiel Command.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;vodka-wired&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.wired.com/2009/12/celebrate-2010-with-a-kalashnikov/|title=Celebrate 2010 with a Kalashnikov!|date=31 December 2009|work=WIRED|access-date=4 March 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170705021921/https://www.wired.com/2009/12/celebrate-2010-with-a-kalashnikov/|archive-date=5 July 2017|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;washingtonpost&quot;&gt;{{cite news |author=Kahaner, Larry |title=Weapon of Mass Destruction |newspaper=[[The Washington Post]] |date=26 November 2006 |url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/11/24/AR2006112400788.html |accessdate=3 April 2010 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110927195809/http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/11/24/AR2006112400788.html |archive-date=27 September 2011 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;watches&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.kalashnikovwatches.com/|title=Kalashnikov watchesswiss made – Kalashnikov uhren|work=Kalashnikov watches- swiss made – Kalashnikov uhren|access-date=13 June 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150615025419/http://www.kalashnikovwatches.com/|archive-date=15 June 2015|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Weapon&quot;&gt;US Department of Defense, North Korea Country Handbook 1997, Appendix A: Equipment Recognition, PPSH 1943 SUBMACHINEGUN (TYPE-50 CHINA/MODEL-49 DPRK), p. A-79.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;worldbayonets.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web | last=Cobb | first=Ralph E. | date=2010 | url=http://worldbayonets.com/Misc__Pages/ak_bayonets/ak_bayonets.html | title=AK Bayonets 101 – The Four Basic Types | publisher=Worldbayonets.com | accessdate=25 November 2015 | archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150324190800/http://worldbayonets.com/Misc__Pages/ak_bayonets/ak_bayonets.html | archive-date=24 March 2015 | url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Azerbaijan&quot;&gt;{{cite web |script-title=ru:Азербайджан приступил к серийному производству автоматов АК-74М по российской лицензии |trans-title=Azerbaijan began serial production of AK-74M assault rifles under Russian license |language=Russian |date=8 July 2011 |work=ЦАМТО |publisher=Centre for Analysis of World Arms Trade |location=Moscow |url=http://www.armstrade.org/includes/periodics/news/2011/0708/10108803/detail.shtml |accessdate=8 July 2011  |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130922064227/http://www.armstrade.org/includes/periodics/news/2011/0708/10108803/detail.shtml |archive-date=22 September 2013 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Hungary&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://weapon.at.ua/load/312 |title=Венгрия – Штурмовые винтовки / Автоматы – Оружие – Энциклопедия оружия и боеприпасов (огнестрельное ручное оружие, боеприпасы и снаряжение) – Страница 1 |accessdate=2 October 2014 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141006092426/http://weapon.at.ua/load/312 |archive-date=6 October 2014 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Izhmash ak103&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=7.62 mm Kalashnikov assault rifles AK103, АК104 |publisher=[[Izhmash]] |url=http://www.izhmash.ru/eng/product/ak103.shtml |accessdate=8 June 2012 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120421155114/http://www.izhmash.ru/eng/product/ak103.shtml |archivedate=21 April 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Kuptsov&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author=Kuptsov, Andrei |script-title=ru:Странная история оружия: С. Г. Симонов, неизвестный гений России, или кто и как разоружил русского солдата |trans-title=Odd History of Weapons: S. G. Simonov, an Unknown Genius of Russia, or How and Who Disarmed the Russian Soldier |language=Russian |page=262 |year=2001 |publisher=Kraft+ |location=Moscow |isbn=978-5-93675-025-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;licensing-1&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title = Восточная Европа захватила рынок продаж автоматов Калашникова | url = http://www.lenta.ru/news/2006/06/13/rifles/ | publisher = Lenta.ru | date =13 June 2006 | archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20060702132440/http://lenta.ru/news/2006/06/13/rifles/| archivedate= 2 July 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;licensing-2&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title = 'Ижмаш' подсчитал контрафактные автоматы Калашникова | publisher = Lenta.ru | url = http://lenta.ru/news/2006/04/15/fake | date = 15 April 2006 | access-date = 13 June 2006 | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20060623151553/http://lenta.ru/news/2006/04/15/fake/ | archive-date = 23 June 2006 | url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Malyuk&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=Raigorodetsky, Aleksandr |script-title=ru:Автомат &quot;Малюк&quot; (&quot;Малыш&quot;) (Украина) |trans-title=&quot;Malyuk&quot; Assault Rifle (Ukraine) |language=Russian |date=6 October 2011 |work=Оружейная экзотика |url=http://raigap.livejournal.com/87857.html?mode=reply |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150903182400/http://raigap.livejournal.com/87857.html?mode=reply |archivedate=3 September 2015 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;MPi-AK&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=MPi-K / MPi-AK Assault Rifle Series |language=Russian |work=Энциклопедия оружия и боеприпасов |url=http://weapon.at.ua/load/290-1-0-792 |accessdate=19 February 2013 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130629205826/http://weapon.at.ua/load/290-1-0-792 |archive-date=29 June 2013 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt; language=Russian
&lt;ref name=&quot;Poland&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Poland. Assault Rifles |language=Russian |work=Энциклопедия оружия и боеприпасов |url=http://weapon.at.ua/load/313 |accessdate=19 February 2013 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130319035451/http://weapon.at.ua/load/313 |archive-date=19 March 2013 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;ForgottenWeapons.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=ForgottenWeapons.com: Russian AK-49 |language=English |url=https://www.forgottenweapons.com/russian-ak-49-the-type-2-milled-receiver-ak/ |accessdate=8 July 2018 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180708162517/https://www.forgottenweapons.com/russian-ak-49-the-type-2-milled-receiver-ak/ |archive-date=8 July 2018 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

== Bibliography ==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book |last=Bolotin |first=David Naumovich |script-title=ru:История советского стрелкового оружия и патронов |trans-title=The History of Soviet Small-arms and Ammunition |series=Voyenno-Istoricheskaya Biblioteka |publisher=Poligon |location=Saint Petersburg |year=1995 |url=http://www.shooting-ua.com/dop_arhiv/dop_2/books/Istor_sovet_orujiya.pdf |language=Russian |isbn=5-85503-072-5 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Monetchikov |first=Sergei Borisovich |script-title=ru:История русского автомата |trans-title=The History of Russian Assault Rifle |series=Entsiklopediya Russkoi Armii |language=Russian |year=2005 |publisher=Izdatel'stvo &quot;Atlant 44&quot; |url=http://www.rulit.net/books/istoriya-russkogo-avtomata-read-249341-1.html |isbn=5-98655-006-4 |ref=harv |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130516010402/http://www.rulit.net/books/istoriya-russkogo-avtomata-read-249341-1.html |archivedate=16 May 2013 }}
* {{cite book |last=Poyer |first=Joe |title=The AK-47 and AK-74 Kalashnikov Rifles and Their Variations: A Shooter's and Collector's Guide |date=1 January 2006 |publisher=North Cape Publications |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=EPArOwAACAAJ |isbn=978-1-882391-41-7 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Rottman |first=Gordon |title=The AK-47: Kalashnikov-series assault rifles |date=24 May 2011 |publisher=[[Osprey Publishing]] |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=qK9Nn-2xocUC |isbn=978-1-84908-835-0 |ref=harv}}
{{refend}}

== Further reading ==
* {{cite book| author = Chivers, C.J| title =The Gun |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=r3VwUEHoDikC&amp;pg=PA459| publisher=Simon &amp; Schuster| date=October 2010|isbn=978-0-7432-7076-2}}
* {{cite book| last = Ezell| first = Edward Clinton|author2= R. Blake Stevens| title = Kalashnikov: The Arms and the Man| date = 1 December 2001| publisher = Collector Grade Publications| location = Cobourg, ON| isbn = 978-0-88935-267-4 }}
* {{cite book |editor-last=Gulevich |editor-first=I. D. |title=НСД. 7,62-мм автомат АК |trans-title=7.62 mm AK |language=Russian |year=1967 |edition=3 |publisher=[[Voenizdat]] |location=Moscow |url=http://weapon.at.ua/blog/2011-07-14-570 |ref={{sfnref|НСД. 7,62-мм автомат АК|1967|pp=161–162}}}}
* {{cite book| author = Michael Hodges| title = Ak47: The Story of the People's Gun| url = https://books.google.com/?id=j82yAAAACAAJ| date = January 2007| publisher = Hodder &amp; Stoughton| isbn = 978-0-340-92104-3 }}
* Honeycutt Jr, Fred L. and Anthony, Patt F.  ''Military Rifles of Japan.'' (1996) ''Fifth Edition'', 8th printing; Julin Books. {{ISBN|0-9623208-7-0}}.
* {{cite book |last=Kahaner |first=Larry |title=AK-47: the weapon that changed the face of war |year=2007 |publisher=[[John Wiley &amp; Sons]] |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=oBAhAQAAIAAJ |isbn=978-0-471-72641-8 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book| author = Kalashnikov, Mikhail Timofeevich |author2= Joly, Elena | title = The gun that changed the world| url = https://books.google.com/?id=CY2HlLDiaNwC| year = 2006| publisher = Polity Press| isbn = 978-0-7456-3691-7 }}
* {{cite book |last=Shilin |first=Valery |last2=Cutshaw |first2=Charlie |title=Legends and Reality of the AK: A Behind-The Scenes Look at the History, Design, and Impact of the Kalashnikov Family of Weapons |date=1 March 2000 |publisher=[[Paladin Press]] |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=U3kIAAAACAAJ |isbn=978-1-58160-069-8}}
* {{cite book |editor-last=Vilchinsky |editor-first=I. K. |title=НСД. 7,62-мм автомат АКМ (АКМС) |trans-title=7.62 mm AKM (AKMS) |language=Russian |year=1983 |edition=3 |publisher=[[Voenizdat]] |location=Moscow |url=http://militera.lib.ru/manuals/nastav_akm/index.html |ref={{sfnref|НСД. 7,62-мм автомат АКМ (АКМС)|1983|pp=149–150}}}}
* {{cite book| author = John Walter| title = Kalashnikov: machine pistols, assault rifles, and machine-guns, 1945 to the present| url = https://books.google.com/?id=XnybC2qSORAC| date = 4 September 1999| publisher = Greenhill Books/[[Lionel Leventhal]]| isbn = 978-1-85367-364-1 }}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20070929102901/http://kalashnikov.guns.ru/ How the AK-47 Rewrote the Rules of Modern Warfare] – Three-part article by [[C. J. Chivers]], for ''[[Wired (magazine)|Wired Magazine]]''
* ''Ружье. Оружие и амуниция'' 1999/3, pp.&amp;nbsp;18–21 has an article about the AK-47 prototypes
* М.Т. Kalashnikov, &quot;[https://web.archive.org/web/20070929102901/http://kalashnikov.guns.ru/ Кто автор АК-47?]&quot; (Who is the author of AK-47?) – an article rejecting some of the alternative theories as to the authorship of the AK-47, ''Kalashnikov'' magazine, 2002/2, pp.&amp;nbsp;4–7 (in Russian)
* М. Degtyaryov, &quot;[https://web.archive.org/web/20070929102901/http://kalashnikov.guns.ru/ Неочевидное очевидное]&quot; – an article comparing the internals of the StG 44 and AK-47, ''Kalashnikov'' magazine, 2009/4, pp.&amp;nbsp;18–23 (in Russian)
* &quot;[https://web.archive.org/web/20070929102901/http://kalashnikov.guns.ru/ В преддверии юбилея...]&quot; Transcription of the commission report on the testing round from the summer of 1947; no winner was selected at this point, but the commission held Kalashnikov's, Dementiev's and Bulkin's designs as most closely satisfying TTT number 3131. ''Kalashnikov'' magazine, 2009/8, pp.&amp;nbsp;18–22 (in Russian)
* &quot;[https://web.archive.org/web/20070929102901/http://kalashnikov.guns.ru/ Путёвка в жизнь]&quot; Report/letter on the final round of testing, 27 December 1947, declaring Kalashnikov's design the winner. ''Kalashnikov'' magazine, 2009/9, pp.&amp;nbsp;16–22 (in Russian)
* Articles on the 1948 military trials: &quot;[https://web.archive.org/web/20070929102901/http://kalashnikov.guns.ru/ На пути в войска]&quot; and &quot;[http://www.kalashnikov.ru/upload/medialibrary/c06/008_013.pdf ПЕРВЫЙ В ДИНАСТИИ]&quot;, ''Kalashnikov'' magazine, 2009/10-11
* {{cite journal | author = Fackler | last2 = Surinchak | year = 1984 | first2 = John S. | last3 = Malinowski | first3 = John A. | last4 = Bowen | first4 = Robert E. | title = Wounding potential of the Russian AK-74 assault rifle | journal = Journal of Trauma-Injury Infection &amp; Critical Care | volume = 24 | pages = 263–6 | doi = 10.1097/00005373-198403000-00014 | pmid = 6708147 | issue = 3 }}

== External links ==
{{Sister project links|AK-47}}
* [[s:AK-47 Operator's Manual|US Army Operator's Manual for the AK-47 Assault Rifle]]
* [http://kalashnikov.guns.ru/ AK Site – Kalashnikov Home Page] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070929102901/http://kalashnikov.guns.ru/ |date=29 September 2007 |title=(Mirror) }}
* [http://www.nazarian.no/images/wep/284_US_Army_AK47.pdf Nazarian's Gun's Recognition Guide (MANUAL) AK 47 Manual (.pdf)]
* [http://www.time.com/time/photogallery/0,29307,1964810,00.html The Timeless, Ubiquitous AK-47] – slideshow by ''[[Time (magazine)|Time]]'' magazine
* [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UQtFYkvascA Legendary Kalashnikov: Story of AK-47 Rifle] ([[RT (TV network)|RT]]'s Documentary)
* [https://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=6539945 AK-47: The Weapon Changed the Face of War] – audio report by ''[[NPR]]''
* [https://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=130493013 The AK-47: The Gun That Changed The Battlefield] – audio report by ''[[NPR]]''
* [https://www.youtube.com/watch_popup?v=na2_Nw31BBI AK-47 Documentary: Part 1] &amp; [https://www.youtube.com/watch_popup?v=PB1VuBWTyvY Part 2] by ''[[Al Jazeera English]]''
* [https://archive.org/details/AkmAk-47TypeFullAutoIraqU.s.Army AK-47 Full Auto, U.S. Army in Iraq] from the ''[[Internet Archive]]''
* [http://www.dawn.com/news/1076328 Years of the gun: A political history of the AK-47 in Pakistan] by ''[[Dawn News]]''
* [https://gearly.org/best-pistol-red-dot-sights/ Piston Red Dot Sights] by ''[[Internet Archive]]''

{{AK-47 derivatives}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Weapons and ammunition introduced in 1947]]
[[Category:7.62×39mm assault rifles]]
[[Category:Infantry weapons of the Cold War]]
[[Category:Rifles of the Cold War]]
[[Category:Cold War weapons of the Soviet Union]]
[[Category:Kalashnikov derivatives]]
[[Category:Assault rifles of the Soviet Union]]
[[Category:Military equipment 1945–1949]]
[[Category:Kalashnikov Concern products]]</text>
      <sha1>i1v55f1zg9qjp4xaihrl4vgnzvwjovd</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
