  <page>
    <title>Amethyst</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1366</id>
    <revision>
      <id>940700608</id>
      <parentid>940700535</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-14T02:31:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>2606:A000:6781:9100:1CAB:DE8B:2481:5336</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Value */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Other uses}}
{{short description|Mineral, quartz variety}}
{{Infobox mineral
| name        = Amethyst
| category    = [[Silicate mineral]]
| boxwidth    =
| boxbgcolor  = #CC99FF
| boxtextcolor = black
| image       = Amethyst. Magaliesburg, South Africa.jpg
| imagesize   = 250px
| caption     = Amethyst cluster from [[Magaliesburg]], South Africa.
| formula     = [[Silica]] (silicon dioxide, [[Silicon|Si]][[Oxygen|O]]&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;)
| molweight   =
| system      = [[Trigonal]]
| class       = Trapezohedral (32)
| color       = Purple, violet
| habit       = 6-sided prism ending in 6-sided pyramid (typical)
| twinning    = Dauphine law, Brazil law, and Japan law
| cleavage    = None
| fracture    = Conchoidal
| mohs        = 7–lower in impure varieties
| luster      = Vitreous/glassy
| refractive  = n&lt;sub&gt;ω&lt;/sub&gt; = 1.543–1.553 &lt;br&gt;n&lt;sub&gt;ε&lt;/sub&gt; = 1.552–1.554
| opticalprop = Uniaxial (+)
| birefringence = +0.009 (B-G interval)
| pleochroism = Weak to moderate purple/reddish purple
| streak      = White
| gravity     = 2.65 constant; variable in impure varieties
| density     =
| melt        = 1650±75&amp;nbsp;°C
| fusibility  =
| diagnostic  =
| solubility  = Insoluble in common solvents
| diaphaneity = Transparent to translucent
| other       = [[Piezoelectric]]
}}

'''Amethyst''' is a [[violet (color)|violet]] variety of [[quartz]]. The name comes from the [[Koine Greek]] ἀμέθυστος ''amethystos'' from ἀ- ''a-'', &quot;not&quot; and μεθύσκω {{transl|grc|methysko}} / μεθύω {{transl|grc|methyo}}, &quot;intoxicate&quot;, a reference to the belief that the stone protected its owner from [[Alcohol intoxication|drunkenness]].&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;&gt;{{EB1911|inline=y|wstitle=Amethyst|volume=1|page=852|first=Frederick William|last=Rudler}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Ancient Greece|ancient Greeks]] wore amethyst and carved [[drinking]] vessels from it in the belief that it would prevent intoxication.

Amethyst is a semiprecious stone often used in [[jewelry]] and is the traditional [[birthstone]] for February.

==Structure==
[[File:Facet Cut Amethyst.jpg|thumb|left|upright|Faceted amethyst]]
[[File:Amethyst close cropped.jpg|thumb|left|upright|[[Emerald]] cut amethyst]]
[[File:Améthystre sceptre2.jpg|alt=Amethyst crystals from Mexico|thumb|Amethyst crystals from [[Mexico]]]]
Amethyst is a purple variety of [[quartz]] (SiO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;) and owes its violet color to [[irradiation]], impurities of [[iron]] and in some cases other [[transition metal]]s, and the presence of other trace elements, which result in complex crystal lattice substitutions.&lt;ref&gt;Norman N. Greenwood and Alan Earnshaw (1997). ''Chemistry of the Elements'' (2nd ed.). Butterworth–Heinemann. {{ISBN|0080379419}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;scielo.br&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|author1=Fernando S. Lameiras |author2=Eduardo H. M. Nunes |author3=Wander L. Vasconcelos |year=2009|doi=10.1590/S1516-14392009000300011 |title=Infrared and Chemical Characterization of Natural Amethysts and Prasiolites Colored by Irradiation|journal=Materials Research|volume=12 |issue=3|pages=315–320}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Gems&gt;Michael O'Donoghue (2006), ''Gems'', Butterworth-Heinemann, 6th ed. {{ISBN|978-0-7506-5856-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Mohs scale of mineral hardness|hardness]] of the mineral is the same as quartz, thus making it suitable for use in jewelry.

==Hue and tone==

Amethyst occurs in primary hues from a light pinkish violet color to a deep purple color. Amethyst may exhibit one or both secondary hues, red and blue.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://geology.com/gemstones/amethyst/|title=Amethyst: The world's most popular purple gemstone|website=geology.com|access-date=2017-08-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; High quality amethyst can be found in [[Siberia]], [[Sri Lanka]], [[Brazil]], [[Uruguay]], and the far East. The ideal grade is called &quot;Deep Siberian&quot; and has a primary purple hue of around 75–80%, with 15–20% blue and (depending on the light source) red secondary hues.&lt;ref name=&quot;WiseSecrets1&quot;&gt;Richard W. Wise (2005), ''Secrets of the Gem Trade; The Connoisseur's Guide to Precious Gemstones'', Brunswick House Press, Lenox, Mass., {{ISBN|0-9728223-8-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; ‘Rose de France’ is defined by its markedly light shade of the [[Purple (color)|purple]], reminiscent of a [[Lavender (color)|lavender]]/[[Lilac (color)|lilac]] shade. These pale colors, were once considered undesirable but have recently become popular due to intensive marketing.

Green quartz is sometimes incorrectly called green amethyst, which is a misnomer and not an appropriate name for the material, the proper terminology being [[prasiolite]]. Other names for green quartz are vermarine or lime citrine.

Of very variable intensity, the color of amethyst is often laid out in stripes parallel to the final faces of the crystal. One aspect in the art of [[lapidary]] involves correctly cutting the stone to place the color in a way that makes the tone of the finished gem homogeneous. Often, the fact that sometimes only a thin surface layer of violet color is present in the stone or that the color is not homogeneous makes for a difficult cutting.

The color of amethyst has been demonstrated to result from substitution by [[irradiation]] of trivalent iron (Fe&lt;sup&gt;3+&lt;/sup&gt;) for silicon in the structure,&lt;ref name=Gems/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author =George R. Rossman|chapter =Ch.13. Colored Varieties of the Silica Minerals|pages=433–468|year=1994|publisher=Mineralogical Society of America|title=Silica: physical behavior, geochemistry, and materials applications|journal =Mineralogical Magazine|editor1=Peter J. Heaney |editor2=Charles T. Prewitt |editor3=Gerald V. Gibbs |series=Reviews in Mineralogy|volume=29|issue =399|isbn=978-0-939950-35-5|bibcode =1996MinM...60..390H|doi =10.1180/minmag.1996.060.399.16}}&lt;/ref&gt; in the presence of trace elements of large ionic radius,&lt;ref name=&quot;scielo.br&quot;/&gt; and, to a certain extent, the amethyst color can naturally result from displacement of [[transition metal|transition elements]] even if the iron concentration is low. Natural amethyst is [[dichroism|dichroic]] in reddish violet and bluish violet,&lt;ref name=Gems/&gt; but when heated, turns yellow-orange, yellow-brown, or dark brownish and may resemble [[Quartz#Citrine|citrine]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mindat.org/min-198.html Amethyst]. Mindat.org&lt;/ref&gt; but loses its dichroism, unlike genuine citrine. When partially heated, amethyst can result in [[ametrine]].

Amethyst can fade in tone if overexposed to light sources and can be artificially darkened with adequate irradiation.&lt;ref name=Gems/&gt;  It does not [[fluorescence|fluoresce]] under either short-wave or long-wave [[UV light]].

==Geographic distribution==
[[File:Druse.jpg|upright=1.3|thumb|An amethyst [[geode]] that formed when large [[crystals]] grew in open spaces inside the rock.]]
Amethyst is produced in abundance from the state of [[Minas Gerais]] in Brazil where it occurs in large [[geode]]s within [[volcanic rock]]s. Many of the hollow agates of southwestern [[Brazil]] and [[Uruguay]] contain a crop of amethyst crystals in the interior. [[Artigas, Uruguay]] and neighboring Brazilian state [[Rio Grande do Sul]] are large world producers exceeding in [[quantity]] [[Minas Gerais]], as well as [[Mato Grosso]], [[Espirito Santo]], [[Bahia]], and [[Ceará]] states, all amethyst producers of importance in Brazil.
[[File:Minirals museum IMG 20180620 151046.jpg|thumb|upright|left|Amethyst from Brazil in the Mineral museum in India]]

It is also found and mined in [[South Korea]]. The largest opencast amethyst vein in the world is in [[Maissau]], Lower [[Austria]]. Much fine amethyst comes from [[Russia]], especially from near Mursinka in the [[Ekaterinburg]] district, where it occurs in [[Druse (geology)|drusy]] cavities in [[granitic]] [[rocks]]. Many localities in south [[India]] yield amethyst.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt; One of the largest global amethyst producers is [[Zambia]] in southern [[Africa]] with an annual production of about 1000 tons.

Amethyst occurs at many localities in the United States. Among these may be mentioned: the [[Mazatzal Mountain]] region in [[Gila County, Arizona|Gila]] and [[Maricopa County, Arizona|Maricopa Counties]], [[Arizona]]; Red Feather Lakes, near Ft Collins, Colorado; Amethyst Mountain, [[Texas]]; [[Yellowstone National Park]]; [[Delaware County, Pennsylvania]]; [[Haywood County, North Carolina]]; Deer Hill and Stow, [[Maine]] and in the [[Lake Superior]] region of [[Minnesota]], [[Wisconsin]] and [[Michigan]].&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt; Amethyst is relatively common in the Canadian provinces of [[Ontario]] and [[Nova Scotia]]. The largest amethyst mine in North America is located in [[Thunder Bay]], Ontario.

Amethyst is the official state gemstone of South Carolina.  Several South Carolina amethysts are on display at the Smithsonian Museum of Natural History.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sciway.net/facts/sc-state-gemstone-amethyst.html South Carolina State Gemstone - Amethyst]. Sciway.net (1969-06-24). Retrieved on 2016-02-04.&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
[[File:Intaglio Caracalla Cdm Paris Chab2101.jpg|thumb|upright|Roman [[Intaglio (printmaking)|intaglio]] [[engraved gem]] of [[Caracalla]] in amethyst, once in the Treasury of [[Sainte-Chapelle]].]]
[[File:Uninscribed amethyst scarab at the center of a string of amethyst ball beads. Middle Kingdom. From Egypt. The Petrie Museum of Egyptian Archaeology, London.jpg|thumb|Uninscribed amethyst scarab at the center of a string of amethyst ball beads. Middle Kingdom. From Egypt. The Petrie Museum of Egyptian Archaeology, London]]
Amethyst was used as a [[gemstone]] by the ancient [[Egypt]]ians and was largely employed in antiquity for [[intaglio (jewelry)|intaglio engraved gems]].&lt;ref name=&quot;castellani&quot;&gt;Augosto Castellani (famous Italian 19th century jeweler) (1871), ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=BwEYAAAAYAAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover Gems, Notes and Extracts]'', p. 34, London, Bell and Daldy, {{ISBN|1-141-06174-0}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Greeks believed amethyst gems could prevent intoxication,&lt;ref name=&quot;smith&quot;&gt;Marcell N. Smith (1913), ''[http://www.farlang.com/gemstones/smith-diamonds-pearls-stones/page_087 Diamonds, Pearls and Precious Stones]'' Griffith Stillings Press, Boston, Mass., p. 74&lt;/ref&gt; while medieval European soldiers wore amethyst [[amulet]]s as protection in battle in the belief that amethysts heal people and keep them cool-headed.&lt;ref&gt;[[George Frederick Kunz]] (1913), ''[http://www.farlang.com/gemstones/kunz-curious-lore-stones/page_077 Curious Lore of Precious Stones]'', Lippincott Company, Philadelphia &amp; London, p. 77&lt;/ref&gt; Beads of amethyst were found in [[Anglo-Saxons|Anglo-Saxon]] graves in England.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Lapidge (ed.) (2000), ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=f65VUNvxQjkC&amp;pg=PA261&amp; The Blackwell Encyclopaedia of Anglo-Saxon England]'', p. 261, {{ISBN|0631224920}}.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Anglican]] bishops wear an [[ecclesiastical ring|episcopal ring]] often set with an amethyst, an allusion to the description of the Apostles as &quot;not drunk&quot; at [[Pentecost]] in Acts 2:15.&lt;ref name=&quot;google&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=This Anglican Church of Ours|author =Bays, P.|date=2012|publisher=Woodlake Book|isbn=9781770644397|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=oxu2zjbxjnwC|page=136}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A large [[geode]], or &quot;amethyst-grotto&quot;, from near Santa Cruz in southern [[Brazil]] was presented at a 1902 exhibition in [[Düsseldorf]], Germany.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt;

In the 19th century, the color of amethyst was attributed to the presence of [[manganese]]. However, since it can be greatly altered and even discharged by heat, the color was believed by some authorities to be from an organic source. [[Iron|Ferric]] [[thiocyanate]] has been suggested, and [[sulfur]] was said to have been detected in the mineral.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt;

==Synthetic amethyst==
Synthetic (laboratory-grown) amethyst is produced by a synthesis method called hydrothermal growth, which grows the crystals inside a high-pressure autoclave.

Synthetic amethyst is made to imitate the best quality amethyst. Its chemical and physical properties are the same as that of natural amethyst and it can not be differentiated with absolute certainty without advanced gemmological testing (which is often cost-prohibitive). One test based on &quot;Brazil law twinning&quot; (a form of [[Crystal twinning|quartz twinning]] where right and left hand quartz structures are combined in a single crystal&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://quartzpage.de/crs_twins.html|title = Quartz Page Twinning Crystals|work=quartzpage.de}}&lt;/ref&gt;) can be used to identify most synthetic amethyst rather easily. It is possible to synthesize twinned amethyst, but this type is not available in large quantities in the market.&lt;ref name=&quot;WiseSecrets1&quot;/&gt; necessary for quartz movements in watches and clocks, which is where a lot of synthetic quartz is used.

Treated amethyst is produced by [[gamma ray]], [[X-ray]] or electron beam irradiation of clear quartz ([[rock crystal]]) which has been first doped with ferric impurities. Exposure to heat partially cancels the irradiation effects and amethyst generally becomes yellow or even green. Much of the [[citrine quartz|citrine]], [[Cairngorm (mineral)|cairngorm]], or yellow quartz of jewelry is said to be merely &quot;burnt amethyst&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author =Michael O'Donoghue|title=Synthetic, Imitation, and Treated Gemstones|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Jm3FwBiHaI4C&amp;pg=PA124|year=1997|publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis|isbn=978-0-7506-3173-0|pages=124–125}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Cultural history==

===Ancient Greece===
The Greek word &quot;amethystos&quot; may be translated as &quot;not drunken&quot;, from Greek ''a-'', &quot;not&quot; + {{transl|grc|methustos}}, &quot;intoxicated&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{OEtymD|amethyst}}&lt;/ref&gt; Amethyst was considered to be a strong antidote against drunkenness,&lt;ref&gt;See, for example:
* The earliest reference to amethyst as a symbol of sobriety is in a poem by [[Asclepiades of Samos]] (born ≈320&amp;nbsp;BCE). See &quot;XXX. Kleopatra's Ring&quot; in: Edward Storer, trans., ''The Windflowers of Asklepiades and the Poems of Poseidippos'' (London, England: Egoist Press, 1920), [https://archive.org/stream/cu31924026460844#page/n17/mode/1up page 14].
* An epigram by &quot;Plato the Younger&quot; also mentions amethyst in connection with drinking: &quot;The stone is an amethyst; but I, the tipler Dionysus, say, &quot;Let it either persuade me to be sober, or let it learn to get drunk.&quot;  See George Burges et al., ''The Greek Anthology'',... (London, England: George Bell and Sons, 1881), [https://books.google.com/books?id=FDgRAAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA369 p. 369].
* Pliny says about amethysts: &quot;The falsehoods of the magicians would persuade us that these stones are preventive of inebriety, and that it is from this that they have derived their name.&quot; See [http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.02.0137%3Abook%3D37%3Achapter%3D40 Chapter 40] of Book 37 of Pliny the Elder's ''The Natural History''.&lt;/ref&gt; which is why wine goblets were often carved from it.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author =Federman, David |title=Modern Jeweler's Consumer Guide to Colored Gemstones|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=flqvBQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA28|date=2012|publisher=Springer Science &amp; Business Media|isbn=978-1-4684-6488-7|pages=28–}}&lt;/ref&gt; In his poem &quot;L'Amethyste, ou les Amours de Bacchus et d'Amethyste&quot; (Amethyst or the loves of Bacchus and Amethyste), the French poet [[Remy Belleau]] (1528–1577) invented a myth in which [[Bacchus]], the god of intoxication, of wine, and grapes was pursuing a maiden named Amethyste, who refused his affections. Amethyste prayed to the gods to remain chaste, a prayer which the chaste goddess [[Diana (mythology)|Diana]] answered, transforming her into a white stone. Humbled by Amethyste's desire to remain chaste, Bacchus poured wine over the stone as an offering, dyeing the crystals purple.&lt;ref&gt;The &quot;myth&quot; of Amethyste and Bacchus was invented by the French poet [[Remy Belleau]] (1528–1577). See &quot;L'Amethyste, ou les Amours de Bacchus et d'Amethyste&quot; from Belleau's collection of poems &quot;Les Amours et Nouveaux Eschanges des Pierres Precieuses: Vertus &amp; Proprietez d'icelles&quot; (The loves and new transformations of the precious stones: their virtues and properties), which was published in Remy Belleau, ''Les Amours et Nouveaux Eschanges des Pierres Precieuses...'' (Paris, France: Mamert Patisson, 1576), [http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/bpt6k522648/f21.image pp. 4–6].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author =George Frederick Kunz|title=Curious Lore of Precious Stones|year=1913|pages=58–59|url=http://www.farlang.com/gemstones/kunz-curious-lore-stones/page_079}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Variations of the story include that Dionysus had been insulted by a mortal and swore to slay the next mortal who crossed his path, creating fierce tigers to carry out his wrath. The mortal turned out to be a beautiful young woman, Amethystos, who was on her way to pay tribute to [[Artemis]]. Her life was spared by Artemis, who transformed the maiden into a statue of pure crystalline quartz to protect her from the brutal claws. Dionysus wept tears of wine in remorse for his action at the sight of the beautiful statue. The god's tears then stained the quartz purple.&lt;ref&gt;[http://gemstone.org/gem-by-gem/english/amethyst.html The amethyst], Gemstone.org&lt;/ref&gt;

This myth and its variations are not found in classical sources. However, the titan [[Rhea (mythology)|Rhea]] does present Dionysus with an amethyst stone to preserve the wine-drinker's sanity in historical text.&lt;ref&gt;[[Nonnus]], ''[[Dionysiaca]],'' 12. 380&lt;/ref&gt;

===Other cultural associations===
Tibetans consider amethyst sacred to the Buddha and make prayer beads from it.&lt;ref&gt;Tropical Gemstones, by Carol Clark p.52&lt;/ref&gt; Amethyst is considered the birthstone of February.&lt;ref name=&quot;americangemsociety.org&quot;&gt;[https://www.americangemsociety.org/february-birthstones February Birthstone | Amethyst]. Americangemsociety.org (2016-01-12). Retrieved on 2016-02-04.&lt;/ref&gt; In the Middle Ages, it was considered a symbol of royalty and used to decorate English regalia.&lt;ref name=&quot;americangemsociety.org&quot;/&gt; In the [[Old World]], amethyst was considered one of the [[Cardinal gem]]s, in that it was one of the five gemstones considered precious above all others, until large deposits were found in Brazil.

==Value==
Up until the 18th century, amethyst was included in the [[Cardinal gem|cardinal]], or most valuable, gemstones (along with diamond, [[sapphire]], [[ruby]], and [[emerald]]). However, since the discovery of extensive deposits in locations such as Brazil, it has lost most of its value.

Collectors look for depth of color, possibly with red flashes if cut conventionally.&lt;ref name=CIBJO&gt;{{cite book | title= THE GEMSTONE BOOK Gemstones, Organic Substances &amp; Artificial Products — Terminology &amp; Classification | publisher= The World Jewellery Confideration (CIBJO) | year= 2012 | url= http://download.cibjo.org/CIBJO_Gemstone_Book_2011-1.pdf | access-date= June 27, 2012 | archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20120812224254/http://download.cibjo.org/CIBJO_Gemstone_Book_2011-1.pdf | archive-date= August 12, 2012 | url-status= dead | df= mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; As amethyst is readily available in large structures the value of the gem is not primarily defined by carat weight; this is different from most gemstones where the carat weight exponentially increases the value of the stone. The biggest factor in the value of amethyst is the color displayed.&lt;ref name=&quot;gemsociety&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gemsociety.org/article/amethyst-jewelry-and-gemstone-information/|title=Amethyst Jewelry and Gemstones Information - International Gem Society IGS|publisher=gemsociety.org|accessdate=2014-10-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The highest grade amethyst (called &quot;Deep Russian&quot;) is exceptionally rare and therefore, when one is found, its value is dependent on the demand of collectors. It is, however, still orders of magnitude cheaper than the highest grade sapphires or rubies.&lt;ref name=WiseSecrets1/&gt;

==See also==
*[[Ametrine]]
*[[Cardinal gem]]
*[[List of minerals]]
*[[Prasiolite]]
*[[Specimen Ridge]]
{{Portal inline|Minerals}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

{{Commons+cat|Amethyst|Amethysts}}

{{Jewellery}}
{{Silica minerals}}
{{Use American English|date=October 2015}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=October 2015}}

[[Category:Quartz gemstones]]
[[Category:Provincial symbols of Ontario]]
[[Category:Trigonal minerals]]</text>
      <sha1>kg332tw7yygosob9e5morwaaqs94am8</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
